  <page>
    <title>Cicero</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6046</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942868112</id>
      <parentid>942599530</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T10:30:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JzG</username>
        <id>760284</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Addind &quot;self-published source&quot; inside ref tags where tagged inline only</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About}}
{{short description|Roman statesman, lawyer, orator and philosopher}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2018}}
{{Infobox person
| name          = Marcus Tullius Cicero
| image         = &quot;Portrait of Cicero&quot; at The Capitoline Museum - Front.jpg
| image_upright = 1.15
| alt           = White marble bust
| caption       = First-century AD bust of Cicero in the [[Capitoline Museums]], Rome
| birth_date    = 3 January 106 BC&lt;!--THIS ARTICLE USES THE BC/AD ERA CONVENTION THROUGHOUT; PLEASE READ WP:ERA AND DISCUSS ON CICERO'S TALK PAGE BEFORE CHANGING--&gt;
| birth_place   = Arpinum, [[Roman Italy|Italy]], [[Roman Republic]] ([[Arpino]], Italy)
| death_date    = 7 December 43 BC (aged 63)
| death_place   = [[Formia]], Italy
| death_cause   = [[Decapitation|Beheaded]] by order of the [[Second Triumvirate]]
| occupation    = Statesman, [[lawyer]], writer, [[orator]]
| works         = [[Writings of Cicero]]
| office        = {{ubl|[[List of Roman consuls|Consul of Rome]] (63 BC)|[[Roman governor|Governor]] of [[Cilicia (Roman province)|Cilicia]] (51–50 BC)}}
| party         = [[Optimates]]
| opponents     = {{ubl|[[Marc Antony]]|[[Publius Clodius Pulcher]]}}
| spouse        = [[Terentia]]
| children      = [[Tullia (daughter of Cicero)|Tullia]] &amp; [[Cicero Minor]]
| relatives     = [[Quintus Tullius Cicero]] (brother)
| family        = [[Tullia (gens)|Tullii]]
| module        = {{Infobox writer
| embed            = yes
| subjects         = {{nowrap|Politics, law, philosophy, [[rhetoric]]}}
| movement         = {{ubl|[[Classical Latin#Republican|Golden Age Latin]]|[[Eclectic philosophy]]}}
| notableworks     = {{ubl|'''Orations:'''|''[[In Verrem]]''|''[[In Catilinam I–IV]]''|'''Philosophy:'''|''[[De Oratore]]''|''[[De re publica]]''|''[[De Natura Deorum]]''|''[[De Officiis]]''}}
}}
}}
{{Ancient Rome and the fall of the Republic}}

'''Marcus Tullius Cicero'''{{efn|Under [[Roman naming conventions]], his full name was rendered as ''Marcus Tullius Marci fīlius Marci nepōs Cicero'', in English &quot;Marcus Tullius, son of Marcus, grandson of Marcus, Cicero&quot;. In official state inscriptions this would appear as {{sqc|M•TVLLIVS•M•F•M•N•CICERO}}.{{sfn|Greenough|Kittredge|Howard|D'Ooge|p=45}} The name is infrequently [[anglicized]] as '''Tully'''&lt;ref&gt;E.g., in H. Jones, ''Master Tully: Cicero in Tudor England'' (Nieuwkoop: De Graaf, 1998).&lt;/ref&gt; ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|t|ʌ|l|i}}).}} ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|s|ɪ|s|ə|r|oʊ}} {{respell|SISS|ə|roh}}, {{IPA-la|ˈmaːrkʊs ˈtʊllɪ.ʊs ˈkɪkɛroː|classical}}; 3 January 106&amp;nbsp;BC&amp;nbsp;– 7 December 43&amp;nbsp;BC) was a [[Ancient Rome|Roman]] statesman, lawyer and [[Academic Skepticism|Academic Skeptic]] [[philosopher]] who [[Writings of Cicero|wrote extensively]] on rhetoric, orations, philosophy and politics, and is considered one of Rome's greatest orators and [[prose]] stylists.&lt;ref&gt;[[Elizabeth Rawson|Rawson, E.]]: ''Cicero, a portrait'' (1975) p. 303&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Haskell, H.J.: ''This was Cicero'' (1964) pp. 300–01&lt;/ref&gt; A leading political figure in the final years of the [[Roman Republic]], Cicero vainly tried to uphold the republican system's integrity during [[crisis of the Roman Republic|the instability]] that led to the establishment of the [[Roman Empire]].{{sfn|Ferguson|Balsdon}} He came from a wealthy [[Municipium|municipal]] family of the [[Roman equestrian order]], and served as [[Roman consul|consul]] in the year 63 BC.

His influence on the [[Latin]] language was immense: it has been said that subsequent prose was either a reaction against or a return to his style, not only in Latin but in European languages up to the 19th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;Inc1995&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last=Merriam-Webster, Inc |title=Merriam-Webster's Encyclopedia of Literature |publisher=Merriam-Webster |year=1995 |isbn=978-0-87779-042-6 |page=244 |chapter=Ciceronian period |access-date=27 August 2013 |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=eKNK1YwHcQ4C&amp;pg=PA244}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cicero, ''Selected Works'', 1971, p. 24&lt;/ref&gt; Cicero introduced the Romans to the chief schools of [[Greek philosophy]]{{cn|date=January 2020}} and created a Latin philosophical vocabulary (with [[neologisms]] such as ''evidentia'',&lt;ref&gt;''Q. Acad.'' 2.17–18&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[humanitas]]'', ''qualitas'', ''quantitas'', and ''essentia''),&lt;ref&gt;Conte, G.B.: &quot;Latin Literature: a history&quot; (1987) p. 199&lt;/ref&gt; distinguishing himself as a translator and philosopher.

Though he was an accomplished orator and successful lawyer, Cicero believed his political career was his most important achievement. It was during his consulship that the [[second Catilinarian conspiracy]] attempted to overthrow the government through an attack on the city by outside forces, and Cicero suppressed the revolt by summarily and controversially executing five conspirators. During the chaotic latter half of the 1st century BC marked by [[Roman civil wars|civil wars]] and the dictatorship of [[Julius Caesar|Gaius Julius Caesar]], Cicero championed a return to the traditional [[Roman Republic|republican]] government. Following Julius Caesar's death, Cicero became an enemy of [[Mark Antony]] in the ensuing power struggle, attacking him in a [[Philippicae|series of speeches]]. He was [[proscribed]] as an enemy of the state by the [[Second Triumvirate]] and consequently executed by soldiers operating on their behalf in 43 BC after having been intercepted during an attempted flight from the Italian peninsula. His severed hands and head were then, as a final revenge of Mark Antony, displayed on the [[Rostra]].

[[Petrarch]]'s rediscovery of Cicero's letters is often credited for initiating the 14th-century [[Renaissance]] in [[Res publica|public affairs]], [[Renaissance humanism|humanism]], and classical Roman culture.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wootton1996&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last=Wootton |first=David |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=78eaIfCg2mcC |title=Modern Political Thought: Readings from Machiavelli to Nietzsche |publisher=Hackett Publishing |year=1996 |isbn=978-0-87220-341-9 |page=1 |access-date=27 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Polish historian [[Tadeusz Stefan Zieliński|Tadeusz Zieliński]], &quot;the Renaissance was above all things a revival of Cicero, and only after him and through him of the rest of Classical antiquity.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Zieliński |first=Tadeusz |title=Cicero Im Wandel Der Jahrhunderte |publisher=Nabu Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; The peak of Cicero's authority and prestige came during the 18th-century Enlightenment,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Wood |first=Neal |title=Cicero's Social and Political Thought |publisher=[[University of California Press]] |year=1991 |isbn=978-0-520-07427-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; and his impact on leading Enlightenment thinkers and political theorists such as [[John Locke]], [[David Hume]], [[Montesquieu]] and [[Edmund Burke]] was substantial.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.nlnrac.org/classical/cicero |title=Cicero and the Natural Law |last=Nicgorski |first=Walter |publisher=Natural Law, Natural Rights, and American Constitutionalism}}&lt;/ref&gt;
His works rank among the most influential in European culture, and today still constitute one of the most important bodies of primary material for the writing and revision of Roman history, especially the last days of the [[Roman Republic]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 |first=Miriam |last=Griffin
|first2=John |last2=Boardman |first3=Jasper |last3=Griffin |first4=Oswyn |last4=Murray
 |title=The Oxford Illustrated History of the Roman World
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=w95Nb-BJWRcC&amp;pg=PA76
|accessdate=10 August 2011
|year=2001
|publisher=Oxford University Press
|isbn=978-0-19-285436-0
|pages=76ff}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
{{Main|Personal life of Cicero}}

===Early life===

Cicero was born on 3 January 106 BC&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.upi.com/Top_News/2019/01/03/UPI-Almanac-for-Thursday-Jan-3-2019/1811546209344/ |title=UPI Almanac for Thursday, Jan. 3, 2019 |date=January 3, 2019 |access-date=September 3, 2019 |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190103223323/https://www.upi.com/Top_News/2019/01/03/UPI-Almanac-for-Thursday-Jan-3-2019/1811546209344/ |archive-date=January 3, 2019 |agency=[[United Press International]] |quote=Roman philosopher Cicero in 106 B.C}}&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Arpinum]], a hill town {{convert|100|km|mi|sp=us}} southeast of Rome. He belonged to the ''[[Roman tribe|tribus]]'' Cornelia.&lt;ref&gt;''Sylloge Inscriptionum Graecarum,'' [http://www.attalus.org/docs/sig2/s747.html 747].&lt;/ref&gt; His father was a well-to-do member of the [[Equestrian (Roman)|equestrian order]] and possessed good connections in Rome.  However, being a semi-invalid, he could not enter public life and studied extensively to compensate. Although little is known about Cicero's mother, Helvia, it was common for the wives of important Roman citizens to be responsible for the management of the household. Cicero's brother [[Quintus Tullius Cicero|Quintus]] wrote in a letter that she was a thrifty housewife.&lt;ref&gt;Rawson, E.: ''Cicero, a portrait'' (1975) pp. 5–6; Cicero, ''Ad Familiares'' [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?lookup=Cic.+Fam.+16.26.2 16.26.2] (Quintus to Cicero)&lt;/ref&gt;

Cicero's [[cognomen]], or personal surname, comes from the Latin for [[chickpea]], ''cicer''. [[Plutarch]] explains that the name was originally given to one of Cicero's ancestors who had a cleft in the tip of his nose resembling a chickpea. However, it is more likely that Cicero's ancestors prospered through the cultivation and sale of chickpeas.&lt;ref&gt;Trollope, Anthony. ''[http://www.gutenberg.org/files/8945/8945-h/8945-h.htm The Life of Cicero]'' Volume 1. p. 42&lt;/ref&gt; Romans often chose down-to-earth personal surnames. The famous family names of [[Fabia (gens)|Fabius]], [[Lentulus]], and [[Piso]] come from the Latin names of beans, lentils, and peas, respectively. Plutarch writes that Cicero was urged to change this deprecatory name when he entered politics, but refused, saying that he would make ''Cicero'' more glorious than ''[[Marcus Aemilius Scaurus (consul 115 BC)|Scaurus]]'' (&quot;Swollen-ankled&quot;) and ''[[Gaius Lutatius Catulus|Catulus]]'' (&quot;Puppy&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;Plutarch, ''Cicero'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Plutarch/Lives/Cicero*.html#1.3 1.3–5]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:The Young Cicero Reading.jpg|left|thumb|''[[The Young Cicero Reading]]'' by [[Vincenzo Foppa]] (fresco, 1464), now at the [[Wallace Collection]]]]

During this period in Roman history, &quot;cultured&quot; meant being able to speak both Latin and Greek. Cicero was therefore educated in the teachings of the ancient Greek philosophers, poets and historians; as he obtained much of his understanding of the theory and practice of [[rhetoric]] from the Greek poet [[Aulus Licinius Archias|Archias]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Anthony Everitt|Everitt, A.]]:&quot;Cicero: The Life and Times of Rome's Greatest Politician&quot; (2001) p.34&lt;/ref&gt; and from the Greek [[rhetoric]]ian [[Apollonius Molon|Apollonius]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/e/roman/texts/plutarch/lives/caesar*.html |title=Life of Caesar |last=Plutarch |website=[[University of Chicago]] |page=447 |quote=After this, Sulla's power being now on the wane, and Caesar's friends at home inviting him to return, Caesar sailed to Rhodes to study under Apollonius the son of Molon, an illustrious rhetorician with the reputation of a worthy character, of whom Cicero also was a pupil.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cicero used his knowledge of Greek to translate many of the theoretical concepts of Greek philosophy into Latin, thus translating Greek philosophical works for a larger audience. It was precisely his broad education that tied him to the traditional Roman elite.&lt;ref name=&quot;everitt_p35&quot;&gt;Everitt, A.: &quot;Cicero: The Life and Times of Rome's Greatest Politician&quot; (2001) p. 35&lt;/ref&gt;

Cicero's interest in philosophy figured heavily in his later career and led to him providing a comprehensive account of Greek philosophy for a Roman audience,&lt;ref&gt;De Officiis, book 1, n. 1&lt;/ref&gt; including creating a philosophical vocabulary in Latin.&lt;ref&gt;Everitt, A.:&quot; Cicero: The Life and Times of Rome's Greatest Politician&quot; (2001) pp. 253–55&lt;/ref&gt; In 87 BC, [[Philo of Larissa]], the head of the Academy that was founded by [[Plato]] in Athens about 300 years earlier, arrived in Rome. Cicero, &quot;inspired by an extraordinary zeal for philosophy&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Rawson: &quot;Cicero, a portrait&quot; (1975) p.18&lt;/ref&gt; sat enthusiastically at his feet and absorbed Plato's philosophy.
Cicero said of Plato's Dialogues, that if Zeus were to speak, he would use their language.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.ellopos.net/elpenor/greek-texts/ancient-greece/plato-homepage.asp |title=Plato |website=www.ellopos.net}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Plutarch, Cicero was an extremely talented student, whose learning attracted attention from all over Rome,&lt;ref&gt;Plutarch, ''Cicero'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Plutarch/Lives/Cicero*.html#2.2 2.2]&lt;/ref&gt; affording him the opportunity to study Roman law under [[Quintus Mucius Scaevola Augur|Quintus Mucius Scaevola]].&lt;ref&gt;Plutarch, ''Cicero'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Plutarch/Lives/Cicero*.html#3.2 3.2]&lt;/ref&gt; Cicero's fellow students were Gaius Marius Minor, [[Servius Sulpicius Rufus]] (who became a famous lawyer, one of the few whom Cicero considered superior to himself in legal matters), and [[Titus Pomponius Atticus|Titus Pomponius]]. The latter two became Cicero's friends for life, and Pomponius (who later received the nickname &quot;Atticus&quot;, and whose sister married Cicero's brother) would become, in Cicero's own words, &quot;as a second brother&quot;, with both maintaining a lifelong correspondence.&lt;ref name=&quot;everitt_p35&quot; /&gt;

In 79 BC, Cicero left for [[Greece]], [[Asia Minor]] and [[Rhodes]]. This was perhaps to avoid the potential wrath of Sulla, as Plutarch claims,&lt;ref&gt;Haskell, H.J.: &quot;This was Cicero&quot; (1940) p. 83&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Plutarch, ''Cicero'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Plutarch/Lives/Cicero*.html#3.2 3.2–5]&lt;/ref&gt; though Cicero himself says it was to hone his skills and improve his physical fitness.&lt;ref&gt;Cicero, ''Brutus'', 313–14&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Athens]] he studied philosophy with [[Antiochus of Ascalon]], the 'Old Academic' and initiator of [[Middle Platonism]].&lt;ref&gt;Cicero, ''Brutus'', 315&lt;/ref&gt; In Asia Minor, he met the leading orators of the region and continued to study with them. Cicero then journeyed to [[Rhodes]] to meet his former teacher, [[Apollonius Molon]], who had previously taught him in Rome. Molon helped Cicero hone the excesses in his style, as well as train his body and lungs for the demands of public speaking.&lt;ref&gt;Cicero, ''Brutus'', 316&lt;/ref&gt; Charting a middle path between the competing [[Atticism|Attic]] and [[Asiatic style]]s, Cicero would ultimately become considered second only to [[Demosthenes]] among history's orators.&lt;ref&gt;Gesine Manuwald, Cicero: Philippics 3–9, vol. 2, Berlin: Walter de Gruyter, 2007, pp. 129f&lt;/ref&gt;

===Family===

[[File:Cicero.PNG|thumb|upright|Marcus Tullius Cicero]]
Cicero married [[Terentia]] probably at the age of 27, in 79 BC. According to the upper class [[wikt:mores#English|mores]] of the day it was a marriage of convenience, but lasted harmoniously for nearly 30 years. Terentia's family was wealthy, probably the [[Plebs|plebeian]] noble house of Terenti Varrones, thus meeting the needs of Cicero's political ambitions in both economic and social terms. She had a half-sister named Fabia, who as a child had become a [[Vestal Virgin]], a very great honour. Terentia was a strong willed woman and (citing Plutarch) &quot;she took more interest in her husband's political career than she allowed him to take in household affairs.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Rawson, E.: &quot;Cicero, a portrait&quot; (1975) p. 25&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 50s BC, Cicero's letters to Terentia became shorter and colder. He complained to his friends that Terentia had betrayed him but did not specify in which sense. Perhaps the marriage simply could not outlast the strain of the political upheaval in Rome, Cicero's involvement in it, and various other disputes between the two. The divorce appears to have taken place in 51 BC or shortly before.&lt;ref&gt;Susan Treggiari, ''Terentia, Tullia and Publilia: the women of Cicero's family'', London: Routledge, 2007, pp. 76ff.&lt;/ref&gt; In 46 or 45 BC,&lt;ref&gt;Treggiari, op. cit., p. 133&lt;/ref&gt; Cicero married a young girl, Publilia, who had been his [[ward (law)|ward]]. It is thought that Cicero needed her money, particularly after having to repay the [[dowry]] of Terentia, who came from a wealthy family.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rawson_1975_225&quot;&gt;Rawson, E.:   ''Cicero'' p. 225&lt;/ref&gt; This marriage did not last long.

Although his marriage to Terentia was one of convenience, it is commonly known that Cicero held great love for his daughter [[Tullia (daughter of Cicero)|Tullia]].&lt;ref&gt;Haskell H.J.: ''This was Cicero'', p. 95&lt;/ref&gt; When she suddenly became ill in February 45 BC and died after having seemingly recovered from giving birth to a son in January, Cicero was stunned. &quot;I have lost the one thing that bound me to life&quot; he wrote to Atticus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Haskell_1964_249&quot;&gt;Haskell, H.J.: &quot;This was Cicero&quot; (1964) p. 249&lt;/ref&gt; Atticus told him to come for a visit during the first weeks of his bereavement, so that he could comfort him when his pain was at its greatest. In Atticus's large library, Cicero read everything that the Greek philosophers had written about overcoming grief, &quot;but my sorrow defeats all consolation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Cicero, ''Letters to Atticus'', 12.14. Rawson, E.: ''Cicero'' p. 225&lt;/ref&gt; Caesar and [[Marcus Junius Brutus the Younger|Brutus]] as well as [[Servius Sulpicius Rufus]] sent him letters of condolence.&lt;ref&gt;Rawson, E.: ''Cicero'' p. 226&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cicero, ''Samtliga brev/Collected letters''&lt;/ref&gt;

Cicero hoped that his son [[Cicero Minor|Marcus]] would become a philosopher like him, but Marcus himself wished for a military career. He joined the army of [[Pompey]] in 49 BC and after Pompey's defeat at [[Battle of Pharsalus|Pharsalus]] 48 BC, he was pardoned by Caesar. Cicero sent him to Athens to study as a disciple of the [[Peripatetic school|peripatetic]] philosopher [[Cratippus of Pergamon|Kratippos]] in 48 BC, but he used this absence from &quot;his father's vigilant eye&quot; to &quot;eat, drink and be merry.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Haskell |first=H.J |title=This was Cicero |year=1964 |pages=103–04}}&lt;/ref&gt; After Cicero's murder he joined the army of the ''[[Liberatores]]'' but was later pardoned by [[Augustus]]. Augustus's bad conscience for not having objected to Cicero's being put on the [[proscription]] list during the [[Second Triumvirate]] led him to aid considerably Marcus Minor's career. He became an [[augur]], and was nominated [[Roman consul|consul]] in 30 BC together with Augustus. As such, he was responsible for revoking the honors of [[Mark Antony]], who was responsible for the proscription, and could in this way take revenge. Later he was appointed [[proconsul]] of [[Syria]] and the province of Asia.&lt;ref&gt;Paavo Castren &amp; L. Pietilä-Castren: ''Antiikin käsikirja/Encyclopedia of the Ancient World''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Public career==
{{Main|Political career of Cicero}}

===Early legal activity===
Cicero wanted to pursue a public career in politics along the steps of the [[Cursus honorum]]. In 90–88 BC, he served both [[Pompeius Strabo]] and [[Lucius Cornelius Sulla]] as they campaigned in the [[Social War (91–88 BC)|Social War]], though he had no taste for military life, being an intellectual first and foremost.

Cicero started his career as a lawyer around 83–81 BC. The first extant speech is a private case from 81 BC (the ''[[pro Quinctio]]''), delivered when Cicero was aged 26, though he refers throughout to previous defenses he had already undertaken.&lt;ref&gt;E.g. Cicero, ''pro Quinctio'' 4&lt;/ref&gt; His first major public case, of which a written record is still extant, was his 80 BC defense of [[Sextus Roscius]] on the charge of [[patricide]].&lt;ref&gt;Rawson, E.: &quot;Cicero, a portrait&quot; (1975) p. 22&lt;/ref&gt; Taking this case was a courageous move for Cicero; patricide was considered an appalling crime, and the people whom Cicero accused of the murder, the most notorious being [[Lucius Cornelius Chrysogonus|Chrysogonus]], were favorites of [[Lucius Cornelius Sulla Felix|Sulla]]. At this time it would have been easy for Sulla to have the unknown Cicero murdered. Cicero's defense was an indirect challenge to the dictator Sulla, and on the strength of his case, Roscius was acquitted.&lt;ref&gt;Everitt, A.: &quot;Cicero: The Life and Times of Rome's Greatest Politician&quot; (2001) p. 61&lt;/ref&gt; Soon after, Cicero again challenged Sulla, by criticising his disenfranchisement of Italian towns in a lost speech on behalf of a woman from [[Arezzo|Arretium]].&lt;ref&gt;Cicero, ''pro Caecina'' 97&lt;/ref&gt;

Cicero's case in the ''[[Pro Roscio Amerino]]'' was divided into three parts. The first part detailed exactly the charge brought by Ericius. Cicero explained how a rustic son of a farmer, who lives off the pleasures of his own land, would not have gained anything from committing patricide because he would have eventually inherited his father's land anyway. The second part concerned the boldness and greed of two of the accusers, Magnus and Capito. Cicero told the jury that they were the more likely perpetrators of murder because the two were greedy, both for conspiring together against a fellow kinsman and, in particular, Magnus, for his boldness and for being unashamed to appear in court to support the false charges. The third part explained that Chrysogonus had immense political power, and the accusation was successfully made due to that power. Even though Chrysogonus may not have been what Cicero said he was, through rhetoric Cicero successfully made him appear to be a foreign freed man who prospered by devious means in the aftermath of the civil war. Cicero surmised that it showed what kind of a person he was and that something like murder was not beneath him.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Vasaly |first=Ann |url=http://web.b.ebscohost.com/ehost/ebookviewer/ebook/bmxlYmtfXzEzMTI1X19BTg2?sid=c9ee3429-cd2e-4d40-9f34-5b332f61d12a@sessionmgr114&amp;vid=1&amp;format=EB&amp;lpid=lp_156&amp;rid=0 |title=Representation: Images of the World in a Ciceronian Territory |publisher=University of California Press |year=1993 |isbn=978-0-520-07755-3 |location=Berkeley |pages=158–68 |archive-url=https://archive.today/20140306005520/http://web.b.ebscohost.com/ehost/ebookviewer/ebook/bmxlYmtfXzEzMTI1X19BTg2?sid=c9ee3429-cd2e-4d40-9f34-5b332f61d12a@sessionmgr114&amp;vid=1&amp;format=EB&amp;lpid=lp_156&amp;rid=0 |archive-date=6 March 2014 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Early political career===
His first office was as one of the twenty annual [[quaestor]]s, a training post for serious public administration in a diversity of areas, but with a traditional emphasis on administration and rigorous accounting of public monies under the guidance of a senior magistrate or provincial commander. Cicero served as quaestor in western [[Sicilia (Roman province)|Sicily]] in 75 BC and demonstrated honesty and integrity in his dealings with the inhabitants. As a result, the grateful Sicilians asked Cicero to prosecute [[Gaius Verres]], a governor of Sicily, who had badly plundered the province. His prosecution of Gaius Verres was a great forensic success&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title=The Oxford illustrated history of the Roman world
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=w95Nb-BJWRcC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;dq=The%20Oxford%20illustrated%20history%20of%20the%20Roman%20world&amp;pg=PA84#v=onepage&amp;q=extortionate&amp;f=false
|accessdate=10 August 2011
|pages=84ff|isbn=978-0-19-285436-0
|last1=Boardman
|first1=John
|date=18 January 2001
}}&lt;/ref&gt; for Cicero. Governor Gaius Verres hired the prominent lawyer of a noble family [[Quintus Hortensius|Quintus Hortensius Hortalus]]. After a lengthy period in Sicily collecting testimonials and evidence and persuading witnesses to come forward, Cicero returned to Rome and won the case in a series of dramatic court battles. His unique style of oratory set him apart from the flamboyant Hortensius. On the conclusion of this case, Cicero came to be considered the greatest orator in Rome. The view that Cicero may have taken the case for reasons of his own is viable. Hortensius was, at this point, known as the best lawyer in Rome; to beat him would guarantee much success and the prestige that Cicero needed to start his career. Cicero's oratorical skill is shown in his [[character assassination]] of Verres and various other techniques of persuasion used on the jury. One such example is found in the speech ''[[In Verrem|Against Verres I]]'', where he states &quot;with you on this bench, gentlemen, with [[Manius Acilius Glabrio (consul 67 BC)|Marcus Acilius Glabrio]] as your president, I do not understand what Verres can hope to achieve&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Trans. Grant, Michael. Cicero: Selected Works. London: Penguin Books. 1960.&lt;/ref&gt; Oratory was considered a great art in ancient Rome and an important tool for disseminating knowledge and promoting oneself in elections, in part because there were no regular newspapers or mass media. Cicero was neither a [[Patrician (ancient Rome)|patrician]] nor a plebeian [[nobiles|noble]]; his rise to political office despite his relatively humble origins has traditionally been attributed to his brilliance as an orator.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.bartleby.com/268/2/11.html |title=III. The First Oration Against Catiline by Cicero. Rome (218 B.C.-84 A.D.). Vol. II. Bryan, William Jennings, ed. 1906. The World's Famous Orations |website=www.bartleby.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cicero grew up in a time of civil unrest and war. [[Sulla]]'s victory in the first of a series of civil wars led to a new constitutional framework that undermined ''[[libertas]]'' (liberty), the fundamental value of the Roman Republic. Nonetheless, Sulla's reforms strengthened the position of the [[Equestrian (Roman)|equestrian]] class, contributing to that class's growing political power. Cicero was both an Italian ''eques'' and a ''[[novus homo]]'', but more importantly he was a [[Constitution of the Roman Republic|Roman constitutionalist]]. His social class and loyalty to the Republic ensured that he would &quot;command the support and confidence of the people as well as the Italian middle classes&quot;. The ''[[optimates]]'' faction never truly accepted Cicero; and this undermined his efforts to reform the Republic while preserving the constitution. Nevertheless, he successfully ascended the ''[[cursus honorum]]'', holding each magistracy at or near the youngest possible age: [[quaestor]] in 75 BC (age 31), [[aedile]] in 69 BC (age 37), and [[praetor]] in 66 BC (age 40), when he served as president of the &quot;Reclamation&quot; (or extortion) Court. He was then elected [[Roman consul|consul]] at age 42.

===Consul===
[[File:Cicerón denuncia a Catilina, por Cesare Maccari.jpg|thumb|upright=2|''Cicero Denounces Catiline'', [[fresco]] by [[Cesare Maccari]], 1882–88]]
Cicero, seizing the opportunity offered by Optimate fear of reform, was elected consul for the year 63 BC.&lt;ref name=&quot;JLP106&quot;&gt;John Leach, Pompey the Great, p.106.&lt;/ref&gt; His co-consul for the year, [[Gaius Antonius Hybrida|Gaius Antonius]], played a minor role. During his year in office, he effectively crushed the reform programme&lt;ref name=JLP106/&gt; and also he thwarted a conspiracy centered on assassinating him and overthrowing the [[Roman Republic]] with the help of foreign armed forces, led by [[Catiline|Lucius Sergius Catilina]]. Cicero procured a ''[[senatus consultum ultimum]]'' (a&amp;nbsp;declaration of [[martial law]]) and drove Catiline from the city with four vehement speeches (the [[Catiline Orations]]), which to this day remain outstanding examples of his rhetorical style. The Orations listed Catiline and his followers' debaucheries, and denounced Catiline's senatorial sympathizers as roguish and dissolute debtors clinging to Catiline as a final and desperate hope. Cicero demanded that Catiline and his followers leave the city. At the conclusion of his first speech, Catiline hurriedly left the Senate, (which was being held in the [[Temple of Jupiter Stator (8th century BC)|Temple of Jupiter Stator]]). In his following speeches, Cicero did not directly address Catiline. He delivered &lt;!--maybe; some scholars think not all the Catilinarians were actually delivered, but were rather published--&gt;the second and third orations before the [[SPQR|people]], and the last one again before the Senate. By these speeches, Cicero wanted to prepare the Senate for the worst possible case; he also delivered more evidence, against Catiline.&lt;ref&gt;Cicero, Marcus Tullius, Selected Works, Penguin Books Ltd, Great Britain, 1971&lt;/ref&gt;

Catiline fled and left behind his followers to start the revolution from within while he himself assaulted the city with an army of &quot;moral bankrupts and honest fanatics&quot;. It is alleged that Catiline had attempted to involve the [[Allobroges]], a tribe of [[Transalpine Gaul]], in their plot, but Cicero, working with the Gauls, was able to seize letters that incriminated the five conspirators and forced them to confess in front of the [[Roman Senate|Senate]].&lt;ref&gt;Cicero, ''In Catilinam'' [https://web.archive.org/web/20080126211815/http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?lookup=Cic.+Catil.+3.4 3.2]  (at the Perseus Project); Sallust, ''Bellum Catilinae'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Sallust/Bellum_Catilinae*.html#40 40–45] (at Lacus Curtius); Plutarch, ''Cicero'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Plutarch/Lives/Cicero*.html#18.4 18.4] (at Lacus Curtius).&lt;/ref&gt;

The Senate then deliberated upon the conspirators' punishment. As it was the dominant advisory body to the various [[legislative]] assemblies rather than a [[judicial]] body, there were limits to its power; however, martial law was in effect, and it was feared that simple house arrest or exile&amp;nbsp;– the standard options&amp;nbsp;– would not remove the threat to the state. At first [[Decimus Junius Silanus (consul)|Decimus Junius Silanus]] spoke for the &quot;extreme penalty&quot;; many were swayed by Julius Caesar, who decried the precedent it would set and argued in favor of life imprisonment in various Italian towns. [[Cato the Younger]] rose in defense of the death penalty and the entire Senate finally agreed on the matter. Cicero had the conspirators taken to the [[Tullianum]], the notorious Roman prison, where they were strangled. Cicero himself accompanied the former consul [[Publius Cornelius Lentulus Sura]], one of the conspirators, to the Tullianum. Cicero received the honorific &quot;''[[Pater Patriae]]''&quot; for his efforts to suppress the conspiracy, but lived thereafter in fear of trial or exile for having put Roman citizens to death without trial.

After the conspirators were put to death, Cicero was proud of his accomplishment. Some of his political enemies argued that though the act gained Cicero popularity, he exaggerated the extent of his success. He overestimated his popularity again several years later after being exiled from Italy and then allowed back from exile. At this time, he claimed that [[Roman Republic|the Republic]] would be restored along with him.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite encyclopedia |title=Cicero (106–43 BC) |encyclopedia=Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy |url=http://www.iep.utm.edu/cicero/#H2 |accessdate=21 October 2013 |last=Clayton |first=Edward}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many Romans at the time, led by [[Populares]] politicians [[Julius Caesar|Gaius Julius Caesar]] and patrician turned plebeian [[Publius Clodius Pulcher]] believed that Cicero's evidence against Catiline was fabricated and the witnesses were bribed. This was done in a concerted effort by [[Optimate]] politicians to prevent social changes in Rome, both in the city and throughout the republic. Catiline had campaigned for and lost the office of Consul four times in as many consecutive years, the last being in 63 BC, the year of Cicero's consulship, for the year 62 with support from the Populares. Cicero, who had been elected Consul with the support of the Optimates, promoted their position as advocates of the status quo resisting social changes, especially more rights for the average inhabitants of Rome.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Arthur D. Kahn |title=The Education of Julius Caesar |publisher=iUniverse.com, Inc |year=2000 |pages=149–175 |orig-year=1986}}{{self-published source|date=February 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{self-published inline|date=February 2020}}

Just after completing his consulship, in late 62 BC, Cicero arranged the purchase of a large townhouse on the [[Palatine Hill]] previously owned by Rome's richest citizen, [[Marcus Licinius Crassus]]. It cost an exorbitant sum, 3.5 million [[sesterces]], which required Cicero to arrange for a loan from his co-consul [[Gaius Antonius Hybrida]] based on the expected profits from Antonius's proconsulship in Macedonia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Anthony Everitt |title=Cicero: The Life and Times of Rome's Greatest Orator |publisher=Random House |year=2003 |page=115–16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dustan, William, 163-164&quot;&gt;Dunstan, William (2010). Ancient Rome. Rowman and Littlefield Publishers. pp. 163–164. {{ISBN|0-7425-6834-2}}.&lt;/ref&gt; At the beginning of his consulship, Cicero had made an arrangement with Hybrida to grant Hybrida the profitable province of Macedonia that had been granted to Cicero by the Senate in exchange for Hybrida staying out of Cicero's way for the year and 1/4 of the profits from the province.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dustan, William, 163-164&quot; /&gt; In return Cicero gained a lavish house which he proudly boasted was ''&quot;in conspectu prope totius urbis&quot;'' (in sight of nearly the whole city), only a short walk away from the [[Roman Forum]].&lt;ref name=&quot;cicero_house&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |last=Steven M. Cerutti |url=https://muse.jhu.edu/article/1104 |title=The Location of the Houses of Cicero and Clodius and the Porticus Catuli on the Palatine Hill |publisher=American Journal of Philology |year=1997 |issue=3 |volume=118 |page=417}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Exile and return===
In 60 BC, [[Julius Caesar]] invited Cicero to be the fourth member of his existing partnership with [[Gnaeus Pompeius Magnus|Pompey]] and [[Marcus Licinius Crassus]], an assembly that would eventually be called the [[First Triumvirate]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Yelegaonkar |first=Dr Shrikant |url=https://books.google.com/?id=nQTECQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT74&amp;lpg=PT74&amp;dq=60+BC,+Julius+Caesar+invited+Cicero+to+be+the+fourth+member+of+his+existing+partnership+with+Pompey+and+Marcus+Licinius+Crassus,+an+assembly+that+would+eventually+be+called+the+First+Triumvirate#v=onepage&amp;q=60%20BC,%20Julius%20Caesar%20invited%20Cicero%20to%20be%20the%20fourth%20member%20of%20his%20existing%20partnership%20with%20Pompey%20and%20Marcus%20Licinius%20Crassus,%20an%20assembly%20that%20would%20eventually%20be%20called%20the%20First%20Triumvirate&amp;f=false |title=Western Thinker's in Political Science |date=2009 |publisher=Lulu.com |isbn=978-1-329-08277-9 |language=en}}{{self-published source|date=February 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{self-published inline|date=February 2020}} Cicero refused the invitation because he suspected it would undermine the Republic.&lt;ref&gt;Rawson, E.: ''Cicero'', 1984 106&lt;/ref&gt;

During Caesar's consulship of 59 BC the Triumvirate had achieved many of their goals now, with Caesar leaving for his provinces, they wished to maintain their stranglehold on politics. They turned to [[Publius Clodius Pulcher]] who had been elected as one of the ten [[tribunes of the plebs]] for 58. Clodius used the Triumvirate's backing to push through legislation that benefited them all. He introduced several laws (the ''[[Leges Clodiae]]'') that made him very popular with the people, strengthening his powerbase, then he turned on Cicero by threatening exile to anyone who executed a Roman citizen without a trial. Cicero, having executed members of the Catiline Conspiracy four years previously without formal trial, was clearly the intended target. Furthermore, many believed that Clodius acted in concert with the Triumvirate who feared that Cicero would seek to abolish many of Caesar's accomplishments while Consul the year before. Cicero argued that the ''[[senatus consultum ultimum]]'' indemnified him from punishment, and he attempted to gain the support of the senators and consuls, especially of Pompey.&lt;ref&gt;Tom Holland, ''Rubicon'', pp 237-239.&lt;/ref&gt;

Cicero grew out his hair, dressed in mourning and toured the streets. Clodius' gangs dogged him, hurling abuse, stones and even excrement. Hortensius, trying to rally to his old rival's support, was almost lynched. The Senate and the consuls were cowed. Caesar, who was still encamped near Rome, was apologetic but said he could do nothing when Cicero brought himself to grovel in the proconsul's tent. Everyone seemed to have abandoned Cicero.&lt;ref&gt;Tom Holland, ''Rubicon'', pp 238-239.&lt;/ref&gt;

When help was not forthcoming, Cicero went into exile. He arrived at [[Thessalonica]], on 23 May 58&amp;nbsp;BC.&lt;ref&gt;Haskell, H.J.: ''This was Cicero'', 1964 200&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Haskell, H.J.: ''This was Cicero'', 1964 p. 201&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Plutarch. ''Cicero'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Plutarch/Lives/Cicero*.html#32 32]&lt;/ref&gt; In his absence, Clodius, who lived next door to Cicero on the Palatine, arranged for Cicero's house to be confiscated by the state, and was even able to purchase a part of the property in order to extend his own house.&lt;ref name=&quot;cicero_house&quot; /&gt; After demolishing Cicero's house, Clodius had the land consecrated and symbolically erected a Temple of [[Libertas|Liberty]] (''aedes Libertatis'') on the vacant spot.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Anthony Everitt |url=https://archive.org/details/cicerolifetimeso00ever |title=Cicero |publisher=Random House |year=2003 |page=[https://archive.org/details/cicerolifetimeso00ever/page/145 145] |url-access=registration}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cicero's exile caused him to fall into depression. He wrote to [[Titus Pomponius Atticus|Atticus]]: &quot;Your pleas have prevented me from committing suicide. But what is there to live for? Don't blame me for complaining. My afflictions surpass any you ever heard of earlier&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Haskell, H.J.: &quot;This was Cicero&quot; (1964) p. 201&lt;/ref&gt; After the intervention of recently elected tribune [[Titus Annius Milo]] (probably working on the behalf of Pompey who wanted Cicero back to help him against Clodius&lt;ref&gt;Tom Holland, ''Rubicon'', p.253.&lt;/ref&gt;), the senate voted in favor of recalling Cicero from exile. Clodius cast the single vote against the decree. Cicero returned to Italy on 5 August 57&amp;nbsp;BC, landing at [[Brundisium]].&lt;ref&gt;Cicero, ''Samtliga brev/Collected letters'' (in a Swedish translation)&lt;/ref&gt; He was greeted by a cheering crowd, and, to his delight, his beloved daughter [[Tullia (daughter of Cicero)|Tullia]].&lt;ref&gt;Haskell. H.J.: ''This was Cicero'', p. 204&lt;/ref&gt; In his ''Oratio De Domo Sua Ad Pontifices'', Cicero convinced the [[College of Pontiffs]] to rule that the consecration of his land was invalid, thereby allowing him to regain his property and rebuild his house on the Palatine.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Anthony Everitt |url=https://archive.org/details/cicerolifetimeso00ever |title=Cicero |publisher=Random House |year=2003 |page=[https://archive.org/details/cicerolifetimeso00ever/page/165 165] |url-access=registration}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Cicero |url=http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus:text:1999.02.0020:text%3DDom.:chapter%3D1 |title=De Domo Sua |publisher=perseus.tufts.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cicero tried to re-enter politics, but his attack on a bill of Caesar's proved unsuccessful. The [[Lucca Conference|conference at Luca]] in 56&amp;nbsp;BC forced Cicero to recant and support the triumvirate. After the conference Cicero lavishly praised Caesar's achievements, got the Senate to vote a thanksgiving for Caesar's victories and grant money to pay his troops, he also delivered a speech ('On the Consular Provinces') which checked an attempt by Caesar's enemies to strip him of his provinces.&lt;ref&gt;John Leach, ''Pompey the Great'', p. 144.&lt;/ref&gt; After this, a cowed Cicero concentrated on his literary works. It is uncertain whether he was directly involved in politics for the following few years.&lt;ref&gt;Grant, M: &quot;Cicero: Selected Works&quot;, p. 67&lt;/ref&gt;

===Governorship of Cilicia===
In 51 BC he reluctantly accepted a [[Promagistrate|promagistracy]] (as proconsul) in [[Cilicia (Roman province)|Cilicia]] for the year, because there were few other eligible [[Roman governor|governorships]] available as a result of a legislative requirement enacted by Pompey in 52&amp;nbsp;BC, specifying an interval of five years between a consulship or praetorship and a [[Roman province|provincial command]].&lt;ref&gt;Everitt, A. &quot;Cicero: The Life and Times of Rome's Greatest Politician&quot; (2001), pp. 186–88&lt;/ref&gt; He served as [[proconsul]] of Cilicia from May 51 to November 50&amp;nbsp;BC. He was given instructions to keep nearby [[Cappadocia]] loyal to the King, [[Ariobarzanes III of Cappadocia|Ariobarzanes III]], which he achieved 'satisfactorily without war.' In 53 BC Marcus Licinius Crassus had been defeated by the [[Parthian Empire|Parthians]] at the [[battle of Carrhae]]. This opened up the Roman East for a Parthian invasion causing much unrest in Syria and Cilicia. Cicero restored calm by his mild system of government. He discovered that much of public property had been embezzled by corrupt previous governors and their staffs, and did his utmost to restore it. Thus he greatly improved the condition of the cities.&lt;ref&gt;[[Alfred John Church]], ''Roman Life in the Days of Cicero'', (Kindle edition), ch. XIII., loc. 1834&lt;/ref&gt; He retained the civil rights of, and exempted from penalties, the men who gave the property back.&lt;ref&gt;Church, loc. 1871&lt;/ref&gt; Besides this, he was extremely frugal in his outlays for staff and private expenses during his governorship, and this made him highly popular among the natives.&lt;ref&gt;Church, loc. 1834&lt;/ref&gt; Previous governors had extorted enormous sums from the provincials in order to supply their households and bodyguard. Besides his activity in ameliorating the hard pecuniary situation of the province, Cicero was also creditably active in the military sphere. Early in his governorship he received information that prince [[Pacorus I|Pacorus]], son of [[Orodes II]] the king of the Parthians, had crossed the [[Euphrates]], and was ravaging the Syrian countryside and had even besieged [[Gaius Cassius Longinus|Cassius]] (the interim Roman commander in Syria) in [[Antioch]].&lt;ref&gt;Church, loc. 1845; Gareth C. Sampson, ''The defeat of Rome, Crassus, Carrhae &amp; the invasion of the East'', pp.155-158; Cicero, ''Letters to friends'', 15.3.1.&lt;/ref&gt; Cicero eventually marched with two understrength legions and a large contingent of auxiliary cavalry to Cassius's relief. Pacorus and his army had already given up on besieging Antioch and were heading south through Syria, ravaging the countryside again, Cassius and his legions followed them, harrying them wherever they went, eventually ambushing and defeating them near Antigonea.&lt;ref&gt;Gareth C. Sampson, ''The defeat of Rome, Crassus, Carrhae &amp; the invasion of the East'', p.159; Cicero, ''Letters to friends'', 2.10.2.&lt;/ref&gt; Another large troop of Parthian horsemen was defeated by Cicero's cavalry who happened to run into them while scouting ahead of the main army. Cicero next defeated some robbers who were based on [[Nur Mountains|Mount Amanus]] and was hailed as [[imperator]] by his troops. Afterwards he led his army against the independent Cilician mountain tribes, besieging their fortress of [[Pindenissum]]. It took him 47 days to reduce the place, which fell in December.&lt;ref&gt;Church, loc. 1855&lt;/ref&gt; Then Cicero left the province to his brother [[Quintus Cicero|Quintus]], who had accompanied him on his governorship as his [[Legatus|legate]].&lt;ref&gt;Church, ibid&lt;/ref&gt; On his way back to Rome he stopped over in [[Rhodes]] and then went to [[Athens]], where he caught up with his old friend [[Titus Pomponius Atticus]] and met men of great learning.&lt;ref&gt;Plutarch, The Life of Cicero, 36.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Julius Caesar's civil war===
The struggle between [[Pompey]] and Julius Caesar grew more intense in 50 BC. Cicero favored Pompey, seeing him as a defender of the senate and Republican tradition, but at that time avoided openly alienating Caesar.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/e/roman/texts/plutarch/lives/caesar*.html |title=Life of Caesar |last=Plutarch |website=University of Chicago |page=575 |quote=It was Cicero who proposed the first honours for [Caesar] in the senate, and their magnitude was, after all, not too great for a man; but others added excessive honours and vied with one another in proposing them, thus rendering Caesar odious and obnoxious even to the mildest citizens because of the pretension and extravagance of what was decreed for him.}}&lt;/ref&gt; When Caesar invaded Italy in 49 BC, Cicero fled Rome. Caesar, seeking an endorsement by a senior senator, courted Cicero's favor, but even so Cicero slipped out of Italy and traveled to Dyrrachium ([[Epidamnos]]), Illyria, where Pompey's staff was situated.&lt;ref&gt;Everitt, Anthony: ''Cicero'' p. 215.&lt;/ref&gt; Cicero traveled with the Pompeian forces to [[Pharsalus]] in 48 BC,&lt;ref&gt;Plutarch, ''Cicero'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Plutarch/Lives/Cicero*.html#38 38.1]&lt;/ref&gt; though he was quickly losing faith in the competence and righteousness of the Pompeian side. Eventually, he provoked the hostility of his fellow senator [[Cato the Younger|Cato]], who told him that he would have been of more use to the cause of the ''optimates'' if he had stayed in Rome. After Caesar's victory at the [[Battle of Pharsalus]] on 9 August, Cicero returned to Rome only very cautiously. Caesar pardoned him and Cicero tried to adjust to the situation and maintain his political work, hoping that Caesar might revive the Republic and its institutions.

In a letter to [[Marcus Terentius Varro|Varro]] on c. 20 April 46 BC, Cicero outlined his strategy under Caesar's dictatorship. Cicero, however, was taken completely by surprise when the ''[[Liberatores]]'' assassinated Caesar on the [[ides of March]], 44 BC. Cicero was not included in the conspiracy, even though the conspirators were sure of his sympathy. [[Marcus Junius Brutus the Younger|Marcus Junius Brutus]] called out Cicero's name, asking him to restore the republic when he lifted his bloodstained dagger after the assassination.&lt;ref&gt;Cicero, ''Second Philippic'' Against Antony&lt;/ref&gt; A letter Cicero wrote in February 43 BC to [[Trebonius]], one of the conspirators, began, &quot;How I could wish that you had invited me to that most glorious banquet on the [[Ides of March]]&quot;!&lt;ref&gt;Cicero, ''Ad Familiares'' [http://www.thelatinlibrary.com/cicero/fam10.shtml#28 10.28]&lt;/ref&gt; Cicero became a popular leader during the period of instability following the assassination. He had no respect for [[Mark Antony]], who was scheming to take revenge upon Caesar's murderers. In exchange for amnesty for the assassins, he arranged for the Senate to agree not to declare Caesar to have been a [[tyrant]], which allowed the Caesarians to have lawful support and kept Caesar's reforms and policies intact.&lt;ref&gt;Cecil W. Wooten, &quot;Cicero's Philippics and Their Demosthenic Model&quot; [[University of North Carolina Press]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Opposition to Mark Antony and death===
[[File:Assassinat de Cicéron.jpg|thumb|Cicero's death (France, 15th century)]]
Cicero and Antony now became the two leading men in Rome: Cicero as spokesman for the Senate; Antony as consul, leader of the Caesarian faction, and unofficial executor of Caesar's public will. Relations between the two, never friendly, worsened after Cicero claimed that Antony was taking liberties in interpreting Caesar's wishes and intentions. [[Augustus|Octavian]] was Caesar's adopted son and heir. After he returned to Italy, Cicero began to play him against Antony. He praised Octavian, declaring he would not make the same mistakes as his father. He attacked Antony in a series of speeches he called the [[Philippicae|Philippics]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://ic.galegroup.com/ic/whic/ReferenceDetailsPage/ReferenceDetailsWindow?zid=5f8cc5dc35ef36395a3da25a000441ad&amp;action=2&amp;catId=&amp;documentId=GALE%7CCX2878000037&amp;userGroupName=ein_remote&amp;jsid=c02d33644f4e1beaed19877135f2bf8c |title=World History in Context |website=ic.galegroup.com |language=en |access-date=3 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; after [[Demosthenes]]'s denunciations of [[Philip&amp;nbsp;II of Macedon]]. At the time Cicero's popularity as a public figure was unrivalled.&lt;ref&gt;Appian, ''Civil Wars'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Appian/Civil_Wars/4*.html#19 4.19]&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Fulvia y Marco Antonio, o La venganza de Fulvia (Museo del Prado).jpg|thumb|left|upright=2|The vengeance of Fulvia by Francisco Maura Y Montaner, 1888 depicting Fulvia inspecting the severed head of Cicero]]
Cicero supported [[Decimus Junius Brutus Albinus]] as governor of [[Cisalpine Gaul]] (''Gallia Cisalpina'') and urged the Senate to name Antony an enemy of the state. The speech of [[Lucius Calpurnius Piso Caesoninus (consul 58 BC)|Lucius Piso]], Caesar's father-in-law, delayed proceedings against Antony. Antony was later declared an [[enemy of the state]] when he refused to lift the siege of [[Mutina]], which was in the hands of Decimus Brutus. Cicero's plan to drive out Antony failed. Antony and Octavian reconciled and allied with [[Marcus Aemilius Lepidus (triumvir)|Lepidus]] to form the [[Second Triumvirate]] after the successive battles of [[Battle of Forum Gallorum|Forum Gallorum]] and [[Battle of Mutina|Mutina]]. The Triumvirate began [[proscription|proscribing]] their enemies and potential rivals immediately after legislating the alliance into official existence for a term of five years with consular ''[[imperium]]''. Cicero and all of his contacts and supporters were numbered among the enemies of the state, even though Octavian argued for two days against Cicero being added to the list.&lt;ref&gt;Plutarch, ''Cicero'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Plutarch/Lives/Cicero*.html#46.3 46.3–5]&lt;/ref&gt;

Cicero was one of the most viciously and doggedly hunted among the proscribed. He was viewed with sympathy by a large segment of the public and many people refused to report that they had seen him. He was caught 7 December 43&amp;nbsp;BC leaving his villa in [[Formiae]] in a [[Litter (vehicle)|litter]] going to the seaside where he hoped to embark on a ship destined for Macedonia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Haskell_1964_293&quot;&gt;Haskell, H.J.: ''This was Cicero'' (1964) p. 293&lt;/ref&gt; When his killers – Herennius (a centurion) and Popilius (a tribune) – arrived, Cicero's own slaves said they had not seen him, but he was given away by Philologus, a [[freedman]] of his brother [[Quintus Tullius Cicero|Quintus Cicero]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Haskell_1964_293&quot; /&gt;

[[File:CiceroBust.jpg|thumb|Cicero about age&amp;nbsp;60, from a marble bust]]

Cicero's last words are said by Cassius Dio to have been &quot;There is nothing proper about what you are doing, soldier, but do try to kill me properly.&quot;{{cn|date=January 2020}} He bowed to his captors, leaning his head out of the litter in a gladiatorial gesture to ease the task. By baring his neck and throat to the soldiers, he was indicating that he would not resist. According to [[Plutarch]], Herennius first slew him, then cut off his head. On Antony's instructions his hands, which had penned the Philippics against Antony, were cut off as well; these were nailed along with his head on the [[Rostra]] in the [[Roman Forum|Forum Romanum]] according to the tradition of [[Gaius Marius|Marius]] and [[Sulla]], both of whom had displayed the heads of their enemies in the Forum. Cicero was the only victim of the proscriptions who was displayed in that manner. According to [[Cassius Dio]] (in a story often mistakenly attributed to Plutarch),&lt;ref&gt;Cassius Dio, ''Roman History'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Cassius_Dio/47*.html#8.4 47.8.4]&lt;/ref&gt; Antony's wife [[Fulvia]] took Cicero's head, pulled out his tongue, and jabbed it repeatedly with her hairpin in final revenge against Cicero's power of speech.&lt;ref&gt;Everitt, A.: ''Cicero, A turbulent life'' (2001)&lt;/ref&gt;

Cicero's son, [[Cicero Minor|Marcus Tullius Cicero Minor]], during his year as a consul in 30&amp;nbsp;BC, avenged his father's death, to a certain extent, when he announced to the Senate Mark Antony's naval defeat at [[Battle of Actium|Actium]] in 31&amp;nbsp;BC by Octavian and his capable commander-in-chief, [[Marcus Vipsanius Agrippa|Agrippa]].

Octavian is reported to have praised Cicero as a patriot and a scholar of meaning in later times, within the circle of his family.&lt;ref&gt;[[Plutarch]], ''Cicero'', [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Plutarch/Lives/Cicero*.html#49.5 49.5]&lt;/ref&gt; However, it was Octavian's acquiescence that had allowed Cicero to be killed, as Cicero was proscribed by the new triumvirate.

Cicero's career as a statesman was marked by inconsistencies and a tendency to shift his position in response to changes in the political climate. His indecision may be attributed to his sensitive and impressionable personality; he was prone to overreaction in the face of political and private change.
&quot;Would that he had been able to endure prosperity with greater self-control, and adversity with more fortitude!&quot; wrote [[Gaius Asinius Pollio (consul 40 BC)|C. Asinius Pollio]], a contemporary Roman statesman and historian.&lt;ref&gt;Haskell, H.J. &quot;This was Cicero&quot; (1964) p. 296&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Castren and Pietilä-Castren: &quot;Antiikin käsikirja&quot; /&quot;Handbook of antiquity&quot; (2000) p. 237&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
{{Republicanism sidebar}}
[[File:Thys Boke Is Myne.jpg|thumb|[[Henry VIII of England|Henry VIII's]] childhood copy of ''[[De Officiis]]'', bearing the inscription in his hand, &quot;Thys boke is myne Prynce Henry&quot;]]
Cicero has been traditionally considered the master of Latin prose, with [[Quintilian]] declaring that Cicero was &quot;not the name of a man, but of eloquence itself.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Quintilian, [[Institutio Oratoria]] 10.1.1 12&lt;/ref&gt; The English words ''[[wikt:Ciceronian|Ciceronian]]'' (meaning &quot;eloquent&quot;) and ''[[wikt:cicerone|cicerone]]'' (meaning &quot;local guide&quot;) derive from his name.&lt;ref&gt;{{OEtymD|Ciceronian}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{OEtymD|cicerone}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is credited with transforming Latin from a modest utilitarian language into a versatile literary medium capable of expressing abstract and complicated thoughts with clarity.&lt;ref&gt;''Merriam-Webster's Encyclopedia of Literature'', &quot;Ciceronian period&quot; (1995) [https://books.google.com/books?id=eKNK1YwHcQ4C&amp;pg=PA244 p. 244]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Julius Caesar]] praised Cicero's achievement by saying &quot;it is more important to have greatly extended the frontiers of the Roman spirit (''ingenium'') than the frontiers of the Roman empire&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Pliny, ''Natural History,'' 7.117&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[John William Mackail]], &quot;Cicero's unique and imperishable glory is that he created the language of the civilized world, and used that language to create a style which nineteen centuries have not replaced, and in some respects have hardly altered.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Cicero, ''Seven orations'', 1912&lt;/ref&gt;

Cicero was also an energetic writer with an interest in a wide variety of subjects, in keeping with the [[Hellenistic philosophy|Hellenistic philosophical]] and rhetorical traditions in which he was trained. The quality and ready accessibility of Ciceronian texts favored very wide distribution and inclusion in teaching curricula, as suggested by a graffito at Pompeii, admonishing: &quot;You will like Cicero, or you will be whipped&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Hasan Niyazi, ''From Pompeii to Cyberspace – Transcending barriers with Twitter'' {{Cite web |url=http://www.3pipe.net/2011/05/from-pompeii-to-cyberspace-transcending.html |title=Account Suspended |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121114062841/http://www.3pipe.net/2011/05/from-pompeii-to-cyberspace-transcending.html |archive-date=14 November 2012 |access-date=7 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Cicero was greatly admired by influential [[Church Fathers]] such as [[Augustine of Hippo]], who credited Cicero's [[Lost work|lost]] ''[[Hortensius (Cicero)|Hortensius]]'' for his eventual conversion to Christianity,&lt;ref&gt;Augustine of Hippo, ''Confessions'', 3:4&lt;/ref&gt; and St. [[Jerome]], who had a feverish vision in which he was accused of being &quot;follower of Cicero and not of Christ&quot; before the judgment seat.&lt;ref&gt;Jerome, ''Letter to Eustochium'', XXII:30&lt;/ref&gt;
This influence further increased after the [[Dark Ages (historiography)|Early Middle Ages]] in Europe, which more of his writings survived than any other Latin author. Medieval philosophers were influenced by Cicero's writings on [[natural law]] and innate rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Goodey |first=C.F. |url=https://books.google.com/?id=zgaiAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA154&amp;lpg=PA154&amp;dq=Medieval+philosophers+were+influenced+by+Cicero's+writings+on+natural+law+and+innate+rights.#v=onepage&amp;q=Cicero&amp;f=false |title=A History of Intelligence and 'Intellectual Disability': The Shaping of Psychology in Early Modern Europe |publisher=Ashgate Publishing |year=2013 |isbn=978-1-4094-8235-2 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{citation needed|date=December 2016}}

[[Petrarch]]'s rediscovery of Cicero's letters provided the impetus for searches for ancient Greek and Latin writings scattered throughout European monasteries, and the subsequent rediscovery of [[classical antiquity]] led to the [[Renaissance]]. Subsequently, Cicero became synonymous with classical Latin to such an extent that a number of humanist scholars began to assert that no Latin word or phrase should be used unless it appeared in Cicero's works, a stance criticised by [[Erasmus]].&lt;ref&gt;Erasmus, [[Ciceronianus]]&lt;/ref&gt;

His voluminous correspondence, much of it addressed to his friend [[Titus Pomponius Atticus|Atticus]], has been especially influential, introducing the art of refined letter writing to European culture. [[Cornelius Nepos]], the 1st century BC biographer of Atticus, remarked that Cicero's letters contained such a wealth of detail &quot;concerning the inclinations of leading men, the faults of the generals, and the revolutions in the government&quot; that their reader had little need for a history of the period.&lt;ref&gt;Cornelius Nepos, ''[http://www.tertullian.org/fathers/nepos.htm#Atticus Atticus]'' 16, trans. John Selby Watson.&lt;/ref&gt;

Among Cicero's admirers were [[Desiderius Erasmus]], [[Martin Luther]], and [[John Locke]].&lt;ref&gt;Richards 2010, p.121&lt;/ref&gt; Following the invention of Johannes Gutenberg's printing press, ''[[De Officiis]]'' was the second book printed in Europe, after the [[Gutenberg Bible]]. Scholars note Cicero's influence on the rebirth of religious toleration in the 17th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.h-net.org/reviews/showrev.php?id=12681 |title=John Marshall. John Locke, Toleration and Early Enlightenment Culture: Religious Toleration and Arguments for Religious Toleration in Early Modern and Early Enlightenment Europe |last=Gibson |first=William |year=2006 |publisher=H-Albion |access-date=8 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cicero was especially popular with the [[Philosophes]] of the 18th century, including [[Edward Gibbon]], [[Diderot]], [[David Hume]], [[Montesquieu]], and [[Voltaire]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Peter Gay |title=The Enlightenment: An Interpretation |publisher=W.W. Norton |year=1966 |page=105}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gibbon wrote of his first experience reading the author's collective works thus: &quot;I tasted the beauty of the language; I breathed the spirit of freedom; and I imbibed from his precepts and examples the public and private sense of a man...after finishing the great author, a library of eloquence and reason, I formed a more extensive plan of reviewing the Latin classics...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Peter Gay |title=The Enlightenment: An Interpretation |publisher=W.W. Norton |year=1966 |page=56}}&lt;/ref&gt; Voltaire called Cicero &quot;the greatest as well as the most elegant of Roman philosophers&quot; and even staged a play based on Cicero's role in the [[Second Catilinarian conspiracy|Catilinarian conspiracy]], called ''Rome Sauvée, ou Catilina'', to &quot;make young people who go to the theatre acquainted with Cicero.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Peter Gay |title=The Enlightenment: An Interpretation |publisher=W.W. Norton |year=1966 |page=106}}&lt;/ref&gt; Voltaire was spurred to pen the drama as a rebuff to his rival [[Claude Prosper Jolyot de Crébillon|Claude Prosper Jolyot de Crébillon's]] own play ''Catilina'', which had portrayed Cicero as a coward and villain who hypocritically married his own daughter to Catiline.&lt;ref name=&quot;Matthew Sharpe&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last=Matthew Sharpe |title=Cicero, Voltaire and the philosophes in the French Enlightenment |page=329}}&lt;/ref&gt; Montesquieu produced his &quot;Discourse on Cicero&quot; in 1717, in which he heaped praise on the author because he rescued &quot;philosophy from the hands of scholars, and freed it from the confusion of a foreign language&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Montesquieu |title=Discourse on Cicero |publisher=Political Theory Vol. 30, No. 5 |page=733–737}}&lt;/ref&gt; Montesquieu went on to declare that Cicero was &quot;of all the ancients, the one who had the most personal merit, and whom I would prefer to resemble.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Matthew Sharpe&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Montesquieu |title=Discourse on Cicero |publisher=Political Theory Vol. 30, No. 5 |page=734}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Across the Atlantic, Cicero the republican inspired the [[Founding Fathers of the United States]] and the revolutionaries of the [[French Revolution]].&lt;ref&gt;De Burgh, W.G., &quot;The legacy of the ancient world&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; [[John Adams]] said, &quot;As all the ages of the world have not produced a greater statesman and philosopher united than Cicero, his authority should have great weight.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''American republicanism: Roman Ideology in the United States'' [[Mortimer Sellers|Mortimer N. S. Sellers]], NYU Press, 1994&lt;/ref&gt; Jefferson names Cicero as one of a handful of major figures who contributed to a tradition &quot;of public right&quot; that informed his draft of the Declaration of Independence and shaped American understandings of &quot;the common sense&quot; basis for the right of revolution.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas Jefferson, &quot;Letter to Henry Lee,&quot; 8 May 1825, in The Political Thought of American Statesmen, eds. Morton Frisch and Richard Stevens (Itasca, Ill.: F. E. Peacock Publishers, 1973), 12.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Camille Desmoulins]] said of the French republicans in 1789 that they were &quot;mostly young people who, nourished by the reading of Cicero at school, had become passionate enthusiasts for liberty&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Aulard |first=François-Alphonse |url=https://archive.org/details/histoirepolitiqu01aula |title=Histoire politique de la Révolution française: Origines et Développement de la Démocratie et de la République (1789–1804) |publisher=Librairie Armand Colin |year=1901 |page=[https://archive.org/details/histoirepolitiqu01aula/page/5 5]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Jim Powell (historian)|Jim Powell]] starts his book on the history of liberty with the sentence: &quot;Marcus Tullius Cicero expressed principles that became the bedrock of liberty in the modern world.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Powell |first=Jim |url=https://archive.org/details/triumphofliberty00powe/page/2 |title=The Triumph of Liberty: A 2,000 Year History Told Through the Lives of Freedom's Greatest Champions |date=2000 |publisher=Free Press |isbn=978-0-684-85967-5 |pages=[https://archive.org/details/triumphofliberty00powe/page/2 2–10]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Likewise, no other ancient personality has inspired as much venomous dislike as Cicero, especially in more modern times.&lt;ref&gt;Bailey, D.R.S. &quot;Cicero's letters to Atticus&quot; (1978) p. 16&lt;/ref&gt; His commitment to the values of the Republic accommodated a hatred of the poor and persistent opposition to the advocates and mechanisms of popular representation.&lt;ref&gt;''Letters to Atticus I &amp; II''&lt;/ref&gt; [[Friedrich Engels]] referred to him as &quot;the most contemptible scoundrel in history&quot; for upholding republican &quot;democracy&quot; while at the same time denouncing land and class reforms.&lt;ref&gt;Noted in Michael Parenti, ''The Assassination of Julius Caesar: A People's History of Ancient Rome'', 2003:86. {{ISBN|1-56584-797-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cicero has faced criticism for exaggerating the democratic qualities of republican Rome, and for defending the Roman oligarchy against the popular reforms of Caesar.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://elearning-gilman.remote-learner.net/pluginfile.php/51701/mod_resource/content/0/Cicero--Justifying_Caesar_s_Death.pdf |title=On Duties |last=Cicero |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170119051143/https://elearning-gilman.remote-learner.net/pluginfile.php/51701/mod_resource/content/0/Cicero--Justifying_Caesar_s_Death.pdf |archive-date=19 January 2017 |df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Michael Parenti]] admits Cicero's abilities as an orator, but finds him a vain, pompous and hypocritical personality who, when it suited him, could show public support for popular causes that he privately despised. Parenti presents Cicero's prosecution of the Catiline conspiracy as legally flawed at least, and possibly unlawful.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Parenti, ''[[The Assassination of Julius Caesar: A People's History of Ancient Rome]]'', 2003, pp. 107–11, 93. {{ISBN|1-56584-797-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cicero also had an influence on modern astronomy. [[Nicolaus Copernicus]], searching for ancient views on earth motion, said that he &quot;first&amp;nbsp;... found in Cicero that [[Hicetas]] supposed the earth to move.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Spielvogel |first=Jackson |url=https://archive.org/details/westerncivilizat00jack_3/page/492 |title=Western Civilization since 1300 |publisher=Cengage Learning |year=2011 |isbn=978-1-111-34219-7 |page=[https://archive.org/details/westerncivilizat00jack_3/page/492 492]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Works==
[[File:Marci Tullii Ciceronis Opera Omnia.tif|thumb|''Marci Tullii Ciceronis Opera Omnia'' (1566)]]
{{Main|Writings of Cicero}}
Cicero was declared a [[righteous pagan]] by the [[Chalcedonian Christianity|Early Church]],&lt;ref&gt;Everitt, A., ''Cicero: The Life and Times of Rome's Greatest Politician'' (2003), p. 259&lt;/ref&gt; and therefore many of his works were deemed worthy of preservation. The [[Bogomils]] considered him a rare exception of a pagan saint.&lt;ref&gt;De Burgh, W.G.&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequent Roman and medieval Christian writers quoted liberally from his works ''[[De Re Publica]]'' (''On the Commonwealth'') and ''[[De Legibus]]'' (''On the Laws''), and much of his work has been recreated from these surviving fragments. Cicero also articulated an early, abstract conceptualization of rights, based on ancient law and custom. Of Cicero's books, six on rhetoric have survived, as well as parts of eight on philosophy. Of his speeches, 88 were recorded, but only 58 survive.

==In archaeology==
Cicero's great repute in Italy has led to numerous ruins being identified as having belonged to him, though none have been substantiated with absolute certainty. In [[Formia]], two Roman-era ruins are popularly believed to be Cicero's mausoleum, the ''Tomba di Cicerone'', and the villa where he was assassinated in 43 BC. The latter building is centered around a central hall with Doric columns and a coffered vault, with a separate [[nymphaeum]], on five acres of land near Formia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=L. Richardson Jr. |url=http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus:text:1999.04.0006:entry=formiae&amp;highlight=formia |title=The Princeton Encyclopedia of Classical Sites |publisher=[[Princeton University Press]] |year=1976}}&lt;/ref&gt; A modern villa was built on the site after the Rubino family purchased the land from [[Ferdinand II of the Two Sicilies]] in 1868. Cicero's supposed tomb is a 24-meter (79 feet) tall tower on an ''[[opus quadratum]]'' base on the ancient Via Appia outside of Formia. Some suggest that it is not in fact Cicero's tomb, but a monument built on the spot where Cicero was intercepted and assassinated while trying to reach the sea.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=Redazione ANSA |url=http://www.ansa.it/english/news/2015/07/21/mayor-launches-appeal-to-save-ciceros-villa-from-ruin_55a57cf3-5104-4a1a-8e19-bc4cd3261dbd.html |title=Mayor launches appeal to save Cicero's villa from ruin |date=25 July 2015 |access-date=19 June 2018 |publisher=ANSA English}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Pompeii]], a large villa excavated in the mid 18th century just outside the Herculaneum Gate was widely believed to have been Cicero's, who was known to have owned a holiday villa in Pompeii he called his ''Pompeianum''. The villa was stripped of its fine frescoes and mosaics and then re-buried after 1763 – it has yet to be re-excavated.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://pompeiiinpictures.com/pompeiiinpictures/RV/Villa%20Cicero.htm |title=Villa Cicero |publisher=pompeiiinpictures.com |access-date=19 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, contemporaneous descriptions of the building from the excavators combined with Cicero's own references to his ''Pompeianum'' differ, making it unlikely that it is Cicero's villa.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Mary Beard |title=The Fires of Vesuvius: Pompeii Lost and Found |publisher=[[Harvard University Press]] |year=2010 |page=45}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Rome, the location of Cicero's house has been roughly identified from excavations of the Republican-era stratum on the northwestern slope of the [[Palatine Hill]].&lt;ref name=&quot;rome_alive&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last=Bolchazy-Carducci |title=Rome Alive: A Source Guide to the Ancient City |year=2004 |page=Vol. 1.5}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://archive1.village.virginia.edu/spw4s/RomanForum/GoogleEarth/AK_GE/AK_HTML/GF-014.html |title=Palatine Hill |publisher=archive1.village.virginia.edu |access-date=20 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cicero's ''domus'' has long been known to have stood in the area, according to his own descriptions and those of later authors, but there is some debate about whether it stood near the base of the hill, very close to the [[Roman Forum]], or nearer to the summit.&lt;ref name=&quot;rome_alive&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Filippo Coarelli |title=Rome and Environs: An Archaeological Guide |year=2014 |page=93}}&lt;/ref&gt; During his life the area was the most desirable in Rome, densely occupied with Patrician houses including the ''Domus Publica'' of Julius Caesar and the home of Cicero's mortal enemy Clodius.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=Samuel Ball Platner &amp; Thomas Ashby |title=Palatinus Mons, Topographical Dictionary of Ancient Rome |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=1929}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the early Imperial era these properties fell into the possession of the [[Julio-Claudian]] dynasty and the substructures of the ''Domus Tiberiana'' were built over the Republican-era buildings.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=Steven M. Cerutti |url=https://muse.jhu.edu/article/1104 |title=The Location of the Houses of Cicero and Clodius and the Porticus Catuli on the Palatine Hill |publisher=American Journal of Philology |year=1997 |issue=3 |volume=118 |pages=417–426}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable fictional portrayals==
[[Ben Jonson]] dramatised the [[Second Catilinarian Conspiracy|conspiracy of Catiline]] in his play ''[[Catiline His Conspiracy]]'', featuring Cicero as a character. Cicero also appears as a minor character in [[William Shakespeare]]'s play ''[[Julius Caesar (play)|Julius Caesar]]''.

Cicero was portrayed on the motion picture screen by British actor [[Alan Napier]] in the 1953 film ''[[Julius Caesar (1953 film)|Julius Caesar]]'', based on Shakespeare's play.&lt;ref&gt;{{tcmdb title|79974|Julius Caesar}}&lt;/ref&gt; He has also been played by such noted actors as [[Michael Hordern]] (in ''[[Cleopatra (1963 film)|Cleopatra]]''),&lt;ref&gt;{{tcmdb title|71069|Cleopatra}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[André Morell]] (in the 1970 ''[[Julius Caesar (1970 film)|Julius Caesar]]'').&lt;ref&gt;{{tcmdb title|79976|Julius Caesar}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most recently, [[List of Rome characters|Cicero]] was portrayed by [[David Bamber]] in the HBO series ''[[Rome (TV series)|Rome]]'' (2005–2007) and appeared in both seasons.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.hbo.com/rome/cast-and-crew |title=Rome – Cast and Crew |website=HBO |language=en |access-date=5 December 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the historical novel series ''[[Masters of Rome]]'', [[Colleen McCullough]] presents a not-so-flattering depiction of Cicero's career, showing him struggling with an inferiority complex and vanity, morally flexible and fatally indiscreet, while his rival [[Julius Caesar]] is shown in a more approving light.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://haciendapublishing.com/articles/caesars-women-%25E2%2580%2594-mcculloughs-idolatry-and-politics-ancient-rome |title=Caesar's Women — McCullough's Idolatry and Politics in Ancient Rome |last=Faria |first=Miguel A. |date=14 August 2013 |website=Hacienda Publishing |access-date=5 December 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cicero is portrayed as a hero in the novel ''[[A Pillar of Iron]]'' by [[Taylor Caldwell]] (1965). [[Robert Harris (novelist)|Robert Harris]]' novels ''[[Imperium (Harris novel)|Imperium]]'', ''[[Lustrum (novel)|Lustrum]]'' (published under the name ''Conspirata'' in the United States) and ''[[Dictator (Harris novel)|Dictator]]'' comprise a three-part series based on the life of Cicero. In these novels Cicero's character is depicted in a more balanced way than in those of McCullough, with his positive traits equaling or outweighing his weaknesses (while conversely Caesar is depicted as more sinister than in McCullough).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=Higgins |first=Charlotte |url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2018/jun/29/robert-harris-interview-cicero |title=Robert Harris: 'I'm not sure you can be the world's superpower and remain a democracy' |date=29 June 2018 |work=The Guardian |access-date=5 December 2018 |language=en-GB |issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cicero is a major recurring character in the ''[[Roma Sub Rosa]]'' series of mystery novels by [[Steven Saylor]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.stevensaylor.com/RomaSubRosa.html |title=Roma Sub Rosa Mystery Series |website=www.stevensaylor.com |access-date=5 December 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also appears several times as a peripheral character in [[John Maddox Roberts]]' [[SPQR series|''SPQR'' series]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Steel |first=C.E.W. |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ARhaAQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA356 |title=The Cambridge Companion to Cicero |publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=2013 |isbn=978-0-521-50993-0 |page=356 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Samuel Barnett (actor)|Samuel Barnett]] portrays Cicero in a 2017 [[Radio drama|audio drama]] series pilot produced by [[Big Finish Productions]].  A full series was released the following year.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.bigfinish.com/releases/v/cicero-series-01-1777 |title=1. Cicero Series 01 - Big Finish Originals - Big Finish |website=www.bigfinish.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; All Episodes are written by [[David Llewellyn (author)|David Llewellyn]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.bigfinish.com/contributors/v/David-Llewellyn-2366 |title=David Llewellyn - Contributions - Big Finish |website=www.bigfinish.com |access-date=2019-09-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; and directed and produced by [[Scott Handcock]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.bigfinish.com/contributors/v/Scott-Handcock-891 |title=Scott Handcock - Contributions - Big Finish |website=www.bigfinish.com |access-date=2019-09-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Llewellyn, Handcock and Barnet re-teamed in the [[Doctor Who]] audio-drama [[Doctor Who – Main Range#2019|Tartarus]] (also produced by Big Finish) starring [[Peter Davison]] as [[Fifth Doctor|the 5th Doctor]]. It is not intended to be apart the Cicero series, in Vortex (Big Finish's official free online magazine) Llewellyn revealed that he was “ worried that if we had Cicero meeting aliens people might go back to the Cicero series and see it through a [[Science fiction|sci-fi]] lens. Then I remembered that [[Simon Callow]] still performs as [[Charles Dickens]], and that he played Dickens before reprising him in the Doctor Who TV episode, ''[[The Unquiet Dead]]'' – so I got over myself!&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.bigfinish.com/vortex/v/127 |title=Issue 127 - Vortex - Big Finish |website=www.bigfinish.com |access-date=2019-09-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; it was released in September 2019.

==See also==
{{Portal|Ancient Rome}}
{{div col|colwidth=22em}}
* ''[[A Dialogue Concerning Oratorical Partitions]]''
* [[Caecilia Attica]]
* [[Caecilia Metella (daughter of Metellus Celer)]]
* ''[[Civis romanus sum]]''
* [[Clausula (rhetoric)]]
* ''[[E pluribus unum]]''
* ''[[Esse quam videri]]''
* ''[[Ipse dixit]]''
* [[List of ancient Romans]]
* [[Lorem ipsum]]
* [[Marcantonius Majoragio]]
* [[Marcus Tullius Tiro]]
* [[Marius Nizolius]]
* [[Novus homo]]
* ''[[O tempora o mores!]]''
* [[Otium]]
* [[Quintus Tullius Cicero]]
* [[Servius Sulpicius Rufus]]
* [[Tempest in a teapot]]
* [[Titus Pomponius Atticus]]
* [[Translation#Western theory|Translation]]
* [[Tullia (daughter of Cicero)]]
* [[Hellenistic philosophy]]
{{div col end}}

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

== References ==
=== Citations ===
{{Reflist}}

=== Sources ===
{{refbegin|40em|indent=y}}
* [[E. Badian|Badian, E]]: &quot;Cicero and the Commission of 146 B.C.&quot;, ''Collection Latomus'' 101 (1969), 54–65.
* {{cite web |last=Ferguson |last2=Balsdon |first=John |first2=J.P.V.D. |title=Marcus Tullius Cicero |encyclopedia=[[Encyclopædia Britannica]] |type=online |url=https://www.britannica.com/biography/Cicero |lastauthoramp=y |authorlink2=J. P. V. D. Balsdon |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last=Caldwell |first=Taylor |title=A Pillar of Iron |publisher=Doubleday &amp; Company |year=1965 |isbn=978-0-385-05303-7 |location=New York |author-link=Taylor Caldwell}}
* Cicero, Marcus Tullius, Cicero's letters to Atticus, Vol, I, II, IV, VI, [[Cambridge University Press]], Great Britain, 1965
* Cicero, Marcus Tullius, Latin extracts of Cicero on Himself, translated by Charles Gordon Cooper, [[University of Queensland Press]], Brisbane, 1963
* Cicero, Marcus Tullius, Selected Political Speeches, Penguin Books Ltd, Great Britain, 1969
* Cicero, Marcus Tullius, De Officiis (On Duties), translated by [[Walter Miller (philologist)|Walter Miller]]. Harvard University Press, 1913, {{ISBN|978-0-674-99033-3|0-674-99033-1}}
* Cicero, Marcus Tullius, Selected Works, Penguin Books Ltd, Great Britain, 1971
* Cowell, F.R. (1948). ''Cicero and the Roman Republic''. Penguin Books
* {{Cite book |last=Everitt |first=Anthony |title=Cicero: the life and times of Rome's greatest politician |publisher=Random House |year=2001 |isbn=978-0-375-50746-5 |location=New York}}
* {{cite book |editor-last=Greenough |year=1903 |editor-first=J.B. |editor2=G.L. Kittredge |editor3=A.A. Howard |editor4=B.L. D'Ooge |title=Allen and Greenough's New Latin Grammar |edition=revised |publisher=Ginn &amp; Company |place=Boston |origyear=1888 |url=https://archive.org/details/allengreenoughsn00alleiala |lastauthoramp=y |editorlink=James B. Greenough |editorlink2=George Lyman Kittredge |ref={{sfnref|Greenough|Kittredge|Howard|D'Ooge}} }}
* {{Cite book |last=Gruen |first=Erich S. |title=The Last Generation of the Roman Republic |publisher=University of California Press |year=1974 |author-link=Erich S. Gruen}}
* {{Cite book |last=Haskell |first=H.J. |title=This was Cicero |publisher=Alfred A. Knopf |year=1942}}
* {{Cite journal |last=March |first=Duane A. |year=1989 |title=Cicero and the 'Gang of Five' |journal=Classical World |volume=82 |issue=4 |pages=225–34 |doi=10.2307/4350381 |jstor=4350381}}
* {{Cite book |last=Narducci |first=Emanuele |title=Cicerone. La parola e la politica |publisher=Laterza |year=2009 |isbn=978-88-420-7605-6}}
* [[Plutarch]] Penguins Classics English translation by Rex Warner, ''Fall of the Roman Republic, Six Lives by Plutarch: Marius, Sulla, Crassus, Pompey, Caesar, Cicero'' (Penguin Books, 1958; with Introduction and notes by Robin Seager, 1972)
* Rawson, Beryl: ''The Politics of Friendship: Pompey and Cicero'' ([[Sydney University Press]], 1978)
* [[Elizabeth Rawson|Rawson, Elizabeth]]:
** {{Cite journal |last=Rawson |first=Elizabeth |year=1972 |title=Cicero the Historian and Cicero the Antiquarian |journal=Journal of Roman Studies |volume=62 |pages=33–45 |doi=10.2307/298924 |jstor=298924}}
** ''Cicero: A Portrait'' (Allen Lane, Penguin Books Ltd., 1975) {{ISBN|0-7139-0864-5}}. Revised edition: Bristol Classical Press, 1983. {{ISBN|0-86292-051-5}}. American edition of revised edition: [[Cornell University Press]], 1983. {{ISBN|0-8014-1628-0}} (hardcover); {{ISBN|0-8014-9256-4}} (paperback).
* {{Cite book |last=Richards |first=Carl J. |title=Why We're All Romans: The Roman Contribution to the Western World |publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield |year=2010 |isbn=978-0-7425-6778-8}}
* [[H.H. Scullard|Scullard, H.H.]] From the Gracchi to Nero, University Paperbacks, Great Britain, 1968
* Smith, R.E: ''Cicero the Statesman'' (Cambridge University Press, 1966)
* Stockton, David: ''Cicero: A Political Biography'' (Oxford University Press, 1971)
* {{Cite journal |last=Strachan-Davidson |first=James Leigh |author-link=James Leigh Strachan-Davidson |year=1936 |title=Cicero and the Fall of the Roman Republic |location=Oxford |publisher=Oxford University Press}}
* {{Cite journal |last=Taylor |first=H. |year=1918 |title=Cicero: A sketch of his life and works |location=Chicago |publisher=A.C. McClurg &amp; Co.}}
* Uttschenko, Sergej L. (1978): ''Cicero'', translated from Russian by Rosemarie Pattloch, VEB [[Deutscher Verlag der Wissenschaften]], Berlin,  Germany.[https://d-nb.info/790155087 Cicero]
* {{Cite book |last=Wistrand |first=M. |title=Cicero Imperator: Studies in Cicero's Correspondence 51–47 B.C |year=1979 |location=Göteborg}}
* {{Cite book |last=Yates |first=Frances A. |title=The Art of Memory |publisher=University of Chicago Press |year=1974 |isbn=978-0-226-95001-3 |location=Chicago |author-link=Frances Yates}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
* Boissier, Gaston, Cicéron et ses amis. Étude sur la société romaine du temps de César (1884)
* {{Cite book |last=Everitt |first=Anthony |title=Cicero. A turbulent life |publisher=John Murray Publishers |year=2001 |isbn=978-0-7195-5493-3 |location=London}}
* {{Cite book |last=Fuhrmann |first=Manfred |url=https://archive.org/details/ciceroromanrepub0000fuhr |title=Cicero and the Roman Republic |publisher=Blackwell |year=1992 |isbn=978-0-631-17879-8 |location=Oxford}}
* Gildenhard, Ingo (2011). ''Creative Eloquence: The Construction of Reality in Cicero's Speeches''. Oxford/New York: Oxford University Press.
* {{Cite book |last=Habicht |first=Christian |title=Cicero the politician |publisher=Johns Hopkins University Press |year=1990 |isbn=978-0-8018-3872-9 |location=Baltimore}}
* Hamza, Gabor, L'optimus status civitatis di Cicerone e la sua tradizione nel pensiero politico. In: Tradizione romanistica e Costituzione.  Cinquanta anni della Corte Costituzionale della Repubblica Italiana. vol. II. Napoli, 2006. 1455–68.
* Hamza, Gabor, Ciceros Verhältnis zu seinen Quellen, mit besonderer Berücksichtigung der Darstellung der Staatslehre in De re publica. KLIO – Beiträge zur alten Geschichte 67 (1985) 492–97.
* Hamza, Gabor, Cicero und der Idealtypus des iurisconsultus. HELIKON 22–27 (1982–1987) 281–96.
* Hamza, Gabor, Il potere (lo Stato) nel pensiero di Cicerone e la sua attualità. Revista Internacional de Derecho Romano (RIDROM) 10 (2013) 1–25. [http://www.ridrom.uclm.es REVISTA INTERNACIONAL DE DERECHO ROMANO-INDEX]
* Hamza, Gabor, Zur Interpretation des Naturrechts in den Werken von Cicero. Pázmány Law Review 2 (2014) 5–15.{{Cite book |last=Macdonald |first=C. |title=De imperio |publisher=Bristol Classical Press |year=1986 |isbn=978-0-86292-182-8 |edition=Nachdr. d. Ausg. Basingstoke 1966. |location=Bristol}}
* {{Cite encyclopedia |year=2008 |title=The Encyclopedia of Libertarianism |encyclopedia=The Encyclopedia of Libertarianism |publisher=[[SAGE Publications|SAGE]]; [[Cato Institute]] |location=Thousand Oaks, CA |last=Palmer |first=Tom G. |authorlink=Tom G. Palmer |editor-last=Hamowy |editor-first=Ronald |editor-link=Ronald Hamowy |page=63 |doi=10.4135/9781412965811.n42 |isbn=978-1-4129-6580-4 |lccn=2008009151 |oclc=750831024 |chapter=Cicero (106–43 B.C.)}}
* {{Cite book |last=Parenti |first=Michael |url=https://archive.org/details/assassinationofj00mich |title=The Assassination of Julius Caesar: A People's History of Ancient Rome |publisher=The New Press |year=2004 |isbn=978-1-56584-942-6 |location=New York}}
* {{Cite book |title=Cicero the philosopher : twelve papers |publisher=Clarendon Press |year=1995 |isbn=978-0-19-814751-0 |editor-last=Powell |editor-first=J.G.F. |location=Oxford}}
* {{Cite book |last=Shackleton Bailey |first=D. R. |title=Cicero |publisher=Duckworth |year=1971 |isbn=978-0-7156-0574-5 |location=London}}
* {{Cite book |last=Sihler |first=Ernest G. |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3TckAAAAMAAJ |title=Cicero of Arpinum: A Political and Literary Biography |publisher=Yale University Press |year=1914 |location=New Haven}}
* Treggiari, S. (2007). ''Terentia, Tullia and Publilia. The women of Cicero's family. ''London: Routledge

==External links==
{{Commons|Marcus Tullius Cicero}}
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Wikisource author}}
{{Wikisourcelang|la|Marcus Tullius Cicero|Marcus Tullius Cicero}}
{{EB1911 poster|Cicero}}
{{Library resources box |by=yes |onlinebooks=yes |others=yes |about=yes |label=Cicero |viaf= |lccn= |lcheading= |wikititle= }}

;Works by Cicero
* [http://catalog.perseus.org/catalog/urn:cite:perseus:author.364 Works by Cicero at Perseus Digital Library]
* {{Gutenberg author |id=128}}
* {{Internet Archive author}}
* {{Librivox author |id=3336}}
* [[The Latin Library]] (Latin): [http://www.thelatinlibrary.com/cic.html Works of Cicero]
* [http://dcc.dickinson.edu/cicero-verres/preface-and-acknowledgements Dickinson College Commentaries: ''Against Verres 2.1.53–86'']
* [http://dcc.dickinson.edu/cicero-de-imperio/preface-and-acknowledgments Dickinson College Commentaries: ''On Pompey’s Command (De Imperio) 27–49'']
* [http://openn.library.upenn.edu/Data/0023/html/horace_ms_1b.html Horace MS 1b Laelius de Amicitia at OPenn]
* [http://openn.library.upenn.edu/Data/0023/html/lewis_e_066.html Lewis E 66 Epistolae ad familiares (Letters to friends)]

;Biographies and descriptions of Cicero's time
* At Project Gutenberg
* [[Plutarch]]'s biography of Cicero contained in the [http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/674 ''Parallel Lives'']
* ''Life of Cicero'' by Anthony Trollope, [http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/8945 Volume I] – Volume II
* [http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/11448 ''Cicero'' by Rev. W. Lucas Collins (''Ancient Classics for English Readers'')]
* [http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/13481 ''Roman life in the days of Cicero'' by Rev. Alfred J. Church]
* [http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/11256 ''Social life at Rome in the Age of Cicero''] by [[W. Warde Fowler]]
* {{Cite web |url=http://www.heraklia.fws1.com/contemporaries/cicero/ |title=At Heraklia website |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060114090741/http://www.heraklia.fws1.com/contemporaries/cicero/ |archive-date=14 January 2006 |access-date=31 March 2017 |df=dmy-all}}
* [http://classics.mit.edu/Plutarch/cicero.html Dryden's translation of ''Cicero'' from Plutarch's ''Parallel Lives'']
* [http://community.middlebury.edu/~harris/LatinAuthors/Cicero.html At Middlebury College website]

{{S-start}}
{{S-off}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Lucius Julius Caesar (consul 64 BC)|L. Julius Caesar]]|before2=[[Gaius Marcius Figulus (consul 64 BC)|C. Marcius Figulus]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[List of Roman consuls|Consul of Rome]]|years=63 BC|with=[[Gaius Antonius Hybrida|C. Antonius Hybrida]]}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Decimus Junius Silanus (consul)|D. Junius Silanus]]|after2=[[Lucius Licinius Murena|L. Licinius Murena]]}}
{{S-end}}
{{Cicero}}
{{Ancient Rome topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Plutarch}}
{{Catholic virtue ethics}}
{{Ethics}}
{{Social and political philosophy}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cicero}}
[[Category:Cicero| ]]
[[Category:106 BC births]]
[[Category:43 BC deaths]]
[[Category:2nd-century BC Romans]]
[[Category:1st-century BC executions]]
[[Category:1st-century BC philosophers]]
[[Category:1st-century BC Romans]]
[[Category:1st-century BC writers]]
[[Category:Academic skepticism]]
[[Category:Ancient Roman equites|Tullius Cicero, Marcus]]
[[Category:Ancient Roman exiles]]
[[Category:Ancient Roman jurists]]
[[Category:Ancient Roman political philosophers]]
[[Category:Ancient Roman proconsuls]]
[[Category:Ancient Roman rhetoricians]]
[[Category:Ancient Roman scholars of religion]]
[[Category:Classical humanists]]
[[Category:Deaths by blade weapons]]
[[Category:Executed ancient Roman people]]
[[Category:Executed philosophers]]
[[Category:Executed writers]]
[[Category:Golden Age Latin writers]]
[[Category:Latin letter writers]]
[[Category:Murdered philosophers]]
[[Category:Optimates]]
[[Category:People executed by the Roman Republic]]
[[Category:People from Arpino]]
[[Category:Philosophers of Roman Italy]]
[[Category:Recipients of ancient Roman pardons]]
[[Category:Roman aediles]]
[[Category:Roman governors of Cilicia]]
[[Category:Roman quaestors]]
[[Category:Augurs of the Roman Republic]]
[[Category:Roman Republican consuls|Tullius Cicero, Marcus]]
[[Category:Roman Republican praetors|Tullius Cicero, Marcus]]
[[Category:Roman-era philosophers]]
[[Category:Roman-era students in Athens]]
[[Category:Senators of the Roman Republic|Tullius Cicero, Marcus]]
[[Category:Translation scholars]]
[[Category:Translators of Ancient Greek texts]]
[[Category:Trope theorists]]
[[Category:Tullii|Cicero, Marcus]]</text>
      <sha1>4og9kata0zu5xtmwfumwrx3qkan24zy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
