  <page>
    <title>Campaign for Real Ale</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6060</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942716194</id>
      <parentid>942383855</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-26T11:17:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Headhitter</username>
        <id>8629330</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* LocAle */ Punctuation</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|British consumer organisation promoting traditional pubs, real ale and real cider}}
{{Redirect|CAMRA|the Canberra-based musical association|Canberra Academy of Music and Related Arts|other uses|CAMRA (disambiguation)}}
{{Primary sources|date=November 2011}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2016}}
{{Use British English|date=January 2016}}
{{Infobox organisation
|name         = Campaign for Real Ale (CAMRA)
|image        = CAMRAlogo.svg
|image_border = 
|size         = 
|caption      = Logo of CAMRA
|map          =
|msize        = 
|mcaption     =
|motto        =
|formation    = {{Start date and age|1971|df=yes}}
|type         = [[Consumer organization|Consumer organisation]]
|headquarters = [[St. Albans]]
|location     = [[United Kingdom]]
|membership   = 192,470  (as of 3 February 2020)
|language     = [[English language|English]]
|leader_title = National Chairman / [[Chief Executive]]
|leader_name  = Nik Antona / Tom Stainer
|key_people   = 
|num_staff    = 
|budget       = 
|website      = [http://www.camra.org.uk/ www.camra.org.uk]
}}
The '''Campaign for Real Ale''' ('''CAMRA''') is an independent voluntary [[consumer organisation]] headquartered in [[St Albans]], England, which promotes [[real ale]], [[real cider]] and the traditional British [[pub]]. With over 192,000 members, it is now the largest single-issue consumer group in the UK,&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite book
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZAZyZvQIhtcC&amp;pg=PA218&amp;dq=largest+single-issue+consumer+group+in+the+UK
|title=England My England: A Treasury of ...&amp;nbsp;– Google Books
|publisher=books.google.co.uk
|accessdate=2009-07-17
|last=
|first=
|isbn=978-1-86105-893-5
|year=2005
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; and is a founding member of the [[European Beer Consumers' Union|European Beer Consumers Union]] (EBCU).

==History==
[[File:Camra bar towel.JPG|thumb|right|CAMRA logo on a bar towel]]
[[File:1975-CAMRA.JPG|thumb|upright|First National CAMRA Beer Festival held at Covent Garden, London, 1975]]
The organisation was founded on 16 March 1971 in Kruger's bar in [[Dunquin]], [[County Kerry|Kerry]], Ireland&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Key Events in CAMRA's History |url=http://www.camra.org.uk/camrahistory |accessdate=25 July 2013 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120919234946/http://camra.org.uk/camrahistory |archivedate=19 September 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-35917816|work=[[BBC News]]|title=Should there be a crusade to save British pubs?|first=Harry|last=Low|date=31 March 2016|accessdate=31 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; by Michael Hardman, Graham Lees, Jim Makin, and Bill Mellor, who were opposed to the growing mass production of beer and the homogenisation of the British [[brewing]] industry. The original name was the Campaign for the Revitalisation of Ale.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/foodanddrink/4810832/Still-bitter-after-all-these-years.html|title=Still bitter after all these years|newspaper=The Telegraph|accessdate=17 July 2009|last=Neill|first=Richard| location=London| date=9 November 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the formation of the Campaign, the first annual general meeting took place in 1972, at the Rose Inn in Coton Road, [[Nuneaton]]. Early membership consisted of the four founders and their friends. Yet interest in CAMRA and its objectives spread rapidly, with 5,000 members signed up by 1973. Other early influential members included Christopher Hutt, author of ''Death of the English Pub'', who succeeded Hardman as chairman, Frank Baillie, author of ''The Beer Drinker's Companion'', and later the many times ''[[Good Beer Guide]]'' editor, [[Roger Protz]].

On 31 March 2016, founder Michael Hardman returned to chair a Revitalisation Project Steering Group. The aim of the Revitalisation Project was to review the organisation's purpose and future direction. Consultation meetings took place in the spring and summer of 2016,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.camra.org.uk/revitalisation/events|title=CAMRA's Revitalisation Project Events – CAMRA|website=CAMRA|language=en-GB|access-date=25 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; and further discussion took place at the [[Bournemouth]] AGM and Conference in spring 2017 leading to possible refinement of proposals then subject to a final vote of all members at spring 2018's AGM and Conference. At that 2018 meeting, all but one of the proposed special resolutions were passed by voting, which all members could participate in. The failed special resolution related to a proposal for the Campaign to act as the voice and represent the interests of all pub-goers and beer, cider and perry drinkers.

==Aims==
CAMRA's stated aims are:
# To secure the long term future of real ale, real cider and real perry by increasing their quality, availability and popularity
#To promote and protect pubs and clubs as social centres as part of the UK's cultural heritage
#To increase recognition of the benefits of responsible, moderate social drinking
#To play a leading role in the provision of information, education and training to all those with an interest in beer, cider and perry of any type
#To ensure, where possible, that producers and retailers of beer, cider and perry act in the best interests of the customer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.camra.org.uk/press-releases/-/asset_publisher/CfaqMGfKvAEU/content/camra-members-vote-to-approve-change-following-largest-consultation-on-47-year-history|title=Archived copy|access-date=15 June 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180615163235/http://www.camra.org.uk/press-releases/-/asset_publisher/CfaqMGfKvAEU/content/camra-members-vote-to-approve-change-following-largest-consultation-on-47-year-history|archive-date=15 June 2018|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

CAMRA's campaigns include promoting small brewing and pub businesses, reforming licensing laws, reducing tax on beer, and stopping continued consolidation among local British brewers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Campaigns&amp;nbsp;– CAMRA|url=http://www.camra.org.uk/campaigns|accessdate=26 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also makes an effort to promote less common varieties of beer, including [[Stout beer|stout]], [[Porter (beer)|porter]], and [[Mild beer|mild]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Different Styles |url=http://www.camra.org.uk/beerstyles |accessdate=25 July 2013 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130729041918/http://www.camra.org.uk/beerstyles |archivedate=29 July 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as traditional [[cider]] and [[perry]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=About Cider&amp;nbsp;– CAMRA|url=http://www.camra.org.uk/aboutcider|accessdate=26 October 2011|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120122031136/http://www.camra.org.uk/aboutcider|archivedate=22 January 2012|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

CAMRA does not support the promotion and sale of keg based [[craft beer]] in the UK. CAMRA's Internal Policy document states that real ale can only be served without the use of additional carbonation. This policy means that &quot;any beer brand which is produced in both cask and keg versions&quot; is not admitted to CAMRA festivals if the brewery's marketing is deemed to imply an equivalence of quality or character between the two versions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Cromarty, CAMRA and crazy cask cancellation|url=http://refreshingbeer.blogspot.co.uk/2013/03/cromarty-and-camra-we-are-not-all-idiots.html|website=I might have a glass of beer|date=March 15, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Organisation==
[[File:CamraBuildingHatfieldRoadStAlbans.jpg|thumb|The CAMRA office building in St Albans]]
In 2009, CAMRA announced that it had reached the 100,000 members mark and subsequently went on to pass the 150,000 members mark in 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation
 |url         = http://www.camra.org.uk/page.php?id=10
 |title       = What is CAMRA?
 |date        = 4 April 2012
 |accessdate  = 2012-04-04
 |publisher   = CAMRA
 |url-status     = dead
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20120406031423/http://camra.org.uk/page.php?id=10
 |archivedate = 6 April 2012
 |df          = dmy-all
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Member benefits include a monthly newspaper, ''What's Brewing'' and a quarterly ''BEER'' magazine, and free or reduced price admission to CAMRA-organised [[beer festival]]s. In recent times CAMRA has obtained benefits for its members from some commercial organisations and increasingly some licensed premises offer members price reductions on real ale (and sometimes cider and perry).

CAMRA is organised on a federal basis, with numerous independent local branches, each covering a particular geographical area of the UK, that contribute to the central body of the organisation based in [[St Albans]]. It is governed by a voluntary unpaid national executive, elected by the membership.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=What is CAMRA?|url=http://www.camra.org.uk/page.aspx?o=181063|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110110102015/http://www.camra.org.uk/page.aspx?o=181063 |url-status=dead |archive-date=10 January 2011  |publisher=CAMRA |accessdate=27 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The local branches are grouped into 16 regions across the UK, such as the [[West Midlands (region)|West Midlands]] or [[Wessex]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=CAMRA Near You|url=http://www.camra.org.uk/branches |publisher=CAMRA|accessdate=26 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Events and publications==
CAMRA publishes the ''[[Good Beer Guide]]'', an annually compiled directory of its recommended pubs and brewers; the ''[[Good Cider Guide]]'', an occasionally compiled directory of pubs that sell [[cider]]; and the ''Good Bottled Beer Guide'', an occasionally compiled review of [[real ale]] in a bottle.
CAMRA members receive a monthly newspaper called ''What's Brewing'' and a quarterly colour magazine called ''Beer''.
It also runs the [[Great British Beer Festival]], a yearly event held in London at which a large selection of [[cask ale]]s and ciders are tasted. It also maintains a [[CAMRA Pub Heritage Group|National Inventory of Historic Pub Interiors]] to help bring greater recognition and protection to Britain's most historic pubs. In 2013 CAMRA launched public access to a national pub database website called WhatPub.com.

==Festivals==
[[File:GBBF 2.jpg|thumb|Great British Beer Festival 2004]]
CAMRA supports and promotes beer and cider festivals around the country, which are organised by local CAMRA branches. Generally, each festival charges an entry fee which either covers entry only or also includes a commemorative glass showing the details of the festival. A festival programme is usually also provided, with a list and description of the drinks available.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.camra.org.uk/beerfestivals |title=List of upcoming CAMRA beer festivals |access-date=25 July 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130729002251/http://www.camra.org.uk/beerfestivals |archive-date=29 July 2013 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Members often get discounted or free entrance to CAMRA festivals.

The Campaign also organises the annual [[Great British Beer Festival]] in August. It is now held in the Great, National &amp; West Halls at the [[Olympia, London|Olympia Exhibition Centre]], in [[Kensington]], London, having been held for a few years at [[Earls Court Exhibition Centre|Earl's Court]] as well as regionally in the past at venues such as Brighton and Leeds.

==Awards==
CAMRA presents awards for beers and pubs, such as the [[National Pub of the Year]], in which approximately 4,000 active CAMRA members from 200 local branches vote for their favourite pub of the year. The branch winners are entered into 16 regional competitions which are then visited by several individuals who select the ones they like best. There are also the [[Pub Design Awards]], which are held in association with [[English Heritage]] and the [[Victorian Society]].  These comprise several categories, including new build, refurbished and converted pubs.  The best known CAMRA award is the [[Champion Beer of Britain]],&lt;ref&gt;{{citation
|url=http://www.camra.org.uk/cbob
|publisher=Campaign for Real Ale
|title=Champion Beer of Britain
|accessdate=25 July 2013
}}&lt;/ref&gt; which is selected at the [[Great British Beer Festival]], other awards include the [[Champion Beer of Scotland]] and the [[Champion Beer of Wales]].

==National Beer Scoring Scheme==
CAMRA developed the National Beer Scoring Scheme&lt;ref&gt;{{citation
|url=http://www.camra.org.uk/nbss
|title=National Beer Scoring Scheme
|publisher=Campaign for Real Ale
|date=12 January 2006
|first=Brett|last=Laniosh
|accessdate=25 July 2013
}}&lt;/ref&gt; (NBSS) as an easy to use scheme for judging beer quality in pubs, to assist CAMRA branches in selecting pubs for the ''Good Beer Guide''. The person filling in the form records their name, date, the pub, the beer and the score. CAMRA members may also input their beer scores on line via the CAMRA website whatpub.com where that may also optionally add price and a free form comment.

==Pub heritage group==
The CAMRA Pub Heritage Group identifies, records and helps to protect [[pub]] interiors of historic and/or architectural importance, and seeks to get them [[Listed building|listed]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation
|url=http://www.heritagepubs.org.uk
|title=Heritage Pubs&amp;nbsp;– An Overview
|publisher=Campaign for Real Ale &lt;!-- black link i.e. same page --&gt;
|accessdate=2009-05-05
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The group maintains two inventories of Heritage pubs, the National Inventory (NI), which contains only those pubs that have been maintained in their original condition (or have been modified very little) for at least thirty years, but usually since at least [[World War II]]. The second, larger, inventory is the Regional Inventory (RI), which is broken down by [[Counties of the United Kingdom|county]] and contains both those pubs listed in the NI and other pubs that are not eligible for the NI, for reasons such as having been overly modified, but are still considered historically important, or have particular architectural value.

The NI contains 289 pubs {{as of|2009|6|lc=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.heritagepubs.org.uk/home/nationalinventory.asp|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090629082124/http://www.heritagepubs.org.uk/home/nationalinventory.asp
|url-status=dead
|archive-date=2009-06-29
|title=Pub Heritage, the Campaign for Real Ale
|publisher=www.heritagepubs.org.uk
|accessdate=2009-07-17
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

==LocAle==
The LocAle scheme was launched in 2007&lt;ref name=&quot;WB-Aug-Loc&quot;&gt; 'Check your beers urges LocAle creator', ''What's Brewing'', August 2010 issue&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;WB-Sep-Loc&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LocAle1&quot;&gt;[http://www.camra.org.uk/locale CAMRA LocAle] (accessed 25 July 2013)&lt;/ref&gt; to promote locally brewed beers. The scheme functions slightly differently in each area, and is managed by each branch, but each is similar: if the beer is to be promoted as a LocAle it must come from a brewery within a predetermined number of miles set by each CAMRA branch, generally around 20, &lt;ref name=&quot;LocAle2&quot;&gt;[http://www.camra.org.uk/page.php?id=141 LocAle&amp;nbsp;– More Information &amp; Downloads for Licensees] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130922055016/http://www.camra.org.uk/page.php?id=141 |date=22 September 2013 }} (accessed 25 July 2013)&lt;/ref&gt; although the North [[London]] branch has set it at 30 miles&lt;ref name=&quot;CAM-NL-Loc&quot;&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20110527155308/http://www.camranorthlondon.org.uk/locale.html CAMRA North London&amp;nbsp;– LocAle] (accessed 6 September 2010)&lt;/ref&gt; from brewery to pub,&lt;ref name=&quot;WB-Sep-Loc&quot;&gt;'LocAle boosts local tourism', ''What's Brewing'', September 2010 issue&lt;/ref&gt; even if it comes from a distribution centre further away;&lt;ref name=&quot;LocAle2&quot;/&gt; in addition, each participating pub must keep at least one LocAle for sale at all times.&lt;ref name=&quot;LocAle2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CAM-NL-Loc&quot;/&gt;

==Investment club==
CAMRA members may join the CAMRA Members' Investment Club which, since 1989, has invested in real ale breweries and pub chains,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://beta.companieshouse.gov.uk/company/02318099|website=[[Companies House]]|accessdate=18 December 2017|title=Company Information}}&lt;/ref&gt; although all investors must be CAMRA members.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Club rules|url=http://www.howarth-associates.com/cic/rules.htm|website=CAMRA Member Investment Club|accessdate=18 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{portal|Beer|United Kingdom}}
*[[Society for the Preservation of Beers from the Wood]]
*[[Society of Independent Brewers]]
*[[Independent Family Brewers of Britain]]
*[[European Beer Consumers' Union]]
*[[Kenneth Clarke]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
*[http://www.camra.org.uk/ CAMRA website]
*{{dmoz|Recreation/Food/Drink/Beer/Organizations/Campaign_for_Real_Ale|Campaign for Real Ale}}
*[http://www.heritagepubs.org.uk/ Pub Heritage Group&amp;nbsp;– Official Site]
*[http://www.gbbf.org.uk/ Great British Beer Festival]

{{British beer}}
{{CAMRA}}
{{Coord|51.7518|-0.3141|display=title}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2013}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Campaign For Real Ale}}
[[Category:1971 establishments in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Beer in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Beer organizations]]
[[Category:British food and drink organisations]]
[[Category:Consumer organisations in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Organisations based in Hertfordshire]]
[[Category:Organizations established in 1971]]</text>
      <sha1>fk7jrqvli8eya14zuyf6xzl1zg6eg8p</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
