  <page>
    <title>Collagen</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6058</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941127349</id>
      <parentid>941121923</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-16T19:25:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Trappist the monk</username>
        <id>10289486</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 941121923 by [[Special:Contributions/2600:1012:B02F:5AC8:CCF8:BAF5:3B59:8C85|2600:1012:B02F:5AC8:CCF8:BAF5:3B59:8C85]] ([[User talk:2600:1012:B02F:5AC8:CCF8:BAF5:3B59:8C85|talk]]) broke citation template;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Collagentriplehelix.png|thumb|upright=1.5|Tropocollagen molecule: three left-handed procollagens (red, green, blue) join to form a right-handed triple helical tropocollagen.]]

'''Collagen''' {{IPAc-en|ˈ|k|ɒ|l|ə|dʒ|ᵻ|n}} is the main structural [[protein]] in the [[extracellular matrix]] in the various [[connective tissue]]s in the body. As the main component of connective tissue, it is the most abundant protein in mammals,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |first=Gloria A. |last=Di Lullo |first2=Shawn M. |last2=Sweeney |first3=Jarmo |last3=Körkkö |first4=Leena |last4=Ala-Kokko |lastauthoramp=yes |first5=James D. |last5=San Antonio |title=Mapping the Ligand-binding Sites and Disease-associated Mutations on the Most Abundant Protein in the Human, Type I Collagen |journal=[[Journal of Biological Chemistry|J. Biol. Chem.]] |volume=277 |issue=6 |pages=4223–4231 |year=2002 |pmid=11704682 |doi=10.1074/jbc.M110709200 }}&lt;/ref&gt; making up from 25% to 35% of the whole-body protein content. Collagen consists of [[amino acid]]s bound together to form a [[triple helix]] of elongated [[fibril]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=https://www.economist.com/news/science-and-technology/21727059-genetic-engineering-used-make-leather-without-animals-leather-grown-using|title=Leather grown using biotechnology is about to hit the catwalk|journal=The Economist|access-date=2017-09-02|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170901230634/https://www.economist.com/news/science-and-technology/21727059-genetic-engineering-used-make-leather-without-animals-leather-grown-using|archivedate=2017-09-01|date=2017-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; known as a [[collagen helix]]. It is mostly found in [[Fibrous connective tissue|fibrous tissues]] such as [[tendon]]s, [[ligament]]s, and [[skin]].

Depending upon the degree of mineralization, collagen tissues may be rigid (bone), compliant (tendon), or have a gradient from rigid to compliant (cartilage). It is also abundant in [[cornea]]s, [[blood vessel]]s, the [[Gut (anatomy)|gut]], [[intervertebral disc]]s, and the [[dentin]] in teeth.&lt;ref&gt;Britannica Concise Encyclopedia 2007&lt;/ref&gt; In [[muscle tissue]], it serves as a major component of the [[endomysium]]. Collagen constitutes one to two percent of muscle tissue and accounts for 6% of the weight of strong, tendinous, muscles.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Sikorski |first=Zdzisław E. |year=2001 |title=Chemical and Functional Properties of Food Proteins |location=Boca Raton |publisher=CRC Press |page=242 |isbn=978-1-56676-960-0 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[fibroblast]] is the most common cell that creates collagen. [[Gelatin]], which is used in food and industry, is collagen that has been irreversibly [[hydrolyzed]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Bogue |first=Robert H. |title=Conditions Affecting the Hydrolysis of Collagen to Gelatin |journal=Industrial and Engineering Chemistry |volume=15 |issue=11 |pages=1154–1159 |year=1923 |doi=10.1021/ie50167a018 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Collagen has many medical uses in treating complications of the bones and skin.

The name ''collagen'' comes from the Greek [[wikt:κόλλα#Ancient Greek|κόλλα]] (''kólla''), meaning &quot;[[glue]]&quot;, and suffix -γέν, ''-gen'', denoting &quot;producing&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;O.E.D. 2nd Edition 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Müller |first=Werner E. G. |title=The Origin of Metazoan Complexity: Porifera as Integrated Animals |journal=Integrative and Comparative Biology |volume=43 |issue=1 |pages=3–10 |year=2003 |doi=10.1093/icb/43.1.3 |pmid=21680404|citeseerx=10.1.1.333.3174 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This refers to the compound's early use in the process of boiling the skin and [[tendon]]s of [[horse]]s and other animals to obtain glue.

==Types==
Over 90% of the collagen in the [[human body]] is [[type I collagen]].&lt;ref&gt;Sabiston textbook of surgery board review, 7th edition. Chapter 5 wound healing, question 14&lt;/ref&gt; However, as of 2011, 30 types of collagen have been identified, described, and divided into several groups according to the structure they form:&lt;ref name=&quot;Ricard-Blum&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |pmc = 3003457|year = 2011|last1 = Ricard-Blum|first1 = S.|title = The Collagen Family|journal = Cold Spring Harbor Perspectives in Biology|volume = 3|issue = 1|pages = a004978|pmid = 21421911|doi = 10.1101/cshperspect.a004978}}&lt;/ref&gt; All of the types contain at least one [[triple helix]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ricard-Blum&quot;/&gt; The number of types shows collagen's diverse functionality.&lt;ref name=&quot;Franzke&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Franzke |first1=CW |last2=Bruckner |first2=P |last3=Bruckner-Tuderman |first3=L |title=Collagenous transmembrane proteins: recent insights into biology and pathology. |journal=The Journal of Biological Chemistry |date=11 February 2005 |volume=280 |issue=6 |pages=4005–8 |doi=10.1074/jbc.R400034200 |pmid=15561712}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*Fibrillar (Type I, II, III, V, XI)
*Non-fibrillar
**[[FACIT collagen|FACIT]] (Fibril Associated Collagens with Interrupted Triple Helices) (Type IX, XII, XIV, XIX, XXI)
**Short chain (Type VIII, X)
**[[Basement membrane]] (Type IV)
**[[Multiplexin]] (Multiple Triple Helix domains with Interruptions) (Type XV, XVIII)
**MACIT (Membrane Associated Collagens with Interrupted Triple Helices) (Type XIII, XVII)
**Other (Type VI, VII)

The five most common types are:

*[[Type I collagen|Type I]]: [[skin]], [[tendon]], vasculature, organs, [[bone]] (main component of the organic part of bone)
*[[Type II collagen|Type II]]: [[cartilage]] (main collagenous component of cartilage)
*[[Collagen, type III, alpha 1|Type III]]: reticulate (main component of [[reticular fiber]]s), commonly found alongside type I
*[[Type IV collagen|Type IV]]: forms basal lamina, the epithelium-secreted layer of the [[basement membrane]]
*[[Type-V collagen|Type V]]: cell surfaces, [[hair]], and [[placenta]]

==Medical uses==

===Cardiac applications===
The collagenous [[cardiac skeleton]] which includes the four [[heart valve]] rings, is histologically, elastically and uniquely bound to cardiac muscle. The cardiac skeleton also includes the separating septa of the heart chambers – the [[interventricular septum]] and the [[atrioventricular septum]]. Collagen contribution to the measure of [[Cardiac stress test|cardiac performance]] summarily represents a continuous torsional force opposed to the [[fluid mechanics]] of [[blood]] pressure emitted from the heart. The collagenous structure that divides the upper chambers of the heart from the lower chambers is an impermeable membrane that excludes both blood and electrical impulses through typical physiological means. With support from collagen, [[atrial fibrillation]] never deteriorates to [[ventricular fibrillation]]. Collagen is layered in variable densities with smooth muscle mass. The mass, distribution, age and density of collagen all contribute to the [[compliance (physiology)|compliance]] required to move blood back and forth. Individual cardiac valvular leaflets are folded into shape by specialized collagen under variable [[pressure]]. Gradual [[calcium]] deposition within collagen occurs as a natural function of aging. Calcified points within collagen matrices show contrast in a moving display of blood and muscle, enabling methods of [[cardiac imaging]] technology to arrive at ratios essentially stating blood in ([[cardiac input]]) and blood out ([[cardiac output]]). Pathology of the collagen underpinning of the heart is understood within the category of [[connective tissue disease]].

===Cosmetic surgery===
Collagen has been widely used in cosmetic surgery, as a healing aid for burn patients for reconstruction of bone and a wide variety of dental, orthopedic, and surgical purposes. Both human and bovine collagen is widely used as dermal fillers for treatment of wrinkles and skin aging.&lt;ref name=&quot;pharmax2&quot;&gt;[http://pharmaxchange.info/press/2011/03/the-ageing-skin-part-4e-dermal-fillers/ Dermal Fillers | The Ageing Skin] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110513225727/http://pharmaxchange.info/press/2011/03/the-ageing-skin-part-4e-dermal-fillers/ |date=2011-05-13 }}. Pharmaxchange.info. Retrieved on 2013-04-21.&lt;/ref&gt; Some points of interest are:
#When used cosmetically, there is a chance of allergic reactions causing prolonged redness; however, this can be virtually eliminated by simple and inconspicuous [[patch test]]ing prior to cosmetic use.
#Most medical collagen is derived from young beef cattle (bovine) from certified [[bovine spongiform encephalopathy|BSE]]-free animals. Most manufacturers use donor animals from either &quot;closed herds&quot;, or from countries which have never had a reported case of BSE such as Australia, Brazil, and New Zealand.

===Bone grafts===
As the skeleton forms the structure of the body, it is vital that it maintains its strength, even after breaks and injuries. Collagen is used in bone grafting as it has a triple helical structure, making it a very strong molecule. It is ideal for use in bones, as it does not compromise the structural integrity of the skeleton. The triple helical structure of collagen prevents it from being broken down by enzymes, it enables adhesiveness of cells and it is important for the proper assembly of the extracellular matrix.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Cunniffe|first=G|author2=F O'Brien|title=Collagen scaffolds for orthopedic regenerative medicine|journal=The Journal of the Minerals, Metals and Materials Society|year=2011|volume=63|issue=4|pages=66–73|doi=10.1007/s11837-011-0061-y|bibcode = 2011JOM....63d..66C }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tissue regeneration===
Collagen scaffolds are used in tissue regeneration, whether in sponges, thin sheets, or gels. Collagen has the correct properties for tissue regeneration such as pore structure, permeability, hydrophilicity, and being stable in vivo. Collagen scaffolds are also ideal for the deposition of cells such as [[osteoblasts]] and [[fibroblast]]s, and once inserted, growth is able to continue as normal in the tissue.&lt;ref name=Oliveira&gt;{{cite journal|last=Oliveira|first=S|author2=R Ringshia |author3=R Legeros |author4=E Clark |author5=L Terracio |author6=C Teixeira M Yost |title=An improved collagen scaffold for skeletal regeneration|journal=Journal of Biomedical Materials|year=2009|volume=94|issue=2|pages=371–379|doi=10.1002/jbm.a.32694|pmc=2891373|pmid=20186736}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reconstructive surgical uses===
Collagens are widely employed in the construction of the [[artificial skin]] substitutes used in the management of severe [[burn (injury)|burns]] and wounds.&lt;ref name=&quot;Singh&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Onkar|first1=Singh|last2=Gupta|first2=Shilpi Singh|last3=Soni|first3=Mohan|last4=Moses|first4=Sonia|last5=Shukla|first5=Sumit|last6=Mathur|first6=Raj Kumar|title=Collagen Dressing Versus Conventional Dressings in Burn and Chronic Wounds: A Retrospective Study|journal= Journal of Cutaneous and Aesthetic Surgery|date=January 2011|volume=4|issue=1|pages=12–16|doi=10.4103/0974-2077.79180|pmc=3081477|accessdate=|pmid=21572675}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|pmc=4717516|year=2016|last1=Gould|first1=L. J.|title=Topical Collagen-Based Biomaterials for Chronic Wounds: Rationale and Clinical Application|journal=Advances in Wound Care|volume=5|issue=1|pages=19–31|doi=10.1089/wound.2014.0595|pmid=26858912}}&lt;/ref&gt; These collagens may be derived from bovine, equine, porcine, or even human sources; and are sometimes used in combination with [[silicone]]s, [[glycosaminoglycan]]s, [[fibroblast]]s, [[growth factor]]s and other substances.

=== Wound healing ===
Collagen is one of the body’s key natural resources and a component of skin tissue that can benefit all stages of [[wound healing]].&lt;ref name=&quot;scr&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Type-1 pericytes accumulate after tissue injury and produce collagen in an organ-dependent manner|journal = Stem Cell Research &amp; Therapy|date = 2014-11-06|issn = 1757-6512|pmc = 4445991|pmid = 25376879|pages = 122|volume = 5|issue = 6|doi = 10.1186/scrt512|first = Alexander|last = Birbrair|first2 = Tan|last2 = Zhang|first3 = Daniel C.|last3 = Files|first4 = Sandeep|last4 = Mannava|first5 = Thomas|last5 = Smith|first6 = Zhong-Min|last6 = Wang|first7 = Maria L.|last7 = Messi|first8 = Akiva|last8 = Mintz|first9 = Osvaldo|last9 = Delbono|df = }}&lt;/ref&gt; When collagen is made available to the wound bed, closure can occur. Wound deterioration, followed sometimes by procedures such as amputation, can thus be avoided.

Collagen is a natural product and is thus used as a natural wound dressing and has properties that artificial wound dressings do not have. It is resistant against bacteria, which is of vital importance in a wound dressing. It helps to keep the wound sterile, because of its natural ability to fight infection. When collagen is used as a burn dressing, healthy [[granulation tissue]] is able to form very quickly over the burn, helping it to heal rapidly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Singh|first=O|author2=SS Gupta |author3=M Soni |author4=S Moses |author5=S Shukla |author6=RK Mathur |title=Collagen dressing versus conventional dressings in burn and chronic wounds: a retrospective study|journal=Journal of Cutaneous and Aesthetic Surgery|year=2011|volume=4|issue=1|pages=12–16|doi=10.4103/0974-2077.79180|pmid=21572675|pmc=3081477}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Throughout the 4 phases of wound healing, collagen performs the following functions in wound healing:
*Guiding function: Collagen fibers serve to guide fibroblasts. Fibroblasts migrate along a connective tissue matrix.
*Chemotactic properties: The large surface area available on collagen fibers can attract fibrogenic cells which help in healing.
*Nucleation: Collagen, in the presence of certain neutral salt molecules can act as a nucleating agent causing formation of fibrillar structures. A collagen wound dressing might serve as a guide for orienting new collagen deposition and capillary growth.
*Hemostatic properties: Blood [[platelet]]s interact with the collagen to make a hemostatic plug.

==As a supplement==
When hydrolyzed, collagen is reduced to small [[peptide]]s, which can be ingested in the form of a [[dietary supplement]] or [[functional food]]s and beverages with the intent to aid joint and bone health and enhance skin health.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Guillerminet|first=Fanny|last2=Beaupied|first2=Hélène|last3=Fabien-Soulé|first3=Véronique|last4=Tomé|first4=Daniel|last5=Benhamou|first5=Claude-Laurent|last6=Roux|first6=Christian|last7=Blais|first7=Anne|date=2010-03-01|title=Hydrolyzed collagen improves bone metabolism and biomechanical parameters in ovariectomized mice: An in vitro and in vivo study|journal=Bone|language=English|volume=46|issue=3|pages=827–834|doi=10.1016/j.bone.2009.10.035|pmid=19895915|issn=8756-3282}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Guillerminet|first=F.|last2=Fabien-Soulé|first2=V.|last3=Even|first3=P. C.|last4=Tomé|first4=D.|last5=Benhamou|first5=C.-L.|last6=Roux|first6=C.|last7=Blais|first7=A.|date=2012-07-01|title=Hydrolyzed collagen improves bone status and prevents bone loss in ovariectomized C3H/HeN mice|journal=Osteoporosis International|language=en|volume=23|issue=7|pages=1909–1919|doi=10.1007/s00198-011-1788-6|pmid=21927918|issn=0937-941X}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Daneault|first=A.|date=2014-04-01|title=Hydrolyzed collagen contributes to osteoblast differentiation in vitro and subsequent bone health in vivo|url=http://www.oarsijournal.com/article/S1063-4584(14)00280-5/fulltext|journal=Osteoarthritis and Cartilage|language=English|volume=22|pages=S131|doi=10.1016/j.joca.2014.02.240|issn=1063-4584}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Daneault|first=Audrey|last2=Prawitt|first2=Janne|last3=Fabien Soulé|first3=Véronique|last4=Coxam|first4=Véronique|last5=Wittrant|first5=Yohann|date=2017-06-13|title=Biological effect of hydrolyzed collagen on bone metabolism|journal=Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition|volume=57|issue=9|pages=1922–1937|doi=10.1080/10408398.2015.1038377|issn=1549-7852|pmid=25976422|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170913183348/https://zenodo.org/record/889529|archivedate=2017-09-13|url=https://zenodo.org/record/889529|access-date=2017-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Jiang|first=J.X.|date=2014|title=Collagen peptides improve knee osteoarthritis in elderly women: A 6-month randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study|url=http://old.teknoscienze.com//articles/agro-food-industry-hi-tech-collagen-peptides-improve-knee-osteoarthritis-in-elderly-women-a.aspx#.WXCW-oSGNtR|journal=Agro FOOD Indusrty Hi Tech|volume=25|pages=19–23|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170913183401/http://old.teknoscienze.com//articles/agro-food-industry-hi-tech-collagen-peptides-improve-knee-osteoarthritis-in-elderly-women-a.aspx#.WXCW-oSGNtR|archivedate=2017-09-13|access-date=2017-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Dar|first=Qurratul-Ain|last2=Schott|first2=Eric M.|last3=Catheline|first3=Sarah E.|last4=Maynard|first4=Robert D.|last5=Liu|first5=Zhaoyang|last6=Kamal|first6=Fadia|last7=Farnsworth|first7=Christopher W.|last8=Ketz|first8=John P.|last9=Mooney|first9=Robert A.|date=2017-04-06|title=Daily oral consumption of hydrolyzed type 1 collagen is chondroprotective and anti-inflammatory in murine posttraumatic osteoarthritis|journal=PLOS ONE|volume=12|issue=4|pages=e0174705|doi=10.1371/journal.pone.0174705|issn=1932-6203|pmc=5383229|pmid=28384173|df=|bibcode=2017PLoSO..1274705D}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Asserin|first=Jérome|last2=Lati|first2=Elian|last3=Shioya|first3=Toshiaki|last4=Prawitt|first4=Janne|date=2015-12-01|title=The effect of oral collagen peptide supplementation on skin moisture and the dermal collagen network: evidence from an ex vivo model and randomized, placebo‐controlled clinical trials|journal=Journal of Cosmetic Dermatology|language=en|volume=14|issue=4|pages=291–301|doi=10.1111/jocd.12174|pmid=26362110|issn=1473-2165|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hydrolyzed collagen]] has a much smaller [[Molecular Weight|molecular weight]] in comparison to native collagen or [[gelatin]]. Studies suggest that more than 90% of hydrolyzed collagen is digested and available as small peptides in the blood stream within one hour. From the blood, the peptides (containing [[hydroxyproline]]) are transported into the target tissues (e.g., skin, bones, and cartilage)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Ichikawa|first=Satomi|last2=Morifuji|first2=Masashi|last3=Ohara|first3=Hiroki|last4=Matsumoto|first4=Hitoshi|last5=Takeuchi|first5=Yasuo|last6=Sato|first6=Kenji|date=2010-02-01|title=Hydroxyproline-containing dipeptides and tripeptides quantified at high concentration in human blood after oral administration of gelatin hydrolysate|journal=International Journal of Food Sciences and Nutrition|volume=61|issue=1|pages=52–60|doi=10.3109/09637480903257711|issn=0963-7486|pmid=19961355}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Shigemura|first=Yasutaka|last2=Kubomura|first2=Daiki|last3=Sato|first3=Yoshio|last4=Sato|first4=Kenji|date=2014-09-15|title=Dose-dependent changes in the levels of free and peptide forms of hydroxyproline in human plasma after collagen hydrolysate ingestion|journal=Food Chemistry|volume=159|pages=328–332|doi=10.1016/j.foodchem.2014.02.091|pmid=24767063}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Watanabe-Kamiyama|first=Mari|last2=Shimizu|first2=Muneshige|last3=Kamiyama|first3=Shin|last4=Taguchi|first4=Yasuki|last5=Sone|first5=Hideyuki|last6=Morimatsu|first6=Fumiki|last7=Shirakawa|first7=Hitoshi|last8=Furukawa|first8=Yuji|last9=Komai|first9=Michio|date=2010-01-27|title=Absorption and Effectiveness of Orally Administered Low Molecular Weight Collagen Hydrolysate in Rats|journal=Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry|volume=58|issue=2|pages=835–841|doi=10.1021/jf9031487|pmid=19957932|issn=0021-8561}}&lt;/ref&gt;, where the peptides act as building blocks for local cells and help boost the production of new collagen fibers.{{Citation needed|reason=The provided references do not show evidence for any boosting effect on collagen production|date=December 2018}}

==Basic research==
Collagen is used in [[basic research|laboratory studies]] for [[cell culture]], studying cell behavior and cellular interactions with the [[extracellular fluid|extracellular environment]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Blow |first=Nathan |year=2009 |title=Cell culture: building a better matrix |journal=Nature Methods |volume=6 |issue=8 |pages=619–622 |doi=10.1038/nmeth0809-619 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Chemistry==
The collagen protein is composed of a triple helix, which generally consists of two identical chains (α1) and an additional chain that differs slightly in its chemical composition (α2).&lt;ref name=&quot;SzpakJAS&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Szpak |first=Paul |title=Fish bone chemistry and ultrastructure: implications for taphonomy and stable isotope analysis |url=https://www.academia.edu/801925 |journal=Journal of Archaeological Science |year=2011 |volume=38 |issue=12 |pages=3358–3372 |doi=10.1016/j.jas.2011.07.022 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140415235652/http://www.academia.edu/801925/Fish_Bone_Chemistry_and_Ultrastructure_Implications_for_Taphonomy_and_Stable_Isotope_Analysis |archivedate=2014-04-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The amino acid composition of collagen is atypical for proteins, particularly with respect to its high [[hydroxyproline]] content. The most common motifs in the amino acid sequence of collagen are [[glycine]]-[[proline]]-X and glycine-X-hydroxyproline, where X is any amino acid other than glycine, proline or hydroxyproline. The average amino acid composition for fish and mammal skin is given.&lt;ref name=&quot;SzpakJAS&quot;/&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! Amino acid !! Abundance in mammal skin&lt;br&gt;([[Residue (biochemistry)|residues]]/1000) !! Abundance in fish skin&lt;Br&gt;(residues/1000)
|-
| [[Glycine]] || 329 || 339
|-
| [[Proline]] || 126 || 108
|-
| [[Alanine]] || 109 || 114
|-
| [[Hydroxyproline]] || 95 || 67
|-
| [[Glutamic acid]] || 74 || 76
|-
| [[Arginine]] || 49 || 52
|-
| [[Aspartic acid]] || 47 || 47
|-
| [[Serine]] || 36 || 46
|-
| [[Lysine]] || 29 || 26
|-
| [[Leucine]] || 24 || 23
|-
| [[Valine]] || 22 || 21
|-
| [[Threonine]] || 19 || 26
|-
| [[Phenylalanine]] || 13 || 14
|-
| [[Isoleucine]] || 11 || 11
|-
| [[Hydroxylysine]] || 6 || 8
|-
| [[Methionine]] || 6 || 13
|-
| [[Histidine]] || 5 || 7
|-
| [[Tyrosine]] || 3 || 3
|-
| [[Cysteine]] || 1 || 1
|-
| [[Tryptophan]] || 0 || 0
|}

==Synthesis==
First, a three-dimensional stranded structure is assembled, with the amino acids glycine and proline as its principal components. This is not yet collagen but its precursor, procollagen. Procollagen is then modified by the addition of [[hydroxyl]] groups to the amino acids [[proline]] and [[lysine]]. This step is important for later [[glycosylation]] and the formation of the triple helix structure of collagen. Because the hydroxylase enzymes that perform these reactions require [[vitamin C]] as a cofactor, a long-term deficiency in this vitamin results in impaired collagen synthesis and [[scurvy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|pmid=1720597|year=1991|last1=Peterkofsky|first1=B|title=Ascorbate requirement for hydroxylation and secretion of procollagen: Relationship to inhibition of collagen synthesis in scurvy|journal=American Journal of Clinical Nutrition|volume=54|issue=6 Suppl|pages=1135S–1140S|doi=10.1093/ajcn/54.6.1135s}}&lt;/ref&gt; These hydroxylation reactions are catalyzed by two different enzymes: prolyl-4-hydroxylase&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Gorres |first1=K. L. |last2=Raines |first2=R. T. |title=Prolyl 4-hydroxylase |journal=Crit. Rev. Biochem. Mol. Biol. |year=2010 |volume=45 |pmid=20199358 |pmc=2841224 |doi=10.3109/10409231003627991 |issue=2 |pages=106–24 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and lysyl-hydroxylase. Vitamin C also serves with them in inducing these reactions. In this service, one molecule of vitamin C is destroyed for each H replaced by OH.
&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Myllylä |first1=R. |last2=Majamaa |first2=K. |last3=Günzler |first3=V. |last4=Hanauske-Abel |first4=H. M. |last5=Kivirikko |first5= K. I. |title=Ascorbate is consumed stoichiometrically in the uncoupled reactions catalyzed by propyl 4-hydroxylase and lysyl hydroxylase |journal=J. Biol. Chem. |year=1984 |volume=259 |pmid=6325436 |issue=9 |pages=5403–5 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
The synthesis of collagen occurs inside and outside of the cell. The formation of collagen which results in fibrillary collagen (most common form) is discussed here. Meshwork collagen, which is often involved in the formation of filtration systems, is the other form of collagen. All types of collagens are triple helices, and the differences lie in the make-up of the alpha peptides created in step 2.
# '''Transcription of mRNA''': About 34 genes are associated with collagen formation, each coding for a specific mRNA sequence, and typically have the &quot;''COL''&quot; prefix. The beginning of collagen synthesis begins with turning on genes which are associated with the formation of a particular alpha peptide (typically alpha 1, 2 or 3).
# '''Pre-pro-peptide formation''': Once the final mRNA exits from the cell nucleus and enters into the cytoplasm, it links with the ribosomal subunits and the process of translation occurs. The early/first part of the new peptide is known as the signal sequence. The signal sequence on the [[N-terminal]] of the peptide is recognized by a [[signal recognition particle]] on the endoplasmic reticulum, which will be responsible for directing the pre-pro-peptide into the endoplasmic reticulum. Therefore, once the synthesis of new peptide is finished, it goes directly into the endoplasmic reticulum for post-translational processing. It is now known as pre-pro-collagen.
# '''Pre-pro-peptide to pro-collagen''': Three modifications of the pre-pro-peptide occur leading to the formation of the alpha peptide:
## The signal peptide on the N-terminal is removed, and the molecule is now known as ''propeptide'' (not procollagen).
## Hydroxylation of lysines and prolines on propeptide by the enzymes 'prolyl hydroxylase' and 'lysyl hydroxylase' (to produce hydroxyproline and hydroxylysine) occurs to aid cross-linking of the alpha peptides. This enzymatic step requires [[vitamin C]] as a cofactor. In [[scurvy]], the lack of hydroxylation of prolines and lysines causes a looser triple helix (which is formed by three alpha peptides). 
## Glycosylation occurs by adding either glucose or galactose monomers onto the hydroxyl groups that were placed onto lysines, but not on prolines. 
## Once these modifications have taken place, three of the hydroxylated and glycosylated propeptides twist into a triple helix forming procollagen. Procollagen still has unwound ends, which will be later trimmed. At this point, the procollagen is packaged into a transfer vesicle destined for the Golgi apparatus. 
# '''Golgi apparatus modification''': In the Golgi apparatus, the procollagen goes through one last post-translational modification before being secreted out of the cell. In this step, oligosaccharides (not monosaccharides as in step 3) are added, and then the procollagen is packaged into a secretory vesicle destined for the extracellular space.
# '''Formation of tropocollagen''': Once outside the cell, membrane bound enzymes known as collagen peptidases, remove the &quot;loose ends&quot; of the procollagen molecule. What is left is known as tropocollagen. Defects in this step produce one of the many collagenopathies known as [[Ehlers-Danlos syndrome]]. This step is absent when synthesizing type III, a type of fibrilar collagen.
# '''Formation of the collagen fibril''': [[lysyl oxidase]], an extracellular [[Copper in health|copper-dependent]] enzyme, produces the final step in the collagen synthesis pathway. This enzyme acts on lysines and hydroxylysines producing aldehyde groups, which will eventually undergo covalent bonding between tropocollagen molecules. This polymer of tropocollogen is known as a collagen fibril.

[[File:Tropocollagen cross-linkage lysyl oxidase (EN).svg|thumb|upright=1.3|Action of [[lysyl oxidase]]]]

===Amino acids===
Collagen has an unusual [[amino acid]] composition and sequence:
* [[Glycine]] is found at almost every third [[residue (biochemistry)|residue]].
* [[Proline]] makes up about 17% of collagen.
* Collagen contains two uncommon derivative amino acids not directly inserted during [[translation (genetics)|translation]]. These amino acids are found at specific locations relative to glycine and are modified post-translationally by different enzymes, both of which require [[vitamin C]] as a [[cofactor (biochemistry)|cofactor]].
** [[Hydroxyproline]] derived from proline
** [[Hydroxylysine]] derived from [[lysine]] - depending on the type of collagen, varying numbers of hydroxylysines are [[glycosylation|glycosylated]] (mostly having [[disaccharide]]s attached).

[[Cortisol]] stimulates [[Amide hydrolysis|degradation]] of (skin) collagen into amino acids.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Houck |first=J. C. |last2=Sharma |first2=V. K. |last3=Patel |first3=Y. M. |last4=Gladner |first4=J. A. |year=1968 |title=Induction of Collagenolytic and Proteolytic Activities by AntiInflammatory Drugs in the Skin and Fibroblasts |journal=[[Biochemical Pharmacology (journal)|Biochemical Pharmacology]] |pmid=4301453 |volume=17 |issue=10 |pages=2081–2090 |doi=10.1016/0006-2952(68)90182-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Collagen I formation ===
Most collagen forms in a similar manner, but the following process is typical for type I:

#Inside the cell
##Two types of alpha chains are formed during [[translation (genetics)|translation]] on ribosomes along the [[rough endoplasmic reticulum]] (RER): alpha-1 and alpha-2 chains. These peptide chains (known as [[preprocollagen]]) have [[registration peptide]]s on each end and a [[signal peptide]].
##Polypeptide chains are released into the lumen of the RER.
##Signal peptides are cleaved inside the RER and the chains are now known as pro-alpha chains.
##[[Hydroxylation]] of [[lysine]] and [[proline]] amino acids occurs inside the lumen. This process is dependent on [[ascorbic acid]] (vitamin C) as a [[cofactor (biochemistry)|cofactor]].
##[[Glycosylation]] of specific hydroxylysine residues occurs.
##Triple alpha helical structure is formed inside the endoplasmic reticulum from two alpha-1 chains and one alpha-2 chain.
##[[Procollagen]] is shipped to the [[Golgi apparatus]], where it is packaged and secreted by [[exocytosis]].
#Outside the cell
##Registration peptides are cleaved and tropocollagen is formed by [[procollagen peptidase]].
##Multiple tropocollagen molecules form collagen fibrils, via covalent cross-linking ([[aldol reaction]]) by [[lysyl oxidase]] which links hydroxylysine and lysine residues. Multiple collagen fibrils form into collagen fibers.
##Collagen may be attached to cell membranes via several types of protein, including [[fibronectin]], [[laminin]], [[fibulin]] and [[integrin]].

===Synthetic pathogenesis===
Vitamin C deficiency causes [[scurvy]], a serious and painful disease in which defective collagen prevents the formation of strong [[connective tissue]]. [[Gingiva|Gums]] deteriorate and bleed, with loss of teeth; skin discolors, and [[wound]]s do not heal. Prior to the 18th century, this condition was notorious among long-duration military, particularly naval, expeditions during which participants were deprived of foods containing vitamin C.

An [[autoimmune disease]] such as [[lupus erythematosus]] or [[rheumatoid arthritis]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Al-Hadithy |first=H. |year=1982 |first2=DA |last3=Addison |first3=IE |last4=Goldstone |first4=AH |last5=Snaith |first5=ML |title=Neutrophil function in systemic lupus erythematosus and other collagen diseases |journal=Ann Rheum Dis |volume=41 |pmid=7065727 |issue=1 |pmc=1000860 |pages=33–38 |doi=10.1136/ard.41.1.33 |displayauthors=2 |last2=Isenberg }}&lt;/ref&gt; may attack healthy collagen fibers.

Many bacteria and viruses secrete [[virulence factor]]s, such as the enzyme [[collagenase]], which destroys collagen or interferes with its production.

==Molecular structure==
A single collagen molecule, tropocollagen, is used to make up larger collagen aggregates, such as fibrils. It is approximately 300&amp;nbsp;[[nanometre|nm]] long and 1.5&amp;nbsp;nm in diameter, and it is made up of three [[polypeptide]] strands (called alpha peptides, see step 2), each of which has the conformation of a left-handed [[helix]] – this should not be confused with the right-handed [[alpha helix]]. These three left-handed helices are twisted together into a right-handed triple helix or &quot;super helix&quot;, a cooperative [[quaternary structure]] stabilized by many [[hydrogen bond]]s. With type I collagen and possibly all fibrillar collagens, if not all collagens, each triple-helix associates into a right-handed super-super-coil referred to as the collagen microfibril. Each microfibril is [[wikt:interdigitate|interdigitated]] with its neighboring microfibrils to a degree that might suggest they are individually unstable, although within collagen fibrils, they are so well ordered as to be crystalline.

[[File:Collagen biosynthesis (en).png|thumb|upright=1.3|Three [[polypeptide]]s coil to form tropocollagen. Many tropocollagens then bind together to form a fibril, and many of these then form a fibre.]]

A distinctive feature of collagen is the regular arrangement of [[amino acid]]s in each of the three chains of these collagen subunits. The sequence often follows the pattern [[glycine|Gly]]-[[proline|Pro]]-X or Gly-X-[[hydroxyproline|Hyp]], where X may be any of various other amino acid residues.&lt;ref name=&quot;SzpakJAS&quot;/&gt; Proline or hydroxyproline constitute about 1/6 of the total sequence. With glycine accounting for the 1/3 of the sequence, this means approximately half of the collagen sequence is not glycine, proline or hydroxyproline, a fact often missed due to the distraction of the unusual GX&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;X&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; character of collagen alpha-peptides. The high glycine content of collagen is important with respect to stabilization of the collagen helix as this allows the very close association of the collagen fibers within the molecule, facilitating hydrogen bonding and the formation of intermolecular cross-links.&lt;ref name=&quot;SzpakJAS&quot;/&gt; This kind of regular repetition and high glycine content is found in only a few other fibrous proteins, such as [[silk]] [[fibroin]].

Collagen is not only a structural protein. Due to its key role in the determination of cell phenotype, cell adhesion, tissue regulation, and infrastructure, many sections of its non-proline-rich regions have cell or matrix association/regulation roles. The relatively high content of proline and hydroxyproline rings, with their geometrically constrained [[carboxyl]] and (secondary) [[amino]] groups, along with the rich abundance of glycine, accounts for the tendency of the individual polypeptide strands to form left-handed helices spontaneously, without any intrachain hydrogen bonding.

Because glycine is the smallest amino acid with no side chain, it plays a unique role in fibrous structural proteins. In collagen, Gly is required at every third position because the assembly of the triple helix puts this residue at the interior (axis) of the helix, where there is no space for a larger side group than glycine’s single [[hydrogen|hydrogen atom]]. For the same reason, the rings of the Pro and Hyp must point outward. These two amino acids help stabilize the triple helix—Hyp even more so than Pro; a lower concentration of them is required in animals such as [[fish]], whose [[thermoregulation|body temperatures]] are lower than most warm-blooded animals. Lower proline and hydroxyproline contents are characteristic of cold-water, but not warm-water fish; the latter tend to have similar proline and hydroxyproline contents to mammals.&lt;ref name=&quot;SzpakJAS&quot;/&gt; The lower proline and hydroxproline contents of cold-water fish and other [[poikilothermic|poikilotherm]] animals leads to their collagen having a lower thermal stability than mammalian collagen.&lt;ref name=&quot;SzpakJAS&quot;/&gt; This lower thermal stability means that [[gelatin]] derived from fish collagen is not suitable for many food and industrial applications.

The tropocollagen [[protein subunit|subunits]] spontaneously [[molecular self-assembly|self-assemble]], with regularly staggered ends, into even larger arrays in the [[extracellular]] spaces of tissues.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Hulmes |first=D. J. |title=Building collagen molecules, fibrils, and suprafibrillar structures |journal=J Struct Biol |year=2002 |volume=137 |issue=1–2 |pmid=12064927 |pages=2–10 |doi=10.1006/jsbi.2002.4450 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hulmes, D.J. 1992. p. 49&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Hulmes |first=D. J. |title=The collagen superfamily—diverse structures and assemblies |journal=Essays Biochem |year=1992 |volume=27|pmid=1425603|pages=49–67}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additional assembly of fibrils is guided by fibroblasts, which deposit fully formed fibrils from fibripositors. In the fibrillar collagens, molecules are staggered to adjacent molecules by about 67&amp;nbsp;[[Nanometre|nm]] (a unit that is referred to as ‘D’ and changes depending upon the hydration state of the aggregate). In each D-period repeat of the microfibril, there is a part containing five molecules in cross-section, called the “overlap”, and a part containing only four molecules, called the &quot;gap&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Orgel&quot; /&gt; These overlap and gap regions are retained as microfibrils assemble into fibrils, and are thus viewable using electron microscopy. The triple helical tropocollagens in the microfibrils are arranged in a quasihexagonal packing pattern.&lt;ref name=&quot;Orgel&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hulmes Miller 1979&quot; /&gt;
[[File:Collagen fibrils in rabbit skin.jpg|thumb|upright|The D-period of collagen fibrils results in visible 67nm bands when observed by electron microscopy.]]
There is some [[covalent bond|covalent]] crosslinking within the triple helices, and a variable amount of covalent crosslinking between tropocollagen helices forming well organized aggregates (such as fibrils).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Perumal |first=S. |first2=O. |last2=Antipova |lastauthoramp=yes |first3=J. P. |last3=Orgel |title=Collagen fibril architecture, domain organization, and triple-helical conformation govern its proteolysis |journal=PNAS |year=2008 |volume=105 |pmid=18287018 |issue=8 |pmc=2268544 |pages=2824–2829 |doi=10.1073/pnas.0710588105 |bibcode = 2008PNAS..105.2824P }}&lt;/ref&gt; Larger fibrillar bundles are formed with the aid of several different classes of proteins (including different collagen types), glycoproteins, and proteoglycans to form the different types of mature tissues from alternate combinations of the same key players.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hulmes, D.J. 1992. p. 49&quot;/&gt; Collagen's [[soluble|insolubility]] was a barrier to the study of monomeric collagen until it was found that tropocollagen from young animals can be extracted because it is not yet fully [[cross-link|crosslinked]]. However, advances in microscopy techniques (i.e. electron microscopy (EM) and atomic force microscopy (AFM)) and X-ray diffraction have enabled researchers to obtain increasingly detailed images of collagen structure ''in situ''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Buchanan|first=Jenna K.|last2=Zhang|first2=Yi|last3=Holmes|first3=Geoff|last4=Covington|first4=Anthony D.|last5=Prabakar|first5=Sujay|date=2019|title=Role of X-ray Scattering Techniques in Understanding the Collagen Structure of Leather|url=https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/slct.201902908|journal=ChemistrySelect|language=en|volume=4|issue=48|pages=14091–14102|doi=10.1002/slct.201902908|issn=2365-6549}}&lt;/ref&gt; These later advances are particularly important to better understanding the way in which collagen structure affects cell–cell and cell–matrix communication and how tissues are constructed in growth and repair and changed in development and disease.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Sweeney |first=S. M. |first2=JP |last3=Fertala |first3=A |last4=McAuliffe |first4=JD |last5=Turner |first5=KR |last6=Di Lullo |first6=GA |last7=Chen |first7=S |last8=Antipova |first8=O |last9=Perumal |first9=S |title=Candidate Cell and Matrix Interaction Domains on the Collagen Fibril, the Predominant Protein of Vertebrates |last10=Ala-Kokko |first10=L. |last11=Forlino |first11=A. |last12=Cabral |first12=W. A. |last13=Barnes |first13=A. M. |last14=Marini |first14=J. C. |last15=Antonio |first15=J. D. S. |journal=J Biol Chem |year=2008 |volume=283 |pmid=18487200 |issue=30 |pmc=2475701 |pages=21187–21197 |doi=10.1074/jbc.M709319200 |displayauthors=2 |last2=Orgel }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Twardowski |first=T. |first2=A. |last3=Orgel |first3=J. P.R.O. |last4=San Antonio |first4=J. D. |title=Type I collagen and collagen mimetics as angiogenesis promoting superpolymers |journal=[[Current Pharmaceutical Design|Curr Pharm Des]] |year=2007 |volume=13 |issue=35 |pages=3608–3621 |doi=10.2174/138161207782794176 |pmid=18220798 |displayauthors=2 |last2=Fertala }}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, using AFM–based nanoindentation it has been shown that a single collagen fibril is a heterogeneous material along its axial direction with significantly different mechanical properties in its gap and overlap regions, correlating with its different molecular organizations in these two regions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|pmid=19694448|year=2009|last1=Minary-Jolandan|first1=M|last2=Yu|first2=MF|title=Nanomechanical heterogeneity in the gap and overlap regions of type I collagen fibrils with implications for bone heterogeneity|volume=10|issue=9|pages=2565–70|doi=10.1021/bm900519v|journal=Biomacromolecules}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Collagen fibrils/aggregates are arranged in different combinations and concentrations in various tissues to provide varying tissue properties. In bone, entire collagen triple helices lie in a parallel, staggered array. 40&amp;nbsp;nm gaps between the ends of the tropocollagen subunits (approximately equal to the gap region) probably serve as nucleation sites for the deposition of long, hard, fine crystals of the mineral component, which is hydroxylapatite (approximately) Ca&lt;sub&gt;10&lt;/sub&gt;(OH)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;(PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;ref&gt;Ross, M. H. and Pawlina, W. (2011) ''Histology'', 6th ed., Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins, p. 218.&lt;/ref&gt; Type I collagen gives bone its [[tensile strength]].

==Associated disorders==

Collagen-related diseases most commonly arise from genetic defects or nutritional deficiencies that affect the biosynthesis, assembly, postranslational modification, secretion, or other processes involved in normal collagen production.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
|+'''Genetic defects of collagen genes'''

| '''Type''' || '''Notes''' || '''Gene(s)''' || '''[[Collagen disease|Disorders]]'''
 |-
 | [[Type-I collagen|I]] || This is the most abundant collagen of the human body. It is present in [[Scar|scar tissue]], the end product when tissue [[healing|heals]] by repair. It is found in [[tendon]]s, skin, artery walls, cornea, the [[endomysium]] surrounding muscle fibers, fibrocartilage, and the organic part of bones and teeth. || [[COL1A1]], [[COL1A2]] || [[Osteogenesis imperfecta]], [[Ehlers–Danlos syndrome]], [[infantile cortical hyperostosis]] a.k.a. Caffey's disease
 |-
 | [[Type-II collagen|II]] || [[Hyaline cartilage]], makes up 50% of all cartilage protein. [[Vitreous humour]] of the eye. || [[COL2A1]] || [[Collagenopathy, types II and XI]]
 |-
 | [[Type-III collagen|III]] || This is the collagen of [[granulation tissue]] and is produced quickly by young fibroblasts before the tougher type I collagen is synthesized. [[Reticular fiber]]. Also found in artery walls, skin, intestines and the uterus || [[COL3A1]] || [[Ehlers–Danlos syndrome]], [[Dupuytren's contracture]]
 |-
 | [[Type-IV collagen|IV]] || [[Basal lamina]]; [[eye lens]]. Also serves as part of the filtration system in [[capillaries]] and the [[glomeruli]] of [[nephron]] in the [[kidney]]. || [[Collagen, type IV, alpha 1|COL4A1]], [[COL4A2]], [[COL4A3]], [[COL4A4]], [[COL4A5]], [[COL4A6]] || [[Alport syndrome]], [[Goodpasture's syndrome]]
 |-
 | V || Most interstitial tissue, assoc. with type I, associated with [[placenta]] || [[COL5A1]], [[COL5A2]], [[COL5A3]] || [[Ehlers–Danlos syndrome]] (classical)
 |-
 | VI || Most interstitial tissue, assoc. with type I || [[COL6A1]], [[COL6A2]], [[COL6A3]], [[COL6A5]] || [[Ulrich myopathy]], [[Bethlem myopathy]], [[atopic dermatitis]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Söderhäll |first=C. |last2=Marenholz |first2=I. |last3=Kerscher |first3=T. |last4=Rüschendorf |first4=F |last5=Rüschendorf |first5=F. |last6=Esparza-Gordillo |first6=J. |last7=Mayr |first7=G |last8=Albrecht |first8=M |title=Variants in a Novel Epidermal Collagen Gene (COL29A1) Are Associated with Atopic Dermatitis |journal=[[PLoS Biology]] |volume=5 |issue=9 |pages=e242 |year=2007 |pmid=17850181 |pmc=1971127 |doi=10.1371/journal.pbio.0050242 |displayauthors=7 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |-
 | VII || Forms [[anchoring fibril]]s in [[dermoepidermal junction]]s || [[COL7A1]] || [[Epidermolysis bullosa dystrophica]]
 |-
 | VIII || Some [[endothelium|endothelial]] cells || [[COL8A1]], [[COL8A2]] || [[Posterior polymorphous corneal dystrophy 2]]
 |-
 | IX || [[FACIT collagen]], cartilage, assoc. with type II and XI fibrils || [[COL9A1]], [[COL9A2]], [[COL9A3]] || [[EDM2]] and [[EDM3]]
 |-
 | X || [[Hypertrophic]] and [[Mineralization (biology)|mineralizing]] cartilage || [[COL10A1]] || [[Schmid metaphyseal dysplasia]]
 |-
 | XI || Cartilage || [[COL11A1]], [[COL11A2]] || [[Collagenopathy, types II and XI]]
 |-
 | XII || [[FACIT collagen]], interacts with type I containing fibrils, [[decorin]] and glycosaminoglycans || [[COL12A1]] || –
 |-
 | XIII || Transmembrane collagen, interacts with integrin a1b1, [[fibronectin]] and components of basement membranes like [[nidogen]] and [[perlecan]]. || [[COL13A1]] || –
 |-
 | XIV|| [[FACIT collagen]], also known as undulin || [[COL14A1]] || –
 |-
 | XV || – || [[COL15A1]] || –
 |-
 | XVI || – || [[COL16A1]] || –
 |-
 | [[Collagen XVII|XVII]] || Transmembrane collagen, also known as BP180, a 180 kDa protein || [[COL17A1]] || [[Bullous pemphigoid]] and certain forms of junctional [[epidermolysis bullosa]]
 |-
 | [[Type XVIII collagen|XVIII]] || Source of [[endostatin]] || [[COL18A1]] || –
 |-
 | XIX || [[FACIT collagen]] || [[COL19A1]] || –
 |-
 | XX || – || [[COL20A1]] || –
 |-
 | XXI || [[FACIT collagen]] || [[COL21A1]] || –
 |-
 | XXII || – || [[COL22A1]] || –
 |-
 | [[Collagen, type XXIII, alpha 1|XXIII]] || MACIT collagen || [[COL23A1]] || –
 |-
 | XXIV || – || [[COL24A1]] || –
 |-
 | XXV || – || [[COL25A1]] || –
 |-
 | XXVI || – || [[EMID2]] || –
 |-
 | XXVII || – || [[COL27A1]] || –
 |-
 | XXVIII || – || [[COL28A1]] || –
 |-
 | XXIX || Epidermal collagen || [[COL29A1]] || Atopic dermatitis&lt;ref name=&quot;col29&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.news-medical.net/health/Collagen-Types-and-Linked-Disorders.aspx |title=Collagen Types and Linked Disorders |date=2011-01-18 |work=News-Medical.net |access-date=2017-11-19 |language=en |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20171201030322/https://www.news-medical.net/health/Collagen-Types-and-Linked-Disorders.aspx |archivedate=2017-12-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

In addition to the above-mentioned disorders, excessive deposition of collagen occurs in [[scleroderma]].

==Diseases==
One thousand mutations have been identified in 12 out of more than 20 types of collagen. These mutations can lead to various diseases at the tissue level.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mahajan, VB 2010&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors = Mahajan VB, Olney AH, Garrett P, Chary A, Dragan E, Lerner G, Murray J, Bassuk AG  |pmid = 20799329|year = 2010|title = Collagen XVIII mutation in Knobloch syndrome with acute lymphoblastic leukemia|volume = 152A|issue = 11|pages = 2875–9|doi = 10.1002/ajmg.a.33621|pmc = 2965270|journal = American Journal of Medical Genetics Part A}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Osteogenesis imperfecta]] – Caused by a mutation in '''type 1 collagen''', dominant autosomal disorder, results in weak bones and irregular connective tissue, some cases can be mild while others can be lethal. Mild cases have lowered levels of collagen type 1 while severe cases have structural defects in collagen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Gajko-Galicka, A|pmid=12362985|url=http://www.actabp.pl/pdf/2_2002/433-441.pdf|year=2002|title=Mutations in type I collagen genes resulting in osteogenesis imperfecta in humans|volume=49|issue=2|pages=433–41|journal=Acta Biochimica Polonica|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130607085009/http://www.actabp.pl/pdf/2_2002/433-441.pdf|archivedate=2013-06-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Chondrodysplasia]]s – Skeletal disorder believed to be caused by a mutation in '''type 2 collagen''', further research is being conducted to confirm this.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid2624272&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors  = Horton WA, Campbell D, Machado MA, Chou J |title = Type II collagen screening in the human chondrodysplasias |journal = Am. J. Med. Genet. |volume = 34 |issue = 4 |pages = 579–83 |year = 1989 |pmid = 2624272 |doi = 10.1002/ajmg.1320340425}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ehlers-Danlos syndrome]] – Thirteen different types of this disorder, which lead to deformities in connective tissue, are known&lt;ref&gt;Malfait F, Francomano C, Byers P, Belmont J, Berglund B, Black J, Bloom L, Bowen JM, Brady AF, Burrows NP, Castori M, Cohen H, Colombi M, Demirdas S, De Backer J, De Paepe A, Fournel-Gigleux S, Frank M, Ghali N, Giunta C, Grahame R, Hakim A, Jeunemaitre X, Johnson D, Juul-Kristensen B, Kapferer-Seebacher I, Kazkaz H, Kosho T, Lavallee ME, Levy H, Mendoza-Londono R, Pepin M, Pope FM, Reinstein E, Robert L, Rohrbach M, Sanders L, Sobey GJ, Van Damme T, Vandersteen A, van Mourik C, Voermans N, Wheeldon N, Zschocke J, Tinkle B. 2017. The 2017 international classification of the Ehlers–Danlos syndromes. Am J Med Genet Part C Semin Med Genet 175C:8–26.&lt;/ref&gt;. Some of the rarer types can be lethal, leading to the rupture of arteries. Each syndrome is caused by a different mutation. For example, the vascular type (vEDS) of this disorder is caused by a mutation in '''collagen type 3'''.&lt;ref name=Hamel&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors = Hamel BC, Pals G, Engels CH, van den Akker E, Boers GH, van Dongen PW, Steijlen PM |title = Ehlers-Danlos syndrome and type III collagen abnormalities: a variable clinical spectrum |journal = Clin. Genet. |volume = 53 |issue = 6 |pages = 440–6 |year = 1998 |pmid = 9712532 |doi = 10.1111/j.1399-0004.1998.tb02592.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Alport syndrome]] – Can be passed on genetically, usually as X-linked dominant, but also as both an autosomal dominant and autosomal recessive disorder, sufferers have problems with their kidneys and eyes, loss of hearing can also develop during the childhood or adolescent years.&lt;ref&gt;Kashtan, CE (1993) &quot;Collagen IV-Related Nephropathies ([https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK1207/ Alport Syndrome and Thin Basement Membrane Nephropathy] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171225220919/https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK1207/ |date=2017-12-25 }})&quot;, in RA Pagon, TD Bird, CR Dolan, K Stephens &amp; MP Adam (eds), GeneReviews, University of Washington, Seattle, Seattle WA {{PMID|20301386}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Knobloch syndrome]] – Caused by a mutation in the [[COL18A1]] gene that codes for the production of collagen XVIII. Patients present with protrusion of the brain tissue and degeneration of the retina; an individual who has family members suffering from the disorder is at an increased risk of developing it themselves since there is a hereditary link.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mahajan, VB 2010&quot;/&gt;

==Characteristics==
Collagen is one of the long, [[fibrous protein|fibrous structural proteins]] whose functions are quite different from those of [[globular protein]]s, such as [[enzyme]]s. Tough bundles of collagen called ''collagen fibers'' are a major component of the [[extracellular matrix]] that supports most tissues and gives cells structure from the outside, but collagen is also found inside certain cells. Collagen has great [[tensile strength]], and is the main component of [[fascia]], [[cartilage]], [[ligament]]s, [[tendon]]s, [[bone]] and skin.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Fratzl |first=P. |title=Collagen: Structure and Mechanics |publisher=Springer |location=New York |year=2008 |isbn=978-0-387-73905-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Buehler |first=M. J. |title=Nature designs tough collagen: Explaining the nanostructure of collagen fibrils |journal=PNAS |year=2006 |volume=103 |pmid=16895989 |issue=33 |pages=12285–12290 |pmc=1567872 |doi=10.1073/pnas.0603216103 |bibcode = 2006PNAS..10312285B }}&lt;/ref&gt; Along with [[elastin]] and soft [[keratin]], it is responsible for [[human skin|skin]] strength and elasticity, and its degradation leads to [[wrinkle]]s that accompany [[aging]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pharmax2&quot; /&gt; It strengthens [[blood vessel]]s and plays a role in [[biological tissue|tissue]] development. It is present in the [[cornea]] and lens of the [[human eye|eye]] in [[crystal]]line form. It may be one of the most abundant proteins in the fossil record, given that it appears to fossilize frequently, even in bones from the [[Mesozoic]] and [[Paleozoic]].&lt;ref name=ZL11&gt;{{cite journal| last1=Zylberberg |first1=L. | last2=Laurin|first2=M.|year=2011 |title=Analysis of fossil bone organic matrix by transmission electron microscopy |journal=Comptes Rendus Palevol |volume=11 |issue=5–6 |pages=357–366 | doi = 10.1016/j.crpv.2011.04.004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Uses===
Collagen has a wide variety of applications, from food to medical. For instance, it is used in [[plastic surgery|cosmetic surgery]] and [[burn (injury)|burn surgery]]. It is widely used in the form of collagen [[casing (sausage)|casings]] for sausages, which are also used in the manufacture of [[Strings (music)#Gut|musical strings]].

If collagen is subject to sufficient [[denaturation (biochemistry)|denaturation]], e.g. by heating, the three tropocollagen strands separate partially or completely into globular domains, containing a different secondary structure to the normal collagen polyproline II (PPII), e.g. [[random coil]]s. This process describes the formation of [[gelatin]], which is used in many [[food]]s, including flavored [[gelatin dessert]]s. Besides food, gelatin has been used in pharmaceutical, cosmetic, and photography industries. It is also used as a [[dietary supplement]].

From the Greek for glue, ''kolla'', the word collagen means &quot;[[animal glue|glue]] producer&quot; and refers to the early process of boiling the skin and [[tendon|sinews]] of [[horse]]s and other animals to obtain glue. Collagen adhesive was used by [[Egypt]]ians about 4,000 years ago, and [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]] used it in [[bow (weapon)|bows]] about 1,500 years ago. The oldest glue in the world, [[radiocarbon dating|carbon-dated]] as more than 8,000 years old, was found to be collagen—used as a protective lining on rope baskets and [[embroidery|embroidered]] [[Textile|fabric]]s, and to hold [[list of eating utensils|utensils]] together; also in crisscross decorations on [[human skull]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.archaeology.org/online/news/glue.html |title=Oldest Glue Discovered |work=Archaeology |date=May 21, 1998 |first=Amélie A. |last=Walker |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20051217224604/http://www.archaeology.org/online/news/glue.html |archivedate=December 17, 2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Collagen normally converts to gelatin, but survived due to dry conditions. Animal glues are [[thermoplastic]], softening again upon reheating, so they are still used in making [[musical instrument]]s such as fine [[violin]]s and [[guitar]]s, which may have to be reopened for repairs—an application incompatible with tough, [[chemical synthesis|synthetic]] [[plastic]] adhesives, which are permanent. Animal sinews and skins, including [[leather]], have been used to make useful articles for millennia.

Gelatin-[[resorcinol]]-[[formaldehyde]] glue (and with formaldehyde replaced by less-toxic pentanedial and [[glyoxal|ethanedial]]) has been used to repair experimental incisions in [[rabbit]] [[lung]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Ennker |first=I. C. |first2=JüRgen |last3=Schoon |first3=Doris |last4=Schoon |first4=Heinz Adolf |last5=Rimpler |first5=Manfred |last6=Hetzer |first6=Roland |title=Formaldehyde-free collagen glue in experimental lung gluing |journal=[[Annals of Thoracic Surgery|Ann. Thorac. Surg.]] |year=1994 |volume=57 |issue=6 |pages=1622–1627 |doi=10.1016/0003-4975(94)90136-8 |url=http://ats.ctsnetjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/57/6/1622 |pmid=8010812 |displayauthors=2 |last2=Ennker |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://archive.today/20120708223544/http://ats.ctsnetjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/57/6/1622 |archivedate=2012-07-08 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
The molecular and packing structures of collagen have eluded scientists over decades of research. The first evidence that it possesses a regular structure at the molecular level was presented in the mid-1930s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Wyckoff |first=R. |first2=R. |last2=Corey |lastauthoramp=yes |first3=J. |last3=Biscoe |title=X-ray reflections of long spacing from tendon |journal=[[Science (journal)|Science]] |year=1935 |volume=82 |pmid=17810172 |issue=2121 |pages=175–176 |doi=10.1126/science.82.2121.175 |bibcode = 1935Sci....82..175W }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Clark |first=G. |last2=Parker |first2=E. |last3=Schaad |first3=J. |lastauthoramp=yes |last4=Warren |first4=W. J. |title=New measurements of previously unknown large interplanar spacings in natural materials |journal=[[Journal of the American Chemical Society|J. Am. Chem. Soc.]] |year=1935 |volume=57 |issue=8 |page=1509 |doi=10.1021/ja01311a504 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Since that time, many prominent scholars, including Nobel laureates [[Francis Crick|Crick]], [[Linus Pauling|Pauling]], [[Alexander Rich|Rich]] and [[Ada Yonath|Yonath]], and others, including [[Barbara Brodsky|Brodsky]], [[Helen M. Berman|Berman]], and [[Gopalasamudram Narayana Iyer Ramachandran|Ramachandran]], concentrated on the conformation of the collagen [[monomer]]. Several competing models, although correctly dealing with the conformation of each individual peptide chain, gave way to the triple-helical &quot;Madras&quot; model of Ramachandran, which provided an essentially correct model of the molecule's [[quaternary structure]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal=Resonance |volume=6 |issue=10 |url=http://www.ias.ac.in/resonance/php/toc.php?vol=06&amp;issue=10 |title=GNR — A Tribute |author=Balasubramanian, D . |date=October 2001 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140110164101/http://www.ias.ac.in/resonance/php/toc.php?vol=06&amp;issue=10 |archivedate=2014-01-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Leonidas |first=Demetres D. |year=2001 |first2=GB |last3=Jardine |first3=AM |last4=Li |first4=S |last5=Shapiro |first5=R |last6=Acharya |first6=KR |title=Binding of Phosphate and pyrophosphate ions at the active site of human angiogenin as revealed by X-ray crystallography |journal=Protein Science |pmid=11468363 |volume=10 |issue=8 |pmc=2374093 |pages=1669–1676 |doi=10.1110/ps.13601 |displayauthors=2 |last2=Chavali }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Subramanian |first=Easwara |year=2001 |title=Obituary: G.N. Ramachandran |journal=[[Nature Structural &amp; Molecular Biology]] |pmid=11373614 |volume=8 |issue=6 |pages=489–491 |doi=10.1038/88544 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This model was supported by further studies, that produced higher resolution data.&lt;ref name=&quot;Saad 1994&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Fraser |first=R. D. |first2=T. P. |last2=MacRae |lastauthoramp=yes |first3=E. |last3=Suzuki |title=Chain conformation in the collagen molecule |journal=[[Journal of Molecular Biology|J Mol Biol]] |year=1979 |volume=129 |issue=3 |pages=463–481 |doi=10.1016/0022-2836(79)90507-2 |pmid=458854}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Okuyama |first=K. |first2=K |last3=Arnott |first3=S |last4=Takayanagi |first4=M |last5=Kakudo |first5=M |title=Crystal and molecular structure of a collagen-like polypeptide (Pro-Pro-Gly)&lt;sub&gt;10&lt;/sub&gt; |journal=J Mol Biol |volume=152 |issue=2 |pages=427–443 |year=1981 |pmid=7328660 |doi=10.1016/0022-2836(81)90252-7 |displayauthors=2 |last2=Okuyama }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Traub |first=W. |first2=A. |last2=Yonath |lastauthoramp=yes |first3=D. M. |last3=Segal |title=On the molecular structure of collagen |journal=[[Nature (journal)|Nature]] |year=1969 |volume=221 |issue=5184 |pages=914–917 |doi=10.1038/221914a0 |pmid=5765503 |bibcode = 1969Natur.221..914T }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Bella |first=J. |first2=M. |last2=Eaton |first3=B. |last3=Brodsky |first4=H. M. |last4=Berman |title=Crystal and molecular structure of a collagen-like peptide at 1.9 A resolution |journal=Science |year=1994 |volume=266 |issue=5182 |pmid=7695699 |pages=75–81 |doi=10.1126/science.7695699 |bibcode = 1994Sci...266...75B }}&lt;/ref&gt; The packing structure of collagen has not been defined to the same degree outside of the [[fibrillar]] collagen types, although it has been long known to be hexagonal or quasi-hexagonal.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hulmes Miller 1979&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Hulmes |first=D. J. |lastauthoramp=yes |first2=A. |last2=Miller |title=Quasi-hexagonal molecular packing in collagen fibrils |journal=Nature |year=1979 |volume=282 |pmid=514368 |issue=5741 |pages=878–880 |doi=10.1038/282878a0 |bibcode = 1979Natur.282..878H }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Jesior |first=J. C. |first2=A. |last2=Miller |lastauthoramp=yes |first3=C. |last3=Berthet-Colominas |title=Crystalline three-dimensional packing is general characteristic of type I collagen fibrils |journal=FEBS Lett |year=1980 |volume=113 |pmid=7389896 |issue=2 |pages=238–240 |doi=10.1016/0014-5793(80)80600-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Fraser |first=R. D. B. |lastauthoramp=yes |first2=T. P. |last2=MacRae |title=Unit cell and molecular connectivity in tendon collagen |journal=[[International Journal of Biological Macromolecules|Int. J. Biol. Macromol.]] |year=1981 |volume=3 |issue=3 |pages=193–200 |doi=10.1016/0141-8130(81)90063-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt; As with its monomeric structure, several conflicting models alleged that either the packing arrangement of collagen molecules is 'sheet-like' or [[microfibril]]lar.&lt;ref name=&quot;Saad 1994&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Saad|first1=Mohamed|title=Low resolution structure and packing investigations of collagen crystalline domains in tendon using Synchrotron Radiation X-rays, Structure factors determination, evaluation of Isomorphous Replacement methods and other modeling.|date=Oct 1994|publisher=PhD Thesis, Université Joseph Fourier Grenoble I|pages=1–221|url=https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B3L_EN9hIuFTTkhuN2lrWEU4RDQ&amp;authuser=0 |doi= 10.13140/2.1.4776.7844}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Fraser |first=R. D. |first2=T. P. |last2=MacRae |first3=A. |last3=Miller |title=Molecular packing in type I collagen fibrils |journal=J Mol Biol |year=1987 |volume=193 |pmid=3586015 |issue=1 |pages=115–125 |doi=10.1016/0022-2836(87)90631-0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Wess |first=T. J. |first2=AP |last3=Wess |first3=L |last4=Miller |first4=A |title=Molecular packing of type I collagen in tendon |journal=J Mol Biol |year=1998 |volume=275 |issue=2 |pmid=9466908 |pages=255–267 |doi=10.1006/jmbi.1997.1449 |displayauthors=2 |last2=Hammersley }}&lt;/ref&gt; The microfibrillar structure of collagen fibrils in tendon, cornea and cartilage has been directly imaged by electron microscopy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Raspanti |first=M. |last2=Ottani |first2=V. |last3=Ruggeri |first3=A. |title=Subfibrillar architecture and functional properties of collagen: a comparative study in rat tendons |journal=[[Journal of Anatomy|J. Anat.]] |year=1990 |volume=172|pages=157–164 |pmc=1257211 |pmid=2272900}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Holmes |first=D. F. |last2=Gilpin |first2=C. J. |last3=Baldock |first3=C. |last4=Ziese |first4=U. |last5=Koster |first5=A. J. |last6=Kadler |first6=K. E. |title=Corneal collagen fibril structure in three dimensions: Structural insights into fibril assembly, mechanical properties, and tissue organization |journal=[[Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences|PNAS]] |year=2001 |volume=98 |pmid=11390960 |issue=13 |pages=7307–7312 |pmc=34664 |doi=10.1073/pnas.111150598 |bibcode = 2001PNAS...98.7307H }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Holmes |first=D. F. |last2=Kadler |first2=KE |title=The 10+4 microfibril structure of thin cartilage fibrils |journal=PNAS |year=2006 |volume=103 |pmid=17088555 |issue=46 |pages=17249–17254 |pmc=1859918 |doi=10.1073/pnas.0608417103 |bibcode = 2006PNAS..10317249H }}&lt;/ref&gt; The microfibrillar structure of tail tendon, as described by Fraser, Miller, and Wess (amongst others), was modeled as being closest to the observed structure,&lt;ref name=&quot;Saad 1994&quot; /&gt; although it oversimplified the topological progression of neighboring collagen molecules, and hence did not predict the correct conformation of the discontinuous D-periodic pentameric arrangement termed simply: the microfibril.&lt;ref name=Orgel&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Orgel |first=J. P. |first2=TC |last3=Miller |first3=A |last4=Wess |first4=TJ |title=Microfibrillar structure of type I collagen in situ |journal=PNAS |year=2006 |volume=103 |issue=24 |pmid=16751282 |pmc=1473175 |pages=9001–9005 |doi=10.1073/pnas.0502718103 |bibcode = 2006PNAS..103.9001O |displayauthors=2 |last2=Irving }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Okuyama&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Okuyama |first=K |last2=Bächinger |first2=HP |last3=Mizuno |first3=K |last4=Boudko |first4=SP |last5=Engel |first5=J|last6=Berisio |first6=R|last7=Vitagliano |first7=L |title=Comment on Microfibrillar structure of type I collagen in situ by Orgel et al. (2006), Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA, 103, 9001–9005 |journal=Acta Crystallographica Section D |year=2009 |volume=65 |issue=Pt9 |pmid=19690380 |pages=1009–10 |doi=10.1107/S0907444909023051}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Orgel|first1=Joseph|title=On the packing structure of collagen: response to Okuyama et al.'s comment on Microfibrillar structure of type I collagen in situ|journal=Acta Crystallographica Section D|volume=D65|issue=9|page=1009&lt;!--|pages=1010--&gt;|doi=10.1107/S0907444909028741|year=2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Various [[Cross-linking agent|cross linking agents]] like [[L-Dopaquinone]], embeline, potassium embelate and 5-O-methyl embelin could be developed as potential
cross-linking/stabilization agents of collagen preparation and its application as wound dressing sheet in clinical applications is enhanced.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Narayanaswamy |first=Radhakrishnan |last2=Shanmugasamy |first2=Sangeetha |title= Bioinformatics in crosslinking chemistry of collagen with selective crosslinkers|journal=BMC Research Notes |year=2011 |volume=4| page=399 |doi=10.1186/1756-0500-4-399 |pmid=21989371 |pmc=3213054 |last3=Shanmugasamy |first3=Sangeetha |last4=Gopal |first4=Ramesh |last5=Mandal |first5=Asit}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The evolution of collagens was a fundamental step in the early [[evolution of animals]], supporting multicellular animal forms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|pmid=12382326|year=2002|last1=Exposito|first1=J. Y.|title=Evolution of collagens|journal=The Anatomical Record|volume=268|issue=3|pages=302–16|last2=Cluzel|first2=C|last3=Garrone|first3=R|last4=Lethias|first4=C|doi=10.1002/ar.10162|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==D-banding==

Collagen D-banding is viable as periodic formation of ridging on all [[fibril]]s forming collagen.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Ortolani|first=F.|last2=Giordano|first2=M.|last3=Marchini|first3=M.|date=2000-11-01|title=A model for type II collagen fibrils: distinctive D-band patterns in native and reconstituted fibrils compared with sequence data for helix and telopeptide domains|pmid=10951330|journal=Biopolymers|volume=54|issue=6|pages=448–463|doi=10.1002/1097-0282(200011)54:6&lt;448::AID-BIP80&gt;3.0.CO;2-Q|issn=0006-3525}}&lt;/ref&gt;  D-bands are created due to the semi-crystalline formation of the collagen within the fibrils.  The pattern exhibited by D-banding is consistently independent of fibril diameter.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Bozec|first=Laurent|date=January 2007|title=Collagen Fibrils: Nanoscale Ropes|journal=Biophysical Journal|volume=92|issue=1|pages=70–75|doi=10.1529/biophysj.106.085704|pmid=17028135|pmc=1697848|bibcode=2007BpJ....92...70B}}&lt;/ref&gt;  When undergoing deformation, collagen fibrils may lose their D-banding, making the disappearance of the d-bands an indicator of the type of damage undergone by then [[tendon]] fibrils.

==See also==
{{col div|colwidth=30em}}
* [[Animal glue]]
* [[Braising]]
* [[Collagen hybridizing peptide]], a peptide that can bind to denatured collagen
* [[Collagenase]], the enzyme involved in collagen breakdown and remodeling
* [[Fibrous protein]]
* [[Gelatin]]
* [[Hydrolyzed collagen]], a common form in which collagen is sold as a supplement
* [[Hypermobility syndrome]]
* [[Lysyl oxidase]]
* [[MMP inhibitors]]
* [[Osteoid]], collagen-containing component of bone
{{colend}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Commons}}
{{Connective tissue}}

{{Fibrous proteins}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Collagens|*]]
[[Category:Structural proteins]]
[[Category:Edible thickening agents]]
[[Category:Aging-related proteins]]</text>
      <sha1>l7mk56ltqdqrrjw8vj6oys14rkw8qun</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
