  <page>
    <title>Celibacy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6035</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942052838</id>
      <parentid>939188494</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-22T08:24:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dawnseeker2000</username>
        <id>1544984</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>link maintenance, refine ref details</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About-distinguish|religious sexual abstinence|Asexuality}}
{{Redirect|Sworn virgins|the Balkan gender category|Albanian sworn virgins}}
{{original research |date=May 2019}}

{{short description|State of voluntary sexual abstinence}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2020}}
[[File:KateriTekakwitha.jpg|thumb|Saint [[Kateri Tekakwitha]], a [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] [[laywoman]] who took a private vow of perpetual virginity]]
'''Celibacy''' (from [[Latin]], ''cælibatus&quot;'') is the state of voluntarily being unmarried, [[Sexual abstinence|sexually abstinent]],&lt;!--NOTE: Sources differ on the and/or matter -- whether celibacy is both unmarried and sexually abstinent, or one or the other; this line follows the sources with WP:Due weight, and the WP:ANDOR guideline. --&gt; or both, usually for religious reasons. Mostly used in terms of abstaining from sexual relations.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Brien&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=Jodi|last= O'Brien| title = Encyclopedia of Gender and Society, Volume 1| publisher =[[Sage Publications|SAGE]]|year = 2009|pages=118–119| isbn = 978-1412909167 |url =https://books.google.com/books?id=_nyHS4WyUKEC&amp;pg=PT150}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Celibate&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Celibate|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|accessdate=11 January 2014|url=http://www.oxforddictionaries.com/us/definition/american_english/celibate}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Celibacy&quot;&gt;{{cite dictionary|title=Celibacy|dictionary=[[The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language]]|accessdate=11 January 2014|url=http://www.ahdictionary.com/word/search.html?q=Celibacy}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Celibacy2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Celibacy|publisher=[[Reference.com]]|accessdate=11 January 2014|url=http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/celibacy}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is often in association with the role of a religious official or devotee.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Brien&quot;/&gt; In its narrow sense, the term ''celibacy'' is applied only to those for whom the unmarried state is the result of a sacred [[vow]], act of renunciation, or religious conviction.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Brien&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Garner2009&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Bryan Garner|title=Garner's Modern American Usage|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=FwmQpyibKkAC&amp;pg=PA145|date=28 July 2009|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-988877-1|page=145}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a wider sense, it is commonly understood to only mean abstinence from [[Human sexual activity|sexual activity]].&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Brien&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Garner2009&quot;/&gt;

Celibacy has existed in one form or another throughout history, in virtually all the major religions of the world, and views on it have varied. [[Judaism]] strongly opposes celibacy.&lt;ref&gt;''Berachot'' 10a; ''Kiddushin'' 29b; Maimonides, ''Ishut'' 15:2; ''Shulchan Aruch, Even Hae'ezer'' 1:3&lt;/ref&gt; However, the priests of the Essenes, a Jewish sect during the Second Temple period, practised celibacy. The [[Ancient Rome|Romans]] viewed celibacy as an aberration and legislated fiscal penalties against it, with the sole exception granted to the [[Vestal Virgins]]. The [[Islamic]] attitudes toward celibacy have been complex as well. Several Hadiths indicate that Prophet Muhammad denounced celibacy, but some [[Sufi]] orders embrace it.

Classical [[Hindu]] culture encouraged asceticism and celibacy in the later stages of life, after one has met his societal obligations. [[Jainism]], on the other hand, preached complete celibacy even for young monks and considered celibacy to be an essential behavior to attain [[Moksha (Jainism)|moksha]]. [[Buddhism]] is similar to Jainism in this respect. There were, however, significant cultural differences in the various areas where Buddhism spread, which affected the local attitudes toward celibacy. It was not well received in China, for example, where other religions movements such as [[Daoism]] were opposed to it.{{Citation needed|date=October 2016}} A somewhat similar situation existed in Japan, where the [[Shinto]] tradition also opposed celibacy. In most native African and American Indian religious traditions, celibacy has been viewed negatively as well, although there were exceptions like periodic celibacy practiced by some Mesoamerican warriors.&lt;ref name=&quot;Olson2007&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Carl Olson|title=Celibacy and Religious Traditions|year=2007|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-804181-8|pages=10–19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology==
The English word ''celibacy'' derives from the Latin ''caelibatus'', &quot;state of being unmarried&quot;, from Latin {{lang|la|caelebs}}, meaning &quot;unmarried&quot;. This word derives from two [[Proto-Indo-European language|Proto-Indo-European]] stems, *{{PIE|kaiwelo-}} &quot;alone&quot; and *{{PIE|lib(h)s-}} &quot;living&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Online Etymology Dictionary, [http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=celibacy Celibacy]. Retrieved 11 August 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Abstinence and celibacy==
The words ''abstinence'' and ''celibacy'' are often used interchangeably, but are not necessarily the same thing. [[Sexual abstinence]], also known as ''continence'',&lt;ref&gt;{{CathEncy |id= 04330b |title= Continence |first= John |last= Melody |accessdate= 23 July 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; is abstaining from some or all aspects of sexual activity, often for some limited period of time,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|chapter=Abstinence and Continence|title=Dictionary of Moral Theology|editor1-last=Palazzini|editor1-first=Pietro|location=London|publisher=Burns &amp; Oates|year=1962}}&lt;/ref&gt; while celibacy may be defined as a voluntary religious vow not to marry or engage in sexual activity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schadé2006&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Johannes P. Schadé|title=Encyclopedia of World Religions|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=XRkfKdho-5cC&amp;pg=PT180|year=2006|publisher=Foreign Media Group|isbn=978-1-60136-000-7|page=180}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ea-bAAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA359|title=Britannica Concise Encyclopedia|page=359|quote=The deliberate abstinence from sexual activity, usually in connection with a religious role or practice. |accessdate=2016-10-12|isbn=9781593394929|date=May 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://kids.britannica.com/comptons/article-9319093/celibacy |title=celibacy |encyclopedia=Britannica Kids|accessdate=2016-10-12|quote=A voluntary refusal to marry or engage in sexual intercourse, celibacy is often associated with taking religious vows. The three types of religious celibacy are sacerdotal, monastic, and institutional.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thefreedictionary.com/celibacy |title=The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language, Fifth Edition, 2011|publisher=thefreedictionary.com|accessdate=2016-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Asexuality]] is commonly conflated with celibacy and sexual abstinence, but it is considered distinct from the two,&lt;ref name=&quot;Halter&quot;&gt;{{cite book|authors=Margaret Jordan Halter, Elizabeth M. Varcarolis|title=Varcarolis' Foundations of Psychiatric Mental Health Nursing|isbn=978-1455753581|publisher=[[Elsevier Health Sciences]]|year=2013|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=mZ15AAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA382}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DePaulo&quot;&gt;{{cite magazine|first=Bella|last=DePaulo|title=ASEXUALS: Who Are They and Why Are They Important?:&lt;!--not sure if colon (rather than spaced ndash (snd-template) &quot; – &quot;) is better for subtitle or here, use (because ending in &quot;?&quot;) quote= --&gt;We have so much more to learn about asexuality. |magazine=[[Psychology Today]]|date=&lt;!--where did that date come from? &quot;Posted&quot;: --&gt;23 December 2009 |accessdate=2016-10-12 |url=http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/living-single/200912/asexuals-who-are-they-and-why-are-they-important}}&lt;/ref&gt; as celibacy and sexual abstinence are behavioral and those who use those terms for themselves are generally motivated by factors such as an individual's personal or religious beliefs.&lt;ref&gt;''The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language'' (3d ed. 1992), entries for ''celibacy'' and thence ''abstinence''&lt;/ref&gt;

A. W. Richard Sipe, while focusing on the topic of celibacy in Catholicism, states that &quot;the most commonly assumed definition of ''celibate'' is simply an unmarried or single person, and celibacy is perceived as synonymous with sexual abstinence or restraint.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sipe1990&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=A.W. Richard Sipe|title=A Secret World: Sexuality and the Search For Celibacy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DxqLZI2Lpp4C&amp;pg=PA3|year=1990|publisher=Routledge|isbn=1-134-85134-0|page=3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sipe adds that even in the relatively uniform milieu of Catholic priests in the United States &quot;there is simply no clear [[operational definition]] of celibacy&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sipe1990b&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=A.W. Richard Sipe|title=A Secret World: Sexuality and the Search For Celibacy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DxqLZI2Lpp4C&amp;pg=PA52|year=1990|publisher=Routledge|isbn=1-134-85134-0|page=52}}&lt;/ref&gt; Elizabeth Abbott commented on the terminology in her ''A History of Celibacy'' (2001): &quot;I also drafted a definition that discarded the rigidly pedantic and unhelpful distinctions between celibacy, chastity and virginity&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Abbott|first=Elizabeth|title=A History of Celibacy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=D1_SNxYovocC&amp;pg=PA17|year=2001|publisher=Da Capo Press|isbn=9780306810411|pages=16–17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The concept of &quot;new celibacy&quot; was introduced by Gabrielle Brown in her 1980 book ''The New Celibacy''.&lt;ref name=&quot;frayser&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Frayser|first1=Suzanne G.|last2=Whitby|first2=Thomas J.|title=Studies in Human Sexuality: A Selected Guide|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZArPH0nFGo0C&amp;pg=PA341|year=1995|publisher=Libraries Unlimited|isbn=9781563081316|page=341}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a revised version (1989) of her book, she claims that &quot;abstinence is a response on the outside to what's going on, and celibacy is a response from the inside&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Brown|first=Gabrielle|title=The New Celibacy: A Journey to Love, Intimacy, and Good Health in a New Age|edition=Rev|location=New York|publisher=McGraw-Hill|year=1989}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to her definition, celibacy (even short-term celibacy that is pursued for non-religious reasons) is much more than not having sex. It is more intentional than abstinence, and its goal is personal growth and empowerment. This new perspective on celibacy is echoed by several authors including Elizabeth Abbott, Wendy Keller, and [[Wendy Shalit]].&lt;ref&gt;Abbott, Elizabeth. ''A History of Celibacy''. Cambridge, Massachusetts: DaCapo, 1999; Keller, Wendy. ''The Cult of the Born-Again Virgin: How Single Women Can Reclaim Their Sexual Power''. Deerfield Beach, Florida: Health Communications, 1999; Shalit, Wendy. ''A Return to Modesty: Discovering the Lost Virtue''. New York: Touchstone, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Buddhism==
[[File:Monks in Wat Phra Singh - Chiang Mai.jpg|thumb|Buddhist monks in Chiang Mai Province, [[Thailand]] ]]
{{main|Brahmacarya}}
The rule of celibacy in the Buddhist religion, whether [[Mahayana]] or [[Theravada]], has a long history. Celibacy was advocated as an ideal rule of life for all [[Bhikkhu|monk]]s and [[Bhikkhuni|nun]]s by [[Gautama Buddha]], except for Japan where it is not strictly followed due to historical and political developments following the [[Meiji Restoration]]. In Japan, celibacy was an ideal among Buddhist clerics for hundreds of years. But violations of clerical celibacy were so common for so long that, finally, in 1872, state laws made marriage legal for Buddhist clerics. Subsequently, ninety percent of Buddhist monks/clerics married.&lt;ref&gt;Richard M. 2001. Neither Monk nor Layman: Clerical Marriage in Modern Japanese Buddhism. New Jersey: Princeton University Press, p. 4&lt;/ref&gt; An example is [[Higashifushimi Kunihide]], a prominent Buddhist priest of Japanese royal ancestry who was married and a father whilst serving as a monk for most of his lifetime.

Gautama, later known as the Buddha, is known for his renunciation of his wife, Princess [[Yasodharā]], and son, [[Rahula]]. In order to pursue an ascetic life, he needed to renounce aspects of the impermanent world, including his wife and son. Later on both his wife and son joined the ascetic community and are mentioned in the Buddhist texts to have become enlightened. In another sense, a [[buddhavacana]] recorded the zen patriarch [[Vimalakirti]] as being an advocate of [[Sexual abstinence|marital continence]] instead of monastic renunciation, the sutra became somewhat popular due to its brash humour as well as integrating the role of women in laity as well as spiritual life.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Thurman|first1=Robert A. F.|title=VIMALAKIRTI NIRDESA SUTRA|url=http://www2.kenyon.edu/Depts/Religion/Fac/Adler/Reln260/Vimalakirti.htm|accessdate=14 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Brahma Kumaris==
In the religious movement of [[Brahma Kumaris]], celibacy is also promoted for peace and to defeat power of [[lust]] and to prepare for life in forthcoming Heaven on earth for 2,500 years when children will be created by the power of the mind even for householders to like holy brother and sister.&lt;ref&gt;Babb, Lawrence A. (1987). Redemptive Encounters: Three Modern Styles in the Hindu Tradition (Comparative Studies in Religion and Society). Oxford University Press. {{ISBN|0-7069-2563-7}}. &quot;Sexual intercourse is unnecessary for reproduction because the souls that enter the world during the first half of the Cycle are in possession of a special yogic power (yog bal) by which they conceive children&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Barrett, David V (2001). The New Believers. Cassell &amp; Co. pp. 265. {{ISBN|0-304-35592-5}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

In this belief system, celibacy is given the utmost importance. It is said that, as per the direction of the Supreme God those lead a pure and celibate life will be successfully able to conquer the surging vices. The power of celibacy creates an unseen environment of divinity bringing peace, power, purity, prosperity and fortune. Those with the power of celibacy are eligible to claim a bright future of Golden Age of heaven / Paradise. Brahma Kumaris' concept of identifying the self as a soul, different from physical body, is deeply linked to the philosophy of celibacy. It is said that the craving for sex and impure thoughts are the reason for the whole trouble in the universe today. And celibacy is to lead the pure relationship in one's life.{{Citation needed|date=January 2014}}

==Christianity==
[[File:Saint Jean-Baptiste au désert, Raphaël (Louvre INV 606) 01.jpg|thumb|''St. John the Baptist in the Wilderness'' by [[Raphael]], circa 1517]]
[[File:Walking russian orthodox nuns and monk Isreal.JPG|thumb|A Russian orthodox nun and monk in the Old City of Jerusalem, 2012]]

When Jesus discusses marriage, he points out that there is some responsibility for a man marrying a woman (and&lt;!-- for sure discussed (or only implied?): --&gt; vice versa). Not having assets of their own, women needed to be protected from the risk of their husbands' putting them on the street at whim. In those times marriage was an economic matter&lt;ref name=Chadwick&gt;Henry Chadwick, The Early Church, {{ISBN|978-0140231991}}&lt;/ref&gt; rather than one of love. A woman and her children could easily be rejected.{{Citation needed|date=August 2016}} Restriction of divorce was based on the necessity of protecting the woman and her position in society, not necessarily in a religious context, but an economic context.&lt;ref&gt;Jonathan Hill, What Has Christianity Ever Done for Us?: How It Shaped the Modern World 978-0830833283&lt;/ref&gt; He also points out that there are those &quot;which were made eunuchs of men: and there be eunuchs, which have made themselves eunuchs for the kingdom of heaven's sake&quot;, but in the original Greek, the word εὐνοῦχος means &quot;castrated person&quot;. It was the custom at the time Jesus lived for priests of some ancient gods and goddesses to be castrated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Versluis, Arthur 2008&quot;&gt;Versluis, Arthur, The secret history of western sexual mysticism. Vermont 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; In the pre-Christian period [[Vestal Virgin|Vestal]]s, who served the [[virgin]] goddess of the [[hearth]], were obliged to forgo marriage, and so were some priests and servants of some ancient deities such as [[Isis]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Versluis, Arthur 2008&quot;/&gt;

There is no commandment in the New Testament that Jesus' disciples have to live in celibacy.&lt;ref name=Chadwick/&gt; The general view on sexuality among the early Jewish Christians was quite positive.&lt;ref name=GeelsRoos&gt;Geels, Antoon &amp; Roos, Lena. Sexuality in world's religions. University press, Lund, Sweden 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Jesus himself does not speak in negative terms of the body in the New Testament. While the Jewish sect of [[essene]]s practiced celibacy the general practice of the Jewish community by that time prescribed marriage for everybody, and at an early age.&lt;ref name=Chadwick/&gt; [[Saint Peter]], also known as Simon Peter, the Apostle was married; Jesus healed Simon Peter's mother-in-law (Matt. 8:14), and other apostles and church members among the early Jewish Christians were also married: Paul's personal friends, [[Priscilla and Aquila]] ({{Bibleref2|Romans|16:3}}), who were Paul's coworkers, [[Andronicus of Pannonia]] ({{Bibleref2|Romans|16:7}}), and [[Junia (New Testament person)|Junia]] ({{Bibleref2|Romans |16:7}}), who were highly regarded among the apostles, [[Ananias and Sapphira]] (Ap 5:1), [[Apphia]] and [[Philemon (New Testament person)|Philemon]] (Phil 1: 1). According to [[Eusebius]] Church History (''Historia Ecclesiastica''), [[Paul the Apostle]], also known as Saul of Tarsus, was also married. It was the custom in the Jewish community to marry early.&lt;ref name=GeelsRoos/&gt;

In his early writings, Paul the Apostle described marriage as a [[Socialization|social obligation]] that has the potential of distracting from Christ. Sex, in turn, is not sinful but natural, and sex within marriage is both proper and necessary.&lt;ref&gt;Will Deming, ''Paul on marriage and celibacy: the hellenistic background of 1 Corinthians 7.'' [[William B. Eerdmans Publishing Co.]] 2003; 2nd edition.&lt;/ref&gt; In his later writings, Paul made parallels between the relations between spouses and God's relationship with the church. &quot;Husbands love your wives even as Christ loved the church. Husbands should love their wives as their own bodies&quot; (Ephesians 5:25–28). The early Christians lived in the belief that the End of the World would soon come upon them, and saw no point in planning new families and having children.&lt;ref name=Chadwick/&gt; This was why Paul encouraged both celibate and marital lifestyles&lt;ref name=Chadwick/&gt; among the members of the Corinthian congregation, regarding celibacy as the preferable of the two.

Paul the Apostle emphasized the importance of overcoming the desires of the flesh and saw the state of celibacy being superior to the marriage.&lt;ref name=&quot;CrooksBaur2010&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author1=Robert Crooks|author2=Karla Baur|title=Our Sexuality |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MpRnPtmdRVwC&amp;pg=PA11|year=2010|publisher=Cengage Learning |isbn=978-0-495-81294-4 |page=11|edition=11th}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Catholic Church, a [[consecrated virgin]], is a woman who has been consecrated by the church to a life of perpetual virginity in the service of God. According to most Christian thought, the first sacred virgin was [[Mary (mother of Jesus)|Mary]], the mother of Jesus, who was consecrated by the Holy Spirit during the Annunciation. Tradition also has it that the Apostle Matthew consecrated virgins. A number of early Christian martyrs were women or girls who had given themselves to Christ in perpetual virginity, such as [[Saint Agnes]] and [[Saint Lucy]].

===Desert Fathers===
[[File:St Macarius the Great with Cherub.jpg|thumb|''Saint [[Macarius of Egypt|Macarius]] and a Cherub'' from [[Saint Catherine's Monastery]], Sinai, Egypt]]
The Desert Fathers were Christian [[hermit]]s, and [[ascetics]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Chryssavgis15&quot; /&gt; who had a major influence on the development of Christianity and celibacy. [[Paul of Thebes]] is often credited with being the first hermit [[monk]] to go to the desert, but it was [[Anthony the Great]] who launched the movement that became the Desert Fathers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Waddell30&quot;&gt;[[#refWaddell1957|Waddell 1957]], p. 30.&lt;/ref&gt; Sometime around AD&amp;nbsp;270, Anthony heard a Sunday sermon stating that perfection could be achieved by selling all of one's possessions, giving the proceeds to the poor, and following Christ.(Matt. 19.21) He followed the advice and made the further step of moving deep into the desert to seek complete solitude.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chryssavgis15&quot;&gt;[[#refChryssavgis2008|Chryssavgis 2008]], p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;

Over time, the model of Anthony and other hermits attracted many followers, who lived alone in the desert or in small groups. They chose a life of extreme [[asceticism]], renouncing all the pleasures of the senses, rich food, baths, rest, and anything that made them comfortable.&lt;ref name=&quot;Riddle43&quot;&gt;[[#refRiddle2008|Riddle 2008]], p. 43.&lt;/ref&gt; Thousands joined them in the desert, mostly men but also a handful of women. Religious seekers also began going to the desert seeking advice and counsel from the early Desert Fathers. By the time of Anthony's death, there were so many men and women living in the desert in celibacy that it was described as &quot;a city&quot; by Anthony's biographer.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chryssavgis15&quot; /&gt; The first Conciliar document on celibacy of the Western Christian Church (Canon 33 of the [[Synod of Elvira]], {{circa|AD&amp;nbsp;305}}) states that the discipline of celibacy is to refrain from the ''use'' of marriage, i.e. refrain from having carnal contact with one's spouse.&lt;ref&gt;Roman Cholij ''Clerical Celibacy in East and West''. Gracewing 1990; 2nd Rev. ed., p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the later [[Jerome|St. Jerome]] ({{circa|347}}{{snd}}420) celibacy is a moral virtue, consisting of living in the flesh, but outside the flesh, and so being not corrupted by it (''vivere in carne praeter carnem''). Celibacy excludes not only libidinous acts, but also sinful thoughts or desires of the flesh.&lt;ref&gt;art. Celibacy, clerical, in ''Dictionary of Moral Theology''. Compiled under the Direction of H. E. Cardinal Roberti. Ed. Mgr. Pietro Palazzini. London: Burns &amp; Oates Publishers of the Holy See 1962;&lt;/ref&gt; Jerome referred to marriage prohibition for priests when he claimed in ''[[Against Jovinianus]]'' that Peter and the other apostles had been married before they were called, but subsequently gave up their marital relations.&lt;ref&gt;''Aduersus Jovinianum I'', 7. 26 ([[Patrologia Latina|PL]] 23, 230C; 256C).&lt;/ref&gt;
Celibacy as a vocation may be independent from [[religious vows]] (as is the case with [[consecrated virgins]], [[ascetics]] and hermits).{{citation needed|date=July 2019}} In the Catholic, [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Orthodox]] and [[Oriental Orthodox Church|Oriental Orthodox]] traditions, bishops are required to be celibate.{{citation needed|date=July 2019}} In the Eastern Christian traditions, priests and deacons are allowed to be married, yet have to remain celibate if they are unmarried at the time of [[ordination]].{{citation needed|date=July 2019}}

===Augustinian view===
[[File:Nuns in procession.jpg|thumb|Nuns in procession, French manuscript, {{circa|1300}}]] 
In the early Church higher clerics lived in marriages. [[Augustine of Hippo]] was one of the first to develop a theory that sexual feelings were sinful and negative. Augustine taught that the original sin of Adam and Eve was either an act of ''foolishness'' (''insipientia'') followed by ''pride'' and ''disobedience'' to God, or else inspired by pride.&lt;ref&gt;He explained to Julian of Eclanum that it was a most subtle job to discern what came first: ''Sed si disputatione subtilissima et elimatissima opus est, ut sciamus utrum primos homines insipientia superbos, an insipientes superbia fecerit''. (''Contra Julianum'', V, 4.18; PL 44, 795)&lt;/ref&gt; The first couple disobeyed God, who had told them not to eat of the [[Tree of the knowledge of good and evil]] (Gen 2:17).&lt;ref&gt;Augustine of Hippo, ''On the Literal Meaning of Genesis'' (''De Genesi ad litteram''), VIII, 6:12, vol. 1, pp. 192–3 and 12:28, vol. 2, pp. 219–20, trans. John Hammond Taylor SJ;[[Bibliothèque Augustinniene|BA]] 49,28 and 50–52; [[Patrologia Latina|PL]] 34, 377; cf. idem, ''De Trinitate'', XII, 12.17; [[Corpus Christianorum|CCL]] 50, 371–372 [v. 26–31;1–36]; ''De natura boni'' 34–35; CSEL 25, 872; PL 42, 551–572&lt;/ref&gt; The tree was a symbol of the order of creation.&lt;ref&gt;Augustine of Hippo, ''On the Literal Meaning of Genesis'' (''De Genesi ad litteram''), VIII, 4.8; [[Bibliothèque Augustinniene|BA]] 49, 20&lt;/ref&gt; Self-centeredness made Adam and Eve eat of it, thus failing to acknowledge and respect the world as it was created by God, with its hierarchy of beings and values.&lt;ref&gt;Augustine explained it in this way: &quot;Why therefore is it enjoined upon mind, that it should know itself? I suppose, in order that it may consider itself, and live according to its own nature; that is, seek to be regulated according to its own nature, viz., under Him to whom it ought to be subject, and above those things to which it is to be preferred; under Him by whom it ought to be ruled, above those things which it ought to rule. For it does many things through vicious desire, as though in forgetfulness of itself. For it sees some things intrinsically excellent, in that more excellent nature which is God: and whereas it ought to remain steadfast that it may enjoy them, it is turned away from Him, by wishing to appropriate those things to itself, and not to be like to Him by His gift, but to be what He is by its own, and it begins to move and slip gradually down into less and less, which it thinks to be more and more.&quot; (&quot;[http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/130105.htm On the Trinity]&quot; (''De Trinitate''), 5:7; [[Corpus Christianorum|CCL]] 50, 320 [1–12])&lt;/ref&gt; They would not have fallen into pride and lack of wisdom, if Satan had not sown into their senses &quot;the root of evil&quot; (''radix Mali'').&lt;ref&gt;Augustine of Hippo, ''Nisi radicem mali humanus tunc reciperet sensus'' (&quot;Contra Julianum&quot;, I, 9.42; PL 44, 670)&lt;/ref&gt; Their nature was wounded by [[concupiscence]] or [[libido]], which affected human intelligence and will, as well as affections and desires, including sexual desire.&lt;ref&gt;In one of Augustine's late works, ''Retractationes'', he made a significant remark indicating the way he understood difference between spiritual, moral libido and the sexual desire: &quot;Libido is not good and righteous use of the libido&quot; (&quot;libido non-est bonus et rectus usus libidinis&quot;). See the whole passage: ''Dixi etiam quodam loco: «Quod enim est cibus ad salutem hominis, hoc est concubitus ad salutem generis, et utrumque non-est sine delectatione carnali, quae tamen modificata et temperantia refrenante in usum naturalem redacta, libido esse non-potest». Quod ideo dictum est, quoniam &quot;libido non-est bonus et rectus usus libidinis&quot;. Sicut enim malum est male uti bonis, ita bonum bene uti malis. De qua re alias, maxime contra novos haereticos Pelagianos, diligentius disputavi''. Cf. ''De bono coniugali'', 16.18; PL 40, 385; ''De nuptiis et concupiscentia'', II, 21.36; PL 44, 443; ''Contra Iulianum'', III, 7.16; PL 44, 710; ibid., V, 16.60; PL 44, 817. See also {{cite book |title= Le mariage chrétien dans l'oeuvre de Saint Augustin. Une théologie baptismale de la vie conjugale |author= Idem |year= 1983 |publisher= Études Augustiniennes |location=Paris |page=97}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The sin of Adam is inherited by all human beings. Already in his pre-Pelagian writings, Augustine taught that Original Sin was transmitted by [[concupiscence]],&lt;ref&gt;Augustine of Hippo, ''Imperfectum Opus contra Iulianum'', II, 218&lt;/ref&gt; which he regarded as the passion of both soul and body,&lt;ref&gt;In 393 or 394 he commented: &quot;Moreover, if unbelief is fornication, and idolatry unbelief, and covetousness idolatry, it is not to be doubted that covetousness also is fornication. Who, then, in that case can rightly separate any unlawful lust whatever from the category of fornication, if covetousness is fornication? And from this we perceive, that because of unlawful lusts, not only those of which one is guilty in acts of uncleanness with another's husband or wife, but any unlawful lusts whatever, which cause the soul making a bad use of the body to wander from the law of God, and to be ruinously and basely corrupted, a man may, without crime, put away his wife, and a wife her husband, because the Lord makes the cause of fornication an exception; which fornication, in accordance with the above considerations, we are compelled to understand as being general and universal&quot; (&quot;[http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/16011.htm On the Sermon on the Mount]&quot;, ''De sermone Domini in monte'', 1:16:46; [[Corpus Christianorum|CCL]] 35, 52)&lt;/ref&gt; making humanity a ''massa damnata'' (mass of perdition, condemned crowd) and much enfeebling, though not destroying, the freedom of the will.

In the early 3rd century, the [[Canons of the Apostles|Canons]] of the [[Apostolic Constitutions]] decreed that only lower clerics might still marry after their ordination, but marriage of bishops, priests, and deacons were not allowed.&lt;ref&gt;Constitutiones apostolorum 8, 47, 26 (SC 336, 280, 83f.) τῶν εις κληρον παρελθόντων ἄγαμον κελεύομεν Βουλομένους γαμεῖν αναγνώστας και ψαλτας μόνους.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Socrates of Constantinople|Socrates Scholasticus]], ''Historia ealesiastica'' I, 11, 5 (GCS Socr. 42, i9f.)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stefan Heid (2000),''Celibacy in the Early Church'', p. 170&lt;/ref&gt; Augustine's view of sexual feelings as sinful affected his view of women. For example, he considered a man's erection to be sinful, though involuntary,&lt;ref&gt;Augustine of Hippo, ''City of God'', 14.17&lt;/ref&gt; because it did not take place under his conscious control. His solution was to place controls on women to limit their ability to influence men.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reuther, R.R. 2007 pp. 47-68&quot;&gt;Reuther, R.R. (2007). &quot;Augustine: sexuality gender and women&quot;, pp. 47–68 in J.C. Stark (Ed.), ''Feminist interpretations of Augustine'', University Park, PA: The Pennsylvania State University Press, {{ISBN|027103257X}}.&lt;/ref&gt; He equated flesh with woman and spirit with man.&lt;ref&gt;Augustine of Hippo, as cited in Trombley, C. (2003). Who said women can’t teach? God’s vision for women in ministry. Gainesville, FL: Bridge-Logos, p. 239, {{ISBN|1458796329}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

He believed that the serpent approached Eve because she was less rational and lacked self-control, while Adam's choice to eat was viewed as an act of kindness so that Eve would not be left alone.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reuther, R.R. 2007 pp. 47-68&quot;/&gt; Augustine believed sin entered the world because man (the spirit) did not exercise control over woman (the flesh).&lt;ref&gt;Edwards, B. (2011) ''Let My People Go: A Call to End the Oppression of Women in the Church'', Charleston, SC: Createspace, {{ISBN|1466401117}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Augustine's views on women were not all negative, however. In his ''Tractates on the Gospel of John'', Augustine, commenting on the Samaritan woman from John 4:1–42, uses the woman as a figure of the church.

According to Raming, the authority of the ''[[Decretum Gratiani]]'', a collection of Roman Catholic [[canon law]] which prohibits women from leading, teaching, or being a witness, rests largely on the views of the early church fathers, especially St. Augustine.&lt;ref&gt;Raming, I. (2004). A history of women and ordination volume two: The priestly office of women – God’s gift to a renewed church. (B. Cooke &amp; G. Macy, Trans.). Lanham, MD: Scarecrow Press Inc. pp. 29–30, {{ISBN|0810848503}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The laws and traditions founded upon St. Augustine's views of sexuality and women continue to exercise considerable influence over church doctrinal positions regarding the role of women in the church.&lt;ref&gt;Edwards, B. (2011). &quot;Let My People Go: A Call to End the Oppression of Women in the Church.&quot; Charleston, SC: Createspace, {{ISBN|1466401117}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

===After Augustine===
[[File:Bp-priests.jpg|thumb|Catholic priests from all over the world in Budapest, 2013]]
One explanation for the origin of obligatory celibacy is that it is based on the writings of [[Saint Paul]], who wrote of the advantages celibacy allowed a man in serving the Lord.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schreck255&quot;&gt;Schreck, p. 255.&lt;/ref&gt; Celibacy was popularised by the early Christian theologians like [[Saint Augustine of Hippo]] and [[Origen]]. Another possible explanation for the origins of obligatory celibacy revolves around more practical reason, &quot;the need to avoid claims on church property by priests' offspring&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.nytimes.com/2009/03/22/nyregion/22egan.html | work=The New York Times | title=On Eve of Retirement, Cardinal Breathes Life into Debate on Priestly Celibacy | first=Paul | last=Vitello | date=22 March 2009 | accessdate=1 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; It remains a matter of [[Canon Law]] (and often a criterion for certain [[religious order]]s, especially [[Franciscans]]) that priests may not own land and therefore cannot pass it on to legitimate or illegitimate children. The land belongs to the Church through the local diocese as administered by the Local Ordinary (usually a bishop), who is often an ''[[ex officio]]'' [[corporation sole]]. Celibacy is viewed differently by the Catholic Church and the various Protestant communities. It includes [[clerical celibacy]], celibacy of the [[consecrated life]], voluntary lay celibacy, and celibacy outside of marriage.{{citation needed|date=July 2019}}

The [[Protestant Reformation]] rejected celibate life and sexual continence for preachers. Protestant celibate communities have emerged, especially from [[Anglican]] and [[Lutheran]] backgrounds.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} A few minor Christian sects advocate celibacy as a better way of life. These groups included the [[Shakers]], the [[Harmony Society]] and the [[Ephrata Cloister]]. Celibacy not only for religious and monastics (brothers/monks and sisters/nuns) but also for bishops is upheld by the Catholic Church traditions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://uk.encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761565340/Celibacy.html Celibacy]. Microsoft Encarta Online Encyclopedia 2009. [https://web.archive.org/web/20080314174700/http://uk.encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761565340/Celibacy.html Archived] 31 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many evangelicals prefer the term &quot;abstinence&quot; to &quot;celibacy.&quot; Assuming everyone will marry, they focus their discussion on refraining from premarital sex and focusing on the joys of a future marriage. But some evangelicals, particularly older singles, desire a positive message of celibacy that moves beyond the &quot;wait until marriage&quot; message of abstinence campaigns. They seek a new understanding of celibacy that is focused on God rather than a future marriage or a lifelong vow to the Church.&lt;ref&gt;Colon, Christine, and Bonnie Field. Singled Out: Why Celibacy Must Be Reinvented in Today's Church. Grand Rapids, MI: Brazos, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

There are also many Pentecostal churches which practice celibate ministry. For instance, The full-time ministers of the Pentecostal Mission are celibate. Most of them are single, married couples can become celibate.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://wordwillsave.com/cpm/|title=TPM (CPM) PENTECOSTAL MISSION {{!}} WORD WILL SAVE|last=www.site5.com|website=wordwillsave.com|language=en-US|access-date=2018-01-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Catholic Church===
[[File:Conventual Franciscan.JPG|thumb|Conventual [[Franciscan]] [[friar]], 2012]]
{{See also|Clerical celibacy in the Catholic Church}}
During the first three or four centuries, no law was promulgated prohibiting clerical marriage. Celibacy was a matter of choice for bishops, priests, and deacons.&lt;ref&gt;[Henry Chadwick, The Early Church, {{ISBN|978-0140231991}}]&lt;/ref&gt;

Statutes forbidding clergy from having wives were written beginning with the Council of Elvira (306) but these early statutes were not universal and were often defied by clerics and then retracted by hierarchy.&lt;ref name=&quot;New Catholic Encyclopedia 1967, p. 366&quot;&gt;New Catholic Encyclopedia, vol 3, Catholic University of America: Washington, D.C. 1967, p. 366&lt;/ref&gt; The Synod of Gangra (345) condemned a false asceticism whereby worshipers boycotted celebrations presided over by married clergy.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopedia of Catholicism,1995, ed. O’Brien, Richard, NY: Harper Collins Publishers, p.290&lt;/ref&gt; The Apostolic Constitutions ({{circa|400}}) excommunicated a priest or bishop who left his wife 'under the pretense of piety&quot;’ (Mansi, 1:51).&lt;ref&gt;New Catholic Encyclopedia, vol 3, Catholic University of America: Washington, D.C. 1967 p. 370&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;A famous letter of Synesius of Cyrene ({{circa|414}}) is evidence both for the respecting of personal decision in the matter and for contemporary appreciation of celibacy. For priests and deacons clerical marriage continued to be in vogue&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;New Catholic Encyclopedia, vol 3, Catholic University of America: Washington, D.C. 1967, p. 323&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;The Second Lateran Council (1139) seems to have enacted the first written law making sacred orders a diriment impediment to marriage for the universal Church.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;New Catholic Encyclopedia 1967, p. 366&quot;/&gt; Celibacy was first required of some clerics in 1123 at the [[First Lateran Council]]. Because clerics resisted it, the celibacy mandate was restated at the Second Lateran Council (1139) and the Council of Trent (1545–64).&lt;ref name=&quot;newadvent.org&quot;&gt;New Advent, [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/03481a.htm &quot;Celibacy of the Clergy&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; In places, coercion and enslavement of clerical wives and children was apparently involved in the enforcement of the law.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;The Catholic Encyclopedia vol 3, New York: The Encyclopedia Press, Inc., 486&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;The earliest decree in which the children [of clerics] were declared to be slaves and never to be enfranchised [freed] seems to have been a canon of the Synod of Pavia in 1018. Similar penalties were promulgated against wives and concubines (see the Synod of Melfi, 1189 can. Xii), who by the very fact of their unlawful connexion with a subdeacon or clerk of higher rank became liable to be seized by the over-lord&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Celibacy for priests continues to be a contested issue even today.

In the [[Roman Catholic Church]], the [[Twelve Apostles]] are considered to have been the first [[priest]]s and [[bishop]]s of the Church. Some say the call to be [[eunuch]]s for the sake of Heaven in Matthew 19 was a call to be sexually continent and that this developed into celibacy for priests as the successors of the apostles. Others see the call to be sexually continent in Matthew 19 to be a caution for men who were too readily divorcing and remarrying.

The view of the Church is that celibacy is a reflection of life in Heaven, a source of detachment from the material world which aids in one's relationship with God. Celibacy is designed to &quot;consecrate themselves with undivided heart to the Lord and to &quot;the affairs of the Lord, they give themselves entirely to God and to men. It is a sign of this new life to the service of which the Church's minister is consecrated; accepted with a joyous heart celibacy radiantly proclaims the Reign of God.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/catechism/p2s2c3a6.htm Catechism of the Roman Catholic Church, 1579] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100111024309/http://www.vatican.va/archive/catechism/p2s2c3a6.htm |date=11 January 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast, [[Saint Peter]], whom the Church considers its first [[Pope]], was married given that he had a [[Healing the mother of Peter's wife|mother-in-law whom Christ healed]] (Matthew 8).

Usually, only celibate men are ordained as priests in the [[Latin Rite]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Canon 1037 |url=http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG1104/__P3R.HTM |publisher=Vatican |work=1983 [[Canon law (Catholic Church)|Code of Canon Law]]|url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080218110036/http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG1104/__P3R.HTM |archivedate=18 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Canon 1031 |url=http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG1104/__P3Q.HTM |publisher=Vatican |work=1983 [[Canon law (Catholic Church)|Code of Canon Law]]|accessdate=9 March 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Married clergy who have converted from other Christian denominations can be ordained Roman Catholic priests without becoming celibate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Cholij| first=Roman |title=Priestly Celibacy in Patristics and in the History of the Church|url=http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/cclergy/documents/rc_con_cclergy_doc_01011993_chisto_en.html |publisher=Vatican |year=1993}} A priest who is married at time of ordination continues to be married, with full obligation to all expectations of the marriage, but cannot remarry and remain in the practice of the priesthood.&lt;/ref&gt; Priestly celibacy is not ''doctrine'' of the Church (such as the belief in the [[Assumption of Mary]]) but a matter of discipline, like the use of the vernacular (local) language in Mass or Lenten fasting and abstinence.&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic.com Article&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Celibacy and the Priesthood |url=http://www.catholic.com/library/Celibacy_and_the_Priesthood.asp |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081205100019/http://www.catholic.com/library/Celibacy_and_the_Priesthood.asp |archivedate=5 December 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; As such, it can theoretically change at any time though it still must be obeyed by Catholics until the change were to take place. The [[Eastern Catholic Churches]] ordain both celibate and married men. However, in both the East and the West, bishops are chosen from among those who are celibate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last =Niebuhur | first =Gustav | title =Bishop's Quiet Action Allows Priest Both Flock And Family | work=The New York Times | date =16 February 1997 | url =https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EEDD133FF935A25751C0A961958260}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = 1990 Codex Canonum Ecclesiarum Orientalium, Canons 285, 373, 374, 758| publisher=Libreria Editrice Vaticana |year= 1990| url = http://www.gwo.cz/pravda/1990_Code_of_Canon_Law.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Ireland, several priests have fathered children, the two most prominent being Bishop [[Eamonn Casey]] and Father [[Michael Cleary (priest)|Michael Cleary]].
[[File:Carmelitas de la comunidad de Nogoyá.jpg|thumb|Discalced Carmelites from Argentina, 2013]]
The classical heritage flourished throughout the Middle Ages in both the Byzantine Greek East and the Latin West. [[Will Durant]] has made a case that certain prominent features of Plato's [[The Republic (Plato)|ideal community]] were discernible in the organization, dogma and effectiveness of &quot;the&quot; Medieval Church in Europe:&lt;ref name=&quot;Durant&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=Will |last=Durant |year=2005 |title=Story of Philosophy |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=suLI7RoaBEEC&amp;pg=PA34 |publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |isbn=978-0-671-69500-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;The clergy, like Plato's guardians, were placed in authority... by their talent as shown in ecclesiastical studies and administration, by their disposition to a life of meditation and simplicity, and ... by the influence of their relatives with the powers of state and church. In the latter half of the period in which they ruled [AD&amp;nbsp;800 onwards], the clergy were as free from family cares as even Plato could desire [for such guardians]... [Clerical] Celibacy was part of the psychological structure of the power of the clergy; for on the one hand they were unimpeded by the narrowing egoism of the family, and on the other their apparent superiority to the call of the flesh added to the awe in which lay sinners held them....&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Durant&quot;/&gt; &quot;In the latter half of the period in which they ruled, the clergy were as free from family cares as even Plato could desire&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Durant&quot;/&gt;

&quot;Greater understanding of human psychology has led to questions regarding the impact of celibacy on the human development of the clergy. The realization that many non-European countries view celibacy negatively has prompted questions concerning the value of retaining celibacy as an absolute and universal requirement for ordained ministry in the Roman Catholic Church&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholicism 1995, p.291&quot;&gt;Encyclopedia of Catholicism,1995, ed. O’Brien, Richard, NY: Harper Collins Publishers, p. 291&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;The declining number of priests in active ministry, the exemption from the requirement of celibacy for married clergy who enter the Catholic Church after having been ordained in the Episcopal Church, and reported incidences of de facto nonobservance of the requirement by clergy in various parts of the world, especially in Africa and Latin America, suggests that the discussion [of celibacy] will continue.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholicism 1995, p.291&quot;/&gt;

The reintroduction of a permanent diaconate has permitted the Church to allow married men to become deacons but they may not go on to become priests.

===Celibate homosexual Christians===
Some homosexual Christians choose to be celibate following their denomination's teachings on homosexuality.&lt;ref name=&quot;religionnews1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.religionnews.com/2014/08/04/gay-christian-celibate-changing-face-homosexuality-debate/ |title=Gay, Christian and ... celibate: The changing face of the homosexuality debate – Religion News Service |publisher=Religionnews.com |accessdate=2015-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014, the [[American Association of Christian Counselors]] amended its code of ethics to eliminate the promotion of [[conversion therapy]] for homosexuals and encouraged them to be celibate instead.&lt;ref name=&quot;religionnews1&quot;/&gt;

==Hinduism==
[[File:A sadhu by the Ghats on the Ganges, Varanasi.jpg|thumb|A [[sadhu]] by the Ghats on the Ganges, Varanasi, 2008]]
In Hinduism, celibacy is usually associated with the ''[[sadhu]]s'' (&quot;holy men&quot;), ascetics who withdraw from society and renounce all worldly ties. Celibacy, termed ''[[brahmacharya]]'' in Vedic scripture, is the fourth of the ''[[yamas]]'' and the word literally translated means &quot;dedicated to the Divinity of Life&quot;. The word is often used in yogic practice to refer to celibacy or denying pleasure, but this is only a small part of what ''brahmacharya'' represents. The purpose of practicing ''brahmacharya'' is to keep a person focused on the purpose in life, the things that instill a feeling of peace and contentment. It is also used to cultivate occult powers and many supernatural feats, called [[siddhi]].

==Islam==
{{See also|Marriage in Islam}}
Islamic attitudes toward celibacy have been complex, Muhammad denounced it, however some [[Sufi]] orders embrace it. Islam does not promote celibacy; rather it condemns [[premarital sex]] and [[extramarital sex]]. In fact, according to Islam, marriage enables one to attain the highest form of righteousness within this sacred spiritual bond and is as such to be sought after and desired. It disagrees with the concept that marriage acts as a form of distraction in attaining nearness to God. The [[Qur'an]] (57:27) states, &quot;But the Monasticism which they invented for themselves, We did not prescribe for them but only to please God therewith, but that they did not observe it with the right observance.&quot;

The following sayings about Muhammad also address celibacy:

&quot;There have been people who have come to the prophet and explained how they love to be engaged in prayer and fasting for the sake of God. The Prophet Mohammed told them that, despite this being good, it is also a blessing to raise a family, to remain moderate and not to concentrate too much on one aspect as not only can this be unhealthy for an individual as well as upon society, it may also take one away from God.&quot;{{Citation needed|date=January 2014}}

Celibacy appears as a peculiarity among some Sufis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The World's Religions: Continuities and Transformations|editor-first1=Peter B.|editor-last1=Clarke|editor-first2=Peter|editor-last2=Beyer|year=2009|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rBgn3xB75ZcC&amp;pg=PA692|page=692|isbn=978-1135211004| ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Celibacy was practiced by women saints in Sufism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The History of Women's Mosques in Chinese Islam: A Mosque of Their Own|first1=Maria|last1=Jaschok|first2=Jingjun|last2=Shui|edition=illustrated|year=2000|publisher=Psychology Press|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jV9_YvgUmpsC&amp;pg=PA43|page=43|isbn=0700713026| ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; Celibacy was debated along with women's roles in Sufism in medieval times.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Women in Muslim Societies: Diversity Within Unity|editor-first1=Herbert L.|editor-last1=Bodman|editor-first2=Nayereh Esfahlani|editor-last2=Tohidi|year=1998|publisher=Lynne Rienner Publishers|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=PFzdA2Hini4C&amp;pg=PA12|page=12|isbn=1555875785| ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Celibacy, poverty, meditation, and mysticism within an ascetic context along with worship centered around Saint's tombs were promoted by the Qadiri Sufi order among Hui Muslims in China.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Islam Outside the Arab World|editor1-first=David|editor1-last=Westerlund|editor2-first=Ingvar|editor2-last=Svanberg|year=1999|publisher=St. Martin's Press|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=weYQMv2RqCgC&amp;pg=PA199|page=199|isbn=0312226918| ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Islam Outside the Arab World|first1=David|last1=Westerlund|first2=Ingvar|last2=Svanberg|year=2012|publisher=Routledge|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=weYQMv2RqCgC&amp;pg=PA199|page=199|isbn=978-1136113307| ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; In China, unlike other Muslim sects, the leaders (Shaikhs) of the [[Qadiriyya]] Sufi order are celibate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Muslim Diversity: Local Islam in Global Contexts|editor-first=Leif O.|editor-last=Manger|volume=Volume 26 of NIAS studies in Asian topics: Nordisk Institut for Asienstudier|number=Nordic Institute of Asian Studies : Nias Studies in Asian Topics, Number 26 |issn=0142-6028|edition=illustrated|year=1999|publisher=Psychology Press|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=uHjR3yeIWzUC&amp;pg=PA118|page=118|isbn=070071104X| ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Oxford History of Islam|editor-first=John L.|editor-last=Esposito|edition=illustrated|year=1999|publisher=Oxford University Press|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=imw_KFD5bsQC&amp;pg=PA452|page=452|isbn=0195107993| ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Central Asia and the Caucasus: Transnationalism and Diaspora|editor1-first=Touraj|editor1-last=Atabaki|editor2-first=Sanjyot|editor2-last=Mehendale|edition=illustrated|year=2004|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=OWMyFWAZLCwC&amp;pg=PA197|page=197|isbn=0203495829| ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Central Asia and the Caucasus: Transnationalism and Diaspora|first=Dru C.|last=Gladney|editor1-first=Touraj|editor1-last=Atabaki|editor2-first=Sanjyot|editor2-last=Mehendale|edition=illustrated|year=2004|publisher=Routledge|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=_EeHWWBpn14C&amp;pg=PA197|page=197|isbn=1134319940| ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Muslim Chinese: Ethnic Nationalism in the People's Republic|first=Dru C.|last=Gladney|issue=149 of East Asian Monographs|volume=Volume 149 of Harvard East Asian monographs|issn=0073-0483|edition=illustrated|year=1996|publisher=Harvard Univ Asia Center|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=_hJ9aht6nZQC&amp;pg=PA44|page=44|isbn=0674594975| ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike other Sufi orders in China, the leadership within the order is not a hereditary position, rather, one of the disciples of the celibate Shaikh is chosen by the Shaikh to succeed him . The 92-year-old celibate Shaikh Yang Shijun was the leader of the Qadiriya order in China as of 1998.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Familiar strangers: a history of Muslims in Northwest China|first=Jonathan Neaman|last=Lipman|year=1998|publisher=University of Washington Press|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Y8Nzux7z6KAC&amp;pg=PA73|page=89|isbn=0295800550| ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Celibacy is practiced by Haydariya Sufi dervishes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Historical Dictionary of Sufism|first=John|last=Renard|series=Historical Dictionaries of Religions, Philosophies, and Movements Series|year=2005|publisher=Scarecrow Press|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qqG240d2L5sC&amp;pg=PA104|page=104|isbn=0810865408| ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The A to Z of Sufism|first=John|last=Renard|volume=Volume 44 of The A to Z Guide Series|year=2009|publisher=Scarecrow Press|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=cTlmtoozRV0C&amp;pg=PA104|page=104|isbn=978-0810863439| ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Meher Baba==
The spiritual teacher [[Meher Baba]] stated that &quot;[F]or the [spiritual] aspirant a life of strict celibacy is preferable to married life, if restraint comes to him easily without undue sense of self-repression. Such restraint is difficult for most persons and sometimes impossible, and for them married life is decidedly more helpful than a life of celibacy. For ordinary persons, married life is undoubtedly advisable unless they have a special aptitude for celibacy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Meher Baba|Baba, Meher]] (1967). ''Discourses''. '''1'''. San Francisco: Sufism Reoriented. pp. 144–45. {{ISBN|978-1-880619-09-4}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Baba also asserted that &quot;The value of celibacy lies in the habit of restraint and the sense of detachment and independence which it gives&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Meher Baba|Baba, Meher]] (1967). ''Discourses''. '''1'''. San Francisco: Sufism Reoriented. p. 145. {{ISBN|978-1-880619-09-4}}.&lt;/ref&gt; and that &quot;The aspirant must choose one of the two courses which are open to him. He must take to the life of celibacy or to the married life, and he must avoid at all costs a cheap compromise between the two. Promiscuity in sex gratification is bound to land the aspirant in a most pitiful and dangerous chaos of ungovernable lust.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Meher Baba|Baba, Meher]] (1967). ''Discourses''. '''1'''. San Francisco: Sufism Reoriented. p. 146. {{ISBN|978-1-880619-09-4}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ancient Greece and Rome==
In [[Sparta]] and many other Greek cities, failure to marry was grounds for loss of citizenship, and could be prosecuted as a crime. Both [[Cicero]] and [[Dionysius of Halicarnassus]] stated that Roman law forbade celibacy. There are no records of such a prosecution, nor is the Roman punishment for refusing to marry known.&lt;ref&gt;[[Numa Denis Fustel de Coulanges]], ''The Ancient City'', 38–39&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Pythagoreanism]] was the system of [[esoteric]] and [[metaphysics|metaphysical]] beliefs held by [[Pythagoras]] and his followers. Pythagorean thinking was dominated by a profoundly mystical view of the world. The Pythagorean code further restricted his members from eating meat, fish, and beans which they practised for religious, ethical and ascetic reasons, in particular the idea of [[metempsychosis]] – the transmigration of souls into the bodies of other animals.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|chapter-url=http://www.oup.com/us/brochure/0195154371/samples/vegetarianism.pdf|title=The Oxford Encyclopedia of Food and Drink|chapter=Vegetarianism|publisher=OUP|year=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Bertrand Russell|Russell, Bertrand]], ''[[History of Western Philosophy (Russell)|History of Western Philosophy]]''&lt;/ref&gt;
&quot;Pythagoras himself established a small community that set a premium on study, vegetarianism, and sexual restraint or abstinence.   Later philosophers believed that celibacy would be conducive to the detachment and equilibrium required by the philosopher's calling.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;celibacy&quot;, The New Encyclopædia Britannica, 15th ed., vol 3, Chicago, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Balkans==
{{Main|Albanian sworn virgins}}
The tradition of sworn virgins developed out of the [[Kanun (Albania)|''Kanuni i Lekë Dukagjinit'']] ({{lang-en|The Code of Lekë Dukagjini}}, or simply the ''Kanun''). The ''Kanun'' is not a religious document&amp;nbsp;– many groups follow it, including [[Roman Catholic]]s, the [[Albanian Orthodox]], and [[Muslim]]s.

Women who become sworn virgins make a vow of celibacy, and are allowed to take on the social role of men: inheriting land, wearing male clothing, etc.

==See also==
* [[Abstinence in Judaism]]
* [[Clerical celibacy]]
* [[Consecrated virgin]]
* [[Feminist views on sexuality]]
* [[Incel]]
* [[Virginity]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
* {{Cite book | author= Heid, Stefan | title = Celibacy in the Early Church: The Beginnings of a Discipline of Obligatory Continence for Clerics in East and West | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=Qxy3l0F7mUwC#v=onepage | others= Michael J. Miller (transl. from German) | publisher = Ignatius Press | year = 2000 | location = San Francisco | isbn = 0-89870-800-1 | page = 376}}
* [[Donald Cozzens]] (2006). ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=jr0Ewaa0vSYC#v=onepage Freeing Celibacy]''. Collegeville, Minn.: Liturgical Press.
* {{Cite book | last = Brown | first = Gabrielle | authorlink = Gabrielle Brown | title = The New Celibacy: Why More Men and Women Are Abstaining from Sex—and Enjoying It | publisher = [[McGraw-Hill]] | year = 1980 | location = New York | isbn = 0-07-008430-0 | postscript = &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Includes bibliography; see [https://books.google.com/books?id=ZArPH0nFGo0C&amp;pg=PA341#v=onepage a summary] | url-access = registration | url = https://archive.org/details/newcelibacywhymo00brow }}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Celibacy}}
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Wiktionary|Wikisaurus:celibate}}
{{EB1911 Poster|Celibacy}}
&lt;!--===========================({{NoMoreLinks}})===============================--&gt;
&lt;!--| DO NOT ADD MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. WIKIPEDIA IS NOT A COLLECTION OF |--&gt;
&lt;!--| LINKS. If you think that your link might be useful, do not add it here, |--&gt;
&lt;!--| but put it on this article's discussion page first or submit your link  |--&gt;
&lt;!--| to the appropriate category at the Open Directory Project (www.dmoz.org)|--&gt;
&lt;!--| and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.             |--&gt;
&lt;!--|                                                                         |--&gt;
&lt;!--|           Links that have not been verified WILL BE DELETED.            |--&gt;
&lt;!--|  See [[Wikipedia:External links]] and [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details    |--&gt;
&lt;!--===========================({{NoMoreLinks}})===============================--&gt;
* [http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/cclergy/documents/rc_con_cclergy_doc_01011993_bfoun_en.html The Biblical foundation of priestly celibacy]
* [http://www.vor.org/rbdisk/calvin/ci_html/4_12#4.12.23 The Reformation view of Celibacy]
* [http://www.hbo.com/docs/programs/celibacy/synopsis.html HBO documentary film ''Celibacy'']

{{Sex}}
{{Human sexuality}}

[[Category:Celibacy| ]]</text>
      <sha1>q00dee6smf3pdvo2nv6pdynqhd0p4ex</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
