  <page>
    <title>Canonization</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6097</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940484256</id>
      <parentid>939915049</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-12T20:28:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>141.161.133.51</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{short description|Act by which churches declare that a person who has died is a saint}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{Use American English|date=February 2016}}
[[File:stcyprian.jpg|thumb|Icon of [[St. Cyprian of Carthage]], who urged diligence in the process of canonization]]

'''Canonization''', in its most exact historical sense, refers to a papal declaration that the Catholic faithful may venerate a particular deceased member of the church. Popes began making such decrees in the tenth century. Up to that point, the local bishops governed the veneration of holy men and women within their own dioceses; and there may have been, for any particular saint, no formal decree at all. In subsequent centuries, the procedures became increasingly regularized and the popes began restricting to themselves the right to declare someone a Catholic saint. In contemporary usage, the term is understood to refer to the act by which any [[Christianity|Christian]] church declares that a person who has died is a saint, upon which declaration the person is included in the list of recognized saints, called the &quot;canon.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Copeland |first1=Clare |title=Saints, Devotions and Canonisation in Early Modern Italy |journal=History Compass |date=2012 |volume=10 |issue=3 |pages=260–269 |doi=10.1111/j.1478-0542.2012.00834.x |language=en |issn=1478-0542}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today, the [[Eastern Orthodox Church]], the [[Oriental Orthodox Church]], and the [[Anglican Communion]] speak of &quot;canonized&quot; saints, in addition to the [[Roman Catholic Church]].

== Historical development ==
The [[Roman Rite]]'s Canon of the [[Mass (liturgy)|Mass]] contains only the names of martyrs, along with that of the [[Mary, mother of Jesus|Blessed Virgin Mary]] and, since 1962, that of [[Saint Joseph]] her spouse.

By the fourth century, however, &quot;[[confessor]]s&quot;—people who had confessed their faith not by dying but by word and life—began to be venerated publicly. Examples of such people are Saint [[Hilarion]] and Saint [[Ephrem the Syrian]] in the East, and Saint [[Martin of Tours]] and Saint [[Hilary of Poitiers]] in the West. Their names were inserted in the [[diptych]]s, the lists of saints explicitly venerated in the [[liturgy]], and their tombs were honoured in like manner as those of the martyrs. Since the witness of their lives was not as unequivocal as that of the martyrs, they were venerated publicly only with the approval by the local [[bishop]]. This process is often referred to as &quot;local canonization&quot;.{{refn|For the history of such canonization, see Kemp.{{sfnp|Kemp|1948}}}}

This approval was required even for veneration of a reputed martyr. In his history of the [[Donatism|Donatist]] heresy, [[Saint Optatus]] recounts that at [[Carthage]] a Catholic matron, named Lucilla, incurred the censures of the Church for having kissed the [[relic]]s of a reputed martyr whose claims to martyrdom had not been juridically proved. And Saint [[Cyprian]] (died 258) recommended that the utmost diligence be observed in investigating the claims of those who were said to have died for the faith. All the circumstances accompanying the martyrdom were to be inquired into; the faith of those who suffered, and the motives that animated them were to be rigorously examined, in order to prevent the recognition of undeserving persons. Evidence was sought from the court records of the trials or from people who had been present at the trials.
 
[[Augustine of Hippo]] (died 430) tells of the procedure which was followed in his day for the recognition of a martyr. The bishop of the diocese in which the martyrdom took place set up a canonical process for conducting the inquiry with the utmost severity. The acts of the process were sent either to the [[Metropolitan bishop|metropolitan]] or [[Primate (bishop)|primate]], who carefully examined the cause, and, after consultation with the [[suffragan]] bishops, declared whether the deceased was worthy of the name of 'martyr' and public veneration.

Though not &quot;canonizations&quot; in the narrow sense, acts of formal recognition, such as the erection of an [[altar]] over the saint's tomb or transferring the saint's relics to a church, were preceded by formal inquiries into the sanctity of the person's life and the miracles attributed to that person's intercession.

Such acts of recognition of a saint were authoritative, in the strict sense, only for the [[diocese]] or [[ecclesiastical province]] for which they were issued, but with the spread of the fame of a saint, were often accepted elsewhere also.

== Anglican Communion ==
{{main|Saints in Anglicanism}}
The [[Church of England]], the [[Mother Church]] of the [[Anglican Communion]], canonized [[Charles I of England|Charles I]] as a saint, in the [[Convocations of Canterbury and York]] of 1660.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mitchell2012&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Mitchell|first=Jolyon|title=Martyrdom: A Very Short Introduction|date=29 November 2012|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=9780191642449|page=99|quote=In 1660 the convocations of Canterbury and York canonized King Charles.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Catholic Church==

=== Nature ===
In the [[Catholic Church]], both [[Latin Church|Latin]] and [[Eastern Catholic Churches|constituent Eastern]] churches, the act of canonization is reserved to the [[Apostolic See]] and occurs at the conclusion of a long process requiring extensive proof that the candidate for canonization lived and died in such an exemplary and holy way that they are worthy to be recognized as a saint. The Church's official recognition of sanctity implies that the person is now in [[Heaven]] and that they may be publicly invoked and mentioned officially in the [[liturgy]] of the Church, including in the ''[[Litany of the Saints]]''.

In the Catholic Church, canonization is a decree that allows universal veneration of the saint in the [[liturgy]]{{Citation needed span|text= of the [[Roman Rite]]|date=February 2020|reason=Is not veneration in any liturgy throughout the entire Roman Catholic Church?}}. For permission to venerate merely locally, only [[beatification]] is needed.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Beatification, in the present discipline, differs from canonization in this: that the former implies (1) a locally restricted, not a universal, permission to venerate, which is (2) a mere permission, and no precept; while canonization implies a universal precept&quot; ([http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/02364b.htm Beccari, Camillo. &quot;Beatification and Canonization&quot;.] ''The Catholic Encyclopedia''. Vol. 2. New York, New York: Robert Appleton Company, 1907. Accessed 27 May 2009.).&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Procedure prior to reservation to the Apostolic See ===
[[File:Pintoricchio 018 detail.jpg|thumb|left|[[Pope Pius II]] canonizes [[Catherine of Siena]]]]

For several centuries the [[Bishop]]s, or in some places only the [[primate (bishop)|Primates]] and [[Patriarch]]s,&lt;ref&gt;August., ''Brevic. Collat. cum Donatistis'', III, 13, no. 25 in ''PL'', XLIII, 628.&lt;/ref&gt; could grant martyrs and confessors public ecclesiastical honor; such honor, however, was always decreed only for the local territory of which the grantors had jurisdiction. Only acceptance of the ''cultus'' by the [[Pope]] made the ''cultus'' universal, because he alone can rule the universal [[Catholic Church]].&lt;ref&gt;Gonzalez Tellez, ''Comm. Perpet. in singulos textus libr. Decr.'', III, xlv, in Cap. 1, ''De reliquiis et vener. Sanct.''&lt;/ref&gt; Abuses, however, crept into this discipline, due as well to indiscretions of popular fervor as to the negligence of some bishops in inquiring into the lives of those whom they permitted to be honoured as saints.

In the Medieval West, the [[Apostolic See]] was asked to intervene in the question of canonizations so as to ensure more authoritative decisions. The canonization of [[Saint Udalric, Bishop of Augsburg]] by [[Pope John XV]] in 993 was the first undoubted example of papal canonization of a saint from outside of [[Rome]] being declared worthy of liturgical veneration for the entire church. Some historians maintain further that the first papal canonization was of [[St. Swibert]] by [[Pope Leo III]] in 804.

Thereafter, recourse to the judgment of the [[Pope]] was had more frequently. Toward the end of the eleventh century the [[Pope]]s began asserting their exclusive right to authorize the veneration of a saint against the older rights of bishops to do so for their dioceses and regions. Popes therefore decreed that the virtues and miracles of persons proposed for public veneration should be examined in councils, more specifically in general councils. [[Pope Urban II]], [[Pope Calixtus II]], and [[Pope Eugene III]] conformed to this discipline.

=== Exclusive reservation to the Apostolic See ===
[[Hugh de Boves]], [[Archbishop of Rouen]], canonized [[Walter of Pontoise]], or St. Gaultier, in 1153, the final saint in [[Western Europe]] to be canonized by an authority other than the [[Pope]]:&lt;ref name = &quot;ofsnlu&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://archive.org/stream/dictionaryofchri01smituoft/dictionaryofchri01smituoft_djvu.txt|title=William Smith and Samuel Cheetham, ''A Dictionary of Christian Antiquities'' (Murray, 1875), p. 283.|publisher=|accessdate=4 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.saint-mike.org/library/papal_library/AlexanderIII/biography.html|title=Pope Alexander III|accessdate=4 October 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131015044654/http://www.saint-mike.org/library/papal_library/alexanderiii/biography.html#|archive-date=15 October 2013|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;The last case of canonization by a metropolitan is said to have been that of [[Walter of Pontoise|St. Gaultier]], or Gaucher, [A]bbot of Pontoise, by the Archbishop of Rouen. A decree of [[Pope Alexander III]] [in] 1170 gave the prerogative to the [P]ope thenceforth, so far as the Western Church was concerned.&quot;&lt;ref name = &quot;ofsnlu&quot;/&gt; In a decretal of 1173, [[Pope Alexander III]] reprimanded some bishops for permitting veneration of a man who was merely killed while intoxicated, prohibited veneration of the man, and most significantly decreed that &quot;you shall not therefore presume to honor him in the future; for, even if miracles were worked through him, it is not lawful for you to venerate him as a saint without the authority of the Catholic Church.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Pope Gregory IX, ''Decretales'', 3, &quot;De reliquiis et veneratione sanctorum&quot;. It is alternatively quoted as follows: &quot;For the future you will not presume to pay him reverence, as, even though miracles were worked through him, it would not allow you to revere him as a saint unless with the authority of the Roman Church&quot;. (C. 1, tit. cit., X, III, xlv.)&lt;/ref&gt; Theologians disagree as to the full import of the decretal of [[Pope Alexander III]]: either a new law was instituted,&lt;ref&gt;St. Robert Bellarmine, ''De Eccles. Triumph.'', I, 8.&lt;/ref&gt; in which case the [[Pope]] then for the first time reserved the right of beatification to himself, or an existing law was confirmed.

However, the procedure initiated by the decretal of [[Pope Alexander III]] was confirmed by a [[papal bull|bull]] of [[Pope Innocent III]] issued on the occasion of the canonization of [[Cunigunde of Luxembourg]] in 1200. The [[Papal bull|bull]] of [[Pope Innocent III]] resulted in increasingly elaborate inquiries to the [[Apostolic See]] concerning canonizations. Because the decretal of [[Pope Alexander III]] did not end all controversy and some bishops did not obey it in so far as it regarded beatification, the right of which they had certainly possessed hitherto, [[Pope Urban VIII]] issued the Apostolic letter ''Caelestis Hierusalem cives'' of 5 July 1634 that exclusively reserved to the [[Apostolic See]] both its immemorial right of canonization and that of [[beatification]]. He further regulated both of these acts by issuing his ''Decreta servanda in beatificatione et canonizatione Sanctorum'' on 12 March 1642.

=== Procedure from 1734 to 1738 to 1983 ===
In his ''De Servorum Dei beatificatione et de Beatorum canonizatione'' of five volumes the eminent canonist Prospero Lambertini (1675–1758), who later became [[Pope Benedict XIV]], elaborated on the procedural norms of [[Pope Urban VIII]]'s Apostolic letter ''Caelestis Hierusalem cives'' of 1634 and ''Decreta servanda in beatificatione et canonizatione Sanctorum'' of 1642, and on the conventional practice of the time. His work published from 1734 to 1738 governed the proceedings until 1917. The article &quot;[[Beatification and canonization process in 1914]]&quot; describes the procedures followed until the promulgation of the ''Codex'' of 1917. The substance of ''De Servorum Dei beatifιcatione et de Beatorum canonizatione'' was incorporated into the ''[[Code of Canon Law|Codex Iuris Canonici]]'' (''Code of Canon Law'') of 1917,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.strasbourginstitute.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Musoni-The-Catholic-Canonization-Process.pdf Aimable Musoni, &quot;Saints without Borders&quot;, pp. 9–10.]&lt;/ref&gt; which governed until the promulgation of the revised ''[[Code of Canon Law|Codex Iuris Canonici]]'' in 1983 by [[Pope John Paul II]]. Prior to promulgation of the revised ''Codex'' in 1983, [[Pope Paul VI|Pope St. Paul VI]] initiated a simplification of the procedures.

=== Since 1983 ===
The [[Apostolic constitution]] ''Divinus Perfectionis Magister'' of [[Pope John Paul II]] of 25 January 1983&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_jp-ii_apc_25011983_divinus-perfectionis-magister_en.html|title=DIVINUS PERFECTIONIS MAGISTER|publisher=|accessdate=4 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the norms issued by the [[Congregation for the Causes of Saints]] on 7 February 1983 to implement the constitution in dioceses, continued the simplification of the process initiated by [[Pope Paul VI]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_jp-blerpii_apc_25011983_divinus-perfectionis-magister_en.html|title=Divinus Perfectionis Magister|publisher=|accessdate=4 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Contrary to popular belief, the reforms did not eliminate the office of the Promoter of the Faith (Latin: ''Promotor Fidei''), popularly known as the &quot;[[Devil's advocate]]&quot;, whose office is to question the material presented in favor of canonization. The reforms were intended to reduce the adversarial nature of the process. In November 2012 [[Pope Benedict XVI]] appointed Monsignor Carmello Pellegrino as Promoter of the Faith.&lt;ref&gt;[https://translate.google.com/translate?hl=en&amp;sl=it&amp;u=http://bari.repubblica.it/cronaca/2012/11/05/news/l_avvocato_del_diavolo_pugliese_tester_le_virt_degli_aspiranti_santi-45975067/&amp;prev=search &quot;Devil's Advocate Is Puglia: 'It will test the virtues of aspiring saints'&quot;, ''la Repubblica'', 5 November 2012.]&lt;/ref&gt;

Candidates for canonization undergo the following process:

* &quot;'''Servant of God'''&quot; (&quot;'''Servus Dei'''&quot;): The process of canonization commences at the diocesan level. A [[bishop]] with jurisdiction, usually the bishop of the place where the candidate died or is buried, although another ordinary can be given this authority, gives permission to open an investigation into the virtues of the individual in response to a petition of members of the faithful, either actually or ''[[pro forma]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Pope John Paul II, [http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_jp-ii_apc_25011983_divinus-perfectionis-magister_en.html ''Divinus Perfectionis Magister''] (25 January 1983), Art. 1, Sec. 1.&lt;/ref&gt; This investigation usually commences no sooner than five years after the death of the person being investigated.&lt;ref&gt;Pietro Cardinal Palazzini, [http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/csaints/documents/rc_con_csaints_doc_07021983_norme_en.html ''Norms to be observed in inquiries made by bishops in the causes of saints''], 1983 {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061022065149/http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/csaints/documents/rc_con_csaints_doc_07021983_norme_en.html |date=22 October 2006 }}, §9(a).&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Pope]], ''qua'' Bishop of Rome, may also open a process and has the authority to waive the waiting period of five years, e. g., as was done for [[St. Teresa of Calcutta]] by [[Pope John Paul II]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/news_services/liturgy/saints/ns_lit_doc_20031019_madre-teresa_en.html ''Mother Teresa of Calcutta (1910–1997), Biography''], Office of Papal Liturgical Celebrations, Internet Office of the Holy See&lt;/ref&gt; and for [[Lúcia Santos]] and for [[Pope John Paul II]] himself by [[Pope Benedict XVI]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.zenit.org/article-21764?l=english|title=Sister Lucia's Beatification Process to Begin|work=ZENIT – The World Seen from Rome|accessdate=4 October 2014|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120927020314/http://www.zenit.org/article-21764?l=english|archivedate=27 September 2012|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Cardinal (Catholicism)|Cardinal]] [[José Saraiva Martins]], [[Claretians|CMF]], [http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/csaints/documents/rc_con_csaints_doc_20050509_rescritto-gpii_en.html ''Response of His Holiness Benedict XVI for the Examination of the Cause for Beatification and Canonization of the Servant of God John Paul II''], 2005 {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090105024819/http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/csaints/documents/rc_con_csaints_doc_20050509_rescritto-gpii_en.html |date=5 January 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Normally, an association to promote the cause of the candidate is instituted, an exhaustive search of the candidate's writings, speeches, and sermons is undertaken, a detailed biography is written, and eyewitness accounts are collected. When sufficient evidence has been collected, the local bishop presents the investigation of the candidate, who is titled &quot;'''Servant of God'''&quot; ([[Latin]]: &quot;'''Servus Dei'''&quot;), to the [[Congregation for the Causes of the Saints]] of the [[Roman Curia]], where the cause is assigned a [[postulator]], whose office is to collect further evidence of the life of the Servant of God. Religious orders that regularly deal with the Congregation often designate their own Postulator General. At some time, permission is then granted for the body of the Servant of God to be exhumed and examined. A certification &quot;''non-cultus''&quot; is made that no superstitious or heretical worship, or improper cult of the Servant of God or his tomb has emerged, and relics are taken and preserved.
* &quot;'''Venerable'''&quot; (&quot;'''Venerabilis'''&quot;; abbreviated &quot;Ven.&quot;) or &quot;'''Heroic in Virtue'''&quot;: When sufficient evidence has been collected, the Congregation recommends to the [[Pope]] that he proclaim the [[heroic virtue]] of the Servant of God; that is, that the Servant of God exercised ''to a heroic degree'' the [[theological virtues]] of faith, hope, and charity and the [[cardinal virtues]] of prudence, justice, fortitude, and temperance. From this time the one said to be &quot;heroic in virtue&quot; is entitled &quot;'''[[Venerable]]'''&quot; ([[Latin]]: &quot;'''Venerabilis'''&quot;). A Venerable does not yet have a [[feast day]], permission to erect churches in his honor has not yet been granted, and the Church does not yet issue a statement on his probable or certain presence in [[Heaven]], but [[prayer card]]s and other materials may be printed to encourage the faithful to pray for a [[miracle]] wrought by his intercession as a sign of God's will that the person be canonized.
* '''&quot;Blessed&quot;''' (&quot;'''Beatus'''&quot; or &quot;'''Beata'''&quot;; abbreviated &quot;Bl.&quot;): Beatification is a statement of the Church that it is &quot;worthy of belief&quot; that the Venerable is in [[Heaven]] and saved. Attaining this grade depends on whether the Venerable is a [[martyr]]:
** For a martyr, the [[Pope]] has only to make a declaration of martyrdom, which is a certification that the Venerable gave his life voluntarily as a witness of the Faith or in an [[act of heroic charity]] for others.
** For a non-martyr, all of them being denominated &quot;confessors&quot; because they &quot;confessed&quot;, i. e., bore witness to the Faith by how they lived, proof is required of the occurrence of a [[miracle]] through the intercession of the Venerable; that is, that God granted a sign that the person is enjoying the [[Beatific Vision]] by performing a miracle for which the Venerable interceded. Presently, these miracles are almost always miraculous cures of infirmity, because these are the easiest to judge given the Church's evidentiary requirements for miracles; e. g., a patient was sick with an illness for which no cure was known; prayers were directed to the Venerable; the patient was cured; the cure was spontaneous, instantaneous, complete, and enduring; and physicians cannot discover any natural explanation for the cure.

The satisfaction of the applicable conditions permits [[beatification]], which then bestows on the Venerable the title of &quot;'''Blessed'''&quot; ([[Latin]]: &quot;'''Beatus'''&quot; or &quot;'''Beata'''&quot;). A [[feast day]] will be designated, but its observance is ordinarily only permitted for the Blessed's home [[diocese]], to specific locations associated with them, or to the churches or houses of the Blessed's religious order if they belonged to one. Parishes may not normally be named in honor of beati.

* '''&quot;Saint&quot;''' (&quot;'''Sanctus'''&quot; or &quot;'''Sancta'''&quot;; abbreviated &quot;St.&quot; or &quot;S.&quot;): To be canonized as a saint, ordinarily at least two miracles must have been performed through the intercession of the Blessed after their death, but for beati confessors, i. e., beati who were not declared martyrs, only one miracle is required, ordinarily being additional to that upon which beatification was premised. Very rarely, a pope may waive the requirement for a second miracle after beatification if they, the [[College of Cardinals|Sacred College of Cardinals]], and the [[Congregation for the Causes of Saints]] all agree that the Blessed lived a life of great merit proven by certain actions. This extraordinary procedure was used in [[Pope Francis]]' canonization of [[Pope John XXIII]], who convoked the first part of the [[Second Vatican Council]].

Canonization is a statement of the Church that the person certainly enjoys the [[Beatific Vision]] of [[Heaven]]. The title of &quot;'''Saint'''&quot; ([[Latin]]: &quot;'''Sanctus'''&quot; or &quot;'''Sancta'''&quot;) is then proper, reflecting that the Saint is a refulgence of the holiness (''sanctitas'') of God Himself, which alone comes from God's gift. The Saint is assigned a [[feast day]] which ''may'' be celebrated anywhere in the universal Church, although it is not necessarily added to the [[General Roman Calendar]] or local calendars as an &quot;obligatory&quot; feast; parish churches may be erected in his honor; and the faithful may freely celebrate and honor the Saint.

Although recognition of sainthood by the [[Pope]] does not directly concern a fact of [[Divine revelation]], nonetheless it must be &quot;definitively held&quot; by the faithful as ''infallible'' pursuant to, at the least, the [[Infallibility of the Church|Universal Magisterium of the Church]], because it is a truth related to revelation by historical necessity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ewtn.com/library/CURIA/CDFADTU.HTM Doctrinal Commentary on the Concluding Formula of the ''Professio Fidei''], by Cardinal Joseph Ratzinger (later [[Pope Benedict XVI]]), Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/02364b.htm &quot;Beatification and Canonization&quot;], ''The Catholic Encyclopedia'', Vol. 2. New York, New York: Robert Appleton Company, 1907. P. 366.&lt;/ref&gt;

Regarding the [[Eastern Catholic Churches]], individual ''[[sui juris]]'' churches have the right to &quot;glorify&quot; saints for their own jurisdictions, though this has rarely happened.

=== Equipollent canonization ===

Popes have several times permitted to the universal Church, without executing the ordinary judicial process of canonization described above, the veneration as a saint, the &quot;''[[Cult (religious practice)|cultus]]''&quot; of one long venerated as such locally. This act of a pope is denominated &quot;equipollent&quot; or &quot;equivalent canonization&quot; and &quot;confirmation of ''cultus''&quot;. According to the rules [[Pope Benedict XIV]] (''regnat'' 17 August 1740 – 3 May 1758) instituted, there are three conditions for an equipollent canonization: (1) existence of an ancient ''cultus'' of the person, (2) a general and constant attestation to the virtues or martyrdom of the person by credible historians, and (3) uninterrupted fame of the person as a worker of miracles.

As examples, prior to his pontificate, of this mode of canonization, [[Pope Benedict XIV]] himself enumerated the equipollent canonizations of Saints:
* [[Romuald]] - 9 July 1595
* [[Norbert]]- 7 September 1621
* [[Bruno of Cologne|Bruno]] - 6 October 1623
* [[Peter Nolasco]] - 20 October 1655
* [[Raymond Nonnatus]] - 10 March 1681
* [[Stephen of Hungary|King Stephen of Hungary]] - 28 November 1686
* [[Saint Margaret of Scotland|Queen Margaret of Scotland]] - 15 September 1691
* [[John of Matha]] and [[Felix of Valois]] - 19 March 1694
* [[Pope Gregory VII]] - 25 September 1728
* [[Wenceslaus I, Duke of Bohemia|Duke Wenceslaus of Bohemia]] - 14 March 1729
* [[Gertrude of Helfta]] - 20 July 1738.

Later equipollent canonizations include those of Saints:
* [[Peter Damian]] - 1 October 1828
* [[Cyril and Methodius]] - 30 September 1880
* [[Cyril of Alexandria]], [[Cyril of Jerusalem]], [[Justin Martyr]] and [[Augustine of Canterbury]] - 28 July 1882
* [[John of Damascus]] and [[Sylvester Gozzolini]] - 29 August 1890
* [[Bede the Venerable]] - 25 May 1899
* [[Boniface]] - 4 May 1919
* [[Ephrem the Syrian]] - 5 October 1920
* [[Albert the Great]] - 15 December 1931
* [[John Fisher]] and [[Thomas More]] - 19 May 1935
* [[Margaret of Hungary (saint)|Margaret of Hungary]] - 19 November 1943
* [[Gregorio Barbarigo]] - 26 May 1960
* [[John of Ávila]] - 31 May 1970
* [[Nikola Tavelić]] and his three companion martyrs - 21 June 1970
* [[Meinhard of Livonia]] - 1993
* [[Marko Krizin]], [[István Pongrácz]], and [[Melchior Grodziecki]] - 2 July 1995
* [[Hildegard of Bingen]] - 10 May 2012

[[Pope Francis]] added Saints:
* [[Angela of Foligno]]&lt;ref&gt;Angelo Amato, &quot;La canonizzazione equipollente della mistica Angela da Foligno&quot; in ''L'Osservatore Romano'' (12 October 2013).&lt;/ref&gt; - 9 October 2013
* [[Peter Faber]] - 17 December 2013
* [[José de Anchieta]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://latino.foxnews.com/latino/news/2014/04/03/pope-canonizes-jose-de-anchieta-known-as-brazil-apostle|title=Pope Canonizes Jose de Anchieta, Known as Brazil's Apostle|work=Fox News Latino|accessdate=4 October 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141006204826/http://latino.foxnews.com/latino/news/2014/04/03/pope-canonizes-jose-de-anchieta-known-as-brazil-apostle/|archive-date=6 October 2014|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Marie of the Incarnation (Ursuline)|Marie of the Incarnation]], and [[François de Laval|Francis-Xavier de Montmorency-Laval]] - 3 April 2014&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ewtn.com/library/mary/canonize.htm|title=P. E. Hallett, &quot;The Canonization of Saints&quot;|publisher=|accessdate=4 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catholicpamphlets.net/pamphlets/BEATIFICATION%20AND%20CANONISATION.pdf J. R. MacMahon, &quot;Beatification and Canonisation&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Bartholomew of Braga]] - 5 July 2019

== Eastern Orthodox Church&lt;!--linked from 'Glorification'--&gt; ==
[[File:Пиотровский. батакская резня. 1889 год.jpeg|thumb|The Turkish [[Batak massacre|atrocities in Bulgaria]] (1876). On 3 April 2011, Batak massacre victims were canonized as saints.]]
[[File:Smyrna-massacre greeks-killed line.jpg|thumb|On 4 November 1992, the [[Holy Synod]] of the [[Church of Greece]] unanimously declared Christians that were tortured and massacred by the Turks in the [[Great fire of Smyrna]] in 1922 as saints.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.triglia.gr/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=26&amp;Itemid=39+%CE%91%CE%B3%CE%B9%CE%BF%CF%82+%CE%A7%CF%81%CF%85%CF%83%CE%BF%CF%83%CF%84%CE%BF%CE%BC%CE%BF%CF%82+%CE%A3%CE%BC%CE%B7%CF%81%CE%BD%CE%B7%CF%82&amp;ct=clnk Αγ. Χρυσόστομος Σμύρνης] {{Webarchive|url=https://archive.is/20110721083437/http://www.triglia.gr/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=26&amp;Itemid=39+%CE%91%CE%B3%CE%B9%CE%BF%CF%82+%CE%A7%CF%81%CF%85%CF%83%CE%BF%CF%83%CF%84%CE%BF%CE%BC%CE%BF%CF%82+%CE%A3%CE%BC%CE%B7%CF%81%CE%BD%CE%B7%CF%82&amp;ct=clnk |date=21 July 2011 }}.'' Municipality of [[Triglia]]. Retrieved: 7 September 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{in lang|el}} Κων/τίνος Β. Χιώλος. ''&quot;[http://www.serrelib.gr/arthra.php?id=25 Ο μαρτυρικός θάνατος του Μητροπολίτου Σμύρνης] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170912215241/http://www.serrelib.gr/arthra.php?id=25 |date=12 September 2017 }}&quot;''. Δημοσια Κεντρικη Βιβλιοθηκη Σερρων. Τετάρτη, 13 Σεπτεμβρίου 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The following terms are used for canonization by the [[autocephalous]] [[National polity|national]] [[Orthodox Church]]es: канонизация&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pravmir.ru/pochemu-byl-kanonizirovan-nikolaj-vtoroj/ &quot;Почему был канонизирован Николай Второй?&quot; by [[Protodeacon]] [[Andrey Kuraev]] at Pravmir.ru (17 July 2009)]&lt;/ref&gt; or прославление&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pravmir.ru/proslavlenie-svyatyx-eto-ne-delo-uzkogo-kruga-specialistov-eto-delo-vsej-cerkvi/ &quot;Прославление святых – это не дело узкого круга специалистов, это дело всей Церкви&quot; by Julija Birjukova at Pravmir.ru (9 Dec. 2013)]&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;[[Glorification#Eastern Orthodox Church|glorification]]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fatheralexander.org/booklets/english/glorification_saints.htm &quot;On the Glorification of Saints&quot;] by [[Protopresbyter]] [[Michael Pomazansky]]&lt;/ref&gt; ([[Russian Orthodox Church]]), კანონიზაცია ''kanonizats’ia'' ([[Georgian Orthodox Church]]), канонизација ([[Serbian Orthodox Church]]), ''canonizare'' ([[Romanian Orthodox Church]]), and Канонизация ([[Bulgarian Orthodox Church]]). The following terms are used for canonization by other [[autocephalous]] [[Orthodox Church]]es: αγιοκατάταξη&lt;ref&gt;[[Georgios Babiniotis]]. ''[[Dictionary of Modern Greek]]'', Athens: Lexicology Centre, 1998, p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt; ([[Katharevousa]]: ἁγιοκατάταξις) ''agiokatataxi/agiokatataxis'', &quot;ranking among saints&quot; ([[Ecumenical Patriarchate of Constantinople]], [[Church of Cyprus]], [[Church of Greece]]), ''kanonizim'' ([[Albanian Orthodox Church]]), ''kanonizacja'' ([[Polish Orthodox Church]]), and ''kanonizace/kanonizácia'' ([[Czech and Slovak Orthodox Church]]).

The [[Orthodox Church in America]], an Eastern Orthodox Church partly recognized as autocephalous, uses the term &quot;glorification&quot; for granting official recognition to someone as a saint—see [[Glorification#Eastern Orthodox Church|glorification]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oca.org/FS.NA-Document.asp?ID=83 &quot;The Glorification of Saints in the Orthodox Church&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160408161218/http://oca.org/FS.NA-Document.asp?ID=83 |date=8 April 2016 }} by Fr. Joseph Frawley&lt;/ref&gt;

== Oriental Orthodox Church ==
Within the [[Armenian Apostolic Church]], part of [[Oriental Orthodoxy]], there had been discussions since the 1980s about canonizing the victims of the [[Armenian Genocide]].&lt;ref&gt;Roberta R. Ervine, ''Worship Traditions in Armenia and the Neighboring Christian East'', St Vladimir's Seminary Press, 2006, p. 346 n. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; On April 23, 2015, all of the victims of the genocide were canonized.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Davlashyan |first=Naira |url=https://news.yahoo.com/armenian-church-canonise-1-5-million-genocide-victims-075841925.html |title=Armenian Church makes saints of 1.5&amp;nbsp;million genocide victims – Yahoo News |publisher=News.yahoo.com |date= |accessdate=2015-04-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.panarmenian.net/eng/news/191101/ |title=Armenian Genocide victims canonized in Holy Etchmiadzin |publisher=Panarmenian.Net |date= |accessdate=2015-04-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.armenianow.com/genocide/62740/armenia_genocide_martyrs_victims_canonization_church_echmiadzin |title=Canonized: Armenian Church proclaims collective martyrdom of Genocide victims – Genocide |publisher=ArmeniaNow.com |date= |accessdate=2015-04-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== United Methodist Church ==
The [[General Conference (United Methodist Church)|General Conference]] of the [[United Methodist Church]] has formally declared individuals ''[[Christian martyr|martyrs]]'', including [[Dietrich Bonhoeffer]] (in 2008) and [[Martin Luther King Jr.]] (in 2012).&lt;ref name=&quot;Hodges2018&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.dallasnews.com/life/faith/2008/06/18/dietrich-bonhoeffer-first-mart|title=Dietrich Bonhoeffer first martyr officially recognized by United Methodists|last=Hodges|first=Sam|year=2008|newspaper=[[Dallas News]]|language=English|accessdate=4 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.umc.org/news-and-media/blogs-commentaries/post/united-methodists-declare-mlk-jr.-a-modern-day-martyr|title=United Methodists declare MLK Jr. a modern-day martyr|last=Mulenga|first=Maidstone|date=1 May 2012|publisher=United Methodist Church|language=English|accessdate=4 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Universal Life Church ==
The [[Universal Life Church]] canonizes Saints for demonstrating three values:

#Faith
#Hope
#Charity

A certificate is issued following a donation if the application for Sainthood is accepted and is then entered into the church's official records.&lt;ref name=&quot;ULC01&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Sainthood Certificate - Official ULC Store |url=https://ulchqcom.ipower.com/osCommerce/catalog/product_info.php?cPath=1&amp;products_id=39 |website=ulchqcom.ipower.com |publisher=Universal Life Church |accessdate=30 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ULC02&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=What Are the Steps to Becoming a Saint? |url=https://www.ulc.org/ulc-blog/what-are-the-steps-to-becoming-a-saint |website=www.ulc.org |accessdate=30 January 2020 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Saints}}
* [[Beatification]]
* [[Devil's advocate]]
* [[Glorification]]
* [[List of canonizations]]
* [[List of saints|List of Christian saints after A.D. 450]] (incomplete list)
* [[List of early Christian saints|List of Christian saints before A.D. 450]]
* [[Litany of the Saints]]

== Notes ==
{{Reflist}}

== References ==
* {{citation |first=Eric Waldram |last=Kemp |title=Canonization and Authority in the Western Church |location=Oxford |publisher=Oxford University Press |date=1948 }}

== External links ==
{{Wiktionary}}
* {{wikisource-inline|list=
** {{cite EB9 |mode=cs2 |wstitle=Canonization |volume=5  |ref={{harvid|''EB''|1878}} |pages=22–23 |noicon=x |short=x}}
** {{cite EB1911 |mode=cs2 |last=Delehaye |first=Hippolyte |authorlink=Hippolyte Delehaye  |wstitle=Canonization |volume=5 |ref={{harvid|''EB''|1911}} |pages=192–193 |noicon=x |short=x}}
** {{CathEncy |last=Beccari |first=Camillo |wstitle=Beatification and Canonization |volume=2 |noicon=x |short=x}}
}}

===Catholic Church===
* [http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_jp-ii_apc_25011983_divinus-perfectionis-magister_en.html ''Divinus Perfectionis Magister''] – Apostolic Constitution of Pope John Paul II (English)
* [http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/csaints/index.htm Congregation for the Causes of Saints] – Vatican Website
* [http://friarsminor.org/xvii4-9.html Historical Sketch of Canonization] – Friarsminor.org

{{canonization}}
{{Saints}}

{{authority control}}

[[Category:Canonization| ]]
[[Category:Saints days]]
[[Category:Christian terminology]]
[[Category:Posthumous recognitions]]
[[Category:Christian behaviour and experience]]
[[Category:Christian saints]]
[[Category:Canon law]]</text>
      <sha1>5ai28gmkltpio73ze0amog6b88mjors</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
