  <page>
    <title>Cathode-ray tube</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6014</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942812286</id>
      <parentid>942809957</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T00:20:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Dating maintenance tags: {{Cn}}</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2013}}
[[File:Cathode ray Tube.PNG|right|thumb|300px|Cathode ray tube using electromagnetic focus and deflection]]
[[File:Oscilloscopic tube.jpg|thumb|A cathode-ray tube as found in an [[oscilloscope]] ]]
[[File:CRT color enhanced.png|right|thumb|250px|Cutaway rendering of a color CRT:&lt;br/&gt;'''1.'''&amp;nbsp;Three electron emitters (for red, green, and blue phosphor dots)&lt;br/&gt;'''2.'''&amp;nbsp;Electron beams&lt;br/&gt;'''3.'''&amp;nbsp;Focusing coils&lt;br/&gt;'''4.'''&amp;nbsp;Deflection coils&lt;br/&gt;'''5.'''&amp;nbsp;Connection for final anodes (referred to as the &quot;ultor&quot; in some receiving tube manuals)&lt;br/&gt;'''6.'''&amp;nbsp;Mask for separating beams for red, green, and blue part of the displayed image&lt;br/&gt;'''7.'''&amp;nbsp;Phosphor layer (screen)with red, green, and blue zones&lt;br/&gt;'''8.'''&amp;nbsp;Close-up of the phosphor-coated inner side of the screen]]

The '''cathode-ray tube''' ('''CRT''') is a [[vacuum tube]] that contains one or more [[electron gun]]s and a [[phosphorescent]] screen and is used to display images.&lt;ref name=crthistory&gt;{{cite web |url=http://inventors.about.com/od/cstartinventions/a/CathodeRayTube.htm |title=History of the Cathode Ray Tube |accessdate=4 October 2009 |work=About.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; It modulates, accelerates, and deflects electron beam(s) onto the screen to create the images. The images may represent electrical [[waveform]]s ([[oscilloscope]]), pictures ([[television]], [[computer monitor]]), [[radar]] targets, or other phenomena. CRTs have also been [[Williams tube|used as memory devices]], in which case the visible light emitted from the fluorescent material (if any) is not intended to have significant meaning to a visual observer (though the visible pattern on the tube face may cryptically represent the stored data).

In television sets and computer monitors, the entire front area of the tube is scanned repetitively and systematically in a fixed pattern called a [[raster scan|raster]]. In color devices, an image is produced by controlling the intensity of each of the three [[electron beams]], one for each additive primary color (red, green, and blue) with a [[video signal]] as a reference.&lt;ref name=workings&gt;{{cite web |title='How Computer Monitors Work'|url=http://computer.howstuffworks.com/monitor7.htm |accessdate=4 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In all modern CRT monitors and televisions, the beams are bent by ''[[Deflection yoke|magnetic deflection]]'', a varying magnetic field generated by coils and driven by electronic circuits around the neck of the tube, although [[electrostatic deflection]] is commonly used in [[oscilloscope]]s, a type of [[electronic test instrument]].&lt;ref name=workings/&gt;
[[File:Crt14.jpg|thumb|right|250px|A 14-inch cathode-ray tube showing its deflection coils and electron guns]]
[[File:Television set from the early 1950s.jpg|thumb|right|Typical 1950s United States [[monochrome]] television set]]
[[File:CRTslowmotion PetesDragon.jpg|thumb|A CRT [[television]] filmed in slow motion. The line of light is being drawn from left to right in a [[raster scan|raster]] pattern]]
[[File:SinclairFTV1frontPCB6.jpg|thumb|A flat CRT assembly inside a 1984 [[TV80|Sinclair FTV1 pocket TV]] ]]
[[File:Egun.jpg|thumb|Electron gun]]

A CRT is constructed from a glass envelope which is large, deep (i.e., long from front screen face to rear end), slightly heavy, and very durable.  The interior of a CRT is [[hard vacuum|evacuated]] to approximately {{Convert|0.01|Pa|atm}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://wps.aw.com/wps/media/objects/877/898586/topics/topic07.pdf Topic 7 |The Cathode-Ray Tube] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171215132600/http://wps.aw.com/wps/media/objects/877/898586/topics/topic07.pdf |date=15 December 2017 }}. aw.com. 2003-08-01&lt;!--The interior of the tube is a very good vacuum, with a pressure of around 0.01 Pa (10^−7 atm) or less. At any greater pressure, collisions of electrons with air molecules would scatter the electron beam excessively.--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; to {{Convert|133|nPa|atm}},&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.repairfaq.org/sam/lasercva.htm repairfaq.org – Sam's Laser FAQ – Vacuum Technology for Home-Built Gas Lasers] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121009185307/http://repairfaq.org/sam/lasercva.htm|date=9 October 2012}}. repairfaq.org. 2012-08-02&lt;!--The actual vacuum inside the CRT of a computer monitor or TV is probably at 10^-9 Torr or better.--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; evacuation being necessary to facilitate the free flight of electrons from the gun(s) to the tube's face. The fact that it is evacuated makes handling an intact CRT potentially dangerous due to the risk of breaking the tube and causing a violent [[implosion (mechanical process)|implosion]] that can hurl shards of glass at great velocity.  As a matter of safety, the face is typically made of thick [[lead glass]] so as to be highly shatter-resistant and to block most [[X-ray]] emissions, particularly if the CRT is used in a consumer product.

Since the late 2000s, CRTs have been largely superseded by newer &quot;[[flat panel]]&quot; display technologies such as [[liquid-crystal display|LCD]], [[plasma display]], and [[OLED]] displays. In the case of LCD and OLED displays, initial picture quality when they were first adapted wasn’t as good. However, as the technology has developed, these displays now provide images of higher quality than CRT, with lower manufacturing costs and power consumption, as well as significantly less weight and bulk. Flat-panel displays can also be made in very large sizes; whereas {{Convert|45|in|cm|abbr=on}} was about the largest size of a CRT television, flat panels are available in {{Convert|90|in|cm|abbr=on}} and even larger sizes.

==History==
[[File:Braun cathode ray tube.jpg|thumb|upright=1.6|Braun's original cold-cathode CRT, 1897]]

Cathode rays were discovered by [[Julius Plücker]] and [[Johann Wilhelm Hittorf]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
 | first =Andre
 | last =Martin
 | contribution =Cathode Ray Tubes for Industrial and Military Applications
 | editor-last =Hawkes
 | editor-first =Peter
 | title =Advances in Electronics and Electron Physics, Volume 67
 | publisher =Academic Press
 | year =1986
 | isbn =9780080577333
 | page =183
 | quote =&quot;Evidence for the existence of &quot;cathode-rays&quot; was first found by Plücker and Hittorf ...&quot;
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hittorf observed that some unknown rays were emitted from the [[cathode]] (negative electrode) which could cast shadows on the glowing wall of the tube, indicating the rays were traveling in straight lines. In 1890, [[Arthur Schuster]] demonstrated cathode rays could be deflected by [[electric field]]s, and [[William Crookes]] showed they could be deflected by magnetic fields. In 1897, [[J. J. Thomson]] succeeded in measuring the mass of cathode rays, showing that they consisted of negatively charged particles smaller than atoms, the first &quot;[[subatomic particle]]s&quot;, which were later named ''[[electron]]s''. The earliest version of the CRT was known as the &quot;Braun tube&quot;, invented by the German physicist [[Ferdinand Braun]] in 1897.&lt;ref&gt;Ferdinand Braun (1897) [http://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=wu.89048352892;view=1up;seq=568 &quot;Ueber ein Verfahren zur Demonstration und zum Studium des zeitlichen Verlaufs variabler Ströme&quot;] (On a process for the display and study of the course in time of variable currents), ''Annalen der Physik und Chemie'', 3rd series, '''60''': 552–559.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Cathode Ray Tube|year=2007|work=Medical Discoveries|publisher=Advameg, Inc.|url=http://www.discoveriesinmedicine.com/Bar-Cod/Cathode-Ray-Tube-CRT.html|accessdate=27 April 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was a [[cold cathode|cold-cathode]] [[diode]], a modification of the [[Crookes tube]] with a [[phosphor]]-coated screen.

The first cathode-ray tube to use a [[hot cathode]] was developed by [[John Bertrand Johnson|John B. Johnson]] (who gave his name to the term [[Johnson–Nyquist noise|Johnson noise]]) and Harry Weiner Weinhart of [[Western Electric]], and became a commercial product in 1922.{{cn|date=February 2020}}

In 1925, [[Kenjiro Takayanagi]] demonstrated a CRT television that received images with a 40-line resolution.&lt;ref name=&quot;nhk.or.jp&quot;&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20160101180643/http://www.nhk.or.jp/strl/aboutstrl/evolution-of-tv-en/p05/ ''Kenjiro Takayanagi: The Father of Japanese Television''], NHK (Japan Broadcasting Corporation), 2002, retrieved 2009-05-23.&lt;/ref&gt; By 1927, he improved the resolution to 100 lines, which was unrivaled until 1931.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=wQhlFaxDwrsC&amp;pg=PA220|title=High Above: The untold story of Astra, Europe's leading satellite company|first=Chris|last=Forrester|date=28 August 2011|publisher=Springer Science &amp; Business Media|via=Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 1928, he was the first to transmit human faces in half-tones on a CRT display.&lt;ref name=&quot;abramson&quot;&gt;Albert Abramson, ''Zworykin, Pioneer of Television'', University of Illinois Press, 1995, p. 231. {{ISBN|0-252-02104-5}}.&lt;/ref&gt; By 1935, he had invented an early all-electronic CRT television.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Popular Photography]]'', [https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=DJsbJq2_djkC&amp;pg=PA5 November 1990, page 5]&lt;/ref&gt;

It was named in 1929 by inventor [[Vladimir K. Zworykin]],&lt;ref&gt;Albert Abramson, ''Zworykin, Pioneer of Television'', University of Illinois Press, 1995, p. 84. {{ISBN|0-252-02104-5}}.&lt;/ref&gt; who was influenced by Takayanagi's earlier work.&lt;ref name=&quot;abramson&quot;/&gt; [[RCA]] was granted a trademark for the term (for its cathode-ray tube) in 1932; it voluntarily released the term to the public domain in 1950.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;RCA Surrenders Rights to Four Trade-Marks,&quot; Radio Age, October 1950, p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt;

The first commercially made electronic television sets with cathode-ray tubes were manufactured by [[Telefunken]] in Germany in 1934.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.earlytelevision.org/telefunken.html Telefunken], Early Electronic TV Gallery, Early Television Foundation.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tvhistory.tv/1934-35-Telefunken-FEIII.JPG 1934–35 Telefunken], Television History: The First 75 Years.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Flat panel display]]s dropped in price and started significantly displacing cathode-ray tubes in the 2000s, with LCD screens exceeding CRTs in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://graphics.thomsonreuters.com/10/04/GLB_TVTECH0410.gif |title=Archived copy |access-date=3 April 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131011135725/http://graphics.thomsonreuters.com/10/04/GLB_TVTECH0410.gif |archive-date=11 October 2013 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
The last known manufacturer of (in this case, recycled) CRTs ceased in 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.npr.org/sections/alltechconsidered/2016/08/15/489629491/saying-goodbye-to-old-technology-and-a-legendary-nyc-repair-shop|title=Saying Goodbye To Old Technology — And A Legendary NYC Repair Shop|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Oscilloscope CRTs==
[[File:Lissajous-Figur 1 zu 3 (Oszilloskop).jpg|thumb|An oscilloscope showing a [[Lissajous curve]]]]
In [[oscilloscope]] CRTs, [[electrostatic deflection]] is used, rather than the magnetic deflection commonly used with television and other large CRTs. The beam is deflected horizontally by applying an [[electric field]] between a pair of plates to its left and right, and vertically by applying an electric field to plates above and below. Televisions use magnetic rather than electrostatic deflection because the deflection plates obstruct the beam when the deflection angle is as large as is required for tubes that are relatively short for their size.

===Phosphor persistence===
Various [[phosphor]]s are available depending upon the needs of the measurement or display application. The brightness, color, and persistence of the illumination depends upon the type of phosphor used on the CRT screen. Phosphors are available with persistences ranging from less than one [[microsecond]] to several seconds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Doebelin |first= Ernest |title= Measurement Systems |publisher= McGraw Hill Professional |year= 2003 |page= 972 |url= https://books.google.com/?id=q1mOopLHnTEC&amp;pg=PA972 |isbn=978-0-07-292201-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; For visual observation of brief transient events, a long persistence phosphor may be desirable. For events which are fast and repetitive, or high frequency, a short-persistence phosphor is generally preferable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Shionoya |first= Shigeo |title= Phosphor handbook |publisher= CRC Press |year= 1999 |page= 499 |url= https://books.google.com/?id=lWlcJEDukRIC&amp;pg=PA499 |isbn=978-0-8493-7560-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Microchannel plate===
When displaying fast one-shot events, the electron beam must deflect very quickly, with few electrons impinging on the screen, leading to a faint or invisible image on the display. Oscilloscope CRTs designed for very fast signals can give a brighter display by passing the electron beam through a [[micro-channel plate]] just before it reaches the screen. Through the phenomenon of [[secondary emission]], this plate multiplies the number of electrons reaching the phosphor screen, giving a significant improvement in writing rate (brightness) and improved sensitivity and spot size as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Williams |first= Jim |title= Analog circuit design: art, science, and personalities |publisher= Newnes |year= 1991 |pages= 115–116 |url= https://books.google.com/?id=CFoEAP2lwLEC&amp;pg=PA115 |isbn= 978-0-7506-9640-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author1=Yen, William M. |author2=Shionoya, Shigeo |author3=Yamamoto, Hajime |title= Practical Applications of Phosphors |publisher= CRC Press |year= 2006 |page= 211 |url= https://books.google.com/?id=cKMSf0iRVSgC&amp;pg=PA211 |isbn=978-1-4200-4369-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Graticules===
Most oscilloscopes have a [[oscilloscope#Graticule|graticule]] as part of the visual display, to facilitate measurements. The graticule may be permanently marked inside the face of the CRT, or it may be a transparent external plate made of glass or [[acrylic glass|acrylic]] plastic. An internal graticule eliminates [[parallax error]], but cannot be changed to accommodate different types of measurements.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author1=Bakshi, U.A. |author2=Godse, A.P. |title= Electronic Devices And Circuits |publisher= Technical Publications |year= 2008 |page= 38 |url= https://books.google.com/?id=uJaQML8-MggC&amp;pg=PA38 |isbn=978-81-8431-332-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Oscilloscopes commonly provide a means for the graticule to be illuminated from the side, which improves its visibility.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Hickman |first= Ian |title= Oscilloscopes: how to use them, how they work |publisher= Newnes |year= 2001 |page= 47 |url= https://books.google.com/?id=O2oj04vbQqgC&amp;pg=PA47 |isbn=978-0-7506-4757-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Image storage tubes===
[[File:Tektronix 564 Analog Storage Oscilloscope.jpg|thumbnail|The Tektronix Type 564: First Mass Produced Analog Phosphor Storage Oscilloscope]]
These are found in ''[[analog television|analog]] phosphor storage oscilloscopes''. These are distinct from ''[[digital storage oscilloscope]]s'' which rely on solid state digital memory to store the image.

Where a single brief event is monitored by an oscilloscope, such an event will be displayed by a conventional tube only while it actually occurs. The use of a long persistence phosphor may allow the image to be observed after the event, but only for a few seconds at best. This limitation can be overcome by the use of a direct view storage cathode-ray tube (storage tube). A storage tube will continue to display the event after it has occurred until such time as it is erased. A storage tube is similar to a conventional tube except that it is equipped with a metal grid coated with a [[dielectric]] layer located immediately behind the phosphor screen. An externally applied voltage to the mesh initially ensures that the whole mesh is at a constant potential. This mesh is constantly exposed to a low velocity electron beam from a 'flood gun' which operates independently of the main gun. This flood gun is not deflected like the main gun but constantly 'illuminates' the whole of the storage mesh. The initial charge on the storage mesh is such as to repel the electrons from the flood gun which are prevented from striking the phosphor screen.

When the main electron gun writes an image to the screen, the energy in the main beam is sufficient to create a 'potential relief' on the storage mesh. The areas where this relief is created no longer repel the electrons from the flood gun which now pass through the mesh and illuminate the phosphor screen. Consequently, the image that was briefly traced out by the main gun continues to be displayed after it has occurred. The image can be 'erased' by resupplying the external voltage to the mesh restoring its constant potential. The time for which the image can be displayed was limited because, in practice, the flood gun slowly neutralises the charge on the storage mesh. One way of allowing the image to be retained for longer is temporarily to turn off the flood gun. It is then possible for the image to be retained for several days. The majority of storage tubes allow for a lower voltage to be applied to the storage mesh which slowly restores the initial charge state. By varying this voltage a variable persistence is obtained. Turning off the flood gun and the voltage supply to the storage mesh allows such a tube to operate as a conventional oscilloscope tube.&lt;ref&gt;The [[Great Soviet Encyclopedia]], 3rd Edition (1970–1979)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Color CRTs==
[[File:CRT screen. closeup.jpg|right|thumb|150px|Magnified view of a delta-gun [[shadow mask]] color CRT]]
[[File:CRT Phosphors.jpg|right|thumb|150px|Magnified view of a [[Trinitron]] color CRT]]
[[File:CRT_phosphors.png|thumb|right|Spectra of constituent blue, green and red phosphors in a common CRT]]
Color tubes use three different phosphors which emit red, green, and blue light respectively. They are packed together in stripes (as in [[aperture grille]] designs) or clusters called [[Triad (monitors)|&quot;triads&quot;]] (as in [[shadow mask]] CRTs).&lt;ref name=crtmonitorwork&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bit-tech.net/hardware/2006/03/20/how_crt_and_lcd_monitors_work/1 |title=How CRT and LCD monitors work |accessdate=4 October 2009 |work=bit-tech.net}}&lt;/ref&gt; Color CRTs have three electron guns, one for each primary color, arranged either in a straight line or in an [[equilateral triangle|equilateral triangular]] configuration (the guns are usually constructed as a single unit). (The triangular configuration is often called &quot;delta-gun&quot;, based on its relation to the shape of the Greek letter delta Δ.) A grille or mask absorbs the electrons that would otherwise hit the wrong phosphor.&lt;ref name=maskgrill&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pcguide.com/ref/crt/crtMask-c.html |title=The Shadow Mask and Aperture Grill |work=PC Guide |access-date=4 October 2009 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100102114333/http://pcguide.com/ref/crt/crtMask-c.html |archive-date=2 January 2010 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[shadow mask]] tube uses a metal plate with tiny holes, placed so that the electron beam only illuminates the correct phosphors on the face of the tube;&lt;ref name=crtmonitorwork/&gt; the holes are tapered so that the electrons that strike the inside of any hole will be reflected back, if they are not absorbed (e.g. due to local charge accumulation), instead of bouncing through the hole to strike a random (wrong) spot on the screen. Another type of color CRT uses an [[aperture grille]] of tensioned vertical wires to achieve the same result.&lt;ref name=maskgrill/&gt;

===Convergence and purity in color CRTs===
Due to limitations in the dimensional precision with which CRTs can be manufactured economically, it has not been practically possible to build color CRTs in which three electron beams could be aligned to hit phosphors of respective color in acceptable coordination, solely on the basis of the geometric configuration of the electron gun axes and gun aperture positions, shadow mask apertures, etc. The shadow mask ensures that one beam will only hit spots of certain colors of phosphors, but minute variations in physical alignment of the internal parts among individual CRTs will cause variations in the exact alignment of the beams through the shadow mask, allowing some electrons from, for example, the red beam to hit, say, blue phosphors, unless some individual compensation is made for the variance among individual tubes.

Color convergence and color purity are two aspects of this single problem. Firstly, for correct color rendering it is necessary that regardless of where the beams are deflected on the screen, all three hit the same spot (and nominally pass through the same hole or slot) on the shadow mask.{{clarify|reason=See Talk page for apparent contradiction|date=August 2019}} This is called convergence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ultimateavmag.com/howto/305picture/|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091126054428/http://www.ultimateavmag.com/howto/305picture/|archivedate=26 November 2009|title=Picture This|date=March 2005|author=Norton, Thomas J. |work= UltimateAVmag.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; More specifically, the convergence at the center of the screen (with no deflection field applied by the yoke) is called static convergence, and the convergence over the rest of the screen area is called dynamic convergence. The beams may converge at the center of the screen and yet stray from each other as they are deflected toward the edges; such a CRT would be said to have good static convergence but poor dynamic convergence. Secondly, each beam must only strike the phosphors of the color it is intended to strike and no others. This is called purity. Like convergence, there is static purity and dynamic purity, with the same meanings of &quot;static&quot; and &quot;dynamic&quot; as for convergence. Convergence and purity are distinct parameters; a CRT could have good purity but poor convergence, or vice versa. Poor convergence causes color &quot;shadows&quot; or &quot;ghosts&quot; along displayed edges and contours, as if the image on the screen were [[Intaglio (printmaking)|intaglio printed]] with poor registration. Poor purity causes objects on the screen to appear off-color while their edges remain sharp. Purity and convergence problems can occur at the same time, in the same or different areas of the screen or both over the whole screen, and either uniformly or to greater or lesser degrees over different parts of the screen.

[[File:Magnet on TV.webm|thumb|A magnet used on a CRT TV. Note the distortion of the image.]]
The solution to the static convergence and purity problems is a set of color alignment magnets installed around the neck of the CRT. These movable weak permanent magnets are usually mounted on the back end of the deflection yoke assembly and are set at the factory to compensate for any static purity and convergence errors that are intrinsic to the unadjusted tube. Typically there are two or three pairs of two magnets in the form of rings made of plastic impregnated with a magnetic material, with their [[magnetic fields]] parallel to the planes of the magnets, which are perpendicular to the electron gun axes. Each pair of magnetic rings forms a single effective magnet whose field [[vector field|vector]] can be fully and freely adjusted (in both direction and magnitude). By rotating a pair of magnets relative to each other, their relative field alignment can be varied, adjusting the effective field strength of the pair. (As they rotate relative to each other, each magnet's field can be considered to have two opposing components at right angles, and these four components [two each for two magnets] form two pairs, one pair reinforcing each other and the other pair opposing and canceling each other. Rotating away from alignment, the magnets' mutually reinforcing field components decrease as they are traded for increasing opposed, mutually cancelling components.) By rotating a pair of magnets together, preserving the relative angle between them, the direction of their collective magnetic field can be varied. Overall, adjusting all of the convergence/purity magnets allows a finely tuned slight electron beam deflection or lateral offset to be applied, which compensates for minor static convergence and purity errors intrinsic to the uncalibrated tube. Once set, these magnets are usually glued in place, but normally they can be freed and readjusted in the field (e.g. by a TV repair shop) if necessary.

On some CRTs, additional fixed adjustable magnets are added for dynamic convergence or dynamic purity at specific points on the screen, typically near the corners or edges. Further adjustment of dynamic convergence and purity typically cannot be done passively, but requires active compensation circuits.

Dynamic color convergence and purity are one of the main reasons why until late in their history, CRTs were long-necked (deep) and had biaxially curved faces; these geometric design characteristics are necessary for intrinsic passive dynamic color convergence and purity. Only starting around the 1990s did sophisticated active dynamic convergence compensation circuits become available that made short-necked and flat-faced CRTs workable. These active compensation circuits use the deflection yoke to finely adjust beam deflection according to the beam target location. The same techniques (and major circuit components) also make possible the adjustment of display image rotation, skew, and other complex [[raster graphics|raster]] geometry parameters through electronics under user control.

===Degaussing===
[[File:Degauss in progress.jpg|thumb|256px|A degaussing in progress.]]
If the shadow mask or aperture grille becomes magnetized, its magnetic field alters the paths of the electron beams. This causes errors of &quot;color purity&quot; as the electrons no longer follow only their intended paths, and some will hit some phosphors of colors other than the one intended. For example, some electrons from the red beam may hit blue or green phosphors, imposing a magenta or yellow tint to parts of the image that are supposed to be pure red. (This effect is localized to a specific area of the screen if the magnetization is localized.) Therefore, it is important that the shadow mask or aperture grille not be magnetized. 

Most color CRT displays, i.e. television sets and computer monitors, each have a built-in [[degaussing]] (demagnetizing) circuit, the primary component of which is a degaussing coil which is mounted around the perimeter of the CRT face inside the [[wikt:bezel|bezel]]. Upon power-up of the CRT display, the degaussing circuit produces a brief, alternating current through the degaussing coil which smoothly decays in strength (fades out) to zero over a period of a few seconds, producing a decaying alternating magnetic field from the coil. This degaussing field is strong enough to remove shadow mask magnetization in most cases.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pcguide.com/ref/crt/crtGauss-c.html|title=Magnetization and Degaussing|accessdate=4 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In unusual cases of strong magnetization where the internal degaussing field is not sufficient, the shadow mask may be degaussed externally with a stronger portable degausser or demagnetizer. However, an excessively strong magnetic field, whether alternating or constant, may mechanically [[deformation (engineering)|deform]] (bend) the shadow mask, causing a permanent color distortion on the display which looks very similar to a magnetization effect.

The degaussing circuit is often built of a [[Thermo-Electricity|thermo-electric]] (not electronic) device containing a small ceramic heating element and a positive thermal [[coefficient of thermal expansion|coefficient]] (PTC) [[resistor-capacitor circuit|resistor]], connected directly to the switched [[AC power]] line with the resistor in series with the degaussing coil. When the power is switched on, the heating element heats the PTC resistor, increasing its resistance to a point where degaussing current is minimal, but not actually zero. In older CRT displays, this low-level current (which produces no significant degaussing field) is sustained along with the action of the heating element as long as the display remains switched on. To repeat a degaussing cycle, the CRT display must be switched off and left off for at least several seconds to reset the degaussing circuit by allowing the PTC resistor to cool to the [[ambient temperature]]; switching the display-off and immediately back on will result in a weak degaussing cycle or effectively no degaussing cycle.

This simple design is effective and cheap to build, but it wastes some power continuously. Later models, especially [[Energy Star]] rated ones, use a [[relay]] to switch the entire degaussing circuit on and off, so that the degaussing circuit uses energy only when it is functionally active and needed. The relay design also enables degaussing on user demand through the unit's front panel controls, without switching the unit off and on again. This relay can often be heard clicking off at the end of the degaussing cycle a few seconds after the monitor is turned on, and on and off during a manually initiated degaussing cycle.

At high refresh rates and resolutions, the deflection coil/yoke starts to produce large amounts of heat, due to the need to quickly move the electron beam (because the electron beam has to scan more lines per second), which in turn requires large amounts of power, for quickly generating strong magnetic fields. This makes CRTs beyond certain resolutions and refresh rates impractical, since the coils would need active cooling, to prevent the heat from the coils  from melting the glue that is used to attach them to the neck of the CRT.

==Vector monitors==
{{Main|Vector monitor}}
Vector monitors were used in early computer aided design systems and are in some late-1970s to mid-1980s arcade games such as ''[[Asteroids (video game)|Asteroids]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= Supercade: A Visual History of the Videogame Age, 1971–1984 |author= Van Burnham |publisher= MIT Press |year= 2001 |isbn= 0-262-52420-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;
They draw graphics point-to-point, rather than scanning a raster. Either monochrome or color CRTs can be used in vector displays, and the essential principles of CRT design and operation are the same for either type of display; the main difference is in the beam deflection patterns and circuits.

==CRT resolution==
[[Dot pitch]] defines the maximum resolution of the display, assuming delta-gun CRTs. In these, as the scanned resolution approaches the dot pitch resolution, [[moiré]] appears, as the detail being displayed is finer than what the shadow mask can render.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.displaymate.com/moire.html |title= Moiré Interference Patterns |accessdate=4 October 2006 |work=DisplayMate Technologies website}}&lt;/ref&gt; Aperture grille monitors do not suffer from vertical moiré; however, because their phosphor stripes have no vertical detail. In smaller CRTs, these strips maintain position by themselves, but larger aperture-grille CRTs require one or two crosswise (horizontal) support strips.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://computer.howstuffworks.com/question406.htm |title=What causes the faint horizontal lines on my monitor? |accessdate=4 October 2009 |work=HowStuffWorks}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Gamma==
CRTs have a pronounced [[triode]] characteristic, which results in significant [[gamma correction|gamma]] (a nonlinear relationship in an electron gun between applied video voltage and beam intensity).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://broadcastengineering.com/newsrooms/broadcasting_gamma_correction/ |title=Gamma correction |accessdate=4 October 2009 |last=Robin |first=Michael |date=1 January 2005 |work=BroadcastEngineering |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090531130845/http://broadcastengineering.com/newsrooms/broadcasting_gamma_correction/ |archivedate=31 May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other types==
===Data storage tubes===
{{Main|Williams tube}}
The Williams tube or Williams-Kilburn tube was a cathode-ray tube used to electronically store binary data. It was used in computers of the 1940s as a random-access digital storage device. In contrast to other CRTs in this article, the Williams tube was not a display device, and in fact could not be viewed since a metal plate covered its screen.

===Cat's eye===
{{Main|Magic eye tube}}
In some [[vacuum tube]] radio sets, a [[Magic eye tube|&quot;Magic Eye&quot; or &quot;Tuning Eye&quot; tube]] was provided to assist in tuning the receiver. Tuning would be adjusted until the width of a radial shadow was minimized. This was used instead of a more expensive electromechanical meter, which later came to be used on higher-end tuners when transistor sets lacked the high voltage required to drive the device.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.vacuumtube.com/eyetubes.htm |title=Tuning-Eye Tubes |accessdate=1 December 2009 |publisher=vacuumtube.com |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090423055711/http://www.vacuumtube.com/eyetubes.htm |archivedate=23 April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The same type of device was used with tape recorders as a recording level meter, and for various other applications including electrical test equipment.

===Charactrons===
{{Main|Charactron}}
Some displays for early computers (those that needed to display more text than was practical using vectors, or that required high speed for photographic output) used Charactron CRTs. These incorporate a perforated metal character mask ([[stencil]]), which shapes a wide electron beam to form a character on the screen. The system selects a character on the mask using one set of deflection circuits, but that causes the extruded beam to be aimed off-axis, so a second set of deflection plates has to re-aim the beam so it is headed toward the center of the screen. A third set of plates places the character wherever required. The beam is unblanked (turned on) briefly to draw the character at that position. Graphics could be drawn by selecting the position on the mask corresponding to the code for a space (in practice, they were simply not drawn), which had a small round hole in the center; this effectively disabled the character mask, and the system reverted to regular vector behavior. Charactrons had exceptionally long necks, because of the need for three deflection systems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.google.com/patents?vid=2735956|title=Cathode ray apparatus|accessdate=4 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.google.com/patents?vid=2824250|title=INPUT|accessdate=4 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Nimo===
{{Main|Nimo tube}}
[[File:Nimo tube BA0000-P31 showing digit 9.jpg|thumb|right|Nimo tube BA0000-P31]]
Nimo was the trademark of a family of small specialised CRTs manufactured by Industrial Electronics Engineers. These had 10 electron guns which produced electron beams in the form of digits in a manner similar to that of the charactron. The tubes were either simple single-digit displays or more complex 4- or 6- digit displays produced by means of a suitable magnetic deflection system. Having little of the complexities of a standard CRT, the tube required a relatively simple driving circuit, and as the image was projected on the glass face, it provided a much wider viewing angle than competitive types (e.g., [[nixie tube]]s).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.tube-tester.com/sites/nixie/dat_arch/BA0000-P31.pdf |title=IEE Nimo CRT 10-gun readout tube datasheet |format=PDF |work=tube-tester.com|accessdate=1 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Flood beam CRT===
{{Main|Electron-stimulated luminescence}}
Flood beam CRTs are small tubes that are arranged as pixels for large screens like [[Jumbotron]]s. The first screen using this technology was introduced by [[Mitsubishi Electric]] for the [[1980 Major League Baseball All-Star Game]]. It differs from a normal CRT in that the electron gun within does not produce a focused controllable beam. Instead, electrons are sprayed in a wide cone across the entire front of the phosphor screen, basically making each unit act as a single light bulb.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.decadecounter.com/vta/articleview.php?item=947|title= Futaba TL-3508XA 'Jumbotron' Display|date= 11 March 2010|accessdate= 2014-12-19|website= The Vintage Technology Association: Military Industrial Electronics Research Preservation|publisher= The Vintage Technology Association}}&lt;/ref&gt; Each one is coated with a red, green or blue phosphor, to make up the color sub-pixels. This technology has largely been replaced with [[light emitting diode]] displays. Unfocused and undeflected CRTs were used as grid-controlled [[Strobe light|stroboscope lamps]] since 1958.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mif.pg.gda.pl/homepages/frank/sheets/074/c/CL60.pdf |publisher=[[Ferranti]], Ltd. |title=''Vacuum light sources — High speed stroboscopic light sources'' data sheet |date=August 1958 |format=PDF |accessdate=7 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Print head CRT===
CRTs with an unphosphored front glass but with fine wires embedded in it were used as [[Printer (computing)#Liquid ink electrostatic printers|electrostatic print head]]s in the 1960s. The wires would pass the electron beam current through the glass onto a sheet of paper where the desired content was therefore deposited as an electrical charge pattern. The paper was then passed near a pool of liquid ink with the opposite charge. The charged areas of the paper attract the ink and thus form the image.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mif.pg.gda.pl/homepages/frank/sheets/138/c/CK1366.pdf |publisher=[[Raytheon|Raytheon Company]]  |title= ''CK1366 CK1367 Printer-type cathode ray tube'' data sheet |date=1 November 1960 |format=PDF |accessdate=29 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mif.pg.gda.pl/homepages/frank/sheets/138/c/CK1368.pdf |publisher=[[Raytheon|Raytheon Company]]  |title= ''CK1368 CK1369 Printer-type cathode ray tube'' data sheet |date=1 November 1960 |format=PDF |accessdate=29 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Zeus thin CRT display===
In the late 1990s and early 2000s [[Philips|Philips Research Laboratories]] experimented with a type of thin CRT known as the ''Zeus'' display which contained CRT-like functionality in a [[flat panel display]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.patentstorm.us/patents/6246165/description.html |title=US Patent 6246165 – Magnetic channel cathode |author=Beeteson, John Stuart |date=21 November 1998 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130518040015/http://www.patentstorm.us/patents/6246165/description.html |archivedate=18 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.freepatentsonline.com/5905336.html |title=US Patent 5905336 – Method of manufacturing a glass substrate coated with a metal oxide|author1=Van Hal |author2=Henricus A. M. |date=18 May 1990|display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1016/S0165-5817(97)84675-X|title=Introduction to Zeus displays|year=1996|last1=Van Gorkom|first1=G.G.P.|journal=Philips Journal of Research|volume=50|issue=3–4|page=269}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1016/S0165-5817(97)84677-3|title=Transport and extraction in Zeus displays|year=1996|last1=Lambert|first1=N.|last2=Montie|first2=E.A.|last3=Baller|first3=T.S.|last4=Van Gorkom|first4=G.G.P.|last5=Hendriks|first5=B.H.W.|last6=Trompenaars|first6=P.H.F.|last7=De Zwart|first7=S.T.|journal=Philips Journal of Research|volume=50|issue=3–4|page=295}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1016/S0165-5817(97)84688-8 |title=The application and system aspects of the Zeus display|year=1996|last1=Doyle|first1=T.|last2=Van Asma|first2=C.|last3=McCormack|first3=J.|last4=De Greef|first4=D.|last5=Haighton|first5=V.|last6=Heijnen|first6=P.|last7=Looymans|first7=M.|last8=Van Velzen|first8=J.|journal=Philips Journal of Research|volume=50|issue=3–4|page=501}}&lt;/ref&gt; The devices were demonstrated but never marketed.

===Slimmer CRT===
[[File:Tabgamb.jpg|250px|thumb|right|A comparison between 21-inch Superslim and Ultraslim CRT]]

Some CRT manufacturers, both LG Display and Samsung Display, innovated CRT technology by creating a slimmer tube. Slimmer CRT has a trade name Superslim and Ultraslim. A {{Convert|21|in|cm|adj=on}} flat CRT has a {{Convert|447.2|mm||adj=on}} depth. The depth of Superslim was {{Convert|352|mm||2}} and Ultraslim was {{Convert|295.7|mm|}}.

==21st century usage==

===Demise===
{{Update|date=May 2017}}
Despite being a mainstay of display technology for decades, CRT-based computer monitors and televisions are now virtually a dead technology. Demand for CRT screens dropped in the late 2000s. The rapid advances and falling prices of [[liquid-crystal display|LCD]] [[flat panel]] technology — first for computer monitors, and then for televisions — spelled doom for competing display technologies such as CRT, [[rear-projection television|rear-projection]], and [[plasma display]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Wong|first=May|title=Flat Panels Drive Old TVs From Market |publisher=AP via USA Today |date= 22 October 2006 |url=https://www.usatoday.com/tech/products/gear/2006-10-22-crt-demise_x.htm |accessdate=8 October 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Most high-end CRT production had ceased by around 2010,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.veritasetvisus.com/LCDTVA/LCDTVA-8,%20Spring-Summer%202009.pdf |title= The Standard TV|publisher= Veritas et Visus |accessdate=12 June 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; including high-end Sony and Panasonic product lines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.signonsandiego.com/uniontrib/20060120/news_1n20sony.html |title=End of an era |newspaper=The San Diego Union-Tribune |date=20 January 2006 |accessdate=12 June 2008 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080615135249/http://www.signonsandiego.com/uniontrib/20060120/news_1n20sony.html |archive-date=15 June 2008 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.engadgethd.com/2005/12/01/matsushita-says-good-bye-to-crts/ |title=Matsushita says good-bye to CRTs |publisher=engadgetHD |date=1 December 2005 |accessdate=12 June 2008 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090114110526/http://www.engadgethd.com/2005/12/01/matsushita-says-good-bye-to-crts/ |archivedate=14 January 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Canada and the United States, the sale and production of high-end CRT TVs ({{Convert|30|in|cm|adj=on}} screens) in these markets had all but ended by 2007. Just a couple of years later, inexpensive &quot;combo&quot; CRT TVs ({{Convert|20|in|cm|adj=on}} screens with an integrated VHS player) disappeared from discount stores.

Electronics retailers such as Best Buy steadily reduced store spaces for CRTs. In 2005, Sony announced that they would stop the production of CRT computer displays. Samsung did not introduce any CRT models for the 2008 model year at the 2008 Consumer Electronics Show; on 4 February 2008, they removed their 30&quot; wide screen CRTs from their North American website and did not replace them with new models.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.samsung.com/us/consumer/subtype/subtype.do?group=televisions&amp;type=televisions&amp;subtype=slimfithdtv |title=SlimFit HDTV|publisher=Samsung |accessdate=12 June 2008 |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080110164950/http://www.samsung.com/us/consumer/subtype/subtype.do?group=televisions&amp;type=televisions&amp;subtype=slimfithdtv &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate= 10 January 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United Kingdom, [[DSG International (retailer)|DSG (Dixons)]], the largest retailer of domestic electronic equipment, reported that CRT models made up 80–90% of the volume of televisions sold at Christmas 2004 and 15–20% a year later, and that they were expected to be less than 5% at the end of 2006. Dixons ceased selling CRT televisions in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=The future is flat as Dixons withdraws sale of 'big box' televisions |newspaper=London Evening Standard |date=26 November 2006 |url=http://www.thisislondon.co.uk/news/article-23376023-details/The+future+is+flat+as+Dixons+withdraws+sale+of+'big+box'+televisions/article.do |archive-url=https://archive.today/20130505112036/http://www.thisislondon.co.uk/news/article-23376023-details/The+future+is+flat+as+Dixons+withdraws+sale+of+'big+box'+televisions/article.do |url-status=dead |archive-date=5 May 2013 |accessdate=3 December 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, the demise of CRTs has been happening more slowly in the developing world. According to iSupply, production in units of CRTs was not surpassed by LCDs production until 4Q 2007, owing largely to CRT production at factories in China.{{cn|date=December 2017}}

====Causes====
{{unreferenced section|date=December 2017}}
CRTs, despite advances, remained relatively heavy and cumbersome in comparison to other display technologies. CRT screens had much deeper cabinets compared to flat panels and rear-projection displays for a given screen size; it was largely impractical to build or use CRTs larger than {{convert|40|in|cm|0}}. The CRT disadvantages became especially significant in light of rapid technological advancements in [[liquid-crystal display|LCD]] and plasma flat-panels, which allowed them to easily surpass these size limitations while also being thin and wall-mountable (two key features that were increasingly being preferred by customers).

==Health concerns==

===Ionizing radiation===
CRTs can emit a small amount of [[X-ray]] radiation as a result of the electron beam's bombardment of the shadow mask/aperture grille and phosphors. The amount of radiation escaping the front of the monitor is widely considered not to be harmful. The [[Food and Drug Administration]] regulations in {{CodeFedReg|21|1020|10}} are used to strictly limit, for instance, television receivers to 0.5 [[Roentgen (unit)|milliroentgens]] per hour (mR/h) (0.13&amp;nbsp;µC/(kg·h) or 36&amp;nbsp;pA/kg) at a distance of {{convert|5|cm|0|abbr=on}} from any external surface; since 2007, most CRTs have emissions that fall well below this limit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.accessdata.fda.gov/scripts/cdrh/cfdocs/cfcfr/CFRSearch.cfm?fr=1020.10 |title=Subchapter J, Radiological Health (21CFR1020.10) |publisher=U.S. Food and Drug Administration |date=1 April 2006 |accessdate=13 August 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Toxicity===
Older color and monochrome CRTs may have been manufactured with toxic substances, such as [[cadmium]], in the phosphors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://takebackmytv.com/pages/toxic_tvs |title=Toxic TVs |accessdate=13 April 2010 |publisher=Electronics TakeBack Coalition |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090227041627/http://takebackmytv.com/pages/toxic_tvs |archivedate=27 February 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://e-stewards.org/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/OccupationalRisksCRTGlassProcessing1.pdf |title=Occupational Risks Associated with Electronics Demanufacturing and CRT Glass Processing Operations and the Impact of Mitigation Activities on Employee Safety and Health |accessdate=20 January 2011 |author1=Peters-Michaud, Neil |author2=Katers, John |author3=Barry, Jim |format=PDF |work=Cascade Asset Management, LLC |publisher=Basel Action Network |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110726012352/http://e-stewards.org/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/OccupationalRisksCRTGlassProcessing1.pdf |archivedate=26 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.americanelements.com/cdm.html |title=Cadmium |accessdate=13 April 2010 |publisher=[[American Elements]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The rear glass tube of modern CRTs may be made from [[lead glass|leaded glass]], which represent an environmental hazard if disposed of improperly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hinkleycenter.com/publications/lead_leachability_99-5.pdf |title=Characterization of Lead Leachability from Cathode Ray Tubes Using the Toxicity Characteristic Leaching Procedure |accessdate=4 October 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140222012228/http://www.hinkleycenter.com/publications/lead_leachability_99-5.pdf |archivedate=22 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the time personal computers were produced, glass in the front panel (the viewable portion of the CRT) used barium rather than lead,{{Citation needed|date=February 2014}} though the rear of the CRT was still produced from leaded glass. Monochrome CRTs typically do not contain enough leaded glass to fail EPA TCLP tests. While the TCLP process grinds the glass into fine particles in order to expose them to weak acids to test for leachate, intact CRT glass does not leach (The lead is vitrified, contained inside the glass itself, similar to leaded glass crystalware).

=== Recycling ===
Due to the toxins contained in CRT monitors the [[United States Environmental Protection Agency]] created rules (in October 2001) stating that CRTs must be brought to special [[Electronic waste|e-waste recycling]] facilities. In November 2002, the [[United States Environmental Protection Agency|EPA]] began fining companies that disposed of CRTs through [[landfill]]s or [[incineration]]. Regulatory agencies, local and statewide, monitor the disposal of CRTs and other computer equipment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.epa.gov/osw/hazard/recycling/electron/index.htm|title=Final Rules on Cathode Ray Tubes and Discarded Mercury-Containing Equipment|accessdate=4 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Various states participate in the recycling of CRTs, each with their reporting requirements for collectors and recycling facilities. For example, in California the recycling of CRTs is governed by CALRecycle, the California Department of Resources Recycling and Recovery through their Payment System. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.calrecycle.ca.gov/electronics/cew|title=Covered Electronic Waste Payment System|first=State of|last=California|website=www.calrecycle.ca.gov}}&lt;/ref&gt;. Recycling facilities that accept CRT devices from business and residential sector must obtain contact information such as address and phone number to ensure the CRTs come from a California source in order to participate in the CRT Recycling Payment System. 

In Europe, disposal of CRT televisions and monitors is covered by the [[WEEE Directive]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.awm-group.com/recycling/WEEEandCRTProcessing.htm |title=WEEE and CRT Processing |accessdate=4 October 2009 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090603065621/http://www.awm-group.com/recycling/WEEEandCRTProcessing.htm |archive-date=3 June 2009 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Flicker===
{{Main|Flicker (screen)}}
At low [[refresh rate]]s (60&amp;nbsp;[[Hertz|Hz]] and below), the periodic scanning of the display may produce a flicker that some people perceive more easily than others, especially when viewed with [[peripheral vision]]. Flicker is commonly associated with CRT as most televisions run at 50&amp;nbsp;Hz (PAL) or 60&amp;nbsp;Hz (NTSC), although there are some 100&amp;nbsp;Hz PAL televisions that are [[flicker-free]]. Typically only low-end monitors run at such low frequencies, with most computer monitors supporting at least 75&amp;nbsp;Hz and high-end monitors capable of 100&amp;nbsp;Hz or more to eliminate any perception of flicker.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pcmech.com/article/crt-monitor-flickering/|archive-url=http://arquivo.pt/wayback/20160515111055/http://www.pcmech.com/article/crt-monitor-flickering/|url-status=dead|archive-date=15 May 2016|title=CRT Monitor Flickering?|accessdate=4 October 2009|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though the 100 Hz PAL was often achieved using interleaved scanning, dividing the circuit and scan into two beams of 50 Hz. Non-computer CRTs or CRT for [[sonar]] or [[radar]] may have long [[Image persistence|persistence]] phosphor and are thus flicker free. If the persistence is too long on a video display, moving images will be blurred.

===High-frequency audible noise===
50&amp;nbsp;Hz/60&amp;nbsp;Hz CRTs used for television operate with horizontal scanning frequencies of 15,734&amp;nbsp;Hz (for [[NTSC]] systems) or 15,625&amp;nbsp;Hz (for [[PAL]] systems).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Netravali |first= Arun N. |author2=Haskell, Barry G. |title= Digital pictures: representation, compression, and standards |publisher= Plenum Publishing Corporation |year= 1995 |page= 100 |url= https://books.google.com/?id=-TXYfZrCBuQC&amp;pg=PA100 |isbn=978-0-306-44917-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; These frequencies are at the upper range of [[human hearing]] and are inaudible to many people; however, some people (especially children) will perceive a high-pitched tone near an operating television CRT.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pcguide.com/ts/x/comp/crt/failWhine-c.html |title=The monitor is producing a high-pitched whine |accessdate=4 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The sound is due to [[magnetostriction]] in the magnetic core and periodic movement of windings of the [[flyback transformer]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Rhys-Jones |first1=J. |title=Television economics |journal=Radiotronics |date=February 1951 |volume=16 |issue=2 |page=37}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This problem does not occur on 100/120&amp;nbsp;Hz TVs and on non-CGA (Color Graphics Adapter) computer displays, because they use much higher horizontal scanning frequencies (22&amp;nbsp;kHz to over 100&amp;nbsp;kHz).

===Implosion===
High [[vacuum]] inside glass-walled cathode-ray tubes permits electron beams to fly freely—without colliding into molecules of air or other gas. If the glass is damaged, atmospheric pressure can collapse the vacuum tube into dangerous fragments which accelerate inward and then spray at high speed in all directions. The implosion energy is proportional to the evacuated volume of the CRT.{{cn|date=December 2017}} Although modern cathode-ray tubes used in televisions and computer displays have [[epoxy]]-bonded face-plates or other measures to prevent shattering of the envelope, CRTs must be handled carefully to avoid personal injury.&lt;ref name=Bali&gt;{{cite book |last= Bali |first= S.P. |title= Colour Television: Theory and Practice |publisher= Tata McGraw–Hill |year= 1994 |page= 129 |url= https://books.google.com/?id=53nnX4fnnNIC&amp;pg=PA129 |isbn=978-0-07-460024-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Electric shock===
To accelerate the electrons from the cathode to the screen with sufficient velocity, a very [[high voltage]] (EHT or Extra High Tension) is required,&lt;ref&gt;Color Television Servicing Manual, Vol-1, by M.D. Aggarwala, 1985, Television for you, Delhi, India&lt;/ref&gt; from a few thousand volts for a small oscilloscope CRT to tens of kV for a larger screen color TV. This is many times greater than household power supply voltage. Even after the power supply is turned off, some associated capacitors and the CRT itself may retain  a charge for some time and therefore dissipate that charge suddenly through a ground such as an inattentive human grounding a capacitor  discharge lead.

==Security concerns==
Under some circumstances, the signal radiated from the [[electron gun]]s, scanning circuitry, and associated wiring of a CRT can be captured remotely and used to reconstruct what is shown on the CRT using a process called [[Van Eck phreaking]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://jya.com/emr.pdf|title=Electromagnetic Radiation from Video Display Units: An Eavesdropping Risk?|accessdate=4 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Special [[TEMPEST]] shielding can mitigate this effect. Such radiation of a potentially exploitable signal, however, occurs also with other display technologies&lt;ref name=Kuhn2004&gt;{{cite journal |author= Kuhn, M.G. |year= 2004 |title= Electromagnetic Eavesdropping Risks of Flat-Panel Displays |journal= 4th Workshop on Privacy Enhancing Technologies |pages= 23–25 |url= http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/~mgk25/pet2004-fpd.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; and with electronics in general.{{Citation needed|date=September 2010}}

==Recycling==
As [[electronic waste]], CRTs are considered one of the hardest types to recycle.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.executiveblueprints.com/aboutweee/WEEECRTandMonitor.htm WEEE: CRT and Monitor Recycling]. Executiveblueprints.com (2 August 2009). Retrieved on 26 August 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; CRTs have relatively high concentration of lead and phosphors (not phosphorus), both of which are necessary for the display. There are several companies in the United States that charge a small fee to collect CRTs, then subsidize their labor by selling the harvested copper, wire, and [[printed circuit board]]s. The [[United States Environmental Protection Agency]] (EPA) includes discarded CRT monitors in its category of &quot;hazardous household waste&quot;&lt;ref name=sb&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.smartbiz.com/article/articleprint/1525/-1/58|publisher=SmartBiz|title=Tips and Tricks for Recycling Old Computers|author=Morgan, Russell|date=21 August 2006|accessdate=17 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; but considers CRTs that have been set aside for testing to be commodities if they are not discarded, speculatively accumulated, or left unprotected from weather and other damage.{{cn|date=December 2017}}

Leaded CRT glass was sold to be remelted into other CRTs, or even broken down and used in road construction.&lt;ref&gt;Weitzman, David. [http://www.nyfederation.org/PDF/14_CRTDilemma.pdf The CRT Dilemma: Cathode Ray Tube Or Cruel Rude Trash] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110727134626/http://www.nyfederation.org/PDF/14_CRTDilemma.pdf |date=27 July 2011 }}. RRT Design &amp; Construction&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Electronics}}
{{div col|colwidth=22em}}

Basics of cathode rays and discharge in low-pressure gas:
*[[Cathode ray]]
*[[Vacuum tube]]

Light production by cathode rays:
*[[Cathodoluminescence]]
*[[Crookes tube]]
*[[Phosphor]]
*[[Scintillation (physics)]]

Manipulating the electron beam:
*[[Blanking (video)]]
**[[Horizontal blanking interval]]
**[[Vertical blanking interval]]
*[[Deflection yoke]]
*[[Electron beam processing]]
*[[Electrostatic deflection]]
*[[Electrostatic lens]]
*[[Magnetic deflection]]
*[[Magnetic lens]]

Applying CRT in different display-purpose:
*[[Analog television]]
*[[Analog television#Displaying an image|Image displaying]]
*[[Comparison of CRT, LCD, plasma, and OLED]]
*[[Comparison of display technology]]
*[[Computer monitor]]
*[[CRT projector]]
*[[Image dissector]]
*[[Monochrome monitor]]
*[[Monoscope]]
*[[Oscilloscope]]
*[[Cathode-ray oscilloscope]]
*[[Overscan]]
*[[Raster scan]]
*[[Scan line]]

Miscellaneous phenomena:
*[[Noise (video)]]

Historical aspects:
*[[Direct-view bistable storage tube]]
*[[Flat panel display]]
*[[History of display technology]]
*[[Image dissector]]
*[[LCD television]], [[LED-backlit LCD]], [[LED display]]
*[[Penetron]]
*[[Surface-conduction electron-emitter display]]
*[[Trinitron]]

Safety and precautions:
*[[Monitor filter]]
*[[Photosensitive epilepsy]]
*[[TCO Certification]]

{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|35em}}

==Selected patents==
*{{US patent|1691324}}: Zworykin Television System

==External links==
{{Commons category|Cathode ray tubes|Cathode ray tube}}
*{{cite web|url=http://www.pctechguide.com/42CRTMonitors.htm|website= PCTechGuide|title= Cathode Ray Tube Monitors}}
*{{cite web|url=http://www.tubecollector.org/list.php?L=-J&amp;M=Y&amp;H=CRTs |title=CRTs |website= Virtual Valve Museum}}
*{{cite web|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060926221732/http://www.repairfaq.org/sam/crtfaq.htm#crtcsa |author=Goldwasser, Samuel M. |title=TV and Monitor CRT (Picture Tube) Information|website=repairfaq.org|date=February 28, 2006}}
*{{cite web|url=https://www.crtsite.com/page3.html |title=The Cathode Ray Tube site|website= crtsite.com}}

{{Display technology}}
{{Electronic components}}
{{Thermionic valves}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cathode Ray Tube}}
[[Category:Cathode ray tube| ]]
[[Category:Consumer electronics]]
[[Category:Display technology]]
[[Category:Television technology]]
[[Category:Vacuum tube displays]]
[[Category:Audiovisual introductions in 1897]]
[[Category:Telecommunications-related introductions in 1897]]</text>
      <sha1>r283umxi34djnup59cs651ksu2pc95z</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
