  <page>
    <title>Corporate title</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5681</id>
    <revision>
      <id>934492839</id>
      <parentid>934492374</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-06T21:03:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Awker22</username>
        <id>30002311</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/2607:FEA8:E3E0:1A72:1E1:ACD9:2162:77CE|2607:FEA8:E3E0:1A72:1E1:ACD9:2162:77CE]] ([[User talk:2607:FEA8:E3E0:1A72:1E1:ACD9:2162:77CE|talk]]): Rv, &quot;confer&quot; is the proper spelling ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{multiple issues|
{{original research|date=February 2012}}
{{More citations needed|date=April 2011}}
{{globalize|date=February 2018}}
}}
{{Business administration}}

'''Corporate titles''' or '''business titles''' are given to company and organization officials to show what duties and responsibilities they have in the organization. Such titles are used by publicly and privately held for-profit [[corporation]]s. In addition, many [[non-profit]] organizations, educational institutions, [[partnership]]s, and [[sole proprietorship]]s also confer corporate titles.

==Variations==
{{unreferenced section|date=February 2012}}
There are considerable variations in the composition and responsibilities of corporate titles.

Within the corporate office or corporate center of a company, some companies have a [[chairman]] and [[chief executive officer]] (CEO) as the top-ranking executive, while the number two is the president and [[chief operating officer]]  (COO); other companies have a president and CEO but no official deputy. Typically, senior managers are &quot;higher&quot; than [[vice president]]s, although many times a senior officer may also hold a vice president title, such as executive vice president and [[chief financial officer]] (CFO). The [[board of directors]] is technically not part of management itself, although its chairman may be considered part of the corporate office if he or she is an executive chairman.

A corporation often consists of different businesses, whose senior executives report directly to the CEO or COO, but depends on the form of the business. If organized as a [[Division (business)|division]] then the top manager is often known as an [[vice president#Hierarchy of vice presidents|executive vice president (EVP)]]. If that business is a [[subsidiary]] which has considerably more independence, then the title might be chairman and CEO.

In many countries, particularly in Europe and Asia, there is a separate executive board for day-to-day business and [[supervisory board]] (elected by shareholders) for control purposes. In these countries, the CEO presides over the executive board and the chairman presides over the supervisory board, and these two roles will always be held by different people. This ensures a distinction between [[management]] by the executive board and [[governance]] by the supervisory board. This seemingly allows for clear lines of authority. There is a strong parallel here with the structure of government, which tends to separate the political [[Cabinet (government)|cabinet]] from the management [[civil service]].

In the United States and other countries that follow a single-board corporate structure, the board of directors (elected by the shareholders) is often equivalent to the European or Asian supervisory board, while the functions of the executive board may be vested either in the board of directors or in a separate committee, which may be called an operating committee (J.P. Morgan Chase),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.nytimes.com/2012/10/07/magazine/ina-drew-jamie-dimon-jpmorgan-chase.html?pagewanted=all | work=The New York Times | first=Susan | last=Dominus | title=Ina Drew, Jamie Dimon and JPMorgan Chase's $6 Billion Mistake | date=2012-10-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; management committee (Goldman Sachs), executive committee ([[Lehman Brothers]]), or executive council ([[Hewlett-Packard]]), or executive board ([[HeiG]]) composed of the division/subsidiary heads and senior officers that report directly to the CEO.

===United States===

State laws in the United States traditionally required certain positions to be created within every corporation, such as [[President (corporate title)|president]], [[Company secretary|secretary]] and [[treasurer]]. Today, the approach under the ''[[Model Business Corporation Act]]'', which is employed in many states, is to grant companies discretion in determining which titles to have, with the only mandated organ being the board of directors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Model Business Corporation Act|url=http://users.wfu.edu/palmitar/ICBCorporations-Companion/Conexus/ModelBusinessCorporationAct.pdf|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121010220809/http://users.wfu.edu/palmitar/ICBCorporations-Companion/Conexus/ModelBusinessCorporationAct.pdf|url-status=dead|archive-date=10 October 2012|accessdate=19 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some states that do not employ the MBCA continue to require that certain offices be established. Under the law of [[Delaware]], where most large US corporations are established, stock certificates must be signed by two officers with titles specified by law (e.g. a president and secretary or a president and treasurer).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Delaware General Corporation Law § 158|url=http://delcode.delaware.gov/title8/c001/sc05/index.shtml|accessdate=19 December 2013|quote=Every holder of stock represented by certificates shall be entitled to have a certificate signed by, or in the name of the corporation by the chairperson or vice-chairperson of the board of directors, or the president or vice-president, and by the treasurer or an assistant treasurer, or the secretary or an assistant secretary of such corporation representing the number of shares registered in certificate form.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Every corporation incorporated in [[California]] must have a chairman of the board or a president (or both), as well as a secretary and a chief financial officer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=California Corporations Code § 312|url=http://www.leginfo.ca.gov/cgi-bin/displaycode?section=corp&amp;group=00001-01000&amp;file=300-318|accessdate=19 December 2013|quote=A corporation shall have a chairman of the board or a president or both, a secretary, a chief financial officer, and such other officers with such titles and duties as shall be stated in the bylaws or determined by the board and as may be necessary to enable it to sign instruments and share certificates.|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121113085241/http://www.leginfo.ca.gov/cgi-bin/displaycode?section=corp&amp;group=00001-01000&amp;file=300-318|archivedate=13 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Limited liability company]] (LLC)-structured companies are generally run directly by their members, but the members can agree to appoint officers such as a CEO or to appoint &quot;managers&quot; to operate the company.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Lawrence|first=George|title=Does an LLC Have to Have a President or CEO?|url=http://smallbusiness.chron.com/llc-president-ceo-17385.html|newspaper=Houston Chronicle|accessdate=20 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

American companies are generally led by a CEO. In some companies, the CEO also has the title of &quot;president&quot;. In other companies, a president is a different person, and the primary duties of the two positions are defined in the company's bylaws (or the laws of the governing legal jurisdiction). Many companies also have a CFO, a [[chief operating officer]] (COO) and other senior positions such as [[chief information officer]] (CIO), [[chief business officer]] (CBO), [[chief marketing officer]] (CMO), etc. that report to the president and CEO as &quot;senior vice presidents&quot; of the company. The next level, which are not executive positions, is middle management and may be called &quot;vice presidents&quot;, &quot;[[Director (business)|directors]]&quot; or &quot;managers&quot;, depending on the size and required managerial depth of the company.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Lowe|first=Keith|title=The Relevance of Employee Titles|url=http://www.entrepreneur.com/article/48776|accessdate=20 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===

In British English, the title of [[managing director]] is generally synonymous with that of chief executive officer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=What is MANAGING DIRECTOR?|url=http://thelawdictionary.org/managing-director/|publisher=The Law Dictionary|accessdate=20 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Managing directors do not have any particular authority under the ''Companies Act'' in the UK, but do have [[implied authority]] based on the general understanding of what their position entails, as well as any authority expressly delegated by the board of directors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Powers of a Managing Director|url=http://www.jordanslawforbusiness.co.uk/articles/the-powers-of-a-managing-director|publisher=Jordans|accessdate=20 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Japan and South Korea===

In Japan, corporate titles are roughly standardized across companies and organizations; although there is variation from company to company, corporate titles within a company are always consistent, and the large companies in Japan generally follow the same outline.&lt;ref name=Whitehill1991&gt;{{cite book|title=Japanese management: tradition and transition|author=Arthur Murray Whitehill|publisher=Taylor &amp;amp; Francis|year=1991|isbn=978-0-415-02253-8|page=[https://archive.org/details/japanesemanageme0000whit/page/113 113]|url=https://archive.org/details/japanesemanageme0000whit/page/113}}&lt;/ref&gt; These titles are the formal titles that are used on business cards.&lt;ref name=Kopp2000&gt;{{cite book|page=172|title=The rice-paper ceiling: breaking through Japanese corporate culture|author=Rochelle Kopp|publisher=[[Stone Bridge Press]], Inc.|year=2000|isbn= 978-1-880656-51-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; Korean corporate titles are similar to those of Japan.

Legally, Japanese and Korean companies are only required to have a board of directors with at least one representative director.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Yamaguchi|first1=Katsuyuki|last2=Dohi|first2=Shinji|title=Corporate governance and directors' duties in Japan: overview|url=https://content.next.westlaw.com/1-502-0177?transitionType=Default&amp;contextData=(sc.Default)&amp;__lrTS=20171118235410021|website=Thompson Reuters Practical Law|publisher=Thompson Reuters}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{citation needed|date=August 2015}} In Japanese, a company director is called a ''torishimariyaku'' (取締役) and a [[Representative Director (Japan)|representative director]] is called a ''daihyo torishimariyaku'' (代表取締役). The equivalent Korean titles are ''isa'' (이사, 理事) and ''daepyo-isa'' (대표이사, 代表理事). These titles are often combined with lower titles, e.g. ''senmu torishimariyaku'' or ''jomu torishimariyaku'' for Japanese executives who are also board members.&lt;ref name=LazerRynn1990 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Condon1984 /&gt; Most Japanese companies also have [[statutory auditor]]s, who operate alongside the board of directors in supervisory roles.

The typical structure of executive titles in large companies includes the following:&lt;ref name=LazerRynn1990&gt;{{cite book|title=International business handbook|volume=1|series=Haworth series in international business|author=William Lazer and Midori Rynn|chapter=Japan|editor=Vishnu H. Kirpalani|publisher=Routledge|year=1990|isbn=978-0-86656-862-3|page=[https://archive.org/details/internationalbus0000unse_q8z9/page/361 361]|url=https://archive.org/details/internationalbus0000unse_q8z9/page/361}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Condon1984&gt;{{cite book|title=With respect to the Japanese: a guide for Americans|volume=4|series=Country orientation series|author=John C. Condon|publisher=Intercultural Press|year=1984|isbn=978-0-933662-49-0|page=[https://archive.org/details/withrespecttojap00cond/page/86 86]|url=https://archive.org/details/withrespecttojap00cond/page/86}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Vogel1975&gt;{{cite book|title=Modern Japanese organization and decision-making|author=Ezra F. Vogel|publisher=University of California Press|year=1975|isbn=978-0-520-02857-9|pages=[https://archive.org/details/modernjapaneseor0000unse/page/135 135, 137]|url=https://archive.org/details/modernjapaneseor0000unse/page/135}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!English gloss
!''Kanji'' (''hanja'')
!Japanese
!Korean
!Comments
|-
|[[Chairman]]
|会長&lt;br /&gt;(會長)
|''Kaicho''
|''Hwejang''&lt;br /&gt;(회장)
|Often a semi-retired president or company founder. Denotes a position with considerable power within the company exercised through behind-the-scenes influence via the active president.
|-
|[[Vice chairman]]
|副会長&lt;br /&gt;(副會長)
|''Fuku-kaicho''
|''Bu-hwejang''&lt;br /&gt;(부회장)
|At Korean family-owned ''[[chaebol]]'' companies such as [[Samsung]], the vice-chairman commonly holds the CEO title (i.e., vice chairman and CEO)
|-
|[[President (corporate title)|President]]
|社長
|''Shacho''
|''Sajang''&lt;br /&gt;(사장)
|Often CEO of the corporation. Some companies do not have the &quot;chairman&quot; position, in which case the &quot;president&quot; is the top position that is equally respected and authoritative.
|-
|Deputy president&lt;br /&gt;or Senior executive vice president
|副社長
|''Fuku-shacho''
|''Bu-sajang''&lt;br /&gt;(부사장)
|Reports to the president
|-
|Executive vice president&lt;br /&gt;
|専務
|''Senmu''
|''Jŏnmu''&lt;br /&gt;(전무)
|
|-
|Senior vice president&lt;br /&gt;
|常務
|''Jomu''
|''Sangmu''&lt;br /&gt;(상무)
|
|-
|Vice president&lt;br /&gt;or general manager&lt;br /&gt;or department head
|部長
|''Bucho''
|''Bujang''&lt;br /&gt;(부장)
|Highest non-executive title; denotes a head of a division or department. There is significant variation in the official English translation used by different companies.
|-
|Deputy general manager
|次長
|''Jicho''
|''Chajang''&lt;br /&gt;(차장)
|Direct subordinate to ''bucho''/''bujang''
|-
|Manager&lt;br /&gt;or section head
|課長
|''Kacho''
|''Gwajang''&lt;br /&gt;(과장)
|Denotes a head of a team or section underneath a larger division/department
|-
|Assistant manager&lt;br /&gt;or team leader
|係長&lt;br /&gt;(代理)
|''Kakaricho''
|''Daeri'''&lt;br /&gt;(대리)
|
|-
|Staff
|社員
|''Shain''
|''Sawon''&lt;br /&gt;(사원)
|Staff without managerial titles are often referred to without using a title at all
|}

The top management group, comprising ''jomu''/''sangmu'' and above, is often referred to collectively as &quot;senior management&quot; (幹部 or 重役; ''kambu'' or ''juyaku'' in Japanese; ''ganbu'' or ''jungyŏk'' in Korean).

Some Japanese and Korean companies have also adopted American-style titles, but these are not yet widespread and their usage varies. For example, although there is a Korean translation for [[chief operating officer]] (''최고운영책임자, choego unyŏng chaegimja''), not many companies have yet adopted it with an exception of a few multi-national companies such as [[Samsung]] and [[CJ Corporation|CJ]], while the CFO title is often used alongside other titles such as ''bu-sajang'' (SEVP) or ''Jŏnmu'' (EVP).

Since the late 1990s, many Japanese companies have introduced the title of ''shikko yakuin'' (執行役員) or &quot;officer&quot;, seeking to emulate the separation of directors and officers found in American companies. In 2002, the statutory title of ''shikko yaku'' (執行役) was introduced for use in companies that introduced a three-committee structure in their board of directors. The titles are frequently given to ''bucho'' and higher-level personnel. Although the two titles are very similar in intent and usage, there are several legal distinctions: ''shikko yaku'' make their own decisions in the course of performing work delegated to them by the board of directors, and are considered managers of the company rather than employees, with a legal status similar to that of directors. ''Shikko yakuin'' are considered employees of the company that follow the decisions of the board of directors, although in some cases directors may have the ''shikko yakuin'' title as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=執行役／執行役員　Operating Officer|url=http://www.nri.co.jp/opinion/r_report/m_word/archive2/sikkouyakuin.html|publisher=[[Nomura Research Institute]]|accessdate=20 August 2013|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120722045228/http://www.nri.co.jp/opinion/r_report/m_word/archive2/sikkouyakuin.html|archivedate=22 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Suzuki|first=Kengo|title=執行役と執行役員の異同|url=http://www.kengosuzuki.com/archive/entries/200810/28post-40.html|accessdate=20 August 2013|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://archive.is/20130820002758/http://www.kengosuzuki.com/archive/entries/200810/28post-40.html|archivedate=20 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Senior management==

The highest-level executives in [[senior management]] usually have titles beginning with &quot;chief&quot; and ending with &quot;officer&quot;, forming what is often called the '''C-Suite''' or '''CxO''', where &quot;x&quot; is a [[Variable (computer science)|variable]] that could be any functional area; not to be confused with [[Chief experience officer|CXO]].  The traditional three such officers are CEO, COO, and CFO. Depending on the management structure, titles may exist instead of, or be blended/overlapped with, other traditional executive titles, such as ''[[President (corporate title)|president]]'', various designations of ''vice presidents'' (e.g. VP of marketing), and ''general managers'' or ''directors'' of various divisions (such as director of marketing); the latter may or may not imply membership of the ''board of directors''.

Certain other prominent positions have emerged, some of which are sector-specific. For example,  [[chief audit executive]] (CAE), chief procurement officer (CPO) and [[chief risk officer]] (CRO) positions are often found in many types of financial services companies. Technology companies of all sorts now tend to have a [[chief technology officer]] (CTO) to manage technology development. A [[chief information officer|CIO]] oversees information technology (IT) matters, either in companies that specialize in IT or in any kind of company that relies on it for supporting infrastructure.

Many companies now also have a CMO, particularly mature companies in competitive sectors, where [[brand management]] is a high priority. A chief value officer (CVO) is introduced in companies where business processes and organizational entities are focused on the creation and maximization of value. A [[chief administrative officer]] may be found in many large complex organizations that have various departments or divisions. Additionally, many companies now call their top diversity leadership position the [[chief diversity officer]] (CDO). However, this and many other nontraditional and lower-ranking titles are not universally recognized as corporate officers, and they tend to be specific to particular organizational cultures or the preferences of employees.

===Specific corporate officer positions===
* [[Chairman|Chairman of the board]] – presiding officer of the corporate board of directors. The chairman influences the board of directors, which in turn elects and removes the officers of a corporation and oversees the human, financial, environmental and technical operations of a corporation.
** The CEO may also hold the title of &quot;chairman&quot;, resulting in an executive chairman. In this case, the board frequently names an independent member of the board as a lead director.
** Executive chairman – the chairman's post may also exist as an office separate from that of CEO, and it is considered an executive chairman if that titleholder wields influence over company operations, such as [[Steve Case]] of [[AOL Time Warner]] and [[Douglas Flint]] of [[HSBC]]. In particular, the group chairmanship of HSBC is considered the top position of that institution, outranking the chief executive, and is responsible for leading the board and representing the company in meetings with government figures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/finance/newsbysector/banksandfinance/8019235/HSBC-investors-against-Michael-Geoghegan-becoming-chairman.html |title=HSBC investors against Michael Geoghegan becoming chairman |newspaper=Telegraph |date= 2010-09-22|accessdate=2011-12-31 |location=London |first1=Harry |last1=Wilson |first2=Sean |last2=Farrell |first3=Philip |last3=Aldrick}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.news.com.au/business/hsbc-chief-michael-geoghegan-to-quit-after-failing-to-get-top-job/story-e6frfm1i-1225928665163 |title=HSBC chief Michael Geoghegan 'to quit' after failing to get top job |publisher=News.com.au |date=2010-09-24 |accessdate=2011-12-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to the creation of the group management board in 2006, HSBC's chairman essentially held the duties of a chief executive at an equivalent institution, while HSBC's chief executive served as the deputy. After the 2006 reorganization, the management cadre ran the business, while the chairman oversaw the controls of the business through compliance and audit and the direction of the business.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/finance/newsbysector/banksandfinance/8212815/HSBC-ex-chief-Michael-Geoghegan-relaxes-as-another-marathon-looms.html |title=HSBC ex-chief Michael Geoghegan relaxes as another marathon looms |newspaper=Telegraph |date= 2010-12-20|accessdate=2011-12-31 |location=London |first=Damian |last=Reece}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** Non-executive chairman – also a separate post from the CEO, unlike an executive chairman, a non-executive chairman does not interfere in day-to-day company matters. Across the world, many companies have separated the roles of chairman and CEO, often resulting in a non-executive chairman, saying that this move improves corporate governance.
* [[Chief business officer]] is a corporate senior executive who assumes full management responsibility for the company's deal making, provides leadership and executes a deal strategy that will allow the company to fulfill its scientific/technology mission and build shareholder value, provides managerial guidance to the company's product development staff as needed.
* [[Chief of staff]] is a corporate director level manager who has overall responsibility for the staff activity within the company who often would have responsibility of hiring and firing of the highest level managers and sometimes directors. They can work with and report directly to managing directors and the chief executive officer.
* [[Commissioner]]
* [[Comptroller|Financial control officer]], FCO or FC, also comptroller or controller – supervises accounting and financial reporting within an organization
* Director or member of a board of directors – high-level official with a fiduciary responsibility of overseeing the operation of a corporation and elects or removes officers of a corporation; nominally, ''directors'', other than the ''chairman'' are usually not considered to be employees of the company ''per se'', although they may receive compensation, often including benefits; in publicly held companies. A ''board of directors'' is normally made up of members (''directors'') who are a mixture of corporate officials who are also management employees of the company ([[inside director]]s) and persons who are not employed by the company in any capacity ([[outside director]]s or [[non-executive director]]s). In privately held companies, the ''board of directors'' often only consists of the statutory corporate officials, and in ''sole proprietorship'' and ''partnerships'', the board is entirely optional, and if it does exist, only operates in an advisory capacity to the owner or ''partners''. Non-profit corporations’ governing board members may be called ''directors'' like most for-profit corporations, or an alternative like ''trustees'', ''governors'', etc.
* [[Director (business)|Director]] – a manager of managers within an organization who is often responsible for a major business function and who sometimes reports to a vice president (note that in some financial services companies the title vice president has a different meaning). Often used with name of a functional area; ''finance director'', ''director of finance'', ''marketing director'', and so on. Not to be confused with a ''member of the board of directors'', who is also referred to as a ''director''. This is a middle management and not an executive level position, unless it is in the banking industry. Alternatively, a manager of managers is often referred to as a &quot;senior manager' or as an &quot;associate vice president&quot;, depending upon levels of management, and industry type.
* [[President (corporate title)|President]] – legally recognized highest &quot;titled&quot; corporate officer, and usually a member of the board of directors. There is much variation; often the CEO also holds the title of president, while in other organizations if there is a separate CEO, the president is then second highest-ranking position. In such a case the president is often the COO and is considered to be more focused upon daily operations compared to the CEO, who is supposed to be the visionary. If the corporate president is not the COO (such as [[Richard Parsons (businessman)|Richard Parsons]] of Time Warner from 1995–2001), then many division heads report directly to the CEO themselves, with the president taking on special assignments from the CEO.
* [[Secretary]] or [[company secretary]] – legally recognized &quot;titled&quot; corporate officer who reports to the board of directors and is responsible for keeping the records of the board and the company. This title is often concurrently held by the ''treasurer'' in a dual position called ''secretary-treasurer''; both positions may be concurrently held by the ''CFO''. Note, however, that the ''secretary'' has a reporting line to the board of directors, regardless of any other reporting lines conferred by concurrent titles.
* [[Treasurer]] – legally recognized corporate officer entrusted with the fiduciary responsibility of caring for company funds. Often this title is held concurrently with that of ''secretary'' in a dual role called ''secretary-treasurer''. It can also be held concurrently with the title of ''CFO'' or fall under the jurisdiction of one, though the CFO tends to oversee the finance department instead, which deals with accounting and audits, while the treasurer deals directly with company funds. Note, however, that the ''treasurer'' has a reporting line to the board of directors, regardless of any other reporting lines conferred by concurrent titles.
* [[Superintendent (disambiguation)|Superintendent]]
* [[Ownership|Owner]] (sometimes proprietor or sole proprietor, for [[sole proprietorship]]s)
* [[Partner (business rank)|Partner]] – Used in many different ways. This may indicate a co-owner as in a legal partnership or may be used in a general way to refer to a broad class of employees or temporary/contract workers who are often assigned field or customer service work. Associate is often used in a similar way.
* Vice chair or [[vice chairman]] – officer of the board of directors who may stand in for the ''chairman'' in his or her absence. However, this type of vice chairman title on its own usually has only an advisory role and not an operational one (such as [[Ted Turner]] at Time Warner).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first= James | last= Welsh|url=http://www.digitalspy.com/ustv/news/a10201/ted-turner-quits-as-aoltw-vice-chairman.html |title=Ted Turner quits as AOLTW Vice Chairman |website=Digital Spy |date=2003-01-29 |accessdate=2011-12-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; An unrelated definition of ''vice chair'' describes an executive who is higher ranking or has more seniority than ''executive vice president''. Sometimes, EVPs report to the vice chair, who in turn reports directly to the CEO (so vice chairs in effect constitute an additional layer of management), other vice chairs have more responsibilities but are otherwise on an equal tier with EVPs. Executive vice chairman are usually ''not'' on the board of directors. [[Royal Bank of Canada]] previously used vice chairs in their inner management circle until 2004 but have since renamed them as ''group heads''.

===List of chief officer (CO) titles===

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable mw-collapsible &quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|+
|-
! scope=&quot;col&quot; style=&quot;width: 30%;&quot; | Title 
! scope=&quot;col&quot; style=&quot;width: 8%;&quot; | [[Post-nominal letters|Postnominal]] 
! scope=&quot;col&quot; style=&quot;width: 62%;&quot; | Explanation 
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief academic officer}} [[chief academic officer]] || CAO || Responsible for [[academic administration]] at [[university|universities]] and other [[higher education]] institutions 
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief accessibility officer}} [[chief accessibility officer]] || CAO || Responsible for overseeing [[accessibility]] and [[Inclusion (disability rights)|inclusion]] for [[Disability|People with Disabilities]] and [[Old age#Senior citizen|seniors]]
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief accounting officer}} [[chief accounting officer]] || CAO || Responsible for overseeing all [[accounting]] and [[bookkeeping]] functions, ensuring that [[ledger]] accounts, [[financial statement]]s, and [[cost control]] systems are operating effectively
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief administrative officer}} [[chief administrative officer]] || CAO || Responsible for [[business administration]], including daily operations and overall performance
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief artificial intelligence officer}} chief artificial intelligence officer || CAIO || Responsible for AI research department
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief analytics officer}} [[chief analytics officer]] || CAO || Responsible for [[data analysis]] and interpretation
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief architect (disambiguation)|chief architect}} [[chief architect (disambiguation)|chief architect]] || CA || Responsible for designing systems for [[high availability]] and [[scalability]], specifically in technology companies. Often called enterprise architects (EA).
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief audit executive}} [[chief audit executive]] || CAE || Responsible for the [[internal audit]]
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief business officer}} [[chief business officer]] || CBO || Responsible for the company's deal making, provides leadership and execute a deal strategy that will allow the company to fulfill its scientific/technology mission and build shareholder value, provides managerial guidance to the company's product development staff as needed.
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief business development officer}} [[chief business development officer]] || CBDO || Responsible for [[business development]] plans, design and implementation of processes to support business growth
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief brand officer}} [[chief brand officer]] || CBO || Responsible for a [[brand]]'s image, experience, and promise, and propagating it throughout all aspects of the company, overseeing [[marketing]], [[advertising]], design, [[public relations]] and [[customer service]] departments
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief commercial officer}} [[chief commercial officer]] || CCO || Responsible for [[commerce|commercial]] strategy and development
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief communications officer}} [[chief communications officer]] || CCO || Responsible for communications to employees, shareholders, media, bloggers, [[Influencer marketing|influencers]], the press, the community, and the public. Practical application of [[communication studies]]
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief compliance officer}} [[chief compliance officer]] || CCO || Responsible for overseeing and managing [[regulatory compliance]].
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief content officer}} [[chief content officer]] || CCO || Responsible for developing and commissioning content for [[broadcasting]] channels and [[multimedia]] exploitation
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief creative officer}} [[chief creative officer]] || CCO || In one sense of the term, responsible for the overall look and feel of marketing, media, and branding. In another sense, similar to chief design officer.
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief customer officer}} [[chief customer officer]] || CCO || Responsible for [[customer relationship management]]
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief development officer}} chief development officer || CDO || Responsible for activities developing the business, usually through added products, added clients, markets or segments
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief data officer}} [[chief data officer]] || CDO || Responsible for enterprise-wide governance and utilization of information and data as assets, via [[data processing]], [[data analysis]], [[data mining]], information trading, and other means
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief design officer}} [[chief design officer]] || CDO || Responsible for overseeing all design aspects of a company's products and services, including [[product design]], [[graphic design]], user experience design, [[industrial design]], and [[package design]], and possibly aspects of advertising, marketing, and engineering
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief digital officer}} [[chief digital officer]] || CDO || Responsible for adoption of [[digital economy|digital technologies]], digital consumer experiences, the process of [[digital transformation]], and devising and executing social strategies
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief diversity officer}} [[chief diversity officer]] || CDO || Responsible for [[diversity (politics)|diversity]] and inclusion, including [[diversity training]] and [[equal employment opportunity]]
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief engineering officer}} [[chief engineering officer]] || CEngO || Similar to the more common chief technology officer (CTO); responsible for technology/product R &amp; D and manufacturing issues in a technology company, oversees the development of technology being [[commercialization|commercialized]]
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief executive officer}} [[chief executive officer]] || CEO || Responsible for the overall vision and direction of an organization, making the final decisions over all of the corporation's operations. The highest-ranking management officer; often also the [[chairman of the board]]. Usually called CEO in the United States, chief executive or [[managing director]] in the United Kingdom, Commonwealth of Nations, and some other countries. 
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief experience officer}} [[chief experience officer]] || CXO || Responsible for [[user experience]], overseeing [[user experience design]] and [[user interface design]]. ''CXO'' is not to be confused with ''CxO'', a term commonly used when referring to any one of various chief officers.
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief financial officer}} [[chief financial officer]] || CFO || Responsible for all aspects of finances
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief gaming officer}} [[chief gaming officer]] || CGO || Responsible for both the game development and the online/offline publishing functions of a company that makes [[video game]]s
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief human resources officer}} [[chief human resources officer]] || CHRO || Responsible for all aspects of [[human resource management]] and [[industrial relations]]
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief information officer}} [[chief information officer]] || CIO || Responsible for  IT, particularly in IT companies or companies that rely heavily on an IT infrastructure
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief information security officer}} [[chief information security officer]] || CISO || Responsible for [[information security]]
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief innovation officer}} [[chief innovation officer]] || CINO || Responsible for innovation
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief investment officer}} [[chief investment officer]] || CIO || Responsible for investment and for the [[asset liability management]] (ALM) of typical large financial institutions such as insurers, banks and/or pension funds
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief information technology officer}} chief information technology officer || CITO || Responsible for information technology. Often equivalent to chief information officer (CIO) and, in a company that sells IT, chief technology officer (CTO).
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief knowledge officer}} [[chief knowledge officer]] || CKO || Responsible for managing [[intellectual capital]] and [[knowledge management]]
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief legal officer}} [[chief legal officer]] || CLO || Responsible for overseeing and identifying legal issues in all departments and their interrelation, as well as [[corporate governance]] and business policy. Often called [[general counsel]] (GC) or chief counsel.
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief learning officer}} [[chief learning officer]] || CLO || Responsible for learning and training
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief marketing officer}} [[chief marketing officer]] || CMO || Responsible for marketing; job may include sales management, product development, [[distribution channel]] management, marketing communications (including advertising and promotions), [[pricing]], [[market research]], and [[customer service]].
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief medical officer}} [[chief medical officer]] || CMO || Responsible for scientific and medical excellence, especially in [[pharmaceutical industry|pharmaceutical companies]], [[health system]]s, [[hospital]]s, and integrated provider networks. The title is used in many countries for the senior government official who advises on matters of [[public health]] importance. In the latter sense compare also [[Chief Dental Officer (Canada)|chief dental officer]].
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief networking officer}} [[chief networking officer]] || CNO || Responsible for [[social capital]] within the company and between the company and its partners
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief nursing officer}} [[chief nursing officer]] || CNO || Responsible for nursing
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief operating officer}} [[chief operating officer]] || COO || Responsible for [[business operations]], including [[operations management]], [[operations research]], and (when applicable) [[manufacturing operations]]; role is highly contingent and situational, changing from company to company and even from a CEO to their successor within the same company. Often called &quot;director of operations&quot; in the nonprofit sector.
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief privacy officer}} [[chief privacy officer]] || CPO || Responsible for all the privacy of the data in an organization, including [[privacy policy]] enforcement
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief process officer}} [[chief process officer]] || CPO || Responsible for [[business process]]es and applied [[process theory]], defining rules, policies, and guidelines to ensure that the main objectives follow the company strategy as well as establishing control mechanisms
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief procurement officer}} [[chief procurement officer]] || CPO || Responsible for [[procurement]], sourcing goods and services and negotiating prices and contracts
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief product officer}} [[chief product officer]] || CPO || Responsible for all product-related matters. The CPO is to the business's product what the CTO is to technology. The responsibilities of the CPO are inclusive of product vision, product strategy, user experience, product design, product development, and product marketing.
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief quality officer}} chief quality officer || CQO || Responsible for quality and [[quality assurance]], setting up quality goals and ensuring that those goals continue to be met over time
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief research and development officer}} chief research and development officer || CRDO || Responsible for [[research and development]]
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief research officer}} [[chief research officer]] || CRO || Responsible for research
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief revenue officer}} [[chief revenue officer]] || CRO || Responsible for measuring and maximizing revenue
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief risk officer}} [[chief risk officer]] || CRO || Responsible for [[risk management]], ensuring that risk is avoided, controlled, accepted, or transferred and that opportunities are not missed. Sometimes called chief risk management officer (CRMO).
|-
|chief system engineer
|CSE
|Responsible for the whole system specification, validation, and verification in development processess. Usually using as the manager of other sub-system engineers.
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief sales officer}} chief sales officer || CSO || Responsible for sales
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief science officer}} [[chief science officer]] || CSO || Responsible for science, usually [[applied science]], including research and development and [[new technologies]] Sometimes called chief scientist.
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief security officer}} [[chief security officer]] || CSO || Responsible for security, including physical security and [[network security]]
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief solutions officer}} [[chief solutions officer]]|| CSO || Responsible for the development and delivery of reliable and innovative business and technology solutions
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief strategy officer}} [[chief strategy officer]] || CSO || Responsible for strategy, usually [[business strategy]], including [[strategic planning]] and [[strategic management]]. Assists the chief executive officer with developing, communicating, executing, and sustaining strategy. Sometimes called chief strategic planning officer (CSPO).
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief sustainability officer}} [[chief sustainability officer]] || CSO || Responsible for environmental/sustainability programs.
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief technology officer}} [[chief technology officer]] || CTO || Responsible for technology and research and development, overseeing the development of technology [[commercialization|to be commercialized]]. (For an information technology company, the subject matter would be similar to the CIO's; however, the CTO's focus is technology for the firm to ''sell'' versus technology used for facilitating the firm's own operations.). Sometimes called chief technical officer.
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief value officer}} chief value officer || CVO || Ensure that all programs, actions, new products, services and investments create and capture customer value.
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief visionary officer}} [[chief visionary officer]] || CVO || Responsible for defining corporate [[vision statement|vision]], business strategy, and working plans
|-
| {{Anchor|Chief web officer}} [[chief web officer]] || CWO || Responsible for the [[web presence]] of the company and usually for the entire online presence, including [[intranet]] and Internet (web, [[mobile app]]s, other)

|}

==Middle management==
* [[Supervisor]]
* [[Shop foreman|Foreman]]
* [[General manager]] or GM
* [[Manager (disambiguation)|Manager]]
* [[Of Counsel]] – A lawyer working on a part-time or temporary basis for a company or law firm.
* [[Vice president]] – Middle or upper manager in a corporation. They often appear in various hierarchical layers such as ''executive vice president'', ''senior vice president'', ''associate vice president'', or ''assistant vice president'', with EVP usually considered the highest and usually reporting to the CEO or president. Many times, corporate officers such as the ''CFO'', ''COO'', ''CIO'', ''CTO'', ''secretary'', or ''treasurer'' will concurrently hold ''vice president'' titles, commonly EVP or SVP. Vice presidents in small companies are also referred to as chiefs of a certain division, such as vice president for finance, or vice president for administration. Note that in some financial contexts, the title of vice president is actually subordinate to a director.

==See also==
{{portal|Companies}}
* [[Corporate governance]]
* [[Corporate liability]]
* [[Imputation (law)|Identification with corporation]]
* [[List of corporate titles]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20160306092218/https://www.fbi.gov/news/stories/2013/november/taking-stoc-corporate-execs-get-scammed Taking Stock - Corporate Execs Get Scammed], [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]]

{{Corporate titles}}
{{Aspects of corporations}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Corporate Title}}
[[Category:Corporate titles|*]]
[[Category:Business occupations|Title]]
[[Category:Corporate directors|.]]
[[Category:Corporation-related lists]]
[[Category:Lists of occupations]]
[[Category:Management occupations]]
[[Category:Positions of authority]]</text>
      <sha1>muh06ft2f0vtkpkza4dn4knp18om117</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
