  <page>
    <title>Copula (linguistics)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5630</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940771103</id>
      <parentid>939684635</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-14T14:37:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>186.47.46.98</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Meanings */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Grammatical concept marking the notion of &quot;is&quot; or &quot;to be&quot;; sometimes implied and often a verb}}

In [[linguistics]], a '''copula''' (plural: '''copulas''' or '''copulae'''; [[list of glossing abbreviations|abbreviated]] {{smallcaps|'''cop'''}}) is a word that links the [[subject (grammar)|subject]] of a [[sentence (linguistics)|sentence]] to a [[subject complement]], such as the word ''is'' in the sentence &quot;The sky '''is''' blue.&quot; The word ''copula'' derives from the [[Latin]] noun for a &quot;link&quot; or &quot;tie&quot; that connects two different things.&lt;ref&gt;See the appendix to Moro 1997 and the references cited there for a short history of the copula.&lt;/ref&gt;

A copula is often a [[verb]] or a verb-like word, though this is not universally the case.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pustet&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Pustet |first=Regina |title=Copulas: Universals in the Categorization of the Lexicon |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-LWcB_FcaIQC&amp;pg=PA54&amp;lpg=PA54&amp;focus=viewport&amp;vq=%22Frajzyngier+(1986)+argues+that+copulas+may+also+develop+from+prepositions%22&amp;dq=Pustet,+Regina+(2005).+Copulas:+Universals+in+the+Categorization+of+the+Lexicon. |date=12 June 2003 |publisher=Oxford University Press |isbn=978-0-19-155530-5 |page=54|quote=Frajzyngier (1986) argues that copulas may also develop from prepositions}}&lt;/ref&gt; A verb that is a copula is sometimes called a '''copulative''' or '''copular verb'''.  In English [[primary education]] [[grammar]] courses, a copula is often called a [[linking verb]]. In other languages, copulas show more resemblances to [[pronoun]]s, as in [[Classical Chinese]] and [[Guarani language|Guarani]], or may take the form of [[suffix]]es attached to a noun, as in [[Korean language|Korean]], [[Beja language|Beja]], and [[Inuit languages]].

Most languages have one main copula, although some (like [[Spanish language|Spanish]], [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]] and [[Thai language|Thai]]) have more than one, and some have [[#Zero copula|none]]. In the case of English, this is the verb ''to be''. While the term ''copula'' is generally used to refer to such principal forms, it may also be used to refer to some other verbs with similar functions, like ''become'', ''get'', ''feel'' and ''seem'' in English (these may also be called &quot;semi-copulas&quot; or &quot;pseudo-copulas&quot;).

==Grammatical function==
The principal use of a copula is to link the [[subject (grammar)|subject]] of a [[clause (grammar)|clause]] to a [[subject complement]]. A copular verb is often considered to be part of the [[predicate (grammar)|predicate]], the remainder being called a [[predicative expression]]. A simple clause containing a copula is illustrated below:
::The book '''is''' on the table.
In that sentence, the [[noun phrase]] ''the book'' is the subject, the verb ''is'' serves as the copula, and the [[prepositional phrase]] ''on the table'' is the predicative expression. The whole expression ''is on the table'' may (in some theories of grammar) be called a predicate or a [[verb phrase]].

The predicative expression accompanying the copula, also known as the [[complement (grammar)|complement]] of the copula, may take any of several possible forms: it may be a noun or noun phrase, an [[adjective]] or adjective phrase, a prepositional phrase (as above) or another adverb or adverbial phrase expressing time or location. Examples are given below (with the copula in bold and the predicative expression in italics):
::Mary and John '''are''' ''my friends''.
::The sky '''was''' ''blue''.
::I '''am''' ''taller than most people''.
::The birds and the beasts '''were''' ''there''.

The three components (subject, copula and predicative expression) do not necessarily appear in that order: their positioning depends on the rules for [[word order]] applicable to the language in question. In English (an [[subject-verb-object|SVO]] language) the ordering given is the normal one, but here too, certain variation is possible:
*In many questions and other clauses with [[subject–auxiliary inversion]], the copula moves in front of the subject: '''''Are you''' happy?''
*In [[inverse copular constructions]] (see below) the predicative expression precedes the copula, but the subject follows it: ''In the room were three men.''

It is also possible, in certain circumstances, for one (or even two) of the three components to be absent:
*In [[null-subject language|null-subject]] (pro-drop) languages, the subject may be omitted, as it may from other types of sentence. In Italian, ''sono stanco'' means &quot;I am tired&quot;, literally &quot;am tired&quot;.
*In [[non-finite clause]]s in languages like English, the subject is often absent, as in the [[participial phrase]] ''being tired'' or the [[infinitive phrase]] ''to be tired''. The same applies to most imperative sentences like ''Be good!''
*For cases in which no copula appears, see {{slink||Zero copula}} below.
*Any of the three components may be omitted as a result of various general types of [[ellipsis (grammar)|ellipsis]]. In particular, in English, the predicative expression may be elided in a construction similar to [[verb phrase ellipsis]], as in short sentences like ''I am''; ''Are they?'' (where the predicative expression is understood from the previous context).

[[Inverse copular constructions]], in which the positions of the predicative expression and the subject are reversed, are found in various languages.&lt;ref&gt;See Everaert et al. 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; They have been the subject of much theoretical analysis, particularly in regard to the difficulty of maintaining, in the case of such sentences, the usual division into a subject [[noun phrase]] and a predicate [[verb phrase]].

Another issue is [[agreement (linguistics)|verb agreement]] when both subject and predicative expression are noun phrases (and differ in number or person): in English, the copula normally agrees with the preceding phrase even if it is not logically the subject, as in ''the cause of the riot '''is''''' (not ''are'') ''these pictures of the wall''. Compare Italian ''la causa della rivolta '''sono''''' (&quot;are&quot;, not ''è'' &quot;is&quot;) ''queste foto del muro''.

The precise definition and scope of the concept of a copula is not necessarily precise in any language. For example, in English though the concept of the copula is most strongly associated with the verb ''be'', there are many other verbs that can be used in a copular sense as well. For example,&lt;ref name=&quot;Givon&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=English Grammar: A function-based introduction | volume=1 | author=Givón, T. | publisher=John Benjamins Publishing Company | year=1993 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=TWZM1bFFMSkC | pages=103-104}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;EG&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=What are copular verbs? | url=https://www.englishgrammar.org/copular-verbs/ | date=November 15, 2010 | access-date=October 31, 2017 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171107014423/https://www.englishgrammar.org/copular-verbs/ | archive-date=November 7, 2017 | url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The boy '''became''' a man.
* The girl '''got''' excited by her new toy.
* The dog '''grew''' tired from the activity.

And even more tenuously&lt;ref name=&quot;Givon&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;EG&quot;/&gt;
* The milk '''turned''' sour.
* The food '''smells''' good.
* You '''seem''' upset.

==Meanings==
Predicates formed using a copula may express identity: that the two noun phrases (subject and complement) have the same [[referent]] or express an identical concept:
::I want only ''to be'' myself.
::The Morning Star ''is'' the Evening Star.
 
They may also express membership of a class or a [[subset]] relationship:
::She ''was'' a nurse.
::Cats ''are'' carnivorous mammals.

Similarly they may express some property, relation or position, permanent or temporary:
:: The trees ''are'' green.
:: I ''am'' your boss.
:: The hen ''is'' next to the cockerel.
:: The children ''are'' confused.

Other special uses of copular verbs are described in some of the following sections.

===Essence vs. state===
Some languages use different copulas, or different syntax, when denoting a permanent, essential characteristic of something and when denoting a temporary state. For examples, see the sections on the [[#Romance|Romance languages]], [[#Slavic|Slavic languages]] and [[#Irish|Irish]].

==Forms==
In many languages the principal copula is a [[verb]], like English ''(to) be'', German ''sein'', [[Mixtec language|Mixtec]] ''kuu'',&lt;ref name=&quot;Pustet2003Mixtec&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Regina Pustet|title=Copulas: Universals in the Categorization of the Lexicon|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-LWcB_FcaIQC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Pustet,+Regina+(2005).+Copulas:+Universals+in+the+Categorization+of+the+Lexicon.&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjFhL3rkoPgAhUi8YMKHXloAdIQ6AEIKjAA#v=snippet&amp;q=mixtec%20kuu&amp;f=false|date=12 June 2003|publisher=OUP Oxford|isbn=978-0-19-155530-5|page=47}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Tuareg languages|Touareg]] ''emous'',&lt;ref name=&quot;Stassen&quot; /&gt; etc. It may inflect for [[grammatical category|grammatical categories]] like [[grammatical tense|tense]], [[grammatical aspect|aspect]] and [[grammatical mood|mood]], like other verbs in the language. Being a very commonly used verb, it is likely that the copula has [[irregular verb|irregular]] inflected forms; in English, the verb ''be'' has a number of highly irregular ([[suppletion|suppletive]]) forms and has more different inflected forms than any other English verb (''am'', ''is'', ''are'', ''was'', ''were'', etc.; see [[English verbs]] for details).

Other copulas show more resemblances to [[pronoun]]s. That is the case for [[Classical Chinese]] and [[Guarani language|Guarani]], for instance. In highly [[synthetic language]]s, copulas are often [[suffix]]es, attached to a noun, but they may still behave otherwise like ordinary verbs: ''-u-'' in [[Inuit languages]].

In some other languages, like [[Beja language|Beja]] and [[Ket language|Ket]], the copula takes the form of suffixes that attach to a noun but are distinct from the [[grammatical conjugation|person agreement markers]] used on [[predicative verb]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stassen&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last=Stassen |first=Leon |year=1997 |title=Intransitive Predication |series=Oxford studies in typology and linguistic theory |publisher=Oxford University Press |page=39 |isbn=978-0-19-925893-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; This phenomenon is known as ''[[nonverbal person agreement]]'' (or ''nonverbal subject agreement''), and the relevant markers are always established as deriving from [[clitic]]ized independent pronouns.

For cases in which the copula is omitted or takes [[zero (linguistics)|zero]] form, see {{slink||Zero copula}} below.

==Additional uses of copular verbs==
A copular verb may also have other uses supplementary to or distinct from its uses as a copula.

===As auxiliary verbs===
The English copular verb ''be'' can be used as an [[English auxiliaries|auxiliary verb]], expressing [[passive voice]] (together with the [[past participle]]) or expressing [[progressive aspect]] (together with the [[present participle]]):
::The man '''was''' killed. (passive)
::It '''is''' raining. (progressive)
Other languages' copulas have additional uses as auxiliaries. For example, French ''être'' can be used to express passive voice similarly to English ''be'', and both French ''être'' and German ''sein'' are used to express the [[Perfect (grammar)|perfect forms]] of certain verbs:
::''Je '''suis''' arrivé.'' French for &quot;I have arrived,&quot; literally &quot;I am arrived.&quot;
The last usage was formerly prevalent in English also. The auxiliary functions of these verbs derive from their copular function, and can be interpreted as a special case of the copular function (the verbal form that follows it being considered adjectival).

Another auxiliary-type usage of the copula in English is together with the [[to-infinitive|''to''-infinitive]] to denote an obligatory action or expected occurrence: &quot;I am to serve you;&quot; &quot;The manager is to resign.&quot; It can be put also into past tense: &quot;We were to leave at 9.&quot; For forms like &quot;if I was/were to come,&quot; see [[English conditional sentences]]. (Note that by certain criteria, the English copula ''be'' may always be considered an auxiliary verb; see [[Auxiliary_verb#Diagnostics_for_identifying_auxiliary_verbs_in_English|Diagnostics for identifying auxiliary verbs in English]].)

===Existential usage===
The English ''to be'', and its equivalents in certain other languages, also have a non-copular use as an existential verb, meaning &quot;to exist.&quot; This use is illustrated in the following sentences: ''I want only '''to be''', and that is enough''; ''[[Cogito ergo sum|I think therefore I '''am''']]''; ''[[To be, or not to be|'''To be''' or not '''to be''']], that is the question.'' In these cases, the verb itself expresses a predicate (that of [[existence]]), rather than linking to a predicative expression as it does when used as a copula. In [[ontology]] it is sometimes suggested that the &quot;is&quot; of existence is reducible to the &quot;is&quot; of property attribution or class membership; to be, [[Aristotle]] held, is to be ''something''. However, [[Abelard]] in his ''Dialectica'' made a ''[[reductio ad absurdum]]'' argument against the idea that the copula can express existence.&lt;ref&gt;Kneale - Kneale 1962 and Moro 1997&lt;/ref&gt;

Similar examples can be found in many other languages; for example, the French and Latin equivalents of ''I think therefore I am'' are ''Je pense, donc je '''suis''''' and ''Cogito ergo '''sum''''', where ''suis'' and ''sum'' are the equivalents of English &quot;am,&quot; normally used as copulas. However, other languages prefer a different verb for existential use, as in the Spanish version ''Pienso, luego '''existo''''' (where the verb ''existir'' &quot;to exist&quot; is used rather than the copula ''ser'' or ''estar'' &quot;to be&quot;).

Another type of existential usage is in clauses of the ''[[there is]]...'' or ''there are...'' type. Languages differ in the way they express such meanings; some of them use the copular verb, possibly with an [[expletive pronoun]] like the English ''there'', while other languages use different verbs and constructions, like the French ''il y a'' (which uses parts of the verb ''avoir'' &quot;to have,&quot; not the copula ''être'') or the Swedish ''finns'' (the passive voice of the verb for &quot;to find&quot;). For details, see [[existential clause]].

Relying on a unified theory of copular sentences, it has been proposed that the English ''there''-sentences are subtypes of [[inverse copular construction]]s.&lt;ref&gt;See Moro 1997, and &quot;existential sentences and expletive ''there''&quot; in Everaert et al. 2006, for a detailed discussion of this issue and a historical survey of the major proposals.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Zero copula==
{{main article|Zero copula}}
In some languages, copula omission occurs within a particular grammatical context. For example, speakers of [[Russian language|Russian]], [[Indonesian language|Indonesian]], [[Turkish language|Turkish]], [[Hungarian language|Hungarian]], [[Arabic language|Arabic]], [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]], and [[Quechuan languages]] consistently drop the copula in present tense: Russian: я человек, ''ya chelovek'' &quot;I (am a) person;&quot; Indonesian: ''saya seorang manusia'' &quot;I (am) a human;&quot; Turkish: ''o insan'' &quot;s/he (is a) human;&quot; Hungarian: ''ő ember'' &quot;s/he (is) a human;&quot; Arabic: أنا إنسان, ''ʔanā ʔinsān'' &quot;I (am a) human;&quot; Hebrew: אני אדם, ''ʔani ʔadam'' &quot;I (am a) human;&quot; Southern Quechua: ''payqa runam'' &quot;s/he (is) a human.&quot;  The usage is known generically as the zero copula. Note that in other tenses (sometimes in forms other than third person singular), the copula usually reappears.

Some languages drop the copula in poetic or [[Aphorism|aphorismic]] contexts. Examples in English include
* ''The more, the better.''
* ''Out of many, one.''
* ''True that.''
Such poetic copula dropping is more pronounced in some languages other than English, like the [[Romance language]]s.

In informal speech of English, the copula may also be dropped in general sentences, as in &quot;She a nurse.&quot; It is a feature of [[African-American Vernacular English]], but is also used by a variety of other English speakers in informal contexts. An example is the sentence &quot;I saw twelve men, each a soldier.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Bender |first=Emily |year=2001 |title=Syntactic Variation and Linguistic Competence: The Case of AAVE Copula Absence |type=Ph.D. Dissertation |publisher=Stanford University |url=http://faculty.washington.edu/ebender/dissertation/bender_thesis.pdf}}{{page needed|date=January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Examples in specific languages===
In Ancient Greek, when an adjective precedes a noun with an article, the copula is understood: ὁ οἴκος ἐστὶ μακρός, &quot;the house is large,&quot; can be written μακρός ὁ οἴκος, &quot;large the house (is).&quot;{{citation needed|date=October 2015}}

In Quechua ([[Southern Quechua]] used for the examples), zero copula is restricted to present tense in third person singular (''kan''): ''Payqa runam'' &amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; &quot;(s)he is a human;&quot; but: ''(paykuna) runakunam kanku'' &quot;(they) are human.&quot;ap{{citation needed|reason=English, Hungarian, and Irish are treated at 'Zero copula'. There are no references for Greek or Quechua here or on that page.|date=February 2014}}

In [[Māori language|Māori]], the zero copula can be used in [[predicative expression]]s and with continuous verbs (many of which take a copulative verb in many Indo-European languages)&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; ''He nui te whare'', literally &quot;a big the house,&quot; &quot;the house (is) big;&quot; ''I te tēpu te pukapuka'', literally &quot;at (past [[locative]] particle) the table the book,&quot; &quot;the book (was) on the table;&quot; ''Nō Ingarangi ia'', literally &quot;from England (s)he,&quot; &quot;(s)he (is) from England,&quot; ''Kei te kai au'', literally &quot;at the (act of) eating I,&quot; &quot;I (am) eating.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://wals.info/languoid/lect/wals_code_mao |title=Language Maori |publisher=WALS Online |accessdate=2014-02-07 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140306092639/http://wals.info/languoid/lect/wals_code_mao |archive-date=2014-03-06 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | last = Moorfield | first = John | year = 2004 | title = Te Kākano | publisher = University of Waikato}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Alternatively, in many cases, the particle ''ko'' can be used as a copulative (though not all instances of ''ko'' are used as thus, like all other Maori particles, ''ko'' has multiple purposes): ''Ko nui te whare'' &quot;The house is big;&quot; ''Ko te pukapuka kei te tēpu'' &quot;It is the book (that is) on the table;&quot; ''Ko au kei te kai'' &quot;It is me eating.&quot;

However, when expressing identity or class membership, ''ko'' must be used: ''Ko tēnei tāku pukapuka'' &quot;This is my book;&quot; ''Ko Ōtautahi he tāone i Te Waipounamu'' &quot;Christchurch is a city in the South Island (of New Zealand);&quot; ''Ko koe tōku hoa'' &quot;You are my friend.&quot;

Note that when expressing identity, ''ko'' can be placed on either object in the clause without changing the meaning (''ko tēnei tāku pukapuka'' is the same as ''ko tāku pukapuka tēnei'') but not on both (''ko tēnei ko tāku pukapuka'' would be equivalent to saying &quot;it is this, it is my book&quot; in English).
&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = Barlow | first = D. Cleve | year = 1981 | title = The Meaning of Ko in New Zealand Maori | journal = Pacific Studies | volume = 4 | pages = 124–141 | url = https://ojs.lib.byu.edu/spc/index.php/PacificStudies/article/viewFile/9191/8840 | accessdate = February 7, 2014 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20140221165723/https://ojs.lib.byu.edu/spc/index.php/PacificStudies/article/viewFile/9191/8840 | archive-date = February 21, 2014 | url-status = dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Hungarian, zero copula is restricted to present tense in third person singular and plural: ''Ő ember''/''Ők emberek''&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; &quot;s/he is a human&quot;/&quot;they are humans;&quot; but: ''(én) ember vagyok'' &quot;I am a human,&quot; ''(te) ember vagy'' &quot;you are a human,&quot; ''mi emberek vagyunk'' &quot;we are humans,&quot; ''(ti) emberek vagytok'' &quot;you (all) are humans.&quot; The copula also reappears for stating locations: ''az emberek a házban vannak'', &quot;the people are in the house,&quot; and for stating time: ''hat óra van'', &quot;it is six o'clock.&quot; However, the copula may be omitted in colloquial language: ''hat óra (van)'', &quot;it is six o'clock.&quot;

Hungarian uses copula ''lenni'' for expressing location: ''Itt van Róbert'' &quot;Bob is here,&quot; but it is omitted in the third person present tense for attribution or identity statements: ''Róbert öreg'' &quot;Bob is old;&quot; ''ők éhesek'' &quot;They are hungry;&quot; ''Kati nyelvtudós'' &quot;Cathy is a linguist&quot; (but ''Róbert öreg volt'' &quot;Bob was old,&quot; ''éhesek voltak'' &quot;They were hungry,&quot; ''Kati nyelvtudós volt'' &quot;Cathy was a linguist).

In Turkish, both the third person singular and the third person plural copulas are omittable. ''Ali burada'' and ''Ali burada'''dır''''' both mean &quot;Ali is here,&quot; and ''Onlar aç'' and ''Onlar aç'''lar''''' both mean &quot;They are hungry.&quot; Both of the sentences are acceptable and grammatically correct, but sentences with the copula are more formal.

The Turkish first person singular copula suffix is omitted when introducing oneself. ''Bora ben'' (I am Bora) is grammatically correct, but &quot;Bora ben'''im'''&quot; (same sentence with the copula) is not for an introduction (but is grammatically correct in other cases).

Further restrictions may apply before omission is permitted. For example, in the [[Irish language]], ''is'', the present tense of the copula, may be omitted when the [[predicate (grammar)|predicate]] is a noun. ''Ba'', the past/conditional, cannot be deleted. If the present copula is omitted, the pronoun (e.g., ''é, í, iad'') preceding the noun is omitted as well.

==Additional copulas==
Sometimes, the term ''copula'' is taken to include not only a language's equivalent(s) to the verb ''be'' but also other verbs or forms that serve to link a subject to a predicative expression (while adding [[semantic]] content of their own). For example, English verbs like ''become'', ''get'', ''feel'', ''look'', ''taste'', ''smell'', and ''seem'' can have this function, as in the following sentences (the predicative expression, the complement of the verb, is in italics):
::She became ''a student''.
::They look ''tired''.
::The milk tastes ''bad''.
::That bread smells ''good''.
::I feel ''bad'' that she can't come with us.
::London ''stands'' (is) on the river Thames.
::How is Mary? ; She ''seems'' (is) well (fine).
(This usage should be distinguished from the use of some of these verbs as &quot;action&quot; verbs, as in ''They look at the wall'', in which ''look'' denotes an action and cannot be replaced by the basic copula ''are''.)

Some verbs have rarer, secondary uses as copular verbs, like the verb ''fall'' in sentences like ''The zebra fell victim to the lion.''

These extra copulas are sometimes called &quot;semi-copulas&quot; or &quot;pseudo-copulas.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=C.S. |last=Butler |title=Structure and Function: A Guide to the Three Major Structural-Functional Theories |publisher=John Benjamins Publishing |year=2003 |pages=425–6 |doi=10.1075/slcs.63 |isbn=9789027296535}}&lt;/ref&gt; For a list of common verbs of this type in English, see [[List of English copulae]].

==In particular languages==

===Indo-European===
{{main article|Indo-European copula}}
In [[Indo-European language]]s, the words meaning ''to be'' are sometimes similar to each other. Due to the high frequency of their use, their inflection retains a considerable degree of similarity in some cases. Thus, for example, the English form ''is'' is a [[cognate]] of German ''ist'', Latin ''est'', Persian ''ast'' and Russian ''&lt;nowiki&gt;jest'&lt;/nowiki&gt;'', even though the Germanic, Italic, Iranian and Slavic language groups split at least 3000 years ago. The origins of the copulas of most Indo-European languages can be traced back to four [[Proto-Indo-European language|Proto-Indo-European]] stems: ''*es-'' (''*h&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;es-''), ''*sta-'' (''*steh&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-''), ''*wes-'' and ''*bhu-'' (''*bʰuH-'').

====English====
{{Redirect|Is||IS (disambiguation){{!}}IS}}
{{redirect|To be|other uses|To Be (disambiguation){{!}}To Be}}
The English copular verb ''be'' has eight forms (more than any other English verb): ''be'', ''am'', ''is'', ''are'', ''being'', ''was'', ''were'', ''been''. Additional archaic forms include ''art'', ''wast'', ''wert'', and occasionally ''beest'' (as a [[English subjunctive|subjunctive]]). For more details see [[English verbs]]. For the etymology of the various forms, see [[Indo-European copula]].

The main uses of the copula in English are described in the above sections. The possibility of copula omission is mentioned under {{slink||Zero copula}}.

A particular construction found in English (particularly in speech) is the use of [[double copula|two successive copulas]] when only one appears necessary, as in ''My point is, is that...''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite conference |url=http://linguistics.berkeley.edu/bls/previous_proceedings/bls32.pdf |title=&quot;The thing is, is&quot; Is No Mere Disfluency |last1=Coppock |first1=Elizabeth |last2=Brenier |first2=Jason |last3=Staum |first3=Laura |last4=Michaelis |first4=Laura |date=February 10, 2006 |publisher=Sheridan Books |book-title=Proceedings of the Thirty-second Annual Meeting of the Berkeley Linguistics Society |pages=85–96 |location=Berkeley, California |conference=32nd Annual Meeting of the Berkeley Linguistics Society |access-date=July 16, 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180717041608/http://linguistics.berkeley.edu/bls/previous_proceedings/bls32.pdf |archive-date=July 17, 2018 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; The acceptability of this construction is a [[English usage controversies|disputed matter in English prescriptive grammar]].

The simple English copula &quot;be&quot; may on occasion be substituted by other verbs with near identical meanings.

====Persian====
In Persian the verb to be can either take the form of ''ast'' cognate to English ''is'' or ''budan'' cognate to ''to be''.

:{| border=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;1&quot;
| align=left |  || align=right |  || align=left | 
|-
| Aseman abi ''ast''.
| {{lang|fa|&quot;آسمان آبی &quot;است}}
| the sky ''is'' blue
|-
| Aseman abi ''khahad bood''.
| {{lang|fa|&quot;آسمان آبی &quot;خواهد بود}}
| the sky ''will be'' blue
|-
| Aseman abi ''bood''.
| {{lang|fa|&quot;آسمان آبی &quot;بود}}
| the sky ''was'' blue

|}

====Romance====
{{main article|Romance copula}}
Copulas in the [[Romance languages]] usually consist of two different verbs that can be translated as &quot;to be,&quot; the main one from the Latin ''esse'' (via [[Vulgar Latin]] ''essere''; ''esse'' deriving from ''*es-''), often referenced as ''sum'' (another of the Latin verb's [[principal parts]]) and a secondary one from ''stare'' (from ''*sta-''), often referenced as ''sto''. The resulting distinction in the modern forms is found in all the [[Iberian Romance languages]], and to a lesser extent Italian, but not in French or Romanian. The difference is that the first usually refers to essential characteristics, while the second refers to states and situations, e.g., &quot;Bob is old&quot; versus &quot;Bob is well.&quot; A similar division is found in the non-Romance Basque language (viz. ''egon'' and ''izan''). (Note that the English words just used, &quot;essential&quot; and &quot;state,&quot; are also cognate with the Latin infinitives ''esse'' and ''stare''. The word &quot;stay&quot; also comes from Latin stare, through Middle French ''estai'', stem of Old French ''ester''.) In Spanish and Portuguese, the high degree of verbal [[inflection]], plus the existence of two copulas (''ser'' and ''estar''), means that there are 105 (Spanish) and 110 (Portuguese)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.conjuga-me.net |title=Conjugação de verbos regulares e irregulares |publisher=Conjuga-me |date=2007-09-06 |accessdate=2014-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; separate forms to express the copula, compared to eight in English and one in Chinese.

{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! rowspan=2 | Copula
! colspan=4 | Language
|-
! Italian
! Spanish
! Portuguese
! English
|- align=left
! align=left | ''Sum''-derived 
| ''Bob'' è ''vecchio''. || ''Bob'' es ''viejo''. || (O) ''Bob'' é ''velho''. || &quot;Bob is old.&quot;
|- align=left
! align=left | ''Sto''-derived
| ''Bob'' sta ''bene''. || ''Bob'' está ''bien''. || ''Bob'' está ''bem'' || &quot;Bob is well.&quot;
|}

In some cases, the verb itself changes the meaning of the adjective/sentence. The following examples are from Portuguese:

{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! rowspan=2 | Copula
! colspan=&quot;3&quot; | Example 1
! colspan=&quot;3&quot; | Example 2
|-
! Portuguese
!Spanish
! English
! Portuguese
!Spanish
! English
|- align=left
! align=left | ''Sum''-derived 
| ''O Bob'' é ''esquisito''. 
|''Bob'' es ''extraño''.|| &quot;Bob is weird.&quot; || ''O Bob'' é ''idiota''. 
|''Bob'' es ''idiota''.|| &quot;Bob is foolish.&quot;
|- align=left
! align=left | ''Sto''-derived
| ''O Bob'' está ''esquisito''. 
|''Bob'' está ''extraño''.|| &quot;Bob is looking/being strange.&quot; || ''O Bob'' está ''idiota''. 
|''Bob'' está ''idiota''.|| &quot;Bob is acting/being silly.&quot;
|}

====Slavic====
Some [[Slavic language]]s make a distinction between essence and state (similar to that discussed in the above section on the [[#Romance|Romance]] languages), by putting a predicative expression denoting a state into the [[instrumental case]], and essential characteristics are in the [[nominative case|nominative]]. This can apply with other copula verbs as well: the verbs for &quot;become&quot; are normally used with the instrumental case.

As noted above under {{slink||Zero copula}}, Russian and other [[East Slavic languages]] generally omit the copula in the present tense.

====Irish====
In [[Irish language|Irish]] and [[Scottish Gaelic]], there are two copulas, and the [[syntax]] is also changed when one is distinguishing between states or situations and essential characteristics.

Describing the subject's state or situation typically uses the normal [[verb–subject–object|VSO ordering]] with the verb ''bí''. The copula ''is'' is used to state essential characteristics or equivalences.

:{| border=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;1&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align=left valign=top|  || align=right valign=top |  || align=left valign=top | 
|- 
|Is ''fear é Liam''.|| &quot;Liam is a man.&quot; ||(Lit., &quot;Is man Liam.&quot;)
|- 
|Is ''leabhar é sin''.|| &quot;That is a book.&quot; ||(Lit., &quot;Is book it that.&quot;) 
|}

The word ''is'' is the copula (rhymes with the English word &quot;miss&quot;).

The pronoun used with the copula is different from the normal pronoun. For a masculine singular noun, ''é'' is used (for &quot;he&quot; or &quot;it&quot;), as opposed to the normal pronoun ''sé''; for a feminine singular noun, ''í'' is used (for &quot;she&quot; or &quot;it&quot;), as opposed to normal pronoun ''sí''; for plural nouns, ''iad'' is used (for &quot;they&quot; or &quot;those&quot;), as opposed to the normal pronoun ''siad''.&lt;ref&gt;Myles Dillon and Donncha ó Cróinín, Irish, Teach Yourself Books, Saint Paul's House, Warwick Lane London EC4. Lesson VIII, &quot;The Copula&quot;, p. 52&lt;/ref&gt;

To describe being in a state, condition, place, or act, the verb &quot;to be&quot; is used: ''Tá mé ag rith.'' &quot;I am running.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.teanglann.ie/ga/fgb/rith|title=Foclóir Gaeilge–Béarla (Ó Dónaill): rith|website=www.teanglann.ie}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bantu languages===
====Chichewa====
{{main|Chichewa tenses}}
In [[Chewa language|Chichewa]], a [[Bantu languages|Bantu]] language spoken mainly in [[Malawi]], a very similar distinction exists between permanent and temporary states as in Spanish and Portuguese, but only in the present tense. For a permanent state, in the 3rd person, the copula used in the present tense is ''ndi'' (negative ''sí''):&lt;ref&gt;Maxson, Nathaniel (2011). ''Chicheŵa for English Speakers: A New and Simplified Approach''. Assemblies of God Literature Press, Malawi, pp. 107, 108, 110.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;*[[Earl Stevick|Stevick, Earl]] et al. (1965). [https://web.archive.org/web/20160307012900/https://fsi-languages.yojik.eu/languages/Chinyanja/Fsi-ChinyanjaBasicCourse-StudentText.pdf ''Chinyanja Basic Course'']. Foreign Service Institute, Washington, D.C., pp. 157, 160–65.&lt;/ref&gt;
:''iyé '''ndi''' mphunzitsi'' &quot;he is a teacher&quot;
:''iyé '''sí''' mphunzitsi'' &quot;he is not a teacher&quot;

For the 1st and 2nd persons the particle ''ndi'' is combined with pronouns, e.g. ''ine'' &quot;I&quot;:
:''ine '''ndine''' mphunzitsi'' &quot;I am a teacher&quot;
:''iwe '''ndiwe''' mphunzitsi'' &quot;you (singular) are a teacher&quot;
:''ine '''síndine''' mphunzitsi'' &quot;I am not a teacher&quot;

For temporary states and location, the copula is the appropriate form of the defective verb ''-li'':
:''iyé '''ali''' bwino'' &quot;he is well&quot;
:''iyé '''sáli''' bwino'' &quot;he is not well&quot;
:''iyé '''ali''' ku nyumbá'' &quot;he is in the house&quot;

For the 1st and 2nd persons the person is shown, as normally with Chichewa verbs, by the appropriate pronominal prefix:
:''ine '''ndili''' bwino'' &quot;I am well&quot;
:''iwe '''uli''' bwino'' &quot;you (sg.) are well&quot;
:''kunyumbá '''kuli''' bwino'' &quot;at home (everything) is fine&quot;

In the past tenses, ''-li'' is used for both types of copula:
:''iyé '''analí''' bwino'' &quot;he was well (this morning)&quot;
:''iyé '''ánaalí''' mphunzitsi'' &quot;he was a teacher (at that time)&quot;

In the future, subjunctive, or conditional tenses, a form of the verb ''khala'' (&quot;sit/dwell&quot;) is used as a copula:
:''máwa '''ákhala''' bwino'' &quot;he'll be fine tomorrow&quot;

=== Muylaq' Aymaran ===

Uniquely, the existence of the copulative verbalizer suffix in the Southern Peruvian [[Aymara language|Aymaran]] language variety, Muylaq' Aymara, is evident only in the surfacing of a vowel that would otherwise have been deleted because of the presence of a following suffix, lexically prespecified to suppress it. As the copulative verbalizer has no independent phonetic structure, it is represented by the Greek letter ʋ in the examples used in this entry.

Accordingly, unlike in most other Aymaran variants, whose copulative verbalizer is expressed with a vowel-lengthening component, -'':'', the presence of the copulative verbalizer in Muylaq' Aymara is often not apparent on the surface at all and is analyzed as existing only meta-linguistically. However, it is also relevant to note that in a verb phrase like &quot;It is old,&quot; the noun ''thantha'' meaning &quot;old&quot; does not require the copulative verbalizer, ''thantha-wa'' &quot;It is old.&quot;

It is now pertinent to make some observations about the distribution of the copulative verbalizer. The best place to start is with words in which its presence or absence is obvious. When the vowel-suppressing first person simple tense suffix attaches to a verb, the vowel of the immediately preceding suffix is suppressed (in the examples in this subsection, the subscript &quot;c&quot; appears prior to vowel-suppressing suffixes in the interlinear gloss to better distinguish instances of [[Vowel deletion|deletion]] that arise from the presence of a lexically pre-specified suffix from those that arise from other (e.g. phonotactic) motivations). Consider the verb ''sara''- which is inflected for the first person simple tense and so, predictably, loses its final root vowel: ''sar(a)-&lt;sub&gt;c&lt;/sub&gt;t-wa'' &quot;I go.&quot;

However, prior to the suffixation of the first person simple suffix -''&lt;sub&gt;c&lt;/sub&gt;t'' to the same root nominalized with the agentive nominalizer -''iri'', the word must be verbalized. The fact that the final vowel of -''iri'' below is not suppressed indicates the presence of an intervening segment, the copulative verbalizer: ''sar(a)-iri-ʋ-t-wa'' &quot;I usually go.&quot;

It is worthwhile to compare of the copulative verbalizer in Muylaq' Aymara as compared to La Paz Aymara, a variant which represents this suffix with vowel lengthening. Consider the near-identical sentences below, both translations of &quot;I have a small house&quot; in which the nominal root ''uta-ni'' &quot;house-attributive&quot; is verbalized with the copulative verbalizer, but note that the correspondence between the copulative verbalizer in these two variants is not always a strict one-to-one relation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Coler |first=Matt |year=2015 |title=A Grammar of Muylaq' Aymara: Aymara as spoken in Southern Peru |series=Brill's Studies in the Indigenous Languages of the Americas |publisher=Brill |pages=472–476 |isbn=978-9-00-428380-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

:{| border=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;1&quot;
| align=left |  || align=right |  || align=left | 
|-
| La Paz Aymara:   
|''ma: jisk'a uta-ni-:-&lt;sub&gt;c&lt;/sub&gt;t(a)-wa''
|-
| Muylaq' Aymara:   
|''ma isk'a uta-ni-ʋ-&lt;sub&gt;c&lt;/sub&gt;t-wa''
|}

===Georgian===
As in English, the verb &quot;to be&quot; (''qopna'') is irregular in [[Georgian language|Georgian]] (a [[South Caucasian languages|Kartvelian language]]); different verb roots are employed in different tenses. The roots -''ar''-, -''kn''-, -''qav''-, and -''qop''- (past participle) are used in the present tense, future tense, past tense and the perfective tenses respectively. Examples:

:{| border=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;1&quot;
| align=left |  || align=right |  || align=left | 
|-
| ''Masc'avlebeli v''ar.
| &quot;I ''am'' a teacher.&quot;
|-
| ''Masc'avlebeli vi''kn''ebi''.
| &quot;I ''will be'' a teacher.&quot;
|-
| ''Masc'avlebeli vi''qav''i''.
| &quot;I ''was'' a teacher.&quot;
|-
| ''Masc'avlebeli v''qop''ilv''ar.
| &quot;I ''have been'' a teacher.&quot;
|-
| ''Masc'avlebeli v''qop''ili''qav''i''.
| &quot;I ''had been'' a teacher.&quot;
|}

Note that, in the last two examples (perfective and pluperfect), two roots are used in one verb compound. In the perfective tense, the root ''qop'' (which is the expected root for the perfective tense) is followed by the root ''ar'', which is the root for the present tense. In the pluperfective tense, again, the root ''qop'' is followed by the past tense root ''qav''. This formation is very similar to [[German language|German]] (an [[Indo-European languages|Indo-European language]]), where the perfect and the pluperfect are expressed in the following way:

:{| border=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;1&quot;
| align=left |  || align=right |  || align=left | 
|-
| ''Ich'' bin ''Lehrer'' gewesen.
| &quot;I have been a teacher,&quot; literally &quot;I ''am'' teacher ''been''.&quot;
|-
| ''Ich'' war ''Lehrer'' gewesen.
| &quot;I had been a teacher,&quot; literally &quot;I ''was'' teacher ''been''.&quot;
|}

Here, ''gewesen'' is the past participle of ''sein'' (&quot;to be&quot;) in German. In both examples, as in Georgian, this participle is used together with the present and the past forms of the verb in order to conjugate for the perfect and the pluperfect aspects.

===Haitian Creole===
[[Haitian Creole language|Haitian Creole]], a [[French-based creole language]], has three forms of the copula: ''se'', ''ye'', and the [[zero copula]], no word at all (the position of which will be indicated with ''Ø'', just for purposes of illustration).

Although no textual record exists of Haitian-Creole at its earliest stages of development from French, ''se'' is derived from French {{IPA-fr|se|}} (written ''c'est''), which is the normal French contraction of {{IPA-fr|sə|}} (that, written ''ce'') and the copula {{IPA-fr|e|}} (is, written ''est'') (a form of the verb ''être'').

The derivation of ''ye'' is less obvious; but we can assume that the French source was {{IPA-fr|ile|}} (&quot;he/it is,&quot; written ''il est''), which, in rapidly spoken French, is very commonly pronounced as {{IPA-fr|je|}} (typically written ''y est'').

The use of a zero copula is unknown in French, and it is thought to be an innovation from the early days when Haitian-Creole was first developing as a Romance-based [[pidgin]].  Latin also sometimes used a zero copula.

Which of ''se'' / ''ye'' / ''Ø'' is used in any given copula clause depends on complex syntactic factors that we can superficially summarize in the following four rules:

1. Use ''Ø'' (i.e., no word at all) in declarative sentences where the complement is an adjective phrase, prepositional phrase, or adverb phrase:

:{| border=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;1&quot;
| align=left |  || align=right |  || align=left | 
|-
| ''Li te Ø an Ayiti.''
| &quot;She was in Haiti.&quot; || (Lit., &quot;She ''past-tense'' in Haiti.&quot;)
|-
| ''Liv-la Ø jon.''
| &quot;The book is yellow.&quot; || (Lit., &quot;Book-the yellow.&quot;)
|-
| ''Timoun-yo Ø lakay.''
| &quot;The kids are [at] home.&quot; || (Lit., &quot;Kids-the home.&quot;)
|}

2. Use ''se'' when the complement is a noun phrase.  But note that, whereas other verbs come ''after'' any tense/mood/aspect particles (like ''pa'' to mark negation, or ''te'' to explicitly mark past tense, or ''ap'' to mark progressive aspect), ''se'' comes ''before'' any such particles:

:{| border=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;1&quot;
| align=left |  || align=right |  || align=left | 
|-
| ''Chal se ekriven.''
| &quot;Charles is writer.&quot;
|-
| ''Chal, ki se ekriven, pa vini.''
| &quot;Charles, who is writer, not come.&quot;
|}

3. Use ''se'' where French and English have a [[dummy pronoun|dummy &quot;it&quot;]] subject:

:{| border=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;1&quot;
| align=left |  || align=right |  || align=left | 
|-
| ''Se mwen!''
| &quot;It's me!&quot; French ''C'est moi!''
|-
| ''Se pa fasil.''
| &quot;It's not easy,&quot; colloquial French ''C'est pas facile.''
|}

4. Finally, use the other copula form ''ye'' in situations where the sentence's syntax leaves the copula at the end of a phrase:

:{| border=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;1&quot;
| align=left |  || align=right |  || align=left | 
|-
| ''Kijan ou ye?''
| &quot;How you are?&quot;
|-
| ''Pou kimoun liv-la te ye?''
| &quot;Whose book was it?&quot; || (Lit., &quot;Of who book-the ''past-tense'' is?)
|-
| ''M pa konnen kimoun li ye.''
| &quot;I don't know who he is.&quot; || (Lit., &quot;I not know who he is.&quot;)
|-
| ''Se yon ekriven Chal ye.''
| &quot;Charles is a ''writer''!&quot; || (Lit., &quot;It's a writer Charles is;&quot; cf. French ''C'est un écrivain qu'il est.'')
|}

The above is, however, only a simplified analysis.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Howe90|Howe 1990]]. Source for most of the Haitian data in this article; for more details on syntactic conditions as well as Haitian-specific copula constructions, like ''se kouri m ap kouri'' (It's run I ''progressive'' run; &quot;I'm really running!&quot;), see the grammar sketch in this publication.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Vald88|Valdman &amp; Rosemond 1988]].&lt;/ref&gt;

===Japanese===
[[File:Ja da ya.png|thumb|Japanese copulae in the mid 20th century]]
[[Japanese language|Japanese]] has copulae that are most often translated as the &quot;to be&quot; verb of English.

The '''Japanese copula''' has many forms. The words ''da'' and ''desu'' are used to [[predicate (grammar)|predicate]] sentences, while ''na'' and ''de'' are particles used within sentences to modify or connect.

Japanese sentences with copulas most often equate one thing with another, that is, they are of the form &quot;A is B.&quot; Examples:

:{| border=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;1&quot;
| align=left |  || align=right |  || align=left | 
|-
| 私は学生だ。
| ''Watashi wa gakusei da.'' || &quot;I'm a student.&quot; || (lit., I &lt;small&gt;TOPIC&lt;/small&gt; student &lt;small&gt;COPULA&lt;/small&gt;)
|-
| これはペンです。
| ''Kore wa pen desu.'' || &quot;This is a pen.&quot; || (lit., this &lt;small&gt;TOPIC&lt;/small&gt; pen &lt;small&gt;COPULA-POLITE&lt;/small&gt;)
|}

The difference between ''da'' and ''desu'' appears simple. For instance, ''desu'' is [[Honorific speech in Japanese|more formal and polite]] than ''da''. Thus, many sentences like the ones below are almost identical in meaning and differ in the speaker's politeness to the [[addressee]] and in nuance of how assured the person is of their statement. However, ''desu'' may never come before the end of a sentence, and ''da'' is used exclusively to delineate subordinate clauses.

:{| border=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;1&quot;
| align=left |  || align=right |  || align=left | 
|-
| あれはホテルだ。
| ''Are wa hoteru da''. || &quot;That's a hotel.&quot; || (lit., that &lt;small&gt;TOPIC&lt;/small&gt; hotel &lt;small&gt;COPULA&lt;/small&gt;)
|-
| あれはホテルです。
| ''Are wa hoteru desu''. || &quot;That is a hotel.&quot; || (lit., that &lt;small&gt;TOPIC&lt;/small&gt; hotel &lt;small&gt;COPULA-POLITE&lt;/small&gt;)
|}

Japanese sentences may be predicated with copulas or with verbs. However, ''desu'' may not always be a predicate. In some cases, its only function is to make a sentence predicated with a [[stative verb]] more polite.  However, ''da'' always functions as a predicate, so it cannot be combined with a stative verb, because sentences need only one predicate. See the examples below.

:{| border=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;1&quot;
| align=left |  || align=right |  || align=left | 
|-
| このビールはおいしい。
| ''Kono bīru wa oishii.'' || &quot;This beer is delicious.&quot; || (lit., this beer &lt;small&gt;TOPIC&lt;/small&gt; be-tasty)
|-
| このビールはおいしいです。
| ''Kono bīru wa oishii desu.'' || &quot;This beer is delicious.&quot; || (lit., this beer &lt;small&gt;TOPIC&lt;/small&gt; be-tasty &lt;small&gt;POLITE&lt;/small&gt;)
|-
| &lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;このビールはおいしいだ。
| &lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;''Kono bīru wa oishii da.'' || colspan=2 | This is unacceptable because ''da'' may only serve as a predicate.
|}

There are several [[theories]] as to the origin of ''desu''; one is that it is a shortened form of であります ''de arimasu'', which is a polite form of である ''de aru''. In general, both forms are used in only writing and more formal situations. Another form, でございます ''de gozaimasu'', which is the more formal version of ''de arimasu'', in the etymological sense a conjugation of でござる ''de gozaru'' and an honorific suffix -ます ''-masu'', is also used in some situations and is very polite. Note that ''de aru'' and ''de gozaru'' are considered to be compounds of a particle で ''de'', and existential verbs ''aru'' and ''gozaru''. です ''desu'' may be pronounced っす ''ssu'' in colloquial speech. The copula is subject to dialectal variation throughout Japan, resulting in forms like や ''ya'' in [[Kansai dialect|Kansai]] and じゃ ''ja'' in [[Hiroshima]] (see map above).

Japanese also has two verbs corresponding to English &quot;to be&quot;: ''aru'' and ''iru''. They are not copulas but existential verbs. ''Aru'' is used for inanimate objects, including plants, whereas ''iru'' is used for animate things like people, animals, and robots, though there are exceptions to this generalization.

:{| border=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;1&quot;
| align=left |  || align=right |  || align=left | 
|-
| 本はテーブルにある。
| ''Hon wa tēburu ni aru''. || &quot;The book is on a table.&quot;
|-
| 小林さんはここにいる。
| ''Kobayashi-san wa koko ni iru''. || &quot;Kobayashi is here.&quot;
|}

[[Japanese language|Japanese]] speakers, when learning English, often drop the auxiliary verbs &quot;be&quot; and &quot;do,&quot; incorrectly believing that &quot;be&quot; is a semantically empty copula equivalent to &quot;desu&quot; and &quot;da.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first=Sayuri|date=Fall 2006|year=|title=The English Copula Be: Japanese Learners' Confusion|url=https://www.hpu.edu/CHSS/English/TESOL/ProfessionalDevelopment/200680TWPfall06/04Kusutani_Syntax.pdf |archiveurl =https://web.archive.org/web/20121201023548/http://www.hpu.edu/CHSS/LangLing/TESOL/ProfessionalDevelopment/200680TWPfall06/04Kusutani_Syntax.pdf|archivedate =2012-12-01 |format=PDF|journal=TESL Working Paper Series|volume=4|issue=2|pages=|via=|author=Kusutani}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Korean===
For sentences with '''predicate nominatives''', the copula &quot;이&quot; (i-) is added to the predicate nominative (with no space in between).

:{| border=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;1&quot;
| align=left |  || align=right |  || align=left | 
|-
| 바나나는 과일이다. 
| ''Ba-na-na-neun gwa-il  
-i-da''. || &quot;Bananas are a fruit.&quot;
|}

Some adjectives (usually colour adjectives) are nominalized and used with the copula &quot;이&quot;(i-).

1. Without the copula &quot;이&quot;(i-):

:{| border=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;1&quot;
| align=left |  || align=right |  || align=left | 
|-
| 장미는 빨개요. 
| ''Jang-mi-neun ppal-gae-yo''. || &quot;Roses are red.&quot;
|}

2. With the copula &quot;이&quot;(i-):

:{| border=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;1&quot;
| align=left |  || align=right |  || align=left | 
|-
| 장미는 빨간색이다. 
| ''Jang-mi-neun ppal-gan-saek-i-da''. || &quot;Roses are red-coloured.&quot;
|}

Some Korean adjectives are derived using the copula. Separating these articles and nominalizing the former part will often result in a sentence with a related, but different meaning. Using the separated sentence in a situation where the un-separated sentence is appropriate is usually acceptable as the listener can decide what the speaker is trying to say using the context.

===Chinese===
&lt;small&gt;N.B. The characters used are [[Simplified Chinese|simplified]] ones, and the transcriptions given in italics reflect [[Standard Chinese]] pronunciation, using the [[pinyin]] system.&lt;/small&gt;

In [[Chinese language|Chinese]], both states and qualities are, in general, expressed with [[stative verb]]s (SV) with no need for a copula, e.g., in [[Traditional Chinese|Chinese]], &quot;to be tired&quot; (累 ''lèi''), &quot;to be hungry&quot; (饿 ''è''), &quot;to be located at&quot; (在 ''zài''), &quot;to be stupid&quot; (笨 ''bèn'') and so forth. A sentence can consist simply of a pronoun and such a verb: for example, 我饿 ''wǒ è'' (&quot;I am hungry&quot;). Usually, however, verbs expressing qualities are qualified by an adverb (meaning &quot;very,&quot; &quot;not,&quot; &quot;quite,&quot; etc.); when not otherwise qualified, they are often preceded by 很 ''hěn'', which in other contexts means &quot;very,&quot; but in this use often has no particular meaning.

{{See also|Chinese adjectives|Chinese particles|Chinese grammar}}

Only sentences with a noun as the complement (e.g., &quot;This is my sister&quot;) use the copular verb &quot;to be&quot;: {{Zh|c={{linktext|是}}|p=shì|labels=no}}. This is used frequently; for example, instead of having a verb meaning &quot;to be Chinese,&quot; the usual expression is &quot;to be a Chinese person&quot; ({{Zh|p=wǒ shì Zhōngguórén|labels=no|s={{linktext|我|是|中国人}}|t={{linktext|我|是|中國人}}|first=|c=}}; {{Abbr|{{small|lit.}}|literally}} &quot;I am a Chinese person;&quot; &quot;I am Chinese&quot;). This {{Zh|c=是|labels=no}} is sometimes called an [[equative]] verb. Another possibility is for the complement to be just a noun modifier (ending in {{Zh|c={{linktext|的}}|p=de|labels=no}}), the noun being omitted: {{Zh|p=wǒ de qìchē shì hóngsè de|labels=no|s={{linktext|我的|汽车|是|红色|的}}|l=My car is red. {{small|([[noun phrase]] indicator)}}|c=|t=}}

Before the [[Han Dynasty]], the character 是 served as a [[demonstrative pronoun]] meaning &quot;this.&quot; (This usage survives in some idioms and [[wikiquote:Chinese proverbs|proverbs]].) Some linguists believe that 是 developed into a copula because it often appeared, as a repetitive subject, after the subject of a sentence (in [[classical Chinese]] we can say, for example: &quot;George W. Bush, ''this'' president of the United States&quot; meaning &quot;George W. Bush ''is'' the president of the United States).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Pulleyblank|first=Edwin G.|title=Outline of Classical Chinese Grammar|publisher=UBC Press|year=1995|location=Vancouver|isbn=0-7748-0541-2}}{{page needed|date=January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The character 是 appears to be formed as a [[Chinese character classification|compound]] of characters with the meanings of &quot;early&quot; and &quot;straight.&quot;

Another use of 是 in modern Chinese is in combination with the modifier 的 ''de'' to mean &quot;yes&quot; or to show agreement. For example: &lt;blockquote&gt;Question: 你的汽车是不是红色的？ ''nǐ de qìchē shì bú shì hóngsè de?'' &quot;Is your car red or not?&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Response: 是的 ''shì de'' &quot;Is,&quot; meaning &quot;Yes,&quot; or 不是 ''bú shì'' &quot;Not is,&quot; meaning &quot;No.&quot; &lt;/blockquote&gt;(A more common way of showing that the person asking the question is correct is by simply saying &quot;right&quot; or &quot;correct,&quot; 对 ''duì''; the corresponding negative answer is 不对 ''bú duì'', &quot;not right.&quot;) 

Yet another use of 是 is in the ''shì...(de)'' construction, which is used to emphasize a particular element of the sentence; see {{Slink|Chinese grammar|Cleft sentences}}.

In [[Hokkien]] 是 ''sī'' acts as the copula, and 是 {{IPA|/z/}} is the equivalent in [[Wu Chinese]]. [[Cantonese]] uses 係 ({{Zh|j=hai6}}) instead of 是; similarly, [[Hakka language|Hakka]] uses 係 ''he&lt;sup&gt;55&lt;/sup&gt;''.

===Siouan languages===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Medicine man]] --&gt;
In Siouan languages like [[Lakota language|Lakota]], in principle almost all words—according to their structure—are verbs. So not only (transitive, intransitive and so-called &quot;stative&quot;) verbs but even nouns often behave like verbs and do not need to have copulas.

For example, the word ''wičháša'' refers to a man, and the verb &quot;to-be-a-man&quot; is expressed as ''wimáčhaša/winíčhaša/wičháša'' (I am/you are/he is a man). Yet there also is a copula ''héčha'' (to be a ...) that in most cases is used: ''wičháša hemáčha/heníčha/héčha'' (I am/you are/he is a man).

In order to express the statement &quot;I am a doctor of profession,&quot; one has to say ''pezuta wičháša hemáčha''. But, in order to express that that person is THE doctor (say, that had been phoned to help), one must use another copula ''iyé'' (to be the one): ''pežúta wičháša (kiŋ) miyé yeló'' (medicine-man DEF ART I-am-the-one MALE ASSERT).

In order to refer to space (e.g., Robert is in the house), various verbs are used, e.g., ''yaŋkÁ'' (lit., to sit) for humans, or ''háŋ/hé'' (to stand upright) for inanimate objects of a certain shape. &quot;Robert is in the house&quot; could be translated as ''Robert thimáhel yaŋké (yeló)'', whereas &quot;There's one restaurant next to the gas station&quot; translates as ''Owótethipi wígli-oínažiŋ kiŋ hél isákhib waŋ hé''.

===Constructed languages===
The [[constructed language]] [[Lojban]] has two words that act similar to a copula in natural languages. The clause ''me ... me'u'' turns whatever follows it into a predicate that means to be (among) what it follows. For example, ''me la .bob. (me'u)'' means &quot;to be Bob,&quot; and ''me le ci mensi (me'u)'' means &quot;to be one of the three sisters.&quot; Another one is ''du'', which is itself a predicate that means all its arguments are the same thing (equal).&lt;ref&gt;[http://ptolemy.tlg.uci.edu/~opoudjis/lojbanbrochure/lessons/less12eq.html Lojban For Beginners] {{webarchive|url=https://archive.today/20060830212608/http://ptolemy.tlg.uci.edu/~opoudjis/lojbanbrochure/lessons/less12eq.html |date=2006-08-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt; One word which is often confused for a copula in Lojban, but isn't one, is ''cu''. It merely indicates that the word which follows is the main predicate of the sentence. For example, ''lo pendo be mi cu zgipre'' means &quot;my friend is a musician,&quot; but the word ''cu'' does not correspond to English ''is''; instead, the word ''zgipre'', which is a predicate, corresponds to the entire phrase &quot;is a musician&quot;. The word ''cu'' is used to prevent ''lo pendo be mi zgipre'', which would mean &quot;the friend-of-me type of musician&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Complete Lojban Language |url=http://lojban.github.io/cll/2/6/ |website=The Lojban Reference Grammar |accessdate=3 July 2019 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190410225800/http://lojban.github.io/cll/2/6/ |archive-date=10 April 2019 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[E-Prime]] language, based on English, simply avoids the issue by not having a generic copula. It requires instead a specific form like &quot;remains,&quot; &quot;becomes,&quot; &quot;lies,&quot; or &quot;equals.&quot;

[[Esperanto]] uses the copula much as English. The infinitive is ''esti'', and the whole conjugation is regular (like all other Esperanto verbs). In addition, adjectival roots can be turned into stative verbs: ''La ĉielo bluas.'' &quot;The sky is blue.&quot;

Likewise, [[Ido (language)|Ido]] has a copula that works as English &quot;to be.&quot; Its infinitive is ''esar'', and, as in Esperanto, all of its forms are regular like all other verbs. The simple present is ''esas'' for all persons; the simple past is ''esis'', the simple future is ''esos'', and the imperative is ''esez'', among a few more forms.

However, Ido also has an alternative irregular form for the simple present (''es''), which some Idists frown upon. The possibility to turn adjectives and even nouns into verbs also exists, although this is mostly done by means of an affix, on top of the verbal endings. The affix is ''-es-''. So, &quot;The sky is blue.&quot; can be said as ''La cielo bluesas.'' As can be seen, the suffix ''-es-'' plus the verbal desinence ''-as'' are simply the verb &quot;to be&quot; annexed to the adjectival or nominal root.

[[Interlingua]] speakers use copulas with the same freedom as speakers of Slavic, Germanic, and Romance languages. In addition to combinations with ''esser'' (&quot;to be&quot;), expressions like ''cader prede'' (&quot;to fall prey&quot;) are common. ''Esser'' is stated, rather than omitted as in Russian.

==See also==
* [[Indo-European copula]]
* [[Nominal sentence]]
* [[Stative verb]]
* [[Subject complement]]
* [[Zero copula]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book | title= Write Well: Improving Writing Skills | url= https://books.google.com/books?id=_XTeNQpNbYMC | first= Barli | last= Bram | date= 5 July 1995 | publisher= Penerbit Kanisius | location= [[Yogyakarta (city)|Yogyakarta]], [[Indonesia]] | isbn= 978-979-497-378-3 | ref= Bram95&lt;!-- | accessdate= 2009-05-04 --&gt; | page= 128}}
* {{cite book | title= The Blackwell Companion to Syntax, Volumes I-V | url= https://books.google.com/books?id=uieX1Q_IKEYC | edition= illustrated, revised |editor-first=Martin |editor-last=Everaert |editor2=van Riemsdijk, Henk | publisher= [[Blackwell Publishing|Wiley-Blackwell]] | isbn= 978-1-4051-1485-1 | page= 849 | year= 2006}} (See &quot;copular sentences&quot; and &quot;existential sentences and expletive ''there''&quot; in Volume II.)
* {{cite book | title= Haitian Creole Newspaper Reader | url= https://books.google.com/books?id=E7FkAAAAMAAJ | first= Catherine | last= Howe | publisher= Dunwoody Press | isbn= 978-0-931745-59-1 | ref= Howe90 | page= 232 | author2= Desmarattes, Jean Lionel | year= 1990}}
* {{cite book | title= The Development of Logic | author= [[William Kneale|Kneale, William]] and Martha | year= 1962 | publisher= [[Oxford University Press|Clarendon Press]] | location= [[Oxford]] | oclc= 373178 | isbn= 0-19-824183-6}}
* {{cite book | title= Editing Today Workbook | url= https://books.google.com/books?id=IBth6ZKCi3EC | edition= 2nd | first= Ron F | last= Smith |author2=O'Connell, Loraine M. | date= March 2003 | publisher= [[Blackwell Publishing|Wiley-Blackwell]] | isbn= 978-0-8138-1317-2 | ref= Smith03&lt;!-- | accessdate= 2009-05-04 --&gt; | page= 264}}
* [http://www.cambridge.org/catalogue/catalogue.asp?ISBN=9780521024785 Moro, A. (1997) ''The Raising of Predicates''. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, England.]
* Tüting, A. W. (December 2003). ''[http://www.fa-kuan.de/LAKSTRUCT.HTML Essay on Lakota syntax]''.
* {{cite book | title= Ann Pale Kreyòl: An Introductory Course in Haitian Creole | url= https://books.google.com/books?id=tU9hAAAACAAJ | edition= Illustrated | first= Albert | last= Valdman |author2=Rosemond, Renote | others= Illustrations: Philippe, Pierre-Henri | year= 1988 | publisher= Creole Institute, [[Indiana University]] | isbn= 978-0-929236-00-1 | ref= Vald88}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |title=The Story of Be: A Verb's-Eye View of the English Language |author=David Crystal |year=2017 |isbn=978-0198791096 |publisher=Oxford University Press}}

== External links ==
{{wikiquote}}

{{lexical categories|state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Copula (Linguistics)}}
[[Category:Parts of speech]]
[[Category:Verb types]]</text>
      <sha1>241s56lbxe1vwhs9ohrplxon1kzw12u</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
