  <page>
    <title>Currency</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5665</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942055810</id>
      <parentid>942055731</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-22T09:01:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pikavoom</username>
        <id>38393977</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 942055731 by [[Special:Contributions/Darshan k achar|Darshan k achar]] ([[User talk:Darshan k achar|talk]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Generally accepted medium of exchange for goods or services}}
{{other uses}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=March 2019}}
{{Numismatics}}

A '''currency''' (from {{lang-enm|curraunt}}, &quot;in circulation&quot;, from {{lang-la|[[Wikt:currens|currens]], -entis}}), in the most specific sense is [[money]] in any form when in use or circulation as a [[medium of exchange]], especially circulating [[banknote]]s and [[coin]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.thefreedictionary.com/currency | title = Currency | publisher = The Free Dictionary}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Bernstein&gt;{{cite book |last =Bernstein |first =Peter |authorlink =Peter L. Bernstein |title=A Primer on Money, Banking and Gold | edition = 3rd |year=2008 |origyear=1965 |publisher=Wiley |location=Hoboken, NJ  |isbn=978-0-470-28758-3 |oclc = 233484849 |chapter= 4–5}}&lt;/ref&gt; A more general definition is that a currency is a ''system of money'' (monetary units) in common use, especially for people in a nation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.investopedia.com/terms/c/currency.asp#axzz2CqfsX9BD | title = Currency | publisher = Investopedia}}&lt;/ref&gt; Under this definition, [[United States dollar|U.S. dollars]] (US$), [[Euro|euros]] (€), [[Japanese yen]] (¥), and [[Pound sterling|pounds sterling]] (£) are examples of currencies. These various currencies are recognized as stores of value and are traded between nations in [[foreign exchange market]]s, which determine the relative values of the different currencies.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | url = https://docs.google.com/fileview?id=0B_Qxj5U7eaJTZTJkODYzN2ItZjE3Yy00Y2M0LTk2ZmUtZGU0NzA3NGI4Y2Y5&amp;hl=en&amp;pli=1 | newspaper = The Economist | title = Guide to the Financial Markets | format = PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; Currencies in this sense are defined by governments, and each type has limited boundaries of acceptance.

Other definitions of the term &quot;currency&quot; are discussed in their respective synonymous articles [[banknote]], [[coin]], and [[money]]. The latter definition,{{clarify|date=March 2019}} pertaining to the currency systems of nations, is the topic of this article. Currencies can be classified into two [[monetary system]]s: [[fiat money]] and [[commodity money]], depending on what guarantees the currency's value (the economy at large vs. the government's physical metal reserves). Some currencies are [[legal tender]] in certain political jurisdictions. Others are simply traded for their economic value. [[Digital currency]] has arisen with the popularity of computers and the [[Internet]].

==History==
&lt;!--Linked from [[Shekel]]--&gt;

===Early currency===
{{refimprove|date=December 2017}}
[[File:A print from 1845 shows cowry shells being used as money by an Arab trader.jpg|thumb|Cowry shells being used as money by an Arab trader.]]
Originally money was a form of receipt, representing grain stored in temple granaries in [[Sumer]] in ancient [[Mesopotamia]] and later in [[Ancient Egypt]].

In this first stage of currency, metals were used as symbols to represent value stored in the form of commodities. This formed the basis of trade in the [[Fertile Crescent]] for over 1500 years. However, the [[Bronze Age collapse|collapse of the Near Eastern trading system]] pointed to a flaw: in an era where there was no place that was safe to store value, the value of a circulating medium could only be as sound as the forces that defended that store. A trade could only reach as far as the credibility of that military. By the late [[Bronze Age]], however, a series of [[Treaty|treaties]] had established safe passage for merchants around the [[Eastern Mediterranean]], spreading from [[Minoan civilization|Minoan]] [[Crete]] and [[Mycenae]] in the northwest to [[Elam]] and [[Bahrain]] in the southeast. It is not known what was used as a currency for these exchanges, but it is thought that [[oxhide ingot|ox-hide shaped ingots]] of copper, produced in [[Cyprus]], may have functioned as a currency.

It is thought that the increase in piracy and raiding associated with the [[Bronze Age collapse]], possibly produced by the [[Peoples of the Sea]], brought the trading system of oxhide ingots to an end. It was only the recovery of Phoenician trade in the 10th and 9th centuries BC that led to a return to prosperity, and the appearance of real coinage, possibly first in Anatolia with [[Croesus]] of [[Lydia]] and subsequently with the Greeks and Persians. In Africa, many forms of value store have been used, including beads, ingots, [[ivory]], various forms of weapons, livestock, the [[manilla currency]], and ochre and other earth oxides. The manilla rings of [[West Africa]] were one of the currencies used from the 15th century onwards to sell slaves. [[African currency]] is still notable for its variety, and in many places, various forms of [[barter]] still apply.

===Coinage===
{{refimprove|date=December 2017}}
{{main|Coin}}
These{{clarify|date=March 2019}} factors led to the metal itself being the store of value: first silver, then both silver and gold, and at one point also bronze. Now we have copper coins and other non-precious metals as coins. Metals were mined, weighed, and stamped into coins. This was to assure the individual accepting the coin that he was getting a certain known weight of precious metal. Coins could be counterfeited, but the existence of standard coins also created a new [[unit of account]], which helped lead to [[banking]]. [[Archimedes' principle]] provided the next link: coins could now be easily tested for their [[Fineness|fine]] weight of metal, and thus the value of a coin could be determined, even if it had been shaved, debased or otherwise tampered with (see [[Numismatics]]).
[[File:Electrum trite, Alyattes, Lydia, 620-563 BC.jpg|thumb|The world's oldest coin, created in the ancient Kingdom of Lydia.]]
Most major economies using coinage had several tiers of coins of different values, made of copper, silver, and gold. Gold coins were the most valuable and were used for large purchases, payment of the military and backing of state activities. Units of account were often defined as the value of a particular type of gold coin. Silver coins were used for midsized transactions, and sometimes also defined a unit of account, while coins of copper or silver, or some mixture of them (see [[debasement]]), might be used for everyday transactions. This system had been used in ancient [[Indian coinage|India]] since the time of the [[Mahajanapadas]]. The exact ratios between the values of the three metals varied greatly between different eras and places; for example, the opening of silver mines in the [[Harz]] mountains of central Europe made silver relatively less valuable, as did the flood of [[New World]] silver [[Price revolution|after the Spanish conquests]]. However, the rarity of gold consistently made it more valuable than silver, and likewise silver was consistently worth more than copper.

=== Paper money ===
{{main|Banknote}}
In [[History of China|premodern]] [[China]], the need for credit and for a medium of exchange that was less physically cumbersome than large numbers of [[copper]] coins led to the introduction of [[paper money]], i.e. [[banknote]]s. Their introduction was a gradual process which lasted from the late [[Tang dynasty]] (618–907) into the [[Song dynasty]] (960–1279). It began as a means for merchants to exchange heavy coinage for [[receipt]]s of deposit issued as [[promissory note]]s by [[wholesaler]]s' shops. These notes were valid for temporary use in a small regional territory. In the 10th century, the [[Song dynasty]] government began to circulate these notes amongst the traders in its [[monopoly|monopolized]] salt industry. The Song government granted several shops the right to issue banknotes, and in the early 12th century the government finally took over these shops to produce state-issued currency. Yet the banknotes issued were still only locally and temporarily valid: it was not until the mid 13th century that a standard and uniform government issue of paper money became an acceptable nationwide currency. The already widespread methods of [[woodblock printing]] and then [[Bi Sheng]]'s [[movable type]] [[printing]] by the 11th century were the impetus for the mass production of paper money in premodern China.

[[File:Jiao zi.jpg|thumb|right|Song dynasty ''Jiaozi,'' the world's earliest paper money]]
At around the same time in the [[Islamic Golden Age|medieval Islamic world]], a vigorous [[monetary economy]] was created during the 7th–12th centuries on the basis of the expanding levels of circulation of a stable high-value currency (the [[dinar]]). Innovations introduced by Muslim economists, traders and merchants include the earliest uses of [[Credit (finance)|credit]],&lt;ref name=Banaji&gt;{{cite journal |last=Banaji |first=Jairus |year=2007 |title=Islam, the Mediterranean and the Rise of Capitalism |journal=Historical Materialism |volume=15 |issue=1 |pages=47–74 |issn=1465-4466 |doi=10.1163/156920607X171591 |oclc=440360743 |url=https://www.scribd.com/doc/14246569/Banaji-Jairus-Islam-The-Mediterranean-and-the-Rise-of-Capitalism |accessdate=August 28, 2010 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090523015524/http://www.scribd.com/doc/14246569/Banaji-Jairus-Islam-The-Mediterranean-and-the-Rise-of-Capitalism |archive-date=May 23, 2009 |url-status=dead  }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[cheque]]s, [[promissory note]]s,&lt;ref name=&quot;Medieval Trade in the Mediterranean World: Illustrative Documents&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Lopez |first1=Robert Sabatino |authorlink1=Roberto Sabatino Lopez |last2=Raymond |first2=Irving Woodworth |last3=Constable |first3=Olivia Remie |title=Medieval trade in the Mediterranean world: Illustrative documents |series=Records of Western civilization.; Records of civilization, sources and studies, no. 52 |year=2001 |origyear=1955 |publisher=[[Columbia University Press]] |location=New York |url=http://cup.columbia.edu/bookpreview/978-0-231-12356-3/ |isbn=978-0-231-12357-0 |oclc=466877309 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120309144011/http://cup.columbia.edu/bookpreview/978-0-231-12356-3/ |archivedate=March 9, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[savings account]]s, [[transaction account]]s, [[loan]]ing, [[Trust law|trusts]], [[exchange rate]]s, the transfer of credit and [[debt]],&lt;ref name=Labib&gt;{{cite journal |last=Labib |first=Subhi Y. |date=March 1969 |title=Capitalism in Medieval Islam |journal=The Journal of Economic History |volume=29 |issue=1 |pages=79–86 |issn=0022-0507 |oclc=478662641 |jstor=2115499 |doi=10.1017/S0022050700097837 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[banking institution]]s for loans and [[deposit account|deposits]].&lt;ref name=Labib /&gt;

In Europe, paper money was first introduced on a regular basis in [[Sweden]] in 1661 (although [[Washington Irving]] records an earlier emergency use of it, by the Spanish in a siege during the [[Conquest of Granada]]). As [[Sweden]] was rich in copper, many copper coins were in circulation, but its relatively low value necessitated extraordinarily big coins, often weighing several kilograms.

The advantages of paper currency were numerous: it reduced the need to transport gold and silver, which was risky; it facilitated loans of gold or silver at interest, since the underlying [[Hard money (policy)|specie]] (money in the form of gold or silver coins rather than notes) never left the possession of the lender until someone else redeemed the note; and it allowed a division of currency into credit- and specie-backed forms. It enabled the sale of [[stock]] in [[joint-stock company|joint-stock companies]] and the redemption of those [[Share (finance)|shares]] in a paper.

But there were also disadvantages. First, since a note has no intrinsic value, there was nothing to stop issuing authorities from printing more notes than they had specie to back them with. Second, because it increased the money supply, it increased inflationary pressures, a fact observed by [[David Hume]] in the 18th century. Thus paper money would often lead to an inflationary bubble, which could collapse if people began demanding hard money, causing the demand for paper notes to fall to zero. The printing of paper money was also associated with wars, and financing of wars, and therefore regarded as part of maintaining a [[standing army]]. For these reasons, paper currency was held in suspicion and hostility in Europe and America. It was also addictive since the speculative profits of trade and capital creation were quite large. Major nations established [[mint (coin)|mints]] to print money and mint coins, and branches of their treasury to collect taxes and hold gold and silver stock.

At that time, both silver and gold were considered a [[legal tender]] and accepted by governments for taxes. However, the [[Gresham's law|instability in the exchange rate]] between the two grew over the course of the 19th century, with the increases both in the supply of these metals, particularly silver, and in trade. The parallel use of both metals is called [[bimetallism]], and the attempt to create a [[Bimetallism|bimetallic]] standard where both gold and silver backed currency remained in circulation occupied the efforts of [[inflation]]ists. Governments at this point could use currency as an instrument of policy, printing paper currency such as the United States [[United States Note|greenback]], to pay for military expenditures. They could also set the terms at which they would redeem notes for specie, by limiting the amount of purchase, or the minimum amount that could be redeemed.

By 1900, most of the industrializing nations were on some form of [[gold standard]], with paper notes and silver coins constituting the circulating medium. Private [[bank]]s and governments across the world followed [[Gresham's law]]: keeping the gold and silver they received but paying out in notes. This did not happen all around the world at the same time, but occurred sporadically, generally in times of war or financial crisis, beginning in the early 20th century and continuing across the world until the late 20th century, when the regime of floating fiat currencies came into force. One of the last countries to break away from the gold standard was the United States in 1971, an action known as the [[Nixon shock]]. No country has an enforceable gold standard or [[silver standard]] currency system.

===Banknote era===
{{main|Banknote|Fiat currency}}
A [[banknote]] (more commonly known as a bill in the [[United States]] and [[Canada]]) is a type of currency and is commonly used as legal tender in many jurisdictions. Together with [[coin]]s, banknotes make up the [[cash]] form of all money. Banknotes are mostly paper, but Australia's [[Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation]] developed a [[Polymer banknote|polymer currency]] in the 1980s; it went into circulation on the nation's bicentenary in 1988.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://banknotes.rba.gov.au/australias-banknotes/history/|title=History of Banknotes|last=|first=|date=|website=Reserve Bank of Australia|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2019-12-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Polymer banknotes [[Manx pound|had already been introduced]] in the [[Isle of Man]] in 1983. As of 2016, [[polymer currency]] is used in over 20 countries (over 40 if counting commemorative issues),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/fandd/2016/06/currency.htm|title=The Future Is Plastic - Currency Notes - Finance &amp; Development, June 2016|website=www.imf.org|access-date=2019-12-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; and dramatically increases the life span of banknotes and reduces counterfeiting.

== Modern currencies ==
[[File:Currency unit name.svg|thumb|left|Name of currency units by country]]
[[File:Strength of currencies.svg|thumb|left|Strength of currencies relative to USD as of April 2016]]
[[File:2002 currency exchange AIGA euro money.png|thumb|upright=0.6|left|Currencies exchange logo]]
{{Most traded currencies}}
{{Further|Tables of historical exchange rates to the United States dollar}}
{{for|a list of which currency or currencies are used by present-day countries or regions|List of circulating currencies}}

The currency usage is based on the concept of [[lex monetae]]; that a sovereign state decides which currency it shall use. The [[International Organization for Standardization]] has introduced a system of three-letter codes ([[ISO 4217]]) to denote currency (as opposed to simple names or [[currency sign]]s), in order to remove the confusion arising because there are dozens of currencies called the [[dollar]] and several called the [[franc]]. Even the [[List of countries using pound currency|&quot;pound&quot;]] is used in nearly a dozen different countries; most of these are tied to the [[Pound Sterling]], while the remainder has varying values. In general, the three-letter code uses the [[ISO 3166-1]] country code for the first two letters and the first letter of the name of the currency (D for dollar, for instance) as the third letter. United States currency, for instance, is globally referred to as [[United States dollar|USD]].

The [[International Monetary Fund]] uses a different system when referring to national currencies.

== Alternative currencies ==
{{main|Alternative currency}}

Distinct from centrally controlled government-issued currencies, private decentralized trust networks support alternative currencies such as [[Bitcoin]], [[Ethereum]], [[Litecoin]], [[Monero (cryptocurrency)|Monero]], [[Peercoin]] or [[Dogecoin]], which are classified as [[cryptocurrency]] since payments made and transfers are untrackable, as well as [[brand]]ed currencies, for example 'obligation' based stores of value, such as quasi-regulated BarterCard, Loyalty Points (Credit Cards, Airlines) or Game-Credits (MMO games) that are based on reputation of commercial products, or highly regulated 'asset-backed' 'alternative currencies' such as mobile-money schemes like MPESA (called E-Money Issuance).&lt;ref name=TEDbrandedCurrency&gt;● ''TED Video:'' {{cite web|url=http://www.ted.com/talks/paul_kemp_robertson_bitcoin_sweat_tide_meet_the_future_of_branded_currency.html |title=Bitcoin. Sweat. Tide. Meet the future of branded currency |last=Kemp-Robertson |first=Paul |date=June 2013 |publisher=[[TED (conference)]] }} ● ''Corresponding written article:'' {{cite web|url=http://blog.ted.com/2013/07/25/10-alternative-currencies-from-bitcoin-to-berkshares-to-sweat-to-laundry-detergent/ |title=10 alternative currencies, from Bitcoin to BerkShares to sweat to laundry detergent |date=July 25, 2013 |publisher=[[TED (conference)]] |archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/6INbHkJat?url=http://blog.ted.com/2013/07/25/10-alternative-currencies-from-bitcoin-to-berkshares-to-sweat-to-laundry-detergent/ |archivedate=July 25, 2013 |url-status=dead  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The currency may be Internet-based and digital, for instance, [[bitcoin]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Hough|first=Jack|title=The Currency That's Up 200,000 Percent|url=https://finance.yahoo.com/news/pf_article_112854.html|work=SmartMoney (The Wall Street Journal)|accessdate=December 14, 2012|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121024131227/http://finance.yahoo.com/news/pf_article_112854.html|archive-date=October 24, 2012|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; is not tied to any specific country, or the IMF's SDR that is based on a basket of currencies (and assets held).

== Control and production ==

In most cases, a [[central bank]] has a [[monopoly]] right to issue of coins and banknotes ([[fiat money]]) for its own area of circulation (a country or group of countries); it regulates the production of currency by banks ([[credit (finance)|credit]]) through [[monetary policy]].

An [[exchange rate]] is a price at which two currencies can be exchanged against each other. This is used for [[international trade|trade]] between the two currency zones. Exchange rates can be classified as either [[floating exchange rate|floating]] or [[fixed exchange-rate system|fixed]]. In the former, day-to-day movements in exchange rates are determined by the market; in the latter, governments intervene in the market to buy or sell their currency to balance supply and demand at a static exchange rate.

In cases where a country has control of its own currency, that control is exercised either by a [[central bank]] or by a [[Finance minister|Ministry of Finance]]. The institution that has control of monetary policy is referred to as the monetary authority. Monetary authorities have varying degrees of autonomy from the governments that create them. A monetary authority is created and supported by its sponsoring government, so independence can be reduced by the legislative or executive authority that creates it.

Several countries can use the same name for their own separate currencies (for example, a ''dollar'' in [[Australian dollar|Australia]], [[Canadian dollar|Canada]], and the [[United States dollar|United States]]). By contrast, several countries can also use the same currency (for example, the [[euro]] or the [[CFA franc]]), or one country can declare the currency of another country to be [[legal tender]]. For example, [[Panama]] and [[El Salvador]] have declared US currency to be legal tender, and from 1791 to 1857, [[Spanish silver coins]] were legal tender in the United States. At various times countries have either re-stamped foreign coins or used [[currency board]]s, issuing one note of currency for each note of a foreign government held, as [[Ecuador]] currently does.

Each currency typically has a main currency unit (the [[dollar]], for example, or the [[euro]]) and a fractional unit, often defined as {{Frac|1|100}} of the main unit: 100 [[Cent (currency)|cents]]&amp;nbsp;= 1&amp;nbsp;[[dollar]], 100 [[centime]]s&amp;nbsp;= 1&amp;nbsp;[[franc]], 100 [[Penny sterling|pence]]&amp;nbsp;= 1&amp;nbsp;[[Pound sterling|pound]], although units of {{Frac|1|10}} or {{Frac|1|1000}} occasionally also occur. Some currencies do not have any smaller units at all, such as the [[Icelandic króna]].

[[Mauritania]] and [[Madagascar]] are the only remaining countries that have theoretical fractional units not based on the decimal system; instead, the [[Mauritanian ouguiya]] is in theory divided into 5 [[khoums]], while the [[Malagasy ariary]] is theoretically divided into 5 [[iraimbilanja]]. In these countries, words like ''dollar'' or ''pound'' &quot;were simply names for given weights of gold&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Collapse of the Dollar&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Turk |first1=James |last2=Rubino |first2=John |title=The collapse of the dollar and how to profit from it: Make a fortune by investing in gold and other hard assets |edition=Paperback |year=2007 |origyear=2004 |publisher=Doubleday |location=New York |isbn=978-0-385-51224-4 |oclc=192055959 |pages=43 of 252}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to [[inflation]] khoums and iraimbilanja have in practice fallen into disuse. (See [[non-decimal currencies]] for other historic currencies with non-decimal divisions.)

== Currency convertibility ==

Convertibility of a currency determines the ability of an individual, corporation or government to convert its local currency to another currency or vice versa with or without central bank/government intervention. Based on the above restrictions or free and readily conversion features, currencies are classified as:
; Fully convertible : When there are no restrictions or limitations on the amount of currency that can be traded on the international market, and the government does not artificially impose a fixed value or minimum value on the currency in international trade. The US dollar is an example of a fully convertible currency and, for this reason, US dollars are one of the major currencies traded in the [[foreign exchange market]].
; Partially convertible : Central banks control international investments flowing into and out of a country. While most domestic transactions are handled without any special requirements, there are significant restrictions on international investing, and special approval is often required in order to convert into other currencies. The Indian rupee and the renminbi are examples of partially convertible currencies.
; Nonconvertible : A government neither participates in the international currency market nor allows conversion of its currency by individuals or companies. These currencies are also known as ''blocked'', e.g. the [[North Korean won]] and the [[Cuban peso]].

== Local currencies ==
{{main|Local currency}}

In economics, a local currency is a currency not backed by a national government and intended to trade only in a small area. Advocates such as [[Jane Jacobs]] argue that this enables an economically depressed region to pull itself up, by giving the people living there a medium of exchange that they can use to exchange services and locally produced goods (in a broader sense, this is the original purpose of all money). Opponents of this concept argue that local currency creates a barrier which can interfere with economies of scale and comparative advantage and that in some cases they can serve as a means of [[tax evasion]].

Local currencies can also come into being when there is economic turmoil involving the national currency. An example of this is the Argentinian economic crisis of 2002 in which [[IOU (debt)|IOUs]] issued by local governments quickly took on some of the characteristics of local currencies.

One of the best examples of a local currency is the original [[LETS]] currency, founded on Vancouver Island in the early 1980s.  In 1982, the [[Bank of Canada|Canadian Central Bank]]’s lending rates ran up to 14% which drove chartered bank lending rates as high as 19%.  The resulting currency and credit scarcity left island residents with few options other than to create a local currency.{{refn|{{cite podcast| format = [[MP3]] | url=
http://media.blubrry.com/extraenvironmentalist/p/extraenvironmentalist.com/audio/low/Ep45_final_lowbitrate.mp3 |title=Opening Money |website =The Extraenvironmentalist  |access-date=December 29, 2016}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite interview |last=Linton |first=Michael |last2=Bober |first2=Jordan |subject-link= |interviewer=Seth Moser-Katz; Justin Ritchie |title=Opening Money |url= http://www.extraenvironmentalist.com/2012/07/11/episode-45-opening-money/ |date=November 7, 2012 |work=The Extraenvironmentalist |access-date=December 29, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

== List of major world payment currencies ==

The following table are estimates of the 15 most frequently used currencies in world payments from 2012 to 2018 by [[SWIFT]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.swift.com/about_swift/shownews?param_dcr=news.data/en/swift_com/2014/PR_RMB_Nov_Dec.xml RMB breaks into the top ten most-used currencies for payments]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.swift.com/about_swift/shownews?param_dcr=news.data/en/swift_com/2014/PR_RMB_Jan.xml Chinese Renminbi Overtakes the Swiss Franc as a World Payments Currency]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.swift.com/about_swift/shownews?param_dcr=news.data/en/swift_com/2014/PR_RMB_records_offshores.xml RMB reaches record levels of payments activity between offshore centres]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://ctmfile.com/story/rmb-role-and-share-of-international-payments-is-declining RMB role and share of international payments is declining] CTMfile. April 5, 2017&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.swift.com/file/56351/download?token=pg_59sd1 RMB Tracker Monthly reporting and statistics on renminbi(RMB) progress towards becoming an international currency] (PDF)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.swift.com/file/58686/download?token=4V_STiPJ][https://www.swift.com/file/56351/download?token=pg_59sd1 RMB Tracker February 2019]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.swift.com/our-solutions/compliance-and-shared-services/business-intelligence/renminbi/rmb-tracker/document-centre?tl=en#topic-tabs-menu RMB Tracker August 2019]&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right; font-size:95%&quot;&quot;
|+ 15 Major Currencies in World Payments (in % of World)
! Rank !! Currency !! January&lt;br&gt;2012!! Currency !! January&lt;br&gt;2014 !! Currency !! January&lt;br&gt;2015 !! Currency !! February&lt;br&gt;2017 !! Currency !! January&lt;br&gt;2018
!Currency
!August&lt;br&gt;2019
|-
|  || align=left|'''''[[World]]''''' || 100.00% || align=left|'''''[[World]]''''' || 100.00% || align=left|'''''[[World]]''''' || 100.00% || align=left|'''''[[World]]''''' || 100.00% || align=left|'''''[[World]]''''' || 100.00%
|'''''[[World]]'''''
|100.00%
|-
| 1 || align=left|{{Flagicon|European Union}} [[Euro]] || 44.04% || align=left|{{nowrap|{{Flagicon|United States}} [[United States dollar]]}} || 38.75% || align=left|{{nowrap|{{Flagicon|United States}} [[United States dollar]]}} || 43.41% || align=left|{{nowrap|{{Flagicon|United States}} [[United States dollar]]}} || 40.86% || align=left|{{nowrap|{{Flagicon|United States}} [[United States dollar]]}} || 38.53%
|align=left|{{nowrap|{{Flagicon|United States}} [[United States dollar]]}}
|42.52%
|-
| 2 || align=left|{{nowrap|{{Flagicon|United States}} [[United States dollar]]}} || 29.73% || align=left|{{Flagicon|European Union}} [[Euro]] || 33.52% || align=left|{{Flagicon|European Union}} [[Euro]] || 28.75% || align=left|{{Flagicon|European Union}} [[Euro]] || 32.00% || align=left|{{Flagicon|European Union}} [[Euro]] || 32.75%
|align=left|{{Flagicon|European Union}} [[Euro]]
|32.06%
|-
| 3 || align=left|{{Flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Pound sterling]] || 9.00% || align=left|{{Flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Pound sterling]] || 9.37% || align=left|{{Flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Pound sterling]] || 8.24% || align=left|{{Flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Pound sterling]] || 7.41% || align=left|{{Flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Pound sterling]] || 7.22%
|align=left|{{Flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Pound sterling]]
|6.21%
|-
| 4 || align=left|{{Flagicon|Japan}} [[Japanese yen]] || 2.48% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Japan}} [[Japanese yen]] || 2.50% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Japan}} [[Japanese yen]] || 2.79% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Japan}} [[Japanese yen]] || 3.30% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Japan}} [[Japanese yen]] || 2.80%
|align=left|{{Flagicon|Japan}} [[Japanese yen]]
|3.61%
|-
| 5 || align=left|{{Flagicon|Australia}} [[Australian dollar]] || 2.08% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Canada}} [[Canadian dollar]] || 1.80% || align=left|{{Flagicon|China}} [[Renminbi]] || 2.06% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Canada}} [[Canadian dollar]] || 1.89% || align=left|{{Flagicon|China}} [[Renminbi]]|| 1.66%
|align=left|{{Flagicon|China}} [[Renminbi]]
|2.22%
|-
| 6 || align=left|{{Flagicon|Canada}} [[Canadian dollar]] || 1.81% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Australia}} [[Australian dollar]] || 1.75% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Canada}} [[Canadian dollar]] || 1.91% || align=left|{{Flagicon|China}} [[Renminbi]] || 1.84% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Canada}} [[Canadian dollar]]|| 1.51%
|align=left|{{Flagicon|Canada}} [[Canadian dollar]]
|1.76%
|-
| 7 || align=left|{{Flagicon|Switzerland}} [[Swiss franc]] || 1.36% || align=left|{{Flagicon|China}} [[Renminbi]] || 1.39% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Switzerland}} [[Swiss franc]] || 1.91% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Switzerland}} [[Swiss franc]] || 1.66% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Switzerland}} [[Swiss franc]]|| 1.42%
|align=left|{{Flagicon|Australia}} [[Australian dollar]]
|1.57%
|-
| 8 || align=left|{{Flagicon|Sweden}} [[Swedish krona]] || 1.05% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Switzerland}} [[Swiss franc]] || 1.38% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Australia}} [[Australian dollar]] || 1.74% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Australia}} [[Australian dollar]] || 1.61% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Australia}} [[Australian dollar]]|| 1.38%
|align=left|{{Flagicon|Hong Kong}} [[Hong Kong dollar]]
|1.48%
|-
| 9 || align=left|{{Flagicon|Singapore}} [[Singapore dollar]] || 1.03% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Hong Kong}} [[Hong Kong dollar]] || 1.09% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Hong Kong}} [[Hong Kong dollar]] || 1.28% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Hong Kong}} [[Hong Kong dollar]] || 1.30% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Hong Kong}} [[Hong Kong dollar]]|| 1.32%
|align=left|{{Flagicon|Thailand}} [[Thai baht]]
|1.00%
|-
| 10 || align=left|{{Flagicon|Hong Kong}} [[Hong Kong dollar]] || 0.95% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Thailand}} [[Thai baht]] || 0.98% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Thailand}} [[Thai baht]] || 0.98% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Thailand}} [[Thai baht]] || 1.01% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Singapore}} [[Singapore dollar]] || 1.01%
|align=left|{{Flagicon|Singapore}} [[Singapore dollar]]
|0.98%
|-
| 11 || align=left|{{Flagicon|Norway}} [[Norwegian krone]] || 0.93% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Sweden}} [[Swedish krona]] || 0.97% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Singapore}} [[Singapore dollar]] || 0.89% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Sweden}} [[Swedish krona]] || 0.97%  || align=left|{{Flagicon|Thailand}} [[Thai baht]] || 0.95%
|align=left|{{Flagicon|Switzerland}} [[Swiss franc]]
|0.98%
|-
| 12 || align=left|{{Flagicon|Thailand}} [[Thai baht]] || 0.82% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Singapore}} [[Singapore dollar]] || 0.88% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Sweden}} [[Swedish krona]] || 0.80% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Singapore}} [[Singapore dollar]] || 0.96% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Sweden}} [[Swedish krona]] || 0.85%
|align=left|{{Flagicon|Sweden}} [[Swedish krona]]
|0.79%
|-
| 13 || align=left|{{Flagicon|Denmark}} [[Danish krone]] || 0.54% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Norway}} [[Norwegian krone]] || 0.80% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Norway}} [[Norwegian krone]] || 0.68% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Norway}} [[Norwegian krone]] || 0.68% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Norway}} [[Norwegian krone]] || 0.64%
|align=left|{{Flagicon|Norway}} [[Norwegian krone]]
|0.71%
|-
| 14 || align=left|{{Flagicon|Russia}} [[Russian ruble]] || 0.52% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Denmark}} [[Danish krone]] || 0.60% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Denmark}} [[Danish krone]] || 0.56% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Poland}} [[Polish złoty]] || 0.51% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Poland}} [[Polish złoty]] || 0.47%
|align=left|{{Flagicon|Poland}} [[Polish złoty]]
|0.56%
|-
| 15 || align=left|{{Flagicon|South Africa}} [[South African rand]] || 0.48% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Poland}} [[Polish złoty]] || 0.58% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Poland}} [[Polish złoty]] || 0.55% || align=left|{{Flagicon|South Africa}} [[South African rand]] || 0.45% || align=left|{{Flagicon|Malaysia}} [[Malaysian ringgit]] || 0.41%
|align=left|{{Flagicon|Malaysia}} [[Malaysian ringgit]]
|0.43%
|}

== See also ==
{{portal|Numismatics|Business and economics|History|Society|Money}}
{{col-begin|width=auto}}
{{col-break}}
'''Related concepts'''
* [[Counterfeit money]]
* [[Currency transaction tax]]
* [[Debasement]]
* [[Exchange rate]]
* [[Fiscal localism]]
* [[Foreign exchange market]]
* [[Foreign exchange reserves]]
* [[History of banking]]
* [[History of money]]
* [[Mutilated currency]]
* [[Optimum currency area]]
* [[Slang terms for money]]
* [[Virtual currency]]
* [[World currency]]
{{col-break|gap=4em}}
'''Accounting units'''
* [[Currency pair]]
* [[Currency symbol]]
* [[Currency strength]]
* [[European Currency Unit]]
* [[Fictional currency]]
* [[Franc Poincaré]]
* [[Local currencies]]
* [[Petrocurrency]]
* [[Special drawing rights]]
{{col-break|gap=4em}}
'''Lists'''
* [[ISO 4217]]
* [[List of alternative names for currency]]
* [[List of currencies]]
* [[List of circulating currencies]]
* [[List of proposed currencies]]
* [[List of historical currencies]]
* [[List of historical exchange rates]]
* [[List of international trade topics]]
* [[List of motifs on banknotes]]
{{col-end}}

== Notes ==
{{NoteFoot}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Wikidata property|P38}}
* {{Commons category-inline|Currency}}
* {{Wikiquote-inline|Currency}}

{{-}}
{{Means of Exchange}}
{{Economics}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Currency| ]]
[[Category:Foreign exchange market]]</text>
      <sha1>35v6eph91dinfzembfn9tpizdeigvcs</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
