  <page>
    <title>Cypress Hill</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5637</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941022924</id>
      <parentid>940830339</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-16T04:01:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DocWatson42</username>
        <id>38455</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */Added a &quot;dead link&quot; template and performed other cleanup.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=May 2019}}
{{distinguish|text=[[Cypress Hills (disambiguation)|Cypress Hills]]}}
{{Infobox musical artist | &lt;!-- See Wikipedia:WikiProject Musicians --&gt;
| name            = Cypress Hill
| image           = 
| caption         = 
| image_size      = 
| landscape       = yes
| background      = group_or_band
| alias           = 
| origin          = [[South Gate, California]], U.S.
| genre           = &lt;!--Do not add unsourced subgenres of hip hop.--&gt;{{flatlist|
* [[Hip hop music|Hip hop]]
* [[trip hop]]
* [[Latin hip hop]]
* [[West coast hip hop]]
* [[hardcore hip hop]]
* [[rap rock]]
* [[rap metal]]
* [[nu metal]]
* [[experimental hip hop]]
* [[gangsta rap]]}}
| years_active    = 1991–present&lt;ref name=&quot;Cypress&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://m.youtube.com/user/CypressHillVideo/about|title=Cypress Hill|publisher=[[YouTube]]|accessdate=2019-10-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| label           = {{hlist|[[Ruffhouse Records|Ruffhouse]]|[[Columbia Records|Columbia]]|[[Priority Records|Priority]]|[[EMI Records|EMI]]}}
| associated_acts = {{hlist|[[The Alchemist (record producer)|The Alchemist]]|[[Fredwreck]]|[[Kottonmouth Kings]]|[[Pitbull (rapper)|Pitbull]]|[[Rusko (musician)|Rusko]]|[[Travis Barker]]|[[Powerflo]]|[[Deadmau5]]}}
| website         = {{URL|cypresshill.com}}
| current_members = 
* [[B-Real]]
* [[DJ Muggs]]
* [[Sen Dog]]
* [[Eric &quot;Bobo&quot; Correa|Eric Bobo]]
* [[Mix Master Mike]]
| past_members = 
}}

'''Cypress Hill''' is an American [[Hip hop music|hip hop]] group from [[South Gate, California]]. Cypress Hill was the first Latino American hip hop recording group to have a star on the [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]] and [[RIAA certification|platinum]] and multi-platinum albums, selling over 20 million albums worldwide. They are considered to be among the main progenitors of [[West Coast rap]] and [[hip hop]] in the early 1990s, being critically acclaimed for their first four albums.&lt;ref name=&quot;Edwards&quot;&gt;Edwards, Paul, 2009, ''[[How to Rap]]: The Art &amp; Science of the Hip-Hop MC'', Chicago Review Press, p. 316.&lt;/ref&gt; The band has also advocated for [[medical marijuana|medical]] and recreational use of [[cannabis in the United States]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Hill|first=Cypress|title=High Times and the High Times Mag Cover|url=http://rapgenius.com/Cypress-hill-high-times-lyrics#note-842809|publisher=Rap Genius}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

===Formation (1988)===
Senen Reyes (also known as [[Sen Dog]]) and Ulpiano Sergio Reyes (also known as [[Mellow Man Ace]]) are brothers born in [[Pinar del Río]], Cuba. In 1971, their family immigrated to the United States from Cuba. They initially lived in [[South Gate, California]]. In 1988, the two brothers teamed up with New York City native Lawrence Muggerud (also known as [[DJ Muggs]], previously in a rap group named [[7A3]]) and Louis Freese (also known as [[B-Real]]) to form a hip-hop group named DVX (Devastating Vocal Excellence). The band soon lost Mellow Man Ace to a solo career, and changed their name to Cypress Hill, after a street in South Gate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Biography&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://whiplash.net/materias/biografias/038946-cypresshill.html |title=Cypress Hill – Biography|publisher=Whiplash|accessdate=April 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Early works and mainstream success (1989–95)===
After recording a demo in 1989, Cypress Hill signed a record deal with Ruffhouse Records. Their [[Cypress Hill (album)|self-titled first album]] was released in August 1991. The lead single was the double [[A-side]] &quot;[[The Phuncky Feel One]]&quot;/&quot;[[How I Could Just Kill a Man]]&quot; which received heavy airplay on urban and college radio. The other two singles released from the album were &quot;Hand on the Pump&quot; and &quot;Latin Lingo&quot;, the latter of which combined English and Spanish lyrics. The success of these singles led to the album selling two million copies in the US alone. Cypress Hill contributed the song &quot;Shoot 'Em Up&quot; to the [[Juice (soundtrack)|soundtrack]] of the movie ''[[Juice (film)|Juice]]''. The group made their first appearance at [[Lollapalooza]] on the side stage in 1992.
[[File:Cypress Hill-mika.jpg|left|thumbnail|Germany 1998]]
''[[Black Sunday (Cypress Hill album)|Black Sunday]]'', the group's second album, debuted at number one on the [[Billboard 200|''Billboard'' 200]] in 1993, recording the highest [[Soundscan]] for a rap group up until that time. Also, with their debut still in the charts, they became the first rap group to have two albums in the top 10 of the ''Billboard'' 200 at the same time. With &quot;[[Insane in the Brain]]&quot; becoming a crossover hit, the album went triple platinum in the U.S. and sold about 3.25&amp;nbsp;million copies.

The band headlined the [[Soul Assassins]] tour with [[House of Pain]] and [[Funkdoobiest]] as support, then performed on a college tour with [[Rage Against the Machine]] and [[Seven Year Bitch]]. In 1993, Cypress Hill also had two tracks on the ''[[Judgment Night (film)|Judgment Night]]'' soundtrack, teaming up with [[Pearl Jam]] (without singer [[Eddie Vedder]]) on the track &quot;Real Thing&quot; and [[Sonic Youth]] on &quot;I Love You Mary Jane&quot;.

The group later played at [[Woodstock 94]], introducing new member Eric Bobo, son of [[Willie Bobo]] and formerly a percussionist with the [[Beastie Boys]]. ''Rolling Stone'' magazine named the group as the best rap group in their music awards voted by critics and readers. Cypress Hill played at [[Lollapalooza]] for two successive years, topping the bill in 1995. They also appeared on the &quot;[[Homerpalooza]]&quot; episode of ''[[The Simpsons]]''. Prior to Bobo joining the crew, Panchito &quot;Ponch&quot; Gomez sat in as a percussionist when not acting.

Their third album ''[[III: Temples of Boom]]'' was released in 1995, the album was certified Platinum by the [[RIAA]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=RIAA|title=RIAA Gold and Platinum Program: Cypress Hill|url=https://www.riaa.com/goldandplatinumdata.php?artist=%22III+%28Temple+of+Boom%29%22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cypress Hill also contributed a track &quot;I Wanna Get High&quot; to the [[High Times]] sponsored ''[[Hempilation]]'' album to support [[National Organization for the Reform of Marijuana Laws|NORML]].

===Continued career (1996–2002)===
Sen Dog took a break from the band to form a Los Angeles-based rap rock band, [[SX-10]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=''SX10 tocara hoy en el DanZoo'' |url=http://www.jornada.unam.mx/2003/05/24/21an2esp.php?printver=1&amp;fly=2 |publisher=[[La Jornada]] |location=Mexico City |date=May 24, 2003 |accessdate=December 31, 2008 |language=Spanish }}&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, in 1996, Cypress Hill appeared on the first Smokin' Grooves tour, featuring [[Ziggy Marley]], [[The Fugees]], [[Busta Rhymes]] and [[A Tribe Called Quest]]. The band also released a nine track EP ''[[Unreleased and Revamped]]'' with rare mixes. In 1997, band members focused on their solo careers. Muggs released ''[[Chapter 1 (Soul Assassins album)|Soul Assassins: Chapter 1]]'' featuring contributions from [[Dr. Dre]], [[KRS-One]], [[Wyclef Jean]] and [[Mobb Deep]]. B-Real appeared with Busta Rhymes, [[Coolio]], [[LL Cool J]] and [[Method Man]] on &quot;Hit Em High&quot; from the multi-platinum ''[[Space Jam (soundtrack)|Space Jam Soundtrack]]''. He also appeared with [[RBX]], [[Nas]] and KRS-One on &quot;East Coast Killer, West Coast Killer&quot; from Dr. Dre's ''[[Dr. Dre Presents the Aftermath]]'' album, and contributed to an album entitled ''[[The Psycho Realm]]'' with [[Psycho Realm|the band of the same name]]. Though the focus that year was not on group efforts, the band played Smokin' Grooves with [[George Clinton (funk musician)|George Clinton]] and [[Erykah Badu]].

Cypress Hill released ''[[IV (Cypress Hill album)|IV]]'' in 1998 which went gold in the US, on the backs of hit singles &quot;Tequila Sunrise&quot; and &quot;Dr. Greenthumb&quot;. Sen Dog also released the ''Get Wood'' sampler as part of SX-10 on the label Flip. In 1999, Cypress Hill helped with the [[Personal computer|PC]] crime video game ''[[Kingpin: Life of Crime]]''. Three of the band's songs from the 1998 ''IV'' album were in the game (&quot;16 Men Till There's No Men Left&quot;, &quot;Checkmate&quot; and &quot;Lightning Strikes&quot;). B-Real also did voice work for some of the game's characters.  Also in 1999, the band released a greatest-hits album in Spanish, ''[[Los grandes éxitos en español]]''. In 2000, Cypress Hill then fused genres with their fifth album, ''[[Skull &amp; Bones (album)|Skull &amp; Bones]]'', which was a two-disc album. The first disc, &quot;Skull&quot; was composed of rap tracks while &quot;Bones&quot; explored further the group's forays into rock. The album reached the Top 5 on the [[Billboard magazine|Billboard]] 200 and number 3 in Canada. The first single was &quot;Rock Superstar&quot; for rock radio and &quot;Rap Superstar&quot; for urban radio. Following the release of the album, Cypress Hill (along with [[MxPx]]) landed a slot opening for [[The Offspring]] on the [[Conspiracy of One]] tour. The band also released ''[[Live at the Fillmore (Cypress Hill album)|Live at the Fillmore]]'', a concert disc recorded at the [[The Fillmore|Fillmore]] (in San Francisco) in 2000. Cypress Hill continued their experimentation with rock on the ''[[Stoned Raiders]]'' album in 2001. However, its sales were a disappointment, as the disc did not even reach the top 50 of the US album charts. In 2001, the group appeared in the film ''[[How High]]''.

===''Till Death Do Us Part'' (2003–07)===
Cypress Hill recorded &quot;Just Another Victim&quot; for [[WWE]] as a theme song for [[Tazz]]. At the time, WWE was using original music for almost all of the wrestlers.  The band released ''[[Till Death Do Us Part (Cypress Hill album)|Till Death Do Us Part]]'' on March 23, 2004. The album saw the band experiment with [[reggae]] especially on the lead single &quot;What's Your Number&quot;. The track features [[Tim Armstrong]] of [[Rancid (band)|Rancid]] on guitar and backup vocals. It is based on the classic song &quot;[[The Guns of Brixton]]&quot; on [[The Clash]]'s ''[[London Calling]]'' and has proven to be a success on the modern rock charts. However, the album represented a further departure from the signature sound of their first four albums. The album also features appearances by [[Damian Marley]], son of [[Bob Marley]], [[Prodigy (rapper)|Prodigy]] of [[Mobb Deep]] and producers [[The Alchemist (musician)|the Alchemist]] and [[Fredwreck]].

In 2004, the song &quot;How I Could Just Kill A Man&quot; was included in the popular video game ''[[Grand Theft Auto: San Andreas]]'' created by [[Rockstar Games]], playing on [[West Coast hip hop]] radio station [[Radio Los Santos]]. In December 2005 a best of [[compilation album]] titled ''[[Greatest Hits From the Bong]]'' was released including nine hits from previous albums and two new tracks. The group's next album was tentatively scheduled for an early 2007 release. In the summer of 2006, B-Real appeared on [[Snoop Dogg]]'s single &quot;[[Vato (song)|Vato]]&quot;, which was produced by [[Pharrell Williams]].

In 2007 Cypress Hill toured with their full line up as a part of the [[Rock the Bells]] tour, held by Guerilla Union, B Simm, and headlined with [[Public Enemy (band)|Public Enemy]], [[Wu-Tang Clan]], [[Nas]], and a reunited [[Rage Against the Machine]].

===Departure from Sony, ''Rise Up'' and ''Elephants on Acid'' (2008–present)===
On July 25, 2008, Cypress Hill performed at a benefit concert at the House of Blues Chicago, where a majority of the proceeds went to the Chicago Alliance to End Homelessness.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.theblackspotlight.com/news/Cypress_Hill_To_Perform_At_Benefit_To_End_Homelessness.html |title=Cypress Hill To Perform at Benefit of Homelessness in youth dance event for euphoria and aid relief |publisher=Theblackspotlight.com |accessdate=20 April 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111004104738/http://www.theblackspotlight.com/news/Cypress_Hill_To_Perform_At_Benefit_To_End_Homelessness.html |archivedate=October 4, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2009, a new song by Cypress Hill, titled &quot;Get 'Em Up&quot;, was made available on iTunes. The song is featured on the Madden NFL 2010 video game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bleacherreport.com/articles/224562-madden-2010-soundtrack-revealed|title=Madden 2010 Soundtrack Revealed|date=July 26, 2009|publisher=Bleacher Report, Inc.|accessdate=April 22, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 2009, a new version of the [[Guns N' Roses]] classic &quot;[[Paradise City]]&quot; performed by Cypress Hill, [[Slash (musician)|Slash]] and [[Fergie (singer)|Fergie]] was made available as a bonus track to Slash's single &quot;[[Sahara (Slash song)|Sahara]]&quot; from Slash's solo album ''[[Slash (album)|Slash]]''.

Cypress Hill's eighth studio album ''[[Rise Up (Cypress Hill album)|Rise Up]]'', features contributions from [[Everlast (musician)|Everlast]], [[Tom Morello]], [[Daron Malakian]], [[Pitbull (rapper)|Pitbull]], [[Marc Anthony]] and [[Mike Shinoda]].&lt;ref name=&quot;RiseUp&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://newsroom.mtv.com/2008/10/03/cypress-hill-to-return-with-help-from-slash-tom-morello-and-mike-shinoda/|title=Cypress Hill to Return With Help From Slash, Tom Morello and Mike Shinoda|accessdate=September 7, 2009|archive-url=https://archive.is/20120630113619/http://newsroom.mtv.com/2008/10/03/cypress-hill-to-return-with-help-from-slash-tom-morello-and-mike-shinoda/|archive-date=June 30, 2012|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; The album was released on [[Priority Records|Priority Records/EMI Entertainment]], as the group was signed to the label by new Creative chairman [[Snoop Dogg]] on January 15, 2010. The album was released on April 20, 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;Priority&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://allhiphop.com/stories/news/archive/2010/01/15/22097556.aspx|title=Snoop Dogg Signs Cypress Hill To Priority|last=Wolfe|first=Roman|date=January 15, 2010|publisher=Infinity, Allhiphop.com, Inc.|accessdate=April 22, 2010|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100418002032/http://allhiphop.com/stories/news/archive/2010/01/15/22097556.aspx|archivedate=April 18, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The album's introduction single, &quot;It Ain't Nothin'&quot; was released as a free download from the group's official website. The song &quot;[[Rise Up (Cypress Hill song)|Rise Up]]&quot; was featured at [[WWE]]'s pay-per-view, [[Elimination Chamber (2010)|Elimination Chamber]], as the official theme song for that event, and was released as the third single for the album, with &quot;Armada Latina&quot; being fourth. The song also appeared in the trailer of the movie ''[[The Green Hornet (2011 film)|The Green Hornet]]''.

Cypress Hill commenced its Rise Up tour in [[Philadelphia]] on April 10, 2010. Julio G had replaced DJ Muggs for the tour. Muggs had been absent due to working on several other projects, including separate albums with B-Real and Sen Dog.  The group was supposed to stop in Tucson, Arizona but canceled the show in protest of the recent immigration legislation. At the [[Rock en Seine]] festival in Paris on August 27, 2010 they said in an interview that they would wait and see what happens with the legislation before going back there.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.english.rfi.fr/visiting-france/20100828-cypress-hill-love-snails-and-dope-not-arizonas-law |title=Cypress Hill – Love the snails and the dope, but not Arizona's law &amp;#124; RFI |accessdate=20 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cypress Hill performed at the [[Reading and Leeds Festivals]] in 2010, on August 28 at Leeds and August 29 at Reading.

On June 5, 2012, Cypress Hill and dubstep artist [[Rusko (musician)|Rusko]] released a collaborative EP entitled ''[[Cypress X Rusko]]''. Also in 2012, Cypress Hill collaborated with [[Deadmau5]] on his sixth studio album ''[[Album Title Goes Here]]'', lending vocals on &quot;Failbait&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=RJ Cubarrubia |url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/news/ep-premiere-deadmau5-the-veldt-20120620 |title=EP Premiere: Deadmau5, 'The Veldt' &amp;#124; Music News |work=Rolling Stone |date=June 20, 2012 |accessdate=10 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2017, Cypress Hill's &quot;Ain't going out like that&quot; was featured as a trailer soundtrack for Netflix's Narcos Season 3.

On September 28, 2018, Cypress Hill released the album [[Elephants on Acid]], which saw the return of DJ Muggs as main composer and producer.

On April 2019 Cypress Hill received a star on the [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.billboard.com/articles/columns/hip-hop/8507891/cypress-hill-star-hollywood-walk-of-fame|title=Cypress Hill Get a Star on Hollywood Walk of Fame: 'Seeing This Here, It Is an Honor'|website=Billboard|access-date=2019-06-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Style==

===Rapping===
One of the band's most striking aspects is B-Real's exaggeratedly high-pitched nasal vocals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Biography&quot; /&gt; In the book ''[[Check the Technique]]'', B-Real describes his nasal style, saying his rapping voice is &quot;high and annoying... the nasal style I have was just something that I developed... my more natural style wasn't so pleasing to [[DJ Muggs]] and [[Sen Dog]]'s ears&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coleman&quot;&gt;Coleman, Brian. ''[[Check The Technique]]: Liner Notes For Hip-Hop Junkies''. New York: Villard/Random House, 2007, pp. 122–123.&lt;/ref&gt; and talking about the nasal style in the book ''[[How to Rap]]'', B-Real says, &quot;you want to stand out from the others and just be distinct... when you got something that can separate you from everybody else, you gotta use it to your advantage.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Edwards&quot; /&gt; In the film Art of Rap, B-Real credits the [[Beastie Boys]] as an influence when developing his rapping style. Sen Dog's voice is deeper, more violent and often shouted alongside the rapping; his vocals are often emphasized by adding another background/choir voice to say them. Sen Dog's style is in contrast to B-Real's, who says, &quot;Sen's voice is so strong,&quot; and &quot;it all blends together&quot; when they are both on the same track.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coleman&quot; /&gt;

Both B-Real and Sen Dog started writing lyrics in both Spanish and English and B-Real was inspired to start writing raps from watching Sen Dog and [[Mellow Man Ace]] writing their lyrics,&lt;ref name=&quot;Coleman&quot; /&gt; and originally B-Real was going to just be the writer for the group rather than a rapper.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coleman&quot; /&gt; Their lyrics are noted for bringing a &quot;cartoonish&quot; approach to violence by [[Peter Shapiro (journalist)|Peter Shapiro]] and Allmusic.&lt;ref name=&quot;Biography&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Shapiro&quot;&gt;Shapiro, Peter, 2005, ''The Rough Guide To Hip-Hop'', 2nd Edition, Penguin, pp. 73–74.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Production===
The sound and groove of their music, produced by Muggs, has spooky sounds and a stoned aesthetic; with its bass-heavy rhythms and odd sample loops (&quot;Insane in the Brain&quot; has a pitched-altered horse neigh looped in its chorus), it carries a psychedelic value, which is lessened in their later albums.&lt;ref name=&quot;Biography&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Shapiro&quot; /&gt;

For using rock/metal instrumentation the band is sometimes classified as a [[rap rock]]/[[metal rap]] group.&lt;ref name=&quot;Biography&quot; /&gt; The double album ''Skull &amp; Bones'' consists of a pure rap album (&quot;Skull&quot;) and an entire CD of rap/rock/nu metal songs (&quot;Bones&quot;). In the live album ''Live at The Fillmore'' some of the old classics are played in a rock/metal version, with Sen Dog's band SX-10 and [[Eric &quot;Bobo&quot; Correa|Eric Bobo]] playing the rock instrument.

While the first album and ''Black Sunday'' follow a more minimalistic and funky sound, ''III (Temples of Boom)'' has a very dark, spooky atmosphere and heavy beats, sometimes approaching [[hardcore rap]]. ''IV'' introduced more diverse sounds on the beats while maintaining the hardcore edge. The first albums are mostly influenced by psychedelic music, but the band eventually got closer to modern rap as it is today while still experimenting with rock from time to time, like on &quot;Skull and Bones&quot; and &quot;Stoned Raiders&quot;.

==Discography==
{{Main|Cypress Hill discography}}

===Studio albums===
* ''[[Cypress Hill (album)|Cypress Hill]]'' (1991)
* ''[[Black Sunday (Cypress Hill album)|Black Sunday]]'' (1993)
* ''[[Cypress Hill III: Temples of Boom]]'' (1995)
* ''[[Cypress Hill IV]]'' (1998)
* ''[[Skull &amp; Bones (album)|Skull &amp; Bones]]'' (2000)
* ''[[Stoned Raiders]]'' (2001)
* ''[[Till Death Do Us Part (Cypress Hill album)|Till Death Do Us Part]]'' (2004)
* ''[[Rise Up (Cypress Hill album)|Rise Up]]'' (2010)
* ''[[Elephants on Acid]]'' (2018)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hiphopdx.com/news/id.37457/title.b-real-announces-title-of-new-cypress-hill-album|title=New Cypress Hill Album 'Elephants on Acid'|website=Hiphopdx.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Extended plays===
* ''[[Unreleased and Revamped]]'' (1996)

==Awards and nominations==
'''Grammy Awards'''
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Year
!Nominated work
!Award
!Result
|-
|align=center|[[Grammy Awards of 1994|1994]]
|&quot;[[Insane in the Brain]]&quot;
|Best Rap Performance by a Group or Duo
|{{nom}}
|-
|align=center|[[Grammy Awards of 1995|1995]]
|&quot;I Ain't Goin' Out Like That&quot;
|Best Rap Performance by a Group or Duo
|{{nom}}
|-
|align=center|[[Grammy Awards of 1996|1996]]
|&quot;Throw Your Set in the Air&quot;
|Best Rap Performance by a Group or Duo
|{{nom}}
|}

[[MTV Video Music Award]]s
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Year
!Nominated work
!Award
!Result
|-
|align=center|[[1994 MTV Video Music Awards|1994]]
|&quot;Insane in the Brain&quot;
|[[MTV Video Music Award for Best Rap Video|Best Rap Video]]
|{{nom}}
|}

[[Hollywood walk of fame]]
{{Awards table}}
|-
|2019
|Cypress Hill
|[[Hollywood Walk of Fame]]
|{{won}}

|}

==Members==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
&lt;!--- Please do not change the order of members, as they are in alphabetical order by the year when they originally joined the group. ---&gt;
;Current
* Louis &quot;[[B-Real]]&quot; Freese – lead vocals (1988–present)
* Senen &quot;[[Sen Dog]]&quot; Reyes – vocals (1988–present)
* Eric &quot;[[Eric &quot;Bobo&quot; Correa|Bobo]]&quot; Correa – drums, percussion (1993–present)
* Lawrence &quot;[[DJ Muggs]]&quot; Muggerud – [[Turntablism|turntables]], [[Sampling (music)|samples]] (1988–2004; 2014–present)
{{col-3}}
;Former
* Ulpiano &quot;[[Mellow Man Ace]]&quot; Reyes – vocals (1988)
* Farid &quot;[[Fredwreck]]&quot; Nassar – turntables, samples (2004–07)
{{col-end}}

;Timeline
{{#tag:timeline|
ImageSize = width:800 height:auto barincrement:20
PlotArea = left:100 bottom:100 top:5 right:20
Alignbars = justify
DateFormat  = mm/dd/yyyy
Period = from:01/01/1988 till:{{#time:m/d/Y}}
TimeAxis = orientation:horizontal format:yyyy
Legend = orientation:vertical position:bottom columns:4
ScaleMajor = increment:2 start:1988

Colors =
  id:Vocals         value:red          legend:Vocals
  id:DJ             value:lavender        legend:Turntables,_samples
  id:Drums          value:orange        legend:Drums,_percussion
  id:Studio         value:black        legend:Studio_album

LineData =
  layer:back
  color:Studio
  at:08/13/1991
  at:07/20/1993
  at:10/31/1995
  at:10/06/1998
  at:04/25/2000
  at:12/04/2001
  at:03/24/2004
  at:04/20/2010
  at:04/20/2010
  at:09/28/2018

BarData =
  bar:Freese       text:&quot;B-Real&quot;
  bar:SReyes       text:&quot;Sen Dog&quot;
  bar:UReyes       text:&quot;Mellow Man Ace&quot;
  bar:Muggerud     text:&quot;DJ Muggs&quot;
  bar:Nassar       text:&quot;Fredwreck&quot;
  bar:Correa       text:&quot;Eric Bobo&quot;

PlotData=
  width:11
  bar:Freese      from:01/01/1988 till:end              color:Vocals
  bar:SReyes      from:01/01/1988 till:end              color:Vocals
  bar:UReyes      from:01/01/1988 till:01/01/1989       color:Vocals
  bar:Muggerud    from:01/01/1988 till:05/11/2004       color:DJ
  bar:Nassar      from:05/12/2004 till:05/11/2007       color:DJ
  bar:Muggerud    from:05/11/2014 till:end              color:DJ
  bar:Correa      from:05/11/1993 till:end              color:Drums
}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons}}
* {{official website|http://www.cypresshill.com/}}
* [http://weave.me/app/weave.html?Cypress_Hill Cypress Hill on Weave]{{dead link|date=February 2020}}

{{Cypress Hill}}
{{DJ Muggs}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Cypress Hill| ]]
[[Category:1988 establishments in California]]
[[Category:American cannabis activists]]
[[Category:Bloods]]
[[Category:Cannabis music]]
[[Category:Columbia Records artists]]
[[Category:Hispanic and Latino American rappers]]
[[Category:Musical groups established in 1988]]
[[Category:Musical groups from California]]
[[Category:People from South Gate, California]]
[[Category:Priority Records artists]]
[[Category:Rappers from Los Angeles]]
[[Category:West Coast hip hop groups]]</text>
      <sha1>oxpnaq2a0v3bab522abfcgjxczefkxj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
