  <page>
    <title>Calendar year</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5662</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943246905</id>
      <parentid>940812645</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T19:36:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jaiyou</username>
        <id>38665624</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>By refering a very important and used calender system.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=June 2009}}
Generally speaking, a '''calendar year''' begins on the [[New Year's Day]] of the given [[calendar]] system and ends on the day before the following New Year's Day, and thus consists of a [[natural number|whole number]] of days. A [[year]] can also be measured by starting on any other named day of the calendar, and ending on the day before this named day in the following year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite dictionary | url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/calendar%20year | title=calendar year | dictionary=Merriam-Webster | accessdate=6 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This may be termed a &quot;year's time&quot;, but not a &quot;calendar year&quot;.  To reconcilie the calendar year with the astronomical cycle (which has a fractional number of days) certain years contain [[Intercalation (timekeeping)|extra days]] (&quot;leap days&quot; or &quot;intercalary days&quot;).

The [[Gregorian calendar|Gregorian]] year, which is in use in most of the world, begins on January 1 and ends on December 31. It has a length of 365 days in an [[common year|ordinary year]], with 8,760 hours, 525,600 minutes, or 31,536,000 seconds; but 366 days in a [[leap year]], with 8,784 hours, 527,040 minutes, or 31,622,400 seconds. With 97 leap years every 400 years, the year has an average length of 365.2425 days. Other formula-based calendars can have lengths which are further out of step with the solar cycle: for example, the [[Julian calendar]] has an average length of 365.25 days, and the [[Hebrew calendar]] has an average length of 365.2468 days. The [[Islamic calendar]] is a [[lunar calendar]] consisting of 12 [[lunar month|months]] in a year of 354 or 355 days. The [[Hindu calendar]] maintains the integrity of the lunar month, but insert an extra full month by complex rules, every few years, to ensure that the festivals and crop-related rituals fall in the appropriate season.

The astronomer's [[mean tropical year]], which is averaged over equinoxes and solstices, is currently 365.24219 days, slightly shorter than the average length of the year in most calendars, but the astronomer's value changes over time, so [[John Herschel]]'s suggested correction to the Gregorian calendar may become unnecessary by the year 4000.

==Quarters==
The calendar year can be divided into four quarters, often abbreviated as Q1, Q2, Q3, and Q4.

In [[Gregorian calendar]]:
* First quarter, Q1: 1 January – 31 March (90 days or 91 days in leap years)
* Second quarter, Q2: 1 April – 30 June (91 days)
* Third quarter, Q3: 1 July – 30 September (92 days)
* Fourth quarter, Q4: 1 October – 31 December (92 days)

While in the [[Chinese calendar]], the quarters are traditionally associated with the 4 [[season]]s of the year:
* [[spring (season)|Spring]]: 1st to 3rd month
* [[Summer]]: 4th to 6th month
* [[Autumn]]: 7th to 9th month
* [[Winter]]: 10th to 12th month

When combined with a year, the quarter/year combination may be written, for example, as Q4{{CURRENTYEAR}} or 4Q{{CURRENTYEAR}} or {{CURRENTYEAR}}Q4.

== See also ==
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [[Academic term]]
* [[Calendar reform]]
* [[Common year]]
* [[Fiscal year]]
* [[ISO 8601]]
* [[ISO week date]]
* [[Leap year]]
* [[Model year]]
* [[Tropical year]]
* [[Seasonal year]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Calendars|Year]]
[[Category:Units of time]]
[[Category:Years]]</text>
      <sha1>eklkaooo8fj5iglfy1g0qp1p3mma130</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
