  <page>
    <title>Consonant</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5641</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937402605</id>
      <parentid>937398324</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-24T20:07:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Megaman en m</username>
        <id>7269056</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted [[WP:AGF|good faith]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/Goo3|Goo3]] ([[User talk:Goo3|talk]]): Very off-topic, this article is about consonants, not the number of phonemes in French ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{for|the alternative rock group|Consonant (band)}}
{{hatnote|Not to be confused with the musical concept of [[Consonance and dissonance|consonance]]}}
[[File:Latin alphabet Tt.svg|thumb|upright=.62|alt=T|The letter [[T]], the most common consonant letter in English&lt;ref&gt;Zim, Herbert Spencer. Codes and secret writing (abridged edition). Scholastic Book Services, fourth printing, 1962. Copyright 1948 Herbert S. Zim. Originally published by William Morrow.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
{{Place of articulation}}
{{IPA notice}}
In [[articulatory phonetics]], a '''consonant''' is a [[speech sound]] that is articulated with complete or partial closure of the [[vocal tract]]. Examples are {{IPA|[p]}}, pronounced with the lips; {{IPA|[t]}}, pronounced with the front of the tongue; {{IPA|[k]}}, pronounced with the back of the tongue; {{IPA|[h]}}, pronounced in the throat; {{IPA|[f]}} and {{IPA|[s]}}, pronounced by forcing air through a narrow channel ([[fricative]]s); and {{IPA|[m]}} and {{IPA|[n]}}, which have air flowing through the nose ([[nasal consonant|nasal]]s). Contrasting with consonants are [[vowel]]s.

Since the number of possible sounds in all of the world's languages is much greater than the number of letters in any one [[alphabet]], [[Linguistics|linguists]] have devised systems such as the [[International Phonetic Alphabet]] (IPA) to assign a unique and unambiguous [[symbol]] to each attested consonant. In fact, the [[English alphabet]] has fewer consonant letters than English has consonant sounds, so [[Digraph (orthography)|digraph]]s like &quot;ch&quot;, &quot;sh&quot;, &quot;th&quot;, and &quot;zh&quot; are used to extend the alphabet, and some letters and digraphs represent more than one consonant. For example, the sound spelled &quot;th&quot; in &quot;this&quot; is a different consonant from the &quot;th&quot; sound in &quot;thin&quot;. (In the [[International Phonetic Alphabet|IPA]], they are transcribed {{IPA|[ð]}} and {{IPA|[θ]}}, respectively.)

==Etymology==
The word ''consonant'' comes from [[Latin]] oblique stem ''cōnsonant-,'' from ''cōnsonāns (littera)'' &quot;sounding-together (letter)&quot;, a [[calque]] of Greek σύμφωνον ''sýmphōnon'' (plural ''sýmphōna'').&lt;ref&gt;{{LSJ|su/mfwnos|σύμφωνος|ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Robert K. Barnhart, ''ed.'', ''Chambers Dictionary of Etymology'', Previously published as ''The Barnhart Dictionary of Etymology'', originally ©1988 The H.W. Wilson Company; Edinburgh, reprinted 2001: Chambers Harrap Publishers Ltd., p. 210.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Dionysius Thrax]] calls consonants ''sýmphōna'' &quot;pronounced with&quot; because they can only be pronounced with a vowel.{{efn|Dionysius Thrax:
:{{lang|grc|σύμφονα δὲ τὰ λοιπὰ ἑπτακαίδεκα· β γ δ ζ θ κ λ μ ν ξ π ρ σ τ φ χ ψ. σύμφοναι δὲ +λέγονται+, ὅτι αὐτὰ μὲν καθ᾽ ἑαυτὰ φωνὴν οὐκ ἔχει, συντασσόμενα δὲ μετὰ τῶν φωνηέντων φωνὴν ἀποτελεῖ.}}
:The remaining seventeen are consonants: b, g, d, z, th, k, l, m, n, x, p, r, s, t, ph, ch, ps. They are called consonants because they do not have a sound on their own, but, when arranged with vowels, they produce a sound.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thrax&quot;&gt;[[Dionysius Thrax]]. τέχνη γραμματική (Art of Grammar), [http://www.hs-augsburg.de/~harsch/graeca/Chronologia/S_ante02/DionysiosThrax/dio_tech.html#06 ς´ περὶ στοιχείου (6. On the Sound)]&lt;/ref&gt;}} He divides them into two subcategories: ''hēmíphōna'', semivowels (&quot;half-pronounced&quot;),&lt;ref&gt;{{LSJ|h(mi/fwnos|ἡμίφωνος|shortref}}&lt;/ref&gt; which correspond to [[continuant]]s, not [[semivowel]]s,{{efn|Dionysius Thrax:
:{{lang|grc|τούτων ἡμίφωνα μέν ἐστιν ὀκτώ· ζ ξ ψ λ μ ν ρ σ. ἡμίφωνα δὲ λέγεται, ὅτι παρ᾽ ὅσον ἧττον τῶν φωνηέντων εὔφωνα καθέστηκεν ἔν τε τοῖς μυγμοῖς καὶ σιγμοῖς.}}
:Of these, eight are semivowels [half-pronounced]: z, x, ps, l, m, n, r, s. They are called semivowels, because, though a little weaker than the vowels, they are still harmonious [well-sounding] in their moaning and hissing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thrax&quot;/&gt;}} and ''áphōna'', mute or silent consonants (&quot;unvoiced&quot;),&lt;ref&gt;{{LSJ|a)/fwnos|ἄφωνος|shortref}}&lt;/ref&gt; which correspond to [[stop consonant|stop]]s, not [[voicelessness|voiceless]] consonants.{{efn|Dionysius Thrax:
:{{lang|grc|ἄφωνα δέ ἐστιν ἐννέα· β γ δ κ π τ θ φ χ. ἄφωνα δὲ λέγεται, ὅτι μᾶλλον τῶν ἄλλων ἐστὶν κακόφωνα, ὥσπερ ἄφωνον λέγομεν τὸν τραγωιδὸν τὸν κακόφωνον.}}
:Nine are silent [unpronounced]: b, g, d, k, p, t, th, ph, ch. They are called silent, because, more than the others, they are discordant [ill-sounding], just as we call the ill-sounding tragedy &quot;silent&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thrax&quot;/&gt;}}

This description does not apply to some [[Natural language|human languages]], such as the [[Salishan languages]], in which stops sometimes occur without vowels (see [[Nuxálk language|Nuxálk]]), and the modern conception of consonant does not require co-occurrence with vowels.

==Letters==
The word '''consonant''' is also used to refer to a [[Letter (alphabet)|letter]] of an [[alphabet]] that denotes a consonant sound. The 21 consonant letters in the English alphabet are [[B]], [[C]], [[D]], [[F]], [[G]], [[H]], [[J]], [[K]], [[L]], [[M]], [[N]], [[P]], [[Q]], [[R]], [[S]], [[T]], [[V]], [[X]], [[Z]], and usually [[W]] and [[Y]]. The letter Y stands for the consonant {{IPA|/j/}} in ''yoke'', the vowel {{IPA|/ɪ/}} in ''myth'', the vowel {{IPA|/i/}} in ''funny'', and the diphthong {{IPA|/aɪ/}} in ''my''. W always represents a consonant except in combination with a vowel letter, as in ''growth'', ''raw'', and ''how'', and in a few [[loanword]]s from [[Welsh language|Welsh]], like ''crwth'' or ''cwm''.

In some other languages, such as Finnish, ''y'' only represents a vowel sound.

==Consonants versus vowels==
Consonants and vowels correspond to distinct parts of a [[syllable]]: The most sonorous part of the syllable (that is, the part that's easiest to sing), called the ''syllabic peak'' or ''[[syllable nucleus|nucleus]],'' is typically a vowel, while the less sonorous margins (called the ''[[syllable onset|onset]]'' and ''[[syllable coda|coda]]'') are typically consonants. Such syllables may be abbreviated CV, V, and CVC, where C stands for consonant and V stands for vowel. This can be argued to be the only pattern found in most of the world's languages, and perhaps the primary pattern in all of them. However, the distinction between consonant and vowel is not always clear cut: there are syllabic consonants and non-syllabic vowels in many of the world's languages.

One blurry area is in segments variously called ''[[semivowel]]s'', ''semiconsonants'', or ''glides''. On one side, there are vowel-like segments that are not in themselves syllabic, but form [[diphthong]]s as part of the syllable nucleus, as the ''i'' in English ''boil'' {{IPA|[ˈbɔɪ̯l]}}. On the other, there are [[approximant]]s that behave like consonants in forming onsets, but are articulated very much like vowels, as the ''y'' in English ''yes'' {{IPA|[ˈjɛs]}}. Some phonologists model these as both being the underlying vowel {{IPA|/i/}}, so that the English word ''bit'' would [[phoneme|phonemically]] be {{IPA|/bit/}}, ''beet'' would be {{IPA|/bii̯t/}}, and ''yield'' would be phonemically {{IPA|/i̯ii̯ld/}}. Likewise, ''foot'' would be {{IPA|/fut/}}, ''food'' would be {{IPA|/fuu̯d/}}, ''wood'' would be {{IPA|/u̯ud/}}, and ''wooed'' would be {{IPA|/u̯uu̯d/}}. However, there is a (perhaps allophonic) difference in articulation between these segments, with the {{IPA|[j]}} in {{IPA|[ˈjɛs]}} ''yes'' and {{IPA|[ˈjiʲld]}} ''yield'' and the {{IPA|[w]}} of {{IPA|[ˈwuʷd]}} ''wooed'' having more constriction and a more definite place of articulation than the {{IPA|[ɪ]}} in {{IPA|[ˈbɔɪ̯l]}} ''boil'' or {{IPA|[ˈbɪt]}} ''bit'' or the {{IPA|[ʊ]}} of {{IPA|[ˈfʊt]}} ''foot''.

The other problematic area is that of syllabic consonants, segments articulated as consonants but occupying the nucleus of a syllable. This may be the case for words such as ''church'' in [[rhotic and non-rhotic accents|rhotic]] dialects of English, although phoneticians differ in whether they consider this to be a syllabic consonant, {{IPA|/ˈtʃɹ̩tʃ/}}, or a rhotic vowel, {{IPA|/ˈtʃɝtʃ/}}: Some distinguish an approximant {{IPA|/ɹ/}} that corresponds to a vowel {{IPA|/ɝ/}}, for ''rural'' as {{IPA|/ˈɹɝl/}} or {{IPA|[ˈɹʷɝːl̩]}}; others see these as a single phoneme, {{IPA|/ˈɹɹ̩l/}}.

Other languages use fricative and often trilled segments as syllabic nuclei, as in [[Czech language|Czech]] and several languages in [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]], and [[China]], including [[Mandarin Chinese]]. In Mandarin, they are historically allophones of {{IPA|/i/}}, and spelled that way in [[Pinyin]]. Ladefoged and Maddieson&lt;ref name=SOWL&gt;{{SOWL}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{page missing|date=August 2018}} call these &quot;fricative vowels&quot; and say that &quot;they can usually be thought of as syllabic fricatives that are allophones of vowels&quot;. That is, phonetically they are consonants, but phonemically they behave as vowels.

Many [[Slavic languages]] allow the trill {{IPA|[r̩]}} and the lateral {{IPA|[l̩]}} as syllabic nuclei (see [[Words without vowels]]). In languages like [[Nuxálk language|Nuxalk]], it is difficult to know what the nucleus of a syllable is, or if all syllables even have nuclei. If the concept of 'syllable' applies in Nuxalk, there are syllabic consonants in words like {{IPA|/sx̩s/}} ({{IPA|/s̩xs̩/}}?) 'seal fat'. [[Miyako language|Miyako]] in Japan is similar, with {{IPA|/f̩ks̩/}} 'to build' and {{IPA|/ps̩ks̩/}} 'to pull'.

==Features==
{{Unreferenced section|date = August 2013}}{{Manner of articulation}}
Each spoken consonant can be distinguished by several phonetic ''[[Distinctive feature|features]]'':
* The [[manner of articulation]] is how air escapes from the vocal tract when the consonant or [[approximant]] (vowel-like) sound is made. Manners include stops, fricatives, and nasals.
* The [[place of articulation]] is where in the vocal tract the obstruction of the consonant occurs, and which speech organs are involved. Places include [[bilabial consonant|bilabial]] (both lips), [[alveolar consonant|alveolar]] (tongue against the gum ridge), and [[velar consonant|velar]] (tongue against soft palate). In addition, there may be a simultaneous narrowing at another place of articulation, such as [[Palatalization (phonetics)|palatalisation]] or [[pharyngealisation]]. Consonants with two simultaneous places of articulation are said to be [[Co-articulated consonant| coarticulated]].
* The [[phonation]] of a consonant is how the [[vocal cords]] vibrate during the articulation. When the vocal cords vibrate fully, the consonant is called [[voiced]]; when they do not vibrate at all, it is [[voiceless]].
* The [[voice onset time]] (VOT) indicates the timing of the phonation. [[Aspiration (phonetics)|Aspiration]] is a feature of VOT. 
* The [[airstream mechanism]] is how the air moving through the vocal tract is powered. Most languages have exclusively [[pulmonic egressive]] consonants, which use the lungs and diaphragm, but [[ejective]]s, [[click consonant|click]]s, and [[implosive]]s use different mechanisms. 
* The [[gemination|length]] is how long the obstruction of a consonant lasts. This feature is borderline distinctive in English, as in &quot;wholly&quot; {{IPA|[hoʊlli]}} vs. &quot;holy&quot; {{IPA|[hoʊli]}}, but cases are limited to morpheme boundaries. Unrelated roots are differentiated in various languages such as Italian, Japanese, and Finnish, with two length levels, &quot;single&quot; and &quot;[[geminate]]&quot;. [[Estonian language|Estonian]] and some [[Sami languages]] have three phonemic lengths: short, geminate, and long geminate, although the distinction between the geminate and overlong geminate includes suprasegmental features.
* The articulatory force is how much muscular energy is involved. This has been proposed many times, but no distinction relying exclusively on force has ever been demonstrated.

All English consonants can be classified by a combination of these features, such as &quot;voiceless alveolar stop&quot; {{IPA|[t]}}. In this case, the airstream mechanism is omitted.

Some pairs of consonants like ''p::b'', ''t::d'' are sometimes called [[fortis and lenis]], but this is a [[phonology|phonological]] rather than phonetic distinction.

Consonants are scheduled by their features in a number of IPA charts:
{{IPA pulmonic consonants}}
{{IPA non-pulmonic consonants|notes=no}}
{{IPA co-articulated consonants}}

==Examples==
The recently extinct [[Ubykh language]] had only 2 or 3 vowels but 84 consonants;&lt;ref&gt;Georges Dumézil and Tevfik Esenç, 1975, ''Le verbe oubykh: études descriptives et comparatives''. Adrien Maisonneuve: Paris.&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Taa language]] has 87 consonants under [[consonant cluster|one analysis]], 164 under [[linguo-pulmonic|another]], plus some 30 vowels and tone.&lt;ref&gt;Naumann, Christfied (2008). &quot;The Consonantal System of West !Xoon&quot;. ''3rd International Symposium on Khoisan Languages and Linguistics''. Riezlern.&lt;/ref&gt; The types of consonants used in various languages are by no means universal. For instance, nearly all [[Australian languages]] lack fricatives; a large percentage of the world's languages lack voiced stops as phonemes, such as {{IPA|[b]}}, {{IPA|[d]}}, and {{IPA|[ɡ]}}. Most languages, however, do include one or more fricatives, with {{IPA|[s]}} being the most common, and a [[liquid consonant]] or two, with {{IPA|[l]}} the most common. The approximant {{IPA|[w]}} is also widespread, and virtually all languages have one or more [[nasal consonant|nasals]], though a very few, such as the Central dialect of [[Rotokas language|Rotokas]], lack even these. This last language has the smallest number of consonants in the world, with just six.

===Most common===
The most common consonants around the world are the three voiceless stops {{IPA|[p]}}, {{IPA|[t]}}, {{IPA|[k]}}, and the two nasals {{IPA|[m]}}, {{IPA|[n]}}. However, even these common five are not universal. Several languages in the vicinity of the [[Sahara Desert]], including [[Arabic language|Arabic]], lack {{IPA|[p]}}. Several languages of North America, such as [[Mohawk language|Mohawk]], lack both of the labials {{IPA|[p]}} and {{IPA|[m]}}. The [[Wichita language]] of [[Oklahoma]] and some West African languages, such as [[Ijo languages|Ijo]], lack the consonant {{IPA|/n/}} on a phonemic level, but do use it as an [[allophone]] of another consonant (of {{IPA|/l/}} in the case of Ijo, and of {{IPA|/ɾ/}} in Wichita). A few languages on [[Bougainville Island]] and around [[Puget Sound]], such as [[Makah language|Makah]], lack both of the nasals {{IPA|[m]}} and {{IPA|[n]}}. The 'click language' [[Nǁng language|Nǁng]] lacks {{IPA|[t]}},{{efn|Nǀu has a {{IPA|[ts]}} instead. [[Hawaiian language|Hawaiian]] is often said to lack a {{IPA|[t]}}, but it actually has a consonant that varies between {{IPA|[t]}} and {{IPA|[k]}}.}} and colloquial [[Samoan language|Samoan]] lacks both alveolars, {{IPA|[t]}} and {{IPA|[n]}}.{{efn|Samoan words written with the letters ''t'' and ''n'' are pronounced with {{IPA|[k]}} and {{IPA|[ŋ]}} except in formal speech. However, Samoan does have an alveolar consonant, {{IPA|[l]}}.}} Despite the 80-odd consonants of [[Ubykh language|Ubykh]], it lacks the plain velar {{IPA|/k/}} in native words, as do the related [[Adyghe language|Adyghe]] and [[Kabardian language|Kabardian]] languages. But with a few striking exceptions, such as [[Xavante language|Xavante]] and [[Tahitian language|Tahitian]]—which have no dorsal consonants whatsoever—nearly all other languages have at least one velar consonant: the few languages that do not have a simple {{IPA|[k]}} usually have a consonant that is very similar.{{efn|The Niʻihau–Kauaʻi dialect of [[Hawaiian language|Hawaiian]] is often said to have no {{IPA|[k]}}, but as in other dialects of Hawaiian it has a consonant that varies between {{IPA|[t]}} and {{IPA|[k]}}, with {{IPA|[t]}} before {{IPA|[i]}} but {{IPA|[k]}} at the beginnings of words, though they are often in [[free variation]].}} For instance, an areal feature of the [[Pacific Northwest]] coast is that historical *{{IPA|[k]}} has become palatalized in many languages, so that [[Saanich language|Saanich]] for example has {{IPA|[tʃ]}} and {{IPA|[kʷ]}} but no plain {{IPA|[k]}};&lt;ref&gt;Ian Maddieson and Sandra Ferrari Disner, 1984, ''Patterns of Sounds.'' Cambridge University Press&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://wals.info/feature/18 The World Atlas of Language Structures Online: Absence of Common Consonants]&lt;/ref&gt; similarly, historical *{{IPA|[k]}} in the [[Northwest Caucasian languages]] became palatalized to {{IPA|/kʲ/}} in [[Ubykh language|Ubykh]] and {{IPA|/tʃ/}} in most [[Circassian languages|Circassian]] dialects.&lt;ref&gt;Viacheslav A. Chirikba, 1996, ''Common West Caucasian: the reconstruction of its phonological system and parts of its lexicon and morphology'', p. 192. Research School CNWS: Leiden.&lt;/ref&gt;

The most ''frequent'' consonant (that is, the one appearing most often in speech) in many languages is {{IPA|[p]}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.vistawide.com/languages/language_statistics.htm|title=World Language Statistics and Facts|website=www.vistawide.com|access-date=2019-01-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Audio samples==
The following pages include consonant charts with links to audio samples.

* [[IPA pulmonic consonant chart with audio]]
* [[Ejective consonant]]
* [[Click consonant]]
* [[Implosive consonant]]

==See also==
*[[Articulatory phonetics]]
*[[List of consonants]]
*[[List of phonetics topics]]
*[[Words without vowels]]

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

;Sources
*Ian Maddieson, ''Patterns of Sounds'', Cambridge University Press, 1984. {{ISBN|0-521-26536-3}}

==External links==
{{Spoken Wikipedia|Consonant.ogg|2005-07-20}}
*{{Commonscatinline|Consonants}}
*[http://www.chass.utoronto.ca/~danhall/phonetics/sammy.html Interactive manner and place of articulation]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20130513063441/http://www.journalofwestafricanlanguages.org/Consonants.aspx Consonants (Journal of West African Languages)]

{{IPA navigation}}

[[Category:Consonants| ]]</text>
      <sha1>87gfpt4y2tqx1718y8gmexh8cjrhoi1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
