  <page>
    <title>Chemical element</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5659</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939242480</id>
      <parentid>939226127</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-05T06:36:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dagænishklaʊd</username>
        <id>15777827</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Description */&quot;With From&quot; is grammatically incorrect, as explained in the 1st solution presented here:
https://ell.stackexchange.com/questions/95981/adjective-with-from-to

Two prepositions may not be used in consequence. &quot;With from&quot; is incorrect syntax, and while the single preposition &quot;with&quot; is better suited here than &quot;from&quot;, there are descriptive words such as &quot;comprising&quot;, &quot;containing&quot;, &quot;composed of&quot;.. anothed elaborate way to say it with correct syntax would be &quot;elements with a proton...</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|A species of atoms having the same number of protons in the atomic nucleus}}
{{pp|small=yes}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}

[[Image:Simple Periodic Table Chart-en.svg|right|400px|thumb|[[Periodic table|The periodic table of the chemical elements]]]]

A '''chemical element''' is a [[chemical species|species]] of [[atom]] having the same number of [[proton]]s in their [[Atomic nucleus|atomic nuclei]] (that is, the same [[atomic number]], or ''Z'').&lt;ref name=goldbookElement&gt;{{GoldBookRef |title=chemical element |file=C01022}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, the atomic number of [[oxygen]] is 8, so the element oxygen describes all atoms which have 8 protons.

In total, 118 elements have been identified. The first 94 occur naturally on [[Earth]], and the remaining 24 are [[synthetic element]]s. There are 80 elements that have at least one stable [[isotope]] and 38 that have exclusively [[radionuclide]]s, which [[Radioactive decay|decay]] over time into other elements. [[Iron]] is the [[abundances of the elements (data page)|most abundant element]] (by [[mass]]) making up Earth, while [[oxygen]] is the [[Abundance of elements in Earth's crust|most common element in the Earth's crust]].&lt;ref name=LosAlamos&gt;{{cite web|title=Periodic Table of Elements: Oxygen|author=Los Alamos National Laboratory|authorlink=Los Alamos National Laboratory|publisher=Los Alamos National Security, LLC|location=Los Alamos, New Mexico|year=2011|url=http://periodic.lanl.gov/8.shtml|accessdate=7 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Chemical elements constitute all of the [[Baryon#Baryonic matter|ordinary]] [[matter]] of the universe. However [[Observational astronomy|astronomical observations]] suggest that ordinary observable matter makes up only about 15% of the matter in the universe. The remainder is [[dark matter]]; the composition of this is unknown, but it is not composed of chemical elements.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Theory of Almost Everything: The Standard Model, the Unsung Triumph of Modern Physics |url=https://archive.org/details/theoryofalmostev0000oert |url-access=registration |last=Oerter |first=Robert |year=2006 |publisher=Penguin |location= |isbn=978-0-452-28786-0 |page=[https://archive.org/details/theoryofalmostev0000oert/page/223 223] }}&lt;/ref&gt;
The two lightest elements, [[hydrogen]] and [[helium]], were mostly formed in the [[Big Bang]] and are the most common elements in the universe. The next three elements ([[lithium]], [[beryllium]] and [[boron]]) were formed mostly by [[cosmic ray spallation]], and are thus rarer than heavier elements. Formation of elements with 6 to 26 protons occurs in [[main sequence]] stars via [[stellar nucleosynthesis]]. The high abundance of oxygen, [[silicon]], and iron on Earth reflects their common production in such stars. Elements with greater than 26 protons are formed by [[supernova nucleosynthesis|nucleosynthesis in supernovae]], which, when they explode, blast these elements as [[supernova remnant]]s far into space, where they may become incorporated into [[planet]]s when they are formed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Synthesis of the Elements in Stars|author1=E.M. Burbidge |author2=G.R. Burbidge |author3=W.A. Fowler |author4=F. Hoyle |journal=Reviews of Modern Physics|volume=29|issue=4|pages=547–650|year=1957|doi=10.1103/RevModPhys.29.547|bibcode=1957RvMP...29..547B}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term &quot;element&quot; is used for atoms with a given number of protons (regardless of whether or not they are [[Ionization|ionized]] or chemically bonded, e.g. hydrogen in [[water]]) as well as for a pure [[chemical substance]] consisting of a single element (e.g. hydrogen gas).{{r|goldbookElement}} For the second meaning, the terms &quot;elementary substance&quot; and &quot;simple substance&quot; have been suggested, but they have not gained much acceptance in [[English language|English]] chemical literature, whereas in some other languages their equivalent is widely used (e.g. [[French language|French]] {{lang|fr|corps simple}}, [[Russian language|Russian]] {{lang|ru|простое вещество}}). A single element can form multiple substances differing in their structure; they are called [[Allotropy|allotropes]] of the element.

When different elements are chemically combined, with the atoms held together by [[chemical bond]]s, they form [[chemical compound]]s. Only a minority of elements are found uncombined as relatively pure [[mineral]]s. Among the more common of such [[native element minerals|native elements]] are [[copper]], [[silver]], [[gold]], [[carbon]] (as [[coal]], [[graphite]], or [[diamond]]s), and [[sulfur]]. All but a few of the most inert elements, such as [[noble gas]]es and [[noble metal]]s, are usually found on Earth in chemically combined form, as chemical compounds. While about 32 of the chemical elements occur on Earth in native uncombined forms, most of these occur as mixtures. For example, atmospheric [[Atmosphere of Earth|air]] is primarily a mixture of [[nitrogen]], oxygen, and [[argon]], and native solid elements occur in [[alloy]]s, such as that of iron and nickel.

The history of the discovery and use of the elements began with [[Primitive (phylogenetics)|primitive]] [[society|human societies]] that found native elements like carbon, sulfur, copper and gold (though the status of these materials as elements was not known at the time). Later civilizations extracted elemental copper, tin, lead and iron from their [[ore]]s by [[smelting]], using [[charcoal]]. [[List of alchemists|Alchemists]] and [[chemist]]s subsequently identified many more; all of the naturally occurring elements were known by 1950.

The properties of the chemical elements are summarized in the [[periodic table]], which organizes the elements by increasing atomic number into rows (&quot;[[period (periodic table)|periods]]&quot;) in which the columns (&quot;[[group (periodic table)|groups]]&quot;) share recurring (&quot;periodic&quot;) [[physical property|physical]] and [[chemical property|chemical properties]]. Save for unstable radioactive elements with short [[half-life|half-lives]], all of the elements are available [[industry|industrially]], most of them in low degrees of [[impurity|impurities]].

==Description==
The lightest chemical elements are hydrogen and [[helium]], both created by [[Big Bang nucleosynthesis]] during the [[Chronology of the universe|first 20 minutes of the universe]]&lt;ref&gt;See the timeline on p.10 in {{cite journal|year=2006|title=Evidence for Dark Matter|url=http://gaitskell.brown.edu/physics/talks/0408_SLAC_SummerSchool/Gaitskell_DMEvidence_v16.pdf|journal=[[Physical Review C]]|volume=74|issue=4|pages=044602|doi=10.1103/PhysRevC.74.044602|bibcode=2006PhRvC..74d4602O|last1=Oganessian|first1=Yu. Ts. |last2=Utyonkov |first2=V.|last3=Lobanov|first3=Yu.|last4=Abdullin|first4=F.|last5=Polyakov|first5=A.|last6=Sagaidak|first6=R.|last7=Shirokovsky|first7=I.|last8=Tsyganov|first8=Yu.|last9=Voinov|first9=A.|display-authors=8}}&lt;/ref&gt; in a [[ratio]] of around 3:1 by mass (or 12:1 by number of atoms),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url =http://pdgusers.lbl.gov/~pslii/uabackup/big_bang/elementabundancies/2300400.html | title =The Universe Adventure Hydrogen and Helium | author =lbl.gov | publisher =[[Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory]] [[United States Department of Energy|U.S. Department of Energy]] | year =2005 | url-status =dead | archiveurl =https://web.archive.org/web/20130921054844/http://pdgusers.lbl.gov/~pslii/uabackup/big_bang/elementabundancies/2300400.html | archivedate =21 September 2013 | df =dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url =http://www.astro.soton.ac.uk/~pac/PH112/notes/notes/node181.html | title =Formation of the light elements | author =astro.soton.ac.uk | publisher =[[University of Southampton]] | date =3 January 2001 | url-status =dead | archiveurl =https://web.archive.org/web/20130921054428/http://www.astro.soton.ac.uk/~pac/PH112/notes/notes/node181.html | archivedate =21 September 2013 | df =dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; along with tiny traces of the next two elements, [[lithium]] and [[beryllium]]. Almost all other elements found in nature were made by various natural methods of [[nucleosynthesis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.foothill.edu/attach/938/Nucleosynthesis.pdf | title =How Stars Make Energy and New Elements | author =foothill.edu | publisher =[[Foothill College]] | date =18 October 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; On Earth, small amounts of new atoms are naturally produced in [[nucleogenic]] reactions, or in [[Environmental radioactivity#Natural|cosmogenic]] processes, such as [[cosmic ray spallation]]. New atoms are also naturally produced on Earth as [[Radiogenic nuclide|radiogenic]] [[Decay product|daughter isotopes]] of ongoing [[radioactive decay]] processes such as [[alpha decay]], [[beta decay]], [[spontaneous fission]], [[cluster decay]], and other rarer modes of decay.

Of the 94 naturally occurring elements, those with atomic numbers 1 through 82 each have at least one [[stable nuclide|stable isotope]] (except for [[technetium]], element 43 and [[promethium]], element 61, which have no stable isotopes). Isotopes considered stable are those for which no radioactive decay has yet been observed. Elements with atomic numbers 83 through 94 are [[Radionuclide|unstable]] to the point that radioactive decay of all isotopes can be detected. Some of these elements, notably [[bismuth]] (atomic number 83), [[thorium]] (atomic number 90), and [[uranium]] (atomic number 92), have one or more isotopes with half-lives long enough to survive as remnants of the explosive [[stellar nucleosynthesis]] that produced the [[heavy metals]] before the formation of our [[Solar System]]. At over 1.9{{e|19}} years, over a billion times longer than the current estimated age of the universe, [[bismuth-209]] (atomic number 83) has the longest known alpha decay half-life of any naturally occurring element, and is almost always considered on par with the 80 stable elements.&lt;ref name=Dume2003&gt;{{cite news|title=Bismuth breaks half-life record for alpha decay|last=Dumé|first=B.|date=23 April 2003|work=Physicsworld.com|publisher=Institute of Physics|location=Bristol, England|url=http://physicsworld.com/cws/article/news/2003/apr/23/bismuth-breaks-half-life-record-for-alpha-decay|accessdate=14 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Marcillac2003&gt;{{cite journal|last=de Marcillac|first=P.|last2=Coron|first2=N.|last3=Dambier |first3=G.|last4=Leblanc|first4=J.|last5=Moalic|first5=J-P|year=2003|title=Experimental detection of alpha-particles from the radioactive decay of natural bismuth|journal=Nature|volume=422|pages=876–8|doi=10.1038/nature01541|pmid=12712201|issue=6934|bibcode=2003Natur.422..876D}}&lt;/ref&gt; The very heaviest elements (those beyond plutonium, element 94) undergo radioactive decay with [[half-life|half-lives]] so short that they are not found in nature and must be [[synthetic element|synthesized]].

As of 2010, there are 118 known elements (in this context, &quot;known&quot; means observed well enough, even from just a few decay products, to have been differentiated from other elements).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Sanderson|first=K.|date=17 October 2006|title=Heaviest element made – again|journal=News@nature|url=http://www.nature.com/news/2006/061016/full/061016-4.html|doi=10.1038/news061016-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Schewe&gt;{{cite web|last=Schewe |first=P. |last2=Stein |first2=B. |date=17 October 2000 |title=Elements 116 and 118 Are Discovered |url=http://www.aip.org/pnu/2006/797.html |work=Physics News Update |publisher=[[American Institute of Physics]] |accessdate=19 October 2006 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120101144201/http://www.aip.org/pnu/2006/797.html |archivedate=1 January 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Of these 118 elements, 94 occur naturally on Earth. Six of these occur in extreme trace quantities: [[technetium]], atomic number 43; [[promethium]], number 61; [[astatine]], number 85; [[francium]], number 87; [[neptunium]], number 93; and [[plutonium]], number 94. These 94 elements have been detected in the universe at large, in the spectra of stars and also supernovae, where short-lived radioactive elements are newly being made. The first 94 elements have been detected directly on Earth as [[primordial nuclide]]s present from the formation of the solar system, or as naturally occurring fission or transmutation products of uranium and thorium.

The remaining 24 heavier elements, not found today either on Earth or in astronomical spectra, have been produced artificially: these are all radioactive, with very short half-lives; if any atoms of these elements were present at the formation of Earth, they are extremely likely, to the point of certainty, to have already decayed, and if present in novae have been in quantities too small to have been noted. Technetium was the first purportedly non-naturally occurring element synthesized, in 1937, although trace amounts of technetium have since been found in nature (and also the element may have been discovered naturally in 1925).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.epa.gov/radiation/radionuclides/technetium.html | title =Technetium-99 | publisher =epa.gov | author =United States Environmental Protection Agency | accessdate =26 February 2013| author-link =United States Environmental Protection Agency }}&lt;/ref&gt; This pattern of artificial production and later natural discovery has been repeated with several other radioactive naturally occurring rare elements.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.cfa.harvard.edu/~ejchaisson/cosmic_evolution/docs/text/text_stel_6.html | title =Origins of Heavy Elements| publisher =cfa.harvard.edu | author =Harvard–Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics | accessdate =26 February 2013| author-link =Harvard–Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[List of chemical elements|List of the elements are available by name, atomic number, density, melting point, boiling point]] and [[Symbol (chemical element)|by symbol]], as well as [[Molar ionization energies of the elements|ionization energies of the elements]]. The nuclides of stable and radioactive elements are also available as a [[list of nuclides]], sorted by length of half-life for those that are unstable. One of the most convenient, and certainly the most traditional presentation of the elements, is in the form of the [[periodic table]], which groups together elements with similar chemical properties (and usually also similar electronic structures).

===Atomic number===
{{main|atomic number}}
The [[atomic number]] of an element is equal to the number of protons in each atom, and defines the element.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.ndt-ed.org/EducationResources/HighSchool/Radiography/atomicmassnumber.htm | title =Atomic Number and Mass Numbers | publisher =ndt-ed.org |accessdate =17 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, all carbon atoms contain 6 protons in their [[atomic nucleus]]; so the atomic number of carbon is 6.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://periodic.lanl.gov/6.shtml | title =Periodic Table of Elements: LANL Carbon | author =periodic.lanl.gov | publisher =[[Los Alamos National Laboratory]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Carbon atoms may have different numbers of neutrons; atoms of the same element having different numbers of neutrons are known as [[isotope]]s of the element.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url =http://faculty.piercecollege.edu/yamadak/classes/Atomic%20mass.pdf | title =Atomic mass, isotopes, and mass number. | author =Katsuya Yamada | publisher =[[Los Angeles Pierce College]] | url-status =dead | archiveurl =https://web.archive.org/web/20140111131537/http://faculty.piercecollege.edu/yamadak/classes/Atomic%20mass.pdf | archivedate =11 January 2014 | df =dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The number of protons in the atomic nucleus also determines its [[electric charge]], which in turn determines the number of [[electron]]s of the atom in its [[ionization|non-ionized]] state. The electrons are placed into [[atomic orbital]]s that determine the atom's various [[chemical property|chemical properties]]. The number of neutrons in a nucleus usually has very little effect on an element's chemical properties (except in the case of [[hydrogen]] and [[deuterium]]). Thus, all carbon isotopes have nearly identical chemical properties because they all have six protons and six electrons, even though carbon atoms may, for example, have 6 or 8 neutrons. That is why the atomic number, rather than [[mass number]] or [[atomic weight]], is considered the identifying characteristic of a chemical element.

The symbol for atomic number is ''Z''.

===Isotopes===
{{Main|Isotope|Stable isotope ratio|List of nuclides}}
[[Isotope]]s are atoms of the same element (that is, with the same number of [[proton]]s in their [[atomic nucleus]]), but having ''different'' numbers of [[neutron]]s. Thus, for example, there are three main isotopes of carbon. All carbon atoms have 6 protons in the nucleus, but they can have either 6, 7, or 8 neutrons. Since the mass numbers of these are 12, 13 and 14 respectively, the three isotopes of carbon are known as [[carbon-12]], [[carbon-13]], and [[carbon-14]], often abbreviated to &lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;C, &lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C, and &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;C. [[Carbon]] in everyday life and in chemistry is a [[mixture]] of &lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;C (about 98.9%), &lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;C (about 1.1%) and about 1 atom per trillion of &lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;C.

Most (66 of 94) naturally occurring elements have more than one stable isotope. Except for the isotopes of hydrogen (which differ greatly from each other in relative mass—enough to cause chemical effects), the isotopes of a given element are chemically nearly indistinguishable.

All of the elements have some isotopes that are radioactive ([[Radionuclide|radioisotopes]]), although not all of these radioisotopes occur naturally. The radioisotopes typically decay into other elements upon radiating an [[Alpha particle|alpha]] or [[beta particle]]. If an element has isotopes that are not radioactive, these are termed &quot;stable&quot; isotopes. All of the known stable isotopes occur naturally (see [[primordial nuclide|primordial isotope]]). The many radioisotopes that are not found in nature have been characterized after being artificially made. Certain elements have no stable isotopes and are composed ''only'' of radioactive isotopes: specifically the elements without any stable isotopes are technetium (atomic number 43), promethium (atomic number 61), and all observed elements with atomic numbers greater than 82.

Of the 80 elements with at least one stable isotope, 26 have only one single stable isotope. The mean number of stable isotopes for the 80 stable elements is 3.1 stable isotopes per element. The largest number of stable isotopes that occur for a single element is 10 (for tin, element 50).

===Isotopic mass and atomic mass===
{{main|atomic mass|relative atomic mass}}

The [[mass number]] of an element, ''A'', is the number of [[nucleon]]s (protons and neutrons) in the atomic nucleus. Different isotopes of a given element are distinguished by their mass numbers, which are conventionally written as a superscript on the left hand side of the atomic symbol (e.g. &lt;sup&gt;238&lt;/sup&gt;U). The mass number is always a whole number and has units of &quot;nucleons&quot;. For example, [[Isotopes of magnesium|magnesium-24]] (24 is the mass number) is an atom with 24 nucleons (12 protons and 12 neutrons).

Whereas the mass number simply counts the total number of neutrons and protons and is thus a natural (or whole) number, the [[atomic mass]] of a single atom is a [[real number]] giving the mass of a particular isotope (or &quot;nuclide&quot;) of the element, expressed in [[atomic mass unit]]s (symbol: u). In general, the mass number of a given nuclide differs in value slightly from its atomic mass, since the mass of each proton and neutron is not exactly 1&amp;nbsp;u; since the electrons contribute a lesser share to the atomic mass as neutron number exceeds proton number; and (finally) because of the [[nuclear binding energy]]. For example, the atomic mass of chlorine-35 to five significant digits is 34.969&amp;nbsp;u and that of chlorine-37 is 36.966&amp;nbsp;u. However, the atomic mass in u of each isotope is quite close to its simple mass number (always within 1%). The only isotope whose atomic mass is exactly a [[natural number]] is &lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;C, which by definition has a mass of exactly 12 because u is defined as 1/12 of the mass of a free neutral carbon-12 atom in the ground state.

The [[standard atomic weight]] (commonly called &quot;atomic weight&quot;) of an element is the ''average'' of the atomic masses of all the chemical element's isotopes as found in a particular environment, weighted by isotopic abundance, relative to the atomic mass unit. This number may be a fraction that is ''not'' close to a whole number. For example, the relative atomic mass of chlorine is 35.453&amp;nbsp;u, which differs greatly from a whole number as it is an average of about 76% chlorine-35 and 24% chlorine-37. Whenever a relative atomic mass value differs by more than 1% from a whole number, it is due to this averaging effect, as significant amounts of more than one isotope are naturally present in a sample of that element.

===Chemically pure and isotopically pure===
Chemists and nuclear scientists have different definitions of a ''pure element''. In chemistry, a pure element means a substance whose atoms all (or in practice almost all) have the same [[atomic number]], or number of [[proton]]s. Nuclear scientists, however, define a pure element as one that consists of only one stable [[isotope]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.euronuclear.org/info/encyclopedia/p/pure-element.htm |title=Pure element |publisher=[[European Nuclear Society]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For example, a copper wire is 99.99% chemically pure if 99.99% of its atoms are copper, with 29 protons each. However it is not isotopically pure since ordinary copper consists of two stable isotopes, 69% &lt;sup&gt;63&lt;/sup&gt;Cu and 31% &lt;sup&gt;65&lt;/sup&gt;Cu, with different numbers of neutrons. However, a pure gold ingot would be both chemically and isotopically pure, since ordinary gold consists only of one isotope, &lt;sup&gt;197&lt;/sup&gt;Au.

===Allotropes===
{{Main|Allotropy}}
Atoms of chemically pure elements may bond to each other chemically in more than one way, allowing the pure element to exist in multiple [[chemical structure]]s ([[Molecular geometry|spatial arrangements of atoms]]), known as [[Allotropy|allotropes]], which differ in their properties. For example, carbon can be found as [[diamond]], which has a tetrahedral structure around each carbon atom; [[graphite]], which has layers of carbon atoms with a hexagonal structure stacked on top of each other; [[graphene]], which is a single layer of graphite that is very strong; [[fullerene]]s, which have nearly spherical shapes; and [[carbon nanotube]]s, which are tubes with a hexagonal structure (even these may differ from each other in electrical properties). The ability of an element to exist in one of many structural forms is known as 'allotropy'.

The [[standard state]], also known as the reference state, of an element is defined as its thermodynamically most stable state at a pressure of 1 [[bar (unit)|bar]] and a given temperature (typically at 298.15&amp;nbsp;K). In [[thermochemistry]], an element is defined to have an [[Standard enthalpy of formation|enthalpy of formation]] of zero in its standard state. For example, the reference state for carbon is graphite, because the structure of graphite is more stable than that of the other allotropes.

===Properties===
Several kinds of descriptive categorizations can be applied broadly to the elements, including consideration of their general physical and chemical properties, their states of matter under familiar conditions, their melting and boiling points, their densities, their crystal structures as solids, and their origins.

====General properties====
Several terms are commonly used to characterize the general physical and chemical properties of the chemical elements. A first distinction is between [[metal]]s, which readily conduct [[electricity]], [[nonmetal]]s, which do not, and a small group, (the ''[[metalloid]]s''), having intermediate properties and often behaving as [[semiconductor]]s.

A more refined classification is often shown in colored presentations of the periodic table. This system restricts the terms &quot;metal&quot; and &quot;nonmetal&quot; to only certain of the more broadly defined metals and nonmetals, adding additional terms for certain sets of the more broadly viewed metals and nonmetals. The version of this classification used in the periodic tables presented here includes: [[actinide]]s, [[alkali metal]]s, [[alkaline earth metal]]s, [[halogen]]s, [[lanthanide]]s, [[transition metal]]s, [[post-transition metal]]s, [[metalloid]]s, [[reactive nonmetal]]s, and [[noble gas]]es. In this system, the alkali metals, alkaline earth metals, and transition metals, as well as the lanthanides and the actinides, are special groups of the metals viewed in a broader sense. Similarly, the reactive nonmetals and the noble gases are nonmetals viewed in the broader sense. In some presentations, the halogens are not distinguished, with [[astatine]] identified as a metalloid and the others identified as nonmetals.

====States of matter====
Another commonly used basic distinction among the elements is their [[state of matter]] (phase), whether [[solid]], [[liquid]], or [[gas]], at a selected [[standard temperature and pressure]] (STP). Most of the elements are solids at conventional temperatures and atmospheric pressure, while several are gases. Only [[bromine]] and [[mercury (element)|mercury]] are liquids at 0 degrees Celsius (32 degrees Fahrenheit) and normal atmospheric pressure; [[caesium]] and [[gallium]] are solids at that temperature, but melt at 28.4&amp;nbsp;°C (83.2&amp;nbsp;°F) and 29.8&amp;nbsp;°C (85.6&amp;nbsp;°F), respectively.

====Melting and boiling points====
[[Melting point|Melting]] and [[boiling point]]s, typically expressed in [[Celsius|degrees Celsius]] at a pressure of one atmosphere, are commonly used in characterizing the various elements. While known for most elements, either or both of these measurements is still undetermined for some of the radioactive elements available in only tiny quantities. Since [[helium]] remains a liquid even at [[absolute zero]] at atmospheric pressure, it has only a boiling point, and not a melting point, in conventional presentations.

====Densities====
{{Main|Densities of the elements (data page)}}
The [[density]] at selected standard temperature and pressure ([[standard temperature and pressure|STP]]) is frequently used in characterizing the elements. Density is often expressed in [[gram]]s per cubic centimeter (g/cm&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;). Since several elements are gases at commonly encountered temperatures, their densities are usually stated for their gaseous forms; when liquefied or solidified, the gaseous elements have densities similar to those of the other elements.

When an element has [[Allotropy|allotropes]] with different densities, one representative allotrope is typically selected in summary presentations, while densities for each allotrope can be stated where more detail is provided. For example, the three familiar [[allotropes of carbon]] ([[amorphous carbon]], [[graphite]], and [[diamond]]) have densities of 1.8–2.1, 2.267, and 3.515&amp;nbsp;g/cm&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;, respectively.

====Crystal structures====
{{Main|Crystal structure}}
The elements studied to date as solid samples have eight kinds of [[crystal structure]]s: [[cubic crystal system|cubic]], [[cubic crystal system|body-centered cubic]], [[cubic crystal system|face-centered cubic]], [[Hexagonal crystal system|hexagonal]], [[Monoclinic crystal system|monoclinic]], [[orthorhombic crystal system|orthorhombic]], [[Trigonal crystal system|rhombohedral]], and [[Tetragonal crystal system|tetragonal]]. For some of the synthetically produced transuranic elements, available samples have been too small to determine crystal structures.

====Occurrence and origin on Earth====
Chemical elements may also be categorized by their origin on Earth, with the first 94 considered naturally occurring, while those with atomic numbers beyond 94 have only been produced artificially as the synthetic products of man-made nuclear reactions.

Of the 94 naturally occurring elements, 83 are considered [[primordial nuclide|primordial]] and either [[stable isotope|stable]] or weakly radioactive. The remaining 11 naturally occurring elements possess [[Half-life|half lives]] too short for them to have been present at the beginning of the [[Solar System]], and are therefore considered transient elements. Of these 11 transient elements, 5 ([[polonium]], [[radon]], [[radium]], [[actinium]], and [[protactinium]]) are relatively common [[decay products]] of [[thorium]] and [[uranium]]. The remaining 6 transient elements ([[technetium]], [[promethium]], [[astatine]], [[francium]], [[neptunium]], and [[plutonium]]) occur only rarely, as products of rare decay modes or nuclear reaction processes involving uranium or other heavy elements.

No radioactive decay has been observed for elements with atomic numbers 1 through 82, except 43 ([[technetium]]) and 61 ([[promethium]]). Observationally stable isotopes of some elements (such as [[tungsten]] and [[lead]]), however, are predicted to be slightly radioactive with very long half-lives:{{NUBASE2016|ref}} for example, the half-lives predicted for the observationally stable lead isotopes range from 10&lt;sup&gt;35&lt;/sup&gt; to 10&lt;sup&gt;189&lt;/sup&gt; years. Elements with atomic numbers 43, 61, and 83 through 94 are unstable enough that their radioactive decay can readily be detected. Three of these elements, bismuth (element 83), thorium (element 90), and uranium (element 92) have one or more isotopes with half-lives long enough to survive as remnants of the explosive [[stellar nucleosynthesis]] that produced the heavy elements before the formation of the [[Solar System]]. For example, at over 1.9{{e|19}} years, over a billion times longer than the current estimated age of the universe, [[bismuth-209]] has the longest known [[alpha decay]] half-life of any naturally occurring element.{{r|Dume2003}}{{r|Marcillac2003}} The very heaviest 24 elements (those beyond plutonium, element 94) undergo radioactive decay with short half-lives and cannot be produced as daughters of longer-lived elements, and thus are not known to occur in nature at all.

===Periodic table===
{{Main|Periodic table}}
{{Periodic table}}

The properties of the chemical elements are often summarized using the [[periodic table]], which powerfully and elegantly organizes the elements by increasing atomic number into rows ([[period (periodic table)|&quot;periods&quot;]]) in which the columns ([[group (periodic table)|&quot;groups&quot;]]) share recurring (&quot;periodic&quot;) physical and chemical properties. The current standard table contains 118 confirmed elements as of 2019.

Although earlier precursors to this presentation exist, its invention is generally credited to the Russian chemist [[Dmitri Mendeleev]] in 1869, who intended the table to illustrate recurring trends in the properties of the elements. The layout of the table has been refined and extended over time as new elements have been discovered and new theoretical models have been developed to explain chemical behavior.

Use of the periodic table is now ubiquitous within the academic discipline of chemistry, providing an extremely useful framework to classify, systematize and compare all the many different forms of chemical behavior. The table has also found wide application in [[physics]], [[geology]], [[biology]], [[materials science]], [[engineering]], [[agriculture]], [[medicine]], [[nutrition]], [[environmental health]], and [[astronomy]]. Its principles are especially important in [[chemical engineering]].

==Nomenclature and symbols==
{{anchor|Nomenclature}}
The various chemical elements are formally identified by their unique [[atomic number]]s, by their accepted names, and by their [[Symbol (chemistry)|symbols]].

===Atomic numbers===
The known elements have atomic numbers from 1 through 118, conventionally presented as [[Arabic numerals]]. Since the elements can be uniquely sequenced by atomic number, conventionally from lowest to highest (as in a [[periodic table]]), sets of elements are sometimes specified by such notation as &quot;through&quot;, &quot;beyond&quot;, or &quot;from ... through&quot;, as in &quot;through iron&quot;, &quot;beyond uranium&quot;, or &quot;from lanthanum through lutetium&quot;. The terms &quot;light&quot; and &quot;heavy&quot; are sometimes also used informally to indicate relative atomic numbers (not densities), as in &quot;lighter than carbon&quot; or &quot;heavier than lead&quot;, although technically the weight or mass of atoms of an element (their atomic weights or atomic masses) do not always increase [[monotonic function|monotonically]] with their atomic numbers.

===Element names===
{{main|Naming of elements}}
The naming of various substances now known as elements precedes the [[Atomic theory|atomic theory of matter]], as names were given locally by various cultures to various minerals, metals, compounds, alloys, mixtures, and other materials, although at the time it was not known which chemicals were elements and which compounds. As they were identified as elements, the existing names for anciently-known elements (e.g., gold, mercury, iron) were kept in most countries. National differences emerged over the names of elements either for convenience, linguistic niceties, or nationalism. For a few illustrative examples: German speakers use &quot;Wasserstoff&quot; (water substance) for &quot;hydrogen&quot;, &quot;Sauerstoff&quot; (acid substance) for &quot;oxygen&quot; and &quot;Stickstoff&quot; (smothering substance) for &quot;nitrogen&quot;, while English and some [[romance language]]s use &quot;sodium&quot; for &quot;natrium&quot; and &quot;potassium&quot; for &quot;kalium&quot;, and the French, Italians, Greeks, Portuguese and Poles prefer &quot;azote/azot/azoto&quot; (from roots meaning &quot;no life&quot;) for &quot;nitrogen&quot;.

For purposes of international communication and trade, the [[Table of chemical elements|official names of the chemical elements]] both ancient and more recently recognized are decided by the [[International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry]] (IUPAC), which has decided on a sort of international English language, drawing on traditional English names even when an element's chemical symbol is based on a Latin or other traditional word, for example adopting &quot;gold&quot; rather than &quot;aurum&quot; as the name for the 79th element (Au). IUPAC prefers the British spellings &quot;[[aluminium]]&quot; and &quot;caesium&quot; over the U.S. spellings &quot;aluminum&quot; and &quot;cesium&quot;, and the U.S. &quot;sulfur&quot; over the British &quot;sulphur&quot;. However, elements that are practical to sell in bulk in many countries often still have locally used national names, and countries whose national language does not use the [[Latin alphabet]] are likely to use the IUPAC element names.

According to IUPAC, chemical elements are not proper nouns in English; consequently, the full name of an element is not routinely capitalized in English, even if derived from a [[proper noun]], as in [[californium]] and [[einsteinium]]. Isotope names of chemical elements are also uncapitalized if written out, ''e.g.,'' [[carbon-12]] or [[uranium-235]]. Chemical element ''symbols'' (such as Cf for californium and Es for einsteinium), are always capitalized (see below).

In the second half of the twentieth century, physics laboratories became able to produce nuclei of chemical elements with half-lives too short for an appreciable amount of them to exist at any time. These are also named by IUPAC, which generally adopts the name chosen by the discoverer. This practice can lead to the controversial question of which research group actually discovered an element, a question that delayed the naming of elements with atomic number of 104 and higher for a considerable amount of time. (See [[element naming controversy]]).

Precursors of such controversies involved the nationalistic namings of elements in the late 19th century. For example, ''[[lutetium]]'' was named in reference to Paris, France. The Germans were reluctant to relinquish naming rights to the French, often calling it ''cassiopeium''. Similarly, the British discoverer of ''[[niobium]]'' originally named it ''columbium,'' in reference to the [[New World]]. It was used extensively as such by American publications before the international standardization (in 1950).

===Chemical symbols===
{{For|listings of current chemical symbols, symbols not currently used, and other symbols that may look like chemical symbols|Symbol (chemistry)}}

====Specific chemical elements====
Before chemistry became a [[science]], [[alchemy|alchemists]] had designed arcane symbols for both metals and common compounds. These were however used as abbreviations in diagrams or procedures; there was no concept of atoms combining to form [[molecule]]s. With his advances in the atomic theory of matter, [[John Dalton]] devised his own simpler symbols, based on circles, to depict molecules.

The current system of chemical notation was invented by [[Jöns Jakob Berzelius|Berzelius]]. In this typographical system, chemical symbols are not mere abbreviations—though each consists of letters of the [[Latin alphabet]]. They are intended as universal symbols for people of all languages and alphabets.

The first of these symbols were intended to be fully universal. Since Latin was the common language of science at that time, they were abbreviations based on the [[Latin]] names of metals. Cu comes from cuprum, Fe comes from ferrum, Ag from argentum. The symbols were not followed by a period (full stop) as with abbreviations. Later chemical elements were also assigned unique chemical symbols, based on the name of the element, but not necessarily in English. For example, [[sodium]] has the chemical symbol 'Na' after the Latin ''natrium''. The same applies to &quot;Fe&quot; (ferrum) for [[iron]], &quot;Hg&quot; (hydrargyrum) for [[Mercury (element)|mercury]], &quot;Sn&quot; (stannum) for [[tin]], &quot;Au&quot; (aurum) for [[gold]], &quot;Ag&quot; (argentum) for [[silver]], &quot;Pb&quot; (plumbum) for [[lead]], &quot;Cu&quot; (cuprum) for [[copper]], and &quot;Sb&quot; (stibium) for [[antimony]]. &quot;W&quot; (wolfram) for [[tungsten]] ultimately derives from German, &quot;K&quot; (kalium) for [[potassium]] ultimately from Arabic.

Chemical symbols are understood internationally when element names might require translation. There have sometimes been differences in the past. For example, Germans in the past have used &quot;J&quot; (for the alternate name Jod) for iodine, but now use &quot;I&quot; and &quot;Iod&quot;.

The first letter of a chemical symbol is always capitalized, as in the preceding examples, and the subsequent letters, if any, are always lower case (small letters). Thus, the symbols for californium and einsteinium are Cf and Es.

====General chemical symbols====
There are also symbols in chemical equations for groups of chemical elements, for example in comparative formulas. These are often a single capital letter, and the letters are reserved and not used for names of specific elements. For example, an &quot;'''X'''&quot; indicates a variable group (usually a [[halogen]]) in a class of compounds, while &quot;'''R'''&quot; is a [[Radical (chemistry)|radical]], meaning a compound structure such as a hydrocarbon chain. The letter &quot;'''Q'''&quot; is reserved for &quot;heat&quot; in a chemical reaction. &quot;'''Y'''&quot; is also often used as a general chemical symbol, although it is also the symbol of [[yttrium]]. &quot;'''Z'''&quot; is also frequently used as a general variable group. &quot;'''E'''&quot; is used in organic chemistry to denote an [[Polar effect|electron-withdrawing group]] or an [[electrophile]]; similarly &quot;'''Nu'''&quot; denotes a [[nucleophile]]. &quot;'''L'''&quot; is used to represent a general [[ligand]] in [[inorganic chemistry|inorganic]] and [[organometallic chemistry]]. &quot;'''M'''&quot; is also often used in place of a general metal.

At least two additional, two-letter generic chemical symbols are also in informal usage, &quot;'''Ln'''&quot; for any [[lanthanide]] element and &quot;'''An'''&quot; for any [[actinide]] element. &quot;'''Rg'''&quot; was formerly used for any [[rare gas]] element, but the group of rare gases has now been renamed [[noble gas]]es and the symbol &quot;'''Rg'''&quot; has now been assigned to the element [[roentgenium]].

====Isotope symbols====
Isotopes are distinguished by the atomic mass number (total protons and neutrons) for a particular isotope of an element, with this number combined with the pertinent element's symbol. IUPAC prefers that isotope symbols be written in superscript notation when practical, for example &lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;C and &lt;sup&gt;235&lt;/sup&gt;U. However, other notations, such as carbon-12 and uranium-235, or C-12 and U-235, are also used.

As a special case, the three naturally occurring isotopes of the element [[hydrogen]] are often specified as '''H''' for &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;H ([[Isotopes of hydrogen#Hydrogen-1 (protium)|protium]]), '''D''' for &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;H ([[deuterium]]), and '''T''' for &lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;H ([[tritium]]). This convention is easier to use in chemical equations, replacing the need to write out the mass number for each atom. For example, the formula for [[heavy water]] may be written D&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O instead of &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O.

==Origin of the elements==
[[File:Universe content pie chart.jpg|thumb|upright=1.7|Estimated distribution of dark matter and dark energy in the universe. Only the fraction of the mass and energy in the universe labeled &quot;atoms&quot; is composed of chemical elements.]]

Only about 4% of the total mass of the universe is made of atoms or [[ion]]s, and thus represented by chemical elements. This fraction is about 15% of the total matter, with the remainder of the matter (85%) being [[dark matter]]. The nature of dark matter is unknown, but it is not composed of atoms of chemical elements because it contains no protons, neutrons, or electrons. (The remaining non-matter part of the mass of the universe is composed of the even more mysterious [[dark energy]]).

The universe's 94 naturally occurring chemical elements are thought to have been produced by at least four [[cosmos|cosmic]] processes. Most of the [[hydrogen]], [[helium]] and a very small quantity of [[lithium]] in the universe was produced primordially in the first few minutes of the [[Big Bang]]. Other three recurrently occurring later processes are thought to have produced the remaining elements. [[Stellar nucleosynthesis]], an ongoing process inside stars, produces all elements from [[carbon]] through [[iron]] in atomic number, but little [[lithium]], [[beryllium]], or [[boron]]. Elements heavier in atomic number than iron, as heavy as [[uranium]] and [[plutonium]], are produced by explosive nucleosynthesis in [[supernova]]s and other cataclysmic cosmic events. [[Cosmic ray spallation]] (fragmentation) of carbon, [[nitrogen]], and [[oxygen]] is important to the production of lithium, beryllium and boron.

During the early phases of the Big Bang, [[Big Bang nucleosynthesis|nucleosynthesis]] of hydrogen nuclei resulted in the production of hydrogen-1 ([[Isotopes of hydrogen#Hydrogen-1 (protium)|protium]], &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;H) and helium-4 (&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;He), as well as a smaller amount of [[deuterium]] (&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;H) and very minuscule amounts (on the order of 10&lt;sup&gt;−10&lt;/sup&gt;) of lithium and beryllium. Even smaller amounts of boron may have been produced in the Big Bang, since it has been observed in some very old stars, while carbon has not.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Wilford|first=J.N.|date=14 January 1992|title=Hubble Observations Bring Some Surprises|url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5D91F3AF937A25752C0A964958260|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is generally agreed that no heavier elements than boron were produced in the Big Bang. As a result, the primordial abundance of atoms (or ions) consisted of roughly 75% &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;H, 25% &lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;He, and 0.01% deuterium, with only tiny traces of lithium, beryllium, and perhaps boron.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Wright|first=E. L.|date=12 September 2004|title=Big Bang Nucleosynthesis|url=http://www.astro.ucla.edu/~wright/BBNS.html|publisher=[[UCLA]], Division of Astronomy|accessdate=22 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequent enrichment of [[galactic spheroid|galactic halos]] occurred due to stellar nucleosynthesis and [[supernova nucleosynthesis]].&lt;ref name=synthesis&gt;{{cite journal|year=1999 |title=Synthesis of the elements in stars: forty years of progress |url=http://www.cococubed.com/papers/wallerstein97.pdf |journal=[[Reviews of Modern Physics]] |volume=69 |issue=4 |pages=995–1084 |doi=10.1103/RevModPhys.69.995 |bibcode=1997RvMP...69..995W |last1=Wallerstein |first1=George |last2=Iben |first2=Icko |last3=Parker |first3=Peter |last4=Boesgaard |first4=Ann |last5=Hale |first5=Gerald |last6=Champagne |first6=Arthur |last7=Barnes |first7=Charles |last8=Käppeler |first8=Franz |last9=Smith |first9=Verne |display-authors=8 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060928043229/http://www.cococubed.com/papers/wallerstein97.pdf |archivedate=28 September 2006 |hdl=2152/61093 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the element abundance in [[intergalactic space]] can still closely resemble primordial conditions, unless it has been enriched by some means.

[[File:Nucleosynthesis periodic table.svg|thumb|upright=2.25|Periodic table showing the cosmogenic origin of each element in the Big Bang, or in large or small stars. Small stars can produce certain elements up to sulfur, by the [[alpha process]]. Supernovae are needed to produce &quot;heavy&quot; elements (those beyond iron and nickel) rapidly by neutron buildup, in the [[r-process]]. Certain large stars slowly produce other elements heavier than iron, in the [[s-process]]; these may then be blown into space in the off-gassing of [[planetary nebulae]]]]

On Earth (and elsewhere), trace amounts of various elements continue to be produced from other elements as products of [[nuclear transmutation]] processes. These include some produced by [[cosmic ray]]s or other nuclear reactions (see [[cosmogenic nuclide|cosmogenic]] and [[nucleogenic]] nuclides), and others produced as [[decay product]]s of long-lived [[primordial nuclide]]s.&lt;ref name=Earnshaw1997&gt;{{cite book|last=Earnshaw|first=A.|last2=Greenwood|first2=N.|year=1997|title=Chemistry of the Elements|edition=2nd|publisher=[[Butterworth-Heinemann]]|isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, trace (but detectable) amounts of [[carbon-14]] (&lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;C) are continually produced in the atmosphere by cosmic rays impacting [[nitrogen]] atoms, and argon-40 (&lt;sup&gt;40&lt;/sup&gt;Ar) is continually produced by the decay of primordially occurring but unstable potassium-40 (&lt;sup&gt;40&lt;/sup&gt;K). Also, three primordially occurring but radioactive [[actinide]]s, [[thorium]], uranium, and plutonium, decay through a series of recurrently produced but unstable radioactive elements such as radium and [[radon]], which are transiently present in any sample of these metals or their ores or compounds. Three other radioactive elements, [[technetium]], [[promethium]], and [[neptunium]], occur only incidentally in natural materials, produced as individual atoms by [[nuclear fission]] of the [[Atomic nucleus|nuclei]] of various heavy elements or in other rare nuclear processes.

[[Human]] [[technology]] has produced various additional elements beyond these first 94, with those through atomic number 118 now known.

==Abundance==
{{Main|Abundance of the chemical elements}}

The following graph (note log scale) shows the abundance of elements in our [[Solar System]]. The table shows the twelve most common elements in our galaxy (estimated spectroscopically), as measured in [[Parts-per notation|parts per million]], by [[mass]].&lt;ref name=croswell&gt;{{cite book|last=Croswell|first=K.|year=1996|title=Alchemy of the Heavens|url=http://kencroswell.com/alchemy.html|publisher=Anchor|isbn=978-0-385-47214-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nearby galaxies that have evolved along similar lines have a corresponding enrichment of elements heavier than hydrogen and helium. The more distant galaxies are being viewed as they appeared in the past, so their abundances of elements appear closer to the primordial mixture. As physical laws and processes appear common throughout the [[visible universe]], however, scientist expect that these galaxies evolved elements in similar abundance.

The abundance of elements in the Solar System is in keeping with their origin from nucleosynthesis in the [[Big Bang]] and a number of progenitor supernova stars. Very abundant hydrogen and helium are products of the Big Bang, but the next three elements are rare since they had little time to form in the Big Bang and are not made in stars (they are, however, produced in small quantities by the breakup of heavier elements in interstellar dust, as a result of impact by [[cosmic ray]]s). Beginning with carbon, elements are produced in stars by buildup from alpha particles (helium nuclei), resulting in an alternatingly larger abundance of elements with even atomic numbers (these are also more stable). In general, such elements up to iron are made in large stars in the process of becoming [[supernova]]s. Iron-56 is particularly common, since it is the most stable element that can easily be made from alpha particles (being a product of decay of radioactive nickel-56, ultimately made from 14 helium nuclei). Elements heavier than iron are made in energy-absorbing processes in large stars, and their abundance in the universe (and on Earth) generally decreases with their atomic number.

The [[abundance of the chemical elements]] on Earth varies from air to crust to ocean, and in various types of life. The abundance of elements in Earth's crust differs from that in the Solar System (as seen in the Sun and heavy planets like Jupiter) mainly in selective loss of the very lightest elements (hydrogen and helium) and also volatile neon, carbon (as hydrocarbons), nitrogen and sulfur, as a result of solar heating in the early formation of the solar system. Oxygen, the most abundant Earth element by mass, is retained on Earth by combination with silicon. Aluminum at 8% by mass is more common in the Earth's crust than in the universe and solar system, but the composition of the far more bulky mantle, which has magnesium and iron in place of aluminum (which occurs there only at 2% of mass) more closely mirrors the elemental composition of the solar system, save for the noted loss of volatile elements to space, and loss of iron which has migrated to the Earth's core.

The [[composition of the human body]], by contrast, more closely follows the composition of [[seawater]]—save that the human body has additional stores of [[carbon]] and [[nitrogen]] necessary to form the [[protein]]s and [[nucleic acid]]s, together with [[phosphorus]] in the nucleic acids and energy transfer molecule [[adenosine triphosphate]] (ATP) that occurs in the cells of all living organisms. Certain kinds of [[organism]]s require particular additional elements, for example the [[magnesium]] in [[chlorophyll]] in green plants, the [[calcium]] in [[mollusc shell]]s, or the [[iron]] in the [[hemoglobin]] in [[vertebrate|vertebrate animals]]' [[red blood cell]]s.

[[File:SolarSystemAbundances.png|thumb|upright=2.7|Abundances of the chemical elements in the Solar System. Hydrogen and helium are most common, from the Big Bang. The next three elements (Li, Be, B) are rare because they are poorly synthesized in the Big Bang and also in stars. The two general trends in the remaining stellar-produced elements are: (1) an alternation of abundance in elements as they have even or odd atomic numbers (the [[Oddo-Harkins rule]]), and (2) a general decrease in abundance as elements become heavier. Iron is especially common because it represents the minimum energy nuclide that can be made by fusion of helium in supernovae.]]

{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Elements in our galaxy!!Parts per million&lt;br /&gt;by mass
|-
|[[Hydrogen]]
|739,000
|-
|[[Helium]]
|240,000
|-
|[[Oxygen]]
|10,400
|-
|[[Carbon]]
|4,600
|-
|[[Neon]]
|1,340
|-
|[[Iron]]
|1,090
|-
|[[Nitrogen]]
|960
|-
|[[Silicon]]
|650
|-
|[[Magnesium]]
|580
|-
|[[Sulfur]]
|440
|-
|[[Potassium]]
|210
|-
|[[Nickel]]
|100
|}
{{clear}}

{{Periodic table (dietary elements)}}

==History&lt;!--linked from 'Classical element'--&gt;==
[[File:Mendeleev's 1869 periodic table.svg|upright=1.35|thumb|[[Mendeleev]]'s 1869 [[periodic table]]: ''An experiment on a system of elements. Based on their atomic weights and chemical similarities.'']]

===Evolving definitions===
The concept of an &quot;element&quot; as an undivisible substance has developed through three major historical phases: Classical definitions (such as those of the ancient Greeks), chemical definitions, and atomic definitions.

====Classical definitions====
[[Ancient philosophy]] posited a set of [[classical element]]s to explain observed patterns in [[nature]]. These ''elements'' originally referred to ''[[Earth (classical element)|earth]]'', ''[[Water (classical element)|water]]'', ''[[Air (classical element)|air]]'' and ''[[Fire (classical element)|fire]]'' rather than the chemical elements of modern science.

The term 'elements' (''stoicheia'') was first used by the Greek philosopher [[Plato]] in about 360 BCE in his dialogue [[Timaeus (dialogue)|Timaeus]], which includes a discussion of the composition of inorganic and organic bodies and is a speculative treatise on chemistry. Plato believed the elements introduced a century earlier by [[Empedocles]] were composed of small [[regular polyhedron|polyhedral]] [[Theory of Forms|forms]]: [[tetrahedron]] (fire), [[octahedron]] (air), [[icosahedron]] (water), and [[cube]] (earth).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Plato|year=2008|origyear=c. 360 BC|title=Timaeus|url=https://books.google.com/?id=xSjvowNydN8C&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;dq=Plato%20timaeus&amp;pg=PA45#v=onepage&amp;q=cube&amp;f=false|publisher=Forgotten Books|page=45|isbn=978-1-60620-018-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Hillar |first=M. |year=2004 |title=The Problem of the Soul in Aristotle's De anima |url=http://www.socinian.org/aristotles_de_anima.html |publisher=[[NASA]]/[[WMAP]] |accessdate=10 August 2006 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060909004214/http://www.socinian.org/aristotles_de_anima.html |archivedate=9 September 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Aristotle]], c. 350 BCE, also used the term ''stoicheia'' and added a fifth element called [[Aether (classical element)|aether]], which formed the heavens. Aristotle defined an element as:

{{quote|Element – one of those bodies into which other bodies can decompose, and that itself is not capable of being divided into other.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Partington|first=J. R.|year=1937|title=A Short History of Chemistry|location=New York|publisher=[[Dover Publications]]|isbn=978-0-486-65977-0|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/shorthistoryofch0000part_q6h4}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

====Chemical definitions====
In 1661, [[Robert Boyle]] proposed his theory of corpuscularism which favoured the analysis of matter as constituted by irreducible units of matter (atoms) and, choosing to side with neither Aristotle's view of the four elements nor [[Paracelsus]]' view of three fundamental elements, left open the question of the number of elements.{{r|boyle}} The first modern list of chemical elements was given in [[Antoine Lavoisier]]'s 1789 ''[[Traité Élémentaire de Chimie|Elements of Chemistry]]'', which contained thirty-three elements, including [[light]] and [[Caloric theory|caloric]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Lavoisier|first=A. L.|year=1790|title=Elements of chemistry translated by Robert Kerr|url=https://books.google.com/?id=4BzAjCpEK4gC&amp;pg=PA175|place=Edinburgh|pages=175–6|isbn=978-0-415-17914-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 1818, [[Jöns Jakob Berzelius]] had determined atomic weights for forty-five of the forty-nine then-accepted elements. [[Dmitri Mendeleev]] had sixty-six elements in his [[periodic table]] of 1869.
[[File:DIMendeleevCab.jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[Dmitri Mendeleev]]]]
From Boyle until the early 20th century, an element was defined as a pure substance that could not be decomposed into any simpler substance.&lt;ref name=boyle&gt;{{cite book|first=R.|last=Boyle|year=1661|title=The Sceptical Chymist|location=London|isbn=978-0-922802-90-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; Put another way, a chemical element cannot be transformed into other chemical elements by chemical processes. Elements during this time were generally distinguished by their atomic weights, a property measurable with fair accuracy by available analytical techniques.

====Atomic definitions====
[[File:Henry Moseley.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Henry Moseley]]]]
The 1913 discovery by English physicist [[Henry Moseley]] that the nuclear charge is the physical basis for an atom's atomic number, further refined when the nature of protons and [[neutrons]] became appreciated, eventually led to the current definition of an element based on atomic number (number of protons per atomic nucleus). The use of atomic numbers, rather than atomic weights, to distinguish elements has greater predictive value (since these numbers are integers), and also resolves some ambiguities in the chemistry-based view due to varying properties of [[isotope]]s and [[allotropes]] within the same element. Currently, [[IUPAC]] defines an element to exist if it has isotopes with a lifetime longer than the 10&lt;sup&gt;−14&lt;/sup&gt; seconds it takes the nucleus to form an electronic cloud.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kernchemie.de/Transactinides/Transactinide-2/transactinide-2.html Transactinide-2]. www.kernchemie.de&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1914, seventy-two elements were known, all naturally occurring.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Carey|first=G.W.|year=1914|title=The Chemistry of Human Life|location=Los Angeles|isbn=978-0-7661-2840-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; The remaining naturally occurring elements were discovered or isolated in subsequent decades, and various additional elements have also been produced synthetically, with much of that work pioneered by [[Glenn T. Seaborg]]. In 1955, element 101 was discovered and named [[mendelevium]] in honor of D.I. Mendeleev, the first to arrange the elements in a periodic manner. Most recently, the synthesis of element 118 (since named [[oganesson]]) was reported in October 2006, and the synthesis of element 117 ([[tennessine]]) was reported in April 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Glanz| first=J.|date=6 April 2010|title=Scientists Discover Heavy New Element|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2010/04/07/science/07element.html?hp|work=[[The New York Times]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Discovery and recognition of various elements===
{{See also|Timeline of chemical elements discoveries}}

Ten materials familiar to various prehistoric cultures are now known to be chemical elements: [[Carbon]], [[copper]], [[gold]], [[iron]], [[lead]], [[mercury (element)|mercury]], [[silver]], [[sulfur]], [[tin]], and [[zinc]]. Three additional materials now accepted as elements, [[arsenic]], [[antimony]], and [[bismuth]], were recognized as distinct substances prior to 1500 AD. [[Phosphorus]], [[cobalt]], and [[platinum]] were isolated before 1750.

Most of the remaining naturally occurring chemical elements were identified and characterized by 1900, including:
* Such now-familiar [[industry|industrial]] materials as [[aluminium]], [[silicon]], [[nickel]], [[chromium]], [[magnesium]], and [[tungsten]]
* Reactive metals such as [[lithium]], [[sodium]], [[potassium]], and [[calcium]]
* The [[halogen]]s [[fluorine]], [[chlorine]], [[bromine]], and [[iodine]]
* Gases such as [[hydrogen]], [[oxygen]], [[nitrogen]], [[helium]], [[argon]], and [[neon]]
* Most of the [[rare-earth elements]], including [[cerium]], [[lanthanum]], [[gadolinium]], and [[neodymium]].
* The more common [[radioactive]] elements, including [[uranium]], [[thorium]], [[radium]], and [[radon]]

Elements isolated or produced since 1900 include:
* The three remaining undiscovered regularly occurring stable natural elements: [[hafnium]], [[lutetium]], and [[rhenium]]
* [[Plutonium]], which was first produced synthetically in 1940 by [[Glenn T. Seaborg]], but is now also known from a few long-persisting natural occurrences
* The three incidentally occurring natural elements ([[neptunium]], [[promethium]], and [[technetium]]), which were all first produced synthetically but later discovered in trace amounts in certain geological samples
* Three scarce decay products of uranium or thorium, ([[astatine]], [[francium]], and [[protactinium]]), and
* Various synthetic [[transuranic]] elements, beginning with [[americium]] and [[curium]]

===Recently discovered elements===
The first [[transuranium element]] (element with atomic number greater than 92) discovered was [[neptunium]] in 1940. Since 1999 claims for the discovery of new elements have been considered by the [[IUPAC/IUPAP Joint Working Party]]. As of January 2016, all 118 elements have been confirmed as discovered by [[International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry|IUPAC]]. The discovery of element 112 was acknowledged in 2009, and the name ''copernicium'' and the atomic symbol ''Cn'' were suggested for it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=20 July 2009|title=IUPAC Announces Start of the Name Approval Process for the Element of Atomic Number 112|url=http://media.iupac.org/news/112_Naming_Process_20090720.pdf|publisher=[[IUPAC]]|accessdate=27 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The name and symbol were officially endorsed by IUPAC on 19 February 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=20 February 2010 |title=IUPAC (International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry): Element 112 is Named Copernicium |url=http://www.iupac.org/web/nt/2010-02-20_112_Copernicium |publisher=[[IUPAC]] |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100224054826/http://www.iupac.org/web/nt/2010-02-20_112_Copernicium |archivedate=24 February 2010 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; The heaviest element that is believed to have been synthesized to date is element 118, [[oganesson]], on 9 October 2006, by the [[Joint Institute for Nuclear Research|Flerov Laboratory]] of Nuclear Reactions in [[Dubna]], Russia.{{r|Schewe}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|year=2006|title=Evidence for Dark Matter|url=http://gaitskell.brown.edu/physics/talks/0408_SLAC_SummerSchool/Gaitskell_DMEvidence_v16.pdf|journal=[[Physical Review C]]|volume=74|issue=4|pages=044602|doi=10.1103/PhysRevC.74.044602|bibcode=2006PhRvC..74d4602O|last1=Oganessian|first1=Yu. Ts. |last2=Utyonkov |first2=V.|last3=Lobanov|first3=Yu.|last4=Abdullin|first4=F.|last5=Polyakov|first5=A.|last6=Sagaidak|first6=R.|last7=Shirokovsky|first7=I.|last8=Tsyganov|first8=Yu.|last9=Voinov|first9=A.|display-authors=8}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Tennessine]], element 117 was the latest element claimed to be discovered, in 2009.&lt;ref name=jinr&gt;{{cite web|last=Greiner |first=W. |title=Recommendations |url=http://www.jinr.ru/img_sections/PAC/NP/31/PAK_NP_31_recom_eng.pdf |work=31st meeting, PAC for Nuclear Physics |publisher=[[Joint Institute for Nuclear Research]] |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100414173735/http://www.jinr.ru/img_sections/PAC/NP/31/PAK_NP_31_recom_eng.pdf |archivedate=14 April 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; On 28 November 2016, scientists at the IUPAC officially recognized the names for four of the newest chemical elements, with atomic numbers 113, 115, 117, and 118.&lt;ref name=&quot;IUPAC-20161130&quot;&gt;{{cite news |author=Staff  |title=IUPAC Announces the Names of the Elements 113, 115, 117, and 118 |url=https://iupac.org/iupac-announces-the-names-of-the-elements-113-115-117-and-118/ |date=30 November 2016 |work=[[IUPAC]] |accessdate=1 December 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT-20161201&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=St. Fleur |first=Nicholas |title=Four New Names Officially Added to the Periodic Table of Elements |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2016/12/01/science/periodic-table-new-elements.html |date=1 December 2016 |work=[[The New York Times]] |accessdate=1 December 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==List of the 118 known chemical elements==
The following sortable table shows the 118 known chemical elements.
* '''Atomic number''', '''name''', and '''symbol''' all serve independently as unique identifiers.
* '''Names''' are those accepted by [[IUPAC]]. &lt;!-- ; provisional names for recently produced elements not yet formally named are in parentheses. --&gt;
* '''Group, period,''' and '''block''' refer to an element's position in the [[periodic table]]. Group numbers here show the currently accepted numbering; for older alternate numberings, see [[Group (periodic table)]].
* '''State of matter''' ''(solid, liquid,'' or ''gas)'' applies at standard [[temperature]] and [[pressure]] conditions ([[Standard Temperature and Pressure|STP]]).
* '''Occurrence''', as indicated by a footnote adjacent to the element's name, distinguishes naturally occurring elements, categorized as either ''primordial'' or ''transient'' (from decay), and additional ''synthetic'' elements that have been produced technologically, but are not known to occur naturally.
* '''Color''' specifies an element's properties using the broad categories commonly presented in periodic tables: [[Actinide]], [[alkali metal]], [[alkaline earth metal]], [[lanthanide]], [[post-transition metal]], [[metalloid]], [[noble gas]], polyatomic or diatomic [[nonmetal]], and [[transition metal]].
{{#section-h:List of chemical elements|List}}

==See also==
{{Wikipedia books
|1=Chemical elements
}}
{{div col|colwidth=22em}}

* [[Chemical database]]
* [[Discovery of the chemical elements]]
* [[Element collecting]]
* [[Fictional element]]
* [[Goldschmidt classification]]
* [[Island of stability]]
* [[List of chemical elements]]
* [[List of nuclides]]
* [[Densities of the elements (data page)|List of the elements' densities]]
* [[Periodic Systems of Small Molecules]]
* [[Prices of elements and their compounds]]
* [[Systematic element name]]
* [[Table of nuclides]]
* [[Timeline of chemical element discoveries]]
* [[The Mystery of Matter (film)|''The Mystery of Matter: Search for the Elements'' (PBS film)]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
{{Commons category|Chemical elements}}
* {{cite book|last=Ball|first=P.|year=2004|title=The Elements: A Very Short Introduction|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|isbn=978-0-19-284099-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Emsley|first=J.|year=2003|title=Nature's Building Blocks: An A–Z Guide to the Elements|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|isbn=978-0-19-850340-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Gray|first=T.|year=2009|title=The Elements: A Visual Exploration of Every Known Atom in the Universe|publisher=Black Dog &amp; Leventhal Publishers Inc|isbn=978-1-57912-814-2|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/elementsvisualex0000gray}}
* {{cite book|last=Scerri|first=E.R.|year=2007|title=The Periodic Table, Its Story and Its Significance|url=https://archive.org/details/periodictableits0000scer|url-access=registration|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|isbn=}}
* {{cite book|last=Strathern|first=P.|year=2000|title=Mendeleyev's Dream: The Quest for the Elements|publisher=[[Hamish Hamilton Ltd]]|isbn=978-0-241-14065-9}}
* {{cite book|title=The Disappearing Spoon: And Other True Tales of Madness, Love, and the History of the World from the Periodic Table of the Elements|last=Kean|first=Sam|year=2011|publisher=Back Bay Books}}
* {{cite book|title=Compendium of Chemical Terminology, 2nd ed. (the &quot;Gold Book&quot;).|authors=Compiled by A.D. McNaught and A. Wilkinson.|editor=Blackwell Scientific Publications, Oxford|year=1997| website=|isbn=978-0-9678550-9-7|doi=10.1351/goldbook}}
*: XML on-line corrected version: created by M. Nic, J. Jirat, B. Kosata; updates compiled by A. Jenkins.

==External links==
* [http://periodicvideos.com/ Videos for each element] by the University of Nottingham
* [http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/p00546sz &quot;Chemical Elements&quot;], ''In Our Time'', BBC Radio 4 discussion with Paul Strathern, Mary Archer and [[John Murrell (chemist)|John Murrell]] (May 25, 2000).

{{PeriodicTablesFooter|state=uncollapsed}}
{{Big History}}
{{Branches of chemistry}}
{{Nature}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Chemical Element}}
[[Category:Chemical elements| ]]
[[Category:Chemistry]]</text>
      <sha1>1phe6vntmak2e4ik2ktycbbbdn4fi5f</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
