  <page>
    <title>Anthony the Great</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3246</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937595157</id>
      <parentid>937594865</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-26T00:49:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wtfiv</username>
        <id>1735438</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Cleaned up previous edit.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Christian saint, monk, and hermit}}
{{Other uses|Saint Anthony (disambiguation)}}
{{redirect|Antonious|Antonius|Antonius}}
{{Multiple issues|
{{POV|date=May 2019}}
{{fiction|date=May 2019}}
}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{Infobox saint
| name=Saint Anthony the Great
| birth_date      = 12 January 251 (reputedly)
| death_date      = {{death date and age|356|1|17|251|1|12|df=yes}}
| feast_day       = 17 January ([[Catholic Church]])&lt;br/&gt; 17 January ([[Eastern Orthodoxy]])&lt;br/&gt;22 [[Month of Tobi|Tobi]] ([[Coptic Calendar]])
| venerated_in    = [[Coptic Orthodox Church]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Assyrian Church of the East]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Eastern Orthodox Church]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Oriental Orthodox Churches]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Catholic Church]]
| image           = San Antonio Abad (Zurbarán).jpg
| imagesize       = 
| caption         = ''San Antonio Abad'', portrait by [[Francisco de Zurbarán]] in 1664
| birth_place     = [[Herakleopolis Magna]], [[Egypt (Roman province)|Egypt]]
| death_place     = Mount Colzim, [[Egypt (Roman province)|Egypt]]
| titles          = Venerable and God-bearing&lt;br/&gt;Father of Monasticism
| beatified_date  = 
| beatified_place = 
| beatified_by    = 
| canonized_date  = [[Pre-Congregation]]
| canonized_place = 
| canonized_by    = 
| attributes      = bell; pig; book; [[Tau Cross]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Complete Dictionary of Symbols|year=2005|publisher=Chronicle Books|location=San Francisco|isbn=0-8118-4767-5|editor=Jack Tresidder|url=https://archive.org/details/completedictiona00jack}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Cornwell|first=Hilarie|title=Saints, Signs, and Symbols|year=2009|publisher=Morehouse Publishing|location=Harrisburg|isbn=0-8192-2345-X|edition=3rd|author2=James Cornwell}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tau cross with bell pendant&lt;ref&gt;''Liechtenstein, the Princely Collections'', catalogue of Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, p.276 [https://books.google.com/books?id=A1f7lsIFyu0C&amp;pg=PA276]&lt;/ref&gt;
| patronage       = Animals, skin diseases, farmers, butchers, basket makers, brushmakers, gravediggers,&lt;ref name=&quot;ButlerLives1991&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Butler's Lives of the Saints|year=1991|publisher=HarperSanFrancisco|location=San Francisco|isbn=0-06-069299-5|edition=Concise, Revised &amp; Updated, 1st HarperCollins|editor=Michael Walsh|url=https://archive.org/details/butlerslivesofsa00butl}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pontifical Ecclesiastical Academy, Rome&lt;ref name=&quot;Vatican&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/pontifical_academies/acdeccles/documents/storia_it.htm |title=Pontificia Accademia Ecclesiastica, Cenni storici (1701-2001) |website=Pontificia Accademia Ecclesiastica |publisher=Vatican, Roman Curia |access-date=17 January 2017 |language=Italian}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| major_shrine    = [[Monastery of Saint Anthony|Monastery of St. Anthony]], Egypt &lt;br /&gt;[[Saint-Antoine-l'Abbaye]], France
| suppressed_date = 
| issues          = 
| prayer          = 
| prayer_attrib   = 
}}

'''Saint Anthony''' or '''Antony'''&lt;!--see talk page--&gt; ({{lang-grc-gre|Ἀντώνιος}} ''Antṓnios''; {{lang-la|Antonius}}; {{Lang-cop|Ⲁⲃⲃⲁ Ⲁⲛⲧⲱⲛⲓ}}; c. 12 January 251 – 17 January 356), was a Christian monk from Egypt, revered since his death as a saint. He is distinguished from [[Saint Anthony (disambiguation)|other saints named Anthony]] such as {{nowrap|[[Anthony of Padua]]}}, by various epithets of his own: {{nowrap|'''Anthony the Great'''}}, {{nowrap|'''Anthony of Egypt'''}}, {{nowrap|'''Antony the Abbot''',}} {{nowrap|'''Anthony of the Desert''',}} {{nowrap|'''Anthony the Anchorite''',}} and {{nowrap|'''Anthony of Thebes'''.}} For his importance among the [[Desert Fathers]] and to all later [[Christian monasticism]], he is also known as the {{nowrap|'''Father of All Monks'''}}. His feast day is celebrated on 17 January among the [[Greek Orthodox Church|Orthodox]] and [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] churches and on [[month of Tobi|Tobi]]&amp;nbsp;22 in the [[Coptic calendar]].

The biography of Anthony's life by [[Athanasius of Alexandria]] helped to spread the concept of Christian [[monasticism]], particularly in Western Europe via its [[Latin]] translations. He is often erroneously considered the first Christian monk, but as his biography and other sources make clear, there were many ascetics before him. Anthony was, however, among the first known to go into the wilderness (about {{sc|ad}}&amp;nbsp;270), which seems to have contributed to his renown.&lt;ref name=&quot;Endsjo2008&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Endsjø|first=Dag Øistein|title=Primordial landscapes, Incorruptible Bodies|year=2008|publisher=Peter Lang Publishing|location=New York|isbn=1-4331-0181-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Accounts of Anthony enduring supernatural temptation during his sojourn in the [[Eastern Desert]] of Egypt inspired the often-repeated subject of [[The temptation of St. Anthony in visual arts|the temptation of St. Anthony]] in Western art and literature.

Anthony is appealed to against infectious diseases, particularly skin diseases. In the past, many such afflictions, including [[ergotism]], [[erysipelas]], and [[Herpes zoster|shingles]], were referred to as ''St. Anthony's fire''.

{{anchor|History|Biography}}

==''Life of St. Anthony''==
Most of what is known about Saint Anthony comes from the ''Life of Anthony''. Written in Greek around 360 by [[Athanasius of Alexandria]], it depicts Anthony as an illiterate and holy man who through his existence in a primordial landscape has an absolute connection to the divine truth, which always is in harmony with that of Athanasius as the biographer.&lt;ref name=&quot;Endsjo2008&quot; /&gt;

A continuation of the genre of secular Greek biography,&lt;ref&gt;[http://bmcr.brynmawr.edu/2012/2012-07-45.html Hägg, Tomas. &quot;The Life of St Antony between Biography and Hagiography&quot;, ''Ashgate Research Companion to Byzantine Hagiography''. Vol. I, Farnham; Burlington, VT:  Ashgate, 2011] {{ISBN|9780754650331}}&lt;/ref&gt; it became his most widely read work.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://legacy.fordham.edu/halsall/basis/vita-antony.asp | title=Athanasius of Alexandria: Vita S. Antoni [Life of St. Antony] (written bwtween 356 and 362) | publisher=Fordham University | accessdate=14 July 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Sometime before 374 it was translated into Latin by [[Evagrius of Antioch]]. The Latin translation helped the ''Life'' become one of the best known works of literature in the Christian world, a status it would hold through the [[Middle Ages]].&lt;ref&gt;The Essential Writings of Christian Mysticism, Bernhart McGinn {{ISBN|0-8129-7421-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Translated into several languages, it became something of a best seller in its day and played an important role in the spreading of the [[ascetic]] ideal in Eastern and Western Christianity. It later served as an inspiration to Christian [[monasticism|monastics]] in both the East and the West,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.christianitytoday.com/ch/131christians/theologians/athanasius.html|title=Athanasius|work=Christian History {{!}} Learn the History of Christianity &amp; the Church|access-date=14 March 2018|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; and helped to spread the concept of Christian monasticism, particularly in Western Europe via its Latin translations.

Many stories are also told about Anthony in various collections of sayings of the [[Desert Fathers]].  He is often erroneously considered the first Christian monk, but as his biography and other sources make clear, there were many ascetics before him. Anthony was, however, the first to go into the wilderness (about AD 270), a geographical move that seems to have contributed to his renown.&lt;ref name=&quot;Endsjo2008&quot; /&gt;

Anthony probably spoke only his native language, [[Coptic language|Coptic]], but his sayings were spread in a [[Greek language|Greek]] translation. He himself dictated letters in Coptic, seven of which are extant.&lt;ref name=crawley/&gt;

== Life ==
=== Early years ===
Anthony was born in [[Coma, Egypt|Coma]] in [[Lower Egypt]] to wealthy landowner parents. When he was about 20 years old, his parents died and left him with the care of his unmarried sister. Shortly thereafter, he decided to follow the gospel exhortation in [[Matthew 19]]: 21, &quot;If you want to be perfect, go, sell what you have and give to the poor, and you will have treasures in heaven.&quot;  Anthony gave away some of his family's lands to his neighbors, sold the remaining property, and donated the funds to the poor.{{sfnp|''EB''|1878}} He then left to live an [[asceticism|ascetic]] life,{{sfnp|''EB''|1878}} placing his sister with a group of [[Consecrated virgin|Christian virgins]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Athanasius|title=Life of Antony|year=1998|publisher=Penguin Books|location=London|isbn=0-8146-2377-8|others=Carolinne White, trans|volume=3|page=10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Hermit ===
[[File:Piero di Cosimo 025.jpg|thumb|261px|Painting of Saint Anthony, a part of ''The Visitation with [[Saint Nicholas]] and Saint Anthony Abbot'' by [[Piero di Cosimo]], {{c.|lk=no|1480}}]]
For the next fifteen years, Anthony remained in the area,{{sfnp|''EB''|1911}} spending the first years as the disciple of another local [[hermit]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ButlerLives1991&quot; /&gt; There are various legends that he worked as a [[swineherd]] during this period.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Sax|first=Boria|title=How Saint Anthony Brought Fire to the World|url=http://www.h-net.org/~nilas/seasons/stanthony.html|accessdate=2013-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Anthony is sometimes considered the first monk,{{sfnp|''EB''|1911}}  and the first to initiate solitary desertification,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://orthodoxthought.sovietpedia.com/2017/03/a-few-words-about-life-and-writings-of.html|title=A few words about the life and writings of St. Anthony the Great|website=orthodoxthought.sovietpedia.com|access-date=2017-03-24|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170325025353/http://orthodoxthought.sovietpedia.com/2017/03/a-few-words-about-life-and-writings-of.html|archive-date=25 March 2017|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; but there were others before him. There were already [[asceticism|ascetic]] [[hermit]]s (the ''[[Therapeutae]]''), and loosely organized [[cenobitic]] communities were described by the [[Jewish philosophy|Jewish philosopher]] [[Philo of Alexandria]] in the 1st century&amp;nbsp;{{sc|ad}} as long established in the harsh environment of [[Lake Mareotis]] and in other less accessible regions. Philo opined that &quot;this class of persons may be met with in many places, for both Greece and barbarian countries want to enjoy whatever is perfectly good.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Philo|title=De Vita Contemplativa|trans-title={{lang-en|The Contemplative Life}} |url=http://www.earlychristianwritings.com/yonge/book34.html }}.&lt;/ref&gt; Christian ascetics such as [[Thecla]] had likewise retreated to isolated locations at the outskirts of cities. Anthony is notable for having decided to surpass this tradition and headed out into the desert proper. He left for the alkaline [[Nitrian Desert]] (later the location of the noted monasteries of [[Nitria (monastic site)|Nitria]], [[Kellia]], and [[Scetis]]) on the edge of the [[Libyan Desert|Western Desert]] about {{convert|95|km|0|abbr=on|sp=us}} west of [[Early centers of Christianity#Alexandria|Alexandria]]. He remained there for 13 years.&lt;ref name=&quot;ButlerLives1991&quot; /&gt;

Anthony maintained a very strict ascetic diet. He ate only bread, salt and water and never meat or wine.&lt;ref&gt;Watterson, Barbara. (1989). ''Coptic Egypt''. Scottish Academic Press. p. 57. {{ISBN|978-0707305561}} &quot;His food consisted of bread, salt and water: meat and wine he never touched at all. He slept upon a mat, and sometimes upon the bare ground; and never washed or cleansed his body with oil and strigil.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; He ate at most only once a day and sometimes [[Fasting|fasted]] through two or four days.&lt;ref&gt;Smedley, Edward; Rose, Hugh James; Rose, Henry John. (1845). [https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=njp.32101078163167&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=238  ''Encyclopaedia Metropolitana'']. Volume 20. London. p. 228. &quot;He never tasted food till sunset, and sometimes fasted through two or even four days; his diet was of the simplest kind, bread, salt and water, his bed was straw, or frequently bare ground.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Harmless, William. (2004). ''Desert Christians: An Introduction to the Literature of Early Monasticism''. Oxford University Press. pp. 61-62. {{ISBN|0-19-516222-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[Athanasius]], the devil fought Anthony by afflicting him with boredom, laziness, and the phantoms of women, which he overcame by the power of prayer, providing a theme for [[Christian art]]. After that, he moved to one of the tombs near his native village. There it was that the ''Life'' records those strange conflicts with demons in the shape of wild beasts, who inflicted blows upon him, and sometimes left him nearly dead.&lt;ref name=Butler&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/01553d.htm Butler, Edward Cuthbert. &quot;St. Anthony.&quot; The Catholic Encyclopedia] Vol. 1. New York: Robert Appleton Company, 1907. 19 May 2019{{PD-notice}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After fifteen years of this life, at the age of thirty-five, Anthony determined to withdraw from the habitations of men and retire in absolute solitude. He went into the desert to a mountain by the [[Nile]] called Pispir (now Der-el-Memun), opposite [[Faiyum|Arsinoë]].{{sfnp|''EB''|1911}} There he lived strictly enclosed in an old abandoned [[Ancient Rome|Roman]] fort for some 20 years.&lt;ref name=&quot;ButlerLives1991&quot; /&gt; Food was thrown to him over the wall. He was at times visited by pilgrims, whom he refused to see; but gradually a number of would-be disciples established themselves in caves and in huts around the mountain. Thus a colony of ascetics was formed, who begged Anthony to come forth and be their guide in the spiritual life. Eventually, he yielded to their importunities and, about the year 305, emerged from his retreat. To the surprise of all, he appeared to be not emaciated, but healthy in mind and body.&lt;ref name=Butler/&gt;

For five or six years he devoted himself to the instruction and organization of the great body of monks that had grown up around him; but then he once again withdrew into the inner desert that lay between the Nile and the Red Sea, near the shore of which he fixed his abode on a mountain where still stands the monastery that bears his name, Der Mar Antonios. Here he spent the last forty-five years of his life, in a seclusion, not so strict as Pispir, for he freely saw those who came to visit him, and he used to cross the desert to Pispir with considerable frequency. Amid the [[Diocletian Persecutions]], around 311 Anthony went to [[Alexandria]] and was conspicuous visiting those who were imprisoned.&lt;ref name=Butler/&gt;

=== Father of Monks ===

[[File:Vitale_da_Bologna_(14e_eeuw)_-_Vier_verhalen_van_Antonius_van_Egypte_(1340)_-_Bologna_Pinacoteca_Nazionale_-_26-04-2012_9-22-59.jpg|thumb|261px|''Four tales on Anthony the Great'' by [[Vitale da Bologna]], c. 1340, at the [[Pinacoteca Nazionale di Bologna]]]]

Anthony was not the first ascetic or hermit, but he may properly be called the &quot;Father of Monasticism&quot; in Christianity,{{sfnp|''EB''|1878}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Britannica, Saint Anthony |url=http://global.britannica.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.coptic.net/synexarion/anthony.txt|title=Saint Anthony Father of the Monks |publisher=www.coptic.net}}&lt;/ref&gt; as he organized his disciples into a community and later, following the spread of Athanasius's hagiography, was the inspiration for similar communities throughout Egypt and, elsewhere. [[Macarius the Great]] was a disciple of Anthony. Visitors traveled great distances to see the celebrated holy man. Anthony is said to have spoken to those of a spiritual disposition, leaving the task of addressing the more worldly visitors to Macarius. Macarius later founded a monastic community in the Scetic desert.&lt;ref name=Healy&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/16056d.htm Healy, Patrick. &quot;Macarius.&quot; ''The Catholic Encyclopedia''] Vol. 16 (Index). New York: The Encyclopedia Press, 1914. 19 May 2019{{PD-notice}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The fame of Anthony spread and reached [[Constantine I (emperor)|Emperor Constantine]], who wrote to him requesting his prayers. The brethren were pleased with the Emperor's letter, but Anthony was not overawed and wrote back exhorting the Emperor and his sons not to esteem this world but remember the next.&lt;ref name=crawley&gt;[http://www.ewtn.com/library/mary/antony.htm &quot;Saint Anthony of Egypt&quot;, ''Lives of the Saints'', John J. Crawley &amp; Co., Inc.]&lt;/ref&gt;

The stories of the meeting of Anthony and [[Paul of Thebes]], the raven who brought them bread, Anthony being sent to fetch the cloak given him by &quot;Athanasius the bishop&quot; to bury Paul's body in, and Paul's death before he returned, are among the familiar legends of the ''Life''. However, belief in the existence of Paul seems to have existed quite independently of the ''Life''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/11590b.htm Bacchus, Francis Joseph. &quot;St. Paul the Hermit.&quot; ''The Catholic Encyclopedia''] Vol. 11. New York: Robert Appleton Company, 1911. 19 May 2019 {{PD-notice}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 338, he left the desert temporarily to visit Alexandria to help refute the teachings of [[Arius]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ButlerLives1991&quot; /&gt;

=== Final days ===
When Saint Anthony sensed his death approaching, he commanded his disciples to give his staff to [[Macarius of Egypt|Saint Macarius]], and to give one [[Sheepskin (material)|sheepskin]] cloak to [[Saint Athanasius]] and the other sheepskin cloak to [[Saint Serapion of Thmuis|Saint Serapion]], his disciple.&lt;ref&gt;Cross, F. L., ed. (1957) ''The Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church''. Oxford U. P., p. 1242&lt;/ref&gt; Anthony was interred, according to his instructions, in a grave next to his cell.&lt;ref name=crawley/&gt;

[[File:Michelangelo Buonarroti - The Torment of Saint Anthony - Google Art Project.jpg|thumb|261px|A copy by the young [[Michelangelo]] after [[The Temptation of St Anthony (Schongauer)|an engraving]] by [[Martin Schongauer]] around 1487–1489, ''[[The Torment of Saint Anthony (Michelangelo)|The Torment of Saint Anthony]]''. Oil and tempera on panel. One of many artistic depictions of Saint Anthony's trials in the desert.]]

== Temptation ==
{{See also|Temptation of Saint Anthony in visual arts}}

Accounts of Anthony enduring supernatural temptation during his sojourn in the Eastern Desert of Egypt inspired the often-repeated subject of the temptation of St. Anthony in Western art and literature.&lt;ref&gt;Alan Shestack; ''Fifteenth century Engravings of Northern Europe''; no.37, 1967, National Gallery of Art, Washington(Catalogue), LOC 67-29080&lt;/ref&gt;

Anthony is said to have faced a series of supernatural [[temptation]]s during his pilgrimage to the desert. The first to report on the temptation was his contemporary [[Athanasius of Alexandria]]. It is possible these events, like the paintings, are full of rich metaphor or in the case of the animals of the desert, perhaps a vision or dream. Emphasis on these stories, however, did not really begin until the [[Middle Ages]] when the psychology of the individual became of greater interest.&lt;ref name=&quot;ButlerLives1991&quot; /&gt;

Some of the stories included in Saint Anthony's biography are perpetuated now mostly in paintings, where they give an opportunity for artists to depict their more lurid or bizarre interpretations. Many artists, including [[Martin Schongauer]], [[Hieronymus Bosch]], [[Dorothea Tanning]], [[Max Ernst]], [[Leonora Carrington]] and [[Salvador Dalí]], have depicted these incidents from the life of Anthony; in prose, the tale was retold and embellished by [[Gustave Flaubert]] in ''[[The Temptation of Saint Anthony (Flaubert)|The Temptation of Saint Anthony]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://flaubert.univ-rouen.fr/article.php?id=26|title=Gustave Flaubert - études critiques - Le saint-poème selon Flaubert : le délire des sens dans  La Tentation de saint Antoine|last=Leclerc|first=Yvan|website=flaubert.univ-rouen.fr|access-date=2017-09-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== The satyr and the centaur ===
[[File:The Meeting of Saint Anthony and Saint Paul, Master of the Osservanza.jpg|thumb|261px|''The Meeting of Saint Anthony and Saint Paul of Thebes'', [[Master of the Osservanza]], 15th century, with the centaur at the background.]]
Saint Anthony was on a journey in the desert to find [[Paul of Thebes|Saint Paul of Thebes]], who according to his dream was a better Hermit than he.&lt;ref name=Jero&gt;''Vitae Patrum'', Book 1a- Collected from Jerome. Ch. VI&lt;/ref&gt; Saint Anthony had been under the impression that he was the first person to ever dwell in the desert; however, due to the dream, Saint Anthony was called into the desert to find his &quot;better&quot;, Saint Paul. On his way there, he ran into two creatures in the forms of a [[centaur]] and a [[satyr]]. Although chroniclers sometimes postulated they might have been living beings, Western theology considers to have been [[demon]]s.&lt;ref name=Jero/&gt;

While traveling through the desert, Saint Anthony first found the centaur, a &quot;creature of mingled shape, half horse half man,&quot; whom he asked about directions. The creature tried to speak in an unintelligible language, but ultimately pointed with his hand the way desired, and then ran away and vanished from sight.&lt;ref name=Jero/&gt; It was interpreted as a demon trying to terrify him, or alternately a creature engendered by the desert.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Bacchus|first=Francis|title=CATHOLIC ENCYCLOPEDIA: Saint Paul the Hermit|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/11590b.htm|publisher=Robert Appleton Company|accessdate=2013-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Saint Anthony found next the satyr, a &quot;a manikin with hooked snout, horned forehead, and extremities like goats's feet.&quot; This creature was peaceful and offered him fruits, and when Saint Anthony asked who he was, the satyr replied, &quot;I'm a mortal being and one of those inhabitants of the desert whom the Gentiles deluded by various forms of error worship under the names of [[Fauns]], [[Satyrs]], and [[Incubi]]. I am sent to represent my tribe. We pray you in our behalf to entreat the favor of your Lord and ours, who, we have learnt, came once to save the world, and 'whose sound has gone forth into all the earth.'&quot; Upon hearing this, Saint Anthony was overjoyed and rejoiced over the glory of Christ. He condemned the city of [[Alexandria]] for worshipping monsters instead of God while beasts like the satyr spoke about Christ.&lt;ref name=Jero/&gt;

=== Silver and gold ===
Another time Saint Anthony was travelling in the desert and found a plate of silver coins in his path.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://oca.org/saints/lives/2015/01/17/100216-venerable-and-god-bearing-father-anthony-the-great|title=Venerable and God-bearing Father Anthony the Great|website=oca.org|language=en|access-date=2017-12-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Demons in the cave ===
Once, Saint Anthony tried hiding in a cave to escape the demons that plagued him. There were so many little demons in the cave though that Saint Anthony's servant had to carry him out because they had beaten him to death. When the hermits were gathered to Saint Anthony's corpse to mourn his death, Saint Anthony was revived. He demanded that his servants take him back to that cave where the demons had beaten him. When he got there he called out to the demons, and they came back as wild beasts to rip him to shreds. All of a sudden a bright light flashed, and the demons ran away. Saint Anthony knew that the light must have come from God, and he asked God where was he before when the demons attacked him. God replied, &quot;I was here but I would see and abide to see thy battle, and because thou hast mainly fought and well maintained thy battle, I shall make thy name to be spread through all the world.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Golden Legend: The Life of Anthony of Egypt |url=http://www.catholic-forum.com/saints/golden153.htm |accessdate=2013-01-04 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130123065522/http://www.catholic-forum.com/saints/golden153.htm |archivedate=23 January 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Veneration ==
[[File:Vaantjeantoniuswarfhuizenkleiner copy.jpg|left|thumb|Pilgrimage banners from the shrine in [[Warfhuizen]]]]
Anthony had been secretly buried on the mountain-top where he had chosen to live. His remains were reportedly discovered in 361, and transferred to [[Alexandria]]. Some time later, they were taken from Alexandria to [[Constantinople]], so that they might escape the destruction being perpetrated by invading [[Saracen]]s. In the eleventh century, the [[Byzantine emperor]] gave them to the [[French people|French]] [[Count]] Jocelin. Jocelin had them transferred to La-Motte-Saint-Didier, later renamed.&lt;ref name=&quot;ButlerLives1991&quot; /&gt; There, Jocelin undertook to build a church to house the remains, but died before the church was even started. The building was finally erected in 1297 and became a centre of veneration and pilgrimage, known as [[Saint-Antoine-l'Abbaye]]. 

Anthony is credited with assisting in a number of miraculous healings, primarily from [[ergotism]], which became known as &quot;St. Anthony's Fire&quot;. He was credited by two local noblemen of assisting them in recovery from the disease. They then founded the [[Hospital Brothers of St. Anthony]] in honor of him, who specialized in nursing the victims of skin diseases.&lt;ref name=&quot;ButlerLives1991&quot; /&gt;
[[File:SAntoine Abbaye 01.jpg|thumb|right|250px|[[Saint-Antoine-l'Abbaye]], [[Isère]]]]

Veneration of Anthony in the East is more restrained. There are comparatively few icons and paintings of him. He is, however, regarded as the &quot;first master of the desert and the pinnacle of holy monks&quot;, and there are monastic communities of the Maronite, Chaldean, and Orthodox churches which state that they follow his monastic rule.&lt;ref name=&quot;ButlerLives1991&quot; /&gt; During the [[Middle Ages]], Anthony, along with [[Quirinus of Neuss]], [[Pope Cornelius|Cornelius]] and [[Hubertus]], was venerated as one of the [[Four Holy Marshals]] (''Vier Marschälle Gottes'') in the [[Rhineland]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Quirinus von Rom|url=http://www.heiligenlexikon.de/BiographienQ/Quirinus_von_Rom_von_Neuss.htm|accessdate=25 April 2012|trans-title={{lang-en|Quirinus of Rome}}|language=German}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
[[Image:Antoniusaltaar.jpg|thumb|250px|The former main altar of the hermitage church in [[Warfhuizen]] in the Netherlands with a mural of Anthony the Abbot and a [[reliquary]] with some of his [[relic]]s. Since then they have been moved to a new golden shrine on a side altar]]

Though Anthony himself did not organize or create a monastery, a community grew around him based on his example of living an [[asceticism|ascetic]] and isolated life. Athanasius' biography helped propagate Anthony's ideals. Athanasius writes, &quot;For monks, the life of Anthony is a sufficient example of [[asceticism]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ButlerLives1991&quot; /&gt;

=== Coptic literature ===
{{Christian mysticism}}
Examples of purely [[Coptic literature]] are the works of Saint Anthony and Saint [[Pachomius]], who only spoke Coptic, and the sermons and preachings of [[Saint Shenouda the Archmandrite]], who chose to only write in Coptic. The earliest original writings in [[Coptic language]] were the letters by Saint Anthony. During the 3rd and 4th centuries many ecclesiastics and monks wrote in Coptic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Coptic Literature|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/136924/Coptic-literature|accessdate=2013-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== In popular literature ==
The main character in the [[Hervey Allen]] novel ''[[Anthony Adverse]]'', and the [[Anthony Adverse|1936 film of the same name]], is an abandoned child who is placed in a [[foundling wheel]] on the saint's feast day, and given the name Anthony in his honor.{{Citation needed|date=May 2019}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Saints}}
* [[Coptic Saints]]
* [[Chariton the Confessor]] (mid-3rd century-c. 350), contemporary monk in the Judaean desert
* [[Desert Fathers]] and [[Desert Mothers]], early Christian hermits, ascetics, and monks who lived mainly in the Scetes desert of Egypt beginning around the third century AD
* [[Hilarion]] (291–371), anchorite and saint considered by some to be the founder of Palestinian monasticism
* [[Monastery of Saint Anthony]], Egypt
* [[Pachomius the Great]] (c. 292–348), Egyptian saint generally recognized as the founder of Christian cenobitic monasticism
* [[Patron saints of ailments, illness and dangers]]
* [[Paul of Thebes]] (c. 226/7-c. 341), known as &quot;Paul, the First Hermit&quot;, who preceded both Anthony and Chariton
* [[St. Anthony Hall]], American fraternity and literary society
* [[Portal:Catholic Church/Patron Archive/January 17|Saint Anthony the Great, patron saint archive]]

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== References ==
* {{cite EB9 |mode=cs2 |wstitle=Saint Anthony |volume=2  |ref={{harvid|EB|1878}} |page=106 }}
* {{cite EB1911 |mode=cs2 |wstitle=Anthony, Saint |volume=2 |ref={{harvid|EB|1911}} |pages=96–97 }}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Saint Anthony the Great|Anthony the Great}}
{{Wikiquote}}
* [http://www.wdl.org/en/item/7084 &quot;Spiritual Considerations on the Life of Saint Antony the Great&quot;] is a manuscript, from 1864, in Arabic, that is a translation of a Latin work about the life of Saint Anthony
* [http://www.christianiconography.info/anthonyAbbot.html &quot;Saint Anthony Abbot&quot;] at the [http://www.christianiconography.info Christian Iconography] website
* [http://www.christianiconography.info/goldenLegend/anthonyAbbot.htm &quot;Of the Life of Saint Anthony&quot;] from Caxton's translation of the Golden Legend
* [http://www.stpetersbasilica.info/Exterior/Colonnades/Saints/St%20Anthony%20abbot-128/StAnthony-Abbot.htm Colonnade Statue in St Peter's Square]
* {{librivox book | title=Life of Anthony | author=Athanasius of Alexandria}}

{{Coptic saints|state=collapsed}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Anthony The Great}}
[[Category:Anthony the Great| ]]
[[Category:356 deaths]]
[[Category:3rd-century people of Roman Egypt]]
[[Category:4th-century Egyptian people]]
[[Category:Saints from Roman Egypt]]
[[Category:Egyptian hermits]]
[[Category:Egyptian centenarians]]
[[Category:Egyptian Christian monks]]
[[Category:3rd-century Christian saints]]
[[Category:4th-century Christian saints]]
[[Category:3rd-century Romans]]
[[Category:4th-century Romans]]
[[Category:4th-century Christian theologians]]
[[Category:Angelic visionaries]]
[[Category:4th-century Christian monks]]
[[Category:3rd-century Christian monks]]
[[Category:4th-century writers]]
[[Category:Antonii]]
[[Category:250s births]]</text>
      <sha1>mbpo7babirr89dc6jwb1imqrybkc1kw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
