  <page>
    <title>Amblypoda</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3250</id>
    <revision>
      <id>774869519</id>
      <parentid>730556037</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-04-11T05:01:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DavidBrooks-AWB</username>
        <id>20962961</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Specific EB1911 attribution using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{multiple issues|
{{One source|date=February 2012}}
{{update|date=January 2014}}
}}
'''Amblypoda''' is a taxonomic hypothesis uniting a group of extinct, herbivorous [[mammal]]s. They were considered a suborder of the primitive [[ungulate]] mammals and have since been shown to represent a [[polyphyletic]] group.

==Characteristics==
The Amblypoda take their name from their short and stumpy feet, which were furnished with five toes each and supported massive pillar-like limbs. The brain cavity was extremely small and insignificant in comparison to the bodily mass, which was equal to that of the largest [[rhinoceros]]es. These animals were descendants of the small ancestral ungulates that retained all the primitive characteristics of the latter, accompanied by a huge increase in body size.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;&gt;{{EB1911|inline=y|wstitle=Amblypoda|volume=1|pages=795-796|first=Richard|last=Lydekker|authorlink=Richard Lydekker}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Amblypoda were confined to the [[Paleocene]] and [[Eocene]] periods and occurred in [[North America]], [[Asia]] (especially [[Mongolia]]) and [[Europe]]. The cheek teeth were short-crowned ([[brachyodont]]), with the tubercles more-or-less completely fused into transverse ridges, or cross-crests ([[lophodont]] type), and the total number of teeth was in one case the typical 44, but in another was fewer. The [[vertebra]] of the neck unite on nearly flat surfaces, the [[humerus]] had lost the foramen, or perforation, at the lower end, and the third trochanter to the [[femur]] may have also been wanting. In the forelimb, the upper and lower series of [[carpal]] (finger) bones scarcely alternated, but in the hind foot, the astragalus overlapped the cuboid, while the [[fibula]], which was quite distinct from the [[tibia]] (as was the [[radius (bone)|radius]] from the [[ulna]] in the forelimb), articulated with both astragalus and calcaneum.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

==Types of amblypods==
The most generalized type was ''[[Coryphodon]]'', representing the family [[Coryphodontidae]], from the lower Eocene of Europe and North America, in which there were 44 teeth and no horn-like excrescences on the long skull, while the femur had a third trochanter. The canines were somewhat elongated and were followed by a short gap in each jaw, and the cheek-teeth were adapted for succulent food. The length of the body reached about six feet in some cases.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

In the middle Eocene formations of North America occurred the more specialized ''[[Uintatherium]]'' (or ''Dinoceras''), typifying the family [[Uintatheriidae]]. Uintatheres were huge creatures with long narrow skulls, of which the elongated facial portion carried three pairs of bony horn-cores, probably covered with short horns in life, the hind-pair having been much the largest. The dental formula was i. 0/3, c. 1/1, p.&amp;nbsp;3/3·4, m. 3/3, the upper canines having been long sabre-like weapons, protected by a descending flange on each side of the lower front jaw.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

In the basal Eocene of North America, the Amblypoda were represented by extremely primitive, five-toed, small ungulates such as ''[[Periptychus]]'' and ''[[Pantolambda]]'', each of these typifying a family{{Vague|date=April 2009}}. The full typical series of 44 teeth was developed in each, but whereas in the [[Periptychidae]], the upper molars were [[bunodont]] and [[tritubercular]], in the [[Pantolambdidae]], they had assumed a [[selenodont]] structure. [[Creodonta|Creodont]] characters were displayed in the skeleton.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

==Current taxonomy of animals once classified in Amblypoda==
Few authorities recognize Amblypoda in modern classifications.  The following mammals were once considered part of this group:

*Order Pholidota ([[pangolin]]s)
*Order [[Pantodonta]]
**Family [[Wangliidae]]
**Family [[Harpyodidae]]
**Family [[Bemalambdidae]]
**Family [[Pastoralodontidae]]
**Family [[Titanoideidae]]
**Family [[Pantolambdidae]] (including ''[[Pantolambda]]'')
**Family [[Barylambdidae]]
**Family [[Cyriacotheriidae]]
**Family [[Pantolambdodontidae]]
**Family [[Coryphodontidae]] (including ''[[Coryphodon]]'')
*Order [[Dinocerata]]
**Family [[Uintatheriidae]] (includes ''[[Uintatherium]]'', ''Eobasileus'', ''Tetheopsis'', etc.  ''[[Gobiatherium]]'' is sometimes placed in its own family.)
*Order [[Condylarthra]]
**Family [[Hyopsodontidae]]
**Family [[Mioclaenidae]]
**Family [[Phenacodontidae]]
**Family [[Periptychidae]] (including ''[[Periptychus]]'')
**Family [[Peligrotheriidae]]
**Family [[Didolodontidae]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Prehistoric placental mammals]]
[[Category:Eocene mammals]]</text>
      <sha1>7y7a2y0qbw4d5mu5hctywnf0naj9d3i</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
