  <page>
    <title>Mexican tetra</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3209</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941946282</id>
      <parentid>941943807</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-21T16:25:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Langcliffe</username>
        <id>7799163</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/96.64.69.249|96.64.69.249]] ([[User talk:96.64.69.249|talk]]) to last revision by 46.253.36.76 ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Blind cave fish|cavefish in general|cavefish}}
{{Speciesbox
 | name = Mexican tetra
 | image = Mexican Tetra (Astyanax mexicanus) (2687270083).jpg
 | image2 = Astyanax mexicanus 01.jpg
 | image2_caption = Mexican tetra, normal form (above) and blind cave form (below)
 | status = LC
 | status_system = IUCN3.1
 | status_ref = &lt;ref name=IUCN&gt;{{cite journal | author = NatureServe | title = ''Astyanax mexicanus'' | journal = [[IUCN Red List of Threatened Species]] | volume= 2013 | page = e.T62191A3109229 | year = 2013 | doi = 10.2305/IUCN.UK.2013-1.RLTS.T62191A3109229.en }}&lt;/ref&gt;
 | taxon = Astyanax mexicanus
 | authority = ([[Filippo de' Filippi|De Filippi]], 1853)
 | range_map = PeixecegoMAPA.gif
 | range_map_caption = Approximate range in red
 | synonyms_ref = &lt;ref&gt;http://www.fishbase.se/Nomenclature/SynonymsList.php?ID=2740&amp;SynCode=23916&amp;GenusName=Astyanax&amp;SpeciesName=mexicanus&lt;/ref&gt; 
 | synonyms = {{Specieslist|Tetragonopterus mexicanus|De Filippi, 1853|Astyanax fasciatus mexicanus|(De Filippi, 1853)|Astyanax argentatus|Baird &amp; Girard, 1854|Tetragonopterus brevimanus|Günther, 1864|Tetragonopterus petenensis|Günther, 1864|Tetragonopterus fulgens|Bocourt, 1868|Tetragonopterus nitidus|Bocourt, 1868|Tetragonopterus streetsii|Cope, 1872}}
}}
The '''Mexican tetra''' (''Astyanax mexicanus''), also known as the '''blind cave fish''', '''blind cave characin''', and '''blind cave tetra''', is a [[freshwater]] [[fish]] of the [[family (biology)|family]] [[Characidae]] of the [[order (biology)|order]] [[Characiformes]].&lt;ref name=&quot;fishbase&quot;&gt;{{FishBase |genus=Astyanax |species=mexicanus |year=2015 |month=October}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;itis&quot;&gt;{{ITIS |id=162850 |taxon=''Astyanax mexicanus'' |accessdate=1 July 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[type species]] of its [[genus]], it is native to the [[Nearctic]] [[ecozone]], originating in the lower [[Rio Grande]] and the [[Nueces River|Neueces]] and [[Pecos River]]s in [[Texas]], as well as the central and eastern parts of Mexico.&lt;ref name=&quot;fishbase&quot;/&gt;

Growing to a maximum [[total length]] of {{convert|12|cm|in|abbr=on}}, the Mexican tetra is of typical characin shape, with unremarkable, drab coloration.&lt;ref name=&quot;fishbase&quot;/&gt; Its [[Blind fish|blind]] cave form, however, is notable for having no eyes or pigment; it has a pinkish-white color to its body (resembling an [[Albinism in biology|albino]]).&lt;ref name=Keene2016&gt;{{cite book | authors=Keene; Yoshizawa; and McGaugh | title=Biology and Evolution of the Mexican Cavefish | year=2016 | pages=68–69, 77–87 | isbn=978-0-12-802148-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This fish, especially the blind variant, is reasonably popular among [[aquarist]]s.&lt;ref name=seriouslyfish&gt;{{cite web | publisher=SeriouslyFish | title=Astyanax mexicanus | url=http://www.seriouslyfish.com/species/astyanax-mexicanus/ | accessdate=2 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''A. mexicanus'' is a peaceful species that spends most of its time in midlevel water above the rocky and sandy bottoms of pools and backwaters of creeks and rivers of its native environment. Coming from a [[subtropical]] climate, it prefers water with 6.5&amp;ndash;8 [[pH]], a [[Hard water|hardness]] of up to 30 [[dGH]], and a temperature range of {{convert|20|to|25|C|F}}. In the winter, some populations migrate to warmer waters. Its natural diet consists of [[crustacean]]s, [[insect]]s, and [[annelid]]s, although in captivity it is [[omnivorous]].&lt;ref name=&quot;fishbase&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=seriouslyfish/&gt;

The Mexican tetra has been treated as a subspecies of ''[[Astayanax faciatus|A. fasciatus]]'', but this is not widely accepted.&lt;ref name=&quot;fishbase&quot; /&gt; Additionally, the blind cave form is sometimes recognized as a separate species, ''[[Astyanax jordani|A. jordani]]'', but this directly contradicts [[Phylogenetics|phylogenetic]] evidence.&lt;ref name=Keene2016/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;gross12&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Gross |first=J.B. |title=The complex origin of Astyanax cave fish |journal=BMC Evolutionary Biology |date=June 2012 |volume=12 |pages=105 |doi=10.1186/1471-2148-12-105 |pmid=22747496 |pmc=3464594}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Jeffrey2009&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Jeffery |first1=W |year=2009 |title = Regressive evolution in Astyanax cavefish |url= |journal = Annu. Rev. Genet. |volume = 43 |issue = |pages = 25–47 |doi=10.1146/annurev-genet-102108-134216| pmid = 19640230 |pmc = 3594788}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Bradic2012&gt;{{cite journal |last1 = Bradic |first1 = M. | last2 = Beerli |first2 = P. |last3 = Garcia-de Leon |first3 = F. J. |last4 = Esquivel-Bobadilla |first4 = S. |last5 = Borowsky |first5 = R. L. |year = 2012 |title = Gene flow and population structure in the Mexican blind cavefish complex (Astyanax mexicanus) |url = |journal = BMC Evol. Biol. |volume = 12 |issue = |page = 9 | doi=10.1186/1471-2148-12-9 |pmid = 22269119 |pmc = 3282648 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Dowling2002&gt;{{cite journal |last1 = Dowling | first1 = T. E. |last2 = Martasian |first2 = D. P. |last3 = Jeffery |first3 = W. R. |year = 2002 |title = Evidence for multiple genetic forms with similar eyeless phenotypes in the blind cavefish, Astyanax mexicanus |url= |journal = Mol. Biol. Evol. |volume=19 |issue=4 |pages=446–455 |doi=10.1093/oxfordjournals.molbev.a004100 |pmid = 11919286 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Strecker2004&gt;{{cite journal |last1 = Strecker |first1 = U. |last2 = Faúndez |first2 = V. H. |last3 = Wilkens |first3 = H. |year = 2004 |title = Phylogeography of surface and cave Astyanax (Teleostei) from Central and North America based on cytochrome b sequence data | url = |journal = Mol. Phylogenet. Evol. |volume = 33 |issue = 2 |pages = 469–481 |doi=10.1016/j.ympev.2004.07.001 |pmid = 15336680 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Blind cave form==
[[Image:Mexican Tetra as Blind Cave Fish.jpg|thumb|left|225px|Mexican tetra in blind cave fish form]]
''A. mexicanus'' is famous for its blind [[Cavefish|cave form]], which is known by such names as '''blind cave tetra''', '''blind tetra''' (leading to easy confusion with the Brazilian ''[[Stygichthys typhlops]]''), '''blind cave characin''' and '''blind cavefish'''. Depending on the exact population, cave forms can have degenerated [[visual perception|sight]] or have total loss of sight and even their [[eye]]s. The fish in the Pachón caves have lost their eyes completely whilst the fish from the Micos cave only have limited sight.&lt;ref name=&quot;gross&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|author=Moran|author2=Softley|author3=Warrant|last-author-amp=yes|title=The energetic cost of vision and the evolution of eyeless Mexican cavefish|journal=Science Advances|date=2015|volume=1|issue=8|pages=e1500363|doi=10.1126/sciadv.1500363|pmid=26601263|pmc=4643782}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Cave fish and surface fish are able to produce fertile offspring.&lt;ref name=&quot;gross&quot;/&gt;

These fish can still, however, find their way around by means of their [[lateral line]]s, which are highly sensitive to fluctuating [[water pressure]].&lt;ref name=&quot;yoshizawa&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Yoshizawa|first=M.|author2=Yamamoto, Y.|author3= O'Quin, K. E.|author4= Jeffery, W. R.|title=Evolution of an adaptive behavior and its sensory receptors promotes eye regression in blind cavefish|journal=BMC Biology|date=December 2012|volume=10|pages=108|doi=10.1186/1741-7007-10-108|pmid=23270452|pmc=3565949}}&lt;/ref&gt; Currently, about 30 cave populations are known, dispersed over three geographically distinct areas in a [[karst]] region of [[San Luis Potosí]] and far southern [[Tamaulipas]], northeastern Mexico.&lt;ref name=&quot;gross12&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Romero2009&gt;{{cite book | author=Romero, A. | title=Cave Biology: Life in Darkness | year=2009 | publisher=Cambridge University Press |pages=147–148 | isbn=978-0-521-82846-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Espinasa2001&gt;{{cite journal | authors=Espinasa; Rivas-Manzano; and Espinosa Pérez | title=A New Blind Cave Fish Population of Genus Astyanax: Geography, Morphology and Behavior |journal=Environmental Biology of Fishes | year=2001 | volume=62 | issue=1 | pages=339–344 | doi=10.1023/A:1011852603162}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among the various cave population are  at least three with only full cave forms (blind and without pigment),  at least eleven with cave, &quot;normal&quot; and intermediate forms, and at least one with both cave and &quot;normal&quot; forms but no intermediates.&lt;ref name=Romero2009/&gt; Studies suggest at least two distinct genetic [[Lineage (evolution)|lineages]] occur among the blind populations, and the current distribution of populations arose by at least five independent invasions.&lt;ref name=&quot;gross12&quot;/&gt;

The eyed and eyeless forms of ''A. mexicanus'', being members of the same species, are closely related and can interbreed&lt;ref name=&quot;retaux&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Retaux|first=S.|author2=Casane, D.|title=Evolution of eye development in the darkness of caves: adaptation, drift, or both?|journal=Evodevo|date=September 2013|volume=4|pages=26|doi=10.1186/2041-9139-4-26|pmc=3849642|pmid=24079393}}&lt;/ref&gt; making this species an excellent [[model organism]] for examining [[convergent evolution|convergent]] and [[parallel evolution]], regressive evolution in cave animals, and the genetic basis of regressive traits.&lt;ref name=&quot;soares&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Soares|first=D.|author2=Niemiller, M. L.|title=Sensory Adaptations of Fishes to Subterranean Environments|journal=BioScience|date=April 2013|volume=63|issue=4|pages=274–283|doi=10.1525/bio.2013.63.4.7}}&lt;/ref&gt; This, combined with the ease of maintaining the species in captivity, has made it the most studied cavefish and likely also the most studied [[List of troglobites|cave organism]] overall.&lt;ref name=Romero2009/&gt;

The blind and colorless cave form of ''A. mexicanus'' is sometimes recognized as a separate species, ''[[Astyanax jordani|A. jordani]]'', but this leaves the remaining ''A. mexicanus'' as a [[paraphyletic]] species and ''A. jordani'' as [[polyphyletic]].&lt;ref name=Keene2016/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;gross12&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Jeffrey2009/&gt;&lt;ref name=Bradic2012/&gt;&lt;ref name=Dowling2002/&gt;&lt;ref name=Strecker2004/&gt; The Cueva Chica Cave in the southern part of the Sierra del Abra system is the [[Type locality (biology)|type locality]] for ''A. jordani''.&lt;ref name=Keene2016/&gt; Other blind populations were initially also recognized as separate species, including ''antrobius'' described in 1946 from the Pachón Cave and ''hubbsi'' described in 1947 from the Los Sabinos Cave (both subsequently merged into ''jordani''/''mexicanus'').&lt;ref name=Keene2016/&gt; The most [[Genetic divergence|divergent]] cave population is the one in Los Sabinos.&lt;ref name=Keene2016/&gt;&lt;ref name=Coghill2014&gt;{{cite journal | authors=Coghill; Hulsey; Chaves-Campos; García de Leon; and Johnson | title=Next Generation Phylogeography of Cave and Surface Astyanax mexicanus|journal=Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution | year=2014 | volume=79 | pages=368–374 | doi=10.1016/j.ympev.2014.06.029| pmid=25014568}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another cave-adapted population of ''Astyanax'', varying from blind and depigmented to individuals showing intermediate features, is known from the Granadas Cave, part of the [[Balsas River]] drainage in [[Guerrero]], southern Mexico, but it is a part of ''[[Astyanax aeneus|A. aeneus]]'' (itself sometimes included in ''A. mexicanus'').&lt;ref name=Keene2016/&gt;&lt;ref name=Espinasa2001/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | authors=Jeffery; Strickler; and Yamamoto | title=To See or Not to See: Evolution of Eye Degeneration in Mexican Blind Cavefish | journal=Integr Comp Biol | year=2003 | volume=43 | issue=4 | pages=531–541 | doi=10.1093/icb/43.4.531| pmid=21680461 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Evolution research===
The surface and cave forms of the Mexican tetra have proven powerful subjects for scientists studying [[evolution]].&lt;ref name=&quot;retaux&quot; /&gt; When the surface-dwelling ancestors of current cave populations entered the subterranean environment, the change in ecological conditions rendered their [[phenotype]]—which included many biological functions dependent on the presence of light—subject to [[natural selection]] and [[genetic drift]].&lt;ref name=&quot;soares&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;wilkens&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Wilkens|first=H|title=Genes, modules and the evolution of cave fish|journal=Heredity|date=November 2012|volume=105|issue=5|pages=413–422|doi=10.1038/hdy.2009.184|pmid=20068586}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of the most striking changes to evolve was the loss of eyes. This is referred to as a &quot;regressive trait&quot; because the surface fish that originally colonized caves possessed eyes.&lt;ref name=&quot;retaux&quot; /&gt; In addition to regressive traits, cave forms evolved &quot;constructive traits&quot;. In contrast to regressive traits, the purpose or benefit of constructive traits is generally accepted.&lt;ref name=&quot;soares&quot; /&gt; Active research focuses on the mechanisms driving the evolution of regressive traits, such as the loss of eyes, in ''A. mexicanus''. Recent studies have produced evidence that the mechanism may be direct selection,&lt;ref name=&quot;Goss08&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Protas|first=M|author2=Tabansky, I.|author3= Conrad, M.|author4= Gross, J. B. |author5=Vidal, O.|author6= Tabin, C. J. |author7=Borowsky, R.|title=Multi-trait evolution in a cave fish, ''Astyanax mexicanus''|journal=Evolution &amp; Development|date= April 2008|volume=10|issue=2|pages=196–209|doi=10.1111/j.1525-142x.2008.00227.x|pmid=18315813}}&lt;/ref&gt; or indirect selection through [[Antagonistic pleiotropy hypothesis|antagonistic pleiotropy]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Jeffery|first=WR|title=Regressive Evolution in Astyanax Cavefish|journal=Annual Review of Genetics|year=2009|volume=43|pages=25–47|doi=10.1146/annurev-genet-102108-134216|pmc=3594788|pmid=19640230}}&lt;/ref&gt; rather than genetic drift and neutral mutation, the traditionally favored hypothesis for regressive evolution.&lt;ref name=&quot;wilkens&quot; /&gt;

The blind form of the Mexican tetra is different from the surface-dwelling form in a number of ways, including having unpigmented skin, having a better [[olfaction|olfactory]] sense by having [[taste bud]]s all over its head, and by being able to store four times more energy as fat, allowing it to deal with irregular food supplies more effectively.&lt;ref&gt;Helfman G., Collette B., &amp; Facey D.: The Diversity of Fishes, Blackwell Publishing, p 315, 1997, {{ISBN|0-86542-256-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Darwin said of sightless fish:{{Quote|By the time that an animal had reached, after numberless generations, the deepest recesses, disuse will on this view have more or less perfectly obliterated its eyes, and natural selection will often have effected other changes, such as an increase in the length of antennae or palpi, as compensation for blindness.|Charles Darwin|Origin of Species (1859)}}

Modern genetics has made clear that the lack of use does not, in itself, necessitate a feature's disappearance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1134/is_5_114/ai_n13811128 |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2007-02-13 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060515160857/http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1134/is_5_114/ai_n13811128 |archivedate=2006-05-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In this context, the positive genetic benefits have to be considered, i.e., what advantages are obtained by cave-dwelling tetras by losing their eyes? Possible explanations include:
*Not developing eyes allows the individual more energy for growth and reproduction. However the species does use other methods to locate food and detect danger, which also consume energy that would be conserved if it had eyes or transparent eyelids.
*There remains less chance of accidental damage and infection, since the previously useless and exposed organ is sealed with a flap of protective skin. It is unknown why this species did not develop transparent skin or eyelids instead, as some species of reptiles did.
*The lack of eyes disables the &quot;body clock&quot;, which is controlled by periods of light and dark, conserving energy. However sunlight does have minimal impact on the &quot;body clock&quot; in caves.{{cn|date=April 2018}}

Another likely explanation for the loss of its eyes is that of selective neutrality and genetic drift; in the dark environment of the cave, the eyes are neither advantageous nor disadvantageous and thus any genetic factors that might impair the eyes (or their development) can take hold with no consequence on the individual or species. Because there is no selection pressure for sight in this environment, any number of genetic abnormalities that give rise to the damage or loss of eyes could proliferate among the population with no effect on the fitness of the population.

Among some [[creation-evolution controversy|creationists]], the cave tetra is seen as evidence 'against' evolution. One argument claims this is an instance of &quot;[[Biological devolution|devolution]]&quot;—showing an evolutionary trend of decreasing complexity. But evolution is a non-directional process, and while increased complexity is a common effect, there is no reason why evolution cannot tend towards simplicity if that makes an organism better suited to its environment.&lt;ref&gt;Dawkins, R.: Climbing Mount Improbable, W. W. Norton &amp; Co, 1997, {{ISBN|0-393-31682-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Inhibition of the [[Hsp90|HSP90 protein]] has a dramatic effect in the development of the blind tetra.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Rohner|first1=N.|last2=Jarosz|first2=D. F.|last3=Kowalko|first3=J. E.|last4=Yoshizawa|first4=M.|last5=Jeffery|first5=W. R.|last6=Borowsky|first6=R. L.|last7=Lindquist|first7=S.|last8=Tabin|first8=C. J. |year=2013 |title=Cryptic variation in morphological evolution: HSP90 as a capacitor for loss of eyes in cavefish | journal=Science|volume=342 |issue=6164 |pages=1372–1375 |doi=10.1126/science.1240276|hdl=1721.1/96714 |pmid=24337296 |pmc=4004346}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===In the aquarium===
The blind cave tetras seen in the [[aquarium]] trade are all based on stock collected in the Cueva Chica Cave in the southern part of the Sierra del Abra system in 1936.&lt;ref name=Keene2016/&gt; These were sent to an aquarium company in Texas, who soon started to distribute them to aquarists. Since then, these have been [[selectively bred]] for their [[troglomorphic]] traits.&lt;ref name=Keene2016/&gt; Today large numbers are bred at commercial facilities, especially in Asia.&lt;ref name=seriouslyfish/&gt;

The blind cave tetra is a hardy species.&lt;ref name=Keene2016/&gt; Their lack of sight does not hinder their ability to get food. They prefer subdued lighting with a rocky substrate, like gravel, mimicking their natural environment. They become semi-aggressive as they age, and are by nature schooling fish.{{Citation needed|date=January 2014}} Experiments have shown that keeping these fish in bright aquarium set-ups has no effect on the development of the skin flap that forms over their eyes as they grow.

==See also==
*[[List of freshwater aquarium fish species]]

==References==
{{Reflist|25em}}

{{Taxonbar|from=Q135378}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mexican Tetra}}
[[Category:Tetras]]
[[Category:Astyanax (fish)]]
[[Category:Freshwater fish of Mexico]]
[[Category:Freshwater fish of the United States]]
[[Category:Cave fish]]
[[Category:Blind animals]]
[[Category:Least concern biota of the United States]]
[[Category:Fish described in 1853]]
[[Category:Taxa named by Filippo De Filippi]]</text>
      <sha1>fb27m82fwvtywpvz2hg30b3l8n1iyf2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
