  <page>
    <title>Attribution of recent climate change</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3201</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940989510</id>
      <parentid>940180950</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-15T22:57:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>RCraig09</username>
        <id>8747689</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* top */ updating image with more condensed single-panel version: [[File:2017 Global warming attribution - based on NCA4 Fig 3.3 - single-panel version.png]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi-indef}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2019}}
[[File:2017 Global warming attribution - based on NCA4 Fig 3.3 - single-panel version.png|thumb|upright=1.5| Accumulation in the atmosphere of [[greenhouse gas]]es, especially those resulting from humans burning [[fossil fuel]]s, has been found to be the predominant cause of global warming and climate change.]]&lt;!-- Source is in small text at the bottom of the chart. --&gt;

'''Attribution of recent climate change''' is the effort to scientifically ascertain mechanisms responsible for [[global warming|recent global warming and related climate changes on Earth]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.nasa.gov/topics/earth/features/climate_by_any_other_name.html|title=NASA – What's in a Name? Global Warming vs. Climate Change|website=nasa.gov|access-date=29 October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The effort has focused on changes observed during the period of [[instrumental temperature record]], particularly in the last 50 years. This is the period when human activity has grown fastest and observations of the [[troposphere|atmosphere above the surface]] have become available. According to the [[Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change]] (IPCC), it is &quot;extremely likely&quot;&lt;ref&gt;The IPCC defines &quot;extremely likely&quot; as indicating a probability of 95 to 100%, based on an expert assessment of all the available evidence. {{harvnb|IPCC AR5 WG1|2013}}, Section: [http://www.climatechange2013.org/images/report/WG1AR5_SPM_FINAL.pdf Summary for Policymakers (finalized version)], page 4, footnote 2.
&lt;/ref&gt; that human influence was the dominant cause of global warming between 1951 and 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|IPCC AR5 WG1|2013}}, Section: [http://www.climatechange2013.org/images/report/WG1AR5_SPM_FINAL.pdf Summary for Policymakers (finalized version)], Chapter: D.3 Detection and Attribution of Climate Change, page 17.  &lt;/ref&gt; The best estimate is that observed warming since 1951 has been entirely human caused.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The likely range of the human contribution to the global mean temperature increase over the period 1951–2010 is 1.1° to 1.4°F (0.6° to 0.8°C), and the central estimate of the observed warming of 1.2°F (0.65°C) lies within this range (high confidence). This translates to a likely human contribution of 93%–123% of the observed 1951–2010 change.&quot; [https://science2017.globalchange.gov/chapter/3/ Chapter 3: Detection and Attribution of Climate Change], ''Climate Science Special Report '', U.S. Global Change Research Program.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of the main human activities that contribute to global warming are:&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|IPCC AR4 WG1|2007}}, chapter &quot;[https://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/ch9s9-7.html 9.7  Combining Evidence of Anthropogenic Climate Change]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* increasing [[atmosphere|atmospheric]] concentrations of [[greenhouse gas]]es, for a warming effect
* global changes to land surface, such as [[deforestation]], for a warming effect
* increasing atmospheric concentrations of [[aerosol]]s, mainly for a cooling effect

In addition to human activities, some natural mechanisms can also cause [[climate change]], including for example, [[climate oscillation]]s, changes in [[Solar activity and climate|solar activity]], and [[volcano|volcanic]] activity.

Multiple lines of evidence support attribution of recent climate change to human activities:&lt;ref name=&quot;epa endangerment fact sheet&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://nepis.epa.gov/Exe/ZyPURL.cgi?Dockey=P100BVZS.txt|title=EPA's Endangerment Finding Climate Change Facts|last=&lt;!--not specified--&gt;|year=2009|website=National Service Center for Environmental Publications (NSCEP)|id=Report ID: 430F09086|access-date=22 December 2017}} 
&lt;/ref&gt;
* A [[physics|physical]] understanding of the [[climate]] system: greenhouse gas concentrations have increased and their warming properties are well-established.
* Historical estimates of past climate changes suggest that the recent changes in global surface temperature are unusual.
* Computer-based [[climate model]]s are unable to replicate the observed warming unless human greenhouse gas emissions are included.
* Natural forces alone (such as solar and volcanic activity) cannot explain the observed warming.

The IPCC's attribution of recent global warming to human activities is a view shared by the scientific community,&lt;ref name=nrc2001&gt;{{cite book
|year=2001
|chapter=Summary
|title=Climate Change Science: An Analysis of Some Key Questions
|publisher=[[National Academies Press]]
 | location=Washington, D.C., USA
|authors=Committee on the Science of Climate Change, US National Research Council
|chapter-url=http://www.nap.edu/openbook.php?record_id=10139&amp;page=1
|pages=1–3
|isbn=0-309-07574-2
|accessdate=20 May 2011| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20110605132107/http://www.nap.edu/openbook.php?record_id=10139&amp;page=1| archivedate= 5 June 2011 | url-status= live}} &quot;The IPCC's conclusion that most of the observed warming of the last 50 years is likely to have been due to the increase in greenhouse gas concentrations accurately reflects the current thinking of the scientific community on this issue&quot; (page 3).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=nrc2008/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{harvnb|Cook|others|2013}}
&lt;/ref&gt; and is also supported by 196 other scientific organizations worldwide&lt;ref name=&quot;opr list of scientific organizations&quot;&gt;
{{harvnb|OPR|n.d.}}
&lt;/ref&gt; (see also: [[Scientific consensus on climate change]]).

==Background==
[[File:Mauna Loa CO2 monthly mean concentration.svg|thumb|The [[Keeling Curve]] shows the long-term increase of atmospheric [[carbon dioxide]] ({{CO2}}) concentrations from 1958–2018. Monthly {{CO2}} measurements display seasonal oscillations in an upward trend. Each year's maximum occurs during the [[Northern Hemisphere]]'s late spring.]]

{{Main article|Climate change#Causes}}
Factors affecting Earth's climate can be broken down into [[Global warming#Feedback|feedbacks]] and forcings.&lt;ref name=nrc2008&gt;{{cite book
 |year=2008 
 |title=Understanding and responding to climate change: Highlights of National Academies Reports, 2008 edition 
 |publisher=National Academy of Sciences 
 |location=500 Fifth St. N.W., Washington, D.C. 20001 
 |author=US National Research Council 
 |url=http://americasclimatechoices.org/climate_change_2008_final.pdf 
 |accessdate=20 May 2011 
 |url-status=dead 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111213210836/http://americasclimatechoices.org/climate_change_2008_final.pdf 
 |archivedate=13 December 2011 
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;{{Rp|7|date=November 2012}} A forcing is something that is imposed externally on the [[climate system]]. External forcings include natural phenomena such as volcanic eruptions and variations in the sun's output.&lt;ref&gt;Le Treut ''et al.'', [http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/ch1.html Chapter 1: Historical Overview of Climate Change Science], [http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/faq-1-1.html FAQ 1.1, What Factors Determine Earth's Climate?], in {{Harvnb|IPCC AR4 WG1|2007}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Human activities can also impose forcings, for example, through changing the composition of the atmosphere.

[[Radiative forcing]] is a measure of how various factors alter the [[First law of thermodynamics|energy balance]] of the [[Atmosphere of Earth|Earth's atmosphere]].&lt;ref&gt;Forster ''et al.'', [http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/ch2.html Chapter 2: Changes in Atmospheric Constituents and Radiative Forcing], [http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/faq-2-1.html FAQ 2.1, How do Human Activities Contribute to Climate Change and How do They Compare with Natural Influences?] in {{Harvnb|IPCC AR4 WG1|2007}}.&lt;/ref&gt; A positive radiative forcing will tend to increase the energy of the Earth-atmosphere system, leading to a warming of the system. Between the start of the [[Industrial Revolution]] in 1750, and the year 2005, the increase in the atmospheric concentration of [[Carbon dioxide in Earth's atmosphere|carbon dioxide]] ([[chemical formula]]: {{CO2}}) led to a positive radiative forcing, averaged over the Earth's [[surface area]], of about 1.66 watts per square metre (abbreviated W&amp;nbsp;m&lt;sup&gt;−2&lt;/sup&gt;).&lt;ref name=&quot;ipcc radiative forcing&quot;&gt;IPCC, [http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/spm.html Summary for Policymakers], [http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/spmsspm-human-and.html Human and Natural Drivers of Climate Change], Figure SPM.2, in {{Harvnb|IPCC AR4 WG1|2007}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Climate feedbacks can either amplify or dampen the response of the climate to a given forcing.&lt;ref name=nrc2008/&gt;{{Rp|7|date=November 2012}}
There are many feedback mechanisms in the climate system that can either amplify (a [[positive feedback]]) or diminish (a [[negative feedback]]) the effects of a change in climate forcing.

The climate system will vary in response to changes in forcings.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
| year=2001
| chapter=2. Natural Climatic Variations
| title=Climate Change Science: An Analysis of Some Key Questions
| publisher=[[National Academies Press]]
| location=Washington, D.C., USA
| authors=Committee on the Science of Climate Change, US National Research Council
| chapter-url=http://www.nap.edu/openbook.php?record_id=10139&amp;page=8
| page=8
| isbn=0-309-07574-2
| accessdate=20 May 2011}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
The climate system will show internal variability both in the presence and absence of forcings imposed on it, (see images opposite). This internal variability is a result of complex interactions between components of the climate system, such as the [[coupling (physics)|coupling]] between the atmosphere and ocean (see also the later section on [[Attribution of recent climate change#Internal climate variability and global warming|Internal climate variability and global warming]]).&lt;ref&gt;Albritton ''et al.'', [http://www.grida.no/climate/ipcc_tar/wg1/010.htm Technical Summary], [http://www.grida.no/climate/ipcc_tar/wg1/011.htm#box1 Box 1: What drives changes in climate?], in {{Harvnb|IPCC TAR WG1|2001}}.&lt;/ref&gt; An example of internal variability is the [[El Niño–Southern Oscillation]].

==Detection vs. attribution==
[[File:Attribution of global warming.jpg|thumb|[[Probability density function]] (PDF) of fraction of surface temperature trends since 1950 attributable to human activity, based on IPCC AR5 10.5]]
[[File:Detection and attribution of climate change (NOAA NCDC).png|thumb |right |425px|alt=Refer to caption and adjacent text|In detection and attribution, the natural factors considered usually include changes in the [[insolation|Sun's output]] and [[volcanic]] eruptions, as well as natural modes of variability such as [[ENSO|El Niño]] and La Niña. Human factors include the emissions of heat-trapping [[greenhouse gas|&quot;greenhouse&quot; gas]]es and [[aerosol|particulate]]s as well as [[deforestation|clearing of forest]]s and other [[land use|land-use]] changes. Figure source: NOAA NCDC.&lt;ref&gt;{{Include-USGov
 | agency=US Global Change Research Program ([[USGCRP]])
 | source=Figure 14: Detection and Attribution as Forensics (source: NOAA NCDC), in: {{citation
 | author=Walsh, J.
 | date=11 January 2013
 | chapter=Appendix II: The Science of Climate Change
 | title=FEDERAL ADVISORY COMMITTEE DRAFT CLIMATE ASSESSMENT. A report by the National Climate Assessment Development Advisory Committee
 | url=http://ncadac.globalchange.gov/
 | chapter-url=http://ncadac.globalchange.gov/download/NCAJan11-2013-publicreviewdraft-appendix2-climateprimer.pdf
|display-authors=etal}}, p.1139 (p.23 of chapter PDF).
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Detection and attribution of climate signals, as well as its common-sense meaning, has a more precise definition within the climate change literature, as expressed by the IPCC.&lt;ref&gt;Mitchell ''et al.'', [http://www.grida.no/climate/ipcc_tar/wg1/439.htm Chapter 12: Detection of Climate Change and Attribution of Causes], [http://www.grida.no/climate/ipcc_tar/wg1/443.htm#1211 Section 12.1.1: The Meaning of Detection and Attribution], in {{Harvnb|IPCC TAR WG1|2001}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Detection of a climate signal does not always imply significant attribution. The IPCC's [[IPCC Fourth Assessment Report|Fourth Assessment Report]] says &quot;it is ''extremely likely'' that human activities have exerted a substantial net warming influence on climate since 1750,&quot; where &quot;extremely likely&quot; indicates a probability greater than 95%.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|IPCC AR4 WG1|2007}}, chapter &quot;[https://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/tssts-6.html TS.6 Robust Findings and Key Uncertainties]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; ''Detection'' of a signal requires demonstrating that an observed change is [[Statistical significance|statistically significantly]] different from that which can be explained by natural internal variability.

''Attribution'' requires demonstrating that a signal is:
* unlikely to be due entirely to internal variability;
* consistent with the estimated responses to the given combination of anthropogenic and natural forcing
* not consistent with alternative, physically plausible explanations of recent climate change that exclude important elements of the given combination of forcings.

==Key attributions==

=== Greenhouse gases ===
[[Carbon dioxide]] is the primary [[greenhouse gas]] that is contributing to recent climate change.&lt;ref name=&quot;epa role of greenhouse gases&quot;&gt;
Quote from public-domain source: {{cite web
 |date=28 June 2012 
 |url=http://www.epa.gov/climatechange/science/causes.html#greenhouseeffect 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170308003615/https://www.epa.gov/climate-change-science/causes-climate-change 
 |archivedate=8 March 2017 
 |url-status=dead 
 |title=Causes of Climate Change: The Greenhouse Effect causes the atmosphere to retain heat 
 |author=US Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) 
 |publisher=EPA 
 |accessdate=1 July 2013 
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; {{chem|CO|2}} is absorbed and emitted naturally as part of the [[carbon cycle]], through animal and plant [[respiratory system|respiration]], [[Volcano|volcanic eruptions]], and ocean-atmosphere exchange.&lt;ref name=&quot;epa role of greenhouse gases&quot;/&gt; Human activities, such as the burning of fossil fuels and changes in land use (see below), release large amounts of carbon to the atmosphere, causing {{chem|CO|2}} concentrations in the atmosphere to rise.&lt;ref name=&quot;epa role of greenhouse gases&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See also: {{citation
 | volume=2. Validity of Observed and Measured Data
 | url=http://www.epa.gov/climatechange/endangerment/comments/volume2.html#1 |title=2.1 Greenhouse Gas Emissions and Concentrations |accessdate=1 July 2013
}}, in {{harvnb|EPA|2009}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

The high-accuracy measurements of atmospheric {{CO2}} concentration, initiated by [[Charles David Keeling]] in 1958, constitute the master time series documenting the changing composition of the [[Atmosphere of Earth|atmosphere]].&lt;ref name=&quot;le treut 2007 co2 fingerprint&quot;&gt;
{{citation
 | author=Le Treut, H.
 | chapter-url=http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/ch1s1-3.html#1-3-1 |chapter=1.3.1 The Human Fingerprint on Greenhouse Gases
 | title=Historical Overview of Climate Change Science
|display-authors=etal}}, in {{Harvnb|IPCC AR4 WG1|2007}}.
&lt;/ref&gt; These data have iconic status in climate change science as evidence of the effect of human activities on the chemical composition of the global atmosphere.&lt;ref name=&quot;le treut 2007 co2 fingerprint&quot;/&gt;

In May 2019 the concentration of CO2 in the atmosphere reached 415 PPM. The last time when it reached this level was 2.6 – 5.3&amp;nbsp;million years ago. Without human intervention, it would be 280 PPM&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Rosane |first1=Olivia |title=CO2 Levels Top 415 PPM for First Time in Human History |url=https://www.ecowatch.com/co2-levels-top-415-ppm-2637007719.html |accessdate=14 May 2019 |agency=Ecowatch |date=13 May 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;.
 
Along with {{CO2}}, [[methane]] and to a lesser extent [[nitrous oxide]] are also major forcing contributors to the [[greenhouse effect]]. The [[Kyoto Protocol]] lists these together with [[hydrofluorocarbon]] (HFCs), [[Fluorocarbon|perfluorocarbons]] (PFCs), and [[sulfur hexafluoride]] (SF&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;),&lt;ref name=&quot;kyoto&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
|title = The Kyoto Protocol
| publisher = [[UNFCCC]]
| url = http://unfccc.int/resource/docs/convkp/kpeng.html
}}&lt;/ref&gt; which are entirely artificial gases, as contributors to radiative forcing. The chart at right attributes anthropogenic greenhouse gas [[Air pollution|emissions]] to eight main economic sectors, of which the largest contributors are [[power station]]s (many of which burn coal or other [[fossil fuel]]s), industrial processes, transportation [[fuel]]s (generally [[fossil fuel]]s), and agricultural by-products (mainly methane from [[enteric fermentation]] and nitrous oxide from [[fertilizer]] use).&lt;ref&gt;see Stern (2006) for more details: {{citation
 |title     = 7. Projecting the Growth of Greenhouse-Gas Emissions
 |url = http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/d/Chapter_7_Projecting_the_Growth_of_Greenhouse-Gas_Emissions.pdf
 |pages       = 171–4
 |url-status     = dead
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20121104032244/http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/d/Chapter_7_Projecting_the_Growth_of_Greenhouse-Gas_Emissions.pdf
 |archivedate = 4 November 2012
 |df          = dmy-all
}}, in {{harvnb|Stern|2006}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

====Water vapor====
[[File:Greenhouse Gas by Sector.png|thumb|350px|alt=Refer to adjacent text|Emission Database for Global Atmospheric Research version 4.2, fast track 2010 project]]

Water vapor is the most abundant greenhouse gas and is the largest contributor to the natural greenhouse effect, despite having a short atmospheric lifetime&lt;ref name=&quot;epa role of greenhouse gases&quot;/&gt; (about 10 days).&lt;ref name=&quot;rc_wv&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.realclimate.org/index.php?p=142 
|title = Water vapour: feedback or forcing? 
|accessdate = 7 April 2008
|last = Schmidt | first = Gavin A. | authorlink = Gavin Schmidt
|date = 6 April 2005 |publisher = [[RealClimate]]
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some human activities can influence local water vapor levels. However, on a global scale, the concentration of water vapor is controlled by temperature, which influences overall rates of [[evaporation]] and [[precipitation]].&lt;ref name=&quot;epa role of greenhouse gases&quot;/&gt; Therefore, the global concentration of water vapor is not substantially affected by direct human emissions.&lt;ref name=&quot;epa role of greenhouse gases&quot;/&gt;

===Land use===
Climate change is attributed to [[land use]] for two main reasons. Between 1750 and 2007, about two-thirds of anthropogenic [[carbon dioxide|{{CO2}}]] emissions were produced from burning fossil fuels, and about one-third of emissions from changes in land use,&lt;ref&gt;
{{citation
 | author=Solomon, S.
 | chapter-url=http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/tssts-2-1-1.html |chapter=TS.2.1.1 Changes in Atmospheric Carbon Dioxide, Methane and Nitrous Oxide
 | title=Technical Summary
|display-authors=etal}}, in {{Harvnb|IPCC AR4 WG1|2007}}.
&lt;/ref&gt; primarily [[deforestation]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Technical Summary&quot;&gt;
{{citation
 | author=Solomon, S.
 | title=Technical Summary
 | url=http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/ts.html
|display-authors=etal}}, in {{Harvnb|IPCC AR4 WG1|2007}}. {{full citation needed|date=November 2012}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Deforestation both reduces the amount of carbon dioxide absorbed by deforested regions and releases greenhouse gases directly, together with aerosols, through [[slash and burn|biomass burning]] that frequently accompanies it.

Some of the causes of climate change are, generally, not connected with it directly in the [[media coverage of global warming|media coverage]]. For example, the harm done by humans to the populations of Elephants and Monkeys contributes to deforestation therefore to climate change.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Cimons |first1=Marlene |title=Elephants and Monkeys Are Working to Protect You From Climate Change |url=https://www.ecowatch.com/elephants-monkeys-climate-change-2639742120.html |accessdate=11 August 2019 |agency=Ecowatch |date=9 August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A second reason that climate change has been attributed to land use is that the [[albedo|terrestrial albedo]] is often altered by use, which leads to [[radiative forcing]]. This effect is more significant locally than globally.&lt;ref name=&quot;Technical Summary&quot;/&gt;

====Livestock and land use====
Worldwide, livestock production occupies 70% of all land used for agriculture, or 30% of the ice-free land surface of the Earth.&lt;ref name=&quot;livestock&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Livestock's Long Shadow |year=2006 |publisher=Food and Agricultural Organization of the U.N. |isbn=9251055718 |url=http://www.virtualcentre.org/en/library/key_pub/longshad/A0701E00.pdf |authors=Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations. Henning Steinfeld .... |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080625012113/http://www.virtualcentre.org/en/library/key_pub/longshad/A0701E00.pdf |archivedate=25 June 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
More than 18% of anthropogenic greenhouse gas emissions are attributed to livestock and livestock-related activities such as deforestation and increasingly fuel-intensive farming practices.&lt;ref name=&quot;livestock&quot; /&gt; Specific attributions to the livestock sector include:
* 9% of global anthropogenic [[carbon dioxide]] emissions
* 35–40% of global anthropogenic [[methane emissions]] (chiefly due to [[enteric fermentation]] and [[manure]])
* 64% of global anthropogenic [[nitrous oxide]] emissions, chiefly due to [[fertilizer]] use.&lt;ref name=&quot;livestock&quot; /&gt;

===Aerosols===
With virtual certainty, scientific consensus has attributed various forms of climate change, chiefly cooling effects, to [[aerosol]]s, which are small particles or droplets suspended in the atmosphere.&lt;ref name=&quot;WG1-2007-FM&quot;&gt;??{{citation needed|date=December 2011}} in {{Harvnb|IPCC AR4 WG1|2007}}. &lt;!-- Original citation TOTALLY SCREWED UP. What is being supported here: 1) &quot;scientific consensus as attributed...&quot;? Or 2) &quot;aerosols ... are ...&quot;? And the &quot;front matter&quot; (title page)? It looks like the editor may have been citing a quote of a review -- quite unacceptable. -JJ --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;
Key sources to which anthropogenic aerosols are attributed&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Aerosols and Climate | last = Geerts | first = B. | url = http://www-das.uwyo.edu/~geerts/cwx/notes/chap02/aerosol&amp;climate.html}}{{verify source|date=September 2011}}&lt;!-- If from a book, provide a _book_ citation, including title, date, and publisher. --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; include:
* biomass burning such as [[slash-and-burn]] deforestation. Aerosols produced are primarily [[black carbon]].
* industrial air pollution, which produces [[soot]] and airborne [[sulfate]]s, [[nitrate]]s, and [[ammonium]]
* dust produced by [[land use]] effects such as [[desertification]]

== Attribution of 20th-century climate change ==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Global warming controversy]] --&gt;
[[File:Climate Change Attribution.png|250px |thumb |alt=Refer to caption |One [[global climate model]]'s reconstruction of temperature change during the 20th century as the result of five studied forcing factors and the amount of temperature change attributed to each.]]
Over the past 150 years human activities have released increasing quantities of [[greenhouse gas]]es into the [[Earth's atmosphere|atmosphere]]. This has led to increases in mean global temperature, or [[global warming]]. Other human effects are relevant—for example, sulphate [[aerosol]]s are believed to have a cooling effect. Natural factors also contribute. According to the [[historical temperature record]] of the last century, the Earth's near-surface air temperature has risen around 0.74 [[Plus–minus sign|±]] 0.18&amp;nbsp;°Celsius (1.3 ± 0.32&amp;nbsp;°Fahrenheit).&lt;ref&gt;[https://www2.ucar.edu/climate/faq/how-much-has-global-temperature-risen-last-100-years UCAR FAQ: How much has global temp. risen over the past 100 years?]&lt;/ref&gt;

A historically important question in climate change research has regarded the relative importance of human activity and non-[[human impact on the environment|anthropogenic]] causes during the period of [[instrumental temperature record|instrumental record]]. In the 1995 [[IPCC Second Assessment Report|Second Assessment Report]] (SAR), the [[Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change|IPCC]] made the widely quoted statement that &quot;The balance of evidence suggests a discernible human influence on global climate&quot;. The phrase &quot;balance of evidence&quot; suggested the (English) common-law standard of proof required in civil as opposed to criminal courts: not as high as &quot;beyond reasonable doubt&quot;. In 2001 the [[IPCC Third Assessment Report|Third Assessment Report]] (TAR) refined this, saying &quot;There is new and stronger evidence that most of the warming observed over the last 50 years is attributable to human activities&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;WG1-2001-SPM&quot;/&gt; The 2007 [[IPCC Fourth Assessment Report|Fourth Assessment Report]] (AR4) strengthened this finding:
* &quot;Anthropogenic warming of the climate system is widespread and can be detected in temperature observations taken at the surface, in the free atmosphere and in the oceans. Evidence of the effect of external influences, both anthropogenic and natural, on the climate system has continued to accumulate since the TAR.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Solomon ''et al.'', [http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/ts.html Technical Summary], [http://www.ipcc.ch/pdf/assessment-report/ar4/wg1/ar4-wg1-ts.pdf p. ?].{{page needed|date=September 2011}} in {{Harvnb|IPCC AR4 WG1|2007}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Other findings of the IPCC Fourth Assessment Report include:
*&quot;It is ''extremely unlikely'' (&lt;5%)&lt;ref name=&quot;ar4 uncertainty&quot;&gt;
In the IPCC Fourth Assessment Report, the following scale is used to quantify uncertainty: &quot;virtually certain&quot; &gt;99%; &quot;extremely likely&quot; &gt;95%; &quot;very likely&quot; &gt;90%; &quot;likely&quot; &gt;66%; &quot;more likely than not&quot; &gt;50%; &quot;about as likely as not&quot; 33 to 66%; &quot;unlikely&quot; &lt;33%; &quot;very unlikely&quot; &lt;10%; &quot;extremely unlikely&quot; &lt;5%; &quot;exceptionally unlikely&quot; &lt;1%. {{citation
 | author=Solomon, S.
 | chapter-url=http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/tssts-2.html |chapter=Box TS.1: Treatment of Uncertainties in the Working Group I Assessment
 | title=Technical Summary
|display-authors=etal}}, in {{Harvnb|IPCC AR4 WG1|2007}}.
&lt;/ref&gt; that the global pattern of warming during the past half century can be explained without external forcing (i.e., it is inconsistent with being the result of internal variability), and ''very unlikely''&lt;ref name=&quot;ar4 uncertainty&quot;/&gt; that it is due to known natural external causes alone. The warming occurred in both the ocean and the atmosphere and took place at a time when natural external forcing factors would likely have produced cooling.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;hegerl 2007 executive summary&quot;/&gt;
*&quot;From new estimates of the combined anthropogenic [[radiative forcing|forcing]] due to greenhouse gases, [[aerosol]]s, and [[land use|land surface changes]], it is ''extremely likely'' (&gt;95%)&lt;ref name=&quot;ar4 uncertainty&quot;/&gt; that human activities have exerted a substantial net warming influence on climate since 1750.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;solomon 2007 drivers of climate change&quot;&gt;
{{citation
 | author=Solomon, S.
 | chapter-url=http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/tssts-6.html |chapter=TS.6.1 Changes in Human and Natural Drivers of Climate
 | title=Technical Summary
|display-authors=etal}}, in {{Harvnb|IPCC AR4 WG1|2007}}.
&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;It is ''virtually certain''&lt;ref name=&quot;ar4 uncertainty&quot;/&gt; that anthropogenic aerosols produce a net negative [[radiative forcing]] (cooling influence) with a greater magnitude in the [[Northern Hemisphere]] than in the [[Southern Hemisphere]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;solomon 2007 drivers of climate change&quot;/&gt;

Over the past five decades there has been a global warming of approximately 0.65&amp;nbsp;°C (1.17&amp;nbsp;°F) at the Earth's surface (see [[historical temperature record]]). Among the possible factors that could produce changes in global mean temperature are internal variability of the climate system, external forcing, an increase in concentration of greenhouse gases, or any combination of these. Current studies indicate that the increase in greenhouse gases, most notably {{CO2}}, is mostly responsible for the observed warming. Evidence for this conclusion includes:
* Estimates of internal variability from climate models, and reconstructions of past temperatures, indicate that the warming is unlikely to be entirely natural.
* Climate models forced by natural factors ''and'' increased greenhouse gases and aerosols reproduce the observed global temperature changes; those forced by natural factors alone do not.&lt;ref name=&quot;WG1-2001-SPM&quot;&gt;IPCC, [http://www.grida.no/climate/ipcc_tar/wg1/007.htm Summary for Policymakers].{{page needed|date=September 2011}} in {{Harvnb|IPCC TAR WG1|2001}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;Fingerprint&quot; methods (see [[Attribution of recent climate change#&quot;Fingerprint&quot; studies|below]]) indicate that the pattern of change is closer to that expected from greenhouse gas-forced change than from natural change.&lt;ref&gt;Mitchell ''et al.'', [http://www.grida.no/climate/ipcc_tar/wg1/439.htm Chapter 12: Detection of Climate Change and Attribution of Causes] [http://www.grida.no/climate/ipcc_tar/wg1/460.htm Section 12.4.3, Optimal Fingerprint Methods], in {{Harvnb|IPCC TAR WG1|2001}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
* The plateau in warming from the 1940s to 1960s can be attributed largely to sulphate aerosol cooling.&lt;ref&gt;{{author?}}&lt;!-- More specifically, need the author/chapter(ch12?)/section. --&gt; [http://www.grida.no/climate/ipcc_tar/wg1/figspm-4.htm Figure 4, Simulated annual global mean surface temperatures], in {{Harvnb|IPCC TAR WG1|2001}}.{{vn|date=December 2011}}&lt;!-- Neither fig 4 nor fig 12.7 mention sulphate aerosol cooling. --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

===Details on attribution===
[[File:2000 Year Temperature Comparison.png|thumb|upright|250px|alt=refer to caption and adjacent text|right |alt=Refer to caption |For Northern Hemisphere temperature, recent decades appear to be the warmest since at least about 1000AD, and the warming since the late 19th century is unprecedented over the last 1000 years.&lt;ref name=&quot;noaa nh temp for last 1300 years&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
 | author=NOAA
 | title=NOAA: NESDIS: NCDC: Frequently Asked Questions: How important are these changes in a longer–(term) context?
 | url=http://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/faqs/climfaq08.html
 |publisher=NOAA
 | date=10 March 2010
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Older data are insufficient to provide reliable hemispheric temperature estimates.&lt;ref name=&quot;noaa nh temp for last 1300 years&quot;/&gt;]]
Recent scientific assessments find that most of the warming of the Earth's surface over the past 50 years has been caused by human activities (see also the section on [[Attribution of recent climate change#Scientific literature and opinion|scientific literature and opinion]]). This conclusion rests on multiple lines of evidence. Like the warming &quot;signal&quot; that has gradually emerged from the &quot;noise&quot; of natural climate variability, the scientific evidence for a human influence on global climate has accumulated over the past several decades, from many hundreds of studies. No single study is a &quot;[[smoking gun]].&quot; Nor has any single study or combination of studies undermined the large body of evidence supporting the conclusion that human activity is the primary driver of recent warming.&lt;!-- Most of the preceding paragraph drawn from the following reference: --&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Karl|others|2009}}, page 19.&lt;/ref&gt;

The first line of evidence is based on a physical understanding of how greenhouse gases trap heat, how the climate system responds to increases in greenhouse gases, and how other human and natural factors influence climate. The second line of evidence is from indirect estimates of climate changes over the last 1,000 to 2,000 years. These records are obtained from living things and their remains (like [[tree ring]]s and [[coral]]s) and from physical quantities (like the ratio between lighter and heavier [[isotope]]s of [[oxygen]] in [[ice core]]s), which change in measurable ways as climate changes. The lesson from these data is that global surface temperatures over the last several decades are clearly unusual, in that they were higher than at any time during at least the past 400 years. For the [[Northern Hemisphere]], the recent temperature rise is clearly unusual in at least the last 1,000 years (see graph opposite).&lt;!-- The preceding paragraph is from the following reference: --&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

The third line of evidence is based on the broad, qualitative consistency between observed changes in climate and the computer model simulations of how climate would be expected to change in response to human activities. For example, when climate models are run with historical increases in greenhouse gases, they show gradual warming of the Earth and ocean surface, increases in ocean heat content and the temperature of the lower atmosphere, a [[current sea level rise|rise]] in global sea level, retreat of [[sea ice]] and snow cover, cooling of the [[stratosphere]], an increase in the amount of atmospheric water vapor, and changes in large-scale [[precipitation (meteorology)|precipitation]] and [[atmospheric pressure|pressure patterns]]. These and other aspects of modelled climate change are in agreement with observations.&lt;!-- The preceding paragraph is from the following reference: --&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

====&quot;Fingerprint&quot; studies====
[[File:Attribution of global warming – simulation of 20th century global mean temperatures (with and without human influences) compared to observations (NASA).png|thumb |right |alt=Refer to caption |Reconstructions of global temperature that include greenhouse gas increases and other human influences (red line, based on many models) closely match measured temperatures (dashed line).&lt;ref name=&quot;lindsey 20th century gmt simulations&quot;&gt;
Quote from public-domain source: {{citation
 | author=Lindsey, R.
 | date=4 May 2010
 | title=If Earth has warmed and cooled throughout history, what makes scientists think that humans are causing global warming now? : Climate Q&amp;A : Blogs
 | url=http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/blogs/climateqa/if-earth-has-warmed-and-cooled-throughout-history-what-makes-scientists-think-that-humans-are-causing-global-warming-now/
 | publisher=Earth Observatory, part of the EOS Project Science Office, located at NASA Goddard Space Flight Center
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Those that only include natural influences (blue line, based on many models) show a slight cooling, which has not occurred.&lt;ref name=&quot;lindsey 20th century gmt simulations&quot;/&gt; The ability of models to generate reasonable histories of global temperature is verified by their response to four 20th-century volcanic eruptions: each eruption caused brief cooling that appeared in observed as well as modeled records.&lt;ref name=&quot;lindsey 20th century gmt simulations&quot;/&gt;]]

Finally, there is extensive statistical evidence from so-called &quot;fingerprint&quot; studies. Each factor that affects climate produces a unique pattern of climate response, much as each person has a unique fingerprint. Fingerprint studies exploit these unique signatures, and allow detailed comparisons of modelled and observed climate change patterns. Scientists rely on such studies to attribute observed changes in climate to a particular cause or set of causes. In the real world, the climate changes that have occurred since the start of the [[Industrial Revolution]] are due to a complex mixture of human and natural causes. The importance of each individual influence in this mixture changes over time. Of course, there are not multiple Earths, which would allow an experimenter to change one factor at a time on each Earth, thus helping to isolate different fingerprints. Therefore, climate models are used to study how individual factors affect climate. For example, a single factor (like greenhouse gases) or a set of factors can be varied, and the response of the modelled climate system to these individual or combined changes can thus be studied.&lt;!-- The preceding paragraph was copied from the following reference: --&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

{{Multiple image
|align=left
|direction=vertical
|width=220
|image1=GISS temperature 2000-09 lrg.png
|alt1=refer to caption
|image2=GISS temperature palette.svg
|alt2=key to above map of temperature changes
|caption2=Two fingerprints of human activities on the climate are that land areas will warm more than the oceans, and that high latitudes will warm more than low latitudes.&lt;ref name=&quot;schneider fingerprint&quot;&gt;
{{citation
 | author=Schneider, S.
 | title=Climate Science
 | url=http://stephenschneider.stanford.edu/Climate/Climate_Science/Science.html#topofpage
 | at=[http://stephenschneider.stanford.edu/Climate/Climate_Science/Science.html#Itislikelythathumanactivitieshavecausedadiscernibleimpactonobservedwarmingtrends It is likely that human activities have caused a discernible impact on observed warming trends]
 | publisher=[[Stephen H. Schneider]], [[Stanford University]]
 | accessdate=28 September 2012
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; These projections have been confirmed by observations (shown above).&lt;ref name=&quot;schneider fingerprint&quot;/&gt;}}
For example, when climate model simulations of the last century include all of the major influences on climate, both human-induced and natural, they can reproduce many important features of observed climate change patterns. When human influences are removed from the model experiments, results suggest that the surface of the Earth would actually have cooled slightly over the last 50 years (see graph, opposite). The clear message from fingerprint studies is that the observed warming over the last half-century cannot be explained by natural factors, and is instead caused primarily by human factors.&lt;!-- The preceding paragraph was copied from the following reference: --&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

Another fingerprint of human effects on climate has been identified by looking at a slice through the layers of the atmosphere, and studying the pattern of temperature changes from the surface up through the stratosphere (see the section on [[Attribution of recent climate change#Solar activity|solar activity]]). The earliest fingerprint work focused on changes in surface and atmospheric temperature. Scientists then applied fingerprint methods to a whole range of climate variables, identifying human-caused climate signals in the heat content of the oceans, the height of the [[tropopause]] (the boundary between the [[troposphere]] and [[stratosphere]], which has shifted upward by hundreds of feet in recent decades), the geographical patterns of precipitation, drought, surface pressure, and the [[surface runoff|runoff]] from major [[river basin]]s.&lt;!-- The preceding paragraph was copied from the following reference: --&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Karl|others|2009}}, page 20.&lt;/ref&gt;

Studies published after the appearance of the [[IPCC Fourth Assessment Report]] in 2007 have also found human fingerprints in the increased levels of atmospheric [[moisture]] (both close to the surface and over the full extent of the atmosphere), in the decline of [[Arctic sea ice]] extent, and in the patterns of changes in [[Arctic]] and [[Antarctic]] surface temperatures.&lt;!-- The preceding paragraph was copied from the following reference: --&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;

The message from this entire body of work is that the climate system is telling a consistent story of increasingly dominant human influence – the changes in temperature, ice extent, moisture, and [[Atmospheric circulation|circulation]] patterns fit together in a physically consistent way, like pieces in a complex puzzle.&lt;!-- The preceding paragraph was copied from the following reference: --&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Karl|others|2009}}, page 21.&lt;/ref&gt;

Increasingly, this type of fingerprint work is shifting its emphasis. As noted, clear and compelling scientific evidence supports the case for a pronounced human influence on global climate. Much of the recent attention is now on climate changes at continental and regional scales, and on variables that can have large impacts on societies. For example, scientists have established causal links between human activities and the changes in [[snowpack]], maximum and minimum ([[Diurnal temperature variation|diurnal]]) temperature, and the seasonal timing of runoff over mountainous regions of the western United States. Human activity is likely to have made a substantial contribution to ocean surface temperature changes in [[hurricane]] formation regions. Researchers are also looking beyond the physical climate system, and are beginning to tie changes in the distribution and seasonal behaviour of plant and animal species to human-caused changes in temperature and precipitation.&lt;!-- The preceding paragraph was copied from the following reference: --&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;

For over a decade, one aspect of the climate change story seemed to show a significant difference between models and observations. In the tropics, all models predicted that with a rise in greenhouse gases, the troposphere would be expected to warm more rapidly than the surface. Observations from weather balloons, satellites, and surface thermometers seemed to show the opposite behaviour (more rapid warming of the surface than the troposphere). This issue was a stumbling block in understanding the causes of climate change. It is now largely resolved. Research showed that there were large uncertainties in the [[satellite]] and [[weather balloon]] data. When uncertainties in models and observations are properly accounted for, newer observational data sets (with better treatment of known problems) are in agreement with climate model results.&lt;!-- The preceding paragraph was copied from the following reference: --&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;

{{multiple image
| align     = right
| direction = horizontal
| total_width = 

| image1    = Effect of various natural and human factors on global mean temperature between 1889-2006 (NASA).png
| caption1  = This set of graphs shows the estimated contribution of various natural and human factors to changes in global mean temperature between 1889 and 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation
 |author1=Lean, J. L. |author2=Rind, D. H.
  |lastauthoramp=yes | year=2008
 | url=http://www.agu.org/pubs/crossref/2008/2008GL034864.shtml
 | title=How natural and anthropogenic influences alter global and regional surface temperatures: 1889 to 2006
 | journal=Geophysical Research Letters
 | volume=35
 | issue=18
 |pages=L18701
 | doi=10.1029/2008GL034864
 | bibcode=2008GeoRL..3518701L
}}, referred to by: {{citation
 | author=Riebeek, H.
 | url=http://www.earthobservatory.nasa.gov/Features/GlobalWarming/page4.php
 | title=Is Current Warming Natural? in: Global Warming (p.4), Feature Articles
 | publisher=Earth Observatory, part of the EOS Project Science Office, located at NASA Goddard Space Flight Center
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Estimated contributions are based on [[multivariate analysis]] rather than model simulations.&lt;ref&gt;
{{citation
 | author=US EPA
 | date=28 January 2009
 | url=http://yosemite.epa.gov/ee/epa/eed.nsf/pages/SeminarsWithVideo.html
 | title=Climate Science Seminar: Natural and Anthropogenic Influences on Earth's Surface Temperature (Judith Lean, U.S. Naval Research Laboratory), Abstract, Seminars with Video: Events: NCEE: US EPA
 | publisher=US Environmental Protection Agency (US EPA): National Center for Environmental Economics (NCEE)
}}. Last updated 2 November 2012.
&lt;/ref&gt; The graphs show that human influence on climate has eclipsed the magnitude of natural temperature changes over the past 120 years.&lt;ref name=&quot;riebeek 20th century contributions&quot;&gt;
{{citation
 | author=Riebeek, H.
 | url=http://www.earthobservatory.nasa.gov/Features/GlobalWarming/page4.php
 | title=Is Current Warming Natural? in: Global Warming (p.4), Feature Articles
 | publisher=Earth Observatory, part of the EOS Project Science Office, located at NASA Goddard Space Flight Center
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Natural influences on temperature—El Niño, solar variability, and volcanic aerosols—have varied approximately plus and minus 0.2&amp;nbsp;°C (0.4&amp;nbsp;°F), (averaging to about zero), while human influences have contributed roughly 0.8&amp;nbsp;°C (1&amp;nbsp;°F) of warming since 1889.&lt;ref name=&quot;riebeek 20th century contributions&quot;/&gt;]]
| width1   = 200

| image2    = 2017 Global warming attribution - based on NCA4 Fig 3.3.png
| caption2  = '''Top chart:''' Observed global average temperature change (1870— ).&lt;br&gt;
'''Bottom chart:''' Data more recent than that plotted at left, and merged for display on the same axis to emphasize relative strengths of forces affecting temperature change. Human-caused forces have increasingly dominated.
| width2   = 200
}}

This does not mean, however, that all remaining differences between models and observations have been resolved. The observed changes in some climate variables, such as Arctic sea ice, some aspects of precipitation, and patterns of surface pressure, appear to be proceeding much more rapidly than models have projected. The reasons for these differences are not well understood. Nevertheless, the bottom-line conclusion from climate fingerprinting is that most of the observed changes studied to date are consistent with each other, and are also consistent with our scientific understanding of how the climate system would be expected to respond to the increase in heat-trapping gases resulting from human activities.&lt;!-- The preceding paragraph was copied from the following reference: --&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Karl|others|2009}}, page 22.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Extreme weather events====
[[File:Shifting Distribution of Summer Temperature Anomalies2.png|thumb|alt=refer to caption|Frequency of occurrence (vertical axis) of local June–July–August temperature anomalies (relative to 1951–1980 mean) for Northern Hemisphere land in units of local [[standard deviation]] (horizontal axis).&lt;ref name=&quot;climate dice&quot;&gt;
{{citation
 | pages=3–4
 | author=Hansen, J.
 | date=July 2012
 | title=The New Climate Dice: Public Perception of Climate Change
 | publisher=Dr James E. Hansen, Columbia University
 | location=New York City
 | url=http://www.columbia.edu/%7Ejeh1/mailings/2012/20120803_DicePopSci.pdf
 |display-authors=etal}}
&lt;/ref&gt; According to Hansen ''et al.'' (2012),&lt;ref name=&quot;climate dice&quot;/&gt; the distribution of anomalies has shifted to the right as a consequence of global warming, meaning that unusually hot summers have become more common. This is analogous to the rolling of a dice: cool summers now cover only half of one side of a six-sided die, white covers one side, red covers four sides, and an extremely hot (red-brown) anomaly covers half of one side.&lt;ref name=&quot;climate dice&quot;/&gt;]]
One of the subjects discussed in the literature is whether or not extreme weather events can be attributed to human activities. Seneviratne ''et al.'' (2012)&lt;ref&gt;{{citation
 | author=Seneviratne, S.I.
 | title=Ch 3. Changes in Climate Extremes and their Impacts on the Natural Physical Environment: FAQ 3.2. Has Climate Change Affected Individual Extreme Events?
 | url=http://ipcc-wg2.gov/SREX/images/uploads/SREX-Chap3_FINAL.pdf
 | display-authors=etal
 | access-date=8 March 2013
 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130215184321/http://ipcc-wg2.gov/SREX/images/uploads/SREX-Chap3_FINAL.pdf
 | archive-date=15 February 2013
 | url-status=dead
 }}, in {{harvnb|IPCC SREX|2012|p=127}}.&lt;/ref&gt; stated that attributing individual extreme weather events to human activities was challenging. They were, however, more confident over attributing changes in long-term trends of extreme weather. For example, Seneviratne ''et al.'' (2012)&lt;ref&gt;{{citation
 | author=Seneviratne, S.I.
 | title=Ch 3. Changes in Climate Extremes and their Impacts on the Natural Physical Environment: Executive summary
 | url=http://ipcc-wg2.gov/SREX/images/uploads/SREX-Chap3_FINAL.pdf
 | display-authors=etal
 | access-date=8 March 2013
 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130215184321/http://ipcc-wg2.gov/SREX/images/uploads/SREX-Chap3_FINAL.pdf
 | archive-date=15 February 2013
 | url-status=dead
 }}, in {{harvnb|IPCC SREX|2012|p=112}}.&lt;/ref&gt; concluded that human activities had likely led to a warming of extreme daily minimum and maximum temperatures at the global scale.

Another way of viewing the problem is to consider the effects of human-induced climate change on the probability of future extreme weather events. Stott ''et al.'' (2003),&lt;ref name=&quot;stott 2003 european heat wave&quot;&gt;
{{citation
 | author=Stott, P.A.
 | year=2004
 | title=Human contribution to the European heatwave of 2003
 | journal=Nature
 | volume=432
 | doi=10.1038/nature03089
 | pages=610–614
|bibcode = 2004Natur.432..610S
 | pmid=15577907
 | issue=7017|display-authors=etal}}
&lt;/ref&gt; for example, considered whether or not human activities had increased the risk of severe [[heat wave]]s in Europe, like the one [[2003 European heat wave|experienced in 2003]]. Their conclusion was that human activities had very likely more than doubled the risk of heat waves of this magnitude.&lt;ref name=&quot;stott 2003 european heat wave&quot;/&gt;

An analogy can be made between an [[sportsperson|athlete]] on [[Doping in sport|steroid]]s and human-induced climate change.&lt;ref&gt;
{{citation
 | author=Stott, P.A.
 | title=Introduction. In: Explaining Extreme Events of 2011 from a Climate Perspective
 | editors=Peterson, T.C. |display-editors=etal
 | work=Bull. Amer. Meteorol. Soc
 | date=July 2012
 | doi=10.1175/BAMS-D-12-00021.1
 | url=http://www.geos.ed.ac.uk/homes/ghegerl/2011-peterson-et-al.pdf
|bibcode = 2012BAMS...93.1041P |display-authors=etal
 | volume=93
 | issue=7
 | pages=1041–1067}}, 1042
&lt;/ref&gt; In the same way that an athlete's performance may increase from using steroids, human-induced climate change increases the risk of some extreme weather events.

Hansen ''et al.'' (2012)&lt;ref&gt;
{{harvnb|Hansen|others|2012|p=1}}
&lt;/ref&gt; suggested that human activities have greatly increased the risk of summertime heat waves. According to their analysis, the land area of the Earth affected by very hot summer temperature anomalies has greatly increased over time (refer to graphs on the left). In the base period 1951–1980, these anomalies covered a few tenths of 1% of the global land area.&lt;ref name=&quot;hansen 2012 discussion&quot;&gt;
Discussion, in {{harvnb|Hansen|others|2012|pp=6–7}}
&lt;/ref&gt; In recent years, this has increased to around 10% of the global land area. With high confidence, Hansen ''et al.'' (2012)&lt;ref name=&quot;hansen 2012 discussion&quot;/&gt; attributed the [[2010 Russian heat wave|2010 Moscow]] and [[2010–12 Southern United States drought|2011 Texas heat wave]]s to human-induced global warming.

An earlier study by Dole ''et al.'' (2011)&lt;ref name=&quot;dole 2011 russian heat wave&quot;&gt;
{{citation
 | author=Dole, R.
 | title=Was there a basis for anticipating the 2010 Russian heat wave?
 | journal=Geophysical Research Letters
 | doi=10.1029/2010GL046582
 | volume=38
 | issue=6
 | pages=n/a
 | date=March 2011
 | url=http://www.esrl.noaa.gov/psd/people/tao.zhang/2010GL046582.pdf
 | bibcode=2011GeoRL..38.6702D
|display-authors=etal}}
&lt;/ref&gt; concluded that the 2010 Moscow heatwave was mostly due to natural weather variability. While not directly citing Dole ''et al.'' (2011),&lt;ref name=&quot;dole 2011 russian heat wave&quot;/&gt; Hansen ''et al.'' (2012)&lt;ref name=&quot;hansen 2012 discussion&quot;/&gt; rejected this type of explanation. Hansen ''et al.'' (2012)&lt;ref name=&quot;hansen 2012 discussion&quot;/&gt; stated that a combination of natural weather variability and human-induced global warming was responsible for the Moscow and Texas heat waves.

== Scientific literature and opinion ==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Climate change]] --&gt;
{{Main article|Scientific consensus on climate change}}

There are a number of examples of published and informal support for the consensus view. As mentioned earlier, the IPCC has concluded that most of the observed increase in globally averaged temperatures since the mid-20th century is &quot;very likely&quot; due to human activities.&lt;ref name=&quot;ipcc 2007 attribution&quot;&gt;
{{citation
 | author=IPCC
 | chapter-url=http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/spmsspm-understanding-and.html |chapter=Understanding and Attributing Climate Change
 | title=Summary for Policymakers
}}, in {{Harvnb|IPCC AR4 WG1|2007}}.
&lt;/ref&gt; The IPCC's conclusions are consistent with those of several reports produced by the [[US National Research Council]].&lt;ref name=nrc2001/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|year=2006
|chapter=Overview
|title=Surface Temperature Reconstructions for the Last 2,000 Years
|publisher=[[National Academies Press]]
|location=Washington, D.C., USA
|authors=Committee on Surface Temperature Reconstructions for the Last 2,000 Years, US National Research Council
|chapter-url=https://books.nap.edu/openbook.php?record_id=11676&amp;page=21
|pages=21–22
|isbn=0-309-66144-7
|accessdate=20 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|year=2010
|chapter=Summary
|title=Advancing the Science of Climate Change
|publisher=[[National Academies Press]]
|location=Washington, D.C., USA
|authors=Panel on Advancing the Science of Climate Change; US National Research Council
|chapter-url=https://books.nap.edu/openbook.php?record_id=12782&amp;page=3
|page=3
|isbn=978-0-309-14588-6
|accessdate=20 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
A report published in 2009 by the [[U.S. Global Change Research Program]] concluded that &quot;[global] warming is unequivocal and primarily human-induced.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Karl|others|2009}}, [http://www.globalchange.gov/publications/reports/scientific-assessments/us-impacts/key-findings Executive Summary], p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt;
A number of scientific organizations have issued statements that support the consensus view. Two examples include:
*a joint statement made in 2005 by the national science academies of the [[G8]], and Brazil, China and [[India]];&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|date=7 June 2005
|title=Joint science academies' statement: Global response to climate change
|publisher=UK Royal Society website
|url=http://royalsociety.org/Joint-science-academies-statement-Global-response-to-climate-change/
|accessdate=20 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*a joint statement made in 2008 by the [[Network of African Science Academies]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|date=1 June 2007
|title=Joint statement by NASAC to the G8 on sustainability, energy efficiency and climate change
|publisher=UK Royal Society website
|url=http://royalsociety.org/Joint-statement-by-NASAC-to-the-G8-on-sustainability-energy-efficiency-and-climate-change/
|accessdate=20 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Detection and attribution studies===
[[File:3 examples of internal climate variability (1950-2012), the El Niño – Southern Oscillation, the Arctic Oscillation, and the North Atlantic Oscillation (NOAA).png|thumb |right |alt=Refer to caption |This image shows three examples of internal climate variability measured between 1950 and 2012: the [[El Niño]]–Southern oscillation, the [[Arctic oscillation]], and the [[North Atlantic oscillation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.climate.gov/|title=Climate.gov|last=&lt;!--no byline--&gt;|date=&lt;!--no source date included--&gt;|website=|publisher=NOAA|at=Global Climate Dashboard &gt; Climate Variability|access-date=22 December 2017}}
&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The IPCC Fourth Assessment Report (2007), concluded that attribution was possible for a number of observed changes in the climate (see [[effects of global warming]]). However, attribution was found to be more difficult when assessing changes over smaller regions (less than continental scale) and over short time periods (less than 50 years).&lt;ref name=&quot;hegerl 2007 executive summary&quot;&gt;Hegerl ''et al.'', [http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/ch9.html Chapter 9: Understanding and Attributing Climate Change], [http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/ch9s9-es.html Executive Summary], in
{{Harvnb|IPCC AR4 WG1|2007}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
Over larger regions, averaging reduces natural variability of the climate, making detection and attribution easier.

* In 1996, in a paper in ''[[Nature (journal)|Nature]]'' titled &quot;A search for human influences on the thermal structure of the atmosphere&quot;, [[Benjamin D. Santer]] et al. wrote: &quot;The observed spatial patterns of temperature change in the free atmosphere from 1963 to 1987 are similar to those predicted by state-of-the-art climate models incorporating various combinations of changes in carbon dioxide, anthropogenic sulphate aerosol and stratospheric ozone concentrations. The degree of pattern similarity between models and observations increases through this period. It is likely that this trend is partially due to human activities, although many uncertainties remain, particularly relating to estimates of natural variability.&quot;
* A 2002 paper in the ''[[Journal of Geophysical Research]]'' says &quot;Our analysis suggests that the early twentieth century warming can best be explained by a combination of warming due to increases in greenhouse gases and natural forcing, some cooling due to other anthropogenic forcings, and a substantial, but not implausible, contribution from internal variability. In the second half of the century we find that the warming is largely caused by changes in greenhouse gases, with changes in sulphates and, perhaps, volcanic aerosol offsetting approximately one third of the warming.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author1=Tett SFB |authorlink1=Simon Tett |title=Estimation of natural and anthropogenic contributions to twentieth century temperature change |journal=J. Geophys. Res. |volume=107 |issue=D16 |page=4306 |year=2002 | doi = 10.1029/2000JD000028 | url = http://www.agu.org/pubs/crossref/2002/2000JD000028.shtml |bibcode=2002JGRD..107.4306T|display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite newsgroup | title = Estimation of natural and anthropogenic contributions to twentieth century temperature change | author = [[William Connolley]] | date = 27 May 2003 | newsgroup = sci.environment |message-id=3ed342eb@news.nwl.ac.uk|url=https://groups.google.com/forum/#!original/sci.environment/v-EOwyTtcus/rBbSfLYhhaoJ|accessdate=13 June 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* A 2005 review of detection and attribution studies by the International [[Ad hoc]] Detection and Attribution Group&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal| title = Detecting and Attributing External Influences on the Climate System: A Review of Recent Advances | first = T. | last = Barnett | journal = Journal of Climate | volume = 18 | issue = 9 |date=May 2005 | pages = 1291–1314 | url = http://www.llnl.gov/tid/lof/documents/pdf/315840.pdf | doi = 10.1175/JCLI3329.1|bibcode = 2005JCli...18.1291. }}&lt;/ref&gt; found that &quot;natural drivers such as solar variability and volcanic activity are at most partially responsible for the large-scale temperature changes observed over the past century, and that a large fraction of the warming over the last 50 yr can be attributed to greenhouse gas increases. Thus, the recent research supports and strengthens the IPCC Third Assessment Report conclusion that 'most of the global warming over the past 50 years is likely due to the increase in greenhouse gases.'&quot;
* Barnett and colleagues (2005) say that the observed warming of the oceans &quot;cannot be explained by natural internal climate variability or solar and volcanic forcing, but is well simulated by two [[human impact on the environment|anthropogenic]]ally forced climate models,&quot; concluding that &quot;it is of human origin, a conclusion robust to observational sampling and model differences&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|vauthors=Barnett TP, Pierce DW, Achutarao KM |title=Penetration of human-induced warming into the world's oceans |journal=Science |volume=309 |issue=5732 |pages=284–7 |date=July 2005|pmid=15933161 | doi = 10.1126/science.1112418|bibcode = 2005Sci...309..284B |display-authors=etal|url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/9d3e17df0925f5e4591a09c88077ee5c45d8e9e8 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Two papers in the journal ''[[Science (journal)|Science]]'' in August 2005&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite web| title = Et Tu LT? | date = 11 August 2007 | publisher = RealClimate.org | last = Schmidt | first = Gavin A. | authorlink = Gavin Schmidt | url = http://www.realclimate.org/index.php?p=170}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = The tropical lapse rate quandary | date = 11 August 2007 | publisher = RealClimate.org | last = Schmidt | first = Gavin A. | authorlink = Gavin Schmidt | url = http://www.realclimate.org/index.php?p=179}}&lt;/ref&gt; resolve the problem, evident at the time of the TAR, of [[troposphere|tropospheric]] temperature trends (see also the section on [[Attribution of recent climate change#&quot;Fingerprint&quot; studies|&quot;fingerprint&quot; studies]]) . The UAH version of the record contained errors, and there is evidence of spurious cooling trends in the radiosonde record, particularly in the tropics. See [[satellite temperature measurements]] for details; and the 2006 US CCSP report.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite journal|title=Temperature Trends in the Lower Atmosphere&amp;nbsp;— Understanding and Reconciling Differences (Executive Summary) |last=Wigley |first=Tom M. L. |publisher=[[National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration|NOAA]] |date=2 May 2006 |url=http://www.climatescience.gov/Library/sap/sap1-1/finalreport/sap1-1-final-execsum.pdf |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070423150153/http://www.climatescience.gov/Library/sap/sap1-1/finalreport/sap1-1-final-execsum.pdf |archivedate=23 April 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Multiple independent reconstructions of the [[temperature record of the past 1000 years]] confirm that the late 20th century is probably the warmest period in that time (see the preceding section -[[attribution of recent climate change#Details on attribution|details on attribution]]).

===Reviews of scientific opinion===
* An essay in ''[[Science (journal)|Science]]'' surveyed 928 [[Abstract (summary)|abstracts]] related to climate change, and concluded that most journal reports accepted the [[Scientific consensus on climate change|consensus]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Oreskes N |title=Beyond the ivory tower. The scientific consensus on climate change |journal=Science |volume=306 |issue=5702 |page=1686 |date=December 2004|pmid=15576594 | doi = 10.1126/science.1103618|url=http://science.sciencemag.org/content/sci/306/5702/1686.full.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt; This is discussed further in [[Scientific consensus on climate change#Surveys of scientists and scientific literature|scientific consensus on climate change]].
*A 2010 paper in the [[Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences]] found that among a pool of roughly 1,000 researchers who work directly on climate issues and publish the most frequently on the subject, 97% agree that anthropogenic climate change is happening.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 | author=Anderegg, W.R.L.
 | title=Expert credibility in climate change
 | journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
 | date=6 July 2010
 | volume=107
 | issue=27
 | pages=12107–12109
 | doi=10.1073/pnas.1003187107
 |bibcode = 2010PNAS..10712107A
 | pmid=20566872
 | pmc=2901439|display-authors=etal}} Referred to by: {{cite web
 | author=Wihbey, J.
 | title=Expert Credibility in Climate Change
 | publisher=Journalist's Resource: Research for Reporting. A project of the Harvard Kennedy School's Shorenstein Center and the Carnegie-Knight Initiative
 | date=3 July 2012
 | url=http://journalistsresource.org/studies/environment/climate-change/expert-credibility/
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
*A 2011 paper from [[George Mason University]] published in the ''International Journal of Public Opinion Research'', &quot;The Structure of Scientific Opinion on Climate Change,&quot; collected the opinions of scientists in the earth, space, atmospheric, oceanic or hydrological sciences.&lt;ref name=&quot;Structure of Scientific Opinion on Climate Change&quot;&gt;
{{cite journal
 | author=Farnsworth, S. J.
 | title= The Structure of Scientific Opinion on Climate Change
 | journal= International Journal of Public Opinion Research
 | doi=10.1093/ijpor/edr033
 | url=http://ijpor.oxfordjournals.org/content/early/2011/10/27/ijpor.edr033.short?rss=1
 | volume=24
 | pages=93–103
 | year=2011
}} Referred to by: {{cite web
 | author=Wihbey, J.
 | title=Structure of Scientific Opinion on Climate Change
 | publisher=Journalist's Resource: Research for Reporting. A project of the Harvard Kennedy School's Shorenstein Center and the Carnegie-Knight Initiative
 | url=http://journalistsresource.org/studies/environment/climate-change/structure-scientific-opinion-climate-change/
 | date=4 November 2011
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; The 489 survey respondents—representing nearly half of all those eligible according to the survey's specific standards – work in academia, government, and industry, and are members of prominent professional organizations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Structure of Scientific Opinion on Climate Change&quot;/&gt; The study found that 97% of the 489 scientists surveyed agreed that global temperatures have risen over the past century.&lt;ref name=&quot;Structure of Scientific Opinion on Climate Change&quot;/&gt; Moreover, 84% agreed that &quot;human-induced greenhouse warming&quot; is now occurring.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Structure of Scientific Opinion on Climate Change&quot;/&gt; Only 5% disagreed with the idea that human activity is a significant cause of global warming.&lt;ref name=&quot;Structure of Scientific Opinion on Climate Change&quot;/&gt;

As described above, a small minority of scientists do disagree with the consensus. For example, [[Willie Soon]] and [[Richard Lindzen]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Lindzen RS |title=Can increasing carbon dioxide cause climate change? |journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America |volume=94 |issue=16 |pages=8335–42 |date=August 1997|pmid=11607742 |pmc=33750 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.94.16.8335|bibcode = 1997PNAS...94.8335L }}&lt;/ref&gt; say that there is insufficient proof for anthropogenic attribution. Generally this position requires new physical mechanisms to explain the observed warming.&lt;ref&gt;for example: {{Cite journal| doi = 10.1007/s00585-000-0583-z |title=Climate hypersensitivity to solar forcing? |year=2000 |last1=Soon |first1=W. |last2=Posmentier |first2=E. |last3=Baliunas |first3=S. |journal=Annales Geophysicae |volume=18 |pages=583–588| issue = 5|bibcode = 2000AnGeo..18..583S |citeseerx=10.1.1.353.2743 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Solar activity==
[[File:Solar irradiance and temperature 1880-2018.jpeg|alt=The graph shows the solar irradiance without a long-term trend. The 11-year solar cycle is also visible. The temperature, in contrast, shows an upward trend.|thumb|Solar irradiance (yellow) plotted together with temperature (red) over 1880 to 2018.]]
[[File:Evidence of human-induced global warming - patterns of temperature change produced by various atmospheric factors, 1958-1999 (USGCRP).png|thumb|right|Modelled simulation of the effect of various factors (including GHGs, Solar irradiance) singly and in combination, showing in particular that solar activity produces a small and nearly uniform warming, unlike what is observed.]]
[[Solar sunspot maximum]] occurs when the magnetic field of the Sun collapses and reverse as part of its average 11-year [[solar cycle]] (22 years for complete North to North restoration).

The role of the Sun in recent climate change has been looked at by climate scientists. Since 1978, [[solar variation|output from the Sun]] has been measured by [[satellite]]s&lt;ref name=nrc2008/&gt;{{Rp|6|date=November 2012}} significantly more accurately than was previously possible from the surface. These measurements indicate that the Sun's total [[solar irradiance]] has not increased since 1978, so the warming during the past 30 years cannot be directly attributed to an increase in total solar energy reaching the Earth (see graph above, left). In the three decades since 1978, the combination of solar and [[volcanic activity]] probably had a slight cooling influence on the climate.&lt;ref&gt;Global Climate Change, in {{Harvnb|Karl|others|2009}}, pp. 15–16.&lt;/ref&gt;

Climate models have been used to examine the role of the Sun in recent climate change.&lt;ref&gt;Hegerl, ''et al''., [http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/ch9.html Chapter 9: Understanding and Attributing Climate Change], [http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/faq-9-2.html Frequently Asked Question 9.2: Can the Warming of the 20th century be Explained by Natural Variability?], in {{Harvnb|IPCC AR4 WG1|2007}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
Models are unable to reproduce the rapid warming observed in recent decades when they only take into account variations in total solar irradiance and volcanic activity. Models are, however, able to simulate the observed 20th century changes in temperature when they include all of the most important external forcings, including human influences and natural forcings. As has already been stated, Hegerl ''et al.'' (2007) concluded that greenhouse gas forcing had &quot;very likely&quot; caused most of the observed global warming since the mid-20th century. In making this conclusion, Hegerl ''et al.'' (2007) allowed for the possibility that climate models had been underestimated the effect of solar forcing.&lt;ref&gt;Hegerl, ''et al''., [http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/ch9.html Chapter 9: Understanding and Attributing Climate Change], [http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/ch9s9-es.html Executive Summary], in
{{Harvnb|IPCC AR4 WG1|2007}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The role of solar activity in climate change has also been calculated over [[paleoclimatology|longer time periods]] using &quot;proxy&quot; datasets, such as [[tree rings]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |date=November 2009
 |author1=Simmon, R.  |author2=D. Herring
  |lastauthoramp=yes | title=Notes for slide number 5 titled &quot;Over 100 years of total solar irradiance data,&quot; in presentation, &quot;Human contributions to global climate change&quot;
 | url=http://www.climate.gov/#understandingClimate/presentationLibrary
 | publisher=Presentation library on the U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's Climate Services website
 | accessdate=23 June 2011| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20110703210729/http://www.climate.gov/| archivedate= 3 July 2011 | url-status= live}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
Models indicate that solar and volcanic forcings can explain periods of relative warmth and cold between [[Anno Domini|AD]]&amp;nbsp;1000 and 1900, but human-induced forcings are needed to reproduce the late-20th century warming.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | year=2006
 | chapter=10. Climate Forcings and Climate Models
 | title=Surface Temperature Reconstructions for the Last 2,000 Years
 | publisher=[[National Academies Press]]
 | location=Washington, D.C., USA
 | authors=Committee on Surface Temperature Reconstructions for the Last 2,000 Years, US National Research Council
 | chapter-url=https://books.nap.edu/openbook.php?record_id=11676&amp;page=109
|page=109
|isbn=0-309-66144-7
|accessdate=23 June 2011}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

Another line of evidence against the sun having caused recent climate change comes from looking at how temperatures at different levels in the Earth's atmosphere have changed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |date=November 2009
 |author1=Simmon, R.  |author2=D. Herring
  |lastauthoramp=yes | title=Notes for slide number 7, titled &quot;Satellite evidence also suggests greenhouse gas warming,&quot; in presentation, &quot;Human contributions to global climate change&quot;
 | url=http://www.climate.gov/#understandingClimate/presentationLibrary
 | publisher=Presentation library on the U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's Climate Services website
 | accessdate=23 June 2011| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20110703210729/http://www.climate.gov/| archivedate= 3 July 2011 | url-status= live}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
Models and observations (see figure above, middle) show that greenhouse gas results in warming of the lower atmosphere at the surface (called the [[troposphere]]) but cooling of the upper atmosphere (called the [[stratosphere]]).&lt;ref&gt;Hegerl ''et al.'', [http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/ch9.html Chapter 9: Understanding and Attributing Climate Change], [http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/faq-9-2.html Frequently Asked Question 9.2: Can the Warming of the 20th century be Explained by Natural Variability?], in {{Harvnb|IPCC AR4 WG1|2007}}. &lt;!-- Hegerl --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; [[ozone depletion|Depletion]] of the [[ozone layer]] by chemical [[refrigerant]]s has also resulted in a cooling effect in the stratosphere. If the Sun was responsible for observed warming, warming of the troposphere at the surface and warming at the top of the stratosphere would be expected as increase solar activity would replenish ozone and [[Nitrogen oxide|oxides of nitrogen]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Karl|others|2009}}, p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt; The stratosphere has a reverse temperature gradient than the troposphere so as the temperature of the troposphere cools with altitude, the stratosphere rises with altitude. [[Hadley cells]] are the mechanism by which equatorial generated ozone in the tropics (highest area of UV irradiance in the stratosphere) is moved poleward. Global climate models suggest that climate change may widen the Hadley cells and push the jetstream northward thereby expanding the tropics region and resulting in warmer, dryer conditions in those areas overall.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Celeste M. Johanson  |author2=Qiang Fu  |lastauthoramp=yes |title=Hadley Cell Widening: Model Simulations versus Observations |journal=Journal of Climate |year=2009 |volume=22 |issue=10 |pages=2713–25 |doi=10.1175/2008JCLI2620.1 |url=http://www.atmos.washington.edu/~qfu/Publications/jc.johanson.2009.pdf |bibcode = 2009JCli...22.2713J }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Non-consensus views==
[[File:Radiative-forcings.svg|thumb|right|alt=Refer to caption|Contribution of natural factors and human activities to [[radiative forcing]] of climate change.&lt;ref name=&quot;ipcc radiative forcing&quot; /&gt; Radiative forcing values are for the year 2005, relative to the pre-industrial era (1750).&lt;ref name=&quot;ipcc radiative forcing&quot; /&gt; The contribution of solar irradiance to radiative forcing is 5% the value of the combined radiative forcing due to increases in the atmospheric concentrations of carbon dioxide, methane and nitrous oxide.&lt;ref name=&quot;epa solar activity&quot; /&gt;]]

{{See also|Climate change denial|extraterrestrial atmospheres}}

[[Habibullo Abdussamatov]] (2004), head of space research at St. Petersburg's [[Pulkovo Observatory|Pulkovo Astronomical Observatory]] in Russia, has argued that the sun is responsible for recently observed climate change.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal
 |title=About the long-term coordinated variations of the activity, radius, total irradiance of the Sun and the Earth's climate
 |first=Habibullo I.
 |last=Abdussamatov
 |journal=Proceedings of the International Astronomical Union
 |date=June 2004
 |volume=223
 |doi=10.1017/S1743921304006775
 |pages=541–542}} &quot;The main cause of climate change during the last millennia is the corresponding cyclic variation of the 80- and 200-year component of irradiance correlated with activity. That is why, the contemporary (climate change) is not anomalous but is ordinary secular global warming.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Journalists for news sources [[canada.com]] (Solomon, 2007b),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
 |title=Look to Mars for the truth on global warming
 |last=Solomon
 |first=Lawrence
 |authorlink=Lawrence Solomon
 |date=2 February 2007
 |work=[[National Post]]
 |url=http://www.canada.com/nationalpost/story.html?id=edae9952-3c3e-47ba-913f-7359a5c7f723&amp;k=0
 |accessdate=2 March 2007
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070306233723/http://www.canada.com/nationalpost/story.html?id=edae9952-3c3e-47ba-913f-7359a5c7f723&amp;k=0
 |archivedate=6 March 2007
 |url-status=dead
}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[National Geographic News]] (Ravillious, 2007),&lt;ref name=natgeo&gt;{{Cite news
 |title=Mars Melt Hints at Solar, Not Human, Cause for Warming, Scientist Says
 |first=Kate
 |last=Ravilious
 |publisher=National Geographic News
 |date=28 February 2007
 |url=http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2007/02/070228-mars-warming.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[LiveScience]] (Than, 2007)&lt;ref name=than&gt;{{Cite news
 |title=Sun Blamed for Warming of Earth and Other Worlds
 |date=12 March 2007
 |first=Ker
 |last=Than
 |publisher=LiveScience.com
 |url=http://www.livescience.com/environment/070312_solarsys_warming.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; reported on the story of warming on [[Mars]]. In these articles, Abdussamatov was quoted. He stated that warming on Mars was evidence that global warming on Earth was being caused by changes in the sun.

Ravillious (2007)&lt;ref name=natgeo /&gt; quoted two scientists who disagreed with Abdussamatov: Amato Evan, a climate scientist at the [[University of Wisconsin–Madison]], in the US, and Colin Wilson, a [[planetary science|planetary physicist]] at [[Oxford University]] in the UK. According to Wilson, &quot;Wobbles in the orbit of Mars are the main cause of its climate change in the current era&quot; (see also [[orbital forcing]]).&lt;ref&gt;See also: {{Cite journal
 |first=Lori K.
 |last=Fenton
 |title=Global warming and climate forcing by recent of albedo changes on Mars
 |date=5 April 2007
 |journal=[[Nature (journal)|Nature]]
 |volume=446
 |issue=7136
 |doi=10.1038/nature05718
 |url=http://humbabe.arc.nasa.gov/~fenton/pdf/fenton/nature05718.pdf
 |pages=646–649
 |accessdate=9 May 2007
 |last2=Geissler
 |first2=Paul E.
 |last3=Haberle
 |first3=Robert M.
 |pmid=17410170
 |bibcode=2007Natur.446..646F
 |url-status=dead
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070708011126/http://humbabe.arc.nasa.gov/~fenton/pdf/fenton/nature05718.pdf
 |archivedate=8 July 2007
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Than (2007) quoted Charles Long, a climate physicist at [[Pacific Northwest National Laboratory|Pacific Northwest National Laboratories]] in the US, who disagreed with Abdussamatov.&lt;ref name=than /&gt;

Than (2007) pointed to the view of [[Benny Peiser]], a [[social anthropologist]] at [[Liverpool John Moores University]] in the UK.&lt;ref name=than /&gt; In his [[newsletter]], Peiser had cited a blog that had commented on warming observed on several planetary bodies in the [[Solar system]]. These included [[Neptune]]'s moon [[Triton (moon)|Triton]],&lt;ref&gt;See also: {{Cite news
 | title=MIT researcher finds evidence of global warming on Neptune's largest moon
 | date=24 June 1998
 | publisher=[[Massachusetts Institute of Technology|MIT]]
 | url=http://web.mit.edu/newsoffice/1998/triton.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jupiter]],&lt;ref&gt;See also: {{Cite news
 | title=New Storm on Jupiter Hints at Climate Change
 | first=Sara
 | last=Goudarzi
 | publisher=Space.com
 | date=4 May 2006
 | url=http://www.space.com/scienceastronomy/060504_red_jr.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pluto]]&lt;ref&gt;See also: {{Cite news
 | title=Pluto is undergoing global warming, researchers find
 | date=9 October 2002
 | publisher=[[Massachusetts Institute of Technology|MIT]]
 | url=http://web.mit.edu/newsoffice/2002/pluto.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Mars. In an e-mail interview with Than (2007), Peiser stated that:&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;I think it is an intriguing coincidence that warming trends have been observed on a number of very diverse planetary bodies in our solar system, (...) Perhaps this is just a fluke.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;Than (2007) provided alternative explanations of why warming had occurred on Triton, Pluto, Jupiter and Mars.

The [[US Environmental Protection Agency]] (US EPA, 2009) responded to public comments on climate change attribution.&lt;ref name=&quot;epa solar activity&quot;&gt;{{cite book
 | year=2009
 | contribution=3.2.2 Solar Irradiance
 | title=Volume 3: Attribution of Observed Climate Change
 | series=Endangerment and Cause or Contribute Findings for Greenhouse Gases under Section 202(a) of the Clean Air Act. EPA's Response to Public Comments
 | publisher=US Environmental Protection Agency
 | author=US Environmental Protection Agency
 | url=http://www.epa.gov/climatechange/endangerment/comments/volume3.html#2-2
 | accessdate=23 June 2011| archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110616210216/http://www.epa.gov/climatechange/endangerment/comments/volume3.html| archivedate=16 June 2011 | url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; A number of commenters had argued that recent climate change could be attributed to changes in solar irradiance. According to the US EPA (2009), this attribution was not supported by the bulk of the [[scientific literature]]. Citing the work of the IPCC (2007), the US EPA pointed to the low contribution of solar irradiance to radiative forcing since the start of the Industrial Revolution in 1750. Over this time period (1750 to 2005),&lt;ref&gt;IPCC, [http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/spm.html Summary for Policymakers],
[http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/spmsspm-human-and.html Human and Natural Drivers of Climate Change], in {{Harvnb|IPCC AR4 WG1|2007}}.&lt;/ref&gt; the estimated contribution of solar irradiance to radiative forcing was 5% the value of the combined radiative forcing due to increases in the atmospheric concentrations of carbon dioxide, methane and nitrous oxide (see graph opposite).

===Effect of cosmic rays===
[[Henrik Svensmark]] has suggested that the [[magnetic]] activity of the sun deflects [[cosmic ray]]s, and that this may influence the generation of [[cloud condensation nuclei]], and thereby have an effect on the climate.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|first=Nigel |last=Marsh |author2=Henrik, Svensmark |title=Cosmic Rays, Clouds, and Climate |journal=Space Science Reviews |volume=94 |pages=215–230 |date=November 2000 |url=http://mek.sitecore.dtu.dk/upload/institutter/space/forskning/05_afdelinger/sun-climate/full_text_publications/marsh2000(gcr-cloud-climate).pdf |doi=10.1023/A:1026723423896 |accessdate=17 April 2007 |issue=1–2 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140201221605/http://mek.sitecore.dtu.dk/upload/institutter/space/forskning/05_afdelinger/sun-climate/full_text_publications/marsh2000%28gcr-cloud-climate%29.pdf |archivedate=1 February 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The website [[ScienceDaily]] reported on a 2009 study that looked at how past changes in climate have been affected by the Earth's magnetic field.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.spacedaily.com/2006/090112183735.ojdq7esu.html|title=The earth's magnetic field impacts climate: Danish study |date=12 January 2009|publisher=SpaceDaily.com|accessdate=5 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Geophysicist Mads Faurschou Knudsen, who co-authored the study, stated that the study's results supported Svensmark's theory. The authors of the study also acknowledged that {{CO2}} plays an important role in climate change.

====Consensus view on cosmic rays====
The view that cosmic rays could provide the mechanism by which changes in solar activity affect climate is not supported by the literature.&lt;ref name=&quot;epa cosmic rays&quot;&gt;{{citation
 | at=[http://www.epa.gov/climatechange/endangerment/comments/volume3.html#3-36 Response 3–36, in Sec 3.2.2 Solar Irradiance]
 | title=EPA's Response to Public Comments
 | volume=3: Attribution of Observed Climate Change
}}, in {{harvnb|EPA|2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Solomon ''et al.'' (2007)&lt;ref&gt;{{citation
 | author=Solomon, S.
 | chapter-url=http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/tssts-2-4.html |chapter=TS.2.4 Radiative Forcing Due to Solar Activity and Volcanic Eruptions
 | title=Technical Summary
 | url=http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/ts.html
|display-authors=etal}}, in {{harvnb|IPCC AR4 WG1|2007|p=31}}&lt;/ref&gt; state:&lt;blockquote&gt;[..] the cosmic ray time series does not appear to correspond to global total cloud cover after 1991 or to global low-level cloud cover after 1994. Together with the lack of a proven physical mechanism and the plausibility of other causal factors affecting changes in cloud cover, this makes the association between galactic cosmic ray-induced changes in aerosol and cloud formation controversial&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Studies by Lockwood and Fröhlich (2007)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Lockwood|first=Mike|author2=Claus Fröhlich | title=Recent oppositely directed trends in solar climate forcings and the global mean surface air temperature|journal=Proceedings of the Royal Society A|volume=463|issue=2086| pages=2447–2460|quote=Our results show that the observed rapid rise in global mean temperatures seen after 1985 cannot be ascribed to solar variability, whichever of the mechanisms is invoked and no matter how much the solar variation is amplified| url=http://www.pubs.royalsoc.ac.uk/media/proceedings_a/rspa20071880.pdf| archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070926023811/http://www.pubs.royalsoc.ac.uk/media/proceedings_a/rspa20071880.pdf| url-status=dead| archive-date=26 September 2007|doi=10.1098/rspa.2007.1880|accessdate=21 July 2007|year=2007| bibcode=2007RSPSA.463.2447L}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Sloan and Wolfendale (2008)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|doi=10.1088/1748-9326/3/2/024001 | title=Testing the proposed causal link between cosmic rays and cloud cover|author1=T Sloan  |author2=A W Wolfendale |lastauthoramp=yes |journal=Environ. Res. Lett.|volume=3|issue=2|page=024001|year=2008|bibcode=2008ERL.....3d4001S|arxiv=0803.2298 }}&lt;/ref&gt; found no relation between warming in recent decades and cosmic rays. Pierce and Adams (2009)&lt;ref name=&quot;pierce adams 2009 cosmic rays&quot;&gt;Abstract, in {{harvnb|Pierce|Adams|2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; used a model to simulate the effect of cosmic rays on cloud properties. They concluded that the hypothesized effect of cosmic rays was too small to explain recent climate change.&lt;ref name=&quot;pierce adams 2009 cosmic rays&quot; /&gt; Pierce and Adams (2009)&lt;ref&gt;paragraph 18, in: 6. Discussion, in {{harvnb|Pierce|Adams|2009|p=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; noted that their findings did not rule out a possible connection between cosmic rays and climate change, and recommended further research.

Erlykin ''et al.'' (2009)&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Erlykin|others|2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; found that the evidence showed that connections between solar variation and climate were more likely to be mediated by direct variation of insolation rather than cosmic rays, and concluded: &quot;Hence within our assumptions, the effect of varying solar activity, either by direct solar irradiance or by varying cosmic ray rates, must be less than 0.07 °C since 1956, i.e. less than 14% of the observed global warming.&quot; Carslaw (2009)&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Carslaw|2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Pittock (2009)&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Pittock|2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; review the recent and historical literature in this field and continue to find that the link between cosmic rays and climate is tenuous, though they encourage continued research. US EPA (2009)&lt;ref name=&quot;epa cosmic rays&quot; /&gt; commented on research by Duplissy ''et al.'' (2009):&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Duplissy|others|2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;The CLOUD experiments at [[CERN]] are interesting research but do not provide conclusive evidence that cosmic rays can serve as a major source of cloud seeding. Preliminary results from the experiment (Duplissy et al., 2009) suggest that though there was some evidence of ion mediated nucleation, for most of the nucleation events observed the contribution of ion processes appeared to be minor. These experiments also showed the difficulty in maintaining sufficiently clean conditions and stable temperatures to prevent spurious aerosol bursts. There is no indication that the earlier Svensmark experiments could even have matched the controlled conditions of the CERN experiment. We find that the Svensmark results on cloud seeding have not yet been shown to be robust or sufficient to materially alter the conclusions of the assessment literature, especially given the abundance of recent literature that is skeptical of the cosmic ray-climate linkage&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Global warming|Energy}}
* [[Climate change adaptation]]
* [[Climate change denial]]
* [[Climate change mitigation]]
* [[Climate resilience]]
* [[Environmental impact of aviation]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
{{Div col|colwidth=30em}} {{refbegin|}}
*{{citation
 | ref=CITEREFCarslaw2009
 | author=Carslaw, K.
 | date=16 July 2009
 | title= Atmospheric physics: Cosmic rays, clouds, and climate
 | journal=Nature
 | volume=460
 | doi= 10.1038/460332a
|bibcode = 2009Natur.460..332C
 | issue=7253
 | pages=332–333}}, pp.&amp;nbsp;332–333. Referred to by {{harvnb|EPA|2009}}: {{citation
 | at=[http://www.epa.gov/climatechange/endangerment/comments/volume3.html#3-36 Response 3-36, in Sec 3.2.2 Solar Irradiance]
 | title=EPA's Response to Public Comments
 | volume=3: Attribution of Observed Climate Change
}}
* {{citation
 | year=2013
 | author=Cook, J.
 | title=Quantifying the consensus on anthropogenic global warming in the scientific literature
 | journal=Environmental Research Letters
 | volume=8
 | issue=2
 | ref=CITEREFCookothers2013
 | doi=10.1088/1748-9326/8/2/024024
|bibcode = 2013ERL.....8b4024C |display-authors=etal
 | pages=024024}}&lt;!--| accessdate=30 November 2013--&gt;. Open-access article.
*{{citation
 | ref=CITEREFDuplissyothers2009
 | author=Duplissy, J.
 | date=2 September 2009
 | title= Results from the CERN pilot CLOUD experiment
 | journal=Atmos. Chem. Phys. Discuss.
 | volume=9
 | url=http://www.atmos-chem-phys-discuss.net/9/18235/2009/acpd-9-18235-2009.html
 | doi=10.5194/acpd-9-18235-2009
 | issue=18235
|display-authors=etal
 | pages=18235–18270| hdl=10138/162406
 }}, pp.&amp;nbsp;18235–18270. Referred to by {{harvnb|EPA|2009}}: {{citation
 | at=[http://www.epa.gov/climatechange/endangerment/comments/volume3.html#3-36 Response 3–36, in Sec 3.2.2 Solar Irradiance]
 | title=EPA's Response to Public Comments
 | volume=3: Attribution of Observed Climate Change
}}
*{{citation
 | ref=CITEREFErlykinothers2009
 | author=Erlykin, A.D.
 | date=June 2009
 | title= The search for cosmic ray effects on clouds
 | journal= Journal of Atmospheric and Solar-Terrestrial Physics
 | volume=71
 | issue=8–9
 | doi=10.1016/j.jastp.2009.03.019
|bibcode = 2009JASTP..71..955E |display-authors=etal
 | pages=955–958}}, pp.&amp;nbsp;955–958. Referred to by {{harvnb|EPA|2009}}: {{citation
 | at=[http://www.epa.gov/climatechange/endangerment/comments/volume3.html#3-36 Response 3-36, in Sec 3.2.2 Solar Irradiance]
 | title=EPA's Response to Public Comments
 | volume=3: Attribution of Observed Climate Change
}}
*{{citation
 | ref=CITEREFHansenothers2012
 |author=James Hansen |authorlink=James Hansen |author2=Makiko Sato |author3=Reto Ruedy |date=August 2012 |title=Perception of climate change |journal=[[Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America]] |volume=109 |issue=32 |pages= E2415–E2423|publisher=[[National Academy of Sciences]] |doi=10.1073/pnas.1205276109 |pmid= 22869707|pmc= 3443154|bibcode = 2012PNAS..109E2415H }}
*{{citation
|year=2002
|last1= Houghton |first1= J.
|contribution= An Overview of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) and Its Process of Science Assessment
|series=Global Environmental Change
|editor1-last= Hester |editor1-first= R.E.
|editor2-last= Harrison |editor2-first= R.M.
|title=Issues in Environmental Science and Technology
|volume = 17
|publisher = The Royal Society of Chemistry
|isbn = 978-0-85404-280-7
|url= http://www.rsc.org/ebooks/archive/free/BK9780854042807/BK9780854042807-00001.pdf
}}.
* {{Citation
|year = 1996
|author = IPCC SAR WG1
|author-link = IPCC
|title = Climate Change 1995: The Science of Climate Change
|series = Contribution of Working Group I to the [[IPCC Second Assessment Report|Second Assessment Report]] of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change
|editor = Houghton, J.T.
|editor2 = Meira Filho, L.G.
|editor3 = Callander, B.A.
|editor4 = Harris, N.
|editor5 = Kattenberg, A.
|editor6 = Maskell, K.
|publisher = Cambridge University Press
|url = https://archive.org/details/climatechange1990000unse_p8l7
|isbn = 0-521-56433-6
|url-access = registration
}} (pb: {{ISBNT|0-521-56436-0}}).
* {{Citation 
 |year=2001 
 |author=IPCC TAR WG1 
 |author-link=IPCC 
 |title=Climate Change 2001: The Scientific Basis 
 |series=Contribution of Working Group I to the [[IPCC Third Assessment Report|Third Assessment Report]] of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change 
 |editor=Houghton, J.T. 
 |editor2=Ding, Y. 
 |editor3=Griggs, D.J. 
 |editor4=Noguer, M. 
 |editor5=van der Linden, P.J. 
 |editor6=Dai, X. 
 |editor7=Maskell, K. 
 |editor8=Johnson, C.A. 
 |publisher=Cambridge University Press 
 |url=https://archive.org/details/climatechange2000000unse 
 |isbn=0-521-80767-0 
 |url-status=dead 
 |url-access=registration 
 }} (pb: {{ISBNT|0-521-01495-6}}).
* {{Citation
| year = 2007
| author = IPCC AR4 WG1
| author-link = IPCC
| title = Climate Change 2007: The Physical Science Basis
| series = Contribution of Working Group I to the [[IPCC Fourth Assessment Report|Fourth Assessment Report]] of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change
| editor = Solomon, S. |editor2=Qin, D. |editor3=Manning, M. |editor4=Chen, Z. |editor5=Marquis, M. |editor6=Averyt, K.B. |editor7=Tignor, M. |editor8=Miller, H.L.
| publisher = Cambridge University Press
| url = http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/contents.html
| isbn = 978-0-521-88009-1
}} (pb: {{ISBNT|978-0-521-70596-7}}).
*{{citation
 |author=IPCC SREX 
 |year=2012 
 |title=Managing the Risks of Extreme Events and Disasters to Advance Climate Change Adaptation (SREX) 
 |editors=Field, C.B. 
 |url=http://ipcc-wg2.gov/SREX/report/full-report/ 
 |publisher=Cambridge University Press 
 |display-editors=etal 
 |url-status=dead 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121219055946/http://ipcc-wg2.gov/SREX/report/full-report/ 
 |archivedate=19 December 2012 
}}. Summary for Policymakers [http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/publications_and_data_reports.shtml available] in Arabic, Chinese, French, Russian, and Spanish.
* {{citation
 | year=2013
 | author=IPCC AR5 WG1
 | editor=Stocker, T.F.
 | title=Climate Change 2013: The Physical Science Basis. Working Group 1 (WG1) Contribution to the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) 5th Assessment Report (AR5)
 | url=http://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar5/wg1/
 | publisher=Cambridge University Press
 | ref=harv
|display-editors=etal}}. [http://www.climatechange2013.org/ Climate Change 2013 Working Group 1 website.]
*
* {{citation
 |date=n.d. 
 |author=OPR 
 |title=Office of Planning and Research (OPR) List of Organizations 
 |url=http://opr.ca.gov/s_listoforganizations.php 
 |publisher=OPR, Office of the Governor, State of California 
 |ref=harv 
 |accessdate=30 November 2013 
 |url-status=bot: unknown 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140401120753/http://opr.ca.gov/s_listoforganizations.php 
 |archivedate=1 April 2014 
}}. Archived page:  The source appears to incorrectly list the Society of Biology (UK) twice.
*{{citation
 | ref=CITEREFPierceAdams2009
 |author1=Pierce J.R. |author2=P.J. Adams  |last-author-amp=yes | date=May 2009
 | title=Can cosmic rays affect cloud condensation nuclei by altering new particle formation rates?
 | journal=Geophys. Res. Lett.
 | volume=36
 | issue=9
 |pages=L09820 | doi=10.1029/2009GL037946
|bibcode = 2009GeoRL..36.9820P |url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/031882e43ffc03f94d8e83020a5067c63815705d }}. L09820.
*{{citation
 | ref=CITEREFPittock2009
 | author=Pittock, B.
 | date=October 2009
 | title= Can solar variations explain variations in the Earth's climate? An editorial comment
 | journal= Climatic Change
 | volume=96
 | issue=4
 | doi= 10.1007/s10584-009-9645-8
 | pages=483–487
}}, pp.&amp;nbsp;483–487. Referred to by {{harvnb|EPA|2009}}: {{citation
 | at=[http://www.epa.gov/climatechange/endangerment/comments/volume3.html#3-36 Response 3-36, in Sec 3.2.2 Solar Irradiance]
 | title=EPA's Response to Public Comments
 | volume=3: Attribution of Observed Climate Change
}}
*{{citation
 |year=2006 
 |last=Stern 
 |first=N. 
 |title=Stern Review Report on the Economics of Climate Change (pre-publication edition) 
 |url=http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/stern_review_report.htm
 |archive-url=http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20100407172811/http://www.hm-treasury.gov.uk/stern_review_report.htm
 |archive-date=7 April 2010
 |publisher=HM Treasury 
 |location=London, UK 
 |url-status=dead 
}}
{{refend}}
{{div col end}}

'''Public-domain sources'''
{{Div col|colwidth=30em}} {{refbegin|}}
*{{Include-USGov
 | agency=US EPA
 | source={{citation
 | year=2009
 | title=Endangerment and Cause or Contribute Findings for Greenhouse Gases under Section 202(a) of the Clean Air Act. EPA's Response to Public Comments
 | publisher= US Environmental Protection Agency (EPA)
 | author=EPA
 | url=http://www.epa.gov/climatechange/endangerment/#comments
}}.
}}
*{{Include-USGov
 | agency=US Global Change Research Program ([[USGCRP]])
 | source={{cite book
|ref=CITEREFKarlothers2009
 | year=2009
 | title=Global Climate Change Impacts in the United States
 |editor1=Karl, T.R. |editor2=Melillo. J. |editor3=Peterson, T. |editor4=Hassol, S.J. | publisher=Cambridge University Press
 | isbn=978-0-521-14407-0
 | url= https://downloads.globalchange.gov/usimpacts/pdfs/climate-impacts-report.pdf
}}. Public-domain status of this report can be found on p.4 of source.
}}
*{{Include-USGov
 | agency=NOAA
 | source={{citation
 | title=Short-term Cooling on a Warming Planet
 | work=ClimateWatch Magazine
 | url=http://www.climatewatch.noaa.gov/article/2009/short-term-cooling-on-a-warming-planet
 | publisher=NOAA
 | last=Scott
 | first=M.
 | date=31 December 2009
 | access-date=22 September 2012
 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130219015155/http://www.climatewatch.noaa.gov/article/2009/short-term-cooling-on-a-warming-planet
 | archive-date=19 February 2013
 | url-status=dead
 }}
}}
{{refend}} {{div col end}}

==External links==
*[http://www.realclimate.org/index.php?p=160 How much of the recent CO2 increase is due to human activities?] (RealClimate, 2005)
*[http://www.epa.gov/climatechange Climate change and global warming] (U.S. EPA)

{{Global warming}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Attribution Of Recent Climate Change}}
[[Category:Climate change]]
[[Category:Environmental impact of the energy industry]]
[[Category:Global warming]]
[[Category:Climatology]]</text>
      <sha1>8gnxa10hmcu9revpb0gn275i9ykrq2n</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
