  <page>
    <title>Book of Alma</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3275</id>
    <revision>
      <id>934606197</id>
      <parentid>927742934</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-07T13:35:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>12.245.228.90</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{More citations needed|date=March 2010}}
[[File: Moroni - Book of Mormon.jpg|thumb|400px|Captain Moroni raises the &quot;Title of Liberty&quot;, as found in the 1910 book ''Cities in the Sun''.]]
{{Books of the Book of Mormon}}
'''The Book of Alma: The Son of Alma''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|æ|l|m|ə}}),&lt;ref&gt;Cj[https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/pronunciation?lang=eng LDS.org: &quot;Book of Mormon Pronunciation Guide&quot;] (retrieved 2012-02-25), [[Wikipedia:IPA for English|IPA]]-ified from «ăl´ma»&lt;/ref&gt; usually referred to as the '''Book of Alma''', is one of the books that make up the [[Book of Mormon]]. The title refers to [[Alma the Younger]], a prophet and &quot;chief judge&quot; of the Nephites. Alma is the longest book in the Book of Mormon and consists of sixty-three chapters,&lt;ref&gt;https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/title-page?lang=eng&lt;/ref&gt; taking up almost a third of the volume.

==Narrative==

===Historical outline===
The Book of Alma is the longest of all the books of the Book of Mormon, consisting of 63 chapters. The book records the first 39 years of what the [[Nephite]]s termed &quot;the reign of the judges&quot;, a period in which the Nephite nation adopted a constitutional theocratic government in which the judicial and executive branches of the government were combined.

The history of the book is outlined as follows:

====Challenges to the beginning of the republic====
The first four chapters, describe the rebellions of followers of [[Nehor]] and [[Amlici]]. Contrary to the dominant lay ministry that existed in the Nephite culture, Nehor established a church in which priests were given separate social status and were paid for their ministry. After killing a religious leader during a theological argument, Nehor was tried and executed for his crimes. The followers of Amlici resented the dominant political and religious parties and sought to reestablish the monarchy that the reign of the judges had replaced. [[Alma the Younger|Alma]], who was chief judge, governor, and high priest over the people of Nephi, led an army against Amlici and his followers and drove the rebellion out of the land.

====Ministry of Alma among the Nephites====
Towards the end of chapter four, Alma realizes that the affairs of the Church require his entire concentration. He resigns from his political office and appoints [[Various Book of Mormon people#Nephihah|Nephihah]] as chief judge and governor of the land.  Chapters 5-16 record sermons and missionary travels of Alma between 83 and 78 BC.  Alma and one of his converted followers, Amulek, provide important teachings about the atonement of Christ, overcoming pride and the natural man, retaining conversion, the resurrection of all men, and judgment day.  Later, their teachings about faith and worship in Alma 32-34 are important sources of instruction and insight.

====Ministry of the sons of Mosiah among the Lamanites====
Chapters 17 to 27 describe the missionary labors of the sons of [[King Mosiah II]] who was the last king over the people of Nephi before the peaceful transition of the nation from a monarchy to a republican form of government. The [[sons of Mosiah]], named Ammon, [[Aaron (Nephite)|Aaron]], [[Omner]] and [[Himni]], chose to devote themselves to missionary labors preaching to the people of the [[Lamanite]] nation, which periodically went to war against the Nephite nation. They lived and taught among the Lamanites between the years 91 and 77 BC.

====Ministry of Alma among the Zoramites====
Chapters 28 to 35 relate the account of a rebellion of a subgroup of the Nephite nation who called themselves [[Zoramites]]. The Zoramites believed in a form of predestination and taught that all others except their people would be damned. Their apostasy from the Church was conspiring against the plans to rebel against the Nephite government. Alma took two of his sons, the sons of Mosiah, Amulek, and [[Zeezrom]] on a mission among the Zoramites in an attempt to restore their loyalty to both the Church and the state.  Alma and his companions had some success among the poor class of Zoramites who were then exiled from the Zoramite community by the governing rich class of Zoramites. The wealthier Zoramites eventually defected and united with the Lamanites.

====Commandments of Alma to his children====
Chapters 36 to 42 record the teachings of Alma to his sons, [[Helaman]], [[Shiblon]], and [[Corianton]]. These teachings discuss the ministry and atonement of [[Jesus]], the laws of justice and mercy, the need for repentance, and the resurrection and judgment of all people.

====Period of war====

Chapters 43 to 62 record the struggles of the Nephite people during a war against the attacking Lamanite nation between the years of 74 and 57 BC. The Chief Captain (senior military commander) of the Nephites during this time was [[Captain Moroni]]. The Nephites were ultimately successful in their defense against the Lamanites.

====Conclusion====
Chapter 63 includes concluding historical notes covering the years 56 to 53 BC. This is largely a period of post-war reconstruction and exploration in the Nephite nation.

===Simple outline===

This outline is based on ''main sections'' and ''[[antagonist]] characters'' in the Book of Alma. There are two main features in this history, chapters 1 - 42 deal with Missionary Work, and chapters 43 - 63 contain the Wars. The history of the [[Zoramites]] provides a transition from Missionary Work to the War chapters of the Book of Alma. The two main sections also mirror the first two antagonist characters, Nehor (''religious agenda'') and Amlici (''political agenda'').

*'''Mission chapters''' ([https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/alma/4.19-20?lang=eng Alma 1-42])
**[[Nehor]]: rebels against the Church ([https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/alma/1.2,15?lang=eng Alma 1])
**[[Amlici]]: rebels against the Republic ([https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/alma/2.1?lang=eng Alma 2])
**[[Korihor]]: the [[AntiChrist]] ([https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/alma/30.12?lang=eng Alma 30])
*'''Zoramites''' ([https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/alma/31.1?lang=eng Alma 31 - 43])
**[[Zoram]]: the Apostate Nephites  ''religious''  ([https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/alma/31.1?lang=eng Alma 31])
**[[Zerahemnah]]: the war leader of the Zoramites  ''political'' ([https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/alma/43.5?lang=eng Alma 43])
*'''War chapters''' ([https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/alma/43.3?lang=eng Alma 43-63])
**[[Amalickiah]]: the man who wants to be king ([https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/alma/46.3?lang=eng Alma 46])
**[[Ammoron]]: the vengeful brother of Amalickiah ([https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/alma/52.3?lang=eng Alma 52])

==Characters==
{{Expand list|date=August 2008}}

===Protagonist===
{{Div col|colwidth=20em}}
*[[Alma the Younger]]
*[[Gideon (Book of Mormon)|Gideon]]
*[[Nephihah]]
*[[Sons of Mosiah]]
**[[Ammon (Book of Mormon)|Ammon]]
**[[Aaron (Nephite)|Aaron&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;]]
**[[Omner]]
**[[Himni]]
*[[Amulek]]
*[[Zoram|Zoram&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;]]
*[[Ammon]]
*Melek
*[[Lehonti]]
*[[Helaman]]
*[[Shiblon]]
*[[Corianton]]
*[[Captain Moroni]]
*[[Two thousand stripling warriors]]
*[[Teancum]]
*[[Laman|Laman&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;]]
*[[Gid (Book of Mormon)|Gid]]
*[[Teomner]]
*[[Pahoran]]
*[[Hagoth]]
*[[Moronihah]]
{{div col end}}

===Antagonist===
{{Div col|colwidth=20em}}
*[[Nehor]]
*[[Amlici]]
*[[Korihor]]
*[[Zoram]]
*[[Zerahemnah]]
*[[Amalickiah]]
*[[Morianton]]
*[[Ammoron]]
*[[Captain Moroni#King-men|King-men]]
*[[Gidoni]]
{{div col end}}

===Converts===
*[[Zeezrom]]
*[[Lamoni]]
*[[Anti-Nephi-Lehi]]

==Doctrine==

=== 50 questions of Alma ===
In {{lds|Alma|alma|5}}, Alma the Younger speaks to the people of Zarahemla in which he asks 50 rhetorical questions, which are widely cited in the LDS church.

===Faith as a seed===

Alma's sermon on faith to the Zoramites in {{lds|Alma|alma|32}} is widely used to explain the process of developing faith.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url= https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/ensign/2001/04/faith-in-jesus-christ |title= Faith in Jesus Christ |first= James O. |last= Mason |authorlink= James O. Mason | date= April 2001 |journal= [[Ensign (LDS magazine)|Ensign]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Investigators are invited to try a similar experiment of faith in order to come to develop a testimony. It is worth noting that Alma doesn't compare faith to a seed, he compares the word to a seed ({{lds|Alma|alma|32|35}}), although this is a common misconception.

===Nephite temple ceremony===
According to [[John W. Welch]], based on the appearance of the following elements in Alma 12-13, the Nephite temple ceremony utilized familiar temple motifs, including:&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |authorlink= John W. Welch |first= John W. |last= Welch |contribution= The Temple in the Book of Mormon |contribution-url= http://publications.maxwellinstitute.byu.edu/fullscreen/?pub=2246&amp;index=14 |title= Temples of the Ancient World |url= http://publications.maxwellinstitute.byu.edu/book/temples-of-the-ancient-world/ |editor-first= Donald W. |editor-last= Parry |editor-link=  Donald W. Parry |year= 1994 |publisher= [[FARMS]] and Deseret Book |isbn= 087579811X |pages= 364–366}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# Abundant creation imagery regarding the fall of Adam and Eve ({{lds|Alma|alma|12|22|26}})
# The redemption ({{lds|Alma|alma|12|25|33}})
# The issuance of commandments ({{lds|Alma|alma|12|31|32}})
# One's calling ({{lds|Alma|alma|13|3|8}})
# Clothing ({{lds|Alma|alma|13|11|12}})
# The facing of judgment ({{lds|Alma|alma|12|14|,32-35|||x}})
# Symbolic entrance into the presence of God ({{lds|Alma|alma|12|36}}; {{lds||alma|13|12}})

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==

*{{Citation
 | editor-last= Nyman 
 | editor-first= Monte
 | editor-link= Monte S. Nyman
 | editor2-last= Tate
 | editor2-first= Charles D.
 | title= The Book of Mormon: Alma, the Testimony of the Word
 | url= https://rsc.byu.edu/out-print/book-mormon-alma-testimony-word
 | series= Book of Mormon Symposium Series (Volume 6)
 | location= Provo, Utah
 | publisher= [[Religious Studies Center]], [[Brigham Young University]]
 | year= 1992
 | isbn= 0-8849-4841-2
 | oclc= 26785256
}}
*{{Citation
 |last= Cheryl
 |first= Brown
 |contribution= Book of Mormon: Book of Alma
 |contribution-url= http://contentdm.lib.byu.edu/cdm/ref/collection/EoM/id/5531
 |pages= 150–152
 |editor1-last= Ludlow
 |editor1-first= Daniel H
 |editor1-link= Daniel H. Ludlow
 |title= [[Encyclopedia of Mormonism]]
 |location= New York
 |publisher= [[Macmillan Publishing]]
 |year= 1992
 |isbn= 0-02-879602-0
 |oclc= 24502140
}}.

==External links==
*{{wikisource-inline|Book of Mormon/Book of Alma|Book of Alma}}
* [https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/bofm/alma/1 The Book of Mormon: The Book of Alma] at LDS.org
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_DVC9AhxH-0 Story of the Book of Mormon - Alma]: An educational summary of this book

{{DEFAULTSORT:Book Of Alma}}
[[Category:Books of the Book of Mormon|Alma]]</text>
      <sha1>nfv53p2wdyinlmgamrndrooy6f49p8f</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
