  <page>
    <title>Running amok</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3253</id>
    <revision>
      <id>936613247</id>
      <parentid>933976999</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-19T22:59:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Moorespoint</username>
        <id>4132682</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Malaysian/Indonesian origin */ Grammar: Fix presently (meaning at present) to currently (meaning now)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Culture-bound syndrome native to South-east Asia}}
{{Redirect|Amok}}
'''Running amok''', sometimes referred to as simply '''amok''' or having '''gone amok''',&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid984220&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Carr JE, Tan EK |title=In search of the true amok: amok as viewed with the Javanese culture |journal=Am J Psychiatry |volume=133 |issue=11 |pages=1295–1299 |date=November 1976 |pmid=984220 |doi= 10.1176/ajp.133.11.1295}}&lt;/ref&gt; also spelled '''amuck''' or '''amuk''', from the [[Southeast Asia]]n [[Austronesian languages]] (especially [[Malaysian language|Malaysian]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.todayifoundout.com/index.php/2013/02/origin-of-the-phrase-run-amok/ | title=Origin of the Phrase &quot;Run Amok&quot; | publisher=Vacca Foeda Media | accessdate=7 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Indonesian language|Indonesian]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://kbbi.web.id/amuk|title=Arti kata amuk|language=id|website=Kamus Besar Bahasa Indonesia}}&lt;/ref&gt;), is &quot;an episode of sudden mass assault against people or objects usually by a single individual following a period of brooding that has traditionally been regarded as occurring especially in Malay culture but is now increasingly viewed as psychopathological behavior&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/medical/amok | title=amok | publisher=Merriam-Webster, Inc | year=2013 | accessdate=7 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The syndrome of &quot;Amok&quot; is found in the ''[[Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders]]'' (DSM-IV TR).&lt;ref name=&quot;Appendix I: Outline for Cultural Formulation and Glossary of Culture-Bound Syndromes&quot;&gt;{{cite book|year=2000|title=Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-IV-TR)|volume=1|edition=4th|doi=10.1176/appi.books.9780890423349.7060|chapter-url=http://www.psychiatryonline.com/content.aspx?aID=14123&amp;searchStr=amok#14123|archive-date=June 5, 2007|archive-url=https://archive.is/20070605073224/http://www.psychiatryonline.com/content.aspx?aID=14123&amp;searchStr=amok%2314123#14123|url-status=dead|chapter=Appendix I: Outline for Cultural Formulation and Glossary of Culture-Bound Syndromes|isbn=0-89042-334-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; The phrase is often used in a less serious manner when describing something that is wildly out of control or causing a frenzy (e.g., a dog tearing up the living room furniture might be termed as &quot;running amok&quot;).

== Malaysian/Indonesian origin ==
Amok originated from the Malaysian/Indonesian word ''meng-âmuk'', which when roughly defined means &quot;to make a furious and desperate charge&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Hempel A.A., Levine R.D., Meloy J.D., Westermeyer J.D. | year = 2000 | title = Cross-cultural review of sudden mass assault by a single individual in the oriental and occidental cultures | url = | journal = Journal of Forensic Sciences | volume = 45 | issue = 3| pages = 582–588 | doi = 10.1520/JFS14732J }}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Malaysian and Indonesian cultures, amok was rooted in a deep spiritual belief.&lt;ref&gt;Van Loon, F.H.G. (1927). &quot;Amok and Latah&quot;. Retrieved March 30, 2013 from PsychINFO. [http://huie.hsu.edu:2308/ehost/detail?vid=3&amp;sid=a71ca420-96ff-40e4-be67-3ac88801c158%40sessionmgr12&amp;hid=3&amp;bdata=JnNpdGU9ZWhvc3QtbGl2ZQ%3d%3d#db=psyh&amp;AN=2006-01643-010]{{Dead link|date=August 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; They believed that amok was caused by the ''hantu belian'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Pusat Rujukan Persuratan Melayu: hantu belian|url=http://prpm.dbp.gov.my/Search.aspx?k=hantu+belian|publisher=Dewan Bahasa dan Pustaka|accessdate=6 November 2011|location=Malaysia|language=Malay, English|quote=hantu belian}}&lt;/ref&gt; which was an evil [[tiger]] spirit that entered one’s body and caused the heinous act. As a result of the belief, those in Indonesian culture tolerated amok and dealt with the after-effects with no ill will towards the assailant.&lt;ref name=&quot;ncbi&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last = Saint Martin | first = Michael | year = 1999 | title = Running Amok: A Modern Perspective on a Culture-Bound Syndrome | journal = Journal of Clinical Psychiatry | issn = 0160-6689| pmc = 181064 | volume = 1 | issue = 3 | pmid = 15014687 | pages = 66–70 | doi=10.4088/pcc.v01n0302}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although commonly used in a colloquial and less-violent sense, the phrase is particularly associated with a specific sociopathic [[culture-bound syndrome]] in the cultures of [[Culture of Malaysia|Malaysia]], [[Culture of Indonesia|Indonesia]] and [[Culture of Brunei|Brunei]]. In a typical case of ''running amok'', an individual (often male), having shown no previous sign of anger or any inclination to violence, will acquire a weapon (traditionally a sword or dagger, but currently any of a variety of weapons) and in a sudden frenzy, will attempt to kill or seriously injure anyone he encounters and himself.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |pmc=181064|year=1999|last1=Saint Martin|first1=M.L.|title=Running Amok: A Modern Perspective on a Culture-Bound Syndrome|journal=Primary Care Companion to the Journal of Clinical Psychiatry|volume=1|issue=3|pages=66–70|pmid=15014687|doi=10.4088/pcc.v01n0302}}&lt;/ref&gt; Amok typically takes place in a well populated or crowded area. Amok episodes of this kind normally end with the attacker being killed by bystanders or committing [[suicide]], eliciting theories that amok may be a form of intentional suicide in cultures where suicide is heavily stigmatized.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.medterms.com/script/main/art.asp?articlekey=23464 |title=Definition of Amok |publisher=Medterms.com |date= |accessdate=2018-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Those who do not commit suicide and are not killed typically lose consciousness, and upon regaining consciousness, claim amnesia.

An early Western description of the practice appears in the journals of [[James Cook|Captain James Cook]], a British explorer, who encountered amok firsthand in 1770 during a voyage around the world. Cook writes of individuals behaving in a reckless, violent manner, without cause and &quot;indiscriminately killing and maiming villagers and animals in a frenzied attack.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, Y. (Ed.). (2006). ''Encyclopedia of Multicultural Psychology''. University of Kansas: Sage Publications&lt;/ref&gt;

A widely accepted explanation links amok with male [[honor]] (amok by women and children is virtually unknown).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Alexanra Ringe|first=Carrie McLaren|title=Curious Mental Illnesses Around the World|url=http://www.stayfreemagazine.org/archives/21/mental_illness.html|publisher=stayfreemagazone.org|accessdate=March 25, 2013|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121218053501/http://www.stayfreemagazine.org/archives/21/mental_illness.html|archive-date=2012-12-18|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Running amok would thus be both a way of escaping the world (since perpetrators were normally killed or committed suicide) and re-establishing one's reputation as a man to be feared and respected.

== Contemporary syndrome ==
&quot;Running amok&quot; is used to refer to the behavior of someone who, in the grip of strong emotion, obtains a weapon and begins attacking people indiscriminately, often with multiple fatalities.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; An episode of amok may be triggered by a period of depression or highly aggressive behavior. The slang terms ''[[going postal]]'' or ''going ballistic'' are similar in scope.
Police describe such an event as a [[spree killer|killing spree]]. If the individual is seeking death, an alternate method is often &quot;[[suicide by cop]]&quot;.

Amok is often described as a culture-bound (or culture-specific) syndrome,&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15014687&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Saint Martin ML |title=Running Amok: A Modern Perspective on a Culture-Bound Syndrome |journal=Prim Care Companion J Clin Psychiatry |volume=1 |issue=3 |pages=66–70 |date=June 1999 |pmid=15014687 |pmc=181064 |doi= 10.4088/pcc.v01n0302|url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid1427677&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Gaw AC, Bernstein RL |title=Classification of amok in DSM-IV |journal=Hosp Community Psychiatry |volume=43 |issue=8 |pages=789–793 |date=August 1992 |pmid=1427677 |url=http://ps.psychiatryonline.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=1427677 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120220142835/http://ps.psychiatryonline.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=1427677 |url-status=dead |archive-date=2012-02-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt; which is a psychological condition whose manifestation is strongly shaped by cultural factors. Other reported culture-bound syndromes are [[latah]] and [[Penis panic|koro]]. Amok is also sometimes considered one of the subcategories of [[dissociative disorders]] (cross-cultural variant).

== Officially classified as a psychiatric condition ==
In 1849, amok was officially classified as a psychiatric condition based on numerous reports and case studies that showed the majority of individuals who committed amok were, in some sense, mentally ill.&lt;ref name=&quot;ncbi&quot; /&gt; The modern [[DSM-IV]] method of [[classification of mental disorders]] contains two official types of amok disorder; beramok and amok. Beramok is considered to be the more common of the two and is associated with the depression and sadness resulting from a loss and the subsequent brooding process. Loss includes, but is not limited to, the death of a spouse or loved one, divorce, loss of a job, money, power, etc. Beramok is associated with mental issues of severe depression or other mood disorders. Amok, the rarer form, is believed to stem from rage, insult, or a vendetta against a person, society, or object for a wide variety of reasons. Amok has been more closely associated with psychosis, personality disorders, bipolar disorder, and delusions.&lt;ref name=&quot;ncbi&quot; /&gt;

== Historical and cross-cultural comparisons ==
Early travelers in Asia sometimes describe a kind of military amok, in which soldiers apparently facing inevitable defeat suddenly burst into a frenzy of violence which so startled their enemies that it either delivered victory or at least ensured what the soldier in that culture considered an honourable death.

An example would be during the [[Battle of Bukit Chandu]] in Singapore during WWII when 41 outnumbered soldiers of the Malay Regiment, led by [[Adnan Saidi]], charged and went all out against a 13 000 strong invading Japanese Army. They continued the fight armed with just knives and bayonets for three days before they were finally defeated.

This form of amok appears to resemble the Scandinavian ''[[Berserker]]'', the ''cafard'' or ''cathard'' (Polynesia), ''mal de pelea'' (Puerto Rico), and ''iich'aa'' (Navaho).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.as.ua.edu/ant/ant100/pdf/MedicalAnthropology.pdf |title=Medical Anthropology: Culture-bound syndromes |accessdate=2009-04-29 }}{{dead link|date=June 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In contemporary [[Indonesia]], the term ''amok'' (''amuk'') generally refers not to individual violence, but to frenzied violence by mobs. Indonesians now commonly use the term 'gelap mata' (literally 'darkened eyes') to refer to individual amok. [[Laurens van der Post]] experienced the phenomenon in the East Indies and wrote in 1955:

{{quote|'Gelap mata', the Dark Eye, is an expression used in Sumatra and Java to describe a curious and disturbing social phenomenon. Socially speaking, the Malays, Sumatrans and Javanese are the best behaved people I have ever encountered. On the surface they are an extremely gentle, refined, submissive people. In fact the word 'Malay' comes from 'malu', 'gentle', and gentleness is a quality prized above all others among the Malays and their neighbours. In their family life, in their submission to traditional and parental authority, in their communal duties, they are among the most obedient people on earth. But every now and then something very disturbing happens. A man who has behaved in this obliging manner all his life and who has always done his duty by the outside world to perfection, suddenly finds it impossible to keep doing so. Overnight he revolts against goodness and dutifulness.&lt;ref&gt;[[Laurens van der Post|van der Post, Laurens]], ''The Dark Eye in Africa'' (London, 1955), pp. 51–52&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In the [[Philippines]], ''amok'' also means unreasoning murderous rage by an individual. In 1876, the Spanish governor-general of the Philippines [[José Malcampo]] coined the term ''[[juramentado]]'' for the behavior (from ''juramentar'' – &quot;to take an oath&quot;), surviving into modern [[Philippine languages]] as ''huramentado''.&lt;ref name=Hurley14&gt;{{cite book |last1=Hurley |first1=Vic |title=Swish of the Kris; The Story of the Moros |url=http://www.nikhef.nl/~tonvr/keris/keris2/swish/index.html |accessdate=April 17, 2011 |edition= |series= |volume= |issue= |year=1936 |month= |origyear= |publisher=E.P. Hutton |location= |isbn= |oclc= |doi= |id= |page= |pages= |chapter=Chapter 14: Juramentados and Amuks |chapterurl=http://www.nikhef.nl/~tonvr/keris/keris2/swish/swk2-14.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20050215042345/http://www.nikhef.nl/~tonvr/keris/keris2/swish/swk2-14.html |archivedate=February 15, 2005 |quote= |ref= }}&lt;/ref&gt; It has historically been linked with the [[Moro people]] of [[Mindanao]], particularly in the [[Sulu Archipelago]], in connection with societal and cultural pressures.&lt;ref name=Tarling231&gt;{{cite book |last1=Tarling |first1=Nicholas |title=The Cambridge History of Southeast Asia: The Nineteenth and Twentieth centuries |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=pBfsaw64rjMC&amp;pg=PA231 |accessdate=May 25, 2009 |year=1992 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=0-521-35506-0 |page=231 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Norse [[Berserker]]s and the [[Zulu people|Zulu]] battle trance are two other examples of the tendency of certain groups to work themselves up into a killing frenzy.

According to the [[Encyclopædia Britannica Eleventh Edition|''Encyclopædia Britannica'' Eleventh Edition]], some notable cases have occurred among the [[Rajputs]]. In 1634, the eldest son of the [[raja]] of [[Jodhpur]] ran amok at the court of [[Shah Jahan]], failing in his attack on the emperor, but killing five of his officials. During the 18th century, again, at [[Hyderabad, Sindh|Hyderabad]] (Sind), two envoys, sent by the Jodhpur chief in regard to a quarrel between the two states, stabbed the prince and twenty-six of his suite before they themselves fell.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;&gt;{{EB1911|inline=y|wstitle=Amuck, Running|volume=1|page=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Active shooter]]
* [[Banzai charge]]
* [[Berserker]]
* [[Grisi siknis]]
* [[Going postal]]
* [[Suicide by cop]]
* [[Juramentado]]
* [[List of rampage killers]]
* [[Osama bin Laden (elephant)]]
* [[Psychogenic non-epileptic seizures]]
* [[Spree killer]]
* [[Tantrum]]
* [[Amok Time]]

== Notes ==
{{Reflist}}

== References ==
{{wiktionary|amok}}
* {{EB1911|wstitle=Amuck, Running}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Culture-bound syndromes]]
[[Category:Malay words and phrases]]
[[Category:Rampages]]</text>
      <sha1>k1t34hls8qkpit2hhl6bav1ybbe4ztc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
