  <page>
    <title>Bonn</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3295</id>
    <restrictions>move=:edit=</restrictions>
    <revision>
      <id>939944994</id>
      <parentid>939476070</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-09T17:39:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lipaosatamate</username>
        <id>38506914</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* 1951 to present */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about|the city in Germany}}
{{short description|Place in North Rhine-Westphalia, Germany}}
{{Infobox German location
|type          = city
|name          = Bonn
|German_name   = 
|image_photo   = Bonn-Bundesviertel, Luftaufnahme 2010.jpg
|image_caption = A view over the ''Bundesviertel'' (the location of the federal government presence in Bonn)
|image_coa     = DEU Bonn COA.svg
|image_flag    = Flagge der kreisfreien Stadt Bonn.svg
|image_plan    = North rhine w BN.svg
|plantext      = Bonn within North Rhine-Westphalia
|coordinates   = {{coord|50|44|N|7|6|E|type:city_region:DE-NW|display=inline,title}}
|state         = Nordrhein-Westfalen
|region        = Cologne
|district      = Kreisfreie Stadt
|elevation     = 60
|area          = 141.06
|Gemeindeschlüssel = 05314000
&lt;!--
|population    = 311287
|Stand         = 2013-12-31
filled via Gemeindeschlüssel --&gt;
|postal_code   = 53111–53229
|PLZ-alt       = 5300
|area_code     = 0228
|licence       = BN
|website       = [https://www.bonn.de/ www.bonn.de]
|mayor = Ashok-Alexander Sridharan
|Bürgermeistertitel = [[Lord Mayor]]
|party         = CDU
|year          = 1st century BC
|category      =
}}
The [[Federal city|Federal City]] of '''Bonn''' ({{IPA-de|bɔn|-|De-Bonn.ogg}}) is a city on the banks of the [[Rhine]] in the [[Germany|German]] state of [[North Rhine-Westphalia]], with a population of over 300,000. About {{convert|24|km|0|abbr=on}} south-southeast of [[Cologne]], Bonn is in the southernmost part of the [[Rhine-Ruhr]] region, Germany's largest metropolitan area, with over 11 million inhabitants. It is famously known as the birthplace of [[Ludwig Van Beethoven|Ludwig van Beethoven]] in 1770. He spent his childhood and teenage years in Bonn.

Founded in the 1st century BC as a [[Germania Inferior|Roman settlement]], Bonn is one of Germany's oldest cities. From 1597 to 1794, Bonn was the capital of the [[Electorate of Cologne]], and residence of the Archbishops and Prince-electors of [[Archbishopric of Cologne|Cologne]]. From 1949 to 1990, Bonn was the [[Capital of Germany|capital]] of [[West Germany]], and Germany's present constitution, the [[Basic Law for the Federal Republic of Germany|Basic Law]], was declared in the city in 1949. The era when Bonn served as the capital of West Germany is referred to by historians as the '''Bonn Republic'''.&lt;ref&gt;The Bonn Republic&amp;nbsp;— West German democracy, 1945-1990, Anthony James Nicholls, Longman, 1997&lt;/ref&gt; From 1990 to 1999, Bonn served as the seat of government – but no longer capital – of [[German reunification|reunited Germany]].

Because of a [[Berlin-Bonn Act|political compromise]] following the reunification, the German federal government maintains a substantial presence in Bonn. Roughly a third of all ministerial jobs are located in Bonn {{as of|2019|lc=y}},&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.tagesschau.de/inland/bonn-berlin-gesetz-101.html|title=Bonn-Berlin-Gesetz: Dieselbe Prozedur wie jedes Jahr|last=tagesschau.de|website=tagesschau.de|language=de|access-date=2019-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the city is considered a second, unofficial, [[Capital of Germany|capital]] of the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cowell&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/24/world/europe/24berlin.html |title=In Germany's Capitals, Cold War Memories and Imperial Ghosts | work=[[The New York Times]] |first=Alan |last=Cowell |date=2011-06-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bonn is the secondary seat of the [[President of Germany|President]], the [[Chancellor of Germany|Chancellor]], the [[Bundesrat of Germany|Bundesrat]] and the primary seat of six federal government ministries and twenty federal authorities. The title of Federal City ({{lang-de|Bundesstadt}}) reflects its important political status within Germany.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://webarchiv.bundestag.de/archive/2008/0912/bau_kunst/debatte/bd_antr2.html|title=Deutscher Bundestag: Berlin-Debatte / Antrag Vollendung der Einheit Deutschlands, Drucksache 12/815|last=Bundestag|first=Deutscher|website=webarchiv.bundestag.de|language=de|access-date=2017-02-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The headquarters of [[Deutsche Post DHL]] and [[Deutsche Telekom]], both [[DAX|DAX-listed]] corporations, are in Bonn. The city is home to the [[University of Bonn]] and a total of 20 [[United Nations]] institutions, the highest number in all of Germany.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.auswaertiges-amt.de/de/aussenpolitik/internationale-organisationen/uno/03-uno-in-deutschland/-/205650|title=Übersicht: Die Vereinten Nationen (VN) in Deutschland|last=Amt|first=Auswärtiges|website=Auswärtiges Amt|language=de|access-date=2020-02-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; These institutions include the headquarters for Secretariat of the UN Framework Convention Climate Change (UNFCCC), the Secretariat of the UN Convention to Combat Desertification (UNCCD), and the UN Volunteers programme.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unbonn.org/organizations UNBonn.org]&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Geography==

{{wide image|General view over bonn.jpg|900px|View over central Bonn as seen from the Stadthaus, including the [[Siebengebirge]],  a hill range on the east bank of the [[Middle Rhine]].|5=center}}

===Topography===
Situated in the southernmost part of the [[Rhine-Ruhr]] region, Germany's largest metropolitan area with over 11 million inhabitants, Bonn lies within the [[States of Germany|German state]] of [[North Rhine-Westphalia]], close to the border with [[Rhineland-Palatinate]]. Spanning an area of more {{convert|141.2|km2|0|abbr=on}} on both sides of the river [[Rhine]], almost three quarters of the city lies on the river's left bank.

To the south and to the west, Bonn is bordering the [[Eifel|Eifel region]] which encompasses the [[Rhineland Nature Park]]. To the north, Bonn borders the [[Cologne Lowland]]. Natural borders are constituted by the river [[Sieg]] to the north-east and by the [[Siebengebirge]] (also known as the Seven Hills) to the east. The largest extension of the city in north-south dimensions is {{convert|15|km|0|abbr=on}} and {{convert|12.5|km|0|abbr=on}} in west-east dimensions. The city borders have a total length of {{convert|61|km|0|abbr=on}}. The geographical centre of Bonn is the Bundeskanzlerplatz ''(Chancellor Square)'' in Bonn-Gronau.

=== Administration ===
The [[States of Germany|German state]] of [[North Rhine-Westphalia]] is divided into five [[Regierungsbezirk|governmental districts]] ({{lang-de|Regierungsbezirk}}), and Bonn is part of the [[Regierungsbezirk Köln|governmental district of Cologne]] ({{lang-de|Regierungsbezirk Köln}}). Within this governmental district, the city of Bonn is an [[List of districts of Germany|urban district]] in its own right. The urban district of Bonn is then again divided into four administrative municipal districts ({{lang-de|Stadtbezirk}}). These are Bonn, Bonn-Bad Godesberg, Bonn-Beuel and Bonn-Hardtberg.
In 1969, the independent towns of [[Bad Godesberg]] and Beuel as well as several villages were incorporated into Bonn, resulting in a city more than twice as large as before.
{| class=&quot;wikitable zebra&quot;
|+Administrative divisions of the Federal City of Bonn&lt;!--Please do not add any sub-districts, as this is the official count.--&gt;
!Municipal district ''(Stadtbezirk)''
!Coat of arms
!Population &lt;small&gt;(as of December 2014)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Wohnberechtigte Bevölkerung in der Stadt Bonn am 31.12.2014 |language=German |periodical=bonn.de |publisher=Stadt Bonn |url=http://www2.bonn.de/statistik/default.asp?2.1 |accessdate=2016-02-02 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140227103913/http://www2.bonn.de/statistik/default.asp?2.1 |archive-date=2014-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;
!Sub-district ''(Stadtteil)''
|-
|[[Bad Godesberg]]
| align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:Wappen-bezirk-badgodesberg.svg|35px|Wappen des Stadtbezirks Bad Godesberg]]
| align=&quot;right&quot; |73.172
|Alt-Godesberg, [[Friesdorf (Bonn)|Friesdorf]], Godesberg-Nord, Godesberg-Villenviertel, Heiderhof, Hochkreuz, Lannesdorf, Mehlem, Muffendorf, Pennenfeld, Plittersdorf, Rüngsdorf, Schweinheim
|-
|[[Beuel]]
| align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:Wappen-bezirk-beuel.svg|35px|Wappen des Stadtbezirks Beuel]]
| align=&quot;right&quot; |66.695
|Beuel-Mitte, Beuel-Ost, Geislar, Hoholz, Holtorf, [[Holzlar]], [[Küdinghoven]], Limperich, [[Oberkassel (Bonn)|Oberkassel]], Pützchen/Bechlinghoven, Ramersdorf, [[Schwarzrheindorf/Vilich-Rheindorf]], Vilich, Vilich-Müldorf
|-
|[[Bonn (municipal district)|Bonn]]
| align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:Bonn1969.svg|35px|Wappen des Stadtbezirks Bonn]]
| align=&quot;right&quot; |149.733
|[[Auerberg]], Bonn-Castell (known until 2003 as Bonn-Nord), Bonn-Zentrum, Buschdorf, Dottendorf, Dransdorf, [[Endenich]], Graurheindorf, Gronau, Ippendorf, [[Kessenich (Bonn)|Kessenich]], Lessenich/Meßdorf, Nordstadt, Poppelsdorf, Röttgen, Südstadt, [[Tannenbusch]], Ückesdorf, Venusberg, Weststadt
|-
|[[Hardtberg]]
| align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:Wappen-bezirk-hardtberg.svg|35px|Wappen des Stadtbezirks Hardtberg]]
| align=&quot;right&quot; |33.360
|Brüser Berg, Duisdorf, [[Hardthöhe]], Lengsdorf
|}

=== Climate ===
{{see also|Rhine-Rhur#Climate}}

Bonn has an [[oceanic climate]] (''Cfb'').&lt;ref name=&quot;Climate-Data.org&quot;/&gt; In the south of the Cologne lowland in the Rhine valley, Bonn is in one of Germany's warmest regions.

{{Weather box
|location = Bonn
|metric first = Yes
|single line = yes

|Jan high C=4.7
|Feb high C=6.1
|Mar high C=9.9
|Apr high C=14.1
|May high C=18.6
|Jun high C=21.8
|Jul high C=23.2
|Aug high C=22.8
|Sep high C=19.8
|Oct high C=14.7
|Nov high C=9
|Dec high C=5.8

|Jan mean C = 2.4
|Feb mean C = 2.8
|Mar mean C = 6.3
|Apr mean C = 9.7
|May mean C = 14.0
|Jun mean C = 16.7
|Jul mean C = 18.8
|Aug mean C = 18.3
|Sep mean C = 14.6
|Oct mean C = 10.5
|Nov mean C = 6.2
|Dec mean C = 3.1
|year mean C = 10.3

|rain colour= green
|Jan rain mm= 61.0
|Feb rain mm= 54.0
|Mar rain mm= 64.0
|Apr rain mm= 54.0
|May rain mm= 72.0
|Jun rain mm= 86.0
|Jul rain mm= 78.0
|Aug rain mm= 78.0
|Sep rain mm= 72.0
|Oct rain mm= 63.0
|Nov rain mm= 66.0
|Dec rain mm= 68.0
|year rain mm= 816.0
|unit rain days= 1.0 mm

|Jan low C=-0.6
|Feb low C=-0.4
|Mar low C=1.6
|Apr low C=4.5
|May low C=8.1
|Jun low C=11.3
|Jul low C=13
|Aug low C=12.5
|Sep low C=10
|Oct low C=6.4
|Nov low C=3.2
|Dec low C=0.6

|Jan sun = 51.0
|Feb sun = 76.0
|Mar sun = 110.0
|Apr sun = 163.0
|May sun = 190.0
|Jun sun = 195.0
|Jul sun = 209.0
|Aug sun = 194.0
|Sep sun = 141.0
|Oct sun = 104.0
|Nov sun = 55.0
|Dec sun = 41.0

|source 1= [[Deutscher Wetterdienst]] (Bonn-Rohleber, period 1971– 2010)

|source 2= Climate-Data.org, high and low averages (altitude: 64m)&lt;ref name=&quot;Climate-Data.org&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://en.climate-data.org/europe/germany/north-rhine-westphalia/bonn-228/ |title=Average Temperature, weather by month, Bonn weather averages |publisher=Climate-Data.org |accessdate=2019-02-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

== History ==

===Founding and Roman times===
{{see also|Timeline of Bonn}}
{{Unreferenced section|date=February 2008}}
[[File:2008-12-25 Bonn Sterntor.jpg|left|thumb|The ''{{lang|de|Sterntor}}'', originally built around 1244, is a gate reconstructed on the remnants of the medieval city wall.]]
The history of the city dates back to Roman times. In about 12 BC, the [[Roman army]] appears to have stationed a small unit in what is presently the historical centre of the city. Even earlier, the army had resettled members of a Germanic tribal group allied with Rome, the [[Ubii]], in Bonn. The Latin name for that settlement, &quot;Bonna&quot;, may stem from the original population of this and many other settlements in the area, the [[Eburones|Eburoni]]. The Eburoni were members of a large tribal coalition effectively wiped out during the final phase of [[Julius Caesar|Caesar]]'s [[Gallic Wars|War in Gaul]]. After several decades, the army gave up the small camp linked to the Ubii-settlement. During the 1st century [[Anno Domini|AD]], the army then chose a site to the north of the emerging town in what is now the section of Bonn-Castell to build a large military installation dubbed [[Castra]] Bonnensis, i.e., literally, &quot;Fort Bonn&quot;. Initially built from wood, the fort was eventually rebuilt in stone. With additions, changes and new construction, the fort remained in use by the army into the waning days of the [[Western Roman Empire]], possibly the mid-5th century. The structures themselves remained standing well into the [[Middle Ages]], when they were called the Bonnburg. They were used by [[Kingdom of the Franks|Frankish]] kings until they fell into disuse. Eventually, much of the building materials seem to have been re-used in the construction of Bonn's 13th-century [[Defensive wall|city wall]]. The Sterntor (''star gate'') in the city center is a reconstruction using the last remnants of the medieval city wall.

To date, Bonn's Roman fort remains the largest fort of its type known from the [[Ancient history|ancient world]], i.e. a fort built to accommodate a full-strength [[Roman legion|Imperial Legion]] and its auxiliaries. The fort covered an area of approximately {{convert|250000|m2|acre}}. Between its walls it contained a dense grid of streets and a multitude of buildings, ranging from spacious headquarters and large officers' quarters to [[barracks]], [[stable]]s and a [[Military prison|military jail]]. Among the legions stationed in Bonn, the &quot;1st&quot;, i.e. the [[Legio I Minervia|Prima Legio Minervia]], seems to have served here the longest. Units of the Bonn legion were deployed to theatres of war ranging from modern-day [[Algeria]] to what is now the Russian republic of [[Chechnya]].

[[File:Altes Rathaus Bonn.jpg|thumb|The ''Altes Rathaus'' (old town hall) as seen from the central market square. It was built in 1737 in [[Rococo|Rococo-style]].]]The chief [[Roman roads|Roman road]] linking the provincial capitals of [[Cologne]] and [[Mainz]] cut right through the fort where it joined the fort's main road (now, Römerstraße). Once past the South Gate, the Cologne–Mainz road continued along what are now streets named Belderberg, Adenauerallee et al. On both sides of the road, the local settlement, ''Bonna'', grew into a sizeable Roman town. Bonn is shown on the 4th century [[Peutinger Map]].

In [[late antiquity]], much of the town seems to have been destroyed by marauding invaders. The remaining civilian population then took refuge inside the fort along with the remnants of the troops stationed here. During the final decades of Imperial rule, the troops were supplied by [[Franks|Franci]] chieftains employed by the Roman administration. When the end came, these troops simply shifted their allegiances to the new barbarian rulers, the [[Kingdom of the Franks]]. From the fort, the Bonnburg, as well as from a new medieval settlement to the South centered around what later became the [[Bonn Minster|minster]], grew the medieval city of Bonn. Local legends arose from this period that the name of the village came from [[Saint Boniface]] via [[Vulgar Latin]] ''*Bonnifatia'', but this proved to be a myth.

=== Middle Ages and Early Modern times ===
[[File:University bonn at night.jpg|thumb|Founded in 1818, the [[University of Bonn]] counts [[Friedrich Nietzsche|Nietzsche]], [[Karl Marx|Marx]] and [[Konrad Adenauer|Adenauer]] among its alumni.]]
Between the 11th and 13th centuries, the [[Romanesque architecture|Romanesque]] style Bonn Minster was built, and in 1597 Bonn became the seat of the [[Diocese|Archdiocese]] of [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Cologne|Cologne]]. The city gained more influence and grew considerably. The city was subject to a major bombardment during the [[Siege of Bonn (1689)|Siege of Bonn]] in 1689. The [[Electorate of Cologne|elector]] [[Clemens August of Bavaria|Clemens August]] (ruled 1723–1761) ordered the construction of a series of [[Baroque]] buildings which still give the city its character. Another memorable ruler was [[Archduke Maximilian Francis of Austria|Max Franz]] (ruled 1784–1794), who founded the university and the spa quarter of [[Bad Godesberg]]. In addition he was a patron of the young [[Ludwig van Beethoven]], who was born in Bonn in 1770; the elector financed the composer's first journey to [[Vienna]].

In 1794, the city was seized by [[France|French]] troops, becoming a part of the [[First French Empire]]. In 1815 following the [[Napoleonic Wars]], Bonn became part of the [[Kingdom of Prussia]]. Administered within the Prussian [[Rhine Province]], the city became part of the [[German Empire]] in 1871 during the Prussian-led [[unification of Germany]]. Bonn was of little relevance in these years.

===20th century and the &quot;Bonn Republic&quot;===
During the [[Second World War]], Bonn acquired military significance because of its strategic location on the Rhine, which formed a natural barrier to easy penetration into the German heartland from the west. The Allied ground advance into Germany reached Bonn on 7 March 1945, and the US [[1st Infantry Division (United States)|1st Infantry Division]] captured the city during the battle of 8–9 March 1945.&lt;ref&gt;Stanton, Shelby, ''World War II Order of Battle: An Encyclopedic Reference to U.S. Army Ground Forces from Battalion through Division, 1939–1946'' (Revised Edition, 2006), Stackpole Books, p. 76.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Bundesarchiv B 145 Bild-F013859-0009, Bonn, Staatsbesuch Präsident Charles de Gaulle.jpg|left|thumb|French president [[Charles de Gaulle]] on state visit to Bonn (1962), the capital of [[West Germany]] until [[German reunification]].]]
Following the Second World War, Bonn was in the [[United Kingdom|British]] zone of occupation. Following the advocacy of West Germany's first chancellor, [[Konrad Adenauer]], a former [[Cologne]] Mayor and a native of that area, Bonn became the ''de facto'' capital, officially designated the &quot;temporary seat of the Federal institutions,&quot; of the newly formed Federal Republic of Germany in 1949. However, the Bundestag, seated in Bonn's [[Bundeshaus (Bonn)|Bundeshaus]], affirmed [[Berlin]]'s status as the German capital. Bonn was chosen as the provisional capital and seat of government despite the fact that [[Frankfurt am Main|Frankfurt]] already had most of the required facilities and using Bonn was estimated to be 95 million DM more expensive than using Frankfurt. Bonn was chosen because Adenauer and other prominent politicians intended to make Berlin the capital of the reunified Germany, and felt that locating the capital in a major city like Frankfurt or [[Hamburg]] would imply a permanent capital and weaken support in West Germany for reunification.

In 1949, the [[Parlamentarischer Rat|Parliamentary Council]] in Bonn drafted and adopted the current German constitution, the [[Basic Law for the Federal Republic of Germany]]. As the political centre of West Germany, Bonn saw six [[Chancellor of Germany|Chancellors]] and six [[President of Germany|Presidents]] of the Federal Republic of Germany. Bonn's time as the capital of West Germany is commonly referred to as the ''Bonn Republic,'' in contrast to the ''Berlin Republic'' which followed reunification in 1990.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Schleichende Wende. Diskurse von Nation und Erinnerung bei der Konstituierung der Berliner Republik|last=Caborn|first=Joannah|publisher=|year=2006|isbn=|location=|pages=12|quote=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bonn in the &quot;Berlin Republic&quot;===
[[File:Villa Hammerschmidt Bonn Seite Adenauerallee 20080831.jpg|left|thumb|Between 1950 and 1994, [[Hammerschmidt Villa|Villa Hammerschmidt]] was the primary official residence of the [[President of Germany]]. Today it serves as the President's secondary residence.]]
[[German reunification]] in 1990 made Berlin the nominal capital of Germany again. This decision, however, did not mandate that the republic's political institutions would also move. While some argued for the seat of government to move to Berlin, others advocated leaving it in Bonn — a situation roughly analogous to that of the [[Netherlands]], where [[Amsterdam]] is the capital but [[The Hague]] is the seat of government. Berlin's previous history as united Germany's capital was strongly connected with the [[German Empire]], the [[Weimar Republic]] and more ominously with [[Nazi Germany]]. It was felt that a new peacefully united Germany should not be governed from a city connected to such overtones of war. Additionally, Bonn was closer to [[Brussels]], headquarters of the [[European Economic Community]]. Former chancellor and mayor of [[West Berlin]] [[Willy Brandt]] caused considerable offence to the Western Allies during the debate by stating that [[France]] would not have kept the seat of government at [[Vichy France|Vichy]] after Liberation.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=o36GDAAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=PA149&amp;dq=Willy%20Brandt%20%20France%20Vichy%20capital&amp;pg=PA149#v=onepage&amp;q=Willy%20Brandt%20%20France%20Vichy%20capital&amp;f=false ''Willy Brandt: a Political Biography''], B. Marshall, Springer, page 149&lt;/ref&gt;

The heated debate that [[Decision on the Capital of Germany|resulted]] was settled by the ''[[Bundestag]]'' (Germany's parliament) only on 20 June 1991. By a vote of 338–320,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thelocal.de/politics/20110615-35655.html &quot;Bonn to Berlin move still controversial&quot;], ''The Local'', &quot;Published 11 June 2011&quot;. Retrieved 01-02-12.&lt;/ref&gt; the Bundestag voted to move the seat of government to Berlin. The vote broke largely along regional lines, with legislators from the south and west favouring Bonn and legislators from the north and east voting for Berlin.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Nationalatlas aktuell&quot;, [http://aktuell.nationalatlas.de/Hauptstadtbeschluss.6_06-2011.0.html &quot;Hauptstadtbeschluss&quot;] by Sebastian Lentz, &quot;Published 17 Juni 2011&quot;. Retrieved 9-20-12.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Laux, Hans-Dieter, &quot;Berlin oder Bonn? Geographische Aspekte eine Parlamentsentscheidung&quot;, &quot;Geographische Rundschau&quot;, 43:12, 740–743, 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;  It also broke along generational lines as well; older legislators with memories of Berlin's past glory favoured Berlin, while younger legislators favoured Bonn. Ultimately, the votes of the [[New states of Germany#Culture|eastern German]] legislators tipped the balance in favour of Berlin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Thompson |first=Wayne C. |year=2008 |title=The World Today Series: Nordic, Central and Southeastern Europe 2008 |publisher=Stryker-Post Publications |location=Harpers Ferry, West Virginia |isbn=978-1-887985-95-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From 1990 to 1999, Bonn served as the seat of government of reunited Germany. In recognition of its former status as German capital, it holds the name of Federal City ({{lang-de|Bundesstadt}}). Bonn currently shares the status of Germany's seat of government with Berlin, with the [[President of Germany|President]], the [[Chancellor of Germany|Chancellor]] and many government ministries maintaining substantial presences in Bonn. Over 8,000 of the 18,000 federal officials remain in Bonn.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cowell&quot;/&gt; A total of 19 [[United Nations|United Nations (UN)]] institutions operate from Bonn today.

==Politics==
[[File:Ashok Alexander Sridharan, Oberbürgermeister Bonn.jpg|thumb|Ashok Alexander Sridharan [[Christian Democratic Union of Germany|(CDU)]] has been the mayor of Bonn since 2015.]]

=== City council ===
The [[city council]] of Bonn used to be based in the [[Rococo|Rococo-style]] and 1737 built ''{{lang|de|Altes Rathaus}}'' (old city hall) adjacent to Bonn's central market square. However, due to the enlargement of Bonn in 1969 through the incorporation of Beuel and Bad Godesberg, it moved into the larger Stadthaus facilities further up north. This was necessary for the city council to accommodate the increased number of representatives. The mayor of Bonn still sits in the ''{{lang|de|Altes Rathaus}}'', which is also used for representative and official purposes.

As of the 2014–2020 election cycle, the [[CDU (Germany)|Christian Democrats (CDU)]] hold a plurality of mandates in the city council (27 seats), followed by the [[Social Democratic Party of Germany|Social Democrats (SPD)]] with 20 seats, the [[Alliance '90/The Greens|Greens (Bündnis '90/Die Grünen)]] with 16 seats, the [[Free Democratic Party (Germany)|Liberals (FDP)]] with 7 seats, the [[The Left (Germany)|Left (Die Linke)]] with 5 seats, the local Bürgerbund Bonn with 4 seats, the [[Alternative for Germany|Alternative for Germany (AfD)]] with 3 seats, and independent candidates with a total of 4 seats. There are currently 86 seats in the city council of Bonn.
[[File:Stadthaus-01-04-2013-133.jpg|thumb|The ''{{lang|de|Stadthaus}}'', home of the city council of Bonn.]]
The mayor is [[:de:Ashok-Alexander Sridharan|Ashok-Alexander Sridharan]] (CDU), directly elected in 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.spiegel.de/politik/deutschland/bonn-waehlt-neuen-cdu-oberbuergermeister-a-1052732.html|title=Neuer Oberbürgermeister: CDU-Kandidat in Bonn gewählt – SPIEGEL ONLINE – Politik|last=Germany|first=SPIEGEL ONLINE, Hamburg|website=SPIEGEL ONLINE|access-date=2017-01-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Landtag election ===
Four delegates represent the Federal city of Bonn in the [[Landtag]] of [[Landtag of North Rhine-Westphalia|North Rhine-Westphalia]]. The last election took place in May 2012. The current delegates are Bernhard von Grünberg [[Social Democratic Party of Germany|(SPD),]]Renate Hendricks [[Social Democratic Party of Germany|(SPD)]], Joachim Stamp [[Free Democratic Party (Germany)|(FDP)]] and Rolf Beu [[Alliance '90/The Greens|(Bündnis 90/Die Grünen)]].

=== German federal election ===
Bonn's [[Electoral district|constituency]] is called ''{{lang|de|Bundeswahlkreis Bonn}}'' (096). In the [[German federal election, 2017|German federal election 2017]], [[Ulrich Kelber]] [[Social Democratic Party of Germany|(SPD)]] was elected a member of [[Bundestag|German Federal parliament, the Bundestag]] by direct mandate. It is his fifth term. [[Katja Dörner]] representing [[Alliance '90/The Greens|Bündnis 90/Die Grünen]], [[Alexander Graf Lambsdorff]] for [[Free Democratic Party of Germany|FDP]] and [[Claudia Lücking-Michel]] of the [[Christian Democratic Union of Germany|CDU]] were elected [[Electoral system of Germany#Regional lists of parliamentary candidates for election to Federal Parliament|from regional lists]].

== Culture ==
Beethoven's birthplace is located in Bonngasse near the market place. Next to the market place is the Old City Hall, built in 1737 in [[Rococo]] style, under the rule of [[Clemens August of Bavaria]]. It is used for receptions of guests of the city, and as an office for the mayor. Nearby is the ''[[Electoral Palace, Bonn|Kurfürstliches Schloss]]'', built as a residence for the prince-elector and now the main building of the [[University of Bonn]]. 
[[File:Bonner Münster.jpg|thumb|Erected in the 11th and 13th century, the [[Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]] [[Bonn Minster|Minster of Bonn]] is one of Germany's oldest churches.]]
The ''Poppelsdorfer Allee'' is an avenue flanked by [[Chestnut|chestnut trees]] which had the first [[horsecar]] of the city. It connects the ''Kurfürstliches Schloss'' with the ''[[Poppelsdorfer Schloss]]'', a palace that was built as a resort for the prince-electors in the first half of the 18th century, and whose grounds are now a [[botanical garden]] (the [[Botanischer Garten Bonn]]). This axis is interrupted by a railway line and [[Bonn Hauptbahnhof]], a building erected in 1883/84.

The [[Beethoven Monument (Bonn)|Beethoven Monument]] stands on the Münsterplatz, which is flanked by the [[Bonn Minster]], one of Germany's oldest churches.

The three highest structures in the city are the [[Westdeutscher Rundfunk|WDR]] [[Radio masts and towers|radio mast]] in Bonn-Venusberg ({{convert|180|m|ft|disp=or|abbr=on}}), the headquarters of the [[Deutsche Post]] called ''[[Post Tower]]'' ({{convert|162.5|m|ft|disp=or|abbr=on}}) and the former building for the German members of parliament ''[[Langer Eugen]]'' ({{convert|114.7|m|ft|disp=or|abbr=on}}) now the location of the [[United Nations|UN]] Campus.

===Churches===
* [[Bonn Minster]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bonner-muenster.de/basilika/index_engl.htm |title=Das Bonner Münster @ Kirche in der City |publisher=Bonner-muenster.de |accessdate=2009-05-05 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090215133139/http://bonner-muenster.de/basilika/index_engl.htm |archivedate=2009-02-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Doppelkirche Schwarzrheindorf]] built in 1151
* [[Alter Friedhof, Bonn|Old Cemetery Bonn]] (''Alter Friedhof''), one of the best known cemeteries in Germany&lt;ref&gt;[[:de:Alter Friedhof Bonn]]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Kreuzbergkirche]], built in 1627 with [[Johann Balthasar Neumann]]'s ''Heilige Stiege'', it is a stairway for Christian pilgrims&lt;ref&gt;[[:de:Kreuzbergkirche]]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[St. Remigius, Bonn|St. Remigius]], where Beethoven was baptized

===Castles and residences===
* [[Godesburg]] fortress ruins&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bonn-region.de/ns/articleview_en.php?folderID=10204&amp;sub_folderID=10215&amp;articleID=623 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20050525113041/http://www.bonn-region.de/ns/articleview_en.php?folderID=10204&amp;sub_folderID=10215&amp;articleID=623 |archivedate=2005-05-25 |title=Bonn Region – Sightseeing – Fortresses and castles – Godesburg mit Michaelskapelle (Fortress Godesburg with St. Michael Chapel) |publisher=Web.archive.org |date=2005-05-25 |accessdate=2009-07-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[:de:Godesburg]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Modern buildings===
[[File:Beetha2.JPG|thumb|[[Beethovenhalle]]]]
* [[Beethovenhalle]]
* [[Bundesviertel]] (federal quarter) with lots of government structures including
** [[Post Tower]], the tallest building in the state [[North Rhine-Westphalia]], housing the headquarters of [[Deutsche Post]]/[[DHL Express|DHL]]
** Maritim Bonn, five-star hotel and convention centre
** [[Schürmann-Bau]], headquarters of [[Deutsche Welle]]
** Langer Eugen, since 2006 the centre of the United Nations Campus, formerly housing the offices of the members of the German parliament
* [[Deutsche Telekom]] headquarters
* [[T-Mobile]] headquarters
* Kameha Grand, five-star hotel

===Museums===
[[File:Kunst- und Ausstellungshalle der Bundesrepublik Deutschland - Bundeskunsthalle-9245.jpg|left|thumb|upright=1.2|The [[Kunst- und Ausstellungshalle der Bundesrepublik Deutschland|Bundeskunsthalle]] focuses on the cultural heritage outside of Germany or Europe, at the crossroads of culture, the arts, and science.]]
Just as Bonn's other four major museums, the ''[[Haus der Geschichte]]'' or Museum of the History of the Federal Republic of Germany, is located on the so-called ''Museumsmeile'' (&quot;Museum Mile&quot;)''.'' The Haus der Geschichte is one of the foremost German museums of contemporary German history, with branches in [[Berlin]] and [[Leipzig]]. In its permanent exhibition, the Haus der Geschichte presents German history from 1945 until the present, also shedding light on Bonn's own role as former capital of West Germany. Numerous temporary exhibitions emphasize different features, such as Nazism or important personalities in German history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hdg.de/index.php?id=1&amp;L=1|title=Stiftung Haus der Geschichte der Bundesrepublik Deutschland: Home|date=2008-06-13|publisher=Hdg.de|accessdate=2009-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''[[Kunstmuseum Bonn]]'' or Bonn Museum of Modern Art is an art museum founded in 1947. The Kunstmuseum exhibits both temporary exhibitions and its permanent collection. The latter is focused on Rhenish [[Expressionism]] and post-war German art.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://kunstmuseum.bonn.de/start_e.htm |title=Kunstmuseum Bonn – Overview |publisher=Kunstmuseum.bonn.de |date= |accessdate=2009-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; German artists on display include [[Georg Baselitz]], [[Joseph Beuys]], [[Hanne Darboven]], [[Anselm Kiefer]], [[Blinky Palermo]] and [[Wolf Vostell]]. The museum owns one of the largest collections of artwork by Expressionist painter [[August Macke]]. His work is also on display in the [[August-Macke-Haus]], located in Macke's former home where he lived from 1911 to 1914.
[[File:2014-06-12 Museum Koenig, Bonn IMG 5509.jpg|thumb|upright=1.4|The [[Museum Koenig]] is Bonn's [[natural history]] museum. ]]
The [[Kunst- und Ausstellungshalle der Bundesrepublik Deutschland|''Bundeskunsthalle'']] (full name: Kunst- und Ausstellungshalle der Bundesrepublik Deutschland or Art and Exhibition Hall of the Federal Republic of Germany), focusses on the crossroads of culture, arts, and science. To date, it attracted more than 17 million visitors.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.museumsmeilebonn.de/portfolio/bundeskunsthalle/|title=MUSEUMSMEILE BONN|website=www.museumsmeilebonn.de|language=de-DE|access-date=2017-02-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of its main objectives is to show the [[cultural heritage]] outside of Germany or Europe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.kah-bonn.de/index_e.htm |title=Art and Exhibition Hall of the Federal Republic of Germany – Bonn – English Version |publisher=Kah-bonn.de |accessdate=2009-05-05 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090509062736/http://www.kah-bonn.de/index_e.htm |archivedate=2009-05-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Next to its changing exhibitions, the Bundeskunsthalle regularly hosts concerts, discussion panels, congresses, and lectures.

The ''[[Museum Koenig]]'' is Bonn's natural history museum. Affiliated with the [[University of Bonn]], it is also a [[Zoology|zoological]] research institution housing the ''Leibniz-Institut für Biodiversität der Tiere''. Politically interesting, it is on the premises of the Museum Koenig where the [[Parlamentarischer Rat]] first met.&lt;ref&gt;[[:de:Museum Koenig]]&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[Deutsches Museum Bonn]]'', affiliated with one of the world's foremost science museums, the [[Deutsches Museum|Deutsches Museum in Munich]], is an interactive science museum focusing on post-war German scientists, engineers, and inventions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.museumsmeilebonn.de/portfolio/deutsches-museum-bonn/|title=MUSEUMSMEILE BONN|website=www.museumsmeilebonn.de|language=de-DE|access-date=2017-02-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other museums include the [[Beethoven House]], birthplace of [[Ludwig van Beethoven]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Fraunhofer-Institut für Medienkommunikation IMK |url=http://www.beethoven-haus-bonn.de/sixcms/detail.php//portal_en |title=Beethoven digitally |publisher=Beethoven-haus-bonn.de |date=2002-03-26 |accessdate=2009-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Rheinisches Landesmuseum Bonn]] (Rhinish Regional Museum Bonn),&lt;ref&gt;[[:de:Rheinisches Landesmuseum Bonn]]&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Bonn Women's Museum]], the [[Rheinisches Malermuseum]] and the [[Arithmeum]].

===Nature===
[[File:Siebengebirge schloss drachenburg ds wv 09 2008.jpg|left|thumb|upright=0.75|[[Schloss Drachenburg|Drachenburg Castle]] in the [[Siebengebirge]] south of Bonn.]]
There are several parks, leisure and protected areas in and around Bonn. The ''[[:de:Rheinaue]]'' is Bonn's most important leisure park, with its role being comparable to what [[Central Park]] is for [[New York City|New York]]. It lies on the banks of the Rhine and is the city's biggest park intra muros.&lt;ref&gt;[[:de:Freizeitpark Rheinaue]]&lt;/ref&gt; The Rhine promenade and the ''Alter Zoll'' (Old Toll Station) are in direct neighbourhood of the city centre and are popular amongst both residents and visitors. The ''[[Arboretum Park Härle]]'' is an [[arboretum]] with specimens dating to back to 1870. The ''[[Botanical Garden, Bonn|Botanischer Garten]]'' (Botanical Garden) is affiliated with the university and it is here where [[Titan arum]] set a world record.&lt;ref&gt;[[:de:Botanischer Garten Bonn]]&lt;/ref&gt; The natural reserve of ''[[Kottenforst]]'' is a large area of protected woods on the hills west of the city centre. It is about {{convert|40|km2|sqmi|abbr=off}} in area and part of the [[Rhineland Nature Park]] ({{convert|1,045|km2|sqmi|disp=or|abbr=on}}).&lt;ref&gt;[[:de:Kottenforst]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the very south of the city, on the border with [[Wachtberg]] and [[Rhineland-Palatinate]], there is an extinct volcano, the [[Rodderberg]], featuring a popular area for hikes. Also south of the city, there is the [[Siebengebirge]] which is part of the lower half of the [[Middle Rhine]] region. The nearby upper half of the [[Middle Rhine]] from [[Bingen am Rhein|Bingen]] to [[Koblenz]] is a [[List of World Heritage Sites in Europe|UNESCO World Heritage Site]] with more than 40 castles and fortresses from the [[Middle Ages]] and important German vineyards.

== Transportation ==
=== Air traffic ===
[[File:Koeln-Bonn-Airport11.JPG|thumb|upright=0.85|The [[Cologne Bonn Airport|international airport of Cologne and Bonn]] ([[International Air Transport Association airport code|IATA]]: CGN) is Germany's [[List of the busiest airports in Germany|seventh-largest]].]]
Named after [[Konrad Adenauer]], the first post-war Chancellor of West Germany, [[Cologne Bonn Airport]] is situated {{convert|15|km|mi|abbr=off}} north-east from the city centre of Bonn. With around 10.3 million passengers passing through it in 2015, it is the [[List of the busiest airports in Germany|seventh-largest passenger airport in Germany]] and the third-largest in terms of cargo operations. By traffic units, which combines cargo and passengers, the airport is in fifth position in Germany.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adv.aero/fileadmin/pdf/statistiken/2015/11.2015_ADV-Monatsstatistik.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2016-01-06 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304204205/http://www.adv.aero/fileadmin/pdf/statistiken/2015/11.2015_ADV-Monatsstatistik.pdf |archivedate=2016-03-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt; As of March 2015, Cologne Bonn Airport had services to 115 passenger destinations in 35 countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.airliners.de/sommerflugplan-2015-sieben-ziele-flughafen-koeln-bonn/35295|title=Sommerflugplan 2015: Sieben neue Ziele ab Flughafen Köln/Bonn|work=airliners.de|accessdate=4 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The airport is one of Germany's few 24-hour airports, and is a hub for [[Eurowings]] and cargo operators [[FedEx Express]] and [[UPS Airlines]].

The federal motorway (''Autobahn'') [[Bundesautobahn 59|A59]] connects the airport with the city. Long distance and regional trains to and from the airport stop at [[Cologne/Bonn Airport station]]. Other major airports within a one-hour drive by car are [[Frankfurt International Airport|Frankurt International Airport]] and [[Düsseldorf Airport|Düsseldorf International Airport]].

=== Rail and bus system ===
[[File:2008-07-28 U-Bahnhof Hauptbahnhof (Bonn).jpg|thumb|upright=0.85|[[Bonn Hauptbahnhof]], Bonn's busiest railway station, is connected to Bonn's partly underground [[U-Bahn]] network.]]
Bonn's central railway station, [[Bonn Hauptbahnhof]], serves urban ([[S-train|S-Bahn]], [[U-Bahn]], sharing the same network with the neighbouring city of [[Cologne]]), regional ([[Regionalbahn]]), and long distance destinations ([[Intercity-Express|ICE]]) such as Berlin, Hamburg, Munich, Zurich, Vienna, Brussels, Amsterdam and Paris. Daily, more than 67,000 people travel via Bonn Hauptbahnhof. In late 2016, around 80 long distance and more than 165 regional trains departed to or from Bonn every day.&lt;ref name=&quot;general041116&quot;&gt;''[http://www.general-anzeiger-bonn.de/bonn/stadt-bonn/Sanierung-geht-in-die-heiße-Phase-article3397749.html Sanierung geht in die heiße Phase]'', [[General-Anzeiger (Bonn)|General-Anzeiger]], 4. November 2016&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;db041116&quot;&gt;''[http://www.deutschebahn.com/presse/duesseldorf/de/aktuell/presseinformationen/12647934/161107_schoene_aussichten.html Schöne Aussichten im Hauptbahnhof Bonn] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161106105046/http://www.deutschebahn.com/presse/duesseldorf/de/aktuell/presseinformationen/12647934/161107_schoene_aussichten.html |date=2016-11-06 }}'', Deutsche Bahn, 4. November 2016&lt;/ref&gt; The other major railway station ([[Siegburg/Bonn station|Siegburg/Bonn]]) lies on the [[Köln–Frankfurt high-speed rail line|high-speed rail line between Cologne and Frankfurt]].

The bus system of Bonn is composed of roughly 30 lines which operate on a regular basis. During peaks, buses usually run every 5 minutes; off-peak buses run every 20 minutes. Several lines offer night services, especially during the weekends. Bonn is part of the [[Verkehrsverbund Rhein-Sieg]] (''Rhine-Sieg Transport Association'') which is the public transport association covering the area of the [[Cologne/Bonn Region|Cologne/Bonn region]].

=== Road network ===
[[File:Region Bonn motorways.png|left|thumb|upright=0.6|Road network adjacent to Bonn.]]
Four German [[Autobahn]]s run through or are adjacent to Bonn: the [[Bundesautobahn 59|A59]] (right bank of the Rhine, connecting Bonn with [[Düsseldorf]] and [[Duisburg]]), the [[Bundesautobahn 555|A555]] (left bank of the [[Rhine]], connecting Bonn with [[Cologne]]), the [[Bundesautobahn 562|A562]] (connecting the right with the left bank of the Rhine south of Bonn), and the [[Bundesautobahn 565|A565]] (connecting the A59 and the A555 with the [[Bundesautobahn 61|A61]] to the southwest). Three Bundesstraßen, which have a general {{convert|100|km/h|abbr=off}} [[speed limit]] in contrast to the Autobahn, connect Bonn to its immediate surroundings (Bundesstraßen B9, B42 and B56).

With Bonn being divided into two parts by the [[Rhine]], three bridges are crucial for inner-city road traffic: the Konrad-Adenauer-Brücke (A562), the Friedrich-Ebert-Brücke (A565), and the Kennedybrücke (B56). In addition, regular ferries operate between Bonn-Mehlem and [[Königswinter]], Bonn-Bad Godesberg and [[Niederdollendorf]], and Graurheindorf and Mondorf.

=== Port ===
Located in the northern sub-district of Graurheindorf, the [[Inland harbor|inland harbour]] of Bonn is used for container traffic as well as oversea transport. The annual turnover amounts to around {{convert|500000|t||abbr=on}}. Regular passenger transport occurs to Cologne and Düsseldorf.

==Economy==
{{Expand section|date=January 2017}}
[[File:Bonn - Posttower.jpg|thumb|Being one of the biggest employers in the region, [[Deutsche Post DHL]] have their headquarters in Bonn.]]
The head offices of [[Deutsche Telekom]], its subsidiary [[T-Mobile]],&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.telekom.com/dtag/cms/content/dt/en/255634;jsessionid=4D01506824470D931FFD9BB00F37BDCA Deutsche Telekom facts and figures]  {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110716204932/http://www.telekom.com/dtag/cms/content/dt/en/255634%3Bjsessionid%3D4D01506824470D931FFD9BB00F37BDCA |date=July 16, 2011 }}.&quot; ''[[T-Mobile]]''. Retrieved on 8 November 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Deutsche Post]], [[Haribo]], [[German Academic Exchange Service]], and [[SolarWorld]] are in Bonn.

==Education==
[[File:Geschäftsstelle der Deutschen Forschungsgemeinschaft in Bonn-Bad Godesberg.jpg|thumb|Offices of [[Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft|DFG]], an important research funding organisation]]

The Rheinische Friedrich Wilhelms Universität Bonn ([[University of Bonn]]) is one of the largest universities in Germany. It is also the location of the German research institute [[Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft]] (DFG) offices and of the [[German Academic Exchange Service]] (''Deutscher Akademischer Austauschdienst'' – DAAD).

===Private schools===
* [[Aloisiuskolleg]], a [[Society of Jesus|Jesuit]] [[private school]] in [[Bad Godesberg]] with boarding facilities
* Amos-Comenius-Gymnasium, a [[Protestantism|Protestant]] [[private school]] in Bad Godesberg
* [[Bonn International School]] (BIS), a private English-speaking school set in the former American Compound in the Rheinaue, which offers places from kindergarten to 12th grade. It follows the curriculum of the [[International Baccalaureate]].
* Libysch Schule, private Arabic high school
* [[Independent Bonn International School]], (IBIS) private primary school (serving from kindergarten, reception, and years 1 to 6)
* [[École de Gaulle - Adenauer]], private French-speaking school serving grades pre-school (&quot;maternelle&quot;) to grade 4 (CM1)
* [[Kardinal-Frings-Gymnasium]] (''KFG''), private catholic school of the [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Cologne|Archdiocese of Cologne]] in [[Beuel]]
* [[Erzbischöfliche Liebfrauenschule Bonn|Liebfrauenschule]] (''LFS''), private catholic school of the Archdiocese of Cologne 
* {{ill|Sankt-Adelheid-Gymnasium|de}}, private catholic school of the Archdiocese of Cologne in Beuel
* {{ill|Clara-Fey-Gymnasium|de}}, private Catholic school of the [[Archdiocese of Cologne]] in Bad Godesberg
* {{ill|Ernst-Kalkuhl-Gymnasium|de}}, private boarding and day school in [[Oberkassel, Bonn|Oberkassel]]
* {{ill|Otto-Kühne-Schule|de}} (&quot;PÄDA&quot;), private day school in Bad Godesberg
* {{ill|Collegium Josephinum Bonn|de}} (&quot;CoJoBo&quot;), private catholic day school
* Akademie für Internationale Bildung, private higher educational facility offering programs for international students

==Demographics==
{{Historical populations|1620|4500|1720|6535|1732|8015|1760|13500|1784|12644|1798|8837|1808|8219|1817|10970|1849|17688|1871|26030|1890|39805|1910|87978|1919|91410|1925|90249|1933|98659|1939|100788|1950|115394|1961|143850|1970|274518|1987|276653|2011|305,765|2017|325,490|align=right|footnote=Population size may be affected by changes in administrative divisions.
 source:&lt;ref&gt;[[:de:Einwohnerentwicklung von Bonn|Link]]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Circular reference|date=August 2019}}}}
[[File:Einwohnerentwicklung von Bonn.svg|thumb|Population development since 1620]]
{{As of|2011}}, Bonn had a population of 327,913.  About 70% of the population was entirely of German origin, while about 100,000 people, equating to roughly 30%, were at least partly of non-German origin. The city is one of the fastest-growing municipalities in Germany and the 18th most populous city in the country. Bonn's population is predicted to surpass the populations of [[Wuppertal]] and [[Bochum]] before the year 2030.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ihk-bonn.de/index.php?id=484&amp;no_cache=1&amp;tx_ttnews[tt_news]=3203&amp;cHash=b391fefbdac6e3220eafe80076f021aa|title=IHK Bonn/Rhein-Sieg: Bonn wächst weiter |date= 2012-11-29|accessdate=2013-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The following list shows the largest groups of origin of minorites with &quot;migration background&quot; in Bonn {{As of|31.12.2017|lc=y}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Eckzahlen der aktuellen Bevölkerungsstatistik (Stichtag 31.12.2017)|url=http://www2.bonn.de/statistik/default.asp?2|website=www2.bonn.de|publisher=Statistikstelle der Bundesstadt Bonn|accessdate=2018-04-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot; |Rank
! style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot; |Nationality
! style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot; |Population (31.12.2018)
|-
|1||{{flag|Turkey}}|| 8,319
|-
|2||{{flag|Syria}}|| 7,846
|-
|3||{{flag|Poland}}|| 7,218
|-
|4||{{flag|Morocco}}|| 5,742
|-
|5||{{flag| Italy}}|| 3,812
|-
|6||{{flag|Russia}}|| 3,758
|-
|7||{{flag|Iran}}||3,165
|-
|8||{{flag|Spain}}|| 2,924
|-
|9||{{flag|Iraq}}|| 2,517
|-
|10||{{flag|Romania}}|| 2,205
|-
|11||{{flag|France}}|| 2,065
|-
|12||{{flag|China}}||1,912
|-
|13||{{flag|Afghanistan}}||1,850
|-
|14||{{flag|USA}}||1,844
|-
|15||{{flag|Greece}}||1,681
|-
|16||{{flag|Kazakhstan}}||1,679
|-
|17||{{flag|Tunisia}}||1,676
|-
|18||{{flag|India}}||1,664
|-
|19||{{flag|Bulgaria}}||1,597
|-
|20||{{flag|UK}}||1,334
|-
|21||{{flag|Netherlands}}||1,253
|-
|22||{{flag|Ukraine}}||1,200
|-
|23||{{flag|Portugal}}||1,196
|-
|24||{{flag|Kosovo}}||1,164
|-
|25||{{flag|Croatia}}||1,157
|-
|}

[[File:Bonn DTAG2.jpg|thumb|upright=0.8|[[Deutsche Telekom]] head office]]

==Sports==
Bonn is home of the [[Telekom Baskets Bonn]], the only basketball club in Germany that owns its arena, the [[Telekom Dome]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telekom-baskets-bonn.de/telekom-dome/uebersicht.html &quot;Telekom Baskets Bonn – Telekom Dome – Übersicht&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131012040651/http://www.telekom-baskets-bonn.de/telekom-dome/uebersicht.html |date=October 12, 2013 }}, ''Telekom-Baskets-Bonn.de''. Retrieved 8 March 2014. {{in lang|de}}&lt;/ref&gt; The club is a regular participant at international competitions such as the [[Basketball Champions League]].

The city also has an seem-professional football team [[Bonner SC]] which was formed in 1965 through the merger of ''Bonner FV'' and ''Tura Bonn''.

The headquarters of the [[International Paralympic Committee]] has been located in Bonn since 1999.

==International relations==
{{See also|List of twin towns and sister cities in Germany}}
Since 1983, the City of Bonn has established friendship relations with the City of [[Tel Aviv]], [[Israel]], and since 1988 Bonn, in former times the residence of the Princes Electors of Cologne, and [[Potsdam]], [[Germany]], the formerly most important residential city of the Prussian rulers, have established a city-to-city partnership.

Central Bonn is surrounded by a number of traditional towns and villages which were independent up to several decades ago. As many of those communities had already established their own contacts and partnerships before the regional and local reorganisation in 1969, the Federal City of Bonn now has a dense network of city district partnerships with European partner towns.

The city district of Bonn is a partner of the English university city of [[Oxford]], [[England]], [[United Kingdom|UK]] (since 1947), of [[Budafok]], District XXII of [[Budapest]], [[Hungary]] (since 1991) and of [[Opole]], [[Poland]] (officially since 1997; contacts were established 1954).

The district of Bad Godesberg has established partnerships with [[Saint-Cloud]] in [[France]], [[Frascati]] in [[Italy]], [[Royal Borough of Windsor and Maidenhead|Windsor and Maidenhead]] in [[England]], [[United Kingdom|UK]] and [[Kortrijk]] in [[Belgium]]; a friendship agreement has been signed with the town of [[Yalova]], [[Turkey]].

The district of Beuel on the right bank of the Rhine and the city district of Hardtberg foster partnerships with towns in [[France]]: [[Mirecourt]] and [[Villemomble]].

Moreover, the city of Bonn has developed a concept of international co-operation and maintains sustainability oriented project partnerships in addition to traditional city twinning, among others with [[Minsk]] in [[Belarus]], [[Ulaanbaatar]] in [[Mongolia]], [[Bukhara]] in [[Uzbekistan]], [[Chengdu]] in [[China]] and [[La Paz]] in [[Bolivia]].

===Twin towns — sister cities===
The city of Bonn is [[Twin towns and sister cities|twinned]] with:&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonn twinning&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bonn.de/wirtschaft_wissenschaft_internationales/internationale_aktivitaeten/staedtepartnerschaften/index.html?lang=en|title=City Twinnings|accessdate=2013-08-01|work=Stadt Bonn|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130410070837/http://www.bonn.de/wirtschaft_wissenschaft_internationales/internationale_aktivitaeten/staedtepartnerschaften/index.html?lang=en|archivedate=2013-04-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* {{flagicon|ISR}} [[Tel Aviv]], [[Israel]], since 1983&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonn twinning&quot;/&gt;
* {{flagicon|GER}} [[Potsdam]], [[Germany]], since 1988&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonn twinning&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Potsdam twinnings&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.potsdam.de/cms/ziel/27222/DE/|title=Die Partnerstädte der Landeshauptstadt Potsdam|work=www.potsdam.de|accessdate=24 June 2010|language=German|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100625001110/http://www.potsdam.de/cms/ziel/27222/DE/|archivedate=25 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bonn city district has partnerships with:

* {{flagicon|UK}} [[Oxford]], [[United Kingdom]], since 1947&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonn twinning&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Oxford twinnings&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oxford.gov.uk/PageRender/decAC/Town_twinning_occw.htm|title=Oxford's International Twin Towns|accessdate=2013-09-03|work=Oxford City Council|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130817150811/http://oxford.gov.uk/PageRender/decAC/Town_twinning_occw.htm|archivedate=2013-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|HUN}} [[Budapest]], [[Budafok]], [[Hungary]], since 1991&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonn twinning&quot;/&gt;
* {{flagicon|POL}} [[Opole]], [[Poland]], since 1997&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonn twinning&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;OpoleTwin&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.opole.pl/miasto/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=blogcategory&amp;id=20&amp;Itemid=108|title=Opole Official Website – Twin Towns|accessdate=2009-06-18|publisher= [[File:Flag of the United Kingdom.svg|14px]] [[File:Flag of Poland.svg|border|10px]] {{fontcolor|Green|(in [[English language|{{fontcolor|Green|English}}]] and [[Polish language|{{fontcolor|Green|Polish}}]])}} [[copyright|©]] 2007–2009 Urząd Miasta Opola}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Bad Godesberg district has partnerships with:&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonn twinning&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bonn.de/rat_verwaltung_buergerdienste/stadtbezirke/bad_godesberg/staedtepartnerschaft/|title=Stadt Bonn – Städtepartnerschaft|last=Bonn|first=Bundesstadt|website=www.bonn.de|language=de|access-date=2017-05-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|FRA}} [[Saint-Cloud]], [[France]], since 1957
* {{flagicon|ITA}} [[Frascati]], [[Italy|Italiy]], since 1957
*{{flagicon|BEL}} [[Kortrijk]], [[Belgium]], since 1957
*{{flagicon|UK}} [[Royal Borough of Windsor and Maidenhead|Windsor and Maidenhead]], [[United Kingdom]], since 1960
The city of Bonn also has project partnerships with:

{{Div col}}

* {{flagicon|UZB}} [[Bukhara]], [[Uzbekistan]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonn twinning&quot;/&gt;
* {{flagicon|GHA}} [[Cape Coast]], [[Ghana]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonn twinning&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cape Coast&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ghananewsagency.org/details/Social/Cape-Coast-signs-sister-city-partnership-with-Bonn/?ci=4&amp;ai=42024#.UEunBbJlTRY |title=Cape Coast signs sister-city partnership with Bonn |publisher=[[Ghana News Agency]] (GNA) |date=April 13, 2012|accessdate=September 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|BLR}} [[Minsk]], [[Belarus]], since 1993&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonn twinning&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Minsk&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://minsk.gov.by/ru/city/|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130502075333/http://minsk.gov.by/ru/city/|title=Twin towns and Sister cities of Minsk ''[via WaybackMachine.com]''|publisher=The department of protocol and international relations of Minsk City Executive Committee|archivedate=2 May 2013|accessdate=2013-07-21|language=Russian}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|BOL}} [[La Paz]], [[Bolivia]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonn twinning&quot;/&gt;
* {{flagicon|PRC}} [[Chengdu]], [[China]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonn twinning&quot;/&gt;
* {{flagicon|ALB}} [[Tirana]], [[Albania]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonn twinning&quot;/&gt;
{{Div col end}}

==Notable residents==

=== Up to the 19th century ===
[[File:Beethoven.jpg|thumb |180px |[[Ludwig van Beethoven]]]]
[[File:Moses-Hess.jpg |thumb |180px |[[Moses Hess]]]]
[[File:Alexander Koenig.jpg |thumb |180px |[[Alexander Koenig]]]]
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 192-132, KZ Mauthausen, Ewald Krebsbach.jpg|thumb|180px|[[Eduard Krebsbach]]]]
* [[Johann Peter Salomon]], baptized 20 February 1745 † 25 November 1815 in London, musician
* [[Franz Anton Ries]], * November 10, 1755 † 1 November 1846 in Bonn, violinist and violin teacher
* [[Ludwig van Beethoven]], * December 16, 1770 † 26 March 1827 in Vienna, composer
* [[Salomon Oppenheim, Jr.]], * June 19, 1772 † November 8, 1828 in Mainz, banker
* [[Peter Joseph Lenné]], * September 29, 1789 † 23 January 1866 in Potsdam, gardener and landscape architect
* [[Friedrich von Gerolt]], * March 5, 1797 † July 27, 1879 in Linz, diplomat
* [[Karl Joseph Simrock]], * August 28, 1802 † 18 July 1876 in Bonn, writer and specialist in German
* [[Wilhelm Neuland]], * July 1806 † December 28, 1889 in Bonn, composer and conductor
* [[Johanna Kinkel]], * July 8, 1810 † 15 November 1858 in London, composer and writer
* [[Moses Hess]], * June 21, 1812 † April 6, 1875 in Paris, philosopher and writer
* [[Johann Gottfried Kinkel]], * August 11, 1815 † 12 November 1882 in Zürich, theologian, writer, and politician 
* [[Alexander Kaufmann]], * May 14, 1817 † 1 May 1893 in Wertheim, author and archivist
* [[Leopold Kaufmann]], * March 13, 1821 † 27 February 1898 in Bonn, mayor
* [[Julius von Haast]], * May 1, 1822 † 16 August 1887 in Christchurch, New Zealand, professor of geology
* [[Dietrich Brandis]], * March 31, 1824 † 28 May 1907 in Bonn, botanist
* [[Balduin Möllhausen]], * 27 January 1825 † 28 May 1905 in Berlin, traveler and writer
* [[Maurus Wolter]], * June 4, 1825 † July 8, 1890 in Beuron, Benedictine, founder and first abbot of the Abbey of Beuron and Beuronese Congregation
* [[August Reifferscheid]], * October 3, 1835 † 10 November 1887 in Strasbourg, philologist
* [[Antonius Maria Bodewig]], * November 2, 1839 † January 8, 1915 in Rome, Jesuit missionary and founder
* [[Nathan Zuntz]], * October 7, 1847 † 23 March 1920 in Berlin, physician
* [[Alexander Koenig]], * February 20, 1858 † July 16, 1940 in Blücherhof, Klocksin, zoologist, founder of [[Museum Koenig]] in Bonn
* [[Alfred Philippson]], * January 1, 1864 † 28 March 1953 in Bonn, geographer
* [[Johanna Elberskirchen]], * April 11, 1864 † 17 May 1943 in Rüdersdorf, feminist writer and activist
* [[Max Alsberg]], * October 16, 1877 † 10 September 1933, lawyer
* [[Kurt Wolff (publisher)|Kurt Wolff]], * March 3, 1887 † 21 October 1963, publisher
* [[Hans Riegel]] (senior), * April 3, 1893 † 31 March 1945, entrepreneur
* [[Eduard Krebsbach]], * August 8, 1894 † May 28, 1947 in Landsberg am Lech, [[SS]] doctor in [[Nazi]] [[Mauthausen concentration camp]], executed for war crimes
* [[Paul Kemp (actor)|Paul Kemp]], * May 20, 1896 † 13 August 1953 in Bonn, actor

=== 20th century ===

==== 1900–1950 ====
[[File:Klaus Barbie.jpg |thumb |180px |[[Klaus Barbie]]]]
[[File:Heidesimonis.jpg |thumb |180px |[[Heide Simonis]]]]
* [[Hermann Josef Abs]], * October 15, 1901 † February 5, 1994 in Bad Soden am Taunus, board member of the [[Deutsche Bank]]
* [[Paul Ludwig Landsberg]], * December 3, 1901 † April 2, 1944 in [[Sachsenhausen concentration camp]], philosopher
* [[Heinrich Lützeler]], * January 27, 1902 † 13 June 1988 in Bonn, philosopher, art historian, and literary scholar
* [[Theodor Schieffer]], * June 11, 1910 † April 9, 1992, historian and medievalist
* [[Irene Sänger-Bredt]], * April 24, 1911 † 20 October 1983 in Stuttgart, mathematician and physicist
* [[Ernst Friedrich Schumacher]], * August 16, 1911 † 4 September 1977 in the train between Geneva and Lausanne, economist
* [[Klaus Barbie]], * October 25, 1913 † 25 September 1991 in Lyon, Nazi SS and [[Gestapo]] war criminal, the &quot;Butcher of Lyon&quot;
* [[Karl-Theodor Molinari]], * February 7, 1915 † 11 December 1993 in Dortmund, General and founding chairman of the German Armed Forces Association
* [[Karlrobert Kreiten]], * June 26, 1916 in Bad Godesberg † September 7, 1943 in Berlin-Plotzensee, pianist
* [[Hannjo Hasse]], * August 31, 1921 † February 5, 1983 in Falkirk, actor
* [[Walter Gotell]], * March 15, 1924 † 5 May 1997 in London, actor
* [[Walter Eschweiler]], born September 20, 1935, football referee
* [[Alexandra Cordes]], * November 16, 1935 † 27 October 1986 in Châteauneuf-du-Pape, writer
* [[Joachim Bißmeier]], born November 22, 1936, actor
* [[Roswitha Esser]], born 18 January 1941, canoeist, gold medal winner at the Olympic Games in 1964 and 1968, Sportswoman of the Year 1964
* [[Heide Simonis]], born July 4, 1943, politician (SPD), former Prime Minister of Schleswig-Holstein, since 2005 honorary chairman of [[UNICEF]] Germany
* [[Paul Alger]], born August 13, 1943, football player
* [[Johannes Mötsch]], born July 8, 1949, archivist and historian 
* [[Klaus Ludwig]], born October 5, 1949, race car driver

==== 1951 to present ====
* [[Günter Ollenschläger]], born March 3, 1951 in Beuel, medical and science journalist
* [[Hans Bongartz|Hans &quot;Hannes&quot; Bongartz]], born October 3, 1951, football player and coach
* [[Christa Goetsch]], born August 28, 1952, politician (Alliance '90 / The Greens)
* [[Thomas de Maizière]], born January 21, 1954, politician (CDU), former Minister of Defence and of the Interior
* [[Gerd Faltings]], born July 28, 1954, mathematician, [[Fields Medal]] winner
* [[Olaf Manthey]], born April 21, 1955, former touring car racing driver
* [[Michael Kühnen]], * June 21, 1955 † April 25, 1991 in Kassel, Neo-Nazi
* [[Roger Willemsen]], * August 15, 1955 † 7 February 2016 in Wentorf, publicist, author, essayist, and presenter
* [[Norman Rentrop]], born October 26, 1957, publisher, author, and investor
* [[Markus Maria Profitlich]], born March 25, 1960, comedian and actor
* [[Guido Westerwelle]], * December 27, 1961 † March 8, 2016, politician (FDP), Foreign Minister and Vice Chancellor of Germany from 2009 to 2011
* [[Mathias Dopfner]], born January 15, 1963, Chief Executive Officer of [[Axel Springer AG]]
* [[Maxim Kontsevich]], born August 25, 1964, mathematician, [[Fields Medal]] winner
* [[Johannes B. Kerner]], born December 9, 1964, TV presenter, Abitur at the [[Aloisiuskolleg]], and studied in Bonn
* [[Anthony Baffoe]], born May 25, 1965 football player, sports presenter, and actor
* [[Sonja Zietlow]], born May 13, 1968, TV presenter
* [[Burkhard Garweg]], born September 1, 1968, member of the [[Red Army Faction]]
* [[Sabriye Tenberken]], born September 19, 1970, Tibetologist, founder of  [[Braille Without Borders]]
* [[Thorsten Libotte]], born July 20, 1972, writer
* [[Tamara Gräfin von Nayhauß]], born July 23, 1972, television presenter
* [[Silke Bodenbender]], born January 31, 1974, actress
* [[Juli Zeh]], born June 30, 1974, writer
* [[Oliver Mintzlaff]], born August 19, 1975, track and field athlete and sports manager, CEO of [[RB Leipzig]]
* [[Markus Dieckmann]], born January 7, 1976, beach volleyball player
* [[Bernadette Heerwagen]], born June 22, 1977, actress
* [[Melanie Amann]], born 1978, journalist
* [[Bushido (rapper)|Bushido]], born September 28, 1978, musician and rapper
* [[Sebastian Stahl]], born September 20, 1978, race car driver
* [[Sonja Fuss]], born November 5, 1978, football player
* [[Andreas Tölzer]], born January 27, 1980, judoka
* [[Jens Hartwig]], born April 16, 1980, actor
* [[Natalie Horler]], born September 23, 1981, front woman of the Dance Project [[Cascada]]
* [[Marcel Ndjeng]], born May 6, 1982, football player
* [[Marc Zwiebler]], born March 13, 1984, badminton player
* [[Benjamin Barg]], born September 15, 1984, football player
* [[Alexandros Margaritis]], born September 20, 1984, race car driver
* [[Ken Miyao]], born March 16, 1986, pop singer
* [[Julia Reda]], born November 30, 1986, politician
* [[Peter Scholze]], born December 11, 1987, mathematician, [[Fields Medal]] winner
* [[Célia Okoyino da Mbabi]], born June 27, 1988, football player
* [[Luke Mockridge]], born March 21, 1989, comedian and author
* [[Pius Heinz]], born May 4, 1989, poker player, 2011 [[World Series of Poker|WSOP]] Main Event champion
* [[Jonas Wohlfarth-Bottermann]], born February 20, 1990, basketball player
* [[Levina (singer)|Levina]], born May 1, 1991, singer
* [[Bienvenue Basala-Mazana]], born January 2, 1992, football player
* [[Annika Beck]], born February 16, 1994, tennis player
* [[Konstanze Klosterhalfen]], born February 18, 1997, track and field athlete

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
{{See also|Timeline of Bonn#Bibliography|l1=Bibliography of the history of Bonn}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Bonn}}
{{wikivoyage|Bonn}}
* [https://www.bonn.de/index.html?lang=en Official Website] {{in lang|en}}
* [https://www.bonn-region.de/en/ Tourist information]
* [https://www.bonn.de/tourismus_kultur_sport_freizeit/bonn_ist_kultur/museen/museumsmeile/index.html?lang=en &quot;The Museum Mile&quot;]
* [http://www.bundeskunsthalle.de/en/home.html Germany's Museum of Art in Bonn]

{{Cities in Germany}}
{{Germany districts north rhine-westphalia}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Bonn| ]]&lt;!--please leave the empty space as standard--&gt;
[[Category:Former national capitals]]
[[Category:Populated places on the Rhine]]
[[Category:Roman towns and cities in Germany]]
[[Category:University towns in Germany]]
[[Category:10s BC establishments in the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:1st-century BC establishments in Germany]]
[[Category:Roman legionary fortresses in Germany]]
[[Category:Roman fortifications in Germania Inferior]]</text>
      <sha1>rb8k4t6l0hjempy5bog2ltds3c8exay</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
