  <page>
    <title>Cape Breton Island</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5724</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937711678</id>
      <parentid>937709158</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-26T19:41:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Daws162432</username>
        <id>38398254</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Retracting an edit I previously made.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2019}}
{{short description|Island in Nova Scotia}}
{{Redirect|Cape Breton}}
{{Infobox islands
| name             = Cape Breton
| image_name       = Cape Breton Island.png
| image_caption    = Cape Breton Island, Nova Scotia, Canada
| image_size       = 
| map              = Canada Nova Scotia
| map_caption      = Cape Breton Island (Nova Scotia, Canada)
|local_name = {{plainlist |
* ''{{lang|mic|Unamaꞌkik}}'' ([[Miꞌkmaq language|Miꞌkmaq]])
* ''{{lang|gd|Ceap Breatainn}}'' ([[Canadian Gaelic|Scottish Gaelic]])
* ''{{lang|fr|Cap-Breton}}'' ([[Acadian French|French]])
}}
| nickname         = 
| location         = [[Nova Scotia]], Canada
| coordinates      = {{coord|46|10|N|60|45|W|scale:1000000|display=inline}}
| archipelago      = 
| total_islands    = 
| major_islands    = 
| area_km2         = 10311
| rank             = 77th
| length_km        =
| width_km         =
| highest_mount    = [[White Hill (Nova Scotia)|White Hill]]
| elevation_m      = 535
| country          = Canada
| country_admin_divisions_title     = Province
| country_admin_divisions           = [[Nova Scotia]]
| country_largest_city              = [[Cape Breton Regional Municipality]]
| country_largest_city_population   = 97,398&lt;ref name = &quot;Table from Statistics Canada CBRM&quot;&gt;''[http://www12.statcan.gc.ca/census-recensement/2011/dp-pd/prof/details/page.cfm?Lang=E&amp;Geo1=CSD&amp;Code1=1217030&amp;Geo2=CD&amp;Code2=1217&amp;Data=Count&amp;SearchText=cape%20breton&amp;SearchType=Begins&amp;SearchPR=01&amp;B1=All&amp;Custom=&amp;TABID=1 Table from Statistics Canada – CBRM]'' (Census Profile, 2011 Census)&lt;/ref&gt;
| population       = 132,010&lt;ref name = &quot;Table from Statistics Canada&quot;&gt;''[http://www12.statcan.gc.ca/census-recensement/2011/dp-pd/prof/details/page.cfm?Lang=E&amp;Tab=1&amp;Geo1=ER&amp;Code1=1210&amp;Geo2=PR&amp;Code2=12&amp;Data=Count&amp;SearchText=cape%20breton&amp;SearchType=Begins&amp;SearchPR=01&amp;B1=All&amp;Custom=&amp;TABID=1 Table from Statistics Canada]'' (Census Profile, 2011 Census)&lt;/ref&gt;
| population_as_of = 2016
| density_km2      = 12.7
| ethnic_groups    =
| demonym = Cape Bretoner&lt;ref name=&quot;Table from Language Portal of Canada&quot;&gt;''[https://www.noslangues-ourlanguages.gc.ca/bien-well/fra-eng/vocabulaire-vocabulary/demonyms-eng.html Table of demonyms in Canada] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140830091113/http://www.noslangues-ourlanguages.gc.ca/bien-well/fra-eng/vocabulaire-vocabulary/demonyms-eng.html |date=30 August 2014 }}''&lt;/ref&gt; 
| additional_info  =
}}
[[File:Wfm cape breton island pseudocolour.jpg|200px|thumb|right|NASA landsat photo of Cape Breton Island]]

'''Cape Breton Island''' ({{lang-fr|link=no|île du Cap-Breton}}—formerly ''{{lang|fr|[[Île-Royale (New France)|Île Royale]]}}''; {{lang-gd|Ceap Breatainn}} or ''{{lang|gd|Eilean Cheap Breatainn}}''; {{lang-mic|Unamaꞌkik}}; or simply ''Cape Breton'') is an island on the [[Atlantic Ocean|Atlantic]] coast of North America and part of the province of [[Nova Scotia]], Canada.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

The {{convert|10311|km2|abbr=on}} island accounts for 18.7% of Nova Scotia's total area. Although the island is physically separated from the [[Nova Scotia peninsula]] by the [[Strait of Canso]], the {{convert|1385|m|ft|abbr=on}} long rock-fill [[Canso Causeway]] connects it to mainland Nova Scotia. The island is east-northeast of the mainland with its northern and western [[coast]]s fronting on the [[Gulf of Saint Lawrence]]; its western coast also forms the eastern limits of the [[Northumberland Strait]]. The eastern and southern coasts front the Atlantic Ocean; its eastern coast also forms the western limits of the [[Cabot Strait]]. Its landmass slopes upward from south to north, culminating in the [[highland]]s of its northern cape. One of the world's larger salt water lakes, {{lang|fr|[[Bras d'Or Lake|Bras d'Or]]}} (&quot;Arm of Gold&quot; in French), dominates the island's centre.

The island is divided into four of Nova Scotia's eighteen counties: [[Cape Breton County, Nova Scotia|Cape Breton]], [[Inverness County, Nova Scotia|Inverness]], [[Richmond County, Nova Scotia|Richmond]], and [[Victoria County, Nova Scotia|Victoria]]. Their total population at the [[Canada 2016 Census|2016 census]] numbered 132,010 Cape Bretoners; this is approximately 15% of the provincial population.&lt;ref name=&quot;Table from Statistics Canada&quot;/&gt; Cape Breton Island has experienced a decline in population of approximately 2.9% since the 2011 census. Approximately 75% of the island's population is in the [[Cape Breton Regional Municipality]] (CBRM) which includes all of Cape Breton County and is often referred to as [[Industrial Cape Breton]], given the history of coal mining and steel manufacturing in this area, which was Nova Scotia's industrial heartland throughout the 20th century.

The island has five [[Indian reserve|reserves]] of the [[Mi'kmaq|Mi'kmaq Nation]]: {{lang|mic|[[Eskasoni First Nation|Eskasoni]]}}, {{lang|mic|[[Membertou First Nation|Membertou]]}}, {{lang|mic|[[Wagmatcook First Nation|Wagmatcook]]}}, {{lang|mic|[[Whycocomagh 2|Waycobah]]}}, and [[Potlotek First Nation|{{lang|mic|Potlotek|nocat=y}}/Chapel Island]]. {{lang|mic|Eskasoni}} is the largest in both population and land area.

==Toponymy==
Its name may derive from {{lang|fr|[[Capbreton]]}} near [[Bayonne]], or more probably from ''[[Cape (geography)|Cape]]'' and the word ''{{lang|fr|Breton}}'', the French [[demonym]] for ''{{lang|fr|[[Brittany|Bretagne]]}}'', the French historical region.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;&gt;{{cite EB1911|wstitle=Cape Breton}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[William Francis Ganong]], however, refutes a French origin for the name and offers, instead, that the earliest form of the name appeared on Portuguese maps as &quot;bertomes&quot;, and, he argues, &quot;that word meant at the time the English and not the French Bretons, and referred to the region which [[John Cabot]] and his Bristol Englishmen discovered on the voyage of 1497...therefore our Cape Breton would mean 'Cape of the English&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Ganong |first1=William Francis |title=Crucial Maps in the Early Cartography and Place-nomenclature of the Atlantic Coast of Canada |date=1964 |publisher=University of Toronto Press |location=Toronto |page=37 |url=https://books.google.ca/books/about/Crucial_Maps_in_the_Early_Cartography_an.html?id=aM-5AAAAIAAJ&amp;redir_esc=y}}&lt;/ref&gt;'&quot;

==History==

Cape Breton Island's first residents were likely [[Archaic period in the Americas|Archaic maritime natives]], ancestors of the [[Mi'kmaq people|Mi'kmaq]]. These peoples and their progeny inhabited the island (known as Unama'ki) for several thousand years and continue to live there to this day. Their traditional lifestyle centred around hunting and fishing because of the unfavourable agricultural conditions of their maritime home. This ocean-centric lifestyle did, however, make them among the first indigenous peoples to discover European explorers and sailors fishing in the St Lawrence Estuary. [[John Cabot]] reportedly visited the island in 1497.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; However, European histories and maps of the period are of too poor quality to be sure whether Cabot first visited [[Newfoundland (island)|Newfoundland]] or Cape Breton Island. This discovery is commemorated by Cape Breton's [[Cabot Trail]], and by the Cabot's Landing Historic Site &amp; Provincial Park, near the village of [[Dingwall, Nova Scotia|Dingwall]].

The local Mi'kmaq peoples began trading with European fishermen when the fishermen began landing in their territories as early as the 1520s. In about 1521–22, the Portuguese under [[João Álvares Fagundes]] established a fishing colony on the island. As many as two hundred settlers lived in a village, the name of which is not known, located according to some historians at what is now [[Ingonish, Nova Scotia|Ingonish]] on the island's northeastern peninsula. These fishermen traded with the local population but did not maintain a permanent settlement. This Portuguese colony's fate is unknown, but it is mentioned as late as 1570.&lt;ref&gt;de Souza, Francisco; ''Tratado das Ilhas Novas'', 1570&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Anglo-French War (1627–29)|Anglo-French War]] of 1627 to 1629, under [[Charles I of England|Charles I]], the [[David Kirke|Kirkes]] took [[Quebec City]]; [[James Stewart, 4th Lord Ochiltree|Sir James Stewart]]&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; of Killeith, [[Lord Ochiltree]] planted a colony on Unama'ki at [[Baleine, Nova Scotia]]; and Alexander's son, [[William Alexander, 1st Earl of Stirling]], established the first incarnation of [[Nova Scotia|&quot;New Scotland&quot;]] at [[Port Royal, Annapolis County, Nova Scotia|Port Royal]]. These claims, and larger European ideals of native conquest were the first time the island was incorporated as European territory, though it would be several decades later that treaties would actually be signed (no copies of these treaties exist).

These Scottish triumphs, which left [[Cape Sable Island|Cape Sable]] as the only major French holding in North America, did not last.&lt;ref&gt;Roger Sarty and Doug Knight. Saint John Fortifications: 1630–1956. New Brunswick Military Heritage Series. 2003. p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; Charles I's haste to make peace with France on the terms most beneficial to him meant the new North American gains would be bargained away in the [[Treaty of Saint-Germain-en-Laye (1632)]],&lt;ref&gt;Nichols, 2010. p. xix&lt;/ref&gt;{{Full citation needed|date=August 2014}} which established which European power had claim over the territories, but did not in fact establish that Europeans had any claim to begin with.

The French quickly defeated the Scots at [[Baleine, Nova Scotia|Baleine]], and established the first European settlements on Île Royale: present day [[Englishtown, Nova Scotia|Englishtown]] (1629) and [[St. Peter's, Nova Scotia|St. Peter's]] (1630). These settlements lasted only one generation, until [[Nicolas Denys]] left in 1659. The island did not have any European settlers for another fifty years before those communities along with [[Louisbourg (community)|Louisbourg]] were re-established in 1713, after which point European settlement was permanently established on the island.

===Île Royale===
[[File:Flag of the Kingdom of France (1814-1830).svg|thumb|100px|French Naval Ensign (pure white) flown over the Colony of Île Royale]]

Known as &quot;''Île Royale''&quot; (&quot;Royal Island&quot;) to the French, the island also saw active settlement by France. After the French ceded their claims to [[Newfoundland (island)|Newfoundland]] and the [[Acadia]]n mainland to the British by the [[Treaty of Utrecht]] in 1713, the French relocated the population of [[Placentia, Newfoundland and Labrador|Plaisance, Newfoundland]], to [[Île-Royale (New France)|Île Royale]] and the French [[garrison]] was established in the central eastern part at [[Fort Sainte Anne (Nova Scotia)|Sainte Anne]]. As the harbour at Sainte Anne experienced icing problems, it was decided to build a much larger fortification at [[Fortress of Louisbourg|Louisbourg]] to improve defences at the entrance to the [[Gulf of Saint Lawrence]] and to defend France's fishing fleet on the [[Grand Banks of Newfoundland|Grand Banks]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cmhg.gc.ca/cmh/en/page_103.asp ''Canadian Military Heritage''] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071008182623/http://www.cmhg.gc.ca/cmh/en/page_103.asp |date=8 October 2007 }}; vol.1, Chapter 6: Soldiers of the Atlantic Seaboard, p103. Government of Canada, 26 April 2004&lt;/ref&gt; The French also built the [[Louisbourg Lighthouse]] in 1734, the first lighthouse in Canada and one of the first in North America. In addition to Cape Breton Island, the French colony of Île Royale also included [[Prince Edward Island|Île Saint-Jean]], today called [[Prince Edward Island]], and [[Les Îles-de-la-Madeleine]].

[[File:Destruction du vaisseau le Prudent et capture du Bienfaisant a Louisbourg 1758.jpg|300px|thumb|right|[[Siege of Louisbourg (1758)]]]]

==== French and Indian War ====
[[Louisbourg]] itself was one of the most important commercial and military centres in New France.  Louisbourg was captured by New Englanders&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; with British naval assistance in [[Siege of Louisbourg (1745)|1745]]&lt;ref name=&quot;timeline&quot; /&gt; and by British forces in 1758. The French population of Île Royale was deported to France after each siege. While French settlers returned to their homes in Île Royale after the [[Treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle (1748)|Treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle]] was signed in 1748,&lt;ref name=timeline&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cbc.ca/acadian/timeline.html |title=The Acadians – Timeline |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |date=2004 |website=The Acadians |publisher=[[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation]] |accessdate=8 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; the fortress was demolished after the [[Siege of Louisbourg (1758)|second siege]]. Île Royale remained formally part of [[New France]] until it was ceded to [[Kingdom of Great Britain|Great Britain]] by the [[Treaty of Paris (1763)|Treaty of Paris]] in 1763. It was then merged with the adjacent, British colony of Nova Scotia (present day peninsular Nova Scotia and [[New Brunswick]]). Acadians who had been [[Expulsion of the Acadians|expelled]] from [[Nova Scotia]] and Île Royale were permitted to settle in Cape Breton beginning in 1764,&lt;ref name=&quot;timeline&quot; /&gt; and established communities in north-western Cape Breton, near [[Cheticamp]], and southern Cape Breton, on and near [[Isle Madame]].

Some of the first British-sanctioned settlers on the island following the [[Seven Years' War]] were Irish, although upon settlement they merged with local French communities to form a culture rich in music and tradition.  From 1763 to 1784, the island was administratively part of the colony of [[Nova Scotia]]&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; and was governed from [[Halifax (former city)|Halifax]].

The first permanently settled [[Scottish people|Scottish]] community on Cape Breton Island was [[Judique, Nova Scotia|Judique]], settled in 1775 by Michael Mor MacDonald. He spent his first winter using his upside-down boat for shelter, which is reflected in the architecture of the village's Community Centre. He composed a song about the area called &quot;O 's àlainn an t-àite&quot;, or &quot;O, Fair is the Place.&quot;

==== American Revolution ====
[[File:The Departure of S.W. Prentice and Five Others from their Shipwrecked Companions, 1781 (inset).png|thumb|300px|left|Samuel Waller Prentice, [[84th Regiment of Foot (Royal Highland Emigrants)|84th Regiment]], 4 January 1780, shipwrecked off [[Cape Breton]], Nova Scotia by [[Robert Pollard (engraver)|Robert Pollard]] (1784)&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.org/stream/cihm_20623#page/n5/mode/2up Samuel Weller Prenties. Narrative of a shipwreck on the island of Cape Breton, in a voyage from Quebec 1780]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.org/stream/navalchronicleco11londiala#page/447/mode/1up Naval Chronicle. Vol. 11, p. 447]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.ca/books?id=xnAMAAAAYAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q=halifax&amp;f=false Naval Chronicle, Vol. 14, p. 28]&lt;/ref&gt;]]

During the [[American Revolution]], on 1 November 1776, [[John Paul Jones]] – the father of the American Navy – set sail in command of ''Alfred'' to free hundreds of American prisoners working in the area's coal mines. Although winter conditions prevented the freeing of the prisoners, the mission did result in the capture of ''Mellish'', a vessel carrying a vital supply of winter clothing intended for [[John Burgoyne]]'s troops in Canada.

Major [[Timothy Hierlihy]] and his regiment on board HMS ''Hope'' worked in and protected from privateer attacks on the coal mines at Sydney Cape Breton.&lt;ref&gt;C. J. MacGillivray. Timothy Hierlihy and his Times: The story of the Founder of Antigonish, Nova Scotia. Nova Scotia Historical Society., p.40&lt;/ref&gt; Sydney Cape Breton provided a vital supply of coal for Halifax throughout the war.  The British began developing the mining site at Sydney Mines in 1777. On 14 May 1778, Major Hierlihy arrived at Cape Breton.  While there, Hierlihy reported that he &quot;beat off many piratical attacks, killed some and took other prisoners.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;C. J. MacGillivray. Timothy Hierlihy and his Times: The story of the Founder of Antigonish, N.S.  Nova Scotia Historical Society., p.42&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://archives.gnb.ca/exhibits/forthavoc/html/AmericanMSSVol1.aspx?culture=en-CA Maj.-Gen. Eyre Massey to General Sir Henry Clinton. 13 June 1778]&lt;/ref&gt;

A few years into the war there was also [[Naval battle off Cape Breton|a naval engagement]] between French ships and a British convoy off Sydney, Nova Scotia, near Spanish River (1781), Cape Breton.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas B. Akins. (1895) History of Halifax. Dartmouth: Brook House Press.p. 82&lt;/ref&gt; French ships (fighting with the Americans) were re-coaling and defeated a British convoy. Six French sailors were killed and 17 British, with many more wounded.

===Colony of Cape Breton===
[[File:Red Ensign of Great Britain (1707-1800).svg|thumb|100px|Flag of the Colony of Cape Breton 1784–1801.]]
[[File:Civil Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|thumb|100px|Flag of the Colony of Cape Breton 1801–1820.]]
In 1784, Britain split the colony of Nova Scotia into three separate colonies:  New Brunswick, Cape Breton Island, and present-day peninsular Nova Scotia, in addition to the adjacent colonies of [[Prince Edward Island|St. John's Island]] (renamed Prince Edward Island in 1798) and [[History of Newfoundland and Labrador|Newfoundland]].  The colony of Cape Breton Island had its capital at [[Sydney, Nova Scotia|Sydney]] on its namesake harbour fronting on [[Spanish Bay (Nova Scotia)|Spanish Bay]] and the [[Cabot Strait]]. Its first Lieutenant-Governor was [[Joseph Frederick Wallet DesBarres]] (1784–1787) and his successor was [[William Macarmick]] (1787).

A number of [[United Empire Loyalists]] emigrated to the Canadian colonies, including Cape Breton. [[David Mathews]], the former [[Mayor of New York City]] during the [[American Revolution]], emigrated with his family to Cape Breton in 1783.  He succeeded Macarmick as head of the colony and served from 1795 to 1798.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite DCB |title=Mathews, David |first=R. J. |last=Morgan |volume=IV |url=http://www.biographi.ca/en/bio/mathews_david_4E.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From 1799 to 1807, the military commandant was [[John Despard]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite DCB |title=Despard, John |first=R. J. |last=Morgan |volume=6 |url=http://www.biographi.ca/en/bio/despard_john_6E.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; brother of [[Edward Despard|Edward]].&lt;ref&gt;Despard, John; ''The Companion to British History'', Routledge&lt;/ref&gt;

An order forbidding the granting of land in Cape Breton, issued in 1763, was removed in 1784. The mineral rights to the island were given over to the [[Prince Frederick, Duke of York and Albany|Duke of York]] by an order-in-council. The British government had intended that the Crown take over the operation of the mines when Cape Breton was made a colony, but this was never done, probably because of the rehabilitation cost of the mines. The mines were in a neglected state, caused by careless operations dating back at least to the time of the final fall of Louisbourg in 1758.

Large-scale shipbuilding began in the 1790s, beginning with [[schooner]]s for local trade moving in the 1820s to larger [[brig]]s and [[brigantine]]s, mostly built for British shipowners. Shipbuilding peaked in the 1850s, marked in 1851 by the [[full-rigged ship]] ''[[Lord Clarendon (ship)|Lord Clarendon]]'', the largest wooden ship ever built in Cape Breton.

===Merger with Nova Scotia===

In 1820, the colony of Cape Breton Island was merged for the second time with Nova Scotia.  This development is one of the factors which led to large-scale industrial development in the Sydney Coal Field of eastern Cape Breton County. By the late 19th century, as a result of the faster shipping, expanding fishery and industrialization of the island, exchanges of people between the island of [[Newfoundland (island)|Newfoundland]] and Cape Breton increased, beginning a cultural exchange that continues to this day.

The 1920s were some of the most violent times in Cape Breton. They were marked by several severe labour disputes.  The famous murder of [[William Davis (miner)|William Davis]] by strike breakers, and the seizing of the [[New Waterford, Nova Scotia|New Waterford]] power plant by striking miners led to a major union sentiment that persists to this day in some circles. [[William Davis Miners' Memorial Day]] is celebrated in coal mining towns to commemorate the deaths of miners at the hands of the coal companies.

===20th century===
{{More citations needed section|date=January 2019}}
The turn of the 20th century saw Cape Breton Island at the forefront of scientific achievement with the now-famous activities launched by inventors [[Alexander Graham Bell]] and [[Guglielmo Marconi]].

Following his successful invention of the telephone and being relatively wealthy, Bell acquired land near [[Baddeck, Nova Scotia|Baddeck]] in 1885, largely due to surroundings reminiscent of his early years in [[Scotland]]. He established a summer estate complete with research laboratories, working with deaf people—including [[Helen Keller]]—and continued to invent. Baddeck would be the site of his experiments with [[hydrofoil]] technologies as well as the [[Aerial Experiment Association]], financed by his wife, which saw the first powered flight in Canada when the [[AEA Silver Dart|AEA ''Silver Dart'']] took off from the ice-covered waters of [[Bras d'Or Lake]]. Bell also built the forerunner to the [[Negative pressure ventilator|iron lung]] and experimented with breeding sheep.

Marconi's contributions to Cape Breton Island were also quite significant, as he used the island's geography to his advantage in transmitting the first North American trans-[[Atlantic Ocean|Atlantic]] radio message from a station constructed at Table Head in [[Glace Bay, Nova Scotia|Glace Bay]] to a receiving station at [[Poldhu]] in Cornwall, England. Marconi's pioneering work in Cape Breton marked the beginning of modern radio technology. Marconi's station at Marconi Towers, on the outskirts of Glace Bay, became the chief communication centre for the [[Royal Canadian Navy]] in World War I through to the early years of World War II.

Promotions for tourism beginning in the 1950s recognized the importance of the Scottish culture to the province, and the provincial government started encouraging the use of Gaelic once again. The establishment of funding for the [[Gaelic College of Celtic Arts and Crafts]] and formal Gaelic [[language courses]] in public schools are intended to address the near-loss of this culture to English [[cultural assimilation|assimilation]].
 
In the 1960s, the [[Fortress of Louisbourg]] was partially reconstructed by [[Parks Canada]]. Since 2009, this [[National Historic Site of Canada]] has attracted an average of 90&amp;nbsp;000 visitors per year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.krausehouse.ca/krause/FortressOfLouisbourgVisitationNumbers.htm |title=Fortress of Louisbourg Visitation Numbers |last1=Krause |first1=Eric R.|date=30 July 2014|publisher=Krause House Info-Research Solutions |accessdate=8 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--

In early 2016, Cape Breton Island humorously announced that any American &quot;refugees&quot; fleeing their nation if [[Donald Trump]] (or possibly [[Hillary Clinton]]) won the presidential election would be welcomed to Cape Breton, with the only requirement being that the newcomers possess Canadian citizenship.&lt;ref name=&quot;cbiftrumpwins.com&quot;&gt;Cape Breton if Donald Trump Wins, via http://cbiftrumpwins.com/#intro&lt;/ref&gt; In their website's FAQ, they state they are doing this both to help American &quot;refugees&quot; and because &quot;...our population is shrinking. A slow economy, in combination with out-migration has us on an unsustainable path. The truth is we welcome all, no matter the ideology. We have a beautiful island, a friendly people, a rich culture and a bright future...&quot;. As of 9 November 2016, the day following [[United States presidential election, 2016|Election Day]], as well as Trump's victory, the offer still stands.&lt;ref name=&quot;cbiftrumpwins.com&quot;/&gt;--&gt;

===Gaelic speakers===
[[Scottish Gaelic|Gaelic speakers]] in Cape Breton, as elsewhere in Nova Scotia, furnished a large proportion of the local population from the eighteenth century on. They brought with them a common culture of poetry, traditional songs and tales, music and dance, and used this to develop distinctive local traditions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://gaelic.novascotia.ca/sites/default/files/files/Gaelic-Report.pdf|title=Gaelic Report|last=Kennedy|first=Michael|date=2001|website=|publisher=Nova Scotia Museum|access-date=13 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Most Gaelic settlement in Nova Scotia happened between 1770 and 1840, with probably over 50,000 Gaelic speakers emigrating from the Scottish Highlands and the Hebrides to [[Nova Scotia]] and [[Prince Edward Island]]. Such emigration was facilitated by changes in Gaelic society and the economy, with sharp increases in rents, confiscation of land and disruption of local customs and rights. In Nova Scotia, poetry and song in Gaelic flourished. George Emmerson argues that an &quot;ancient and rich&quot; tradition of storytelling, song, and Gaelic poetry emerged during the eighteenth century and was transplanted from the Highlands of Scotland to Nova Scotia, where the language similarly took root there.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/2678091|title=The Scottish tradition in Canada|last=Emmerson|first=George|date=1976|publisher=McClelland and Stewart in association with the Multiculturalism Program, Dept. of the Secretary of State of Canada and the Pub. Centre, Supply and Services Canada|others=Reid, W. Stanford (William Stanford), 1913–1996.|isbn=0771074433|location=Toronto|oclc=2678091}}&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of those settling in Nova Scotia from the end of the eighteenth century through to middle of the next were from the Scottish Highlands, rather than the Lowlands, making the Highland tradition's impact more profound on the region.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Highland Settler: A Portrait of the Scottish Gael in Nova Scotia|last=Dunn|first=Charles|publisher=University of Toronto Press|year=1968|pages=3–4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gaelic settlement in Cape Breton began in earnest in the early nineteenth century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://gaelic.novascotia.ca/sites/default/files/files/Gaelic-Report.pdf|title=Gaelic Report|last=Kennedy|first=Michael|date=2001|website=|publisher=Nova Scotia Museum|access-date=13 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
The Gaelic language became dominant from [[Colchester County]] in the west of Nova Scotia into Cape Breton County in the east. It was reinforced in Cape Breton in the first half of the 19th century with an influx of [[Highland Scots]] numbering approximately 50,000 as a result of the [[Highland Clearances]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://thechronicleherald.ca/novascotia/1211615-great-scots-the-past-comes-to-life-at-highland-village-museum|title=Great Scots: The past comes to life at Highland Village Museum|date=1 June 2014|work=The Chronicle Herald|access-date=14 June 2018|language=en|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180614122616/http://thechronicleherald.ca/novascotia/1211615-great-scots-the-past-comes-to-life-at-highland-village-museum|archive-date=14 June 2018|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://cabotshores.com/history-of-cape-breton-island-272|title=History of Cape Breton Island|date=8 February 2010|work=The Cabot Trail's Wilderness Resort on Cape Breton Island|access-date=14 June 2018|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Gaelic speakers, however, tended to be poor; they were largely illiterate and had little access to education. This situation still obtained in the early twentieth century. In 1921 Gaelic was approved as an optional subject in the curriculum of Nova Scotia, but few teachers could be found and children were discouraged from using the language in schools. By 1931 the number of Gaelic speakers in Nova Scotia had fallen to approximately 25,000, mostly in discrete pockets. In Cape Breton it was still a majority language, but the proportion was falling. Children were no longer being raised with Gaelic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://gaelic.novascotia.ca/sites/default/files/files/Gaelic-Report.pdf|title=Gaelic Report|last=Kennedy|first=Michael|date=2001|website=|publisher=Nova Scotia Museum|access-date=13 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From 1939 on attempts were made to strengthen its position in the public school system in Nova Scotia, but funding, official commitment and the availability of teachers continued to be a problem. By the 1950s the number of speakers was less than 7,000. The advent of [[multiculturalism in Canada]] in the 1960s meant that new educational opportunities became available, with a gradual strengthening of the language at secondary and tertiary level. At present several schools in Cape Breton offer Gaelic Studies and Gaelic language programs, and the language is taught at [[University College of Cape Breton]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://gaelic.novascotia.ca/sites/default/files/files/Gaelic-Report.pdf|title=Gaelic Report|last=Kennedy|first=Michael|date=2001|website=|publisher=Nova Scotia Museum|access-date=13 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2016 Canadian Census shows that there are only 40 reported speakers of Gaelic as a mother tongue in Cape Breton.&lt;ref&gt;https://www12.statcan.gc.ca/census-recensement/2016/dp-pd/prof/details/page.cfm?Lang=E&amp;Geo1=CD&amp;Code1=1217&amp;Geo2=PR&amp;Code2=12&amp;Data=Count&amp;SearchText=Cape%20Breton&amp;SearchType=Begins&amp;SearchPR=01&amp;TABID=1&amp;B1=All&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, there are families and individuals who have recommenced intergenerational transmission. They include fluent speakers from Gaelic-speaking areas of Scotland and speakers who became fluent in Nova Scotia and who in some cases studied in Scotland. Other revitalization activities include adult education, community cultural events and publishing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= https://gaelic.co/gaelic-identities/|title=Contrasting Gaelic Identities|last=McEwan|first=Emily|date=2017|website=|access-date=13 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Environment==

===Geography===
[[File:Sydney, Nova Scotia.jpg|thumb|right|200px|The Sydney waterfront, focal point of the largest population centre on Cape Breton Island.]]
The island measures {{convert|10311|km2|0}} in area, making it the [[List of islands by area|77th largest island in the world]] and [[List of Canadian islands by area|Canada's 18th largest island]]. Cape Breton Island is composed mainly of rocky shores, rolling farmland, glacial valleys, barren headlands, mountains, woods and plateaus. Geological evidence suggests at least part of the island was joined with present-day Scotland and Norway, now separated by millions of years of [[plate tectonics]].

Cape Breton Island's northern portion is dominated by the [[Cape Breton Highlands]], commonly shortened to simply the &quot;Highlands&quot;, which are an extension of the [[Appalachian Mountains|Appalachian mountain chain]]. The Highlands comprise the northern portions of [[Inverness County, Nova Scotia|Inverness]] and [[Victoria County, Nova Scotia|Victoria counties]]. In 1936, the federal government established the [[Cape Breton Highlands National Park]] covering {{convert|949|km2|sqmi|abbr=on}} across the northern third of the Highlands. The [[Cabot Trail]] scenic highway also encircles the plateau's coastal perimeter.
[[File:Sydney, Cape Breton waterfront buildings.jpg|thumb|left|Downtown Sydney is home to City Hall (right) as well as apartment complexes and hotels]]
Cape Breton Island's hydrological features include the [[Bras d'Or Lake]] system, a salt-water [[fjord]] at the heart of the island, and [[freshwater]] features including [[Lake Ainslie]], the [[Margaree River]] system, and the [[Mira River (Nova Scotia)|Mira River]]. Innumerable smaller rivers and streams drain into the Bras d'Or Lake [[estuary]] and on to the Gulf of St. Lawrence and Atlantic coasts.

Cape Breton Island is joined to the mainland by the [[Canso Causeway]], which was completed in 1955, enabling direct road and rail traffic to and from the island, but requiring [[marine traffic]] to pass through the [[Canso Canal]] at the eastern end of the [[causeway]].

Cape Breton Island is divided into four counties: [[Cape Breton County, Nova Scotia|Cape Breton]], [[Inverness County, Nova Scotia|Inverness]], [[Richmond County, Nova Scotia|Richmond]], and [[Victoria County, Nova Scotia|Victoria]].

The climate is one of mild, often pleasantly warm summers and cold winters, although the proximity to the Atlantic Ocean and [[Gulf Stream]] moderates the extreme winter cold found on the mainland, especially on the east side that faces the Atlantic. Precipitation is abundant year round, with annual totals up to 60 inches on the eastern side facing the Atlantic storms. Considerable snowfall occurs in winter, especially in the highlands.

===Wildlife===
{{see also|Cape Breton Highlands National Park}}

==Demographics==
[[File:Glace Bay Shul, August 2012.jpg|thumb|200px|The former Congregation Sons of Israel synagogue, in Glace Bay. In 1902, the synagogue was Nova Scotia's first purpose built synagogue. It permanently closed in July 2010. To the left is the also closed Talmud Torah community centre. This was the location of the Hebrew school and functions like Bar Mitzvah and wedding dinners.]]

The island's residents can be grouped into five main cultures: [[Scottish people|Scottish]], [[Mi'kmaq people|Mi'kmaq]], [[Acadian]], Irish, English, with respective languages [[Scottish Gaelic]], [[Míkmaq language|Mi'kmaq]], [[Acadian French|French]], and English. English is now the primary language, including a locally distinctive [[Cape Breton accent]], while Mi'kmaq, Scottish Gaelic and Acadian French are still spoken in some communities.

Later migrations of [[Black Loyalist]]s, Italians, and Eastern Europeans mostly settled in the island's eastern part around the industrial Cape Breton region. Cape Breton Island's population has been in decline two decades with an increasing exodus in recent years due to economic conditions.

According to the Census of Canada, the population of Cape Breton [Economic region] in 2016 / 2011 / 2006 / 1996 was 132,010 / 135,974 / 142,298 / 158,260.

===Religious groups===

[[Canada 2001 Census|Statistics Canada]] in 2001 reported a &quot;religion&quot; total of 145,525 for Cape Breton, including 5,245 with &quot;no religious affiliation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www12.statcan.ca/english/profil01/CP01/Details/Page.cfm?Lang=E&amp;Geo1=CD&amp;Code1=1217&amp;Geo2=CD&amp;Code2=1216&amp;Data=Count&amp;SearchText=Cape%20Breton%20County&amp;SearchType=Begins&amp;SearchPR=01&amp;B1=All&amp;Custom= Table from Statistics Canada – Cape Breton &amp; Richmond Counties]'' (Nova Scotia Statistics Agency)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www12.statcan.ca/english/profil01/CP01/Details/Page.cfm?Lang=E&amp;Geo1=CD&amp;Code1=1218&amp;Geo2=CD&amp;Code2=1215&amp;Data=Count&amp;SearchText=Cape%20Breton%20County&amp;SearchType=Begins&amp;SearchPR=01&amp;B1=All&amp;Custom= Table from Statistics Canada – Victoria &amp; Inverness Counties]'' (Nova Scotia Statistics Agency)&lt;/ref&gt; Major categories included:
* [[Roman Catholic]] : 96,260 (includes Eastern Catholic, Polish National Catholic Church, Old Catholic)
* [[Protestant]]: 42,390
* Christian, not included elsewhere: 580
* [[Orthodox Church|Orthodox]]: 395
* [[Jewish]]: 250
* [[Muslim]]: 145

==Economy==
[[File:Cape Breton Flag - Popular.jpg|thumb|100px|Cape Breton Island's most recognizable and commonly used flag.]]
[[File:Cape Breton Island flag 1997.png|thumb|100px|Cape Breton Island's &quot;Eagle&quot; flag (1994).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.capebretonpost.com/Football/2009-11-23/article-774026/Woman-wants-Cape-Breton-flag-designed-by-her-daughter-recognized/1 Woman wants Cape Breton flag designed by her daughter recognized – Football] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140413142115/http://www.capebretonpost.com/Football/2009-11-23/article-774026/Woman-wants-Cape-Breton-flag-designed-by-her-daughter-recognized/1 |date=13 April 2014 }}. Cape Breton Post (23 November 2009). Retrieved on 12 April 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[File:Cape Breton Island flag 1990s.png|thumb|100px|Cape Breton Island's second cultural flag, the &quot;Tartan&quot; flag (early 1990s)]]
[[File:Cape Breton Island Flag 1940s.svg|thumb|100px|Cape Breton Island's first cultural flag, the blue-and-yellow flag dates to the 1940s]]

Much of the recent economic history of Cape Breton Island can be tied to the coal industry.

The island has two major coal deposits:

* the Sydney Coal Field in the southeastern part of the island along the Atlantic Ocean drove the Industrial Cape Breton economy throughout the 19th and 20th centuries—until after [[World War II]], its industries were the largest private employers in Canada.
* the Inverness Coal Field in the western part of the island along the Gulf of St. Lawrence is significantly smaller but hosted several mines.

[[Sydney, Nova Scotia|Sydney]] has traditionally been the main port, with facilities in a large, sheltered, natural harbour. It is the island's largest commercial centre and home to the ''[[Cape Breton Post]]'' daily newspaper, as well as one television station, [[CJCB-TV]] (CTV),{{refn|group=&quot;Note&quot;|[[CBIT-TV]] (CBC) existed from 1972 until 31 July 2012, when the CBC closed its over-the-air analog transmitters in small markets. It produced a local news broadcast until 1991, when local news shows were consolidated to Halifax. The CBC Nova Scotia television signal, which originates from Halifax, is now available only by cable or satellite providers.&lt;ref name=&quot;CBC closes transmitters&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 |title=Revocation of licences for the rebroadcasting stations CBIT Sydney and CBKST Saskatoon and licence amendment to remove analog transmitters for 23 English- and French-language television stations 
 |work=Decisions, Notices and Orders 
 |publisher=Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission 
 |url=http://www.crtc.gc.ca/eng/archive/2012/2012-384.htm 
 |date=17 July 2012 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120728043036/http://www.crtc.gc.ca/eng/archive/2012/2012-384.htm
 |archivedate=28 July 2012
 |url-status=live
 |location=Ottawa 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} and several radio stations. The [[Marine Atlantic]] terminal at [[North Sydney, Nova Scotia|North Sydney]] is the terminal for large ferries traveling to [[Channel-Port aux Basques]] and seasonally to [[Argentia]], both on the island of [[Newfoundland (island)|Newfoundland]].

[[Point Edward, Nova Scotia|Point Edward]] on the west side of Sydney Harbour is the location of Sydport, a former [[Royal Canadian Navy|navy]] base ({{HMCS|Protector}}) now converted to commercial use. The [[Canadian Coast Guard College]] is nearby at Westmount. Petroleum, bulk coal, and cruise ship facilities are also in Sydney Harbour.

[[Glace Bay, Nova Scotia|Glace Bay]], the second largest urban community in population, was the island's main coal mining centre until its last mine closed in the 1980s. Glace Bay was the hub of the Sydney &amp; Louisburg Railway and a major fishing port. At one time, Glace Bay was known as the largest town in Nova Scotia, based on population.

[[Port Hawkesbury]] has risen to prominence since the completion of the Canso Causeway and [[Canso Canal]] created an artificial deep-water port, allowing extensive petrochemical, pulp and paper, and gypsum handling facilities to be established. The Strait of Canso is completely navigable to [[Seawaymax]] vessels, and Port Hawkesbury is open to the deepest-draught vessels on the world's oceans. Large marine vessels may also enter Bras d'Or Lake through the Great Bras d'Or channel, and small craft can use the Little Bras d'Or channel or [[St. Peters Canal]]. While commercial shipping no longer uses the St. Peters Canal, it remains an important waterway for recreational vessels.

The industrial Cape Breton area faced several challenges with the closure of the [[Cape Breton Development Corporation]]'s (DEVCO) coal mines and the [[Sydney Steel Corporation]]'s (SYSCO) [[steel mill]]. In recent years, the Island's residents have tried to diversify the area economy by investing in tourism developments, [[call centre]]s, and small businesses, as well as manufacturing ventures in fields such as auto parts, pharmaceuticals, and window glazings.

While the [[Cape Breton Regional Municipality]] is in transition from an industrial to a service-based economy, the rest of Cape Breton Island outside the industrial area surrounding Sydney-Glace Bay has been more stable, with a mixture of fishing, forestry, small-scale agriculture, and tourism.

Tourism in particular has grown throughout the post-[[Second World War]] era, especially the growth in vehicle-based touring, which was furthered by the creation of the [[Cabot Trail]] scenic drive.  The scenery of the island is rivalled in northeastern North America by only [[Newfoundland (island)|Newfoundland]];{{Citation needed|reason=Subjective?|date=September 2013}} and Cape Breton Island tourism marketing places a heavy emphasis on its Scottish [[Gaels|Gaelic]] heritage through events such as the Celtic Colours Festival, held each October, as well as promotions through the [[Gaelic College of Celtic Arts and Crafts]].

Whale-watching is a popular attraction for tourists. Whale-watching cruises are operated by vendors from Baddeck to Cheticamp. The most popular species of whale found in Cape Breton's waters is the [[Pilot whale]].

The island's primary east-west road is [[Nova Scotia Highway 105|Highway 105]], the [[Trans-Canada Highway]], although [[Nova Scotia Trunk 4|Trunk 4]] is also heavily used. [[Nova Scotia Highway 125|Highway 125]] is an important arterial route around Sydney Harbour in the [[Cape Breton Regional Municipality]]. The [[Cabot Trail]], circling the Cape Breton Highlands, and [[Nova Scotia Trunk 19|Trunk 19]], along the island's western coast, are important secondary roads. The [[Cape Breton and Central Nova Scotia Railway]] maintains railway connections between the port of Sydney to the [[Canadian National Railway]] in [[Truro, Nova Scotia|Truro]]

The [[Cabot Trail]] is a scenic road circuit around and over the [[Cape Breton Highlands]] with spectacular coastal vistas; over 400,000 visitors drive the Cabot Trail each summer and fall. Coupled with the [[Fortress of Louisbourg]], it has driven the growth of the tourism industry on the island in recent decades. The ''[[Condé Nast Publications|Condé Nast]]'' travel guide has rated Cape Breton Island as one of the world's best island destinations.

==Traditional music==
{{main|Cape Breton fiddling}}

Cape Breton is well known for its traditional fiddle music, which was brought to North America by Scottish immigrants during the [[Highland Clearances]]. The traditional style has been well preserved in Cape Breton, and [[céilidh]]s have become a popular attraction for tourists. [[Inverness County, Nova Scotia|Inverness County]] in particular has a heavy concentration of musical activity, with regular performances in communities such as [[Mabou, Nova Scotia|Mabou]] and [[Judique, Nova Scotia|Judique]]. Judique is recognized as 'Baile nam Fonn', (literally: Village of Tunes) or the 'Home of Celtic Music', featuring the Celtic Music Interpretive Centre. Performers who have received significant recognition outside of Cape Breton include [[Angus Chisholm]], [[Buddy MacMaster]], [[Joseph Cormier]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.acadianfiddle.com/artists2/2015/1/29/joe-cormier |title=JOE CORMIER}}, article from {{cite web|url=http://www.acadianfiddle.com/|title=ACADIAN FIDDLE}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.arts.gov/honors/heritage/fellows/joseph-cormier|title=Joseph Cormier}}, biography from {{cite web|url=https://www.arts.gov/|title=NATIONAL ENDOWMENT for the ARTS}}&lt;/ref&gt;, first Cape Breton fiddler to record an album made available in Europe (1974)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.discogs.com/fr/Joseph-Cormier-Scottish-Violin-Music-From-Cape-Breton-Island/release/8594111 |title=Joseph Cormier - Scottish Violin Music From Cape Breton Island, |publisher=[[Rounder Records]], USA}} {{cite web|url=https://img.discogs.com/lKFIoYIVRs6FG22c5hl1r8BeJDY=/fit-in/600x594/filters:strip_icc():format(jpeg):mode_rgb():quality(90)/discogs-images/R-8594111-1464725269-4093.jpeg.jpg|title=Vinyl album, 1974}}&lt;/ref&gt;, [[Lee Cremo]], [[Bruce Guthro]], [[Natalie MacMaster]], [[Ashley MacIsaac]], [[The Rankin Family]], [[Aselin Debison]], [[Gordie Sampson]], Dawn and Margie Beaton, also known as &quot;[[The Beaton Sisters]]&quot;, and the [[Barra MacNeils]]. The Margaree's of Cape Breton also serve as a large contributor of fiddle music celebrated throughout the island. This traditional fiddle music of Cape Breton is studied by musicians around the world, where its global recognition continues to rise.

[[The Men of the Deeps]] are a male choral group of current and former miners from the industrial Cape Breton area.

==Film and television==
*''[[Squanto: A Warrior's Tale]]'' (1994) starring [[Adam Beach]]
*''[[Margaret's Museum]]'' (1995) starring [[Helena Bonham Carter]]
*''[[The Bay Boy]]'' (1984) starring [[Kiefer Sutherland]]
*''[[New Waterford Girl]]'' (1999) directed by [[Allan Moyle]]
*''[[The Hanging Garden (film)|The Hanging Garden]]'' (1997) directed by [[Thom Fitzgerald]]
*''[[Marion Bridge (film)|Marion Bridge]]'' (2002) directed by [[Wiebke von Carolsfeld]]
*''[[My Bloody Valentine (film)|My Bloody Valentine]]'' (1981) directed by George Mihalka
*''[[Pit Pony (film)|Pit Pony]]'' (1997), TV movie and [[Pit Pony (TV series)|series]] adapted from the [[Pit Pony (novel)|novel]] by [[Joyce Barkhouse]]
*''[[The Book of Negroes (miniseries)|The Book of Negroes]]'' (2015) starring [[Cuba Gooding Jr.]] adapted from the novel of the same name by [[Lawrence Hill]]

==Notable people==
{{Main|List of people from Cape Breton}}

Cape Breton artists who have been recognized with major national or international awards include actor [[Harold Russell]] of [[North Sydney, Nova Scotia|North Sydney]], who won an [[Academy Awards|Academy Award]] in 1946 for his portrayal of Homer Parrish in ''[[The Best Years of Our Lives]]'', and [[Lynn Coady]] and [[Linden MacIntyre]] of [[Inverness County, Nova Scotia|Inverness County]], who are both past winners of the [[Giller Prize]] for [[Canadian literature]]. [[The Rankin Family]] and [[Rita MacNeil]] have recorded multiple [[Music album|albums]] [[Music recording sales certification|certified]] as Double Platinum by [[Music Canada]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | title =Gold/Platinum
 | publisher =[[Music Canada]]
 | url =https://musiccanada.com/gold-platinum/
 | format =Searchable database
 | accessdate =31 July 2014
 | archive-url =https://web.archive.org/web/20160602053405/http://musiccanada.com/gold-platinum/
 | archive-date =2 June 2016
 | url-status =dead
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

People from Cape Breton have also achieved a number of firsts in [[Canadian politics]] and governance. These include [[Mayann Francis]] of [[Whitney Pier]], the first [[Black Nova Scotians|Black]] [[Lieutenant Governor of Nova Scotia]], [[Isaac Phills]] of Sydney, Nova Scotia, the first person of [[Africans|African descent]] to be awarded the [[Order of Canada]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1638&amp;dat=19670707&amp;id=zik6AAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=PioMAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=489,4625692
 | title = The North Bay Nugget – July 7, 1967
 | accessdate = 7 September 2018
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Elizabeth May]] of [[Margaree Harbour, Nova Scotia|Margaree Harbour]], the first member of the [[Green Party of Canada]] elected to the [[House of Commons of Canada]].

Cape Breton Island is also home to YouTube weather forecaster [[Frankie MacDonald]], who has over 200,000 subscribers. He accurately predicted an magnitude 7 earthquake in New Zealand in November 2016.

American artists like sculptor [[Richard Serra]], composer [[Philip Glass]] and abstract painter [[John Beardman]] spent part of the year on Cape Breton Island.

[[Steve Arbuckle]] is a Canadian-born actor born in Cape Breton Island.

Director [[Ashley McKenzie (director)|Ashley McKenzie]]'s 2016 film ''[[Werewolf (2016 film)|Werewolf]]'' is set on the island and features local actors; McKenzie grew up on the island.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/nova-scotia/cape-breton-films-makes-splash-in-europe-1.3993103|title=Cape Breton film gets 'overwhelming' reaction at Berlin film festival|work=[[CBC News]]|access-date=6 March 2017|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Bruce Guthro]]; Lead singer and guitarist of the former [[Scottish Gaelic|Scottish]] [[Celtic nations|Celtic]] band [[Runrig]], which disbanded in 2018 after 46 years. Guthro resides in [[Hammonds Plains, Nova Scotia|Hammonds Plains]], [[Nova Scotia]].

[[Dylan Guthro]]; musician.  Son of [[Bruce Guthro]].

== Photo gallery ==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Cabotslanding.jpg|Cabot's Landing, Victoria County, commemorating the &quot;first land seen&quot; by explorer John Cabot in 1497
File:Cape breton island 1.jpg
File:Cape breton island 2.jpg|The shoreline of [[Bras d'Or Lake]] at [[Marble Mountain, Nova Scotia|Marble Mountain]], [[Inverness County, Nova Scotia|Inverness Co.]].
File:Cape breton island 3.jpg|A bulk carrier in the [[Strait of Canso]] docked at the Martin Marietta Materials quarry at Cape Porcupine.
File:NS CapeBretonHighlands2 tango7174.jpg|[[Cape Breton Highlands National Park]].
File:NS SmeltBrook tango7174.jpg|[[Smelt Brook, Nova Scotia|Smelt Brook]] on the northern shore.
File:CapeBretonEntrance.jpg|Entering Cape Breton Island from [[Canso Causeway]].
File:Capebretonmainlandbridge.jpg|[[Seal Island Bridge]] in Victoria County, the 3rd longest in Nova Scotia.
File:Sydney Harbour aerial view.jpg|[[Sydney, Nova Scotia|Sydney]] Harbour with Point Edward, Westmount, and downtown Sydney visible.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
* [[Canadian Gaelic]]
* [[Cape Breton accent]]
* [[Cape Breton Labour Party]]
* [[Cape Breton Regional Municipality]]
* [[Provinces and territories of Canada]]
* [[Province of Cape Breton Island]]
* [[Sydney Tar Ponds]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist|group=&quot;Note&quot;}}

== References ==
=== Citations ===
{{Reflist}}

=== Sources ===
{{refbegin|30em}}

====Books and journals====
* {{cite book
 |last         = Akins
 |first        = Thomas B.
 |title        = History of Halifax
 |year         = 1895
 |publisher    = Brook House Press
 |location     = Dartmouth
 |ref          = harv
}}
*{{cite book |last       = Barlow
 |first      = Maude
 |last2      = May
 |first2     = Elizabeth
 |title      = Frederick Street: Life and Death on Canada's Love Canal
 |publisher  = HarperCollins Publishers
 |location   = Toronto
 |year       = 2000
 |isbn       = 978-0-00-638529-5
 |ref        = harv
 |url-access = registration
 |url        = https://archive.org/details/topicsinoptimald0000unse
}}
*{{cite book
 | last       = Brown
 | first      = Thomas J.
 | url        = https://archive.org/stream/placenamesofprov00browrich#page/140/mode/2up
 | title      = Place-names of the province of Nova Scotia
 | publisher  = Royal Print &amp; Litho
 | location   = Halifax
 | year       = 1922
 | ref        = harv
}}
*{{cite journal
 | last       = Caplan
 | first      = Ronald
 | title      = Sydney Harbour in World War 2
 | journal    = Cape Breton's Magazine
 | date       = 1 June 1976
 | issue      = 13
 | pages      = 27–40
 | url        = http://capebretonsmagazine.com/modules/publisher/item.php?itemid=417
 | accessdate = 6 January 2013
 | publisher  = Breton Books
 | location   = Wreck Cove, Cape Breton, Nova Scotia
 | issn       = 0319-4639
 | ref        = harv
}}
*{{ cite book
 | last      = Doyle
 | first     = Bill
 | title     = Cape Breton Facts and Folklore
 | publisher = Nimbus Publishing
 | location  = Halifax, Nova Scotia
 | isbn      = 978-1-55109-867-8
 | year      = 2011
 | ref       = harv
}}
*{{cite book
 | last       = Harris
 | first      = Michael
 | title      = Justice Denied: The Law versus Donald Marshall
 | publisher  = Totem Books
 | year       = 1987
 | location   = Toronto
 | isbn       = 978-0-00-217890-7
 | ref        = harv
}}
* {{cite book
 | last       = Howe
 | first      = C. D.
 | title      = The Canada Year Book 1955: The Official Statistical Annual of the Resources, History, Institutions, and Social and Economic Conditions of the Dominion
 | year       = 1955
 | publisher  = Canada Year Book Section Information Services Division
 | location   = Ottawa
 | url        = http://www66.statcan.gc.ca/eng/acyb_c1955-eng.aspx?opt=/eng/1955/195501670141_p.%20141.pdf
 | ref        = harv
}}
*{{cite book
 |last        = MacDonald
 |first       = Herb
 |title       = Cape Breton Railways: An Illustrated History
 |year        = 2012
 |publisher   = Cape Breton University Press
 |location    = Sydney, Nova Scotia
 |isbn        = 978-1-897009-67-3 
 |ref         = harv
}}
*{{cite book
 |last        = Morgan
 |first       = Robert J.
 |title       = Rise Again!: the Story of Cape Breton Island - Book One
 |year        = 2008
 |publisher   = Breton Books
 |location    = Wreck Cove, Nova Scotia
 |isbn        = 978-1-895415-81-0
 |editor      = Ronald Caplan
 |editor-link = Ronald Caplan
 |ref         = harv
}}
* {{cite web
 |url = http://www.gov.ns.ca/nsarm/virtual/places/page.asp?ID=657 
 |title = Place-Names and Places of Nova Scotia/with an introd. by Charles Bruce Fergusson 
 |year=1967 
 |author=Public Archives of Nova Scotia 
 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20130603011553/http://www.gov.ns.ca/nsarm/virtual/places/page.asp?ID=657 
 |archivedate=3 June 2013 
 |ref=harv 
 |location=Halifax 
 |url-status=dead 
}}
* {{cite book
 | last       = Sarty
 | first      = Roger F.
 | title      = War in the St. Lawerance: The Forgotten U-boat Battles on Canada's Shores
 | year       = 2012
 | publisher  = Allen Lane
 | location   = Toronto
 | isbn       = 978-0-670-06787-9
 | ref        = harv
}}
*{{cite book
 | last       = Stevens
 | first      = H. H.
 | title      = The Canada Year Book 1932: The Official Statistical Annual of the Resources, History, Institutions, and Social and Economic Conditions of the Dominion
 | year       = 1932
 | publisher  = Dominion Bureau of Statistics General Statistics Branch 
 | location   = Ottawa
 | url        = http://www66.statcan.gc.ca/eng/acyb_c1932-eng.aspx?opt=/eng/1932/193201410103_p.%20103.pdf
 | ref        = harv
}}
*{{cite book
 | last       = Tennyson
 | first      = B. D.
 | title      = Cape Bretoniana: an annotated bibliography
 | year       = 2004
 | publisher  = University of Toronto Press
 | location   = Toronto
 | ref        = harv
}}
*{{cite book
 | last       = Tennyson
 | first      = Brian Douglas
 | last2      = Sarty
 | first2     = Roger F.
 | title      = Guardian of the Gulf: Sydney, Cape Breton, and the Atlantic wars
 | year       = 2000
 | publisher  = University of Toronto Press
 | location   = Toronto
 | isbn       = 0-8020-4492-1
 | url        = https://archive.org/details/guardianofgulfsy0000tenn
 | url-access = registration
 | ref        = harv
}}
*{{cite book
 | last       = Winters
 | first      = Robert. H.
 | title      = Canada Year Book 1967: Official Statistical Annual of the Resources, History, Institutions, and Social and Economic Conditions of the Dominion 
 | year       = 1967
 | publisher  = Dominion Bureau of Statistics Canada Year Book Division 
 | location   = Ottawa
 | url        = http://www66.statcan.gc.ca/eng/acyb_c1932-eng.aspx?opt=/eng/1932/193201410103_p.%20103.pdf
 | ref = harv
}}

====News media====
* {{cite news
  | author      = CP Special
  | title       = March through Sydney: 20,000 protest DOSCO closing
  | newspaper   = The Toronto Daily Star
  | date        = 20 November 1967
  | page        = 5
  | location    = Toronto
  | ref         = harv
}}
*{{cite news
  | last        = Grimes
  | first       = William
  | title       = Donald Marshall Jr., Symbol of Bias, Dies at 55
  | newspaper   = The New York Times
  | date        = 7 August 2009&lt;!-- Don't remove, as this is how the Harvard references links to this citation --&gt;
  | page        = A20
  | location    = New York
  | url         = https://www.nytimes.com/2009/08/07/world/americas/07marshall.html
  | accessdate  = 11 January 2013
  | ref         = harv
}}
* {{cite news
   | last       = Lebel
   | first      = Ronald
   | title      = Premier calls for government aid to keep Dosco going four months
   | newspaper  = The Globe and Mail
   | date       = 18 October 1967 &lt;!-- Don't remove, as this is how the Harvard references links to this citation --&gt;
   | location   = Toronto
   | pages      = 1, 2
   | ref        = harv
}}
* {{cite news
   | last       = Loring
   | first      = Rex
   | title      = The marvellous microwave network
   | work       = Scan
   | publisher  = CBC News Digital Archives
   | date       = 30 June 1958
   | location   = Toronto
   | url        = http://www.cbc.ca/archives/categories/arts-entertainment/media/canada-tunes-in-the-early-years-of-radio-and-tv/the-marvellous-microwave-network.html
   | accessdate = 11 January 2013
   | ref        = harv
}}
* {{cite news
   | last       = MacDonald
   | first      = Randy
   | title      = Holy Angels graduation &quot;bittersweet&quot; as Sydney school sets to close
   | url        = http://atlantic.ctv.ca/servlet/an/local/CTVNews/20110620/holy_angels_110620/20110620/?hub=AtlanticHome
   | accessdate = 16 May 2012
   | newspaper  = CTV Atlantic News
   | date       = 20 June 2011
   | location   = Halifax
   | ref        = harv
}}
* {{cite news
   | last       = Milton
   | first      = Steve
   | title      = New name needed for AHL import: Something from the animal kingdom is very much in vogue now
   | newspaper  = The Hamilton Spectator
   | date       = 9 May 1996 &lt;!-- Don't remove, as this is how the Harvard references links to this citation --&gt;
   | page       = C1
   | location   = Hamilton, Ontario
   | ref        = harv
}}
* {{cite news
   | author     = Special to the Star
   | title      = Nova Scotia will buy Dosco plant, operate it until at least April '69
   | newspaper  = Toronto Daily Star 
   | page       = 1 
   | date       = 23 November 1967
   | ref        = harv
}}
* {{cite news
   | author     = Spectator Staff
   | title      = 7,006 fill the Dog House: A large walkup crowd was entertained to Fight Night in Steeltown as the Hamilton Bulldogs officially took to the ice last night.
   | newspaper  = The Hamilton Spectator
   | date       = 5 October 1996&lt;!-- Don't remove, as this is how the Harvard references links to this citation --&gt;
   | page       = C1
   | location   = Hamilton, Ontario
   | ref        = harv
}}
* {{cite news
   | author     = Star Staff
   | title      = Nova Scotia will buy Dosco plant, operate it until at least April '69
   | newspaper  = Toronto Daily Star
   | date       = 23 November 1967&lt;!-- Don't remove, as this is how the Harvard references links to this citation --&gt;
   | page       = 1
   | edition    = 2 Star
   | location   = Toronto
   | ref = harv
}}

====Other online sources====
* {{cite web
 |title = Demographic Information 
 |url = http://www.cbrm.ns.ca/planning-development-department.html 
 |work=Planning and Development Department 
 |publisher=Cape Breton Regional Municipality 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120903093653/http://www.cbrm.ns.ca/planning-development-department.html
 |archivedate=3 September 2012
 |location=Sydney, Nova Scotia 
 |year=2012 
 |ref={{harvid|Cape Breton Regional Municipality|(2012)}} 
 |url-status=dead
}}

*{{cite web
 | author           = Environment Canada
 | url           = http://www.climate.weatheroffice.gc.ca/climate_normals/results_e.html?stnID=6486&amp;prov=&amp;lang=e&amp;dCode=1&amp;dispBack=1&amp;StationName=Sydney&amp;SearchType=Contains&amp;province=ALL&amp;provBut=&amp;month1=0&amp;month2=12
 | title           = Canadian Climate Normals 1971–2000: Sydney, Nova Scotia
 | work           = National Climate Data and Information Archive
 | accessdate           = 23 May 2012
 | archiveurl           = https://web.archive.org/web/20130612051713/http://www.climate.weatheroffice.gc.ca/climate_normals/results_e.html?stnID=6486&amp;prov=&amp;lang=e&amp;dCode=1&amp;dispBack=1&amp;StationName=Sydney&amp;SearchType=Contains&amp;province=ALL&amp;provBut=&amp;month1=0&amp;month2=12
 | archivedate           = 12 June 2013
 | publisher           = Queen's Printer for Canada
 | location           = Ottawa
 | year           = 2012a
 | ref           = harv
 | url-status           = dead
 }}
*{{cite web
 | title        = Hourly Data: Sydney, Nova Scotia
 | url        = http://www.climate.weatheroffice.gc.ca/climateData/hourlydata_e.html?timeframe=1&amp;Prov=XX&amp;StationID=6486&amp;Year=2012&amp;Month=5&amp;Day=22
 | work        = National Climate Data and Information Archive
 | publisher        = Queen's Printer for Canada
 | accessdate        = 23 May 2012
 | author        = Environment Canada
 | archiveurl        = https://web.archive.org/web/20130612063050/http://www.climate.weatheroffice.gc.ca/climateData/hourlydata_e.html?timeframe=1&amp;Prov=XX&amp;StationID=6486&amp;Year=2012&amp;Month=5&amp;Day=22
 | archivedate        = 12 June 2013
 | location        = Ottawa
 | date        = 10 May 2012
 | ref        = harv
 | url-status        = dead
 }}
* {{cite web
 | title        = History
 | url        = http://38.108.70.85/lang_en/index.php?page=27844&amp;id_equipe=8¤tseason=112
 | work        = Cape Breton Screaming Eagles
 | publisher        = Quebec Major Junior Hockey League
 | archiveurl        = https://www.webcitation.org/6A1RsvPzS?url=http://38.108.70.85/lang_en/index.php?page=27844&amp;id_equipe=8&amp;currentseason=112
 | archivedate        = 19 August 2012
 | location        = Montreal
 | year        = 2012
 | ref        = {{harvid|Quebec Major Junior Hockey League|(2012)}}
 | url-status        = dead
 }}
*{{cite web
 | url  = http://www12.statcan.gc.ca/census-recensement/2011/dp-pd/prof/details/Page.cfm?Lang=E&amp;Geo1=POPC&amp;Code1=0913&amp;Geo2=CSD&amp;Code2=1217030&amp;Data=Count&amp;SearchText=Sydney&amp;SearchType=Begins&amp;SearchPR=12&amp;B1=All&amp;Custom=
 | title  = Cape Breton – Sydney, Nova Scotia (Code 0913) and Cape Breton, Nova Scotia (Code 1217030) (table). Census Profile
 | author  = Statistics Canada
 | authorlink  = Statistics Canada
 | work  = 2011 Census. Statistics Canada Catalogue no. 98-316-XWE
 | publisher  = Queen's Printer for Canada
 | location  = Ottawa
 | accessdate  = 16 May 2012
 | archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20130207115404/http://www12.statcan.gc.ca/census-recensement/2011/dp-pd/prof/details/Page.cfm?Lang=E&amp;Geo1=POPC&amp;Code1=0913&amp;Geo2=CSD&amp;Code2=1217030&amp;Data=Count&amp;SearchText=Sydney&amp;SearchType=Begins&amp;SearchPR=12&amp;B1=All&amp;Custom=
 | archivedate  = 7 February 2013
 | year  = 2012a
 | ref  = harv
 | url-status  = dead
 }}
*{{cite web
 | title         = Map: Cape Breton – Sydney (Population Centre), Nova Scotia
 | url         = http://www12.statcan.gc.ca/census-recensement/2011/dp-pd/prof/details/page_Map-Carte.cfm?Lang=E&amp;Tab=3&amp;Geo1=POPC&amp;Code1=0913&amp;Geo2=CSD&amp;Code2=1217030&amp;Data=Count&amp;SearchText=Sydney&amp;SearchType=Begins&amp;SearchPR=12&amp;B1=All&amp;Custom=&amp;TABID=1
 | work         = 2011 Census
 | publisher         = Queen's Printer for Canada
 | accessdate         = 18 May 2012
 | author         = Statistics Canada
 | archiveurl         = https://web.archive.org/web/20130207124555/http://www12.statcan.gc.ca/census-recensement/2011/dp-pd/prof/details/page_Map-Carte.cfm?Lang=E&amp;Tab=3&amp;Geo1=POPC&amp;Code1=0913&amp;Geo2=CSD&amp;Code2=1217030&amp;Data=Count&amp;SearchText=Sydney&amp;SearchType=Begins&amp;SearchPR=12&amp;B1=All&amp;Custom=&amp;TABID=1
 | archivedate         = 7 February 2013
 | location         = Ottawa
 | year         = 2012b
 | ref         = harv
 | url-status         = dead
 }}
*{{cite web
 |last1=Deibel 
 |first1=James 
 |last2=Norda 
 |first2=Jacob 
 |title=Historical Weather for the Last Twelve Months in Sydney, Nova Scotia, Canada 
 |url=http://weatherspark.com/history/28351/2012/Sydney-Nova-Scotia-Canada 
 |work=WeatherSpark 
 |publisher=Vector Magic, Inc. 
 |accessdate=26 December 2012 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130521235637/http://weatherspark.com/history/28351/2012/Sydney-Nova-Scotia-Canada
 |archivedate=21 May 2013
 |url-status=live
 |location=San Francisco 
 |year=2012 
 |ref=harv 
}}
*{{cite web
 |title=Sydney Academy 
 |url=http://www.cbv.ns.ca/Schools/#Sydney%20Academy 
 |work=CB-VRSB Schools 
 |publisher=Cape Breton-Victoria Regional School Board 
 |accessdate=26 December 2012 
 |author=CB-VRSB Staff 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130101075513/http://www.cbv.ns.ca/Schools/
 |archivedate=1 January 2013
 |url-status=dead
 |location=Sydney, Nova Scotia 
 |year=2012 
 |ref=harv 
}}
*{{cite web
 |last=Kernaghan 
 |first=Lois 
 |title=University College of Cape Breton 
 |url=http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/articles/university-college-of-cape-breton 
 |work=The Canadian Encyclopedia 
 |publisher=Institute Historica/Dominion Institute 
 |accessdate=6 January 2013 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130519141733/http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/articles/university-college-of-cape-breton
 |archivedate=19 May 2013
 |url-status=live
 |location=Toronto 
 |year=2012 
 |ref=harv 
}}
*{{cite web
 |title=Revocation of licences for the rebroadcasting stations CBIT Sydney and CBKST Saskatoon and licence amendment to remove analog transmitters for 23 English- and French-language television stations 
 |work=Decisions, Notices and Orders 
 |publisher=Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission 
 |url=http://www.crtc.gc.ca/eng/archive/2012/2012-384.htm 
 |date=17 July 2012 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120728043036/http://www.crtc.gc.ca/eng/archive/2012/2012-384.htm
 |archivedate=28 July 2012
 |url-status=live
 |location=Ottawa 
 |ref={{harvid|CRTC|2012}} 
}}
*{{cite web
 |last        = Dulmage
 |first       = Bill
 |title       = Nova Scotia CBIT-TV (CBC-TV), Sydney, Canadian Broadcasting Corporation
 |url         = http://www.broadcasting-history.ca/index3.html?url=http://www.broadcasting-history.ca/listings_and_histories/television/histories.php?id=77&amp;historyID=88
 |work        = Television Station History
 |publisher   = Canadian Communications Foundation
 |accessdate  = 26 December 2012
 |location    = Toronto
 |date        = July 2012
 |ref         = harv
 |df          = dmy-all
}}{{dead link|date=July 2019|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}
*{{cite web
 |title        = Radio History: CJCB-AM, Sydney, Maritime Broadcasting Ltd.
 |url          = http://www.broadcasting-history.ca/index3.html?url=http%3A//www.broadcasting-history.ca/listings_and_histories/radio/histories.php%3Fid%3D679%26historyID%3D266
 |publisher    = Canadian Communications Foundation
 |year         = 2013
 |accessdate   = 10 January 2013
 |location     = Toronto
 |ref          = {{harvid|Canadian Communications Foundation|2013}}
 |archive-url  = https://web.archive.org/web/20160304065938/http://www.broadcasting-history.ca/index3.html?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.broadcasting-history.ca%2Flistings_and_histories%2Fradio%2Fhistories.php%3Fid%3D679%26historyID%3D266
 |archive-date = 4 March 2016
 |url-status     = dead
}}
*{{cite web
 |last         = Dulmage
 |first        = Bill
 |title        = Radio History: CBI-AM (Radio One), Sydney, Canadian Broadcasting Corporation
 |url          = http://www.broadcasting-history.ca/index3.html?url=http%3A//www.broadcasting-history.ca/listings_and_histories/radio/histories.php%3Fid%3D676%26historyID%3D488
 |publisher    = Canadian Communications Foundation
 |year         = 2012a
 |accessdate   = 10 January 2013
 |location     = Toronto
 |ref          = harv
 |archive-url  = https://web.archive.org/web/20161005114303/http://www.broadcasting-history.ca/index3.html?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.broadcasting-history.ca%2Flistings_and_histories%2Fradio%2Fhistories.php%3Fid%3D676%26historyID%3D488
 |archive-date = 5 October 2016
 |url-status     = dead
 |df           = dmy-all
}}
* {{cite web
 |last         = Dulmage
 |first        = Bill
 |title        = Radio History: CBI-FM (Radio Two), Sydney, Canadian Broadcasting Corporation
 |url          = http://www.broadcasting-history.ca/index3.html?url=http%3A//www.broadcasting-history.ca/listings_and_histories/radio/histories.php%3Fid%3D677%26historyID%3D489
 |publisher    = Canadian Communications Foundation
 |year         = 2011
 |accessdate   = 10 January 2013
 |location     = Toronto
 |ref          = harv
 |archive-url  = https://web.archive.org/web/20161005114358/http://www.broadcasting-history.ca/index3.html?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.broadcasting-history.ca%2Flistings_and_histories%2Fradio%2Fhistories.php%3Fid%3D677%26historyID%3D489
 |archive-date = 5 October 2016
 |url-status     = dead
}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Prone to spam|date=August 2014}}
{{Z148}}&lt;!--     {{No more links}}

       Please be cautious adding more external links.

Wikipedia is not a collection of links and should not be used for advertising.

     Excessive or inappropriate links will be removed.

 See [[Wikipedia:External links]] and [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.

If there are already suitable links, propose additions or replacements on
the article's talk page, or submit your link to the relevant category at
DMOZ (dmoz.org) and link there using {{Dmoz}}.

--&gt;
{{Commons category|Cape Breton Island}}
* {{wikivoyage-inline|Cape Breton Island}}
* [http://cbisland.com/ Cape Breton Island Official Travel Guide]

{{Subdivisions of Nova Scotia}}
{{Canadian colonies}}
{{British overseas territories}}
{{Celtic languages}}

{{coord|46|10|N|60|45|W|region:CA_type:isle_scale:1000000|display=title}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Cape Breton Island| ]]
[[Category:British North America]]
[[Category:Canadian Gaelic]]
[[Category:Former British colonies and protectorates in the Americas]]
[[Category:Geographic regions of Nova Scotia]]
[[Category:Islands of Nova Scotia]]</text>
      <sha1>c9f1aczifewdnoasu5trmch8chrahq2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
