  <page>
    <title>Catullus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5768</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939093425</id>
      <parentid>937135824</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-04T08:50:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Shuipzv3</username>
        <id>12051049</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Intellectual influences */ Extra comma</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{for|the asteroid|11965 Catullus}}
{{hatnote|Not to be confused with Romans named &quot;Catulus&quot;, see [[Catulus]].}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=April 2013}}
[[File:Catull Sirmione.jpg|thumb|Modern bust of Catullus on the Piazza Carducci in [[Sirmione]].&lt;ref&gt;The bust was commissioned in 1935 by Sirmione's mayor, Luigi Trojani, and produced by the Milanese foundry Clodoveo Barzaghi with the assistance of the sculptor Villarubbia Norri (N. Criniti &amp; M. Arduino (eds.), ''Catullo e Sirmione. Società e cultura della Cisalpina alle soglie dell'impero'' (Brescia: Grafo, 1994), p. 4).&lt;/ref&gt;]]  
'''Gaius Valerius Catullus''' ({{IPAc-en|k|ə|ˈ|t|ʌ|l|ə|s}} {{respell|kə|TUL|əs}}, {{IPA-la|kaˈtʊllʊs|lang}}; c. 84 – c. 54 BCE) was a [[Latin poetry|Latin poet]] of the late [[Roman Republic]] who wrote chiefly in the [[neoteric]] style of poetry, which is about personal life rather than classical heroes. [[Poetry of Catullus|His surviving works]] are still read widely and continue to influence poetry and other forms of art.

Catullus's poems were widely appreciated by other poets, significantly influencing [[Ovid]] and [[Virgil]], among others. After his rediscovery in the [[Late Middle Ages]], Catullus again found admirers. The explicit sexual imagery which he uses in some of his poems has shocked many readers. At many instruction levels, Catullus is considered a resource for teachers of Latin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.ca/books?id=2buHe449NoAC&amp;pg=PT481|last=Skinner|first=Marilyn B.|publisher=Wiley-Blackwell|isbn=9781444339253|title=A Companion to Catullus|page=481|year=2010|accessdate=2019-07-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; His body of work is still frequently read from secondary school to graduate programs across the world, with his [[Catullus 64|64th]] poem often considered his greatest.

==Life==
Gaius Valerius Catullus ({{IPA-la|ˈɡaːɪ.ʊs waˈlɛrɪ.ʊs kaˈtʊllʊs|classical}}) was born to a leading [[Equestrian (Roman)|equestrian]] family of [[Verona, Italy|Verona]], in [[Cisalpine Gaul]]. The social prominence of the Catullus family allowed the father of Gaius Valerius to entertain [[Julius Caesar]] when he was the [[Promagistrate]] (proconsul) of both [[Gaul|Gallic]] [[Roman province|provinces]].&lt;ref name=bio&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bookrags.com/biography/gaius-valerius-catullus/|title=Gaius Valerius Catullus|work=www.BookRags.com|accessdate=September 13, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a poem, Catullus describes his happy homecoming to the family villa at [[Sirmio]], on [[Lake Garda]], near Verona; he also owned a villa near the resort of [[Tivoli, Italy|Tibur]] (Tivoli).&lt;ref name=bio/&gt;

Catullus appears to have spent most of his young adult years in Rome. His friends there included the poets [[Licinius Macer Calvus|Licinius Calvus]], and [[Helvius Cinna]], Quintus Hortensius (son of [[Quintus Hortensius|the orator]] and rival of [[Cicero]]) and the biographer [[Cornelius Nepos]], to whom Catullus dedicated a ''[[libellus]]'' of poems,&lt;ref name=bio/&gt; the relation of which to the extant collection remains a matter of debate.&lt;ref&gt;M. Skinner, &quot;Authorial Arrangement of the Collection&quot;, pp. 46–48, in: ''A Companion to Catullus'', Wiley-Blackwell, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; He appears to have been acquainted with the poet [[Marcus Furius Bibaculus]]. A number of prominent contemporaries appear in his poetry, including Cicero, Caesar and [[Pompey]]. According to an anecdote preserved by [[Suetonius]], Caesar did not deny that Catullus's lampoons left an indelible stain on his reputation, but when Catullus apologized, he invited the poet for dinner the very same day.&lt;ref&gt;Suetonius ''Divus Iulius'' [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus:abo:phi,1348,011:73 73]&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Catullus at Lesbia's by Sir Laurence Alma Tadema.jpg|thumb|left|''Catullus at Lesbia's'' by Sir [[Lawrence Alma-Tadema]]]]
It was probably in Rome that Catullus fell deeply in love with the &quot;[[Lesbia]]&quot; of his poems, who is usually identified with [[Claudia Pulchra (wife of Metellus)|Clodia Metelli]], a sophisticated woman from the aristocratic house of patrician family Claudii Pulchri, sister of the infamous [[Publius Clodius Pulcher]], and wife to proconsul Quintus Caecilius Metellus Celer. In his poems Catullus describes several stages of their relationship: initial euphoria, doubts, separation, and his wrenching feelings of loss. Clodia had several other partners; &quot;From the poems one can adduce no fewer than five lovers in addition to Catullus: Egnatius (poem 37), Gellius (poem 91), Quintius (poem 82), Rufus (poem 77), and Lesbius (poem 79).&quot; There is also some question surrounding her husband's mysterious death in 59 B.C., some critics believing he was domestically poisoned. Yet, a sensitive and passionate Catullus could not relinquish his flame for Clodia, regardless of her obvious indifference to his desire for a deep and permanent relationship. In his poems, Catullus wavers between devout, sweltering love and bitter, scornful insults that he directs at her blatant infidelity (as demonstrated in poems 11 and 58). His passion for her is unrelenting—yet it is unclear when exactly the couple split up for good. Catullus's poems about the relationship display striking depth and psychological insight.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Howe, Jr.|first=Quincy|title=Introduction to Catullus, The Complete Poems for American Readers|year=1970|publisher=E. P. Dutton &amp; Co., Inc.|location=New York|pages=vii to xvii}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He spent the provincial command year summer 57 to summer 56 BCE in [[Bithynia]] on the staff of the commander [[Gaius Memmius (Poet)|Gaius Memmius]]. While in the East, he traveled to the [[Troad]] to perform rites at his brother's tomb, an event recorded in a moving poem.&lt;ref name=bio/&gt;

[[File:REmpire-29 Bithynia.png|thumb|right|[[Bithynia]] within the Roman Empire]]
There survives no ancient biography of Catullus: his life has to be pieced together from scattered references to him in other ancient authors and from his poems. Thus it is uncertain when he was born and when he died. [[St. Jerome]] says that he died in his 30th year, and was born in 87 BCE. But the poems include references to events of 55 and 54 BCE. Since the Roman [[fasti consulares|consular fasti]] make it somewhat easy to confuse 87–57 BCE with 84–54 BCE, many scholars accept the dates 84 BCE–54 BCE,&lt;ref name=bio/&gt; supposing that his latest poems and the publication of his ''libellus'' coincided with the year of his death. Other authors suggest 52 or 51 BCE as the year of the poet's death.&lt;ref&gt;M. Skinner, &quot;Introduction&quot;, p.3, in: ''A Companion to Catullus'', Wiley-Blackwell, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Though upon his elder brother's death Catullus lamented that their &quot;whole house was buried along&quot; with the deceased, the existence (and prominence) of ''Valerii Catulli'' is attested in the following centuries. [[T.P. Wiseman]] argues that after the brother's death Catullus could have married, and that, in this case, the later ''Valerii Catulli'' may have been his descendants.&lt;ref&gt;T.P. Wiseman, &quot;The Valerii Catulli of Verona&quot;, in: M. Skinner, ed., ''A Companion to Catullus'', Wiley-Blackwell, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Poetry==
{{Main|Poetry of Catullus}}
{{See also|List of poems by Catullus}}
[[File:Catullus et in eum commentarius.tif|thumb|''Catullus et in eum commentarius'' (1554)]]

===Sources and organization===
Catullus's poems have been preserved in an [[anthology]] of 116 ''carmina'' (the actual number of poems may slightly vary in various editions), which can be divided into three parts according to their form: sixty short poems in varying meters, called ''[[polymetra]]'', eight longer poems, and forty-eight [[epigram]]s.

There is no scholarly consensus on whether Catullus himself arranged the order of the poems. The longer poems differ from the ''polymetra'' and the epigrams not only in length but also in their subjects: There are seven [[hymn]]s and one mini-[[epic poetry|epic]], or epyllion, the most highly prized form for the &quot;[[Neoteric#Latin Neoterics|new poets]]&quot;.

The ''polymetra'' and the epigrams can be divided into four major [[Theme (literature)|thematic]] groups (ignoring a rather large number of poems that elude such categorization):

* poems to and about his friends (e.g., an invitation like poem 13).
* [[erotic]] poems: some of them ([[Catullus 50|50]] and [[Catullus 99|99]]) are about his homosexual desires and acts, but most are about women, especially about one he calls &quot;[[Lesbia]]&quot; (which served as a false name for his married girlfriend, [[Claudia Pulchra (wife of Metellus)|Clodia]], source and inspiration of many of his poems).
* [[invective]]s: often rude and sometimes downright [[obscene]] poems targeted at friends-turned-traitors (e.g., poem [[Catullus 16|16]]), other lovers of Lesbia, well-known poets, politicians (e.g., [[Julius Caesar]]) and [[rhetor]]s, including Cicero.
* [[condolence]]s: some poems of Catullus are solemn in nature. [[Catullus 96|96]] comforts a friend in the death of a loved one; several others, most famously [[Catullus 101|101]], lament the death of his brother.

All these poems describe the lifestyle of Catullus and his friends, who, despite Catullus's temporary political post in Bithynia, lived their lives withdrawn from politics. They were interested mainly in poetry and love. Above all other qualities, Catullus seems to have valued ''venustas'', or charm, in his acquaintances, a theme which he explores in a number of his poems. The ancient Roman concept of ''virtus'' (i.e. of [[virtue]] that had to be proved by a political or military career), which [[Cicero]] suggested as the solution to the societal problems of the late [[Roman Republic|Republic]], meant little to them.

However Catullus does not reject traditional notions, but rather their particular application to the ''[[vita activa]]'' of politics and war. Indeed, he tries to reinvent these notions from a personal point of view and to introduce them into human relationships. For example, he applies the word ''fides'', which traditionally meant faithfulness towards one's political allies, to his relationship with Lesbia and reinterprets it as unconditional faithfulness in love. So, despite the seeming frivolity of his lifestyle, Catullus measured himself and his friends by quite ambitious standards.

===Intellectual influences===
[[File:John_Reinhard_Weguelin_Lesbia.jpg|thumb|250px| ''Lesbia'', 1878 painting by [[John Reinhard Weguelin]] inspired by the poems of Catullus]]
Catullus's poetry was influenced by the innovative poetry of the [[Hellenistic Age]], and especially by [[Callimachus]] and the Alexandrian school, which had propagated a new style of poetry that deliberately turned away from the classical [[epic poetry]] in the tradition of [[Homer]]. Cicero called these local innovators  ''[[neoteroi]]'' (νεώτεροι) or 'moderns' (in Latin ''[[Neoteric#Latin Neoterics|poetae novi]]'' or '[[Neoteric#Latin Neoterics|new poets]]'), in that they cast off the heroic model handed down from [[Ennius]] in order to strike new ground and ring a contemporary note. Catullus and Callimachus did not describe the feats of ancient [[hero]]es and gods (except perhaps in re-evaluating and predominantly artistic circumstances, e.g. poems 63 and 64), focusing instead on small-scale personal themes. Although these poems sometimes seem quite superficial and their subjects often are mere everyday concerns, they are accomplished works of art. Catullus described his work as ''expolitum'', or polished, to show that the language he used was very carefully and artistically composed.

Catullus was also an admirer of [[Sappho]], a female poet of the seventh century BCE. [[Catullus 51]] partly translates, partly imitates and transforms [[Sappho 31]].  Some hypothesize that [[Catullus 61|61]] and [[Catullus 62|62]] were perhaps inspired by [[lost work]]s of Sappho but this is purely speculative. Both of the latter are ''[[Epithalamium|epithalamia]]'', a form of [[wikt:laudatory|laudatory]] or erotic wedding-poetry that Sappho was famous for. Catullus twice used a meter that Sappho developed, called the Sapphic [[strophe]], in poems [[Catullus 11|11]] and 51, perhaps prompting his successor Horace's interest in the form.

Catullus, as was common to his era, was greatly influenced by stories from Greek and Roman myth. His longer poems—such as [[Catullus 63|63]], [[Catullus 64|64]], [[Catullus 65|65]], [[Catullus 66|66]], and [[Catullus 68|68]]—allude to mythology in various ways. Some stories he refers to are the wedding of [[Peleus]] and [[Thetis]], the departure of the [[Argonauts]], [[Theseus]] and the Minotaur, [[Ariadne]]'s abandonment, [[Tereus]] and [[Procne]], as well as [[Protesilaus|Protesilaus and Laodamia]].

===Style===
Catullus wrote in many different meters including hendecasyllabic verse and elegiac couplets (common in love poetry). A great part of his poetry shows strong and occasionally wild emotions, especially in regard to [[Lesbia]]. His love poems are very emotional and ardent, and we can relate to them even today. Catullus describes his Lesbia as having multiple suitors and often showing little affection towards him. He also demonstrates a great sense of humour such as in [[Catullus 13]].

===Musical settings===
''Catullus Dreams'' (2011) is a song cycle by David Glaser set to texts of Catullus. The cycle is scored for soprano and seven instruments. It was premiered at Symphony Space in New York by soprano Linda Larson and Sequitur Ensemble.

''[[Catulli Carmina]]'' is a [[cantata]] by [[Carl Orff]] to the texts of Catullus.

&quot;Carmina Catulli&quot; is a song cycle arranged from 17 of Catullus' poems by American composer Michael Linton. The cycle was recorded in December 2013 and premiered at Carnegie Hall's Weill Recital Hall in March 2014 by French baritone Edwin Crossley-Mercer and pianist Jason Paul Peterson.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://refinersfire.us/linton-carmina-catulli/ | publisher=RefinersFire | title=New Release: Linton: Carmina Catulli | accessdate=October 8, 2014 | date=August 19, 2014 | last=McMurtry | first=Chris | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141008192346/http://refinersfire.us/linton-carmina-catulli/ | archivedate=October 8, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.operanews.com/Opera_News_Magazine/2015/2/Recordings/LINTON__Carmina_Catulli.html|title=LINTON: Carmina Catulli|website=www.operanews.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.forumopera.com/cd/carmina-catulli-priape-lesbie-diane-et-caetera|title=Priape, Lesbie, Diane et caetera - Forum Opéra|website=www.forumopera.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Catullus 5]], the love poem &quot;Vivamus mea Lesbia atque amemus&quot;, in the translation by [[Ben Jonson]] was set to music&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://gerbode.net/ft2/composers//Ferrabosco/songs/06_come_my_celia/pdf/06_come_my_celia.pdf |title=Archived copy |access-date=August 20, 2011 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111005184436/http://gerbode.net/ft2/composers//Ferrabosco/songs/06_come_my_celia/pdf/06_come_my_celia.pdf |archive-date=October 5, 2011 |url-status=dead |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; ([[lute]] accompanied song) by [[Alfonso Ferrabosco the younger]]. [[Thomas Campion]] also wrote a lute-song using his own translation of the first six lines of Catullus 5 followed by two verses of his own. The translation by [[Richard Crashaw]] was set to music&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cpdl.org/wiki/images/3/37/Web-com.pdf|format=PDF|title=Come and let us live : Samuel Webbe Jr. (c. 1770–1843) : Music score|website=Cpdl.org|accessdate=16 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; in a four-part [[Glee (music)|glee]] by [[Samuel Webbe Jr.]] It was also set to music&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cpdl.org/wiki/images/5/52/Smi-let.pdf|format=PDF|title=Let us, my Lesbia, live and love : John Stafford Smith (1750-1836) : Music score|website=Cpdl.org|accessdate=16 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; in a three-part [[Glee (music)|glee]] by [[John Stafford Smith]].
The  Hungarian born British composer [[Matyas Seiber]] set poem 31 for unaccompanied mixed chorus Sirmio in 1957.
Finnish jazz singer Reine Rimón has recorded poems of Catullus set to standard jazz tunes.

The American composer, [[Ned Rorem]], set Catullus 101 to music for voice and piano. The song, &quot;Catallus: on the Burial of His Brother&quot; was originally published in 1969.

The Icelandic composer, [[Jóhann Jóhannsson]], set [[Catullus 85]] to music. The poem is sung through a [[vocoder]]. The music is played by a [[string quartet]] and [[piano]]. Titled &quot;Odi Et Amo&quot;, the song is found on Jóhannsson's album ''[[Englabörn]]''.

==Cultural depictions==
* The 1888 play ''[[Lesbia (play)|Lesbia]]'' by Richard Davey depicts the relationship between Catullus and Lesbia, based on incidents from his poems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Our Play-Box: ''Lesbia'' |work=The Theatre |date=1 November 1888 |pages=256–257 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=1XwTTdl8FjYC&amp;pg=RA8-PA256&amp;lpg=RA8-PA256}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Amusements: ''Lesbia'' |work=The New York Times |date=9 October 1890 |page=4 |url=https://www.newspapers.com/clip/26383477/the_new_york_times/ |via=[[Newspapers.com]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Catullus was the main protagonist of the historical novel Farewell, Catullus (1953) by [[Pierson Dixon]]. The novel shows the corruption of [[Roman Empire|Roman]] society.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.biblio.com/book/farewell-catullus-dixon-pierson/d/700773444|title=Farewell, Catullus|first=Pierson|last=Dixon|publisher=|via=Biblio.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation| author1=Reine Rimón and her Hot Papas jazz band| author2=Gregg Stafford| author3=Tuomo Pekkanen| author4=Gaius Valerius Catullus| title=Variationes iazzicae Catullianae| language=Latin| url=http://www.reinerimonjazz.com/recordings.shtml| accessdate=2013-10-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[W. G. Hardy]]'s novel ''The City of Libertines'' (1957), tells the fictionalized story of Catullus and a love affair during the time of Julius Caesar. The ''[[Financial Post]]'' described the book as &quot;an authentic story of an absorbing era&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The City of Libertines by W. G. Hardy|date=December 7, 1957|newspaper=Winnipeg Free Press|location=Winnipeg, Manitoba|page=38|url=https://newspaperarchive.com/sports-clipping-dec-07-1957-1461222/}}{{free access}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* A poem by Catullus is being recited to [[Cleopatra]] in the eponymous [[Cleopatra (1963 film)|1963 film]] when [[Julius Caesar]] comes to visit her; they talk about him (Cleopatra: 'Catullus doesn't approve of you. Why haven't you had him killed?' Caesar: 'Because I approve of him.') and Caesar then recites other poems by him.
*The American poet [[Louis Zukofsky|Louis Zokofsky]] in 1969 wrote an extraordinary set of [[Homophonic translation|homophonic translations]] of Catullus that attempted in English to replicate the sound as primary emphasis, rather than the more common emphasis on sense of the originals (although the relationship between sound and sense there is often misrepresented and has been clarified by [http://www.z-site.net/notes-to-poetry/catullus-1969-with-celia-zukofsky/ careful study]); his Catullus versions have had extensive influence on contemporary innovative poetry and homophonic translation, including poets like [[Robert Duncan (poet)|Robert Duncan]], [[Robert Kelly (poet)|Robert Kelly]], and [[Charles Bernstein]].
*Catullus is the protagonist of [[Tom Holland (author)|Tom Holland]]'s 1995 novel ''Attis.''

==See also==
*[[Codex Vaticanus Ottobonianus Latinus 1829]]
*[[Poetry of Catullus]]
*[[Prosody (Latin)]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book|last1=Balme|first1=M.|last2=Morwood|first2=J|title=Oxford Latin Reader|year=1997|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford}}
*{{cite book|last1=Balmer|first1=J.|title=Catullus: Poems of Love and Hate|year=2004|publisher=Bloodaxe|location=Hexham}}
*{{cite journal|last=Barrett|first=A. A.|title=Catullus 52 and the Consulship of Vatinius|journal=Transactions and Proceedings of the American Philological Association|year=1972|volume=103|pages=23–38}}
*{{cite journal|last=Barwick|first=K.|title=Zyklen bei Martial und in den kleinen Gedichten des Catull|journal=Philologus|year=1958|volume=102|pages=284–318}}
* Claes, P. (2002). ''Concatenatio Catulliana, A New Reading of the Carmina.'' Amsterdam: J.C. Gieben 
*{{cite journal|last= Clarke |first= Jacqueline |title= Bridal Songs: Catullan Epithalamia and Prudentius Peristephanon 3|journal=Antichthon|year=2006|volume=40|pages=89–103}}
*{{cite journal|last=Coleman|first=K.M.|title=The persona of Catullus' Phaselus|journal=Greece &amp; Rome|year=1981|volume=28|series=N.S.|pages=68–72|doi=10.1017/s0017383500033507}}
*{{cite book|last=Dettmer|first=Helena|title=Love by the Numbers: Form and the Meaning in the poetry of Catullus|year=1997|publisher=Peter Lang Publishing}}
* {{cite journal|last=Deuling|first=Judy|title=Catullus 17 and 67, and the Catullan Construct|journal=Antichthon|year=2006|volume=40|pages=1–9}}
*{{cite journal|last=Dorey|first=T.A.|title=The Aurelii and the Furii|journal=Proceedings of the African Classical Associations|year=1959|volume=2|pages=9–10}}
*{{cite journal|last=Duhigg|first=J|title=The Elegiac Metre of Catullus|journal=Antichthon|year=1971|volume=5|pages=57–67}}
*{{cite book|last=Ellis|first=R.|title=A Commentary on Catullus|url=https://archive.org/details/commentaryoncatu00elliiala|publisher=Clarendon Press|location=Oxford|year=1889}}
*{{cite journal|last=Ferguson|first=J.|title=Catullus and Martial|journal=Proceedings of the African Classical Associations|year=1963|volume=6|pages=3–15}}
*{{cite book|last=Ferguson|first=J.|title=Catullus |series=Greece &amp; Rome:New Surveys in the Classics|volume=20|year=1988|publisher=Clarendon Press|location=Oxford}}
* {{cite book|last=Ferrero|first=L.|title=Interpretazione di Catullo|year=1955|publisher=Torino, Rosenberg &amp; Sellier|location=Torino|language=Italian}}
* {{cite book|last=Fitzgerald|first=W.|title=Catullan Provocations; Lyric Poetry and the Drama of Position|year=1995|publisher=University of California Press|location=Berkeley}}
* {{cite journal|last=Fletcher|first=G.B.A.|title=Catulliana|journal=Latomus|year=1967|volume=26|pages=104–106}}
*{{cite journal|last=Fletcher|first=G.B.A.|title= Further Catulliana |journal=Latomus|year=1991|volume=50|pages=92–93}}
* {{cite book|last=Fordyce|first=C.J.|title=Catullus, A Commentary|year=1961|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford}}
* {{cite book|last=Gaisser|first=Julia Haig|title=Catullus And His Renaissance Readers|year=1993|publisher=Clarendon Press|location=Oxford}}
*{{cite journal|last= Greene |first= Ellen |title= Catullus, Caesar and the Roman Masculine Identity |journal=Antichthon|year=2006|volume=40|pages=49–64}}
* {{cite journal|last= Hallett |first= Judith |title= Catullus and Horace on Roman Women Poets |journal=Antichthon|year=2006|volume=40|pages=65–88}}
*{{cite book|last=Harrington|first=Karl Pomeroy|title=Catullus and His Influence|year=1963|publisher=Cooper Square Publishers|location=New York}}
* {{cite book|last=Havelock|first=E.A.|title=The Lyric Genius of Catullus|year=1939|publisher=B. Blackwell|location=Oxford}}
* Hild, Christian (2013). ''Liebesgedichte als Wagnis. Emotionen und generationelle Prozesse in Catulls Lesbiagedichten''. St.Ingbert:      Röhrig. {{ISBN|978-3-86110-517-6}}.
* {{cite journal|last= Jackson |first= Anna |title= Catullus in the Playground |journal=Antichthon|year=2006|volume=40|pages=104–116}}
*Kaggelaris, N. (2015), &quot;Wedding Cry: Sappho (Fr. 109 LP, Fr. 104(a) LP)- Catullus (c. 62. 20-5)- modern greek folk songs&quot; [in Greek] in Avdikos, E.- Koziou-Kolofotia, B. (ed.)'' Modern Greek folk songs and history'', Karditsa, pp.&amp;nbsp;260–70 [https://www.academia.edu/24597922/%CE%93%CE%B1%CE%BC%CE%AE%CE%BB%CE%B9%CE%BF%CE%B9_%CE%98%CF%81%CE%AE%CE%BD%CE%BF%CE%B9_%CE%A3%CE%B1%CF%80%CF%86%CF%8E_Fr._109_LP_Fr._104_a_LP_-_%CE%9A%CE%AC%CF%84%CE%BF%CF%85%CE%BB%CE%BB%CE%BF%CF%82_c._62._20-5_-_%CE%BD%CE%B5%CE%BF%CE%B5%CE%BB%CE%BB%CE%B7%CE%BD%CE%B9%CE%BA%CF%8C_%CE%B4%CE%B7%CE%BC%CE%BF%CF%84%CE%B9%CE%BA%CF%8C_%CF%84%CF%81%CE%B1%CE%B3%CE%BF%CF%8D%CE%B4%CE%B9_Wedding_Cry_Sappho_Fr._109_LP_Fr._104_a_LP_-_Catullus_c._62._20-5_-_modern_greek_folk_songs_]
*{{cite journal|last= Kidd |first= D.A. |title= Some Problems in Catullus lxvi |journal=Antichthon|year=1970|volume=4|pages=38–49}}
* {{cite journal|last=Kokoszkiewicz|first=Konrad W.|title=Et futura panda sive de Catulli carmine sexto corrigendo|journal=Hermes|year=2004|volume=32|pages=125–128}}
* {{cite book|last=Kroll|first=Wilhelm|title=C. Valerius Catullus|year=1929|publisher=B.G. Teubner|location=Leipzig|language=German}}
* {{cite journal|last=Maas|first=Paul|title=The Chronology of the Poems of Catullus|journal=Classical Quarterly|year=1942|volume=36|pages=79–82|doi=10.1017/s0009838800024605}}
*{{cite book|last=Martin|first=Charles|title=Catullus|year=1992|publisher=Yale Univ. Press|location=New Haven|isbn=0-300-05199-9}}
* {{cite book|last=Munro|first=H.A.J.|title=Criticisms and Elucidations of Catullus|url=https://archive.org/details/criticismsandel00munrgoog|year=1878|publisher=Deighton, Bell and co.|location=Cambridge}}
*{{cite book|last=Newman|first=John Kevin|title=Roman Catullus and the Modification of the Alexandrian Sensibility|year=1990|publisher=Weidmann|location=Hildesheim}}
* {{cite book|last=Quinn|first=Kenneth|title=The Catullan Revolution|year=1959|publisher=Melbourne University Press|location=Melbourne}}
*{{cite book|last=Quinn|first=Kenneth|title=Catullus: The Poems|year=1973|publisher=Macmillan|location=London|edition=2nd}}
* {{cite journal|last=Rothstein|first=Max|title=Catull und Lesbia|journal=Philologus|year=1923|volume=78|pages=1–34}}
*{{cite book|last=Small|first=Stuart G.P.|title=Catullus|url=https://archive.org/details/catullusreadersg0000smal|url-access=registration|year=1983|publisher=University Press of America|location=Lanham, Md.|isbn=0-8191-2905-4}}
* {{cite book|last=Swann|first=Bruce W.|title=Martial's Catullus. The Reception of an Epigrammatic Rival|year=1994|publisher=Georg Olms|location=Hildesheim}}
*{{cite book|last=Thomson|first=Douglas Ferguson Scott|title=Catullus: Edited with a Textual and Interpretative Commentary|year=1997|publisher=University of Toronto Press|location=Toronto|series=Phoenix|volume=34: suppl.|isbn=0-8020-0676-0}}
* {{cite journal|last=Townend|first=G.B.|title=A Further Point in Catullus' attack on Volusius|journal=Greece &amp; Rome|year=1980|volume=27|series= n.s.|pages=134–136|doi=10.1017/s0017383500025791}}
* {{cite journal|last=Townend|first=G.B.|title= The Unstated Climax of Catullus 64|journal=Greece &amp; Rome|year=1983|volume=30|series= n.s.|pages=21–30|doi=10.1017/s0017383500026437}}
* {{cite journal|last= Tesoriero |first= Charles |title= Hidden Kisses in Catullus: Poems 5, 6, 7 and 8|journal=Antichthon|year=2006|volume=40|pages=10–18}}
* {{cite journal|last=Tuplin|first=C.J.|title=Catullus 68|journal=Classical Quarterly|year=1981|volume=31|series=n.s.|pages=113–139|doi=10.1017/s000983880002111x}}
* {{cite journal|last= Uden |first= James |title= Embracing the Young Man in Love: Catullus 75 and the Comic Adulescens |journal=Antichthon|year=2006|volume=40|pages=19–34}}
* {{cite journal|last= Watson |first= Lindsay C. |title= Bassa's Borborysms: on Martial and Catullus |journal=Antichthon|year=2003|volume=37|pages=1–12}}
* {{cite journal|last= Watson |first= Lindsay C. |title= Catullus and the Poetics of Incest |journal=Antichthon|year=2006|volume=40|pages=35–48}}
* {{cite book|last=Wheeler|first=A. L.|title=Catullus and the Traditions of Ancient Poetry|year=1934|publisher=University of California Press|location=Berkeley|series=Sather Classical Lectures|volume=9}}
* {{cite book|last=Wilamowitz-Möllendorf|first=Ulrich von|title=Sappho und Simonides|year=1913|publisher=Weidmann|location=Berlin|language=German}}
* {{cite book|last=Wiseman|first=T. P.|title=Catullan Questions|year=1969|publisher=Leicester University Press|location=Leicester}}
*{{cite book|last=Wiseman|first=T. P.|title=Catullus and His World: A Reappraisal|year=2002|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Cambridge|isbn=0-521-31968-4|edition=1st pbk.}}
*{{cite book|last=Wiseman|first=T. P.|title=Cinna the poet and other Roman essays|year=1974|publisher=Leicester University Press|location=Leicester|isbn=0-7185-1120-4}}

==External links==
{{wikisource author}}
{{wikibooks|The Poetry of Gaius Valerius Catullus}}
{{Wikiquote}}
{{commons category}}
{{Library resources box |by=yes |onlinebooks=yes |others=yes |about=yes |label=Catullus
  |viaf= |lccn= |lcheading= |wikititle= }}
* [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/searchresults?q=Catullus&amp;redirect=true Works by Catullus at Perseus Digital Library]
* {{Gutenberg author | id=8308}}
* {{Internet Archive author}}
* {{Librivox author |id=1907}}
* [http://www.negenborn.net/catullus/ Catullus translations]: Catullus's work in Latin and multiple (ten or more) modern languages, including scanned versions of every poem
* [http://www.vroma.org/~hwalker/VRomaCatullus/ Catullus] in Latin and English
* [http://www.poetryintranslation.com/PITBR/Latin/Catullus.htm Catullus translated exclusively in English] Translated by A. S. Kline
* [http://www.catullusonline.org/ Catullus Online]: searchable Latin text, repertory of conjectures, and images of the most important manuscripts
* [http://www.intratext.com/Catalogo/Autori/AUT61.HTM Catullus]: Latin text, concordances and frequency list
* [http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/classicsfacpub/2/ Catullus purified: a brief history of Carmen 16] by [[Thomas Nelson Winter]]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120227140432/http://www.rhapsodes.fll.vt.edu/catullus1.htm SORGLL:  Catullus 5, read by Robert Sonkowsky]
* [http://classicalpoets.org/a-translation-of-catulluss-ad-sirmium-insulam-by-douglas-thornton/ A Translation of Catullus’s ‘Ad Sirmium Insulam’] Translated by Douglas Thornton

{{Catullus}}
{{Ancient Rome topics|state=collapsed}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:1st-century BC Romans]]
[[Category:1st-century BC Roman poets]]
[[Category:Bisexual writers]]
[[Category:Catullus| ]]
[[Category:Elegiac poets]]
[[Category:Golden Age Latin writers]]
[[Category:Iambic poets]]
[[Category:80s BC births]]
[[Category:54 BC deaths]]
[[Category:People from Verona]]
[[Category:Erotic poetry]]
[[Category:LGBT poets]]
[[Category:LGBT people from Italy]]
[[Category:LGBT history in Italy]]
[[Category:Ancient LGBT history]]
[[Category:Valerii]]
[[Category:Ancient LGBT people]]</text>
      <sha1>sujbjf3psr8lcm2t3333yng0y16da3d</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
