  <page>
    <title>Cross-dressing</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5700</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943338775</id>
      <parentid>943338582</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T09:19:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>VectorIvan</username>
        <id>38669068</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* History */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Practice of dressing and acting in a style or manner traditionally associated with the opposite sex}}
[[File:This-Is-The-Army gals (Broadway).jpg|thumb|right|[[Irving Berlin|Irving Berlin's]] &quot;This Is the Army, Mr. Jones&quot;, performed by cross-dressers (1942)]]

{{Crossdressing}}
'''Cross-dressing''' is the act of wearing items of clothing and other [[accoutrements]] commonly associated with the opposite sex within a particular society.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;cross-dress.&quot; ''The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language, Fourth Edition.'' Houghton Mifflin Company, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; Cross-dressing has been used for purposes of disguise, comfort, and self-expression in modern times and throughout history.

Almost every human society throughout history has had [[gender role|expected norms for each gender]] relating to style, color, or type of clothing they are expected to wear, and likewise most societies have had a set of [[Social aspects of clothing|guidelines, views or even laws]] defining what type of clothing is appropriate for each gender.

The term ''cross-dressing'' refers to an action or a behavior, without attributing or implying any specific causes or motives for that behavior. Cross-dressing is not synonymous with being [[transgender]].

==Terminology==
The phenomenon of cross-dressing is an old recorded practice, being referred to as far back as [[Hebrew Bible]].&lt;ref name=&quot;aggrawal_2009_16_3&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Aggrawal, Anil. |title=References to the paraphilias and sexual crimes in the Bible |journal=J Forensic Leg Med |volume=16 |issue=3 |pages=109–14 |date=April 2009 |pmid=19239958 |doi=10.1016/j.jflm.2008.07.006 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the terms to describe it change. The Anglo-Saxon &quot;cross-dresser&quot; has largely superseded the Latinate &quot;[[transvestite]]&quot;, which has come to be seen as outdated and derogatory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Vaccaro&quot;&gt;{{cite book|authors=Annemarie Vaccaro, Gerri August, Megan S. Kennedy|title=Safe Spaces: Making Schools and Communities Welcoming to LGBT Youth|publisher=[[ABC-CLIO]]|isbn=978-0313393686|year=2011|page=142|accessdate=October 21, 2016|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZkxjSnI2e0UC&amp;pg=PA142|quote=Cross-dresser/cross-dressing. (1) The most neutral word to describe a person who dresses, at least partially or part of the time, and for any number of reasons, in clothing associated with another gender within a particular society. Carries no implications of 'usual' gender appearance, or sexual orientation. Has replaced transvestite, which is outdated, problematic, and generally offensive since it was historically used to diagnose medical/mental health disorders.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Capuzza&quot;&gt;{{cite book|authors=Jamie C. Capuzza, Leland G. Spencer|title=Transgender Communication Studies: Histories, Trends, and Trajectories|publisher=[[Lexington Books]]|isbn=978-1498500067|year=2015|page=174|accessdate=October 21, 2016|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=A1emBgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA174|quote=Eventually, the transvestite label fell out of favor because it was deemed to be derogatory; cross-dresser has emerged as a more suitable replacement ([[GLAAD]], 2014b).}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Zastrow&quot;&gt;{{cite book|authors=Charles Zastrow|title=Empowerment Series: Introduction to Social Work and Social Welfare: Empowering People|publisher=[[Cengage Learning]]|isbn=978-1305388338|year=2016|page=239|accessdate=October 21, 2016|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DB5TCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA239|quote=It should be noted the term transvestite is often considered an offensive term.}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is because the latter was historically used to diagnose psychiatric disorders (e.g. [[transvestic fetishism]]), but the former was coined by the [[transgender]] community.&lt;ref name=&quot;Vaccaro&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gerstner&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=David A. Gerstner|title=Routledge International Encyclopedia of Queer Culture|publisher=[[Routledge]]|isbn=978-0313393686|year=2006|page=568|accessdate=October 21, 2016|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=XS_SnVPixE8C&amp;pg=PA568|quote=A variety of derogatory terms are still used to describe any aspect of the transgender condition. [...] The term transvestite being older [than cross-dresser] and associated with the medical community's negative view of the practice, has come to be seen as a derogatory term. [...] The term cross-dresser, in contrast, having come from the transgender community itself, is a term seen as not possessing these negative connotations.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Oxford English Dictionary]] gives 1911 as the earliest citation, by [[Edward Carpenter]]: &quot;Cross-dressing must be taken as a general indication of, and a cognate phenomenon to, homosexuality&quot;. In 1928 [[Havelock Ellis]] used the two terms, &quot;cross-dressing&quot; and &quot;transvestism&quot;, interchangeably. The earliest citations for &quot;cross-dress&quot; and &quot;cross-dresser&quot; are 1966 and 1976 respectively.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.oed.com/;jsessionid=54290019DADF286E3311933DC816B7ED?authRejection=true&amp;url=%2Fview%2FEntry%2F44812%3FredirectedFrom%3Dcross-dress|title=Home : Oxford English Dictionary|website=www.oed.com|language=en|access-date=2019-02-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{Main|History of cross-dressing}}
[[File:Potters at work. The one on the right is a man in woman's garb (Itneg people, 1922).jpg|thumb|[[Itneg people|Itneg]] potters, the person on the right is a ''bayok'' in female attire in the [[Philippines]] (c. 1922)]]
[[File:Crossdressing circa 1890 Frances Benjamin Johnston (right).jpg|thumb|[[Frances Benjamin Johnston]] (right) poses with two cross-dressing friends; the &quot;lady&quot; is identified by Johnston as the illustrator Mills Thompson.]]

Cross-dressing has been practiced throughout much of recorded history, in many societies, and for many reasons. Examples exist in [[Greek mythology|Greek]], [[Norse mythology|Norse]], and [[Hindu mythology]]. There is a rich history of cross-dressing found in folklore, literature, theater, and music, such as [[Kabuki]], [[Korean shamanism#Chaesu-gut (채수굿)|Korean shamanism]], and [[Babaylan|native religions in the Philippines]] and Indonesia,. In the British and European context, theatrical troupes (&quot;[[playing company|playing companies]]&quot;) were all-male, with the female parts undertaken by [[boy player]]s.

A wide variety of historical figures are known to have cross-dressed to varying degrees. Many women found they had to disguise themselves as men in order to participate in the wider world. For example, [[Margaret King]] cross-dressed in the early nineteenth century to attend medical school, as none would accept female students. A century later, [[Vita Sackville-West]] dressed as a young soldier in order to &quot;walk out&quot; with her girlfriend [[Violet Keppel]], to avoid the street harassment that two women would have faced. The prohibition on women wearing male garb, once strictly applied, still has echoes today in some Western societies which require girls and women to wear skirts, for example as part of [[school uniform]] or office [[dress code]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Doig |first1=Liz |title=BBC News {{!}} UK {{!}} Who's wearing the trousers? |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/505095.stm |accessdate=12 December 2018 |work=news.bbc.co.uk |agency=BBC |date=November 4, 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt; In some countries, even in casual settings, women are still prohibited from wearing traditionally male clothing. Sometimes all trousers, no matter how loose and long, are automatically considered &quot;indecent&quot;, which may render their wearer subject to severe punishment, as in the case of [[Lubna al-Hussein]] in Sudan in 2009.

==Varieties==
[[File:Lady Bunny and Sherry Vine by David Shankbone.JPG|thumb|left|[[Drag queen]]s are a form of cross-dressing as [[performance art]].]]
There are many different kinds of cross-dressing and many different reasons why an individual might engage in cross-dressing behavior.&lt;ref name = &quot;eucwqo&quot;&gt;''Rainbow Reader'', Fort Wayne, Indiana&lt;/ref&gt; Some people cross-dress as a matter of comfort or style, out of personal preference for clothing associated with the opposite sex. In this case, a person's cross-dressing may or may not be apparent to other people. Some people cross-dress to shock others or challenge [[Norm (sociology)|social norms]]. Some people attempt to pass as a member of the opposite sex in order to gain access to places or resources they would not otherwise be able to reach.

===Gender disguise===
Gender disguise has been used by women and girls to [[Passing (gender)|pass]] as male, and by men and boys to pass as female. Gender disguise has also been used as a [[plot device]] in storytelling, particularly in narrative [[ballads]],&lt;ref name=&quot;child106&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Child|first=Francis James|title=The English and Scottish Popular Ballads|publisher=Dover Publications Inc|volume=II|pages=428–432|isbn=978-0-486-43146-8|year=2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is a recurring motif in literature, theater, and film.  Historically, some women have cross-dressed to take up male-dominated or male-exclusive professions, such as military service. Conversely, some men have cross-dressed to escape from mandatory military service&lt;ref&gt;See the television series ''M.A.S.H.'' for an example of a cross-dresser who didn't want to serve in the military (Max Klinger). Although the character was played for laughs, his situation was based on military regulations prohibiting cross-dressing.&lt;/ref&gt; or as a disguise to assist in political or social protest, as men in Wales did in the [[Rebecca Riots]] and when conducting [[Ceffyl Pren]] as a form of mob justice.

[[Undercover journalism]] may require cross-dressing, as with [[Norah Vincent]]'s project [[Self-Made Man (book)|''Self-Made Man'']].

Some girls in Afghanistan, long after the fall of the [[Taliban]], are still disguised by their families as boys. This is known as ''[[bacha posh]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Sethi |first1=Anita |title=The Underground Girls of Kabul: The Hidden Lives of Afghan Girls Disguised As Boys by Jenny Nordberg – review |url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2014/nov/02/underground-girls-of-kabul-review-afghan-disguised-boys-nordberg-bacha-posh |accessdate=24 December 2018 |work=The Guardian |date=2 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Theatre and performance===
Single-sex theatrical troupes often have some performers who cross-dress to play roles written for members of the opposite sex ([[Travesti (theatre)|travesti]] and [[trouser role]]s). Cross-dressing, particularly the depiction of males wearing dresses, is often used for comic effect onstage and on-screen.

[[Drag (clothing)|Drag]] is a special form of [[performance art]] based on the act of cross-dressing. A [[drag queen]] is usually a [[Sex assignment|male-assigned]] person who performs as an exaggeratedly feminine character, in heightened costuming sometimes consisting of a showy dress, high-heeled shoes, obvious make-up, and [[Wig (hair)|wig]]. A drag queen may imitate famous female film or pop-music stars. A [[faux queen]] is a female-assigned person employing the same techniques. A [[drag king]] is a counterpart of the drag queen - a female-assigned person who adopts a masculine persona in performance or imitates a male film or pop-music star. Some female-assigned people undergoing [[gender reassignment therapy]] also self-identify as ''drag kings'' although this use of &quot;drag king&quot; would generally be considered inaccurate.

The modern activity of [[battle reenactment]]s has raised the question of women passing as male soldiers. In 1989, Lauren Burgess dressed as a male soldier in a [[U.S. National Park Service]] reenactment of the [[Battle of Antietam]], and was ejected after she was discovered to be a woman. Burgess sued the Park Service for [[sexual discrimination]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author= |last1=Robinson |first1=Lynda |last2= |first2= |agency= |date=September 30, 1991 |title=Battle re-enactor finds herself at war with U.S. Park Service |url=http://articles.baltimoresun.com/1991-09-30/news/1991273008_1_re-enactors-civil-war-burgess/2 |work=[[Baltimore Sun]] |issn=1930-8965 |oclc=244481759 |publisher=Trif Alatzas |archive-url= |archive-date= |access-date=13 August 2018 |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt; The case spurred spirited debate among Civil War buffs. In 1993, a federal judge ruled in Burgess's favor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Meyer |first1=Eugene L |agency=[[Washington Post]] |date=March 18, 1993 |title=Woman Wins Fight Over Civil War 'Battle' Garb |url=http://articles.latimes.com/1993-03-18/news/mn-12369_1_civil-war-generals |url-status=live |work=[[Los Angeles Times]] |issn= |publisher= |location= |archive-url= |archive-date= |access-date=14 August 2018 |quote=U.S. District Judge Royce C. Lamberth ruled that... the Antietam park policy of 'categorically barring women from portraying male soldiers... constitutes unconstitutional discrimination against women.{{'&quot;}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;Wigging&quot; refers to the practice of male [[stunt double]]s taking the place of an actress, parallel to &quot;[[blackface|paint downs]]&quot;, where white stunt doubles are made up to resemble black actors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Robb |first1=David |last2=Robb |first2=David |title=Stuntwomen Panel: Evangeline Lilly Says She Was Intentionally Injured While Filming 'Lost' |url=https://deadline.com/2018/05/stuntwomen-panel-evangeline-lilly-deven-macnair-1202393558/ |accessdate=12 December 2018 |work=Deadline |date=17 May 2018 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Female stunt doubles have begun to protest this norm of &quot;historical sexism&quot;, saying that it restricts their already limited job possibilities&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Carroll |first1=Rory |title='It's historical sexism' – the fight to end stuntmen doubling for women |url=https://www.theguardian.com/film/2018/feb/10/wigging-stuntmen-doubling-for-women-lawsuit |accessdate=12 December 2018 |work=The Guardian |date=10 February 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Lavelle |first1=Daniel |title=Why stuntwomen are angry about 'wigging' – and are changing the industry from within |url=https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2018/nov/27/why-stuntwomen-are-angry-about-wigging-and-are-changing-the-industry-from-within |accessdate=12 December 2018 |work=The Guardian |date=27 November 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sexual fetishes===
[[File:Transvestite in latex clothes.JPG|thumb|A transvestic fetishist wearing latex clothes]]
A [[transvestic fetishism|transvestic fetishist]] is a person who cross-dresses as part of a [[sexual fetish]]. According to the fourth edition of ''[[Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders]]'', this fetishism was limited to [[heterosexual]] men; however, DSM-5 does not have this restriction, and opens it to women and men, regardless of their [[sexual orientation]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dsm5.org/Documents/Paraphilic%20Disorders%20Fact%20Sheet.pdf DSM-5 Documents: Paraphilic Disorders Fact Sheet&lt;/ref&gt;

The term ''underdressing'' is used by male cross-dressers to describe wearing female undergarments such as panties under their male clothes. The famous low-budget film-maker [[Edward D. Wood, Jr.]] said he often wore women's underwear under his military uniform as a Marine during World War II.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Corliss|first=Richard|date=June 1, 1992|title=The World's Worst Director|url=|journal=Time|volume=139|pages=79|via=Biography Reference Bank}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Female masking'' is a form of cross-dressing in which men wear masks that present them as female.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://vicestyle.com/en/news/today/post/female-masking | title=Female Masking | publisher=Vice Style | author=Jamie Clifton | date=August 30, 2011 | accessdate=2012-02-07 | url-status=dead | archiveurl=https://archive.is/20120717035229/http://vicestyle.com/en/news/today/post/female-masking | archivedate=July 17, 2012 | df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sometimes either member of a heterosexual couple will cross-dress in order to arouse the other. For example, the male might wear skirts or lingerie and/or the female will wear boxers or other male clothing. (See also [[forced feminization]])

===Passing or not===
{{Main|Passing (gender)}}
Some people who cross-dress may endeavor to project a complete impression of belonging to another gender, including mannerisms, [[Speech communication|speech]] patterns, and emulation of [[Sex-determination system|sexual characteristics]]. This is referred to as passing or &quot;trying to pass&quot; depending how successful the person is. An observer who sees through the cross-dresser's attempt to pass is said to have ''read'' or ''clocked'' them. There are videos, books, and magazines on how a man may look more like a woman.&lt;ref&gt;''Transformation'' magazine; interviews for ''Rainbow Reader'', Fort Wayne, Indiana&lt;/ref&gt;

Others may choose to take a mixed approach, adopting some feminine traits and some masculine traits in their appearance. For instance, a man might wear both a dress and a beard. This is sometimes known as ''[[genderfuck]]''.  In a broader context, cross-dressing may also refer to other actions undertaken to pass as a particular sex, such as [[Packing (phallus)|packing]] (accentuating the male crotch bulge) or, the opposite, [[tucking]] (concealing the male crotch bulge).&lt;ref&gt;Rankin, Sue, and Genny Beemyn. &quot;Beyond a binary: The lives of gender‐nonconforming youth.&quot; About Campus 17.4 (2012): 2-10&lt;/ref&gt;

==Clothes==
{{More citations needed section|date=October 2014}}

The actual determination of cross-dressing is largely [[socially constructed]]. For example, in Western society, trousers have long been adopted for usage by women, and it is no longer regarded as cross-dressing. In cultures where men have traditionally worn [[Men's skirts|skirt-like garments]] such as the [[kilt]] or [[sarong]], these are not seen as women's clothing, and wearing them is not seen as cross-dressing for men. As societies are becoming more global in nature, both men's and women's clothing are adopting styles of dress associated with other cultures.

[[File:vanessatv.jpg|thumb|Some male crossdressers seek a more subtle feminine image.]]
[[Cosplaying]] may also involve cross-dressing, for some females may wish to dress as a male, and vice versa (see [[Crossplay]]). Breast binding (for females) is not uncommon and is one of the things likely needed to cosplay a male character.

In most parts of the world it remains socially disapproved for men to wear clothes traditionally associated with women. Attempts are occasionally made, e.g. by [[fashion designer]]s, to promote the acceptance of [[male skirt|skirts]] as everyday wear for men. Cross-dressers have complained that society permits women to wear pants or jeans and other masculine clothing, while condemning any man who wants to wear clothing sold for women.

While creating a more feminine figure, male cross-dressers will often utilize different types and styles of [[breast forms]], which are silicone [[prostheses]] traditionally used by women who have undergone [[mastectomies]] to recreate the visual appearance of a breast.

While most male cross-dressers utilize clothing associated with modern women, some are involved in subcultures that involve dressing as little girls or in [[vintage clothing]]. Some such men have written that they enjoy dressing as femininely as possible, so they wear frilly dresses with lace and ribbons, [[bridal gown]]s complete with veils, as well as multiple [[petticoat]]s, [[corset]]s, [[girdle]]s and/or [[garter belt]]s with [[nylon stockings]].

==Social issues==
[[File:A Morning Frolic, or the Transmutation of the Sexes.jpg|thumb|left|Satire on cross-dressing, around 1780 Britain]]
Cross-dressers may begin wearing clothing associated with the opposite sex in childhood, using the clothes of a sibling, parent, or friend. Some parents have said they allowed their children to cross-dress and, in many cases, the child stopped when they became older. The same pattern often continues into adulthood, where there may be confrontations with a spouse, partner, family member or friend. Married cross-dressers can experience considerable anxiety and guilt if their spouse objects to their behavior.

Sometimes because of guilt or other reasons cross-dressers dispose of all their clothing, a practice called &quot;purging&quot;, only to start collecting other gender's clothing again.&lt;ref name = &quot;eucwqo&quot;/&gt;

==Festivals==
Celebrations of cross-dressing occur in widespread cultures. The [[Abissa]] festival in Côte d'Ivoire,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Hall |title=Bibliographic Guide to Dance |date=1992 |pages=4 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Ofudamaki in Japan,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Egli |first1=Justin |title=Visiting an ancient Japanese cross-dressing festival |url=http://www.dazeddigital.com/artsandculture/article/32036/1/visiting-an-ancient-japanese-cross-dressing-festival |accessdate=12 December 2018 |work=Dazed |date=13 July 2016 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Kottankulangara Festival]] in India&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Cross-dressing for the Goddess - Times of India |url=https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/Cross-dressing-for-the-Goddess/articleshow/2929677.cms? |accessdate=12 December 2018 |work=The Times of India |date=Apr 6, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; are all examples of this.

==Analysis==
The historical associations of maleness with power and femaleness with submission and frivolity mean that in the present time a woman dressing in men's clothing and a man dressing in women's clothing evoke very different responses. A woman dressing in men's clothing is considered to be a more acceptable activity.{{cn|date=October 2019}}

Advocacy for social change has done much to relax the constrictions of gender roles on men and women, but they are still subject to prejudice from some people.&lt;ref&gt;Butler, Judith, Gender Trouble: Feminism and the Subversion of Identity, Routledge, New York, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Halberstam, Judith, Female Masculinity, Duke University Press, Durham and London, 1998&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Epstein, Julia, Straub, Kristina; Eds, Body Guards: The Cultural Politics of Gender Ambiguity, Routledge, London, 1991&lt;/ref&gt; It is noticeable that as 'transgender' is becoming more socially accepted as a normal human condition, the prejudices against cross-dressing are changing quite quickly, just as the similar prejudices against homosexuals have changed rapidly in recent decades.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.pewsocialtrends.org/2013/06/13/chapter-2-social-acceptance/|title=A Survey of LGBT Americans - Chapter 2: Social Acceptance|date=2013-06-13|work=Pew Research Center’s Social &amp; Demographic Trends Project|access-date=2018-03-07|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The reason it is so hard to have statistics for female-assigned cross-dressers is that the line where cross-dressing stops and cross-dressing begins has become blurred, whereas the same line for men is as well defined as ever. This is one of the many issues being addressed by third wave feminism as well as the modern-day [[masculism|masculist]] movement.

The general culture has very mixed views about cross-dressing. A woman who wears her husband's shirt to bed is considered attractive while a man who wears his wife's nightgown to bed may be considered transgressive.  [[Marlene Dietrich]] in a tuxedo was considered very erotic; [[Jack Lemmon]] in a dress was considered ridiculous.&lt;ref&gt;Blechner, M. J. (2009) ''Sex Changes: Transformations in Society and Psychoanalysis.''  New York: Routledge.&lt;/ref&gt; All this may result from an overall gender role rigidity for males; that is, because of the prevalent gender dynamic throughout the world, men frequently encounter discrimination when deviating from masculine gender norms, particularly violations of [[heteronormativity]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://steinhardt.nyu.edu/scmsAdmin/media/users/lec321/Sirin_Articles/Sirin_McCriery__Mahalik_2004.pdf |title=Differential Reactions to Men and Women's Gender Role Transgressions: Perceptions of Social Status, Sexual Orientation, and Value Dissimilarity |publisher=NYU |accessdate=1 June 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A man's adoption of feminine clothing is often considered a going down in the gendered social order whereas a woman's adoption of what are traditionally men's clothing (at least in the English-speaking world) has less of an impact because women have been traditionally subordinate to men, unable to affect serious change through style of dress. Thus when a male cross-dresser puts on his clothes, he transforms into the quasi-female and thereby becomes an embodiment of the conflicted gender dynamic. Following the work of [[Judith Butler|Butler]], gender proceeds along through ritualized performances, but in male cross-dressing it becomes a performative &quot;breaking&quot; of the masculine and a &quot;subversive repetition&quot; of the feminine.&lt;ref name=Butler&gt;{{cite web|last=Butler|first=Judith|title=Performative Acts and Gender Construction: An Essay in Phenomenology and Feminist Theory|url=http://www.mariabuszek.com/kcai/PoMoSeminar/Readings/BtlrPerfActs.pdf|accessdate=1 June 2012|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120112054310/http://www.mariabuszek.com/kcai/PoMoSeminar/Readings/BtlrPerfActs.pdf|archivedate=12 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Psychoanalysts today do not regard cross-dressing by itself as a psychological problem, unless it interferes with a person's life. &quot;For instance,&quot; said Dr. Joseph Merlino, senior editor of ''Freud at 150: 21st Century Essays on a Man of Genius'', &quot;[suppose that]...I'm a cross-dresser and I don't want to keep it confined to my circle of friends, or my party circle, and I want to take that to my wife and I don't understand why she doesn't accept it, or I take it to my office and I don't understand why they don't accept it, then it's become a problem because it's interfering with my relationships and environment.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Shankbone, David. &quot;[[n:Dr. Joseph Merlino on sexuality, insanity, Freud, fetishes and apathy#Gender identity and Heteronormativity|Interview with Dr. Joseph Merlino]]&quot;,  ''[[Wikinews]]'' (October 5, 2007)&lt;/ref&gt;

==British pantomime, television and comedy==
[[Image:1896 DanLeno-WidowTwankey.jpg|thumb|upright|Comedian [[Dan Leno]] as [[Widow Twankey]] in the 1896 [[pantomime]] ''Aladdin'' at [[Theatre Royal, Drury Lane]], London]]
Cross-dressing is a traditional popular trope in [[British comedy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=The Brits and Cross-Dressing: A History |url=http://www.bbcamerica.com/anglophenia/2014/11/brits-cross-dressing-history |accessdate=26 April 2019 |agency=BBC America}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Pantomime dame]] in British [[pantomime]] dates from the 19th century, which is part of the theatrical tradition of female characters portrayed by male actors in drag. The [[Monty Python]] comedy troupe donned frocks and makeup, playing female roles themselves while speaking in [[falsetto]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Cross-Dressing and Fish-Slapping, One Python at a Time |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/22/arts/television/crossdressing-and-fishslapping-one-python-at-a-time.html |accessdate=26 April 2019 |agency=New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; Character comics such as [[Benny Hill]] and [[Dick Emery]] drew upon several female identities. In the [[BBC]]’s long-running sketch show ''The Dick Emery Show'' (broadcast from 1963 to 1981), Emery played Mandy, a busty peroxide blonde whose catchphrase, &quot;Ooh, you are awful ... but I like you!&quot;, was given in response to a seemingly innocent remark made by her interviewer, but perceived by her as ribald double entendre.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=The Dick Emery Show |url=https://www.britishclassiccomedy.co.uk/ooh-you-are-awful-but-i-like-you |accessdate=26 April 2019 |agency=British classic comedy}}&lt;/ref&gt; The popular tradition of cross dressing in British comedy extended to the 1984 music video for [[Queen (band)|Queen]]’s &quot;[[I Want to Break Free]]&quot; where the band parody several female characters from the soap opera ''[[Coronation Street]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=10 things you may not know about Queen's biggest 80s hits |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/articles/4C6GqGSRcDydqhJNh5xpgyZ/10-things-you-may-not-know-about-queens-biggest-80s-hits |first=Fraser |last=McAlpine |date=29 November 2018 |agency=BBC|access-date=6 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Literature==
Women dressed as men, and less often men dressed as women, is a common trope in fiction&lt;ref name=&quot;C&amp;G 395&quot;&gt;Clute &amp; Grant 1997, p. 395&lt;/ref&gt; and folklore. For example, in [[Norse myth]], [[Thor]] disguised himself as [[Freya]].&lt;ref name=&quot;C&amp;G 395&quot; /&gt; These [[disguise]]s were also popular in [[Gothic fiction]], such as in works by [[Charles Dickens]], [[Alexandre Dumas, père]], and [[Eugène Sue]],&lt;ref name=&quot;C&amp;G 395&quot; /&gt; and in a number of [[William Shakespeare|Shakespeare]]'s plays, such as ''[[Twelfth Night]]''.  In ''[[The Wind in the Willows]]'', Toad dresses as a washerwoman, and in ''[[Lord of the Rings]]'', Éowyn pretends to be a man.

In [[science fiction]], [[fantasy]] and [[Women's writing in English|women's literature]], this [[literary motif]] is occasionally taken further, with literal transformation of a character from male to female or vice versa.  [[Virginia Woolf]]'s ''[[Orlando: A Biography]]'' focuses on a man who becomes a woman, as does a warrior in [[Peter S. Beagle]]'s ''The Innkeeper's Song'';&lt;ref name=&quot;C&amp;G 396&quot;&gt;Clute &amp; Grant 1997, p. 396&lt;/ref&gt; while in [[Geoff Ryman]]'s ''The Warrior who Carried Life'', Cara magically transforms herself into a man.&lt;ref name=&quot;C&amp;G 396&quot; /&gt;

Other popular examples of gender disguise include ''[[Madame Doubtfire]]'' (published as ''Alias Madame Doubtfire'' in the United States) and its movie adaptation ''[[Mrs. Doubtfire]]'', featuring a man disguised as a woman.&lt;ref&gt;Anita Silvey [https://books.google.com/books?id=8GUNHGutszEC&amp;pg=PA284&amp;dq=characters+disguised+as+human#v=onepage&amp;q=characters%20disguised%20as%20human&amp;f=false The essential guide to children's books and their creators] p.155&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, the movie ''[[Tootsie]]'' features [[Dustin Hoffman]] disguised as a woman, while the movie ''[[The Associate (1996 film)|The Associate]]'' features [[Whoopi Goldberg]] disguised as a man.

==Medical views==

The 10th edition of the [[International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems]] lists ''dual-role transvestism'' (non-sexual cross-dressing)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://icd.who.int/browse10/2016/en#/F64.1 |title=ICD-10 Version:2016 |website=icd.who.int |access-date=2019-10-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''fetishistic transvestism'' (cross-dressing for sexual pleasure) as disorders.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://icd.who.int/browse10/2016/en#/F65.1 |title=ICD-10 Version:2016 |website=icd.who.int |access-date=2019-10-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both listings were removed for the 11th edition.&lt;ref name=&quot;lgbtq&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.lgbtqnation.com/2019/05/world-health-organization-will-no-longer-classify-transgender-mental-disorder/ |title=The World Health Organization will no longer classify being transgender as a ‘mental disorder’ |last=Bollinger |first=Alex |date=2019-05-28 |website=www.lgbtqnation.com |access-date=2019-10-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[Transvestic fetishism]] is a [[paraphilia]], and a psychiatric diagnosis in the [[DSM-5]] version of the ''[[Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;DSM-5-paraphillic&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| first=| last= American Psychiatric Association| year= 2013| title=Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders| edition=Fifth| publisher=American Psychiatric Publishing| location=Arlington, VA| pages=685–705| isbn= 978-0-89042-555-8 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|fashion}}
{{div col|colwidth=20em}}
* [[Androgyny]]
* [[Autogynephilia]]
* [[Breeches role]]
* [[Breeching (boys)]]
* [[Cross dressing ball]]
* [[Cross-dressing in film and television]]
* [[Cross-dressing in literature]]
* [[Cross-gender acting]]
* [[En femme]]
* [[En homme]]
* [[The Famous Flower of Serving-Men]]
* [[Feminization (activity)|Feminization]]
* [[Gender identity]]
* [[Hijra (South Asia)]]
* [[Kathoey]]
* [[List of transgender-related topics]]
* [[List of wartime crossdressers]]
* ''[[Otokonoko]]'', male crossdressing in Japan
* [[Passing (gender)]]
* [[Sex and gender distinction]]
* [[Drag Queen#History of Drag|History of Drag]]
* [[Sexual orientation hypothesis]]
* [[Transvestism]]
* [[Travesti (theatre)]]
* [[Tri-Ess]]
* [[Twelfth Night]]
* [[Two-spirit]]
* [[Womanless wedding]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* Anders, Charles. ''The Lazy Crossdresser'', [[Greenery Press]], 2002. {{ISBN|1-890159-37-9}}.
* [[Helen Boyd|Boyd, Helen]]. ''[[My Husband Betty]]'', Thunder's Mouth Press, 2003
* {{citation |last=Chesser |first=Lucy Sarah |title=Parting with My Sex: Cross-dressing, Inversion and Sexuality in Australian Cultural Life |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CKRE6-CWLAoC |year=2008 |publisher=Sydney University Press |isbn=978-1-920898-31-1 |oclc=488863093}}
* [[John Clute|Clute, John]] &amp; Grant, John. ''[[The Encyclopedia of Fantasy]]'', Orbit Books, 1997. {{ISBN|978-1-85723-368-1}}
* {{citation |last1=Dekker |first1=Rudolf M |last2=van de Pol |first2=Lotte C  |author3=Kazi Maruful Islam |title=The Tradition Of Female Cross-Dressing In Early Modern Europe |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=buewCwAAQBAJ |date=8 February 1989 |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan UK |isbn=978-1-349-19752-1}}
* Gravois, Valory. ''[http://www.crossdressingnovel.com Cherry Single]'', Alchemist/Light Publishing, 1997 (Available to read free, online), {{ISBN|0-9600650-5-9}}
* {{citation |last=Hauk |first=Savannah |title=Living with Crossdressing: Defining a New Normal |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CJ8uDwAAQBAJ |date=1 September 2017 |isbn=978-1-5378-6529-4 |oclc=1013928885}}
* &quot;Lynne&quot;. [https://web.archive.org/web/20160305000529/https://gendercentre.org.au/resources/polare-archive/archived-articles/a-cross-dressing-perspective.htm &quot;A Cross-Dressing-Perspective&quot;]

==External links==
{{Commons category|Cross-dressing}}
* [http://www.gendercentre.org.au/ The Gender Centre (Australia)]
* [http://www.xdresser.ca/ Crossdressing Support Group (Canada)]

{{Drag performance}}
{{Crossdressing footer}}

[[Category:Cross-dressing| ]]</text>
      <sha1>8n7951bcu4z7iyab0ibs352umpuxouw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
