  <page>
    <title>Cave</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5778</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939093917</id>
      <parentid>939093811</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-04T08:56:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>213.82.128.139</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{other uses}}
{{redirect|Cavern}}
{{short description|Natural underground space large enough for a human to enter}}
[[File:Lechuguilla Cave Pearlsian Gulf.jpg|thumb|upright=1.3|[[Lechuguilla Cave]], [[New Mexico]], United States]]
A '''cave''' or '''cavern''' is a natural void in the [[Earth#Surface|ground]],&lt;ref&gt;Whitney, W. D. (1889). &quot;Cave, n.1.&quot; def. 1. ''The Century dictionary: An encyclopedic lexicon of the English language'' (Vol. 1, p. 871). New York: The Century Co.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Cave&quot; ''Oxford English Dictionary'' Second Edition on CD-ROM (v. 4.0) © Oxford University Press 2009&lt;/ref&gt; specifically a space large enough for a human to enter. Caves often form by the [[weathering]] of rock and often extend deep underground. The word ''cave'' can also refer to much smaller openings such as [[sea cave]]s, [[rock shelter]]s, and [[grotto]]s, though strictly speaking a cave is exogene, meaning it is deeper than its opening is wide,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jUm0BQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA304&amp;lpg=PA304|page=304|title=California Archaeology|first=Michael J.|last=Moratto|publisher=Academic Press|year=2014|isbn=9781483277356}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a rock shelter is endogene.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=OEODBAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA142|title=Reconstructing Quaternary Environments|last=Lowe|first=J. John|last2=Walker|first2=Michael J. C.|date=2014|publisher=Routledge|isbn=9781317753711|pages=141–42}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Speleology]] is the science of exploration and study of all aspects of caves and the cave environment. Visiting or exploring caves for recreation may be called [[Caving|''caving'', ''potholing'', or ''spelunking'']].

==Types and formation==
The formation and development of caves is known as ''[[speleogenesis]]''; it can occur over the course of millions of years.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Laureano|first=Fernando V.|last2=Karmann|first2=Ivo|last3=Granger|first3=Darryl E.|last4=Auler|first4=Augusto S.|last5=Almeida|first5=Renato P.|last6=Cruz|first6=Franciso W.|last7=Strícks|first7=Nicolás M.|last8=Novello|first8=Valdir F.|date=2016-11-15|title=Two million years of river and cave aggradation in NE Brazil: Implications for speleogenesis and landscape evolution|journal=Geomorphology|volume=273|pages=63–77|doi=10.1016/j.geomorph.2016.08.009|bibcode=2016Geomo.273...63L}}&lt;/ref&gt; Caves can range widely in size, and are formed by various geological processes. These may involve a combination of chemical processes, erosion by water, tectonic forces, microorganisms, pressure, and atmospheric influences. Isotopic dating techniques can be applied to cave sediments, to determine the timescale of the geological events which formed and shaped present-day caves.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

It is estimated that a cave cannot be more than {{convert|3000|m}} vertically beneath the surface due to the pressure of overlying rocks. This does not, however, impose a maximum depth for a cave which is measured from its highest entrance to its lowest point, as the amount of rock above the lowest point is dependent on the topography of the landscape above it.  For [[karst]] caves the maximum depth is determined on the basis of the lower limit of karst forming processes, coinciding with the base of the soluble carbonate rocks.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rgo-speleo.ru/books/termin/termin1.htm#a9 Комиссия спелеологии и карстоведения. Д. А. Тимофеев, В. Н. Дублянский, Т. З. Кикнадзе. Терминология карста. Базис карстования] D.A. Timofeev, V.N. Dublyansky, T.Z. Kiknadze, 1991, ''Karst Terminology'', The Commission for Speleology and Karst, Moscow Center of the Russian Geographical Society&lt;!-- Google translate --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; Most caves are formed in [[limestone]] by [[Solvation|dissolution]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/earth/how-caves-form.html|publisher=[[Nova (American TV series)]]|title=How Caves Form|accessdate=2013-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Caves can be classified in various other ways as well, including a contrast between active and relict: active caves have water flowing through them; relict caves do not, though water may be retained in them. Types of active caves include inflow caves (&quot;into which a stream sinks&quot;), outflow caves (&quot;from which a stream emerges&quot;), and through caves (&quot;traversed by a stream&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book  |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NsscjizazXAC&amp;pg=PA38 |title=The Cave Book|last=Silvestru|first=Emil |date=2008|publisher=New Leaf|isbn=9780890514962|page=38}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:HallOfTheMountainKings.jpg|thumb|[[Speleothem]]s in Hall of the Mountain King of [[Ogof Craig a Ffynnon]], a solutional cave in [[South Wales]].]]

===Solutional cave===
{{Main|Solutional cave}}
'''Solutional caves''' or '''karst caves''' are the most frequently occurring caves. Such caves form in rock that is soluble; most occur in [[limestone]], but they can also form in other rocks including [[chalk]], [[Dolomite (rock)|dolomite]], marble, salt, and [[gypsum]]. Rock is dissolved by natural acid in groundwater that seeps through [[Bed (geology)|bedding planes]], [[Fault (geology)|faults]], joints, and comparable features. Over time cracks enlarge to become caves and cave systems.

The largest and most abundant solutional caves are located in limestone. Limestone dissolves under the action of rainwater and groundwater charged with H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;CO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; ([[carbonic acid]]) and naturally occurring [[organic acid]]s. The dissolution process produces a distinctive landform known as ''[[karst]]'', characterized by [[sinkhole]]s and underground drainage. Limestone caves are often adorned with [[calcium carbonate]] formations produced through slow precipitation. These include [[flowstone]]s, [[stalactite]]s, [[stalagmite]]s, [[helictite]]s, [[soda straw]]s and columns. These secondary mineral deposits in caves are called ''[[speleothem]]s''.

The portions of a solutional cave that are below the [[water table]] or the local level of the groundwater will be flooded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.amazingcaves.com/learn_formed.html |title=Learning about caves; how caves are formed |accessdate=September 8, 2009 |author=John Burcham |work=Journey into amazing caves |publisher=Project Underground |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090503192150/http://www.amazingcaves.com/learn_formed.html |archivedate=May 3, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Lechuguilla Cave]] in [[New Mexico]] and nearby [[Carlsbad Cavern]] are now believed to be examples of another type of solutional cave. They were formed by H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;S ([[hydrogen sulfide]]) gas rising from below, where reservoirs of oil give off sulfurous fumes. This gas mixes with groundwater and forms H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;SO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; ([[sulfuric acid]]). The acid then dissolves the limestone from below, rather than from above, by acidic water percolating from the surface.

===Primary cave===
&lt;!--{{main|Primary cave}}--&gt;
[[File:hawaiian lava tube.jpg|thumb|Exploring a [[lava tube]] in [[Hawaii]].]]
Caves formed at the same time as the surrounding rock are called '''primary caves'''.

[[Lava tube]]s are formed through [[Volcano|volcanic]] activity and are the most common primary caves. As [[lava]] flows downhill, its surface cools and solidifies. Hot liquid lava continues to flow under that crust, and if most of it flows out, a hollow tube remains. Such caves can be found in the [[Canary Islands]], [[Jeju Province|Jeju-do]], the basaltic plains of [[Eastern Idaho]], and in other places. [[Kazumura Cave]] near [[Hilo]], [[Hawaii (island)|Hawaii]] is a remarkably long and deep lava tube; it is {{convert|65.6|km|mi|abbr=on|adj=mid|long}}.

Lava caves include but are not limited to lava tubes. Other caves formed through volcanic activity include rifts, lava molds, open vertical conduits, inflationary, blisters, among others.&lt;ref name=&quot;ENCYCLO&quot;&gt;{{cite book|page=84|title=Encyclopedia of Caves|first=David C.|last=Culver|publisher=Elsevier Academic Press|year=2004|isbn=978-0121986513}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sea cave or littoral cave===
{{Main|Sea cave}}
[[File:Painted cave.jpg|thumb|Painted Cave, a large [[sea cave]], [[Santa Cruz Island]], [[California]]]]
Sea caves are found along coasts around the world. A special case is littoral caves, which are formed by wave action in zones of weakness in sea cliffs. Often these weaknesses are faults, but they may also be dykes or bedding-plane contacts. Some wave-cut caves are now above sea level because of later uplift. Elsewhere, in places such as Thailand's [[Phang Nga Bay]], solutional caves have been flooded by the sea and are now subject to littoral erosion. Sea caves are generally around {{convert|5|to|50|m}} in length, but may exceed {{convert|300|m}}.

===Corrasional cave or erosional cave===
[[Image:Sodom Salt Cave 031712.JPG|thumb|[[Halite (mineral)|Salt]] cave in [[Mount Sodom]], [[Israel]].]]
Corrasional or erosional caves are those that form entirely by erosion by flowing streams carrying rocks and other sediments. These can form in any type of rock, including hard rocks such as granite. Generally there must be some zone of weakness to guide the water, such as a fault or joint. A subtype of the erosional cave is the wind or aeolian cave, carved by wind-born sediments.&lt;ref name=&quot;ENCYCLO&quot;/&gt; Many caves formed initially by solutional processes often undergo a subsequent phase of erosional or vadose enlargement where active streams or rivers pass through them.

===Glacier cave===
{{Main|Glacier cave}}
[[File:Big Four Glacier Ice cave.jpg|thumb|[[Glacier cave]] in Big Four Glacier, [[Big Four Mountain]], [[Washington (state)|Washington]], [[circa|ca.]] 1920]]
Glacier caves are formed by melting ice and flowing water within and under glaciers.  The cavities are influenced by the [[Creep (deformation)|very slow flow]] of the ice, which tends to collapse the caves again. Glacier caves are sometimes misidentified as &quot;[[ice cave]]s&quot;, though this latter term is properly reserved for bedrock caves that contain year-round ice formations.

===Fracture cave===
Fracture caves are formed when layers of more soluble minerals, such as gypsum, dissolve out from between layers of less soluble rock. These rocks fracture and collapse in blocks of stone.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Paleogeophysics &amp; Geodynamics, Stockholm, Sweden|last2=Mörner|first2=Nils-Axel|last3=Sjöberg|first3=Rabbe|last4=Obbola, Umeå, Sweden|date=September 2018|title=Merging the concepts of pseudokarst and paleoseismicity in Sweden: A unified theory on the formation of fractures, fracture caves, and angular block heape|journal=International Journal of Speleology|volume=47|issue=3|pages=393–405|doi=10.5038/1827-806X.47.3.2225|issn=0392-6672}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Talus cave===
Talus caves are formed by the openings among large boulders that have fallen down into a random heap, often at the bases of cliffs.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Kolawole|first=F.|last2=Anifowose|first2=A. Y. B.|date=2011-01-01|title=Talus Caves: Geotourist Attractions Formed by Spheroidal and Exfoliation Weathering on Akure-Ado Inselbergs, Southwestern Nigeria.|journal=Ethiopian Journal of Environmental Studies and Management|volume=4|issue=3|pages=1–6|doi=10.4314/ejesm.v4i3.1|issn=1998-0507}}&lt;/ref&gt;  These unstable deposits are called talus or [[scree]], and may be subject to frequent [[rockfall]]s and [[landslide]]s.

===Anchialine cave===
{{Main|Anchialine cave}}
Anchialine caves are caves, usually coastal, containing a mixture of freshwater and saline water (usually sea water). They occur in many parts of the world, and often contain highly specialized and endemic fauna.{{citation needed|date=January 2019}}

==Physical patterns==
*''Branchwork caves'' resemble surface dendritic stream patterns; they are made up of passages that join downstream as tributaries. Branchwork caves are the most common of cave patterns and are formed near [[sinkhole]]s where [[groundwater recharge]] occurs. Each passage or branch is fed by a separate recharge source and converges into other higher order branches downstream.&lt;ref name=Easterbrook&gt;Easterbrook, Don, 1999, ''Surface Processes and Landforms [2nd edition]'', New Jersey, Prentice Hall, p. 207&lt;/ref&gt;
*''Angular network caves'' form from intersecting fissures of carbonate rock that have had fractures widened by chemical erosion. These fractures form high, narrow, straight passages that persist in widespread closed loops.&lt;ref name=Easterbrook /&gt;
*''Anastomotic caves'' largely resemble surface braided streams with their passages separating and then meeting further down drainage. They usually form along one bed or structure, and only rarely cross into upper or lower beds.&lt;ref name=Easterbrook /&gt;
*''Spongework caves'' are formed when solution cavities are joined by mixing of chemically diverse water. The cavities form a pattern that is three-dimensional and random, resembling a sponge.&lt;ref name=Easterbrook /&gt;
*''Ramiform caves'' form as irregular large rooms, galleries, and passages. These randomized three-dimensional rooms form from a rising water table that erodes the carbonate rock with hydrogen-sulfide enriched water.&lt;ref name=Easterbrook /&gt;
*''[[Pit cave]]s'' (vertical caves, potholes, or simply &quot;pits&quot;) consist of a vertical shaft rather than a horizontal cave passage. They may or may not be associated with one of the above structural patterns.

==Geographic distribution==
[[Image:Domica Cave 22.jpg|thumb|[[Domica|Domica Cave]] in [[Slovak Karst]] ([[Slovakia]])]]
Caves are found throughout the world, but only a small portion of them have been explored and documented by cavers.{{cn|date=October 2019}} The distribution of documented cave systems is widely skewed toward countries where caving has been popular for many years (such as France, Italy, Australia, the UK, the United States, etc.). As a result, explored caves are found widely in Europe, Asia, North America and Oceania, but are sparse in South America, Africa, and Antarctica.

This is a rough generalization, as large expanses of North America and Asia contain no documented caves, whereas areas such as the [[Madagascar dry deciduous forests]] and parts of [[Brazil]] contain many documented caves. As the world's expanses of soluble bedrock are researched by cavers, the distribution of documented caves is likely to shift. For example, China, despite containing around half the world's exposed limestone—more than {{convert|1000000|km2}}—has relatively few documented caves.

==Records and superlatives==
*The cave system with the ''greatest total length'' of surveyed passage is [[Mammoth Cave National Park|Mammoth Cave]] in [[Kentucky]], US, at {{convert|652|km|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;NSS-GEO2&quot;&gt;[http://www.caverbob.com/wlong.htm World’s Longest Caves List from The National Speleological Society]&lt;/ref&gt;
*The longest surveyed ''underwater cave'', and second longest overall, is [[Sistema Sac Actun]] in [[Yucatán Peninsula|Yucatán]], Mexico at {{convert|335|km|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;NSS-GEO2&quot; /&gt;
*The ''deepest known cave'' — measured from its highest entrance to its lowest point — is [[Veryovkina Cave]] in [[Abkhazia]], [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]], with a depth of {{convert|2,204|m|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=wdeep&gt;[http://www.caverbob.com/wdeep.htm World's Deepest Caves List from The National Speleological Society]&lt;/ref&gt; This was the first cave to be explored to a depth of more than {{convert|2|km|abbr=on}}. (The first cave to be descended below {{convert|1|km|abbr=on}} was [[Gouffre Berger]] in France.) The [[Sarma, Georgia|Sarma]] and [[Illyuzia-Mezhonnogo-Snezhnaya]] caves in Georgia, ({{convert|1830|m|abbr=on|disp=or}}, and {{convert|1753|m|abbr=on|disp=or}} respectively) are the current second- and third-deepest caves.&lt;ref name=wdeep /&gt; The deepest outside Georgia is [[Lamprechtsofen|Lamprechtsofen Vogelschacht Weg Schacht]] in Austria, which is {{convert|1,623|m|abbr=on}} deep.&lt;ref name=wdeep /&gt;
*The ''deepest vertical shaft'' in a cave is {{convert|603|m|abbr=on}} in [[Vrtoglavica Cave]] in [[Slovenia]]. The second deepest is Ghar-e-Ghala at {{convert|562|m|abbr=on}} in the Parau massif near [[Kermanshah]] in [[Iran]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Brocklebank|first1=Tony|title=Iranian cavers discover one of the world's deepest shafts|url=http://darknessbelow.co.uk/iranian-cavers-discover-one-of-the-worlds-deepest-shafts/|website=Darkness Below UK|accessdate=1 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The deepest ''underwater cave'' bottomed by a [[remotely operated underwater vehicle]] at {{convert|404|m|ft}}, is the [[Hranice Abyss]] in the [[Czech Republic]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nationalgeographic.com/adventure/activities/caving-and-canyoneering/deepest-underwater-cave-discovered/| title=Exclusive: Deepest Underwater Cave Discovered}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The ''largest known room'' is [[Sarawak Chamber]], in the [[Gunung Mulu National Park]] ([[Miri, Malaysia|Miri]], [[Sarawak]], [[Borneo]], [[Malaysia]]), a sloping, boulder strewn chamber with an area of approximately {{convert|700|by|400|m|ft|0|abbr=on}} and a height of {{convert|80|m|abbr=on}}. The nearby [[Clearwater Cave System]] is believed to be the world's ''largest cave by volume'', with a calculated volume of {{convert|3800000|m3|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Is the Clearwater System the biggest of them all?|url=http://www.mulucaves.org/wordpress/articles/is-the-clearwater-system-the-biggest-of-them-all|website=The Mulu Caves Project|accessdate=19 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The largest room in a [[show cave]] is the [[La Verna cave|salle de La Verna]] in the French [[Pyrenees]].
*The ''largest passage'' ever discovered is in the [[Son Doong Cave]] in [[Phong Nha-Kẻ Bàng National Park]] in [[Quảng Bình Province]], [[Vietnam]]. It is {{convert|4.6|km|mi|abbr=on}} in length, {{convert|80|m|ft|abbr=on}} high and wide over most of its length, but over {{convert|140|m|ft|abbr=on}} high and wide for part of its length.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| last = Owen
| first = James
| title = World's Biggest Cave Found in Vietnam
| work = National Geographic News
| publisher = [[National Geographic Society]]
| date = 2009-07-04
| url = http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2009/07/090724-biggest-cave-vietnam.html
| accessdate =2009-07-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===World's five longest surveyed caves===
{{for|more|List of longest caves}}
# [[Mammoth Cave]], [[Kentucky]], US&lt;ref name=&quot;NSS-GEO2&quot; /&gt;
# [[Sistema Sac Actun]]/[[Sistema Dos Ojos]], Mexico&lt;ref name=&quot;NSS-GEO2&quot; /&gt;
# [[Jewel Cave]], [[South Dakota]], US&lt;ref name=&quot;NSS-GEO2&quot; /&gt;
# [[Sistema Ox Bel Ha]], Mexico&lt;ref name=&quot;NSS-GEO2&quot; /&gt;
# [[Optymistychna Cave]], [[Ukraine]]&lt;ref name=&quot;NSS-GEO2&quot; /&gt;

==Ecology==
{{Main|Biospeleology}}
[[File:townsends in music hall.jpg|thumb|[[Townsend's big-eared bat]]s in a cave in California]]
[[File:Proteus anguinus Postojnska Jama Slovenija.jpg|thumb|[[Olm]]s in a Slovenian cave]]
Cave-inhabiting animals are often categorized as [[troglobite]]s (cave-limited species), [[troglophile]]s (species that can live their entire lives in caves, but also occur in other environments), [[trogloxene]]s (species that use caves, but cannot complete their life cycle fully in caves) and accidentals (animals not in one of the previous categories). Some authors use separate terminology for aquatic forms (for example, [[stygobite]]s, [[stygophile]]s, and [[stygoxene]]s).

Of these animals, the troglobites are perhaps the most unusual organisms. Troglobitic species often show a number of characteristics, termed troglomorphic, associated with their adaptation to subterranean life. These characteristics may include a loss of pigment (often resulting in a pale or white coloration), a loss of eyes (or at least of optical functionality), an elongation of appendages, and an enhancement of other senses (such as the ability to sense vibrations in water). Aquatic troglobites (or stygobites), such as the endangered [[Alabama cave shrimp]], live in bodies of water found in caves and get nutrients from detritus washed into their caves and from the feces of bats and other cave inhabitants. Other aquatic troglobites include cave fish, and [[cave salamander]]s such as the [[olm]] and the [[Texas blind salamander]].

[[Cave insects]] such as Oligaphorura (formerly Archaphorura) schoetti are troglophiles, reaching {{convert|1.7|mm}} in length. They have extensive distribution and have been studied fairly widely. Most specimens are female, but a male specimen was collected from [[St Cuthberts Swallet]] in 1969.

[[Bat]]s, such as the [[gray bat]] and [[Mexican free-tailed bat]], are trogloxenes and are often found in caves; they forage outside of the caves. Some species of [[cave cricket]]s are classified as trogloxenes, because they roost in caves by day and forage above ground at night.

Because of the fragile nature of the cave ecosystem, and the fact that cave regions tend to be isolated from one another, caves harbor a number of endangered species, such as the [[Tooth cave spider]], [[Liphistiidae|liphistius trapdoor spider]], and the gray bat.

Caves are visited by many surface-living animals, including humans. These are usually relatively short-lived incursions, due to the lack of light and sustenance.

Cave entrances often have typical florae. For instance, in the eastern temperate United States, cave entrances are most frequently (and often densely) populated by the bulblet fern, ''[[Cystopteris bulbifera]]''.

==Archaeological and cultural importance==
[[File:Taino petroglyph in cave.jpg|thumb|[[Taíno people|Taíno]] [[petroglyph]]s in a cave in Puerto Rico]]
Throughout history, primitive peoples have made use of caves. The earliest human [[fossil]]s found in caves come from a series of caves near Krugersdorp and Mokopane in South Africa. The cave sites of [[Sterkfontein]], [[Swartkrans]], [[Kromdraai]] B, [[Drimolen]], [[Malapa]], Cooper's D, Gladysvale, Gondolin and Makapansgat have yielded a range of early human species dating back to between three and one million years ago, including [[Australopithecus africanus]], [[Australopithecus sediba]] and [[Paranthropus robustus]]. However, it is not generally thought that these early humans were living in the caves, but that they were brought into the caves by carnivores that had killed them.

The first early hominid ever found in Africa, the [[Taung Child]] in 1924, was also thought for many years to come from a cave, where it had been deposited after being predated on by an eagle. However, this is now debated (Hopley et al., 2013; Am. J. Phys. Anthrop.). Caves do form in the dolomite of the Ghaap Plateau, including the Early, Middle and Later Stone Age site of [[Wonderwerk Cave]]; however, the caves that form along the escarpment's edge, like that hypothesised for the Taung Child, are formed within a secondary limestone deposit called [[tufa]]. There is numerous evidence for other early human species inhabiting caves from at least one million years ago in different parts of the world, including [[Homo erectus]] in China at [[Zhoukoudian]], [[Homo rhodesiensis]] in South Africa at the Cave of Hearths ([[Makapansgat]]), [[Homo neandertalensis]] and [[Homo heidelbergensis]] in Europe at [[Archaeological Site of Atapuerca]], [[Homo floresiensis]] in Indonesia, and the [[Denisovans]] in southern Siberia.

In southern Africa, early modern humans regularly used sea caves as shelter starting about 180,000 years ago when they learned to exploit the sea for the first time (Marean et al., 2007; Nature). The oldest known site is PP13B at [[Pinnacle Point]]. This may have allowed rapid expansion of humans out of Africa and colonization of areas of the world such as Australia by 60–50,000 years ago. Throughout southern Africa, Australia, and Europe, early modern humans used caves and rock shelters as sites for rock art, such as those at [[Giants Castle]]. Caves such as the [[yaodong]] in China were used for shelter; other caves were used for burials (such as [[rock-cut tombs]]), or as religious sites (such as [[:Category:Buddhist caves|Buddhist caves]]). Among the known sacred caves are China's Cave of a Thousand Buddhas&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Olsen|first=Brad|title=Sacred Places Around the World: 108 Destinations|year=2004|publisher=CCC Publishing|isbn=9781888729160|page=16|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7FS40w2nrqQC&amp;pg=PA16&amp;q=sacred%20caves}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[sacred caves of Crete]].

==See also==

{{div col}}
* {{annotated link|Cave conservancy}}
* {{annotated link|Cave gate}}
* {{annotated link|Cave waterfall}}
* {{annotated link|Caving}}
* {{annotated link|Caving organizations}}
* {{annotated link|Cenote}}
* {{annotated link|List of caves}}
* {{annotated link|Pit cave}}
* {{annotated link|Speleology}}
* {{annotated link|Speleothem}}
* {{annotated link|Subterranean river}}
* {{annotated link|Underground lake}}
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Caves}}
{{Wikivoyage|Caves|Caves|travel information}}
{{Americana Poster}}

{{Caves}}

{{Authority control}}

&lt;!-- Categories --&gt;
[[Category:Caves| ]]
[[Category:Coastal geography]]
[[Category:Erosion landforms]]
[[Category:Fluvial landforms]]</text>
      <sha1>n1vve0lcffryqvo3riqbp9kelg2yzu4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
