  <page>
    <title>Collectivism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5708</id>
    <revision>
      <id>932702284</id>
      <parentid>932662315</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-27T18:34:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DoubleCross</username>
        <id>49709</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* References */ add template</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|A cultural value that is characterized by emphasis on cohesiveness among individuals and prioritization of the group over self}}
{{distinguish|collecting|collectives}}
{{use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
'''Collectivism''' is a value that is characterized by emphasis on [[Group cohesiveness|cohesiveness]] among individuals and prioritization of the group over the self. Individuals or groups that subscribe to a collectivist worldview tend to find common values and goals as particularly salient&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Schwartz|first=S. H.|date=1990|title=Individualism–collectivism: Critique and proposed refinements|url=|journal=Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology|volume=21|issue=2|pages=139–157|doi=10.1177/0022022190212001}}&lt;/ref&gt; and demonstrate greater orientation toward [[Ingroups and outgroups|in-group]] than toward out-group.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Oyserman|first=D.|date=1993|title=The lens of personhood: Viewing the self, others, and conflict in a multicultural society|url=|journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology|volume=65|issue=5|pages=993–1009|doi=10.1037/0022-3514.65.5.993|hdl=2027.42/89930}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term &quot;in-group&quot; is thought to be more diffusely defined for collectivist individuals to include societal units ranging from the nuclear family to a religious or racial/ethnic group.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Hui|first=C. H.|date=1988|title=Measurement of individualism–collectivism|url=|journal=Journal of Research in Personality|volume=22|pages=17–36|doi=10.1016/0092-6566(88)90022-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Individualism and Collectivism|last=Triandis|first=H. C.|publisher=Westview Press|year=1995|isbn=|location=Boulder, CO|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

== Origins and historical perspectives ==
The German sociologist [[Ferdinand Tönnies]] described an early model of collectivism and [[individualism]] using the terms ''Gemeinschaft'' (community) and ''Gesellschaft'' (society).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Community and association| author = F. Tönnies |publisher=Harper Torchbooks | year=1957|isbn= |pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Gemeinschaft'' relationships, in which communalism is prioritized, were thought to be characteristic of small, rural village communities. An anthropologist, Redfield (1941) echoed this notion in work contrasting folk society with urban society.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title= The folk culture of Yucatán|first=Robert|last=Redfield |publisher=University of Chicago Press |year=1941| isbn= |pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Max Weber]] (1930) contrasted collectivism and individualism through the lens of religion, believing that Protestants were more individualistic and self-reliant compared to Catholics, who endorsed hierarchical, interdependent relationships among people.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title= The Protestant ethic and the spirit of capitalism| author = M. Weber |publisher= Routledge|year=1930|isbn=|location=New York|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Geert Hofstede|Hofstede]] (1980) was highly influential in ushering in an era of cross-cultural research making comparisons along the dimension of collectivism versus individualism. Hofstede conceptualized collectivism and individualism as part of a single continuum, with each cultural construct representing an opposite pole. The author characterized individuals that endorsed a high degree of collectivism as being embedded in their social contexts and prioritizing communal goals over individual goals.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Culture's consequences|last=Hofstede|first=G.|publisher=Sage|year=1980|isbn=|location=Beverly Hills|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Marxism–Leninism ===
{{Main|New Soviet man}}
Collectivism was an important part of [[Marxism–Leninism|Marxist–Leninist]] ideology in the [[Soviet Union]], where it played a key part in forming the New Soviet man, willingly sacrificing his or her life for the good of the collective. Terms such as &quot;collective&quot; and &quot;the masses&quot; were frequently used in the official language and praised in [[agitprop]] literature, for example by [[Vladimir Mayakovsky]] (''Who needs a &quot;1&quot;'') and [[Bertolt Brecht]] ([[The Decision (play)|The Decision]], [[Man Equals Man]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Dictators: Hitler's Germany, Stalin's Russia|last=Overy|first=Richard|year=2004|isbn=978-0-393-02030-4|location=|pages=301}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Horn|first=Eva|date=2006|title=Actors/Agents: Bertolt Brecht and the Politics of Secrecy|url=|journal=Grey Room|volume=24|pages=38–55|doi=10.1162/grey.2006.1.24.38}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Terminology and measurement ==
The construct of collectivism is represented in empirical literature under several different names. Most commonly, the term interdependent self-construal is used.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Markus, H. R., &amp; Kitayama, S.|date=1991|title=Culture and the self: Implications for cognition, emotion, and motivation|url=|journal=Psychological Review|volume=98|issue=2|pages=224–253|doi=10.1037/0033-295x.98.2.224|citeseerx=10.1.1.320.1159}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other phrases used to describe the concept of collectivism-individualism include allocentrism-idiocentrism,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Allocentric vs. idiocentric social behavior: A major cultural difference between Hispanics and mainstream (Technical reports)|last=Triandis|first=H. C.|publisher=Department of Psychology, University of Illinois|year=1983|isbn=|location=Champaign|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; collective-private self,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Trafimow, D., [[Triandis, H. C.]], &amp; Goto, S. G.|date=1991|title=Some tests of the distinction between the private self and the collective self|url=|journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology|volume=60|issue=5|pages=649–665|doi=10.1037/0022-3514.60.5.649}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as subtypes of collectivism-individualism (meaning, vertical and horizontal subtypes).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Triandis, H. C., Bhawuk, D. P. S., &amp; Gelfand, M. J.|date=1995|title=Horizontal and vertical dimensions of individualism and collectivism: A theoretical and measurement refinement|url=|journal=Cross-Cultural Research|volume=29|issue=3|pages=240–275|doi=10.1177/106939719502900302}}&lt;/ref&gt; Inconsistent terminology is thought to account for some of the difficulty in effectively synthesizing the empirical literature on collectivism.&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Taras|display-authors=et al|date=2014|title=Opposite Ends of the Same Stick? Multi-Method Test of the Dimensionality of Individualism and Collectivism|url=http://repository.bilkent.edu.tr/bitstream/11693/12980/1/6983.pdf|journal=Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology|volume=45 | issue = 2 |pages=213–245|doi=10.1177/0022022113509132|hdl=11693/12980}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Theoretical models ==
In one critical model of collectivism, Markus and Kitayama&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Markus, H. R., &amp; Kitayma, S.|date=2010|title=Cultures and selves: A cycle of mutual constitution|url=|journal=Perspectives on Psychological Science|volume=5 | issue = 4 |pages=420–430|doi=10.1177/1745691610375557|pmid=26162188}}&lt;/ref&gt; describe the interdependent (i.e., collectivistic) self as fundamentally connected to the social context. As such, one's sense of self depends on and is defined in part by those around them and is primarily manifested in public, overt behavior. As such, the organization of the self is guided by using others as a reference. That is, an interdependent individual uses the unexpressed thoughts, feelings, and beliefs of another person with whom they have a relationship, as well as the other person's behaviors, to make decisions about their own internal attributes and actions.

Markus and Kitayama also contributed to the literature by challenging Hofstede's unidimensional model of collectivism-individualism.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt; The authors conceptualized these two constructs bidimensionally, such that both collectivism and individualism can be endorsed independently and potentially to the same degree. This notion has been echoed by other prominent theorists in the field.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:5&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Singelis|first=T.|date=1994|title=The measurement of independent and interdependent self-construal|url=|journal=Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin|volume=20|issue=5|pages=580–591|doi=10.1177/0146167294205014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:6&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=INDCOL (Unpublished research scale on individualism and collectivism)|last=Triandis|first=H. C.|publisher=University of Illinois|year=1994|isbn=|location=Champaign|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some researchers have expanded the collectivism-individualism framework to include a more comprehensive view. Specifically, Triandis and colleagues introduced a theoretical model that incorporates the notion of relational contexts.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Singelis, T. M., Triandis, H. C., Bhawuk, D. P. S., &amp; Gelfand, M. J.|date=1995|title=Horizontal and vertical dimensions of individualism and collectivism: A theoretical and measurement refinement|url=|journal=Cross-Cultural Research|volume=29|issue=3|pages=240–275|doi=10.1177/106939719502900302}}&lt;/ref&gt; The authors argue that the domains of collectivism and individualism can be further described by horizontal and vertical relationships. Horizontal relationships are believed to be status-equal whereas vertical relationships are characterized as hierarchical and status-unequal. As such, horizontal collectivism is manifested as an orientation in which group harmony is highly valued and in-group members are perceived to experience equal standing. Vertical collectivism involves the prioritization of group goals over individual goals, implying a hierarchical positioning of the self in relation to the overarching in-group. The horizontal-vertical individualism-collectivism model has received empirical support and has been used to explore patterns within cultures.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Komarraju, M., &amp; Cokley, K. O.|date=2008|title=Horizontal and vertical dimensions of individualism–collectivism: A comparison of African Americans and European Americans|url=|journal=Cultural Diversity and Ethnic Minority Psychology|volume=14|issue=4|pages=336–343|doi=10.1037/1099-9809.14.4.336|pmid=18954169}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Lalwani, A. K., Shavitt, S., &amp; Johnson, T.|date=2006|title=What is the relation between cultural orientation and socially desirable responding?|url=|journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology|volume=90|issue=1|pages=165–178|doi=10.1037/0022-3514.90.1.165|pmid=16448316|citeseerx=10.1.1.561.5342}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Originated by W. E. B. DuBois,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The souls of Black folk|last=DuBois|first=W. E. B.|publisher=Signet|year=1969 |orig-year=1903 |isbn=|location=New York|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; some researchers have adopted a historical perspective on the emergence of collectivism among some cultural groups. DuBois and others argued that oppressed minority groups contend with internal division, meaning that the development of self-identity for individuals from these groups involves the integration of one's own perceptions of their group as well as typically negative, societal views of their group.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Gaines, Jr., S. O., &amp; Reed, E. S.|date=1995|title=Prejudice: From Allport to DuBois|url=|journal=American Psychologist|volume=50 | issue = 2 |pages=96–103|doi=10.1037/0003-066x.50.2.96}}&lt;/ref&gt; This division is thought to impact goal formation such that people from marginalized groups tend to emphasize collectivistic over individualistic values.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Black men|last=Asante|first=M. K.|publisher=Sage|year=1981|isbn=|editor-last=Gray|editor-first=L.|location=Beverly Hills|pages=75–82|chapter=Black male and female relationships: An Afrocentric context}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Research with Hispanic populations|last=Marin, G., &amp; Marin, B. V.|publisher=Sage|year=1991|isbn=|location=Newbury Park|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The psychology of Blacks: An African American perspective|last=White, J. L., &amp; Parham, T. A.|publisher=Prentice-Hall|year=1990|isbn=|location=Englewood Cliffs|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Thinking clearly about psychology|last=Wiggins|first=J. S.|publisher=University of Minnesota Press|year=1991|isbn=|editor-last=W. Grove &amp; D. Cicchetti|editor-first=|location=Minneapolis|pages=|chapter=Agency and communion as conceptual coordinates for the understanding and measurement of interpersonal behavior}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some organizational research has found different variations of collectivism. These include institutional collectivism and in-group collectivism. Institutional collectivism is the idea that a work environment creates a sense of collectivist nature due to similar statuses and similar rewards, such as earning the same salary. In-group collectivism is the idea that an individual's chosen group of people, such as family or friend groups, create a sense of collectivist nature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/culture-leadership-and-organizations/book226013|title=Culture, Leadership, and Organizations|last1=House|first1=Robert J.|last2=Hanges|first2=Paul J.|last3=Javidan|first3=Mansour|last4=Dorfman|first4=Peter W.|last5=Gupta|first5=Vipin|date=2004|publisher=Sage Publications, Inc.|page=12}}&lt;/ref&gt; In-group collectivism can be referred to as family collectivism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Brewer|first1=Paul|last2=Venaik|first2=Sunil|date=April 2011|title=Individualism-Collectivism in Hofstede and GLOBE|journal= Journal of International Business Studies|volume=42|issue=3|pages=436–445|doi=10.1057/jibs.2010.62|jstor=29789431}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Macro-level effects ==
Cultural views are believed to have a reciprocal relationship with macro-level processes such as economics, social change, and politics.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Culture Shift in Advanced Industrial Society|last=Inglehart|first=R.|publisher=Princeton University Press|year=1990|isbn=|location=Princeton|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Modernization and Postmodernization: Cultural, Economic, and Political Change in 43 Societies|last=Inglehart|first=R.|publisher=Princeton University Press|year=1997|isbn=|location=Princeton|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Societal changes in the [[People's Republic of China]] exemplifies this well. Beginning in the early 1980s, China experienced dramatic expansion of economic and social structures, resulting in greater income inequality between families, less involvement of the government in social welfare programs, and increased competition for employment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Transforming China: Economic reform and its political implications|last=Zhang|first=W. W.|publisher=St. Martin's Press|year=2000|isbn=|location=New York|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Corresponding with these changes was a shift in ideology among Chinese citizens, especially among those who were younger, away from collectivism (the prevailing cultural ideology) toward individualism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Cai, X., &amp; Wu, P.|date=1999|title=A study of the modernity of social concept of younger students in China|url=http://en.cnki.com.cn/Article_en/CJFDTOTAL-XLKX199902013.htm|journal=Psychological Science |volume=22|pages=148–152|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Huang|first=M.|date=1999|title=A comparative study of the value outlook of Chinese adolescent students|url=|journal=Journal of Southwest China Normal University (Philosophy and Social Sciences)|volume=25|pages=83–88|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; China also saw this shift reflected in educational policies, such that teachers were encouraged to promote the development of their students’ individual opinions and self-efficacy, which prior to the aforementioned economic changes, was not emphasized in Chinese culture.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Xu, X., &amp; Peng, L.|date=2001|title=Reflection on parents' educational beliefs in the new century|url=|journal=Theory and Practice of Education|volume=21|pages=62–63|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Yu, R.|date=2002|title=On the reform of elementary school education in China|url=|journal=Educational Exploration|volume=129|pages=56–57|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Attempts to study the association of collectivism and political views and behaviors has largely occurred at the aggregate national level. However, more isolated political movements have also adopted a collectivistic framework. For example, [[collectivist anarchism]] is a revolutionary&lt;ref name=&quot;Patsouras, Louis 2005. p. 54&quot;&gt;Patsouras, Louis. 2005. ''Marx in Context''. iUniverse. p. 54&lt;/ref&gt; [[anarchist]] doctrine that advocates the abolition of both the [[State (polity)|state]] and [[private property|private ownership]] of the [[means of production]]. It instead envisions the means of production being owned collectively and controlled and managed by the producers themselves.&lt;ref name=&quot;Patsouras, Louis 2005. p. 54&quot; /&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Collective guilt]]
* [[Collective identity]]
* [[Collective leadership]]
* [[Collective narcissism]]
* [[Collective responsibility]]
* [[Communitarianism]]
* [[Corporatism]]
* [[Cultural conservatism]]
* [[Enclosure]]
* [[Interdependence]]
* [[Nationalism]]
* [[Social solidarity]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{Conformity}}

{{authority control}}
[[Category:Collectivism| ]]
[[Category:Political theories]]</text>
      <sha1>eoky1pestnj99zza9b9d1cquvwgmogk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
