  <page>
    <title>Call of Cthulhu (role-playing game)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5722</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937099847</id>
      <parentid>932738853</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-22T23:20:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BOZ</username>
        <id>861759</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Early releases */ link</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=January 2018}}
{{italic title}}
{{Infobox game
|title=''Call of Cthulhu''
|image=[[File:Call of Cthulhu RPG 1st ed 1981.jpg]]
|caption=''Call of Cthulhu'' 1st edition box cover, 1981.&lt;br&gt;Illustration by [[Gene Day]].
|designer=[[Sandy Petersen]]
|publisher=[[Chaosium]]
|date=1981
|genre=Horror
|system=[[Basic Role-Playing]] (adaptations into other systems also available)
}}
'''''Call of Cthulhu''''' is a [[horror fiction]] [[role-playing game]] based on [[H. P. Lovecraft]]'s [[The Call of Cthulhu|story of the same name]] and the associated [[Cthulhu Mythos]].&lt;ref name=&quot;HG&quot;&gt;{{Cite book | contribution=Call of Cthulhu | title=Hobby Games: The 100 Best | last=Cook | first=Monte | authorlink=Monte Cook | editor-last=Lowder | editor-first=James | editor-link=James Lowder | publisher=[[Green Ronin Publishing]] | year=2007 | pages=42–45 | isbn=978-1-932442-96-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; The game, often abbreviated as ''CoC'', is published by [[Chaosium]]; it was first released in 1981 and is currently in its seventh edition, with many different versions released. It makes use of Chaosium's [[Basic Role-Playing]] (BRP) system, with special rules for Sanity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Petersen|first1=Sandy|last2=Willis|first2=Lynn|title=Game Info: Call of Cthulhu|url=http://index.rpg.net/display-entry.phtml?mainid=20|website=RPG.net|publisher=Skotos Tech, Inc.|accessdate=March 29, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Gameplay==
The setting of ''Call of Cthulhu'' is a [[Dark fantasy|darker]] version of our world, based on H. P. Lovecraft's observation (from his essay, &quot;[[Supernatural Horror in Literature]]&quot;) that &quot;The oldest and strongest emotion of mankind is fear, and the strongest kind of fear is fear of the unknown.&quot; The original game, first published in 1981, uses mechanics from [[Basic Role-Playing]], and is set in the 1920s, the setting of many of Lovecraft's stories. Additional settings were developed in the ''[[Cthulhu by Gaslight]]'' supplement, a blend of occult and [[Sherlock Holmes|Holmesian]] mystery and mostly set in England during the 1890s, and modern/1980s conspiracy with ''[[Cthulhu Now]]'' and ''[[Delta Green]]''. More recent additions include 1000 AD (''Cthulhu: Dark Ages''), 23rd century (''Cthulhu Rising'') and Ancient Roman times (''Cthulhu Invictus''). The protagonists may also travel to places that are not of this earth, represented in the Dreamlands (which can be accessed through dreams as well as being physically connected to the earth), to other planets, or into the voids of space. In keeping with the Lovecraftian theme, the [[gamemaster]] is called the Keeper of Arcane Lore, or simply the keeper, while [[player character]]s are called &quot;investigators&quot;.

''CoC'' uses the [[Basic Role-Playing]] system first developed for ''[[RuneQuest]]'' and used in other Chaosium games. It is skill-based, with player characters getting better with their skills by succeeding at using them for as long as they stay functionally healthy and sane. They do not, however, gain hit points and do not become significantly harder to kill. The game does not use [[Experience point#Level-based progression|level]]s. 

''CoC'' uses percentile dice (with a results ranging from 1 to 100) to determine success or failure. Every player statistic is intended to be compatible with the notion that there is a probability of success for a particular action given what the player is capable of doing. For example, an artist may have a 75% chance of being able to draw something (represented by having 75 in Art skill), and thus rolling a number under 75 would yield a success. Rolling {{fract|1|5}} or less of the skill level (1-15 in the example) would be a &quot;special success&quot; (or an &quot;impale&quot; for combat skills) and would yield some extra bonus to be determined by the keeper. For example, the artist character might draw especially well or especially fast, or catch some unapparent detail in the drawing.

The players take the roles of ordinary people drawn into the realm of the mysterious: detectives, criminals, scholars, artists, war veterans, etc. Often, happenings begin innocently enough, until more and more of the workings behind the scenes are revealed. As the characters learn more of the true horrors of the world and the irrelevance of humanity, their sanity (represented by &quot;Sanity Points&quot;, abbreviated SAN) inevitably withers away. The game includes a mechanism for determining how damaged a character's sanity is at any given point; encountering the horrific beings usually triggers a loss of SAN points. To gain the tools they need to defeat the horrors – mystic knowledge and magic – the characters may end up losing some of their sanity, though other means such as pure firepower or simply outsmarting one's opponents also exist. ''CoC'' has a reputation as a game in which it is quite common for a player character to die in gruesome circumstances or end up in a mental institution. Eventual triumph of the players is not assumed.

==History==
The original conception of ''Call of Cthulhu'' was ''Dark Worlds'', a game commissioned by the publisher Chaosium but never published. [[Sandy Petersen]] contacted them regarding writing a supplement for their popular fantasy game ''[[RuneQuest]]'' set in Lovecraft's [[Dreamlands]]. He took over the writing of ''Call of Cthulhu'', and the game was released in 1981.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| last =Turnbull| first =Don| authorlink = | coauthors =  | title =Open Box: Call of Cthulhu| journal =[[White Dwarf (magazine)|White Dwarf]]| volume = | issue = 32| pages =18| publisher =[[Games Workshop]]|date=August 1982| issn = 0265-8712}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Editions===
Since Petersen's departure from Chaosium, continuing development of ''Call of Cthulhu'' passed to [[Lynn Willis]], credited as co-author in the fifth and sixth editions, and more recently to [[Paul Fricker]] and [[Mike Mason (game designer)|Mike Mason]]. The game system underwent only minor rules changes in its first six editions (between 1981 and 2011); the current seventh edition, released 2014, includes more significant rules alterations than in any previous release.&lt;ref name=&quot;Inside Call of Cthulhu 7th Edition&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://theunspeakableoath.com/home/?p=1024|title= Inside Call of Cthulhu 7th Edition| first=Shane | last=Ivey | authorlink=Shane Ivey | accessdate= January 25, 2013|date= July 24, 2012|publisher= The Unspeakable Oath}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! scope=&quot;col&quot; width=&quot;20%&quot; | Edition
! scope=&quot;col&quot; width=&quot;15%&quot; | Published
! scope=&quot;col&quot; width=&quot;20%&quot; | Format
! scope=&quot;col&quot; width=&quot;45%&quot; | Notes
|-
| 1st edition || 1981&lt;ref name=&quot;Original publication date&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=''Call of Cthulhu'' 20th Anniversary Edition|url=http://www.caliverbooks.com/Partizan%20Press/valk%20website/rv_CoC20.html|website=Valkyrie Quarterly|author1=Paul Maclean|accessdate=September 2, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; || Boxed set || Includes 16-page ''Basic Role-Playing'' booklet in addition to main rulebook.&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGGeek 1st Edition&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Call of Cthulhu (1st Edition)|url=https://rpggeek.com/rpg/347/call-cthulhu-1st-edition|website=RPGGeek.com|accessdate=September 1, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 2nd edition || 1983 || Boxed set || Includes a single rulebook; minor rules changes.&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGGeek 2nd Edition&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Call of Cthulhu (2nd Edition)|url=https://rpggeek.com/rpgitem/46421/call-cthulhu-2nd-edition|website=RPGGeek.com|accessdate=September 1, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 3rd edition|| 1986 || Boxed set || Divides rules into separate ''Investigator's Book'' and ''Keeper's Book'' booklets.&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGGeek 3rd Edition&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Call of Cthulhu (3rd Edition)|url=https://rpggeek.com/rpgitem/46419/call-cthulhu-3rd-edition|website=RPGGeek.com|accessdate=September 1, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 4th edition || 1989 || Softcover || Includes content from the ''Cthulhu Companion'' and ''[[Fragments of Fear: The Second Cthulhu Companion]]'' supplements.&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGGeek 4th Edition&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Call of Cthulhu (4th Edition)|url=https://rpggeek.com/rpgitem/46424/call-cthulhu-4th-edition|website=RPGGeek.com|accessdate=September 1, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 5th edition || 1992 || Softcover || First version to credit [[Lynn Willis]] as co-author.&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGGeek 5th Edition&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Call of Cthulhu (5th Edition)|url=https://rpggeek.com/rpgitem/44055/call-cthulhu-5th-edition|website=RPGGeek.com|accessdate=September 1, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| Edition 5.5 || 1998 || Softcover || Reorganized and updated version of the 5th edition, with new cover art; &quot;Edition 5.5&quot; designator appears on title page.&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGGeek 5th Edition&quot;/&gt;
|-
| 20th Anniversary Edition || 2001 || Leather-bound hardcover book || Limited edition bound in green leather, with new &quot;ancient tome&quot; layout.&lt;ref name=&quot;20th Anniversary Edition catalogue page&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=20th Anniversary Edition Call Of Cthulhu RPG|url=http://www.chaosium.com/cthulhu/rpg/2399.shtml|website=Chaosium.com|publisher=Chaosium|accessdate=September 12, 2015|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20011020105443/http://www.chaosium.com/cthulhu/rpg/2399.shtml|archivedate=October 20, 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGGeek 6th Edition/20th Anniversary&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Call of Cthulhu (6th Edition/20th Anniversary releases)|url=https://rpggeek.com/rpgitem/53224/call-cthulhu-6th-edition20th-anniversary-releases|website=RPGGeek.com|accessdate=September 1, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 6th edition || 2004 || Hardcover, softcover, or [[PDF]] file || Same layout and content as 20th Anniversary Edition.&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGGeek 6th Edition&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Call of Cthulhu (6th Edition)|url=https://rpggeek.com/rpgitem/43842/call-cthulhu-6th-edition|website=RPGGeek.com|accessdate=September 1, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 7th edition || 2014|| Hardcover, softcover, or electronic file || Rules significantly revised by [[Paul Fricker]] and [[Mike Mason (game designer)|Mike Mason]]. New cover art and full-color layout. Print version released spring 2016.&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGGeek 7th Edition&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Call of Cthulhu (7th Edition)|url=https://rpggeek.com/rpg/23113/call-cthulhu-7th-edition|website=RPGGeek.com|accessdate=September 1, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

===Early releases===
For those grounded in the RPG tradition, the very first release of ''Call of Cthulhu'' created a brand new framework for table-top gaming. Rather than the traditional format established by ''[[Dungeons &amp; Dragons]]'', which often involved the characters wandering through caves or tunnels and fighting different types of monsters, Sandy Petersen introduced the concept of the ''Onion Skin'': Interlocking layers of information and nested clues that lead the player characters from seemingly minor investigations into a missing person to discovering mind-numbingly awful, global conspiracies to destroy the world. Unlike its predecessor games, ''CoC'' assumed that most investigators would not survive, alive or sane, and that the only safe way to deal with the vast majority of nasty things described in the rule books was to run away. A well-run ''CoC'' campaign should engender a sense of foreboding and inevitable doom in its players. The style and setting of the game, in a relatively modern time period, created an emphasis on real-life settings, character research, and thinking one's way around trouble.

The first book of ''Call of Cthulhu'' adventures was ''[[Shadows of Yog-Sothoth]]''. In this work, the characters come upon a secret society's foul plot to destroy mankind, and pursue it first near to home and then in a series of exotic locations. This template was to be followed in many subsequent campaigns, including ''Fungi from Yuggoth'' (later known as ''Curse of Cthulhu'' and ''Day of the Beast''), ''Spawn of Azathoth'', and possibly the most highly acclaimed, ''[[Masks of Nyarlathotep]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal  | last =Frances  | first =Phil  | authorlink =  | coauthors =  | title =Open Box: Dungeon Modules  | format =  | journal =[[White Dwarf (magazine)|White Dwarf]]  | volume =  | issue = 71  | pages =7–8  | publisher =[[Games Workshop]]  |date=November 1985  | url =  | issn =0265-8712  | accessdate =  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Shadows of Yog-Sothoth'' is important not only because it represents the first published addition to the boxed first edition of ''Call of Cthulhu'', but because its format defined a new way of approaching a campaign of linked RPG scenarios involving actual clues for the would-be detectives amongst the players to follow and link in order to uncover the dastardly plots afoot. Its format has been used by every other campaign-length ''Call of Cthulhu'' publication. The standard of ''CoC'' scenarios was well received by independent reviewers. ''The Asylum and Other Tales'', a series of stand alone articles released in 1983, rated an overall 9/10 in Issue 47 of ''[[White Dwarf (magazine)|White Dwarf]]'' magazine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal  | last =Sutherland  | first =Jon  | authorlink =  | coauthors =  | title =Open Box: Dungeon Modules  | format =  | journal =[[White Dwarf (magazine)|White Dwarf]]  | volume =  | issue = 47  | pages =14  | publisher =[[Games Workshop]]  |date=November 1983  | url =  | issn =0265-8712  | accessdate =  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The standard of the included 'clue' material varies from scenario to scenario, but reached its zenith in the original boxed versions of the ''[[Masks of Nyarlathotep]]'' and ''[[Horror on the Orient Express]]'' campaigns. Inside these one could find matchbooks and business cards apparently defaced by non-player characters, newspaper cuttings and (in the case of ''Orient Express'') period passports to which players could attach their photographs, increasing the sense of immersion. Indeed, during the period that these supplements were produced, third party campaign publishers strove to emulate the quality of the additional materials, often offering separately-priced 'deluxe' clue packages for their campaigns.

Additional milieux were provided by Chaosium with the release of ''[[H.P. Lovecraft's Dreamlands|Dreamlands]]'', a boxed supplement containing additional rules needed for playing within the Lovecraft Dreamlands, a large map and a scenario booklet, and ''Cthulhu By Gaslight'', another boxed set which moved the action from the 1920s to the 1890s.

===Supplement campaigns===
* ''[[Shadows of Yog-Sothoth]]'', 1982
* ''Fungi from Yuggoth'', 1984
* ''[[Masks of Nyarlathotep]]'', 1984
* ''Spawn of Azathoth'', 1986
* ''Horror on the Orient Express'', 1991
* ''Beyond the Mountains of Madness'', 1999

===''Cthulhu Now''===
In 1987, Chaosium issued the supplement titled ''[[Cthulhu Now]]'', a collection of rules, supplemental source materials and scenarios for playing ''Call of Cthulhu'' in the present day. This proved to be a very popular alternative milieu, so much so that much of the supplemental material is now included in the core rule book.

===''Delta Green''===
{{main|Delta Green}}
[[Pagan Publishing]] released ''Delta Green'', a series of supplements originally set in the 1990s, although later supplements add support for playing closer to the present day. In these, player characters are agents of a secret agency known as Delta Green, which fights against creatures from the Mythos and conspiracies related to them. [[Arc Dream Publishing]] released a new version of ''Delta Green'' in 2016 as a standalone game, partially using the mechanics from ''Call of Cthulhu''.

===''Lovecraft Country''===
{{Main|Lovecraft Country#Roleplaying games}}

''Lovecraft Country'' was a line of supplements for ''Call of Cthulhu'' released in 1990. These supplements were overseen by [[Keith Herber]] and provided backgrounds and adventures set in Lovecraft's fictional towns of [[Arkham]], [[Kingsport (Lovecraft)|Kingsport]], [[Innsmouth]], [[Dunwich (Lovecraft)|Dunwich]], and their environs. The intent was to give investigators a common base, as well as to center the action on well-drawn characters with clear motivations.

===Recent history===
In the years since the collapse of the ''Mythos'' collectible card game (production ceased in 1997), the release of ''CoC'' books has been very sporadic with up to a year between releases. Chaosium struggled with near bankruptcy for many years before finally starting their upward climb again.

2005 was Chaosium's busiest year for many years with ten releases for the game. Chaosium took to marketing &quot;monographs&quot;—short books by individual writers with editing and layout provided out-of-house—directly to the consumer, allowing the company to gauge market response to possible new works. The range of times and places in which the horrors of the Mythos can be encountered was also expanded in late 2005 onwards with the addition of ''Cthulhu Dark Ages'' by Stéphane Gesbert, which gives a framework for playing games set in 11th century Europe, ''Secrets of Japan'' by Michael Dziesinski for gaming in modern-day Japan, and ''Secrets of Kenya'' by [[David Conyers]] for gaming in interwar period Africa.

In July 2011, Chaosium announced it would re-release a 30th anniversary edition of the ''CoC'' 6th edition role-playing game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.chaosium.com/article.php?story_id=487|title=Taking Preorders: Call of Cthulhu 30th Anniversary Edition|work=Chaosium.com|accessdate=July 16, 2011|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110730140218/http://www.chaosium.com/article.php?story_id=487|archivedate=July 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; This 320-page book features thick (3&amp;nbsp;mm) leatherette hardcovers with the front cover and spine stamped with gold foil. The interior pages are printed in black ink, on 90 gsm matte art paper. The binding is thread sewn, square backed. Chaosium offered a one-time printing of this Collector's Edition.

On May 28, 2013, a [[crowdfunding]] campaign on [[Kickstarter]] for the 7th Edition of ''Call of Cthulhu'' was launched with a goal of $40,000; it ended on June 29 of the same year having collected $561,836.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kickstarter.com/projects/448333182/call-of-cthulhu-7th-edition]&lt;/ref&gt; It included many more major revisions than any previous edition, and also split the core rules into two books, a Player's Guide and Keeper's Guide.&lt;ref name=&quot;Inside Call of Cthulhu 7th Edition&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGGeek 7th Edition&quot; /&gt; Problems and delays fulfilling the [[Kickstarter]]s for the 7th edition of ''Call of Cthulhu'' led Greg Stafford and Sandy Petersen (who had both left in 1998) to return to an active role at Chaosium in June 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/448333182/call-of-cthulhu-7th-edition/posts/1251694|title=Call of Cthulhu 7th Edition|website=Kickstarter|accessdate=June 11, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Licenses==
Chaosium has licensed other publishers to create supplements using their rule system, notably including ''[[Delta Green]]'' by [[Pagan Publishing]].  Other licensees have included Infogrames, Miskatonic River Press, Theater of the Mind Enterprises, Triad Entertainment, [[Games Workshop]],&lt;ref&gt;Games Workshop was active with Chaosium from 1983 to 1987, mostly publishing the BRP games in hardback bookform but producing some material, notably ''Green and Pleasant Land'' (1987) by [[Marc Gascoigne]], [[Bryan Ansell]] and others&lt;/ref&gt; [[Fantasy Flight Games]], [[RAFM Company, Inc.|RAFM]], [[Goodman Games]], [[Grenadier Models Inc.]] and Yog-Sothoth.com. These supplements may be set in different time frames or even different game universes from the original game.

===''Shadow of the Comet''===
{{main|Shadow of the Comet}}

''Shadow of the Comet'' (later repackaged as ''Call of Cthulhu: Shadow of the Comet'') is an [[adventure game]] developed and released by [[Infogrames]] in 1993. The game is based on [[H. P. Lovecraft]]'s [[Cthulhu Mythos]] and uses many elements from Lovecraft's ''[[The Dunwich Horror]]'' and ''[[The Shadow Over Innsmouth]]''. A follow-up game, ''[[Prisoner of Ice]]'', is not a direct sequel.

===''Prisoner of Ice''===
{{main|Prisoner of Ice}}

''Prisoner of Ice'' (also ''Call of Cthulhu: Prisoner of Ice'') is an [[adventure game]] developed and released by [[Infogrames]] for the PC and [[Macintosh]] computers in 1995 in America and Europe. It is based on [[H. P. Lovecraft]]'s [[Cthulhu Mythos]], particularly ''[[At the Mountains of Madness]]'', and is a follow-up to Infogrames' earlier ''[[Shadow of the Comet]]''. In 1997, the game was ported to the [[Sega Saturn]] and [[PlayStation (console)|PlayStation]] exclusively in Japan.

===''d20 Call of Cthulhu''===
In 2001, a stand-alone version of ''Call of Cthulhu'' was released by [[Wizards of the Coast]], for the [[d20 system]]. Intended to preserve the feeling of the original game, the d20 conversion of the game rules were supposed to make the game more accessible to the large ''D&amp;amp;D'' player base. The d20 system also made it possible to use ''[[Dungeons &amp; Dragons]]'' characters in ''Call of Cthulhu'', as well as to introduce the Cthulhu Mythos into ''Dungeons &amp; Dragons'' games. The d20 version of the game is no longer supported by Wizards as per their contract with Chaosium.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.yog-sothoth.com/articles.html/_/main/news-archive/wizards-d20-cthulhu-forum-to-close-r1090 |title=Wizards' d20 Cthulhu Forum to Close |accessdate=March 28, 2016 |date=November 18, 2003 |publisher=Yog-Sothoth.com }}{{Dead link|date=October 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; Chaosium included d20 stats as an appendix in three releases (see [[Lovecraft Country]]), but have since dropped the &quot;dual stat&quot; idea.

===''Dark Corners of the Earth''===
{{main|Call of Cthulhu: Dark Corners of the Earth}}

A licensed&lt;ref&gt;[http://uk.ign.com/articles/2000/02/09/call-of-cthulhu-dark-corners-of-the-earth-interview Call of Cthulhu: Dark Corners of the Earth Interview], IGN, February 8, 2000&lt;/ref&gt; first-person shooter adventure game by [[Headfirst Productions]], based on ''Call of Cthulhu'' campaign ''Escape from Innsmouth'' and released by [[Bethesda Softworks]] in 2005/2006 for the PC and [[Xbox (console)|Xbox]].

===''Trail of Cthulhu''===
{{main|Trail of Cthulhu}}

In February 2008, [[Pelgrane Press]] published ''Trail of Cthulhu'', a stand-alone game created by [[Kenneth Hite]] using the [[GUMSHOE System]] developed by [[Robin Laws]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pelgranepress.com/gumshoe/trail.html|title=The Trail of Cthulhu|accessdate=August 17, 2007|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110715062411/http://pelgranepress.com/gumshoe/trail.html|archivedate=July 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Trail of Cthulhu''{{'}}s system is more mystery oriented and focuses mostly on interpreting clues.

===''Shadows of Cthulhu''===
In September 2008, Reality Deviant Publications published ''Shadows of Cthulhu'', a supplement that brings Lovecraftian gaming to [[Green Ronin]]'s [[True20]] system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rpgobjects.com/index.php?c=news&amp;news_id=437|title=Shadows of Cthulhu is now on sale!|accessdate=September 16, 2008|author=david jarvis|date=September 15, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Realms of Cthulhu''===
In October 2009, Reality Blurs published ''Realms of Cthulhu'', a supplement for [[Pinnacle Entertainment]]'s [[Savage Worlds]] system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://realityblurs.com/wordpress/?page_id=911|title=Realms of Cthulhu|accessdate=January 30, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''The Laundry''===
In 2010, [[Cubicle 7]] published an official [[role-playing game]], ''[[The Laundry (role-playing game)|The Laundry]]''&lt;ref&gt;2010, {{ISBN|1-907204-93-8}}, [[Gareth Hanrahan]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.antipope.org/charlie/blog-static/2010/12/top-secret.html
| title = A message from our sponsors
| accessdate = June 13, 2011
| last = Stross
| first = Charles
| date = December 12, 2010
| work = Charlie's Diary
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.ukroleplayers.com/latest-news/charles-stross-the-laundry-files-rpg-announced
| title = Charles Stross' &quot;The Laundry Files&quot; RPG Announced
| accessdate = June 13, 2011
| author = [http://www.ukroleplayers.com UK Roleplayers]
| date = March 10, 2010
| archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20110727144521/http://www.ukroleplayers.com/latest-news/charles-stross-the-laundry-files-rpg-announced/
| archive-date = July 27, 2011
| url-status = dead
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a number of supplements, all based on [[Charles Stross]]'s &quot;[[The Laundry Files|Laundry Files]]&quot; series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://shop.cubicle7store.com/epages/es113347.sf/en_GB/?ObjectPath=/Shops/es113347_shop/Categories/The_Laundry
| title = The Laundry – Cubicle 7 Entertainment Web Store
| accessdate = June 13, 2011
| author = [http://www.cubicle7.co.uk/ Cubicle 7]
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''The Wasted Land''===
{{main|Call of Cthulhu: The Wasted Land}}

In April 2011, Chaosium and new developer Red Wasp Design announced a joint project to produce a mobile video game based on the ''Call of Cthulhu'' RPG, entitled ''Call of Cthulhu: The Wasted Land''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chaosium.com/article.php?story_id=493|title=Call of Cthulhu Coming to Mobile|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110517053529/http://www.chaosium.com/article.php?story_id=493|archivedate=May 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://redwaspdesign.wordpress.com/call-of-cthulhu/|title=Call of Cthulhu The Wasted Land|accessdate=June 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The game was released on January 30, 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://redwaspdesign.wordpress.com/2012/01/30/the-stars-are-right-as-call-of-cthulhu-the-wasted-land-launches/|title=Call of Cthulhu The Wasted Land Launches|accessdate=February 7, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Cthulhu Chronicles''===
In 2018, Metarcade produced ''[[Cthulhu Chronicles]]'', a game for iOS with a campaign of nine mobile interactive fiction stories set in 1920s England based on ''Call of Cthulhu''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/cthulhu-chronicles/id1343328830|title=Apple Store: Cthulhu Chronicles|accessdate=July 10, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.metaarcade.com/cthulhu-chronicles|title=MetaArcade: Cthulhu Chronicles|accessdate=July 10, 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180711023030/https://www.metaarcade.com/cthulhu-chronicles|archive-date=July 11, 2018|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first five stories were released on July 10, 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://venturebeat.com/2018/07/10/metaarcade-launches-cthulhu-chronicles-horror-game-on-ios/|title=MetaArcade launches Cthulhu Chronicles horror game on iOS|accessdate=July 10, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Card games===
{{main|Mythos (card game)|Call of Cthulhu: The Card Game}}

''Mythos'' was a [[collectible card game]] (CCG) based on the Cthulhu Mythos that Chaosium produced and marketed during the mid-1990s. While generally praised for its fast gameplay and unique mechanics, it ultimately failed to gain a very large market presence. It bears mention because its eventual failure brought the company to hard times that affected its ability to produce material for ''Call of Cthulhu''. ''Call of Cthulhu: The Card Game'' is a second collectible card game, produced by [[Fantasy Flight Games]].

===Miniatures===
The first licensed ''Call of Cthulhu'' {{convert|25|mm|1|abbr=off|adj=mid}} gaming miniatures were sculpted by Andrew Chernack and released by Grenadier Models in boxed sets and blister packs in 1983. The license was later transferred to RAFM. As of 2011, RAFM still produce licensed C''all of Cthulhu'' models sculpted by Bob Murch. Both lines include investigator player character models and the iconic monsters of the Cthulhu mythos.
As of July 2015, Reaper Miniatures started its third &quot;[https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1513061270/reaper-miniatures-bones-3-the-search-for-mr-bones Bones Kickstarter]&quot;, a Kickstarter intended to help the company migrate some miniatures from metal to plastic, and introducing some new ones. Among the stretch goals was the second $50 expansion, devoted to the Mythos, with miniatures such as Cultists, Deep Ones, Mi'Go, and an extra $15 Shub-Niggurath &quot;miniature&quot; (it is, at least, 6x4 squares). It is expected for those miniatures to remain in the Reaper Miniatures catalogue after the Kickstarter project finishes.

===''The Official Video Game''===
{{main|Call of Cthulhu: The Official Video Game}}

'''''Call of Cthulhu: The Official Video Game''''' is a [[survival horror]] [[role-playing video game]] developed by [[Cyanide (company)|Cyanide]] and published by [[Focus Home Interactive]] for [[PlayStation 4]], [[Xbox One]] and [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]]. The game features a [[Open world|semi-open world]] environment and incorporates themes of [[Lovecraftian horror|Lovecraftian]] and [[psychological horror]] into a story which includes elements of investigation and [[Stealth game|stealth]]. It is inspired by [[H. P. Lovecraft]]'s short story &quot;[[The Call of Cthulhu]]&quot;.

==Reception==
Several reviews of various editions appeared in ''[[The Space Gamer|Space Gamer/Fantasy Gamer]]''. 
* In the March 1982 edition (No. 49), William A. Barton noted that there were some shortcomings resulting from an assumption by the designers that players would have access to rules from ''[[RuneQuest]]'' that were not in ''Call of Cthulhu'', but otherwise Barton called the game &quot;an excellent piece of work.... The worlds of H. P. Lovecraft are truly open for the fantasy gamer.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SG49&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Barton |first=William A. |date=March 1982 |title=Featured Review: Call of Cthulhu|journal=[[The Space Gamer]]|publisher=[[Steve Jackson Games]]|issue=49|pages=4-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* In the October–November 1987 edition (No. 80), Lisa Cohen reviewed the 3rd edition, saying, &quot;&quot;This book can be for collectors of art, players, or anyone interested in knowledge about old time occult. It is the one reprint that is worth the money.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SG80&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Cohen |first=Lisa |date=October–November 1987 |title=Call of Cthulhu|journal=[[The Space Gamer|Space Gamer/Fantasy Gamer]]|publisher=[[Diverse Talents, Incorporated]]|issue=80|pages=40}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several reviews of various editions appeared in ''[[White Dwarf (magazine)|White Dwarf]]''.
* In the August 1982 edition (Issue 32), Ian Bailey admired much about the first edition of the game; his only criticism was that the game was too &quot;U.S. orientated and consequently any Keeper... who wants to set his game in the UK will have a lot of research to do.&quot; Bailey gave the game an above average rating of 9 out of 10, saying, &quot;''Call of Cthulhu'' is an excellent game and a welcome addition to the world of role-playing.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;wd32&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Bailey|first=Ian |date=August 1982 |title=Open Box|journal=[[White Dwarf (magazine)|White Dwarf]]|publisher=[[Games Workshop]]|issue=32|pages=18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In the August 1986 edition (Issue 80), Ashley Shepherd thought the inclusion of much material in the 3rd edition that had been previously published as supplementary books &quot;makes the game incredibly good value.&quot; He concluded, &quot;This package is going to keep ''Call of Cthulhu'' at the front of the fantasy game genre.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;wd80&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Shepherd|first=Ashley |date=August 1986 |title=Open Box|journal=[[White Dwarf (magazine)|White Dwarf]]|publisher=[[Games Workshop]]|issue=80|pages=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;    

Several reviews of various editions and supplements also appeared in ''[[Dragon (magazine)|Dragon]]''. 
* In the May 1982 edition (Issue 61), [[David Cook (game designer)|David Cook]] thought the rules were too complex for new gamers, but said, &quot;It is a good game for experienced role-playing gamers and ambitious judges, especially if they like Lovecraft’s type of story.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dragon #61&quot;&gt;{{cite journal| last = Cook| first = David| authorlink = David Cook (game designer)| title = The Dragon's Augury| journal = [[Dragon (magazine)|Dragon]]| issue = #61| page = 70-71| publisher = [[TSR, Inc.|TSR]]| location = [[Lake Geneva, Wisconsin]]| date = May 1982}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In the August 1987 edition (Issue 124), [[Ken Rolston]] reviewed the ''Terror Australis'' supplement for 3rd edition that introduced an Australian setting in the 1920s. Bambra thought that &quot;Literate, macabre doom shambles from each page. Good reading, and a good campaign setting for COC adventures.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dragon124&quot;&gt;{{cite journal| last = Rolston| first = Ken| authorlink = Ken Rolston| title = Roleplaying Review| journal = [[Dragon (magazine)|Dragon]]| issue = #124| page = 14| publisher = [[TSR, Inc.|TSR]]| location = [[Lake Geneva, Wisconsin]]| date = August 1987}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In the October 1988 edition (Issue 138), Ken Rolston gave an overview of the 3rd edition, and placed it ahead of its competitors due to superior campaign setting, tone and atmosphere, the player characters as investigators, and the use of realistic player handouts such as authentic-looking newspaper clippings. Rolston concluded, &quot;''CoC'' is one of role-playing’s acknowledged classics. Its various supplements over the years have maintained an exceptional level of quality; several, including ''Shadows of Yog-Sothoth'' and ''Masks of Nyarlathotep'', deserve consideration among the greatest pinnacles of the fantasy role-playing game design.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dragon138&quot;&gt;{{cite journal| last = Rolston| first = Ken| authorlink = Ken Rolston| title = Roleplaying Reviews| journal = [[Dragon (magazine)|Dragon]]| issue = #138| page = 78-79| publisher = [[TSR, Inc.|TSR]]| location = [[Lake Geneva, Wisconsin]]| date = October 1988}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In the June 1990 edition (Issue 158), [[Jim Bambra]] liked the updated setting of the 4th edition, placing the game firmly in Lovecraft's 1920s. He also liked the number of adventures included in the 192-page rulebook: &quot;The fourth edition contains enough adventures to keep any group happily entertained and sanity blasted.&quot; However, while Cook questioned whether owners of the 2nd or 3rd edition would get good value for their money — &quot;You lack only the car-chase rules and the improved layout of the three books in one. The rest of the material has received minor editing but no substantial changes&quot; — Cook strongly recommended the new edition to newcomers, saying, &quot;If you don’t already play ''CoC'', all I can do is urge you to give it a try.... discover for yourself why it has made so many converts since its release.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dragon158&quot;&gt;{{cite journal| last = Bambra| first = Jim| authorlink = Jim Bambra| title = Roleplaying Reviews| journal = [[Dragon (magazine)|Dragon]]| issue = #158| page = 82-88| publisher = [[TSR, Inc.|TSR]]| location = [[Lake Geneva, Wisconsin]]| date = June 1990}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In the October 1992 edition (Issue 186), [[Rick Swan]] admitted that he was skeptical that the 5th edition would offer anything new, but instead found that the new edition benefited from &quot;fresh material, judicious editing, and thorough polishes.&quot; He concluded, &quot;Few RPGs exceed the ''CoC'' game’s scope or match its skillful integration of background and game systems. And there’s no game more fun.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dragon186&quot;&gt;{{cite journal| last = Swan| first = Rick| authorlink = Rick Swan| title = Roleplaying Reviews II| journal = [[Dragon (magazine)|Dragon]]| issue = #186| page = 96-97| publisher = [[TSR, Inc.|TSR]]| location = [[Lake Geneva, Wisconsin]]| date = October 1992}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In a 1996 reader poll by ''Arcane'' magazine to determine the 50 most popular roleplaying games of all time, ''Call of Cthulhu'' was ranked 1st.  Editor Paul Pettengale commented: &quot;''Call of Cthulhu'' is fully deserved of the title as the most popular roleplaying system ever - it's a game that doesn't age, is eminently playable, and which hangs together perfectly. The system, even though it's over ten years old, it still one of the very best you'll find in any roleplaying game. Also, there's not a referee in the land who could say they've read every Lovecraft inspired book or story going, so there's a pretty-well endless supply of scenario ideas. It's simply marvellous.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Arcane14&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last= Pettengale|first=Paul|date= Christmas 1996 |title=Arcane Presents the Top 50 Roleplaying Games 1996|journal=Arcane|publisher=[[Future plc|Future Publishing]]|issue=14|pages=25-35}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards==
The game has won several major awards:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Chaosium Awards|url=http://www.chaosium.com/chaosium-awards/|publisher=Chaosium|accessdate=April 27, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1982, Origins Awards, ''Best Role Playing Game''
* 1981, Game Designer's Guild, ''Select Award''
* 1985, Games Day Award, ''Best Role Playing Game''
* 1986, Games Day Award, ''Best Contemporary Role Playing Game''
* 1987, Games Day Award, ''Best Other Role Playing Game''
* 1993, Leeds Wargame Club, ''Best Role Playing Game''
* 1994, Gamer's Choice Award, ''Hall of Fame''
* 1995, Origins Award, ''Hall of Fame''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.originsgamefair.com/awards/1995/list-of-winners| title=Origins Award Winners (1995)| publisher=Academy of Adventure Gaming Arts &amp; Design| accessdate=2007-11-01 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20080102044110/http://www.originsgamefair.com/awards/1995/list-of-winners  |archivedate = 2008-01-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2001, Origins Award, ''Best Graphic Presentation of a Book Product'' (for ''Call of Cthulhu'' 20th anniversary edition)
* 2003, GamingReport.com readers voted it as the number-one Gothic/Horror RPG

==See also==
{{portal|Novels}}
* ''[[Arkham Horror]]'' - a cooperative board game based on the Mythos.
* ''[[Cthulhu Live]]'' - a live action role-playing game version of ''Call of Cthulhu''.
* ''[[CthulhuTech]]'' - another role-playing game, conceived for a &quot;Cthulhu science-fiction setting&quot;.

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite journal | last=Lhomme | first=Tristan | title=Call of Cthulhu, la 5e édition américaine | journal=Casus Belli | issue=70 | pages=26 | date= July–August 1992}} Review {{in lang|fr}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
* [http://www.chaosium.com Chaosium]

{{Media based on H. P. Lovecraft works}}
{{The Call of Cthulhu}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Call Of Cthulhu (Role-Playing Game)}}
[[Category:American role-playing games]]
[[Category:Basic Role-Playing System]]
[[Category:Call of Cthulhu (role-playing game)| ]]
[[Category:Cthulhu Mythos games]]
[[Category:D20 System]]
[[Category:Horror role-playing games]]
[[Category:Origins Award winners]]
[[Category:Role-playing games based on novels]]
[[Category:Role-playing games introduced in 1981]]
[[Category:Sandy Petersen games]]</text>
      <sha1>bi9wpch1kzlbreefftxiidps68lftja</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
