  <page>
    <title>Çatalhöyük</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5765</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942648573</id>
      <parentid>941767563</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-25T23:50:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Hse643</username>
        <id>35273663</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rm a cat and alphabetized cat list.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Archaelogical site in Turkey}}
{{redirect-distinguish|Çatalhüyük|Çatalhüyük, Ceyhan}}
{{Infobox ancient site
 |name = Çatalhöyük
 |native_name = 
 |alternate_name = 
 |image = Çatalhöyük after the first excavations by James Mellaart and his team..jpg
 |image_size=300
 |alt = 
 |caption = Çatalhöyük after the first excavations
 |map_type = Near East#Turkey
 |map_alt = 
 |map_size = 300
 |relief=yes
 |coordinates = {{coord|37|40|00|N|32|49|41|E|display=inline,title}}
 |location = Küçükköy, [[Konya Province]], [[Turkey]]
 |region = [[Anatolia]]
 |type = Settlement
 |part_of = 
 |length = 
 |width = 
 |area = 
 |height = 
 |builder = 
 |material = 
 |built = Approximately 6700 BC 
 |abandoned = Approximately 5700 BC
 |epochs = [[Neolithic]] to [[Chalcolithic]]
 |cultures = 
 |dependency_of = 
 |occupants = 
 |event = 
 |excavations = 
 |archaeologists =
 |condition =
 |ownership =
 |management =
 |public_access = 
 |website = &lt;!-- {{http://catalhoyuk.com/|catalhoyuk.com}} --&gt;
 |notes = 
| designation1          = WHS
| designation1_offname  = Neolithic Site of Çatalhöyük
| designation1_date     = 2012 &lt;small&gt;(36th [[World Heritage Committee|session]])&lt;/small&gt;
| designation1_number   = [https://whc.unesco.org/en/list/1405 1405]
| designation1_criteria = iii, iv
| designation1_type     = Cultural
| designation1_free1name = State Party
| designation1_free1value = [[Turkey]]
| designation1_free2name = Region
| designation1_free2value = [[List of World Heritage Sites in Southern Europe|Europe and North America]] 
}}
[[File:Calibrated Carbon 14 dates for Çatalhöyük as of 2013.jpg|thumb|Calibrated Carbon 14 dates for Çatalhöyük as of 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Shukurov |first1=Anvar |last2=Sarson |first2=Graeme R. |last3=Gangal |first3=Kavita |title=The Near-Eastern Roots of the Neolithic in South Asia |journal=PLOS ONE |date=7 May 2014 |volume=9 |issue=5 |pages=Appendix S1 |doi=10.1371/journal.pone.0095714 |pmid=24806472 |language=en |issn=1932-6203|pmc=4012948 }}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
'''Çatalhöyük''' ({{IPA-tr|tʃaˈtaɫhœjyc}}; also ''Çatal Höyük'' and ''Çatal Hüyük''; from [[Turkish language|Turkish]] ''çatal'' &quot;fork&quot; + ''höyük'' &quot;[[tumulus]]&quot;) was a very large [[Neolithic]] and [[Chalcolithic]] [[proto-city]] settlement in southern [[Anatolia]], which existed from approximately 7100 BC to 5700 BC, and flourished around 7000 BC.&lt;ref name=Langer&gt;{{cite book | title = An Encyclopedia of World History | editor-last = Langer | editor-first = William L. | edition = 5th | publisher = Houghton Mifflin Company | location = Boston, MA | year = 1972 | isbn = 978-0-395-13592-1 | pages = [https://archive.org/details/encyclopediaworl00will/page/9 9] | url-access = registration | url = https://archive.org/details/encyclopediaworl00will/page/9 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2012, it was inscribed as a [[UNESCO]] [[World Heritage Site]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://whc.unesco.org/en/list/1405] Çatalhöyük entry on the UNESCO World Heritage List site&lt;/ref&gt;

Çatalhöyük is located overlooking the [[Konya Plain]], southeast of the present-day city of [[Konya]] (ancient [[Iconium]]) in [[Turkey]], approximately 140&amp;nbsp;km (87&amp;nbsp;mi) from the twin-coned volcano of [[Mount Hasan]]. The eastern settlement forms a mound which would have risen about 20&amp;nbsp;m (66&amp;nbsp;ft) above the plain at the time of the latest Neolithic occupation. There is also a smaller settlement mound to the west and a [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine]] settlement a few hundred meters to the east. The prehistoric mound settlements were abandoned before the [[Bronze Age]]. A channel of the [[Çarşamba River]] once flowed between the two mounds, and the settlement was built on [[alluvium|alluvial clay]] which may have been favorable for early [[agriculture]].

==Archaeology==
The site was first excavated by [[James Mellaart]] in 1958. He later led a team which further excavated there for four seasons between 1961 and 1965.&lt;ref&gt;J. Mellaart, Excavations at Çatal Hüyük, first preliminary report: 1961. Anatolian Studies, vol. 12, pp. 41–65, 1962&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;J. Mellaart, Excavations at Çatal Hüyük, second preliminary report: 1962. Anatolian Studies, vol. 13, pp. 43–103, 1963&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;J. Mellaart, Excavations at Çatal Hüyük, third preliminary report: 1963. Anatolian Studies, vol. 14, pp. 39–119, 1964&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;J. Mellaart, Excavations at Çatal Hüyük, fourth preliminary report: at 1965. Anatolian Studies, vol. 16, pp. 15–191, 1966&lt;/ref&gt; These excavations revealed this section of [[Anatolia]] as a centre of advanced culture in the [[Neolithic]] period.&lt;ref name=gard&gt;{{cite book | first = Fred S. | last = Kleiner |author2=Mamiya, Christin J.  | year = 2006 | title = Gardner's Art Through the Ages: The Western Perspective: Volume 1 | edition = Twelfth | publisher = Wadsworth Publishing | location = Belmont, California | isbn = 978-0-495-00479-0 | pages = 12–4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Excavation revealed 18 successive layers of buildings signifying various stages of the settlement and eras of history. The bottom layer of buildings can be dated as early as 7100 BC while the top layer is of 5600 BC.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/antiquity/article/tale-of-two-tells-dating-the-catalhoyuk-west-mound/01F804089ECB6CC4AA6E47D452E3B9D1/core-reader] David Orton et al., A tale of two tells: dating the Çatalhöyük West Mound, Antiquity, vol. 92, iss. 363, pp. 620-639, June 2018&lt;/ref&gt;

Mellaart was banned from Turkey for his involvement in the [[Dorak affair]] in which he published drawings of supposedly important Bronze Age artifacts that later went missing.&lt;ref&gt;Kenneth Pearson and Patricia Connor, The Dorak affair, New York, Atheneum, 1968&lt;/ref&gt; After this scandal, the site lay idle until 1993, when investigations began under the leadership of [[Ian Hodder]], then at the [[University of Cambridge]].&lt;ref&gt;I. Hodder, Çatalhöyük, Anatolian Archaeology, vol. 4, pp. 8–10, 1998&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;I. Hodder, Getting to the Bottom of Thing: Çatalhöyük 1999, Anatolian Archaeology, vol. 5, pp. 4–7, 1999&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;I. Hodder, Çatalhöyük, Anatolian Archaeology, vol. 8, pp. 5–7, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;I. Hodder, A New Phase of Excavation at Çatalhöyük, Anatolian Archaeology, vol. 9, pp. 9–11, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catalhoyuk.com/sites/default/files/media/pdf/Archive_Report_2008.pdf] Çatalhöyük: Excavations of a Neolithic Anatolian Höyük - Çatalhöyük Archive Report 2008&lt;/ref&gt; These investigations are among the most ambitious excavation projects currently in progress according to archaeologist [[Colin Renfrew]], among others.{{cn |date=March 2019 }}{{Update-inline |date=March 2019 }} In addition to extensive use of [[archaeological science]], psychological and artistic interpretations of the [[symbol]]ism of the [[Wall painting in Turkey|wall paintings]] have been employed. Hodder, a former student of Mellaart, chose the site as the first &quot;real world&quot; test of his then-controversial theory of [[post-processual archaeology]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.11141/ia.42.7 | issue=42 | title=Analog to Digital: Transitions in Theory and Practice in Archaeological Photography at Çatalhöyük | year=2016 | journal=Internet Archaeology | last1 = Morgan | first1 = Colleen | last2 = University | url=http://eprints.whiterose.ac.uk/107945/1/Internet_Archaeology_final.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt; The site has always had a strong research emphasis upon engagement with digital methodologies, driven by the project's experimental and reflexive methodological framework.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.11141/ia.47.1 | issue=47 | title='The Rise of the Machine': the impact of digital tablet recording in the field at Çatalhöyük | year=2018 | journal=Internet Archaeology | last1 = Taylor | first1 = James | last2 = University | last3 = Issavi | first3 = Justine | last4 = Berggren | first4 = Åsa | last5 = Lukas | first5 = Dominik | last6 = Mazzucato | first6 = Camilla | last7 = Tung | first7 = Burcu | last8 = Dell'Unto | first8 = Nicoló}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sponsors and collaborators of the current dig include [[Yapı ve Kredi Bankası|Yapi Kredi]], [[Boeing]], [[University of York]], [[Selçuk University]], [[British Institute at Ankara]], [[Cardiff University]], [[Stanford University]], [[Turkish Cultural Foundation]], and [[University at Buffalo]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catalhoyuk.com/book/export/html/70, Sponsors and Contributors of current dig]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Culture==
[[File:Catal Hüyük Restoration B.jpg|left|thumb|200px|On-site restoration of a typical interior]]
[[File:Catal Hüyük EL.JPG|left|thumb|200px|On-site restoration of a typical interior]]
[[File:Çatalhöyük excavations ..jpg|upright|thumb|200px|The earliest excavations of the site]]
[[File:Çatalhöyük_trench.jpg|left|thumb|200px|Deep trenches in the site]]
[[File:Çatalhöyük 2006 IMG 2225 (207467760).jpg|upright|thumb|200px|view of southern part of the site]]

&lt;!--DO NOT try to correct the name of this picture to &quot;CatalHüyük Restauration B.JPG&quot;, it will just mess it up.  Thank you.--&gt;Çatalhöyük was composed entirely of domestic buildings, with no obvious public buildings. While some of the larger ones have rather ornate [[murals]], the purpose of some rooms remains unclear.&lt;ref name=gard/&gt;

The population of the eastern mound has been estimated to be, at maximum, 10,000 people, but the population likely varied over the community's history. An average population of between 5,000 and 7,000 is a reasonable estimate. The sites were set up as large numbers of buildings clustered together. Households looked to their neighbors for help, trade, and possible marriage for their children.&lt;ref name=Maynes&gt;{{cite book|last1=Maynes|first1=Mary Jo|last2=Waltner|first2=Ann|title=The Family: A World History|date=2012|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=New York, New York|isbn=978-0-19-530476-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; The inhabitants lived in [[mudbrick]] houses that were crammed together in an aggregate structure. No footpaths or streets were used between the dwellings, which were clustered in a honeycomb-like maze. Most were accessed by holes in the ceiling and doors on the side of the houses, with doors reached by ladders and stairs. The rooftops were effectively streets. The ceiling openings also served as the only source of ventilation, allowing smoke from the houses' open hearths and ovens to escape. 
&lt;!--{{Neolithic}}--&gt;
Houses had [[plaster]] interiors characterized by squared-off timber ladders or steep stairs. These were usually on the south wall of the room, as were [[cooking hearth]]s and [[oven]]s. The main rooms contained raised platforms that may have been used for a range of domestic activities. Typical houses contained two rooms for everyday activity, such as cooking and crafting.&lt;ref name=Maynes/&gt; All interior walls and platforms were plastered to a smooth finish.&lt;ref name=gard/&gt; Ancillary rooms were used as storage, and were accessed through low openings from main rooms.

All rooms were kept scrupulously clean. Archaeologists identified very little rubbish in the buildings, finding middens outside the ruins, with sewage and food waste, as well as significant amounts of ash from burning wood, reeds and animal dung&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|authorlink1=Lisa-Marie Shillito |last1=Shillito |first1=Lisa-Marie |last2=Matthews |first2=Wendy |last3=Almond |first3=Matthew |last4=Bull |first4=Ian D. |title=The microstratigraphy of middens: capturing daily routine in rubbish at Neolithic Çatalhöyük, Turkey |journal=Antiquity |date=2011 |volume=85 |issue=329 |pages=1024–1038 |doi=10.1017/S0003598X00068460 }}&lt;/ref&gt;. In good weather, many daily activities may also have taken place on the rooftops, which may have formed a plaza. In later periods, large communal ovens appear to have been built on these rooftops. Over time, houses were renewed by partial demolition and rebuilding on a foundation of rubble, which was how the mound was gradually built up. As many as eighteen levels of settlement have been uncovered.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://whc.unesco.org/en/list/1405/|title=Neolithic Site of Çatalhöyük|last=Centre|first=UNESCO World Heritage|website=UNESCO World Heritage Centre|language=en|access-date=2020-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As a part of ritual life, the people of Çatalhöyük buried their dead within the village.&lt;ref name=Maynes/&gt; Human remains have been found in pits beneath the floors and, especially, beneath hearths, the platforms within the main rooms, and under beds. Bodies were tightly flexed before burial and were often placed in [[baskets]] or wound and wrapped in reed mats. Disarticulated bones in some graves suggest that bodies may have been exposed in the open air for a time before the bones were gathered and buried. In some cases, graves were disturbed, and the individual's head removed from the skeleton. These heads may have been used in rituals, as some were found in other areas of the community. In a woman's grave spinning whorls were recovered and in a man's grave, stone axes.&lt;ref name=Maynes/&gt; Some [[Plastered human skulls|skulls were plastered]] and painted with [[ochre]] to recreate faces, a custom more characteristic of Neolithic sites in Syria and at Neolithic [[Jericho]] than at sites closer by.

Vivid [[murals]] and [[figurine]]s are found throughout the settlement, on interior and exterior walls. Distinctive [[clay]] figurines of women, notably the [[Seated Woman of Çatalhöyük]], have been found in the upper levels of the site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://arstechnica.com/science/2016/09/amazing-intact-statue-of-a-woman-unearthed-at-the-neolithic-city-of-catalhoyuk-in-turkey/ |title=Incredible discovery of intact female figurine from neolithic era in Turkey &amp;#124; Ars Technica |format= |website= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although no identifiable temples have been found, the graves, murals, and figurines suggest that the people of Çatalhöyük had a religion rich in symbols. Rooms with concentrations of these items may have been [[shrines]] or public meeting areas. Predominant images include men with erect phalluses, hunting scenes, red images of the now extinct [[aurochs]] (wild cattle) and [[stags]], and [[vultures]] swooping down on headless figures.&lt;ref name=gard/&gt; [[Relief]] figures are carved on walls, such as of [[lion]]esses facing one another.

Heads of animals, especially of cattle, were mounted on walls. A painting of the village, with the twin mountain peaks of [[Mount Hasan|Hasan Dağ]] in the background,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web 
|url= http://dbcfaa79b34c8f5dfffa-7d3a62c63519b1618047ef2108473a39.r81.cf2.rackcdn.com/wp-content/uploads/volcano-260x154.jpg
|title= Çatalhöyük mural
|author=  Noah Wiener &lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |authorlink= 
|date=  November 1, 2013
|website= Bible History Daily
|publisher= Biblical Archaeology Society
|archiveurl= http://www.biblicalarchaeology.org/daily/news/catalhoyuk-mural-the-earliest-representation-of-a-volcanic-eruption/
|archivedate= November 24, 2013
|quote= This Çatalhöyük mural is thought to represent a nearby volcanic eruption. New scientific evidence confirms a contemporaneous eruption at nearby Hasan Dağ.
}}&lt;/ref&gt; is frequently cited as the [[History of cartography|world's oldest map]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://cartographic-images.net/Cartographic_Images/100_Town_Plan_from_Catal_Hyuk.html Cartographic Images] (accessed February 23, 2014)&lt;/ref&gt; and the first [[landscape]] painting.&lt;ref name=gard/&gt; However, some archaeologists question this interpretation. Stephanie Meece, for example, argues that it is more likely a painting of a leopard skin instead of a volcano, and a decorative geometric design instead of a map.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dspace.cam.ac.uk/handle/1810/195777 A bird's eye view - of a leopard's spots. The Çatalhöyük ‘map’ and the development of cartographic representation in prehistory.] ''Anatolian Studies'' 56, 2006, pp. 1–16. Published by The British Institute of Archaeology at Ankara&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;gallery caption=&quot;Artifacts&quot; widths=&quot;220px&quot; heights=&quot;150px&quot;&gt;
File:Catal Hüyük 10.JPG|Excavations at the southern area of the site
File:Catal Hüyük 13.JPG|Excavations at the southern area of the site
File:Museum of Anatolian Civilizations016.jpg|The earliest known textile fragments. They may be fabrics used to wrap the dead. They are carbonized in a fire and [[radiocarbon]] dated to c. 6000 BC.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cambridge 1&quot;&gt;Jenkins, pp. 39–47&lt;/ref&gt; 
File:Museum of Anatolian Civilizations011.jpg|Images of deities
File:Catal Hüyük, bull heads.JPG|Bull heads from Catal Hüyük in [[Museum of Anatolian Civilizations]] in Ankara
File:Çatalhöyük_view_5.jpg|[[Aurochs]] heads
File:Ankara Muzeum B20-10.jpg|Mother Goddess from Çatalhöyük (Turkey), neolithic age (about 5500-6000 BC), today in [[Museum of Anatolian Civilizations]] in Ankara
File:Twin goddess, marble statuette, Çatalhöyük, 6000-5500 BC, MACA, 99031.jpg|Twin goddess. Marble statuette, height 17.2&amp;nbsp;cm, from Çatalhöyük, 6000-5500 BC. [[Museum of Anatolian Civilizations]], Ankara.
File:Stamp seal, Çatalhöyük (?) 6000-5500 BC, MACA, 99035.jpg|Stamp seal, small terracotta. Çatalhöyük, 6000-5500 BC. [[Museum of Anatolian Civilizations]], Ankara.
File:Obsidian mirrors, Çatalhöyük, 6000-5500 BC, MACA, 99034.jpg|Obsidian mirrors. Çatalhöyük, 6000-5500 BC. [[Museum of Anatolian Civilizations]], Ankara.
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

==Religion==
[[File:AnkaraMuseumCatal.jpg|thumb|Mural, [[Museum of Anatolian Civilizations]]]]
[[File:Mural from Çatalhöyük excavated by James Mellaart showing neolithic hunters attacking an aurochs (Bos primigenius)..jpg|thumb|left|Neolithic hunters attacking an aurochs, Museum of Anatolian Civilizations]]
[[File:Detail of the mural showing the hind part of the aurochs, a deer and hunters..jpg|thumb|left|Detail of the mural showing the hind part of the aurochs, a deer and hunters]]
[[File:Museum of Anatolian Civilizations 1320512 nevit.jpg|thumb|left|Murals, [[Museum of Anatolian Civilizations]]]]
[[File:Museum of Anatolian Civilizations 1320259 nevit.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Seated Woman of Çatalhöyük|Seated goddess]] flanked by two [[Felidae|felines]], lionesses]]

{{see also|History of religion}}
A striking feature of Çatalhöyük are its female figurines.  Mellaart, the original excavator, argued that these well-formed, carefully made figurines, carved and molded from marble, blue and brown limestone, schist, calcite, basalt, alabaster, and clay, represented a [[female deity]]. Although a male deity existed as well, &quot;statues of a female [[deity]] far outnumber those of the male deity, who moreover, does not appear to be represented at all after Level&amp;nbsp;VI&quot;.&lt;ref name=mellart181&gt;{{cite book | first = James | last = Mellaart |year = 1967 | title = Catal Huyuk: A Neolithic Town in Anatolia | publisher = [[McGraw-Hill]] | pages = 181}}&lt;/ref&gt; To date, eighteen levels have been identified. These artfully-hewn figurines were found primarily in areas Mellaart believed to be shrines. The stately goddess seated on a [[throne]] flanked by two lionesses (''illustration'') was found in a grain bin, which Mellaart suggests might have been a means of ensuring the harvest or protecting the food supply.&lt;ref name=mellart180&gt;Mellaart (1967), 180.&lt;/ref&gt; In later cultures, similar depictions are seen of [[Cybele]], a mountain goddess.

Whereas Mellaart excavated nearly two hundred buildings in four seasons, the current excavator, Ian Hodder, spent an entire season excavating one building alone.&lt;ref name=balter127&gt;{{cite book | first = Michael | last = Balter | title = The Goddess and the Bull | year = 2005 | publisher = Free Press | location = New York | isbn = 978-0-7432-4360-5 | pages = 127}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Hodder and his team, in 2004 and 2005, began to believe that the patterns suggested by Mellaart were false.  They found one similar figurine, but the vast majority did not imitate the [[Mother Goddess]] style that Mellaart suggested. Instead of a Mother Goddess culture, Hodder points out that the site gives little indication of a [[matriarchy]] or [[patriarchy]].

{{quote|There are full breasts on which the hands rest, and the stomach is extended in the central part. There is a hole in the top for the head which is missing. As one turns the figurine around one notices that the arms are very thin, and then on the back of the figurine one sees a depiction of either a skeleton or the bones of a very thin and depleted human. The ribs and vertebrae are clear, as are the scapulae and the main pelvic bones. The figurine can be interpreted in a number of ways - as a woman turning into an ancestor, as a woman associated with death, or as death and life conjoined. It is possible that the lines around the body represent wrapping rather than ribs. Whatever the specific interpretation, this is a unique piece that may force us to change our views of the nature of Çatalhöyük society and imagery. Perhaps the importance of female imagery was related to some special role of the female in relation to death as much as to the roles of mother and nurturer.&lt;ref name=hodder&gt;{{cite web | last = Hodder | first = Ian | title = New finds and new interpretations at Çatalhöyük | work = Çatalhöyük 2005 Archive Report | publisher = Catalhoyuk Research Project, Institute of Archaeology | year = 2005 | url = http://www.catalhoyuk.com/archive_reports/2005/ar05_01.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In an article in the ''Turkish Daily News'', Hodder is reported as denying that Çatalhöyük was a matriarchal society and quoted as saying &quot;When we look at what they eat and drink and at their social statues, we see that men and women had the same social status. There was a balance of power. Another example is the skulls found. If one's social status was of high importance in Çatalhöyük, the body and head were separated after death. The number of female and male skulls found during the excavations is almost equal.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.turkishdailynews.com.tr/article.php?enewsid=93856 | title = A Journey to 9000 years ago | date = 2008-01-17 | accessdate = 2008-08-07 | last = Hodder | first = Ian }}&lt;/ref&gt; In another article in the ''Hurriyet Daily News'' Hodder is reported to say &quot;We have learned that men and women were equally approached&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.hurriyetdailynews.com/Default.aspx?PageID=238&amp;NID=72411&amp;NewsCatID=375 | title = Çatalhöyük excavations reveal gender equality in ancient settled life | date = 2015-03-25 | accessdate = 2015-03-25 | last = Hodder | first = Ian }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a report in September 2009 on the discovery of around 2000 figurines Hodder is quoted as saying:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Çatalhöyük was excavated in the 1960s in a methodical way, but not using the full range of natural science techniques that are available to us today. Sir James Mellaart who excavated the site in the 1960s came up with all sorts of ideas about the way the site was organized and how it was lived in and so on ... We’ve now started working there since the mid 1990s and come up with very different ideas about the site. One of the most obvious examples of that is that Çatalhöyük is perhaps best known for the idea of the mother [[goddess]]. But our work more recently has tended to show that in fact there is very little evidence of a mother goddess and very little evidence of some sort of female-based matriarchy. That's just one of the many myths that the modern scientific work is undermining.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Brien&quot;&gt;O'Brien, Jeremy &quot;New techniques undermine 'mother goddess' role in the community&quot; ''Irish Times'' September 20, 2009 [http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/ireland/2009/0910/1224254196976.html]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[File:Fertile crescent Neolithic B circa 7500 BC.jpg|thumb|upright=1.3|Area of the [[fertile crescent]], circa 7500 BC, with main sites. Çatalhöyük was one of the foremost sites of the [[Pre-Pottery Neolithic]] period]] 
Professor Lynn Meskell explained that while the original excavations had found only 200 figures, the new excavations had uncovered 2,000 figurines of which most were animals, with less than 5% of the figurines women.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Brien&quot; /&gt;

Estonian folklorist [[Uku Masing]] has suggested as early as in 1976, that Çatalhöyük was probably a hunting and gathering religion and the Mother Goddess figurine did not represent a female deity. He implied that perhaps a longer period of time was needed in order to develop symbols for agricultural rites.&lt;ref name=Masing&gt;{{cite book | first = Uku | last = Masing | year = 2011 | title = Aarded Tellistes | publisher = Ilmamaa | location = Tartu, Estonia | isbn = 978-9985-77-351-2 | pages = 209–227}}&lt;/ref&gt; His theory was developed in the paper &quot;Some remarks on the mythology of the people of Catal Hüyük&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Oriental Studies 3. Acta et Commentationes Universitatis Tartuensis 392 / Tartu Riikliku Ülikooli Toimetised 392. Tartu 1976, 75–92.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Economy ==
Çatalhöyük has strong evidence of an [[Egalitarianism|egalitarian]] society, as no houses with distinctive features (belonging to [[Monarch|royalty]] or [[priest|religious hierarchy]], for example) have been found so far.  The most recent investigations also reveal little [[social stratification|social distinction]] based on gender, with men and women receiving equivalent nutrition and seeming to have equal social status, as typically found in [[Paleolithic]] cultures.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stavrianos&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=MKhe6qNva10C&amp;q=paleolithic+society&amp;dq=paleolithic+society|title=A Global History from Prehistory to the Present|author=Leften Stavros Stavrianos|publisher=Prentice Hall|year=1991|isbn=978-0-13-357005-2|location=New Jersey, USA}} [https://books.google.com/books?id=MKhe6qNva10C&amp;q=paleolithic+society&amp;dq=paleolithic+society&amp;pgis=1 Pages 9–13]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gutrie&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=3u6JNwMyMCEC&amp;printsec=frontcover#PPA420,M1|title=The Nature of Paleolithic art|author=R Dale Gutrie|publisher=University of Chicago Press|year=2005|isbn=978-0-226-31126-5|location=Chicago}} [https://books.google.com/books?id=3u6JNwMyMCEC&amp;printsec=frontcover#PPA420,M1 Page 420-422]&lt;/ref&gt; Children observed domestic areas. They learned how to perform rituals and how to build or repair houses by watching the adults make statues, beads and other objects.&lt;ref name=&quot;Maynes&quot; /&gt;
Çatalhöyük's spatial layout may be due to the close kin relations exhibited amongst the people. It can be seen, in the layout, that the people were &quot;divided into two groups who lived on opposite sides of the town, separated by a gully.&quot; Furthermore, because no nearby towns were found from which marriage partners could be drawn, &quot;this spatial separation must have marked two intermarrying kinship groups.&quot; This would help explain how a settlement so early on would become so large.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Family: A World History|last1=Maynes|first1=Mary Jo|last2=Waltner|first2=Ann|date=2012|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-530476-3|location=New York, New York|page=8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In upper levels of the site, it becomes apparent that the people of Çatalhöyük were gaining skills in [[agriculture]] and the domestication of animals. Female figurines have been found within bins used for storage of [[cereal]]s, such as [[wheat]] and [[barley]], and the figurines are presumed to be of a deity protecting the grain. [[Peas]] were also grown, and [[almonds]], [[pistachio]]s, and fruit were harvested from trees in the surrounding hills. [[domestic sheep|Sheep]] were domesticated and evidence suggests the beginning of [[cattle]] [[domestication]] as well.  However, [[hunting]] continued to be a major source of food for the community. [[Pottery]] and [[obsidian]] [[tools]] appear to have been major industries; [[obsidian]] tools were probably both used and also traded for items such as [[Mediterranean]] [[sea]] [[animal shell|shells]] and [[flint]] from [[Syria]]. There is also evidence that the settlement was the first place in the world to mine and smelt metal in the form of [[lead]]. Noting the lack of hierarchy and economic inequality, historian [[Murray Bookchin]] has argued that Çatalhöyük was an early example of [[anarcho-communism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Rise of Urbanisation and Decline of Citizenship|last=Bookchin|first=Murray|year=|isbn=|location=|pages=18–22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Chronology==
&lt;center&gt;{{Near East Neolithic}}&lt;/center&gt;

==See also==
*[[Cities of the ancient Near East]]
*[[Cucuteni–Trypillian culture]]
*[[Göbekli Tepe]]
*[[Kamyana Mohyla]]
*[[List of largest cities throughout history]]
*[[List of Stone Age art]]
*[[Matriarchy]]
*[[Neolithic Revolution]]
*[[Old Europe (archaeology)]]
*[[Sacred bull]]
*[[Venus figurines]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Bailey, Douglass. ''Prehistoric Figurines: Representation and Corporeality in the Neolithic.'' New York: Routledge, 2005 (hardcover, {{ISBN|0-415-33151-X}}; paperback, {{ISBN|0-415-33152-8}}).
* Balter, Michael. ''The Goddess and the Bull: Çatalhöyük: An Archaeological Journey to the Dawn of Civilization.'' New York: Free Press, 2004 (hardcover, {{ISBN|0-7432-4360-9}}); Walnut Creek, CA: Left Coast Press, 2006 (paperback, {{ISBN|1-59874-069-5}}). A highly condensed version was published in [http://www.smithsonianmagazine.com/ ''The Smithsonian Magazine''], May 2005.
* Dural, Sadrettin. &quot;Protecting Catalhoyuk: Memoir of an Archaeological Site Guard.&quot; Contributions by Ian Hodder.  Translated by Duygu Camurcuoglu Cleere.  Walnut Creek, CA: Left Coast Press, 2007. {{ISBN|978-1-59874-050-9}}.
* [[Ian Hodder|Hodder, Ian]]. &quot;Women and Men at Çatalhöyük,&quot; [http://www.sciam.com/ ''Scientific American Magazine''], January 2004 (update V15:1, 2005).
* Hodder, Ian. ''The Leopard's Tale: Revealing the Mysteries of Çatalhöyük''. London; New York: Thames&amp;nbsp;&amp; Hudson, 2006 (hardcover, {{ISBN|0-500-05141-0}}). (The UK title of this work is ''Çatalhöyük: The Leopard's Tale''.)
*Mallett, Marla,  [https://web.archive.org/web/20080930222048/http://marlamallett.com/chupdate.htm &quot;The Goddess from Anatolia:  An Updated View of the Catak Huyuk Controversy],&quot; in Oriental Rug Review, Vol. XIII, No. 2 (December 1992/January 1993).
* [[James Mellaart|Mellaart, James]]. ''Çatal Hüyük: A Neolithic Town in Anatolia.'' London: Thames&amp;nbsp;&amp; Hudson, 1967; New York: McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1967.
* ''On the Surface: Çatalhöyük 1993–95'', edited by Ian Hodder. Cambridge: McDonald Institute for Archaeological Research and British Institute of Archaeology at Ankara, 1996 ({{ISBN|0-9519420-3-4}}).
*{{citation |first=James Stuart |last=Taylor |year=2016 |title=Making Time For Space At Çatalhöyük: GIS as a tool for exploring intra-site spatiotemporality within complex stratigraphic sequences |publisher=University of York (PhD thesis) |url=http://etheses.whiterose.ac.uk/13500/ }} {{open access}}
* Todd, Ian A. ''Çatal Hüyük in Perspective''. Menlo Park, CA: Cummings Pub. Co., 1976 ({{ISBN|0-8465-1958-5}}; {{ISBN|0-8465-1957-7}}).

==External links==
{{Wikivoyage}}
{{Commons|Çatalhöyük}}
* [http://www.catalhoyuk.com Çatalhöyük &amp;mdash; Excavations of a Neolithic Anatolian Höyük], Çatalhöyük excavation official website
* [https://www.flickr.com/photos/catalhoyuk/ Çatalhöyük photos]
* [http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/282/5393/1442 The First Cities: Why Settle Down? The Mystery of Communities], by Michael Balter, Çatalhöyük excavation official biographer
* [http://www.huffingtonpost.com/entry/ian-hodder-%C3%A7atalh%C3%B6y%C3%BCk-religion-templetons-25_us_58fe2a64e4b0f02c3870ecf0 Interview with Ian Hodder March 201 &quot;Ian Hodder: Çatalhöyük, Religion &amp; Templeton's 25%&quot;]
{{Former settlements in Turkey}}
{{World Heritage Sites in Turkey}}
{{Prehistoric technology| state=expanded}}
{{Archaeological museums in Turkey}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Catalhoyuk}}
[[Category:Anatolia]]
[[Category:Archaeological museums in Turkey]]
[[Category:Archaeological sites in Central Anatolia]]
[[Category:Archaeological sites of prehistoric Anatolia]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Konya Province]]
[[Category:Chalcolithic sites of Asia]]
[[Category:Former populated places in Turkey]]
[[Category:Museums in Konya Province]]
[[Category:Neolithic settlements]]
[[Category:Neolithic sites of Asia]]</text>
      <sha1>4ts9ufop9kxd3ibgmiboa4ibeozk2ie</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
