  <page>
    <title>Caving</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5776</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942731985</id>
      <parentid>931189136</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-26T14:06:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Iridescent</username>
        <id>937705</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* History */Cleanup and [[WP:AWB/T|typo fixing]], [[WP:AWB/T|typo(s) fixed]]: 1847-8 → 1847–8</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Recreational pastime of exploring cave systems}}
{{Redirect|Caver|other uses}}
{{Redirect-acronym|Potholing|digging small deep holes to look for buried [[public utilities]]: see [[vacuum excavation]]}}
[[Image:Caving2.jpg|thumb|Caving in a muddy section of [[Black Chasm Cave]] in [[California]]|alt=A man caving in muddy passage with helictite formations on the walls and ceiling]]
[[Image:Alabama cave 2005-04-24.km.jpg|thumb|220px|upright|Stephens Gap, a vertical cave in [[Alabama]]]]

'''Caving''' –  also known as '''spelunking''' in the United States and Canada and '''potholing''' in the United Kingdom and Ireland – is the recreational [[pastime]] of exploring wild [[cave]] systems (as distinguished from [[show cave]]s). In contrast, [[speleology]] is the scientific study of caves and the cave environment.&lt;ref name=&quot;CAVE1&quot;&gt;[http://www.teara.govt.nz/TheBush/BushAndMountainRecreation/Caving/3/en Caving in New Zealand] (from [[Te Ara: The Encyclopedia of New Zealand]], Accessed 2012-11.)&lt;/ref&gt;

The challenges involved in caving vary according to the cave being visited; in addition to the total absence of light beyond the entrance, negotiating [[Pitch (ascent/descent)|pitches]], squeezes,&lt;ref name=CHALL/&gt; and water hazards can be difficult.&lt;ref name=CAVENZ&gt;{{cite news|title=Caving in New Zealand|url=http://www.stuff.co.nz/travel/new-zealand/4118082/Caving-in-New-Zealand|accessdate=12 November 2012|newspaper=Stuff.co.nz - Fairfax NZ News|author=Pearson, Anna}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cave diving]] is a distinct, and more hazardous, sub-speciality undertaken by a small minority of technically proficient cavers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=About Caving |url=http://british-caving.org.uk/wiki3/doku.php?id=press:about_caving |publisher=[[British Caving Association]]|website=british-caving.org.uk |accessdate=31 August 2018 |language=en |quote=... people start... as sporting cavers and develop... other interests such as... cave diving...}}&lt;/ref&gt; In an area of overlap between recreational pursuit and scientific study, the most devoted and serious-minded cavers become accomplished at the [[Cave survey|surveying and mapping of caves]] and the formal publication of their efforts. These are usually published freely and publicly, especially in the UK and other European countries, although in the US, these are generally private. 

Sometimes categorized as an &quot;[[extreme sport]]&quot;, it is not commonly considered as such by longtime enthusiasts, who may dislike the term for its connotation of disregard for safety.&lt;ref name=CHALL&gt;{{cite news|title=Many find caving's challenges, thrills illuminating|url=http://newsok.com/many-find-cavings-challenges-thrills-illuminating/article/3253500/|accessdate=12 November 2012|newspaper=NewsOK|date=8 June 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Extreme Caving - Gorgeous settings present dangers and challenges in Omnimax film|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=_YZIAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=bHADAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=3867,4897282&amp;dq=caving+extreme-sport&amp;hl=en|accessdate=12 November 2012|newspaper=Pittsburgh Post-Gazette|date=6 April 2001|author=Chiacchia, Ken}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many caving skills overlap with those involved in [[canyoning]] and [[mine exploration|mine]] and [[urban exploration]].

== Motivation ==
Caving is often undertaken for the enjoyment of the [[outdoor activity]] or for physical exercise, as well as original exploration, similar to [[mountaineering]] or [[Underwater diving|diving]]. Physical or biological science is also an important goal for some cavers, while others are engaged in cave photography.&lt;ref name=CHALL/&gt; Virgin cave systems comprise some of the last unexplored regions on [[Earth]] and much effort is put into trying to locate, enter and survey them. In well-explored regions (such as most developed nations), the most accessible caves have already been explored, and gaining access to new caves often requires [[cave digging]] or cave diving.

Caving, in certain areas, has also been utilized as a form of eco and adventure tourism, for example [[Caving in New Zealand|in New Zealand]]. Tour companies have established an industry leading and guiding tours into and through caves. Depending on the type of cave and the type of tour, the experience could be adventure-based or ecological-based. There are tours led through lava tubes by a guiding service (e.g. [[Lava River Cave]], the oceanic islands of [[Cueva del Viento|Tenerife]], [http://cave.is/caves-in-iceland/leidarendi-cave/ Iceland] and [https://www.nps.gov/havo/planyourvisit/craterrimtour_tube.htm Hawaii]).

Caving has also been described as an &quot;individualist's team sport&quot; by some,&lt;ref name=CAVENZ/&gt; as cavers can often make a trip without direct physical assistance from others but will generally go in a group for companionship or to provide emergency help if needed. Some however consider the assistance cavers give each other as a typical team sport activity.&lt;ref name=REALU&gt;{{cite news|title=Plunge into Roanoke's real underground|url=http://www.roanoke.com/neighbors/columnists/foley/wb/153436|accessdate=12 November 2012|newspaper=Roanoke Times|date=7 March 2008|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111208213820/http://www.roanoke.com/neighbors/columnists/foley/wb/153436|archive-date=2011-12-08|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Etymology ==
The base term ''caving'' comes from the Latin ''cavea'' or ''caverna'', meaning simply, a cave.

''Potholing'' refers to the act of exploring ''potholes'', a word originating in the north of [[England]] for predominantly [[vertical caving|vertical caves]].[[File:Caveman-ic.jpg|thumb|upright|Caving in the north of [[England]], an area that is also popular for [[pit cave|pothole exploring]]]]
[[Clay Perry]], an American caver of the 1940s, wrote about a group of men and boys who explored and studied caves throughout [[New England]]. This group referred to themselves as ''spelunkers'', a term derived&lt;ref&gt;{{OEtymD|spelunk}}&lt;/ref&gt; from the [[Latin]] ''{{lang|la|spēlunca}}'' (&quot;cave, cavern, den&quot;),&lt;ref&gt;{{L&amp;S|spelunca|ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; itself from the [[Greek language|Greek]] {{lang|grc|σπῆλυγξ}} ''spēlynks'' (&quot;cave&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;{{LSJ|sph{{=}}lugc|σπῆλυγξ|ref}}.&lt;/ref&gt; This is regarded as the first use of the word in the [[Americas]]. Throughout the 1950s, ''spelunking'' was the general term used for exploring caves in [[American English|US English]]. It was used freely, without any positive or negative connotations, although only rarely outside the US.

In the 1960s, the terms ''spelunking'' and ''spelunker'' began to be considered [[wiktionary:déclassé|déclassé]] among experienced enthusiasts. In 1985, Steve Knutson&amp;nbsp;– editor of the [[National Speleological Society]] (NSS) publication ''American Caving Accidents''&amp;nbsp;– made the following distinction:

{{quote|…Note that I use the term 'spelunker' to denote someone untrained and unknowledgeable in current exploration techniques, and 'caver' for those who are.}}

This sentiment is exemplified by [[bumper sticker]]s and T-shirts displayed by some cavers: &quot;Cavers rescue spelunkers&quot;. Nevertheless, outside the caving community, &quot;spelunking&quot; and &quot;spelunkers&quot; predominately remain neutral terms referring to the practice and practitioners, without any respect to skill level.

== History ==
{{Unreferenced section|date=February 2018}}
In the mid-nineteenth century, [[John Birkbeck]] explored potholes in England, notably [[Gaping Gill]] in 1842 and [[Alum Pot]] in 1847–8, returning there in the 1870s. In the mid-1880s, [[Herbert E. Balch]] began exploring [[Wookey Hole Caves]] and in the 1890s, Balch was introduced to the [[caves of the Mendip Hills]]. One of the oldest established caving clubs, [[Yorkshire Ramblers' Club]], was founded in 1892.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yrc.org.uk/yrcweb/index.php/theclub-menu|title=The Club|work=Yorkshire Rambler's Club Website|publisher=YRC Committee|accessdate=10 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Caving as a specialized pursuit was pioneered by [[Édouard-Alfred Martel]] (1859–1938), who first achieved the descent and exploration of the [[Gouffre de Padirac]], in France, as early as 1889 and the first complete descent of a 110-metre wet vertical shaft at Gaping Gill in 1895. He developed his own techniques based on ropes and metallic ladders. Martel visited [[Kentucky]] and notably [[Mammoth Cave National Park]] in October 1912. In the 1920s famous US caver [[Floyd Collins]] made important explorations in the area and in the 1930s, as caving became increasingly popular, small exploration teams both in the [[Alps]] and in the karstic high plateaus of southwest France ([[Causses]] and [[Pyrenees]]) transformed cave exploration into both a scientific and recreational activity. [[Robert de Joly]],  [[Guy de Lavaur]]  and [[Norbert Casteret]] were prominent figures of that time, surveying mostly caves in Southwest France.  During [[World War II]], an alpine team composed of [[Pierre Chevalier (caver)|Pierre Chevalier]], [[Fernand Petzl]], Charles Petit-Didier and others explored the [[Dent de Crolles]] cave system near [[Grenoble]], which became the deepest explored system in the world (-658m) at that time. The lack of available equipment during the war forced Pierre Chevalier and the rest of the team to develop their own equipment, leading to technical innovation. The scaling-pole (1940), nylon ropes (1942), use of explosives in caves (1947) and mechanical rope-ascenders (Henri Brenot's &quot;monkeys&quot;, first used by Chevalier and Brenot in a cave in 1934) can be directly associated to the exploration of the Dent de Crolles cave system.

In 1941, American cavers organized themselves into the [[National Speleological Society]] (NSS) to advance the exploration, conservation, study and understanding of caves in the United States. American caver [[Bill Cuddington]], known as &quot;Vertical Bill&quot;, further developed the [[single-rope technique]] (SRT) in the late 1950s. In 1958, two Swiss alpinists, Juesi and Marti teamed together, creating the first rope ascender known as the [[Jumar]]. In 1968 Bruno Dressler asked Fernand Petzl, who worked as a metals machinist, to build a rope-ascending tool, today known as the [[Petzl Croll]], that he had developed by adapting the Jumar to vertical caving. Pursuing these developments, Petzl started in the 1970s a caving equipment manufacturing company named [[Petzl]].  The development of the [[rappel rack]] and the evolution of mechanical ascension systems extended the practice and safety of vertical exploration to a wider range of cavers.

== Practice and equipment ==
{{Main|Caving equipment}}
[[Image:caving1.jpg|thumb|Caver in an [[Alabama]] cave showing common caving wear: coveralls, helmet-mounted lights, heavy boots and gloves.]]

[[Hard hat]]s are worn to protect the head from bumps and falling rocks. The caver's primary light source is usually mounted on the helmet in order to keep the hands free. Electric [[LED]] lights are most common. Many cavers carry two or more sources of light – one as primary and the others as backup in case the first fails.  More often than not, a second light will be mounted to the helmet for quick transition if the primary fails. [[Carbide lamp]] systems are an older form of illumination, inspired by miner's equipment, and are still used by some cavers, particularly on remote expeditions where electric charging facilities are not available.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.teara.govt.nz/TheBush/BushAndMountainRecreation/Caving/4/en Caving equipment and culture] (from [[Te Ara: The Encyclopedia of New Zealand]])&lt;/ref&gt;

The type of [[clothes]] worn underground varies according to the environment of the cave being explored, and the local culture. In cold caves, the caver may wear a warm base layer that retains its insulating properties when wet, such as a [[Wool|fleece]] (&quot;furry&quot;) suit or polypropylene underwear, and an oversuit of hard-wearing (e.g., [[cordura]]) or waterproof (e.g., [[Polyvinyl chloride|PVC]]) material. Lighter clothing may be worn in warm caves, particularly if the cave is dry, and in tropical caves thin polypropylene clothing is used, to provide some abrasion protection while remaining as cool as possible. [[Wetsuit]]s may be worn if the cave is particularly wet or involves stream passages.  On the feet [[boot]]s are worn&amp;nbsp;– hiking-style boots in drier caves, or rubber boots (such as [[wellies]]) often with [[neoprene]] socks (&quot;wetsocks&quot;) in wetter caves. [[Knee]]-pads (and sometimes [[Elbow-joint|elbow]]-pads) are popular for protecting joints during crawls. Depending on the nature of the cave, gloves are sometimes worn to protect the hands against abrasion or cold.  In pristine areas and for restoration, clean oversuits and powder-free, non-latex [[Medical gloves|surgical gloves]] are used to protect the cave itself from contaminants.
Ropes are used for descending or ascending pitches (single rope technique or SRT) or for protection. [[Knot]]s commonly used in caving are the [[figure-of-eight loop|figure-of-eight]]- (or [[figure-of-nine loop|figure-of-nine]]-) loop, [[bowline]], [[alpine butterfly knot|alpine butterfly]], and [[Italian hitch]]. Ropes are usually rigged using [[bolt (climbing)|bolts]], [[sling (climbing equipment)|sling]]s, and [[carabiner]]s. In some cases cavers may choose to bring and use a flexible metal [[ladder]].

In addition to the equipment already described, cavers frequently carry packs containing [[First aid|first-aid]] kits, emergency equipment, and food. Containers for securely transporting [[urine]] are also commonly carried{{fact?|date=July 2018}}.  On longer trips, containers for securely transporting [[feces]] out of the cave are carried{{fact?|date=July 2018}}.

During very long trips, it may be necessary to camp in the cave&amp;nbsp;– some cavers have stayed underground for many days, or in particularly extreme cases, for weeks at a time. This is particularly the case when exploring or mapping very extended cave systems, where it would be impractical to retrace the route back to the surface regularly. Such long trips necessitate the cavers carrying provisions, sleeping and cooking equipment.

== Safety ==
[[Image:Caving3.jpg|thumb|right|A caver begins rope descent of a vertical shaft using an abseil rack.]]
{{See also|Cave rescue}}
Caves can be dangerous places; hypothermia, [[falling (accident)|falling]], [[flooding]], falling rocks and physical [[Fatigue (medical)|exhaustion]] are the main risks. Rescuing people from underground is difficult and time-consuming, and requires special skills, training, and equipment. Full-scale cave rescues often involve the efforts of dozens of rescue workers (often other long-time cavers who have participated in specialized courses, as normal rescue staff are not sufficiently experienced in cave environments), who may themselves be put in jeopardy in effecting the rescue. This said, caving is not necessarily a high-risk sport (especially if it does not involve difficult climbs or diving). As in all physical sports, knowing one's limitations is key.

Caving in warmer climates carries the risk of contracting [[histoplasmosis]], a fungal infection that is contracted from bird or bat droppings. It can cause [[pneumonia]] and can disseminate in the body to cause continued infections.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Stenn|first1=Frederick|title=Cave Disease or Speleonosis|journal=American Medical Association Internal Medicine|date=1960|volume=105|issue=2|pages=181–183}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In many parts of the world, [[leptospirosis]] (&quot;a type of bacterial infection spread by animals&quot; including rats&lt;ref&gt;Leptospirosis is a type of bacterial infection spread by animals. It's caused by a strain of bacteria called leptospira.  In 90% of cases, leptospirosis only causes mild flu-like symptoms, such as a headache, chills and muscle pain.  However, in some cases the infection is more severe and can cause life-threatening problems, including organ failure and internal bleeding. In its most severe form, leptospirosis is also known as Weil's disease. http://www.nhs.uk/conditions/leptospirosis/Pages/Introduction.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;) is a distinct threat due to the presence of rat urine in rainwater or precipitation that enters the caves water system. Complications are uncommon, but can be serious.
Safety risks while caving can be minimized by using a number of techniques:

* Checking that there is no danger of flooding during the expedition. Rainwater funneled underground can flood a cave very quickly, trapping people in cut-off passages and [[drowning]] them. In the UK, drowning accounts for almost half of all caving fatalities (see [[List of UK caving fatalities]]).
* Using teams of several cavers, preferably at least four. If an injury occurs, one caver stays with the injured person while the other two go out for help, providing assistance to each other on their way out.
* Notifying people outside the cave as to the intended return time. After an appropriate delay without a return, these will then organize a search party (usually made up by other cavers trained in [[cave rescue]]s, as even professional emergency personnel are unlikely to have the skills to effect a rescue in difficult conditions).
* Use of helmet-mounted lights (hands-free) with extra batteries. American cavers recommend a minimum of three independent sources of light per person,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=A Guide to Responsible Caving|last=|first=|publisher=National Speleological Society|year=2016|isbn=|location=|pages=11|quote=|via=https://caves.org/brochure/Guide_to_Resp_Caving_2016.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; but two lights is common practice among European cavers.{{citation needed|date=February 2017}} 
* Sturdy clothing and footwear, as well as a [[helmet]], are necessary to reduce the impact of abrasions, falls, and falling objects. Synthetic fibers and woolens, which dry quickly, shed water, and are warm when wet, are vastly preferred to cotton materials, which retain water and increase the risk of hypothermia. It is also helpful to have several layers of clothing, which can be shed (and stored in the pack) or added as needed. In watery cave passages, [[polypropylene]] thermal underwear or wetsuits may be required to avoid [[hypothermia]].
* Cave passages look different from different directions. In long or complex caves, even experienced cavers can become lost. To reduce the risk of becoming lost, it is necessary to memorize the appearance of key navigational points in the cave as they are passed by the exploring party. Each member of a cave party shares responsibility for being able to remember the route out of the cave. In some caves it may be acceptable to mark a small number of key junctions with small stacks or &quot;cairns&quot; of rocks, or to leave a non-permanent mark such as high-visibility [[flagging (tape)|flagging tape]] tied to a projection.
* [[Pit cave|Vertical caving]] uses ladders or single rope technique (SRT) to avoid the need for climbing passages that are too difficult. SRT however is a complex skill and requires proper training before use underground and needs well-maintained equipment. Some drops that are [[abseiling|abseiled]] down may be as deep as several hundred meters (for example [[Harwood Hole]]).

==Cave conservation==
Many cave environments are very fragile.  Many [[speleothem]]s can be damaged by even the slightest touch and some by impacts as slight as a breath. Research suggests that increased carbon dioxide levels can lead to &quot;a higher equilibrium concentration of calcium within the drip waters feeding the speleothems, and hence causes dissolution of existing features.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Baker 1998 165–175&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Baker|first=A.|author2=Genty, D.|title=Environmental pressures on conserving cave speleothems: effects of changing surface land use and increased cave tourism.|journal=Journal of Environmental Management|date=June 1998|volume=53|issue=2|pages=165–175|doi=10.1006/jema.1998.0208}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2008, researchers found evidence that respiration from cave visitors may generate elevated carbon dioxide concentrations in caves, leading to increased temperatures of up to 3&amp;nbsp;°C and a dissolution of existing features.&lt;ref name=&quot;Baker 1998 165–175&quot;/&gt;

Pollution is also of concern.  Since water that flows through a cave eventually comes out in streams and rivers, any pollution may ultimately end up in someone's drinking water, and can even seriously affect the surface environment, as well.  Even minor pollution such as dropping [[organic material]] can have a dramatic effect on the cave biota.

Cave-dwelling species are also very fragile, and often, a particular species found in a cave may live within that cave alone, and be found nowhere else in the world, such as [[Alabama cave shrimp]].  Cave-dwelling species are accustomed to a near-constant climate of temperature and humidity, and any disturbance can be disruptive to the species' life cycles. Though cave wildlife may not always be immediately visible, it is typically nonetheless present in most caves.

[[Bat]]s are one such fragile species of cave-dwelling animal. Bats which [[hibernation|hibernate]] are most vulnerable during the winter season, when no food supply exists on the surface to replenish the bat's store of energy should it be awakened from hibernation. Bats which [[Bird migration|migrate]] are most sensitive during the summer months when they are raising their young.  For these reasons, visiting caves inhabited by hibernating bats is discouraged during cold months; and visiting caves inhabited by migratory bats is discouraged during the warmer months when they are most sensitive and vulnerable.  Due to an affliction affecting bats in the northeastern US known as [[white nose syndrome]] (WNS),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fws.gov/northeast/white_nose.html|title=Page Redirect|author=Northeast Region Web Development Group|work=fws.gov}}&lt;/ref&gt; the US Fish &amp; Wildlife Service has called for a moratorium [http://www.caves.org/WNS/USFWS-WNS_cave_advisory_news_rls_2009-03-26_final-1.pdf] effective March 26, 2009, on caving activity in states known to have hibernacula (MD, NY, VT, NH, MA, CT, NJ, PA, VA, and WV) affected by WNS, as well as adjoining states.

Some cave passages may be marked with flagging tape or other indicators to show biologically, aesthetically, or archaeologically sensitive areas. Marked paths may show ways around notably fragile areas such as a pristine floor of [[sand]] or [[silt]] which may be thousands of years old, dating from the last time water flowed through the cave. Such deposits may easily be spoiled forever by a single misplaced step. Active formations such as [[flowstone]] can be similarly marred with a muddy footprint or handprint, and ancient human artifacts, such as fiber products, may even crumble to dust under all but the most gentle touch.

In 1988, concerned that cave resources were becoming increasingly damaged through unregulated use, Congress enacted the [[Federal Cave Resources Protection Act of 1988|Federal Cave Resources Protection Act]], giving land management agencies in the United States expanded authority to manage cave conservation on public land.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Iraola|first=Roberto|title=Statutory overview: The Federal Cave Resources Protection Act of 1988|journal=Fordham Environmental Law Review|date=October 2005|volume=17|pages=89–271}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Europe there have been some [[360 Panorama|panoramic 360°]] records and [[Virtual reality|VR]] projects as a means of sharing interesting caves or quarries:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Virtual Caving|url=http://www.jphd360.net/index.php/en/im360/im360-caving|access-date=2014-05-25|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140622020210/http://www.jphd360.net/index.php/en/im360/im360-caving|archive-date=2014-06-22|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;border:1px solid #999; background-color:#FFFFFF&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot; 
|- bgcolor=&quot;#CCCCCC&quot;
! Ref.
! Cave name
! Cave location&lt;br /&gt;
! Panoramic tour&lt;br /&gt;
! Full screen&lt;br /&gt;
! Cave map&lt;br /&gt;
! 3D View&lt;br /&gt;
! VR Mode&lt;br /&gt;
! Source/Reference&lt;br /&gt;
! Publication date&lt;br /&gt;
|-
| 13
| ''Armedia''
| [[France]], [[Languedoc-Roussillon]], [[Gard]]
| [http://www.jphd360.net/visites/Armedia/Armedia.html Armedia] 
| -
| -
| -
| -
| ''jphd360/Les Plutons/Les Troglodytes''
| 2015/05
|-
| 12
| ''Les Deux Avens''
| [[France]], [[Rhône-Alpes]], [[:fr:Ardèche (département)|Ardèche]]
| [http://www.jphd360.net/visites/LesDeuxAvens/LesDeuxAvens.html Les deux Avens] 
| -
| -
| -
| -
| ''jphd360/Les Plutons''
| 2014/05
|-
| 11
| ''Grotte du Noû Bleû''
| [[Belgium]], [[Wallonia]], [[Liège (province)|province of Liège]], [[Sprimont]]
| [https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/33757898/Visite%20Virtuelle%2001.14/virtualtour.swf dropboxusercontent.com]{{Dead link|date=August 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}
| Yes
| Yes
| -
| -
| ''Collectif Noû Bleû''
| 2014/04
|-
| 10
| ''Grange du Bacque''
| [[France]], [[Rhône-Alpes]], [[:fr:Ardèche (département)|Ardèche]]
| [http://www.jphd360.net/visites/LaGrangeduBacque/LaGrangeduBacque.html La grange du Bacque] 
| -
| -
| -
| -
| ''jphd360/Les Plutons/GSVans''
| 2014/03
|-
| 9
| ''[[Fontaine de Vaucluse]]''
| [[France]], [[Provence-Alpes-Côte d'Azur]], [[Vaucluse (département)|Vaucluse]], [[Fontaine-de-Vaucluse]]
| [https://web.archive.org/web/20140414233033/http://www.ssfv.fr/panorama/ ssfv.fr]
| -
| -
| -
| -
| ''SSFV''
| 2014/03
|-
| 8
| ''[[:fr:Baume du Coudrier|Baume du Coudrier]]''
| [[France]], [[Franche-Comté]], [[Jura (département)|Jura]]
| [http://www.jphd360.net/visites/BaumeCoudrier/BaumeCoudrier.html La Baume du Coudrier] 
| -
| -
| -
| -
| ''jphd360/Les Plutons/CARS''
| 2013/04
|-
| 7
| ''Les carrières de l'Echaillon''
| [[France]], [[Rhône-Alpes]], [[Isère (département)|Isère]]
| [http://www.jphd360.net/visites/Echaillon/Echaillon.html Les carrières de l'Echaillon] 
| Yes
| -
| -
| -
| ''jphd360/Les Plutons''
| 2012/09
|-
| 6
| ''Aven de la Grande Salamandre''
| [[France]], [[Languedoc-Roussillon]], [[Gard]]
| [http://www.jphd360.net/visites/LaGSalamandre/LaGSalamandre.html La Grande Salamandre] 
| Yes
| Yes
| Anaglyph
| -
| ''jphd360/Les Plutons''
| 2011/06
|-
| 5
| ''Grotte du Burlandier''
| [[France]], [[Rhône-Alpes]], [[Ain (département)|Ain]]
| [http://www.jphd360.net/visites/LeBurlandier/LeBurlandier.html Le Burlandier] 
| Yes
| Yes
| Anaglyph
| -
| ''jphd360/Les Plutons''
| 2011/05
|-
| 4
| ''Grotte Nouvelle de Vallon''
| [[France]], [[Rhône-Alpes]], [[:fr:Ardèche (département)|Ardèche]]
| [http://www.jphd360.net/visites/GNouvelleVallon/GNouvelleVallon.html La grotte Nouvelle de Vallon] 
| Yes
| Yes
| Anaglyph
| -
| ''jphd360/Les Plutons''
| 2010/11
|-
| 3
| ''Aven des Oublis''
| [[France]], [[Languedoc-Roussillon]], [[Gard]]
| [http://www.jphd360.net/visites/LesOublis/LesOublis.html Les Oublis]
| Yes
| Yes
| Anaglyph
| -
| ''jphd360/Les Plutons''
| 2010/05
|-
| 2
| ''Grotte du Crochet Supérieur''
| [[France]], [[Rhône-Alpes]], [[Ain (département)|Ain]]
| [http://www.jphd360.net/visites/LeCrochet/LeCrochetSup.html Le Crochet Supérieur]
| Yes
| Yes
| Anaglyph
| [http://eleana.jphd360.net/speleo/lecrochetsup/lecrochetsup.html Yes, here! (auto-detection)]{{dead link|date=January 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}
| ''Eleana/jphd360/Les Plutons''
| 2010/05 - 2016/11
|-
| 1
| ''Gouffre de La Morgne''
| [[France]], [[Rhône-Alpes]], [[Ain (département)|Ain]]
| [http://www.jphd360.net/visites/LaMorgne/LaMorgne.html La Morgne]
| Yes
| Yes
| Anaglyph
| -
| ''jphd360/Les Plutons''
| 2009/05
|-
|}

== Caving organizations ==
{{main|Caving organizations}}
Cavers in many countries have created organizations for the administration and oversight of caving activities within their nations. The oldest of these is the [[French Federation of Speleology]] (originally Société de spéléologie) founded by Édouard-Alfred Martel in 1895, which produced the first periodical journal in speleology, ''Spelunca''. The first University-based speleological institute in the world was founded in 1920 in [[Cluj-Napoca]], Romania, by [[Emil Racovita]], a Romanian biologist, zoologist, speleologist and explorer of Antarctica.

The [[British Speleological Association]] was established in 1935 and the [[National Speleological Society]] in the US was founded in 1941 (originally formed as the Speleological Society of [[Washington, D.C.|the District of Columbia]] on May 6, 1939).

An international speleological congress was proposed at a meeting in Valence-sur-Rhone, France in 1949 and first held in 1953 in Paris. The [[International Union of Speleology]] (UIS) was founded in 1965.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.uis-speleo.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=60&amp;Itemid=184|title=What is the UIS?|website=www.uis-speleo.org|access-date=2019-04-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* {{annotated link|List of caves}}
* {{annotated link|List of longest caves}}
* {{annotated link|List of deepest caves}}
* {{annotated link|Speleology}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

* {{Cite book
 | author = Burger, Paul
 | year = 2006
 | title = Cave exploring
 | isbn = 0-7627-2560-5
 | publisher = FalconGuide
 | location = Guilford, Conn.
 | oclc = 53912806 
}}
* {{Cite book | author=Marbach, George; Tourte, Bernard; Alspaugh, Melanie (translator) | authorlink= | title=Alpine Caving Techniques | publisher=Speleo Projects, Switzerland | location= | isbn=3-908495-10-5 | pages=}}

==External links==
{{Commons|Cave|Caving}}
{{Wiktionary}}
*{{dmoz|Recreation/Outdoors/Caving}}

{{Caves}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Caving| ]]

[[ro:Speologie]]
[[vi:Thám hiểm hang động]]</text>
      <sha1>hbjelhirxcatispqkc19zpq9lsi04mu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
