  <page>
    <title>Cincinnati Bengals</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6612</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941002762</id>
      <parentid>941001425</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-16T00:56:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Eagles247</username>
        <id>9792575</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/NFL6253|NFL6253]] ([[User talk:NFL6253|talk]]) to last version by KristofferAG</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|the current Cincinnati Bengals team|the team that existed between 1937–1941|Cincinnati Bengals (1937–41)}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=January 2019}}

{{short description|National Football League franchise in Cincinnati, Ohio}}
{{Infobox NFL team
| name = Cincinnati Bengals
| current = 2019 Cincinnati Bengals season
| logo = Cincinnati Bengals logo.svg
| wordmark = Cincinnati Bengals wordmark.svg
| founded = {{Start date and years ago|May 23, 1967}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Cincinnati Bengals Team Facts|url=http://www.profootballhof.com/teams/cincinnati-bengals/team-facts/|publisher=NFL Enterprises, LLC|website=ProFootballHOF.com|access-date=October 2, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| first_season = [[1968 Cincinnati Bengals season|1968]]
| city = and '''headquartered''' in [[Paul Brown Stadium]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Cincinnati|Cincinnati, Ohio]]
| uniform = File:AFCN-Uniform-CIN.PNG
| colors = Black, orange, white&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=LaPlaca|first=Michael|title=Bengals 2019 Uniform Schedule; Color Rush Dates Revealed|url=https://www.bengals.com/news/bengals-2019-uniform-schedule-color-rush-dates-revealed|publisher=NFL Enterprises, LLC|website=Bengals.com|date=September 2, 2019|access-date=September 4, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Cincinnati Bengals Team Capsule|url=http://www.nfl.com/static/content/public/photo/2018/08/09/0ap3000000946101.pdf#page=52|publisher=NFL Enterprises, LLC|work=2018 Official National Football League Record and Fact Book|date=August 9, 2018|access-date=September 12, 2018|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{{color box|#000000}} {{color box|#FB4F14}} {{color box|#FFFFFF}}
| song = Bengals Growl
| mascot = Bengal tiger (Who Dey)&lt;ref name=&quot;WhoDey&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Who Dey Appearance Request|url=https://www.bengals.com/fans/whodeyappearance|publisher=NFL Enterprises, LLC|website=Bengals.com|access-date=July 5, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| owner = [[Mike Brown (American football executive)|Mike Brown]]
| president = Mike Brown
| general manager = Mike Brown
| coach = [[Zac Taylor]]
| hist_yr = 1968
| affiliate_old =
[[American Football League]] (1968–1969)
* [[AFL West]] (1968–1969)
| NFL_start_yr = 1970
| division_hist =
* '''[[American Football Conference]] (1970–present)'''
** [[AFC Central]] (1970–2001)
** '''[[AFC North]] (2002–present)'''
| no_conf_champs = 2
| no_div_champs = 9
| conf_champs =
* '''AFC:''' [[1981 NFL season|1981]], [[1988 NFL season|1988]]
| div_champs =
* '''AFC Central:''' [[1970 NFL season|1970]], [[1973 NFL season|1973]], [[1981 NFL season|1981]], [[1988 NFL season|1988]], [[1990 NFL season|1990]]
* '''AFC North:''' [[2005 NFL season|2005]], [[2009 NFL season|2009]], [[2013 NFL season|2013]], [[2015 NFL season|2015]]
| playoff_appearances =
* '''NFL:''' [[1970–71 NFL playoffs|1970]], [[1973–74 NFL playoffs|1973]], [[1975–76 NFL playoffs|1975]], [[1981–82 NFL playoffs|1981]], [[1982–83 NFL playoffs|1982]], [[1988–89 NFL playoffs|1988]], [[1990–91 NFL playoffs|1990]], [[2005–06 NFL playoffs|2005]], [[2009–10 NFL playoffs|2009]], [[2011–12 NFL playoffs|2011]], [[2012–13 NFL playoffs|2012]], [[2013–14 NFL playoffs|2013]], [[2014–15 NFL playoffs|2014]], [[2015–16 NFL playoffs|2015]]
| no_playoff_appearances = 14
| stadium_years =
* [[Nippert Stadium]] (1968–1969)
* [[Riverfront Stadium]] (1970–1999)
* '''[[Paul Brown Stadium]] (2000–present)'''
}}

The '''Cincinnati Bengals''' are a professional [[American football]] franchise based in [[Cincinnati|Cincinnati, Ohio]]. The Bengals compete in the [[National Football League]] (NFL) as a member club of the league's [[American Football Conference]] (AFC) [[AFC North|North]] division. Their home stadium is [[Paul Brown Stadium]], located in [[downtown Cincinnati]]. Their divisional opponents are the [[Baltimore Ravens]], [[Cleveland Browns]] and [[Pittsburgh Steelers]].

The Bengals were founded in {{nfly|1966}} as a member of the [[American Football League]] (AFL) by former Cleveland Browns head coach [[Paul Brown]], and began play in the 1968 season. Brown was the Bengals' head coach from their inception to {{nfly|1975}}. After being dismissed as the Browns' head coach by [[Art Modell]] (who had purchased majority interest in the team in {{nfly|1961}}) in January {{nfly|1963}}, Brown had shown interest in establishing another NFL franchise in Ohio and looked at both Cincinnati and [[Columbus, Ohio|Columbus]]. He ultimately chose the former when a deal between the city, [[Hamilton County, Ohio|Hamilton County]], and [[Major League Baseball]]'s [[Cincinnati Reds]] (who were seeking a replacement for the obsolete [[Crosley Field]]) was struck that resulted in an agreement to build [[Riverfront Stadium|a multipurpose stadium]] which could host both baseball and football games.

Due to the [[AFL–NFL merger|impending merger]] of the AFL and the NFL, which was scheduled to take full effect in the {{nfly|1970}} season, Brown agreed to join the AFL as its tenth and final franchise. The Bengals, like the other former AFL teams, were assigned to the AFC following the merger. Cincinnati was also selected because, like their neighbors the Reds, they could draw from several large neighboring cities ([[Louisville, Kentucky|Louisville]] and [[Lexington, Kentucky]]; [[Columbus, Ohio|Columbus]], [[Dayton, Ohio|Dayton]], and [[Springfield, Ohio]]) that are all no more than {{convert|110|mi}} away from downtown Cincinnati, along with [[Indianapolis]], until the [[Baltimore Colts relocation to Indianapolis|Baltimore Colts relocated]] there prior to the [[1984 NFL season]].

The Bengals won the [[AFC Championship Game|AFC championship]] in {{nfly|1981}} and {{nfly|1988}}, but lost [[Super Bowl]]s [[Super Bowl XVI|XVI]] and [[Super Bowl XXIII|XXIII]] to the [[San Francisco 49ers]]. After Paul Brown's death in 1991, controlling interest in the team was inherited by his son, [[Mike Brown (American football executive)|Mike Brown]]. In 2011, Brown purchased shares of the team owned by the estate of co-founder [[Austin Knowlton]] and is now the majority owner of the Bengals franchise.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Katzowitz|first=Josh|title=Mike Brown Now Owns Most of Bengals Franchise|url=http://www.cbssports.com/mcc/blogs/entry/22475988/34008660|publisher=[[CBS Interactive]]|website=CBSSports.com|date=December 23, 2011|accessdate=December 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 1990s and the 2000s were a period of great struggle. Following the 1990 season, the team went 14 years without posting a winning record, nor qualifying to play in the [[NFL playoffs]]. The Bengals had several head coaches and several of their top [[NFL Draft|draft]] picks did not pan out. Mike Brown, the team's ''de facto'' general manager,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=HBO Shows Bengals Behind the Scenes|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/nfl/trainingcamp09/news/story?id=4412908|publisher=[[ESPN]]|agency=[[Associated Press]]|date=August 20, 2009|accessdate=December 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; was rated as among the worst team owners in American professional sports.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The 16 Worst Owners in Sports: Mike Brown – Cincinnati Bengals|url=http://www.businessinsider.com/worst-owners-in-sports-2011-5#mike-brown--cincinnati-bengals-13|website=[[Business Insider]]|accessdate=December 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the mid-2000s, the team's fortunes have improved. Two years after becoming head coach, [[Marvin Lewis]] guided the Bengals to their first winning season and first division title in over a decade. After the acquisition of [[Andy Dalton]] as quarterback in 2011, the Bengals had made the playoffs each season until 2016, ranking highly among NFL teams in win totals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Owczarski|first=Jim|title=Polian: Questioning Bengals success 'absurd'|url=http://www.cincinnati.com/story/sports/nfl/bengals/2015/05/17/bengals-bill-polian/27479191/|newspaper=[[Cincinnati Enquirer]]|date=May 17, 2015|accessdate=May 7, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Bengals drafts are also highly touted, leading to a consistency that had long escaped the franchise. However, the team has remained unable to win in the postseason and have not won a playoff game since 1990, which is the longest active drought in the NFL.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Chase|first=Chris|title=The Bengals 9,123-day playoff win drought is looking like it'll continue in 2016|url=http://ftw.usatoday.com/2015/12/poor-cincinnati-its-shaping-up-to-be-another-wild-card-loss-for-the-bengals|newspaper=[[USA Today]]|date=December 29, 2015|accessdate=May 7, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Bengals are one of the 12 NFL teams to not have won a [[Super Bowl]] {{As of|2018|alt=as of the {{nfly|2018}} season}}; they are also one of 8 NFL teams that have been to at least one Super Bowl, but have not won the game.

==History of the Cincinnati Bengals==
{{main|History of the Cincinnati Bengals}}
In [[1967 AFL season|1967]], an ownership group led by Paul Brown was granted a franchise in the [[American Football League]]. Brown named the team the Bengals in order &quot;to give it a link with past professional football in Cincinnati&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Team Chronology|url=http://prod.static.bengals.clubs.nfl.com/assets/docs/2017/17-history.pdf#page=2|publisher=Cincinnati Bengals|date=June 26, 2017|accessdate=May 7, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another [[Cincinnati Bengals (1937–41)|Cincinnati Bengals]] team had existed in the city and played in three previous American Football Leagues&lt;ref&gt;[[American Football League (1936)|AFL II]] 1937, [[American Football League (1938)|AFL/APFA]] 1939, [[American Football League (1940)|AFL III]] 1940–1941&lt;/ref&gt; from [[1937 American Football League season|1937]] to 1942. The city's world-renowned [[Cincinnati Zoo|zoo]] was also home to a rare white [[Bengal tiger]]. However, possibly as an insult to [[Art Modell]], or possibly as a homage to his own start as a head coach to the [[Massillon Washington High School|Massillon Tigers]], Brown chose the exact shade of orange used by his former team. He added black as the secondary color. Brown chose a very simple logo: the word &quot;BENGALS&quot; in black lettering. One of the potential helmet designs Brown rejected was a striped motif that was similar to the helmets adopted by the team in 1981 and which is still in use; however, that design featured yellow stripes on a turquoise helmet{{citation needed|date=May 2017}} which were more uniform in width. The Bengals would begin play in the [[1968 AFL season|1968 season]].

In 1966, the American Football League agreed to [[AFL–NFL merger|a merger]] with its older and more established rival, the [[National Football League]]. Among the terms of the merger was that the AFL was permitted to add one additional franchise. One of the reasons the NFL agreed to this was that they wanted an even number of clubs in the merged league, so a team needed to be added that brought the combined total number clubs in the merged league to twenty-six teams. The NFL was content for that team to be in the American Football League because it meant that the existing nine AFL clubs were the ones that had to provide players in the ensuing [[expansion draft]] and the NFL owners preferred for the ensuing dilution of talent to occur in what they had always considered to be an inferior league.{{citation needed|date=September 2015}} For the AFL, a key motive behind their agreement to accept a new team was that the guarantee of an eventual place in the NFL meant the league could charge a steep expansion fee of $10 million–400 times the $25,000 the original eight owners paid when they founded the league in 1960. The cash from the new team provided the American Football League with the funds needed to pay the indemnities required to be paid by the AFL to the NFL, as stipulated by the merger agreement.

Prior to the merger being announced, Brown had not seriously considered joining the American Football League, and was not a supporter of what he openly regarded to be an inferior competition, once famously stating that &quot;I didn't pay ten million dollars to be in the AFL.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.conigliofamily.com/PaulBrown.htm|title=Paul Brown|publisher=Conigliofamily.com|accessdate=December 16, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, with the announcement of the merger, Brown realized that the AFL expansion franchise would likely be his only realistic path back into the NFL in the short to medium term. He ultimately acquiesced to joining the AFL when after learning that the team was guaranteed to become an NFL franchise after the merger was completed in 1970.

There was also a complication: [[Major League Baseball]]'s [[Cincinnati Reds]] were in need of a facility to replace the antiquated, obsolete [[Crosley Field]], which they had used since 1912. Parking nightmares had plagued the city as far back as the 1950s, the little park lacked modern amenities, and New York City, which in 1957 had lost both its [[National League]] teams (the [[Los Angeles Dodgers|Dodgers]] and the [[San Francisco Giants|Giants]]) to Los Angeles and San Francisco, respectively, was actively courting Reds owner [[Powel Crosley]]. However, Crosley was adamant that the Reds remain in Cincinnati and tolerated worsening problems with the Crosley Field location, which were exacerbated by the [[Mill Creek Expressway]] ([[I-75]]) project that ran alongside the park.
[[File:Cincinnati-paul-brown-stadium2.jpg|thumb|left|200px|[[Paul Brown Stadium]], home of the Bengals.]]
With assistance from Ohio governor James A. Rhodes, [[Hamilton County, Ohio|Hamilton County]] and the Cincinnati city council agreed to build a single multi-purpose facility on the dilapidated riverfront section of the city. The new facility had to be ready by the opening of the [[1970 NFL season]] and was officially named [[Riverfront Stadium]]. With the completion of the merger in [[1970 NFL season|1970]], the Cleveland Browns were one of three NFL teams that voluntarily moved to the AFL-based American Football Conference to give both conferences an equal number of teams and placed in the [[AFC Central]], the same division as the Bengals. An instant [[Battle of Ohio (NFL)|rivalry was born]], fueled initially by Paul Brown's rivalry with Art Modell.

For their first two seasons, the Bengals played at [[Nippert Stadium]] which is the current home of the [[University of Cincinnati]] [[Cincinnati Bearcats football|Bearcats]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=a6JQAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=u1wDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4236,1676508&amp;dq=nippert+stadium+cincinnati+bengals&amp;hl=en|title=Hot Football Time in Old Cincy Tonight|newspaper=[[St. Petersburg Times]]|agency=Associated Press|date=August 3, 1968|page=2C|accessdate=December 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The team held training camp at [[Wilmington College (Ohio)|Wilmington College]] in [[Wilmington, Ohio|Wilmington]], through the 1968 preseason. The team finished its first season with a 3–11 record&lt;ref name=&quot;encyc&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.pro-football-reference.com/teams/cin|title=Cincinnati Bengals Team Encyclopedia|website=[[Pro-Football-Reference.com]]|publisher=Sports Reference|accessdate=December 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and running back [[Paul Robinson (American football player)|Paul Robinson]], who rushed for 1,023 yards, and was named the AFL Rookie of the Year.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://talesfromtheamericanfootballleague.com/1968-afl-rookie-of-the-year-paul-robinson/|title=&gt;1968 AFL Rookie of the Year – Paul Robinson {{!}} Tales from the AFL|website=talesfromtheamericanfootballleague.com|language=en-US|access-date=March 15, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Carson Palmer under center.jpg|thumb|left|200px|[[Quarterback]] [[Carson Palmer]], [[wide receiver]] #84 [[T. J. Houshmandzadeh]], and the rest of the Bengals line up to play the [[Pittsburgh Steelers]] in 2006.]]

Founder Paul Brown coached the team for its first eight seasons. One of Brown's college draft strategies was to draft players with above-average intelligence. Punter/wide receiver [[Pat McInally]] attended [[Harvard University]] and linebacker Reggie Williams attended [[Dartmouth College]] and served on Cincinnati city council while on the Bengals' roster. Because of this policy, many former players were highly articulate and went on to have successful careers in [[Play-by-play|commentary]] and [[broadcasting]] as well as the arts. In addition, Brown had a knack for locating and recognizing pro football talent in unusual places.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Verderame|first1=Matt|title=Paul Brown and his Lasting Influence on the NFL|url=http://fansided.com/2016/09/06/paul-brown-nfl-browns-bengals-innovations/|website=Fansided|publisher=Sports Illustrated|accessdate=November 22, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1970, the Bengals moved to play at Riverfront Stadium, a home they shared with the [[Cincinnati Reds]] until the team moved to [[Paul Brown Stadium]] in [[2000 NFL season|2000]]. The team reached the playoffs three times during that decade, but could not win any of those postseason games. In [[1975 NFL season|1975]], the [[1975 Cincinnati Bengals season|team]] posted an 11–3 record, giving them what is to this day the highest winning percentage (.786) in franchise history. But it only earned them a wild card spot in the playoffs, behind the 12–2 [[1975 Pittsburgh Steelers season|Pittsburgh Steelers]], who went on to win the Super Bowl. The Bengals lost to the [[1975 Oakland Raiders season|Oakland Raiders]] 31–28 in the divisional playoffs.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.pro-football-reference.com/boxscores/197512280rai.htm|title=Divisional Round - Cincinnati Bengals at Oakland Raiders - December 28th, 1975 {{!}} Pro-Football-Reference.com|website=Pro-Football-Reference.com|language=en|access-date=March 15, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:QB Andy Dalton.jpg|thumb|right|200px|[[Andy Dalton (American football)|Andy Dalton]] takes a snap before a game against the Baltimore Ravens on January 1, 2012.]]

[[File:1986 Jeno's Pizza - 27 - Dan Bunz.jpg|thumb|left|The Bengals played against the 49ers in Super Bowl XVI (''pictured'') and XXIII, but lost in both games.]]
The Bengals reached the Super Bowl twice during the 1980s, in [[Super Bowl XVI]] and [[Super Bowl XXIII]], but lost both times to the [[San Francisco 49ers]]. The team appeared in the playoffs in [[1990 NFL season|1990]], making it to the second round  before losing to the Los Angeles Raiders. Before the [[1991 NFL Season|following season]] got underway, Paul Brown died at age 82. He had already transferred control to his son, [[Mike Brown (football team owner)|Mike Brown]], but was reported to still influence the daily operations of the team.  The Bengals' fortunes changed for the worse as the team posted 14 consecutive non-winning seasons and were saddled with numerous draft busts. They began to emerge from that dismal period into a new era of increased consistency, however, after the team finished with its worst record in history, 2–14, which led to the hiring of [[Marvin Lewis]] as head coach in 2003. [[Carson Palmer]], the future star quarterback, was drafted in [[2003 NFL Draft|2003]], but did not play a snap that whole season, as [[Jon Kitna]] had a comeback year (voted NFL Comeback Player of the Year). Despite Kitna's success, Palmer was promoted to starting quarterback the [[2004 NFL season|following season]]. Under Palmer, the team advanced to the playoffs for the first time since 1990 in the [[2005 NFL season|2005 season]], which also was the first time the team had a winning percentage above .500 since 1990.

The Bengals returned to the playoffs again in [[2009 NFL season|2009]] in a season that included the franchise's first ever division sweep. This was especially impressive since two of the teams swept by the Bengals (the Pittsburgh Steelers and the Baltimore Ravens) had both made it to the AFC Championship Game the previous season. Marvin Lewis was rewarded for the accomplishment with the NFL Coach of the Year Award.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/17/sports/football/17lewis.html|title=Bengals’ Lewis Is N.F.L. Coach of the Year|last=The Associated Press|date=January 16, 2010|work=The New York Times|access-date=March 15, 2017|issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[2010 NFL season|2010 season]], the Bengals posted a 4–12 record.

Following the disappointing 2010 season, quarterback Carson Palmer demanded to be traded.  When the Bengals refused to do so, Palmer announced his retirement from the NFL.  He later was moved at the NFL trade deadline to the [[Oakland Raiders]].  In the [[2011 NFL draft]], the Bengals selected wide receiver [[A. J. Green|AJ Green]] in the first round, and quarterback [[Andy Dalton]] in the second round.  The Bengals improved to 9–7 in the [[2011 NFL season|2011 season]], and clinched a playoff spot. Dalton and Green became the most prolific rookie WR-QB duo in history, connecting 65 times for 1,057 yards.  However, they lost to the [[Houston Texans]] 31–10 in the Wild Card Round. In the [[2012 NFL season|2012 season]], the Bengals clinched a playoff spot once more with a win over the [[Pittsburgh Steelers]], going to the playoffs in back-to-back years for the first time since 1982. However, the Bengals faced the Texans in the first round yet again and took another early exit, losing 19–13.

In the [[2013 NFL season|2013 season]], for the third straight year, the Bengals clinched a playoff berth and also won the AFC North, finishing with an 11–5 record. But once again, the Bengals were defeated in the wild card round, this time by the [[San Diego Chargers]], 27–10. Most of the blame was put on Andy Dalton, who threw 2 interceptions and fumbled on a forward dive. This made the Bengals 0–5 in playoff games since Mike Brown took over as owner. The [[2014 NFL season|2014 season]] started well with the Bengals winning their first three contests against the Baltimore Ravens, the Atlanta Falcons, and the Tennessee Titans. However, they lost their week 5 matchup at the New England Patriots, 43–17. An overtime tie to the [[Carolina Panthers]] and shutout loss to the [[Indianapolis Colts]] followed the primetime loss to the Patriots. Finishing the season 10–5–1 as the 5th seed, they lost to the Colts, 26–10, in the first round of the playoffs. This was the first time the franchise made the playoffs four straight seasons.

In 2015, the Bengals got out to a franchise-best 8–0 start with a 31–10 win over the [[Cleveland Browns]], but they then lost multiple consequtive games yet clinched a playoff berth.  However, they lost to the division rival [[Pittsburgh Steelers]], 18–16, in the Wild Card round in the final minute, making them the first franchise in NFL history to lose five straight opening round playoff games. This frustration continued in 2016 for the Bengals. The Bengals finished the 2016 campaign with a 6–9–1 record, losing several key players to injury including AJ Green, [[Giovani Bernard]], and [[Jeremy Hill]]. They missed the playoffs for the first time since 2010, marking the first time Andy Dalton missed the playoffs as the Bengals' starting quarterback. One notable game was a 27–27 tie against the [[Washington Redskins]] which was played in [[London]] in 2016.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://pro32.ap.org/article/redskins-bengals-battle-27-27-tie-london|title=Redskins, Bengals battle to 27-27 tie in London|date=October 30, 2016|work=Pro32: Head to Head|access-date=March 15, 2017|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following a rough 2016 season, the Bengals looked forward into 2017. However, after starting 0–3, the Bengals never found their footing. At one point in the season, the Bengals were 5–9. There were rumors that Marvin Lewis would not return for the next season as the Bengals' head coach. However, after two come-from-behind victories over the Lions and Ravens, that eliminated both teams from the playoffs, the Bengals finished 7–9.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.pro-football-reference.com/teams/cin/2017.htm |title=2017 Cincinnati Bengals Statistics &amp; Players |website=Pro-Football-Reference.com |language=en |access-date=June 16, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The final two games were convincing enough for owner Mike Brown to give Lewis a new two-year contract.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://abcnews.go.com/Sports/bengals-sign-marvin-lewis-year-deal-2019/story?id=52103182 |title=Bengals sign Marvin Lewis to two-year deal through 2019 |date=January 2, 2018 |work=ABC News |access-date=July 17, 2018 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2018 campaign began with promise for the Bengals under Lewis. Cincinnati began the season with a 4-1 record with impressive wins over the Colts, Ravens, Falcons, and the Dolphins. However, the Bengals suffered many setbacks after the hot start. Defensive Coordinator [[Teryl Austin]] was fired mid-season because of defensive woes,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nfl.com/news/story/0ap3000000987470/article/bengals-fire-dc-teryl-austin-after-loss-to-saints&lt;/ref&gt; AJ Green was injured and officially out for the last 4 games, and Andy Dalton injured his thumb in the Bengals' first game against the Browns and replaced by [[Jeff Driskel]] for the rest of the season. The Bengals ended 2018 with a final record of 6-10 and last place in the AFC North. On December 31, 2018, with one year to go on his contract, Lewis and the Bengals mutually parted ways after three straight losing seasons under his watch.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.espn.com/nfl/story/_/id/25653722/bengals-fire-coach-marvin-lewis-6-10-season |title=Marvin Lewis out as coach of Bengals after long run |last=Terrell |first=Katherine |publisher=ESPN |date=December 31, 2018 |access-date=December 31, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With Zac Taylor assuming the head coaching mantle, the 2019 campaign started off pretty well, barely losing to Seattle 21-20 in CenturyLink Field, but what started with promise, ended in disaster. The Bengals then lost 10 more games and were 0-11 heading into December 2019. To open the month of December, they got their first win against the Jets 22-6 in Cincinnati. They eventually lost to the Patriots and lost to the Dolphins 38-35 in OT after Dalton led the team back from 23 points down in the fourth quarter. With the loss to the Dolphins, the Bengals officially clinched the #1 Overall Pick in the 2020 NFL Draft. They'd cap off the season with a win against the underperforming Cleveland Browns, finishing 2-14, equaling the 2002 season as the team's worst record in history.

==Logos and uniforms==
When the team debuted in 1968, the Bengals' uniforms were modeled after the [[Cleveland Browns]]. When Paul Brown was fired by [[Art Modell]], Brown still owned the equipment used by Cleveland so, after the firing, Paul Brown packed up all his equipment which he then used for his new team in Cincinnati. The Cleveland Browns' team colors were brown, orange, and white, and their helmets were solid orange with a white dorsal stripe over the crest.

The Bengals' team colors were orange, black, and white, and their helmets were a similar shade of orange, with the only variations being the word &quot;Bengals&quot; in black block letters (with a white outline) on either side of the helmet and no stripe on the helmet. The Cincinnati Bengals were unique in the NFL as they did not have secondary uniform numbers on the jerseys (called ''TV numbers'') until the 1980 season, when they appeared on the sleeves; they were the only NFL team that did not have them prior to that point. That same year, the team changed their helmet facemask color from gray to black. The team did not discard their Cleveland-like uniforms until 1981. During that year, a then-unique uniform design was introduced. Although the team kept black jerseys, white jerseys, and white pants, they were now trimmed with orange and black tiger stripes. The team also introduced the orange helmets with black tiger stripes that are still in use today.

In 1997, the Bengals designed a logo consisting of a leaping tiger, and it was added to the uniform sleeves (with this, the ''TV numbers'' moved to the shoulder). Another alternate logo consisted of a Bengal's head facing to the left. However, the orange helmet with black tiger stripes continued to be the trademark. In 2004, a new tiger stripe pattern and more accents were added to the uniforms. The black jerseys now featured orange tiger-striped sleeves and white side panels, while the white jerseys began to use black tiger-striped sleeves and orange shoulders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=2004-Present: The New Stripes|url=http://www.bengals.com/team/history/uniforms-2004.html|publisher=Cincinnati Bengals|accessdate=September 30, 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090813104026/http://www.bengals.com/team/history/uniforms-2004.html|archive-date=August 13, 2009|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; A new logo consisting of an orange &quot;B&quot; covered with black tiger stripes was introduced.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Bengals Logos - Then &amp; Now|url=http://www.bengals.com/team/history/bengals-logos.html|publisher=NFL Enterprises, LLC|website=Bengals.com|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20091127142856/http://www.bengals.com/team/history/bengals-logos.html|archive-date=November 27, 2009|access-date=September 12, 2018|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; The team also started rotating black pants and debuted an alternate orange jersey, with white side panels and black tiger-striped sleeves. The Bengals have worn their black uniforms at home throughout their history, with some exceptions such as the 1970 season when the Bengals wore white at home for the entire season, and most of the 1971 season. Since 2005, the Bengals wear white for September home games where the heat could become a factor.

==Mascots==
The team's official mascot is a [[Bengal tiger]] named Who Dey.&lt;ref name=&quot;WhoDey&quot; /&gt; Aside from Who Dey, the team also has the [[Cincinnati Ben–Gals]], the team's [[NFL Cheerleading|cheerleading squad]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bengals.com/cheerleaders/index.html|title=Ben-Gals Cheerleaders Home|publisher=Bengals.com|accessdate=August 15, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; which included [[Laura Vikmanis]], the oldest cheerleader in league history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-1349473/Laura-Vikmanis-42-NFLs-oldest-cheerleader-Can-younger-girls.html|title=Laura Vikmanis, 42, is NFL's oldest cheerleader: Can she keep up with younger girls?|publisher=Dailymail.co.uk|date=January 22, 2011|accessdate=July 9, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Contributions to NFL culture==

===No-huddle offense===
A [[no-huddle offense]] was commonly used by all teams when time in the game was running low. However, [[Sam Wyche]], the head coach of the Bengals in 1988, along with offensive coordinator [[Bruce Coslet]], made the high-paced offense the standard modality for the ball club regardless of time remaining. By quickly substituting and setting up for the next play—often within 5–10 seconds after the last play despite being afforded 45 seconds—the Bengals hindered the other team's defense from substituting situational players, regrouping for tactical purpose, and resting. In response the NFL instituted rules allowing the defense ample time for substitutions when offensive substitutions were made.
The hurry-up tactic was used by the franchise during the late 1980s while Sam Wyche was the coach. A rival for AFC supremacy during this time was the [[Buffalo Bills]], coached by [[Marv Levy]], who also used a version of the no-huddle offense starting with the 1989 season.  The Bengals had beaten the Bills three times in 1988 (pre-season, regular season, and the AFC Championship Game). Marv Levy threatened to fake injuries if the Bengals used the &quot;no-huddle&quot; in the AFC Championship. Wyche was notified that the commissioner had ordered the &quot;no-huddle&quot; illegal for the game.  The official notified Wyche and the Bengals' team just two hours before the game kickoff.  Wyche asked to talk directly to the commissioner and word immediately came back that the &quot;no-huddle&quot; would not be penalized.  Levy did not have his players fake injuries in the game, but installed his version the next year, 1989.  The Bengals first used the &quot;no-huddle&quot; in 1984.  Most of the high-profile games (the various games for AFC titles and regular season games) between the two led to these changes in NFL rules.  Wyche also first used the timeout periods as an opportunity to bring his entire team to the sideline to talk to all eleven players, plus substitutes, at one time.  This allowed trainers time to treat a cut or bruise and equipment managers time to repair an equipment defect.

===West Coast offense===
The [[West Coast offense]] is the popular name for the high-percentage passing scheme designed by former Bengals assistant [[Bill Walsh (American football coach)|Bill Walsh]]. Walsh formulated what has become popularly known as the West Coast offense during his tenure as assistant coach for the Cincinnati Bengals from 1968 to 1975, while working under the tutelage of Brown (and before embarking on his legendary coaching tenure with the San Francisco 49ers in the 1980s). Bengals quarterback [[Virgil Carter]] was the first player to successfully implement Walsh's system, leading the NFL in pass completion percentage in 1971. [[Ken Anderson (quarterback)|Ken Anderson]] replaced Carter as Cincinnati's starting quarterback in 1972 and was even more successful. In 1975 he would bring widespread recognition to the West Coast offense as well as to the Cincinnati team and its quarterback in a nationally televised Monday night contest between the Bengals and a Buffalo Bills team built around the running game of star player [[O.J. Simpson]]. Anderson's 447 passing yards were enough to overcome Simpson's 197 yards on the ground in a game that proved a milestone, providing a striking contrast between the &quot;old&quot; game of defense-minded football and the new game of higher scores and more action through a sophisticated aerial attack. The game, in effect, offered its viewers a glimpse of the future of professional football. Anderson, who was drafted by Paul Brown in 1971 and installed as starting quarterback in 1972, made four trips to the Pro Bowl, won four passing titles, was named NFL MVP in 1981, and set the record for completion percentage in a single season in 1982 with 70.66%. Defeated frequently during the 1970s by the Pittsburgh Steelers, a team that won four Super Bowls with 9 future Hall of Fame players, the Bengals under Anderson and head coach Forrest Gregg would finally break through the [[Steel Curtain]], defeating the Steelers during both of their meetings in 1980 and again in 1981. Anderson, who had been named the &quot;team franchise&quot; by Bengal tight end [[Bob Trumpy]], would ultimately prove his worth with a career record of 91 wins and 81 losses, making him, to date, the Bengals' only winning quarterback.

===Zone blitz===
The defense created to combat the West Coast offense also came from Cincinnati. Then-Bengals [[defensive coordinator]] [[Dick LeBeau]] (who later served as the team's head coach from 2000–2002) created the [[zone blitz]] in the 1980s in response to the West Coast offense.

==Season-by-season records==
{{main|List of Cincinnati Bengals seasons}}

==Players of note==
{{Category see also|Cincinnati Bengals players}}

===Current roster===
{{Cincinnati Bengals roster}}

===Retired numbers===
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;
|-
| colspan=5 style=&quot;{{NFLPrimaryStyle|Cincinnati Bengals}};&quot;| '''Cincinnati Bengals retired numbers'''
|-
!  style=&quot;{{NFLAltPrimaryStyle|Cincinnati Bengals}};&quot;|No.
!  style=&quot;{{NFLAltPrimaryStyle|Cincinnati Bengals}};&quot;|Player
!  style=&quot;{{NFLAltPrimaryStyle|Cincinnati Bengals}};&quot;|Position
!  style=&quot;{{NFLAltPrimaryStyle|Cincinnati Bengals}};&quot;|Seasons
!  style=&quot;{{NFLAltPrimaryStyle|Cincinnati Bengals}};&quot;|Retired
|-
| '''54''' || [[Bob Johnson (American football)|Bob Johnson]] || [[Center (American football)|C]] || 1968–79 || December 17, 1978
|}

===Pro Football Hall of Fame members===
Three members of the Hall of Fame have spent some portion of their career with the Bengals, only one spent their entire career with the Bengals. Bengals founder and former coach Paul Brown is also in the Hall of Fame, however he was inducted before founding the Bengals and therefore is not recognized as a Bengals Hall of Famer.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;
|-
! colspan=&quot;5&quot; style=&quot;{{NFLPrimaryStyle|Cincinnati Bengals}};&quot; | Cincinnati Bengals Hall of Famers
|-
! colspan=&quot;5&quot; style=&quot;{{NFLAltPrimaryStyle|Cincinnati Bengals}};&quot; | Players
|-
! No.
! Name
! Position(s)
! Season(s)
! Inducted
|-&lt;!-- Do not add Paul Brown. His tenure with the Bengals is not recognized by the Hall of Fame as being why he was inducted --&gt;
| '''18''' || [[Charlie Joiner]] || [[Wide receiver|WR]] || 1972–1975 || 1996&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.profootballhof.com/hof/member.aspx?PlayerId=107 | title=Charlie Joiner | publisher=Pro Football Hall of Fame | accessdate=December 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| '''78''' || '''[[Anthony Muñoz]]''' || [[Offensive tackle|OT]] || 1980–1992 || 1998&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.profootballhof.com/hof/member.aspx?PlayerId=158 | title=Anthony Muñoz | publisher=Pro Football Hall of Fame | accessdate=December 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| '''81''' || [[Terrell Owens]] || [[Wide receiver|WR]] || 2010 || 2018
|}

===Cincinnati Bengals individual awards===
{{col-begin}}
{{col-3}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;
|-
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; style=&quot;{{NFLPrimaryStyle|Cincinnati Bengals}};&quot;| '''NFL MVP Winners'''
|-
!  style=&quot;{{NFLAltPrimaryStyle|Cincinnati Bengals}};&quot;| Season
!  style=&quot;{{NFLAltPrimaryStyle|Cincinnati Bengals}};&quot;| Player
!  style=&quot;{{NFLAltPrimaryStyle|Cincinnati Bengals}};&quot;| Position
|-
|[[1981 NFL season|1981]]||[[Ken Anderson (quarterback)|Ken Anderson]]||[[Quarterback|QB]]
|-
|[[1988 NFL season|1988]]||[[Boomer Esiason]]||[[Quarterback|QB]]
|}
{{col-3}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;
|-
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; style=&quot;{{NFLPrimaryStyle|Cincinnati Bengals}};&quot;| '''AFL/NFL Rookie of the Year'''
|-
!  style=&quot;{{NFLAltPrimaryStyle|Cincinnati Bengals}};&quot;| Season
!  style=&quot;{{NFLAltPrimaryStyle|Cincinnati Bengals}};&quot;| Player
!  style=&quot;{{NFLAltPrimaryStyle|Cincinnati Bengals}};&quot;| Position
|-
|[[1968 American Football League season|1968]]||[[Paul Robinson (American football player)|Paul Robinson]]||[[Running back|RB]]
|-
|[[1969 American Football League season|1969]]||[[Greg Cook]]||[[Quarterback|QB]]
|-
|[[1985 NFL season|1985]]||[[Eddie Brown (wide receiver)|Eddie Brown]]||[[Wide receiver|WR]]
|-
|[[1992 NFL season|1992]]||[[Carl Pickens]]||[[Wide receiver|WR]]
|}
{{col-3}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;{{NFLPrimaryStyle|Cincinnati Bengals}};&quot; nowrap| '''Maxwell Club NFL Coach of the Year'''
|-
!  style=&quot;{{NFLAltPrimaryStyle|Cincinnati Bengals}};&quot;| Season
!  style=&quot;{{NFLAltPrimaryStyle|Cincinnati Bengals}};&quot;|Coach
|-
|[[1969 American Football League season|1969]]|| rowspan=2|[[Paul Brown]]
|-
|[[1970 NFL Season|1970]]
|-
|[[2009 NFL season|2009]]||[[Marvin Lewis]]
|}
 {{col-end}}

===40th anniversary team===
In 2007, in celebration of their 40th anniversary the Bengals named an all-time team voted on by the fans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Bengals 40th Anniversary Team|url=http://www.bengals.com/team/history/all-time-team.html|website=Bengals.com|access-date=May 4, 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090326123454/http://www.bengals.com/team/history/all-time-team.html|archive-date=March 26, 2009|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;
|-
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;{{NFLPrimaryStyle|Cincinnati Bengals|border=2}};&quot;|Offense
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;{{NFLPrimaryStyle|Cincinnati Bengals|border=2}};&quot;|Defense
|-
|[[Carson Palmer]]||QB||[[Justin Smith (defensive end)|Justin Smith]]||DE
|-
|[[James Brooks (American football)|James Brooks]]||RB||[[Ross Browner]]||DE
|-
|[[Ickey Woods]]||FB||[[Tim Krumrie]]||DT
|-
|[[Chad Johnson]]||WR||[[Mike Reid (singer)|Mike Reid]]||DT
|-
|[[T. J. Houshmandzadeh]]||WR||[[Reggie Williams (linebacker)|Reggie Williams]]||LB
|-
|[[Dan Ross (American football)|Dan Ross]]||TE||[[Takeo Spikes]]||LB
|-
|[[Anthony Muñoz]]||T||[[Brian Simmons]]||LB
|-
|[[Willie Anderson (American football)|Willie Anderson]]||T||[[Ken Riley]]||CB
|-
|[[Max Montoya]]||G||[[Lemar Parrish]]||CB
|-
|[[Dave Lapham]]||G||[[David Fulcher]]||S
|-
|[[Rich Braham]]||C||[[Solomon Wilcots]]||S
|-
!colspan=&quot;4&quot; style=&quot;{{NFLPrimaryStyle|Cincinnati Bengals|border=2}};&quot;|Special Teams
|-
|colspan=&quot;4&quot;|[[Shayne Graham]] (K), [[Lee Johnson (punter)|Lee Johnson]] (P)
|}&lt;/center&gt;

==Coaching staff==
===Head coaches===
{{main|List of Cincinnati Bengals head coaches}}

===Current staff===
{{Cincinnati Bengals staff}}

==Radio and television==
{{Further|List of Cincinnati Bengals broadcasters|Cincinnati Bengals Radio Network}}
The Bengals contract with [[iHeartMedia]] as their radio partner, with their flagship radio stations being [[WCKY (AM)|WCKY]] (1530) and [[WEBN]] (102.7 FM), along with [[WLW]] (700) if not in conflict with the [[Cincinnati Reds|Reds]]. Most preseason and regular season games, are telecast on [[CBS]] affiliate [[WKRC-TV]] (channel 12). The current TV announcers for preseason games are [[Dan Hoard]] on play-by-play, and [[Dave Lapham]] as analyst.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Cincinnati Bengals weekly news release|url=http://prod.static.bengals.clubs.nfl.com/assets/docs/weekly-releases/2016/reg-week-11-bengals.pdf|website=bengals.com|publisher=Cincinnati Bengals|accessdate=November 22, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Chant==
&quot;Who Dey?!&quot; is the name of a chant of support by fans of the Cincinnati Bengals, in use since the 1980s. The entire chant is: &quot;Who dey, who dey, who dey think gonna beat dem Bengals?&quot; The answer screamed in unison, &quot;Nobody.&quot; Sometimes fans will instead shout &quot;Who Dey?&quot; to represent the entire cheer. &quot;Who Dey&quot; is also the name of the team's [[mascot]], a [[Bengal tiger]].&lt;ref name=&quot;WhoDey&quot; /&gt;

The Who Dey chant was first known to be used by fans of the [[1980 Cincinnati Bengals season|1980 Cincinnati Bengals]]. While the origins of the chant is disputed, one possible source for the chant is a 1980 commercial for (the now-defunct) Red Frazier Ford of Cincinnati, which used this tagline: &quot;Who's going to give you a better deal than Red Frazier?...Nobody!&quot; Cincinnati fans who had seen the commercial many times may have just copied it when cheering.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://fifthdown.blogs.nytimes.com/2006/12/14/who-dey-vs-who-dat/ | title=Who Dey vs. Who Dat | work=[[The New York Times]] | date=December 14, 2006 | accessdate=June 15, 2011 | author=Monkovic, Toni}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Who Dey chant is also steeped in local beer lore. Hudy, a leading product of [[Hudepohl Brewing Company]] through the late 1980s, bears a phonetic similarity to the &quot;Who Dey&quot; chant. Beer vendors who carried full cases of bottled local beer up and down the steep upper stairs of what was then Riverfront Stadium would call out &quot;If Hudy&quot;, &quot;Berger&quot; and other local beer names. Raucous fans would often chant back and forth with them as the vendors called out. During the 1980 season the banter with the Hudepohl vendors grew organically into the now famous (Hu-Dey) -Who They?- chant.&lt;ref&gt;This is an eye witness account from a Cincinnati Bengals season ticket holder.  This family held season tickets for the Bengals from their inaugural season in 1968 through the 2000 season when the Bengals moved to Paul Brown Stadium.&lt;/ref&gt;

The chant bears some similarities to the phrase &quot;[[Who Dat?]]&quot;, which was officially adopted by the [[New Orleans Saints]] in 1983 but had been used by Louisiana's high school team fans for some time. The saying &quot;Who Dat?&quot; originated in [[minstrel shows]] and vaudeville acts in the late 19th and early 20th centuries, then it was taken up by [[Dixieland|New Orleans Jazz]] and various Big band folks in the 1920s and 1930s. In the late 1960s, local [[Louisiana]] High Schools, [[St. Augustine High School (New Orleans)|St. Augustine High School]] and [[Patterson High School (Louisiana)|Patterson High School]] reportedly have been using the cheer and Gulf Coast fans of [[Alcorn State University]] and [[Louisiana State University]] picked up the cheer in the 1970s. [[Southern University]] in Baton Rouge, Louisiana claims to have originated the cheer in the late 1960s in their version: &quot;Who dat talking 'bout beating dem Jags?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.2theadvocate.com/features/80308957.html |title=Where dat from? |website=2theadvocate.com |date=December 30, 2009 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100127191420/http://www.2theadvocate.com/features/80308957.html |archive-date=January 27, 2010 |url-status=dead |access-date=May 23, 2015 |last=Morris |first=George}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{commons category}}
* {{Official website}}

{{Cincinnati Bengals}}
{{Navboxes
|titlestyle = {{NFLPrimaryStyle|Cincinnati Bengals|border=2}}
|list =
{{NFL}}
{{American Football League navbox}}
{{Ohio Sports}}
}}
{{Portal bar|American football|Ohio}}

[[Category:Cincinnati Bengals| ]]
[[Category:National Football League teams]]
[[Category:1968 establishments in Ohio]]
[[Category:American football teams established in 1968]]
[[Category:American Football League teams]]</text>
      <sha1>1y1bx33lj8zcxjw0ecpiy91kamk0gb9</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
