  <page>
    <title>Cleveland Indians</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6652</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941609747</id>
      <parentid>941148214</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-19T16:43:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Arjayay</username>
        <id>5718152</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>a &gt; an</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{other uses}}
{{short description|Baseball team and Major League Baseball franchise in Cleveland, Ohio, United States}}
{{Infobox MLB
| name = Cleveland Indians
| established = 1894
| misc =
| logo = Cleveland Indians primary logo.svg
| uniformlogo = Cleveland Indians cap logo.svg
| current league = American League
| y1 = 1901
| division = [[American League Central|Central Division]]
| y2 = 1994
| past division = [[American League East|East Division]]
| y5 = 1969
| y6 = 1993
| Uniform = MLB-ALC-CLE-Uniform.png
| retirednumbers = {{hlist| [[Earl Averill|3]] | [[Lou Boudreau|5]] | [[Larry Doby|14]] | [[Mel Harder|18]] | [[Bob Feller|19]] |[[Frank Robinson|20]] | [[Bob Lemon|21]] | [[Jim Thome|25]] | [[Jackie Robinson|42]] | 455 }}
| colors = Red, navy blue, white&lt;br /&gt;{{color box|#E31937}} {{color box|#002B5C}} {{color box|#FFFFFF}}
| y3 = 1915
| nicknames = The Tribe, The Wahoos
| pastnames =
* Cleveland Naps ({{baseball year|1903}}–{{baseball year|1914}})
* Cleveland Broncos ({{baseball year|1902}})
* Cleveland Bluebirds ({{baseball year|1901}})
* Cleveland Lake Shores ({{baseball year|1900}})
* Grand Rapids Rustlers ({{baseball year|1894}}–{{baseball year|1899}})
| ballpark = [[Progressive Field]]
| y4 = 1994
| pastparks =
* [[Cleveland Stadium]] ({{MLBy|1932}}–{{MLBy|1933}}, {{MLBy|1937}}–{{MLBy|1993}})
** nights, weekends, and select games from {{MLBy|1937}}–{{MLBy|1946}}
* [[League Park]] ({{MLBy|1901}}–{{MLBy|1932}}, {{MLBy|1934}}–{{MLBy|1946}})
| WS = (2)
| WORLD CHAMPIONS = {{hlist| {{wsy|1920}} | {{wsy|1948}} }}
| LEAGUE = AL
| P = (6)
| PENNANTS = {{hlist| [[1920 Cleveland Indians season|1920]] | [[1948 American League tie-breaker game|1948]] | [[1954 Cleveland Indians season|1954]] | [[1995 American League Championship Series|1995]] | [[1997 American League Championship Series|1997]] | [[2016 American League Championship Series|2016]]}}
| misc1 =
| OTHER PENNANTS =
| DIV = Central
| DV = (10)
| Division Champs = {{hlist| [[1995 Cleveland Indians season|1995]] | [[1996 Cleveland Indians season|1996]] | [[1997 Cleveland Indians season|1997]] | [[1998 Cleveland Indians season|1998]] | [[1999 Cleveland Indians season|1999]] | [[2001 Cleveland Indians season|2001]] | [[2007 Cleveland Indians season|2007]] | [[2016 Cleveland Indians season|2016]] | [[2017 Cleveland Indians season|2017]] | [[2018 Cleveland Indians season|2018]]}}
| misc5 =
| OTHER DIV CHAMPS =
| WC = (1)
| Wild Card = [[2013 Cleveland Indians season|2013]]
| misc6 =
| owner = [[Larry Dolan]] (principal owner)&lt;br /&gt;[[Paul Dolan (baseball)|Paul Dolan]] (controlling owner/[[Chairman]]/[[CEO]])&lt;br /&gt;[[Matt Dolan]] (part owner) 
| presbo = [[Chris Antonetti]]
| gm = [[Mike Chernoff (baseball)|Mike Chernoff]]
| manager = [[Terry Francona]]
}}

The '''Cleveland Indians''' are an American professional [[baseball]] team based in [[Cleveland]], [[Ohio]]. They compete in [[Major League Baseball]] (MLB) as a member club of the [[American League]] (AL) [[American League Central|Central division]]. Since {{baseball year|1994}}, they have played at [[Progressive Field]]. The team's [[spring training]] facility is at [[Goodyear Ballpark]] in [[Goodyear, Arizona]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Goodyear Ballpark|url=https://www.mlb.com/indians/spring-training/ballpark|publisher=[[MLB Advanced Media]]|website=Indians.com|access-date=July 4, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since their establishment as a major league franchise in 1901, the team has won 10 Central Division titles, six [[List of American League pennant winners|American League pennants]], and two [[World Series]] championships, (in [[1920 World Series|1920]] and [[1948 World Series|1948]]). The team's current 71-year World Series championship drought is the [[List of Major League Baseball franchise postseason droughts#Longest current World Series championship drought|longest active]] among all 30 current Major League teams.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Axisa|first=Mike|title=Now that Cubs are champs, Indians have MLB's longest World series drought|url=http://www.cbssports.com/mlb/news/now-that-the-cubs-are-champs-the-indians-have-baseballs-longest-world-series-drought/|publisher=[[CBS Sports]]|date=November 3, 2016|accessdate=November 3, 2016|quote=So, with the Cubs finally on top, the longest championship drought in baseball now belongs to the team they beat - the Indians. Cleveland has not won a World Series since way back in 1948.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The name &quot;Indians&quot; originated from a request by club owner [[Charles Somers]] to baseball writers to choose a new name to replace &quot;Cleveland Naps&quot; following the departure of [[Nap Lajoie]] after the 1914 season. It was a revival of the nickname that fans gave to the [[Cleveland Spiders]] while [[Louis Sockalexis]], a [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]], was playing for the team.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The early years–Indians History Overview|url=http://cleveland.indians.mlb.com/cle/history/cle_history_overview.jsp|publisher=MLB Advanced Media|website=Indians.com|accessdate=March 23, 2016|quote=The Naps lost a then franchise record 102 games in 1914 and attendance sank to disastrous lows as the Lajoie era in Cleveland came to a close. Lajoie's departure, following the 1914 season, prompted a name change for the Cleveland franchise. On January 17, two Cleveland newspapers (''The Leader'' and ''The Plain Dealer'') reported that Indians had been chosen to replace Naps. ''The Plain Dealer'' said, &quot;President Somers invited the Cleveland baseball writers to make the selection. The title of Indians was their choice, it having been one of the names applied to the old National League club of Cleveland many years ago.&quot; When Chief Sockalexis first arrived, baseball in Cleveland suffered an abrupt downturn in fortune. Now, the Indians would rise to glory with a new owner and star player.}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Common [[List of baseball nicknames|nicknames]] for the Indians include the &quot;Tribe&quot; and the &quot;Wahoos&quot;, the latter referencing their former logo, [[Chief Wahoo]]. The team's mascot is named &quot;Slider.&quot;

The franchise originated in 1894 as the '''Grand Rapids Rustlers''', a minor league team in the [[Western League (1885–1899)|Western League]]. The team relocated to Cleveland in 1900 and was renamed the '''Cleveland Lake Shores'''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Adler|first1=David|last2=Kelly|first2=Matt|title=History lesson: 20 amazing Cubs and Indians facts|url=https://www.mlb.com/news/20-amazing-cubs-and-indians-facts/c-206973260|publisher=[[MLB Advanced Media]]|website=MLB.com|date=October 23, 2016|access-date=July 4, 2019|quote=The Indians' history actually begins in Grand Rapids, Mich., where they were known as the Grand Rapids Rustlers of the Western League from 1894-99. The franchise then moved to Cleveland and became known as the Lake Shores before joining the brand-new American League as the Bluebirds in 1901.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Western League itself was renamed the American League while continuing its minor league status. One of the American League's eight charter franchises, the major league incarnation of the club was founded in Cleveland in [[1901 Major League Baseball season|1901]]. Originally called the '''Cleveland Bluebirds''', the team played in [[League Park]] until moving permanently to [[Cleveland Stadium]] in [[1946 Major League Baseball season|1946]]. At the end of the 2019 season, they had a regular season franchise record of {{Win-loss record|w=9,477|l=9,037}} ({{winpct|9477|9037}}). From August 24 to September 14, 2017, the Indians won 22 consecutive games, the [[List of Major League Baseball longest winning streaks|longest winning streak]] in American League history.

==Cleveland baseball prior to the Indians franchise==
''&quot;In 1857 baseball games were a daily spectacle in Cleveland's Public Squares. City authorities tried to find an ordinance forbidding it, to the joy of the crowd, they were unsuccessful.&amp;nbsp;– Harold Seymour&quot;'' &lt;ref&gt;[[#Harold60|Harold 1960]]: 4&lt;/ref&gt;

;1865–1868 Forest Citys of Cleveland ''(Amateur)''
;1869–1872 Forest Citys of Cleveland
[[File:Forest Citys.jpg|thumb|Forest City Baseball Club]]

From 1865 to 1868 Forest Citys was an amateur ball club. During the [[1869 in baseball|1869]] season, Cleveland was among several cities that established professional baseball teams following the success of the 1869 [[Cincinnati Red Stockings]], the first fully professional team.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.todayifoundout.com/index.php/2011/04/the-first-professional-baseball-team-was-the-1869-cincinnati-red-stockings/|title=The First Professional Baseball Team Was the 1869 Cincinnati Red Stockings|date=2011-04-04|work=Today I Found Out|access-date=2017-10-13|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3ZyJHkplESoC&amp;pg=PA36&amp;lpg=PA36&amp;dq=the+success+of+the+1869+Cincinnati+Red+Stockings,+the+first+fully+professional+team&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=JokIHBAFsX&amp;sig=DYd8Yrk8yLTHW1aq2GXtZC_NVTM&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwik_qX6--3WAhUC34MKHd23A90Q6AEIVzAG#v=onepage&amp;q=the%20success%20of%20the%201869%20Cincinnati%20Red%20Stockings,%20the%20first%20fully%20professional%20team&amp;f=false|title=Ohio, the Buckeye State|last=Martin|first=Michael A.|date=2001|publisher=Gareth Stevens|year=|isbn=9780836851243|location=|pages=|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the newspapers before and after 1870, the team was often called the [[Cleveland Forest Citys|Forest Citys]], in the same generic way that the team from Chicago was sometimes called The Chicagos.

In [[1871 in baseball|1871]] the Forest Citys joined the new [[National Association of Professional Base Ball Players]] (NA), the first professional league. Ultimately, two of the league's western clubs went out of business during the first season and the [[1871 Great Chicago Fire|Chicago Fire]] left that city's [[Chicago Cubs|White Stockings]] impoverished, unable to field a team again until [[1874 in baseball|1874]]. Cleveland was thus the NA's westernmost outpost in [[1872 in baseball|1872]], the year the club folded. Cleveland played its full schedule to July 19 followed by two games versus Boston in mid-August and disbanded at the end of the season.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The 1872 Cleveland Forest Citys |url=http://www.retrosheet.org/boxesetc/1872/TCL101872.htm |publisher=retrosheet.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;1879–1881 Cleveland Forest Citys
;1882–1884 Cleveland Blues

In [[1876 in baseball|1876]], the [[National League]] (NL) supplanted the NA as the major professional league. Cleveland was not among its charter members, but by [[1879 in baseball|1879]] the league was looking for new entries and the city gained an NL team.  The Cleveland Forest Citys were recreated, but rebranded in 1882 as the [[Cleveland Blues (NL)|Cleveland Blues]], because the National League required distinct colors for that season.  The Blues had mediocre records for six seasons and were ruined by a trade war with the [[Union Association]] (UA) in [[1884 in baseball|1884]], when its three best players ([[Fred Dunlap]], [[Jack Glasscock]], and [[Jim McCormick (pitcher)|Jim McCormick]]) jumped to the UA after being offered higher salaries.  The Cleveland Blues merged with the St. Louis Maroons UA team in [[1885 in baseball|1885]].

;1887–1899 Cleveland Spiders&amp;nbsp;— nickname &quot;Blues&quot;

Cleveland went without major league baseball for two seasons until gaining a team in the [[American Association (19th century)|American Association]] (AA) in [[1887 in baseball|1887]]. After the AA's [[Pittsburgh Alleghenys|Allegheny club]] jumped to the NL, Cleveland followed suit in [[1889 in baseball|1889]], as the AA began to crumble. The Cleveland ball club, named the [[Cleveland Spiders|Spiders]] (supposedly inspired by their &quot;skinny and spindly&quot; players) slowly became a power in the league.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book  | last =Schneider  | first = Russell  | authorlink =  | title = Cleveland Indians Encyclopedia  | publisher = Sports Publishing LLC  | year = 2001  | location =  | page =9
  | url = https://books.google.com/?id=9jkqN0qu-fcC  | doi =  | id =  | isbn = 1-58261-376-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; The next year the Spiders moved into [[League Park]], which would serve as the home of Cleveland professional baseball for the next 55 years. Led by native Ohioan [[Cy Young]], the Spiders became a contender in the mid-1890s, playing in the [[Temple Cup]] Series (that era's World Series) twice and winning it in [[1895 in baseball|1895]]. The team began to fade after this success, and was dealt a severe blow under the ownership of the [[Robison Field|Robison brothers]].

Prior to the {{baseball year|1899}} season, Frank Robison, the Spiders' owner, bought the [[St. Louis Browns (NL)|St. Louis Browns]], thus owning two clubs at the same time. The Browns were renamed the &quot;Perfectos&quot;, and restocked with Cleveland talent. Just weeks before the season opener, most of the better Spiders were transferred to St. Louis, including three future Hall of Famers: Cy Young, [[Jesse Burkett]] and [[Bobby Wallace (baseball)|Bobby Wallace]].
&lt;ref name=perfectos&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wcnet.org/~dlfleitz/cleve.htm |title=The 1899 Cleveland Spiders |accessdate=2008-07-27 |work=David Fleitz |publisher=wcnet.org |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080501205105/http://www.wcnet.org/~dlfleitz/cleve.htm |archivedate=May 1, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
The roster maneuvers failed to create a powerhouse Perfectos team, as St. Louis finished fifth in both 1899 and {{baseball year|1900}}. The Spiders were left with essentially a minor league lineup, and began to lose games at a record pace. Drawing almost no fans at home, they ended up playing most of their season on the road, and became known as &quot;The Wanderers.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book  | last = Hittner  | first = Arthur  | authorlink = | title = Honus Wagner: The Life of Baseball's Flying Dutchman  | publisher = McFarland &amp; Company  | series =  | year = 2003  | doi =  | isbn = 0-7864-1811-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The team ended the season in 12th place, 84 games out of first place, with an all-time worst record of 20-134 (.130 winning percentage).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://espn.go.com/sportscentury/features/00016661.html|title=Bob Diskin, Special to ESPN.com, ''A pitcher worthy of a trophy''|publisher=|accessdate=14 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Following the 1899 season, the National League disbanded four teams, including the Spiders franchise. The disastrous 1899 season would actually be a step toward a new future for Cleveland fans the next year.

;1890, Cleveland Infants&amp;nbsp;— nickname &quot;Babes&quot;

The Cleveland Infants competed in the [[Players' League]], which was well-attended in some cities, but club owners lacked the confidence to continue beyond the one season. The Cleveland Infants finished with 55 wins and 75 losses, playing their home games at [[Brotherhood Park]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.projectballpark.org/history/pl/brotherhood.html|title=Project Ballpark|publisher=|accessdate=14 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Franchise history==
{{main|History of the Cleveland Indians}}

===1894–1935: Beginning to middle===
The '''Grand Rapids Rustlers''' were founded in Michigan in 1894 and were part of the [[Western League (1885–1899)|Western League]].  In 1900 the team moved to Cleveland and was named the '''Cleveland Lake Shores'''. Around the same time [[Ban Johnson]] changed the name of his minor league (Western League) to the American League.  In 1900 the American League was still considered a minor league.  In 1901 team was renamed the '''Cleveland Bluebirds''' when the American League broke with the National Agreement and declared itself a competing Major League.  The Cleveland franchise was among its eight charter members, and is one of four teams that remain in its original city, along with [[Boston Red Sox|Boston]], [[Chicago White Sox|Chicago]], and [[Detroit Tigers|Detroit]].

[[File:Nap Lajoie 1913.jpg|left|thumb|upright|[[Nap Lajoie]], who won the 1903 American League Batting Championship with the Indians, was the team's namesake from 1903–15, and an [[MLB Hall of Fame]]r.]]
The new team was owned by coal magnate [[Charles Somers]] and tailor Jack Kilfoyl. Somers, a wealthy industrialist and also co-owner of the [[Boston Americans]], lent money to other team owners, including [[Connie Mack]]'s [[Philadelphia Athletics]], to keep them and the new league afloat. Players didn't think the name &quot;Bluebirds&quot; was suitable for a baseball team.&lt;ref name=&quot;TBT&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Team-by-Team Encyclopedia of Major League Baseball |last=Purdy |first=Dennis |authorlink= |year=2006 |publisher=[[Workman Publishing Company|Workman]] |location=New York City |isbn=0-7611-3943-5 |pages= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Writers frequently shortened it to '''Cleveland Blues''' due to the players' all-blue uniforms,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last =Schneider | first = Russell | authorlink = | title = Cleveland Indians Encyclopedia | publisher = Sports Publishing LLC | year = 2001  | location = | page =11  | url = https://books.google.com/?id=9jkqN0qu-fcC | doi = | id=
  | isbn = 1-58261-376-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;  but the players didn't like this unofficial name either.{{citation needed|date=October 2012}}  The players themselves tried to change the name to '''Cleveland Broncos''' in {{baseball year|1902}}, but this unofficial name never really caught on.&lt;ref name=&quot;TBT&quot;/&gt;

The Bluebirds suffered from financial problems in their first two seasons. This led Somers to seriously consider moving to either [[Pittsburgh]] or [[Cincinnati]]. Relief came in 1902 as a result of the conflict between the National and American Leagues.  In 1901, [[Nap Lajoie|Napoleon &quot;Nap&quot; Lajoie]], the [[Philadelphia Phillies]]' star second baseman, jumped to the A's after his contract was capped at $2,400 per year—one of the highest-profile players to jump to the upstart AL. The Phillies subsequently filed an injunction to force Lajoie's return, which was granted by the [[Pennsylvania Supreme Court]]. The injunction appeared to doom any hopes of an early settlement between the warring leagues.  However, a lawyer discovered that the injunction was only enforceable in the state of Pennsylvania.&lt;ref name=&quot;TBT&quot;/&gt; Mack, partly to thank Somers for his past financial support, agreed to trade Lajoie to the then-moribund Blues, who offered $25,000 salary over three years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last =Schneider | first = Russell | authorlink = | title = Cleveland Indians Encyclopedia | publisher = Sports Publishing LLC | year = 2001  | location = | pages =12–13  | url = https://books.google.com/?id=9jkqN0qu-fcC | doi = | id= | isbn = 1-58261-376-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Due to the injunction, however, Lajoie had to sit out any games played against the A's in Philadelphia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last =Seymour | first = Harold | authorlink = | title = Baseball | publisher = Oxford University Press, US | year =1960 | location = | pages =214–215 | url = https://books.google.com/?id=zQO-WWL1v1AC | doi = | id = | isbn =0-19-500100-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Lajoie arrived in Cleveland on June 4 and was an immediate hit, drawing 10,000 fans to League Park.  Soon afterward, he was named team captain, and in 1903 the team was renamed the '''Cleveland Napoleons''' (soon shortened to '''Naps''') after a newspaper conducted a write-in contest.&lt;ref name=&quot;TBT&quot;/&gt;

Lajoie was named manager in {{MLBy|1905}}, and the team's fortunes improved somewhat. They finished half a game short of the pennant in 1908.&lt;ref name=1908AL&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.baseball-reference.com/leagues/AL_1908.shtml |title=1908 American League Standings |accessdate=2008-06-19 |work=Baseball-Reference.com |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090215121155/http://www.baseball-reference.com/leagues/AL_1908.shtml |archive-date=2009-02-15 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, the success did not last and Lajoie resigned during the 1909 season as manager but remained on as a player.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last =Schneider | first = Russell | authorlink = | title = Cleveland Indians Encyclopedia | publisher = Sports Publishing LLC | year = 2001 | location = | page =319 | url = https://books.google.com/?id=9jkqN0qu-fcC | doi = | id = | isbn = 1-58261-376-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:1909 Cleveland Naps.jpg|thumb|right|[[1909 Cleveland Naps season|1909 Cleveland Naps]]]]
After that, the team began to unravel, leading Kilfoyl to sell his share of the team to Somers. [[Cy Young]], who returned to Cleveland in 1909, was ineffective for most of his three remaining years&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last =Schneider | first = Russell | authorlink = | title = Cleveland Indians Encyclopedia | publisher = Sports Publishing LLC | year = 2001 | location = | page =413 | url = https://books.google.com/?id=9jkqN0qu-fcC | doi = | id = | isbn = 1-58261-376-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Addie Joss]] died from tubercular meningitis prior to the [[1911 Major League Baseball season|1911]] season.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= |last= |authorlink= |title=Obituary, Pitcher Joss Dead: Ill Only Few Days |url=https://timesmachine.nytimes.com/timesmachine/1911/04/15/104862167.pdf |work=New York Times |publisher= |date=April 15, 1911 |accessdate=2008-06-20 | format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite a strong lineup anchored by the potent Lajoie and [[Shoeless Joe Jackson]], poor pitching kept the team below third place for most of the next decade. One reporter referred to the team as the Napkins, &quot;because they fold up so easily&quot;. The team hit bottom in 1914 and 1915, finishing in the cellar both years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.baseball-reference.com/leagues/AL_1914.shtml |title=1914 American League Standings |accessdate=2008-06-27 |work=Baseball-Reference.com |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080704131724/http://www.baseball-reference.com/leagues/AL_1914.shtml |archive-date=2008-07-04 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.baseball-reference.com/leagues/AL_1915.shtml |title=1915 American League Standings |accessdate=2008-06-27 |work=Baseball-Reference.com |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080622121215/http://www.baseball-reference.com/leagues/AL_1915.shtml |archive-date=2008-06-22 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

1915 brought significant changes to the team. Lajoie, nearly 40 years old, was no longer a top hitter in the league, batting only .258 in 1914. With Lajoie engaged in a feud with manager [[Joe Birmingham]], the team sold Lajoie back to the A's.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last =Schneider | first = Russell | authorlink = | title = Cleveland Indians Encyclopedia | publisher = Sports Publishing LLC | year = 2001 | location = | page =321 | url = https://books.google.com/?id=9jkqN0qu-fcC | doi = | id = | isbn = 1-58261-376-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With Lajoie gone, the club needed a new name. Somers asked the local baseball writers to come up with a new name, and based on their input, the team was renamed the '''Cleveland Indians'''.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Baseball writers select 'Indians' as the best name to apply to the former Naps&quot; ''[[The Plain Dealer]]'' January 17, 1915: 15&lt;/ref&gt; The name referenced the nickname &quot;Indians&quot; that was applied to the [[Cleveland Spiders]] baseball club during the time when [[Louis Sockalexis]], a [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]], played in Cleveland (1897–99).&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Looking Backwards&quot; ''The Plain Dealer'' January 18, 1915: 8&lt;/ref&gt;

At the same time, Somers' business ventures began to fail, leaving him deeply in debt. With the Indians playing poorly, attendance and revenue suffered.&lt;ref name=Somers&gt;{{cite book| author=Lewis, Franklin| chapter=| title=The Cleveland Indians | editor=| publisher=Kent State University Press reprint from Putnam| isbn= 978-0-87338-885-6
| year=2006| pages=76–77}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Somers decided to trade Jackson midway through the 1915 season for two players and $31,500, one of the largest sums paid for a player at the time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| author=Ratajczak, Kenneth| chapter=| title=The Wrong Man Out| editor=| publisher=AuthorHouse |year=2008 | isbn= 1-4343-5678-7| pages=76–77| url=https://books.google.com/books?id=h9URNmfOwFIC&amp;pg=PA27&amp;dq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By [[1916 Major League Baseball season|1916]], Somers was at the end of his tether, and sold the team to a syndicate headed by Chicago railroad contractor [[Jim Dunn (baseball owner)|James C. &quot;Jack&quot; Dunn]].&lt;ref name=Somers/&gt;  Manager Lee Fohl, who had taken over in early 1915, acquired two minor league pitchers, [[Stan Coveleski]] and [[Jim Bagby, Sr.|Jim Bagby]] and traded for center fielder [[Tris Speaker]], who was engaged in a salary dispute with the [[Boston Red Sox|Red Sox]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last =Schneider | first = Russell | authorlink = | title = Cleveland Indians Encyclopedia | publisher = Sports Publishing LLC | year = 2001 | location = | pages =23–24 | url = https://books.google.com/?id=9jkqN0qu-fcC | doi = | id =  | isbn = 1-58261-376-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;  All three would ultimately become key players in bringing a championship to Cleveland.

{{Wide image|1920 Cleveland Indians Pano.jpg|800px|The 1920 Indians, who won the first World Series Championship in team history.|right}}
Speaker took over the reins as [[player-manager]] in {{MLBy|1919}}, and led the team to a championship in 1920. On August 16, 1920, the Indians were playing the [[1920 New York Yankees season|Yankees]] at the [[Polo Grounds]] in New York. Shortstop [[Ray Chapman]], who often crowded the plate, was batting against [[Carl Mays]], who had an unusual underhand delivery. It was also late in the afternoon and the infield was completely shaded with the center field area (the batters' background) bathed in sunlight. As well, at the time, &quot;part of every pitcher's job was to dirty up a new ball the moment it was thrown onto the field. By turns, they smeared it with dirt, licorice, tobacco juice; it was deliberately scuffed, sandpapered, scarred, cut, even spiked. The result was a misshapen, earth-colored ball that traveled through the air erratically, tended to soften in the later innings, and as it came over the plate, was very hard to see.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Ward|first=Geoffrey C. |author2=Burns, Ken|title=Baseball: An Illustrated History|publisher=Knopf |year=1996|page=153|isbn=0-679-76541-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In any case, Chapman did not move reflexively when Mays' pitch came his way. The pitch hit Chapman in the head, fracturing his skull. Chapman died the next day, becoming the only player to sustain a fatal injury from a pitched ball.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/packages/html/sports/year_in_sports/08.17.html|title=Report of Chapman's Death|work= New York Times|date=1920-08-01|publisher=|accessdate=14 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Indians, who at the time were locked in a tight three-way pennant race with the Yankees and [[1920 Chicago White Sox season|White Sox]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Standings&amp;nbsp;– Monday, Aug 16, 1920 |url=https://www.baseball-reference.com/games/standings.cgi?date=1920-08-16 | website=Baseball-Reference.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; were not slowed down by the death of their teammate. Rookie [[Joe Sewell]] hit .329 after replacing Chapman in the lineup.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Ira |last=Berkow |authorlink= |title=SPORTS OF THE TIMES; When Sewell Replaced Ray Chapman  |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1989/10/13/sports/sports-of-the-times-when-sewell-replaced-ray-chapman.html|work=New York Times |publisher= |date=1989-10-13 |accessdate=2008-06-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 1920, the [[Black Sox Scandal]] came to a boil. With just a few games left in the season, and Cleveland and Chicago neck-and-neck for first place at 94–54 and 95–56 respectively,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=CLE 1920 Cleveland Indians Schedule |url=http://www.baseball-almanac.com/teamstats/schedule.php?y=1920&amp;t=CLE |work=Baseball Almanac |accessdate=2009-02-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=1920 Chicago White Sox Schedule |url=http://www.baseball-almanac.com/teamstats/schedule.php?y=1920&amp;t=CHA |publisher=Baseball Almanac |accessdate=2009-02-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Chicago owner suspended eight players. The White Sox lost two of three in their final series, while Cleveland won four and lost two in their final two series. Cleveland finished two games ahead of Chicago and three games ahead of the Yankees to win its first pennant, led by Speaker's .388 hitting, Jim Bagby's 30 victories and solid performances from [[Steve O'Neill]] and Stan Coveleski. Cleveland went on to defeat the [[1920 Brooklyn Robins season|Brooklyn Robins]] 5–2 in the [[1920 World Series|World Series]] for their first title, winning four games in a row after the Robins took a 2–1 Series lead. The Series included three memorable &quot;firsts&quot;, all of them in Game 5 at Cleveland, and all by the home team. In the first inning, right fielder [[Elmer Smith (20th century outfielder)|Elmer Smith]] hit the first Series grand slam. In the fourth inning, [[Jim Bagby, Sr.|Jim Bagby]] hit the first Series home run by a pitcher. And in the top of the fifth inning, second baseman [[Bill Wambsganss]] executed the first (and only, so far) unassisted triple play in World Series history, in fact the only Series triple play of any kind.

The team would not reach the heights of 1920 again for 28 years. Speaker and Coveleski were aging and the Yankees were rising with a new weapon: [[Babe Ruth]] and the home run. They managed two second-place finishes but spent much of the decade in the cellar. In 1927 Dunn's widow, Mrs. George Pross (Dunn had died in 1922), sold the team to a syndicate headed by [[Alva Bradley]].

===1936–1946: Bob Feller enters the show===
The Indians were a middling team by the 1930s, finishing third or fourth most years. {{Baseball Year|1936}} brought Cleveland a new superstar in 17-year-old pitcher [[Bob Feller]], who came from [[Iowa]] with a dominating [[fastball]]. That season, Feller set a record with 17 strikeouts in a single game and went on to lead the league in strikeouts from 1938–1941.
[[File:Bob Feller.jpg|right|thumb|[[Bob Feller]]; winner of the A.L. pitching [[Major League Baseball Triple Crown|Triple Crown]] in 1940, member of the [[1948 World Series]] Championship team, the Indians all-time leader in wins and strikeouts, and an [[MLB Hall of Fame]]r.]]

On August 20, 1938, Indians catchers [[Hank Helf]] and [[Frank Pytlak]] set the &quot;all-time altitude mark&quot; by catching baseballs dropped from the {{convert|708|ft|adj=on}} [[Terminal Tower]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/vault/article/magazine/MAG1119227/index.htm |date=March 11, 1985 |title=When Baseballs Fell from On High, Henry Helf Rose to the Occasion |author=Bruce Anderson |work=[[Sports Illustrated]] |accessdate=October 20, 2013 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121102205626/http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/vault/article/magazine/MAG1119227/index.htm |archivedate=November 2, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

By {{MLBy|1940}}, Feller, along with [[Ken Keltner]], [[Mel Harder]] and [[Lou Boudreau]], led the Indians to within one game of the pennant. However, the team was wracked with dissension, with some players (including Feller and Mel Harder) going so far as to request that Bradley fire manager [[Ossie Vitt]]. Reporters lampooned them as the Cleveland Crybabies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=C. Phillip Francis |url=http://www.chatterfromthedugout.com/cleveland_crybabies.htm |title=The Cleveland Crybabies |accessdate=2008-06-27 |work=Chatter from the Dugout |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071012214434/http://www.chatterfromthedugout.com/cleveland_crybabies.htm |archivedate=2007-10-12 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Better source|date=August 2012}} Feller, who had pitched a [[no-hitter]] to open the season and won 27 games, lost the final game of the season to unknown pitcher Floyd Giebell of the [[Detroit Tigers]]. The [[1940 Detroit Tigers season|Tigers]] won the pennant and Giebell never won another major league game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Lisa |last=DeMaio Brewer |title=A National Treasure Calls Wilkes &quot;Home&quot; |url=http://www.therecordofwilkes.com/rec20000621/index.htm |work=The Record of Wilkes, N.C. |date=2000-06-21 |accessdate=2008-06-27 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090126002835/http://www.therecordofwilkes.com/rec20000621/index.htm |archivedate=2009-01-26 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cleveland entered [[1941 Major League Baseball season|1941]] with a young team and a new manager; [[Roger Peckinpaugh]] had replaced the despised Vitt; but the team regressed, finishing in fourth. Cleveland would soon be depleted of two stars. [[Hal Trosky]] retired in 1941 due to migraine headaches&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Leighton |last=Housh |title=Hal Trosky, Norway, 1965 |url=http://www.desmoinesregister.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/19650404/SPORTS11/50710015 |archive-url=https://wayback.archive-it.org/all/20090213210927/http://www.desmoinesregister.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/19650404/SPORTS11/50710015 |url-status=dead |archive-date=2009-02-13 |work=Des Moines Register |date=1965-04-04 |accessdate=2008-06-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and Bob Feller enlisted in the [[United States Navy|Navy]] two days after the [[Attack on Pearl Harbor]].  Starting third baseman [[Ken Keltner]] and outfielder [[Ray Mack]] were both drafted in 1945 taking two more starters out of the lineup.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last =Schneider | first = Russell  | authorlink =  | title = Cleveland Indians Encyclopedia  | publisher = Sports Publishing LLC  | year = 2001  | location =  | page =52  | url = https://books.google.com/?id=9jkqN0qu-fcC | doi = | id = | isbn = 1-58261-376-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1946–1949: The Bill Veeck years===
In {{Baseball Year|1946}}, [[Bill Veeck]] formed an investment group that purchased the Cleveland Indians from Bradley's group for a reported $1.6 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last =Schneider | first = Russell
  | authorlink = | title = Cleveland Indians Encyclopedia  | publisher = Sports Publishing LLC | year = 2001  | location =  | pages =56, 346  | url = https://books.google.com/?id=9jkqN0qu-fcC  | doi =  | id = | isbn = 1-58261-376-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among the investors was [[Bob Hope]], who had grown up in Cleveland, and former Tigers slugger, [[Hank Greenberg]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last =Boxerman | first = Burton Alan  | authorlink = |author2=Benita W. Boxerman | title = Ebbets to Veeck to Busch: Eight Owners Who Shaped Baseball | publisher = McFarland  | year = 2003  | location =  | page =128  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=YBdRu_j0kcIC&amp;pg=PA128&amp;dq=  | doi =  | id = | isbn = 0-7864-1562-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;
A former owner of a minor league franchise in Milwaukee, Veeck brought to Cleveland a gift for promotion. At one point, Veeck hired rubber-faced&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Baseball's Clown Prince Dies |url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/1999/10/30/archive/main68511.shtml |publisher=CBS News |accessdate=2008-02-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Max Patkin]], the &quot;Clown Prince of Baseball&quot; as a coach. Patkin's appearance in the coaching box was the sort of promotional stunt that delighted fans but infuriated the American League front office.

Recognizing that he had acquired a solid team, Veeck soon abandoned the aging, small and lightless League Park to take up full-time residence in massive [[Cleveland Municipal Stadium]].&lt;ref name=Borsvold&gt;{{cite book | last =Borsvold | first = David  | authorlink = | title = The Cleveland Indians: Cleveland Press Years, 1920–1982 | publisher = Arcadia Publishing  | year = 2003 | location = | pages =37–38  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=v0hgrNuScVMC&amp;pg=PA37&amp;dq= | doi = | id = | isbn = 0-7385-2325-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Indians had briefly moved from League Park to Municipal Stadium in mid-1932, but moved back to League Park due to complaints about the cavernous environment.  From 1937 onward, however, the Indians began playing an increasing number of games at Municipal, until by 1940 they played most of their home slate there.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Lowry|first=Phillip|title=Green Cathedrals|url=https://archive.org/details/greencathedralsu0000lowr_u1c9|url-access=registration|year=2005|publisher=Walker &amp; Company|location=New York City|isbn=0-8027-1562-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; League Park was mostly demolished in 1951, but has since been rebuilt as a recreational park.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Briggs|first=David|title=League Park may glisten once again|url=http://cleveland.indians.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20070806&amp;content_id=2133242&amp;vkey=cle_gameface&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=cle|publisher=MLB Advanced Media|website=Indians.com|date=August 8, 2007|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080401010151/http://cleveland.indians.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20070806&amp;content_id=2133242&amp;vkey=cle_gameface&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=cle|archive-date=April 1, 2008|access-date=July 4, 2019|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Logo of the Cleveland Indians (1946-1950).png|thumb|The Cleveland Indians logo from 1946–1950]]

Making the most of the cavernous stadium, Veeck had a portable center field fence installed, which he could move in or out depending on how the distance favored the Indians against their opponents in a given series. The fence moved as much as {{convert|15|ft|m|0}} between series opponents. Following the 1947 season, the American League countered with a rule change that fixed the distance of an outfield wall for the duration of a season.  The massive stadium did, however, permit the Indians to set the then record for the largest crowd to see a Major League baseball game.  On October 10, 1948, Game 5 of the [[1948 World Series|World Series]] against the [[Boston Braves (baseball)|Boston Braves]] drew over 84,000. The record stood until the [[Los Angeles Dodgers]] drew a crowd in excess of 92,500 to watch Game 5 of the [[1959 World Series]] at the [[Los Angeles Memorial Coliseum]] against the [[Chicago White Sox]].

Under Veeck's leadership, one of Cleveland's most significant achievements was breaking the [[Baseball color line|color barrier]] in the [[American League]] by signing [[Larry Doby]], formerly a player for the Negro League's [[Newark Eagles]] in {{Baseball year|1947}}, 11 weeks after [[Jackie Robinson]] signed with the [[Brooklyn Dodgers|Dodgers]].&lt;ref name=Borsvold/&gt;  Similar to Robinson, Doby battled racism on and off the field but posted a .301 batting average in 1948, his first full season. A power-hitting center fielder, Doby led the American League twice in homers.

In 1948, needing pitching for the stretch run of the pennant race, Veeck turned to the [[Negro League]] again and signed pitching great [[Satchel Paige]] amid much controversy.&lt;ref name=Borsvold/&gt;  Barred from Major League Baseball during his prime, Veeck's signing of the aging star in 1948 was viewed by many as another publicity stunt. At an official age of 42, Paige became the oldest rookie in Major League baseball history, and the first black pitcher. Paige ended the year with a 6–1 record with a 2.48 ERA, 45 strikeouts and two shutouts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.baseball-reference.com/teams/CLE/1948.shtml |title= Satchel Paige 1948 Statistics|accessdate=2008-06-28 |website=Baseball-Reference.com }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:LouBoudreau1953bowman.jpg|thumb|180px|[[Lou Boudreau]], 1948 American League MVP]]
In {{MLBy|1948}}, veterans Boudreau, Keltner, and [[Joe Gordon]] had career offensive seasons, while newcomers Doby and [[Gene Bearden]] also had standout seasons. The team went down to the wire with the [[1948 Boston Red Sox season|Boston Red Sox]], winning a one-game playoff, the first in American League history, to go to the [[1948 World Series|World Series]]. In the series, the Indians defeated the [[Atlanta Braves#History|Boston Braves]] four games to two for their first championship in 28 years. Boudreau won the [[Major League Baseball Most Valuable Player Award|American League MVP Award]].

The Indians appeared in a film the following [[1949 in film|year]] titled ''[[The Kid From Cleveland]]'', in which Veeck had an interest.&lt;ref name=Borsvold/&gt;  The film portrayed the team helping out a &quot;troubled teenaged fan&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Kid from Cleveland |url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0041545/ |publisher=IMDB.com | accessdate=2009-02-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; and featured many members of the Indians organization. However, filming during the season cost the players valuable rest days leading to fatigue towards the end of the season.&lt;ref name=Borsvold/&gt;  That season, Cleveland again contended before falling to third place. On September 23, 1949, Bill Veeck and the Indians buried their 1948 pennant in center field the day after they were mathematically eliminated from the pennant race.&lt;ref name=Borsvold/&gt;

Later in 1949, Veeck's first wife (who had a half-stake in Veeck's share of the team) divorced him. With most of his money tied up in the Indians, Veeck was forced to sell the team&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last =Ribowsky | first = Mark | authorlink = | title = Don't Look Back: Satchel Paige in the Shadows of Baseball  | publisher = De Capo Press  | year = 2000  | location =  | page =286  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=LT2pirW9nSYC&amp;pg=RA1-PA286&amp;dq= | doi =  | id = | isbn = 0-306-80963-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; to a syndicate headed by insurance magnate Ellis Ryan.

===1950–1959: Near misses===
[[File:Al Rosen 1953.jpg|thumb|180px|[[Al Rosen]], 1953 Most Valuable Player.]]
In {{MLBy|1953}}, [[Al Rosen]] was an All Star for the second year in a row, was named ''The Sporting News'' Major League Player of the Year, and won the [[American League Most Valuable Player Award]] in a unanimous vote playing for the Indians after leading the AL in runs, home runs, RBIs (for the second year in a row), and slugging percentage, and coming in second by one point in batting average.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.baseball-reference.com/players/r/rosenal01.shtml]&lt;/ref&gt; Ryan was forced out in 1953 in favor of Myron Wilson, who in turn gave way to William Daley in {{MLBy|1956}}.  Despite this turnover in the ownership, a powerhouse team composed of Feller, Doby, [[Minnie Miñoso]], [[Luke Easter (baseball)|Luke Easter]], [[Bobby Ávila]], [[Al Rosen]], [[Early Wynn]], [[Bob Lemon]], and [[Mike Garcia (AL pitcher)|Mike Garcia]] continued to contend through the early 1950s. However, Cleveland only won a single pennant in the decade, in [[1954 Major League Baseball season|1954]], finishing second to the [[1954 New York Yankees season|New York Yankees]] five times.

[[File:Herb Score 1955.JPG|upright|thumb|[[Herb Score]] – who was the 1955 [[American League Rookie of the Year]], a two-time A.L. All-Star, and after his playing career went on to be the longest tenured announcer in club history, serving 34 seasons (1964–1997) as a member of the Indians broadcast team.]]
The winningest season in franchise history came in 1954, when the [[1954 Cleveland Indians season|Indians]] finished the season with a record of 111–43 (.721). That mark set an American League record for wins that stood for 44 years until the [[1998 New York Yankees season|Yankees]] won 114 games in [[1998 Major League Baseball season|1998]] (a 162-game regular season). The Indians 1954 winning percentage of .721 is still an American League record. The Indians returned to the [[1954 World Series|World Series]] to face the [[1954 New York Giants (MLB) season|New York Giants]]. The team could not bring home the title, however, ultimately being upset by the Giants in a sweep. The series was notable for [[Willie Mays]]' [[The Catch (baseball)|over-the-shoulder catch]] off the bat of [[Vic Wertz]] in Game 1. Cleveland remained a talented team throughout the remainder of the decade, finishing in second place in 1959, [[George Strickland (baseball)|George Strickland]]'s last full year in the majors.

===1960–1993: The 33-year slump===
From 1960 to 1993, the Indians managed one third-place finish (in 1968) and six fourth-place finishes (in 1960, 1974 to 1976, 1990, and 1992) but spent the rest of the time at or near the bottom of the standings.

====Frank Lane becomes general manager====
The Indians hired general manager [[Frank Lane]], known as &quot;Trader&quot; Lane, away from the [[St. Louis Cardinals]] in [[1957 Major League Baseball season|1957]]. Lane over the years had gained a reputation as a GM who loved to make deals.  With the White Sox, Lane had made over 100 trades involving over 400 players in seven years.&lt;ref name=Cards&gt;{{cite book | last =Eisenbath  | first = Mike  | authorlink =  |author2=Stan Musial  | title = The Cardinals Encyclopedia | publisher = Temple University Press  | year = 1999  | location =  | pages =  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=hymGG28xYcoC&amp;pg=PA410&amp;lpg=PA410&amp;dq=  | doi =  | id = | isbn = 1-56639-703-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In a short stint in St. Louis, he traded away [[Red Schoendienst]] and [[Harvey Haddix]].&lt;ref name=Cards/&gt;  Lane summed up his philosophy when he said that the only deals he regretted were the ones that he didn't make.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
| last =Schneider | first = Russell  | authorlink = | title = Tales from the Tribe Dugout | publisher = Sports Publishing LLC | year = 2002 | location = | pages = | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=ZCNvizFvLy0C&amp;pg=PA100&amp;lpg=PA100&amp;dq= | doi = | id = | isbn = 1-58261-303-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One of Lane's early trades in Cleveland was to send [[Roger Maris]] to the [[History of the Kansas City Athletics|Kansas City Athletics]] in the middle of [[1958 Major League Baseball season|1958]]. Indians executive [[Hank Greenberg]] was not happy about the trade&lt;ref name=Maris&gt;{{cite book  | last =Rosenfeld  | first = Harvey  | authorlink =  | title = Still a Legend: The Story of Roger Maris | publisher = iUniverse | year = 2002 | location = | pages = | url =https://books.google.com/books?id=LIQLHXQrAssC&amp;pg=PA44&amp;lpg=PA44&amp;dq= | doi = | id = | isbn = 0-595-24615-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; and neither was Maris, who said that he could not stand Lane.&lt;ref name=Maris/&gt;  After Maris broke Babe Ruth's home run record, Lane defended himself by saying he still would have done the deal because Maris was unknown and he received good ballplayers in exchange.&lt;ref name=Maris/&gt;

After the Maris trade, Lane acquired 25-year-old [[Norm Cash]] from the White Sox for [[Minnie Miñoso]] and then traded him to Detroit before he ever played a game for the Indians; Cash went on to hit over 350 home runs for the Tigers. The Indians received [[Steve Demeter]] in the deal, who had only five at-bats for Cleveland.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last = Dow  | first = Bill | title = Former Tiger Norm Cash  | work = Baseball Digest  | url = http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0FCI/is_9_60/ai_76928886  | archive-url = https://archive.is/20120710070550/http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0FCI/is_9_60/ai_76928886  | url-status = dead  | archive-date = 2012-07-10  |date=September 2001 | accessdate = 2006-08-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Curse of Rocky Colavito====
{{see also|Curse of Rocky Colavito}}

In 1960, Lane made the trade that would define his tenure in Cleveland when he dealt slugging right fielder and fan favorite&lt;ref name=Colavito&gt;{{cite book | last =Borsvold | first = David | authorlink = | title = The Cleveland Indians: Cleveland Press Years, 1920–1982  | publisher = Arcadia Publishing | year =1960 | location = | page =81  | url = https://books.google.com/?id=v0hgrNuScVMC&amp;pg=PA81&amp;dq=%2B%22colavito%22+%2Bfan+%2Bfavorite | doi = | id = | isbn =0-7385-2325-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Rocky Colavito]] to the [[Detroit Tigers]] for [[Harvey Kuenn]] just before Opening Day in {{MLBy|1960}}.

It was a blockbuster trade that swapped the {{MLBy|1959}} AL home run co-champion (Colavito) for the AL batting champion (Kuenn). After the trade, however, Colavito hit over 30 home runs four times and made three All-Star teams for Detroit and Kansas City before returning to Cleveland in {{MLBy|1965}}. Kuenn, on the other hand, played only one season for the Indians before departing for [[San Francisco Giants|San Francisco]] in a trade for an aging [[Johnny Antonelli]] and [[Willie Kirkland]]. ''[[Akron Beacon Journal]]'' columnist [[Terry Pluto]] documented the decades of woe that followed the trade in his book ''The Curse of Rocky Colavito''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= Steve|last= Gietschier |title= The Curse of Rocky Colavito: A Loving Look at a Thirty-Year Slump.&amp;nbsp;– book reviews |url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1208/is_n17_v217/ai_15355261 |archive-url=https://archive.is/20120713173059/http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1208/is_n17_v217/ai_15355261 |url-status=dead |archive-date=2012-07-13 |work= The Sporting News|date=1994-09-25 |accessdate=2008-06-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Despite being attached to the curse, Colavito said that he never placed a curse on the Indians but that the trade was prompted by a salary dispute with Lane.&lt;ref name = Curse&gt;{{cite news |first= Stan|last= Grossfeld |authorlink= |author= |title= Colavito Always Straight Shooter |url=http://www.boston.com/sports/baseball/redsox/articles/2007/10/12/colavito_always_straight_shooter/ |work= The Boston Globe|publisher= |location= |id= |pages= |page= |date=2007-10-12 |accessdate=2008-06-29 |language= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lane also engineered a unique trade of managers in mid-season 1960, sending [[Joe Gordon]] to the Tigers in exchange for [[Jimmy Dykes]]. Lane left the team in 1961, but ill-advised trades continued. In 1965, the Indians traded pitcher [[Tommy John]], who would go on to win 288 games in his career, and 1966 Rookie of the Year [[Tommy Agee]] to the White Sox to get Colavito back.&lt;ref name = Curse/&gt;

Indians' pitchers also set numerous strikeout records. They led the league in K's every year from 1963 to 1968, and narrowly missed in 1969. The 1964 staff was the first to amass 1,100 strikeouts, and in 1968, they were the first to collect more strikeouts than hits allowed.

====1969: Move to the AL East division====
The 1970s were not much better, with the Indians trading away several future stars, including [[Graig Nettles]], [[Dennis Eckersley]], [[Buddy Bell]] and 1971 Rookie of the Year [[Chris Chambliss]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last =Riess | first = Steven  | title = Encyclopedia of Major League Baseball Clubs: Volume 1 | publisher = Univ of South Carolina Press | year = 2006 | location = | page =1067 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=ZCcJVZyl5oYC | doi = | id = | isbn = 0-313-32993-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; for a number of players who made no impact.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The 10-best Yankee Trades of All Time |url=http://sports.espn.go.com/espn/page2/story?page=list/bestyankeetrades |publisher=ESPN.com |date=2004-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Constant ownership changes did not help the Indians. In 1963, Daley's syndicate sold the team to a group headed by general manager [[Gabe Paul]].&lt;ref name=&quot;TBT&quot;/&gt;  Three years later, Paul sold the Indians to [[Vernon Stouffer]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Murray Chass |title=BASEBALL; Demise and Pall Of the Indians |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1991/07/02/sports/baseball-demise-and-pall-of-the-indians.html?pagewanted=all |work=New York Times |date=1991-07-02 |accessdate=2008-02-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; of the [[Stouffer's]] frozen-food empire. Prior to Stouffer's purchase, the team was rumored to be relocated due to poor attendance. Despite the potential for a financially strong owner, Stouffer had some non-baseball related financial setbacks and, consequently, the team was cash-poor.  In order to solve some financial problems, Stouffer had made an agreement to play a minimum of 30 home games in [[New Orleans]] with a view to a possible move there.&lt;ref name=Mileti&gt;{{cite news|author=Ron Fimrite |title=Circle The Wagons, Indian Uprising! |url=http://vault.sportsillustrated.cnn.com/vault/article/magazine/MAG1086136/index.htm |work=Sports Illustrated |date=1972-05-29 |accessdate=2008-02-16 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120826001322/http://vault.sportsillustrated.cnn.com/vault/article/magazine/MAG1086136/index.htm |archivedate=August 26, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  After rejecting an offer from [[George Steinbrenner]] and former Indian [[Al Rosen]], Stouffer sold the team in 1972 to a group led by [[Cleveland Cavaliers]] and [[Cleveland Barons (1937–1973)|Cleveland Barons]] owner [[Nick Mileti]].&lt;ref name=Mileti/&gt;  Steinbrenner went on to buy the New York Yankees in 1973.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last =Schneider | first = Russell | authorlink = | title = Cleveland Indians Encyclopedia | publisher = Sports Publishing LLC | year = 2001 | location = | page =352  | url = https://books.google.com/?id=9jkqN0qu-fcC | doi = | id = | isbn = 1-58261-376-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Only five years later, Mileti's group sold the team for $11 million to a syndicate headed by trucking magnate Steve O'Neill and including former general manager and owner Gabe Paul.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Richard Goldstein |title=Gabe Paul, Ex-Yankee Official, Dies at 88 |url= https://www.nytimes.com/1998/04/28/sports/gabe-paul-ex-yankee-official-dies-at-88.html?pagewanted=all |work=New York Times |date=1998-04-28 |accessdate=2008-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;  O'Neill's death in 1983 led to the team going on the market once more. O'Neill's nephew Patrick O'Neill did not find a buyer until real estate magnates [[Richard Jacobs (businessman)|Richard]] and David Jacobs purchased the team in 1986.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://clevelandmagazine.com/in-the-cle/the-30-people-who-defined-cleveland-1972-2002-richard-jacobs|title=The 30 People Who Defined Cleveland 1972-2002: Richard Jacobs|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The team was unable to move out of the cellar, with losing seasons between 1969 and 1975. One highlight was the acquisition of [[Gaylord Perry]] in {{MLBy|1972}}. The Indians traded fireballer [[Sam McDowell|&quot;Sudden Sam&quot; McDowell]] for Perry, who became the first Indian pitcher to win the [[Cy Young Award]]. In {{MLBy|1975}}, Cleveland broke another color barrier with the hiring of [[Frank Robinson]] as Major League Baseball's first African American manager. Robinson served as player-manager and  provided a franchise highlight when he hit a pinch hit home run on Opening Day. But the high-profile signing of [[Wayne Garland]], a 20-game winner in [[Baltimore Orioles|Baltimore]], proved to be a disaster after Garland suffered from shoulder problems and went 28–48 over five years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Schneider | first = Russell | authorlink = | title = More Tales From the Tribe Dugout | publisher = Sports Publishing, LLC | series = | year = 2005  | url= https://books.google.com/?id=2UHG0hiDunkC  | doi = | isbn = 1-58261-680-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The team failed to improve with Robinson as manager and he was fired in {{MLBy|1977}}. In 1977, pitcher [[Dennis Eckersley]] threw a no-hitter against the [[1977 California Angels season|California Angels]]. The next season, he was be dealt to the [[Boston Red Sox]] where he won 20 games in 1978 and another 17 in 1979.

The 1970s also featured the infamous [[Ten Cent Beer Night]] at Cleveland Municipal Stadium. The ill-conceived promotion at a [[1974 Major League Baseball season|1974]] game against the [[1974 Texas Rangers season|Texas Rangers]] ended in a riot by fans and a forfeit by the Indians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Jackson | first = Paul | title = The night beer and violence bubbled over in Cleveland | url = http://sports.espn.go.com/espn/page2/story?page=beernight/080604&amp;sportCat=mlb | date=2008-06-04 |accessdate = 2009-02-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

There were more bright spots in the 1980s. In May 1981, [[Len Barker]] threw a [[Perfect game (baseball)|perfect game]] against the [[1981 Toronto Blue Jays season|Toronto Blue Jays]], joining Addie Joss as the only other Indian pitcher to do so.&lt;ref name=Barker&gt;{{cite web |author= Anthony Castrovince |url=http://mlb.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20060514&amp;content_id=1453617&amp;vkey=news_cle&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=cle |title=Barker's special night remains vivid |date=2006-05-15 |accessdate=2008-07-01 |work=MLB.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Joe Charboneau|&quot;Super Joe&quot; Charbonneau]] won the [[Major League Baseball Rookie of the Year Award|American League Rookie of the Year]] award. Unfortunately, Charboneau was out of baseball by 1983 after falling victim to back injuries&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author= Stephen Ripley |url=http://slam.canoe.ca/Slam/Golf/News/2007/07/08/4323392-sun.html |title=Missing in Action  |date=2007-07-08 |accessdate=2008-07-01 |work=Winnipeg Sun}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Barker, who was also hampered by injuries, never became a consistently dominant starting pitcher.&lt;ref name=Barker/&gt;

Eventually, the Indians traded Barker to the [[Atlanta Braves]] for [[Brett Butler (baseball)|Brett Butler]] and [[Brook Jacoby]],&lt;ref name=Barker/&gt; who became mainstays of the team for the remainder of the decade. Butler and Jacoby were joined by [[Joe Carter]], [[Mel Hall]], [[Julio Franco]] and [[Cory Snyder]], bringing new hope to fans in the late 1980s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Ron Fimrite |title=Pow! Wow! |url=http://vault.sportsillustrated.cnn.com/vault/article/magazine/MAG1065788/index.htm |work=Sports Illustrated |date=1987-04-06 |accessdate=2008-02-16 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120826001347/http://vault.sportsillustrated.cnn.com/vault/article/magazine/MAG1065788/index.htm |archivedate=August 26, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cleveland's struggles over the 30-year span were highlighted in the 1989 film ''[[Major League (film)|Major League]]'', which comically depicted a hapless Cleveland ball club going from worst to first by the end of the film.

====Organizational turnaround====
Throughout the 1980s, the Indians' owners had pushed for a new stadium. Cleveland Stadium had been a symbol of the Indians' glory years in the 1940s and 1950s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://cleveland.indians.mlb.com/cle/history/cle_history_overview.jsp?story=3|title=History Timeline|website=Cleveland Indians|access-date=2016-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, during the lean years even crowds of 40,000 were swallowed up by the cavernous environment. The old stadium was not aging gracefully; chunks of concrete were falling off in sections and the old wooden pilings now petrified.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Jon Morgan |url=http://www.chicagotribune.com/news/local/bal-modell121795,1,3690562.story?page=1 |title=Inside the Browns deal |date=1995-12-17 |accessdate=2008-07-01 |work=Baltimore Sun, reprinted by the Chicago Tribune}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1984, a proposal for a $150 million domed stadium was defeated in a referendum 2–1.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1984/05/10/us/tax-rise-and-domed-stadium-are-voted-down-in-cleveland.html |title=Tax Rise and Domed Stadium Are Voted Down in Cleveland |date=05-10-1984 |accessdate=2008-07-01 |agency=Associated Press | work=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Finally, in May 1990, [[Cuyahoga County, Ohio|Cuyahoga County]] voters passed an [[Pigovian tax|excise tax]] on sales of alcohol and cigarettes in the county. The tax proceeds were to be used for financing the construction of the [[Gateway Sports and Entertainment Complex]], which would include [[Jacobs Field]] for the Indians and [[Gund Arena]] for the [[Cleveland Cavaliers]] basketball team.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Jennifer Stoffel |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1990/06/13/business/real-estate-new-sports-complex-for-cleveland.html |title=New Sports Complex for Cleveland |date=1990-06-13 |accessdate=2008-07-01 |work=New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The team's fortunes started to turn in {{Baseball year|1989}}, ironically with a very unpopular trade. The team sent power-hitting outfielder [[Joe Carter]] to the [[San Diego Padres]] for two unproven players, [[Sandy Alomar, Jr.]] and [[Carlos Baerga]]. Alomar made an immediate impact, not only being elected to the [[1990 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|All-Star team]] but also winning Cleveland's fourth [[MLB Rookie of the Year Award|Rookie of the Year]] award and a [[Gold Glove Award|Gold Glove]]. Baerga became a three-time All-Star with consistent offensive production.

Indians general manager [[John Hart (baseball)|John Hart]] made a number of moves that finally brought success to the team. In {{MLBy|1991}}, he hired former Indians [[Mike Hargrove]] to manage and traded catcher [[Eddie Taubensee]] to the [[Houston Astros]] who, with a surplus of outfielders, were willing to part with [[Kenny Lofton]]. Lofton finished second in AL Rookie of the Year balloting with a .285 average and 66 [[stolen bases]].

The Indians were named &quot;Organization of the Year&quot; by ''Baseball America'' &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Official Site of The Cleveland Indians: History: Indians History |url=http://cleveland.indians.mlb.com/cle/history/cle_history_overview.jsp?story=5 |publisher=Major League Baseball, Cleveland Indians |accessdate=2009-02-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; in 1992, in response to the appearance of offensive bright spots and an improving [[Farm team|farm system]].

The team suffered a tragedy during spring training of {{MLBy|1993}}, when a boat carrying pitchers [[Steve Olin]], [[Tim Crews]], and [[Bob Ojeda]] crashed into a pier. Olin and Crews were killed, and Ojeda was seriously injured. (Ojeda missed most of the season, and retired the following year).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Jayson Stark |url=http://sports.espn.go.com/espn/print?id=1527339&amp;type=columnist |title=Ten years later, the pain is still there |date=2003-03-21 |accessdate=2008-06-30 |work=ESPN.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By the end of the 1993 season, the team was in transition, leaving Cleveland Stadium and fielding a talented nucleus of young players. Many of those players came from the Indians' new [[AAA (baseball)|AAA]] farm team, the [[Charlotte Knights]], who won the [[International League]] title that year.

===1994–2001: New beginnings===
====1994: Jacobs Field opens====
{{main|1994 Cleveland Indians season}}

[[File:Progressive Field.jpg|right|thumb|[[Progressive Field]] in 2008]]
Indians General Manager [[John Hart (baseball)|John Hart]] and team owner [[Richard Jacobs (businessman)|Richard Jacobs]] managed to turn the team's fortunes around. The Indians opened [[Jacobs Field]] in [[1994 Major League Baseball season|1994]] with the aim of improving on the prior season's sixth-place finish. The Indians were only one game behind the division-leading [[1994 Chicago White Sox season|Chicago White Sox]] on August 12 when a [[1994–95 Major League Baseball strike|players strike]] wiped out the rest of the season.

====1995: First AL pennant since 1954====
{{main|1995 Cleveland Indians season}}

Having contended for the division in the aborted 1994 season, Cleveland sprinted to a 100–44 record (the season was shortened by 18 games due to player/owner negotiations) in 1995, winning its first ever divisional title. Veterans [[Dennis Martínez]], [[Orel Hershiser]] and [[Eddie Murray]] combined with a young core of players including [[Omar Vizquel]], [[Albert Belle]], [[Jim Thome]], [[Manny Ramírez]], [[Kenny Lofton]] and [[Charles Nagy]] to lead the league in team batting average as well as team ERA.

After defeating the [[1995 Boston Red Sox season|Boston Red Sox]] in the [[1995 American League Division Series|Division Series]] and the [[1995 Seattle Mariners season|Seattle Mariners]] in the [[1995 American League Championship Series|ALCS]], Cleveland clinched the American League pennant and a [[World Series]] berth, for the first time since 1954. The [[1995 World Series|World Series]] ended in disappointment with the Indians falling in six games to the [[1995 Atlanta Braves season|Atlanta Braves]].

====1996====
{{main|1996 Cleveland Indians season}}
Tickets for every Indians home game sold out several months before opening day in [[1996 Major League Baseball season|1996]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Tickets&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Indians plan to sell additional tickets|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1996/03/07/sports/baseball-indians-plan-to-sell-additional-tickets.html|accessdate=October 19, 2016|work=[[The New York Times]]|agency=[[Associated Press]]|date=March 7, 1996}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Indians repeated as AL Central champions but lost to the [[1996 Baltimore Orioles season|Baltimore Orioles]] in the [[1996 American League Division Series|Division Series]].

====1997: One inning away====
{{main|1997 Cleveland Indians season}}

In [[1997 Major League Baseball season|1997]] Cleveland started slow but finished with an 86–75 record. Taking their third consecutive AL Central title, the Indians defeated the [[1997 New York Yankees season|New York Yankees]] in the [[1997 American League Division Series|Division Series]], 3–2. After defeating the [[1997 Baltimore Orioles season|Baltimore Orioles]] in the [[1997 American League Championship Series|ALCS]], Cleveland went on to face the [[1997 Florida Marlins season|Florida Marlins]] in the [[1997 World Series|World Series]] that featured the coldest game in World Series history. With the series tied after Game 6, the Indians went into the ninth inning of Game Seven with a 2–1 lead, but closer [[José Mesa]] allowed the Marlins to tie the game. In the eleventh inning, [[Édgar Rentería]] drove in the winning run giving the Marlins their first championship.  Cleveland became the first team to lose the World Series after carrying the lead into the ninth inning of the seventh game.

====1998–2001====
In [[1998 Cleveland Indians season|1998]], the Indians made the postseason for the fourth straight year. After defeating the wild-card [[1998 Boston Red Sox season|Boston Red Sox]] 3–1 in the [[1998 American League Division Series|Division Series]], Cleveland lost the [[1998 American League Championship Series|1998 ALCS]] in six games to the [[1998 New York Yankees season|New York Yankees]], who had come into the postseason with a then-AL record 114 wins in the regular season.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=No work Yankees |url=http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/baseball/mlb/1998/postseason/news/1998/10/14/series_yankees/ |work=Sports Illustrated |date=1998-10-15 |accessdate=2008-09-08 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20010619025513/http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/baseball/mlb/1998/postseason/news/1998/10/14/series_yankees/ |archivedate=June 19, 2001 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

For the [[1999 Cleveland Indians season|1999]] season, Cleveland added relief pitcher [[Ricardo Rincón]] and second baseman [[Roberto Alomar]], brother of catcher Sandy Alomar, Jr,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Ros|last=Newhan |title=Early Returns Favor Braves|url=http://articles.latimes.com/1998/nov/29/sports/sp-48911 |work=[[Los Angeles Times]] |date=1998-11-29 |accessdate=2008-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; and won the Central Division title for the fifth consecutive year. The team scored 1,009 runs, becoming the first (and to date only) team since the 1950 Boston Red Sox to score more than 1,000 runs in a season. This time, Cleveland did not make it past the first round, losing the [[1999 American League Division Series|Division Series]] to the [[1999 Boston Red Sox season|Red Sox]], despite taking a 2–0 lead in the series. In game three, Indians starter Dave Burba went down with an injury in the 4th inning.&lt;ref name=Burba&gt;{{cite news |first=Joe|last=Lapointe |title=1999 PLAYOFFS: DIVISION SERIES; Red Sox Find Answers, Raising More Questions |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1999/10/10/sports/1999-playoffs-division-series-red-sox-find-answers-raising-more-questions.html?pagewanted=all |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=1999-10-10 |accessdate=2008-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Four pitchers, including presumed game four starter [[Jaret Wright]], surrendered nine runs in relief. Without a long reliever or emergency starter on the playoff roster, Hargrove started both [[Bartolo Colón]] and [[Charles Nagy]] in games four and five on only three days rest.&lt;ref name=Burba/&gt;  The Indians lost game four 23–7 and game five 12–8.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Red Sox headed to ALCS after beating Cleveland 12–8 |url=http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/baseball/mlb/1999/postseason/division_series/al_div2/news/1999/10/11/redsox_indians_ap/ |work=CNNSI.com |date=1999-10-12 |accessdate=2008-09-08 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070714034232/http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/baseball/mlb/1999/postseason/division_series/al_div2/news/1999/10/11/redsox_indians_ap/ |archivedate=July 14, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Four days later, Hargrove was dismissed as manager.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=John Snyder |title=Indians Journal |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9jkqN0qu-fcC&amp;pg=PA501&amp;lpg=PA501&amp;dq |publisher=Menasha Ridge Press | year=2008 |isbn=1-57860-308-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[2000 Major League Baseball season|2000]], the [[2000 Cleveland Indians season|Indians]] had a 44–42 start, but caught fire after the All Star break and went 46–30 the rest of the way to finish 90–72.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.baseball-reference.com/games/standings.cgi?date=2000-07-09|title=Standings on Sunday, July 9, 2000 - Baseball-Reference.com|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The team had one of the league's best offenses that year and a defense that yielded three gold gloves. However, they ended up five games behind the [[2000 Chicago White Sox season|Chicago White Sox]] in the Central division and missed the wild card by one game to the [[2000 Seattle Mariners season|Seattle Mariners]]. Mid-season trades brought [[Bob Wickman]] and [[Jake Westbrook]] to Cleveland.  After the season, free agent outfielder [[Manny Ramírez]] departed for the [[Boston Red Sox]].

In 2000, [[Larry Dolan]] bought the Indians for $320 million from Richard Jacobs, who, along with his late brother David, had paid $45 million for the club in 1986. The sale set a record at the time for the sale of a baseball franchise.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Cleveland Indians sold to Dolan|url=http://www.marketwatch.com/news/story/-cleveland-indians-sold-dolan/story.aspx?guid=%7B30D9D583-27E3-4DC4-88E4-46E59CB9252B%7D|work=CBS Marketwatch |date=1999-11-04 |accessdate=2008-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[2001 Cleveland Indians season|2001]] saw a return to the postseason. After the departures of Ramírez and [[Sandy Alomar, Jr.]], the Indians signed Ellis Burks and former [[MLB Most Valuable Player Award|MVP]] [[Juan González (baseball)|Juan González]], who helped the team win the Central division with a 91–71 record.  One of the highlights came on August 5, when the Indians completed the biggest comeback in MLB History. Cleveland rallied to close a 14–2 deficit in the seventh inning to defeat the [[2001 Seattle Mariners season|Seattle Mariners]] 15–14 in 11 innings. The Mariners, who won an MLB record-tying 116 games that season, had a strong bullpen, and Indians manager [[Charlie Manuel]] had already pulled many of his starters with the game seemingly out of reach.

Seattle and Cleveland met in the [[2001 American League Division Series|first round of the postseason]], however the Mariners won the series 3–2. In the 2001–02 offseason, GM John Hart resigned and his assistant, [[Mark Shapiro (sports executive)|Mark Shapiro]], took the reins.

===2002–2010: The Shapiro/Wedge years===
[[File:Mark Shapiro.png|upright|thumb|[[Mark Shapiro (sports executive)|Mark Shapiro]] – Indians GM from 2001–2010,  President from 2010–2015, and two-time [[Sporting News Executive of the Year Award|Sporting News Executive of the Year]].]]

====First &quot;rebuilding of the team&quot;====
Shapiro moved to rebuild by dealing aging veterans for younger talent. He traded [[Roberto Alomar]] to the [[New York Mets]] for a package that included outfielder [[Matt Lawton]] and prospects [[Alex Escobar]] and [[Billy Traber]]. When the team fell out of contention in mid-{{MLBy|2002}}, Shapiro fired manager [[Charlie Manuel]] and traded pitching ace [[Bartolo Colón]] for prospects [[Brandon Phillips]], [[Cliff Lee]], and [[Grady Sizemore]]; acquired [[Travis Hafner]] from the [[Texas Rangers (baseball)|Rangers]] for [[Ryan Drese]] and [[Einar Díaz]]; and picked up [[Coco Crisp]] from the [[St. Louis Cardinals]] for aging starter [[Chuck Finley]]. [[Jim Thome]] left after the season, going to the Phillies for a larger contract.

Young Indians teams finished far out of contention in 2002 and {{MLBy|2003}} under new manager [[Eric Wedge]]. They posted strong offensive numbers in {{MLBy|2004}}, but continued to struggle with a bullpen that blew more than 20 saves. A highlight of the season was a 22–0 victory over the [[2004 New York Yankees season|New York Yankees]] on August 31, one of the worst defeats suffered by the Yankees in team history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://sports.espn.go.com/mlb/recap?gameId=240831110 |title=Vizquel's six hits tie AL record |accessdate=2008-06-08 |publisher=ESPN |date=2004-08-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In early {{MLBy|2005}}, the offense got off to a poor start. After a brief July slump, the [[2005 Cleveland Indians season|Indians]] caught fire in August, and cut a 15.5 game deficit in the Central Division down to 1.5 games. However, the season came to an end as the Indians went on to lose six of their last seven games, five of them by one run, missing the playoffs by only two games. Shapiro was named [[Sporting News Executive of the Year Award|Executive of the Year]] in 2005.&lt;ref name=&quot;cleveland.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cleveland.com/tribe/plaindealer/index.ssf?/base/sports/1194342071241541.xml&amp;coll=2 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071107073357/http://www.cleveland.com/tribe/plaindealer/index.ssf?%2Fbase%2Fsports%2F1194342071241541.xml&amp;coll=2 |url-status=dead |archive-date=7 November 2007 |title=Northeast Ohio |accessdate=14 September 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[2006 Major League Baseball season|The next season]], the club made several roster changes, while retaining its nucleus of young players. The off-season was highlighted by the acquisition of top prospect [[Andy Marte]] from the [[Boston Red Sox]].  The Indians had a solid offensive season, led by career years from [[Travis Hafner]] and [[Grady Sizemore]]. Hafner, despite missing the last month of the season, tied the single season grand slam record of six, which was set in {{MLBy|1987}} by [[Don Mattingly]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/14/sports/baseball/14haffner.html|title=BASEBALL; Hafner's 6th Grand Slam Ties Mattingly |date=2006-08-14|work=[[The New York Times]]|accessdate=2009-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the solid offensive performance, the bullpen struggled with 23 blown saves (a Major League worst), and the Indians finished a disappointing fourth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.newsnet5.com/mlb031/11405274/detail.html |title=Cleveland Indians 2007 Preview |last=Ruddick |first=Chris |date=2007-03-27 |publisher=News Net 5 |accessdate=2009-03-21 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120324085206/http://www.newsnet5.com/mlb031/11405274/detail.html |archivedate=March 24, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In {{MLBy|2007}}, Shapiro signed veteran help for the bullpen and outfield in the offseason. Veterans [[Aaron Fultz]] and [[Joe Borowski (baseball)|Joe Borowski]] joined [[Rafael Betancourt]] in the Indians bullpen.&lt;ref name=&quot;MLB2007&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://mlb.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20070328&amp;content_id=1864413&amp;vkey=news_cle&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=cle|title=Indians Opening Day outlook|last=Castrovince|first=Anthony |date=2007-03-30|publisher=MLB.com|accessdate=2009-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Indians improved significantly over the prior year and went into the All-Star break in second place. The team brought back [[Kenny Lofton]] for his third stint with the team in late July.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/mlb/playoffs2007/columns/story?columnist=crasnick_jerry&amp;id=3049840|title=Lofton keeps on ticking, delivers huge performance for Indians|last=Crasnick|first=Jerry|date=2007-10-04|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Indians finished with a 96–66 record tied with the Red Sox for best in baseball, their seventh Central Division title in 13 years and their first postseason trip since 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;WP2007&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/10/11/AR2007101102506_pf.html|title=Boston Red Sox vs. Cleveland Indians|date=2007-10-12|work=Washington Post|accessdate=2009-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:CC Sabathia.jpg|right|thumb|172px|[[CC Sabathia]] – who won the 2007 A.L. [[Cy Young Award]] with the Indians, and was the first of back-to-back Indians Cy Young winners (with teammate [[Cliff Lee]] winning the following year).]]

The Indians began their playoff run by defeating the [[2007 New York Yankees season|Yankees]] in the [[2007 American League Division Series|ALDS]] three games to one. This series will be most remembered for the swarm of bugs that overtook the field in the later innings of Game Two. They also jumped out to a three-games-to-one lead over the [[Boston Red Sox|Red Sox]] in the [[2007 American League Championship Series|ALCS]]. The season ended in disappointment when Boston swept the final three games to advance to the [[2007 World Series]].&lt;ref name=&quot;WP2007&quot;/&gt;

Despite the loss, Cleveland players took home a number of awards. [[Grady Sizemore]], who had a .995 [[fielding percentage]] and only two errors in 405 chances, won the [[Rawlings Gold Glove Award|Gold Glove award]], Cleveland's first since 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://mlb.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20071106&amp;content_id=2293684&amp;vkey=news_cle&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=cle|title=Sizemore earns first Gold Glove Award|last=Castrovince|first=Anthony|date=2007-11-06|publisher=MLB.com|accessdate=2009-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Indians Pitcher [[CC Sabathia]] won the second [[Cy Young Award]] in team history with a 19–7 record, a 3.21 ERA and an MLB-leading 241 [[innings pitched]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/mlb/news/story?id=3108321|title=Sabathia only second Indians pitcher to win Cy Young|date=2007-11-14|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eric Wedge was awarded the first [[Manager of the Year Award]] in team history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cbc.ca/sports/baseball/story/2007/11/14/baseball-managers.html?ref=rss|title=Wedge, Melvin voted baseball's top managers|date=2007-11-14|publisher=CBC Sports|accessdate=2009-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shapiro was named to his second [[Sporting News Executive of the Year Award|Executive of the Year]] in 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;cleveland.com&quot;/&gt;

====Second &quot;rebuilding of the team&quot;====
The [[2008 Cleveland Indians season|Indians]] struggled during the [[2008 Major League Baseball season|2008 season]].  Injuries to sluggers [[Travis Hafner]] and [[Victor Martinez (baseball)|Victor Martinez]], as well as starting pitchers [[Jake Westbrook]] and [[Fausto Carmona]] led to a poor start.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.usatoday.com/sports/baseball/al/indians/2008-12-23-indiansreport_N.htm|title=Indians have closer in fold, but infield in flux|last=Antonen|first=Mel|date=2008-12-25|work=USA Today|accessdate=2009-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Indians, falling to last place for a short time in June and July, traded [[CC Sabathia]] to the [[Milwaukee Brewers]] for prospects [[Matt LaPorta]], Rob Bryson, and [[Michael Brantley]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2008/07/08/sports/baseball/08brewers.html?n=Top/Reference/Times%20Topics/Subjects/B/Baseball|title=Looking to Postseason, Brewers Trade for Sabathia |last=Curry|first=Jack|date=2008-07-08|work=[[The New York Times]]|accessdate=2009-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; and traded starting third baseman Casey Blake for catching prospect Carlos Santana.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.minorleaguebaseball.com/milb/stats/stats.jsp?pos=C&amp;sid=milb&amp;t=p_pbp&amp;pid=467793|title=Carlos Santana Stats, Highlights, Bio – MiLB.com Stats – The Official Site of Minor League Baseball|work=MiLB.com|accessdate=14 September 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100901005459/http://web.minorleaguebaseball.com/milb/stats/stats.jsp?pos=C&amp;sid=milb&amp;t=p_pbp&amp;pid=467793|archive-date=2010-09-01|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Pitcher [[Cliff Lee]] went 22–3 with an ERA of 2.54 and earned the AL Cy Young Award.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2008/11/13/sports/BBA-AL-Cy-Young.php?page=1 |title=Cleveland lefty Cliff Lee wins AL Cy Young Award |date=2009-11-13 |work=International Herald Tribune |accessdate=2009-03-20 }}{{dead link|date=May 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Grady Sizemore]] had a career year, winning a [[Gold Glove Award]] and a [[Silver Slugger Award]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://mlb.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20081113&amp;content_id=3678011&amp;vkey=news_cle&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=cle|title=Sizemore adds Silver Slugger to list|last=Beck|first=Jason|date=2008-11-13|publisher=MLB.com|accessdate=2009-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Indians finished with a record of 81–81.

Prospects for the [[2009 Major League Baseball season|2009 season]] dimmed early when the [[2009 Cleveland Indians season|Indians]] ended May with a record of 22–30. Shapiro made multiple trades: [[Cliff Lee]] and [[Ben Francisco]] to the [[Philadelphia Phillies]] for prospects [[Jason Knapp (baseball)|Jason Knapp]], [[Carlos Carrasco (baseball)|Carlos Carrasco]], [[Jason Donald (baseball)|Jason Donald]] and [[Lou Marson]]; [[Víctor Martínez (baseball)|Victor Martinez]] to the [[Boston Red Sox]] for prospects [[Bryan Price]], [[Nick Hagadone]] and [[Justin Masterson]]; [[Ryan Garko]] to the [[Texas Rangers (baseball)|Texas Rangers]] for [[Scott Barnes (baseball)|Scott Barnes]]; and [[Kelly Shoppach]] to the [[Tampa Bay Rays]] for [[Mitch Talbot]]. The Indians finished the season tied for fourth in their division, with a record of 65–97. The team announced on September 30, 2009, that Eric Wedge and all of the team's coaching staff were released at the end of the 2009 season.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Castrovince|first=Anthony|title=Indians dismiss Wedge, coaching staff|url=http://cleveland.indians.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20090930&amp;content_id=7241814&amp;vkey=news_cle&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=cle|publisher=MLB Advanced Media|website=Indians.com|date=2009-09-30|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131014083849/http://cleveland.indians.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20090930&amp;content_id=7241814&amp;vkey=news_cle&amp;c_id=cle&amp;fext=.jsp|archive-date=October 14, 2013|access-date=July 4, 2019|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Manny Acta]] was hired as the team's 40th manager on October 25, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Castrovince|first=Anthony|title=Tribe tabs Acta to be new manager|url=http://mlb.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20091025&amp;content_id=7544218|publisher=MLB Advanced Media|website=MLB.com|date=October 25, 2009|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121107045726/http://mlb.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20091025&amp;content_id=7544218|archive-date=November 7, 2012|access-date=July 4, 2019|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On February 18, 2010, it was announced that Shapiro (following the end of the 2010 season) would be promoted to team President, with current President [[Paul Dolan (baseball)|Paul Dolan]] becoming the new Chairman/CEO, and longtime Shapiro assistant [[Chris Antonetti]] filling the GM role.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Paul |last=Hoynes |title=Cleveland Indians know what future holds, announce plan for changes in front office |url=http://www.cleveland.com/tribe/index.ssf/2010/02/cleveland_indians_know_what_fu.html |work=The Plain Dealer |location=Cleveland, Ohio |date=2010-02-19 |accessdate=2010-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2011–present: Antonetti/Francona era===
[[File:Terry Francona on June 26, 2013.jpg|upright|thumb|Two-time [[World Series]] winner [[Terry Francona]], who became Indians manager on October 6, 2012&lt;br /&gt;In his tenure with the Tribe, he is a two-time AL Manager of the Year (2013, 2016) and led the team to the 2016 AL Championship.]]

On January 18, 2011, longtime popular former first baseman and manager [[Mike Hargrove]] was brought in as a special adviser. The Indians started the [[2011 Major League Baseball season|2011 season]] strong&amp;nbsp;– going 30–15 in their first 45 games and seven games ahead of the [[2011 Detroit Tigers season|Detroit Tigers]] for first place. Injuries led to a slump where the Indians fell out of first place. Many minor leaguers such as [[Jason Kipnis]] and [[Lonnie Chisenhall]] got opportunities to fill in for the injuries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cbssports.com/mlb/gametracker/preview/MLB_20120405_TOR@CLE/blue-jaysindians-preview |title=MLB Preview – Toronto Blue Jays at Cleveland Indians – Apr 05, 2012 |work=CBSSports.com |accessdate=2013-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The biggest news of the season came on July 30 when the Indians traded four prospects for [[Colorado Rockies]] star pitcher, [[Ubaldo Jiménez]]. The Indians sent their top two pitchers in the minors, [[Alex White (baseball)|Alex White]] and [[Drew Pomeranz]] along with [[Joe Gardner (baseball)|Joe Gardner]] and [[Matt McBride]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://content.usatoday.com/communities/dailypitch/post/2011/07/ubaldo-jimenez-trades-to-cleveland-indians/1#.T39J-BB5mK0|title=Ubaldo Jimenez traded to Indians for four players|work=USATODAY.COM|accessdate=14 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; On August 25, the Indians signed the team leader in home runs, [[Jim Thome]] off of waivers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=AP File |url=http://www.cleveland.com/tribe/index.ssf/2011/08/cleveland_indians_working_on_d.html |title=Back where he began: Cleveland Indians obtain Jim Thome from Twins for player to be named |publisher=cleveland.com |accessdate=2013-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; He made his first appearance in an Indians uniform since he left Cleveland after the 2002 season. To honor Thome, the Indians placed him at his original position, third base, for one pitch against the Minnesota Twins on September 25. It was his first appearance at third base since 1996, and his last for Cleveland.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Northeast Ohio |url=http://www.cleveland.com/tribe/index.ssf/2011/09/shelley_duncans_2-run_hr_gives.html |title=Minnesota Twins beat Cleveland Indians, 6–4, in 10 innings; Jim Thome makes appearance at 3B |publisher=cleveland.com |accessdate=2013-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Indians finished the season in 2nd place, 15 games behind the division champion Tigers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.usatoday.com/sports/baseball/story/2012-04-03/AL-Central-preview/53985226/1 | work=USA Today | title=Most Popular E-mail Newsletter | date=2012-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Corey Kluber on June 27, 2013.jpg|left|thumb|175px|[[Corey Kluber]] – who is a two-time AL [[Cy Young Award]] winner with the Indians (2014, 2017) -  giving the team four winners over 11 seasons.]]

The Indians broke [[Progressive Field]]'s Opening Day attendance record with 43,190 against the [[2012 Toronto Blue Jays season|Toronto Blue Jays]] on April 5, 2012. The game went 16 innings, setting the MLB Opening Day record, and lasted 5 hours and 14 minutes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wbaltv.com/r/30847185/detail.html |archive-url=https://archive.is/20130209022636/http://www.wbaltv.com/r/30847185/detail.html |url-status=dead |archive-date=2013-02-09 |title=Blue Jays Win Longest Opening Day Game In History &amp;#124; WBAL Home – WBAL Home |publisher=Wbaltv.com |date=2012-04-06 |accessdate=2013-01-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 27, 2012, with six games left in the Indians' 2012 season, [[Manny Acta]] was fired; [[Sandy Alomar, Jr.]] was named interim manager for the remainder of the season.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Cleveland Indians fire manager Manny Acta|url=http://espn.go.com/mlb/story/_/id/8432168/cleveland-indians-fire-manager-manny-acta-6-games-remaining-season|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=31 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On October 6, the Indians announced that [[Terry Francona]], who managed the Boston Red Sox to five playoff appearances and two World Series between 2004 and 2011, would take over as manager for 2013.&lt;ref name=foxsports&gt;{{cite web|title=Francona Hired as Indians manager|url=http://msn.foxsports.com/mlb/story/terry-francona-cleveland-indians-manager-opening-100612|work=Fox Sports|accessdate=31 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Indians entered the [[2013 Major League Baseball season|2013 season]] following an active offseason of dramatic roster turnover.  Key acquisitions included free agent 1B/OF [[Nick Swisher]] and CF [[Michael Bourn]].&lt;ref name=rosenthal&gt;{{cite web|last=Rosenthal|first=Ken|title=Bourn makes Tribe relevant again|url=http://msn.foxsports.com/mlb/story/michael-bourn-deal-makes-cleveland-indians-relevant-again-terry-francona-nick-swisher-drew-stubbs-michael-brantley-021113|work=Fox Sports|accessdate=31 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The team added prized right handed pitching prospect [[Trevor Bauer]], OF [[Drew Stubbs]], and relief pitchers [[Bryan Shaw (baseball)|Bryan Shaw]] and  [[Matt Albers]] in a three-way trade with the [[Arizona Diamondbacks]] and [[Cincinnati Reds]] that sent RF [[Shin-Soo Choo]] to the Reds, and [[Tony Sipp]] to the [[Arizona Diamondbacks]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Baskin|first=Andy|title=Getting to know your 2013 Indians: Trevor Bauer|url=http://www.newsnet5.com/dpp/sports/baseball/indians/getting-to-know-your-2013-indians-trevor-bauer|accessdate=31 March 2013|newspaper=News Net 5|date=5 March 2013|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130508202938/http://www.newsnet5.com/dpp/sports/baseball/indians/getting-to-know-your-2013-indians-trevor-bauer|archive-date=2013-05-08|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other notable additions included utility man [[Mike Aviles]], catcher [[Yan Gomes]], designated hitter [[Jason Giambi]], and starting pitcher [[Scott Kazmir]].&lt;ref name=rosenthal/&gt;&lt;ref name=hoynes&gt;{{cite web|last=Hoynes|first=Paul|title=Cleveland Indians 2013: A look back at their significant offseason moves|url=http://www.cleveland.com/tribe/index.ssf/2013/03/cleveland_indians_2013_a_look.html|work=Cleveland.com|accessdate=31 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The 2013 Indians increased their win total by 24 over 2012 (from 68 to 92), finishing in second place,  one game behind Detroit in the Central Division, but securing the number one seed in the American League Wild Card Standings.  In their first postseason appearance since 2007, Cleveland lost the [[2013 American League Wild Card Game]] 4-0 at home to Tampa Bay.  Francona was recognized for the turnaround with the 2013 [[American League Manager of the Year]] Award.

With an 85-77 record, the 2014 Indians had consecutive winning seasons for the first time since 1999-2001, but they were eliminated from playoff contention during the last week of the season and finished third in the AL Central.

In 2015, after struggling through the first half of the season, the Indians finished 81-80 for their third consecutive winning season, which the team had not done since 1999–2001.  For the second straight year, the Tribe finished third in the Central and was eliminated from the Wild Card race during the last week of the season. Following the departure of longtime team executive [[Mark Shapiro (sports executive)|Mark Shapiro]] on October 6, the Indians promoted GM [[Chris Antonetti]] to President of Baseball Operations, assistant general manager [[Mike Chernoff (baseball)|Mike Chernoff]] to GM, and named [[Derek Falvey]] as assistant GM.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wkyc.com/story/sports/mlb/indians/2015/10/06/indians-promote-chris-antonetti-to-president/73451268/|title=Cleveland Indians promote Chris Antonetti to President|first=|last=TEGNA|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Falvey was later hired by the [[Minnesota Twins]] in 2016, becoming their President of Baseball Operations.

====2016:  Return to the World Series====
The Indians set what was then a franchise record for longest winning streak when they won their 14th consecutive game, a 2–1 win over the [[2016 Toronto Blue Jays season|Toronto Blue Jays]] in 19 innings on July 1, 2016 at [[Rogers Centre]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://espn.go.com/mlb/recap?gameId=360701114|title=Indians' streak hits 14 after 19-inning win vs. Jays|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/sport/2017/sep/15/cleveland-indians-win-streak-ends-royals|title=Cleveland Indians' record win streak ended at 22 by Kansas City Royals|agency=Associated Press|date=September 16, 2017 |work=The Guardian|access-date=September 19, 2017 |language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt; The team clinched the Central Division pennant on September 26, their eighth division title overall and first since 2007, as well as returning to the playoffs for the first time since 2013. They finished the regular season at 94–67, marking their fourth straight winning season, a feat not accomplished since the 1990s and early 2000s.

The Indians began the 2016 postseason by sweeping the [[2016 Boston Red Sox season|Boston Red Sox]] in the best-of-five [[2016 American League Division Series|American League Division Series]], then defeated the Blue Jays in five games in the [[2016 American League Championship Series]] to claim their sixth American League pennant and advance to the [[2016 World Series|World Series]] against the [[2016 Chicago Cubs season|Chicago Cubs]]. It marked the first appearance for the Indians in the World Series since 1997 and first for the Cubs since 1945. The Indians took a 3–1 series lead following a victory in Game 4 at [[Wrigley Field]], but the Cubs rallied to take the final three games and won the series 4 games to 3.  The Indians' 2016 success led to Francona winning his second AL Manager of the Year Award with the club.

====2017: Record-setting winning streak====
From August 24 through September 15 during the 2017 season, the Indians set a new American League record by winning 22 games in a row.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbssports.com/mlb/news/here-are-22-stats-and-facts-about-the-indians-record-22-game-winning-streak 22 stats &amp; facts about the Indians' 22 game winning streak - CBS Sports.com]&lt;/ref&gt; On September 28, the Indians won their 100th game of the season, marking only the third time in history the team has reached that milestone. They finished the regular season with 102 wins, second most in team history (behind 1954's 111 win team). The Indians earned the AL Central Title for the second consecutive year, along with home-field advantage throughout the American League playoffs, but they lost the [[2017 ALDS]] to the [[2017 New York Yankees season|Yankees]] 3–2 after being up 2–0.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.cleveland.com/tribe/index.ssf/2017/10/cleveland_indians_2017_a_great.html|title=Cleveland Indians 2017: A great regular season that turned oh so bad in the postseason|work=cleveland.com|access-date=2018-01-21|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Season-by-season results==
{{main|List of Cleveland Indians seasons}}

==Rivalries==
===Interleague===
{{See also|Ohio Cup}}
[[File:Ohio Cup Trophy.jpg|thumb|The Ohio Cup trophy]]
The rivalry with fellow [[Ohio]] team the [[Cincinnati Reds]] is known as the Battle of Ohio or Buckeye Series and features the [[Ohio Cup]] trophy for the winner. Prior to 1997, the winner of the cup was determined by an annual [[spring training|pre-season]] baseball game, played each year at minor-league [[Cooper Stadium]] in the state capital of [[Columbus, Ohio|Columbus]], and staged just days before the start of each new [[Major League Baseball]] season. A total of eight Ohio Cup games were played, with the Indians winning six of them. It ended with the start of [[interleague play]] in 1997. The winner of the game each year was awarded the Ohio Cup in postgame ceremonies. The Ohio Cup was a favorite among baseball fans in Columbus, with attendances regularly topping 15,000.

Since 1997, the two teams have played each other as part of the regular season, with the exception of 2002. The Ohio Cup was reintroduced in 2008 and is presented to the team who wins the most games in the series that season. Initially, the teams played one three-game series per season, meeting in Cleveland in 1997 and Cincinnati the following year. Since 1999, the teams have played two series per season against each other, one at each ballpark. Since 2013, each series is two games, except in years when the AL &amp; NL Central divisions meet interleague play, it is extended to three.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=On schedule: New Interleague format brings twists |url=http://m.mlb.com/news/article/48380512/on-schedule-new-interleague-format-brings-twists |author=Schlegel, John |date=May 23, 2013 |work=MLB.com |publisher=[[Major League Baseball]] |accessdate=May 20, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Through the 2019 meetings, the Indians lead the series 63–50.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Head-to-Head results for Cleveland Indians vs. Cincinnati Reds from 1901 to 2018 |url=https://www.baseball-reference.com/games/head2head-games.cgi?team1=CLE&amp;team2=CIN&amp;from=1901&amp;to=2019 |work=Baseball-Reference.com |year=2018 |accessdate=July 18, 2019 |publisher=Sports Reference LLC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Divisional===
As the Indians play 19 games every year with each of their AL Central competitors, several rivalries have developed.

The Indians have a geographic rivalry with the [[Detroit Tigers]], highlighted in recent years by intense battles for the AL Central title.  The match up has some carryover elements from the [[Ohio State-Michigan rivalry]], as well as the general historic rivalry between Michigan and Ohio dating back to the [[Toledo War]].

The [[Chicago White Sox]] are another rival, dating back to the 1959 season, when the Sox slipped past the Tribe to win the AL pennant. The rivalry intensified when both clubs were moved to the new AL Central in 1994.  During that season, the two teams challenged for the division title, with the Indians one game back of Chicago when the strike began in August. During a game in Chicago, the White Sox confiscated [[Albert Belle]]'s corked bat, followed by an attempt by Indians pitcher [[Jason Grimsley]] to crawl through the [[Comiskey Park II|Comiskey Park]] clubhouse ceiling to retrieve it. Belle later signed with the White Sox in 1997, adding additional intensity to the rivalry.

==Logos and uniforms==
{{See also|Major League Baseball uniforms}}

For the first time in over 70 years, the Indians featured uniforms without the Chief Wahoo logo in 2019, with the official team colors being red, navy blue, and white.&lt;ref name=&quot;IndiansUniformPlan&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Berry|first=Adam|title=Indians adjust uniform plan for 2017|url=https://www.mlb.com/indians/news/indians-adjust-uniforms-for-2017/c-211201118|publisher=[[MLB Advanced Media]]|website=Indians.com|date=December 14, 2016|accessdate=June 10, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|title=Major League Baseball and the Cleveland Indians unveil the official logo of the 2019 All-Star Game presented by Mastercard|url=https://www.mlb.com/news/mlb-indians-unveil-official-logo-of-2019-all-star-game-presented-by-mastercard/c-289267376|publisher=[[MLB Advanced Media]]|website=[[MLB.com]]|date=August 7, 2018|accessdate=November 20, 2018|quote=The official logo of the 2019 All-Star Game celebrates the rich culture of Cleveland. Here in the spiritual birthplace of Rock and Roll, baseball and music are brought together through the icon of a guitar. Baseball stitching creates the shape that hold the &quot;Rock and Roll&quot; stylized letters of the All-Star Game and its host. The MLB logo punctuates this stylized representation as the head of the guitar. The Club's colors of red and blue are joined with tones of gray used for depth and dimension, while the six strings of the guitar are cleverly used in theme art to recognize Cleveland's sixth time hosting the Midsummer Classic.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;IndiansRockTheRed&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Castrovince|first=Anthony|title=Tribe will rock the red after new uniform unveil|url=https://www.mlb.com/indians/news/indians-unveil-2019-uniforms-with-red-jerseys/c-300898744|publisher=[[MLB Advanced Media]]|website=Indians.com|date=November 19, 2018|accessdate=November 19, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;'''Home'''
The primary home uniform is white with navy piping around each sleeve. Across the front of the jersey in script font is the word &quot;Indians&quot; in red with a navy blue outline, with navy blue undershirts, belts, and socks.

The alternate home jersey is red with a [[navy blue]] script &quot;Indians&quot; trimmed in white on the front, and navy blue piping on the sleeves, with navy blue undershirts, belts, and socks.

The home cap is navy blue with a red bill and features a red block &quot;C&quot; on the front.

;'''Road'''
The primary road uniform is gray, with &quot;Cleveland&quot; in navy blue block letters trimmed in red across the front of the jersey, navy blue piping around the sleeves, and navy blue undershirts, belts, and socks.

The alternate road jersey is [[navy blue]] with &quot;Cleveland&quot; in red block letters trimmed in white on the front of the jersey, and navy blue undershirts, belts, and socks.

The road cap is similar to the home cap, with the only difference being the bill is navy blue.

;'''Universal'''
For all games, the team uses a navy blue batting helmet with a red block &quot;C&quot; on the front.

During the 2019 season, all jerseys featured a patch on the left sleeve commemorating the [[2019 Major League Baseball All-Star Game]], which was played at Progressive Field.&lt;ref name=&quot;IndiansRockTheRed&quot; /&gt;

==Fan support and traditions==
===The Drummer===
[[File:John Adams drummer.jpg|upright|thumb|[[John Adams (drummer)|John Adams]] – who (along with his drum) has been an iconic fixture at Indians home games for over 40 years.]]
{{main|John Adams (drummer)}}
John Adams, known by baseball fans as &quot;The Drummer&quot;, has played a [[bass drum]] at nearly every home game since 1973. He is the only fan for whom the team has dedicated a [[bobble head]] day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Andrew |last=Bare |title=No new-school drummer boy |url=http://cleveland.indians.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20060717&amp;content_id=1561217&amp;vkey=cle_gameface&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=cle |work=[[MLB.com]] |date=2006-07-19 |accessdate=2009-06-08 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080331033859/http://cleveland.indians.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20060717&amp;content_id=1561217&amp;vkey=cle_gameface&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=cle |archive-date=2008-03-31 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; Adams originally paid for his tickets (one for himself, and one for his drum), but recently the Indians have paid for his seats in honor of the contributions he has made to the ballpark atmosphere. He has been featured and interviewed on national TV shows and newspaper articles.
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Sarah |last=Crump |authorlink= |title=Pound for pound, there's no greater Tribe fan around: Sarah Crump's My Cleveland |url=http://www.cleveland.com/mycleveland/index.ssf/2009/06/pound_for_pound_theres_no_grea.html |work=[[The Plain Dealer]] |publisher= |date=2009-06-06 |accessdate=2009-06-08 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sellout streak===
Between June 12, 1995 and April 4, 2001, the Indians sold out 455 consecutive home games, drawing a total of 19,324,248 fans to [[Jacobs Field]]. The demand for tickets was so great that all 81 home games were sold out before [[Opening Day]] on at least three separate occasions. The sellout streak set a Major League Baseball record; this was broken by the [[Boston Red Sox]] on September 8, 2008.

===Signature songs===
The Indians play &quot;[[Hang On Sloopy]]&quot; by [[The McCoys]] during the middle of the 8th inning, bringing with it the [[Ohio State Buckeyes]]' tradition of the fans chanting &quot;O-H-I-O&quot; during the chorus. They also play &quot;[[Cleveland Rocks]]&quot; at the end of the game for Indians wins.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.espn.com/blog/music/post/_/id/2236/signature-songs-cleveland-indians|title=Stadium Songs: Cleveland Indians|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Nickname and logo controversy==
{{main|Cleveland Indians name and logo controversy}}
{{see also|Native American mascot controversy}}

The club nickname and its cartoon logo have been criticized by some for perpetuating Native American stereotypes. In 1997 and 1998, protesters were arrested after effigies were burned. Charges were dismissed in the 1997 case, and were not filed in the 1998 case. Protesters arrested in the 1998 incident subsequently fought and lost a lawsuit alleging that their [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]] rights had been violated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://courttv.com/archive/verdicts/bellecourt.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071012183735/http://courttv.com/archive/verdicts/bellecourt.html |archivedate=2007-10-12 |title=court TV becomes truTV |publisher=Web.archive.org |date=2012-12-07 |accessdate=2013-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.workers.org/ww/1997/cleveland1106.html |title=Workers World Nov. 6, 1997: Native leaders arrested during World Series |publisher=Workers.org |date=1997-11-06 |accessdate=2013-01-23 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121105002825/http://www.workers.org/ww/1997/cleveland1106.html |archive-date=2012-11-05 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=OSSC&gt;{{cite court|litigants=Bellecourt v. Cleveland|vol=104|reporter=Ohio St, 3d.|opinion=439|court=Ohio State Supreme Court|year=2004|url=http://www.sconet.state.oh.us/rod/newpdf/0/2004/2004-ohio-6551.pdf|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.supremecourt.ohio.gov/PIO/summaries/2004/1215/031202.asp |title=Supreme Court of Ohio Case Summaries |publisher=Supremecourt.ohio.gov |accessdate=2013-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Bud Selig]] (then-[[Commissioner of Baseball]]) said in 2014 that he had never received a complaint about the logo. He has heard that there are some protesting mascots, but individual teams such as the Indians and [[Atlanta Braves]], whose nickname was also criticized for similar reasons, should make their own decisions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Brady|first=Erik|title=Selig claims he's received no complaints over Cleveland Indians' logo|url=http://ftw.usatoday.com/2014/07/bud-selig-chief-wahoo|newspaper=[[USA Today]]|date=July 15, 2014|accessdate=January 29, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; An organized group consisting of Native Americans protested [[Chief Wahoo]] on [[Opening Day]] 2015, as they have for many years, making note that this is the 100th anniversary of the team becoming the Indians. Owner [[Paul Dolan (baseball)|Paul Dolan]], while stating he is respectful of critics, says he mainly hears from fans who want to keep Chief Wahoo, and has no plans to change.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Beres|first=Tom|title=Wahoo Protesters: A century of 'Indians' is enough|url=http://www.wkyc.com/story/news/local/cleveland/2015/04/09/cleveland--protesters-a-century-of-indians-is-enough/25538785/|publisher=[[WKYC]]|date=April 9, 2015|accessdate=January 29, 2018|archive-url=https://archive.is/20150411031430/http://www.wkyc.com/story/news/local/cleveland/2015/04/09/cleveland--protesters-a-century-of-indians-is-enough/25538785/|archive-date=April 11, 2015|url-status=dead|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On January 29, 2018, Major League Baseball announced that Chief Wahoo would be removed from the Indians' uniforms as of the 2019 season, stating that the logo was no longer appropriate for on-field use.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Bastian|first=Jordan|title=Indians to stop using Wahoo logo starting in '19|url=https://www.mlb.com/indians/news/indians-to-stop-using-chief-wahoo-logo/c-265489544|publisher=Major League Baseball Advanced Media|date=January 29, 2018|accessdate=January 29, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Waldstein|first=David|title=Cleveland Indians Will Abandon Chief Wahoo Logo Next Year|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2018/01/29/sports/baseball/cleveland-indians-chief-wahoo-logo.html|newspaper=The New York Times|date=January 29, 2018|accessdate=January 29, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The team will consider a new logo in the future, but the block &quot;C&quot; will be promoted to the primary logo; additionally, there are no plans to change the team's name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://indiancountrymedianetwork.com/culture/sports/no-wahoo-cleveland-indians-discontinue-chief-wahoo-logo-2019/ |title=NO MORE WAHOO: Cleveland Indians To Discontinue Chief Wahoo Logo in 2019 |last=Schilling |first=Vincent |publisher=Indian Country Media Network |date=January 29, 2018 |website=indiancountrymedianetwork.com |access-date=February 11, 2018 |quote=According to the MLB site, the Cleveland Indians may consider a new logo in the future, but will promote the capital letter C for now. There are no current plans to change the Indians’ team name. |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180211072919/https://indiancountrymedianetwork.com/culture/sports/no-wahoo-cleveland-indians-discontinue-chief-wahoo-logo-2019/ |archive-date=February 11, 2018 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Media==
{{Main|List of Cleveland Indians broadcasters}}
[[File:US Navy 060828-N-1805P-007 Chief of Naval Personnel Vice Adm. John C. Harvey Jr. chats with broadcasters from Cleveland radio station WTAM 1100 AM during a Major League Baseball game at Jacobs Field between the Cleveland Indian.jpg|right|thumb|185px|Indians TV announcer [[Matt Underwood]] (seated, center) and longtime lead radio announcer [[Tom Hamilton (broadcaster)|Tom Hamilton]] (right)]]
Cleveland radio stations [[WTAM]] (1100&amp;nbsp;AM) and [[WMMS]] (100.7&amp;nbsp;FM) serve as flagship stations for the [[Cleveland Indians Radio Network]].&lt;ref name=radio&gt;{{cite web |url=http://cleveland.indians.mlb.com/cle/schedule/radio_affiliates.jsp |title= Radio Affiliates |work=Clevelandindians.com |accessdate=2008-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Tom Hamilton (broadcaster)|Tom Hamilton]] and [[Jim Rosenhaus]] serve as play-by-play announcers.&lt;ref name=broadcasters&gt;{{cite web |url=http://mlb.mlb.com/team/broadcasters.jsp?c_id=cle |title= Broadcaster |work=Clevelandindians.com |accessdate=2008-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The television rights are held by [[SportsTime Ohio]] (STO), [[Matt Underwood]] and former Indians [[Gold Glove]] winning CF [[Rick Manning]] form the announcing team,&lt;ref name=broadcasters/&gt;  with veteran Cleveland sportscaster Andre Knott as field reporter,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.news-herald.com/sports/20150305/sports-media-notes-andre-knott-will-be-cleveland-indians-sideline-reporter-source-says Sports Media notes] ''Lake County News Herald''&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Al Pawlowski]] and former Indians pitcher [[Jensen Lewis]] as pregame/postgame hosts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ohio.com/sports/indians/former-pitcher-jensen-lewis-finds-second-dream-job-as-part-of-indians-television-team-1.498505|title=Former pitcher Jensen Lewis finds second dream job as part of Indians’ television team|first=Stephanie|last=Storm|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Select games are shown on free TV, airing on [[NBC]] affiliate [[WKYC]] channel 3 via simulcast.

Notable former Indians broadcasters include Tom Manning, [[Jack Graney]] (the first ex-baseball player to become a play-by-play announcer), [[Ken Coleman]], [[Joe Castiglione]], [[Van Patrick]], [[Nev Chandler]], [[Bruce Drennan]], [[Mudcat Grant|Jim &quot;Mudcat&quot; Grant]], [[Rocky Colavito]], [[Dan Coughlin (sportscaster)|Dan Coughlin]], and [[Jim Donovan (sportscaster)|Jim Donovan]].

Previous broadcasters who have had lengthy tenures with the team include [[Joe Tait]] (15 seasons between TV and radio), [[Jack Corrigan (radio)|Jack Corrigan]] (18 seasons on TV), [[Ford C. Frick Award]] winner [[Jimmy Dudley]] (19 seasons on radio), [[Mike Hegan]] (23 seasons between TV and radio), and [[Herb Score]] (34 seasons between TV and radio).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cleveland.com/tribe/index.ssf/2008/11/former_indians_broadcaster_her.html|title=Former Indians broadcaster Herb Score dies at age 75|last=Dolgan|first=Bob|work=Cleveland Plain Dealer|date=November 11, 2008|accessdate=February 16, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cleveland Indians in popular culture==
Over the years, the Indians have been featured in several movies and television shows.  Examples include:
*''[[The Kid From Cleveland]]'' – a 1949 film featuring then owner Bill Veeck and numerous players from the team (coming off winning the [[1948 World Series]]).
*''[[Major League (film)|Major League]]'' – a 1989 film centered around a fictionalized version of the team
*''[[Major League II]]'' – a 1994 sequel to the original from five years earlier
*''[[Looney Tunes]]'' – In ''[[The Hardship of Miles Standish]]'', the Cleveland Indians are referenced.
*''[[Goofy]]'' – In ''[[Californy 'er Bust]]'', a Cleveland Indian sits in on the powwow.
*In the 1994 film ''[[Little Big League]]'', the main character Billy Heywood quotes Indians' Hall-of-Fame pitcher [[Bob Lemon]]: &quot;Baseball was made for kids; grownups only screw it up.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://time.com/2945816/little-big-league-anniversary/|title=Little Big League: The Most Underrated Baseball Movie of All Time|work=Time|accessdate=July 1, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, catcher [[Sandy Alomar Jr.]] and second baseman [[Carlos Baerga]] have cameo appearances.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0110363/fullcredits?ref_=tt_cl_sm#cast|title=Little Big League cast|work=imdb.com|accessdate=June 29, 1994}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
*In an episode from the 1968 animated series ''[[Go Go Gophers]]'' titled &quot;The Cleveland Indians&quot;, Indian characters Ruffled Feathers and Running Board not only accused the team of not being real Indians and not wearing any feathers, but also called them fakes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hN9sasxzt5s|title=Go Go Gophers – The Cleveland Indians|work=YouTube|accessdate=July 19, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*In the children's book ''[[Danny Dunn, Time Traveler]]'', when they are sitting around with Benjamin Franklin and explaining their presence in 1763, Danny's role model, a professor, is unable to name any Indian tribe as the one they claimed had captured them.  The professor named the only Indian &quot;tribe&quot; he could think of: the Cleveland Indians.
*In an episode of ''[[I Love Lucy]]'' (&quot;Lucy and Bob Hope&quot;) Lucy spots [[Bob Hope]] at an Indians-Yankees Game in [[Yankee Stadium]] (At the time, Bob Hope was a minority owner of The Indians) and tries to talk to him into appearing with her husband Ricky at the Grand Opening of Club Babalu while disguised as a Hot Dog Vendor then an Indians Player.

==Awards and honors==
{{see also|Cleveland Indians award winners and league leaders}}

===Baseball Hall of Famers===
[[File:Nap Lajoie Baseball Card.jpg|upright|thumb|[[Nap Lajoie]] on a 1911 [[baseball card]]]]
{{Baseball hall of fame list 
|Current Team Name = Cleveland Indians
|   All Team Names = Indians or Naps
|          ColorA# = E31937
|          ColorB# = FFFFFF
|          ColorC# = 002B5C
|          ColorD# = FFFFFF
|      Team Name 1 = '''Cleveland Naps'''
|         List 1.1 =
|         List 1.2 = '''[[Elmer Flick]]''' *
|         List 1.3 = '''[[Addie Joss]]''' *&lt;br /&gt;'''[[Nap Lajoie]]''' *
|         List 1.4 = '''[[Cy Young]]''' *
|         List 1.5 =
|      Team Name 2 = '''Cleveland Indians'''
|         List 2.1 = [[Roberto Alomar]]
&lt;br /&gt;'''[[Earl Averill]]''' *
&lt;br /&gt;[[Harold Baines]]
&lt;br /&gt;[[Bert Blyleven]]
&lt;br /&gt;'''[[Lou Boudreau]]''' *
&lt;br /&gt;[[Steve Carlton]]
&lt;br /&gt;'''[[Stan Coveleski]]''' *
|         List 2.2 = '''[[Larry Doby]]''' *
&lt;br /&gt;[[Dennis Eckersley]]
&lt;br /&gt;[[Billy Evans]]
&lt;br /&gt;'''[[Bob Feller]]''' *
&lt;br /&gt;[[Joe Gordon]]
&lt;br /&gt; [[Walter Johnson]]
|         List 2.3 = [[Ralph Kiner]]
&lt;br /&gt;'''[[Bob Lemon]]''' *
&lt;br /&gt;'''[[Al López]]'''
&lt;br /&gt;[[Jack Morris]]
&lt;br /&gt;[[Eddie Murray]]
&lt;br /&gt;[[Hal Newhouser]]
|         List 2.4 = [[Phil Niekro]]
&lt;br /&gt;[[Satchel Paige]]
&lt;br /&gt;[[Gaylord Perry]]
&lt;br /&gt;[[Sam Rice]]
&lt;br /&gt;[[Frank Robinson]]
&lt;br /&gt;'''[[Joe Sewell]]''' *
|         List 2.5 = [[Billy Southworth]]
&lt;br /&gt;'''[[Tris Speaker]]''' *
&lt;br /&gt;'''[[Jim Thome]]''' *
&lt;br /&gt;[[Hoyt Wilhelm]]
&lt;br /&gt;[[Dick Williams]]
&lt;br /&gt;[[Dave Winfield]]
&lt;br /&gt;'''[[Early Wynn]]''' *
|      Team Name 3 =
|         List 3.1 =
|         List 3.2 =
|         List 3.3 =
|         List 3.4 =
|         List 3.5 =
|      Team Name 4 =
|         List 4.1 =
|         List 4.2 =
|         List 4.3 =
|         List 4.4 =
|         List 4.5 =
|        Footnote1 = * Cleveland Indians listed as primary team according to the Hall of Fame
|        Footnote2 =
|        Footnote3 =
|        Footnote4 =
|}}

===Ford C. Frick Award recipients===
{{Ford C. Frick award list
|Current Team Name = Cleveland Indians
|   All Team Names = Indians
|          ColorA# = E31937
|          ColorB# = FFFFFF
|          ColorC# = 002B5C
|          ColorD# = FFFFFF
|         List 1   =
|         List 2   = [[Mel Allen]]
|         List 3   = 
|         List 4   = '''[[Jimmy Dudley]]'''
|         List 5   =
|        Footnote1 =
|        Footnote2 =
|        Footnote3 =
|        Footnote4 =
|}}

===Retired numbers===
{{See also|List of Major League Baseball retired numbers}}
{{retired number list|
{{retired number|image=EarlAverill.png|alt=3|name=[[Earl Averill|Earl&lt;br/&gt;Averill]]|pos=CF&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;|date=&lt;br/&gt;June 8, 1975}}
{{retired number|image=LouBoudreau.png|alt=5|name=[[Lou Boudreau|Lou&lt;br/&gt;Boudreau]]|pos=SS&lt;br/&gt;Manager|date=&lt;br /&gt;July 9, 1970}}
{{retired number|image=LarryDoby_14.png|alt=14|name=[[Larry Doby|Larry&lt;br/&gt;Doby]]|pos=CF&lt;br/&gt;Coach|date=&lt;br /&gt;July 3, 1994}}
{{retired number|image=MelHarder.png|alt=18|name=[[Mel Harder|Mel&lt;br/&gt;Harder]]|pos=SP&lt;br/&gt;Coach|date=&lt;br /&gt;July 28, 1990}}
{{retired number|image=BobFeller.png|alt=19|name=[[Bob Feller|Bob&lt;br/&gt;Feller]]|pos=SP&lt;br/&gt;Coach|date=&lt;br/&gt;December 27, 1956}}
{{retired number|image=Indians20_FrankRobinson.png|alt=20|name=[[Frank Robinson|Frank&lt;br/&gt;Robinson]]|pos=OF&lt;br/&gt;Manager|date=&lt;br /&gt;May 28, 2017}}
{{retired number|image=BobLemon.png|alt=21|name=[[Bob Lemon|Bob&lt;br/&gt;Lemon]]|pos=P&lt;br/&gt;Coach|date=&lt;br /&gt;June 20, 1998}}
{{retired number|image=Indians25_JimThome.png|alt=25|name=[[Jim Thome|Jim&lt;br/&gt;Thome]]|pos=1B, DH, 3B&lt;br/&gt;|date=&lt;br /&gt;August 18, 2018}}
{{retired number|image=JackieRobinsonCleveland.png|alt=42|name=[[Jackie Robinson|Jackie&lt;br/&gt;Robinson]]|pos=&lt;br/&gt;All MLB|date=&lt;br /&gt;April 15, 1997}}
{{retired number|image=TheFans.png|alt=455|name=[[455 The Fans|The&lt;br/&gt;Fans]]|pos=&amp;nbsp;&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;|date=&lt;br /&gt;May 29, 2001}}
}}

* Jackie Robinson's number 42 is retired throughout Major League Baseball.
* The number 455 was retired in honor of the Indians fans after the team [[455 The Fans|sold out 455 consecutive games]] between 1995 and 2001, which was an MLB record until it was surpassed by the [[Boston Red Sox]] on September 8, 2008.
[[File:Larry Doby Statue.jpg|thumb|This statue of Larry Doby is located outside the right field gate at Progressive Field.]]

===Indians Hall of Fame===
{{further|Cleveland Indians award winners and league leaders#Cleveland Indians Hall of Fame}}

===Statues===
Numerous Indians players have had statues made in their honor:

====In and around Progressive Field====
*[[Bob Feller]] (Indians all-time leader in wins and strikeouts by a pitcher, [[1948 World Series]] Champion, eight-time All-Star) – since 1994*
*[[Jim Thome]] (Indians all-time leader in home runs and walks by a hitter, three-time All-Star with the Indians) – since 2014*
*[[Larry Doby]] (First black player in the American League, [[1948 World Series]] Champion, seven-time All-Star) – since 2015*
*[[Frank Robinson]] (Became first black manager in MLB history when he served as player/manager for the Indians from 1975-1977) – since 2017
*[[Lou Boudreau]] (1948 AL MVP, [[1948 World Series]] Champion as player/manager, eight-time All-Star) – since 2017*&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cleveland.com/tribe/index.ssf/2017/01/cleveland_indians_to_unveil_st_1.html|title=Cleveland Indians to unveil statues of Frank Robinson, Lou Boudreau -- Who should be next?|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====In and around Cleveland====
*Indians (then Naps) Hall of Fame outfielder [[Elmer Flick]] has a statue in his hometown of [[Bedford, Ohio]], a nearby suburb of Cleveland - since 2013*
*Former Indians outfielder [[Luke Easter (baseball)|Luke Easter]] has a statue outside of his namesake park on the east side of Cleveland - since 1980 (when the park was renamed in Easter's honor following his murder)&lt;ref&gt;[http://sculpturecenter.org/oosi/items/show/369 Luke Easter statue - Ohio Outdoor Sculpture]&lt;/ref&gt;

(*) - Inducted into the [[Baseball Hall of Fame]] as an Indian/Nap.

==Franchise records==
{{main|List of Cleveland Indians team records}}

===Season records===
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* Highest batting average: .408, [[Shoeless Joe Jackson|Joe Jackson]] (1911)
* Most games: 163, [[Leon Wagner]] (1964)
* Most runs: 140, [[Earl Averill]] (1930)
* Highest slugging %: .714, [[Albert Belle]] (1994)
* Most doubles: 64, [[George Burns (first baseman)|George Burns]] (1926)
* Most triples: 26, [[Shoeless Joe Jackson|Joe Jackson]] (1912)
* Most home runs: 52, [[Jim Thome]] (2002)
* Most RBIs: 165, [[Manny Ramirez]] (1999)
* Most stolen bases: 75, [[Kenny Lofton]] (1996)
* Most wins: 31, [[Jim Bagby, Sr.]] (1920)
* Lowest ERA: 1.16, [[Addie Joss]] (1908)
* Strikeouts: 348, [[Bob Feller]] (1946)
* Complete games: 36, [[Bob Feller]] (1946)
* Saves: 46, [[José Mesa]] (1995)
* Longest Win Streak: 22 games (2017) 
{{div col end}}

==Roster==
[[file:Francisco Lindor 2017.jpg|right|thumb|200px|Starting shortstop and four-time All Star [[Francisco Lindor]]]]
{{Cleveland Indians roster}}

==Minor league affiliations==
{{Main|List of Cleveland Indians minor league affiliates}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;text-align:center; {{Baseball primary style|Cleveland Indians|border=2}};&quot;|Level
! style=&quot;text-align:center; {{Baseball primary style|Cleveland Indians|border=2}};&quot;|Team
! style=&quot;text-align:center; {{Baseball primary style|Cleveland Indians|border=2}};&quot;|League
! style=&quot;text-align:center; {{Baseball primary style|Cleveland Indians|border=2}};&quot;|Location
|-
| ''AAA''
| [[Columbus Clippers]]
| [[International League]]
| [[Columbus, Ohio]]
|-
| ''AA''
| [[Akron RubberDucks]]
| [[Eastern League (U.S. baseball)|Eastern League]]
| [[Akron, Ohio]]
|-
| ''Advanced A''
| [[Lynchburg Hillcats]]
| [[Carolina League]]
| [[Lynchburg, Virginia]]
|-
| ''A''
| [[Lake County Captains]]
| [[Midwest League]]
| [[Eastlake, Ohio]]
|-
|''Short Season A''
| [[Mahoning Valley Scrappers]]
| [[New York–Penn League]]
| [[Niles, Ohio]]
|-
|rowspan=4|''Rookie''
| [[Arizona League Indians|AZL Indians 1 (Red)]]
| [[Arizona League]]
| [[Goodyear, Arizona]]
|-
| [[Arizona League Indians|AZL Indians 2 (Blue)]]
| Arizona League
| Goodyear, Arizona
|-
| [[Dominican Summer Indians|DSL Indians]]
| [[Dominican Summer League]]
| [[Dominican Republic]]
|-
| [[Dominican Summer Indians|DSL Indians/Brewers]]
| Dominican Summer League
| Dominican Republic
|}

==Regular season home attendance==
===Jacobs Field===
{| cellpadding=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;width:300px; font-size:90%; border:2px solid #E31937;&quot;
|- style=&quot;text-align:center; font-size:larger;&quot;
| colspan=5 style=&quot;{{Baseball primary style|Cleveland Indians}};&quot;|'''Home Attendance at Jacobs Field'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.baseball-reference.com/teams/CLE/attend.shtml 
|title=Cleveland Indians Attendance, Stadiums, and Park Factors |publisher=Baseball-Reference.com |date= |accessdate=May 5, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- style={{Baseball secondary style|Cleveland Indians}};&quot;
| '''Year''' || '''Total attendance''' || '''Game average''' || '''League rank'''
|-
| [[2000 Cleveland Indians season|2000]]
| 3,456,278 
| 42,670 
| 1st
|-
| [[2001 Cleveland Indians season|2001]]
| 3,175,523
| 39,694
| 3rd
|-
| [[2002 Cleveland Indians season|2002]]
| 2,616,940
| 32,308
| 5th
|-
| [[2003 Cleveland Indians season|2003]]
| 1,730,002
| 21,358
| 12th 
|-
| [[2004 Cleveland Indians season|2004]]
| 1,814,401
| 22,400
| 12th 
|-
| [[2005 Cleveland Indians season|2005]]
| 2,013,763
| 24,861
| 12th 
|-
| [[2006 Cleveland Indians season|2006]]
| 1,997,995
| 24,667
| 11th 
|-
| [[2007 Cleveland Indians season|2007]]
| 2,275,912
| 28,449
| 9th 
|}
===Progressive Field===
{| cellpadding=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;width:300px; font-size:90%; border:2px solid #E31937;&quot;
|- style=&quot;text-align:center; font-size:larger;&quot;
| colspan=5 style=&quot;{{Baseball primary style|Cleveland Indians}};&quot;|'''Home Attendance at Progressive Field'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.baseball-reference.com/teams/CLE/attend.shtml 
|title=Cleveland Indians Attendance, Stadiums, and Park Factors |publisher=Baseball-Reference.com |date= |accessdate=May 5, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- style={{Baseball secondary style|Cleveland Indians}};&quot;
| '''Year''' || '''Total attendance''' || '''Game average''' || '''League rank'''
|-
| [[2008 Cleveland Indians season|2008]]
| 2,169,760
| 26,787
| 9th 
|-
| [[2009 Cleveland Indians season|2009]]
| 1,766,242
| 21,805
| 13th 
|-
| [[2010 Cleveland Indians season|2010]]
| 1,391,644
| 17,181
| 14th 
|-
| [[2011 Cleveland Indians season|2011]]
| 1,840,835
| 22,726
| 9th 
|-
| [[2012 Cleveland Indians season|2012]]
| 1,603,596
| 19,797
| 13th 
|-
| [[2013 Cleveland Indians season|2013]]
| 1,572,926
| 19,419
| 14th 
|-
| [[2014 Cleveland Indians season|2014]]
| 1,437,393
| 17,746
| 15th 
|-
| [[2015 Cleveland Indians season|2015]]
| 1,388,905
| 17,361
| 14th 
|-
| [[2016 Cleveland Indians season|2016]]
| 1,591,667
| 19,650
| 13th 
|-
| [[2017 Cleveland Indians season|2017]]
| 2,048,138
| 25,286
| 11th
|-
| [[2018 Cleveland Indians season|2018]]
| 1,926,701
| 23,786
| 9th  
|-
| [[2019 Cleveland Indians season|2019]]
| 1,738,642
| 21,465	
| 9th  
|}

==See also==
* [[Cleveland Indians all-time roster]]
* [[List of Cleveland Indians seasons]]
* [[List of Cleveland Indians team records]]
* [[List of Cleveland Indians managers]]
* [[List of World Series champions]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
* {{MLBTeam|Cleveland|Indians|CLE}}
* [https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1059019/0000950152-99-002807.txt Cleveland Indians 1998 Annual Report], the last filed with the SEC
* [http://www.sportsecyclopedia.com/al/clevind/indians.html Sports E-Cyclopedia]

{{s-start}}
{{s-bef|before = [[Cincinnati Reds]]&lt;br /&gt;[[1919 World Series|1919]]}}
{{s-ttl|title = World Series champions&lt;br /&gt;Cleveland Indians|years = [[1920 World Series|1920]]}}
{{s-aft|after = [[History of the New York Giants (baseball)|New York Giants]]&lt;br /&gt;[[1921 World Series|1921]] and [[1922 World Series|1922]]}}
{{s-bef|before = [[New York Yankees]]&lt;br /&gt;[[1947 World Series|1947]]}}
{{s-ttl|title = World Series champions&lt;br /&gt;Cleveland Indians|years = [[1948 World Series|1948]]}}
{{s-aft|after = [[New York Yankees]]&lt;br /&gt;[[1949 World Series|1949]], [[1950 World Series|1950]], [[1951 World Series|1951]], [[1952 World Series|1952]], [[1953 World Series|1953]]}}
{{s-end}}
{{s-start}}
{{s-bef|before = [[Chicago White Sox]]&lt;br /&gt;{{Baseball year|1919}}}}
{{s-ttl|title = American League champions&lt;br /&gt;Cleveland Indians|years = {{Baseball year|1920}}}}
{{s-aft|after = [[New York Yankees]]&lt;br /&gt;{{Baseball year|1921}} and {{Baseball year|1922}}}}
{{s-bef|before = [[New York Yankees]]&lt;br /&gt;{{Baseball year|1947}}}}
{{s-ttl|title = American League champions&lt;br /&gt;Cleveland Indians|years = {{Baseball year|1948}}}}
{{s-aft|after = [[New York Yankees]]&lt;br /&gt;{{Baseball year|1949}}, {{Baseball year|1950}}, {{Baseball year|1951}}, {{Baseball year|1952}}, {{Baseball year|1953}}}}
{{s-bef|before = [[New York Yankees]]&lt;br /&gt;{{Baseball year|1949}}, {{Baseball year|1950}}, {{Baseball year|1951}}, {{Baseball year|1952}}, {{Baseball year|1953}}}}
{{s-ttl|title = American League champions&lt;br /&gt;Cleveland Indians|years = {{Baseball year|1954}}}}
{{s-aft|after = [[New York Yankees]]&lt;br /&gt;{{Baseball year|1955}}, {{Baseball year|1956}}, {{Baseball year|1957}}, {{Baseball year|1958}}}}
{{s-bef|before = [[Toronto Blue Jays]]&lt;br /&gt;[[1992 American League Championship Series|1992]] and [[1993 American League Championship Series|1993]]}}
{{s-ttl|title = American League champions&lt;br /&gt;Cleveland Indians|years = [[1995 American League Championship Series|1995]]}}
{{s-aft|after = [[New York Yankees]]&lt;br /&gt;[[1996 American League Championship Series|1996]]}}
{{s-bef|before = [[New York Yankees]]&lt;br /&gt;[[1996 American League Championship Series|1996]]}}
{{s-ttl|title = American League champions&lt;br /&gt;Cleveland Indians|years = [[1997 American League Championship Series|1997]]}}
{{s-aft|after =[[New York Yankees]]&lt;br /&gt;[[1998 American League Championship Series|1998]], [[1999 American League Championship Series|1999]], [[2000 American League Championship Series|2000]], [[2001 American League Championship Series|2001]]}}
{{s-bef|before = [[Kansas City Royals]]&lt;br /&gt;[[2015 American League Championship Series|2015]]}}
{{s-ttl|title = American League champions&lt;br /&gt;Cleveland Indians|years = [[2016 American League Championship Series|2016]]}}
{{s-aft|after = [[Houston Astros]]&lt;br /&gt;[[2017 American League Championship Series|2017]]}}
{{s-end}}
{{Cleveland Indians}}
{{Navboxes|titlestyle={{Baseball primary style|Cleveland Indians|border=2}};|list1=
{{Cleveland Indians retired numbers}}
{{Navbox|navbar = plain|title = [[World Series|&lt;span style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;World Series&lt;/span&gt;]] championship navigation boxes|titlestyle={{Baseball primary style|Cleveland Indians|border=2}};|list1=
{{1920 Cleveland Indians}}
{{1948 Cleveland Indians}}
}}
{{American League}}
{{Native American mascot controversy}}
{{MLB}}
{{Cleveland Sports}}
{{Ohio Sports}}
{{Cleveland}}
}}
{{Portal bar|Baseball|Ohio}}

[[Category:1894 establishments in Ohio]]
[[Category:Cactus League]]
[[Category:Cleveland Indians| ]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball teams]]
[[Category:Sports clubs established in 1894]]</text>
      <sha1>q2nk3li3pgp0m31j5ds1zxvt6hr6gee</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
