  <page>
    <title>Citadel</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6695</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942139280</id>
      <parentid>939569311</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-22T21:12:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marisauna</username>
        <id>31599192</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about|the fortification}}
[[File:Casale Monferrato map (018 003).jpg|thumb|In this seventeenth-century plan of the fortified city of [[Casale Monferrato]] the citadel is the large [[Bastion fort|star-shaped structure]] on the left.]]
A '''citadel''' is the core fortified area of a town or city. It may be a [[castle]], [[fortress]], or fortified center. The term is a diminutive of &quot;city&quot; and thus means &quot;little city&quot;, so called because it is a smaller part of the city of which it is the defensive core. [[Ancient Sparta]] had a citadel, as did many other [[Ancient Greece|Greek]] cities and towns.

In a [[fortification]] with [[bastion]]s, the citadel is the strongest part of the system, sometimes well inside the outer walls and bastions, but often forming part of the outer wall for the sake of economy. It is positioned to be the last line of defense, should the enemy breach the other components of the fortification system. The functions of the police and the army, as well as the army [[barracks]] were developed in the citadel.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Encyclopedia of the City|last=Caves|first=R. W.|publisher=Routledge|year=2004|isbn=|location=|pages=83}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
===3300–1300 BCE===
Some of the oldest known structures which have served as citadels were built by the [[Indus Valley Civilisation]], where the citadel represented a centralised authority. The main citadel in Indus Valley was almost 12 meters tall.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Thapar |first=B. K. |year=1975 |title=Kalibangan: A Harappan Metropolis Beyond the Indus Valley |journal=Expedition |volume=17 |issue=2 |pages=19–32}}&lt;/ref&gt; The purpose of these structures, however, remains debated. Though the structures found in the ruins of [[Mohenjo-daro]] were walled, it is far from clear that these structures were defensive against enemy attacks. Rather, they may have been built to divert flood waters.

Several settlements in [[Anatolia]], including the Assyrian city of Kaneš in modern-day [[Kültepe]], featured citadels. Kaneš' citadel contained the city's palace, temples, and official buildings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Michel|first1=Cecile|publisher=Oxford|year=2016|isbn=9780199336012|title=The Oxford Handbook of Ancient Anatolia: (10,000-323 BCE)|editor=Sharon R. Steadman, Gregory McMahon|pages=313–320}}&lt;/ref&gt; The citadel of the Greek city of [[Mycenae]] was built atop a highly-defensible rectangular hill and was later surrounded by walls in order to increase its defensive capabilities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Citadel to City-State: The Transformation of Greece, 1200-700 B.C.E.|last1=Thomas|first1=Carol G.|last2=Conant|first2=Craig|pages=2–10|isbn=9780253216021|publisher=Indiana University Press|year=2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===800 BCE – 600===
[[File:Bibracte Porte Rebout.jpg|thumb|Reconstruction of the redoubt of [[Bibracte]], a part of the Gaulish ''[[oppidum]]''. The [[Celts]] utilized these fortified cities in the 2nd and 1st centuries BC.]]
In [[Ancient Greece]], the  [[Acropolis]] (literally: &quot;high city&quot;), placed on a commanding eminence, was important in the life of the people, serving as a refuge and stronghold in peril and containing military and food supplies, the [[shrine]] of the god and a royal [[palace]]. The most well known is the [[Acropolis of Athens]], but nearly every Greek city-state had one – the [[Acrocorinth]] famed as a particularly strong fortress. In a much later period, when Greece was ruled by the [[Latin Empire]], the same strong points were used by the new feudal rulers for much the same purpose.

In the first millennium BCE, the [[Castro culture]] emerged in northwestern Portugal and Spain in the region extending from the [[Douro]] river up to the [[Minho River|Minho]], but soon expanding north along the coast, and east following the river valleys. It was an autochthonous evolution of [[Atlantic Bronze Age]] communities. In 2008, the origins of the [[Celts]] were attributed to this period by [[John T. Koch]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Koch | first = John | title = Tartessian: Celtic from the Southwest at the Dawn of History in Acta Palaeohispanica X Palaeohispanica 9 (2009)| publisher = Palaeohispanica | year = 2009 | pages = 339–351 | url = http://ifc.dpz.es/recursos/publicaciones/29/54/26koch.pdf | issn = 1578-5386 | accessdate = 2010-05-17 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20100623034727/http://ifc.dpz.es/recursos/publicaciones/29/54/26koch.pdf| archivedate= 23 June 2010 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; and supported by [[Barry Cunliffe]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Cunliffe|first=Barry|title=A Race Apart: Insularity and Connectivity in Proceedings of the Prehistoric Society 75, 2009, pp. 55–64|year=2008| publisher=The Prehistoric Society|page=61}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Ave River]] Valley in Portugal was the core region of this culture,&lt;ref name=&quot;castrejoNWPort&quot;&gt;Armando Coelho Ferreira da Silva. ''A Cultura Castreja no Noroeste de Portugal''. Museu Arqueológico da Citânia de Sanfins, 1986&lt;/ref&gt; with a large number of small settlements (the ''castros''), but also settlements known as citadels or [[oppida]] by the Roman conquerors. These had several rings of walls and the Roman conquest of the citadels of Abobriga, Lambriaca and Cinania around 138 B.C. was possible only by prolonged [[siege]].&lt;ref name=&quot;galeg&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Don José de Santiago y Gómez|title=Historia de Vigo y Su comarca |publisher=Imprenta y Lotografía Del Asilo De Huérfanos Del Sagrado Corázon de Jesús|year=1896}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ruins of notable citadels still exist, and are known by archaeologists as [[Citânia de Briteiros]], [[Citânia de Sanfins]], [[Cividade de Terroso]] and [[Cividade de Bagunte]].&lt;ref name=&quot;castrejoNWPort&quot;/&gt;

====167–160 BCE====
Rebels who took power in the city but with the citadel still held by the former rulers could by no means regard their tenure of power as secure. One such incident played an important part in the history of the [[Maccabean Revolt]] against the [[Seleucid Empire]]. The [[Hellenistic]] [[garrison]] of [[Jerusalem]] and local supporters of the Seleucids held out for many years in the [[Acra (fortress)|Acra]] citadel, making Maccabean rule in the rest of Jerusalem precarious. When finally gaining possession of the place, the Maccabeans pointedly destroyed and razed the Acra, though they constructed another citadel for their own use in a different part of Jerusalem.

===500–1600===
[[File:Siége de la flotte turc.jpg|thumb|Although much of [[Nice]] was ransacked during the 1543 [[Siege of Nice|siege of the city]], [[Franco-Ottoman alliance|Franco-Ottoman]] forces besieging Nice were unable to capture its Citadel. Citadels have often been used as a last defence for a besieged army. ]]
At various periods, and particularly during the [[Middle Ages]] and the [[Renaissance]], the citadel – having its own fortifications, independent of the city walls – was the last defence of a besieged army, often held after the town had been conquered. Locals and defending armies have often held out citadels long after the city had fallen. For example, in the 1543 [[Siege of Nice]] the Ottoman forces led by [[Hayreddin Barbarossa|Barbarossa]] conquered and pillaged the town and took many captives, but the citadel held out.

In the [[Philippines]], the Ivatan people of the northern islands of [[Batanes]] often built fortifications to protect themselves during times of war. They built their so-called ''idjangs'' on hills and elevated areas. These fortifications were likened to European castles because of their purpose. Usually, the only entrance to the castles would be via a rope ladder that would only be lowered for the villagers and could be kept away when invaders arrived.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.filipiknow.net/archaeological-discoveries-in-the-philippines/|title=15 Most Intense Archaeological Discoveries in Philippine History|publisher=Filipknow|date=2018-07-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1600–present===
In time of war the citadel in many cases afforded retreat to the people living in the areas around the town. However, citadels were often used also to protect a garrison or political power from the inhabitants of the town where it was located, being designed to ensure loyalty from the town that they defended.

[[File:Battle-1t.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Americans assault the citadel during the [[Battle of Huế]], 1968. The battle showcased the effectiveness of citadels in modern warfare.]]
For example, during the [[Dutch Wars]] of 1664-1667, King [[Charles II of England]] constructed a Royal Citadel at [[Royal Citadel, Plymouth|Plymouth]], an important channel port which needed to be defended from a possible naval attack. However, due to Plymouth's support for the [[Roundhead|Parliamentarians]] in the then-recent [[English Civil War]], the Plymouth Citadel was so designed that its guns could fire on the town as well as on the sea approaches.

[[Barcelona]] had a great citadel built in 1714 to intimidate the [[Catalan people|Catalans]] against repeating their mid-17th- and early-18th-century rebellions against the Spanish central government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Vargas |first1=Michael |title=Constructing Catalan Identity |date=2018 |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |isbn=978-3-319-76744-4 |pages=89 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Y4lXDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA89&amp;lpg=PA89&amp;dq=citadel+in+barcelona+built+after+catalonia+attack&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=E7jfvHM7s5&amp;sig=ACfU3U2CQH6ZH70Hf-nU70ExborQ00bLJg&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwj8-9yqt5zmAhVOaq0KHS_DAn8Q6AEwDnoECAoQAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=citadel%20in%20barcelona%20built%20after%20catalonia%20attack&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 19th century, when the political climate had liberalized enough to permit it, the people of Barcelona had the citadel torn down, and replaced it with the city's main central park, the [[Parc de la Ciutadella]]. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Vargas |first1=Michael |title=Constructing Catalan Identity |date=2018 |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |isbn=978-3-319-76744-4 |pages=90 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Y4lXDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA89&amp;lpg=PA89&amp;dq=citadel+in+barcelona+built+after+catalonia+attack&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=E7jfvHM7s5&amp;sig=ACfU3U2CQH6ZH70Hf-nU70ExborQ00bLJg&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwj8-9yqt5zmAhVOaq0KHS_DAn8Q6AEwDnoECAoQAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=citadel%20in%20barcelona%20built%20after%20catalonia%20attack&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; A similar example is the [[Citadella]] in [[Budapest]], Hungary.

The attack on the [[Bastille]] in the [[French Revolution]] – though afterwards remembered mainly for the release of the handful of prisoners incarcerated there – was to considerable degree motivated by the structure's being a Royal citadel in the midst of revolutionary Paris.

Similarly, after [[Garibaldi]]'s overthrow of [[House of Bourbon|Bourbon]] rule in [[Palermo]], during the 1860 [[Unification of Italy]], Palermo's Castellamare Citadel – symbol of the hated and oppressive former rule – was ceremoniously demolished.

Following Belgium declaring independence in 1830, a Dutch garrison under General [[David Hendrik Chassé]] held out in [[Antwerp Citadel]] between 1830 and 1832, while the city had already become part of the independent Belgium.

The [[Siege of the Alcázar]] in the [[Spanish Civil War]], in which the Nationalists held out against a much larger Republican force for two months until relieved, shows that in some cases a citadel can be effective even in modern warfare; a similar case is the [[Battle of Huế]] during the [[Vietnam war]], where a [[North Vietnamese Army]] division held the citadel of Huế for 26 days against roughly their own numbers of much better-equipped US and South Vietnamese troops.

===Modern usage===
[[File:Royal 22e Régiment - panoramio.jpg|thumb|The [[Royal 22nd Regiment]]'s home garrison is the [[Citadelle of Quebec]] in [[Canada]]. The citadel is the largest still in military operation in North America.]]
The [[Citadelle of Québec]] (construction started 1673, completed 1820) still survives as the largest citadel still in official military operation in [[North America]]. It is home to the [[Royal 22nd Regiment]] of the [[Canadian Army]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.lacitadelle.qc.ca/en/la-citadelle.html |title=Musée Royal 22e Régiment - La Citadelle |accessdate=28 February 2014 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140228223051/http://www.lacitadelle.qc.ca/en/la-citadelle.html |archive-date=28 February 2014 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; and forms part of the [[Ramparts of Quebec City]] dating back to 1620s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.historicplaces.ca/en/rep-reg/place-lieu.aspx?id=13037&amp;pid=0 |title=Canada's Historic Places - HistoricPlaces.ca |accessdate=28 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the mid 20th century, citadels commonly enclose military command and control centres, rather than cities or strategic points of defense on the boundaries of a country. These modern citadels are built to protect the command center from heavy attacks, such as aerial or nuclear bombardment. The [[military citadels under London]] in the UK, including the massive underground complex Pindar beneath the [[Ministry of Defence (United Kingdom)|Ministry of Defence]], are examples, as is the [[Cheyenne Mountain nuclear bunker]] in the US.

==Naval term==
{{unreferenced section|date=July 2019}}
On armored warships, the heavily armored section of the ship that protects the ammunition and machinery spaces is called the [[armored citadel]].

A modern naval interpretation refers to the heaviest protected part of the hull as &quot;the vitals&quot;, and the citadel is the semi-armoured freeboard above the vitals. Generally Anglo-American and German language follow this while Russian sources/language refer to &quot;the vitals&quot; as цитадел &quot;tsitadel&quot;. Likewise Russian literature often refers to the turret of a tank as the 'tower'.

The [[safe room]] on a ship is also called a citadel.

==List of citadels==
{{see also|List of forts}}
{{Div col|colwidth=25em}}
* [[Amman Citadel]], Amman, Jordan
* [[Antwerp Citadel]], Belgium (demolished)
* [[Bam Citadel]], Iran
* [[Cairo Citadel]], Egypt
* [[Citadel of Aleppo]], Syria (partly destroyed, being rebuilt)
* [[Citadel of Erbil]], Iraq (partially ruined)
* [[Citadel of Ghazni]], Afghanistan
* [[Citadel of Liège]], Belgium (partially demolished)
* [[Citadel Počitelj]], Bosnia and Herzegovina
* [[Citadel Prins Frederik]], Indonesia (demolished)
* [[Citadel of Salah Ed-Din]], Syria (partially ruined)
* [[Citadella]], Hungary
* [[Cittadella (Gozo)]], Malta
* [[Citadelle Laferrière]], Haiti
* [[Citadelle of Quebec]], Canada
* [[Citadel Hill (Fort George)|Halifax Citadel]], Canada
* [[Herat Citadel]], Afghanistan
* Jerusalem Citadel or [[Tower of David]], Israel
* [[Landskrona Citadel]], Sweden
* [[Mainz Citadel]], Germany
* [[Petersberg Citadel]], Germany
* [[Royal Citadel, Plymouth]], United Kingdom
* [[Spandau Citadel]], Germany
* [[Verne Citadel]], United Kingdom
{{Div col end}}

==See also== 
* [[Acropolis]]
* [[Alcazaba]] a term for Moorish citadels in Spain
* [[Alcázar]]
* [[Arx (Roman)]]
* [[Fujian Tulou]]
* [[Kasbah]] a synonym
* [[Kremlin (fortification)]]
* [[Presidio]]
* [[Rocca (architecture)]]

==References==
{{Reflist|40em}}

==External links==
* {{commons category-inline|Citadels}}

{{Fortifications}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Fortifications by type]]
[[Category:Military strategy]]</text>
      <sha1>0xc5m1mb1lyb1k53txo1tp4e3zo121x</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
