  <page>
    <title>Compactification (mathematics)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6617</id>
    <revision>
      <id>930625584</id>
      <parentid>922868366</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-13T19:42:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Citation bot</username>
        <id>7903804</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Alter: issue, template type. Add: hdl. Formatted [[WP:ENDASH|dashes]]. | You can [[WP:UCB|use this bot]] yourself. [[WP:DBUG|Report bugs here]].| Activated by [[User:Nemo bis]] | via #UCB_webform</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">In [[mathematics]], in [[general topology]], '''compactification''' is the process or result of making a [[topological space]] into a [[compact space]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Munkres | first=James R. | authorlink=James Munkres | title=Topology | edition=2nd | publisher=[[Prentice Hall]] | year=2000 | isbn=0-13-181629-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; A compact space is a space in which every [[open cover]] of the space contains a finite subcover. The methods of compactification are various, but each is a way of controlling points from &quot;going off to infinity&quot; by in some way adding &quot;points at infinity&quot; or preventing such an &quot;escape&quot;.

==An example==

Consider the [[real line]] with its ordinary topology. This space is not compact; in a sense, points can go off to infinity to the left or to the right. It is possible to turn the real line into a compact space by adding a single &quot;point at infinity&quot; which we will denote by ∞. The resulting compactification can be thought of as a circle (which is compact as a closed and bounded subset of the Euclidean plane). Every sequence that ran off to infinity in the real line will then converge to ∞ in this compactification.

Intuitively, the process can be pictured as follows: first shrink the real line to the [[open interval]] (-[[pi|π]],π) on the ''x''-axis; then bend the ends of this interval upwards (in positive ''y''-direction) and move them towards each other, until you get a circle with one point (the topmost one) missing. This point is our new point ∞ &quot;at infinity&quot;; adding it in completes the compact circle.

A bit more formally: we represent a point on the [[unit circle]] by its [[angle]], in [[radian]]s, going from -π to π for simplicity.  Identify each such point θ on the circle with the corresponding point on the real line [[tangent|tan]](θ/2).  This function is undefined at the point π, since tan(π/2) is undefined; we will identify this point with our point ∞.

Since tangents and inverse tangents are both continuous, our identification function is a [[homeomorphism]] between the real line and the unit circle without ∞. What we have constructed is called the ''Alexandroff one-point compactification'' of the real line, discussed in more generality below. It is also possible to compactify the real line by adding ''two'' points, +∞ and -∞; this results in the [[extended real line]].

==Definition==

An [[embedding]] of a topological space ''X'' as a [[dense set|dense]] subset of a compact space is called a '''compactification''' of ''X''. It is often useful to embed [[topological space]]s in [[compact space]]s, because of the special properties compact spaces have.

Embeddings into compact [[Hausdorff space]]s may be of particular interest. Since every compact Hausdorff space is a [[Tychonoff space]], and every subspace of a Tychonoff space is Tychonoff, we conclude that any space possessing a Hausdorff compactification must be a Tychonoff space.  In fact, the converse is also true; being a Tychonoff space is both necessary and sufficient for possessing a Hausdorff compactification.

The fact that large and interesting classes of non-compact spaces do in fact have compactifications of particular sorts makes compactification a common technique in topology.

===Alexandroff one-point compactification===
{{main|One-point compactification}}
For any topological space ''X'' the ('''Alexandroff''') '''one-point compactification''' α''X'' of ''X'' is obtained by adding one extra point ∞ (often called a ''point at infinity'') and defining the [[open set]]s of the new space to be the open sets of ''X'' together with the sets of the form ''G''&amp;nbsp;∪&amp;nbsp;{∞}, where ''G'' is an open subset of ''X'' such that ''X'' \ ''G'' is compact. The one-point compactification of ''X'' is Hausdorff if and only if ''X'' is Hausdorff and [[locally compact]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|first=Pavel S.|last= Alexandroff|authorlink=Pavel Alexandroff| journal=  [[Mathematische Annalen]] |volume= 92|issue=3–4  |year=1924|pages= 294–301|title= Über die Metrisation der im Kleinen kompakten topologischen Räume | url=https://eudml.org/doc/159072 | doi=10.1007/BF01448011 | jfm=50.0128.04 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Stone–Čech compactification===
{{main|Stone–Čech compactification}}
Of particular interest are Hausdorff compactifications, i.e., compactifications in which the compact space is [[Hausdorff space|Hausdorff]]. A topological space has a Hausdorff compactification if and only if it is [[Tychonoff space|Tychonoff]]. In this case, there is a unique ([[up to]] [[homeomorphism]]) &quot;most general&quot; Hausdorff compactification, the [[Stone–Čech compactification]] of ''X'', denoted by β''X''; formally, this exhibits the [[category (mathematics)|category]] of Compact Hausdorff spaces and continuous maps as a [[reflective subcategory]] of the category of Tychonoff spaces and continuous maps.

&quot;Most general&quot; or formally &quot;reflective&quot; means that the space β''X'' is characterized by the [[universal property]] that any [[continuous function (topology)|continuous function]] from ''X'' to a compact Hausdorff space ''K'' can be extended to a continuous function from β''X'' to ''K'' in a unique way. More explicitly, β''X'' is a compact Hausdorff space containing ''X'' such that the [[subspace topology|induced topology]] on ''X'' by β''X'' is the same as the given topology on ''X'', and for any continuous map ''f'':''X'' → ''K'', where ''K'' is a compact Hausdorff space, there is a unique continuous map ''g'':β''X'' → ''K'' for which ''g'' restricted to ''X'' is identically ''f''.

The Stone–Čech compactification can be constructed explicitly as follows: let ''C'' be the set of continuous functions from ''X'' to the closed interval [0,1].  Then each point in ''X'' can be identified with an evaluation function on ''C''.  Thus ''X'' can be identified with a subset of [0,1]&lt;sup&gt;''C''&lt;/sup&gt;, the space of ''all'' functions from ''C'' to [0,1].  Since the latter is compact by [[Tychonoff's theorem]], the closure of ''X'' as a subset of that space will also be compact.  This is the Stone–Čech compactification.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first=Eduard|last= Čech|authorlink=Eduard Čech| title=On bicompact spaces|journal=  [[Annals of Mathematics]] |volume= 38  |year=1937  |pages= 823–844|doi=10.2307/1968839|issue=4|jstor=1968839|hdl= 10338.dmlcz/100420}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|first=Marshall H.|last= Stone|authorlink=Marshall Harvey Stone|title=Applications of the theory of Boolean rings to general topology  |journal=[[Transactions of the American Mathematical Society]] |volume= 41  |year=1937|pages= 375–481
|issue=3|doi=10.2307/1989788 |jstor=1989788}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Spacetime compactification===
[[Walter Benz]] and [[Isaak Yaglom]] have shown how [[stereographic projection]] onto a single-sheet [[hyperboloid]] can be used to provide a [[Motor variable#Compactification|compactification for split complex numbers]]. In fact, the hyperboloid is part of a [[quadric]] in real projective four-space. The method is similar to that used to provide a base manifold for [[group action (mathematics)|group action]] of the [[conformal group of spacetime]].&lt;ref&gt;15 parameter conformal group of spacetime described in {{Wikibooks-inline|Associative Composition Algebra/Homographies}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Projective space==
[[Real projective space]] '''RP'''&lt;sup&gt;''n''&lt;/sup&gt; is a compactification of Euclidean space '''R'''&lt;sup&gt;''n''&lt;/sup&gt;. For each possible &quot;direction&quot; in which points in '''R'''&lt;sup&gt;''n''&lt;/sup&gt; can &quot;escape&quot;, one new point at infinity is added (but each direction is identified with its opposite). The Alexandroff one-point compactification of '''R''' we constructed in the example above is in fact homeomorphic to '''RP'''&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;. Note however that the [[projective plane]] '''RP'''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; is ''not'' the one-point compactification of the plane '''R'''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; since more than one point is added.

[[Complex projective space]] '''CP'''&lt;sup&gt;''n''&lt;/sup&gt; is also a compactification of  '''C'''&lt;sup&gt;''n''&lt;/sup&gt;; the Alexandroff one-point compactification of the plane '''C''' is (homeomorphic to) the complex projective line '''CP'''&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;, which in turn can be identified with a sphere, the [[Riemann sphere]].

Passing to projective space is a common tool in [[algebraic geometry]] because the added points at infinity lead to simpler formulations of many theorems. For example, any two different lines in '''RP'''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; intersect in precisely one point, a statement that is not true in '''R'''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;. More generally, [[Bézout's theorem]], which is fundamental in [[intersection theory]], holds in projective space but not affine space. This distinct behavior of intersections in affine space and projective space is reflected in [[algebraic topology]] in the [[cohomology ring]]s – the cohomology of affine space is trivial, while the cohomology of projective space is non-trivial and reflects the key features of intersection theory (dimension and degree of a subvariety, with intersection being [[Poincaré dual]] to the [[cup product]]).

Compactification of [[moduli space]]s generally require allowing certain degeneracies – for example, allowing certain singularities or reducible varieties. This is notably used in the Deligne–Mumford compactification of the [[Moduli of algebraic curves|moduli space of algebraic curves]].

==Compactification and discrete subgroups of Lie groups==

In the study of [[discrete space|discrete]] subgroups of [[Lie group]]s, the [[Quotient space (topology)|quotient space]] of [[coset]]s is often a candidate for more subtle '''compactification''' to preserve structure at a richer level than just topological.

For example, [[modular curve]]s are compactified by the addition of single points for each [[cusp (singularity)|cusp]], making them [[Riemann surface]]s (and so, since they are compact, [[algebraic curve]]s). Here the cusps are there for a good reason: the curves parametrize a space of [[lattice (group)|lattices]], and those lattices can degenerate ('go off to infinity'), often in a number of ways (taking into account some auxiliary structure of ''level''). The cusps stand in for those different 'directions to infinity'.

That is all for lattices in the plane. In ''n''-dimensional [[Euclidean space]] the same questions can be posed, for example about SO(n)\SL&lt;sub&gt;''n''&lt;/sub&gt;('''R''')/SL&lt;sub&gt;''n''&lt;/sub&gt;('''Z'''). This is harder to compactify. There are a variety of compactifications, such as the [[Borel–Serre compactification]], the [[reductive Borel-Serre compactification]], and the [[Satake compactification]]s, that can be formed.

==Other compactification theories==

*The theories of [[end (topology)|ends of a space]] and [[prime end]]s.
*Some 'boundary' theories such as the [[collaring of an open manifold]], [[Martin boundary]], [[Shilov boundary]] and [[Furstenberg boundary]].
*The [[Bohr compactification]] of a [[topological group]] arises from the consideration of [[almost periodic function]]s.
*The [[projective line over a ring]] for a [[topological ring]] may compactify it.
*The [[Baily–Borel compactification]] of a quotient of a [[Hermitian symmetric space]].
*The [[wonderful compactification]] of a quotient of algebraic groups.
*The compactifications that are simultaneously convex subsets in a locally convex space are called [[convex compactification]]s, their additional linear structure allowing e.g. for developing a differential calculus and more advanced considerations e.g. in relaxation in variational calculus or optimization theory.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Roubíček | first=T. | authorlink=Tomas Roubicek | title=Relaxation in Optimization Theory and Variational Calculus | publisher=[[W. de Gruyter]] |place = Berlin | year=1997 | isbn=3-11-014542-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Compactification| ]]</text>
      <sha1>8bh08xvsw2sw0t0xv9c6u9f5e7294ap</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
