  <page>
    <title>Code of Hammurabi</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7604</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942336110</id>
      <parentid>942336083</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-24T02:11:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Hypoxine</username>
        <id>38533828</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/119.18.36.80|119.18.36.80]] ([[User talk:119.18.36.80|talk]]) to last revision by El C ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|The Code of Hammurabi|the BT song|_ (album)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2015}}
{{Infobox document
|document_name=Code of Hammurabi
|image=Code-de-Hammurabi-1.jpg
|image_width=250px
|image_caption= A side view of the [[stele]] &quot;fingertip&quot; at the [[Louvre Museum]]
|date_created= c. 1754 BC
|date_ratified=|writer=[[Hammurabi]]
|
|wikisource=The Code of Hammurabi
}}

The '''Code of Hammurabi''' is a well-preserved [[Babylon]]ian [[code of law]] of ancient [[Mesopotamia]], dated to about 1754 BC ([[Middle Chronology]]). It is one of the oldest deciphered writings of significant length in the world. The sixth Babylonian king, [[Hammurabi]], enacted the code. A partial copy exists on a 2.25-metre-tall (7.5&amp;nbsp;ft) stone [[stele]]. It consists of 282 laws, with scaled punishments, adjusting &quot;an [[eye for an eye]], a tooth for a tooth&quot; ({{Lang|la|[[lex talionis]]}})&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Prince|first=J. Dyneley|date=July 1904|title=The Code of Hammurabi|url=|journal=The American Journal of Theology|type=|publisher=The University of Chicago Press|volume=8|issue=3|pages=601–609|doi=10.1086/478479|jstor=3153895}}&lt;/ref&gt; as graded based on [[social stratification]] depending on social status and gender, of [[Slavery in the Ancient Near East|slave]] versus free, man versus woman.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bar&quot;&gt;Gabriele Bartz &amp; Eberhard König, ''Arts and Architecture—Louvre'', (Köln: Könemann, 2005), {{ISBN|978-3-8331-1943-9}}. The laws were based with scaled punishments, adjusting &quot;[[an eye for an eye]]&quot; depending on social status and gender.&lt;/ref&gt;

Nearly half of the code deals with matters of contract, establishing the wages to be paid to an ox driver or a surgeon for example. Other provisions set the terms of a transaction, the liability of a builder for a house that collapses, or property that is damaged while left in the care of another. A third of the code addresses issues concerning household and family relationships such as inheritance, divorce, paternity, and [[sexual behavior|reproductive behavior]]. Only one provision appears to impose obligations on a government official; this provision establishes that a judge who alters his decision after it is written down is to be fined and removed from the bench permanently.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.commonlaw.com/Hammurabi.html Code of Hammurabi] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070921205329/http://www.commonlaw.com/Hammurabi.html |date=21 September 2007 }} at commonlaw.com  {{citation |url=http://www.commonlaw.com/home/legal-history-and-philosophy/code-of-hammurabi |date=22 May 2017 |title=Code of Hammarubi at Commonlaw }}&lt;/ref&gt; A few provisions address issues related to military service.

The code was discovered by modern [[archaeology|archaeologists]] in 1901, and its {{Lang|la|[[editio princeps]]}} translation published in 1902 by [[Jean-Vincent Scheil]]. This nearly complete example of the code is carved into a [[diorite]] stele&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Ancient mesopotamian materials and industries : the archaeological evidence|last=Moorey, P. R. S. (Peter Roger Stuart), 1937-|date=1999|publisher=Eisenbrauns|isbn=1575060426|location=Winona Lake, Ind.|pages=29|oclc=42907384}}&lt;/ref&gt; in the shape of a huge [[index finger]],&lt;ref&gt;Iconographic Evidence for Some Mesopotamian Cult Statues, Dominique Collon, Die Welt der Götterbilder, Edited by Groneberg, Brigitte; Spieckermann, Hermann;, and Weiershäuser, Frauke, Berlin, New York (Walter de Gruyter) 2007, pp. 57–84&lt;/ref&gt; {{convert|2.25|m|foot|abbr=on}} tall. The code is inscribed in the [[Akkadian language]], using [[cuneiform script]] carved into the stele. The material was imported into Sumeria from [[Magan (civilization)|Magan]] - today the area covered by the [[United Arab Emirates]] and [[Oman]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=STORY OF CHALDEA FROM THE EARLIEST TIMES TO THE RISE OF ASSYRIA : treated as a general ... introduction to the study of ancient history.|last=RAGOZIN, ZENAIDE A.|date=2017|publisher=FORGOTTEN Books|isbn=978-1330342589|location=[Place of publication not identified]|pages=209|oclc=990104817}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is currently on display in the [[Louvre]], with replicas in numerous institutions, including the [[University of Chicago Oriental Institute|Oriental Institute at the University of Chicago]], the Northwestern Pritzker School of Law in Chicago, the Clendening History of Medicine Library &amp; Museum at the University of Kansas Medical Center, the library of the [[Theological University of the Reformed Churches]] in the Netherlands, the [[Pergamon Museum]] of Berlin, the Arts Faculty of the University of Leuven in Belgium, the [[National Museum of Iran]] in Tehran, the Department of Anthropology, [[National Museum of Natural History]], [[Smithsonian Institution]], the [[University of Pennsylvania Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology|University Museum at the University of Pennsylvania]], the [[Pushkin State Museum of Fine Arts]] in Russia, the Prewitt-Allen Archaeological Museum at Corban University, Garrett-Evangelical Theological Seminary, and [[Museum of the Bible]] in Washington, DC.

==History==
{{multiple image
| image1 = Prologue Hammurabi Code Louvre AO10237.jpg
| width1 = 136
| caption1 = The code on clay tablets
| image2 = Code of Hammurabi.jpg
| width2 = 136
| caption2 = The code on a diorite stele
| footer = Two versions of the Code at the [[Louvre]]
| align = 
| direction = 
| total_width = 
| alt1 = 
}}
[[Hammurabi]] ruled from 1792 to 1750 BC (according to the [[middle chronology]]). At the head of the stone slab is Hammurabi receiving the law from [[Shamash]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Wells |first=H. G. |title=The Outline of History: Volume&amp;nbsp;1 |date=1961 |publisher=Doubleday |p=176}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in the preface, he states, &quot;[[Anu]] and [[Bel (mythology)|Bel]] called by name me, Hammurabi, the exalted prince, who feared God, to bring about the rule of righteousness in the land, to destroy the wicked and the evil-doers; so that the strong should not harm the weak; so that I should rule over the black-headed people like [[Shamash]], and enlighten the land, to further the well-being of mankind.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;wsu&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wsu.edu/~dee/MESO/CODE.HTM |title=Mesopotamia: The Code of Hammurabi |accessdate=14 September 2007 |publisher=Washington State University |year=1996 |author1=Edited by Richard Hooker |author2=Translated by L.W King |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070909114038/http://www.wsu.edu/~dee/MESO/CODE.HTM |archivedate=9 September 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The 282 laws were arranged in 44 columns and 28 paragraphs; some follow along the rules of &quot;an [[eye for an eye]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Hammurabi's Code&quot; {{cite web|url=http://library.thinkquest.org/20176/hammurabis_code.htm |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2011-11-11 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111101094743/http://library.thinkquest.org/20176/hammurabis_code.htm |archivedate=1 November 2011 }}, Think Quest, retrieved on 2 Nov 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

It was taken as plunder by the [[Elam]]ite king [[Shutruk-Nahhunte]] in the 12th century BC and was taken to [[Susa]] in [[Elam]] (located in the present-day [[Khuzestan Province]] of Iran), where it was no longer available to the Babylonian people. However, when [[Cyrus the Great]] brought both Babylon and Susa under the rule of his [[Achaemenid Empire|Persian Empire]] and placed copies of the document in the [[Library of Sippar]], the text became available for all the peoples of the vast Persian Empire to view.&lt;ref&gt;Marc Van De Mieroop: A History of the Ancient Near East, second edition p. 296&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1901, Egyptologist [[Gustave Jéquier]], a member of an expedition headed by [[Jacques de Morgan]], found the stele containing the Code of Hammurabi during archaeological excavations at the ancient site of Susa in Khuzestan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0H0EpSm8aioC&amp;pg=PA313&amp;dq=khuzestan+susa+hammurabi#v=onepage&amp;q=khuzestan%20susa%20hammurabi|title=Cultures in Contact: From Mesopotamia to the Mediterranean in the Second Millennium B.C|publisher=[[Metropolitan Museum of Art]]|date=2013|access-date=1 November 2015|isbn=9781588394750}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Laws of Hammurabi's Code==
{{Main|Babylonian law}}
The Code of Hammurabi was one of the only sets of laws in the [[ancient Near East]] and also one of the first forms of law.&lt;ref name=&quot;yale&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/medieval/hamframe.htm |title=The Code of Hammurabi: Translated by L.W. King |accessdate=14 September 2007 |publisher=Yale University |year=2005 |author=L.W. King |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070916163034/http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/medieval/hamframe.htm |archivedate=16 September 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The code of laws was arranged in orderly groups, so that all who read the laws would know what was required of them.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Code of Hammurabi: Introduction,&quot; [http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/ancient/hamcode.asp], Ancient History Sourcebook, March 1998, retrieved on 2 November 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Earlier collections of laws include the [[Code of Ur-Nammu]], king of [[Ur]] (c. {{Spaces|1}}2050 BC), the [[Laws of Eshnunna]] (c.{{Spaces|1}}1930 BC) and the codex of [[Lipit-Ishtar]] of [[Isin]] (c.{{Spaces|1}}1870 BC), while later ones include the [[Hittite laws]], the [[Assyrian law]]s, and [[Mosaic Law]].&lt;ref&gt;Barton, G.A: ''Archaeology and the Bible''. University of Michigan Library, 2009, (originally published in 1916 by American Sunday-School Union) p. 406.&lt;/ref&gt; These codes come from similar cultures in a relatively small geographical area, and they have passages that resemble each other.&lt;ref&gt;Barton 2009, p. 406. Barton, a scientist of Semitic languages at the University of Pennsylvania from 1922 to 1931, stated that while there are similarities between the Mosaic Law and the Code of Hammurabi, a study of the entirety of both laws &quot;convinces the student that the laws of the Old Testament are in no essential way dependent upon the Babylonian laws.&quot; He states that &quot;such resemblances&quot; arose from &quot;a similarity of antecedents and of general intellectual outlook&quot; between the two cultures, but that &quot;the striking differences show that there was no direct borrowing.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Milkau Oberer Teil der Stele mit dem Text von Hammurapis Gesetzescode 369-2.png|thumb|Figures at the top of the stele &quot;fingernail&quot;, above Hammurabi's code of laws.]]
The Code of Hammurabi is the longest surviving text from the Old Babylonian period.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Code of Hammurabi,&quot; [http://www.historyguide.org/ancient/hammurabi.html], The History Guide, 3 August 2009, Retrieved on 2 November 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The code has been seen as an early example of a fundamental law, regulating a government – i.e., a primitive [[constitution]].&lt;ref&gt;What is a Constitution? William David Thomas, Gareth Stevens (2008) p. 8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Flach, Jacques.  Le Code de Hammourabi et la constitution originaire de la propriete dans l'ancienne Chaldee. (Revue historique.  Paris, 1907. 8. v. 94, pp. 272–289.&lt;/ref&gt; The code is also one of the earliest examples of the idea of [[presumption of innocence]], and it also suggests that both the accused and accuser have the opportunity to provide [[evidence]].&lt;ref&gt;Victimology: Theories and Applications, Ann Wolbert Burgess, Albert R. Roberts, Cheryl Regehr, Jones &amp; Bartlett Learning, 2009, p. 103&lt;/ref&gt; The occasional nature of many provisions suggests that the code may be better understood as a codification of Hammurabi's supplementary judicial decisions, and that, by memorializing his wisdom and justice, its purpose may have been the self-glorification of Hammurabi rather than a modern legal code or constitution. However, its copying in subsequent generations indicates that it was used as a model of legal and judicial reasoning.&lt;ref&gt;For this alternative interpretation see Jean Bottéro, &quot;The 'Code' of Hammurabi&quot; in ''Mesopotamia: Writing, Reasoning and the Gods'' (University of Chicago, 1992), pp. 156–184.&lt;/ref&gt;

While the Code of Hammurabi was trying to achieve equality, biases still existed against those categorized in the lower end of the social spectrum and some of the punishments and justice could be gruesome. The magnitude of criminal penalties often was based on the identity and gender of both the person committing the crime and the victim. The Code issues justice following the three classes of Babylonian society: property owners, freed men, and slaves.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.history.com/news/history-lists/8-things-you-may-not-know-about-hammurabis-code|title=8 Things You May Not Know About Hammurabi's Code|work=History.com|access-date=2017-09-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Punishments for someone assaulting someone from a lower class were far lighter than if they had assaulted someone of equal or higher status.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;/&gt; For example, if a doctor killed a rich patient, he would have his hands cut off, but if he killed a slave, only financial restitution was required.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historyextra.com/article/international-history/nutshell-babylon|title=What was Babylon?|work=History Extra|access-date=16 February 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160129094221/http://www.historyextra.com/article/international-history/nutshell-babylon|archive-date=29 January 2016|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Women could also receive punishments that their male counterparts would not, as men were permitted to have affairs with their servants and slaves, whereas married women would be harshly punished for committing adultery.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

==Other copies==
[[File: Hammurabi stele amnh ny.JPG|thumb|The Hammurabi stele at the [[American Museum of Natural History]], New York.]]
[[File: Hammurabi code Istanbul.jpg|thumb|A version of the code at the [[Istanbul Archaeological Museums]].]]
Various copies of portions of the Code of Hammurabi have been found on baked clay tablets, some possibly older than the celebrated basalt stele now in the Louvre. The Prologue of the Code of Hammurabi (the first 305 inscribed squares on the stele) is on such a tablet, also at the Louvre (Inv #AO 10237). Some gaps in the list of benefits bestowed on cities recently annexed by Hammurabi may imply that it is older than the famous stele (currently dated to the early 18th century BC).&lt;ref&gt;Fant, Clyde E. and Mitchell G. Reddish (2008), [https://books.google.com/books?id=Dj6zVQJz7zYC&amp;pg=PA62&amp;dq=%22Code+of+Hammurabi%22+AND+2358 ''Lost Treasures of the Bible: Understanding the Bible Through Archaeological Artifacts in World Museums''], Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing Co., p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt; Likewise, the Museum of the Ancient Orient, part of the [[Istanbul Archaeology Museums]], also has a &quot;Code of Hammurabi&quot; clay tablet, dated to 1790 BC (in Room 5, Inv # Ni 2358).&lt;ref&gt;[[John Freely|Freely, John]], ''Blue Guide Istanbul'' (5th ed., 2000), London: [[A&amp;C Black]], New York: [[WW Norton]], p. 121. (&quot;The most historic of the inscriptions here [i.e., Room 5, Museum of the Ancient Orient, Istanbul] is the famous Code of Hammurabi (#Ni 2358) dated 1750 BC, the world's oldest recorded set of laws.&quot;)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.istanbul.gov.tr/Default.aspx?pid=13150 Museum of the Ancient Orient website] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120503212551/http://english.istanbul.gov.tr/Default.aspx?pid=13150 |date=3 May 2012 }} (&quot;This museum contains a rich collection of ancient ... archaeological finds, including ... seals from Nippur and a copy of the Code of Hammurabi.&quot;)&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2010, archaeologists reported that a fragmentary Akkadian cuneiform tablet was discovered at [[Tel Hazor]], [[Israel]], containing a c.{{Spaces|1}}1700 BC text that was said to be partly parallel to portions of the Hammurabi code. The Hazor law code fragments are currently being prepared for publication by a team from the [[Hebrew University of Jerusalem]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.israelnationalnews.com/News/News.aspx/138788|title=Code of Hammurabi Tablet Found |work=Inside Israel News – Arutz Sheva}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Laws covered==
{{external media | width = 210px | align = right | headerimage = [[File:P1050763 Louvre code Hammurabi face rwk.JPG|210px]] | video1 = [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JO9YxZYd0qY Law Code Stele of King Hammurabi, 1792–1750 BC], [[Smarthistory]]
}}
One of the best known laws from Hammurabi's code was:
{{quote| Ex. Law #196: &quot;If a man destroy the eye of another man, they shall destroy his eye. If one break a man's bone, they shall break his bone. If one destroy the eye of a freeman or break the bone of a freeman he shall pay one gold [[Mina (unit)|mina]]. If one destroy the eye of a man's slave or break a bone of a man's slave he shall pay one-half his price.&quot;&lt;ref name=Code/&gt;}}

Hammurabi had many other punishments, as well. If a son strikes his father, his hands shall be hewn off. Translations vary.&lt;ref name=&quot;king translation&quot;&gt;Translated by L.W. King, Hammurabi's Code of Laws, [http://eawc.evansville.edu/anthology/hammurabi.htm ''Hammurabi's Code of Laws''] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080509192326/http://eawc.evansville.edu/anthology/hammurabi.htm |date=9 May 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;harper translation&quot;&gt;Translated by L.W. King, Hammurabi's Code of Laws, [//upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/4/4e/The_code_of_Hammurabi.pdf The Code of Hammurabi King of Babylon] by Robert Francis Harper (PDF)&lt;/ref&gt;

The laws covered such subjects as:

; Slander
: Ex. Law #127: &quot;If any one 'point the finger' at a sister of a god or the wife of any one, and can not prove it, this man shall be taken before the judges and his brow shall be marked (by cutting the skin, or perhaps hair).&quot;&lt;ref name=Code&gt;{{cite web|title=The Code of Hammurabi|website= Internet Sacred Text Archive|publisher= Evinity Publishing  |year=2011|accessdate=17 November 2013|url=http://www.sacred-texts.com/ane/ham/ham06.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; Fraud
: Ex. Law #265:  &quot;If a herdsman, to whose care cattle or sheep have been entrusted, be guilty of fraud and make false returns of the natural increase, or sell them for money, then shall he be convicted and pay the owner ten times the loss.&quot;&lt;ref name=Code/&gt;
; Slavery and status of slaves as property
: Ex. Law #15:  &quot;If any one take a male or female slave of the court, or a male or female slave of a freed man, outside the city gates, he shall be put to death.&quot;&lt;ref name=Code/&gt;
; The duties of workers
: Ex. Law #42:  &quot;If any one take over a field to till it, and obtain no harvest therefrom, it must be proved that he did no work on the field, and he must deliver grain, just as his neighbor raised, to the owner of the field.&quot;&lt;ref name=Code/&gt;
; Theft
: Ex. Law #22: &quot;If any one is committing a robbery and is caught, then he shall be put to death.&quot;&lt;ref name=Code/&gt;
; Trade
: Ex. Law #104: &quot;If a merchant give an agent grain, wool, oil, or any  other goods to transport, the agent shall give a receipt for the amount, and compensate the merchant therefore, he shall obtain a receipt from the merchant for the money that he gives the merchant.&quot;&lt;ref name=Code/&gt;
; Liability
: Ex. Law #53: &quot;If any one be too apathetic to keep his dam in primly condition, and does not so keep it; if then the dam break and all the fields be flooded, then shall he in whose dam the break occurred be sold for money, and the money shall replace the crops which he has caused to be ruined.&quot;&lt;ref name=Code/&gt;
;Divorce
: Ex. Law #142: &quot;If a woman quarrel with her husband, and say: &quot;You are not congenial to me,&quot; the reasons for her prejudice must be presented. If she is guiltless, and there is no fault on her part, but he leaves and neglects her, then no guilt attaches to this woman, she shall take her dowry and go back to her father's house.&quot;&lt;ref name=Code/&gt;
;Adultery
: Ex. Law #129: &quot;If the wife of a man has been caught lying with another man, they shall bind them and throw them into the waters. If the owner of the wife would save his wife then in turn the king could save his servant.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Western Civilization Volume 1: From the Origins of Civilization to the Age of Absolutism|last=C. Sax|first=Benjamin|publisher=Greenhaven Press|year=2001|isbn=978-1-56510-988-9|location=San Diego|page=[https://archive.org/details/westerncivilizat0000unse/page/35 35]|url=https://archive.org/details/westerncivilizat0000unse/page/35}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; Perjury
: Ex. Law #3: &quot;If a man has borne false witness in a trial, or has not established the statement that he has made, if that case be a capital trial, that man shall be put to death.&quot;&lt;ref name=Code/&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Law|Asia|Middle East}}
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
*[[Code of the Assura]]
*[[Cuneiform Law]]
*[[Hippocratic Oath]]
*[[List of ancient legal codes]]
*''[[Quid pro quo]]''
*[[Urukagina]] – Sumerian king and creator of what is sometimes cited as the first example of a legal code in recorded history
{{div col end}}

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
*{{Cite book|last=Beck|first=Roger B.|authorlink=|author2 = Linda Black, Larry S. Krieger, Phillip C. Naylor, Dahia Ibo Shabaka|title=World History: Patterns of Interaction|publisher=McDougal Luttrell |year=1999 |location=Evanston, IL|pages=|url=|doi=|isbn=978-0-395-87274-1 }}
* Bonhomme, Brian, and Cathleen Boivin. &quot;Code of Hammurabi.&quot; Milestone Documents in World History. Exploring the Primary Sources That Shaped the World: 2350 BCE – 1058 CE. Vol. 1. Dallas, TX: Schlager Group, 2010. 23–31.
*{{Cite book|last=Bryant |first=Tamera|title=The Life &amp; Times of Hammurabi|publisher=Mitchell Lane Publishers|location=Bear|year=2005|isbn=978-1-58415-338-2}}
*{{Cite book|author1=Driver, G.R.  |author2=J.C. Miles | title = The Babylonian Laws | publisher = Wipf and Stock|location=Eugene|year=2007 |isbn=978-1-55635-229-4}}
*Elsen-Novák, G./Novák, M.: ''Der 'König der Gerechtigkeit'. Zur Ikonologie und Teleologie des 'Codex' Hammurapi.'' In: Baghdader Mitteilungen 37 (2006), pp.&amp;nbsp;131–156.
*Falkenstein, A. (1956–57). ''Die neusumerischen Gerichtsurkunden I–III''. München.
* Febbraro, Flavio, and Burkhard Schwetje. ''How to Read World History in Art''. New York: Abrams, 2010. Print.
*{{Cite book |last=Hammurabi |first=King |author2=C. H. W. Johns (Translator)|title=The Oldest Code of Laws in the World|publisher=Lawbook Exchange Ltd|location=City|year=2000|isbn=978-1-58477-061-9}}
*{{Cite book|last=Mieroop|first=Marc|title=King Hammurabi of Babylon: a Biography|publisher=Blackwell Publishers|location=Cambridge|year=2004|isbn=978-1-4051-2660-1|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/kinghammurabiofb00marc}}
*[[Julius Oppert]] and [[Joachim Menant]] (1877). ''Documents juridiques de l'Assyrie et de la Chaldee''. París.
*{{Cite book|last=Roth|first=Martha T.|title=Law Collections from Mesopotamia and Asia Minor|publisher=Scholars Press|location= Atlanta |year=1997|isbn=978-0-7885-0378-8}}
* [[Editio princeps]]: {{cite book|chapter=Code des Lois de Hammurabi|chapter-url=https://archive.org/stream/mmoires04franuoft#page/11/mode/1up|authorlink= Jean-Vincent Scheil|first=Jean-Vincent|last=Scheil|volume=4 (Textes Elamites-Semitiques)|title=Memoires de la delegation en Perse|date=1902|publisher=Paris P. Geuthner [etc.]}}
* Thomas, D. Winton, ed. (1958). ''Documents from Old Testament Times''. London and New York.
{{div col end}}

==External links==
{{Commons+cat}}
{{Wikisource|Codex Hammurabi}}
{{Wiktionary|Hammurabi}}
* [http://www.general-intelligence.com/library/hr.pdf The Code of Hammurabi Translated by L. W. King].
* [http://www.louvre.fr/en/oeuvre-notices/law-code-hammurabi-king-babylon Law Code of Hammurabi, king of Babylon | Musée du Louvre]
* [http://fancyfrindle.com/the-code-of-hammurabi-a-king-with-rules/ The Code of Hammurabi: A King with Rules]
* [[wikisource:The Code of Hammurabi (Harper translation)|The Code of Hammurabi (Harper translation)]] at [[Wikisource]]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20100901185237/http://cliojournal.wikispaces.com/Hammurabi's+Code Hammurabi's Code], Blaise Joseph, ''Clio History Journal'', 2009.
{{Louvre Museum}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Code Of Hammurabi}}
[[Category:18th-century BC works]]
[[Category:2nd-millennium BC steles]]
[[Category:1901 archaeological discoveries]]
[[Category:Legal codes]]
[[Category:Ancient Near East law]]
[[Category:Babylonia]]
[[Category:Codes of conduct]]
[[Category:Near East and Middle East antiquities of the Louvre]]
[[Category:Bronze Age literature]]
[[Category:Ancient Near East steles]]
[[Category:Akkadian inscriptions]]
[[Category:Slavery law]]
[[Category:Archaeological discoveries in Iran]]
[[Category:1901 in Iran]]</text>
      <sha1>07a983pauaee6dzd57sx3a3id634jk3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
