  <page>
    <title>Collagen helix</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7607</id>
    <revision>
      <id>929456331</id>
      <parentid>929453835</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-05T23:22:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ananya.ray11</username>
        <id>37630244</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox protein family
| Symbol = Collagen
| Name = Collagen triple helix
| image = 1K6F Crystal Structure Of The Collagen Triple Helix Model Pro- Pro-Gly103 04.png
| width =
| caption = Model of a collagen helix.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid11790836&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Berisio R, Vitagliano L, Mazzarella L, Zagari A |title=Crystal structure of the collagen triple helix model [(Pro-Pro-Gly)(10)](3) |journal=Protein Sci. |volume=11 |issue=2 |pages=262–70 |date=February 2002 |pmid=11790836 |pmc=2373432 |doi=10.1110/ps.32602 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| Pfam = PF01391
| InterPro = IPR008160
| SMART =
| PROSITE =
| SCOP = 1a9a
| TCDB = 
| OPM family = 
| OPM protein = 
| PDB = {{PDB2|1q7d}}, {{PDB2|1rj7}}, {{PDB2|1rj8}} 
}}

[[Image:Fibers of Collagen Type I - TEM.jpg|thumb|[[Transmission electron microscopy|TEM]] image of collagen fibres.]]
In [[collagen]], the '''collagen helix''', or '''type-2 helix''', is a major shape in [[secondary structure]]. It consists of a [[triple helix]] made of the repetitious [[amino acid]] sequence [[glycine]] - X - Y, where X and Y are frequently [[proline]] or [[hydroxyproline]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Bhattacharjee A, Bansal M |title=Collagen structure: the Madras triple helix and the current scenario |journal=IUBMB Life |volume=57 |issue=3 |pages=161–72 |date=March 2005 |pmid=16036578 |doi=10.1080/15216540500090710}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Saad 1994&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Saad|first1=Mohamed|title=Low resolution structure and packing investigations of collagen crystalline domains in tendon using Synchrotron Radiation X-rays, Structure factors determination, evaluation of Isomorphous Replacement methods and other modeling.|date=Oct 1994|publisher=PhD Thesis, Université Joseph Fourier Grenoble I|pages=1–221|url=https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B3L_EN9hIuFTTkhuN2lrWEU4RDQ&amp;authuser=0 |doi= 10.13140/2.1.4776.7844}}&lt;/ref&gt; Glycine, proline, and hydroxyproline must be in their designated positions with the correct configuration. For example, hydroxyproline in the Y position increases the thermal stability of the triple helix, but not when it is located in the X position.&lt;ref&gt;Berisio R, Vitagliano L, Mazzarella L, Zagari A (February 2002). &quot;Crystal structure of the collagen triple helix model [(Pro-Pro-Gly)(10)](3)&quot;. Protein Sci. 11 (2): 262–70. doi:10.1110/ps.32602. PMC 2373432. {{PMID|11790836}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The thermal stabilization is also hindered when the hydroxyl group has the wrong configuration. Due to the high abundance of glycine and proline contents, collagen fails to form a regular α-helix and β-sheet structure. Three left-handed helical strands twist to form a right-handed triple helix.&lt;ref&gt;Bella, Jordi. “Collagen Structure: New Tricks from a Very Old Dog.” The Biochemical Journal, vol. 473, no. 8, 2016, pp. 1001–1025.&lt;/ref&gt;A collagen triple helix has 3.3 residues per turn.&lt;ref&gt;Harpers Illustrated Biochemistry, 30th edition&lt;/ref&gt;
Each of the three chains is stabilized by the [[steric repulsion]] due to the [[pyrrolidine]] rings of [[proline]] and [[hydroxyproline]] [[residue (biochemistry)|residue]]s. The pyrrolidine rings keep out of each other’s way when the [[polypeptide]] chain assumes this extended [[Helix|helical]] form, which is much more open than the tightly coiled form of the [[alpha helix]].
The three chains are [[hydrogen bond]]ed to each other. The [[Hydrogen bonding#Bonding|hydrogen bond donors]] are the [[peptide]] NH groups of [[glycine]] residues. The [[Hydrogen bonding#Bonding|hydrogen bond acceptors]] are the CO groups of residues on the other chains. The OH group of [[hydroxyproline]] does not participate in hydrogen bonding but stabilises the trans isomer of proline by stereoelectronic effects, therefore stabilizing the entire triple helix. The rise of the collagen helix ([[superhelix]]) is 2.9 Å (0.29&amp;nbsp;nm) per residue. The center of the collagen triple helix is very small and hydrophobic, and every third residue of the helix must have contact with the center.&lt;ref&gt;Brodsky, Barbara, et al. “Triple‐Helical Peptides: An Approach to Collagen Conformation, Stability, and Self‐Association.” Biopolymers, vol. 89, no. 5, 2008, pp. 345–353.&lt;/ref&gt; Due to the very tiny and tight space at the center, only the small hydrogen of the glycine side chain is capable of interacting with the center.&lt;ref&gt;Brodsky, Barbara, et al. “Triple‐Helical Peptides: An Approach to Collagen Conformation, Stability, and Self‐Association.” Biopolymers, vol. 89, no. 5, 2008, pp. 345–353.&lt;/ref&gt; This contact is impossible even when a slightly bigger amino acid residue is present other than glycine.

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Protein tandem repeats}}

{{Protein secondary structure}}
{{Spirals}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Collagen Helix}}
[[Category:Protein structural motifs]]
[[Category:Helices]]
[[Category:Protein families]]

{{protein-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>qqekjyeojumcsdof69c05hg18wmdkvx</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
