  <page>
    <title>Chuck Jones</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7672</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940013241</id>
      <parentid>939990617</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-10T01:32:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Nikkimaria</username>
        <id>372290</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>doc</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{For|other people with the name Charles Jones|Charles Jones (disambiguation){{!}}Charles Jones}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=April 2018}}
{{Infobox person
| name          = Chuck Jones
| image         = Chuck Jones1.jpg
| caption       = Jones in 1978.
| birth_name    = Charles Martin Jones
| birth_date    = {{birth date|mf=yes|1912|9|21}}
| birth_place   = [[Spokane, Washington]], U.S.
| death_date    = {{death date and age|mf=yes|2002|2|22|1912|9|21}}
| death_place   = [[Newport Beach, California]], U.S.
| children      = 1
| other_names   = Charles M. Jones &lt;br&gt;The Father of Contemporary Animation&lt;br&gt;M. Charl Jones
| alma_mater    = [[Chouinard Art Institute]]
| occupation    = Animated filmmaker and cartoonist
| years_active  = 1931–2002&lt;ref&gt;http://www.achievement.org/achiever/chuck-jones/&lt;/ref&gt;
| employer      = [[Warner Bros. Cartoons]] (1933-1962)&lt;br /&gt;[[Walt Disney Animation Studios]] (1953)&lt;br /&gt;[[Sib Tower 12 Productions]] (1962-1970)
| spouse        = {{marriage|Dorothy Webster|1935|1978|end=her death}}&lt;br&gt;{{marriage|Marian Dern|1981|2002|end=his death}}
| website       = https://www.ChuckJones.com
}}

'''Charles Martin Jones''' (September 21, 1912&amp;nbsp;– February 22, 2002) was an American animated filmmaker and cartoonist, best known for his work with [[Warner Bros. Cartoons]] on the ''[[Looney Tunes]]'' and ''[[Merrie Melodies]]'' shorts. He wrote, produced, and/or directed many classic [[animated cartoon]] shorts starring [[Bugs Bunny]], [[Daffy Duck]], [[Wile E. Coyote and the Road Runner]], [[Pepé Le Pew]], [[Porky Pig]], [[Michigan J. Frog]], the [[The Three Bears (Looney Tunes)|Three Bears]], and a slew of other Warner characters.

After his career at Warner Bros. ended in 1962, Jones started [[MGM Animation/Visual Arts|Sib Tower 12 Productions]], and began producing cartoons for [[Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer]], including a new series of [[Tom and Jerry: The Chuck Jones Collection|''Tom and Jerry'' shorts]] and the television adaptation of [[Dr. Seuss]]' ''[[How the Grinch Stole Christmas (TV Special)|How the Grinch Stole Christmas!]]''. He later started his own studio, Chuck Jones Enterprises, which created several one-shot specials, and periodically worked on ''Looney Tunes'' related works.

Jones was nominated for eight [[Academy Awards]], winning three times. He won for the cartoons ''[[For Scent-imental Reasons]]'', ''[[So Much for So Little]]'', and ''[[The Dot and the Line]]''. [[Robin Williams]] presented Jones with an [[Honorary Academy Award]] in 1996 for his iconic work in the animation industry. Film historian [[Leonard Maltin]] has praised Jones' work at Warner Bros., MGM and Chuck Jones Enterprises. He also said that the &quot;feud&quot; that there may have been between Jones and colleague [[Bob Clampett]] was mainly because they were so different from each other. In [[Jerry Beck]]'s ''[[The 50 Greatest Cartoons]]'', ten of the entries were directed by Jones, with four out of the five top cartoons (including first place) being Jones shorts.

==Early life==
Jones was born on September 21, 1912, in [[Spokane, Washington]], the son of Mabel McQuiddy (Martin) and Charles Adams Jones.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=bZIv8NKfNKwC&amp;pg=PA22&amp;lpg=PA22&amp;dq=%22Mabel+McQuiddy+Martin%22|title=Chuck Jones: A Flurry of Drawings|author1=Hugh Kenner|author2=Chuck Jones|page=22|accessdate=2017-05-04|isbn=9780520087972|date=1994-01-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; He later moved with his parents and three siblings to the Los Angeles, California area.&lt;ref name=obit/&gt;

In his autobiography, ''Chuck Amuck'', Jones credits his artistic bent to circumstances surrounding his father, who was an unsuccessful businessman in California in the 1920s. His father, Jones recounts, would start every new business venture by purchasing new stationery and new pencils with the company name on them. When the business failed, his father would quietly turn the huge stacks of useless stationery and pencils over to his children, requiring them to use up all the material as fast as possible. Armed with an endless supply of high-quality paper and pencils, the children drew constantly. Later, in one art school class, the professor gravely informed the students that they each had 100,000 bad drawings in them that they must first get past before they could possibly draw anything worthwhile. Jones recounted years later that this pronouncement came as a great relief to him, as he was well past the 200,000 mark, having used up all that stationery. Jones and several of his siblings went on to artistic careers.&lt;ref&gt;Jones, Chuck (1989). ''Chuck Amuck : The Life and Times of an Animated Cartoonist'', New York: Farrar Straus &amp; Giroux; {{ISBN|0-374-12348-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jones, Chuck (1996). ''Chuck Reducks: Drawing from the Fun Side of Life''. New York: Warner Books; {{ISBN|0-446-51893-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During his artistic education, he worked part-time as a janitor. After graduating from [[Chouinard Art Institute]], Jones got a phone call from a friend named Fred Kopietz, who had been hired by the [[Ub Iwerks]] studio and offered him a job. He worked his way up in the animation industry, starting as a cel washer; &quot;then I moved up to become a painter in black and white, some color. Then I went on to take animator's drawings and traced them onto the celluloid. Then I became what they call an in-betweener, which is the guy that does the drawing between the drawings the animator makes&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.achievement.org/autodoc/page/jon1int-3|title=Archived copy|accessdate=2014-07-21|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140727215042/http://www.achievement.org/autodoc/page/jon1int-3 |archivedate=July 27, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; While at Iwerks, he met a cel painter named Dorothy Webster, who later became his first wife.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Williams|first=Jasmin|date=May 7, 2009|title=Chuck Jones – Master Animator|url=|journal=New York Post|volume=|page=34|via=Business Insights: Global}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Warner Bros.==
{{See also|Chuck Jones filmography}}
Jones joined [[Leon Schlesinger|Leon Schlesinger Productions]], the independent studio that produced ''[[Looney Tunes]]'' and ''[[Merrie Melodies]]'' for [[Warner Bros.]], in 1933 as an assistant animator. In 1935, he was promoted to animator and assigned to work with a new Schlesinger director [[Tex Avery]]. There was no room for the new Avery unit in Schlesinger's small studio, so Avery, Jones, and fellow animators [[Bob Clampett]], [[Virgil Ross]], and [[Sidney Sutherland|Sid Sutherland]] were moved into a small adjacent building they dubbed &quot;Termite Terrace&quot;. When Clampett was promoted to director in 1937, Jones was assigned to his unit; the Clampett unit was briefly assigned to work with Jones' old employer, [[Ub Iwerks]] when Iwerks subcontracted four cartoons to Schlesinger in 1937. Jones became a director (or &quot;supervisor&quot;, the original title for an animation director in the studio) himself in 1938 when [[Frank Tashlin]] left the studio. The following year Jones created his first major character, [[Sniffles]], a cute Disney-style mouse, who went on to star in twelve Warner Bros. cartoons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://chuckjonescenter.org/characters/sniffles|title=Sniffles|website=Chuck Jones Center|accessdate=December 16, 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171216201311/http://chuckjonescenter.org/characters/sniffles|archive-date=December 16, 2017|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He was actively involved in efforts to unionize the staff of [[Warner Bros. Cartoons|Leon Schlesinger Studios]]. He was responsible for recruiting animators, layout men, and background people. Almost all animators joined, in reaction to salary cuts imposed by [[Leon Schlesinger]]. The [[Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer cartoon studio]] had already signed a union contract, encouraging their counterparts under Schlesinger.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sigall&quot;&gt;Sigall (2005), pp. 59–61&lt;/ref&gt; In a meeting with his staff, Schlesinger talked for a few minutes, then turned over the meeting to his attorney. His insulting manner had a unifying effect on the staff. Jones gave a pep talk at the union headquarters. As negotiations broke down, the staff decided to go on strike. Schlesinger locked them out of the studio for a few days, before agreeing to sign the contract.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sigall&quot;/&gt; A Labor-Management Committee was formed and Jones served as a moderator. Because of his role as a supervisor in the studio, he could not himself join the union.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sigall&quot;/&gt; Jones created many of his lesser-known characters during this period, including [[Charlie Dog]], [[Hubie and Bertie]], and [[The Three Bears (Looney Tunes)|The Three Bears]].{{citation needed|date=June 2015}}

[[File:The Outpost.ogv|thumb|left|thumbtime=1:59|'Outpost', a Private Snafu cartoon directed by Chuck Jones in 1944]]
During [[World War II]], Jones worked closely with Theodor Geisel, better known as [[Dr. Seuss]], to create the ''[[Private Snafu]]'' series of Army educational cartoons (the character was created by director [[Frank Capra]]). Jones later collaborated with Seuss on animated adaptations of Seuss' books, including ''[[How the Grinch Stole Christmas!]]'' in 1966. Jones directed such shorts as ''[[The Weakly Reporter]]'', a 1944 short that related to shortages and rationing on the home front. During the same year, he directed ''[[Hell-Bent for Election]]'', a campaign film for [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]].&lt;ref name=&quot;imdb&quot;&gt;{{IMDb name|0005062|Chuck Jones}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Jones created characters through the late 1940s and the 1950s, which include [[Claude Cat]], [[Marc Antony and Pussyfoot]], [[List of Looney Tunes and Merrie Melodies characters#Charlie Dog|Charlie Dog]], [[Michigan J. Frog]], [[Gossamer (Looney Tunes)|Gossamer]], and his four most popular creations, [[Marvin the Martian]], [[Pepé Le Pew]], [[Wile E. Coyote and the Road Runner]]. Jones and writer [[Michael Maltese]] collaborated on the Road Runner cartoons, ''[[Duck Amuck]]'', ''[[One Froggy Evening]]'', and ''[[What's Opera, Doc?]]''. Other staff at Unit A that Jones collaborated with include layout artist, background designer, co-director [[Maurice Noble]]; animator and co-director [[Abe Levitow]]; and animators [[Ken Harris]] and [[Ben Washam]].

Jones remained at Warner Bros. throughout the 1950s, except for a brief period in 1953 when Warner closed the animation studio. During this interim, Jones found employment at [[Walt Disney Animation Studios|Walt Disney Productions]], where he teamed with [[Ward Kimball]] for a four-month period of uncredited work on ''[[Sleeping Beauty (1959 film)|Sleeping Beauty]]'' (1959). Upon the reopening of the Warner animation department, Jones was rehired and reunited with most of his unit.{{citation needed|date=June 2015}}

In the early 1960s, Jones and his wife Dorothy wrote the screenplay for the animated feature ''[[Gay Purr-ee]]''. The finished film would feature the voices of [[Judy Garland]], [[Robert Goulet]] and [[Red Buttons]] as cats in Paris, France. The feature was produced by [[United Productions of America|UPA]] and directed by his former Warner Bros. collaborator, Abe Levitow.

Jones moonlighted to work on the film since he had an exclusive contract with Warner Bros. UPA completed the film and made it available for distribution in 1962; it was picked up by Warner Bros. When Warner Bros. discovered that Jones had violated his exclusive contract with them, they terminated him.&lt;ref name=&quot;endofstudio&quot;&gt;Barrier, Michael (1999). ''Hollywood Cartoons''. New York: Oxford University Press. pp. 562–563; {{ISBN|0-19-516729-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jones' former animation unit was laid off after completing the final cartoon in their pipeline, ''[[The Iceman Ducketh]]'', and the rest of the Warner Bros. Cartoons studio was closed in early 1963.&lt;ref name=&quot;endofstudio&quot;/&gt;

==Post-Warner Bros.==
With business partner Les Goldman, Jones started an independent animation studio, Sib Tower 12 Productions, and brought on most of his unit from Warner Bros., including Maurice Noble and Michael Maltese. In 1963, Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer contracted with Sib Tower 12 to have Jones and his staff produce new ''[[Tom and Jerry]]'' cartoons as well as a television adaptation of all ''Tom and Jerry'' theatricals produced to that date. This included major editing, including writing out the African-American maid, Mammy Two-Shoes, and replacing her with one of Irish descent voiced by [[June Foray]]. In 1964, Sib Tower 12 was absorbed by MGM and was renamed [[MGM Animation/Visual Arts]]. His animated short film, ''[[The Dot and the Line|The Dot and the Line: A Romance in Lower Mathematics]]'', won the 1965 [[Academy Award for Best Animated Short Film]]. Jones directed the classic animated short ''[[The Bear That Wasn't]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;imdb&quot;/&gt;

As the ''Tom and Jerry'' series wound down (it was discontinued in 1967), Jones produced more for television. In 1966, he produced and directed the TV special ''[[How the Grinch Stole Christmas! (TV special)|How the Grinch Stole Christmas]]!'', featuring the voice and facial models based on the readings by [[Boris Karloff]].&lt;ref name=bcdb&gt;{{bcdb|15585|How The Grinch Stole Christmas!}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Jones continued to work on other TV specials such as ''[[Horton Hears a Who! (TV special)|Horton Hears a Who!]]'' (1970), but his main focus during this time was producing the feature film ''[[The Phantom Tollbooth (film)|The Phantom Tollbooth]]'', which did lukewarm business when [[Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer|MGM]] released it in 1970. Jones co-directed 1969's ''The Pogo Special Birthday Special'', based on the [[Walt Kelly]] comic strip, and voiced the characters of Porky Pine and Bun Rab. It was at this point that he decided to start ST Incorporated.&lt;ref name=&quot;imdb&quot;/&gt;

MGM closed the animation division in 1970, and Jones once again started his own studio, Chuck Jones Enterprises. He produced a Saturday morning children's TV series for the [[American Broadcasting Company]] called ''[[Curiosity Shop|The Curiosity Shop]]'' in 1971. In 1973, he produced an animated version of the [[George Selden (author)|George Selden]] book ''[[The Cricket in Times Square]]'' and would go on to produce two sequels.&lt;ref name=&quot;imdb&quot;/&gt;

Three of his works during this period were animated TV adaptations of short stories from [[Rudyard Kipling]]'s ''[[Mowgli's Brothers (TV special)|Mowgli's Brothers]]'', ''[[The White Seal]]'' and ''[[Rikki-Tikki-Tavi]]''. During this period, Jones began to experiment with more realistically designed characters, most of which having larger eyes, leaner bodies, and altered proportions, such as those of the Looney Tunes characters.{{citation needed|date=June 2015}}

Jones resumed working with Warner Bros. in 1976 with the animated TV adaptation of ''[[Bugs and Daffy's Carnival of the Animals|The Carnival of the Animals]]'' with Bugs Bunny and Daffy Duck. Jones also produced ''[[The Bugs Bunny/Road Runner Movie]]'' (1979) which was a compilation of Jones' best theatrical shorts; Jones produced new Road Runner shorts for ''[[The Electric Company]]'' series and ''Bugs Bunny's Looney Christmas Tales'' (1979). New shorts were made for ''Bugs Bunny's Bustin' Out All Over'' (1980).&lt;ref name=&quot;imdb&quot;/&gt;

From 1977 to 1978, Jones wrote and drew the newspaper comic strip ''Crawford'' (also known as ''Crawford &amp; Morgan'') for the [[Tribune Media Services|Chicago Tribune-NY News Syndicate]]. In 2011 [[IDW Publishing]] collected Jones' strip as part of their Library of American Comic Strips.&lt;ref name=&quot;lambiek.net&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.lambiek.net/artists/j/jones_chuck.htm |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2016-08-08 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160821162408/https://www.lambiek.net/artists/j/jones_chuck.htm |archivedate=August 21, 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1978, Jones' wife Dorothy died; three years later, he married Marian Dern, the writer of the comic strip ''[[Rick O'Shay]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;lambiek.net&quot;/&gt;

===Jones–Avery letter===
On December 11, 1975,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lettersofnote.com/2009/10/unadulterated-hogwash.html |title=Unadulterated Hogwash |publisher=Letters of Note |date=October 21, 2009 |accessdate=2017-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; shortly after the release of ''[[Bugs Bunny Superstar]]'', which prominently featured [[Bob Clampett]], Jones wrote a letter to [[Tex Avery]], accusing Clampett of taking credit for ideas that were not his, and for characters created by other directors (notably Jones' Sniffles and [[Friz Freleng]]'s Yosemite Sam). Their correspondence was never published in the media. It was forwarded to [[Michael Barrier (historian)|Michael Barrier]], who conducted the interview with Clampett and was distributed by Jones to multiple people concerned with animation over the years. [[Robert McKimson]] claimed in an interview that many animators but mostly Clampett contributed to the crazy personality of Bugs, while others like Chuck Jones concentrated more on the more calmed-down gags. As far as plagiarism is concerned, McKimson claimed the animators would always be looking at each other's sheets to see if they could borrow some punchlines and cracks.&lt;ref&gt;[http://michaelbarrier.com/Essays/JonesAveryLetter/JonesAveryLetter.html Robert McKimson account], Michaelbarrier.com; accessed June 18, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Later years==
Through the 1980s and 1990s, Jones was painting cartoon and parody art, sold through animation galleries by his daughter's company, Linda Jones Enterprises.&lt;ref name=obit&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2002/feb/23/local/me-jones23|title=Chuck Jones, 89; Animation Pioneer|last=Martin|first=Hugo|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=February 23, 2002|accessdate=2014-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jones was the creative consultant and character designer for two [[Raggedy Ann]] animated specials and the first ''[[Alvin and the Chipmunks]]'' Christmas special ''[[A Chipmunk Christmas]]''. He made a cameo appearance in the film ''[[Gremlins]]'' (1984)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ign.com/articles/2012/05/21/gremlins-blu-ray-review|title=Gremlins Blu-ray Review|last=Shaffer|first=R. L.|work=[[IGN]]|date=May 21, 2012|accessdate=2014-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; and directed the Bugs Bunny/Daffy Duck animated sequences that bookend its sequel ''[[Gremlins 2: The New Batch]]'' (1990).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/style/longterm/movies/videos/gremlins2thenewbatchpg13hinson_a0a978.htm|title=Gremlins 2: The New Batch|last=Hinson|first=Hal|work=[[The Washington Post]]|date=June 15, 1990|accessdate=2014-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jones directed animated sequences for various features such as a lengthy sequence in the film ''[[Stay Tuned (film)|Stay Tuned]]'' (1992)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.courant.com/1992-08-15/features/0000113682_1_looney-tunes-john-ritter-chuck-jones|title=No Need To 'Stay Tuned' To This One|last=Johnson|first=Malcolm|work=[[Hartford Courant]]|date=August 15, 1992|accessdate=2014-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a shorter one seen at the start of the [[Robin Williams]] vehicle ''[[Mrs. Doubtfire]]'' (1993).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/02/28/AR2008022801310.html|title=Go Behind The Seams of 'Mrs. Doubtfire'|last=Fields|first=Curt|work=[[The Washington Post]]|date=February 29, 2008|accessdate=2014-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also during the 1980s and 1990s, Jones served on the advisory board of the [[National Student Film Institute]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Editor|title=National Student Film Institute/L.A: The Sixteenth Annual Los Angeles Student Film Festival|date=June 10, 1994|location=The Directors Guild Theatre|pages=10–11|ref=Program}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Editor|title=Los Angeles Student Film Institute: 13th Annual Student Film Festival|date=June 7, 1991|location=The Directors Guild Theatre|page=3|ref=Program}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Jones' final Looney Tunes cartoon was ''[[From Hare to Eternity]]'' (1997), which starred Bugs Bunny and [[Yosemite Sam]], with [[Greg Burson]] voicing Bugs. The cartoon was dedicated to [[Friz Freleng]], who had died in 1995. Jones' final animation project was a series of 13 shorts starring a timber wolf character he had designed in the 1960s named Thomas Timber Wolf. The series was released online by Warner Bros. in 2000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2000/aug/17/entertainment/ca-5778|title=Chuck Jones's Latest Creation Will Prowl the Web|last=Botwin|first=Michele|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=August 17, 2000|accessdate=2014-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; From 2001 until 2004, [[Cartoon Network]] aired ''The Chuck Jones Show'' which features shorts directed by him. The show won the [[Annie Award]] for Outstanding Achievement in an Animated Special Project.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://annieawards.org/29th-annie-awards|title=29th Annual Annie Award Nominees and Winners(2001)|work=[[Annie Award]]|accessdate=2014-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1997, Jones was awarded the [[Edward MacDowell Medal]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=MacDowell Medal winners 1960-2011 |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/theatre/theatre-news/8447621/MacDowell-Medal-winners-1960-2011.html |website=[[The Daily Telegraph|The Telegraph]] |date=13 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1999, he founded the non-profit Chuck Jones Center for Creativity, in Costa Mesa, California, an art education &quot;gymnasium for the brain&quot; dedicated to teaching creative skills, primarily to children and seniors, which is still in operation.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.chuckjonescenter.org/&lt;/ref&gt;

===Death===
Jones died of [[heart failure]] on February 22, 2002, at the age of 89. He was cremated and his ashes were scattered at sea.&lt;ref name=obit/&gt; After his death, the Looney Tunes cartoon ''Daffy Duck for President'', based on [[Daffy Duck for President|the book]] that Jones had written and using Jones' style for the characters, originally scheduled to be released in 2000,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Bugs on Video – The 1960s|url=http://www.dohtem.com/bugs/1960s.htm#president|work=The Bugs Bunny Video Guide|accessdate=April 27, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; was released in 2004 as part of disc three of the ''[[Looney Tunes Golden Collection: Volume 2]]'' DVD set.

==Accolades==
Jones was a historical authority as well as a major contributor to the development of animation throughout the 20th century. In 1990, Jones received the Golden Plate Award of the [[American Academy of Achievement]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title= Golden Plate Awardees of the American Academy of Achievement |website=www.achievement.org|publisher=[[American Academy of Achievement]]|url=https://www.achievement.org/our-history/golden-plate-awards/}}&lt;/ref&gt; He received an honorary degree from [[Oglethorpe University]] in 1993.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oglethorpe.edu/about_us/history/honorary_degrees.asp |title=Honorary Degrees Awarded by Oglethorpe University |work=[[Oglethorpe University]] |accessdate=2014-04-22 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150319104000/http://www.oglethorpe.edu/about_us/history/honorary_degrees.asp |archivedate=March 19, 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt; For his contribution to the motion picture industry, Jones has a star on the [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]] at 7011 Hollywood Blvd.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://projects.latimes.com/hollywood/star-walk/chuck-jones/|title=Chuck Jones|last=Martin|first=Hugo|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=February 23, 2002|accessdate=2014-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:So Much for So Little.webm|thumb|''[[So Much for So Little]]'' from 1949 won Jones an Academy Award]]
Jones, whose work had been nominated eight times over his career for an [[Academy Awards|Oscar]] (winning the award three times: ''[[For Scent-imental Reasons]]'', ''[[So Much for So Little]]'', and ''[[The Dot and the Line]]''), received an [[Honorary Academy Award]] in 1996 by the board of governors of the [[Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences]], for &quot;the creation of classic cartoons and cartoon characters whose animated lives have brought joy to our real ones for more than half a century.&quot;  At that year's awards show, [[Robin Williams]], a self-confessed &quot;Jones-aholic,&quot; presented the honorary award to Jones, calling him &quot;The [[Orson Welles]] of cartoons.&quot;, and the audience gave Jones a [[standing ovation]] as he walked onto the stage. For himself, a flattered Jones wryly remarked in his acceptance speech, &quot;Well, what can I say in the face of such humiliating evidence? I stand guilty before the world of directing over three hundred cartoons in the last fifty or sixty years. Hopefully, this means you've forgiven me.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Jones|first=Chuck|title=Honorary Award: Acceptance Speech|url=http://aaspeechesdb.oscars.org/link/068-26|publisher=Academy of Motion Pictures, Arts and Sciences|accessdate=February 21, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; He received the Lifetime Achievement Award at the World Festival of Animated Film – [[Animafest Zagreb]] in 1988.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://animafest.hr/en/1988/home |title=Animafest Zagreb |website=Animafest.hr |date=June 3, 1988 |accessdate=2017-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Jones' life and legacy were celebrated on January 12, 2012, with the official grand opening of ''The Chuck Jones Experience'' at [[Circus Circus Las Vegas]]. Many of Jones' family welcomed celebrities, animation aficionados and visitors to the new attraction when they opened the attraction in an appropriate and unconventional way. Among those in attendance were Jones' widow, Marian Jones; daughter Linda Clough; and grandchildren Craig, Todd and Valerie Kausen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://blog.bcdb.com/the-chuck-jones-experience-opens-las-vegas-3631-2671|title=&quot;The Chuck Jones Experience&quot; opens in Las Vegas|first=Paul|last=Anderson|newspaper=Big Cartoon News|date=January 13, 2011|accessdate=June 18, 2015}}{{dead link|date=October 2019|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Publications==
* {{cite book| author1 = Chuck Jones | author2= Steven Spielberg |title= Chuck Amuck: The Life and Times of an Animated Cartoonist | date = February 19, 1990 | publisher = Simon &amp; Schuster Ltd | isbn= 978-0671710248}}
* Jones, Chuck (1996). ''Chuck Reducks: Drawing from the Fun Side of Life''. New York: Warner Books. {{ISBN|0-446-51893-X}}.
* {{cite book| author = Chuck Jones | title= Daffy Duck for President | date = July 1997 | publisher = Warner Bros. | isbn= 978-1890371005}}
* {{cite book | author1 = Stefan Kanfer | author2 = Chuck Jones | title = Serious Business: The Art and Commerce of Animation in America from Betty Boop to Toy Story | date = May 1, 2000 | publisher = Da Capo | isbn = 978-0306809187 | url-access = registration | url = https://archive.org/details/seriousbusinessa00kanf }}
* {{cite book| author = Chuck Jones | title= Chuck Jones: The Dream that Never Was | date = December 27, 2011 | publisher = [[IDW Publishing]] &amp; [[The Library of American Comics]] | isbn= 978-1613770306}}

==See also==
* [[Warner Bros. Cartoons]]
* [[Warner Bros. Animation]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Sources==
* {{Cite book|last=Sigall|first=Martha|title=Living Life Inside the Lines: Tales from the Golden Age of Animation|chapter=The Boys of Termite Terrace| year=2005|publisher=[[University Press of Mississippi]]|isbn=9781578067497|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/?id=diKnDBs0wrIC&amp;pg=PA49 }}
* Barrier, Michael (1999). ''Hollywood Cartoons: American Animation in Its Golden Age''. Oxford: Oxford University Press; {{ISBN|0-19-516729-5}}.
* {{Cite book|last=Sigall|first=Martha|title=Living Life Inside the Lines: Tales from the Golden Age of Animation|chapter=The Boys of Termite Terrace|year=2005|publisher=[[University Press of Mississippi]]|isbn=9781578067497|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/?id=diKnDBs0wrIC&amp;pg=PA49 }}

==Further reading==
* [http://ark.cdlib.org/ark:/13030/ft6q2nb3x1/ Kenner, Hugh. Chuck Jones: A Flurry of Drawings, Portraits of American Genius. Berkeley:  University of California Press,  c1994 1994.  Free Online – UC Press E-Books Collection]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20151025070857/http://www.animationartconservation.com/chuck-jones%2C-in-his-own-words-page-one.html &quot;Chuck Jones, in his own words&quot; The final print interview with Chuck Jones by Ron Barbagallo, ''Animation Art Conservation'' (1996, 1999 / revised 2015)]
* [http://www.cartoonbrew.com/classic/chuck-jones-article-by-john-canemaker.html &quot;Chuck Jones&quot; by John Canemaker] from ''Cartoonist PROfiles'' #45 (March 1980)
* [http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060115/REVIEWS08/601150301 Chuck Jones: Three Cartoons (1953–1957)] – [[Roger Ebert]] discusses Jones' three films in the United States [[Library of Congress]] National Film Registry.
* [http://www.adcglobal.org/archive/hof/1998/?id=316 Art Directors Club biography, portrait and images of work]
* [http://www.michaelbarrier.com/Funnyworld/Clampett/interview_bob_clampett.htm Bob Clampetts interview for Funnyworld]
* [http://www.lettersofnote.com/2009/10/unadulterated-hogwash.html The Jones-Avery Letter]

==External links==
* {{IMDb name|id=nm0005062}}
* {{commons category inline}}
{{wikiquote}}
* {{Official website|http://www.chuckjones.com/}}
* [https://www.chuckjonescenter.org/ Chuck Jones Center for Creativity]
* {{bcdb |Other_Studios/J/Chuck_Jones_Film_Productions/|Chuck Jones Film Productions}}
* {{bcdb |www.bcdb.com/cartoons/Other_Studios/J/Chuck_Jones_Enterprises/|Chuck Jones Enterprises}}
* {{emmytvlegends name|chuck-jones}}
* {{cite web|title= Chuck Jones Biography and Interview |website=www.achievement.org|publisher=[[American Academy of Achievement]]|url=https://www.achievement.org/achiever/chuck-jones/#interview}}

{{Chuck Jones}}
{{Looney Tunes &amp; Merrie Melodies}}
{{The Chuck Jones Tom and Jerry shorts}}
{{Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer Cartoons}}
{{Academy Honorary Award}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Jones, Chuck}}
[[Category:1912 births]]
[[Category:2002 deaths]]
[[Category:Animators from Washington (state)]]
[[Category:American animated film directors]]
[[Category:American animated film producers]]
[[Category:American comics artists]]
[[Category:Animation screenwriters]]
[[Category:Artists from Los Angeles]]
[[Category:Artists from Spokane, Washington]]
[[Category:Directors of Best Animated Short Academy Award winners]]
[[Category:Film directors from Washington (state)]]
[[Category:Chouinard Art Institute alumni]]
[[Category:Academy Honorary Award recipients]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Warner Bros. Cartoons people]]
[[Category:Walt Disney Animation Studios people]]
[[Category:Film directors from Los Angeles]]</text>
      <sha1>qm2qsimtvr432j6xdbosejpl5sm7nmh</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
