  <page>
    <title>The Family International</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7602</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943366540</id>
      <parentid>943366412</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T13:53:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>108.34.144.82</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* The Children of God (1968–1977) */Fixed typo</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{For|[[Ohioan]] [[parachurch organization]]|Teens for Christ}}
{{Distinguish |Family|The Fellowship (Christian organization)|The Family (Australian New Age group)}}
{{use MDY dates|date=June 2019}}
{{Multiple issues|
{{Unreliable sources|date=July 2016}}
{{POV|date=July 2016}}}}
{{Infobox Christian denomination
| abbreviation = TFI
| predecessor  = The Family
| successor    =
| formation    = &lt;!-- {{Start date and age|YYYY|MM|DD}} --&gt;
| other_names  = Teens for Christ&lt;br /&gt;The Children of God&lt;br /&gt;The Family of Love&lt;br /&gt;The Family
| founder      = [[David Brandt Berg|David Berg]]
| type = [[Christianity |Christian]] [[new religious movement]]
| leader_title = Leader
| leader_name  = [[Karen Zerby]] (1994–)
| key_people   =
| website      = {{URL |http://thefamilyinternational.org/}}
}}
'''The Family International''' ('''TFI''') is a [[cult]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.icsahome.com/articles/the-children-of-godthe-family-raine |title=The Children of God/The Family |website=International Cultic Studies Association (ICSA) |accessdate=December 23, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= https://www.culteducation.com/group/918-children-of-god-the-family.html |title=Group Information Archives |website=Cult Education Institute |accessdate=December 23, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; which was founded in [[Huntington Beach, California]], US in 1968.  It was originally named ''Teens for Christ'' and it later gained notoriety as ''The Children of God'' (''COG''). It was later renamed and reorganized as ''The Family of Love'', which was eventually shortened to ''The Family''. It is currently named ''The Family''.

== Overview ==
TFI initially spread a message of [[salvation]], [[apocalypticism]], spiritual &quot;revolution and happiness&quot; and distrust of the outside world, which the members called ''The System''. In 1976,&lt;ref name=&quot;davidberg.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.davidberg.org/mission/flirty-fishing |title=Flirty-fishing |website=DavidBerg.org |accessdate=2014-03-02 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140809234611/http://www.davidberg.org/mission/flirty-fishing |archivedate=2014-08-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt; it began a method of [[evangelism]] called [[Flirty Fishing]] that used sex to &quot;show God's love and mercy&quot; and win converts, resulting in controversy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |first=Gustav |last=Niebuhr |title='The Family' and Final Harvest |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/national/longterm/cult/children_of_god/child1.htm |quote=Sure, Alexander concedes, plenty of people object that The Family's 'Law of Love' permits sex outside marriage and that the group once used (and still espouses the concept and beliefs about) a practice known as 'flirty fishing' – the use of free sex to win converts. |newspaper=[[The Washington Post]] |date=2 June 1993 |page=A01 |accessdate=2008-04-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt; TFI's founder and prophetic leader, [[David Berg]] (who was first called &quot;Moses David&quot; in the Texas press), gave himself the titles of &quot;King&quot;, &quot;The Last Endtime Prophet&quot;, &quot;Moses&quot;, and &quot;David&quot;.

He communicated with his followers via &quot;Mo Letters&quot;—letters of instruction and counsel on myriad spiritual and practical subjects—until his death in late 1994.&lt;ref name=moletters&gt;{{cite web |url=http://pubs.xfamily.org |title=Index |website=The xFamily.org Publications Database |date=2012-02-20 |accessdate=2016-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; After his death, his widow [[Karen Zerby]] became the leader of TFI, taking the titles of &quot;Queen&quot; and &quot;Prophetess&quot;. She married Steve Kelly (also known as Peter Amsterdam), an assistant of Berg's whom Berg had handpicked as her &quot;consort&quot;. Kelly took the title of &quot;King Peter&quot; and became the face of TFI, speaking in public more often than either David Berg or Karen Zerby. There have been multiple allegations of child sexual abuse made by past members.&lt;ref name=&quot;suicide&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cnn.com/2007/US/12/04/kaye.murdersuicide/ |website=CNN |title=Young man's suicide blamed on mother's cult |date=5 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;brazilian&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.uol/noticias/especiais/comunidade-meninos-de-deus-.htm#tematico-1 |title=Sexo, mentiras e videotape |journal=UOL notícias |language=pt-BR |accessdate=2 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==

=== The Children of God (1968–1977) ===
Members of The Children of God (COG) founded [[commune (intentional community)|communes]], first called colonies (now referred to as homes), in various cities. They would [[proselytism|proselytize]] in the streets and distribute pamphlets. Leaders within COG were referred to as ''The Chain''.

The founder of the movement, David Brandt Berg (1919–1994), was a former [[Christian and Missionary Alliance]] pastor.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.davidberg.org/mission/history |title=History – Mission |website=DavidBerg.org |access-date=2016-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Berg communicated with his followers by writing letters. He published nearly 3,000 letters over a period of 24 years, referred to as the ''Mo Letters''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.davidberg.org/mission|title=The Man – Mission |website=DavidBerg.org|access-date=2016-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a letter written in January 1972, Berg stated that he was God's prophet for the contemporary world, attempting to further solidify his spiritual authority within the group. Berg's letters also contained public acknowledgement of his own failings and weaknesses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Chancellor |first=James |year=2000 |title=Life in The Family: An Oral History of the Children of God |publisher=University of Syracuse Press |location=Syracuse, NY |pages=64–67}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Verify source|date=July 2016}}

By 1972, COG had 130 communities around the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.thefamilyinternational.org/en/about/our-history/|title=Our History |website=The Family International |access-date=2016-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Children of God was abolished in February 1978. Berg reorganized the movement amid reports of serious misconduct and financial mismanagement, The Chain's abuse of authority, and disagreements within it about the continued use of [[Flirty Fishing]]. The group was also accused of sexually abusing and raping minors within the organization, with considerable evidence to support this claim.  One-eighth of the total membership left the movement. Those who remained became part of a reorganized movement called the Family of Love, and later, The Family. The majority of the group's beliefs remained the same.&lt;ref name=Origins&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thefamily.org/dossier/statements/origins.htm |title=Origins |website=The Family International |accessdate=2016-07-24 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090429042335/http://www.thefamily.org/dossier/statements/origins.htm |archivedate=2009-04-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== The Family of Love (1978–1981) ===
The Family of Love era was characterized by international expansion.

In 1976, before the dissolution of The Children of God,&lt;ref name=&quot;davidberg.org&quot; /&gt; David Berg had introduced a new proselytizing method called [[Flirty Fishing]] (or FFing), which encouraged female members to &quot;show God's love&quot; through sexual relationships with potential converts. Flirty Fishing was practiced by members of Berg's inner circle starting in 1973, and was introduced to the general membership in 1976 and became common practice within the group. In some areas flirty fishers used escort agencies to meet potential converts. According to TFI  &quot;over 100,000 received God's gift of salvation through Jesus, and some chose to live the life of a disciple and [[missionary]]&quot; as a result of Flirty Fishing.&lt;ref name=Origins /&gt; Researcher Bill Bainbridge obtained data from TFI suggesting that, from 1974 until 1987, members had sexual contact with 223,989 people while practicing Flirty Fishing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Bainbridge |first=William Sims |year=1996 |title=The Sociology of Religious Movements |publisher=Routledge |isbn=978-0-415-91202-0 |page=223}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== The Family (1982–1994) ===
In March 1989, TF issued a statement that, in &quot;early 1985&quot;, an urgent memorandum had been sent to all members &quot;reminding them that any such activities [adult–child sexual contact] are ''strictly forbidden'' within our group&quot; (emphasis in original), and such activities were grounds for immediate [[excommunication]] from the group.&lt;ref name=&quot;Child Abuse?!&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.xfamily.org/index.php/Child_Abuse%3F%21 |title=Child Abuse?! |website=XFamily |date=2008-01-24 |accessdate=2016-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; In January 2005, Claire Borowik, a spokesperson for TFI, stated that:&lt;blockquote&gt;[d]ue to the fact that our current zero-tolerance policy regarding sexual interaction between adults and underage minors was not in our literature published before 1986, we came to the realization that during a transitional stage of our movement, from 1978 until 1986, there were cases when some minors were subject to sexually inappropriate advances&amp;nbsp;... This was corrected officially in 1986, when any contact between an adult and minor (any person under 21 years of age) was declared an excommunicable offense.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.newdaynews.com/resource/davidito/borowick-01.htm |title=Statement From Family International |first=Claire |last=Borowik |website=NewDayNews.com |accessdate=2005-06-30 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20050914142114/http://www.newdaynews.com/resource/davidito/borowick-01.htm |archivedate=2005-09-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

=== The Family (1995–2003) ===
After Berg's death in October 1994, Karen Zerby (known in the group as Mama Maria, Queen Maria, Maria David, or Maria Fontaine), assumed leadership of the group.

In February 1995, the group introduced the ''Love Charter'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://thefamily.org/dossier/charter/overview.htm |title=Charter of the Family International – Governing Documents |website=TheFamily.org |accessdate=2016-07-24 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100825230258/http://www.thefamily.org/dossier/charter/overview.htm |archivedate=2010-08-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt; which defined the rights and responsibilities of Charter Members and Homes. The Charter also included the ''Fundamental Family Rules'', a summary of rules and guidelines from past TF publications which were still in effect.

In the 1994–95 British court case, [[The Right Honorable|the Rt. Hon.]] [[Alan Ward (judge)|Lord Justice Alan Ward]] ruled that the group, including some of its top leaders, had in the past engaged in abusive sexual practices involving minors and had also used severe [[corporal punishment]] and sequestration of minors.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.exfamily.org/the-family/judgement-lord-justice-ward-intro.shtml |title=The Judgement of Lord Justice Ward, 1995 |website=Ex-Family.org |access-date=2016-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; He found that by 1995 TF had abandoned these practices and concluded that they were a safe environment for children.{{citation needed|date=July 2019}} Nevertheless, he did require that the group cease all corporal punishment of children in the United Kingdom and denounce any of Berg's writings that were &quot;responsible for children in TF having been subjected to sexually inappropriate behaviour&quot;.{{citation needed|date=July 2016}}

=== The Family International (2004–present) ===

The Love Charter is The Family's set governing document that entails each member's rights, responsibilities and requirements, while the ''Missionary Member Statutes'' and ''Fellow Member Statutes'' were written for the governance of TFI's Missionary member and Fellow Member circles, respectively. FD Homes were reviewed every six months against a published set of criteria. The Love Charter increased the number of single family homes as well as homes that relied on jobs such as self-employment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first1=Gary |last1=Shepherd  |first2=Gordon |last2=Shepherd |date=August 2005 |title=Accommodation and Reformation in the Family/Children of God |journal=[[Nova Religio]] |volume=9 |issue=1 |pages=67–92 |doi=10.1525/nr.2005.9.1.067}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Recent teachings ===
TFI's recent teachings are based on beliefs they term the &quot;new [spiritual] weapons&quot;. TFI members believe that they are soldiers in the [[spiritual warfare|spiritual war]] of [[conflict between good and evil|good versus evil]] for the souls and hearts of men.

==== Spirit Helpers ====
These include [[angel]]s, departed humans, other religious and mythical figures, and even celebrities; for example the goddess [[Aphrodite]], the Snowman, [[Merlin]], the [[Sphinx]], [[Elvis]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://pubs.xfamily.org/text.php?t=3059 |title=Pre-Release of &quot;Who Said They're Dead?&quot; Part 1 |website=The xFamily.org Publications Database |date=April 3, 2003 |accessdate=2016-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Marilyn Monroe]], [[Audrey Hepburn]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://pubs.xfamily.org/text.php?t=3060 |title=Pre-Release of &quot;Who Said They're Dead?&quot; Part 2 |website=The xFamily.org Publications Database |date=April 3, 2003 |accessdate=2016-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Richard Nixon]], and [[Winston Churchill]].

==== The Keys of the Kingdom ====
TFI believes that the Biblical passage &quot;I will give you the keys of the kingdom of heaven, and whatsoever you bind on earth will be bound in heaven, and whatsoever you loose on earth will be loosed in heaven&quot; ({{bibleref|Matthew|16:19}}), refers to an increasing amount of spiritual authority that was given to [[Saint Peter|Peter]] and the [[First disciples of Jesus|early disciples]]. According to TFI beliefs, this passage refers to keys that were hidden and unused in the centuries that followed, but were again revealed through Karen Zerby as more power to pray and obtain miracles. TFI members call on the various Keys of the Kingdom for extra effect during prayer. The Keys, like most TFI beliefs, were published in magazines that looked like comic-books in order to make them teachable to children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://archive.xfamily.org/docs/fam/mlk/mlk_190.pdf |format=PDF |title=Using The Keys Part 1 |website=archive.xfamily.org |accessdate=2016-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; These beliefs are still generally held and practiced, even after the &quot;reboot&quot; documents of 2010.

==== Loving Jesus ====
This is a term TFI members use to describe their intimate, sexual relationship with [[Jesus]]. TFI describes its &quot;Loving Jesus&quot; teaching as a radical form of [[bridal theology]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thefamily.org/dossier/statements/lj.htm |title=About The Family International |website=The Family International |accessdate=2016-07-24 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090429093717/http://www.thefamily.org/dossier/statements/lj.htm |archivedate=2009-04-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt; They believe the church of followers is Christ's bride, called to love and serve him with wifely fervor. But they take bridal theology further, encouraging members to imagine Jesus is joining them during [[sexual intercourse]] and [[masturbation]]. Male members are cautioned to visualize themselves as women, in order to avoid a homosexual relationship with Jesus. Many TFI publications, and spirit messages claimed to be from Jesus himself, elaborate this intimate, sexual relation they believe Jesus desires and needs. TFI imagines itself as his special &quot;bride&quot; in graphic poetry, guided visualizations, artwork,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.xfamily.org/index.php?title=File:Tamar_558.jpg&amp;filetimestamp=20050609225658 |title=File:Tamar 558.jpg – XFamily – Children of God |website=XFamily |date= |accessdate=2016-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; and songs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.xfamily.org/index.php/Loving_Jesus_album |title=Loving Jesus album – XFamily – Children of God |website=XFamily |date=2008-06-11 |accessdate=2016-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some TFI literature is not brought into conservative countries for fear it may be classified at customs as pornography.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.xfamily.org/index.php/Love_words_to_Jesus |title=Love words to Jesus – XFamily – Children of God |website=XFamily |date=2008-09-12 |accessdate=2016-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; The literature outlining this view of Jesus and his desire for a sexual relationship with believers was edited for younger teens,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.xfamily.org/index.php/Loving_Jesus#For_minors |title=Loving Jesus – XFamily – Children of God |website=XFamily |date=2012-03-16 |accessdate=2016-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; then further edited for children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archive.xfamily.org/docs/fam/mlk/mlk_168.pdf |title=Mlk 168 |format=PDF |date= |website=archive.xfamily.org |accessdate=2016-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Issues ==

=== The second generation ===
Second-generation adults (known as &quot;SGAs&quot;) are adults born or reared in TFI.

Anti-TFI sentiment has been publicly expressed by some who have left the group; examples include sisters Celeste Jones, Kristina Jones, and Juliana Buhring, who wrote a book&lt;ref name=&quot;nwms&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Jones |first1=K. |last2=Jones |first2=C. |last3=Buhring |first3=J. |year=2007 |title=Not Without My Sister |url=https://archive.org/details/notwithoutmysist00jone_0 |url-access=registration |publisher=Harper Collins Publishing |location=London |lastauthoramp=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; on their lives in TFI.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.notwithoutmysister.com/bios.php |title=Bios |website=notwithoutmysister.com |accessdate=2009-03-12 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100528120850/http://www.notwithoutmysister.com/bios.php |archivedate=2010-05-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Relationship with the authorities ===
{{Anchor|Secrecy}}
TFI members are expected to respect legal and civil authorities where they live. Members have typically cooperated with appointed authorities, even during the police and social-service raids of their communities in the early 1990s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Bainbridge |first=William Sims |year=2002 |title=The Endtime Family: Children of God |publisher=State University of New York Press |location=Albany, NY}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Reception ==
The group has been criticized by the press and the [[anti-cult movement]]. In 1971, an organization called [[FREECOG]] was founded by concerned parents and others, including [[deprogramming|deprogrammer]] [[Ted Patrick]], to &quot;free&quot; members of the COG from their involvement in the group. Academics were [[Anti-cult movement#Polarized views among scholars|divided]], with some categorizing TFI as a &quot;new religious movement&quot;, and others, such as [[Benjamin Beit-Hallahmi]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Beit-Hallahmi&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last=Beit-Hallahmi |first=Benjamin |title=The Illustrated Encyclopedia of Active New Religions, Sects, and Cults |publisher=Rosen Publishing Group |year=1993 |isbn=978-0-8239-1505-7 |url=https://archive.org/details/illustratedencyc00beit }}&lt;/ref&gt; and John Huxley,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://xfamily.org/index.php/Sunday_Times:_Sex-cult_children_held_-_Children_of_God |last=Huxley |first=J. |date=May 17, 1992 |title=Sex-cult children held – Children of God |newspaper=[[The Sunday Times]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; labeling the group a &quot;cult&quot;.

== Notable members (past and present) ==
* [[Jeremy Spencer]], [[blues]] [[slide guitar]]ist and a founding member of [[Fleetwood Mac]], which he left in 1971 when he joined TFI.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://media.xfamily.org/docs/press/jeremy-spencer-classic-rock-2006-03.pdf |format=PDF |title=Mac, Myths and Mysteries |first=Martin |last=Celmins |website=Media.xfamily.org |accessdate=2016-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Raised in the COG as children, but left it later in their lives ===
{{Anchor|Raised in COG as children}}
* [[Christopher Owens]]: musician, of San Francisco indie band [[Girls (band)|Girls]], was brought up in TFI by his parents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Ryan |last=Dombal |url=http://www.pitchfork.com/features/interviews/8669-girls/ |title=Girls |website=Pitchfork |date=2011-09-14 |accessdate=2016-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.faqmagazine.org/ChristopherGirls.htm |title=Christopher Owens |first=Emily |last=Easley |website=FAQ magazine |accessdate=2012-10-13 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121005052054/http://www.faqmagazine.org/ChristopherGirls.htm |archivedate=2012-10-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Celeste Jones and Kristina Jones: co-authors, along with [[Juliana Buhring]], of ''[[Not Without My Sister]]'', an autobiography detailing extensive abuse they suffered in COG.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.notwithoutmysister.com/index.php |title=Home |website=Notwithoutmysister.com |accessdate=2009-03-12 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100529193613/http://www.notwithoutmysister.com/index.php |archivedate=2010-05-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This book is used by the organization [[RAINN]] as a reference for [[child sexual abuse]] victims.
* [[Juliana Buhring]]: first woman to bicycle around the world&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/9763072/Juliana-Buhring-becomes-first-woman-to-cycle-round-the-world-as-she-pedals-into-Naples-after-152-days-on-the-road.html |location=London |newspaper=[[The Daily Telegraph]] |first=Cole |last=Moreton |title=Juliana Buhring becomes first woman to cycle round the world as she pedals into Naples after 152 days on the road |date=22 December 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and co-author of ''[[Not Without My Sister]]''.
* [[Rose McGowan]]: film actress, described her TFI childhood in interviews with [[Howard Stern]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Howard Stern radio broadcast |url=http://lavender.fortunecity.com/dale/536/media/arthoward.htm |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20000819115657/http://lavender.fortunecity.com/dale/536/media/arthoward.htm |archivedate=August 19, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[People (American magazine)|People]]'' magazine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.people.com/people/article/0,,20522622,00.html|title=Rose McGowan: How She Survived and Escaped a Cult|website=People|accessdate=February 15, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and later in her book &quot;Brave&quot;.
* [[River Phoenix]], [[Joaquin Phoenix]], [[Rain Phoenix]], and [[Summer Phoenix]]: actors, were members of the group (with their sister [[Liberty Phoenix]]) from 1972 to 1978. River Phoenix, who died of a drug overdose in 1993, told ''[[Details (magazine)|Details]]'' magazine in November 1991 that &quot;they're ruining people's lives.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Friend |first=Tad |date=March 1994 |title=River, with love and anger |journal=[[Esquire (magazine)|Esquire]] |volume=121 |issue=3 |pages=108–117 |issn=0014-0791 |url=http://www.aleka.org/phoenix/zines/phoenix7.htm |accessdate=22 March 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090216162846/http://aleka.org/phoenix/zines/phoenix7.htm |archivedate=16 February 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Susan Justice]]: American pop rock singer-songwriter and guitarist, known best for her debut self-recorded album, ''The Subway Recordings''.
* [[Tina Dupuy]]: American journalist and syndicated columnist.
* [[Ricky Rodriguez]]: subject of the suppressed manual advocating adult-child sexual contact, committed a [[murder-suicide]] in 2005, killing one of the women who raised and allegedly sexually abused him, then himself.&lt;ref name=&quot;suicide&quot;/&gt;
* Lauren Hough: author,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/society/2016/nov/27/family-religious-cult-former-member-recalls-experiences |title=Work, pray, fear: my life in the Family cult |last=Hough |first=Lauren |date=2016-11-27 |newspaper=The Guardian |language=en-GB |issn=0261-3077 |access-date=2016-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; brought up in TFI.
* Flor Edwards, author, &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://floredwards.com/about/|title=Apocalypse Child|access-date=2020-02-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; who was raised inside the cult before her parents moved out.
* Dawn Watson: Brazilian, victim of sexual abuse while living in a TFI community.&lt;ref name=&quot;brazilian&quot;/&gt;
* Taylor Stevens, author, &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.huffingtonpost.com/taylor-stevens/post_1818_b_834665.html|title=On Writing 'The Informationist' and Coming from a Cult Background |website=Huffington Post |date=25 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;brought up in the cult from age 12 until she left in her twenties with her two children.

== Media featuring the group ==
* 'The Jesus Trip' (1971), a documentary by [[Denis Tuohy]] that has interviews with Children of God members.
* ''Children of God'', a 63-minute [[Channel 4]] documentary by [[John Smithson]]; detailing the Padilla family and the abuse of their three underage daughters and the death of another.
* ''Children of God: Lost and Found'', a 75-minute documentary by Noah Thomson, featured at the [[2007 Slamdance Film Festival]]&lt;ref&gt;{{IMDb title|0806136|Children of God: Lost and Found}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Cult Killer: The Rick Rodriguez Story'' (53-minute UK documentary with transcript)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.xfamily.org/index.php/Cult_Killer:_The_Rick_Rodriguez_Story |title=Cult Killer: The Rick Rodriguez Story – XFamily – Children of God |publisher=XFamily |date= |accessdate=2016-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In the first episode of ''[[Louis Theroux's Weird Weekends]]'', ''Born Again Christians'', Louis visits a Texas TFI family.
* [[Buzzcocks]] mentions the group (as &quot;Children Of God&quot;) in their song, &quot;[[Orgasm Addict]]&quot;.
* [[RedLetterMedia]] featured the Family International video &quot;S.O.S.&quot; on an episode of &quot;Best of the Worst.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://redlettermedia.com/best-of-the-worst-wheel-of-the-worst-5/ |title=Red Letter Media Best of the Worst: Wheel of the Worst #5  |website=Redlettermedia.com |date=2014-06-03 |accessdate=2016-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Mentioned in ''Tony Robbins: I Am Not Your Guru'' documentary at 52 minutes of the film as an organization where children are forced to have sex from the age of six.&lt;ref&gt;{{IMDb title|tt5151716|Tony Robbins: I Am Not Your Guru}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Parcast]] Podcast 'Cults': Episodes 11 &amp; 12.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.parcast.com/cults/ |title=Cults |website=Parcast |language=en-US |access-date=2017-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Citizen Rose: A five part documentary series shown on the E! Channel. The first episode premiered on January 30, 2018. The series follows actress Rose McGowan who was born into the cult.
* [[The Last Podcast on the Left]] did a four part series on the Cult: Episodes 248-251
* [[A&amp;E (TV channel)|A&amp;E]]'s ''[[Cults and Extreme Belief (TV series)|Cults and Extreme Belief]]'', episode 3 (2018) is about the Children of God.&lt;ref name=&quot;AECEB&quot;&gt;[https://www.aetv.com/shows/cults-and-extreme-belief/season-1/episode-3 ''Cults and Extreme Belief'' S1E3, aired June 5, 2018. Retrieved June 13, 2018.]&lt;/ref&gt;
*

== See also ==
* [[Comet Kohoutek]] was viewed by David Berg as a prophetic sign of imminent disaster.
* [[Jim Palosaari]] co-formed the ''Jesus People Army'', left it before the group joined the Children of God, and tried to convince Linda Meissner not to join it.
* [[Love bombing]] describes a manipulative style of recruiting.
* [[Panton Hill, Victoria]], the location of one of the communes, where a large government raid occurred and many children were removed by social services

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== Further reading ==
{{Refbegin}}
* Davis, Deborah (Linda Berg) (1984). ''THE CHILDREN OF GOD: The Inside Story''. Zondervan Books, Grand Rapids, Michigan. {{ISBN|0-310-27840-6}}. Expose by the founder's eldest daughter who left the cult.
{{Refend}}

=== Academic ===
{{Refbegin}}
* Chancellor, James (2000). ''Life in The Family: An Oral History of the Children of God''. University of Syracuse Press, Syracuse, NY.
* Bainbridge, William Sims (2002). ''The Endtime Family: Children of God''. State University of New York Press. {{ISBN|0-7914-5264-6}}.
* Bainbridge, William Sims (1996). ''The Sociology of Religious Movements''. Routledge. {{ISBN|0-415-91202-4}}.
* Barker, Eileen. (1989). ''New Religious Movements, A Practical Introduction''. Her Majesty's Stationery Office. {{ISBN|0-11-340927-3}}.
* Barrett, DV (1996). ''Sects, Cults and Alternative Religions''. Blandford A. Cassell. {{ISBN|0-7137-2567-2}}.
* {{Cite journal | doi = 10.1177/0891241602031003003 | author = Boeri, Miriam Williams | year = 2002 | title = Women After the Utopia: The Gendered Lives of Former Cult Members | url = | journal = Journal of Contemporary Ethnography | volume = 31 | issue = 3| pages = 323–360 }}
* {{Cite journal | author = Kent, Stephen A. | year = 1994 | title = Lustful prophet: A psycho-sexual historical study of the children of god's leader, David Berg | url = http://www.arts.ualberta.ca/~skent/Linkedfiles/lustfulprophet.htm | journal = Cultic Studies Journal | volume = 11 | issue = 2| pages = 135–188 }}
* {{Cite journal | doi = 10.1007/BF02354497 | pmid = 24263783 | author = Kent, Stephen A. | year = 1994 | title = Misattribution and social control in the Children of God | url = http://www.xfamily.org/index.php/Misattribution_and_Social_Control_in_the_Children_of_God | journal = Journal of Religion and Health | volume = 33 | issue = 1| pages = 29–43 }}
* {{Cite journal | author = Kent, Stephen A. | year = 2000 | title = Brainwashing and re-indoctrination programs in the Children of God/The Family | url = http://www.arts.ualberta.ca/~skent/Linkedfiles/cog_brainwashing.htm | journal = Cultist Studies Journal | volume = 17 | issue = | pages = 56–78 }}
* Lewis, James R, and Melton, J. Gordon (eds). (1994). [https://archive.is/20121228095119/http://www.thefamily.org/dossier/books/book1/toc.htm ''Sex, Slander, and Salvation: Investigating The Family/Children of God'']. Center for Academic Press, Stanford, CA.
* Lynch, Dalva, and Paul Carden (1990). [http://www.iclnet.org/pub/resources/text/cri/cri-jrnl/web/crj0075a.html &quot;Inside the 'Heavenly Elite': The Children of God Today.&quot;]. ''Christian Research Journal'', pp 16.
* McFarland, Robert (1994). [https://web.archive.org/web/20041209223047/http://www.vote.org/ramsey/cults.htm &quot;The Children of God.&quot;] ''The Journal of Psychohistory'' '''4'''(21).
* Melton, J. Gordon (2004). ''[https://archive.is/20060323035923/http://www.signaturebooks.com/children.htm ''The Children of God, &quot;The Family&quot; ''(Studies in Contemporary Religion vol. 7)]''. Signature Books. {{ISBN|1-56085-180-5}}.
* Melton, J. Gordon (2004). [http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/701799/The-Family-International The Family International Britannica Article]
* Melton, J. Gordon and Robert L. Moore (1982). ''The Cult Experience: Responding to the New Religious Pluralism''. The Pilgrim Press, New York, USA.
* Palmer, Susan J. (1994). [https://archive.is/20121228093207/http://www.thefamily.org/dossier/books/book1/chapter1.htm &quot;Heaven's Children: The Children of God's Second Generation&quot;] in ''Sex, Slander, and Salvation'', ''op. cit.''
* Palmer, Susan J., and Charlotte Hardman eds. (1999). ''Children in New Religions'' (3rd ed.). Rutgers University Press. {{ISBN|0-8135-2620-5}}.
* Shepherd, Gary, and Lawrence Lilliston (1994). [http://webarchive.loc.gov/all/20020914213946/http://www.thefamily.org/dossier/books/book1/chapter5.htm &quot;Field Observations of Young People's Experience and Role in The Family&quot;] in ''Sex, Slander, and Salvation'', ''op. cit.''
* Shepherd, Gary, and Shepherd, Gordon (August 2005). [http://caliber.ucpress.net/doi/abs/10.1525/nr.2005.9.1.067 &quot;Accommodation and Reformation in The Family/Children of God&quot;], ''Nova Religio'' (Journal of the University of California)
* Shepherd, Gary and Shepherd, Gordon (Spring 2000).[https://web.archive.org/web/20051026005804/http://www2.oakland.edu/oujournal/files/Shepherd.pdf &quot;The Moral Career of a New Religious Movement&quot;] ''The Oakland Journal''.
* Wilson, Bryan and Jamie Cresswell, eds. (1999). ''New Religious Movements: Challenge and Response''. ''Routledge'', London, UK.
* Wright, Stuart (1987). ''Leaving Cults: The Dynamics of Defection''. Society for the Scientific Study of Religion. Washington, D.C., USA. {{ISBN|0-932566-06-5}} (Contains interviews with ex-members of three groups, among others the Children of God)
* Van Zandt, David (1991). ''Living in the Children of God''. Princeton University Press, Princeton, New Jersey.
* Young, Shawn David, ''Hippies, Jesus Freaks, and Music'' (Ann Arbor: Xanedu/Copley Original Works, 2005). {{ISBN|1-59399-201-7}}.
{{Refend}}

=== Journalistic and popular ===
{{Refbegin}}
* McManus, Una (1980). ''Not for a Million Dollars''. Impact Books. {{ISBN|0-914850-54-7}}.
* Williams, Miriam (1999). ''Heaven's Harlots: My Fifteen Years As a Sacred Prostitute in the Children of God Cult''. Quill. {{ISBN|0-688-17012-9}}.
* [https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/national/longterm/cult/children_of_god/main.htm &quot;30 Members of Children of God arrested&quot;] (September 2, 1993). ''Washington Post'', pp. A05
* [https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/national/longterm/cult/children_of_god/child1.htm &quot;The Family&quot; and Final Harvest&quot;] (June 2, 1993). ''Washington Post'', pp. A01
* Goodstein, Laurie (2005), ''[https://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/15/national/15cult.html &quot;Murder and Suicide Reviving Claims of Child Abuse in Cult]&quot;, ''[[The New York Times]]'', January 15, 2005, pg. A-1
* Don Lattin: ''Jesus Freaks: A True Story of Murder and Madness on the Evangelical Edge''. HarperOne. {{ISBN|0-06-111804-4}}.
* Johnson, Abe (2011). [https://www.amazon.com/Cult-Child-Tells-All-Johnson-ebook/dp/B0051UBT68/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1481203425&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=cult+child+tells+all ''Cult Child Tells All''] Amazon Books.
{{Refend}}

== External links ==
{{Wiktionary|family}}
*[http://www.thefamilyinternational.org Official website]
 
{{Family International}}
{{Authority control}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Family International}}
[[Category:Family International]]
[[Category:1968 establishments in California]]
[[Category:Christian new religious movements]]
[[Category:Christian organizations established in the 20th century]]
[[Category:Intentional communities]]
[[Category:Jesus movement]]
[[Category:Religious organizations established in 1968]]</text>
      <sha1>rey5yrbcefrfblnkctr6012y3zli507</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
