  <page>
    <title>Daniel Defoe</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8193</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940591901</id>
      <parentid>940589984</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-13T13:07:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>FriendlyCaribou</username>
        <id>21050569</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/81.133.77.232|81.133.77.232]] ([[User talk:81.133.77.232|talk]]) ([[WP:HG|HG]]) (3.4.9)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|18th-century English trader, writer and journalist}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2017}}
{{EngvarB|date=July 2017}}
{{Infobox writer
| name = Daniel Defoe
| image = Daniel Defoe Kneller Style.jpg
| image_size =
| caption =
| birth_name = Daniel Foe
| birth_date = 1659–1660
| birth_place = London, England
| death_date = 24 April 1731 (aged 70)
| death_place = London, England
| resting_place = [[Bunhill Fields]]
| occupation = Writer, journalist, merchant
| genre = Adventure
| spouse = Mary Tuffley
}}

'''Daniel Defoe''' ({{IPAc-en|d|ᵻ|ˈ|f|əʊ}}; c. 1660 – 24 April 1731),&lt;ref&gt;According to [[Paul Duguid]] in [http://firstmonday.org/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/1405/1323 &quot;Limits of self organization&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110615130952/http://firstmonday.org/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/1405/1323 |date=15 June 2011 }}, ''[[First Monday]]'' (11 September 2006): &quot;Most reliable sources hold that the date of Defoe's birth was uncertain and may have fallen in 1659 or 1661. The day of his death is also uncertain.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; born '''Daniel Foe''', was an English trader, writer, journalist, [[pamphleteer]] and spy. He is most famous for his novel ''[[Robinson Crusoe]]'', which is second only to the [[Bible]] in its number of translations.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/7421|title=Daniel Defoe (1660?–1731)|last=Backscheider|first=Paula R.|date=January 2008|edition=online |orig-year=2004 |website=Oxford Dictionary of National Biography|access-date=|doi=10.1093/ref:odnb/7421}} {{subscription required|s}}&lt;/ref&gt; He has been seen as one of the earliest proponents of the [[English novel]], and helped to popularise the form in Britain with others such as [[Aphra Behn]] and [[Samuel Richardson]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Defoe&quot;, ''The Oxford Companion to English Literature'', ed. Margaret Drabble. (Oxford: Oxford University Press,1996), p. 265.&lt;/ref&gt;  Defoe wrote many political tracts and was often in trouble with the authorities, and spent a period in prison.  Intellectuals and political leaders paid attention to his fresh ideas and sometimes consulted with him.

Defoe was a prolific and versatile writer, producing more than three hundred works&lt;ref&gt;Backscheider (2008/2004). &quot;Even the most conservative lists of Defoe's works include 318 titles, and most Defoe scholars would credit him with at least 50 more.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;—books, pamphlets, and journals—on diverse topics, including politics, crime, religion, marriage, psychology, and the supernatural. He was also a pioneer of [[business journalism]]&lt;ref&gt;Margarett A. James, and Dorothy F. Tucker. &quot;Daniel Defoe, Journalist.&quot; ''Business History Review'' 2.1 (1928): 2–6.&lt;/ref&gt; and economic journalism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Letters to John Law&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=Gavin John |last=Adams |authorlink=Gavin John Adams |title=Letters to John Law|year=2012|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=espxkAw-5bsC&amp;pg=PR53|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140102074401/http://books.google.com/books?id=espxkAw-5bsC&amp;pg=PR53|url-status=dead|archive-date=2014-01-02|publisher= Newton Page  |pages=liii–lv |isbn= 978-1-934619-08-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Early life ==
Daniel Foe (his original name) was probably born in [[Fore Street (London)|Fore Street]] in the parish of [[St Giles-without-Cripplegate|St Giles]] [[Cripplegate]], London.&lt;ref name=EncylLon&gt;{{cite book|author1=[[Christopher Hibbert|Hibbert, Christopher]]; Ben Weinreb; John Keay; Julia Keay.|title=The London Encyclopaedia|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=xa0D0PqiwfEC&amp;pg=PA304|year=2010|location=London|publisher=Pan Macmillan|isbn=978-0-230-73878-2|page=304}}&lt;/ref&gt; Defoe later added the aristocratic-sounding &quot;De&quot; to his name, and on occasion claimed descent from the family of De Beau Faux. His birthdate and birthplace are uncertain, and sources offer dates from 1659 to 1662, with the summer or early autumn of 1660 considered the most likely.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Bastian |first1=F. |year=1981 |title=Defoe's Early Years |url=https://books.google.com/?id=yNquCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA8&amp;dq=%22early+autumn+of+1660%22#v=onepage&amp;q=%22early%20autumn%20of%201660%22&amp;f=false |location=London |publisher=Macmillan Press |page=8 |isbn=978-0333274323 |access-date=23 October 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt; His father, James Foe, was a prosperous [[tallow]] [[Chandlery|chandler]] and a member of the [[Worshipful Company of Butchers]]. In Defoe's early life, he experienced some of the most unusual occurrences in English history: in 1665, 70,000 were killed by the [[Great Plague of London]], and the next year, the [[Great Fire of London]] left standing only Defoe's and two other houses in his neighbourhood.&lt;ref name = west&gt;Richard West (1998) ''Daniel Defoe: The Life and Strange, Surprising Adventures''. New York: Carroll &amp; Graf. {{ISBN|978-0-7867-0557-3}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1667, when he was probably about seven, a Dutch fleet sailed up the [[River Medway|Medway]] via the [[River Thames]] and attacked the town of [[Chatham, Kent|Chatham]] in the [[raid on the Medway]]. His mother, Annie, had died by the time he was about ten.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2006&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=The Broadview Anthology of Literature: The Restoration and the Eighteenth Century|year=2006|publisher=Broadview Press|location=Toronto|isbn=978-1-55111-611-2|editor=Joseph Laurence Black}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = rich&gt;John J. Richetti (2005) ''The Life of Daniel Defoe''. Malden, MA: Blackwell Publishing, {{ISBN|978-0-631-19529-0}}, {{DOI|10.1002/9780470754665}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Education==
Defoe was educated at the Rev. James Fisher's boarding school in Pixham Lane in [[Dorking]], Surrey.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thereandwhere.com/where/Dorking Dorking – Famous residents and literary connections]. Retrieved 1 August 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; His parents were [[Presbyterianism|Presbyterian]] [[English Dissenters|dissenters]], and around the age of 14, he attended a [[Dissenting academies|dissenting academy]] at [[Newington Green]] in London run by [[Charles Morton (educator)|Charles Morton]], and he is believed to have attended the [[Newington Green Unitarian Church]] and kept practising his Presbyterian religion.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gradesaver.com/author/daniel-defoe/ Biography of Daniel Defoe (1659?–1731)]. Retrieved 1 August 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Defoe in Stoke Newington&quot;. Arthur Secord, P.M.L.A. Vol. 66, p. 211, 1951. Cited in Thorncroft, p. 9, who identifies him as &quot;an American scholar&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; During this period, the English government persecuted those who chose to worship outside the [[Church of England]].

== Business career ==
Defoe entered the world of business as a general merchant, dealing at different times in hosiery, general woollen goods, and wine. His ambitions were great and he was able to buy a country estate and a ship (as well as [[civet]]s to make perfume), though he was rarely out of debt. He was forced to declare bankruptcy in 1692.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; On 1 January 1684, Defoe married Mary Tuffley at [[St Botolph's Aldgate]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Novak 2001&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Novak |first=Maximillian |title=Daniel Defoe : master of fictions : his life and ideas |url=https://archive.org/details/danieldefoemaste00maxi |url-access=registration |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford; New York |year=2001 |isbn=978-0199261543 |oclc=51963527}}&lt;/ref&gt; She was the daughter of a London merchant, receiving a dowry of £3,700—a huge amount by the standards of the day. With his debts and political difficulties, the marriage may have been troubled, but it lasted 47  years and produced eight children.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2006&quot;/&gt;

In 1685, Defoe joined the ill-fated [[Monmouth Rebellion]] but gained a pardon, by which he escaped the [[Bloody Assizes]] of Judge [[George Jeffreys, 1st Baron Jeffreys|George Jeffreys]]. [[Mary II of England|Queen Mary]] and her husband [[William III of England|William III]] were jointly crowned in 1689, and Defoe became one of William's close allies and a secret agent.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2006&quot;/&gt; Some of the new policies led to conflict with France, thus damaging prosperous trade relationships for Defoe, who had established himself as a merchant.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2006&quot;/&gt; In 1692, Defoe was arrested for debts of £700, though his total debts may have amounted to £17,000. His laments were loud and he always defended unfortunate debtors, but there is evidence that his financial dealings were not always honest.{{Citation needed|date=July 2015}} He died with little wealth and evidence of lawsuits with the royal treasury.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

Following his release from debtor's prison, he probably travelled in Europe and Scotland,&lt;ref name=&quot;Backscheider 1989&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last=Backscheider | first=Paula | title=Daniel Defoe : his life | publisher=Johns Hopkins University Press | location=Baltimore | year=1989 | isbn=978-0801845123 | pages=380–381 |oclc=59911734 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and it may have been at this time that he traded wine to [[Cadiz]], [[Porto]] and [[Lisbon]]. By 1695, he was back in England, now formally using the name &quot;Defoe&quot; and serving as a &quot;commissioner of the glass duty&quot;, responsible for collecting taxes on bottles. In 1696, he ran a tile and brick factory in what is now [[Tilbury]] in [[History of Essex|Essex]] and lived in the parish of [[Chadwell St Mary]].

== Writing ==

As many as 545 titles have been ascribed to Defoe, ranging from satirical poems, political and religious pamphlets, and volumes. ([[P. N. Furbank|Furbank]] and Owens argue for the much smaller number of 276 published items in ''Critical Bibliography'' (1998).)

=== Pamphleteering and prison ===
[[File:Daniel Defoe by James Charles Armytage.jpg|thumb|Daniel Defoe in the [[pillory]], 1862 line engraving by [[James Charles Armytage]] after [[Eyre Crowe (painter)|Eyre Crowe]]]]

Defoe's first notable publication was ''[[An essay upon projects]]'', a series of proposals for social and economic improvement, published in 1697. From 1697 to 1698, he defended the right of King [[William III of England|William III]] to a [[standing army]] during disarmament, after the [[Treaty of Ryswick]] (1697) had ended the [[Nine Years' War]] (1688–1697). His most successful poem, ''[[The True-Born Englishman]]'' (1701), defended the king against the perceived xenophobia of his enemies, satirising the English claim to racial purity. In 1701, Defoe presented the ''Legion's Memorial'' to [[Robert Harley, 1st Earl of Oxford and Earl Mortimer|Robert Harley]], then [[Speaker of the House of Commons (United Kingdom)|Speaker of the House of Commons]]—and his subsequent employer—while flanked by a guard of sixteen gentlemen of quality. It demanded the release of the Kentish petitioners, who had asked Parliament to support the king in an imminent war against France.

The death of [[William III of England|William III]] in 1702 once again created a political upheaval, as the king was replaced by [[Anne, Queen of Great Britain|Queen Anne]] who immediately began her offensive against [[Nonconformist (Protestantism)|Nonconformists]].&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2006&quot;/&gt; Defoe was a natural target, and his pamphleteering and political activities resulted in his arrest and placement in a [[pillory]] on 31 July 1703, principally on account of his December 1702 pamphlet entitled ''[[The Shortest Way with the Dissenters|The Shortest-Way with the Dissenters; Or, Proposals for the Establishment of the Church]]'', purporting to argue for their extermination.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web|url=http://www.bartleby.com/27/12.html|author=Daniel Defoe|year=1702|title=The shortest way with the Dissenters|accessdate=18 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In it, he ruthlessly satirised both the [[High church]] [[Tory|Tories]] and those [[Dissenter]]s who hypocritically practised so-called &quot;occasional conformity&quot;, such as his [[Stoke Newington]] neighbour Sir [[Thomas Abney]]. It was published anonymously, but the true authorship was quickly discovered and Defoe was arrested.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2006&quot;/&gt; He was charged with seditious libel and found guilty in a trial at the [[Old Bailey]] in front of the notoriously sadistic judge [[Salathiel Lovell]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Letters to John Law&quot;/&gt; Lovell sentenced him to a punitive fine of 200 [[Mark (currency)|marks]], to public humiliation in a [[pillory]], and to an indeterminate length of imprisonment which would only end upon the discharge of the punitive fine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Letters to John Law&quot;/&gt; According to legend, the publication of his poem ''Hymn to the Pillory'' caused his audience at the pillory to throw flowers instead of the customary harmful and noxious objects and to drink to his health. The truth of this story is questioned by most scholars, although [[John Robert Moore]] later said that &quot;no man in England but Defoe ever stood in the pillory and later rose to eminence among his fellow men&quot;.&lt;ref name = rich/&gt;
{{Quote box
 |quote = &quot;Wherever God erects a house of prayer&lt;br /&gt;the Devil always builds a chapel there;&lt;br /&gt;And 't will be found, upon examination,&lt;br /&gt;the latter has the largest congregation.&quot;
 |source = — Defoe's ''The True-Born Englishman'', 1701
}}

After his three days in the pillory, Defoe went into [[Newgate Prison]]. [[Robert Harley, 1st Earl of Oxford and Earl Mortimer]], brokered his release in exchange for Defoe's co-operation as an intelligence agent for the Tories. In exchange for such co-operation with the rival political side, Harley paid some of Defoe's outstanding debts, improving his financial situation considerably.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2006&quot;/&gt;

Within a week of his release from prison, Defoe witnessed the [[Great Storm of 1703]], which raged through the night of 26/27 November. It caused severe damage to London and [[Bristol]], uprooted millions of trees, and killed more than 8,000 people, mostly at sea. The event became the subject of Defoe's ''[[The Storm (Daniel Defoe)|The Storm]]'' (1704), which includes a collection of witness accounts of the tempest.&lt;ref&gt;''The Storm: or, a collection of the most remarkable casualties and disasters which happen'd in the late dreadful tempest, both by sea and land''. London: 1704.&lt;/ref&gt; Many regard it as one of the world's first examples of modern journalism.&lt;ref&gt;[[John J. Miller (journalist)|John J. Miller]] (13 August 2011) [https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB10001424053111904800304576476142821212156?KEYWORDS=masterpiece &quot;Writing Up a Storm&quot;], ''The Wall Street Journal''.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the same year, he set up his [[Periodical literature|periodical]] ''A Review of the Affairs of France'' which supported the [[Harley Ministry]], chronicling the events of the [[War of the Spanish Succession]] (1702–1714). The ''Review'' ran three times a week without interruption until 1713. Defoe was amazed that a man as gifted as Harley left vital state papers lying in the open, and warned that he was almost inviting an unscrupulous clerk to commit treason; his warnings were fully justified by the [[William Gregg (clerk and spy)|William Gregg]] affair.

When Harley was ousted from the ministry in 1708, Defoe continued writing the ''Review'' to support [[Sidney Godolphin, 1st Earl of Godolphin|Godolphin]], then again to support Harley and the [[Tory (British political party)|Tories]] in the Tory ministry of 1710–1714. The Tories fell from power with the death of [[Anne, Queen of Great Britain|Queen Anne]], but Defoe continued doing intelligence work for the [[Whig (British political party)|Whig]] government, writing &quot;Tory&quot; pamphlets that undermined the Tory point of view.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2006&quot;/&gt;

Not all of Defoe's pamphlet writing was political. One pamphlet was originally published anonymously, entitled &quot;''A True Relation of the Apparition of One Mrs. Veal the Next Day after her Death to One Mrs. Bargrave at Canterbury the 8th of September, 1705''.&quot; It deals with interaction between the spiritual realm and the physical realm and was most likely written in support of [[Charles Drelincourt]]'s ''The Christian Defense against the Fears of Death'' (1651). It describes Mrs. Bargrave's encounter with her old friend Mrs. Veal after she had died. It is clear from this piece and other writings that the political portion of Defoe's life was by no means his only focus.

=== Anglo-Scottish Union of 1707 ===
{{more citations needed|section|date=July 2017}}&lt;!--lots of paragraphs without citations--&gt;

[[File:Defoe 1709 The History Of The Union Of Great Britain.JPG|thumb|Title page from Daniel Defoe's: ''The History of the Union of Great Britain'' dated 1709 and printed in Edinburgh by the Heirs of Anderson]]
In despair during his imprisonment for the seditious libel case, Defoe wrote to [[William Paterson (banker)|William Paterson]], the London Scot and founder of the [[Bank of England]] and part instigator of the [[Darien scheme]], who was in the confidence of [[Robert Harley, 1st Earl of Oxford and Earl Mortimer]], leading minister and spymaster in the [[Governance of England|English Government]]. Harley accepted Defoe's services and released him in 1703. He immediately published ''The Review'', which appeared weekly, then three times a week, written mostly by himself. This was the main mouthpiece of the English Government promoting the [[Acts of Union 1707|Act of Union 1707]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Downie |first1=J. A. |title=Robert Harley and the Press |url=https://theses.ncl.ac.uk/dspace/bitstream/10443/165/1/downie76.pdf |website=University of Newcastle eTheses |publisher=University of Newcastle |accessdate=24 January 2019 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190125183319/https://theses.ncl.ac.uk/dspace/bitstream/10443/165/1/downie76.pdf |archive-date=25 January 2019 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1709, Defoe authored a rather lengthy book entitled ''The History of the Union of Great Britain'', an Edinburgh publication printed by the Heirs of Anderson.&lt;ref&gt;[http://truescans.com/index-Defoe.htm ''The History Of The Union Of Great Britain'', 1709; Edinburgh, Heirs of Anderson.] at TrueScans&lt;/ref&gt; The book was not published anonymously and cites Defoe twice as being its author.&lt;ref&gt;[http://truescans.com/Images/Defoe_1709/DSCN9162.JPG First Defoe book author reference – cited as DANIEL DEFOE]. truescans.com. Retrieved 31 July 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://truescans.com/Images/Defoe_1709/DSCN9166.JPG Second Defoe book author crediting – stipulated as D. DE FOE]. truescans.com. Retrieved 31 July 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; The book attempts to explain the facts leading up to the Act of Union 1707, dating all the way back to 6 December 1604 when [[James I of England|King James I]] was presented with a proposal for unification.&lt;ref&gt;[http://truescans.com/Images/Defoe_1709/DSCN9167A.JPG Page 19 from the chapter entitled, ''A General History of Unions in Britain''; ''The History Of The Union Of Great Britain'', 1709; Edinburgh, Heirs Of Anderson]. truescans.com. Retrieved 31 July 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; This so-called &quot;first draft&quot; for unification took place 100 years before the signing of the 1707 accord, which respectively preceded the commencement of ''Robinson Crusoe'' by another ten years.

Defoe began his campaign in ''The Review'' and other pamphlets aimed at English opinion, claiming that it would end the threat from the north, gaining for the Treasury an &quot;inexhaustible treasury of men&quot;, a valuable new market increasing the power of England. By September 1706, Harley ordered Defoe to [[Edinburgh]] as a secret agent to do everything possible to help secure acquiescence in the [[Treaty of Union]]. He was conscious of the risk to himself. Thanks to books such as ''The Letters of Daniel Defoe'' (edited by G. H. Healey, Oxford 1955), far more is known about his activities than is usual with such agents.

His first reports included vivid descriptions of violent demonstrations against the Union. &quot;A Scots rabble is the worst of its kind&quot;, he reported. Years later [[Sir John Clerk, 2nd Baronet|John Clerk of Penicuik]], a leading Unionist, wrote in his memoirs that it was not known at the time that Defoe had been sent by Godolphin : {{quote|… to give a faithful account to him from time to time how everything past here. He was therefor&lt;!--sic--&gt; a spy among us, but not known to be such, otherways the [[wikt:mob|Mob]] of [[Edinburgh|Edin.]]&lt;!--sic--&gt; had pull him to pieces.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Clerk|first1=John|editor1-last=Gray|editor1-first=John Miller|title=Memoirs of the life of Sir John Clerk of Penicuik, baronet, baron of the Exchequer, extracted by himself from his own journals, 1676–1755|date=1892|publisher=Scottish Historical Society|location=Edinburgh|pages=63–64|url=https://archive.org/details/memoirslifesirj01clergoog}} In a side-note at this point Clerk recommends Defoe's ''History of the Union of Great Britain'' : &quot;This History of the Union deserves to be read. It was published in folio. There is not one fact in it which I can challenge&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;|sign=|source=}}

Defoe was a [[Presbyterian]] who had suffered in England for his convictions, and as such he was accepted as an adviser to the [[General Assembly of the Church of Scotland]] and committees of the [[Parliament of Scotland]]. He told Harley that he was &quot;privy to all their folly&quot; but &quot;Perfectly unsuspected as with corresponding with anybody in England&quot;. He was then able to influence the proposals that were put to Parliament and reported,

{{quote|Having had the honour to be always sent for the committee to whom these amendments were referrèd,&lt;br /&gt;I have had the good fortune to break their measures in two particulars via the bounty on Corn and&lt;br /&gt;proportion of the Excise.}}

For Scotland, he used different arguments, even the opposite of those which he used in England, usually ignoring the English doctrine of the [[Parliamentary sovereignty in the United Kingdom|Sovereignty of Parliament]], for example, telling the Scots that they could have complete confidence in the guarantees in the Treaty. Some of his pamphlets were purported to be written by Scots, misleading even reputable historians into quoting them as evidence of Scottish opinion of the time. The same is true of a massive history of the Union which Defoe published in 1709 and which some historians still treat as a valuable contemporary source for their own works. Defoe took pains to give his history an air of objectivity by giving some space to arguments against the Union but always having the last word for himself.

He disposed of the main Union opponent, [[Andrew Fletcher (politician)|Andrew Fletcher]] of [[East Saltoun and West Saltoun|Saltoun]], by ignoring him. Nor does he account for the deviousness of the [[Duke of Hamilton]], the official leader of the various factions opposed to the Union, who seemingly betrayed his former colleagues when he switched to the Unionist/Government side in the decisive final stages of the debate.

Defoe made no attempt to explain why the same Parliament of Scotland which was so vehement for its independence from 1703 to 1705 became so supine in 1706. He received very little reward from his paymasters and of course no recognition for his services by the government. He made use of his Scottish experience to write his ''Tour thro' the whole Island of Great Britain'', published in 1726, where he admitted that the increase of trade and population in Scotland which he had predicted as a consequence of the Union was &quot;not the case, but rather the contrary&quot;.

[[File:Glasgow Bridge c.1758.JPG|thumb|Glasgow Bridge as Defoe might have seen it in the 18th century]]
Defoe's description of [[Glasgow]] (Glaschu) as a &quot;Dear Green Place&quot; has often been misquoted as a [[Scottish Gaelic|Gaelic]] translation for the town's name. The Gaelic ''Glas'' could mean grey or green, while ''chu'' means dog or hollow. ''Glaschu'' probably means &quot;Green Hollow&quot;. The &quot;Dear Green Place&quot;, like much of Scotland, was a hotbed of unrest against the Union. The local [[St George's-Tron Church|Tron]] [[Minister (Christianity)|minister]] urged his congregation &quot;to up and anent for the City of God&quot;.

The &quot;Dear Green Place&quot; and &quot;City of God&quot; required government troops to put down the rioters tearing up copies of the Treaty at almost every [[mercat cross]] in Scotland. When Defoe visited in the mid-1720s, he claimed that the hostility towards his party was &quot;because they were English and because of the Union, which they were almost universally exclaimed against&quot;.{{Citation needed|date=July 2015}}

=== Late writing ===
The extent and particulars are widely contested concerning Defoe's writing in the period from the Tory fall in 1714 to the publication of ''[[Robinson Crusoe]]'' in 1719. Defoe comments on the tendency to attribute tracts of uncertain authorship to him in his apologia ''Appeal to Honour and Justice'' (1715), a defence of his part in Harley's Tory ministry (1710–1714). Other works that anticipate his novelistic career include ''The Family Instructor'' (1715), a conduct manual on religious duty; ''Minutes of the Negotiations of Monsr. Mesnager'' (1717), in which he impersonates [[Nicolas Mesnager]], the French plenipotentiary who negotiated the [[Treaty of Utrecht]] (1713); and ''A Continuation of the [[Letters Writ by a Turkish Spy]]'' (1718), a satire of European politics and religion, ostensibly written by a [[Muslim]] in Paris.

[[File:Daniel Defoe monument Bunhill Fields.jpg|thumb|upright|Memorial to &quot;Daniel De-Foe&quot;, [[Bunhill Fields]], [[City Road]], [[Borough of Islington]], London]]

From 1719 to 1724, Defoe published the novels for which he is famous (see below). In the final decade of his life, he also wrote conduct manuals, including ''Religious Courtship'' (1722), ''The Complete English Tradesman'' (1726) and ''The New Family Instructor'' (1727). He published a number of books decrying the breakdown of the social order, such as ''The Great Law of Subordination Considered'' (1724) and ''Everybody's Business is Nobody's Business'' (1725) and works on the supernatural, like ''[[The Political History of the Devil]]'' (1726), ''A System of Magick'' (1727) and ''An Essay on the History and Reality of Apparitions'' (1727). His works on foreign travel and trade include ''A General History of Discoveries and Improvements'' (1727) and ''Atlas Maritimus and Commercialis'' (1728). Perhaps his greatest achievement with the novels is the magisterial ''[[A tour thro' the whole island of Great Britain]]'' (1724–1727), which provided a panoramic survey of British trade on the eve of the [[Industrial Revolution]].

====''The Complete English Tradesman''====

Published in 1726, ''The Complete English Tradesman'' is an example of Defoe's political works. He discusses the role of the tradesman in England in comparison to tradesmen internationally, arguing that the British system of trade is far superior.&lt;ref name=defoe1 /&gt; He also implies that trade is the backbone of the British economy: &quot;estate's a pond, but trade's a spring.&quot;&lt;ref name=defoe1&gt;[Defoe, Daniel. The complete English tradesman. London: Tegg, 1841. Print.]&lt;/ref&gt; He praises the practicality of trade not only within the economy but the social stratification as well. Most of the British [[gentry]], he argues is at one time or another inextricably linked with the institution of trade, either through personal experience, marriage or genealogy.&lt;ref name=defoe1 /&gt; Oftentimes younger members of noble families entered into trade. Marriage to a tradesman's daughter by a [[nobleman]] was also common. Overall Defoe demonstrated a high respect for '''tradesmen''', being one himself.

Not only does Defoe elevate individual British tradesmen to the level of [[gentleman]], but he praises the entirety of British trade as a superior system.&lt;ref name=defoe1 /&gt; Trade, Defoe argues is a much better catalyst for social and economic change than war. He states that through [[imperialism]] and trade expansion the British empire is able to &quot;increase commerce at home&quot; through job creation and increased [[Consumption (economics)|consumption]].&lt;ref name= defoe1 /&gt; He states that increased consumption, by laws of supply and demand, increases production and in turn raises wages for the poor therefore lifting part of British society further out of poverty.&lt;ref name=defoe1 /&gt;

=== Novels ===
====''Robinson Crusoe''====
{{main|Robinson Crusoe}}
Published in his late fifties,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/cu31924013179902|title=Daniel Defoe|last=Minto|first=William|publisher=Harper &amp; Bros.|year=1879|isbn=|location=New York|pages=|language=English|oclc=562533988}}&lt;/ref&gt; this novel relates the story of a man's shipwreck on a desert island for twenty-eight years and his subsequent adventures.  Throughout its episodic narrative, Crusoe's struggles with faith are apparent as he bargains with God in times of life-threatening crises, but time and again he turns his back after his deliverances. He is finally content with his lot in life, separated from society, following a more genuine conversion experience.

Usually read as fiction, a coincidence of background geography suggests that this may be non-fiction.{{citation needed|date=March 2019}}  In the opening pages of ''[[The Farther Adventures of Robinson Crusoe]]'', the author describes how Crusoe settled in [[Bedfordshire]], married and produced a family, and that when his wife died, he went off on these further adventures.  Bedford is also the place where the brother of &quot;H. F.&quot; in ''[[A Journal of the Plague Year]]'' retired to avoid the danger of the plague, so that by implication, if these works were not fiction, Defoe's family met Crusoe in Bedford, from whence the information in these books was gathered.  Defoe went to school in Stoke Newington, London, with a friend named Caruso.

The novel has been assumed to be based in part on the story of the Scottish castaway [[Alexander Selkirk]], who spent four years stranded in the [[Juan Fernández Islands]],&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2006&quot;/&gt; but this experience is inconsistent with the details of the narrative.  The island Selkirk lived on was named Más a Tierra (Closer to Land) at the time and was renamed [[Robinson Crusoe Island]] in 1966. It has been supposed that Defoe may have also been inspired by the Latin or English translation of a book by the [[Al-Andalus|Andalusian]]-Arab Muslim polymath [[Ibn Tufail]], who was known as &quot;Abubacer&quot; in Europe. The Latin edition of the book was entitled ''[[Hayy ibn Yaqdhan|Philosophus Autodidactus]]'' and it was an earlier novel that is also set on a deserted island.&lt;ref&gt;Nawal Muhammad Hassan (1980), ''Hayy bin Yaqzan and Robinson Crusoe: A study of an early Arabic impact on English literature'', Al-Rashid House for Publication.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cyril Glassé (2001), ''The New Encyclopedia of Islam'', Rowman Altamira, p. 202, {{ISBN|0-7591-0190-6}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Amber&gt;{{cite journal|author=Amber Haque |year=2004|title=Psychology from Islamic Perspective: Contributions of Early Muslim Scholars and Challenges to Contemporary Muslim Psychologists|journal=Journal of Religion and Health|volume=43|issue=4|pages= 357–377 [369]|jstor=27512819|doi=10.1007/s10943-004-4302-z}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Wainwright&gt;Martin Wainwright (22 March 2003) [http://books.guardian.co.uk/review/story/0,12084,918454,00.html Desert island scripts], ''[[The Guardian]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Daniel Defoe former house England.jpg|thumb|A house where Defoe once lived, near London, England]]

====''Captain Singleton''====

Defoe's next novel was ''[[Captain Singleton]]'' (1720), an adventure story whose first half covers a traversal of Africa which anticipated subsequent discoveries by [[David Livingstone]] and whose second half taps into the contemporary fascination with [[piracy]]. The novel has been commended for its sensitive depiction of the close relationship between the hero and his religious mentor, [[Religious Society of Friends|Quaker]] William Walters.  Its description of the geography of Africa and some of its fauna does not use the language or knowledge of a fiction writer and suggests an eyewitness experience.

==== ''Memoirs of a Cavalier'' ====

''[[Memoirs of a Cavalier]]'' (1720) is set during the [[Thirty Years' War]] and the [[English Civil War]].

==== ''A Journal of the Plague Year'' ====

A novel often read as non-fiction, this is an account of the Great Plague of London in 1665, which is undersigned by the initials &quot;H. F.&quot;, suggesting the author's uncle Henry Foe as its primary source.  It is a historical account of the events based on extensive research and seen through an eyewitness experience, published in 1722.

&lt;blockquote&gt;''Bring out your dead!'' The ceaseless chant of doom echoed through a city of emptied streets and filled grave pits. For this was London in the year of 1665, the Year of the Great Plague&amp;nbsp;… In 1721, when the Black Death again threatened the European Continent, Daniel Defoe wrote &quot;[[A Journal of the Plague Year]]&quot; to alert an indifferent populace to the horror that was almost upon them. Through the eyes of a saddler who had chosen to remain while multitudes fled, the master realist vividly depicted a plague-stricken city. He re-enacted the terror of a helpless people caught in a tragedy they could not comprehend: the weak preying on the dying, the strong administering to the sick, the sinful orgies of the cynical, the quiet faith of the pious. With dramatic insight, he captured for all time the death throes of a great city.&lt;p&gt;— Back cover of the New American Library version of &quot;A Journal of the Plague Year&quot;; Signet Classic, 1960&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==== ''Colonel Jack'' ====

'''''[[Colonel Jack]]''''' (1722) follows an orphaned boy from a life of poverty and crime to colonial prosperity, military and marital imbroglios, and religious conversion, driven by a problematic notion of becoming a &quot;gentleman.&quot;

==== ''Moll Flanders'' ====
Also in 1722, Defoe wrote '''''[[Moll Flanders]]''''', another first-person [[picaresque novel]] of the fall and eventual redemption, both material and spiritual, of a lone woman in 17th-century England. The titular heroine appears as a whore, bigamist, and thief, lives in [[Liberty of the Mint|The Mint]], commits adultery and incest, and yet manages to retain the reader's sympathy. Her savvy manipulation of both men and wealth earns her a life of trials but ultimately an ending in reward. Although Moll struggles with the morality of some of her actions and decisions, religion seems to be far from her concerns throughout most of her story. However, like Robinson Crusoe, she finally repents. ''Moll Flanders'' is an important work in the development of the novel, as it challenged the common perception of femininity and gender roles in 18th-century British society.&lt;ref name=&quot;Novak 2001&quot; /&gt; More recently it has come to be misunderstood as an example of [[erotica]].&lt;ref name=&quot;historyextra&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.historyextra.com/period/moll-the-life-and-times-of-moll-flanders/|title=Moll: The Life and Times of Moll Flanders|website=History Extra|access-date=30 May 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190428084347/https://www.historyextra.com/period/moll-the-life-and-times-of-moll-flanders/|archive-date=28 April 2019|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== ''Roxana'' ====

''Moll Flanders'' and Defoe's final novel, '''''[[Roxana: The Fortunate Mistress]]''''' (1724), are examples of the remarkable way in which Defoe seems to inhabit his fictional characters (yet &quot;drawn from life&quot;), not least in that they are women. ''Roxana'' narrates the moral and spiritual decline of a high society courtesan. ''Roxana'' differs from other Defoe works because the main character does not exhibit a conversion experience, even though she claims to be a penitent later in her life, at the time that she's relaying her story.

== Death ==
[[File:Bunhill Fields, London 13.JPG|thumb|Bunhill Fields monument detail]]
Daniel Defoe died on 24 April 1731, probably while in hiding from his creditors. He often was in debtors' prison.&lt;ref&gt;Pat Rogers,  &quot;Defoe in the Fleet Prison.&quot; ''Review of English Studies''22.88 (1971): 451–455.&lt;/ref&gt; The cause of his death was labelled as lethargy, but he probably experienced a stroke.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; He was interred in [[Bunhill Fields]] (today Bunhill Fields Burial and Gardens), [[Borough of Islington]], London, where a monument was erected to his memory in 1870.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Kennedy|first1=Maev|title=Burial ground of Bunyan, Defoe and Blake earns protected status|url=https://www.theguardian.com/culture/2011/feb/22/bunhill-fields-bunyan-defoe-blake|accessdate=21 January 2015|work=The Guardian|date=22 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Defoe is known to have used at least 198 [[Pen name|pen names]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The appendices offer even more: a listing of Voltaire's and Daniel Defoe's numerous pseudonyms (178 and 198, respectively)&amp;nbsp;…&quot; in ''A Dictionary of Pseudonyms and Their Origins, with Stories of Name Changes'', 3rd ed., Mcfarland &amp; Co Inc Pub., 1998, {{ISBN|0-7864-0423-X}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Selected works ==

===Novels===

* ''[[The Consolidator|The Consolidator, or Memoirs of Sundry Transactions from the World in the Moon: Translated from the Lunar Language]]'' (1705)&lt;ref name=SFE&gt;[http://www.sf-encyclopedia.com/entry/defoe_daniel &quot;Defoe, Daniel&quot;]. &lt;i&gt;[[The Encyclopedia of Science Fiction]]&lt;/i&gt;. Online edition (3rd ed., 2011). Biographical entry by editors John Clute and Peter Nicholls. Retrieved 12 September 2019.&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[Robinson Crusoe]]'' (1719) – originally published in two volumes:&lt;ref name=SFE/&gt;
** ''The Life and Strange Surprizing Adventures of Robinson Crusoe, of York, Mariner: Who Lived Eight and Twenty Years [...]''
** ''[[The Farther Adventures of Robinson Crusoe]]: Being the Second and Last  Part of His Life [...]''
* ''[[Serious Reflections During the Life and Surprising Adventures of Robinson Crusoe: With his Vision of the Angelick World]]'' (1720)
* ''[[Captain Singleton]]'' (1720)
* ''[[Memoirs of a Cavalier]]'' (1720)
* ''[[A Journal of the Plague Year]]'' (1722)
* ''[[Colonel Jack]]'' (1722)
* ''[[Moll Flanders]]'' (1722)
* ''[[Roxana: The Fortunate Mistress]]'' (1724)

===Non-fiction===
* ''[[An Essay Upon Projects]]'' (1697) – which includes a chapter suggesting a national insurance scheme.
* ''[[The Storm (Daniel Defoe)|The Storm]]'' (1704) – describes the worst storm ever to hit Britain in recorded times.  Includes eyewitness accounts.
* ''[[Atlantis Major]]'' (1711)
* ''[[The Family Instructor]]'' (1715)
* ''[[Memoirs of the Church of Scotland]]'' (1717)
* ''[[The History of the Remarkable Life of John Sheppard]]'' (1724) – describing Sheppard's life of crime and concluding with the miraculous escapes from prison for which he had become a public sensation.
* ''[[A Narrative of All The Robberies, Escapes, &amp;c. of John Sheppard]]'' (1724) – written by or taken from Sheppard himself in the condemned cell before he was hanged for theft, apparently by way of conclusion to the Defoe work.  According to the Introduction to Volume 16 of the works of Defoe published by J M Dent in 1895, Sheppard handed the manuscript to the publisher Applebee from the prisoners' cart as he was taken away to be hanged.  It included a correction of a factual detail and an explanation of how his escapes from prison were achieved.
* ''[[A tour thro' the whole island of Great Britain|A tour thro' the whole island of Great Britain, divided into circuits or journies]]'' (1724–1727)
* ''[[The Political History of the Devil]]'' (1726)
* ''[[The Complete English Tradesman]]'' (1726)
* ''A treatise concerning the use and abuse of the marriage bed... (1727)
* ''[[A Plan of the English Commerce]]'' (1728)

===Pamphlets or essays in prose===
* ''[[The Poor Man's Plea]]'' (1698)
* ''[[The History of the Kentish Petition]]'' (1701)
* ''[[The Shortest Way with the Dissenters]]'' (1702)
* ''[[The Great Law of Subordination Consider'd]]'' (1704)
* ''[[Giving Alms No Charity, and Employing the Poor]]'' (1704)
* ''[[An Appeal to Honour and Justice, Tho' it be of his Worst Enemies, by Daniel Defoe, Being a True Account of His Conduct in Publick Affairs]]'' (1715)
* ''A Vindication of the Press: Or, An Essay on the Usefulness of Writing, on Criticism, and the Qualification of Authors'' (1718)
* ''[[Every-body's Business, Is No-body's Business]]'' (1725)
* ''[[The Protestant Monastery]]'' (1726)
* ''[[Parochial Tyranny]]'' (1727)
* ''[[Augusta Triumphans]]'' (1728)
* ''[[Second Thoughts are Best]]'' (1729)
* ''[[An Essay Upon Literature]]'' (1726)
* ''[[Mere Nature Delineated]]'' (1726)
* ''[[Conjugal Lewdness]]'' (1727)

===Pamphlets or essays in verse===
* ''[[The True-Born Englishman]]: A Satyr'' (1701)
* ''Hymn to the Pillory'' (1703)
* ''An Essay on the Late Storm'' (1704)

===Some contested works attributed to Defoe===
* ''[[A Friendly Epistle by way of reproof from one of the people called Quakers, to T. B., a dealer in many words]]'' (1715).
* ''[[The King of Pirates]]'' (1719) – purporting to be an account of the pirate [[Henry Avery]].
* ''[[The Pirate Gow]]'' (1725) – an account of [[John Gow]].
* ''[[A General History of the Pyrates]]'' (1724, 1725, 1726, 1828) – published in two volumes by Charles Rivington, who had a shop near [[St. Paul's Cathedral]], London.  Published under the name of [[Captain Charles Johnson]], it sold in many editions.
* Captain Carleton's ''Memoirs of an English Officer'' (1728).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Baine |first1=Rodney M. |title=Daniel Defoe and Captain Carleton's ''Memoirs of an English Officer'' |journal=Texas Studies in Literature and Language |date=1972 |volume=13 |issue=4 |pages=613–627 |issn=0040-4691|jstor=40755201 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[Christian Davies|The life and adventures of Mrs. Christian Davies, commonly call'd Mother Ross]]'' (1740) – published anonymously; printed and sold by R. Montagu in London; and attributed to Defoe but more recently not accepted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Catalog entry: The life and adventures of Mrs. Christian Davies, commonly call'd Mother Ross; who, in several campaigns under King William and the late Duke of Marlborough, in the quality of a foot-soldier and dragoon, gave many signal proofs of an unparallell'd courage and personal bravery. Taken from her own mouth when a pensioner of Chelsea-Hospital, and known to be true by many who were engaged in those great scenes of action. |url=http://collections.soane.org/b10155 |website=Sir John Soane's Museum Collection Online |accessdate=16 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Apprentice complex]]
* [[Moubray House]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin|40em}}
* Backscheider, Paula R. ''Daniel Defoe: His Life'' (1989).
* Backscheider, Paula R. ''Daniel Defoe: Ambition and Innovation'' (UP of Kentucky, 2015).
* Baines, Paul. ''Daniel Defoe-Robinson Crusoe/Moll Flanders'' (Palgrave Macmillan, 2007).
* Di Renzo, Anthony. &quot;The complete English tradesman: Daniel Defoe and the emergence of business writing.&quot; ''Journal of technical writing and communication'' 28.4 (1998): 325–334.
* Furbank, Philip Nicholas, and William Robert Owens. ''A political biography of Daniel Defoe'' (Routledge, 2015). [https://www.questia.com/library/120093155/a-political-biography-of-daniel-defoe online]
* Gollapudi, Aparna. &quot;Personhood, Property Rights, and the Child in John Locke's Two Treatises of Government and Daniel Defoe's Fiction.&quot; ''Eighteenth-Century Fiction'' 28.1 (2015): 25–58.
* Gregg, Stephen H. ''Defoe's Writings and Manliness: Contrary Men'' (Routledge, 2016).
* Guilhamet, Leon. ''Defoe and the Whig Novel: A Reading of the Major Fiction'' (U of Delaware Press, 2010).
* Hammond, John R. ed. ''A Defoe companion'' (Macmillan, 1993).
* Marshall, Ashley. &quot;Fabricating Defoes: From Anonymous Hack to Master of Fictions.&quot; ''Eighteenth-Century Life'' 36.2 (2012): 1–35. Historiography
* Novak, Maximillian E. ''Daniel Defoe: Master of Fictions: His Life and Ideas'' (2001) [https://www.amazon.com/Daniel-Defoe-Master-Fictions-Ideas/dp/0198126867/  excerpt]
* O'Brien, John. &quot;The Character of Credit: Defoe's&quot; Lady Credit,&quot; The Fortunate Mistress, and the Resources of Inconsistency in Early Eighteenth-Century Britain.&quot; ''ELH'' 63.3 (1996): 603–631. [https://muse.jhu.edu/article/11339/summary online]
* Novak, Maximillian E. ''Realism, myth, and history in Defoe's fiction'' (U of Nebraska Press, 1983).
* Richetti, John. ''The Life of Daniel Defoe: A Critical Biography'' (2015).
* {{cite journal|jstor=513276|title=Defoe in the Fleet Prison|journal=The Review of English Studies|volume=22|issue=88|pages=451–455|last1=Rogers|first1=Pat|year=1971|doi=10.1093/res/XXII.88.451}}
* Sutherland, J.R. ''Defoe'' (Taylor &amp; Francis, 1950), older scholarly biography. [https://www.questia.com/library/429269/defoe online]
{{refend}}

===Primary sources===
* Defoe, Daniel. ''The best of Defoe's Review: an anthology'' (Columbia UP, 1951).
* W. R. Owens, and Philip Nicholas Furbank, eds. ''Political and economic writings of Daniel Defoe'' (Pickering &amp; Chatto, 2000).

== External links ==
{{Wikisource author}}
{{wikiquote}}
{{Commons category}}
* {{Gutenberg author |id=204}}
* {{FadedPage|id=DeFoe, Daniel|name=Daniel DeFoe|author=yes}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Daniel Defoe}}
* {{Librivox author |id=895}}
* [http://ufdc.ufl.edu/defoe Full online versions of various copies of Defoe's Robinson Crusoe and the Robinsonades]
* [http://www.literature.at/elib/index.php5?title=Daniel_Defoe_-_1660-1731#Information Full texts in German and English]{{Dead link|date=July 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }} – eLibrary Projekt (eLib)
* [http://www.visionofbritain.org.uk/text/contents_page.jsp?t_id=Defoe The Journeys of Daniel Defoe around Britain] (from a Vision of Britain)
* [http://www.geopoesia.ru/ru/main/stat-main/01-crusoe-en.html Russian toponyms in Daniel Defoe's novels]
* [http://www.worldcat.org/identities/lccn-n79-53974 Defoe, Daniel 1661?–1731 WorldCat Identity]
* [https://archive.org/details/systemofmagic00defo A System of Magick]
* [http://aaronskirboll.com ''The Thief-Taker Hangings: How Daniel Defoe, Jonathan Wild, and Jack Sheppard Captivated London and Created the Celebrity Criminal'' by Aaron Skirboll]

{{Daniel Defoe|state=expanded}}

{{Robinson Crusoe}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Defoe, Daniel}}
[[Category:Daniel Defoe| ]]
[[Category:1660 births]]
[[Category:1731 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Chadwell St Mary]]
[[Category:People from the City of London]]
[[Category:17th-century English people]]
[[Category:17th-century spies]]
[[Category:18th-century male writers]]
[[Category:18th-century English novelists]]
[[Category:18th-century spies]]
[[Category:Burials at Bunhill Fields]]
[[Category:English children's writers]]
[[Category:English essayists]]
[[Category:English male journalists]]
[[Category:English male novelists]]
[[Category:English pamphlet writers]]
[[Category:English Presbyterians]]
[[Category:English people of French descent]]
[[Category:English satirists]]
[[Category:English spies]]
[[Category:Haberdashers]]
[[Category:Male essayists]]
[[Category:Neoclassical writers]]</text>
      <sha1>l1gihkr0ovt3z3jq9wpmywirpsiihca</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
