  <page>
    <title>Dante Alighieri</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8169</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943191192</id>
      <parentid>943191158</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T12:12:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>CLCStudent</username>
        <id>26398660</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/93.64.186.130|93.64.186.130]] ([[User talk:93.64.186.130|talk]]) to last version by Deor</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Dante}}
{{short description|Italian poet}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=December 2019}}
{{Infobox writer
|name        = Dante Alighieri
|image       = Portrait de Dante.jpg
|caption     = [[wikt:posthumous|Posthumous]] portrait in [[tempera]]&lt;br&gt;by [[Sandro Botticelli]], 1495
|alt         = head-and-chest side portrait of Dante in red and white coat and cowl
|birth_date  = {{circa|1265}}
|birth_place = [[Florence]], [[Republic of Florence]]
|death_date  = September 13 or 14, 1321&lt;br&gt;(aged around 56)
|death_place = [[Ravenna]], [[Papal States]]
|occupation  = Statesman, poet, language theorist, [[political theory|political theorist]]
|nationality = Italian
|movement    = ''[[Dolce Stil Novo]]''
|period      = [[Late Middle Ages]]
|notableworks = ''[[Divine Comedy]]''
|language=Italian
}}

'''Durante di Alighiero degli Alighieri''' ({{IPA-it|duˈrante deʎʎ aliˈɡjɛːri|lang}}; {{lang-la|Dantes}}), commonly known by his pen name '''Dante Alighieri''' or [[Mononymous person|simply]] as '''Dante''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|d|ɑː|n|t|eɪ|,_|ˈ|d|æ|n|t|eɪ|,_|ˈ|d|æ|n|t|i}},&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.collinsdictionary.com/dictionary/english/dante|title=Dante|work=[[Collins English Dictionary]]|publisher=[[HarperCollins]]|accessdate=May 20, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/us/Dante &quot;Dante&quot;] (US) and {{Cite Oxford Dictionaries|Dante|accessdate=May 20, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;small&gt;also&lt;/small&gt; {{IPAc-en|US|ˈ|d|ɑː|n|t|i}},&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite Merriam-Webster|Dante|accessdate=May 20, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{IPA-it|ˈdante|lang}}; {{c.|1265}} – 1321)&lt;!--full dates in infobox--&gt;, was an [[Italian poetry|Italian poet]]. His ''[[Divine Comedy]]'', originally called {{lang|it|Comedìa}} (modern Italian: ''Commedia'') and later christened {{lang|it|Divina}} by [[Giovanni Boccaccio]], is widely considered the most important poem of the [[Middle Ages]] and the greatest literary work in the Italian language.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Bloom|first=Harold|authorlink=Harold Bloom|title=The Western Canon|url=https://archive.org/details/westerncanonbook00bloo|url-access=registration|year=1994}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Shaw|first1=Prue|title=Reading Dante: From Here to Eternity|date=2014|publisher=Liveright Publishing Corporation|location=New York|isbn=978-0-87140-742-9|pages=Introduction}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Late Middle Ages]], most poetry was written in [[Latin]], making it accessible only to the most educated readers. In ''[[De vulgari eloquentia]]'' (''On Eloquence in the Vernacular''), however, Dante defended the use of the [[vernacular]] in literature. He would even write in the [[Tuscan dialect]] for works such as ''[[La Vita Nuova|The New Life]]'' (1295) and the ''Divine Comedy''; this highly unorthodox choice set a precedent that important later Italian writers such as [[Petrarch]] and Boccaccio would follow.

Dante was instrumental in establishing the literature of Italy, and his depictions of [[Hell]], [[Purgatory]] and [[Heaven]] provided inspiration for the larger body of [[Western art]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Haller |first=Elizabeth K. |editor-first=Lister M. |editor-last=Matheson |title=Icons of the Middle Ages: Rulers, Writers, Rebels, and Saints |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rETxD8KcnUIC&amp;pg=PA244 |volume=1 |publisher=Greenwood |location=Santa Barbara, CA |date=2012 |page=244 |chapter=Dante Alighieri |isbn=978-0-313-34080-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Human accomplishment: the pursuit of excellence in the arts and sciences, 800 B.C. to 1950|last=A.|first=Murray, Charles|date=2003|publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=978-0-06-019247-1|edition=1st|location=New York|oclc=52047270|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/humanaccomplishm00murr}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is cited as an influence on [[John Milton]], [[Geoffrey Chaucer]] and [[Alfred, Lord Tennyson|Alfred Tennyson]], among many others. In addition, the first use of the interlocking three-line rhyme scheme, or the ''[[terza rima]]'', is attributed to him. He is described as the &quot;father&quot; of the Italian language,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title =The Cambridge Companion to Dante's ‘Commedia'|editor1-first =Zygmunt G.|editor1-last =Barański|editor2-first =Simon|editor2-last =Gilson|publisher =Cambridge University Press|date =2018|page =108|isbn =9781108421294}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in Italy, he is often referred to as ''{{lang|it|il Sommo Poeta}}'' (&quot;the Supreme Poet&quot;). Dante, Petrarch, and Boccaccio are also called the {{lang|it|tre corone}} (&quot;three crowns&quot;) of Italian literature.

==Life==
===Early life===
Dante was born in [[Florence]], [[Republic of Florence]], in what is now Italy. The exact date of his birth is unknown, although it is generally believed to be around 1265. This can be deduced from autobiographic allusions in the ''[[Divine Comedy]].'' Its first section, the ''[[Inferno (Dante)|Inferno]],'' begins, ''&quot;Nel mezzo del cammin di nostra vita&quot;'' (&quot;Midway upon the journey of our life&quot;), implying that Dante was around 35 years old, since the average lifespan according to the Bible (Psalm 89:10&lt;!-- do not change to Ps. 90; in the Vulgate, as specified, the chapter is 89 --&gt;, Vulgate) is 70 years; and since his imaginary travel to the netherworld took place in 1300, he was most probably born around 1265. Some verses of the ''Paradiso'' section of the ''Divine Comedy'' also provide a possible clue that he was born under the sign of [[Gemini (astrology)|Gemini]]: &quot;As I revolved with the eternal twins, I saw revealed, from hills to river outlets, the threshing-floor that makes us so ferocious&quot; (XXII&amp;nbsp;151–154). In 1265, the sun was in Gemini between approximately May 11 and June 11 ([[Julian calendar]]).&lt;ref&gt;His birth date is listed as &quot;probably in the end of May&quot; by Robert Hollander in &quot;Dante&quot; in ''[[Dictionary of the Middle Ages]],'' volume&amp;nbsp;4. According to Boccaccio, the poet himself said he was born in May. See &quot;Alighieri, Dante&quot; in the ''Dizionario Biografico degli Italiani.''&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Dante-alighieri.jpg|thumb|''Dante Alighieri'', attributed to [[Giotto di Bondone|Giotto]], in the chapel of the [[Bargello]] palace in Florence. This oldest picture of Dante was painted just prior to his exile and has since been heavily restored.]]
[[File:Dante alighieri, Palazzo dei Giudici.jpg|thumb|upright|left|Portrait of Dante, from a fresco in the Palazzo dei Giudici, Florence]]
[[Giovanni Boccaccio]] described Dante's appearance and demeanor as follows: &quot;the poet was of middle height, and in his later years he walked somewhat bent over, with a grave and gentle gait. He was clad always in most seemly attire, such as befitted his ripe years. His face was long, his nose aquiline, and his eyes big rather than small. His jaws were large, and his lower lip protruded. He had a brown complexion, his hair and beard were thick, black, and curly, and his countenance was always melancholy and thoughtful.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Holbrook, Richard. &quot;Portraits of Dante from Giotto to Raffael: a critical study, with a concise iconography&quot;. 1911. London: P.L. Warner; Boston, New York, Houghton Mifflin company. p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt;

Dante claimed that his family descended from the ancient Romans (''Inferno'', XV, 76), but the earliest relative he could mention by name was [[Cacciaguida]] degli Elisei (''Paradiso'', XV, 135), born no earlier than about 1100. Dante's father, Alighiero&lt;ref name=Trecc/&gt; or [[Alighiero di Bellincione]], was a White [[Guelphs and Ghibellines|Guelph]] who suffered no reprisals after the [[Guelphs and Ghibellines|Ghibellines]] won the [[Battle of Montaperti]] in the middle of the 13th&amp;nbsp;century. This suggests that Alighiero or his family may have enjoyed some protective prestige and status, although some suggest that the politically inactive Alighiero was of such low standing that he was not considered worth exiling.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Santagata |first=Marco |date=2012 |title=Dante: Il romanzo della sua vita |url= |location=Milan |publisher=Mondadori |page=21 |isbn=978-88-04-62026-6 |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dante's family was loyal to the Guelphs, a political alliance that supported the [[Papacy]] and which was involved in complex opposition to the Ghibellines, who were backed by the [[Holy Roman Emperor]]. The poet's mother was Bella, probably a member of the Abati family.&lt;ref name=Trecc/&gt; She died when Dante was not yet ten years old, and Alighiero soon married again, to Lapa di Chiarissimo Cialuffi. It is uncertain whether he really married her, since widowers were socially limited in such matters, but this woman definitely bore him two children, Dante's half-brother Francesco and half-sister Tana (Gaetana). When Dante was 12, he was promised in marriage to Gemma di Manetto Donati, daughter of Manetto Donati, member of the powerful Donati family.&lt;ref name=Trecc&gt;{{cite book|work=Dizionario Biografico degli Italiani|publisher=[[Enciclopedia Italiana]]|url=http://www.treccani.it/enciclopedia/dante-alighieri_(Dizionario-Biografico)/|title=Alighieri, Dante|first=S.A|last=Chimenz|language=Italian|accessdate=March 7, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Contracting marriages at this early age was quite common and involved a formal ceremony, including contracts signed before a [[civil law notary|notary]]. But by this time Dante had fallen in love with another, [[Beatrice Portinari]] (known also as Bice), whom he first met when he was only nine. Years after his marriage to Gemma he claims to have met Beatrice again; he wrote several sonnets to Beatrice but never mentioned Gemma in any of his poems. The exact date of his marriage is not known: the only certain information is that, before his exile in 1301, he had three children (Pietro, Jacopo and Antonia).&lt;ref name=Trecc/&gt;

Dante fought with the Guelph cavalry at the [[Battle of Campaldino]] (June 11, 1289).&lt;ref name=&quot;Davenport2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Davenport|first=John|title=Dante: Poet, Author, and Proud Florentine|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MWWKW15MjqMC&amp;pg=PA53|year=2005|publisher=Infobase Publishing|isbn=978-1-4381-0415-7|page=53|accessdate=March 7, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; This victory brought about a reformation of the [[Republic of Florence|Florentine]] constitution. To take any part in public life, one had to enroll in one of the city's many commercial or artisan guilds, so Dante entered the Physicians' and Apothecaries' Guild. In the following years, his name is occasionally recorded as speaking or voting in the various councils of the republic. A substantial portion of minutes from such meetings in the years 1298–1300 was lost, however, so the true extent of Dante's participation in the city's councils is uncertain.

Gemma bore Dante several children. Although several others subsequently claimed to be his offspring, it is likely that only [[Jacopo Alighieri|Jacopo]], Pietro, Giovanni, and Antonia were his actual children. Antonia later became a nun, taking the name Sister Beatrice.

===Education and poetry===
{{More citations needed section|date=December 2015}}
[[File:DanteFresco.jpg|thumb|upright|Mural of Dante in the [[Uffizi]], Florence, by [[Andrea del Castagno]], c. 1450]]

Not much is known about Dante's education; he presumably studied at home or in a chapter school attached to a church or monastery in Florence. It is known that he studied [[Tuscany|Tuscan]] poetry and that he admired the compositions of the Bolognese poet [[Guido Guinizelli]]—whom in ''Purgatorio'' XXVI he characterized as his &quot;father&quot;—at a time when the [[Sicilian School]] (''Scuola poetica Siciliana''), a cultural group from [[Sicily]], was becoming known in Tuscany. His interests brought him to discover the [[Occitan|Provençal]] poetry of the [[troubadours]], such as [[Arnaut Daniel]], and the Latin writers of [[classical antiquity]], including [[Cicero]], [[Ovid]] and especially [[Virgil]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.poets.org/poetsorg/poet/dante-alighieri |title=Dante Alighieri |author=&lt;!--Not stated--&gt; |date= |website=poets.org |publisher=Academy of American Poets |access-date=20 December 2019 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dante said he first met [[Beatrice Portinari]], daughter of [[Folco Portinari]], at age nine, and claimed to have fallen in love with her &quot;[[Love at first sight|at first sight]]&quot;, apparently without even talking with her.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Delphi Complete Works of Dante Alighieri |edition= Illustrated |volume=6 |author=Dante Alighieri |publisher= Delphi Classics |year=2013 |isbn=978-1-909496-19-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; He saw her frequently after age 18, often exchanging greetings in the street, but never knew her well. In effect, he set an example of so-called [[courtly love]], a phenomenon developed in French and Provençal poetry of prior centuries. Dante's experience of such love was typical, but his expression of it was unique. It was in the name of this love that Dante left his imprint on the ''[[dolce stil novo]]'' (''sweet new style,'' a term which Dante himself coined), and he would join other contemporary poets and writers in exploring never-before-emphasized aspects of love (''Amore''). Love for Beatrice (as [[Petrarch]] would show for Laura somewhat differently) would be his reason for poetry and for living, together with political passions. In many of his poems, she is depicted as semi-divine, watching over him constantly and providing spiritual instruction, sometimes harshly. When Beatrice died in 1290, Dante sought refuge in Latin literature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= Names and Naming in Young Adult Literature |volume=27 |author= Alleen Pace Nilsen, Don L.F. Nilsen |publisher= Scarecrow Press |year= 2007 |isbn= 978-0-8108-6685-0 |page= 133}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[Convivio]]'' chronicles his having read [[Boethius]]'s ''[[The Consolation of Philosophy|De consolatione philosophiae]]'' and Cicero's ''[[Laelius de Amicitia|De Amicitia]].'' He then dedicated himself to philosophical studies at religious schools like the Dominican one in [[Santa Maria Novella]]. He took part in the disputes that the two principal [[mendicant order|mendicant]] orders ([[Franciscan]] and [[Dominican Order|Dominican]]) publicly or indirectly held in Florence, the former explaining the doctrines of the mystics and of St. [[Bonaventure]], the latter expounding on the theories of St. [[Thomas Aquinas]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= The Paradiso of Dante Alighieri |url= https://archive.org/details/paradisoofdantea00dantrich |author= Dante Alighieri |editor= Philip Henry Wicksteed, Herman Oelsner |edition= fifth |publisher= J.M. Dent and Company |year= 1904 |page= [https://archive.org/details/paradisoofdantea00dantrich/page/129 129]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At 18, Dante met [[Guido Cavalcanti]], [[Lapo Gianni]], [[Cino da Pistoia]] and soon after [[Brunetto Latini]]; together they became the leaders of the ''dolce stil novo.'' Brunetto later received special mention in the ''Divine Comedy'' (''Inferno'', XV, 28) for what he had taught Dante: ''Nor speaking less on that account I go With Ser Brunetto, and I ask who are his most known and most eminent companions.''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= Critical Companion to Dante |author= Jay Ruud |publisher= Infobase Publishing |year= 2008 |isbn= 978-1-4381-0841-4 |page= 138}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some fifty poetical commentaries by Dante are known (the so-called ''[[The Rime|Rime]],'' rhymes), others being included in the later ''Vita Nuova'' and ''Convivio.'' Other studies are reported, or deduced from ''Vita Nuova'' or the ''Comedy,'' regarding painting and music.

===Florence and politics===
{{More citations needed section|date=December 2015}}
{{further|Guelphs and Ghibellines}}
[[File:Dante Alighieri01.jpg|thumb|upright|Statue of Dante at the Uffizi]]
[[File:Dante Alighieri Florence Firenze JBU01.JPG|thumb|upright|[[Monument to Dante|Statue of Dante]] in the [[Piazza Santa Croce]] in Florence, [[Enrico Pazzi]], 1865]]
Dante, like most Florentines of his day, was embroiled in the [[Guelphs and Ghibellines|Guelph–Ghibelline conflict]]. He fought in the [[Battle of Campaldino]] (June 11, 1289), with the Florentine Guelphs against [[Arezzo]] Ghibellines;&lt;ref name=&quot;Davenport2005&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=DASM&gt;{{cite web |title=Guelphs and Ghibellines |url=http://www.dantemass.org/html/guelphs-and-ghibellines.html |publisher=Dante Alighieri Society of Massachusetts |accessdate=December 30, 2015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151212042335/http://www.dantemass.org/html/guelphs-and-ghibellines.html |archivedate=December 12, 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt; then in 1294 he was among the escorts of [[Charles Martel of Anjou]] (grandson of [[Charles&amp;nbsp;I of Anjou]]) while he was in Florence. To further his political career, he became a pharmacist. He did not intend to practice as one, but a law issued in 1295 required nobles aspiring to public office to be enrolled in one of the Corporazioni delle Arti e dei Mestieri, so Dante obtained admission to the Apothecaries' Guild. This profession was not inappropriate since at that time books were sold from apothecaries' shops. As a politician, he accomplished little but held various offices over some years in a city rife with political unrest.

After defeating the Ghibellines, the Guelphs divided into two factions: the White Guelphs (''Guelfi Bianchi'')—Dante's party, led by Vieri dei Cerchi—and the Black Guelphs (''Guelfi Neri''), led by [[Corso Donati]]. Although the split was along family lines at first, ideological differences arose based on opposing views of the papal role in Florentine affairs, with the Blacks supporting the Pope and the Whites wanting more freedom from Rome. The Whites took power first and expelled the Blacks. In response, [[Pope Boniface VIII]] planned a military occupation of Florence. In 1301, [[Charles of Valois]], brother of King [[Philip IV of France]], was expected to visit Florence because the Pope had appointed him peacemaker for [[Tuscany]]. But the city's government had treated the Pope's ambassadors badly a few weeks before, seeking independence from papal influence. It was believed that Charles had received other unofficial instructions, so the council sent a delegation to Rome to ascertain the Pope's intentions. Dante was one of the delegates.

===Exile and death===
Pope Boniface quickly dismissed the other delegates and asked Dante alone to remain in Rome. At the same time (November 1, 1301), Charles of Valois entered Florence with the Black Guelphs, who in the next six days destroyed much of the city and killed many of their enemies. A new Black Guelph government was installed, and [[Cante dei Gabrielli]] da [[Gubbio]] was appointed ''[[podestà]]'' of the city. In March 1302, Dante, a White Guelph by affiliation, along with the [[Gherardini family]], was condemned to exile for two years and ordered to pay a large fine.&lt;ref&gt;[[Dino Compagni]], ''Cronica delle cose occorrenti ne' tempi suoi''&lt;/ref&gt; Dante was accused of corruption and financial wrongdoing by the Black Guelphs for the time that Dante was serving as city prior (Florence's highest position) for two months in 1300.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Harrison, &quot;Dante on Trial&quot;, ''NY Review of Books'', February 19, 2015, pp. 36–37&lt;/ref&gt; The poet was still in Rome in 1302 where the Pope, who had backed the Black Guelphs, had &quot;suggested&quot; that Dante stay. Florence under the Black Guelphs therefore considered Dante an absconder.&lt;ref&gt;Harrison, p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt; Dante did not pay the fine, in part because he believed he was not guilty and in part because all his assets in Florence had been seized by the Black Guelphs. He was condemned to perpetual exile; if he returned to Florence without paying the fine, he could have been burned at the stake. (In June 2008, nearly seven centuries after his death, the city council of Florence passed a motion rescinding Dante's sentence.)&lt;ref&gt;Malcolm Moore [https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/newstopics/howaboutthat/2145378/Dante's-infernal-crimes-forgiven.html &quot;Dante's infernal crimes forgiven&quot;], ''The Daily Telegraph'', June 17, 2008. Retrieved June 18, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Antonio Cotti - Dante a Verona.jpg|thumbnail|left|''Dante in Verona'', by Antonio Cotti]]
He took part in several attempts by the White Guelphs to regain power, but these failed due to treachery. Dante, bitter at the treatment he received from his enemies, also grew disgusted with the infighting and ineffectiveness of his erstwhile allies and vowed to become a party of one. He went to [[Verona, Italy|Verona]] as a guest of [[Bartolomeo I della Scala]], then moved to [[Sarzana]] in Liguria. Later he is supposed to have lived in [[Lucca]] with a woman called Gentucca, who made his stay comfortable (and was later gratefully mentioned in ''Purgatorio'', XXIV, 37). Some speculative sources claim he visited Paris between 1308 and 1310, and other sources even less trustworthy took him to [[Oxford]]: these claims, first occurring in [[Giovanni Boccaccio|Boccaccio]]'s book on Dante several decades after his death, seem inspired by readers who were impressed with the poet's wide learning and erudition. Evidently, Dante's command of philosophy and his literary interests deepened in exile and when he was no longer busy with the day-to-day business of Florentine domestic politics, and this is evidenced in his prose writings in this period, but there is no real evidence that he ever left Italy. Dante's ''Immensa Dei dilectione testante'' to Henry VII of Luxembourg confirms his residence &quot;beneath the springs of Arno, near Tuscany&quot; in March 1311.

In 1310, Holy Roman Emperor [[Henry VII, Holy Roman Emperor|Henry VII]] of [[Luxembourg]] marched into Italy at the head of 5,000 troops. Dante saw in him a new [[Charlemagne]] who would restore the office of the Holy Roman Emperor to its former glory and also retake Florence from the Black Guelphs. He wrote to Henry and several Italian princes, demanding that they destroy the Black Guelphs. Mixing religion and private concerns in his writings, he invoked the worst anger of God against his city and suggested several particular targets that were also his personal enemies. It was during this time that he wrote ''[[De Monarchia]]'', proposing a [[universal monarchy]] under Henry VII.

At some point during his exile, he conceived of the ''Comedy'', but the date is uncertain. The work is much more assured and on a larger scale than anything he had produced in Florence; it is likely he would have undertaken such a work only after he realized his political ambitions, which had been central to him up to his banishment, had been halted for some time, possibly forever. It is also noticeable that Beatrice has returned to his imagination with renewed force and with a wider meaning than in the ''Vita Nuova''; in ''Convivio'' (written c. 1304–07) he had declared that the memory of this youthful romance belonged to the past.

An early outside indication that the poem was underway is a notice by Francesco da Barberino, tucked into his ''Documenti d'Amore'' (''Lessons of Love''), written probably in 1314 or early 1315. Speaking of Virgil, Francesco notes in appreciative words that Dante followed the Roman classic in a poem called &quot;Comedy&quot; and that the setting of this poem (or part of it) was the underworld; i.e., hell.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.bookrags.com/tandf/francesco-daccorso-tf/ Bookrags.com] and Tigerstedt, E.N. 1967, ''Dante; Tiden Mannen Verket'' (''Dante; The Age, the Man, the Work''), Bonniers, Stockholm, 1967. {{dead link|date=June 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt; The brief note gives no incontestable indication that he himself had seen or read even the ''Inferno'' or that this part had been published at the time, but it indicates composition was well underway and that the sketching of the poem might have begun some years before. (It has been suggested that a knowledge of Dante's work also underlies some of the illuminations in Francesco da Barberino's earlier ''Officiolum'' [c. 1305–08], a manuscript that came to light only in 2003.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.spolia.it/online/en/argomenti/letterature_romanze/filologia/2003/barberino.htm|title=L′''Officiolum'' ritrovato di Francesco da Barberino|author=Fabio M. Bertolo|year= 2003|work=Spolia&amp;nbsp;– Journal of Medieval Studies|accessdate=August 18, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;) We know that the ''Inferno'' had been published by 1317; this is established by quoted lines interspersed in the margins of contemporary dated records from [[Bologna]], but there is no certainty as to whether the three parts of the poem were each published in full or, rather, a few cantos at a time. ''Paradiso'' seems to have been published posthumously.

In Florence, [[Baldo d'Aguglione]] pardoned most of the White Guelphs in exile and allowed them to return. However, Dante had gone too far in his violent letters to ''Arrigo'' (Henry VII) and his sentence was not revoked.

[[File:Monument to Dante (Verona).jpg|thumb|upright|Statue of Dante Alighieri in Verona]]
In 1312 Henry assaulted Florence and defeated the Black Guelphs, but there is no evidence that Dante was involved. Some say he refused to participate in the assault on his city by a foreigner; others suggest that he had become unpopular with the White Guelphs, too, and that any trace of his passage had carefully been removed. Henry VII died (from a fever) in 1313, and with him any hope for Dante to see Florence again. He returned to Verona, where [[Cangrande I della Scala]] allowed him to live in certain security and, presumably, in a fair degree of prosperity. Cangrande was admitted to Dante's Paradise (''Paradiso'', XVII, 76).

During the period of his exile Dante corresponded with Dominican theologian Fr. [[Nicholas Brunacci]] OP [1240–1322] who had been a student of [[Thomas Aquinas]] at the Santa Sabina ''studium'' in Rome, later at Paris,&lt;ref name=&quot;aquinatis.blogspot.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aquinatis.blogspot.com/2008/05/vida-de-santo-toms-de-aquino.html |title=Aquinatis: Vida de Santo Tomás de Aquino |website=Aquinatis.blogspot.com |accessdate=March 27, 2017|date=May 22, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.brunacci.it/s--tommaso.html |title=Le famiglie Brunacci |website=Brunacci.it |accessdate=March 27, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; and of [[Albert the Great]] at the Cologne ''studium''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sVP3vBmDktQC&amp;pg=PA85&amp;lpg=PA85&amp;dq=brunacci#v=onepage&amp;q=brunacci&amp;f=false |title=History of Italian Philosophy: VIBS |author=Eugenio Garin |page=85 |accessdate=March 27, 2017|isbn=978-90-420-2321-5 |year=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Brunacci became lector at the Santa Sabina ''studium'', forerunner of the [[Pontifical University of Saint Thomas Aquinas]], and later served in the [[Roman curia|papal curia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Frater Nicolaus Brunatii [† 1322] sacerdos et predicator gratiosus, fuit lector castellanus, arectinus, perusinus, urbevetanus et romanus apud Sanctam Sabinam tempore quo papa erat in Urbe, viterbiensis et florentinus in studio generali legens ibidem annis tribus (Cr Pg 37v). Cuius sollicita procuratione conventus perusinus meruit habere gratiam a summo pontifice papa Benedicto XI ecclesiam scilicet et parrochiam Sancti Stephani tempore quo [maggio 13041 ipse prior actu in Perusio erat (Cr Pg 38r)|url=http://www.e-theca.net/emiliopanella/lector12.htm|website=E-theca.net|accessdate=May 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1315, Florence was forced by [[Uguccione della Faggiuola]] (the military officer controlling the town) to grant an amnesty to those in exile, including Dante. But for this, Florence required public penance in addition to a heavy fine. Dante refused, preferring to remain in exile. When Uguccione defeated Florence, Dante's death sentence was commuted to house arrest on condition that he go to Florence to swear he would never enter the town again. He refused to go, and his death sentence was confirmed and extended to his sons. He still hoped late in life that he might be invited back to Florence on honorable terms. For Dante, exile was nearly a form of death, stripping him of much of his identity and his heritage. He addressed the pain of exile in ''Paradiso'', XVII (55–60), where Cacciaguida, his great-great-grandfather, warns him what to expect:
{{Verse translation|
{{lang|it|... Tu lascerai ogne cosa diletta
più caramente; e questo è quello strale
che l'arco de lo essilio pria saetta.
Tu proverai sì come sa di sale
lo pane altrui, e come è duro calle
lo scendere e 'l salir per l'altrui scale ...}}
|
... You shall leave everything you love most:
this is the arrow that the bow of exile
shoots first. You are to know the bitter taste
of others' bread, how salty it is, and know
how hard a path it is for one who goes
ascending and descending others' stairs ...}}

As for the hope of returning to Florence, he describes it as if he had already accepted its impossibility (in ''Paradiso'', XXV, 1–9):
{{Verse translation|
{{lang|it|Se mai continga che 'l poema sacro
al quale ha posto mano e cielo e terra,
sì che m'ha fatto per molti anni macro,
vinca la crudeltà che fuor mi serra
del bello ovile ov'io dormi' agnello,
nimico ai lupi che li danno guerra;
con altra voce omai, con altro vello
ritornerò poeta, e in sul fonte
del mio battesmo prenderò 'l cappello ...}}
|
If it ever comes to pass that the sacred poem
to which both heaven and earth have set their hand
so as to have made me lean for many years
should overcome the cruelty that bars me
from the fair sheepfold where I slept as a lamb,
an enemy to the wolves that make war on it,
with another voice now and other fleece
I shall return a poet and at the font
of my baptism take the [[laurel wreath|laurel crown]] ...}}

{{multiple image
| align = right
| image1 = Dante Alieghri tomb in Ravenna (exterior).jpg
| width1 = 155
| alt1 = 
| caption1 = 
| image2 = Dante Alieghri tomb in Ravenna (interior).jpg
| width2 = 165
| alt2 = 
| caption2 = 
| footer = Dante's tomb exterior and interior in Ravenna, built in 1780
}}
Alighieri accepted Prince [[Guido II da Polenta|Guido Novello da Polenta]]'s invitation to [[Ravenna]] in 1318. He finished ''Paradiso'' and died in 1321 (aged 56) while returning to Ravenna from a diplomatic mission to Venice, possibly of [[malaria]] contracted there. He was buried in Ravenna at the Church of San Pier Maggiore (later called [[Basilica of San Francesco, Ravenna|Basilica di San Francesco]]). Bernardo Bembo, [[praetor]] of [[Venice]], erected [[Tomb of Dante|a tomb for him]] in 1483.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.theflorentine.net/art-culture/2017/04/dante-ravenna-florence-battle-of-bones/, Dante’s Tomb&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://www.italymagazine.com/news/dantes-tomb, Dante’s Tomb&lt;/ref&gt;

On the grave, a verse of [[Bernardo Canaccio]], a friend of Dante, is dedicated to Florence:
{{Verse translation|
{{lang|it|parvi Florentia mater amoris}}
|
Florence, mother of little love}}

==Legacy==
The first formal biography of Dante was the ''Vita di Dante'' (also known as ''Trattatello in laude di Dante''), written after 1348 by [[Giovanni Boccaccio]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/04628a.htm|title=Dante Alighieri|publisher=The Catholic Encyclopedia|accessdate=May 2, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although several statements and episodes of it have been deemed unreliable on the basis of modern research, an earlier account of Dante's life and works had been included in the ''[[Nuova Cronica]]'' of the Florentine chronicler [[Giovanni Villani]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Vauchez|first=André|last2=Dobson|first2=Richard Barrie|last3=Lapidge|first3=Michael|title=Encyclopedia of the Middle Ages|year=2000|publisher=Fitzroy Dearborn Publishers|location=Chicago|page=1517}}; {{cite book|last=Caesar|first=Michael|title=Dante, the Critical Heritage, 1314(?)–1870|year=1989|publisher=Routledge|location=London|page=xi}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Santa Croce Firenze Apr 2008 (17).JPG|thumb|upright|left|[[Cenotaph]] in [[Basilica di Santa Croce di Firenze|Basilica of Santa Croce, Florence]]]]
Florence eventually came to regret Dante's exile, and the city made repeated requests for the return of his remains. The custodians of the body in Ravenna refused, at one point going so far as to conceal the bones in a false wall of the monastery. Nonetheless, a tomb was built for him in Florence in 1829, in the [[Basilica di Santa Croce di Firenze|Basilica of Santa Croce]]. That [[cenotaph|tomb has been empty]] ever since, with Dante's body remaining in Ravenna, far from the land he had loved so dearly. The front of his tomb in Florence reads ''Onorate l'altissimo poeta''—which roughly translates as &quot;Honor the most exalted poet&quot;. The phrase is a quote from the fourth canto of the ''Inferno,'' depicting Virgil's welcome as he returns among the great ancient poets spending eternity in limbo. The ensuing line, ''L'ombra sua torna, ch'era dipartita'' (&quot;his spirit, which had left us, returns&quot;), is poignantly absent from the empty tomb.

[[File:Dante.deathmask.jpg|thumb|upright|Recreated death mask of Dante Alighieri in Palazzo Vecchio, Florence]]
A copy of Dante's so-called death mask has been displayed since 1911 in the [[Palazzo Vecchio]]; scholars today believe it is not a true death mask and was probably carved in 1483, perhaps by Pietro and Tullio Lombardo.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.florenceinferno.com/dante-death-mask/, DANTE DEATH MASK&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://listverse.com/2014/10/22/10-controversial-death-masks-of-famous-people/, 10 Controversial Death Masks Of Famous People&lt;/ref&gt;

Italy's first dreadnought battleship was completed in 1913 and named ''[[Italian battleship Dante Alighieri|Dante Alighieri]]'' in honor of him.

On April 30, 1921, in honor of the 600th anniversary of Dante's death, [[Pope Benedict XV]] promulgated an encyclical named ''[[In praeclara summorum]]'', calling him one &quot;of the many celebrated geniuses of whom the Catholic faith can boast&quot; and the &quot;pride and glory of humanity&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/benedict_xv/encyclicals/documents/hf_ben-xv_enc_30041921_in-praeclara-summorum_en.html &quot;''In praeclara summorum'': Encyclical of Pope Benedict XV on Dante&quot;]. The Holy See. Retrieved November 7, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, a reconstruction of Dante's face was undertaken in a collaborative project. Artists from Pisa University and engineers at the University of Bologna at [[Forlì]] constructed the model, portraying Dante's features as somewhat different from what was once thought.&lt;ref name=&quot;nosejob&quot;&gt;{{cite news|first=Philip|last=Pullella|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/oddlyEnoughNews/idUSL1171092320070112|title=Dante gets posthumous nose job – 700 years on|work=Statesman|agency=Reuters|date=January 12, 2007 |accessdate=November 5, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Benazzi | first1 = S | year = 2009 | title = The Face of the Poet Dante Alighieri, Reconstructed by Virtual Modeling and Forensic Anthropology Techniques | journal = Journal of Archaeological Science | volume = 36 | issue = 2| pages = 278–283 | doi = 10.1016/j.jas.2008.09.006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, the Municipality of Florence officially apologized for expelling Dante 700 years earlier.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.upi.com/Florence-sorry-for-banishing-Dante/23851217358714/ Florence sorry for banishing Dante]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://content.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,1828023,00.html|title=A City's Infernal Dante Dispute|last=Israely|first=Jeff|date=July 31, 2008 |work=Time|accessdate=September 25, 2018 |issn=0040-781X}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/7461459.stm|title=Florence 'to revoke Dante exile' |last=Duff |first=Mark|date=June 18, 2008|publisher=BBC}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.repubblica.it/2008/05/sezioni/spettacoli_e_cultura/dante-riabilitazione/dante-riabilitazione/dante-riabilitazione.html|title=Firenze riabilita Dante Alighieri: L'iniziativa a 700 anni dall'esilio |date=March 30, 2008|work=La Repubblica}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A celebration was held in 2015 at Italy's [[Senate of the Republic (Italy)|Senate of the Republic]] for the 750th anniversary of Dante's birth. It included a commemoration from [[Pope Francis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://press.vatican.va/content/salastampa/en/bollettino/pubblico/2015/05/04/0333/00726.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150504193814/http://press.vatican.va/content/salastampa/en/bollettino/pubblico/2015/05/04/0333/00726.html |archivedate=May 4, 2015 |title=Messaggio del Santo Padre al Presidente del Pontificio Consiglio della Cultura in occasione della celebrazione del 750° anniversario della nascita di Dante Alighieri |publisher=Press.vatican.va |accessdate=October 21, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.microsofttranslator.com/BV.aspx?ref=IE8Activity&amp;a=http%3A%2F%2Fpress.vatican.va%2Fcontent%2Fsalastampa%2Fen%2Fbollettino%2Fpubblico%2F2015%2F05%2F04%2F0333%2F00726.html |title=Translator |publisher=Microsofttranslator.com |accessdate=October 21, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Works==
{{see also|Category:Works by Dante Alighieri}}
[[File:Alighieri - Divina Commedia, Nel mille quatro cento septe et due nel quarto mese adi cinque et sei - 2384293 id00022000 Scan00006.jpg|thumb|upright|''Divina Commedia'' (1472)]]
[[File:Dante Luca.jpg|thumb|Dante Alighieri, detail from [[Luca Signorelli]]'s fresco, [[Chapel of San Brizio]], [[Orvieto Cathedral]]]]
[[File:DanteDetail.jpg|thumb|left|Dante, poised between the mountain of purgatory and the city of Florence, displays the [[incipit]] ''Nel mezzo del cammin di nostra vita'' in a detail of [[Domenico di Michelino]]'s painting, Florence, 1465]]

The ''[[Divine Comedy]]'' describes Dante's journey through [[Divine Comedy#Inferno|Hell]] (''Inferno''), [[Divine Comedy#Purgatorio|Purgatory]] (''Purgatorio''), and [[9 spheres of heaven|Paradise]] (''Paradiso''); he is first guided by the Roman poet [[Virgil]] and then by [[Beatrice Portinari|Beatrice]], the subject of his love (and of another of his works, ''[[La Vita Nuova]]''). Of the books, ''Purgatorio'' is arguably the most lyrical of the three, referring to more contemporary poets and artists than ''Inferno''; ''Paradiso'' is the most heavily theological, and the one in which, many scholars have argued, the ''Divine Comedy'''s most beautiful and mystic passages appear (e.g., when Dante looks into the face of God: &quot;all'alta fantasia qui mancò possa&quot;—&quot;at this high moment, ability failed my capacity to describe,&quot; ''Paradiso,'' XXXIII, 142).

With its seriousness of purpose, its literary stature and the range—both stylistic and thematic—of its content, the ''Comedy'' soon became a cornerstone in the evolution of Italian as an established literary language. Dante was more aware than most early Italian writers of the variety of Italian dialects and of the need to create a literature and a unified literary language beyond the limits of Latin writing at the time; in that sense, he is a forerunner of the [[Renaissance]], with its effort to create vernacular literature in competition with earlier classical writers. Dante's in-depth knowledge (within the limits of his time) of Roman antiquity, and his evident admiration for some aspects of pagan Rome, also point forward to the 15th century. Ironically, while he was widely honored in the centuries after his death, the ''Comedy'' slipped out of fashion among men of letters: too medieval, too rough and tragic, and not stylistically refined in the respects that the high and late Renaissance came to demand of literature.

He wrote the ''Comedy'' in a language he called &quot;Italian&quot;, in some sense an amalgamated literary language mostly based on the regional dialect of Tuscany, but with some elements of Latin and other regional dialects.&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;&gt;{{Britannica|151164|Dante}}&lt;/ref&gt; He deliberately aimed to reach a readership throughout Italy including laymen, clergymen and other poets. By creating a poem of epic structure and philosophic purpose, he established that the Italian language was suitable for the highest sort of expression. In French, Italian is sometimes nicknamed ''la langue de Dante''. Publishing in the vernacular language marked Dante as one of the first in [[Roman Catholic]] Western Europe (among others such as [[Geoffrey Chaucer]] and [[Giovanni Boccaccio]]) to break free from standards of publishing in only Latin (the language of [[liturgy]], history and scholarship in general, but often also of lyric poetry). This break set a precedent and allowed more literature to be published for a wider audience, setting the stage for greater levels of literacy in the future. However, unlike Boccaccio, [[John Milton|Milton]] or [[Ludovico Ariosto|Ariosto]], Dante did not really become an author read across Europe until the Romantic era. To the Romantics, Dante, like [[Homer]] and [[William Shakespeare|Shakespeare]], was a prime example of the &quot;original genius&quot; who set his own rules, created persons of overpowering stature and depth, and went far beyond any imitation of the patterns of earlier masters; and who, in turn, could not truly be imitated.{{Citation needed|date=February 2020}} Throughout the 19th century, Dante's reputation grew and solidified; and by 1865, the 600th anniversary of his birth, he had become established as one of the greatest literary icons of the Western world.

New readers often wonder how such a serious work may be called a &quot;comedy&quot;. [[Comedy#Etymology|In the classical sense]] the word ''comedy'' refers to works which reflect belief in an ordered universe, in which events tend toward not only a happy or amusing ending but one influenced by a Providential will that orders all things to an ultimate good. By this meaning of the word, as Dante himself wrote in a letter to [[Cangrande I della Scala]], the progression of the pilgrimage from Hell to Paradise is the paradigmatic expression of comedy, since the work begins with the pilgrim's moral confusion and ends with the vision of God.

Dante's other works include ''[[Convivio]]'' (&quot;The Banquet&quot;),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.danteonline.it/english/opere.asp?idope=2&amp;idlang=UK|title=Banquet|publisher=Dante online|accessdate=September 2, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; a collection of his longest poems with an (unfinished) allegorical commentary; ''[[De Monarchia]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.danteonline.it/english/opere.asp?idope=4&amp;idlang=UK|title=Monarchia|publisher=Dante online|accessdate=September 2, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; a summary treatise of political philosophy in Latin which was condemned and burned after Dante's death&lt;ref&gt;Anthony K. Cassell
[https://web.archive.org/web/20151208162106/http://cuapress.cua.edu/BOOKS/viewbook.cfm?Book=CAMC The Monarchia Controversy]. The Monarchia stayed on the [[Index Librorum Prohibitorum]] from its inception until 1881.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Giuseppe Cappelli, [https://books.google.com/books?id=_ssFAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=RA1-PA28 ''La divina commedia'' di Dante Alighieri], in Italian.&lt;/ref&gt; by the Papal Legate [[Bertrando del Poggetto]], which argues for the necessity of a universal or global monarchy to establish universal peace in this life, and this monarchy's relationship to the Roman Catholic Church as guide to eternal peace; ''[[De vulgari eloquentia]]'' (&quot;On the Eloquence of Vernacular&quot;),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.danteonline.it/english/opere.asp?idope=3&amp;idlang=UK|title=De vulgari Eloquentia|publisher=Dante online|accessdate=September 2, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; on vernacular literature, partly inspired by the ''Razos de trobar'' of [[Raimon Vidal de Bezaudun]]; and ''La Vita Nuova'' (&quot;The New Life&quot;),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.danteonline.it/english/opere.asp?idope=5&amp;idlang=UK |title=New Life|publisher=Dante online|accessdate=September 2, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; the story of his love for [[Beatrice Portinari]], who also served as the ultimate symbol of salvation in the ''Comedy''. The ''Vita Nuova'' contains many of Dante's love poems in Tuscan, which was not unprecedented; the vernacular had been regularly used for lyric works before, during all the thirteenth century. However, Dante's commentary on his own work is also in the vernacular—both in the ''Vita Nuova'' and in the ''Convivio''—instead of the Latin that was almost universally used.

&lt;gallery mode=&quot;packed&quot; heights=&quot;200px&quot;&gt;
File:Purgatory (Purgatorio).jpg|Illustration for ''Purgatorio'' (of ''The Divine Comedy'') by [[Gustave Doré]]
File:Gustave Dore XIV.jpg|Illustration for ''Paradiso'' (of ''The Divine Comedy'') by Gustave Doré
File:Paradise (Paradiso) II.jpg|Illustration for ''Paradiso'' (of ''The Divine Comedy'') by Gustave Doré
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== References ==
* {{cite book|last=Allitt |first=John Stewart |authorlink= |title=Dante, il Pellegrino |edition=Edizioni Villadiseriane |language=Italian |publisher=Villa di Serio (BG) |location= |year=2011 |isbn=}}
* Teodolinda Barolini (ed.). ''Dante's Lyric Poetry: Poems of Youth and of the 'Vita Nuova'''. University of Toronto Press, 2014.
* {{cite book|last=Gardner |first=Edmund Garratt |authorlink=Edmund Garratt Gardner |title=Dante |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=London |year=1921 |isbn= |oclc=690699123 |url=https://archive.org/details/dantedante00gardrich |accessdate=March 7, 2016}}
* {{cite book|last=Hede |first=Jesper |authorlink= |title=Reading Dante: The Pursuit of Meaning |publisher=Lexington Books |location=Lanham |year=2007 |isbn=978-0-7391-2196-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Miles |first=Thomas |editor-first=Jon |editor-last=Stewart |title=Kierkegaard and the Patristic and Medieval Traditions |publisher=Ashgate |year=2008 |pages=223–236 |chapter=Dante: Tours of Hell: Mapping the Landscape of Sin and Despair |isbn=978-0-7546-6391-1}}
* {{cite book|last=Raffa |first=Guy P. |title=The Complete Danteworlds: A Reader's Guide to the Divine Comedy |publisher=University of Chicago Press |location=Chicago |year=2009 |isbn=978-0-226-70270-4}}
* {{cite book|last=Scartazzini |first=Giovanni Andrea |authorlink=Giovanni Andrea Scartazzini |title=La Divina Commedia riveduta e commentata (4 volumes) |location= |year=1874–1890 |isbn= |oclc=558999245}}
* {{cite book|last=Scartazzini |first=Giovanni Andrea |authorlink= |title=Enciclopedia dantesca: dizionario critico e ragionato di quanto concerne la vita e le opere di Dante Alighieri (2 volumes)|location= |year=1896–1898 |isbn= |oclc=12202483}}
* {{cite book|last=Scott |first=John A. |authorlink= |title=Dante's Political Purgatory |publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press |location=Philadelphia |year=1996 |isbn=978-0-585-12724-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Seung |first=T.K. |authorlink=T. K. Seung |title=The Fragile Leaves of the Sibyl: Dante's Master Plan |publisher=Newman Press |location=Westminster, MD |year=1962 |isbn= |oclc=1426455}}
* {{cite book|last=Toynbee |first=Paget |authorlink= |title=A Dictionary of the Proper Names and Notable Matters in the Works of Dante |publisher=The Clarendon Press |location=London |year=1898 |isbn= |oclc=343895 |url=https://archive.org/details/adictionaryprop00toyngoog |accessdate=March 7, 2016}}
* {{cite book|last=Whiting |first=Mary Bradford |authorlink= |title=Dante the Man and the Poet |url=https://archive.org/details/cu31924011891698 |publisher=W. Heffer &amp; Sons |location=Cambridge |year=1922 |isbn= |oclc=224789}}
* Guénon, René (1925). ''The Esoterism of Dante'', trans. by C.B. Berhill, in the ''Perennial Wisdom Series''. Ghent, NY: Sophia Perennis et Universalis, 1996. viii, 72 p. ''N.B''.: Originally published in French, entitled L'Esoterisme de Danté, in 1925. {{ISBN|0-900588-02-0}}

==External links==
{{Sister project links|s=Author:Dante Alighieri|wikt=no|voy=no|b=no|n=no|v=no|d=Q1067}}
* {{Britannica|151164|Dante}}
* {{Curlie|Arts/Literature/Periods_and_Movements/Medieval/Dante_Alighieri/}}
* {{Gutenberg author |id=507}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Dante}}
* {{Librivox author |id=1189}}
* [https://onemorelibrary.com/index.php/en/search-results/author/dante-alighieri-381?order=loc&amp;ord_t=asc Works by Dante Alighieri] at [https://onemorelibrary.com/index.php/en One More Library] (Works in English, Italian, Latin, Arabic, German, French and Spanish)
* {{cite SEP |url-id=dante |title=Dante Alighieri |last=Wetherbee |first=Winthrop}}
* The [http://www.museocasadidante.it/en/ Dante Museum in Florence]: his life, his books and a history &amp; literature blog about Dante
* The [https://web.archive.org/web/20170830160755/http://www.worldofdante.org/ World of Dante] multimedia, texts, maps, gallery, searchable database, music, teacher resources, timeline
* The [http://etcweb.princeton.edu/dante/index.html Princeton Dante Project] texts and multimedia
* The [http://dante.dartmouth.edu/ Dartmouth Dante Project] searchable database of commentary
* [http://www.danteonline.it/english/home_ita.asp Dante Online] manuscripts of works, images and text transcripts by Società Dantesca Italiana
* [http://dante.ilt.columbia.edu/ Digital Dante] – ''Divine Comedy'' with commentary, other works, scholars on Dante
* [http://oyc.yale.edu/italian-language-and-literature/ital-310 Open Yale Course on Dante] by [[Yale University]]
* [http://perunaenciclopediadantescadigitale.eu/dantesources/en/ DanteSources] project about Dante's primary sources developed by [[Istituto di Scienza e Tecnologie dell'Informazione|ISTI]]-[[National Research Council (Italy)|CNR]] and the [[University of Pisa]]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20100113213731/http://www.intratext.com/Catalogo/Autori/AUT11.HTM Works] Italian and Latin texts, concordances and frequency lists by [[IntraText]]
* [https://research.bowdoin.edu/dante-today/ Dante Today] citings and sightings of Dante in contemporary culture
* [https://repository.upenn.edu/bibdant/ Bibliotheca Dantesca] journal dedicated to all tendencies in Dante studies

{{Dante|state=uncollapsed}}
{{Divine Comedy navbox}}
{{Social and political philosophy}}
{{History of Catholic theology}}
{{Seven Deadly Sins}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Dante Alighieri| ]]
[[Category:Medieval Latin poets]]
[[Category:1265 births]]
[[Category:1321 deaths]]
[[Category:Catholic poets]]
[[Category:Christian writers]]
[[Category:Demonologists]]
[[Category:Epic poets]]
[[Category:Italian-language poets]]
[[Category:Italian male poets]]
[[Category:Italian political philosophers]]
[[Category:Italian politicians]]
[[Category:Italian Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic writers]]
[[Category:Sonneteers]]
[[Category:14th-century people of the Republic of Florence]]
[[Category:14th-century Italian poets]]
[[Category:14th-century Italian writers]]
[[Category:14th-century Latin writers]]
[[Category:People from Florence]]
[[Category:Culture in Florence]]
[[Category:Apothecaries]]</text>
      <sha1>8tm1c41nrezfmn9js8gotn1flqhqnm5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
