  <page>
    <title>Dumbarton Bridge (California)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8117</id>
    <revision>
      <id>916488206</id>
      <parentid>908772870</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-09-19T04:45:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Monkbot</username>
        <id>20483999</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[User:Monkbot/task 16: remove replace deprecated dead-url params|Task 16]]: replaced (6×) / removed (0×) deprecated |dead-url= and |deadurl= with |url-status=;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox bridge
|bridge_name= Dumbarton Bridge
|image= DumbartonBridgeCA and Towers.jpg
|caption= The Dumbarton Bridge and its adjacent powerline towers
|official_name= 
|also_known_as= 
|carries= 6 lanes of {{jct|state=CA|CA|84}}, bike/pedestrian
|crosses= [[San Francisco Bay]]
|locale= [[Menlo Park, California]] and [[Fremont, California]]
|owner= [[State of California]]
|maint= [[California Department of Transportation]] and the [[Bay Area Toll Authority]]
|id= 
|design= [[Twin]] [[Concrete]] [[Girder Bridge]]
|mainspan= {{convert|103.63|m|ft|abbr=off|sp=us}}
|length= {{convert|2,621.28|m|ft|abbr=off|sp=us}}, 1.63 miles
|width= 
|clearance= 
|below= {{convert|25.91|m|ft|abbr=off|sp=us}} (main span)
|traffic= 70,000+ (auto)&lt;br /&gt;118 (bike &amp; pedestrian)
|open= October 1982
|closed= 
|toll= Cars (westbound only) &lt;br /&gt; $6.00 (cash or [[FasTrak]]), $3.00 (carpools during peak hours, FasTrak only)
|map_image= San_Francisco_Bay_Bridges_map_en.svg
|map_caption= Dumbarton Bridge crosses the southern portion of San Francisco Bay.
|map_width= 
|coordinates = {{coord|37.5069|-122.1169|scale:50000_region:US-CA_type:landmark|display=inline,title}}
}}

The '''Dumbarton Bridge''' is the southernmost of the highway bridges across [[San Francisco Bay]] in [[California]]. Carrying over 70,000 vehicles&lt;ref name=&quot;dumbarton-study-2017&quot;&gt;{{cite report|url=http://www.samtrans.com/Assets/Dumbarton+Rail+Corridor/PDFs/171120+DTCS+-+Full+Report.pdf|title=Dumbarton Transportation Corridor Study|date=November 2017|accessdate=March 3, 2019|publisher=San Mateo County Transit District}}&lt;/ref&gt; and about 118 pedestrian and bicycle crossings daily,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Spotswood|first1=Dick|title=Dick Spotswood: Richmond bridge third lane is working, but more needs to be done|url=http://www.marinij.com/opinion/20180508/dick-spotswood-richmond-bridge-third-lane-is-working-but-more-needs-to-be-done|accessdate=9 May 2018|agency=Marin Independent Journal|date=8 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; it is the shortest bridge across San Francisco Bay at {{convert|1.63|mi|ft m}}. Its eastern end is in [[Fremont, California|Fremont]], near [[Newark, California|Newark]] in the [[San Francisco Bay National Wildlife Refuge]], and its western end is in [[Menlo Park, California|Menlo Park]]. Bridging [[California State Route 84|State Route 84]] across the bay, it has three lanes each way and a separated bike/pedestrian lane along its south side. Like the [[San Mateo Bridge]] to the north, [[electric power transmission|power line]]s parallel the bridge.

==History and engineering features==
[[Image:DumbartonBr.jpg|thumb|right|The original vertical-lift span of the Dumbarton Bridge, shown in 1984 shortly before it was demolished]]The bridge has never been officially named, but its commonly used name comes from Dumbarton Point, named in 1876 after [[Dumbarton, Scotland]]. Built originally to provide a shortcut for traffic originating in San Mateo and Santa Clara counties, the bridge served industrial and residential areas on both sides. The earlier bridge opened on January 17, 1927, and was the first vehicular bridge to cross San Francisco Bay. A portion of this old drawbridge remains as a fishing pier on the east side of the Bay. The original bridge was built with private capital and then purchased by the state for $2.5 million in 1951.

Its age and the two-lane undivided roadway and lift-span led to a replacement bridge being built to the north. This bridge opened in October 1982 as a four-lane, high-level structure. The structure was re-striped to accommodate six lanes on October 18, 1989, in response to the temporary closing of the [[San Francisco–Oakland Bay Bridge]] due to the [[Loma Prieta earthquake]], and the permanent widening of the approaches was completed by July 2003.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Dumbarton Bridge&quot; {{cite web|url=http://bata.mtc.ca.gov/bridges/dumbarton.htm |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2012-02-28 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120221185117/http://bata.mtc.ca.gov/bridges/dumbarton.htm |archivedate=2012-02-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The cost of the complete replacement project was $200 million. The current bridge includes a two-way bicycle and separate pedestrian path on the south-facing side. A {{convert|340|ft|m|0|abbr=on}} center span provides {{convert|85|ft|m|0|abbr=on}} of vertical clearance for shipping. The approach spans on both sides of the Bay are of pre-stressed [[lightweight concrete]] [[girder]]s supporting a lightweight concrete deck. The center spans are twin steel trapezoidal girders which also support a lightweight concrete deck.

The center span of the original bridge was demolished in a controlled explosion in September 1984.
[[Image:Dumbarton Bridge CA from the air.JPG|thumb|right|A view from the air, above Palo Alto, looking towards Fremont]]

==Roadway connections==
The bridge is part of [[California State Route 84|State Route 84]], and is directly connected to [[Interstate 880 (California)|Interstate 880]] by a [[freeway]] segment north of the Fremont end.
There is no freeway connection between [[U.S. Route 101 in California|U.S. 101]] and the southwest end of the Dumbarton Bridge. Motorists must traverse one of three at-grade routes to connect from the Bayshore Freeway to the bridge. These are (from northwest to southeast):
# the Bayfront Expressway, a [[limited-access road]] linking to U.S. 101 at Marsh Road, [[Atherton, California|Atherton]] (the official routing of SR 84)
# Willow Road ([[California State Route 114|SR 114]]), an approximately one-mile expressway through east Menlo Park to U.S. 101
# University Avenue ([[California State Route 109|SR 109]]), an [[arterial road]] and the main commercial street of [[East Palo Alto, California|East Palo Alto]].

The Willow Road and University Avenue junctions with Bayfront Expressway are at-grade intersections controlled by traffic lights; there are two additional controlled intersections at Chilco Road and Marsh Road, and the Marsh Road interchange on U.S. 101 is a [[Partial cloverleaf interchange|parclo]]. The result is that Bayfront Expressway is frequently congested, and when not congested is often the site of high-speed car crashes. In 2007, prominent author [[David Halberstam]] was killed in one such crash at the Willow Road intersection.

Access to [[Interstate 280 in California|I-280]] is available via State Route 84 to [[Woodside Road]] (as signed) or other arterial routes. There are no cross-Peninsula freeway connections between State Routes 92 and 85. In addition, there are no direct cross-Peninsula arterial routes between State Route 84 and Page Mill Road, a five-mile gap.

Although the present situation has resulted in severe traffic problems on the bridge itself and in Menlo Park and East Palo Alto, Caltrans has been unable to upgrade the relevant portion of Highway 84 to freeway standards for several decades, due to opposition from the cities of Menlo Park, Atherton and [[Palo Alto, California|Palo Alto]]. Freeway opponents fear that upgrading Highway 84 will encourage more people to live in southern [[Alameda County, California|Alameda County]] (where housing is more affordable) and commute to jobs in the mid-Peninsula area (where businesses wish to be located in order to be close to [[Silicon Valley]]), thus increasing traffic in their neighborhoods to the south and west of U.S. 101 and even along State Routes 85 and 237.

Bus service across the bridge is provided by the [[Dumbarton Express]], run by a consortium of local transit agencies ([[SamTrans]], [[AC Transit]], [[Santa Clara Valley Transportation Authority|VTA]] and others) which connects to [[Bay Area Rapid Transit|BART]] at Union City and [[Caltrain]] at Palo Alto and California Avenue. AC Transit also runs Transbay buses U ([[Fremont (BART station)|Fremont BART]] and [[Fremont-Centerville (Amtrak station)|Amtrak]] to [[Stanford University|Stanford]]) and DA (Ardenwood to [[Oracle Corporation|Oracle]] and [[Facebook]] headquarters) across the bridge. The free [[Stanford Marguerite Shuttle]] also runs buses AE-F and EB across the bridge.

==Environmental factors==

When the current bridge was planned in the 1970s, [[Caltrans]] conducted extensive environmental research on the [[marine biology|aquatic]] and [[landform|terrestrial]] environment. Principal concerns of the public were [[air pollution]] and [[noise pollution]] impacts, particularly in some residential areas of Menlo Park and [[East Palo Alto]]. Studies were conducted to produce contour maps of projected [[Sound exposure level|sound level]]s and [[carbon monoxide]] concentrations throughout the western approaches, for each alternative connection scheme.&lt;ref&gt;C.M. Hogan, Leda Patmore, Harry Seidman et al., ''Air Quality and Acoustics Analysis for the Dumbarton Bridge Replacement Project'', ESL Inc., prepared for the Bay Area Division of Toll Crossings (1973)&lt;/ref&gt;

The area around the bridge is an important ecological area, hosting many species of birds, fish and mammals. The [[endangered species]] [[California clapper rail]] is known to be present in the western bridge terminus area.

Near the bridge on the Peninsula are Menlo Park's Bayfront Park, East Palo Alto's Ravenswood Open Space Preserve, and the [[Palo Alto Baylands Nature Preserve]]. An accessible portion of the [[San Francisco Bay National Wildlife]] Refuge lies immediately north of the western bridge terminus, where the Ravenswood trail runs.&lt;ref&gt;''San Francisco Bay Shoreline Guide'', by California State Coastal Conservancy, University of California Press (1995) {{ISBN|0-520-08878-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On both sides of the east end of the bridge are large salt ponds and [[levee]] trails belonging to the [[Don Edwards San Francisco Bay National Wildlife Refuge]]. The headquarters and visitor center for the refuge is on a hill south of the bridge approach. North of the east end of the bridge is [[Coyote Hills Regional Park]], with its network of trails running over tall hills. North of that is the [[Alameda Creek Regional Trail]] from the Bay to [[Niles Canyon]]. East of [[Coyote Hills (Alameda County)|Coyote Hills]] is [[Ardenwood Historic Farm]], a restored working farm that preserves and displays turn-of-the-century farming methods

==Tolls==
Tolls are only collected from westbound traffic at the toll plaza on the east side of the bay. Drivers may either pay by cash or use the [[FasTrak]] electronic toll collection device. There are seven toll lanes at the plaza. During peak traffic hours, the leftmost lane is designated a FasTrak-only [[HOV lane]], allowing [[carpool]] vehicles carrying two or more people or motorcycles to pass for a toll of $2.50. The next two leftmost lanes are FasTrak-only lanes for all vehicles, and all other lanes accept both cash and FasTrak. During non-peak hours the HOV lane is open to vehicles carrying only one person, but remains FasTrak-only.

===Historical toll rates===
Prior to 1969, tolls on the Dumbarton Bridge were collected in both directions. When it opened, the original 1927 span had a toll of $0.40 per car plus $0.05 per passenger. In 1959, tolls were set to $0.35 per car. It was raised to $0.70 in 1969, then $0.75 in 1976. The toll per car remained at $0.75 when the replacement bridge opened in the 1980s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.dot.ca.gov/dist4/documents/tollfees.pdf | title=History of California's Bridge Tolls | publisher=[[California Department of Transportation|Caltrans]] | accessdate=June 3, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The basic toll (for automobiles) on the seven state-owned bridges, including the Dumbarton Bridge, was raised to $1 by Regional Measure 1, approved by Bay Area voters in 1988.&lt;ref&gt;[http://bata.mtc.ca.gov/projects/rm1.htm Regional Measure 1 Toll Bridge Program]. ''bata.mtc.ca.gov''; [[Bay Area Toll Authority]]. {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101104094253/http://bata.mtc.ca.gov/projects/rm1.htm |date=November 4, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A $1 seismic retrofit surcharge was added in 1998 by the state legislature, originally for eight years, but since then extended to December 2037 (AB1171, October 2001).&lt;ref name='AB1171'&gt;{{cite news|first=John |last=Dutra |title=AB 1171 Assembly Bill – Chaptered |date=October 14, 2001 |publisher=[[California State Assembly]] |url=http://www.leginfo.ca.gov/pub/01-02/bill/asm/ab_1151-1200/ab_1171_bill_20011014_chaptered.html |accessdate=August 7, 2008 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120315184435/http://www.leginfo.ca.gov/pub/01-02/bill/asm/ab_1151-1200/ab_1171_bill_20011014_chaptered.html |archivedate=March 15, 2012 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; On March 2, 2004, voters approved Regional Measure 2, raising the toll by another dollar to a total of $3. An additional dollar was added to the toll starting January 1, 2007, to cover cost overruns concerning the replacement of the eastern span.

The [[Metropolitan Transportation Commission (San Francisco Bay Area)|Metropolitan Transportation Commission]], a regional transportation agency, in its capacity as the [[Bay Area Toll Authority]], administers RM1 and RM2 funds, a significant portion of which are allocated to public transit capital improvements and operating subsidies in the transportation corridors served by the bridges. Caltrans administers the &quot;second dollar&quot; seismic surcharge, and receives some of the MTC-administered funds to perform other maintenance work on the bridges. The Bay Area Toll Authority is made up of appointed officials put in place by various city and county governments, and is not subject to direct voter oversight.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=About MTC |publisher=Metropolitan Transportation Commission |date=October 15, 2009 |url=http://www.mtc.ca.gov/about_mtc/about.htm |accessdate=October 15, 2009 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101103124604/http://www.mtc.ca.gov/about_mtc/about.htm |archivedate=November 3, 2010 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Due to further funding shortages for seismic retrofit projects, the Bay Area Toll Authority again raised tolls on all seven of the state-owned bridges in July 2010. The toll rate for autos on the Dumbarton Bridge was thus increased to $5.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Frequently Asked Toll Questions |publisher=Bay Area Toll Authority |date=June 1, 2010 |url=http://www.mtc.ca.gov/tolls/faq.htm#2 |accessdate=June 29, 2010 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101122040153/http://www.mtc.ca.gov/tolls/faq.htm#2 |archivedate=November 22, 2010 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2018, Bay Area voters approved Regional Measure 3 to further raise the tolls on all seven of the state-owned bridges to fund $4.5 billion worth of transportation improvements in the area.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=https://www.sfgate.com/bayarea/article/3-hike-to-Bay-Area-tolls-appears-to-have-support-12972027.php | title=Regional Measure 3: Work on transportation improvements could start next year | first=Michael | last=Cabanatuan | newspaper=SFGate.com | date=June 6, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.ktvu.com/news/bay-area-bridge-tolls-to-increase-one-dollar-in-january-except-golden-gate | title=Bay Area bridge tolls to increase one dollar in January, except Golden Gate | first=Christien | last=Kafton | publisher=KTVU | date=November 28, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Under the passed measure, the toll rate for autos on the Dumbarton Bridge will be increased to $6 on January 1, 2019; to $7 on January 1, 2022; and then to $8 on January 1, 2025.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release | url=https://mtc.ca.gov/whats-happening/news/tolls-seven-bay-area-bridges-set-rise-next-month | title=Tolls on Seven Bay Area Bridges Set to Rise Next Month | publisher=Metropolitan Transportation Commission | date=December 11, 2018 | accessdate=December 16, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Dumbarton Rail Bridge==
{{main|Dumbarton Rail Bridge}}

[[Image:Dumbarton Bridge1.jpg|right|thumb|Dumbarton Rail Bridge in 2007, as seen from a kayak]]
Just to the south of the car bridge lies the '''Dumbarton Rail Bridge'''. Built in 1910, the rail bridge has been unused since 1982 and its western approach collapsed in a fire in 1998.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = https://www.paloaltoonline.com/weekly/morgue/news/1998_Jan_7.FIRE.html|title = FIREFIGHTERS: Dumbarton rail bridge destroyed|publisher = Paloaltoonline.com|date = 1998-01-07|accessdate = 2015-05-25|last = Kazak|first = Don|archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20040814110454/https://www.paloaltoonline.com/weekly/morgue/news/1998_Jan_7.FIRE.html|archivedate = 2004-08-14|url-status = live}}&lt;/ref&gt; When the bridge was in use, boaters would signal the operator, who would start a diesel engine and rotate the bridge to the open position on a large gear. The bridge is now left in the open position as shown. There are plans for a new rail bridge and rehabilitation of the rail line to serve a commuter rail service to connect Union City, [[Fremont, California|Fremont]], and Newark to various [[San Francisco Peninsula|Peninsula]] destinations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.smcta.com/Dumbarton_Rail/information.asp |title=Dumbarton Rail Corridor |publisher=SMCTA |date=2011-05-24 |accessdate=2011-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A successful March 2004 regional transportation ballot measure included funding to rehabilitate the rail bridge for the commuter rail service, but in October 2008 the Metropolitan Transportation Commission transferred $91 million from this project to the [[BART]] [[Bay Area Rapid Transit expansion#Warm Springs extension|Warm Springs Extension Project]] in Fremont&lt;!-- , delaying for at least a decade plans to send commuter trains across the bridge --&gt;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  | authorlink = 
  | author = 
  | coauthors = 
  | title = BART's Warm Springs Extension Gets Boost From Regional Measure 2 Cash
  | url = http://www.newsrx.com/newsletters/Healthcare-Finance,-Tax-and-Law-Weekly/2008-10-08/3010082008199HFT.html
  | work = Healthcare Finance, Tax &amp; Law Weekly
  | publisher = 
  | date = October 8, 2008
  | accessdate = 2009-08-02
  | quote = 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Hetch Hetchy Aqueduct==
Between the Dumbarton Bridge and the Dumbarton Rail Bridge is the Bay crossing of the [[Hetch Hetchy Aqueduct]]. The aqueduct rises above ground in Newark at the east side of the Bay, falls below the water's surface at a pump station in Fremont, re-emerges in the middle of the Bay and then continues above water until it reaches the west side of the Bay at Menlo Park.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Ronald Horii |url=http://baytrail.abag.ca.gov/vtour/map3/access/Btdmbrtn/Btdmbrtn.htm |title=Dumbarton Bridge |publisher=Baytrail.abag.ca.gov |accessdate=2011-08-21 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110807051038/http://baytrail.abag.ca.gov/vtour/map3/access/Btdmbrtn/Btdmbrtn.htm |archivedate=2011-08-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== In popular culture ==
A scene of the 1970 movie ''[[Harold and Maude]]'' was filmed at the original toll plaza and showed Maude speeding and disobeying a police officer.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.harold-and-maude.com/dumbartonbridge.html|title=Dumbarton Bridge|website=harold-and-maude.com|access-date=2019-05-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* [http://www.dot.ca.gov/dist4/dumbarton/ California Dept. of Transportation: Dumbarton Bridge]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110807051038/http://baytrail.abag.ca.gov/vtour/map3/access/Btdmbrtn/Btdmbrtn.htm Bay Trail: Dumbarton Bridge]
* {{Structurae|id=20009342|title=Dumbarton Bridge}}

{{San Francisco Bay watershed}}
{{Menlo Park, California}}
{{Crossings navbox
|structure       = Crossings
|place           = [[San Francisco Bay]]
|bridge          = Dumbarton Bridge
|bridge signs    = [[Image:California 84.svg|20px|State Route 84]]
|upstream text   = South
|upstream        = [[Hetch Hetchy]] Aqueduct
|upstream signs  = 
|downstream text = North
|downstream      = [[San Mateo-Hayward Bridge]]
|downstream signs = [[Image:California 92.svg|20px|State Route 92]]
}}

 &lt;!-- required --&gt;

[[Category:Bridges in the San Francisco Bay Area]]
[[Category:Road bridges in California]]
[[Category:Railroad bridges in California]]
[[Category:Bridges in Alameda County, California]]
[[Category:Bridges in San Mateo County, California]]
[[Category:Concrete bridges in California]]
[[Category:Swing bridges in the United States]]
[[Category:Toll bridges in California]]
[[Category:Bridges completed in 1927]]
[[Category:Bridges completed in 1982]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Fremont, California]]
[[Category:Menlo Park, California]]
[[Category:San Francisco Bay]]
[[Category:San Francisco Bay Trail]]
[[Category:1927 establishments in California]]
[[Category:Girder bridges in the United States]]</text>
      <sha1>gw2hw2cmp2zuttv2a7ghzacfmhh240y</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
