  <page>
    <title>Black and Tans</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4922</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941973763</id>
      <parentid>936860229</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-21T19:55:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>90.202.110.237</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{other uses|Black and tan (disambiguation)}}
{{EngvarB|date=August 2014}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2014}}
[[File:A Black and Tan on duty in Dublin.jpg|thumb|250px|A Black and Tan in Dublin, smoking and carrying a [[Lewis gun]], February 1921]]
The '''Black and Tans''' ({{lang-ga|Dúchrónaigh}})&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.tearma.ie/Search.aspx?term=the+Black+and+Tans&amp;lang=3116649 |title=tearma.ie - Dictionary of Irish Terms - Foclóir Téarmaíochta |accessdate=6 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; were [[Special Constable|constables]] recruited into the [[Royal Irish Constabulary]] (RIC) as reinforcements during the [[Irish War of Independence]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ndic.edu/press/pdf/5463.pdf ''Improving the law Enforcement-Intelligence Community Relationship''] {{webarchive |url= https://web.archive.org/web/20090327013025/http://www.ndic.edu/press/pdf/5463.pdf |date=27 March 2009 }}. National Defense Intelligence College, Washington, DC. June 2007. p. 120&lt;/ref&gt; Recruitment began in Great Britain in January 1920 and about 10,000 men enlisted during the conflict. The vast majority were unemployed former [[British Army|soldiers]] from Britain who fought in the [[First World War]], although some were from Ireland.&lt;ref name=&quot;warinpeace&quot;&gt;{{citation|editor1=Robert Gerwarth|editor2=John Horne|title=War in Peace: Paramilitary Violence in Europe After the Great War|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford|year=2013|page=202|quote=The Black and Tans were the ex-servicemen recruited as RIC constables throughout Britain in late 1919 and constituted a force of approximately 9,000 men before the war's end. However, 'Black and Tans' also came to refer to the temporary cadets of the Auxiliary Division of the RIC, a force of some 2,200 ex-officers, formed in July 1920, and in practice virtually independent of military and policy control. Both forces were made up of veterans from all services. ... Both Auxiliaries and Black and Tans had Irish members.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Padraig Og O Ruairc, Blood on the Banner, The Republican Struggle in Clare, pp. 332–33&lt;/ref&gt; 

The [[Dublin Castle administration|British administration in Ireland]] promoted the idea of bolstering the RIC with British recruits. They were to help the overstretched RIC maintain control and suppress the [[Irish Republican Army (1917–22)|Irish Republican Army]] (IRA), although they were less well trained in ordinary policing. The nickname &quot;Black and Tans&quot; arose from the colours of the improvised uniforms they initially wore, a mixture of dark green RIC (which appeared black) and [[khaki]] British Army. They served in all parts of Ireland, but most were sent to southern and western regions where fighting was heaviest. By 1921, Black and Tans made up almost half of the RIC in [[County Tipperary]], for example. 

The Black and Tans gained a reputation for [[police brutality]] and became notorious for reprisal attacks on civilians and civilian property, including [[extrajudicial killing]]s, arson and looting. Their actions further swayed Irish public opinion against British rule; their actions incited condemnation in Britain as well.

The Black and Tans were sometimes confused with the [[Auxiliary Division]], a [[counter-insurgency]] unit of the RIC, also recruited during the conflict and made up of former British officers.&lt;ref&gt;O'Connell, T. ''Interrogation and Treatment of republican suspects by the British Auxiliary Forces, 'Black and Tans', January 1921'', Irish Historical Documents since 1800, edited by Alan O'Day. Gill and MacMillan. p. 169.&lt;/ref&gt; However, sometimes the term &quot;Black and Tans&quot; covers both groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;warinpeace&quot; /&gt; A similar force, the [[Ulster Special Constabulary]], was founded to reinforce the RIC in [[Northern Ireland]]. Some sources say the Black and Tans were officially named the &quot;Royal Irish Constabulary Special Reserve&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historyireland.com/volume-23/the-burning-of-cork-december-1920-the-fire-service-response/ &quot;The burning of Cork, December 1920: the fire service response&quot;]. [[History Ireland]], November/December 2015 issue.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds, John. [https://ulir.ul.ie/bitstream/handle/10344/3618/Reynolds_2013_divided.pdf?sequence=5 ''Divided loyalties: the Royal Irish Constabulary in county Tipperary, 1919–22''. University of Limerick, 2013. p. 83]&lt;/ref&gt; but this is denied by other sources,&lt;ref&gt; David M Leeson, The Black and Tans, British Police and Auxiliaries in the Irish War of Independence, (Oxford University Press, 2011) p.26&lt;/ref&gt; which say they were &quot;recruits to the regular RIC&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Richard Abbot, ''Police casualties in Ireland 1919-1921'' (2019), p.81&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;enlisted as regular constabulary&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Charles Townshend, ''The Republic, The Fight for Irish Independence'' (2013)p.102&lt;/ref&gt;

==Foundation==
The early 20th century in [[Ireland]] was dominated by [[Irish nationalism|Irish nationalists']] pursuit of [[Irish Home Rule movement|Home Rule]] from the [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|United Kingdom]]. The issue of Home Rule was shelved with the outbreak of [[World War I]], and in 1916 [[Irish republicanism|Irish republicans]] staged the [[Easter Rising]] against British rule in an attempt to establish an independent republic. Growing support amongst the Irish populace for the republican [[Sinn Féin]] party saw it win a majority of Irish seats in the [[1918 Irish general election|1918 general election]]. On 21 January 1919, Sinn Féin followed through on its [[Sinn Féin Manifesto 1918|manifesto]] and founded an [[First Dáil|independent Irish parliament]] (Dáil Éireann), which then declared an independent [[Irish Republic]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.oireachtas.ie/parliament/about/history/ |title=History, Houses of the Oireachtas |publisher=Houses of the Oireachtas |website=www.oireachtas.ie |accessdate=6 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Dáil called on the public to [[boycott]] the RIC, while the [[Irish Republican Army (1917–22)|Irish Republican Army]] (IRA) began attacking police barracks and ambushing police patrols. In September 1919 [[David Lloyd George]], the British Prime Minister, outlawed the Dáil and augmented the British Army presence in Ireland.&lt;ref&gt;''In Search of Ireland's Heroes'' [[Carmel McCaffrey]]. Ivan R. Dee. p 231&lt;/ref&gt;

After the First World War, there were many unemployed ex-servicemen in Britain. British [[Unionism in Ireland|Unionist]] leader [[Walter Long, 1st Viscount Long|Walter Long]] had suggested recruiting these men into the RIC in a May 1919 letter to the [[John French, 1st Earl of Ypres|John French]], the [[Lord Lieutenant of Ireland]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Leeson24&quot;&gt;Leeson, D M. ''The Black and Tans: British Police and Auxiliaries in the Irish War of Independence, 1920–1921''. Oxford University Press, 2011. p.24&lt;/ref&gt; The idea was promoted by French as well as by [[Frederick Shaw (British Army officer)|Frederick Shaw]], [[Commander-in-Chief, Ireland|Commander of the British Army in Ireland]]. The RIC's Inspector General, [[Joseph Byrne (British Army officer)|Joseph Byrne]], was against it. He resisted the militarization of the police and believed ex-soldiers could not be controlled by police discipline. In December 1919, Byrne was replaced by his deputy T. J. Smith, an [[Orange Order|Orangeman]]. On 27 December, Smith issued an order authorizing recruitment in Britain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leeson24&quot;/&gt; The advertisements appeared in major cities calling for men willing to &quot;face a rough and dangerous task&quot;. The first British recruits joined the RIC six days later, on 2 January 1920.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leeson24&quot;/&gt;

===Recruits===

About 10,000 were recruited between January 1920 and the end of the conflict.&lt;ref&gt;Coleman, Marie. ''The Irish Revolution, 1916-1923''. Routledge, 2013. p.70&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Walsh, Oonagh. ''Ireland's Independence: 1880-1923''. Routledge, 2003. p.67&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;irishtimes jan 2020&quot;&gt;[https://www.irishtimes.com/news/ireland/irish-news/ric-and-dmp-policemen-to-be-commemorated-for-first-time-by-state-1.4128214 &quot;RIC and DMP policemen to be commemorated for first time by State&quot;]. ''[[Irish Times]]'', 1 January 2020.&lt;/ref&gt; About 100 were recruited each month from January to June 1920. The recruitment rate rose from July, when the RIC was given a large pay raise.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leeson25&quot;&gt;Leeson, p.25&lt;/ref&gt; The RIC began losing men at a high rate in the summer of 1920, due to the IRA campaign. On an average week, about 100 men resigned or retired while only 76 recruits enlisted to replace them. More police were needed, but enough replacements could not be found in Ireland; on average, the RIC recruited only seven Irishmen per week.&lt;ref&gt;Leeson, pp.22-23&lt;/ref&gt; The intake of British recruits steadily rose and then surged from late September, following the widely publicized [[Sack of Balbriggan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Leeson25&quot;/&gt; 

This sudden influx of men led to a shortage of RIC uniforms, and the new recruits were issued with [[khaki]] army uniforms (usually only trousers) and dark green RIC tunics, caps and belts. These uniforms differentiated them from both the regular RIC and the British Army, and gave rise to their nickname: &quot;Black and Tans&quot;. Christopher O'Sullivan wrote in the ''[[Limerick Echo]]'' on 25 March 1920 that, meeting a group of recruits on a train at [[Limerick Junction]], the attire of one reminded him of the [[Scarteen]] [[fox hunting|Hunt]], whose &quot;Black and Tans&quot; nickname derived from the colours of its [[Kerry Beagle]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Spellissy1998&quot;&gt;{{cite book| last = Spellissy| first = Séan| title = The history of Limerick City| date = December 1998| publisher = Celtic Bookshop| isbn = 978-0-9534683-0-0| pages = 87–88 }}&lt;!--| accessdate = 9 August 2010--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; Ennis comedian [[Mike Nono]] elaborated the joke in Limerick's Theatre Royal, and the nickname soon took hold,&lt;ref name=&quot;Spellissy1998&quot; /&gt; persisting even after the men received full RIC uniforms.

The new recruits were trained at [[Gormanstown Camp]] near Dublin, most spending two or three weeks there before being sent to RIC barracks around the country. In general, the recruits were poorly trained for police duties and received much less training than the existing Irish RIC constables.&lt;ref&gt;Leeson, pp.78-79&lt;/ref&gt;

The vast majority of Black and Tans were unemployed First World War veterans in their twenties, most of whom joined for economic reasons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Augusteijn pages 938-940&quot;/&gt; The RIC offered men good wages, a chance for promotion, and the prospect of a pension.&lt;ref&gt;Leeson, p.77&lt;/ref&gt; According to historian David Leeson, &quot;The typical Black and Tan was in his early twenties and relatively short in stature. He was an unmarried Protestant from London or the [[Home Counties]] who had fought in the British Army [...] He was a working-class man with few skills&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Leeson, p.68&lt;/ref&gt; The popular Irish claim made at the time that most Black and Tans had criminal records and had been recruited straight from British prisons is incorrect, as a criminal record would disqualify one from working as a policeman.&lt;ref name=&quot;Augusteijn pages 938-940&quot;&gt;Augusteijn, Joost Review of ''The Black and Tans: British Police and Auxiliaries in the Irish War of Independence, 1920–1921'' by D. M. Leeson pp. 938–40 from ''The Journal of Modern History'', Volume 85, Issue # 4, December 2013 p. 939.&lt;/ref&gt; According to Jim Herlihy, author of ''The Royal Irish Constabulary - A Short History and Genealogical Guide'', 10,936 Black and Tans were recruited, of whom 883 (8%) were born in Ireland.&lt;ref name=&quot;irishtimes jan 2020&quot;/&gt;

The British government also founded a new [[Auxiliary Division]] of the RIC, which was also composed mostly of British recruits. While the Black and Tans were recruited into the RIC as regular constables, the Auxiliaries were an offensive &quot;[[paramilitary]] force composed of ex British military and naval officers, dressed in distinctive uniforms and organised in military style companies...officially temporary cadets paid and ranked as RIC sergeants&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Leeson, p.30&lt;/ref&gt; At least some of the crimes attributed to the Black and Tans were actually the work of the Auxiliaries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Spain |first=Adam |title=Review of ''The Black and Tans'' by DM Leeson |newspaper=Irish Independent |date=17 September 2011|url= http://www.independent.ie/entertainment/books/review-history-the-black-and-tans-by-dm-leeson-26772652.html |accessdate=2015-11-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, sometimes the term &quot;Black and Tans&quot; covered both groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;warinpeace&quot; /&gt;

==Deployment and conduct==
{{See also |Timeline of the Irish War of Independence}}

[[File:Outside the London and North Western Hotel in Dublin, April 21, 1921.jpg|thumb|250px|A group of Black and Tans and Auxiliaries outside the London and North Western Hotel in Dublin following an attack by the IRA, April 1921]]

Black and Tans served in all parts of Ireland, but most were sent to southern and western regions where the IRA was most active and fighting was heaviest.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leeson26&quot;&gt;Leeson, p.26&lt;/ref&gt; By 1921, Black and Tans made up nearly half of all RIC constables in County Tipperary, for example.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leeson26&quot;/&gt; Few were sent to what became [[Northern Ireland]], however.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leeson26&quot;/&gt; The authorities there raised their own reserve force, the [[Ulster Special Constabulary]]. For the most part, the Black and Tans were &quot;treated as ordinary constables, despite their strange uniforms, and they lived and worked in barracks alongside the Irish police&quot;. They spent most of their time manning police posts or on patrol—&quot;walking, cycling, or riding on Crossley Tenders&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Leeson, pp.26-27&lt;/ref&gt; They also undertook guard, escort and crowd control duties. While some Irish constables got along well with the Black and Tans, &quot;it seems that many Irish police did not like their new British colleagues&quot; and saw them as &quot;rough&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Leeson, pp.29-30&lt;/ref&gt; 

Alexander Will,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.policememorial.org.uk/Forces/IRELAND/RIC_Roll.htm |title=RIC Record |accessdate=6 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; from [[Forfar]] in Scotland, was the first Black and Tan to die in the conflict. He was killed during an IRA attack on the RIC barracks in [[Rathmore, County Kerry|Rathmore]], County Kerry, on 11 July 1920.

The Black and Tans soon gained a reputation for brutality.&lt;ref&gt;''[https://www.theguardian.com/fromthearchive/story/0,,1920235,00.html Don't be too tragic about Ireland]'' – The Guardian, 12 October 1921&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/irelands-war-of-independence-the-chilling-story-of-the-black-and-tans-475005.html Ireland's War of Independence: The chilling story of the Black and Tans ]'' – The Independent, 21 April 2006&lt;/ref&gt; In the summer of 1920, Black and Tans began responding to IRA attacks by carrying out arbitrary reprisals against civilians, especially republicans. This usually involved the burning of homes, businesses, meeting halls and farms. Some buildings were also attacked with gunfire and grenades, and businesses were looted. Mass reprisals on property &quot;were often accompanied by beatings and killings&quot;. Many villages suffered mass reprisals, including the [[Sack of Balbriggan]] (20 September), [[Kilkee]] (26 September), [[Trim, County Meath|Trim]] (27 September), [[Tubbercurry]] (30 September) and [[Granard]] (31 October).&lt;ref&gt;Leeson, pp.167-176&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Guerrilla Warfare in the Irish War of Independence, 1919-1921, pp.178-181&lt;/ref&gt; Following the [[Rineen ambush]] (22 September) in which six RIC men were killed, police burned many houses in the surrounding villages of [[Milltown Malbay]], [[Lahinch]] and [[Ennistymon]], and killed five civilians.&lt;ref&gt;Padraig Ó Ruairc. ''Blood on the Banner, The Republican Struggle in Clare''. Mercier, 2009, pp.169-171&lt;/ref&gt; In early November, Black and Tans [[Siege of Tralee|&quot;besieged&quot; Tralee]] in revenge for the IRA abduction and killing of two local RIC men. They closed all the businesses in the town, let no food in for a week and shot dead three local civilians. On 14 November, Black and Tans were suspected of abducting and murdering a Roman Catholic priest, Father [[Michael Griffin (Irish priest)|Michael Griffin]], in [[Galway]]. His body was found in a bog in [[Barna]] a week later. From October 1920 to July 1921, the Galway region was &quot;remarkable in many ways&quot;, most notably the level of police brutality towards suspected IRA members, which was far above the norm in the rest of Ireland.&lt;ref name=&quot;Augusteijn pages 938-940&quot;/&gt; The villages of [[Clifden]] and [[Knockcroghery]] suffered mass reprisals in March and June 1921.

Members of the British government, the British administration in Ireland, and senior officers in the RIC tacitly supported reprisals as a way of scaring the population into rejecting the IRA. In December 1920, the government officially approved certain reprisals against property. There were an estimated 150 official reprisals over the next six months.&lt;ref&gt;Coleman, Marie. ''The Irish Revolution, 1916-1923''. Routledge, 2013. pp.86-87&lt;/ref&gt; Taken together with an increased emphasis on discipline in the RIC, this helped to curb the random atrocities the Black and Tans committed for the remainder of the war, if only because reprisals were now directed from above rather than being the result of a spontaneous desire for revenge.&lt;ref name=&quot;Labour Commission&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Gibbons|first=Ivan|date=2013-05-14|title=The British Parliamentary Labour Party and the Government of Ireland Act 1920|journal=Parliamentary History|volume=32|issue=3|pages=506–521|doi=10.1111/1750-0206.12024|issn=0264-2824}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Many of the activities popularly attributed to the Black and Tans may have been committed by the [[Auxiliary Division]] or 'old' RIC constables. For instance, [[Tomás Mac Curtain]], the Mayor of Cork, was assassinated in March 1920 by local RIC men under the command of an Inspector General who had been a 'plague on the local Catholic population'. The [[Burning of Cork]] city on December 11, 1920 was carried out by K Company of the Auxiliary Division, in reprisal for an IRA ambush at Dillon's Cross.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Hopkinson, The Irish War of Independence, (2002), p.83)&lt;/ref&gt; The shooting dead by Crown forces of 13 civilians at [[Croke Park]] on [[Bloody Sunday (1920)|Bloody Sunday]], in retaliation for the killing of British intelligence officers was carried out by a mixed force of military, Auxiliaries and RIC, though it is not clear who initiated the shooting.&lt;ref&gt;Charles Townshend, The Republic, The Fight for Irish Independence (2013), p.201-202&lt;/ref&gt; In the aftermath, &quot;The army blamed the Auxiliaries and the Auxiliaries blamed the regular police&quot;.&lt;ref&gt; Townshend, p.202&lt;/ref&gt;  Most Republicans did not make a distinction, and &quot;Black and Tans&quot; was often used as a catch-all term for all police groups.

===Reaction===
The actions of the Black and Tans alienated public opinion in both Ireland and Great Britain. Their violent tactics encouraged the Irish public to increase their covert support of the IRA, while the British public pressed for a move towards a peaceful resolution. 

In January 1921, the British Labour Commission produced a report on the situation in Ireland which was highly critical of the government's security policy. It said the government, in forming the Black and Tans, had &quot;liberated forces which it is not at present able to dominate&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Labour Commission&quot;/&gt; [[E. F. L. Wood, 1st Earl of Halifax|Edward Wood]] MP, better known as the future [[Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs|Foreign Secretary]] Lord Halifax, rejected force and urged the British government to make an offer to the Irish &quot;conceived on the most generous lines&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Frederick Smith, 2nd Earl of Birkenhead|Lord Birkenhead]], ''Halifax'' (Hamish Hamilton, 1965), p. 122.&lt;/ref&gt; Sir [[John Simon, 1st Viscount Simon|John Simon]] MP, another future Foreign Secretary, was also horrified at the tactics being used. [[Lionel Curtis]], writing in the imperialist journal ''[[The Round Table Journal|The Round Table]]'', wrote: &quot;If the British Commonwealth can only be preserved by such means, it would become a negation of the principle for which it has stood&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Lionel Curtis, ''The Round Table'', Vol. XI, No. 43 (June 1921), p. 505.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[George V of the United Kingdom|King]], senior Anglican bishops, MPs from the [[Liberal Party (UK)|Liberal]] and [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour]] parties, [[Oswald Mosley]], [[Jan Smuts]], the [[Trades Union Congress]] and parts of the press were increasingly critical of the actions of the Black and Tans. [[Mahatma Gandhi]] said of the British peace offer: &quot;It is not fear of losing more lives that has compelled a reluctant offer from England but it is the shame of any further imposition of agony upon a people that loves liberty above everything else&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Lawrence James, ''The Rise and Fall of the British Empire'' (Abacus, 1998), p. 384.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Disbandment==
More than one-third left the service before they were disbanded along with the rest of the RIC in 1922, an extremely high wastage rate, and well over half received government pensions. A total of over 500 members of the RIC died in the conflict and more than 600 were wounded. Some sources have stated that 525 police were killed in the conflict, including 152 Black and Tans and 44 Auxiliaries.&lt;ref name=&quot;irishtimes jan 2020&quot;/&gt; This figure of total police killed would also include 72 members of the Ulster Special Constabulary killed between 1920 and 1922 &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Ulster Special Constabulary 1921-1970 |website=National Police Officers Roll of Honour and Remembrance |url= http://www.policerollofhonour.org.uk/forces/n_ireland/usc/usc_roll.htm }}&lt;/ref&gt; and 12 members of the [[Dublin Metropolitan Police]].&lt;ref&gt;Jim Herlihy, The Dublin Metropolitan Police, a Short History and Genealogical Guide, Four Courts Press, 2001 p.182&lt;/ref&gt;

Many Black and Tans were left unemployed after the RIC was disbanded and about 3,000 were in need of financial assistance after their employment in Ireland was terminated.&lt;ref&gt; [https://www.theirishstory.com/2020/01/13/the-black-and-tans-and-auxiliaries-an-overview/ |Sean William Gannon The Black and Tans and Auxiliaries - An Overview, The Irish Story, January 2020]&lt;/ref&gt; About 250 Black and Tans and Auxiliaries, among over 1,300 former RIC personnel, joined the [[Royal Ulster Constabulary]]. Another 700 joined the [[Palestine Police Force]] which was led by former RIC head, Henry Hugh Tudor. Others were resettled in Canada or elsewhere by the RIC Resettlement branch.&lt;ref&gt; [https://www.theirishstory.com/2020/01/13/the-black-and-tans-and-auxiliaries-an-overview/ |Sean William Gannon The Black and Tans and Auxiliaries - An Overview, The Irish Story, January 2020]&lt;/ref&gt; Those who returned to civilian life sometimes had problems re-integrating. At least two former Black and Tans were hanged for murder in Britain and another (Scott Cullen) wanted for murder committed suicide before the police could arrest him.&lt;ref&gt;Bennett, Richard ''The Black and Tans''(London 1959), p. 222&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
Due to the ferocity of the Tans' behaviour in Ireland and the numerous [[war crimes]] they committed, feelings continue to run high regarding their actions. The term can still stir bad reactions because of their remembered brutality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.irishexaminer.com/ireland/nike-forced-to-run-like-hell-away-over-black-and-tan-trainer-branding-187151.html |title=Nike forced to run like hell away over Black and Tan trainer branding|date=15 March 2012|publisher=|accessdate=6 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of the best known Irish Republican songs is [[Dominic Behan]]'s &quot;[[Come out Ye Black and Tans]]&quot;. The [[Irish War of Independence]] is sometimes referred to as the &quot;Tan War&quot; or &quot;Black-and-Tan War.&quot; This term was preferred by those who fought on the anti-Treaty side in the [[Irish Civil War]] and is still used by Republicans today. The &quot;Cogadh na Saoirse&quot; (&quot;War of Independence&quot;) medal, awarded since 1941 by the [[Government of Ireland|Irish government]] to IRA veterans of the War of Independence, bears a ribbon with two vertical stripes in black and tan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.militaryarchives.ie/fileadmin/user_upload/Publications/Medals_of_the_Irish_Defence_Forces/Medals_of_the_Irish_Defence_Forces.html#p=94 |title=Medals of the Irish Defence Forces |year=2010 |publisher=militaryarchives.ie |page=94 |accessdate=22 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.irishmedals.ie/Black-and-Tan-Medal.php |title=1919 – 1921 War of Independence |accessdate=6 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/hi/english/events/northern_ireland/history/newsid_64000/64204.stm BBC News Northern Ireland ''1917–20 The Road to Partition'' posted March 18, 1999]
* [http://eprints.qut.edu.au/archive/00000009/01/Ainsworth_Black_conf.PDF &quot;The Black &amp; Tans and Auxiliaries in Ireland, 1920–1921: Their Origins, Roles and Legacy&quot;, by John Ainsworth, 2001]
* D. M. Leeson: [https://encyclopedia.1914-1918-online.net/article/black_and_tans_and_auxiliaries/ Black and Tans and Auxiliaries], in: [https://encyclopedia.1914-1918-online.net/home.html/ 1914-1918-online. International Encyclopedia of the First World War].
* [http://homepage.tinet.ie/~abbeydorney/book/burning.html Account of the Burning of Abbeydorney, Co. Kerry]
* [http://eprints.qut.edu.au/6/1/British_Security_Policy_in_Ireland.pdf ''British Security Policy in Ireland, 1920–1921''] Ainsworth, John S. (2001) Australian Journal of Irish Studies, 1. pp.&amp;nbsp;176–90
* [https://archive.is/20130217215646/http://www.kennys.ie/News/OldGalway/30112006-BlackandTans/ Black &amp; Tans in Galway] (first hand account and photos)
* [https://archive.is/20130217221500/http://www.kennys.ie/News/OldGalway/16042009_seanbroderick/ Sean Broderick and the Black &amp; Tans] (first hand account and photos from Galway)
* [https://archive.is/20130217175957/http://www.kennys.ie/News/OldGalway/10112005-FatherMichaelGriffin/ Father Michael Griffin] (first hand account and photos from Galway)

{{DEFAULTSORT:Black And Tans}}
[[Category:Irish War of Independence]]
[[Category:Royal Irish Constabulary]]
[[Category:Paramilitary organisations based in Ireland]]
[[Category:Political repression in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:1919 establishments in Ireland]]
[[Category:1919 establishments in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:1922 disestablishments in Ireland]]
[[Category:1922 establishments in the United Kingdom]]</text>
      <sha1>it3j2g3344z7kwgby0dvac6xy2vqnyy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
