  <page>
    <title>Barbagia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4995</id>
    <revision>
      <id>875777463</id>
      <parentid>875777247</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-12-28T23:06:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dk1919 Franking</username>
        <id>12748534</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{unreferenced|date=June 2009|bot=yes}}
[[File:Rifugi Monte Ortobene 018.JPG|thumb|right|[[Nuoro]], the main urban center in Barbagia]]
[[File:Sardegna Barbaria.png|thumbnail|The Barbaria (in blue) and the Roman controlled regions of Sardinia (in yellow)]]

'''Barbagia''' ({{lang-sc|Barbàgia}} or {{lang|sc|Barbàza}}) is a mountain area of inner [[Sardinia]]. It is a [[natural region]] mostly contained in the [[province of Nuoro]] and located alongside the [[Gennargentu]] massif.

The name comes from [[Cicero]], who described it as a land of [[barbarians]] (''Barbaria'', Βαρβαρία in [[Ancient Greek]]). This word derives from the Greek Βάρβαρος, which means &quot;stuttering&quot;. The [[Sardinians]] from this area were also known, by the [[Ancient Rome|ancient Romans]], with the pejorative term ''latrones mastrucati'', which means &quot;thieves with a rough garment in wool&quot;; Roman domination in this part of Sardinia was never more than nominal.

In 594, Pope [[Gregory the Great]] wrote a letter to [[Hospito]], a Christian whom he calls the &quot;leader of the Barbaricini&quot; (''dux barbaricinorum''). Hospito apparently permitted the evangelisation of pagan Barbagia by Christian missionaries.

The area is usually divided into five Barbagias: the Barbagia of [[Ollolai]], the [[Barbagia di Seulo|Barbagia of Seulo]], the [[Barbagia of Belvì]], the [[Mandrolisai]], and finally the ''Barbagia Trigònia'', the historical name by which the area of [[Ogliastra]] was once referred to. The latter two are named after a sub-region, and the others after their main villages.

The area is full of hard hills and mountains, and there is little human presence. Barbagia is one of the least populated areas in Europe, which has allowed Barbagia to preserve its cultural and natural treasures. Barbagia is one of the few Sardinian regions where the [[Sardinian language]] in its own varieties, both [[Logudorese dialect|Nuorese]] and [[Campidanese dialect|Campidanese]], is still spoken on an everyday basis, while the rest of the island has already undergone [[language shift|shift]] to Italian.

One of the most important villages is [[Gavoi]]. [[Orgosolo]] was famous for its bandits and kidnappers and typical [[murals]]. [[Oliena]] is well known for its [[wine]]s (especially the ''Nepente'', a  wine made with [[Cannonau]] grapes). Another well known town is [[Fonni]], the highest town in Sardinia at more than 1,000 meters above sea level. Fonni is also the gateway to the Gennargentu mountain system.

The economy consists of agriculture, sheep breeding, art and tradition related business, tourism and light industry.

==See also==
*[[Cantu a tenore]]

{{coord|40|9.2|scale:500000|display=title}}

[[Category:Geography of Sardinia]]
[[Category:Geographical, historical and cultural regions of Italy]]
[[Category:Blue Zones]]
[[Category:Natural regions]]
[[Category:History of Sardinia]]</text>
      <sha1>mpgsl7n0gkjjqa2uebh3flwkp80xf4y</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
