  <page>
    <title>Born again</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4950</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942850662</id>
      <parentid>941180756</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T06:54:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>VarjoGrayJay</username>
        <id>36902145</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Origin */ typographical correction</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|the Christian term|other uses|Born Again (disambiguation){{!}}Born Again}}
{{Short description|Evangelical Christian term}}
{{Use American English|date = February 2019}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2017}}

'''Born again''', or to experience the '''new birth''', is a phrase, particularly in [[evangelicalism]], that refers to &quot;spiritual rebirth&quot;, or a [[Regeneration (theology)|regeneration]] of the human spirit from the [[Holy Spirit in Christianity|Holy Spirit]], contrasted with physical birth.

In contemporary Christian usage, the term is distinct from sometimes similar terms used in mainstream [[Christianity]] to refer to being or becoming Christian, which is linked to [[baptism]]. Individuals who profess to be &quot;born again&quot; often state that they have a personal relationship with [[Jesus in Christianity|Jesus Christ]].&lt;ref name=Price&gt;{{cite book|author=Robert M. Price|title=Beyond Born Again: Toward Evangelical Maturity|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MEYaWhQnd0QC&amp;pg=PA53&amp;dq=personal+relationship+with+jesus+christ+born+again#v=onepage&amp;q=personal%20relationship%20with%20jesus%20christ%20born%20again&amp;f=false|publisher=[[Wildside Press]]|quote=&quot;I have a personal relationship with Jesus Christ.&quot; If you are an Evangelical Christian you can remember saying these words probably more times than you can count. If on the other hand you are not &quot;Born Again,&quot; you may have heard this phrase from an Evangelical inviting you to establish such a relationship with Christ.|year=1993|accessdate=30 July 2011|isbn=9781434477484}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Bornstein&gt;{{cite book|author=Erica Bornstein|title=The spirit of development: Protestant NGOs, morality, and economics in Zimbabwe|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RQM1kPlOFBkC&amp;pg=PA81&amp;dq=personal+relationship+with+jesus+christ+born+again#v=onepage&amp;q=personal%20relationship%20with%20jesus%20christ%20born%20again&amp;f=false|publisher=[[Stanford University Press]]|quote=A senior staff member in World Vision's California office elaborated on the importance of being &quot;born again,&quot; emphasizing a fundamental &quot;relationship&quot; between individuals and Jesus Christ: &quot;...the importance of a personal relationship with Christ [is] that it's not just a matter of going to Christ or being baptized when you are an infant. We believe that people need to be regenerated. They need a spiritual rebirth. The need to be born again. ...You must be born again before you can see, or enter, the Kingdom of Heaven.&quot;|year=2005|accessdate=30 July 2011|isbn=9780804753364}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Lever&gt;{{cite book|author=A. B. Lever|title=And God Said...|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=d1fWE9H8zJYC&amp;pg=PA291&amp;dq=personal+relationship+with+jesus+christ+born+again#v=onepage&amp;q=personal%20relationship%20with%20jesus%20christ%20born%20again&amp;f=false|quote=From speaking to other Christians I know that the distinction of a born again believer is a personal experience of God that leads to a personal relationship with Him.|year=2007|accessdate=30 July 2011|isbn=9781604771152}}&lt;/ref&gt; The phrase &quot;born again&quot; is also used as an adjective to describe individual members of the movement who espouse this belief, as well as the movement itself (&quot;born-again Christian&quot; and the &quot;born-again movement&quot;).

==Origin==

The term is derived from an event in the [[Gospel of John]] in which the words of [[Jesus]] were not understood by a Jewish pharisee, [[Nicodemus]].
{{Quote |text=Jesus replied, &quot;Very truly I tell you, no one can see the kingdom of God unless they are born again.&quot; &quot;How can someone be born when they are old?&quot; Nicodemus asked. &quot;Surely they cannot enter a second time into their mother's womb to be born!&quot; Jesus answered, &quot;Very truly I tell you, no one can enter the kingdom of God unless they are born of water and the Spirit.&quot; |title=Gospel of John |source={{bibleref2|John|3:3-5|NIV|chapter 3, verses 3–5, NIV}}}}

John's Gospel was written in [[Koine Greek]], and the original text is ambiguous which results in a [[double entendre]] that Nicodemus misunderstands.  The word translated as ''again'' is ἄνωθεν (''ánōtʰen''), which could mean either &quot;a second time&quot;, or &quot;from above&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;jesusbefore&quot; /&gt;  Nicodemus takes only the literal meaning from Jesus's statement, while Jesus clarifies that he means more of a spirtual rebirth from above.  English translations have to pick one sense of the phrase or another; the NIV, [[King James Version]], and [[Revised Version]] use &quot;born again&quot;, while the [[New Revised Standard Version]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleref2c|John|3:3|NRSV|Jn 3:3 NET}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[New English Translation]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleref2c|John|3:3|NET|Jn 3:3 NET}}&lt;/ref&gt; prefer the &quot;born from above&quot; translation.&lt;ref name = &quot;MSM&quot; /&gt;  Most versions will note the alternative sense of the phrase ''anōthen'' in a footnote.

Edwyn Hoskyns argues that &quot;born from above&quot; is to be preferred as the fundamental meaning and he drew attention to phrases such as &quot;birth of the Spirit ({{bibleref2|Jn|1:5|KJV|v.5}})&quot;, &quot;birth from God (cf. {{bibleref2|Jn|1:12-13|KJV}}; {{bibleref2|1Jn|2:29|KJV}}, {{bibleref2-nb|1Jn|3:9|KJV}}, {{bibleref2-nb|1Jn|4:7|KJV}}, {{bibleref2-nb|1Jn|5:18|KJV}})&quot; but maintains that this necessarily carries with it an emphasis upon the newness of the life as given by God himself.&lt;ref&gt;Hoskyns, Sir Edwyn C. and Davy, F.N.(ed), ''The Fourth Gospel'', Faber &amp; Faber 2nd ed. 1947, pp. 211,212&lt;/ref&gt;

The final use of the phrase occurs in the [[First Epistle of Peter]], rendered in the King James Version as:
{{Quote|Seeing ye have purified your souls in obeying the truth through the Spirit unto unfeigned love of the brethren, [see that ye] love one another with a pure heart fervently: / Being born again, not of corruptible seed, but of incorruptible, by the word of God, which liveth and abideth for ever.{{Bibleref2c|1Peter|1:22-23|KJV|1 Peter 1:22-23}}}}

Here, the Greek word translated as &quot;born again&quot; is {{lang|el|ἀναγεγεννημένοι}} ({{transl|el|''anagegennēménoi''}}).&lt;ref name = &quot;SJF&quot;&gt;Fisichella, SJ., ''Taking Away the Veil: To See Beyond the Curtain of Illusion'', iUniverse, 2003, pp. 55-56.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Interpretations===
The traditional Jewish understanding of the promise of salvation is interpreted as being rooted in &quot;the seed of Abraham&quot;; that is, physical lineage from Abraham. Jesus explained to Nicodemus that this doctrine was in error—that every person must have two births—natural birth of the physical body and another of the water and the spirit.&lt;ref&gt;Emmons, Samuel B. ''A Bible Dictionary.'' BiblioLife, 2008. {{ISBN|978-0-554-89108-8}}.&lt;/ref&gt; This discourse with Nicodemus established the Christian belief that all human beings—whether Jew or Gentile—must be &quot;born again&quot; of the spiritual seed of Christ. The [[Apostle Peter]] further reinforced this understanding in {{Bibleref2|1Peter|1:23|KJV|1 Peter 1:23}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;SJF&quot; /&gt; The ''Catholic Encyclopedia'' states that &quot;[a] controversy existed in the primitive church over the interpretation of the expression ''the [[seed of Abraham]]''. It is [the Apostle Paul's] teaching in one instance that all who are Christ's by faith are Abraham's seed, and heirs according to promise. He is concerned, however, with the fact that the promise is not being fulfilled to the seed of Abraham (referring to the Jews).&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Driscoll, James F. &quot;Divine Promise (in Scripture)&quot;. The Catholic Encyclopedia. Vol. 12. New York: Robert Appleton Company, 1911. 15 November 2009.[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/12453a.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Charles Hodge]] writes that &quot;The subjective change wrought in the soul by the grace of God, is variously designated in Scripture&quot; with terms such as ''new birth'', ''resurrection'', ''new life'', ''new creation'', ''renewing of the mind'', ''dying to sin and living to righteousness'', and ''translation from darkness to light''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hodge1&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/hodge/theology3.iii.i.i.html|title=Systematic Theology - Volume III - Christian Classics Ethereal Library|website=www.ccel.org|access-date=2019-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Jesus used the &quot;birth&quot; analogy in tracing spiritual newness of life to a divine beginning. Contemporary Christian theologians have provided explanations for &quot;born from above&quot; being a more accurate translation of the original Greek word transliterated ''anōthen.''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblestudytools.com/lexicons/greek/nas/anothen.html ''The New Testament Greek Lexicon.''] 30 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Frank Stagg (theologian)|Theologian Frank Stagg]] cites two reasons why the newer translation is significant:
# The emphasis &quot;from ''above''&quot; (implying &quot;from ''Heaven''&quot;) calls attention to the source of the &quot;newness of life&quot;. Stagg writes that the word &quot;again&quot; does not include the ''source'' of the new kind of beginning;
# More than personal improvement is needed. &quot;a new destiny requires a new origin, and the new origin must be from God.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Stagg, Evelyn and Frank. ''Woman in the World of Jesus.'' Philadelphia: Westminster Press, 1978. {{ISBN|0-664-24195-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An early example of the term in its more modern use appears in the sermons of [[John Wesley]]. In the sermon entitled ''A New Birth'' he writes, &quot;none can be holy unless he be born again&quot;, and &quot;except he be born again, none can be happy even in this world. For ... a man should not be happy who is not holy.&quot; Also, &quot;I say, [a man] may be born again and so become an heir of salvation.&quot; Wesley also states infants who are baptized are born again, but for adults it is different:
{{quote|our church supposes, that all who are baptized in their infancy, are at the same time born again. ... But ... it is sure all of riper years, who are baptized, are not at the same time born again.&lt;ref&gt;Wesley, J., ''The works of  the Reverend John Wesley'', Methodist Episcopal Church, 1831, pp. 405–406.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

A [[Unitarianism|Unitarian]] work called ''The Gospel Anchor'' noted in the 1830s that the phrase was not mentioned by the other Evangelists, nor by the Apostles except Peter. &quot;It was not regarded by any of the Evangelists but John of sufficient importance to record.&quot; It adds that without John, &quot;we should hardly have known that it was necessary for one to be born again.&quot; This suggests that &quot;the text and context was meant to apply to Nicodemus particularly, and not to the world.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;LeFevre, CF. and Williamson, ID., ''The Gospel anchor''. Troy, NY, 1831–32, p. 66. [https://books.google.com/books?id=3T4rAAAAYAAJ&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Historicity===
Scholars of [[Historical Jesus]], that is, attempting to ascertain how closely the stories of Jesus match the historical events they are based on, generally treat Jesus's conversation with Nicodemus in [[John 3]] with skepticism.  It details what is presumably a private conversation between Jesus and Nicodemus, with none of the disciples seemingly attending, making it unclear how a record of this conversation was acquired.  In addition, the conversation is recorded in no other ancient Christian source other than John and works based on John.&lt;ref name=&quot;jesusbefore&quot; /&gt;  According to [[Bart Ehrman]], the larger issue is that the same problem English translations of the Bible have with the Greek ἄνωθεν (''anōthen'') is a problem in the [[Aramaic language]] as well: there is no single word in Aramaic that means both &quot;again&quot; and &quot;from above&quot;, yet the conversation rests on Nicodemus making this misunderstanding.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://etb-biblical-errancy.blogspot.com/2012/04/born-again-dialogue-in-gospel-of-john.html|title=Biblical Errancy: The &quot;Born Again&quot; Dialogue In the Gospel of John|website=Biblical Errancy|access-date=2019-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;  As the conversation was between two Jews in Jerusalem, where Aramaic was the native language, there is no reason to think that they'd have spoken in Greek.&lt;ref name=&quot;jesusbefore&quot; /&gt;  This implies that even if based on a real conversation, the author of John heavily modified it to include Greek wordplay and idiom.&lt;ref name=&quot;jesusbefore&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=Jesus Before the Gospels: How the Earliest Christians Remembered, Changed, and Invented Their Stories of the Savior |last=Ehrman |first=Bart |authorlink=Bart Ehrman | pages = 108&amp;ndash;109 | publisher=[[HarperOne]] | year=2016 | isbn=978-0062285201}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Denominational positions==
''The Oxford Handbook of Religion and American Politics'' notes: &quot;The [[General Social Survey|GSS]] ... has asked a born-again question on three occasions ... 'Would you say you have been 'born again' or have had a 'born-again' experience?&quot; The Handbook says that &quot;Evangelical, black, and Latino Protestants tend to respond similarly, with about two-thirds of each group answering in the affirmative. In contrast, only about one third of mainline Protestants and one sixth of Catholics (Anglo and Latino) claim a born-again experience.&quot; However, the handbook suggests that &quot;born-again questions are poor measures even for capturing evangelical respondents. ... it is likely that people who report a born-again experience also claim it as an identity.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''The Oxford Handbook of Religion and American Politics'', OUP, p16.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Catholicism===
Historically, the classic text from [[John 3]] was consistently interpreted by the early church fathers as a reference to baptism.&lt;ref&gt;Joel C. Elworthy, Ed. ''Ancient Christian Commentary on Scripture, New Testament IVa'', ''John 1-10'' (Downers Grove: Intervarsity Press, 2007), p. 109-110&lt;/ref&gt; Modern Catholic interpreters have noted that the phrase 'born from above' or 'born again' (John 3:3) is clarified as 'being born of water and Spirit' (John 3:5).

Catholic commentator John F. McHugh notes, &quot;Rebirth, and the commencement of this new life, are said to come about ἐξ ὕδατος καὶ πνεύματος, of water and spirit. This phrase (without the article) refers to a rebirth which the early Church regarded as taking place through baptism (1 Pet 1.3, 23; Tit 3.5).&quot;&lt;ref&gt;John F. McHugh, ''John 1-4, The International Critical Commentary'' (New York: T&amp;T Clark, 2009), p. 227&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''[[Catechism of the Catholic Church]]'' notes that the essential elements of Christian initiation are: &quot;proclamation of the Word, acceptance of the Gospel entailing conversion, profession of faith, Baptism itself, and the outpouring of the Holy Spirit, and admission to Eucharistic communion&quot; (CCC 1229). Baptism gives the person the grace of forgiveness for all prior sins; it makes the newly baptized person a new creature and an adopted son of God (2 Corinthians 5:17; 2 Peter 1:4); it incorporates them into the Body of Christ (Ephesians 4:25) and creates a sacramental bond of unity leaving an indelible mark on our souls (CCC 1262-1274). &quot;Incorporated into Christ by Baptism, the person baptized is configured to Christ. Baptism seals the Christian with the indelible spiritual mark (character) of his belonging to Christ. No sin can erase this mark, even if sin prevents Baptism from bearing the fruits of salvation. Given once for all, Baptism cannot be repeated&quot; (CCC 1272). The Holy Spirit is involved with each aspect of the movement of grace. &quot;The first work of the grace of the Holy Spirit is conversion. ... Moved by grace, man turns toward God and away from sin, thus accepting forgiveness and righteousness from on high&quot; (CCC 1989).

The Catholic Church also teaches that under special circumstances the need for water baptism can be superseded by the Holy Spirit in a 'baptism of desire', such as when [[catechumen]]s die or are martyred prior to receiving baptism (CCC 1260).

[[Pope John Paul II]] wrote about &quot;the problem of children baptized in infancy [who] come for catechesis in the parish without receiving any other initiation into the faith and still without any explicit personal attachment to Jesus Christ&quot; (''Catechesi Tradendae'' 19).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://w2.vatican.va/content/john-paul-ii/en/apost_exhortations/documents/hf_jp-ii_exh_16101979_catechesi-tradendae.html|title=Catechesi Tradendae (October 16, 1979) - John Paul II|publisher=|accessdate=17 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; He noted that &quot;being a Christian means saying 'yes' to Jesus Christ, but let us remember that this 'yes' has two levels: It consists of surrendering to the word of God and relying on it, but it also means, at a later stage, endeavoring to know better&amp;mdash;and better the profound meaning of this word&quot; (CT 20).

The modern expression being &quot;born again&quot; is really about the concept of &quot;conversion&quot;.
	
The National Directory of Catechesis (published by the United States Conference of Catholic Bishops, USCCB) defines conversion as, &quot;the acceptance of a personal relationship with Christ, a sincere adherence to him, and a willingness to conform one's life to his.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic Bishops 2005 p. 48&quot;&gt;''United States Conference of Catholic Bishops, National Directory of Catechesis'' (2005) p. 48&lt;/ref&gt; To put it more simply &quot;Conversion to Christ involves making a genuine commitment to him and a personal decision to follow him as his disciple.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic Bishops 2005 p. 48&quot;/&gt;
 	
Echoing the writings of Pope John Paul II, the ''National Directory of Catechesis'' describes a new intervention required by our modern world called the &quot;New Evangelization&quot;. The New Evangelization is directed to the Church herself, to the baptized who were never effectively evangelized before, to those who have never made a personal commitment to Christ and the Gospel, to those formed by the values of the secular culture, to those who have lost a sense of faith, and to those who are alienated.&lt;ref&gt;''United States Conference of Catholic Bishops, National Directory of Catechesis'' (2005) p. 47&lt;/ref&gt;

Declan O'Sullivan, co-founder of the Catholic Men's Fellowship and knight of the [[Sovereign Military Order of Malta]], wrote that the &quot;New Evangelization emphasizes the personal encounter with Jesus Christ as a pre-condition for spreading the gospel. The born-again experience is not just an emotional, mystical high; the really important matter is what happened in the convert's life after the moment or period of radical change.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=O'Sullivan|first= Declan |title=The Evangelizing Catholic|year=2014|publisher=FriesenPress |language=English|page=9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lutheranism===
The [[Lutheranism|Lutheran Church]] holds that &quot;we are cleansed of our sins and born again and renewed in Holy Baptism by the Holy Ghost. But she also teaches that whoever is baptized must, through daily contrition and repentance, drown The Old Adam so that daily a new man come forth and arise who walks before God in righteousness and purity forever. She teaches that whoever lives in sins after his baptism has again lost the grace of baptism.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Walther2008&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Walther|first=Carl Ferdinand Wilhelm|title=Sermons and prayers for Reformation and Luther commemorations|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qWqjkSf4zKMC&amp;pg=PA27|accessdate=10 April 2014|year=2008|publisher=Joel Baseley|isbn=9780982252321|page=27|quote=Furthermore, the Lutheran Church also thoroughly teaches that we are cleansed of our sins and born again and renewed in Holy Baptism by the Holy Ghost. But she also teaches that whoever is baptized must, though daily contrition and repentance, drown The Old Adam so that daily a new man come forth and arise who walks before God in righteousness and purity forever. She teaches that whoever lives in sins after his baptism has again lost the grace of baptism.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Anglicanism===
The phrase ''born again'' is mentioned in the [[39 Articles]] of the [[Anglican Church]] in article XV, entitled &quot;Of Christ alone without Sin&quot;. In part, it reads: &quot;sin, as S. John saith, was not in Him. But all we the rest, although baptized and born again in Christ, yet offend in many things: and if we say we have no sin, we deceive ourselves, and the truth is not in us.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eskimo.com/~lhowell/bcp1662/articles/articles.html] Accessed 8 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the phrase &quot;baptized and born again in Christ&quot; occurs in Article XV, the reference is clearly to the scripture passage in John 3:3.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccepiscopal.org/handouts/bcp-1662.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reformed===
In Reformed theology, [[Holy Baptism]] is the sign and the seal of one's regeneration, which is of comfort to the believer.&lt;ref name=&quot;RCA1992&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Confirmation and the Reformed Church |url=https://www.rca.org/resources/confirmation-and-reformed-church |publisher=[[Reformed Church in America]] |accessdate=19 June 2019 |language=English |date=1992}}&lt;/ref&gt; The time of one's regeneration, however, is a mystery to oneself according to the [[Canons of Dort]].&lt;ref name=&quot;RCA1992&quot;/&gt; 

According to the [[Dutch Reformed Church|Reformed churches]] being born again refers to &quot;the inward working of the Spirit which induces the sinner to respond to the effectual call&quot;. According to the Westminster Shorter Catechism, Q 88, &quot;the outward and ordinary means whereby Christ communicateth to us the benefits of redemption are, his ordinances, especially the word, sacraments, and prayer; all of which are made effectual to the elect for salvation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shortercatechism.com/resources/wsc/wsc_088.html|title=Bible Presbyterian Church Online: WSC Question 88|website=www.shortercatechism.com|accessdate=12 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Effectual calling is &quot;the work of God's Spirit, whereby, convincing us of our sin and misery, enlightening our minds in the knowledge of Christ, and renewing our wills, he doth persuade and enable us to embrace Jesus Christ, freely offered to us in the gospel.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Shorter Westminster Catechism, Question 31''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reformed.com/publications/bornagain.php |title=Do You Know the Truth About Being Born Again? |last=Pribble |first=Stephen |publisher=Reformed Presbyterian Church |accessdate=10 April 2014 |location=Southfield |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140413131944/http://www.reformed.com/publications/bornagain.php |archivedate=13 April 2014 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Reformed theology, &quot;regeneration precedes faith.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sproul2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Sproul|first=R. C.|title=What is Reformed Theology?: Understanding the Basics|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dF3w9I0kxxMC&amp;pg=PA179|accessdate=10 April 2014|date=1 June 2005|publisher=Baker Books|isbn=9781585586523|page=179}}&lt;/ref&gt; Samuel Storms writes that, &quot;Calvinists insist that the sole cause of regeneration or being born again is the will of God. God first sovereignly and efficaciously regenerates, and only in consequence of that do we act. Therefore, the individual is passive in regeneration, neither preparing himself nor making himself receptive to what God will do. Regeneration is a change wrought in us by God, not an autonomous act performed by us for ourselves.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Storms2007&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Storms|first=Samuel|title=Chosen for Life: The Case for Divine Election|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kh6xpUFPG8gC&amp;pg=PA150|accessdate=10 April 2014|date=25 January 2007|publisher=Crossway|isbn=9781433519635|page=150}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Methodism===
In [[Methodism]], the &quot;new birth is necessary for salvation because it marks the move toward holiness. That comes with faith.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Joyner2007&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Joyner|first=F. Belton|title=United Methodist Questions, United Methodist Answers: Exploring Christian Faith|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5wH-h0WQ0aEC&amp;pg=PA39|accessdate=10 April 2014|year=2007|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|isbn=9780664230395|page=39|quote=The new birth is necessary for salvation because it marks the move toward holiness. That comes with faith.}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[John Wesley]], founder of the Methodist Church, held that the New Birth &quot;is that great change which God works in the soul when he brings it into life, when he raises it from the death of sin to the life of righteousness&quot; (''Works'', vol. 2, pp.&amp;nbsp;193–194).&lt;ref name=&quot;Joyner2007&quot;/&gt; In the life of a Christian, the new birth is considered the [[first work of grace]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Stokes1998&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Stokes|first=Mack B.|title=Major United Methodist Beliefs|year=1998|publisher=Abingdon Press|language=English|isbn=9780687082124|page=95}}&lt;/ref&gt; In keeping with [[Wesleyan-Arminian covenant theology]], the ''[[Articles of Religion (Methodist)|Articles of Religion]]'', in Article XVII—Of Baptism, state that [[baptism]] is a &quot;sign of regeneration or the new birth.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archives.umc.org/interior.asp?ptid=1&amp;mid=1651 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060427002238/http://archives.umc.org/interior.asp?ptid=1&amp;mid=1651 |url-status=dead |archive-date=27 April 2006 |title=The Articles of Religion of the Methodist Church XVI-XVIII |year=2004 |work=The Book of Discipline of The United Methodist Church |publisher=The United Methodist Church |accessdate=10 April 2014 |quote=Article XVII—Of Baptism: Baptism is not only a sign of profession and mark of difference whereby Christians are distinguished from others that are not baptized; but it is also a sign of regeneration or the new birth. The Baptism of young children is to be retained in the Church. }}&lt;/ref&gt; ''The Methodist Visitor'' in describing this doctrine, admonishes individuals: &quot;'Ye must be born again.' Yield to God that He may perform this work in and for you. Admit Him to your heart. 'Believe on the Lord Jesus Christ, and thou shalt be saved.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Methodist Visitor|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=uEAEAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA137|year=1876|publisher=Elliot Stock, 62, Paternoster Row, E.C. |page=137|quote=&quot;Ye must be born again.&quot; Yield to God that He may perform this work in and for you. Admit Him to your heart. &quot;Believe on the Lord Jesus Christ, and thou shalt be saved.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RicheyRowe1993&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Richey|first1=Russell E.|last2=Rowe|first2=Kenneth E.|last3=Schmidt|first3=Jean Miller|title=Perspectives on American Methodism: interpretive essays|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=P1vuAAAAMAAJ|accessdate=10 April 2014|date=19 January 1993|publisher=Kingswood Books|isbn=9780687307821}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Evangelicalism===
Belief in the New Birth is an essential and distinctive element of [[evangelicalism|Evangelical Christianity]].&lt;ref&gt;Brian Stiller, ''Evangelicals Around the World: A Global Handbook for the 21st Century'', Éditions Thomas Nelson, USA, 2015, p. 34&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Randall Herbert Balmer, ''Encyclopedia of Evangelicalism'', Westminster John Knox Press, USA, 2002, p. 236&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Orlando O. Espín, James B. Nickoloff, ''An Introductory Dictionary of Theology and Religious Studies'', Liturgical Press, USA, 2007, p.  425&lt;/ref&gt; For Evangelical Christians, the new birth always occurs before [[Believer's baptism|baptism]].&lt;ref&gt;Michael J. Meiring, ''Preserving Evangelical Unity: Welcoming Diversity in Non-Essentials'', Wipf and Stock Publishers, USA, 2009, p. 117&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Baptist churches]], it is synonymous with the [[Baptism with the Holy Spirit]]; however, it is considered a distinct experience in [[Pentecostalism]], the [[Charismatic Movement]], and the [[Neo-charismatic movement]].&lt;ref&gt;Allan Anderson, ''An Introduction to Pentecostalism: Global Charismatic Christianity'', Cambridge University Press, UK, 2013, p. 184&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Veli-Matti Karkkainen, ''The Spirit in the World: Emerging Pentecostal Theologies in Global Contexts'', Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing, USA, 2009, p. 39&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;Although many evangelicals allow that conversion can be a process, generally they see it as a specific, identifiable moment of time when a person simply and sincerely trusts in Jesus Christ as savior.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;MSM&quot;&gt;Mullen, MS., in Kurian, GT., ''The Encyclopedia of Christian Civilization'', J. Wiley &amp; Sons, 2012, p. 302.&lt;/ref&gt; They understand {{Bibleref2|Romans|10:9}} to indicate a requirement of salvation: &quot;That if you confess with your mouth, 'Jesus is Lord', and believe in your heart that God raised him from the dead, you will be saved.&quot; So, &quot;to be born again&quot; means &quot;to be saved&quot; because to be saved, one must confess Jesus is Lord with one's mouth and believe it in one's heart. Also, to be born again means to follow {{Bibleref2|Romans|10:10}} that &quot;with your heart that you believe and are justified, and it is with your mouth that you profess your faith and are saved&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Graham, RC. ''I healed you with my word'', Xulan, 2007, p. 414.&lt;/ref&gt;  For some evangelical denominations, it is the beginning of the [[sanctification]] of the believer.&lt;ref&gt;Justo L. González, ''Essential Theological Terms'', Westminster John Knox Press, USA, 2005, p. 155&lt;/ref&gt; For others, it is an opportunity to receive entire [[sanctification]].&lt;ref&gt;Roger E. Olson, ''The Westminster Handbook to Evangelical Theology'', Westminster John Knox Press, USA, 2004, p. 319&lt;/ref&gt;

===Jehovah's Witnesses===
[[Jehovah's Witnesses]] believe that individuals do not have the power to choose to be born again, but that God calls and selects his followers &quot;from above&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|journal=The Watchtower|title=The New Birth—A Personal Decision?|date=1 April 2009|pages=5&amp;ndash;6|url=http://wol.jw.org/en/wol/d/r1/lp-e/2009242}}&lt;/ref&gt; Only those belonging to the &quot;[[144000 (number)#Jehovah's Witnesses|144,000]]&quot; are considered to be born again.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Reasoning From the Scriptures|date=1985|chapter=Born Again|chapter-url=http://wol.jw.org/en/wol/d/r1/lp-e/1101989216}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://www.jw.org/en/bible-teachings/questions/what-does-it-mean-to-be-born-again&lt;/ref&gt;

==Disagreements between denominations==
{{Over-quotation|section|date=June 2014}}
The term &quot;born again&quot; is used by several Christian denominations, but there are disagreements on what the term means, and whether members of other denominations are justified in claiming to be born-again Christians.

[[Catholic Answers]] says:{{quote|Catholics should ask Protestants, &quot;Are you born again—the way the Bible understands that concept?&quot; If the Evangelical has not been properly water baptized, he has not been born again &quot;the Bible way,&quot; regardless of what he may think.&lt;ref name=&quot;catholic.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.catholic.com/tract/are-catholics-born-again|title=Are Catholics Born Again? - Catholic Answers|publisher=|accessdate=24 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

On the other hand, an Evangelical site argues:{{quote|Another of many examples is the Catholic who claims he also is &quot;born again.&quot; ... However, what the committed Catholic means is that he received his spiritual birth when he was baptized—either as an infant or when as an adult he converted to Catholicism. That's not what Jesus meant when He told Nicodemus he &quot;must be born again&quot; (Jn 3:3-8). The deliberate adoption of biblical terms which have different meanings for Catholics has become an effective tool in Rome's ecumenical agenda.&lt;ref&gt;McMahon, TA, ''The &quot;Evangelical&quot; Seduction'', [http://www.reachingcatholics.org/seduction.html], Accessed 10 Feb 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The Reformed view of regeneration may be set apart from other outlooks in at least two ways. {{quote|First, classical Roman Catholicism teaches that regeneration occurs at baptism, a view known as baptismal regeneration. Reformed theology has insisted that regeneration may take place at any time in a person's life, even in the womb. It is not somehow the automatic result of baptism. Second, it is common for many other evangelical branches of the church to speak of repentance and faith leading to regeneration (i.e., people are born again only after they exercise saving faith). By contrast, Reformed theology teaches that original sin and total depravity deprive all people of the moral ability and will to exercise saving faith. ... Regeneration is entirely the work of God the Holy Spirit - we can do nothing on our own to obtain it. God alone raises the elect from spiritual death to new life in Christ (Eph. 2:1-10).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thirdmill.org/studybible/note.asp/id/40917|title=Regeneration and New Birth: Must I Be Born Again?|publisher=Third Millennium Ministries|accessdate=10 April 2014|quote=In Reformed theology regeneration, the equivalent to being &quot;born again,&quot; is a technical term referring to God revitalizing a person by implanting new desire, purpose and moral ability that lead to a positive response to the Gospel of Christ.|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140420194927/http://thirdmill.org/studybible/note.asp/id/40917|archive-date=20 April 2014|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==History and usage==
Historically, Christianity has used various [[metaphors]] to describe its [[rite]] of initiation, that is, [[baptismal regeneration|spiritual regeneration]] via the [[sacrament]] of [[baptism]] by the power of the water and the [[Holy Spirit|spirit]]. This remains the common understanding in most of [[Christendom]], held, for example, in [[Roman Catholicism]], [[Eastern Orthodoxy]], [[Oriental Orthodoxy]], [[Anglicanism]],&lt;ref&gt;See the section on Anglicanism in [[Baptismal regeneration#brganglican|Baptismal regeneration]]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lutheranism]], and in much of [[Protestantism]]. However, sometime after the [[Protestant Reformation|Reformation]], [[Evangelicalism]] attributed greater significance to the expression ''born again''&lt;ref name=&quot;GoodWord&quot;&gt;&quot;born-again.&quot; ''Good Word Guide.'' London: A&amp;C Black, 2007. Credo Reference. 30 July 2009&lt;/ref&gt; as an experience of [[religious conversion]] ({{Bibleverse|Heb|10:16|KJV}}), symbolized by deep-water baptism, and rooted in a commitment to one's own personal faith in Jesus Christ for salvation. This same belief is, historically, also an integral part of [[Methodist]] doctrine,&lt;ref name=&quot;Methodist&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Samuel Fallows (Bishop); Herbert Lockwood Willett|url=https://archive.org/details/popularandcriti00willgoog |page=[https://archive.org/details/popularandcriti00willgoog/page/n538 1154]|title=The popular and critical Bible encyclopædia and scriptural dictionary, fully defining and explaining all religious terms, including biographical, geographical, historical, archæological and doctrinal themes, to which is added an exhaustive appendix illustrated with over 600 maps and engravings|publisher=Chicago, Howard-Severance Co.|quote=The New Birth. Regeneration is an important Methodist doctrine, and is the new birth, a change of heart. All Methodists teach that &quot;Except a man be born again, he cannot see the kingdom of God.&quot; It is the work of the Holy Spirit and is a conscious change in the heart and the life.
|year=1901|accessdate=19 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Primal&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Charles Spencer Smith, Daniel Alexander Payne|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gmDZAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA266&amp;dq=born+again+methodism#v=onepage&amp;q=born%20again%20methodism&amp;f=false|title=A History of the African Methodist Episcopal Church|publisher=Johnson Reprint Corporation
|quote=Whatever the Church may do, and there is much that it can and should do, for the betterment of man's physical being, its primal work is the regeneration of man's spiritual nature. Methodism has insisted on this as the supreme end and aim of the Church.|year=1922|accessdate=19 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is connected with the doctrine of [[Justification (theology)|Justification]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Justification&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url= https://books.google.com/books?id=6kI6AAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA172 |author=Robert Southey; Charles Cuthbert Southey|title=The Life of Wesley: And the Rise and Progress of Methodism|page=172
|quote=Connected with his doctrine of the New Birth was that of Justification, which he affirmed to be inseparable from it, yet easily to be distinguished, as being not the same, but of a widely different nature. In order of time, neither of these is before the other; in the moment we are justified by the grace of God, through the redemption that is in Jesus, we are also born of the Spirit; but in order of thinking, as it is termed, Justification precedes the New Birth.
|publisher=[[Nabu Press]]|date=16 March 2010|accessdate=5 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to ''[[Encyclopædia Britannica]]'':
{{quote|'Rebirth' has often been identified with a definite, temporally datable form of 'conversion'. ... With the voluntaristic type, rebirth is expressed in a new alignment of the will, in the liberation of new capabilities and powers that were hitherto undeveloped in the person concerned. With the intellectual type, it leads to an activation of the capabilities for understanding, to the breakthrough of a &quot;vision&quot;. With others it leads to the discovery of an unexpected beauty in the order of nature or to the discovery of the mysterious meaning of history. With still others it leads to a new vision of the moral life and its orders, to a selfless realization of love of neighbour. ... each person affected perceives his life in Christ at any given time as “newness of life.”&lt;ref&gt;''Encyclopædia Britannica'', entry for The Doctrine of Man (from Christianity), 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

According to [[J. Gordon Melton]]:
{{quote|Born again is a phrase used by many Protestants to describe the phenomenon of gaining faith in Jesus Christ. It is an experience when everything they have been taught as Christians becomes real, and they develop a direct and personal relationship with God.&lt;ref&gt;Melton, JG., ''Encyclopedia Of Protestantism (Encyclopedia of World Religions)''&lt;/ref&gt;}}

According to [[Andrew Purves]] and Charles Partee:
{{quote|Sometimes the phrase seems to be judgmental, making a distinction between genuine and nominal Christians. Sometimes ... descriptive, like the distinction between liberal and conservative Christians. Occasionally, the phrase seems historic, like the division between Catholic and Protestant Christians. ... [the term] usually includes the notion of human choice in salvation and excludes a view of divine election by grace alone.&lt;ref&gt;Purves, A. and Partee, C., ''Encountering God: Christian Faith in Turbulent Times'', Westminster John Knox Press, 2000, p. 96&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The term ''born again'' has become widely associated with the [[Evangelicalism|evangelical]] Christian renewal since the late 1960s, first in the United States and then around the world. Associated perhaps initially with [[Jesus movement|Jesus People]] and the Christian counterculture, ''born again'' came to refer to a conversion experience, accepting Jesus Christ as lord and savior in order to be saved from hell and given eternal life with God in heaven, and was increasingly used as a term to identify devout believers.&lt;ref name = &quot;MSM&quot; /&gt; By the mid-1970s, ''born again'' Christians were increasingly referred to in the mainstream media as part of the born again movement.

In 1976, [[Watergate scandal|Watergate]] conspirator [[Chuck Colson]]'s book ''Born Again'' gained international notice. [[Time (magazine)|''Time'' magazine]] named him &quot;One of the 25 most influential Evangelicals in America.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/covers/1101050207/photoessay/5.html The 25 Most Influential Evangelicals in America.] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110624163631/http://www.time.com/time/covers/1101050207/photoessay/5.html |date=24 June 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The term was sufficiently prevalent so that during the year's presidential campaign, [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic party]] nominee [[Jimmy Carter]] described himself as &quot;born again&quot; in the first ''[[Playboy]]'' magazine interview of an American presidential candidate.

Colson describes his path to faith in conjunction with his criminal imprisonment and played a significant role in solidifying the &quot;born again&quot; identity as a [[cultural construct]] in the US. He writes that his spiritual experience followed considerable struggle and hesitancy to have a &quot;personal encounter with God.&quot; He recalls:
{{quote|while I sat alone staring at the sea I love, words I had not been certain I could understand or say fell from my lips: &quot;Lord Jesus, I believe in You. I accept You. Please come into my life. I commit it to You.&quot;  With these few words...came a sureness of mind that matched the depth of feeling in my heart. There came something more: strength and serenity, a wonderful new assurance about life, a fresh perception of myself in the world around me.&lt;ref&gt;Colson, Charles W. ''Born Again.'' Chosen Books (Baker Publishing), 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[Jimmy Carter]] was the first President of the United States to publicly declare that he was born-again, in 1976.&lt;ref&gt;Hough, JF., ''Changing party coalitions'', Algora Publishing, 2006, p. 203.&lt;/ref&gt; By the [[1980 United States presidential election|1980 campaign]], all three major candidates stated that they had been born again.&lt;ref&gt;Utter, GH. and Tru, JL.,''Conservative Christians and political participation: a reference handbook'', ABC-CLIO, 2004, p. 137.&lt;/ref&gt;

Sider and Knippers&lt;ref&gt;Sider, J. and Knippers, D. (eds), ''Toward an Evangelical Public Policy: Political Strategies for the Health of the Nation,'' Baker Books, 2005, p.51.&lt;/ref&gt; state that &quot;[[Ronald Reagan]]'s election that fall [was] aided by the votes of 61% of 'born-again' white Protestants.&quot;

The [[Gallup (company)|Gallup Organization]] reported that &quot;In 2003, 42% of U.S. adults said they were born-again or evangelical; the 2004 percentage is 41%&quot; and that, &quot;[[African American|Black Americans]] are far more likely to identify themselves as born-again or evangelical, with 63% of blacks saying they are born-again, compared with 39% of [[white American]]s. [[Republican Party (United States)|Republicans]] are far more likely to say they are born-again (52%) than [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democrats]] (36%) or independents (32%).&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gallup.com/poll/14632/who-has-been-born-again.aspx |title=Winseman. A.L., ''Who has been born again'', Gallup, 2004 |publisher=Gallup.com |date= |accessdate=11 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Haiven refers to &quot;born-agains&quot; as having &quot;a type of intolerance&quot;. She says, &quot;The instant and thoughtless panaceas of born-again Christianity will be seen as a vast sanctuary by millions of North Americans.&quot; She continues, &quot;Is this sanctuary really a recruitment camp for [[Right-wing politics|right-wing movements]]? It would be naive to think otherwise.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Haiven, J., ''Faith, hope, no charity: an inside look at the born again movement in Canada and the United States,'' New Star Books, 1984, p.218.&lt;/ref&gt;

''The Oxford Handbook of Religion and American Politics'', referring to several studies, reports &quot;that 'born-again' identification is associated with lower support for government anti-poverty programs.&quot; It also notes that &quot;self-reported born-again&quot; Christianity, &quot;strongly shapes attitudes towards economic policy.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Smidt, C., Kellstedt, L., and Guth, J., ''The Oxford Handbook of Religion and American Politics'', Oxford Handbooks Online, 2009, pp.195-196.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Names inspired by the term==
{{main|Renatus}}
The idea of  &quot;rebirth in Christ&quot; has inspired&lt;ref&gt;''Oxford Dictionary of First Names''&lt;/ref&gt; some common European [[Given name|forenames]]: French [[René]]/[[Renée]], Dutch Renaat/Renate, Italian, Spanish and Portuguese [[Renatus|Renato/Renata]], Latin [[Renatus]]/Renata, which all mean &quot;reborn&quot;, &quot;born again&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Chambers's Twentieth Century Dictionary'', W. &amp; R. Chambers (1954) p.1355&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Christianity|Evangelical Christianity}}
* [[Altar call]] – invitation to become a Christian; given at a church service or event
* [[Baptismal regeneration]] – overview of doctrinal debate about the effect of the baptism rite
* [[Born-again virgin]] – a person who, though not still a virgin, chooses to live as one
* [[Dvija]], or twice-born – in [[Hinduism]], a person who has formally taken on the roles of one of the first three [[Caste system in India|castes]]
* [[Evangelism]] – the preaching of the Christian Gospel to others with the object of conversion
* [[Justus Velsius#London: more religious turmoil|Justus Velsius]] – a 16th-century Dutch dissident who promoted the view that through a new birth man could become like Christ
* [[Monergism]] – the belief that being born again is entirely God's work (and not the believer's work)
* [[Sinner's prayer]] – the prayer of a person seeking forgiveness and wanting to become a Christian

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20121123231747/http://www.umcmission.org/Find-Resources/Global-Worship-and-Spiritual-Growth/John-Wesley-Sermons/Sermon-45-The-New-Birth The New Birth], [[John Wesley]], sermon No. 45.  Wesley's teaching on being born again, and argument that it is fundamental to Christianity.

{{DEFAULTSORT:Born Again (Christianity)}}
[[Category:Christian fundamentalism]]
[[Category:Christian terminology]]
[[Category:Evangelical theology]]</text>
      <sha1>hwtt5e72qd8m0d2hujf4jdzyq872hfw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
