  <page>
    <title>Bokken</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4955</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938610168</id>
      <parentid>938610145</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-01T08:27:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>64.180.151.198</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Japanese wooden sword used for training}}
{{Multiple issues|
{{More citations needed|date=March 2008}}
{{Japanese|date=May 2015}}
}}
{{Italic title|reason=[[:Category:Japanese words and phrases]]}}
[[File:Various bokken or bukuto.jpg|thumb|150px|Various types of ''bokken'']]
A '''''bokken''''' ({{lang|ja|[[Wiktionary:木剣|木剣]]}}, ''bok(u)'', &quot;wood&quot;, and ''ken'', &quot;sword&quot;) (or a ''bokutō'' {{lang|ja|[[Wiktionary:木刀|木刀]]}}, as they are instead called in Japan) is a Japanese [[waster|wooden sword]] used for training. It is usually the size and shape of a ''[[katana]]'', but is sometimes shaped like other [[sword]]s, such as the ''[[wakizashi]]'' and ''[[tantō]]''. Some ornamental bokken are decorated with mother-of-pearl work and elaborate carvings.  Sometimes it is spelled &quot;boken&quot; in English.

''Bokken'' should not be confused with ''[[shinai]]'', practice swords made of flexible bamboo.

==History==
''Bokken'' were designed to lessen the damage caused by fighting with real swords and were used for the training of [[samurai]] warriors in feudal Japan. Bokken eventually became lethal weapons themselves in the hands of trained experts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Ratti|first1=Oscar|last2=Westbrook|first2=Adele|title=Secrets of the Samurai; A Survey of the Martial Arts of Feudal Japan|date=1991|publisher=C.E. Tuttle Co.|location=Rutland, Vt.|isbn=978-0-8048-1684-7|page=272|edition=1st pbk.|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Z9lmmkvQOpoC&amp;pg=PA272&amp;dq=samurai+bokken&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=WUsuT-D4KIaftwftuqm-Cw&amp;ved=0CGYQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Miyamoto Musashi]], a [[kenjutsu]] master, was renowned for fighting fully armed foes with only one or two bokkens. In a famous legend, he defeated [[Sasaki Kojirō|Sasaki Kojiro]] with a bokken he had carved from an [[oar]] while traveling on a boat to the [[Ganryūjima|predetermined island]] for the duel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Wilson|first1=William Scott|title=The Lone Samurai: The Life of Miyamoto Musashi|date=2004|publisher=Kodansha International|location=Tokyo|isbn=9784770029423|page=19|edition=1st|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0p0C7Y8lkH8C&amp;pg=PA18&amp;dq=musashi+came+late+and+unkempt&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=Nv-UT--UBomC8ATMqsn9Aw&amp;ved=0CEYQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=musashi%20came%20late%20and%20unkempt&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although it is hard to determine precisely when the first Bokken appeared due to the nature of secrecy in ancient martial arts training, the oldest Bokken known to have been used as training tools date from the Edo period. Before the Meiji era, Bokken were very likely manufactured by woodworkers not specialized in Bokken manufacture. It is at the beginning of the 20th century that Bokken manufacture started, mainly in Miyakonojo (Kyushu region). Today, the last four workshops of Japan are still located in Miyakonojo.

The &quot;standard Bokken&quot;, mostly used in [[Kendo]], [[Iaido]], and [[Aikido]] was created by master Aramaki in collaboration with the All Japan Kendo Federation in the 1950s and was the first standardized Bokken ever created.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Seido - Budo Equipment &amp; Practice in Japan|title=[Interview] Aramaki Yasuo - Bokken Manufacture 3rd Generation Craftsman (Part 1/2)|date=2017-10-05|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TvbS_4p7Jy8|accessdate=2018-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Usage==
[[File:Several bokken.jpg|thumb|130px|Various styles of bokken]]
The ''bokken'' is used as an inexpensive and relatively safe substitute for a real sword in several [[martial arts]] such as ''[[aikido]]'', ''[[kendo]]'',  ''[[iaido]]'', ''[[kenjutsu]]'' and ''[[jodo]]''. Its simple wooden construction demands less care and maintenance than a katana. In addition, training with a bokken does not carry the same mortal risk associated with that of a sharp metal sword, both for the user and other practitioners nearby. While its use has several advantages over use of a live edged weapon, it can still be deadly, and any training with a bokken should be done with due care. Injuries occurring from bokken are very similar to those caused by clubs and similar battering weapons and include compound fractures, ruptured organs, and other such blunt force injuries. In some ways, a bokken can be more dangerous as the injuries caused are often unseen and inexperienced practitioners may underestimate the risk of harm. It is not a sparring weapon, but is intended to be used in [[kata]] and to acclimate the student to the feel of a real sword. For sparring, a bamboo [[shinai]] is typically used instead for obvious safety reasons.

In 2003, the [[All Japan Kendo Federation]] (AJKF) introduced a set of basic exercises using a ''bokuto'' called ''Bokuto Ni Yoru Kendo Kihon-waza Keiko-ho''. This form of practice is intended primarily for kendo practitioners up to [[Dan (rank)#Ranks in Japanese|Nidan]] ranking, but can be beneficial for all kendo students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://zenkenren-shop.com/kendo/books/|title=全日本剣道連盟オンライン・ショップ：剣道書籍|last=|first=|date=|website=|publisher=Zenkenren-shop.com|archive-url=|archive-date=|accessdate=2015-11-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Suburito]]'' are ''bokken'' designed for use in ''[[suburi]]''. ''Suburi'', literally &quot;bare swinging,&quot; are solo cutting exercises. Suburito are thicker and heavier than normal ''bokken'' and users of suburito must therefore develop both strength and technique. Their weight makes them unsuitable for paired practice and solo forms. One famous user of the suburi-sized bokken is [[Miyamoto Musashi]] who used one in his duel against [[Sasaki Kojiro]].

As late as 2015, bokken were issued to the Los Angeles Police Mounted Unit for use as batons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lapdonline.org/lapd_equipment |title=LAPD Equipment - Los Angeles Police Department |publisher=Lapdonline.org |date= |accessdate=2015-11-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Edwards|first=Holly|title=Mounted Patrols Train for Handling Unrest at Convention|page=N3|newspaper=[[Los Angeles Daily News]]|date=August 6, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- April 8, 2011 - The August 6, 2000 Daily News cite is only for that the bokken were issued. It does not confirm that they are for use as batons. The Daily News article itself only has &quot;The officers are also trained to use a bokken, a long wooden sword used only by mounted police.&quot; The LAPD's Mounted Unit is currently overseen by Captain Incontro (see http://www.lapdonline.org/metropolitan_division). I contacted him via e-mail and asked if the Wikipedia article claim &quot;Bokken are currently issued to the Los Angeles Police Mounted Unit for use as batons&quot; was true. He replied back with &quot;We do use the bokken.&quot; --&gt;

==Types==
Bokken can be made to represent any style of weapon required such as [[nagamaki]], [[Nodachi|no-dachi]], [[yari]], [[naginata]], [[kama (weapon)|kama]], etc. The most widely used styles are:

* ''daitō'' or ''tachi'' ([[katana]]-sized), long sword
* ''shoto'' or ''kodachi'' or ''wakizashi bo'', short sword, ([[wakizashi]]-sized)
* ''tantō bo'' ([[tantō]]-sized)
* ''suburito'' can be made in ''daitō'' and ''shoto'' sizes

Additionally, various [[koryu]] (traditional Japanese martial arts) have their own distinct styles of bokken which can vary slightly in length, tip shape, or in whether or not a tsuba (hilt guard) is added.

The [[All Japan Kendo Federation]] specify the dimensions of ''bokken'' for use in the modern kendo kata, called ''Nippon kendo kata''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://zenkenren-shop.com/en/eigo/index.html#050106 |title=AJKF Online-shop : English version |publisher=Zenkenren-shop.com |date= |accessdate=2015-11-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Tachi]]: Total length, approx. 102&amp;nbsp;cm; ''tsuka'' (handle) approx. 24&amp;nbsp;cm.
*[[Kodachi]]: Total length, approx. 55&amp;nbsp;cm; ''tsuka'' (handle) approx. 14&amp;nbsp;cm.

==In fiction==
Bokken has been depicted in film, manga, anime, and comic books.

*In the film ''[[The Last Samurai]]'', the bokken is seen in multiple instances. In one scene a group of children is playing/sparring with them. Later in the film, Nathan Algren (played by [[Tom Cruise]]) is seen undergoing sword training with a bokken.
*In Hiroyuki Takei's manga and anime series ''[[Shaman King]]'', Umemiya Ryunosuke possesses a wooden sword and uses it as his main weapon, and is accordingly known as &quot;Wooden Sword&quot; Ryu.
*In the anime ''[[Outlaw Star]]''  Twilight Suzuka utilizes a bokken with immense skill and is able to use it more efficiently than an actual sword.
*In the anime ''[[Demon City Shinjuku]]'', the hero Kyoya Izayoi wields a bokken which he can infuse with spiritual energy.
*In the [[Wolverine (comic book)|''Wolverine'' limited series]] (1982) by Chris Claremont and Frank Miller, Wolverine is nearly killed by [[Shingen Yashida]], using a bokken to deliver nerve strikes.
*In the anime and the manga, ''[[Gin Tama]]'', the protagonist, [[Gintoki Sakata]], uses a bokken as his main weapon. His skills with it are powerful enough to overpower even real swords. Other characters, especially [[Shinpachi Shimura]], are frequently seen using bokken to practice.
*In the anime and manga, ''[[Rurouni Kenshin]]'', [[Kamiya Kaoru]] uses a bokken as her main weapon.
*In the anime and light novel series, ''[[Toradora!]]'', Aisaka Taiga can be seen wielding a bokken.
*In the anime and manga, ''[[Ranma ½]]'', [[Kuno Tatewaki]] wields a bokken and occasionally a [[shinai]].
*In the anime and manga, ''[[Highschool of the Dead]]'', [[List of Highschool of the Dead characters#Saeko Busujima|Saeko Busujima]] initially wield a bokken. She replaces it with a katana later in the series.
*In the anime and manga, ''[[Hunter × Hunter|Hunter x Hunter]],'' [[List of Hunter × Hunter characters#Kurapika|Kurapika]] wields two ''wakizashi''-sized bokken attached via a rope. In the 1999 anime, the bokken is actually a sheathed sword.
*In the anime and manga ''[[Demon Slayer: Kimetsu no Yaiba|Demon Slayer: Kimetsu no Yaiba]]'', the character of [[Sabito]] is seen wielding a wodden bokken in his first appearance and in his fight against [[Tanjiro Kamado|Tanjiro]]. 

==See also==
* [[Aiki-Ken]]
* [[Iaido]]
* [[Jō]]
* [[Kendō]]/[[Kenjutsu]]
* [[Kinomichi]]
* [[Waster]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Bokken (bokuto)}}
* [http://www.aikiweb.com/weapons/goedkoop1.html A discussion of different woods with regard to bokken design, focusing particularly on durability]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20160406044337/http://www.uoguelph.ca/~kataylor/bokuto.htm Information about making or selecting a bokken]
([[Wayback Machine]] copy)

{{Japanese (samurai) weapons, armour and equipment}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Samurai weapons and equipment]]
[[Category:Practice swords of Japan]]</text>
      <sha1>78pz7f0voq036avtphf8eqokvjqpgrf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
