  <page>
    <title>Bagpuss</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4942</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937870976</id>
      <parentid>937136388</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-27T18:56:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>81.159.166.27</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>1</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{Infobox television
| show_name          = Bagpuss
| image              = Bagpuss title screen.png
| caption            = The opening sequence of Bagpuss features a series of [[Photographic_print_toning#Sepia_toning|sepia toned]] photographs, which suggest the Victorian or Edwardian period.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=R. Moseley|title=Hand-Made Television: Stop-Frame Animation for Children in Britain, 1961-1974|publisher=Springer|date=2016|page=62}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| runtime            = 
| creator            = [[Peter Firmin]] and [[Oliver Postgate]]
| voices           = Oliver Postgate&lt;br/&gt;[[Sandra Kerr]]&lt;br/&gt;John Faulkner
| narrated           = [[Oliver Postgate]]
| country      = United Kingdom
| network      = [[BBC1]]&lt;!--Only show the original network -- see template documentation--&gt;
| company    = [[Smallfilms]]
| first_aired  = 12 February 1974
| last_aired   = 7 May 1974
| num_seasons = 1
| num_episodes = 13
}}
'''''Bagpuss''''' is a British [[children's television series]], made by [[Peter Firmin]] and [[Oliver Postgate]] through their company [[Smallfilms]]. The series of 13 episodes was first broadcast from 12 February &lt;ref name=T&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/tvandradio/10631604/Happy-40th-birthday-Bagpuss.html|title=Happy 40th birthday, Bagpuss!|last=Runcie|first=Charlotte|date=12 February 2014|work=[[The Daily Telegraph]]|accessdate=12 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; to 7 May 1974. The title character was &quot;a saggy, old cloth cat, baggy, and a bit loose at the seams&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smallfilms&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.smallfilms.co.uk/bagpuss/intro.htm |title=Bagpuss&amp;nbsp;– The intro|accessdate=11 November 2007 |work=The Smallfilms Treasury| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20071221021416/http://www.smallfilms.co.uk/bagpuss/intro.htm| archivedate= 21 December 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although only 13 episodes were made, it remains fondly remembered,&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/magazine/7773124.stm |title=Bagpuss&amp;nbsp;– See Emily Play |accessdate=12 September 2008 |work=BBC | date=9 December 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was frequently repeated in the UK until 1987.&lt;ref name=ODNB&gt;{{citation |last=Hayward |first=Anthony |contribution=Postgate, (Richard) Oliver (1925–2008) |title=Oxford Dictionary of National Biography |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=2012 |url=http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/100678 |accessdate=28 May 2012}} {{ODNBsub}}&lt;/ref&gt; In early 1999, ''Bagpuss'' topped a BBC poll for the UK's favourite children's television programme.

==Format==
Each programme began in the same way: through a series of [[sepia tone|sepia]] photographs, the viewer is told of a little girl named Emily (played by Emily Firmin, the daughter of illustrator Peter Firmin),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Duffy |first=Jonathan |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/magazine/7773124.stm |title=UK &amp;#124; Magazine &amp;#124; See Emily play |work=BBC News |date=9 December 2008 |accessdate=24 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; who owned a shop. Emily found lost and broken things and displayed them in the window, so their owners could come and collect them; the shop did not sell anything. 

She would leave the object in front of her favourite stuffed toy, the large, saggy, pink and white striped cat named Bagpuss, originally intended by Firmin to be a retired Indian Army cat who entertained children in the hospital with his &quot;visible&quot; thoughts appearing in a &quot;[[Speech balloon#Thought bubbles|thinks bubble]]&quot; above his head. When Postgate and Firmin were asked to develop this character for a BBC programme Postgate placed him in the shop with other characters and his &quot;thinks bubble&quot; became a way to illustrate the stories and mend or explore the objects that Emily had found. Emily then recited a verse:&lt;ref name=&quot;Smallfilms&quot;/&gt;

{{quote|Bagpuss, dear Bagpuss&lt;br /&gt;Old Fat Furry Catpuss&lt;br /&gt;Wake up and look at this thing that I bring&lt;br /&gt;Wake up, be bright, be golden and light&lt;br /&gt;Bagpuss, oh hear what I sing}}

After Emily had left, Bagpuss woke up. The programme shifted from sepia to colour [[stop motion]] film, and various toys in the shop came to life: Gabriel the toad (who, unlike most Smallfilms characters, could move by a special device beneath his can without the use of stop motion animation) and a [[rag doll]] called Madeleine. The wooden woodpecker bookend became the drily academic Professor [[Yaffle]] (based on the philosopher [[Bertrand Russell]], whom Postgate had once met),&lt;ref&gt;[[Channel 4]] News, 9 December 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; while the mice carved on the side of the &quot;mouse organ&quot; (a small mechanical [[pipe organ]] that played rolls of music) woke up and scurried around, singing in high-pitched voices. [[Sandra Kerr (folk singer)|Sandra Kerr]] and [[John Faulkner (musician)|John Faulkner]] provided the voices of Madeleine and Gabriel respectively, and put together and performed all the [[folk song]]s. All the other voices (including the narrator and one out-of-tune mouse) were provided by [[Oliver Postgate|Postgate]], who also wrote the stories.

The toys discussed what the new object was; someone (usually Madeleine) would tell a story related to the object (shown in an animated thought bubble over Bagpuss's head), often with a song, accompanied by Gabriel on the [[banjo]] (which often sounded a lot more like a guitar), and then the mice, singing in high-pitched squeaky harmony to the tune of ''[[Sumer Is Icumen In]]'' as they worked, mended the broken object. There was much banter between the characters, with the pompous Yaffle constantly finding fault with the playful mice: his complaint, 'Those mice are never serious!' became his main catchphrase. However, peace was always restored by the end of the episode, usually thanks to the timely intervention of Bagpuss, Gabriel or Madeleine. The newly mended thing was then placed in the shop window, so that whoever had lost it would see it as they went past, and could come in and claim it. Then Bagpuss would start yawning again, and as he fell asleep the narrator would speak as the colour faded to sepia and they all became toys again.

{{quote|And so their work was done.&lt;br /&gt;  Bagpuss gave a big yawn and settled down to sleep&lt;br /&gt;And, of course, when Bagpuss goes to sleep,&lt;br /&gt;All his friends go to sleep too.&lt;br /&gt;The mice were ornaments on the mouse organ.&lt;br /&gt;Gabriel and Madeleine were just dolls.&lt;br /&gt;And Professor Yaffle was a carved, wooden [[bookend]] in the shape of a woodpecker.&lt;br /&gt;Even Bagpuss himself, once he was asleep, was just an old, saggy cloth cat,&lt;br /&gt;Baggy, and a bit loose at the seams,&lt;br /&gt;But Emily loved him.}}

==Title sequence==
The scene is set at the turn of the 20th century, with Emily Firmin (Peter Firmin's daughter) playing the part of the [[Victorian era|Victorian]] child Emily.&lt;ref&gt;Postgate, Oliver (2000) ''Seeing Things-A Memoir'' {{ISBN|978-1-84767-840-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first antique village vignette is a cropped image of [[Horrabridge]] taken in 1898, though nothing is known of the other photo of the children with the pram.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title =Francis Frith Archive|url=http://www.francisfrith.com/horrabridge/| accessdate=22 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The shop window was at the Firmin family home in [[Blean]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot; /&gt;

==Episodes==
The episodes were originally broadcast at 1:45 pm on BBC1. The titles of the episodes each refer in some way to the object Emily found.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.smallfilms.co.uk/bagpuss/stories.htm
|title=The Stories|publisher=Smallfilms
|accessdate=26 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Episode!! width=140pt|Title !! Original air date !! Summary
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|&amp;nbsp;{{nowrap|&quot;Ship in a Bottle&quot;}}&amp;nbsp;
|align=&quot;right&quot;|&amp;nbsp;{{nowrap|12 February 1974}}&lt;ref name=T /&gt;&amp;nbsp;
|&amp;nbsp;Some splints of wood are shaken out of a bottle by the mice. Bagpuss tells a story about mermaids and the magic repairs the model ship. The mice put it back into the bottle and raise the sails.
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot;|2
|&amp;nbsp;&quot;The Owls of Athens&quot;
|align=&quot;right&quot;|19 February 1974&amp;nbsp;
|&amp;nbsp;A dirty rag reveals a picture of an owl. Once cleaned, Madeleine recounts a story explaining why owls sound like they do. Gabriel recounts in song the story of a king who needed a cushion to sit on.
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot;|3
|&amp;nbsp;&quot;The Frog Princess&quot;
|align=&quot;right&quot;|26 February 1974&amp;nbsp;
|&amp;nbsp;Assorted jewels, which initially are thought to represent a cat and a bird but which Gabriel decides were the crown jewels of a frog princess.
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot;|4
|&amp;nbsp;&quot;The Ballet Shoe&quot;
|align=&quot;right&quot;|5 March 1974&amp;nbsp;
|&amp;nbsp;Put to inventive use by the mice, and the subject of a very silly song about its possible use as a [[rowing boat]].
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot;|5
|&amp;nbsp;&quot;The Hamish&quot;
|align=&quot;right&quot;|12 March 1974&amp;nbsp;
|&amp;nbsp;A [[tartan]] porcupine [[pincushion]], and a legend of a small, soft creature from Scotland.
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot;|6
|&amp;nbsp;&quot;The Wise Man&quot;
|align=&quot;right&quot;|19 March 1974&amp;nbsp;
|&amp;nbsp;A broken figurine of a Chinese man (the Wise Man of Ling-Po, Yaffle explains) and a turtle.
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot;|7
|&amp;nbsp;&quot;The Elephant&quot;
|align=&quot;right&quot;|26 March 1974&amp;nbsp;
|&amp;nbsp;An [[elephant]] missing its ears.
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot;|8
|&amp;nbsp;&quot;The Mouse Mill&quot;
|align=&quot;right&quot;|2 April 1974&amp;nbsp;
|&amp;nbsp;A wooden toy [[Mill (grinding)|mill]] demonstrated by the mice to make chocolate biscuits out of [[Lima bean|butterbeans]] and breadcrumbs. This turns out to be a mischievous fraud. Gabriel and Madeleine sing a song about how ploughmen, farmers, millers, and bakers work at different stages of bread production. Even stern old Professor Yaffle cries.
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot;|9
|&amp;nbsp;&quot;The Giant&quot;
|align=&quot;right&quot;|9 April 1974&amp;nbsp;
|&amp;nbsp;A [[statuette]], and a lesson about how sizes are relative.
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot;|10
|&amp;nbsp;&quot;The Old Man's Beard&quot;
|align=&quot;right&quot;|16 April 1974&amp;nbsp;
|&amp;nbsp;A tangly plant (''[[Clematis vitalba]]'' seeding), and a [[loom]] for [[weaving]].
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot;|11
|&amp;nbsp;&quot;The Fiddle&quot;
|align=&quot;right&quot;|23 April 1974&amp;nbsp;
|&amp;nbsp;A [[fiddle]] that plays itself, and a [[leprechaun]].
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot;|12
|&amp;nbsp;&quot;Flying&quot;
|align=&quot;right&quot;|30 April 1974&amp;nbsp;
|&amp;nbsp;A basket that the mice attempt to turn into a flying machine. Professor Yaffle recites a poem about Percy Pratt, a man who apparently invented the aeroplane.
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot;|13
|&amp;nbsp;&quot;Uncle Feedle&quot;
|align=&quot;right&quot;|7 May 1974&amp;nbsp;
|&amp;nbsp;A piece of cloth, destined to be a house for a rag doll.
|}

==Production==
[[File:BagpussCharacters.jpg|thumb|upright|The characters of Bagpuss]]

The programmes were made using [[stop motion|stop-frame animation]]. Bagpuss is an actual cloth cat, but was not intended to be such an electric pink. &quot;It should have been a ginger marmalade cat but the company in [[Folkestone]] dyeing the material made a mistake and it turned out pink and cream. It was the best thing that ever happened,&quot; said Firmin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Adscene&quot;&gt;
{{cite news |title=Saggy old cloth cat pulls in the crowds |work=Canterbury Adscene |publisher=Kent Regional News and Media |pages=4–5 |date=9 November 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Madeleine the rag doll was made by Firmin's wife, Joan, with an extra long dress to hold their children's nightdresses, but Postgate asked Joan to make a new version as one of the characters.

Gabriel the Toad was the only character in the series who could move freely without the use of stop-frame animation. Scenes featuring him playing the banjo and singing would have taken quite a bit of time if filmed with the stop-frame method, so Peter Firmin created a mechanism that helped him control Gabriel through a hole in his can. The character was based on a real toad that lived in the basement area of the flat that Peter and Joan rented in Twickenham beside the River Thames. Gabriel (named after Walter Gabriel in [[List of The Archers characters|''The Archers'']], a long-running British radio soap opera) was originally made for Firmin’s live ITV programme ''The Musical Box''. Postgate chose him to be one of the characters in ''Bagpuss'' and he was made into a new, slightly larger version.

Professor Yaffle was created as the book-End who had access to &quot;facts&quot;.  The BBC did not like the original character, a man in top hat made from black Irish [[bog oak]], called &quot;Professor Bogwood&quot;. They thought he was too frightening and asked for a non-human instead.

Bagpuss is now retired. First, he lived with [[Rupert Bear]] in the Rupert Bear Museum in Canterbury, part of the [[Canterbury Heritage Museum]]. After its closure at the end of 2017, he and Rupert Bear moved to the [[Beaney House of Art and Knowledge]] in [[Canterbury]].

[[File:Bagpuss in Canterbury.jpg|thumb|The original Bagpuss doll in the Beaney House of Art and Knowledge in Canterbury, June 2018]]

Most of the stories and songs used in the series are based on folk songs and [[fairy tale]]s from around the world.

==Recognition==
In 1987, the [[University of Kent|University of Kent at Canterbury]] awarded [[honorary degrees]] to Postgate and Firmin. In his speech, Postgate stated that the degree was really intended for Bagpuss, who was subsequently displayed in academic dress.&lt;ref name=&quot;CANTCHRO&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.kent.ac.uk/arts/campus/chronicle.html |title=A Canterbury Chronicle |work=Arts, leisure and public events |publisher=University of Kent |accessdate=29 November 2006 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070930024111/http://www.kent.ac.uk/arts/campus/chronicle.html |archivedate=30 September 2007 |url-status=dead |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1999, ''Bagpuss'' came first in a BBC poll selecting the nation's favourite children's programme made and broadcast by that corporation.&lt;ref name=&quot;news&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Entertainment: Bagpuss cream of television |work=[[BBC News]] |date=1 October 1999 |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/246080.stm |accessdate=21 September 2007 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also came fourth in the [[Channel 4]] poll, ''[[The 100 Greatest Kids' TV Shows]]'', broadcast in 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;chan4&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Simpsons tops kids' TV poll |work=[[BBC News]] |date=28 September 2001 |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/tv_and_radio/1512890.stm |accessdate=21 September 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2002 and 2005, a stage show of ''Bagpuss'' songs toured the UK [[folk festival]]s and theatres with original singers [[Sandra Kerr]] and [[John Faulkner (musician)|John Faulkner]], along with Kerr's daughter [[Nancy Kerr]] and her husband, James Fagan.

In June 2002, the charity [[Hospices of Hope]] opened the Bagpuss Children's Wing in its hospice in [[Brașov]], [[Romania]].  The wing was funded entirely by [[Oliver Postgate|Postgate]] from [[royalties]] received from the [[BBC]]. In April 2012, [[Marc Jenner]] from [[Tunbridge Wells]] in Kent ran in the [[Virgin London Marathon]] dressed in a {{convert|7|ft|adj=on}} Bagpuss costume to raise money for the charity, supported by [[Emily Firmin]] (seen in the programme’s opening titles) and [[Oliver Postgate|Postgate]]'s family.

[[Thom Yorke]] of the band [[Radiohead]] has claimed to be a fan of the series, watching it with his son. It was an influence for 2003 album ''[[Hail to the Thief]]''. Gabriel's song in Episode 2 was the acknowledged inspiration for the album track (and first single) &quot;[[There There]]&quot; (originally titled &quot;The Bony King of Nowhere&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pulk-pull.org/message-124-bagpuss/ |title=Message 124: Bagpuss |work=Pulk-Pull* : an on-going investigation of Radiohead's music and art |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140517125138/http://pulk-pull.org/message-124-bagpuss/ |archivedate=17 May 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bagpuss appeared on one of the twelve postage stamps issued by [[Royal Mail]] in January 2014 to celebrate classic children's programmes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=https://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/gallery/2014/jan/04/royal-mail-childrens-tv-stamps-in-pictures?picture=426262861
|title=Royal Mail's children's TV stamps – in pictures
|date=4 January 2014|work=[[The Guardian]]
|accessdate=12 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Home media==
In 1993 and then in May 1999, [[PolyGram Filmed Entertainment|PolyGram]] released a video entitled ''The Complete Bagpuss'' which included all 13 episodes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/341007.stm
|title=Made in the 70s, still going strong|work=BBC News
|date=17 May 1999|accessdate=26 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.smallfilms.co.uk/bagpuss/video.htm
|title=The Video and DVD|publisher=Smallfilms
|accessdate=26 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was released in DVD format in April 2005,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.bbcshop.com/Childrens/Bagpuss-The-Complete-Bagpuss-Animated-DVD/invt/8234175
|title=Bagpuss: The Complete Bagpuss (Animated) (DVD)
|work=BBCSHOP.COM
|accessdate=26 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; and then re-released in April 2015.

The first video was released by Channel 5, and the rest were released by [[Universal Pictures]].

===VHS===
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot; width=99%
!VHS video title
! style=&quot;width:09%;&quot;| Year of release
!Episodes
|- 
| align=&quot;center&quot;|''Bagpuss''
| align=&quot;center&quot;|1993 
| align=&quot;center&quot;|&quot;The Owls Of Athens&quot;, &quot;Flying&quot;, &quot;The Mouse Mill&quot;,&lt;br&gt;&quot;The Ballet Shoe&quot;, &quot;Uncle Feedle&quot;
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot;|''Bagpuss (Re-Release)''
| align=&quot;center&quot;|16 June 1997
| align=&quot;center&quot;|&quot;The Owls Of Athens&quot;, &quot;Flying&quot;, &quot;The Mouse Mill&quot;,&lt;br&gt;&quot;The Ballet Shoe&quot;, &quot;Uncle Feedle&quot;
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot;|''Bagpuss: The Complete Series''
| align=&quot;center&quot;|10 May 1999
| align=&quot;center&quot;|&quot;Ship In A Bottle&quot;, &quot;The Owls Of Athens&quot;, &quot;The Frog Princess&quot;,&lt;br&gt;&quot;The Ballet Shoe&quot;, &quot;The Hamish&quot;, &quot;The Wise Man&quot;,&lt;br&gt;&quot;The Elephant&quot;, &quot;The Mouse Mill&quot;, &quot;The Giant&quot;,&lt;br&gt;&quot;The Old Man's Beard&quot;, &quot;The Fiddle&quot;, &quot;Flying&quot;, &quot;Uncle Feedle&quot; (All 13 episodes)
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot;|''Bagpuss: The Ballet Shoe and other stories''
| align=&quot;center&quot;|18 April 2001
| align=&quot;center&quot;|&quot;The Ballet Shoe&quot;, &quot;Uncle Feedle&quot;, &quot;Flying&quot;
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot;|''Bagpuss: The Mouse Mill and other stories''
| align=&quot;center&quot;|18 April 2001
| align=&quot;center&quot;|&quot;The Mouse Mill&quot;, &quot;The Hamish&quot;, &quot;The Wise Man&quot;
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot;|''Bagpuss: Ship In The Bottle and other stories''
| align=&quot;center&quot;|21 April 2003
| align=&quot;center&quot;|&quot;Ship In A Bottle&quot;, &quot;The Owls Of Athens&quot;, &quot;The Giant&quot;
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot;|''Bagpuss: Frog Princess and other stories''
| align=&quot;center&quot;|21 April 2003
| align=&quot;center&quot;|&quot;The Frog Princess&quot;, &quot;The Elephant&quot;, &quot;The Old Man's Beard&quot;
|-
|}

A cd and vinyl lp of the original songs from the series was released in 2018.&lt;ref&gt;https://bagpuss.bandcamp.com/merch&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|33em}}

==External links==
* {{BBC Online|id=cult/ilove/tv/bagpuss/index.shtml|title=''Bagpuss''}}
*{{IMDb title|id=0070970|title=Bagpuss}}
* [http://www.smallfilms.co.uk/bagpuss The Smallfilms Treasury's Bagpuss site]
* [http://www.screenonline.org.uk/tv/id/562331/index.html ''Bagpuss'' at British Film Institute Screen Online]
* [http://www.anorakzone.com/bagpuss Bagpuss &amp; Co]

{{Smallfilms}}
{{Watch with Mother}}

[[Category:1970s British children's television series]]
[[Category:1974 British television series debuts]]
[[Category:1974 British television series endings]]
[[Category:BBC children's television programmes]]
[[Category:British children's television programmes]]
[[Category:British children's animated television programmes]]
[[Category:Animated television series about cats]]
[[Category:Television series by Smallfilms]]
[[Category:Sentient toys in fiction]]
[[Category:British stop-motion animated television series]]
[[Category:British animated television programmes featuring anthropomorphic characters]]
[[Category:English-language television programs]]
[[Category:1970s British animated television series]]</text>
      <sha1>8mud677m0lkpfu3vm4jr8omdnc1jsyy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
