  <page>
    <title>Breathy voice</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4946</id>
    <revision>
      <id>934493504</id>
      <parentid>920029307</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-06T21:08:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>W.andrea</username>
        <id>14672439</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Phonological property */ syntax</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{redirects here|Voiced aspirate|true voiced aspirates|Aspirated consonant#Voiced stop}}
{{More footnotes|date=April 2009}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{Infobox IPA
| above = Breathy
| ipa symbol  = ◌̤
| ipa symbol2 = ◌ʱ
| decimal=804
}}

'''Breathy voice''' (also called '''murmured voice''', '''whispery voice''', '''soughing''' and '''susurration''') is a [[phonation]] in which the [[vocal folds]] vibrate, as they do in normal (modal) voicing, but are adjusted to let more air escape&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Chávez-Peón|first=Mario E.|title=Non-modal phonation in Quiaviní Zapotec: an acoustic investigation*|url=http://www.ailla.utexas.org/site/cilla5/Chavez_CILLA_V.pdf|publisher=Instituto de Investigaciones Antropológicas Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México|accessdate=26 May 2013|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140826115820/http://www.ailla.utexas.org/site/cilla5/Chavez_CILLA_V.pdf|archivedate=26 August 2014|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; which produces a sighing-like sound. A simple breathy phonation, {{IPA|[ɦ]}} (not actually a [[fricative consonant]], as a literal reading of the IPA chart would suggest), can sometimes be heard as an [[allophone]] of English {{IPA|/h/}} between vowels, such as in the word ''behind'', for some speakers.

In the context of the [[Indo-Aryan languages]] like [[Sanskrit]] and [[Hindi]] and comparative [[Indo-European languages|Indo-European studies]], breathy consonants are often called ''voiced aspirated'', as in the Hindi and Sanskrit stops normally denoted ''bh, dh, ḍh, jh,'' and ''gh'' and the reconstructed [[Proto-Indo-European language|Proto-Indo-European]] phoneme ''gʷʰ''. From an articulatory perspective, that terminology is inaccurate, as breathy voice is a different type of phonation from [[aspirated consonant|aspiration]]. However, breathy and aspirated stops are acoustically similar in that in both cases there is a delay in the onset of full voicing. In the history of several languages, like [[Greek language|Greek]] and some [[varieties of Chinese]], breathy stops have developed into aspirated stops.

==Classification and terminology==
There is some confusion as to the nature of murmured phonation. The IPA and authors such as [[Peter Ladefoged]] equate phonemically contrastive murmur with ''breathy voice'' in which the vocal folds are held with lower tension (and further apart) than in modal voice, with a concomitant increase in airflow and slower vibration of the glottis. In that model, murmur is a point in a continuum of glottal aperture between modal voice and breath phonation (voicelessness).

Others, such as Laver, Catford, Trask and the authors of the [[Voice Quality Symbols]] (VoQS), equate murmur with ''whispery voice'' in which the vocal folds or, at least, the anterior part of the vocal folds vibrates, as in modal voice, but the arytenoid cartilages are held apart to allow a large turbulent airflow between them. In that model, murmur is a compound phonation of approximately modal voice plus whisper.

It is possible that the realization of murmur varies among individuals or languages. The IPA uses the term &quot;breathy voice&quot;, but VoQS uses the term &quot;whispery voice&quot;. Both accept the term &quot;murmur&quot;, popularised by Ladefoged.&lt;ref&gt;Trask (1996) &quot;breathy voice&quot;, &quot;murmur&quot;, &quot;whispery voice&quot;, in ''A Dictionary of Phonetics and Phonology''.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Transcription==
A stop with breathy release or a breathy nasal is transcribed in the [[International Phonetic Alphabet]] as {{IPA|[bʱ], [dʱ], [ɡʱ], [mʱ]}} etc. or as {{IPA|[b̤], [d̤], [ɡ̈], [m̤]}} etc. Breathy vowels are most often written {{IPA|[a̤], [e̤],}} etc.

In VoQS, the notation {{IPA|{V̤}}} is used for whispery voice (or murmur), and {{IPA|{Vʰ}}} is used for breathy voice. Some authors, such as Laver, suggest the alternative transcription {{angbr IPA|ḅạɾ}} (rather than IPA {{angbr IPA|b̤a̤ɾ}}) as the correct analysis of [[Gujarati language|Gujarati]] {{IPA|/bɦaɾ/}}, but it could be confused with the replacement of modal voicing in voiced segments with [[whispering|whispered]] phonation, conventionally transcribed with the diacritic {{IPA|◌̣}}.&lt;ref&gt;Laver (1994) ''Principles of Phonetics'', p. 354&lt;/ref&gt;

==Methods of production==
There are several ways to produce breathy sounds such as {{IPAblink|ɦ}}. One is to hold the vocal folds apart, so that they are lax as they are for {{IPA|[h]}}, but to increase the volume of airflow so that they vibrate loosely. A second is to bring the vocal folds closer together along their entire length than in voiceless {{IPA|[h]}}, but not as close as in modally voiced sounds such as vowels. This results in an airflow intermediate between {{IPA|[h]}} and vowels, and is the case with English intervocalic /h/. A third is to constrict the glottis, but separate the [[arytenoid cartilage]]s that control one end. This results in the vocal folds being drawn together for voicing in the back, but separated to allow the passage of large volumes of air in the front. This is the situation with Hindi.

The distinction between the latter two of these realizations, vocal folds somewhat separated along their length (''breathy voice'') and vocal folds together with the arytenoids making an opening (''whispery voice''), is phonetically relevant in [[Hmong language|White Hmong]] (''Hmong Daw'').&lt;ref&gt;Fulop &amp; Golston (2008), ''Breathy and whispery voicing in White Hmong'', http://zimmer.csufresno.edu/~chrisg/index_files/FulopGolston2009.pdf. Retrieved 17 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Phonological property==
A number of languages use breathy voicing in a phonologically contrastive way. Many [[Indo-Aryan languages]], such as [[Hindi]], typically have a four-way contrast among plosives and affricates (voiced, breathy, [[tenuis consonant|tenuis]], aspirated) and a two-way contrast among nasals (voiced, breathy). The [[Nguni languages]] within the southern branch of the [[Bantu languages]], including [[Phuthi language|Phuthi]], [[Xhosa language|Xhosa]], [[Zulu language|Zulu]], [[Southern Ndebele language|Southern Ndebele]] and [[Swazi language|Swazi]], also have contrastive breathy voice. In the case of Xhosa, there is a four-way contrast analogous to Indic in oral [[click consonant|clicks]], and similarly a two-way contrast among nasal clicks, but a three-way contrast among plosives and affricates (breathy, aspirated, and [[ejective consonant|ejective]]), and two-way contrasts among fricatives (voiceless and breathy) and nasals (voiced and breathy).

In some Bantu languages, historically breathy stops have been phonetically devoiced,&lt;ref&gt;Traill, Anthony, James S. M. Khumalo and Paul Fridjhon (1987). Depressing facts about Zulu. African Studies 46: 255–274.&lt;/ref&gt; but the four-way contrast in the system has been retained. In all five of the southeastern Bantu languages named, the breathy stops (even if they are realised phonetically as devoiced aspirates) have a marked tone-lowering (or tone-depressing) effect on the following [[tautosyllabic]] vowels. For this reason, such stop consonants are frequently referred to in the local linguistic literature as 'depressor' stops.

Swazi, and to a greater extent Phuthi, display good evidence that breathy voicing can be used as a morphological property independent of any consonant voicing value. For example, in both languages, the standard morphological mechanism for achieving the [[Morphology (linguistics)#Paradigms and morphosyntax|morphosyntactic]] [[copula (linguistics)|copula]] is to simply execute the noun prefix syllable as breathy (or 'depressed').

In [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]], vowels after the [[stress (linguistics)#Lexical stress|stressed syllable]] can be pronounced with breathy voice.&lt;ref&gt;Callou, Dinah. Leite, Yonne. &quot;Iniciação à Fonética e à Fonologia&quot;. Jorge Zahar Editor 2001, p. 20&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Gujarati language|Gujarati]] is unusual in [[Gujarati_phonology#Murmur|contrasting breathy vowels and consonants]]: {{IPA|/baɾ/}} 'twelve', {{IPA|/ba̤ɾ/}} 'outside', {{IPA|/bʱaɾ/}} 'burden'.&lt;ref&gt;{{SOWL}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{page missing|date=August 2018}}

[[Juǀ'hoan dialect|Tsumkwe Juǀ'hoan]] makes the following rare distinctions : {{IPA|/nǂʱao/}} fall, land (of a bird etc.); {{IPA|/nǂʱao̤/}} walk; {{IPA|/nǂʱaˤo/}} herb species; and /n|ʱoaᵑ/ greedy person; /n|oaʱᵑ/ cat.&lt;ref&gt;Dickens, Patick (1994) English-Ju/'hoan Ju/'hoan-English dictionary {{ISBN|3927620556}}, 9783927620551&lt;/ref&gt;

Breathy stops in [[Punjabi language|Punjabi]] lost their phonation, merging with voiceless and voiced stops in various positions, and a system of high and low [[tone (linguistics)|tones]] developed in syllables that formerly had these sounds.

Breathy voice can also be observed in place of [[debuccalization|debuccalized]] coda {{IPA|/s/}} in [[Spanish dialects and varieties|some dialects of colloquial Spanish]], e.g. {{IPA|[ˈt̪o̞ðo̞ʱ lo̞ ˈθiʱne̞ ˈsõ̞m ˈblãŋko̞]}} for ''{{wt|es|todos}} {{wt|es|los}} {{wt|es|cisnes}} {{wt|es|son}} {{wt|es|blancos}}''.

==See also==
* [[Aspirated consonant]]
* [[Creaky voice]]
* [[Index of phonetics articles]]
* [[Slack voice]]
* [[Whispering]]
* [[Guttural]]
* [[Voiced glottal fricative]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{phonation}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Breathy Voice}}
[[Category:Phonation]]</text>
      <sha1>nc19oosr1bspvutcqgijkb026gwlh2q</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
