  <page>
    <title>Rockwell B-1 Lancer</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4952</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942219916</id>
      <parentid>940572838</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-23T10:37:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Balon Greyjoy</username>
        <id>20164867</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Air Force Global Strike Command */ changing tense</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|American strategic bomber by Rockwell, later Boeing}}
{{Good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2019}}
&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] for recommended layout, and guidelines. --&gt;
{|{{Infobox aircraft begin
 |name= B-1 Lancer
 |image= File:B-1B air refueling.jpg
 |caption= A B-1B in flight
 |alt= Top view of B-1B in-flight with white clouds scattered underneath. Its wings are swept fully forward as the gray aircraft flies over the ocean.
}}{{Infobox aircraft type
 |type= [[Supersonic]] [[strategic bomber|strategic]] [[heavy bomber]]
 |national origin= [[United States]]
 |manufacturer= [[Rockwell International|North American Rockwell/Rockwell International]] &lt;br&gt;[[Boeing]]&lt;!-- Upgrades and support --&gt;
 |designer= 
 |first flight= {{Start date and age|1974|12|23|df=yes}}
 |introduction= 1 October 1986
 |retired= 
 |produced= 1973–1974, 1983–1988
 |primary user= [[United States Air Force]]
 |more users= 
 |number built= B-1A: 4 &lt;br&gt;B-1B: 100
 |status= In service
 |unit cost= B-1B: [[United States dollar|US$]]283.1 million in 1998&lt;ref name=&quot;Skaarup p.17&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Skaarup |2002|p=17}}.&lt;/ref&gt; (${{format price|{{Inflation|US-GDP|283100000|1998}}}} in {{Inflation-year|US-GDP}} dollars{{Inflation-fn|US-GDP}})
 |developed from= 
 |variants with their own articles= 
}}
|}

The '''Rockwell B-1 Lancer'''{{#tag:ref|The name &quot;Lancer&quot; was only applied to the B-1B variant in 1990.&lt;ref name= Jenkins_p67/&gt;|group=N}} is a supersonic [[variable-sweep wing]], [[heavy bomber]] used by the [[United States Air Force]]. It is commonly called the &quot;Bone&quot; (from &quot;B-One&quot;). It is one of three [[strategic bomber]]s in the U.S. Air Force fleet {{as of|2020|lc=yes}}, the other two being the [[B-2 Spirit]] and the [[B-52 Stratofortress]].

The B-1 was first envisioned in the 1960s as a platform that would combine the Mach 2 speed of the [[B-58 Hustler]] with the range and payload of the B-52, and was meant to ultimately replace both bombers. After a long series of studies, [[Rockwell International]] (now part of [[Boeing]]) won the design contest for what emerged as the B-1A. This version had a top speed of [[Mach number|Mach]] 2.2 at high altitude and the capability of flying for long distances at Mach 0.85 at very low altitudes. The combination of the high cost of the aircraft, the introduction of the [[AGM-86 ALCM|AGM-86]] [[cruise missile]] that flew the same basic profile, and early work on the stealth bomber all significantly affected the need for the B-1. This led to the program being canceled in 1977, after the B-1A prototypes had been built.

The program was restarted in 1981, largely as an interim measure due to delays in the B-2 [[Stealth aircraft|stealth bomber]] program, with the B-2 eventually reaching initial operational capability in 1997. This led to a redesign as the B-1B, which differed from the B-1A by having a lower top speed at high [[altitude]] of Mach 1.25, but improved low-altitude performance of Mach 0.96. The electronics were also extensively improved during the redesign, and the airframe was improved to allow takeoff with the maximum possible fuel and weapons load. The B-1B began deliveries in 1986 and formally entered service with [[Strategic Air Command]] (SAC) as a nuclear bomber in that same year. By 1988, all 100 aircraft had been delivered.

In the early 1990s, following the [[Gulf War]] and concurrent with the disestablishment of SAC and its reassignment to the newly formed [[Air Combat Command]], the B-1B was converted to conventional bombing use. It first served in combat during [[Bombing of Iraq (1998)|Operation Desert Fox]] in 1998 and again during the [[NATO bombing of Yugoslavia|NATO action in Kosovo]] the following year. The B-1B has supported U.S. and [[NATO]] military forces in [[War in Afghanistan (2001–present)|Afghanistan]] and [[Iraq War|Iraq]].  The Air Force had 66 B-1Bs in service as of September 2012.  The B-1B is expected to continue to serve into the 2030s, with the [[Northrop Grumman B-21 Raider]] to begin replacing the B-1B after 2025. The B-1s in inventory are planned to be retired by 2036.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.airforcemag.com/Features/Pages/2018/February%202018/USAF-to-Retire-B-1-B-2-in-Early-2030s-as-B-21-Comes-On-Line.aspx &quot;USAF to Retire B-1, B-2 in Early 2030s as B-21 Comes On-Line&quot;]. ''Air Force Magazine''. 11 February 2018.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Development==

===Background===
{{main|North American XB-70 Valkyrie}}

In 1955, the USAF issued requirements for a new bomber combining the payload and range of the [[Boeing B-52 Stratofortress]] with the Mach&amp;nbsp;2 maximum speed of the [[Convair B-58 Hustler]].&lt;ref name= Jenkins_99_p10&gt;Jenkins 1999, p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt; In December 1957, the USAF selected [[North American Aviation]]'s [[North American XB-70 Valkyrie|B-70 Valkyrie]] for this role.&lt;ref name= Jenkins_p12-13&gt;{{harvnb|Jenkins|1999|pp=12–13.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Valkyrie was a six-engine bomber that could cruise at [[Mach number|Mach]]&amp;nbsp;3 at high altitude ({{convert|70000|ft|m|abbr=on|sigfig=2|disp=or}}).&lt;ref name=Jenkins_p15-7&gt;{{harvnb|Jenkins|1999|pp=15–17.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Soviet [[interceptor aircraft]], the only effective anti-bomber weapon in the 1950s,&lt;ref name=&quot;Schwartz p.118&quot;/&gt; were already unable to intercept the high-flying [[Lockheed U-2]];&lt;ref&gt;Rich, Ben and Leo Janos. ''Skunk Works''. Boston: Little, Brown &amp; Company, 1994. {{ISBN|0-316-74300-3}}.&lt;/ref&gt; the Valkyrie would fly at similar altitudes, but much higher speeds, and was expected to fly right by the fighters.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schwartz p.118&quot;/&gt;

[[File:North American XB-70 in Flight EC68-2131.jpg|thumb|left|The XB-70 Valkyrie was chosen in 1957 to replace the B-58 Hustler, but suffered as a result of a switch in doctrine from high to low-altitude flying profiles]]
By the late 1950s, however, antiaircraft [[surface-to-air missile]]s (SAMs) could threaten high-altitude aircraft,&lt;ref name=Jenkins_1999_p21&gt;{{harvnb|Jenkins|1999|p=21.}}&lt;/ref&gt; as demonstrated by the [[1960 U-2 incident|1960 downing]] of [[Gary Powers]]' U-2.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.keesings.com/search?kssp_selected_tab=article&amp;kssp_a_id=17425n01sov &quot;May 1960&amp;nbsp;– The U-2 Incident.&amp;nbsp;– Soviet and American Statements.&quot;] ''Keesing's Record of World Events'', Volume 6, 1960.&lt;/ref&gt; The USAF Strategic Air Command (SAC) was aware of these developments and had begun moving its bombers to low-level penetration even before the U-2 downing. This tactic greatly reduces radar detection distances through the use of [[terrain mask#Terrain masking|terrain masking]]; using features of the terrain like hills and valleys, the line-of-sight from the radar to the bomber can be broken, rendering the radar (and human observers) incapable of seeing it.&lt;ref name=Spick_1986_p6-8/&gt; Additionally, radars of the era were subject to &quot;[[clutter (radar)|clutter]]&quot; from stray returns from the ground and other objects, which meant a minimum angle existed above the horizon where they could detect a target. Bombers flying at low altitudes could remain under these angles simply by keeping their distance from the radar sites. This combination of effects made SAMs of the era ineffective against low-flying aircraft.&lt;ref name=Spick_1986_p6-8&gt;{{harvnb|Spick|1986|pp=6–8.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schwartz p.119&quot;/&gt; The same effects also meant that low-flying aircraft were difficult to detect by higher-flying interceptors, since their radar systems could not readily pick out opposing aircraft against the clutter from ground reflections (lack of [[look-down/shoot-down]] capability).

The switch from high-altitude to low-altitude flight profiles severely affected the B-70, whose design was highly tuned to provide the desired high-altitude performance. Planners outlined a series of low-level profiles for the B-70, but higher [[aerodynamic drag]] at low level limited the B-70 to subsonic speed while dramatically decreasing its range.&lt;ref name=Jenkins_1999_p21/&gt; The result would be an aircraft with somewhat higher subsonic speed than the B-52, but less range. Unsuited for the new low-altitude role, and because of a growing shift to the [[intercontinental ballistic missile]] (ICBM) force, the B-70 bomber program was cancelled in 1961 by President [[John F. Kennedy]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Schwartz p.118&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schwartz|1998|p=118.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://ntrs.nasa.gov/archive/nasa/casi.ntrs.nasa.gov/19950002358_1995102358.pdf &quot;NASA-CR-115702, B-70 Aircraft Study Final Report, Vol. I, p. I-38.&quot;] ''NASA'', 1972.&lt;/ref&gt; and the two XB-70 prototypes were used in a supersonic research program.&lt;ref name=Jenkins_p14-6&gt;{{harvnb|Jenkins|1999|pp=14–16.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although never intended for the low-level role, the B-52's flexibility allowed it to outlast its intended successor as the nature of the air war environment changed. The B-52's huge fuel load allowed it to operate at lower altitudes for longer times, and the large airframe allowed the addition of improved [[radar jamming and deception]] suites to deal with radars.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Knaack|1988|pp=279–280.}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the [[Vietnam War]], the concept that all future wars would be nuclear was turned on its head, and the &quot;big belly&quot; modifications increased the B-52's total bomb load to {{convert|60000|lb|kg}},&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Knaack|1988|p=256.}}&lt;/ref&gt; turning it into a powerful tactical aircraft which could be used against ground troops along with strategic targets from high altitudes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schwartz p.119&quot;/&gt; The much smaller bomb bay of the B-70 would have made it much less useful in this role.

===Design studies and delays===
Although effective, the B-52 was not ideal for the low-level role. This led to a number of aircraft designs known as [[penetrator (aircraft)|penetrators]], which were tuned specifically for long-range low-altitude flight. The first of these designs to see operation was the supersonic [[General Dynamics F-111 Aardvark|F-111]] fighter-bomber, which used variable-sweep wings for tactical missions.&lt;ref&gt;Gunston 1978, pp. 12–13.&lt;/ref&gt; Similar aircraft also emerged for other users as well, notably the [[BAC TSR-2]], and later, [[Panavia Tornado]] and [[Sukhoi Su-24]]. A number of studies on a strategic-range counterpart followed.

The first post-B-70 strategic penetrator study was known as the Subsonic Low-Altitude Bomber (SLAB), which was completed in 1961. This produced a design that looked more like an airliner than a bomber, with a large swept wing, [[T-tail]], and large [[turbofan|high-bypass engines]].&lt;ref&gt;Taylor, Gordon. [http://www.dtic.mil/cgi-bin/GetTRDoc?Location=U2&amp;doc=GetTRDoc.pdf&amp;AD=AD0330289 &quot;Subsonic Low Altitude Bomber&quot;], Wright-Patterson Air Force Base ASD-TDR-62-426, June 1962.&lt;/ref&gt; This was followed by the similar Extended Range Strike Aircraft (ERSA), which added a [[variable-sweep wing]], then en vogue in the aviation industry. ERSA envisioned a relatively small aircraft with a {{convert|10000|lb|kg|adj=on}} payload and a range of {{convert|8750|nmi}} including {{convert|2500|nmi}} flown at low altitudes. In August 1963, the similar Low-Altitude Manned Penetrator design was completed, which called for an aircraft with a {{convert|20000|lb|adj=on}} bomb load and somewhat shorter range of {{convert|7150|nmi}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Pace|1998|pp=11–14.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Knaack pp.575-6&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Knaack|1988|pp=575–576.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

These all culminated in the October 1963 Advanced Manned Precision Strike System (AMPSS), which led to industry studies at [[Boeing]], [[General Dynamics]], and [[North American Aviation|North American]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Casil|2003|p=8.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Knaack p.576&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Knaack|1988|p=576.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In mid-1964, the USAF had revised its requirements and retitled the project as Advanced Manned Strategic Aircraft (AMSA), which differed from AMPSS primarily in that it also demanded a high-speed high-altitude capability, similar to that of the existing Mach&amp;nbsp;2-class [[Convair B-58 Hustler]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Knaack p.575&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Knaack|1988|p=575.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Given the lengthy series of design studies, Rockwell engineers joked that the new name actually stood for &quot;America's Most Studied Aircraft&quot;.&lt;ref name=study&gt;Wykes, J. H. [http://www.aiaa.org/content.cfm?pageid=406&amp;gTable=mtgpaper&amp;gID=62575 &quot;The Evolution of a Strategic Bomber.&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070930181453/http://www.aiaa.org/content.cfm?pageid=406&amp;gTable=mtgpaper&amp;gID=62575 |date=30 September 2007}} ''AIAA'', 12–14 May 1981. Retrieved: 8 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Jenkins_p23&gt;{{harvnb|Jenkins|1999|p=23.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The arguments that led to the cancellation of the B-70 program had led some to question the need for a new strategic bomber of any sort. The USAF was adamant about retaining bombers as part of the [[nuclear triad]] concept that included bombers, ICBMs, and [[submarine-launched ballistic missile]]s (SLBMs) in a combined package that complicated any potential defense. They argued that the bomber was needed to attack hardened military targets and to provide a safe [[counterforce]] option because the bombers could be quickly launched into safe loitering areas where they could not be attacked. However, the introduction of the SLBM made moot the mobility and survivability argument, and a newer generation of ICBMs, such as the [[LGM-30 Minuteman|Minuteman III]], had the accuracy and speed needed to attack point targets. During this time, ICBMs were seen as a less costly option based on their lower unit cost,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Pace|1998|p=10.}}&lt;/ref&gt; but development costs were much higher.&lt;ref name=Jenkins_1999_p21/&gt; [[Secretary of Defense]] [[Robert McNamara]] preferred ICBMs over bombers for the Air Force portion of the deterrent force&lt;ref name=&quot;Knaack pp.576-7&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Knaack|1988|pp=576–577.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and felt a new expensive bomber was not needed.&lt;ref name=fas&gt;[https://fas.org/nuke/guide/usa/bomber/b-1a.htm &quot;B-1A page.&quot;] ''fas.org''. Retrieved: 20 March 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Knaack p.576-8&quot;/&gt; McNamara limited the AMSA program to studies and component development beginning in 1964.&lt;ref name=&quot;Knaack p.576-8&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Knaack|1988|pp=576–578.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Program studies continued; [[IBM]] and [[Autonetics]] were awarded AMSA advanced avionics study contracts in 1968.&lt;ref name=&quot;Knaack p.576-8&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Jenkins_p23-6/&gt; McNamara remained opposed to the program in favor of upgrading the existing B-52 fleet and adding nearly 300 [[General Dynamics F-111 Aardvark#FB-111A / F-111G|FB-111s]] for shorter range roles then being filled by the B-58.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schwartz p.119&quot;&gt;Schwartz 1998, p. 119.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Knaack p.576-8&quot;/&gt; He again vetoed funding for AMSA aircraft development in 1968.&lt;ref name=Jenkins_p23-6&gt;{{harvnb|Jenkins|1999|pp=23–26.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===B-1A program===
[[File:RARF Antenna, Reflecting Array Radio Frequency, Raytheon, 1968-1969, Ku-band, over 3500 phase shifting modules, for the AN-APQ-140 radar - National Electronics Museum - DSC00376.JPG|thumb|right|150px|[[AN/APQ-140]] radar for the B-1A&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.designation-systems.net/usmilav/jetds/an-apq.html |title=AN/APQ – Airborne Multipurpose/Special Radars |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |date=1 July 2007 |website=Designation-systems.net |access-date=2015-01-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

President [[Richard Nixon]] reestablished the AMSA program after taking office, keeping with his administration's [[flexible response]] strategy that required a [[Single Integrated Operations Plan#Counterforce migrates to deterrence and warfighting|broad range of options short of general nuclear war]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Knaack p.579&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Knaack|1988|p=579.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nixon's Secretary of Defense, [[Melvin Laird]], reviewed the programs and decided to lower the numbers of FB-111s, since they lacked the desired range, and recommended that the AMSA design studies be accelerated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Knaack p.579&quot;/&gt; In April 1969, the program officially became the ''B-1A''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schwartz p.119&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Knaack p.579&quot;/&gt; This was the first entry in the [[1962 United States Tri-Service aircraft designation system|new bomber designation series]], first created in 1962. The Air Force issued a request for proposals in November 1969.&lt;ref name=Pace_p22-3/&gt;

[[File:Rockwell B-1A 1.jpg|thumb|left|B-1A prototype]]
Proposals were submitted by Boeing, General Dynamics and North American Rockwell in January 1970.&lt;ref name=Pace_p22-3/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kocivar, Ben. [https://books.google.com/books?id=9AAAAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA86 &quot;Our New B-1 Bomber&amp;nbsp;– High, Low, Fast, and Slow.&quot;] ''Popular Science'', Volume 197, Issue 5, November 1970, p. 86.&lt;/ref&gt; In June 1970, North American Rockwell's design was selected and was awarded a development contract.&lt;ref name=Pace_p22-3&gt;{{harvnb|Pace|1998|pp=22–23.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The original program called for two test airframes, five flyable aircraft, and 40 engines. This was cut in 1971 to one ground and three flight test aircraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;Knaack p.584&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Knaack|1988|p=584.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The company changed its name to [[Rockwell International]] and named its aircraft division North American Aircraft Operations in 1973.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.boeing.com/history/narrative/n086roc.html &quot;Rockwell International history 1970–1986.&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071011202047/http://www.boeing.com/history/narrative/n086roc.html |date=11 October 2007}} ''Boeing''. Retrieved: 8 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; A fourth prototype, built to production standards, was ordered in the fiscal year 1976 budget. Plans called for 240 B-1As to be built, with [[initial operational capability]] set for 1979.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sorrels p.27&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Sorrels|1983|p=27.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rockwell's design featured a number of features common to 1960s U.S. designs. Among these was the use of a [[escape crew capsule|crew escape capsule]] that ejected as a unit during emergencies, which was introduced to improve survivability in the case of an ejection at high speed. Additionally, the design featured large variable-sweep wings in order to provide both high [[lift (force)|lift]] during takeoff and landing, and low drag during a high-speed dash phase.&lt;ref name=&quot;lee p.13&quot;/&gt; With the wings set to their widest position the aircraft had considerably better lift and power than the B-52, allowing it to operate from a much wider variety of bases. Penetration of the [[Soviet Union]]'s defenses would take place at [[supersonic speed]], crossing them as quickly as possible before entering into the less defended &quot;heartland&quot; where speeds could be reduced again.&lt;ref name=&quot;lee p.13&quot;/&gt; The large size and fuel capacity of the design would allow the &quot;dash&quot; portion of the flight to be relatively long.

In order to achieve the required Mach&amp;nbsp;2 performance at high altitudes, the exhaust nozzles and air [[intake ramp]]s were variable.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Whitford|1987|p=136.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Initially, it had been expected that a Mach&amp;nbsp;1.2 performance could be achieved at low altitude, which required that titanium be used in critical areas in the fuselage and wing structure. The low altitude performance requirement was later lowered to Mach&amp;nbsp;0.85, reducing the amount of titanium and therefore cost.&lt;ref name=&quot;Knaack p.584&quot;/&gt; A pair of small [[Canard (aeronautics)|vanes]] mounted near the nose are part of an active vibration damping system that smooths out the otherwise bumpy low-altitude ride.&lt;ref&gt;Schefter, Jim. [https://books.google.com/books?id=cwEAAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA110 &quot;The Other Story About The Controversial B-1.&quot;] ''Popular Science'', Volume 210. Issue 5, May 1977, p. 112.&lt;/ref&gt; The first three B-1As featured the escape capsule that ejected the cockpit with all four crew members inside. The fourth B-1A was equipped with a conventional [[ejection seat]] for each crew member.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Spick|1986|pp=30–32.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The B-1A mockup review occurred in late October 1971.&lt;ref name=&quot;Knaack p.586&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Knaack|1988|p=586.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first B-1A prototype (Air Force serial no. 74-0158) flew on 23 December 1974. Three more B-1A prototypes followed.&lt;ref name=B-1B_backgrounder&gt;[http://www.boeing.com/defense-space/military/b1-lancer/docs/B-1B_overview.pdf &quot;B-1B Background Information.&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061026163809/http://www.boeing.com/defense-space/military/b1-lancer/docs/B-1B_overview.pdf |date=26 October 2006}} ''Boeing''. Retrieved: 8 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; As the program continued the per-unit cost continued to rise in part because of high [[inflation]] during that period. In 1970, the estimated unit cost was $40 million, and by 1975, this figure had climbed to $70 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Jenkins|1999|p=44.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===New problems and cancellation===
[[File:B-1A underside 1982.jpg|thumb|left|B-1A Prototype 4 showing its underside in 1981 |alt= A B-1A flying with its wings swept back, showing its underside]]
[[File:B1A160wingsmuseum.JPG|thumb|left|B-1A nose section with ejection capsule denoted. Three of the four B-1As were fitted with escape capsules. |alt= The nose section of a B-1A on display with outline of the ejection capsule denoted]]

In 1976, Soviet pilot [[Viktor Belenko]] defected to [[Japan]] with his [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-25|MiG-25 &quot;Foxbat&quot;]].&lt;ref&gt;Willis, David K. [https://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/csmonitor_historic/access/261218552.html?dids=261218552:261218552&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:AI&amp;date=Sep+16%2C+1976&amp;author=By+David+K.+Willis+Staff+correspondent+of+The+Christian+Science+Monitor&amp;pub=Christian+Science+Monitor&amp;desc=Japan's+scrutiny+of+Soviet+jet+jars+detente&amp;pqatl=google &quot;Japan's scrutiny of Soviet jet jars détente.&quot;] ''Christian Science Monitor'', 16 September 1976. Retrieved: 23 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; During debriefing he described a new &quot;super-Foxbat&quot; (almost certainly referring to the [[Mikoyan MiG-31|MiG-31]]) that had [[look-down/shoot-down]] [[radar]] in order to attack cruise missiles. This would also make any low-level penetration aircraft &quot;visible&quot; and easy to attack.&lt;ref&gt;Donald 2004, p. 120.&lt;/ref&gt; Given that the B-1's armament suite was similar to the B-52, and it now appeared no more likely to survive Soviet airspace than the B-52, the program was increasingly questioned.&lt;ref name=&quot;Knaack p.590&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Knaack|1988|p=590.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In particular, Senator [[William Proxmire]] continually derided the B-1 in public, arguing it was an outlandishly expensive dinosaur. During the [[1976 United States presidential election|1976 federal election]] campaign, [[Jimmy Carter]] made it one of the Democratic Party's platforms, saying &quot;The B-1 bomber is an example of a proposed system which should not be funded and would be wasteful of taxpayers' dollars.&quot;&lt;ref name=time&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,919040-1,00.html &quot;Carter's Big Decision: Down Goes the B-1, Here Comes the Cruise.&quot;] ''Time'', 11 July 1977. Retrieved: 8 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

When Carter took office in 1977 he ordered a review of the entire program. By this point the projected cost of the program had risen to over $100 million per aircraft, although this was lifetime cost over 20 years. He was informed of the relatively new work on [[stealth aircraft]] that had started in 1975, and he decided that this was a better avenue of approach than the B-1. [[The Pentagon|Pentagon]] officials also stated that the [[AGM-86 ALCM|AGM-86]] Air Launched Cruise Missile (ALCM) launched from the existing B-52 fleet would give the USAF equal capability of penetrating Soviet airspace. With a range of {{convert|1500|mi|km}}, the ALCM could be launched well outside the range of any Soviet defenses and penetrate at low altitude like a bomber (with a much lower [[radar cross-section]] due to smaller size), and in much greater numbers at a lower cost.&lt;ref name=&quot;Withington p.7&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Withington|2006|p=7.}}&lt;/ref&gt; A small number of B-52s could launch hundreds of ALCMs, saturating the defense. A program to improve the B-52 and develop and deploy the ALCM would cost perhaps 20% of the price to deploy the planned 244 B-1As.&lt;ref name=time/&gt;

On 30 June 1977, Carter announced that the B-1A would be canceled in favor of ICBMs, SLBMs, and a fleet of modernized B-52s armed with ALCMs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sorrels p.27&quot;/&gt; Carter called it &quot;one of the most difficult decisions that I've made since I've been in office.&quot;  No mention of the stealth work was made public with the program being [[Classified information|top secret]], but today it is known that in early 1978 he authorized the ''Advanced Technology Bomber'' (ATB) project, which eventually led to the [[Northrop Grumman B-2 Spirit|B-2 Spirit]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Pace p20-27&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Pace|1999|pp=20–27.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Domestically, the reaction to the cancellation was split along partisan lines. The Department of Defense was surprised by the announcement; internal expectations were that the number of B-1s ordered would be reduced to around 150.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sorrels p.23&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Sorrels|1983|p=23.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Congressman [[Robert Dornan]] (R-CA) claimed, &quot;They're breaking out the vodka and caviar in Moscow.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Belcher, Jerry. [https://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/653499322.html?dids=653499322:653499322&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:AI&amp;type=historic&amp;date=Jun+11%2C+1977&amp;author=&amp;pub=Los+Angeles+Times&amp;desc=Dropping+B-1+Would+Bring+World+War+III%2C+Dornan+Says&amp;pqatl=google &quot;Dropping B-1 Would Bring World War III, Dornan Says.&quot;] ''Los Angeles Times'', 11 June 1977.&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast, it appears the Soviets were more concerned by large numbers of ALCMs representing a much greater threat than a smaller number of B-1s. Soviet news agency [[Telegraph Agency of the Soviet Union|TASS]] commented that &quot;the implementation of these militaristic plans has seriously complicated efforts for the limitation of the strategic arms race.&quot;&lt;ref name=time/&gt; Western military leaders were generally happy with the decision. NATO commander [[Alexander Haig]] described the ALCM as an &quot;attractive alternative&quot; to the B-1. French General Georges Buis stated &quot;The B-1 is a formidable weapon, but not terribly useful. For the price of one bomber, you can have 200 cruise missiles.&quot;&lt;ref name=time/&gt;

Flight tests of the four B-1A prototypes for the B-1A program continued through April 1981. The program included 70 flights totaling 378 hours. A top speed of Mach&amp;nbsp;2.22 was reached by the second B-1A. Engine testing also continued during this time with the YF101 engines totaling almost 7,600 hours.&lt;ref name=Jenkins_p46&gt;{{harvnb|Jenkins|1999|p=46.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Shifting priorities===
[[File:USAF B-1A Lancer.JPEG|thumb|upright=1.4|A Rockwell B-1A in 1984 |alt= A right side view of a B-1A on the ground in 1984]]

It was during this period that the Soviets started to assert themselves in several new theaters of action, in particular through [[Cuban intervention in Angola|Cuban proxies]] during the [[Angolan Civil War]] starting in 1975 and the [[Soviet–Afghan War|Soviet invasion of Afghanistan]] in 1979. U.S. strategy to this point had been focused on [[containment|containing]] [[Communism]] and preparation for war in Europe. The new Soviet actions revealed that the military lacked capability outside these narrow confines.&lt;ref name=LRCA&gt;Liggett, Lieutenant Colonel William R. [http://www.airpower.maxwell.af.mil/airchronicles/aureview/1982/jul-aug/liggett.html &quot;Long-Range Combat Aircraft and Rapid Deployment Forces.&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061004221302/http://www.airpower.maxwell.af.mil/airchronicles/aureview/1982/jul-aug/liggett.html |date=4 October 2006 }} Maxwell Air Force Base, ''Air University Review'', July–August 1982. Retrieved: 8 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

The U.S. Department of Defense responded by accelerating its [[United States Rapid Deployment Forces|Rapid Deployment Forces]] concept but suffered from major problems with airlift and sealift capability.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Moore|first=John Leo|title=U.S. Defense Policy: Weapons, Strategy, and Commitments|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qcQdAAAAMAAJ|year=1980|publisher=Congressional Quarterly|isbn=978-0-87187-158-9|pages=65, 79}}&lt;/ref&gt; In order to slow an enemy invasion of other countries, air power was critical; however the key Iran-Afghanistan border was outside the range of the [[U.S. Navy]]'s carrier-based attack aircraft, leaving this role to the U.S. Air Force. Although the B-52 had the range to support on-demand global missions, its long runway requirements limited the forward basing possibilities.&lt;ref&gt;Herbet, Adam J. [http://www.airforce-magazine.com/MagazineArchive/Documents/2002/January%202002/0102base.pdf &quot;The Search for Asian Bases.&quot;] ''AIR FORCE Magazine'', January 2002, pp. 51–53.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 1980 presidential campaign, [[Ronald Reagan]] campaigned heavily on the platform that Carter was weak on defense, citing the cancellation of the B-1 program as an example, a theme he continued using into the 1980s.&lt;ref&gt;Reagan, President Ronald. [http://www.presidentreagan.info/speeches/address_to_nation/1984_10_20.cfm &quot;Reagan's Radio Address to the Nation on Foreign Policy.&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070317181440/http://www.presidentreagan.info/speeches/address_to_nation/1984_10_20.cfm |date=17 March 2007}} ''presidentreagan.info''. 20 October 1984.&lt;/ref&gt; During this time Carter's defense secretary, [[Harold Brown (Secretary of Defense)|Harold Brown]], announced the stealth bomber project, apparently implying that this was the reason for the B-1 cancellation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schwartz p.120&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schwartz|1998|p=120.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===B-1B program===
[[File:First B-1, Palmdale.jpg|thumb|left|The first B-1B debuted outside a hangar in [[Palmdale, California]], 1984|alt= The first B-1B at its roll-out ceremony outside a hangar in Palmdale, California in 1984]]

On taking office, Reagan was faced with the same decision as Carter before: whether to continue with the B-1 for the short term, or to wait for the development of the ATB, a much more advanced aircraft. Studies suggested that the existing B-52 fleet with [[Air-launched cruise missile|ALCM]] would remain a credible threat until 1985. It was predicted that 75% of the B-52 force would survive to attack its targets.&lt;ref name=post-b-52&gt;Mitchell, Douglas D. [https://digital.library.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metacrs8615/ &quot;IB81107, &quot;Bomber Options for Replacing B-52s.&quot;] ''Library of Congress Congressional Research Service, via Digital Library, UNT,'' 3 May 1982. Retrieved: 16 July 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; After 1985, the introduction of the [[SA-10]] missile, the MiG-31 interceptor and the first Soviet [[Airborne Early Warning and Control]] (AWACS) systems would make the B-52 increasingly vulnerable.&lt;ref&gt;Jumper, John P. [http://oai.dtic.mil/oai/oai?verb=getRecord&amp;metadataPrefix=html&amp;identifier=ADA518979 &quot;Global Strike Task Force: A Transforming Concept, Forged by Experience.&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120312075538/http://oai.dtic.mil/oai/oai?verb=getRecord&amp;metadataPrefix=html&amp;identifier=ADA518979 |date=12 March 2012}} ''Aerospace Power Journal'' 15, no. 1, Spring 2001, pp. 30–31. Originally published by ''Air University'', Maxwell Air Force Base, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; During 1981, funds were allocated to a new study for a bomber for the 1990s time-frame which led to developing the ''Long-Range Combat Aircraft'' (LRCA) project. The LRCA evaluated the B-1, F-111, and ATB as possible solutions; an emphasis was placed on multi-role capabilities, as opposed to purely strategic operations.&lt;ref name=post-b-52/&gt;

In 1981, it was believed the B-1 could be in operation before the [[Advanced Technology Bomber|ATB]], covering the transitional period between the B-52's increasing vulnerability and the ATB's introduction. Reagan decided the best solution was to procure both the B-1 and ATB, and on 2 October 1981 he announced that 100 B-1s were to be ordered to fill the LRCA role.&lt;ref name=&quot;lee p.13&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Reagan approves&quot;&gt;Coates, James. [https://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/chicagotribune/access/635722892.html?dids=635722892:635722892&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:AI&amp;type=historic&amp;date=Oct+03%2C+1981&amp;author=&amp;pub=Chicago+Tribune&amp;desc=Reagan+approves+B-1%2C+alters+basing+for+MX&amp;pqatl=google &quot;Reagan approves B-1, alters basing for MX.&quot;] ''Chicago Tribune'', 3 October 1981. Retrieved: 28 July 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 1982, the U.S. Air Force awarded two contracts to Rockwell worth a combined $2.2 billion for the development and production of 100 new B-1 bombers.&lt;ref name=Jenkins_p62&gt;{{harvnb|Jenkins|1999|p=62.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Numerous changes were made to the design to make it better suited to the now expected missions, resulting in the ''B-1B''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Withington p.7&quot;/&gt; These changes included a reduction in maximum speed,&lt;ref name=&quot;Schwartz p.120&quot;/&gt; which allowed the variable-aspect [[Inlet cone|intake ramps]] to be replaced by simpler fixed geometry intake ramps in the newer design. This reduced the B-1B's radar signature or [[radar cross-section]]; this reduction was seen as a good trade off for the speed decrease.&lt;ref name=&quot;lee p.13&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Lee|2008|p=13.}}&lt;/ref&gt; High subsonic speeds at low altitude became a focus area for the revised design,&lt;ref name=&quot;Schwartz p.120&quot;/&gt; and low-level speeds were increased from about Mach&amp;nbsp;0.85 to 0.92. The B-1B has a maximum speed of Mach&amp;nbsp;1.25 at higher altitudes.&lt;ref name=&quot;lee p.13&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=BNA_B-1B_specs/&gt;

The B-1B's maximum takeoff weight was increased to {{convert|477000|lb|kg}} from the B-1A's {{convert|395000|lb|kg}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;lee p.13&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Spick_1986_p28/&gt; The weight increase was to allow for takeoff with a full internal fuel load and for external weapons to be carried. Rockwell engineers were able to reinforce critical areas and lighten non-critical areas of the airframe, so the increase in [[Basic aircraft empty weight|empty weight]] was minimal.&lt;ref name=Spick_1986_p28&gt;{{harvnb|Spick|1986|p=28.}}&lt;/ref&gt; To deal with the introduction of the [[MiG-31]] equipped with the new [[Zaslon]] radar system, and other aircraft with [[Look-down/shoot-down|look-down]] capability (which reduced the B-1s low-flying advantage), the B-1B's [[electronic warfare]] suite was significantly upgraded.&lt;ref name=&quot;lee p.13&quot;/&gt;

[[File:A B-1 Lancer performs a fly-by during a firepower demonstration.jpg|thumb|B-1B banking during a demonstration in 2004 |alt= B-1B with its wings swept back doing a banked turn during a demonstration]]
Opposition to the plan was widespread within Congress. Critics pointed out that many of the original problems remained in both areas of performance and expense.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Casil|2003|p=7.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In particular it seemed the B-52 fitted with electronics similar to the B-1B would be equally able to avoid interception, as the speed advantage of the B-1 was now minimal. It also appeared that the &quot;interim&quot; time frame served by the B-1B would be less than a decade, being rendered obsolete shortly after the introduction of a much more capable ATB design.&lt;ref&gt;Germani, Clara, ed. [http://www.csmonitor.com/1981/0921/092119.html &quot;Former defense chief raps B-1 bomber plan.&quot;] ''Christian Science Monitor,'' 21 September 1981. Retrieved: 28 July 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The primary argument in favor of the B-1 was its large [[conventional weapon]] payload, and that its takeoff performance allowed it to operate with a credible bomb load from a much wider variety of airfields. The USAF spread production subcontracts across many congressional districts, making the aircraft more popular on [[Capitol Hill]].&lt;ref name=post-b-52/&gt;

B-1A No. 1 was disassembled and used for radar testing at the [[Rome Laboratory|Rome Air Development Center]] at the former [[Griffiss Air Force Base]], [[New York (state)|New York]].&lt;ref name=Jenkins_p70&gt;{{harvnb|Jenkins|1999|pp=70–74.}}&lt;/ref&gt; B-1As No. 2 and No. 4 were then modified to include B-1B systems. The first B-1B was completed and began flight testing in March 1983. The first production B-1B was rolled out on 4 September 1984 and first flew on 18 October 1984.&lt;ref name=Jenkins_p63-4&gt;{{harvnb|Jenkins|1999|pp=63–64.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 100th and final B-1B was delivered on 2 May 1988;&lt;ref name=B-1B_backgrounder/&gt; before the last B-1B was delivered, the USAF had determined that the aircraft was vulnerable to Soviet air defenses.&lt;ref name=&quot;dao 1&quot;&gt;Dao 2001, p.1&lt;/ref&gt;

==Design==

===Overview===
The B-1 has a [[blended wing body]] configuration, with [[variable-sweep wing]], four [[turbofan|turbofan engines]], triangular fin control surfaces and [[cruciform tail]]. The wings can sweep from 15 degrees to 67.5 degrees (full forward to full sweep). Forward-swept wing settings are used for [[takeoff]], [[landing]]s and high-altitude maximum [[cruise (flight)|cruise]]. Aft-swept wing settings are used in high subsonic and supersonic flight.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Withington|2006|p=16.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The B-1's variable-sweep wings and [[thrust-to-weight ratio]] provide it with improved takeoff performance, allowing it to use shorter runways than previous bombers.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Knaack|1988|p=587.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The length of the aircraft presented a flexing problem due to air turbulence at low altitude. To alleviate this, Rockwell included small triangular fin control surfaces or vanes near the nose on the B-1. The B-1's Structural Mode Control System rotates the vanes automatically to counteract turbulence and smooth out the ride.&lt;ref&gt;Wykes, J. H. [http://www.aiaa.org/content.cfm?pageid=406&amp;gTable=mtgpaper&amp;gID=57365 &quot;AIAA-1972-772, B-1 Structural Mode Control System.&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070927230619/http://www.aiaa.org/content.cfm?pageid=406&amp;gTable=mtgpaper&amp;gID=57365 |date=27 September 2007}} ''American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics'' (AIAA), 9 August 1972. Retrieved: 3 August 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:RIAT2004-B1B.jpg|thumb|Rear view of B-1B in flight, 2004|alt= A rear view of a B-1B at [[Royal International Air Tattoo]] air show in 2004]]
Unlike the B-1A, the B-1B cannot reach Mach&amp;nbsp;2+ speeds; its maximum speed is Mach&amp;nbsp;1.25 (about 950&amp;nbsp;mph or 1,530&amp;nbsp;km/h at altitude),&lt;ref name=Jenkins_p60&gt;{{harvnb|Jenkins|1999|p=60.}}&lt;/ref&gt; but its low-level speed increased to Mach&amp;nbsp;0.92 (700&amp;nbsp;mph, 1,130&amp;nbsp;km/h).&lt;ref name=BNA_B-1B_specs&gt;{{harvnb|Pace|1998|p=64.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The speed of the current version of the aircraft is limited by the need to avoid damage to its structure and air intakes. To help lower its radar cross section (RCS), the B-1B uses [[serpentine shape|serpentine]] air [[intake|intake ducts]] (see [[S-duct]]) and fixed [[intake ramp]]s, which limit its speed compared to the B-1A. Vanes in the intake ducts serve to deflect and shield radar emissions from the highly reflective engine compressor blades.&lt;ref name=Spick_1986_p44-5&gt;{{harvnb|Spick|1986|pp=44–45.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The B-1A's engine was modified slightly to produce the [[General Electric F101|GE F101-102]] for the B-1B, with an emphasis on durability, and increased efficiency.&lt;ref name=Modern_Warplanes&gt;{{harvnb|Spick|1987|p=498.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The core of this engine has since been re-used in several other engine designs, including the [[General Electric F110|GE F110]] which has seen use in the [[Grumman F-14 Tomcat|F-14 Tomcat]], [[McDonnell Douglas F-15E Strike Eagle|F-15K/SG]] variants and most recent versions of the [[General Dynamics F-16 Fighting Falcon]].&lt;ref name=&quot;GE&quot;&gt;[http://www.geae.com/aboutgeae/presscenter/military/military_2003616.html &quot;F110 Family.&quot;] ''GE Aviation.'' Retrieved: 25 January 2010&lt;/ref&gt; It is also the basis for the non-[[afterburner|afterburning]] [[General Electric F118|GE F118]] used in the B-2 Spirit and the [[Lockheed U-2|U-2S]].&lt;ref name=&quot;GE&quot;/&gt; The F101 engine was the basis for the core of the extremely popular [[CFM International CFM56|CFM56]] civil engine, which can be found on some versions of practically every small-to-medium-sized airliner.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cfm56.com/press/news/cfm+delivers+20000th+cfm56+engine/511 &quot;CFM delivers 20,000th engine&quot;.] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110722140937/http://www.cfm56.com/press/news/cfm+delivers+20000th+cfm56+engine/511 |date=22 July 2011}} ''CFM International''. Retrieved: 25 January 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The nose gear cover door has controls for the [[auxiliary power unit]]s (APUs), which allow for quick starts of the APUs upon order to scramble.&lt;ref name=Spick_1986_p44&gt;{{harvnb|Spick|1986|p=44.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Pace_p44&gt;{{harvnb|Pace|1998|p=44.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Avionics===
[[File:B-1cockpitnight.jpg|thumb|left|B-1B cockpit at night |alt=The interior of a B-1B cockpit at night]]
[[File:AN-APQ-164 radar, Westinghouse, developed in 1982 - National Electronics Museum - DSC00384.JPG|thumb|AN/APQ-164 [[passive electronically scanned array]]]]

The B-1's main computer is the [[IBM AP-101]], which was also used on the [[Space Shuttle orbiter]] and the [[B-52]] bomber.&lt;ref name=&quot;ap101&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hq.nasa.gov/office/pao/History/computers/Ch4-3.html|title=Ch4-3|work=nasa.gov|accessdate=1 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The computer is programmed with the [[JOVIAL (programming language)|JOVIAL]] programming language.&lt;ref name=&quot;jovial&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://business.highbeam.com/438317/article-1G1-3161147/jovial-smooth-us-air-force-shift-ada |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121012015607/http://business.highbeam.com/438317/article-1G1-3161147/jovial-smooth-us-air-force-shift-ada |url-status=dead |archive-date=12 October 2012 |title=Jovial to smooth U.S. Air Force shift to Ada. (processing language) |website=Business.highbeam.com |date=1 March 1984 |accessdate=3 March 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Lancer's offensive [[avionics]] include the [[Westinghouse Electronic Systems|Westinghouse]] (now [[Northrop Grumman]]) {{anchor|AN/APQ-164|APQ-164|radar}}AN/APQ-164 forward-looking offensive [[passive electronically scanned array]] radar set with electronic beam steering (and a fixed antenna pointed downward for reduced radar observability), [[synthetic aperture radar]], ground [[moving target indication]] (GMTI), and [[terrain-following radar]] modes, [[Doppler radar#Doppler navigation|Doppler navigation]], [[radar altimeter]], and an [[inertial navigation]] suite.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.es.northropgrumman.com/solutions/b1radar/ &quot;AN/APQ-164 B-1B Radar&quot;.] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110212010148/http://www.es.northropgrumman.com/solutions/b1radar/ |date=12 February 2011}} ''Northrop Grumman''. Retrieved: 25 January 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The B-1B Block D upgrade added a [[Global Positioning System]] (GPS) receiver beginning in 1995.&lt;ref name=Withington_p33-4&gt;{{harvnb|Withington|2006|pp=33–34.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The B-1's defensive electronics include the [[Eaton Corporation|Eaton]] AN/ALQ-161A [[Radar warning receiver|radar warning]] and defensive [[Radar jamming and deception|jamming]] equipment,&lt;ref name=&quot;lee p.15&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Lee|2008|p=15.}}&lt;/ref&gt; which has three sets of antennas; one at the front base of each wing and the third rear-facing in the tail [[radome]].&lt;ref name=Spick_1986_p52-3&gt;{{harvnb|Spick|1986|pp=52–53.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Jenkins_p106&gt;{{harvnb|Jenkins|1999|p=106.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also in the tail radome is the [[AN/ALQ-153]] [[missile approach warning system]] ([[pulse-Doppler radar]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.fas.org/man/dod-101/sys/ac/equip/an-alq-153.htm |title=AN/ALQ-153 Missile Warning System |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |website=FAS |publisher=FAS |accessdate=2 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ALQ-161 is linked to a total of eight AN/ALE-49 [[Flare (countermeasure)|flare]] dispensers located on top behind the canopy, which are handled by the AN/ASQ-184 avionics management system.&lt;ref name=&quot;Skaarup p.18&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Skaarup|2002|p=18.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Each AN/ALE-49 dispenser has a capacity of 12 MJU-23A/B flares. The MJU-23A/B flare is one of the world's largest [[infrared countermeasure]] flares at a weight of over {{convert|3.3|lb|kg}}.&lt;ref&gt;Humphries, J. A. and D. E. Miller. [http://pdf.aiaa.org/preview/1997/PV1997_2963.pdf &quot;AIAA-1997-2963: B-1B/MJU-23 flare strike test program.&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070620042701/http://pdf.aiaa.org/preview/1997/PV1997_2963.pdf |date=20 June 2007}} ''American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics'', AIAA/ASME/SAE/ASEE Joint Propulsion Conference and Exhibit, 33rd, Seattle, Washington, 6–9 July 1997. Retrieved: 8 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The B-1 has also been equipped to carry the [[ALE-50 towed decoy system]].&lt;ref name=AF_sheet&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.af.mil/About-Us/Fact-Sheets/Display/Article/104500/b-1b-lancer/ |title=&quot;B-1B USAF fact sheet&quot;}}. ''U.S. Air Force''. Retrieved: 25 June 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;

Also aiding the B-1's survivability is its relatively low [[radar cross-section]] (RCS). Although not technically a [[stealth aircraft]] in a comprehensive sense, thanks to the aircraft's structure, serpentine intake paths and use of [[radar-absorbent material]] its RCS is about 1/50th of the similar sized B-52's RCS; this is about 26&amp;nbsp;ft&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; or 2.4&amp;nbsp;m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, roughly equivalent to the RCS of a small [[fighter aircraft]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Skaarup p.18&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sbfisica.org.br/rfai/Vol15/Num1/v15_24.pdf |title=Radar Cross Section Measurements (8–12 GHz) of Magnetic and Dielectric Microwave Absorbing Thin Sheets |website=Sbfisica.org.br |accessdate=3 March 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cunningham, Jim. [http://www.dtic.mil/cgi-bin/GetTRDoc?Location=U2&amp;doc=GetTRDoc.pdf&amp;AD=ADA332536 &quot;The New Old Threat: Fighter Upgrades and What They Mean for the USAF&quot;, p. 7.] ''Illinois State University'', 3 December 1997.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Upgrades===
[[File:A B-1B Lancer with a Sniper pod.jpeg|thumb|Nose of B-1 with the [[Sniper Advanced Targeting Pod|Sniper XR pod]] hanging below|alt=Sideview of a B-1B's nose section, which features a Sniper XR pod mounted on its chin]]

The B-1 has been upgraded since production, beginning with the &quot;Conventional Mission Upgrade Program&quot; (CMUP), which added a new [[MIL-STD-1760]] smart-weapons interface to enable the use of precision-guided conventional weapons. CMUP began with Block A, which was the standard B-1B with the capability to deliver non-precision gravity bombs. Block B brought an improved Synthetic Aperture Radar, and upgrades to the Defensive Countermeasures System and was fielded in 1995. Block C provided an &quot;enhanced capability&quot; for delivery of up to 30 cluster bomb units (CBUs) per [[sortie]] with modifications made to 50 bomb racks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Skaarup p.19&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Skaarup|2002|p=19.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Block D added a &quot;Near Precision Capability&quot; via improved weapons and targeting systems, and added advanced secure communications capabilities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Skaarup p.19&quot;/&gt; The first part of the electronic countermeasures upgrade added [[Joint Direct Attack Munition]] (JDAM), [[ALE-50 towed decoy system]], and anti-jam radios.&lt;ref name=&quot;lee p.15&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.boeing.com/defense-space/military/b1-lancer/news/1998/news_release_981204n.htm &quot;Boeing Completes Block E Avionics Upgrade of B-1 Bomber Fleet.&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070203172944/http://www.boeing.com/defense-space/military/b1-lancer/news/1998/news_release_981204n.htm |date=3 February 2007}} ''Boeing'', 4 December 1998. Retrieved: 8 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Adams, Charlotte. [http://www.aviationtoday.com/av/issue/feature/Building-Blocks-to-Upgrade-to-B-1B_12802.html &quot;Building Blocks to Upgrade to B-1B.&quot;] ''Avionics Magazine'', 1 August 2002. Retrieved: 24 June 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Block E upgraded the avionics computers and incorporated the [[Wind Corrected Munitions Dispenser]] (WCMD), the [[AGM-154 Joint Standoff Weapon]] (JSOW) and the [[AGM-158 JASSM]] (Joint Air to Surface Standoff Munition), substantially improving the bomber's capability. Upgrades were completed in September 2006.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.boeing.com/defense-space/military/b1-lancer/news/2006/q3/060927d_nr.html &quot;Boeing 2006 Block E Upgrades.&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071011155539/http://boeing.com/defense-space/military/b1-lancer/news/2006/q3/060927d_nr.html |date=11 October 2007}} ''Boeing'', 27 September 2006. Retrieved: 14 August 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Block F was the Defensive Systems Upgrade Program (DSUP) to improve the aircraft's electronic countermeasures and jamming capabilities, but it was canceled in December 2002 due to cost overruns and schedule slips.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20080408234341/http://www.b1b.wpafb.af.mil/pages/pdf/dsuptermination.pdf &quot;Block F Upgrades.&quot;] ''US Air Force'', 21 January 2003. Retrieved: 24 June 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005, a program began to upgrade crew stations and integrate data linking.&lt;ref&gt;Young, Susan H. [http://www.airforce-magazine.com/MagazineArchive/Magazine%20Documents/2009/May%202009/0509weapons.pdf &quot;Gallery of USAF Weapons.&quot;] ''Air Force Magazine'', May 2009. Retrieved: 8 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; A B-1 equipped with the fully integrated data link (FIDL) first flew on 29 July 2009; the FIDL enables electronic data sharing, eliminating the need to enter information between systems by hand.&lt;ref&gt;Maull, Lisa and Forrest Gossett. [http://boeing.mediaroom.com/index.php?s=43&amp;item=795 &quot;Boeing B-1 Upgraded With Fully Integrated Data Link Completes 1st Flight.&quot;] ''Boeing'', 13 August 2009. Retrieved: 8 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; In January 2013, Boeing delivered the first integrated battle station (IBS) equipped B-1. This replaced several displays with new multi-function color display units, an upgraded central integrated test system, and a newer aircraft performance monitoring computer.&lt;ref&gt;[http://boeing.mediaroom.com/US-Air-Force-Receives-1st-B-1-Equipped-with-Boeing-Integrated-Battle-Station &quot;US Air Force Receives 1st B-1 Equipped with Boeing Integrated Battle Station.&quot;] Boeing&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=B-1B_Upgrade_Contract&gt;&quot;Boeing Awarded B-1B Upgrade Contract&quot;. September 2011. ''AirForces Monthly''. Issue 282. p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.acc.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123377914 &quot;Dyess receives first operational IBS-upgraded B-1&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150212001956/http://www.acc.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123377914 |date=12 February 2015}}. USAF, 24 January 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2012, the B-1Bs are receiving Sustainment-Block 16 upgrades to add [[Link 16]] networking and digital flight instrumentation.&lt;ref&gt;Rivezzo, Charles V. [http://www.af.mil/News/ArticleDisplay/tabid/223/Article/111068/new-upgrades-revitalize-b-1b-lancers.aspx &quot;New upgrades revitalize B-1B Lancers.&quot;] ''USAF'', 2 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, the [[Sniper Advanced Targeting Pod|Sniper XR]] targeting pod was integrated on the B-1 fleet. The pod is mounted on an external hardpoint at the aircraft's chin near the forward bomb bay.&lt;ref&gt;Hernandez, Jason. [http://www.edwards.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123042301 &quot;419th FLTS demonstrates Sniper pod capability.&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090705235409/http://www.edwards.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123042301 |date=5 July 2009}} ''US Air Force'', 23 February 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Following accelerated testing, the Sniper pod was fielded in summer 2008.&lt;ref name=Sniper_combat/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;La Rue, Nori. [http://www.edwards.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123101089 &quot;B-1 Sniper pod aims to hit summer target.&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080608123406/http://www.edwards.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123101089 |date=8 June 2008}} ''US Air Force'', 4 June 2008. Retrieved: 8 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Future precision munitions include the [[Small Diameter Bomb]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Wicke, Russell. |url=http://www.af.mil/news/story.asp?storyID=123028580 |title= ACC declares small diameter bomb initially operational |publisher= US Air Force |date= 5 October 2006 |access-date=28 September 2007 |url-status=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://archive.today/20120802142216/http://www.af.mil/news/story.asp?storyID=123028580 |archivedate=2 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011, the Air Force was considering upgrading B-1s with multiple ejector racks so that they can carry three times as many smaller JDAMs than previously.&lt;ref&gt;Rivezzo, Charles. {{cite web |url=http://www.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123250639 |title=&quot;B-1B Lancer upgrade will triple payload.&quot; |accessdate=12 April 2011 |url-status=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://archive.today/20120720134626/http://www.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123250639 |archivedate=20 July 2012}} ''USAF'', 11 April 2011. Retrieved: 31 August 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2014, work began on a multi-year upgrade of 62 B-1Bs, scheduled to be completed by 2019. The vertical situation display upgrade (VSDU) replaces existing flight instruments with multifunction color displays, a second display aids with threat evasion and targeting, and act as a back-up display. Additional memory capacity is to be installed for the diagnostics database.  Procurement and installation of the IBS upgrades is expected to cost $918 million, research and engineering costs are estimated at $391 million.  Other additions are to replace the two spinning mass gyroscopic inertial navigation system with [[ring laser gyroscope|ring laser gyroscopic]] systems and a GPS antenna, replacement of the [[AN/APG-66|APQ-164 radar]] with the Scalable Agile Beam Radar – Global Strike ([[SABR-GS]]) [[active electronically scanned array]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.northropgrumman.com/Capabilities/SABR-GS/Pages/default.aspx |title=Scalable Agile Beam Radar – Global Strike (SABR-GS) AESA for the B-1B |website=Northropgrumman.com |accessdate=3 March 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a new attitude indicator.&lt;ref name=&quot;defensetech21feb14&quot;&gt;[http://defensetech.org/2014/02/21/air-force-begins-massive-b-1b-overhaul/ Air Force Begins Massive B-1B Overhaul] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140221231712/http://defensetech.org/2014/02/21/air-force-begins-massive-b-1b-overhaul/ |date=21 February 2014 }} – Defensetech.org, 21 February 2014&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operational history==

===Strategic Air Command===
The second B-1B, &quot;The Star of Abilene&quot;, was the first B-1B delivered to the USAF [[Strategic Air Command]] (SAC) in June 1985. Initial operational capability was reached on 1 October 1986 and the B-1B was placed on nuclear alert status.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Pace|1998|pp=62, 69.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Jenkins_p83&gt;{{harvnb|Jenkins|1999|p=83.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The B-1 received the official name &quot;Lancer&quot; on 15 March 1990. However, the bomber has been commonly called the &quot;Bone&quot;; a nickname that appears to stem from an early newspaper article on the aircraft wherein its name was phonetically spelled out as &quot;B-ONE&quot; with the hyphen inadvertently omitted.&lt;ref name= Jenkins_p67&gt;{{harvnb|Jenkins|1999|p=67.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Decommissioned B-1 Bomber Travels Along I-5 (6327003326).jpg|thumb|left|A dismantled decommissioned B-1 being transported by flatbed truck]]
In late 1990, engine fires in two Lancers led to a grounding of the fleet. The cause was traced back to problems in the first-stage fan, and the aircraft were placed on &quot;limited alert&quot;; in other words, they were grounded unless a nuclear war broke out. Following inspections and repairs they were returned to duty beginning on 6 February 1991.&lt;ref name=Jenkins_p116&gt;{{harvnb|Jenkins|1999|p=116.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;B-1 aircrew logbook entry.&lt;/ref&gt; By 1991, the B-1 had a fledgling conventional capability, forty of them able to drop the {{convert|500|lb|adj=on}} Mk-82 General Purpose (GP) bomb, although mostly from low altitude. Despite being cleared for this role, the problems with the engines prevented their use in [[Operation Desert Storm]] during the [[Gulf War]].&lt;ref name=&quot;dao 1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Withington p. 10&quot;/&gt; B-1s were primarily reserved for strategic nuclear strike missions at this time, providing the role of airborne nuclear deterrent against the Soviet Union.&lt;ref name=&quot;Withington p. 10&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Withington|2006|p=10.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The B-52 was more suited to the role of conventional warfare and it was used by coalition forces instead.&lt;ref name=&quot;Withington p. 10&quot;/&gt;

Originally designed strictly for nuclear war, the B-1's development as an effective conventional bomber was delayed. The collapse of the Soviet Union had brought the B-1's nuclear role into question, leading to President [[George H. W. Bush]] ordering a $3 billion conventional refit.&lt;ref name=&quot;dao 4&quot;&gt;Dao 2001, p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt;

After the inactivation of Strategic Air Command (SAC) and the establishment of the [[Air Combat Command]] (ACC) in 1992, the B-1 developed a greater conventional weapons capability. Part of this development was the start-up of the U.S. Air Force Weapons School B-1 Division.&lt;ref&gt;Scott, Ed. [https://web.archive.org/web/20121105211815/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-78360407.html &quot;JDAM Course Ushers B-1 Students Into New Era&quot;.] ''Program Manager'', 1 November 1999. Retrieved: 14 August 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1994, two additional B-1 bomb wings were also created in the [[Air National Guard]], with former fighter wings in the [[Kansas Air National Guard]] and the [[Georgia Air National Guard]] converting to the aircraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;Withington p. 11&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Withington|2006|p=11.}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the mid-1990s, the B-1 could employ GP weapons as well as various CBUs. By the end of the 1990s, with the advent of the &quot;Block D&quot; upgrade, the B-1 boasted a full array of guided and unguided munitions.

The B-1B no longer carries nuclear weapons;&lt;ref name=&quot;lee p.13&quot;/&gt; its nuclear capability was disabled by 1995 with the removal of nuclear arming and fuzing hardware.&lt;ref name=Jenkins_p141&gt;{{harvnb|Jenkins|1999|p=141.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Under provisions of the [[New START]] treaty with Russia, further conversion were performed. These included modification of aircraft hardpoints to prevent nuclear weapon pylons from being attached, removal of weapons bay wiring bundles for arming nuclear weapons, and destruction of nuclear weapon pylons. The conversion process was completed in 2011, and Russian officials inspect the aircraft every year to verify compliance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Pawlyk |first1=Oriana |title=START Lanced the B-1's Nukes, But the Bomber Will Still Get New Bombs |url=http://www.military.com/daily-news/2017/07/12/start-lanced-the-b-1s-nukes-but-bomber-will-still-get-new-bombs.html |website=Military.com |publisher=Military Advantage |accessdate=25 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Air Combat Command===
[[File:B1s.jpg|thumb|A B-1B Lancer with wings swept full forward |alt=Top forward view of gray aircraft with wings swept forward banking right. Underneath are strips of white clouds and uninhabited terrain.]]

The B-1 was first used in combat in support of operations in [[Iraq]] during [[Operation Desert Fox]] in December 1998, employing unguided GP weapons. B-1s have been subsequently used in [[Operation Allied Force]] (Kosovo) and, most notably, in [[War in Afghanistan (2001–present)|Operation Enduring Freedom]] in Afghanistan and the [[2003 invasion of Iraq]].&lt;ref name=&quot;lee p.13&quot;/&gt; The B-1's role in Operation Allied Force has been criticized as the aircraft was not used until after enemy defenses had been suppressed by aircraft like the older B-52 it was intended to replace.&lt;ref name=&quot;dao 1&quot;/&gt; The B-1 has deployed an array of conventional weapons in war zones, most notably the GBU-31, {{convert|2000|lb|adj=on}} [[Joint Direct Attack Munition]] (JDAM).&lt;ref name=&quot;lee p.13&quot;/&gt; In the first six months of Operation Enduring Freedom, eight B-1s dropped almost 40 percent of aerial ordnance, including some 3,900 JDAMs.&lt;ref name=&quot;defensetech21feb14&quot;/&gt; JDAM munitions were heavily used by the B-1 over Iraq, notably on 7 April 2003 in an unsuccessful attempt to kill [[Saddam Hussein]] and his two sons.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Withington|2006|pp=75–76.}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the height of the Iraq War, a B-1 was continuously kept airborne to provide rapid precision bombardment upon important targets as intelligence identified them.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb |Withington|2006|p=77.}}&lt;/ref&gt; During Operation Enduring Freedom, the B-1 was able to raise its [[availability|mission capable rate]] to 79%.&lt;ref name=AF_sheet/&gt;

The B-1 has higher survivability and speed than the older B-52, which it was intended to replace. It also holds 61 [[Fédération Aéronautique Internationale|FAI]] world records for speed, payload, distance, and time-to-climb in different aircraft weight classes.&lt;ref name=Jenkins_appE&gt;{{harvnb |Jenkins|1999|p=Appendix E.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.boeing.com/history/bna/b1b.htm &quot;History&amp;nbsp;– B-1 Lancer Bomber.&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120523004351/http://www.boeing.com/history/bna/b1b.htm |date=23 May 2012}} Boeing. Retrieved: 31 July 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; In November 1993, three B-1Bs set a long distance record for the aircraft, which demonstrated its ability to conduct extended mission lengths to strike anywhere in the world and return to base without any stops.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb |Dorr|1997|p=224.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[National Aeronautic Association]] recognized the B-1B for completing one of the 10 most memorable record flights for 1994.&lt;ref name=AF_sheet/&gt;

Of the 100 B-1Bs built, 93 remained in 2000 after losses in accidents. In June 2001, the Pentagon sought to place one-third of its then fleet into storage; this proposal resulted in several U.S. Air National Guard officers and members of Congress lobbying against the proposal, including the drafting of an amendment to prevent such cuts.&lt;ref name=&quot;dao 1&quot;/&gt; The 2001 proposal was intended to allow money to be diverted to further upgrades to the remaining B-1Bs, such as computer modernization.&lt;ref name=&quot;dao 1&quot;/&gt; In 2003, accompanied by the removal of B-1Bs from the two bomb wings in the Air National Guard, the USAF decided to retire 33 aircraft to concentrate its budget on maintaining availability of remaining B-1Bs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product=ADSB&amp;s_site=azstarnet&amp;f_site=azstarnet&amp;f_sitename=Arizona+Daily+Star%2C+The+%28AZ%29&amp;p_multi=ADSB&amp;p_theme=gannett&amp;p_action=search&amp;p_maxdocs=200&amp;p_topdoc=1&amp;p_text_direct-0=0F59D36BE743E3B9&amp;p_field_direct-0=document_id&amp;p_perpage=10&amp;p_sort=YMD_date:D&amp;s_trackval=GooglePM &quot;B-1 bomber's final flight.&quot;] ''Arizona Star'', 21 August 2002. Retrieved: 14 August 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, a new [[appropriation bill]] called for some of the retired aircraft to return to service,&lt;ref&gt;Klamper, Amy. [http://www.govexec.com/dailyfed/0604/062504cdam1.htm &quot;Lawmakers look after home military installations.&quot;] {{Webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080828224859/http://www.govexec.com/dailyfed/0604/062504cdam1.htm |date=28 August 2008}} ''govexec.com'', 25 June 2004. Retrieved: 31 July 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; and the USAF returned seven mothballed bombers to service to increase the fleet to 67 aircraft.&lt;ref name=AF_Alma_facts-figs_2005&gt;Mehuron, Tamar A. [http://www.airforce-magazine.com/MagazineArchive/Magazine%20Documents/2005/May%202005/0505facts_figs.pdf &quot;USAF Almanac: Facts and Figures&quot; (data as of 30 September 2004).] ''Air Force Magazine,'' May 2005. Retrieved: 3 July 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The Air Force has an inventory of 62 B-1s as of 2017.&lt;ref name=AF_Times_Aug2017/&gt;

[[File:JDAM B-1B Lancer.jpg|thumb|left|Crew members transferring a [[Joint Direct Attack Munition|GBU-31 Joint Direct Attack Munition]] (JDAM) to a lift truck for loading onto a B-1B on 29 March 2007, in Southwest Asia |alt=Ammunition and yellow bombs lay as two crew member, using lift truck, transfer them to a gray B-1 parked nearby in the background]]
On 14 July 2007, the Associated Press reported on the growing USAF presence in Iraq, including reintroduction of B-1Bs as a close-at-hand platform to support Coalition ground forces.&lt;ref name=AP_B-1_recall&gt;Hanley, Charles J. [http://www.commondreams.org/archive/2007/07/15/2547 &quot;Air Force Quietly Building Iraq Presence.&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121010094936/http://www.commondreams.org/archive/2007/07/15/2547 |date=10 October 2012}} ''commondreams.org'', 14 July 2007. Retrieved: 30 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Since 2008, B-1s have been used in Iraq and Afghanistan in an &quot;armed overwatch&quot; role, loitering for surveillance purposes while ready to deliver guided bombs in support of ground troops if contacted.&lt;ref&gt;Wicke, Tech. Sgt. Russell, [http://www.acc.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123094826 &quot;B-1 performs as never envisioned after 20 years.&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080502034352/http://www.acc.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123094826 |date=2 May 2008}} ''US Air Force'', 17 April 2008. Retrieved: 8 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Lancer_Force&gt;Door 2010, pp. 40–45.&lt;/ref&gt;

The B-1B underwent a series of flight tests using a 50/50 mix of synthetic and petroleum fuel; on 19 March 2008, a B-1B from [[Dyess Air Force Base]], Texas, became the first USAF aircraft to fly at supersonic speed using a [[synthetic fuel]] during a flight over Texas and New Mexico. This was conducted as part of an ongoing Air Force testing and certification program to reduce reliance on traditional oil sources.&lt;ref&gt;Bates, Matthew. {{cite web |url=http://www.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123090913 |title=&quot;B-1B achieves first supersonic flight using synthetic fuel.&quot; |accessdate=20 March 2008 |url-status=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://archive.today/20120717105220/http://www.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123090913 |archivedate=17 July 2012}} ''Air Force News'', 20 March 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; On 4 August 2008, a B-1B flew the first [[Lockheed Martin Sniper XR|Sniper Advanced Targeting Pod]] equipped combat sortie where the crew successfully targeted enemy ground forces and dropped a GBU-38 guided bomb in Afghanistan.&lt;ref name=Sniper_combat&gt;Pate, Capt. Kristen. {{cite web |url=http://www.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123110313 |title=&quot;Sniper ATP-equipped B-1B has combat first.&quot; |accessdate=16 September 2008 |url-status=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://archive.today/20121212203544/http://www.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123110313 |archivedate=12 December 2012}} ''US Air Force'', 11 August 2008. Retrieved: 8 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2011, B-1Bs from [[Ellsworth Air Force Base]] attacked undisclosed targets in [[Libya]] as part of [[Operation Odyssey Dawn]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rapidcityjournal.com/news/article_7477796e-5a81-11e0-b42d-001cc4c002e0.html &quot;Ellsworth Airmen join Operation Odyssey Dawn.&quot;] ''Rapid City Journal,'' 29 March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

With upgrades to keep the B-1 viable, the Air Force may keep it in service until approximately 2038.&lt;ref&gt;Hebert, Adam J. [http://www.airforce-magazine.com/MagazineArchive/Pages/2006/October%202006/10062018.aspx &quot;The 2018 Bomber and Its Friends.&quot;] ''Air Force magazine,'' October 2006. Retrieved: 14 August 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Despite upgrades, the B-1 has repair and cost issues; every flight hour needs 48.4 hours of repair. The fuel, repairs, and other needs for a 12-hour mission cost $720,000 as of 2010.&lt;ref&gt;Shachtman, Noah. [http://www.brookings.edu/opinions/2010/0715_airforce_shachtman.aspx &quot;The Air Force Needs a Serious Upgrade,&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101008022450/http://www.brookings.edu/opinions/2010/0715_airforce_shachtman.aspx |date=8 October 2010}} ''Brookings Institution'', 15 July 2010. Retrieved: 31 August 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The $63,000 cost per flight hour is, however, less than the $72,000 for the B-52 and the $135,000 of the B-2.&lt;ref name=&quot;axe20120326&quot;&gt;Axe, David. [https://www.theatlantic.com/national/archive/2012/03/why-cant-the-air-force-build-an-affordable-plane/254998/ &quot;Why Can't the Air Force Build an Affordable Plane?&quot;] ''The Atlantic,'' 26 March 2012. Retrieved: 30 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2010, senior USAF officials met to consider retiring the entire fleet to meet budget cuts.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reporternews.com/news/2010/jun/28/b-1b-fleet-could-be-retired-early/ &quot;Budget cutting axe may fall on the U.S. bomber force.&quot;] ''Reporter News.'' Retrieved: 25 July 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The Pentagon plans to begin replacing the aircraft with the [[Northrop Grumman B-21 Raider]] after 2025.&lt;ref name=&quot;Replace Reuters&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=New B-21 bomber named 'Raider': U.S. Air Force|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-airforce-northrop-grumman-bomber-idUSKCN11P1TZ|accessdate=23 April 2017|work=Reuters|date=19 September 2016|quote=The stealth B-21, the first new U.S. bomber of the 21st century, is part of an effort to replace the Air Force's aging B-52 and B-1 bombers, though it is not slated to be ready for combat use before 2025.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the meantime, its &quot;capabilities are particularly well-suited to the vast distances and unique challenges of the Pacific region, and we'll continue to invest in, and rely on, the B-1 in support of the focus on the Pacific&quot; as part of President Obama's [[People's Republic of China–United States relations#Obama administration|&quot;Pivot to East Asia&quot;]].&lt;ref&gt;Brook, Tom Vanden. [https://www.usatoday.com/money/industries/manufacturing/story/2012-05-11/b-1-bomber-obama-new-strategy/56097706/1 &quot;B-1 bomber mission shifts from Afghanistan to China, Pacific.&quot;] ''USA Today'', 11 May 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2012, the 9th Expeditionary Bomb Squadron returned from a six-month tour in Afghanistan. Its 9 B-1Bs flew 770 sorties, the most of any B-1B squadron on a single deployment. The squadron spent 9,500 hours airborne, keeping one of its bombers in the air at all times. They accounted for a quarter of all combat aircraft sorties over the country during that time and fulfilled an average of two to three air support requests per day.&lt;ref&gt;[http://strategypage.com/htmw/htairfo/articles/20120815.aspx &quot;The 24/7 Bone Over Afghanistan.&quot;] ''Strategypage.com,'' 15 August 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; On 4 September 2013, a B-1B participated in a maritime evaluation exercise, deploying munitions such as laser-guided 500&amp;nbsp;lb [[GBU-54]] bombs, 500&amp;nbsp;lb and 2,000&amp;nbsp;lb [[Joint Direct Attack Munition]]s (JDAM), and [[Long Range Anti-Ship Missile]]s (LRASM). The aim was to detect and engage several small craft using existing weapons and tactics developed from conventional warfare against ground targets; the B-1 is seen as a useful asset for maritime duties such as patrolling shipping lanes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.navyrecognition.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=1252 U.S. Air Force tests B-1B Lancer bomber for maritime environment &amp; anti-ship missions] – Navyrecognition.com, 19 September 2013&lt;/ref&gt;

The USAF had 66 B-1Bs in service in September 2012, split among four squadrons organized into two Bomb Wings: the 7th Bomb Wing at [[Dyess Air Force Base|Dyess AFB]], Texas, and the 28th Bomb Wing at [[Ellsworth Air Force Base|Ellsworth AFB]], South Dakota.&lt;ref name= B-1B_Upgrade_Contract /&gt;&lt;ref name=AF_Alma_facts-figs_2013&gt;[http://www.airforcemag.com/MagazineArchive/Magazine%20Documents/2013/May%202013/0513facts_figures.pdf &quot;The Air Force in Facts and Figures&amp;nbsp;– 2013 USAF Almanac.&quot;] ''Air Force Magazine'', Journal of the Air Force Association, Vol. 96, Issue 5, May 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

Beginning in 2014, the B-1 was used by the U.S. against the Islamic State (IS) in the [[Syrian Civil War]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://en.ria.ru/military_news/20140923/193187865/United-States-Arab-Allies-Hit-IS-Targets-in-Syria---Reports.html |title=United States, Arab Allies Hit IS Targets in Syria: Reports |date=23 September 2014 |website=ria.ru – Sputnik |accessdate=1 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; From August 2014 to January 2015, the B-1 accounted for eight percent of USAF sorties during [[Operation Inherent Resolve]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.defensenews.com/story/defense/2015/01/19/a10-strikes-isis-11-percent/21875911/ &quot;A-10 Performing 11 Percent of Anti-ISIS Sorties&quot;]. Defensenews.com, 19 January 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; The 9th Bomb Squadron was deployed to Qatar in July 2014 to support missions in Afghanistan, but when the air campaign against IS began on 8 August, the aircraft were employed in Iraq.  During the [[Battle of Kobane]] in Syria, the squadron's B-1s dropped 660 bombs over 5 months in support of Kurdish forces defending the city, one-third of all bombs used during OIR during the period, killing some 1,000 ISIL fighters. The 9th Bomb Squadron's B-1s went &quot;Winchester&quot;, dropping all weapons on board, 31 times during their deployment. They dropped over 2,000 JDAMs during the 6-month rotation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.militarytimes.com/story/military/2015/08/23/inside-b-1-crew-pounded-isis-1800-bombs/31166125/ &quot;Inside the B-1 crew that pounded ISIS with 1,800 bombs&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150826012407/http://www.militarytimes.com/story/military/2015/08/23/inside-b-1-crew-pounded-isis-1800-bombs/31166125/ |date=26 August 2015}}. Militarytimes.com, 23 August 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; B-1s from the 28th Bomb Wing flew 490 sorties where they dropped 3,800 munitions on 3,700 targets during a six-month deployment. In February 2016, the B-1s were sent back to the U.S. for cockpit upgrades.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://edition.cnn.com/2016/02/19/politics/b-1-bombers-isis/index.html?iid=ob_article_footer_expansion&amp;iref=obnetwork |title=B-1 bombers pulled from ISIS fight |publisher=CNN |date=21 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Air Force Global Strike Command===

As part of a USAF organizational realignment announced in April 2015, all B-1B aircraft were reassigned from Air Combat Command to [[Global Strike Command]] (GSC) in October 2015.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.af.mil/News/ArticleDisplay/tabid/223/Article/585547/af-realigns-b-1-lrs-b-under-air-force-global-strike-command.aspx &quot;AF realigns B-1, LRS-B under Air Force Global Strike Command&quot;]. U.S. Air Force, 20 April 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 8 July 2017, the USAF flew two B-1 Lancers near the North Korean border in a show of force amid increasing tensions, particularly in response to North Korea's 4 July test of an ICBM capable of reaching Alaska.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foxnews.com/world/2017/07/08/2-us-air-force-b-1-bombers-fly-near-north-korean-border-in-show-force.html|title=2 US Air Force B-1 bombers fly near North Korean border in show of force|first=Lucas|last=Tomlinson|date=8 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 14 April 2018, B-1B bombers launched 19 [[AGM-158 JASSM]] missiles as part of the [[2018 bombing of Damascus and Homs]] in Syria.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.thedrive.com/the-war-zone/20055/united-states-france-and-uk-begin-air-strikes-on-syria-updating-live|title=United States, France, And UK Begin Air Strikes on Syria (Updating Live)|first=Tyler Rogoway and Joseph|last=Trevithick|website=The Drive}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.cnn.com/2018/04/14/politics/syria-airstrikes-weapons-used-intl/index.html|title=Weapons the US, UK and France used to target Syria|author=Brad Lendon|website=CNN}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.military.com/defensetech/2018/04/17/us-may-ramp-buy-missile-just-made-combat-debut-syria.html|title=US May Ramp Up Buy of the Missile That Just Made Combat Debut in Syria|first=Oriana|last=Pawlyk|date=17 April 2018|website=Military.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Variants==
[[File:B1ArearWingsMus.JPG|thumb|The rear section showing the B-1A's pointed radome |alt=]]

;B-1A: The B-1A was the original B-1 design with variable engine intakes and Mach&amp;nbsp;2.2 top speed. Four prototypes were built; no production units were manufactured.&lt;ref name=AF_Alma_facts-figs_2005/&gt;&lt;ref name=Complete_Encyclopedia&gt;Donald 1997, p. 723.&lt;/ref&gt;
;B-1B: The B-1B is a revised B-1 design with reduced radar signature and a top speed of Mach&amp;nbsp;1.25. It is optimized for low-level penetration. A total of 100 B-1Bs were produced.&lt;ref name=Complete_Encyclopedia/&gt;
;B-1R: The B-1R was a proposed upgrade of existing B-1B aircraft.&lt;ref name=B-1R&gt;Lewis, Paul and Erik Simonsen. [https://web.archive.org/web/20071212053150/http://www.boeing.com/ids/allsystemsgo/issues/vol2/num2/story01.html &quot;Offering Unique Solutions for Global Strike Force.&quot;] ''All Systems Go, (Boeing)'' Vol. 2, Issue 2, 2004. (copy on Archive.org) Retrieved: 8 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The B-1R (R for &quot;regional&quot;) would be fitted with advanced radars, [[air-to-air missile]]s, and new [[Pratt &amp; Whitney F119]] engines. This variant would have a top speed of Mach&amp;nbsp;2.2, but with 20% shorter range.&lt;ref name=Hebert_Long-Range_Strike&gt;Hebert, Adam J. [http://www.airforce-magazine.com/MagazineArchive/Pages/2004/November%202004/1104strike.aspx &quot;Long-Range Strike in a Hurry.&quot;] ''Air Force Magazine'', November 2004. Retrieved: 8 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Existing external hardpoints would be modified to allow multiple conventional weapons to be carried, increasing overall loadout. For air-to-air defense, an [[active electronically scanned array]] (AESA) radar would be added and some existing hardpoints modified to carry air-to-air missiles. If needed the B-1R could escape from unfavorable air-to-air encounters with its Mach&amp;nbsp;2+ speed, as few aircraft are capable of sustained speeds over Mach&amp;nbsp;2.&lt;ref name=B-1R/&gt;

==Operators==
[[File:B-1 Lancer Night.jpg|thumb|A 28th Bomb Wing B-1B on the ramp in the early morning at Ellsworth Air Force Base, South Dakota |alt=Front view of B-1 parked on ramp at night. Nearby yellow flood lights illuminate the area. In the background are buildings]]
[[File:B-1B Lancer On Display.jpg|thumb|A B-1B on public display at Ellsworth AFB, 2003 |alt=]]
[[File:rockwell b-1b lancer af86-103 landing arp.jpg|thumb|USAF B-1B arrives at [[Royal International Air Tattoo]] 2008 |alt=Gray aircraft before landing, flying left, with gears extended. Green grass make up the foreground. Buildings and communication towers are in the background]]
{{see also|List of B-1 units of the United States Air Force}}

The USAF had 62 B-1Bs in service as of August 2017.&lt;ref name=AF_Times_Aug2017&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.airforcetimes.com/news/your-air-force/2017/08/12/less-than-half-of-the-us-bomber-fleet-is-ready-to-fight-tonight/|title=Less than half of the US bomber fleet is ready to 'fight tonight' |first=Tara |last=Copp |date=14 August 2017 |website=Air Force Times |access-date= 30 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{glossary}}
{{term|id=United States|{{USA}}}}
{{defn|
 {{glossary}}
 {{term|[[United States Air Force]]}}
 {{defn|
  {{glossary}}
  {{term|[[Strategic Air Command]] 1985–1992}}
  {{term|[[Air Combat Command]] 1992–2015}}
  {{term|[[Air Force Global Strike Command]] 2015–present}}
  {{defn|{{unordered list
   | [[7th Bomb Wing]] – [[Dyess AFB]], [[Texas]]{{unordered list
    | [[9th Bomb Squadron]] 1993–present
    | [[13th Bomb Squadron]] 2000–2005
    | [[28th Bomb Squadron]] 1994–present
    | [[337th Bomb Squadron]] 1993–1994
   }}
   | [[28th Bomb Wing]] – [[Ellsworth AFB]], [[South Dakota]]{{unordered list
    | [[34th Bomb Squadron]] 1994–1997, 2002–present
    | [[37th Bomb Squadron]] 1986–present
    | 77th Bomb Squadron 1985–95, 1997–2002
   }}
   | [[53d Test and Evaluation Group]] – [[Nellis AFB]], [[Nevada]]{{unordered list
    | [[337th Test and Evaluation Squadron]] (Dyess AFB, Texas) 2004–present
   }}
   | [[57th Wing]] – [[Nellis AFB]], [[Nevada]]{{unordered list
    | [[77th Weapons Squadron]] (Dyess AFB, Texas) 2003–present
   }}
   | [[96th Bomb Wing]] – Dyess AFB, Texas{{unordered list
    | [[337th Bomb Squadron]] 1985–1993
    | [[338th Combat Crew Training Squadron]] 1986–1993
    | [[4018th Combat Crew Training Squadron]] 1985–1986
   }}
   | 319th Bomb Wing – [[Grand Forks AFB]], [[North Dakota]] 1987–1994{{unordered list
    | [[46th Bomb Squadron]]
   }}
   | [[366th Wing]] – [[Mountain Home AFB]], [[Idaho]] 1997–2002{{unordered list
    | 34th Bomb Squadron
   }}
   | [[384th Bomb Wing]] – [[McConnell AFB]], [[Kansas]] 1987–1994{{unordered list
    | 28th Bomb Squadron
   }}
  }}}}
  {{term|[[Air National Guard]]}}{{defn|{{unordered list
   | [[116th Bomb Wing]] – [[Robins AFB]], [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]] 1996–2002{{unordered list
    | 128th Bomb Squadron
   }}
   | 184th Bomb Wing – McConnell AFB, Kansas 1994–2002{{unordered list
    | 127th Bomb Squadron
   }}
  }}}}
  {{term|[[Air Force Flight Test Center]] – [[Edwards AFB]], [[California]]}}{{defn|{{unordered list
   | [[412th Operations Group]] 1989–1992{{unordered list
    | [[410th Flight Test Squadron]]
   }}
   | [[412th Test Wing]] 1992–present{{unordered list
    | [[419th Flight Test Squadron]]
   }}
   | 6510th Test Wing 1974–1989{{unordered list
    | 6519th Flight Test Squadron
   }}
  }}}}
  {{glossary end}}
 }}
 {{glossary end}}
 }}
{{glossary end}}

==Aircraft on display==
[[File:18-37-242-B1.jpg|thumb|B-1B at the [[Museum of Aviation (Warner Robins)|Museum of Aviation]], [[Robins AFB]]]]
[[File:B-1B du NMUSAF.jpg|thumb|B-1B at the National Museum of the USAF, Dayton, OH]]

;B-1A: {{unordered list
 | 74-0160 – [[Wings Over the Rockies Air and Space Museum|Wings Over the Rockies Museum]] at the former [[Lowry Air Force Base]] in [[Denver, Colorado]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://wingsmuseum.org/1970-b1-a-lancer/ &quot;B-1A Lancer/74-160.&quot;] ''Wings Over The Rockies Air &amp; Space Museum''. Retrieved: 11 December 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;
 | 76-0174 – [[Strategic Air Command &amp; Aerospace Museum]] near [[Ashland, Nebraska]]. This aircraft has conventional [[ejection seats]] and other features used on the B-1B variant.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sasmuseum.com/exhibits/aircraft/ &quot;B-1A Lancer/76-174.&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151208221507/http://sasmuseum.com/exhibits/aircraft/ |date=8 December 2015 }} ''Strategic Air Command Museum.'' Retrieved: 11 December 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
;B-1B: {{unordered list
 | 83-0065 ''Star of Abilene'' – Dyess Linear Air Park at [[Dyess Air Force Base]], [[Texas]]. This was the first aircraft delivered to the U.S. Air Force. Dyess AFB is home to one of two active Air Force B-1B wings.&lt;ref&gt;[http://aerialvisuals.ca/LocationDossier.php?Serial=3696 &quot;B-1B Lancer/83-0065.&quot;] aerialvisuals.ca. Retrieved: 11 December 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;
 | 83-0066 ''Ole Puss'' – Heritage Park at [[Mountain Home Air Force Base]], [[Idaho]] with wheels in the wells.&lt;ref&gt;[http://aerialvisuals.ca/LocationDossier.php?Serial=2332 &quot;B-1B Lancer/83-0066.&quot;] aerialvisuals.ca. Retrieved: 11 December 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;
 | 83-0067 ''Texas Raider'' – [[South Dakota Air and Space Museum]] at [[Ellsworth Air Force Base]], [[South Dakota]]. Ellsworth AFB is home to one of two active Air Force B-1B wings.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sdairandspacemuseum.com/ &quot;B-1B Lancer/83-0067.&quot;] ''South Dakota Air and Space Museum''. Retrieved: 11 December 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;
 | 83-0068 ''Spuds'' – Reflections of Freedom Air Park at [[McConnell Air Force Base]] in [[Wichita, Kansas]], a former Air Force and [[Air National Guard]] B-1B base.&lt;ref&gt;[http://aerialvisuals.ca/LocationDossier.php?Serial=2639 &quot;B-1B Lancer/83-0068.&quot;] aerialvisuals.ca. Retrieved: 11 December 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;
 | 83-0069 ''Silent Penetrator'' – [[Museum of Aviation (Warner Robins)|Museum of Aviation]] at [[Robins Air Force Base]] in [[Warner Robins, Georgia]], a former [[Air National Guard]] B-1B base. This aircraft was the sixth B-1 produced, and was delivered to the [[96th Bomb Wing]] at Dyess AFB, Texas on 13 March 1986. This aircraft arrived at Robins AFB in September 2002. Robins AFB was previously home to one of two Air National Guard B-1B wings.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.museumofaviation.org/B1.php &quot;B-1B Lancer/83-0069.&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110602143538/http://www.museumofaviation.org/B1.php |date=2 June 2011}} ''Museum of Aviation''. Retrieved: 31 July 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Renamed ''Midnight Train From Georgia'' by April 2015
 | 83-0070 ''7 Wishes'' – [[Hill Aerospace Museum]] at [[Hill Air Force Base]] in [[Ogden, Utah]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hill.af.mil/library/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=5802 &quot;B-1B Lancer/83-0070.&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110622070753/http://www.hill.af.mil/library/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=5802 |date=22 June 2011}} ''Hill Aerospace Museum''. Retrieved: 31 July 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
 | 83-0071 ''Spit Fire'' – near the main gate at [[Tinker Air Force Base]], [[Oklahoma]]. This aircraft was one of two that suffered an in-flight engine failure in 1990 that led to grounding of the fleet.&lt;ref&gt;[http://aerialvisuals.ca/LocationDossier.php?Serial=3454 &quot;B-1B Lancer/83-0071.&quot;] aerialvisuals.ca. Retrieved: 11 December 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;
 | 84-0051 ''Boss Hawg'' – [[National Museum of the United States Air Force]] at [[Wright-Patterson AFB]] near [[Dayton, Ohio]]. It is displayed in the Museum's Cold War Gallery, and replaces the B-1A (76-0174) formerly on display.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalmuseum.af.mil/Visit/MuseumExhibits/FactSheets/Display/tabid/509/Article/198101/boeing-b-1b-lancer.aspx &quot;B-1B Lancer/84-0051.&quot;] ''National Museum of the United States Air Force''. Retrieved: 11 December 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==Accidents and incidents==
[[File:B1 fire.jpg|thumb|A B-1B with a brake fire after a hard landing at [[Rhein-Main Air Base|Rhein-Main AB]], Germany, June 1994. |alt=Black aircraft trailed by a column of black smoke and fire on the runway as fire trucks close in on the flame from behind]]

From 1984 to 2001, ten B-1s were lost due to accidents with 17 crew members or people on board killed.&lt;ref name=AP&gt;[https://www.usatoday.com/news/sept11/2001/12/12/bomber-down.htm &quot;Bomber Crew Rescued from Sea.&quot;] ''[[USA Today]]'', 12 December 2001. Retrieved: 18 July 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

* In September 1987, B-1B (s/n 84-0052) from the [[96th Bomb Wing]], 338th Combat Crew Training Squadron, [[Dyess Air Force Base|Dyess AFB]] crashed near [[La Junta, Colorado]] while flying on a low-level training route. This was the only B-1B crash to occur with six crew members aboard. The two crew members in [[jump seat]]s, and one of the four crew members in [[ejection seat]]s perished. The root cause of the accident was thought to be a [[bird strike]] on a wing's [[leading edge]] during the low-level flight. The impact was severe enough to sever fuel and hydraulic lines on one side of the aircraft, the other side's engines functioned long enough to allow for ejection. The B-1B fleet was later modified to protect these supply lines.&lt;ref name=Jenkins_p114&gt;{{harvnb|Jenkins|1999|pp=114–116.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In October 1990, while flying a training route in eastern Colorado, B-1B (s/n 86-0128) from the [[384th Bomb Wing]], 28th Bomb Squadron, [[McConnell AFB]], experienced an explosion as the engines reached full power without afterburners. Fire on the aircraft's left was spotted. The No. 1 engine was shut down and its [[fire extinguisher]] was activated. The accident investigation determined that the engine had suffered catastrophic failure, engine blades had cut through the engine mounts and the engine became detached from the aircraft.&lt;ref name=Jenkins_p114/&gt;
* In December 1990, B-1B (s/n 83-0071) from the 96th Bomb Wing, 337th Bomb Squadron, Dyess AFB, Texas, experienced a jolt that caused the No. 3 engine to shut down with its fire extinguisher activating. This event, coupled with the October 1990 engine incident, led to a 50+ day grounding of the B-1Bs not on [[Second strike#Implementation|nuclear alert]] status. The problem was eventually traced back to problems in the first-stage fan, and all B-1Bs were equipped with modified engines.&lt;ref name=Jenkins_p114/&gt;
&lt;!--
      Only notable/significant incidents or accidents here please. Ask on talk page if there are questions. --&gt;

==Specifications (B-1B)==
[[File:B-1 Dimensions from TO 00-105E-9.JPG|right|350px|B-1A orthographic projection |alt=Three sketched diagrams showing the front, top and side views of the B-1. The top view, in particular, shows the maximum sweep angles of the wings]]
[[File:B1 Cockpit.JPG|thumb|B-1B cockpit |alt=A flightdeck, dominated by a mix of new and analogue instruments. On both sides are control yokes. Light enters through the forward windows]]
[[File:B-1 Lancer bomb bay.jpg|thumb|right|B-1B forward bomb bay fitted with a rotary launcher]]
{{external media|topic=Rockwell B-1A Cutaway|width= |align=right |image1=[http://www.flightglobal.com/airspace/media/militaryaviation1946-2006cutaways/images/14182/rockwell-b-1a-cutaway.jpg Rockwell B-1A Cutaway from] [[Flightglobal.com]]}}
{{Aircraft specs
|ref=USAF Fact Sheet,&lt;ref name=AF_sheet/&gt; Jenkins,&lt;ref name=Jenkins_B-1&gt;{{harvnb|Jenkins|1999|nopp=y.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pace,&lt;ref name=BNA_B-1B_specs/&gt; Lee&lt;ref name=&quot;lee p.15&quot;/&gt;
|prime units?=kts
&lt;!--
        General characteristics --&gt;
|crew=4 (Aircraft Commander, [[Aircraft pilot|Pilot]], Offensive Systems Officer, and Defensive Systems Officer)
|length ft=146
|length in=
|length note=
|span ft=137
|span in=
|span note=
|swept ft=79
|swept in=&lt;!-- swing-wings --&gt;
|swept note=
|height ft=34
|height in=
|height note=
|wing area sqft=1950
|wing area note=
|swept area sqft=&lt;!-- swing-wings --&gt;
|swept area note=
|aspect ratio=&lt;!-- sailplanes --&gt;
|airfoil=[[NACA airfoil|NACA69-190-2]]
|empty weight lb=192000
|empty weight note=
|gross weight lb=326000
|gross weight note=
|max takeoff weight lb=477000
|max takeoff weight note=
|fuel capacity=
|more general=
&lt;!--
        Powerplant --&gt;
|eng1 number=4
|eng1 name=[[General Electric F101-GE-102]]
|eng1 type=[[Afterburner|afterburning]] [[turbofan]] engines
|eng1 kn=&lt;!-- jet/rocket engines --&gt;
|eng1 lbf=17390
|eng1 note=
|eng1 kn-ab=&lt;!-- afterburners --&gt;
|eng1 lbf-ab=30780
&lt;!--
        Performance --&gt;
|max speed kts=721
|max speed note= (M1.25) at {{cvt|40000|ft}}
::::{{cvt|608|kn|mph km/h}} (M0.92) at {{cvt|200|-|500|ft}}
|cruise speed kts=
|cruise speed note=
|stall speed kts=
|stall speed note=
|never exceed speed kts=
|never exceed speed note=
|minimum control speed kts=
|minimum control speed note=
|range nmi=5100
|range note=
|combat range nmi=2993
|combat range note=
|ferry range nmi=
|ferry range note=
|endurance=&lt;!-- if range unknown --&gt;
|ceiling ft=60000
|ceiling note=
|g limits=&lt;!-- aerobatic --&gt;
|roll rate=&lt;!-- aerobatic --&gt;
|climb rate ftmin=5678
|climb rate note=
|time to altitude=
|wing loading lb/sqft=167
|wing loading note=
|fuel consumption lb/mi=
|thrust/weight=0.28

|more performance=
&lt;!--
        Armament --&gt;
|hardpoints=6 external hardpoints for {{convert|50000|lb|kg}} of ordnance{{#tag:ref|Use for weapons restricted by [[START I|arms treaties]].&lt;ref name=Sniper_combat/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.acq.osd.mil/tc/treaties/start1/other/letters_bear_b1.htm &quot;ACQWeb&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160203221234/http://www.acq.osd.mil/tc/treaties/start1/other/letters_bear_b1.htm |date=3 February 2016}} START I: Letter on B-1&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}} and 3 internal bomb bays for {{convert|75000|lb|kg}} of ordnance.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.boeing.com/defense/b-1b-bomber/|title=Boeing: B-1B Lancer|website=www.boeing.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|hardpoint capacity={{cvt|125000|lb}} internal and external
|bombs=&lt;br&gt;
** 84× [[Mark 82 bomb|Mk-82]] air inflatable retarder (AIR) general purpose (GP) bombs&lt;ref&gt;As per B-1B Weapons Loading Checklist T.O. 1B-1B-33-2-1CL-8&lt;/ref&gt;
** 81× Mk-82 low drag general purpose (LDGP) bombs&lt;ref&gt;As per B-1B Weapons Loading Checklist T.O. 1B-1B-33-2-1CL-7 (changed from 84 to 81 due to fit issues on 28X CBM with new tailkits)&lt;/ref&gt;
** 84× [[Mark 82 bomb|Mk-62 ''Quickstrike'']] sea mines&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.airforce-magazine.com/MagazineArchive/Magazine%20Documents/Forms/DispForm.aspx?ID=408 &quot;Bad to the B-ONE.&quot;] ''Air Force Magazine'', March 2007, p. 63. Retrieved: 25 July 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
** 24× [[Mark 84 bomb|Mk-84]] general-purpose bombs
** 24× Mk-65 naval mines&lt;ref name=Jenkins_p142/&gt;
** 30× CBU-87/[[CBU-89 Gator|89]]/CBU-97 Cluster Bomb Units (CBU){{#tag:ref|As per B-1B Weapons Loading Checklist T.O. 1B-1B-33-2-1CL-13|group=N}}
** 30× CBU-103/104/105 [[Wind Corrected Munitions Dispenser]] (WCMD) CBUs
** 24× GBU-31 [[Joint Direct Attack Munition|JDAM]] GPS guided bombs (Mk-84 GP or BLU-109 warhead){{#tag:ref|both Mk-84 general purpose and [[BLU-109]] penetrating bombs|group=N}}
** 15× GBU-38 JDAM GPS guided bombs (Mk-82 GP warhead){{#tag:ref|As per B-1B Weapons Loading Checklist T.O. 1B-1B-33-2-1CL-12 Section 3.4 (Only six each in forward and intermediate bays and three each in the aft bay)|group=N}}
** 48× GBU-38 JDAM (using rotary launcher mounted multiple ejector racks)&lt;ref name=&quot;Rivezzo&quot;&gt;Rivezzo, Charles V. [http://www.eglin.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123250570 &quot;337 TES demonstrates ability to triple B-1 payload.&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110916002629/http://www.eglin.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123250570 |date=16 September 2011}} ''7th Bomb Wing Public Affairs, USAF'', 7 April 2011. Retrieved: 29 February 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
** 48× GBU-54 LaserJDAM (using rotary launcher mounted multiple ejector racks)&lt;ref name=&quot;Rivezzo&quot;/&gt;
** 96× or 144× [[GBU-39 Small Diameter Bomb]] GPS guided bombs{{#tag:ref|96 if using four-packs, 144 if using 6-packs. This capability has not yet been fielded on the B-1|group=N}} (not fielded on B-1 yet)
** 24× [[AGM-154 Joint Standoff Weapon]] (JSOW)
** 24x [[AGM-158C LRASM|AGM-158C Long Range Anti-Ship Missile]] (LRASM)&lt;ref name=B1BsNewMissionLRASM&gt;Mizokami, Kyle [https://www.popularmechanics.com/military/weapons/a27855/b-1-bomber-ship-killer/ &quot;The B-1 Bomber Has a New Mission&quot;] ''Popular Mechanics'', 22 August 2017. Retrieved: 10 June 2019.&lt;/ref&gt;
** 24× [[AGM-158 JASSM|AGM-158 Joint Air to Surface Standoff Missile]] (JASSM)
: Previously up to 24× [[B61 nuclear bomb|B61]] or [[B83 nuclear bomb|B83]] nuclear bombs could be carried.&lt;ref name=Jenkins_p142&gt;{{harvnb|Jenkins|1999|p=142.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|missiles=
|avionics=
* 1× [[APG-66|AN/APQ-164]] forward-looking offensive [[Passive electronically scanned array]] [[radar]]
* 1× AN/ALQ-161 [[radar warning receiver]] and defensive [[Radar jamming and deception|jamming]] equipment
* 1× AN/ASQ-184 defensive management system
* 1× [[Sniper Advanced Targeting Pod]] (optional)&lt;ref name=AFmag_Big_Squeeze&gt;Tirpak, John A. [http://www.airforce-magazine.com/MagazineArchive/Pages/2007/October%202007/1007squeeze.aspx &quot;The Big Squeeze.&quot;] ''Air Force Magazine'', Journal of the Air Force Association, Volume 90, Issue 10, October 2007. {{ISSN|0730-6784}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=sniper&gt;Kessler, Capt. Carrie L. [http://www.acc.af.mil/news/story_print.asp?id=123088382 &quot;B-1 crews conduct TWF test; receive pod spin-up.&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090705235137/http://www.acc.af.mil/news/story_print.asp?id=123088382 |date=5 July 2009}} ''Air Force Print News Today'', 29 February 2008. Retrieved: 30 June 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;background:white; text-align:center; float:left;&quot;
|-
! colspan=5 | B-1B Lancer internal weapons loads
|-
! Bomb rack &amp; stores&lt;ref name=WeaponsFile&gt;[https://peonet.eglin.af.mil/weapons &quot;The Weapons File &quot;]{{dead link|date=January 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes}} Air Armament Center&lt;/ref&gt;
! Bay 1
! Bay 2
! Bay 3
! Total
|-
! colspan=5 | Conventional
|-
| '''CBM'''&lt;br&gt;2816 to 3513&amp;nbsp;lb
| 1
| 1
| 1
|-
|
{{col-begin|width=auto}}
{{col-break}}
* '''Mk-82'''
* '''Mk-82 AIR'''
* '''Mk-36'''
* '''Mk-62'''
{{col-end}}
| 28
| 28
| 28
| 84
|-
! colspan=5 | Conventional
|-
| '''SECBM'''&lt;br&gt;(CBM w/ TMD upgrade)&lt;br&gt;2816&amp;nbsp;lb empty
| 1
| 1
| 1
|-
|
{{col-begin|width=auto}}
{{col-break}}
* '''CBU-87'''
* '''CBU-89'''
* '''CBU-97'''
* '''CBU-103'''
* '''CBU-104'''
* '''CBU-105'''
{{col-end}}
| 10
| 10
| 10
| 30
|-
| '''GBU-38'''
| 6
| 6
| 3
| 15
|-
! colspan=5 | Multi-purpose
|-
| '''MPRL'''&lt;br&gt;1300 to 2055&amp;nbsp;lb
| 1
| 1
| 1
|-
|
{{col-begin|width=auto}}
{{col-break}}
* '''Mk-84'''
* '''GBU-31'''
* '''AGM-154'''
* '''AGM-158'''
{{col-end}}
| 8
| 8
| 8
| 24
|-
| '''Mk-65 naval mines '''
| 4
| 4
| 4
| 12
|-
|
{{col-begin|width=auto}}
{{col-break}}
* '''4-pack GBU-39'''
* '''6-pack GBU-39'''
{{col-end}}
| 8
| 8
| 8
| 96 or 144
|-
! colspan=5 | Multi-purpose (mixed)
|-
| '''MPRL'''&lt;br&gt;(MER upgrade)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.af.mil/News/ArticleDisplay/tabid/223/Article/113656/b-1b-lancer-upgrade-will-triple-payload.aspx &quot;B-1B Lancer upgrade will triple payload&quot;] US Air Force News, 11 April 2011&lt;/ref&gt;
| 1
| 1
| 1
|-
|
{{col-begin|width=auto}}
{{col-break}}
* '''GBU-38''', '''GBU-32''', '''GBU-31'''
{{col-end}}
| 4
| 4
| 4
| 36
|-
| '''GBU-38'''
| 16
| 16
| 16
| 48
|-
! colspan=5 | Ferry/range extension
|-
| '''Fuel tank'''&lt;br&gt;2975 gal&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Uncovering the Rockwell B-1B Lancer&quot; Willy Peeters, Daco Publications, {{ISBN|978-9080674776}}, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
| 1
| 1
| 1
| 3&lt;br&gt;9157 gal&lt;ref name=TO00105&gt;Technical Order 00-105E-9 Revision 11, 1 February 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! colspan=5 | Nuclear (uniform; out of use)
|-
|
{{col-begin|width=auto}}
{{col-break}}
* '''MPRL'''&lt;br&gt;1300 to 2055&amp;nbsp;lb
{{col-end}}
| 1
| 1
| 1
|-
| '''B28'''&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Encyclopedia of Modern U.S. Military Weapons&quot;, Berkley Hardcover; 1st edition, 1 August 1995, {{ISBN|978-0425147818}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| 4
| 4
| 4
| 12
|-
|
{{col-begin|width=auto}}
{{col-break}}
* '''AGM-69'''
* '''B61'''
* '''B83'''
{{col-end}}
| 8
| 8
| 8
| 24
|-
! colspan=5 | Nuclear (mixed)(out of use)&lt;ref name=CBO198808&gt;[http://www.cbo.gov/sites/default/files/cbofiles/ftpdocs/62xx/doc6257/doc07b-entire.pdf &quot;The B-1B Bomber and Options for hancements&quot;] Congressional Budget Office, August 1988&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|
{{col-begin|width=auto}}
{{col-break}}
* '''CSRL'''
{{col-end}}
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;|1
|
|
|-
| '''AGM-86B'''
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;|Small fuel tank&lt;br&gt;8
|
| 8
|}
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;background:white; text-align:center; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! colspan=5 | External weapons loads (mostly unused due to [[radar cross-section|RCS]])
|-
! Bomb rack &amp; stores&lt;ref name=WeaponsFile/&gt;
! Fwd stations 1–2
! Int. stations 3–6
! Aft stations 7–8
! Total
|-
! colspan=5 | Nuclear (out of use)
|-
| '''Dual-pylon'''
| 2
| 2
| 2
|-
| '''Single-pylon'''
|
| 2
|
|-
|
{{col-begin|width=auto}}
{{col-break}}
* '''AGM-86B'''
* '''B-61'''
{{col-end}}
| 2×2
| 2×2 + 2
| 2×2
| 14{{#tag:ref|Restricted to 12 under [[Strategic Arms Limitation Talks|SALT II]].&lt;ref name=CBO198808/&gt;|group=N}}
|-
! colspan=5 | Conventional (uniform)
|-
| '''Mk-82'''
| 2×6
| 2×6 + 2×6
| 2×6
| 44
|-
! colspan=5 | Targeting&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.af.mil/News/ArticleDisplay/tabid/223/Article/122748/sniper-atp-equipped-b-1b-has-combat-first.aspx &quot;Sniper ATP-equipped B-1B has combat first&quot;] US Air Force News, 11 August 2008&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| '''Pylon'''&lt;br&gt;884&amp;nbsp;lb
| 1 (right station)
|
|
|
|-
| '''Sniper XR targeting pod'''
| 1 (right station)
|
|
| 1&lt;br&gt;440&amp;nbsp;lb
|-
! colspan=5 | Ferry/range extension&lt;ref name=TO00105/&gt;&lt;ref name=NAfactbook&gt;[https://fas.org/nuke/guide/usa/bomber/b1b-factbook.pdf &quot;NA 95-1210 B-1B Fact Book&quot;]. North American Aircraft, Rockwell International, 20 July 1995. Retrieved: 28 December 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| '''Fuel tank'''&lt;br&gt;923 gal
| 2
| 2
| 2
| 6&lt;br&gt;5538 gal
|}
{{clear}}

==Notable appearances in media==
&lt;!-- ===============({{NoMoreCruft}})===============--&gt;
&lt;!-- Please READ [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] and [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history#Popular culture]] before adding any &quot;Popular culture&quot; items.

Please do not add the many minor appearances of the aircraft. This section is only for major cultural appearances where the aircraft plays a MAJOR part in the story line, or has an &quot;especially notable&quot; role in what is listed. A verifiable source proving the appearance's notability may be required. Random cruft, including ALL Ace Combat, Battlefield, and Metal Gear Solid appearances, and ALL anime/fiction lookalike speculation, WILL BE removed.

If your item has been removed, please discuss it on the talk page FIRST. A verifiable source proving the appearance's notability may be required. If a consensus is reached to include your item, a regular editor of this page will add it back. Thank you for your cooperation.--&gt;
&lt;!-- ===============({{NoMoreCruft}})=============== --&gt;
{{main|Aircraft in fiction#B-1 Lancer}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Aviation}}
{{aircontent
|see also= &lt;!-- other related articles that have not already linked: --&gt;
* [[Political positions of Ronald Reagan]]
* [[ASALM]], Advanced Strategic Air-Launched Missile
|related= &lt;!-- From which older designs was this aircraft developed, and what aircraft did it lead to? --&gt;
|similar aircraft= &lt;!-- aircraft with similar Role, Era, and Capability --&gt;
* [[Tupolev Tu-22M]]
* [[Tupolev Tu-160]]
* [[General Dynamics F-111 Aardvark#FB-111A / F-111G|General Dynamics FB-111]]
|lists= &lt;!-- lists of similar aircraft (aircraft from the same nation, with the same mission profile, etc.) --&gt;
* [[List of active United States military aircraft]]
* [[List of bomber aircraft]]
&lt;!-- See [[WP:Air/PC]] for more explanation of these fields. --&gt;
}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group=N}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite book |last=Casil |first=Amy Sterling |title=The B-1 Lancer |location=New York |publisher=Rosen |year=2003 |isbn=0-8239-3871-9 |ref=harv}}
* Dao, James. [https://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/01/us/much-maligned-b-1-bomber-proves-hard-to-kill.html?src=pm &quot;Much-Maligned B-1 Bomber Proves Hard to Kill.&quot;] ''The New York Times'', 1 August 2001.
* Donald, David, ed. &quot;Rockwell B-1B&quot;. ''The Complete Encyclopedia of World Aircraft''. New York: Barnes &amp; Noble, 1997. {{ISBN|0-7607-0592-5}}.
* {{cite book |last= Donald |first= David |author-mask= 3 |title= The Pocket Guide to Military Aircraft: And the World's Airforces |place= London |publisher= Octopus |year= 2004 |ISBN= 0-681-03185-9}}.
* {{Cite book |last= Dorr |first= Robert F |title=7th Bombardment Group/Wing, 1918–1995 |location= Turner, [[Maine|ME]] |publisher=Turner |year= 1997 |isbn= 1-56311-278-7 |ref= harv}}
* {{cite book |last= Dorr |first= Robert F |author-mask= 3 |newspaper= Combat Aircraft Monthly |title= Lancer Force |place= London |publisher= Ian Allan |date=June 2010}}.
* {{Citation |last= Gunston |first= William 'Bill' |title= F-111 |place= New York |publisher= Charles Scribner's Sons |year= 1978 |ISBN= 0-684-15753-5}}.
* {{cite book |last=Jenkins |first=Dennis R |title= B-1 Lancer: The Most Complicated Warplane Ever Developed |location =New York |publisher= McGraw-Hill |year= 1999 |isbn= 0-07-134694-5 |ref= harv}}
* {{Cite book |last= Knaack |first= Marcelle Size |title= Post-World War II Bombers, 1945–1973 |location= Washington, DC |format= PDF |publisher= Office of Air Force History |year= 1988 |url= http://www.airforcehistory.hq.af.mil/Publications/fulltext/encyclopedia_postww2_bombers.pdf |isbn= 0-16-002260-6 |ref= harv |url-status= dead |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20071025174047/http://www.airforcehistory.hq.af.mil/Publications/fulltext/encyclopedia_postww2_bombers.pdf |archivedate= 25 October 2007 |df= dmy-all}}
* {{Cite book |last=Lee |first=Tae-Woo |title= Military Technologies of the World |volume= 1 |location= Santa Barbara, [[California|CA]] |publisher=ABC-CLIO |year= 2008 |isbn=0-275-99535-6 |ref= harv}}
&lt;!-- * {{Cite book |last=Logan |first=Don |title= Rockwell B-1B: SAC's Last Bomber |location=Atglen, PA |publisher= Schiffer |year= 1995 |isbn= 0-88740-666-1 |ref= harv}} --&gt;
* {{Cite book |last= Pace |first= Steve |title= Boeing North American B-1 Lancer |location= North Branch, [[Minnesota|MN]] |publisher=Specialty Press |year= 1998 |isbn=1-58007-012-4 |ref= harv}}
* {{Cite book |last= Pace |first= Steve |author-mask= 3 |title= B-2 Spirit: The Most Capable War Machine on the Planet |location= New York |publisher=McGraw-Hill |year= 1999 |isbn=0-07-134433-0 |ref= harv}}
* {{Cite book |last=Schwartz |first=Stephen I |title= Atomic Audit: The Costs and Consequences of U.S. Nuclear Weapons since 1940 |location=Washington, DC |publisher= Brookings Institution Press |year= 1998 |isbn= 0-8157-7773-6 |ref= harv}}
* {{Cite book |last= Skaarup |first= Harold A |title= South Dakota Warbird Survivors 2003: A Handbook on Where to Find Them |location= Bloomington, [[Indiana|IN]] |publisher= iUniverse |year= 2002 |isbn= 0-595-26379-8 |ref= harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Sorrels |first=Charles A. |title=U.S. Cruise Missile Programs: Development, Deployment, and Implications for Arms Control |location=New York |publisher=McGraw-Hill |year=1983 |isbn=0-08-030527-X |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last= Spick |first= Michael 'Mike' |series= Modern Fighting Aircraft |title= B-1B |place= New York |publisher= Prentice Hall |year= 1986 |ISBN= 0-13-055237-2}}.
* {{Cite book |editor-last= Spick |editor-first= Mike |author-mask= 3 |title= The Great Book of Modern Warplanes |location= New York |publisher=Salamander Books |year= 1987 |isbn=0-517-63367-1 |ref= harv}}
* {{Cite book |last= Whitford |first= Ray |title= Design for Air Combat |location= London |publisher= Jane's Information Group |year= 1987 |isbn=0-7106-0426-2|ref= harv}}
* {{Cite book |editor-last= Winchester |editor-first= Jim |title= Military Aircraft of the Cold War – Rockwell B-1A |series= The Aviation Factfile |location= London |publisher= Grange Books |year= 2006 |isbn= 1-84013-929-3 |ref= harv}}
* {{Cite book |last= Withington |first= Thomas |title= B-1B Lancer Units in Combat |series= Combat Aircraft |volume= 60 |location= London |publisher= Osprey Publishing |year= 2006 |isbn= 1-84176-992-4|ref= harv}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons and category|B-1 Lancer}}
* [http://www.af.mil/AboutUs/FactSheets/Display/tabid/224/Article/104500/b-1b-lancer.aspx B-1B Fact Sheet on af.mil]
* [http://www.boeing.com/defense/b-1b-bomber/ B-1B product page] and [http://www.boeing.com/history/products/b-1b-lancer.page B-1B history page on Boeing.com]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090730165808/http://oea.larc.nasa.gov/PAIS/Partners/B_1B.html B-1 history page on NASA/Langley Research Center site]
* [http://globalsecurity.org/wmd/systems/b-1.htm B-1 page on GlobalSecurity.org, Detailed History, Development and Data]
* [https://airman.dodlive.mil/2018/05/17/b1-b-lancer/ B-1B Lancer in Airman Magazine's Airframe Profiles]
* {{webarchive |date=12 December 2012 |url=https://archive.today/20121212034421/http://www.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123038283 |title=B-1B Lancer USAF 20-year history article}}

{{North American Aviation aircraft}}
{{Boeing combat aircraft}}
{{US bomber aircraft}}

[[Category:Aircraft first flown in 1974]]
[[Category:Cruciform tail aircraft]]
[[Category:Quadjets]]
[[Category:Rockwell aircraft|B-001]]
[[Category:1970s United States bomber aircraft]]
[[Category:Variable-sweep-wing aircraft]]
[[Category:Supersonic aircraft]]</text>
      <sha1>dv64r23r39ubbh29crq50bvsy1dmor1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
