  <page>
    <title>Epistle to the Ephesians</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9869</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942919830</id>
      <parentid>942919109</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T18:19:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Doug Weller</username>
        <id>1304678</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted to revision 942867237 by [[Special:Contributions/Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]): Don't revert until you get consensus on the talk page ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2013}}{{Paul}}{{Books of the New Testament}}
The '''Epistle to the Ephesians''', also called the '''Letter to the Ephesians''' and often shortened to '''Ephesians''', is the tenth book of the [[New Testament]]. Its authorship has traditionally been attributed to [[Paul the Apostle]] but starting in 1792, this has been challenged  as [[Authorship of the Pauline epistles|Deutero-Pauline]], that is, [[Pseudepigrapha|written in Paul's name]] by a later author strongly influenced by Paul's thought, probably &quot;by a loyal disciple to sum up Paul’s teaching and to apply it to a new situation fifteen to twenty-five years after the Apostle’s death&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ephesians&quot;&gt;Authenticity of [http://www.bible-apologetics.com/history/ephesians.htm Ephesians]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hoehner 2002&quot;&gt;[[Harold Hoehner|Hoehner, Harold]]. ''Ephesians: An Exegetical Commentary.'' Baker Academic, 2002. {{ISBN|978-0-8010-2614-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ehrman 2004 381–384&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|last=Ehrman |first=Bart D.|authorlink=Bart D. Ehrman |title=The New Testament: A Historical Introduction to the Early Christian Writings |year=2004 |publisher=Oxford |location=New York |isbn=0-19-515462-2 |pages=381–84}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nccbuscc.org&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=USCCB – NAB – Ephesians – Introduction |accessdate=2009-01-17 |url=http://www.nccbuscc.org/nab/bible/ephesians/intro.htm |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090104184919/http://www.nccbuscc.org/nab/bible/ephesians/intro.htm |archivedate=4 January 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=barth/&gt;&lt;ref name=PerrinDuling1982&gt;{{Cite book|last1=Perrin |first1=Norman|authorlink=Norman Perrin |last2=Duling|first2=Dennis C.|title=The New Testament: An Introduction. Second Edition. |year=1982 |publisher=Harcourt Brace Jovanovich |location=New York |isbn=0-15-565726-7 |pages=218–22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Brown1984&gt;Brown, Raymond E. ''The churches the apostles left behind'', Paulist Press, 1984. {{ISBN|978-0809126118}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;sup&gt;{{rp|p.47}}&lt;/sup&gt;

==Themes==
According to New Testament scholar [[Daniel B. Wallace|Daniel Wallace]], the theme may be stated pragmatically as &quot;Christians, get along with each other! Maintain the unity practically which Christ has effected positionally by his death.&quot;&lt;ref name=Wallace&gt;Wallace, Daniel B. &quot;Ephesians:Introduction, Argument, and Outline.&quot; Web: [http://bible.org/seriespage/ephesians-introduction-argument-and-outline] 1 January 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

Another major theme in Ephesians is the keeping of Christ's body (that is, the Church) pure and holy. 
{{quote|Therefore be imitators of God, as beloved children. And walk in love, as Christ loved us and gave himself up for us, a fragrant offering and sacrifice to God.|{{bibleref2|Ephesians|5:1–2}}}}

In the second part of the letter, Ephesians 4:17–6:20, the author gives practical advice in how to live a holy, pure, and Christ-inspired lifestyle.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Ephesians+4&amp;version=NIV|title=Bible Gateway passage: Ephesians 4 - New International Version|website=Bible Gateway|access-date=2020-01-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Composition==
According to tradition, the Apostle Paul wrote the letter while he was in prison in Rome (around AD 62). This would be about the same time as the [[Epistle to the Colossians]] (which in many points it resembles) and the [[Epistle to Philemon]]. However, many critical scholars have questioned the authorship of the letter and suggest that it may have been written between AD 80 and 100.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ehrman 2004 381–384&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nccbuscc.org&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=barth/&gt;

===Authorship===
{{Main article|Authorship of the Pauline Epistles}}
The first verse in the letter identifies Paul as its author. While early lists of New Testament books, including [[Marcion|Marcion's]] canon and the [[Muratorian fragment]], attribute the letter to Paul,&lt;ref name=&quot;Bruce142&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Bruce |first=F. F. |author-link=F. F. Bruce |title=The Canon of Scripture |date=1988 |publisher=InterVarsity Press |place=Downers Grove, IL |isbn=978-0830812585 |pages=142, 158–60}}&lt;/ref&gt; more recently there have been challenges to Pauline authorship on the basis of the letter's characteristically non-Pauline syntax, terminology, and [[eschatology]].&lt;ref name=&quot;HarperCollinsSB&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The HarperCollins Study Bible |edition=Revised |date=2006 |publisher=HarperCollins |place=New York |isbn=978-0061228407 |editor-last1=Attridge |editor-first1=Harold W. |editor-last2=Meeks |editor-first2=Wayne A. |pages=1982–83}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Biblical scholar [[Harold Hoehner]], surveying 279 commentaries written between 1519 and 2001, found that 54% favored Pauline authorship, 39% concluded against Pauline authorship and 7% remained uncertain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hoehner 2002&quot; /&gt; [[Norman Perrin]] and  Dennis C. Duling found that of six authoritative scholarly references, &quot;four of the six decide for pseudonymity, and the other two ([[Peake's Commentary on the Bible]] and the [[Jerome Biblical Commentary]]) recognize the difficulties in maintaining Pauline authorship. Indeed, the difficulties are insurmountable.&quot;&lt;ref name=PerrinDuling1982/&gt; Bible scholar [[Raymond E. Brown]] asserts that about 80% of critical scholarship judges that Paul did not write Ephesians.&lt;ref name=Brown1984/&gt;{{rp|p.47}}

There are four main theories in biblical scholarship that address the question of Pauline authorship.&lt;ref&gt;These four views all come from Markus Barth, Ephesians: Introduction, Translation, and Commentary on Chapters 1–3 (New York: Doubleday and Company Inc., 1974), 38&lt;/ref&gt;
* The traditional view that the epistle is written by Paul is supported by scholars that include [[Ezra Abbot]], Ragnar Asting, [[Markus Barth]], [[F. F. Bruce]], A. Robert, and André Feuillet, Gaugler, Grant, [[Adolf von Harnack|Harnack]], [[Erich Haupt|Haupt]], [[Fenton John Anthony Hort]], [[Albertus|Klijn]], [[Johann David Michaelis]], A. Van Roon, [[James A. Sanders|Sanders]], Schille, [[Klyne Snodgrass]], [[John R. W. Stott]], Frank Thielman, [[Daniel B. Wallace]], [[Brooke Foss Westcott]], and [[Theodor Zahn]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ephesians&quot;/&gt; For a defense of the Pauline authorship of  Ephesians, see ''Ephesians: An Exegetical Commentary'' by [[Harold Hoehner]], pp 2–61.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hoehner 2002&quot;/&gt;
* A second position suggests that Ephesians was dictated by Paul with interpolations from another author. Some of the scholars that espouse this view include Albertz, Benoit, Cerfaux, Goguel, Harrison, [[H. J. Holtzmann]], [[Jerome Murphy-O'Connor|Murphy-O'Connor]], and Wagenfuhrer.
* Currently, many [[biblical criticism|critical scholars]] think it improbable that Paul authored Ephesians. Among this group are Allan, Beare, Brandon, Bultmann, Conzelmann, [[Martin Dibelius|Dibelius]], Goodspeed, Kilsemann, J. Knox, W.L. Knox, Kümmel, K and S Lake, Marxsen, Masson, Mitton, Moffatt, [[Dennis Nineham|Nineham]], Pokorny, Schweizer, and J. Weiss.
* Still other scholars suggest there is a lack of conclusive evidence. Some of this group are Cadbury, Julicher, McNeile, and Williams.

===Place, date, and purpose of the writing of the letter===
While most English translations indicate that the letter was addressed to &quot;the saints who are in [[Ephesus]]&quot; (1:1), the words &quot;in Ephesus&quot; do not appear in the best and earliest manuscripts of the letter, leading most [[Textual criticism|textual critics]], like [[Bart Ehrman]], to regard the words as an [[Interpolation (manuscripts)|interpolation]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ehrman 2004 381–384&quot;/&gt; This lack of any internal references to [[Ephesus]] in the early manuscripts may have led [[Marcion]], a second-century [[heresiarch]] [[Development of the New Testament canon#Marcion of Sinope|who created the first New Testament canon]], to believe that the letter was actually addressed to the church at [[Laodicea on the Lycus|Laodicea]], for details see [[Epistle to the Laodiceans]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bruce142&quot;/&gt; .

Furthermore, if Paul is regarded as the author, the impersonal character of the letter, which lacks personal greetings or any indication that the author has personal knowledge of his recipients, is incongruous with the account in Acts of Paul staying more than two years in Ephesus.&lt;ref name=&quot;OBrien5&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=O'Brien |first=Peter T. |author-link=Peter O'Brien (theologian) |date=1999 |title=The Letter to the Ephesians |publisher=Eerdmans |place=Grand Rapids, Michigan |series=The Pillar New Testament Commentary |isbn=978-0802837363 |editor-last=Carson |editor-first=D. A. |editor-link=D. A. Carson |page=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; For these reasons, most regard Ephesians to be a circular letter intended for many churches.&lt;ref name=&quot;HarperCollinsSB&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;OBrien5&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Snodgrass |first=Klyne |author-link=Klyne Snodgrass |title=The NIV Application Commentary: Ephesians |date=1996 |publisher=Zondervan |isbn=978-0310493402 |page=21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Jerusalem Bible]] notes that some critics think the words &quot;who are ...&quot; would have been followed by a blank to be filled in with the name of &quot;whichever church was being sent the letter&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Jerusalem Bible (1966), Footnote a at Ephesians 1:1&lt;/ref&gt;

If Paul was the author of the letter, then it was probably written from Rome during Paul's first imprisonment ({{Bibleref2-nb|Eph|3:1}}; {{Bibleref2-nb|Eph|4:1}}; {{Bibleref2-nb|Eph.|6:20}}), and probably soon after his arrival there in the year 62, four years after he had parted with the Ephesian elders at Miletus. However, scholars who dispute Paul's authorship date the letter to between 70–80 AD.&lt;ref name=&quot;barth&quot; /&gt; In the latter case, the possible location of the authorship could have been within the church of Ephesus itself. [[Ignatius of Antioch]] himself seemed to be very well versed in the epistle to the Ephesians, and mirrors many of his own thoughts in his own epistle to the Ephesians.&lt;ref name=&quot;barth&quot;&gt;See Markus Barth, Ephesians: Introduction, Translation, and Commentary on Chapters 1–3 (New York: Doubleday and Company Inc., 1974), 50–51&lt;/ref&gt;

==Outline==
Ephesians contains:
* '''[[Ephesians 1#Greeting (1:1–2)|1:1,2]].''' The greeting, from Paul to the church of Ephesus.
* '''[[Ephesians 1:3|1:3]]–[[Ephesians 2:10|2:10]].''' A general account of the blessings that the [[gospel]] reveals. This includes the source of these blessings, the means by which they are attained, the reason why they are given, and their final result. The whole of the section {{Bibleref2-nb|Eph|1:3–23}} consists in the original Greek of just two lengthy and complex sentences ({{Bibleref2-nb|Eph|1:3–14, 15–23}}). It ends with a fervent [[prayer]] for the further spiritual enrichment of the Ephesians.
* '''{{Bibleverse-nb|Eph.|2:11–3:21|KJV}}.''' A description of the change in the spiritual position of [[Gentile]]s as a result of the work of Christ. It ends with an account of how Paul was selected and qualified to be an [[Twelve Apostles#Other apostles|apostle]] to the Gentiles, in the hope that this will keep them from being dispirited and lead him to pray for them.
* '''{{Bibleverse-nb|Eph.|4:1–16|KJV}}.''' A chapter on unity in the midst of the diversity of gifts among believers.
* '''{{Bibleverse-nb|Eph.|4:17–6:9|KJV}}.''' [[Household code|Instructions about ordinary life and different relationships]].
* '''{{Bibleverse-nb|Eph.|6:10–24|KJV}}.''' The imagery of [[spiritual warfare]] (including the metaphor of the [[Armor of God]]), the mission of [[Tychicus]], and valedictory blessings.

==Founding of the church at Ephesus==
{{see also|Early centers of Christianity#Asia Minor}}
Paul's first and hurried visit for the space of three months to [[Ephesus]] is recorded in {{Bibleref2|Acts|18:19–21}}. The work he began on this occasion was carried forward by [[Apollos]]{{Bibleref2c-nb|Ac.|18:24–26}} and [[Aquila (bible)|Aquila]] and [[Priscilla (Christian)|Priscilla]]. On his second visit early in the following year, he remained at Ephesus &quot;three years&quot;, for he found it was the key to the western provinces of [[Anatolia|Asia Minor]]. Here &quot;a great door and effectual&quot; was opened to him,{{Bibleref2c|1Cor|16:9||1 Cor 16:9}} and the church was established and strengthened by his diligent labours there.{{Bibleref2c|Acts|20:20,31}} From Ephesus the gospel spread abroad &quot;almost throughout all Asia.&quot;{{Bibleref2c-nb|Acts|19:26}} The word &quot;mightily grew and prevailed&quot; despite all the opposition and persecution he encountered.

On his last journey to [[Jerusalem]], the apostle landed at [[Miletus]] and, summoning together the elders of the church from Ephesus, delivered to them a farewell charge,{{Bibleref2c-nb|Acts|20:18–35}} expecting to see them no more.

The following parallels between this epistle and the Milesian charge may be traced:

# {{Bibleref2|Acts|20:19}} = {{Bibleref2|Eph.|4:2}}. The phrase &quot;lowliness of mind&quot;.
# {{Bibleref2|Acts|20:27}} = {{Bibleref2|Eph.|1:11}}. The word &quot;counsel&quot;, denoting the divine plan.
# {{Bibleref2|Acts|20:32}} = {{Bibleref2|Eph.|3:20}}. The divine ability.
# {{Bibleref2|Acts|20:32}} = {{Bibleref2|Eph.|2:20}}. The building upon the foundation.
# {{Bibleref2|Acts|20:32}} = {{Bibleref2|Eph.|1:14,18}} &quot;The inheritance of the saints.&quot;

==Purpose==
The purpose of the epistle, and to whom it was written, are matters of much speculation.&lt;ref name=Bruce&gt;Bruce, F.F. ''The New International Commentary on the New Testament''. Eerdmans, 1984, 1991. {{ISBN|0-8028-2401-3}}.&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|229}} It was regarded by [[C.H. Dodd]] as the &quot;crown of Paulinism.&quot;&lt;ref name=Bruce/&gt;{{rp|229}} In general, it is born out of its particular socio-historical context and the situational context of both the author and the audience. Originating in the circumstance of a [[multicultural]] church (primarily [[Jewish]] and [[Hellenistic]]), the author addressed issues appropriate to the diverse religious and cultural backgrounds present in the community.{{Citation needed|reason=Your explanation here|date=October 2016}}
[[File:Ein Herr Ein Glaube Eine Taufe.jpg|thumb|220px|right|German inscription of the text, &quot;One Lord, One faith, One baptism,&quot; (Ephesians 4:5).]]

The author exhorts the church repeatedly to embrace a specific view of salvation, which he then explicates.

Frank Charles Thompson,&lt;ref&gt;Thompson, Frank C. ''Thompson Chain Reference Study Bible (NIV).'' Kirkbride Bible Company, 2000. {{ISBN|978-0-88707-009-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;  argues that the main theme of Ephesians is in response to the newly converted Jews who often separated themselves from their Gentile brethren. The unity of the church, especially between Jew and Gentile believers, is the keynote of the book.

==Interpretations==
Ephesians is notable for its domestic code treatment in {{bibleref2-nb|Ephesians|5:22–6:9}}, covering husband-wife, parent-child, and master-slave relationships. In {{bibleref2-nb|Ephesians|5:22}}, wives are urged to submit to their husbands, and husbands to love their wives &quot;as Christ loved the Church.&quot; [[Christian egalitarianism|Christian Egalitarian theologians]], such as [[Katharine Bushnell]] and Jessie Penn-Lewis, interpret these commands in the context of the preceding verse, {{bibleref2-nb|Ephesians|5:21}} for all Christians to &quot;submit to one another.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Bushnell |first=Katharine |title=Dr. Katharine C. Bushnell: A Brief Sketch of Her Life Work |date=December 1930 |journal=Biblical Recorder |page=13 |accessdate=July 5, 2016 |url=http://godswordtowomen.org/bushnell_brief_sketch.pdf |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160625051650/http://godswordtowomen.org/bushnell_brief_sketch.pdf |archivedate=25 June 2016 |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Haddad |first=Mimi |date=Spring 2008 |title=Jessie Penn-Lewis's Cross Theology: Gender Relations in the New Covenant |journal=Priscilla Papers |publisher=Christians for Biblical Equality |volume=22 |issue=2 |page=7 |accessdate=July 5, 2016 |url=http://www.cbeinternational.org/sites/default/files/pp222_jplct_0.pdf |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160705130500/http://www.cbeinternational.org/sites/default/files/pp222_jplct_0.pdf |archivedate=5 July 2016 |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, it is two-way, mutual submission of both husbands to wives and wives to husbands. But according to [[Peter O'Brien (theologian)|Peter O'Brien]], Professor Emeritus at [[Moore Theological College]], this would be the only instance of this meaning of submission in the whole New Testament, indeed in any extant comparable Greek texts; by O'Brien's account, the word simply does not connote mutuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=O'Brien |first=Peter T. |author-link=Peter O'Brien (theologian) |date=1999 |title=The Letter to the Ephesians |publisher=Eerdmans |place=Grand Rapids, Michigan |series=The Pillar New Testament Commentary |isbn=978-0802837363 |editor-last=Carson |editor-first=D. A. |editor-link=D. A. Carson |pages=401–04}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Dallas Theological Seminary]] professor Daniel Wallace understands it to be an extension of {{bibleref2-nb|Ephesians|5:15–21}} on being filled by the Holy Spirit.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wallace&quot; /&gt;

In the period leading up to the [[American Civil War]] (1861–65), {{Bibleref2|Ephesians|6:5}} on master-slave relationships was one of the Bible verses used by [[Confederate States of America|Confederate]] slaveholders in support of a slaveholding position.&lt;ref&gt;E.N. Elliott, ed. ''Cotton is king, and pro-slavery arguments comprising the writings of Hammond, Harper, Christy, Stringfellow, Hodge, Bledsoe, and Cartwright, on this important subject''. Augusta, Ga. : Pritchard, Abbott &amp; Loomis, 1860. {{Cite book| title = Cotton is King – Google Books| accessdate = 2009-03-13| url = https://books.google.com/books?id=ml8zC335PhEC| author1 = Christy| first1 = David| last2 = Bledsoe| first2 = Albert Taylor| last3 = Stringfellow| first3 = Thornton| last4 = Harper| first4 = Robert Goodloe| last5 = Hammond| first5 = James Henry| last6 = Cartwright| first6 = Samuel Adolphus| last7 = Hodge| first7 = Charles| year = 1860}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Earlier Epistle to the Ephesians]]
* [[Textual variants in the New Testament#Epistle to the Ephesians|Textual variants in the Epistle to the Ephesians]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
* {{EBD|wstitle=Ephesians, Epistle to the}}

==External links==
{{wikisource|Ephesians (Bible)|Ephesians}}
{{wikiquote}}
* [http://www.vts.edu/ftpimages/95/download/download_group10628_id432549.pdf A Brief Introduction to Ephesians]
* [http://www.tyndale.ca/seminary/mtsmodular/reading-rooms/newt/ephesians Ephesians Online Reading Room] – extensive collection of online resources for Ephesians; Tyndale Seminary
* [http://www.sermonsfortoday.org/browse_sermons/sermonsInSeries.php?series=Series%20on%20Ephesians Biblical Expository on Ephesians]
* [http://www.raystedman.org/new-testament/ephesians Ephesians: The Calling of the Saints] – Ephesians Messages, Audio &amp; Podcast by Ray Stedman
* {{librivox book | title=Ephesians}} Various versions
* {{Cite AmCyc |last=Schem |first=A. J. |authorlink=A. J. Schem |wstitle=Ephesians, Epistle to the |short=x}}

{{S-start}}
{{S-hou|[[Pauline epistles|Pauline]] Prison [[Epistles|Epistle]]|||}}
{{S-bef|before=[[Epistle to the Galatians|Galatians]]}}
{{S-ttl|title=&lt;small&gt;[[New Testament]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Books of the Bible]]}}
{{S-aft|after=[[Epistle to the Philippians|Philippians]]}}
{{s-end}}
{{Epistle to the Ephesians}}
{{Books of the Bible}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Epistle to the Ephesians}}
[[Category:1st-century Christian texts]]
[[Category:Canonical epistles|Ephesians]]
[[Category:Pauline epistles]]
[[Category:Prison writings]]
[[Category:New Testament books|Ephesians]]
[[Category:Epistle to the Ephesians| ]]</text>
      <sha1>dcw52z64asjch1vhk3okykpe3jxwyl0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
