  <page>
    <title>Edna St. Vincent Millay</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9824</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940304590</id>
      <parentid>935030298</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-11T19:13:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>86.149.123.104</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Works */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2019}}
{{Infobox writer &lt;!-- for more information see [[:Template:Infobox writer/doc]] --&gt;
| name        = Edna St. Vincent Millay
| image       = Edna St. Vincent Millay 1933 van Vechten.jpg
| caption     = Edna St. Vincent Millay, photographed by [[Carl Van Vechten]], 1933
| pseudonym   = Nancy Boyd
| birth_date  = {{birth date|1892|2|22}}
| birth_place = [[Rockland, Maine]], US
| death_date  = {{death date and age|1950|10|19|1892|2|22}}
| death_place = [[Austerlitz, New York]], US
| occupation  = Poet
| alma_mater  = [[Vassar College]]
| nationality = American
| awards      = {{awd|Pulitzer Prize for Poetry|&lt;small&gt;(1923)&lt;/small&gt;}}{{awd|[[Robert Frost Medal]]|&lt;small&gt;(1943)&lt;/small&gt;}}
}}

'''Edna St. Vincent Millay''' (February 22, 1892 – October 19, 1950) was an American [[lyric poetry|poet]] and playwright.&lt;ref name=&quot;WVobit&quot;&gt;Obituary ''[[Variety Obituaries|Variety]]'', October 25, 1950.&lt;/ref&gt; She received the [[Pulitzer Prize for Poetry]] in 1923, the third &lt;!-- THIRD is correct; do not change to FIRST. Sara Teasdale won the Pulitzer for poetry in 1918, and Margaret Widdemer in 1919 --&gt;woman to win the award for poetry,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pulitzer.org/prize-winners-by-category/224|title=Poetry |website=www.pulitzer.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was also known for her [[feminist activism]]. She used the pseudonym '''Nancy Boyd''' for her prose work. The poet [[Richard Wilbur]] asserted, &quot;She wrote some of the best [[sonnet]]s of the century.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Millay, Edna St. Vincent. ''Selected Poems''. Harper Collins, 1991&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
Millay was born in [[Rockland, Maine]], to Cora Lounella Buzelle, a nurse, and Henry Tolman Millay, a schoolteacher who would later become a superintendent of schools.  Her middle name derives from [[St. Vincent's Hospital (Manhattan)|St. Vincent's Hospital]] in [[New York City|New York]], where her uncle's life had been saved just before her birth. The family's house was &quot;between the mountains and the sea where baskets of apples and drying herbs on the porch mingled their scents with those of the neighboring pine woods.&quot;&lt;ref Name = &quot;NYT&quot;/&gt; In 1904, Cora officially divorced Millay's father for financial irresponsibility and domestic abuse, but they had already been separated for some years. Henry and Millay kept a letter correspondence for many years, but he never re-entered the family. Cora and her three daughters, Edna (who called herself &quot;Vincent&quot;), Norma Lounella (born 1893), and Kathleen Kalloch (born 1896), moved from town to town, living in poverty and surviving various illnesses. Cora travelled with a trunk full of classic literature, including [[William Shakespeare|Shakespeare]] and [[John Milton|Milton]], which she read to her children. The family settled in a small house on the property of Cora's aunt in [[Camden, Maine]], where Millay would write the first of the poems that would bring her literary fame.

[[Image:Millay magn.jpg|thumb|right|Edna St. Vincent Millay in Mamaroneck,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/agc1996000549/PP/|title=Edna St. Vincent Millay at Mitchell Kennerley's house in Mamaroneck, New York|first=Genthe, Arnold|last=1869-1942|date=September 24, 2018|website=www.loc.gov}}&lt;/ref&gt; NY, 1914, by [[Arnold Genthe]].]]

The three sisters were independent and spoke their minds, which did not always sit well with the authority figures in their lives. Millay's grade school principal, offended by her frank attitudes, refused to call her Vincent. Instead, he called her by any woman's name that started with a V.&lt;ref name=&quot;epstein&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Epstein | first = Daniel Mark | year = 2001 | title = What Lips My Lips Have Kissed: The Loves and Love Poems of Edna St. Vincent Millay | location = New York | publisher = Henry Holt | isbn = 0-8050-6727-2 | url = https://archive.org/details/whatlipsmylipsha0000epst }}&lt;/ref&gt; At Camden High School, Millay began developing her literary talents, starting at the school's literary magazine, ''The Megunticook''.  At 14 she won the St. Nicholas Gold Badge for poetry, and by 15, she had published her poetry in the popular children's magazine ''St. Nicholas'', the ''Camden Herald'', and the high-profile anthology ''Current Literature''.

Millay entered [[Vassar College]] in 1913 when she was 21 years old, later than usual. She had relationships with many fellow students during her time there and kept scrapbooks including drafts of plays written during the period.&lt;ref name=&quot;epstein&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Brinkman, B. &quot;Modern American Archives and Scrapbook Modernism.&quot; ''The Cambridge Companion to Modern American Poetry'' (2015):&lt;/ref&gt; While at school, she had several relationships with women, including [[Edith Wynne Matthison]], who would go on to become an actress in silent films.&lt;ref name=&quot;AAP&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.poets.org/poet.php/prmPID/160|title=Edna St. Vincent Millay|last=Millay|first=Edna St. Vincent|date=February 4, 2014|website=Edna St. Vincent Millay}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==New York City==
[[File:Edna St. Vincent Millay home 1923–24.jpg|thumb|Edna St. Vincent Millay's home in 1923–24 at 75½ Bedford Street, Greenwich Village (2013 photo)]]
After her graduation from Vassar in 1917, Millay moved to [[New York City]]. She lived in a number of places in [[Greenwich Village]], including a house owned by the [[Cherry Lane Theatre]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Nevius&quot;&gt;{{cite book | first = Michelle and James | last = Nevius| title = Inside the Apple: A Streetwise History of New York City| place = New York| publisher = Free Press| year = 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[75½ Bedford Street]], renowned for being the narrowest&lt;ref name=NYT2&gt;{{cite news|last1=Gray|first1=Christopher|title=For Rent: 3-Floor House, 9 1/2 Ft. Wide, $6,000 a Month|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1996/11/10/realestate/for-rent-3-floor-house-9-1-2-ft-wide-6000-a-month.html|accessdate=December 14, 2015|newspaper=The New York Times|date=November 10, 1996}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=WSJ&gt;{{cite news|last1=Barbanel|first1=Josh|title=Grand on a Small Scale|url=https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB10001424127887323308504579085060860112966|accessdate=December 14, 2015|newspaper=The Wall Street Journal|date=September 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; in New York City.&lt;ref&gt;Wetzsteon, Ross. 2002. ''Republic of Dreams: Greenwich Village, the American Bohemia, 1910-1960''. New York: Simon &amp; Schuster. p. 283&lt;/ref&gt;  The critic [[Floyd Dell]] wrote that the red-haired and beautiful Millay was &quot;a frivolous young woman, with a brand-new pair of dancing slippers and a mouth like a valentine.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT&quot;/&gt;  Millay described her life in New York as &quot;very, very poor and very, very merry.&quot; While establishing her career as a poet, Millay initially worked with the Provincetown Players on Macdougal Street and the Theatre Guild. In 1924 Millay and others founded the Cherry Lane Theater &quot;to continue the staging of experimental drama.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Delaney, Edmund T. 1968. ''New York's Greenwich Village''. Barre, Mass: Barre Publishers. p. 112&lt;/ref&gt; Magazine articles under a pseudonym also helped support her early days in the village.&lt;ref Name = &quot;NYT&quot;/&gt;

Counted among Millay's close friends were the writers [[Witter Bynner]], [[Arthur Davison Ficke]], and [[Susan Glaspell]], as well as [[Floyd Dell]] and the critic [[Edmund Wilson]], both of whom proposed marriage to her and were refused.&lt;ref name=&quot;AAP&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Milford | first = Nancy | year = 2001 | title = Savage Beauty: The Life of Edna St. Vincent Millay | location = New York | publisher = Random House | isbn = 0-375-76081-4 | pages = [https://archive.org/details/savagebeautylife00milf/page/191 191–192] | url = https://archive.org/details/savagebeautylife00milf/page/191 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Career==
Millay's fame began in 1912 when, at the age of 20, she entered her poem &quot;[[Renascence (poem)|Renascence]]&quot; in a poetry contest in ''The Lyric Year''.  The poem was widely considered the best submission, and when it was ultimately awarded fourth place, it created a scandal which brought Millay publicity. The first-place winner [[Orrick Johns]] was among those who felt that &quot;Renascence&quot; was the best poem, and stated that &quot;the award was as much an embarrassment to me as a triumph.&quot;  A second-prize winner offered Millay his $250 prize money.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dash&quot;&gt;{{cite book| first = Joan | last = Dash| title = A Life of One's Own: Three Gifted Women and the Men They Married| place = New York| publisher = Harper &amp; Row | year = 1973}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In the immediate aftermath of the ''Lyric Year'' controversy, wealthy arts patron Caroline B. Dow heard Millay reciting her poetry and playing the piano at the Whitehall Inn in [[Camden, Maine]], and was so impressed that she offered to pay for Millay's education at [[Vassar College]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.csustan.edu/english/reuben/pal/chap7/millay.html |title = Chapter 7: Edna St. Vincent Millay | last = Reuben | first = Paul P |work = PAL: Perspectives in American Literature – A Research and Reference Guide | publisher = CSUSTAN | accessdate= July 2, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After graduating from Vassar, Millay moved to Greenwich Village. A friend remembered seeing her red hair flying as she ran down MacDougal Street, “flushed and laughing like a nymph.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Flame|url= https://www.theattic.space/home-page-blogs/2018/1/5/the-flame-of-hope |website=The Attic|accessdate=July 27, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; She would soon fall out of love, bluntly answering a marriage proposal: &quot;Never ask a girl poet to marry you.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Ibid.&lt;/ref&gt; Holed up in a small, unheated apartment, she began to write shorter, pithier poems. 

Millay’s 1920 collection ''A Few Figs From Thistles'' drew controversy for its exploration of female sexuality and feminism.&lt;ref&gt;Millay, Edna St. Vincent. [http://www2.hn.psu.edu/faculty/jmanis/esv-millay/figs-thistles.pdf ''A few Figs from Thistles'']&lt;/ref&gt; In 1919, she wrote the anti-war play ''Aria da Capo'', which starred her sister Norma Millay at the [[Provincetown Playhouse]] in New York City. Millay won the [[Pulitzer Prize]] for Poetry in 1923 for &quot;The Ballad of the Harp-Weaver&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;Millay, Edna St. Vincent, [http://digital.library.upenn.edu/women/millay/ballad/ballad.html &quot;The Ballad of the Harp-Weaver&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; she was the third woman to win the poetry prize, after [[Sara Teasdale]] (1918) and [[Margaret Widdemer]] (1919).&lt;ref name = &quot;Pulitzer site&quot;&gt;{{Citation | url = http://www.pulitzer.org/bycat/Poetry | title = Pulitzer | contribution = Poetry | accessdate = December 9, 2010}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Millay also wrote short stories for the magazine Ainslee's - but she was a canny protector of her identity as a poet and an aesthete, and insisted on publishing this more mass-appeal work under a pseudonym, Nancy Boyd.  As her fame grew and she became a household name, the publisher of Ainslee's offered to double her fees if he could use her real name.  She refused.

In January 1921, she went to [[Paris]], where she met and befriended the sculptors [[Thelma Wood]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Herring | first = Phillip | year = 1995 | title = Djuna: The Life and Work of Djuna Barnes | location = New York | publisher = Penguin Books | isbn = 0-14-017842-2 | page = 158}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Constantin Brancusi]], photographer [[Man Ray]], had affairs with journalists George Slocombe and John Carter, and became pregnant by a man named Daubigny and secured a marriage license, but instead returned to England where her mother Cora helped induce an abortion with [[alkanet]] as recommended in her old copy of [[Culpeper's Complete Herbal]].&lt;ref&gt;Milford 2001, pp 234-9.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Steepletop main house, Austerlitz, NY.jpg|300px|right|thumb|Main house at Steepletop, where Millay spent the last 25 years of her life]]
Possibly as a result, Millay was frequently ill and weak for much of the next four years. After his remarkable attentions to her during her illness, in 1923 she married 43-year-old Eugen Jan [[Boissevain family|Boissevain]] (1880–1949), the widower of the labor lawyer and war correspondent [[Inez Milholland]], a political icon Millay had met during her time at Vassar.&lt;ref&gt;Milford 2001, pp268-275.&lt;/ref&gt; A self-proclaimed feminist, Boissevain supported her career and took primary care of domestic responsibilities. Both Millay and Boissevain had other lovers throughout their twenty-six-year marriage. For Millay, a significant such relationship was with the poet [[George Dillon (poet)|George Dillon]]. She met Dillon at one of her readings at the University of Chicago in 1928 where he was a student. He was fourteen years her junior, and the relationship inspired the [[sonnet]]s in the collection ''Fatal Interview'' (published 1931).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.poetryfoundation.org/bio/edna-st-vincent-millay | title=Edna St. Vincent Millay | publisher=Poetry Foundation | accessdate=June 27, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1925, Boissevain and Millay bought [[Steepletop]] near [[Austerlitz, New York]], which had been a {{convert|635|acre|ha|adj=on}} blueberry farm.&lt;ref name=&quot;Millay Colony history&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=History|url=http://www.millaycolony.org/history | publisher = [[Millay Colony for the Arts]] | accessdate= January 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The couple built a barn (from a [[Sears|Sears Roebuck]] kit), and then a writing cabin and a tennis court. Millay grew her own vegetables in a small garden.&lt;ref name = &quot;Millay Colony history&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Millay society grounds page&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=The Grounds at Steepletop |url=http://www.millaysociety.org/millaystpgrounds.htm |publisher=Edna St. Vincent Millay Society |year=2008 |accessdate=January 23, 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081121181408/http://www.millaysociety.org/millaystpgrounds.htm |archivedate=November 21, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The couple later bought [[Ragged Island (Harpswell, Maine)|Ragged Island]] in [[Casco Bay]], Maine, as a summer retreat.&lt;ref&gt;Milford 2001, pp368-371.&lt;/ref&gt; The couple often had trouble with servants, with Millay writing, &quot;The only people I really hate are servants. They are not really human beings at all.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bryson, Bill. ''At Home, A Short History of Private Life'', Random House, 2010, p 111&lt;/ref&gt; 

In the summer of 1936, Millay was riding in a station wagon when the door suddenly swung open, and &quot;I was hurled out into the pitch-darkness...and rolled for some distance down a rocky gully&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Letter from Millay to Ferdinand Earle, September 14, 1940. Quoted in Milford 2001, p449.&lt;/ref&gt;, severely damaging nerves in her spine, requiring frequent surgeries and hospitalizations, at least daily doses of morphine, and she lived the rest of her life in &quot;constant pain&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Milford 2001, pp438-449.&lt;/ref&gt; Despite this, she was sufficiently alarmed by the rise of fascism to write against it. During the first world war, Millay had been a dedicated and active pacifist; however, from 1940, she advocated for the U.S. to enter the war against the Axis.  After it did, she was an ardent supporter of the war effort.  She later worked with [[Writers' War Board]] to create propaganda, including poetry.&lt;ref&gt;[http://vcencyclopedia.vassar.edu/alumni/edna-st-vincent-millay.html &quot;Edna St. Vincent Millay&quot;] ''Vassar Encyclopaedia'', Vassar College&lt;/ref&gt; Her reputation in poetry circles was damaged by her war work. Merle Rubin noted, &quot;She seems to have caught more flak from the literary critics for supporting democracy than [[Ezra Pound]] did for championing [[fascism]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Rubin|first1=Merle|title=Lyrical, Rebellious And Almost Forgotten |url=https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB999736509740821352|accessdate=February 24, 2015 |work=[[The Wall Street Journal]] |date=September 6, 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1942 in ''The New York Times Magazine'', Millay mourned the destruction of the Czechoslovak town of [[Lidice]]. Nazi forces had razed Lidice, slaughtered its male inhabitants and scattered its surviving residents in retaliation for the assassination of [[Reinhard Heydrich]].  Millay wrote:

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;poem&gt;The whole world holds in its arms today
The murdered village of Lidice, 
Like the murdered body of a little child.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT&quot;/&gt;&lt;/poem&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

This article would serve as the basis of her 32-page poem, [[Murder of Lidice]] in 1942&lt;ref name=&quot;goodreads.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/3193672-the-murder-of-lidice|title=The Murder of Lidice|author=|date=|website=www.goodreads.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; and loosely served as the basis of the 1943 [[MGM]] movie [[Hitler's Madman]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Hitler's Madman]]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Circular reference|date=April 2018}} [[Douglas Sirk]] directed the movie. [[Harper and Brothers]] published the poem in 1942.&lt;ref name=&quot;goodreads.com&quot;/&gt; 

In 1943, Millay was the sixth person and the second woman to be awarded the [[Frost Medal]] for her lifetime contribution to American poetry.

Despite the excellent sales of her books in the 1930s, her declining reputation, constant medical bills, and frequent demands from her mentally-ill sister Kathleen meant that for most of her last years, Millay was in debt to her own publisher.&lt;ref&gt;Milford 2001, p442&lt;/ref&gt; Author Daniel Mark Epstein also concludes from her correspondence that Millay developed a passion for thoroughbred horse-racing, and spent much of her income investing in a racing stable, of which she had quietly become an owner. &lt;ref&gt;Epstein, Daniel Mark (2001). What Lips My Lips Have Kissed: The Loves and Love Poems of Edna St. Vincent Millay. New York: Henry Holt. {{ISBN|0-8050-6727-2}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Boissevain died in 1949 of [[lung cancer]], and Millay lived alone for the last year of her life.

==Death and legacy==
Millay died at her home on October 19, 1950. She had fallen down stairs and was found approximately eight hours after her death. Her physician reported that she had suffered a [[myocardial infarction|heart attack]] following a [[coronary occlusion]].&lt;ref Name = &quot;NYT&quot;&gt;{{Citation | url = https://www.nytimes.com/learning/general/onthisday/bday/0222.html?scp=5&amp;sq=st%20vincent%20millay&amp;st=cse | newspaper = The New York Times | type = obituary | date = October 20, 1950 | title = Edna St. V. Millay Found Dead At 58 | accessdate = September 13, 2010}}.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Sfn | Milford | 2001 | p = 508}}{{Sfn | Epstein 2001 | p = 273}}  She was 58 years old. She is buried alongside her husband at [[Steepletop]], Austerlitz, New York.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, Scott. ''Resting Places: The Burial Sites of More Than 14,000 Famous Persons'', 3d ed.: 2 (Kindle Location 32422). McFarland &amp; Company, Inc., Publishers. Kindle Edition.&lt;/ref&gt;

Millay's sister Norma and her husband, the painter and actor Charles Frederick Ellis, moved to Steepletop after Millay's death. In 1973, they established [[Millay Colony for the Arts]] on the seven acres around the house and barn.  After the death of her husband in 1976, Norma continued to run the program until her death in 1986.&lt;ref name=&quot;Millay Colony history&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Edna St. Vincent Millay's gravestone at Steepletop in Austerlitz, NY.jpg|thumb|250px|left|Edna St. Vincent Millay's (and her husband's) gravestone at Steepletop]]
At 17, the poet [[Mary Oliver]] visited Steepletop and became a close friend of Norma. Oliver eventually lived there for seven years and helped to organize Millay's papers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Land&quot;&gt;{{Citation | url = http://travel.nytimes.com/2009/07/05/travel/05oliver.html?pagewanted=3 | title = The Land and Words of Mary Oliver, the Bard of Provincetown | date = July 5, 2009 | newspaper = The New York Times | accessdate = September 7, 2010}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Mary Oliver herself went on to become a Pulitzer Prize-winning poet, greatly inspired by Millay's work.&lt;ref name=&quot;PoetryFound&quot;&gt;[http://www.poetryfoundation.org/archive/poet.html?id=5130 Poetry Foundation Oliver biography]. Accessed September 7, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006, the state of [[New York (state)|New York]] paid $1.69 million to acquire {{convert|230|acre|km2}} of Steepletop, to add the land to a nearby state forest preserve. The proceeds of the sale were used by the Edna St. Vincent Millay Society to restore the farmhouse and grounds and turn it into a museum. The museum opened to the public in the summer 2010, and guided tours of Steepletop and Millay's gardens were available from the end of May through the middle of October. Effective November 2018 Steepletop closed to the public due to financial challenges and restoration needs. Fundraising efforts continue as do considerations for the future of this museum house.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.berkshireeagle.com/stories/the-edna-st-vincent-millay-society-saving-steepletop,578678|title=The Edna St. Vincent Millay Society: Saving Steepletop|last=Cassidy|first=Benjamin|last2=Eagle|first2=The Berkshire|website=The Berkshire Eagle|language=en|access-date=July 14, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;references group=&quot;The Edna St. Vincent Millay Society: Saving Steepletop, Berkshire Eagle July 5, 2019&quot; /&gt;Parts of the grounds of Steepletop, including the Millay Poetry Trail that leads to her grave, are now open for occasional scheduled events.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.millay.org/steepletoptrails.php|title=Steepletop Trails|website=www.millay.org|access-date=2020-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Details of Millay's life were compiled by biographer [[Nancy Milford]] in the book titled ''Savage Beauty: The Life of Edna St Vincent Millay'', published in 2001. Milford was sought out by Millay's only living connection at the time, her sister [[Norma Millay Ellis]], and was chosen for her previous, successful biography ''Zelda''. Milford would then go on to edit and write an introduction for a collection of Millay's poems called ''The Selected Poetry of Edna St. Vincent Millay.''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Selected Poems of Edna St. Vincent Millay|last=Milford|first=Nancy|publisher=Random House|year=2002|isbn=0-375-76123-3|location=New York|pages=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2015, she was named by Equality Forum as one of their 31 Icons of the 2015 [[LGBT History Month]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= Malcolm Lazin |url=http://www.advocate.com/commentary/2015/08/20/op-ed-here-are-31-icons-2015s-gay-history-month |title=Op-ed: Here Are the 31 Icons of 2015's Gay History Month |publisher=Advocate.com |date=August 20, 2015 |accessdate=August 21, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Millay has been the inspiration for several plays and musicals, including the biographical play ''Words Like Fresh Skin,'' written by Megan Lohne and produced at [[Adelphi University]]. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.wordslikefreshskin.org/|title=Words like Fresh Skin -|website=Words like Fresh Skin|language=en|access-date=2020-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Works==
{{Quote box |width=300px |align=right |quoted=true |bgcolor=#FFFFF0 |salign=right
 |quote  =&lt;poem&gt;
My candle burns at both ends;
It will not last the night;
But ah, my foes, and oh, my friends—
It gives a lovely light!
&lt;/poem&gt; |source =&quot;First Fig&quot; &lt;br&gt;from ''A Few Figs from Thistles'' (1920)&lt;ref name=&quot;Herald&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.tropicfan.com/The%20Eternal%20Flame%20by%20Michael%20Browning.htm |title= The Eternal Flame |author= Michael Browning |work= [[The Miami Herald]] |date= 18 August 1996 |url-status= dead |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20101217090416/http://www.tropicfan.com/The%20Eternal%20Flame%20by%20Michael%20Browning.htm |archivedate= 17 December 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Millay wrote six [[verse drama]]s early in her career, including ''Two Slatterns and a King'' and ''The Lamp and the Bell'', a poem written for [[Vassar College]] about love between women.&lt;ref name=&quot;AAP&quot;/&gt; She was commissioned by the [[Metropolitan Opera|Metropolitan Opera House]] to write a [[libretto]] for an opera composed by [[Deems Taylor]]. The result, ''[[The King's Henchman]]'', drew on the ''[[Anglo-Saxon Chronicle]]'s'' account of [[Edgar the Peaceful|Eadgar, King of Wessex]], and was described as the most effectively and artistically wrought American opera ever to reach the stage. Within three weeks, her publishers had run through four editions of the book.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT&quot;/&gt;

Her pacifist verse drama ''Aria da Capo'', a one-act play written for the [[Provincetown Players]], is often anthologized.  It aired live as an episode of ''[[Academy Theatre]]'' in 1949 on NBC.{{cn|date=October 2019}}

&quot;[[s:Euclid alone has looked on Beauty bare|Euclid alone has looked on Beauty bare]]&quot; (1922)  is an homage to the [[geometry of Euclid]].&lt;ref&gt;Sinclair, N. et al. (2006). ''Mathematics and the Aesthetic''. New York: Springer. p. 111.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Renascence (poem)|&quot;Renascence&quot;]]&lt;ref&gt;Millay, Edna St. Vincent. [http://www.bartleby.com/131/1.html &quot;Renascence&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;The Ballad of the Harp-Weaver&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Millay, Edna St. Vincent. [http://www.americanpoems.com/poets/ednamillay/7356 &quot;The Ballad of the Harp-Weaver&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; are often considered her finest poems. On her death, ''The New York Times'' described her as &quot;an idol of the younger generation during the glorious early days of Greenwich Village [...] One of the greatest American poets of her time.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT&quot;/&gt; [[Thomas Hardy]] said that America had two great attractions: the skyscraper and the poetry of Edna St. Vincent Millay.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.danverslibrary.org/readthis/?p=140979|title=Poetry Pairing: Edna St. Vincent Millay|date=2018-04-18|website=READ THIS|language=en-US|access-date=2020-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Publications==
{{Main article|Edna St. Vincent Millay bibliography}}


{{Portal bar|Poetry|Biography|United States|New York City}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* Atkins, Elizabeth (1936). ''Edna St. Vincent Millay and Her Times''. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.
* {{cite book | last=Barnet | first=Andrea | title=All-Night Party: The Women of Bohemian Greenwich Village and Harlem, 1913–1930 | location=Chapel Hill, NC | publisher=Algonquin Books | year=2004 | isbn=1-56512-381-6 | ref=Harv | url=https://archive.org/details/allnightpartywom00barn }}
* {{cite book | last = Epstein | first = Daniel Mark | year = 2001 | title = What Lips my Lips Have Kissed: The Loves and Love Poems of Edna St. Vincent Millay | location = New York | publisher = Henry Holt | isbn = 0-8050-6727-2 | ref = Harv | url = https://archive.org/details/whatlipsmylipsha0000epst }}
* {{cite book | last = Milford | first = Nancy | year = 2001 | title = Savage Beauty: The Life of Edna St. Vincent Millay | location = New York | publisher = Random House | isbn = 0-375-76081-4 | pages = [https://archive.org/details/savagebeautylife00milf/page/191 191–92] | ref = Harv | url = https://archive.org/details/savagebeautylife00milf/page/191 }}
* Milford, Nancy (2002). ''The Selected Poems of Edna St Vincent Millay''. New York: Random House. {{ISBN|0-375-76123-3}}.
* Millay, Edna St. Vincent (1991) ''Selected Poems''. Harper Collins

==External links==
{{Library resources box|by=yes|onlinebooksby=yes|viaf=90721763}}
{{wikisource author}}
{{wikiquote|Edna St. Vincent Millay}}
{{Commons category}}
* [http://www.poetryfoundation.org/archive/poet.html?id=4717 Edna St. Vincent Millay at the Poetry Foundation].
* [https://www.poets.org/poetsorg/poet/edna-st-vincent-millay Works by Edna St. Vincent Millay at the Academy of American Poets]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120320031630/http://rpo.library.utoronto.ca/poet/224.html Selected Poetry of Edna St. Vincent Millay] - Biography &amp; 18 poems (Ashes of Life, The Betrothal, Departure, Dirge, Ebb, Feast, First Fig, [Four Sonnets 1922], Grown Up, Humoresque, Lament, The Penitent, Recuerdo, Second Fig, Sonnets 1923, Sonnets from an Ungrafted Tree, Sorrow, Spring)
* {{Gutenberg author |id=70 | name=Edna St. Vincent Millay}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Edna St. Vincent Millay}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Nancy Boyd}}
* {{Librivox author |id=32}}
* [http://collections.si.edu/search/results.jsp?view=&amp;dsort=&amp;date.slider=&amp;q=Edna+St.+Vincent+Millay Archive and images at] the [[Smithsonian Institution]].
* [https://www.nytimes.com/learning/general/onthisday/bday/0222.html ''New York Times'' Obituary October 20, 1950 &quot;Edna St. V. Millay Found Dead At 58&quot;]. Accessed 2010-09-13
* [http://mms.newberry.org/xml/xml_files/GurkoDell.xml Miriam Gurko-Floyd Dell Papers] at [[The Newberry Library]]
* [http://specialcollections.vassar.edu/collections/manuscripts/findingaids/millay_edna.html Guide to the Edna St. Vincent Millay] at Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library

{{PulitzerPrize PoetryAuthors 1922–1950}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Millay, Edna St. Vincent}}
[[Category:American dramatists and playwrights]]
[[Category:1892 births]]
[[Category:1950 deaths]]
[[Category:American feminist writers]]
[[Category:American opera librettists]]
[[Category:Women opera librettists]]
[[Category:American women poets]]
[[Category:American women dramatists and playwrights]]
[[Category:Bisexual writers]]
[[Category:Bisexual women]]
[[Category:Formalist poets]]
[[Category:LGBT poets]]
[[Category:LGBT writers from the United States]]
[[Category:Sonneteers]]
[[Category:American librettists]]
[[Category:Women librettists]]
[[Category:Pulitzer Prize for Poetry winners]]
[[Category:LGBT people from Maine]]
[[Category:LGBT people from New York (state)]]
[[Category:Poets from Maine]]
[[Category:Writers from Maine]]
[[Category:Writers from New York (state)]]
[[Category:Vassar College alumni]]
[[Category:People from Camden, Maine]]
[[Category:People from Greenwich Village]]
[[Category:People from Rockland, Maine]]
[[Category:Accidental deaths from falls]]
[[Category:Accidental deaths in New York (state)]]
[[Category:20th-century American poets]]
[[Category:20th-century dramatists and playwrights]]
[[Category:20th-century American women writers]]</text>
      <sha1>nro42b4qcf2bx02vqx48aceld1ok9pf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
