  <page>
    <title>Exile</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9855</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937781847</id>
      <parentid>937781486</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-27T05:14:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kore's Cosmaupia</username>
        <id>37542802</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* In popular culture */This is a minor edit.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{redirect2|Banish|Banishment}}
{{distinguish-otheruses2|Exhile|Exile}}
[[File:Napoleon sainthelene.jpg|thumb|''[[Napoleon]]'s Exile on [[Saint Helena]]'' by {{Interlanguage link multi|Franz Josef Sandmann|de}} (1820)]]
[[File:The First Night in Exile.jpg|thumb|''The First Night in Exile'' - This painting comes from a celebrated series illustrating one of Hinduism's great epics, the ''[[Ramayana]]''. It tells the story of prince Rama, who is wrongly exiled from his father's kingdom, accompanied only by his wife and brother.]]
[[Image:Dante exile.jpg|thumb|''[[Dante]] in Exile'' by {{Interlanguage link multi|Domenico Petarlini|es}}]]

To be in '''exile''' means to be away from one's home (i.e. [[village]], [[town]], [[city]], [[State (polity)|state]], [[province]], [[territory]] or even [[country]]), while either being explicitly refused permission to return or being threatened with imprisonment or death upon return.

In [[Roman law]], ''exsilium'' denoted both voluntary exile and banishment as a [[capital punishment]] alternative to death. [[Deportation]] was forced exile, and entailed the lifelong loss of citizenship and property. [[Relegatio|Relegation]] was a milder form of deportation, which preserved the subject's citizenship and property.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | author=William Smith | entry=BANISHMENT (ROMAN) | title=Dictionary of Greek and Roman Antiquities | edition=3rd | year=1890 | pages=136–137| title-link=Dictionary of Greek and Roman Antiquities | author-link=William Smith (lexicographer) }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The terms [[diaspora]] and [[refugee]] describe group exile, both voluntary and forced, and &quot;[[government in exile]]&quot; describes a government of a country that has relocated and argues its legitimacy from outside that country. Voluntary exile is often depicted as a form of protest by the person who claims it, to avoid persecution and prosecution (such as tax or criminal allegations), an act of shame or repentance, or isolating oneself to be able to devote time to a particular pursuit.

Article 9 of the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] states that &quot;No one shall be subjected to arbitrary arrest, detention or exile.&quot;

==For individuals==
=== Exiled heads of state ===
{{main|List of heads of state or government who have been in exile}}
In some cases the [[Deposition (politics)|deposed]] [[head of state]] is allowed to go into exile following a [[coup]] or other change of government, allowing a more peaceful transition to take place or to escape justice.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Geoghegan |first=Tom |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-13052996 |title=BBC News - What happens to deposed leaders? |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date=2011-04-14 |accessdate=2014-05-12|work=BBC News }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Avoiding tax or legal matters ===
{{main|Tax exile|Fugitive}}
A wealthy citizen who moves to a jurisdiction with lower taxes is termed a ''tax exile''. Creative people such as authors and musicians who achieve sudden wealth sometimes choose this solution. Examples include the British-Canadian writer [[Arthur Hailey]], who moved to the Bahamas to avoid taxes following the runaway success of his novels ''Hotel'' and ''Airport'',&lt;ref&gt;Stevie Cameron, ''Blue Trust: The Author, The Lawyer, His Wife, And Her Money,'' 1998&lt;/ref&gt; and the English rock band the [[Rolling Stones]] who, in the spring of 1971, owed more in taxes than they could pay and left Britain before the government could seize their assets. Members of the band all moved to France for a period of time where they recorded music for the album that came to be called ''Exile on Main Street'', the Main Street of the title referring to the French Riviera.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Greenfield, ''Exile on Main Street: A Season in Hell with the Rolling Stones,'' 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2012, [[Eduardo Saverin]], one of the founders of Facebook, made headlines by renouncing his U.S. citizenship before his company's [[Initial public offering|IPO]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Kucera|first=Danielle|title=Facebook Co-Founder Saverin Gives Up U.S. Citizenship Before IPO|url=https://www.bloomberg.com/news/2012-05-11/facebook-co-founder-saverin-gives-up-u-s-citizenship-before-ipo.html|publisher=Bloomberg News|accessdate=2 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The dual Brazilian/U.S. citizen's decision to move to Singapore and renounce his citizenship spurred a bill in the U.S. Senate, the [[Ex-PATRIOT Act]], which would have forced such wealthy ''tax exiles'' to pay a special tax in order to re-enter the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Drawbaugh|first=Kevin|title=Facebook's Saverin fires back at tax-dodge critics|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/2012/05/17/us-facebook-taxes-idUSBRE84G11A20120517|accessdate=2 November 2012|newspaper=Reuters|date=May 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In some cases a person voluntarily lives in exile to avoid legal issues, such as [[litigation]] or [[criminal prosecution]]. An example of this is [[Asil Nadir]], who fled to the [[Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus]] for 17 years rather than face [[prosecution]] in connection with the failed £1.7 bn company [[Polly Peck]] in the [[United Kingdom]].

=== Avoiding violence or persecution, or in the aftermath of war ===
Examples include:
:* [[Iraq]]i academics asked to return home &quot;from exile&quot; to help rebuild Iraq in 2009&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url= http://chronicle.com/article/Iraq-Appeals-Anew-to-Exiled/47791 |title=Iraq Appeals Anew to Exiled Academics to Return Home|first=Andrew |last=Mills |journal=The Chronicle of Higher Education |date=2009-06-23|accessdate=2011-04-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:* [[Jew]]s who fled persecution from [[Nazi Germany]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.thejc.com/news/uk-news/46415/libyan-exile-plan-uks-frozen-assets |title=Libyan exile plan for UK's frozen assets|first=Simon |last=Rocker |website=[[The Jewish Chronicle]] |date=2011-03-10 |accessdate=2011-04-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:* People undertaking a religious or [[civil liberties]] role in society may be forced into exile due to threat of persecution. For example, [[nun]]s were exiled following the [[Communism|Communist]] [[1948 Czechoslovak coup d'état|coup d'état of 1948]] in [[Czechoslovakia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://articles.latimes.com/1990-01-20/news/mn-233_1_bila-voda |title=For Exiled Nuns, It's Too Late : Banished by the Communist regime, Czechoslovakia's sisters of Bila Voda were symbols of persecution. Now most are too old or weak to benefit from the revolution |first=Dan |last=Fisher |newspaper=Los Angeles Times |date=1990-01-20 |accessdate=2011-04-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Euphemism for convict===
Exile, government man and assigned servant were all [[euphemism|euphemisms]] used in Australia in the 19th century for [[convicts in Australia|convicts under sentence]] who had been [[penal transportation|transported]] from Britain to the colonies.&lt;ref&gt;Morris, Edward E., (1898, reprinted 1973), ''A dictionary of Austral English'', Sydney, Sydney University Press, p.140 &amp; 166. {{ISBN|0424063905}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==For groups, nations and governments==
===Comfortable exile===
{{main|Social alienation|Identity (social science)}}
It is an alternative theory recently developed by a young anthropologist, Balan in 2018. According to him, comfortable exile is a &quot;social exile of people who have been excluded from the mainstream society.  Such people are considered 'aliens' or internal 'others' on the grounds of their religious, racial, ethnic, linguistic or caste-based identity and therefore they migrate to a comfortable space elsewhere after having risked their lives to restore representation, identity and civil rights in their own country and often capture a comfortable identity to being part of a dominant religion, society or culture.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Balan|first1=Binesh|title=Making of Comfortable Exile through Sanskritization: Reflections on Imagination of Identity Notions in India|journal=Contemporary Voice of Dalit, Sage Pub.|volume=10|issue=10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Nation in exile===
{{main|Diaspora|Refugee}}
When a large group, or occasionally a whole people or [[nation]] is exiled, it can be said that this nation is in exile, or &quot;diaspora&quot;. Nations that have been in exile for substantial periods include the [[Jew]]s, who were deported by [[Babylon]]ian king [[Nebuchadnezzar II]] in 586 BC and again following the destruction of the second [[Temple in Jerusalem]] in AD 70. Many Jewish prayers include a yearning to return to Jerusalem and the Jewish homeland.

After the [[partitions of Poland]] in the late 18th century, and following the uprisings (like [[Kościuszko Uprising]], [[November Uprising]] and [[January Uprising]]) against the partitioning powers ([[Russian Empire]], [[Prussia]] and [[Austro-Hungary]]), many Poles have chosen&amp;nbsp;– or been forced&amp;nbsp;– to go into exile, forming large diasporas (known as [[Polish diaspora|Polonia]]), especially in France and the United States. The entire population of [[Crimean Tatars]] (200,000) that remained in their homeland [[Crimean Peninsula|Crimea]] was exiled on 18 May 1944 to Central Asia as a form of [[ethnic cleansing]] and [[collective punishment]] on false accusations. At [[Diego Garcia]], between 1967 and 1973 the British Government forcibly removed some 2,000 [[Chagossians|Chagossian]] resident islanders to make way for a military base today jointly operated by the US and UK.

Since the [[Cuban Revolution]] over one million [[Cubans]] have left [[Cuba]]. Most of these self-identified as exiles as their motivation for leaving the island is political in nature. At the time of the [[Cuban Revolution]], [[Cuba]] only had a population of 6.5 million, and was not a country that had a history of significant emigration, it being the sixth largest recipient of immigrants in the world as of 1958. Most of the exiles' children also consider themselves to be [[Cuban exile]]s. Under Cuban law, children of Cubans born abroad are considered Cuban citizens.

===Government in exile===
{{main|Government in exile}}
During a foreign [[Military occupation|occupation]] or after a [[coup d'état]], a ''government in exile'' of a such afflicted country may be established abroad. One of the most well-known instances of this is the [[Polish government-in-exile]], a government in exile that commanded [[Polish contribution to World War II|Polish armed forces]] operating outside Poland after German occupation during World War II. Other examples include the [[Free French Forces]] government of [[Charles de Gaulle]] of the same time, and the [[Central Tibetan Administration]], commonly known as the Tibetan government-in-exile, and headed by the [[14th Dalai Lama]].

== In popular culture ==
===Drama ===
[[File:Jason and Medea - John William Waterhouse.jpg|thumb|left|''[[Jason and Medea]]'', by [[John William Waterhouse]], 1907]]
[[File:Rama vanavas.jpg|thumb|Rama on the way]]

Exile is an early motif in [[Ancient Greece|ancient Greek]] [[tragedy]]. In the ancient Greek world, this was seen as a fate worse than death. The motif reaches its peak on the play ''[[Medea (play)|Medea]]'', written by [[Euripides]] in the fifth century BC, and rooted in the very old oral traditions of  Greek mythology. Euripides’ [[Medea]] has remained the most frequently performed Greek tragedy through the 20th century.&lt;ref&gt;Cf. Helene P. Foley: ''Reimagining Greek Tragedy on the American Stage''. University of California Press, 2012, p. 190&lt;/ref&gt;

===Art===
[[File:Klaus Mann.jpg|thumb|Exiled [[Klaus Mann]] as Staff Sergeant of the 5th US Army, Italy 1944]]
[[File:Anna Seghers Das siebte Kreuz 1942.jpg|thumb|Cover of [[Anna Seghers]]’ ''[[The Seventh Cross|Das siebte Kreuz]]'']]

After [[Medea]] was abandoned by [[Jason]] and had become a murderess out of revenge, she fled to Athens and married king [[Aigeus]] there, and became the stepmother of the hero [[Theseus]]. Due to a conflict with him, she must leave the [[Polis]] and go away into exile. [[John William Waterhouse]] (1849–1917), the English [[Pre-Raphaelite]] painter’s famous picture ''[[Jason and Medea]]'' shows a key moment before, when Medea tries to poison Theseus.&lt;ref&gt;Cf. Elisabeth Prettejohn: ''Art of the Pre-Raphaelites''. Princeton University Press, London 2000, pp. 165-207. {{ISBN|0-691-07057-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Literature===

In ancient Rome, the Roman Senate had the power to declare the exile to individuals, families or even entire regions. One of the Roman victims was the poet [[Ovid]], who lived during the reign of [[Augustus]]. He was forced to leave Rome and move away to the city of Tomis on the Black Sea, now Constanta. There he wrote his famous work ''Tristia'' (Sorrows) about his bitter feelings in exile.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Tristia by Ovid – high drama and hoax|url= https://www.theguardian.com/books/2015/aug/21/tristia-by-ovid-high-drama-and-hoax|newspaper=The Guardian|date= 2015-08-21|last1= Baggott|first1= Sophie}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Another, at least in a temporary exile, was [[Dante]].

The German-language writer Franz Kafka describes the exile of Karl Rossmann in the posthumously published novel ''Amerika''.&lt;ref&gt;Cf. an unabridged reading by [[Sven Regener]]: ''Amerika'', Roof Music, Bochum 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the period of National Socialism in the first few years after 1933, many Jews, as well as a significant number of German artists and intellectuals fled into exile; for instance, the authors [[Klaus Mann]]  and [[Anna Seghers]]. So Germany's own exile literature emerged and received worldwide credit.&lt;ref&gt;See Martin Mauthner: ''German Writers in French Exile, 1933–1940'', Vallentine Mitchell, London 2007, {{ISBN|978-0-85303-540-4}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Klaus Mann finished his novel ''{{Interlanguage link multi|Der Vulkan|de}}'' (''The Volcano. A Novel Among Emigrants'') in 1939&lt;ref&gt;which he started in September 1936, when he came to New York. Cf. Jan Patocka in: ''Escape to Life. German Intellectuals in New York. A Compendium on Exile after 1933'', ed. by Eckart Goebel/Sigrid Weigel. De Gruyter, Berlin/Boston 2012, p 354. {{ISBN|978-3-11-025867-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; describing the German exile scene, &quot;to bring the rich, scattered and murky experience of exile into epic form&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Cf. Klaus Mann: Der Wendepunkt. Ein Lebensbericht''. (1949), Frankfurt am Main 2006, p. 514.&lt;/ref&gt; as he wrote in his literary balance sheet.  At the same place and in the same year, Anna Seghers published her famous novel ''Das siebte Kreuz'' (''[[The Seventh Cross]]'', published in the United States in 1942).

Important exile literatures in recent years include that of the Caribbean, many of whose artists emigrated to Europe or the United States for political or economic reasons. These writers include Nobel Prize winners [[V. S. Naipaul]] and [[Derek Walcott]] as well as the novelists [[Edwidge Danticat]] and [[Sam Selvon]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1080/14788810.2016.1220790|title=Forms of Exile: Experimental Self-Positioning in Postcolonial Caribbean Poetry|journal=Atlantic Studies|volume=13|issue=4|pages=457–471|year=2016|last1=Müller|first1=Timo}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Outlawry]]
* [[Ban (law)|Ban]]
* [[Defection]]
* [[Deportation]]
* [[Émigré]]
* [[:Category:Exiles by nationality|Exiles by nationality]]
* [[Ostracism]] - procedure under the Athenian democracy
* [[Penal transportation]] - [[penal colony]]
* [[Petalism]]
* [[Porcian Laws]], the Roman laws granting citizens the right to voluntary exile in place of capital punishment
* [[Refugee]]
* [[Right of asylum]] (political asylum)
* [[Scouts-in-Exile]]
* [[Shimanagashi]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{wiktionary|exile}}
{{commonscatinline|Exiles}}
{{wikiquote}}
* [http://www.berlin1969.com/#/without-a-country/4371208 Without a Country]  Varied experiences of American and British exiles in the 20th century.
* {{tcmdb title|id=3061|title=The Seventh Cross}}
* {{imdb title|0037263|The Seventh Cross}}

{{Navboxes
|list =
{{Capital punishment}}
{{Particular human rights}}
}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Exile| ]]
[[Category:Punishments]]
[[Category:Literary motifs]]</text>
      <sha1>7aqk0h5qavgaep50mo7x0ne47uo2zlf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
