  <page>
    <title>Ethnocentrism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9827</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942825203</id>
      <parentid>942825151</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T02:16:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Editor2020</username>
        <id>6046894</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Adding local [[Wikipedia:Short description|short description]]: &quot;Judging another culture solely by the values and standards of one's own culture&quot;, overriding Wikidata description &quot;judging another culture solely by the values and standards of one's own culture&quot; ([[Wikipedia:Shortdesc helper|Shortdesc helper]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Judging another culture solely by the values and standards of one's own culture}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2015}}
{{Anthropology |methods}}
'''Ethnocentrism''' is used in social sciences and anthropology to describe the act of judging another culture and believing that the values and standards of one's own culture are superior – especially with regard to language, behavior, customs, and religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Choices and Connections: An Introduction to Communication|last=McCornack|first=Steven|last2=Ortiz|first2=Joseph|publisher=Bedford/St.Martin's|year=2017|isbn=978-1-319-20116-6|location=Boston, New York|pages=109|oclc=1102471079}}&lt;/ref&gt; These aspects or categories are distinctions that define each ethnicity's unique cultural identity.

The term ethnocentrism, deriving from the Greek word ''ethnos'' meaning &quot;nation, people, or cultural grouping&quot; and the Latin word ''centric'' meaning &quot;center,&quot; was first applied in the social sciences by American sociologist [[William Graham Sumner|William G. Sumner]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Encyclopedia of Diversity and Social Justice|last=Shala|first=Blerim|last2=Cooper|first2=Robin|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers|year=2014|isbn=978-1-4422-1606-8|editor-last=Thompson|editor-first=Sherwood|location=Lanham|pages=|oclc=900277068}}&lt;/ref&gt; In his 1906 book, ''Folkways,'' Sumner describes ethnocentrism as; &quot;the technical name for the view of things in which one's own group is the center of everything, and all others are scaled and rated with reference to it.&quot; He further characterized ethnocentrism as often leading to [[pride]], [[vanity]], the belief in one's own group's [[Superior (hierarchy)|superiority]], and [[contempt]] for outsiders.{{sfn|Sumner|1906|p=13}}

Over time, ethnocentrism developed alongside the progression of social understandings by people such as social theorist, [[Theodor W. Adorno|Theodore W. Adorno]]. In Adorno's ''[[The Authoritarian Personality]]'', he and his colleagues of the [[Frankfurt School]] established a broader definition of the term as a result of &quot;in group-out group differentiation&quot;, stating that ethnocentrism &quot;combines a positive attitude toward one's own ethnic/cultural group (the in-group) with a negative attitude toward the other ethnic/cultural group (the out-group)&quot;. Both of these juxtaposing attitudes are also a result of a process known as ''social identification'' and ''social counter-identification''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | url=https://books.google.com/?id=pvHRNNk9hHEC&amp;vq=Social+Identification |title = Encyclopedia of Nationalism|isbn = 9780080545240|date = 2000|entry=Ethnocentrism|pp=152-153|edition=Two-Volume Set|publisher=Elsevier|last=Motyl |first=Alexander J. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origins and development==
The term ''ethnocentrism'' is believed by scholars to have been created by Austrian sociologist [[Ludwig Gumplowicz]] in the 19th century, although alternate theories suggest that he only popularized the concept as opposed to inventing it.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;Naturalism in Sociology of the Turn of the Century (by Alexander Hofman and Alexander Kovalev), A History of Classical Sociology. Ed. by [[Igor Kon]]. Moscow, 1989, p. 84. {{ISBN|5-01-001102-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bizumic2014&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal | doi=10.5964/jspp.v2i1.264 | title=Who Coined the Concept of Ethnocentrism? A Brief Report| journal=Journal of Social and Political Psychology| volume=2| pages=3–10| year=2014| last1=Bizumic| first1=Boris|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; He saw ethnocentrism as a phenomenon similar to the delusions of [[geocentrism]] and [[anthropocentrism]], defining Ethnocentrism as &quot;the reasons by virtue of which each group of people believed it had always occupied the highest point, not only among contemporaneous peoples and nations, but also in relation to all peoples of the historical past.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;

Subsequently in the 20th century, American social scientist [[William Graham Sumner|William G. Sumner]] proposed two different definitions in his 1906 book ''Folkways.'' Sumner stated that &quot;Ethnocentrism is the technical name for this view of things in which one's own group is the center of everything, and all others are scaled and rated with reference to it.&quot;&lt;ref name=folkways&gt;{{cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/folkwaysstudyofs00sumnrich|page=[https://archive.org/details/folkwaysstudyofs00sumnrich/page/13 13]|title=Folkways: A Study of the Sociological Importance of Usages, Manners, Customs, Mores, and Morals|last=Sumner|first=William Graham|date=1906|website=|publisher=Ginn and Company|via=|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2019-01-18|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the ''War and Other Essays (1911)'', he wrote that &quot;the sentiment of cohesion, internal comradeship, and devotion to the in-group, which carries with it a sense of superiority to any out-group and readiness to defend the interests of the in-group against the out-group, is technically known as ethnocentrism.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/warandotheressa01kellgoog|page=[https://archive.org/details/warandotheressa01kellgoog/page/n46 12]|title=War, and Other Essays|last=Sumner|first=William Graham|date=1911|website=|publisher=Yale University Press|via=|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2019-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Boris Bizumic it is a popular misunderstanding that Sumner originated the term ethnocentrism, stating that in actuality he brought ethnocentrism into the mainstreams of [[anthropology]], [[social science]], and [[psychology]] through his English publications.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bizumic2014&quot;/&gt;

Several theories have been reinforced through the social and psychological understandings of ethnocentrism including [[Theodor W. Adorno|T.W Adorno's]] [[The Authoritarian Personality|Authoritarian Personality Theory]] (1950), [[Donald T. Campbell|Donald T. Campbell's]] [[Realistic Group Conflict Theory]] (1972), and [[Henri Tajfel|Henri Tajfel's]] [[Social identity theory|Social Identity Theory]] (1986). These theories have helped to distinguish ethnocentrism as a means to better understand the behaviors caused by [[in-group and out-group]] differentiation throughout history and society.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bizumic2014&quot;/&gt;

== Anthropology ==
The classifications of ethnocentrism originate from the studies of [[anthropology]]. With its omnipresence throughout history, ethnocentrism has always been a factor in how different cultures and groups related to one another.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt; Examples including how historically, foreigners would be characterized as 'Barbarians', or China would believe their nation to be the 'Empire of the Center' and viewing foreigners as privileged subordinates.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Citation|chapter=Ethnocentrism|date=2003|chapter-url=http://sk.sagepub.com/reference/dictionary-of-race-ethnicity-and-culture/n79.xml|publisher=SAGE Publications Ltd|doi=10.4135/9781446220375.n79|isbn=9780761969006|access-date=2019-07-22|title=Dictionary of Race, Ethnicity and Culture}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, the anthropocentric interpretations initially took place most notably in the 19th century when anthropologists began to describe and rank various cultures according to the degree to which they had developed significant milestones such as; monotheistic religions, technological advancements, and other historical progressions. 

Most rankings were strongly influenced by colonization and the belief to improve societies they colonized, ranking the cultures based on the progression of their western societies and what they classified as milestones. Comparisons were mostly based on what the colonists believed as superior and what their western societies have accomplished. [[Thomas Babington Macaulay|Thomas Macaulay]], an English politician in the 19&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; Century, attempted to validate the opinion that &quot;one shelf of a Western library&quot; had more knowledge then the years of text and literature developed by the Eastern societies.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Berkshire Encyclopedia of World History|last=Bagchi|first=Kaushik|date=2010|publisher=Berkshire Publishing Group|others=McNeill, William Hardy, 1917-2016.|isbn=978-1-84972-976-5|edition=2nd|location=Great Barrington, Mass.|pages=952–954|oclc=707606528}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ideas developed by [[Charles Darwin]] has ethnocentric ideals where societies who believed they were superior were most likely to survive and prosper.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt; Edward Said’s orientalist concept represented how Western reactions to non-Western societies were based on an &quot;unequal power relationship&quot; that Western peoples developed due to colonization and the influence it held over non-Western societies.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=New Dictionary of the History of Ideas|last=Bangura|first=Ahmed S.|date=2005|publisher=Charles Scribner's Sons|others=Horowitz, Maryanne Cline, 1945-|isbn=0-684-31377-4|volume=4|location=Detroit, MI|pages=1679–1680|chapter=African and Black Orientalism|oclc=55800981}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ethnocentric classification of &quot;primitive&quot; were also used by 19&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; and 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century anthropologists and represented how unawareness in cultural and religious understanding changed overall reactions to non-Western societies. Modern anthropologist [[Edward Burnett Tylor|Sir Edward Burnett Tylor]] wrote about &quot;primitive&quot; societies in ''Primitive Culture'' (1871) creating a &quot;civilization&quot; scale where it was implied that ethnic cultures preceded civilized societies.&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Encyclopedia of Race and Racism|last=Moore|first=John H.|date=2013|publisher=Macmillan Reference USA|others=Mason, Patrick L.|isbn=978-0-02-866195-7|edition=2nd|volume=2|location=Detroit, MI|pages=124–125|chapter=Ethnocentrism|oclc=825005867}}&lt;/ref&gt; The use of &quot;savage&quot; as a classification is modernly known as &quot;tribal&quot; or &quot;pre-literate&quot; where it was usually referred as a derogatory term as the &quot;civilization&quot; scale became more common.&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot; /&gt; Examples that demonstrate a lack of understanding include when European travelers judged different languages based on that fact that they could not understand it and displayed a negative reaction, or the intolerance displayed by Westerners when exposed to unknown religions and symbolisms.&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot; /&gt; [[Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel]], a German philosopher, justified Western colonization by reasoning that since the non-Western societies were &quot;primitive&quot; and &quot;uncivilized,&quot; their culture and history was not worth conserving and should allow Westernization.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Encyclopedia of Western Colonialism since 1450|last=Da Baets|first=Antoon|date=2007|publisher=Macmillan Reference USA|editor-last=Benjamin|editor-first=Thomas|isbn=978-0-02-866085-1|location=Detroit, MI|pages=456–461|chapter=Eurocentrism|oclc=74840473|chapter-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20191216195643/http://1.droppdf.com/files/noC4Z/encyclopedia-of-western-colonialism-since-1450.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Anthropologist [[Franz Boas]] saw the flaws in this formulaic approach to ranking and interpreting cultural development and committed himself to overthrowing this inaccurate reasoning due to many factors involving their individual characteristics. With his methodological innovations, Boas sought to show the error of the proposition that race determined cultural capacity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eriksen2015&quot;&gt;{{Cite book | doi=10.2307/j.ctt183p184 |title = Small Places, Large Issues: An Introduction to Social and Cultural Anthropology|year = 2015|last1 = Eriksen|first1 = Thomas Hylland|isbn = 9781783715176|url = &lt;!--  --&gt;}} pp. 10-18. [https://web.archive.org/web/20161020125353/https://toleratedindividuality.files.wordpress.com/2015/02/small-places-large-issues-an-introduction-to-social-and-cultural-anthropology-culture-and-society.pdf 2nd edition available online].&lt;/ref&gt; In his 1911 book ''[[The Mind of Primitive Man]]'', Boas wrote that:&lt;blockquote class=&quot;templatequote&quot;&gt;It is somewhat difficult for us to recognize that the value which we attribute to our own civilization is due to the fact that we participate in this civilization, and that it has been controlling all our actions from the time of our birth; but it is certainly conceivable that there may be other civilizations, based perhaps on different traditions and on a different equilibrium of emotion and reason, which are of no less value than ours, although it may be impossible for us to appreciate their values without having grown up under their influence.{{sfn|Boas|1911|pp=207-208}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;Together, Boas and his colleagues propagated the certainty that there are no inferior races or cultures. This egalitarian approach introduced the concept of [[Cultural relativism|cultural relativism]] to anthropology, a methodological principle for investigating and comparing societies in as unprejudiced as possible and without using a developmental scale as anthropologists at the time were implementing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eriksen2015&quot; /&gt; Boas and anthropologist [[Bronislaw Malinowski]] argued that any human science had to transcend the ethnocentric views that could blind any scientist's ultimate conclusions.{{Citation needed|date=July 2019}}

Both had also urged anthropologists to conduct [[Ethnography|ethnographic]] fieldwork in order to overcome their ethnocentrism. To help, Malinowski would develop the theory of [[Structural functionalism|functionalism]] as guides for producing non-ethnocentric studies of different cultures. Classic examples of anti-ethnocentric anthropology include [[Margaret Mead]]'s ''[[Coming of Age in Samoa]]'' (1928), which in time has met with severe criticism for its incorrect data and generalisations, Malinowski's ''[[The Sexual Life of Savages in North-Western Melanesia]]'' (1929), and [[Ruth Benedict]]'s ''[[Ruth Benedict#Patterns of Culture|Patterns of Culture]]'' (1934). Mead and Benedict were two of Boas's students.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eriksen2015&quot;/&gt;

Scholars generally agree that Boas developed his ideas under the influence of the German philosopher [[Immanuel Kant]]. Legend has it that, on a field trip to the Baffin Islands in 1883, Boas would pass the frigid nights reading Kant's ''[[Critique of Pure Reason]]''. In that work, Kant argued that human understanding could not be described according to the laws that applied to the operations of nature, and that its operations were therefore free, not determined, and that ideas regulated human action, sometimes independent of material interests. Following Kant, Boas pointed out the starving Eskimos who, because of their religious beliefs, would not hunt seals to feed themselves, thus showing that no pragmatic or material calculus determined their values.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=UyC1AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA222|title=The Mind of Primitive Man|last=Boas|first=Franz|date=1911|website=|publisher=The Macmillan Company|location=New York|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2019-01-19|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |jstor = 29790560|title = Critical Implications of Franz Boas' Theory and Methodology|journal = Dialectical Anthropology|volume = 19|issue = 2/3|pages = 237–253|last1 = Hitchens|first1 = Janine|year = 1994|doi = 10.1007/BF01301456}} p. 244.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Causes==
Ethnocentrism is believed to be a [[Behavior|learned behavior]] embedded into a variety of beliefs and values of an individual or group.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;/&gt;

Due to [[enculturation]], individuals in in-groups have a deeper sense of loyalty and are more likely to following the norms and develop relationships with associated members.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; Within relation to enculturation, ethnocentrism is said to be a transgenerational problem since stereotypes and similar perspectives can be enforced and encouraged as time progresses.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; Although loyalty can increase better in-grouper approval, limited interactions with other cultures can prevent individuals to have an understanding and appreciation towards cultural differences resulting in greater ethnocentrism.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

The [[social identity approach]] suggests that ethnocentric beliefs are caused by a strong identification with one's own culture that directly creates a positive view of that culture. It is theorized by [[Henri Tajfel]] and [[John C. Turner]] that in order to maintain that positive view, people make [[Social comparison theory|social comparisons]] that cast competing cultural groups in an unfavorable light.&lt;ref&gt;Tajfel, H., &amp; Turner, J. (2001). [https://web.archive.org/web/20191126151828/http://ark143.org/wordpress2/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/Tajfel-Turner-1979-An-Integrative-Theory-of-Intergroup-Conflict.pdf An integrative theory of intergroup conflict]. In M. A. Hogg &amp; D. Abrams (Eds.), Key readings in social psychology. Intergroup relations: Essential readings (pp. 94-109). New York, NY, US: Psychology Press.&lt;/ref&gt;

Alternative or opposite perspectives could cause individuals to develop [[naïve realism]] and be subject to limitations in understandings.&lt;ref name=&quot;:5&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Sammut|first=Gordon|last2=Bezzina|first2=Frank|last3=Sartawi|first3=Mohammad|date=2015|title=The spiral of conflict: Naïve realism and the black sheep effect in attributions of knowledge and ignorance|journal=Peace and Conflict: Journal of Peace Psychology|volume=21|issue=2|pages=289–294|doi=10.1037/pac0000098}}&lt;/ref&gt; These characteristics can also lead to individuals to become subject to ethnocentrism, when referencing out-groups, and [[black sheep effect]], where personal perspectives contradict those from fellow in-groupers.&lt;ref name=&quot;:5&quot; /&gt;

[[Realistic conflict theory]] assumes that ethnocentrism happens due to &quot;real or perceived conflict&quot; between groups. This also happens when a dominant group may perceive the new members as a threat.&lt;ref name=&quot;:122&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Ethnocentrism. International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences|last=Darity|first=William A.|publisher=Macmillan Reference USA|year=2008|isbn=978-0028661179|location=|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;Scholars have recently demonstrated that individuals are more likely to develop in-group identification and out-group negatively in response to intergroup competition, conflict, or threat.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

Although the causes of ethnocentric beliefs and actions can have varying roots of context and reason, the effects of ethnocentrism has had both negative and positive effects throughout history. The most detrimental effects of ethnocentrism resulting into [[genocide]], [[apartheid]], [[slavery]], and many violent conflicts. Historical examples of these negative effects of ethnocentrism are [[The Holocaust]], the [[Crusades]], the [[Trail of Tears]], and the [[internment of Japanese Americans]]. These events were a result of cultural differences reinforced inhumanely by a superior, majority group. In his 1976 book on evolution, ''[[The Selfish Gene]]'', evolutionary biologist [[Richard Dawkins]] writes that &quot;blood-feuds and inter-clan warfare are easily interpretative in terms of [[W. D. Hamilton|Hamilton's]] genetic theory.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dawkins200622&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=go0e5sBRznYC&amp;pg=PA99|title=The selfish gene|last=Dawkins|first=Richard|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2006|isbn=978-0-19-929115-1|page=99}}&lt;/ref&gt; Simulation-based experiments in [[evolutionary game theory]] have attempted to provide an explanation for the selection of ethnocentric-strategy phenotypes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Hammond|first1=R. A.|last2=Axelrod|first2=R.|year=2006|title=The Evolution of Ethnocentrism|journal=Journal of Conflict Resolution|volume=50|issue=6|pages=926–936|doi=10.1177/0022002706293470|pmc=|pmid=|url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/4e9fd78420a0aef9b89940ac221e6bf909e4ec9f}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | doi=10.18564/jasss.2176 |title = The Evolutionary Dominance of Ethnocentric Cooperation|journal = Journal of Artificial Societies and Social Simulation|volume = 16|issue = 3|year = 2013|last1 = Hartshorn|first1 = Max|last2 = Kaznatcheev|first2 = Artem|last3 = Shultz|first3 = Thomas|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The positive examples of ethnocentrism throughout history have aimed to prohibit the callousness of ethnocentrism and reverse the perspectives of living in a single culture. These organizations can include the formation of the [[United Nations]]; aimed to maintain international relations, and the [[Olympic Games]]; a celebration of sports and friendly competition between cultures.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;

== Effects ==
A study in New Zealand was used to compare how individuals associate with in-groups and out-groupers and has a connotation to [[discrimination]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:6&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Barriers to Multiculturalism: Ingroup Favoritism and Outgroup Hostility are Independently Associated with Policy Opposition|last=Perry|first=Ryan|last2=Priest|first2=Naomi|date=2017-03-27|last3=Paradies|first3=Yin|last4=Barlow|first4=Fiona|last5=Sibley|first5=Chris G|doi = 10.31219/osf.io/nk334|url = http://osf.io/nk334/}}&lt;/ref&gt; Strong in-group favoritism benefits the dominant groups and is different from out-group hostility and/or punishment.&lt;ref name=&quot;:6&quot; /&gt; A suggested solution is to limit the perceived threat from the out-group that also decreases the likeliness for those supporting the in-groups to negatively react.&lt;ref name=&quot;:6&quot; /&gt;

Ethnocentrism also influences consumer preference over which goods they purchase. A study that used several in-group and out-group orientations have shown a correlation between [[national identity]], consumer cosmopolitanism, [[consumer ethnocentrism]], and the methods consumer choose their products, whether imported or domestic.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Zeugner-Roth|first=Katharina Petra|last2=Žabkar|first2=Vesna|last3=Diamantopoulos|first3=Adamantios|date=2015|title=Consumer Ethnocentrism, National Identity, and Consumer Cosmopolitanism as Drivers of Consumer Behavior: A Social Identity Theory Perspective|journal=Journal of International Marketing|volume=23|issue=2|pages=25–54|doi=10.1509/jim.14.0038}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{col-begin}}{{col-break}}
* [[Afrocentrism]]
* [[Afrophobia]]
* [[American exceptionalism]]
* [[Americentrism]]
* [[Anglo-Saxonism]]
* [[Asiocentrism]]
* [[Barbarian]]
* [[Chosen people]] 
* [[Chronocentrism]]
* [[Collective narcissism]]
* [[Consumer ethnocentrism]]
{{col-break}}
* [[Cross-cultural communication]]
* [[Cultural bias]]
* [[Cultural diversity]]
* [[Cultural racism]]
* [[Cultural relativism]]
* [[Endogamy]]
* [[Ethnic nationalism]]
* [[Ethnic nepotism]]
{{col-break}}
* [[Eurocentrism]]
* [[Hellenocentrism]]
* [[Imperialism]]
* [[Indocentrism]]
* [[In-group–out-group bias]]
* [[Intercultural communication principles]]
* [[Intercultural competence]]
* [[Nationalism]]
* [[Nordicism]]
* [[Pseudospeciation]]
* [[Racism]]
{{col-break}}
* [[Relativism]]
* [[Religiocentrism]]
* [[Sinocentrism]]
* ''[[Sojunghwa]]'' (Korean ethnocentrism)
* [[Stereotype]]
* [[Supremacism]]
* [[Structural violence]]
* [[Tribalism]]
* [[Universalism in geography]]
* [[Xenocentrism]]
{{col-end}}

== References ==
'''Notes'''
{{Reflist}}

'''Further reading'''
* {{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=hzr4-09oo3MC|title=Coexisting Contemporary Civilizations: Arabo-Muslim, Bharati, Chinese, and Western : a Scientific Essay|last=Ankerl|first=Guy|date=2000|publisher=INU PRESS|location=Geneva|isbn=978-2-88155-004-1}}
* {{cite book|title=Us against them: ethnocentric foundations of American opinion|last=Kinder|first=Donald R.|last2=Kam|first2=Cindy D.|date=2009|publisher=University of Chicago Press|location=Chicago|isbn=978-0226435718}}
* {{cite book|title=How to Observe Morals and manners|url=https://archive.org/details/howtoobservemor00martgoog|last=Martineau|first=H.|date=1838|publisher=Charles Knight and Co.|location=London}}
* {{cite book|title=The Sociobiology of Ethnocentrism|editor-last=Reynolds|editor-first=V.|editor-last2=Falger|editor-first2=V.|editor-last3=Vine|editor-first3=I.|date=1987|publisher=[[University of Georgia Press]]|location=Athens, Georgia}}
* {{cite book|title=Risky Transactions. Trust, Kinship, and Ethnicity|editor-last=Salter|editor-first=F. K.|date=2002|publisher=Berghahn|location=Oxford and New York|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NbVQAwAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q=ethnocentrism&amp;f=false|isbn=9781571813190}}
* {{cite book|title=The ethnic phenomenon|last=van den Berghe|first=P. L.|date=1981|publisher=Praeger|location=Westport, Connecticut|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=esAA9Njteu0C&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=snippet&amp;q=ethnocentrism&amp;f=false|isbn=9780275927097}}
* {{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/11/science/11hormone.html|title=The Dark Side of Oxytocin, the Hormone of Love: Ethnocentrism|last=Wade|first=Nicholas|date=2011-01-10|work=The New York Times|access-date=2019-01-19|issn=0362-4331}}

== External links ==
* [http://gpi.sagepub.com/ Group Processes and Intergroup Relations]
* Examples of ethnocentric maps: select [https://persuasivemaps.library.cornell.edu/browse-subject &quot;Ethnocentrism&quot; subject at the Persuasive Cartography, The PJ Mode Collection], Cornell University Library

{{Ethnocentrism}}
{{Ethnicity}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Ethnocentrism| ]]
[[Category:Chauvinism]]
[[Category:Ethnicity]]
[[Category:Sociology of culture]]
[[Category:Words coined in the 1900s]]</text>
      <sha1>7kubprkmm9vlunkxy306z5u5a06rod6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
