  <page>
    <title>Elbląg</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9857</id>
    <restrictions>move=:edit=</restrictions>
    <revision>
      <id>942647964</id>
      <parentid>932740679</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-25T23:43:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Gian piero milanetti</username>
        <id>9324177</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Third Reich */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Place in Warmian-Masurian, Poland}}
{{redirect|Elbing}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=September 2016}}
{{Infobox settlement
| name = Elbląg
| other_name = Elbing
| image_skyline = {{nowrap|&lt;!--
--&gt;[[File:SM Elbląg Kościół św Mikołaja (3) ID 644686.jpg|250px]]&lt;br/&gt;&lt;!--
--&gt;[[File:Buildings in Elblag.JPG|125px]]&lt;!--
--&gt;[[File:Elblag, Clock tower.JPG|125px]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;!--
--&gt;[[File:Elbląg Kanał Elbląski nr 644900 fota 8.JPG|250px]]&lt;br/&gt;&lt;!--
--&gt;}}
| image_caption = {{hlist|Left to right: [[St. Nicholas Cathedral, Elbląg|St. Nicholas Cathedral]]|Elbląg Old Town|Market Gate|[[Elbląg Canal]]}}
| image_flag = POL Elbląg flag.svg
| image_shield = POL Elbląg COA.svg
| pushpin_map = Warmian-Masurian Voivodeship#Poland
| pushpin_label_position = right
| subdivision_type = [[List of sovereign states|Country]]
| subdivision_name = {{POL}}
| subdivision_type1 = [[Voivodeships of Poland|Voivodeship]]
| subdivision_name1 = {{flag|Warmian-Masurian Voivodeship|name=Warmian-Masurian}}
| subdivision_type2 = [[Powiat|County]]
| subdivision_name2 = ''City county''
| leader_party = [[Polish People's Party|PSL]]
| leader_title = Mayor
| leader_name = Witold Wróblewski
| established_title = Established
| established_date = 1237
| established_title3 = City rights
| established_date3 = 1246
| area_total_km2 = 79.82
| population_as_of = 31 December 2018
| population_total = 120,142 {{decrease}} (31st)&lt;ref name=&quot;population&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://bdl.stat.gov.pl/BDL/dane/teryt/jednostka|title=Local Data Bank|accessdate=2 June 2019|publisher=Statistics Poland}} Data for territorial unit 2861000.&lt;/ref&gt;
| population_density_km2 = auto
| timezone = [[Central European Time|CET]]
| utc_offset = +1
| timezone_DST = [[Central European Summer Time|CEST]]
| utc_offset_DST = +2
| coordinates = {{coord|54|10|0|N|19|24|0|E|region:PL|display=inline}}
| postal_code_type = Postal code
| postal_code = 82-300 to 82-315
| area_code = +48 55
| blank_name = [[Vehicle registration plates of Poland|Car plates]]
| blank_info = NE
| blank1_name = [[Köppen climate classification|Climate]]
| blank1_info = [[Humid continental climate#Mild/cool summer subtype|Dfb]]
| website = http://www.elblag.eu}}
'''Elbląg''' ({{IPA-pl|ˈɛlblɔŋk|lang|Pl-Elbląg-2.ogg}}; {{lang-de|Elbing}}; [[Old Prussian language|Old Prussian]]: {{lang|prg|Elbings}}) is a [[city]] in northern [[Poland]] on the eastern edge of the [[Żuławy]] region with 120,142 inhabitants (December 2018).&lt;ref name=&quot;population&quot;&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; It is the capital of [[Elbląg County]] and has been assigned (since 1999) to the [[Warmian-Masurian Voivodeship]]. Previously it was the capital of [[Elbląg Voivodeship]] (1975–1998) and a county seat within [[Gdańsk Voivodeship]] (1945–1975).

Elbląg is one of the oldest cities in the province.&lt;ref name=&quot;premier.gov.pl&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.premier.gov.pl/en/news/news/history-of-elblag.html|title=History of Elbląg|publisher=|accessdate=April 5, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its history dates back to 1237, when the [[Teutonic Order]] constructed their fortified stronghold on the banks of a nearby river. The castle subsequently served as the official seat of the Teutonic Order Masters.

Elbląg became part of the [[Hanseatic League]], which contributed much to the city's wealth. Through the [[Hanseatic League|Hansa agreement]], the city was linked to other major ports like [[Gdańsk]], [[Lübeck]] and [[Amsterdam]]. Elbląg joined Poland in 1454 and after the defeat of the Teutonic Knights in the [[Thirteen Years’ War (1454–1466)|Thirteen Years’ War]] was recognized as part of Poland in the [[Second Peace of Thorn]] in 1466. It then flourished and turned into a significant trading point, but its growth was eventually hindered by the [[Second Northern War]] and the [[Swedish Deluge]].

The city was transferred to [[Prussia]] after the [[first partition of Poland]] in 1772.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.castlesofpoland.com/prusy/elbl_hist_en.htm|title=History of Elblag - Castles of Poland|publisher=|accessdate=April 5, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its trading role greatly weakened, until the era of [[Industrial era|industrialization]], which occurred in the 19th century. It was then that the famous [[Elbląg Canal]] was commissioned.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.toursingdansk.pl/oferty,elblag-canal-tour.html|title=Elblag Ostroda Canal Tour|first=|last=CoolPage.pl|publisher=|accessdate=April 5, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After [[World War II]] the city again became part of Poland. The war casualties were catastrophic, especially the severe destruction of the Old Town district, one of the grandest and most beautiful in [[East Prussia]]. 

Today, Elbląg has over 120,000 inhabitants and is a &quot;vibrant city with an [[Tourism in Poland|attractive tourist base]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;premier.gov.pl&quot;/&gt; It serves as an academic and financial center and among its numerous historic monuments is the Market Gate from 1309 and [[Cathedral of St. Nicholas, Elbląg|St. Nicholas Cathedral]]. Elbląg is also known for its archaeological sites, museums and the [[Elbrewery|largest]] [[brewery]] in the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.staypoland.com/cityHistory.aspx?TownId=16|title=History of Elblag|first=StayPoland Sp. z|last=o.o.|publisher=|accessdate=April 5, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Elbląg Canal]], built in 1825–44 under Prussia, is a tourist site of Elbląg. The canal is believed to be one of the most important monuments related to the history of [[engineering]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.poland.travel/en-us/technological-and-industrial-monuments/the-canal-in-elblag|title=The Canal in Elbląg|publisher=|accessdate=April 5, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; and has been named one of the [[Seven Wonders of Poland]].&lt;ref&gt;{{in lang|pl}} As per results of a plebiscite for the [http://www.budowle.pl/news,153,wyniki-plebiscytu-na-siedem-cudow-polski.html 'Seven Wonders of Poland'] conducted by [[Rzeczpospolita (newspaper)]], cited at www.budowle.pl.&lt;/ref&gt; The canal was also named one of Poland's official national [[List of Historical Monuments (Poland)|Historic Monuments]] (''[[Pomnik historii]]'') in 2011. Its listing is maintained by the [[Narodowy Instytut Dziedzictwa|National Heritage Board of Poland]].

==Etymology==
''Elbląg'' derives from the earlier [[German-language]] ''Elbing'', which is the name by which the [[Teutonic Knights]] knew both the river here and the citadel they established on its banks in 1237. The purpose of the citadel was to prevent the [[Old Prussians|Old Prussian]] settlement of Truso from being reoccupied, the German crusaders being at war with the pagan Prussians. The citadel was named after the river, itself of uncertain etymology. One traditional etymology connects it to the name of the [[Helveconae]], a [[Germanic peoples|Germanic tribe]] mentioned in [[Ancient Greek]] and [[Latin]] sources, but the etymology or language of the [[tribal name]] remains unknown. The oldest known mention of the river or town Elbing is in the form ''Ylfing'' in the report of a sailor Wulfstan from the end of the 9th century, in ''[[Wikisource:Bright's Anglo-Saxon Reader/The Voyages of Ohthere and Wulfstan|The Voyages of Ohthere and Wulfstan]]'' which was written in Anglo-Saxon in [[King Alfred]]'s reign.

== Modern city ==
[[File:Elbląg - Brama Targowa.jpg|thumb|Market Gate, Old City]]
[[File:Elbląg, układ urbanistyczny Starego Miasta.jpg|thumb|upright=1.5|Panorama of the Old City in Elbląg]]

Elbing was almost completely destroyed at the end of [[World War II]]. The city became the Polish Elbląg after the war, when the area was ceded to Poland under border changes promulgated at the [[Potsdam Conference]]. Parts of the inner city were gradually rebuilt, and around 2000 rebuilding was begun in a style emulating the previous architecture, in many cases over the same foundations and utilizing old bricks and portions of the same walls. The western suburbs of the old city have not been reconstructed.

The modern city adjoins about half the length of the river between [[Lake Drużno]] and Elbląg Bay (''Zatoka Elbląska'', an arm of the [[Vistula Lagoon]]), and spreads out on both banks, though mainly on the eastern side. To the east is the Elbląg Upland (''Wysoczyzna Elbląska''), a dome pushed up by glacial compression, 390&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; in diameter and {{convert|200|m|2|abbr=on}} high at its greatest elevation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://academic.emporia.edu/aberjame/ice/lec14/lec14.htm#n_poland REGIONAL GLACIATION OF SOUTHERN &amp; EASTERN BALTIC], Emporia State University Lecture #14, by James S. Aber.&lt;/ref&gt; It gives the appearance of ridges and parkland.

Views to the west show flat fields extending to the horizon; this part of the Vistula Delta (''Żuławy Wiślane'') is used mainly for agricultural purposes. To the south are the marshes and swamps of Drużno. The [[Elbląg River]] has been left in a more natural state through the city, but elsewhere it is a controlled channel with branches. One of them, the Jagiellonski Channel (''Kanał Jagielloński''), leads to the [[Nogat]] River, along which navigation to Gdańsk is common. The [[Elbląg Canal]] (''Kanał Elbląski'') connecting Lake Drużno with [[Drwęca]] River and Lake [[Jeziorak]] is a popular tourist site.

Elbląg is not a deep-water port. The draft of vessels using its waterways must be no greater than {{convert|1.5|m|2|abbr=on}} by law. The turning area at Elbląg is {{convert|120|m|2|abbr=on}} diameter and a pilot is required for large vessels.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.polfracht.pl/polfracht/psal/localinf/elb/portelb1.htm Port Elbląg] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060805113641/http://www.polfracht.pl/polfracht/psal/localinf/elb/portelb1.htm |date=August 5, 2006 }}, site maintained by Polfracht Shipping Agency Ltd.&lt;/ref&gt; Deep water vessels cannot manoeuvre; in that sense, Elbląg has become a subsidiary [[port of Gdańsk]]. Traffic of smaller vessels at Elbląg is within the river and very marginal, while larger vessels cannot reach the open [[Baltic Sea]] because the channel, once built in [[East Prussia|East-Prussia]] to go through the peninsula, has belonged to [[Russia]] since 1945. The city features three quay complexes, movable cranes, and railways.

&lt;gallery caption=&quot;Ancient and recent views of Elbląg&quot;&gt;
File:Elblag Merian 1626.jpg|The Old City of 1626. The view toward Lake Drużno (''{{lang-de|Drausen}}'') in the south
File:Elbląg- miedzioryt z XVIII wieku.jpg|Elbing in 1720 atlas by Pieter van der Aa, based on earlier print by [[Matthäus Merian]] (left picture)
File:Elbląg,_Wigilijna_Street_No_1-5.jpg|Reconstructed buildings in the Old Town
File:6 Elblag 93.jpg| St. Nicholas Church
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== Geographical location ==
Elbląg is located about {{convert|55|km|0|abbr=off}} south-east of [[Gdańsk]] and {{convert|90|km|0|abbr=on}} south-west of [[Kaliningrad]], [[Russia]].
The city is a [[port]] on the river [[Elbląg (river)|Elbląg]], which flows into the [[Vistula Lagoon]] about {{convert|10|km|0|abbr=on}} to the north, thus giving the city access to the [[Baltic Sea]] via the Russian-controlled [[Strait of Baltiysk]]. The Old Town ({{lang-pl|Stare Miasto}}) is located on the river [[Elbląg (river)|Elbląg]] connecting Lake [[Drużno]] to the [[Vistula Lagoon]], about {{convert|10|km|0|abbr=on}} from the lagoon and {{convert|60|km|0|abbr=on}} from Gdańsk.

==History==

===Truso===
[[File:Wieża Katedry w Elblągu przed 1945.jpg|thumb|right|St. Nicholas Cathedral before 1945]]
{{Main|Truso}}
{{Quote box |width=25em |align=left   |bgcolor=#B0C4DE
|title=Historical affiliations
|fontsize=80% |quote={{flagicon image|Teuton-jelvény.png}} [[State of the Teutonic Order|Teutonic Order]] 1246–1454&lt;br&gt;
{{flagicon image|Kingdom of Poland-flag.svg}} [[Kingdom of Poland (1385–1569)|Kingdom of Poland]] 1454–1569&lt;br&gt;
{{flagicon image|Chorągiew królewska króla Zygmunta III Wazy.svg}} [[Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth]] 1569–1772&lt;br&gt;
{{flagicon image|Flag of the Kingdom of Prussia (1803-1892).svg}} [[Kingdom of Prussia]] 1772–1871&lt;br&gt;
{{flagicon image|Flag of the German Empire.svg}} [[German Empire]] 1871–1918&lt;br&gt;
{{flagicon image|Flag of Germany.svg}} [[Weimar Germany]] 1918–1933&lt;br&gt;
{{flagicon image|Flag of the German Reich (1935–1945).svg}} [[Nazi Germany]] 1933–1945 &lt;br&gt;
{{flagicon image|Flag of Poland.svg}} [[People's Republic of Poland]] 1945–1989&lt;br&gt;
{{flag|Republic of Poland|1848}} 1989–present
}}
The settlement was first mentioned as &quot;Ilfing&quot; in ''[[Wikisource:Bright's Anglo-Saxon Reader/The Voyages of Ohthere and Wulfstan|The Voyages of Ohthere and Wulfstan]]'', an [[Old English|Anglo-Saxon]] chronicle written in [[King Alfred]]'s reign using information from a Viking who had visited the area.

During [[Middle Ages|the Middle Ages]], the Viking settlement of [[Truso]] was located on [[Drużno|Lake Drużno]], near the current site of Elbląg in historical [[Pogesania]]; the settlement burned down in the 10th century.&lt;ref&gt;According to the Elbląg museum&lt;/ref&gt; Early in the 13th century the [[Teutonic Knights]] conquered the region, built a castle, and founded Elbing on the lake, with a population mostly from [[Lübeck]] (today the lake, now much smaller, no longer reaches the city). After the uprising against the Teutonic Knights and the destruction of the castle by the inhabitants, the city successively came under the sovereignty of the [[Crown of the Polish Kingdom|Polish crown]] (1454), the [[Kingdom of Prussia]] (1772), and [[Germany]] (1871). Elbing was heavily damaged in [[World War II]], and its German citizens [[Expulsion of Germans after World War II|were expelled]] upon the war's end. The city became part of Poland in 1945 and was repopulated with Polish citizens.

The seaport of '''Truso''' was first mentioned ca. 890 by [[Wulfstan of Hedeby]], an [[Anglo-Saxons|Anglo-Saxon]] sailor, travelling on the south coast of the [[Baltic Sea]] at the behest of King [[Alfred the Great]] of [[England]]. The exact location of Truso was not known for a long time, as the seashore has significantly changed, but most historians trace the settlement inside or near to modern Elbląg on Lake [[Drużno]]. Truso was located at territory already known to the [[Roman Empire]] and earlier.

It was an important seaport serving the [[Vistula River]] bay on the [[Early Middle Ages|early medieval]] Baltic Sea [[trade route]]s which led from [[Birka]] in the north to the island of [[Gotland]] and to [[Visby]] in the Baltic Sea. From there, traders continued further south to [[Carnuntum]] along the [[Amber Road]]. The ancient Amber Road led further southwest and southeast to the [[Black Sea]] and eventually to [[Asia]]. The east-west trade route went from Truso, along the Baltic Sea to [[Jutland]], and from there inland by river to [[Hedeby]], a large trading center in Jutland. The main goods of Truso were [[amber]], furs, and slaves.

Archaeological finds in 1897 and diggings in the 1920s placed Truso at Gut Hansdorf. A large burial field was also found at Elbing. Recent Polish diggings have found burned beams and ashes and thousand-year-old artifacts in an area of about 20 [[hectares]]. Many of these artifacts are now displayed at the [[Elbing Museum|Muzeum w Elblągu]].

=== Prussian Crusade ===
{{Main|Prussian Crusade}}
[[File:Elbląskie kamienice - panoramio.jpg|thumb|right|Reconstructed [[Pseudohistory|pseudo-historical]] [[tenements]] and houses in the Old Town]]
[[File:Gimnazjum nr 5 w Elblągu.jpg|thumb|right|A high school building from the 1920s on Agrykola Street]]
[[File:Elbląg Warszawska 55 willa nr 644843 fota 7.JPG|thumb|right|Brick manors, built in the [[Neogothic]] style, can be seen in the outer suburbs of Elbląg]]

Attempts to conquer Prussian land began in 997, when [[Bolesław I the Brave]], at the urging of the Pope, sent a contingent of soldiers and a missionary ([[Adalbert of Prague]]) to the pagan Prussians, a non-Slavic people, on a crusade of conquest and conversion. The crusade encompassed much of the Baltic Sea coast, including [[Danzig]] (present day Gdańsk), and other areas of the coast up to Sambia. Starting in 1209 additional crusades were called for by [[Konrad I of Masovia|Konrad of Masovia]], who mainly sought to conquer Prussian territory, rather than actually convert the [[indigenous peoples|indigenous]] Prussians. Despite heroic efforts, Old Prussian sovereignty would eventually collapse after a succession of wars instigated by [[Pope Honorius III]] and his frequent calls for crusade.

Before the Prussians and their neighbors to the west, [[Pomeranians (Slavic tribe)|the Pomeranians]], were finally brought to heel, Polish rulers and the [[Duchy of Masovia]], both by then [[Christianity|Christianised]] peoples, would be continually frustrated in their attempts at northern expansion. Aside from minor border raids, major campaigns against the Prussians would be launched in 1219, 1220, and 1222. After a particularly sound defeat by Prussian forces in 1223, Polish forces in [[Chełmno]], the seat of [[Christian of Oliva]] and the [[Masovia|Duchy of Masovia]], were forced onto the defensive.

In 1226 Duke [[Konrad I of Masovia]] summoned the [[Teutonic Knights]] for assistance; by 1230 they had secured [[Chełmno]] (Culm) and begun claiming conquered territories for themselves under the authority of the [[Holy Roman Empire]], although these claims were rejected by the Poles, whose ambition had been to conquer Prussia all along. The Teutonic Order's strategy was to move down the Vistula and secure the delta, establishing a barrier between the Prussians and Danzig. The victorious Teutonic Knights built a castle at Elbing.

The [[Chronicon terrae Prussiae]]&lt;ref&gt;3.14&lt;/ref&gt; describes the conflict in the vicinity of Lake Drusen (now Drużno) shortly before the founding of Elbing:

:″Omnia propugnacula, que habebant in illo loco, qui dicitur (list) ... circa stagnum Drusine ... occisis et captiis infidelibus, potenter expugnavit, et in cinerem redigendo terre alteri coequavit.&quot;

:&quot;All the little redoubts that they had in that place, which are said to be (list) ... and around the Drusine marsh ... he (frater Hermannus magister) assaulted and levelled by rendering them into ash, after the infidels had been killed or captured.&quot;

Truso did not disappear suddenly to be replaced with the citadel and town of Elbing during the Prussian Crusade. It had already burned down in the tenth century, with the population dispersed in the area.

=== Foundation of Elbing ===
The [[Chronicon terrae Prussiae]]&lt;ref&gt;3.15&lt;/ref&gt; describes the founding of Elbing under the leadership of [[Hermann Balk]]. After building two ships, the Pilgerim (Pilgrim) and the Vridelant (Friedland), with the assistance of Margrave [[Henry III, Margrave of Meissen|Henry III]] of [[Margraviate of Meissen]], the Teutonic Knights used them to clear the Vistula Lagoon (''Frisches Haff'') and the [[Vistula Spit]] of Prussians:
:... ''et recens mare purgatum fuit ab insultu infidelium'' ...
:... &quot;and the Vistula Spit was purged of the insult of the infidels...&quot;

Apparently the river was in [[Pomesania]], which the knights had just finished clearing, but the bay was in [[Pogesania]]. The first Elbing was placed in Pogesania:
:''Magister ... venit ad terram Pogesanie, ad insulam illam ... que est in media fluminis Elbingi, in illo loco, ubi Elbingus intrat recens mare et erexit ibi castrum, quod a nomine fluminis Elbingum appellavit, anno dominice incarnacionis MCCXXXVII. Aliqui referunt, quod idem castrum postea ab infidelibus fuerit expugnatum, et tunc ad eum locum, ubi nunc situm est, translatum, et circa ipsum civitas collocata.''&lt;ref&gt;Notes on the passage. [[Medieval Latin]] often used e for ae: Pogesanie for Pogesaniae, que for quae, etc. Recens mare is &quot;the [[fresh water|fresh-water]] sea&quot;. [[Castrum]] is citadel, not yet of brick.&lt;/ref&gt;

:&quot;The master ... came to the region of Pogesania, to that island which is in the middle of the Elbing river, in that place where the Elbing enters the Vistula Lagoon, and built there a fort, which he called by the name of the Elbing River, in the year of the incarnation of the Lord, 1237. Others report that the same fort was attacked by the infidels and then was moved to the place where it is now situated, and the city gathered around it.&quot;

[[File:Elbląg Świętego Ducha 25.JPG|thumb|right|Holy Ghost Street, ''ulica Świętego Ducha'', possesses several pre-war examples of social housing]]

Both landings were amphibious operations conducted from the ships. The ''Chronicon'' relates that they were in use for many years and then were sunk in Lake Drusen. In 1238 the [[Dominican Order]] was invited to build a monastery on a grant of land. Pomesania was not secured, however, and from 1240-1242 the order began building a brick castle on the south side of the settlement. It may be significant that Elbing's first industry was the same as Truso's had been: manufacture of amber and bone artifacts for export. In 1243 [[William of Modena]] created the Diocese of Pomesania and three others. They were at first only ideological constructs, but the tides of time turned them into reality in that same century.

The foundation of Elbing was perhaps not the end of the Old Prussian story in the region. In 1825 a manuscript listing a vocabulary of the [[Baltic languages|Baltic]] [[Old Prussian|Old Prussian language]], named the Elbing-Prussian Dictionary ({{lang-de|Elbing-Preußisches Wörterbuch}}), or more commonly in English just Elbing Vocabulary, was found among some manuscripts from a merchant's house. It contained 802 words in a dialect now termed Pomesanian with their equivalents in an early form of German.

The origin of the vocabulary remains unknown. Its format is like that of modern travel dictionaries; i.e., it may have been used by German speakers to communicate with Old Prussians, but the specific circumstances are only speculative. The manuscript became the Codex Neumannianus. It disappeared after a British [[Strategic bombing|bombing raid]] destroyed the library at Elbing but before then facsimiles had been made. The date of the MSS was estimated at ca. 1400, but it was a copy. There is no evidence concerning the provenance of the original, except that it must have been in Pomesanian.

===Hanseatic Elbing===
[[File:Siegel Elbing 1350.jpg|thumb|right|Seal of the city of Elbing from 1350, ''Sigillum civitatis Elbingensis'']]
In 1246 the town was granted a constitution under [[Lübeck law]], used in maritime circumstances, instead of [[Magdeburg rights]] common in other cities in [[Central Europe]]. This decision of the Order was in keeping with its general strategy of espousing the [[Industry trade group|trade association]] that in 1358 would become the [[Hanseatic League]]. The Order seized on this association early and used it to establish bases throughout the Baltic. The Order's involvement in the League was somewhat contradictory. In whatever cities they founded the ultimate authority was the commander of the town, who kept office in the citadel, typically used as a prison. Lübeck law, on the other hand, provided for self-government of the town.

Membership in the Hanseatic League meant having important trading contacts with [[England]], [[Flanders]], [[France]], and the [[Netherlands]]. The city received numerous merchant privileges from the [[List of the monarchs of the Kingdom of England|rulers of England]], Poland, Pomerania, and the Teutonic Order. For instance, the privilege of the Old Town was upgraded in 1343, while in 1393 it was granted an emporium privilege for grains, metals, and forest products.

Except for the citadel and churches, Elbing at the time was more of a small village by modern standards. Its area was {{convert|300|x|500|m|2|abbr=on|lk=out}}. It featured a wharf, a marketplace and five streets, as well as a number of churches. The castle was completed in 1251. In 1288 fire destroyed the entire settlement except for the churches, which were of brick. A new circuit wall was started immediately. From 1315 to 1340 Elbląg was rebuilt. A separate settlement called New Town was founded ca. 1337 and received [[Lübeck rights]] in 1347. In 1349 the [[Black Death]] struck the town, toward the end of the European plague. After the population recovered it continued building up the city and in 1364 a [[crane (machine)|crane]] was built for the port.

The German-language ''Elbinger Rechtsbuch'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?lr=&amp;as_brr=0&amp;q=%22Elbinger+Rechtsbuch%22&amp;btnG=Search+Books |title=&quot;Elbinger Rechtsbuch&quot; - Google Books |publisher=Books.google.com |accessdate=July 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; written in Elbing, Prussia documented among other laws for the first time Polish common law. The German-language Polish laws are based on the [[Sachsenspiegel]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=8NYNAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA337&amp;dq=elbing+vocabular#PPA337,M1 |title=Archiv für das Studium der neueren ... - Google Books |publisher=Books.google.com |date=September 21, 2007 |accessdate=July 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and were written down to aid the judges. It is thus the oldest source for documented Polish [[common law]] and is in Polish referred to as the ''Księga Elbląska'' (Book of Elbląg&lt;ref&gt;Towarzystwo Naukowe Warszawskie: The Journal of Juristic Papyrology, 1946 [https://books.google.com/books?lr=&amp;as_brr=0&amp;q=%22Book+of+Elbing%22&amp;btnG=Search+Books]&lt;/ref&gt;). It was written down in the second half of the 13th century.

===Kingdom of Poland===
[[File:SM Elbląg Wigilijna3 (0).jpg|thumb|right|Preserved tenements often resemble [[Amsterdam]] and [[Gdańsk]]]]
In 1440 several western and eastern Prussian towns formed the [[Prussian Confederation]], which led the revolt of Prussia against the rule of the Teutonic Knights in 1454. For assistance against the Order, the Confederation asked for help from King [[Casimir IV of Poland]]. The burghers of Elbląg recognized Casimir as rightful ruler. After paying homage to the King, the city was granted great privileges, similar to those of [[Toruń]] and [[Gdańsk]]. Casimir's incorporation of Prussia led to the [[Thirteen Years' War (1454–66)|Thirteen Years' War]].

After the Polish victory over the Teutonic Order, the city became part of the [[Malbork Voivodeship]] in the newly established [[autonomous area|autonomous province]] of [[Royal Prussia]] under the suzerainty of the Polish crown in the [[Second Peace of Thorn (1466)|Second Peace of Thorn]]. The city was known to the Polish crown by its Polish name '''Elbląg'''. With the creation of the [[Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth]] in 1569, the city was brought under direct control of the Polish crown. As one of the largest and most influential cities of Poland, it enjoyed voting rights during the [[Royal elections in Poland|royal election]] period in Poland.&lt;ref&gt;Polska Encyklopedia Szlachecka, t. I, Warsaw 1935, p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt;

With the 16th century [[Protestant Reformation]] the burghers became [[Protestantism|Lutherans]] and the first Lutheran [[Gymnasium (school)|Gymnasium]] was established in Elbląg in 1535.

From 1579 Elbląg had close trade relations with [[England]], to which the city accorded [[free trade]]. English, [[Scotland|Scottish]], and [[Ireland|Irish]] merchants settled in the city. They formed the Scottish Reformed Church of Elbląg and became Elbląg citizens, aiding Lutheran [[Swedish Empire|Sweden]] in the [[Thirty Years' War]]. The rivalry of nearby Danzig interrupted trading links several times. By 1618 Elbląg had left the Hanseatic League owing to its close business dealings with England.

Famous inhabitants of the city at that time included native sons [[Hans von Bodeck]] and [[Samuel Hartlib]]. During the [[Thirty Years' War]], Swedish Chancellor [[Axel Oxenstierna]] brought the [[Moravian Church|Moravian Brethren]] refugee [[John Amos Comenius]] to Elbląg for six years (1642–1648). In 1642 [[Johann Stobäus]], who composed with [[Johann Eccard]], published the '' Preussische Fest-Lieder'', a number of evangelical Prussian songs. In 1646 the city recorder Daniel Barholz noted that the [[city council]] employed ''Bernsteindreher'', or ''Paternostermacher'', licensed and guilded amber craftsmen who worked on [[prayer beads]], [[rosary|rosaries]], and many other items made of amber. Members of the Barholz family became mayors and councillors.

During the [[Thirty Years' War]], the Vistula Lagoon was the main southern Baltic base of King [[Gustavus Adolphus of Sweden]], who was hailed as the protector of the Protestants. By 1660 the Vistula Lagoon had gone to Elector [[Frederick William, Elector of Brandenburg|Frederick William]] of [[Brandenburg|Brandenburg-Prussia]], but was returned in 1700.

The poet [[Christian Wernicke]] was born in 1661 in Elbląg, while [[Gottfried Achenwall]] became famous for his teachings in [[natural law]] and [[International human rights law|human rights law]]. In 1700–1710 it was occupied by Swedish troops. In 1709 it was besieged, taken by storm on February 2, 1710 by Russian troops with support of Prussian artillery. The city was handed over to [[List of Polish monarchs|Polish King]] Augustus II in 1712.

The [[Holy Roman Empire|Imperial]] cartographer [[Johann Friedrich Endersch]] completed a map of [[Warmia]] in 1755 and also made a [[copper]] [[etching]] of the galley named &quot;The City of Elbing&quot; .

During the [[War of the Polish Succession]] in 1734, Elbląg wasplaced under [[military occupation]] by [[Russian Empire|Russia]] and [[Saxony]].&lt;ref&gt;''{{in lang|de}} Book: Merian-Chronik, Cöln 1737/8: Elbingische Geschichte Zu gleicher Zeit Danzigs Belagerung 1734... Ordentliches Tage-Register von den Unternehmungen der Russen und Sachsen by der Belagerung der Stadt Dantzig. Nachricht, Wie viele Personen das 1734te Jahr durch in der Stadt Dantzig getauffet/verehelichet und begraben worden...''&lt;/ref&gt; The town came again under occupation by Russia from 1758-1762 during the [[Seven Years' War]].

===Kingdom of Prussia===
[[File:Cerkiew greko-katolicka ul. Traugutta.JPG|thumb|right|The [[Greek-Catholic]] Church of Elbląg]]
During the [[First Partition of Poland]] in 1772 Elbląg was annexed by King [[Frederick II of Prussia|Frederick the Great]] of the [[Kingdom of Prussia]]. Elbing became part of the new Prussian Province of [[West Prussia]] in 1773. In the 1815 provincial reorganization following the [[Napoleonic Wars]], Elbing and its hinterland were included within [[Regierungsbezirk Danzig]] in West Prussia.

Elbing [[industrialisation|industrialized]] under the sovereignty of the [[House of Hohenzollern|Hohenzollern]] kings in [[Berlin]]. In 1828 the first steamship was built by Ignatz Grunau. In 1837 [[Ferdinand Schichau]] started the [[Schichau-Werke]] company in Elbing as well as another shipyard in Danzig later on. Schichau constructed the ''Borussia'', the first [[Screw ship|screw-vessel]] in Germany. Schichau-Werke built [[hydraulics|hydraulic]] machinery, ships, [[steam engine]]s, and [[torpedo]]es. After the inauguration of the railway to [[Königsberg]] in 1853, Elbing's industry began to grow. Schichau worked together with his son-in-law Carl H. Zise, who continued the industrial complex after Schichau's death. Schichau erected large complexes for his many thousands of workers.

[[Georg Steenke]], an engineer from Königsberg, connected Elbing near the Baltic Sea with the southern part of Prussia by building the Oberländischer Kanal ([[Elbląg Canal]]).

[[File:Elbląg Holy Trinity church Kielecka 24-007.JPG|thumb|right|[[Timber-framed]] Holy Trinity Church]]

Elbing became part of the Prussian-led [[German Empire]] in 1871 during the [[unification of Germany]]. As Elbing became an industrial city, the [[Social Democratic Party of Germany]] (SPD) frequently received the majority of votes; in the 1912 [[Reichstag (German Empire)|Reichstag]] elections the SPD received 51% of the vote. After [[World War I]], most of West Prussia became part of the [[Second Polish Republic]]. Elbing was joined to German [[East Prussia]], and was separated from [[Weimar Republic|Weimar Germany]] by the so-called [[Polish Corridor]].

===Third Reich===
During the Nazi Germany era (1933–1945), three subcamps of the [[Stutthof concentration camp]] were located near the town: ''Elbing'', ''Elbing (Org. Todt)'', and ''Elbing (Schinau)''. These were closed and many of the German inhabitants of Elbing forced to flee as the [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] [[Red Army]] approached the city toward the end of [[World War II]] (see [[Evacuation of East Prussia]]). Laid under siege since January 23, 1945, about 65% of the city infrastructure&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.triposo.com/loc/ElblC485g/history/background|title=Elbląg History|author=|date=|website=www.triposo.com|accessdate=April 17, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; was destroyed, including most of the historical city center. The town was captured by the Soviet Red Army during the night of February 9/10, 1945.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.castlesofpoland.com/prusy/elbl_hist_en.htm|title=History of Elblag - Castles of Poland|website=www.castlesofpoland.com|accessdate=May 28, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the first days of the siege most of the population of approximately 100,000 persons fled. After the end of war, in spring 1945, the region together with the town of Elbing became part of [[People's Republic of Poland|Poland]] as a result of the [[Potsdam Conference]] and the area was settled by Poles after remaining Germans were either [[Expulsion of Germans after World War II|transferred or fled]] to Germany.{{cn|date=June 2019}}

===History after 1945===
The city was repopulated and given the Polish name ''Elbląg''. Elbląg' was part of the so-called [[Recovered Territories]] and out of the new inhabitants, 98% were [[Poles]] expelled from [[Territories of Poland annexed by the Soviet Union|Polish areas annexed by the Soviet Union]] from central Poland. Parts of the damaged historical city center were completely demolished, with the bricks being used to rebuild [[Warsaw]] and [[Gdańsk]]. The [[People's Republic of Poland|Communist authorities]] had originally planned that the Old Town, utterly destroyed during the fighting since January 23, 1945, would be built over with [[Tower block|blocks of flats]]; however, economic difficulties thwarted this effort. Two [[church (building)|churches]] were reconstructed and the remaining ruins of the old town were torn down in the 1960s.

Along with [[Tricity, Poland|Tricity]] and [[Szczecin]], Elbląg was the scene of rioting in the coastal cities in 1970 (see also [[Polish 1970 protests]]). Since 1990 the German minority population has had a modest resurgence, with the Elbinger Deutsche Minderheit Organization counting around 450 members in 2000{{fact|date=April 2019}}.

[[File:Butelki piwa EB.jpg|thumb|200px|right|[[Elbrewery|EB]] - [[Beer in Poland|Polish beer]] produced by the Elbrewery Company in Elbląg]]
Restoration of the Old Town began after 1989. Since the beginning of the restoration, an extensive archaeological programme has been carried out. Most of the city's heritage was destroyed during the construction of basements in the 19th century or during World War II, but the backyards and [[latrine]]s of the houses remained largely unchanged, and have provided information on the city's history. In some instances, private investors have incorporated parts of preserved stonework into new architecture. By 2006, approximately 75% of the Old Town had been reconstructed. The city museum presents many pieces of art and items of everyday use, including the only 15th century [[binoculars]] preserved in Europe.

Elbląg is also home to the [[Elbrewery]], Poland's largest brewery, which belongs to the [[Żywiec Brewery|Żywiec Group]] (Heineken). The history of the Elblag Brewing Tradition dates back to 1309, when Teutonic Master Siegfried von Leuchtwangen granted brewing privileges to the town of Elbing. The present brewery was founded in 1872 as the Elbinger Aktien-Brauerei. In the early 1900s, the brewery was the exclusive supplier of [[Pilsner|Pilsner beer]] to the court of German Emperor [[Wilhelm II]].

==Historic buildings==
Until World War II there were many Gothic, renaissance and baroque houses in Elbląg's Old Town; some of them are reconstructed. Other preserved buildings are:
*[[St. Nicholas Cathedral, Elbląg|St. Nicholas Cathedral]] - a monumental 13th-century Gothic church (cathedral only from 1992, before it was a [[parish church|parochial church]]), destroyed by fire in the late 18th century, then damaged in World War II and repaired
*city gate (''Brama Targowa'') - erected in 1319
*St. Mary's Church - former Dominican church, erected in the 13th century, rebuilt in the 14th and 16th centuries; damaged in World War II and reconstructed in 1961 as an [[art museum|art gallery]]; remnants of cloister are partially preserved
*Holy Ghost church with hospital, from the 14th century
*Corpus Christi church from the 14th century

==Population==
{{Historical populations
|align=none
|1772|11952
|1781|15768
|1831|17761
|1875|33520
|1880|35842
|1885|38278
|1890|41576
|1900|52518
|1910|58636
|1925|67878
|1933|72409
|1939|83190
|1950|48000
|1970|90000
|2011|124257
}}

==Institutions of higher education==

* Elbląg Higher School of Arts and Economics ({{lang-pl|Elbląska Uczelnia Humanistyczno-Ekonomiczna}})&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://euhe.edu.pl/ |title=Elbląska Uczelnia Humanistyczno-Ekonomiczna |publisher=Euhe.edu.pl |accessdate=October 10, 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071217111917/http://www.euhe.edu.pl/ |archivedate=December 17, 2007 |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt;
** Faculty of Pedagogy
** Faculty of Administration
** Faculty of Health Sciences
** Faculty of Economics and Politics
* Elbląg Higher State College of [[Vocational education|Vocational Education]] (''Państwowa Wyższa Szkoła Zawodowa'')&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pwsz.elblag.pl/ |title=Państwowa Wyższa Szkoła Zawodowa w Elblągu :: Studia dzienne bezpłatne :: Strona główna |publisher=Pwsz.elblag.pl |date= |accessdate=October 10, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** Faculty of Pedagogy and Foreign Languages
** Faculty of Economics
** Faculty of Applied Computer Science
** Faculty of Technical Sciences
* Bogdan Jański Higher School, Faculty in Elbląg (''Szkoła Wyższa im. Bogdana Jańskiego'')&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.janski.pl/uczelnia/wydzial.html |title=Studia: Zarządzanie,Socjologia,Pedagogika,Politologia,Gospodarka przestrzenna :: Szkoły Wyższe im. B. Jańskiego |publisher=Janski.pl |date=June 24, 2009 |accessdate=July 25, 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071010151636/http://www.janski.pl/uczelnia/wydzial.html |archivedate=October 10, 2007 |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt;
** Faculty of Management and [[Land management|Land Management]]
* Elbląg Diocese [[Seminary|Theological Seminary]] (''Wyższe Seminarium Duchowne Diecezji Elbląskiej'')&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seminarium.elblag.opoka.org.pl/ |archive-url=https://archive.is/20120912192634/http://www.seminarium.elblag.opoka.org.pl/ |url-status=dead |archive-date=September 12, 2012 |title=WyĹźsze Seminarium Duchowne Diecezji ElblÄ…skiej |publisher=Seminarium.elblag.opoka.org.pl |accessdate=October 10, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Regent College - [[Foreign language|Foreign Language]] [[Teacher education|Teacher Training]] College (''Regent College - Nauczycielskie Kolegium Języków Obcych'')&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.anglistyka.edu.pl/ |title=Regent College - Aktualności |publisher=Anglistyka.edu.pl |date= |accessdate=October 10, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** Faculty of [[English studies|English Studies]]

==Sports==
* [[EB Start Elbląg]] - women's [[Handball in Poland|handball]] team playing in [[Polish Ekstraklasa Women's Handball League]]: 5th place in 2003/2004 season.
* [[Olimpia Elbląg]] - men's football club

==Politics==

===Elbląg constituency===
[[Member of Parliament|Members of Parliament]] ([[Sejm of the Republic of Poland|Sejm]]) elected from Elbląg constituency

* [[Jan Antochowski]], [[Democratic Left Alliance|SLD]]-[[Labour Union (Poland)|UP]]
* [[Danuta Ciborowska]], [[Democratic Left Alliance-Labor Union|SLD-UP]]
* [[Witold Gintowt-Dziewałtowski]], SLD-UP
* [[Stanisław Gorczyca]], [[Civic Platform|PO]]
* [[Jerzy Müller]], SLD-UP
* [[Adam Ołdakowski]], [[Samoobrona]]
* [[Andrzej Umiński]], SLD-UP
* [[Stanisław Żelichowski]], [[Polish People's Party|PSL]]
&lt;!--

===Municipal politics===
to be written yet--&gt;

==International relations==
{{See also|List of twin towns and sister cities in Poland}}

===Twin towns — sister cities===
Elbląg is [[Twin towns and sister cities|twinned]] with:&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.info.elblag.pl/index.php?id=niezbednik_&amp;pid=31&amp;strona=1|title=Elbląg - Podstrony / Miasta partnerskie |accessdate=August 1, 2013 |work=Elbląski Dziennik Internetowy|language=Polish|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110315153700/http://info.elblag.pl/index.php?id=niezbednik_&amp;pid=31&amp;strona=1 |archivedate=March 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings 2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.elblag.net/niezbednik/miasta-partnerskie,65|title=Elbląg - Miasta partnerskie|accessdate=August 1, 2013 |work=Elbląg.net|language=Polish}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|
*{{flagicon|UKR}} [[Ternopil]], Ukraine &lt;small&gt;''(since 1992)''&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
*{{flagicon|GER}} [[Leer]], [[Lower Saxony]], Germany &lt;small&gt;''(since June 23, 2001)''&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
*{{flagicon|RUS}} [[Kaliningrad]], [[Kaliningrad Oblast]], Russia &lt;small&gt;''(since 1994)''&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
*{{flagicon|RUS}} [[Baltiysk]], [[Kaliningrad Oblast]], Russia &lt;small&gt;''(since 1994)''&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
*{{flagicon|SWE}} [[Ronneby]], Sweden &lt;small&gt;''(since 1991)''&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
*{{flagicon|LTU}} [[Druskininkai]], Lithuania &lt;small&gt;''(since 1996)''&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Druskininkai twinnings&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.druskininkai.lt/go.php/Tarptautinis%20bendradarbiavimas889 |title=Tarptautinis Bendradarbiavimas |trans-title=Druskininkai international cooperation |work=Druskininkų savivaldybės administracija |date=March 22, 2012 |language=Lithuanian |accessdate=August 3, 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130803232932/http://www.druskininkai.lt/go.php/Tarptautinis%20bendradarbiavimas889 |archive-date=August 3, 2013 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
*{{flagicon|LVA}} [[Liepāja]], Latvia &lt;small&gt;''(since 1991)''&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
||

*{{flagicon|BLR}} [[Navahradak]], Belarus &lt;small&gt;''(since 1995)''&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
*{{flagicon|FRA}} [[Compiègne]], France &lt;small&gt;''(since 2002)''&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
*{{flagicon|UK}} [[Trowbridge]], West Wiltshire, UK &lt;small&gt;''(since March 31, 2000)''&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Trowbridge twinnings&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Trowbridge - Market town twins with Arab city|date=October 3, 2006 |publisher=BBC News Channel|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/wiltshire/5401592.stm|work=BBC News |accessdate=August 1, 2013 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071021084445/http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/wiltshire/5401592.stm |archivedate=October 21, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
*{{flagicon|CHI}} [[Coquimbo]], Chile &lt;small&gt;''(since 1995)''&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
*{{flagicon|PRC}} [[Baoji]], [[Shaanxi]], People's Republic of China &lt;small&gt;''(since 1997)''&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
*{{flagicon|ROC}} [[Tainan]], Taiwan &lt;small&gt;''(since April 29, 2004)''&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Elbląg twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tianan twinnings&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.tainan.gov.tw/tainan/Intro.asp?nsub=L1A400 |script-title=zh:姊妹市暨友誼市 |work=Tainan City Government |language=Chinese |archiveurl=https://archive.is/20120805172419/http://www.tainan.gov.tw/tainan/Intro.asp?nsub=L1A400 |archivedate=August 5, 2012 |url-status=dead |accessdate=September 22, 2016 |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
*{{flagicon|POL}} [[Nowy Sącz]], Poland&lt;ref name=&quot;Nowy Sącz twinnings&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nowysacz.pl/miasta_partnerskie |title=Miasta partnerskie i zaprzyjaźnione Nowego Sącza |work=Urząd Miasta Nowego Sącza |language=Polish |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130523172036/http://www.nowysacz.pl/miasta_partnerskie |archivedate=May 23, 2013 |accessdate=August 1, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

|}

==Notable residents==
=== Before 1800 ===
* [[List of mayors of Danzig|Georg Kleefeld]] (1522–1576), mayor of Danzig
* [[Hans von Bodeck]] (1582–1658), diplomat and Chancellor of Brandenburg
* [[John Amos Comenius]] (1592–1670), educator
* [[Samuel Hartlib]] (ca. 1600-1662), teacher and scientist
* [[Christian Wernicke]] (1661–1725), epigrammist and diplomat
* [[Charles Aloysius Ramsay]] (1677–1680) Scottish-Prussian writer on stenography and translator 
* [[Johann Friedrich Endersch]] (1705–1769), mathematician geographer
* [[Gottfried Achenwall]] (1719–1772), statistician
* [[Eberhard Gottlieb Graff]] (1780–1841) German philologist.
* [[Wilhelm Baum (surgeon)|Wilhelm Baum]] (1799–1883) a German surgeon 

=== 1800 to 1900 ===
* [[Wilhelm Eduard Albrecht]] (1800–1876), lawyer, member of [[Göttinger Sieben]]
* [[Bruno Erhard Abegg]] (1803–1848), statesman of [[Königsberg]]
* [[Ferdinand Schichau]] (1814–1896), founder of the ''Schichau-Werke'' in Elbing and [[Danzig]]
* [[John Prince-Smith]] (1809–1874), liberal economist and politician in Germany
* [[Johannes Kohtz]] (1843–1918), German chess player
* [[Reinhold Felderhoff]] (1865–1919) German sculptor.
* [[Maximilian Consbruch]] (1866–1927) German West Prussian classical philologist and gymnasium principal 
* [[Hermann Schulz (politician)|Hermann Schulz]] (1872–1929), German politician 
* [[Paul Pulewka]] (1896–1989) German [[pharmacology|pharmacologist]]
* [[Max Reimann]] (1898–1977), president of the [[Communist Party of Germany]]

===1900 to date===
* [[Erich Brost]] (1903–1995) publisher
* [[Günter Kuhnke]] (1912–1990), Admiral
* [[Hans-Dieter Lange]] (1926–2012), journalist
* [[Hans-Jürgen Krupp]] (born 1933) German politician, economist and University professor 
* [[Brigitte Birnbaum]] (born 1938) German author of books, mainly for children and young people
* [[Ursula Karusseit]] (1939–2019), German actress
* [[Bernd Neumann]] (born 1942), German politician
* [[Ortwin Runde]] (born 1944), mayor of [[Hamburg]] from 1997 to 2001.
* [[Andrzej Sakson]] (born 1950), sociologist and director of the [[Western Institute]]
* [[Henryk Iwaniec]] (born 1947), mathematician
* [[Wojciech Cejrowski]] (born 1964), journalist, writer
* [[Adam Fedoruk]] (born 1966), footballer
* [[Ewa Białołęcka]] (born 1967), [[fantasy|fantasy writer]]
* [[Piotr Wadecki]] (born 1973), cyclist
* [[Maciej Bykowski]] (born 1977), footballer
* [[Adam Wadecki]] (born 1977), cyclist
* [[Dominika Figurska]] (born 1978), actress
* [[Radosław Wojtaszek]] (born 1987), [[chess grandmaster]]
* [[Krzysztof Jotko]] (born 1989), [[MMA]] fighter
==See also==
* [[Elbrewery|EB]] - [[Beer in Poland|Polish beer]] produced by the Elbrewery Company
* [[List of cities and towns in East Prussia]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons|Elbląg}}
{{Wikivoyage}}

=== Government websites ===
* [http://www.umelblag.pl/ Municipal website]
* [http://www.gminaelblag.pl/ Gmina of Elbląg] {{in lang|pl}}
* [http://www.powiat.elblag.pl/ Elbląg County] {{in lang|pl}}

=== Tourism and historical sites ===
* [http://www.castlesofpoland.com/prusy/elblag_en.htm CastlesOfPoland.com]
*[http://www.domwarminski.pl/images/stories/warmia_regionem/mapy_historyczne_tabula_geografica_w.jpg Map of Warmia with Elbing from 1755]
* [http://plan.elblag.com.pl/ Interactive map of Elbląg] {{in lang|pl}}
* [http://www.it.elblag.com.pl/index.php?new_lang=en Tourism information]
* [http://donelaitis.vdu.lt/prussian/Elbin.pdf Elbing Vocabulary], presentation by Dr. Letis Palmaitis

=== Web portals ===
* [http://www.elblag.pl/ Wirtualny Elbląg - portal] {{in lang|pl}}
* [http://www.portel.pl/ Elbląska Gazeta Internetowa - portal] {{in lang|pl}}
* [http://www.elblag24.pl/ Elblag24 - portal] {{in lang|pl}}
* [http://info.elblag.pl/ info.elblag.pl - portal] {{in lang|pl}}
* [http://www.nocnyelblag.pl/ Nocny Elbląg - portal] {{in lang|pl}}
* [http://www.wm.pl/index.php?ct=elblag Dziennik Elbląski newspaper] {{in lang|pl}}
* [http://www.elbing.org/dfkelbing/index.html/ Die Elbing Seite- Deutsche Minderheit- portal] {{in lang|de}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20130921002704/http://www.many-roads.com/photo-galleries/kreis-elbing-u-westpreussen/ Elbing Damals- Elbing as it was before the war] 
* [http://www.many-roads.com/libraries/prussia-histories/ Extensive East &amp; West Prussian Historical Materials] {{in lang|en|de}}
{{Navboxes
|title= Articles related to Elbląg
|list=
{{Hanseatic League}}
{{Baltic emporia}}
{{Warmian-Masurian Voivodeship|state=autocollapse}}
{{Elbląg County|state=autocollapse}}
{{Gmina Elbląg|state=autocollapse}}
{{Principal cities of Poland}}
}}
{{Coord|54|10|N|19|24|E|display=title}}


{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Elblag}}
[[Category:Elbląg| ]]
[[Category:City counties of Poland]]
[[Category:Cities and towns in Warmian-Masurian Voivodeship]]
[[Category:Free imperial cities]]
[[Category:Members of the Hanseatic League]]
[[Category:Cities with powiat rights]]</text>
      <sha1>cv300ulhmjd37016ve5y3sahz5drm7y</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
