  <page>
    <title>Ezra</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9839</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938024155</id>
      <parentid>928911011</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-28T17:50:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JCW-CleanerBot</username>
        <id>31737083</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[User:JCW-CleanerBot#Logic|task]], replaced: Revue Benedictine → Revue Bénédictine</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
[[File:109.Ezra Reads the Law to the People.jpg|thumb|''Ezra Reads the Law to the People'', one of [[Gustave Doré's illustrations for La Grande Bible de Tours|Gustave Doré's illustrations for ''La Grande Bible de Tours'']]]]

'''Ezra''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|ɛ|z|r|ə}}; {{lang-he-n|עזרא}}, ''{{transl|he|‘Ezrā}}'';&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[God] helps&quot; – [[Emil G. Hirsch]], [[Isaac Broydé]], &quot;[http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=578&amp;letter=E Ezra the Scribe]&quot;, ''[[Jewish Encyclopedia]]'' (Online)&lt;/ref&gt; fl. 480–440 BCE), also called '''Ezra the Scribe''' ({{Hebrew|עזרא הסופר}}, ''{{transl|he|Ezra ha-Sofer}}'') and '''Ezra the Priest''' in the [[Book of Ezra]], was a Jewish scribe (''[[sofer]]'') and priest (''[[kohen]]''). In [[Ancient Greek|Greco]]-[[Latin]] Ezra is called [[Esdras]]  ({{lang-grc-gre|Ἔσδρας}}). According to the Hebrew Bible he was a descendant of Sraya ({{bibleverse||Ezra|7:1|NIV}})&lt;ref&gt;In Ezra he is described as the son of Seraya.&lt;/ref&gt; the last [[High Priest]] to serve in the [[First Temple]] ({{bibleverse|2|Kings|25:18|NIV}}), and a close relative of [[Joshua the High Priest|Joshua the first High Priest]] of the [[Second Temple]] ([[Ezra 3:2]]). He returned from [[Babylonian exile]] and reintroduced the [[Torah]] in Jerusalem ({{bibleverse||Ezra|7–10|NIV}} and {{bibleverse||Neh|8|NIV}}). According to [[1 Esdras]], a Greek translation of the Book of Ezra still in use in [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Eastern Orthodoxy]], he was also a High Priest. Rabbinic tradition holds that he was an ordinary member of the priesthood.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ezra&quot; group=&gt;{{cite web|title=1901 The Jewish Encyclopedia Complete vol. 5 |page=231|url=https://archive.org/details/1901TheJewishEncyclopediaIAachApocalypticLiterature_201605|website=Internet Archive|accessdate=15 May 2017|language=English}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several traditions have developed over his place of burial. One tradition says that he is buried in al-Uzayr near [[Basra]] (Iraq), while another tradition alleges that he is buried in [[Tedef|Tadif]] near [[Aleppo]], in northern Syria.&lt;ref&gt;Tawil, Hayim &amp; Schneider, Bernard 2010, ''Crown of Aleppo: The Mystery of the Oldest Hebrew Bible Codex'', Philadelphia, Jewish Publication Society 2010, p. 63 {{ISBN|9780827608955}}; Laniado, David, ''Li-Qedošim ašer ba-areṣ'', Jerusalem 1980, p. 26 (Hebrew); Frenkel, Miriam, article: ''Atare pulḥan yehudiyyim be-ḥalab bi-yme ha-benayim ha-tikhoniyyim'', published in: ''Harel'' ({{Hebrew|הראל}}), Yaron, Assis, Yom Ṭov &amp; Frenkel, Miriam (eds.), ''Ereṣ u-mlo’ah: meḥqarim be-toledot qehillat aram ṣova'' (''ḥalab'') ''ve-tarbutah'', vol. I, Ben-Zvi Institute: Jerusalem 2009, pp. 174–75 (Hebrew); Khatib, Muḥammad Zuhair, ''Rabṭ al-Sabāba al-yamanī''.&lt;/ref&gt;

His name may be an abbreviation of {{Hebrew|עזריהו}} ''{{transl|he|Azaryahu}}'', &quot;[[Jah|Yah]] helps&quot;. In the Greek [[Septuagint]] the name is rendered ''{{transl|grc|Ésdrās}}'' ({{lang|grc|{{linktext|Ἔσδρας}}}}), from which the Latin name {{lang|la|Esdras}} comes.

The [[Book of Ezra]] describes how he led a group of [[Babylonian captivity|Judean exiles]] living in [[Babylon]] to their home city of [[Jerusalem]] ({{bibleverse||Ezra|8.2–14|NIV}}) where he is said to have enforced observance of the Torah. He was described as exhorting the Israelite people to be sure to follow the Torah Law so as not to intermarry with people of particular different religions, a set of commandments described in the [[Pentateuch]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BrillPauly&quot;&gt;Liwak, Rüdiger; Schwemer, Anna Maria. &quot;Ezra&quot;. Brill's New Pauly.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;&gt;&quot;Ezra&quot;. [[Encyclopædia Britannica]]. 2007. ''Encyclopædia Britannica Online''
&lt;/ref&gt;

Ezra, known as &quot;Ezra the scribe&quot; in [[Chazal]]ic literature,&lt;ref&gt;[[Edward Kessler]], Neil Wenborn, ''A Dictionary of Jewish-Christian Relations'', [[Cambridge University Press]], p. 398&lt;/ref&gt; is a highly respected figure in [[Judaism]].&lt;ref&gt;''The New Encyclopedia of Judaism'', &quot;Ezra&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==In the Hebrew Bible==
The canonical [[Book of Ezra]] and [[Book of Nehemiah]] are the oldest sources for the activity of Ezra,&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;/&gt; whereas many of the other books ascribed to Ezra (First Esdras, 3–6 Ezra) are later literary works dependent on the canonical books of Ezra and Nehemiah.

The book of [[Ezra–Nehemiah]] was always written as one scroll.&lt;ref&gt;[[Hugh G. M. Williamson]], ''Ezra, Nehemiah'', Word Biblical Commentary Vol. 16 (Dallas:Word, 1985), pp. xxi–lii.&lt;/ref&gt; In late medieval Christian bibles, the single book was divided in two, as First and Second Ezra; and this division became Jewish practice in the first printed Hebrew bibles.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|volume=110|pages=5–26|last=Bogaert|first=Pierre-Maurice|title=Les livres d’Esdras et leur numérotation dans l’histoire du canon de la Bible latin|journal=Revue Bénédictine|date=2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Modern Hebrew Bibles call the two books Ezra and Nehemiah, as do other modern Bible translations. A few parts of the Book of Ezra (4:8 to 6:18 and 7:12–26) were written in [[Aramaic]], and the majority in [[Hebrew]], Ezra himself being skilled in both languages.&lt;ref&gt;James H. Charlesworth – [http://www.ijco.org/?categoryId=28681 &quot;Announcing a Dead Sea Scrolls Fragment of Nehemiah&quot;] – ''The Institute for Judaism and Christian Origins'' – Retrieved 20 August 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Ezra was living in Babylon when in the seventh year of [[Artaxerxes I of Persia|Artaxerxes I]], king of Persia (c. 457 BCE), the king sent him to Jerusalem to teach the laws of God to any who did not know them. Ezra led a large body of exiles back to Jerusalem, where he discovered that Jewish men had been marrying non-Jewish women. He tore his garments in despair and confessed the sins of Israel before God, then braved the opposition of some of his own countrymen to purify the community by enforcing the dissolution of the sinful marriages. Some years later Artaxerxes sent Nehemiah (a Jewish noble in his personal service) to Jerusalem as governor with the task of rebuilding the city walls. Once this task was completed Nehemiah had Ezra read the Law of Moses (the [[Torah]]) to the assembled Israelites, and the people and priests entered into a covenant to keep the law and separate themselves from all other peoples.

==In later Second Temple period literature==

===1 Esdras===
[[1 Esdras]], probably from the late 2nd/early 1st centuries BCE, preserves a [[Ancient Greek|Greek]] text of Ezra and a part of Nehemiah distinctly different from that of Ezra–Nehemiah – in particular it eliminates Nehemiah from the story and gives some of his deeds to Ezra, as well as telling events in a different order. Scholars are divided on whether it is based on Ezra–Nehemiah, or reflects an earlier literary stage before the combination of Ezra and Nehemiah accounts.

===Josephus===
The first-century Jewish historian [[Josephus]] deals with Ezra in his ''[[Antiquities of the Jews]]''. He uses the name Xerxes for Artaxerxes I reserving the name Artaxerxes for the later Artaxerxes II whom he identifies as the Ahasuerus of Esther, thus placing Ezra before the events of the book of Esther.  Josephus's account of the deeds of Ezra derives  entirely from [[1 Esdras]], which he cites as the 'Book of Ezra' in his numeration of the Hebrew bible.  Contrariwise, Josephus does not appear to recognise Ezra-Nehemiah as a biblical book, does not quote from it, and relies entirely on other traditions in his account of the deeds of [[Nehemiah]].

===The apocalyptic Ezra traditions===
The [[apocalypse|apocalyptic]] [[2 Esdras|fourth book of Ezra]] (also sometimes called the 'second book of Esdras' or the 'third book of Esdras') was written c. CE 100, probably in [[Judeo-Aramaic language|Hebrew-Aramaic]], but now survives in Latin, Slavonic and Ethiopic. It was one of the most important sources for [[Jewish philosophy|Jewish theology]] at the end of the 1st century.{{citation needed|date=June 2019}} In this book, Ezra has a seven part prophetic revelation, converses with an [[angel]] of God three times and has four visions. Ezra, thirty years into the Babylonian Exile (4 Ezra 3:1 / 2 Esdras 1:1), recounts the [[Siege of Jerusalem (587 BC)|siege of Jerusalem]] and the destruction of [[Solomon's Temple]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BrillPauly&quot;/&gt; This would place these revelations in the year 557 BCE, a full century before the date given in the canonical Ezra. The central theological themes are &quot;the question of theodicy, God's justness in the face of the triumph of the heathens over the pious, the course of world history in terms of the teaching of the four kingdoms,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Daniel|2:1|HE}}, {{bibleverse||Daniel|7:1|HE}}, {{bibleverse||Daniel|8:1|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt; the function of the law, the eschatological judgment, the appearance on Earth of the heavenly Jerusalem, the [[Messianic Age|Messianic Period]], at the end of which the [[Messiah]] will die,&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.today/20120712081932/http://etext.virginia.edu/etcbin/toccer-new2?id=Kjv4Ezr.sgm&amp;images=images/modeng&amp;data=/texts/english/modeng/parsed&amp;tag=public&amp;part=7&amp;division=div2 4 Ezra (Apocrypha), chapter 7, verse 29]&lt;/ref&gt; the end of this world and the coming of the next, and [[Last Judgment|the Last Judgment]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;BrillPauly&quot; /&gt; Ezra restores the law that was destroyed with the burning of the [[Temple in Jerusalem]]. He dictates 24 books for the public (i.e. the Hebrew Bible) and another 70 for the wise alone (70 unnamed revelatory works).&lt;ref name=&quot;cox&quot;&gt;Howard H. Cox, ''The Pentateuch: History Or Story?'', p. 101&lt;/ref&gt; At the end, he is taken up to [[heaven]] like Enoch and [[Elijah]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BrillPauly&quot;/&gt; Ezra is seen as a new Moses in this book.&lt;ref name=&quot;BrillPauly&quot;/&gt;

There is also another work, thought to be influenced by this one, known as the ''[[Greek Apocalypse of Ezra]]''.

==Ezra in rabbinic literature==
{{further|Ezra in rabbinic literature}}
[[File:Schnorr von Carolsfeld Bibel in Bildern 1860 125.png|thumb|The return from exile is depicted in this woodcut for ''Die Bibel in Bildern'', 1860, by [[Julius Schnorr von Carolsfeld]].]]
Traditionally Judaism credits Ezra with establishing the [[Great Assembly]] of scholars and prophets, the forerunner of the [[Sanhedrin]], as the authority on matters of religious law. The Great Assembly is credited with establishing numerous features of contemporary traditional Judaism in something like their present form, including [[Torah reading]], the [[Amidah]], and celebration of the feast of [[Purim]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish Encyclopedia&quot;&gt;[[Emil G. Hirsch]], [[Isaac Broydé]], &quot;[http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=578&amp;letter=E Ezra the Scribe]&quot;, ''[[Jewish Encyclopedia]]'' (Online)&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Rabbinic literature|Rabbinic]] traditions, Ezra is metaphorically referred to as the &quot;flowers that appear on the earth&quot; signifying the springtime in the national [[Jewish history|history of Judaism]] {{Citation needed|date=August 2019}}. A disciple of [[Baruch ben Neriah]], he favored study of the Law over the [[Second Temple of Jerusalem|reconstruction of the Temple]] {{Citation needed|date=August 2019}} and thus because of his studies, he did not join the first party returning to Jerusalem in the reign of [[Cyrus the Great|Cyrus]]. According to another opinion, he did not join the first party so as not to compete, even involuntarily, with [[Joshua the High Priest|Jeshua ben Jozadak]] for the office of chief priest.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish Encyclopedia&quot;/&gt;

According to Jewish tradition, Ezra was the writer of the [[Books of Chronicles]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish Encyclopedia&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Babylonian Talmud (''Baba Bathra'' 15a)&lt;/ref&gt; and is the same prophet known also as Malachi.&lt;ref&gt;Introduction to the Aramaic [[Targum]] of [[Jonathan ben Uzziel|Yonathan ben Uzziel]] on the Prophet [[Malachi]] (Minor Prophets); Yehoshua b. Ḳarḥa (''Megillah'' 15a) .&lt;/ref&gt; There is a slight controversy within rabbinic sources as to whether or not Ezra had served as [[Kohen Gadol]].&lt;ref&gt;HaQoton, Reb Chaim [http://rchaimqoton.blogspot.co.il/2013/07/was-ezra-high-priest.html &quot;Was Ezra a High Priest&quot;] also printed in the [[Jewish Bible Quarterly]] (July 2013); see also [http://jbq.jewishbible.org/41-3-july-september-201/]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the [[Babylonian Talmud]], Ezra the scribe is said to have enacted ten standing laws and orders,&lt;ref&gt;Babylonian Talmud (''Baba Kama'' 82a); Jerusalem Talmud (''Megillah'' 29a-b)&lt;/ref&gt; which are as follows: 1) That the public come together to read from the [[Torah|scroll of the Law]] on Sabbath days during the time of the afternoon oblation ([[Minchah]]), because of those travelling merchants who loiter in the closed shops in the street corners, and who may have missed the biblical lections that were read during the weekdays;&lt;ref&gt;[[Maimonides]], [[Mishne Torah]] (''Hilchot Tefillah'' 12:1)&lt;/ref&gt; 2) that the [[Beth din|courts]] be opened throughout the Jewish townships on Mondays and Thursdays; 3) that women do not wait beyond Thursday to launder their clothes, because of the honor due to the Sabbath day; 4) that men would accustom themselves to eat [cooked] garlic on the eve of the Sabbath (believed to enhance love between a man and his wife); 5) that women would rise up early on Friday mornings to bake bread, so that a piece of bread will be available for the poor; 6) that Jewish women in every place be girded with a wide belt (waist band), whether from the front or from behind, out of modesty; 7) that Jewish women, during their menses, wash and comb their hair three days prior to their purification in a ritual bath; 8) that the travelling merchants make regular rounds into the Jewish townships because of the honor due to the daughters of Israel; 9) that Jewish women and/or girls, as a precautionary measure, be accustomed to conversing with one another while one of their party goes out to relieve herself in the outhouse; 10) that men who may have suffered a seminal emission (especially after accompanying with their wives) be required to immerse themselves in a [[Mikveh|ritual bath]] before being permitted to read from the scroll of the Law.

In the Syrian village of [[Tedef]], a synagogue said to be the place where Ezra stopped over has been venerated by Jews for centuries. Another tradition locates his tomb near Basra, Iraq.

==Ezra in Christian traditions==
Early Christian writers occasionally cited Ezra as author of the apocalyptic books attributed to him. [[Clement of Alexandria]] in his ''[[Stromata]]'' referred to Ezra as an example of prophetic inspiration, quoting a section from [[2 Esdras]]. Where early Christian writers refer to the 'Book of Ezra' it is always the text of [[1 Esdras]] that is being cited.  No early Christian writer cites the [[Book of Ezra]] as a record of the deeds of Ezra &lt;ref&gt;The Apocryphal Apocalypse: the reception of the second book of Esdras Alastair Hamilton – 1999 p. 22 &quot;that were part of the canon.13 Although Clement of Alexandria, who was writing in the late second and early third century, showed more interest in 1 Esdras, he cited 2 Esdras in his Stromata, referring to Esdras as an example of prophetic inspiration...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ezra in Islam==
{{main|Uzair}}
In Islam he is known as [[Uzair]] ({{lang|ar|عُزَيْر}}). He was mentioned in the [[Qur'an]]. Although he was not mentioned as one of the [[Prophets of Islam]], he is considered as one of them by some [[Muslim]] scholars, based on [[Islam]]ic traditions.&lt;ref name=&quot;shahid&quot;&gt;But the Qur'an 9:30 quotes Jews as saying that he is the &quot;son of God&quot; {{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=5GiZqe3tI1gC&amp;pg=PP1&amp;dq=Encyclopaedia+of+Holy+Prophet+and+Companions|title=Encyclopaedia of Holy Prophet and Companions|last=Ashraf|first=Shahid|publisher=Anmol Publications Pvt. Ltd.|year=2005|isbn=978-81-261-1940-0|location=[[Daryaganj]], [[New Delhi]]|pages=199–200|chapter=Prophets ’Uzair, Zakariya and Yahya|format=[[Google Books]]|via=|accessdate=20 November 2007|chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=2UqxApJT4JAC&amp;pg=PA199&amp;dq=uzair+was+a+prophet&amp;as_brr=3&amp;ei=RJ4qR8eBN5nKiQGl3py1DA&amp;ie=ISO-8859-1&amp;sig=z2JJi_4OVbBJcni08qyCMP5wu2I}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;kathir&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.islambasics.com/view.php?bkID=80&amp;chapter=12|title='Uzair (Ezra)|last=|first=|authorlink=Ibn Kathir|date=|publisher=Islambasics.com|others=Ali As-Sayed Al-Halawani (trans)|access-date=|accessdate=21 November 2007|author=Ibn Kathir|website=Stories Of The Quran}}
&lt;/ref&gt; His tomb at [[Ezra's Tomb|Al-ʻUzair]] on the banks of the [[Tigris]] near [[Basra]], [[Iraq]], is a pilgrimage site for the local [[Marsh Arabs]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://memrieconomicblog.org/bin/content.cgi?article=15# Environmental and Cultural Terrorism – The Destruction of Iraqi Marshes and Their Revival: Some Personal Reflections]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.jameswbell.com/a012ezrastomb.html |title=Ezra's Tomb |access-date=15 March 2010 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100402070013/http://www.jameswbell.com/a012ezrastomb.html |archive-date=2 April 2010 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Many Islamic scholars and modern Western academics do not view Uzair as &quot;Ezra&quot;; for example Professor Gordon Darnell Newby associates Uzair with Enoch and [[Metatron]]. On this [[Timothy Winter]] (Abdal Hakim Murad) and Gordon Darnell Newby [http://www.js.emory.edu/faculty/newby.htm] associate Uzair again with [[Enoch (ancestor of Noah)]] and by extension [[Metatron]] the creator-angel.[http://www.marquette.edu/maqom/metatronyhwh.html].

== Academic view ==

=== Timeline ===
Scholars are divided over the chronological sequence of the activities of Ezra and Nehemiah. Ezra came to Jerusalem &quot;in the seventh year of Artaxerxes the King&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Ezra|7:7|131}}&lt;/ref&gt; The text does not specify whether the king in the passage refers to Artaxerxes I (465–424 BCE) or to [[Artaxerxes II of Persia|Artaxerxes II]] (404–359 BCE).&lt;ref name=&quot;igb&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Illustrated Guide to the Bible|last=Porter|first=J.R. |year= 2000|publisher=Barnes &amp; Noble Books|location=New York|isbn=978-0-7607-2278-7  |pages=115–16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The dates of Nehemiah's and Ezra's respective missions, and their chronological relation to each other, are uncertain, because each mission is dated solely by a regnal year of an [[Achaemenid Empire|Achaemenian]] King Artaxerxes; and in either case we do not know for certain whether the [[Artaxerxes I of Persia|Artaxerxes]] in question is Artaxerxes I (465–424 BCE) or [[Artaxerxes II of Persia|Artaxerxes II]] (404–359 BCE). So we do not know whether the date of Ezra's mission was 458 BCE or 397 BCE' [[Arnold Toynbee]], ''A Study of History'', vol. 12 (1961) [[Oxford University Press]], 1964 pp. 484–85 n.2&lt;/ref&gt; Most scholars hold that Ezra lived during the rule of Artaxerxes I, though some have difficulties with this assumption:&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;/&gt; Nehemiah and Ezra &quot;seem to have no knowledge of each other; their missions do not overlap&quot;, however, in Nehemiah 12, both are leading processions on the wall as part of the wall dedication ceremony.  So, they clearly were contemporaries working together in Jerusalem at the time the wall and the city of Jerusalem was rebuilt in contrast to the previously stated viewpoint.;.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;MaryJ2&quot;&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Winn Leith
 | first = Mary Joan
 | editor = Michael David Coogan
 | title = The Oxford History of the Biblical World
 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=zFhvECwNQD0C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=The+Oxford+History+of+the+Biblical+World
 | format = [[Google Books]]
 | accessdate =13 December 2007
 | origyear = 1998
 | year = 2001
 | publisher = [[Oxford University Press]]
 | location = [[Oxford]]; [[New York City|New York]]
 | isbn = 978-0-19-513937-2
 | oclc = 44650958
 | pages = 281
 | chapter = Israel among the Nations: The Persian Period
 | chapterurl = https://books.google.com/books?id=zFhvECwNQD0C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=The+Oxford+History+of+the+Biblical+World&amp;ei=v-FhR-q_MJKIiQGU-eCIBw&amp;sig=09eixie3bqkoalqx66xDGO9GBqI#PRA2-PA281,M1
 | lccn = 98016042
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;  These difficulties have led many scholars to assume that Ezra arrived in the seventh year of the rule of Artaxerxes II, i.e. some 50 years after Nehemiah. This assumption would imply that the biblical account is not chronological. The last group of scholars regard &quot;the seventh year&quot; as a scribal error and hold that the two men were contemporaries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;John Boederman, ''The Cambridge Ancient History'', 2002, p. 272&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Historicity ===
[[File:Tomb of Ezra.jpg|thumb|Site traditionally described as the [[Ezra's Tomb|tomb of Ezra]] at Al-Uzayr near [[Basra]], Iraq.]]
Mary Joan Winn Leith in ''The Oxford History of the Biblical World'' believes that Ezra was a historical figure whose life was enhanced in the scripture and given a theological buildup.&lt;ref name=&quot;MaryJ1&quot;&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Winn Leith
 | first = Mary Joan
 | editor = Michael David Coogan
 | title = The Oxford History of the Biblical World
 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=zFhvECwNQD0C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=The+Oxford+History+of+the+Biblical+World
 | format = [[Google Books]]
 | accessdate =13 December 2007
 | origyear = 1998
 | year = 2001
 | publisher = [[Oxford University Press]]
 | location = [[Oxford]]; [[New York City|New York]]
 | isbn = 978-0-19-513937-2
 | oclc = 44650958
 | pages = 306
 | chapter = Israel among the Nations: The Persian Period
 | chapterurl = https://books.google.com/books?id=zFhvECwNQD0C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=The+Oxford+History+of+the+Biblical+World&amp;ei=v-FhR-q_MJKIiQGU-eCIBw&amp;sig=09eixie3bqkoalqx66xDGO9GBqI#PRA2-PA306,M1
 | lccn = 98016042
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Gosta W. Ahlstrom argues the inconsistencies of the [[Bible|biblical]] tradition are insufficient to say that Ezra, with his central position as the 'father of Judaism' in the Jewish tradition, has been a later literary invention.&lt;ref&gt;Gosta W. Ahlstrom, ''The History of Ancient Palestine'', Fortress Press, p. 888&lt;/ref&gt; Those who argue against the historicity of Ezra argue that the presentation style of Ezra as a leader and lawgiver resembles that of Moses. There are also similarities between Ezra the priest-scribe (but not [[Kohen Gadol|high priest]]) and Nehemiah the secular governor on the one hand and Joshua and [[Zerubbabel]] on the other hand. The early 2nd-century BCE Jewish author [[Ben Sira]] praises Nehemiah, but makes no mention of Ezra.&lt;ref name=&quot;MaryJ1&quot;/&gt;

[[Richard Elliott Friedman|Richard Friedman]] argued in his book ''Who Wrote the Bible?'' (p.&amp;nbsp;232 1997 edition) that Ezra is the one who redacted the Torah, and in fact effectively produced the first Torah.&lt;ref&gt;''Who Wrote the Bible?'' (Harper San Francisco) (1987, new preface 1997) {{ISBN|978-0060630355}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has been argued that even if one does not accept the documentary hypothesis, Ezra was instrumental in the start of the process of bringing the Torah together.&lt;ref&gt;The Canonization of the Pentateuch: When and Why? (Part I)* Alexander Fantalkin/Oren Tal p.4 http://archaeology.tau.ac.il/arch_files/directory/zaw124-1-2_fantalkin-tal.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Esdras]] – about the classification of the books ascribed to Ezra
*[[Book of Ezra]] and [[Book of Nehemiah]] – the non-rabbinical tradition
*[[Ezra–Nehemiah]] – the combination of the above two books
*[[1 Esdras]] and [[2 Esdras]] – the Greek version of the texts (Meir)

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite journal|last=Bossman|first=D.|title=Ezra's Marriage Reform: Israel Redefined|journal=Biblical Theology Bulletin|year=1979|volume=9|pages=32–38|doi=10.1177/014610797900900105}}
*{{cite book|last=Bright|first=John|title=A history of Israel|year=1981|publisher=Westminster Press|location=Philadelphia|isbn=978-0-664-21381-7|edition=3rd}}
*{{cite book|last=Fensham|first=F. Charles|title=The books of Ezra and Nehemiah|year=1983|publisher=W.B. Eerdmans Publishing Company|location=Grand Rapids, MI|isbn=978-0-8028-2362-5}}
*{{cite book|last1=LaSor|first1=William Sanford|last2=Hubbard |first2=David Allan |last3=Bush|first3=Frederick William|title=Old Testament survey|year=1982|publisher=Eerdmans|location=Grand Rapids, Mich.|isbn=978-0-8028-3556-7}}
*{{cite book|last=Williamson|first=H.G.M.|title=Ezra and Nehemiah|year=1987|publisher=JSOT for the Society for Old Testament Study|location=Sheffield|isbn=978-1-85075-045-1}}

== External links ==
{{wikiquote}}
{{Commons category|Ezra}}
* [http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=578&amp;letter=E&amp;search=Ezra Jewish Encyclopedia: Ezra the Scribe]
* [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/05535a.htm Catholic Encyclopedia: Esdras]
* {{Cite EB1911|wstitle=Ezra|short=x}}

{{Muslim saints}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Hebrew Bible people]]
[[Category:Jewish scribes (soferim)]]
[[Category:Jewish priests]]
[[Category:Christian saints from the Old Testament]]
[[Category:Prophets of Islam]]
[[Category:Ezra–Nehemiah]]
[[Category:Ancient Near Eastern scribes]]
[[Category:Angelic visionaries]]
[[Category:Tribe of Levi]]</text>
      <sha1>ji6a7he7fzfnxypyix1kcv5iee0qatz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
