  <page>
    <title>Calico</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7521</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942172223</id>
      <parentid>923364332</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-23T01:38:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Þjarkur</username>
        <id>33824435</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Calico printing */ Link target</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{other uses}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2018}}
{{Use Indian English|date=July 2018}}
[[File:Calico Sample.JPG|thumb|The weave of calico sample from a [[shopping bag]] shown against a [[centimetre]] scale.]]
'''Calico''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|k|æ|l|ɪ|k|oʊ}}; in British usage since 1505)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=KuQyRKaoJmUC&amp;dq=calico+calicut&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s |title=Lynda Mugglestone &quot;The Oxford History of English&quot; |publisher=Books.google.co.in |date= |accessdate=2014-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a [[plain weave|plain-woven]] [[textile]] made from unbleached and often not fully processed [[cotton]]. It may contain unseparated husk parts, for example. The fabric is far less fine than [[muslin]], but less coarse and thick than [[canvas]] or [[denim]], but it is still very cheap owing to its unfinished and undyed appearance.

The fabric was originally from the city of [[Calicut]] in southwestern [[India]]. It was made by the traditional weavers called [[Saliya|cāliyans]]. The raw fabric was dyed and printed in bright hues, and [[Chintz|calico prints]] became popular in [[Europe]].

==History==
Calico originated in [[Calicut]] (from which the name of the textile came) in southwestern India (in present-day [[Kerala]]) during the 11th century.&lt;ref name=eb-calico/&gt; The cloth was known as &quot;cāliyan&quot; to the natives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Jill |last=Condra |title=The Greenwood Encyclopedia of Clothing Through World History: 1801 to the Present |volume= 3 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=q6FI2czFz6MC&amp;dq=calico+calicut}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It was mentioned in Indian literature by the 12th century when the writer [[Acharya Hemachandra|Hēmacandra]] described calico fabric prints with a lotus design.&lt;ref name=eb-calico&gt;''Encyclopædia Britannica'' (2008). &quot;calico&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; By the 15th century calico from [[Gujarat|Gujǎrāt]] made its appearance in [[Egypt]].&lt;ref name=eb-calico/&gt; Trade with Europe followed from the 17th century onwards.&lt;ref name=eb-calico/&gt;

Calico was woven using [[Surat|Sūrat]] cotton for both the [[Warp (weaving)|warp]] and [[weft]].

The commercial method of calico printing using engraved rollers was invented in 1821 in [[New Mills]]. [[John Potts (engraver)|John Potts]] of Potts, Oliver and Potts used a copper-engraved master to produce rollers to transfer the inks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Glover216&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Glover |first=Stephen |title=The history and gazetteer of the county of Derby |year=1831 |page=216|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=BsoHAAAAQAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false |access-date=26 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Politics of cotton===
In the 18th century, England was famous for its [[woollen]] and [[worsted|worsted cloth]]. That industry, centred in the east and south in towns such as [[Norwich]], jealously protected their product. Cotton processing was tiny: in 1701 only {{convert|1,985,868|lb|kg}} of cottonwool was imported into England, and by 1730 this had fallen to {{convert|1,545,472|lb|kg}}. This was due to commercial legislation to protect the woollen industry.&lt;ref name=E296&gt;{{Harvnb|Espinasse|1874|p=296}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cheap [[Chintz|calico prints]], imported by the [[East India Company]] from [[Hindustan|Hindustān (India)]], had become popular. In 1700 an [[Act of Parliament]]&lt;!--Act 11 William III--&gt; passed to prevent the importation of dyed or printed calicoes from India, China or Persia. This caused demand to switch to imported grey cloth instead—calico that had not been finished—dyed or printed. These were printed with popular patterns in southern England.{{who|date=June 2016}} Also, [[Lancashire]] businessmen produced grey cloth with linen warp and cotton weft, known as [[fustian]], which they sent to London for finishing.&lt;ref name=E296/&gt; Cottonwool imports recovered though, and by 1720 were almost back to their 1701 levels. Again the woollen manufacturers, in true [[Protectionism|protectionist]] fashion, claimed that the imports were taking jobs away&lt;!--  why is it artificial? --&gt; from workers in [[Coventry]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Espinasse|1874|p=298}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Woollen, etc., Manufactures Act 1720]] was passed, enacting fines against anyone caught wearing printed or stained calico muslins. Neckcloths and fustians were exempted. The Lancashire manufacturers exploited this exemption; coloured cotton [[weft]] with [[linen]] warp were specifically permitted by the [[1736 Manchester Act]]. There now was an [[artificial demand]] for woven cloth.{{why|date=June 2016}}&lt;!--  why in there demand and why is it artificial, also? --&gt;

In 1764, {{convert|3,870,392|lb|kg}} of cotton-wool were imported.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Espinasse|1874|p=299}}&lt;/ref&gt; This change in consumption patterns, as a result of the restriction on imported finished goods, was a key part of the process that reduced the Indian economy from sophisticated textile production to the mere supply of raw materials. These events occurred under colonial rule, which started after 1757, and were described by [[Jawaharlal Nehru|Nehru]] and also some more recent scholars as &quot;de-industrialization&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=India’s De-Industrialization Under British Rule: New Ideas, New Evidence |first=David |last=Clingingsmith |first2=Jeffrey G. |last2=Williamson |work=NBER Working Paper No. 10586 |date=June 2004 |doi=10.3386/w10586 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Calico printing===
[[File:Calico sample Crum &amp; Co..jpg|thumb|left|Sample of calico printed with a six-colour machine by Walter Crum &amp; Co., from [[Frederick Crace Calvert]], ''Dyeing and Calico Printing'' (1878).]]

Early Indian [[chintz]], that is, glazed calico with a large floral pattern, was primarily produced using painting techniques.&lt;ref name=Turnbull&gt;Turnbull, ''A History of Calico Printing in Great Britain'', 1951.&lt;/ref&gt; Later, the hues were applied by wooden blocks, and the cloth manufacturers in Britain printed calico using [[Woodblock printing|wooden block printing]]. Calico printers at work are depicted in one of the [[stained glass]] windows made by Stephen Adam for the [[Maryhill Burgh Halls]], [[Glasgow]]. Confusingly, linen and silk printed this way were known as ''linen calicoes'' and ''silk calicoes''. Early European calicoes (1680) were cheap [[plain weave]] white cotton fabric, or cream or unbleached cotton, with a design block-printed using a single [[Rose madder|alizarin dye]] fixed with two mordants, giving a red and black pattern. Polychromatic prints were possible, using two sets of blocks and an additional blue dye. The Indian taste was for dark printed backgrounds, while the European market preferred a pattern on a cream base. As the century progressed the European preference moved from the large chintz patterns to smaller, tighter patterns.&lt;ref name=dreamstress/&gt;

[[Thomas Bell (printer)|Thomas Bell]] patented a printing technique in 1783 that used copper rollers. In 1785, [[Livesey, Hargreaves and Company]] put the first machine that used this technique into operation in [[Walton-le-Dale]], [[Lancashire]]. The production volume for printed cloth in Lancashire in 1750 was estimated at 50,000 pieces of {{convert|30|yd|m}}; in 1850, it was 20,000,000 pieces.&lt;ref name=Turnbull/&gt; After 1888, block printing was only used for short-run specialized jobs. After 1880, profits from printing fell due to [[overcapacity]] and the firms started to form [[Business group|combines]]. In the first, three Scottish firms formed the United Turkey Red Co. Ltd in 1897, and the second, in 1899, was the much larger [[Calico Printers' Association]] 46 printing concerns and 13 merchants combined, representing 85% of the British printing capacity.&lt;ref name=gg&gt;[http://www.gracesguide.co.uk/Calico_Printers_Association Grace's Guides]&lt;/ref&gt; Some of this capacity was removed{{how|date=June 2016}} and in 1901 Calico had 48% of the printing trade. In 1916, they and the other printers formed and joined a trade association, which then set minimum prices for each 'price section' of the industry.{{cn|date=August 2017}}

The trade association remained in operation until 1954, when the arrangement was challenged by the government [[Monopolies Commission]]. Over the intervening period much trade had been lost overseas.&lt;ref name=&quot;M&amp;M&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|last=Hughes
|first=William
|title=Report on the Process of Calico Printing
|url=http://www.competition-commission.org.uk/ulcc-bin/htsearch/Default.aspx?config=COMPCOM2&amp;sort=score&amp;matchesperpage=20&amp;restrict=&amp;words=Calico+printing
|accessdate=2010-12-08
|date=1954-04-13
|publisher=Monopolies and Restrictive Practices Commission
|location=House of Commons, London
|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120121052518/http://www.competition-commission.org.uk/ulcc-bin/htsearch/Default.aspx?config=COMPCOM2&amp;sort=score&amp;matchesperpage=20&amp;restrict=&amp;words=Calico+printing
|archive-date=21 January 2012
|url-status=dead
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Terminology==
[[File:Calico printing Wellcome L0011294.jpg|thumb|Calico printing]]
In the UK, Australia and New Zealand:
*Calico – simple, cheap equal weft and warp plain weave fabric in white, cream or unbleached cotton.
*Calico bag - a bag made of calico used by banks and other financial institutions.
*[[Muslin]] – a very fine, light plain weave cotton fabric.
*Muslin gauze – muslin.
*Gauze – extremely soft and fine cotton fabric with a very open plain weave.
*Cheesecloth – gauze.
*Tote Bag - sometimes made of calico

In the US:
*Calico – cotton fabric with a small, all-over floral print&lt;ref&gt;Kadolph, Sara J., ed. (2007) ''Textiles'', 10th ed., p. 463, Pearson/Prentice-Hall {{ISBN|0-13-118769-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Muslin – simple, cheap equal weft and warp plain weave fabric in white, cream or unbleached cotton and/or a very fine, light plain weave cotton fabric (sometimes called muslin gauze).
*Muslin gauze – the very lightest, most open weave of muslin.
*[[Gauze]] – any very light fabric, generally with a plain weave
*[[Cheesecloth]] – extremely soft and fine cotton fabric with a very open plain weave.

Printed calico was imported into the United States from Lancashire in the 1780s, and here a linguistic separation occurred, while Europe maintained the word calico for the fabric, in the States it was used to refer to the printed design.&lt;ref name=dreamstress/&gt;

These colorful, small-patterned printed fabrics gave rise to the use of the word calico to describe a cat coat color: &quot;[[calico cat]]&quot;. The patterned fabric also gave its name to two species of North American crabs; see the [[Ovalipes ocellatus|calico crab]].&lt;ref name=dreamstress&gt;[http://thedreamstress.com/?s=calico%2C+Muslin%2C+gauze Calico, muslin, gauze – terminology]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Calico Acts]]
*[[Calico cat]]
*[[Calico_(goldfish)|Calico goldfish]]
*[[Calico Jack]]

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

==External links==
{{commons category|Calico}}
*{{cite book|last=Espinasse|first=Francis|authorlink=Francis Espinasse|title=Lancashire Worthies|url=https://archive.org/stream/lancashireworthi00espi#page/322/mode/2up|accessdate=2010-12-01|year=1874|publisher=Simpkin, Marshall, &amp; Co.|location= London|ref=harv }}
*{{Cite NSRW|wstitle=Calico}}
* Charles O'Neill (1869) [http://lhldigital.lindahall.org/cdm/ref/collection/color/id/24565 ''A dictionary of dyeing and calico printing''] - digital facsimile from the [[Linda Hall Library]]
* William Crookes (1874) [http://lhldigital.lindahall.org/cdm/ref/collection/color/id/13351 ''A practical handbook of dyeing and calico-printing'']. Illustrated with period fabric swatches. - digital facsimile from the Linda Hall Library
* Deazley, R. (2008) ‘Commentary on the Calico Printers' Act 1787', in Primary Sources on Copyright (1450-1900), eds L. Bently &amp; M. Kretschmer,[http://www.copyrighthistory.org/cam/commentary/uk_1787/uk_1787_com_1072007131417.html Copyright History 1787 Calico Printers' Act] 
{{fabric}}

[[Category:History of Kerala]]
[[Category:Woven fabrics]]
[[Category:Indian inventions]]
[[Category:History of Kozhikode]]
[[Category:Economy of Kozhikode]]
[[Category:Cotton industry in India]]</text>
      <sha1>n6cai41tw3wt1ljprjgeme3lfqu6fi6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
