  <page>
    <title>Christianity and Judaism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7502</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942266195</id>
      <parentid>942266098</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-23T17:18:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>El C</username>
        <id>92203</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/2A03:D5C0:1C08:10D:16C9:E5A0:9025:F08|2A03:D5C0:1C08:10D:16C9:E5A0:9025:F08]] ([[User talk:2A03:D5C0:1C08:10D:16C9:E5A0:9025:F08|talk]]) to last version by Epinoia</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Christianity}}
{{Jews and Judaism sidebar}}
[[Christianity]] is rooted in [[Second Temple Judaism]], but the two religions [[Split of early Christianity and Judaism|diverged in the first centuries]] of the [[Christian Era]]. Christianity emphasizes correct belief (or [[orthodoxy]]), focusing on the [[New Covenant]] as [[Mediator (Christ as Mediator)|mediated]] through [[Jesus in Christianity|Jesus]] [[Christ (title)|Christ]],&lt;ref name=&quot;bibleverse||Hebrews|8:6|NIV&quot;&gt;{{bibleverse||Hebrews|8:6|NIV}}&lt;/ref&gt; as recorded in the [[New Testament]]. Judaism places emphasis on correct conduct (or [[Orthopraxy#Judaism|orthopraxy]]),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Jackson |first=Elizabeth |title=The Illustrated Dictionary of Culture |publisher=Lotus Press |year=2007 |isbn=978-81-89093-26-6 |pages= 147}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Westley |first=Miles |title=The Bibliophile's Dictionary |publisher=Writer's Digest Books |year=2005 |pages=91 |isbn=978-1-58297-356-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=McKim |first=Donald K. |title=Westminster Dictionary of Theological Terms |publisher=Westminster John Knox Press |year=1996 |pages=197 |isbn=978-0-664-25511-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; focusing on the [[Mosaic covenant]], as recorded in the [[Torah]] and [[Talmud]].

[[Christians]] believe in [[individual salvation]] from [[Christian views on sin|sin]] through receiving Jesus Christ as their Lord (God) and [[Redeemer (Christianity)|savior]]. [[Jews]] believe in individual and collective participation in an eternal dialogue with God through tradition, rituals, [[Jewish prayer|prayers]] and [[Jewish ethics|ethical actions]]. Christianity generally believes in a [[Trinity|Triune God]], one [[person]] of whom [[Incarnation (Christianity)|became human]]. Judaism emphasizes the [[Divine simplicity|Oneness of God]] and rejects the Christian concept of [[God the Son|God in human form]].

==Jewish self-identification==
{{Main|Jewish Christian}}
{{See also|Christian theology}}
{{rewrite section|date=June 2018}}
Judaism's purpose is to carry out what it holds to be the only [[Covenant (biblical)#Mosaic covenant|covenant]] between [[God in Judaism|God]] and the [[Jewish people]]. The Torah (lit. &quot;teaching&quot;), both [[Torah|written]] and [[Oral Torah|oral]], tell the story of this covenant, and provides Jews with the terms of the covenant. The Oral Torah is the primary guide for Jews to abide by these terms, as expressed in tractate Gittin 60b, &quot;the Holy One, Blessed be He, did not make His covenant with [[Israel]] except by virtue of the Oral Law&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Chief Rabbi of the Commonwealth, Dr. [[Immanuel Jakobovits]] in the Forward to, Schimmel, H. Chaim, ''The Oral Law: A study of the rabbinic contribution to Torah she-be-al-peh'', 2nd rev.ed., Feldheim Publishers, New York, 1996&lt;/ref&gt; to help them learn how to live a holy life, and to bring holiness, peace and love into the world and into every part of life, so that life may be elevated to a high level of [[kedushah]], originally through study and practice of the Torah, and since the destruction of the [[Second Temple]], through prayer as expressed in tractate Sotah 49a &quot;Since the destruction of the Temple, every day is more cursed than the preceding one; and the existence of the world is assured only by the kedusha...and the words spoken after the study of Torah.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Jacobs, Louis, God, in Arthur A. Cohen, Paul Mendes-Flohr, ''20th Century Jewish Religious Thought: Original Essays on Critical Concepts'', Jewish Publication Society, 2009, p. 394 cited in [[Elie Munk]]. The World of Prayer 1 (1961), p. 182.&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the adoption of the [[Amidah]], the acknowledgement of God through the declaration from Isaiah 6:3 &quot;Kadosh [holy], kadosh, kadosh, is HaShem, Master of Legions; the whole world is filled with His glory&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Scherman Nosson &amp; Zlotowitz, Meir, eds., TANACH: The Torah, Prophets, Writings, The Twenty-Four Books of the Bible Newly Translated and Annotated, Mesorah Publications, Ltd., Brooklyn, 1996, p. 963&lt;/ref&gt; as a replacement for the study of Torah, which is a daily obligation for a Jew,&lt;ref&gt;Jacobs, Louis, God, in Arthur A. Cohen, Paul Mendes-Flohr, ''20th Century Jewish Religious Thought: Original Essays on Critical Concepts'', Jewish Publication Society, 2009, p. 394&lt;/ref&gt; and sanctifies God in itself. This continuous maintenance of relationship between the individual Jew and God through either study, or [[Jewish prayer|prayer]] repeated three times daily, is the confirmation of the original covenant. This allows the Jewish people as a community to strive and fulfill the prophecy &quot;I, the Lord, have called you in righteousness, and will hold your hand and keep you. And I will establish you as a covenant of the people, for a light unto the nations.&quot; ({{bibleverse||Isa|42:6|HE}}) (i.e., a [[role model]]) over the course of history, and a part of the divine intent of bringing about an [[Kingdom of God#Judaism|age of peace and sanctity]] where ideally a faithful life and good deeds should be ends in themselves, not means. See also [[Jewish principles of faith]].

According to [[Christian theologian]] [[Alister McGrath]], the Jewish Christians affirmed every aspect of then contemporary [[Second Temple Judaism]] with the addition of the belief that Jesus was the messiah,&lt;ref&gt;McGrath, Alister E., Christianity: An Introduction. Blackwell Publishing (2006). {{ISBN|1-4051-0899-1}}. p. 174: &quot;In effect, they [Jewish Christians] seemed to regard Christianity as an affirmation of every aspect of contemporary Judaism, with the addition of one extra belief—that Jesus is the Messiah. Unless males were [[Circumcision controversy in early Christianity|circumcised]], they could not be saved ({{bibleverse||Acts|15:1}}).&quot;;see also [[Paleo-orthodoxy]]&lt;/ref&gt; with Isaiah 49:6, &quot;an explicit parallel to 42:6&quot; quoted by [[Paul the Apostle]] in Acts 13:47&lt;ref&gt;Beale, Gregory K., Other Religions in New Testament Theology, in David Weston Baker, ed., ''Biblical faith and other religions: an evangelical assessment'', Kregel Academic, 2004, p. 85&lt;/ref&gt; and reinterpreted by [[Justin Martyr]].&lt;ref&gt;McKeehan, James, ''An Overview of the Old Testament and How It Relates to the New Testament'', iUniverse, 2002, p. 265&lt;/ref&gt; According to Christian writers, most notably Paul, the Bible teaches that people are, in their current state, [[sin]]ful,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Romans|3:23}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[New Testament]] reveals that Jesus is both the [[Son of man]] and the [[Son of God]], united in the [[hypostatic union]], [[God the Son]], [[God in Christianity|God]] made [[incarnate]];&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||John|1:1}}, {{bibleverse||John|1:14}}, {{bibleverse||John|1:29}}&lt;/ref&gt; that [[Crucifixion of Jesus|Jesus' death by crucifixion]] was a [[Atonement in Christianity|sacrifice to atone]] for all of humanity's sins, and that acceptance of Jesus as [[Christian soteriology|Savior]] and [[Hæland|Lord]] saves one from [[Divine Judgment]],&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||John|5:24}}&lt;/ref&gt; giving [[Eternal life (Christianity)|Eternal life]].&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||John|3:16|NIV}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jesus is the mediator of the New Covenant.&lt;ref name=&quot;bibleverse||Hebrews|8:6|NIV&quot;/&gt; His famous [[Sermon on the Mount]] is considered by some Christian scholars&lt;ref&gt;See also [[Expounding of the Law#Antithesis of the Law|Antithesis of the Law]]&lt;/ref&gt; to be the proclamation of the [[Ethics in religion#Christian ethics|New Covenant ethics]], in [[Typology (theology)|contrast]] to the [[Mosaic Covenant]] of [[Moses]] from [[Biblical Mount Sinai|Mount Sinai]].

==Sacred texts==
{{Main|Development of the Hebrew Bible canon|Development of the Christian Biblical canon}}
The [[Tanakh|Hebrew Bible]] is composed of three parts; the [[Torah]] (Instruction, the [[Septuagint]] translated the Hebrew to ''nomos'' or ''Law''), the [[Nevi'im]] (Prophets) and the [[Ketuvim]] (Writings). Collectively, these are known as the [[Tanakh]]. According to [[Rabbinic Judaism]] the Torah was revealed by God to Moses; within it, Jews find [[613 Mitzvot]] (commandments).

Rabbinic tradition asserts that God revealed two Torahs to Moses, one  that was written down, and one that was transmitted orally. Whereas the written Torah has a fixed form, the [[Oral Torah]] is a living tradition that includes not only specific supplements to the written Torah (for instance, what is the proper manner of ''[[shechita]]'' and what is meant by &quot;Frontlets&quot; in the [[Shema]]), but also procedures for understanding and talking about the written Torah (thus, the Oral Torah revealed at Sinai includes debates among rabbis who lived long after Moses). The Oral Law elaborations of narratives in the Bible and stories about the rabbis are referred to as ''[[aggadah]]''. It also includes elaboration of the 613 commandments in the form of laws referred to as ''[[halakha]]''. Elements of the Oral Torah were committed to writing and edited by [[Judah HaNasi]] in the [[Mishnah]] in 200 CE; much more of the Oral Torah were committed to writing in the [[Babylonian Talmud|Babylonian]] and [[Jerusalem Talmud]]s, which were edited around 600 CE and 450 CE, respectively. The Talmuds are notable for the way they combine law and lore, for their explication of the [[midrash]]ic method of interpreting tests, and for their accounts of debates among rabbis, which preserve divergent and conflicting interpretations of the Bible and legal rulings.

Since the transcription of the Talmud, notable rabbis have compiled law codes that are generally held in high regard: the [[Mishneh Torah]], the [[Arba'ah Turim|Tur]], and the [[Shulchan Aruch]]. The latter, which was based on earlier codes and supplemented by the commentary by [[Moshe Isserles]] that notes other practices and customs practiced by Jews in different communities, especially among Ashkenazim, is generally held to be authoritative by Orthodox Jews. The [[Zohar]], which was written in the 13th century, is generally held as the most important esoteric treatise of the Jews.

All contemporary Jewish movements consider the Tanakh, and the Oral Torah in the form of the Mishnah and Talmuds as sacred, although movements are divided as to claims concerning their divine revelation, and also their authority. For Jews, the Torah—written and oral—is the primary guide to the relationship between God and man, a living document that has unfolded and will continue to unfold whole new insights over the generations and millennia. A saying that captures this goes, &quot;Turn it [the Torah's words] over and over again, for everything is in it.&quot;

Christians accept the Written Torah and other books of the [[Hebrew Bible]] (alternatively called [[Old Testament]]) as [[Scripture]], although they generally give readings from the [[Koine Greek]] [[Septuagint]] translation instead of the [[Biblical Hebrew]]/[[Biblical Aramaic]] [[Masoretic Text]]. Two notable examples are:
* [[Isaiah 7:14]] – &quot;virgin&quot; instead of &quot;young woman&quot;
* [[They have pierced my hands and my feet|Psalm 22:16]] – &quot;they have pierced my hands and feet&quot; instead of &quot;like a lion, (they are at) my hands and feet&quot;

Instead of the traditional Jewish order and names for the books, Christians organize and name the books closer to that found in the Septuagint. Some Christian denominations (such as Anglican, Roman Catholic, and Eastern Orthodox), include a number of books that are not in the Hebrew Bible (the [[biblical apocrypha]] or [[deuterocanonical books]] or [[Anagignoskomena]], see [[Development of the Old Testament canon]]) in their [[biblical canon]] that are not in today's Jewish canon, although they were included in the Septuagint. Christians reject the Jewish Oral Torah, which was still in oral, and therefore unwritten, form in the time of Jesus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=254&amp;letter=J&amp;search=Jesus Jewish Encyclopedia: Jesus] notes: &quot;Jesus, however, does not appear to have taken into account the fact that the [[Halakah]] was at this period just becoming crystallized, and that much variation existed as to its definite form; the disputes of the [[Hillel the Elder|Bet Hillel]] and [[Shammai|Bet Shammai]] were occurring about the time of his maturity.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Bloch-SermonOnTheMount.jpg|thumb|300px|right|Jesus depicted delivering the [[Sermon on the Mount]] which included [[Matthew 5#Antitheses|commentary on the Old Covenant]]. Some scholars consider this to be an [[Typology (theology)|antitype]] of the proclamation of the [[Ten Commandments]] or [[Mosaic Covenant]] by [[Moses]] from the [[Biblical Mount Sinai]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ODCC self&quot;&gt;&quot;Sermon on the Mount.&quot; Cross, F. L., ed. ''The Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church''. New York: Oxford University Press. 2005&lt;/ref&gt;]]

==Covenant theology==
{{more citations needed section|date=November 2018}}
Christians believe that God has established a New Covenant with people through Jesus, as recorded in the Gospels, Acts of the Apostles, Epistles, and other books collectively called the New Testament (the word ''testament'' attributed to [[Tertullian]] is commonly interchanged with the word ''covenant'').&lt;ref&gt;Sometimes the ''New Covenant'' is referred to as the [New Testament, on the basis of passages such as {{bibleverse||Heb|9:16|KJV}}, in its traditional ([[KJV]]) translation. This usage reflects the [[Vulgate]], in which the word &quot;covenant&quot; was translated ''testamentum''. Biblical scholars, such as [[O. Palmer Robertson]], have argued against this translation, however, since the word ''testamentum'', in [[Latin]], expresses the concept of a &quot;last will&quot;, not an agreement between two parties sealed with a self-maledictory oath. See also [http://www.theopedia.com/Covenant Theopedia: &quot;Covenant&quot;] and [http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=837&amp;letter=C&amp;search=Mosaic%20Covenant#2888 Jewish Encyclopedia: &quot;Covenant: The Old and the New Covenant&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt; For some Christians, such as [[Roman Catholicism|Roman Catholics]] and [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Orthodox Christians]], this New Covenant includes authoritative [[sacred tradition]]s and [[canon law]]. Others, especially [[Protestantism|Protestants]], reject the authority of such traditions and instead hold to the principle of ''[[sola scriptura]]'', which accepts only the Bible itself as the final rule of faith and practice. Anglicans do not believe in ''sola scriptura''. For them scripture is the longest leg of a 3-legged stool: scripture, tradition and reason. Scripture cannot stand on its own since it must be interpreted in the light of the Church's patristic teaching and ecumenical creeds. Additionally, some denominations{{which|date= November 2018}} include the &quot;oral teachings of Jesus to the Apostles&quot;, which they believe have been handed down to this day by [[apostolic succession]].{{citation needed|date=November 2018}}

Christians refer to the biblical books about Jesus as the New Testament, and to the canon of Hebrew books as the [[Old Testament]]. Judaism does not accept the [[wikt:retronym|retronymic]] labeling of its [[scripture|sacred texts]] as the &quot;Old Testament&quot;, and some Jews{{who|date= November 2018}} refer to the New Testament as the Christian Testament or Christian Bible. Judaism rejects all claims that the Christian New Covenant [[supersessionism|supersedes]], [[Abrogation of Old Covenant laws|abrogates]], fulfills, or is the unfolding or consummation of the covenant expressed in the Written and Oral Torahs. Therefore, just as Christianity does not accept that Mosaic law has any authority over Christians, Judaism does not accept that the New Testament has any religious authority over Jews.

==Law==
{{See also|Antinomianism|Biblical law in Christianity|Christian anarchism}}
Many Jews view Christians as having quite an ambivalent view of the Torah, or Mosaic law: on one hand Christians speak of it as God's absolute word, but on the other, they apply its commandments with a certain selectivity. Some Jews{{who|date= November 2018}} contend that Christians cite commandments from the Old Testament to support one point of view but then ignore other commandments of a similar class and of equal weight. Examples of this are certain commandments that God states explicitly be a &quot;lasting covenant&quot; ([[NIV]] {{bibleverse||Exod|31:16-17|niv}}). Some translate the Hebrew as a &quot;perpetual covenant&quot; ({{bibleverse||Exod|31:16–17|he}}).

Christians explain that such selectivity is based on rulings made by early Jewish Christians in the [[Book of Acts]], at the [[Council of Jerusalem]], that, while believing gentiles did not need to fully convert to Judaism, they should follow some aspects of Torah like avoiding [[idolatry]] and [[fornication]] and [[Taboo food and drink#Blood|blood]],&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Acts|15:28–29}}, {{bibleverse-nb||Acts|21:25}}&lt;/ref&gt; including, according to some interpretations,{{which|date= November 2018}} [[Homosexuality and Christianity|homosexuality]]. This view is also reflected by modern Judaism, in that [[Ger toshav|Righteous gentiles]] needn't convert to Judaism and need to observe only the Noahide Laws, which also contain prohibitions against idolatry and fornication and blood.&lt;ref&gt;[http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=142&amp;letter=G#543 Jewish Encyclopedia: Gentiles: Gentiles May Not Be Taught the Torah] states: &quot;[[Jacob Emden|R. Emden]] (), in a remarkable apology for Christianity contained in his appendix to &quot;Seder 'Olam&quot; (pp. 32b–34b, Hamburg, 1752), gives it as his opinion that the original intention of Jesus, and especially of Paul, was to convert only the gentiles to the [[Seven Laws of Noah|seven moral laws of Noah]] and to let the Jews follow the Mosaic law—which explains the apparent contradictions in the New Testament regarding the [[Biblical law in Christianity|laws of Moses]] and the [[Biblical Sabbath|Sabbath]].&lt;/ref&gt;

Some Christians{{who|date= November 2018}} agree that Jews who accept Jesus should still observe all of Torah, see for example [[Dual-covenant theology]], based on warnings by Jesus to Jews not to use him as an excuse to disregard it,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Matt|5:19}}&lt;/ref&gt; and they support efforts of those such as Messianic Jews ([[Messianic Judaism]] is considered by most Christians and Jews to be a form of Christianity&lt;ref name=&quot;Denominations&quot;&gt;
;[[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox]]
:{{cite web
| url = http://www.aish.com/jw/s/48892792.html
| title = Why Jews Don't Believe in Jesus
| accessdate = July 28, 2010
| last = Simmons
| first = Shraga
| publisher = [[Aish HaTorah]]
| quote = Jews do not accept Jesus as the messiah because:&lt;br /&gt; #Jesus did not fulfill the messianic prophecies. #Jesus did not embody the personal qualifications of the Messiah. #Biblical verses &quot;referring&quot; to Jesus are mistranslations. #Jewish belief is based on national revelation.
}}
;[[Conservative Judaism|Conservative]]:{{cite web
| url = http://www.uscj.org/Messianic_Jews_Not_J5480.html
| title = Messianic Jews Are Not Jews
| accessdate = 2007-02-14
| last = Waxman
| first = Jonathan
| year = 2006
| publisher = [[United Synagogue of Conservative Judaism]]
| quote = Hebrew Christian, Jewish Christian, Jew for Jesus, Messianic Jew, Fulfilled Jew. The name may have changed over the course of time, but all of the names reflect the same phenomenon: one who asserts that s/he is straddling the theological fence between Christianity and Judaism, but in truth is firmly on the Christian side.…we must affirm as did the Israeli Supreme Court in the well-known Brother Daniel case that to adopt Christianity is to have crossed the line out of the Jewish community.
| archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20060628033541/http://www.uscj.org/Messianic_Jews_Not_J5480.html
| archivedate = June 28, 2006
}}
;[[Reform Judaism|Reform]]:{{cite web
| url = http://www.huc.edu/news/mi.html
| title = Missionary Impossible
| accessdate = 2007-02-14
| date = August 9, 1999
| publisher = [[Hebrew Union College]]
| quote = Missionary Impossible, an imaginative video and curriculum guide for teachers, educators, and rabbis to teach Jewish youth how to recognize and respond to &quot;Jews-for-Jesus&quot;, &quot;Messianic Jews&quot;, and other Christian proselytizers, has been produced by six rabbinic students at Hebrew Union College-Jewish Institute of Religion's Cincinnati School. The students created the video as a tool for teaching why Jewish college and high school youth and Jews in intermarried couples are primary targets of Christian missionaries.
| url-status = dead
| archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20060928080259/http://www.huc.edu/news/mi.html
| archivedate = September 28, 2006
}}
;[[Reconstructionist Judaism|Reconstructionist]]/[[Jewish Renewal|Renewal]]:{{cite web
 | url = https://www.aleph.org/faq.htm
 | title = FAQ's About Jewish Renewal
 | accessdate = 2007-12-20
 | year = 2007
 | publisher = [https://www.aleph.org/start.taf Aleph.org]
 | quote = '''''What is ALEPH's position on so called messianic Judaism?''''' ALEPH has a policy of respect for other spiritual traditions, but objects to deceptive practices and will not collaborate with denominations which actively target Jews for recruitment. Our position on so-called &quot;Messianic Judaism&quot; is that it is Christianity and its proponents would be more honest to call it that.
 | url-status = dead
 | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20141023183108/https://www.aleph.org/faq.htm
 | archivedate = 2014-10-23
 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Berman&quot;&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://www.wwrn.org/article.php?idd=21820&amp;sec=59&amp;con=35
| title = Aliyah with a cat, a dog and Jesus
| accessdate = August 9, 2010
| last = Berman
| first = Daphna
| date = June 10, 2006
| newspaper = [[Haaretz]]
| quote = In rejecting their petition, Supreme Court Justice [[Menachem Elon]] cited their belief in Jesus. ‘In the last two thousand years of history…the Jewish people have decided that messianic Jews do not belong to the Jewish nation…and have no right to force themselves on it,’ he wrote, concluding that ‘those who believe in Jesus, are, in fact Christians.’
| url-status = dead
| archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20080117214825/http://www.wwrn.org/article.php?idd=21820&amp;sec=59&amp;con=35
| archivedate = January 17, 2008
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Christians&quot;&gt;
*{{Cite book
 | last = Harries
 | first = Richard
 | authorlink = Richard Harries, Baron Harries of Pentregarth
 | title = After the evil: Christianity and Judaism in the shadow of the Holocaust
 |date=August 2003
 | publisher = [[Oxford University Press]]
 | location = [[New York, NY]]
 | isbn = 0-19-926313-2
 | page = g. 119
 | chapter = Should Christians Try to Convert Jews?
 | quote = Thirdly, there is Jews for Jesus or, more generally, Messianic Judaism. This is a movement of people often of Jewish background who have come to believe Jesus is the expected Jewish messiah.…They often have congregations independent of other churches and specifically target Jews for conversion to their form of Christianity.
 | lccn = 2003273342|nopp=yes
}}
*{{Cite book
 | last = Kessler
 | first = Edward
 | editor = Edward Kessler
 | editor2 = Neil Wenborn
 | title = A dictionary of Jewish-Christian relations 
 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=QkI_JNv3rIwC| year = 2005
 | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]]
 | location = [[Cambridge]]; [[New York (state)|New York]]
 | isbn = 978-0-521-82692-1
 | oclc = 60340826
 | pages = 292–293
 | chapter = Messianic Jews
 | chapterurl = https://books.google.com/books?id=QkI_JNv3rIwC&amp;dq=Christian+view+of+Messianic+Judaism&amp;pg=PA292&amp;prev=http://www.google.com/search%3Fhl%3Den%26q%3DChristian%2Bview%2Bof%2BMessianic%2BJudaism%26btnG%3DSearch&amp;cd=3&amp;cad=legacy#PPA292,M1
 | quote = Messianic Judaism is proactive in seeking Jewish converts and is condemned by the vast majority of the Jewish community. Although a Jewish convert to Christianity may still be categorised a Jew according to a strict interpretation of the '''''halakhah''''' (Jewish law), most Jews are adamantly opposed to the idea that one can convert to Christianity and still remoan a Jew or be considered part of Jewish life. From a mainstream Christian perspective Messianic Judaisms can also provoke hostility for misrepresenting Christianity.
 | lccn = 2005012923
}}
*{{Cite book
 | last = Harris-Shapiro
 | first = Carol
 | authorlink = Carol Harris-Shapiro
 | title = Messianic Judaism: A Rabbi’s Journey Through Religious Change in America
 | url =https://books.google.com/books?id=72QTLABTllwC| year = 1999
 | publisher = [[Beacon Press]]
 | location = [[Boston]], [[Massachusetts]]
 | isbn = 0-8070-1040-5
 | oclc = 45729039
 | pages = g. 3
 | chapter = Studying the Messianic Jews
 | chapterurl = https://books.google.com/books?id=72QTLABTllwC&amp;dq=Christian+relationship+to+Messianic+Judaism&amp;pg=PA118&amp;prev=http://www.google.com/search%3Fq%3DChristian%2Brelationship%2Bto%2BMessianic%2BJudaism%26btnG%3DSearch%26hl%3Den&amp;cd=1&amp;cad=legacy#PPA3,M1
 | quote = And while many evangelical Churches are openly supportive of Messianic Judaism, they treat it as an ethnic church squarely within evangelical Christianity, rather than as a separate entity.
 | lccn = 98054864
 }}
*[[Ed Stetzer|Stetzer, Ed]] (October 13, 2005). [http://www.christianindex.org/1657.article &quot;A Missional Church&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110723215712/http://www.christianindex.org/1657.article |date=July 23, 2011 }}, ''The Christian Index''. &quot;Missional churches are indigenous. Churches that are indigenous have taken root in the soil and reflect, to some degree, the culture of their community...  The messianic congregation (is)... in this case indigenous to Jewish culture.&quot;
&lt;/ref&gt;) to do that, but some Protestant forms of Christianity{{which|date= November 2018}} oppose all observance to the Mosaic law, even by Jews, which [[Martin Luther|Luther]] [[Martin Luther#Antinomian controversy|criticised as Antinomianism]].

A minority view in Christianity, known as [[Christian Torah-submission]], holds that the Mosaic law as it is written is binding on all followers of God under the New Covenant, even for gentiles, because it views God's commands as &quot;everlasting&quot; ({{bibleverse||Ps|119:152}}, {{bibleverse-nb||Ps|119:160}}; {{bibleverse||Ex|12:24}}, {{bibleverse-nb||Ex|29:9}}; {{bibleverse||Lev|16:29}}) and &quot;good&quot; ({{bibleverse||Neh|9:13}}; {{bibleverse||Ps|119:39}}; {{bibleverse||Rom|7:7-12}}).

==Concepts of God==
{{Main|God in Judaism|God in Christianity}}
{{unreferenced section|date=November 2018}}
Traditionally, both Judaism and Christianity believe in the [[God]] of [[Abraham]], [[Isaac]] and [[Jacob]], for Jews the God of the [[Tanakh]], for Christians the God of the Old Testament, the [[Creator God|creator of the universe]]. Judaism and major sects of Christianity reject the view that God is entirely [[Immanence|immanent]] (although some{{who|date= November 2018}} see this as the concept of the Holy Ghost) and within the world as a physical presence, (although Christians believe in the [[incarnation]] of God). Both religions reject the view that God is entirely [[Transcendence (religion)|transcendent]], and thus separate from the world, as the pre-Christian Greek [[Unknown God]]. Both religions reject [[atheism]] on one hand and [[polytheism]] on the other.

Both religions agree that God shares both transcendent and immanent qualities. How these religions resolve this issue is where the religions differ. Christianity posits that God exists as a [[Trinity]]; in this view God exists as three distinct persons who share a single divine [[Ousia|essence]], or [[Consubstantiality|substance]]. In those three there is one, and in that one there are three; the one God is indivisible, while the three persons are distinct and unconfused, [[God the Father]], [[God the Son]], and [[God the Holy Spirit]]. It teaches that God became especially immanent in physical form through the [[Incarnation (Christianity)|Incarnation]] of God the Son who was born as [[Jesus of Nazareth]], who is believed to be at once [[Hypostatic union|fully God and fully human]]. There are denominations self-describing as Christian who question one or more of these doctrines, however, see [[Nontrinitarianism]]. By contrast, Judaism sees God as a [[Divine simplicity|single entity]], and views trinitarianism as both incomprehensible and a violation of the Bible's teaching that God is one. It rejects the notion that Jesus or any other object or living being could be 'God', that God could have a literal 'son' in physical form or is divisible in any way, or that God could be made to be joined to the [[Nature|material world]] in such fashion. Although Judaism provides Jews with a word to label God's transcendence (''[[Ein Sof]]'', without end) and immanence (''[[Shekhinah]]'', in-dwelling), these are merely human words to describe two ways of experiencing God; God is one and indivisible.

===Shituf===
{{Main|Shituf}}
A minority Jewish view, which appears in some{{which|date= November 2018}} codes of [[halakha|Jewish law]], is that while Christian worship is polytheistic (due to the multiplicity of the Trinity), it is permissible for them to swear in God's name, since they are referring to the one God. This theology is referred to in [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] as [[Shituf]] (literally &quot;partnership&quot; or &quot;association&quot;). Although worship of a trinity is considered to be not different from any other form of idolatry for Jews, it may be an acceptable belief for non-Jews (according to the ruling of some Rabbinic authorities{{who|date= November 2018}}).

==Right action==

===Faith versus good deeds===
{{unreferenced section|date=November 2018}}
{{See also|Joint Declaration on the Doctrine of Justification|Biblical law in Christianity}}
Judaism teaches that the purpose of the Torah is to teach us how to act correctly. God's existence is a given in Judaism, and not something that most authorities see as a matter of required belief. Although some authorities{{who|date= November 2018}} see the Torah as commanding Jews to believe in God, Jews see belief in God as a necessary, but not sufficient, condition for a Jewish life. The quintessential verbal expression of Judaism is the [[Shema Yisrael]], the statement that the God of the Bible is their God, and that this God is unique and one. The quintessential physical expression of Judaism is behaving in accordance with the 613 Mitzvot (the commandments specified in the Torah), and thus live one's life in God's ways.

Thus fundamentally in Judaism, one is enjoined to bring holiness into life (with the guidance of God's laws), rather than removing oneself from life to be holy.

Much of Christianity also teaches that God wants people to perform [[good works]], but all branches hold that good works alone will not lead to salvation, which is called [[Legalism (theology)|Legalism]], the exception being [[dual-covenant theology]]. Some Christian denominations{{which|date= November 2018}} hold that salvation depends upon transformational faith in Jesus, which expresses itself in good works as a testament (or witness) to ones faith for others to see (primarily Eastern Orthodox Christianity and Roman Catholicism), while others (including most Protestants) hold that [[Sola fide|faith alone]] is necessary for salvation. Some{{who|date= November 2018}} argue that the difference is not as great as it seems, because it really hinges on the [[Faith in Christianity|definition of &quot;faith&quot; used]]. The first group generally uses the term &quot;faith&quot; to mean &quot;intellectual and heartfelt assent and submission&quot;. Such a faith will not be salvific until a person has allowed it to effect a life transforming conversion (turning towards God) in their being (see [[Ontotheology]]). The Christians that hold to &quot;salvation by faith alone&quot; (also called by its Latin name &quot;[[sola fide]]&quot;) define faith as being implicitly [[ontological]]—mere intellectual assent is not termed &quot;faith&quot; by these groups. Faith, then, is life-transforming by definition.

===Sin===
{{Unreferenced section|date=April 2009}}
{{Main|Jewish views of sin|Christian views on sin}}
In both religions, offenses against the will of God are called [[sin]]. These sins can be thoughts, words, or deeds.

Catholicism categorizes sins into various groups. A wounding of the relationship with God is often called [[venial sin]]; a complete rupture of the relationship with God is often called [[mortal sin]]. Without salvation from sin (see below), a person's separation from God is permanent, causing such a person to enter [[Hell]] in the [[afterlife]]. Both the Catholic Church and the Orthodox Church define sin more or less as a &quot;macula&quot;, a spiritual stain or uncleanliness that constitutes damage to man's image and likeness of God.

Hebrew has several words for sin, each with its own specific meaning. The word ''pesha'', or &quot;trespass&quot;, means a sin done out of rebelliousness. The word ''aveira'' means &quot;transgression&quot;. And the word ''avone'', or &quot;iniquity&quot;, means a sin done out of moral failing. The word most commonly translated simply as &quot;sin&quot;, ''het'', literally means &quot;to go astray&quot;. Just as Jewish law, ''halakha'' provides the proper &quot;way&quot; (or path) to live, sin involves straying from that path. Judaism teaches that humans are born with [[free will]], and morally neutral, with both a ''[[yetzer hatov]]'', (literally, &quot;the good inclination&quot;, in some views{{which|date= November 2018}}, a tendency towards goodness, in others{{which|date= November 2018}}, a tendency towards having a productive life and a tendency to be concerned with others) and a ''[[yetzer hara]]'', (literally &quot;the evil inclination&quot;, in some views{{which|date= November 2018}}, a tendency towards evil, and in others{{which|date= November 2018}}, a tendency towards base or animal behavior and a tendency to be selfish). In Judaism all human beings are believed to have free will and can choose the path in life that they will take. It does not teach that choosing good is impossible—only at times more difficult. There is almost always a &quot;way back&quot; if a person wills it. (Although texts mention certain categories for whom the way back will be exceedingly hard, such as the slanderer, the habitual gossip, and the malicious person)

The rabbis recognize a positive value to the ''yetzer hara'': one tradition identifies it with the observation on the last day of creation that God's accomplishment was &quot;very good&quot; (God's work on the preceding days was just described as &quot;good&quot;) and explain that without the yetzer ha'ra there would be no marriage, children, commerce or other fruits of human labor; the implication is that yetzer ha'tov and yetzer ha'ra are best understood not as moral categories of good and evil but as selfless versus selfish orientations, either of which used rightly can serve God's will.

In contrast to the Jewish view of being morally balanced, [[Original Sin]] refers to the idea that the sin of [[Adam and Eve]]'s disobedience (sin &quot;at the origin&quot;) has passed on a spiritual heritage, so to speak. Christians teach that human beings inherit a corrupted or damaged human nature in which the tendency to do bad is greater than it would have been otherwise, so much so that human nature would not be capable now of participating in the afterlife with God. This is not a matter of being &quot;guilty&quot; of anything; each person is only personally guilty of their own actual sins. However, this understanding of original sin is what lies behind the Christian emphasis on the need for spiritual salvation from a spiritual Saviour, who can forgive and set aside sin even though humans are not inherently pure and worthy of such salvation. Paul the Apostle in Romans and I Corinthians placed special emphasis on this doctrine, and stressed that belief in Jesus would allow Christians to overcome death and attain salvation in the hereafter.

Roman Catholics, Eastern Orthodox Christians, and some Protestants{{who|date= November 2018}} teach the Sacrament of [[Baptism]] is the means by which each person's damaged human nature is healed and [[Sanctifying Grace]] (capacity to enjoy and participate in the spiritual life of God) is restored. This is referred to as &quot;being born of water and the Spirit&quot;, following the terminology in the Gospel of St. John. Most Protestants believe this salvific grace comes about at the moment of personal decision to follow Jesus, and that baptism is a symbol of the grace already received.

===Love===
{{Main|Jewish theology of love|Great Commandment|Agape}}
The Hebrew word for &quot;love&quot;, ''ahavah'' (אהבה), is used to describe intimate or romantic feelings or relationships, such as the love between parent and child in Genesis 22:2; 25: 28; 37:3; the love between close friends in I Samuel 18:2, 20:17; or the love between a young man and young woman in [[Song of Songs]]. Christians will often use the Greek of the Septuagint to make distinctions between the types of love: ''[[philia]]'' for brotherly, ''[[Eros (concept)|eros]]'' for romantic and ''[[agape]]'' for self-sacrificing love.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.calvin.edu/~jks4/city/Oord~Defining+Love.pdf|title=James K.A. Smith|website=Calvin College}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Like many Jewish scholars and theologians, literary critic Harold Bloom understands Judaism as fundamentally a religion of love. But he argues that one can understand the Hebrew conception of love only by looking at one of the core commandments of Judaism, Leviticus 19:18, &quot;Love your neighbor as yourself&quot;, also called the second [[Great Commandment]]. Talmudic sages Hillel and [[Rabbi Akiva]] commented that this is a major element of the Jewish religion. Also, this commandment is arguably at the center of the Jewish faith. As the third book of the Torah, Leviticus is literally the central book. Historically, Jews have considered it of central importance: traditionally, children began their study of the Torah with Leviticus, and the midrashic literature on Leviticus is among the longest and most detailed of midrashic literature (see Bamberger 1981: 737). [[Bernard Jacob Bamberger]] considers Leviticus 19, beginning with God's commandment in verse 3—&quot;You shall be holy, for I the Lord your God, am holy&quot;—to be &quot;the climactic chapter of the book, the one most often read and quoted&quot; (1981:889). Leviticus 19:18 is itself the climax of this chapter.

===Abortion===
{{Main|Judaism and abortion|Christianity and abortion}}
The only statements in the Tanakh about the status of a fetus state that killing an unborn infant does not have the same status as killing a born human being, and mandates a much lesser penalty (Exodus 21: 22–25)&lt;ref&gt;Daniel Schiff, 2002,''Abortion in Judaism''Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2002. 9–11&lt;/ref&gt; (although this interpretation is disputed, the passage could refer to an injury to a woman that causes a premature, live birth).

The Talmud states that the fetus is not yet a full human being until it has been born (either the head or the body is mostly outside of the woman), therefore killing a fetus is not murder, and [[abortion]]—in restricted circumstances—has always been legal under Jewish law. [[Rashi]], the great 12th century commentator on the Bible and Talmud, states clearly of the fetus ''lav nefesh hu'': &quot;it is not a person.&quot; The Talmud contains the expression ''ubar yerech imo''—the fetus is as the thigh of its mother,' i.e., the fetus is deemed to be part and parcel of the pregnant woman's body.&quot; The Babylonian Talmud [[Yevamot]] 69b states that: &quot;the embryo is considered to be mere water until the fortieth day.&quot; Afterwards, it is considered subhuman until it is born. Christians who agree with these views may refer to this idea as abortion before the [[quickening]] of the fetus.

Judaism unilaterally supports, in fact [[Pikuach nefesh|mandates]], abortion if doctors believe that it is necessary to save the life of the woman. Many rabbinic authorities allow abortions on the grounds of gross genetic imperfections of the fetus. They also allow abortion if the woman were suicidal because of such defects. However, Judaism holds that abortion is impermissible for family planning or convenience reasons. Each case must be decided individually, however, and the decision should lie with the pregnant woman, the man who impregnated her, and their Rabbi.

===War, violence and pacifism===
{{Unreferenced section|date=April 2009}}
{{main|Christian pacifism}}
Jews and Christians accept as valid and binding many of the same moral principles taught in the Torah. There is a great deal of overlap between the ethical systems of these two faiths. Nonetheless, there are some highly significant doctrinal differences.

Judaism has many teachings about peace and compromise, and its teachings make physical violence the last possible option. Nonetheless, the Talmud teaches that &quot;If someone comes with the intention to murder you, then one is obligated to kill in self-defense [rather than be killed]&quot;. The clear implication is that to bare one's throat would be tantamount to suicide (which Jewish law forbids) and it would also be considered helping a murderer kill someone and thus would &quot;place an obstacle in front of a blind man&quot; (i.e., makes it easier for another person to falter in their ways). The tension between the laws dealing with peace, and the obligation to self-defense, has led to a set of Jewish teachings that have been described as tactical-pacifism. This is the avoidance of force and violence whenever possible, but the use of force when necessary to save the lives of one's self and one's people.

Although killing oneself is forbidden under normal Jewish law as being a denial of God's goodness in the world, under extreme circumstances when there has seemed no choice but to either be killed or forced to betray their religion, Jews have committed [[suicide]] or mass suicide (see [[Masada]], [[History of the Jews in France#First persecution of the Jews|First French persecution of the Jews]], and [[York Castle]] for examples). As a grim reminder of those times, there is even a prayer in the Jewish liturgy for &quot;when the knife is at the throat&quot;, for those dying &quot;to sanctify God's Name&quot;. (See: ''[[Martyrdom]]''). These acts have received mixed responses by Jewish authorities. Where some Jews regard them as examples of heroic martyrdom, but others saying that while Jews should always be willing to face martyrdom if necessary, it was wrong for them to take their own lives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.religionfacts.com/euthanasia/judaism.htm|title=Judaism and Euthanasia|publisher=|access-date=2007-04-16|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060506200930/http://www.religionfacts.com/euthanasia/judaism.htm|archive-date=2006-05-06|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Because Judaism focuses on this life, many questions to do with survival and conflict (such as the classic [[morality|moral]] [[dilemma]] of two people in a desert with only enough water for one to survive) were analysed in great depth by the rabbis within the Talmud, in the attempt to understand the principles a godly person should draw upon in such a circumstance.

The Sermon on the Mount records that Jesus taught that if someone comes to harm you, then one must [[turn the other cheek]]. This has led four Protestant Christian denominations to develop a [[Christian pacifism|theology of pacifism]], the avoidance of force and violence at all times. They are known historically as the ''[[peace churches]]'', and have incorporated Christ's teachings on [[Nonviolent resistance|nonviolence]] into their theology so as to apply it to participation in the use of violent force; those denominations are the [[Religious Society of Friends|Quakers]], [[Mennonites]], [[Amish]], and the [[Church of the Brethren]]. Many other churches have people who hold to the doctrine without making it a part of their doctrines, or who apply it to individuals but not to governments, see also [[Evangelical counsels]]. The vast majority of Christian nations and groups have not adopted this theology, nor have they followed it in practice. See also [[But to bring a sword]].

===Capital punishment===
{{Unreferenced section|date=April 2009}}
{{Further|Religion and capital punishment}}
Although the [[List of capital crimes in the bible|Hebrew Bible has many references to capital punishment]], the Jewish sages used their authority to make it nearly impossible for a [[Sanhedrin|Jewish court]] to impose a death sentence. Even when such a sentence might have been imposed, the [[Cities of Refuge]] and other sanctuaries, were at hand for those [[manslaughter|unintentionally guilty]] of capital offences. It was said in the Talmud about the death penalty in Judaism, that if a court killed more than one person in seventy years, it was a barbarous (or &quot;bloody&quot;) court and should be condemned as such.

Christianity usually reserved the death penalty for [[Christian heresy|heresy]], the denial of the orthodox view of God's view, and [[witchcraft]] or similar non-Christian practices. For example, in Spain, unrepentant Jews were exiled, and it was only those [[Crypto-Judaism|crypto-Jews]] who had accepted baptism under pressure but retained Jewish customs in private, who were punished in this way. It is presently acknowledged by most of Christianity that these uses of capital punishment were deeply immoral.

===Taboo food and drink===
{{Main|Taboo food and drink|Kashrut}}
Orthodox Jews, unlike most Christians, still practice a restrictive diet that has many rules. Most Christians believe that the kosher food laws have been [[Supersessionism|superseded]], for example citing what Jesus taught in [[Mark 7]]: what you eat doesn't make you unclean but what comes out of a man's heart makes him unclean—although Roman Catholicism and Eastern Orthodoxy have their own set of dietary observances. [[Eastern Orthodoxy#Fasting|Eastern Orthodoxy, in particular has very elaborate and strict rules of fasting]], and continues to observe the [[Council of Jerusalem]]'s apostolic decree of Act 15.&lt;ref&gt;[[Karl Josef von Hefele]]'s [http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.viii.v.iv.ii.html commentary on canon II of Gangra] notes: &quot;We further see that, at the time of the Synod of [[Gangra]], the rule of the Apostolic Synod with regard to blood and things strangled was still in force. With the Greeks, indeed, it continued always in force as their Euchologies still show. [[Balsamon]] also, the well-known commentator on the canons of the Middle Ages, in his commentary on the sixty-third [[Canons of the Apostles|Apostolic Canon]], expressly blames the Latins because they had ceased to observe this command. What the Latin Church, however, thought on this subject about the year 400, is shown by [[Augustine of Hippo|Augustine]] in his work [[Contra Faustum]], where he states that the Apostles had given this command in order to unite the heathens and Jews in the one ark of Noah; but that then, when the barrier between Jewish and heathen converts had fallen, this command concerning things strangled and blood had lost its meaning, and was only observed by few. But still, as late as the eighth century, [[Pope Gregory III|Pope Gregory the Third]] (731) forbade the eating of blood or things strangled under threat of a penance of forty days. No one will pretend that the disciplinary enactments of any council, even though it be one of the undisputed [[Ecumenical council|Ecumenical Synods]], can be of greater and more unchanging force than the decree of that first council, held by the Holy Apostles at Jerusalem, and the fact that its decree has been obsolete for centuries in the West is proof that even Ecumenical canons may be of only temporary utility and may be repealed by disuse, like other laws.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Some Christian denominations observe some biblical food laws, for example the practice of [[Ital]] in [[Rastifarianism]]. [[Jehovah's Witnesses]] do not eat blood products and are known for their refusal to accept [[blood transfusion]]s based on not &quot;eating blood&quot;.

==Salvation==
{{Main|Salvation}}
Judaism does not see human beings as inherently flawed or sinful and needful of being saved from it, but rather capable with a free will of being righteous, and unlike Christianity does not closely associate ideas of &quot;salvation&quot; with a New Covenant delivered by a Jewish messiah, although in Judaism Jewish people will have a renewed national commitment of observing God's commandments under the New Covenant, and the [[Jewish Messiah]] will also be ruling at a time of global peace and acceptance of God by all people.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.jewsforjudaism.org/web/faq/general_messiah-criteria02.html |title=JfJ ''Messiah : The Criteria'' |access-date=2007-12-23 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071219214921/http://www.jewsforjudaism.org/web/faq/general_messiah-criteria02.html |archive-date=2007-12-19 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Judaism holds instead that proper living is accomplished through good works and heartfelt [[prayer]], as well as a strong faith in God. Judaism also teaches that gentiles can receive a share in &quot;[[Jewish eschatology|the world to come]]&quot;. This is codified in the Mishna [[Pirkei Avot|Avot]] 4:29, the Babylonian Talmud in tractates [[Avodah Zarah]] 10b, and [[Ketubot]] 111b, and in Maimonides's 12th century law code, the ''[[Mishneh Torah]]'', in ''Hilkhot Melachim'' (Laws of Kings) 8.11.

[[Sola gratia|The Protestant view]] is that every human is a sinner, and being saved by God's grace, not simply by the merit of one's own actions, pardons a damnatory sentence to Hell.&lt;ref&gt;Catechism of the Catholic Church No. 1446. The Vatican.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Forgiveness===
{{main|Forgiveness#Judaism|Forgiveness#Christianity}}
In Judaism, one must go ''to those he has harmed'' in order to be entitled to forgiveness.&lt;ref name = YomKippur&gt;{{cite web | year = 2006 | url = http://www.jewfaq.org/holiday4.htm | title = ''JewFAQ discussion of forgiveness on Yom Kippur'' | accessdate = 2006-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; This means that in Judaism a person cannot obtain forgiveness from God for wrongs the person has done to other people. This also means that, unless the victim forgave the perpetrator before he died, murder is unforgivable in Judaism, and they will answer to God for it, though the victims' family and friends can forgive the murderer for the grief they caused them.

Thus the &quot;reward&quot; for forgiving others is not God's forgiveness for wrongs done to others, but rather help ''in obtaining forgiveness from the other person.''

Sir [[Jonathan Sacks]], Chief Rabbi of the United Hebrew Congregations of the Commonwealth, summarized: &quot;it is not that God forgives, while human beings do not. To the contrary, we believe that just as only God can forgive sins against God, so only human beings can forgive sins against human beings.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | year = 2006 | url = http://www.chiefrabbi.org/thoughts/vayigash5766.pdf | title = ''Covenant and Conversation'' | accessdate = 2009-02-07 | url-status = dead | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20090319205218/http://www.chiefrabbi.org/thoughts/vayigash5766.pdf | archivedate = 2009-03-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Christianity, forgiveness by God is promised to the repentant even though the wronged party has not forgiven the offender: &quot;If we confess our sins, he is faithful and just and will forgive us our sins and purify us from all unrighteousness.&quot; (1 John 1:9 ) Jesus, however, requires his disciples to forgive others if they want to be forgiven themselves. [[Matthew 6:14–15]], which follows the Lord's Prayer, says &quot;For if you forgive men when they sin against you, your heavenly Father will also forgive you. But if you do not forgive men their sins, your Father will not forgive your sins.&quot; Forgiveness is not an option to a Christian, rather one must forgive to be a Christian.

===Judgment===
{{main|Last judgment}}
Both Christianity and Judaism believe in some form of judgment. Most Christians (the exception is [[Full Preterism]]) believe in the future [[Second Coming]] of Jesus, which includes the [[Resurrection of the Dead]] and the [[Last Judgment]]. Those who have accepted Jesus as their personal saviour will be saved and live in God's presence in the [[Kingdom of God|Kingdom of Heaven]], those who have not accepted Jesus as their saviour, will be cast into the [[Lake of fire|Lake of Fire]] (eternal torment, finite torment, or simply annihilated), see for example [[The Sheep and the Goats]].

In Jewish liturgy there is significant prayer and talk of a &quot;book of life&quot; that one is written into, indicating that God judges each person each year even after death. This annual judgment process begins on [[Rosh Hashanah]] and ends with [[Yom Kippur]]. Additionally, God sits daily in judgment concerning a person's daily activities. Upon the anticipated arrival of the [[Messiah]], God will judge the nations for their persecution of Israel during the exile. Later, God will also judge the Jews over their observance of the Torah.

===Heaven and Hell===
{{main|Eschatology|Heaven|Hell}}
There is little Jewish literature on heaven or hell as actual places, and there are few references to the afterlife in the Hebrew Bible. One is the ghostly apparition of Samuel, called up by the [[Witch of Endor]] at King Saul's command. Another is a mention by the [[Prophet Daniel]] of those who sleep in the earth rising to either everlasting life or everlasting abhorrence.&lt;ref&gt;Daniel 12:2&lt;/ref&gt;

Early Hebrew views were more concerned with the fate of the nation of Israel as a whole, rather than with individual immortality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=233&amp;letter=R&amp;search=Resurrection|title=RESURRECTION - JewishEncyclopedia.com|website=jewishencyclopedia.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; A stronger belief in an afterlife for each person developed during the Second Temple period but was contested by various Jewish sects. [[Pharisees]] believed that in death, people rest in their graves until they are physically resurrected with the coming of the Messiah, and within that resurrected body the soul would exist eternally.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=252&amp;letter=P|title=PHARISEES - JewishEncyclopedia.com|website=jewishencyclopedia.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Maimonides also included the concept of resurrection in his [[Jewish principles of faith|Thirteen Principles of Faith]].

Judaism's view is summed up by a biblical observation about the Torah: in the beginning God clothes the naked (Adam), and at the end God buries the dead (Moses). The Children of Israel mourned for 40&amp;nbsp;days, then got on with their lives.

In Judaism, [[Heaven]] is sometimes described as a place where God debates [[Talmuds|Talmudic law]] with the angels, and where Jews spend eternity studying the Written and Oral Torah. Jews do not believe in &quot;Hell&quot; as a place of eternal torment. [[Gehenna]] is a place or condition of [[purgatory]] where Jews spend up to twelve months purifying to get into heaven,{{Citation needed|date=September 2008}} depending on how sinful they have been, although some suggest that certain types of sinners can never be purified enough to go to heaven and rather than facing eternal torment, simply cease to exist. Therefore, some violations like suicide would be punished by separation from the community, such as not being buried in a Jewish cemetery (in practice, rabbis often rule suicides to be mentally incompetent and thus not responsible for their actions). Judaism also does not have a notion of hell as a place ruled by [[Satan]] since God's dominion is total and Satan is only one of God's angels.

Catholics also believe in a [[purgatory]] for those who are going to heaven, but Christians in general believe that Hell is a fiery place of torment that never ceases, called the [[Lake of Fire]]. A small minority believe this is not permanent, and that those who go there will eventually either be saved or cease to exist. Heaven for Christians is depicted in various ways. As the [[Kingdom of God]] described in the New Testament and particularly the [[Book of Revelation]], Heaven is a new or restored earth, a [[World to Come]], free of sin and death, with a [[New Jerusalem]] led by God, Jesus, and the most righteous of believers starting with [[144,000]] Israelites from every tribe, and all others who received salvation living peacefully and making [[pilgrimages]] to give glory to the city.&lt;ref&gt;Book of Revelation 20–22&lt;/ref&gt;

In Christianity, promises of Heaven and Hell as rewards and punishments are often used to motivate good and bad behavior, as threats of disaster were used by prophets like [[Jeremiah]] to motivate the Israelites. Modern Judaism generally rejects this form of motivation, instead teaching to do the right thing because it's the right thing to do. As Maimonides wrote:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;A man should not say: I shall carry out the precepts of the Torah and study her wisdom in order to receive all the blessings written therein or in order to merit the life of the World to Come and I shall keep away from the sins forbidden by the Torah in order to be spared the curses mentioned in the Torah or in order not to be cut off from the life of the World to Come. It is not proper to serve God in this fashion. For one who serves thus serves out of fear. Such a way is not that of the prophets and sages. Only the ignorant, and the women and children serve God in this way. These are trained to serve out of fear until they obtain sufficient knowledge to serve out of love. One who serves God out of love studies the Torah and practices the precepts and walks in the way of wisdom for no ulterior motive at all, neither out of fear of evil nor in order to acquire the good, but follows the truth because it is true and the good will follow the merit of attaining to it. It is the stage of Abraham our father whom the Holy One, blessed be God, called &quot;My friend&quot; (Isaiah 41:8 – ''ohavi'' = the one who loves me) because he served out of love alone. It is regarding this stage that the Holy One, Blessed be God, commanded us through Moses, as it is said: &quot;You shall love the Lord your God&quot; (Deuteronomy 6:5). When man loves God with a love that is fitting he automatically carries out all the precepts of love.
(Maimonides ''Yad'' Chapter 10, quoted in Jacobs 1973: 159)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===The Messiah===
{{Main|Messiah}}
Jews believe that a descendant of [[King David]] will one day appear to restore the Kingdom of Israel and usher in an era of peace, prosperity, and spiritual understanding for Israel and all the nations of the world. Jews refer to this person as [[Jewish eschatology|Moshiach]] or &quot;anointed one&quot;, translated as messiah in English. The traditional Jewish understanding of the messiah is that he is fully human and born of human parents without any supernatural element. The messiah is expected to have a relationship with God similar to that of the [[Nevi'im|prophets]] of the Tanakh. In his commentary on the Talmud, Maimonides (Rabbi Moshe ben Maimon) wrote:

:All of the people Israel will come back to Torah; The people of Israel will be gathered back to the land of Israel; The Temple in Jerusalem will be rebuilt; Israel will live among the nations as an equal, and will be strong enough to defend herself; Eventually, war, hatred and famine will end, and an era of peace and prosperity will come upon the Earth.

He adds:
:&quot;And if a king shall stand up from among the House of David, studying Torah and indulging in commandments like his father David, according to the written and oral Torah, and he will coerce all Israel to follow it and to strengthen its weak points, and will fight The Lord's wars, this one is to be treated as if he were the anointed one. If he succeeded [and won all nations surrounding him. Old prints and mss.] and built a Holy Temple in its proper place and gathered the strayed ones of Israel together, this is indeed the anointed one for certain, and he will mend the entire world to worship the Lord together ... But if he did not succeed until now, or if he was killed, it becomes known that he is not this one of whom the Torah had promised us, and he is indeed like all [other] proper and wholesome kings of the House of David who died.&quot;

He also clarified the nature of the Messiah:
:&quot;Do not imagine that the anointed King must perform miracles and signs and create new things in the world or resurrect the dead and so on. The matter is not so: For Rabbi Akiba was a great scholar of the sages of the Mishnah, and he was the assistant-warrior of the king Ben Coziba Simon bar Kokhba... He and all the Sages of his generation deemed him the anointed king, until he was killed by sins; only since he was killed, they knew that he was not. The Sages asked him neither a miracle nor a sign...&quot;

The Christian view of Jesus as Messiah goes beyond such claims and is the fulfillment and union of three anointed offices; a prophet like Moses who delivers God's commands and covenant and frees people from bondage, a High Priest in the order of [[Melchizedek]] overshadowing the [[Levite priesthood]] and a king like King David ruling over Jews, and like God ruling over the whole world and coming from the line of David.

For Christians, Jesus is also [[hypostatic union|fully human and fully divine]] as the [[Logos|Word of God]] who sacrifices himself so that humans can receive salvation. Jesus [[Session of Christ|sits]] in [[Heaven (Christianity)|Heaven]] at the [[Right Hand of God]] and will [[Last Judgment|judge humanity]] in the [[end times]] when he [[Second Coming of Christ|returns to earth]].

Christian readings of the Hebrew Bible find many references to Jesus. This can take the form of specific prophesy, and in other cases of foreshadowing by [[Typology (theology)|types]] or forerunners. Traditionally, most Christian readings of the Bible maintained that almost every prophecy was actually about the coming of Jesus, and that the entire Old Testament of the Bible is a prophecy about the [[Ministry of Jesus|coming of Jesus]].

====Catholic views====
Catholicism teaches ''[[Extra Ecclesiam Nulla Salus]]'' (&quot;Outside the Church there is no salvation&quot;), which some, like Fr. [[Leonard Feeney]], interpreted as limiting salvation to Catholics only. At the same time, it does not deny the possibility that those not visibly members of the Church may attain salvation as well. In recent times, its teaching has been most notably expressed in the Vatican II council documents ''[[Unitatis Redintegratio]]'' (1964), ''[[Lumen gentium]]'' (1964), ''[[Nostra aetate]]'' (1965), an encyclical issued by Pope John Paul II: ''[[Ut unum sint]]'' (1995), and in a document issued by the [[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith]], ''[[Dominus Iesus]]'' in 2000. The latter document has been criticised for claiming that non-Christians are in a &quot;gravely deficient situation&quot; as compared to Catholics, but also adds that &quot;for those who are not formally and visibly members of the Church, salvation in Christ is accessible by virtue of a grace which, while having a mysterious relationship to the Church, does not make them formally part of the Church, but enlightens them in a way which is accommodated to their spiritual and material situation.&quot;

[[Pope John Paul II]] on October 2, 2000 emphasized that this document did not say that non-Christians were actively denied salvation: &quot;...this confession does not deny salvation to non-Christians, but points to its ultimate source in Christ, in whom man and God are united&quot;. On December 6 the Pope issued a statement to further emphasize that the Church continued to support its traditional stance that salvation was available to believers of other faiths: &quot;The gospel teaches us that those who live in accordance with the Beatitudes—the poor in spirit, the pure of heart, those who bear lovingly the sufferings of life—will enter God's kingdom.&quot; He further added, &quot;All who seek God with a sincere heart, including those who do not know Christ and his church, contribute under the influence of Grace to the building of this Kingdom.&quot; On August 13, 2002 American Catholic bishops issued a joint statement with leaders of [[Reform Judaism|Reform]] and [[Conservative Judaism]], called &quot;Reflections on Covenant and Mission&quot;, which affirmed that Christians should not target Jews for conversion. The document stated: &quot;Jews already dwell in a saving covenant with God&quot; and &quot;Jews are also called by God to prepare the world for God's Kingdom.&quot; However, many Christian denominations still believe it is their duty to reach out to &quot;unbelieving&quot; Jews.

In December 2015, the [[Holy See|Vatican]] released a 10,000-word document that, among other things, stated that Jews do not need to be converted to find salvation, and that Catholics should work with Jews to fight antisemitism.&lt;ref name=&quot;NPR.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2015/12/10/459223058/catholics-should-not-try-to-convert-jews-vatican-commission-says|title=Catholics Should Not Try To Convert Jews, Vatican Commission Says|date=10 December 2015|work=NPR.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Philip Pullella&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-pope-jews-idUSKBN0TT1BK20151210#bdz0KPLr1Y8xfUAR.97|title=Vatican says Catholics should not try to convert Jews, should fight anti-semitism|author=Philip Pullella|date=10 December 2015|work=Reuters}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;news.va&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.news.va/en/news/vatican-issues-new-document-on-christian-jewish-di|title=Vatican issues new document on Christian-Jewish dialogue|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Eastern Orthodox views====
{{unreferenced section|date=July 2019}}
Eastern Orthodox Christianity emphasizes a continuing life of repentance or ''metanoia'', which includes an increasing improvement in thought, belief and action. Regarding the salvation of Jews, [[Muslims]], and other non-Christians, the Orthodox have traditionally taught that there is no salvation outside the church. Orthodoxy recognizes that other religions may contain truth, to the extent that they are in agreement with Christianity.

God is thought to be good, just, and merciful; it would not seem just to condemn someone because they never heard the Gospel message, or were taught a distorted version of the Gospel by [[Heresy|heretics]]. Therefore, the reasoning goes, they must at some point have an opportunity to make a genuine informed decision.{{citation needed|date=December 2010}} Ultimately, those who persist in rejecting God condemn themselves, by cutting themselves off from the ultimate source of all Life, and from the God who is Love embodied. Jews, Muslims, and members of other faiths, then, are expected to convert to Christianity in the afterlife.

===Proselytizing===
Judaism is not a [[proselytizing]] religion. Orthodox Judaism deliberately makes it very difficult to [[Conversion to Judaism|convert]] and become a Jew, and requires a significant and full-time effort in living, study, righteousness, and conduct over several years. The final decision is by no means a foregone conclusion. A person cannot become Jewish by marrying a Jew, or by joining a synagogue, nor by any degree of involvement in the community or religion, but only by explicitly undertaking intense, formal, and supervised work over years aimed towards that goal. Some{{which|date= November 2018}} less strict versions of Judaism have made this process somewhat easier but it is still far from common.

In the past, Judaism was more evangelistic,&lt;ref&gt;H.H. Ben-Sasson's ''A History of the Jewish People'', Harvard University Press, 1976, {{ISBN|0-674-39731-2}}, p. 288: &quot;Explicit evidence of a systematic attempt to propagate the Jewish faith in the city of Rome is found as early as 139 BCE. With the increase of the Jewish population of Rome, the Jews intensified their efforts to make converts among the Romans. Although the activity of Jewish missionaries in Roman society caused Tiberius to expel them from that city in 19 CE, they soon returned, and Jewish religious propaganda was resumed and maintained even after the destruction of the Temple. Tacitus mentions it regretfully (''Histories'' 5.5), and Juvenal, in his Fourteenth Satire (11. 96ff.), describes how Roman families 'degenerated' into Judaism: the fathers permitted themselves to adopt some of its customs and the sons became Jews in every respect. ... the Bible provided the apostles of Judaism with a literature unparalleled in any other religion.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; but this was often more akin just to &quot;greater openness to converts&quot; rather than active soliciting of conversions. Since Jews believe that one need not be a Jew to approach God, there is no religious pressure to convert non-Jews to their faith.

The [[Chabad-Lubavitch]] branch of [[Hasidic Judaism]] has been an exception to this non-proselytizing standard, since in recent decades it has been actively promoting Noahide Laws for gentiles as an alternative to Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.noahide.org/article.asp?Level=493&amp;Parent=88 ''The Seven Laws of Noah and the Non-Jews who Follow Them ''] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071128101917/http://noahide.org/article.asp?Level=493&amp;Parent=88 |date=2007-11-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/z?c102:H.J.RES.104.ENR:], 102nd Congress of the United States of America, March 5, 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;

By contrast, Christianity is an explicitly [[evangelism|evangelistic]] religion. Christians are commanded by Jesus to &quot;[[Great Commission|Therefore go and make disciples of all nations]]&quot;. Historically, evangelism has on rare occasions led to [[forced conversion]] under threat of death or mass expulsion.

==Mutual views==

===Common Jewish views of Christianity===
{{Main|Judaism's view of Jesus}}
Many Jews view Jesus as one in a long list of failed [[List of messiah claimants|Jewish claimants to be the Messiah]], none of whom fulfilled the [[Jewish view of Jesus#Prophecy and Jesus|tests]] of a prophet specified in the Law of Moses. Others see Jesus as a teacher who worked with the gentiles and ascribe the messianic claims that Jews find objectionable to his later followers. Because much physical and spiritual violence was done to Jews in the name of Jesus and his followers,{{citation needed|date=May 2012}} and because [[evangelism]] is still an active aspect of many church's activities, many Jews are uncomfortable with discussing Jesus and treat him as a [[Yeshu|non-person]]. In answering the question &quot;What do Jews think of Jesus&quot;, philosopher Milton Steinberg claims, for Jews, Jesus cannot be accepted as anything more than a teacher. &quot;In only a few respects did Jesus deviate from the Tradition,&quot; Steinberg concludes, &quot;and in all of them, Jews believe, he blundered.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;M. Steinberg, 1975 ''Basic Judaism'' p. 108, New York: Harcourt, Brace Jovanovich&lt;/ref&gt;

Judaism does not believe that God requires the sacrifice of any human. This is emphasized in Jewish traditions concerning the story of the [[Binding of Isaac|Akedah]], the binding of Isaac. In the Jewish explanation, this is a story in the Torah whereby God wanted to test Abraham's faith and willingness, and Isaac was never going to be actually sacrificed. Thus, Judaism rejects the notion that anyone can or should die for anyone else's sin.&lt;ref&gt;Spiegel, 1993&lt;/ref&gt; Judaism is more focused on the practicalities of understanding how one may live a sacred life in the world according to God's will, rather than a hope of a future one. Judaism does not believe in the Christian concept of hell but does have a punishment stage in the afterlife (i.e. Gehenna, a term that also appears in the New Testament and translated as hell) as well as a Heaven ([[Olam Haba|Gan Eden]]), but the religion does not intend it as a focus.

Judaism views the worship of Jesus as inherently polytheistic, and rejects the Christian attempts to explain the [[Trinity]] as a complex monotheism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/trinity/judaic-islamic-trinity.html|title=Trinity &gt; Judaic and Islamic Objections (Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy)|website=plato.stanford.edu|access-date=2020-01-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Christian festivals have no religious significance in Judaism and are not celebrated, but some secular Jews in the West treat [[Christmas]] as a secular holiday.

===Common Christian views of Judaism===
Christians believe that Christianity is the fulfillment and successor of Judaism, retaining much of its doctrine and many of its practices including [[monotheism]], the belief in a Messiah, and certain forms of worship like prayer and reading from religious texts. Christians believe that Judaism requires blood sacrifice to atone for sins, and believe that Judaism has abandoned this since the [[destruction of the Second Temple]]. Most Christians consider the Mosaic Law to have been a necessary intermediate stage, but that once the [[crucifixion of Jesus]] occurred, adherence to civil and ceremonial Law was superseded by the New Covenant.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Hebrews+7:11-28;&amp;version=31;|title=Bible Gateway passage: Hebrews 7:11-28 - New International Version|website=Bible Gateway}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some Christians{{who|date= November 2018}} adhere to [[New Covenant theology]], which states that with the arrival of his New Covenant, Jews have ceased being blessed under his [[Mosaic covenant]]. This position has been softened or disputed by other Christians{{who|date= November 2018}}, where Jews are recognized to have a special status under the [[Abrahamic covenant]]. New Covenant theology is thus in contrast to [[Dual-covenant theology]].{{citation needed|date= November 2018}}

Some Christians{{who|date= November 2018}} who view the Jewish people as close to God seek to understand and incorporate elements of Jewish understanding or perspective into their beliefs as a means to [[Philo-Semitism|respect]] their &quot;parent&quot; religion of Judaism, or to more fully seek out and return to their Christian roots. Christians embracing aspects of Judaism are sometimes criticized as Biblical [[Judaizers]] by Christians when they pressure gentile Christians to observe Mosaic teachings rejected by most modern Christians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.tabletmag.com/jewish-life-and-religion/161086/observing-torah-like-jesus | title=FOR SOME BELIEVERS TRYING TO CONNECT WITH JESUS, THE ANSWER IS TO LIVE LIKE A JEW | work=Tablet | date=4 February 2014 | accessdate=27 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Messianic Judaism ===
{{Main|Messianic Judaism}}

=== Jewish Christians ===
{{Main|Jewish Christian}}
Some scholars have found evidence of continuous interactions between Jewish-Christian and rabbinic movements from the mid- to late second century CE to the fourth century CE.&lt;ref&gt;See for instance: Lily C. Vuong, ''Gender and Purity in the Protevangelium of James'', WissenschaftlicheUntersuchungen zum Neuen Testament 2.358 (Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2013), 210–13; Jonathan Bourgel, &quot;The Holders of the “Word of Truth”: The Pharisees in Pseudo-Clementine Recognitions 1.27–71,&quot; ''Journal of Early Christian Studies'' 25.2 (2017) 171–200.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Inter-relationship==
{{See also|Split of early Christianity and Judaism|Christian anti-Judaism|Anti-Christian}}
In addition to each having varied views on the other as a religion, there has also been a long and often painful [[Christianity and anti-Semitism|history]] of conflict, persecution and at times, reconciliation, between the two religions, which have influenced their mutual views of their relationship over time.

Since the time of the [[History of Christianity during the Middle Ages|Middle Ages]], the [[Catholic Church]] upheld ''Constitution pro Judæis'' (Formal Statement on the Jews), which stated {{quotation|We decree that no Christian shall use violence to force them to be baptized, so long as they are unwilling and refuse. ... Without the judgment of the political authority of the land, no Christian shall presume to wound them or kill them or rob them of their money or change the good customs that they have thus far enjoyed in the place where they live.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;BaskinSeeskin2010&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Baskin|first1=Judith R.|last2=Seeskin|first2=Kenneth|title=The Cambridge Guide to Jewish History, Religion, and Culture|date=12 July 2010|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=9780521869607|page=120}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[Persecution]], forcible conversion, and forcible [[Forced migration|displacement]] of Jews ([[i.e.]] [[hate crime]]s) occurred for many centuries, with occasional gestures to reconciliation from time to time. [[Pogroms]] were common throughout Christian Europe, including organized violence, restrictive land ownership and professional lives, forcible relocation and [[ghetto]]ization, mandatory dress codes, and at times humiliating actions and [[torture]]. All had major effects on Jewish cultures. There have also been non-coercive outreach and missionary efforts such as the [[Church of England]]'s [[Church's Ministry Among Jewish People|Ministry Among Jewish People]], founded in 1809.

For Martin Buber, Judaism and Christianity were variations on the same theme of messianism.  Buber made this theme the basis of a famous definition of the tension between Judaism and Christianity:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Pre-messianically, our destinies are divided. Now to the Christian, the Jew is the incomprehensibly obdurate man who declines to see what has happened; and to the Jew, the Christian is the incomprehensibly daring man who affirms in an unredeemed world that its redemption has been accomplished. This is a gulf which no human power can bridge.&lt;ref&gt;Martin Buber, &quot;The Two Foci of the Jewish Soul&quot;, cited in The Writings of Martin Buber, Will Herberg (editor), New York: Meridian Books, 1956, p. 276.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The [[Nazi Party]] was known for its [[Kirchenkampf|persecution of Christian Churches]]; many of them, such as the Protestant [[Confessing Church]] and the Catholic Church,&lt;ref&gt;Gill, Anton (1994). An Honourable Defeat; A History of the German Resistance to Hitler. Heinemann Mandarin. 1995 paperback {{ISBN|978-0-434-29276-9}}; p. 57&lt;/ref&gt; as well as [[Quakers]] and [[Jehovah's Witnesses]], aided and rescued Jews who were being targeted by the antireligious régime.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gottfried2001&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Gottfried|first=Ted|title=Heroes of the Holocaust|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sdKyZVcVmuQC&amp;pg=PA25|accessdate=14 January 2017|year=2001|publisher=Twenty-First Century Books|isbn=9780761317173|pages=24–25|quote=Some groups that are known to have helped Jews were religious in nature. One of these was the Confessing Church, a Protestant denomination formed in May 1934, the year after Hitler became chancellor of Germany. One of its goals was to repeal the Nazi law &quot;which required that the civil service would be purged of all those who were either Jewish or of partly Jewish descent.&quot; Another was to help those &quot;who suffered through repressive laws, or violence.&quot; About 7,000 of the 17,000 Protestant clergy in Germany joined the Confessing Church. Much of their work has one unrecognized, but two who will never forget them are Max Krakauer and his wife. Sheltered in sixty-six houses and helped by more than eighty individuals who belonged to the Confessing Church, they owe them their lives. German Catholic churches went out of their way to protect Catholics of Jewish ancestry. More inclusive was the principled stand taken by Catholic Bishop Clemens Count von Galen of Munster. He publicly denounced the Nazi slaughter of Jews and actually succeeded in having the problem halted for a short time. ... Members of the Society of Friends—German Quakers working with organizations of Friends from other countries—were particularly successful in rescuing Jews. ... Jehovah's Witnesses, themselves targeted for concentration camps, also provided help to Jews.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the [[The Holocaust|Holocaust]], attempts have been made to construct a new Jewish-Christian relationship of mutual respect for differences, through the inauguration of the interfaith body the [[Council of Christians and Jews]] in 1942 and [[International Council of Christians and Jews]]. The [[Seelisberg Conference]] in 1947 established 10 points relating to the sources of [[Christian antisemitism]]. The ICCJ's &quot;Twelve points of Berlin&quot; sixty years later aim to reflect a recommitment to interreligious dialogue between the two communities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.iccj.org/en/index.php?id=455 |title=Home |publisher=Iccj.org |date=2012-02-23 |accessdate=2012-08-15 }}{{Dead link|date=July 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Pope [[John Paul II]] and the Catholic Church have &quot;upheld the Church's acceptance of the continuing and permanent election of the Jewish people&quot; as well as a [[Dual-covenant theology|reaffirmation of the covenant]] between [[God in Christianity|God]] and the Jews.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wigoder1988&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Wigoder|first=Geoffrey|title=Jewish-Christian Relations Since the Second World War|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9N9RAQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA87|accessdate=14 January 2017|year=1988|publisher=Manchester University Press|language=English|isbn=9780719026393|page=87}}&lt;/ref&gt; In December 2015, the [[Holy See|Vatican]] released a 10,000-word document that, among other things, stated that Catholics should work with Jews to fight antisemitism.&lt;ref name=&quot;NPR.org&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Philip Pullella&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;news.va&quot;/&gt;

===Orthodox Rabbinic Statement on Christianity===
On December 3, 2015, the [[Center for Jewish-Christian Understanding and Cooperation]] (CJCUC) spearheaded a petition of orthodox rabbis from around the world calling for increased partnership between Jews and Christians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.breakingisraelnews.com/55561/groundbreaking-petition-signed-leading-rabbis-calls-increased-partnership-between-jews-christians-biblical-zionism/|title=Groundbreaking Petition Signed by Leading Rabbis Calls for Increased Partnership Between Jews and Christians|first= Adam Eliyahu|last=Berkowitz|publisher=Breaking Israel News|date=7 December 2015|access-date=29 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thejewishweek.com/news/national/modern-orthodox-leaders-bless-interfaith-dialogue|title=Modern Orthodox Leaders Bless Interfaith Dialogue|first=Steve|last=Lipman|publisher=[[The Jewish Week]]|date=8 December 2015|access-date=29 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.post-gazette.com/news/nation/2015/12/11/Vatican-Orthodox-rabbis-issue-interfaith-statements-affirming-each-other-s-faith/stories/201512110164|title=Vatican, Orthodox rabbis issue interfaith statements affirming each other’s faith|first=Peter|last=Smith|newspaper=[[Pittsburgh Post-Gazette]]|date=11 December 2015|access-date=29 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/rabbi-shmuly-yanklowitz/towards-jewish-christian-reconciliation_b_9133926.html|title=Towards Jewish-Christian Reconciliation &amp; Partnership|first=Rabbi Shmuly|last=Yanklowitz|work=[[Huffington Post]]|date=3 February 2016|access-date=29 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.jpost.com/Blogs/Intellectual-Judaism/Mutual-Judeo-Christian-spiritual-foundation-of-Judaism-and-Christianity-444183|title=Mutual Judeo-Christian spiritual foundation of Judaism and Christianity|first=Vladimir|last=Minkov|newspaper=[[Jerusalem Post]]|date=7 February 2016|accessdate=29 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;vaticanradio&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://en.radiovaticana.va/news/2015/12/10/orthodox_rabbis_issue_groundbreaking_statement_on_christians/1193458|title=Orthodox Rabbis issue groundbreaking statement on Christianity|publisher=[[Vatican Radio]]|date=10 December 2015|access-date=29 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The unprecedented [[Center for Jewish-Christian Understanding and Cooperation#Orthodox Rabbinic Statement on Christianity|Orthodox Rabbinic Statement on Christianity]], entitled ''&quot;To Do the Will of Our Father in Heaven: Toward a Partnership between Jews and Christians&quot;'', was initially signed by over 25 prominent Orthodox rabbis in Israel, United States and Europe&lt;ref name=&quot;vaticanradio&quot; /&gt; and now has over 60 signatories.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cjcuc.com/site/2015/12/03/orthodox-rabbinic-statement-on-christianity/|title=Orthodox Rabbinic Statement on Christianity – To Do the Will of Our Father in Heaven – Toward a Partnership between Jews and Christians|website=CJCUC|date=3 December 2015|access-date=29 October 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161016174221/http://cjcuc.com/site/2015/12/03/orthodox-rabbinic-statement-on-christianity/|archive-date=16 October 2016|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Between Jerusalem and Rome===
On August 31, 2017, representatives of the [[Conference of European Rabbis]], the [[Rabbinical Council of America]], and the Commission of the [[Chief Rabbinate of Israel]] issued and presented the [[Holy See]] with a statement entitled ''Between Jerusalem and Rome''. The document pays particular tribute to the Second Vatican Council's Declaration ''[[Nostra Aetate]]'', whose fourth chapter represents the “Magna Carta” of the Holy See's dialogue with the Jewish world. The Statement ''Between Jerusalem and Rome'' does not hide the theological differences that exist between the two faith traditions while all the same it expresses a firm resolve to collaborate more closely, now and in the future.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://w2.vatican.va/content/francesco/en/speeches/2017/august/documents/papa-francesco_20170831_delegazione-rabbini.html|title=Address of His Holiness Pope Francis to the Delegation of Rabbis for the Presenration of the Statement &quot;Between Jerusalem and Rome&quot;|website=[[Vatican Publishing House|The Vatican]]|date=31 August 2017|access-date=3 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jcrelations.net/Between_Jerusalem_and_Rome_-.5580.0.html?|title=Between Jerusalem and Rome - כלל ופרט בין ירושלים לרומי|website=Jewish-Christian Relations|date=31 August 2017|access-date=3 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{columns-list|colwidth=30em|
* [[Christianity and Islam]]
* [[Christian–Jewish reconciliation]]
* [[Christian views on the Old Covenant]]
* [[Islamic–Jewish relations]]
* [[Judeo-Christian]]
* [[Messianic Judaism]]
* [[Mormonism and Judaism]]
* [[Noahidism]]
* [[Relations between Eastern Orthodoxy and Judaism|Orthodox Christianity and Judaism]]
* [[Pope John Paul II and Judaism]]
* [[Relations between Catholicism and Judaism|Roman Catholicism and Judaism]]
* [[Supersessionism]]
* [[Split of Christianity and Judaism]]
}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Bamberger, Bernard (1981). &quot;Commentary to Leviticus&quot; in ''The Torah: A Modern Commentary'', edited by W. Gunther Plaut, New York: [[Union of American Hebrew Congregations]]. {{ISBN|0-8074-0055-6}}
* Bloom, Harold (2005). ''Jesus and Yahweh: The Names Divine'', Riverhead. {{ISBN|1-57322-322-0}}
* Herberg, Will (1951). ''Judaism and Modern Man: An Interpretation of Jewish religion'', Jewish Publication Society. {{ISBN|0-689-70232-9}}
* Jacobs, Louis (1973). ''A Jewish Theology'', Behrman House. {{ISBN|0-87441-226-9}}
* Rosenzweig, Franz (2005). ''The Star of Redemption'', [[University of Wisconsin Press]]. {{ISBN|0-299-20724-2}}
* Rouvière, Jean-Marc (2006). ''Brèves méditations sur la création du monde'', L'Harmattan Paris.
* Speigel, Shalom (1993). ''The Last Trial: On the Legends and Lore of the Command to Abraham to Offer Isaac As a Sacrifice: The Akedah'', Jewish Lights Publishing; Reprint edition. {{ISBN|1-879045-29-X}}
* Welker, Carmen (2007). ''Should Christians be Torah Observant?'', Netzari Press. {{ISBN|978-1-934916-00-1}}
*Zuckermann, Ghil'ad (2006). &quot;'[[folk etymology|Etymythological]] [[Othering]]' and the Power of 'Lexical Engineering' in [[Judaism]], [[Islam]] and [[Christianity]]. A Socio-Philo(sopho)logical Perspective&quot;, ''Explorations in the Sociology of [[Language]] and [[Religion]]'', edited by Tope Omoniyi and Joshua A. Fishman, Amsterdam: John Benjamins, pp.&amp;nbsp;237–258. {{ISBN|90-272-2710-1}}

==External links==
* [http://www.religioustolerance.org/rcc_othe.htm Roman Catholic Church's views on other faiths]
* [http://JewishStudies.eteacherbiblical.com Jewish Studies for Christians Online Study Group by Dr. Eli]
* [http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=489&amp;letter=C&amp;search=Christianity Jewish Encyclopedia: Christianity in its Relation to Judaism]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080412081828/http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=245&amp;letter=N&amp;search=New%20Testament#700 Jewish Encyclopedia: New Testament: For and Against the Law]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20160304030959/http://www.levant.info/MER039.html A Rival, a Relative, or Both? Differing Christian Stances Toward Judaism Over Two Millennia] by Dr. Graham Keith (Middle East Resources)
*[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/cfaith/pcb_documents/rc_con_cfaith_doc_20020212_popolo-ebraico_en.html The Pontifical Biblical Commission: The Jewish People and their Sacred Scriptures in the Christian Bible]

{{Christianity and Judaism}}
{{Jews and Judaism}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Christianity And Judaism}}
[[Category:Christianity and Judaism| ]]</text>
      <sha1>kclrxlmihbue6l5b8t2qna7r7boilv2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
