  <page>
    <title>Commodore (rank)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7581</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941846630</id>
      <parentid>941846512</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-21T01:12:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Thecorrector21</username>
        <id>37935088</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Military ranks}}
{{Navalranks}}

'''Commodore''' is a senior [[military rank|naval rank]] used in many [[navy|navies]] which is equivalent to [[Brigadier]] and [[Air Commodore]] that is superior to a navy [[Captain (Navy)|captain]], but below a [[rear admiral]]. It is either regarded as the most junior of the flag officers rank or may not hold the jurisdiction of a flag officer at all depending on the officer's appointment. Non-English-speaking nations often use the rank of [[flotilla admiral]], [[counter admiral]], or [[senior captain]] as an equivalent, although counter admiral may also correspond to rear admiral.

Traditionally, &quot;commodore&quot; is the title for any officer assigned to command more than one ship at a time, even temporarily, much as &quot;captain&quot; is the traditional title for the commanding officer of a single ship even if the officer's official title in the service is a lower rank. As an official rank, a commodore typically commands a [[flotilla]] or [[squadron (naval)|squadron]] of ships as part of a larger [[task force]] or [[naval fleet]] commanded by an [[admiral]].  A commodore's ship is typically designated by the flying of a [[broad pennant]], as opposed to an admiral's flag. 

It is often regarded as a [[one-star rank]] with a [[NATO]] code of [[OF-6]] (which is known in the U.S. as &quot;[[rear admiral]] (lower half)&quot;), but whether it is regarded as a [[flag rank]] varies between countries.&lt;ref&gt;Whether &quot;commodore&quot; is a [[flag rank]] (or not) varies by country. Often, &quot;rear admiral&quot; is the first of the &quot;flag ranks&quot;. For example, it was not until 2001 that the UK made &quot;commodore&quot; a &quot;flag rank&quot;, and changed the shoulder rank insignia (although not the cuff rings) of the higher ranking admirals accordingly. Australia made this change in the mid-1990s, and also changed the commodore rank insignia to include a star.&lt;/ref&gt;

It is sometimes abbreviated: as &quot;Cdre&quot; in British Royal Navy, &quot;CDRE&quot; in the US Navy, &quot;Cmdre&quot; in the Royal Canadian Navy, &quot;COMO&quot; in the Spanish Navy and in some navies speaking the Spanish language, or &quot;CMDE&quot; as used in some other Navies of several countries.&lt;ref&gt;The &quot;Cdre&quot; abbreviation for the OF-6 rank of commodore is sometimes confused with the &quot;Cmdr&quot; abbreviation for the OF-4 rank of &quot;[[commander]]&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology==
The rank of commodore derives from the [[French language|French]] ''commandeur'', which was one of the highest ranks in the [[orders of knighthood]], and in [[Military order (monastic society)|military orders]] the title of the knight in charge of a ''commande'' (a local part of the order's territorial possessions).

==History==
The [[Dutch Navy]] also used the rank of ''[[commandeur]]'' from the end of the 16th century for a variety of temporary positions, until it became a conventional permanent rank in 1955. The [[Royal Netherlands Air Force]] has adopted the English spelling of ''commodore'' for an equivalent rank.

In the [[Royal Navy]], [[commodore (Royal Navy)|the position]] was introduced in the 17th Century to combat the cost of appointing more admirals—a costly business with a fleet as large as the Royal Navy's at that time.

The rank of commodore was at first a position created as a temporary title to be bestowed upon captains who commanded [[Squadron (naval)|squadrons]] of more than one vessel. In many navies, the rank of commodore was merely viewed as a [[senior captain]] position, whereas other naval services bestowed upon the rank of commodore the prestige of [[flag officer]] status.

=== United States ===
{{main|Commodore (United States)}}
In 1899, the substantive rank of commodore was discontinued in the [[United States Navy]], but revived during World War II in both the U.S. Navy and [[U.S. Coast Guard]]. It was discontinued as a rank in these services during the postwar period, but as an appointment, the title &quot;commodore&quot; was then used to identify senior [[captain (U.S. Navy)|U.S. Navy captains]] who commanded squadrons of more than one vessel or functional air wings or air groups that were not part of a carrier air wing or carrier air group. Concurrently, until the early 1980s, [[U.S. Navy]] and [[U.S. Coast Guard]] captains selected for promotion to the rank of [[rear admiral]] (lower half), would wear the same insignia as rear admiral (upper half), i.e., two silver stars for collar insignia or sleeve braid of one wide and one narrow gold stripe, even though they were actually only equivalent to one-star officers and paid at the one-star rate.

To correct this inequity, the rank of commodore as a single star flag officer was reinstated by both services in the early 1980s. This immediately caused confusion with those senior U.S. Navy captains commanding destroyer squadrons, submarine squadrons, functional air wings and air groups, and so on, who held the temporary &quot;title&quot; of commodore while in their major command billet. As a result of this confusion, the services soon renamed the new one-star rank as [[commodore admiral]] (CADM) within the first six months following the rank's reintroduction. However, this was considered an awkward title and the one-star flag rank was renamed a few months later to its current title of rear admiral (lower half), later abbreviated by the U.S. Navy and U.S. Coast Guard as RDML.

The &quot;title&quot; of commodore continues to be used in the U.S. Navy and Coast Guard for those senior captains in command of organizations consisting of groups of ships or submarines organized into [[Squadron (naval)|squadrons]]; air wings or air groups of multiple [[Squadron (aviation)|aviation squadrons]] other than carrier air wings (the latter whose commanders still use the title &quot;[[Commander, Air Group|CAG]]&quot;); explosive ordnance disposal ([[Explosive Ordnance Disposal|EOD]]), mine warfare and special warfare ([[United States Navy SEALs|SEAL]]) groups; Mobile Inshore Underwater Warfare (MIUW) groups; and construction ([[SeaBee]]) regiments. Although not flag officers, modern day commodores in the U.S. Navy rate a blue and white command pennant, also known as a [[broad pennant]], that is normally flown at their headquarters facilities ashore or from ships that they are embarked aboard when they are the senior officer present afloat (SOPA).

===Argentina===
In the Argentine Navy, the position of commodore was created in the late 1990s, and is usually, but not always, issued to senior captains holding rear-admirals' positions. It is not a rank but a distinction and, as such, can be issued by the chief of staff without congressional approval. Its equivalents are colonel-major in the Army and commodore-major in the Air Force. It is usually—but incorrectly—referred to as &quot;navy commodore&quot;, to avoid confusion with the &quot;air force commodore&quot;, which is equivalent to the navy's captain and army's colonel. The sleeve lace is identical to that of the Royal Navy, and wears one star on the epaulette.

==Naval rank==
The following articles deal with the rank of commodore (or its equivalent) as it is employed [[OF-6]] [[one-star rank|one-star]] flag officer rank in various countries.
{| class=wikitable
!Country !! Rank !! Remark
|-
| Argentina || ''Comodoro'' || abbreviated &quot;COMO&quot;
|-
| Australia || Commodore || abbreviated as CDRE&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.navy.gov.au/about/organisation/uniform-ranks |title=Uniform Ranks |work=Royal Australian Navy |publisher=[[Australian Government]] |accessdate=17 April 2016 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150124133502/http://www.navy.gov.au/about/organisation/uniform-ranks |archivedate=24 January 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|Bangladesh|| Commodore|| abbreviated as &quot;CDRE&quot;
|-
| Bulgaria || ''Komodor''   ||
|-
| Canada || [[Commodore (Canada)|Commodore]] || abbreviated &quot;Cmdre&quot;
|-
| Chile || ''Comodoro'' || denomitation for some Officials
|-
| Croatia || ''Komodor'' ||
|-
| Denmark|| ''Flotilleadmiral'' ||
|-
|[[Estonian Navy|Estonia]]
|Kommodoor
|Introduced in 2000. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.riigiteataja.ee/akt/71902|title=Kaitseväeteenistuse seadus – Riigi Teataja|website=www.riigiteataja.ee|access-date=2019-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| Finland || [[Commodore (Finland)|''Kommodori'']] || Equivalent to colonel
|-
|rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | France || ''Chef de division'' || historical
|-
|                         ''Contre-Amiral''    || [[French Navy]] rank [[OF-6]]
|-
|rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Germany || ''[[Flottillenadmiral]]'' || [[Rank insignia of the German Bundeswehr#Generals and Flag officers|Deutsche Marine]] rank [[OF-6]]
|-
|                         ''[[Kommodore]]''         || German [[Uniforms and insignia of the Kriegsmarine#Officer ranks|Kriegsmarine]] rank [[OF-5]] until 1945
|-
| Greece || ''Archiploiarchos (Αρχιπλοίαρχος)'' ||
|-
| India || Commodore || abbreviated as &quot;CMDE&quot;
|-
| Indonesia || ''Komodor'' || used until 1973, then replaced with [[Indonesian military ranks|Laksamana Pertama]]
|-
| Iran || ''Daryādār'' ({{lang|fa|دریادار}}) || 
|-
| Ireland || Commodore (Irish: ''Ceannasóir'') || 
|-
| Italy || ''[[w:it:Sottoammiraglio|Sottoammiraglio]]'' o ''[[w:it:Comandante superiore|Comandante superiore]]''|| SA during Kingdom of Italy 1918-1923; CS it continues
|-
| Netherlands || ''[[w:nl:Commandeur (marine)|Commandeur]]'' || 
|-
| Pakistan|| Commodore || Cdre. (One-star)
|-
| Poland || ''Kontradmirał'' || ''[[w:pl:Komandor|Komandor]]'' OF-5 rank
|-
| Portugal || ''[[w:pt:Comodoro (patente)|Comodoro]]'' || 
|-
| Romania || ''Contraamiral de flotilă'' || ''Comandor'' OF-5 rank
|-
| Spain || ''Contraalmirante'' || 
|-
| Turkey || ''Tugamiral'' || 
|-
| United Kingdom || [[Commodore (Royal Navy)|Commodore]] || 
|-
| United States || [[Commodore (United States)|Commodore]] || United States - abbreviated when used &quot;CDRE&quot;&lt;ref&gt;The modern US rank for this level is [[Rear admiral (United States)#Rear admiral (lower half)|rear admiral (lower half)]]&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Royal Australian Navy OF-6.svg|Australian Navy&lt;br&gt;shoulder board
File:10.BNF-CDRE.svg|Bangladesh Navy&lt;br&gt;shoulder board
File:British Royal Navy OF-6.svg|British Royal Navy&lt;br /&gt;shoulder board
File:EgyptianNavyInsignia-Commodore-shoulderboard.svg|Egyptian Navy&lt;br&gt;shoulder board
File:GR-Navy-OF6.svg|Greek Navy&lt;br&gt;shoulder board
File:18-Daryadar.png|Iranian Navy&lt;br&gt;shoulder board
File:IE_Navy_Rank_Insignia-Cdre.svg|Irish Naval Service
File:IN_Commodore.png|Indian Navy&lt;br&gt;shoulder Board
File:Pakistan Navy Commodore.png|Pakistan Navy&lt;br&gt;shoulder board
File:Generic-Navy-O8.svg|Portuguese Navy&lt;br&gt;sleeve insignia

&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Air force ranks==
Commodore, in Spanish ''comodoro'', is a rank in the [[Argentine Air Force]]. This rank is the equivalent of a [[colonel]] in the [[Argentine Army]], and a colonel or [[group captain]] in other air forces of the world. The Argentine rank below commodore is the rank of vice-commodore (Spanish ''vicecomodoro'') equivalent to a [[lieutenant-colonel]] in the Argentine Army, and a lieutenant-colonel or [[Wing Commander (rank)|wing commander]] in other air forces.

Commodore is a rank in the [[Royal Netherlands Air Force]]. It is a [[one-star rank]] and has essentially the same rank insignia as the British [[air commodore]].

Many air forces use the rank of [[air commodore]]. This rank was first used by the [[Royal Air Force]] and is now used in many countries such as Australia, Bangladesh, Greece, India, New Zealand, Nigeria, Pakistan, Thailand and Zimbabwe. It is the equivalent rank to the navy rank of &quot;commodore&quot;, and the army ranks of [[brigadier]] and [[brigadier general]].

The German air force used the concept of a unit commodore for the commander of a wing, usually in the rank of colonel (OF-5).

==Merchant Service (Merchant Marine) rank and Yacht Club chief directors==
&lt;!-- An internal link from [[RMS Titanic]] is targeted to this section. Please change the link on that page if you change the section name here! Thanks. --&gt;
Commodore is also a title held by many captains as recognition of exceptional navigation ability and seagoing seniority in the Merchant Service, and by the directors of a few yacht clubs and boating associations. Commodores 'in command' as Master aboard Merchant Marine ships wear distinctive rank and cap insignia denoting their honorific high rank position.

==Convoy commodore==

During wartime, a shipping [[convoy]] will have a ranking officer—sometimes an active-duty naval [[commissioned officer|officer]], at other times a [[civilian]] [[Master Mariner|master]] or retired naval officer—designated as the ''convoy commodore''. This title is not related to the individual{{'}}s military rank (if any), but instead is the title of the senior individual responsible for the overall operation of the [[merchant ship]]s and naval [[auxiliary ship]]s that make up the convoy. The convoy commodore does not command the convoy{{'}} escort forces (if any), which are commanded by a naval officer who serves as escort commander.

==Other uses==

The [[U.S. Coast Guard Auxiliary]] also employs variants of the ''title'' of commodore.  Members of the Auxiliary serve in the Coast Guard's [[Auxiliaries|uniformed auxiliary service]] and they do not have military rank, but who do wear modified U.S. Coast Guard uniforms and U.S. military-style officer rank insignia to indicate office.  Auxiliary members who have been elected or appointed to positions in the highest levels of the organization, similar in nature to active and reserve rear admirals and vice admirals use the term commodore (e.g., District Commodore, Assistant National Commodore, Deputy National Commodore, National Commodore, etc.).  These Coast Guard Auxiliarists may permanently append the title commodore, sometimes abbreviated COMO, to their names (e.g., Commodore James A. Smith, National Commodore; or COMO Jim Smith, (NACO)).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.uscg.mil/hq/cg3/cg3pcx/cginfo/uniforms/insignia-national.asp |title=USCGAux Insignia of Office: Flotilla, Division, District and National Offices |date=7 May 2013 |publisher=[[United States Coast Guard Auxiliary|United States Coast Guard Auxiliary Division]] |accessdate=18 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Philippine Coast Guard Auxiliary]]—PCGA—each of the directors in command of the ten Coast Guard Auxiliary districts are commodores, as well as most of the Deputy National Directors (some may be rear admirals). Commodore is abbreviated to COMMO in the PCGA.

[[Vanderbilt University]]'s intercollegiate athletics teams are nicknamed the &quot;[[Vanderbilt Commodores|Commodores]]&quot;, a reference to [[Cornelius Vanderbilt]]'s self-appointed title (he was the master of a large shipping fleet).

In the U.S. [[Sea Scouts (Boy Scouts of America)|Sea Scouting]] program (which is part of the [[Boy Scouts of America]]), all National, Regional, Area, and Council committee chairs are titled as commodore, while senior committee members are addressed as vice commodore. Ship committee chairs do not hold this recognition.

==See also==
* [[Air Commodore]]
* [[Commodore-in-Chief]]
* [[Comparative military ranks]]

==References==
;Notes
{{Reflist}}

{{Military ranks by country}}
{{Star officer ranks}}
{{Highest Military Ranks}}

[[Category:Naval ranks]]
[[Category:1 star officers]]</text>
      <sha1>5e9a433v6ybq5ogfqvp3u0qufsrxeay</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
