  <page>
    <title>Christmas in Poland</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7565</id>
    <revision>
      <id>935840753</id>
      <parentid>932739597</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-15T02:05:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead.) #IABot (v2.0</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox
|above=Christmas in Poland
|image=[[File:Szopka krakowska, Bronisław Pięcik, MHK, 1998.jpg|220px]]
|caption=[[Nativity scene]] ([[szopka]]) by [[Bronisław Pięcik]], [[UNESCO Intangible Cultural Heritage]]&lt;ref name=&quot;unesco.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://ich.unesco.org/en/RL/nativity-scene-szopka-tradition-in-krakow-01362|title=UNESCO - Nativity scene (szopka) tradition in Krakow|website=ich.unesco.org|accessdate=30 November 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|image2=[[File:Wigilia potrawy 554.jpg|220px]]
|caption2=[[Christmas Eve]] Supper
|image3=[[File:Bigos polonia.jpg|220px]]
|caption3=Traditional [[Christmas Day]] dinner serving of [[bigos]] on December 25
|image4=[[File:0020 Krakauer Weihnachtsmarkt 2012.JPG|220px]]
|caption4=Christmas markets are held in every major city, especially in [[Kraków]] (pictured)
|image5=[[File:04567 Christmas nativity scene at the Franciscan church in Sanok, 2010.jpg|220px]]
|caption5=Nativity scene at the Catholic Church of Christ the King in [[Sanok]]
|image6=[[File:17 weihnachten strohstern sanok.JPG|220px]]
|caption6=Nativity play (''Jasełka'' or ''Herody'') by children
|image7=[[File:DSC07089 Santa Claus in Sanok.JPG|220px]]
|caption7=[[Kulig]] with Saint Nicholas 
}}
'''Christmas in Poland''' is a major annual celebration, as in most countries of the [[Christianity|Christian]] world. The observance of [[Christmas]] developed gradually over the centuries, beginning in ancient times; combining old Polish [[Paganism|pagan]] customs with the religious [[Christmas|ones]] introduced after the [[Christianization of Poland]] by the [[Catholic Church]]. Later influences include mutual permeating of local traditions and various folk cultures. It is one of the most important religious holidays for Poles, who follow a somewhat strict traditional custom. [[Christmas tree]]s are decorated and lit in family rooms on the day of [[Christmas Eve]]. Other trees are placed in most public areas and outside churches.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmkamsterdam&quot; /&gt; Christmas in Poland is called &quot;Boże Narodzenie&quot;, which translates to 'God's Birth'.&lt;ref name=&quot;onet-translation&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://portalwiedzy.onet.pl/tlumacz.html?tr=ang-auto&amp;translate=OK&amp;qs=Christmas | title = Christmas - Tłumacz - Onet.pl Portal wiedzy | accessdate = 2013-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Saint Nicholas Day|Day of Saint Nicholas]] on 6 December is the unofficial beginning of the festive season in [[Poland]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.thespruce.com/polish-christmas-customs-and-traditions-1136853|title=How Poles Celebrate Christmas (Recipes Included)|publisher=|accessdate=15 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Well-behaved children receive small gifts on the day, whereas naughty children receive a lump of coal or a twig, called &quot;rózga&quot;. The highlight of the holiday is the most significant day, [[Christmas Eve]] on the 24 December. Polish [[Wigilia]] begins with the appearance of the first star, which corresponds to the [[Star of Bethlehem]]. During preparation, hay is spread beneath the tablecloth as a reminder that [[Jesus Christ]] was born in a [[manger]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wordpress.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://razemutah.wordpress.com/2015/12/07/traditional-christmas-eve-in-poland-wigilia-w-polsce-tradycje/|title=Traditional Christmas Eve in Poland- Wigilia w Polsce- tradycje|date=7 December 2015|publisher=|accessdate=15 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to tradition, an empty place setting is symbolically left at the table for the Lord or, for a lost wanderer who may be in need of food or shelter.&lt;ref name=&quot;wordpress.com&quot;/&gt; The supper begins with the breaking of the [[Christmas wafer]] known as &quot;opłatek&quot;, a custom only observed in Poland and some parts of [[Lithuania]]. The meals must be meatless as a sign of [[fasting]] and twelve different dishes are made, thus symbolizing the [[Twelve Apostles]]. The celebration ends with the exchange of gifts and a [[midnight mass]] in churches.

Other aspects of Polish Christmas include nativity plays called &quot;Jasełka&quot; or &quot;Herody&quot;, outdoor [[nativity scene]]s, the singing of [[Christmas carol|carols]], most notably &quot;[[God Is Born]]&quot;, and [[Kulig]], a sleigh ride with [[Saint Nicholas]]. The tradition of crafting and hand-making Christmas [[szopka]]s in [[Kraków]] was declared [[UNESCO Intangible Cultural Heritage]].&lt;ref name=&quot;unesco.org&quot;/&gt;

==Advent==
[[File:Piotrus XMAS Tree 2008 05.JPG|thumb|left|Christmas tree in a Polish home. Traditionally, they are decorated and lit on Christmas Eve – [[Wigilia]]]]
Among the special tasks carried out in private homes during [[Advent]] (a time of waiting for the celebration of the [[Nativity of Jesus]]) is the baking of the Christmas [[Pierniki|piernik]] (gingerbread), and the making of Christmas decorations. Pierniks are made in a variety of shapes, including hearts, animals, and [[St. Nicholas]] figures. St. Nicholas does not play a major role on Christmas Day, but is celebrated on his Saint feast day of December 6. He visits good children in secret and leaves presents for them.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmkamsterdam&quot; /&gt;

Traditionally, the Christmas trees are decorated with glass [[Christmas ornament|baubles]], garlands and many homemade [[Decorative arts|ornaments]] including painted eggshells, shiny red apples, walnuts, wrapped chocolate shapes, candles, etc. They are lit on [[Christmas Eve]] before [[Wigilia]]. At the top of each tree there is a star or a glittering [[tree topper]]. In many homes, [[sparkler]]s are hung on the branches of the trees for wintery ambiance. Sometimes the trees are left standing until February 2, the [[feast day]] of St. Mary of the Candle of Lighting.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmkamsterdam&quot;/&gt;

During Advent and all the way until [[Epiphany (holiday)|Epiphany]], or the [[baptism of Jesus]] (day of January 6), the &quot;gwiazdory&quot;, or the star carriers walk through the villages. Some of them sing [[carols]]; others recite verses or put on &quot;szopki&quot;, or &quot;herody&quot; ([[nativity scene]]s). The last two customs are inspired by the traditional [[manger]] scenes or &quot;Jasełka&quot; ([[Nativity scene|crib]]). One tradition unique to Poland is the sharing of the &quot;[[opłatek]]&quot;, a thin wafer into which a holy picture is pressed. In the old days people carried these wafers from house to house wishing their neighbors a Merry Christmas. Nowadays, opłatek is mostly shared with members of the family and immediate neighbors before the Christmas Eve supper ([[Wigilia]] in the Polish language). As each person shares pieces of the wafer with another, they are supposed to forgive each other any hurts that have occurred over the past year and wish them happiness in the coming year.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmkamsterdam&quot; /&gt;

==''Wigilia'', the Christmas Eve supper==
In Poland, [[Christmas Eve]] is a day first of [[fasting]], then of feasting. The [[Wigilia]] feast begins at the appearance of the first star. There is no red meat served but fish, usually [[carp]]. The supper, which includes many traditional dishes and desserts can sometimes last for over two hours. It is followed by the exchange of gifts. The next day, the [[Christmas Day]], is often spent visiting friends. In Polish tradition, people combine religion and family closeness at Christmas. Although gift-giving plays a major role in the rituals, emphasis is placed more on the making of special foods and decorations.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmkamsterdam&quot; /&gt;

On the night of Christmas Eve, so important is the appearance of the first star in remembrance of the [[Star of Bethlehem]], that it has been given an affectionate name of &quot;the little star&quot; or Gwiazdka (the female counterpart of St. Nicholas). On that evening, children watch the sky anxiously hoping to be the first to cry out, &quot;The star has come!&quot; Only after it appears, the family members sit down to a dinner table.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmkamsterdam&quot; /&gt;

According to tradition, bits of hay are spread beneath the tablecloth as a reminder that Christ was born in a [[manger]]. Others partake in the practice of placing money under the table cloth for each guest, in order to wish for prosperity in the coming year. Some practice the superstition that an even number of people must be seated around the table. In many homes an empty place setting is symbolically left at the table for the [[Baby Jesus]] or, for a lonely wanderer who may be in need of food, or if a deceased relative should come and would like to share in the meal.

The supper begins with the breaking of the [[opłatek]]. Everyone at the table breaks off a piece and eats it as a symbol of their unity with Christ. They then share a piece with each family member. A tradition exists among some families to serve twelve different dishes at Wigilia symbolizing the [[Twelve Apostles]], or perhaps, an odd number of dishes for good luck (usually five, seven, or nine).

A traditional Wigilia supper in Poland includes fried [[carp]] and [[borscht]] (beetroot soup) with [[uszka]] (ravioli). Carp provides a main component of the Christmas Eve meal across Poland; [[carp]] fillet, carp in [[aspic]] and [[gefilte fish]]. Universal Polish Christmas foods are [[pierogi]] as well as some [[herring]] dishes, and for dessert, [[makowiec (pastry)|makowiec]] or noodles with poppy seed. Often, there is a [[compote]] of dry fruits for a drink.

The remainder of the evening is given to stories and songs around the Christmas tree. In some areas of the country, children are taught that &quot;The Little Star&quot; brings the gifts. As presents are unwrapped, carollers may walk from house to house receiving treats along the way.

Christmas Eve ends with &quot;[[Pasterka]]&quot;, the Midnight Mass at the local church. The tradition commemorates the arrival of the shepherds to Bethlehem and their paying of respect and bearing witness to the new born Messiah. The custom of Christmas night liturgy was introduced in the Christian churches after the second half of the 5th century. In Poland that custom arrived together with the coming of  Christianity.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmkamsterdam&quot;&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20080107101742/http://www.pmkamsterdam.nl/PL/Czytelnia/BozeNar.htm  &quot;Boże Narodzenie i polskie tradycje,&quot;] Polska Misja Katolicka, Amsterdam {{in lang|pl}}&lt;/ref&gt; The next day (December 25) begins with the early morning mass followed by daytime masses. According to scripture, the Christmas Day masses are interchangeable allowing for greater flexibility in choosing the religious services by individual parishioners.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kędzierski&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.przewodnik-katolicki.pl/nr/ksiadz_odpowiada/pasterka_przed_polnoca.html |title=Pasterka przed północą... (Pasterka before midnight) |publisher=Drukarnia i Księgarnia św. Wojciecha |work=Przewodnik Katolicki 02/2009 (Catholic Guide) |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://archive.is/20130416091647/http://www.przewodnik-katolicki.pl/nr/ksiadz_odpowiada/pasterka_przed_polnoca.html |archivedate=2013-04-16 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==''Kolędy'', the Christmas carols==
[[File:Mummers Play in Poland.jpg|thumb|right|280px|[[Mummers play|Mummers]] with a [[Turoń|Turoń creature]] singing Christmas carols called ''kolędy'' in Poland, 1929 postcard]]
[[Christmas carols]] are not celebrated in Poland until during-and-after the Christmas Vigil Mass called &quot;[[Pasterka]]&quot; held between 24 and 25 of December.&lt;ref name=&quot;LC&quot;&gt;[http://liturgicalcenter.org/?a=liturg&amp;sub=trad&amp;grupa=35&amp;mod=49 &quot;The Shepherds' Mass&quot;.] Polish-American Liturgical Center.org. 2008. Retrieved December 21, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The Christmas season often runs until February 2. The early hymns sung in Catholic church were brought to Poland by the [[Franciscan Brothers of Peace|Franciscan Brothers]] in the [[Middle Ages]]. The early Christmas music was Latin in origin. When the Polish words and melodies started to become popular, including many new secular [[pastoral]]s (pastoralka, or shepherd's songs), they were not written down originally, but rather taught among people by heart. Notably, the song &quot;[[God Is Born]]&quot; (''Bóg się rodzi'') with lyrics written by [[Franciszek Karpiński]] in 1792 became the Christmas hymn of Poland already in the court of King [[Stefan Batory]]. Many of the early Polish carols were collected in 1838 by {{interlanguage link|Michał Mioduszewski|lt=Rev. Mioduszewski|ca|Michał Mioduszewski|eo|Michał Marcin Mioduszewski|pl|Michał Mioduszewski}} in a book called ''Pastorałki i Kolędy z Melodiami'' (Pastorals and Carols with Melodies).&lt;ref name=&quot;polishsite&quot;&gt;Lorraine Grochowsa Kiefer, [http://culture.polishsite.us/articles/art336.html Christmas Kolędy - Polish Carols] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110317140708/http://culture.polishsite.us/articles/art336.html |date=2011-03-17 }}, at culture.polishsite.us&lt;/ref&gt;

==Polish hand-made Christmas ornaments==
[[File:Koronkowa dekoracja bombek choinkowych - Zbąszyń - 001185c.jpg|thumb|right|280px|Traditional Polish glass baubles with [[lace]] details. Poland is a major exporter of Christmas decorations, especially hand-blown ornaments]]
Poland produces some of the finest hand blown glass Christmas ornaments in Europe. Families and collectors value these ornaments for high quality, traditional artwork, and unique decorations.&lt;ref name=&quot;luxorna&quot;/&gt;

Polish blown-glass Christmas ornaments are generally manufactured only in winter season. The modern glass workshops and manufacturers tend to be localized in the southern regions of Poland.&lt;ref name=&quot;luxorna&quot;&gt;LUXORNA, [http://www.luxorna.pl/index.php?go=content&amp;section=o_nas  Polskie ręcznie wytwarzane i zdobione bombki choinkowe, katalog.] Retrieved December 29, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://bilinski.nazwa.pl/pl/c/Ozdoby-Formowane/9  Lista produktów kategorii Ozdoby Formowane.] Bilinski. Retrieved December 29, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Christianity|Poland}}
*[[God Is Born]]
*[[Kraków szopka]]
*[[Wigilia]] the Christmas Eve vigil supper
*[[Christmas worldwide]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Christmas in Poland}}
*[http://culture.pl/en/article/polish-christmas-eve-traditions Polish Christmas Eve Traditions]
*[http://goeasteurope.about.com/od/poland/a/Polandchristmastraditions.htm Polish Kulture]
* [http://www.polishworld.com/christmas/ Christmas in Poland]
*[http://www.christmasgifts.com/Christmasblog/2006/10/16/how-to-celebrate-a-polish-style-christmas/ How to celebrate Christmas in Poland]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20080107101742/http://www.pmkamsterdam.nl/PL/Czytelnia/BozeNar.htm  Boże Narodzenie, www.pmkamsterdam.nl (Polska Misja Katolicka, Amsterdam)]
*[http://www.polishamericancenter.org/Wigilia.htm Wigilia article from the Polish American Center]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20101127040410/http://www.polishcenter.org/Christmas/WIGILIA-ENG.htm Wigilia article from Pope John Paul II Polish Center]
*[http://polishmuseumofamerica.org/english/ActivePages/specialprojects/Wigilia.htm Wigilia article from the Polish Museum of America]{{Dead link|date=July 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}
{{Christmas}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Christmas In Poland}}
[[Category:Polish traditions]]
[[Category:Christmas in Poland| ]]</text>
      <sha1>j71wj4zut8hugevc3hjv6sqyqrt313q</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
