  <page>
    <title>Foreign policy of the United States</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7564</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941997539</id>
      <parentid>941997478</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-21T23:09:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>King of Scorpions</username>
        <id>38384655</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/65.121.54.230|65.121.54.230]] ([[User talk:65.121.54.230|talk]]): Undoing test edit ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|National foreign policy}}{{Use American English|date=May 2018}} 
{{Use mdy dates|date=May 2018}}
{{Politics of the United States}}

The '''foreign policy of the United States''' is its interactions with foreign nations and how it sets standards of interaction for its organizations, corporations and system citizens of the [[United States]].

The officially stated goals of the foreign policy of the United States of America, including all the Bureaus and Offices in the [[United States Department of State]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://2009-2017.state.gov/r/pa/ei/rls/dos/1718.htm|title=Alphabetical List of Bureaus and Offices|work=U.S. Department of State|accessdate=April 20, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; as mentioned in the ''Foreign Policy Agenda'' of the Department of State, are &quot;to build and sustain a more democratic, secure, and prosperous world for the benefit of the American people and the international community&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://2009-2017.state.gov/s/d/rm/index.htm#mission|title=Bureau of Budget and Planning|website=State.gov|accessdate=18 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the [[United States House Committee on Foreign Affairs]] states as some of its jurisdictional goals: &quot;export controls, including nonproliferation of nuclear technology and nuclear hardware; measures to foster commercial interaction with foreign nations and to safeguard American business abroad; international commodity agreements; international education; and protection of American citizens abroad and expatriation&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.internationalrelations.house.gov/about.asp?nav=jurisdiction |title=About the Committee |accessdate=18 February 2015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120415105402/http://www.internationalrelations.house.gov/about.asp?nav=jurisdiction |archivedate=April 15, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; U.S. foreign policy and [[Foreign policy of the United States#Foreign aid|foreign aid]] have been the subject of much debate, praise and [[Foreign policy of the United States#Criticism|criticism]], both domestically and abroad.

==Powers of the President==
The President sets the tone for all foreign policy. The State Department and all members design and implement all details to the President's policy. The Congress approves the President's picks for ambassadors and as a secondary function, can declare war. The President of the United States negotiates treaties with foreign nations, then treaties enter into force only if ratified by two-thirds of the Senate. The President is also [[Commander in Chief]] of the [[United States Armed Forces]], and as such has broad authority over the armed forces. Both the Secretary of State and ambassadors are appointed by the President, with the advice and consent of the Senate. The [[United States Secretary of State]] acts similarly to a [[foreign minister]] and under the President's leadership, is the primary conductor of state-to-state diplomacy.

==Powers of the Congress==
{{Main|Treaty Clause|War Powers Clause|Appointments Clause|Commerce Clause|l4=Foreign Commerce Clause}}
[[File:Foreign policy US government structure.png|thumb|The U.S. Constitution gives much of the foreign policy decision-making to the presidency, but the Senate has a role in ratifying treaties, and the Supreme Court interprets treaties when cases are presented to it.]]

Congress is the only branch of government that has the authority to declare war. Furthermore, Congress writes the civilian and military budget, thus has vast power in military action and foreign aid. Congress also has power to regulate commerce with foreign nations.&lt;ref&gt;James M. McCormick, ''American Foreign Policy and  Process'' (2009)  ch. 7–8&lt;/ref&gt;

==Historical overview==
{{Main|History of U.S. foreign policy|Timeline of United States diplomatic history}}

The main trend regarding the history of U.S. foreign policy since the American Revolution is the shift from [[non-interventionism]] before and after [[World War I]], to its growth as a world power and global [[hegemony]] during and since World War II and the end of the [[Cold War]] in the 20th century.&lt;ref&gt;George C. Herring, ''[https://archive.org/details/fromcolonytosupe00herr From Colony to Superpower: U.S. Foreign Relations Since 1776]'' (2008)&lt;/ref&gt; Since the 19th century, U.S. foreign policy also has been characterized by a shift from the [[Political realism|realist school]] to the idealistic or [[Wilsonian]] school of international relations.&lt;ref&gt;Richard Russell, &quot;American Diplomatic Realism: A Tradition Practised and Preached by George F. Kennan,&quot; ''Diplomacy and Statecraft'', Nov 2000, Vol. 11 Issue 3, pp.&amp;nbsp;159–83&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Jay-treaty.jpg|thumb|upright|left|The [[Jay Treaty]] of 1795 aligned the U.S. more with Britain and less with France, leading to political polarization at home]]

Foreign policy themes were expressed considerably in [[George Washington]]'s [[George Washington's Farewell Address|farewell address]]; these included, among other things, observing good faith and justice towards all nations and cultivating peace and harmony with all, excluding both &quot;inveterate antipathies against particular nations, and passionate attachments for others&quot;, &quot;steer[ing] clear of permanent alliances with any portion of the foreign world&quot;, and advocating trade with all nations. These policies became the basis of the [[Federalist Party]] in the 1790s, but the rival Jeffersonians feared Britain and favored France in the 1790s, declaring the [[War of 1812]] on Britain. After the 1778 alliance with France, the U.S. did not sign another permanent treaty until the [[North Atlantic Treaty]] in 1949. Over time, other themes, key goals, attitudes, or stances have been variously expressed by [[United States Presidential doctrines|Presidential 'doctrines']], named for them. Initially these were uncommon events, but since WWII, these have been made by most presidents.

Jeffersonians vigorously opposed a large standing army and any navy until attacks against American shipping by [[Barbary corsairs]] spurred the country into developing a naval force projection capability, resulting in the [[First Barbary War]] in 1801.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Oren|first=Michael B.|title=The Middle East and the Making of the United States, 1776 to 1815|date=2005-11-03|url=http://www.columbia.edu/cu/news/05/11/michaelOren.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite two wars with European Powers—the [[War of 1812]] and the [[Spanish–American War]] in 1898—American foreign policy was mostly peaceful and marked by steady expansion of its foreign trade during the 19th century. The [[Louisiana Purchase]] in 1803 doubled the nation's geographical area; [[Adams–Onís Treaty|Spain ceded]] the territory of [[Florida]] in 1819; annexation brought in the independent Texas Republic in 1845; a [[Mexican–American War|war with Mexico]] added California, Arizona, Utah, Nevada, and New Mexico in 1848. The U.S. [[Alaska Purchase|bought Alaska]] from the Russian Empire in 1867, and it annexed the independent [[Republic of Hawaii]] in 1898. Victory over Spain in 1898 brought the [[Philippines]] and [[Puerto Rico]], as well as oversight of Cuba. The short experiment in imperialism ended by 1908, as the U.S. turned its attention to the Panama Canal and the stabilization of regions to its south, including [[Mexico]].

===20th century===
{{Further|History of U.S. foreign policy, 1897–1913}}

====World War I====
{{Further|Presidency of Woodrow Wilson}}
The 20th century was marked by two world wars in which Allied powers, along with the United States, defeated their enemies, and through this participation the United States increased its international reputation. Entry into the First World War was a hotly debated issue in the 1916 presidential election.&lt;ref&gt;Arthur S. Link and William M. Leary Jr. &quot;Election of 1916: 'He Kept Us out of War'.&quot; in  Arthur M, Schlesinger, Jr., ed.,  ''The Coming to Power: Critical Elections in American History'' (1971): 296-321.&lt;/ref&gt;

President [[Woodrow Wilson|Wilson]]'s [[Fourteen Points]] was developed from his idealistic [[Wilsonianism]] program of spreading democracy and fighting militarism to prevent future wars. It became the basis of the German Armistice (which amounted to a military surrender) and the 1919 [[Paris Peace Conference, 1919|Paris Peace Conference]]. The resulting [[Treaty of Versailles]], due to European allies' punitive and territorial designs, showed insufficient conformity with these points, and the U.S. signed separate treaties with each of its adversaries; due to Senate objections also, the U.S. never joined the [[League of Nations]], which was established as a result of Wilson's initiative. In the 1920s, the United States followed an independent course, and succeeded in a program of [[Washington Naval Conference|naval disarmament]], and [[Dawes Plan|refunding the German economy]]. Operating outside the League it became a dominant player in diplomatic affairs. New York became the financial capital of the world,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Donald L. Miller|title=Supreme City: How Jazz Age Manhattan Gave Birth to Modern America|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Mg1DCQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA44|year=2015|publisher=Simon and Schuster|pages=44–45|isbn=9781416550204}}&lt;/ref&gt; but the [[Wall Street Crash of 1929]] hurled the Western industrialized world into the [[Great Depression]]. American trade policy relied on high tariffs under the Republicans, and reciprocal trade agreements under the Democrats, but in any case exports were at very low levels in the 1930s.

====World War II====
{{main|Diplomatic history of World War II#United States}}
[[File:Yalta Conference cropped.jpg|thumb|[[Allies of World War II]] at the [[Yalta Conference]]: [[Winston Churchill]], [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] and [[Joseph Stalin]]]]

The United States adopted a non-interventionist foreign policy from 1932 to 1938, but then President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] moved toward strong support of the Allies in their wars against Germany and Japan. As a result of intense internal debate, the national policy was one of becoming the [[Arsenal of Democracy]], that is financing and equipping the Allied armies without sending American combat soldiers. Roosevelt mentioned four fundamental freedoms, which ought to be enjoyed by people &quot;everywhere in the world&quot;; these included the freedom of speech and religion, as well as freedom from want and fear. Roosevelt helped establish terms for a post-war world among potential allies at the [[Atlantic Charter|Atlantic Conference]]; [[Atlantic Charter#Content and analysis|specific points]] were included to correct earlier failures, which became a step toward the [[United Nations]]. American policy was to threaten Japan, to force it out of China, and to prevent its attacking the Soviet Union. However, Japan reacted by an attack on Pearl Harbor in December 1941, and the United States was at war with Japan, Germany, and Italy. Instead of the loans given to allies in World War I, the United States provided Lend-Lease grants of $50,000,000,000. Working closely with [[Winston Churchill]] of Britain, and Joseph Stalin of the Soviet Union, Roosevelt sent his forces into the Pacific against Japan, then into North Africa against Italy and Germany, and finally into Europe starting with France and Italy in 1944 against the Germans. The American economy roared forward, doubling industrial production, and building vast quantities of airplanes, ships, tanks, munitions, and, finally, the atomic bomb. Much of the American war effort went to strategic bombers, which flattened the cities of Japan and Germany.

====Cold War====
{{main|Cold War}}
[[File: President Nixon meets with China's Communist Party Leader, Mao Tse- Tung, 02-29-1972 - NARA - 194759.tif|thumb|President Richard Nixon went to China to open friendly relations and meet Chinese Communist Party Chairman [[Mao Zedong]] in 1972.]]

After the war, the U.S. rose to become the dominant economic power with broad influence in much of the world, with the key policies of the [[Marshall Plan]] and the [[Truman Doctrine]]. Almost immediately, however, the world witnessed division into broad two camps during the [[Cold War]]; one side was led by the U.S. and the other by the Soviet Union, but this situation also led to the establishment of the [[Non-Aligned Movement]]. This period lasted until almost the end of the 20th century and is thought to be both an ideological and power struggle between the two superpowers. A policy of [[containment]] was adopted to limit Soviet expansion, and a series of proxy wars were fought with mixed results. In 1991, the Soviet Union dissolved into separate nations, and the Cold War formally ended as the United States gave separate diplomatic recognition to the Russian Federation and other former Soviet states.

In domestic politics, foreign policy is not usually a central issue. In 1945–1970 the Democratic Party took a strong anti-Communist line and supported wars in Korea and Vietnam. Then the party split with a strong, &quot;dovish&quot;, pacifist element (typified by 1972 presidential candidate George McGovern).  Many &quot;hawks&quot;, advocates for war, joined the [[Neoconservative]] movement and started supporting the Republicans—especially Reagan—based on foreign policy.&lt;ref&gt;Seymour Martin Lipset, &quot;Neoconservatism: Myth and reality.&quot; ''Society'' 25.5 (1988): pp. 9-13 [http://www.diss.fu-berlin.de/docs/servlets/MCRFileNodeServlet/FUDOCS_derivate_000000001215/fraenkelvortraege01.pdf online].&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, down to 1952 the Republican Party was split between an isolationist wing, based in the Midwest and led by Senator [[Robert A. Taft]], and an internationalist wing based in the East and led by [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]]. Eisenhower defeated Taft for the 1952 nomination largely on foreign policy grounds. Since then the Republicans have been characterized by a hawkish and intense [[American nationalism]], and strong opposition to Communism, and strong [[Israel–United States relations|support for Israel]].&lt;ref&gt;Colin  Dueck, ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=LKhB2ENzgvAC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Hard Line: The Republican Party and U.S. Foreign Policy since World War II]'' (2010).&lt;/ref&gt;

===21st century===
In the 21st century, U.S. influence remains strong but, in relative terms, is declining in terms of economic output compared to rising nations such as China, India, Russia, and the newly consolidated [[European Union]]. Substantial problems remain, such as [[climate change]], [[nuclear proliferation]], and the specter of [[nuclear terrorism]]. Foreign policy analysts Hachigian and Sutphen in their book ''The Next American Century'' suggest all five powers have similar vested interests in stability and terrorism prevention and trade; if they can find common ground, then the next decades may be marked by peaceful growth and prosperity.&lt;ref name=tws13jans3w2&gt;{{cite news|author=Nikolas K. Gvosdev |title=FDR's Children |quote=Hachigian&amp;nbsp;... and Sutphen&amp;nbsp;... recognize that the global balance of power is changing; that despite America's continued predominance, the other pivotal powers &quot;do challenge American dominance and impinge on the freedom of action the U.S. has come to enjoy and expect&quot;. Rather than focusing on the negatives, however, they believe that these six powers have the same vested interests: All are dependent on the free flow of goods around the world and all require global stability in order to ensure continued economic growth (and the prosperity it engenders). |work=National Interest |date=2008-01-02 |url=http://nationalinterest.org/bookreview/fdrs-children-1931 |accessdate=2010-01-13 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100826001356/http://nationalinterest.org/bookreview/fdrs-children-1931 |archivedate=August 26, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2017 diplomats from other countries developed new tactics to deal with President [[Donald Trump]].  The ''New York Times'' reported on the eve of his first foreign trip as president:

:For foreign leaders trying to figure out the best way to approach an American president unlike any they have known, it is a time of experimentation. Embassies in Washington trade tips and ambassadors send cables to presidents and ministers back home suggesting how to handle a mercurial, strong-willed leader with no real experience on the world stage, a preference for personal diplomacy and a taste for glitz....certain rules have emerged: Keep it short — no 30-minute monologue for a 30-second attention span. Do not assume he knows the history of the country or its major points of contention. Compliment him on his Electoral College victory. Contrast him favorably with President Barack Obama. Do not get hung up on whatever was said during the campaign. Stay in regular touch. Do not go in with a shopping list but bring some sort of deal he can call a victory.&lt;ref&gt;See Peter Baker,
 &quot;Tips for Leaders Meeting Trump: Keep It Short and Give Him a Win,&quot;
 [https://www.nytimes.com/2017/05/18/world/middleeast/trump-saudi-arabia-foreign-trip.html ''New York Times'' May 18, 2017]&lt;/ref&gt;

Trump has numerous aides giving advice on foreign policy. The chief diplomat was Secretary of State [[Rex Tillerson]]. His major foreign policy positions were often at odds with Trump, including:
:urging the United States to stay in the Trans-Pacific Partnership and the Paris climate accord, taking a hard line on Russia, advocating negotiations and dialogue to defuse the mounting crisis with North Korea, advocating for continued U.S. adherence to the Iran nuclear deal, taking a neutral position in the dispute between Qatar and Saudi Arabia, and reassuring jittery allies, from South Korea and Japan to our NATO partners, that America still has their back.&lt;ref&gt;Aaron David Miller and Richard Sokolsky, &quot;Should Rex Tillerson Resign?,&quot; [http://www.politico.com/magazine/story/2017/10/01/should-rex-tillerson-resign-215664 ''Politico''  October 1, 2017]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Law==
In the United States, there are three types of [[treaty]]-related law:
* '''Treaties''' are formal written agreements specified by the [[Treaty Clause]] of the [[United States Constitution|Constitution]]. The [[President of the United States|President]] makes a treaty with foreign powers, but then the proposed treaty must be ratified by a two-thirds vote in the [[United States Senate|Senate]]. For example, President [[Woodrow Wilson|Wilson]] proposed the [[Treaty of Versailles]] after World War I after consulting with allied powers, but this treaty was rejected by the Senate; as a result, the U.S. subsequently made separate agreements with different nations. While most international law has a broader interpretation of the term ''treaty'', the U.S. sense of the term is more restricted. In ''[[Missouri v. Holland]]'', the [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] ruled that the power to make treaties under the U.S. Constitution is a power separate from the other enumerated powers of the federal government, and hence the federal government can use treaties to legislate in areas which would otherwise fall within the exclusive authority of the states.
* '''[[Executive agreement]]s''' are made by the President—in the exercise of his [[President of the United States#Article II executive powers|Constitutional executive powers]]—alone. 
* '''Congressional-executive agreements''' are made by the President and [[United States Congress|Congress]]. A majority of both houses makes it binding much like regular legislation after it is signed by the president. The Constitution does not expressly state that these agreements are allowed, and constitutional scholars such as [[Laurence Tribe]] think they are unconstitutional.&lt;ref&gt;Laurence H. Tribe, &quot;[https://www.jstor.org/stable/1341856 Taking Text and Structure Seriously: Reflections on Free-Form Method in Constitutional Interpretation],&quot; 108 Harv. L. Rev. 1221, 1227 (1995).&lt;/ref&gt;

In contrast to most other nations, the United States considers the three types of agreements as distinct. Further, the United States incorporates treaty law into the body of U.S. federal law. As a result, Congress can modify or repeal treaties afterward. It can overrule an agreed-upon treaty obligation even if that is seen as a violation of the treaty under international law. Several U.S. court rulings confirmed this understanding, including Supreme Court decisions in ''[[The Paquete Habana|Paquete Habana v. the United States]]'' (1900), and ''[[Reid v. Covert]]'' (1957), as well as a lower court ruling in ''[[Garcia-Mir v. Meese]]'' (1986). Further, the Supreme Court has declared itself as having the power to rule a treaty as void by declaring it &quot;unconstitutional&quot; although as of 2011, it has never exercised that power.{{citation needed|date=June 2015}}

The [[United States Department of State|State Department]] has taken the position that the [[Vienna Convention on the Law of Treaties]] represents established law. Generally, when the U.S. signs a treaty, it is binding. However, as a result of the ''Reid v. Covert'' decision, the U.S. adds a [[reservation (law)|reservation]] to the text of every treaty that says in effect that the U.S. intends to abide by the treaty but that if the treaty is found to be in violation of the Constitution, the U.S. legally is then unable to abide by the treaty since the U.S. signature would be ''[[ultra vires]]''.

==International agreements==

The United States has ratified and participates in many other multilateral treaties, including [[arms control|arms control treaties]] (especially with the Soviet Union), human rights treaties, [[environmental protocol]]s, and [[free trade agreement]]s.
{{further|List of United States treaties}}

===Economic and general government===

The United States is a founding member of the [[United Nations]] and most of its [[List of specialized agencies of the United Nations|specialized agencies]], notably the [[World Bank Group]] and [[International Monetary Fund]].  The U.S. has at times withheld payment of dues, owing to disagreements with the UN.

The United States is also member of:
* [[Organization of American States]]
* [[Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development]] (OECD)
* [[Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe]] (OSCE)
* [[NAFTA]], the regional trade bloc with Canada and Mexico
* [[World Trade Organization]]
* [[Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation]] (APEC)
* [[Group of Seven]] (G7)
* [[World Customs Organization]]

===Freely Associated States===

After it captured the islands from Japan during World War II, the United States administered the [[Trust Territory of the Pacific Islands]] from 1947 to 1986 (1994 for Palau).  The [[Northern Mariana Islands]] became a U.S. territory (part of the United States), while [[Federated States of Micronesia]], the [[Marshall Islands]], and [[Palau]] became independent countries.  Each has signed a [[Compact of Free Association]] that gives the United States exclusive military access in return for U.S. defense protection and conduct of military foreign affairs (except the declaration of war) and a few billion dollars of aid.  These agreements also generally allow citizens of these countries to live and work in the United States with their spouses (and vice versa), and provide for largely free trade.  The federal government also grants access to services from domestic agencies, including the [[Federal Emergency Management Agency]], [[National Weather Service]], the [[United States Postal Service]], the [[Federal Aviation Administration]], the [[Federal Communications Commission]], and U.S. representation to the International Frequency Registration Board of the [[International Telecommunication Union]].

{{further|Associated state}}

===Non-participation in multi-lateral agreements===

The United States notably does not participate in various international agreements adhered to by almost all other industrialized countries, by almost all the countries of the Americas, or by almost all other countries in the world.  With a large population and economy, on a practical level this can undermine the effect of certain agreements,&lt;ref&gt;The power of the League was limited by the United States' refusal to join.{{cite book |last = Northedge |first = F.S |year = 1986 |title = The League of Nations: Its Life and Times, 1920–1946 |publisher = Holmes &amp; Meier|isbn = 0-7185-1316-9 |ref = harv|pp=276–78}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The United States was responsible for 36% of greenhouse gas emissions at the time of the [[Kyoto Protocol]]&lt;/ref&gt; or give other countries a precedent to cite for non-participation in various agreements.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/entry/the-united-states-should_b_10930236 The United States Should Ratify The Law Of The Sea Convention] (due to China citing U.S. citing non-ratification as a reason it doesn't need to follow the agreement)&lt;/ref&gt;

In some cases the arguments against participation include that the United States should maximize its sovereignty and freedom of action, or that ratification would create a basis for lawsuits that would treat American citizens unfairly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=https://www.economist.com/blogs/economist-explains/2013/10/economist-explains-2|title=Why won't America ratify the UN convention on children's rights?|journal=The Economist|accessdate=October 14, 2017|date=October 6, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In other cases, the debate became involved in domestic political issues, such as [[Gun politics in the United States|gun control]], [[Climate change in the United States|climate change]], and the [[Capital punishment in the United States|death penalty]].

Examples include:
* [[Versailles Treaty]] and the [[League of Nations]] covenant (in force 1920–45, signed but not ratified)
* [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights#United States|International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]] (took effect in 1976, ratified with substantial reservations)
* [[International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights]] (took effect in 1976, signed but not ratified)
* [[American Convention on Human Rights]] (took effect in 1978)
* [[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women]] (took effect in 1981, signed but not ratified)
* [[Convention on the Rights of the Child]] (took effect in 1990, signed but not ratified)
* [[United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea]] (took effect in 1994)
* [[Comprehensive Nuclear-Test-Ban Treaty]] (signed in 1996 but never ratified and never took effect)
* [[Mine Ban Treaty]] (took effect in 1999)
* [[United States and the International Criminal Court|International Criminal Court]] (took effect in 2002)
* [[Kyoto Protocol]] (in force 2005–12, signed but not ratified)
* [[Optional Protocol to the Convention against Torture]] (took effect in 2006)
* [[Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities]] (took effect in 2008, signed but not ratified)
* [[Convention on Cluster Munitions]] (took effect in 2010)
* [[International Convention for the Protection of All Persons from Enforced Disappearance]] (took effect in 2010)
* [[Arms Trade Treaty]] (took effect in 2014)
* [[Human rights in the United States#Other treaties not signed or signed but not ratified|Other human rights treaties]]

{{further|List of treaties unsigned or unratified by the United States}}

===Hub and spoke vs multilateral===
While America's relationships with Europe have tended to be in terms of multilateral frameworks, such as NATO, America's relations with Asia have tended to be based on a &quot;hub and spoke&quot; model using a series of bilateral relationships where states coordinate with the United States and do not collaborate with each other.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Hufbauer|first1=Gary Clyde|last2=Schott|first2=Jeffrey J.|title=Western Hemisphere Economic Integration|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rYeeuxAkipUC&amp;pg=PA132|year=1994|publisher=Peterson Institute|pages=132–22|isbn=9780881321593}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On May 30, 2009, at the [[Shangri-La Dialogue]] Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates urged the nations of Asia to build on this hub and spoke model as they established and grew multilateral institutions such as [[ASEAN]], [[APEC]] and the ad hoc arrangements in the area.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/library/news/2009/05/mil-090530-afps03.htm|title=Gates Delivers Keynote Address to Open Asia Security Conference|author=John Pike|website=Globalsecurity.org|accessdate=18 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in 2011 Gates said that the United States must serve as the &quot;indispensable nation,&quot; for building multilateral cooperation.&lt;ref&gt;Shanker, Tom. [https://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/03/world/asia/03Gates.html &quot;Gates Talks of Boosting Asian Security Despite Budget Cuts.&quot;] ''New York Times'', 1 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Oil==
===Persian Gulf===
{{Further|Energy policy of the United States|Petroleum politics}}
[[File:US Navy 030402-N-5362A-004 U.S. Army Sgt. Mark Phiffer stands guard duty near a burning oil well in the Rumaylah Oil Fields in Southern Iraq.jpg|thumb|A U.S. soldier stands guard duty near a burning oil well in the [[Rumaila oil field]], Iraq, April 2003]]
As of 2014, the U.S. currently produces about 66% of the [[Petroleum|oil]] that it consumes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eia.gov/countries/country-data.cfm?fips=US|title=United States - U.S. Energy Information Administration (EIA)|website=Eia.gov|accessdate=April 20, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; While its imports have exceeded domestic production since the early 1990s, new [[hydraulic fracturing]] techniques and discovery of shale oil deposits in Canada and the American Dakotas offer the potential for increased [[United States energy independence|energy independence]] from oil exporting countries such as [[OPEC]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eia.doe.gov/pub/oil_gas/petroleum/data_publications/company_level_imports/current/import.html|title=Company Level Imports|website=Eia.doe.gov|accessdate=April 20, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Former U.S. President [[George W. Bush]] identified dependence on imported oil as an urgent ''&quot;national security concern&quot;.''&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=10000087&amp;sid=ar4D7HVGikXo&amp;refer=top_world_news Bush Leverage With Russia, Iran, China Falls as Oil Prices Rise], Bloomberg.com&lt;/ref&gt;

Two-thirds of the world's proven [[oil reserves]] are estimated to be found in the
[[Persian Gulf]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E4D6123AF93AA15752C0A9649C8B63 Shrinking Our Presence in Saudi Arabia], New York Times&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://science.nationalgeographic.com/science/environment/alternative-energy/end-cheap-oil.html The End of Cheap Oil], National Geographic&lt;/ref&gt; Despite its distance, the Persian Gulf region was first proclaimed to be of national interest to the United States during World War II. [[Petroleum]] is of central importance to modern armies, and the United States—as the world's leading oil producer at that time—supplied most of the oil for the [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] armies. Many U.S. strategists were concerned that the war would dangerously reduce the U.S. oil supply, and so they sought to establish good relations with [[Saudi Arabia]], a [[Monarchy|kingdom]] with large oil reserves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.globalpolicy.org/security/oil/2005/crudedesigns.htm|title=Crude Designs|author=James Paul |publisher=Global Policy Forum|accessdate=18 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Persian Gulf region continued to be regarded as an area of vital importance to the United States during the [[Cold War]]. Three Cold War [[United States Presidential doctrines]]—the [[Truman Doctrine]], the [[Eisenhower Doctrine]], and the [[Nixon Doctrine]]—played roles in the formulation of the [[Carter Doctrine]], which stated that the United States would use military force if necessary to defend its &quot;[[national interest]]s&quot; in the [[Persian Gulf]] region.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nbcnews.com/id/20874331 The war is about oil but it's not that simple], NBC News&lt;/ref&gt; Carter's successor, President [[Ronald Reagan]], extended the policy in October 1981 with what is sometimes called the ''&quot;Reagan Corollary to the Carter Doctrine&quot;'', which proclaimed that the United States would intervene to protect Saudi Arabia, whose security was threatened after the outbreak of the [[Iran–Iraq War]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.history.navy.mil/wars/dstorm/sword-shield.htm|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150101230128/http://www.history.navy.mil/wars/dstorm/sword-shield.htm|url-status=dead|title=The United States Navy and the Persian Gulf|archivedate=January 1, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some analysts have argued that the implementation of the Carter Doctrine and the Reagan Corollary also played a role in the outbreak of the [[Iraq War|2003 Iraq War]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/996605.html What if the Chinese were to apply the Carter Doctrine?], Haaretz - Israel News&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,921819,00.html Selling the Carter Doctrine], TIME&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/article2461214.ece Alan Greenspan claims Iraq war was really for oil], Times Online&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/jun/20/iraq.oil Oil giants to sign contracts with Iraq], The Guardian&lt;/ref&gt;

===Canada===
Almost all of Canada's energy exports go to the United States, making it the largest foreign source of U.S. energy imports: Canada is consistently among the top sources for U.S. oil imports, and it is the largest source of U.S. natural gas and electricity imports.&lt;ref&gt;See Energy Information Administration, [http://www.eia.doe.gov/emeu/cabs/Canada/Background.html &quot;Canada&quot; (2009 report)] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101210173605/http://www.eia.doe.gov/emeu/cabs/Canada/Background.html |date=December 10, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Africa===
In 2007 the U.S. was [[Sub-Saharan Africa]]'s largest single export market accounting for 28% of exports (second in total to the EU at 31%). 81% of U.S. imports from this region were petroleum products.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.agoa.gov/resources/US_African_Trade_Profile_2009.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2009-06-04 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090812223826/http://agoa.gov/resources/US_African_Trade_Profile_2009.pdf |archivedate=August 12, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Foreign aid==
{{Main|United States foreign aid|United States Agency for International Development}}
Foreign assistance is a core component of the State Department's international affairs budget, which is $49 billion in all for 2014.&lt;ref name=&quot;appropriations.house.gov&quot;&gt;See [http://appropriations.house.gov/uploadedfiles/01.13.14_fy_2014_omnibus_-_state_foreign_operations_-_summary.pdf &quot;FY 2014 Omnibus – State and Foreign Operations Appropriations&quot; (Jan 2014)]&lt;/ref&gt;  Aid is considered an essential instrument of U.S. foreign policy. There are four major categories of non-military foreign assistance: bilateral development aid, economic assistance supporting U.S. political and security goals, humanitarian aid, and multilateral economic contributions (for example, contributions to the World Bank and International Monetary Fund).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://fpc.state.gov/documents/organization/31987.pdf|title=We're sorry, that page can't be found.|website=fpc.state.gov|accessdate=October 14, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In absolute dollar terms, the United States government is the largest international aid donor ($23 billion in 2014).&lt;ref name=&quot;appropriations.house.gov&quot;/&gt;  The [[USAID|U.S. Agency for International Development]] (USAID) manages the bulk of bilateral economic assistance; the Treasury Department handles most multilateral aid. In addition many private agencies, churches and philanthropies provide aid.

Although the United States is the largest donor in absolute dollar terms, it is actually ranked 19 out of 27 countries on the [[Commitment to Development Index]]. The CDI ranks the 27 richest donor countries on their policies that affect the developing world. In the aid component the United States is penalized for low net aid volume as a share of the economy, a large share of [[tied aid|tied]] or partially tied aid, and a large share of aid given to less poor and relatively undemocratic governments.

Foreign aid is a highly partisan issue in the United States, with liberals, on average, supporting foreign aid much more than conservatives do.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sup.org/books/title/?id=23736|title=The Politics of American Foreign Policy: How Ideology Divides Liberals and Conservatives over Foreign Affairs - Peter Hays Gries|author=Stanford University Press|website=Sup.org|accessdate=18 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Military==
As of 2016, the United States is actively conducting military operations against the [[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant]] and [[Al-Qaeda]] under the [[Authorization for Use of Military Force of 2001]], including in areas of fighting in the [[Syrian Civil War]] and [[Yemeni Civil War (2015–present)|Yemeni Civil War]].  The [[Guantanamo Bay Naval Base]] holds what the federal government considers [[unlawful combatant]]s from these ongoing activities, and has been a controversial issue in foreign relations, domestic politics, and [[Cuba–United States relations]].  Other major U.S. military concerns include stability in Afghanistan and Iraq after the recent U.S.–led invasions of those countries, [[Russian military intervention in Ukraine (2014–present)|Russian military activity in Ukraine]] and [[Saudi Arabian-led intervention in Yemen]].

===Mutual defense agreements===
[[File:USA military relations 2007.png|thumb|A map of allies of the United States&lt;br /&gt;
{{legend|#1f78b4|[[NATO]] member states, including their colonies and overseas possessions}}
{{legend|#a6cee3|[[Major non-NATO ally|Major non-NATO allies]], plus [[Taiwan|Republic of China (Taiwan)]]}}
{{legend|#b2df8a|Signatories of [[Partnership for Peace]] with NATO}}]]
The United States is a founding member of [[NATO]], an alliance of 29 North American and European nations formed to defend Western Europe against the Soviet Union during the [[Cold War]].  Under the NATO charter, the United States is compelled to defend any NATO state that is attacked by a foreign power.  The United States itself was the first country to invoke the mutual defense provisions of the alliance, in response to the [[September 11 attacks]].

The United States also has mutual military defense treaties with:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://2009-2017.state.gov/s/l/treaty/collectivedefense|title=U.S. Collective Defense Arrangements|website=State.gov|accessdate=October 14, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[ANZUS|Australia and New Zealand]]
* [[Treaty of Mutual Cooperation and Security between the United States and Japan|Japan]]
* [[Mutual Defense Treaty Between the United States and the Republic of Korea|South Korea]]
* [[Mutual Defense Treaty (United States–Philippines)|Philippines]]
* [[Thailand]], with other states formerly in the [[Southeast Asia Treaty Organization]]
* Most countries in South America, Central America, and the Caribbean, through the [[Inter-American Treaty of Reciprocal Assistance]]

The United States has responsibility for the defense of the three [[Compact of Free Association]] states: [[Federated States of Micronesia]], the [[Marshall Islands]], and [[Palau]].

===Other allies and multilateral organizations===
[[File:American bases worldwide.svg|thumb|upright=1.5|Countries with [[List of United States military bases|U.S. military bases]] (excluding the U.S. Coast Guard).]]
In 1989, the United States also granted five nations the [[major non-NATO ally]] status (MNNA), and additions by later presidents have brought the list to 28 nations. Each such state has a unique relationship with the United States, involving various military and economic partnerships and alliances.

[[File:Members of the U.S. Air Force Special Operations Command, assigned to the 23rd Special Tactics Squadron.jpg|thumb|U.S. Air Force Special Tactics Commandos training with Jordanian special operations forces]]

and lesser agreements with:
* [[Taiwan Relations Act|Taiwan]]
* [[Israel–United States relations|Israel]]
* [[Saudi Arabia–United States relations|Saudi Arabia]]

The U.S. participates in various military-related multi-lateral organizations, including:
* [[Organisation for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons]]
* [[International Atomic Energy Agency]]

The U.S. also operates hundreds of military bases around the world.

===Unilateral vs. multilateral military actions===
The United States has undertaken unilateral and multilateral military operations throughout its history (see [[Timeline of United States military operations]]).  In the post-World War II era, the country has had permanent membership and veto power in the [[United Nations Security Council]], allowing it to undertake any military action without formal Security Council opposition.  With vast military expenditures, the United States is known as the sole remaining [[superpower]] after the collapse of the Soviet Union.  The U.S. contributes a relatively small number of personnel for [[United Nations peacekeeping]] operations.  It sometimes acts through NATO, as with the [[NATO intervention in Bosnia and Herzegovina]], [[NATO bombing of Yugoslavia]], and [[International Security Assistance Force|ISAF in Afghanistan]], but often acts unilaterally or in ad-hoc coalitions as with the [[2003 invasion of Iraq]].

The [[United Nations Charter]] requires that military operations be either for self-defense or affirmatively approved by the Security Council.  Though many of their operations have followed these rules, the United States and NATO have been accused of committing [[crime against peace|crimes against peace]] in international law, for example in the 1999 Yugoslavia and 2003 Iraq operations.

===Aid===
{{Main|United States military aid|United States Foreign Military Financing|Foreign Military Sales}}
[[File:Flickr - The U.S. Army - Humanitarian aid in Rajan Kala, Afghanistan.jpg|thumb|U.S. Soldiers unload humanitarian aid for distribution to the town of Rajan Kala, [[Afghanistan]], December 2009]]
The [[United States military aid|U.S. provides military aid]] through many different channels. Counting the items that appear in the budget as '[[United States Foreign Military Financing|Foreign Military Financing]]' and '[[Plan Colombia]]', the U.S. spent approximately $4.5 billion in military aid in 2001, of which $2 billion went to [[Israel]], $1.3 billion went to [[Egypt]], and $1 billion went to [[Colombia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.amnestyusa.org/all-countries/colombia/us-military-aid-to-colombia/page.do?id=1101863 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081022165529/http://www.amnestyusa.org/all-countries/colombia/us-military-aid-to-colombia/page.do?id=1101863 |url-status=dead |archive-date=2008-10-22 |title=U.S. Policy in Colombia &amp;#124; Amnesty International USA |publisher=Amnestyusa.org |accessdate=2014-08-18 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Since [[9/11]], [[Pakistan]] has received approximately $11.5 billion in direct military aid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.thenews.com.pk/archive/print/462363-all-our-rulers-have-carried-a-begging-bowl-to-us |title=The News International: Latest, Breaking, Pakistan, Sports and Video News |publisher= |accessdate=18 February 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of 2004, according to Fox News, the U.S. had more than 700 military bases in 130 different countries.&lt;ref&gt;Fox News, 1 November 2004 [http://www.globalsecurity.org/org/news/2004/041101-iraq-basing.htm Analysts Ponder U.S. Basing in Iraq]&lt;/ref&gt;

Estimated U.S. foreign military financing and aid by recipient for 2010:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Recipient !!Military aid 2010 (USD Billions)
|-
|{{flag|Iraq}}||6.50
|-
|{{flag|Afghanistan}}||5.60&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://fas.org/sgp/crs/row/R40699.pdf|title=Afghanistan: US foreign assistance|website=Fas.org|accessdate=October 14, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{flag|Israel}}||2.75&lt;ref name=&quot;jewishvirtuallibrary.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/US-Israel/aid2010.html|title=Page Not Found|website=www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org|accessdate=October 14, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{flag|Egypt}}||1.75&lt;ref name=smh&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.smh.com.au/world/us-aid-tied-to-purchase-of-arms-20100101-llsb.html|title=US aid tied to purchase of arms|author=Anne Davies|date=January 2, 2010|accessdate=October 14, 2017|newspaper=[[The Sydney Morning Herald]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{flag|Pakistan}}||1.60&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://belfercenter.ksg.harvard.edu/files/Final_DP_2009_06_08092009.pdf|title=Aid to Pakistan|website=Belfercenter.ksg.harvard.edu|accessdate=October 14, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{flag|Colombia}}||.834&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ciponline.org/facts/below_the_radar_eng.pdf|title=U.S. Arms and Training Fuel UAE's War in Yemen|website=Ciponline.org|accessdate=14 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{flag|Jordan}}||.300&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://fas.org/sgp/crs/mideast/RL33546.pdf|title=Jordan: Background and U.S relations|website=Fas.org|accessdate=October 14, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{flag|Palestinian Authority}}||.100&lt;ref name=smh/&gt;
|-
|{{flag|Yemen}}||.070
|}

According to a 2016 report by the [[Congressional Research Service]], the U.S. topped the market in global weapon sales for 2015, with $40 billion sold. The largest buyers were Qatar, Egypt, Saudi Arabia, South Korea, Pakistan, Israel, the United Arab Emirates and Iraq.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2016/12/26/us/politics/united-states-global-weapons-sales.html?_r=0|title=U.S. Sold $40 Billion in Weapons in 2015, Topping Global Market|newspaper=The New York Times |date= 2016-12-26 |accessdate=2017-01-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Missile defense===
{{Main|National missile defense|Strategic Defense Initiative}}
The [[Strategic Defense Initiative]] (SDI) was a proposal by U.S. President [[Ronald Reagan]] on March 23, 1983&lt;ref&gt;[[Federation of American Scientists]]. [https://fas.org/spp/starwars/program/milestone.htm Missile Defense Milestones] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160306023546/http://fas.org/spp/starwars/program/milestone.htm |date=March 6, 2016 }}. Accessed March 10, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; to use ground and space-based systems to protect the United States from attack by strategic [[nuclear weapon|nuclear]] [[ballistic missile]]s,&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.independent.co.uk/opinion/commentators/johann-hari/johann-hari-obamas-chance-to-end-the--fantasy-that-is-star-wars-1015509.html Johann Hari: Obama's chance to end the fantasy that is Star Wars], The Independent, November 13, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; later dubbed ''&quot;Star Wars&quot;''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/SPECIALS/cold.war/episodes/22/documents/starwars.speech/ Historical Documents: Reagan's 'Star Wars' speech] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081219114207/http://www.cnn.com/SPECIALS/cold.war/episodes/22/documents/starwars.speech/ |date=December 19, 2008 }}, CNN Cold War&lt;/ref&gt; The initiative focused on strategic defense rather than the prior strategic offense doctrine of [[mutual assured destruction]] (MAD). Though it was never fully developed or deployed, the research and technologies of SDI paved the way for some [[anti-ballistic missile]] systems of today.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://science.howstuffworks.com/missile-defense3.htm|title=Son of &quot;Star Wars&quot; - How Missile Defense Systems Will Work|work=HowStuffWorks|accessdate=18 February 2015|date=April 5, 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2007, the U.S. started formal negotiations with Poland and [[Czech Republic]] concerning construction of missile shield installations in those countries for a [[Ground-Based Midcourse Defense]] system&lt;ref name=&quot;news.yahoo.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20080823/ap_on_go_co/us_russia_missile_defense|title=Missile defense backers now cite Russia threat|website=News.yahoo.com|accessdate=October 14, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; (in April 2007, 57% of [[Poles]] opposed the plan).&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/04/24/AR2007042400871.html U.S. Might Negotiate on Missile Defense], washingtonpost.com&lt;/ref&gt; According to press reports the government of the Czech Republic agreed (while 67% Czechs disagree)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cvvm.cas.cz/upl/zpravy/100761s_pm80306.pdf Citizens on U.S. Anti-Missile Radar Base in Czech Republic] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081130053315/http://www.cvvm.cas.cz/upl/zpravy/100761s_pm80306.pdf |date=November 30, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; to host a [[missile defense]] radar on its territory while a base of missile interceptors is supposed to be built in Poland.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/6704669.stm Europe diary: Missile defence], BBC News&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.rand.org/commentary/032907IHT.html|title=Missile Defense: Avoiding a Crisis in Europe|website=rand.org|accessdate=18 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Russia threatened to place short-range [[nuclear missiles]] on the Russia's border with [[NATO]] if the United States refuses to abandon plans to deploy 10 interceptor missiles and a radar in Poland and the Czech Republic.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/1569495/Russia-piles-pressure-on-EU-over-missile-shield.html Russia piles pressure on EU over missile shield], Telegraph&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2008/05/23/asia/AS-GEN-China-Russia.php China, Russia sign nuclear deal, condemn U.S. missile defense plans], International Herald Tribune&lt;/ref&gt; In April 2007, Putin warned of a new [[Cold War]] if the Americans deployed the shield in Central Europe.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/world/2007/apr/11/usa.topstories3 Russia threatening new cold war over missile defence], The Guardian&lt;/ref&gt; Putin also said that Russia is prepared to abandon its obligations under an [[Intermediate-Range Nuclear Forces Treaty]] of 1987 with the United States.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.usatoday.com/news/world/2007-10-12-us-russia_N.htm U.S., Russia no closer on missile defense], USATODAY.com&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 14, 2008, the United States and Poland announced a deal to implement the [[U.S. missile defense complex in Poland|missile defense system in Polish territory]], with a tracking system placed in the Czech Republic.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/2008/08/15/world/europe/16poland.html?hp Russia Lashes Out on Missile Deal], The New York Times, August 15, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;The fact that this was signed in a period of very difficult crisis in the relations between Russia and the United States over the situation in [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]] shows that, of course, the missile defense system will be deployed not against [[Iran]] but against the strategic potential of Russia&quot;, Dmitry Rogozin, Russia's [[NATO]] envoy, said.&lt;ref name=&quot;news.yahoo.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/news/europe/2008/08/200881514010734640.html Russia angry over U.S. missile shield], Al Jazeera English, August 15, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

Keir A. Lieber and Daryl G. Press, argue in Foreign Affairs that U.S. missile defenses are designed to secure Washington's nuclear primacy and are chiefly directed at potential rivals, such as Russia and China. The authors note that Washington continues to eschew nuclear first strike and contend that deploying missile defenses &quot;would be valuable primarily in an offensive context, not a defensive one; as an adjunct to a US First Strike capability, not as a stand-alone shield&quot;:

&lt;blockquote&gt;If the United States launched a nuclear attack against Russia (or China), the targeted country would be left with only a tiny surviving arsenal, if any at all. At that point, even a relatively modest or inefficient missile defense system might well be enough to protect against any retaliatory strikes.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.foreignaffairs.com/articles/united-states/2006-03-01/rise-us-nuclear-primacy &quot;The Rise of U.S. Nuclear Primacy&quot;] Keir A. Lieber and Daryl G. Press, Foreign Affairs, March/April 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

This analysis is corroborated by the Pentagon's 1992 Defense Planning Guidance (DPG), prepared by then Secretary of Defense Richard Cheney and his deputies. The DPG declares that the United States should use its power to &quot;prevent the reemergence of a new rival&quot; either on former Soviet territory or elsewhere. The authors of the Guidance determined that the United States had to &quot;Field a missile defense system as a shield against accidental missile launches or limited missile strikes by 'international outlaws'&quot; and also must &quot;Find ways to integrate the 'new democracies' of the former Soviet bloc into the U.S.-led system&quot;. The National Archive notes that Document 10 of the DPG includes wording about &quot;disarming capabilities to destroy&quot; which is followed by several blacked out words. &quot;This suggests that some of the heavily excised pages in the still-classified DPG drafts may include some discussion of preventive action against threatening nuclear and other WMD programs.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://nsarchive.gwu.edu/nukevault/ebb245/ &quot;Prevent the Reemergence of a New Rival&quot;] The National Security Archive&lt;/ref&gt;

Finally, Robert David English, writing in Foreign Affairs, observes that in addition to the deployment U.S. missile defenses, the DPG's second recommendation has also been proceeding on course. &quot;Washington has pursued policies that have ignored Russian interests (and sometimes international law as well) in order to encircle Moscow with military alliances and trade blocs conducive to U.S. interests.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.foreignaffairs.com/articles/russian-federation/2017-03-10/russia-trump-and-new-d-tente &quot;Russia, Trump, and a New Détente&quot;] Foreign Affairs, March 10, 2017&lt;/ref&gt;

===Exporting democracy===
  {{See also|Democracy promotion by the United States}}

Studies have been devoted to the historical success rate of the U.S. in exporting democracy abroad. Some studies of American intervention have been pessimistic about the overall effectiveness of U.S. efforts to encourage democracy in foreign nations.&lt;ref name=&quot;operation&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
|first=John A.
|last=Tures
|title=Operation Exporting Freedom: The Quest for Democratization via United States Military Operations
|journal=[[Whitehead Journal of Diplomacy and International Relations]]
|url=http://blogs.shu.edu/diplomacy/files/archives/09_tures.pdf
}}PDF file.&lt;/ref&gt; Until recently, scholars have generally agreed with international relations professor Abraham Lowenthal that U.S. attempts to export democracy have been &quot;negligible, often counterproductive, and only occasionally positive&quot;.&lt;ref name = &quot;Abraham&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|last=Lowenthal
|first=Abraham
|title=The United States and Latin American Democracy: Learning from History
|year=1991
|publisher=Johns Hopkins University Press
|pages=243–65
|location=Baltimore
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;mark7&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|last=Peceny
|first=Mark
|year=1999
|title=Democracy at the Point of Bayonets
|publisher=University Park: Pennsylvania State University Press
|page=183
|isbn=0-271-01883-6
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other studies find [[List of United States military history events|U.S. intervention]] has had mixed results,&lt;ref name=&quot;operation&quot; /&gt; and another by Hermann and Kegley has found that military interventions have improved democracy in other countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;promote&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |first=Margaret G. |last=Hermann|authorlink1=Margaret Hermann |year=1998 |title=The U.S. Use of Military Intervention to Promote Democracy: Evaluating the Record |journal=International Interactions  |volume=24 |issue=2 |pages=91–114 |doi=10.1080/03050629808434922 |last2=Kegley |first2=Charles}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Opinion that U.S. intervention does not export democracy====
In [[United States]] history, critics have charged that [[President of the United States|presidents]] have used [[democracy]] to justify [[List of United States military history events|military intervention]] abroad.&lt;ref name=&quot;Why&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
 |first       = Bruce Bueno de
 |last        = Mesquita
 |date        = Spring 2004
 |title       = Why Gun-Barrel Democracy Doesn't Work
 |journal     = Hoover Digest
 |volume      = 2
 |url         = http://www.hooverdigest.org/042/bdm.html
 |url-status     = dead
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20080705115001/http://www.hooverdigest.org/042/bdm.html
 |archivedate = July 5, 2008
 |df          = mdy
}} Also see [https://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/travbailey/why.html&amp;date=2009-10-25+23:16:02 this page].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Meernik 1996 391&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
|first=James
|last=Meernik
|year=1996
|title=United States Military Intervention and the Promotion of Democracy
|journal=Journal of Peace Research
|volume=33
|issue=4
|pages=391–402
|doi=10.1177/0022343396033004002
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Critics have also charged that the U.S. helped local militaries overthrow democratically elected governments in [[Operation Ajax|Iran]], [[Operation PBSUCCESS|Guatemala]], and in other instances. 

Professor Paul W. Drake argued that the U.S. first attempted to export [[democracy]] in [[Latin America]] through intervention from 1912 to 1932. Drake argued that this was contradictory because international law defines [[invasion|intervention]] as &quot;dictatorial interference in the affairs of another state for the purpose of altering the condition of things&quot;. The study suggested that efforts to promote democracy failed because democracy needs to develop out of internal conditions, and can not be forcibly imposed. There was disagreement about what constituted ''[[democracy]]''; Drake suggested American leaders sometimes defined democracy in a narrow sense of a nation having elections; Drake suggested a broader understanding was needed. Further, there was disagreement about what constituted a &quot;rebellion&quot;; Drake saw a pattern in which the [[United States Department of State|U.S. State Department]] disapproved of any type of rebellion, even so-called &quot;revolutions&quot;, and in some instances rebellions against dictatorships.&lt;ref name=&quot;LA1&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Lowenthal |first=Abraham F. |date=March 1, 1991 |title=Exporting Democracy : The United States and Latin America |pages=[https://archive.org/details/exportingdemocra00lowe_1/page/1 1, 4, 5] |publisher=The Johns Hopkins University Press |isbn=0-8018-4132-1 |url=https://archive.org/details/exportingdemocra00lowe_1/page/1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Historian [[Walter LaFeber]] stated, &quot;The world's leading revolutionary nation (the U.S.) in the eighteenth century became the leading protector of the status quo in the twentieth century.&quot;&lt;ref name = &quot;Walter&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Lafeber |first=Walter |year=1993 |title=Inevitable Revolutions: The United States in Central America |publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company |isbn=0-393-30964-9 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/inevitablerevolu00laferich }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Kissinger, Ford, Suharto and Malik (cropped).jpg|thumb|Indonesian President [[Suharto]] with U.S. President [[Gerald Ford]] in Jakarta on 6 December 1975, one day before the [[Indonesian invasion of East Timor]].]]
[[Bruce Bueno de Mesquita|Mesquita]] and Downs evaluated 35 U.S. interventions from 1945 to 2004 and concluded that in only one case, [[Colombia]], did a &quot;full fledged, stable democracy&quot; develop within ten years following the intervention.&lt;ref name=&quot;Why2&quot;&gt;Factors included limits on [[executive power]], clear rules for the transition of power, [[Universal suffrage|universal adult suffrage]], and
competitive elections.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.hoover.org/research/why-gun-barrel-democracy-doesnt-work|title=Why Gun-Barrel Democracy Doesn't Work|website=Hoover Institution|language=en|access-date=2019-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Samia Amin Pei argued that nation building in developed countries usually unravelled four to six years after American intervention ended. Pei, based on study of a database on worldwide democracies called ''[[Polity]]'', agreed with Mesquita and Downs that U.S. intervention efforts usually don't produce real democracies, and that most cases result in greater authoritarianism after ten years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
|first=Samia Amin
|last=Pei
|date=March 17, 2004
|title=Why Nation-Building Fails in Mid-Course
|journal=International Herald Tribune
|url=http://www.carnegieendowment.org/publications/index.cfm?fa=view&amp;id=1479
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Professor [[Joshua Muravchik]] argued U.S. occupation was critical for [[Axis Powers|Axis power]] democratization after [[World War II]], but America's failure to encourage democracy in the [[third world]] &quot;prove&amp;nbsp;... that U.S. military occupation is not a sufficient condition to make a country democratic&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mark4&quot;&gt;Peceny, p. 186.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;joshua&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|last=Muravchik
|first=Joshua
|year=1991
|title=Exporting Democracy: Fulfilling America's Destiny
|publisher=American Enterprise Institute Press
|pages=91–118
|location=Washington, DC
|isbn=0-8447-3734-8
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The success of democracy in former Axis countries such as [[Italy]] were seen as a result of high national per-capita income, although U.S. protection was seen as a key to stabilization and important for encouraging the transition to democracy. Steven Krasner agreed that there was a link between wealth and democracy; when per-capita incomes of $6,000 were achieved in a democracy, there was little chance of that country ever reverting to an [[autocracy]], according to an analysis of his research in the ''[[Los Angeles Times]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;LA2&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
 |first        = Stephen D.
 |last         = Krasner
 |date         = November 26, 2003
 |title        = We Don't Know How To Build Democracy
 |journal      = Los Angeles Times
 |url          = http://cddrl.stanford.edu/news/krasner_opinion_piece_in_la_times_asserts_we_dont_know_how_to_build_democracy_20031117/
 |access-date  = April 12, 2008
 |archive-url  = https://web.archive.org/web/20120117192652/http://cddrl.stanford.edu/news/krasner_opinion_piece_in_la_times_asserts_we_dont_know_how_to_build_democracy_20031117/
 |archive-date = January 17, 2012
 |url-status     = dead
 |df           = mdy-all
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Opinion that U.S. intervention has mixed results====
Tures examined 228 cases of American intervention from 1973 to 2005, using [[Freedom House]] data. A plurality of interventions, 96, caused no change in the country's democracy. In 69 instances, the country became less democratic after the intervention. In the remaining 63 cases, a country became more democratic.&lt;ref name=&quot;operation&quot;/&gt; However this does not take into account the direction the country would have gone with no U.S. intervention.

====Opinion that U.S. intervention effectively exports democracy====
Hermann and Kegley found that American military interventions designed to protect or promote democracy increased freedom in those countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;promote&quot;/&gt; Peceny argued that the democracies created after military intervention are still closer to an [[autocracy]] than a [[democracy]], quoting Przeworski &quot;while some democracies are more democratic than others, unless offices are contested, no regime should be considered democratic.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Przeworski|first=Adam|authorlink=|last2=Przeworski|first2=Adam|last3=Limongi Neto|first3=Fernando Papaterra|last4=Alvarez|first4=Michael M.|year=1996|title=What Makes Democracy Endure|journal=Journal of Democracy|volume=7|issue=1|pages=39–55|doi=10.1353/jod.1996.0016|url=https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/382b52829b7cdf7b77cbc19d9bc31175d3c20712}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, Peceny concludes, it is difficult to know from the Hermann and Kegley study whether U.S. intervention has only produced less repressive autocratic governments or genuine democracies.&lt;ref&gt;Peceny, p. 193&lt;/ref&gt;

Peceny stated that the United States attempted to export democracy in 33 of its 93 20th-century military interventions.&lt;ref name=&quot;mark6&quot;&gt;Peceny, p. 2&lt;/ref&gt; Peceny argued that proliberal policies after military intervention had a positive impact on democracy.&lt;ref&gt;Review: {{cite journal
 |first=Michael 
 |last=Shifter 
 |date=Winter 2001 
 |title=Democracy at the Point of Bayonets 
 |journal=Latin American Politics and Society 
 |volume=43 
 |issue=4 
 |page=150 
 |url=http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa4000/is_200101/ai_n8943833
 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20050320015036/http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa4000/is_200101/ai_n8943833
 |url-status=dead
 |archive-date=2005-03-20
 |doi=10.2307/3177036 
 |last2=Peceny 
 |first2=Mark 
|jstor=3177036 
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Global opinion==
A global survey done by Pewglobal indicated that at (as of 2014) least 33 surveyed countries have a positive view (50% or above) of the United States. With the top ten most positive countries being Philippines (92%), Israel (84%), South Korea (82%), Kenya (80%), El Salvador (80%), Italy (78%), Ghana (77%), Vietnam (76%), Bangladesh (76%), and Tanzania (75%). While 10 surveyed countries have the most negative view (Below 50%) of the United States. With the countries being Egypt (10%), Jordan (12%), Pakistan (14%), Turkey (19%), Russia (23%), Palestinian Territories (30%), Greece (34%), Argentina (36%), Lebanon (41%), Tunisia (42%). Americans' own view of the United States was viewed at 84%.&lt;ref name=&quot;Global opinion&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pewglobal.org/database/indicator/1/survey/16/|title=Global Indicators Database|date=April 22, 2010|website=Pewglobal.org|accessdate=October 14, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
International opinion about the US has often changed with different executive administrations. For example, in 2009, the French public favored the United States when President Barack Obama (75% favorable) replaced President George W. Bush (42%). After President Donald Trump took the helm in 2017, French public opinion about the US fell from 63% to 46%. These trends were also seen in other European countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2017/08/18/6-trends-in-international-public-opinion-from-our-global-indicators-database/ |title = 5 trends in international public opinion from our searchable Global Indicators Database}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Covert actions==
{{anchor|Covert United States involvement in regime change}}
{{Main|United States involvement in regime change|History of the Central Intelligence Agency}}
{{See also|Clandestine HUMINT and covert action}}
{{Covert United States involvement in regime change}}
United States foreign policy also includes covert actions to topple foreign governments that have been opposed to the United States. According to J. Dana Stuster, writing in ''[[Foreign Policy]]'', there are seven &quot;confirmed cases&quot; where the U.S.—acting principally through the [[Central Intelligence Agency]] (CIA), but sometimes with the support of other parts of the U.S. government, including the [[United States Navy|Navy]] and [[United States Department of State|State Department]]—covertly assisted in the overthrow of a foreign government: [[1953 Iranian coup d'état|Iran in 1953]], [[1954 Guatemalan coup d'état|Guatemala in 1954]], [[Patrice Lumumba#United States involvement|Congo in 1960]], [[Rafael Trujillo#Assassination|the Dominican Republic in 1961]], [[1963 South Vietnamese coup|South Vietnam in 1963]], [[1964 Brazilian coup d'état|Brazil in 1964]], and [[1973 Chilean coup d'état|Chile in 1973]]. Stuster states that this list excludes &quot;U.S.-supported insurgencies and failed assassination attempts&quot; such as [[Cuban Project#Assassination proposals|those directed against Cuba's Fidel Castro]], as well as instances where U.S. involvement has been alleged but not proven (such as [[March 1949 Syrian coup d'état|Syria in 1949]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Stuster|first=J. Dana|url=https://foreignpolicy.com/2013/08/20/mapped-the-7-governments-the-u-s-has-overthrown/|title=Mapped: The 7 Governments the U.S. Has Overthrown|work=[[Foreign Policy]]|date=2013-08-20|accessdate=2016-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1953 the CIA, working with the British government, initiated ''[[Operation Ajax]]'' against the [[Prime Minister of Iran]] [[Mohammad Mossadegh]] who had attempted to [[nationalize]] Iran's oil, threatening the interests of the [[Anglo-Persian Oil Company]]. This had the effect of restoring and strengthening the authoritarian monarchical reign of [[Shah]] [[Mohammad Reza Pahlavi]].&lt;ref name=NYTsr2000&gt;{{Cite news|work=[[The New York Times]]|title=Special Report: Secret History of the CIA in Iran|url=https://www.nytimes.com/library/world/mideast/041600iran-cia-index.html| year=2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1957, the CIA and [[Israel]]i [[Mossad]] aided the Iranian government in establishing its intelligence service, [[SAVAK]], later blamed for the torture and execution of the regime's opponents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/irancountrystudy00curt_2/page/276|title=Iran: A Country Study|editor-first1=Glenn E.|editor-last1=Curtis|editor-first2=Eric|editor-last2=Hooglund|publisher=Library of Congress, Federal Research Division|location=Washington, D.C.|edition=Fifth|year=2008|page=[https://archive.org/details/irancountrystudy00curt_2/page/276 276]|isbn=9780844411873}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.pbs.org/newshour/updates/middle_east-jan-june10-timeline/|title=Timeline: A Modern History of Iran|work=[[PBS NewsHour]]|date=February 11, 2010|accessdate=  November 23, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A year later, in [[1954 Guatemalan coup d'état|''Operation PBSUCCESS'']], the CIA assisted the local military in toppling the democratically elected left-wing government of [[Jacobo Árbenz]] in [[Guatemala]] and installing the military dictator [[Carlos Castillo Armas]]. The [[United Fruit Company]] lobbied for Árbenz overthrow as his [[Decree 900|land reforms]] jeopardized their land holdings in Guatemala, and painted these reforms as a communist threat. The coup triggered a decades long [[Guatemalan Civil War|civil war]] which claimed the lives of an estimated 200,000 people (42,275 individual cases have been documented), mostly through [[Guatemalan genocide|626 massacres against the Maya population]] perpetrated by the U.S.-backed Guatemalan military.&lt;ref&gt;[[Stephen Schlesinger]] (3 June 2011). [https://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/04/opinion/04schlesinger.html?_r=0 Ghosts of Guatemala's Past]. ''[[The New York Times]].'' Retrieved 5 July 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Navarro&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Navarro |first= Mireya|date= February 26, 1999 |title= Guatemalan Army Waged 'Genocide,' New Report Finds|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1999/02/26/world/guatemalan-army-waged-genocide-new-report-finds.html|newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |location= |access-date=November 21, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Jones|first=Maggie|date=June 30, 2016|title=The Secrets in Guatemala's Bones|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2016/07/03/magazine/the-secrets-in-guatemalas-bones.html?_r=1 |newspaper=The New York Times|access-date=November 21, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Allan|last=Cooper|year=2008|title=The Geography of Genocide|publisher=[[University Press of America]]|isbn=978-0761840978|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Uyh8kdcuA1kC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA171#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |page=171}}&lt;/ref&gt; An independent Historical Clarification Commission found that U.S. corporations and government officials &quot;exercised pressure to maintain the country's archaic and unjust socio-economic structure,&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Navarro&quot;/&gt; and that U.S. military assistance had a &quot;significant bearing on human rights violations during the armed confrontation&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Blakeley|first=Ruth|date=2009 |title=State Terrorism and Neoliberalism: The North in the South|url=http://www.routledge.com/books/details/9780415462402/|location= |publisher=[[Routledge]]|page=94|isbn=978-0415686174}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Indonesian mass killings of 1965–66|massacre of at least 500,000 alleged communists]] in 1960s Indonesia, U.S. government officials encouraged and applauded the mass killings while providing covert assistance to the Indonesian military which helped facilitate them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Robinson|first=Geoffrey B.|date= 2018|title=The Killing Season: A History of the Indonesian Massacres, 1965-66|url=https://press.princeton.edu/titles/11135.html|location= |publisher=[[Princeton University Press]] |pages=22–23, 177|isbn=9781400888863}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Beech |first=Hannah |date=October 18, 2017 |title=U.S. Stood by as Indonesia Killed a Half-Million People, Papers Show|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2017/10/18/world/asia/indonesia-cables-communist-massacres.html|work=The New York Times |location= |access-date= October 19, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Simpson|first=Bradley|date= 2010|title=Economists with Guns: Authoritarian Development and U.S.–Indonesian Relations, 1960-1968|url= |location= |publisher=[[Stanford University Press]]|page=193|isbn=978-0804771825|quote=&quot;Washington did everything in its power to encourage and facilitate the army-led massacre of alleged PKI members, and U.S. officials worried only that the killing of the party's unarmed supporters might not go far enough, permitting Sukarno to return to power and frustrate the [Johnson] Administration's emerging plans for a post-Sukarno Indonesia.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Thaler&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Scott&quot;/&gt; This included the U.S. Embassy in Jakarta supplying Indonesian forces with lists of up to 5,000 names of suspected members of the [[Communist Party of Indonesia]] (PKI), who were subsequently killed in the massacres.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Robinson|first=Geoffrey B.|date= 2018|title=The Killing Season: A History of the Indonesian Massacres, 1965-66|url=https://press.princeton.edu/titles/11135.html|location= |publisher=[[Princeton University Press]] |page=203 |isbn=9781400888863|quote=a US Embassy official in Jakarta, Robert Martens, had supplied the Indonesian Army with lists containing the names of thousands of PKI officials in the months after the alleged coup attempt. According to the journalist Kathy Kadane, &quot;As many as 5,000 names were furnished over a period of months to the Army there, and the Americans later checked off the names of those who had been killed or captured.&quot; Despite Martens later denials of any such intent, these actions almost certainly aided in the death or detention of many innocent people. They also sent a powerful message that the US government agreed with and supported the army's campaign against the PKI, even as that campaign took its terrible toll in human lives.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bellamy, Alex J. (2012). ''Massacres and Morality: Mass Atrocities in an Age of Civilian Immunity.'' [[Oxford University Press]]. {{ISBN|0-19-928842-9}}. [https://books.google.com/books?id=EK8eK2xPCycC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA210#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false p. 210.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name =&quot;BlumenthalMcCormack&quot;&gt;Mark Aarons (2007). &quot;[https://books.google.com/books?id=dg0hWswKgTIC&amp;lpg=PA80&amp;pg=PA69#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Justice Betrayed: Post-1945 Responses to Genocide].&quot; In David A. Blumenthal and Timothy L. H. McCormack (eds). ''[http://www.brill.com/legacy-nuremberg-civilising-influence-or-institutionalised-vengeance The Legacy of Nuremberg: Civilising Influence or Institutionalised Vengeance? (International Humanitarian Law).]'' [[Martinus Nijhoff Publishers]]. {{ISBN|9004156917}} [https://books.google.com/books?id=dg0hWswKgTIC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA81#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false pp.&amp;nbsp;80–81]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Valentino|first=Benjamin A.|date=2005 |title=Final Solutions: Mass Killing and Genocide in the 20th Century|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZNy55BHupsoC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA27#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|location= |publisher=[[Cornell University Press]]|page=27 |isbn=978-0801472732}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2001, the CIA attempted to prevent the publication of the State Department volume ''Foreign Relations of the United States, 1964–1968'', which documents the [[CIA activities in Indonesia#Anti-communist purge|U.S. role]] in providing covert assistance to the Indonesian military for the express purpose of the extirpation of the PKI.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scott&quot;&gt;Margaret Scott (November 2, 2015) [http://www.nybooks.com/blogs/nyrblog/2015/nov/02/indonesian-massacre-what-did-us-know/ The Indonesian Massacre: What Did the US Know?] ''[[The New York Review of Books]].'' Retrieved November 6, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.latimes.com/2001/jul/28/news/mn-27536 U.S. Seeks to Keep Lid on Far East Purge Role]. ''The Associated Press'' via ''The Los Angeles Times'', July 28, 2001. Retrieved November 6, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Thomas Blanton (ed). [http://nsarchive.gwu.edu/NSAEBB/NSAEBB52/ CIA Stalling State Department Histories: State Historians Conclude U.S. Passed Names Of Communists To Indonesian Army, Which Killed At Least 105,000 In 1965–66]. National Security Archive Electronic Briefing Book No. 52., July 27, 2001. Retrieved November 6, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2016,  an international panel of judges ruled the killings constitute crimes against humanity, and that the US, along with other Western governments, were complicit in these crimes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Perry|first=Juliet |date=July 21, 2016|title=Tribunal finds Indonesia guilty of 1965 genocide; US, UK complicit|url=http://www.cnn.com/2016/07/21/asia/indonesia-genocide-panel/index.html|work=CNN |location= |access-date=June 5, 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1970, the [[United States intervention in Chile#Track II|CIA worked with coup-plotters]] in Chile in the attempted kidnapping of General [[René Schneider]], who was targeted for refusing to participate in a military coup upon the election of [[Salvador Allende]]. Schneider was shot in the botched attempt and died three days later. The CIA later paid the group $35,000 for the failed kidnapping.&lt;ref&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/International/story?id=82588 CIA Admits Involvement in Chile]. ''[[ABC News]].'' September 20&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[John Dinges]]. ''The Condor Years: How Pinochet And His Allies Brought Terrorism To Three Continents.'' [[The New Press]], 2005. [https://books.google.com/books?id=3JjtHROah_YC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA20#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false p. 20]. {{ISBN|1565849779}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Influencing foreign elections==
{{Main|Foreign electoral intervention}}
According to one peer-reviewed study, the U.S. intervened in 81 foreign elections between 1946 and 2000, while the Soviet Union or Russia intervened in 36.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Levin|first=Dov H.|url=http://isq.oxfordjournals.org/content/60/2/189|title=When the Great Power Gets a Vote: The Effects of Great Power Electoral Interventions on Election Results|journal=[[International Studies Quarterly]]|volume=60|issue=2|pages=189–202|date=June 2016|doi=10.1093/isq/sqv016}} See the full list of interventions in the [http://isq.oxfordjournals.org/content/isq/suppl/2016/02/29/sqv016.DC1/appendix_2.pdf appendix.] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170118105110/http://isq.oxfordjournals.org/content/isq/suppl/2016/02/29/sqv016.DC1/appendix_2.pdf |date=January 18, 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Agrawal|first=Nina|url=http://www.latimes.com/nation/la-na-us-intervention-foreign-elections-20161213-story.html|title=The U.S. is no stranger to interfering in the elections of other countries|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=2016-12-21|accessdate=2018-01-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Human rights==
{{See also|Human rights violations by the CIA|United States and state-sponsored terrorism|United States and state terrorism}}
[[File:Mobutu Nixon.gif|thumb|[[Zaire]]an dictator [[Mobutu Sese Seko]] and Richard Nixon in Washington, D.C., October 1973]]
Since the 1970s, issues of human rights have become increasingly important in American foreign policy.&lt;ref&gt;Joe Renouard, ''Human Rights in American Foreign Policy: From the 1960s to the Soviet Collapse'' (U of Pennsylvania Press, 2016). 324 pp.&lt;/ref&gt; Congress took the lead in the 1970s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crabb &amp; Holt&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Crabb|first=Cecil V.|title=Invitation to Struggle: Congress, the President and Foreign Policy|year=1992|publisher=Congressional Quarterly|location=Michigan|isbn=978-0-87187-622-5|pages=187–211|url=https://books.google.com/?id=vW2GAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=Invitation+to+Struggle&amp;dq=Invitation+to+Struggle|edition=2nd|author2=Pat Holt}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the [[Vietnam War]], the feeling that U.S. foreign policy had grown apart from traditional American values was seized upon by [[Donald M. Fraser|Senator Donald M. Fraser (D, MI)]], leading the Subcommittee on International Organizations and Movements, in criticizing Republican Foreign Policy under [[Richard Nixon#Presidency|the Nixon administration]]. In the early 1970s, Congress concluded the Vietnam War and passed the [[War Powers Resolution|War Powers Act]]. As &quot;part of a growing assertiveness by Congress about many aspects of Foreign Policy,&quot;&lt;ref name=Forsythe&gt;{{cite book|last=Forsythe|first=David|title=Human Rights and U.S. Foreign Policy: Congress Reconsidered|year=1988|publisher=University Press of Florida|location=Gainesville|isbn=978-0-8130-0885-1|pages=[https://archive.org/details/humanrightsusfor00fors/page/1 1]–23|url=https://archive.org/details/humanrightsusfor00fors|url-access=registration|quote=Human Rights and U.S. Foreign Policy: Congress Reconsidered.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Human Rights concerns became a battleground between the Legislative and the Executive branches in the formulation of foreign policy. David Forsythe points to three specific, early examples of Congress interjecting its own thoughts on foreign policy:

# Subsection (a) of the International Financial Assistance Act of 1977: ensured assistance through international financial institutions would be limited to countries &quot;other than those whose governments engage in a consistent pattern of gross violations of internationally recognized human rights&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Forsythe&quot; /&gt;
# Section 116 of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961, as amended in 1984: reads in part, &quot;No assistance may be provided under this part to the government of any country which engages in a consistent pattern of gross violations of internationally recognized human rights.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Forsythe&quot; /&gt;
# Section 502B of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961, as amended in 1978: &quot;No security assistance may be provided to any country the government of which engages in a consistent pattern of gross violations of internationally recognized human rights.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Forsythe&quot; /&gt;

[[File:King Salman bin Abdulaziz of Saudi Arabia bids farewell to President Barack Obama at Erga Palace in Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.jpg|thumb|Barack Obama with King [[Salman of Saudi Arabia]], January 2015. According to Amnesty International, &quot;For too long, the USA has shied away from publicly confronting [[Saudi Arabia]] over its human rights record, largely turning a blind eye to a mounting catalogue of abuses.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2014/03/saudi-arabia-president-obama-must-not-shirk-responsibility-tackle-human-rights-during-visit/ Saudi Arabia: President Obama must not shirk responsibility to tackle human rights during visit]&quot;. [[Amnesty International]]. March 28, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
These measures were repeatedly used by Congress, with varying success, to affect U.S. foreign policy towards the inclusion of Human Rights concerns. Specific examples include [[El Salvador]], [[Nicaragua]], [[Guatemala]] and [[South Africa]]. The Executive (from Nixon to Reagan) argued that the [[Cold War]] required placing regional security in favor of U.S. interests over any behavioral concerns of national allies. Congress argued the opposite, in favor of distancing the United States from oppressive regimes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crabb &amp; Holt&quot; /&gt; Nevertheless, according to historian [[Daniel Goldhagen]], during the last two decades of the Cold War, the number of American client states practicing mass murder outnumbered those of the [[Soviet Union]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Daniel Goldhagen]] (2009). ''Worse Than War.'' [[PublicAffairs]]. {{ISBN|1-58648-769-8}} p. 537
* &quot;During the 1970s and 1980s, the number of American client states practicing mass-murderous politics exceeded those of the Soviets.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; [[John Henry Coatsworth]], a historian of Latin America and the provost of Columbia University, suggests the number of repression victims in Latin America alone far surpassed that of the USSR and its East European satellites during the period 1960 to 1990.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Coatsworth|first1=John Henry|author-link=John Henry Coatsworth |chapter= The Cold War in Central America, 1975–1991 | editor1-last=Leffler|editor1-first=Melvyn P.|editor1-link=Melvyn P. Leffler|editor2-last=Westad|editor2-first=Odd Arne|editor2-link=Odd Arne Westad|date=2012 |title=The Cambridge History of the Cold War (Volume 3)|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=xjTVBAAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PT230#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|location= |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|page=230 |isbn=978-1107602311}}&lt;/ref&gt; W. John Green contends that the United States was an &quot;essential enabler&quot; of &quot;Latin America's political murder habit, bringing out and allowing to flourish some of the region's worst tendencies&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;W. John Green (June 1, 2015). ''[http://www.sunypress.edu/p-6060-a-history-of-political-murder-i.aspx A History of Political Murder in Latin America: Killing the Messengers of Change] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160310163927/http://www.sunypress.edu/p-6060-a-history-of-political-murder-i.aspx |date=March 10, 2016 }}.'' [[SUNY Press]]. [https://books.google.com/books?id=NyezCAAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA147#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false p. 147]. {{ISBN|1438456638}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On December 6, 2011, Obama instructed agencies to consider [[LGBT rights by country or territory|LGBT rights]] when issuing financial aid to foreign countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=McVeigh|first=Karen|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/dec/07/gay-rights-us-aid-criteria|title=Gay rights must be criterion for U.S. aid allocations, instructs Obama|newspaper=The Guardian|location=London|date=December 6, 2011|accessdate=January 4, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also criticized Russia's law discriminating against gays,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Adomanis|first=Mark|url=https://www.forbes.com/sites/markadomanis/2013/12/19/barack-obama-is-right-to-promote-gay-rights-in-russia-now-he-should-be-consistent/|title=Barack Obama Is Right To Promote Gay Rights In Russia, Now He Should Be Consistent|newspaper=[[Forbes]]|date=December 19, 2013|accessdate=December 25, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; joining other western leaders in the [[boycott]] of the [[2014 Winter Olympics]] in Russia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Bershidsky|first=Leonid|url=https://www.bloomberg.com/news/2013-12-19/putin-plays-games-to-salvage-olympics.html|title=Putin Plays Games to Salvage Olympics|publisher=Bloomberg.com|date=December 19, 2013|accessdate=December 25, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2014, a Chilean court ruled that the United States played a key role in the murders of [[Charles Horman]] and [[Frank Teruggi]], both American citizens, shortly after the [[1973 Chilean coup d'état]].&lt;ref&gt;Pascale Bonnefoy (30 June 2014). [https://www.nytimes.com/2014/07/01/world/americas/chilean-court-rules-us-had-role-in-murders.html?_r=0 Chilean Court Rules U.S. Had Role in Murders]. ''[[The New York Times]].'' Retrieved 4 July 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

==War on Drugs==
{{Main|War on Drugs}}
United States foreign policy is influenced by the efforts of the U.S. government to control imports of illicit [[illegal drug trade|drugs]], including [[cocaine]], [[heroin]], [[methamphetamine]], and [[Cannabis (drug)|cannabis]]. This is especially true in Latin America, a focus for the U.S. [[War on Drugs]]. Those efforts date back to at least 1880, when the U.S. and China completed an agreement that [[Prohibition (drugs)|prohibited]] the shipment of [[opium]] between the two countries.

Over a century later, the Foreign Relations Authorization Act requires the President to identify the major drug transit or major illicit drug-producing countries. In September 2005,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://georgewbush-whitehouse.archives.gov/news/releases/2005/09/20050915-2.html|title=Memorandum for the Secretary of State|date=15 September 2005|website=Georgewbush-whitehouse.archives.gov|accessdate=18 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; the following countries were identified: [[Bahamas]], [[Bolivia]], [[Brazil]], [[Burma]], [[Colombia]], [[Dominican Republic]], [[Ecuador]], [[Guatemala]], [[Haiti]], India, [[Jamaica]], [[Laos]], Mexico, [[Nigeria]], Pakistan, [[Panama]], [[Paraguay]], [[Peru]] and [[Venezuela]]. Two of these, Burma and Venezuela are countries that the U.S. considers to have failed to adhere to their obligations under international counternarcotics agreements during the previous 12 months. Notably absent from the 2005 list were [[Afghanistan]], the [[People's Republic of China]] and [[Vietnam]]; Canada was also omitted in spite of evidence that criminal groups there are increasingly involved in the production of [[MDMA]] destined for the United States and that large-scale cross-border trafficking of Canadian-grown cannabis continues. The U.S. believes that the Netherlands are successfully countering the production and flow of MDMA to the U.S.

==Criticism==
{{Main|Criticism of American foreign policy}}
[[File:DigiGes PRISM Yes we scan - Demo am Checkpoint Charlie June 2013.jpg|thumb|Demonstration at [[Checkpoint Charlie]] in Berlin against the [[National Security Agency|NSA]] surveillance program [[PRISM (surveillance program)|PRISM]], June 2013]]
Critics from the left cite episodes that undercut leftist governments or showed support for Israel. Others cite human rights abuses and violations of international law. Critics have charged that the [[President of the United States|U.S. presidents]] have used [[democracy]] to justify [[List of United States military history events|military intervention]] abroad.&lt;ref name=&quot;Why&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Meernik 1996 391&quot;/&gt; Critics also point to declassified records which indicate that the CIA under [[Allen Dulles]] and the FBI under [[J. Edgar Hoover]] aggressively recruited more than 1,000 Nazis, including those responsible for war crimes, to use as spies and informants against the [[Soviet Union]] in the Cold War.&lt;ref&gt;Eric Lichtblau (October 26, 2014). [https://www.nytimes.com/2014/10/27/us/in-cold-war-us-spy-agencies-used-1000-nazis.html In Cold War, U.S. Spy Agencies Used 1,000 Nazis]. ''[[The New York Times]].'' Retrieved November 10, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.democracynow.org/2014/10/31/the_nazis_next_door_eric_lichtblau The Nazis Next Door: Eric Lichtblau on How the CIA &amp; FBI Secretly Sheltered Nazi War Criminals]. ''[[Democracy Now!]]'' October 31, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

The U.S. has faced criticism for backing right-wing dictators that systematically violated human rights, such as [[Augusto Pinochet]] of Chile,&lt;ref&gt;[[Peter Kornbluh]] (September 11, 2013). ''[[The Pinochet File: A Declassified Dossier on Atrocity and Accountability]].'' [[The New Press]]. {{ISBN|1595589120}} [https://books.google.com/books?id=WHYRBAAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PR18#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false p. xviii]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Alfredo Stroessner]] of Paraguay,&lt;ref name=&quot;Hixson&quot;&gt;Walter L. Hixson (2009). ''[http://yalepress.yale.edu/book.asp?isbn=9780300119121 The Myth of American Diplomacy: National Identity and U.S. Foreign Policy].'' [[Yale University Press]]. [https://books.google.com/books?id=DNId6HxkzQwC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA223#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false p. 223]. {{ISBN|0300151314}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Efraín Ríos Montt]] of Guatemala,&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/roomfordebate/2013/05/19/what-guilt-does-the-us-bear-in-guatemala What Guilt Does the U.S. Bear in Guatemala?] ''[[The New York Times]],'' May 19, 2013. Retrieved July 1, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jorge Rafael Videla]] of Argentina,&lt;ref&gt;Duncan Campbell (December 5, 2003). [https://www.theguardian.com/world/2003/dec/06/argentina.usa Kissinger approved Argentinian 'dirty war']. ''[[The Guardian]].'' Retrieved August 29, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hissène Habré]] of Chad&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/2016/05/31/world/africa/hissene-habre-leader-chad-war-crimes.html?_r=0 Hissène Habré, Ex-President of Chad, Is Convicted of War Crimes]. ''The New York Times.'' May 30, 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.democracynow.org/2016/5/31/from_us_ally_to_convicted_war From U.S. Ally to Convicted War Criminal: Inside Chad's Hissène Habré's Close Ties to Reagan Admin]. ''[[Democracy Now!]]'' May 31, 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Yahya Khan]] of Pakistan&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newyorker.com/news/news-desk/looking-away-from-genocide Looking Away from Genocide]. ''[[The New Yorker]]''. November 19, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Suharto]] of Indonesia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thaler&quot;&gt;Kai Thaler (December 2, 2015). [https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/monkey-cage/wp/2015/12/02/50-years-ago-today-the-u-s-embassy-endorsed-mass-killings-in-indonesia-heres-what-that-means-for-today/ 50 years ago today, American diplomats endorsed mass killings in Indonesia. Here's what that means for today.] ''[[The Washington Post]].'' Retrieved December 4, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name =&quot;BlumenthalMcCormack&quot;/&gt; Critics have also accused the United States of facilitating and supporting [[United States and state terrorism|state terrorism]] in the [[Global South]] during the Cold War, such as [[Operation Condor]], an international campaign of political assassination and state terror organized by right-wing military dictatorships in the [[Southern Cone]] of South America.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Blakeley|first=Ruth|date=2009 |title=State Terrorism and Neoliberalism: The North in the South|url=http://www.routledge.com/books/details/9780415462402/|location= |publisher=[[Routledge]]|page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=rft8AgAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA22#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 22] &amp; [https://books.google.com/books?id=rft8AgAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA23#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 23]|isbn=978-0415686174}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=McSherry|first1=J. Patrice|author-link1= J. Patrice McSherry|editor1=Esparza, Marcia |editor2=Henry R. Huttenbach|editor3=Daniel Feierstein|title=State Violence and Genocide in Latin America: The Cold War Years (Critical Terrorism Studies)|chapter=Chapter 5: &quot;Industrial repression&quot; and Operation Condor in Latin America |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=acGNAgAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA107#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 107]|publisher=[[Routledge]]|year=2011|isbn=978-0415664578|chapter-url=https://www.routledge.com/State-Violence-and-Genocide-in-Latin-America-The-Cold-War-Years/Esparza-Huttenbach-Feierstein/p/book/9780415496377|quote=Operation Condor also had the covert support of the US government. Washington provided Condor with military intelligence and training, financial assistance, advanced computers, sophisticated tracking technology, and access to the continental telecommunications system housed in the Panama Canal Zone.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hixson&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Greg Grandin]] (2011). ''[http://www.press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/L/bo11643711.html The Last Colonial Massacre: Latin America in the Cold War].'' [[University of Chicago Press]]. [https://books.google.com/books?id=6FivSpNY2fkC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA75#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false p. 75]. {{ISBN|9780226306902}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Journalists and human rights organizations have been critical of US-led airstrikes and [[targeted killings]] by [[Unmanned combat aerial vehicle|drones]] which have in some cases resulted in [[collateral damage]] of civilian populations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/2016/07/19/world/syria-airstrikes-civilian-casualties/ U.S.-led airstrikes in Syria kill civilians, rights groups say]. [[CNN]]. July 20, 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Jeremy Scahill]] and the staff of ''[[The Intercept]]'' (2016).  ''The Assassination Complex: Inside the Government's Secret Drone Warfare Program.'' [[Simon &amp; Schuster]]. {{ISBN|9781501144134}}&lt;/ref&gt; In early 2017, the U.S. faced criticism from some scholars, activists and media outlets for dropping 26,171 bombs on seven different countries throughout 2016: Syria, Iraq, Afghanistan, Libya, Yemen, Somalia and Pakistan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Grandin|first=Greg |date=January 15, 2017 |title= Why Did the US Drop 26,171 Bombs on the World Last Year?|url=https://www.thenation.com/article/why-did-the-us-dropped-26171-bombs-on-the-world-last-year/|work=[[The Nation]] |location=|authorlink=Greg Grandin|access-date= April 14, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Agerholm|first=Harriet |date=January 19, 2017 |title=Map shows where President Barack Obama dropped his 20,000 bombs|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/americas/us-president-barack-obama-bomb-map-drone-wars-strikes-20000-pakistan-middle-east-afghanistan-a7534851.html|work=The Independent |location= |access-date=April 14, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last= Benjamin|first=Medea|date= January 9, 2017|title=America dropped 26,171 bombs in 2016. What a bloody end to Obama's reign|url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2017/jan/09/america-dropped-26171-bombs-2016-obama-legacy|work=[[The Guardian]] |location= |authorlink=Medea Benjamin|access-date= April 14, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. has been accused of complicity in war crimes for backing the [[Saudi Arabian-led intervention in Yemen|Saudi Arabian-led intervention]] into the [[Yemeni Civil War (2015–present)]], which has triggered a humanitarian catastrophe, including a [[2016–18 Yemen cholera outbreak|cholera outbreak]] and [[Famine in Yemen (2016–present)|millions facing starvation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-saudi-yemen-idUSKCN12A0BQ |title=Exclusive: As Saudis bombed Yemen, U.S. worried about legal blowback |author=Warren Strobel, Jonathan Landay |agency=[[Reuters]] |date=5 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Emmons|first=Alex|date=November 14, 2017|title=Chris Murphy Accuses the U.S. of Complicity in War Crimes from the Floor of the Senate|url=https://theintercept.com/2017/11/14/chris-murphy-accuses-u-s-of-complicity-in-war-crimes-from-the-floor-of-the-senate/|work=[[The Intercept]]|access-date=November 16, 2017|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20171115110927/https://theintercept.com/2017/11/14/chris-murphy-accuses-u-s-of-complicity-in-war-crimes-from-the-floor-of-the-senate/|archivedate=15 November 2017|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last= |first= |date=July 19, 2018 |title=PBS Report from Yemen: As Millions Face Starvation, American-Made Bombs Are Killing Civilians|url=https://www.democracynow.org/2018/7/19/pbs_report_from_yemen_as_millions|work=[[Democracy Now!]]|location= |access-date=August 5, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Studies have been devoted to the historical success rate of the U.S. in exporting democracy abroad. Some studies of American intervention have been pessimistic about the overall effectiveness of U.S. efforts to encourage democracy in foreign nations.&lt;ref name=&quot;operation&quot;/&gt; Some scholars have generally agreed with international relations professor Abraham Lowenthal that U.S. attempts to export democracy have been &quot;negligible, often counterproductive, and only occasionally positive&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Abraham&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;mark7&quot;/&gt; Other studies find [[List of United States military history events|U.S. intervention]] has had mixed results,&lt;ref name=&quot;operation&quot; /&gt; and another by Hermann and Kegley has found that military interventions have improved democracy in other countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;promote&quot;/&gt; A 2013 global poll in 68 countries with 66,000 respondents by Win/Gallup found that the U.S. is perceived as the biggest threat to world peace.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Goodenough |first=Patrick |url=http://cnsnews.com/news/article/patrick-goodenough/and-country-posing-greatest-threat-peace-2013-ends |title=And The Country Posing The Greatest Threat to Peace as 2013 Ends is … |work=CNS News |accessdate=2014-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rt.com/news/us-biggest-threat-peace-079/ |title=US the biggest threat to world peace in 2013 – poll |publisher=Rt.com |date= |accessdate=2014-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Editorial |first=Post |url=https://nypost.com/2014/01/05/us-is-the-greatest-threat-to-world-peace-poll/ |title=US is the greatest threat to world peace: poll &amp;#124; New York Post |publisher=Nypost.com |date=2014-01-05 |accessdate=2014-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Support==
[[File:Bratislava's Hviezdoslavovo Square 2005-02-24.jpg|thumb|250px|right|President [[George W. Bush]] and Slovakia's Prime Minister [[Mikulas Dzurinda]] are greeted by a crowd of thousands gathered in [[Bratislava]]'s [[Hviezdoslavovo námestie (Bratislava)|Hviezdoslavovo Square]] (February 2005).]]
Regarding support for certain anti-Communist dictatorships during the [[Cold War]], a response is that they were seen as a necessary evil, with the alternatives even worse Communist or fundamentalist dictatorships. David Schmitz says this policy did not serve U.S. interests. Friendly tyrants resisted necessary reforms and destroyed the political center (though not in South Korea), while the '[[Political realism|realist]]' policy of coddling dictators brought a backlash among foreign populations with long memories.&lt;ref&gt;The United States and Right-Wing Dictatorships, 1965–1989. David F. Schmitz. 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;[https://www.telegraph.co.uk/opinion/main.jhtml?xml=/opinion/2005/12/11/do1102.xml&amp;sSheet=/opinion/2005/12/11/ixopinion.html Do the sums, then compare U.S. and Communist crimes from the Cold War] Telegraph, 11 December 2005, Niall Ferguson&lt;/ref&gt;

Many democracies have voluntary military ties with United States. See [[NATO]], [[ANZUS]], [[Treaty of Mutual Cooperation and Security between the United States and Japan]], [[Mutual Defense Treaty]] with [[South Korea]], and [[Major non-NATO ally]]. Those nations with military alliances with the U.S. can spend less on the military since they can count on U.S. protection. This may give a false impression that the U.S. is less peaceful than those nations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.economist.com/world/international/displaystory.cfm?story_id=9266967 Give peace a rating] May 31, 2007, from ''The Economist'' print edition&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20070626090409/http://www.japantoday.com/jp/news/407850/all Japan ranked as world's 5th most peaceful nation: report] Japan Today, May 31, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

Research on the [[democratic peace theory]] has generally found that democracies, including the United States, have not made war on one another. There have been U.S. support for coups against some democracies, but for example [[Spencer R. Weart]] argues that part of the explanation was the perception, correct or not, that these states were turning into Communist dictatorships. Also important was the role of rarely transparent United States government agencies, who sometimes mislead or did not fully implement the decisions of elected civilian leaders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Weart|first=Spencer R.|authorlink=Spencer R. Weart|title=Never at War|publisher=Yale University Press|year=1998|isbn=0-300-07017-9|title-link=Never at War}} pp. 221–24, 314.&lt;/ref&gt;

Empirical studies (see [[democide]]) have found that democracies, including the United States, have killed much fewer civilians than dictatorships.&lt;ref&gt;Death By Government By R.J. Rummel New Brunswick, N.J.: Transaction Publishers, 1994. Online links: [http://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills/NOTE1.HTM] [http://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills/SOD.FIG23.4.GIF] [http://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills/POWER.FIG2.GIF]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.cidcm.umd.edu/inscr/genocide/ No Lessons Learned from the Holocaust?] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071030201259/http://www.cidcm.umd.edu/inscr/genocide/ |date=October 30, 2007 }}'', Barbara Harff, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; Media may be biased against the U.S. regarding reporting human rights violations. Studies have found that ''The New York Times'' coverage of worldwide human rights violations predominantly focuses on the human rights violations in nations where there is clear U.S. involvement, while having relatively little coverage of the human rights violations in other nations.&lt;ref name=Caliendo1999&gt;{{cite journal|author=Caliendo, S.M.|year=1999|title=All the News That's Fit to Print? New York Times Coverage of Human-Rights Violations|journal=The Harvard International Journal of Press/Politics|volume=4|pages=48–69|url=http://muse.jhu.edu/login?uri=/journals/harvard_international_journal_of_press_politics/v004/4.4caliendo.html|accessdate=2008-04-02|doi=10.1177/1081180x9900400404}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Caliendo, Stephen.  |author2=Gibney, Mark.|year=2006|title=American Print Media Coverage of Human Rights Violations|url=http://www.allacademic.com/meta/p152798_index.html?type=info|accessdate=2008-04-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, the bloodiest war in recent time, involving eight nations and killing millions of civilians, was the [[Second Congo War]], which was almost completely ignored by the media.

[[Niall Ferguson]] argues that the U.S. is incorrectly blamed for all the human rights violations in nations they have supported. He writes that it is generally agreed that Guatemala was the worst of the US-backed regimes during the Cold War. However, the U.S. cannot credibly be blamed for all the 200,000 deaths during the long [[Guatemalan Civil War]].&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot; /&gt; The U.S. Intelligence Oversight Board writes that military aid was cut for long periods because of such violations, that the U.S. helped stop a coup in 1993, and that efforts were made to improve the conduct of the security services.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ciponline.org/iob.htm Report on the Guatemala Review] Intelligence Oversight Board. June 28, 1996.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Abdulredha Buhmaid on floor.jpeg|thumb|[[Bahrain]]i pro-democracy protesters killed by the U.S.-allied regime, February 2011]]
Today the U.S. states that democratic nations best support U.S. national interests. According to the U.S. State Department, &quot;Democracy is the one national interest that helps to secure all the others. Democratically governed nations are more likely to secure the peace, deter aggression, expand open markets, promote economic development, protect American citizens, combat international terrorism and crime, uphold human and worker rights, avoid humanitarian crises and refugee flows, improve the global environment, and protect human health.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://2001-2009.state.gov/g/drl/democ|title=Democracy|website=State.gov|accessdate=18 February 2015|date=May 10, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to former U.S. President [[Bill Clinton]], &quot;Ultimately, the best strategy to ensure our security and to build a durable peace is to support the advance of democracy elsewhere. Democracies don't attack each other.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Clinton, Bill|title=1994 State Of The Union Address|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/politics/special/states/docs/sou94.htm|accessdate=2006-01-22|work=The Washington Post|date=January 28, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; In one view mentioned by the U.S. State Department, democracy is also good for business. Countries that embrace political reforms are also more likely to pursue economic reforms that improve the productivity of businesses. Accordingly, since the mid-1980s, under President [[Ronald Reagan]], there has been an increase in levels of foreign direct investment going to emerging market democracies relative to countries that have not undertaken political reforms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://usinfo.state.gov/usinfo/USINFO/Products/Webchats/bohn_27_mar_2007.html |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2016-02-05 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081114105330/http://usinfo.state.gov/usinfo/USINFO/Products/Webchats/bohn_27_mar_2007.html |archivedate=November 14, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Leaked cables in 2010 suggested that the &quot;dark shadow of terrorism still dominates the United States' relations with the world&quot;.&lt;ref name=twsDecZ16af&gt;{{cite news|first1=Scott|last1=Shane|first2=Andrew W.|last2=Lehren|title=Leaked Cables Offer Raw Look at U.S. Diplomacy|work=The New York Times|quote=The cables show that nearly a decade after the attacks of Sept. 11, 2001, the dark shadow of terrorism still dominates the United States' relations with the world.&amp;nbsp;... |date=2010-11-28|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/29/world/29cables.html?_r=2&amp;pagewanted=2|accessdate=2010-12-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The United States officially maintains that it supports democracy and human rights through several tools &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://2001-2009.state.gov/g/drl|title=Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor|website=State.gov|accessdate=18 February 2015|date=January 5, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Examples of these tools are as follows:
* A published yearly report by the State Department entitled &quot;Advancing Freedom and Democracy&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://2009-2017.state.gov/j/drl/rls/afdr/index.htm|title=Advancing Freedom and Democracy|website=State.gov|accessdate=April 20, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; issued in compliance with ADVANCE Democracy Act of 2007 (earlier the report was known as &quot;Supporting Human Rights and Democracy: The U.S. Record&quot; and was issued in compliance with a 2002 law).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://2001-2009.state.gov/g/drl/rls/shrd|title=Supporting Human Rights and Democracy: The U.S. Record|website=State.gov|accessdate=18 February 2015|date=April 20, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* A yearly published &quot;[[Country Reports on Human Rights Practices]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://2001-2009.state.gov/g/drl/rls/hrrpt|title=Human Rights Reports|website=State.gov|accessdate=18 February 2015|date=March 6, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 2006 (under President [[George W. Bush]]), the United States created a &quot;Human Rights Defenders Fund&quot; and &quot;Freedom Awards&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://2001-2009.state.gov/g/drl/hr/c20063.htm|title=International Human Rights Week|date=December 15, 2006|accessdate=October 14, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The &quot;Human Rights and Democracy Achievement Award&quot; recognizes the exceptional achievement of officers of foreign affairs agencies posted abroad.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://2001-2009.state.gov/g/drl/rls/77769.htm|title=2006 Human Rights and Democracy Achievement Award|first=Bureau of Public Affairs|last=Department Of State. The Office of Electronic Information|date=December 14, 2006|website=2001-2009.state.gov}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The &quot;Ambassadorial Roundtable Series&quot;, created in 2006, are informal discussions between newly confirmed U.S. [[Ambassador]]s and human rights and democracy non-governmental organizations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://2001-2009.state.gov/g/drl/hr/c18970.htm|title=Ambassadorial Roundtable Series|date=March 14, 2007|accessdate=October 14, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[National Endowment for Democracy]], a private non-profit created by Congress in 1983 (and signed into law by President [[Ronald Reagan]]), which is mostly funded by the U.S. Government and gives cash grants to strengthen democratic institutions around the world.

==See also==
{{American Empire}}
* [[International relations, 1648–1814]]
* [[International relations of the Great Powers (1814–1919)]]
* [[International relations (1919–1939)]]
* [[American entry into World War I]]
* [[Diplomatic history of World War I]]
* [[Diplomatic history of World War II]]
* [[Cold War]]
* [[United States foreign policy in the Middle East]]
* [[United States and state terrorism]] 
* [[United States and state-sponsored terrorism]]
{{col-begin}}

===Constitutional and international law===
* [[Advice and consent]]
* [[List of United States treaties]]
* ''[[Missouri v. Holland]]''
* [[Treaty Clause]]
{{col-break}}

===Diplomacy===
* [[Council on Foreign Relations]]
* [[Cowboy diplomacy]]
* [[George Washington's Farewell Address]]
* [[List of diplomatic missions of the United States]]
* [[List of diplomatic missions in the United States]]
* [[United States and the United Nations]]
* [[United States Agency for International Development]]
* [[United States foreign aid]]

===Intelligence===
* [[Extraordinary rendition]]
* [[Special Activities Division]]
* [[Torture and the United States]]

===Military===
* [[NATO]]
* [[United States Foreign Military Financing]]
* [[United States involvement in regime change]]
* [[United States military aid]]
{{col-break}}

===Policy and doctrine===
* [[Anti-Americanism]]
* [[American imperialism]]
* [[American exceptionalism]]
* [[Bush Doctrine]]
* [[Carter Doctrine]]
* [[China containment policy]]
* [[Containment]]
* ''[[Détente]]''
* [[Foreign policy of the Bill Clinton administration]]
* [[Foreign policy of the George W. Bush administration]]
* [[Foreign policy of the Barack Obama administration]]
* [[Foreign policy of the Donald Trump administration]]
* [[Human rights in the United States]]
* [[Kirkpatrick Doctrine]]
* ''[[Human Rights Record of the United States]]'' ([[People's Republic of China|Chinese]] [[State Council Information Office|publication]])
* [[Monroe Doctrine]]
* [[Nixon Doctrine]]
* [[Powell Doctrine]]
* [[Reagan Doctrine]]
* [[Roosevelt Corollary]]
* [[Special Relationship]]
* [[Truman Doctrine]]
{{col-end}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin|30em}}
* Bailey, Thomas. ''A Diplomatic History of the American People'' (10th ed. Prentice Hall, 1980)
* [[William Blum|Blum, William]]. ''[[Killing Hope|Killing Hope: U.S. Military and C.I.A. Interventions since World War II]]'' (Common Courage Press, 2003) 
* Borgwardt, Elizabeth. &quot;[https://books.google.com/books?id=3GGmssOod2YC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false A New Deal for the World]&quot; (Harvard UP, 2005)
* [[Noam Chomsky|Chomsky, Noam]]. ''[[Hegemony or Survival|Hegemony or Survival: America's Quest for Global Dominance]]'' (Metropolitan Books, 2003)
* Cohen, Warren I. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=WS6nU7EUHE0C&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false The Cambridge History of American Foreign Relations: Volume 4, America in the Age of Soviet Power, 1945–1991]'' (Cambridge UP, 1995)
* Dueck, Colin. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=LKhB2ENzgvAC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Hard Line: The Republican Party and U.S. Foreign Policy since World War II]'' (2010).
* Fawcett, Louise, ed. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=nNUiHaUzzNgC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false International Relations of the Middle East]'' (3rd ed. Oxford U.P. 2013)
* Freedman, Lawrence. ''A Choice of Enemies: America Confronts the Middle East'' (PublicAffairs, 2009)
* Gries, Peter Hays. ''The Politics of American Foreign Policy: How Ideology Divides Liberals and Conservatives over Foreign Affairs'' (Stanford University Press, 2014)
* Hastedt, Glenn P. ''Encyclopedia of American Foreign Policy'' (2004) [https://archive.org/details/encyclopediaofam0000hast online free to borrow]
* Hastedt, Glenn P. ''American foreign policy'' (4th ed. 2000)  [https://openlibrary.org/books/OL36108M/American_foreign_policy online free to borrow]
* {{Cite journal
|first=Margaret G.
|last=Hermann
|authorlink=
|year=1998
|title=The U.S. Use of Military Intervention to Promote Democracy: Evaluating the Record
|journal=International Interactions
|volume=24
|issue=2
|pages=91–114
|id=
|url=
|doi=10.1080/03050629808434922
|last2=Kegley
|first2=Charles
}}
* Herring, George C. ''[https://archive.org/details/fromcolonytosupe00herr From Colony to Superpower: U.S. Foreign Relations Since 1776]'' (Oxford History of the United States) (2008)
* Hixson, Walter L.  ''The Myth of American Diplomacy: National Identity and U.S. Foreign Policy.'' [[Yale University Press]], 2009.  {{ISBN|0300151314}}
* Hook, Steven W. and John Spanier. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=I-y3hBzjRTQC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false American Foreign Policy Since WWII]'' (19th ed. 2012)
* Ikenberry, G. John, ed. ''American Foreign Policy: Theoretical Essays'' (6th ed. Wadsworth, 2010), 640pp; essays by scholars
* Iriye, Akira. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=3moWFmpaRvQC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false The Cambridge History of American Foreign Relations: Volume 3, The Globalizing of America, 1913–1945]'' (Cambridge UP, 1995)
* Jentleson, Bruce W. ''American Foreign Policy: The Dynamics of Choice in the 21st Century'' (4th ed. W. W. Norton, 2010)
* Jentleson, Bruce W. and Thomas G. Paterson, eds. ''Encyclopedia of U.S. Foreign Relations'' (4 vol 1997), long historical articles by scholars
* LaFeber, Walter. ''The Cambridge History of American Foreign Relations: The American Search for Opportunity, 1865–1913, vol. 2'' (Cambridge UP, 1995)
* {{Cite book
|last=Lowenthal
|first=Abraham F.
|date=March 1, 1991
|title=Exporting Democracy : The United States and Latin America
|publisher=The Johns Hopkins University Press
|location=
|isbn=0-8018-4132-1
|url=https://archive.org/details/exportingdemocra00lowe_1
}}
* McCormick, James M. et al. '' [https://books.google.com/books?id=r6MzZF7EZtIC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false The Domestic Sources of American Foreign Policy: Insights and Evidence]'' (2012)
* McDougall, Walter. &quot;Promised Land, Crusader State&quot; (2004)
* Mead, Walter Russell, and Richard C. Leone. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=TmlDcE0BBrsC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Special Providence: American Foreign Policy and How It Changed the World]'' (2002)
* {{Cite journal
|first=James
|last=Meernik
|year=1996
|title=United States Military Intervention and the Promotion of Democracy
|journal=Journal of Peace Research
|volume=33
|issue=4
|pages=391–402
|id=
|doi=10.1177/0022343396033004002
|jstor=424565
}}
* Nichols, Christopher McKnight. &quot;[https://books.google.com/books?id=uXDSQwdP3dgC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Promise and Peril: America at the Dawn of a Global Age]&quot; (2011)
* Paterson, Thomas G. and others. ''American Foreign Relations'' (6th ed. 2 vol, Wadsworth, 2004), a detailed history
* Perkins, Bradford. ''The Cambridge History of American Foreign Relations: Volume 1, The Creation of a Republican Empire, 1776–1865'' (Cambridge UP, 1995)
* [[Samantha Power|Power, Samantha.]] ''[[A Problem from Hell|&quot;A Problem from Hell&quot;: America and the Age of Genocide]]'' (2002) covers Bosnia, Kosovo, Srebenica, and Rwanda; Pulitzer Prize.[https://openlibrary.org/works/OL264876W/A_Problem_from_Hell online free to borrow] 
* Sergent, Daniel J. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=SYYbBQAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false A Superpower Transformed: The Remaking of American Foreign Relations in the 1970s]'' (2015)
*  Schulzinger, Robert. ''U.S. Diplomacy Since 1900'' (6th ed. 2008)
*  Schulzinger, Robert. ''A Companion to American Foreign Relations'' (Wiley Blackwell Companions to American History) (2006). 26 essays by scholars; emphasis on historiography
* {{Cite book
|last=Smith
|first=Tony
|authorlink=
|author2=Richard C. Leone
|year=1995
|title=America's Mission: The United States and the Worldwide Struggle for Democracy in the Twentieth Century
|publisher=Princeton University Press
|isbn=0-691-04466-X
}}
* Watry, David M. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=OnqOAwAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Diplomacy at the Brink: Eisenhower, Churchill, and Eden in the Cold War].'' Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 2014.
* Wittkopf, Eugene R. et al. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=jO4Kowz4KKcC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false American Foreign Policy: Pattern and Process]'' (2007)
{{refend}}

==Primary sources==
* Engel, Jeffrey A. et al. eds. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=FLvzAgAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false America in the World: A History in Documents from the War with Spain to the War on Terror]'' (2014)

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}{{Library resources box}}

* [https://history.state.gov/countries/ History of the United States' relations with the countries of the world]
* [https://history.state.gov/milestones/ Milestones of U.S. diplomatic history]
* [https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/ Foreign Relations of the United States (FRUS): Official Documentary History of U.S. Foreign Relations]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20160303235133/http://ucblibraries.colorado.edu/govpubs/us/foraffrs.htm Foreign Relations and International Aid] from ''UCB Libraries G
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20081220124800/http://www.cfr.org/publication/9488/ U.S. Political Parties and Foreign Policy], a background Q&amp;A by [[Council on Foreign Relations]]
* [https://fas.org/sgp/crs/row/R44891.pdf U.S. Role in the World: Background and Issues for Congress] [[Congressional Research Service]]
* [http://digital.library.wisc.edu/1711.dl/FRUS Foreign Relations of the United States] 1861–1960 (full text from the University of Wisconsin-Madison Libraries)
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20170623070615/https://www.publicagenda.org/citizen/researchstudies/foreign-policy Confidence in U.S. Foreign Policy Index] Tracking survey of American public attitudes on foreign policy, conducted by Public Agenda with [[Foreign Affairs]] magazine.
* [http://www.historyisaweapon.com/defcon2/world.html An interactive map of some examples of a sampling of U.S. Foreign Policy]
* [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=708243 Analysis of Congressional-Executive Agreements (Article by Steve Charnovitz from the American Journal of International Law)]
* [http://purl.access.gpo.gov/GPO/LPS11657 ''Treaties and Other International Agreements: The Role of the United States Senate: A Study Prepared for the Committee on Foreign Relations, United States Senate, by the Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress'']
* [http://hdl.handle.net/10822/552551 Rethinking U.S. Aid] from the [https://repository.library.georgetown.edu/handle/10822/552494 Dean Peter Krogh Foreign Affairs Digital Archives]
* [https://archive.org/details/PeterGowanInterview2009 Peter Gowan interview on U.S. foreign policy since 1945]
* [https://www.commentarymagazine.com/articles/the-good-country/ The Good Country] from ''[[Commentary (magazine)|Commentary]]''
* [https://www.truthdig.com/videos/the-american-empire-murder-inc/ The American Empire: Murder Inc.] [[Chris Hedges]] interviews  American investigative journalist [[Allan Nairn]]

{{United States policy}}
{{Foreign relations of the United States |expanded=DPC}}
{{United States topics}}

[[Category:United States law]]
[[Category:Foreign policy|United States]]
[[Category:United States foreign policy| ]]
[[Category:United States diplomacy]]</text>
      <sha1>ghu6gebpxj1f754s1nzhram4aock59k</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
