  <page>
    <title>Carinatae</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7598</id>
    <revision>
      <id>920852169</id>
      <parentid>871891714</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-10-12T09:08:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rjwilmsi</username>
        <id>203434</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Definition */Added 1 doi to a journal cite</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about|bird taxonomy|the pottery shape|Carinate}}

'''Carinatae''' is the group of all [[bird]]s and their extinct relatives to possess a [[Keel (bird anatomy)|keel]], or &quot;carina&quot;, on the underside of the [[breastbone]] used to anchor large flight muscles.

==Classification==
===Definition===
Traditionally, Carinatae were defined as all birds whose [[sternum]] (breast bone) has a [[keel (bird)|keel]] (''carina''). The keel is a strong median ridge running down the length of the sternum. This is an important area for the attachment of flight muscles. Thus, all flying birds have a pronounced keel. [[Ratite]]s, all of which are flightless, lack a strong keel. Thus, living birds were divided into carinatae (keeled) and ratites (from ''ratis'', &quot;raft&quot;, referring to the flatness of the sternum). The difficulty with this scheme [[phylogenetics|phylogenetically]] was that some flightless birds, without strong keels, are descended directly from ordinary flying birds possessing one. Examples include the [[kakapo]], a flightless [[parrot]], and the [[dodo]], a columbiform (the [[pigeon]] family). None of these birds is a ratite. Thus, this supposedly distinctive feature was easy to use, but had nothing to do with actual phylogenetic relationship.

Beginning in the 1980s, Carinatae was given several [[phylogenetic]] definitions. The first was as a node-based [[clade]] uniting ''[[Ichthyornis]]'' with modern birds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Cracraft |first=Joel |authorlink= |year=1986 |month= |title=The origin and early diversification of birds |journal=[[Paleobiology (journal)|Paleobiology]] |volume=12 |issue=4 |pages=383–399 |id= |url= |accessdate= |quote= |doi=10.1017/s0094837300003122}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in many analyses, this definition would be synonymous with the more widely used name [[Ornithurae]]. An alternate definition was provided in 2001, naming Carinatae an [[apomorphy]]-based clade defined by the presence of a keeled sternum.&lt;ref name=gauhthier2001&gt;Gauthier, J., &amp; De Queiroz, K. (2001). Feathered dinosaurs, flying dinosaurs, crown dinosaurs, and the name “Aves”. New Perspectives on the Origin and Early Evolution of Birds, 7-41.&lt;/ref&gt;

The most primitive known bird relative with a keeled breastbone is ''[[Confuciusornis]]''. While some specimens of this stem-bird have flat breastbones, some show a small ridge that could have supported a cartilaginous keel.&lt;ref&gt;Chiappe, L. M., Ji, S. A., Ji, Q., &amp; Norell, M. A. (1999). Anatomy and systematics of the Confuciusornithidae (Theropoda, Aves) from the late Mesozoic of northeastern China. Bulletin of the AMNH; no. 242.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Carinatae]]


{{bird-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>3w65nczokw3pgm6wsa9h0m2a6uuy34z</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
