  <page>
    <title>Bombay Sapphire</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4832</id>
    <revision>
      <id>931780626</id>
      <parentid>931780155</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-21T04:42:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Blairall</username>
        <id>20266143</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>External links</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox drink
| name         = Bombay Sapphire
| image        = Bombay Sapphire - bouteilles.JPG
| type         = [[Gin]]
| abv          = 40% (UK, The Nordics, Cont. Europe, Canada, Australia)&lt;br /&gt;47% (US and export/duty-free)
| proof        = 80 (UK, The Nordics, Cont. Europe Canada, Australia)&lt;br /&gt;94 (US and export/duty-free)
| manufacturer = Bombay Spirits Co., Ltd.
| distributor  = [[Bacardi]]
| origin       = [[England]]
| introduced   = 1986
| discontinued =
| colour       = Clear
| flavour      =
| variants     =
| related      = Bombay Original Dry
| website      = [https://www.bombaysapphire.com/ bombaysapphire.com]
}}

'''Bombay Sapphire''' is a brand of [[gin]] that was first launched in 1986 by English [[Vintner|wine-merchant]] [[International Distillers &amp; Vintners|IDV]]. In 1997 [[Diageo]] sold the brand to [[Bacardi]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.grovesandwhitnall.co.uk/gj-distillers-warrington/ |title=Archived copy |access-date=2013-11-05 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151208041747/http://www.grovesandwhitnall.co.uk/gj-distillers-warrington/ |archive-date=2015-12-08 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; Its name originates from the popularity of gin in [[Indian subcontinent|India]] during the [[British Raj]] and &quot;Sapphire&quot; refers to the violet-blue [[Star of Bombay]] which was mined from [[Sri Lanka]] and is now on display at the [[Smithsonian Institution]].&lt;ref name=&quot;bacardilimited1&quot;&gt;[http://www.bacardilimited.com/our-brands/bombay-sapphire-gin Bombay Sapphire]&lt;/ref&gt; Bombay Sapphire is marketed in a flat-sided, sapphire-coloured bottle that bears a picture of [[Queen Victoria]] on the label.&lt;ref name=&quot;bacardilimited1&quot;/&gt;

The flavouring of the drink comes from a recipe of ten ingredients: [[almond]], [[lemon]] peel, [[liquorice]], [[juniper berries]], [[orris root]], [[angelica]], [[coriander]], [[Cinnamomum aromaticum|cassia]], [[cubeb]], and [[Aframomum melegueta|grains of paradise]]. Alcohol brought in from another supplier is evaporated three times using a carterhead still, and the alcohol vapours are passed through a mesh/basket containing the ten botanicals, in order to gain flavour and aroma. This is felt to give the gin a lighter, more floral taste compared to those gins that are created using a copper [[pot still]]. Water from [[Lake Vyrnwy]] is added to bring the strength of Bombay Sapphire down to 40.0% (UK, the Nordics, several continental European markets, Canada and Australia).

The 47.0% version is the standard for sale at duty-free stores in all markets.

==Production==
In 2011, plans were announced to move the manufacturing process to a new facility at [[Laverstoke Mill]] in [[Whitchurch, Hampshire]], including the restoration of the former [[De La Rue|Portal]]'s paper mill at the proposed site, and the construction of a visitor centre.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.andoveradvertiser.co.uk/news/9025413.Gin_firm___s_tonic_for_historic_mill/ |title=Gin firm’s tonic for historic mill (From Andover Advertiser) |publisher=Andoveradvertiser.co.uk |date=2011-05-13 |accessdate=2012-10-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Planning permission was granted in February 2012, and the centre opened to the public in the autumn of  2014.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gintime.com/news/gintime-lowdown-with-will-brix/|title=Gintime Lowdown with Will Brix|date=23 October 2013|work=gintime.com|accessdate=15 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gintime.com/news/a-first-glimpse-of-the-bombay-sapphire-distillery/ A first glimpse of the Bombay Sapphire distillery] ''Gintime'' 19 September 2014,&lt;/ref&gt; The visitor centre included a new construction by [[Thomas Heatherwick]] of two glasshouses for plants used as botanicals in the production of Bombay Sapphire gin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.heatherwick.com/distillery/ |title=Bombay Sapphire Distillery, Laverstoke, UK |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |date= |website=Heatherwick Studio |publisher=Heatherwick Studio |access-date=5 November 2016 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Production and bottling of the drink is contracted out by Bacardi to G&amp;J Greenall.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Richard Haffner |url=http://www.just-drinks.com/news/new-gj-greenall-owners-plot-marketing-drive-eye-acquisitions_id104668.aspx?lk=dm |title=G&amp;J Greenall eyes acquisitions, plots ad spend |publisher=Just-drinks.com |date= |accessdate=2012-10-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Bombay Sapphire distillery, Laverstoke 01.jpg|[[Laverstoke Mill]]
File:Thomas Heatherwick glasshouses for the Bombay Sapphire distillery 01.jpg|Glasshouses by [[Thomas Heatherwick]] for growing the botanicals
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Varieties==
[[File:Bombay Sapphire different bottles.jpg|thumb|Three of the Bombay varieties]]
Bacardi also markets '''Bombay Original London Dry Gin''' (or '''Bombay Original Dry'''). Eight botanical ingredients are used in the production of the Original Dry variety, as opposed to the ten in Bombay Sapphire. ''[[Wine Enthusiast Magazine|Wine Enthusiast]]'' preferred Bombay Sapphire.&lt;ref&gt;Bombay Original London Dry Gin listing on Proof66: http://www.proof66.com/gin/bombay-original-gin.html&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2011, '''Bombay Sapphire East''' was launched in test markets in [[New York City|New York]] and [[Las Vegas Valley|Las Vegas]]. This variety has another two botanicals, lemongrass and black peppercorns, in addition to the original ten. It is bottled at 42% and was designed to counteract the sweetness of American [[tonic water]].

A special edition of Bombay gin called '''Star of Bombay''' was produced in 2015 for the UK market. It is bottled at 47.5% and is distilled from grain. It features bergamot and ambrette seeds in harmony with Bombay's signature botanicals. This version has later been extended to several other markets.

In summer 2019, Bacardi launched a limited edition gin called '''Bombay Sapphire English Estate''', which features three additional English sourced botanicals: Pennyroyal Mint, rosehip and hazelnut. It is bottled at 41%.

==Design connection==
{{unreferenced|section|date=July 2018}}
The brand started a series of [[design]] collaborations. Their first step into the design world was a series of advertisements featuring work from currently popular designers. Their works, varying from [[Martini (cocktail)|martini]] glasses to tiles and cloth patterns, are labelled as “Inspired by Bombay Sapphire”. The campaign featured designers such as [[Marcel Wanders]], [[Yves Behar]], [[Karim Rashid]], [[Ulla Darni]], and [[Dror Benshetrit]] and performance artist Jurgen Hahn.

From the success of this campaign, the company began a series of events and sponsored locations. The best known is the Bombay Sapphire Designer Glass Competition, held each year, where design students from all over the world can participate by designing their own “inspired” martini cocktail glass. The finalists (one from each participating country) are then invited to the yearly Salone del Mobile, an international design fair in Milano, where the winner is chosen.

Bombay Sapphire also endorses glass artists and designers with the Bombay Sapphire Prize, which is awarded every year to an outstanding design which features glass. Bombay Sapphire also showcases the designers' work in the Bombay Sapphire endorsed blue room, which is a design exhibition touring the world each year.

From 2008 the Bombay Sapphire Designer Glass Competition final will be held at 100% Design in London, UK and the Bombay Sapphire Prize will take place in Milan at the Salone Del Mobile.

==Evaluation==
Bombay Sapphire has been reviewed by several outside [[spirit ratings]] organizations to mixed success.  Recently, it was awarded a score of 92 (on a 100-point scale) from the [[Beverage Testing Institute]].  Ratings aggregator Proof66.com categorizes the Sapphire as a Tier 2 spirit, indicating highly favourable &quot;expert&quot; reviews.&lt;ref&gt;Bombay Sapphire listing on Proof66: http://www.proof66.com/gin/bombay-sapphire.html {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121004072918/http://www.proof66.com/gin/bombay-sapphire.html# |date=2012-10-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cultural references==
{{Unreferenced|section|date=May 2019}}
* Bombay Sapphire was used in the video work ''Victoria Day (Bombay Sapphire)'', 2002 by contemporary artists [[Marina Roy]] and Abbas Akhavan.
* Long time sports radio personality [[Jim Rome]] is known for his love of Bombay Sapphire Gin, which he often refers to as &quot;the Magic Blue&quot;.
* American hip-hop artist [[Wiz Khalifa]] and his &quot;Taylor Gang&quot; are also known  for their love of Bombay Sapphire dry gin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mlynar2016&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last1=Mlynar |first1=Phillip |title=A Hip-Hop Head's Guide to Drinking |url=https://firstwefeast.com/drink/2016/07/hip-hop-drink-guide/ |accessdate=27 August 2019 |work=First We Feast |date=2 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Former [[Las Vegas, Nevada]] mayor Oscar Goodman is known for his love of Bombay Sapphire Gin, and he has served as a spokesman for the brand.
* American musician Robert Earl Keen references &quot;a quart of Bombay gin&quot; in the song &quot;The Road Goes on Forever&quot;.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Commonscat|Bombay Sapphire}}
*{{official|https://www.bombaysapphire.com/}}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20110708083617/http://www.boozebasher.com/2007-07-04/gin/review-bombay-sapphire-gin/ BoozeBasher review of Bombay Sapphire]
*[http://www.designerglasscompetition.com/ Bombay Sapphire Designer Glass Competition]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20160303205635/http://www.bombaysapphireprize.com/ Bombay Sapphire Prize]
*[http://www.dfnionline.com/article/Bombay-Sapphire-sparkles-in-latest-collaboration-1856077.html Bombay Sapphire sparkles in latest collaboration]

[[Category:Gins]]
[[Category:Bacardi]]
[[Category:Products introduced in 1986]]
[[Category:English distilled drinks]]</text>
      <sha1>jqjdmmeh13wfyd0h6owaucwujsrak2c</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
