  <page>
    <title>Balance of trade</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4810</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941108912</id>
      <parentid>936229541</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-16T17:20:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BD2412</username>
        <id>196446</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Fixing [[Wikipedia:Disambiguation pages with links|links to disambiguation pages]], improving links, other minor cleanup tasks</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Difference between the monetary value of exports and imports}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2013}}
[[File:Cumulative Current Account Balance.png|thumb|upright=1.8|[[Cumulativity|Cumulative]] [[Current account (balance of payments)|current account]] balance 1980–2008 based on [[International Monetary Fund]] data.]]
[[File:Cumulative Current Account Balance per capita.png|thumb|upright=1.8|Cumulative current account balance '''per capita''' 1980–2008 based on [[International Monetary Fund]] data.]]

The '''balance of trade''', '''commercial balance''', or '''net exports''' (sometimes symbolized as '''NX'''), is the difference between the monetary value of a nation's [[exports]] and [[imports]] over a certain time period.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=O'Sullivan |first=Arthur |authorlink=Arthur O'Sullivan (economist) |first2=Steven M. |last2=Sheffrin |title=Economics: Principles in Action |publisher=Pearson Prentice Hall |year=2003 |location=Upper Saddle River, New Jersey 07458 |page=462 |isbn=0-13-063085-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sometimes a distinction is made between a balance of trade for goods versus one for services. The balance of trade measures a [[flow variable|flow]] of exports and imports over a given period of time. The notion of the balance of trade does not mean that exports and imports are &quot;in balance&quot; with each other.

If a country exports a greater value than it imports, it has a '''trade surplus''' or '''positive trade balance''', and conversely, if a country imports a greater value than it exports, it has a '''trade deficit''' or '''negative trade balance.''' As of 2016, [[List of countries by net exports|about 60 out of 200 countries have a trade surplus]]. The notion that bilateral trade deficits are bad in and of themselves is overwhelmingly rejected by trade experts and economists.&lt;ref name=&quot;:16&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:15&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2018/06/09/upshot/what-is-the-trade-deficit.html|title=What Is the Trade Deficit?|last=|first=|date=2018-06-09|work=The New York Times|access-date=2018-06-10|language=en-US|issn=0362-4331|quote=The vast majority of economists view it differently. In this mainstream view, trade deficits are not inherently good or bad. They can be either, depending on circumstances.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Explanation==
[[File:Balance of trade in goods and services (Eurozone countries).png|thumb|Balance of trade in goods and services (Eurozone countries)]]
[[File:US Trade Balance from 1960.svg|thumb|US trade balance from 1960]]
[[File:U.S. Trade Balance (1895–2015) and Trade Policies.png|thumb|U.S. trade balance and trade policy (1895–2015)]]
[[File:U.K. balance of trade in goods (since 1870).png|thumb|U.K. balance of trade in goods (since 1870)]]
The balance of trade forms part of the [[Current account (balance of payments)|current account]], which includes other transactions such as income from the [[net international investment position]] as well as international aid. If the current account is in surplus, the country's net international asset position increases correspondingly. Equally, a deficit decreases the net international asset position.

The trade balance is identical to the difference between a country's output and its domestic demand (the difference between what goods a country produces and how many goods it buys from abroad; this does not include money re-spent on foreign stock, nor does it factor in the concept of importing goods to produce for the domestic market).

Measuring the balance of trade can be problematic because of problems with recording and collecting data. As an illustration of this problem, when official data for all the world's countries are added up, exports exceed imports by almost 1%; it appears the world is running a positive balance of trade with itself. This cannot be true, because all transactions involve an equal [[credit (finance)|credit]] or [[debit]] in the account of each nation. The discrepancy is widely believed to be explained by transactions intended to launder money or evade taxes, smuggling and other visibility problems. While the accuracy of developing countries statistics would be suspicious, most of the discrepancy actually occurs between developed countries of trusted statistics,&lt;ref&gt;The US and the UK both report a trade surplus with each other https://www.ft.com/content/82ebed88-9ede-11e7-8cd4-932067fbf946&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://www.npr.org/sections/money/2018/03/21/595769659/trump-vs-trudeau-both-right-both-wrong?t=1531683871253&amp;t=1568444810715
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Comparing Canadian and US bilateral trade in goods data, 2014, 2015 and 2016 https://www150.statcan.gc.ca/n1/daily-quotidien/180206/dq180206b-eng.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

Factors that can affect the balance of trade include:
* The cost of production (land, labor, capital, taxes, incentives, etc.) in the exporting economy ''vis-à-vis'' those in the importing economy;
* The cost and availability of raw materials, intermediate goods and other inputs;
* Currency exchange rate movements;
* Multilateral, bilateral and unilateral taxes or restrictions on trade;
* Non-tariff barriers such as environmental, health or safety standards;
* The availability of adequate foreign exchange with which to pay for imports; and
* Prices of goods manufactured at home (influenced by the responsiveness of supply)

In addition, the trade balance is likely to differ across the [[business cycle]]. In export-led growth (such as oil and early industrial goods), the balance of trade will shift towards exports during an economic expansion.{{Citation needed|date=May 2016}} However, with domestic demand-led growth (as in the United States and Australia) the trade balance will shift towards imports at the same stage in the business cycle.

The monetary balance of trade is different from the physical balance of trade&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://stats.oecd.org/glossary/detail.asp?ID=6542|title=Physical Trade Balance, OECD Glossary of Statistical Terms|publisher=|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; (which is expressed in amount of raw materials, known also as Total Material Consumption). Developed countries usually import a substantial amount of raw materials from developing countries. Typically, these imported materials are transformed into finished products, and might be exported after adding value. Financial trade balance statistics conceal material flow. Most developed countries have a large physical trade deficit, because they consume more raw materials than they produce. Many{{who|date=May 2016}} civil society organisations claim this imbalance is predatory and campaign for [[ecological debt]] repayment.

==Examples==
{{See also|Foreign trade of the United States}}

===Historical example===
Many countries in early modern Europe adopted a policy of [[mercantilism]], which theorized that a trade surplus was beneficial to a country, among other elements such as [[colonialism]] and [[trade barrier]]s with other countries and their colonies.  ([[Bullionism]] was an early philosophy supporting mercantilism.)
[[File:Merchandise exports (1870-1992).png|thumb|Merchandise exports (1870–1992)]]
[[File:Trade policy, exports and growth in selected European countries.png|thumb|Trade policy, exports and growth in selected European countries]]

The practices and abuses of mercantilism led the natural resources and cash crops of [[British North America]] to be exported in exchange for finished goods from Great Britain, a factor leading to the [[American Revolution]]. An early statement appeared in ''Discourse of the Common Wealth of this Realm of England'', 1549: &quot;We must always take heed that we buy no more from strangers than we sell them, for so should we impoverish ourselves and enrich them.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Now attributed to [[Thomas Smith (diplomat)|Sir Thomas Smith]]; quoted in [[José Rizal]], ''The Wheels of Commerce'', vol. II of ''Civilization and Capitalism 15th–18th Century'', 1979:204.&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly a systematic and coherent explanation of balance of trade was made public through [[Thomas Mun]]'s 1630 &quot;England's treasure by foreign trade, or, The balance of our foreign trade is the rule of our treasure&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Thomas Mun, Oxford National Dictionary of Biography&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the mid-1980s, the [[United States Balance of trade|United States has had a growing deficit in tradeable goods]], especially with Asian nations (China and Japan) which now hold large sums of U.S debt that has in part funded the consumption.&lt;ref name=Bivens&gt;Bivens, L. Josh (14 December 2004). [http://www.epinet.org/Issuebriefs/203/ib203.pdf Debt and the dollar] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20041217041437/http://www.epinet.org/Issuebriefs/203/ib203.pdf |date=17 December 2004 }} ''Economic Policy Institute''. Retrieved on 8 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=debt&gt;[http://www.treas.gov/tic/mfh.txt Major foreign holders of Treasury securities]. United States Treasury.&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. has a trade surplus with nations such as Australia. The issue of trade deficits can be complex. Trade deficits generated in tradeable goods such as manufactured goods or software may impact domestic employment to different degrees than do trade deficits in raw materials.

Economies which have savings surpluses, such as Japan and Germany, typically run trade surpluses. China, a high-growth economy, has tended to run trade surpluses. A higher savings rate generally corresponds to a trade surplus. Correspondingly, the U.S. with its lower savings rate has tended to run high trade deficits, especially with Asian nations.

Some have said that China pursues a mercantilist economic policy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2009/12/31/macroeconomic-effects-of-chinese-mercantilism/|title=Macroeconomic effects of Chinese mercantilism|publisher=|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.industryweek.com/public-policy/chinas-economic-mercantilism|title=China's Economic Mercantilism|date=24 July 2013|publisher=|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-china-usa-business/u-s-tech-group-urges-global-action-against-chinese-mercantilism-idUSKBN16N0YJ|title=U.S. tech group urges global action against Chinese|date=16 March 2017|publisher=|via=Reuters|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Russia pursues a policy based on protectionism, according to which international trade is not a &quot;win-win&quot; game but a zero-sum game: surplus countries get richer at the expense of deficit countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.investopedia.com/terms/p/protectionism.asp|title=Protectionism|last=Staff|first=Investopedia|date=25 November 2003|publisher=|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-trade-protectionism/russia-was-most-protectionist-nation-in-2013-study-idUSBRE9BT0GP20131230|title=Russia was most protectionist nation in 2013: study|date=30 December 2013|publisher=|via=Reuters|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://russia-insider.com/en/politics/study-russia-insulated-further-sanctions-import-substitution-success/ri20491|title=Study: Russia Insulated From Further Sanctions by Import Substitution Success|date=26 July 2017|publisher=|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.rbth.com/business/2017/02/09/food-import-substitution-turns-out-to-be-extremely-profitable_699158|title=Food import substitution turns out to be extremely profitable|last=Samofalova|first=Olga|date=10 February 2017|publisher=|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://thebarentsobserver.com/en/arctic/2017/03/made-russia-made-arctic|title=Made in Russia. Made for Arctic|publisher=|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ft.com/content/422a8252-2443-11e7-8691-d5f7e0cd0a16?mhq5j=e7|title=Subscribe to read|website=Financial Times|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===In 2016===

{|
|+ Balance of trade in some  geographic zones
|-
| {{Graph:Chart 
|width=450 |height=200 
|type=rect
|yAxisTitle=€ Millions
|yAxisFormat:.3s
|xAxisTitle=Geographic zone
|xAxisAngle=-45
|showValues=format:.3s, fontcolor:black, offset: 8
|x=EU28
-c2018,Russia,Canada,USA, Mexico,Brazil,China (-HK),Japan,S Korea,India,Singapore
|y1=32458 ,93263 ,-12640 ,-719571,-11908 ,43078,460490,34337,80617,-87070,42336
|y2=1745852,257919 ,351398,1312826,337774 ,167346,1895055,582647 ,447572,235185,298013,
|y3=1713393,164655 ,364039,2032397,349683 ,124267,1434565,548309 ,366954,322255,255677,
|colors=#c0808080,#c0ff4040,#c00036cc
|legend=Balance of trade, Import et exports (2016)
|y1Title=Balance of trade
|y2Title=Exports
|y3Title=Imports
}}
|-
| Sources: Eurostat 2016&lt;ref&gt;[http://appsso.eurostat.ec.europa.eu/nui/show.do?query=BOOKMARK_DS-054606_QID_73860F21_UID_-3F171EB0&amp;layout=GEO,L,X,0;INDIC_ET,L,Y,0;TIME,C,Z,0;SITC06,L,Z,1;INDICATORS,C,Z,2;&amp;zSelection=DS-054606SITC06,TOTAL;DS-054606INDICATORS,OBS_FLAG;DS-054606TIME,2016;&amp;rankName1=SITC06_1_2_-1_2&amp;rankName2=INDICATORS_1_2_-1_2&amp;rankName3=TIME_1_0_0_0&amp;rankName4=GEO_1_2_0_0&amp;rankName5=INDIC-ET_1_2_0_1&amp;rStp=&amp;cStp=&amp;rDCh=&amp;cDCh=&amp;rDM=true&amp;cDM=true&amp;footnes=false&amp;empty=false&amp;wai=false&amp;time_mode=NONE&amp;time_most_recent=false&amp;lang=EN&amp;cfo=%23%23%23%2C%23%23%23.%23%23%23]{{Dead link|date=August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{,}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/statistics-explained/index.php/International_trade_in_goods/fr|title=Le commerce international de biens - Statistics Explained|website=ec.europa.eu}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

===Country example: Armenia===
In March 2019, Armenia recorded a trade deficit of US$203.90 Million. For the last two decades, the Armenian trade balance has been negative, reaching the all-time high of –33.98 USD Million in August, 2003. The reason of trade deficit is because Armenia's foreign trade is limited due to landlocked location and border disputes with Turkey and Azerbaijan, from the west and east sides respectively. The situation results in the country's usual report of high trade deficits.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ceicdata.com/en/indicator/armenia/trade-balance|title=Armenia Trade Balance [1995 - 2019] [Data &amp; Charts]|website=www.ceicdata.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Views on economic impact==
The notion that bilateral trade deficits are bad in and of themselves is overwhelmingly rejected by trade experts and economists.&lt;ref name=&quot;:16&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://foreignpolicy.com/2017/03/06/economists-take-aim-at-trump-trade-theory-again-peter-navarro-bilateral-multilateral-trade-deals-china-germany-national-security/|title=Economists Take Aim at Trump Trade Theory — Again|last=Gramer|first=Robbie|date=March 6, 2017|work=[[Foreign Policy (magazine)|Foreign Policy]]|access-date=March 12, 2017|quote=Navarro’s comments drew skepticism from trade experts and economists across the political spectrum, who said that line of thinking on economics was flawed. Economists say trade deficits aren’t an indication of good or bad economic times, but rather a function of savings and investments. (The United States enjoyed a stellar trade surplus during the Great Depression in the 1930s, for example.) “He won’t find economists — either on the left or the right — that believe trade deficits are this huge a problem,” Chip Roh, a former assistant U.S. trade representative and trade lawyer, told Foreign Policy. “It doesn’t make economic sense.” “When economists hear, ‘Our goal is reduce the trade deficit,’ it baffles us,” Gordon Hanson, a trade economist at the University of California, San Diego, told FP. “He’s either using it as a cheap political ploy or there’s a misconception&amp;nbsp;— he doesn’t understand how it operates.”}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:15&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/wonk/wp/2017/03/07/trump-rails-against-the-trade-deficit-but-economists-say-theres-no-easy-way-for-him-to-make-it-go-away/|title=Analysis: Trump rails against trade deficit, but economists say there’s no easy way for him to make it go away|work=Washington Post|access-date=March 12, 2017|quote=At a conference Monday morning in Washington, Peter Navarro, the director of Trump’s National Trade Council, reiterated the administration’s focus on the trade deficit. The Trump administration policy is one of “free and fair and truly reciprocal trade that begins and ends with the belief that bilateral trade deficits do indeed matter,” he said. “Trade deficits not only matter when it comes to jobs and growth and national security, they matter a great deal,” Navarro said. Many economists disagree with this claim, saying that the factors behind the trade balance can be complex — and that the trade deficit is far from the best economic metric for policymakers to target... In an interview Monday, Angus Deaton, who won the Nobel Prize for economics in 2015, called the administration’s attitude on trade deficits “an old-fashioned mercantilist position.” “If you stand on a platform, it makes you six inches taller,” he said. “It’s a ridiculous argument.”}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.pri.org/stories/2017-03-01/trump-warns-trade-deficits-economists-say-who-cares|title=Trump warns of trade deficits. Economists say, who cares?|work=Public Radio International|access-date=2017-10-17|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.igmchicago.org/surveys/trade-balances|title=www.igmchicago.org/surveys/trade-balances|website=www.igmchicago.org|access-date=2017-10-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt; According to the [[International Monetary Fund|IMF]] trade deficits can cause a [[balance of payments]] problem, which can affect foreign exchange shortages and hurt countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.imf.org/external/np/exr/center/action/eng/devalue/index.htm|title=The IMF in Action: How can the IMF help in a crisis? Getting a member country's economy back on track|website=www.imf.org|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, [[Joseph Stiglitz]] points out that countries running surpluses exert a &quot;negative externality&quot; on trading partners, and pose a threat to global prosperity, far more than those in deficit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2010/may/05/reform-euro-or-bin-it-greece-germany|title=Reform the euro or bin it &amp;#124; Joseph Stiglitz|first=Joseph|last=Stiglitz|date=5 May 2010|via=www.theguardian.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2016/08/21/books/review/euro-joseph-e-stiglitz.html|title=Nobel Laureate Joseph Stiglitz Says the Euro Needs Big Reform|first=Roger|last=Lowenstein|date=16 August 2016|publisher=|accessdate=15 March 2018|via=NYTimes.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://lahcenbounadereconomics.blogspot.com/2016/12/a-critical-issue-adressed-to-joseph.html|title=Lahcen Bounader's weblog: A Critical Issue Adressed {{sic|nolink=y}} to Joseph Stiglitz|first=Lahcen|last=Bounader|date=31 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ben Bernanke]] argues that &quot;persistent imbalances within the euro zone are... unhealthy, as they lead to financial imbalances as well as to unbalanced growth. The fact that Germany is selling so much more than it is buying redirects demand from its neighbors (as well as from other countries around the world), reducing output and employment outside Germany.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.brookings.edu/blog/ben-bernanke/2015/04/03/germanys-trade-surplus-is-a-problem/|title=Germany’s trade surplus is a problem|first=Ben S.|last=Bernanke|publisher=|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2018 National Bureau of Economic Research paper by economists at the International Monetary Fund and University of California, Berkeley, found in a study of 151 countries over 1963-2014 that the imposition of tariffs had little effect on the trade balance.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Furceri|first=Davide|last2=Hannan|first2=Swarnali A|last3=Ostry|first3=Jonathan D|last4=Rose|first4=Andrew K|date=2018|title=Macroeconomic Consequences of Tariffs|url=http://www.nber.org/papers/w25402|journal=|volume=|pages=|doi=10.3386/w25402|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Classical theory===

====Adam Smith on the balance of trade====
{{See also|Friedrich List}}
{{quote|In the foregoing part of this chapter I have endeavoured to show, even upon the principles of the commercial system, how unnecessary it is to lay extraordinary restraints upon the importation of goods from those countries with which the balance of trade is supposed to be disadvantageous.

Nothing, however, can be more absurd than this whole doctrine of the balance of trade, upon which, not only these restraints, but almost all the other regulations of commerce are founded. When two places trade with one another, this [absurd] doctrine supposes that, if the balance be even, neither of them either loses or gains; but if it leans in any degree to one side, that one of them loses and the other gains in proportion to its declension from the exact equilibrium.|Smith, 1776, book IV, ch. iii, part ii&lt;ref&gt;Smith, Adam. (1776). An Inquiry into the Nature and Causes of the Wealth of Nations, Indianapolis: Liberty Fund, 1981, 2 vols., (1776) (reprint of the Clarendon Press edition, Oxford 1976, with Edward Cannan's original index from 1922)&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Keynesian theory===

In the last few years of his life, [[John Maynard Keynes]] was much preoccupied with the question of balance in international trade. He was the leader of the British delegation to the [[United Nations Monetary and Financial Conference]] in 1944 that established the [[Bretton Woods system]] of international currency management.
He was the principal author of a proposal – the so-called Keynes Plan – for an [[International Clearing Union]]. The two governing principles of the plan were that the problem of settling outstanding balances should be solved by 'creating' additional 'international money', and that debtor and creditor should be treated almost alike as disturbers of equilibrium. In the event, though, the plans were rejected, in part because &quot;American opinion was naturally reluctant to accept the principle of equality of treatment so novel in debtor-creditor relationships&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book|author=Crowther, Geoffrey|title=An Outline of Money|version=Second Edition|publisher= Thomas Nelson and Sons|year=1948|pages=326–29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The new system is not founded on free-trade (liberalisation&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.investopedia.com/terms/d/deregulate.asp|title=Deregulation|first=Investopedia|last=Staff|date=25 November 2003|publisher=|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; of foreign trade&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.investopedia.com/terms/t/trade-liberalization.asp|title=Trade Liberalization|first=Investopedia|last=Staff|date=3 April 2010|publisher=|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;) but rather on the regulation of international trade, in order to eliminate trade imbalances: the nations with a surplus would have a powerful incentive to get rid of it, and in doing so they would automatically clear other nations deficits.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://scholarworks.umass.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?referer=https://en.wikipedia.org/&amp;httpsredir=1&amp;article=1127&amp;context=peri_workingpapers |title=Current Global Imbalances and the Keynes Plan |last=Costabile |first=Lilia |date=2007 |website=scholarworks.umass.edu |access-date=2019-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; He proposed a global bank that would issue its own currency – the bancor – which was exchangeable with national currencies at fixed rates of exchange and would become the unit of account between nations, which means it would be used to measure a country's trade deficit or trade surplus. Every country would have an overdraft facility in its bancor account at the International Clearing Union. He pointed out that surpluses lead to weak global aggregate demand – countries running surpluses exert a &quot;negative externality&quot; on trading partners, and posed far more than those in deficit, a threat to global prosperity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2010/may/05/reform-euro-or-bin-it-greece-germany|title=Reform the euro or bin it - Joseph Stiglitz|first=Joseph|last=Stiglitz|date=5 May 2010|website=the Guardian|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In ''&quot;National Self-Sufficiency&quot; The Yale Review, Vol. 22, no. 4 (June 1933)'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://grepa.es/|title=Inicio|website=Grupo de Economía Política Alternativa}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.india-seminar.com/2009/601/601_david_singh_grewali.htm|title=601 David Singh Grewal, What Keynes warned about globalization|website=www.india-seminar.com|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; he already highlighted the problems created by free trade.

His view, supported by many economists and commentators at the time, was that creditor nations may be just as responsible as debtor nations for disequilibrium in exchanges and that both should be under an obligation to bring trade back into a state of balance. Failure for them to do so could have serious consequences. In the words of [[Geoffrey Crowther, Baron Crowther|Geoffrey Crowther]], then editor of [[The Economist]], &quot;If the economic relationships between nations are not, by one means or another, brought fairly close to balance, then there is no set of financial arrangements that can rescue the world from the impoverishing results of chaos.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author= Crowther, Geoffrey|title=An Outline of Money|version=Second Edition|publisher=Thomas Nelson and Sons
|year=1948|page=336}}&lt;/ref&gt;

These ideas were informed by events prior to the [[Great Depression]] when – in the opinion of Keynes and others – international lending, primarily by the U.S., exceeded the capacity of sound investment and so got diverted into non-productive and speculative uses, which in turn invited default and a sudden stop to the process of lending.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Crowther, Geoffrey| title=An Outline of Money|version=Second Edition|publisher=Thomas Nelson and Sons|year=1948|pages= 368–72}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Influenced by Keynes, economics texts in the immediate post-war period put a significant emphasis on balance in trade. For example, the second edition of the popular introductory textbook, ''An Outline of Money'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Crowther, Geoffrey|title=An Outline of Money|version= Second Edition|publisher=Thomas Nelson and Sons|year=1948}}&lt;/ref&gt; devoted the last three of its ten chapters to questions of foreign exchange management and in particular the 'problem of balance'. However, in more recent years, since the end of the [[Bretton Woods system]] in 1971, with the increasing influence of [[monetarist]] schools of thought in the 1980s, and particularly in the face of large sustained trade imbalances, these concerns – and particularly concerns about the destabilising effects of large trade surpluses – have largely disappeared from [[mainstream economics]] discourse&lt;ref&gt;See for example, Krugman, P and Wells, R (2006). &quot;Economics&quot;, Worth Publishers&lt;/ref&gt; and Keynes' insights have slipped from view.&lt;ref&gt;although see Duncan, R (2005). &quot;The Dollar Crisis: Causes, Consequences, Cures&quot;, Wiley&lt;/ref&gt; They are receiving some attention again in the wake of the [[financial crisis of 2007–08]].&lt;ref&gt;See for example,{{cite web|url= http://www.monbiot.com/archives/2008/11/18/clearing-up-this-mess/|title=Clearing Up This Mess| date=18 November 2008| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20090123161345/http://www.monbiot.com/archives/2008/11/18/clearing-up-this-mess/| archivedate= 23 January 2009 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Monetarist theory===
Prior to 20th century monetarist theory, the 19th century economist and philosopher [[Frédéric Bastiat]] expressed the idea that trade deficits actually were a manifestation of profit, rather than a loss. He proposed as an example to suppose that he, a Frenchman, exported French wine and imported British coal, turning a profit. He supposed he was in France, and sent a cask of wine which was worth 50 francs to England. The customhouse would record an export of 50 francs. If, in England, the wine sold for 70 francs (or the pound equivalent), which he then used to buy coal, which he imported into France, and was found to be worth 90 francs in France, he would have made a profit of 40 francs. But the customhouse would say that the value of imports exceeded that of exports and was trade deficit against the ledger of France.

By ''[[reductio ad absurdum]]'', Bastiat argued that the national trade deficit was an indicator of a successful economy, rather than a failing one. Bastiat predicted that a successful, growing economy would result in greater trade deficits, and an unsuccessful, shrinking economy would result in lower trade deficits. This was later, in the 20th century, echoed by economist [[Milton Friedman]].

In the 1980s, [[Milton Friedman]], a [[Nobel Memorial Prize in Economic Sciences|Nobel Memorial Prize]]-winning economist and a proponent of [[monetarism]], contended that some of the concerns of trade deficits are unfair criticisms in an attempt to push macroeconomic policies favorable to exporting industries.

Friedman argued that trade deficits are not necessarily important, as high exports raise the value of the currency, reducing aforementioned exports, and vice versa for imports, thus naturally removing trade deficits ''not due to investment''. Since 1971, when the Nixon administration decided to abolish fixed exchange rates, America's Current Account accumulated trade deficits have totaled $7.75 trillion as of 2010. This deficit exists as it is matched by investment coming into the United States – purely by the definition of the balance of payments, any current account deficit that exists is matched by an inflow of foreign investment.

In the late 1970s and early 1980s, the U.S. had experienced high inflation and Friedman's policy positions tended to defend the stronger dollar at that time. He stated his belief that these trade deficits were not necessarily harmful to the economy at the time since the currency comes back to the country (country A sells to country B, country B sells to country C who buys from country A, but the trade deficit only includes A and B). However, it may be in one form or another including the possible tradeoff of foreign control of assets. In his view, the &quot;worst-case scenario&quot; of the currency never returning to the country of origin was actually the best possible outcome: the country actually purchased its goods by exchanging them for pieces of cheaply made paper. As Friedman put it, this would be the same result as if the exporting country burned the dollars it earned, never returning it to market circulation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ideachannel.tv/|title=TheIdeaChannel.tv|website=www.ideachannel.tv|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This position is a more refined version of the theorem first discovered by [[David Hume]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Hume, David|title=Essays, Moral, Political, and Literary|url=https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.45548}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hume argued that England could not permanently gain from exports, because hoarding gold (i.e., currency) would make gold more plentiful in England; therefore, the prices of English goods would rise, making them less attractive exports and making foreign goods more attractive imports. In this way, countries' trade balances would balance out.

Friedman presented his analysis of the balance of trade in ''[[Free to Choose]]'', widely considered his most significant popular work.

===Trade balance’s effects upon a nation's GDP===
Exports directly increase and imports directly reduce a nation's balance of trade (i.e. net exports). A trade surplus is a positive net balance of trade, and a trade deficit is a negative net balance of trade. Due to the balance of trade being explicitly added to the calculation of the nation's gross domestic product using the expenditure method of calculating gross domestic product (i.e. GDP), trade surpluses are contributions and trade deficits are &quot;drags&quot; upon their nation's GDP.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.investopedia.com/terms/e/expenditure-method.asp|title=Expenditure Method|first=Investopedia|last=Staff|date=11 May 2010|publisher=|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bea.gov/methodologies/index.htm#national_meth|title=Bureau of Economic Analysis|first=US Department of Commerce, BEA, Bureau of Economic|last=Analysis|website=www.bea.gov|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.britannica.com/topic/gross-domestic-product|title=gross domestic product - Definition &amp; Formula|publisher=|accessdate=15 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Balance of trade vs. balance of payments==
{{prose|section|date=April 2016}}

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|- 
! style=&quot;width:50%&quot; | Balance of trade !! style = &quot;width:50%&quot; | Balance of payments
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;
| Includes only visible imports and exports, i.e. imports and exports of merchandise. The difference between exports and imports is called the balance of trade. If imports are greater than exports, it is sometimes called an unfavourable balance of trade. If exports exceed imports, it is sometimes called a favourable balance of trade. || Includes all those visible and invisible items exported from and imported into the country in addition to exports and imports of merchandise.
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;
| Includes revenues received or paid on account of imports and exports of merchandise. It shows only revenue items. || Includes all revenue and capital items whether visible or non-visible. The balance of trade thus forms a part of the balance of payments.
|}

==See also==
*[[Dutch disease]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Wikisource1911Enc|Balance of Trade}}
* [http://www.dollarsandsense.org/archives/2004/0304dollar.html Where Do U.S. Dollars Go When the United States Runs a Trade Deficit?] from [[Dollars &amp; Sense]] magazine
* [http://stats.oecd.org/Index.aspx?QueryId=166 OECD Trade balance statistics]
* [http://www.export.gov/ U.S. Government Export Assistance]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20121104065109/http://www.capcredit.com/us-trade-deficit/ U.S Trade Deficit Depicted in an Infographic]

{{Trade|state=expanded}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Balance Of Trade}}
[[Category:National accounts]]
[[Category:International trade theory]]
[[Category:International trade]]
[[Category:International macroeconomics]]</text>
      <sha1>dqo13ytelp3pcrfq8kny033xmuw67gp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
