  <page>
    <title>Babylon 5</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4800</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942430650</id>
      <parentid>942387395</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-24T16:57:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Fettlemap</username>
        <id>16120725</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 942387395 by [[Special:Contributions/Academikz|Academikz]] ([[User talk:Academikz|talk]]) not an improvement</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Good article}}
{{short description|American space opera television series}}
{{Infobox television
| show_name = Babylon 5
| image = Smb5-s4.jpg
| alt = Season 4 poster
| caption = Season 4 poster
| genre = {{unbulleted list|[[Space opera]]|Drama}}
| creator = [[J. Michael Straczynski]]
| starring = {{Plain list|
* [[Bruce Boxleitner]]
* [[Michael O'Hare]]
* [[Claudia Christian]]
* [[Jerry Doyle]]
* [[Mira Furlan]]
* [[Richard Biggs]]
* [[Andrea Thompson]]
* [[Bill Mumy]]
* [[Jason Carter (actor)|Jason Carter]]
* [[Tracy Scoggins]]
* [[Stephen Furst]]
* [[Patricia Tallman]]
* [[Peter Jurasik]]
* [[Andreas Katsulas]]
* [[Jeff Conaway]]
* [[Robert Rusler]]
}}
| composer = {{unbulleted list|[[Christopher Franke]]|[[Stewart Copeland]] {{Small|(pilot)}}}}
| country = United States
| language = English
| num_seasons = 5
| num_episodes = 110 (+ 6 TV films)
| list_episodes = List of Babylon 5 episodes
| executive_producer = {{unbulleted list|[[Douglas Netter]]|J. Michael Straczynski}}
| cinematography = {{unbulleted list|John C. Flinn III&lt;small&gt;&lt;br&gt;(102 episodes, 1994–1998)&lt;/small&gt;|Fred V. Murphy&lt;br&gt; &lt;small&gt;(8 episodes, 1995–1998)&lt;/small&gt;}}
| company = Babylonian Productions, Inc.&lt;br&gt;Synthetic Worlds, Ltd.&lt;br&gt;(pilot)&lt;br&gt;[[Warner Bros. Television|Warner Bros. Domestic Television Distribution]]
| distributor = [[Warner Bros. Domestic Television Distribution]]&lt;br&gt;(1993-1997)&lt;br&gt;(seasons 1-4)&lt;br&gt;[[Warner Bros. Television|Warner Bros. Domestic Pay-TV, Cable &amp; Network Features Distribution]]&lt;br&gt;(1998-1999)&lt;br&gt;(season 5)
| runtime = 43 minutes
| network = {{unbulleted list|[[Broadcast syndication|Syndicated]] (1993–1997)|[[TNT (American TV network)|TNT]] (1998)}}
| first_aired = {{Start date|1993|02|22}}
| last_aired = {{End date|1998|11|25}}
| audio_format = [[Dolby Surround]] 2.0 
| website = https://web.archive.org/web/20070602112525/http://babylon5.warnerbros.com/
| preceded_by = ''[[Babylon 5: The Gathering]]''
| followed_by = ''[[Crusade (TV series)]]''
| related = ''[[Babylon 5: The Legend of the Rangers|The Legend of the Rangers]]'' &lt;br /&gt;''[[Babylon 5: The Lost Tales|The Lost Tales]]''
}}

'''''Babylon 5''''' is an American [[space opera]] television series created by writer and producer [[J. Michael Straczynski]], under the Babylonian Productions label, in association with Straczynski's Synthetic Worlds Ltd. and [[Warner Bros. Television|Warner Bros. Domestic Television]]. After the successful airing of a [[test pilot movie]] on February 22, 1993, ''[[Babylon 5: The Gathering]]'', in May 1993 Warner Bros. commissioned the series for production as part of its [[Prime Time Entertainment Network]] (PTEN).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.thefreelibrary.com/PRIME+TIME+ENTERTAINMENT+NETWORK+ANNOUNCES+EXPANSION+PLANS+AND...-a013164529|title=PRIME TIME ENTERTAINMENT NETWORK ANNOUNCES EXPANSION PLANS AND PROGRAMMING SLATE FOR JANUARY 1994 - Free Online Library|last=Lieberman|first=Cynthia|date=May 27, 1993|website=PR Newswire|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150903212653/http://www.thefreelibrary.com/PRIME+TIME+ENTERTAINMENT+NETWORK+ANNOUNCES+EXPANSION+PLANS+AND...-a013164529|archive-date=September 3, 2015|url-status=dead|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The show premiered in the US on January 26, 1994, and ran for five seasons.

Unusual for the time, ''Babylon 5'' was conceived as a &quot;novel for television&quot;, with a defined beginning, middle, and end; in essence, each episode would be a single &quot;chapter&quot; of this &quot;novel&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=20481|title=JMSNews You say, &quot;New characters and sets...|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=January 22, 1993|website=jmsnews.com|language=en|access-date=February 24, 2019|quote=One final note: B5 has always been conceived as, fundamentally, a five year story, a novel for television, which makes it very different as well.}}&lt;/ref&gt; A coherent five-year [[story arc]] unfolds over five 22-episode seasons. Tie-in novels, comic books, and short stories were also developed to play a significant [[canon (fiction)|canonical]] part in the overall story.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=12967|title=JMSNews Re: ATTN: JMS Books and TV Plot|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=April 26, 1996|website=jmsnews.com|language=en|access-date=February 24, 2019|quote=My theory is that *in general* the novels and comics tend to be canon, but the details may not always be, mainly because it's virtually impossible to ride herd on every single line of all this the way I do the show. It physically can't be done. But where possible, we keep it as close to cointinuity [sic] as possible.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The series follows the human military staff and alien diplomats stationed on a [[space station]], ''[[Babylon 5 (space station)|Babylon 5]]'', built in the aftermath of several major inter-species wars as a neutral focal point for galactic diplomacy and trade. ''Babylon 5'' was an early example of a television series featuring story arcs which spanned episodes or whole seasons. Whereas contemporary television shows tended to confine conflicts to individual episodes, maintaining the overall status quo, each season of ''Babylon 5'' contains plot elements which permanently change the series universe.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://io9.gizmodo.com/everything-you-need-to-know-about-babylon-5-5876320|title=Everything You Need To Know About Babylon 5|last=Shankel|first=Jason|date=January 18, 2012|website=io9|language=en-US|access-date=February 6, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Babylon 5'' utilized multiple episodes to address the repercussions of some plot events or character decisions, and episode plots would at times reference or be influenced by events from prior episodes or seasons.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.inverse.com/article/44949-babylon-5-streaming-amazon-prime|title=The Most Important Sci-Fi Show of the '90s Hits Amazon Prime in June|last=Britt|first=Ryan|date=|website=Inverse|language=en|access-date=February 16, 2019|quote=in the Nineties it was still exceedingly rare for a TV show to have episodes directly lead into each other. Two-part episodes were a big deal, and season long story arcs (with the obvious exception of daytime soap operas) were unheard of. But, Babylon 5 changed all that.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many races of sentient creatures are seen frequenting the station, with most episodes drawing from a core of around a dozen species. Major plotlines included ''Babylon 5'''s embroilment in a millennia-long cyclical conflict between ancient, powerful races, inter-race wars and their aftermaths, and intrigue or upheaval within particular races, including the human characters who fight to resist Earth's descent into [[totalitarianism]]. Many episodes focus on the effect of wider events on individual characters, with episodes containing themes such as personal change, loss, subjugation, corruption, defiance, and redemption.

==Setting==
''Babylon 5'', set primarily between the years 2257 and 2262, depicts a future where Earth has a unifying [[Earth Alliance (Babylon 5)#Early development|Earth government]] and has gained the technology for [[faster-than-light]] travel. Colonies within the solar system, and beyond, make up the [[Earth Alliance (Babylon 5)|Earth Alliance]], which has established contact with other [[Spacefaring#Spacefaring in popular culture|spacefaring]] species. Ten years before the series is set, Earth itself was nearly defeated in a war with the spiritual [[Minbari]], only to escape destruction when the Minbari unexpectedly surrendered at the brink of victory; since then, Earth has established peaceful relationships with them.

Among the other species are the imperialist [[Centauri (Babylon 5)|Centauri]]; the [[Narn]], who only recently gained independence from the Centauri empire; and the mysterious, powerful [[Vorlon]]s. Several dozen less powerful species from the [[League of Non-Aligned Worlds]] also have diplomatic contact with the major races, including the [[Drazi]], [[Brakiri]], [[Vree]], [[Civilizations in Babylon 5#Markab|Markab]], and [[pak'ma'ra]]. An ancient and secretive race, the [[Shadow (Babylon 5)|Shadows]], unknown to humans but documented in many other races' religious texts, malevolently influence events to bring chaos and war among the known species.

The [[Babylon 5 (fictional space station)|''Babylon 5'' space station]] is located in the [[Epsilon Eridani]] system, at the [[Trojan (celestial body)|fifth Lagrangian point]] between the fictional planet Epsilon III and its moon.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.midwinter.com/lurk/universe/station-1.html|title=Babylon 5 Universe: The Station|author=Straczynski, J. Michael|date=October 8, 1995|accessdate=July 28, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is an [[O'Neill cylinder]] {{convert|5|mi|km}} long and {{convert|0.5-1.0|mi|km}} in diameter. The station is the last of its line; the first three stations were all destroyed before completion, while ''[[Babylon 4]]'' mysteriously vanished shortly after being made operational.&lt;ref name=&quot;4thSeason&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://articles.chicagotribune.com/1996-11-21/features/9611210323_1_straczynski-earth-minbari-war-space-station-babylon|title='Babylon 5' Plans Explosive 4th Season|author=Ian Spelling|date=November 21, 1996|work=[[Chicago Tribune]] (reprinted from [[The New York Times]])|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121104012950/http://articles.chicagotribune.com/1996-11-21/features/9611210323_1_straczynski-earth-minbari-war-space-station-babylon|archive-date=November 4, 2012|accessdate=January 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It contains living areas which accommodate various alien species, providing differing atmospheres and gravities. Human visitors to the alien sectors are shown using breathing equipment and other measures to tolerate the conditions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=21366|title=There are, in fact, a number of...|author=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=January 3, 1992|website=JMSNews|publisher=Midnight Design Productions, LLC|accessdate=February 26, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Cast ==
{{Main|List of Babylon 5 characters|Civilizations in Babylon 5}}

=== Regular cast ===
''Babylon 5'' featured an [[ensemble cast]] which changed over the course of the show's run:

* [[Michael O'Hare]] as Commander [[Jeffrey Sinclair]] (season 1; guest seasons 2-3): The first commander of ''Babylon 5'', later assigned to be Earth's ambassador to Minbar.
* [[Bruce Boxleitner]] as Captain [[John Sheridan (Babylon 5)|John Sheridan]] (seasons 2-5): Sinclair's replacement on ''Babylon 5'' after his reassignment, and a central figure of several prophecies within the Shadow war.
* [[Claudia Christian]] as Lt. Commander [[Susan Ivanova]] (seasons 1-4, guest season 5): Second in command to ''Babylon 5''.
* [[Jerry Doyle]] as [[Michael Garibaldi]] (seasons 1-5): ''Babylon 5''{{'}}s Chief of Station Security.
* [[Mira Furlan]] as [[Delenn]] (seasons 1-5): The Minbari ambassador to ''Babylon 5''. Originally born Minbari, she uses a special artifact at the start of the 2nd season to become a Minbari-human hybrid.
* [[Richard Biggs]] as Doctor [[Stephen Franklin (Babylon 5)|Stephen Franklin]] (seasons 1-5): ''Babylon 5''{{'}}s chief medical officer.
* [[Andrea Thompson]] as [[Talia Winters]] (season 1-2): A commercial Psi-Corps telepath that works aboard the station.
* [[Stephen Furst]] as [[Vir Cotto]] (seasons 1-5): Diplomatic aide to Centauri Ambassador Londo Mollari.
* [[Bill Mumy]] as [[Lennier]] (seasons 1-5): Diplomatic aide to Minbari Ambassador Delenn.
* [[Tracy Scoggins]] as Captain [[Elizabeth Lochley]] (season 5): ''Babylon 5''{{'}}s station commander following Ivanova's departure.
* [[Jason Carter (actor)|Jason Carter]] as [[Marcus Cole]] (seasons 3-4): A Ranger, one of a group of covert agents who fight against the Shadows.
* [[Julie Caitlin Brown|Caitlin Brown]] (season 1, guest season 5) and [[Mary Kay Adams]] (season 2) as [[Na'Toth]]: Diplomatic aide to Narn Ambassador G'Kar.
* [[Robert Rusler]] as Warren Keffer (season 2): Commander of the Zeta Wing, one of ''Babylon 5''{{'}}s small fighter fleets.
* [[Jeff Conaway]] as [[Zack Allan]] (guest season 2, main seasons 3-5): A sergeant within the ''Babylon 5'' security force.
* [[Patricia Tallman]] as [[Lyta Alexander]] (original TV movie, guest seasons 2-3, main seasons 4-5): A commercial Psi-Corps telepath that takes over for Talia when she leaves the station.
* [[Andreas Katsulas]] as [[G'Kar]] (seasons 1-5): The Narn ambassador to ''Babylon 5.''
* [[Peter Jurasik]] as [[Londo Mollari]] (seasons 1-5): The Centauri ambassador to ''Babylon 5.''

=== Recurring guests ===
* [[Wayne Alexander (actor)|Wayne Alexander]] as [[Lorien (Babylon 5)|Lorien]]: An alien of unknown origin that comes to Sheridan's aid after a critical moment in the Shadow War
* [[Ardwight Chamberlain]] (voice)/Jeffery Willerth (in the encounter-suit) as [[Kosh Naranek]], the [[Vorlon]] ambassador to ''Babylon 5''
* [[Tim Choate]] as [[Zathras]], an alien of unknown origins that is central to the disappearance of ''Babylon 4''
* Joshua Cox as Lt. [[List of Babylon 5 characters#David Corwin|David Corwin]], a technician in ''Babylon 5''{{'}}s Command and Control center
* [[David L. Crowley]] as Ofc. [[Lou Welch]], a member of the ''Babylon 5'' security staff
* [[Robin Atkin Downes]] as [[Byron (Babylon 5)|Byron]], a rogue telepath
* William Forward&lt;ref name=&quot;Forward1&quot;&gt;{{IMDb name|id=0287480|name=William Forward}}&lt;/ref&gt; as [[Antono Refa|Lord Antono Refa]], a colleague of Ambassador Mollari who has his own sights set for taking the Centauri Emperor.
* [[Robert Foxworth]] as [[General William Hague]], commanding officer that oversees military operations related to ''Babylon 5''
* [[Denise Gentile]] as [[Lise Hampton]], a former romantic interest for Michael Garibaldi during his time on the Mars colony
* [[Melissa Gilbert]] as [[Anna Sheridan]], Captain Sheridan's wife. The first appearance of Anna Sheridan was portrayed by [[Beth Toussaint]] in a recorded message.
* [[Lenore Kasdorf]] as a reporter for the Interstellar News (ISN) network
* [[Walter Koenig]] as [[Alfred Bester (Babylon 5)|Alfred Bester]], a senior officer of Psi-Corps
* [[Wortham Krimmer]] as Centauri [[Emperor Cartagia]]
* [[Damian London]] as [[Virini|Regent Virini]], a member of the Centauri court under Emperor Cartagia
* [[Leigh McCloskey]] as Thomas
* [[Marjorie Monaghan]] as [[Number One (Babylon 5)|Number One / Tessa Holloran]], the leader of the Mars resistance
* [[Julia Nickson-Soul]] as [[List of Babylon 5 characters#Catherine Sakai|Catherine Sakai]], a commercial explorer and Commander Sinclair's love interest before he is reassigned
* [[Jim Norton (Irish actor)|Jim Norton]] as [[Ombuds]] Wellington, a judiciary aboard ''Babylon 5''
* [[John Schuck]] as [[Draal]] (younger), Delenn's teacher and friend from Minbar that becomes part of the Great Machine buried within Epsilon III
* [[Louis Turenne]] as [[List of Babylon 5 characters#Brother Theo|Brother Theo]], the leader of a group of Roman Catholic monks living aboard ''Babylon 5''.
* [[John Vickery (actor)|John Vickery]] as [[Neroon]], a member of the Minbari warrior caste that replaced Delenn within the Grey Council following her transformation
* [[Ed Wasser]] as [[Morden (Babylon 5)|Morden]], a human agent working for the Shadows
* [[Efrem Zimbalist, Jr.]] as [[William Edgars]], a business leader based on the Mars colony

In addition, several other actors have filled more than one minor role on the series. [[Kim Strauss]] played the [[Drazi|Drazi Ambassador]] in four episodes, as well as nine other characters in ten more episodes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0833836/?ref_=fn_al_nm_1|title=Kim Strauss - IMDb|last=|first=|date=|website=IMDb|accessdate=August 26, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some actors had difficulty dealing with the application of prosthetics required to play some of the alien characters. The producers therefore used the same group of people (as many as 12) in various mid-level speaking roles, taking full head and body casts from each. The group came to be unofficially known by the production as the &quot;Babylon 5 Alien Rep Group.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=17146|title=JMSNews JMS: Utility Actor????|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=November 16, 1994|website=jmsnews.com|language=en|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Synopsis ==

{{Main|List of Babylon 5 episodes}}
{{:List of Babylon 5 episodes}}
The five seasons of the series each correspond to one fictional sequential year in the period 2258–2262. Each season shares its title with an episode that is central to that season's plot.

=== Season 1: Signs and Portents (1994) ===
Sinclair, the commander of ''Babylon 5'', is a hero of the Minbari war, troubled by his inability to remember events of the war’s last day. Though supported by Minbari ambassador Delenn, who is secretly a member of the Minbari ruling Grey Council, other Minbari remain distrustful of him. The Narn have recently succeeded in regaining their independence from Centauri, and Centauri ambassador Mollari finds a new ally in the enigmatic Mr. Morden to strike back at the Narn. Xenophobic groups on Earth challenge humanity's contact with aliens, and President Santiago, who has favored such contact, is assassinated.

=== Season 2: The Coming of Shadows (1994–1995) ===
Sinclair is transferred to be ambassador to Minbar, and Sheridan is assigned command of the station. He and Delenn believe Santiago's death is part of a conspiracy as now-president Clark takes steps to isolate Earth and install a totalitarian government. The aging Centauri Emperor dies, and against his wishes, Mollari and his ally Lord Refa replace him with his unstable nephew Cartagia. Aided by Morden's allies, the Shadows, the Centauri initiate a full-scale attack on the Narn homeworld, re-conquering it. Vorlon ambassador Kosh requests Sheridan's help to fight the Shadows.

=== Season 3: Point of No Return (1995–1996) ===
Sheridan and Delenn establish a &quot;conspiracy of light&quot; to fight the influence of the Shadows. When Clark declares martial law, Sheridan declares ''Babylon 5'''s independence from Earth government. Mollari realizes his deal with Morden has become dangerous but is unable to end it. Sinclair travels back in time to become Valen, the legendary Minbari religious leader. In retaliation for involving the Vorlons in the war, Kosh is killed by the Shadows. Despite Kosh's warnings, Sheridan goes to Z'ha'dum, the Shadow homeworld, and crashes a spacecraft filled with explosives on it, seemingly dying in the explosion.

=== Season 4: No Surrender, No Retreat (1996–1997) ===
Sheridan is rescued from Z'ha'dum by the mysterious Lorien. With the Shadows in retreat, the Vorlons further their efforts to destroy any species touched by the Shadows. Mollari overthrows Cartagia with the aid of Narn ambassador G’Kar. Sheridan discovers the Vorlons and Shadows have used the younger races in a [[proxy war]], and convinces both sides to stop the war and leave the younger races in peace. Sheridan leads Minbar, Centauri, and Narn to form a new Interstellar Alliance. With their help, Sheridan is able to free Earth from control of President Clark and install a new, more peaceful regime.

=== Season 5: The Wheel of Fire (1998) ===
A group of rogue human telepaths take sanctuary on the station, seeking Sheridan’s aid to escape the control of Psi Corps, the autocratic Earth agency that oversees telepaths. Remnants of the Shadows' allies attempt to break up the Alliance by setting the various races against each other, and manipulate events on Centauri to install Mollari as Emperor but under their control. Mollari withdraws Centauri from the Alliance. Twenty years later, Sheridan has a last reunion with his friends before leaving to join Lorien and the older races &quot;beyond the rim&quot;. No longer needed, ''Babylon 5'' is decommissioned and scuttled.

== Production ==

=== Origin ===
Having worked on a number of television science fiction shows which had regularly gone over budget, Straczynski concluded that a lack of long-term planning was to blame, and set about looking at ways in which a series could be done responsibly. Taking note of the lessons of mainstream television, which brought stories to a centralized location such as a hospital, police station, or law office, he decided that instead of &quot;[going] in search of new worlds, building them anew each week&quot;, a fixed space station setting would keep costs at a reasonable level. A fan of sagas such as the [[Foundation series|''Foundation'' series]], ''[[Childhood's End]]'', ''[[The Lord of the Rings]]'', ''[[Dune (franchise)|Dune]]'' and the [[Lensman series|''Lensman'' series]], Straczynski wondered why no one had done a television series with the same epic sweep, and concurrently with the first idea started developing the concept for a vastly ambitious epic covering massive battles and other universe-changing events. Realizing that both the fixed-locale series and the epic could be done in a single series, he began to sketch the initial outline of what would become ''Babylon 5''.&lt;ref name=&quot;GEnie-1992&quot;&gt;{{cite web&lt;!-- Archive URL date taken from page metadata, main URL date taken is the one used for the entire document --&gt;|url=http://www.midwinter.com/b5/GEnie/jms92-04|title=Babylon 5 (GEnie) posts by JMS for April, 1992|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|authorlink=J. Michael Straczynski|date=April 1992|work=[[The Lurker's Guide to Babylon 5]]|publisher=Steven Grimm|archiveurl=http://mirrors.ntua.gr/b5/GEnie/jms92-04|archivedate=March 13, 1994|accessdate=October 19, 2009|quote=I *love* sagas, and B5 will present a chance to tell that kind of saga. ... But this is hardly revelation; the world of SF print has been doing this now ever since the Lensman books. The job now is translating that approach to television...}}&lt;!-- original {{cite web |url=http://mirrors.ntua.gr/b5/GEnie/jms92-04 |title=[[GEnie]] posts by JMS for April, 1992 |accessdate=August 18, 2006}} --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=16576|title=Re: ATTN JMS: Why Accelerate t|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=January 25, 1995|website=JMSNews|language=en|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box
| quote = Once I had the locale, I began to populate it with characters, and sketch out directions that might be interesting. I dragged out my notes on religion, philosophy, history, sociology, psychology, science (the ones that didn't make my head explode), and started stitching together a crazy quilt pattern that eventually formed a picture. Once I had that picture in my head, once I knew what the major theme was, the rest fell into place. All at once, I saw the full five-year story in a flash, and I frantically began scribbling down notes.
| source = —J. Michael Straczynski, 1995&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://www.jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=16576 |title=Re: ATTN JMS: Why Accelerate t |last=Straczynski |first=J. Michael |date=January 25, 1995 |website=JMSNews |access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| align = left
| width = 40%
| salign = right
}}

Straczynski set five goals for ''Babylon 5''. He said that the show &quot;would have to be good science fiction&quot; as well as good television – &quot;rarely are shows both good [science fiction] ''and'' good TV; there're {{sic}} generally one or the other [emphasis in original].&quot; It would have to do for science fiction television what ''[[Hill Street Blues]]'' had done for [[police drama]]s, by taking an adult approach to the subject. It would have to be reasonably budgeted, and &quot;it would have to look unlike anything ever seen before on TV, presenting individual stories against a much broader canvas.&quot; He further stressed that his approach was &quot;to take [science fiction] seriously, to build characters for grown-ups, to incorporate real science but keep the characters at the center of the story.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;io9 evolution&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://io9.gizmodo.com/the-strange-secret-evolution-of-babylon-5-5985727|title=The Strange, Secret Evolution of Babylon 5|last=Shankel|first=Jason|date=February 21, 2013|work=[[io9]]|accessdate=August 31, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GEnie-1991&quot;&gt;{{cite web&lt;!-- Note: The Google Cache archive for this cite has been removed because it is a dead link. Google Cache is not an archive; it's a cache. --&gt;|url=http://ftp.midwinter.com/b5/GEnie/jms92-01|title=Babylon 5 (GEnie) posts by JMS for November 1991 through Jan, 1992|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|authorlink=J. Michael Straczynski|date=November 1991|work=[[The Lurker's Guide to Babylon 5]]|publisher=Steven Grimm|archiveurl=http://mirrors.ntua.gr/b5/GEnie/jms92-01|archivedate=March 13, 1994|accessdate=October 20, 2009|quote=For years, at conventions, I have heard fans lament, and even sat in on panels entitled WHY CAN'T THEY GET IT RIGHT?}}&lt;!-- original {{cite web|url=http://ftp.midwinter.com/b5/GEnie/jms92-01 |title=Babylon 5 posts by JMS for November 1991 through Jan, 1992 |author=Straczynski, J. Michael |year=1992 |accessdate=July 19, 2007 |archivedate=December 9, 2012 |archiveurl=https://archive.today/20121209180134/https://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:s4lsbb_HEiMJ:www.midwinter.com/b5/GEnie/jms92-01+%22It+would+have+to+be+good+TELEVISION%22&amp;ct=clnk&amp;cd=3&amp;gl=us |url-status=dead }} --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; Some of the staples of television science fiction were also out of the question (the show would have &quot;no kids or cute robots&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=21376|title=Well, lemme comment on that. One...|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=December 5, 1991|website=JMSNews|language=en|access-date=February 24, 2019|quote=How they want solid characters, imaginative stories, no kids or cute robots, using science the way it should be used, not talking down to the audience. That desire has been noted.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The idea was not to present a perfect utopian future, but one with greed and homelessness; one where characters grow, develop, live, and die; one where not everything was the same at the end of the day's events. Citing [[Mark Twain]] as an influence, Straczynski said he wanted the show to be a mirror to the real world and to covertly teach.&lt;ref name=&quot;GEnie-1992&quot;/&gt;

Following production on ''[[Captain Power and the Soldiers of the Future]]'', Straczynski approached John Copeland and Doug Netter, who had also been involved with ''Captain Power'' and showed him the [[Bible (screenwriting)|bible]] and pilot script for his show, and both were impressed with his ideas.&lt;ref name=&quot;sonq&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = https://www.syfy.com/syfywire/an-oral-history-of-babylon-5-the-beloved-tv-novel-that-showed-a-different-way-to-tell-sci | title = An Oral History Of Babylon 5: The Beloved Tv Novel That Showed A Different Way To Tell Sci-fi |first = Lisa | last = Granshaw | date = June 27, 2018 | accessdate = August 31, 2018 | work = [[Syfy Wire]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; They were able to secure an order for the pilot from [[Warner Bros.]] who were looking at the time to get programming for a planned broadcast network. Warner Bros. had remained skeptical about the show even after greenlighting the pilot. According to Straczynski, Warner Bros. had three main concerns: that American attention spans were too short for a series-long narrative to work, that it would be difficult to sell the show into [[Broadcast syndication|syndication]] as the syndicate networks would air the episodes out of order, and that no other science-fiction television show outside of ''Star Trek'' had gone more than three seasons before it was cancelled.&lt;ref name=&quot;newsarama 2019&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = https://www.newsarama.com/44664-jms-revisits-babylon-5-on-show-s-25th-anniversary.html | title = JMS Revisits BABYLON 5 On Show's 25th Anniversary | first  = Jonathan | last = Encarnacion | date=  April 8, 2019 | accessdate = April 12, 2019 | work = [[Newsarama]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Straczynski had proved out that the syndication fear was incorrect, since syndicate stations told him they show their shows in episode order to track broadcasts for royalties; however, he could not assure Warner Bros. about the attention span or premature cancellation concerns, but still set out to show Warner Bros. they were wrong.&lt;ref name=&quot;newsarama 2019&quot;/&gt;

=== Writing ===
Straczynski wrote 92 of the 110 episodes of ''Babylon 5'', including all 44 episodes in the third and fourth seasons;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |publisher=Lurker's Guide to Babylon 5 |title=Writers/Directors list (JMS entry) |url=http://www.midwinter.com/lurk/making/write-direct.html#JMichaelStraczynski |accessdate=November 8, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; according to Straczynski, a feat never before accomplished in American television.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=13039|title=Re: ATTN: JMS I heard that with you writing the entire season, you will be the 1st in tv history?|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=April 22, 1996|website=JMSNews|language=en|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other writers to have contributed scripts to the show include [[Peter David]], [[Neil Gaiman]], [[Kathryn M. Drennan]], [[Larry DiTillio|Lawrence G. DiTillio]], [[D. C. Fontana]], and [[David Gerrold]]. [[Harlan Ellison]], a creative consultant on the show, received story credits for two episodes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |publisher=Lurker's Guide to Babylon 5 |title=Writers/Directors list |url=http://www.midwinter.com/lurk/making/write-direct.html#write |accessdate=November 8, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Each writer was informed of the overarching storyline, enabling the show to be produced consistently under-budget. The rules of production were strict; scripts were written six episodes in advance, and changes could not be made once production had started.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://tech.mit.edu/V118/N24/discuss.24n.html |title=Straczynski, Jablokov Discuss Television, The Future |author=Brett Altschul |work=[[The Tech (newspaper)|The Tech]] |date=May 5, 1998 |accessdate=December 13, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With not all cast members being hired for every episode of a season, the five-year plot length caused some planning difficulties. If a critical scene involving an actor not hired for every episode had to be moved, that actor had to be paid for work on an extra episode.&lt;ref name=&quot;newsarama 2019&quot;/&gt; It was sometimes necessary to adjust the plotline to accommodate external influences, an example being the &quot;trap door&quot; that was written for every character: in the event of that actor's unexpected departure from the series, the character could be written out with minimal impact on the storyline.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.midwinter.com/lurk/misc/cc-leave.html |title=JMS on Claudia Christian's departure |accessdate=November 14, 2006| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20061019022537/http://www.midwinter.com/lurk/misc/cc-leave.html| archivedate= October 19, 2006 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Straczynski stated, &quot;As a writer, doing a long-term story, it'd be dangerous and short-sighted for me to construct the story without trap doors for every single character. ... That was one of the big risks going into a long-term storyline which I considered long in advance;...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=13003|title=Re: ATTN: JMS Changes in the Story due to Actors|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=April 24, 1996|website=JMSNews|language=en|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; This device was eventually used to facilitate the departure of Claudia Christian and Andrea Thompson from the series.

{{Quote box
| quote = First thing I did was to flip out the stand-alones, which traditionally have taken up the first 6 or so episodes of each season; between two years, that's 12 episodes, over half a season right there. Then you would usually get a fair number of additional stand-alones scattered across the course of the season. So figure another 3–4 per season, say 8, that's 20 out of 44. So now you're left with basically 24 episodes to fill out the main arc of the story.
| source = —J. Michael Straczynski, 1996&lt;ref name=&quot;writing&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=From jms re: yr 4/5 |last=Straczynski |first=J. Michael|date=December 18, 1996 |publisher=Midnight Design Productions, LLC |url=http://www.jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=10251 |accessdate=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| align = right
| width = 40%
| salign = right
}}

Straczynski purposely went light on the five-year narrative elements during the first season as he felt the audience would not be ready for the full narrative at the time, but he still managed to drop in some scenes that would be critical to the future narrative. This also made it a challenge for the actors, as to understand motivations without being told what those were driving towards; Straczynski said &quot;I didn’t want to tell them too much, because that risks having them play the result, rather than the process.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;newsarama 2019&quot;/&gt; He recalled that Peter Jurasik had asked him about the scene from &quot;[[Midnight on the Firing Line]]&quot; where Londo and G'Kar are choking themselves to death, as to determine the context of the scene, and Straczynsky had to be coy with this.&lt;ref name=&quot;newsarama 2019&quot;/&gt;

During production of the fourth season, the [[Prime Time Entertainment Network]], which Warner Bros. opted to use for ''Babylon 5'', was shut down, leaving the planned fifth season in doubt. Unwilling to short-change fans of the show,  Straczynski began preparing modifications to the fourth season that would allow him to conclude his overall arc should a fifth season not be greenlit, which ultimately became the direction the fourth season took. Straczynski identified three primary [[narrative thread]]s which would require resolution: the Shadow war, Earth's slide into a dictatorship, and a series of sub-threads which branched off from those. Estimating they would still take around 27 episodes to resolve without having the season feel rushed, the solution came when the [[Turner Network Television|TNT]] network commissioned two ''Babylon 5'' television films. Several hours of material was thus able to be moved into the films, including a three-episode arc which would deal with the background to the [[Earth–Minbari War]], and a sub-thread which would have set up the sequel series, ''Crusade''. Further standalone episodes and plot-threads were dropped from season four, which could be inserted into ''Crusade'', or the fifth season, were it to be given the [[greenlight]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.jmsnews.com/Messages/Message?id=10251|title=Year 4/5|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=December 18, 1996|website=JMSNews|access-date=February 18, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The intended series finale, &quot;[[Sleeping in Light]]&quot;, was filmed during season four as a precaution against cancellation. When word came that TNT had picked up ''Babylon 5'', this was moved to the end of season five and replaced with a newly filmed season four finale, &quot;[[The Deconstruction of Falling Stars]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=How will this play out |author=Straczynski, J. Michael|date=May 21, 1997 |publisher=Midnight Design Productions, LLC |url=http://www.jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=9221 |accessdate=February 26, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Costume ===
Ann Bruice Aling was costume designer for the show, after [[production designer]] John Iacovelli suggested her for the position having previously worked with Bruice on a number of film and theatrical productions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Iacovelli3&quot;&gt;{{cite AV media|url=|title=Designing Tomorrow: The Look of Babylon 5|date=2003|people=Iacovelli, John|first=|type=|language=|publisher=Warner Bros. Entertainment|format=|medium=DVD Featurette - Babylon 5, Season 3 Box Set}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With the variety of costumes required she compared ''Babylon 5'' to &quot;eclectic theatre&quot;, with fewer rules about period, line, shape and textures having to be adhered to.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bruice2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.midwinter.com/b5/America-Online/bruice-iacovelli.txt|title=Behind the Scenes Interview with Ann Bruice Aling and John Iacovelli|author=Bruice Aling, Ann|date=October 15, 1995|website=The Lurker's Guide to Babylon 5|publisher=OMNI Online, Archived on Midwinter.com|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121120095916/http://www.midwinter.com/b5/America-Online/bruice-iacovelli.txt|archivedate=November 20, 2012|url-status=dead|accessdate=February 8, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Preferring natural materials whenever possible, such as [[ostrich leather]] in the [[Narn]] body armor, Bruice combined and layered fabrics as diverse as rayon and silk with [[brocade]]s from the 1930s and '40s to give the clothing the appearance of having evolved within different cultures.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bruice1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Online Chat Transcripts: Ann Bruice Aling and Kim Holly |author=Bruice Aling, Ann |date=May 21, 1998 |url=http://www.harrellnews.org/babylon5/transcripts/annbruicealingchat.html |publisher=Official B5 Fan Club |accessdate=December 27, 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120426080858/http://www.harrellnews.org/babylon5/transcripts/annbruicealingchat.html |archivedate=April 26, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kim1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Interview with Kim Holly, Babylon Podcast #45|author=Holly, Kim|date=December 13, 2006 |url=http://www.babylonpodcast.com/2006/12/13/babylon-podcast-show-45/|publisher=The Babylon Podcast|accessdate=December 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box |quote=Often we try to coordinate the sensibilities of the aliens. I try to work with Optic Nerve to ensure that the head meets the body in some sensible way. We talk about similar qualities, textures and colors and the flow of the total being. Truthfully, often the look of the prosthetic comes somewhat earlier and from that I have an understanding of what direction to go. |source=— Ann Bruice Aling, 1995&lt;ref name=&quot;Bruice2&quot;/&gt;|align=right |width=40% |salign=right}}With an interest in costume history, she initially worked closely with Straczynski to get a sense of the historical perspective of the major alien races, &quot;so I knew if they were a peaceful people or a warring people, cold climate etc. and then I would interpret what kind of sensibility that called for.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bruice1&quot;/&gt; Collaborating with other departments to establish co-ordinated visual themes for each race, a broad palette of colors was developed with Iacovelli, which he referred to as &quot;spicy brights&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Iacovelli1&quot;&gt;{{cite video|people=Iacovelli, John (Production Designer)|date=August 17, 2004|title=Babylon 5: The Movie Collection, Disc 5 Extras: &quot;Creating the Future&quot;|url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0105946/dvd#B0002B15UQ|medium=DVD|publisher=Warner Home Video|location=|archiveurl=http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/56388948|archivedate=December 6, 2009|accessdate=December 6, 2009|id={{UPC|085393343729}}|isbn=0-7907-9132-3|first=|language=|type=}}&lt;!-- original cite: Babylon 5: The Movie Collection, disc 5, &quot;Creating the Future&quot;. --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; These warm shades of grey and secondary colors, such as certain blues for the [[Minbari]], would often be included when designing both the costumes and relevant sets. As the main characters evolved, Bruice referred back to Straczynski and producer John Copeland who she viewed as &quot;surprisingly more accessible to me as advisors than other producers and directors&quot;, so the costumes could reflect these changes. Ambassador [[Londo Mollari]]'s purple coat became dark blue and more tailored while his waistcoats became less patterned and brightly colored as Bruice felt &quot;Londo has evolved in my mind from a buffoonish character to one who has become more serious and darker.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bruice2&quot;/&gt;

Normally there were three changes of costume for the primary actors; one for on set, one for the stunt double and one on standby in case of &quot;coffee spills&quot;. For human civilians, garments were generally purchased [[Ready-to-wear|off-the-rack]] and altered in various ways, such as removing lapels from jackets and shirts while rearranging [[Hook-and-eye closure|closures]], to suggest future fashions. For some of the main female characters a more [[Haute couture|couture]] approach was taken, as in the suits worn by [[Talia Winters]] which Bruice described as being designed and fitted to within &quot;an inch of their life&quot;. Costumes for the destitute residents of downbelow would be distressed through a combination of bleaching, sanding, dipping in dye baths and having stage blood added.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bruice1&quot;/&gt;

Like many of the crew on the show, members of the costume department made onscreen [[Cameo appearance|cameos]]. During the season 4 episode &quot;[[Atonement (Babylon 5)|Atonement]]&quot;, the tailors and costume supervisor appeared as the Minbari women fitting [[Zack Allan]] for his new uniform as the recently promoted head of security. His complaints, and the subsequent stabbing of him with a needle by costume supervisor Kim Holly, was a light-hearted reference to the previous security uniforms, a design carried over from the pilot movie which were difficult to work with and wear due to the combination of leather and wool.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kim1&quot;/&gt;

=== Prosthetic makeup and animatronics ===
While the original pilot film featured some [[Extraterrestrial life|aliens]] which were puppets and [[animatronics]], the decision was made early on in the show's production to portray most alien species as [[humanoid]] in appearance. Barring isolated appearances, fully [[Computer-generated imagery|computer-generated]] aliens were discounted as an idea due to the &quot;massive [[rendering (computer graphics)|rendering]] power&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=17581|title=Alien looking aliens|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=September 6, 1994|website=JMSNews|language=en|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; required. Long-term use of puppets and animatronics was also discounted, as Straczynski believed they would not be able to convey &quot;real emotion&quot; without an actor inside.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;

=== Visuals ===
{{See also|#Mastering problems}}
In anticipation of future [[High-definition television|HDTV]] broadcasts and [[Laserdisc]] releases, rather than the usual [[4:3]] format, the series was shot in [[16:9]], with the image cropped to 4:3 for initial television transmissions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=20076|title=We are shooting in 16:9|author=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=September 22, 1993|website=|publisher=Midnight Design Productions, LLC|accessdate=February 26, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Babylon 5'' also distinguished itself at a time when models and miniature were still standard by becoming one of the first television shows to use computer technology in creating [[visual effects]]. This was more due out of budgetary concerns, as they did not have the budget to produce miniatures and other practical specific effects; Straczynski estimated that each of their episodes cost {{USD|650,000}} to make compared to the {{USD|1.5 million}} each episode of ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation]]'' had cost.&lt;ref name=&quot;newsarama 2019&quot;/&gt; The visual effects were achieved using [[Amiga]]-based [[Video Toaster]]s at first, and later [[Pentium compatible processor|Pentium]], [[Apple Macintosh|Macs]], and [[DEC Alpha|Alpha]]-based systems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.midwinter.com/lurk/making/effects.html|title=Babylon 5 Behind the Scenes: The Effects|last=|first=|date=August 12, 1997|work=The Lurker's Guide To Babylon 5|accessdate=February 8, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also attempted to respect [[Newtonian physics]] in its effects sequences, with particular emphasis on the effects of inertia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=20155|title=Re: Physics of Babylon 5|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=September 10, 1993|website=JMSNews|language=en|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Foundation Imaging]] provided the special effects for the pilot film (for which it won an Emmy) and the first three seasons of the show, led by Ron Thornton. After co-executive producer Douglas Netter and producer John Copeland approached Straczynski with the idea of producing the effects in-house, Straczynski agreed to replace Foundation, for season 4 and 5, once a new team had been established by [[Netter Digital]], and an equal level of quality was assured,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.babylonpodcast.com/tag/jms/ |title=Babylon Podcast #161: Interview with JMS, Part 1 |author=Straczynski, J. Michael|date=June 16, 2009 |publisher= Babylon Podcast|accessdate=November 28, 2009| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20091109005352/http://www.babylonpodcast.com/tag/jms/| archivedate= November 9, 2009 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; by using similar technology and a number of former Foundation employees.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=11343|title=Re: ATTN JMS: Foundation Imaging Collapse - Sinking into the sand?|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=September 11, 1996|website=JMSNews|language=en|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Emmy-winning alien make-up was provided by Optic Nerve Studios.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://makeupmag.com/optic-nerve-co-founder-john-vulich-dead-55/|title=Optic Nerve Co-Founder John Vulich Dead at 55|last=Nazzarro|first=Joe|date=October 17, 2016|website=Make-Up Artist Magazine|language=en-US|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Music and scoring ===
{{Infobox album
| name       = Sleeping in Light
| type       = soundtrack
| artist     = [[Christopher Franke]]
| cover      = B5SleepLightCover.gif
| alt        =
| released   = {{Start date|1999|03|23}}
| recorded   =
| venue      =
| studio     =
| genre      = [[European classical music|Classical]], [[Electroacoustic music|Electroacoustic]]
| length     = 25:01
| label      = Sonic Images
| producer   =
| prev_title =
| prev_year  =
| next_title =
| next_year  =
}}
{{Album ratings
|rev1     = [[AllMusic]]
|rev1Score= {{Rating|4|5}}&lt;ref name=&quot;AllMusic1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Babylon 5: Sleeping in Light (Television Soundtrack)|author=Ankeny, Jason |url=http://www.allmusic.com/album/babylon-5-sleeping-in-light-television-soundtrack-r400716|website=[[AllMusic]] |accessdate=December 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
[[Christopher Franke]] [[Musical composition|composed]] and [[Sheet music|scored]] the musical soundtrack for all 5 years of the show when [[Stewart Copeland]], who worked on the original telefilm, was unable to return for the first season due to recording and touring commitments.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=19189|title=Music change from Gathering to|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=February 8, 1994|website=JMSNews|language=en|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Initially concerned composing for an episodic television show could become &quot;annoying because of the repetition&quot;, Franke found the evolving characters and story of ''Babylon 5'' afforded him the opportunity to continually take new directions.&lt;ref name=&quot;ChrisFranke1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ChrisFranke2&quot; /&gt; Given creative freedom by the producers, Franke also [[Orchestration#Film orchestration|orchestrated]] and [[Audio mixing (recorded music)|mixed]] all the music, which one reviewer described as having &quot;added another dimension of mystery, suspense, and excitement to the show, with an easily distinguishable character that separates &quot;Babylon 5&quot; from other sci-fi television entries of the era.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ChrisFranke1&quot;&gt;{{cite AV media|url=|title=Celestial Sounds|date=2003|people=Franke, Christopher|first=|type=DVD Featurette - Babylon 5, Season 4 Box Set|language=English|publisher=Warner Bros. Entertainment|format=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Babylon 5: Messages from Earth|author=Editorial Review|date=July 7, 1999 |url=http://www.filmtracks.com/titles/b5_messages.html|publisher=[[Filmtracks.com]]|accessdate=December 27, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With his recording studio in the same building as his home located in the [[Hollywood Hills]], Franke would attend creative meetings before scoring the on average 25 minutes of music for each episode.&lt;ref name=&quot;ChrisFranke1&quot; /&gt; Utilizing the &quot;acoustic dirt produced by live instruments and the ability to play so well between two semitones&quot; and the &quot;frequency range, dynamics and control&quot; provided by synthesizers, he described his approach &quot;as experimental friendly as possible without leaving the happy marriage between the orchestral and electronic sounds&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ChrisFranke2&quot; /&gt;

Utilising [[Steinberg Cubase|Cubase]] software through an [[electronic keyboard]], or for more complex pieces a [[light pen]] and [[graphics tablet]], he would begin by developing the [[Melody|melodic]] content round which the [[Ambient music|ambient]] components and [[Transition (music)|transitions]] were added. Using playbacks with digital [[Sampling (music)|samples]] of the appropriate instruments, such as a group of violins, he would decide which tracks to produce electronically or record [[Acoustic music|acoustically]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ChrisFranke1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ChrisFranke2&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Babylon 5: Messages From Earth – The Interview |author=Franke, Christopher| date=April 23, 1995 |url=http://christopherfranke.com/interview.html|publisher=Rudy Koppl (interviewer)|accessdate=January 3, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Scores for the acoustic tracks were emailed to his Berlin scoring stage, and would require from four musicians to the full orchestra, with a maximum of 24 present at any one time. One of three conductors would also be required for any score that involved more than 6 musicians. Franke would direct recording sessions via six fibre optic digital telephone lines to transmit and receive video, music and the [[SMPTE timecode]]. The final edit and mixing of the tracks would take place in his Los Angeles studio.

A total of 24 episode and three television film soundtracks were released under Franke's record label, Sonic Images Records, between 1995 and 2001. These contain the musical scores in the same chronological order as they played in the corresponding episodes, or television films. Three compilation albums were also produced, containing extensively re-orchestrated and remixed musical passages taken from throughout the series to create more elaborate suites. In 2007 his soundtrack for [[Babylon 5: The Lost Tales|The Lost Tales]] was released under the [[Varèse Sarabande]] record label.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; width=70%
|-
! colspan=&quot;5&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left; border: 0&quot;|'''Music CD Releases'''
|-
! style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;| Episodic Soundtracks || Tracks || Running Time || Release Date || Catalog No.
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Severed Dreams || 5 || 33:15 || Sep 16, 1997 || SID-0310
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | A Late Delivery From Avalon || 6 || 26:37 || Sep 16, 1997 || SID-0312
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Walkabout || 6 || 28:58 || Sep 16, 1997 || SID-0318
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Shadow Dancing || 6 || 33:50|| Sep 16, 1997 || SID-0321
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Z'Ha'Dum || 6 || 36:23|| Sep 16, 1997 || SID-0322
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | The Fall of Night || 6 || 22:45|| April 14, 1998 || SID-0222
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Interludes and Examinations || 6 || 30:14|| April 14, 1998 || SID-0315
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Into The Fire || 6 || 35:05|| April 14, 1998 || SID-0406
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | No Surrender, No Retreat || 6 || 30:53|| April 14, 1998 || SID-0415
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | The Face of the Enemy || 6 || 32:20|| April 14, 1998 || SID-0417
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | The Ragged Edge || 6 || 22:42|| April 14, 1998 || SID-0513
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Chrysalis || 6 || 24:51|| Aug 11, 1998 || SID-0112
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | The Coming of Shadows || 6 || 26:00|| Aug 11, 1998 || SID-0209
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | War Without End, Part 1 || 6 || 32:04|| Aug 11, 1998 || SID-0316
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | War Without End, Part 2 || 6 || 32:41|| Aug 11, 1998 || SID-0317
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Whatever Happened To Mr. Garibaldi || 6 || 28:41|| Aug 11, 1998 || SID-0402
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | The Long Night || 6 || 24:32|| Aug 11, 1998 || SID-0405
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Lines of Communication || 6 || 31:44|| Aug 11, 1998 || SID-0411
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Endgame || 6 || 35:25|| Aug 11, 1998 || SID-0420
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Falling Toward Apotheosis || 6 || 23:03|| Feb 16, 1999 || SID-0404
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Darkness Ascending || 6 || 32:41|| Feb 16, 1999 || SID-0516
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Objects at Rest || 6 || 27:52|| Feb 16, 1999 || SID-0522
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Sleeping in Light || 6 || 24:40|| Feb 16, 1999 || SID-0523
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | And The Rock Cried Out, No Hiding Place || 6 || 27:59|| Jan 9, 2001 || SID-0320
|-
! colspan=&quot;5&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left; border: 0&quot;|'''Movie Soundtracks'''
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | In The Beginning || 6 || 57:12|| Aug 11, 1998 || SID-8812
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Thirdspace || 5 || 59:22|| Jan 12, 1999 || SID-8900
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | The River of Souls || 6 || 49:55 || May 18, 1999 || SID-8907
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | The Lost Tales (released by [[Varèse Sarabande]])|| 28 || 39:39 || July 24, 2007 || VSD-6829
|-
! colspan=&quot;5&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left; border: 0&quot;|'''Extended Compilations'''
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Babylon 5 Vol.1 – Babylon 5 Suites || 6 || 58:03 || April 11, 1995 || SID-6502
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Babylon 5 Vol.2 – Messages from Earth || 6 || 57:03|| Feb 11, 1997 || SID-6602
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | The Best of Babylon 5 || 6 || 50:02|| Jan 9, 2001 || SID-8931
|}

=== Broadcast history ===
Warner Bros. slotted the show to premiere on its nascent [[Prime Time Entertainment Network]] (PTEN). As original content from another studio, it was somewhat anomalous in a stable of syndicated content from Warner Bros., and the cause of some friction between Straczynski's company and Warner Bros.&lt;ref name=&quot;newsarama 2019&quot; /&gt;

The pilot film, [[Babylon 5: The Gathering|''The Gathering'']], premiered on February 22, 1993, with strong viewing figures, achieving a 9.7 in the [[Nielsen ratings|Nielsen]] national syndication rankings.&lt;ref name=&quot;benson&quot;&gt;{{cite magazine|author=Jim Benson|date=May 28, 1993|title=Warner weblet to 2-night sked|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR107288.html?categoryid=14&amp;cs=1|magazine=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071114130149/http://www.variety.com/article/VR107288.html?categoryid=14&amp;cs=1|archive-date=November 14, 2007|accessdate=December 5, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The regular series initially aired from January 26, 1994 through November 25, 1998,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.midwinter.com/lurk/countries/master/eplist.html|title=Original US airdates at Lurker's Guide|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070825175544/http://www.midwinter.com/lurk/countries/master/eplist.html|archivedate=August 25, 2007|accessdate=August 22, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; first on PTEN, then in [[Broadcast syndication#First-run syndication in the U.S.|first-run syndication]], debuting with a 6.8 rating/10 share. Figures dipped in its second week, and while it posted a solid 5.0 rating/8 share, with an increase in several major markets,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|author=Joe Flint|date=February 9, 1994|title='Babylon 5' slips a bit in second week|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR118151.html?categoryid=14&amp;cs=1|magazine=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071202224847/http://www.variety.com/article/VR118151.html?categoryid=14&amp;cs=1|archive-date=December 2, 2007|accessdate=December 5, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; ratings for the first season continued to fall, to a low of 3.4 during [[rerun]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://variety.com/article/VR120389.html?categoryid=14&amp;cs=1|title=Sun and hoops sink syndies, rout 'Rush' - Entertainment News, TV News, Media - Variety|date=July 22, 2009|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090722232531/https://variety.com/article/VR120389.html?categoryid=14&amp;cs=1|archive-date=July 22, 2009|access-date=February 7, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ratings remained low-to-middling throughout the first four seasons,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|author=Andrew Hindes|date=February 13, 1997|title=U's 'Xena'|url=http://www.variety.com/vstory/VR1117435926.html?categoryid=38&amp;cs=|magazine=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071202225051/http://www.variety.com/vstory/VR1117435926.html?categoryid=38&amp;cs=|archivedate=December 2, 2007|accessdate=November 6, 2007|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; but ''Babylon 5'' scored well with the [[demographics]] required to attract the leading national sponsors and saved up to $300,000 per episode by shooting off the studio lot,&lt;ref name=&quot;benson&quot; /&gt; therefore remaining profitable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite newsgroup|title=Notes from jms|author=Straczynski, J. Michael|date=October 11, 1995|newsgroup=rec.arts.sf.tv.babylon5.moderated|url=http://jmsnews.com/msg.aspx?id=1-13613|accessdate=November 6, 2007|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071029025150/http://www.jmsnews.com/msg.aspx?id=1-13613|archivedate=October 29, 2007|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; The fifth season, which aired on cable network [[TNT (American TV network)|TNT]], had ratings about 1.0% lower than seasons two through four.

In the United Kingdom, the show aired every week on [[Channel 4]] without a break, with the result that the last four or five episodes of the early seasons screened in the UK before the US.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.zocalo.nildram.co.uk/UKAirDates.html|title=Original UK airdates|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070911120237/http://www.zocalo.nildram.co.uk/UKAirDates.html|archivedate=September 11, 2007|accessdate=August 22, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Babylon 5'' was one of the better-rated US television shows on Channel 4,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=16068|title=JMS: UK C4 ratings|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=April 3, 1995|website=JMSNews|language=en|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; and achieved high audience [[Appreciation Index]]es, with the season 4 episode [[Endgame (Babylon 5)|&quot;Endgame]]&quot; achieving the rare feat of beating the prime-time soap operas for first position.&lt;ref&gt;''[[TV Zone]]'', January 1998 issue&lt;/ref&gt;

Straczynski stated that PTEN only required the show to be profitable for the network to remain in production, and said that while this was the case for its first four seasons, on paper it was always losing money; Straczynski estimated in 2019 that the show ended about {{USD|30 million}} in the red, and stated that he had never made any profits on ''Babylon 5''.&lt;ref name=&quot;newsarama 2019&quot; /&gt; The entire series cost an estimated $90 million for 110 episodes.&lt;ref name=&quot;aicn1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aintitcool.com/display.cgi?id=23963|title=Babylon 5 Returns|author=Merrick|date=July 24, 2006|work=[[Ain't It Cool News]]|publisher=Harry Knowles|location=Austin, Texas 78767-1641|accessdate=October 24, 2009|quote=Anyway, they asked if I wanted to do a feature film but I declined mainly because I can't yet picture structuring a B5 movie as long as [Andreas Katsulas] and [Richard Biggs] insist on staying dead.}}&lt;!-- original {{cite web |title=Babylon 5 Returns |author= |date=July 24, 2006 |url=http://www.aintitcool.com/display.cgi?id=23963 |publisher=[[Ain't It Cool News]] |accessdate=November 6, 2007}} --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

''Babylon 5'' successfully completed its five-year story arc on November 25, 1998, after five seasons and 109 aired episodes, when TNT aired the 110th ([[epilogue]]) episode &quot;[[Sleeping in Light]],&quot; which had been filmed as the Season finale 4 when ''Babylon 5'' was under threat of ending production at that point. After a fifth season was assured, a new Season 4 finale was used so that &quot;[[Sleeping in Light]]&quot; could remain as the series finale. As of 2018, Babylon 5 reruns have become part of the programming for the [[Comet (TV network)|Comet Channel]].

== Themes ==
Throughout its run, ''Babylon 5'' found ways to portray [[theme (literature)|themes]] relevant to modern and historical social issues. It marked several firsts in television science fiction, such as the exploration of the political and social landscapes of the first human colonies, their interactions with Earth, and the underlying tensions.&lt;ref name=&quot;mars&quot;/&gt; ''Babylon 5'' was also one of the first television science fiction shows to [[wikt:denotative|denotatively]] refer to a [[same-sex relationship]].&lt;ref name=&quot;dyke1&quot;&gt;{{cite web&lt;!-- The article date was taken from the Internet Archive copy &quot;Page info.&quot; The author was taken from the IA copy &quot;Page source.&quot; --&gt;|url=http://www.dykesvision.com/en/interviews/lesbian-babylon5.html|title=First Lesbians in Space|author=&quot;Ivanova&quot;, DykesVision Staff|date=January 19, 2004|work=DykesVision|location=Germany|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20041011155941/http://dykesvision.com/en/interviews/lesbian-babylon5.html|archivedate=October 11, 2004|accessdate=October 18, 2009|quote=I think I...loved Talia.}}&lt;!-- Original web cite {{cite web|url=http://www.dykesvision.com/en/interviews/lesbian-babylon5.html |title=First Lesbians in Space |publisher=dykesvision.com |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20041011000000/http://www.dykesvision.com/en/interviews/lesbian-babylon5.html |archivedate=October 11, 2004 }} --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.webpan.com/dsinclair/tng.html|title=Gay, Lesbian &amp; Bisexual Star Trek|website=Webpan|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20020614005253/http://www.webpan.com/dsinclair/tng.html|archive-date=June 14, 2002|url-status=dead|access-date=February 24, 2019|quote=When Babylon 5 revealed two of its lead characters to be bisexual or lesbian in its second season, and established that gay marriage is legally recognized, and generally accepted, on Earth in the 23rd century, there was no uproar, no drop in ratings, and no boycotts.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the show, [[sexual orientation]] is as much of an issue as &quot;being left-handed or right-handed&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=19037|title=Re: BABYLON 5 To Include Gay/B|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=February 23, 1994|website=JMSNews|language=en|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Unrequited love]] is explored as a source of pain for the characters, though not all the relationships end unhappily.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.space.com/sciencefiction/tv/soap_opera_babylon_000317.html|title=Soap Opera 'Babylon' - B5 and the Soaps|last=Parks|first=Jo-Ann|date=March 17, 2000|website=SPACE|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20001216112200/http://www.space.com/sciencefiction/tv/soap_opera_babylon_000317.html|archive-date=December 16, 2000|url-status=dead|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Order vs. chaos; authoritarianism vs. free will ===
{{Quote box |quote=Neither the Vorlons nor the Shadows saw themselves as conquerors or adversaries. Both believed they were doing what was right for us. And like any possessive parent, they'll keep on believing that until the kid is strong enough to stand up and say, 'No, this is what '''''I''''' want.' |source=—[[J. Michael Straczynski]], 1997&lt;ref name=&quot;js&quot;/&gt; |align=right |width=40% |salign=right}}

The clash between order and chaos, and the people caught in between, plays an important role in ''Babylon 5''. The conflict between two unimaginably powerful older races, the [[Vorlon]]s and the [[Shadow (Babylon 5)|Shadows]], is represented as a battle between competing ideologies, each seeking to turn the humans and the other younger races to their beliefs. The Vorlons represent an [[authoritarian]] philosophy of unquestioning obedience. Vorlon characters frequently ask, &quot;who are you?&quot; focusing on identity as a catalyst for shaping personal goals;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jmsnews.com/Messages/Thread?threadid=_%3E%3EZHD%20-%20Thoughts%3C%3C&amp;messageid=10775|title=ZHD – Thoughts|author=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=May 11, 1996|website=JMSNews|accessdate=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;signs&quot;/&gt; the intention is not to solicit a correct answer, but to &quot;tear down the artifices we construct around ourselves until we're left facing ourselves, not our roles.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.fsl.cs.sunysb.edu/pipermail/b5jms/1995-October/000003.html|title=JMS on Compuserve: October 1, 1995|last=Poster|first=B5JMS|date=October 9, 1995|website=|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Shadows represent another [[authoritarian]] philosophy cloaked in a disguise of evolution through fire, of fomenting conflict in order to promote evolutionary progress.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=7430|title=Re: Attn JMS: Shadows and Hegel?|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=April 28, 1998|website=JMSNews|language=en|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Characters affiliated with the Shadows repeatedly ask, &quot;what do you want?&quot; emphasising personal desire and ambition, using it to shape identity,&lt;ref name=&quot;signs&quot;/&gt; encouraging conflict between groups who choose to serve their own glory or profit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=10546|title=Questioning...|author=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=November 23, 1996|website=JMSNews|accessdate=September 2, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; The representation of order and chaos was informed by the [[Babylonian mythology|Babylonian myth]] that the universe was born in the conflict between both. The climax of this conflict comes with the younger races' exposing of the Vorlons' and the Shadows' &quot;true faces&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;js&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=JMS Speaks |author=Straczynski, J. Michael|url=http://www.midwinter.com/lurk/guide/072.html#JS |publisher= Lurker's Guide to Babylon 5 |accessdate=November 7, 2007 |quote=The notion of the Vorlons and Shadows representing Order and Chaos goes back to the Babylonian creation myths, that the universe was born in the conflict between order and chaos, hence part of the reason I decided to name this show after Babylon. That's called *research*. It informs the show, but it is not the show.| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20071013085744/http://midwinter.com/lurk/guide/072.html| archivedate= October 13, 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the rejection of both philosophies,&lt;ref name=&quot;signs&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.space.com/sciencefiction/tv/babylon_5_signs_portents_001013.html|title=A B5 Milestone Remembered|author=O'Callaghan|first=Scott|date=October 13, 2000|work=Space.com|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20001027204131/http://www.space.com/sciencefiction/tv/babylon_5_signs_portents_001013.html|archive-date=October 27, 2000|url-status=dead|accessdate=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; heralding the dawn of a new age without their interference.

The notion that the war was about &quot;killing your parents&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;js&quot;/&gt; is echoed in the portrayal of the civil war between the human colonies and Earth. Deliberately dealing in historical and political metaphor, with particular emphasis upon [[McCarthyism]] and the [[House Un-American Activities Committee|HUAC]],&lt;ref name=&quot;commie&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=14128|title=Re:nightwatch|author=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=February 28, 1996|website=|publisher=Midnight Design Productions, LLC|accessdate=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Earth Alliance (Babylon 5)|Earth Alliance]] becomes increasingly authoritarian, eventually sliding into a dictatorship. The show examines the impositions on [[civil liberties]] under the pretext of greater defense against outside threats which aid its rise, and the self-delusion of a populace which believes its moral superiority will never allow a dictatorship to come to power, until it is too late.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jmsnews.com/Messages/Message?id=13917|title=Point of No Return|author=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=March 7, 1996|website=|publisher=Midnight Design Productions, LLC|accessdate=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The successful rebellion led by the Babylon 5 station results in the restoration of a democratic government and true autonomy for Mars and the colonies.&lt;ref&gt;Episode 4x21, &quot;[[Rising Star (Babylon 5)|Rising Star]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

=== War and peace ===
{{Quote box |quote=What interests me, what I wanted to do with making this show, was in large measure to examine the issues and emotions and events that precede a war, precipitate a war, the effects of the war itself, the end of the war and the aftermath of the war. The war is hardware; the people are at the center of the story. |width=40% |source=—J. Michael Straczynski, 1997&lt;ref name=&quot;jswar&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Great Job (as usual) |last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=February 2, 1997 |url=http://www.jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=9894 |publisher=Midnight Design Productions, LLC|accessdate=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; |align=right |salign=right}}The ''Babylon 5'' universe deals with numerous armed conflicts which range on an interstellar scale. The story begins in the aftermath of a war which brought the human race to the brink of extinction, caused by a misunderstanding during a [[first contact (science fiction)|first contact]].&lt;ref name=&quot;january&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Since it is now January 1st, time... |author=Straczynski, J. Michael|date=December 31, 1991 |url=http://www.jmsnews.com/msg.aspx?id=1-7707 |publisher=Midnight Design Productions, LLC|accessdate=November 5, 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20071010152146/http://www.jmsnews.com/msg.aspx?id=1-7707| archivedate= October 10, 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Babylon 5 is built to foster peace through diplomacy, described as the &quot;last, best hope for peace&quot; in the opening credits monologue during its first three seasons. Wars between separate alien civilizations are featured. The conflict between the [[Narn]] and the [[Centauri (Babylon 5)|Centauri]] is followed from its beginnings as a minor territorial dispute amplified by historical animosity, through to its end, in which [[weapons of mass destruction]] are employed to subjugate and enslave a planet. The war is an attempt to portray a more sobering kind of conflict than usually seen on science fiction television. Informed by the events of the first [[Gulf War]], the [[Cuban Missile Crisis]] and the [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] [[Prague Spring#Invasion|invasion of Prague]], the intent was to recreate these moments when &quot;the world held its breath&quot; and the emotional core of the conflict was the disbelief that the situation could have occurred at all, and the desperation to find a way to bring it to an end.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=16470|title=Coming of Shadows *SPOILERS*|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=February 6, 1995|website=JMSNews|language=en|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the start of the third season, the opening monologue had changed to say that the hope for peace had &quot;failed&quot; and the Babylon 5 station had become the &quot;last, best hope for victory&quot;, indicating that while peace is ostensibly a laudable goal, it can also mean a capitulation to an enemy intent on committing horrendous acts and that &quot;peace is a byproduct of victory against those who do not want peace.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=7354|title=Season 3 voiceover|author=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=May 17, 1998|website=JMSNews|publisher=Midnight Design Productions, LLC|accessdate=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Shadow War also features prominently in the show, wherein the Shadows work to instigate conflict between other races to promote technological and cultural advancement, opposed by the Vorlons who are attempting to impose their own authoritarian philosophy of obedience. The gradual discovery of the scheme and the rebellion against it underpin the first three seasons,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=14592|title=&lt;Voices&gt;|author=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=February 4, 1996|website=JMSNews|publisher=Midnight Design Productions, LLC|accessdate=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; but also as a wider metaphor for competing forces of order and chaos. In that respect, Straczynski stated he presented Earth's descent into a dictatorship as its own &quot;shadow war&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;home&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=14458|title=Re: Instant Gratification|author=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=February 13, 1996|website=JMSNews|publisher=Midnight Design Productions, LLC|accessdate=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ending the Shadow War before the conclusion of the series, the show was able to more fully explore its aftermath, and it is this &quot;war at home&quot; which forms the bulk of the remaining two seasons. The struggle for independence between [[Mars]] and Earth culminates with a civil war between the human colonies (led by the Babylon 5 station) and the home planet. Choosing Mars as both the spark for the civil war, and the staging ground for its dramatic conclusion, enabled the viewer to understand the conflict more fully than had it involved an anonymous colony orbiting a distant star.&lt;ref name=&quot;mars&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.space.com/sciencefiction/tv/mars_babylon5_991203.html|title=Babylon 5 and the Red Planet|author=Aylott|first=Chris|date=December 3, 1999|website=SPACE|publisher=Space.com|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20010211102406/http://www.space.com/sciencefiction/tv/mars_babylon5_991203.html|archive-date=February 11, 2001|url-status=dead|accessdate=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The conflict, and the reasons behind it, were informed by Nazism, McCarthyism and the breakup of [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]],&lt;ref name=&quot;commie&quot;/&gt; and the destruction of the state also served as partial inspiration for the Minbari civil war.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=13899|title=The Future of B5|author=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=March 9, 1996|website=JMSNews|publisher=Midnight Design Productions, LLC|accessdate=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jmsnews.com/msg.aspx?id=1-6010|title=Richard Hatch|author=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=August 24, 1996|website=JMSNews|publisher=Midnight Design Productions, LLC|accessdate=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The post-war landscape has its roots in the [[Reconstruction era of the United States|Reconstruction]]. The attempt to resolve the [[issues of the American Civil War]] after the conflict had ended, and this struggle for survival in a changed world was also informed by works such as ''[[Alas, Babylon]]'', a novel dealing with the after-effects of a [[nuclear warfare|nuclear war]] on a small American town.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=9783|title=Re: ATTN JMS: Comparison to &quot;Lucifer's Hammer&quot;|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=February 14, 1997|website=JMSNews|language=en|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The show expresses that the end of these wars is not an end to war itself. Events shown hundreds of years into the show's future tell of wars which will once again bring the human race to the edge of annihilation, demonstrating that humanity will not change, and the best that can be hoped for after it falls is that it climbs a little higher each time, until it can one day &quot;take [its] place among the stars, teaching those who follow.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=8433|title=Re: to JMS: deconstruction|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=October 30, 1997|website=JMSNews|language=en|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Religion ===
{{Quote box
| quote = If you look at the long history of human society, religion – whether you describe that as organized, disorganized, or the various degrees of accepted superstition – has always been present. And it will be present 200 years from now... To totally ignore that part of the human equation would be as false and wrong-headed as ignoring the fact that people get mad, or passionate, or strive for better lives.
| source = —J. Michael Straczynski,  1993&lt;ref name=&quot;religion1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=20161 |title=Religion in B5 |last=Straczynski |first=J. Michael |date=September 9, 1993
 |website=JMSNews |access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| align = right
| width = 45em
| salign = right
}}
Many of Earth's contemporary religions are shown to still exist, with the main human characters often having religious convictions. Among those specifically identified are the [[Roman Catholicism|Roman Catholic]] branch of [[Christianity]] (including the [[Society of Jesus|Jesuits]]), [[Judaism]], and the fictional Foundationism (which developed after first contact with alien races).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=16598|title=Christianity in 23rd century|author=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=January 23, 1995|website=JMSNews|publisher=Midnight Design Productions, LLC|accessdate=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Alien beliefs in the show range from the [[Centauri (Babylon 5)|Centauri]]'s [[Bacchanalia]]n-influenced religions,&lt;ref name=&quot;religion1&quot;/&gt; of which there are up to seventy different denominations,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jmsnews.com/msg.aspx?id=1-15929|title=Re:Franklin and Ivanova|author=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=December 11, 1995|website=JMSNews|publisher=Midnight Design Productions, LLC|accessdate=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; to the more [[pantheism|pantheistic]] as with the [[Narn]] and [[Minbari]] religions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.philjohn.com/rev_tv/pjkdt_b52.html#Myths07 |title=Myths and Fiction |author=Philipp Kneis |date=April 17, 1999 |accessdate=December 13, 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20071217192440/http://www.philjohn.com/rev_tv/pjkdt_b52.html#Myths07| archivedate= December 17, 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the show's third season, a community of [[Cistercians|Cistercian monks]] takes up residence on the Babylon 5 station, in order to learn what other races call God,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=14871|title=9 Billion Names of God and Bro|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=November 22, 1995|website=JMSNews|language=en|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; and to come to a better understanding of the different religions through study at close quarters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=13986|title=Re:Messages from Earth|author=Straczynski, J. Michael|first=J. Michael|date=March 4, 1996|website=JMSNews|publisher=Midnight Design Productions, LLC|accessdate=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

References to both human and alien religion is often subtle and brief, but can also form the main theme of an episode.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite newsgroup |title=Pilot Question? Religion? |author=Straczynski, J. Michael|date=December 6, 1993 |newsgroup=rec.arts.sf.tv.babylon5.moderated |url=http://www.jmsnews.com/msg.aspx?id=1-15341 |accessdate=November 23, 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20071028180104/http://www.jmsnews.com/msg.aspx?id=1-15341| archivedate= October 28, 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first season episode &quot;[[The Parliament of Dreams]]&quot; is a conventional &quot;showcase&quot; for religion, in which each species on the Babylon 5 station has an opportunity to demonstrate its beliefs (humanity's are presented as being numerous and varied),&lt;ref name=&quot;religion1&quot;/&gt; while &quot;[[Passing Through Gethsemane]]&quot; focuses on a specific position of Roman Catholic beliefs,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.space.com/sciencefiction/tv/babylon_5_305_001208.html|title=Babylon 5 – 'Voices of Authority'|author=Tom Janulewicz|date=December 8, 2000|work=Space.com|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20010211100756/http://www.space.com/sciencefiction/tv/babylon_5_305_001208.html|archive-date=February 11, 2001|url-status=dead|accessdate=February 23, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as concepts of justice, vengeance, and biblical forgiveness.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.space.com/sciencefiction/tv/babylon_5_304_001207.html|title=Babylon 5 – 'Passing Through Gethsemane'|author=Janulewicz|first=Tom|date=December 7, 2000|work=Space.com|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20010211102400/http://www.space.com/sciencefiction/tv/babylon_5_304_001207.html|archive-date=February 11, 2001|url-status=dead|accessdate=February 23, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other treatments have been more contentious, such as the [[David Gerrold]]-scripted &quot;[[Believers (Babylon 5)|Believers]]&quot;, in which alien parents would rather see their son die than undergo a life-saving operation because their religious beliefs forbid it.&lt;ref name=&quot;religion1&quot;/&gt;

When religion is an integral part of an episode, various characters express differing view points. In the episode &quot;[[Soul Hunter (Babylon 5)|Soul Hunter]]&quot;, where the concept of an [[Soul (spirit)|immortal soul]] is touched upon, and whether after death it is destroyed, reincarnated, or simply does not exist. The character arguing the latter, [[Stephen Franklin (Babylon 5)|Doctor Stephen Franklin]], often appears in the more spiritual storylines as his scientific rationality is used to create dramatic conflict. Undercurrents of religions such as Buddhism have been viewed by some in various episode scripts,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.hundredmountain.com/Pages/foundobjects_pages/sum01_babylon5.html |title=Tuning in to some Buddhist undercurrents in the alternate universe of TV's &quot;Babylon 5&quot; |publisher=Hundred Mountain |date=Summer 2001 |accessdate=December 13, 2007 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070902174919/http://www.hundredmountain.com/Pages/foundobjects_pages/sum01_babylon5.html |archivedate=September 2, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and while identifying himself as an [[atheist]],&lt;ref name=&quot;religion1&quot; /&gt; Straczynski believes that passages of dialog can take on distinct meanings to viewers of differing faiths, and that the show ultimately expresses ideas which cross religious boundaries.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=4492|title=Re: Attn JMS: Southern Baptists and B5 -- Was: S2 commentary comment|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=June 21, 2003|website=JMSNews|language=en|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Addiction ===
Substance abuse and its impact on human personalities also features in the ''Babylon 5'' storyline. Garibaldi is a relapsing-remitting alcoholic, who practices complete [[abstinence]] throughout most of the series until the [[Phoenix Rising (Babylon 5)|middle of season five]], only recovering at the end of the season. [[Zack Allan]], his eventual replacement as chief of security, was given a second chance by Garibaldi after overcoming his own addiction to an unspecified drug. Dr. [[Stephen Franklin (Babylon 5)|Stephen Franklin]] develops an addiction to injectable [[stimulant]] drugs while trying to cope with the chronic stress and work overload in Medlab, and takes a leave of absence from his position to recover. Executive Officer [[Susan Ivanova]] mentions that her father became an alcoholic after her mother's suicide. Captain [[Elizabeth Lochley]] tells Garibaldi that her father was an alcoholic, and that she is a recovering alcoholic herself.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Recap/BabylonFiveS05E19TheWheelOfFire|title=Babylon Five S 05 E 19 The Wheel Of Fire / Recap|last=|first=|date=|website=TV Tropes|access-date=February 19, 2019|quote=...children of alcoholics usually wind up one of two ways, either they try to help everybody else because they couldn't help themselves, or they become alcoholics. I couldn't stop what was happening to my father, so I became the very thing I hated.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Influences ==

''Babylon 5'' draws upon a number of cultural, historical, political and religious influences to inform and illustrate its characters and storylines. Straczynski has stated that there was no intent to wholly represent any particular period of history or preceding work of fiction, but has acknowledged their influence on the series, insamuch as it uses similar well established storytelling structures, such as the [[Hero's journey|Hero's Journey]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.midwinter.com/lurk/find/Usenet/jms95-03-usenet/142.html|title=Usenet post by JMS|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=March 19, 1995|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20021102170520/http://www.midwinter.com/lurk/find/Usenet/jms95-03-usenet/142.html|archive-date=November 2, 2002|url-status=|access-date=February 8, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.fsl.cs.sunysb.edu/pipermail/b5jms/1995-December/000212.html|title=JMS conference on Compuserve: full logged text|last=|first=|date=December 3, 1995|access-date=February 8, 2019|quote=I knew that the best series set up where the stories come to you, in a police station or a hospital or a law office, and decided in an SF environment a space station would work well for that...added the backdrop of myth and archetype, constructed a Hero's Journey, and took it from there.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While the series is replete with elements which some argue are intended to invoke other works of fiction, myth or legend, there are a number of specific literary references. Several episodes take their titles from Shakespearean monologues,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.midwinter.com/lurk/guide/091.html|title=Guide Page: &quot;The Paragon of Animals&quot;|last=|first=|date=July 13, 2004|website=The Lurker's Guide to Babylon 5|access-date=February 8, 2019|quote=The title is from Shakespeare's &quot;Hamlet,&quot; specifically Hamlet's [[What a piece of work is a man]] speech in act 2, scene 2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.midwinter.com/lurk/guide/021.html|title=Guide Page: &quot;The Quality of Mercy&quot;|last=|first=|date=July 13, 2004|website=The Lurker's Guide to Babylon 5|access-date=February 8, 2019|quote=&quot;The Quality of Mercy&quot; title is drawn from the same source as Compton's book, Shakespeare.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and at least one character quotes Shakespeare directly.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.midwinter.com/lurk/guide/004.html|title=Guide Page: Infection|last=|first=|date=November 5, 1999|website=The Lurker's Guide to Babylon 5|access-date=February 8, 2019|quote=&quot;How sharper than a serpent's tooth.&quot; (His reply to Garibaldi's joking guess that Sinclair's interview would get him shipped off the station and himself promoted into Sinclair's position.) This is a quote from Shakespeare (King Lear.)}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Psi-Cop [[Alfred Bester (Babylon 5)|Alfred Bester]] was named after the [[Alfred Bester|science fiction author of the same name]], as his work influenced the autocratic [[Psi Corps]] organisation the character represents.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.midwinter.com/lurk/making/literary.html|title=Babylon 5 Behind the Scenes: Literary and Historical References|last=|first=|date=|website=www.midwinter.com|access-date=February 2, 2019|quote=The antagonist in &quot;Mind War&quot; was named after Alfred Bester, author of &quot;The Demolished Man,&quot; a classic SF work about telepathy. The novel also featured a telepaths' guild similar in many ways to B5's Psi Corps.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are a number of references to the [[legend of King Arthur]], with ships named ''Excalibur'' appearing in the main series and the [[Crusade (TV series)|''Crusade'']] spin-off, and a character in &quot;[[A Late Delivery from Avalon]]&quot; claiming to possess the [[Excalibur|sword]] itself. Straczynski links the incident which sparked the Earth-Minbari war, in which actions are misinterpreted during a tense situation, to a sequence in ''[[Le Morte d'Arthur]]'', in which a standoff between two armies turns violent when innocent actions are misinterpreted as hostile.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.midwinter.com/lurk/guide/031.html|title=Guide Page: &quot;The Coming of Shadows&quot;|last=|first=|date=July 13, 2004|website=The Lurker's Guide to Babylon 5|access-date=February 8, 2019|quote=The G'Kar-Emperor thread was similar to the King Arthur legend: Arthur's and Mordred's armies are poised for battle but make one last attempt to negotiate, but a soldier raises his sword to kill a snake and everyone attacks. There's another applicable metaphor for the sword story; you'll see it a little later [in season 3].}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The series also references contemporary and ancient history. The [[Centauri (Babylon 5)|Centauri]] are in part modelled on the Roman empire.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.smashwords.com/extreader/read/237868/1/babylon-5-asked-answered-centauri-excerpt-b5-creator-j-micha|title=Babylon 5 Asked &amp; Answered: B5 Creator J. Michael Straczynski Answers 5,296 Questions About Babylon 5 &amp; Beyond|last=|first=|date=|website=www.smashwords.com|access-date=February 7, 2019|quote=&quot;to some extent the Roman civilization is one of the sources for constructing the Centauri&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; Emperor [[Cartagia]] believes himself to be a god, a deliberate reference to [[Caligula]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Killick&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=B5: No Surrender, No Retreat|last=Killick|first=Jane|publisher=Del Rey|year=1998|isbn=978-0345424501|location=|pages=[https://archive.org/details/nosurrendernoret00kill/page/36 36]|quote=(Quoting J. Michael Straczynski) Caligula is probably the most obvious comparison, hence why I had that name reflect that sound a little bit. I wanted someone who you would be very much in fear of, not because he was rampaging around screaming all the time, but because he was completely and totally arbitrary.|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/nosurrendernoret00kill/page/36}}&lt;/ref&gt; His eventual assassination leads to the ascension of Londo and eventually Vir, both unlikely candidates for the throne, similar to [[Claudius]]' improbable ascension after Caligula was assassinated.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.sf-foundation.org/publications/academictrack/keen.php|title=I, Cartagia: a mad emperor in Babylon 5 and his historical antecedents|last=Keen|first=Tony|date=2007|website=The Science Fiction Foundation|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070316172902/http://www.sf-foundation.org/publications/academictrack/keen.php|archive-date=March 16, 2007|access-date=February 8, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The series also references the novel [[I, Claudius]] by [[Robert Graves]] when Cartagia jokes that he has cured a man of his cough after having him beheaded, something also done by Caligula.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.sf-foundation.org/publications/essays/keen.html|title=I, Cartagia: a mad emperor in Babylon 5 and his historical antecedents {{!}} The Science Fiction Foundation|last=|first=|date=|website=www.sf-foundation.org|access-date=February 7, 2019|quote=...there is a clear reference to I, Claudius included in Babylon 5. In 'Falling Towards Apotheosis', Cartagia introduces Mollari to his secret 'council' of the severed heads of senior figures he has had executed. He mentions that one was always coughing, but that he has now cured this (by cutting his head off). This is a clear reference to a scene in I, Claudius, in the episode 'Zeus, by Jove'. Gemellus, co-heir of the previous emperor Tiberius and therefore rival of Caligula, has a persistent cough. Caligula has him executed, and when his severed head is brought into his presence, he tells Claudius &quot;I cured his cough.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In more recent historical references, in the episode &quot;[[In the Shadow of Z'ha'dum|In the Shadow of Z'ha'dhum]],&quot; Sheridan ponders [[Winston Churchill|Winston Churchill's]] [[Coventry Blitz#Coventry and Ultra|Coventry dilemma]], of whether or not to act on covertly gathered intelligence during a war. Lives would be saved, but at the risk of revealing to the enemy that their intentions are known, which may be far more damaging in the long term. The swearing in of Vice President Morgan Clark invokes the [[John F. Kennedy assassination|assassination of President John F. Kennedy]], being deliberately staged to mirror the scene aboard [[Air Force One]] when [[First inauguration of Lyndon B. Johnson|Lyndon Johnson was sworn in as President]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.midwinter.com/lurk/guide/022.html|title=Guide Page: &quot;Chrysalis&quot;|last=|first=|date=July 13, 2004|website=The Lurker's Guide to Babylon 5|access-date=February 8, 2019|quote=[Straczynski] I gave very particular instructions to re-create the staging of the photograph in which Lyndon Johnson takes over from JFK after the assassination. The same layout, posture, background, and so on. We even had a photo on set for reference. The creepy thing is that the day we shot the scene was the anniversary of the day it actually took place; very weird atmosphere on set that day.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although Straczynski is a professed [[Atheism|atheist]], ''Babylon 5'' refers to the Christian faith in a number of places. Several episodes have titles which refer to the Christian faith, such as &quot;[[Passing Through Gethsemane]]&quot;, &quot;[[A Voice in the Wilderness (Babylon 5)|A Voice in the Wilderness]],&quot; and &quot;[[And the Rock Cried Out, No Hiding Place]],&quot; the latter being a line from the [[Gospel music|gospel song]] &quot;There's no Hiding Place Down Here.&quot;  The monks led by [[Brother Theo]] who, in the episode &quot;[[Convictions (Babylon 5)|Convictions]],&quot; take up residence on Babylon 5, belong to the [[Order of Preachers|Dominican Order]], a Roman Catholic mendicant  Order.

== Use of the Internet ==
{{Main|Babylon 5's use of the Internet}}
The show employed Internet marketing to create a buzz among online readers far in advance of the airing of the pilot episode,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=20359|title=Passage through jumpgates|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=July 9, 1993|website=JMSNews|language=en|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; with Straczynski participating in online communities on [[USENET]] (in the [[rec.arts.sf.tv.babylon5.moderated]] newsgroup), and the [[GEnie]] and [[CompuServe]] systems before the Web came together as it exists today. The station's location, in &quot;grid epsilon&quot; at coordinates of 470/18/22, was a reference to [[GEnie]] (&quot;grid epsilon&quot; = &quot;GE&quot;)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.worldsofjms.com/b5/gei.htm|title=Babylon 5 Grid Epsilon Irregulars|last=|first=|date=|website=Worlds of JMS|access-date=February 19, 2019|quote=In recognition of their support, JMS placed the Babylon 5 station in Grid Epsilon -- taking the &quot;GE&quot; from GEnie.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the original forum's address on the system's bulletin boards (page 470, category 18, topic 22).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.midwinter.com/lurk/resources/fans.html#effect|title=Babylon 5 Resources: Fans|last=|first=|date=|website=The Lurker's Guide to Babylon 5|access-date=February 19, 2019|quote=The location of Babylon 5 is at Grid Epsilon 470,18,22 which corresponds to the original location of the Babylon 5 topic on GEnie (Page 470, CAT 18, Topic 22).}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Also during this time, [[Warner Bros.]] executive Jim Moloshok created and distributed electronic [[trading cards]] to help advertise the series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=19386|title=Digital Cards and so forth|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=January 19, 1994|website=JMSNews|accessdate=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1995, Warner Bros. started the Official ''Babylon 5'' Website on the now defunct [[Pathfinder.com|Pathfinder]] portal. In September 1995, they hired series fan [[Troy Rutter]] to take over the site and move it to its own domain name, and to oversee the ''Keyword B5'' area on [[AOL|America Online]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://babylonprojectpodcast.wordpress.com/2014/10/07/bps-002-troy-rutter-interview/|title=BPS-002 Troy Rutter Interview|date=October 7, 2014|website=The Babylon Project Podcast|language=en|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Reception ==
In 2004 and 2007, [[TV Guide]] ranked ''Babylon 5'' #13 and #16 on its list of the top cult shows  ever.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=25 Top Cult Shows Ever!|work=TV Guide |date=May 30, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.tvguide.com/news/top-cult-shows-40239/|title=TV Guide Names the Top Cult Shows Ever|publisher=TVGuide.com|date=June 29, 2007|accessdate=June 21, 2019
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Awards ===
Awards presented to ''Babylon 5'' include:
* [[Primetime Emmy Award|Emmy Award]]: ''[[Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Special Visual Effects|Outstanding Individual Achievement in Special Visual Effects]]'', 1993 (''[[Babylon 5: The Gathering|The Gathering]]'')&lt;ref name=&quot;Emmy Awards &amp; Nominations&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.emmys.com/shows/babylon-5|title=Babylon 5|last=|first=|date=|website=Television Academy|accessdate=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Emmy Award: ''Outstanding Individual Achievement in Hairstyling for a Series '', 1994 (episode, &quot;[[The Parliament of Dreams]]&quot;)&lt;ref name=&quot;Emmy Awards &amp; Nominations&quot;/&gt;
* [[Hugo Award]]: ''[[Hugo Award for Best Dramatic Presentation|Best Dramatic Presentation]]'', 1996 (episode, &quot;[[The Coming of Shadows]]&quot;)&lt;ref name=&quot;Hugo1&quot;/&gt;
* Hugo Award: ''Best Dramatic Presentation'', 1997 (episode, &quot;[[Severed Dreams]]&quot;)&lt;ref name=&quot;Hugo2&quot;/&gt;
* [[Saturn Award]]: ''[[Saturn Award for Best Syndicated/Cable Television Series|Best Syndicated/Cable Television Series]]'', 1998&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Listing of Past Saturn Awards |url=http://www.saturnawards.org/past.html |accessdate=June 9, 2006 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060507111522/http://saturnawards.org/past.html |archivedate=May 7, 2006 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Space Frontier Foundation Award: ''Vision of the Future'', 1994
* Space Frontier Foundation Award: ''Vision of the Future'', 1996
* E Pluribus Unum Award: (Presented By American Cinema Association), 1997&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title= Second E Pluribus Unum Awards (1997)| url= http://www.cinemafoundation.com/about/about_the_acf_96_2000.html| accessdate= June 9, 2006| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20060615061324/http://cinemafoundation.com/about/about_the_acf_96_2000.html| archivedate= June 15, 2006| url-status= dead| df= mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Nominated Awards include:
* Emmy Award: ''Outstanding Individual Achievement in Makeup for a Series'', 1995 (episode, &quot;[[Acts of Sacrifice]]&quot;)&lt;ref name=&quot;Emmy Awards &amp; Nominations&quot;/&gt;
* Emmy Award: ''Outstanding Individual Achievement in Hairstyling for a Series'', 1995 (episode, &quot;[[The Geometry of Shadows]]&quot;)
* Emmy Award: ''Outstanding Individual Achievement in Cinematography for a Series'', 1995 (episode, &quot;The Geometry Of Shadows&quot;)
* Emmy Award: ''Outstanding Cinematography for a Series'', 1996
* Emmy Award: ''Outstanding Makeup for a Series'', 1997 (episode, &quot;[[The Summoning (Babylon 5)|The Summoning]]&quot;)
* Emmy Award: ''Outstanding Makeup for a Series'', 1998 (television movie, ''[[Babylon 5: In the Beginning|In The Beginning]]'')

=== ''Star Trek: Deep Space Nine'' and Paramount plagiarism controversy ===
Straczynski indicated that [[Paramount Television]] was aware of his concept as early as 1989,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=18023|title=Misinformed|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=December 7, 1994|website=|publisher=Midnight Design Productions, LLC|accessdate=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; when he attempted to sell the show to the studio, and provided them with the series [[Bible (writing)|bible]], pilot script, artwork, lengthy character background histories, and plot synopses for 22 &quot;or so planned episodes taken from the overall course of the planned series&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=14711|title=Actually, we've already *had* ST...|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=January 13, 1996|website=JMSNews|publisher=Midnight Design Productions, LLC|accessdate=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dvdverdict.com/reviews/ds9season1.php|title=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine: Season One (review)|authors=Sylvain, Nicholas, Judge (Retired)|date=April 8, 2003|publisher=Mike Jackson/DVD Verdict|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20031011154632/http://www.dvdverdict.com/reviews/ds9season1.php|archive-date=October 11, 2003|url-status=dead|access-date=February 26, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Paramount declined to produce ''Babylon 5'', but later announced ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]'' was in development, two months after Warner Bros. announced its plans for ''Babylon 5''. Unlike previous ''Star Trek'' shows, ''Deep Space Nine'' was based on a space station, and had themes similar to those of ''Babylon 5'', which drew some to compare it with ''Babylon 5''.  Straczynski stated that, even though he was confident that ''Deep Space Nine'' producer/creators [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]] had not seen this material, he suspected that Paramount executives used his bible and scripts to steer development of ''Deep Space Nine''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=21322|title=nic, you persist in this notion...|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=February 4, 1992|website=JMSNews|publisher=Midnight Design Productions, LLC|accessdate=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=8676|title=Grand Theft, drama!|last=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=September 15, 1997|website=JMSNews|publisher=Midnight Design Productions, LLC|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GEnie&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mirrors.ntua.gr/b5/GEnie/jms92-02|title=B5 information from GEnie|last=Michael Straczynski|first=J.|date=|website=|publisher=National Technical University of Athens|accessdate=6 July 2016|quote=If there is any (to use your term) winking and nudging going on, it's on the level of 'Okay, YOU (Paramount) know what happened, and *I* know what happened, but let's try to be grownup about it for now,' though I must say that the shapechanging thing nearly tipped me back over the edge again. If there are no more major similarities that crop up in the next few weeks or months, with luck we can continue that way.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Straczynski and Warner did not file suit against Paramount, largely because he believed it would negatively affect both TV series. He argued the same when confronted by claims that the lack of legal action was proof that his allegation was unfounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;GEnie&quot;/&gt;

===Influence and legacy===
Generally viewed as having &quot;launched the new era of television CGI visual effects&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=NewTek Honors Visual Effects Artists at the Academy of Television Arts and Sciences|author=Donetta Colboch |date=October 24, 2011 |url=http://www.cgw.com/Press-Center/News/2011/NewTek-Honors-Visual-Effects-Artists-at-the-Acad.aspx|publisher=CG World (from press release) |accessdate=December 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Babylon 5'' received multiple awards during its initial run, including two consecutive Hugo Awards for [[Hugo Award for Best Dramatic Presentation|best dramatic presentation]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Hugo1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=List of Hugo Award Winners (1996)|url=http://www.nesfa.org/data/LL/Hugos/hugos1996.html|publisher=[[New England Science Fiction Association]]|accessdate=June 9, 2006|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140102104246/http://www.nesfa.org/data/LL/Hugos/hugos1996.html|archive-date=January 2, 2014|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hugo2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=List of Hugo Award Winners (1997)|url=http://www.nesfa.org/data/LL/Hugos/hugos1997.html|publisher=[[New England Science Fiction Association]]|accessdate=June 9, 2006|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140102104619/http://www.nesfa.org/data/LL/Hugos/hugos1997.html|archive-date=January 2, 2014|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; and continues to regularly feature prominently in various polls and listings highlighting top-rated science fiction series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |title=The World's Best Space Sci-Fi Ever: Your verdict|date=October 26, 2005 |url=https://www.newscientist.com/article/dn8211 |magazine=New Scientist|accessdate=December 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|url=https://www.tvguide.com/news/top-cult-shows-40239/|title=TV Guide Names the Top Cult Shows Ever|date=June 29, 2007|magazine=TV Guide|accessdate=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Top Science Fiction TV Series |date=May 7, 2010 |url=http://www.themarknews.com/articles/1460-the-top-science-fiction-tv-series |publisher=Doug Mann, Professor of Media Studies and Sociology, University of Western Ontario and King's College |accessdate=December 22, 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111207153425/http://www.themarknews.com/articles/1460-the-top-science-fiction-tv-series |archivedate=December 7, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Babylon 5'' has been praised for its depth and complexity against a backdrop of contemporary shows which largely lacked long-term consequences, with plots typically being resolved in the course of a single episode, occasionally two.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.syfy.com/syfywire/an-oral-history-of-babylon-5-the-beloved-tv-novel-that-showed-a-different-way-to-tell-sci|title=An oral history of Babylon 5: The beloved TV novel that showed a different way to tell sci-fi|last=Granshaw|first=Lisa|date=June 27, 2018|website=SYFY WIRE|language=en|access-date=February 22, 2019|quote=It had serialized plots and adventures to follow from episode to episode and season to season with characters that didn't just reset every week but evolved over time.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Straczynski was deeply involved in scriptwriting, writing 92 of 110 teleplays, a greater proportion than some of his contemporaries.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.tor.com/2012/10/08/all-alone-in-the-night-when-babylon-5-invented-21st-century-fandom/|title=All Alone in the Night: When Babylon 5 Invented 21st Century Fandom|last=Britt|first=Ryan|date=October 8, 2012|website=Tor.com|language=en-US|access-date=February 22, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reviewers rated the quality of writing on a widely varying scale, identifying both eloquent [[soliloquy|soliloquies]] and dialogue that felt &quot;stilted and theatrical.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.geek.com/television/remembering-babylon-5-one-of-the-smartest-sci-fi-series-ever-25-years-after-its-debut-1770010/|title=Remembering 'Babylon 5,' One of the Smartest Sci-Fi Series Ever, 25 Years After Its Debut|last=|first=|date=January 16, 2019|website=Geek.com|language=en-US|access-date=February 22, 2019|quote=The show was one of the first to use extensive CGI instead of models for space scenes, which allowed them the freedom to shoot multiple angles. That said, the CGI looks incredibly primitive today and is upscaled for modern TVs badly.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://mattllavin.wordpress.com/2012/09/01/b5/|title=Why Babylon 5 is the Worst Best Thing in Televised Science Fiction – Ever|last=mattllavin|date=September 1, 2012|website=Big Hot Future!|language=en|access-date=February 22, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Straczynski has claimed that the multi-year story arc, now a feature of most mainstream televised drama, is the lasting legacy of the series.&lt;ref name=&quot;syfy oral&quot;/&gt; He stated that both [[Ronald D. Moore]] and [[Damon Lindelof]] used the 5-year narrative structure of ''Babylon 5'' as blueprints for their respective shows, ''[[Battlestar Galactica (2004 TV series)|Battlestar Galactica]]'' and ''[[Lost (TV series)|Lost]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;newsarama 2019&quot;/&gt; He also claims ''Babylon 5'' was the first series to be shot in the [[16:9 aspect ratio]], and to use 5.1 channel sound mixes.&lt;ref name=&quot;syfy oral&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.syfy.com/syfywire/an-oral-history-of-babylon-5-the-beloved-tv-novel-that-showed-a-different-way-to-tell-sci|title=An oral history of Babylon 5: The beloved TV novel that showed a different way to tell sci-fi|last=Granshaw|first=Lisa|date=June 27, 2018|website=SYFY WIRE|language=en|access-date=February 22, 2019|quote=The biggest legacy in many ways has been the five-year arc. In the years since B5, starting with Lost and Battlestar [Galactica], which took that concept to its next level, nearly every dramatic series now has a multi-year arc. What started out the aberration has become the rule. That one singular development changed the television landscape forever in ways that we are still discovering.}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was an early example of widespread use of CGI rather than models for space scenes, which allowed for more freedom and larger scale in creating said scenes. While praised at the time, due to budgetary and mastering issues these sequences are considered to have aged poorly.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://domnardireviews.wordpress.com/2015/03/02/babylon-5-retrospective-legacy/|title=&quot;Babylon 5&quot; Retrospective (Legacy)|last=Dom|date=March 2, 2015|website=NardiViews|language=en|access-date=February 22, 2019|quote=Unfortunately, the production values date the show. As TV screens get bigger and audiences become accustomed to HD, I worry that most modern viewers will be put off by the dated effects and low visual quality.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A recurring theme among reviewers is that the series was more than the sum of its parts: while variously criticising the writing, directing, acting and effects, particularly by comparison to current television productions, reviewers praised the consistency of plotting over the series' run, transcending the quality of its individual elements. Many retrospectives, while criticising virtually every individual aspect of the production, have praised the series as a whole for its narrative cohesion and contribution to serialized television.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://ordinary-times.com/2014/05/15/why-babylon-5-is-the-best-and-worst-television-science-fiction-show-ever-made/|title=Why Babylon 5 is the Best - and Worst - Television Science Fiction Show Ever Made|last=Kelly|first=Tod|date=May 15, 2014|website=Ordinary Times|language=en-US|access-date=February 22, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://eugenia.queru.com/2011/02/03/a-second-look-at-babylon-5/|title=A second look at Babylon 5|date=February 4, 2011|website=Eugenia's Rants and Thoughts|language=en-US|access-date=February 22, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.dvewlsh.com/news/if-you-go-to-zhadum-you-will-die-or-rewatching-babylon-5-remembering-harlan-ellison/|title=If You Go to Z'Ha'Dum, You Will Die; or, Rewatching Babylon 5, Remembering Harlan Ellison|last=Walsh|first=Dave|date=August 2, 2018|website=Dave Walsh, Writer, Dude|language=en-US|access-date=February 22, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Giesbrecht |first1=Jennifer |title=Babylon 5 Is the Greatest, Most Terrible SF Series |url=https://www.tor.com/2019/06/13/babylon-5-is-the-greatest-most-terrible-sf-series/ |accessdate=15 June 2019 |work=[[Tor.com]] |date=13 June 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[DC Comics|DC]] began publishing [[Babylon 5 novels, short stories and comic books#Comic books|''Babylon 5'' comics]] in 1994, with stories (initially written by Straczynski) that closely tied in with events depicted in the show, with events in the comics eventually being referenced onscreen in the actual television series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Guide to DC's Babylon 5 comic|url=http://www.midwinter.com/lurk/comic/index.html|publisher=The Lurker's Guide to Babylon 5|accessdate=December 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Media franchise#Development to other forms|franchise]] continued to expand into short stories, RPGs, and novels, with the [[Technomage#In books|Technomage trilogy]] of books being the last to be published in 2001, shortly after the spin-off television series, ''[[Crusade (TV series)|Crusade]]'', was cancelled. Excepting movie rights, which are retained by Straczynski, all production rights for the franchise are owned by Warner Bros.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.com/tv/ustv/a855453/babylon-5-revival-wont-ever-happen-j-michael-straczynski/|title=Babylon 5 creator says revival won't EVER happen|last=Joe Anderton|date=April 23, 2018|website=Digital Spy|language=en-GB|access-date=February 7, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Media franchise ==
{{Main|Babylon 5 (franchise)}}
In November 1994, [[DC Comics|DC]] began publishing monthly ''Babylon 5'' comics. A number of short stories and novels were also produced between 1995 and 2001. Additional books were published by the gaming companies Chameleon Eclectic and [[Mongoose Publishing]], to support their desk-top strategy and [[Role-playing game|role-playing]] games.

Three tv films were released by [[TNT (American TV network)|Turner Network Television]] (TNT) in 1998, after funding a fifth season of ''Babylon 5'', following the demise of the [[Prime Time Entertainment Network]] the previous year. In addition to ''[[Babylon 5: In the Beginning|In the Beginning]]'', ''[[Babylon 5: Thirdspace|Thirdspace]]'', and ''[[Babylon 5: The River of Souls|The River of Souls]]'', they released a re-edited special edition of the original 1993 tv film, ''[[Babylon 5: The Gathering|The Gathering]]''. In 1999, a fifth tv film was also produced, ''[[Babylon 5: A Call to Arms|A Call to Arms]]'', which acted as a pilot movie for the spin-off series ''[[Crusade (TV series)|Crusade]]'', which TNT cancelled after 13 episodes had been filmed.

[[Dell Publishing]] started publication of a series of ''Babylon 5'' novels in 1995, which were ostensibly considered canon within the TV series' continuity, nominally supervised by Straczynski, with later novels in the line being more directly based upon Straczynski's own notes and story outlines. In 1997, [[Del Rey Books|Del Rey]] obtained the publication license from Warner Bros., and proceeded to release a number of original trilogies directly scenarized by Straczynski, as well as novelizations of three of the TNT telefilms (''In the Beginning, Thirdspace'', and ''A Call to Arms''). All of the Del Rey novels are considered completely canonical within the filmic ''Babylon 5'' universe.

In 2000, the [[Syfy|Sci-Fi Channel]] purchased the rights to rerun the ''Babylon 5'' series, and premiered a new telefilm, ''[[Babylon 5: The Legend of the Rangers|The Legend of the Rangers]]'' in 2002, which failed to be picked up as a series. In 2007, the first in a planned anthology of straight-to-DVD short stories entitled, ''[[Babylon 5: The Lost Tales|The Lost Tales]]'', was released by [[Warner Home Video]], but no others were produced, due to funding issues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jmsnews.com/messages/message?id=3681|title=from jms: update|author=Straczynski|first=J. Michael|date=July 13, 2008|website=JMSNews|publisher=Midnight Design Productions, LLC|accessdate=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Straczynski announced a ''Babylon 5'' film at the 2014 [[San Diego Comic-Con]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tvwise.co.uk/2014/08/babylon-5-movie-eyes-2016-production-start/|title=J. Michael Straczynski Announces 'Babylon 5′ Feature Film Reboot, Eyes 2016 Production Start|last=Munn|first=Patrick|date=August 6, 2014|publisher=[[TVWise]]|accessdate=August 8, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; but stated in 2016 that it had been delayed while he completed other productions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bleedingcool.com/2016/07/31/the-future-of-the-babylon-5-movie/|title=The Future Of The Babylon 5 Movie|website=www.bleedingcool.com|access-date=February 18, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2018 Straczynski stated that although he possesses the movie rights, he believed that neither a film nor television series revival would happen while Warner Bros. retained the intellectual property for the TV series, believing that Warner Bros would insist on handling production, and that other studios would be hesitant to produce a film without also having the rights to the TV series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = https://www.syfy.com/syfywire/a-babylon-5-television-revival-or-movie-in-your-dreams-says-j-michael-straczynski | title=  A Babylon 5 Television Revival Or Movie? In Your Dreams, Says J. Michael Straczynski | first = Josh | last = Weiss | date = April 20, 2018 | accessdate = September 4, 2018 | work = [[Syfy Wire]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Home video releases ==
In July 1995, [[Warner Home Video]] began distributing ''Babylon 5'' VHS video tapes under its Beyond Vision label in the UK. Beginning with the original telefilm, ''[[Babylon 5: The Gathering|The Gathering]]'', these were [[PAL]] tapes, showing video in the same [[Aspect ratio (image)#Current video standards|4:3 aspect ratio]] as the initial television broadcasts. By the release of Season 2, tapes included [[closed captioning]] of dialogue and [[Dolby Surround]] sound. [[Columbia House]] began distributing [[NTSC]] tapes, via mail order in 1997, followed by repackaged collector's editions and three-tape [[box sets|boxed sets]] in 1999, by which time the original pilot telefilm had been replaced by the re-edited TNT special edition. Additional movie and complete season boxed-sets were also released by Warner Bros. until 2000.

[[Image Entertainment]] released ''Babylon 5'' [[laserdiscs]] between December 1998 and September 1999. Produced on double-sided 12-inch [[Pioneer Corporation|Pioneer]] discs, each contained two episodes displayed in the 4:3 broadcast aspect-ratio, with Dolby Surround audio and closed captioning for the dialogue. Starting with two TNT telefilms, ''[[Babylon 5: In the Beginning|In the Beginning]]'' and the re-edited special edition of ''The Gathering'', Seasons 1 and 5 were released simultaneously over a six-month period. Seasons 2 and 4 followed, but with the decision to halt production due to a drop in sales, precipitated by rumors of a pending DVD release, only the first twelve episodes of Season 2 and the first six episodes of Season 4 were ultimately released.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Babylon 5: The Gathering / In The Beginning|author=Germano, Derek M|year=2001|url=http://www.thecinemalaser.com/dvd2/reviews/babylon-5-tgitb-dvd.htm|publisher=thecinemalaser.com|accessdate=January 11, 2011|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101230075959/http://thecinemalaser.com/dvd2/reviews/babylon-5-tgitb-dvd.htm|archivedate=December 30, 2010|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot;
|-
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left; border: 0&quot;|''Laserdiscs (Image Entertainment)''
|-
! style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;| '''Volume / Title''' || Release Date
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 1.01 The Gathering || {{dts|1998-12-15}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 1.02 Midnight On Firing Line / Soul Hunter || {{dts|1998-12-15}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 1.03 Born to the Purple / Infection || {{dts|1998-12-15}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 1.04 Parliament of Dreams / Mind War || {{dts|1999-02-09}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 1.05 The War Prayer / The Sky Full of Stars || {{dts|1999-02-09}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 1.06 Deathwalker / Believers || {{dts|1999-02-09}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 1.07 Survivors / By Any Means Necessary || {{dts|1999-03-09}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 1.08 Signs &amp; Portents / TKO || {{dts|1999-03-09}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 1.09 Grail / Eyes || {{dts|1999-03-09}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 1.10 Legacies / Voice in the Wilderness #1 || {{dts|1999-04-20}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 1.11 Voice in Wilderness #2 / Babylon Squared || {{dts|1999-04-06}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 1.12 The Quality of Mercy / Chrysalis || {{dts|1999-04-06}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 2.00 Points of Departure / Revelations || {{dts|1999-05-25}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 2.01 The Geometry of Shadows / A Distant Star || {{dts|1999-05-25}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 2.02 The Long Dark / Spider in the Web || {{dts|1999-05-25}}
|- class=&quot;expand-child&quot;
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em; color: gray&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; | ''Due to a numbering issue, no Vol. 2.03 exists.''
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 2.04 A Race Through Dark Places / Soul Mates || {{dts|1999-09-28}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 2.05 The Coming of Shadows / Gropos || {{dts|1999-09-28}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 2.06 All Alone in the Night / Acts of Sacrifice || {{dts|1999-09-28}}
|- class=&quot;expand-child&quot;
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em; color: gray&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; | ''Season 2 episodes 13 through 22 were never released on laserdisc.''
|- class=&quot;expand-child&quot;
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em; color: gray&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; | ''Season 3 was never released on laserdisc.''
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 4.01 Hour of the Wolf / Whatever Happened To Mr Garibaldi? || {{dts|1999-09-28}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 4.02 The Summoning / Falling Toward Apotheosis || {{dts|1999-09-28}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 4.03 The Long Night / Into the Fire || {{dts|1999-09-28}}
|- class=&quot;expand-child&quot;
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em; color: gray&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; | ''Season 4 episodes 7 through 22 were never released on laserdisc.''
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 5.01 In the Beginning || {{dts|1998-12-25}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 5.02 No Compromises / Long Night Londo Mollari || {{dts|1999-02-09}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 5.03 Paragon of Animals / View from Gallery || {{dts|1999-02-09}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 5.04 Learning Curve / Strange Relations || {{dts|1999-02-09}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 5.05 Secrets of Soul / Kingdom of the Blind || {{dts|1999-03-09}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 5.06 A Tragedy of Telepaths / Day of the Dead || {{dts|1999-03-09}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 5.07 Phoenix Rising / The Ragged Edge || {{dts|1999-03-09}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 5.08 Corps Is Mother / Meditations On Abyss || {{dts|1999-04-06}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 5.09 Darkness Ascending / And All My Dreams || {{dts|1999-04-06}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 5.10 Movements of Fire / Fall Centauri Prime || {{dts|1999-04-06}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 5.11 Wheel of Fire/Objects in Motion || {{dts|1999-05-25}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Vol. 5.12 Objects at Rest / Sleeping in Light || {{dts|1999-05-25}}
|}

In November 2001, Warner Home Video began distributing ''Babylon 5'' DVDs with a two-movie set containing the re-edited TNT special edition of ''The Gathering'' and ''In The Beginning''. The telefilms were later individually released in [[DVD region code#Region codes and countries|region 2]] in April 2002, though some markets received the original version of ''The Gathering'' in identical packaging.

DVD boxed sets of the individual seasons, each containing six discs, began being released in October 2002. Each included a printed booklet containing episode summaries, with each disc containing audio options for German, French, and English, plus [[wikt:Special:Search/subtitle|subtitles]] in a wider range of languages, including Arabic and Dutch. Video was digitally remastered from original broadcast masters and displayed in [[anamorphic widescreen]] with remastered and remixed [[Dolby Digital]] [[5.1 surround sound|5.1]] sound. Disc 1 of each set contained an introduction to the season by [[J. Michael Straczynski|Straczynski]], while disc 6 included [[featurettes]] containing interviews with various production staff, as well as information on the [[fictional universe]], and a [[gag reel]]. Three episodes in each season also contained commentary from either Straczynski, members of the main cast, and/or the episode director.

Since its initial release, a number of repackaged DVD boxed sets have been produced for various [[DVD region code#Region codes and countries|regional markets]]. With slightly altered [[cover art]], they included no additional content, but the discs were more securely stored in slimline cases, rather than the early &quot;book&quot; format, with hard plastic pages used during the original release of the first three seasons.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot;
|-
! colspan=&quot;4&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left; border: 0&quot;|'''Initial DVD release'''
|-
! style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;| '''Episode box sets''' || [[DVD region code#Region codes and countries|Region 1]] || [[DVD region code#Region codes and countries|Region 2]] || [[DVD region code#Region codes and countries|Region 4]]
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Babylon 5: The Complete First Season || Nov 5, 2002 || Oct 28, 2002 || Nov 27, 2002
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Babylon 5: The Complete Second Season || April 29, 2003 || May 26, 2003 || Jul 9, 2003
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Babylon 5: The Complete Third Season || Aug 12, 2003 || Nov 10, 2003 || Dec 19, 2003
|-
| style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | Babylon 5: The Complete Fourth Season || Jan 6, 2004 || April 19, 2004 || Aug 19, 2004
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Babylon 5: The Complete Fifth Season || April 13, 2004 || Jan 2005 || Dec 16, 2004
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Babylon 5: The Complete Television Series || Aug 17, 2004 || N/A || N/A
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Babylon 5: The Complete Universe (inc. all movies and Crusade episodes)|| N/A || October 24, 2005 || N/A
|-
! colspan=&quot;4&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left; border: 0&quot;|'''Movie releases and box sets'''
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Babylon 5: The Gathering / In the Beginning || Dec 4, 2001 || N/A || Nov 21, 2001
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Babylon 5: The Gathering || N/A || April 8, 2002 || N/A
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Babylon 5: In the Beginning || N/A || April 8, 2002 || N/A
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Babylon 5: The Movie Collection || Aug 17, 2004 || N/A || Mar 2, 2005
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Babylon 5: Movie Box Set || N/A || Feb 21, 2005 || N/A
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Babylon 5: The Legend of the Rangers || March 14, 2006 || Oct 24, 2005 || Nov 16, 2005
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;padding-left: 1em&quot; | Babylon 5: The Lost Tales || July 31, 2007 || Sep 3, 2007 || Jan 2, 2008
|}

=== Mastering problems ===
While the series was in pre-production, studios were looking at ways for their existing shows to make the transition from the then-standard [[Aspect ratio (image)#4:3 standard|4:3 aspect ratio]] to the [[widescreen]] formats that would accompany the next generation of televisions. After visiting [[Warner Bros.]], who were stretching the [[Horizontal blanking interval|horizontal interval]] for an episode of ''[[Lois &amp; Clark: The New Adventures of Superman|Lois &amp; Clark]]'', producer John Copeland convinced them to allow ''Babylon 5'' to be shot on [[Super 35|Super 35mm film stock]]. &quot;The idea being that we would [[telecine]] to 4:3 for the original broadcast of the series. But what it also gave us was a negative that had been shot for the new 16×9 widescreen-format televisions that we knew were on the horizon.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Copeland74&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Interview with John Copeland: page 4|author=Copeland, John|date=June 4, 2008|url=http://www.b5scrolls.com/#Screen1_09_3|publisher=B5Scrolls|accessdate=February 4, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box |quote=The widescreen conversion thing was executive short sightedness at its finest!!! We offered to do ALL of ''Babylon 5'' in widescreen mode if Warner Bros would buy us a reference monitor so we could check our output. (only $5000 at the time) Ken Parkes (the &quot;Business affairs&quot; guy) and Netter (penny wise, but pound foolish) said no! So we did everything so it could be CROPPED to be widescreen! Each blamed the other by the way. Doug Netter said, &quot;Ken Parkes said no&quot;. Ken Parkes said, &quot;Doug Netter said no&quot;. SHEESH!!! So for $75 an episode they could have had AWESOME near Hi-Def. |source=— Ron Thornton, 2008&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Interview with Ron Thornton: page 4|author=Thornton, Ron|date=February 10, 2008|url=http://www.b5scrolls.com/#Screen1_01_6|publisher=B5Scrolls|accessdate=February 4, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; |align=right |width=40% |salign=right}}Though the CG scenes, and those containing live action combined with digital elements, could have been created in a suitable widescreen format, a cost-saving decision was taken to produce them in the 4:3 aspect ratio. When those images were prepared for widescreen release, the top and bottom of the images were simply cropped, and the remaining image 'blown up' to match the dimensions of the live action footage, noticeably reducing the image quality.&lt;ref name=&quot;Copeland74&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.engadget.com/2018/06/22/babylon-5-digital-video-quality/|title=‘Babylon 5’ is great, so why does it look so bad?|last=Cooper|first=Daniel|date=June 22, 2018|website=Engadget|language=en|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2019-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; The scenes containing live action ready to be [[Digital compositing|composited]] with [[matte paintings]], [[Computer animation|CG animation]], etc., were delivered on tape already telecined to the 4:3 aspect-ratio, and contained a high level of [[Film grain|grain]], which resulted in further [[image noise]] being present when enlarged and stretched for widescreen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Interview with Ron Thornton: page 5|author=Thornton, Ron|date=February 10, 2008|url=http://www.b5scrolls.com/#Screen1_01_6|publisher=B5Scrolls|accessdate=February 4, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For the purely live-action scenes, rather than using the film negatives, according to Copeland, &quot;Warners had even forgotten that they had those. They used [[PAL]] versions and converted them to [[NTSC]] for the US market. They actually didn't go back and retransfer the shows.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Copeland75&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Interview with John Copeland: page 5|author=Copeland, John|date=June 4, 2008|url=http://www.b5scrolls.com/#Screen1_09_4|publisher=B5Scrolls|accessdate=February 4, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; With the resulting [[aliasing]], and the [[progressive scan]] transfer of the video to DVD, this has created a number of visual flaws throughout the widescreen release. In particular, quality has been noted to drop significantly in composite shots.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Babylon 5 – The Complete First Season|author=Ordway, Holly E.|date=November 5, 2002|url=http://www.dvdtalk.com/reviews/4929/babylon-5-the-complete-first-season/|publisher=DVDTalk.com|accessdate=January 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://uk.ign.com/articles/2004/02/11/babylon-5-the-complete-fourth-season|title=Babylon 5: The Complete Fourth Season|author=Non, Sergio|date=February 11, 2004|website=IGN.com|accessdate=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
*[[Babylon 5's use of the Internet|''Babylon 5's'' use of the Internet]]
* [[rec.arts.sf.tv.babylon5.moderated]]
* [[The Be Five]]
* [[The Lurker's Guide to Babylon 5|The Lurker's Guide to ''Babylon 5'']]

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
&lt;!--Please do not add BABYLON5SCRIPTS babylon5scripts.com here. It's already listed in the references section above.--&gt;
&lt;!--Please do not add WIKIA wikia.com here. It's up to community consensus.--&gt;
{{Commons}}
{{Wikiquote}}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20070602112525/http://babylon5.warnerbros.com/ ''Babylon 5'' official site]. Archived from the original {{Official website}} on June 6, 2007.
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20020408121202/http://www.scifi.com/babylon5/ ''Babylon 5'']  official site ([[Syfy]]). Archived from [http://www.scifi.com/babylon5/ the original] on February 8, 2002.
*{{IMDb title|id=0105946}}
*{{tv.com show|babylon-5}}
*{{Curlie|Arts/Television/Programs/Science_Fiction_and_Fantasy/B/Babylon_5}}
*[http://www.midwinter.com/lurk/lurker.html The Lurker's Guide to ''Babylon 5'']: ''Babylon 5'' reference and episode guide
*[http://www.b5scrolls.com/ The ''Babylon 5 Scrolls'']: Collection of interviews, concept art and screen used 3D models from FX artists who created ''Babylon 5''
*[http://www.zteamproductions.com/protob5.html Early ''Babylon 5'' Designs]: Information from the original 1991 promotional flyer, with different character names and [[Peter Ledger]]'s artwork

{{Babylon 5}}
{{Hugo Award for Best Dramatic Presentation}}
{{J. Michael Straczynski}}
{{Nebula Award for Best Script/Bradbury Award 1973–2000}}
{{Saturn Award for Best Syndicated/Cable Television Series}}
{{TNTShows}}

[[Category:Babylon 5| ]]
[[Category:First-run syndicated television programs in the United States]]
[[Category:1990s American science fiction television series]]
[[Category:Prime Time Entertainment Network]]
[[Category:American adventure television series]]
[[Category:American science fiction television series]]
[[Category:Serial drama television series]]
[[Category:Television series by Warner Bros. Television]]
[[Category:TNT (American TV network) original programming]]
[[Category:1993 American television series debuts]]
[[Category:1998 American television series endings]]
[[Category:Hugo Award-winning television series]]
[[Category:Saturn Award-winning television series]]
[[Category:Space adventure television series]]
[[Category:Television series set in the 23rd century]]
[[Category:English-language television programs]]
[[Category:Television programs adapted into comics]]
[[Category:Television programs adapted into novels]]
[[Category:Television series created by J. Michael Straczynski]]
[[Category:Fictional space stations]]</text>
      <sha1>jpb0cqysm7fqcr0dk68yjmezu37kbkd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
