  <page>
    <title>Balkan Wars</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4823</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942865975</id>
      <parentid>942835689</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T10:05:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>61.94.102.165</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Hatnote|For the articles examining each war individually, see [[First Balkan War]] and [[Second Balkan War]]. For the 1990s conflicts in the region, see [[Yugoslav Wars]].}}
{{Short description|Two wars on Balkan Peninsula 1912-1913, leading to the Balkan Crisis of 1914 and start of WWI}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2011}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Balkan Wars
| partof=
| image       = Balkanska-voina2.jpg
| caption     = Bulgarian soldiers charging the Turkish defenses in the [[Battle of Kirk Kilisse]]
| date        = 8 October 1912 – 18 July 1913&lt;br/&gt;({{age in years, months, weeks and days|month1=10|day1=08|year1=1912|month2=07|day2=18|year2=1913}})&lt;br/&gt;'''First Balkan War:'''&lt;br&gt;8 October 1912 – 30 May 1913&lt;br&gt;({{Age in years, months, weeks and days|month1=10|day1=08|year1=1912|month2=05|day2=30|year2=1913}})&lt;br&gt;'''Second Balkan War:'''&lt;br&gt;29 June –  10 August 1913&lt;br&gt;({{Age in months, weeks and days|month1=06|day1=29|year1=1913|month2=8|day2=10|year2=1913}})
| place       = {{hlist |[[Adrianople Vilayet|Adrianople]]
 |[[Scutari Vilayet|Scutari]]
 |[[Kosovo Vilayet|Kosovo]]
 |[[Monastir Vilayet|Manastir]]
 |[[Salonica Vilayet|Salonica provinces]]
 |[[Aegean Islands]]
 |[[Aegean Sea]]}}
| territory=
| result      = {{Collapsible list|title='''First Balkan War:'''|titlestyle=font-weight:normal;background:transparent;text-align:left;|
* Balkan League victory 
* [[Treaty of London, 1913|Treaty of London]]
}}
{{Collapsible list|title='''Second Balkan War:'''|titlestyle=font-weight:normal;background:transparent;text-align:left;|
* [[Treaty of Bucharest, 1913|Treaty of Bucharest]] 
* [[Treaty of Constantinople (1913)|Treaty of Constantinople]]
}}
| status=
| combatants_header=
| combatant1  = {{Collapsible list|title='''[[First Balkan War]]'''|titlestyle=font-weight:normal;background:transparent;text-align:left;|{{flag|Ottoman Empire}}
&lt;br/&gt;'''Support:'''&lt;br/&gt;
{{Flag|Austria-Hungary}}
}}
| combatant1a = {{Collapsible list|title='''[[Second Balkan War]]'''|titlestyle=font-weight:normal;background:transparent;text-align:left;| {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Bulgaria}}
}}
| combatant2  = {{Collapsible list|title='''[[First Balkan War]]'''|titlestyle=font-weight:normal;background:transparent;text-align:left;|
[[Balkan League]]:
{{plainlist|
*{{flagcountry|Kingdom of Bulgaria}}
*{{flagcountry|Kingdom of Serbia}}
*{{flagcountry|Kingdom of Greece|state}}
*{{flagcountry|Kingdom of Montenegro}}
*'''Support:'''
*{{flagcountry|Russian Empire}}}}
}}
| combatant2a = {{Collapsible list|title='''[[Second Balkan War]]'''|titlestyle=font-weight:normal;background:transparent;text-align:left;|{{plainlist|
*{{flagcountry|Kingdom of Serbia}}
*{{flagcountry|Kingdom of Romania}}
*{{flagcountry|Kingdom of Greece|state}}
*{{flagcountry|Kingdom of Montenegro}}
&lt;hr/&gt;
*{{flag|Ottoman Empire}}}}
}}
| commander1  = {{smalldiv |{{plainlist|
*{{flagicon|Ottoman Empire}} [[Mehmed V]]
*{{flagicon|Ottoman Empire}} [[Enver Pasha]]
*{{flagicon|Ottoman Empire}} [[Nazım Pasha]]
*{{flagicon|Ottoman Empire}} [[Zeki Pasha]]
*{{nowrap|{{flagicon|Ottoman Empire}} [[Kölemen Abdullah Pasha]]}}
*{{flagicon|Ottoman Empire}} [[Ali Rıza Pasha]]
*{{nowrap|{{flagicon|Ottoman Empire}} [[Hasan Tahsin Pasha]]{{surrendered}}}} 
*{{flagicon|Ottoman Empire}} [[İsmail Hakkı Okday|İsmail Hakkı Pasha]]
*{{flagicon|Ottoman Empire}} [[Rauf Orbay|Rauf Pasha]]}}}}
&lt;hr&gt;
{{smalldiv |{{plainlist|
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Bulgaria}} [[Ferdinand of Bulgaria|Ferdinand I]]
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Bulgaria}} [[Mihail Savov]]
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Bulgaria}} [[Vasil Kutinchev]]
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Bulgaria}} [[Nikola Ivanov]]
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Bulgaria}} [[Radko Dimitriev]]
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Bulgaria}} [[Stiliyan Kovachev]]
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Bulgaria}} [[Stefan Toshev]]}}}}
| commander2  = {{smalldiv |{{plainlist|
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Bulgaria}} [[Ferdinand I of Bulgaria|Ferdinand I]]
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Bulgaria}} [[Mihail Savov]]
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Bulgaria}} [[Ivan Fichev]]
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Bulgaria}} [[Vasil Kutinchev]]
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Bulgaria}} [[Nikola Ivanov]]
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Bulgaria}} [[Radko Dimitriev]]
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Serbia}} [[Radomir Putnik]]
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Serbia}} [[Petar Bojović]]
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Serbia}} [[Stepa Stepanović]]
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Serbia}} [[Živojin Mišić]]
*{{nowrap|{{flagicon|Kingdom of Greece|state}} [[Constantine I of Greece|Crown Prince Constantine]]}}
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Greece|state}} [[Panagiotis Danglis]]
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Greece|state}} [[Pavlos Kountouriotis]]
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Montenegro}} [[Nicholas I of Montenegro|Nicholas I]]
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Montenegro}} [[Danilo, Crown Prince of Montenegro|Prince Danilo Petrović]]
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Montenegro}} [[Janko Vukotić]]
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Romania}} [[Carol I of Romania|Carol I]]
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Romania}} [[Ferdinand I of Romania|Ferdinand I]]
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Romania}} [[Alexandru Averescu]]}}}}
| strength1 = | strength2 = | strength3 = 
| casualties1 = | casualties2 = | casualties3 = 
| notes = | campaignbox = 
}}
{{Campaignbox First Balkan War}}
{{Campaignbox Second Balkan War}}
{{Events leading to World War I}}
{{More citations needed|date=February 2019}}

The '''Balkan Wars''' ({{lang-tr|Balkan Savaşları}}, literally &quot;the Balkan Wars&quot; or ''Balkan Faciası'', meaning &quot;the Balkan Tragedy&quot;) consisted of two conflicts that took place in the [[Balkan Peninsula]] in 1912 and 1913. Four Balkan states defeated the [[Ottoman Empire]] in the first war. In the Second Balkan War, Bulgaria fought against all four original combatants of the first war along with facing a surprise attack from Romania from the north. The conflicts ended catastrophically for the Ottoman Empire, which lost the bulk of its territory in Europe. Austria-Hungary, although not a combatant, became relatively weaker as a much enlarged Serbia pushed for union of the South Slavic peoples.{{sfn|Clark|2013|pp=45, 559}} The war set the stage for the [[July Crisis|Balkan crisis of 1914]] and thus served as a &quot;prelude to the [[First World War]]&quot;.{{sfn|Hall|2000}}

By the early 20th century, [[Kingdom of Bulgaria|Bulgaria]], [[Kingdom of Greece (Glücksburg)|Greece]], [[Kingdom of Montenegro|Montenegro]] and [[Kingdom of Serbia|Serbia]] had achieved independence from the [[Ottoman Empire]], but large elements of their ethnic populations remained under Ottoman rule. In 1912 these countries formed the [[Balkan League]]. The First Balkan War had three main causes:{{sfn|Helmreich|1938}}{{sfn|Hall|2000}}

# The Ottoman Empire was unable to reform itself, govern satisfactorily, or deal with the rising ethnic nationalism of its diverse peoples.
# The [[Great Power]]s quarreled amongst themselves and failed to ensure that the Ottomans would carry out the needed reforms. This led the Balkan states to impose their own solution.
# Most importantly, the Balkan League had been formed, and its members were confident that it could defeat the Turks.

The Ottoman Empire lost all its European territories to the west of the River [[Maritsa]] as a result of the two Balkan Wars, which thus delineated present-day Turkey's western border. A large influx of Turks started to flee into the [[Anatolia|Ottoman heartland]] from the lost lands. By 1914, the remaining core region of the Ottoman Empire had experienced a population increase of around 2.5 million because of the flood of immigration from the Balkans.

Citizens of Turkey regard the Balkan Wars as a major disaster (''Balkan harbi faciası'') in the [[Ottoman Empire#Defeat and dissolution (1908–1922)|nation's history]]. The unexpected fall and sudden relinquishing of Turkish-dominated European territories created a [[Psychological trauma|psycho-traumatic]] event amongst many Turks that triggered the ultimate [[Partitioning of the Ottoman Empire|collapse]] of the empire itself within five years. [[Nazım Pasha]], Chief of Staff of the [[Ottoman Army]], was held responsible for the failure and was assassinated on 23 January 1913 during the [[1913 Ottoman coup d'état]].&lt;ref&gt;Gul Tokay. &quot;Ottoman diplomacy, the Balkan Wars and the Great Powers&quot;. In Dominik Geppert, William Mulligan, Andreas Rose, eds. ''The Wars before the Great War'' {{ISBN|978-1-107-06347-1}}, 2015, p. 70&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[First Balkan War]] began when the League member states attacked the Ottoman Empire on 8 October 1912 and ended eight months later with the signing of the [[Treaty of London (1913)|Treaty of London]] on 30 May 1913. The [[Second Balkan War]] began on 16 June 1913. Both Serbia and Greece, utilizing the argument that the war had been prolonged, repudiated important particulars of the pre-war treaty and retained occupation of all the conquered districts in their possession, which were to be divided according to specific predefined boundaries. Seeing the treaty as trampled, [[Kingdom of Bulgaria|Bulgaria]] was dissatisfied over the division of the spoils in [[Macedonia (region)|Macedonia]] (made in secret by its former allies, Serbia and Greece) and commenced military action against them. The more numerous combined Serbian and Greek armies repelled the Bulgarian offensive and counter-attacked into [[Kingdom of Bulgaria|Bulgaria]] from the west and the south. [[Romania]], having taken no part in the conflict, had intact armies to strike with and invaded Bulgaria from the north in violation of a peace treaty between the two states. The Ottoman Empire also attacked Bulgaria and advanced in Thrace regaining [[Adrianople]]. In the resulting [[Treaty of Bucharest (1913)|Treaty of Bucharest]], Bulgaria lost most of the territories it had gained in the First Balkan War in addition to being forced to cede the ex-Ottoman south-third of [[Dobruja|Dobroudja province]] to [[Romania]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Winston Churchill|title=[[The World Crisis]], 1911–1918|year=1931|publisher=Thornton Butterworth|p=278}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
{{See also|Rise of nationalism under the Ottoman Empire}}
[[File:Map-of-Ottoman-Empire-1900.png|thumb|left|Map of the Ottoman Empire in 1900, with the names of the [[Vilayet|Ottoman provinces]].]]

[[File:Balkan troubles1.jpg|thumb|Germany, France, Russia, Austria-Hungary, and Britain attempting to keep the lid on the simmering cauldron of imperialist and nationalist tensions in the Balkans to prevent a general European war. They were successful in 1912 and 1913 but did not succeed in 1914.]]

[[File:Meurtre de Nazim Pacha illustration, 9 February 1913.jpg|thumb|[[Nazım Pasha]], the chief of staff of the Ottoman army, was assassinated by [[Young Turks]] due to his failure.]]
The background to the wars lies in the incomplete emergence of [[nation-states]] on the European territory of the Ottoman Empire during the second half of the 19th century. Serbia had gained substantial territory during the [[Russo-Turkish War, 1877–1878]], while Greece acquired [[Thessaly]] in 1881 (although [[Treaty of Constantinople (1897)|it lost a small area]] back to the Ottoman Empire in 1897) and Bulgaria (an autonomous [[principality]] since 1878) incorporated the formerly distinct province of [[Eastern Rumelia]] (1885). All three countries, as well as Montenegro, sought additional territories within the large Ottoman-ruled region known as [[Rumelia]], comprising Eastern Rumelia, [[Albania]], Macedonia, and [[Thrace]].

===Policies of the Great Powers===
Throughout the 19th century, the [[Great Power]]s shared different aims over the &quot;[[Eastern Question]]&quot; and the integrity of the Ottoman Empire. [[Russia]] wanted access to the &quot;warm waters&quot; of the [[Mediterranean]] from the Black Sea; it pursued a [[Pan-Slavism|pan-Slavic]] foreign policy and therefore supported Bulgaria and Serbia. Britain wished to deny Russia access to the &quot;warm waters&quot; and supported the integrity of the Ottoman Empire, although it also supported a limited expansion of [[Kingdom of Greece (Glücksburg)|Greece]] as a backup plan in case integrity of the Empire was no longer possible. France wished to strengthen its position in the region, especially in the [[Levant]] (today's [[Lebanon]], [[Syria]], and [[Israel]]).

[[Habsburg]]-ruled [[Austria-Hungary]] wished for a continuation of the existence of the Ottoman Empire, since both were troubled multinational entities and thus the collapse of the one might weaken the other. The Habsburgs also saw a strong Ottoman presence in the area as a counterweight to the Serbian nationalistic call to their own Serb subjects in [[Bosnia]], Vojvodina and other parts of the empire. [[Kingdom of Italy|Italy]]'s primary aim at the time seems to have been the denial of access to the [[Adriatic Sea]] to another major sea power. [[The German Empire]], in turn, under the &quot;[[Drang nach Osten]]&quot; policy, aspired to turn the Ottoman Empire into its own de facto colony, and thus supported its integrity.

In the late 19th and early 20th century, Bulgaria and Greece contended for Ottoman Macedonia and Thrace. Ethnic Greeks sought the forced &quot;Hellenization&quot; of ethnic Bulgars, who sought &quot;Bulgarization&quot; of Greeks ([[Rise of nationalism in the Ottoman Empire#Bulgarians|Rise of nationalism]]). Both nations sent armed irregulars into Ottoman territory to protect and assist their ethnic kindred. From 1904, there was low intensity warfare in Macedonia between the Greek and Bulgarian bands and the Ottoman army (the [[Struggle for Macedonia]]). After the [[Young Turks|Young Turk revolution]] of July 1908, the situation changed drastically.

===Young Turk Revolution===
{{Main|Young Turk Revolution}}
The 1908 [[Young Turk Revolution]] saw the reinstatement of constitutional monarchy in the Ottoman Empire and the start of the [[Second Constitutional Era]]. When the revolt broke out, it was supported by intellectuals, the army, and almost all the ethnic minorities of the Empire, and forced Sultan [[Abdul Hamid II]] to re-adopt the long defunct [[Ottoman constitution of 1876]] and [[Ottoman parliament|parliament]]. Hopes were raised among the Balkan ethnicities of reforms and autonomy, and elections were held to form a representative, multi-ethnic, Ottoman parliament. However, following the Sultan's [[Ottoman countercoup of 1909|attempted counter-coup]], the liberal element of the Young Turks was sidelined and the nationalist element became dominant.

At the same time, in October 1908, Austria-Hungary seized the opportunity of the Ottoman political upheaval to annex the ''de jure'' Ottoman province of [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]], which it had occupied since 1878 (see ''[[Bosnian Crisis]]''). Bulgaria declared independence as it had done in 1878, but this time the independence was internationally recognised. The Greeks of the autonomous [[Cretan State]] proclaimed unification with Greece, though the opposition of the Great Powers prevented the latter action from taking practical effect. It has large influence in the consequent world order.

===Reaction in the Balkan States===

Serbia was frustrated in the north by Austria-Hungary's incorporation of Bosnia. In March 1909, Serbia was forced to accept the annexation and restrain anti-Habsburg agitation by Serbian nationalists. Instead, the Serbian government (PM: [[Nikola Pašić]]) looked to formerly Serb territories in the south, notably &quot;Old Serbia&quot; (the [[Sanjak of Novi Pazar]] and the province of [[Kosovo]]).

On 15 August 1909, the [[Military League]], a group of Greek officers, took action against the government to reform their country's national government and reorganize the army. The Military League found itself unable to create a new political system, until the League summoned the Cretan politician [[Eleutherios Venizelos]] to Athens as its political adviser. Venizelos persuaded king [[George I of Greece#Later reign and assassination|George I]] to revise the constitution and asked the League to disband in favor of a National Assembly. In March 1910, the Military League dissolved itself.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9052680 &quot;Military League&quot;], Encyclopædia Britannica Online&lt;/ref&gt;

Bulgaria, which had secured Ottoman recognition of her independence in April 1909 and enjoyed the friendship of Russia,&lt;ref name=&quot;Congress&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=2007 |url = http://countrystudies.us/bulgaria/12.htm|title = THE BALKAN WARS|publisher=[[US Library of Congress]]| accessdate =15 April 2008 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt; also looked to annex districts of Ottoman Thrace and Macedonia. In August 1910, Montenegro followed Bulgaria's precedent by becoming a kingdom.

===Balkan League===
{{Main|Balkan League}}
[[File:Bulgarian army adrinople.jpg|thumb|left|250px|Bulgarian forces waiting to start their assault on [[Adrianople]]]]

Following Italy's victory in the [[Italo-Turkish War]] of 1911–1912, the Young Turks fell from power after a coup. The Balkan countries saw this as an opportunity to attack the Ottoman Empire and fulfill their desires of expansion.

With the initial encouragement of Russian agents, a series of agreements was concluded between Serbia and Bulgaria in March 1912. Military victory against the Ottoman Empire would not be possible while it could bring reinforcements from Asia. The condition of the Ottoman railways of the time was not advanced, so most reinforcements would have to come by sea through the [[Aegean Sea]]. Greece was the only Balkan country with a navy powerful enough to deny use of the Aegean to the Ottoman Empire, thus a treaty between Greece and Bulgaria became necessary; it was signed in May 1912.

Montenegro concluded agreements between Serbia and Bulgaria later that year. Bulgaria signed treaties with Serbia to divide the territory of northern Macedonia.

This alliance between Greece, Serbia, Bulgaria, and Montenegro became known as the Balkan League; its existence was undesirable to all the Great Powers. The League was loose at best, though secret liaison officers were exchanged between the Greek and the Serbian army after the war began. Greece delayed the start of the war several times in the summer of 1912, to better prepare her navy, but Montenegro declared war on 8 October (25 September [[Adoption of the Gregorian calendar#Adoption in Eastern Europe|O.S.]]). Following an ultimatum to the Ottoman Empire, the remaining members of the alliance entered the conflict on 17 October.

==First Balkan War==
{{Main|First Balkan War}}
[[File:Balkan belligerants 1914.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Territorial changes as a result of the First Balkan war, as of April 1913 showing the prewar agreed line of expansion between [[Serbia]] and [[Bulgaria]]]]
[[File:King George I of Greece and Tsar Ferdinand of Bulgaria at Thessaloniki.jpg|thumb|right|250px|The apple of discord: King [[George I of Greece]] and Tsar [[Ferdinand of Bulgaria]] at Thessaloniki, December 1912. Despite their alliance, Greco-Bulgarian antagonism over the city and Macedonia in general did not abate.]]

The three Slavic allies (Bulgaria, Serbia and Montenegro) had laid out extensive plans to coordinate their war efforts, in continuation of their secret prewar settlements and under close Russian supervision (Greece was not included). Serbia and Montenegro would attack in the theater of Sandjak, Bulgaria and Serbia in Macedonia and Thrace.

The Ottoman Empire's situation was difficult. Its population of about 26 million people provided a massive pool of manpower, but three quarters of the population and nearly all of [[Islam in the Ottoman Empire|the Muslim component]] lived in the Asian part of the Empire. Reinforcements had to come from Asia mainly by sea, which depended on the result of battles between the Turkish and Greek navies in the Aegean.

With the outbreak of the war, the Ottoman Empire activated three Army HQs: the Thracian HQ in [[Constantinople]], the Western HQ in Salonika, and the Vardar HQ in [[Skopje]], against the Bulgarians, the Greeks and the Serbians respectively. Most of their available forces were allocated to these fronts. Smaller independent units were allocated elsewhere, mostly around heavily fortified cities.

Montenegro was the first that declared war on 8 October{{sfn|Hall|2000}} (25 September O.S.). Its main thrust was towards [[Shkodra]], with secondary operations in the [[Novi Pazar]] area. The rest of the Allies, after giving a common ultimatum, declared war a week later. Bulgaria attacked towards Eastern Thrace, being stopped only at the outskirts of [[Constantinople]] at the [[Çatalca]] line and the isthmus of the [[Gallipoli peninsula]], while secondary forces captured Western Thrace and Eastern Macedonia. Serbia attacked south towards [[Skopje]] and [[Monastir, Macedonia|Monastir]] and then turned west to present-day [[Albania]], reaching the [[Adriatic]], while a second Army captured [[Kosovo]] and linked with the Montenegrin forces. Greece's main forces attacked from [[Thessaly]] into Macedonia through the [[Sarantaporo]] strait and after capturing [[Thessaloniki]] on 12 November (on 26 October 1912, [[Adoption of the Gregorian calendar#Adoption in Eastern Europe|O.S.]]) expanded its occupied area and linked up with the Serbian army to the northwest, while its main forces turned east towards [[Kavala]], reaching the Bulgarians. Another Greek army attacked into [[Epirus]] towards [[Ioannina]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BA01&quot;&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9011972 Balkan Wars] Encyclopædia Britannica Online.&lt;/ref&gt;

On the naval front, the Ottoman fleet twice exited the [[Dardanelles]] and was twice defeated by the [[Greek Navy]], in the battles of [[Naval Battle of Elli|Elli]] and [[Naval Battle of Lemnos|Lemnos]]. Greek dominance on the [[Aegean Sea]] made it impossible for the Ottomans to transfer the planned troops from the Middle East to the Thracian (against the Bulgarian) and to the Macedonian (against the Greeks and Serbians) fronts.{{sfn|Erickson|2003|p=333}} According to E.J. Erickson the Greek Navy also played a crucial, albeit indirect role, in the Thracian campaign by neutralizing no less than three Thracian Corps (see [[First Balkan War]], the Bulgarian theater of operations), a significant portion of the Ottoman Army there, in the all-important opening round of the war.{{sfn|Erickson|2003|p=333}} After the defeating of the Ottoman fleet the Greek Navy was also free to liberate the islands of the Aegean. General [[Nikola Ivanov]] identified the activity of the Greek Navy as the chief factor in the general success of the allies.{{sfn|Erickson|2003|p=333}}{{sfn|Hall|2000|p=65}}

In January, after a successful coup by young army officers, the Ottoman Empire decided to continue the war. After a failed Ottoman counter-attack in the Western-Thracian front, Bulgarian forces, with the help of the Serbian Army, managed to conquer [[Battle of Adrianople (1913)|Adrianople]], while Greek forces managed to take [[Ioannina]] after defeating the Ottomans in the [[battle of Bizani]]. In the joint Serbian-Montenegrin theater of operation, the Montenegrin army besieged and captured the [[Shkodra]], ending the Ottoman presence in Europe west of the Çatalca line after nearly 500 years. The war ended officially with the [[Treaty of London, 1913|Treaty of London]] on 30(17) May 1913.

==Second Balkan War==
{{Main|Second Balkan War}}
[[File:With the conquered Turk (1913) cholera patients arriving.png|thumb|250px|[[Cholera]] was common among the soldiers of the combatant nations]]
[[File:Balkan Wars Boundaries.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Boundaries on the Balkans after the First and the Second Balkan War (1912–1913)]]

Though the Balkan allies had fought together against the common enemy, that was not enough to overcome their mutual rivalries. In the original document for the Balkans league, Serbia promised Bulgaria most of Macedonia. But before the first war come to an end, Serbia (in violation of the previous agreement) and Greece revealed their plan to keep possession of the territories that their forces had occupied. This act prompted the tsar of Bulgaria to invade his allies. The Second Balkan War broke out on 29(16) June 1913 when Bulgaria attacked its erstwhile allies in the First Balkan War, Serbia and Greece, while Montenegro and the Ottoman Empire intervened later against Bulgaria, with Romania attacking Bulgaria from the north in violation of a peace treaty.

When the Greek army had entered [[Thessaloniki]] in the First Balkan War ahead of the Bulgarian 7th division by only a day, they were asked to allow a Bulgarian battalion to enter the city. Greece accepted in exchange for allowing a Greek unit to enter the city of [[Serres, Greece|Serres]]. The Bulgarian unit that entered Thessaloniki turned out to be an 18,000-strong division instead of the battalion, something which caused concern among the Greeks, who viewed it as a Bulgarian attempt to establish a [[Condominium (international law)|condominium]] over the city. In the event, due to the urgently needed reinforcements in the Thracian front, Bulgarian Headquarters was soon forced to remove its troops from the city (while the Greeks agreed by mutual treaty to remove their units based in [[Serres]]) and transport them to Dedeağaç (modern [[Alexandroupolis]]), but still it left behind a battalion that started fortifying its positions.

Greece had also allowed the Bulgarians to control the stretch of the Thessaloniki-Constantinople railroad that lay in Greek-occupied territory, since Bulgaria controlled the largest part of this railroad towards Thrace. After the end of the operations in Thrace—and confirming Greek concerns—Bulgaria was not satisfied with the territory it controlled in Macedonia and immediately asked Greece to relinquish its control over Thessaloniki and the land north of [[Pieria (regional unit)|Pieria]], effectively handing over all Aegean Macedonia. These unacceptable demands,  with the Bulgarian refusal to demobilize its army after the [[Treaty of London (1913)|Treaty of London]] had ended the common war against the Ottomans, alarmed Greece, which decided to also keep its army mobilized.

Similarly, in northern Macedonia, the tension between Serbia and Bulgaria due to the latter's aspirations over [[Vardar Macedonia]] generated many incidents between their respective armies, prompting Serbia to keep its army mobilized. Serbia and Greece proposed that each of the three countries reduce its army by one fourth, as a first step to facilitate a peaceful solution, but Bulgaria rejected it. Seeing the omens, Greece and Serbia started a series of negotiations and signed a treaty on 1 June(19 May) 1913. With this treaty, a mutual border was agreed between the two countries, together with an agreement for mutual military and diplomatic support in case of a Bulgarian or/and Austro-Hungarian attack. Tsar [[Nicholas II of Russia]], being well informed, tried to stop the upcoming conflict on 8 June, by sending an identical personal message to the Kings of Bulgaria and Serbia, offering to act as arbitrator according to the provisions of the 1912 Serbo-Bulgarian treaty. But Bulgaria, by making the acceptance of Russian [[arbitration]] conditional, in effect denied any discussion, causing Russia to repudiate its alliance with Bulgaria (see Russo-Bulgarian military convention signed 31 May 1902).

The Serbs and the Greeks had a military advantage on the eve of the war because their armies confronted comparatively weak Ottoman forces in the First Balkan War and suffered relatively light casualties,{{sfn|Hall|2000|p=117}} while the Bulgarians were involved in heavy fighting in Thrace. The Serbs and Greeks had time to fortify their positions in Macedonia. The Bulgarians also held some advantages, controlling internal communication and supply lines.{{sfn|Hall|2000|p=117}}

On 29(16) June 1913, General Savov, under direct orders of Tsar [[Ferdinand of Bulgaria|Ferdinand I]], issued attacking orders against both Greece and Serbia without consulting the Bulgarian government and without any official declaration of war.&lt;ref name=&quot;macedonia-istinata&quot;&gt;{{cite web| date= Winter 1995| url= http://macedonia-istinata.hit.bg/MacEnigma.html| title= THE MACEDONIAN ENIGMA| publisher= Magazine: Australia &amp;World Affairs| accessdate= 15 April 2008| last= George Phillipov| quote= | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080420191403/http://macedonia-istinata.hit.bg/MacEnigma.html| archivedate= 20 April 2008|url-status = dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the night of 30(17) June 1913, they attacked the Serbian army at [[Bregalnica river]] and then the Greek army in [[Nigrita]]. The Serbian army resisted the sudden night attack, while most of soldiers did not even know who they were fighting with, as Bulgarian camps were located next to Serbs and were considered allies. Montenegro's forces were just a few kilometers away and also rushed to the battle. The Bulgarian attack was halted.

The Greek army was also successful.{{sfn|Hall|2000|p=117}} It retreated according to plan for two days while [[Thessaloniki]] was cleared of the remaining Bulgarian regiment. Then, the Greek army counter-attacked and defeated the Bulgarians at [[Battle of Kilkis|Kilkis]] (Kukush), after which the mostly Bulgarian town was destroyed and part of its mostly Bulgarian population massacred by the Greek army.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=keWGAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA279&amp;lpg=PA279&amp;dq=kukush+massacre&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Vl7nRdQrCQ&amp;sig=U5ZmW08ZeHX49vRhVaDuR2ljpmA&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwj2qv-p6O3dAhWmVN8KHXDYCWUQ6AEwAHoECAcQAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=kukush+massacre&amp;f=false|title=Report of the International Commission to Inquire Into the Causes and Conduct of the Balkan Wars|first=International Commission to Inquire into the Causes and Conduct of the Balkan|last=Wars|date=26 October 2018|publisher=Carnegie Endowment for International Peace|via=Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the capture of Kilkis, the Greek army's pace was not quick enough to prevent the retaliatory destruction of [[Nigrita]], [[Serres]], and [[Doxato]] and massacres of non-combatant Greek inhabitants at [[Sidirokastro]] and Doxato by the Bulgarian army.&lt;ref&gt;Report of the International Commission to Inquire into the Causes and Conduct of the Balkan Wars, published by the Endowment Washington, D.C. 1914, p. 97-99 [http://www.kroraina.com/knigi/en/carnegie/chapter2_2.html pp.79–95]&lt;/ref&gt; The Greek army then divided its forces and advanced in two directions. Part proceeded east and occupied [[Western Thrace]]. The rest of the Greek army advanced up to the [[Struma River]] valley, defeating the Bulgarian army in the battles of [[Battle of Doiran (1913)|Doiran]] and Mt. Beles, and continued its advance to the north towards [[Sofia]]. In the [[Battle of Kresna Gorge|Kresna straits]], the Greeks were ambushed by the Bulgarian 2nd and 1st Army newly arrived from the Serbian front that had already taken defensive positions there following the Bulgarian victory at [[battle of Kalimanci|Kalimanci]].

[[File:Battle of Kilkis1913.jpg|thumb|Greek lithograph of the [[Battle of Kilkis–Lachanas]]]]
By 30 July, the Greek army was outnumbered by the counter-attacking Bulgarian army, which attempted to encircle the Greeks in a [[Battle of Cannae|Cannae]]-type battle, by applying pressure on their flanks.{{sfn|Hall|2000|p=121}} The Greek army was exhausted and faced logistical difficulties. The battle was continued for 11 days, between 29 July and 9 August over 20&amp;nbsp;km of a maze of forests and mountains with no conclusion. The Greek King, seeing that the units he fought were from the Serbian front, tried to convince the Serbs to renew their attack, as the front ahead of them was now thinner, but the Serbs declined. By then, news came of the Romanian advance toward Sofia and its imminent fall. Facing the danger of encirclement, Constantine realized that his army could no longer continue hostilities, agreed to [[Eleftherios Venizelos]]' proposal and accepted the Bulgarian request for armistice as this had been communicated through Romania.

Romania had raised an army and declared war on Bulgaria on 10 July(27 June) as it had from 28(15) June officially warned Bulgaria that it would not remain neutral in a new Balkan war, due to Bulgaria's refusal to cede the fortress of Silistra as promised before the First Balkan war in exchange for Romanian neutrality. Its forces encountered little resistance and by the time the Greeks accepted the Bulgarian request for armistice they had reached [[Vrazhdebna]], {{convert|7|mi|km|order=flip|0|abbr=on}} from the center of [[Sofia]].

Seeing the military position of the Bulgarian army the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottomans]] decided to intervene. They attacked, and, finding no opposition, managed to recover eastern [[Thrace]] with its fortified city of [[Edirne|Adrianople]], regaining an area in Europe which was only slightly larger than the present-day European territory of the [[Republic of Turkey]].

==Reactions among the Great Powers during the wars==
[[File:Bazar Tirana (ca. 1900)2.jpg|thumb|[[Tirana]] [[Bazaar]] at the turn of the 20th century.]]
[[File:Serbian poster celebrating victory over Bulgarina in the second Balkan war.jpg|thumb|Serbian propaganda poster, depicting king Alexander I beating the losing Bulgarian ruler.]]

The developments that led to the '''First Balkan War''' did not go unnoticed by the Great Powers, but although there was an official consensus between the European Powers over the [[Eastern Question|territorial integrity of the Ottoman Empire]], which led to a stern warning to the Balkan states, unofficially each of them took a different diplomatic approach due to their conflicting interests in the area. As a result, any possible preventive effect of the common official warning was cancelled by the mixed unofficial signals, and failed to prevent or to stop the war:

*[[Russian Empire|Russia]] was a prime mover in the establishment of the Balkan League and saw it as an essential tool in case of a future war against its rival, the Austro-Hungarian Empire.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stowell1&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Stowell | first = Ellery Cory|authorlink=Ellery Cory Stowell | title =The Diplomacy Of The War Of 1914: The Beginnings Of The War (1915) | publisher=Kessinger Publishing, LLC. | year =2009 | isbn =978-1-104-48758-4 | page =94 }}&lt;/ref&gt; But it was unaware of the Bulgarian plans over Thrace and Constantinople, territories on which it had long-held ambitions, and on which it had just secured a secret agreement of expansion from its allies France and Britain, as a reward for participating in the upcoming [[World War I|Great War]] against the [[Central Powers]].
*[[French Third Republic|France]], not feeling ready for a war against Germany in 1912, took a totally negative position against the war, firmly informing its ally Russia that it would not take part in a potential conflict between Russia and Austria-Hungary if it resulted from the actions of the Balkan League. The French, however, failed to achieve British participation in a common intervention to stop the Balkan conflict.
*The [[British Empire]], although officially a staunch supporter of the Ottoman Empire's integrity, took secret diplomatic steps encouraging Greek entry into the League in order to counteract Russian influence. At the same time, it encouraged Bulgarian aspirations over Thrace, preferring a Bulgarian Thrace to a Russian one, despite the assurances the British had given to the Russians in regard to their expansion there.
*[[Austria-Hungary]], struggling for a port on the [[Adriatic]] and seeking ways for expansion in the south at the expense of the Ottoman Empire, was totally opposed to any other nation's expansion in the area. At the same time, the Habsburg empire had its own internal problems with significant Slav populations that campaigned against German-Hungarian control of the multinational state. Serbia, whose aspirations in the direction of Austrian-held Bosnia were no secret, was considered an enemy and the main tool of Russian machinations that were behind the agitation of Austria's Slav subjects. But Austria-Hungary failed to secure German backup for a firm reaction. Initially, Emperor [[Wilhelm II]] told the [[Archduke Franz Ferdinand of Austria|Archduke Franz Ferdinand]] that Germany was ready to support Austria in all circumstances—even at the risk of a world war, but the Austro-Hungarians hesitated. Finally, in the [[German Imperial War Council of 8 December 1912]] the consensus was that Germany would not be ready for war until at least mid-1914 and passed notes to that effect to the Habsburgs. Consequently, no actions could be taken when the Serbs acceded to the Austrian ultimatum of 18 October and withdrew from Albania.
*[[German Empire|Germany]], already heavily involved in internal Ottoman politics, officially opposed a war against the Empire. But, in her effort to win Bulgaria for the [[Central Powers]], and seeing the [[Sick man of Europe|inevitability]] of Ottoman disintegration, was toying with the idea of replacing the Balkan area of the Ottomans with a friendly Greater Bulgaria in her [[Treaty of San Stefano|San Stefano]] borders—an idea that was based on the German origin of the [[Ferdinand of Bulgaria|Bulgarian King]] and his anti-Russian sentiments.

The '''Second Balkan war''' was a catastrophic blow to Russian policies in the Balkans, which for centuries had focused on access to the &quot;warm seas&quot;. First, it marked the end of the Balkan League, a vital arm of the Russian system of defense against Austria-Hungary. Second, the clearly pro-Serbian position Russia had been forced to take in the conflict, mainly due to the disagreements over land partitioning between Serbia and Bulgaria, caused a permanent break-up between the two countries. Accordingly, Bulgaria reverted its policy to one closer to the [[Central Powers]]' understanding over an anti-Serbian front, due to its new national aspirations, now expressed mainly against Serbia. As a result, Serbia was isolated militarily against its rival Austria-Hungary, a development that eventually doomed Serbia in the coming war a year later. But, most damaging, the new situation effectively trapped Russian foreign policy: After 1913, Russia could not afford losing its last ally in this crucial area and thus had no alternatives but to unconditionally support Serbia when the crisis between Serbia and Austria broke out in 1914. This was a position that inevitably drew her, although unwillingly, into a World War with devastating results for her, since she was less prepared (both militarily and socially) for that event than any other Great Power.

Austria-Hungary took alarm at the great increase in Serbia's territory at the expense of its national aspirations in the region, as well as Serbia's rising status, especially to Austria-Hungary's Slavic populations. This concern was shared by Germany, which saw Serbia as a satellite of Russia. This contributed significantly to the two Central Powers' willingness to go to war as soon as possible.

Finally, when [[Black Hand (Serbia)|a Serbian backed organization]] assassinated [[Archduke Franz Ferdinand of Austria|the heir of the Austro-Hungarian throne]], causing the 1914 [[July Crisis]], no-one could stop the conflict and the [[First World War]] broke out.

==Aftermath==
Soviet demographer Boris Urlanis estimated in ''Voini I Narodo-Nacelenie Europi'' (1960) that in the first and second Balkan wars there were 122,000 killed in action, 20,000 dead of wounds, and 82,000 dead of disease.
[[File:Zapleneti turski topovi od strana na srpskata vojska pred crkata vo Kumanovo, Balkanska vojna, 1912.tif|thumb|Captured Turkish cannons by the Serbian army, displayed in front of a church in [[Kumanovo]], 1912]]

==All Balkan War conflicts==
===First Balkan War conflicts===
====Bulgarian-Ottoman battles====
{| style=&quot;width:76%;&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:25%;&quot;| Battle
! style=&quot;width:8%;&quot;| Year
! style=&quot;width:10%;&quot;| {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Bulgaria|size=22px}} Commander
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| {{flag|Ottoman Empire|size=22px}} Commander
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Result
|- style=&quot;background:#adff2f;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Kumanovo]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1912 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Radomir Putnik]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Zeki Pasha]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Bulgarian Victory
|- style=&quot;background:#adff2f;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Kardzhali]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1912 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Vasil Delov|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Mehmed Pasha|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Bulgarian Victory
|- style=&quot;background:#adff2f;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Kirk Kilisse]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1912 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Radko Dimitriev]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Mahmut Pasha|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Bulgarian Victory
|- style=&quot;background:#adff2f;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Lule Burgas]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1912 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Radko Dimitriev]] || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Abdullah Pasha|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Bulgarian Victory
|- style=&quot;background:#adff2f;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Merhamli]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1912 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Nikola Genev|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Mehmed Pasha|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Bulgarian Victory
|- style=&quot;background:#adff2f;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Kaliakra (1912)|Naval Battle of Kaliakra]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1912 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Dimitar Dobrev|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Rauf Orbay|Hüseyin Bey]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Bulgarian Victory
|- style=&quot;background:lightgrey;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[First Battle of Çatalca]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1912 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Radko Dimitriev]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Nazim Pasha]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|Indecisive&lt;ref&gt;Vŭchkov, pp. 99-103&lt;/ref&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#adff2f;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Bulair]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1913 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Georgi Todorov (general)|Georgi Todorov]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Mustafa Kemal]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Bulgarian Victory
|- style=&quot;background:#adff2f;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Şarköy]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1913 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Stiliyan Kovachev]] || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Enver Pasha]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Bulgarian Victory
|- style=&quot;background:#adff2f;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Adrianople (1913)|Siege of Adrianople]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1913 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Georgi Vazov|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Gazi Pasha|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Bulgarian Victory
|- style=&quot;background:lightgrey;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Second Battle of Çatalca]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1913 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Vasil Kutinchev]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Ahmed Izzet Pasha|Ahmet Pasha]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Indecisive
|}

====Greek–Ottoman battles====
{| style=&quot;width:76%;&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:25%;&quot;| Battle
! style=&quot;width:8%;&quot;| Year
! style=&quot;width:10%;&quot;| {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Greece|size=22px}} Commander
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| {{flag|Ottoman Empire|size=22px}} Commander
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Result
|- style=&quot;background:#0285f5;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Sarantaporo]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1912 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Constantine I of Greece|Constantine I]] || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Hasan Tahsin Pasha|Hasan Pasha]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Greek Victory
|- style=&quot;background:#0285f5;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Yenidje]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1912 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Constantine I of Greece|Constantine I]] || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Hasan Tahsin Pasha|Hasan Pasha]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Greek Victory
|- style=&quot;background:#0285f5;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Pente Pigadia]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1912 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Konstantinos Sapountzakis|Sapountzakis]] || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Mehmet Esat Bülkat|Esat Pasha]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Greek Victory
|- style=&quot;background:#f62f3d;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Sorovich]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1912 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Dimitrios Matthaiopoulos|Matthaiopoulos]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Hasan Tahsin Pasha|Hasan Pasha]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Ottoman Victory
|- style=&quot;background:#0285f5;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Himara revolt of 1912|Revolt of Himara]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1912 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Konstantinos Sapountzakis|Sapountzakis]] || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Mehmet Esat Bülkat|Esat Pasha]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Greek Victory
|- style=&quot;background:#f62f3d;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| Battle of Dryskos|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1912 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Dimitrios Matthaiopoulos|Matthaiopoulos]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Mehmet Esat Bülkat|Esat Pasha]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Ottoman Victory
|- style=&quot;background:#0285f5;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Elli]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1912 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Pavlos Kountouriotis|Kountouriotis]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Remzi Bey|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Greek Victory
|- style=&quot;background:#0285f5;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Capture of Korytsa]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1912 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Konstantinos Damianos|Damianos]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Davit Pasha|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Greek Victory
|- style=&quot;background:#0285f5;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Lemnos (1913)|Battle of Lemnos]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1913 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Pavlos Kountouriotis|Kountouriotis]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Remzi Bey|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Greek Victory
|- style=&quot;background:#0285f5;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Bizani]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1913 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Constantine I of Greece|Constantine I]] || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Mehmet Esat Bülkat|Esat Pasha]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Greek Victory
|}

====Serbian–Ottoman battles====
{| style=&quot;width:76%;&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:25%;&quot;| Battle
! style=&quot;width:8%;&quot;| Year
! style=&quot;width:10%;&quot;| {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Serbia}} Commander
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| {{flag|Ottoman Empire|size=22px}} Commander
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Result
|- style=&quot;background:#9a56f8;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Kumanovo]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1912 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Radomir Putnik]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Zeki Pasha]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Serbian Victory
|- style=&quot;background:#9a56f8;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Prilep]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1912 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Petar Bojović]] || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Zeki Pasha]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Serbian Victory
|- style=&quot;background:#9a56f8;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Monastir]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1912 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Petar Bojović]] || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Zeki Pasha]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Serbian Victory

|- style=&quot;background:lightgrey;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Siege of Scutari (1912-1913)|Siege of Scutari]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1913 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Nikola I Petrović-Njegoš|Nikola I]] || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Hasan Riza Pasha|Hasan Pasha]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|[[Status quo ante bellum]]&lt;ref&gt;Somel, Selçuk Akşin. ''Historical dictionary of the Ottoman Empire''. Scarecrow Press Inc. 2003. lxvi.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|- style=&quot;background:#9a56f8;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Adrianople (1913)|Siege of Adrianople]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1913 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Stepa Stepanovic]] || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Gazi Pasha|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Serbian Victory 
|}

===Second Balkan War conflicts===
====Bulgarian–Greek battles====
{| style=&quot;width:76%;&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:25%;&quot;| Battle
! style=&quot;width:8%;&quot;| Date
! style=&quot;width:10%;&quot;| {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Bulgaria|size=22px}} Commander
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Greece|size=22px}} Commander
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Result
|- style=&quot;background:#0285f5;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Kilkis-Lahanas]] || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 19–21 June 1913 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Nikola Ivanov]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Constantine I of Greece|Constantine I]] || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|Greek  Victory
|- style=&quot;background:#0285f5;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Doiran (1913)|Battle of Doiran]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 23 June 1913 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Nikola Ivanov]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Constantine I of Greece|Constantine I]] || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|Greek  Victory
|- style=&quot;background:#adff2f;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| Battle of Demir Hisar|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 26–27 June 1913|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Nikola Ivanov]] || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|  [[Constantine I of Greece|Constantine I]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|Bulgarian Victory
|- style=&quot;background:lightgrey;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Kresna Gorge|Truce of Kresna Gorge]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 27–31 July 1913|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Mihail Savov]] || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Constantine I of Greece|Constantine I]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|Stalemate
|}

====Bulgarian–Serbian battles====
{| style=&quot;width:76%; text-align:center&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:20%;&quot;| Battle
! style=&quot;width:13%;&quot;| Date
! style=&quot;width:13%;&quot;| {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Bulgaria|size=22px}} Commander
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Serbia|size=22px}} Commander
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Result
|-
|- style=&quot;background:#9a56f8;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Bregalnica]]
|align=&quot;right&quot;| 30 June–9 July 1913
| [[Mihail Savov]]
| [[Radomir Putnik]]
| Serbian victory
|-
|- style=&quot;background:#adff2f;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Knjaževac]]
|align=&quot;right&quot;| 4–7 July 1913
| [[Vasil Kutinchev]]
| Vukoman Aračić
| Bulgarian victory
|- style=&quot;background:#adff2f;&quot;
|- style=&quot;background:#9a56f8;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Pirot (1913)|Battle of Pirot]]
|align=&quot;right&quot;| 6–8 July 1913
|[[Mihail Savov]]
| [[Božidar Janković]]
| Serbian victory
|-
|- style=&quot;background:#9a56f8;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| Battle of Belogradchik
|align=&quot;right&quot;| 8 July 1913
|[[Mihail Savov]]
|[[Božidar Janković]]
| Serbian victory
|- style=&quot;background:#adff2f;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Siege of Vidin (1913)|Siege of Vidin]]
|align=&quot;right&quot;| 12–18 July 1913
| Krastyu Marinov
| Vukoman Aračić
| Peace treaty
|-
|- style=&quot;background:#adff2f;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Battle of Kalimanci]]
|align=&quot;right&quot;| 18–19 July 1913
| [[Mihail Savov]]
| [[Božidar Janković]]
| Bulgarian victory
|}

====Bulgarian–Ottoman battles====
{| style=&quot;width:76%;&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:25%;&quot;| Battle
! style=&quot;width:8%;&quot;| Year
! style=&quot;width:10%;&quot;| {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Bulgaria|size=22px}} Commander
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| {{flag|Ottoman Empire|size=22px}} Commander
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Result
|- style=&quot;background:#f62f3d;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Second Balkan War#Ottoman Intervention|Second Battle of Adrianople]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1913 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Mihail Savov]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Enver Pasha]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| First Armistice
|- style=&quot;background:#adff2f;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Second Balkan War#Treaty of Constantinople|Ottoman Advance of Thrace]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1913 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Vulko Velchev|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Ahmed Izzet Pasha|Ahmed Pasha]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Treaty of Constantinople (1913)|Final Armistice]]
|}

====Bulgarian–Romanian battles====
{| style=&quot;width:76%;&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:25%;&quot;| Battle
! style=&quot;width:8%;&quot;| Year
! style=&quot;width:10%;&quot;| {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Bulgaria|size=22px}} Commander
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Romania|size=22px}} Commander
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Result
|- style=&quot;background:yellow;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Treaty of Bucharest (1913)|Romanian Occupation of Dobruja]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1913 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Ferdinand I of Bulgaria|Ferdinand I]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|[[Carol I of Romania]] || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| First Armistice
|- style=&quot;background:#adff2f;&quot;
|align=&quot;left&quot;| [[Treaty of Bucharest (1913)|Romanian South Western Advance]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1913 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Ferdinand I of Bulgaria|Ferdinand I]]|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|[[Carol I of Romania]] || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[Treaty of Bucharest (1913)|Final Armistice]]
|}

== See also ==
*[[International relations (1814–1919)]]

Since the area has been referred to as the [[Balkans]], notable conflicts have included the following:

*The [[Ottoman wars in Europe]]
*The [[Serbo-Bulgarian War]] (1885)
*The [[Albanian Revolt of 1910]]
*The [[Albanian Revolt of 1911]]
*The [[Albanian Revolt of 1912]]
*The [[Balkans Campaign (World War I)]]
*The [[Balkans Campaign (World War II)]]
*The [[Yugoslav Wars]] (1991–1999)
*[[Destruction of the Thracian Bulgarians in 1913]]
*[[List of places burned during the Balkan Wars]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== Further reading ==
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* {{Cite book|ref=harv|editor-last=Bataković|editor-first=Dušan T.|editor-link=Dušan T. Bataković|title=Histoire du peuple serbe|trans-title=History of the Serbian People|language=French|date=2005|location=Lausanne|publisher=L’Age d’Homme|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=a0jA_LdH6nsC}}
* {{cite book|last1=Boeckh|first1=Katrin|last2=Rutar|first2=Sabina|title=The Balkan Wars from Contemporary Perception to Historic Memory|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0IhaDQEACAAJ|year=2017|publisher=Springer|isbn=978-3-319-44641-7}}
* {{Cite book|ref=harv|last=Ćirković|first=Sima|authorlink=Sima Ćirković|title=The Serbs|year=2004|location=Malden|publisher=Blackwell Publishing|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2Wc-DWRzoeIC}}
* {{cite book|last=Clark|first=Christopher|title=The Sleepwalkers: How Europe Went to War in 1914|chapter=Balkan Entanglements|url=https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780061146657|url-access=registration|year=2013|publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=978-0-06-219922-5|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Crampton|first=R. J.|title=The hollow detente: Anglo-German relations in the Balkans, 1911-1914|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=pRhFAQAAIAAJ|year=1980|publisher=G. Prior|isbn=978-0-391-02159-4}}
* {{cite book|last1=Erickson|first1=Edward J.|last2=Bush|first2=Brighton C.|title=Defeat in Detail: The Ottoman Army in the Balkans, 1912–1913  |year=2003|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|isbn=0-275-97888-5|ref=harv}}
* Ginio, Eyal.  ''The Ottoman Culture of Defeat: The Balkan Wars and  their Aftermath'' (Oxford UP, 2016) 377 pp. [http://www.h-net.msu.edu/reviews/showrev.php?id=52198 online review]
* {{cite book|last=Hall|first=Richard C.|title=The Balkan Wars, 1912–1913: Prelude to the First World War|edition=1st|year=2000|publisher=Routledge|isbn=0-415-22946-4|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Helmreich|first=Ernst Christian|title=The Diplomacy of the Balkan Wars, 1912-1913|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=AvVMMQAACAAJ|year=1938|publisher=Harvard University Press|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|ref=harv|last=Jelavich|first=Barbara|authorlink=Barbara Jelavich|title=History of the Balkans: Twentieth Century|volume=2|year=1983|publisher=Cambridge University Press|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Hd-or3qtqrsC}}
* {{cite book|last1=Király|first1=Béla K.|last2=Rothenberg|first2=Gunther E.|title=War and Society in East Central Europe: East Central European Society and the Balkan Wars|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=q2HfAAAAMAAJ|year=1987|publisher=Brooklyn College Press|isbn=978-0-88033-099-2}}
* {{cite book|last=MacMillan|first=Margaret|title=The War That Ended Peace: The Road to 1914|chapter=The First Balkan Wars|url=|year=2013|publisher=Random House Publishing Group|isbn=978-0-8129-9470-4}}
* {{cite book|last=Meyer|first=Alfred|title=Der Balkankrieg, 1912-13: Unter Benutzung zuverlässiger Quellen kulturgeschichtlich und militärisch dargestellt|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=tGTOAAAAMAAJ|year=1913|publisher=Vossische Buchhandlung}}
* {{cite book|last1=Popović|first1=Dimitrije|last2=Bataković|first2=Dušan T.|last3=Popović|first3=Bogdan Lj.|title=Balkanski ratovi 1912/1913|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=XHfiAAAAMAAJ|year=1993|publisher=Srpska književna zadruga}}
* {{cite book|last=Rossos|first=Andrew|title=Russia and the Balkans: inter-Balkan rivalries and Russian foreign policy, 1908-1914|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-7K6AAAAIAAJ|year=1981|publisher=University of Toronto Press}}
* {{cite book|last1=Rudić|first1=Srđan|last2=Milkić|first2=Miljan|title=Balkanski ratovi 1912-1913: Nova viđenja i tumačenja|trans-title=The Balkan Wars 1912/1913: New Views and Interpretations|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5ZBKDQAAQBAJ|year=2013|publisher=Istorijski institut, Institut za strategijska istrazivanja|isbn=978-86-7743-103-7}}
* {{cite book|last=Schurman|first=Jacob Gould|title=The Balkan Wars 1912–1913|url=https://archive.org/details/balkanwars19121900schuuoft|edition=1st|year=1914|publisher=Princeton University|isbn=}}
* {{cite book|author=Army History Directorate (Greece)|title=A concise history of the Balkan Wars, 1912-1913|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=n4-RAAAAIAAJ|year=1998|publisher=Army History Directorate|isbn=978-960-7897-07-7}}
* Stavrianos, L.S. '' The Balkans Since 1453'' (1958), major scholarly history; [https://archive.org/details/balkanssince145300lsst online free to borrow]
{{div col end}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Balkan Wars}}
*[https://www.mtholyoke.edu/acad/intrel/boshtml/bos143.htm U.S. State Department. &quot;The Formation of the Balkan Alliance of 1912&quot; (1918)]
* C. Hall, Richard: [https://encyclopedia.1914-1918-online.net/article/balkan_wars_1912-1913/ Balkan Wars 1912-1913], in: [https://encyclopedia.1914-1918-online.net/home.html/ 1914-1918-online. International Encyclopedia of the First World War].
*[http://www.gutenberg.org/files/11676/11676.txt Project Gutenberg's The Balkan Wars: 1912–1913, by Jacob Gould Schurman]
*[http://countrystudies.us/bulgaria/12.htm US Library of Congress in the Balkan Wars]
*[http://cnparm.home.texas.net/Wars/BalkanCrises/BalkanCrises00.htm The Balkan crises, 1903–1914].]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20081231100539/http://www.turkeyswar.com/prelude/balkanwars1.htm Balkan Wars from a Turkish perspective]
*[[Wikisource]]: [[:s:The New Student's Reference Work/The Balkans and the Peace of Europe|The New Student's Reference Work/The Balkans and the Peace of Europe]]
*[http://www.europeanfilmgateway.eu/node/33/efg1914%20balkan%20war/multilingual:1/showOnly:video Historic films about the Balkan Wars at europeanfilmgateway.eu]

{{Balkan Wars}}
{{Great power diplomacy}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Balkan Wars| ]]
[[Category:Causes of World War I]]
[[Category:1910s in Europe]]</text>
      <sha1>gxn5t2sylu5lzh4t16iuohn64s2p32b</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
