  <page>
    <title>Black letter law</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3358</id>
    <revision>
      <id>905631945</id>
      <parentid>884379469</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-07-10T09:45:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Citation bot</username>
        <id>7903804</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Add: title. Converted bare reference to cite template. | You can [[WP:UCB|use this bot]] yourself. [[WP:DBUG|Report bugs here]].| Activated by [[User:Headbomb]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=April 2008}}
[[Image:L Old London.svg|right|thumb|[[Blackletter]] ''L'']]
In [[common law]] legal systems, '''black letter laws''' are the well-established legal rules that are no longer subject to reasonable dispute.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://www.oxfordreference.com/view/10.1093/oi/authority.20110803095510675 |title = Black-letter law - Oxford Reference}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some examples are the &quot;black-letter law&quot; that the formation of a [[contract]] requires consideration, or the &quot;black-letter law&quot; that the registration of a [[trademark]] requires established use in the course of trade. Black-letter law can be contrasted with [[legal theory]] or unsettled legal issues.

==History and etymology==
In an 1831 case in the [[U.S. Supreme Court]], ''Jackson [[ex dem.]] Bradstreet v. Huntington'', the phrase &quot;[[black letter]]&quot; was used: &quot;It is seldom that a case in our time savours so much of the black letter; but the course of decisions in New York renders it unavoidable...&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Jackson ex dem. Bradstreet v. Huntington'', 30 U.S. 402, 434 (1831).&lt;/ref&gt; The phrase &quot;black-letter law&quot; was used in the [[Pennsylvania Supreme Court]] case ''Naglee v. Ingersoll,'' 7 Pa. 185 (1847). The phrase does not come from association with [[Black's Law Dictionary]], which was first published in 1891. Instead, it presumably refers to the practice of setting law books and citing legal precedents in [[blackletter]] type, a tradition that survived long after the switch to Roman and italic text for other printed works.

The phrase definitely refers to a distillation of the [[common law]] into general and accepted legal principles. This can be seen in the quote above from the Supreme Court where the court is noting that while the black letter law is clear, [[New York (state)|New York]] precedent deviates from the general principles.

In [[common law]], the informal black letter legal doctrine includes the basic principles of [[law]] generally accepted by the [[court]]s and/or embodied in the [[statute]]s of a particular [[jurisdiction]]. The letter of the law is its actual implementation, thereby demonstrating that black letter laws are those [[statute]]s, rules, [[acts]], [[laws]], provisions, etc. that are or have been written down, codified, or indicated somewhere in [[legal]] texts throughout history of specific [[State (polity)|state]] law. This is often the case for many [[precedent]]s that have been set in the [[common law]]. An example of such a state within the [[common law jurisdiction]], and using the black letter [[legal doctrine]] is [[Canada]]. Canada is a [[monarchical state]], with its roots invested in [[Colonial England]], and black letter law is the [[principles of law]] accepted by the [[majority of judges]] in most [[provinces]] and [[Territories of Canada|territories]]. Sometimes this is referred to as &quot;[[hornbook law]]&quot; meaning [[treatise]] or textbook, often relied upon as [[authoritative]], competent, and generally accepted in the field of Canadian law. In [[Legal English|lawyer lingo]], hornbook law or black letter law is a fundamental and well-accepted legal principle that does not require any further explanation, since a hornbook is a primer of basics. Law is the rule which establish that a [[principle]], [[provision (law)|provision]], [[reference]]s, [[inference]], [[observation]], etc. may not require further explanation or clarification when the very nature of them shows that they are basic and elementary.

==Similar phrases==
The phrase is nearly synonymous with the phrase &quot;[[hornbook law]]&quot;. There are a number of venerable legal sources that distill the common law on various subjects known as [[Restatement of the Law]]. The specific titles will be &quot;The Restatement (First) of Contracts&quot; or &quot;The Restatement of Agency&quot; etc. Each of these volumes is divided into sections that begin with a text in boldface that summarizes a basic rule on an aspect of the law of contracts, agency etc. This &quot;restatement&quot; is followed by commentary and examples that expand on the principle stated.

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Black Letter Law}}
[[Category:Informal legal terminology]]</text>
      <sha1>6ivrld3yvanpd9rmgnpi46uduum1efn</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
