  <page>
    <title>Blue law</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3359</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941054334</id>
      <parentid>941054195</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-16T09:36:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Isingness</username>
        <id>30546857</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Canada */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Legal restrictions designated for Sunday activity}}
{{About|laws created to enforce strict moral standards|early Colony of Connecticut laws|Blue Laws (Connecticut)}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2012}}
[[File:Sabbath Eve.jpg|thumb|300px|''Sabbath Eve'', painting by [[Alexander Johnston (artist)|Alexander Johnston]]]]
'''Blue laws''', also known as '''Sunday laws''', are laws designed to restrict or ban some or all Sunday activities for religious or secular reasons, particularly to promote the observance of a day of worship or rest. Blue laws may also restrict shopping or ban sale of certain items on specific days, most often on Sundays in the western world. Blue laws are enforced in parts of the United States and Canada as well as some European countries, particularly in Austria, Germany, Switzerland, and Norway, keeping most stores closed on Sundays.

In the United States, the [[U.S. Supreme Court]] has held blue laws as constitutional numerous times, citing [[secular]] bases such as securing a day of rest for mail carriers,&lt;ref name=&quot;Fuller2010&quot;/&gt; as well as protecting workers and families, in turn contributing to societal stability and guaranteeing the [[free exercise of religion]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldberg2000&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith2003&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;O'FlahertyPetersen2010&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=O'Flaherty|first1=Edward|last2=Petersen|first2=Rodney L.|last3=Norton|first3=Timothy A.|title=Sunday, Sabbath, and the Weekend: Managing Time in a Global Culture|date=7 September 2010|publisher=Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing|language=English|isbn=9780802865830|page=167}}&lt;/ref&gt; The origin of the blue laws also partially stems from religion, particularly the prohibition of [[Sabbath desecration]] in Christian Churches following the [[first-day Sabbatarian]] tradition. Both [[labour unions]] and [[trade associations]] have historically supported the legislation of blue laws.&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldberg2000&quot;/&gt; Most blue laws have been repealed in the United States, although some states ban the sale of [[alcoholic beverages]] on Sundays and many states ban selling cars on Sundays.

==History==
The very first known law regarding prohibition of Sunday labor for religious reasons was in AD 321, by Emperor Constantine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://biblelight.net/sunday.htm|title=Encyclopedia of Religion and Ethics (New York: Scribner, 1928)|publisher=|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|''On the venerable Day of the Sun let the magistrates and people residing in cities rest, and let all workshops be closed.''|source=''[[Codex Justinianus]]'', lib. 3, tit. 12, 3}}

The first occurrence of the phrase ''blue laws'' so far found is in the ''New-York Mercury'' of March 3, 1755, where the writer imagines a future newspaper praising the revival of &quot;our [[Connecticut]]'s [[Blue Laws (Connecticut)|old Blue Laws]]&quot;. In his 1781 book ''General History of Connecticut'', the Reverend [[Samuel Peters]] (1735–1826) used it to describe various laws first enacted by [[Puritan]] colonies in the 17th century that prohibited various activities, recreational as well as commercial, on Sunday (Saturday evening through Sunday night). Sometimes the sale of certain types of merchandise was prohibited, and in some cases all retail and business activity.

Contrary to popular belief, there is no evidence that blue laws were originally printed on blue paper. Rather, the word ''blue'' was used in the 17th century as a disparaging reference to rigid moral codes and those who observed them, particularly in ''blue-stocking'', a reference to [[Oliver Cromwell]]'s supporters in the parliament of 1653.&lt;ref&gt;''Oxford English Dictionary''.&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, although Reverend Peters claimed that the term ''blue law'' was originally used by Puritan colonists, his work has since been found to be unreliable.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.snopes.com/language/colors/bluelaws.htm Snopes.com: American &quot;blue laws&quot; were so named because they were originally printed on blue paper.]. Retrieved July 12, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; In any event, Peters never asserted that the blue laws were originally printed on blue paper, and this has come to be regarded as an example of [[false etymology]], another version of which is that the laws were first bound in books with blue covers.

As Protestant moral reformers organized the Sabbath reform in nineteenth-century America, calls for the enactment and enforcement of stricter Sunday laws developed. Numerous Americans were arrested for working, keeping an open shop, drinking alcohol, traveling, and recreating on Sundays. Erwin Fahlbusch and Geoffrey William Bromiley write that throughout their existence, organizations advocating [[first-day Sabbatarianism]], such as the [[Lord's Day Alliance]] in North America and the [[Lord's Day Observance Society]] in the British Isles, were supported by [[labor unions]] in lobbying &quot;to prevent secular and commercial interests from hampering freedom of worship and from exploiting workers.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;FahlbuschBromiley2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Fahlbusch|first1=Erwin|last2=Bromiley|first2=Geoffrey William|title=The Encyclopedia of Christianity|year=2005|publisher=Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing|isbn=9780802824165|page=787}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, the [[United States Congress]] was supported by the Lord's Day Alliance in securing &quot;a day of rest for city postal clerks whose hours of labor, unlike those of city mail carriers, were largely unregulated.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fuller2010&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Fuller|first=Wayne E.|title=Morality and the Mail in Nineteenth-Century America|date=1 October 2010|publisher=University of Illinois Press|language=English|isbn=9780252091353|page=93}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Canada, the ''Ligue du Dimanche'', a Roman Catholic Sunday league, supported the [[Lord's Day Act]] in 1923 and promoted first-day Sabbatarian legislation.&lt;ref name=&quot;2005Roy&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Roy|first=Christian|title=Traditional Festivals: A Multicultural Encyclopedia|url=https://archive.org/details/traditionalfesti0000royc/page/457|url-access=registration|year=2005|publisher=ABC-CLIO|language=English|isbn=9781576070895|page=[https://archive.org/details/traditionalfesti0000royc/page/457 457]|quote=However, an amendment was made that left is enforcement to the discretion of the provinces, so that it remained a dead letter in mostly French Quebec. A Catholic Sunday League was formed in 1923 to combat this laxity and promote sabbatarian restrictions in that province--especially against movie theaters.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rybczyński1991&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Rybczyński|first=Witold|title=Waiting for the Weekend|url=https://archive.org/details/waitingforweeken00rybc|url-access=registration|year=1991|publisher=Viking Penguin|language=English|isbn=9780670830015|page=[https://archive.org/details/waitingforweeken00rybc/page/78 78]|quote=In 1922, inspired by a pastoral letter decrying the lax observance of Sunday as a day of rest, the Ligue du Dimanche (Sunday League) was formed. For fourteen years the League agitated for Sabbatarian legislation, particularly against cinemas ...}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beginning in the 1840s, workingmen, Jews, Seventh Day Baptists, free-thinkers, and other groups began to organize opposition. Throughout the century, Sunday laws served as a major source of church-state controversy and as an issue that drove the emergence of modern American minority-rights politics.&lt;ref&gt;Kyle G. Volk (2014), ''[https://www.amazon.com/Moral-Minorities-Making-American-Democracy/dp/0199371911/ Moral Minorities and the Making of American Democracy]''. New York: Oxford University Press. {{ISBN|019937192X}}.&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, the more recent ''[[Dies Domini]]'', written by [[Pope John Paul II]] in 1998, advocates Sunday legislation in that it protects civil servants and workers; the North Dakota Catholic Conference in 2011 likewise maintained that blue laws, in accordance with the Compendium of the Social Doctrine of the Church, &quot;ensure that, for reasons of economic productivity, citizens are not denied time for rest and divine worship.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://religiousliberty.tv/north-dakota-catholic-conference-says-sunday-law-benefits-all-people-ewtn-news.html|title=North Dakota Catholic Conference says 'Sunday law' Benefits All People|date=19 September 2011|publisher=EWTN News|language=English|accessdate=5 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, Chief Justice [[Earl Warren]], while acknowledging the partial religious origin of blue laws, acknowledged their &quot;secular purpose they served by providing a benefit to workers at the same time that they enhanced labor productivity.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldberg2000&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Goldberg|first=Steven|title=Seduced by Science: How American Religion Has Lost Its Way|year=2000|publisher=NYU Press|language=English|isbn=9780814731055|page=106}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many European countries{{which|date=January 2013}} still place strong restrictions on store opening hours on Sundays, an example being Germany's [[Ladenschlussgesetz]].

==Canada==
[[File:Ontario Sunday Laws.jpg|thumb|right|Sunday laws in Ontario, 1911]]
The ''Lord's Day Act'', which since 1906 had prohibited business transactions from taking place on Sundays, was declared unconstitutional in the 1985 case ''[[R. v. Big M Drug Mart Ltd.]]'' Calgary police officers witnessed several transactions at the Big M Drug Mart, all of which occurred on a Sunday. Big M was charged with a violation of the ''Lord's Day Act''. A provincial court ruled that the ''Lord's Day Act'' was unconstitutional, but the Crown proceeded to appeal all the way to the [[Supreme Court of Canada]]. In a unanimous 6–0 decision, the ''Lord's Day Act'' was ruled an infringement of the freedom of conscience and religion defined in section 2(a) of the [[Charter of Rights and Freedoms]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://canlii.org/en/ca/scc/doc/1985/1985canlii69/1985canlii69.html |title=CanLII – 1985 CanLII 69 (S.C.C.) |publisher=Canadian Legal Information Institute (CanLII.org) |date=September 3, 2009 |accessdate=2009-09-24 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110509175904/http://www.canlii.org/en/ca/scc/doc/1985/1985canlii69/1985canlii69.html |archivedate=May 9, 2011 |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A Toronto referendum in 1950 allowed only team sports to be played professionally on Sunday. Theatre performances, movie screenings, and horse racing were not permitted until the 1960s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.nationalpost.com/full-comment/allan-levine-never-mind-ford-nation-hogtown-has-a-long-history-of-drunks-tyrants-and-loudmouths-running-city-hall|title=Allan Levine: Never mind Ford Nation. Hogtown has a long history of drunks, tyrants and loudmouths running City Hall|publisher=|accessdate=February 2, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Supreme Court later concluded, in ''[[R. v. Edwards Books and Art Ltd.]]'' [1986] (2 S.C.R. 713), that Ontario's ''Retail Business Holiday Act'', which required some Sunday closings, did not violate the Charter because it did not have a religious purpose. Nonetheless, as of today, virtually all provincial Sunday closing laws have ceased to exist. Some were struck down by provincial courts, but most were simply abrogated,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Raynault-Ollu |first1=Louis-Philippe |title=Sunday Observance Laws in North America |date=2012 |doi=10.2139/ssrn.2260582 |language=en |issn=1556-5068|ssrn=2260582}}&lt;/ref&gt; often due to competitive reasons where out-of-province or foreign merchants were open.

==Cook Islands, Tonga and Niue==
In the [[Cook Islands]], blue laws were the first written legislation, enacted by the [[London Missionary Society]] in 1827, with the consent of ''[[Ali'i|ariki]]'' (chiefs). In [[Tonga]], the [[Vava'u Code]] (1839) was inspired by [[Methodism|Methodist]] [[missionary]] teachings, and was a form of blue law. In [[Niue]], certain activities remain forbidden on Sunday, reflecting [[History of Niue|the country's history]] of observing Christian Sabbath tradition.

==Denmark==
In [[Denmark]] the closing laws restricting retail trade on Sundays have been abolished with effect from October 1, 2012. From then on retail trade is only restricted on public holidays (New Years Day, [[Maundy Thursday]], Good Friday, Easter Sunday, Easter Monday, Day of Prayer, Ascension Day, Whit Sunday, Whit Monday, Christmas Day and Boxing Day) and on Constitution Day, Christmas Eve and New Year's Eve (on New Year's Eve from 3&amp;nbsp;pm only). On these days almost all shops will remain closed. Exempt are bakeries, DIYs, garden centres, gas stations and smaller supermarkets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite act|url=https://www.retsinformation.dk/Forms/R0710.aspx?id=132057|title=Lov om ændring af lov om detailsalg fra butikker m.v. - Liberalisering af reglerne om åbningstid |trans-title=Act Amending the Law on Retail Sales from Shops, etc. - Liberalization of the Rules on Opening Hours|number= 543 |date=26 May 2010 |publisher=Danish Civil Protection Agency - retsinformation.dk|accessdate=23 September 2018|language=Danish|article-type=amendment}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==England and Wales==

===Before 1994===
Prior to 1994, trading laws forbade sale of certain products on a Sunday; the distinction between those that could and could not be sold was increasingly seen as arbitrary, and the laws were inadequately enforced and widely flouted. For example, some supermarkets would treat the relatively modest fines arising as a business cost and open nonetheless.{{cn|date=December 2019}}

===Since 1994===
The [[Sunday Trading Act 1994]] relaxed restrictions on Sunday trading. This produced vocal opposition from bodies such as the Keep Sunday Special campaign, and the [[Lord's Day Observance Society]]: on religious grounds, on the grounds that it would increase consumerism, and that it would reduce shop assistants' weekend leisure time.

The legislation permits large shops (those with a relevant floor area in excess of 280 square metres) to open for up to six hours on Sunday between the hours of 10&amp;nbsp;am and 6&amp;nbsp;pm. Small shops, those with an area of below 280 square metres, are free to set their own Sunday trading times. Some large shops, such as off-licences, service stations and garages, are exempt from the restrictions.

Some very large shops (e.g. department stores) open for longer than six hours on a Sunday by allowing customers in to browse 30 minutes prior to allowing them to make a purchase, since the six-hour restriction only applies to time during which the shop may make sales.

Christmas Day and Easter Sunday are non-trading days. This applies even to garden centres, which earlier had been trading over Easter, but not to small shops (those with an area of below 280 square metres).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.gov.uk/trading-hours-for-retailers-the-law|title=Trading hours for retailers: the law|publisher=|accessdate=January 27, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Northern Ireland==
Prior to 2008, [[Sunday football in Northern Ireland|no football was permitted to be played on Sundays]] by clubs affiliated to the [[Irish Football Association]] in Northern Ireland.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2007/sep/02/northernireland.northernireland|title=New bid for Sunday football|author=Henry McDonald|work=the Guardian|accessdate=January 27, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Shops with a floor area of over {{Convert|280|m2}} may only open from 1 to 6pm on Sundays.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nibusinessinfo.co.uk/content/seasonal-and-sunday-trading|title=Seasonal and Sunday Trading|accessdate=March 10, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Belfast]], public playgrounds were closed on Sundays until 1965. [[Swing (seat)|Swings]] in public parks were tied up and padlocked to prevent their use.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.rte.ie//archives/category/society/2015/0308/685176-belfast-children-allowed-to-use-swings-on-sunday/|title=Belfast Children Allowed To Use Swings On Sunday|website=RTÉ Archives}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/theguardian/1999/mar/25/features11.g27|title=The banned played on|first=Guardian|last=Staff|date=March 25, 1999|via=www.theguardian.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similar laws formerly applied to cinemas, pubs and parks.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/northern_ireland/8068342.stm|title=Never on a Sunday? Not any more|date=May 27, 2009|via=news.bbc.co.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Poland==
{{See also|Sunday shopping#Poland}}
Since 2007, blue laws were enacted and resulted in stores closing on the [[Public holidays in Poland|13 state holidays]] in [[Poland]] - these are both religious and secular days of rest. In 2014, an initiative by the [[Law and Justice]] party failed to pass the reading in the [[Sejm]] to ban trading on Sundays and state holidays. 
However, since 2018, the ruling government and the President of Poland has signed a law that restricts store trading from 1st March 2018 to the first and last Sunday of the month, [[Palm Sunday]], the 3rd and 4th [[Advent]] Sundays, as well as trading until 14.00 for [[Easter Saturday]] and [[Christmas Eve]].
This will change in 2019 to trading permitted solely on the last Sunday of the month, as well as [[Palm Sunday]], the 3rd and 4th [[Advent]] Sundays, as well as trading until 14.00 for [[Easter Saturday]] and [[Christmas Eve]].
From 2020, stores may only be open on 7 Sundays in the year: [[Palm Sunday]], the 3rd and 4th [[Advent]] Sundays, the last Sunday of January, April, June and August as well as trading until 14.00 for [[Easter Saturday]] and [[Christmas Eve]]. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uk.businessinsider.com/ap-poland-limits-sunday-shopping-to-benefit-family-life-2018-1|title=Poland limits Sunday shopping to benefit family life|website=Business Insider|accessdate=January 30, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==United States==
{{main|Blue laws in the United States}}
In the United States, judges have defended blue laws &quot;in terms of their secular benefit to workers&quot;, holding that &quot;the laws were essential to social well-being&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith2003&quot;/&gt; In 1896, Supreme Court Chief Justice [[Stephen Johnson Field]], opined with regard to Sunday blue laws:&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith2003&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Smith|first=Christian|title=The Secular Revolution: Power, Interests, and Conflict in the Secularization of American Public Life|year=2003|publisher=University of California Press|language=English |isbn=9780520230002|page=319}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quotation|Its requirement is a cessation from labor. In its enactment, the legislature has given the sanction of law to a rule of conduct, which the entire civilized world recognizes as essential to the physical and moral well-being of society. Upon no subject is there such a concurrence of opinion, among philosophers, moralists and statesmen of all nations, as on the necessity of periodical cessation from labor. One day in seven is the rule, founded in experience and sustained by science. ... The prohibition of secular business on Sunday is advocated on the ground that by it the general welfare is advanced, labor protected, and the moral and physical well-being of society promoted.|''Hennington v. Georgia'', 163 U.S. 299 (1896)&lt;ref&gt;''[[Hennington v. Georgia]]'', {{Ussc|163|299|1896}}.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Many states prohibit selling [[alcoholic beverage|alcohol]] for on and off-premises sales in one form or another on Sundays at some restricted time, under the idea that people should be in church on Sunday morning, or at least not drinking.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.alcoholproblemsandsolutions.org/Controversies/Alcohol-Blue-Laws.html|title=Alcohol Blue Laws (Laws Prohibiting Sunday Sales of Alcoholic Beverages)|last=Ph.D.|first=Prof. David J. Hanson|language=en-US|access-date=2016-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.goupstate.com/news/20160924/gaffney-churches-seek-to-stop-sunday-alcohol-sales|title=Gaffney churches seek to stop Sunday alcohol sales|last=Montgomery|first=Bob|access-date=2016-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another feature of [[blue laws in the United States]] restricts the purchase of particular items on Sundays. Some of these laws restrict the ability to buy cars, groceries, office supplies, and housewares among other things. Though most of these laws have been relaxed or repealed in most states, they are still enforced in some other states.

In Texas, for example, blue laws prohibited selling housewares such as pots, pans, and washing machines on Sunday until 1985. In [[Colorado]], [[Illinois]], [[Indiana]], [[Iowa]], [[Louisiana]], [[Maine]], [[Minnesota]], [[Missouri]], [[Oklahoma]], [[New Jersey]], [[North Dakota]], [[Pennsylvania]], and [[Wisconsin]], car dealerships continue to operate under blue-law prohibitions in which an automobile may not be purchased or traded on a Sunday. [[Maryland]] permits Sunday automobile sales only in the counties of [[Charles County, Maryland|Charles]], [[Prince George's County, Maryland|Prince George's]], [[Montgomery County, Maryland|Montgomery]], and [[Howard County, Maryland|Howard]]; similarly, [[Michigan]] restricts Sunday sales to only those counties with a population of less than 130,000. Texas and [[Utah]] prohibit car dealerships from operating over consecutive weekend days. In some cases these laws were created or retained with the support of those whom they affected, to allow them a day off each week without fear of their competitors still being open.&lt;ref&gt;[http://wcco.com/consumer/local_story_324235359.html Good Question: Why Can't We Buy Alcohol On Sunday?], [[WCCO-TV]], November 20, 2006  {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070929084311/http://wcco.com/consumer/local_story_324235359.html |date=September 29, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Blue laws may also prohibit retail activity on days other than Sunday. In [[Massachusetts]], [[Rhode Island]], and [[Maine]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mainelegislature.org/legis/statutes/17/title17sec3204.html|title=Title 17, §3204: Business, traveling or recreation on Sunday|publisher=|accessdate=January 27, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; for example, blue laws prohibit most retail stores, including grocery stores, from opening on [[Thanksgiving]] and Christmas.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.boston.com/news/globe/editorial_opinion/editorials/articles/2006/11/25/a_turkey_of_a_blue_law/ &quot;A turkey of a blue law&quot;], ''[[Boston Globe]]''. Retrieved November 25, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

Research regarding the effect of the repeal of blue laws has been conducted, with Professor Elesha Coffman of [[Baylor University]] writing:&lt;ref name=&quot;Coffman2009&quot;&gt;{{cite magazine|url=http://www.christianitytoday.com/history/2009/february/bye-bye-blue-laws.html|title=Bye-Bye, Blue Laws?|last=Coffman|first=Elesha|year=2009|magazine=[[Christianity Today]]|language=English|accessdate=6 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quotation|Regarding culture, the impact of vanishing blue laws could be larger. A study in New Mexico in 2006 found a sharp increase in drunken driving on Sundays after that state dropped its Sunday ban on packaged alcohol sales. A broader study published by MIT and Notre Dame economists in 2008 found that the repeal of blue laws led to decreased church attendance, decreased donations to churches, and increased alcohol and drug use among religious individuals. These wide-ranging effects cannot easily be pinpointed to specific causes, but one of the latter study's authors, Daniel Hungerman, suggested to ''[[Christianity Today]]'' that blue laws might have been fulfilling their original intent, to keep people pious.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coffman2009&quot;/&gt;}}

===Court cases===
Beginning in the mid-19th century, religious and ethno-cultural minorities arrested for violating state and local blue laws appealed their convictions to state supreme courts. In ''Specht v. Commonwealth'' (Pa. 1848), for example, German Seventh Day Baptists in Pennsylvania employed attorney [[Thaddeus Stevens]] to challenge the constitutionality of Pennsylvania's Sunday law.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite court |litigants=Specht v. Commonwealth |vol=8 |reporter=Pa. |opinion=312 |pinpoint= |court=Penn. |date=1848 |url= |accessdate=September 22, 2019}}.&lt;/ref&gt; As in cases in other states, litigants pointed to the provisions of state constitutions protecting religious liberty and maintained that Sunday laws were a blatant violation. Though typically unsuccessful (most state supreme courts upheld the constitutionality of Sunday laws), these constitutional challenges helped set a pattern by which subsequent moral minorities would seek to protect religious freedom and minority rights.&lt;ref&gt;Kyle G. Volk, ''Moral Minorities and the Making of American Democracy'' (Oxford, 2014), 59-68, 190-201.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Supreme Court of the United States]] held in its landmark case, ''[[McGowan v. Maryland]]'' (1961), that [[Maryland]]'s blue laws violated neither the [[Free Exercise Clause]] nor the [[Establishment Clause]] of the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution]].&lt;ref&gt;''[[McGowan v. Maryland]]'', {{Ussc|366|420|1961}}.&lt;/ref&gt; It approved the state's blue law restricting commercial activities on Sunday, noting that while such laws originated to encourage [[church attendance|attendance at Christian churches]], the contemporary Maryland laws were intended to serve &quot;to provide a uniform day of rest for all citizens&quot; on a secular basis and to promote the secular values of &quot;health, safety, recreation, and general well-being&quot; through a common day of rest. That this day coincides with [[Christian Sabbath]] is not a bar to the state's secular goals; it neither reduces its effectiveness for secular purposes nor prevents adherents of other religions from observing their own holy days.&lt;ref&gt;''McGowan'', {{Ussc|366|420|1961|pin=445}} &quot;The present purpose and effect of most of our Sunday Closing Laws is to provide a uniform day of rest for all citizens; and the fact that this day is Sunday, a day of particular significance for the dominant Christian sects, does not bar the State from achieving its secular goals.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

''McGowan'' was but one of four Sunday closing cases decided together by the Court in May of 1961. In ''[[Gallagher v. Crown Kosher Super Market of Mass., Inc.]]'',&lt;ref&gt;''[[Gallagher v. Crown Kosher Super Market of Mass., Inc.]]'', {{Ussc|366|617|1961}}.&lt;/ref&gt; the Court ruled against a Kosher deli that closed on Saturday but was open on Sunday.  The other two cases were ''[[Braunfeld v. Brown]]'', &lt;ref&gt;''[[Braunfeld v. Brown]]'', {{ussc|366|599|1961}}.&lt;/ref&gt; and ''Two Guys from Harrison vs. McGinley''.&lt;ref&gt;''Two Guys from Harrison vs. McGinley'', {{ussc|366|582|1961}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://worldincrisis.org/NSLC/NSLC-9.htm The LANDMARK Cases], National Sunday Law Crisis. Retrieved May 21, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Chief Justice [[Earl Warren]] declared that &quot;the State seeks to set one day apart from all others as a day of rest, repose, recreation and tranquility--a day which all members of the family and community have the opportunity to spend and enjoy together, a day on which there exists relative quiet and disassociation from the everyday intensity of commercial activities, a day on which people may visit friends and relative who are not available during working days.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldberg2000&quot;/&gt;

In March 2006, Texas judges upheld the state blue law that requires car dealerships to close either Saturday or Sunday each weekend.&lt;ref name=&quot;kvia.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.kvia.com/Global/story.asp?S=4669315 &quot;'Blue Law' for car sales upheld by Judge&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080531032841/http://www.kvia.com/Global/story.asp?S=4669315 |date=May 31, 2008 }}, [[KVIA]], March 22, 2006. Retrieved May 28, 2008. &quot;A Texas judge has upheld an old law that requires car dealerships in the Lone Star state to close one day each weekend. They must now choose to open either Saturday or Sunday.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Desuetude]]
* [[Dry county]]
* [[Neo-prohibitionism]]
* [[Raines law]]
* [[Religious law]]
* [[Sunday shopping]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
* Algeo, Matthew (2006). ''Last Team Standing''. Philadelphia: Da Capo Press. {{ISBN|978-0-306-81472-3}}
* Ruck, Rob; with Patterson, Maggie Jones and Weber, Michael P. (2010). ''Rooney: A Sporting Life''. Lincoln, Neb.: University of Nebraska Press. {{ISBN|978-0-8032-2283-0}}
* Volk, Kyle G. (2014). ''Moral Minorities and the Making of American Democracy''. New York: Oxford University Press. {{ISBN|019937192X}}.
* Westcott, Rich (2001). ''A Century of Philadelphia Sports''. Philadelphia: Temple University Press. {{ISBN|978-1-56639-861-9}}

==External links==
* [https://litigation-essentials.lexisnexis.com/webcd/app?action=DocumentDisplay&amp;crawlid=1&amp;srctype=smi&amp;srcid=3B15&amp;doctype=cite&amp;docid=60+Vand.+L.+Rev.+1273&amp;key=0bb1c77e13ff46d548b229939805df78 Red, White, but Mostly Blue: The Validity of Modern Sunday Closing Laws Under the Establishment Clause - Vanderbilt Law Review (2007)]
* [http://digital.library.okstate.edu/encyclopedia/entries/B/BL014.html Encyclopedia of Oklahoma History and Culture – Blue Laws]
* [http://www.mass.gov/lwd/labor-standards/dls/mass-blue-laws/ The Massachusetts Blue Laws]
* [http://www.pantagraph.com/news/local/sunday-movies-come-to-bloomington-in/article_27ea9b0c-a481-11e2-889a-001a4bcf887a.html Blue Law - Pantagraph] (Bloomington, Illinois newspaper)

{{DEFAULTSORT:Blue Law}}
[[Category:Political terminology of the United States]]
[[Category:Religion and law]]
[[Category:Sunday shopping]]
[[Category:Sabbath in Christianity]]</text>
      <sha1>7eoayefp64v4o6i5xjmm293wahyik5i</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
