  <page>
    <title>Ballroom dance</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3332</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941102263</id>
      <parentid>939901908</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-16T16:33:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>PPEMES</username>
        <id>16917609</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|a set of partner dances}}
[[File:Michael Foskett &amp; Nika Vlasenko 2.JPG|thumb|WDC World Youth (Under 21) Champions 2013, Michael Foskett &amp; Nika Vlasenko]]
'''Ballroom dance''' is a set of [[partner dance]]s, which are enjoyed both [[social dance|socially]] and [[ballroom dance#Competitive dancing|competitively]] around the world. Because of its [[performance dance|performance]] and [[entertainment]] aspects, ballroom dance is also widely enjoyed on stage, film, and television.

''Ballroom dance'' may refer, at its widest definition, to almost any recreational dance with a partner.  However, with the emergence of dance competition (now known as [[Dancesport]]), two principal schools have emerged and the term is used more narrowly to refer to the dances recognized by those schools.

* The International School, originally developed in England&lt;ref name=Franks&gt;Franks A.H. 1963. ''Social dance: a short history''. Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, London.&lt;/ref&gt; and now regulated by the [[World Dance Council]] ([https://www.wdcdance.com/ WDC]) and the [[World DanceSport Federation]] ([https://www.worlddancesport.org/ WDSF]), is most prevalent in Europe.  It encompasses two categories, Standard and Latin, each of which consist of five dances—International Waltz, International Tango, International Viennese Waltz, International Slow Foxtrot, and International Quickstep in the Standard category and International Samba, International Cha Cha, International Rumba, International Paso Doble, and International Jive in the Latin category.  A &quot;Standard&quot; or &quot;Latin&quot; competition encompasses all five dances in the respective category, and a &quot;Ten Dance&quot; competition encompasses all ten dances.  The two styles, while differing in technique, rhythm, and costumes, exemplify core elements of ballroom dancing such as control and cohesiveness.
* The American School, also called North American School, is most prevalent in the United States and Canada, where it's regulated by [https://usadance.org/ USA Dance] and Canada Dancesport ([http://www.dancesport.ca/ CDS]) -- the respective national member bodies of the WDSF.  It also consists of two categories analogous to the Standard and Latin categories of the International School, respectively called Smooth and Rhythm.  The Smooth category consists of only four dances—American Waltz, American Tango, American Foxtrot, and American Viennese Waltz, omitting American Peabody (the American School equivalent to Quickstep) -- while the dances selected for competition in the Rhythm category are American Cha Cha, American Rumba, American East Coast Swing (the American School equivalent to International Jive), American Bolero, and American Mambo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Dancesport Rulebook 2019 |url=https://cdn.ymaws.com/usadance.org/resource/resmgr/governance/rules/2019a_dancesport_rulebook_ed.pdf |website=USA Dance, Inc. |publisher=USA Dance, Inc. |accessdate=5 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=CDS Constitution and Bylaws/Reglement Generaux |url=http://www.dancesport.ca/attachments/File/Rules/2018-19%20CDS%20Rule%20Book%20.pdf |website=Canada Dancesport/Dansesport Canada |publisher=Canada Dancesport/Dansesport Canada |accessdate=5 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A &quot;Smooth&quot; or &quot;Rhythm&quot; competition encompasses the dances in the respective category, and a &quot;Nine Dance&quot; competition encompassing all nine of these dances is analogous to the &quot;Ten Dance&quot; competition of the International School.  USA Dance additionally recognizes American Peabody, American Merengue, American Paso Doble, American Samba, American West Coast Swing, American Polka, and American Hustle as ballroom dances in which sanctioned competition may take place.

Note that dances of the two schools that bear the same name may differ considerably in permitted patterns (figures), technique, and styling.

Exhibitions and social situations that feature ballroom dancing also may include additional partner dances such as Lindy Hop, Night Club Two Step, Night Club Swing, Bachata, Country Two Step, and regional (local or national) favorites that normally are not regarded as part of the ballroom family, and a number of historical dances also may be danced in ballrooms or salons.  Additionally, some sources regard Sequence Dancing, in pairs or other formations, to be a style of ballroom dance.&lt;ref&gt;Silvester, Victor 1980. ''Old Time and sequence dancing''. Barrie and Jenkins, London.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Definitions and history ==
[[File:Galliard.jpg|right|thumb|130px|Galliard in [[Siena]], Italy, 15th century]]
The term 'ballroom dancing' is derived from the word ''ball'' which in turn originates from the Latin word ''ballare'' which means 'to dance' (a ball-room being a large room specially designed for such dances). In times past, ballroom dancing was [[Social dance|social dancing]] for the privileged, leaving [[folk dancing]] for the lower classes. These boundaries have since become blurred. The definition of ballroom dance also depends on the era: balls have featured popular dances of the day such as the [[Minuet]], [[Quadrille]], [[Polonaise]], [[Polka]], [[Mazurka]], and others, which are now considered to be [[historical dance]]s.

=== Early modern period ===
The first authoritative knowledge of the earliest ballroom dances was recorded toward the end of the 16th century, when Jehan Tabourot, under the pen name &quot;[[Thoinot Arbeau|Thoinot-Arbeau]]&quot;, published in 1588 his ''Orchésographie'', a study of late 16th-century French renaissance social dance. Among the dances described were the solemn [[basse danse]], the livelier [[branle]], [[pavane]], and the [[galliarde]] which [[Shakespeare]] called the &quot;cinq pace&quot; as it was made of five steps.&lt;ref name=silvester/&gt;

In 1650 the [[Minuet]], originally a peasant dance of [[Poitou]], was introduced into Paris and set to music by [[Jean-Baptiste Lully]] and danced by the King [[Louis XIV]] in public. The Minuet dominated the ballroom from that time until the close of the 18th century.

Toward the later half of the 16th century, Louis XIV founded his '[[Académie Royale de Musique|Académie Royale de Musique et de Danse]]', where specific rules for the execution of every dance and the &quot;[[Positions of the feet in ballet|five positions]]&quot; of the feet were formulated for the first time by members of the Académie. Eventually, the first definite cleavage between ballet and ballroom came when professional dancers appeared in the ballets, and the ballets left the Court and went to the stage. Ballet technique such as the [[Turnout (ballet)|turned out]] positions of the feet, however, lingered for over two centuries and past the end of the Victoria era.&lt;ref name=silvester /&gt;

===19th century===
[[File:Vernon and Irene Castle2.jpg|thumb|right|200px|[[Vernon and Irene Castle]], early ballroom dance pioneers, c. 1910–18]]
The waltz with its modern hold took root in England in about 1812; in 1819 [[Carl Maria von Weber]] wrote ''[[Invitation to the Dance (Weber)|Invitation to the Dance]]'', which marked the adoption of the waltz form into the sphere of absolute music. The dance was initially met with tremendous opposition due to the semblance of impropriety associated with the closed hold, though the stance gradually softened.&lt;ref name=silvester&gt;Silvester, Victor 1993. ''Modern Ballroom Dancing''; rev. ed. London: Stanley Paul. (1st edition: London: H. Jenkins, 1927)&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1840s several new dances made their appearance in the ballroom, including the [[polka]], [[mazurka]], and the [[Schottische]]. In the meantime a strong tendency emerged to drop all 'decorative' steps such as ''entrechats'' and ''ronds de jambes'' that had found a place in the Quadrilles and other dances.

=== Early 20th century ===
Modern ballroom dance has its roots early in the 20th century, when several different things happened more or less at the same time. The first was a movement away from the sequence dances towards dances where the couples moved independently. This had been pre-figured by the waltz, which had already made this transition. The second was a wave of popular music, such as [[jazz]]. Since dance is to a large extent tied to music, this led to a burst of newly invented dances. There were many dance crazes in the period 1910–1930.

The third event was a concerted effort to transform some of the dance crazes into dances which could be taught to a wider dance public in the U.S. and Europe. Here [[Vernon and Irene Castle]] were important, and so was a generation of English dancers in the 1920s, including [[Josephine Bradley]] and [[Victor Silvester]]. These professionals analysed, codified, published, and taught a number of standard dances. It was essential, if popular dance was to flourish, for dancers to have some basic movements they could confidently perform with any partner they might meet. Here the huge [[Arthur Murray]] organisation in America, and the dance societies in England, such as the [[Imperial Society of Teachers of Dancing]], were highly influential. Finally, much of this happened during and after a period of World War, and the effect of such a conflict in dissolving older social customs was considerable.&lt;ref name=Franks/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Richardson P.J S. 1948. ''The history of English ballroom dancing (1900–1945)''. London: Jenkins&lt;/ref&gt;

Later, in the 1930s, the on-screen dance pairing of [[Fred Astaire]] and [[Ginger Rogers]] influenced all forms of dance in the U.S. and elsewhere. Although both actors had separate careers, their filmed dance sequences together, which included portrayals of the Castles, have reached iconic status.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.musicals101.com/1930film3.htm |title=History of Musical Film, by John Kenrick |year=1996 |accessdate=2008-05-29 |publisher=Musicals101.com| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080511172708/http://www.musicals101.com/1930film3.htm| archivedate= 11 May 2008 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Much of Astaire and Rogers' work portrayed social dancing, although the performances were highly choreographed (often by Astaire or [[Hermes Pan (choreographer)|Hermes Pan]]) and meticulously staged and rehearsed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/19980215/REVIEWS08/401010363/1023 |title=Review of &quot;Swing Time&quot; (1936) |date=1998-02-15 |accessdate=2008-05-29 |publisher=[[Roger Ebert|rogerebert.com]] |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080503164308/http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=%2F19980215%2FREVIEWS08%2F401010363%2F1023 |archivedate=2008-05-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Competitive dancing ==
{{Main|Dancesport}}
[[File:Ballroom dance competition cha cha 3.jpg|thumb|right|Young couple dancing [[Cha-cha-cha (dance)|cha-cha-cha]] at a junior Latin dance competition in the [[Czech Republic]]]]

Competitions, sometimes referred to as [[dancesport]], range from world championships, regulated by the [[World Dance Council]] (WDC), to less advanced dancers at various proficiency levels. Most competitions are divided into professional and amateur, though in the USA [[pro-am]] competitions typically accompany professional competitions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unitedstatesdancechampionships.com/ USDC] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070311000126/http://www.unitedstatesdancechampionships.com/ |date=2007-03-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[International Olympic Committee]] now recognizes [[competitive dance|competitive]] ballroom dance.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.idsf.net/index.tpl?id=30 Certificate of Olympic recognition of WDSF] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100626010044/http://www.idsf.net/index.tpl?id=30 |date=2010-06-26 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It has recognized another body, the [[World DanceSport Federation]] (WDSF), as the sole representative body for dancesport in the [[Olympic Games]]. However, it seems doubtful that dance will be included in the Olympic Games, especially in light of efforts to reduce the number of participating sports.{{citation needed|date=July 2013}}

Ballroom dance competitions are regulated by each country in its own way. There are about 30 countries which compete regularly in international competitions. There are another 20 or so countries which have membership of the WDC and/or the WDSF, but whose dancers rarely appear in international competitions.&lt;ref&gt;Complete listings of affiliations are given in the programmes of the major competitions.&lt;/ref&gt; In Britain there is the [[British Dance Council]], which grants national and regional championship titles, such as the British Ballroom Championships, the [[British Sequence Championships]] and the United Kingdom Championships. In the United States, the member branches of the WDC (National Dance Council of America) and the WDSF ([[USA Dance]]) both grant national and regional championship titles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.unitedstatesdancechampionships.com/ |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2007-03-20 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070311000126/http://www.unitedstatesdancechampionships.com/ |archivedate=2007-03-11 }}  USDC&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.usadancenationals.com/ |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2017-03-23 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170508194905/http://www.usadancenationals.com/ |archivedate=2017-05-08 }} USA Dance Nationals&lt;/ref&gt;

Ballroom dancing competitions in the former USSR also included the [[Soviet Ballroom dances]], or ''Soviet Programme''. Australian [[New Vogue (dance)|New Vogue]] is danced both competitively and socially. In competition, there are 15 recognized New Vogue dances, which are performed by the competitors in sequence. These dance forms are not recognized internationally, neither are the US variations such as American Smooth, and Rhythm. Such variations in dance and competition methods are attempts to meets perceived needs in the local market-place.

Internationally, the [[Blackpool Dance Festival]], hosted annually at [[Blackpool]], England is considered the most prestigious event a dancesport competitor can attend.

[[Formation dance]] is another style of competitive dance recognized by the WDSF. In this style, multiple dancers (usually in couples and typically up to 16 dancers at one time) compete on the same team, moving in and out of various formations while dancing.

=== Elements of competition ===
[[File:MIT 2006 Latin Intermediate.jpg|thumb|Intermediate level international style Latin dancing at the 2006 [[Massachusetts Institute of Technology|MIT]] ballroom dance competition. A judge stands in the foreground.]]

In competitive ballroom, dancers are judged by diverse criteria such as poise, the hold or frame, posture, musicality and expression, timing, body alignment and shape, floor craft, foot and leg action, and presentation. Judging in a performance-oriented sport is inevitably subjective in nature, and controversy and complaints by competitors over judging placements are not uncommon. The scorekeepers—called scrutineers—will tally the total number recalls accumulated by each couple through each round until the finals when the [[Skating system]] is used to place each couple by ordinals, typically 1–6, though the number of couples in the final may vary. Sometimes, up to 8 couples may be present on the floor during the finals.

Competitors dance at different levels based on their ability and experience. The levels are split into two categories, syllabus and open. The syllabus levels are newcomer/pre-bronze, bronze, silver, and gold—with gold the highest syllabus level and newcomer the lowest. In these levels, moves are restricted to those written in a syllabus, and illegal moves can lead to disqualification. Each level, bronze, silver, and gold, has different moves on their syllabus, increasing in difficulty. There are three levels in the open category; novice, pre-champ, and champ in increasing order of skill. At those levels, dancers no longer have restrictions on their moves, so complex routines are more common.

=== Medal evaluations ===
Medal evaluations for amateurs enable dancers' individual abilities to be recognized according to conventional standards. In medal evaluations, which are run by bodies such as the [[Imperial Society of Teachers of Dancing]] (ISTD) and the [[United Kingdom Alliance (UKA)]], each dancer performs two or more dances in a certain genre in front of a judge. Genres such as Modern Ballroom or Latin are the most popular. Societies such as the ISTD and UKA also offer medal tests on other dance styles (such as Country &amp; Western, Rock 'n Roll or Tap). In some North American examinations, levels include Newcomer, Bronze, Silver, Gold, Novice, Pre-championship, and Championship; each level may be further subdivided into either two or four separate sections.

== Collegiate ballroom ==
[[File:Colligate ballroom.jpg|right|thumb|People on the dance floor waiting to dance and compete.]]
There is a part of the ballroom world dedicated to college students. These chapters are typically clubs or teams that have an interest in ballroom dancing. Teams hold fundraisers, social events, and ballroom dance lessons. Ballroom dance teams' goals are to have fun and learn to dance well. There is a strong focus on finding a compatible dance partner and bonding with teammates. There is also a competitive side to collegiate ballroom - collegiate teams often hold competitions and invite other teams to participate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Ballroom 101|url=http://usadance.org/college/ballroom-101/|publisher=USA Dance, Inc.|accessdate=9 April 2014|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140413155208/http://usadance.org/college/ballroom-101/|archivedate=13 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; These competitions are often run with many of the same rules are regular amateur competitions as outlined above, but are usually organized entirely by collegiate teams. Examples include the MIT Open Ballroom Dance Competition, Purdue Ballroom Classic, Cardinal Classic, Berkeley Classic, and Harvard Invitational.

== Dances ==
&quot;Ballroom dance&quot; refers most often to the ten dances of '''Standard''' and '''Latin''', though the term is also often used interchangeably with the five International Ballroom dances.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url= http://linus.socs.uts.edu.au/%7Edon/pubs/modern.html| title= History of Modern Ballroom Dancing| accessdate= 2007-02-20| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070226125005/http://linus.socs.uts.edu.au/~don/pubs/modern.html| archivedate= 26 February 2007| url-status= dead| df= dmy-all}}.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sequence dancing]], which is danced predominantly in the United Kingdom, and its development [[New Vogue (dance)|New Vogue]] in Australia and New Zealand, are also sometimes included as a type of Ballroom dancing.

In the United States and Canada, the '''American Style''' ('''American Smooth''' and '''American Rhythm''') also exists. The dance technique used for both International and American styles is similar, but International Ballroom allows only [[Ballroom glossary#Closed position|closed dance positions]], whereas American Smooth allows closed, open and separated dance movements. In addition, different sets of dance figures are usually taught for the two styles. International Latin and American Rhythm have different styling, and have different dance figures in their respective syllabi.

Other dances sometimes placed under the umbrella &quot;ballroom dance&quot; include nightclub dances such as [[Lindy Hop]], [[West Coast swing]], [[nightclub two step]], [[Hustle (dance)|hustle]], [[Salsa (dance)|salsa]], and [[merengue (dance)|merengue]]. The categorization of dances as &quot;ballroom dances&quot; has always been fluid, with new dances or folk dances being added to or removed from the ballroom repertoire from time to time, so no list of subcategories or dances is any more than a description of current practices. There are other dances historically accepted as ballroom dances, and are revived via the [[vintage dance]] movement.

In Europe, Latin Swing dances include [[Argentine tango]], [[Mambo (dance)|mambo]], [[Lindy Hop]], swing boogie (sometimes also known as nostalgic boogie), and [[discofox]]. One example of this is the subcategory of [[cajun dance]]s that originated in [[Acadiana]], with branches reaching both coasts of the United States.

Standard/Smooth dances are normally danced to Western music (often from the mid-twentieth century), and couples dance counter-clockwise around a rectangular floor following the [[Ballroom glossary#Line of dance|line of dance]]. In competitions, competitors are costumed as would be appropriate for a [[white tie]] affair, with full gowns for the ladies and [[bow tie]] and [[tail coat]]s for the men; though in American Smooth it is now conventional for the men to abandon the tailsuit in favor of shorter [[tuxedo (clothing)|tuxedo]]s, vests, and other creative outfits.

Latin/Rhythm dances are commonly danced to contemporary Latin American music and (in case of jive) Western music. With the exception of a few traveling dances like [[Samba (ballroom)|samba]] and [[pasodoble]], couples do not follow the line of dance but perform their routines more or less in one spot. In competitions, the women are often dressed in short-skirted Latin outfits while the men are outfitted in tight-fitting shirts and pants, the goal being to emphasize the dancers' leg action and body movements.

== Competitive dances ==
[[File:Tango ballroom standard.png|thumb|180px|Victor Fung and Anna Mikhed dancing a [[Tango (ballroom)|tango]] in 2006. The couple, dancing for the US, came third in the Professional [[World Ballroom Dance Championship|World Championship]] 2009.]]

===Standard/Smooth===
==== Waltz ====
{{Main|Waltz (International Standard)}}
Waltz began as a country folk dance in [[Austria]] and [[Bavaria]] in the 17th century. In the early 19th century it was introduced in England. It was the first dance where a man held a woman close to his body. When performing the dance, the upper body is kept to the left throughout all figures, follow's body leaves the right side of the lead while the head is extended to follow the elbow. Figures with rotation have little rise. The start of the rise begins slowly from the first count, peaks on the 2nd count and lowers slowly on the 3rd. Sway is also used on the second step to make the step longer and also to slow down the momentum by bringing the feet together. Waltz is performed for both International Standard and American Smooth.

==== Viennese Waltz ====
{{Main|Viennese Waltz}}
Viennese waltz originated in [[Provence]] area in France in 1559 and is recognized as the oldest of all ballroom dances. It was introduced in England as German waltz in 1812 and became popular throughout the 19th century by the music of [[Josef Strauss|Josef]] and [[Johann Strauss II|Johann Strauss]]. It is often referred to as the classic “old-school” ballroom. Viennese Waltz music is quite fast. Slight shaping of the body moves towards the inside of the turn and shaping forward and up to lengthen the opposite side from direction. Reverse turn is used to travel down long side and is overturned. While natural turn is used to travel short side and is underturned to go around the corners. Viennese waltz is performed for both International Standard and American Smooth.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.dancecentral.info/ballroom/international-style|title=International Style - DanceCentral.info|website=www.dancecentral.info|access-date=2017-05-05|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170514234052/http://www.dancecentral.info/ballroom/international-style|archivedate=2017-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.pbs.org/americas-ballroom-challenge/ballroom-dance-styles/|title=Ballroom Dance Styles {{!}} America's Ballroom Challenge {{!}} PBS|website=Ballroom Dance Styles {{!}} America's Ballroom Challenge {{!}} PBS|access-date=2017-05-05|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170505151122/http://www.pbs.org/americas-ballroom-challenge/ballroom-dance-styles/|archivedate=2017-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.justdanceballroom.com/styles.html#waltz|title=Just Dance Ballroom :: Dance Styles|website=www.justdanceballroom.com|access-date=2017-05-05|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170429183138/http://www.justdanceballroom.com/styles.html#waltz|archivedate=2017-04-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Tango ====
{{Main|Tango}}
Tango originated in [[Buenos Aires]] in the late 19th century. Modern [[Argentine tango]] is danced in both open and closed embraces which focuses on the lead and follow moving in harmony of the tango's passionate charging music. The tango's technique is like walking to the music while keeping feet grounded and allowing ankles and knees to brush against one another during each step taken. Tango is a flat-footed dance and unlike the other dances, has no rise and fall. Body weight is kept over the toes and the connection is held between the dancers in the hips.

[[Ballroom tango]], however, is a dance with a far more open frame, often utilising strong and [[staccato]] movements. Ballroom tango, rather than Argentine tango, is performed in international competition.

==== Foxtrot ====
{{Main|Foxtrot}}
The foxtrot is an American dance, believed to be of African-American origin. It was named by a [[vaudeville]] performer [[Harry Fox]] in 1914. Fox was rapidly trotting step to [[ragtime]] music. The dance therefore was originally named as the “Fox’s trot”. The foxtrot can be danced at slow, medium, or fast tempos depending on the speed of the jazz or big band music. The partners are facing one another and frame rotates from one side to another, changing direction after a measure. The dance is flat, with no rise and fall. The walking steps are taken as slow for the two beats per steps and quick for one beat per step. Foxtrot is performed for both International Standard and American Smooth.

==== Quickstep ====
{{Main|Quickstep}}
The quickstep is an English dance and was invented in the 1920s as a combination of faster tempo of foxtrot and the [[Charleston (dance)|Charleston]]. It is a fast moving dance, so men are allowed to close their feet and the couples move in short syncopated steps. Quickstep includes the walks, runs, chasses, and turns of the original foxtrot dance, with some other fast figures such as locks, hops, run, quick step, jump and skips. Quick step is performed as an International Standard dance.

===Latin/Rhythm===
==== Pasodoble ====
{{Main|Pasodoble}}
The pasodoble originated from Spain and its dramatic bullfights. The dance is mostly performed only in competitions and rarely socially because of its many choreographic rules. The lead plays the role of the [[Bullfighter|matador]] while the follow takes the role of the matador's cape, the bull, or even the matador. The chassez cape refers to the lead using the follow to turn them as if they are the cape, and the apel is when the lead stomps their foot to get the bull's attention. Pasodoble is performed as an International Latin dance.

==== Spanish bolero ====
{{Main|Bolero (Spanish dance)}}
The Spanish bolero was developed in the late 18th century out of the ''[[seguidilla]]'', and its popularization is attributed to court dancers such as [[Sebastiano Carezo|Sebastián Cerezo]]. It became one of the most popular ballroom dances of the 19th century and saw many classical adaptations. However, by the 20th century it had become old-fashioned. A Cuban music genre of the same name, [[bolero]], which became popular in the early 20th century, is unrelated to the Spanish dance.

====Cuban bolero====
{{Main|Bolero}}
Although Cuban bolero was born as a form of ''[[trova]]'', traditional singer/songwriter tradition from eastern Cuba, with no associated dance, it soon became a ballroom favorite in Cuba and all of Latin America. The dance most commonly represents the couple falling in love. Modern bolero is seen as a combination of many dances: like a slow salsa with contra-body movement of tango, patterns of rhumba, and rise and fall technique and personality of waltz and foxtrot. Bolero can be danced in a closed hold or singly and then coming back together. It is performed as an American Rhythm dance.

==== Samba ====
{{Main|Samba (Brazilian dance)}}
Samba is the national dance of [[Brazil]]. The rhythm of samba and its name originated from the language and culture of West African slaves. In 1905, samba became known to other countries during an exhibition in Paris. In the 1940s, samba was introduced in America through [[Carmen Miranda]]. The international version of Ballroom Samba has been based on an early version of Brazilian Samba called Maxixe, but has since developed away and differs strongly from Brazilian Ballroom Samba, which is called Samba de Gafieira. International Ballroom Samba is danced with a slight bounce which is created through the bending and straightening the knee. It is performed as an International Latin dance, although most of its modern development has occurred outside Latin America.

==== Rhumba ====
{{Main|Rhumba}}
Rhumba came to the United States from Cuba in the 1920s and became a popular [[cabaret]] dance during [[Prohibition in the United States|prohibition]]. Rhumba is a ballroom adaptation of [[son cubano]] and [[bolero]] (the Cuban genre) and, despite its name, it rarely included elements of [[Cuban rumba]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Daniel|first1=Yvonne|editor1-last=Malnig|editor1-first=Julie|title=Ballroom, Boogie, Shimmy Sham, Shake: A Social and Popular Dance Reader|date=2009|publisher=University of Illinois|location=Chicago, IL|page=162|url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=zCSDBjRqC5EC|chapter=Rumba Then and Now}}&lt;/ref&gt; It includes Cuban motions through knee-strengthening, figure-eight hip rotation, and swiveling foot action. An important characteristic of rhumba is the powerful and direct lead achieved through the ball of the foot. Rhumba is performed for both International Latin and American Rhythm.

==== Mambo ====
{{Main|Mambo (dance)}}
Mambo was developed as an offshoot of [[danzón]], the national dance of Cuba, in the late 1930s by [[Orestes López]] and his brother [[Cachao]], of [[Arcaño y sus Maravillas]]. They conceived a new form of danzón influenced by [[son cubano]], with a faster, improvised final section, which allowed dancers to more freely express themselves, given that danzón had traditionally a very rigid structure. In the 1940s, [[Dámaso Pérez Prado]] transformed the mambo from the charanga into the [[big band]] format, and took it to Mexico and the United States, where it became a &quot;dance craze&quot;.

==== Cha Cha ====
{{Main|Cha-cha-cha (dance)}}
Cha Cha (sometimes wrongly called Cha Cha Cha based on a &quot;street version&quot; of the dance with shifted timing) was delevoped by [[Enrique Jorrín]] in the early 1950s, as a slower alternative to Mambo—and, in fact, was originally called Triple Mambo. The Cha Cha is a flirtatious dance with many hip rotations and partners synchronising their movements. The dance includes bending and straightening of the knee giving it a touch of Cuban motion. Cha-cha is performed for both International Latin and American Rhythm.

==== East Coast Swing ====
{{Main|East Coast Swing}}
Swing in 1927 was originally named the [[Lindy Hop]] named by [[George Snowden|Shorty George Snowden]]. There have been 40 different versions documented over the years; most common is the East Coast swing which is performed in the American Smooth (or American Rhythm) only in the U.S. or Canada. The East Coast swing was established by Arthur Murray and others only shortly after World War II. Swing music is very lively and upbeat and can be danced to jazz or big band music. The swing dancing is a style with lots of bounce and energy. Swing also includes many spins and underarm turns. East Coast swing is performed as an American Rhythm dance.

==== Jive ====
{{Main|Jive (dance)}}
The jive is part of the [[Swing (dance)|swing dance]] group and is a very lively variation of the [[jitterbug]]. Jive originated from African American clubs in the early 1940s. During World War II, American soldiers introduced the jive in England where it was adapted to today's competitive jive. In jive, the man leads the dance while the woman encourages the man to ask them to dance. It is danced to [[big band]] music, and some technique is taken from salsa, swing and tango. Jive is performed as an International Latin dance.

== Dance style classification ==
===  International Style competition dances ===

According to [[World Dance Council]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dancewdc.org/downloads/WDC%20Competition%20Rules%20current%20June%202015.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=October 26, 2015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150910165950/http://www.dancewdc.org/downloads/WDC%20Competition%20Rules%20current%20June%202015.pdf |archivedate=September 10, 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Standard====
'''[[Waltz (International Standard)|Waltz]]''':
28 bars per minute, {{music|time|3|4}} time, also known as ''Slow Waltz'' or ''English Waltz'' depending on locality

'''[[Ballroom tango|Tango]]''':
32 bars per minute, {{music|time|4|4}} time

'''[[Viennese Waltz]]''':
60 bars per minute, {{music|time|3|4}} time.
On the European continent, the Viennese waltz is known simply as ''waltz'', while the [[waltz]] is recognized as ''English waltz'' or ''Slow Waltz''.

'''[[Foxtrot]]''':
28 bars per minute, {{music|time|4|4}} time

'''[[Quickstep]]''':
50 bars per minute, {{music|time|4|4}} time

====Latin====
'''[[Cha-cha-cha (dance)|Cha-cha-cha]]''':
30 bars per minute, {{music|time|4|4}} time

'''[[Samba (ballroom)|Samba]]''':
48 bars per minute, {{music|time|2|4}} time

'''[[Rhumba|Rumba]]''':
24 bars per minute, {{music|time|4|4}} time

'''[[Paso Doble]]''':
56 bars per minute, {{music|time|2|4}} time

'''[[Jive (dance)|Jive]]''':
42 bars per minute, {{music|time|4|4}} time

=== American Style competition dances (only in the U.S. &amp; Canada) ===

====Smooth====
'''[[Waltz]]''':
29–30 bars per minute
30–32 bars per minute for Bronze

'''[[Ballroom tango|Tango]]''':
60 bars per minute
30–32 bars per minute for Bronze

'''[[Foxtrot (dance)|Foxtrot]]''':
30 bars per minute
32–34 bars per minute for Bronze

'''[[Viennese Waltz]]''':
53–54 bars per minute
54 bars per minute for Bronze

====Rhythm====
'''[[Cha-cha-cha (dance)|Cha Cha]]''':
30 bars per minute

'''[[Rhumba|Rumba]]''':
30–32 bars per minute
32–36 bars per minute for Bronze

'''[[East Coast Swing]]''':
36 bars per minute
34–36 bars per minute for Bronze

'''[[Bolero]]''':
24 bars per minute
24–26 bars per minute for Bronze

'''[[Mambo dance|Mambo]]''':
47 bars per minute
48–51 bars per minute for Bronze

=== Others ===
Historical/Vintage Ballroom dance:
:[[Waltz]] – [[Polka]] – [[Schottische]] – [[Tango (dance)|Tango]] – [[One-Step]] – [[Foxtrot (dance)|Foxtrot]] – [[Peabody (dance)|Peabody]]

Other dances occasionally categorized as ballroom:

: '''Nightclub'''
:[[Nightclub Two-step]] – [[Hustle (dance)|Hustle]] – [[Modern Jive]] / [[LeRoc]] / [[Ceroc]] – and the whole swing variety: [[West Coast Swing]] / [[East Coast Swing]]/ [[Lindy Hop]] (always included in the &quot;Rhythm-Swing&quot; category) / [[Carolina Shag]] / [[Collegiate Shag]] / [[Balboa (dance)|Balboa]] / [[Blues]] – [[Fusion dance|Fusion]]

: '''Latin nightclub'''
:[[Salsa (dance)|Salsa]] – [[Cumbia]] – [[Mambo (dance)|Mambo]] – [[Merengue (dance)|Merengue]] – [[Porro]] – [[Cha-cha-cha (dance)|Cha cha]] – [[Bachata (dance)|Bachata]]

: '''African nightclub'''
:[[Kizomba]] – [[Semba]] – [[Zouk]]

: '''Brazilian Dances'''
:[[Forró]] – [[Pagode]] – [[Samba de Gafieira]] – [[Lambada]] - Zouk-Lambada

: '''[[Country-western dance|Country/Western]]'''
:[[C/W Polka]] – [[C/W Cha-cha]] – [[Country-western two-step|C/W Two-step]] – [[C/W Waltz]]

: '''Cajun dances'''
:[[Cajun One Step]] or [[Cajun Jig]] – [[Two-step (dance move)|Cajun Two Step]] – [[Zydeco (dance)|Zydeco]] – [[Cajun Waltz]] – [[Cajun Jitterbug]]

: '''[[Bal-musette|Musette dances]]'''
:[[Java (dance)|Java]] – musette-waltz – musette-tango – musette-paso-doble

: '''Other'''
:[[Argentine tango]] – [[New Vogue (dance)|New Vogue]]

== See also ==
* [[Dance in Canada]]
* [[Sport in Austria#DanceSport in Austria|Dance sport in Austria]]
* [[Australian Dance Awards|Australian Dance]]
* [[Dancesport at the Asian Games]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book|last=Nott|first=James|title= Going to the Palais: a social and cultural history of dancing and dance halls in Britain, 1918-60 |date= 2015|publisher= OUP |isbn=9780199605194|url=https://global.oup.com/academic/product/going-to-the-palais-9780199605194}}
* [[Arthur Murray]],(1938) ''How To Become A Good Dancer'' {{ISBN|1447416767}}, {{ISBN|9781447416760}}
* Abra, Allison. &quot;Review of James Nott, Going to the palais: a social and cultural history of dancing and dance halls in Britain, 1918–1960.&quot; ''Contemporary British History'' (Sep 2016) 30#3 pp 432–433.
* {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150114135433/http://www.tdcomsa.com/niche_site/ballroom-dancing/ |title=Ballroom Dancing Judging Criteria}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
*Digitized material from the [https://www.loc.gov/collections/dance-instruction-manuals-from-1490-to-1920/about-this-collection/ American Ballroom Companion Collection: Dance Instruction Manuals] (ca. 1490-1920) in the [https://www.loc.gov/rr/rarebook/ Rare Book and Special Collections Division] of the [[Library of Congress]]
{{commons category|Ballroom dance}}
{{Dance}}
{{Parties}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ballroom Dance}}
[[Category:Ballroom dance| ]]
[[Category:Partner dance]]
[[Category:Social dance]]
[[Category:Dancesport]]
[[Category:Competitive dance]]</text>
      <sha1>aaqsdav4e2oru9ezo7c06r5jc3z0zon</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
