  <page>
    <title>Beadwork</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3398</id>
    <revision>
      <id>915535049</id>
      <parentid>914528613</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-09-13T20:55:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Monkbot</username>
        <id>20483999</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Native American beadwork */[[User:Monkbot/task 16: remove replace deprecated dead-url params|Task 16]]: replaced (1×) / removed (0×) deprecated |dead-url= and |deadurl= with |url-status=;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{More citations needed|date=July 2009}}
[[File:Beadwork on Container (2131611625).jpg|thumb|[[Ethiopia]]n beadwork on basket, from the ethnographic collection of the National Museum, [[Addis Ababa]]]]
'''Beadwork''' is the art or craft of attaching [[bead]]s to one another by stringing them with a [[sewing needle]] or beading needle and thread or thin wire, or sewing them to cloth.&lt;ref name=dict_beads&gt;{{cite dictionary|title=Beadwork|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/beadwork|dictionary=Merriam-Webster|accessdate=3 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beads come in a variety of materials, shapes and sizes. Beads are used to create [[jewellery|jewelry]] or other articles of personal adornment; they are also used in wall hangings and [[sculpture]] and many other artworks.

Beadwork techniques are broadly divided into [[Bead weaving|loom]] and [[Bead weaving|off-loom]] weaving, [[Bead stringing|stringing]], [[bead embroidery]], [[bead crochet]], [[bead knitting]], and [[bead tatting]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Tatted Lace of Beads, the Techniques of BEANILE LACE|last = Libin|first = Nina|publisher = LACIS|year = 1998|isbn = 0-916896-93-5|location = Berkeley, CA|pages = 112}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Beads, made of durable materials, survive in the archaeological record appearing with the very advent of modern man, ''[[Homo sapiens]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = The History of Beads: From 100,000 B.C. to the Present|last = Dubin|first = Lois Sherr|publisher = Harry N. Abrams|year = 2009|isbn = 978-0810951747|location = New York|pages = 16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Beads are used for [[religion|religious]] purposes, as good luck [[amulet|talismans]], for barter, and as curative agents.
[[File:MRAW Bellyband Tri Wing Ring from Contemporary Geometric Beadwork by Kate McKinnon .webm|thumb|MRAW Bellyband Tri Wing Ring from Contemporary Geometric Beadwork by Kate McKinnon]]

== Modern beading ==
[[File:Beadwork adaptation of Vittore Crivelli.jpg|thumb|Beadwork adaptation of painting by [[Vittore Crivelli]].]]
Modern beadwork is often used as a creative [[hobby]] to create [[jewelry]], [[handbag]]s, coasters, plus dozens of other crafts, and even copies of paintings. Beads are available in many different designs, sizes, colors, shapes, and materials, allowing much variation among bead artisans and projects. Simple projects can be created in less than an hour by novice beaders, while complex beadwork may take weeks of meticulous work with specialized tools and equipment. Many free patterns and tutorials can be found in Internet.

== Ancient beading ==
[[File:Broad Collar, ca. 1336-1327 B.C.E., ca. 1327-1323 B.C.E., or ca.1323-1295 B.C.E.,40.522.jpg|thumbnail|Broad Collar, c. 1336–1327 B.C.E., c. 1327–1323 B.C.E., or c. 1323–1295 B.C.E., 40.522, [[Brooklyn Museum]]]]
[[Egyptian faience|Faience]] is a mixture of powdered clays and lime, soda and silica sand. This is mixed with water to make a paste and molded around a small stick or bit of straw. It is then ready to be fired into a bead. As the bead heats up, the soda, sand and lime melt into glass that incorporates and covers the clay. The result is a hard bead covered in bluish glass.

This process was probably discovered first in [[Mesopotamia]] and then imported to [[ancient Egypt]]. However, it was the Egyptians who made it their own art form. Since before the [[First Dynasty of Egypt|1st dynasty]] of [[Narmer]] (3100 B.C.) to the last dynasty of the [[Ptolemaic Kingdom]] (33 B.C.) and to the present day, faience beads have been made in the same way.

These beads predate glass beads and were probably a forerunner of glass making. If a beadmaker was a little short of clay and had a little extra lime and the fire is hotter than usual, the mixture will become glass. In fact some early tubular faience beads are clayish at one end and pure glass at the other end. Apparently the beads weren't fired evenly.

The uneven beads were noticed early on, this led to experimentation, slowly at first. It took a long time for new ideas to be accepted in a conservative, agricultural society. One of the first variations to take hold was to color the faience beads by adding metallic salts. By the beginning of the eighteenth dynasty (1850 B.C.), faience making and glass making had become two separate crafts.

Faience beads were so common because they were cheaper and less labor-intensive to make than stone beads. Aside from personal use and daily wear they were used to create beaded netting to cover mummies. Most of the archaeological specimens come from burials.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Fernandes|first1=Beverly|title=Faience Beads from Egypt|url=http://www.harlequinbeads.com/faience-beads-from-egypt-article|accessdate=17 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As early as the [[Old Kingdom of Egypt|Old Kingdom]] (circa 2670–2195 B.C.), Egyptian artisans fashioned images of gods, kings, and mortals wearing broad collars made of molded tubular and teardrop beads. These beaded collars may have been derived from floral prototypes. In antiquity the collar was called a ''wesekh'', literally &quot;the broad one&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Broad Collar|url=http://www.brooklynmuseum.org/opencollection/objects/3453/Broad_Collar|accessdate=17 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Americas, the [[Cherokee]] used bead work to tell stories. They told them by the patterns in the beads. They used dried berries, gray Indian corn, teeth, bones, claws, or sometimes sea shells when they traded with coastal tribes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://nativeamerican-art.com/cherokee-art.html|title=Native American Art- Cherokee Beadwork and Basketry|website=nativeamerican-art.com|access-date=2017-11-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://visitcherokeenc.com/cherokee-beadwork/|title=Cherokee Indian Beadwork and Beading Patterns  {{!}} Cherokee, NC|last=Cherokee|first=Eastern Band of|website=Cherokee, NC|language=en|access-date=2017-11-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== 3D beading ==
[[File:Perlentier.JPG|thumb|230px|Polar bear made of seed beads]]
[[File:Beadknitting.JPG|thumb|230px|[[Bead knitting]] on double-pointed
 [[knitting needle]]s]]
3D beading generally uses the techniques of [[bead weaving]], which can be further divided into right angle weave and [[peyote stitch]].

Many 3D beading patterns are done in right angle weave, but sometimes both techniques are combined in the same piece. Both stitches are done using either fishing line or nylon thread. Fishing line lends itself better to right angle
weave because it is stiffer than nylon thread, so it holds the beads in a tighter arrangement and does not easily break when tugged upon.

Nylon thread is more suited to peyote stitch because it is softer and more pliable than fishing line, which permits the beads of
the stitch to sit straight without undue tension bending the arrangement out of place. Two needle right angle weave is done using both ends of the fishing
line, in which beads are strung in repeated circular arrangements, and the fishing line is pulled tight after each bead circle is made. Single needed right angle weave was popularized in the 90's by David Chatt and has become the norm.

Peyote
stitch is stitched using only one end of the nylon thread. The other end of the string is left dangling at the beginning of the piece, while the first end of the thread progresses through the stitch. In peyote stitch, beads are woven into the piece in a very similar fashion to knitting or cross stitching.

In fact, it is not uncommon for cross stitch patterns to be beaded in peyote stitch technique. Peyote stitch patterns are very easy to depict diagrammatically because they are typically stitched flat.

Right angle weave lends itself better to 3D beading, but peyote stitch offers the advantage of allowing the beads to be more tightly knit, which is sometimes necessary to portray an object properly in three dimensions.

== European beadwork ==
Beadwork in Europe has a history dating back millennia to a time when shells and animal bones were used as beads in [[necklace]]s.

Glass beads were being made in [[Murano]] by the end of the 14th century. French beaded flowers were being made as early as the 16th century, and [[murano beads|lampwork glass]] was invented in the 18th century. [[beads#Seed beads|Seed beads]] began to be used for embroidery, crochet, and numerous [[Bead weaving#Off-loom beadweaving|off-loom]] techniques.

== Native American beadwork ==
[[File:Nat Am beadwork sampler.jpg|thumb|right|230px|Examples of contemporary Native American beadwork]]
Beadwork is a [[Native American art]] form which evolved to  mostly use glass beads imported from Europe and recently Asia. Glass beads have been in use for almost five centuries in the Americas. Today a wide range of beading styles flourish.

Alongside the widespread popularity of glass beads, bead artists continue incorporating natural items such as [[Quillwork|dyed porcupine quills]], shell such as wampum, and dendrite, and even sea urchin spines in a similar manner as beads.

Wampum shell beads are ceremonially and politically important to a range of Eastern tribes,&lt;ref&gt;Dubin, p. 170-171&lt;/ref&gt; and were used to depict several important treaties between the Native peoples and the colonists, as in the case of the [[Two Row Wampum Treaty]].

In the Great Lakes, [[Ursulines|Ursuline]] nuns introduced floral patterns to tribes who quickly applied them to beadwork.&lt;ref&gt;Dubin, p. 50&lt;/ref&gt; [[Great Lakes]] tribes are known for their bandolier bags that might take an entire year to complete.&lt;ref&gt;Dubin, p. 218&lt;/ref&gt; During the 20th century the Plateau tribes, such as the [[Nez Perce (tribe)|Nez Perce]], perfected contour-style beadwork in which the lines of beads are stitched to emphasize the pictorial imagery. Plains tribes are master beaders, and today dance regalia for men and women feature a variety of beadwork styles. While Plains and Plateau tribes are renowned for their beaded [[Trap (carriage)|horse trappings]], Subarctic tribes such as the [[Dene]] create lavish beaded floral dog blankets.&lt;ref&gt;Berlo and Philips, p. 151&lt;/ref&gt; Eastern tribes have a completely different beadwork aesthetic: [[Innu]], [[Mi'kmaq people|Mi'kmaq]], [[Penobscot people|Penobscot]], and [[Haudenosaunee]] tribes are known for symmetrical scroll motifs in white beads, called the &quot;double curve.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Berlo and Phillips, p. 146&lt;/ref&gt; Iroquois are also known for &quot;embossed&quot; beading in which strings pulled taut force beads to pop up from the surface, creating a [[bas-relief]]. [[Tammy Rahr]] (Cayuga) is a contemporary practitioner of this style. [[Zuni people|Zuni]] artists have developed a tradition of three-dimensional beaded sculptures.

[[File:Huichol Trabajando.JPG|thumb|right|240px|Huichol bead artist, photo by Mario Jareda Beivide]][[Huichol people|Huichol]] Indians of [[Jalisco]] and [[Nayarit]], [[Mexico]] have a completely unique approach to beadwork. They adhere beads one by one to a surface such as wood or a gourd with a mixture of resin and beeswax.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Huichol Web of Life: Creation and Prayer {{!}} Lesson Two: Jicaras, Kukus and Seeds |last1=Hillman |first1=Paul |url=http://www.beadmuseumaz.org/Huichol/huichol4.htm |website=Community Arts Resource Exchange |publisher=The Bead Museum |accessdate=13 March 2009 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080518111414/http://www.beadmuseumaz.org/Huichol/huichol4.htm |archivedate=18 May 2008 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Most Native beadwork is created for tribal use, but beadworkers also create conceptual work for the art world. [[Richard Aitson]] ([[Kiowa]]-[[Apache]]), enjoying both an Indian and non-Indian audience, is known for his fully beaded [[cradle board|cradleboards]]. Another Kiowa beadworker, [[Teri Greeves]], has won top honors for her beadwork which consciously integrates both traditional and contemporary motifs such as beaded dancers on Converse high-tops. Greeves also beads on buckskin and explores such issues as warfare or Native American voting rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |last1=Lopez |first1=Antonio |title=Focus on Native Artists {{!}} Teri Greeves |magazine=Southwest Art Magazine |date=August 2000 |url=https://www.southwestart.com/articles-interviews/feature-articles/focus_artists |accessdate=13 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Marcus Amerman]], [[Choctaw]], one of today's most celebrated bead artists, pioneered a movement of highly realistic beaded portraits.&lt;ref&gt;Berlo and Phillips, p. 32&lt;/ref&gt; His imagery ranges from 19th century Native leaders to pop icons including [[Janet Jackson]] and [[Brooke Shields]].

Roger Amerman, Marcus' brother, and [[Martha Berry (artist)|Martha Berry]], [[Cherokee]], have effectively revived Southeastern beadwork, a style that had been lost because of the forced removal of their tribes to Indian Territory. Their beadwork commonly features white bead outlines, an echo of the shell beads or pearls Southeastern tribes used before contact.&lt;ref&gt;Berlo and Phillips, p. 87&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Jamie Okuma]] ([[Luiseño people|Luiseño]]-[[Shoshone]]-[[Bannock (tribe)|Bannock]]) has won top awards with her beaded dolls, which can include entire families or horses and riders, all with fully beaded regalia. The antique Venetian beads she uses can be as small as size 22°, about the size of a grain of salt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |last1=Indyke |first1=Dottie |title=Native Arts {{!}} Jamie Okuma |magazine=Southwest Art Magazine |date=May 2001 |url=https://www.southwestart.com/native-american-arts/jamie_okuma |accessdate=13 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Juanita Growing Thunder Fogarty]], Rhonda Holy Bear, and Charlene Holy Bear are also prominent beaded doll makers.

== See also ==
*[[Beetlewing]]
*[[French wire]]
*[[Jewelry wire gauge]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

*{{cite book |last= Berlo |first= Janet C. |authorlink=  |author2= Ruth B. Phillips |title= Native North American Art |series= Oxford History of Art |year= 1998 |publisher= Oxford University Press |isbn= 978-0-19-284218-3 |url-access= registration |url= https://archive.org/details/nativenorthameri00berl_0 }}
* Dubin, Lois Sherr (1999). ''North American Indian Jewelry and Adornment: From Prehistory to the Present.'' New York: Harry N. Abrams. {{ISBN|0-8109-3689-5}}
* Dubin, Lois Sherr (2009). ''The History of Beads: From 100,000 B.C. to the Present''. New York: Harry N. Abrams.  {{ISBN|978-0810951747}}.
* Beads and beadwork. (1996). ''In Encyclopedia of north american indians, Houghton Mifflin.'' Retrieved January 27, 2014, from http://search.credoreference.com/

== External links ==
&lt;!--==========================({{nomorelinks}})==============================

    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. WIKIPEDIA IS   |
    | NOT A COLLECTION OF LINKS NOR SHOULD IT BE USED FOR ADVERTISING.        |
    |                                                                         |
    |               Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    |  See [[Wikipedia:External links]] and [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.   |
    |                                                                         |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or       |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page.  Or submit your link    |
    | to the appropriate category at the Open Directory Project (www.dmoz.org)|
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.             |

==========================({{nomorelinks}})==============================--&gt;
{{Commons category|Beadwork}}
{{Wikivoyage|Bead shopping}}
{{beadwork}}
{{textile arts}}
{{decorative arts}}
{{Prehistoric technology}}

[[Category:Beadwork| 01]]
[[Category:Handicrafts]]
[[Category:Beadworkers|*]]
[[Category:Decorative arts]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]</text>
      <sha1>49kymozitzei45skhvfbpe2kz0zrokh</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
