  <page>
    <title>Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8622</id>
    <revision>
      <id>935540788</id>
      <parentid>935131890</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-13T05:35:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>199.188.194.190</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Fixed typo</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Principal protocol used to assign IPv4 addresses on an IPv4 network}}
{{Redirect|DHCP}}
{{IPstack}}

The '''Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol''' ('''DHCP''') is a [[network protocol|network management protocol]] used on [[Internet Protocol]] networks whereby a DHCP server dynamically assigns an [[IP address]] and other network configuration parameters to each device on a network so they can communicate with other IP networks.&lt;ref name=TechTarget&gt;TechTarget Network: [http://searchnetworking.techtarget.com/definition/DHCP DHCP (Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol)]&lt;/ref&gt; A DHCP server enables computers to request IP addresses and networking parameters automatically from the [[Internet service provider]] (ISP), reducing the need for a [[network administrator]] or a user to manually assign IP addresses to all network devices.&lt;ref name=TechTarget/&gt; In the absence of a DHCP server, a computer or other device on the network needs to be manually assigned an IP address, or to assign itself an [[APIPA]] address, which will not enable it to communicate outside its local subnet.

DHCP can be implemented on networks ranging in size from [[home network]]s to large [[campus network]]s and regional [[Internet service provider]] networks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Peterson |first1=Larry L. |last2=Davie |first2=Bruce S. |date=2011 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=BvaFreun1W8C&amp;pg=PA372&amp;lpg=PA372 |title=Computer Networks: A Systems Approach |publisher=Elsevier |isbn=0123850606 |edition=5th |accessdate=March 21, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Router (computing)|router]] or a [[residential gateway]] can be enabled to act as a DHCP server. Most residential network routers receive a globally unique IP address within the ISP network. Within a local network, a DHCP server assigns a local IP address to each device connected to the network.

==History==
In 1984, the [[Reverse Address Resolution Protocol]] (RARP), defined in RFC 903, was introduced to allow simple devices such as [[diskless workstation]]s to dynamically obtain a suitable IP address. However, because it acted at the [[data link layer]] it made implementation difficult on many server platforms, and also required that a server be present on each individual network link. RARP was superseded by the Bootstrap Protocol ([[BOOTP]]) defined in RFC 951 in September 1985. This introduced the concept of a ''relay agent'', which allowed the forwarding of BOOTP packets across networks, allowing one central BOOTP server to serve hosts on many IP subnets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc951#section-6 |title = RFC 951 - Bootstrap Protocol |author = Bill Croft |author2 = John Gilmore |date = September 1985 |work = Network Working Group }}&lt;/ref&gt;

DHCP is based on BOOTP but can dynamically allocate IP addresses from a pool and reclaim them when they are no longer in use. It can also be used to deliver a wide range of extra configuration parameters to IP clients, including platform-specific parameters.&lt;ref name=&quot;Network+ certification&quot;&gt;Network+ Certification 2006 Published By Microsoft Press.&lt;/ref&gt; DHCP was first defined in RFC 1531 in October 1993; but due to errors in the editorial process was almost immediately reissued as RFC 1541.

Four years later the DHCPINFORM message type&lt;ref&gt;used for the Web Proxy Autodiscovery Protocol [[Web Proxy Autodiscovery Protocol]] (WPAD)&lt;/ref&gt; and other small changes were added by RFC 2131; which {{as of | 2014 | lc = on}} remains the standard for IPv4 networks.

[[DHCPv6]] was initially described by RFC 3315 in 2003, but this has been updated by many subsequent RFCs.&lt;ref&gt;RFC 4361, RFC 5494, RFC 6221, RFC 6422, RFC 6644, RFC 7083, RFC 7227, RFC 7283&lt;/ref&gt; RFC 3633 added a DHCPv6 mechanism for [[prefix delegation]], and [[stateless address autoconfiguration]]  was added by RFC 3736.

=={{Anchor|LEASE}}Overview==
[[Internet Protocol]] (IP) defines how devices communicate within and across local networks on the Internet.  A DHCP server can manage IP settings for devices on its local network, e.g., by assigning IP addresses to those devices automatically and dynamically.

DHCP operates based on the [[client–server model]]. When a computer or other device connects to a network, the DHCP client software sends a DHCP [[Broadcasting (computing)|broadcast]] query requesting the necessary information. Any DHCP server on the network may service the request. The DHCP server manages a pool of IP addresses and information about client configuration parameters such as [[default gateway]], [[domain name]], the [[name server]]s, and [[time server]]s. On receiving a DHCP request, the DHCP server may respond with specific information for each client, as previously configured by an administrator, or with a specific address and any other information valid for the entire network and for the time period for which the allocation (''lease'') is valid. A DHCP client typically queries for this information immediately after [[booting]], and periodically thereafter before the expiration of the information. When a DHCP client refreshes an assignment, it initially requests the same parameter values, but the DHCP server may assign a new address based on the assignment policies set by administrators.

On large networks that consist of multiple links, a single DHCP server may service the entire network when aided by DHCP relay agents located on the interconnecting routers. Such agents relay messages between DHCP clients and DHCP servers located on different subnets.

Depending on implementation, the DHCP server may have three methods of allocating IP addresses:

;Dynamic allocation: A [[network administrator]] reserves a range of IP addresses for DHCP, and each DHCP client on the [[LAN]] is configured to request an IP address from the DHCP [[Server (computing)|server]] during network initialization. The request-and-grant process uses a lease concept with a controllable time period, allowing the DHCP server to reclaim and then reallocate IP addresses that are not renewed.

;Automatic allocation: The DHCP server permanently assigns an IP address to a requesting client from the range defined by the administrator. This is like dynamic allocation, but the DHCP server keeps a table of past IP address assignments, so that it can preferentially assign to a client the same IP address that the client previously had.

;Manual allocation: Also commonly called ''static allocation'' and ''reservations''.The DHCP server issues a private IP address dependent upon each client's ''client id'' (or, traditionally, the client [[MAC address]]), based on a predefined mapping by the administrator. This feature is variously called ''static DHCP assignment'' by [[DD-WRT]], ''fixed-address'' by the dhcpd documentation, ''address reservation'' by Netgear, ''DHCP reservation'' or ''static DHCP'' by [[Cisco]] and [[Linksys]], and ''IP address reservation'' or ''MAC/IP address binding'' by various other router manufacturers. If no match for the client's  ''client ID'' (if provided) or [[MAC address]] (if no client id is provided) is found, the server may or may not optionally fall back to either Dynamic or Automatic allocation.

DHCP is used for [[Internet Protocol version 4]] (IPv4) and [[IPv6]]. While both versions serve the same purpose, the details of the protocol for IPv4 and IPv6 differ sufficiently that they may be considered separate protocols.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title = The DHCP Handbook |year = 2003 |isbn = 978-0-672-32327-0 |first1= Ralph |last1=Droms |first2= Ted |last2=Lemon |publisher = [[SAMS Publishing]] |page = 436 }}&lt;/ref&gt; For the IPv6 operation, devices may alternatively use [[IPv6 stateless address autoconfiguration|stateless address autoconfiguration]]. IPv6 hosts may also use [[link-local addressing]] to achieve operations restricted to the local network link.

==Operation==
[[File:DHCP session.svg|thumb|right|upright=1.2|An illustration of a typical non-renewing DHCP session; each message may be either a broadcast or a [[unicast]], depending on the DHCP client capabilities.&lt;ref name=&quot;droms41&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2131#section-4.1|title=Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol|first=Ralph|last=Droms|website=tools.ietf.org|accessdate=4 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The DHCP employs a [[Connectionless communication|connectionless]] service model, using the [[User Datagram Protocol]] (UDP). It is implemented with two UDP port numbers for its operations which are the same as for the bootstrap protocol ([[BOOTP]]). UDP port number 67 is the destination port of a server, and UDP port number 68 is used by the client.

DHCP operations fall into four phases: server discovery, IP lease offer, IP lease request, and IP lease acknowledgement. These stages are often abbreviated as DORA for discovery, offer, request, and acknowledgement.

The DHCP operation begins with clients [[Broadcasting (computing)|broadcasting]] a request. If the client and server are on different subnets, a [[#Relaying|DHCP Helper or DHCP Relay Agent]] may be used. Clients requesting renewal of an existing lease may communicate directly via UDP [[unicast]], since the client already has an established IP address at that point. Additionally, there is a BROADCAST flag (1 bit in 2 byte flags field, where all other bits are reserved and so are set to 0) the client can use to indicate in which way (broadcast or unicast) it can receive the DHCPOFFER: 0x8000 for broadcast, 0x0000 for unicast.&lt;ref name=&quot;droms41&quot; /&gt; Usually, the DHCPOFFER is sent through unicast. For those hosts which cannot accept unicast packets before IP addresses are configured, this flag can be used to work around this issue.

===Discovery===
The DHCP client broadcasts a DHCPDISCOVER message on the network subnet using the destination address 255.255.255.255 (limited broadcast) or the specific subnet broadcast address (directed broadcast). A DHCP client may also request its last known IP address. If the client remains connected to the same network, the server may grant the request. Otherwise, it depends whether the server is set up as authoritative or not. An authoritative server denies the request, causing the client to issue a new request. A non-authoritative server simply ignores the request, leading to an implementation-dependent timeout for the client to expire the request and ask for a new IP address.

For example, if HTYPE is set to 1, to specify that the medium used is [[Ethernet]], HLEN is set to 6 because an Ethernet address (MAC address) is 6 octets long. The CHADDR is set to the MAC address used by the client. Some options are set as well.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+ Example DHCPDISCOVER message
|-
| colspan=4 |
Ethernet: source=sender's MAC; destination=FF:FF:FF:FF:FF:FF
|-
| colspan=4 |
IP: source=0.0.0.0; destination=255.255.255.255 &lt;br/&gt;
[[User Datagram Protocol|UDP]]: source port=68; destination port=67
|-
! Octet 0 !! Octet 1 !! Octet 2 !! Octet 3
|-
! OP !! HTYPE !! HLEN !! HOPS
|-
| 0x01 || 0x01 || 0x06 || 0x00
|-
! colspan=4 | XID
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x3903F326
|-
! colspan=2 | SECS !! colspan=2 | FLAGS
|-
| colspan=2 | 0x0000 || colspan=2 | 0x0000
|-
! colspan=4 | CIADDR (Client IP address)
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x00000000
|-
! colspan=4 | YIADDR (Your IP address)
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x00000000
|-
! colspan=4 | SIADDR (Server IP address)
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x00000000
|-
! colspan=4 | GIADDR (Gateway IP address)
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x00000000
|-
! colspan=4 | CHADDR (Client hardware address)
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x00053C04
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x8D590000
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x00000000
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x00000000
|-
| colspan=4 | 192 octets of 0s, or overflow space for additional options; [[BOOTP]] legacy.
|-
! colspan=4 | [[Magic cookie]]
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x63825363
|-
! colspan=4 | DHCP options
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x350101 53: 1 (DHCP Discover)
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x3204c0a80164 50: 192.168.1.100 requested
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x370401030f06 55 (Parameter Request List):{{unordered list
 | 1 (Request Subnet Mask),
 | 3 (Router),
 | 15 (Domain Name),
 | 6 (Domain Name Server)
}}
|-
| colspan=4 | 0xff 255 (Endmark)
|}

===Offer===
When a DHCP server receives a DHCPDISCOVER message from a client, which is an IP address lease request, the DHCP server reserves an IP address for the client and makes a lease offer by sending a DHCPOFFER message to the client. This message contains the client's client id (traditionally a MAC address), the IP address that the server is offering, the subnet mask, the lease duration, and the IP address of the DHCP server making the offer. The DHCP server may also take notice of the hardware-level MAC address in the underlying transport layer: according to current [[Request for Comments|RFC]]s the transport layer MAC address may be used if no client ID is provided in the DHCP packet.

The DHCP server determines the configuration based on the client's hardware address as specified in the CHADDR (client hardware address) field. Here the server, 192.168.1.1, specifies the client's IP address in the YIADDR (your IP address) field.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+ DHCPOFFER message
|-
| colspan=4 |
Ethernet: source=sender's MAC; destination=client mac address
|-
| colspan=4 |
IP: source=192.168.1.1; destination=255.255.255.255 &lt;br/&gt;
[[User Datagram Protocol|UDP]]: source port=67; destination port=68
|-
! Octet 0 !! Octet 1 !! Octet 2 !! Octet 3
|-
! OP !! HTYPE !! HLEN !! HOPS
|-
| 0x02 || 0x01 || 0x06 || 0x00
|-
! colspan=4 | XID
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x3903F326
|-
! colspan=2 | SECS !! colspan=2 | FLAGS
|-
| colspan=2 | 0x0000 || colspan=2 | 0x0000
|-
! colspan=4 | CIADDR (Client IP address)
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x00000000
|-
! colspan=5 | YIADDR (Your IP address)
|-
| colspan=5 | 0xC0A80164 (192.168.1.100)
|-
! colspan=4 | SIADDR (Server IP address)
|-
| colspan=4 | 0xC0A80101 (192.168.1.1)
|-
! colspan=4 | GIADDR (Gateway IP address)
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x00000000
|-
! colspan=4 | CHADDR (Client hardware address)
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x00053C04
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x8D590000
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x00000000
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x00000000
|-
| colspan=4 | 192 octets of 0s; [[BOOTP]] legacy.
|-
! colspan=4 | [[Magic cookie]]
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x63825363
|-
! colspan=4 | DHCP options
|-
| colspan=4 | 53: 2 (DHCP Offer)
|-
| colspan=4 | 1 (subnet mask): 255.255.255.0
|-
| colspan=4 | 3 (Router): 192.168.1.1
|-
| colspan=4 | 51 (IP address lease time): 86400s (1 day)
|-
| colspan=4 | 54 (DHCP server): 192.168.1.1
|-
| colspan=4 | 6 (DNS servers):{{unordered list
 | 9.7.10.15,
 | 9.7.10.16,
 | 9.7.10.18
 }}
|}

===Request===
In response to the DHCP offer, the client replies with a DHCPREQUEST message, broadcast to the server,{{Efn|name=&quot;optional-unicasts&quot;|As an optional client behavior, some broadcasts, such as those carrying DHCP discovery and request messages, may be replaced with unicasts in case the DHCP client already knows the DHCP server's IP address.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2131#section-4.4.4|title=Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol|first=Ralph|last=Droms|website=tools.ietf.org|accessdate=4 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} requesting the offered address. A client can receive DHCP offers from multiple servers, but it will accept only one DHCP offer. Based on required ''server identification'' option in the request and broadcast messaging, servers are informed whose offer the client has accepted.&lt;ref name=rfc2131&gt;{{cite IETF
| title = DHCP Options and BOOTP Vendor Extensions
| rfc = 2131
| last1 = Droms
| first1 = Ralph
|date=March 1997 
| publisher = [[Internet Engineering Task Force|IETF]]
| accessdate = September 9, 2014
}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|Section 3.1, Item 3}} When other DHCP servers receive this message, they withdraw any offers that they have made to the client and return the offered IP address to the pool of available addresses.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+ DHCPREQUEST message
|-
| colspan=4 |
Ethernet: source=sender's MAC; destination=FF:FF:FF:FF:FF:FF
|-
| colspan=4 |
IP: source=0.0.0.0; destination=255.255.255.255;{{Efn|name=&quot;optional-unicasts&quot;}} &lt;br/&gt;
[[User Datagram Protocol|UDP]]: source port=68; destination port=67
|-
! Octet 0 !! Octet 1 !! Octet 2 !! Octet 3
|-
! OP !! HTYPE !! HLEN !! HOPS
|-
| 0x01 || 0x01 || 0x06 || 0x00
|-
! colspan=5 | XID
|-
| colspan=5 | 0x3903F326
|-
! colspan=2 | SECS !! colspan=2 | FLAGS
|-
| colspan=2 | 0x0000 || colspan=2 | 0x0000
|-
! colspan=4 | CIADDR (Client IP address)
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x00000000
|-
! colspan=4 | YIADDR (Your IP address)
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x00000000
|-
! colspan=4 | SIADDR (Server IP address)
|-
| colspan=4 | 0xC0A80101 (192.168.1.1)
|-
! colspan=4 | GIADDR (Gateway IP address)
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x00000000
|-
! colspan=4 | CHADDR (Client hardware address)
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x00053C04
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x8D590000
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x00000000
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x00000000
|-
| colspan=4 | 192 octets of 0s; [[BOOTP]] legacy.
|-
! colspan=4 | [[Magic cookie]]
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x63825363
|-
! colspan=4 | DHCP options
|-
| colspan=4 | 53: 3 (DHCP Request)
|-
| colspan=4 | 50: 192.168.1.100 requested
|-
| colspan=4 | 54 (DHCP server): 192.168.1.1
|}

===Acknowledgement===
When the DHCP server receives the DHCPREQUEST message from the client, the configuration process enters its final phase. The acknowledgement phase involves sending a DHCPACK packet to the client. This packet includes the lease duration and any other configuration information that the client might have requested. At this point, the IP configuration process is completed.

The protocol expects the DHCP client to configure its network interface with the negotiated parameters.

After the client obtains an IP address, it should probe the newly received address&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=RFC2131 Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol: Dynamic allocation of network addresses |url=http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2131#section-2.2 |website=tools.ietf.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; (e.g. with ARP [[Address Resolution Protocol]]) to prevent address conflicts caused by overlapping address pools of DHCP servers.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+ DHCPACK message
|-
| colspan=4 |
Ethernet: source=sender's MAC; destination=client's MAC
|-
| colspan=4 |
IP: source=192.168.1.1; destination=255.255.255.255 &lt;br/&gt;
[[User Datagram Protocol|UDP]]: source port=67; destination port=68
|-
! Octet 0 !! Octet 1 !! Octet 2 !! Octet 3
|-
! OP !! HTYPE !! HLEN !! HOPS
|-
| 0x02 || 0x01 || 0x06 || 0x00
|-
! colspan=4 | XID
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x3903F326
|-
! colspan=2 | SECS !! colspan=2 | FLAGS
|-
| colspan=2 | 0x0000 || colspan=2 | 0x0000
|-
! colspan=4 | CIADDR (Client IP address)
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x00000000
|-
! colspan=4 | YIADDR (Your IP address)
|-
| colspan=4 | 0xC0A80164 (192.168.1.100)
|-
! colspan=4 | SIADDR (Server IP address)
|-
| colspan=4 | 0xC0A80101 (192.168.1.1)
|-
! colspan=4 | GIADDR (Gateway IP address switched by relay)
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x00000000
|-
! colspan=4 | CHADDR (Client hardware address)
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x00053C04
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x8D590000
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x00000000
&lt;/tt&gt;
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x00000000
|-
| colspan=4 | 192 octets of 0s. [[BOOTP]] legacy
|-
! colspan=4 | [[Magic cookie]]
|-
| colspan=4 | 0x63825363
|-
! colspan=4 | DHCP options
|-
| colspan=4 | 53: 5 (DHCP ACK) or 6 (DHCP NAK)
|-
| colspan=4 | 1 (subnet mask): 255.255.255.0
|-
| colspan=4 | 3 (Router): 192.168.1.1
|-
| colspan=4 | 51 (IP address lease time): 86400s (1 day)
|-
| colspan=4 | 54 (DHCP server): 192.168.1.1
|-
| colspan=4 | 6 (DNS servers):{{unordered list
 | 9.7.10.15,
 | 9.7.10.16,
 | 9.7.10.18
 }}
|}

===Information===
A DHCP client may request more information than the server sent with the original DHCPOFFER. The client may also request repeat data for a particular application. For example, browsers use ''DHCP Inform'' to obtain web proxy settings via [[Web Proxy Auto-Discovery Protocol|{{abbr|WPAD|Web Proxy Autodiscovery Protocol}}]].

===Releasing===
The client sends a request to the DHCP server to release the DHCP information and the client deactivates its IP address. As client devices usually do not know when users may unplug them from the network, the protocol does not mandate the sending of ''DHCP Release''.

==Client configuration parameters==
A DHCP server can provide optional configuration parameters to the client. RFC 2132 describes the available DHCP options defined by [[Internet Assigned Numbers Authority]] (IANA) -  DHCP and BOOTP PARAMETERS.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.iana.org/assignments/bootp-dhcp-parameters/bootp-dhcp-parameters.xhtml|title=Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) and Bootstrap Protocol (BOOTP) Parameters|publisher=iana.org|accessdate=2018-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A DHCP client can select, manipulate and overwrite parameters provided by a DHCP server. In Unix-like systems this client-level refinement typically takes place according to the values in the configuration file ''/etc/dhclient.conf''.

==Options==
Options are octet strings of varying length. The first octet is the option code, the second octet is the number of following octets and the remaining octets are code dependent.
For example, the DHCP message-type option for an offer would appear as 0x35, 0x01, 0x02, where 0x35 is code 53 for &quot;DHCP message type&quot;, 0x01 means one octet follows and 0x02 is the value of &quot;offer&quot;.

===Documented in RFC 2132===

The following tables list the available DHCP options, as listed in RFC 2132&lt;ref name=&quot;rfc2132&quot;&gt;{{cite IETF
| title = DHCP options and BOOTP vendor extensions
| rfc = 2132
| last1 = Alexander
| first1 = Steve
| last2 = Droms
| first2 = Ralph
|date=March 1997
| publisher = [[Internet Engineering Task Force|IETF]]
| accessdate = June 10, 2012
| doi = 10.17487/RFC2132
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and IANA registry.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|+ RFC 1497 (BOOTP Vendor Information Extensions) vendor extensions&lt;ref name=rfc2132/&gt;{{rp|Section 3}}
|-
! Code !! Name !! Length !! Notes
|-
| 0 || Pad&lt;ref name=rfc2132/&gt;{{rp|Section 3.1}} || 0 [[Octet (computing)|octets]] || Can be used to pad other options so that they are aligned to the word boundary; is not followed by length byte
|-
| 1 || Subnet mask&lt;ref name=rfc2132/&gt;{{rp|Section 3.3}} || 4 octets || Must be sent before the router option (option 3) if both are included
|-
| 2 || Time offset&lt;ref name=rfc2132/&gt;{{rp|Section 3.4}} || 4 octets ||
|-
| 3 || Router || Multiples of 4 octets || Available routers, should be listed in order of preference
|-
| 4 || Time server || Multiples of 4 octets || Available time servers to synchronise with, should be listed in order of preference
|-
| 5 || Name server || Multiples of 4 octets || Available [[IEN 116]] name servers, should be listed in order of preference
|-
| 6 || Domain name server || Multiples of 4 octets || Available [[Domain Name System|DNS]] servers, should be listed in order of preference
|-
| 7 || Log server || Multiples of 4 octets || Available log servers, should be listed in order of preference.
|-
| 8 || Cookie server || Multiples of 4 octets || ''Cookie ''in this case means &quot;fortune cookie&quot; or &quot;quote of the day&quot;, a pithy or humorous anecdote often sent as part of a logon process on large computers; it has nothing to do with [[HTTP cookie|cookies sent by websites]].
|-
| 9 || LPR Server || Multiples of 4 octets ||
|-
| 10 || Impress server || Multiples of 4 octets ||
|-
| 11 || Resource location server || Multiples of 4 octets ||
|-
| 12 || Host name || Minimum of 1 octet ||
|-
| 13 || Boot file size || 2 octets || Length of the boot image in 4KiB blocks
|-
| 14 || [[Merit Network|Merit]] dump file || Minimum of 1 octet || Path where crash dumps should be stored
|-
| 15 || Domain name || Minimum of 1 octet ||
|-
| 16 || Swap server || 4 octets ||
|-
| 17 || Root path || Minimum of 1 octet ||
|-
| 18 || Extensions path || Minimum of 1 octet ||
|-
| 255 || End || 0 octets || Used to mark the end of the vendor option field
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|+  IP layer parameters per host&lt;ref name=rfc2132/&gt;{{rp|Section 4}}
|-
! Code !! Name !! Length !! Notes
|-
| 19 || IP forwarding enable/disable || 1 octet ||
|-
| 20 || Non-local source routing enable/disable || 1 octet ||
|-
| 21 || Policy filter || Multiples of 8 octets ||
|-
| 22 || Maximum datagram reassembly size || 2 octets ||
|-
| 23 || Default IP time-to-live || 1 octet ||
|-
| 24 || Path MTU aging timeout || 4 octets ||
|-
| 25 || Path MTU plateau table || Multiples of 2 octets ||
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|+ IP Layer Parameters per Interface&lt;ref name=rfc2132/&gt;{{rp|Section 5}}
|-
! Code !! Name !! Length !! Notes
|-
| 26 || Interface MTU || 2 octets ||
|-
| 27 || All subnets are local || 1 octet ||
|-
| 28 || Broadcast address || 4 octets ||
|-
| 29 || Perform mask discovery || 1 octet ||
|-
| 30 || Mask supplier || 1 octet ||
|-
| 31 || Perform router discovery || 1 octet ||
|-
| 32 || Router solicitation address || 4 octets ||
|-
| 33 || Static route || Multiples of 8 octets || A list of destination/router pairs
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|+  Link layer parameters per interface&lt;ref name=rfc2132/&gt;{{rp|Section 6}}
|-
! Code !! Name !! Length !! Notes
|-
| 34 || Trailer encapsulation option || 1 octet ||
|-
| 35 || ARP cache timeout || 4 octets ||
|-
| 36 || Ethernet encapsulation || 1 octet ||
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|+  TCP parameters&lt;ref name=rfc2132/&gt;{{rp|Section 7}}
|-
! Code !! Name !! Length !! Notes
|-
| 37 || TCP default TTL || 1 octet ||
|-
| 38 || TCP keepalive interval || 4 octets ||
|-
| 39 || TCP keepalive garbage || 1 octet ||
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|+  Application and service parameters&lt;ref name=rfc2132/&gt;{{rp|Section 8}}
|-
! Code !! Name !! Length !! Notes
|-
| 40 || Network information service domain || Minimum of 1 octet ||
|-
| 41 || Network information servers || Multiples of 4 octets ||
|-
| 42 || [[Network Time Protocol]] (NTP) servers || Multiples of 4 octets ||
|-
| 43 || Vendor-specific information || Minimum of 1 octets ||
|-
| 44 || NetBIOS over TCP/IP name server || Multiples of 4 octets ||
|-
| 45 || NetBIOS over TCP/IP datagram Distribution Server || Multiples of 4 octets ||
|-
| 46 || NetBIOS over TCP/IP node type || 1 octet ||
|-
| 47 || NetBIOS over TCP/IP scope || Minimum of 1 octet ||
|-
| 48 || [[X Window System]] font server || Multiples of 4 octets ||
|-
| 49 || X Window System display manager || Multiples of 4 octets ||
|-
| 64 || [[Network Information Service]]+ domain || Minimum of 1 octet ||
|-
| 65 || Network Information Service+ servers || Multiples of 4 octets ||
|-
| 68 || Mobile IP home agent || Multiples of 4 octets ||
|-
| 69 || [[Simple Mail Transfer Protocol]] (SMTP) server || Multiples of 4 octets ||
|-
| 70 || [[Post Office Protocol]] (POP3) server || Multiples of 4 octets ||
|-
| 71 || [[Network News Transfer Protocol]] (NNTP) server || Multiples of 4 octets ||
|-
| 72 || Default [[World Wide Web]] (WWW) server || Multiples of 4 octets ||
|-
| 73 || Default [[Finger protocol]] server || Multiples of 4 octets ||
|-
| 74 || Default [[Internet Relay Chat]] (IRC) server || Multiples of 4 octets ||
|-
| 75 || [[StreetTalk]] server || Multiples of 4 octets ||
|-
| 76 || StreetTalk Directory Assistance (STDA) server || Multiples of 4 octets ||
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|+  DHCP extensions&lt;ref name=rfc2132/&gt;{{rp|Section 9}}
|-
! Code !! Name !! Length !! Notes
|-
| 50 || Requested IP address || 4 octets ||
|-
| 51 || IP address lease time || 4 octets ||
|-
| 52 || Option overload || 1 octet ||
|-
| 53 || DHCP message type || 1 octet ||
|-
| 54 || Server identifier || 4 octets ||
|-
| 55 || Parameter request list || Minimum of 1 octet ||
|-
| 56 || Message || Minimum of 1 octet ||
|-
| 57 || Maximum DHCP message size || 2 octets ||
|-
| 58 || Renewal (T1) time value || 4 octets ||
|-
| 59 || Rebinding (T2) time value || 4 octets ||
|-
| 60 || Vendor class identifier || Minimum of 1 octet ||
|-
| 61 || Client-identifier || Minimum of 2 octets ||
|-
| 66 || TFTP server name || Minimum of 1 octet ||
|-
| 67 || Bootfile name || Minimum of 1 octet ||
|}

====Client vendor identification====
An option exists to identify the vendor and functionality of a DHCP client. The information is a [[Variable-length code|variable-length string]] of characters or octets which has a meaning specified by the vendor of the DHCP client. One method that a DHCP client can utilize to communicate to the server that it is using a certain type of hardware or firmware is to set a value in its DHCP requests called the Vendor Class Identifier (VCI) (Option 60).

This method allows a DHCP server to differentiate between the two kinds of client machines and process the requests from the two types of modems appropriately. Some types of [[set-top boxes]] also set the VCI (Option 60) to inform the DHCP server about the hardware type and functionality of the device. The value this option is set to gives the DHCP server a hint about any required extra information that this client needs in a DHCP response.

===Documented elsewhere===

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|+ Documented DHCP options
|-
! Code !! Name !! Length !! RFC
|-
| 82 || [[#Relay agent information sub-options|Relay agent information]] || Minimum of 2 octets || RFC 3046&lt;ref name=&quot;ietf_spec_dhcp82&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Patrick|first1=Michael|title=DHCP Relay Agent Information Option|url=https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3046|website=IETF Documents|publisher=[[Internet Engineering Task Force|IETF]]|accessdate=22 July 2017|doi=10.17487/RFC3046|date=January 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 85 || [[Novell Directory Service]] (NDS) servers || Minimum of 4 octets, multiple of 4 octets || RFC 2241&lt;ref name=&quot;ietf_spec_dhcp85-86-87&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Provan|first1=Don|title=RFC 2241 – DHCP Options for Novell Directory Services|url=https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2241|website=IETF Documents|publisher=[[Internet Engineering Task Force|IETF]]|accessdate=23 July 2017|doi=10.17487/RFC3256|date=November 1997}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|Section 2}}
|-
| 86 || NDS tree name || Variable || RFC 2241&lt;ref name=&quot;ietf_spec_dhcp85-86-87&quot;/&gt;{{rp|Section 3}}
|-
| 87 || NDS context || Variable || RFC 2241&lt;ref name=&quot;ietf_spec_dhcp85-86-87&quot;/&gt;{{rp|Section 4}}
|-
| 100 || [[Search domain|Time zone]], POSIX style || Variable || RFC 4833&lt;ref name=&quot;ietf_spec_dhcp100-101&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Lear|first1=E.|last2=Eggert|first2=P.|title=Timezone Options for DHCP|url=https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4833|website=IETF Documents|publisher=[[Internet Engineering Task Force|IETF]]|date=April 2007|accessdate=28 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 101 || [[Search domain|Time zone]], [[tz database]] style || Variable || RFC 4833&lt;ref name=&quot;ietf_spec_dhcp100-101&quot;/&gt;
|-
| 119 || [[Search domain|Domain search]] || Variable || RFC 3397&lt;ref name=&quot;ietf_spec_dhcp119&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.17487/RFC3397|last1=Bernard|first1=Aboba|last2=Stuart|first2=Cheshire|title=RFC 3397 – Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) Domain Search Option|url=https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3397|website=IETF Documents|publisher=[[Internet Engineering Task Force|IETF]]|date=November 2002|accessdate=22 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 121 || Classless static route || Variable || RFC 3442&lt;ref name=&quot;ietf_spec_dhcp121&quot;&gt;[https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3442 RFC 3442]&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

====Relay agent information sub-options====

The relay agent information option (option 82)&lt;ref name=&quot;ietf_spec_dhcp82&quot;/&gt; specifies container for attaching sub-options to DHCP requests transmitted between a DHCP relay and a DHCP server.

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|+ Relay agent sub-options
|-
! Code !! Name !! Length !! RFC
|-
| 4 || Data-Over-Cable Service Interface Specifications (DOCSIS) device class || 4 octets || RFC 3256&lt;ref name=&quot;ietf_spec_riasub4&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Doug|first1=Jones|last2=Rich|first2=Woundy|title=RFC 3256 – The DOCSIS (Data-Over-Cable Service Interface Specifications) Device Class DHCP (Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol) Relay Agent Information Sub-option|url=https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3256|website=IETF Documents|publisher=[[Internet Engineering Task Force|IETF]]|accessdate=23 July 2017|doi=10.17487/RFC3256|date=April 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

==Relaying==
In small networks, where only one IP subnet is being managed, DHCP clients communicate directly with DHCP servers. However, DHCP servers can also provide IP addresses for multiple subnets. In this case, a DHCP client that has not yet acquired an IP address cannot communicate directly with the DHCP server using IP routing, because it does not have a routable IP address, does not know the link layer address of a router and does not know the IP address of the DHCP server.

In order to allow DHCP clients on subnets not directly served by DHCP servers to communicate with DHCP servers, DHCP relay agents can be installed on these subnets. The DHCP client broadcasts on the local link; the relay agent receives the broadcast and transmits it to one or more DHCP servers using [[unicast]]. The relay agent stores its own IP address in field ''GIADDR'' field of the DHCP packet. The DHCP server uses the GIADDR-value to determine the subnet on which the relay agent received the broadcast, and allocates an IP address on that subnet. When the DHCP server replies to the client, it sends the reply to the GIADDR-address, again using unicast. The relay agent then retransmits the response on the local network.

In this situation, the communication between the relay agent and the DHCP server typically uses both a source and destination UDP port of 67.

==Reliability==
The DHCP ensures reliability in several ways: periodic renewal, rebinding,&lt;ref name=rfc2131/&gt;{{rp|Section 4.4.5}} and failover. DHCP clients are allocated leases that last for some period of time. Clients begin to attempt to renew their leases once half the lease interval has expired.&lt;ref name=rfc2131/&gt;{{rp|Section 4.4.5 Paragraph 3}}   They do this by sending a unicast ''DHCPREQUEST'' message to the DHCP server that granted the original lease. If that server is down or unreachable, it will fail to respond to the ''DHCPREQUEST''. However, in that case the client repeats the ''DHCPREQUEST'' from time to time,&lt;ref name=rfc2131/&gt;{{rp|Section 4.4.5 Paragraph 8}}{{Efn|The RFC calls for the client to wait one half of the remaining time until T2 before it retransmits the ''DHCPREQUEST'' packet}} so if the DHCP server comes back up or becomes reachable again, the DHCP client will succeed in contacting it and renew the lease.

If the DHCP server is unreachable for an extended period of time,&lt;ref name=rfc2131/&gt;{{rp|Section 4.4.5 Paragraph 5}} the DHCP client will attempt to rebind, by broadcasting its ''DHCPREQUEST'' rather than unicasting it. Because it is [[Broadcasting (networking)|broadcast]], the ''DHCPREQUEST'' message will reach all available DHCP servers. If some other DHCP server is able to renew the lease, it will do so at this time.

In order for rebinding to work, when the client successfully contacts a backup DHCP server, that server must have accurate information about the client's binding. Maintaining accurate binding information between two servers is a complicated problem; if both servers are able to update the same lease database, there must be a mechanism to avoid conflicts between updates on the independent servers. A proposal for implementing [[Fault-tolerant design|fault-tolerant]] DHCP servers was submitted to the Internet Engineering Task Force, but never formalized.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite IETF
| title = DHCP Failover Protocol
| draft = draft-ietf-dhc-failover-12
| last1 = Droms | first1 = Ralph
| last2 = Kinnear | first2 = Kim
| last3 = Stapp | first3 = Mark
| last4 = Volz | first4 = Bernie
| last5 = Gonczi | first5 = Steve
| last6 = Rabil | first6 = Greg
| last7 = Dooley | first7 = Michael
| last8 = Kapur | first8 = Arun
| date = March 2003
| publisher = [[Internet Engineering Task Force|IETF]]
| accessdate = May 9, 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Efn|The proposal provided a mechanism whereby two servers could remain loosely in sync with each other in such a way that even in the event of a total failure of one server, the other server could recover the lease database and continue operating. Due to the length and complexity of the specification, it was never published as a standard; however, the techniques described in the specification are in wide use, with one open-source implementation in the [[ISC DHCP]] server, as well as several commercial implementations.}}

If rebinding fails, the lease will eventually expire. When the lease expires, the client must stop using the IP address granted to it in its lease.&lt;ref name=rfc2131/&gt;{{rp|Section 4.4.5 Paragraph 9}}   At that time it will restart the DHCP process from the beginning by broadcasting a &lt;code&gt;DHCPDISCOVER&lt;/code&gt; message. Since its lease has expired, it will accept any IP address offered to it. Once it has a new IP address (presumably from a different DHCP server) it will once again be able to use the network. However, since its IP address has changed, any ongoing connections will be broken.

== Modern application ==
As of 2018, DHCP remains widely-used to automatically assign IP addresses.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.networkworld.com/article/3297800/why-dhcps-days-might-be-numbered.html|title=Why DHCP's days might be numbered|last=Weinberg|first=Neal|date=2018-08-14|website=Network World|language=en|access-date=2019-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Newer iterations for assigning IP addresses include [[DHCPv6]] and [[Stateless address autoconfiguration|SLAAC]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;

==Security==
{{see also|DHCP snooping}}
The base DHCP does not include any mechanism for authentication.&lt;ref name=&quot;RAIOSec&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url = http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3046#section-7 |title = RFC 3046 - DHCP Relay Agent Information Option |first= Michael |last=Patrick |date = January 2001 |work = Network Working Group }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Because of this, it is vulnerable to a variety of attacks. These attacks fall into three main categories:
* Unauthorized DHCP servers providing false information to clients.&lt;ref name=&quot;DHCPv4Sec&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url = http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2131#section-7 |title = RFC 2131 - Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol |first= Ralph |last=Droms |date = March 1997 |work = Network Working Group }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Unauthorized clients gaining access to resources.&lt;ref name=&quot;DHCPv4Sec&quot;/&gt;
* Resource exhaustion attacks from malicious DHCP clients.&lt;ref name=&quot;DHCPv4Sec&quot;/&gt;

Because the client has no way to validate the identity of a DHCP server, unauthorized DHCP servers (commonly called &quot;[[rogue DHCP]]&quot;) can be operated on networks, providing incorrect information to DHCP clients.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stapko2011&quot;/&gt;  This can serve either as a denial-of-service attack, preventing the client from gaining access to network connectivity,&lt;ref name=&quot;Rountree2013&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first= Derrick |last=Rountree |title = Windows 2012 Server Network Security: Securing Your Windows Network Systems and Infrastructure |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=NFzou_d4MGUC&amp;pg=SA2-PA13 |year = 2013 |publisher = Newnes |isbn = 978-1-59749-965-1 |page = 22 }}&lt;/ref&gt; or as a [[man-in-the-middle attack]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Rooney2011&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first= Timothy |last=Rooney |title = Introduction to IP Address Management |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=QgRDxkuI1MkC&amp;pg=PA180 |year = 2010 |publisher = John Wiley &amp; Sons |isbn = 978-1-118-07380-3 |page = 180 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Because the DHCP server provides the DHCP client with server IP addresses, such as the IP address of one or more DNS servers,&lt;ref name=&quot;DHCPv4Sec&quot;/&gt; an attacker can convince a DHCP client to do its DNS lookups through its own DNS server, and can therefore provide its own answers to DNS queries from the client.&lt;ref name=&quot;DNSRedirect&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.securelist.com/en/blog/208188095/TDSS_loader_now_got_legs |title = TDSS loader now got &quot;legs&quot; |first= Sergey |last=Golovanov (Kaspersky Labs) |date = June 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Vulnerabilites&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url = http://greyhatsspeak.blogspot.com/2015/11/dhcp-protocol-and-its-vulnerabilities.html |title = dhcp protocol and its vulnerabilities |first= Akash K |last=Sunny |date = October 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This in turn allows the attacker to redirect network traffic through itself, allowing it to eavesdrop on connections between the client and network servers it contacts, or to simply replace those network servers with its own.&lt;ref name=&quot;DNSRedirect&quot; /&gt;

Because the DHCP server has no secure mechanism for authenticating the client, clients can gain unauthorized access to IP addresses by presenting credentials, such as client identifiers, that belong to other DHCP clients.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stapko2011&quot;/&gt; This also allows DHCP clients to exhaust the DHCP server's store of IP addresses—by presenting new credentials each time it asks for an address, the client can consume all the available IP addresses on a particular network link, preventing other DHCP clients from getting service.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stapko2011&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first= Timothy |last=Stapko |title = Practical Embedded Security: Building Secure Resource-Constrained Systems |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=Mly55VntuYMC&amp;pg=PA39 |year = 2011 |publisher = Newnes |isbn = 978-0-08-055131-9 |page = 39 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

DHCP does provide some mechanisms for mitigating these problems. The [[#Relay Agent Information Sub-options|Relay Agent Information Option]] protocol extension (RFC 3046, usually referred to in the industry by its actual number as ''Option 82''&lt;ref name=&quot;HensCaballero2008&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first1 = Francisco J. |last1=Hens |first2 = José M. |last2=Caballero |title = Triple Play: Building the converged network for IP, VoIP and IPTV |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=aS1ZngveBIkC&amp;pg=PA239 |year = 2008 |publisher = John Wiley &amp; Sons |isbn = 978-0-470-75439-9 |page = 239 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ramirez2008&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first= David H. |last=Ramirez |title = IPTV Security: Protecting High-Value Digital Contents |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=70tr_hSDULwC&amp;pg=PA55 |year = 2008 |publisher = John Wiley &amp; Sons |isbn = 978-0-470-72719-5 |page = 55 }}&lt;/ref&gt;) allows network operators to attach tags to DHCP messages as these messages arrive on the network operator's trusted network. This tag is then used as an authorization token to control the client's access to network resources. Because the client has no access to the network upstream of the relay agent, the lack of authentication does not prevent the DHCP server operator from relying on the authorization token.&lt;ref name=&quot;RAIOSec&quot;/&gt;

Another extension, Authentication for DHCP Messages ([https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3118 RFC 3118]), provides a mechanism for authenticating DHCP messages. As of 2002, &lt;nowiki&gt;RFC 3118&lt;/nowiki&gt; had not seen widespread adoption because of the problems of managing keys for large numbers of DHCP clients.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/dhcwg/current/msg00876.html |title = Implementation of RFC 3118 |first= Ted |last=Lemon |date = April 2002 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2007 book about DSL technologies remarked that:&lt;blockquote&gt;there were numerous security vulnerabilities identified against the security measures proposed by RFC 3118. This fact, combined with the introduction of [[802.1x]], slowed the deployment and take-rate of authenticated DHCP, and it has never been widely deployed.&lt;ref name=&quot;GoldenDedieu2007&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first1 = Philip |last1=Golden |first2 = Hervé |last2=Dedieu |first3 = Krista S. |last3=Jacobsen |title = Implementation and Applications of DSL Technology |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=Jjkd74jY47oC&amp;pg=PA484 |year = 2007 |publisher = Taylor &amp; Francis |isbn = 978-1-4200-1307-8 |page = 484 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; A 2010 book notes that:&lt;blockquote&gt;[t]here have been very few implementations of DHCP Authentication. The challenges of key management and processing delays due to hash computation have been deemed too heavy a price to pay for the perceived benefits.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rooney2011b&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first= Timothy |last=Rooney |title = Introduction to IP Address Management |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=QgRDxkuI1MkC&amp;pg=PA181 |year = 2010 |publisher = John Wiley &amp; Sons |isbn = 978-1-118-07380-3 |pages = 181–182 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Architectural proposals from 2008 involve authenticating DHCP requests using [[802.1x]] or [[Protocol for Carrying Authentication for Network Access|PANA]] (both of which transport [[Extensible Authentication Protocol|EAP]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Copeland2008&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first= Rebecca |last=Copeland |title = Converging NGN Wireline and Mobile 3G Networks with IMS |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=ruWv8RGkBGgC&amp;pg=PA142 |year = 2008 |publisher = Taylor &amp; Francis |isbn = 978-1-4200-1378-8 |pages = 142–143 }}&lt;/ref&gt; An IETF proposal was made for including EAP in DHCP itself, the so-called &lt;abbr&gt;EAPoDHCP&lt;/abbr&gt;;&lt;ref name=&quot;PrasadMihovska2009&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first1 = Ramjee |last1=Prasad |first2 = Albena |last2=Mihovska |title = New Horizons in Mobile and Wireless Communications: Networks, services, and applications |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=w9bEwBwd33MC&amp;pg=PA339 |year = 2009 |publisher = Artech House |isbn = 978-1-60783-970-5 |page = 339 |volume = 2 }}&lt;/ref&gt; this does not appear to have progressed beyond IETF draft level, the last of which dates to 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://tools.ietf.org/search/draft-pruss-dhcp-auth-dsl-07 |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2013-12-12 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150403091552/http://tools.ietf.org/search/draft-pruss-dhcp-auth-dsl-07 |archivedate=2015-04-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==IETF standards documents==
* RFC 2131, Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol
* RFC 2132, DHCP Options and BOOTP Vendor Extensions
* RFC 3046, DHCP Relay Agent Information Option
* RFC 3397, Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) Domain Search Option
* RFC 3942, Reclassifying Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol Version Four (DHCPv4) Options
* RFC 4242, Information Refresh Time Option for Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol for IPv6
* RFC 4361, Node-specific Client Identifiers for Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol Version Four (DHCPv4)
* RFC 4436, Detecting Network Attachment in IPv4 (DNAv4)
* RFC 3442, Classless Static Route Option for Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) version 4

==See also==
{{Div col|colwidth=25em}}
* [[Boot Service Discovery Protocol]] (BSDP){{snd}} a DHCP extension used by Apple's [[NetBoot]]
* [[Comparison of DHCP server software]]
* [[Peg DHCP]] (RFC 2322)
* [[Preboot Execution Environment]] (PXE)
* [[Reverse Address Resolution Protocol]] (RARP)
* [[Rogue DHCP]]
* [[UDP Helper Address]]{{snd}} a tool for routing DHCP requests across subnet boundaries
* [[Zeroconf]]{{snd}} Zero Configuration Networking
{{Div col end}}

==Notes==
{{Notelist|30em}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
{{Z148}}
* {{commons category inline|Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP)}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Application layer protocols]]
[[Category:Internet Standards]]
[[Category:Network service]]</text>
      <sha1>tjrw4u473y8t1bmgj5kw27ttj7c6gyz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
