  <page>
    <title>Divination</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8691</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942636127</id>
      <parentid>940225901</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-25T21:58:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Iridescent</username>
        <id>937705</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Academic */Cleanup and [[WP:AWB/T|typo fixing]], [[WP:AWB/T|typo(s) fixed]]: 334-458 → 334–458 (2)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{distinguish-otheruses2|Divinization (disambiguation){{!}}Divinization|Divination}}
{{redirect|Divining|pseudoscientific attempts to find water or other things|Dowsing}}
{{Anthropology of religion|Basic|image=[[File:Rhumsiki crab sorceror.jpg|frameless|upright=0.8|center]]|caption=This man in [[Rhumsiki]], [[Cameroon]], attempts to tell the future by interpreting the changes in position of various objects as caused by a freshwater crab through the practice of [[nggàm]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://era.anthropology.ac.uk/Divination|title=Anthropological Studies of Divination|work=anthropology.ac.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{Paranormal}}
'''Divination''' (from Latin ''divinare'' &quot;to foresee, to foretell, to predict, to prophesy &quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/morph?l=divinare&amp;la=la#lexicon|title=Lewis and Short's Latin Lexicon via the Perseus Project (http://www.perseus.tufts.edu)}}&lt;/ref&gt; related to ''divinus'', [[divinity|divine]]), or &quot;to be inspired by a god&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/secondary/SMIGRA*/Divinatio.html|title=LacusCurtius • Greek and Roman Divination (Smith's Dictionary, 1875)|work=uchicago.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; is the attempt to gain insight into a question or situation by way of an [[occult]]ic, standardized process or ritual.&lt;ref&gt;Peek, P.M. ''African Divination Systems: Ways of Knowing.'' page 2. Indiana University Press. 1991.&lt;/ref&gt; Used in various forms throughout history, diviners ascertain their interpretations of how a [[querent]] should proceed by reading signs, events, or [[omen]]s, or through alleged contact with a [[supernatural]] agency.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Silva|first=Sónia|year=2016|title=Object and Objectivity in Divination|journal=Material Religion|volume=12|issue=4|pages=507–509|doi=10.1080/17432200.2016.1227638|issn=1743-2200}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Divination display at the Pitt Rivers Museum.jpg|thumb|upright=1.2|Display on divination, featuring a cross-cultural range of items, in the [[Pitt Rivers Museum]] in [[Oxford]], [[England]].]]
Divination can be seen as a systematic method with which to organize what appear to be disjointed, random facets of existence such that they provide insight into a problem at hand. If a distinction is to be made between divination and [[fortune-telling]], divination has a more formal or ritualistic element and often contains a more social character, usually in a [[religion|religious]] context, as seen in [[traditional African medicine]]. Fortune-telling, on the other hand, is a more everyday practice for personal purposes. Particular divination methods vary by culture and religion.

Divination is dismissed by the [[scientific community]] and skeptics as being [[superstition]]; experiments do not support the idea that divination techniques can actually predict the future more reliably or precisely than would be possible without it.&lt;ref&gt;Yau, Julianna. (2002). ''Witchcraft and Magic''. In [[Michael Shermer]]. ''The Skeptic Encyclopedia of Pseudoscience''. ABC-CLIO. pp. 278-282. {{ISBN|1-57607-654-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Regal, Brian. (2009). ''Pseudoscience: A Critical Encyclopedia''. Greenwood. p. 55. {{ISBN|978-0-313-35507-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 2nd century, [[Lucian]] devoted a witty essay to the career of a [[charlatan]], &quot;[[Alexander of Abonoteichus|Alexander the false prophet]]&quot;, trained by &quot;one of those who advertise enchantments, miraculous incantations, charms for your love-affairs, visitations for your enemies, disclosures of buried treasure, and successions to estates&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tertullian.org/rpearse/lucian/lucian_alexander.htm|title=Lucian of Samosata : Alexander the False Prophet|work=tertullian.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; even though most Romans believed in prophetic dreams and [[Amulet|charms]].{{Citation needed|reason=Did most Romans believe in these things?|date=November 2018}}

==Categories==
[[Image:ChickenDivination.jpg|thumb|[[Russia]]n peasant girls using [[chicken]]s for divination; 19th century [[lubok]].]]
{{Further|List of magical terms and traditions}}

==History==

===Antiquity===
The Oracle of [[Amun]] at the [[Siwa Oasis]] was made famous when [[Alexander the Great]] visited it after conquering Egypt from Persia in 332 BC.{{cn|date=November 2019}}
 
{{bibleref2|Deuteronomy|18:10-12}} or {{bibleref2|Leviticus|19:26}} can be interpreted as categorically forbidding divination. However, some would claim that divination is indeed practiced in the Bible, such as in Exodus 28, when the [[Urim and Thummim]] are mentioned. Some would also say that [[Gideon]] also practiced divination, though when he uses a piece of fleece or wool in {{bibleref2|Judges|6:36-40}}, he is not attempting to predict the outcome of an important battle; rather, he is communicating with [[Yahweh|God]]. Communicating with God through prayer may in some cases be considered divination; both are open, typically two-way conversations with God. In addition, the method of &quot;casting lots&quot; used in {{bibleref2|Joshua|14:1-5}} and {{bibleref2|Joshua|18:1-10}} to divide the conquered lands of [[Canaan]] between the twelve tribes is not seen by some as divination, but as done at the behest of God ({{bibleref2|Numbers 26:55}}).

{{See also|Oracle|Greek divination}}
Both oracles and seers in ancient Greece practiced divination. [[Oracle#Greece|Oracles]] were the conduits for the gods on earth; their prophecies were understood to be the will of the gods verbatim. Because of the high demand for oracle consultations and the oracles’ limited work schedule, they were not the main source of divination for the ancient Greeks. That role fell to the seers (''μάντεις'' in Greek).{{cn|date=November 2019}}

Seers were not in direct contact with the gods; instead, they were interpreters of signs provided by the gods. Seers used many methods to explicate the will of the gods including [[extispicy]], bird signs, etc. They were more numerous than the oracles and did not keep a limited schedule; thus, they were highly valued by all Greeks, not just those with the capacity to travel to Delphi or other such distant sites.{{cn|date=November 2019}}

The disadvantage to seers was that only direct yes-or-no questions could be answered. Oracles could answer more generalized questions, and seers often had to perform several sacrifices in order to get the most consistent answer. For example, if a general wanted to know if the omens were proper for him to advance on the enemy, he would ask his seer both that question and if it were better for him to remain on the defensive. If the seer gave consistent answers, the advice was considered valid.{{cn|date=November 2019}}

At battle, generals would frequently ask seers at both the [[campground]] (a process called the ''hiera'') and at the [[battle]]field (called the ''sphagia''). The hiera entailed the seer slaughtering a sheep and examining its liver for answers regarding a more generic question; the sphagia involved killing a young female goat by slitting its throat and noting the animal's last movements and blood flow. The battlefield sacrifice only occurred when two armies prepared for battle against each other. Neither force would advance until the seer revealed appropriate [[omen]]s.{{cn|date=November 2019}}

Because the seers had such power over influential individuals in ancient Greece, many were skeptical of the accuracy and honesty of the seers. The degree to which seers were honest depends entirely on the individual seers. Despite the doubt surrounding individual seers, the craft as a whole was well regarded and trusted by the Greeks.&lt;ref&gt;Flower, Michael Attyah. ''The Seer in Ancient Greece.'' Berkeley: University of California Press, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Middle Ages and Early Modern period===
{{see|Medieval magic|Renaissance magic|Folk Catholicism}}
The divination method of casting lots ([[Cleromancy]]) was used by the remaining eleven disciples of Jesus in {{bibleref2|Acts|1:23-26}} to select a replacement for [[Judas Iscariot]]. Therefore, divination was arguably an accepted practice in the early church. However, divination became viewed as a pagan practice by Christian [[emperor]]s during [[ancient Rome]].&lt;ref&gt;Bailey, Michael David. (2007). ''Magic and Superstition in Europe''. Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers, Inc. pp. 52-53. {{ISBN|0-7425-3386-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 692 the [[Quinisext Council]], also known as the &quot;Council in Trullo&quot; in the [[Eastern Orthodox Church]], passed canons to eliminate pagan and divination practices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://apostolicconfraternityseminary.com/council_of_trullo.html|title=Council of Trullo - Apostolic Confraternity Seminary|work=apostolicconfraternityseminary.com|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110707152243/http://apostolicconfraternityseminary.com/council_of_trullo.html|archivedate=2011-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Fortune-telling]] and other forms of divination were widespread through the [[Middle Ages]].&lt;ref&gt;Bailey, Michael David. (2007). ''Magic and Superstition in Europe''. Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers, Inc. pp. 88-89. {{ISBN|0-7425-3386-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the constitution of 1572 and public regulations of 1661 of Kur-Saxony, capital punishment was used on those predicting the future.&lt;ref&gt;Ennemoser, Joseph. (1856). ''The History of Magic''. London: Henry G. Bohn, York Street, Covent Garden. p. 59&lt;/ref&gt; Laws forbidding divination practice continue to this day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pluralism.org/news/view/147|title=Wiccan Priest Fights Local Ordinance Banning Fortune Telling (Louisiana)|work=pluralism.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Småland]] is famous for [[Årsgång]], a practice which occurred until the early 19th century in some parts of Småland. Generally occurring on Christmas and New Year's Eve, it is a practice in which one would fast and keep themselves away from light in a room until midnight to then complete a set of complex events to interpret symbols encountered throughout the journey to foresee the coming year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Kuusela|first= Tommy|year= 2014|title= Swedish year walk: from folk tradition to computer game. In: Island Dynamics Conference on Folk Belief &amp; Traditions of the Supernatural: Experience, Place, Ritual, &amp; Narrative. Shetland Isles, UK, 24–30 March 2014|url= https://www.academia.edu/6624109 |accessdate= &lt;!-- 09/07/14 --&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mesoamerica===
{{see also|Mesoamerican religion}}
Divination was a central component of ancient [[Mesoamerican]] religious life. Many [[Aztec religion|Aztec gods]], including central [[creator deity|creator gods]], were described as diviners and were closely associated with [[Magic (paranormal)|sorcery]]. [[Tezcatlipoca]] is the patron of sorcerers and practitioners of [[Magic (paranormal)|magic]]. His name means &quot;smoking mirror&quot;, a reference to a device used for divinatory [[scrying]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller 2007&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Miller|first=Mary|title=Gods and Symbols of Ancient Mexico|year=2007|publisher=Thames &amp; Hudson|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Maya mythology|Mayan]] ''[[Popol Vuh]]'', the creator gods [[Xmucane and Xpiacoc]] perform divinatory hand casting during the creation of people.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller 2007&quot;/&gt;

Every civilization that developed in [[pre-Columbian Mexico]], from the [[Olmecs]] to the [[Aztecs]], practiced divination in daily life, both public and private. Scrying through the use of reflective water surfaces, [[Mirrors in Mesoamerican culture|mirrors]], or the [[Cleromancy|casting of lots]] were among the most widespread forms of divinatory practice. [[Vision (spirituality)|Vision]]s derived from [[hallucinogens]] were another important form of divination, and are still widely used among contemporary diviners of Mexico. Among the more common [[hallucinogenic plants]] used in divination are [[morning glory]], [[jimson weed]], and [[peyote]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller 2007&quot;/&gt;

==Contemporary folk religion==
===Asia===
==== Japan ====

Although Japan retains a history of traditional and local methods of divination, such as [[Onmyōdō|omyodo]], contemporary divination in Japan, called ''uranai'', derives from outside sources.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Miller|first=Laura|date=2014|title=The divination arts in girl culture|url=https://www.academia.edu/25806189|journal=Capturing Contemporary Japan: Differentiation and Uncertainty|publisher=University of Hawai'i Press|volume=|pages=334–358|via=Academia}}&lt;/ref&gt; Contemporary methods of divination in Japan include both Western and Chinese [[astrology]], [[geomancy]] or [[feng shui]], [[Tarot|tarot cards]], [[I Ching]] (Book of Changes), and [[physiognomy]] (methods of reading the body to identify traits).&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; Rather than indicate [[cultural appropriation]], understood as inappropriate acts of appropriation by a dominant culture in the context of colonization or inequality, Japanese divination represents instances of unique and creative amalgamation of cultural elements. This concept may be referred to as [[syncretism]], [[creolization]], or [[cultural hybridity]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Miller|first=Laura|date=2017|title=Japanese Tarot Cards|journal=ASIANetwork Exchange: A Journal for Asian Studies in the Liberal Arts|volume=24|issue=1|pages=1–28|doi=10.16995/ane.244}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the example of feng shui, Japanese adaptations of feng shui extend outside the traditional form, featuring such hybrids as &quot;car feng shui,&quot; &quot;workplace feng shui,&quot; &quot;makeup feng shui,&quot; and even &quot;toilet feng shui.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

===== Personality types =====
Personality typing as a form of divination has been prevalent in Japan since the 1980s. Various methods exist for divining personality type. Each attempt to reveal glimpses of an individual's destiny, productive and inhibiting traits, future parenting technique, and compatibility in marriage. Personality type is increasingly important for young Japanese, who consider personality the driving factor of compatibility, given the ongoing marriage drought and [[Birthrate decline|birth rate decline]] in Japan.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;

An import to Japan, [[Chinese zodiac]] signs based on birth year in 12 year cycles (rat, ox, tiger, hare, dragon, snake, horse, sheep, monkey, cock, dog, and boar) are frequently combined with other forms of divination, such as so-called 'celestial types' based on the planets (Saturn, Venus, Mars, Jupiter, Mercury, or Uranus). Personality can also be divined using cardinal directions, the [[Classical element|four elements]] (water, earth, fire, air), and [[Yin and yang|yin-yang]]. Names can also lend important personality information under name classification which asserts that names bearing certain Japanese vowel sounds (a, i, u, e, o) share common characteristics. [[Numerology]], which utilizes methods of diving 'birth numbers' from significant numbers such as birth date, may also reveal character traits of individuals.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;

Individuals can also assess their own and others' personalities according to physical characteristics. [[Blood type]] remains a popular form of divination from physiology. Stemming from Western influences, body reading or ''ninsou'', determines personality traits based on body measurements. The face is the most commonly analyzed feature, with eye size, pupil shape, mouth shape, and eyebrow shape representing the most important traits. An upturned mouth may be cheerful, and a triangle eyebrow may indicate that someone is strong-willed.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;

Methods of assessment in daily life may include self-taken measurements or quizzes. As such, magazines targeted at women in their early-to-mid twenties feature the highest concentration of personality assessment guides. There are approximately 144 different women's magazines, known as ''nihon zashi koukoku kyoukai'', published in Japan aimed at this audience.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Miller|first=Laura|date=1997|title=People Types: Personality Classification in Japanese Women's Magazines|url=https://www.academia.edu/28155359|journal=The Journal of Popular Culture|volume=31|issue=2|pages=143–159|via=Academia.edu|doi=10.1111/j.0022-3840.1997.00143.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===== Japanese tarot =====
The adaptation of the Western divination method of tarot cards into Japanese culture presents a particularly unique example of contemporary divination as this adaptation mingles with Japan's robust visual culture. Japanese tarot cards are created by professional artists, advertisers, and fans of tarot. One tarot card collector claimed to have accumulated more than 1,500 Japan-made decks of tarot cards. Japanese tarot cards fall into diverse categories such as Inspiration Tarot (''reikan tarotto''), I-Ching Tarot (''ekisen tarotto''), Spiritual Tarot (''supirichuaru tarotto''), Western Tarot (''seiyō tarotto''), and Eastern Tarot (''tōyō tarotto''). The images on tarot cards may come from images from Japanese popular culture, such as characters from [[manga]] and [[anime]] including [[Hello Kitty]], or may feature cultural symbols. Tarot cards may adapt the images of Japanese historical figures, such as high priestess [[Himiko]] (170-248CE) or imperial court wizard [[Abe no Seimei]] (921-1005CE) . Still others may feature images of cultural displacement, such as English knights, [[pentagram]]s, the Jewish [[Torah]], or invented [[glyph]]&lt;nowiki/&gt;s. The introduction of such cards began by the 1930s and reached prominence 1970s. Japanese tarot cards were originally created by men, often based on the Rider-Waite-Smith tarot published by the Rider company in London in 1909.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt; Since, the practice of Japanese tarot has become overwhelmingly feminine and intertwined with [[kawaii]] culture. Referring to the cuteness of tarot cards, Japanese model Kuromiya Niina was quoted as saying &quot;because the images are cute, even holding them is enjoyable.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Miller|first=Laura|date=May 2011|title=Tantalizing Tarot and Cute Cartomancy in Japan|url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/254312114|journal=Japanese Studies|volume=31|issue=1|pages=73–91|doi=10.1080/10371397.2011.560659|via=ResearchGate}}&lt;/ref&gt; While these differences exist, Japanese tarot cards function similarly to their Western counterparts. Cards are shuffled and cut into piles then used to forecast the future, for spiritual reflection, or as a tool for self-understanding.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;

====Taiwan====
As seen previous to this section, many different cultures around the world use divination as a way of understanding the future. The most common act of divination in the Bao’an village in Taiwan is called the Poe, Bao’an is not the actual name of the village, but for privacy purposes that is what it will be called. The Poe translated to English means “moon boards”. The Poe consists of two wood or bamboo blocks cut into the shape of a crescent moon. The one edge is rounded while the other is flat; the two are mirror images. Both crescents are held out in one's palms and while kneeling, they are raised to the forehead level. Once in this position the blocks are dropped and the future can be understood depending on their landing. If both fall flat side up or both fall rounded side up, that can be taken as a failure of the deity to agree. If the blocks land one rounded and one flat, the deity agrees. “Laughing poe” is when rounded sides land down and they rock before coming to a standstill. “Negative poe” is seen when the flat sides fall downward and abruptly stop, this indicates anger. When there is a positive fall, is called “sacred poe”, although the negative falls are not usually taken seriously. As the blocks are being dropped the question is said in a murmur, and if the answer is yes, the blocks are dropped again. To make sure the answer is definitely a yes, the blocks must fall in a “yes” position three times in a row.{{cn|date=November 2019}}
 
A more serious type of divination is the Kiō-á. There is a small wooden chair, and around the sides of the chair are small pieces of wood that can move up and down in their sockets, this causes a clicking sounds when the chair is moved in any way. Two men hold this chair by its legs before an altar, during this incense are being burned, and the supernatural agent is asked to descend into the chair. It is seen that it is in the chair by an onset of motion. Eventually the chair crashes onto a table prepared with wood chips and burlap. The characters on the table are then traced and these are said to be written by the god who possessed the chair, these characters are then interpreted.&lt;ref&gt;Rohsenow, Hill Gates, and David K. Jordan. “Gods, Ghosts, and Ancestors: The Folk Religion of a Taiwanese Village.” The Journal of Asian Studies, vol. 33, no. 3, 1974, p. 478., doi:10.2307/2052956.&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Japan]], divination methods include [[Futomani]] from the [[Shinto]] tradition.{{CN|date=November 2019}}

===Africa===
{{see|African divination}}

Divination is one of the tenets of [[Serer religion]]. However, only those who have been initiated as [[Saltigue]]s (the [[Serer people|Serer]] high priests and priestesses) can divine the future.&lt;ref&gt;[[Alioune Sarr|Sarr, Alioune]], « Histoire du Sine-Saloum » (introduction, bibliographie et notes par Charles Becker), in Bulletin de l'IFAN, tome 46, série B, nos 3-4, 1986-1987 pp 31-38&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kalis&quot;&gt;Kalis, Simone, &quot;Medecine Traditionnele Religion et Divination Chez Les [[Serer people|Seereer]] [[Kingdom of Sine|Siin]] du [[Senegal]]&quot;, L'Harmattan (1997), pp 11-297 {{ISBN|2-7384-5196-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; These are the &quot;hereditary rain priests&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Galvan&quot;/&gt; whose role is both religious and medicinal.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kalis&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Galvan&quot;&gt;Galvan, Dennis Charles, &quot;The State Must be our Master of Fire : How Peasants Craft Culturally Sustainable Development in Senegal&quot;, Berkeley, University of California Press, (2004), pp 86-135, {{ISBN|978-0-520-23591-5}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Specialized diviners called Ob'guega (doctor of Oguega oracle), as well as Ob'Oronmila (doctor of Oronmila oracle) from the [[Edo people]] of [[West Africa]] for thousands have used divination as a means of foretelling the past, present and future. These diviners are initiated and trained in Iha (divination) of either Ominigbon or Oronmila (Benin Orunmila).{{cn|date=November 2019}}

The  [[Yoruba people]] of [[West Africa]] are internationally known for having developed the [[Ifá]] system, an intricate process of divination that is performed by an ''[[Babalawo|Awo]]'', an initiated priest or priestess of [[Orunmila]], the spirit of the Yoruba [[oracle]].{{cn|date=November 2019}}

==See also==
* [[Methods of divination]]
* [[Prophet]]
* [[List of dreams#Prophetic dreams|Prophetic dreams]]
* [[Sandobele]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==

===Academic===
* K. Beerden, ''Worlds full of signs: ancient Greek divination in context''. Leiden: Brill. (2013). 
* D. Engels, ''Das römische Vorzeichenwesen (753-27 v.Chr.). Quellen, Terminologie, Kommentar, historische Entwicklung,'' Stuttgart 2007 (Franz Steiner-Verlag)
* E. E. Evans-Pritchard, ''Witchcraft, oracles, and magic among the Azande'' (1976)
* Toufic Fahd, ''La divination arabe; études religieuses, sociologiques et folkloriques sur le milieu natif d’Islam'' (1966)
* Philip K. Hitti. ''Makers of Arab History''. Princeton, New Jersey. St. Martin's Press. 1968. Pg 61.
* {{cite book |author= Alisa LaGamma | title= ''Art and oracle: African art and rituals of divination'' | location=New York | publisher=The Metropolitan Museum of Art | year=2000 | isbn=9780870999338 | url= http://libmma.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/compoundobject/collection/p15324coll10/id/42448/rec/1}}
* Michael Loewe and Carmen Blacke, eds. ''Oracles and divination'' (Shambhala/Random House, 1981) {{ISBN|0-87773-214-0}}
*[[Laura Miller (anthropologist)|Miller, Laura]]. &quot;The divination arts in girl culture.&quot; In ''Capturing Contemporary Japan: Differentiation and Uncertainty'', edited by Satsuki Kawano, Glenda S. Roberts, and Susan Long, Honolulu: University of Hawai'i Press, 334–458.
* Miller, Laura. &quot;Japanese tarot cards. ''ASIA Network Exchange: A Journal for Asian Studies in the Liberal Art.'' 24(1): 1-28.
* Miller, Laura. &quot;People Types: Personality classification in Japanese women's magazines.&quot; ''Journal of Popular Culture'', Vol.31 No.2, pp.&amp;nbsp;133–150.
* Miller, Laura. &quot;Tantalizing tarot and cute cartomancy in Japan.&quot; ''Japanese Studies'' Vol. 31, Issue 1, pp.&amp;nbsp;73–91.
* [[William Montgomery Watt|W. Montgomery Watt]]. ''Muhammad: Prophet and Statesman''. Edinburgh, Scotland. Oxford Press, 1961. Pgs 1–2.
* Sonia Silva. &quot;Object and Objectivity in Divination&quot;. ''Material Religion'' 12 (4), 2016.
* [[J. P. Vernant]], ''Divination et rationalité'', Paris: Editions du Seuil (1974)

==External links==
{{wiktionary}}
{{wikisource}}
{{Wikiquote}}
{{commons category}}
* [https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.168757 ''Greek Divination: a study of its methods and principles''], William Reginald Halliday, Macmillan, 1913, 309pp - a complete scanned edition of a general treatment of Greek divination (at [[Google Books]])
* David Zeitlyn and others on African Divination systems: [http://era.anthropology.ac.uk/Divination/ Africa Divination: Mambila and others]
* {{CathEncy|wstitle=Divination}}

{{Divination}}
{{Witchcraft}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Divination| ]]
[[Category:Romani religion]]</text>
      <sha1>epdl061hwo22y4hboea8px022b52jct</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
