  <page>
    <title>Diets of Nuremberg</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8693</id>
    <revision>
      <id>879089814</id>
      <parentid>878979882</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-01-18T23:01:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Epiphyllumlover</username>
        <id>883802</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* The 1524 Diet of Nuremberg */ more aftermath</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Unreferenced|date=November 2007}}
The '''Diets of Nuremberg''', also called the [[Imperial Diet (Holy Roman Empire)|Imperial Diets]] of [[Nuremberg]], took place at different times between the [[Middle Ages]] and the 17th century. 

The first Diet of Nuremberg, in 1211, elected the future emperor [[Frederick II, Holy Roman Emperor|Frederick II of Hohenstaufen]] as German king.

At the Diet of 1356 the [[Charles IV, Holy Roman Emperor|Emperor Charles IV]] issued the [[Golden Bull of 1356]], which required each [[Holy Roman Emperor]] to summon the first Imperial [[Diet (assembly)|Diet]] after his election at Nuremberg. Apart from that, a number of other diets were held there.

Important to [[Protestantism]] were the Diets of 1522 (&quot;First Diet of Nuremberg&quot;), 1524 (&quot;Second Diet of Nuremberg&quot;) and 1532 (&quot;Third Diet of Nuremberg&quot;).

==The 1522 Diet of Nuremberg==
This Diet has become known mostly for the reaction of the papacy to the decision made on [[Martin Luther|Luther]] at the [[Diet of Worms]] the previous year. The new pope, [[Adrian VI]], sent his nuncio [[Francesco Chieregati]] to the Diet, to insist both that the [[Edict of Worms]] be executed, and that action be taken promptly against Luther. This demand, however, was coupled with a promise of thorough reform in the Roman hierarchy, frankly admitting the partial guilt of the Vatican in the decline of the Church.

In the recess drafted on 9 February 1523, however, the German princes rejected this appeal. Using Adrian's admissions, they declared that they could not have it appear 'as though they wished to oppress evangelical truth and assist unchristian and evil abuses.'

==The 1524 Diet of Nuremberg==
This Diet generally took the same line as the previous one. The Estates reiterated their decision from the previous Diet. The Cardinal-legate, Campeggio, who was present, showed his disgust at the behaviour of the Estates. On 18 April, the Estates decided to call 'a general gathering of the German nation', to meet at [[Speyer]] the following year and to decide what would be done until the meeting of the general council of the Church which they demanded. This resulted in the [[Diet of Speyer (1526)]], which in turn was followed by the [[Diet of Speyer (1529)]]. The latter included the [[Protestation at Speyer]].

==References==
* [[Karl Brandi]], ''The Emperor Charles V'' (1939), pp.&amp;nbsp;185–188

[[Category:Imperial Diets (Holy Roman Empire)|Nuremberg]]
[[Category:History of Nuremberg]]</text>
      <sha1>4bxavsfq8fk5un1gjqxs6kwbyqtzw7z</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
