  <page>
    <title>Dianic Wicca</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8620</id>
    <revision>
      <id>928638963</id>
      <parentid>927050756</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-11-30T17:46:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>84.46.53.210</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* McFarland Dianic */ 5 identical references for 5 consecutive statements reduced to 1 reference</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Feminism sidebar|Variants (religious)}}
{{Infobox religion
| name                = Dianic Wicca
| image               = Triple-Goddess-Pentagram.svg
| imagewidth          = 300px
| alt                 = 
| caption             = Symbol of the [[Triple Goddess (Neopaganism)|Goddess]] with the [[Pentacle]].
| abbreviation        = DW
| type                = [[Wicca]]
| main_classification = 
| orientation         = Feminist orientated Wicca
| scripture           = 
| theology            = [[Goddess movement]]
| polity              = 
| governance          = Female-orientation Priesthood
| structure           =
| leader_title        = 
| leader_name         = 
| leader_title1       = 
| leader_name1        = 
| leader_title2       = 
| leader_name2        = 
| fellowships_type    =
| fellowships         = 
| fellowships_type1   =
| fellowships1        =
| associations        = 
| area                = [[United States]]
| headquarters        = 
| founder             = [[Zsuzsanna Budapest]]
| founded_date        = 1970s
| founded_place       = United States
| separated_from      = 
| parent              = 
| merger              = 
| absorbed            =
| separations         = 
| merged_into         =
| defunct             =
| congregations_type  = Coven
| congregations       = 
| members             = Around 1,000-2,000
| ministers_type      = Priestness
| ministers           = 
| missionaries        =
| temples             =
| hospitals           = 
| nursing_homes       = 
| aid                 = 
| primary_schools     = 
| secondary_schools   = 
| tertiary            = 
| other_names         = 
| publications        = 
| website             = 
| footnotes           = 
}}

'''Dianic Wicca''', also known as '''Dianic Witchcraft''',&lt;ref name=&quot;River May 2004&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|last=River
|first=Falcon
|title=The Dianic Wiccan Tradition
|url=http://www.witchvox.com/va/dt_va.html?a=uswi&amp;c=trads&amp;id=8451
|publisher=The Witches Voice
|accessdate=23 May 2007
|date=7 May 2004
}} and, to some also as &quot;Dianism,&quot; &quot;Dianic Feminist Witchcraft,&quot; or simply &quot;Feminist Witchcraft&quot;'&lt;/ref&gt; is a [[neopagan]] religion female-centered [[goddess]] ritual and tradition. While some adherents identify as [[Wicca]]n, it differs from most traditions of Wicca in that only goddesses are honored (whereas most Wiccan traditions honor both female and male deities).&lt;ref name=Budapest1&gt;Budapest, Zsuzsanna. ''Holy Book of Women's Mysteries'', The. 1980 (2003 electronic). {{ISBN|0-914728-67-9}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Adler1&gt;[[Margot Adler|Adler, Margot]]. ''Drawing Down the Moon: Witches, Druids, Goddess-Worshippers, and Other Pagans in America Today''. Boston: Beacon press, 1979; 1986. {{ISBN|0-8070-3237-9}}. Chapter 8: Women, Feminism, and the Craft&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;

While there is more than one tradition that calls itself Dianic,&lt;ref name=Adler1 /&gt; the best known is the female-only variety,&lt;ref name=&quot;River May 2004&quot;/&gt; founded by [[Zsuzsanna Budapest]] in the United States in the 1970s.&lt;ref name=Budapest1 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Adler1 /&gt; It is notable for its worship of a single [[Goddess movement|Goddess]] and focus on egalitarian matriarchy. It is named after the [[Roman goddess]] [[Diana (mythology)|Diana]], but Dianics worship goddesses from many cultures, seeing them as &quot;aspects&quot; of a [[monotheistic]] goddess.&lt;ref name=Budapest1 /&gt;  Dianic Wicca is an [[Wicca#Eclectic Wicca|eclectic]] combination of elements from [[British Traditional Wicca]], Italian folk-magic as recorded by [[Charles Leland]] in ''[[Aradia, or the Gospel of the Witches|Aradia]]'', the importance of womanhood, folk magic and healing practices from a variety of different cultures.&lt;ref name=Budapest1 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Adler1 /&gt;

==Beliefs and practices==
[[File:Diana with a Stag and a Dog LACMA M.78.77.jpg|thumb|250px|Diana (or Artemis, by her Greek name) as a protector of women and wild nature&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.templeofdiana.org/dwt.htm|title=Temple of Diana - The Tradition of Dianic Wicca|work=templeofdiana.org|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131206194250/http://www.templeofdiana.org/dwt.htm|archivedate=2013-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Dianic Wiccans of the Budapest lineage worship the [[Goddess]], who they see as containing all goddesses, from all cultures; she is seen as the source of all living things and containing all that is within her.&lt;ref name=Budapest1 /&gt; Dianic covens practice [[Magic (paranormal)|magic]] in the form of [[mediation]] and visualization in addition to spell work. They focus especially on healing themselves from the wounds of the [[patriarchy]] while affirming their own womanhood.

Rituals can include reenacting religious and spiritual lore from a female-centered standpoint, celebrating the female body, and mourning society's abuses of women.&lt;ref name=Foltz&gt;Foltz, Tanic G. “Women's Spirituality Research: Doing Feminism,” Sociology of Religion 64.4 (2000): 409-418.&lt;/ref&gt; The practice of magic is rooted in the belief that energy or 'life force' can be directed to enact change.&lt;ref name=SmithHorne&gt;Smith, Brandy and Sharon Horne. &quot;Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual and Transgendered (GLBT) Experiences with Earth-Spirited Faith.&quot; The Journal of Homosexuality, 52.3/4 (2007): 235-248.&lt;/ref&gt; However it is important to note that rituals are often improvised to suit individual or group needs and vary from coven to coven.&lt;ref name=Warwick&gt;Warwick, Lynda L. &quot;Feminist Wicca: Paths to Empowerment.&quot; Women &amp; Therapy 16.2-3 (1995): 121.&lt;/ref&gt; Some Dianic Wiccans eschew manipulative [[Spell (paranormal)|spellwork]] and [[Curse|hexing]] because it goes against the [[Wiccan Rede]]. However, many other Dianic witches (notably Budapest) do not consider hexing or binding of those who attack women to be wrong, and actively encourage the binding of [[rape|rapists]].&lt;ref name=Budapest1 /&gt;

===Differences from mainstream Wicca===
Like other Wiccans, Dianics may form [[coven]]s, attend [[festival]]s, celebrate the eight major [[Sabbat|Wiccan holidays]], and gather on [[Esbat]]s.&lt;ref name=Budapest1 /&gt; They use many of the same [[Magical tools in Wicca|altar tools]], rituals, and vocabulary as other Wiccans. Dianics may also gather in less formal Circles.&lt;ref name=&quot;Velkoborska 2010&quot;/&gt; The most noticeable difference between the two are that Dianic covens of Budapest lineage are composed entirely of women.&lt;ref name=Budapest1 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Adler1 /&gt;

When asked why &quot;men and gods&quot; are excluded from her rituals, Budapest stated:

{{Quote|It's the natural law, as women fare so fares the world, their children, and that's everybody. If you lift up the women you have lifted up humanity. Men have to learn to develop their own mysteries. Where is the order of Attis? Pan? Zagreus? Not only research it, but then popularize it as well as I have done. Where are the Dionysian rites? I think men are lazy in this aspect by not working this up for themselves. It's their own task, not ours.|during a 2007 interview&lt;ref name=&quot;Velkoborska 2010&quot;&gt;{{citation
|last=Velkoborska
|first=Kamila
|title=Wicca in the USA: How a British-born Religion Became Americanized
|url=http://conference.uaa.utb.cz/TheoriesAndPractice2010.pdf#page=245
|publisher=Tomas Bata University
|accessdate=25 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

There is therapeutic value inherent in Dianic ritual—many women use it to overcome personal trauma and raise awareness about violence towards women, earning comparisons to female-centered [[consciousness-raising]] groups in the 1960s and 70s.&lt;ref name=FoltzGriffin1&gt;Foltz, Tanic G. and Wendy Griffin. &quot;Ethnographic Journeys of Self Discovery&quot;, ''Composing Ethnography: Alternative Forms of Qualitative Writing''. (1996): 301–330.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=FoltzLozano&gt;Lozano, Wendy G. and Tanic G. Foltz. &quot;An Ethnographic Study of Witchcraft and Death&quot;, ''Qualitative Sociology'', Vol. 13, No. 13. (1990): 211–234.&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, some groups develop rituals specifically to confront gendered personal trauma, such as battery, rape, incest, and partner abuse. In one ethnographic study of such a ritual, women shifted their understanding of power from the hands of their abusers to themselves. It was found that this ritual had improved self-perception in participants in the short-term, and that the results could be sustained with ongoing practice.&lt;ref name=Jacobs1&gt;Jacobs, Janet L. &quot;The Effects of Ritual Healing on Female Victims of Abuse: A Study of Empowerment and Transformation&quot;. ''Sociological Analysis'', 50.3 (1989): 265–279.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Jacobs2&gt;Jacobs, Janet L. &quot;Women, Ritual, and Power&quot;. ''Frontiers: A Journal of Women Studies'', 11.2–3 (1990): 39–44.&lt;/ref&gt; 
 
Dianics pride themselves on the inclusion of [[lesbian]] and [[bisexual]] members. It is a goal within many covens to explore female sexuality and sensuality outside of male control, and many rituals function to affirm lesbian sexuality,&lt;ref name=Barrett&gt;Barrett, Ruth Rhiannon. &quot;Lesbian Rituals and Dianic Tradition&quot;. ''Journal of Lesbian Studies'', 7.2 (2003): 15–28. Web. 12 Feb. 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; making it a popular tradition for women who have come out.&lt;ref name=&quot;SmithHorne&quot;/&gt; Some covens exclusively consist of same-sex oriented women and advocate [[lesbian separatism]].

Dianic Wicca developed from the [[Women's Liberation Movement]] and covens traditionally compare themselves with [[radical feminism]]. Some of these covens reject [[Transgender|transgender people]] who were [[sex assignment|assigned male at birth]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Barrett&quot;/&gt; Some groups also directly challenge [[gender identity]].&lt;ref name=&quot;FoltzLozano&quot;/&gt;

==History==
[[File:Triple-Goddess Wiccan Symbol (modified).png|thumb|modified Triple-Goddess Wiccan symbol]]
[[Aradia, or the Gospel of the Witches]] claims that ancient Diana, [[Aphrodite]], Aradia, and [[Herodius]] cults linked to the [[Sacred Mysteries]] are the origin of the all-female [[coven]] and many witch myths as we know them.
Dianic Wicca began on the [[Winter Solstice]] of 1971, when Budapest led a ceremony in Hollywood, California.&lt;ref name=Budapest1 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Adler1 /&gt; Self-identifying as a &quot;hereditary witch,&quot;&lt;ref name=Budapest1 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Adler1 /&gt; and claiming to have learned folk magic from her mother,&lt;ref name=Budapest1 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Adler1 /&gt; Budapest is frequently considered the mother of modern Dianic Wiccan tradition.&lt;ref name=Adler1 /&gt; Dianic Wicca itself is named after the Roman goddess of the same name.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oswald 2003&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|last=Oswald
|first=Ramona Faith
|title=Lesbian rites: symbolic acts and the power of community
|year=2003
|publisher=Harrington Park Press
|location=Bringhampton, New York
|isbn=1-56023-315-X
|pages=15, 16, 17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Denominations and related traditions==
* Traditions derived from Zsuzsanna Budapest - Female-only covens run by priestesses trained and initiated by Budapest.
* Independent Dianic witches - who may have been inspired by Budapest, her published work (such as ''The Holy Book of Women's Mysteries'') or other woman's spirituality movements, and who emphasize independent study and self-initiation.

===McFarland Dianic===
McFarland Dianic is a Neopagan tradition of goddess worship founded by Morgan McFarland and Mark Roberts which, despite the shared name, has a different theology and in some cases accepts male participants.&lt;ref name=Adler1 /&gt; McFarland largely bases their tradition on the work of [[Robert Graves]] and his book ''[[The White Goddess]]''. While some McFarland covens will initiate men, the leadership is limited to female priestesses. Like other Dianic traditions, &quot;McFarland Dianic covens espouse feminism as an all-important concept.&quot; They consider the decision whether to include or exclude males as &quot;solely the choice of [a member coven's] individual High Priestess.&quot;&lt;ref name=McFarlandSite1&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.mcfarlanddianic.org/a-chronology.php| archive-date=27 July 2011 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110727074227/http://www.mcfarlanddianic.org/a-chronology.php | title= The McFarland Dianics -- A Chronology - Spring Equinox, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Feminist theology]]
**[[Goddess movement]]
**[[Thealogy]]
*[[Pachamama]]
*[[Sacred feminine]]
*[[Sacred Mysteries]]
*[[Shaktism]]
*[[Gynocentrism]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* Barrett, Ruth. ''Women's Rites, Women's Mysteries: Intuitive Ritual Creation''. Llewellyn Publications; 2007, {{ISBN|0-7387-0924-7}}. Earlier publishing: ''Women's Rites, Women's Mysteries: Creating Ritual in the Dianic Wiccan Tradition''. Authorhouse; 2004, {{ISBN|1-4184-8295-1}}.
* [[Riane Eisler|Eisler, Riane]], ''The Chalice and the Blade''.
* Mountainwater, Shekhinah, ''[[Ariadne]]'s Thread''.
* Ochshorn, Judith and [[Ellen Cole|Cole, Ellen]]. ''Women's Spirituality, Women's Lives''. Haworth Press 1995. {{ISBN|1-56024-722-3}}. pp 122 &amp; 133 referring to Z Budapest and Shekinah Mountainwater, among others, in a discussion of Dianic Witchcraft.
* Pond, Gina, et al. ''[http://st4r.org/main/circle-of-cerridwen/gender-and-transgender-in-modern-paganism-anthology/ Gender and Transgender in Modern Paganism]''. Circle of Cerridwen Press, 2012. {{ISBN|978-1-105-43378-8}}
* [http://www.witchvox.com/va/dt_va.html?a=usca&amp;c=trads&amp;id=3212 On Starhawk, the Reclaiming Tradition and feminism, M. Macha NightMare].
* ''Interview with [[Starhawk]] in Modern Pagans: An Investigation of Contemporary Pagan Practices'', ed. V. Vale and John Sulak, Re/Search, San Francisco, 2001, {{ISBN|1-889307-10-6}}.

==External links==
*[http://dianic.org/ Dianic Wicca, Official Website]
*[http://www.dianictradition.com/ Dianic Tradition, Official Website]
*[http://dianicwicca.com/ Dianic Wicca, Website]
*[http://zbudapest.com/ Z. Budapest]
*[http://goddess-festival.com/ International Goddess Conference]
*[http://susanbanthonycoven.com/ Susan B. Anthony Coven, Dianic Wicca Website]
*[http://www.templeofdiana.org/ Temple of Diana]
*[http://www.mcfarlanddianic.org/ The McFarland Dianic Tradition]


{{WiccaandWitchcraft}}

[[Category:Dianic Wicca| ]]
[[Category:Monotheism]]
[[Category:Theism]]
[[Category:Feminist spirituality]]
[[Category:Neopaganism in the United States]]
[[Category:Wiccan feminism]]
[[Category:Diana (mythology)]]</text>
      <sha1>3opp22qohw3b9reavsrrfgv59o7putg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
