  <page>
    <title>Telecommunications in the Central African Republic</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5484</id>
    <revision>
      <id>932738649</id>
      <parentid>915027883</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-27T23:02:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Monkbot</username>
        <id>20483999</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Radio and television */[[User:Monkbot/task 15: normalize lang icon templates|Task 15]]:  language icon template(s) replaced (1×);</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Telecommunications in the Central African Republic''' includes radio, television, fixed and mobile telephones, and the Internet as well as the postal system.

Persistent conflict has hampered telecommunication and media development in the [[Central African Republic]]. There are active television services, radio stations, [[internet service providers]], and [[Mobile network operator|mobile phone carriers]]. Radio is the most-popular communications medium.&lt;ref name=BBCNews-CAR-2013&gt;[https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-13150043 &quot;Central African Republic profile: Media&quot;], ''BBC News'', 20 September 2013. Retrieved 23 January 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Socatel]] is the leading provider for both Internet and mobile phone access throughout the country. The primary governmental regulating bodies of telecommunications are the ''Ministère des Postes'' (Ministry of Posts), and ''Télécommunications et des Nouvelles Technologies'' (Telecommunications and New Technologies). Support is received from the [[ITU-D|ITU Telecommunication Development Sector]] (ITU-D) within the [[International Telecommunication Union]] to improve telecommunications infrastructure.{{citation needed |date=January 2014}}

==Radio and television==

* [[Radio broadcasting|Radio stations]]: the State-owned radio network, Radio Centrafrique, is supplemented by a small number of privately owned broadcast stations as well as a few community radio stations; transmissions of at least 2 international broadcasters are available (2007).&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-CentralAfricanRepublic-2014&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/ct.html &quot;Communications: Central African Republic&quot;], ''World Factbook'', U.S. Central Intelligence Agency, 13 January 2014. Retrieved 23 January 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[BBC World Service]] (90.2 FM), [[Radio France Internationale]], and the [[Voice of America]] are available via local relays in the capital, [[Bangui]].&lt;ref name=BBCNews-CAR-2013/&gt;
* [[Receiver (radio)|Radios]]: 283,000 (1997).{{update after|2014|1|24}}
* [[Television broadcasting|Television stations]]: Government-owned network, ''Radiodiffusion Television Centrafricaine'' (Central Television Broadcasting), provides domestic TV broadcasting; licenses for 2 private TV stations were pending (2007).&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-CentralAfricanRepublic-2014/&gt;
* [[Television sets]]: 18,000 (1997).{{update after|2014|1|24}}

In Bangui, UN-sponsored Radio ''Ndeke Luka'' (&quot;bird of luck&quot;) provides balanced output, and rebroadcasts international news programming. Other radio and TV stations are run by the state-run ''Radiodiffusion-Television Centrafricaine'' and provide little coverage of the political opposition. There are about two dozen privately owned radio stations. Many, such as Radio Notre Dame, run by religious organisations.&lt;ref name=BBCNews-CAR-2013/&gt;

Starting 24 November 2011 ''La Radio et la Télévision nationale centrafricaine (TVCA)'' (Central African Radio (CAR) and National Television) are available via satellite. This move brought state-run national radio and television coverage to the entire country.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amb-rcaparis.org/site/information-numero-35?PHPSESSID=imds7m7koruld16pia02a1ssk3 &quot;La Radio et la télévision centrafricaine enfin sur satellite!&quot;] {{in lang|fr}}, La diplomatie de Centrafrique à Paris, CAR Embassy in Paris. [https://translate.google.com/translate?hl=en&amp;sl=fr&amp;u=http://www.amb-rcaparis.org/site/information-numero-35%3FPHPSESSID%3Dimds7m7koruld16pia02a1ssk3&amp;prev=/search%3Fq%3DRadio%25E2%2580%2593T%25C3%25A9l%25C3%25A9vision%2BCentrafrique%26client%3Dfirefox-beta%26hs%3DkOO%26rls%3Dorg.mozilla:en-US:official%26channel%3Dsb English translation]. Retrieved 24 January 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Telephones==
{{See also |Telephone numbers in the Central African Republic}}

* [[Calling code]]: +236&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-CentralAfricanRepublic-2014/&gt;
* [[List of international call prefixes|International call prefix]]: 00&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.itu.int/dms_pub/itu-t/opb/sp/T-SP-E.164C-2011-PDF-E.pdf ''Dialing Procedures (International Prefix, National (Trunk) Prefix and National (Significant) Number) (in Accordance with ITY-T Recommendation E.164 (11/2010))], Annex to ITU Operational Bulletin No. 994-15.XII.2011, International Telecommunication Union (ITU, Geneva), 15 December 2011. Retrieved 2 January 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Main lines: 5,600 lines in use, 209th in the world (2012).&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-CentralAfricanRepublic-2014/&gt;
* Mobile cellular: 1.1 million lines, 157th in the world (2012).&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-CentralAfricanRepublic-2014/&gt;
* Telephone system: The network consists principally of [[microwave radio relay]] and low-capacity, low-powered [[radiotelephone]] communication; limited telephone service with less than one fixed-line connection per 100 persons; spurred by the presence of multiple mobile-cellular service providers, cellular usage is increasing from a low base; most fixed-line and mobile-cellular telephone services are concentrated in the capital, [[Bangui]] (2011).&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-CentralAfricanRepublic-2014/&gt;
* [[Communications satellite|Satellite earth stations]]: 1 [[Intelsat]] ([[Atlantic Ocean]]) (2011).&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-CentralAfricanRepublic-2014/&gt;

[[GSM]] coverage was for a long time limited to the capital area. But in June 2006 coverage was expanded at least to Berberati in the western part of the country. There are currently two GSM-900 mobile operators, Telecel CAR and [[NationLink Telecom]] RCA. A third network, Centrafrique Telecom Plus closed down in late 2005 after failing to attract more than 5,000 subscribers and failing to renew its license, in accordance with the then new [[François Bozizé|Bozize government]] policies.{{citation needed |date=January 2014}}

==Internet==

* [[Top-level domain]]: [[.cf]]&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-CentralAfricanRepublic-2014/&gt;
* [[List of countries by number of Internet users|Internet users]]:
** 151,716 users, 160th in the world; 3.0% of the population, 195th in the world (2012).&lt;ref name=NIUCalc&gt;Calculated using penetration rate and population data from [https://www.census.gov/population/international/data/idb/rank.php &quot;Countries and Areas Ranked by Population: 2012&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170329060848/https://www.census.gov/population/international/data/idb/rank.php |date=2017-03-29 }}, Population data, International Programs, U.S. Census Bureau, retrieved 26 June 2013&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ITU-IndividualsUsingTheInternet&gt;[http://www.itu.int/en/ITU-D/Statistics/Documents/statistics/2013/Individuals_Internet_2000-2012.xls &quot;Percentage of Individuals using the Internet 2000–2012&quot;], International Telecommunications Union (Geneva), June 2013, retrieved 22 June 2013&lt;/ref&gt; 
** &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;22,600 users, 192nd in the world (2009).&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-CentralAfricanRepublic-2014/&gt;
* [[List of countries by number of Internet hosts|Internet hosts]]: 20 hosts, 221st in the world (2012).&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-CentralAfricanRepublic-2014/&gt;
* [[List of countries by IPv4 address allocation|IPv4]]: 4,352 addresses allocated, less than 0.05% of the world total, 0.9 addresses per 1000 people (2012).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.countryipblocks.net/country-blocks/select-formats/ Select Formats] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090513033601/http://www.countryipblocks.net/country-blocks/select-formats/ |date=2009-05-13 }}, Country IP Blocks. Accessed on 2 April 2012. Note: Site is said to be updated daily.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/fields/2119.html Population], [[The World Factbook]], [[United States]] [[Central Intelligence Agency]]. Accessed on 2 April 2012. Note: Data are mostly for 1 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Internet Service Providers]] (ISPs): Moov, [[Orange S.A.|Orange]], [[Socatel]], and Telecel.{{citation needed |date=January 2014}}

===Internet censorship and surveillance===

There are no government restrictions on access to the Internet or credible reports that the government monitors [[e-mail]] or Internet [[chat rooms]] without judicial oversight.&lt;ref name=USDOS-CAR-2012&gt;[https://2009-2017.state.gov/j/drl/rls/hrrpt/humanrightsreport/index.htm?year=2012&amp;dlid=204102 &quot;Central African Republic&quot;], ''Country Reports on Human Rights Practices for 2012'', Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights and Labor, U.S. Department of State, 28 March 2013. Retrieved 23 January 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the constitution and law provide for [[freedom of speech]] and [[freedom of the press|press]], authorities occasionally arrest journalists critical of the government and in some cases the government impedes individuals’ right to free speech. Imprisonment for [[defamation]] and [[censorship]] were abolished in 2005; however, journalists found guilty of [[libel]] or [[slander]] face fines of 100,000 to eight million CFA francs ($200 to US$16,000). The law provides for imprisonment and fines of as much as one million CFA francs (US$2,000) for journalists who use the media to incite disobedience among security forces or incite persons to violence, [[hate speech|hatred]], or discrimination. Similar fines and imprisonment of six months to two years may be imposed for the publication or broadcast of false or fabricated information that &quot;would disturb the peace.&quot;&lt;ref name=USDOS-CAR-2012/&gt;

== Postal System==

L'Office National de la Poste et de l'Épargne (ONPE) is the government organization responsible for the postal service.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.microsofttranslator.com/BV.aspx?ref=IE8Activity&amp;a=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.armniger.org%2Findex.php%2Fpresentation-de-poste%3Fshowall%3D1%26limitstart%3D|title=Presentation Station|last=|first=|date=2018|website=|access-date=October 19, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==

* [[Media of the Central African Republic]]
* [[Economy of the Central African Republic]]
* [[Central African Republic]]

==References==

* {{CIA World Factbook |year=2014}}
* {{US DOS |year=2012}}
{{reflist |30em}}

==External links==
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/country_profiles/1067518.stm Central African Republic profile], ''BBC News''.

{{Clear}}
{{Central African Republic topics}}
{{Africa topic|Telecommunications in}}
{{Telecommunications}}
{{Internet censorship by country}}

[[Category:Telecommunications in the Central African Republic| ]]
[[Category:Communications in the Central African Republic]]</text>
      <sha1>gdlfv051upzu4n52hmmnoysqly97l6n</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
