  <page>
    <title>Foreign relations of the Cayman Islands</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5477</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941847671</id>
      <parentid>789244587</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-21T01:21:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>210.48.190.54</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>No references have been provided for this article, therefore an unreferenced tag has been added to this article.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{unreferenced|date=February 2020}}
The '''foreign relations of the [[Cayman Islands]]''' are largely managed from the [[United Kingdom]], as the islands remains [[British overseas territories|one of 14 overseas territories]] under [[British Empire|British jurisdiction and sovereignty]]. However, the [[Government of the Cayman Islands]] have [[autonomy]] and often resolves important issues with foreign governments alone, without intervention from Britain. Although in its early days, the Cayman Islands' most important relationships were with Britain and [[Jamaica]], in recent years, this has shifted, and they now rely more so on the [[United States]] and [[Canada]].

Though the Cayman Islands are involved in no major international disputes, they have come under some criticism due to the use of their territory for [[narcotics trafficking]] and [[money laundering]]. In an attempt to address this, the Government entered into the Narcotics Agreement of 1984 and the [[Mutual Legal Assistance Treaty]] of 1986 with the United States, in order to reduce the use of their facilities associated with these activities. In more recent years, they have stepped up the fight against money laundering, by limiting banking secrecy, introducing requirements for customer identification and record keeping, and requiring banks to cooperate with foreign investigators.

Due to their status as an overseas territory of the UK, the Cayman Islands have no representation either on the [[United Nations]], or in most other international organizations. However, the Cayman Islands still participates in some international organisations, being a full member of the [[Central Development Bank]] and [[International Olympic Committee]], an associate member of [[Caricom]] and [[UNESCO]], and a member of a subbureau of [[Interpol (organization)|Interpol]].

==Bilateral relations==
===India===
{{main|Cayman Islands–India relations}}

===United States===
{{main|Cayman Islands–United States relations}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==See also==
*[[Foreign relations of the United Kingdom]]
*[[British Overseas Territories]]

{{Foreign relations in the Caribbean}}
{{Americas topic|Foreign relations of|title=Foreign relations in the Americas}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Foreign Relations of the Cayman Islands}}
[[Category:Government of the Cayman Islands]]
[[Category:Foreign relations of the Caribbean]]</text>
      <sha1>esgz76rrjyb4k57ktgd7wohgy3u9r0r</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
