  <page>
    <title>Politics of Cambodia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5431</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941587169</id>
      <parentid>928872470</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-19T13:50:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Vpab15</username>
        <id>26557985</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>oppostion</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{more citations needed|date=February 2013}}
{{Politics of Cambodia}}
The '''politics of Cambodia''' are defined within the framework of a [[constitutional monarchy]], in which the [[Monarchy of Cambodia|King]] serves as the [[head of state]], and the [[Prime Minister of Cambodia|prime minister]] is the [[head of government]]. The [[Collapse of Communism|collapse of communism]] set in motion events that led to the withdrawal of the [[People's Army of Vietnam|Vietnamese armed forces]], which had established their presence in the country since the [[Khmer Rouge#Fall|fall of the Khmer Rouge]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.usip.org/publications/2017/05/lessons-cambodias-paris-peace-accords-political-unrest-today|title=Lessons from Cambodia's Paris Peace Accords for Political Unrest Today|website=United States Institute of Peace|language=en|access-date=2018-06-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Constitution of Cambodia|1993 constitution]], which is currently in force, was promulgated as a result of the [[1991 Paris Peace Agreements]], followed by [[1993 Cambodian general election|elections]] organized under the aegis of the [[United Nations Transitional Authority in Cambodia]]. The constitution proclaims a liberal, multiparty democracy in which powers are devolved to the [[Executive (government)|executive]], the [[judiciary]] and the [[legislature]]. However, there is no effective opposition to the Prime Minister [[Hun Sen]], who has been in power for over 35 years. His [[Cambodian People's Party]] won all 125 seats in the National Assembly in 2018 after the banning of opposition party [[CNRP]]. Furthermore, the governing charter declares Cambodia to be an &quot;independent, sovereign, peaceful, permanently neutral and non-aligned State.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=xXQ6Od8xVMsC&amp;pg=PA210&amp;lpg=PA210&amp;dq=independent,+sovereign,+peaceful,+permanently+neutral+and+non-aligned+State+cambodia#v=onepage&amp;q=independent,%20sovereign,%20peaceful,%20permanently%20neutral%20and%20non-aligned%20State%20cambodia&amp;f=false|title=Framing the State in Times of Transition: Case Studies in Constitution Making|last=Miller|first=Laurel E.|last2=Aucoin|first2=Louis|date=2010|publisher=US Institute of Peace Press|isbn=9781601270559|location=|pages=210|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Executive power is exercised by the Royal Government, on behalf of and with the consent of the monarch. The government is constituted of the Council of Ministers, headed by the prime minister. The prime minister is aided in his functions by members of the Council such as deputy prime ministers, senior ministers and other ministers. Legislative power is vested in a [[Bicameralism|bicameral legislature]] composed of the [[National Assembly of Cambodia|National Assembly]], which has the power to vote on draft law, and the [[Senate of Cambodia|Senate]], that has the power of review. Upon passage of legislation through the two chambers, the draft law is presented to the monarch for signing and promulgation. The judiciary is tasked with the protection of rights and liberties of the citizens, and with being an impartial arbiter of disputes. The Supreme Court is the highest court of the country and takes appeals from lower courts on questions of law. A separate body called the Constitutional Council was established to provide interpretations of the constitution and the laws, and also to resolve disputes related to election of members of the legislature.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.nyulawglobal.org/globalex/Cambodia.html|title=Overview of the Cambodian History, Governance and Legal Sources - GlobaLex|website=www.nyulawglobal.org|language=en|access-date=2018-06-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Cambodian People's Party]] has dominated the political landscape since the [[1997 clashes in Cambodia|1997 armed clashes]] in Phnom Penh. Other prominent political parties include the royalist [[FUNCINPEC]] and the erstwhile [[Cambodia National Rescue Party]] that was dissolved by the Supreme Court in 2017. Comparative political scientists [[Steven Levitsky]] and Lucan Way have described Cambodia as a &quot;competitive authoritarian regime&quot;, a [[hybrid regime]] type with important characteristics of both democracy and authoritarianism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/competitive-authoritarianism/20A51BE2EBAB59B8AAEFD91B8FA3C9D6|title=Competitive Authoritarianism by Steven Levitsky|last=Way|first=Lucan A.|last2=Levitsky|first2=Steven|date=2010|website=Cambridge Core|page=3|language=en|access-date=2019-04-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Legal framework ==
Cambodia is a [[constitutional monarchy]] with a [[Unitary state|unitary]] structure&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.adb.org/publications/deconcentration-and-decentralization-reforms-cambodia-recommendations-institutional|title=Deconcentration and Decentralization Reforms in Cambodia: Recommendations for an Institutional Framework|last=Niazi|first=Tariq H.|date=2011-06-01|publisher=Asian Development Bank|isbn=9789290922650|location=|pages=74|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a [[Representative democracy|parliamentary]] form of government.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://2009-2017.state.gov/documents/organization/186476.pdf|title=Country Reports for Human Rights Practices for 2011|last=US State Department|date=2011|website=state.gov|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The constitution, which prescribes the governing framework, was promulgated in September 1993 by the [[Cambodia Constituent Assembly|Constituent Assembly]] that resulted from the [[1993 Cambodian general election|1993 general election]] conducted under the auspices of the [[United Nations Transitional Authority in Cambodia]] (UNTAC). The assembly adopted the basic principles and measures mandated under the [[1991 Paris Peace Agreements|Paris Peace Agreements]] into the text of the constitution. Assimilated into the governing charter, these provisions place the constitution as the supreme law of the land; declare Cambodia's status as a sovereign, independent and neutral state; enshrine a liberal, multi-party democracy with fair and periodic elections; guarantee respect for human rights; and provide for an independent judiciary.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.cambodia.org/facts/?page=1991+Paris+Peace+Agreements|title=1991 Paris Peace Agreements - Government, Constitution, National Anthem and Facts of Cambodia|last=|first=|date=|website=Cambodia Information Center|access-date=2019-03-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; The brutality of the [[Democratic Kampuchea]] regime had especially necessitated the inclusion of provisions concerning human rights&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Ratner|first=Steven R.|date=1993|title=The Cambodia Settlement Agreements|journal=The American Journal of International Law|volume=87|issue=1|pages=25–28|doi=10.2307/2203851|issn=0002-9300|jstor=2203851}}&lt;/ref&gt; in order to prevent a return to the policies and practices of the past.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.ohchr.org/EN/NewsEvents/Pages/Cambodia-20yearsonfromtheParisPeace.aspx|title=OHCHR {{!}} Cambodia - 20 years on from the Paris Peace Agreements|website=www.ohchr.org|access-date=2019-04-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; These criteria had been drawn from the Namibian constitution drafting process that took place in 1982.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt; German constitutional law scholar, [[W:de:Jörg Menzel|Jörg Menzel]], characterized these benchmarks as the &quot;necessary nucleus of a modern constitutional state.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Menzel, Jörg. Cambodia from Civil War to a Constitution to Constitutionalism? Hor Peng et al. ''Cambodian Constitutional Law'' pp. 16-17&lt;/ref&gt; The constitution further sanctifies the status of international law in the issue of human rights by binding Cambodia to &quot;respect&quot; the provisions of human rights treaties adopted by the UN.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://harvard-yenching.org/features/hyi-working-paper-series-kuong-teilee-0|title=Cambodian Constitutional Provisions on Treaties: A Story of Constitutional Evolution Beyond Rhetoric|last=Kuong|first=Teilee|date=|website=Harvard Yenching Institute|access-date=2019-04-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 1993 constitution has been amended nine times since its passage – in 1994, 1999, 2001, 2005, 2006, 2008, 2014&lt;ref&gt;Hor Peng. The Constitution of the Kingdom of Cambodia: The Evolution of Constitutional Theories and Interpretation. Hor Peng et al. ''Cambodian Constitutional Law''. p. 47&lt;/ref&gt; and 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.phnompenhpost.com/national-politics/lese-majeste-law-now-effect|title=Lèse majesté law now in effect, National, Politics, Phnom Penh Post|last=Chheng|first=Niem|last2=Nachemson|first2=Andrew|date=5 March 2018|website=www.phnompenhpost.com|language=en|access-date=2019-04-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Separation of powers ===
The powers are devolved to three branches of the state: the [[Parliament of Cambodia|legislature]], the executive and the judiciary, in recognition of the doctrine of [[separation of powers]]. [[Westphalian sovereignty|Political sovereignty]] rests with the Cambodian people, who exercise their power through the three arms of the state. The Royal Government, which wields executive power, is directly responsible to the [[National Assembly of Cambodia|National Assembly]]. The judiciary, which is an independent power, is tasked with the protection of citizens' rights and liberties.&lt;ref&gt;Hor Peng. The Constitution of the Kingdom of Cambodia: The Evolution of Constitutional Theories and Interpretation. Hor Peng et al. ''Cambodian Constitutional Law''. p. 45&lt;/ref&gt; Buddhism is proclaimed as the state religion.&lt;ref&gt;Kong Phallack. Freedom of Religion in Cambodia. Hor Peng et al. ''Cambodian Constitutional Law''. p. 393&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Influences on legal system ===
The legal system of Cambodia is [[Civil law (legal system)|civil law]] and has been strongly influenced by the [[Law of France|legal heritage]] of France as a consequence of [[French Protectorate of Cambodia|colonial rule]].&lt;ref&gt;Menzel, Jörg. Cambodia from Civil War to a Constitution to Constitutionalism? Hor Peng et al. ''Cambodian Constitutional Law'' p. 31&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Socialist law|Soviet-Vietnamese system]] dominated the country from 1981 until 1989, and Sri Lankan jurist [[Basil Fernando]] argues that its elements are present in the current system as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://catalogue.nla.gov.au/Record/461500|title=Problems facing the Cambodian legal system|last=Fernando|first=Basil|last2=Kirby|first2=M. D.|date=1998|publisher=Asian Human Rights Commission|others=Asian Human Rights Commission|isbn=9789628314027|location=Hong Kong, China|pages=vi}}&lt;/ref&gt; The role of [[customary law]], based on Buddhist beliefs and unwritten law drawn from the [[Angkor|Angkorean period]], is also prevalent.&lt;ref&gt;Kong Phallack. Overview of the Cambodian Legal and Judicial System and Recent Efforts at Legal and Judicial Reform. Hor Peng et al. ''Introduction to Cambodian Law''. pp. 7-8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hor Peng. The Constitution of the Kingdom of Cambodia: The Evolution of Constitutional Theories and Interpretation. Hor Peng et al. ''Cambodian Constitutional Law''. pp. 44-45&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Market economy ===
The constitution contains a commitment to the &quot;market economy system&quot;, which along with accompanying provisions effects a fundamental change in the role of the state from the past.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=St John|first=Ronald Bruce|date=1995|title=The Political Economy of the Royal Government of Cambodia|journal=Contemporary Southeast Asia|volume=17|issue=3|pages=266–269|issn=0129-797X|jstor=25798289}}&lt;/ref&gt; Security of private property and the right to sell and exchange freely, necessary conditions for the functioning of the market economy,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Ear|first=Sophal|date=1995|title=Cambodia's Economic Development in Historical Perspective: A Contribution to the Study of Cambodia's Economy|url=https://www.academia.edu/2336758|journal=|language=en|volume=|page=82|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; are provided for. The state's powers of expropriation are limited to the extent they serve public interest, to be exercised only when &quot;fair and just&quot; compensation is made in advance.&lt;ref&gt;Kuong Teilee. Economic Rights and the National Economic System. Hor Peng et al. ''Cambodian Constitutional Law''. p. 498&lt;/ref&gt; Operating under the slogan &quot;''Le Cambodge s'aide lui-même''&quot; or &quot;Cambodia will help itself&quot;, one of the earliest undertakings of the Royal Government was to implement programs to ensure the economic rehabilitation of Cambodia and its integration in the regional and global economies. On 10 March 1994, the Royal Government declared an &quot;irreversible and irrevocable&quot; move away from a centrally-planned economy towards a market-oriented economy.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;

==Monarchy==
[[File:Norodom king of Cambodia.jpg|right|thumb|[[King]] [[Norodom Sihamoni]]]]
Cambodia is a [[constitutional monarchy]], i.e. the King reigns but does not rule, in similar fashion to Queen [[Elizabeth II of the United Kingdom]]. The King is officially the [[Head of State]] and is the symbol of unity and &quot;perpetuity&quot; of the nation, as defined by Cambodia's constitution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Cambodia 1993 (rev. 2008)|url=https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Cambodia_2008?lang=en#26|website=Constitute|accessdate=17 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From September 24, 1993 through October 7, 2004, [[Norodom Sihanouk]] reigned as King, after having previously served in a number of offices (including King) since 1941. Under the Constitution, the King has no political power, but as Norodom Sihanouk was revered in the country, his word often carried much influence in the government.  While such views are not prevalent in Cambodia, his word was respected by his subjects. The King, often irritated over the conflicts in his government, several times threatened to abdicate unless the political factions in the government got along. This put pressure on the government to solve their differences.  This influence of the King was often used to help mediate differences in government.

After the abdication of King Norodom Sihanouk in 2004, he was succeeded by his son [[Norodom Sihamoni]]. While the retired King was highly revered in his country for dedicating his lifetime to Cambodia, the current King has spent most of his life abroad in [[France]]. Thus, it remains to be seen whether the new King's views will be as highly respected as his father's.

Although in the [[Khmer language]] there are many words meaning &quot;king&quot;, the word officially used in Khmer (as found in the 1993 Cambodian Constitution) is ''preahmâhaksat'' (Khmer regular script: ព្រះមហាក្សត្រ), which literally means: ''preah''- (&quot;excellent&quot;, cognate of the [[Pali]] word [[w:wiktionary:vara#Pali|vara]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://sealang.net/api/api.pl?query=%E1%9E%96%E1%9F%92%E1%9E%9A%E1%9F%87&amp;service=dictionary|title=Native orthography for &quot;ព្រះ&quot;, SEAlang Dictionary|website=sealang.net|access-date=2019-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;) -''mâha''- (from [[Sanskrit]], meaning &quot;great&quot;, cognate with &quot;maha-&quot; in [[maharaja]]) -''ksat'' (&quot;warrior, ruler&quot;, cognate of the Sanskrit word [[w:wiktionary:क्षत्र|kṣatrá]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://sealang.net/api/api.pl?query=%E1%9E%80%E1%9F%92%E1%9E%9F%E1%9E%8F%E1%9F%92%E1%9E%9A&amp;service=dictionary|title=Native orthography for &quot;ក្សត្រ&quot;, SEAlang Dictionary|website=sealang.net|access-date=2019-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;).

On the occasion of King Norodom Sihanouk's retirement in September 2004, the Cambodian National Assembly coined a new word for the retired king: ''preahmâhaviraksat'' (Khmer regular script: ព្រះមហាវីរក្សត្រ), where ''vira'' comes from Sanskrit ''vīra'', meaning &quot;brave or eminent man, hero, chief&quot;, cognate of [[Latin]] ''vir'', ''viris'', [[English language|English]] ''virile''. ''Preahmâhaviraksat'' is translated in English as &quot;King-Father&quot; ({{lang-fr|Roi-Père}}), although the word &quot;father&quot; does not appear in the Khmer noun.

As ''preahmâhaviraksat'', Norodom Sihanouk retained many of the prerogatives he formerly held as ''preahmâhaksat'' and was a highly respected and listened-to figure. Thus, in effect, Cambodia could be described as a country with two Kings during Sihanouk's lifetime: the one who was the Head of State, the ''preahmâhaksat'' Norodom Sihamoni, and the one who was not the Head of State, the ''preahmâhaviraksat'' Norodom Sihanouk.{{Citation needed|date=March 2019}}

Sihanouk died of a pulmonary infarction on October 15, 2012.

===Succession to the throne===
Unlike most monarchies, Cambodia's monarchy is not necessarily [[hereditary monarchy|hereditary]] and the King is not allowed to select his own heir.  Instead, a new King is chosen by a Royal Council of the Throne, consisting of the president of the National Assembly, the Prime Minister, the President of the Senate, the First and Second Vice Presidents of the Senate, the Chiefs of the orders of [[Buddhism in Cambodia#Cambodian adaptations|Mohanikay and Thammayut]], and the First and Second Vice-President of the Assembly.  The Royal Council meets within a week of the King's death or abdication and selects a new King from a pool of candidates with royal blood.

It has been suggested that Cambodia's ability to peacefully appoint a new King shows that Cambodia's government has stabilized incredibly from the situation the country was in during the 1970s (see [[History of Cambodia]]).

==Executive branch==
[[File:Hun_Sen_(2016)_cropped.jpg|thumb|[[Hun Sen]] – [[Prime Minister of Cambodia|Prime Minister]]]]
[[File:Seal of the Cabinet of Cambodia.svg|thumb|Seal of the Royal Government]]The [[Prime Minister of Cambodia]] is a representative from the ruling party of the National Assembly. He or she is appointed by the King on the recommendation of the President and Vice Presidents of the National Assembly.  In order for a person to become Prime Minister, he or she must first be given a vote of confidence by the National Assembly.

The Prime Minister is officially the [[Head of Government]] in Cambodia. Upon entry into office, he or she appoints a Council of Ministers who are responsible to the Prime Minister.  Officially, the Prime Minister's duties include chairing meetings of the Council of Ministers (Cambodia's version of a [[Cabinet (government)|Cabinet]]) and appointing and leading a government. The Prime Minister and his government make up Cambodia's [[executive (government)|executive branch]] of government.

The current Prime Minister is [[Cambodian People's Party]] (CPP) member [[Hun Sen]]. He has held this position since the criticized 1998 election, one year after the CPP staged a bloody [[coup d'état|coup]] in Phnom Penh&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://cambodia.ohchr.org/Documents/Statements%20and%20Speeches/English/40.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2007-06-27 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070627054853/http://cambodia.ohchr.org/Documents/Statements%20and%20Speeches/English/40.pdf |archivedate=2007-06-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hri.org/docs/statedep/1997/97-07-08.std.html&lt;/ref&gt; to overthrow elected Prime Minister Prince [[Norodom Ranariddh]], president of the [[FUNCINPEC]] party.

==Legislative branch==
{{update|section|date=December 2013 }}
The [[legislature|legislative branch]] of the Cambodian government is made up of a [[bicameral]] [[parliament]].

* The '''[[National Assembly of Cambodia|National Assembly]]''' (''Radhsaphea'') has 125 members, elected for a five-year term by [[proportional representation]].
* The '''[[Senate of Cambodia|Senate]]''' (''Protsaphea'') has 61 members.  Two of these members are appointed by the King, two are elected by the lower house of the government, and the remaining fifty-seven are elected popularly by &quot;functional constituencies.&quot;  Members in this house serve a six-year term.

The official duty of the Parliament is to legislate and make laws.  Bills passed by the Parliament are given to the King who gives the proposed bills [[royal assent]].  The King does not have [[veto]] power over bills passed by the National Assembly and thus, cannot withhold royal assent.  The National Assembly also has the power to dismiss the Prime Minister and his government by a two-thirds [[vote of no confidence]].

===Senate===

The upper house of the Cambodian legislature is called the ''Senate''. It consists of sixty-one members.  Two of these members are appointed by the King, two are elected by the lower house of the government, and the remaining fifty-seven are elected popularly by electors from provincial and local governments, in a similar fashion to the [[Senate of France]]. Members in this house serve six-year terms.

Prior to 2006, elections had last been held for the Senate in 1999. New elections were supposed to have occurred in 2004, but these elections were initially postponed. On January 22, 2006, 11,352 possible voters went to the poll and chose their candidates. This election was criticized by local monitoring non-governmental organizations as being undemocratic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/4638406.stm|title=Ruling party wins Cambodia poll|author=|date=19 May 2018|via=news.bbc.co.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{As of|2006}}, the [[Cambodian People's Party]] holds forty-three seats in the Senate, constituting a significant majority. The two other major parties holding seats in the Senate are the [[Funcinpec]] party (holding twelve seats) and the [[Sam Rainsy Party]] (holding two seats).

===National Assembly===

The lower house of the legislature is called the ''National Assembly''.  It is made up of 125 members, elected by popular vote to serve a five-year term.  Elections were last held for the National Assembly in July 2013.

In order to vote in legislative elections, one must be at least eighteen years of age. However, in order to be elected to the Legislature, one must be at least twenty-five years of age.

The National Assembly is led by a President and two Vice Presidents who are selected by Assembly members prior to each session.

{{As of|2018}}, the [[Cambodian People's Party]] holds all 125 seats in the National Assembly.

==Political parties and elections==
[[File:Sam Rainsy (cropped).jpg|170px|thumb|right|Former opposition leader and CNRP President [[Sam Rainsy]]]]
[[File:Norodom Ranariddh (2014).jpg|170px|thumb|right|Former First Prime Minister and FUNCINPEC President [[Norodom Ranariddh]]]]
{{elect|List of political parties in Cambodia|Elections in Cambodia}}

===2018 general election results===
{{#section-h:2018 Cambodian general election|Results}}

==Judicial branch==

The [[judiciary|judicial branch]] is independent from the rest of the government, as specified by the Cambodian [[Constitution]]. The highest court of judicial branch is the [[Supreme Council of the Magistracy]]. Other, lower courts also exist. Until 1997, Cambodia did not have a judicial branch of government despite the nation's Constitution requiring one.

The main duties of the judiciary are to prosecute criminals, settle lawsuits, and, most importantly, protect the freedoms and rights of Cambodian citizens. However, in reality, the judicial branch in Cambodia is highly corrupt and often serves as a tool of the executive branch to silence civil society and its leaders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hrw.org/english/docs/2006/01/18/cambod12269.htm|title=Essential Background: Overview of human rights issues in Cambodia |website=Human Rights Watch|date=31 December 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are currently 17 justices on the Supreme Council.

==International organization participation==
ACCT, [[Asian Development Bank|AsDB]], [[ASEAN]], ESCAP, FAO, G-77, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, [[International Criminal Court|ICC]], ICRM, IDA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, ILO, IMF, IMO, Intelsat (nonsignatory user), [[International Monetary Fund]], Interpol, IOC, ISO (subscriber), ITU, NAM, OPCW, PCA, [[United Nations|UN]], UNCTAD, [[UNESCO]], UNIDO, UPU, [[World Bank|WB]], WFTU, WHO, WIPO, WMO, [[World Trade Organization|WTO]], WToO, WTrO (applicant)

=== International rankings ===

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Organization 	 !! Survey 	 !! Ranking !! Score
|-
| [[Transparency International]]|| [[Corruption Perceptions Index]] (2012)|| 164 Out of 184|| 89.13%
|-
| [[United Nations Development Programme]]||  	[[Human Development Index]] (2012)|| 139 Out of 184|| 75.5%
|-
| [[World Gold Council]]|| [[Gold reserve]] (2010)|| 65 Out of 110|| 60%
|-
| [[Reporters Without Borders]]|| [[Worldwide Press Freedom Index]] (2012)|| 117 out of 179|| 65.3%
|-
| [[The Heritage Foundation]]||  [[Indices of Economic Freedom]] (2012)|| 102 Out of 179|| 57%
|-
| [[Global Competitiveness Report]]|| [[World Economic Forum]] (2012)|| 97 out of 142|| 68.3%
|-
|}

==Provincial and local governments==
{{see also|Administrative divisions of Cambodia}}
Below the central government are 24 provincial and municipal administration.&lt;ref name=wb&gt;''Private Solutions for Infrastructure in Cambodia: A Country Framework Report''. [[World Bank]] (2002), [https://books.google.com/books?id=ktRy_5sKrGEC&amp;pg=PA65 p65]. {{ISBN|0-8213-5076-5}}.&lt;/ref&gt; (In rural areas, first-level administrative divisions are called provinces; in urban areas, they are called municipalities.)  The administrations are a part of the [[Ministry of the Interior (Cambodia)|Ministry of the Interior]] and their members are appointed by the central government.&lt;ref name=wb/&gt; Provincial and municipal administrations participate in the creation of nation budget; they also issue land titles and license businesses.&lt;ref name=wb/&gt;

Since 2002, commune-level governments ([[commune council]]s) have been composed of members directly elected by commune residents every five years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.embassyofcambodia.org.nz/March2007/March2007-3.htm|title=Account Suspended|author=|date=|website=www.embassyofcambodia.org.nz}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In practice, the allocation of responsibilities between various levels of government is uncertain.&lt;ref name=wb/&gt;  This uncertainty has created additional opportunities for corruption and increased costs for investors.&lt;ref name=wb/&gt;

== Citations ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== References ==
{{refbegin|60em}}
*{{cite book |editor-last=Hor |editor-first=Peng |editor2-last=Kong |editor2-first=Phallack |editor3-last=Menzel |editor3-first=Jörg |title=Introduction to Cambodian Law|url=https://www.kas.de/single-title/-/content/einfuehrung-in-das-kambodschanische-recht |publisher=Konrad Adenauer Stiftung, Cambodia |date=21 May 2012}}
*{{cite book |editor-last=Hor |editor-first=Peng |editor2-last=Kong |editor2-first=Phallack |editor3-last=Menzel |editor3-first=Jörg |title=Cambodian Constitutional Law|url=https://www.kas.de/web/kambodscha/single-title/-/content/kambodschanisches-verfassungsrecht |publisher=Konrad Adenauer Stiftung, Cambodia |date=July 2016}}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
* [https://archive.today/20130414213804/http://report.globalintegrity.org/cambodia Global Integrity Report: Cambodia] reports on corruption and anti-corruption in Cambodia

===Royalty===
*[http://www.norodomsihamoni.org King of Cambodia, Norodom Sihamoni] Official Website of King Norodom Sihamoni
*[http://www.norodomsihanouk.info King of Cambodia, Norodom Sihanouk] Official Website of former King Norodom Sihanouk

===Official===
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20061005044434/http://www.cambodia.gov.kh/unisql1/egov/english/home.view.html Cambodia.gov.kh] Official Royal Government of Cambodia Website (English Version) ([https://web.archive.org/web/20051207102921/http://www.cambodia.gov.kh/unisql2/egov/khmer/home.view.html Cambodia.gov.kh Khmer Version])
*[http://www.cdc-crdb.gov.kh CDC] Council for the Development of Cambodia
*[http://www.ccc.gov.kh/ Conseil Constitutionnel du Cambodge] Constitution council of Cambodia
*[http://www.maff.gov.kh/ Department of Fisheries]
*[http://www.foodsecurity.gov.kh/ Food Security and Nutrition Information System Cambodia]
*[http://www.moc.gov.kh/ Ministry of Commerce]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20051125210221/http://www.moi-coci.gov.kh/culture/ Ministry of Culture and Fine Arts]
*[http://www.mef.gov.kh/ Ministry of Economy and Finance]
*[http://www.moeys.gov.kh Ministry of Education, Youth and Sport]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20051202123408/http://www.camnet.com.kh/moe/ Ministry of Environment]
*[http://www.mptc.gov.kh/ Ministry of Posts and Telecommunications]
*[http://www.mpwt.gov.kh/ Ministry of Public Works and Transport]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20020202171903/http://www.mot.gov.kh/ Ministry of Tourism]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20090525141512/http://www.nida.gov.kh/ NiDA] National Information Communications Technology Development Authority
*[http://www.mop.gov.kh/ Ministry of Planning]
*[http://www.nis.gov.kh/ NIS] National Institute of Statistics of Cambodia
*[http://www.interior.gov.kh/ Ministry of Interior]
*[http://www.ncct.gov.kh/ N.C.C.T] National Committee for Counter Trafficking in person

===Other===
* [http://www.embassy.org/cambodia/cambodia/constitu.htm Constitution of Cambodia]

{{Asia topic|Politics of}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Politics Of Cambodia}}
&lt;!--Categories--&gt;
[[Category:Politics of Cambodia| ]]
[[Category:Government of Cambodia]]
[[Category:Politics of Southeast Asia|Cambodia]]</text>
      <sha1>ju7195z43kh84eb5txpfvwralzwpnib</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
