  <page>
    <title>History of the Central African Republic</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5479</id>
    <revision>
      <id>932738633</id>
      <parentid>932469272</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-27T23:02:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Monkbot</username>
        <id>20483999</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* 2012–2014: Civil War */[[User:Monkbot/task 15: normalize lang icon templates|Task 15]]:  language icon template(s) replaced (1×);</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2013}}
{{History of the Central African Republic|expanded=all}}
The  '''history of the [[Central African Republic]]''' is roughly composed of four distinct periods. The earliest period of settlement began around 10,000 years ago when nomadic people first began to settle, farm and fish in the region. The next period began around 1,000 to 3,000 years ago when several non-indigenous groups began to migrate into the region from other parts of the continent. The third period involved the colonial conquest and rule of the country by France and Germany which spanned from the late 1800s until 1960 when the Central African Republic became an independent state. The final period has been the era during which the Central African Republic has been an independent state.

== Early history ==
Approximately 10,000 years ago, [[desertification]] forced hunter-gatherer societies south into the Sahel regions of northern Central Africa, where some groups settled and began farming as part of the [[Neolithic Revolution]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Eastern Africa 2011, pg. 4&quot;&gt;The History of Central and Eastern Africa, Amy McKenna, 2011, pg. 4&lt;/ref&gt; Initial farming of [[Dioscorea rotundata|white yam]] progressed into [[millet]] and [[sorghum]], and then later the domestication of [[Elaeis guineensis|African oil palm]] improved the groups' nutrition and allowed for expansion of the local populations.&lt;ref&gt;The History of Central and Eastern Africa, Amy McKenna, 2011, pg. 5&lt;/ref&gt; Bananas arrived in the region and added an important source of carbohydrates to the diet; they were also used in the production of alcohol.{{when|date=June 2014}} This Agricultural Revolution, combined with a &quot;Fish-stew Revolution&quot;, in which fishing began to take place, and the use of boats, allowed for the transportation of goods. Products were often moved in [[ceramic]] pots, which are the first known examples of [[artistic expression]] from the region's inhabitants.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eastern Africa 2011, pg. 4&quot;/&gt;

The [[Bouar|Bouar Megaliths]] in the western region of the country indicate an advanced level of habitation dating back to the very late [[Neolithic|Neolithic Era]] (c. 3500-2700 BC).&lt;ref&gt;Methodology and African Prehistory by, [[UNESCO]]. International Scientific Committee for the Drafting of a General History of Africa, pg. 548&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;UNESCO World Heritage, Les mégalithes de Bouar, https://whc.unesco.org/en/tentativelists/4003/&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ferrous metallurgy|Ironworking]] arrived in the region by around 1000 BC, likely from early Bantu cultures in what is today southeast [[Nigeria]] and/or [[Cameroon]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Nok: African Sculpture in Archaeological Context|last=Eggert|first=Manfred|publisher=Africa Magna Verlag Press|year=2014|isbn=|editor-last=Breunig|editor-first=P|location=Frankfurt, Germany|pages=55|chapter=Early iron in West and Central Africa|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=BBn1BQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA38&amp;dq=Nok+Breunig&amp;hl=en&amp;newbks=1&amp;newbks_redir=0&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwiGwYHuvbjlAhXlhOAKHR4LAgoQ6AEwAHoECAIQAg#v=onepage&amp;q=Nok%20Breunig&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; The site of Gbabiri (in the Central African Republic) has yielded evidence of iron metallurgy, from a reduction furnace and blacksmith workshop; with earliest dates of 896-773 BC and 907-796 BC respectively.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Nok: African Sculpture in Archaeological Context|last=Eggert|first=Manfred|publisher=Africa Magna Verlag Press|year=2014|isbn=|editor-last=Breunig|editor-first=P|location=Frankfurt, Germany|pages=53-54|chapter=Early iron in West and Central Africa|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=BBn1BQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA38&amp;dq=Nok+Breunig&amp;hl=en&amp;newbks=1&amp;newbks_redir=0&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwiGwYHuvbjlAhXlhOAKHR4LAgoQ6AEwAHoECAIQAg#v=onepage&amp;q=Nok%20Breunig&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some earlier iron metallurgy dates of 2,000 BC from the site of Oboui (also in the Central Africa Republic) have also been proposed,&lt;ref&gt;Zangato, E. (2007) ''Les Ateliers d’Oboui: Premières Communautés Métallurgistes dans le Nord-Ést du Centrafrique''. Paris: Editions Recherche sur les Civilisations (ERC).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Zangato, E. and Holl, A.F.C. (2010) ‘On the iron front: new evidence from Central Africa’, Journal of African Archaeology 8:7-23.&lt;/ref&gt; but these are disputed by some archaeologists.&lt;ref&gt;Clist, B. (2012) Vers une réduction des prejugés et la fonte des antagonisms: un bilan de l’expansion de la métallurgie du fer en Afrique sud-Saharienne,  ''Journal of African Archaeology'' 10:71-84.&lt;/ref&gt; 

During the [[Bantu expansion|Bantu Migrations]] from about 1000 BC to AD 1000, [[Ubangian]]-speaking people spread eastward from Cameroon to Sudan, [[Bantu languages|Bantu]]-speaking people settled in the southwestern regions of the CAR, and [[Central Sudanic]]-speaking people settled along the [[Ubangi River]] in what is today Central and East CAR.{{citation needed|date=June 2014}}

Production of [[copper]], [[salt]], [[dried fish]], and [[textiles]] dominated the economic trade in the Central African region.&lt;ref&gt;The History of Central and Eastern Africa, Amy McKenna, 2011, pg. 10&lt;/ref&gt;

The territory of modern [[Central African Republic]] is known to have been settled from at least the 7th century &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.worldtravelguide.net/central-african-republic/history-language-culture|title=Central African Republic History, Language and Culture|website=www.worldtravelguide.net|access-date=2016-10-11|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161012150606/http://www.worldtravelguide.net/central-african-republic/history-language-culture|archive-date=12 October 2016|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; on by overlapping empires, including the [[Kanem Empire|Kanem-Bornu]], [[Ouaddai Kingdom|Ouaddai]], [[Baguirmi Kingdom|Baguirmi]], and [[Dafour]] groups based on the [[Lake Chad]] region and along the [[Upper Nile, Sudan|Upper Nile]].

== Early modern history ==
During the 16th and 17th centuries [[arab slave trade|Muslim slave traders]] began to raid the region and their captives were shipped to the Mediterranean coast, Europe, Arabia, the Western Hemisphere, or to the slave ports and factories along the West African coast.&lt;ref name=&quot;africanhistory.about.com&quot;&gt;Central Africa Republic Timeline -- Part 1: From Prehistory to Independence (13 August 1960), A Chronology of Key Events in Central Africa Republic, By Alistair Boddy-Evans, About.com, http://africanhistory.about.com/od/car/l/bl-CAR-Timeline-1.htm&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Bangi language|Bobangi people]] became major slave traders{{when|date=June 2014}} and sold their captives to the Americas using the Ubangi river to reach the coast.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/102152/Central-African-Republic/214025/The-arts-and-cultural-institutions Central African Republic]&quot;. Encyclopædia Britannica.&lt;/ref&gt; During the 18th century Bandia-Nzakara peoples established the Bangassou Kingdom along the Ubangi river.&lt;ref name=&quot;africanhistory.about.com&quot;/&gt;

Population [[Migration (human)|migration]] in the 18th and 19th centuries brought new migrants into the area, including the [[Zande people|Zande]], [[Banda (CAR)|Banda]], and [[Gbaya people|Baya-Mandjia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.worldatlas.com/webimage/countrys/africa/centralafricanrepublic/cftimeln.htm|title=Central African Republic Time Line Chronological Timetable of Events - Worldatlas.com|website=www.worldatlas.com|access-date=2019-02-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Central African Republic Investment and Business Guide Volume 1 Strategic and Practical Information (World Business and Investment Library)|last=|first=|publisher=Ibp Usa|year=2016|isbn=1514529149|location=|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Colonial period ==
In 1875, the [[Sudan]]ese sultan [[Rabih az-Zubayr]] governed Upper-Oubangui, which included present-day CAR. Europeans, primarily the French, German, and [[Belgium|Belgians]], arrived in the area in 1885. The French consolidated their legal claim to the area through an 1887 convention with [[Congo Free State]], which granted France possession of the right bank of the [[Oubangui River]]. Two years later, the French established an outpost at [[Bangui]], and in 1894, [[Oubangui-Chari]] became a French territory. However, the French did not consolidate their control over the area until 1903, after having defeated the forces of Rabih in the [[battle of Kousséri]], and established colonial administration throughout the territory. In 1906, the Oubangui-Chari territory was united with the [[Chad]] colony; in 1910, it became one of the four territories of the [[Federation of French Equatorial Africa]] (AEF), along with Chad, [[Republic of the Congo|Middle Congo]], and [[Gabon]]. The next thirty years were marked by mostly small scale revolts against French rule and the development of a [[plantation]]-style economy. The largest of these revolts was the [[Kongo-Wara rebellion]], when over 350,000 natives rebelled against the colonial administration.

The European penetration of Central African territory began in the late 19th century during the [[Scramble for Africa]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.discoverfrance.net/Colonies/Centr_Afr_Rep.shtml French Colonies – Central African Republic]. Discoverfrance.net. Retrieved on 6 April 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; Count [[Savorgnan de Brazza]] established the [[French Congo]] and sent expeditions up the Ubangi River from [[Brazzaville]] in an effort to expand France's claims to territory in Central Africa. [[Belgium]], [[German Empire|Germany]], and the [[United Kingdom]] also competed to establish their claims to territory in the region.

In 1889, the French established a post on the Ubangi River at Bangui. In 1890–91, de Brazza sent expeditions up the [[Sangha River]], in what is now south-western CAR, up the center of the Ubangi basin toward [[Lake Chad]], and eastward along the Ubangi River toward the [[Nile]], with the intention of expanding the borders of the French Congo to link up the other French territories in Africa. In 1894, the French Congo's borders with [[Leopold II of Belgium]]'s [[Congo Free State]] and [[German Cameroon]] were fixed by diplomatic agreements. In 1899, the French Congo's border with Sudan was fixed along the [[Congo-Nile divide]]. This situation left France without her much coveted outlet on the Nile.

Once European negotiators had agreed upon the borders of the French Congo, France had to decide how to pay for the costly occupation, administration, and development of the territory it had acquired. The reported financial successes of Leopold II's concessionary companies in the Congo Free State convinced the French government to grant 17 private companies large concessions in the Ubangi-Shari region in 1899. In return for the right to exploit these lands by buying local products and selling European goods, the companies promised to pay rent to France and to promote the development of their concessions. The companies employed European and African agents who frequently used brutal methods to force the natives to labor.

At the same time, the French colonial administration began to force the local population to pay [[tax]]es and to provide the state with free labor. The companies and the French administration at times collaborated in forcing the Central Africans to work for them. Some French officials{{who|date=January 2014}} reported abuses committed by private company militias, and their own colonial colleagues and troops, but efforts to hold these people accountable almost invariably failed. When any news of atrocities committed against Central Africans reached France and caused an outcry, investigations were undertaken and some feeble attempts at reform were made{{by whom|date=January 2014}}, but the [[facts on the ground|situation on the ground]] in Ubangi-Shari remained virtually unchanged.{{Citation needed|date=January 2014}}

During the first decade of French colonial rule, from about 1900 to 1910, the rulers of the Ubangi-Shari region increased both their slave-raiding activities and the selling of local produce to Europe. They took advantage of their treaties with the French to procure more [[Firearm|weapons]], which were used to capture more slaves: much of the eastern half of Ubangi-Shari was depopulated as a result of slave-trading by local rulers during the first decade of colonial rule. After the power of local African rulers was destroyed by the French, slave raiding greatly diminished.{{citation needed|date=April 2013}}

In 1911, the Sangha and Lobaye basins were ceded to Germany as part of an agreement which gave France a free hand in [[Morocco]]. Western Ubangi-Shari remained under German rule until World War I, after which France again annexed the territory using Central African troops.

[[File:De Gaulle Bangui 1940.jpg|thumb|250px|[[Charles de Gaulle]] in Bangui, 1940]]
From 1920 to 1930, a network of roads was built, [[cash crop]]s were promoted and mobile health services were formed to combat [[African trypanosomiasis|sleeping sickness]]. [[Protestant]] [[Mission (Christianity)|missions]] were established in different parts of the country. New forms of forced labor were also introduced, however, as the French conscripted large numbers of Ubangians to work on the [[Congo-Ocean Railway]]; many of these recruits died of exhaustion and illness as a result of the poor conditions.

In 1925, the French writer [[André Gide]] published ''[[Voyage au Congo]]'', in which he described the alarming consequences of conscription for the Congo-Ocean railroad. He exposed the continuing atrocities committed against Central Africans in Western Ubangi-Shari by such employers as the Forestry Company of Sangha-Ubangi. In 1928, a major insurrection, the [[Kongo-Wara rebellion]] or 'war of the hoe handle', broke out in Western Ubangi-Shari and continued for several years. The extent of this insurrection, which was perhaps the largest anti-colonial rebellion in Africa during the interwar years, was carefully hidden from the French public because it provided evidence of strong opposition to French colonial rule and forced labor.

During the 1930s, [[cotton]], [[tea]], and [[coffee]] emerged as important cash crops in Ubangi-Shari and the mining of [[diamond]]s and [[gold]] began in earnest. Several cotton companies were granted purchasing [[Monopoly|monopolies]] over large areas of cotton production and were able to fix the prices paid to cultivators, which assured profits for their shareholders. In September 1940, during the [[Second World War]], [[Charles de Gaulle|pro-Gaullist]] French officers took control of Ubangi-Shari.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/102152/Central-African-Republic/40700/The-colonial-era Central African Republic: The colonial era – Britannica Online Encyclopedia]. Britannica.com. Retrieved on 6 April 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 1940, the territory responded, with the rest of the AEF, to the call from General [[Charles de Gaulle]] to fight for [[Free France]]. After World War II, the [[French Constitution]] of 1946 inaugurated the first of a series of reforms that led eventually to complete independence for all French territories in western and equatorial Africa. In 1946, all AEF inhabitants were granted French citizenship and allowed to establish local assemblies. The assembly in CAR was led by [[Barthélemy Boganda]], a Catholic priest who also was known for his forthright statements in the French Assembly on the need for African emancipation. In 1956 French legislation eliminated certain voting inequalities and provided for the creation of some organs of self-government in each territory.

The French constitutional referendum of September 1958 dissolved the AEF, and on 1 December of the same year the Assembly declared the birth of the autonomous Central African Republic with Boganda as head of government. Boganda ruled until his death in a plane crash on 29 March 1959. His cousin, [[David Dacko]], replaced him as head of Government. On 12 July 1960 France agreed to the Central African Republic becoming fully independent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://select.nytimes.com/mem/archive/pdf?res=F00D1FFA3D581A7A93C1A8178CD85F448685F9 | work=The New York Times | first=W. Granger | last=Blair | title=3 More Nations Gain Freedom Through Pacts Signed by France; Congo, Central African and Chad Republics Are Given Sovereignty in Paris | date=13 July 1960}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 13 August 1960 the Central African Republic became an independent country and [[David Dacko]] became its first President.

== Independence ==
{{unreferenced section|date=June 2014}}

=== Central African Empire ===
{{main|Central African Empire}}
On 1 January 1966, following a swift and almost [[Saint-Sylvestre coup d'état|bloodless overnight coup]], Colonel [[Jean-Bédel Bokassa]] assumed power as president of the Republic. Bokassa abolished the [[Constitution of the Central African Republic|constitution of 1959]], dissolved the [[National Assembly of the Central African Republic|National Assembly]], and issued a decree that [[Fusion of powers|placed all legislative and executive powers in the hands of the president]]. On the 4 March 1972, Bokassa's presidency was extended [[President for life|to a life term]]. On 4 December 1976, the republic became a monarchy –&amp;nbsp;the [[Central African Empire]]&amp;nbsp;– with the promulgation of the imperial constitution and the [[Coronation of Bokassa I|coronation]] of the president as [[Emperor Bokassa I]]. His [[authoritarian regime]] was characterized by numerous [[human rights violations]].

=== Dacko ===
[[File:David Dacko 1962 crop.jpg|thumb|130px|First [[President of the Central African Republic|Central African President]] David Dacko in 1962]]
On 20 September 1979, Dacko, with French support, led a bloodless coup that [[1979 Central African Republic coup d'état|overthrew Bokassa]] while he was out of the country. The republic was restored, and Bokassa, who took refuge in [[Ivory Coast]] and France, was sentenced to death in absentia for various crimes, including [[cannibalism]]. Moreover, an African judicial commission reported that he had &quot;almost certainly&quot; taken part in the massacre of some 100 children for refusing to wear the compulsory school uniforms. In January 1981, six of his supporters, including two sons-in-law, were executed. Bokassa returned unexpectedly in October 1986 and on 12 June 1987, he was convicted of having ordered the murders of at least 20 prisoners and the arrest of the schoolchildren who were murdered. He was sentenced to death, but this was commuted to a life term in February 1988. He was released from prison on 1 September 1993, as a result of an amnesty and died of a heart attack in [[Bangui]] on 3 November 1996 at age 75.

=== Kolingba ===
Dacko's efforts to promote economic and political reforms proved ineffectual, and on 20 September 1981, he in turn was overthrown in a bloodless coup by General [[André Kolingba]]. For four years, Kolingba led the country as head of the Military Committee for National Recovery (CRMN).

Kolingba suspended the constitution and ruled with a military junta until 1985. In 1985, the CRMN was dissolved, and Kolingba named a new cabinet with increased civilian participation, signaling the start of a return to civilian rule. The process of democratization quickened in 1986 with the creation of a new political party, the Rassemblement Démocratique Centrafricain (RDC), and the drafting of a new constitution that subsequently was ratified in a national referendum. General Kolingba was sworn in as constitutional President on 29 November 1986. The constitution established a National Assembly made up of 52 elected deputies, elected in July 1987 and municipal elections were held in 1988. Kolingba's two major political opponents, Abel Goumba and [[Ange-Félix Patassé]], boycotted these elections because their parties were not allowed to participate.{{citation needed|date=June 2014}}

By 1990, inspired by the fall of the Berlin Wall, a pro-democracy movement became very active. In May 1990, a letter signed by 253 prominent citizens asked for the convocation of a National Conference, but Kolingba refused this request and instead detained several opponents. Pressure from the United States, France, and from a group of locally represented countries and agencies called GIBAFOR (France, the USA, Germany, Japan, the EU, the World Bank, and the UN) finally led Kolingba to agree, in principle, to hold free elections in October 1992 with help from the UN Office of Electoral Affairs.

After using the excuse of alleged irregularities to suspend the results of the elections as a pretext for holding on to power, President Kolingba came under intense pressure from GIBAFOR to establish a &quot;Conseil National Politique Provisoire de la République&quot; (Provisional National Political Council, CNPPR) and to set up a &quot;Mixed Electoral Commission&quot;, which included representatives from all political parties.

=== Patassé ===
When elections were finally held in 1993, again with the help of the international community, [[Ange-Félix Patassé]] led in the first round and Kolingba came in fourth behind Abel Goumba and David Dacko. In the second round, Patassé won 53% of the vote while Goumba won 45.6%. Most of Patassé's support came from Gbaya, Kare, and Kaba voters in seven heavily populated prefectures in the northwest while Goumba's support came largely from ten less-populated prefectures in the south and east. Furthermore, Patassé's party, the ''Mouvement pour la Libération du Peuple Centrafricain'' (MLPC) or Movement for the Liberation of the Central African People, gained a simple but not an absolute majority of seats in parliament, which meant Patassé's party required coalition partners.

Patassé relieved former President Kolingba of his military rank of general in March 1994 and then charged several former ministers with various crimes. Patassé also removed many [[Yakoma people|Yakoma]] from important, lucrative posts in the government. Two hundred predominantly Yakoma members of the presidential guard were also dismissed or reassigned to the army. Kolingba's RDC loudly proclaimed that Patassé's government was conducting a &quot;witch hunt&quot; against the Yakoma.

A new constitution was approved on 28 December 1994 and promulgated on 14 January 1995, but this constitution, like those before it, did not have much impact on the country's politics. In 1996–1997, reflecting steadily decreasing public confidence in the government's erratic behaviour, three mutinies against Patassé's administration were accompanied by widespread destruction of property and heightened ethnic tension. On 25 January 1997, the [[Bangui Agreements]], which provided for the deployment of an inter-African military mission, the ''Mission Interafricaine de Surveillance des Accords de Bangui'' (MISAB), were signed. Mali's former president, [[Amadou Toumani Touré|Amadou Touré]], served as chief mediator and brokered the entry of ex-mutineers into the government on 7 April 1997. The MISAB mission was later replaced by a U.N. peacekeeping force, the ''Mission des Nations Unies en RCA'' ([[United Nations Security Council Resolution 1159|MINURCA]]).

In 1998, parliamentary elections resulted in Kolingba's RDC winning 20 out of 109 seats, constituting a comeback. However, in 1999, in spite of widespread public anger in urban centers over his corrupt rule, Patassé won free elections to become president for a second term.

== Current period ==
On 28 May 2001, rebels stormed strategic buildings in Bangui in an unsuccessful coup attempt. The army chief of staff, Abel Abrou, and General François N'Djadder Bedaya were killed, but Patassé regained the upper hand by bringing in at least 300 troops of the rebel leader [[Jean-Pierre Bemba]] (from across the river in the [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]]) and by Libyan soldiers.{{citation needed|date=May 2014}}

=== 2003–2007: Bush War ===
{{main|Central African Republic Bush War}}
In the aftermath of the failed [[Coup d'état|coup]], militias loyal to Patassé sought revenge against rebels in many neighborhoods of the capital, Bangui, and incited unrest which resulted in the destruction of many homes as well as the torture and murder of many opponents. Eventually, Patassé came to suspect that General [[François Bozizé]] was involved in another coup attempt against him, which led Bozizé  to flee with loyal troops to Chad. In March 2003, Bozizé launched a surprise attack against Patassé, who was out of the country. Libyan troops and some 1,000 soldiers of Bemba's Congolese rebel organization failed to stop the rebels, who took control of the country and thus succeeded in overthrowing Patassé. {{citation needed|date=May 2014}}

[[File:Rebel in northern Central African Republic 04.jpg|left|thumb|Rebel in northern Central African Republic]]
On 15 March 2003, while Patassé was abroad, rebels moved into Bangui and installed their commander, General [[François Bozizé]], as president. Bozizé has since been elected President in an election considered by observers to be fair and free.

Patassé has been found guilty of major crimes in Bangui and CAR has brought a case to the International Criminal Court against him and Jean Pierre Bemba from the neighbouring Democratic Republic of Congo accusing them both of multiple crimes in suppressing one of the mutinies against Patasse. Civil tranquillity has yet to be established and parts of the country remain out of government control. The UN continues to maintain a peace building mission in Bangui.

Despite these shortcomings, and his promise to step down at the end of the transition, Bozizé contested the 13 March 2005 presidential elections in which all of the leading opposition candidates were allowed to run except for Patassé. Bozizé won on the second run-off round on 8 May 2005, defeating [[Martin Ziguélé]], who ran on the ticket of the MLPC, the former ruling party. The National Elections Commission declared Bozizé the winner with 64.6 percent of the vote to 35.4 percent for Ziguélé. The election was generally considered to be fair, although the absence of Patassé cast a shadow over the legitimacy of the process.

After Bozizé seized power in 2003, the [[Central African Republic Bush War]] began with the rebellion by the [[Union of Democratic Forces for Unity]] (UFDR), led by [[Michel Djotodia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |first=Stephanie |last=Hancock |url=http://reliefweb.int/report/central-african-republic/feature-bush-war-leaves-central-african-villages-deserted |title=Feature&amp;nbsp;- Bush war leaves Central African villages deserted |publisher=[[ReliefWeb]] |agency=[[Reuters]] |date=30 August 2007 |accessdate=2012-12-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; This quickly escalated into major fighting during 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/4035239.stm |title=Raid on CAR town 'leaves 20 dead' |work=[[BBC News]] |date=23 December 2004 |accessdate=2012-12-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; The UFDR rebel forces consisted of three allies, the ''Groupe d'action patriotique pour la liberation de Centrafrique'' (GAPLC), the [[Convention of Patriots for Justice and Peace]] (CPJP), the [[People's Army for the Restoration of Democracy (CAR)|People's Army for the Restoration of Democracy]] (APRD), the [[Movement of Central African Liberators for Justice]] (MLCJ), and the ''Front démocratique Centrafricain'' (FDC).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://allafrica.com/stories/200611020004.html |title=Central African Republic: Rebels Call for Dialogue After Capturing Key Town |publisher=[[AllAfrica.com]] |agency=[[IRIN]] |date=2 November 2006 |accessdate=2012-12-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 8 May 2005, Bozizé gained yet a further victory when his coalition, Convergence [[Kwa Na Kwa]], won 42 parliamentary seats in the legislative run-off vote. The MLPC came in second with 11 seats while the RDC won only eight seats. The remaining seats were won by independents or by smaller parties. In June later that year, the [[African Union]] (AU) lifted sanctions against the country, which had been applied after the 2003 coup.

In early 2006, Bozizé's government appeared stable. However, Patassé, who was living in exile in [[Togo]], could not be ruled out as a leader of a future uprising. His supporters reportedly were joining or were prepared to join rebel movements in belief that their leader was still the rightful head of state of the country. Further, members of Kolingba's [[Yakoma people|Yakoma]] tribe in the south posed a potential threat to Bozizé's government because of their widespread boycott of the second round of the legislative elections. Members of the Yakoma dominate the army.

On 13 April 2007, a peace agreement between the government and the UFDR was signed in Birao. The agreement provided for an amnesty for the UFDR, its recognition as a political party, and the integration of its fighters into the army.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://allafrica.com/stories/200611130081.html |title=Central African Republic: Concern As Civilians Flee, Government Denies Rebel Capture of Third Town |publisher=[[AllAfrica.com]] |agency=[[IRIN]] |date=13 November 2006 |accessdate=2012-12-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.usatoday.com/news/world/2007-04-13-central-africa_N.htm |title=Central African Republic, rebels sign peace deal |work=[[USA Today]] |agency=[[Associated Press]] |date=13 April 2007 |accessdate=2012-12-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Further negotiations resulted in an agreement in 2008 for reconciliation, a unity government, and local elections in 2009 and parliamentary and presidential elections in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.taipeitimes.com/News/world/archives/2009/01/20/2003434210 |title=CAR president dissolves government, vows unity |work=[[Taipei Times]] |agency=[[Agence France-Presse]] |date=20 January 2009 |accessdate=2012-12-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; The new unity government that resulted was formed in January 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5iDaBqt-PZaqJ6IPUfGowi9_x95Ag |title=Touadera names rebels in new Central African Republic govt |publisher=[[Google News]] |agency=[[Agence France-Presse]] |date=19 January 2009 |accessdate=2012-12-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== 2012–2014: Civil War ===
{{main|Central African Republic Civil War (2012–2014)}}
[[File:Central African Republic 2012 Battles-en.svg|thumb|300px|Conflict in the Central African Republic (2012–2014)]]
In late 2012, a coalition of old rebel groups under new name of [[Séléka CPSK-CPJP-UFDR|Séléka]] [[Central African Republic conflict (2012–present)|renewed fighting]]. Two other, previously unknown groups, the Alliance for Revival and Rebuilding (A2R) and the Patriotic Convention for Saving the Country (CPSK) also joined the coalition, as well as the Chadian group [[Popular Front for Recovery|FPR]],.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|title=Le FPR soutient l'UFDR dans son combat contre le Dictateur Bozizé|url=http://ambenatna.over-blog.com/article-le-fpr-soutient-l-ufdr-dans-combat-contre-le-dictateur-bozize-113660691.html|publisher=FPR |date=18 December 2012|accessdate=2 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 27 December 2012, CAR President Francois Bozizé requested international assistance to help with the rebellion, in particular from France and the United States. [[President of France|French President]] [[François Hollande]] rejected the plea, saying that the 250 French troops stationed at [[Bangui M'Poko International Airport]] are there &quot;in no way to intervene in the internal affairs&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dailystar.com.lb/News/International/2012/Dec-28/200123-car-leader-appeals-for-help-to-halt-rebel-advance.ashx#axzz2GInl7HTD CAR leader appeals for help to halt rebel advance (The Daily Star Lebanon)]&lt;/ref&gt;

On 11 January 2013, a ceasefire agreement was signed [[Libreville]], [[Gabon]]. The rebels dropped their demand for President François Bozizé to resign, but he had to appoint a new [[Prime Minister of the Central African Republic|prime minister]] from the opposition party by 18 January 2013.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2013/01/12/world/africa/rebels-agree-to-cease-fire-in-central-african-republic.html?_r=0|title=Rebel Coalition in Central African Republic Agrees to a Short Cease-Fire|last=Sayare|first=Scott|date=11 January 2013|work=The New York Times|accessdate=12 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 13 January, Bozizé signed a decree that removed [[List of heads of government of the Central African Republic and Central African Empire|Prime Minister]] [[Faustin-Archange Touadéra]] from power, as part of the agreement with the rebel coalition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/africa/prime-minister-booted-from-job-in-central-african-republic-part-of-peace-deal-with-rebels/2013/01/13/bcebaf14-5dcf-11e2-8acb-ab5cb77e95c8_print.html|title=Prime minister booted from job in Central African Republic, part of peace deal with rebels|date=13 January 2013|work=The Washington Post|accessdate=15 January 2013}} {{Dead link|date=April 2014|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 17 January, [[Nicolas Tiangaye]] was appointed  Prime Minister.&lt;ref name=Fort&gt;Patrick Fort, [https://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5i29CmpNUhK93R12SF_Oyz_6o5uug?docId=CNG.376beea6edfc8b0d9c41b73f138d6700.4f1 &quot;Tiangaye named Central African PM, says 'hard work' begins&quot;], Agence France-Presse, 17 January 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{see also|Central African Republic conflict under the Djotodia administration}}
On 24 March 2013, rebel forces heavily attacked the capital [[Bangui]] and took control of major structures, including the presidential palace. Bozizé's family fled across the river to the [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]]&lt;ref name=reuters24march&gt;{{cite news|title=Central African Republic capital falls to rebels, Bozizé flees|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/2013/03/24/us-centralafrica-rebels-idUSBRE92M0AU20130324|accessdate=24 March 2013|agency=Reuters|date=24 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and then to [[Yaounde]], the capital of [[Cameroon]] where he has been granted temporary refuge.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.aljazeera.com/news/africa/2013/03/201332565033211834.html |title=CAR president seeks refuge in Cameroon - Africa |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date=25 March 2013 |accessdate=2013-03-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Séléka leader [[Michel Djotodia]] declared himself President. Djotodia said that there would be a three-year transitional period and that Tiangaye would continue to serve as Prime Minister.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.trust.org/alertnet/news/cafrican-republic-rebel-chief-to-name-power-sharing-government/ &quot;C.African Republic rebel chief to name power-sharing government&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://archive.today/20130416050815/http://www.trust.org/alertnet/news/cafrican-republic-rebel-chief-to-name-power-sharing-government/ |date=16 April 2013 }}, Reuters, 25 March 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; Djotodia promptly suspended the constitution and dissolved the government, as well as the National Assembly.&lt;ref name=&quot;DjotodiaSuspends&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-21934433 |title=CAR rebel head Michel Djotodia 'suspends constitution' |work=BBC News |date=25 March 2013 |accessdate=26 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; He then reappointed Tiangaye as Prime Minister on 27 March 2013.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lepoint.fr/monde/centrafrique-nicolas-tiangaye-reconduit-premier-ministre-27-03-2013-1646583_24.php &quot;Centrafrique: Nicolas Tiangaye reconduit Premier ministre&quot;], AFP, 27 March 2013 {{in lang|fr}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Top military and police officers met with Djotodia and recognized him as President on 28 March 2013.&lt;ref&gt;Ange Aboa, [http://www.trust.org/alertnet/news/cafrican-republic-army-chiefs-pledge-allegiance-to-coup-leader/ &quot;C.African Republic army chiefs pledge allegiance to coup leader&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130401023549/http://www.trust.org/alertnet/news/cafrican-republic-army-chiefs-pledge-allegiance-to-coup-leader/ |date=1 April 2013 }}, Reuters, 28 March 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Catherine Samba-Panza]] assumed the office of [[interim president]] on 23 January 2014.

=== 2015–present: Civil War === &lt;!-- Copied from &quot;Central African Republic Civil War (2015–present)&quot; --&gt;
{{main|Central African Republic Civil War (2015–present)}}
By 2015, there was little government control outside of the capital, Bangui.&lt;ref name=fp1015&gt;{{cite magazine|url=https://foreignpolicy.com/2015/10/28/one-day-we-will-start-a-big-war-central-african-republic-un-violence/|title=One day we will start a big war|magazine=Foreign Policy|accessdate=13 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The dissolution of Seleka led to ex-Seleka fighters forming new militia that often fight each other.&lt;ref name=fp1015/&gt; The rebel leader Noureddine Adam declared the autonomous [[Republic of Logone]] on 14 December 2015.&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-centralafrica-politics-idUSKBN0TY1F620151215|title=Central African rebel leader declares autonomous republic|publisher=|accessdate=16 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Peacekeeping largely transitioned from the [[ECCAS]] led [[MICOPAX]] to the [[African Union|AU]] led [[MISCA]] to the [[UN]] led [[MINUSCA]] while the French peacekeeping mission was known as [[Operation Sangaris]].

Armed entrepreneurs had carved out personal fiefdoms in which they set up checkpoints, collect illegal taxes, and take in millions of dollars from the illicit coffee, mineral, and timber trades.&lt;ref name=fp1015/&gt; By 2017, more than 14 armed groups vied for territory, notably four factions formed by ex-Séléka leaders who control about 60% of the country's territory.&lt;ref name=ep0217&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.enoughproject.org/reports/dangerous-divisions-central-african-republic-faces-threat-secession|title=Dangerous Divisions: The Central African Republic faces the threat of secession|publisher=Enough Project|date=15 February 2017|accessdate=1 March 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; With the de facto partition of the country between ex-Séléka militias in the north and east and Antibalaka militias in the south and west, hostilities between both sides decreased&lt;ref name=irin0217&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.irinnews.org/analysis/2017/02/24/central-african-republic-what’s-gone-wrong|title=Central African Republic: What's gone wrong?|publisher=IRIN|date=24 February 2017|accessdate=26 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; but sporadic fighting continued.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/inpictures/car-violence-rises-shot-children-husband-180211091014962.html|title=CAR violence rises: 'They shot my children and husband'|publisher=Al Jazeera|date=12 February 2018|accessdate=15 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msf.org/en/article/car-four-things-know-about-conflict-central-african-republic|title=CAR: Four things to know about the conflict in the Central African Republic|publisher=MSF|date=10 April 2018|accessdate=15 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; In February 2016, after a peaceful [[2015–16 Central African general election|election]], the former Prime Minister [[Faustin-Archange Touadéra]] was elected president. In October 2016, France announced that it was ending its peacekeeping mission in the country, [[Operation Sangaris]] and largely withdrew its troops, saying that the operation was a success.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://foreignpolicy.com/2016/11/01/french-peacekeepers-pull-out-as-new-violence-erupts-in-the-central-african-republic/|title=French Peacekeepers Pull Out as New Violence Erupts in the Central African Republic|publisher=foreign policy magazine|accessdate=3 November 2016|date=1 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Faustin Touadera.jpg|thumb|left|150px|[[Faustin Touadera]] succeeded interim head [[Catherine Samba-Panza]] to become President following the [[2015–16 Central African general election|2015–16 elections]]]]
Tensions erupted in competition between Ex-Seleka militias arising over control of a goldmine in November 2016, where MPC&lt;ref name=lacroix/&gt; and the FPRC coalition which incorporated elements of their former enemy, the Anti-balaka,&lt;ref name=irin0517&gt;{{cite news|last=Kleinfeld|first=Philip|title=Rebel schism drives alarming upsurge of violence in Central African Republic|url=http://www.irinnews.org/feature/2017/05/18/rebel-schism-drives-alarming-upsurge-violence-central-african-republic|newspaper=Irin news|date=18 May 2017|accessdate= 18 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; attacked UPC.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.hrw.org/news/2017/02/16/central-african-republic-executions-rebel-group|title=Central African Republic: Executions by rebel group|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=17 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=newsweek0217/&gt; The violence is often ethnic in nature with the FPRC associated with the  [[Kara people|Gula]] and [[Aiki language|Runga]] people and the UPC associated with the [[Fulani]].&lt;ref name=irin0217/&gt; Most of the fighting was in the centrally located [[Ouaka]] prefecture, which has the country's second largest city [[Bambari]], because of its strategic location between the Muslim and Christian regions of the country and its wealth.&lt;ref name=lacroix&gt;{{cite web|url=https://international.la-croix.com/news/the-battle-of-ouaka-in-central-african-republic/4756|title=The battle of Ouaka in Central African Republic|publisher=LaCroix International|date=27 February 2017|accessdate=27 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The fight for Bambari in early 2017 displaced 20,000.&lt;ref name=reuters0217&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-centralafrica-violence-idUSKBN15R0WC|title=U.N. air strikes in Central African Republic kill several: militia|work=Reuters|accessdate=14 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=newsweek0217/&gt; MINUSCA made a robust deployment to prevent FPRC taking the city and in February 2017, [[Joseph Zoundeiko]], the chief of staff&lt;ref name=bbc0714&gt;{{cite news |last= |first= |date=29 July 2014 |title=CAR crisis: Meeting the rebel army chief |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-28526362 |newspaper=BBC News |location= |publisher= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt; of FPRC who previously led the military wing of Seleka, was killed by MINUSCA after crossing one of the red lines.&lt;ref name=newsweek0217&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newsweek.com/central-african-republic-war-fprc-car-556068|title=U.N. ‘KILLS REBEL COMMANDER’ IN CENTRAL AFRICAN REPUBLIC AIRSTRIKES|publisher=|accessdate=14 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, MINUSCA negotiated the removal of Darassa from the city. This led to UPC to find new territory, spreading the fighting from urban to rural areas previously spared. Additionally, the thinly spread MINUSCA relied on Ugandan as well as American special forces to keep the peace in the southeast as they were part of a campaign to eliminate the [[Lord's Resistance Army]] but the mission ended in April 2017.&lt;ref name=irin0517/&gt; By the latter half of 2017, the fighting largely shifted to the Southeast where the UPC reorganized and were pursued by the FPRC and antibalaka with the level of violence only matched by the early stage of the war.&lt;ref name=irin1117&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.irinnews.org/feature/2017/10/30/people-are-dying-every-day-car-refugees-fleeing-war-suffer-congo|title=CAR refugees fleeing war suffer in Congo|publisher=Irin News|date= 30 October 2017|accessdate=26 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.aljazeera.com/news/2017/05/red-cross-115-bodies-car-bangassou-170517114611855.html|title=Red Cross: 115 bodies found in CAR's Bangassou|publisher=Aljazeera|date= 17 May 2017|accessdate=18 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; About 15,000 people fled from their homes in an attack in May and six U.N. peacekeepers were killed - the deadliest month for the mission yet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://abcnews.go.com/International/wireStory/red-cross-finds-115-dead-central-african-republic-47460509|title=Red Cross finds 115 dead in Central African Republic town|publisher=ABC|date=17 May 2017|accessdate=18 May 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170517155002/http://abcnews.go.com/International/wireStory/red-cross-finds-115-dead-central-african-republic-47460509|archive-date=17 May 2017|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2017, another ceasefire was signed in Rome by the government and 14 armed groups including FPRC but the next day fighting between an FPRC faction and antibalaka militias killed more than 100 people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2017-06-24/bodies-strewn-across-town-after-central-african-republic-clashes|title=Bodies Strewn Across Town After Central African Republic Clashes|publisher=Bloomberg|date=24 June 2017|accessdate=8 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; In October 2017, another ceasefire was signed between the UPC, the FPRC, and anti-balaka groups and FPRC announced Ali Darassa as coalition vice-president but fighting continued afterward.&lt;ref name=irin1117/&gt; By July 2018, FPRC, now headed by Abdoulaye Hissène and based in the northeastern town of Ndélé, had troops threatening to move onto Bangui.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.france24.com/en/20180713-reporters-plus-central-african-republic-way-warlords|title=Central African Republic: The way of the warlord|publisher=France 24|date=13 July 2018|accessdate=30 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Western CAR, another rebel group, with no known links to Seleka or Antibalaka, called &quot;Return, Reclamation, Rehabilitation&quot; (3R) formed in 2015 reportedly by self-proclaimed&lt;ref name=hrw1216&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.hrw.org/news/2016/12/20/central-african-republic-mayhem-new-group|title=Central African Republic: Mayhem by New Group|publisher=Human Rights Watch|date=20 December 2016|accessdate=28 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; general Sidiki Abass, claiming to be protecting Muslim [[Fulani people]] from an Antibalaka militia led by Abbas Rafal.&lt;ref name=hrw1216/&gt;&lt;ref name=aljazeera1216&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.aljazeera.com/news/2016/12/newly-formed-3r-rebel-group-inflicts-horrors-car-161223035217671.html|title=Newly formed 3R rebel group inflicts horrors in CAR: UN|publisher=Al jazeera|date=23 December 2016|accessdate=28 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; They are accused of displacing 17,000 people in November 2016 and at least 30,000 people in the [[Ouham-Pendé]] prefecture in December 2016.&lt;ref name=aljazeera1216/&gt; In Northwestern CAR around [[Paoua]], fighting since December 2017 between Revolution and Justice (RJ) and Movement for the Liberation of the Central African Republic People (MNLC) displaced around 60,000 people. MNLC, founded in October 2017,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.demorgen.be/buitenland/honderden-mensen-op-de-vlucht-voor-geweld-in-centraal-afrikaanse-republiek-bfce6eec/|title=Honderden mensen op de vlucht voor geweld in Centraal-Afrikaanse Republiek|publisher=DeMorgan|date=31 December 2017|accessdate=18 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; was led by Ahamat Bahar, a former member and co-founder of FPRC and MRC, and is allegedly backed by Fulani fighters from Chad. The Christian&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.voanews.com/a/central-african-republic-new-national-army/3651217.html|title=CAR Gets First Building Block in New National Army|publisher=Voice of America|date=26 December 2016|accessdate=18 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; militant group RJ was formed in 2013, mostly by members of the presidential guard of former President Ange Felix Patassé, and were composed mainly of ethnic [[Kaba languages|Sara-Kaba]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.irinnews.org/report/100623/armed-groups-car|title=Armed groups in CAR|publisher=Irinnews|date=17 September 2014|accessdate=18 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; While both groups had previously divided the territory in the Northwest, tensions erupted after the killing of RJ leader, Clément Bélanga,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.lemonde.fr/afrique/article/2018/01/09/centrafrique-au-moins-25-000-nouveaux-deplaces-dans-le-nord-ouest_5239303_3212.html|title=Centrafrique : au moins 25 000 nouveaux déplacés dans le nord-ouest
|newspaper=Le Monde|date=9 January 2018|accessdate=18 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; in November 2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.timeslive.co.za/news/africa/2018-01-17-in-central-african-republic-militia-violence-leaves-villages-devastated/|title=In Central African Republic, militia violence leaves villages devastated|publisher=AFP|date=17 January 2018|accessdate=18 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{portal|Central African Republic}}
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [[Brazzaville Conference]]
* [[French Equatorial Africa]]
* [[Central Africa#History|History of Central Africa]]
* [[Ubangi-Shari]]
{{div end}}

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}
* Maria Petringa, ''Brazza, A Life for Africa'' (2006) {{ISBN|978-1-425-91198-0}}

== External links ==
* [https://2009-2017.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/4007.htm Background Note: Central African Republic]

{{Central African Republic topics}}
{{History of Africa}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History of the Central African Republic}}
[[Category:History of the Central African Republic| ]]
[[Category:History of Central Africa|*]]
[[Category:History of Africa by country|Central African Republic]]</text>
      <sha1>2zy9d2xfh6vign2600eggflhzfwuof5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
