  <page>
    <title>Anthem</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2439</id>
    <revision>
      <id>936902488</id>
      <parentid>936901560</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-21T18:55:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jerome Kohl</username>
        <id>1920374</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/41.113.206.44|41.113.206.44]] ([[User talk:41.113.206.44|talk]]) to last revision by Illegitimate Barrister ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{other uses}}
An '''anthem''' is a [[musical composition]] of [[wikt:celebration|celebration]], usually used as a symbol for a distinct group, particularly the [[national anthem]]s of [[country|countries]]. Originally, and in [[music theory]] and religious contexts, it also refers more particularly to short sacred [[choral music|choral work]] (still frequently seen in [[Sacred Harp]] and other types of [[shape note]] singing) and still more particularly to a specific form of [[Anglican church music]].

{{anchor|Word|Name}}

==Etymology==
''Anthem'' is derived from the [[Ancient Greek language|Greek]] {{lang|grc|ἀντίφωνα}} (''antíphōna'') via [[Old English]] {{lang|ang|antefn}}. Both words originally referred to [[antiphon]]s, a [[call and response (music)|call-and-response]] style of singing.{{sfnp|''EB''|1878}} The adjectival form is &quot;anthemic&quot;.

==History==
Anthems were originally a form of [[liturgical music]]. In the [[Church of England]], the [[rubric]] appoints them to follow the third [[collect]] at morning and evening prayer. Several anthems are included in the [[Coronation of the British monarch|British coronation service]].{{sfnp|''EB''|1878}} The words are selected from [[Holy Scripture]] or in some cases from the [[Liturgy]] and the music is generally more elaborate and varied than that of [[psalm]] or [[hymn tune]]s.{{sfnp|''EB''|1878}} Being written for a trained [[choir]] rather than the congregation, the Anglican anthem is analogous to the [[motet]] of the [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] and [[Lutheran Church]]es but represents an essentially English [[musical form]].{{sfnp|''EB''|1911}} Anthems may be described as &quot;[[verse anthem|verse]]&quot;, &quot;full&quot;, or &quot;full with verse&quot;, depending on whether they are intended for [[solo (music)|solo]]ists, the [[choir|full choir]], or both. Another way of describing an anthem is that it is a piece of music written specifically to fit a certain accompanying text, and it is often difficult to make any other text fit that same melodic arrangement. It also often changes melody and/or meter, frequently multiple times within a single song, and is sung straight through from start to finish, without repeating the melody for following verses like a normal song (although certain sections may be repeated when marked). An example of an anthem with multiple meter shifts a, fuguing, and repeated sections is &quot;Claremont&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WhQIKXmsohA|title=Claremont|first=|last=Western Massachusetts Sacred Harp Convention - Topic|date=11 October 2015|publisher=|via=YouTube}}&lt;/ref&gt; or &quot;Vital Spark of Heav'nly Flame&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;/&gt; Another well known example is [[William Billings|William Billing]]'s &quot;Easter Anthem&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nccHbHJaGLg|title=236 Easter Anthem Sacred Harp|first=|last=jsalzer262|date=10 May 2015|publisher=|via=YouTube}}&lt;/ref&gt; also known as &quot;The Lord Is Risen Indeed!&quot; after the opening lines. This anthem is still one of the more popular songs in the Sacred harp tune book.{{sfnp|''EB''|1878}}

The anthem developed as a replacement for the [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] &quot;votive antiphon&quot; commonly sung as an appendix to the main [[Liturgy of the Hours|office]] to the [[Blessed Virgin Mary]] or [[saint (Christianity)|other saints]]. During the [[Elizabethan period]], notable anthems were composed by [[Thomas Tallis]], [[William Byrd]], Tye, and Farrant{{sfnp|''EB''|1878}} but they were not mentioned in the [[Book of Common Prayer]] until 1662 when the famous [[rubric]] &quot;In quires and places where they sing here followeth the Anthem&quot; first appears. Early anthems tended to be simple and [[homophony|homophonic]] in texture, so that the words could be clearly heard. During the 17th century, notable anthems were composed by [[Orlando Gibbons]], [[Henry Purcell]], and [[John Blow]],{{sfnp|''EB''|1878}} with the [[verse anthem]] becoming the dominant musical form of the [[English Restoration|Restoration]].{{citation needed|date=August 2015}} In the 18th century, famed anthems were composed by Croft, Boyce, [[James Kent]], [[James Nares]], [[Benjamin Cooke]], and [[Samuel Arnold (composer)|Samuel Arnold]].{{sfnp|''EB''|1878}} In the 19th, [[Samuel Sebastian Wesley]] wrote anthems influenced by contemporary [[oratorio]] which stretch to several [[movement (music)|movements]] and last twenty minutes or longer. Later in the century, [[Charles Villiers Stanford]] used symphonic techniques to produce a more concise and unified structure. Many anthems have been composed since this time, generally by [[organist]]s rather than professional [[composer]]s and often in a conservative style. Major composers have usually composed anthems in response to commissions and for special occasions. Examples include [[Edward Elgar]]'s 1912 &quot;Great is the Lord&quot; and 1914 &quot;Give unto the Lord&quot; (both with orchestral accompaniment), [[Benjamin Britten]]'s 1943 &quot;[[Rejoice in the Lamb]]&quot; (a modern example of a multi-movement anthem, today heard mainly as a concert piece), and, on a much smaller scale, [[Ralph Vaughan Williams]]'s 1952 &quot;O Taste and See&quot; written for the coronation of [[Elizabeth II|Queen Elizabeth II]]. With the relaxation of the rule, in [[England]] at least, that anthems should be only in English, the repertoire has been greatly enhanced by the addition of many works from the Latin repertoire.

==Types==
The word &quot;anthem&quot; is commonly used to describe any celebratory song or composition for a distinct group, as in [[national anthem]]s. Many [[Pop music|pop song]]s are used as [[sports anthem]]s, notably including [[Queen (band)|Queen]]'s &quot;[[We Are the Champions]]&quot; and &quot;[[We Will Rock You]]&quot;, and some sporting events have their own anthems, most notably including [[UEFA Champions League Anthem|UEFA Champions League]]. Further, some songs are artistically styled as anthems, whether or not they are used as such, including [[Marilyn Manson (band)|Marilyn Manson]]'s &quot;[[Irresponsible Hate Anthem]]&quot;, [[Silverchair]]'s &quot;[[Anthem for the Year 2000]]&quot;, and [[Toto (band)|Toto]]'s &quot;Child's Anthem&quot;.

===National anthem===
{{main|National anthem}}
A national anthem (also state anthem, national hymn, national song, etc.) is generally a [[Patriotism|patriotic]] musical composition that evokes and eulogizes the history, traditions, and struggles of a [[Sovereign state|country]]'s people, recognized either by that state's [[government]] as the official national [[song]], or by [[convention (norm)|convention]] through use by the people. The majority of national anthems are [[March (music)|marches]] or [[hymn]]s in style. The countries of [[Latin America]], [[Central Asia]], and [[Europe]] tend towards more ornate and [[opera]]tic pieces, while those in the [[Middle East]], [[Oceania]], [[Africa]], and the [[Caribbean]] use a more simplistic [[fanfare]]. Some [[List of sovereign states|countries]] that are devolved into multiple constituent states have their own official musical compositions for them (such as with the United Kingdom, Russian Federation, and the former Soviet Union); their constituencies' songs are sometimes referred to as national anthems even though they are not [[sovereign state]]s.

===Flag anthem===
{{Listen
|title=&quot;Zhōnghuá Míngúo Gúoqígē&quot;
|filename=National Flag Anthem of the Republic of China中華民國國旗歌 (演奏版).oga
|description=The Taiwanese flag anthem &quot;[[Zhōnghuá Míngúo Gúoqígē]]&quot;; formerly the flag anthem of China until 1949.}}
A [[flag anthem]] is generally a [[Patriotism|patriotic]] musical composition that extols and praises a flag, typically one of a country, in which case it is sometimes called a national flag anthem. It is often either sung or performed during or immediately before the raising or lowering of a flag during a ceremony. Most countries use their respective national anthems or some other patriotic song for this purpose.&lt;ref name=GrandOldFlag&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-G-3wIV-ehE|date=February 1, 2012|title=Morning Colors Ceremony Camp Pendleton 2-1-12|first=|last=|website=YouTube}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, some countries, particularly in South America, use a discrete flag anthem for such purposes. Not all countries have flag anthems. Some used them in the past but no longer do, such as Iran, China, and South Africa. Flag anthems can be officially codified in law, or unofficially recognized as such through mere custom and convention. In some countries, the flag anthem may be just another song, and in others, it may be an official symbol of the state akin to a second national anthem, such as in Taiwan.

=== Shared anthems ===
Although anthems are used to distinguish states and territories, there are instances of shared anthems. &quot;[[Nkosi Sikelel' iAfrika]]&quot; became a [[pan-African]] liberation anthem and was later adopted as the national anthem of five countries in [[Africa]] including [[Zambia]], [[Tanzania]], [[Namibia]] and [[Zimbabwe]] after independence. Zimbabwe and Namibia have since adopted new national anthems. Since 1997, the [[South Africa]]n national anthem has been a hybrid song combining new English lyrics with extracts of &quot;Nkosi Sikelel' iAfrika&quot; and the former state anthem &quot;[[Die Stem van Suid-Afrika]]&quot;.

&quot;[[Hymn to Liberty]]&quot; is the longest national anthem in the world by length of text.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://nationalanthems.me/greece-hymn-to-liberty/ | title=Greece – Hymn to Liberty | publisher=NationalAnthems.me | accessdate=2 November 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1865, the first three stanzas and later the first two officially became the national anthem of [[Greece]] and later also that of the [[Republic of Cyprus]].

&quot;[[Forged from the Love of Liberty]]&quot; was composed as the national anthem for the short-lived [[West Indies Federation]] (1958–1962) and was adopted by [[Trinidad and Tobago]] when it became independent in 1962.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = Understanding our national anthem | publisher = FIRST Magazine | year = 2012 | url = http://www.firstmagazine.com/DownloadSpecialistPublicationDetail.647.ashx | access-date = 2013-03-05 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20130928035953/http://www.firstmagazine.com/DownloadSpecialistPublicationDetail.647.ashx | archive-date = 2013-09-28 | url-status = dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;[[Esta É a Nossa Pátria Bem Amada]]&quot; is the national anthem of [[Guinea-Bissau]] and was also the national anthem of [[Cape Verde]] until 1996.

&quot;[[Oben am jungen Rhein]]&quot;, national anthem of [[Liechtenstein]] is set to the tune of &quot;God Save the Queen&quot;. Other anthems that have used the same melody include &quot;[[Heil dir im Siegerkranz]]&quot;, &quot;[[Kongesangen]]&quot;, &quot;[[My Country, 'Tis of Thee]]&quot;, &quot;[[Rufst du, mein Vaterland]]&quot;, &quot;[[E Ola Ke Alii Ke Akua]]&quot;, and &quot;[[The Prayer of Russians]]&quot;F.

The [[Estonia]]n anthem &quot;[[Mu isamaa, mu õnn ja rõõm]]&quot; is set to a melody composed in 1848 by [[Fredrik Pacius|Fredrik (Friedrich) Pacius]] which is also that of the national anthem of [[Finland]]: &quot;[[Maamme]]&quot; (&quot;Vårt Land&quot; in Swedish).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://nationalanthems.me/estonia-mu-isamaa-mu-onn-ja-room | title=Estonia – Mu isamaa, mu õnn ja rõõm | publisher=NationalAnthems.me | accessdate=21 November 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It is also considered to be ethnic anthem for the [[Livonian people]] with lyrics &quot;[[Min izāmō|Min izāmō, min sindimō]]&quot; (&quot;My Fatherland, my native land&quot;).

&quot;[[Hey, Slavs]]&quot; is dedicated to [[Slavic peoples]]. Its first lyrics were written in 1834 under the title &quot;Hey, Slovaks&quot; (&quot;Hej, Slováci&quot;) by [[Samuel Tomášik]] and it has since served as the ethnic anthem of the [[Pan-Slavic]] movement, the organizational anthem of the [[Sokol]] physical education and political movement, the national anthem of [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]] and the transitional anthem of the State Union of [[Serbia and Montenegro]]. The song is also considered to be the second, unofficial anthem of the Slovaks. Its melody is based on [[Mazurek Dabrowskiego|Mazurek Dąbrowskiego]], which has been also the anthem of [[Poland]] since 1926, but the Yugoslav variation is much slower and more accentuated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite av media|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cZ1SUCpekyM|title=Mazurek Dąbrowskiego &amp; Hej Slaveni|date=2 March 2011|work=YouTube|accessdate=20 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Between 1991 and 1994 &quot;[[Deșteaptă-te, române!]]&quot; was the national anthem of both [[Romania]] and [[Moldova]], but in the case of the latter was replaced by the current Moldovan national anthem, &quot;[[Limba noastră]]&quot;.

The modern national anthem of [[Germany]], &quot;[[Deutschlandlied|Das Lied der Deutschen]]&quot;,{{Efn|Translates from German as &quot;The Song of the Germans&quot;.}} uses the same tune as the 19th and early 20th-century [[Austria-Hungary|Austro-Hungarian]] royal anthem &quot;[[Gott erhalte Franz den Kaiser]]&quot;.{{efn|Translates from German as &quot;God save Emperor Francis&quot;.}}

The &quot;[[National Anthem of the Soviet Union|Hymn of the Soviet Union]]&quot;,{{efn|Russian: ''Государственный гимн СССР''; transliterated as ''Gosudarstvenniy Gimn SSSR''.}} used until its dissolution in 1991, which was given new words and [[National anthem of Russia|adopted]] by the [[Russia|Russian Federation]] in 2000 to replace an instrumental national anthem that had been introduced in 1990.&lt;ref name='rianovosti'&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.rian.ru/symbols/20070607/66606928.html|title=National Anthem|accessdate=20 December 2009|date=7 June 2007|work=Russia's State Symbols|publisher=RIA Novosti}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=zolotov&gt;{{cite news | first=Andrei | last=Zolotov |title=Russian Orthodox Church Approves as Putin Decides to Sing to a Soviet Tune | date=1 December 2000 | publisher=Christianity Today International | url =http://www.christianitytoday.com/ct/2000/decemberweb-only/57.0.html | work =Christianity Today Magazine | accessdate = 19 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;[[Bro Gozh ma Zadoù]]&quot;, the regional anthem of [[Brittany]] and, &quot;[[Bro Goth Agan Tasow]]&quot;, the [[Cornwall|Cornish]] regional anthem, are sung to the same tune as that of the Welsh regional anthem &quot;[[Hen Wlad Fy Nhadau]]&quot;, with similar words.

===For parts of states=== 
{{See also|List of regional anthems}}
{{listen
|filename=&quot;Marcha de Zacatecas&quot;, performed by the United States Navy Band.wav
|title=&quot;Marcha de Zacatecas&quot;
|description=The &quot;[[Marcha de Zacatecas]]&quot;, the regional anthem of the Mexican state of [[Zacatecas]].}}
{{listen
|filename=National anthem of Tajikistan, performed by the U.S. Navy Band.flac
|title=&quot;Surudi Milli&quot;
|description=Tajikistan's national anthem &quot;[[Surudi Milli]]&quot;, the tune of which was previously used in the regional anthem of the [[Tajik Soviet Socialist Republic]] during that state's existence..}}
{{listen
|filename=U.S. Navy Band - God Save the Queen.oga
|title=&quot;God Save the Queen&quot;
|description=Unlike Wales, England does not have an officially-designated regional anthem. Thus, the UK's national anthem &quot;[[God Save the Queen]]&quot; is typically used as a ''de facto'' regional anthem of England for occasions requiring the use of one.}}
{{listen
|filename=Regional anthem of the Northern Mariana Islands, performed by the United States Navy Band.oga
|title=&quot;Gi Talo Gi Halom Tasi&quot;
|description=&quot;[[Gi Talo Gi Halom Tasi]]&quot;, the regional anthem of the [[Northern Mariana Islands]].
|filename2=United States Navy Band - La Borinqueña.ogg
|title2=&quot;La Borinqueña&quot;
|description2=&quot;[[La Borinqueña]]&quot;, the regional anthem of Puerto Rico.
|filename3=Regional anthem of the United States Virgin Islands.wav
|title3=&quot;Virgin Islands March&quot;
|description3=The &quot;[[Virgin Islands March]]&quot;, the regional anthem of the [[United States Virgin Islands|US Virgin Islands]].}}
{{listen
|filename=National anthem of Serbia, performed by the United States Navy Band.wav
|title=&quot;Bože pravde&quot;
|description=&quot;[[Bože pravde]]&quot;, the regional anthem of [[Republic of Serbia (1992–2006)|Serbia]] when it was a part of [[Serbia and Montenegro]]. It is now the national anthem of Serbia.}}
Some countries, such as the former [[Soviet Union]], [[Spain]], and the [[United Kingdom]], among others, are held to be unions of several &quot;nations&quot; by various definitions. Each of the different &quot;nations&quot; may have their own regional anthem and these songs may or may not be officially recognized. These compositions are typically referred to as regional anthems.
====Austria====
In [[Austria]], the situation is similar to that in Germany. The regional anthem of [[Upper Austria]], the &quot;Hoamatgsang&quot; ({{Lang-en|&quot;Chant of the Homeland&quot;}}), is notable in the way that it is the only (official) German-language anthem written – and sung – entirely in dialect.
====Belgium====
In [[Belgium]], [[Wallonia]] uses &quot;[[Le Chant des Wallons]]&quot; and Flanders uses &quot;[[De Vlaamse Leeuw]]&quot;.
====Canada====
The Canadian province of [[Newfoundland and Labrador]], having been the independent [[Dominion of Newfoundland]] before 1949, also has its own regional anthem from its days as a dominion and colony of the UK, the &quot;[[Ode to Newfoundland]]&quot;. It was the only Canadian province with its own anthem until 2010, when [[Prince Edward Island]] adopted the 1908 song &quot;[[The Island Hymn]]&quot; as its provincial anthem.
====Czechoslovakia====
[[Czechoslovakia]] had a national anthem composed of two parts, the [[Kde domov můj?|Czech]] regional anthem followed by one verse of the [[Nad Tatrou sa blýska|Slovak one]]. After the [[dissolution of Czechoslovakia]], the [[Czech Republic]] adopted its own regional anthem as its national one, whereas [[Slovakia]] did so with slightly changed lyrics and an additional stanza.
====Germany====
In [[Germany]], many of the [[States of Germany|Länder]] have their own anthems, some of which predate the [[unification of Germany]] in 1871. A prominent example is the [[Bayernhymne|Hymn of Bavaria]], which also has the status of an official anthem (and thus enjoys legal protection). There are also several unofficial regional anthems, like the &quot;[[Badnerlied]]&quot; or the &quot;[[Niedersachsenlied]]&quot;.
====Malaysia====
All the individual states of [[Malaysia]] have their own regional anthems.
====Mexico====
In [[Mexico]], after the national anthem was established in 1854, most of the states of the federation adopted their own regional anthems, which often emphasize heroes, virtues or particular landscapes. In particular, the regional anthem of [[Zacatecas]], the &quot;[[Marcha de Zacatecas]]&quot;, is one of the more well-known of Mexico's various regional anthems.&lt;ref&gt;https://web.archive.org/web/20061210032717/http://www.navyband.navy.mil/disc_worldclassmarches.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;

====Soviet Union====
{{Main|Regional anthems of the Soviet Union}}
Fourteen of the fifteen [[republics of the Soviet Union|constituent states of the Soviet Union]] had their own official song which was used at events connected to that region, and also written and sung in that region's own language. The [[Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic]] used the Soviet Union's national anthem as its regional anthem (&quot;[[The Internationale]]&quot; from 1917 to 1944 and the &quot;[[National Anthem of the Soviet Union]]&quot; from 1944 to 1990) until 1990, the last of the Soviet constituent states to do so. After the Soviet Union disbanded in the early 1990s, some of its former constituent states, now sovereign nations in their own right, retained the melodies of their old Soviet-era regional anthems until replacing them or, in some cases, still use them today.

Unlike most national anthems, few of which were composed by renowned composers, the Soviet Union's various regional anthems were composed by some of the best Soviet composers, including world-renowned [[Gustav Ernesaks]] (Estonia), [[Aram Khachaturian]] (Armenia), [[Otar Taktakishvili]] (Georgia), and [[Uzeyir Hajibeyov]] (Azerbaijan).

The lyrics present great similarities, all having mentions to [[Vladimir Lenin]] (and most, in their initial versions, to [[Joseph Stalin]], the Armenian and Uzbek anthems being exceptions), to the guiding role of the [[Communist Party of the Soviet Union]], and to the brotherhood of the Soviet peoples, including a specific reference to the friendship of the [[Russians|Russian]] people (the Estonian, Georgian and Karelo-Finnish anthems were apparently an exception to this last rule).

Some of the Soviet regional anthems' melodies can be sung in the [[State Anthem of the Soviet Union#Lyrics|Soviet Union anthem lyrics]] (Ukrainian and Belarus are the most fitted in this case).

Most of these regional anthems were replaced with new national ones during or after the [[dissolution of the Soviet Union]]; [[National anthem of Belarus|Belarus]], [[National anthem of Kazakhstan|Kazakhstan]] (until 2006), [[National anthem of Tajikistan|Tajikistan]], [[National anthem of Turkmenistan|Turkmenistan]] (until 1997), and [[National anthem of Uzbekistan|Uzbekistan]] kept the melodies, but with different lyrics. [[Russia]] itself had abandoned the Soviet hymn, replacing it with [[Patrioticheskaya Pesnya|a tune]] by [[Mikhail Glinka|Glinka]]. However, with [[Vladimir Putin]] coming to power, the old Soviet tune was restored, with [[National Anthem of Russia|new lyrics]] written to it.

Like the [[hammer and sickle]] and [[red star]], the public performance of the anthems of the Soviet Union's various regional anthems the national anthem of the Soviet Union itself are considered as occupation symbols as well as symbols of [[totalitarianism]] and [[state terror]] by several countries formerly either members of or occupied by the [[Soviet Union]]. Accordingly, Latvia,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=BC, Riga, 16.05.2013|url=http://www.baltic-course.com/eng/legislation/&amp;doc=74860|website=The Baltic course|accessdate=3 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lithuania,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/low/europe/7459976.stm | work=BBC News | title=Lithuanian ban on Soviet symbols | date=17 June 2008 | accessdate=22 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hungary,&lt;ref&gt;Hungarian Criminal Code 269/B.§ (1993) “(1) A person who (a) disseminates, (b) uses in public or (c) exhibits a swastika, an SS-badge, an arrow-cross, a symbol of the sickle and hammer or a red star, or a symbol depicting any of them, commits a misdemeanor—unless a more serious crime is committed—and shall be sentenced to a criminal fine (''pénzbüntetés'').”&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Decommunization in Ukraine|Ukraine]]&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=https://www.wsj.com/articles/ukraine-bans-soviet-era-symbols-1428606171 | title=Ukraine Bans Soviet-Era Symbols}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.memory.gov.ua/laws/law-ukraine-condemnation-communist-and-national-socialist-nazi-regimes-and-prohibition-propagan | title=LAW OF UKRAINE. On the condemnation of the communist and national socialist (Nazi) regimes, and prohibition of propaganda of their symbols}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://zakon4.rada.gov.ua/laws/show/317-viii&lt;/ref&gt; have banned those anthems amongst other things deemed to be symbols of fascism, socialism, communism, and the Soviet Union and its republics. In [[Poland]], dissemination of items which are “media of fascist, communist, or other totalitarian symbolism” was criminalized in 1997. However, in 2011 the [[Constitutional Tribunal (Poland)|Constitutional Tribunal]] found this sanction to be unconstitutional.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://trybunal.gov.pl/rozprawy/komunikaty-prasowe/komunikaty-po/art/2628-nowelizacja-kodeksu-karnego/s/k-1110/|title=Nowelizacja kodeksu karnego.|language=pl|date=2011-07-19|accessdate=2015-04-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast to this treatment of the ''symbolism'', promotion of fascist, communist and other totalitarian ''ideology'' remains illegal. Those laws do not apply to the anthems of [[Russia]], [[Belarus]], [[Uzbekistan]], [[Kazakhstan]], and [[Tajikistan]] which used the melody with different lyrics.

====Spain====
In [[Spain]], the situation is similar to that in Austria and Germany. Unlike the national anthem, most of the [[Anthems of the autonomous communities of Spain|anthems of the autonomous communities]] have words. All are official. Three prominent examples are &quot;[[Els Segadors]]&quot; of [[Catalonia]], &quot;[[Eusko Abendaren Ereserkia]]&quot; of the [[Basque Country (autonomous community)|Basque Country]], and &quot;[[Os Pinos]]&quot; of [[Galicia (Spain)|Galicia]], all written and sung in the local languages.
====United Kingdom====
The United Kingdom's national anthem is &quot;God Save the Queen&quot; but [[Countries of the United Kingdom|its constituent countries]] and [[Crown Dependencies]] also have their own regional anthems which have varying degrees of official recognition. [[England]], [[Scotland]], [[Wales]], and [[Northern Ireland]], as well as [[Jersey]], [[Guernsey]] and the [[Isle of Man]], each has a number of anthems which are played at occasions such as sports matches and official events.&lt;ref&gt;Johnson, H. (2015). [https://www.researchgate.net/publication/299135674_Anthem_for_Jersey_Music_Media_and_Politics_in_an_Island_Setting MEDIANZ, 15(1), 96-118.].&lt;/ref&gt; The song usually [[National anthem of England|used as a regional anthem for England]] is &quot;God Save the Queen&quot;, though sometimes &quot;[[And did those feet in ancient time|Jerusalem]]&quot;, &quot;[[I Vow To Thee, My Country]]&quot; and &quot;[[Land of Hope and Glory]]&quot; may be played instead. Scotland has adopted &quot;[[Flower of Scotland]]&quot; as its unofficial &quot;national&quot; anthem, while Wales has sung &quot;[[Mae Hen Wlad Fy Nhadau]]&quot; since 1856 when it was written by father and son [[Evan James (poet)|Evan]] and [[James James]]; the translation and music were adopted by [[Brittany (administrative region)|Brittany]] as its regional (often called &quot;national&quot;) anthem. &quot;Hen Wlad fy Nhadau&quot; was sometimes accompanied by the hymn, &quot;[[Cwm Rhondda|Guide Me, O thou Great Redeemer]]&quot;, especially at rugby matches. Northern Ireland has used &quot;God Save the Queen&quot; though &quot;[[Londonderry Air]]&quot; is also used.

====United States====
Although the United States has &quot;[[The Star-Spangled Banner]]&quot; as its official national anthem, its constituent states and territories also has their own regional anthem (referred to by most US states as a &quot;[[List of U.S. state songs|state song]]&quot;), along with [[Washington, D.C.|Washington, DC]]. A notable exception is [[New Jersey]], which is the only US state to be without a regional anthem.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.state.nj.us/faqs/facts.html/|title=Frequently Asked Questions {{!}} NJ Facts|website=www.state.nj.us|access-date=2019-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Forty-nine of the [[United States]]' fifty [[U.S. state|constituent states]] have one or more regional anthems (usually referred to as a &quot;state song&quot; in US parlance), which are selected by each [[State legislature (United States)|state legislature]], and/or state governor, as a symbol (or emblem) of that particular US state. 

Some US states have more than one official state song, and may refer to some of their official songs by other names; for example, [[Arkansas]] officially has two state songs, plus a state anthem, and a state historical song. [[Tennessee]] has the most state songs, with 9 official state songs and an official bicentennial [[rapping|rap]].

[[Arizona]] has a song that was written specifically as a state anthem in 1915, as well as the 1981 country hit &quot;Arizona&quot;, which it adopted as the alternate state anthem in 1982.&lt;ref name=RJo/&gt;

Two individuals, [[Stephen Foster]], and [[John Denver]], have written or co-written two state songs. Foster's two state songs, &quot;[[Old Folks at Home]]&quot; (better known as &quot;Swanee Ribber&quot; or &quot;Suwannee River&quot;), adopted by Florida, and &quot;[[My Old Kentucky Home]]&quot; are among the best-known songs in the US On March 12, 2007, the Colorado Senate passed a resolution to make Denver's trademark 1972 hit &quot;[[Rocky Mountain High]]&quot; one of the state's two official state songs, sharing duties with its predecessor, &quot;Where the Columbines Grow&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Official State Song|url=http://www.netstate.com/states/symb/song/co_rocky_mountain_high.htm |accessdate=April 16, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; On March 7, 2014, the West Virginia Legislature approved a resolution to make Denver's &quot;[[Take Me Home, Country Roads]]&quot; one of four official state songs of West Virginia. Governor Earl Ray Tomblin signed the resolution into law on March 8, 2014.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.netstate.com/states/symb/song/co_rocky_mountain_high.htm|title=Colorado State Song Rocky Mountain High composed by John Denver|author=|date=|website=www.netstate.com|accessdate=5 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Additionally, [[Woody Guthrie]] wrote or co-wrote two state ''folk songs'' - [[Roll On, Columbia, Roll On]] and [[Oklahoma Hills]] - but they have separate status from the official state ''songs'' of Washington and Oklahoma, respectively.  Other well-known state songs include &quot;[[Yankee Doodle]]&quot;, &quot;[[You Are My Sunshine]]&quot;, &quot;[[Rocky Top]]&quot;, and &quot;[[Home on the Range]]&quot;; a number of others are popular standards, including &quot;[[Oklahoma (Rodgers and Hammerstein song)|Oklahoma]]&quot; (from the [[Rodgers and Hammerstein]] musical), [[Hoagy Carmichael]]'s &quot;[[Georgia on My Mind]]&quot;, &quot;[[Tennessee Waltz]]&quot;, &quot;[[Missouri Waltz]]&quot;, and &quot;[[On the Banks of the Wabash, Far Away]]&quot;. Many of the others are much less well-known, especially outside the state.

[[New Jersey]] has no official state song, while [[Virginia]]'s previous state song, &quot;[[Carry Me Back to Old Virginny]]&quot;, adopted in 1940,&lt;ref name=&quot;RJo&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Johnson|first1=Roger R.|title=State Songs|url=http://www.welcometoamerica.us/info/songs.html|publisher=Welcome to America|accessdate=18 November 2014|date=2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; was later rescinded in 1997 due to its racist language by the [[Virginia General Assembly]].&lt;ref name=&quot;VA&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url= http://www.virginiastatesong.com/ | title= Official State Song of the Commonwealth of Virginia | accessdate= 2007-02-06 | year= 2006 | archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20070429004929/http://www.virginiastatesong.com/ | archive-date= 2007-04-29 | url-status= dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2015, &quot;[[Our Great Virginia]]&quot; was made the new state song of Virginia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Patch&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url= http://patch.com/virginia/fairfaxcity/listen-virginia-now-has-2-state-songs | title= Listen: Virginia Now Has 2 State Songs | accessdate= 2015-04-02 |year=2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Maryland (&quot;[[Maryland, My Maryland]]&quot;) and Iowa (&quot;[[The Song of Iowa]]&quot;) use the tune from the song &quot;[[O Tannenbaum]]&quot; as the melody to their official state songs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.baltimoresun.com/news/opinion/editorial/bs-ed-state-song-20160315-story.html &quot;Maryland, my meh song&quot;], ''[[The Baltimore Sun]]'', Baltimore, 15 March 2016. Retrieved on 05 June 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Yugoslavia====
In [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]], each of the country's constituent states (except for [[Socialist Republic of Bosnia and Herzegovina|Bosnia and Herzegovina]]) had the right to have its own regional anthem, but only the [[Socialist Republic of Croatia|Croatia]]n one actually did so initially, later joined by the [[Socialist Republic of Slovenia|Slovene]] one on the brink of the [[breakup of Yugoslavia]]. Before 1989, [[Socialist Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]] did not officially use a regional anthem, even though one was proclaimed during the [[World War II]] by [[ASNOM]].
=====Serbia and Montenegro=====
In 2005 and 2004 respectively, the [[Republic of Serbia (1992–2006)|Serbian]] and [[Republic of Montenegro (1992–2006)|Montenegrin]] regions of [[Serbia and Montenegro]] adopted their own regional anthems. When the two regions both became independent countries in mid-2006, their regional anthems became their national ones.

=== International organizations ===
Larger entities also sometimes have anthems, in some cases known as 'international anthems'. ''Lullaby'' is the official anthem of [[UNICEF]] composed by [[Steve Barakatt]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unicef.org/infobycountry/canada_51822.html A musical call to action: ‘Lullaby: The UNICEF Anthem’] UNICEF Website, 19 November 2009&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;[[The Internationale]]&quot; is the organizational anthem of the [[socialism|socialist]] movement and the [[communism|communist]] movement. Before March 1944, it was also the anthem of the Soviet Union and the [[Comintern]]. [[ASEAN Way]] is the official anthem of [[ASEAN]]. The tune of the &quot;[[Ode to Joy]]&quot; from [[Symphony No. 9 (Beethoven)|Beethoven's Symphony No. 9]] is the official [[Anthem of Europe|anthem of the European Union]] and of the [[Council of Europe]].  Let's All Unite and Celebrate is the official anthem of the African Union&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.africa-union.org/AU%20symbols/ausymblos.htm AU Symbols] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20050304021240/http://www.africa-union.org/AU%20symbols/ausymblos.htm |date=2005-03-04 }}.&lt;/ref&gt; (&quot;[[Let Us All Unite and Celebrate Together]]&quot;).

The Olympic Movement also has its own [[Olympic Hymn|organizational anthem]]. [[Esperanto]] speakers at meetings often use the song &quot;[[La Espero]]&quot; as their linguistic anthem. The first [[South Asian Anthem]] by poet-diplomat [[Abhay K]] may inspire [[SAARC]] to come up with an official [[SAARC Anthem]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://aninews.in/newsdetail4/story142658/indian-poet-diplomat-pens-s-asian-anthem-after-earth-anthem-success.html Indian poet-diplomat pens S.Asian anthem after Earth anthem success] ANI, 27 November 2013&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;[[Ireland's Call]]&quot; was commissioned as the sporting anthem of both the [[Ireland national rugby union team]] and the [[Ireland national rugby league team]], which are composed of players from both jurisdictions on the island of Ireland, in response to dissatisfaction among Northern Ireland [[Ulster unionism|unionist]]s with the use of the [[Amhrán na bhFiann|Irish national anthem]]. &quot;Ireland's Call&quot; has since been used by some other all-island bodies.

An International Anthem also unifies a group of organizations sharing the same appellation such as the International Anthem of the Royal Golf Clubs composed by [[Steve Barakatt]].

===Global anthem ===
{{main|Earth Anthem}}
Various artists have created &quot;[[Earth Anthem]]s&quot; for the entire planet, typically extolling the ideas of [[planetary consciousness]]. Though [[UNESCO]] have praised the idea of a global anthem,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.business-standard.com/article/news-ani/unesco-finds-indian-poet-diplomat-s-idea-of-an-earth-anthem-inspiring-114022700403_1.html UNESCO finds Indian poet-diplomat's idea of an Earth Anthem inspiring] Business Standard, 27 February 2014&lt;/ref&gt; the [[UN]] has never adopted an official song.

==See also==
{{Portal|Music}}
{{divcol}}
*[[Antiphon]]
*[[Motet]]
*[[List of national anthems]]
*[[Sports anthem]]
*[[Stadium anthem]]s
*[[Verse anthem]]
{{divcol-end}}

==Notes==
{{Notelist}}
==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite EB9 |mode=cs2 |wstitle=Anthem |volume=2  |ref={{harvid|EB|1878}} |page=102 }}
* {{cite EB1911 |mode=cs2 |wstitle=Anthem |volume=2 |ref={{harvid|EB|1911}} |page=93 }}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Anthems|*]]
[[Category:Christian songs|*]]
[[Category:Song forms]]</text>
      <sha1>jmy6ztmyun7ektzt6owuql4oho13pj7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
