  <page>
    <title>Albrecht Dürer</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2402</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939823411</id>
      <parentid>939802848</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-08T23:14:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ewulp</username>
        <id>998182</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rv, unsourced</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|German Renaissance artist}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2018}}
{{Infobox artist
| name = Albrecht Dürer
| image = File:Albrecht Dürer, Selbstbildnis mit 26 Jahren (Prado, Madrid).jpg
| caption = Dürer's [[Self-Portrait (Dürer, Madrid)|self-portrait at 26]]
| birth_name = 
| birth_date = {{Birth date|1471|05|21|df=yes}}
| birth_place = [[Nuremberg]], [[Holy Roman Empire]]
| death_date = {{Death date and age|1528|4|6|1471|5|21|df=y}}
| death_place = Nuremberg, Holy Roman Empire
| nationality = German
| movement = [[High Renaissance]]
| buried_in = 
| field = {{hlist |[[Painting]] |[[printmaking]]}}
| works = 
}}

'''Albrecht Dürer''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|dj|ʊər|ər}};&lt;ref name=&quot;LPD&quot;&gt;{{citation|last=Wells|first=John C.|year=2008|title=Longman Pronunciation Dictionary|edition=3rd|publisher=Longman|isbn=9781405881180}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{IPA-de|ˈʔalbʁɛçt ˈdyːʁɐ|lang}};&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://de.langenscheidt.com/franzoesisch-deutsch/search?term=Albrecht|title=Albrecht - Deutsch-Übersetzung - Langenscheidt Französisch-Deutsch Wörterbuch|publisher=[[Langenscheidt]]|accessdate=22 October 2018|language=de, fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.duden.de/rechtschreibung/Duerer|title=Duden {{!}} Dürer {{!}} Rechtschreibung, Bedeutung, Definition|work=[[Duden]]|accessdate=22 October 2018|language=de}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LPD&quot;/&gt; 21 May 1471 – 6 April 1528),&lt;ref name=Mueller&gt;Müller, Peter O. (1993) ''Substantiv-Derivation in Den Schriften Albrecht Dürers'', Walter de Gruyter. {{ISBN|3-11-012815-2}}.&lt;/ref&gt; sometimes spelt in English as '''Durer''' or '''Duerer''', without [[Umlaut (linguistics)|umlaut]], was a [[German art|German painter]], [[Old master prints|printmaker]], and [[history of geometry#Renaissance|theorist]] of the [[German Renaissance]]. Born in [[Free Imperial City of Nuremberg|Nuremberg]], Dürer established his reputation and influence across Europe when he was in his twenties due to his high-quality [[List of woodcuts by Dürer|woodcut prints]]. He was in communication with the major Italian artists of his time, including [[Raphael]], [[Giovanni Bellini]] and [[Leonardo da Vinci]], and from 1512 he was patronized by Emperor [[Maximilian I, Holy Roman Emperor|Maximilian I]]. Dürer is commemorated by both the Lutheran and Episcopal Churches.

[[File:Albrecht Dürer - 1500 self-portrait (High resolution and detail).jpg|thumb|Dürer's [[Self-Portrait (Dürer, Munich)|self-portrait at 28]] (1500)]]

Dürer's vast body of work includes [[List of engravings by Dürer|engraving]]s, his preferred technique in his later prints, altarpieces, portraits and self-portraits, [[watercolour]]s and books. The woodcuts, such as the ''[[Apocalypse (Dürer)|Apocalypse]]'' series (1498), are more [[Gothic art|Gothic]] than the rest of his work. 
His well-known engravings include the ''[[Knight, Death and the Devil]]'' (1513), ''[[Saint Jerome in His Study (Dürer)|Saint Jerome in his Study]]'' (1514) and ''[[Melencolia I]]'' (1514), which has been the subject of extensive analysis and interpretation. His watercolours also mark him as one of the first European [[landscape art]]ists, while his ambitious woodcuts revolutionized the potential of that medium.

Dürer's introduction of [[Roman mythology|classical motifs]] into Northern art, through his knowledge of [[Italian Renaissance|Italian artists]] and [[Humanism in Germany|German humanists]], has secured his reputation as one of the most important figures of the [[Northern Renaissance]]. This is reinforced by his theoretical treatises, which involve principles of mathematics, [[linear perspective|perspective]], and [[body proportions|ideal proportions]].

Albrecht Dürer has been credited with inventing the basic principle of [[Ray tracing (graphics)|ray tracing]], a technique used in modern computer graphics.&lt;ref name=&quot;raytracing&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|title=Who invented ray tracing?|author=Georg Rainer Hofmann|publisher=The Visual Computer|year=1990|url=https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/BF01911003}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biography==
===Early life (1471–1490)===
[[File:Self-portrait at 13 by Albrecht Dürer.jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[Self-portrait]] [[silverpoint]] drawing by the thirteen-year-old Dürer, 1484]]

Dürer was born on 21 May 1471, third child and second son of his parents, who had at least fourteen and possibly as many as eighteen children.  His father, [[Albrecht Dürer the Elder]] (originally Albrecht Ajtósi), was a successful [[goldsmith]] who in 1455 had moved to Nuremberg from {{interlanguage link|Ajtós|hu|Ajtós|fr|Ajtós}}, near [[Gyula (town)|Gyula]] in [[Hungary]].&lt;ref name=&quot;heaton&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|title=The Life of Albrecht Dürer of Nürnberg: With a Translation of His Letters and Journal and an Account of His Works|first=Mrs. Charles|last=Heaton|authorlink=Mary Margaret Heaton|publisher=Seeley, Jackson and Halliday|year=1881|page=[https://archive.org/details/lifeofalbrechtdu00heat/page/29 29]|url=https://archive.org/details/lifeofalbrechtdu00heat}}.&lt;/ref&gt; One of Albrecht's brothers, [[Hans Dürer]], was also a painter and trained under him. Another of Albrecht's brothers, Endres Dürer, took over their father's business and was a master goldsmith.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=|first=|year=|title=Dürer – oi|url=http://oxfordindex.oup.com/view/10.1093/oi/authority.20110803095736400?rskey=Y8iIbB&amp;result=0&amp;q=durer|journal=|language=en|volume=|pages=|doi=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The German name &quot;Dürer&quot; is a translation from the Hungarian, &quot;Ajtósi&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;heaton&quot;/&gt; Initially, it was &quot;Türer&quot;, meaning doormaker, which is &quot;ajtós&quot; in Hungarian (from &quot;ajtó&quot;, meaning door). A door is featured in the [[coat-of-arms]] the family acquired. Albrecht Dürer the Younger later changed &quot;Türer&quot;, his father's diction of the family's surname, to &quot;Dürer&quot;, to adapt to the local Nuremberg dialect. Dürer the Elder married Barbara Holper, daughter of his master when he himself qualified as a master in 1467.&lt;ref&gt;Bartrum, 93, note 1&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Coat of Arms of Albrecht Dürer MET DP816462.jpg|thumb|upright|Woodcut by Dürer of his [[coat of arms]], which featured a door as a pun on his name, as well as the winged bust of a [[Moors|Moor]]]]

Dürer's godfather was [[Anton Koberger]], who left goldsmithing to become a printer and publisher in the year of Dürer's birth, and became the most successful publisher in Germany, eventually owning twenty-four [[printing-press]]es and built a number of offices in Germany and abroad. Koberger's most famous publication was the ''[[Nuremberg Chronicle]]'', published in 1493 in German and Latin editions. It contained an unprecedented 1,809 [[woodcut]] illustrations (albeit with many repeated uses of the same block) by the [[Wolgemut]] workshop. Dürer may have worked on some of these, as the work on the project began while he was with Wolgemut.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartrum&quot;&gt;[[Giulia Bartrum]], &quot;Albrecht Dürer and his Legacy&quot;, British Museum Press, 2002, {{ISBN|0-7141-2633-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Because Dürer left autobiographical writings and became very famous by his mid-twenties, his life is well documented by several sources. After a few years of school, Dürer started to learn the basics of goldsmithing and drawing from his father. Though his father wanted him to continue his training as a goldsmith, he showed such a precocious talent in drawing that he started as an apprentice to [[Michael Wolgemut]] at the age of fifteen in 1486. A self-portrait, a drawing in [[silverpoint]], is dated 1484 ([[Albertina, Vienna]]) &quot;when I was a child&quot;, as his later inscription says. Wolgemut was the leading artist in Nuremberg at the time, with a large workshop producing a variety of works of art, in particular woodcuts for books. Nuremberg was then an important and prosperous city, a centre for publishing and many luxury trades. It had strong links with Italy, especially [[Venice]], a relatively short distance across the [[Alps]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartrum&quot;/&gt;

===''Wanderjahre'' and marriage (1490–1494)===
[[File:Albrecht-self.jpg|thumb|left|The earliest painted ''[[Portrait of the Artist Holding a Thistle (Albrecht Dürer)|Self-Portrait]]'' (1493) by Albrecht Dürer, oil, originally on [[vellum]] ([[Louvre]], [[Paris]])]]

After completing his apprenticeship, Dürer followed the common German custom of taking ''[[Wanderjahre]]''—in effect [[gap year]]s—in which the apprentice learned skills from artists in other areas; Dürer was to spend about four years away.  He left in 1490, possibly to work under [[Martin Schongauer]], the leading engraver of Northern Europe, but who died shortly before Dürer's arrival at [[Colmar]] in 1492. It is unclear where Dürer travelled in the intervening period, though it is likely that he went to [[Frankfurt]] and the [[Netherlands]]. In Colmar, Dürer was welcomed by Schongauer's brothers, the goldsmiths Caspar and Paul and the painter Ludwig. In 1493 Dürer went to [[Strasbourg]], where he would have experienced the sculpture of [[Nikolaus Gerhaert]]. Dürer's first painted self-portrait (now in the [[Louvre]]) was painted at this time, probably to be sent back to his fiancée in Nuremberg.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartrum&quot;/&gt;

In early 1492 Dürer travelled to [[Basel]] to stay with another brother of Martin Schongauer, the goldsmith Georg.&lt;ref&gt;Here he produced a woodcut of [[St Jerome]] as a frontispiece for Nicholaus Kessler's 'Epistolare beati Hieronymi'. [[Erwin Panofsky]] argues that this print combined the '[[Ulm]]ian style' of Koberger's 'Lives of the Saints' (1488) and that of Wolgemut's workshop. Panofsky, 21&lt;/ref&gt; Very soon after his return to Nuremberg, on 7 July 1494, at the age of 23, Dürer was married to [[Agnes Frey]] following an arrangement made during his absence. Agnes was the daughter of a prominent brass worker (and amateur harpist) in the city. However, no children resulted from the marriage, and with Albrecht the Dürer name died out. The marriage between Agnes and Albrecht was not a generally happy one, as indicated by the letters of Dürer in which he quipped to [[Willibald Pirckheimer]] in an extremely rough tone about his wife. He called her an &quot;old crow&quot; and made other vulgar remarks. Pirckheimer also made no secret of his antipathy towards Agnes, describing her as a miserly shrew with a bitter tongue, who helped cause Dürer's death at a young age.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wilmot-BuxtonPoynter1881&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Harry John Wilmot-Buxton|author2=Edward John Poynter|title=German, Flemish and Dutch Painting|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=aLgnAAAAYAAJ|year=1881|publisher=Scribner and Welford|page=24}}&lt;/ref&gt; One author speculates that Albrecht was bisexual, if not homosexual, due to several of his works containing themes of homosexual desire, as well as the intimate nature of his correspondence with certain very close male friends.&lt;ref name=&quot;Haggerty2013&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=George Haggerty|title=Encyclopedia of Gay Histories and Cultures|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Pez9AQAAQBAJ|date=5 November 2013|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|isbn=978-1-135-58513-6|page=262}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===First journey to Italy (1494–1495)===
[[File:Agnes Duerer 1494.jpg|thumb|left|Dürer's sketch of his wife Agnes Frey 1494]]

Within three months of his marriage, Dürer left for Italy, alone, perhaps stimulated by an outbreak of [[Black Death|plague]] in Nuremberg. He made watercolour sketches as he traveled over the Alps. Some have survived and others may be deduced from accurate landscapes of real places in his later work, for example his engraving ''Nemesis''.

In Italy, he went to Venice to study its more advanced artistic world.&lt;ref name=Lee&gt;Lee, Raymond L. &amp; Alistair B. Fraser. (2001) ''The Rainbow Bridge'', Penn State Press. {{ISBN|0-271-01977-8}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Through Wolgemut's tutelage, Dürer had learned how to make prints in [[drypoint]] and design [[woodcut]]s in the German style, based on the works of [[Martin Schongauer]] and the [[Housebook Master]].&lt;ref name=Lee /&gt; He also would have had access to some Italian works in Germany, but the two visits he made to Italy had an enormous influence on him. He wrote that [[Giovanni Bellini]] was the oldest and still the best of the artists in Venice. His drawings and engravings show the influence of others, notably [[Antonio Pollaiuolo]], with his interest in the proportions of the body; [[Lorenzo di Credi]]; and [[Andrea Mantegna]], whose work he produced copies of while training.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, Angela and Raftery, Andrew. &quot;Remaking Dürer: Investigating the Master Engravings by Masterful Engraving,&quot; [http://artinprint.org/article/remaking-durer-investigating-the-master-engravings/ ''Art in Print'' Vol. 2 No. 4] (November–December 2012).&lt;/ref&gt; Dürer probably also visited [[Padua, Italy|Padua]] and [[Mantua]] on this trip.&lt;ref&gt;The evidence for this trip is not conclusive; the suggestion it happened is supported by Panofsky (in his Albrecht Dürer, 1943) and others, but it has been disputed by other scholars, including Katherine Crawford Luber (in her Albrecht Dürer and the Venetian Renaissance, 2005).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Return to Nuremberg (1495–1505)===
[[File:Albrecht Dürer - Melencolia I - Google Art Project (427760).jpg|thumb|upright|''[[Melencolia I]]'' (1514), engraving]]

On his return to [[Nuremberg]] in 1495, Dürer opened his own workshop (being married was a requirement for this). Over the next five years, his style increasingly integrated Italian influences into underlying Northern forms. Arguably his best works in the first years of the workshop were his [[woodcut]] prints, mostly religious, but including secular scenes such as ''The Men's Bath House'' (ca. 1496). These were larger and more finely cut than the great majority of German woodcuts hitherto, and far more complex and balanced in composition.

It is now thought unlikely that Dürer cut any of the woodblocks himself; this task would have been performed by a specialist craftsman. However, his training in Wolgemut's studio, which made many carved and painted altarpieces and both designed and cut woodblocks for woodcut, evidently gave him great understanding of what the technique could be made to produce, and how to work with block cutters. Dürer either drew his design directly onto the woodblock itself, or glued a paper drawing to the block. Either way, his drawings were destroyed during the cutting of the block.

[[File:Albrecht Dürer - Portrait of Oswolt Krel - WGA6934.jpg|thumb|left|''Portrait of Oswolt Krel'', a merchant from [[Lindau]] ([[Lake Constance]]), participating in the South German medieval trade corporation Große [[Ravensburg]]er Handelsgesellschaft, 1499.]]

His famous series of sixteen great designs for the ''Apocalypse&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.payer.de/christentum/apokalypse.htm Johannesapokalypse in klassischen Comics]&lt;/ref&gt;'' is dated 1498, as is his engraving of'' [[St. Michael Fighting the Dragon-Albrecht Durer|St. Michael Fighting the Dragon]]''. He made the first seven scenes of the ''Great Passion'' in the same year, and a little later, a series of eleven on the [[Holy Family]] and saints. The ''[[Polyptych of the Seven Sorrows|Seven Sorrows Polyptych]]'', commissioned by [[Frederick III, Elector of Saxony|Frederick III of Saxony]] in 1496, was executed by Dürer and his assistants c.&amp;nbsp;1500. In 1502, Dürer's father died. Around 1503–1505 Dürer produced the first 17 of a set illustrating the ''[[Life of the Virgin]]'', which he did not finish for some years. Neither these nor the ''Great Passion'' were published as sets until several years later, but prints were sold individually in considerable numbers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartrum&quot;/&gt;

During the same period Dürer trained himself in the difficult art of using the [[Burin (engraving)|burin]] to make engravings. It is possible he had begun learning this skill during his early training with his father, as it was also an essential skill of the goldsmith. In 1496 he executed the ''Prodigal Son'', which the Italian Renaissance art historian [[Giorgio Vasari]] singled out for praise some decades later, noting its Germanic quality. He was soon producing some spectacular and original images, notably ''Nemesis'' (1502), ''The Sea Monster'' (1498), and ''Saint Eustace'' (c. 1501), with a highly detailed landscape background and animals. His landscapes of this period, such as ''Pond in the Woods'' and ''Willow Mill'', are quite different from his earlier watercolours. There is a much greater emphasis on capturing atmosphere, rather than depicting topography. He made a number of [[Madonna (art)|Madonna]]s, single religious figures, and small scenes with comic peasant figures. Prints are highly portable and these works made Dürer famous throughout the main artistic centres of Europe within a very few years.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartrum&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Albrecht Dürer Betende Hände.jpg|upright|thumb|''[[Praying Hands (Dürer)|Praying Hands]]'', pen-and-ink drawing (c. 1508)]]

The Venetian artist [[Jacopo de' Barbari]], whom Dürer had met in Venice, visited Nuremberg in 1500, and Dürer said that he learned much about the new developments in [[perspective (graphical)|perspective]], [[anatomy]], and [[Body proportions|proportion]] from him.  De' Barbari was unwilling to explain everything he knew, so Dürer began his own studies, which would become a lifelong preoccupation. A series of extant drawings show Dürer's experiments in human proportion, leading to the famous engraving of ''[[Adam and Eve (Dürer)|Adam and Eve]]'' (1504), which shows his subtlety while using the burin in the texturing of flesh surfaces.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartrum&quot;/&gt; This is the only existing engraving signed with his full name.

Dürer created large numbers of preparatory drawings, especially for his paintings and engravings, and many survive, most famously the ''[[Betende Hände]]'' (''Praying Hands'') from circa 1508, a study for an apostle in the Heller altarpiece. He continued to make images in watercolour and [[bodycolour]] (usually combined), including a number of still lifes of meadow sections or animals, including his ''[[Young Hare]]'' (1502) and the ''[[Great Piece of Turf]]'' (1503).

===Second journey to Italy (1505–1507)===
[[File:Albrecht Dürer - Jesus among the Doctors - Google Art Project.jpg|thumb|upright|''[[Christ among the Doctors (Dürer)|Christ among the Doctors]]'' (1506), [[Thyssen-Bornemisza Museum]]]]

In Italy, he returned to painting, at first producing a series of works executed in [[tempera]] on [[linen]]. These include portraits and altarpieces, notably, the [[Paumgartner altarpiece]] and the ''[[Adoration of the Magi (Dürer)|Adoration of the Magi]]''. In early 1506, he returned to Venice and stayed there until the spring of 1507.&lt;ref name=Mueller /&gt; By this time Dürer's engravings had attained great popularity and were being copied. In Venice he was given a valuable commission from the emigrant German community for the church of [[San Bartolomeo, Venice|San Bartolomeo]]. This was the altar-piece known as the ''[[Feast of the Rosary|Adoration of the Virgin]]'' or the ''Feast of Rose Garlands''. It includes portraits of members of Venice's German community, but shows a strong Italian influence. It was subsequently acquired by the Emperor [[Rudolf II, Holy Roman Emperor|Rudolf II]] and taken to Prague. Other paintings Dürer produced in Venice include ''The Virgin and Child with the Goldfinch'', ''[[Christ among the Doctors (Dürer)|Christ among the Doctors]]'' (supposedly produced in a mere five days), and a number of smaller works.

===Nuremberg and the masterworks (1507–1520)===
[[File:Albrecht Dürer, Adam and Eve, 1504, Engraving.jpg|thumb|''Adam and Eve'', 1504]]
[[File:Albrecht Dürer - Adam and Eve (Prado) 2.jpg|thumb|''[[Adam and Eve (Dürer)|Adam and Eve]]'', 1507, [[Museo del Prado]]]]

Despite the regard in which he was held by the Venetians, Dürer returned to Nuremberg by mid-1507, remaining in Germany until 1520. His reputation had spread throughout Europe and he was on friendly terms and in communication with most of the major artists including [[Raphael]],{{efn|According to Vasari, Dürer sent Raphael a self-portrait in watercolour, and Raphael sent back multiple drawings. One is dated 1515 and has an inscription by Dürer (or one of his heirs) affirming that Raphael sent it to him.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Salmi |first1=Mario |author1link=Mario Salmi|last2=Becherucci |first2=Luisa |last3=Marabottini |first3=Alessandro |last4=Tempesti |first4=Anna Forlani |last5=Marchini |first5=Giuseppe |last6=Becatti |author6link=Giovanni Becatti |first6=Giovanni |last7=Castagnoli |first7=Ferdinando |author7link=Ferdinando Castagnoli |last8=Golzio |first8=Vincenzo |title=The Complete Work of Raphael |date=1969 |publisher=Reynal and Co., [[William Morrow and Company]] |location=New York |pp=278, 407}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} [[Giovanni Bellini]] and—mainly through [[Lorenzo di Credi]]—[[Leonardo da Vinci]].{{citation needed|date=April 2017}}

Between 1507 and 1511 Dürer worked on some of his most celebrated paintings: ''[[Adam and Eve (Dürer)|Adam and Eve]]'' (1507), ''[[The Martyrdom of the Ten Thousand (Dürer)|The Martyrdom of the Ten Thousand]]'' (1508, for Frederick of Saxony), ''Virgin with the Iris'' (1508), the altarpiece ''Assumption of the Virgin'' (1509, for Jacob Heller of Frankfurt), and ''[[Adoration of the Trinity]]'' (1511, for Matthaeus Landauer). During this period he also completed two woodcut series, the ''Great Passion'' and the ''Life of the Virgin'', both published in 1511 together with a second edition of the ''Apocalypse'' series. The post-Venetian woodcuts show Dürer's development of [[chiaroscuro]] modelling effects,&lt;ref&gt;Panofsky, 135&lt;/ref&gt; creating a mid-tone throughout the print to which the highlights and shadows can be contrasted.

Other works from this period include the thirty-seven woodcut subjects of the ''Little Passion'', published first in 1511, and a set of fifteen small engravings on the same theme in 1512. Indeed, complaining that painting did not make enough money to justify the time spent when compared to his prints, he produced no paintings from 1513 to 1516. However, in 1513 and 1514 Dürer created his three most famous [[engraving]]s: ''[[Knight, Death, and the Devil]]'' (1513, probably based on [[Desiderius Erasmus|Erasmus]]'s treatise ''[[Enchiridion militis Christiani]]''), ''[[St. Jerome in His Study (Dürer)|St. Jerome in his Study]]'', and the much-debated ''[[Melencolia&amp;nbsp;I]]'' (both 1514, the year Dürer's mother died). Further outstanding pen and ink drawings of Dürer's period of art work of 1513 were drafts for his friend [[Willibald Pirckheimer]]. These drafts were later used to design the famous chandeliers [[lusterweibchen]].

In 1515, he created his ''[[Dürer's Rhinoceros|woodcut of a Rhinoceros]]'' which had arrived in [[Lisbon]] from a written description and sketch by another artist, without ever seeing the animal himself. An image of the [[Indian rhinoceros]], the image has such force that it remains one of his best-known and was still used in some German school science text-books as late as last century.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartrum&quot;/&gt; In the years leading to 1520 he produced a wide range of works, including the woodblocks for the first western printed star charts in 1515&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ianridpath.com/startales/durer.htm Dürer's hemispheres of 1515—the first European printed star charts]&lt;/ref&gt; and portraits in [[tempera]] on [[linen]] in 1516. His only experiments with [[etching]] came in this period, producing five 1515–1516 and a sixth 1518; a technique he may have abandoned as unsuited to his aesthetic of methodical, classical form.&lt;ref&gt;Cohen, Brian D. [http://artinprint.org/article/freedom-and-resistance-in-the-act-of-engraving-or-why-durer-gave-up-on-etching/ &quot;Freedom and Resistance in the Act of Engraving (or, Why Dürer Gave up on Etching),&quot;] ''Art in Print'' Vol. 7 No. 3 (September–October 2017).&lt;/ref&gt;

====Patronage of Maximilian I====
[[File:Albrecht Dürer - Portrait of Maximilian I - Google Art Project.jpg|thumb|''Portrait of Maximilian I'']]

From 1512, [[Maximilian I, Holy Roman Emperor|Maximilian I]] became Dürer's major patron. His commissions included ''[[The Triumphal Arch]]'', a vast work printed from 192 separate blocks, the symbolism of which is partly informed by Pirckheimer's translation of [[Horapollo]]'s ''Hieroglyphica''. The design program and explanations were devised by [[Johannes Stabius]], the architectural design by the master builder and court-painter Jörg Kölderer and the woodcutting itself by Hieronymous Andreae, with Dürer as designer-in-chief. ''The Arch'' was followed by ''[[The Triumphal Procession]]'', the program of which was worked out in 1512 by [[:de:Marx Treitzsaurwein|Marx Treitz-Saurwein]] and includes woodcuts by [[Albrecht Altdorfer]] and [[Hans Springinklee]], as well as Dürer.

Dürer worked with pen on the marginal images for an edition of the Emperor's printed Prayer-Book; these were quite unknown until facsimiles were published in 1808 as part of the first book published in [[lithography]]. Dürer's work on the book was halted for an unknown reason, and the decoration was continued by artists including [[Lucas Cranach the Elder]] and [[Hans Baldung]]. Dürer also made several portraits of the Emperor, including one shortly before Maximilian's death in 1519.

===Journey to the Netherlands (1520–1521)===
[[File:Bezoek van Albrecht Dürer in Antwerpen in 1520, Henri Leys, 1855, Koninklijk Museum voor Schone Kunsten Antwerpen, 2198.jpg|thumb|400px|Visit of Albrecht Dürer in Antwerp in 1520, [[Jan August Hendrik Leys]], 1855, [[Royal Museum of Fine Arts Antwerp]], 2198]]
Maximilian's death came at a time when Dürer was concerned he was losing &quot;my sight and freedom of hand&quot; (perhaps caused by [[arthritis]]) and increasingly affected by the writings of [[Martin Luther]].&lt;ref&gt;Bartrum, 204. Quotation from a letter to the secretary of the Elector of Saxony&lt;/ref&gt; In July 1520 Dürer made his fourth and last major journey, to renew the Imperial pension Maximilian had given him and to secure the patronage of the new emperor, [[Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor|Charles V]], who was to be crowned at [[Aachen]]. Dürer journeyed with his wife and her maid via the [[Rhine]] to [[Cologne]] and then to [[Antwerp]], where he was well received and produced numerous drawings in [[silverpoint]], chalk and charcoal. In addition to going to the coronation, he made excursions to Cologne (where he admired the painting of [[Stefan Lochner]]), [[Nijmegen]], [['s-Hertogenbosch]], [[Bruges]] (where he saw [[Michelangelo]]'s [[Madonna of Bruges]]), [[Ghent]] (where he admired [[Jan van Eyck|van Eyck]]'s altarpiece), and [[Zeeland]].

Dürer took a large stock of prints with him and wrote in his diary to whom he gave, exchanged or sold them, and for how much. This provides rare information of the monetary value placed on prints at this time. Unlike paintings, their sale was very rarely documented.&lt;ref&gt;Landau &amp; Parshall:350-54 and ''passim''&lt;/ref&gt; While providing valuable documentary evidence, Dürer's Netherlandish diary also reveals that the trip was not a profitable one. For example, Dürer offered his last portrait of Maximilian to his daughter, [[Margaret of Habsburg (1480–1530)|Margaret of Austria]], but eventually traded the picture for some white cloth after Margaret disliked the portrait and declined to accept it. During this trip he also met [[Bernard van Orley]], [[Jan Provoost]], [[Gerard Horenbout]], [[Jean Mone]], [[Joachim Patinir]] and [[Tommaso Vincidor]], though he did not, it seems, meet [[Quentin Matsys]].&lt;ref&gt;Panofsky, 209&lt;/ref&gt;

At the request of [[Christian II of Denmark]], Dürer went to Brussels to paint the King's portrait. There he saw &quot;the things which have been sent to the king from the golden land&quot;—the [[Aztec]] treasure that [[Hernán Cortés]] had sent home to Holy Roman Emperor Charles V following the fall of Mexico. Dürer wrote that this treasure &quot;was much more beautiful to me than miracles. These things are so precious that they have been valued at 100,000 [[Florin (Italian coin)|florin]]s&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartrum&quot;/&gt; Dürer also appears to have been collecting for his own [[cabinet of curiosities]], and he sent back to Nuremberg various animal horns, a piece of [[coral]], some large fish fins, and a wooden weapon from the [[East Indies]].

Having secured his pension, Dürer finally returned home in July 1521, having caught an undetermined illness—perhaps [[malaria]]&lt;ref&gt;Panofsky&lt;/ref&gt;—which afflicted him for the rest of his life, and greatly reduced his rate of work.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartrum&quot;/&gt;

===Final years in Nuremberg (1521–1528)===
[[File:Salvator Mundi, by Albrecht Dürer, MET.jpg|thumb|''Salvator Mundi'', an unfinished oil painting on wood, full painting]]

On his return to Nuremberg, Dürer worked on a number of grand projects with religious themes, including a crucifixion scene and a [[Sacra conversazione]], though neither was completed.&lt;ref&gt;Panofsky, 223&lt;/ref&gt; This may have been due in part to his declining health, but perhaps also because of the time he gave to the preparation of his theoretical works on geometry and perspective, the [[body proportions|proportions]] of men and horses, and [[fortification]].

However, one consequence of this shift in emphasis was that during the last years of his life, Dürer produced comparatively little as an artist. In painting, there was only a portrait of [[commons:File:Albrecht Dürer 078.jpg|Hieronymus Holtzschuher]], a [[commons:File:Albrecht Dürer 061.jpg|''Madonna and Child'' (1526)]], [[commons:File:Albrecht dürer salvator mundi.JPG|''Salvator Mundi '' (1526)]], and two panels showing [[John the Apostle|St. John]] with [[St. Peter]] in [[commons:File:Albrecht Dürer 026.jpg|background]] and [[Paul of Tarsus|St. Paul]] with [[Mark the Evangelist|St. Mark]] in the [[commons:File:Albrecht Dürer 027.jpg|background]]. This last great work, [[the Four Apostles]], was given by Dürer to the City of Nuremberg—although he was given 100 guilders in return.&lt;ref name=&quot;Panofsky&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Dürer Salvator Mundi detail.jpg|thumb|left|A close up reveals Dürer's highly detailed preparatory drawing|alt=|295x295px]]

As for engravings, Dürer's work was restricted to portraits and illustrations for his treatise. The portraits include Cardinal-Elector [[Albert of Mainz]]; [[Frederick the Wise]], elector of Saxony; the [[Humanism|humanist]] scholar [[Willibald Pirckheimer]]; [[Philipp Melanchthon]], and [[Desiderius Erasmus|Erasmus of Rotterdam]]. For those of [[Albert of Mainz|the Cardinal]], Melanchthon, and Dürer's final major work, a drawn portrait of the Nuremberg patrician Ulrich Starck, Dürer depicted the sitters in profile, perhaps reflecting a more mathematical approach.

Despite complaining of his lack of a formal classical education, Dürer was greatly interested in intellectual matters and learned much from his boyhood friend [[Willibald Pirckheimer]], whom he no doubt consulted on the content of many of his images.&lt;ref&gt;[[Corine Schleif]] (2010), &quot;Albrecht Dürer between Agnes Frey and Willibald Pirckheimer&quot;, ''The Essential Dürer'', ed. Larry Silver and [[Jeffrey Chipps Smith]], Philadelphia, 85–205&lt;/ref&gt; He also derived great satisfaction from his friendships and correspondence with Erasmus and other scholars. Dürer succeeded in producing two books during his lifetime. &quot;The Four Books on Measurement&quot; were published at Nuremberg in 1525 and was the first book for adults on [[mathematics]] in German,&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartrum&quot;/&gt; as well as being cited later by [[Galileo]] and [[Johannes Kepler|Kepler]]. The other, a work on city fortifications, was published in 1527. &quot;The Four Books on Human Proportion&quot; were published posthumously, shortly after his death in 1528.&lt;ref name=Mueller /&gt;

Dürer died in Nuremberg at the age of 56, leaving an estate valued at 6,874 florins – a considerable sum.  He is buried in the ''Johannisfriedhof'' cemetery. [[Albrecht Dürer's House|His large house]] (purchased in 1509 from the heirs of the astronomer [[Bernhard Walther]]), where his workshop was located and where his widow lived until her death in 1539, remains a prominent Nuremberg landmark.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartrum&quot;/&gt; It is now a museum.

====Dürer and the Reformation====
[[File:Albrecht-Dürer-Haus - Tiergärtnerplatz - Nuremberg, Germany - DSC02033.jpg|thumb|[[Albrecht Dürer's House]] in [[Nuremberg]]]]

Dürer's writings suggest that he may have been sympathetic to [[Martin Luther]]'s ideas, though it is unclear if he ever left the Catholic Church. Dürer wrote of his desire to draw Luther in his diary in 1520: &quot;And God help me that I may go to Dr. Martin Luther; thus I intend to make a portrait of him with great care and engrave him on a copper plate to create a lasting memorial of the Christian man who helped me overcome so many difficulties.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Price (2003), 225&lt;/ref&gt; In a letter to [[Nicholas Kratzer]] in 1524, Dürer wrote, &quot;because of our Christian faith we have to stand in scorn and danger, for we are reviled and called heretics&quot;. Most tellingly, [[Willibald Pirckheimer|Pirckheimer]] wrote in a letter to Johann Tscherte in 1530: &quot;I confess that in the beginning I believed in Luther, like our Albert of blessed memory ... but as anyone can see, the situation has become worse.&quot; Dürer may even have contributed to the Nuremberg City Council's mandating Lutheran sermons and services in March 1525. Notably, Dürer had contacts with various reformers, such as [[Huldrych Zwingli|Zwingli]], [[Andreas Karlstadt]], [[Philipp Melanchthon|Melanchthon]], [[Desiderius Erasmus|Erasmus]] and Cornelius Grapheus from whom Dürer received Luther's ''[[On the Babylonian Captivity of the Church|Babylonian Captivity]]'' in 1520.&lt;ref&gt;Price:225–248&lt;/ref&gt; From 1525, however, &quot;the year that saw the peak and collapse of the Peasants' War, the artist can be seen to distance himself somewhat from the [Lutheran] movement....&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Norbert Wolf, '' Albrecht Durer 1471-1528 the Genius of the German Renaissance'', (Taschen, 2006), p. 74.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Landscape with a Large Cannon MET MM7867.jpg|thumb|right|''The Cannon'', Dürer's largest etching, 1518]]

Dürer's later works have also been claimed to show [[Protestant]] sympathies. For example, his woodcut of ''[[The Last Supper]]'' of 1523 has often been understood to have an [[Evangelicalism|evangelical]] theme, focusing as it does on Christ espousing the [[Gospel]], as well the inclusion of the [[Eucharist]]ic cup, an expression of Protestant [[Utraquist|utraquism]],&lt;ref&gt;Strauss, 1981&lt;/ref&gt; although this interpretation has been questioned.&lt;ref&gt;Price:254&lt;/ref&gt; The delaying of the engraving of [[Philip the Apostle|St Philip]], completed in 1523 but not distributed until 1526, may have been due to Dürer's uneasiness with images of Saints; even if Dürer was not an [[iconoclasm|iconoclast]], in his last years he evaluated and questioned the role of art in religion.&lt;ref&gt;Harbison&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy and influence==
[[File:Albrecht Dürer - Adoration of the Trinity (Landauer Altar) - Google Art Project.jpg|thumb|''Adoration of the Trinity'' (Landauer Altar)]]
[[File:Albrecht Dürer - Feast of Rose Garlands - Google Art Project.jpg|thumb|''[[Feast of the Rosary]]'' (1506)]]
[[File:Albrecht Dürer - Adorazione dei Magi - Google Art Project.jpg|thumb|''Adoration of the Magi'' (1504), oil on wood [[Galleria degli Uffizi]], [[Florence]]]]

Dürer exerted a huge influence on the artists of succeeding generations, especially in printmaking, the medium through which his contemporaries mostly experienced his art, as his paintings were predominantly in private collections located in only a few cities. His success in spreading his reputation across Europe through prints was undoubtedly an inspiration for major artists such as Raphael, [[Titian]], and [[Parmigianino]], all of whom collaborated with printmakers in order to promote and distribute their work.

His work in [[engraving]] seems to have had an intimidating effect upon his German successors, the &quot;[[Little Masters]]&quot; who attempted few large engravings but continued Dürer's themes in small, rather cramped compositions. [[Lucas van Leyden]] was the only Northern European engraver to successfully continue to produce large engravings in the first third of the 16th century. The generation of Italian engravers who trained in the shadow of Dürer all either directly copied parts of his landscape backgrounds ([[Giulio Campagnola]], [[Giovanni Battista Palumba]], [[Benedetto Montagna]] and [[Cristofano Robetta]]), or whole prints ([[Marcantonio Raimondi]] and [[Agostino Veneziano]]). However, Dürer's influence became less dominant after 1515, when Marcantonio perfected his new engraving style, which in turn travelled over the Alps to dominate Northern engraving also.

In painting, Dürer had relatively little influence in Italy, where probably only his altarpiece in Venice was seen, and his German successors were less effective in blending German and Italian styles. His intense and self-dramatizing self-portraits have continued to have a strong influence up to the present, especially on painters in the 19th and 20th century who desired a more dramatic portrait style. Dürer has never fallen from critical favour, and there have been significant revivals of interest in his works in Germany in the ''Dürer Renaissance'' of about 1570 to 1630, in the early nineteenth century, and in German [[nationalism]] from 1870 to 1945.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartrum&quot;/&gt;

Dürer's study of human proportions and the use of transformations to a coordinate grid to demonstrate facial variation inspired similar work by [[D'Arcy Thompson]] in his book ''On Growth and Form''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Thompson, D'Arcy|year=1917|title=On Growth and Form|url=https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.74784|place=Cambridge|publisher=Cambridge University Press|pages=290–292}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1498, Dürer painted a series of self-portraits, quite possibly the first examples of an artist depicting himself. His 1507 panel paintings of ''Adam and Eve'' are the first full-size nudes in Northern European art.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Rick Steves Spain 2019|last=Steves|first=Rick|publisher=|year=2019|isbn=978-1-63121-840-8|location=|pages=458-459}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Lutheran Church]] remembers Dürer as a great Christian annually on 6 April,&lt;ref&gt;''Lutheranism 101'' edited by Scot A. Kinnaman, CPH, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; along with [[Lucas Cranach the Elder]] and [[Hans Burgkmair]]. The [[Calendar of saints (Episcopal Church in the United States of America)|liturgical calendar of the Episcopal Church (United States)]] remembers him, Cranach and [[Matthias Grünewald]] on 5 August.

==Theoretical works==

In all his theoretical works, in order to communicate his theories in the [[German language]] rather than in [[Latin]], Dürer used graphic expressions based on a [[vernacular]], craftsmen's language. For example, &quot;Schneckenlinie&quot; (&quot;snail-line&quot;) was his term for a spiral form. Thus, Dürer contributed to the expansion in German prose which [[Martin Luther]] had begun with his translation of the [[Luther Bible|Bible]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Panofsky&quot;&gt;Erwin Panofsky, ''The Life and Art of Albrecht Dürer'', Princeton, 1945, {{ISBN|0-691-00303-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Four Books on Measurement''===
{{more citations needed|section|date=May 2017}}
Dürer's work on [[geometry]] is called the ''Four Books on Measurement'' (''Underweysung der Messung mit dem Zirckel und Richtscheyt'' or ''Instructions for Measuring with [[Compass (drawing tool)|Compass]] and Ruler'').&lt;ref&gt;A. Koyre, &quot;The Exact Sciences&quot;, in ''The Beginnings of Modern Science'', edited by Rene Taton, translated by A. J. Pomerans&lt;/ref&gt; The first book focuses on linear geometry. Dürer's geometric constructions include [[helices]], [[Conchoid (mathematics)|conchoids]] and [[epicycloid]]s. He also draws on [[Apollonius of Perga|Apollonius]], and [[Johannes Werner]]'s 'Libellus super viginti duobus elementis conicis' of 1522.

The second book moves onto two-dimensional geometry, i.e. the construction of regular [[polygon]]s. Here Dürer favours the methods of [[Ptolemy]] over [[Euclid]]. The third book applies these principles of geometry to [[architecture]], [[engineering]] and [[typography]].

In architecture Dürer cites [[Vitruvius]] but elaborates his own classical designs and [[classical orders|columns]]. In [[typography]], Dürer depicts the geometric construction of the [[Latin alphabet]], relying on [[History of western typography#Classical revival|Italian precedent]]. However, his construction of the [[Gothic alphabet]] is based upon an entirely different [[modular]] system. The fourth book completes the progression of the first and second by moving to three-dimensional forms and the construction of [[Polyhedron|polyhedra]]. Here Dürer discusses the five [[Platonic solid]]s, as well as seven [[Archimedean solid|Archimedean]] semi-regular solids, as well as several of his own invention.

In all these, Dürer shows the objects as [[Net (polyhedron)|nets]]. Finally, Dürer discusses the [[Doubling the cube|Delian Problem]] and moves on to the 'construzione legittima', a method of depicting a cube in two dimensions through [[linear perspective]]. He is thought to be the first to describe a visualization technique used in modern computers, [[Ray tracing (graphics)| ray tracing]].&lt;ref name=&quot;raytracing&quot;&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; It was in [[Bologna]] that Dürer was taught (possibly by [[Luca Pacioli]] or [[Bramante]]) the principles of [[linear perspective]], and evidently became familiar with the 'costruzione legittima' in a written description of these principles found only, at this time, in the unpublished treatise of [[Piero della Francesca]]. He was also familiar with the 'abbreviated construction' as described by Alberti and the geometrical construction of shadows, a technique of [[Leonardo da Vinci]]. Although Dürer made no innovations in these areas, he is notable as the first Northern European to treat matters of visual representation in a scientific way, and with understanding of Euclidean principles. In addition to these geometrical constructions, Dürer discusses in this last book of ''Underweysung der Messung'' an assortment of mechanisms for drawing in perspective from models and provides woodcut illustrations of these methods that are often reproduced in discussions of perspective.

===''Four Books on Human Proportion''===
[[File:Dürer - Vier Bücher von menschlicher Proportion ita., 1594 - 168613 Illustrazione 3v.jpg|thumb|Illustration from the ''Four Books on Human Proportion'']]

Dürer's work on [[body proportions|human proportions]] is called the ''Four Books on Human Proportion'' (''Vier Bücher von Menschlicher Proportion'') of 1528.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://archive.org/details/hierinnsindbegri00dure|title=Hierinn sind begriffen vier Bucher von menschlicher Proportion durch Albrechten Durer von Nurerberg|last=Durer|first=Albrecht|date=1528|publisher=Hieronymus Andreae Formschneider|access-date=6 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first book was mainly composed by 1512/13 and completed by 1523, showing five differently constructed types of both male and female figures, all parts of the body expressed in fractions of the total height. Dürer based these constructions on both [[Vitruvius]] and empirical observations of &quot;two to three hundred living persons&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Panofsky&quot;/&gt; in his own words. The second book includes eight further types, broken down not into fractions but an [[Leone Battista Alberti|Albertian]] system, which Dürer probably learned from [[Francesco di Giorgio]]'s 'De harmonica mundi totius' of 1525. In the third book, Dürer gives principles by which the proportions of the figures can be modified, including the mathematical simulation of [[convex mirror|convex]] and [[concave mirror]]s; here Dürer also deals with human [[physiognomy]]. The fourth book is devoted to the theory of movement.

Appended to the last book, however, is a self-contained essay on aesthetics, which Dürer worked on between 1512 and 1528, and it is here that we learn of his theories concerning 'ideal beauty'. Dürer rejected Alberti's concept of an objective beauty, proposing a relativist notion of beauty based on variety. Nonetheless, Dürer still believed that truth was hidden within nature, and that there were rules which ordered beauty, even though he found it difficult to define the criteria for such a code. In 1512/13 his three criteria were function ('Nutz'), naïve approval ('Wohlgefallen') and the happy medium ('Mittelmass'). However, unlike Alberti and Leonardo, Dürer was most troubled by understanding not just the abstract notions of beauty but also as to how an artist can create beautiful images. Between 1512 and the final draft in 1528, Dürer's belief developed from an understanding of human creativity as spontaneous or [[artistic inspiration|inspired]] to a concept of 'selective inward synthesis'.&lt;ref name=&quot;Panofsky&quot;/&gt; In other words, that an artist builds on a wealth of visual experiences in order to imagine beautiful things. Dürer's belief in the abilities of a single artist over inspiration prompted him to assert that &quot;one man may sketch something with his pen on half a sheet of paper in one day, or may cut it into a tiny piece of wood with his little iron, and it turns out to be better and more artistic than another's work at which its author labours with the utmost diligence for a whole year&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Panofsky, 283&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;gallery widths=&quot;140px&quot; heights=&quot;140px&quot; perrow=&quot;4&quot;&gt;
File:AlbrechtDürer01.jpg|Title page of ''Vier Bücher von menschlicher Proportion'' showing the monogram signature of artist
File:Durer foot.jpg|Dürer often used [[multiview orthographic projection]]s
File:Durer face transforms.jpg|Dürer's study of human proportions
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Exhibitions==
An important exhibition runs at the [[Albertina]] in [[Vienna]] (Austria) from 20 September 2019 to 6 January 2020. The Albertina has the largest collection in the world of Dürer drawings with more than 140 works.  With loans, over 200 works will be exhibited.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Albrecht Dürer|url=https://www.albertina.at/en/exhibitions/albrecht-duerer/|website=albertina.at}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other exhibitions include: Paris Autumn-Winter 2012–13 Exhibition &quot;Albrecht Dürer and his time: From the Reformation to the Thirty Years' War&quot;, from the collection of the Beaux-arts de Paris, October 24, 2012 to January 13, 2013.  Exhibition in [[Liege]], 25 March – 21 May 2011, based on the collections of the [[University of Liege]].  The question of copies is also raised through a selection of engravings made by anonymous artists or by [[copyist]]s such as [[Marcantonio Raimondi]] (1480–1534).

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery widths=&quot;168&quot; heights=&quot;200&quot; perrow=&quot;4&quot; caption=&quot;Paintings&quot;&gt;
File:Albrecht Dürer - Ritratto del padre - Google Art Project.jpg|''[[Portrait Diptych of Dürer's Parents|Albrecht Dürer the Elder with a Rosary]]'', 1490, [[Uffizi|Galleria degli Uffizi]], [[Florence]]
File:Albrecht Dürer 012.jpg|''St Jerome in the Wilderness'', 1495, oil on panel, [[National Gallery]], London
File:Madonna Haller.jpg|Detail, ''[[Haller Madonna]]'', 1505, [[National Gallery]]
File:Albrecht Dürer - Virgin and child with a pear - Google Art Project.jpg|''Madonna of the Pear'', 1512, oil on panel, [[Kunsthistorisches Museum]]
File:Albrecht Dürer - Portrait of Bernhard von Reesen - Google Art Project.jpg|''Portrait of Bernhard von Reesen'', 1521, [[Kunsthistorisches Museum]], [[Gemäldegalerie]]
File:Albrecht Dürer Saint Jerome 1521.jpg|''Saint Jerome'', 1521, [[Museu Nacional de Arte Antiga]], [[Lisbon]]
File:Albrecht Dürer 078.jpg|''Portrait of Hieronymus Holzschuher'', 1526
&lt;/gallery&gt;

&lt;gallery widths=&quot;168px&quot; heights=&quot;168px&quot; perrow=&quot;4&quot; caption=&quot;Watercolours&quot;&gt;
File:Innsbruck castle courtyard.jpg|''Innsbruck Castle Courtyard'', 1494, Gouache and watercolour on paper
File:Chateau-fort-Durer.jpg|Castle Segonzano, 1502, gouache and watercolour on paper
File:Albrecht Dürer - Hare, 1502 - Google Art Project.jpg|''[[Young Hare]]'', (1502), Watercolour and bodycolour ([[Albertina, Vienna]])
File:Albrecht Dürer - The Large Piece of Turf, 1503 - Google Art Project.jpg|''[[Great Piece of Turf]]'', 1503
File:Albrecht Dürer, Tuft of Cowslips, 1526, NGA 74162.jpg|Albrecht Dürer, Tuft of Cowslips, 1526, [[National Gallery of Art]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

&lt;gallery widths=&quot;168&quot; heights=&quot;200&quot; perrow=&quot;4&quot; caption=&quot;Drawings and engravings&quot;&gt;
File:Albrecht Dürer - The Expulsion from Paradise (NGA 1943.3.3634).jpg|''The Expulsion From Paradise'', 1510
File:Albrecht Dürer - Man of Sorrows - Google Art Project.jpg|''Man of Sorrows''
File:Albrecht Dürer - Head of an Old Man, 1521 - Google Art Project.jpg|''Head of an Old Man'', 1521
File:Albrecht Dürer - Bearing of the Cross - Google Art Project.jpg|''Bearing of the Cross''
File:Saint Christopher Facing Left MET DP815920.jpg|''St. Christopher'', [[engraving]], 1521
File:Albrecht Dürer - The Small Horse - Google Art Project.jpg|''The Small Horse''
File:Albrecht Dürer - Nemesis - Google Art Project.jpg|''Nemesis''
File:Albrecht Dürer - Bearded Saint in a Forest, c. 1516 - Google Art Project.jpg|''Bearded Saint in a Forest'', c. 1516
File:Albrecht Dürer - The Rhinoceros (NGA 1964.8.697).jpg|''[[Durer's rhinoceros|Rhinoceros]],'' 1515, [[National Gallery of Art]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==List of works==
For lists of Albrecht Dürer's works, see:
* [[List of paintings by Albrecht Dürer]]
* [[List of engravings by Dürer]]
* [[List of woodcuts by Dürer]]

==Notes==
'''Footnotes'''
{{Notelist}}

'''Citations'''
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
*Bartrum, Giulia. ''Albrecht Dürer and his Legacy''. British Museum Press, 2002. {{ISBN|0-7141-2633-0}}
*Campbell Hutchison, Jane. ''Albrecht Dürer: A Biography''. Princeton University Press, 1990. {{ISBN|0-691-00297-5}}
*Demele, Christine. ''Dürers Nacktheit – Das Weimarer Selbstbildnis.'' Rhema Verlag, Münster 2012, {{ISBN|978-3-86887-008-4}}
*Dürer, Albrecht (translated by R.T. Nichol from the Latin text), ''Of the Just Shaping of Letters'', Dover Publications. {{ISBN|0-486-21306-4}}
*Harbison, Craig. &quot;Dürer and the Reformation: The Problem of the Re-dating of the ''St. Philip'' Engraving&quot;. ''The Art Bulletin'', Vol. 58, No. 3, 368–373. September 1976.
*Korolija Fontana-Giusti, Gordana. &quot;The Unconscious and Space: Venice and the work of Albrecht Dürer&quot;, in ''Architecture and the Unconscious'', eds. J. Hendrix and L.Holm, Farnham Surrey: Ashgate, 2016. pp.&amp;nbsp;27–44,  {{ISBN|9781472456472}}.
*Koerner, Joseph Leo. The Moment of Self-Portraiture in German Renaissance Art. Chicago/London: University of Chicago Press, 1993.
*Landau David; Parshall, Peter. ''The Renaissance Print''. Yale, 1996. {{ISBN|0-300-06883-2}}
*Panofsky, Erwin. ''The Life and Art of Albrecht Dürer'', Princeton, 2005. {{ISBN|9780691122762}}
*Price, David Hotchkiss.  ''Albrecht Dürer's Renaissance: Humanism, Reformation and the Art of Faith''. Michigan, 2003. {{ISBN|9780472113439}}.
*Strauss, Walter L. (ed.). ''The Complete Engravings, Etchings and Drypoints of Albrecht Durer''. Dover Publications, 1973. {{ISBN|0-486-22851-7}}
*Wilhelm, Kurth (ed.). ''The Complete Woodcuts of Albrecht Durer'', Dover Publications, 2000. {{ISBN|0-486-21097-9}}
*Wolf, Norbert. ''Albrecht Dürer''. Prestel, 2010. {{ISBN|978-3-7913-4426-3}}

==External links==
{{sister project links|Commonscat=Albrecht Dürer|s=Author:Albrecht Dürer|wikt=no|n=no|q=Albrecht Dürer|b=no|v=no}}
* {{Britannica|174214}}
* {{cite EB1911|wstitle=Dürer,_Albrecht |volume=8 |short=x}}
*[http://www.albrecht-durer.org/ Albrecht Durer – The complete works]
*[http://www.clarkart.edu/exhibitions/durer/content/exhibition.cfm/ The Strange World of Albrecht Dürer] at the [[Sterling and Francine Clark Art Institute]]. 14 November 2010 – 13 March 2011
*[https://www.youtube.com/user/ClarkArtInstitute#g/c/E28247179CB5963C Dürer Prints Close-up]. Made to accompany The Strange World of Albrecht Dürer at the Sterling and Francine Clark Art Institute. 14 November 2010 – 13 March 2011
*[https://www.nlm.nih.gov/exhibition/historicalanatomies/durer_home.html Albrecht Dürer: ''Vier Bücher von menschlicher Proportion'' (Nuremberg, 1528)]. Selected pages scanned from the original work. Historical Anatomies on the Web. [[US National Library of Medicine]].
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Albrecht Dürer |sopt=w}} 
* {{Gutenberg author | id=Albrecht+Dürer | name=Albrecht Dürer}}
* [http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/hd/durr/hd_durr.htm &quot;Albrecht Dürer (1471–1528)&quot;.] In ''Heilbrunn Timeline of Art History''. New York: The Metropolitan Museum of Art
* {{PM20|FID=pe/004307}}
* [https://www.albertina.at/en/exhibitions/albrecht-duerer Albrecht Durer, Exhibition, Albertina, Vienna]. 20 September 2019 – 6 January 2020

{{Dürer}}
{{Mathematical art|state=collapsed}}

{{Authority control|MBA=}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Durer, Albrecht}}
[[Category:Albrecht Dürer| ]]
[[Category:1471 births]]
[[Category:1528 deaths]]
[[Category:15th-century German painters]]
[[Category:16th-century German painters]]
[[Category:Animal artists]]
[[Category:Artist authors]]
[[Category:German draughtsmen]]
[[Category:German engravers]]
[[Category:German Lutherans]]
[[Category:German male painters]]
[[Category:German people of Hungarian descent]]
[[Category:German printmakers]]
[[Category:German Renaissance painters]]
[[Category:German Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Heraldic artists]]
[[Category:Manuscript illuminators]]
[[Category:Mathematical artists]]
[[Category:People celebrated in the Lutheran liturgical calendar]]
[[Category:People from Nuremberg]]
[[Category:Renaissance engravers]]
[[Category:Woodcut designers]]</text>
      <sha1>snyo90c6lrel5g5t5igpshxse9t25gl</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
