  <page>
    <title>Aurochs</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2494</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941811936</id>
      <parentid>941777640</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-20T20:47:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Iridescent</username>
        <id>937705</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Cultural significance */Cleanup and [[WP:AWB/T|typo fixing]], [[WP:AWB/T|typo(s) fixed]]: a 15th century → a 15th-century</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Distinguish|European bison}}
{{pp-pc1}}
{{short description|An extinct species of large wild cattle that inhabited Asia, Europe, and North Africa}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2017}}
{{Speciesbox
| fossil_range = From early [[Pleistocene]]&amp;nbsp;to&lt;br /&gt;1627&amp;nbsp;(wild form) resp. Present&amp;nbsp;(domestic form)
| status = EX
| status_system = IUCN3.1
| status_ref = &lt;ref name=&quot;IUCN&quot; /&gt;
| extinct = 1627
| image = Copenhagen Aurochse.jpg
| image_upright = 1.1
| image_caption = Mounted skeleton of a bull at the [[National Museum of Denmark]] in [[Copenhagen]]
| taxon = Bos primigenius
| authority = ([[Ludwig Heinrich Bojanus|Bojanus]], 1827)
| subdivision_ranks = Subspecies
| subdivision =
Wild:
*†''Bos primigenius primigenius'' &lt;small&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;(Bojanus, 1827)&lt;/small&gt;
*†''[[Bos primigenius namadicus]]'' &lt;small&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;([[Hugh Falconer|Falconer]], 1859)&lt;/small&gt;
*†''Bos primigenius africanus'' &lt;small&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;(P. Thomas, 1881)&lt;/small&gt;
domestic:
*''[[Bos primigenius taurus]]'' &lt;small&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;([[Carl Linnaeus|Linnaeus]], [[10th edition of Systema Naturae|1758]])&lt;/small&gt;
*''[[Bos primigenius indicus]]'' &lt;small&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;(Linnaeus, 1758)&lt;/small&gt;
| range_map = Bos primigenius map.jpg
| range_map_upright = 1.1
| range_map_caption = Distribution of the three subspecies
| synonyms ={{collapsible list|bullets = true|title=&lt;small&gt;List&lt;/small&gt;
|''Bos mauretanicus'' &lt;small&gt;Thomas, 1881&lt;/small&gt;
|''Bosurus minutus'' &lt;small&gt;v. D. Malsburg, 1911&lt;/small&gt;
|''Bos namadicus'' &lt;small&gt;Falconer, 1859&lt;/small&gt;
|''Bos taurus''
|''Bos indicus''
|''Bos urus''
}}
}}

The '''aurochs''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|ɔː|r|ɒ|k|s}} or {{IPAc-en|ˈ|aʊ|r|ɒ|k|s}}; pl. '''aurochs''', or rarely '''aurochsen''', '''aurochses'''), also known as '''urus''' or '''ure''' (''Bos primigenius''), is an [[extinct]] species of large wild [[cattle]] that inhabited Asia, Europe, and North Africa. It is the ancestor of domestic cattle. The species survived in Europe until 1627, when the last recorded aurochs died in the [[Jaktorów]] Forest, [[Poland]].

During the [[Neolithic Revolution]], which occurred during the early [[Holocene]], at least two aurochs [[domestication]] events occurred: one related to the [[Indian aurochs|Indian subspecies]], leading to [[zebu]] cattle, and the other one related to the Eurasian subspecies, leading to [[taurine cattle]]. Other species of wild bovines were also domesticated, namely the [[wild water buffalo]], [[gaur]], [[wild yak]] and [[banteng]]. In modern cattle, numerous breeds share characteristics of the aurochs, such as a dark colour in the bulls with a light eel stripe along the back (the cows being lighter), or a typical aurochs-like horn shape.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.petermaas.nl/extinct/speciesinfo/aurochs.htm |title=Aurochs – ''Bos primigenius'' |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |website=petermaas.nl |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090420140454/http://www.petermaas.nl/extinct/speciesinfo/aurochs.htm |archivedate=20 April 2009 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Taxonomy ==
[[File:Tur ZHerberstein pol XVIw small.jpg|thumb|left|Illustration from [[Sigismund von Herberstein]]'s book published in 1556 captioned : &quot;I am 'urus', ''{{lang|pl|tur}}'' in Polish, ''{{lang|de|aurox}}'' in German ([[dunce]]s call me [[bison]]) lit. ''(the) ignorant (ones) had given me the name (of) Bison''&quot;; Latin original: ''{{lang|la|Urus sum, polonis Tur, germanis Aurox: ignari Bisontis nomen dederant}}'']]
The aurochs was variously classified as ''Bos primigenius'', ''Bos taurus'', or, in old sources, ''Bos urus''. However, in 2003, the [[International Commission on Zoological Nomenclature]] &quot;conserved the usage of 17 specific names based on wild species, which are predated by or contemporary with those based on domestic forms&quot;,&lt;ref name=iczn&gt;{{cite web|url=http://iczn.org/content/biodiversity-studies |title=ICZN, Biodiversity Studies BZN Volume 63, Part 3, General Articles &amp; Nomenclatural Notes |publisher= |date=30 September 2006 |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt; confirming ''Bos primigenius'' for the aurochs. Taxonomists who consider domesticated cattle a subspecies of the wild aurochs should use ''B. primigenius taurus''; those who consider domesticated cattle to be a separate species may use the name ''B. taurus'', which the Commission has kept available for that purpose.&lt;ref&gt;International Commission on Zoological Nomenclature. 2003. ''Opinion 2027 (Case 3010).'' Usage of 17 specific names based on wild species which are pre-dated by or contemporary with those based on domestic animals (Lepidoptera, Osteichthyes, Mammalia): conserved. Bull.Zool.Nomencl., 60:81–84&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Etymology ===
The words aurochs, urus, and wisent have all been used [[synonym]]ously in English.&lt;ref name=ahd /&gt;&lt;ref name=mwu /&gt; But the extinct aurochs/urus is a completely separate species from the still-extant [[European bison|wisent]], also known as the European bison. The two were often confused, and some 16th-century illustrations of aurochs and wisent have hybrid features.&lt;ref name=anh /&gt; The word ''urus'' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|jʊər|ə|s}}; plural ''uri'')&lt;ref name=ahd /&gt;&lt;ref name=mwu /&gt; is a Latin word, but was borrowed into Latin from [[Germanic languages|Germanic]] (cf. [[Old English]]/[[Old High German]] ''ūr'', [[Old Norse]] ''úr'').&lt;ref name=ahd /&gt; In German, [[Old High German|OHG]] ''ūr'' &quot;primordial&quot; was compounded with ''ohso'' &quot;ox&quot;, giving ''ūrohso'', which became the early modern ''Aurochs''. The modern form is ''Auerochse''.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt;

The word ''aurochs'' was borrowed from early modern German, replacing archaic ''urochs'', also from an earlier form of German. The word is invariable in number in English, though sometimes a [[English plural#Back-formation|back-formed]] singular ''auroch'' and/or innovated plural ''aurochses'' occur.&lt;ref name=mwu /&gt; The use in English of the plural form ''{{lang|en|aurochsen}}'' is nonstandard, but mentioned in ''The Cambridge Encyclopedia of the English Language''. It is directly parallel to the German plural ''Ochsen'' (singular ''Ochse'') and recreates by analogy the same distinction as English ''ox'' (singular) and ''oxen'' (plural).&lt;ref name=crystal /&gt;

=== Evolution ===
[[File:Copenhagen Zoological Museum Aurochs bull.jpg|thumb|The Prejlerup-aurochs, a bull at the Zoological Museum in Copenhagen from 7400 BC]]
[[File:Aurochs reconstruction.jpg|thumb|Life restoration of an aurochs bull found in [[Braunschweig]], Germany]]
[[File:Indian Aurochs B p namadicus 3.jpg|thumb|Speculative life restoration of the [[Indian aurochs]] (''B. p. namadicus'')]]
During the [[Pliocene]], the colder climate caused an extension of open grassland, which led to the evolution of large grazers, such as wild bovines.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt; ''[[Bos acutifrons]]'' is an [[extinction|extinct]] species of cattle that has been suggested as an ancestor for the aurochs.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt;

The oldest aurochs remains have been dated to about 2 million years ago, in India. The Indian subspecies was the first to appear.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt; During the [[Pleistocene]], the species migrated west into the [[Middle East]] (western Asia), as well as to the east. They reached Europe about 270,000 years ago.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt; The South Asian domestic cattle, or [[zebu]], descended from [[Indian aurochs]] at the edge of the [[Thar Desert]]; the zebu is resistant to [[drought]]. Domestic [[yak]], [[gayal]], and [[Bali cattle]] do not descend from aurochs.

The first complete mitochondrial genome (16,338 [[base pairs]]) DNA sequence analysis of ''Bos primigenius'' from an archaeologically verified and exceptionally well preserved aurochs bone sample was published in 2010,&lt;ref name=&quot;Edwards 2010&quot;/&gt; followed by the publication in 2015 of the complete genome sequence of ''Bos primigenius'' using DNA isolated from a 6,750-year-old British aurochs bone.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Park|first=Stephen D. E.|last2=Magee|first2=David A.|last3=McGettigan|first3=Paul A.|last4=Teasdale|first4=Matthew D.|last5=Edwards|first5=Ceiridwen J.|last6=Lohan|first6=Amanda J.|last7=Murphy|first7=Alison|last8=Braud|first8=Martin|last9=Donoghue|first9=Mark T.|date=2015-10-26|title=Genome sequencing of the extinct Eurasian wild aurochs, Bos primigenius, illuminates the phylogeography and evolution of cattle | journal = Genome Biology|volume=16|pages=234|doi=10.1186/s13059-015-0790-2 | pmc = 4620651 | pmid = 26498365 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Further studies using the ''Bos primigenius'' whole genome sequence have identified candidate microRNA-regulated domestication genes&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Braud|first=Martin|last2=Magee|first2=David A.|last3=Park|first3=Stephen D. E.|last4=Sonstegard|first4=Tad S.|last5=Waters|first5=Sinead M.|last6=MacHugh|first6=David E.|last7=Spillane|first7=Charles|date=2017|title=Genome-Wide microRNA Binding Site Variation between Extinct Wild Aurochs and Modern Cattle Identifies Candidate microRNA-Regulated Domestication Genes | journal = Frontiers in Genetics | volume = 8 | pages = 3 | doi = 10.3389/fgene.2017.00003 | pmc = 5281612 | pmid = 28197171 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A DNA study has also suggested that the modern [[European bison]] originally developed as a prehistoric cross-breed between the aurochs and the [[steppe bison]].&lt;ref&gt;Soubrier, J.; Gower, G.; Chen, K.; Richards, S. M.; Llamas, B.; Mitchell, K. J.; Ho, S. Y. W.; Kosintsev, P.; Lee, M. S. Y.; Baryshnikov, G.; Bollongino, R.; Bover, P.; Burger, J.; Chivall, D.; Crégut-Bonnoure, E.; Decker, J. E.; Doronichev, V. B.; Douka, K.; Fordham, D. A.; Fontana, F.; Fritz, C.; Glimmerveen, J.; Golovanova, L. V.; Groves, C.; Guerreschi, A.; Haak, W.; Higham, T.; Hofman-Kamińska, E.; Immel, A.; Julien, M.-A.; Krause, J.; Krotova, O.; Langbein, F.; Larson, G.; Rohrlach, A.; Scheu, A.; Schnabel, R. D.; Taylor, J. F.; Tokarska, M.; Tosello, G.; van der Plicht, J.; van Loenen, A.; Vigne, J.-D.; Wooley, O.; Orlando, L.; Kowalczyk, R.; Shapiro, B.; Cooper, A. (18 October 2016). &quot;Early cave art and ancient DNA record the origin of European bison&quot;. Nature Communications. 7 (13158): 13158. doi:10.1038/ncomms13158. PMC 5071849. {{PMID|27754477}}. Retrieved 2016-11-26.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=https://www.adelaide.edu.au/news/news88542.html |title=The Higgs Bison - mystery species hidden in cave art |first1=Alan |last1=Cooper |first2=Julien |last2=Soubrier |first3=Robyn |last3=Mills |date=19 October 2016 |publisher=The University of Adelaide |accessdate=13 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Three wild subspecies of aurochs are recognised. Only the Eurasian subspecies survived until recent times.
* The Eurasian aurochs (''B. p. primigenius'') once ranged across the [[steppe]]s and [[taiga]]s of Europe, [[Siberia]] and Central Asia, and East Asia. It is noted as part of the [[Pleistocene megafauna]], and declined in numbers along with other megafauna species by the end of the Pleistocene. The Eurasian aurochs were domesticated into modern taurine cattle breeds around the sixth millennium BC in the Middle East, and possibly also at about the same time in the Far East. Aurochs were still widespread in Europe during the time of the [[Roman Empire]], when they were widely popular as a battle beast in [[Amphitheatre#Roman amphitheatres|Roman arenas]]. Excessive hunting began and continued until the species was nearly extinct. By the 13th century, aurochs existed only in small numbers in [[Eastern Europe]], and the hunting of aurochs became a privilege of nobles, and later royal households. The aurochs were not saved from extinction, and the last recorded live aurochs, a female, died in 1627 in the Jaktorów Forest, Poland, from natural causes. Aurochs were found to have lived on the island of [[Sicily]], having migrated via a [[land bridge]] from Italy. After the disappearance of the land bridge, Sicilian aurochs (''B. p. siciliae'') evolved to be 20% smaller than their mainland relatives due to [[insular dwarfism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt; Fossilized specimens were found in [[Japan]], possibly herded with [[steppe bison]].&lt;ref name=OushuCattle&gt;{{cite journal|author=Kurosawa Y.|title=モノが語る牛と人間の文化 -　② 岩手の牛たち|url=http://liaj.lin.gr.jp/japanese/liajnews/liaj10909.pdf|pages=29–31|publisher=[[:jp:奥州市牛の博物館|Oshu city Cattle Museum]]|journal=LIAJ News No.109|accessdate=6 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=KuzuuFossil&gt;{{cite journal|author=HASEGAWA Y.，OKUMURA Y., TATSUKAWA H.|year=2009|title=First record of Late Pleistocene Bison from the fissure deposits of the Kuzuu Limestone, Yamasuge，Sano-shi，Tochigi Prefecture，Japan|url=http://www.gmnh.pref.gunma.jp/research/no_13/bulletin13_5.pdf|publisher=Gunma Museum of Natural History and Kuzuu Fossil Museum|journal=Bull.Gunma Mus.Natu.Hist.(13)|pages=47–52|accessdate=6 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Indian aurochs]] (''B. p. namadicus'') once inhabited [[India]]. It was the first subspecies of the aurochs to appear, at 2 million years ago, and from about 9000 years ago, it was domesticated as the zebu.&lt;ref name=nap /&gt; Fossil remains indicate  wild Indian aurochs besides domesticated zebu cattle were in [[Gujarat]] and the Ganges area until about 4–5000 years ago. Remains from wild aurochs 4400 years old are clearly identified from [[Karnataka]] in [[South India]].&lt;ref name=mess /&gt;
* The [[North African aurochs]] (''B. p. africanus'') once lived in the woodland and shrubland of [[North Africa]].&lt;ref name=&quot;IUCN&quot; /&gt; It descended from aurochs populations migrating from the [[Middle East]]. The North African aurochs was morphologically very similar to the Eurasian subspecies, so this [[taxon]] may exist only in a [[biogeography|biogeographic]] sense.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt; Depictions show that North African aurochs may have had a light saddle marking on its back.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frisch&quot; /&gt; This population may have been extinct before the [[Middle Ages]].&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt;

== Description ==

The appearance of the aurochs has been reconstructed from skeletal material, historical descriptions, and contemporaneous depictions, such as [[cave painting]]s, engravings, or [[Sigismund von Herberstein]]’s illustration. The work by [[Charles Hamilton Smith]] is a copy of a painting owned by a merchant in [[Augsburg]], which may date to the 16th century. Scholars have proposed that Smith's illustration was based on a cattle/aurochs hybrid, or an aurochs-like breed.&lt;ref name=anh2 /&gt; The aurochs was depicted in prehistoric cave paintings and described in [[Julius Caesar]]'s ''[[Commentarii de Bello Gallico|The Gallic War]], Book 6, Ch. 28''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://classics.mit.edu/Caesar/gallic.6.6.html|title=The Internet Classics Archive – The Gallic Wars by Julius Caesar|website=classics.mit.edu}} Book 6, Ch. 28'' Translator. W. A. McDevitte. Translator. W. S. Bohn. 1st Edition. New York. [[Harper &amp; Brothers]]. 1869. Harper's New Classical Library&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Size ===

[[File:Aurochs skull fromberlin.jpg|thumb|right|Holocene aurochs bull skull in [[Berlin]]]]
The aurochs were one of the largest [[herbivore]]s in postglacial Europe, comparable to the wisent ([[European bison]]). The size of an aurochs appears to have varied by region; in Europe, northern populations were bigger on average than those from the south. For example, during the [[Holocene]], aurochs from Denmark and Germany had an average height at the shoulders of {{convert|155|–|180|cm|in|abbr=on}} in bulls and {{Convert|135|-|155|cm|in|abbr=on}} in cows, while aurochs populations in [[Hungary]] had bulls reaching {{convert|155|–|160|cm|in|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=kysel /&gt; The body mass of aurochs appears to have shown some variability. Some individuals were comparable in weight to the wisent and the banteng, reaching around {{convert|700|kg|lb|-1|abbr=on}}, whereas those from the Late Middle Pleistocene are estimated to have weighed up to {{convert|1500|kg|lb|-1|abbr=on}}, as much as the largest [[gaur]] (the largest extant bovid).&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt; The [[sexual dimorphism]] between bulls and cows was strongly expressed, with the cows being significantly shorter than bulls on average.

[[File:Aurochsfeatures.jpg|thumb|Restoration of the aurochs based on a bull skeleton from Lund and a cow skeleton from Cambridge, with chart of characteristic external features of the aurochs]]

=== Horns ===
Because of the massive horns, the [[frontal bones]] of aurochs were elongated and broad. The horns of the aurochs were characteristic in size, curvature, and orientation. They were curved in three directions: upwards and outwards at the base, then swinging forwards and inwards, then inwards and upwards. Aurochs horns could reach {{Convert|80|cm|in|abbr=on}} in length and between {{Convert|10|and|20|cm|in|abbr=on}} in diameter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frisch&quot; /&gt; The horns of bulls were larger, with the curvature more strongly expressed than in cows. The horns grew from the skull at a 60° angle to the muzzle, facing forwards.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt;

=== Body shape ===
The proportions and body shape of the aurochs were strikingly different from many modern cattle breeds.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt; For example, the legs were considerably longer and more slender, resulting in a shoulder height that nearly equalled the trunk length. The skull, carrying the large horns, was substantially larger and more elongated than in most cattle breeds. As in other wild bovines, the body shape of the aurochs was athletic, and especially in bulls, showed a strongly expressed neck and shoulder musculature. Therefore, the fore hand was larger than the rear, similar to the wisent, but unlike many domesticated cattle.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt; Even in carrying cows, the udder was small and hardly visible from the side; this feature is equal to that of other wild bovines.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt;
[[File:Lascaux painting.jpg|thumb|Aurochs in a [[cave painting]] in [[Lascaux]], [[France]]]]

=== Coat colour{{anchor|Coat colour}} ===
The coat colour of the aurochs can be reconstructed by using historical and contemporary depictions. In his letter to [[Conrad Gesner]] (1602), [[Anton Schneeberger]] describes the aurochs, a description that agrees with cave paintings in [[Lascaux]] and [[Chauvet Cave|Chauvet]]. Calves were born a chestnut colour. Young bulls changed their coat colour at a few months old to a very deep brown or black, with a white [[eel stripe]] running down the spine. Cows retained the reddish-brown colour. Both sexes had a light-coloured muzzle.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt; Some North African engravings show aurochs with a light-coloured &quot;saddle&quot; on the back,&lt;ref name=&quot;Frisch&quot; /&gt; but otherwise  no evidence of variation in coat colour is seen throughout its range. A passage from Mucante (1596) describes the “wild ox” as gray, but is ambiguous and may refer to the wisent. Egyptian grave paintings show cattle with a reddish-brown coat colour in both sexes, with a light saddle, but the horn shape of these suggest that they may depict domesticated cattle.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt; Remains of aurochs hair were not known until the early 1980s.&lt;ref name=doi /&gt;

=== Colour of forelocks ===
Some primitive cattle breeds display similar coat colours to the aurochs, including the black colour in bulls with a light eel stripe, a pale mouth, and similar sexual dimorphism in colour. A feature often attributed to the aurochs is blond forehead hairs. Historical descriptions tell that the aurochs had long and curly forehead hair, but none mentions a certain colour for it. Cis van Vuure (2005) says that, although the colour is present in a variety of primitive cattle breeds, it is probably a discolouration that appeared after domestication. The gene responsible for this feature has not yet been identified.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt; Zebu breeds show lightly coloured inner sides of the legs and belly, caused by the so-called zebu-tipping gene. It has not been tested if this gene is present in remains of Indian aurochs.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt;

== Behaviour and ecology ==
[[File:Long horned european wild ox.jpg|thumb|A painting by [[Heinrich Harder]] showing an aurochs fighting off a [[wolf]] pack]]
Like many bovids, aurochs formed herds for at least a part of the year. These probably did not number much more than 30. If aurochs had social behaviour similar to their descendants, social status was gained through displays and fights, in which cows engaged as well as bulls.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frisch&quot; /&gt; Indeed, aurochs bulls were reported to often have had severe fights.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt; As in other wild cattle [[ungulate]]s that form unisexual herds, considerable [[sexual dimorphism]] was expressed. Ungulates that form herds containing animals of both sexes, such as [[horse]]s, have more weakly developed sexual dimorphism.&lt;ref name=mess2 /&gt;

During the mating season, which probably took place during the late summer or early autumn,&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt; the bulls had severe fights, and evidence from the forest of Jaktorów shows these could lead to death. In autumn, aurochs fed up for the winter and got fatter and shinier than during the rest of the year, according to Schneeberger.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt; Calves were born in spring. According to Schneeberger, the calf stayed at the cow's side until it was strong enough to join and keep up with the herd on the feeding grounds.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt;

Calves were vulnerable to [[Wolf|wolves]] and, to an extent, [[bear]]s, while healthy adult aurochs probably did not have to fear these predators.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt; In prehistoric Europe, North Africa, and Asia, [[big cat]]s, such as lions and tigers, and hyenas were additional predators that probably preyed on aurochs.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt;

Historical descriptions, like Caesar's ''[[Commentarii de Bello Gallico]]'' or Schneeberger, tell that aurochs were swift and fast, and could be very aggressive. According to Schneeberger, aurochs were not concerned when a man approached, but when teased or hunted, an aurochs could get very aggressive and dangerous, and throw the teasing person into the air, as he described in a 1602 letter to Gesner.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt;

== Habitat and distribution ==
[[File:Elsbruch Saarmund.JPG|thumb|Floodplain forests like this one in Germany were the aurochs' last refuge during its final centuries of existence.]]
No consensus exists concerning the habitat of the aurochs. Van Vuure points out that throughout much of the last few thousand years European landscapes probably consisted of dense forests, and as such the aurochs were confined to open areas in marshlands along rivers.&lt;ref name=vuure/&gt; Comparisons of the ratios of certain mineral [[isotope]]s in recovered bones of aurochs from the [[Mesolithic]] with domestic cattle has shown they lived in floodplain forests or marshes, areas much wetter than in which modern domesticated cattle live.&lt;ref name=vuure/&gt;&lt;ref name=lynch /&gt; According to the author such cattle were not able to create and maintain open landscapes without the help of man.&lt;ref name=vuure/&gt; While some authors propose that the habitat selection of the aurochs was comparable to the [[African forest buffalo]], others describe the species as inhabiting open grassland and helping maintain open areas by grazing, together with other large herbivores.&lt;ref name=beutl /&gt;&lt;ref name=druke /&gt; With its [[hypsodont]] jaw, the aurochs was probably a grazer and had a food selection very similar to domesticated cattle.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt; It was not a browser like many [[deer]] species, nor a semi-intermediary feeder like the wisent.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt; Schneeberger describes that during winter, the aurochs ate twigs and acorns in addition to grasses.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt;

After the beginning of the [[Common Era]], the habitat of aurochs became more fragmented because of the steadily growing human population. During the last centuries of its existence, the aurochs was limited to remote regions in northeastern Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt;

At one point, the range of the aurochs was from Europe (excluding Ireland and northern [[Scandinavia]]), to northern Africa, the Middle East, India, and Central Asia.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=bbc /&gt; Until at least 3,000 years ago, the aurochs was also found in [[East China|eastern China]], where it is recorded at the Dingjiabao Reservoir in [[Yangyuan County]]. Most remains in China are known from the area east of 105°E, but the species has also been reported from the eastern margin of the [[Tibetan plateau]], close to the [[Heihe River]].&lt;ref name=zongg&gt;{{cite journal |last=Zong |first=G. |date=1984 |title=A record of ''Bos primigenius'' from the Quaternary of the Aba Tibetan Autonomous Region (translation by Jeremy Dehut, April 1991) |url=http://www.nau.edu/~qsp/will_downs/79.Bos.pdf |journal=Vertebrata PalAsiatica |volume=22 |issue=#3 |pages=239–245 |doi= |access-date=7 January 2020|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070927083310/http://www.nau.edu/~qsp/will_downs/79.Bos.pdf |archive-date=27 September 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In Japan, excavations in various locations, such as in [[Iwate Prefecture|Iwate]] and [[Tochigi Prefecture|Tochigi]] Prefectures, have found aurochs which may have herded with steppe bison.&lt;ref name=OushuCattle /&gt;&lt;ref name=KuzuuFossil /&gt;

== Relationship with humans ==

=== Domestication ===
[[File:Bos primigenius Vig uroksen.jpg|thumb|left|The Vig-aurochs, one of two very well-preserved aurochs skeletons found in Denmark. The circles indicate where the animal was wounded by arrows.]]
[[File:Texas Longhorn cow.jpg|thumb|Genetic analyses show that the [[Texas Longhorn]] breed of cattle originated from a hybrid between an Iberian breed of domesticated wild aurochs from the Middle East and domesticated [[Indian aurochs]].]]

The aurochs, which ranged throughout much of [[Eurasia]] and [[Northern Africa]] during the [[late Pleistocene]] and early [[Holocene]], is the wild ancestor of modern cattle. Archaeological evidence shows that domestication occurred independently in the [[Near East]] and the [[Indian subcontinent]] between 10,000 and 8,000 years ago, giving rise to the two major domestic taxa observed today: humpless ''[[Bos taurus]]'' (taurine) and humped ''[[Bos indicus]]'' (zebu), respectively. This is confirmed by genetic analyses of matrilineal [[mitochondrial DNA]] sequences, which reveal a marked differentiation between modern ''B. taurus'' and ''B. indicus'' [[haplotype]]s, demonstrating their derivation from two geographically and genetically divergent wild populations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Edwards 2010&quot; /&gt;
&lt;ref name=Beja2006&gt;{{cite journal |last=Beja-Pereira |first=Albano |last2=Caramelli |first2=David |last3=Lalueza-Fox |first3=Carles |last4=Vernesi |first4=Cristiano |last5=Ferrand |first5=Nuno |last6=Casoli |first6=Antonella |last7=Goyache |first7=Felix |last8=Royo |first8=Luis J. |last9=Conti |first9=Serena |last10=Lari |first10=Martina |last11=Martini |first11=Andrea |last12=Ouragh |first12=Lahousine |last13=Magid |first13=Ayed |last14=Atash |first14=Abdulkarim |last15=Zsolnai |first15=Attila |last16=Boscato |first16=Paolo |last17=Triantaphylidis |first17=Costas |last18=Ploumi |first18=Konstantoula |last19=Sineo |first19=Luca |last20=Mallegni |first20=Francesco |last21=Taberlet |first21=Pierre |last22=Erhardt |first22=Georg |last23=Sampietro |first23=Lourdes |last24=Bertranpetit |first24=Jaume |last25=Barbujani |first25=Guido |last26=Luikart |first26=Gordon |last27=Bertorelle |first27=Giorgio |date=June 2006 |title=The origin of European cattle: Evidence from modern and ancient DNA |url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/7090141 |journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America |volume=103 |issue=21 |pages=8113–8118 |pmid=16690747 |pmc=1472438 |doi=10.1073/pnas.0509210103}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other possible domestication events may have occurred, the [[sanga cattle]], a zebu-like cattle breed with no back hump, is commonly believed to originate from crosses between humped zebus with taurine cattle breeds. However, a 1991 study examining the remains of domestic taurine cattle from Egypt from the third millennium theorised that sanga were domesticated independently in Africa and that bloodlines of taurine and zebu cattle were introduced only within the last few hundreds years, based on the similarity of the bones.&lt;ref name=grigson1991&gt;{{cite journal |title=An African origin for African cattle? — some archaeological evidence |last=Grigson |first=Caroline |year=1991 |journal=African Archaeological Review |volume=9 |issue=1 |pages=119–144 |doi=10.1007/BF01117218}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, a 1996 study of cow genetics indicates this is highly unlikely.&lt;ref name=Bradley1996&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Bradley | first1 = DG | last2 = MacHugh | first2 = DE | last3 = Cunningham | first3 = P | last4 = Loftus | first4 = RT | year = 1996 | title = Mitochondrial diversity and the origins of African and European cattle | url = | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 93 | issue = 10| pages = 5131–5 | doi=10.1073/pnas.93.10.5131| pmid = 8643540 | pmc = 39419 | bibcode = 1996PNAS...93.5131B }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

An number of [[mitochondrial DNA]] studies, most recently from the 2010s, suggest that all domesticated taurine cattle originated from about 80 wild female aurochs in the Near East.&lt;ref name=nosource2 /&gt;&lt;ref name=oxfj /&gt; Domestication of the aurochs began in the southern [[Caucasus]] and northern [[Mesopotamia]] from about the sixth millennium BC.&lt;ref name=Bradley1996/&gt; Domesticated cattle and aurochs are so different in size that they have been regarded as separate species; however, large ancient cattle and aurochs have more similar morphological characteristics, with significant differences only in the horns and some parts of the cranium.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=Beja2006/&gt;

Aurochs were independently domesticated in India. Indian zebu, although domesticated eight to 10 thousand years ago, are related to aurochs that diverged from the Near Eastern ones some 200,000 years ago. African cattle are thought to have descended from aurochs more closely related to the Near Eastern ones. The Near Eastern and African aurochs groups are thought to have split some 25,000 years ago, probably 15,000 years before domestication.&lt;ref name=Bradley1996/&gt;

[[File:Ur-painting.jpg|thumb|Charles Hamilton Smith's copy of a painting possibly dating to the 16th century]]

Aurochs became extinct in Britain during the [[Bronze Age]], and analysis of bones from aurochs that lived about the same time as domesticated cattle has suggested no genetic contribution to modern breeds.&lt;ref name=Park&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Park|first1=Stephen D E|last2=Magee|first2=David A.|last3=McGettigan|first3=Paul A.|last4=Teasdale|first4=Matthew D.|last5=Edwards|first5=Ceiridwen J.|last6=Lohan|first6=Amanda J.|last7=Murphy|first7=Alison|last8=Braud|first8=Martin|last9=Donoghue|first9=Mark T.|last10=Liu|first10=Yuan|last11=Chamberlain|first11=Andrew T.|last12=Rue-Albrecht|first12=Kévin|last13=Schroeder|first13=Steven|last14=Spillane|first14=Charles|last15=Tai|first15=Shuaishuai|last16=Bradley|first16=Daniel G.|last17=Sonstegard|first17=Tad S.|last18=Loftus|first18=Brendan J.|last19=MacHugh|first19=David E.|title=Genome sequencing of the extinct Eurasian wild aurochs, ''Bos primigenius'', illuminates the phylogeography and evolution of cattle|journal=Genome Biology|date=26 October 2015|volume=16|issue=1|doi=10.1186/s13059-015-0790-2|pmid=26498365|pmc=4620651}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some older studies dispute this. One study has pointed to possible [[introgression]] of local aurochs into the &quot;[[Turano-Mongolian]]&quot; type of cattle now found in northern China, Mongolia, Korea and Japan,&lt;ref name=&quot;Mannen2004&quot; /&gt; another found small introgression into local Italian breeds,&lt;ref name=Beja2006/&gt; with a later study finding similar results in indigenous British and Irish cattle [[landrace]]s. In this last study, researchers mapped the draft genome of a British aurochs dated to 6,750 years before present and compared it to the genomes of 73 modern cattle populations and found that traditional or cattle breeds of Scottish, Irish, Welsh, and English origin – such as Highland, Dexter, [[Kerry cattle|Kerry]], Welsh Black, and White Park, had more genetic similarity to the aurochs in question than other populations.&lt;ref name=Park/&gt; Another study concluded that because of this genomic introgression of the aurochs into these breeds, if this reflects &quot;the bigger picture across the aurochs/cattle range, perhaps several subpopulations of aurochs are not extinct at all.&quot;&lt;ref name=sinding2016&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.5334/oq.25|title=The Draft Genome of Extinct European Aurochs and its Implications for De-Extinction|journal=Open Quaternary|volume=2|year=2016|last1=Sinding|first1=Mikkel-Holger S.|last2=Gilbert|first2=M. Thomas P.|url=http://www.openquaternary.com/jms/article/download/oq.25/37}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Canelle et Elina de la Ganne.JPG|thumb|[[Highland cattle]] – their genome may have been secondarily [[Introgression|introgressed]] by European aurochs.]]

=== Extinction ===
[[File:Hunting horn of Sigismund III of Poland.jpg|thumb|The ornamented horn of the last aurochs bull that belonged to King [[Sigismund III of Poland]]]]
[[File:Jaktorow pomnik tura.jpg|thumb|left|The inscription reads: &quot;The Aurochs – Bos primigenius bojanus, the ancestor of domestic cattle, lived in this forest Jaktorów until the year 1627.&quot;]]
By the time of [[Herodotus]] (5th century BC), aurochs had disappeared from southern [[Greece]], but remained common in the area north and east of the Echedorus River close to modern [[Thessaloniki]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;&quot;Ηρόδοτος&quot; 5th century BC: Πολύμνια.&lt;/ref&gt; The last reports of the species in the southern tip of the [[Balkans]] date to the 1st century BC, when [[Varro]] reported that fierce wild oxen lived in Dardania (southern [[Serbia]]) and [[Thrace]].&lt;ref&gt;Kitchell, K.F. 2013: Animals in the Ancient Word from A to Z.&lt;/ref&gt;  By the 13th century AD, the aurochs' range was restricted to [[Poland]], [[Lithuania]], [[Moldavia]], [[Transylvania]], and [[East Prussia]]. Archeological data indicate that they survived in [[Bulgaria]], in the northeastern part of the country and around Sofia, until the 16th - 17th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Boev|first=Z.|year=2016|title=Subfossil Vertebrate Fauna from Forum Serdica (Sofia, Bulgaria), 16-18th Century AD|journal=Acta Zoologica Bulgarica|volume=68|issue=3|pages=415–424|url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/308747936}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Poland, the right to hunt large animals on any land was restricted first to nobles, and then gradually, to only the royal households. As the population of aurochs declined, hunting ceased altogether. The Polish Royal Family used gamekeepers to provide open fields for grazing for the aurochs, exempting them from local taxes in exchange for their service. [[Poaching]] aurochs was made a crime punishable by death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Newman |first1=Lenore |title=Lost feast: Culinary extinction and the future of food |publisher=ECW Press |location=Toronto |pages=66–67}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to a Polish royal survey in 1564, the gamekeepers knew of 38 animals. The last recorded live aurochs, a female, died in 1627 in the Jaktorów Forest, Poland, from natural causes. The causes of extinction were unrestricted hunting, a narrowing of habitat due to the development of farming, and diseases transmitted by domesticated cattle.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=rokosz /&gt;

== Breeding of aurochs-like cattle ==

While all the wild subspecies are extinct, ''B. primigenius'' lives on in domesticated cattle, and attempts are being made to breed similar types suitable for filling the extinct subspecies' role in the former ecosystem.

The idea of breeding back the aurochs was first proposed in the 19th century by [[Feliks Paweł Jarocki]].&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt; In the 1920s, a first attempt was undertaken by the Heck brothers in Germany with the aim of breeding an effigy (a look-alike) of the aurochs. Starting in the 1990s [[Conservation grazing|grazing]] and [[Rewilding (conservation biology)|rewilding projects]] brought new impetus to the idea and new breeding-back efforts came underway, this time with the aim of recreating an animal not only with the looks, but also with the behaviour and the ecological impact of the aurochs, to be able to fill the ecological role of the aurochs.

The drive behind reintroduction efforts of the aurochs is largely motivated by a belief that an aesthetically pleasing open park-like landscape is &quot;natural&quot;.&lt;ref name=RE-1 /&gt; The former natural European landscapes probably consisted of dense forests, with the aurochs being confined to open areas in marshlands along rivers. Research into the impact of large [[herbivores]] on forest growth has concluded that large herbivores are only able to create and maintain an open park-like landscape with the help of man.&lt;ref name=vuure/&gt; [[Grazing]] behaviour by livestock alters the landscape, which one organisation promotes as &quot;natural grazing&quot; (also called [[conservation grazing]]). The [[Rewilding Europe]] foundation advocates for &quot;returning&quot; lands to their &quot;natural state&quot; and believes that, without grazing, everything becomes forest.&lt;ref name=RE-1 /&gt; According to one theory, &quot;mosaic landscapes&quot; and gradients between different environments, from open soil to grassland, are important for [[biodiversity]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Monks&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last1=Monks |first1=Kieron |title=The wild, extinct supercow returning to Europe |url=https://www.cnn.com/2017/01/09/world/auroch-rewilding/index.html |website=cnn |publisher=CNN |accessdate=30 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Hausrindlainz.jpg|thumb|[[Heck cattle]]: the first attempt to breed a look-alike from modern cattle from the 1920s]]

Approaches that aim to breed an aurochs-like [[phenotype]] do not equate to an aurochs-like [[genotype]]. One study proposed that using the mapped out genomes of prehistoric specimens it will be possible to [[breeding back|breed back]] cattle &quot;that are genetically akin to specific original aurochs populations, through selective cross-breeding of local cattle breeds bearing local aurochs-genome ancestry.&quot;&lt;ref name=sinding2016/&gt;

=== Heck cattle ===

{{Main|Heck cattle}}
In the early 1920s, two German zoo directors (in [[Berlin]] and [[Munich]]), the brothers [[Heinz Heck|Heinz]] and [[Lutz Heck]], began a [[selective breeding]] program to breed back the aurochs into existence from the descendant domesticated cattle. Their plan was based on the concept that a species is not extinct as long as all its genes are still present in a living population.&lt;ref name=doi5 /&gt; The result is the breed called [[Heck cattle]]. According to van Vuure, it bears little resemblance to what is known about the appearance of the aurochs.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt;

=== Taurus Project ===

{{Main|Taurus cattle}}
The ''Arbeitsgemeinschaft Biologischer Umweltschutz'', a conservation group in Germany, started to crossbreed Heck cattle with southern-European primitive breeds in 1996, with the goal of increasing the aurochs-likeness of certain Heck cattle herds. These crossbreeds are called Taurus cattle. It is intended to bring in aurochs-like features that are supposedly missing in Heck cattle using [[Sayaguesa Cattle]] and [[Chianina]], and to a lesser extent [[Spanish Fighting Bull|Spanish Fighting Cattle]] (Lidia). The same breeding program is being carried out in Latvia,&lt;ref name=&quot;økologisk erstatning 2005&quot; /&gt; in [[Lille Vildmose#Project Aurochs|Lille Vildmose National Park]] in Denmark, and in the Hungarian [[Hortobágy National Park]]. The program in [[Hortobágy National Park|Hungary]] also includes [[Hungarian Grey cattle]] and [[Ankole-Watusi|Watusi]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Status rapport 2003–2010&quot; /&gt;

=== Tauros Programme ===

[[File:Tauros bull Manolo.JPG|thumb|First-generation cross bull from [[Tauros Programme]]]]
{{Main|Tauros Programme}}
The Dutch-based Tauros Programme,&lt;ref name=sticht /&gt; (initially TaurOs Project) is trying to DNA-sequence breeds of primitive cattle to find gene sequences that match those found in &quot;ancient DNA&quot; from aurochs samples. The modern cattle would be selectively bred to try to produce the aurochs-type genes in a single animal.&lt;ref name=time /&gt; Starting around 2007&lt;!--precise year?--&gt;, Tauros Programme selected a number of primitive breeds mainly from Iberia and Italy, such as [[Sayaguesa|Sayaguesa cattle]], [[Maremmana|Maremmana primitivo]], [[Pajuna cattle]], [[Limia cattle]], [[Maronesa|Maronesa cattle]], [[Tudanca cattle]], and others, which already bear considerable resemblance to the aurochs in certain features. Tauros Programme started collaborations with [[Rewilding Europe]]&lt;ref name=RE-1 /&gt;&lt;ref name=RE-2 /&gt; and [[European Wildlife]],&lt;ref name=EW-1 /&gt;&lt;ref name=EW-2 /&gt; two European organizations for ecological restoration and rewilding, and now has breeding herds not only in the Netherlands but also in Portugal, Croatia, Romania, and the Czech Republic. Numerous crossbred calves of the first, second, and third offspring generations have already been born.&lt;ref name=sticht2 /&gt; An ecologist working on the Tauros programme has estimated it will take 7 generations for the project to achieve its aims, possibly by 2025.&lt;ref name=&quot;Monks&quot;/&gt;

=== Uruz Project ===

{{Main|Uruz Project}}
Another back-breeding effort, the Uruz project, was started in 2013 by the True Nature Foundation, an organization for ecological restoration and rewilding.&lt;ref name=kjpr /&gt; It differs from the other projects in that it is planning to make use of genome editing.&lt;ref name=truen /&gt;&lt;ref name=tnf2 /&gt; In 2013 it planned to use either Sayaguesa, Maremmana primitive, Hungarian Grey (Steppe) cattle, [[Texas Longhorn]] with wild-type colour or [[Barrosã cattle]].&lt;ref name=melk /&gt;

=== Auerrind Project ===

Another back-breeding effort, the ''Auerrindprojekt'',&lt;ref name=auerrind0 /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lorsch Abbey&quot;&gt;Lorsch Abbey website: [http://www.kloster-lorsch.de/en/lauresham0/auerrinder/ “The Aurcattle project.”] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170518082753/http://www.kloster-lorsch.de/en/lauresham0/auerrinder/ |date=18 May 2017 }} Retrieved 5 June 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; was started in 2015 as a conjoined effort&lt;ref name=auerrind1 /&gt; of the Experimentalarchäologisches Freilichtlabor Lauresham (run by [[Lorsch Abbey]]),&lt;ref name=eaoall /&gt; the Förderkreis Große Pflanzenfresser im Kreis Bergstraße e.V.&lt;ref name=megaherbs0 /&gt; and the Landschaftspflegebetrieb Hohmeyer.&lt;ref name=hohmeyer0 /&gt; The five breeds used include [[Ankole-Watusi|Watusi]], [[Chianina]], [[Sayaguesa]], [[Maremmana]] and [[Hungarian Grey cattle]]. The project will not use Heck cattle as they have been deemed too genetically dissimilar to the extinct Aurochs, and it will not use any fighting breeds of cattle, because the breeders prefer to create a docile type of cattle.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.gulf-times.com/story/580791/Scientists-work-to-bring-back-the-aurochs-or-somet Gulf Times - Scientists Work to Bring Back the Aurochs, or something like it]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Other projects ===

Scientists of the Polish Foundation for Recreating the Aurochs (PFOT) in Poland hope to use DNA from bones in museums to recreate the aurochs. They plan to return this animal to the forests of Poland. The project has gained the support of the [[Ministry of Environment (Poland)|Polish Ministry of the Environment]]. They plan research on ancient preserved DNA. Polish scientists [[Ryszard Słomski]] and Jacek A. Modliński believe that modern genetics and biotechnology make it possible to recreate an animal similar to the aurochs.&lt;ref name=nauka /&gt;{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}&lt;!-- This is only a press release: need a proper ref. --&gt;

== Cultural significance ==
{{See also|Bull (mythology)}}
[[File:Grotta del romito2H.JPG|thumb|left|Cro-Magnon graffito of ''Bos primigenius'' in ''Grotta del Romito'', [[Papasidero]], Italy]]
[[File:Chauvet´s cave horses.jpg|thumb|left|Replica of [[Chauvet cave]] art depicting aurochs, [[woolly rhino]], and [[wild horse]]s]]
The aurochs was an important game animal appearing in both Paleolithic European and Mesopotamian [[cave painting]]s, such as those found at [[Lascaux]] and [[Livernon]] in France.{{fact|date=January 2020}} An archaeological excavation in Israel found traces of a feast held by the [[Natufian]] culture around 12,000 [[Before Present|B.P.]], in which three aurochs (and numerous tortoises) were eaten, this appears to be an uncommon occurrence in the culture and was held in conjunction with the burial of an older woman, presumably of some social status.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Munro |first=Natalie D. |last2=Grosman |first2=Leore |date=31 August 2010 |title=Early evidence (ca. 12,000 B.P.) for feasting at a burial cave in Israel |journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America |volume=107 |issue=35 |pages=15362–15366 |doi=10.1073/pnas.1001809107 |pmid=20805510 |pmc=2932561 |bibcode=2010PNAS..10715362M }}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2012 archaeological mission in [[Sidon]], Lebanon, discovered the remains numerous animal species, including an aurochs, and a few human bones and plant foods, dating from around 3700 B.P., which appear to have been buried together in some sort of necropolis.&lt;ref name=leorient /&gt; A 1999 archaeological dig in [[Peterborough]], England, uncovered the skull of an aurochs. The front part of the skull had been removed, but the horns remained attached. The supposition is that the killing of the aurochs in this instance was a sacrificial act.{{fact|date=January 2020}}
[[File:Gold cup Vafio 1500 to 1450 BC, NAMA 1758 080866.jpg|thumb|The violent cup of [[Vaphio]] showing aurochs hunting, Greece, (15th century B.C.)]]
[[File:Mural from Çatalhöyük excavated by James Mellaart showing neolithic hunters attacking an aurochs (Bos primigenius)..jpg|thumb|right|Mural from [[Çatalhöyük]] excavated by [[James Mellaart]] showing Neolithic hunters attacking an aurochs]]

[[File:Mecklenburg Arms.svg|thumb|right|upright|An aurochs bull used in [[heraldry]]: [[Coat of arms]] of [[Mecklenburg]] region, Germany]]
Also during antiquity, the aurochs was regarded as an animal of cultural value. Aurochs are depicted on the [[Ishtar Gate]].{{fact|date=January 2020}} In the [[Peloponnese]] there is a 15th-century B.C. depiction on the so-called violent cup of [[Vaphio]], of hunters trying to capture with nets three wild bulls being probably aurochs,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Ajmone-Marsan | first1 = P. | last2 = Garcia | first2 = J.F. | last3 = Lenstra | first3 = J.A. | year = 2010 | title = On the Origin of Cattle: How Aurochs Became Cattle and Colonized the World | url = | journal = Evolutionary Anthropology | volume = 19 | issue = #4| pages = 148–157 | doi=10.1002/evan.20267}}&lt;/ref&gt; in a possibly [[Cretan date palm]] stand. The one of the bulls throws one hunter on the ground while attacking the second with its horns. The cup despite the older perception of being [[Minoan]] seems to be [[Mycenaean Greece|Mycenaean]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Davis | first1 = E.N. | year = 1974 | title = The Vapheio Cups: One Minoan and One Mycenean? | url = | journal = The Art Bulletin | volume = 56 | issue = 4| pages = 472–487 | doi=10.1080/00043079.1974.10789932}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = De Grummond | first1 = W.W. | year = 1980 | title = Hands and Tails on the Vapheio Cups | url = | journal = American Journal of Archaeology | volume = 84 | issue = #3| pages = 335–337 | doi=10.2307/504710| jstor = 504710 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Greeks]] and [[Paeonians]] were hunting aurochs (wild oxen/bulls) and used their huge horns as trophies, cups for wine, and offers to the gods and heroes. For example, according to Douglas (1927), the ox, mentioned by Samus, Philippus of Thessalonica and [[Antipater]], killed by [[Philip V of Macedon]] on the foothills of mountain [[Orvilos]], was actually an aurochs; Philip offered the horns which were 105&amp;nbsp;cm long and the skin to a temple of [[Hercules]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Douglas, N. 1927: Birds and Beasts of the Greek Anthology. Florence.&lt;/ref&gt;

They survived in the wild in Europe till late in the [[Roman Empire]] and in 1847 were believed to be occasionally captured and exhibited in shows (''[[venatio]]nes'') in [[Roman amphitheatre]]s such as the [[colosseum]].&lt;ref&gt;''The National Cyclopaedia of Useful Knowledge'', Vol III, (1847), London, Charles Knight, p.368.&lt;/ref&gt; Aurochs horns were often used by Romans as hunting horns.{{fact|date=January 2020}} [[Julius Caesar]] described aurochs in [[Gaul]]:
{{quote|...&amp;nbsp;those animals which are called uri. These are a little below the elephant in size, and of the appearance, colour, and shape of a bull. Their strength and speed are extraordinary; they spare neither man nor wild beast which they have espied. These the Germans take with much pains in pits and kill them. The young men harden themselves with this exercise, and practice themselves in this sort of hunting, and those who have slain the greatest number of them, having produced the horns in public, to serve as evidence, receive great praise. But not even when taken very young can they be rendered familiar to men and tamed. The size, shape, and appearance of their horns differ much from the horns of our oxen. These they anxiously seek after, and bind at the tips with silver, and use as cups at their most sumptuous entertainments.|source= [[Julius Caesar]]. ''[[Commentarii de Bello Gallico|Gallic War Commentaries]]'', Chapter&amp;nbsp;6.28|}} 

The [[Hebrew Bible]] contains numerous references to the untameable strength of the ''[[re'em]]'',&lt;ref name=bible /&gt; translated as &quot;bullock&quot; or &quot;wild-ox&quot; in Jewish translations and translated rather poorly in the [[King James Version]] as &quot;[[unicorn]]&quot;, but recognized from the last century by Hebrew scholars as the aurochs.&lt;ref name=comments /&gt;&lt;ref name=biblecyc /&gt;

When the aurochs became rarer, hunting it became a privilege of the [[nobility]] and a sign of a high social status. The &quot;[[Nibelungenlied]]&quot; describes [[Sigurd|Siegfried]] killing aurochs: &quot;''Dar nâch sluoc er schiere einen wisent und einen elch / starker ûwer viere und einen grimmen schelch''&quot; (Nibelungenlied 937.1-2),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Das Nibelungenlied und die Klage: Nach der Handschrift 857 der Stiftsbibliothek St. Gallen |editor-last=Heinzle |editor-first=Joachim |publisher=Deutscher Klassiker |year=2013 |page=300}}&lt;/ref&gt; meaning &quot;After that, he quickly defeated one wisent and one elk, four strong aurochs, and one terrible schelch.&quot;{{efn|The meaning of ''schelch'' is uncertain. Suggestions include the bull [[moose]], the [[Irish elk]], the [[wild horse]], or the [[Eurasian lynx]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Das Nibelungenlied und die Klage: Nach der Handschrift 857 der Stiftsbibliothek St. Gallen |editor-last=Heinzle |editor-first=Joachim |publisher=Deutscher Klassiker |year=2013 |page=1247}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} Aurochs horns were commonly used as drinking horns by the nobility, which led to the fact that many aurochs horn sheaths are preserved today (albeit often discoloured).{{fact|date=January 2020}} The drinking horn at [[Corpus Christi College, Cambridge]], given to the college on its foundation in 1352, probably by the college's founders, the Guilds of Corpus Christi and the Blessed Virgin Mary, is thought to come from an aurochs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://theparkerlibrary.wordpress.com/2012/12/03/corpus-drinking-horn/|title=Corpus Drinking Horn|date=3 December 2012|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; A painting by [[Willem Kalf]] depicts an aurochs horn.{{fact|date=January 2020}} The horns of the last aurochs bulls, which died in 1620, were ornamented with gold and are located at the [[Livrustkammaren]] in Stockholm today.{{fact|date=January 2020}}

Schneeberger writes that aurochs were hunted with arrows, nets, and hunting dogs. With the aurochs immobilized, the curly hair on the forehead was cut from the living animal. Belts were made out of this hair and were believed to increase the fertility of women. When the aurochs was slaughtered, a cross-like bone (''os cardis'') was extracted from the heart. This bone, which is also present in domesticated cattle, contributed to the mystique of the animal and magical powers have been attributed to it.&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot; /&gt;
[[File:Moldavia's coat of Arms of 1481.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Coat of arms of Moldavia]] from 1481]]
[[File:Enichires.jpg|thumb|left|A 16th-century illustration by [[Teodoro Ghisi]], believed to show an aurochs, although the horns and muzzle differ from those of an aurochs.]]
In eastern Europe, where it survived until nearly 400 years ago, the aurochs has left traces in fixed expressions. In [[Russia]], a drunken person behaving badly was described as &quot;behaving like an aurochs&quot;, whereas in Poland, big, strong people were characterized as being &quot;a bloke like an aurochs&quot;.&lt;ref name=vuure /&gt;

In Central Europe, the aurochs features in toponyms and heraldic coats of arms. For example, the names [[Ursenbach]] and [[Aurach am Hongar]] are derived from the aurochs. An aurochs head, the traditional arms of the German region [[Mecklenburg]], figures in the [[coat of arms of Mecklenburg-Vorpommern]]. The aurochs ([[Romanian language|Romanian]] ''bour'', from Latin ''būbalus'') was also the symbol of [[Moldavia]]; nowadays, they can be found in the coat of arms of both [[Coat of arms of Romania|Romania]] and [[Coat of arms of Moldova|Moldova]]. An aurochs head is featured on an 1858 series of Moldavian stamps, the so-called [[Moldavian Bull's Heads|Bull's Heads]] (''cap de bour'' in Romanian), renowned for their rarity and price among collectors. In Romania there are still villages named [[Boureni (disambiguation)|Boureni]], after the Romanian word for the aurochs. The horn of the aurochs is a [[Charge (heraldry)|charge]] of the coat of arms of [[Tauragė]], Lithuania, (the name of Tauragė is a compound of ''taũras'' &quot;auroch&quot; and ''ragas'' &quot;horn&quot;). It is also present in the emblem of [[Kaunas]], Lithuania, and was part of the emblem of [[Bukovina]] during its time as an [[Austria-Hungary|Austro-Hungarian]] ''[[Cisleithania|Kronland]]''. The Swiss [[Canton of Uri]] is named after the aurochs; its yellow flag shows a black aurochs head.{{fact|date=January 2020}} East Slavic surnames Turenin, Turishchev, Turov, and [[Cyril of Turaw|Turovsky]] originate from the Slavic name of the species ''tur''.&lt;ref name=fedos /&gt; In [[Slovakia]],  toponyms such as [[Turany]], Turíčky, [[Turie]], Turie Pole, [[Turík]], [[Turová]] (villages), [[Turiec]] (river and region), Turská dolina (valley) and others are used. [[Turopolje]], a large lowland floodplain south of the [[Sava]] River in [[Croatia]], got its name from the aurochs (Croatian: {{lang|hr|tur}}). The ancient name of the [[Estonia]]n town of [[Rakvere]], ''Tarwanpe'' or ''Tarvanpea'', probably derives from &quot;Aurochs head&quot; (''Tarvan pea'') in ancient [[Estonian language|Estonian]].{{fact|date=January 2020}}

In 2002, a 3.5-m-high and 7.1-m-long statue of an aurochs was erected in Rakvere, Estonia, for the town's 700th birthday. The sculpture, by artist Tauno Kangro, has become a symbol of the town.&lt;ref name=rakve /&gt;

== See also ==
{{Div col}}

{{portal|Paleontology}}
* [[Lion Hunt of Ashurbanipal#Assyrian lion hunts|Ashurnasirpal II's hunting of &quot;wild oxen&quot;]]
* [[Chillingham cattle]]
* [[Ur (rune)]]
* [[American bison]] (''Bison bison'')
* [[Beefalo]]
* ''[[Bison antiquus]]'' (antique or ancient bison)
* ''[[Bison latifrons]]'' (giant bison or long-horned bison)
* ''Bison priscus'' ([[steppe bison]])
* [[Bison]]
* [[Bovid hybrid]]
* [[Domestic yak]]
* [[European bison]] (''Bison bonasus'')
* [[Gaur]]
* [[Water buffalo]]
* [[Wild water buffalo]]
* [[Wild yak]]
* [[Wood bison]] (''Bison bison athabascae'')
* [[Żubroń]]

{{colend}}

==Footnotes==
{{notelist}}

== Notes ==
This article incorporates [[Creative Commons license]] CC BY-2.5 text from reference.&lt;ref name=&quot;Edwards 2010&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Edwards | first1 = C.J. | last2 = Magee | first2 = D.A. | last3 = Park | first3 = S.D.E. | last4 = McGettigan | first4 = P.A. | last5 = Lohan | first5 = A.J. | display-authors = etal | year = 2010 | title = A Complete Mitochondrial Genome Sequence from a Mesolithic Wild Aurochs (''Bos primigenius'')&quot;. | url = | journal = [[PLoS ONE]] | volume = 5 | issue = 2| page = e9255 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pone.0009255 | pmid=20174668 | pmc=2822870| bibcode = 2010PLoSO...5.9255E }}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Reflist|33em|refs=

&lt;ref name=&quot;IUCN&quot;&gt;{{Cite iucn | author = Tikhonov, A. | title = ''Bos primigenius'' | volume = 2008 | page = e.T136721A4332142 | date = 2008 | doi = 10.2305/IUCN.UK.2008.RLTS.T136721A4332142.en | access-date = 11 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=anh&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Pyle | first1 = C. M. | title = Some late sixteenth-century depictions of the aurochs (''Bos primigenius'' Bojanus, extinct 1627): New evidence from Vatican MS Urb. Lat. 276 | doi = 10.3366/anh.1994.21.3.275 | journal = Archives of Natural History | volume = 21 | issue = 3 | pages = 275–288 | year = 1994}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=ahd&gt;American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language, 4th edition (AHD4). [[Houghton Mifflin]], 2000. Headwords ''aurochs'', ''urus'', ''wisent''&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=mwu&gt;[http://unabridged.merriam-webster.com/ Merriam-Webster Unabridged] (MWU). (Online subscription-based reference service of [[Merriam-Webster]], based on Webster's Third New International Dictionary, Unabridged. Merriam-Webster, 2002.) s.vv. &quot;aurochs&quot;, &quot;urus&quot;, &quot;wisent&quot;. Accessed 2007-06-02&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=crystal&gt;{{cite book|last=Crystal|first=David |authorlink=David Crystal |title=The Cambridge Encyclopedia of the English Language|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|year=2003 |edition=2nd |isbn=0-521-53033-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=nap&gt;{{cite book |url=http://www.nap.edu/openbook.php?record_id=12692&amp;page=96 |title=In the Light of Evolution III: Two Centuries of Darwin |year=2009 |publisher=National Academies Press |isbn= |page=96 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=mess&gt;Shanyuan Chen, Bang-Zhong Lin, Mumtaz Baig, Bikash Mitra, Ricardo J. Lopes, António M. Santos, David A. Magee, Marisa Azevedo, Pedro Tarroso, Shinji Sasazaki, Stephane Ostrowski, Osman Mahgoub, Tapas K. Chaudhuri, Ya-ping Zhang, Vânia Costa, Luis J. Royo, Félix Goyache, Gordon Luikart, Nicole Boivin, Dorian Q. Fuller, Hideyuki Mannen, Daniel G. Bradley, and Albano Beja-Pereira. &quot;Zebu Cattle Are an Exclusive Legacy of the South Asia Neolithic&quot;, ''Mol Biol Evol'' (2010) 27(1): 1-6 first published online 21 September 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=anh2&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Pyle | first1 = C. M. | title = Update to: &quot;Some late sixteenth-century depictions of the aurochs (''Bos primigenius'' Bojanus, extinct 1627): New evidence from Vatican MS Urb. Lat. 276&quot; | doi = 10.3366/anh.1995.22.3.437 | journal = Archives of Natural History | volume = 22 | issue = 3 | pages = 437–438 | year = 1995}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=kysel&gt;{{cite book |url= |title=Aurochs and potential crossbreeding with domestic cattle in Central Europe in the Eneolithic period. A metric analysis of bones from the archaeological site of Kutná Hora-Denemark (Czech Republic) |first=René |last=Kysely |year=2008 |publisher=Anthropozoologica |isbn= |page= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Frisch&quot;&gt;{{cite book |url= |title=Der Auerochs: Das europäische Rind |first=Walter |last=Frisch |year=2010 |publisher= |isbn=978-3-00-026764-2 |page= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=doi&gt;{{Cite journal
| last1 = Ryder | first1 = M. L.
| doi = 10.1016/0305-4403(84)90045-1
| title = The first hair remains from an aurochs (Bos primigenius) and some medieval domestic cattle hair
| journal = Journal of Archaeological Science
| volume = 11
| pages = 99–101
| year = 1984
| pmid = 
| pmc = 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=mess2&gt;Bunzel-Drüke, Finck, Kämmer, Luick, Reisinger, Riecken, Riedl, Scharf &amp; Zimball: ''&quot;Wilde Weiden: Praxisleitfaden für Ganzjahresbeweidung in Naturschutz und Landschaftsentwicklung''&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=beutl&gt;{{cite book |url= |title=Die Großtierfauna Europas und ihr Einfluss auf Vegetation und Landschaft |first=Axel |last=Beutler |year=1996 |publisher= |isbn= |page= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=druke&gt;{{cite book |url= |title=Der Einfluss von Großherbivoren auf die Naturlandschaft Mitteleuropas |author=Magret Bunzel-Drüke |author2=Joachim Drüke |author3=Henning Vierhaus  |last-author-amp=yes|year=2001 |publisher= |isbn= |page= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=lynch&gt;{{cite book |url= |title=Where the Wild Things Are: Aurochs and Cattle in England |author=Anthony H. Lynch Julie Hamilton |author2=Robert E. M. Hedges |last-author-amp=yes|year=2008 |publisher= |isbn= |page= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=nosource2&gt;''Molecular Biology and Evolution'', 14 March 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=oxfj&gt;{{cite web |url=http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/content/29/9/2101.full.pdf+html |title=Modern Taurine Cattle Descended from Small Number of Near-Eastern Founders |format=PDF |accessdate=23 April 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Mannen2004&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://webpages.icav.up.pt/ptdc/CVT/105223/2008/References%20for%20BigBos%20proposal%20%5BPTDC-CVT-105223-2008%5D/PDF%20files%20of%20references_max30%20%5BBigBos%5D/Mannen%20et%20al%202004_MPE-%20Independent%20origin%20of%20Northeastern%20Asian%20cattle.pdf|author=Hideyuki Mannen|title=Independent mitochondrial origin and historical genetic differentiation in North Eastern Asian cattle|publisher=Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution, Volume 32, issue 2 |pages=539–544 |date=August 2004 |accessdate=8 July 2013 |display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=bbc&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/scotland/highlands_and_islands/8516598.stm | work=[[BBC News]] | first=Steven | last=McKenzie | title=Ancient giant cattle genome first | date=17 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=rokosz&gt;{{cite journal|last=Rokosz' |first=Mieczyslaw |year=1995 |title=History of the Aurochs (Bos Taurus Primigenius) in Poland |journal=Animal Genetics Resources Information |publisher=[[Food and Agriculture Organization]] |volume=16 |pages=5–12 |url=http://agtr.ilri.cgiar.org/agtrweb/Documents/Library/docs/agri16_95.pdf |doi=10.1017/s1014233900004582 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130114152435/http://agtr.ilri.cgiar.org/agtrweb/Documents/Library/docs/agri16_95.pdf |archivedate=14 January 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=doi5&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Heck |first=H. |title=The Breeding-Back of the Aurochs |doi=10.1017/S0030605300035286 |journal=Oryx |volume=1 |issue=3 |pages=117–122 |year=1951}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Status rapport 2003–2010&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aalborgkommune.dk/kultur-og-fritid/Natur/Naturomraader/Lillevildmose/Documents/Status-rapport-endelig.pdf |author=Uffe Gjøl Sørensen |title=Vildokserne ved Lille Vildmose 2003–2010. Status rapport med anbefalinger til projektets forvaltning København: UG Sørensen Consult, 2010 |publisher= |date= |accessdate=  |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20131114130052/http://www.aalborgkommune.dk/kultur-og-fritid/Natur/Naturomraader/Lillevildmose/Documents/Status-rapport-endelig.pdf|archivedate = 14 November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;økologisk erstatning 2005&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nepenthes.dk/files/Taurus_ebook.pdf |author=Margret Bunzel-Drüke |title=Projekt Taurus – En økologisk erstatning for uroksen. Translated into Danish by Karsten Thomsen. Lohne: ABU 2004; Århus: Nepenthes, 2005 |publisher= |date= |accessdate= |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20160304042100/http://www.nepenthes.dk/files/Taurus_ebook.pdf |archivedate =4 March 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=sticht&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.stichtingtaurus.nl/NIEUWS/index.php?newsPeriod=archive |title=Stichting Taurus Vee |date=2010 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110724165735/http://www.stichtingtaurus.nl/NIEUWS/index.php?newsPeriod=archive |archive-date=24 July 2011 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=time&gt;{{cite magazine|url=http://www.time.com/time/health/article/0,8599,1961918,00.html |author=Stephan Faris |title=Breeding Ancient Cattle Back from Extinction |magazine=TIME |date=12 February 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=RE-1&gt;[[Rewilding Europe]]: [https://www.rewildingeurope.com/tauros-programme/ “Tauros Programme.”] Retrieved 6 March 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=RE-2&gt;Rewilding Europe: [https://www.rewildingeurope.com/partners/rewilding-partners/ “Rewilding Partners.”] Retrieved 6 March 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=EW-1&gt;European Wildlife: [http://www.eurowildlife.org/about-us/how-we-work/ “How we work.”] Retrieved 6 March 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=EW-2&gt;European Wildlife (13 April 2011): [http://www.eurowildlife.org/news/the-aurochs-is-coming-back-to-european-forests-and-grasslands/ “The Aurochs is coming back to European forests and grasslands.”] Retrieved 6 March 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=sticht2&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stichtingtaurus.nl/ |title=Stichting Taurus, Official website |publisher= |date= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=kjpr&gt;{{cite web|title=True Nature Foundation Starts International Project To Bring Back The Aurochs|url=http://www.kjprnews.com/apps/blog/show/34541087-true-nature-foundation-starts-international-project-to-bring-back-the-aurochs|publisher=Kjprnews.com|date=26 October 2013|accessdate=6 March 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140307154251/http://www.kjprnews.com/apps/blog/show/34541087-true-nature-foundation-starts-international-project-to-bring-back-the-aurochs|archive-date=7 March 2014|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=truen&gt;{{cite web|title=Uruz Project|url=http://www.truenaturefoundation.org/project/species-restoration/uruz-project|publisher=True Nature Foundation|accessdate=6 March 2014|year=2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140307155814/http://www.truenaturefoundation.org/project/species-restoration/uruz-project|archive-date=7 March 2014|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=melk&gt;{{cite web|title=Gentechnologie voor fokken oeros|url=https://www.melkvee.nl/artikel/47447-project-met-gentechnologie-voor-fokken-oeros/|author=Gineke Mons|publisher=melkvee.nl|date=3 October 2013|accessdate=6 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=tnf2&gt;True Nature Foundation: [http://www.truenaturefoundation.org/wildlife/aurochs “Aurochs: Species Restoration.”] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150116173809/http://www.truenaturefoundation.org/wildlife/aurochs |date=16 January 2015 }} Retrieved 6 March 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=auerrind0&gt;[https://auerrind.wordpress.com/ Auerrindprojekt.] Official website. Retrieved 6 March 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=auerrind1&gt;Auerrindprojekt: [https://auerrind.wordpress.com/ueber-das-projekt/projektpartner/ “Partner.”] Retrieved 6 March 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=eaoall&gt;Kloster Lorsch (Lorsch Abbey): [http://www.kloster-lorsch.de/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=176&amp;Itemid=703 Freilichtlabor Lauresham: Allgemeine Informationen.] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160306035828/http://www.kloster-lorsch.de/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=176&amp;Itemid=703 |date=6 March 2016 }} Official website. Retrieved 6 March 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=megaherbs0&gt;[http://www.megaherbivoren.de/ Förderkreis Große Pflanzenfresser im Kreis Bergstraße e.V.] Official website. Retrieved 6 March 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=hohmeyer0&gt;[http://www.cachena.de/de/index.htm Landschaftspflegebetrieb Hohmeyer] Official website. Retrieved 6 March 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=nauka&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.naukawpolsce.pap.pl/en/news/news,68335,polish-geneticists-want-to-recreate-the-extinct-auroch.html |title=Polish geneticists want to recreate the extinct auroch Science and Scholarship in Poland |publisher=Polish Press Agency (PAP) |date=28 November 2007 |accessdate= |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131019175003/http://www.naukawpolsce.pap.pl/en/news/news,68335,polish-geneticists-want-to-recreate-the-extinct-auroch.html |archive-date=19 October 2013 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- This is only a press release: need a proper ref. --&gt;

&lt;ref name=leorient&gt;{{cite news |last=Makarem |first=May |date=11 July 2012 |title=Et si Europe était sidonienne? |url=http://www.lorientlejour.com/category/À+La+Une/article/767714/Et_si_Europe_etait_sidonienne_.html |work=L'Orient Le Jour |location=Beirut |access-date=3 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=bible&gt;(Strong's # 07214) in the [[Bible]] (Numbers 23:22 and 24:8, Deuteronomy 33:17, Job 39:9–10, Psalms 22:21, 29:6, 92:10 and Isaiah 34:7)&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=comments&gt;The identification was first made by Johann Ulrich Duerst, ''Die Rinder von Babylonian, Assyrien und Ägypten''(Berlin, 1899:7-8), and was generally accepted, as by Salo Jonas, &quot;Cattle Raising in Palestine&quot; ''Agricultural History'' '''26'''.3 (July 1952), pp. 93-104&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=biblecyc&gt;{{cite book |url= |title=The International Standard Bible Encyclopedia, Entry for 'Wild Ox' |year=1939 |publisher=Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing Co. |isbn= |page= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=vuure&gt;{{cite journal |last=van Vuure |first=T. (Cis) |date=2002 |title=History, , Morphology and Ecology of the Aurochs (''Bos primigenius'') |url=http://members.chello.nl/~t.vanvuure/oeros/uk/lutra.pdf |journal=Lutra |volume=45 |issue=1 |pages= |doi= |access-date= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;vVuure05&quot;&gt;{{cite book |url= |title=Retracing the Aurochs – History, Morphology and Ecology of an extinct wild Ox |first=T. (Cis) |last=van Vuure |year=2005 |location=Sofia-Moscow |publisher=Pensoft Publishers |isbn=954-642-235-5 |page= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=fedos&gt;{{cite book |url= |title=Russian Surnames. Popular Etymological Dictionary |edition=6th |first=Yu. A. |last=Fedosyuk |year= |publisher= |isbn= |page= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=rakve&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rakvere.ee/print.php?main=518 |title=Rakvere linn |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110719160810/http://www.rakvere.ee/print.php?main=518 |archivedate=19 July 2011 |url-status=dead |language=et |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

== Further reading ==
*Heptner, V. G. ; Nasimovich, A. A. ; Bannikov, A. G. ; Hoffman, R. S. (1988) [https://archive.org/details/mammalsofsovietu11988gept ''Mammals of the Soviet Union''], Volume I, Washington, D.C. : Smithsonian Institution Libraries and National Science Foundation
*{{cite document |last=Sparavigna |first=Amelia |title=The Pleiades: the celestial herd of ancient timekeepers |publisher=Cornell University |arxiv=0810.1592 |year=2008 |bibcode=2008arXiv0810.1592S }}

== References ==
*Bunzel-Drüke, M. 2001. ''Ecological substitutes for Wild Horse'' (Equus ferus Boddaert, 1785 = E. przewalslii Poljakov, 1881) and ''Aurochs'' (Bos primigenius Bojanus, 1827). Natur- und Kulturlandschaft, Höxter/Jena, 4, 10 p. AFKP. [https://web.archive.org/web/20060309153745/http://www.abu-naturschutz.de/_dnload/substitu.pdf Online pdf (298&amp;nbsp;kB)]

== External links ==
{{Commons|Bos primigenius|Aurochs}}
{{Wikispecies|Bos primigenius|Aurochs}}
{{EB1911 poster|Aurochs}}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20090420140454/http://www.petermaas.nl/extinct/speciesinfo/aurochs.htm The Extinction Website – Aurochs (''Bos primigenius primigenius'')]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20080416214357/http://users.aristotle.net/~swarmack/aurochs.html History of aurochs in Poland]
*{{Cite AmCyc|wstitle=Aurochs |short=x}}

{{Taxonbar|from=Q168903}}

[[Category:Mammals described in 1827]]
[[Category:Bovines]]
[[Category:Extinct mammals of Europe]]
[[Category:Extinct mammals]]
[[Category:Extinct mammals of Asia]]
[[Category:Extinct mammals of Africa]]
[[Category:Fossil taxa described in 1827]]
[[Category:Holocene extinctions]]
[[Category:Mammal extinctions since 1500]]
[[Category:Pleistocene even-toed ungulates]]
[[Category:Pleistocene first appearances]]
[[Category:Pliocene even-toed ungulates]]
[[Category:Prehistoric bovids]]
[[Category:Species made extinct by human activities]]
[[Category:Bovids of Africa]]</text>
      <sha1>ptf6921iqaba6q56nd5dsgmwb87x27i</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
