  <page>
    <title>Aardvark</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>680</id>
    <revision>
      <id>935620920</id>
      <parentid>933620245</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-13T18:17:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Thylacine24</username>
        <id>32084967</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Feeding */ Added italics</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{pp-semi-vandalism|small=yes}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{speciesbox
| name = Aardvark
| fossil_range = {{Fossil range|5|0|Early [[Pliocene]] – Recent}}
| image = Porc formiguer.JPG
| image_caption =
| status = LC
| status_system = IUCN3.1
| status_ref = &lt;ref name=&quot;iucn&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Lindsey|Cilliers|Griffin|Taylor|2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| genus = Orycteropus
| species = afer
| authority = ([[Peter Simon Pallas|Pallas]], 1766)
| subdivision_ranks = Subspecies
| subdivision = See text
| range_map = Aardvark area.png
| range_map_caption = Aardvark range
| range_map_alt = Map of Africa showing a highlighted range (in green) covering most of the continent south of the Sahara desert
}}
[[File:Aardvark Skeleton.jpg|thumb|Skeleton of an aardvark on display at the [[Museum of Osteology]].]]
The '''aardvark''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|ɑːr|d|v|ɑːr|k|}} {{respell|ARD|vark}}; ''Orycteropus afer'') is a medium-sized, burrowing, [[nocturnal]] [[mammal]] native to [[Africa]].&lt;ref name=EB&gt;{{harvnb|Hoiberg|2010|pp=3–4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.dsae.co.za/entry/aardvark/e00015 &quot;Aardvark, n.&quot;] ''Dictionary of South African English''. Dictionary Unit for South African English, 2018. 26 February 2019.&lt;/ref&gt; It is the only living [[species]] of the order [[Tubulidentata]],&lt;ref name=&quot;MSW3&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schlitter|2005|p=86}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=EoM/&gt; although other prehistoric species and genera of Tubulidentata are known. Unlike other [[insectivore]]s, it has a long [[pig]]-like snout, which is used to sniff out food. It roams over most of the southern two-thirds of the African continent, avoiding areas that are mainly rocky. A nocturnal feeder, it subsists on ants and termites, which it will dig out of their hills using its sharp claws and powerful legs. It also digs to create burrows in which to live and rear its young. It receives a &quot;least concern&quot; rating from the [[IUCN]], although its numbers seem to be decreasing.

Aardvarks are [[afrothere]]s, a [[clade]] which also includes [[elephants]], [[manatees]], and [[hyraxes]].

==Name and taxonomy==

=== Name  ===
The aardvark is sometimes colloquially called &quot;African ant bear&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Colliers&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Goodwin|1997|pp=2–3}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;anteater&quot; (not to be confused with the [[anteater|South American anteater]]), or the &quot;Cape anteater&quot;&lt;ref name=Colliers/&gt; after the [[Cape of Good Hope]]. The name &quot;aardvark&quot; is [[Afrikaans]] ({{IPA-af|ˈɑːrtfark}}), comes from earlier Afrikaans (erdvark)&lt;ref name=Colliers/&gt; and means &quot;earth [[pig]]&quot; or &quot;ground pig&quot; (''aarde'': earth/ground, ''vark'': pig), because of its burrowing habits.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Merriam-Webster Online Dictionary|2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
&quot;aardvark, n.&quot; ''OED Online'', Oxford University Press, March 2018, www.oed.com/view/Entry/22. Accessed 24 May 2018.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.dsae.co.za/entry/aardvark/e00015 &quot;Aardvark, n.&quot;] ''Dictionary of South African English''. Dictionary Unit for South African English, 2018. 25 February 2019.&lt;/ref&gt; The name ''Orycteropus'' means burrowing foot, and the name ''afer'' refers to Africa.&lt;ref name=sho/&gt; The name of the aardvarks's order, ''Tubulidentata,'' comes from the tubule-style teeth.&lt;ref name=sho1&gt;{{harvnb|Shoshani|2002|p=619}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Taxonomy ===
[[File:Aardvark skull.JPG|thumb|The skull of an aardvark]]
The aardvark is not closely related to the pig; rather, it is the sole extant representative of the obscure mammalian [[order (biology)|order]] [[Tubulidentata]],&lt;ref name=sho&gt;{{harvnb|Shoshani|2002|p=618}}&lt;/ref&gt; in which it is usually considered to form one variable species of the genus ''[[Orycteropus]]'', the sole surviving genus in the family [[Orycteropodidae]]. The aardvark is not closely related to the [[South America]]n [[anteater]], despite sharing some characteristics and a superficial resemblance.&lt;ref name=awf/&gt; The similarities are based on [[convergent evolution]].&lt;ref name=UR2/&gt; The closest living relatives of the aardvark are the [[elephant shrew]]s, [[tenrecidae|tenrec]]s and [[golden mole]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Asher|Bennett|Lehmann|2009|p=854}}&lt;/ref&gt; Along with the [[sirenian]]s, [[hyrax]]es, [[elephant]]s,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Rodriguez|2013|p=6}}&lt;/ref&gt; and their extinct relatives, these animals form the superorder [[Afrotheria]].&lt;ref name=UR&gt;{{harvnb|Rahm|1990|pp=450–451}}&lt;/ref&gt; Studies of the brain have shown the similarities with [[Condylarthra]],&lt;ref name=UR2/&gt; and given the clade's status as a [[wastebasket taxon]] it may mean some species traditionally classified as &quot;condylarths&quot; are actually stem-aardvarks.{{citation needed|date=September 2015}}

=== Evolutionary history ===
Based on fossils, Bryan Patterson has concluded that early relatives of the aardvark appeared in [[Africa]] around the end of the [[Paleocene]].&lt;ref name=UR2/&gt;&lt;ref name=sho2&gt;{{harvnb|Shoshani|2002|p=620}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[ptolemaiida]]ns, a mysterious clade of mammals with uncertain affinities, may actually be stem-aardvarks, either as a sister clade to [[Tubulidentata]] or as a grade leading to true tubulidentates.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cote et al 2007&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Cote S, Werdelin L, Seiffert ER, Barry JC |title=Additional material of the enigmatic Early Miocene mammal ''Kelba'' and its relationship to the order Ptolemaiida |journal=Proc Natl Acad Sci USA |volume=104 |issue=13 |pages=5510–5 |date=March 2007 |pmid=17372202 |pmc=1838468 |doi=10.1073/pnas.0700441104 |bibcode = 2007PNAS..104.5510C }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Seifert2007&gt;{{cite journal|last=Seiffert|first=Erik R|title=A new estimate of afrotherian phylogeny based on simultaneous analysis of genomic, morphological, and fossil evidence|journal=BMC Evolutionary Biology|year=2007|volume=7|issue=1|pages=224|doi=10.1186/1471-2148-7-224|url=http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2148/7/224|pmid=17999766|pmc=2248600}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first unambiguous tubulidentate was probably ''[[Myorycteropus africanus]]'' from [[Kenya]]n [[Miocene]] deposits.&lt;ref name=UR2/&gt; The earliest example from the genus ''[[Orycteropus]]'' was ''[[Orycteropus mauritanicus]]'', found in [[Algeria]] in deposits from the middle Miocene, with an equally old version found in Kenya.&lt;ref name=UR2/&gt; Fossils from the aardvark have been dated to 5 million years, and have been located throughout [[Europe]] and the [[Near East]].&lt;ref name=UR2/&gt;

The mysterious Pleistocene ''[[Plesiorycteropus]]'' from [[Madagascar]] was originally thought to be a tubulidentate that was descended from ancestors that entered the island during the [[Eocene]]. However, a number of subtle anatomical differences coupled with recent molecular evidence now lead researchers to believe that ''Plesiorycteropus'' is a relative of golden moles and tenrecs that achieved an aardvark-like appearance and ecological niche through convergent evolution.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley, M. 2013. A molecular phylogeny of Plesiorycteropus reassigns the extinct mammalian order 'Bibymalagasia'. PLoS ONE 8(3):e59614.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Subspecies===
The aardvark has seventeen poorly defined subspecies listed:&lt;ref name=&quot;MSW3&quot;/&gt;

* ''Orycteropus afer afer''
* ''O. a. adametzi'' &lt;small&gt; Grote, 1921&lt;/small&gt;
* ''O. a. aethiopicus'' &lt;small&gt; [[Carl Jakob Sundevall|Sundevall]], 1843&lt;/small&gt;
* ''O. a. angolensis'' &lt;small&gt; Zukowsky &amp; [[Theodor Haltenorth|Haltenorth]], 1957&lt;/small&gt;
* ''O. a. erikssoni'' &lt;small&gt; [[Einar Lönnberg|Lönnberg]], 1906&lt;/small&gt;
* ''O. a. faradjius'' &lt;small&gt; Hatt, 1932&lt;/small&gt;
* ''O. a. haussanus'' &lt;small&gt; [[Paul Matschie|Matschie]], 1900&lt;/small&gt;
* ''O. a. kordofanicus'' &lt;small&gt; [[Walter Rothschild, 2nd Baron Rothschild|Rothschild]], 1927&lt;/small&gt;
* ''O. a. lademanni'' &lt;small&gt; Grote, 1911&lt;/small&gt;
* ''O. a. leptodon'' &lt;small&gt; Hirst, 1906&lt;/small&gt;
* ''O. a. matschiei'' &lt;small&gt; Grote, 1921&lt;/small&gt;
* ''O. a. observandus'' &lt;small&gt;Grote, 1921&lt;/small&gt;
* ''O. a. ruvanensis'' &lt;small&gt;Grote, 1921&lt;/small&gt;
* ''O. a. senegalensis'' &lt;small&gt;[[René Primevère Lesson|Lesson]], 1840&lt;/small&gt;
* ''O. a. somalicus'' &lt;small&gt;[[Richard Lydekker|Lydekker]], 1908&lt;/small&gt;
* ''O. a. wardi'' &lt;small&gt;Lydekker, 1908&lt;/small&gt;
* ''O. a. wertheri'' &lt;small&gt; Matschie, 1898&lt;/small&gt;

The 1911 Encyclopædia Britannica also mentions ''O. a. capensis'' or Cape ant-bear from South Africa.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite EB1911|wstitle=Aard-vark|volume=1|page=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Description==
[[File:Aardvark skeleton mount.JPG|thumb|right|An aardvark skeleton and mounted individual]]
The aardvark is vaguely pig-like in appearance. Its body is stout with a prominently arched back&lt;ref name=UR1&gt;{{harvnb|Rahm|1990|p=452}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is sparsely covered with coarse hairs. The limbs are of moderate length, with the rear legs being longer than the forelegs.&lt;ref name=UR/&gt; The front feet have lost the pollex (or 'thumb'), resulting in four toes, while the rear feet have all five toes. Each toe bears a large, robust [[Nail (anatomy)|nail]] which is somewhat flattened and shovel-like, and appears to be intermediate between a [[claw]] and a hoof. Whereas the aardvark is considered [[digitigrade]], it appears at time to be [[plantigrade]]. This confusion happens because when it squats it stands on its soles.&lt;ref name=UR1/&gt; A contributing characteristic to the burrow digging capabilities of aardvarks is an endosteal tissue called compacted coarse cancellous bone (CCCB). The stress and strain resistance provided by CCCB allows aardvarks to create their burrows, ultimately leading to a favorable environment for plants and a variety of animals. &lt;ref&gt;Botha-Brink, J., &amp; Legendre, J. L. (2018). Digging the compromise: investigating the link 
between limb and bone histology and fossoriality in the aardvark (Orycteropus afer). PeerJ, 6, 1-40.
Haussmann, S. N., Louw, A. M., Lewis, S., Nicol, J.H. K., Merwe, S., Le Roux, C. P. (2018). 
Ecosystem engineering through aardvark (Orycteropus afer) burrowing: Mechanisms and effects. Elsevier, 118, 66-72.&lt;/ref&gt;

An aardvark's weight is typically between {{convert|60|and(-)|80|kg}}.&lt;ref name=UR/&gt; An aardvark's length is usually between {{convert|105|and(-)|130|cm|ft}},&lt;ref name=EoM/&gt; and can reach lengths of {{convert|2.2|m}} when its tail (which can be up to {{convert|70|cm}}) is taken into account. It is {{convert|60|cm|in}} tall at the shoulder, and has a girth of about {{convert|100|cm|ft}}.&lt;ref name=UR1/&gt; It is the [[Largest organisms|largest]] member of the proposed clade [[Afroinsectiphilia]]. The aardvark is pale yellowish-gray in color and often stained reddish-brown by [[soil]]. The aardvark's coat is thin, and the animal's primary protection is its tough skin. Its hair is short on its head and tail; however its legs tend to have longer hair.&lt;ref name=EoM/&gt; The hair on the majority of its body is grouped in clusters of 3-4 hairs.&lt;ref name=UR1/&gt; The hair surrounding its nostrils is dense to help filter particulate matter out as it digs. Its tail is very thick at the base and gradually tapers.

===Head===
The greatly elongated head is set on a short, thick neck, and the end of the snout bears a disc, which houses the nostrils. It contains a thin but complete [[zygomatic arch]].&lt;ref name=UR1/&gt; The head of the aardvark contains many unique and different features. One of the most distinctive characteristics of the Tubulidentata is their [[Tooth|teeth]]. Instead of having a [[pulp (tooth)|pulp cavity]], each tooth has a cluster of thin, hexagonal, upright, parallel tubes of vasodentin (a modified form of [[dentine]]), with individual pulp canals, held together by [[cementum]].&lt;ref name=UR/&gt; The number of columns is dependent on the size of the tooth, with the largest having about 1,500.&lt;ref name=UR2/&gt; The teeth have no [[Tooth enamel|enamel]] coating and are worn away and regrow continuously.&lt;ref name=sho1/&gt; The aardvark is born with conventional incisors and [[canine tooth|canines]] at the front of the jaw, which fall out and are not replaced. Adult aardvarks have only cheek teeth at the back of the [[jaw]], and have a [[dentition|dental formula]] of: {{DentalFormula|upper=0.0.2-3.3|lower=0.0.2.3}} These remaining teeth are peg-like and rootless and are of unique composition.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Martin|1983|p=377}}&lt;/ref&gt; The teeth consist of 14 upper and 12 lower jaw molars.&lt;ref name=Colliers/&gt; The nasal area of the aardvark is another unique area, as it contains ten [[nasal concha]]e, more than any other placental mammal.&lt;ref name=UR/&gt;

The sides of the nostrils are thick with hair.&lt;ref name=UR1/&gt; The tip of the snout is highly mobile and is moved by modified [[mimetic muscles]].&lt;ref name=UR/&gt; The fleshy dividing tissue between its nostrils probably has sensory functions,&lt;ref name=EoM/&gt; but it is uncertain whether they are olfactory or vibratory in nature.&lt;ref name=UR6&gt;{{harvnb|Rahm|1990|p=458}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its nose is made up of more [[turbinate]] bones than any other mammal, with between 9 and 11, compared to dogs with 4 to 5.&lt;ref name=sho1/&gt; With a large quantity of turbinate bones, the aardvark has more space for the moist [[epithelium]], which is the location of the olfactory bulb.&lt;ref name=sho1/&gt; The nose contains nine [[olfactory bulb]]s, more than any other mammal.&lt;ref name=UR1/&gt; Its keen sense of smell is not just from the quantity of bulbs in the nose but also in the development of the brain, as its [[Olfactory bulb|olfactory lobe]] is very developed.&lt;ref name=UR2&gt;{{harvnb|Rahm|1990|pp=453–454}}&lt;/ref&gt; The snout resembles an elongated pig snout. The mouth is small and tubular, typical of species that feed on [[ant]]s and [[termite]]s. The aardvark has a long, thin, snakelike, protruding tongue (as much as {{convert|30|cm|in}} long)&lt;ref name=Colliers/&gt; and elaborate structures supporting a keen [[olfaction|sense of smell]].&lt;ref name=&quot;TaylorSkinner&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Taylor|Skinner|2004|p=106}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ears, which are very effective,&lt;ref name=Colliers/&gt; are disproportionately long, about {{convert|20|-|25|cm|in}} long.&lt;ref name=UR1/&gt; The eyes are small for its head, and consist only of [[rod cell|rods]].&lt;ref name=UR1/&gt;

===Digestive system===
The aardvark's stomach has a muscular [[pyloric]] area that acts as a [[gizzard]] to grind swallowed food up, thereby rendering chewing unnecessary.&lt;ref name=EoM/&gt; Its [[cecum]] is large.&lt;ref name=UR/&gt; Both sexes emit a strong smelling secretion from an anal gland.&lt;ref name=EoM/&gt; Its [[salivary gland]]s are highly developed and almost completely ring the neck;&lt;ref name=UR/&gt; their output is what causes the tongue to maintain its tackiness.&lt;ref name=UR1/&gt; The female has two pairs of [[teat]]s in the inguinal region.&lt;ref name=UR/&gt;

[[Gene]]tically speaking, the aardvark is a [[living fossil]], as its [[chromosome]]s are highly conserved, reflecting much of the early [[eutherian]] arrangement before the divergence of the major modern [[taxon|taxa]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Anon|2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Habitat and range==
Aardvarks are found in [[sub-Saharan Africa]], where suitable [[habitat]] ([[savanna]]s, [[grassland]]s, [[woodland]]s and [[bushland]]) and food (i.e., [[ants]] and [[termites]]) is available.&lt;ref name=&quot;awf&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|African Wildlife Foundation|2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; They spend the daylight hours in dark burrows to avoid the heat of the day.&lt;ref name=ez&gt;{{harvnb|Anon|2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The only major habitat that they are not present in is swamp forest, as the high water table precludes digging to a sufficient depth.&lt;ref name=&quot;iucn&quot;/&gt; They also avoid terrain rocky enough to cause problems with digging.&lt;ref name=UR3&gt;{{harvnb|Rahm|1990|p=455}}&lt;/ref&gt; They have been documented as high as {{convert|3200|m|ft}} in Ethiopia. They are present throughout sub-Saharan Africa all the way to South Africa with few exceptions. These exceptions include the coastal areas of [[Namibia]], [[Ivory Coast]], and [[Ghana]]. They are not found in Madagascar.&lt;ref name=&quot;iucn&quot;/&gt;

==Ecology and behavior==
[[File:Orycteropus afer.jpg|thumb|upright|right|Aardvark resting]]
[[File:Erdvarkgat, Dingaanstat.jpg|thumb|right|Entrance to a burrow]]
[[File:SanWild17.jpg|thumb|right|Emerging from a burrow]]
Aardvarks live for up to 23&amp;nbsp;years in [[captivity (animal)|captivity]].&lt;ref name=UR/&gt; Its keen hearing warns it of predators: [[lion]]s, [[leopard]]s, cheetahs, [[African wild dog]]s, [[hyena]]s, and [[pythonidae|pythons]].&lt;ref name=Colliers/&gt;&lt;ref name=UR6/&gt; Some humans also hunt aardvarks for meat.&lt;ref name=Colliers/&gt; Aardvarks can dig fast or run in zigzag fashion to elude enemies, but if all else fails, they will strike with their claws, tail and shoulders, sometimes flipping onto their backs lying motionless except to lash out with all four feet.&lt;ref name=UR6/&gt; They are capable of causing substantial damage to unprotected areas of an attacker.&lt;ref name=sho1/&gt; They will also dig to escape as they can, when pressed, dig extremely quickly.&lt;ref name=UR6/&gt; 

===Feeding===
The aardvark is [[nocturnal]] and is a solitary creature that feeds almost exclusively on [[ant]]s and [[termite]]s ([[myrmecophagy]]);&lt;ref name=&quot;EoM&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|van Aarde|1984|pp=466–467}}&lt;/ref&gt; the only fruit eaten by aardvarks is the [[aardvark cucumber]].&lt;ref name=UR6/&gt; In fact, the cucumber and the aardvark have a symbiotic relationship as they eat the subterranean fruit, then defecate the seeds near their burrows, which then grow rapidly due to the loose soil and fertile nature of the area. The time spent in the intestine of the aardvark helps the fertility of the seed, and the fruit provides needed moisture for the aardvark.&lt;ref name=sho1/&gt;&lt;ref name=UR6/&gt; They avoid eating the African [[driver ant]] and red ants.&lt;ref name=UR4/&gt; Due to their stringent diet requirements, they require a large range to survive.&lt;ref name=UR3/&gt; An aardvark emerges from its burrow in the late afternoon or shortly after sunset, and forages over a considerable home range encompassing {{convert|10|to|30|km|mi}}. While foraging for food, the aardvark will keep its nose to the ground and its ears pointed forward, which indicates that both smell and hearing are involved in the search for food. They zig-zag as they forage and will usually not repeat a route for 5–8 days as they appear to allow time for the termite nests to recover before feeding on it again.&lt;ref name=UR4/&gt;

During a foraging period, they will stop and dig a &quot;V&quot; shaped trench with their forefeet and then sniff it profusely as a means to explore their location.&lt;ref name=EoM/&gt; When a concentration of ants or termites is detected, the aardvark digs into it with its powerful front legs, keeping its long ears upright to listen for predators, and takes up an astonishing number of [[insect]]s with its long, sticky tongue—as many as 50,000 in one night have been recorded. Its claws enable it to dig through the extremely hard crust of a termite or ant mound quickly. It avoids inhaling the dust by sealing the nostrils.&lt;ref name=ez/&gt; When successful, the aardvark's long (up to {{convert|30|cm|in}})&lt;ref name=EB/&gt; tongue licks up the insects; the termites' biting, or the ants' stinging attacks are rendered futile by the tough skin. After an aardvark visit at a termite mound, other animals will visit to pick up all the leftovers.&lt;ref name=UR5&gt;{{harvnb|Rahm|1990|p=457}}&lt;/ref&gt; Termite mounds alone don't provide enough food for the aardvark, so they look for termites that are on the move. When these insects move, they can form columns {{convert|10|-|40|m|ft}} long and these tend to provide easy pickings with little effort exerted by the aardvark. These columns are more common in areas of livestock or other hoofed animals.&lt;ref name=UR5/&gt; The trampled grass and dung attract termites from the ''[[Odontotermes]]'', ''[[Microtermes]]'', and ''[[Pseudacanthotermes]]'' genera.&lt;ref name=UR5/&gt;

On a nightly basis they tend to be more active during the first portion of the night time (20:00-00:00); however, they don't seem to prefer bright or dark nights over the other. During adverse weather or if disturbed they will retreat to their burrow systems. They cover between {{convert|2|and|5|km|mi}} per night; however, some studies have shown that they may traverse as far as {{convert|30|km|mi}} in a night.&lt;ref name=EoM/&gt;

===Vocalization===
The aardvark is a rather quiet animal. However, it does make soft grunting sounds as it forages and loud grunts as it makes for its tunnel entrance.&lt;ref name=UR3/&gt; It makes a bleating sound if frightened.&lt;ref name=UR4&gt;{{harvnb|Rahm|1990|p=456}}&lt;/ref&gt; When it is threatened it will make for one of its burrows. If one is not close it will dig a new one rapidly. This new one will be short and require the aardvark to back out when the coast is clear.&lt;ref name=UR4/&gt;

===Movement===
The aardvark is known to be a good swimmer and has been witnessed successfully swimming in strong currents.&lt;ref name=UR4/&gt; It can dig a yard of tunnel in about five minutes,&lt;ref name=UR3/&gt; but otherwise moves fairly slowly.

When leaving the burrow at night, they pause at the entrance for about ten minutes, sniffing and listening. After this period of watchfulness, it will bound out and within seconds it will be {{convert|10|m|ft}} away. It will then pause, prick its ears, twisting its head to listen, then jump and move off to start foraging.&lt;ref name=UR3/&gt;

Aside from digging out ants and termites, the aardvark also [[fossorial|excavates]] burrows in which to live; of which they generally fall into three categories: burrows made while foraging, refuge and resting location, and permanent homes.&lt;ref name=EoM/&gt; Temporary sites are scattered around the home range and are used as refuges, while the main [[burrow]] is also used for breeding. Main burrows can be deep and extensive, have several entrances and can be as long as {{convert|13|m|ft}}.&lt;ref name=EoM/&gt; These burrows can be large enough for a man to enter.&lt;ref name=Colliers/&gt; The aardvark changes the layout of its home burrow regularly, and periodically moves on and makes a new one. The old burrows are an important part of the African wildlife scene. As they are vacated, then they are inhabited by smaller animals like the [[African Wild Dog|African wild dog]], [[ant-eating chat]], ''[[Nycteris thebaica]]'' and [[warthog]]s.&lt;ref name=UR4/&gt; Other animals that use them are hares, mongooses, hyenas, owls, pythons, and lizards. Without these refuges many animals would die during wildfire season.&lt;ref name=UR4/&gt; Only mothers and young share burrows; however, the aardvark is known to live in small family groups or as a solitary creature.&lt;ref name=Colliers/&gt; If attacked in the tunnel, it will escape by digging out of the tunnel thereby placing the fresh fill between it and its predator, or if it decides to fight it will roll onto its back, and attack with its claws.&lt;ref name=Colliers/&gt; The aardvark has been known to sleep in a recently excavated [[ant]] nest, which also serves as protection from its [[predator]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Anon|2013a}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reproduction===
[[File:Aardvarks.jpg|thumb|right|Aardvark mother and young]]
Aardvarks pair only during the breeding season; after a [[gestation]] period of seven months,&lt;ref name=EoM/&gt; one cub weighing around {{convert|1.7|-|1.9|kg|lb}}&lt;ref name=UR/&gt; is born during May–July.&lt;ref name=Colliers/&gt; When born, the young has flaccid ears and many wrinkles. When nursing, it will nurse off each teat in succession.&lt;ref name=UR6/&gt; After two weeks, the folds of skin disappear and after three, the ears can be held upright.&lt;ref name=UR6/&gt; After 5–6 weeks, body hair starts growing.&lt;ref name=UR6/&gt; It is able to leave the burrow to accompany its mother after only two weeks and eats termites at 9&amp;nbsp;weeks,&lt;ref name=UR6/&gt; and is weaned between three months&lt;ref name=UR/&gt; and 16&amp;nbsp;weeks.&lt;ref name=EoM/&gt; At six months of age, it is able to dig its own burrows, but it will often remain with the mother until the next [[mating season]],&lt;ref name=EoM/&gt; and is sexually mature from approximately two years of age.&lt;ref name=UR/&gt;

==Conservation==
Aardvarks were thought to have declining numbers,&lt;ref name=Colliers/&gt; however, this is possibly due to the fact that they are not readily seen.&lt;ref name=&quot;iucn&quot;/&gt; There are no definitive counts because of their nocturnal and secretive habits; however, their numbers seem to be stable overall. They are not considered common anywhere in Africa, but due to their large range, they maintain sufficient numbers. There may be a slight decrease in numbers in eastern, northern, and western Africa. Southern African numbers are not decreasing. It receives an official designation from the IUCN as [[least concern]].&lt;ref name=&quot;iucn&quot;/&gt; However, they are a species in a precarious situation, as they are so dependent on such specific food; therefore if a problem arises with the abundance of termites, the species as a whole would be affected drastically.&lt;ref name=EoM/&gt;

Aardvarks handle captivity well. The first zoo to have one was [[London Zoo]] in 1869, which had an animal from [[South Africa]].&lt;ref name=UR6/&gt;

==Mythology and popular culture==
[[File:F-14A Tomcat of VF-114 in flight 1977.jpg|thumb|200px|F-14 Tomcat from VF-114 Aardvarks with the squadron mascot painted on the tail]]

In [[African folklore]], the aardvark is much admired because of its diligent quest for food and its fearless response to [[army ant|soldier ants]]. [[Hausa people|Hausa]] magicians make a charm from the heart, skin, forehead, and nails of the aardvark, which they then proceed to pound together with the root of a certain tree. Wrapped in a piece of skin and worn on the chest, the charm is said to give the owner the ability to pass through walls or roofs at night. The charm is said to be used by burglars and those seeking to visit young girls without their parents' permission.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Rebecca|2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, some tribes, such as the [[Mangbetu people|Margbetu]], [[Ayanda]], and [[Logo people|Logo]],&lt;ref name=EoM/&gt; will use aardvark teeth to make bracelets, which are regarded as good luck charms.&lt;ref name=Colliers/&gt; The meat, which has a resemblance to pork, is eaten in certain cultures.&lt;ref name=EoM/&gt;

The [[Egyptian mythology|Egyptian god]] [[Set (mythology)|Set]] is usually depicted with the head of an [[Set animal|unidentified animal]], whose similarity to an aardvark has been noted in scholarship.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|te Velde|1997|p=13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Arthur Read|titular character]] of ''[[Arthur (TV series)|Arthur]]'', an animated television series for children based on a book series and produced by [[WGBH-TV|WGBH]], shown in more than 180 countries, is an aardvark.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|WGBH|2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Otis the Aardvark]] was a puppet character used on [[Children's BBC]] programming.

An aardvark features as the antagonist in the cartoon ''[[The Ant and the Aardvark]]'' as well as in the Canadian animated series ''[[The Raccoons]]''.

In the military, the Air Force supersonic fighter-bomber [[General Dynamics F-111 Aardvark|F-111/FB-111]] was nicknamed the Aardvark because of its long nose resembling the animal.  It also had similarities with its nocturnal missions flown at a very low level employing ordnance that could penetrate deep into the ground.  In the US Navy, the squadron [[VF-114]] was nicknamed the Aardvarks, flying [[McDonnell Douglas F-4 Phantom II|F-4]]s and then [[Grumman F-14 Tomcat|F-14]]s.  The squadron mascot was adapted from the animal in the comic strip ''[[B.C. (comic strip)#Animals and other non-human characters|B.C.]]'', which the F-4 was said to resemble.

[[Cerebus the Aardvark]] is a 300-issue comic book series by Dave Sim.

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
{{refbegin|2}}
* {{cite web | author = African Wildlife Foundation | title = Aardvark | publisher = African Wildlife Foundation | url=http://www.awf.org/content/wildlife/detail/aardvark | accessdate = 2013-11-18 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080105044436/http://www.awf.org/content/wildlife/detail/aardvark | archivedate= 5 January 2008 | url-status= live | year = 2013 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite web|author=Anon |title=All About Aardvarks |url=http://www.easyscienceforkids.com/all-about-aardvarks.html |website=Easy Science for Kids |publisher=Online Science Tutor for Kids |accessdate=2013-11-18 |year=2013 |ref=harv |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131111151040/http://www.easyscienceforkids.com/all-about-aardvarks.html |archivedate=11 November 2013 }}
* {{cite web|author=Anon |website=Animal Corner |year=2013a |title=Rainforest Aardvark |url=http://www.animalcorner.co.uk/rainforests/aardvark.html |accessdate=10 January 2014 |ref=harv |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130726194347/http://www.animalcorner.co.uk/rainforests/aardvark.html |archivedate=26 July 2013 }}
* {{cite news | author = Anon | title = Great Uncle Aardvark? | website = BBC News | date = 20 January 2003 | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/science/nature/2676377.stm | accessdate = 2013-11-18 | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20080207170352/http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/science/nature/2676377.stm | archivedate = 7 February 2008 | ref = harv }}
* {{Cite journal | last = Asher | first = R. J. | last2 = Bennett | first2 = N. | last3 = Lehmann | first3 = T. | title = The new framework for understanding placental mammal evolution | journal = BioEssays | volume = 31 | issue = 8 | pages = 853–864 | year = 2009 | pmid = 19582725| pmc = | doi = 10.1002/bies.200900053 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite encyclopedia | last1 = Goodwin | first1 = George G. | editor-last = Johnston | editor-first = Bernard | encyclopedia = Collier's Encyclopedia | title = Aardvark | edition = 1st | year = 1997 | publisher = P.F. Collier | volume = I: A to Ameland | location = New York, NY | isbn = 978-1571610935 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite encyclopedia | editor-last = Hoiberg | editor-first = Dale H. | encyclopedia = Encyclopædia Britannica | title = Aardvark | edition = 15th | year = 2010 | publisher = Encyclopædia Britannica Inc. | volume = I: A-ak Bayes | location = Chicago, IL | isbn = 978-1-59339-837-8 | ref = harv | url = https://archive.org/details/newencyclopaedia2009ency }}
* {{cite iucn | author = Lindsey, P. | author2 = Cilliers, S. | author3 = Griffin, M. | author4 = Taylor, A. | author5 = Lehmann, T. | author6 = Rathbun, G. | year = 2008 | url = https://www.iucnredlist.org/details/41504/0 | title = Orycteropus afer | access-date = 2013-11-18|ref={{harvid|Lindsey|Cilliers|Griffin|Taylor|2008}} }}
* {{cite encyclopedia | last = Martin | first = Elizabeth A. | encyclopedia = MacMillan Dictionary of Life Sciences | title = Tubulidentata | isbn = 978-0333348673 | year = 1983 | edition = 2nd | publisher = MacMillan | ref = harv }}
* {{cite web | author = Merriam-Webster Online Dictionary | title = aardvark | year = 2010 | website = Merriam-Webster Online Dictionary | accessdate = 2013-11-18 | url = http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/aardvark | ref = harv }}
* {{cite encyclopedia | last = Rahm | first = Urs | editor-last = Parker | editor-first = Sybil P. | title = Tubulidentates: Aardvark | encyclopedia = Grzimek's Encyclopedia of Mammals | volume = 4 | publisher = McGraw-Hill Publishing Company | location = New York, NY | isbn = 978-0-07-909508-4 | year = 1990 | pp = [https://archive.org/details/grzimeksencyclop0005unse/page/450 450 458] | ref = harv | url = https://archive.org/details/grzimeksencyclop0005unse/page/450 }}
* {{cite web | author = Rebecca | title = Cute as a Button but a Pain in my Butt: The Aardvark | url = http://www.themagicalbuffet.com/Issues/Vol02_Iss07/Article_049.html | accessdate = 2013-11-18 | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20080117180543/http://www.themagicalbuffet.com/Issues/Vol02_Iss07/Article_049.html | archivedate = 17 January 2008  | url-status = live | year = 2007 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite journal | last = Rodriguez | first = Tommy | title = Technological Perspectives in Phylogeny Research: Revisiting Comparative Analysis of Complete Mitochondrial Genomes for Time-Extended Lineages | journal = Figshare | doi = 10.6084/m9.figshare.804317 | year = 2013 | pages = 1–9 | ref = harv}}
* {{MSW3 Tubulidentata | id = 11300004|ref={{harvid|Schlitter|2005}} }}
* {{cite encyclopedia | last = Shoshani | first = Jeheskel | editor-last = Robertson | editor-first = Sarah | title = Tubulidentata | encyclopedia = Encyclopedia of Life Sciences | year = 2002 | volume = 18: Svedberg, Theodor to Two-hybrid and Related Systems | publisher = Nature Publishing Group | location = London, UK | isbn = 978-1-56159-274-6 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite journal | last1 = Taylor | first1 = W. A. | last2 = Skinner | first2 = J. D. | title = Adaptations of the Aardvark for Survival in the Karoo: A Review | journal = Transactions of the Royal Society of South Africa | volume = 59 | issue = 2 | year = 2004 | doi = 10.1080/00359190409519169 | pages = 105–108 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = te Velde | first = Henk | title = Seth, God of Confusion: A Study of His Role in Egyptian Mythology and Religion (Ancient Near East) | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=0po3AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA13 | year = 1997 | publisher = Brill Academic Pub | isbn = 978-9004054028 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite encyclopedia | last = van Aarde | first = Rudi J. | editor-last = Macdonald | editor-first = David | title = Aardvark | encyclopedia = The Encyclopedia of Mammals | year = 1984 | publisher = Facts on File Publications | location = New York, NY | isbn = 978-0-87196-871-5 | ref = harv | url = https://archive.org/details/encyclopediaofma00mals_0 }}
* {{cite web | author = WGBH | url = https://www.pbs.org/parents/Arthur/program/prog_summary.html | title = About the Program: &quot;Arthur&quot; | website = PBS.org | publisher = Public Broadcasting System | year = 2013 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite web | author =  | title = aardvark | year = 2018 | website = Dictionary of South African English | accessdate = 2019-02-25 | url = http://www.dsae.co.za/entry/aardvark/e00015 | ref = harv }}

{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Wikispecies|Orycteropus afer}}
{{Commons|Orycteropus afer}}
* {{Cite web | url = https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1Z5OoBqqYsk&amp;t=0m46s | title = Aardvarks at the Bronx Zoo | accessdate = 2013-11-18 }}
* [http://www.aardvarkafrica.org IUCN/SSC Afrotheria Specialist Group - Aardvark website]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080907110513/http://www.wackywildlifewonders.com/files/animals/antbear.html Antbear/Aardvark] at wackywildlifewonders.com
* [http://animaldiversity.ummz.umich.edu/site/accounts/information/Orycteropus_afer.html Information] at Animal Diversity Web: [[University of Michigan]] Museum of Zoology
* [[wikisource:File:Aardvark.pdf|&quot;The Biology of the Aardvark&quot;]] (''Orycteropus afer'') diploma thesis (without pictures)
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080414134457/http://www.tierseiten.com/roehrenzaehner/aardvark.pdf &quot;The Biology of the Aardvark&quot; (''Orycteropus afer'')] same diploma thesis (including the pictures)
* [http://www.zooborns.typepad.com/zooborns/aardvark/ Some good photos of baby aardvarks]
* {{Wikisource-inline|list=
** &quot;[[s:Popular Science Monthly/Volume 14/March 1879/The Aard-Vark or Earth-Hog|The Aard-Vark or Earth-Hog]]&quot; in ''[[Popular Science Monthly]]'', Vol. 14 (March 1879)
** {{Cite NSRW|wstitle=Aardvark |short=x |noicon=x}}
** {{Cite Collier's|wstitle=Aard-vark |short=x |noicon=x}}
}}

{{mammals}}
{{Taxonbar|from=Q46212}}

[[Category:Mammals of Africa]]
[[Category:Myrmecophagous mammals]]
[[Category:Mammals described in 1766]]
[[Category:Extant Zanclean first appearances]]</text>
      <sha1>bopc5xguppikge6vlpvx5n8f50ryi3x</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
