  <page>
    <title>Amphibian</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>621</id>
    <revision>
      <id>936904985</id>
      <parentid>934269320</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-21T19:14:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jimmyeatskids</username>
        <id>3210302</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|A class of ectothermic tetrapods, which typically breed in water}}
{{other uses|Amphibian (disambiguation)}}
{{redirect|Amphibia|the TV series|Amphibia (TV series)}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=June 2013}}
{{automatic taxobox
| name = Amphibians
| fossil_range = [[Late Devonian]]–[[present]], {{fossil range|370|0}}
| image = Amphibians.png
| image_upright = 1.15
| image_alt = Collage of amphibians
| image_caption = Clockwise from top right: ''[[Seymouria]]'', [[Mexican burrowing caecilian]], [[eastern newt]] and [[leaf green tree frog]]
| taxon = Amphibia
| authority = [[John Edward Gray|Gray]] 1825&lt;ref name=BlackburnWake/&gt;
| subdivision_ranks = Subclasses
| subdivision =
* {{extinct}}[[Temnospondyli]]
* [[Lissamphibia]] (modern amphibians)
}}

'''Amphibians''' are [[ectotherm]]ic, [[tetrapod]] [[vertebrate]]s of the [[Class (biology)|class]] '''Amphibia'''. Modern amphibians are all [[Lissamphibia]]. They inhabit a wide variety of [[habitat]]s, with most species living within [[terrestrial animal|terrestrial]], [[fossorial]], [[arboreal]] or freshwater [[aquatic ecosystems]]. Thus amphibians typically start out as [[larva]]e living in water, but some species have developed behavioural adaptations to bypass this. The young generally undergo [[metamorphosis]] from larva with gills to an adult air-breathing form with [[lung]]s. Amphibians use their skin as a secondary respiratory surface and some small terrestrial [[salamander]]s and [[frog]]s lack lungs and rely entirely on their skin. They are superficially similar to [[lizard]]s but, along with mammals and birds, reptiles are [[amniote]]s and do not require water bodies in which to breed. With their complex reproductive needs and permeable skins, amphibians are often [[ecological indicator]]s; in recent decades there has been a dramatic [[decline in amphibian populations]] for many species around the globe.

The earliest amphibians [[evolution of tetrapods|evolved]] in the [[Devonian]] period from [[sarcopterygian]] fish with lungs and bony-limbed fins, features that were helpful in adapting to dry land. They diversified and became dominant during the [[Carboniferous]] and [[Permian]] periods, but were later displaced by reptiles and other vertebrates. Over time, amphibians shrank in size and decreased in diversity, leaving only the modern subclass Lissamphibia.

The three modern orders of amphibians are [[Anura (frog)|Anura]] (the frogs and toads), [[Urodela]] (the salamanders), and [[caecilian|Apoda]] (the caecilians). The number of known amphibian species is approximately 8,000, of which nearly 90% are frogs. The smallest amphibian (and vertebrate) in the world is a frog from [[New Guinea]] (''[[Paedophryne amauensis]]'') with a length of just {{convert|7.7|mm|in|abbr=on}}. The largest living amphibian is the {{convert|1.8|m|0|abbr=on}} [[South China giant salamander]] (''Andrias sligoi''), but this is dwarfed by the extinct {{convert|9|m|0|abbr=on}} ''[[Prionosuchus]]'' from the [[Guadalupian|middle Permian]] of Brazil. The study of amphibians is called [[batrachology]], while the study of both reptiles and amphibians is called [[herpetology]].

== Classification ==
{{see also|List of amphibians}}
[[File:Paratype of Paedophryne amauensis (LSUMZ 95004).png|thumb|alt=World's smallest vertebrate|The world's smallest known vertebrate, ''[[Paedophryne amauensis]]'', sitting on a [[Dime (United States coin)|U.S. dime]]. The dime is 17.9&amp;nbsp;mm in diameter, for scale]]

The word &quot;amphibian&quot; is derived from the [[Ancient Greek]] term ἀμφίβιος (''amphíbios''), which means &quot;both kinds of life&quot;, ''ἀμφί'' meaning &quot;of both kinds&quot; and ''βιος'' meaning &quot;life&quot;. The term was initially used as a general adjective for animals that could live on land or in water, including seals and otters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=A Concise Etymological Dictionary of the English Language |last=Skeat |first=Walter W. |year=1897 |publisher=Clarendon Press |page=39 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Traditionally, the class Amphibia includes all tetrapod vertebrates that are not amniotes. Amphibia in its widest sense (''[[sensu lato]]'') was divided into three [[Class (biology)|subclasses]], two of which are extinct:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Baird, Donald |date=May 1965 |title=Paleozoic lepospondyl amphibians |journal=Integrative and Comparative Biology |volume=5 |issue=2 |pages=287–294 |doi=10.1093/icb/5.2.287 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Subclass [[Lepospondyli]]† (small Paleozoic group, which may actually be more closely related to amniotes than Lissamphibia)
* Subclass [[Temnospondyli]]† (diverse Paleozoic and early Mesozoic grade)
* Subclass [[Lissamphibia]] (all modern amphibians, including frogs, toads, salamanders, newts and caecilians)
** Salientia ([[frog]]s, [[toad]]s and relatives): Jurassic to present—6,200 current species in 53 families
** Caudata ([[salamander]]s, [[newt]]s and relatives): Jurassic to present—652 current species in 9 families
** Gymnophiona ([[caecilian]]s and relatives): Jurassic to present—192 current species in 10 families

[[File:Triadobatrachus.jpg|thumb|alt=''Triadobatrachus massinoti''|''[[Triadobatrachus|Triadobatrachus massinoti]]'', a proto-frog from the Early Triassic of Madagascar]]
The actual number of species in each group depends on the taxonomic classification followed. The two most common systems are the classification adopted by the website AmphibiaWeb, [[University of California, Berkeley]] and the classification by [[Herpetology|herpetologist]] [[Darrel Frost]] and the [[American Museum of Natural History]], available as the online reference database &quot;Amphibian Species of the World&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://research.amnh.org/vz/herpetology/amphibia/ |title= American Museum of Natural History: Amphibian Species of the World 5.6, an Online Reference |author=Frost, Darrel |year=2013 |publisher=The American Museum of Natural History |accessdate=October 24, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The numbers of species cited above follows Frost and the total number of known amphibian species as of March 31, 2019 is exactly 8,000,&lt;ref&gt;http://amphibiaweb.org:8000/lists/index.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; of which nearly 90% are frogs.&lt;ref name=&quot;species&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|author=Crump, Martha L. |year=2009 |title=Amphibian diversity and life history |journal=Amphibian Ecology and Conservation. A Handbook of Techniques |pages=3–20 |url=http://fds.oup.com/www.oup.com/pdf/13/9780199541188_chapter1.pdf |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110715022035/http://fds.oup.com/www.oup.com/pdf/13/9780199541188_chapter1.pdf |archivedate=July 15, 2011 |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

With the [[Phylogenetics|phylogenetic]] classification, the taxon [[Labyrinthodontia]] has been discarded as it is a [[Paraphyly|polyparaphyletic]] group without unique defining features apart from [[Cladistics#plesiomorphy|shared primitive characteristics]]. Classification varies according to the preferred phylogeny of the author and whether they use a [[Cladistics#Three definitions of clade|stem-based or a node-based]] classification. Traditionally, amphibians as a class are defined as all tetrapods with a larval stage, while the group that includes the common ancestors of all living amphibians (frogs, salamanders and caecilians) and all their descendants is called Lissamphibia. The phylogeny of Paleozoic amphibians is uncertain, and Lissamphibia may possibly fall within extinct groups, like the Temnospondyli (traditionally placed in the subclass Labyrinthodontia) or the Lepospondyli, and in some analyses even in the amniotes. This means that advocates of [[phylogenetic nomenclature]] have removed a large number of [[basal (phylogenetics)|basal]] Devonian and Carboniferous amphibian-type tetrapod groups that were formerly placed in Amphibia in [[Linnaean taxonomy]], and included them elsewhere under [[cladistic taxonomy]].&lt;ref name=BlackburnWake&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Blackburn, D. C. |author2=Wake, D. B. | title=Class Amphibia Gray, 1825. In: Zhang, Z.-Q. (Ed.) Animal biodiversity: An outline of higher-level classification and survey of taxonomic richness | journal=Zootaxa| volume=3148| year=2011| pages=39–55| url=http://mapress.com/zootaxa/2011/f/zt03148p055.pdf|doi=10.11646/zootaxa.3148.1.8 }}&lt;/ref&gt; If the common ancestor of amphibians and amniotes is included in Amphibia, it becomes a paraphyletic group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ucmp.berkeley.edu/vertebrates/tetrapods/amphibsy.html |title=Amphibia: Systematics |author1=Speer, B. W. |author2=Waggoner, Ben |year=1995 |publisher=University of California Museum of Paleontology |accessdate=December 13, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

All modern amphibians are included in the subclass Lissamphibia, which is usually considered a [[clade]], a group of species that have evolved from a common ancestor. The three modern orders are Anura (the frogs and toads), Caudata (or Urodela, the salamanders), and Gymnophiona (or Apoda, the caecilians).{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | p=3 }} It has been suggested that salamanders arose separately from a Temnospondyl-like ancestor, and even that caecilians are the sister group of the advanced [[reptiliomorpha|reptiliomorph]] amphibians, and thus of amniotes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Anderson&quot; /&gt; Although the fossils of several older proto-frogs with primitive characteristics are known, the oldest &quot;true frog&quot; is ''[[Prosalirus bitis]]'', from the [[Early Jurassic]] [[Kayenta Formation]] of Arizona. It is anatomically very similar to modern frogs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=Amphibian Biology: Paleontology: The Evolutionary History of Amphibians | editor1-last=Heatwole | editor1-first=H. | editor2-last=Carroll | editor2-first=R. L. | year=2000 | volume=4 | publisher=Surrey Beatty &amp; Sons | isbn=978-0-949324-87-0 | chapter=14. Mesozoic Amphibians | last1=Roček | first1=Z. | pages=1295–1331 | chapter-url=http://rocek.gli.cas.cz/Reprints/AmphBiol3.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; The oldest known caecilian is another Early Jurassic species, ''[[Eocaecilia micropodia]]'', also from Arizona.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Jenkins, Farish A. Jr. |author2=Walsh, Denis M. |author3=Carroll, Robert L. |year=2007 |title=Anatomy of ''Eocaecilia micropodia'', a limbed caecilian of the Early Jurassic |journal=Bulletin of the Museum of Comparative Zoology |volume=158 |issue=6 |pages=285–365 |doi=10.3099/0027-4100(2007)158[285:AOEMAL]2.0.CO;2 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The earliest salamander is ''[[Beiyanerpeton jianpingensis]]'' from the [[Late Jurassic]] of northeastern China.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Gaoa, Ke-Qin |author2=Shubin, Neil H. |year=2012 |title=Late Jurassic salamandroid from western Liaoning, China |journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America |volume=109 |issue=15 |pages=5767–5772 |doi=10.1073/pnas.1009828109 |pmid=22411790 |pmc=3326464 |bibcode=2012PNAS..109.5767G }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Authorities disagree as to whether Salientia is a superorder that includes the order Anura, or whether Anura is a sub-order of the order Salientia. The Lissamphibia are traditionally divided into three [[Order (biology)|orders]], but an extinct salamander-like family, the [[Albanerpetontidae]], is now considered part of Lissamphibia alongside the superorder Salientia. Furthermore, Salientia includes all three recent orders plus the Triassic proto-frog, ''[[Triadobatrachus]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://tolweb.org/Salientia/14938 |title=Salientia |author=Cannatella, David |year=2008 |work=Tree of Life Web Project |accessdate=August 31, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Evolutionary history ==
{{Main|Evolution of tetrapods}}
{{see also|List of prehistoric amphibians}}
{{multiple image
| align     = right
| direction = vertical
| header    =
| width     = 220

| image1    = Eusthenopteron BW.jpg
| alt1      =
| caption1  =

| image2    = Tiktaalik BW.jpg
| alt2      =
| caption2  = '''Top:''' Restoration of ''[[Eusthenopteron]]'', a fully aquatic lobe-finned fish

'''Bottom:''' Restoration of ''[[Tiktaalik]]'', an advanced tetrapodomorph fish
}}
The first major groups of amphibians developed in the [[Devonian]] period, around 370 million years ago, from [[Sarcopterygii|lobe-finned fish]] which were similar to the modern [[coelacanth]] and [[lungfish]].&lt;ref name=&quot;evoamphib&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://sci.waikato.ac.nz/evolution/AnimalEvolution.shtml#evolutionofamphibian |title=Evolution of amphibians |publisher=University of Waikato: Plant and animal evolution |accessdate=September 30, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; These ancient lobe-finned fish had evolved multi-jointed leg-like fins with digits that enabled them to crawl along the sea bottom. Some fish had developed primitive lungs that help them breathe air when the stagnant pools of the Devonian swamps were low in oxygen. They could also use their strong fins to hoist themselves out of the water and onto dry land if circumstances so required. Eventually, their bony fins would [[evolution|evolve]] into limbs and they would become the ancestors to all [[tetrapod]]s, including modern amphibians, reptiles, birds, and [[mammal]]s. Despite being able to crawl on land, many of these prehistoric [[tetrapodomorph]] fish still spent most of their time in the water. They had started to develop lungs, but still breathed predominantly with gills.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carroll&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Patterns of Evolution, as Illustrated by the Fossil Record |last=Carroll |first=Robert L. |editor=Hallam, Anthony |editor-link= Anthony Hallam|year=1977 |publisher=Elsevier |isbn=978-0-444-41142-6 |pages=405–420 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=q7GjDIyyWegC&amp;pg=PA405&amp;dq=Amphibian+evolution#v=onepage&amp;q=Amphibian%20evolution&amp;f=false }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many examples of species showing [[transitional fossil|transitional features]] have been discovered. ''[[Ichthyostega]]'' was one of the first primitive amphibians, with nostrils and more efficient lungs. It had four sturdy limbs, a neck, a tail with fins and a skull very similar to that of the lobe-finned fish, ''[[Eusthenopteron]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;evoamphib&quot; /&gt; Amphibians evolved adaptations that allowed them to stay out of the water for longer periods. Their lungs improved and their skeletons became heavier and stronger, better able to support the weight of their bodies on land.&lt;!--'cope with the increased gravitational effect of life' - The gravitational force is effectively the same on the surface of the land as in the sea; however, in water, a body experiences a buoyancy force.--&gt; They developed &quot;hands&quot; and &quot;feet&quot; with five or more digits;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ichthyostega&quot; /&gt; the skin became more capable of retaining body fluids and resisting desiccation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carroll&quot; /&gt; The fish's [[hyomandibula]] bone in the [[hyoid bone|hyoid]] region behind the gills diminished in size and became the [[stapes]] of the amphibian ear, an adaptation necessary for hearing on dry land.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Lombard, R. E. |author2=Bolt, J. R. |year=1979 |title=Evolution of the tetrapod ear: an analysis and reinterpretation |journal=Biological Journal of the Linnean Society |volume=11 |issue=1 |pages=19–76 |doi=10.1111/j.1095-8312.1979.tb00027.x |url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/230169547 }}&lt;/ref&gt; An affinity between the amphibians and the [[teleost]] fish is the multi-folded structure of the teeth and the paired [[Occipital bone|supra-occipital bones]] at the back of the head, neither of these features being found elsewhere in the animal kingdom.&lt;ref name=&quot;Spoczynska&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Diplocaulus vale21DB.jpg|thumb|left|upright|alt=''Diplocaulus''|The Permian lepospondyl ''[[Diplocaulus]]'' was largely aquatic]]
At the end of the Devonian period (360 million years ago), the seas, rivers and lakes were teeming with life while the land was the realm of early plants and devoid of vertebrates,&lt;ref name=&quot;Spoczynska&quot;/&gt; though some, such as ''Ichthyostega'', may have sometimes hauled themselves out of the water. It is thought they may have propelled themselves with their forelimbs, dragging their hindquarters in a similar manner to that used by the [[elephant seal]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ichthyostega&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://tolweb.org/Ichthyostega |title=''Ichthyostega'' |author=Clack, Jennifer A. |year=2006 |work=Tree of Life Web Project |accessdate=September 29, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the early [[Carboniferous]] (360 to 345 million years ago), the climate became wet and warm. Extensive swamps developed with [[moss]]es, [[fern]]s, [[horsetail]]s and [[calamites]]. Air-breathing [[arthropod]]s evolved and invaded the land where they provided food for the [[Carnivore|carnivorous]] amphibians that began to adapt to the terrestrial environment. There were no other tetrapods on the land and the amphibians were at the top of the food chain, occupying the ecological position currently held by the crocodile. Though equipped with limbs and the ability to breathe air, most still had a long tapering body and strong tail.&lt;ref name=&quot;Spoczynska&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Fossils: A Study in Evolution |last=Spoczynska |first=J. O. I. |year=1971 |publisher=Frederick Muller Ltd |isbn=978-0-584-10093-8 |pages=120–125 }}&lt;/ref&gt; They were the top land predators, sometimes reaching several metres in length, preying on the large insects of the period and the many types of fish in the water. They still needed to return to water to lay their shell-less eggs, and even most modern amphibians have a fully aquatic larval stage with gills like their fish ancestors. It was the development of the [[amniote|amniotic]] egg, which prevents the developing embryo from drying out, that enabled the reptiles to reproduce on land and which led to their [[Dominance (ecology)|dominance]] in the period that followed.&lt;ref name=&quot;evoamphib&quot;/&gt;

After the [[Carboniferous rainforest collapse]] amphibian dominance gave way to reptiles,&lt;ref name=&quot;SahneyBentonFerry2010LinksDiversityVertebrates&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | author=Sahney, S. | author2=Benton, M.J. | author3=Ferry, P.A. | last-author-amp=yes | year=2010 | title=Links between global taxonomic diversity, ecological diversity and the expansion of vertebrates on land | journal=Biology Letters | doi=10.1098/rsbl.2009.1024 | volume=6 | pages=544–547 | issue=4 | pmid=20106856 | pmc=2936204 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and amphibians were further devastated by the [[Permian–Triassic extinction event]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SahneyBenton2008RecoveryFromProfoundExtinction&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Sahney, S.  |author2=Benton, M.J. | year=2008 | title=Recovery from the most profound mass extinction of all time | journal=Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences | doi=10.1098/rspb.2007.1370 | volume = 275 | pages = 759–65| pmid=18198148 | issue=1636 | pmc=2596898}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the [[Triassic|Triassic Period]] (250 to 200 million years ago), the reptiles continued to out-compete the amphibians, leading to a reduction in both the amphibians' size and their importance in the [[biosphere]]. According to the fossil record, [[Lissamphibia]], which includes all modern amphibians and is the only surviving lineage, may have branched off from the extinct groups [[Temnospondyli]] and [[Lepospondyli]] at some period between the Late Carboniferous and the Early Triassic. The relative scarcity of fossil evidence precludes precise dating,&lt;ref name=&quot;Carroll&quot; /&gt; but the most recent molecular study, based on [[multilocus sequence typing]], suggests a Late Carboniferous/[[Cisuralian|Early Permian]] origin for extant amphibians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=San Mauro|first=D. |year=2010|title=A multilocus timescale for the origin of extant amphibians|journal=Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution |volume=56 |pages=554–561 |doi=10.1016/j.ympev.2010.04.019 |pmid=20399871|issue=2|url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/43182452}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Eryops - National Museum of Natural History - IMG 1974.JPG|thumb|alt=''Eryops''|The temnospondyl ''[[Eryops]]'' had sturdy limbs to support its body on land]]
The origins and evolutionary relationships between the three main groups of amphibians is a matter of debate. A 2005 molecular phylogeny, based on [[Ribosomal DNA|rDNA]] analysis, suggests that salamanders and caecilians are more closely related to each other than they are to frogs. It also appears that the divergence of the three groups took place in the [[Paleozoic]] or early [[Mesozoic]] (around 250 million years ago), before the breakup of the supercontinent [[Pangaea]] and soon after their divergence from the lobe-finned fish. The briefness of this period, and the swiftness with which radiation took place, would help account for the relative scarcity of primitive amphibian fossils.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=San Mauro, Diego |author2=Vences, Miguel |author3=Alcobendas, Marina |author4=Zardoya, Rafael |author5=Meyer, Axel |year=2005 |title=Initial diversification of living amphibians predated the breakup of Pangaea |journal=The American Naturalist |volume=165 |issue=5 |pages=590–599 |doi=10.1086/429523 |pmid=15795855 |url=http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:bsz:352-opus-33053 }}&lt;/ref&gt; There are large gaps in the [[fossil record]], but the discovery of a [[Gerobatrachus hottoni]] from the Early Permian in Texas in 2008 provided a missing link with many of the characteristics of modern frogs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Anderson&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Anderson, J. |author2=Reisz, R. |author3=Scott, D. |author4=Fröbisch, N. |author5=Sumida, S. |year=2008 |title=A stem batrachian from the Early Permian of Texas and the origin of frogs and salamanders |journal=Nature |volume=453 |issue= 7194|pages=515–518 |doi=10.1038/nature06865 |pmid= 18497824 |bibcode = 2008Natur.453..515A |url=https://www.academia.edu/13288317 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Molecular phylogenetics|Molecular analysis]] suggests that the frog–salamander divergence took place considerably earlier than the [[Paleontology|palaeontological]] evidence indicates.&lt;ref name=&quot;Anderson&quot; /&gt; Newer research indicates that the common ancestor of all Lissamphibians lived about 315 million years ago, and that [[Stereospondyli|stereospondyls]] are the closest relatives to the caecilians.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2017/06/170619151534.htm Tiny fossils reveal backstory of the most mysterious amphibian alive]&lt;/ref&gt;

As they evolved from lunged fish, amphibians had to make certain adaptations for living on land, including the need to develop new means of locomotion. In the water, the sideways thrusts of their tails had propelled them forward, but on land, quite different mechanisms were required. Their vertebral columns, limbs, limb girdles and musculature needed to be strong enough to raise them off the ground for locomotion and feeding. Terrestrial adults discarded their [[lateral line]] systems and adapted their sensory systems to receive stimuli via the medium of the air. They needed to develop new methods to regulate their body heat to cope with fluctuations in ambient temperature. They developed behaviours suitable for reproduction in a terrestrial environment. Their skins were exposed to harmful [[ultraviolet]] rays that had previously been absorbed by the water. The skin changed to become more protective and prevent excessive water loss.{{sfn | Dorit | Walker | Barnes | 1991 | pp=843–859 }}

== Characteristics ==
The superclass [[Tetrapoda]] is divided into four classes of vertebrate animals with four limbs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://tolweb.org/Terrestrial_Vertebrates/14952 |title=Terrestrial Vertebrates |author=Laurin, Michel |year=2011 |work=Tree of Life Web Project |accessdate=September 16, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reptiles, birds and mammals are amniotes, the eggs of which are either laid or carried by the female and are surrounded by several membranes, some of which are impervious.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://tolweb.org/Amniota/14990 |title=Amniota |author1=Laurin, Michel |author2=Gauthier, Jacques A. |year=2012 |work=Tree of Life Web Project |accessdate=September 16, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lacking these membranes, amphibians require water bodies for reproduction, although some species have developed various strategies for protecting or bypassing the vulnerable aquatic larval stage.{{sfn | Dorit | Walker | Barnes | 1991 | pp=843–859 }} They are not found in the sea with the exception of one or two frogs that live in [[brackish water]] in [[mangrove]] swamps;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Introduction to the Biology of Marine Life |last=Sumich |first=James L. |author2= Morrissey, John F. |year=2004 |publisher=Jones &amp; Bartlett Learning |isbn=978-0-7637-3313-1 |page=171 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=Y8vTCze3dHgC&amp;dq=%22+amphibians+in+the+sea%3F%22&amp;q=Amphibians#v=snippet&amp;q=Amphibians&amp;f=false }}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Anderson's salamander]] meanwhile occurs in brackish or salt water lakes.&lt;ref&gt;Brad Shaffer; Oscar Flores-Villela; Gabriela Parra-Olea; David Wake (2004). &quot;Ambystoma andersoni&quot;. IUCN Red List of Threatened Species. Version 2013.2. International Union for Conservation of Nature&lt;/ref&gt; On land, amphibians are restricted to moist habitats because of the need to keep their skin damp.{{sfn | Dorit | Walker | Barnes | 1991 | pp=843–859 }}

The smallest amphibian (and vertebrate) in the world is a [[microhylid]] frog from [[New Guinea]] (''[[Paedophryne amauensis]]'') first discovered in 2012. It has an average length of {{convert|7.7|mm|in|abbr=on}} and is part of a genus that contains four of the world's ten smallest frog species.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Rittmeyer|first1=Eric N. |last2=Allison |first2=Allen |last3=Gründler |first3=Michael C. |last4=Thompson |first4=Derrick K. |last5=Austin |first5=Christopher C. |year=2012 |title=Ecological guild evolution and the discovery of the world's smallest vertebrate |journal=PLoS ONE |volume=7 |issue=1 |pages= e29797 |doi=10.1371/journal.pone.0029797 |pmid=22253785 |pmc=3256195|bibcode = 2012PLoSO...729797R }}&lt;/ref&gt; The largest living amphibian is the {{convert|1.8|m|0|abbr=on}} [[Chinese giant salamander]] (''Andrias davidianus'')&lt;ref name=&quot;Amphibianfacts&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://amphibiaweb.org/amphibian/facts.html|title=Amphibian Facts |author1=Nguyen, Brent |author2=Cavagnaro, John |date=July 2012 |publisher=AmphibiaWeb |accessdate=November 9, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; but this is a great deal smaller than the largest amphibian that ever existed—the extinct {{convert|9|m|0|abbr=on}} ''[[Prionosuchus]]'', a crocodile-like temnospondyl dating to 270 million years ago from the middle Permian of Brazil.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Price, L. I.|year=1948 |title=Um anfibio Labirinthodonte da formacao Pedra de Fogo, Estado do Maranhao |journal=Boletim |volume=24 |pages=7–32 |publisher=Ministerio da Agricultura, Departamento Nacional da Producao ineral Divisao de Geologia e Mineralogia}}&lt;/ref&gt; The largest frog is the African [[Goliath frog]] (''Conraua goliath''), which can reach {{convert|32|cm|0|abbr=on}} and weigh {{convert|3|kg|1|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amphibianfacts&quot; /&gt;

Amphibians are ectothermic (cold-blooded) vertebrates that do not maintain their body temperature through internal [[Physiology|physiological]] processes. Their [[Basal metabolic rate|metabolic rate]] is low and as a result, their food and energy requirements are limited. In the adult state, they have tear ducts and movable eyelids, and most species have ears that can detect airborne or ground vibrations. They have muscular tongues, which in many species can be protruded. Modern amphibians have fully [[Ossification|ossified]] vertebrae with [[articular processes]]. Their ribs are usually short and may be fused to the vertebrae. Their skulls are mostly broad and short, and are often incompletely ossified. Their skin contains little [[keratin]] and lacks scales, apart from a few fish-like scales in certain caecilians. The skin contains many [[mucous gland]]s and in some species, [[Skin|poison glands]] (a type of granular gland). The hearts of amphibians have three chambers, two [[atrium (heart)|atria]] and one [[ventricle (heart)|ventricle]]. They have a [[urinary bladder]] and nitrogenous waste products are excreted primarily as [[urea]]. Most amphibians lay their eggs in water and have aquatic larvae that undergo metamorphosis to become terrestrial adults. Amphibians breathe by means of a pump action in which air is first drawn into the [[Buccopharyngeal membrane|buccopharyngeal]] region through the nostrils. These are then closed and the air is forced into the lungs by contraction of the throat.{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | pp=24–25 }} They supplement this with [[gas exchange]] through the skin.{{sfn | Dorit | Walker | Barnes | 1991 | pp=843–859 }}

=== Anura ===
[[File:Red eyed tree frog edit2.jpg|thumb|alt=Red-eyed tree frog|[[Agalychnis callidryas|Red-eyed tree frog]] (''Agalychnis callidryas'') with limbs and feet specialised for climbing]]
The order [[Anura (frog)|Anura]] (from the Ancient Greek ''[[Privative a|a(n)-]]'' meaning &quot;without&quot; and ''oura'' meaning &quot;tail&quot;) comprises the frogs and toads. They usually have long hind limbs that fold underneath them, shorter forelimbs, webbed toes with no claws, no tails, large eyes and glandular moist skin.{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | p=3 }} Members of this order with smooth skins are commonly referred to as frogs, while those with [[wikt:warty|warty]] skins are known as toads. The difference is not a formal one taxonomically and there are numerous exceptions to this rule. Members of the family [[Bufonidae]] are known as the &quot;true toads&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.tolweb.org/Bufonidae |title=Bufonidae, True Toads |author1=Cannatella, David |author2=Graybeal, Anna |year=2008 |work=Tree of Life Web Project |accessdate=December 1, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Frogs range in size from the {{convert|30|cm|adj=on}} [[Goliath frog]] (''Conraua goliath'') of West Africa&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amnh.org/exhibitions/past-exhibitions/frogs-a-chorus-of-colors/frog-fun-facts|title=Frog fun facts |date=January 12, 2010 |publisher=American Museum of Natural History |accessdate=August 29, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; to the {{convert|7.7|mm|adj=on}} ''[[Paedophryne amauensis]]'', first described in Papua New Guinea in 2012, which is also the smallest known vertebrate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=World's smallest frog discovered in Papua New Guinea |author=Challenger, David |url=http://articles.cnn.com/2012-01-12/asia/world_asia_new-frogs_1_frog-papua-new-guinea-body-size?_s=PM:ASIA |newspaper=CNN |date=January 12, 2012 |accessdate=August 29, 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120420193348/http://articles.cnn.com/2012-01-12/asia/world_asia_new-frogs_1_frog-papua-new-guinea-body-size?_s=PM:ASIA |archivedate=April 20, 2012 |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Although most species are associated with water and damp habitats, some are specialised to live in trees or in deserts. They are found worldwide except for polar areas.&lt;ref name=&quot;Collins&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Reptiles and Amphibians of Britain and Europe |last1=Arnold |first1=Nicholas |last2=Ovenden |first2= Denys |year=2002 |publisher=Harper Collins Publishers |isbn=978-0-00-219318-4 |pages=13–18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Anura is divided into three suborders that are broadly accepted by the scientific community, but the relationships between some families remain unclear. Future [[molecular genetics|molecular]] studies should provide further insights into their evolutionary relationships.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Faivovich| first=J.|author2=Haddad, C. F. B.|author3= Garcia, P. C. A.|author4= Frost, D. R.|author5= Campbell, J. A.|author6= Wheeler, W. C.| title=Systematic review of the frog family Hylidae, with special reference to Hylinae: Phylogenetic analysis and revision| journal=Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History| volume=294| pages=1–240| doi=10.1206/0003-0090(2005)294[0001:SROTFF]2.0.CO;2| year=2005|citeseerx=10.1.1.470.2967}}&lt;/ref&gt; The suborder [[Archaeobatrachia]] contains four families of primitive frogs. These are [[Ascaphidae]], [[Bombinatoridae]], [[Discoglossidae]] and [[Leiopelmatidae]] which have few derived features and are probably paraphyletic with regard to other frog lineages.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ford&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Ford| first=L. S.|author2=Cannatella, D. C.| year=1993| title=The major clades of frogs| journal=Herpetological Monographs| volume=7| pages=94–117| doi=10.2307/1466954| jstor=1466954| url=https://www.academia.edu/11966468}}&lt;/ref&gt; The six families in the more evolutionarily advanced suborder [[Mesobatrachia]] are the [[fossorial]] [[Megophryidae]], [[Pelobatidae]], [[Pelodytidae]], [[Scaphiopodidae]] and [[Rhinophrynidae]] and the obligatorily aquatic [[Pipidae]]. These have certain characteristics that are intermediate between the two other suborders.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ford&quot; /&gt; [[Neobatrachia]] is by far the largest suborder and includes the remaining families of modern frogs, including most common species. Ninety-six percent of the over 5,000 extant species of frog are neobatrachians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last=San Mauro | first=Diego | title=Initial diversification of living amphibians predated the breakup of Pangaea | journal=American Naturalist | volume=165 | pages=590–599 | year=2005 |author2=Vences, Miguel|author3= Alcobendas, Marina|author4= Zardoya, Rafael|author5= Meyer, Axel | doi=10.1086/429523 | issue=5 | pmid=15795855 |url=http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:bsz:352-opus-33053 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Caudata ===
[[File:Cryptobranchus japonicus.jpg|thumb|left|upright|alt=Japanese giant salamander|[[Japanese giant salamander]] &lt;br&gt;(''Andrias japonicus''), a primitive salamander]]

The order [[Caudata]] (from the Latin ''cauda'' meaning &quot;tail&quot;) consists of the salamanders—elongated, low-slung animals that mostly resemble lizards in form. This is a [[Symplesiomorphy|symplesiomorphic trait]] and they are no more closely related to lizards than they are to mammals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nature.com/scitable/topicpage/trait-evolution-on-a-phylogenetic-tree-relatedness-41936|title=Trait Evolution on a Phylogenetic Tree: Relatedness, Similarity, and the Myth of Evolutionary Advancement |author=Baum, David |year=2008 |publisher=Nature Education |accessdate=December 1, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Salamanders lack claws, have scale-free skins, either smooth or covered with [[tubercle]]s, and tails that are usually flattened from side to side and often finned. They range in size from the [[Chinese giant salamander]] (''Andrias davidianus''), which has been reported to grow to a length of {{convert|1.8|m}},&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://amphibiaweb.org/cgi/amphib_query?where-genus=Andrias&amp;where-species=davidianus|title=''Andrias davidianus'' Chinese giant salamander |author=Sparreboom, Max |date=February 7, 2000 |publisher=AmphibiaWeb |accessdate=December 1, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; to the diminutive ''[[Thorius pennatulus]]'' from Mexico which seldom exceeds {{convert|20|mm|1|abbr=on}} in length.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://amphibiaweb.org/cgi/amphib_query?where-genus=Thorius&amp;where-species=pennatulus|title=''Thorius pennatulus'' |author=Wake, David B. |date=November 8, 2000 |publisher=AmphibiaWeb |accessdate=August 25, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Salamanders have a mostly [[Laurasia]]n distribution, being present in much of the [[Holarctic]] region of the northern hemisphere. The family [[Plethodontidae]] is also found in Central America and South America north of the [[Amazon basin]];&lt;ref name=&quot;Collins&quot; /&gt; South America was apparently invaded from Central America by about the start of the [[Miocene]], 23 million years ago.&lt;ref name=&quot;Elmer2013&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Elmer|first1=K. R.|last2=Bonett|first2=R. M.|last3=Wake|first3=D. B.|last4=Lougheed|first4=S. C.|title=Early Miocene origin and cryptic diversification of South American salamanders|journal=BMC Evolutionary Biology|volume= 13|issue=1|date= 2013-03-04|pages= 59|doi= 10.1186/1471-2148-13-59|pmid=23497060|pmc=3602097}}&lt;/ref&gt; Urodela is a name sometimes used for all the [[extant taxon|extant]] species of salamanders.&lt;ref name=&quot;larson&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal| last=Larson | first=A. | last2=Dimmick | first2=W. | year=1993 | title=Phylogenetic relationships of the salamander families: an analysis of the congruence among morphological and molecular characters | journal=Herpetological Monographs | volume=7 | issue=7 | pages=77–93 | doi =10.2307/1466953 | jstor=1466953}}&lt;/ref&gt; Members of several salamander families have become [[Neoteny|paedomorphic]] and either fail to complete their metamorphosis or retain some larval characteristics as adults.{{sfn | Dorit | Walker | Barnes | 1991 | p=852}} Most salamanders are under {{convert|15|cm|0|abbr=on}} long. They may be terrestrial or aquatic and many spend part of the year in each habitat. When on land, they mostly spend the day hidden under stones or logs or in dense vegetation, emerging in the evening and night to forage for worms, insects and other invertebrates.&lt;ref name=&quot;Collins&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Triturus dobrogicus dunai tarajosgőte.jpg|thumb|alt=Danube crested newt|[[Danube crested newt]] &lt;br&gt;(''Triturus dobrogicus''), an advanced salamander]]

The suborder [[Cryptobranchoidea]] contains the primitive salamanders. A number of fossil cryptobranchids have been found, but there are only three living species, the Chinese giant salamander (''Andrias davidianus''), the [[Japanese giant salamander]] (''Andrias japonicus'') and the [[hellbender]] (''Cryptobranchus alleganiensis'') from North America. These large amphibians retain several larval characteristics in their adult state; gills slits are present and the eyes are unlidded. A unique feature is their ability to feed by suction, depressing either the left side of their lower jaw or the right.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADWCrypto&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://animaldiversity.ummz.umich.edu/site/accounts/information/Cryptobranchidae.html | title=Cryptobranchidae | author=Heying, Heather | year=2003 | work=Animal Diversity Web | publisher=University of Michigan | accessdate=August 25, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The males excavate nests, persuade females to lay their egg strings inside them, and guard them. As well as breathing with lungs, they respire through the many folds in their thin skin, which has [[Capillary|capillaries]] close to the surface.&lt;ref name=&quot;EHSAR&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.fws.gov/midwest/es/soc/amphibians/eahe-sa.pdf | title=Eastern Hellbender Status Assessment Report |author1=Mayasich, J. |author2=Grandmaison, D. |author3=Phillips, C. | date=June 1, 2003 | publisher=U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service | accessdate=August 25, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The suborder [[Salamandroidea]] contains the advanced salamanders. They differ from the cryptobranchids by having fused [[Mandible|prearticular bones]] in the lower jaw, and by using internal fertilisation. In salamandrids, the male deposits a bundle of sperm, the [[spermatophore]], and the female picks it up and inserts it into her cloaca where the sperm is stored until the eggs are laid.&lt;ref name=&quot;BritCaudata&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/100353/Caudata |title=Caudata |author=Wake, David B |encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Britannica Online |publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica |accessdate=August 25, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The largest family in this group is Plethodontidae, the lungless salamanders, which includes 60% of all salamander species. The [[Family (biology)|family]] [[Salamandridae]] includes the true salamanders and the name &quot;[[newt]]&quot; is given to members of its subfamily [[Pleurodelinae]].{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | p=3 }}

The third suborder, [[Sirenoidea]], contains the four species of sirens, which are in a single family, [[Sirenidae]]. Members of this order are [[eel]]-like aquatic salamanders with much reduced forelimbs and no hind limbs. Some of their features are primitive while others are derived.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Cogger, H. G. |editor=Zweifel, R. G |year=1998 |title=Encyclopedia of Reptiles and Amphibians |publisher= Academic Press |pages= 69–70 |isbn=978-0-12-178560-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fertilisation is likely to be external as sirenids lack the cloacal glands used by male salamandrids to produce spermatophores and the females lack [[spermatheca]]e for sperm storage. Despite this, the eggs are laid singly, a behaviour not conducive for external fertilisation.&lt;ref name=&quot;BritCaudata&quot; /&gt;

=== Gymnophiona ===
[[File:Siphonops paulensis02.jpg|thumb|alt=''Siphonops paulensis''|The limbless South American caecilian ''[[Siphonops paulensis]]'']]
The order [[Gymnophiona]] (from the Greek ''gymnos'' meaning &quot;naked&quot; and ''ophis'' meaning &quot;serpent&quot;) or Apoda comprises the caecilians. These are long, cylindrical, limbless animals with a snake- or [[Annelid|worm-like]] form. The adults vary in length from 8 to 75 centimetres (3 to 30 inches) with the exception of [[Caecilia thompsoni|Thomson's caecilian]] (''Caecilia thompsoni''), which can reach {{convert|150|cm|ft|abbr=off}}. A caecilian's skin has a large number of transverse folds and in some species contains tiny embedded dermal scales. It has rudimentary eyes covered in skin, which are probably limited to discerning differences in light intensity. It also has a pair of short [[tentacle]]s near the eye that can be extended and which have [[Somatosensory system|tactile]] and [[Olfaction|olfactory]] functions. Most caecilians live underground in burrows in damp soil, in rotten wood and under plant debris, but some are aquatic.{{sfn| Stebbins| Cohen | 1995 | p=4}} Most species lay their eggs underground and when the larvae hatch, they make their way to adjacent bodies of water. Others brood their eggs and the larvae undergo metamorphosis before the eggs hatch. A few species give birth to live young, nourishing them with glandular secretions while they are in the oviduct.{{sfn | Dorit | Walker | Barnes | 1991 | p=858}} Caecilians have a mostly [[Gondwana]]n distribution, being found in tropical regions of Africa, Asia and Central and South America.&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/29797/Gymnophiona |title=Gymnophiona |author=Duellman, William E. |encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Britannica Online |publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica |accessdate=September 30, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Anatomy and physiology ==

=== Skin ===
[[File:Tree frog congo.jpg|thumb|left|upright|alt=Common reed frog|The [[Aposematism|bright colours]] of the [[common reed frog]] (''Hyperolius viridiflavus'') are typical of a toxic species]]
The [[Wikt:integument|integumentary]] structure contains some typical characteristics common to terrestrial vertebrates, such as the presence of highly [[Keratin#Cornification|cornified]] outer layers, renewed periodically through a moulting process controlled by the [[pituitary gland|pituitary]] and [[thyroid]] glands. Local thickenings (often called warts) are common, such as those found on toads. The outside of the skin is shed periodically mostly in one piece, in contrast to mammals and birds where it is shed in flakes. Amphibians often eat the sloughed skin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Collins&quot; /&gt; Caecilians are unique among amphibians in having mineralized dermal scales embedded in the [[dermis]] between the furrows in the skin. The similarity of these to the scales of bony fish is largely superficial. [[Squamata|Lizards]] and some frogs have somewhat similar [[osteoderm]]s forming bony deposits in the dermis, but this is an example of [[convergent evolution]] with similar structures having arisen independently in diverse vertebrate lineages.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Zylberberg, Louise |author2=Wake, Marvalee H. |year=1990 |title=Structure of the scales of ''Dermophis'' and ''Microcaecilia'' (Amphibia: Gymnophiona), and a comparison to dermal ossifications of other vertebrates |journal=Journal of Morphology |volume=206 |issue=1 |pages=25–43 |doi=10.1002/jmor.1052060104 |url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/227806326 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:FrogSkin.png|thumb|upright=1.35|Cross section of frog skin. A: Mucous gland, B: Chromatophore, C: Granular poison gland, D: [[Connective tissue]], E: [[Stratum corneum]], F: Transition zone, G: [[Epidermis]], H: [[Dermis]]]]
Amphibian skin is permeable to water. Gas exchange can take place through the skin ([[cutaneous respiration]]) and this allows adult amphibians to respire without rising to the surface of water and to hibernate at the bottom of ponds.&lt;ref name=&quot;Collins&quot; /&gt; To compensate for their thin and delicate skin, amphibians have evolved mucous glands, principally on their heads, backs and tails. The secretions produced by these help keep the skin moist. In addition, most species of amphibian have granular glands that secrete distasteful or poisonous substances. Some amphibian toxins can be lethal to humans while others have little effect.&lt;ref name=&quot;amphibfacts&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eoearth.org/article/Amphibian_morphology_and_reproduction |title=Amphibian morphology and reproduction |date=October 12, 2008 |authors=Biodiversity Institute of Ontario; Hebert, Paul D. N. |encyclopedia=Encyclopedia of Earth |accessdate=August 15, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The main poison-producing glands, the [[Parotoid gland|paratoids]], produce the neurotoxin [[bufotoxin]] and are located behind the ears of toads, along the backs of frogs, behind the eyes of salamanders and on the upper surface of caecilians.{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | pp=10–11 }}

The skin colour of amphibians is produced by three layers of pigment cells called [[chromatophore]]s. These three cell layers consist of the melanophores (occupying the deepest layer), the guanophores (forming an intermediate layer and containing many granules, producing a blue-green colour) and the lipophores (yellow, the most superficial layer). The colour change displayed by many species is initiated by [[hormone]]s secreted by the pituitary gland. Unlike bony fish, there is no direct control of the pigment cells by the nervous system, and this results in the colour change taking place more slowly than happens in fish. A vividly coloured skin usually indicates that the species is toxic and is a warning sign to predators.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Integument: A Textbook of Skin Biology |last=Spearman |first=R. I. C. |year=1973 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=978-0-521-20048-6 |page=81 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=F7A8AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA81&amp;lpg=PA81&amp;dq=Amphibian+%22skin+colour%22#v=onepage&amp;q=Amphibian%20%22skin%20colour%22&amp;f=false }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Skeletal system and locomotion ===
Amphibians have a skeletal system that is structurally [[Homology (biology)|homologous]] to other tetrapods, though with a number of variations. They all have four limbs except for the legless caecilians and a few species of salamander with reduced or no limbs. The bones are hollow and lightweight. The musculoskeletal system is strong to enable it to support the head and body. The bones are fully [[ossification|ossified]] and the vertebrae interlock with each other by means of overlapping processes. The [[pectoral girdle]] is supported by muscle, and the well-developed [[pelvic girdle]] is attached to the backbone by a pair of sacral ribs. The [[ilium (bone)|ilium]] slopes forward and the body is held closer to the ground than is the case in mammals.{{sfn | Dorit | Walker | Barnes | 1991 | p=846 }}

[[File:Ceratophrys cornuta skeleton front.jpg|thumb|alt=Frog skeleton|Skeleton of the [[Surinam horned frog]]&lt;br&gt;(''Ceratophrys cornuta'')]]
In most amphibians, there are four digits on the fore foot and five on the hind foot, but no claws on either. Some salamanders have fewer digits and the [[amphiuma]]s are eel-like in appearance with tiny, stubby legs. The [[Siren (genus)|sirens]] are aquatic salamanders with stumpy forelimbs and no hind limbs. The caecilians are limbless. They burrow in the manner of earthworms with zones of muscle contractions moving along the body. On the surface of the ground or in water they move by undulating their body from side to side.{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | pp=26–36 }}

In frogs, the hind legs are larger than the fore legs, especially so in those species that principally move by jumping or swimming. In the walkers and runners the hind limbs are not so large, and the burrowers mostly have short limbs and broad bodies. The feet have adaptations for the way of life, with webbing between the toes for swimming, broad adhesive toe pads for climbing, and keratinised tubercles on the hind feet for digging (frogs usually dig backwards into the soil). In most salamanders, the limbs are short and more or less the same length and project at right angles from the body. Locomotion on land is by walking and the tail often swings from side to side or is used as a prop, particularly when climbing. In their normal gait, only one leg is advanced at a time in the manner adopted by their ancestors, the lobe-finned fish.{{sfn | Dorit | Walker | Barnes | 1991 | p=846 }} Some salamanders in the genus ''[[Aneides]]'' and certain [[lungless salamander|plethodontids]] climb trees and have long limbs, large toepads and prehensile tails.&lt;ref name=&quot;BritCaudata&quot; /&gt; In aquatic salamanders and in frog tadpoles, the tail has [[dorsal fin|dorsal]] and [[ventral fin|ventral]] fins and is moved from side to side as a means of propulsion. Adult frogs do not have tails and caecilians have only very short ones.{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | pp=26–36 }}

Salamanders use their tails in defence and some are prepared to jettison them to save their lives in a process known as [[autotomy]]. Certain species in the Plethodontidae have a weak zone at the base of the tail and use this strategy readily. The tail often continues to twitch after separation which may distract the attacker and allow the salamander to escape. Both tails and limbs can be regenerated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Beneski&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | author=Beneski, John T. Jr. | date=September 1989 | title=Adaptive significance of tail autotomy in the salamander, ''Ensatina'' | journal=Journal of Herpetology | volume=23 | issue=3 | pages=322–324 | doi=10.2307/1564465 | jstor=1564465 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Adult frogs are unable to regrow limbs but tadpoles can do so.{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | pp=26–36 }}

=== Circulatory system ===
[[File:Didactic model of an amphibian heart-FMVZ USP-14.jpg|thumb|left|upright=0.65|[[Educational toy|Didactic model]] of an amphibian heart.]]
[[File:Juvenile Amphibian Circulatory System.svg|thumb|Juvenile amphibian circulatory systems are single loop systems which resemble fish.&lt;br&gt; 1 – Internal gills where the blood is reoxygenated&lt;br&gt;2 – Point where the blood is depleted of oxygen and returns to the heart via veins&lt;br&gt;3 – Two chambered heart.&lt;br&gt;Red indicates oxygenated blood, and blue represents oxygen depleted blood.]]
Amphibians have a juvenile stage and an adult stage, and the circulatory systems of the two are distinct. In the juvenile (or tadpole) stage, the circulation is similar to that of a fish; the two-chambered heart pumps the blood through the gills where it is oxygenated, and is spread around the body and back to the heart in a single loop. In the adult stage, amphibians (especially frogs) lose their gills and develop lungs. They have a heart that consists of a single ventricle and two atria. When the ventricle starts contracting, deoxygenated blood is pumped through the [[pulmonary artery]] to the lungs. Continued contraction then pumps oxygenated blood around the rest of the body. Mixing of the two bloodstreams is minimized by the anatomy of the chambers.{{sfn | Dorit | Walker | Barnes | 1991 | p=306 }}

=== Nervous and sensory systems ===
The [[nervous system]] is basically the same as in other vertebrates, with a central brain, a spinal cord, and nerves throughout the body. The amphibian brain is less well developed than that of reptiles, birds and mammals but is similar in morphology and function to that of a fish. It is believed amphibians are capable of perceiving [[Pain in amphibians|pain]].  The brain consists of equal parts, [[cerebrum]], [[midbrain]] and [[cerebellum]]. Various parts of the cerebrum process sensory input, such as smell in the olfactory lobe and sight in the optic lobe, and it is additionally the centre of behaviour and learning. The cerebellum is the center of muscular coordination and the [[medulla oblongata]] controls some organ functions including heartbeat and respiration. The brain sends signals through the spinal cord and nerves to regulate activity in the rest of the body. The [[pineal body]], known to regulate sleep patterns in humans, is thought to produce the hormones involved in [[hibernation]] and [[aestivation]] in amphibians.{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | p=100 }}

Tadpoles retain the lateral line system of their ancestral fishes, but this is lost in terrestrial adult amphibians. Some caecilians possess [[Electroreception|electroreceptors]] that allow them to locate objects around them when submerged in water. The ears are well developed in frogs. There is no external ear, but the large circular [[Tympanum (anatomy)|eardrum]] lies on the surface of the head just behind the eye. This vibrates and sound is transmitted through a single bone, the [[stapes]], to the inner ear. Only high-frequency sounds like mating calls are heard in this way, but low-frequency noises can be detected through another mechanism.{{sfn | Dorit | Walker | Barnes | 1991 | p=846 }} There is a patch of specialized haircells, called ''papilla amphibiorum'', in the inner ear capable of detecting deeper sounds. Another feature, unique to frogs and salamanders, is the columella-operculum complex adjoining the auditory capsule which is involved in the transmission of both airborne and seismic signals.{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | p=69 }} The ears of salamanders and caecilians are less highly developed than those of frogs as they do not normally communicate with each other through the medium of sound.&lt;ref name=&quot;EBAmphibia&quot; /&gt;

The eyes of tadpoles lack lids, but at metamorphosis, the [[cornea]] becomes more dome-shaped, the [[Lens (anatomy)|lens]] becomes flatter, and [[eyelid]]s and associated glands and ducts develop.{{sfn | Dorit | Walker | Barnes | 1991 | p=846 }} The adult eyes are an improvement on invertebrate eyes and were a first step in the development of more advanced vertebrate eyes. They allow colour vision and depth of focus. In the retinas are green rods, which are receptive to a wide range of wavelengths.&lt;ref name=&quot;EBAmphibia&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/21445/amphibian/ |title=Amphibian |author1=Duellman, William E. |author2=Zug, George R. |year=2012 |encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Britannica Online |publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica |accessdate=March 27, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Digestive and excretory systems ===
[[File:Frog anatomy tags.PNG|thumb|alt=Dissected frog|Dissected frog: 1&amp;nbsp;Right&amp;nbsp;atrium, 2&amp;nbsp;Liver, 3&amp;nbsp;Aorta, 4&amp;nbsp;Egg mass, 5&amp;nbsp;Colon, 6&amp;nbsp;Left&amp;nbsp;atrium, 7&amp;nbsp;Ventricle, 8&amp;nbsp;Stomach, 9&amp;nbsp;Left lung, 10&amp;nbsp;Spleen, 11&amp;nbsp;Small&amp;nbsp;intestine, 12&amp;nbsp;Cloaca]]
Many amphibians catch their prey by flicking out an elongated tongue with a sticky tip and drawing it back into the mouth before seizing the item with their jaws. Some use inertial feeding to help them swallow the prey, repeatedly thrusting their head forward sharply causing the food to move backwards in their mouth by [[inertia]]. Most amphibians swallow their prey whole without much chewing so they possess voluminous stomachs. The short [[Esophagus|oesophagus]] is lined with [[Cilium|cilia]] that help to move the food to the stomach and [[mucus]] produced by glands in the mouth and [[pharynx]] eases its passage. The enzyme [[chitinase]] produced in the stomach helps digest the [[chitin]]ous cuticle of arthropod prey.{{sfn | Dorit | Walker | Barnes | 1991 | p=847 }}

Amphibians possess a [[pancreas]], [[liver]] and [[gall bladder]]. The liver is usually large with two lobes. Its size is determined by its function as a [[glycogen]] and fat storage unit, and may change with the seasons as these reserves are built or used up. [[Adipose tissue]] is another important means of storing energy and this occurs in the abdomen (in internal structures called fat bodies), under the skin and, in some salamanders, in the tail.{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | p=66 }}
&lt;!--In aquatic amphibians, the liver plays only a small role in processing nitrogen for excretion, and [[ammonia]] is diffused mainly through the skin. The liver of terrestrial amphibians converts ammonia to urea, a less toxic, water-soluble nitrogenous compound, as a means of water conservation. In some species, urea is further converted into [[uric acid]]. [[Bile]] secretions from the liver collect in the gall bladder and flow into the small intestine. In the small intestine, enzymes digest carbohydrates, fats, and proteins. Salamanders lack a valve separating the small intestine from the large intestine. Salt and water absorption occur in the large intestine, as well as mucous secretion to aid in the transport of faecal matter, which is passed out through the [[cloaca]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Anatomy&quot; /&gt;---Omitting this until a more reliable source can be found.---&gt;

There are two [[kidney]]s located dorsally, near the roof of the body cavity. Their job is to filter the blood of metabolic waste and transport the urine via ureters to the urinary bladder where it is stored before being passed out periodically through the cloacal vent. Larvae and most aquatic adult amphibians excrete the nitrogen as ammonia in large quantities of dilute urine, while terrestrial species, with a greater need to conserve water, excrete the less toxic product urea. Some tree frogs with limited access to water excrete most of their metabolic waste as uric acid.{{sfn | Dorit | Walker | Barnes | 1991 | p=849 }}

=== Respiratory system ===
[[File:Axolotl ganz.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Axolotl|The [[axolotl]] (''Ambystoma mexicanum'') retains its larval form with gills into adulthood]]
The lungs in amphibians are primitive compared to those of amniotes, possessing few internal [[alveolar septum|septa]] and large [[Pulmonary alveolus|alveoli]], and consequently having a comparatively slow diffusion rate for oxygen entering the blood. Ventilation is accomplished by [[buccal pumping]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Brainerd|first1=E. L. |title=New perspectives on the evolution of lung ventilation mechanisms in vertebrates |journal=Experimental Biology Online |year=1999 |volume=4 |issue=2 |pages=1–28 |doi=10.1007/s00898-999-0002-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Most amphibians, however, are able to exchange gases with the water or air via their skin. To enable sufficient [[cutaneous respiration]], the surface of their highly vascularised skin must remain moist to allow the oxygen to diffuse at a sufficiently high rate.{{sfn | Dorit | Walker | Barnes | 1991 | p=847 }} Because oxygen concentration in the water increases at both low temperatures and high flow rates, aquatic amphibians in these situations can rely primarily on cutaneous respiration, as in the [[Telmatobius culeus|Titicaca water frog]] and the [[Cryptobranchus|hellbender salamander]]. In air, where oxygen is more concentrated, some small species can rely solely on cutaneous gas exchange, most famously the [[Plethodontidae|plethodontid salamanders]], which have neither lungs nor gills. Many aquatic salamanders and all tadpoles have gills in their larval stage, with some (such as the [[axolotl]]) retaining gills as aquatic adults.{{sfn | Dorit | Walker | Barnes | 1991 | p=847 }}

== Reproduction ==
{{see also|Sexual selection in amphibians}}
[[File:Litoria xanthomera amplexus.jpg|thumb|alt=Orange-thighed frogs in amplexus|Male [[orange-thighed frog]] (''Litoria xanthomera'') grasping the female during [[amplexus]]]]
For the purpose of [[Biological reproduction|reproduction]] most amphibians require [[fresh water]] although some lay their eggs on land and have developed various means of keeping them moist. A few (e.g. ''[[Fejervarya raja]]'') can inhabit brackish water, but there are no true [[marine (ocean)|marine]] amphibians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Hopkins Gareth R. |author2=Brodie Edmund D., Jr | year = 2015 | title = Occurrence of Amphibians in Saline Habitats: A Review and Evolutionary Perspective | journal = Herpetological Monographs | volume = 29 | issue = 1| pages = 1–27 | doi = 10.1655/HERPMONOGRAPHS-D-14-00006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; There are reports, however, of particular amphibian populations unexpectedly invading marine waters. Such was the case with the [[Black Sea]] invasion of the natural hybrid ''[[Pelophylax esculentus]]'' reported in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Natchev, Nikolay |author2=Tzankov, Nikolay |author3=Geme, Richard |year=2011 |title=Green frog invasion in the Black Sea: habitat ecology of the ''Pelophylax esculentus'' complex (Anura, Amphibia) population in the region of Shablenska Тuzla lagoon in Bulgaria |journal=Herpetology Notes |volume=4 |pages=347–351 |url=http://www.herpetologynotes.seh-herpetology.org/Volume4_PDFs/Natchev_et_al_Herpetology_Notes_Volume4_pages347-351.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several hundred frog species in [[adaptive radiation]]s (e.g., ''[[Eleutherodactylus]]'', the Pacific ''[[Platymantis]]'', the Australo-Papuan [[microhylid]]s, and many other tropical frogs), however, do not need any water for [[breeding in the wild]]. They reproduce via direct development, an ecological and evolutionary adaptation that has allowed them to be completely independent from free-standing water. Almost all of these frogs live in wet [[Tropical and subtropical moist broadleaf forests|tropical rainforests]] and their eggs hatch directly into miniature versions of the adult, passing through the [[tadpole]] stage within the egg. Reproductive success of many amphibians is dependent not only on the quantity of rainfall, but the seasonal timing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eoearth.org/article/Abiotic_factor?topic=49461 |title=Abiotic factor |author=Hogan, C. Michael |date=July 31, 2010 |encyclopedia=Encyclopedia of Earth |publisher=National Council for Science and the Environment |accessdate=September 30, 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130608071757/http://www.eoearth.org/article/Abiotic_factor?topic=49461 |archivedate=June 8, 2013 |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the tropics, many amphibians breed continuously or at any time of year. In temperate regions, breeding is mostly seasonal, usually in the spring, and is triggered by increasing day length, rising temperatures or rainfall. Experiments have shown the importance of temperature, but the trigger event, especially in arid regions, is often a storm. In anurans, males usually arrive at the breeding sites before females and the vocal chorus they produce may stimulate ovulation in females and the endocrine activity of males that are not yet reproductively active.{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | pp=140–141 }}

In caecilians, fertilisation is internal, the male extruding an [[intromittent organ]], the phallodeum, and inserting it into the female cloaca. The paired Müllerian glands inside the male cloaca secrete a fluid which resembles that produced by mammalian [[prostate]] glands and which may transport and nourish the sperm. Fertilisation probably takes place in the oviduct.&lt;ref name=&quot;Duellman&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Biology of Amphibians |last=Duellman|first=Willia E. |author2= Trueb, Linda |year=1994 |publisher=JHU Press |isbn=978-0-8018-4780-6 |pages=77–79 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=CzxVvKmrtIgC&amp;pg=PA77&amp;lpg=PA77&amp;dq=phallodeum#v=onepage&amp;q=phallodeum&amp;f=false }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The majority of salamanders also engage in internal fertilisation. In most of these, the male deposits a spermatophore, a small packet of sperm on top of a gelatinous cone, on the [[Substrate (biology)|substrate]] either on land or in the water. The female takes up the sperm packet by grasping it with the lips of the cloaca and pushing it into the vent. The spermatozoa move to the spermatheca in the roof of the cloaca where they remain until ovulation which may be many months later. Courtship rituals and methods of transfer of the spermatophore vary between species. In some, the spermatophore may be placed directly into the female cloaca while in others, the female may be guided to the spermatophore or restrained with an embrace called [[amplexus]]. Certain primitive salamanders in the families Sirenidae, [[Hynobiidae]] and [[Cryptobranchidae]] practice external fertilisation in a similar manner to frogs, with the female laying the eggs in water and the male releasing sperm onto the egg mass.&lt;ref name=&quot;Duellman&quot; /&gt;

With a few exceptions, frogs use external fertilisation. The male grasps the female tightly with his forelimbs either behind the arms or in front of the back legs, or in the case of ''[[Epipedobates tricolor]]'', around the neck. They remain in amplexus with their cloacae positioned close together while the female lays the eggs and the male covers them with sperm. Roughened nuptial pads on the male's hands aid in retaining grip. Often the male collects and retains the egg mass, forming a sort of basket with the hind feet. An exception is the [[granular poison frog]] (''Oophaga granulifera'') where the male and female place their cloacae in close proximity while facing in opposite directions and then release eggs and sperm simultaneously. The [[tailed frog]] (''Ascaphus truei'') exhibits internal fertilisation. The &quot;tail&quot; is only possessed by the male and is an extension of the cloaca and used to inseminate the female. This frog lives in fast-flowing streams and internal fertilisation prevents the sperm from being washed away before fertilisation occurs.{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | pp=154–162 }} The sperm may be retained in storage tubes attached to the [[oviduct]] until the following spring.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://amphibiaweb.org/cgi/amphib_query?where-genus=Ascaphus&amp;where-species=truei |title=''Ascaphus truei'' |author1=Adams, Michael J. |author2=Pearl, Christopher A. |year=2005 |publisher=AmphibiaWeb |accessdate=November 23, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Most frogs can be classified as either prolonged or explosive breeders. Typically, prolonged breeders congregate at a breeding site, the males usually arriving first, calling and setting up territories. Other satellite males remain quietly nearby, waiting for their opportunity to take over a territory. The females arrive sporadically, mate selection takes place and eggs are laid. The females depart and territories may change hands. More females appear and in due course, the breeding season comes to an end. Explosive breeders on the other hand are found where temporary pools appear in dry regions after rainfall. These frogs are typically [[wikt:fossorial|fossorial]] species that emerge after heavy rains and congregate at a breeding site. They are attracted there by the calling of the first male to find a suitable place, perhaps a pool that forms in the same place each rainy season. The assembled frogs may call in unison and frenzied activity ensues, the males scrambling to mate with the usually smaller number of females.{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | pp=154–162 }}

[[File:Plethodon cinereus.jpg|right|thumb|upright=1.1|Sexual selection has been studied in the [[red back salamander]]]]
&lt;!--[[Sexual selection]] typically manifests as male-male competition where males will arrive at the waters edge first in large number, producing a wide range of vocalizations and other complex behaviours to attract mates, with the [[fitness (biology)|fittest]] males having the deepest croaks and the best territories. It also exists as [[mate choice]], with females known to choose a mate, at least partly based on the male's depth of croaking. This has led to [[sexual dimorphism]], with females being larger than males in 90% of species, males larger in 10% of species and males fighting for groups of females.--&gt;

There is a direct competition between males to win the attention of the females in salamanders and newts, with elaborate courtship displays to keep the female's attention long enough to get her interested in choosing him to [[mating|mate]] with.&lt;ref name=romano&gt;{{cite journal|last=Romano|first=Antonio|author2=Bruni, Giacomo |title=Courtship behaviour, mating season and male sexual interference in ''Salamandrina perspicillata''|journal=Amphibia-Reptilia|year=2011|volume=32|issue=1|pages=63–76|doi=10.1163/017353710X541878|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some species store [[sperm]] through long breeding seasons, as the extra time may allow for interactions with rival sperm.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Adams|first=Erika M.|author2=Jones, A. G. |author3=Arnold, S. J. |title=Multiple paternity in a natural population of a salamander with long-term sperm storage |journal=Molecular Ecology |year=2005 |volume=14 |issue=6 |pages=1803–1810 |doi=10.1111/j.1365-294X.2005.02539.x |pmid=15836651|url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/7899857 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Life cycle ==
Most amphibians go through [[metamorphosis]], a process of significant morphological change after birth. In typical amphibian development, eggs are laid in water and larvae are adapted to an aquatic lifestyle. Frogs, toads and salamanders all hatch from the egg as larvae with external gills. Metamorphosis in amphibians is regulated by [[thyroxine]] concentration in the blood, which stimulates metamorphosis, and [[prolactin]], which counteracts thyroxine's effect. Specific events are dependent on threshold values for different tissues.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| last1 = Kikuyama | first1 = Sakae
 | last2 = Kawamura | first2 = Kousuke
 | last3 = Tanaka | first3 = Shigeyasu
 | last4 = Yamamoto | first4 = Kakutoshi
 | title = International Review of Cytology: A Survey of Cell Biology
 | chapter = Aspects of amphibian metamorphosis: Hormonal control
 | publisher = Academic Press
 | pages = 105–126
 | year = 1993
 | chapter-url = https://books.google.com/?id=wfSM70CuYqYC&amp;pg=PA105&amp;dq=amphibian+metamorphosis#v=onepage&amp;q=amphibian%20metamorphosis&amp;f=false
 | isbn = 978-0-12-364548-7
 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Because most embryonic development is outside the parental body, it is subject to many adaptations due to specific environmental circumstances. For this reason tadpoles can have horny ridges instead of teeth, whisker-like skin extensions or fins. They also make use of a sensory lateral line organ similar to that of fish. After metamorphosis, these organs become redundant and will be reabsorbed by controlled cell death, called [[apoptosis]]. The variety of adaptations to specific environmental circumstances among amphibians is wide, with many discoveries still being made.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Newman, Robert A. |year=1992 |title=Adaptive plasticity in amphibian metamorphosis |journal=BioScience |volume=42 |issue=9 |pages=671–678 |doi= 10.2307/1312173 |jstor=1312173}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Eggs ===
[[File:Frogspawn closeup.jpg|thumb|alt=Frogspawn|Frogspawn, a mass of eggs surrounded by jelly]]
[[File:Amphibian Egg Diagram.svg|thumb|Amphibian egg:&lt;br&gt; 1. Jelly capsule 2. Vitelline membrane &lt;br&gt; 3. Perivitelline fluid 4. [[Yolk plug]] &lt;br&gt; 5. Embryo]]

The egg of an amphibian is typically surrounded by a transparent gelatinous covering secreted by the oviducts and containing [[mucoprotein]]s and [[mucopolysaccharide]]s. This capsule is permeable to water and gases, and swells considerably as it absorbs water. The ovum is at first rigidly held, but in fertilised eggs the innermost layer liquefies and allows the [[embryo]] to move freely. This also happens in salamander eggs, even when they are unfertilised. Eggs of some salamanders and frogs contain unicellular green algae. These penetrate the jelly envelope after the eggs are laid and may increase the supply of oxygen to the embryo through photosynthesis. They seem to both speed up the development of the larvae and reduce mortality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Gilbert, Perry W. |year=1942 |title=Observations on the eggs of ''Ambystoma maculatum'' with especial reference to the green algae found within the egg envelopes |journal=Ecology |volume=23 |pages=215–227 |jstor=1931088 |doi=10.2307/1931088 |issue=2 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Most eggs contain the pigment [[melanin]] which raises their temperature through the absorption of light and also protects them against [[ultraviolet radiation]]. Caecilians, some [[plethodontid]] salamanders and certain frogs lay eggs underground that are unpigmented. In the [[wood frog]] (''Rana sylvatica''), the interior of the globular egg cluster has been found to be up to {{convert|6|C-change|F-change}} warmer than its surroundings, which is an advantage in its cool northern habitat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Waldman, Bruce |author2=Ryan, Michael J. |year=1983 |title=Thermal advantages of communal egg mass deposition in wood frogs (''Rana sylvatica'') |journal=Journal of Herpetology |volume=17 |issue=1 |pages=70–72 |jstor=1563783 |doi=10.2307/1563783|url=https://www.academia.edu/14057397 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The eggs may be deposited singly or in small groups, or may take the form of spherical egg masses, rafts or long strings. In terrestrial caecilians, the eggs are laid in grape-like clusters in burrows near streams. The amphibious salamander ''[[Ensatina]]'' attaches its similar clusters by stalks to underwater stems and roots. The [[Eleutherodactylus planirostris|greenhouse frog]] (''Eleutherodactylus planirostris'') lays eggs in small groups in the soil where they develop in about two weeks directly into juvenile frogs without an intervening larval stage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://amphibiaweb.org/cgi-bin/amphib_query?query_src=aw_search_index&amp;where-genus=Eleutherodactylus&amp;where-species=planirostris |title=''Eleutherodactylus planirostris'' |author=Meshaka, Walter E. Jr |publisher=AmphibiaWeb |accessdate=December 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[tungara frog]] (''Physalaemus pustulosus'') builds a floating nest from foam to protect its eggs. First a raft is built, then eggs are laid in the centre, and finally a foam cap is overlaid. The foam has anti-microbial properties. It contains no [[detergent]]s but is created by whipping up [[protein]]s and [[lectin]]s secreted by the female.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Dalgetty, Laura |author2=Kennedy, Malcolm W. |year=2010 |title=Building a home from foam: túngara frog foam nest architecture and three-phase construction process |journal=Biology Letters |volume=6 |issue=3 |pages=293–296 |doi=10.1098/rsbl.2009.0934 |pmid=20106853 |pmc=2880057 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gla.ac.uk/schools/lifesciences/staff/malcolmkennedy/malcolmkennedy/proteinsoffrogfoamnests/ |title=Proteins of frog foam nests |publisher=School of Life Sciences, University of Glasgow |accessdate=August 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Larvae ===
[[File:Frog spawn time-lapse.gif|thumb|left|alt=Frog spawn development|Early stages in the development of the embryos of the [[common frog]] (''Rana temporaria'')]]
The eggs of amphibians are typically laid in water and hatch into free-living larvae that complete their development in water and later transform into either aquatic or terrestrial adults. In many species of frog and in most lungless salamanders (Plethodontidae), direct development takes place, the larvae growing within the eggs and emerging as miniature adults. Many caecilians and some other amphibians lay their eggs on land, and the newly hatched larvae wriggle or are transported to water bodies. Some caecilians, the [[alpine salamander]] (''Salamandra atra'') and some of the [[Nectophrynoides|African live-bearing toads]] (''Nectophrynoides spp.'') are [[Viviparity|viviparous]]. Their larvae feed on glandular secretions and develop within the female's oviduct, often for long periods. Other amphibians, but not caecilians, are [[Ovoviviparity|ovoviviparous]]. The eggs are retained in or on the parent's body, but the larvae subsist on the yolks of their eggs and receive no nourishment from the adult. The larvae emerge at varying stages of their growth, either before or after metamorphosis, according to their species.{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | pp=6–9 }} The toad genus ''Nectophrynoides'' exhibits all of these developmental patterns among its dozen or so members.&lt;ref name=&quot;species&quot;/&gt;

==== Frogs ====
Frog larvae are known as tadpoles and typically have oval bodies and long, vertically flattened tails with fins. The free-living larvae are normally fully aquatic, but the tadpoles of some species (such as ''[[Nannophrys ceylonensis]]'') are semi-terrestrial and live among wet rocks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://amphibiaweb.org/cgi-bin/amphib_query?query_src=aw_lists_genera_&amp;table=amphib&amp;where-genus=Nannophrys&amp;where-species=ceylonensis |title=''Nannophrys ceylonensis'' |author=Janzen, Peter |date=May 10, 2005 |publisher=AmphibiaWeb |accessdate=July 20, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tadpoles have cartilaginous skeletons, gills for respiration (external gills at first, internal gills later), [[lateral line system]]s and large tails that they use for swimming.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-40603/Anura |title=Anura: From tadpole to adult |author1=Duellman, W. E. |author2=Zug, G. R. |encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Britannica Online |accessdate=July 13, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Newly hatched tadpoles soon develop gill pouches that cover the gills. The lungs develop early and are used as accessory breathing organs, the tadpoles rising to the water surface to gulp air. Some species complete their development inside the egg and hatch directly into small frogs. These larvae do not have gills but instead have specialised areas of skin through which respiration takes place. While tadpoles do not have true teeth, in most species, the jaws have long, parallel rows of small keratinized structures called keradonts surrounded by a horny beak.{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | pp=179–181 }} Front legs are formed under the gill sac and hind legs become visible a few days later.

Iodine and T4 (over stimulate the spectacular [[apoptosis]] [programmed cell death] of the cells of the larval gills, tail and fins) also stimulate the [[evolution of nervous systems]] transforming the aquatic, vegetarian tadpole into the terrestrial, carnivorous frog with better neurological, visuospatial, olfactory and cognitive abilities for hunting.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Venturi, Sebastiano|title=Evolutionary Significance of Iodine|journal=Current Chemical Biology|volume=5 |pages=155–162|year=2011|issn=1872-3136|doi=10.2174/187231311796765012|issue=3|url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/272210714}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Venturi, Sebastiano|title=Iodine, PUFAs and Iodolipids in Health and Disease: An Evolutionary Perspective|journal=Human Evolution-|volume= 29 |issue= 1–3|pages=185–205|year=2014|issn=0393-9375}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In fact, tadpoles developing in ponds and streams are typically [[herbivore|herbivorous]]. Pond tadpoles tend to have deep bodies, large caudal fins and small mouths; they swim in the quiet waters feeding on growing or loose fragments of vegetation. Stream dwellers mostly have larger mouths, shallow bodies and caudal fins; they attach themselves to plants and stones and feed on the surface films of [[algae]] and bacteria.&lt;ref name=&quot;EBAnura&quot;/&gt; They also feed on [[diatom]]s, filtered from the water through the [[gill]]s, and stir up the sediment at bottom of the pond, ingesting edible fragments. They have a relatively long, spiral-shaped gut to enable them to digest this diet.&lt;ref name=&quot;EBAnura&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/29023/Anura |title=Anura |author1=Duellman, William E. |author2=Zug, George R. |year=2012 |encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Britannica Online |publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica |accessdate=March 26, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some species are carnivorous at the tadpole stage, eating insects, smaller tadpoles and fish. Young of the [[Cuban tree frog]] (''Osteopilus septentrionalis'') can occasionally be [[Cannibalism (zoology)|cannibalistic]], the younger tadpoles attacking a larger, more developed tadpole when it is undergoing metamorphosis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Crump, Martha L. |year=1986 |title=Cannibalism by younger tadpoles: another hazard of metamorphosis |journal=Copeia |volume=1986 |pages=1007–1009 |jstor=1445301 |doi=10.2307/1445301 |issue=4 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{wide image|Bufobufotadpoles.jpg|800px|alt=Metamorphosis|Successive stages in the development of [[common toad]] (''Bufo bufo'') tadpoles, finishing with metamorphosis}}
At metamorphosis, rapid changes in the body take place as the lifestyle of the frog changes completely. The spiral‐shaped mouth with horny tooth ridges is reabsorbed together with the spiral gut. The animal develops a large jaw, and its gills disappear along with its gill sac. Eyes and legs grow quickly, and a tongue is formed. There are associated changes in the neural networks such as development of stereoscopic vision and loss of the lateral line system. All this can happen in about a day. A few days later, the tail is reabsorbed, due to the higher thyroxine concentration required for this to take place.&lt;ref name=&quot;EBAnura&quot; /&gt;

==== Salamanders ====
[[File:Ambystoma macrodactylum 26597.JPG|thumb|alt=Larva of the long-toed salamander|Larva of the [[long-toed salamander]] &lt;br&gt;(''Ambystoma macrodactylum'')]]
[[File:Mesotriton alpestris apuanus04.jpg|thumb|alt=Larvae of the alpine newt|Larvae of the [[alpine newt]] &lt;br&gt;(''Ichthyosaura alpestris'')]]
At hatching, a typical salamander larva has eyes without lids, teeth in both upper and lower jaws, three pairs of feathery external gills, a somewhat laterally flattened body and a long tail with [[Anatomical terms of location#Dorsal and ventral|dorsal]] and [[Anatomical terms of location#Dorsal and ventral|ventral]] fins. The forelimbs may be partially developed and the hind limbs are rudimentary in pond-living species but may be rather more developed in species that reproduce in moving water. Pond-type larvae often have a pair of balancers, rod-like structures on either side of the head that may prevent the gills from becoming clogged up with sediment. Some members of the genera ''[[Ambystoma]]'' and ''[[Dicamptodon]]'' have larvae that never fully develop into the adult form, but this varies with species and with populations. The [[northwestern salamander]] (''Ambystoma gracile'') is one of these and, depending on environmental factors, either remains permanently in the larval state, a condition known as [[neoteny]], or transforms into an adult.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Valentine, Barry D. |author2=Dennis, David M. | year=1964 | title=A comparison of the gill-arch system and fins of three genera of larval salamanders, ''Rhyacotriton'', ''Gyrinophilus'', and ''Ambystoma'' | journal=Copeia | volume=1964 | issue=1 | pages=196–201 | jstor=1440850 | doi=10.2307/1440850 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Both of these are able to breed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.amphibiaweb.org/cgi-bin/amphib_query?where-genus=Ambystoma&amp;where-species=gracile |title=''Ambystoma gracile'' |author=Shaffer, H. Bradley |year=2005 |publisher=AmphibiaWeb |accessdate=November 21, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Neoteny occurs when the animal's growth rate is very low and is usually linked to adverse conditions such as low water temperatures that may change the response of the tissues to the hormone thyroxine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://pages.uoregon.edu/titus/herp_old/neoteny.htm |title=Metamorphosis vs. neoteny (paedomorphosis) in salamanders (Caudata) |author=Kiyonaga, Robin R |accessdate=November 21, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other factors that may inhibit metamorphosis include lack of food, lack of trace elements and competition from [[conspecific]]s. The [[tiger salamander]] (''Ambystoma tigrinum'') also sometimes behaves in this way and may grow particularly large in the process. The adult tiger salamander is terrestrial, but the larva is aquatic and able to breed while still in the larval state. When conditions are particularly inhospitable on land, larval breeding may allow continuation of a population that would otherwise die out. There are fifteen species of [[wikt:obligate|obligate]] neotenic salamanders, including species of ''[[Necturus]]'', ''[[Olm|Proteus]]'' and ''Amphiuma'', and many examples of [[wikt:facultative|facultative]] ones that adopt this strategy under appropriate environmental circumstances.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Biology of Amphibians |last=Duellman |first=William E. |author2=Trueb, Linda |year=1994 |publisher=JHU Press |isbn=978-0-8018-4780-6 |pages=191–192 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=CzxVvKmrtIgC&amp;pg=PA191&amp;lpg=PA191&amp;dq=salamander+obligate+neoteny#v=onepage&amp;q=salamander%20obligate%20neoteny&amp;f=false }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lungless salamanders in the family Plethodontidae are terrestrial and lay a small number of unpigmented eggs in a cluster among damp leaf litter. Each egg has a large yolk sac and the larva feeds on this while it develops inside the egg, emerging fully formed as a juvenile salamander. The female salamander often broods the eggs. In the genus ''[[Ensatinas]]'', the female has been observed to coil around them and press her throat area against them, effectively massaging them with a mucous secretion.{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | p=196 }}

In newts and salamanders, metamorphosis is less dramatic than in frogs. This is because the larvae are already carnivorous and continue to feed as predators when they are adults so few changes are needed to their digestive systems. Their lungs are functional early, but the larvae do not make as much use of them as do tadpoles. Their gills are never covered by gill sacs and are reabsorbed just before the animals leave the water. Other changes include the reduction in size or loss of tail fins, the closure of gill slits, thickening of the skin, the development of eyelids, and certain changes in dentition and tongue structure. Salamanders are at their most vulnerable at metamorphosis as swimming speeds are reduced and transforming tails are encumbrances on land.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Shaffer, H. Bradley |author2=Austin, C. C. |author3=Huey, R. B. |year=1991 |title=The consequences of metamorphosis on salamander (''Ambystoma'') locomotor performance |journal=Physiological Zoology |volume=64 |issue=1 |pages=212–231 |jstor=30158520 |doi=10.1086/physzool.64.1.30158520 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Adult salamanders often have an aquatic phase in spring and summer, and a land phase in winter. For adaptation to a water phase, prolactin is the required hormone, and for adaptation to the land phase, thyroxine. External gills do not return in subsequent aquatic phases because these are completely absorbed upon leaving the water for the first time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/100353/Caudata |title=Caudata |author=Wake, David B. |year=2012 |encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Britannica Online |publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica |accessdate=March 26, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Caecilians ====
[[File:CaecilianNHM.png|thumb|left|alt=''Ichthyophis glutinosus''|The caecilian ''Ichthyophis glutinosus'' with eggs and developing embryo]]
Most terrestrial caecilians that lay eggs do so in burrows or moist places on land near bodies of water. The development of the young of ''[[Ichthyophis glutinosus]]'', a species from Sri Lanka, has been much studied. The eel-like larvae hatch out of the eggs and make their way to water. They have three pairs of external red feathery gills, a blunt head with two rudimentary eyes, a lateral line system and a short tail with fins. They swim by undulating their body from side to side. They are mostly active at night, soon lose their gills and make sorties onto land. Metamorphosis is gradual. By the age of about ten months they have developed a pointed head with sensory tentacles near the mouth and lost their eyes, lateral line systems and tails. The skin thickens, embedded scales develop and the body divides into segments. By this time, the caecilian has constructed a burrow and is living on land.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Breckenridge, W. R. |author2=Nathanael, S. |author3=Pereira, L. |year=1987 |title=Some aspects of the biology and development of ''Ichthyophis glutinosus'' |journal=Journal of Zoology |volume=211 |issue=3 |pages=437–449 |doi=10.1111/jzo.1987.211.3.437 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Siphonops annulatus.jpg|thumb|alt=Ringed caecilian|The [[Siphonops annulatus|ringed caecilian]] (''Siphonops annulatus'') resembles an earthworm]]
In the majority of species of caecilians, the young are produced by viviparity. ''[[Typhlonectes compressicauda]]'', a species from South America, is typical of these. Up to nine larvae can develop in the oviduct at any one time. They are elongated and have paired sac-like gills, small eyes and specialised scraping teeth. At first, they feed on the yolks of the eggs, but as this source of nourishment declines they begin to rasp at the ciliated epithelial cells that line the oviduct. This stimulates the secretion of fluids rich in [[lipid]]s and mucoproteins on which they feed along with scrapings from the oviduct wall. They may increase their length sixfold and be two-fifths as long as their mother before being born. By this time they have undergone metamorphosis, lost their eyes and gills, developed a thicker skin and mouth tentacles, and reabsorbed their teeth. A permanent set of teeth grow through soon after birth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Wake, Marvalee H. |year=1977 |title=Fetal maintenance and its evolutionary significance in the Amphibia: Gymnophiona |journal=Journal of Herpetology |volume=11 |issue=4 |pages=379–386 |jstor=1562719 |doi=10.2307/1562719 |url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/265101247 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/29797/Gymnophiona |title=Gymnophiona |author=Duellman, William E. |year=2012 |encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Britannica Online |publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica |accessdate=March 26, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ringed caecilian (''[[Siphonops annulatus]]'') has developed a unique adaptation for the purposes of reproduction. The progeny feed on a skin layer that is specially developed by the adult in a phenomenon known as maternal dermatophagy. The brood feed as a batch for about seven minutes at intervals of approximately three days which gives the skin an opportunity to regenerate. Meanwhile, they have been observed to ingest fluid exuded from the maternal cloaca.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Wilkinson, Mark |author2=Kupfer, Alexander |author3=Marques-Porto, Rafael |author4=Jeffkins, Hilary |author5=Antoniazzi, Marta M. |author6=Jared, Carlos |year=2008 |title= One hundred million years of skin feeding? Extended parental care in a Neotropical caecilian (Amphibia: Gymnophiona) |journal=[[Biology Letters]] |doi=10.1098/rsbl.2008.0217 |volume=4 |pages=358–361 |issue=4 |pmc=2610157 |pmid=18547909}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Parental care ===
[[File:Panama Poison Dart Frog Colostethus panamensis with tadpoles.jpg|thumb|alt=Common rocket frog|Male [[common rocket frog]] (''Colostethus panamensis'') carrying tadpoles on his back]]

The care of offspring among amphibians has been little studied but, in general, the larger the number of eggs in a batch, the less likely it is that any degree of parental care takes place. Nevertheless, it is estimated that in up to 20% of amphibian species, one or both adults play some role in the care of the young.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Crump| first=Martha L.| year=1996| chapter=Parental care among the Amphibia| volume=25| pages=109–144| doi=10.1016/S0065-3454(08)60331-9 | series=Advances in the Study of Behavior| isbn=978-0-12-004525-9| title=Parental Care: Evolution, Mechanisms, and Adaptive Significance}}&lt;/ref&gt; Those species that breed in smaller water bodies or other specialised habitats tend to have complex patterns of behaviour in the care of their young.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | doi=10.1086/650727 | last1=Brown | first1=J. L. | last2=Morales | first2=V. | last3=Summers | first3=K. | year=2010 | title=A key ecological trait drove the evolution of biparental care and monogamy in an amphibian | journal=American Naturalist | volume=175 | issue=4 | pages=436–446 | pmid=20180700 | url=https://www.academia.edu/11096788 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many woodland salamanders lay clutches of eggs under dead logs or stones on land. The [[black mountain salamander]] (''Desmognathus welteri'') does this, the mother brooding the eggs and guarding them from predation as the embryos feed on the yolks of their eggs. When fully developed, they break their way out of the egg capsules and disperse as juvenile salamanders.{{sfn | Dorit | Walker | Barnes | 1991 | pp=853–854 }} The male hellbender, a primitive salamander, excavates an underwater nest and encourages females to lay there. The male then guards the site for the two or three months before the eggs hatch, using body undulations to fan the eggs and increase their supply of oxygen.&lt;ref name=&quot;EHSAR&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Alytes obstetricans almogavarii - male with eggs 2.jpg|thumb|left|Male [[common midwife toad]] (''Alytes obstetricans'') carrying eggs]]
The male ''[[Colostethus subpunctatus]]'', a tiny frog, protects the egg cluster which is hidden under a stone or log. When the eggs hatch, the male transports the tadpoles on his back, stuck there by a mucous secretion, to a temporary pool where he dips himself into the water and the tadpoles drop off.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Fandiño, María Claudia |author2=Lüddecke, Horst |author3=Amézquita, Adolfo |year=1997 |title=Vocalisation and larval transportation of male ''Colostethus subpunctatus'' (Anura: Dendrobatidae) |journal=Amphibia-Reptilia |volume=18 |issue=1 |pages=39–48 |doi=10.1163/156853897X00297 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The male [[Common midwife toad|midwife toad]] (''Alytes obstetricans'') winds egg strings round his thighs and carries the eggs around for up to eight weeks. He keeps them moist and when they are ready to hatch, he visits a pond or ditch and releases the tadpoles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://amphibiaweb.org/cgi-bin/amphib_query?where-genus=Alytes&amp;where-species=obstetricans |title=''Alytes obstetricans'' |author=van der Meijden, Arie |date=January 18, 2010 |publisher=AmphibiaWeb |accessdate=November 29, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The female [[gastric-brooding frog]] (''Rheobatrachus spp.'') reared larvae in her stomach after swallowing either the eggs or hatchlings; however, this stage was never observed before the species became extinct. The tadpoles secrete a hormone that inhibits digestion in the mother whilst they develop by consuming their very large yolk supply.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://animaldiversity.ummz.umich.edu/site/accounts/information/Rheobatrachus_silus.html |title=''Rheobatrachus silus'' |author=Semeyn, E. |year=2002 |work=Animal Diversity Web |publisher=University of Michigan Museum of Zoology |accessdate=August 5, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[pouched frog]] (''Assa darlingtoni'') lays eggs on the ground. When they hatch, the male carries the tadpoles around in brood pouches on his hind legs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.iucnredlist.org/species/41130/10403727#habitat-ecology |title=''Assa darlingtoni'' |authors=Hero, Jean-Marc; Clarke, John; Meyer, Ed |year=2004 |work=IUCN Red List of Threatened Species. Version 2012.2 |accessdate=October 2, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The aquatic [[Surinam toad]] (''Pipa pipa'') raises its young in pores on its back where they remain until metamorphosis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.iucnredlist.org/species/58163/61414791#habitat-ecology |title=''Pipa pipa'' (Suriname Toad) |author1=La Marca, Enrique |author2=Azevedo-Ramos, Claudia |author3=Silvano, Débora |author4=Coloma, Luis A. |author5=Ron, Santiago |author6=Hardy, Jerry |author7=Beier, Manfred |year=2010 |work=IUCN Red List of Threatened Species. Version 2012.1 |accessdate=October 2, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The granular poison frog (''Oophaga granulifera'') is typical of a number of tree frogs in the poison dart frog family [[Dendrobatidae]]. Its eggs are laid on the forest floor and when they hatch, the tadpoles are carried one by one on the back of an adult to a suitable water-filled crevice such as the [[wikt:axil|axil]] of a leaf or the [[Rosette (botany)|rosette]] of a [[Bromeliaceae|bromeliad]]. The female visits the nursery sites regularly and deposits unfertilised eggs in the water and these are consumed by the tadpoles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=van Wijngaarden, René |author2=Bolaños, Federico |year=1992 |title=Parental care in ''Dendrobates granuliferus'' (Anura: Dendrobatidae), with a description of the tadpole |journal=Journal of Herpetology |volume=26 |issue=1 |pages=102–105 |jstor=1565037 |doi=10.2307/1565037 |url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/275943004 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Feeding and diet ==
[[File:Pacific brown salamander eating a worm.jpg|thumb|alt=Northwestern salamander|[[Northwestern salamander]] &lt;br&gt;(''Ambystoma gracile'') eating a worm]]
With a few exceptions, adult amphibians are [[Predation|predators]], feeding on virtually anything that moves that they can swallow. The diet mostly consists of small prey that do not move too fast such as beetles, caterpillars, earthworms and spiders. The sirens (''[[Siren (genus)|Siren spp.]]'') often ingest aquatic plant material with the invertebrates on which they feed&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://animaldiversity.ummz.umich.edu/site/accounts/information/Siren_intermedia.html |title=''Siren intermedia'': Lesser Siren |author=Gabbard, Jesse |year=2000 |work=Animal Diversity Web |publisher=University of Michigan Museum of Zoology |accessdate=August 11, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a Brazilian tree frog (''[[Xenohyla truncata]]'') includes a large quantity of fruit in its diet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Da Silva, H. R. |author2=De Britto-Pereira, M. C. |year=2006 |title=How much fruit do fruit-eating frogs eat? An investigation on the diet of ''Xenohyla truncata'' (Lissamphibia: Anura: Hylidae) |journal=Journal of Zoology |volume=270 |issue=4 |pages=692–698 |doi=10.1111/j.1469-7998.2006.00192.x |url=https://www.academia.edu/26660305 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Mexican burrowing toad]] (''Rhinophrynus dorsalis'') has a specially adapted tongue for picking up ants and termites. It projects it with the tip foremost whereas other frogs flick out the rear part first, their tongues being hinged at the front.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Trueb, Linda |author2=Gans, Carl |year=1983 |title=Feeding specializations of the Mexican burrowing toad, ''Rhinophrynus dorsalis'' (Anura: Rhinophrynidae) |journal=Journal of Zoology |volume=199 |issue=2 |pages=189–208 |doi=10.1111/j.1469-7998.1983.tb02090.x |url=https://deepblue.lib.umich.edu/bitstream/2027.42/74489/1/j.1469-7998.1983.tb02090.x.pdf |hdl=2027.42/74489 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Food is mostly selected by sight, even in conditions of dim light. Movement of the prey triggers a feeding response. Frogs have been caught on fish hooks baited with red flannel and [[Rana clamitans|green frogs]] (''Rana clamitans'') have been found with stomachs full of elm seeds that they had seen floating past.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Hamilton, W. J. Jr. |year=1948 |title=The food and feeding behavior of the green frog, ''Rana clamitans'' Latreille, in New York State |journal=Copeia |volume=1948 |issue=3 |pages=203–207 |publisher=American Society of Ichthyologists and Herpetologists |jstor=1438455 |doi=10.2307/1438455 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Toads, salamanders and caecilians also use smell to detect prey. This response is mostly secondary because salamanders have been observed to remain stationary near odoriferous prey but only feed if it moves. Cave-dwelling amphibians normally hunt by smell. Some salamanders seem to have learned to recognize immobile prey when it has no smell, even in complete darkness.{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | p=56 }}

Amphibians usually swallow food whole but may chew it lightly first to subdue it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Collins&quot; /&gt; They typically have small hinged [[pedicellate teeth]], a feature unique to amphibians. The base and crown of these are composed of [[dentine]] separated by an [[Calcification|uncalcified]] layer and they are replaced at intervals. Salamanders, caecilians and some frogs have one or two rows of teeth in both jaws, but some frogs (''Rana spp.'') lack teeth in the lower jaw, and toads (''Bufo spp.'') have no teeth. In many amphibians there are also [[vomerine teeth]] attached to a facial bone in the roof of the mouth.{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | pp=57–58 }}

[[File:Teichfrosch isst teichfrosch.JPG|thumb|left|alt=Edible frog eating a fellow edible frog|[[Edible frog]] (''Pelophylax esculentus'') exhibiting [[Cannibalism (zoology)|cannibalism]]]]
The [[tiger salamander]] (''Ambystoma tigrinum'') is typical of the frogs and salamanders that hide under cover ready to ambush unwary invertebrates. Others amphibians, such as the ''Bufo spp.'' toads, actively search for prey, while the [[Argentine horned frog]] (''Ceratophrys ornata'') lures inquisitive prey closer by raising its hind feet over its back and vibrating its yellow toes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Radcliffe, Charles W. |author2=Chiszar, David |author3=Estep, Karen |author4=Murphy, James B. |author5=Smith, Hobart M. |year=1986 |title=Observations on pedal luring and pedal movements in Leptodactylid frogs |journal=Journal of Herpetology |volume=20 |issue=3 |pages=300–306 |jstor=1564496 |doi=10.2307/1564496 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Among leaf litter frogs in Panama, frogs that actively hunt prey have narrow mouths and are slim, often brightly coloured and toxic, while ambushers have wide mouths and are broad and well-camouflaged.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Toft, Catherine A. |year=1981 |title=Feeding ecology of Panamanian litter anurans: patterns in diet and foraging mode |journal=Journal of Herpetology |volume=15 |issue=2 |pages=139–144 |jstor=1563372 |doi=10.2307/1563372 |url=https://www.academia.edu/364846 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Caecilians do not flick their tongues, but catch their prey by grabbing it with their slightly backward-pointing teeth. The struggles of the prey and further jaw movements work it inwards and the caecilian usually retreats into its burrow. The subdued prey is gulped down whole.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Bemis, W. E. |author2=Schwenk, K. |author3=Wake, M. H. |year=1983 |title=Morphology and function of the feeding apparatus in ''Dermophis mexicanus'' (Amphibia: Gymnophiona) |journal=Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society |volume=77 |issue=1 |pages=75–96 |doi=10.1111/j.1096-3642.1983.tb01722.x |url=https://www.academia.edu/23250634 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

When they are newly hatched, frog larvae feed on the yolk of the egg. When this is exhausted some move on to feed on bacteria, algal crusts, detritus and raspings from submerged plants. Water is drawn in through their mouths, which are usually at the bottom of their heads, and passes through branchial food traps between their mouths and their gills where fine particles are trapped in mucus and filtered out. Others have specialised mouthparts consisting of a horny beak edged by several rows of labial teeth. They scrape and bite food of many kinds as well as stirring up the bottom sediment, filtering out larger particles with the papillae around their mouths. Some, such as the spadefoot toads, have strong biting jaws and are carnivorous or even cannibalistic.{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | pp=181–185 }}
[[file:Sophisticated-Communication-in-the-Brazilian-Torrent-Frog-Hylodes-japi-pone.0145444.s001.oga|left|thumb|Audio showing Brazilian torrent frog males executing advertisement, peep, and squeal calls.]]

== Vocalization ==
[[File:Dendropsophus microcephalus - calling male (Cope, 1886).jpg|thumb|alt=Male treefrog calling|Male treefrog (''[[Dendropsophus microcephalus]]'') inflating his air sac as he calls]]
The calls made by caecilians and salamanders are limited to occasional soft squeaks, grunts or hisses and have not been much studied. A clicking sound sometimes produced by caecilians may be a means of orientation, as in bats, or a form of communication. Most salamanders are considered voiceless, but the [[California giant salamander]] (''Dicamptodon ensatus'') has vocal cords and can produce a rattling or barking sound. Some species of salamander emit a quiet squeak or yelp if attacked.{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | pp=76–77 }}

[[File:American Toad singing.jpg|thumb|American toad, (''[[Anaxyrus americanus]]'') singing]]
Frogs are much more vocal, especially during the breeding season when they use their voices to attract mates. The presence of a particular species in an area may be more easily discerned by its characteristic call than by a fleeting glimpse of the animal itself. In most species, the sound is produced by expelling air from the lungs over the vocal cords into an [[Gular skin|air sac]] or sacs in the throat or at the corner of the mouth. This may distend like a balloon and acts as a resonator, helping to transfer the sound to the atmosphere, or the water at times when the animal is submerged.{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | pp=76–77 }} The main vocalisation is the male's loud advertisement call which seeks to both encourage a female to approach and discourage other males from intruding on its territory. This call is modified to a quieter courtship call on the approach of a female or to a more aggressive version if a male intruder draws near. Calling carries the risk of attracting predators and involves the expenditure of much energy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Sullivan, Brian K. |year=1992 |title=Sexual selection and calling behavior in the American toad (''Bufo americanus'') |journal=Copeia |volume=1992 |issue=1 |pages=1–7 |jstor=1446530 |doi=10.2307/1446530 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Other calls include those given by a female in response to the advertisement call and a release call given by a male or female during unwanted attempts at amplexus. When a frog is attacked, a distress or fright call is emitted, often resembling a scream.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite thesis |chapter=Capitulo 4 |title=When frogs scream! A review of anuran defensive vocalizations |chapter-url=http://www.athena.biblioteca.unesp.br/exlibris/bd/brc/33004137003P3/2007/pereira_lftr_dr_rcla.pdf#page=110 |author1=Toledo, L. F. |author2=Haddad, C. F. B. |year=2007 |publisher=Instituto de Biociências, São Paulo }}&lt;/ref&gt; The usually nocturnal Cuban tree frog (''Osteopilus septentrionalis'') produces a rain call when there is rainfall during daylight hours.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://edis.ifas.ufl.edu/uw259 |title=The Cuban Treefrog (''Osteopilus septentrionalis'') in Florida |author=Johnson, Steve A. |year=2010 |work=EDIS |publisher=University of Florida |accessdate=August 13, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Territorial behaviour ==
Little is known of the territorial behaviour of caecilians, but some frogs and salamanders defend home ranges. These are usually feeding, breeding or sheltering sites. Males normally exhibit such behaviour though in some species, females and even juveniles are also involved. Although in many frog species, females are larger than males, this is not the case in most species where males are actively involved in territorial defence. Some of these have specific adaptations such as enlarged teeth for biting or spines on the chest, arms or thumbs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Shine, Richard |year=1979 |title=Sexual selection and sexual dimorphism in the Amphibia |journal=Copeia |volume=1979 |issue=2 |pages=297–306 |jstor=1443418 |doi=10.2307/1443418 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Redback salamander.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Red-backed salamander|The red back salamander (''[[Plethodon cinereus]]'') defends a territory against intruders.]]
In salamanders, defence of a territory involves adopting an aggressive posture and if necessary attacking the intruder. This may involve snapping, chasing and sometimes biting, occasionally causing the loss of a tail. The behaviour of [[red back salamander]]s (''Plethodon cinereus'') has been much studied. 91% of marked individuals that were later recaptured were within a metre (yard) of their original daytime retreat under a log or rock.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gergits&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Gergits, W. F. |author2=Jaeger, R. G. | year=1990 | title=Site attachment by the red-backed salamander, ''Plethodon cinereus'' | journal=Journal of Herpetology | volume=24 | issue=1 | pages=91–93 | jstor=1564297 | doi=10.2307/1564297 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A similar proportion, when moved experimentally a distance of {{convert|30|m}}, found their way back to their home base.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gergits&quot;/&gt; The salamanders left odour marks around their territories which averaged {{convert|0.16|to|0.33|m2}} in size and were sometimes inhabited by a male and female pair.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://amphibiaweb.org/cgi-bin/amphib_query?query_src=aw_search_index&amp;where-genus=Plethodon&amp;where-species=cinereus&amp;rel-genus=equals&amp;rel-species=equals|title=''Plethodon cinereus'' |author=Casper, Gary S |publisher=AmphibiaWeb |accessdate=September 25, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; These deterred the intrusion of others and delineated the boundaries between neighbouring areas. Much of their behaviour seemed stereotyped and did not involve any actual contact between individuals. An aggressive posture involved raising the body off the ground and glaring at the opponent who often turned away submissively. If the intruder persisted, a biting lunge was usually launched at either the tail region or the naso-labial grooves. Damage to either of these areas can reduce the fitness of the rival, either because of the need to regenerate tissue or because it impairs its ability to detect food.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gergits&quot; /&gt;

In frogs, male territorial behaviour is often observed at breeding locations; calling is both an announcement of ownership of part of this resource and an advertisement call to potential mates. In general, a deeper voice represents a heavier and more powerful individual, and this may be sufficient to prevent intrusion by smaller males. Much energy is used in the vocalization and it takes a toll on the territory holder who may be displaced by a fitter rival if he tires. There is a tendency for males to tolerate the holders of neighbouring territories while vigorously attacking unknown intruders. Holders of territories have a &quot;home advantage&quot; and usually come off better in an encounter between two similar-sized frogs. If threats are insufficient, chest to chest tussles may take place. Fighting methods include pushing and shoving, deflating the opponent's vocal sac, seizing him by the head, jumping on his back, biting, chasing, splashing, and ducking him under the water.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Wells, K. D. | year=1977 | title=Territoriality and male mating success in the green frog (''Rana clamitans'') | journal=Ecology | volume=58 | issue=4 | pages=750–762 | jstor=1936211 | doi=10.2307/1936211 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Defence mechanisms ==
[[File:Adult Cane toad.jpg|thumb|alt=Cane toad|[[Cane toad]] (''Rhinella marina'') with poison glands behind the eyes]]

Amphibians have soft bodies with thin skins, and lack claws, defensive armour, or spines. Nevertheless, they have evolved various defence mechanisms to keep themselves alive. The first line of defence in salamanders and frogs is the mucous secretion that they produce. This keeps their skin moist and makes them slippery and difficult to grip. The secretion is often sticky and distasteful or toxic.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barthalmus&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Barthalmus, G. T. |author2=Zielinski W. J. |year=1988 |title=''Xenopus'' skin mucus induces oral dyskinesias that promote escape from snakes |journal=Pharmacology Biochemistry and Behavior |volume=30 |issue=4 |pages=957–959 |pmid=3227042 |doi=10.1016/0091-3057(88)90126-8 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Snakes have been observed yawning and gaping when trying to swallow [[African clawed frog]]s (''Xenopus laevis''), which gives the frogs an opportunity to escape.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barthalmus&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://amphibiaweb.org/cgi/amphib_query?where-genus=Xenopus&amp;where-species=laevis |title=Xenopus laevis | author = Crayon, John J | publisher=AmphibiaWeb | accessdate=October 8, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Caecilians have been little studied in this respect, but the Cayenne caecilian (''Typhlonectes compressicauda'') produces toxic mucus that has killed predatory fish in a feeding experiment in Brazil.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Moodie, G. E. E. |year=1978 |title=Observations on the life history of the caecilian ''Typhlonectes compressicaudus'' (Dumeril and Bibron) in the Amazon basin |journal=Canadian Journal of Zoology |volume=56 |issue=4 |pages=1005–1008 |doi=10.1139/z78-141 |url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/237980659 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In some salamanders, the skin is poisonous. The [[rough-skinned newt]] (''Taricha granulosa'') from North America and other members of its genus contain the neurotoxin [[tetrodotoxin]] (TTX), the most toxic non-protein substance known and almost identical to that produced by [[pufferfish]]. Handling the newts does not cause harm, but ingestion of even the most minute amounts of the skin is deadly. In feeding trials, fish, frogs, reptiles, birds and mammals were all found to be susceptible.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author= Brodie, Edmund D. Jr. |year=1968 |title=Investigations on the skin toxin of the adult rough-skinned newt, ''Taricha granulosa'' |journal=Copeia |volume=1968 |issue=2 |pages=307–313 |jstor=1441757 |doi= 10.2307/1441757 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Hanifin&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Hanifin, Charles T. |author2=Yotsu-Yamashita, Mari |author3=Yasumoto, Takeshi |author4=Brodie, Edmund D. |author5=Brodie, Edmund D. Jr. |year=1999 |title=Toxicity of dangerous prey: variation of tetrodotoxin levels within and among populations of the newt ''Taricha granulosa'' |journal=Journal of Chemical Ecology |volume=25 |issue=9 |pages=2161–2175 |doi=10.1023/A:1021049125805 |url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/225869249 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The only predators with some tolerance to the poison are certain populations of [[Common Garter Snake|common garter snake]] (''Thamnophis sirtalis'').
In locations where both snake and salamander co-exist, the snakes have developed immunity through genetic changes and they feed on the amphibians with impunity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Geffeney, Shana L. |author2=Fujimoto, Esther |author3=Brodie, Edmund D. |author4=Brodie, Edmund D. Jr. |author5=Ruben, Peter C. |year=2005 |title=Evolutionary diversification of TTX-resistant sodium channels in a predator–prey interaction |journal=Nature |volume=434 |pages=759–763 |doi=10.1038/nature03444 |issue=7034 |pmid=15815629 |bibcode=2005Natur.434..759G }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Coevolution]] occurs with the newt increasing its toxic capabilities at the same rate as the snake further develops its immunity.&lt;ref name=Hanifin/&gt; Some frogs and toads are toxic, the main poison glands being at the side of the neck and under the warts on the back. These regions are presented to the attacking animal and their secretions may be foul-tasting or cause various physical or neurological symptoms. Altogether, over 200 toxins have been isolated from the limited number of amphibian species that have been investigated.{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | p=110 }}

[[File:Salamander-olympus.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Fire salamander|The [[fire salamander]] (''Salamandra salamandra''), a toxic species, wears warning colours.]]
[[File:Schrecklicherpfeilgiftfrosch-01.jpg|thumb|left|Perhaps the most poisonous animal in the world, the [[golden poison frog]] (''Phyllobates terribilis'') is endemic to [[Colombia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Patocka |first1=Jiri |last2=Wulff |first2=Kräuff |last3=Palomeque |first3=MaríaVictoria |year=1999 |title=Dart Poison Frogs and Their Toxins |journal=ASA Newsletter |volume=5 |issue=75 |issn=1057-9419 |url=http://www.asanltr.com/ASANews-99/995frogs.htm |accessdate=January 29, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

Poisonous species often use bright colouring to warn potential predators of their toxicity. These warning colours tend to be red or yellow combined with black, with the [[fire salamander]] (''Salamandra salamandra'') being an example. Once a predator has sampled one of these, it is likely to remember the colouration next time it encounters a similar animal. In some species, such as the [[fire-bellied toad]] (''Bombina spp.''), the warning colouration is on the belly and these animals adopt a defensive pose when attacked, exhibiting their bright colours to the predator. The frog ''[[Allobates zaparo]]'' is not poisonous, but [[Batesian mimicry|mimics]] the appearance of other toxic species in its locality, a strategy that may deceive predators.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Darst, Catherine R. |author2=Cummings, Molly E. |date=9 March 2006 |title=Predator learning favours mimicry of a less-toxic model in poison frogs |journal=Nature |volume=440 |pages=208–211 |doi=10.1038/nature04297 |issue=7081 |pmid=16525472 |bibcode=2006Natur.440..208D |doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many amphibians are nocturnal and hide during the day, thereby avoiding diurnal predators that hunt by sight. Other amphibians use [[camouflage]] to avoid being detected. They have various colourings such as mottled browns, greys and olives to blend into the background. Some salamanders adopt defensive poses when faced by a potential predator such as the North American [[northern short-tailed shrew]] (''Blarina brevicauda''). Their bodies writhe and they raise and lash their tails which makes it difficult for the predator to avoid contact with their poison-producing granular glands.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Brodie, Edmund D. Jr. |author2=Nowak, Robert T. |author3=Harvey, William R. |year=1979 |title=Antipredator secretions and behavior of selected salamanders against shrews |journal=Copeia |volume=1979 |issue=2 |pages=270–274 |jstor=1443413 |doi=10.2307/1443413 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A few salamanders will autotomise their tails when attacked, sacrificing this part of their anatomy to enable them to escape. The tail may have a constriction at its base to allow it to be easily detached. The tail is regenerated later, but the energy cost to the animal of replacing it is significant.&lt;ref name=&quot;Beneski&quot; /&gt;
Some frogs and toads inflate themselves to make themselves look large and fierce, and some spadefoot toads (''[[Pelobates]] spp'') scream and leap towards the attacker.&lt;ref name=&quot;Collins&quot; /&gt; Giant salamanders of the genus ''[[Andrias]]'', as well as [[Ceratophryinae|Ceratophrine]] and ''[[Pyxicephalus]]'' frogs possess sharp teeth and are capable of drawing blood with a defensive bite. The [[blackbelly salamander]] (''Desmognathus quadramaculatus'') can bite an attacking common garter snake (''Thamnophis sirtalis'') two or three times its size on the head and often manages to escape.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Brodie, E. D. Jr. |year=1978 |title=Biting and vocalisation as antipredator mechanisms in terrestrial salamanders |journal=Copeia |volume=1978 |issue=1 |pages=127–129 |jstor=1443832 |doi=10.2307/1443832 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Cognition ==
In amphibians, there is evidence of [[habituation]], [[associative learning]] through both [[Classical conditioning|classical]] and [[instrumental learning]], and discrimination abilities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Hloch, A.|year=2010|title=What Does a Salamander Remember After Winter?|publisher=University of Vienna. Fakultät für Lebenswissenschaften|url=http://othes.univie.ac.at/11007/1/2010-09-03_0400713.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In one experiment, when offered live fruit flies (''[[Drosophila]] virilis''), salamanders chose the larger of 1 vs 2 and 2 vs 3. Frogs can distinguish between low numbers (1 vs 2, 2 vs 3, but not 3 vs 4) and large numbers (3 vs 6, 4 vs 8, but not 4 vs 6) of prey. This is irrespective of other characteristics, i.e. surface area, volume, weight and movement, although discrimination among large numbers may be based on surface area.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stancher&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Stancher, G.|author2= Rugani, R.|author3= Regolin, L.|author4=Vallortigara, G.|authorlink4=Giorgio Vallortigara|year=2015|title=Numerical discrimination by frogs (Bombina orientalis)|journal=Animal Cognition|volume=18|issue=1|pages=219–229|doi=10.1007/s10071-014-0791-7|url=https://www.academia.edu/12580390|pmid=25108417}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Conservation ==
{{main|Decline in amphibian populations}}

[[File:Bufo periglenes1.jpg|thumb|alt=Golden toad|The extinct [[golden toad]] (''Bufo periglenes''), last seen in 1989]]
Dramatic declines in amphibian populations, including population crashes and mass localized [[extinction]], have been noted since the late 1980s from locations all over the world, and amphibian declines are thus perceived to be one of the most critical threats to global [[biodiversity]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=McCallum |first1=M. L. |year=2007 |title=Amphibian decline or extinction? Current declines dwarf background extinction rate |journal=Journal of Herpetology |volume=41 |issue=3 |pages=483–491 |doi=10.1670/0022-1511(2007)41[483:ADOECD]2.0.CO;2}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, the [[International Union for Conservation of Nature]] (IUCN) reported stating that currently birds,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=What does it mean to be human?|url=http://humanorigins.si.edu/human-characteristics/change|publisher=Smithsonian National Museum of Natural History|accessdate=November 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; mammals, and amphibians extinction rates were at minimum 48 times greater than natural extinction rates—possibly 1,024 times higher.
In 2006 there were believed to be 4,035 species of amphibians that depended on water at some stage during their life cycle. Of these, 1,356 (33.6%) were considered to be threatened and this figure is likely to be an underestimate because it excludes 1,427 species for which there was insufficient data to assess their status.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://app.databasin.org/app/pages/datasetPage.jsp?id=461e58214aa54ad79382066ab829c05f |title=Number of Globally Threatened Amphibian Species by Freshwater Ecoregion |author1=Hoekstra, J. M. |author2=Molnar, J. L. |author3=Jennings, M. |author4=Revenga, C. |author5=Spalding, M. D. |author6=Boucher, T. M. |author7=Robertson, J. C. |author8=Heibel, T. J. |author9=Ellison, K. |year=2010 |work=The Atlas of Global Conservation: Changes, Challenges, and Opportunities to Make a Difference |publisher=The Nature Conservancy |accessdate=September 5, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; A number of causes are believed to be involved, including [[habitat destruction]] and modification, [[over-exploitation]], [[pollution]], [[introduced species]], [[global warming]], [[endocrine-disrupting chemical|endocrine-disrupting pollutants]], destruction of the [[ozone layer]] ([[ultraviolet radiation]] has shown to be especially damaging to the skin, eyes, and eggs of amphibians), and diseases like [[chytridiomycosis]]. However, many of the causes of amphibian declines are still poorly understood, and are a topic of ongoing discussion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.amphibians.org/ |title=Amphibian Specialist Group |publisher=IUCN SSC Amphibian Specialist Group |accessdate=March 30, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Israel painted frog.JPG|thumb|left|alt=Hula painted frog|The [[Hula painted frog]] (''Discoglossus nigriventer'') was believed to be extinct but was rediscovered in 2011.]]
With their complex reproductive needs and permeable skins, amphibians are often considered to be [[ecological indicator]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Waddle&quot;&gt;{{Cite thesis |type=Ph.D. |chapter= |title=Use of amphibians as ecosystem indicator species |url=http://etd.fcla.edu/UF/UFE0016760/waddle_j.pdf |last=Waddle |first=James Hardin |year=2006 |publisher=University of Florida }}&lt;/ref&gt; In many terrestrial ecosystems, they constitute one of the largest parts of the vertebrate biomass. Any decline in amphibian numbers will affect the patterns of predation. The loss of carnivorous species near the top of the food chain will upset the delicate ecosystem balance and may cause dramatic increases in opportunistic species. In the Middle East, a growing appetite for eating frog legs and the consequent gathering of them for food was linked to an increase in [[mosquito]]es.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| last1 = Regier| first1 = Henry A.
| last2 = Baskerville | first2 = Gordon, L.
| title = Sustainable redevelopment of regional ecosystems degraded by exploitive development
| chapter = Sustainability Issues for Resource Managers
| publisher = DIANE Publishing
| pages = 36–38
| year = 1996
| isbn = 978-0-7881-4699-2
| chapter-url = https://books.google.com/?id=e66hatcSAsUC&amp;pg=PA21&amp;dq=Sustainable+redevelopment+of+regional+ecosystems+degraded+by#v=onepage&amp;q=Sustainable%20redevelopment%20of%20regional%20ecosystems%20degraded%20by&amp;f=false
 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Predators that feed on amphibians are affected by their decline. The [[western terrestrial garter snake]] (''Thamnophis elegans'') in California is largely aquatic and depends heavily on two species of frog that are decreasing in numbers, the [[Yosemite toad]] (''Bufo canorus'') and the [[mountain yellow-legged frog]] (''Rana muscosa''), putting the snake's future at risk. If the snake were to become scarce, this would affect birds of prey and other predators that feed on it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Jennings, W. Bryan |author2=Bradford, David F. |author3=Johnson, Dale F. |year=1992 |title=Dependence of the garter snake ''Thamnophis elegans'' on amphibians in the Sierra Nevada of California |journal=Journal of Herpetology |volume=26 |issue=4 |pages=503–505 |jstor=1565132 |doi=10.2307/1565132 |url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/270389669 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, in the ponds and lakes, fewer frogs means fewer tadpoles. These normally play an important role in controlling the growth of algae and also forage on [[detritus]] that accumulates as sediment on the bottom. A reduction in the number of tadpoles may lead to an overgrowth of algae, resulting in depletion of oxygen in the water when the algae later die and decompose. Aquatic invertebrates and fish might then die and there would be unpredictable ecological consequences.{{sfn | Stebbins | Cohen | 1995 | p=249 }}

A [[global strategy]] to stem the crisis was released in 2005 in the form of the Amphibian Conservation Action Plan. Developed by over eighty leading experts in the field, this call to action details what would be required to curtail amphibian declines and extinctions over the following five years and how much this would cost. The Amphibian Specialist Group of the IUCN is spearheading efforts to implement a comprehensive global strategy for amphibian conservation.&lt;ref name=&quot;AmphibianArk&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iucn.org/about/union/secretariat/offices/asia/regional_activities/asian_amphibian_crisis/taking_action/amphibian_conservation_action_plan/ |title=Amphibian Conservation Action Plan |work=IUCN |accessdate=March 30, 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120427134336/http://www.iucn.org/about/union/secretariat/offices/asia/regional_activities/asian_amphibian_crisis/taking_action/amphibian_conservation_action_plan/ |archivedate=April 27, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Amphibian Ark]] is an organization that was formed to implement the ex-situ conservation recommendations of this plan, and they have been working with zoos and aquaria around the world, encouraging them to create assurance colonies of threatened amphibians.&lt;ref name=&quot;AmphibianArk&quot; /&gt; One such project is the Panama Amphibian Rescue and Conservation Project that built on existing conservation efforts in Panama to create a country-wide response to the threat of chytridiomycosis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://amphibianrescue.org/?page_id=91 |title=Panama Amphibian Rescue and Conservation Project |publisher=Amphibian Ark |accessdate=March 30, 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100614024615/http://amphibianrescue.org/?page_id=91 |archive-date=June 14, 2010 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[List of amphibians]]
* [[List of amphibian genera]]
* [[List of threatened reptiles and amphibians of the United States]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

=== Cited texts ===
* {{cite book |title=Zoology |url=https://archive.org/details/zoology0000dori |url-access=registration |last1=Dorit |first1=R. L. |last2=Walker |first2=W. F. |last3=Barnes |first3=R. D. |year=1991 |publisher=Saunders College Publishing |isbn=978-0-03-030504-7 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book |title=A Natural History of Amphibians |last1=Stebbins |first1=Robert C. |authorlink1=Robert C. Stebbins|last2=Cohen |first2=Nathan W. |year=1995 |publisher=Princeton University Press |isbn=978-0-691-03281-8 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=0v47ou53yVsC&amp;pg=PR11&amp;dq=Caudata+Urodela#v=onepage&amp;q=Caudata%20Urodela&amp;f=false |ref=harv }}

== Further reading ==
* {{cite book
| last = Carroll
| first = Robert L.
| title = Vertebrate Paleontology and Evolution
| url = https://archive.org/details/vertebratepaleon0000carr
| url-access = registration
| year = 1988
| publisher = W. H. Freeman
| isbn = 978-0-7167-1822-2
  }}
* {{cite book
| last = Carroll
| first = Robert L.
| title = The Rise of Amphibians: 365 Million Years of Evolution
| year = 2009
| publisher = Johns Hopkins University Press
| isbn = 978-0-8018-9140-3
  }}
* {{cite book
| last = Duellman
| first = William E.
|author2=Linda Trueb
| title = Biology of Amphibians
| year = 1994
| publisher = Johns Hopkins University Press
| isbn = 978-0-8018-4780-6
  }}
* {{cite journal
| last1 = Frost
| first1 = Darrel R.
| title = The Amphibian Tree of Life
| hdl = 2246/5781
| journal = Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History
| volume = 297
| pages = 1–291
| year = 2006
| last2 = Grant | first2 = Taran
| last3 = Faivovich | first3 = Julián
| last4 = Bain | first4 = Raoul H.
| last5 = Haas | first5 = Alexander
| last6 = Haddad |first6 = Célio F.B.
| last7 = De Sá | first7 = Rafael O.
| last8 = Channing | first8 = Alan
| last9 = Wilkinson | first9 = Mark
| last10 = Donnellan | first10 = Stephen C.
| last11 = Raxworthy | first11 = Christopher J.
| last12 = Campbell | first12 = Jonathan A.
| last13 = Blotto | first13 = Boris L.
| last14 = Moler | first14 = Paul
| last15 = Drewes | first15 = Robert C.
| last16 = Nussbaum |first16 = Ronald A.
| last17 = Lynch | first17 = John D.
| last18 = Green | first18 = David M.
| last19 = Wheeler | first19 = Ward C.
| doi = 10.1206/0003-0090(2006)297[0001:TATOL]2.0.CO;2
| url = https://www.researchgate.net/publication/213771051}}
* {{cite journal
| last1 = Pounds
| first1 = J. Alan
| title = Widespread amphibian extinctions from epidemic disease driven by global warming
| journal = Nature
| volume = 439
| issue = 7073
| pages = 161–167
| year = 2006
| pmid = 16407945
| doi = 10.1038/nature04246
| last2 = Bustamante | first2 = Martín R.
| last3 = Coloma | first3 = Luis A.
| last4 = Consuegra | first4 = Jamie A.
| last5 = Fogden | first5 = Michael P. L.
| last6 = Foster | first6 = Pru N.
| last7 = La Marca | first7 = Enrique
| last8 = Masters | first8 = Karen L.
| last9 = Merino-Viteri | first9 = Andrés
| last10 = Puschendorf | first10 = Robert
| last11 = Ron | first11 = Santiago R.
| last12 = Sánchez-Azofeifa | first12 = G. Arturo
| last13 = Still | first13 = Christopher J.
| last14 = Young | first14 = Bruce E.
| bibcode = 2006Natur.439..161A
| url = https://www.academia.edu/13811723}}
* {{cite journal
| last1 = Stuart | first1 = Simon N.
| last2 = Chanson | first2 = Janice S.
| last3 = Cox | first3 = Neil A.
| last4 = Young | first4 = Bruce E.
| last5 = Rodrigues | first5 = Ana S. L.
| last6 = Fischman | first6 = Debra L.
| last7 = Waller | first7 = Robert W.
| title = Status and trends of amphibian declines and extinctions worldwide
| journal = Science
| volume = 306
| issue = 5702
| pages = 1783–1786
| year = 2004
| doi = 10.1126/science.1103538
| pmid = 15486254
| bibcode = 2004Sci...306.1783S
| citeseerx = 10.1.1.225.9620}}
* {{cite book
| editor1 = Stuart, S. N.
| editor2 = Hoffmann, M.
| editor3 = Chanson, J. S.
| editor4 = Cox, N. A.
| editor5 = Berridge, R. J.
| editor6 = Ramani, P.
| editor7 = Young, B. E.
| title = Threatened Amphibians of the World
| publisher = Published by [[Lynx Edicions]], in association with [[IUCN-The World Conservation Union]], [[Conservation International]] and [[NatureServe]].
| year = 2008
| isbn = 978-84-96553-41-5
| url = http://www.amphibians.org/publications/threatened-amphibians-of-the-world/
| access-date = October 30, 2014
| archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20141030220413/http://www.amphibians.org/publications/threatened-amphibians-of-the-world/
| archive-date = October 30, 2014
| url-status = dead
}}

== External links ==

{{Commons category|Amphibia}}
{{Wikispecies|Amphibia}}
{{Wikibooks|Dichotomous Key|Amphibia}}
* [http://www.animalspot.net/category/amphibians Amphibians] – AnimalSpot.net
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20130726202037/http://photos.archeozoo.org/index/category/54-amphibiens_langen_amphibians_lang_langes_anfibios_lang_?lang=en_UK ArchéoZooThèque : Amphibians skeletons drawings] : available in vector, image and PDF formats
* [http://www.amphibians.org/ Amphibian Specialist Group]
* [http://www.amphibianark.org/ Amphibian Ark]
* [http://www.amphibiaweb.org/ AmphibiaWeb]
* [http://www.globalamphibians.org/ Global Amphibian Assessment]
* [http://sounds.bl.uk/Browse.aspx?category=Environment&amp;collection=Amphibians Amphibian vocalisations on Archival Sound Recordings]

{{Amphibians}}
{{Chordata}}
{{Taxonbar|from=Q10908}}
{{Authority control}}
{{Featured article}}

[[Category:Amphibians| ]]
[[Category:Amphibious organisms]]
&lt;!-- [[Category:Animal classes]] moved to Latin name redirect --&gt;
[[Category:Extant Late Devonian first appearances]]
[[Category:Taxa named by John Edward Gray]]</text>
      <sha1>njsgkmee5d7rzvc4fbfwbziilvgsia2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
