  <page>
    <title>Buffy the Vampire Slayer (film)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4231</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943274625</id>
      <parentid>942060210</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T22:49:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2600:1012:B013:FA50:BD28:3C80:3EFE:13E5</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Fixed typo</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox film
| name           = Buffy the Vampire Slayer
| image          = Buffy The Vampire Slayer Movie.jpg
| alt            = Photograph of a person in a cheerleading outfit holding a wooden stake and a pom pom
| caption        = Theatrical release poster
| director       = [[Fran Rubel Kuzui]]
| producer       = [[Howard Rosenman]]&lt;br&gt;[[Kaz Kuzui]]
| writer         = [[Joss Whedon]]
| starring       = {{Plainlist|
* [[Kristy Swanson]]
* [[Donald Sutherland]]
* [[Paul Reubens]]
* [[Rutger Hauer]]
* [[Luke Perry]]
}}
| music          = [[Carter Burwell]]
| cinematography = [[James Hayman]]
| editing        = [[Jill Savitt]]
| studio         = Sandollar&lt;br/&gt;Kuzui Enterprises
| distributor    = [[20th Century Fox]]
| released       = {{Film date|1992|07|31}}
| runtime        = 86 minutes
| country        = United States
| language       = English
| budget         = $7 million
| gross          = $16.6 million&lt;ref name=&quot;mojo&quot;/&gt;
}}

'''''Buffy the Vampire Slayer''''' is a 1992 American [[comedy horror]] film directed by [[Fran Rubel Kuzui]] and starring [[Kristy Swanson]], [[Donald Sutherland]], [[Paul Reubens]], [[Rutger Hauer]], [[Luke Perry]], and [[Hilary Swank]]. It follows a [[Valley girl]] [[Cheerleading|cheerleader]] named [[Buffy Summers|Buffy]] who learns that it is her fate to hunt vampires.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://articles.latimes.com/1992-05-17/entertainment/ca-176_1_encino-man | work=Los Angeles Times | first=Andy | last=Marx | title=A look inside Hollywood and the movies : SUMMERTIME BRUISE : Who Dares Intrude During the Season of the Giants? Several Rock-Slinging Davids | date=1992-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was a moderate success at the box office&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?page=weekend&amp;id=buffythevampireslayer.htm|title=Buffy the Vampire Slayer (1992) Weekend Box Office|work=Box Office Mojo|accessdate=2007-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; but received mixed reception from critics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/buffy_the_vampire_slayer/|title=Buffy the Vampire Slayer (1992)|work=Rotten Tomatoes|accessdate=February 6, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film was taken in a different direction from the one its writer [[Joss Whedon]] intended, and five years later, he created the darker and acclaimed TV series [[Buffy the Vampire Slayer|of the same name]].

==Plot==
High school senior [[Buffy Summers]] ([[Kristy Swanson]]) attends Hemery High School in [[Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles]]; her main concerns are shopping and spending time with her rich, snooty friends and her boyfriend, Jeffrey ([[Randall Batinkoff]]). While at school one day, she is approached by a man who calls himself [[Minor characters of Buffy the Vampire Slayer#Merrick|Merrick]] ([[Donald Sutherland]]). He informs her that she is [[Slayer (Buffyverse)|The Slayer]], or Chosen One, destined to kill vampires, and he is a [[Watcher (Buffy the Vampire Slayer)|Watcher]] whose duty it is to guide and train her. She initially rejects his claim but is convinced that he's right when he's able to describe a recurring dream of hers in detail. In addition, Buffy is exhibiting uncanny abilities not known to her, including heightened agility, senses, and endurance, yet she repeatedly tries Merrick's patience with her frivolous nature, indifference to slaying, and sharp-tongued remarks.

After several successful outings, Buffy is drawn into conflict with Lothos ([[Rutger Hauer]]), a local vampire king and his acolyte, Amilyn ([[Paul Reubens]]). Two young men, [[Pike (Buffyverse character)|Oliver Pike]] ([[Luke Perry]]) and Benny ([[David Arquette]]), who resented Buffy and her friends due to differing social circles, are out drinking when they're attacked by Amilyn. Benny is turned, but Pike is saved by Merrick. As a vampire, Benny visits Pike and tries to get him to join him. Later, when Pike and his boss are discussing Benny, Pike tells him to run if he sees him.

Amilyn also abducts Cassandra ([[Natasha Gregson Wagner]]), a studious girl from Buffy's class, to sacrifice to Lothos. When her body is found, the news spreads through L.A. and Hemery High, but her murder is met with indifference from Buffy's clique.

When Pike realizes there's something wrong with Benny and that he's no longer safe, he decides to leave town. His plan is thwarted, however, when he encounters Amilyn and his gang of vampires. Amilyn hitches a ride on the hood of his van which crashes into a tree just before Amilyn loses an arm. Buffy and Merrick arrive to rescue him and Amilyn leaves the fight to talk to Lothos. After this encounter, Buffy and Pike start a friendship that eventually becomes romantic, and Pike becomes Buffy's partner in fighting the undead.

During a basketball game, Buffy discovers that one of the players, and a friend of Jeffrey's, is a vampire. After a quick chase to a parade float storage yard, Buffy confronts Lothos, shortly after she and Pike take down his gang. Lothos puts Buffy into a trance, which is broken due to Merrick's intervention. Lothos stabs Merrick with the stake he attempted to use on him. Lothos leaves, saying Buffy is not ready. As Merrick dies, he tells Buffy to do things her own way rather than live by the rules of others and gives her one final clue: &quot;Remember about the music.&quot;

Because of her new life, its responsibilities, and the heartbreak of losing her Watcher, Buffy, emotionally shocked, starts neglecting her Slayer duties. When she arrives at school, she attempts to explain things to her friends, but they refuse to understand her, as they are more concerned with an upcoming school dance. Buffy falls out with them as she realizes she has outgrown their immature, selfish behavior.

At the senior dance, Buffy is dismayed to find Jeffrey has dumped her for one of her friends. However, she meets up with Pike, and as they start to dance and kiss, Lothos sends his remaining minions to the school to attack the humans at the dance.

Buffy confronts the vampires outside, while inside the gym Pike fights and kills the vampiric Benny. After overpowering the vampires, Buffy confronts Lothos inside the school and kills Amilyn. Lothos attempts to ensorcel Buffy again, but when the dance music stops, she remembers Merrick's words and defends herself.

She first tries to repel Lothos with a cross, but the vampire king is unimpressed. He grabs the cross, setting it afire, but Buffy uses her hair spray as a makeshift flame-thrower and burns him before escaping to the gym. Buffy sees her classmates recovering from the vampire attack, but Lothos bursts into the gym, promising to kill everyone. The Slayer and vampire duel, a wooden flagpole versus a [[katana]]. In the end, Buffy stakes Lothos and kills him.

As the survivors leave, Buffy and Pike decide to finish their dance. The film ends with the two of them leaving the dance on a motorcycle. A skeptical news crew headed up by [[Liz Smith (journalist)|Liz Smith]] interviews the students and the principal about the attack during the credits.

==Cast==
{{div col|colwidth=22em}}
* [[Kristy Swanson]] as [[Buffy Summers]]
* [[Luke Perry]] as [[Pike (Buffyverse character)|Pike]]
* [[Rutger Hauer]] as Lothos
* [[Donald Sutherland]] as [[Minor characters of Buffy the Vampire Slayer#Merrick|Merrick Jamison-Smythe]]
* [[Paul Reubens]] as Amilyn
* [[Hilary Swank]] as Kimberly Hannah
* Paris Vaughan as Nicole &quot;Nicki&quot;
* Michele Abrams as Jennifer
* [[Randall Batinkoff]] as Jeffrey Kramer
* [[David Arquette]] as Benny Jacks
* [[Stephen Root]] as Principal Gary Murray
* [[Natasha Gregson Wagner]] as Cassandra
* [[Sasha Jenson]] as Grueller
* [[Thomas Jane|Tom Jane]] as Zeph
* [[Candy Clark]] as [[Joyce Summers|Buffy's Mom]]&lt;!-- this character is not credited as Joyce Summers, who was created for the TV series --&gt;
* [[Ben Affleck]] (''uncredited'') as Basketball Player #10
* [[Ricki Lake]] (''uncredited'') as Charlotte
* [[Seth Green]] (''uncredited'') as a vampire
* [[Alexis Arquette]] (''uncredited'') as vampire DJ
{{div col end}}

==Production==
Writer Whedon sold the film to Dolly Parton's production company, Sandollar, in the fall of 1991.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.yahoo.com/movies/joss-whedon-buffy-the-vampire-slayer-118217991342.html |title=Remembering Buffy the Vampire Slayer film |publisher=Yahoo movies |date=May 5, 2015 |accessdate=June 25, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Production was limited to five weeks to accommodate [[Luke Perry]]'s ''[[Beverly Hills 90210]]'' filming schedule.&lt;ref name=&quot;Robin Burks&quot;&gt;{{cite article| url=https://screenrant.com/buffy-movie-shocking-trivia-facts/| title=Things You Didn't Know About the Buffy the Vampire Slayer Movie| author=Robin Burks| publisher=screenrant.com| date=2017-12-22| access-date=2018-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Whedon was involved in an advisory role early in the production but departed after becoming dissatisfied with the direction the film was taking.&lt;ref name=&quot;Robin Burks&quot;/&gt; Executives at [[20th Century Fox]] removed many of Whedon's jokes, believing the humor to be too abstract for audiences. They also disliked the darker elements in Whedon's original script, wanting to make it a lighter comedy. Merrick's suicide was replaced with his being killed by Lothos, and Buffy's burning down her high school gym to kill all the vampires was eliminated altogether.

All this led Whedon to finally walk off the set.&lt;ref name=&quot;Robin Burks&quot; /&gt; He has been highly critical of actor Donald Sutherland's behavior on set, describing him as entitled and difficult to work with.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tasha Robinson&quot;&gt;{{cite article| url=https://www.avclub.com/joss-whedon-1798208181| title=Joss Whedon Interview| author=Tasha Robinson| publisher=AVClub| date=2001-09-05| access-date=2018-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sutherland had a penchant for improvising or altering his lines in the script, which director Rubel Kuzui allowed him to do freely because he was the film's most high-profile star. Whedon felt this made Merrick's dialogue in the film disjointed and unintelligible.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=https://thoughtcatalog.com/nico-lang/2013/01/25-little-known-facts-about-buffy-the-vampire-slayer/| title=25 Little-Known Facts About 'Buffy the Vampire Slayer'| author=Nico Lang| publisher=thoughtcatalog.com| date=2013-01-02| access-date=2018-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tasha Robinson&quot; /&gt;

Filming in [[Los Angeles]] included the ballroom of the [[Park Plaza Hotel (Los Angeles)|Park Plaza Hotel]], where Merrick lives and trains Buffy; [[John Marshall High School (Los Angeles)|John Marshall High School]] in [[Los Feliz, Los Angeles|Los Feliz]];&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=https://www.movie-locations.com/movies/b/buffy.html#.WouKzXtFzIU| title=Film locations for 'Buffy the Vampire Slayer'| publisher=movie-locations.com| access-date=2018-02-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the gymnasium of [[University High School (Los Angeles)|University High School]] in [[West Los Angeles]], where the high school dance and vampire attack was filmed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite article|url= https://broadly.vice.com/en_us/article/paeyk9/perverting-the-youth-of-america-the-oral-history-of-teen-classic-jawbreaker|title='Perverting the Youth of America': The Oral History of Teen Classic 'Jawbreaker' | author=Mitchell Sunderland | publisher=Broadly | date=February 5, 2011 | accessdate= July 20, 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reception==
===Box office===
The film debuted at #5 at the North American box office&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Weekend Box Office `Honors' Tops in a Lackluster Bunch|newspaper= [[The Los Angeles Times]]|date=1994-05-10|url= http://articles.latimes.com/1994-05-10/entertainment/ca-56005_1_weekend-box-office|accessdate=2010-12-28|first=Robert W.|last=Welkos}}&lt;/ref&gt; and eventually grossed a modest $16,624,456 against a $7 million production budget.&lt;ref name=&quot;mojo&quot;&gt;{{mojo title|buffythevampireslayer|Buffy the Vampire Slayer}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Critical reception===
[[Alexander Walker (critic)|Alexander Walker]] of the [[Evening Standard]] wrote that &quot;to enjoy this moronic rubbish, you'd need to put your IQ into total unconsciousness.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|magazine=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|title=Crix' Pix|date=October 26, 1992|page=7}}&lt;/ref&gt; On [[review aggregator]] website [[Rotten Tomatoes]], the film has an approval rating of 35%, based on 52 reviews, with an average rating of 4.3/10. The consensus reads, &quot;''Buffy the Vampire Slayer''{{'}}s supernatural coming of age tale is let down by poor directing and even poorer plotting -- though Kristy Swanson and Paul Reubens' game performances still manage to slay.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/buffy_the_vampire_slayer |title=Buffy the Vampire Slayer |website=[[Rotten Tomatoes]] |access-date=27 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; On [[Metacritic]], the film has a weighted average score of 48 out of 100, based on 17 critics, indicating &quot;mixed or average reviews&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.metacritic.com/movie/buffy-the-vampire-slayer |title=Buffy the Vampire Slayer reviews |website=[[Metacritic.com]] |access-date=25 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Home media==
The film was released on [[VHS]] and Laserdisc in the U.S. in 1992 by [[20th Century Fox Home Entertainment|Fox Video]] and re-released in 1995 under the Twentieth Century Fox Selections banner. It was released on [[DVD]] in the U.S. in 2001 and on [[Blu-ray]] in 2011.

==Spin offs==
===Television===
{{main|Buffy the Vampire Slayer}}
The film was taken in a different direction from what one of its writer [[Joss Whedon]] intended, and five years later, he created the darker and acclaimed TV series [[Buffy the Vampire Slayer|of the same name]].

Many of the details given in the film differ from the [[Buffyverse canon|those of the later television series]]. For example, Buffy's age and history are dissimilar; she's a senior in high school in the film, but the series starts with her as a sophomore. The film does portray who the Buffy of the TV series was before she learned of her destiny as the Slayer: a popular but selfish and superficial cheerleader. In the film, her parents are wealthy but negligent socialites who care little for her and spend their time at parties and golf tournaments; in the TV series, Buffy has a caring, newly divorced mother named [[Joyce Summers|Joyce]]. The supernatural abilities of both vampires and the Slayer are depicted differently. The vampires in the film die like humans; in the TV series, they turn to dust. Unlike the TV series, their faces remain human albeit pale, fanged, and with notched ears, whereas in the TV series, they take on a demonic aspect, especially when newly raised. The TV series suggests that new vampires must consciously learn to maintain a human appearance. In the film, Merrick is hundreds of years old, having lived many lives training many Slayers; in the TV series, Watchers are mortal and specially trained for their role and mission. Merrick's British accent and the manner of his death are different when he appears in flashbacks in the TV series.

Joss Whedon has expressed his disapproval with the film's interpretation of the script,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cise.ufl.edu/cgi-bin/cgiwrap/hsiao/buffy/get-archive?date=19990117 Bronze VIP Archive - January 17, 1999&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141220181357/http://www.cise.ufl.edu/cgi-bin/cgiwrap/hsiao/buffy/get-archive?date=19990117 |date=December 20, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; stating &quot;I finally sat down and had written it and somebody had made it into a movie, and I felt like - well, that's not quite her. It's a start, but it's not quite the girl.&quot;

According to the ''Official Buffy Watcher's Guide'', Whedon wrote the pilot to the TV series as a sequel to his original script, which is why the TV series makes references to events that did not occur in the film. In 1999, [[Dark Horse Comics]] released a graphic novel adaptation of Whedon's original script under the title ''[[The Origin (Buffy comic)|The Origin]]''. Whedon stated: &quot;The ''Origin'' comic, though I have issues with it, CAN pretty much be accepted as canonical. They did a cool job of combining the movie script with the series, that was nice, and using the series Merrick and not a certain OTHER thespian who shall remain hated.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cise.ufl.edu/cgi-bin/cgiwrap/hsiao/buffy/get-archive?date=19990117 |title=Bronze VIP Archive - January 17, 1999 |publisher=Cise.ufl.edu |date=1999-01-17 |accessdate=2010-08-23 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141220181357/http://www.cise.ufl.edu/cgi-bin/cgiwrap/hsiao/buffy/get-archive?date=19990117 |archivedate=December 20, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Soundtrack==
{{Infobox album
| name       = Buffy the Vampire Slayer (Original Motion Picture Soundtrack)
| type       = soundtrack
| artist     = Various
| cover      =
| alt        =
| released   = July 28, 1992
| recorded   =
| venue      =
| studio     =
| genre      =
| length     = 41:57
| label      = [[Columbia Records]]
| producer   =
| prev_title =
| prev_year  =
| next_title =
| next_year  =
}} 
{{Track listing
| collapsed       = 
| headline        = Buffy the Vampire Slayer (Original Motion Picture Soundtrack)
| extra_column    = Original artist(s)

| all_writing     = 
| all_lyrics      = 
| all_music       =

| title1          = [[Keep It Comin' (Dance Till You Can't Dance No More)]]
| extra1          = [[C+C Music Factory]] featuring [[Deborah Cooper]] and [[Q-Unique]]  
| length1         = 3:58

| title2          = Man Smart, Woman Smarter
| extra2          = [[Dream Warriors (band)|Dream Warriors]]  
| length2         = 4:31

| title3          = Silent City
| extra3          = [[Matthew Sweet]]  
| length3         = 2:51

| title4          = We Close Our Eyes 
| extra4          = [[Susanna Hoffs]] 
| note4          = originally by [[Oingo Boingo]]
| length4         = 3:54

| title5          = Little Heaven
| extra5          = [[Toad the Wet Sprocket]]  
| length5         = 4:27

| title6          =  [[I Ain't Gonna Eat Out My Heart Anymore]]
| extra6          = [[Divinyls|diVINYLS]]
| length6         = 4:32

| title7          = [[Party with the Animals]]
| extra7          = [[Ozzy Osbourne]] 
| length7         = 4:18

| title8          = Zap City
| extra8          = [[The Cult]]  
| length8         = 5:14

| title9          = [[I Fought the Law]]
| extra9          = [[Mary's Danish]] 
| note9           = originally by [[The Crickets]]
| length9         = 3:19

| title10         =  Light Comes Out of Black
| extra10         = [[Rob Halford]] and [[Pantera]]
| length10        = 4:59
}}

The soundtrack does not include every song played in the film, which also included &quot;[[War Babies (War Babies album)|In the Wind]]&quot; by [[War Babies (band)|War Babies]] and &quot;Inner Mind&quot; by [[Eon (musician)|Eon]].

==Possible remake==
On May 25, 2009, ''[[The Hollywood Reporter]]'' reported that [[Roy Lee]] and Doug Davison of [[Vertigo Entertainment]] were working with Fran Rubel Kuzui and Kaz Kuzui on a re-envisioning or relaunch of the ''Buffy'' film for the big screen. The film would not be a [[sequel]] or [[prequel]] to the existing film or television franchise, and [[Joss Whedon]] would have no involvement in the project. None of the characters, cast, or crew from the television series would be featured.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Kit |first=Borys |url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/content_display/film/news/e3i666afabc28491e6a2f12dfb80c0f7098 |title='Buffy' in for feature relaunch |work=[[The Hollywood Reporter]]|date=2009-05-25 |accessdate=2010-08-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Television series executive producer [[Marti Noxon]] later reflected that this story might have been produced by the studio in order to frighten Whedon into taking the reins of the project.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fearnet.com/news/interviews/b19604_exclusive_marti_noxon_on_future_of_buffy.html|title=Exclusive: Marti Noxon on the Future of 'Buffy'|accessdate=2010-07-24|date=2010-07-21|work=[[Fearnet]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; On November 22, 2010, ''[[The Hollywood Reporter]]'' confirmed that Warner Bros. had picked up the movie rights to the remake.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/blogs/heat-vision/buffy-remake-finds-home-warner-48105 | work=The Hollywood Reporter | first=Borys | last=Kit | title='Buffy' Remake Finds a Home at Warner Bros | date=2010-11-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film was set for release sometime in 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.comingsoon.net/films.php?id=71841|title=Comingsoon.net|accessdate=December 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 20th Century Fox, which usually holds the rights to both  ''Buffy'' and ''[[Angel (1999 TV series)|Angel]]'' television series, would retain merchandising and some distribution rights.{{citation needed|date=December 2011}}

The idea of the remake caused wrath among fans of the TV series, since Whedon is not involved. The project did not have any connection with the show and would not conform to the [[Continuity (fiction)|continuity]] maintained with the ''[[Buffy the Vampire Slayer Season Eight]]'' and ''[[Buffy the Vampire Slayer Season Nine|Season Nine]]'' [[comic book]] titles. Not only the fandom, but the main cast members of both the ''Buffy'' and ''[[Angel (1999 TV series)|Angel]]'' series expressed disagreement with the report on Twitter and in recent interviews. [[Sarah Michelle Gellar]] said, &quot;I think it's a horrible idea. To try to do a ''Buffy'' without Joss Whedon... to be incredibly non-eloquent: that's the dumbest idea I've ever heard.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TOiyLDsHHfw |title=YouTube |publisher=YouTube |date= |accessdate=2014-05-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Proposed shooting locations included Black Wood and other areas in rural England, due to budgetary constraints and the potential setting being outside of the city, an unusual change for the franchise.{{fact|date=November 2019}}

In December 2011, more than a year after the official reboot announcement, the ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' site reported that Whit Anderson, the writer picked for the new ''Buffy'' movie, had her script rejected by the producers behind the project, and that a new writer was being sought. Sources also stated that &quot;If you're going to bring it back, you have to do it right. [Anderson] came in with some great ideas and she had reinvented some of the lore and it was pretty cool but in the end there just wasn't enough on the page.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://herocomplex.latimes.com/2011/12/22/buffy-the-vampire-slayer-movie-looking-for-new-writer/?dlvrit=63378 |title='Buffy the Vampire Slayer' movie looking for new writer &amp;#124; Hero Complex – latimes.com |work=Herocomplex.latimes.com |date=2011-12-22 |accessdate=2012-06-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of July 2018, Joss Whedon announced at San Diego Comic Con that he was working on a reboot of the series and that it might feature a slayer of color.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theverge.com/2018/7/26/17619650/buffy-the-vampire-slayer-monica-owusu-breen-reboot-sequel-series-new-slayer-fray-comics|title=Buffy reboot showrunner clarifies: it’s not a reboot, it’s a sequel|first=Tasha|last=Robinson|date=26 July 2018|website=The Verge}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* ''[[The Origin (Buffy comic)|The Origin]]'', a comic book reinterpretation of the movie script
* [[Vampire film]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
* {{IMDb title|0103893|Buffy the Vampire Slayer}}
* {{allrovi movie|7425|Buffy the Vampire Slayer}}
* {{mojo title|buffythevampireslayer|Buffy the Vampire Slayer}}
* {{rotten-tomatoes|buffy_the_vampire_slayer|Buffy the Vampire Slayer}}

{{Joss Whedon}}
{{Buffy the Vampire Slayer}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Buffy The Vampire Slayer (Film)}}
[[Category:1990s comedy horror films]]
[[Category:1990s high school films]]
[[Category:1990s teen comedy films]]
[[Category:1990s teen horror films]]
[[Category:1992 films]]
[[Category:1992 horror films]]
[[Category:20th Century Fox films]]
[[Category:20th Century Fox franchises]]
[[Category:American comedy horror films]]
[[Category:American fantasy films]]
[[Category:American films]]
[[Category:American high school films]]
[[Category:American supernatural horror films]]
[[Category:American teen comedy films]]
[[Category:American teen horror films]]
[[Category:Cheerleading films]]
[[Category:Dark fantasy films]]
[[Category:English-language films]]
[[Category:1990s feminist films]]
[[Category:Films about proms]]
[[Category:Films adapted into television programs]]
[[Category:Films scored by Carter Burwell]]
[[Category:Films set in Los Angeles]]
[[Category:Films shot in Los Angeles]]
[[Category:Films with screenplays by Joss Whedon]]
[[Category:Vampire comedy films]]
[[Category:Buffy the Vampire Slayer]]
[[Category:Works based on Buffy the Vampire Slayer|Film]]
[[Category:American feminist films]]
[[Category:American action comedy films]]
[[Category:American action horror films]]
[[Category:1990s action comedy films]]</text>
      <sha1>5lrpb7q79oyhmp87qslk3h10snwc2bt</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
