  <page>
    <title>Base pair</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4292</id>
    <revision>
      <id>931435015</id>
      <parentid>930692140</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-18T22:07:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelinking 1 books for [[WP:V|verifiability]].) #IABot (v2.1alpha3</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[File:AT DNA base pair.png|thumb|250px|Depiction of the [[adenine]]–[[thymine]] Watson–Crick base pair]]
A '''base pair''' ('''bp''') is a unit consisting of two [[nucleobase]]s bound to each other by [[hydrogen bond]]s.  They form the building blocks of the [[DNA]] double helix and contribute to the folded structure of both DNA and [[RNA]]. Dictated by specific [[hydrogen bond]]ing patterns, Watson–Crick base pairs ([[guanine]]–[[cytosine]] and [[adenine]]–[[thymine]]) allow the DNA helix to maintain a regular helical structure that is subtly dependent on its [[nucleotide sequence]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Sequence-Dependent Variability of B-DNA | doi=10.1007/0-387-29148-2_2 | journal=DNA Conformation and Transcription |pages=18–34 |year=2005 | vauthors = Zhurkin VB, Tolstorukov MY, Xu F, Colasanti AV, Olson WK  | isbn=978-0-387-25579-8 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Complementarity (molecular biology)|complementary]] nature of this based-paired structure provides a redundant copy of the [[genetic information]] encoded within each strand of DNA. The regular structure and data redundancy provided by the DNA double helix make DNA well suited to the storage of genetic information, while base-pairing between DNA and incoming nucleotides provides the mechanism through which [[DNA polymerase]] replicates DNA and [[RNA polymerase]] transcribes DNA into RNA. Many DNA-binding proteins can recognize specific base-pairing patterns that identify particular regulatory regions of genes.

Intramolecular base pairs can occur within single-stranded nucleic acids. This is particularly important in RNA molecules (e.g., [[transfer RNA]]), where Watson–Crick base pairs (guanine–cytosine and adenine–[[uracil]]) permit the formation of short double-stranded helices, and a wide variety of non-Watson–Crick interactions (e.g., G–U or A–A) allow RNAs to fold into a vast range of specific three-dimensional [[RNA structure|structures]]. In addition, base-pairing between [[transfer RNA]] (tRNA) and [[messenger RNA]] (mRNA) forms the basis for the [[molecular recognition]] events that result in the nucleotide sequence of mRNA becoming [[Genetic code|translated]] into the amino acid sequence of [[protein]]s via the [[genetic code]].

The size of an individual [[gene]] or an organism's entire [[genome]] is often measured in base pairs because DNA is usually double-stranded. Hence, the number of total base pairs is equal to the number of nucleotides in one of the strands (with the exception of non-coding single-stranded regions of [[telomere]]s). The [[haploid]] [[human genome]] (23 [[chromosome]]s) is estimated to be about 3.2 billion bases long and to contain 20,000–25,000 distinct protein-coding genes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Moran |first=Laurence A. | name-list-format = vanc |url=http://sandwalk.blogspot.com/2011/03/how-big-is-human-genome.html |title=The total size of the human genome is very likely to be ~3,200 Mb |publisher=Sandwalk.blogspot.com |date=2011-03-24 |access-date=2012-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.strategicgenomics.com/Genome/index.htm |title=The finished length of the human genome is 2.86 Gb |publisher=Strategicgenomics.com |date=2006-06-12 |access-date=2012-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;IHSGC2004&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | author = International Human Genome Sequencing Consortium | title = Finishing the euchromatic sequence of the human genome | journal = Nature | volume = 431 | issue = 7011 | pages = 931–45 | date = October 2004 | pmid = 15496913 | doi = 10.1038/nature03001 | bibcode = 2004Natur.431..931H }}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[kilobase]] (kb) is a unit of measurement in [[molecular biology]] equal to 1000 base pairs of DNA or RNA.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Cockburn AF, Newkirk MJ, Firtel RA | title = Organization of the ribosomal RNA genes of Dictyostelium discoideum: mapping of the nontranscribed spacer regions | journal = Cell | volume = 9 | issue = 4 Pt 1 | pages = 605–13 | date = December 1976 | pmid = 1034500 | doi = 10.1016/0092-8674(76)90043-X }}&lt;/ref&gt; The total amount of related [[DNA]] base pairs on Earth is estimated at 5.0{{e|37}} and weighs 50 billion [[tonne]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT-20150718-rn&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Nuwer |first=Rachel | name-list-format = vanc |date=18 July 2015 |title=Counting All the DNA on Earth |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2015/07/21/science/counting-all-the-dna-on-earth.html |work=The New York Times |location=New York |publisher=The New York Times Company |issn=0362-4331 |access-date=2015-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--- PLOS paper cited by NYT used 'tonne' unit. ---&gt; In comparison, the total [[Biomass (ecology)|mass]] of the [[biosphere]] has been estimated to be as much as 4&amp;nbsp;[[tonnes#Derived units|TtC]] (trillion tons of [[carbon]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;AGCI-2015&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.agci.org/classroom/biosphere/index.php |title=The Biosphere: Diversity of Life |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |website=Aspen Global Change Institute |location=Basalt, CO |access-date=2015-07-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--- Aspen Global Change Institute (US-based) defined TtC as 'trillion tons of C'. ---&gt;

==Hydrogen bonding and stability==
&lt;div class=&quot;thumb tright&quot; style=&quot;background:#f9f9f9; border:1px solid #ccc; margin:0.5em;&quot;&gt;
{| border=&quot;0&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width:230px; font-size:85%; border:1px solid #ccc; margin:0.3em;&quot;
|-
|[[File:Base pair GC.svg|282px]]
|}
{| border=&quot;0&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width:230px; font-size:85%; border:1px solid #ccc; margin:0.3em;&quot;
|-
|[[File:Base pair AT.svg|282px]]
|}
&lt;div style=&quot;border: none; width:282px;&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;thumbcaption&quot;&gt;Top, a '''G.C''' base pair with three [[hydrogen bond]]s. Bottom, an '''A.T''' base pair with two hydrogen bonds. Non-covalent hydrogen bonds between the bases are shown as dashed lines. The wiggly lines stand for the connection to the pentose sugar and point in the direction of the minor groove. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

[[Hydrogen bond]]ing is the chemical interaction that underlies the base-pairing rules described above. Appropriate geometrical correspondence of hydrogen bond donors and acceptors allows only the &quot;right&quot; pairs to form stably. DNA with high [[GC-content]] is more stable than DNA with low GC-content. But, contrary to popular belief, the hydrogen bonds do not stabilize the DNA significantly; stabilization is mainly due to stacking interactions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Yakovchuk2006&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Yakovchuk P, Protozanova E, Frank-Kamenetskii MD | title = Base-stacking and base-pairing contributions into thermal stability of the DNA double helix | journal = Nucleic Acids Research | volume = 34 | issue = 2 | pages = 564–74 | date = 2006-01-30 | pmid = 16449200 | pmc = 1360284 | doi = 10.1093/nar/gkj454 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The bigger [[nucleobase]]s, adenine and guanine, are members of a class of double-ringed chemical structures called [[purine]]s; the smaller nucleobases, cytosine and thymine (and uracil), are members of a class of single-ringed chemical structures called [[pyrimidine]]s. Purines are complementary only with pyrimidines: pyrimidine-pyrimidine pairings are energetically unfavorable because the molecules are too far apart for hydrogen bonding to be established; purine-purine pairings are energetically unfavorable because the molecules are too close, leading to overlap repulsion. Purine-pyrimidine base-pairing of AT or GC or UA (in RNA) results in proper duplex structure. The only other purine-pyrimidine pairings would be AC and GT and UG (in RNA); these pairings are mismatches because the patterns of hydrogen donors and acceptors do not correspond. The GU pairing, with two hydrogen bonds, does occur fairly often in [[RNA]] (see [[wobble base pair]]).

Paired DNA and RNA molecules are comparatively stable at room temperature, but the two nucleotide strands will separate above a [[Dna melting|melting point]] that is determined by the length of the molecules, the extent of mispairing (if any), and the GC content. Higher GC content results in higher melting temperatures; it is, therefore, unsurprising that the genomes of [[extremophile]] organisms such as ''[[Thermus thermophilus]]'' are particularly GC-rich. On the converse, regions of a genome that need to separate frequently — for example, the promoter regions for often-[[transcription (genetics)|transcribed]] genes — are comparatively GC-poor (for example, see [[TATA box]]). GC content and melting temperature must also be taken into account when designing  [[primer (molecular biology)|primers]] for [[PCR]] reactions.

===Examples===
The following DNA sequences illustrate pair double-stranded patterns. By convention, the top strand is written from the [[5' end]] to the [[3' end]]; thus, the bottom strand is written 3' to 5'.

:A base-paired DNA sequence:
::{{code|ATCGATTGAGCTCTAGCG}}
::{{code|TAGCTAACTCGAGATCGC}}

:The corresponding RNA sequence, in which [[uracil]] is substituted for thymine in the RNA strand:
::{{code|AUCGAUUGAGCUCUAGCG}}
::{{code|UAGCUAACUCGAGAUCGC}}

==Base analogs and intercalators==

{{Main|Nucleic acid analogues}}
Chemical analogs of nucleotides can take the place of proper nucleotides and establish non-canonical base-pairing, leading to errors (mostly [[point mutation]]s) in [[DNA replication]] and [[Transcription (genetics)|DNA transcription]]. This is due to their [[isosteric]] chemistry. One common mutagenic base analog is [[5-bromouracil]], which resembles thymine but can base-pair to guanine in its [[enol]] form.

Other chemicals, known as [[DNA intercalation|DNA intercalators]], fit into the gap between adjacent bases on a single strand and induce [[frameshift mutation]]s by &quot;masquerading&quot; as a base, causing the DNA replication machinery to skip or insert additional nucleotides at the intercalated site. Most intercalators are large [[polyaromatic]] compounds and are known or suspected [[carcinogen]]s. Examples include [[ethidium bromide]] and [[acridine]].

==Unnatural base pair (UBP)==
{{See also|Artificial gene synthesis|Expanded genetic code|Nucleic acid analogue|Synthetic genomics}}
An unnatural base pair (UBP) is a designed subunit (or [[nucleobase]]) of [[DNA]] which is created in a laboratory and does not occur in nature.  DNA sequences have been described which use newly created nucleobases to form a third base pair, in addition to the two base pairs found in nature, A-T ([[adenine]] – [[thymine]]) and G-C ([[guanine]] – [[cytosine]]).  A few research groups have been searching for a third base pair for DNA, including teams led by [[Steven A. Benner]], [[Philippe Marliere]], [[Floyd Romesberg]] and [[Ichiro Hirao]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fikes&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.utsandiego.com/news/2014/may/08/tp-life-engineered-with-expanded-genetic-code/|title=Life engineered with expanded genetic code|last=Fikes|first=Bradley J.| name-list-format = vanc |date=May 8, 2014|work=San Diego Union Tribune|access-date=8 May 2014|url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140509001048/http://www.utsandiego.com/news/2014/may/08/tp-life-engineered-with-expanded-genetic-code/|archive-date=9 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some new base pairs have been reported.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Yang Z, Chen F, Alvarado JB, Benner SA | title = Amplification, mutation, and sequencing of a six-letter synthetic genetic system | journal = Journal of the American Chemical Society | volume = 133 | issue = 38 | pages = 15105–12 | date = September 2011 | pmid = 21842904 | pmc = 3427765 | doi = 10.1021/ja204910n }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Yamashige R, Kimoto M, Takezawa Y, Sato A, Mitsui T, Yokoyama S, Hirao I | title = Highly specific unnatural base pair systems as a third base pair for PCR amplification | journal = Nucleic Acids Research | volume = 40 | issue = 6 | pages = 2793–806 | date = March 2012 | pmid = 22121213 | pmc = 3315302 | doi = 10.1093/nar/gkr1068 | url = http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/content/40/6/2793 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Malyshev PNAS 20120724&quot;/&gt;

In 1989 Steven Benner (then working at the [[ETH Zurich|Swiss Federal Institute of Technology]] in Zurich) and his team led with modified forms of cytosine and guanine into DNA molecules ''in vitro''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Switzer C, Moroney SE, Benner SA | title = Enzymatic incorporation of a new base pair into DNA and RNA | date = 1989 | journal = J. Am. Chem. Soc. | volume = 111 | issue = 21| pages = 8322–8323 | doi = 10.1021/ja00203a067 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The nucleotides, which encoded RNA and proteins, were successfully replicated ''in vitro''. Since then, Benner's team has been trying to engineer cells that can make foreign bases from scratch, obviating the need for a feedstock.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ewan&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2014/05/07/living-organism-artificial-dna_n_5283095.html |title=Scientists Create First Living Organism With 'Artificial' DNA| last=Callaway| first=Ewan | name-list-format = vanc |date=May 7, 2014| work=Nature News| publisher=Huffington Post| access-date=8 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2002, Ichiro Hirao's group in Japan developed an unnatural base pair between 2-amino-8-(2-thienyl)purine (s) and pyridine-2-one (y) that functions in transcription and translation, for the site-specific incorporation of non-standard amino acids into proteins.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hirao I, Ohtsuki T, Fujiwara T, Mitsui T, Yokogawa T, Okuni T, Nakayama H, Takio K, Yabuki T, Kigawa T, Kodama K, Yokogawa T, Nishikawa K, Yokoyama S | title = An unnatural base pair for incorporating amino acid analogs into proteins | journal = Nature Biotechnology | volume = 20 | issue = 2 | pages = 177–82 | date = February 2002 | pmid = 11821864 | doi = 10.1038/nbt0202-177 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006, they created 7-(2-thienyl)imidazo[4,5-b]pyridine (Ds) and pyrrole-2-carbaldehyde (Pa) as a third base pair for replication and transcription.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hirao I, Kimoto M, Mitsui T, Fujiwara T, Kawai R, Sato A, Harada Y, Yokoyama S | title = An unnatural hydrophobic base pair system: site-specific incorporation of nucleotide analogs into DNA and RNA | journal = Nature Methods | volume = 3 | issue = 9 | pages = 729–35 | date = September 2006 | pmid = 16929319 | doi = 10.1038/nmeth915 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Afterward, Ds and 4-[3-(6-aminohexanamido)-1-propynyl]-2-nitropyrrole (Px) was discovered as a high fidelity pair in PCR amplification.&lt;ref&gt;Kimoto, M. et al. (2009) An unnatural base pair system for efficient PCR amplification and functionalization of DNA molecules. Nucleic acids Res. 37, e14&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Yamashige R, Kimoto M, Takezawa Y, Sato A, Mitsui T, Yokoyama S, Hirao I | title = Highly specific unnatural base pair systems as a third base pair for PCR amplification | journal = Nucleic Acids Research | volume = 40 | issue = 6 | pages = 2793–806 | date = March 2012 | pmid = 22121213 | pmc = 3315302 | doi = 10.1093/nar/gkr1068 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2013, they applied the Ds-Px pair to DNA aptamer generation by ''in vitro'' selection (SELEX) and demonstrated the genetic alphabet expansion significantly augment DNA aptamer affinities to target proteins.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Kimoto M, Yamashige R, Matsunaga K, Yokoyama S, Hirao I | title = Generation of high-affinity DNA aptamers using an expanded genetic alphabet | journal = Nature Biotechnology | volume = 31 | issue = 5 | pages = 453–7 | date = May 2013 | pmid = 23563318 | doi = 10.1038/nbt.2556 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2012, a group of American scientists led by Floyd Romesberg, a chemical biologist at the [[Scripps Research Institute]] in San Diego, California, published that his team designed an unnatural base pair (UBP).&lt;ref name=&quot;Malyshev PNAS 20120724&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Malyshev DA, Dhami K, Quach HT, Lavergne T, Ordoukhanian P, Torkamani A, Romesberg FE | title = Efficient and sequence-independent replication of DNA containing a third base pair establishes a functional six-letter genetic alphabet | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 109 | issue = 30 | pages = 12005–10 | date = July 2012 | pmid = 22773812 | pmc = 3409741 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.1205176109 | bibcode = 2012PNAS..10912005M }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The two new artificial nucleotides or ''Unnatural Base Pair'' (UBP) were named [[d5SICS]] and [[dNaM]]. More technically, these artificial [[nucleotide]]s bearing hydrophobic [[nucleobase]]s, feature two fused [[Aromatic hydrocarbon|aromatic rings]] that form a (d5SICS–dNaM) complex or base pair in DNA.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ewan&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NATJ-20140507&quot; /&gt; His team designed a variety of ''in vitro'' or &quot;test tube&quot; templates containing the unnatural base pair and they confirmed that it was efficiently replicated with high fidelity in virtually all sequence contexts using the modern standard ''in vitro'' techniques, namely [[Polymerase chain reaction|PCR amplification of DNA]] and PCR-based applications.&lt;ref name=&quot;Malyshev PNAS 20120724&quot;/&gt; Their results show that for PCR and PCR-based applications, the d5SICS–dNaM unnatural base pair is functionally equivalent to a natural base pair, and when combined with the other two natural base pairs used by all organisms, A–T and G–C, they provide a fully functional and expanded six-letter &quot;genetic alphabet&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;NATJ-20140507&quot;/&gt;

In 2014 the same team from the Scripps Research Institute reported that they synthesized a stretch of circular DNA known as a [[plasmid]] containing natural T-A and C-G base pairs along with the best-performing UBP Romesberg's laboratory had designed and inserted it into cells of the common bacterium ''[[Escherichia coli|E. coli]]'' that successfully replicated the unnatural base pairs through multiple generations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fikes&quot;/&gt; The [[transfection]] did not hamper the growth of the ''E. coli'' cells and showed no sign of losing its unnatural base pairs to its natural [[DNA repair]] mechanisms. This is the first known example of a living organism passing along an expanded genetic code to subsequent generations.&lt;ref name=&quot;NATJ-20140507&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Malyshev DA, Dhami K, Lavergne T, Chen T, Dai N, Foster JM, Corrêa IR, Romesberg FE | title = A semi-synthetic organism with an expanded genetic alphabet | journal = Nature | volume = 509 | issue = 7500 | pages = 385–8 | date = May 2014 | pmid = 24805238 | pmc = 4058825 | doi = 10.1038/nature13314 | bibcode = 2014Natur.509..385M }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sample&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/may/07/living-organism-pass-down-artificial-dna-us-scientists| title=First life forms to pass on artificial DNA engineered by US scientists| last=Sample|first=Ian| name-list-format = vanc |date=May 7, 2014|work=The Guardian|access-date=8 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Romesberg said he and his colleagues created 300 variants to refine the design of nucleotides that would be stable enough and would be replicated as easily as the natural ones when the cells divide.  This was in part achieved by the addition of a supportive [[Algae|algal gene]] that expresses a [[Nucleoside triphosphate|nucleotide triphosphate]] transporter which efficiently imports the triphosphates of both d5SICSTP and dNaMTP into ''E. coli'' bacteria.&lt;ref name=&quot;NATJ-20140507&quot;/&gt; Then, the natural bacterial replication pathways use them to accurately replicate a [[plasmid]] containing d5SICS–dNaM. Other researchers were surprised that the bacteria replicated these human-made DNA subunits.&lt;ref name = &quot;fox&quot; /&gt;

The successful incorporation of a third base pair is a significant breakthrough toward the goal of greatly expanding the number of [[amino acid]]s which can be encoded by DNA, from the existing 20 amino acids to a theoretically possible 172, thereby expanding the potential for living organisms to produce novel [[protein]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fikes&quot;/&gt; The artificial strings of DNA do not encode for anything yet, but scientists speculate they could be designed to manufacture new proteins which could have industrial or pharmaceutical uses.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pollack&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.nytimes.com/2014/05/08/business/researchers-report-breakthrough-in-creating-artificial-genetic-code.html?hpw&amp;rref=business&amp;_r=0| title=Scientists Add Letters to DNA’s Alphabet, Raising Hope and Fear |last=Pollack| first=Andrew| name-list-format = vanc | date=May 7, 2014| work=New York Times| access-date=8 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Experts said the synthetic DNA incorporating the unnatural base pair raises the possibility of life forms based on a different DNA code.&lt;ref name = &quot;fox&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.foxnews.com/health/2014/05/08/scientists-create-organism-using-artificial-dna/| title=Scientists create first living organism containing artificial DNA| date=May 8, 2014| work=The Wall Street Journal |publisher=Fox News| access-date=8 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Pollack&quot; /&gt;

==Length measurements==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[KB]] --&gt;
The following abbreviations are commonly used to describe the length of a D/R[[DNA|NA molecule]]:
* bp  = base pair(s)—one bp corresponds to approximately 3.4 [[Angstrom|Å]] (340 [[picometre|pm]])&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| vauthors = Alberts B, Johnson A, Lewis J, Morgan D, Raff M, Roberts K, Walter P |title=Molecular Biology of the Cell|date=December 2014|publisher=Garland Science, Taylor &amp; Francis Group|location=New York/Abingdon|isbn=978-0-8153-4432-2|page=177|edition=6th|ref=alberts_mboc}}&lt;/ref&gt;  of length along the strand, and to roughly 618 or 643 [[Atomic mass units|daltons]] for DNA and RNA respectively.
* kb (= kbp) = kilo base pairs = 1,000 bp
* Mb (= Mbp) = mega base pairs = 1,000,000 bp
* Gb = giga base pairs = 1,000,000,000 bp.

For single-stranded DNA/RNA, units of [[nucleotide]]s are used—abbreviated nt (or knt, Mnt, Gnt)—as they are not paired.
To distinguish between units of [[computer storage]] and bases, kbp, Mbp, Gbp, etc. may be used for base pairs.

The [[centimorgan]] is also often used to imply distance along a chromosome, but the number of base pairs it corresponds to varies widely. In the Human genome, the centimorgan is about 1 million base pairs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/Glossary.aspx?acronym=False#C |title=NIH ORDR – Glossary – C |publisher=Rarediseases.info.nih.gov |access-date=2012-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |vauthors=Scott MP, Matsudaira P, Lodish H, Darnell J, Zipursky L, Kaiser CA, Berk A, Krieger M |title=Molecular Cell Biology |edition=Fifth |publisher=W. H. Freeman |location=San Francisco |date=2004 |page=[https://archive.org/details/molecularcellbio00harv/page/396 396] |isbn=978-0-7167-4366-8 |quote=...in humans 1 centimorgan on average represents a distance of about 7.5x10&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; base pairs. |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/molecularcellbio00harv/page/396 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[List of Y-DNA single-nucleotide polymorphisms]]
* [[Non-canonical base pairing]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Further reading ==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book | vauthors = Watson JD, Baker TA, Bell SP, Gann A, Levine M, Losick R |date=2004 |title=Molecular Biology of the Gene |edition=5th |publisher=Pearson Benjamin Cummings: CSHL Press}} (See esp. ch. 6 and 9)
* {{cite book | veditors = Sigel A, Sigel H, Sigel RK |title=Interplay between Metal Ions and Nucleic Acids|series=Metal Ions in Life Sciences |volume=10 |date=2012 |publisher=Springer |doi=10.1007/978-94-007-2172-2 |isbn=978-9-4007-2171-5}}
* {{cite book | vauthors = Clever GH, Shionoya M |doi=10.1007/978-94-007-2172-2_10 |pmid=22210343 |pages=269–294 |chapter=Chapter 10. Alternative DNA Base-Pairing through Metal Coordination |title=Interplay between Metal Ions and Nucleic Acids |volume=10 |date=2012 |series=Metal Ions in Life Sciences |isbn=978-94-007-2171-5 }}
* {{cite book | vauthors = Megger DA, Megger N, Mueller J |doi=10.1007/978-94-007-2172-2_11 |pmid=22210344 |pages=295–317 |chapter=Chapter 11. Metal-Mediated Base Pairs in Nucleic Acids with Purine and Pyrimidine-Derived Neucleosides |title=Interplay between Metal Ions and Nucleic Acids |volume=10 |date=2012 |series=Metal Ions in Life Sciences |isbn=978-94-007-2171-5 }}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Base pairing}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060624093746/http://bioweb.pasteur.fr/seqanal/interfaces/dan.html DAN]—webserver version of the [[EMBOSS]] tool for calculating melting temperatures

{{Genetics}}
{{Nucleic acids}}
{{Nucleobases, nucleosides, and nucleotides}}
{{Portal bar|Biology}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Base Pair}}
[[Category:Nucleobases]]
[[Category:Molecular genetics]]
[[Category:Nucleic acids]]</text>
      <sha1>d8ggwrza333zphtj73r90n1lxvft1t0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
