  <page>
    <title>Benedictines</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4240</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942725646</id>
      <parentid>933643396</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-26T13:06:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Epistulae ad Familiares</username>
        <id>35787237</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Other orders */Combine for simplicity</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|a monastic order of the Catholic Church|similar monastic orders of the Eastern Orthodox Church|Order of Saint Benedict (Orthodox)|similar monastic orders of the Anglican Communion|Order of St. Benedict (Anglican)|other uses|Benedictine (disambiguation)}}
{{Redirect|O.S.B.||OSB (disambiguation){{!}}OSB}}
{{short description|Roman Catholic monastic order}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2015}}

{{Infobox organization
| name = Order of Saint Benedict
| native_name = ''Ordo Sancti Benedicti''
| image = Medalla San Benito.PNG
| size = 180px
| caption = Design on the obverse side of the [[Saint Benedict Medal]]
| abbreviation = OSB
| motto = ''Ora et Labora''&lt;br/&gt;{{smaller|(&quot;Pray and Work&quot;)}}
| formation = {{start date and age|529}}
| headquarters = [[Church of Sant'Anselmo all'Aventino, Rome]]
| leader_title = Abbot Primate
| leader_name = Gregory Polan
| main_organ = [[Benedictine Confederation]]
| parent_organization = [[Catholic Church]]
| type = [[Catholic religious order]]
| founder = [[Benedict of Nursia]]
| website = {{url|osb.org}}
| secessions = 
| founding_location = [[Subiaco Abbey]]
}}

The '''Benedictines''', officially the '''Order of Saint Benedict''' ({{lang-la|Ordo Sancti Benedicti}}, abbreviated as '''OSB'''), are a [[Christian monasticism|monastic]] [[Catholic religious order]] of monks and nuns that follow the [[Rule of Saint Benedict]]. They are also sometimes called the '''Black Monks''', in reference to the colour of the members' [[religious habit]]s.

Despite being called an order, the Benedictines do not operate under a single hierarchy but are instead organised as a collection of independent [[Cenobium|monastic communities]], with each community ([[monastery]], [[priory]] or [[abbey]]) within the order maintaining its autonomy. Unlike other religious orders, the Benedictines do not have a [[superior general]] or [[motherhouse]] with universal jurisdiction. Instead, the order is represented internationally by the [[Benedictine Confederation]], an organization that was set up in 1893 to represent the order's shared interests.

==Historical development==
{{Main|Benedict of Nursia}}
[[File:Fra Angelico 031.jpg|thumb|left|Saint Benedict of Nursia (c.&amp;nbsp;480–543). Detail from a [[fresco]] by [[Fra Angelico]] (c.&amp;nbsp;1400–1455) in the [[San Marco, Florence|Friary of San Marco]] [[Florence]].]]

The monastery at [[Subiaco, Lazio|Subiaco]] in Italy, established by [[Benedict of Nursia|Saint Benedict of Nursia]] {{circa}} 529, was the first of the dozen monasteries he founded. He later founded the [[Abbey of Monte Cassino]]. There is no evidence, however, that he intended to found an order and the [[Rule of Saint Benedict]] presupposes the autonomy of each community. When Monte Cassino was sacked by the Lombards about the year 580, the monks fled to Rome, and it seems probable that this constituted an important factor in the diffusion of a knowledge of Benedictine monasticism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic&quot;&gt;{{cite CE1913|wstitle=Benedictine Order|inline=yes|last=Alston|first=Cyprian|volume=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It was from the monastery of St. Andrew in Rome that [[Augustine of Canterbury|Augustine]], the prior, and his forty companions set forth in 595 on their mission for the evangelization of England. At various stopping places during the journey, the monks left behind them traditions concerning their rule and form of life, and probably also some copies of the Rule. [[Lérins Abbey]], for instance, founded by [[Honoratus]] in 375, probably received its first knowledge of the Benedictine Rule from the visit of St. Augustine and his companions in 596.&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic&quot;/&gt;

[[Gregory of Tours]] says that at [[Basilica of Saint-Martin d'Ainay#Ainay Abbey|Ainay Abbey]], in the sixth century, the monks &quot;followed the rules of Basil, Cassian, Caesarius, and other fathers, taking and using whatever seemed proper to the conditions of time and place&quot;, and doubtless the same liberty was taken with the Benedictine Rule when it reached them. In Gaul and Switzerland, it supplemented the much stricter Irish or Celtic Rule introduced by [[Columbanus]] and others. In many monasteries it eventually entirely displaced the earlier codes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Benedikt von Aniane.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Benedict of Aniane]] (747–821).]]
By the ninth century, however, the Benedictine had become the standard form of monastic life throughout the whole of Western Europe, excepting Scotland, Wales, and Ireland, where the Celtic observance still prevailed for another century or two.&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic&quot;/&gt; Largely through the work of [[Benedict of Aniane]], it became the rule of choice for monasteries throughout the Carolingian empire.&lt;ref name=Theisen&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.osb.org/gen/benedictines.html|title=The Benedictines: An Introduction by Abbot Primate Jerome Theisen OSB. Liturgical Press.|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Monastic scriptoria flourished from the ninth through the twelfth centuries. Sacred Scripture was always at the heart of every monastic scriptorium. As a general rule those of the monks who possessed skill as writers made this their chief, if not their sole active work. An anonymous writer of the ninth or tenth century speaks of six hours a day as the usual task of a scribe, which would absorb almost all the time available for active work in the day of a medieval monk.&lt;ref name=&quot;CE1913_Scriptorium&quot;&gt;{{cite CE1913|last= Huddleston|first= Gilbert Roger|wstitle=Scriptorium|volume= 13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Middle Ages monasteries were often founded by the nobility. [[Cluny Abbey]] was founded by [[William I, Duke of Aquitaine]] in 910. The abbey was noted for its strict adherence to the Rule of St. Benedict. The abbot of Cluny was the superior of all the daughter houses, through appointed priors.&lt;ref name=Theisen/&gt;

One of the earliest reforms of Benedictine practice was that initiated in 980 by [[Romuald]], who founded the [[Camaldolese]] community.

The dominance of the Benedictine monastic way of life began to decline towards the end of the twelfth century, which saw the rise of the Franciscans and Dominicans.&lt;ref name=Theisen/&gt; Benedictines took a fourth vow of &quot;stability&quot;, which professed loyalty to a particular foundation. Not being bound by location, the mendicants were better able to respond to an increasingly &quot;urban&quot; environment. This decline was further exacerbated by the practice of appointing a commendatory abbot, a lay person, appointed by a noble to oversee and to protect the goods of the monastery. Oftentimes, however, this resulted in the appropriation of the assets of monasteries at the expense of the community which they were intended to support.

===England===
The English Benedictine Congregation is the oldest of the nineteen Benedictine congregations. Augustine of Canterbury and his monks established the first English Benedictine monastery at Canterbury soon after their arrival in 597. Other foundations quickly followed. Through the influence of [[Wilfrid]], [[Benedict Biscop]], and [[Dunstan]], the Benedictine Rule spread with extraordinary rapidity, and in the North it was adopted in most of the monasteries that had been founded by the Celtic missionaries from Iona. Many of the episcopal sees of England were founded and governed by the Benedictines, and no fewer than nine of the old cathedrals were served by the black monks of the priories attached to them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic&quot;/&gt; Monasteries served as hospitals and places of refuge for the weak and homeless. The monks studied the healing properties of plants and minerals to alleviate the sufferings of the sick.&lt;ref name=Hicks&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.osb.org/gen/hicks/index.html|author=Dom Bruno Hicks OSB|title=  The Benedictines|date=2009|access-date=15 February 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171105194639/http://www.osb.org/gen/hicks/index.html|archive-date=5 November 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Germany was evangelized by English Benedictines. [[Willibrord]] and [[Boniface]] preached there in the seventh and eighth centuries and founded several abbeys.&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic&quot;/&gt;
 
In the [[English Reformation]], all [[Dissolution of the monasteries|monasteries were dissolved]] and their lands confiscated by the Crown, forcing their [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] members to flee into exile on the Continent. During the 19th century they were able to return to England, including to [[Selby Abbey]] in [[Yorkshire]], one of the few great monastic churches to survive the Dissolution.
[[File:Saint Benedict Medal.jpg|thumb|The two sides of a ''Saint Benedict Medal'']]

[[Minster-in-Thanet|St. Mildred's Priory]], on the [[Isle of Thanet]], [[Kent]], was built in 1027 on the site of an abbey founded in 670 by the daughter of the first Christian [[King of Kent]]. Currently the priory is home to a community of Benedictine nuns. Five of the most notable English abbeys are the Basilica of St Gregory the Great at Downside, commonly known as [[Downside Abbey]], The Abbey of St Edmund, King and Martyr commonly known as [[Douai Abbey]] in Upper Woolhampton, Reading, Berkshire, [[Ealing Abbey]] in Ealing, West London, and [[Worth Abbey]].&lt;ref name=Battell&gt;{{cite magazine|author=Colin Battell, OSB|title=Spirituality on the beach|magazine=The Tablet|date= 2 December 2006|pp= 18–19}} The late Cardinal [[Basil Hume]] was Abbot of Ampleforth Abbey before being appointed Archbishop of Westminster.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Martin&gt;{{cite book|first=Christopher |last=Martin |title=A Glimpse of Heaven: Catholic Churches in England and Wales|location=London|publisher= English Heritage|date= 2007}} Examines the abbeys rebuilt after 1850 (by benefactors among the Catholic aristocracy and recusant squirearchy), mainly Benedictine but including a Cistercian Abbey at Mount St. Bernard (by Pugin) and a Carthusian Charterhouse in Sussex. There is a review of book by Richard Lethbridge &quot;Monuments to Catholic confidence,&quot; ''The Tablet'' 10 February 2007, 27.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Prinknash Abbey]], used by Henry VIII as a hunting lodge, was officially returned to the Benedictines four hundred years later, in 1928. During the next few years, so-called Prinknash Park was used as a home until it was returned to the order.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|author=Mian Ridge |title=Prinknash monks downsize|magazine=The Tablet|date= 12 November 2005|p= 34}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ampleforth Abbey|St. Lawrence's Abbey]] in Ampleforth, Yorkshire was founded in 1802. In 1955, Ampleforth set up a daughter house, a priory at St. Louis, Missouri which became independent in 1973 and became [[Saint Louis Abbey]] in its own right in 1989.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.stlouisabbey.org/history/ &quot;History&quot;, Saint Louis Abbey]&lt;/ref&gt;

As of 2015, the English Congregation consists of three abbeys of nuns and ten abbeys of monks. Members of the congregation are found in England, Wales, the United States of America, Peru and Zimbabwe.&lt;ref name=English&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.benedictines.org.uk/our-tradition/history/|title=History - The English Benedictine Congregation|work=benedictines.org.uk|access-date=11 February 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150211095014/http://www.benedictines.org.uk/our-tradition/history/|archive-date=11 February 2015|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In England there are also houses of the [[Subiaco Cassinese Congregation#English Province|Subiaco Cassinese Congregation]]: Farnborough, Prinknash, and Chilworth: the [[Solesmes Congregation]], Quarr and St Cecilia's on the Isle of Wight,  as well as a diocesan monastery following the Rule of St Benedict: The [https://glastonburymonastery.co.uk Community of Our Lady of Glastonbury].

Since the [[Oxford Movement]], there has also been a modest flourishing of Benedictine monasticism in the [[Anglican Communion|Anglican Church]] and Protestant Churches. Anglican Benedictine Abbots are invited&lt;!---invited, right? Not just &quot;drop by.&quot; :)---&gt; guests of the Benedictine Abbot Primate in Rome at Abbatial gatherings at Sant'Anselmo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Daniel |last=Rees |chapter=Anglican Monasticism |title=Encyclopedia of Monasticism |editor-first=William |editor-last=Johnston |location=New York |publisher=Fitzroy Dearborn Publisher |year=2000 |page=29 |isbn=1-57958-090-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt; There are an estimated 2,400 celibate Anglican Religious (1,080 men and 1,320 women) in the Anglican Communion as a whole, some of whom have adopted the Rule of St. Benedict.

====Monastic Libraries in England====
The forty-eighth rule of Saint Benedict prescribes extensive and habitual &quot;holy reading&quot; for the brethren.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Kaur |first= Nirmal|date= 2005|title= History of Education |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=EaGGhbpebLYC&amp;pg=PA44|publisher= Mittal Publications|page= 44|isbn= 81-7099-984-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; Three primary types of reading were done by the monks during this time. Monks would read privately during their personal time, as well as publicly during services and at meal times. In addition to these three mentioned in the Rule, monks would also read in the infirmary.

However, Benedictine monks were disallowed worldly possessions, thus necessitating the preservation and collection of sacred texts in monastic libraries for communal use.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1= Wormald |last2=Wright|first1= Francis |first2=C.E.|date= 1958|title= The English Library before 1700|via= University of London|publisher= The Athlone Press|location=London|page= 15}}&lt;/ref&gt; For the sake of convenience, the books in the monastery were housed in a few different places, namely the [[sacristy]], which contained books for the choir and other liturgical books, the [[rectory]], which housed books for public reading such as sermons and lives of the saints, and the [[library]], which contained the largest collection of books and was typically in the cloister.

The first record of a monastic library in England is in [[Canterbury]]. To assist with [[Augustine of Canterbury]]'s [[Gregorian mission|English mission]], Pope [[Pope Gregory I|Gregory the Great]] gave him nine books which included the Gregorian Bible in two volumes, the Psalter of Augustine, two copies of the [[Gospels]], two [[martyrologies]], an Exposition of the Gospels and Epistles, and a [[Psalter]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Savage1912&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last= Savage|first= Ernest|date= 1912|title= Old English Libraries|url= https://archive.org/details/cu31924029526112|location= London|publisher= Methuen &amp; Co. Ltd.}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|23–25}} [[Theodore of Tarsus]] brought Greek books to Canterbury more than seventy years later, when he founded a school for the study of Greek.&lt;ref name=&quot;Savage1912&quot; /&gt;{{rp|26}}

===France===
Monasteries were among the institutions of the Catholic Church swept away during the [[French Revolution]]. Monasteries were again allowed to form in the 19th century under the [[Bourbon Restoration]]. Later that century, under the [[Third French Republic]], laws were enacted preventing religious teaching. The original intent was to allow secular schools. Thus in 1880 and 1882, Benedictine teaching monks were effectively exiled; this was not completed until 1901.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.st-benoit-du-lac.com/histoire1/history1.html|title=Historique I|publisher=st-benoit-du-lac.com|accessdate=29 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chadwick1998&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Chadwick|first=Owen |title=A History of the Popes, 1830-1914|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Wk1KzHS1IagC&amp;pg=PA495|year=1998|publisher=Clarendon Press|isbn=978-0-19-826922-9|pages=495–}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ryde.shalfleet.net/wootton_and_quarr.htm Wootton and Fishbourne]. Ryde.shalfleet.net (4 August 2013). Retrieved on 7 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.citeaux.net/assisi2005/delivrance-eng.htm RGM 2005 OCSO]. Citeaux.net (28 February 1947). Retrieved on 7 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Germany===
[[Saint Blaise Abbey, Black Forest|Saint Blaise Abbey]] in the Black Forest of Baden-Württemberg is believed to have been founded around the latter part of the tenth century. Other houses either reformed by, or founded as priories of, St Blasien were: Muri Abbey (1082), Ochsenhausen Abbey (1093), Göttweig Abbey (1094), Stein am Rhein Abbey (before 1123) and Prüm Abbey (1132). It also had significant influence on the abbeys of Alpirsbach (1099), Ettenheimmünster (1124) and Sulzburg (ca 1125), and the priories of Weitenau (ca 1100), Bürgeln (before 1130) and Sitzenkirch (ca 1130).

===Switzerland===
The abbey of [[Engelberg Abbey|Our Lady of the Angels]] was founded in 1120.

=== United States ===
The first Benedictine to live in the United States was Pierre-Joseph Didier. He came to the United States in 1790 from [[Paris]] and served in the Ohio and St. Louis areas until his death. The first actual Benedictine monastery founded was [[Saint Vincent Archabbey]], located in [[Latrobe, Pennsylvania|Latrobe]], Pennsylvania. It was founded in 1832 by [[Boniface Wimmer|Bonifice Wimmer]], a German monk, who sought to serve German immigrants in America. In 1856, Wimmer started to lay the foundations for [[Saint John's Abbey, Collegeville|St. John's Abbey]] in Minnesota. In 1876, Father Herman Wolfe, of Saint Vincent Archabbey established [[Belmont Abbey, North Carolina|Belmont Abbey]] in North Carolina.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://belmontabbey.org/learn-about-the-monastery/history-of-belmont-abbey/ |title=&quot;History of Belmont Abbey&quot;, Belmont Abbey, North Carolina |access-date=4 November 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180416152335/http://belmontabbey.org/learn-about-the-monastery/history-of-belmont-abbey/ |archive-date=16 April 2018 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; By the time of his death in 1887, Wimmer had sent Benedictine monks to Kansas, New Jersey, North Carolina, Georgia, Florida, Alabama, Illinois, and Colorado.&lt;ref name=&quot;RB 1980&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title = RB 1980: the rule of St. Benedict in Latin and English with notes|author=[[St Benedict]]|translator-last = Fry|translator-first = Timothy|publisher = The Liturgical Press|year = 1981|isbn = 0-8146-1211-3|location = Collegeville, Minnesota|pages = 136–141|ol=4255653M}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Wimmer also asked for Benedictine [[Nun#Distinction between a nun and a religious sister|sister]]s to be sent to America by St. Walburg Convent in [[Eichstätt]], Bavaria. In 1852, [[Sister Benedicta Riepp]] and two other sisters founded [[St. Marys, Pennsylvania]]. Soon they would send sisters to Michigan, New Jersey, and Minnesota.&lt;ref name=&quot;RB 1980&quot; /&gt;

By 1854, Swiss monks began to arrive and founded [[St. Meinrad Archabbey|St. Meinrad Abbey]] in Indiana, and they soon spread to Arkansas and Louisiana. They were soon followed by Swiss sisters.&lt;ref name=&quot;RB 1980&quot; /&gt;

There are now over 100 Benedictine houses across America. Most Benedictine houses are part of one of four large Congregations: American-Cassinese, Swiss-American, St. Scholastica, and St. Benedict. The congregations mostly are made up of monasteries that share the same lineage. For instance the American-Cassinese congregation included the 22 monasteries that descended from Boniface Wimmer.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = The Benedictine Congregations and Federations of North America in the Benedictine Confederation.|url = http://www.osb.org/intl/confed/nacong.html|website = www.osb.org|accessdate = 2015-11-24|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20170903031504/http://www.osb.org/intl/confed/nacong.html|archive-date = 3 September 2017|url-status = dead|df = dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Benedictine vow and life==
{{Main|Rule of Saint Benedict}}
[[File:BenedictineVespers.jpg|thumb|left|Benedictine [[monk]]s singing [[Vespers]] on [[Holy Saturday]] in [[Morristown, New Jersey]], U.S.]]
The sense of community was a defining characteristic of the order since the beginning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.durhamworldheritagesite.com/history/benedictine-order/history |title=The Defining Features of the Benedictine Order|website= Durham World Heritage Site}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Section 17 in chapter 58 of the [[Rule of Saint Benedict]] states the solemn promise candidates for reception into a Benedictine community are required to make: a promise of stability (i.e. to remain in the same community), ''conversatio morum'' (an idiomatic Latin phrase suggesting &quot;conversion of manners&quot;; see below) and obedience to the community's superior.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.saintjohnsabbey.org/monastic-life/order/ &quot;The Order of Saint Benedict&quot;, St. John's Abbey]&lt;/ref&gt; This solemn commitment tends to be referred to as the &quot;Benedictine vow&quot; and is the Benedictine antecedent and equivalent of the [[evangelical counsels]] professed by candidates for reception into a [[religious order]].

Much scholarship over the last fifty years has been dedicated to the translation and interpretation of &quot;''conversatio morum''&quot;.  The older translation &quot;conversion of life&quot; has generally been replaced with phrases such as &quot;[conversion to] a monastic manner of life&quot;, drawing from the Vulgate's use of ''conversatio'' as a translation of &quot;citizenship&quot; or &quot;homeland&quot; in Philippians 3:20.  Some scholars have claimed that the vow formula of the Rule is best translated as &quot;to live in this place as a monk, in obedience to its rule and abbot.&quot;

Benedictine [[abbot]]s and [[abbess]]es have full jurisdiction of their [[abbey]] and thus absolute authority over the [[Roman Catholic monk|monk]]s or [[nun]]s who are resident.  This authority includes the power to assign duties, to decide which books may or may not be read, to regulate comings and goings, and to punish and to [[excommunicate]], in the sense of an enforced isolation from the monastic community.

A tight communal timetable{{spaced ndash}}the [[horarium]]{{spaced ndash}}is meant to ensure that the time given by God is not wasted but used in God's service, whether for prayer, work, meals, spiritual reading or sleep.

Although Benedictines do not take a vow of silence, hours of strict silence are set, and at other times silence is maintained as much as is practically possible. Social conversations tend to be limited to communal recreation times. But such details, like the many other details of the daily routine of a Benedictine house that the Rule of St Benedict leaves to the discretion of the superior, are set out in its 'customary'. A ' customary' is the code adopted by a particular Benedictine house, adapting the Rule to local conditions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.mountmichael.org/Media/MountMichaelAbbey/Abbey/CUSTOMARY.pdf |title=Customary: Mount Michael Abbey|date=1 September 2013 |access-date=15 October 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160323023219/http://mountmichael.org/Media/MountMichaelAbbey/Abbey/CUSTOMARY.pdf |archive-date=23 March 2016 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Roman Catholic Church, according to the norms of the 1983 [[Code of Canon Law]], a Benedictine abbey is a &quot;[[religious institute]]&quot; and its members are therefore members of the [[consecrated life]]&lt;!--?: , commonly referred to as &quot;Religious&quot;--&gt;. While Canon Law 588 §1 explains that Benedictine monks are &quot;neither clerical nor lay&quot;, they can, however, be ordained.

Some monasteries adopt a more active ministry in living the monastic life, running schools or parishes; others are more focused on contemplation, with more of an emphasis on prayer and work within the confines of the cloister.

==Organization==
Benedictine monasticism is fundamentally different from other Western religious orders insofar as its individual communities are not part of a religious order with &quot;Generalates&quot; and &quot;Superiors General&quot;. Each Benedictine house is independent and governed by an Abbot.

In modern times, the various groups of autonomous houses (national, reform, etc.) have formed themselves loosely into congregations (for example, Cassinese, English, Solesmes, Subiaco, Camaldolese, Sylvestrines). These, in turn, are represented in the [[Benedictine Confederation]] that came into existence through [[Pope Leo XIII]]'s Apostolic Brief &quot;Summum semper&quot; on 12 July 1893.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Benedictine Confederation |url=http://www.osb.org/the-benedictine-order/the-benedictine-confederation/ |website=OSB.org |accessdate=24 October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; This organization facilitates dialogue of Benedictine communities with each other and the relationship between Benedictine communities and other [[religious order]]s and the church at large. The Abbot Primate resides at the Monastery of Sant’ Anselmo in Rome.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.benedictinemonks.co.uk/news/st-benedict-the-order/ The Benedictine Monks, UK]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1313 [[Bernardo Tolomei]] established the [[Olivetans|Order of Our Lady of Mount Olivet]]. The community adopted the Rule of St. Benedict and received canonical approval in 1344. The Olivetans are part of the Benedictine Confederation.

==Other orders==
The Rule of Saint Benedict is also used by a number of religious orders that began as reforms of the Benedictine tradition such as the [[Cistercian]]s and [[Trappist]]s. These groups are separate congregations and not members of the [[Benedictine Confederation]].

Although Benedictines are traditionally Catholic, there are also some communities that claim adherence to the Rule of Saint Benedict within the [[Anglican Communion]], [[Eastern Orthodox Church]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Simpson2016&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |title=Directory of Parishes |last=Simpson |first=Fr. Benedict |work=The Western Rite Communities of the Russian Orthodox Church Outside Russia |date=2016 |access-date=26 August 2019 |url= https://www.rocor-wr.org/parishes/ |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.saintlaurenceosb.org/monastery.html |title=Holy Monasteries of Our Lady and Saint Laurence Antiochian Orthodox Christian Archdiocese of North America, Western Rite Vicariate |website= The Benedictine Fellowship of Saint Laurence|access-date=10 March 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180404152547/http://www.saintlaurenceosb.org/monastery.html |archive-date=4 April 2018 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Lutheran Church]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SAH2018&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |title=Who we are… |author= |work=Saint Augustine's House |date=2018 |access-date=26 August 2019 |url= http://www.staugustineshouse.org/ |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable Benedictines==
[[File:Bonifatius-gregorius-aedelbertus-noordwijk.JPG|thumb|upright|[[Saint Boniface]] (c.&amp;nbsp;680–750), [[Pope Gregory I]] (c.&amp;nbsp;540–604, pope 590–604), [[Adalbert of Egmond]] (8th century) and priest Jeroen van Noordwijk, depicted in a 1529 painting by Jan Joostsz van Hillegom currently on display at the [[Frans Hals Museum]]]]
[[File:Ruperthead.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Late Gothic (art)|Late Gothic]] sculpture of [[Rupert of Salzburg]] (c.&amp;nbsp;660–710)]]
[[File:Bernhard von Clairvaux (Initiale-B).jpg|thumb|upright|[[Bernard of Clairvaux]] (1090–1153) featured in a 13th-century illuminated manuscript]]
[[File:Raban-Maur Alcuin Otgar.jpg|thumb|upright|A [[Carolingian art|Carolingian manuscript]], c.&amp;nbsp;840, depicting [[Rabanus Maurus]] (left), supported by [[Alcuin]] (middle), presenting his work to [[Odgar|Otgar of Mainz]]]]
[[File:BritLibRoyal14CVIIFol006rMattParisSelfPort.jpg|thumb|upright|Self portrait of [[Matthew Paris]] (c.1200–59)]]
[[File:Abbot Suger.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Abbot Suger]] (c.1081–1135) in a medieval stained-glass window]]
[[File:Dom Pérignon découvrant la prise de mousse.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Dom Pérignon (monk)|Dom Pérignon]]]]

===Saints and Blesseds===
{{columns list|colwidth=30em|
*[[Pope Gregory I]] (c. 540–604, r. 590–604)
*[[Augustine of Canterbury]] (d. 604)
*[[Saint Boniface]] (c. 680–755)
*[[Willibrord]] (c. 658–739)
*[[Rupert of Salzburg]] (c. 660–710)
*[[Suitbert of Kaiserwerdt]] (d. 713)
*[[Saint Sturm]] (c. 705–79)
*[[Ansgar]] (801–65)
*[[Wolfgang of Regensburg]] (934–994)
*[[Adalbert of Prague]] (c. 956–97)
*[[Gerard of Csanád]] (c. 980–1046)&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic&quot;/&gt;
*[[Pope Gregory VII]] (c. 1020–85, r. 1073–85)
*[[Pope Victor III]] (c. 1026–87, r. 1086–87)
*[[Pope Celestine V]] (1215–96, r. 1294)
*[[Pope Urban V]] (1310–70, r. 1362–70)
*[[Pope Pius VII]] (1742–1823, r. 1800–23); Servant of God
}}

===Monks===

====Popes====
{{columns list|colwidth=30em|
*[[Pope Sylvester II]] (c. 946–1003, r. 999–1003)
*[[Pope Paschal II]] (d. 1118, r. 1099–1118)
*[[Pope Gelasius II]] (d. 1119, r. 1118–19)
*[[Pope Clement VI]] (1291–1352, r. 1342–52)
*[[Pope Gregory XVI]] (1765–1846, r. 1831–46)&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic&quot;/&gt;
}}

====Founders of abbeys and congregations and prominent reformers====
{{columns list|colwidth=30em|
*[[Earconwald]] (c. 630–93)
*[[Benedict Biscop]] (c. 628–90)
*[[Leudwinus]] (c. 665–713)
*[[Benedict of Aniane]] (747–821)
*[[Dunstan]] (909–88)
*[[Berno of Cluny]] (c. 850–927)
*[[Odo of Cluny]] (c. 878–942)
*[[Majolus of Cluny]] (c. 906–94)
*[[Odilo of Cluny]] (c. 962–c. 1048)
*[[Walter of Pontoise]] (c. 1030–c. 1099)
*[[Bernard of Cluny]] (d. 1109)
*[[Peter the Venerable]] (c. 1092–1156)
*[[Romuald]] (c. 956–c. 1026)
*[[Robert of Molesme]] (c. 1028–1111)
*[[Alberic of Cîteaux]] (d. 1109)
*[[Stephen Harding]] (d. 1134)
*[[Bernard of Clairvaux]] (1090–1153)
*[[William of Hirsau]] (c. 1030–91)
*[[John Gualbert]] (995–1073)
*[[Stephen of Obazine]] (1084–1154)
*[[Robert of Arbrissel]] (c. 1045–1116)
*[[William of Montevergine]] (1085–1142)
*[[Nicholas Justiniani]] (fl.1153-1179)
*[[Sylvester Gozzolini]] (1177–1267)
*[[Bernardo Tolomei]] (1272–1348)
*[[Laurent Bénard]] (1573–1620)
*[[Prosper Guéranger]] (1805–1875)
*[[Jean-Baptiste Muard]] (1809–1854)
*[[Boniface Wimmer]] (1809–1887)
*[[Maurus Wolter]] (1825–1890)
*[[Martin Marty (bishop)|Martin Marty]] (1834–1896)&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic&quot;/&gt;
*[[Andreas Amrhein]] (1844–1927)
*[[Lambert Beauduin]] (1873–1960)
*[[Margit Slachta]]  (or ''Schlachta'', 1884–1974)
}}

====Scholars, historians, and spiritual writers====
{{columns list|colwidth=30em|
*[[Jonas of Bobbio]] (600-659)
*[[Bede]] (673–735)
*[[Aldhelm]] (c. 639–709)
*[[Alcuin]] (d. 804)
*[[Rabanus Maurus]] (c. 780–856)
*[[Paschasius Radbertus]] (785–865)
*[[Ratramnus]] (d. 866)
*[[Walafrid Strabo]] (c. 808–49)
*[[Notker Labeo]] (c. 950–1022)
*[[Guido of Arezzo]] (991–1050)
*[[Hermann of Reichenau]] (1013–54)
*[[Paul the Deacon]] (c. 720–99)
*[[Hincmar]] (806–82)
*[[Saint Maurus of Pécs]] (c. 1000–c. 1075)
*[[Peter Damian]] (c. 1007–72)
*[[Lanfranc]] (c 1005–89)
*[[Anselm of Canterbury]] (c 1033–1109)
*[[Eadmer]] (c 1060–c1126)
*[[Florence of Worcester]] (d. 1118)
*[[Symeon of Durham]] (d. 1130)
*[[Jocelyn de Brakelond]] (d. 1211)
*[[Matthew Paris]] (c. 1200–59)
*[[William of Malmesbury]] (c. 1095–c. 1143)
*[[Gervase of Canterbury]] (c. 1141–c. 1210)
*[[Roger of Wendover]] (d. 1236)
*[[Peter the Deacon]] (d. 1140)
*[[Adam Easton]] (d. 1397)
*[[Honoré Bonet]] (c. 1340–c1410)
*[[John Lydgate]] (c. 1370–c. 1451)
*[[John Whethamstede]] (d. 1465)
*[[Johannes Trithemius]] (1462–1516)
*[[Louis de Blois]] (1506–66)
*[[Benedict van Haeften]] (1588–1648)
*[[Augustine Baker]] (1575–1641)
*[[Jean Mabillon]] (1632-1707)
*[[Mariano Armellino]] (1657–1737)
*[[Antoine Augustin Calmet]] (1672–1757)
*[[Magnoald Ziegelbauer]] (1689–1750)
*[[Marquard Herrgott]] (1694–1762)
*[[Luigi Tosti]] (1811–97)
*[[Jean Baptiste François Pitra]] (1812–89)
*[[Oswald William Moosmuller]] (1842-1901)
*[[Suitbert Bäumer]] (1845–94)
*[[Francis Aidan Gasquet]] (1846–1929)
*[[Fernand Cabrol]] (1855–1937)
*[[Germain Morin]] (1861–1946)
*[[John Chapman (priest)|John Chapman]] (1865–1933)
*[[Edward Cuthbert Butler|Cuthbert Butler]] (1858–1934)&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic&quot;/&gt;
}}

====Maurists====
{{columns list|colwidth=30em|
*[[Nicolas-Hugues Ménard]] (1585–1644)
*[[Luc d'Achery]] (1609–85)
*[[Antoine-Joseph Mège]] (1625–91)
*[[Thierry Ruinart]] (1657–1709)
*[[François Lamy (theologian)|François Lamy]] (1636–1711)
*[[Pierre Coustant]] (1654–1721)
*[[Edmond Martène]] (1654–1739)
*[[Ursin Durand]] (1682–1771)
*[[Bernard de Montfaucon]] (1655–1741)
*[[René-Prosper Tassin]] (1697–1777)&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic&quot;/&gt;
}}

====Bishops and martyrs====
{{columns list|colwidth=30em|
*[[Saint Ernest]] (d. 1148)
*[[Laurence of Canterbury]] (d. 619)
*[[Mellitus]] (d. 624)
*[[Justus]] (d. 627)
*[[Paulinus of York]] (d. 644)
*[[Leudwinus]] (c. 665–713)
*[[Oda of Canterbury]] (d. 958)
*[[Bertin]] (c. 615–c. 709)
*[[Wilfrid]] (c. 633–c. 709)
*[[Cuthbert]] (c. 634–87)
*[[John of Beverley]] (d. 721)
*[[Swithun]] (d. 862)
*[[Æthelwold of Winchester]] (d. 984)
*[[Edmund Rich]] (1175–1240)
*[[Abbot Suger]] (c. 1081–1151)
*[[Thomas Marshall (abbot)|John Beche]] (d. 1539)
*[[Richard Whiting (abbot)|Richard Whiting]] (d. 1539)
*[[Hugh Cook Faringdon]] (d. 1539)
*[[Sigebert Buckley]] (c. 1520–c. 1610)
*[[John Roberts (martyr)|John Roberts]] (1577-1610)
*[[Gabriel Gifford]] (1554–1629)
*[[Alban Roe]] (1583-1642)
*[[Philip Michael Ellis]] (1652–1726)
*[[Charles Walmesley]] (1722–97)
*[[William Placid Morris]] (1794–1872)
*[[John Polding]] (1794–1877)
*[[William Bernard Ullathorne]] (1806–89)
*[[Roger Vaughan]] (1834–83)
*[[Guglielmo Sanfelice d'Acquavilla]] (1834–1897)&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic&quot;/&gt;
*[[Joseph Pothier]] (1835–1923)
*[[John Cuthbert Hedley]] (1837–1915)
*[[Domenico Serafini]] (1852–1918)
*[[Placidus Nkalanga]] (1918 - 2015)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hanganews.blogspot.com/2011/06/bishop-gervas-placidus-nkalanga-osb-of.html|title=Hanga News|author=Hangablog|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

====Twentieth century====
[[File:Schustercardinal.jpg|thumb|Cardinal Schuster.]]
{{columns list|colwidth=30em|
*[[Lambert Beauduin]] (1873–1960)
*Bl. [[Alfredo Schuster]] (1880–1954)
*[[Bede Griffiths]] (1906–1993)
*[[Paul Augustin Mayer]] (1911–2010)
*[[Hans Hermann Groër]] (1919–2003)
*[[Basil Hume]] (1923–1999)
*[[Rembert Weakland]] (1927–)
*[[Daniel M. Buechlein]] (1938-2018)
*[[Jerome Hanus]] (1940-)
*[[Anselm Grün]] (1945–)
*[[Knut Ansgar Nelson]] (1906-1990)
}}

===Nuns===
[[File:046 Ajuntament de Terrassa, galeria de terrassencs il·lustres, Antoni M. Marcet.JPG|thumb|Abbot of [[Santa Maria de Montserrat Abbey|Montserrat]]]]
{{columns list|colwidth=30em|
*[[Scholastica]] (c. 480–547)
*[[Æthelthryth]] (c. 636–79)
*[[Hilda of Whitby]] (c. 614–80)
*[[Werburh]] (d. 699)
*[[Mildrith]] (d. early 7th century)
*[[Saint Walpurga]] (c. 710–79)
*[[Wulfthryth of Wilton]] (c. 937–1000)
*[[Saint Edith of Wilton]] (c. 961–984)
*[[Hildegard of Bingen]] (1098–1179)
*[[Gertrude the Great]] (1256–c. 1302)&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic&quot;/&gt;
*[[Joan Chittister]] (1936-)
*[[Noella Marcellino]] (1951-)
*[[Teresa Forcades]] (1966–)
}}

===Oblates===
[[File:BonifatiusBecker.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Bonifatius Becker]]]]
Benedictine [[Oblate (religion)|Oblate]]s endeavor to embrace the spirit of the Benedictine vow in their own life in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;CCC928&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |title=928: Secular institutes |author= |work=Catechism of the Catholic Church - Part 1 Section 2 Chapter 3 Article 9 Paragraph 4 |date= |access-date=26 August 2019 |url= http://www.scborromeo.org/ccc/p123a9p4.htm#III |language= |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Oblates are affiliated with a particular monastery.
{{columns list|colwidth=30em| 
*[[Henry II, Holy Roman Emperor|Emperor Henry II]] (972–1024)
*[[Frances of Rome]] (1384–1440)
*[[Joris-Karl Huysmans]] (1848–1907)&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic&quot;/&gt;
*[[Jacques Maritain]] (1882–1973)
*[[Romano Guardini]] (1885–1968)
*[[Dorothy Day]] (1897–1980)
*[[Walker Percy]] (1916–1990)
*[[Kathleen Norris (poet)|Kathleen Norris]] (1947– )
}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Catholicism}}
* [[Dom Pérignon (monk)|Dom Pierre Pérignon]]
* [[Benedictine Confederation]]
* [[Catholic religious order]]
* [[Cistercians]]
* [[French Romanesque architecture]]
* [[Sisters of Social Service]]
* [[Trappists]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin}}
* Dom [[Columba Marmion]], ''Christ the Ideal of the Monk – Spiritual Conferences on the Monastic and Religious Life'' (Engl. edition London 1926, trsl. from the French by a nun of Tyburn Convent).
* Mariano Dell'Omo, ''Storia del monachesimo occidentale dal medioevo all'età contemporanea. Il carisma di san Benedetto tra VI e XX secolo''. Jaca Book, Milano 2011. {{ISBN|978-88-16-30493-2}}
*{{cite EB1911 |wstitle=Abbey/Benedictine |display=Abbey: Benedictine |volume=1 |pages=12–14 |short=x}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Order of Saint Benedict}}

* [http://www.osb.org Official Website]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080704171611/http://osb-international.info/  ''Confoederatio Benedictina Ordinis Sancti Benedicti'', the Benedictine Confederation of Congregations]
* [http://www.osb.org/intl/confed/confed.html Links of the Congregations]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20160629022213/http://www.saintvincentarchabbey.org/about_us Saint Vincent Archabbey]
* [http://www.bonifacewimmer.org/About Boniface WIMMER]
* http://www.aimintl.org/index.php/en/
* [http://www.odis.be/lnk/OR_11713 Benedictines - Abbey of Dendermonde] in [https://www.odis.eu ODIS - Online Database for Intermediary Structures]
* [http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.rbc/MedievalRen.59133 Benedictine rule for nuns in Middle English, Manuscript, ca. 1320, at The Library of Congress]

{{Catholicism}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Order of Saint Benedict| ]]
[[Category:Catholic spirituality]]
[[Category:Institutes of consecrated life]]</text>
      <sha1>szqg2o0opm6lxr6k4fj20krkpnub0o0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
