  <page>
    <title>Burgundians</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4257</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941648204</id>
      <parentid>941342445</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-19T21:24:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Krakkos</username>
        <id>17328627</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Historical East Germanic ethnic group}}
[[File:Roman Empire 125.png|thumb|right|320px|The Roman empire under [[Hadrian]] (ruled 117–138 AD), showing the location of the Burgundiones Germanic group, inhabiting the region between the Viadua ([[Oder]]) and Visula ([[Vistula]]) rivers (Poland)]]

The '''Burgundians''' ({{lang-la|Burgundiōnes, Burgundī}}; {{lang-on|Burgundar}}; {{lang-ang|Burgendas}}&lt;!-- also Burgendan and Burgende --&gt;; {{lang-grc-gre|Βούργουνδοι}}&lt;!-- also Βουρούγουνδοι and Οὐρουγοῦνδοι --&gt;) were an early [[Germanic peoples|Germanic]] people tribe or group of tribes. They appeared in the Rhine region, near the Roman empire, and were later moved into the empire, in the western [[Alps]] and southeastern [[Gaul]]. They were perhaps mentioned much earlier in the time of the  [[Roman Empire]] as living in the part the region of [[Germania]] that is now part of [[Poland]].

In the [[History of the Roman Empire#284–301: Diocletian and the Tetrarchy|late Roman period]], as the empire came under pressure from many such &quot;barbarian&quot; peoples, a powerful group of Burgundians and other Vandalic tribes moved westwards towards the Roman frontiers along the [[Rhine|Rhine Valley]], making them neighbors of the [[Franks]] who formed their kingdoms to the north, and the [[Suebi]]c [[Alemanni]] who were settling to their south, also near the Rhine. They established themselves in [[Worms, Germany|Worms]], but with Roman cooperation their descendants eventually established the [[Kingdom of the Burgundians]] much further south, and within the empire, in the [[western Alps]] region where modern Switzerland, France and Italy meet. This later became a component of the [[Frankish empire]]. The name of this kingdom survives in the regional appellation, [[Burgundy]], which is a region in modern France, representing only a part of that kingdom.

Another part of the Burgundians stayed in their previous homeland in the [[Oder]]-[[Vistula]] basin and formed a contingent in [[Attila]]'s [[Hunnic Empire|Hunnic]] army by 451.&lt;ref name=Appolinarius&gt;Sidonnius Appolinarius, ''Carmina'', 7, 322&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Luebe&gt;Luebe, ''Die Burgunder'', in Krüger II, p. 373 n. 21, in [[Herbert Schutz]], ''Tools, weapons and ornaments: Germanic material culture in Pre-Carolingian Central Europe, 400-750'', BRILL, 2001, p.36&lt;/ref&gt;

Before clear documentary evidence begins, the Burgundians may have originally emigrated from mainland [[Scandinavia]] to the Baltic island of [[Bornholm]], and from there to the [[Vistula]] basin, in the middle of what is now Poland.&lt;ref name=&quot;EBBurgundy&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://global.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/85188/Burgundy/253115/History |title=Burgundy: History |last1= |first1= |last2= |first2= |date= |website=[[Encyclopædia Britannica Online]] |publisher=[[Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.]] |accessdate=January 17, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Name==
The [[ethnonym]] Burgundians is commonly used in English to refer to the ''Burgundi'' (''Burgundionei'', ''Burgundiones'' or ''Burgunds'') who settled in [[Sapaudia]] (Savoy), in the western Alps, during the 5th century. The original [[Kingdom of the Burgundians]] barely intersected the modern ''Bourgogne'' and more closely matched the boundaries of the [[Arpitan]] or [[Romand]] ([[Franco-Provençal language|Franco-Provençal]]) language area,&lt;ref&gt;Andres Kristol, &quot;Francoprovencal&quot;, in ''The Oxford Guide to the Romance Languages'', Oxford, Oxford University Press, pp. 351–2.&lt;/ref&gt; centred on the ''[[Rhône-Alpes|Rôno-Arpes]]'' (Rhône-Alpes) region of France, [[Romandy]] in west Switzerland and ''[[Aosta Valley|Val d'Outa]]'' (Val d'Aosta), in north west Italy.

In modern usage, however, &quot;Burgundians&quot; can sometimes refer to later inhabitants of the geographical ''[[Bourgogne]]'' or ''Borgogne'' (Burgundy), named after the old kingdom, but not corresponding to the original boundaries of it. Between the 6th and 20th centuries, the boundaries and political connections of &quot;Burgundy&quot; have changed frequently. In modern times the only area still referred to as [[Burgundy (region)|Burgundy]] is in France, which derives its name from the [[Duchy of Burgundy]]. But in the context of the Middle Ages the term Burgundian (or similar spellings) can refer even to the powerful political entity the Dukes controlled which included not only Burgundy itself but had actually expanded to have a strong association with areas now in modern [[Belgium]] and Southern [[Netherlands]]. The parts of the old Kingdom not within the French controlled Duchy tended to come under different names, except for the [[County of Burgundy]].

==Classification==
The Burgundians are classified as a [[Germanic peoples|Germanic]] people.{{Efn|name=Drinkwater|&quot;Burgundians (Burgundiones), a Germanic people who first appear on the Main soon after ad 250.&quot;{{sfn|Drinkwater|2012}} }}{{Efn|name=Darvill|&quot;Burgundians. Germanic people of the middle Rhine who were settled in the early decades of the 5th century ad near Geneva, where they established a kingdom in the Rhône Valley.&quot;{{sfn|Darvill|2009}} }}{{Efn|name=Hitchner|&quot;Burgundians... a Germanic tribe that crossed the Rhine in 406 and settled in the middle Rhineland.&quot;{{sfn|Hitchner|2005}} }}{{Efn|name=Buchberger|&quot;Burgundians... A *Germanic people...&quot;{{sfn|Buchberger|2018}} }} Unlike other [[East Germanic languages|East Germanic]]-speaking Germanic peoples, such as the [[Goths]] and [[Vandals]], the Burgundians were considered among the ''Germani'' by the [[ancient Rome|Romans]]. This was because they entered [[Gaul]] through [[Germania]] itself.{{Efn|name=Wolfram|&quot;Goths, Vandals, and other East Germanic tribes were differentiated from the Germans and were referred to as Scythians, Goths, or some other special names. The sole exception are the Burgundians, who were considered German because they came to Gaul via Germania. In keeping with this classification, post-Tacitean Scandinavians were also no longer counted among the Germans....&quot;{{sfn|Wolfram|1997|p=5}} }}

==History==
===Uncertain early history===
[[File:DenmarkBornholm2.png|thumb|right|220px|Location of the island of [[Bornholm]]]]

The origins of the Burgundians before they reached the area near the Roman-controlled Rhine is a subject of various old proposals, but these are doubted by modern scholars such as Ian Wood and Walter Goffart. As remarked by Susan Reynolds:&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds, &quot;Our Forefathers&quot; in Goofart (ed.) After Rome's Fall, p.35, citing Wood &quot;Ethnicity and Ethnogenesis of the Burgundians&quot; in Wolfram (ed.) Typen de Ethnogenese.&lt;/ref&gt;
:Wood suggests that those who were called Burgundians in their early sixth-century laws were not a single ethnic group, but covered any non-Roman followed of Gundobad and Sigismund. Some of the leaders of Goths and Burgundians may have descended from long-distant ancestors somewhere round the Baltic. Maybe, but everyone has a lot of ancestors, and some of theirs may well have come from elsewhere. There is, as Walter Goffart has repeatedly argued, little reason to believe that sixth-century or later references to what look like names for Scandinavia, or for places in it, mean that traditions from those particular ancestors had been handed through thick and thin.

They have long been associated with [[Scandinavia]]n origin based on place-name evidence and archaeological evidence (Stjerna) and many consider their tradition to be correct (e.g. Musset, p.&amp;nbsp;62). According to such proposals, the Burgundians are believed to have then emigrated to the Baltic island of [[Bornholm]] (&quot;the island of the Burgundians&quot; in [[Old Norse]]). However, by about 250 AD, the population of Bornholm had largely disappeared from the island. Most cemeteries ceased to be used, and those that were still used had few burials (Stjerna, in Nerman 1925:176). In ''[[Þorsteins saga Víkingssonar]]'' (''The Saga of Thorstein, Viking's Son''), a man (or group) named [[Veseti]] settled on a [[holm (island)|holm]] (island) called ''borgundarhólmr'' in Old Norse, i.e. Bornholm. [[Alfred the Great]]'s translation of ''[[Paulus Orosius|Orosius]]'' uses the name ''Burgenda land'' to refer to a territory next to the land of [[Suiones|Sweons]] (&quot;Swedes&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.gutenberg.org/etext/4076 http://www.gutenberg.org]&lt;/ref&gt; The poet and early mythologist [[Viktor Rydberg]] (1828–1895), (''Our Fathers' Godsaga'') asserted from an early medieval source, ''[[Sigismund of Burgundy|Vita Sigismundi]]'', that they themselves retained oral traditions about their Scandinavian origin.

Early Roman sources, such as [[Tacitus]] and [[Pliny the Elder]], knew little concerning the Germanic peoples east of the Elbe river, or on the Baltic Sea. Pliny (IV.28) however mentions a group with a similar names among the [[Vandals|Vandalic]] or [[Eastern Germanic]] Germani peoples, including also the [[Goths]]. [[Claudius Ptolemy]] lists these also, as living between the Suevus (probably the [[Oder river|Oder]]) and Vistula rivers, north of the [[Lugii]], and south of the coast dwelling tribes. Around the mid 2nd century AD, there was a significant migration by Germanic tribes of Scandinavian origin ([[Rugii]], Goths, [[Gepids|Gepidae]], Vandals, Burgundians, and others)&lt;ref name=&quot;TheGermansAndTheHuns&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://global.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/195896/history-of-Europe/58257/Barbarian-migrations-and-invasions |title=History of Europe: The Germans and Huns |last1= |first1= |last2= |first2= |date= |website=[[Encyclopædia Britannica Online]] |publisher=[[Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.]] |accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; towards the south-east, creating turmoil along the entire Roman frontier.&lt;ref name=&quot;TheGermansAndTheHuns&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TheBarbarianInvasions&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://global.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/507905/ancient-Rome/26693/The-barbarian-invasions |title=Ancient Rome: The barbarian invasions |last1= |first1= |last2= |first2= |date= |website=[[Encyclopædia Britannica Online]] |publisher=[[Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.]] |accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GermanicPeoples&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://global.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/231063/Germanic-peoples |title=Germanic peoples |last1= |first1= |last2= |first2= |date= |website=[[Encyclopædia Britannica Online]] |publisher=[[Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.]] |accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;EBGermanyAncientHistory&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://global.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/231186/Germany/58075/The-press |title=Germany: Ancient History |last1= |first1= |last2= |first2= |date= |website=[[Encyclopædia Britannica Online]] |publisher=[[Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.]] |accessdate=January 16, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; These migrations culminated in the [[Marcomannic Wars]], which resulted in widespread destruction and the first invasion of [[Italy]] in the Roman Empire period.&lt;ref name=&quot;EBGermanyAncientHistory&quot;/&gt; [[Jordanes]] reports that during the 3rd century, the Burgundians living in the Vistula basin were almost annihilated by [[Fastida]], king of the Gepids, whose kingdom was at the mouth of the Vistula.

In the late 3rd century, the Burgundians appeared on the east bank of the Rhine, confronting Roman Gaul. [[Zosimus]] (1.68) reports them being defeated by the emperor [[Marcus Aurelius Probus|Probus]] in 278 in Gaul. At this time, they were led by a Vandal king. A few years later, [[Claudius Mamertinus]] mentions them along with the [[Alamanni]], a [[Suebi]]c people. These two peoples had moved into the [[Agri Decumates]] on the eastern side of the Rhine, an area today referred to still as [[Swabia]], at times attacking Roman Gaul together and sometimes fighting each other. He also mentions that the Goths had previously defeated the Burgundians.

[[Ammianus Marcellinus]], on the other hand, claimed that the Burgundians were descended from Romans. The Roman sources do not speak of any specific migration from Poland by the Burgundians (although other Vandalic peoples are more clearly mentioned as having moved west in this period), and so there have historically been some doubts about the link between the eastern and western Burgundians.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus:text:1999.04.0064:entry=burgundiones-geo&amp;highlight=burgundiones |title=Dictionary of Greek and Roman Geography |year=1854| first=William |last=Smith}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 369/370, the Emperor [[Valentinian I]] enlisted the aid of the Burgundians in his war against the Alemanni.

Approximately four decades later, the Burgundians appear again. Following [[Stilicho]]'s withdrawal of troops to fight [[Alaric I]] the [[Visigoths|Visigoth]] in AD 406-408, a large group of peoples from central Europe north of the Danube, came west and crossed the Rhine, entering the Empire, near the lands of the Burgundians who had moved much earlier. The dominant groups were [[Alans]], [[Vandals]] ([[Hasdingi]] and [[Silingi]]), and Danubian [[Suevi]] (probably descended from [[Marcomanni]] and [[Quadi]]). The majority of these Danubian peoples moved through Gaul and eventually established themselves in kingdoms in Roman Hispania. One group of Alans was settled in northern Gaul by the Romans.

Some Burgundians also migrated westwards and settled as ''[[foederati]]'' in the Roman province of [[Germania Prima]] along the [[Middle Rhine]]. Other Burgundians however remained outside the empire and apparently formed a contingent in [[Attila]]'s [[Hunnic Empire|Hunnic]] army by 451.&lt;ref name=Appolinarius /&gt;&lt;ref name=Luebe /&gt;

===Kingdom===
{{Main|Kingdom of the Burgundians}}

====Establishment====
In 411, the Burgundian king [[Gunther|Gundahar]] (or ''Gundicar'') set up a puppet emperor, [[Jovinus]], in cooperation with [[Goar]], king of the [[Alans]]. With the authority of the [[Gallo-Roman culture|Gallic emperor]] that he controlled, Gundahar settled on the left (Roman) bank of the Rhine, between the river [[Lauter (Rhine)|Lauter]] and the [[Nahe (Rhine)|Nahe]], seizing [[Worms, Germany|Worms]], [[Speyer]], and [[Strassburg]]. Apparently as part of a truce, the Emperor [[Honorius (emperor)|Honorius]] later officially &quot;granted&quot; them the land,&lt;ref&gt;Prosper, a. 386&lt;/ref&gt; with its capital at the old Celtic Roman settlement of Borbetomagus (present [[Worms, Germany|Worms]]).

Despite their new status as ''foederati'', Burgundian raids into Roman Upper [[Gallia Belgica]] became intolerable and were ruthlessly brought to an end in 436, when the Roman general [[Flavius Aëtius|Aëtius]] called in [[Hun]] mercenaries, who overwhelmed the Rhineland kingdom in 437. Gundahar was killed in the fighting, reportedly along with the majority of the Burgundian tribe.&lt;ref&gt;Prosper; ''Chronica Gallica 452''; Hydatius; and Sidonius Apollinaris&lt;/ref&gt;

The destruction of Worms and the Burgundian kingdom by the Huns became the subject of heroic legends that were afterwards incorporated in the ''[[Nibelungenlied]]''—on which [[Richard Wagner|Wagner]] based his [[Ring Cycle]]—where King Gunther (Gundahar) and Queen [[Brünnehilde|Brünhild]] hold their court at Worms, and [[Sigurd|Siegfried]] comes to woo Kriemhild. (In Old Norse sources the names are ''Gunnar'', ''Brynhild'', and ''Gudrún'' as normally rendered in English.) In fact, the ''Etzel'' of the ''Nibelungenlied'' is based on [[Attila the Hun]].

===Settlement in Savoy===
[[File:Map Burgundian Kingdom EN.png|thumb|right|230px|The Second Burgundian Kingdom between 443 and 476]]

For reasons not cited in the sources, the Burgundians were granted ''foederati'' status a second time, and in 443 were resettled by [[Flavius Aëtius|Aëtius]] in the region of ''Sapaudia''.&lt;ref&gt;''Chronica Gallica 452''&lt;/ref&gt; Though the precise geography is uncertain, ''Sapaudia'' corresponds to the modern-day [[Savoy]], and the Burgundians probably lived near ''Lugdunum'', known today as [[Lyon]].&lt;ref&gt;Wood 1994, Gregory II, 9&lt;/ref&gt; A new king, [[Gundioc]] or ''Gunderic'', presumed to be Gundahar's son, appears to have reigned following his father's death.&lt;ref name=&quot;Drew, p. 1&quot;&gt;Drew, p.&amp;nbsp;1&lt;/ref&gt; The historian Pline{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}} tells us that Gonderic ruled the areas of Saône, Dauphiny, Savoie and a part of Provence. He set up [[Vienne, Isère|Vienne]] as the capital of the kingdom of Burgundy. In all, eight Burgundian kings of the house of Gundahar ruled until the kingdom was overrun by the Franks in 534.

As allies of Rome in its last decades, the Burgundians fought alongside Aëtius and a confederation of Visigoths and others in the battle against [[Attila the Hun|Attila]] at the [[Battle of Châlons]] (also called &quot;The Battle of the Catalaunian Fields&quot;) in 451. The alliance between Burgundians and Visigoths seems to have been strong, as Gundioc and his brother Chilperic I accompanied [[Theodoric II]] to Spain to fight the Sueves in 455.&lt;ref&gt;Jordanes, ''Getica'', 231&lt;/ref&gt;

====Aspirations to the empire====
Also in 455, an ambiguous reference ''infidoque tibi Burdundio ductu''&lt;ref&gt;[[Sidonius Apollinaris]] in ''Panegyr. Avit''. 442.&lt;/ref&gt; implicates an unnamed treacherous Burgundian leader in the murder of the emperor [[Petronius Maximus]] in the chaos preceding the sack of Rome by the [[Vandals]]. The Patrician [[Ricimer]] is also blamed; this event marks the first indication of the link between the Burgundians and Ricimer, who was probably Gundioc's brother-in-law and [[Gundobad]]'s uncle.&lt;ref&gt;John Malalas, 374&lt;/ref&gt;

In 456, the Burgundians, apparently confident in their growing power, negotiated a territorial expansion and power sharing arrangement with the local Roman senators.&lt;ref&gt;Marius of Avenches&lt;/ref&gt;

In 457, Ricimer overthrew another emperor, [[Avitus]], raising [[Majorian]] to the throne. This new emperor proved unhelpful to Ricimer and the Burgundians. The year after his ascension, Majorian stripped the Burgundians of the lands they had acquired two years earlier. After showing further signs of independence, he was murdered by Ricimer in 461.

Ten years later, in 472, Ricimer–who was by now the son-in-law of the Western Emperor [[Anthemius]]–was plotting with Gundobad to kill his father-in-law; Gundobad beheaded the emperor (apparently personally).&lt;ref&gt;''Chronica Gallica 511''; John of Antioch, fr. 209; Jordanes, ''Getica'', 239&lt;/ref&gt; Ricimer then appointed [[Olybrius]]; both died, surprisingly of natural causes, within a few months. Gundobad seems then to have succeeded his uncle as Patrician and king-maker, and raised [[Glycerius]] to the throne.&lt;ref&gt;Marius of Avenches; John of Antioch, fr. 209&lt;/ref&gt;

In 474, Burgundian influence over the empire seems to have ended. Glycerius was deposed in favor of [[Julius Nepos]], and Gundobad returned to Burgundy, presumably at the death of his father Gundioc. At this time or shortly afterwards, the Burgundian kingdom was divided among Gundobad and his brothers, Godigisel, Chilperic II, and Gundomar I.&lt;ref&gt;Gregory, II, 28&lt;/ref&gt;

====Consolidation of the kingdom====
[[File:Conquests of Clovis.png|thumbnail|Kingdom of the Burgundians in around 500]]

According to [[Gregory of Tours]], the years following Gundobad's return to Burgundy saw a bloody consolidation of power. Gregory states that Gundobad murdered his brother Chilperic, drowning his wife and exiling their daughters (one of whom was to become the wife of [[Clovis I|Clovis]] the [[Franks|Frank]], and was reputedly responsible for his conversion).&lt;ref&gt;Gregory, II, 28. Gregory's chronology of the events surrounding Clovis and Gundobad has been questioned by Bury, Shanzer, and Wood, among others. Gregory was somewhat of a Frankish apologist, and commonly discredited the enemies of Clovis by attributing to them some fairly shocking acts. As with Godegisel, he also commonly refers to the treachery of Clovis' allies, when in fact Clovis seems to have bought them off (e.g., in the case of the Ripuarians).&lt;/ref&gt; This is contested by, e.g., Bury, who points out problems in much of Gregory's chronology for the events.

In c. 500, when Gundobad and Clovis were at war, Gundobad appears to have been betrayed by his brother Godegisel, who joined the Franks; together Godegisel's and Clovis' forces &quot;crushed the army of Gundobad&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Marius a. 500; Gregory, II, 32&lt;/ref&gt; Gundobad was temporarily holed up in Avignon, but was able to re-muster his army and sacked Vienne, where Godegisel and many of his followers were put to death. From this point, Gundobad appears to have been the sole king of Burgundy.&lt;ref&gt;e.g., Gregory, II, 33&lt;/ref&gt; This would imply that his brother Gundomar was already dead, though there are no specific mentions of the event in the sources.

Either Gundobad and Clovis reconciled their differences, or Gundobad was forced into some sort of vassalage by Clovis' earlier victory, as the Burgundian king appears to have assisted the Franks in 507 in their victory over [[Alaric II]] the Visigoth.

During the upheaval, sometime between 483–501, Gundobad began to set forth the ''Lex Gundobada'' (see below), issuing roughly the first half, which drew upon the ''Lex Visigothorum''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Drew, p. 1&quot;/&gt; Following his consolidation of power, between 501 and his death in 516, Gundobad issued the second half of his law, which was more originally Burgundian.

====Fall====
[[File:Map Burgundian Kingdom 2 EN.png|thumb|right|230px|Burgundy as part of the Frankish Empire between 534 and 843]]

The Burgundians were extending their power over southeastern [[Gaul]]—that is, northern Italy, western Switzerland, and southeastern France. In 493, [[Clovis I|Clovis]], king of the Franks, married the Burgundian princess [[Clotilde|Clotilda]] (daughter of Chilperic), who converted him to the Catholic faith.

At first allied with [[Clovis I|Clovis']] [[Franks]] against the [[Visigoths]] in the early 6th century, the Burgundians were eventually conquered at [[Battle of Autun (532)|Autun]] by the Franks in 532 after a first attempt in the [[Battle of Vézeronce]]. The Burgundian kingdom was made part of the [[Merovingian]] kingdoms, and the Burgundians themselves were by and large absorbed as well.

==Physical appearance==
The 5th century [[Gallo-Roman]] [[poet]] and [[landowner]] [[Sidonius Apollinaris|Sidonius]], who at one point lived with the Burgundians, described them as a long-haired people of immense physical size:{{quote| &quot;Why... do you [an obscure senator by the name of Catullinus] bid me compose a song dedicated to Venus... placed as I am among long-haired hordes, having to endure Germanic speech, praising often with a wry face the song of the gluttonous Burgundian who spreads rancid butter on his hair? ... You don't have a reek of garlic and foul onions discharged upon you at early morn from ten breakfasts, and you are not invaded before dawn... by a crowd of giants.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Heater197&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Heather|2007|pp=196–197}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{clear right}}

==Language==
{{Infobox language
|name=Burgundian
|region=[[Gaul]]
|extinct=6th century
|familycolor=Indo-European
|fam2=[[Germanic languages|Germanic]]
|fam3=[[East Germanic languages|East Germanic]]
|iso3=none
|linglist=qlb
|glotto=none
}}

The '''Burgundian language''' was described as Germanic by [[Sidonius Appolinarius]].&lt;ref&gt;Sidonius Appolinaris, Epistulae, V, 5.1-3&lt;/ref&gt; [[Herwig Wolfram]] has interpreted this as being because they had entered Gaul from ''Germania''.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Wolfram|1997|p=5}} &quot;Goths, Vandals, and other East Germanic tribes were differentiated from the Germans and were referred to as Scythians, Goths, or some other special names. The sole exception are the Burgundians, who were considered German because they came to Gaul via Germania. In keeping with this classification, post-Tacitean Scandinavians were also no longer counted among the Germans....&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

More specifically their language is thought to have belonged to the [[East Germanic languages|East Germanic language group]], based upon their presumed equivalence to the Burgundians named much earlier by Pliny in the east, and some names and placenames. However this is now considered uncertain.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Wolfram|1997|p=259}} &quot;For a long time linguists considered the Burgundians to be an East Germanic people, but today they are no longer so sure.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Little is known of the language. Some proper names of Burgundians are recorded, and some words used in the area in modern times are thought to be derived from the ancient Burgundian language,&lt;ref name=Lockwood/&gt; but it is often difficult to distinguish these from Germanic words of other origin, and in any case the modern form of the words is rarely suitable to infer much about the form in the old language.

The language appears to have become extinct during the late sixth century.&lt;ref name=Lockwood&gt;W.B. Lockwood, &quot;A Panorama of Indo-European Languages&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Religion==
Somewhere in the east the Burgundians had converted to the [[Arianism|Arian Christianity]] from earlier [[Germanic paganism]]. Their Arianism proved a source of suspicion and distrust between the Burgundians and the [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] [[Western Roman Empire]].

Divisions were evidently healed or healing circa 500, however, as [[Gundobad]], one of the last Burgundian kings, maintained a close personal friendship with [[Avitus of Vienne|Avitus]], the [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Vienne|bishop of Vienne]]. Moreover, Gundobad's son and successor, [[Sigismund of Burgundy|Sigismund]], was himself a Catholic, and there is evidence that many of the Burgundian people had converted by this time as well, including several female members of the ruling family.

==Law==
{{Expand French|Burgondes|date=March 2013|topic = culture}}&lt;!-- Expand section. --&gt;

The Burgundians left three [[legal code]]s, among the earliest from any of the Germanic tribes.

The '''Liber Constitutionum sive Lex Gundobada''' (&quot;The Book of Constitutions or Law of Gundobad&quot;), also known as the ''[[Lex Burgundionum]]'', or more simply the ''Lex Gundobada'' or the ''Liber'', was issued in several parts between 483 and 516, principally by Gundobad, but also by his son, Sigismund.&lt;ref&gt;Drew, p.&amp;nbsp;6–7&lt;/ref&gt; It was a record of Burgundian customary law and is typical of the many Germanic law codes from this period. In particular, the ''Liber'' borrowed from the ''[[Lex Visigothorum]]''&lt;ref&gt;Drew, p.&amp;nbsp;6&lt;/ref&gt; and influenced the later ''[[Lex Ripuaria]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Rivers, p.&amp;nbsp;9&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Liber'' is one of the primary sources for contemporary Burgundian life, as well as the history of its kings.

Like many of the Germanic tribes, the Burgundians' legal traditions allowed the application of separate laws for separate ethnicities. Thus, in addition to the ''Lex Gundobada'', Gundobad also issued (or codified) a set of laws for Roman subjects of the Burgundian kingdom, the ''Lex Romana Burgundionum'' (''The Roman Law of the Burgundians'').

In addition to the above codes, Gundobad's son Sigismund later published the ''Prima Constitutio''.&lt;!-- I have been unable to find a source for this. –[[User:Ryanmcdaniel|Ryan McDaniel]] --&gt;

==See also==
{{portal|Ancient Germanic culture}}
* [[Dauphiné]]
* [[Duchy of Burgundy]]
* [[Franche-Comté]]
* [[List of ancient Germanic peoples and tribes]]
* [[List of kings of Burgundy]]
* ''[[Nibelung]]'' (later legends of the Burgundian kings)

===Notes===
{{Notelist}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

===Sources===
{{refbegin|35em}}
*{{cite book |last1=Buchberger |first1=Erica |author-link1= |date=2018 |year= |orig-year= |chapter=Burgundians |chapter-url=https://www.oxfordreference.com/view/10.1093/acref/9780198662778.001.0001/acref-9780198662778-e-828? |editor1-last=Nicholson |editor1-first=Oliver |editor1-link= |title=The Oxford Dictionary of Late Antiquity |trans-title= |url= |url-status= |format= |type= |series= |language= |volume= |issue= |edition= |location= |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |page= |pages= |isbn=9780191744457 |archive-url= |archive-date= |access-date=January 26, 2020 |via= |subscription= |quote= |ref=harv}}
* Bury, J. B. ''The Invasion of Europe by the Barbarians''. London: Macmillan and Co., 1928.
* [[Ormonde Maddock Dalton|Dalton, O. M.]] ''The History of the Franks, by Gregory of Tours''. Oxford: The Clarendon Press, 1927.
*{{cite book |last1= |first1= |author-link1= |date=2009 |year= |orig-year= |chapter=Burgundians |chapter-url=https://www.oxfordreference.com/view/10.1093/acref/9780199534043.001.0001/acref-9780199534043-e-586? |editor1-last=Darvill |editor1-first=Timothy |editor1-link=Timothy Darvill |title=The Concise Oxford Dictionary of Archaeology |trans-title= |url= |url-status= |format= |type= |series= |language= |volume= |issue= |edition=3 |location= |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |page= |pages= |isbn=9780191727139 |archive-url= |archive-date= |access-date=January 26, 2020 |via= |subscription= |quote= |ref=harv}}
* Drew, Katherine Fischer. ''The Burgundian Code''. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1972.
*{{cite book |last1=Drinkwater |first1=John Frederick |author-link1=John Frederick Drinkwater |date=2012 |year= |orig-year= |chapter=Burgundians |chapter-url=https://www.oxfordreference.com/view/10.1093/acref/9780199545568.001.0001/acref-9780199545568-e-1198?rskey=iHPXih&amp;result=5 |editor1-last=Hornblower |editor1-first=Simon |editor1-link=Simon Hornblower |editor2-last=Spawforth |editor2-first=Antony |editor2-link= |editor3-last=Eidinow |editor3-first=Esther |editor3-link=Esther Eidinow |title=[[The Oxford Classical Dictionary]] |trans-title= |url= |url-status= |format= |type= |series= |language= |volume= |issue= |edition=4 |location= |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |page= |pages= |isbn=9780191735257 |archive-url= |archive-date= |access-date=January 25, 2020 |via= |subscription= |quote= |ref=harv}}
* Gordon, C.D. ''The Age of Attila''. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1961.
* Guichard, Rene, ''Essai sur l'histoire du peuple burgonde, de Bornholm (Burgundarholm) vers la Bourgogne et les Bourguignons'', 1965, published by A. et J. Picard et Cie.
* {{cite book |last=Heather |first=Peter |author-link=Peter Heather |date=11 June 2007 |title=The Fall of the Roman Empire: A New History of Rome and the Barbarians |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MmXFrafifw0C |location= |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |page= |isbn=0195325419 |access-date=31 May 2015 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last1=Hitchner |first1=R. Bruce |author-link1=R. Bruce Hitchner |date=2005 |year= |orig-year= |chapter=Burgundians |chapter-url=https://www.oxfordreference.com/view/10.1093/acref/9780195046526.001.0001/acref-9780195046526-e-0852 |editor1-last=Kazhdan |editor1-first=Alexander P. |editor1-link=Alexander Kazhdan |title=[[The Oxford Dictionary of Byzantium]] |trans-title= |url= |url-status= |format= |type= |series= |language= |volume= |issue= |edition= |location= |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |page= |pages= |isbn=9780195187922 |archive-url= |archive-date= |access-date=January 26, 2020 |via= |subscription= |quote= |ref=harv}}
* Murray, Alexander Callander. ''From Roman to Merovingian Gaul''. Broadview Press, 2000.
* Musset, Lucien. ''The Germanic Invasions: The Making of Europe AD 400–600''. University Park, Pennsylvania: The Pennsylvania State University Press, 1975. {{ISBN|978-0-271-01198-1}}.
* Nerman, Birger. ''Det svenska rikets uppkomst''. Generalstabens litagrafiska anstalt: Stockholm. 1925.
* Rivers, Theodore John. ''Laws of the Salian and Ripuarian Franks''. New York: AMS Press, 1986.
* Rolfe, J.C., trans, ''Ammianus Marcellinus''. Cambridge, Massachusetts: Harvard University Press, 1950.
* Shanzer, Danuta. 'Dating the Baptism of Clovis.' In ''Early Medieval Europe'', volume 7, pages 29–57. Oxford: Blackwell Publishers Ltd, 1998.
* Shanzer, D. and I. Wood. ''Avitus of Vienne: Letters and Selected Prose. Translated with an Introduction and Notes''. Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2002.
* Werner, J. (1953). &quot;Beiträge sur Archäologie des Attila-Reiches&quot;, ''Die Bayerische Akademie der Wissenschaft. Abhandlungen''. {{small|N.F. XXXVIII&amp;nbsp;A}} Philosophische-philologische und historische Klasse. Münche
* {{cite book |last=Wolfram |first=Herwig |author-link=Herwig Wolfram |year=1997 |chapter= |editor-last= |editor-first= |editor-link= |title=The Roman Empire and Its Germanic Peoples |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=tOnQDfRU-poC |series= |language= |volume= |edition= |location= |publisher=[[University of California Press]] |page= |pages= |isbn=978-0520085114 |archive-url= |archive-date= |access-date= |via= |registration= |subscription= |quote= |ref=harv}}
* Wood, Ian N. &quot;Ethnicity and the Ethnogenesis of the Burgundians&quot;. In Herwig Wolfram and Walter Pohl, editors, ''Typen der Ethnogenese unter besonderer Berücksichtigung der Bayern'', volume 1, pages 53–69. Vienna: Denkschriften der Österreichische Akademie der Wissenschaften, 1990.
* Wood, Ian N. ''The Merovingian Kingdoms''. Harlow, England: The Longman Group, 1994.
{{refend}}

== External links ==
* {{Commons category-inline}}

{{Germanic languages}}
{{Germanic peoples}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Burgundians| ]]
[[Category:Early Germanic peoples]]
[[Category:Vandals]]</text>
      <sha1>kg0k9llyrzfolls6897m98scfq81xj7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
