  <page>
    <title>Bayezid I</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4241</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943281613</id>
      <parentid>943273595</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T23:52:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>188.141.25.160</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reference added for Heneage novel which features Bayazid as a character.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2017}}
{{Infobox royalty
| name         = Bayezid I &lt;br /&gt;بايزيد اول
| title        = 
| titletext    = 
| more         = 
| type         = 
| image        = Bayezid I by Cristofano dell'Altissimo.jpg
| alt          = 
| caption      = Portrait of Bayezid I by Cristofano dell'Altissimo (1552–1562)
| succession   = 4th [[List of sultans of the Ottoman Empire|Ottoman Sultan]]
| moretext     = 
| reign        = 16 June 1389 ‒ 20 July 1402
 
| coronation   = 
| cor-type     = 
| predecessor  = [[Murad I]]
| regent       = 
| reg-type     = 
| successor    = [[Ottoman Interregnum|''Interregnum'']] (1402 – 1413)&lt;br /&gt;[[Mehmed I]]
| spouse       = [[Sultan Hatun (wife of Bayezid I)|Sultan Hatun]]&lt;br&gt;[[Devlet Hatun]]&lt;br&gt;[[Hafsa Hatun]]&lt;br&gt;[[Olivera Lazarević|Despina Hatun]]&lt;br&gt;Maria Hatun
| spouse-type  = Consorts
| issue        = See [[Bayezid I#Family|below]]
| full name    = Bayezid bin Murad
| house        = [[Ottoman dynasty|Ottoman]]
| house-type   = Dynasty
| father       = [[Murad I]]
| mother       = [[Gülçiçek Hatun]]
| birth_date   = 10 May 1354
| birth_place  = [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman Beylik]]
| death_date   = {{death date and age|1403|3|8|1354|5|10|df=yes}}
| death_place  = [[Timurid Empire]]
| burial_date  = 
| burial_place = [[Bursa]]
| signature_type = [[Tughra]]
| religion     = [[Islam]]
| signature    = File:Tughra of Bayezid I png.png
}}
'''Bayezid I''' ({{lang-ota|بايزيد اول}}; {{lang-tr|I. Bayezid, Yıldırım Bayezid}} (nicknamed '''''Yıldırım''''' (Ottoman Turkish: یلدیرم), &quot;Lightning, Thunderbolt&quot;); 1354 – 8 March 1403)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.britannica.com/biography/Bayezid-I|title=Bayezid I - Ottoman sultan|website=britannica.com|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160402083632/http://www.britannica.com/biography/Bayezid-I|archivedate=2 April 2016|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; was the [[List of sultans of the Ottoman Empire|Ottoman Sultan]] from 1389 to 1402. He was the son of [[Murad I]]&lt;ref name=Lowry&gt;Lowry, Heath W. (2003) ''The Nature of the Early Ottoman State''. Albany, NY: State University of New York Press, p. 153&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Runciman&gt;Runciman, Steven ''The Fall of Constantinople''. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, p. 36&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Gülçiçek Hatun]]. He built one of the largest armies in the known world at the time and unsuccessfully besieged [[Constantinople]]. He adopted the title of Sultan-i Rûm, [[Rûm]] being an old Islamic name for the [[Roman Empire]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=L6-VRgVzRcUC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=The Imperial Harem: Women and Sovereignty in the Ottoman Empire|first=Leslie P.|last=Peirce|date=11 May 1993|publisher=Oxford University Press|via=Google Books|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170923193805/https://books.google.nl/books?id=L6-VRgVzRcUC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;redir_esc=y&amp;hl=nl#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|archivedate=23 September 2017|df=dmy-all|isbn=9780195086775}}&lt;/ref&gt; He decisively defeated the Crusaders at [[Battle of Nicopolis|Nicopolis]] (in modern Bulgaria) in 1396, and was himself defeated and captured by [[Timur]] at the [[Battle of Ankara]] in 1402 and died in captivity in March 1403, triggering the [[Ottoman Interregnum]].

==Biography==

The first major role of Bayezid was as governor of Kütahya, a city that was conquered from the [[Germiyanids]]. He was an impetuous soldier, earning the nickname Lightning in a battle against the [[Karamanids]].
 
Bayezid ascended to the throne following the death of his father Murad I, who was killed by Serbian knight [[Miloš Obilić]] during (15 June), or immediately after (16 June), the [[Battle of Kosovo]] in 1389, by which Serbia became a vassal of the Ottoman Sultanate. Immediately after obtaining the throne, he had his younger brother strangled to avoid a plot. In 1390, Bayezid took as a wife Princess [[Olivera Despina]], the daughter of Prince [[Lazar of Serbia]],&lt;ref&gt;Halil Inalcik, &quot;Bayezid I&quot;, ''The Encyclopedia of Islam'', Vol. I, Ed. H.A.R. Gibb, J.H. Kramers, E. Levi-Provencal and J. Schacht, (Brill, 1986), 1118.&lt;/ref&gt; who also lost his life in Kosovo. Bayezid recognized [[Stefan Lazarević]], the son of Lazar, as the new Serbian leader (later despot), with considerable autonomy.
[[File:Qur'anic Manuscript - Mid to Late 15th Century, Turkey.jpg|thumb|262px|A manuscript of the [[Quran]] from the reign of Bayezid I.]]
The upper Serbia resisted the Ottomans until general [[Pasha Yiğit Bey]] captured the city of Skopje in 1391, converting the city to an important base of operations.

==Efforts to unify Anatolia==

Meanwhile, the sultan began unifying Anatolia under his rule. Forcible expansion into Muslim territories could endanger the Ottoman relationship with the [[gazi]]s, who were an important        source of warriors for this ruling house on the European frontier. So Bayezid began the practice to first secure ''fatwa''s, or legal rulings from Islamic scholars, justifying their wars against these Muslim states. However he suspected the loyalty of his Muslim [[Turkmen people|Turkoman]] followers, for Bayezid relied heavily on his Serbian and Byzantine vassal troops to perform these conquests.&lt;ref&gt;Stanford Shaw, ''History of the Ottoman Empire and Modern Turkey'' (Cambridge: University Press, 1976), vol. 1 p. 30&lt;/ref&gt;

In a single campaign over the summer and fall of 1390, Bayezid conquered the beyliks of [[Beylik of Aydın|Aydin]], [[Sarukhanids|Saruhan]] and [[Menteshe]]. His major rival Sulayman, the emir of [[Karaman]], responded by allying himself with the ruler of [[Sivas]], [[Kadi Burhan al-Din]] and the remaining Turkish beyliks. Nevertheless, Bayezid pushed on and in the fall and winter of 1390 overwhelmed the remaining beyliks -- [[Hamidids|Hamid]], [[Beylik of Teke|Teke]], and [[Germiyan]]—as well as taking the cities of [[Akşehir]] and [[Niğde]], as well as their capital [[Konya]] from the Karaman. At this point, Bayezid accepted peace proposals from Karaman (1391), concerned that further advances would antagonize his Turkoman followers and lead them to ally with Kadi Burhan al-Din. Once peace had been made with Karaman, Bayezid moved north against [[Kastamonu]] which had given refuge to many fleeing from his forces, and conquered both that city as well as [[Sinop, Turkey|Sinop]].&lt;ref&gt;Shaw, ''History of the Ottoman Empire'', vol. 1 pp. 30f&lt;/ref&gt; However, his subsequent campaign was stopped by Burhan al-Din at the [[Battle of Kırkdilim]].

From 1389 to 1395 he conquered [[Bulgaria]] and northern [[Greece]]. In 1394 Bayezid crossed the River [[Danube]] to attack [[Wallachia]], ruled at that time by [[Mircea I of Wallachia|Mircea the Elder]]. The Ottomans were superior in number, but on 10 October 1394 (or 17 May 1395), in the [[Battle of Rovine]], on forested and swampy terrain, the [[Wallachia]]ns won the fierce battle and prevented Bayezid's army from advancing beyond the Danube.&lt;ref&gt;John V.A. Fine, ''The Late Medieval Balkans'', (The University of Michigan Press, 1994), 424.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1394, Bayezid laid siege to [[Constantinople]],&lt;ref&gt;Mango, Cyril. ''The Oxford History of Byzantium''. 1st ed. New York: Oxford UP, 2002. p. 273-4&lt;/ref&gt; the capital of the [[Byzantine Empire]]. [[Anadoluhisarı]] fortress was built between 1393 and 1394 as part of preparations for the Second Ottoman Siege of Constantinople, which took place in 1395. On the urgings of the Byzantine emperor [[Manuel II Palaeologus]] a new [[crusade]] was organized to defeat him. This proved unsuccessful: in 1396 the [[Christianity|Christian]] allies, under the leadership of the King of [[Kingdom of Hungary|Hungary]] and future [[Holy Roman Emperor]] (in 1433) [[Sigismund, Holy Roman Emperor|Sigismund]], were defeated in the [[Battle of Nicopolis]]. Bayezid built the magnificent [[Bursa Grand Mosque|Ulu Cami]] in Bursa, to celebrate this victory.

Thus the siege of Constantinople continued, lasting until 1402.&lt;ref&gt;Nancy Bisaha, ''Creating East And West: Renaissance Humanists And the Ottoman Turks'', (University of Pennsylvania Press, 2004), 98.&lt;/ref&gt; The beleaguered Byzantines had their reprieve when Bayezid fought the [[Timurid dynasty|Timurid Empire]] in the East.&lt;ref&gt;Dimitris J. Kastritsis, ''The Sons of Bayezid: Empire Building and Representation in the Ottoman Civil War of 1402-13'', (Brill, 2007), 5.&lt;/ref&gt; At this time, the empire of Bayezid included [[Thrace]] (except [[Constantinople]]), [[Macedonia (region)|Macedonia]], [[Bulgaria]], and parts of [[Serbia]] in Europe. In Asia, his domains extended to the [[Taurus Mountains]]. His army was considered one of the best in the Islamic world.

==Clash with Timur==

In 1397, Bayezid defeated the emir of Karaman in Akçay, killing him and annexing his territory. In 1398, the sultan conquered the Djanik emirate and the territory of Burhan al-Din, violating the accord with Timur. Finally, Bayezid occupied Elbistan and Malatya.

In 1400, the [[Turco-Mongol]] warlord [[Timur]] succeeded in rousing the local Turkic [[Anatolian beyliks|beyliks]] who had been vassals of the Ottomans to join him in his attack on Bayezid, who was also considered one of the most powerful rulers in the Muslim world during that period. Years of insulting letters had passed between Timur and Bayezid. Both rulers insulted each other in their own way while Timur preferred to undermine Bayezid's position as a ruler and play down the significance of his military successes. 

This is the excerpt from one of Timur's letters addressed to Ottoman sultan:

&quot;Believe me, you are but pismire ant: don't seek to fight the elephants for they'll crush you under their feet. Shall a petty prince such as you are contend with us? But your rodomontades (braggadocio) are not extraordinary; for a [[Turcoman]] never spake with judgement. If you don't follow our counsels you will regret it&lt;ref&gt;Rhoads Murphey, Exploring Ottoman Sovereignty: Tradition, Image and Practice in the Ottoman Imperial Household 1400-1800; published by Continium, 2008; page-58&lt;/ref&gt;&quot;.

In the fateful [[Battle of Ankara]], on 20 July 1402, Bayezid was captured by Timur and the Ottoman army was defeated. Many writers claim that Bayezid was mistreated by the Timurids. However, writers and historians from Timur's own court reported that Bayezid was treated well, and that Timur even mourned his death&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=XDmZXIDiZG8C&amp;pg=PA208&amp;lpg=PA208&amp;dq=timur+%22mourned%22+bayezid#v=onepage&amp;q=timur%20%22mourned%22%20bayezid&amp;f=false|title=Empires of Islam in Renaissance Historical Thought|last=MESERVE|first=Margaret|last2=Meserve|first2=Margaret|date=2009-06-30|publisher=Harvard University Press|isbn=9780674040953|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;. One of Bayezid's sons, [[Mustafa Çelebi]], was captured with him and held captive in [[Samarkand]] until 1405.

Four of Bayezid's sons, specifically [[Süleyman Çelebi]], [[İsa Çelebi]], [[Mehmed Çelebi]], and [[Musa Çelebi]], however, escaped from the battlefield and later started a civil war for the Ottoman throne known as the [[Ottoman Interregnum]].&lt;ref&gt;Dimitris J. Kastritsis,1-3.&lt;/ref&gt; After Mehmed's victory, his coronation as [[Mehmed I]], and the death of all four but Mehmed, Bayezid's other son [[Mustafa Çelebi]] emerged from hiding and began two failed rebellions against his brother Mehmed and, after Mehmed's death, his nephew [[Murat II]].
[[File:Chlebowski-Bajazyt w niewoli.jpg|thumb|262px|Bayezid I held captive by [[Timur]], painting by [[Stanisław Chlebowski]] (oil on canvas, 1878).]]
==Family==
His mother was [[Gülçiçek Hatun]] who was of ethnic [[Greeks|Greek]] descent.&lt;ref name=Lowry/&gt;&lt;ref name=Shaw&gt;Shaw, ''History of the Ottoman Empire'', Vol. 1 p. 28&lt;/ref&gt;

;Consorts
Bayezid had five consorts
*[[Sultan Hatun (wife of Bayezid I)|Sultan Hatun]] (m. 1381), daughter of Prince Süleyman Şah Çelebi of the [[Germiyanids]] and Mutahhare Abide Hatun;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Mehmet Fuat|last=Köprülü|title=Edebiyat araştırmaları|publisher=Türk Tarih Kurumu Basımevi|year=1966|pages=76|isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;necdet&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first=Necdet|last=Öztürk|title=Osmanlı Sosyal Hayati|publisher=Işık Yayıncılık Ticaret|date=January 30, 2014|pages=|isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Devlet Hatun]], mother of [[Mehmed I]]; 
*[[Olivera Lazarević|Despina Hatun]] (m. 1389), daughter of [[Prince Lazar|Prince Lazar of Serbia]] and [[Princess Milica of Serbia|Princess Miliza]];&lt;ref name=&quot;ulucay&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first=M. Çağatay|last=Uluçay|title=Padişahların kadınları ve kızları|publisher=Türk Tarih Kurumu|year=1985|pages=24–5|isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;necdet&quot;/&gt;
*[[Hafsa Hatun]] (m. 1390), daughter of Prince Fahreddin Isa Bey of the [[Aydinids]];&lt;ref name=&quot;ulucay&quot;/&gt;
*Maria Hatun (m. 1394), daughter of [[Louis Fadrique]], [[Lordship of Salona|Count of Salona]] and [[Helena Asanina Kantakouzene]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Donald MacGillivray|last=Nicol|title=The Byzantine Family of Kantakouzenos (Cantacuzenus) Ca. 1100-1460: A Genealogical and Prosopographical Study, Volume 11|publisher=Dumbarton Oaks Center for Byzantine Studies, trustees for Harvard University|year=1968|pages=161|isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Yildirim Tomb 7151.jpg|thumb|262px|The [[türbe]] ''([[tomb]])'' of [[Yıldırım Bayezid]] is located at [[Yıldırım Bayezid Camii]].]]
;Sons
* Şehzade Ertuğrul Çelebi; (1378 – 1400);
* Şehzade [[Süleyman Çelebi]] (1377 – 1411), co-sultan of [[Rumelia]];
* Şehzade [[İsa Çelebi]] (1380 – 1403), governor of [[Anatolia]];
* Şehzade [[Mehmed Çelebi]] (1382 – 1421), governor of [[Anatolia]], and later sultan Mehmed I (reign 1413–1421), with [[Devlet Hatun]];
* Şehzade [[Musa Çelebi]] (1388 – 1413), sultan of [[Rumelia]] (1410–1413)
* Şehzade [[Mustafa Çelebi]] (1393 – 1422);
* Şehzade Yusuf Çelebi, converted to Christianity, changed his name to Demetrios;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvtxt|Kastritsis|2007|p=41}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Şehzade Kasım Çelebi, sent as a hostage to Constantinople together with his sister, Fatma Hatun;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvtxt|Kastritsis|2007|p=41}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;Daughters
* Hundi Hatun, married to Damat Seyyid Şemseddin Mehmed Buhari, Emir Sultan;&lt;ref name=&quot;ulucay1&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Mustafa Çağatay Uluçay|title=Padişahların kadınları ve kızları|pages=25–6|publisher=Ankara, Ötüken|year=2011|isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Erhondu Hatun, married to Damat Yakup Bey son of Pars Bey;&lt;ref name=&quot;ulucay1&quot;/&gt;
* Fatma Hatun, married to a Sanjak Bey;&lt;ref name=&quot;ulucay1&quot;/&gt;
* Oruz Hatun, who had a daughter named Ayşe Hatun;&lt;ref name=&quot;ulucay1&quot;/&gt;
* A daughter, married to Abu Bakar Mirza, son of Jalal ud-din Miran Shah son of [[Timur]];

==In fiction==
[[File:1396-Battle of Nicopolis.jpg|thumb|262px|The [[Battle of Nicopolis]], as depicted by Turkish miniaturist in 1588.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Battle of Nicopolis (1396)&quot; from Seyyid Lokman (1588): ''Hünernâme''&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The defeat of Bayezid became a popular subject for later Western writers, composers, and painters. They embellished the legend that he was taken by Timur to [[Samarkand]] with a cast of characters to create an oriental fantasy that has maintained its appeal. [[Christopher Marlowe]]'s play ''[[Tamburlaine (play)|Tamburlaine the Great]]'' was first performed in [[London]] in 1587, three years after the formal opening of English-Ottoman trade relations when [[William Harborne]] sailed for Constantinople as an agent of the [[Levant Company]].

In 1648, the play ''Le Gran Tamerlan et Bejezet'' by [[Jean Magnon]] appeared in London, and in 1725, [[Handel]]'s ''[[Tamerlano]]'' was first performed and published in London;&lt;ref&gt;London: Printed &amp; sold by J. Cluer, [1725]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Vivaldi]]'s version of the story, ''[[Bajazet (opera)|Bajazet]]'', was written in 1735. Magnon had given Bayezid an intriguing wife and daughter; the Handel and Vivaldi renditions included, as well as Tamerlane and Bayezid and his daughter, a prince of Byzantium and a princess of [[Trabzon|Trebizond]] ([[Trabzon]]) in a passionate love story. A cycle of paintings in [[Schloss Eggenberg]], near [[Graz]] in [[Austria]], translated the theme to a different medium; this was completed in the 1670s shortly before the Ottoman army attacked the [[Habsburgs]] in central [[Europe]].&lt;ref&gt;Finkel, C. (2006) ''The History of the Ottoman Empire: Osman's Dream''. New York: Basic Books; p. 30&lt;/ref&gt;

The historical novel ''The Grand Cham'' (1921) by [[Harold Lamb]] focuses on the quest of its European hero to gain the assistance of Tamerlane in defeating Bayezid.&lt;ref&gt;Lamb, Harold. ''Swords from the West''. Lincoln; University of Nebraska Press, 2009 {{ISBN|9780803226203}} (p.603) &lt;/ref&gt; Bayezid (spelled Bayazid) is a central character in the [[Robert E. Howard]] story ''Lord of Samarcand,''&lt;ref&gt;Howard, Robert E. (1973) ''Sowers of the Thunder,'' Ace Science Fiction&lt;/ref&gt; where he commits suicide at Tamerlane's victory banquet. Bayazid is a main character in the novel ''The Walls of Byzantium'' (2013) by [[James Heneage]].&lt;ref&gt; &quot; ''The Walls of Byzantium''...[where] The Armies of the Ottoman Emperor Bayazid threaten Constantinople and the few remaining outposts of its empire&quot;. Cited in &quot;Three More Tales of the Byzantine Empire&quot;. ''[[BBC History]]'' Magazine, 10 September 2015 (p. 74).&lt;/ref&gt; 

==In popular culture==
Sultan Bayazit was portrayed in the Serbian 1989 historical drama film [[Battle of Kosovo(film)|Battle of Kosovo]], as a participant of the [[Battle of Kosovo]] by actor [[Branislav Lečić]], and in the Romanian historical drama ''[[Mircea (film)|Mircea (Proud heritage)]]'' by [[Ion Ritiu]] as a young Sultan who fought in the battles of [[Battle of Rovine|Rovine]], [[Battle of Nicopolis|Nicopolis]] and [[Battle of Angora|Angora]].

==See also==
*[[Amir Sultan]]
*[[Timur]]
*[[Timurid Empire]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==Sources==
* {{EI2 | last = İnalcık | first = Halil | authorlink = Halil İnalcık | title = Bāyazīd | volume = 1 | pages = 1117–1119 | url = https://dx.doi.org/10.1163/1573-3912_islam_SIM_1302 }}
* Harris, Jonathan (2010) ''The End of Byzantium''. New Haven and London: Yale University Press {{ISBN|978-0-300-11786-8}}
* {{Cite book|last=Imber |first=Colin |title=The Ottoman Empire, 1300-1650: The Structure of Power |edition=2 |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |place=New York |date=2009 |isbn=978-0-230-57451-9 }}
* {{cite book | last = Kastritsis | first = Dimitris | title = The Sons of Bayezid: Empire Building and Representation in the Ottoman Civil War of 1402-13 | publisher = BRILL | year = 2007 | isbn = 978-90-04-15836-8 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=u_evCQAAQBAJ | ref=harv}}
* Nicolle, David (1999) ''Nicopolis 1396: The Last Crusade''. Oxford: Osprey Books {{ISBN|978-1-85532-918-8}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Bayezid I}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20101227153900/http://www.waitmeturkey.com/yildirim-bayezid-i-ottoman-empire-sultan.html Yıldırım Bayezid I]

{{S-start}}
{{S-hou|[[Ottoman Dynasty|House of Osman]]||1354||8 March 1403}}
{{S-reg|}}
{{S-bef|before=[[Murad I]]}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[List of sultans of the Ottoman Empire|Ottoman Sultan]]|years= 16 June 1389 – 20 July 1402}}
{{S-aft|after=[[Mehmed I]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{Sultans of the Ottoman Empire}}
{{Sons of the Ottoman Sultans}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bayezid 01}}
[[Category:1361 births]]
[[Category:1403 deaths]]
[[Category:14th-century Ottoman sultans]]
[[Category:15th-century Ottoman sultans]]
[[Category:People of the Bulgarian–Ottoman wars]]
[[Category:Monarchs imprisoned and detained during war]]
[[Category:Muslims of the Crusade of Nicopolis]]
[[Category:Ottoman people of the Byzantine–Ottoman wars]]
[[Category:Ottoman sultans born to Greek mothers]]
[[Category:Turkish poets]]</text>
      <sha1>bigbneqbg6lsuuxyzfj8eh8s3xk9dt1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
