  <page>
    <title>Big Brother (Nineteen Eighty-Four)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4261</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941407260</id>
      <parentid>941346142</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-18T11:51:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Keith D</username>
        <id>2278355</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Criticism and use as metaphor */Fix cite date error</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about|the novel character||Big Brother (disambiguation)}}
{{DISPLAYTITLE:Big Brother (''Nineteen Eighty-Four'')}}
{{use British English|date=August 2012}}
{{use dmy dates|date=April 2015}}
{{Infobox character
|name=Big Brother
|image=1984-Big-Brother.jpg
|first = ''[[Nineteen Eighty-Four]]'' (1949)
|creator=[[George Orwell]]
|gender=Male
|occupation=Leader of [[Oceania (1984)|Oceania]]
}}
'''Big Brother''' is a fictional character and symbol in [[George Orwell]]'s [[dystopia]]n novel ''[[Nineteen Eighty-Four]]'', published in 1949.

He is ostensibly the leader of [[Oceania (1984)|Oceania]], a [[Totalitarianism|totalitarian]] state wherein the ruling party [[Ingsoc]] wields total power &quot;for its own sake&quot; over the inhabitants. In the society that Orwell describes, every citizen is under constant [[surveillance]] by the authorities, mainly by [[telescreen]]s (with the exception of the [[Proles (Nineteen Eighty-Four)|Proles]]). The people are constantly reminded of this by the slogan &quot;Big Brother is watching you&quot;: a maxim that is ubiquitously on display.

In modern culture, the term &quot;Big Brother&quot; has entered the [[lexicon]] as a synonym for abuse of government power, particularly in respect to [[civil liberties]], often specifically related to [[mass surveillance]].

== Character origins ==
In the essay section of his novel ''[[1985 (Anthony Burgess novel)|1985]]'', [[Anthony Burgess]] states that Orwell got the idea for the name of Big Brother from advertising [[billboard]]s for educational [[correspondence course]]s from a company called Bennett's during [[World War II]]. The original posters showed [[J. M. Bennett]] himself, a kindly-looking old man offering guidance and support to would-be students with the phrase &quot;Let me be your father.&quot; According to Burgess, after Bennett's death, his son took over the company and the posters were replaced with pictures of the son (who looked imposing and stern in contrast to his father's kindly demeanor) with the text &quot;Let me be your big brother&quot;.

Additional speculation from [[Douglas Kellner]] of the [[University of California, Los Angeles]] argued that Big Brother represents [[Joseph Stalin]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gseis.ucla.edu/faculty/kellner/index.html |title=Douglas Kellner, George F. Kneller Philosophy of Education Chair, UCLA |work=ucla.edu |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110709224448/http://gseis.ucla.edu/faculty/kellner/index.html |archivedate=9 July 2011 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gseis.ucla.edu/faculty/kellner/essays/from1984toonedimensional.pdf|title=From 1984 to One-Dimensional Man: Critical Reflections on Orwell and Marcuse|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110829021052/http://gseis.ucla.edu/faculty/kellner/essays/from1984toonedimensional.pdf|archivedate=29 August 2011|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another theory is that the inspiration for Big Brother was [[Brendan Bracken]], the [[Ministry of Information (United Kingdom)|Minister of Information]] until 1945. Orwell worked under Bracken on the [[BBC]]'s Indian Service. Bracken was customarily referred to by his employees by his initials, B.B., the same initials as the character Big Brother. Orwell also resented the wartime censorship and need to manipulate information which he felt came from the highest levels of the Minister of Information and from Bracken's office in particular.

== Portrayal in the novel ==
=== Existence ===
[[File:Telescreen.png|thumb|250px|Big Brother's face looms from giant telescreens in [[Trafalgar Square#Cultural references|Victory Square]].]]
In the novel, it is never made clear whether Big Brother is or had been a real person, or is a [[National personification|fictional personification]] of [[Ingsoc|the Party]], similar to [[Britannia]] and [[Uncle Sam]]. Big Brother is described as appearing on posters and telescreens as a man in his mid-40s. In Party propaganda, Big Brother is presented as one of the founders of the Party.

At one point, [[Winston Smith]], the protagonist of Orwell's novel, tries &quot;to remember in what year he had first heard mention of Big Brother. He thought it must have been at some time in the sixties, but it was impossible to be certain. In the Party histories, Big Brother figured as the leader and guardian of the Revolution since its very earliest days. His exploits had been gradually pushed backwards in time until already they extended into the fabulous world of the forties and the thirties, when the capitalists in their strange cylindrical hats still rode through the streets of London&quot;.

In the book ''[[The Theory and Practice of Oligarchical Collectivism]]'', read by Winston Smith and purportedly written by Goldstein, Big Brother is referred to as infallible and all-powerful. No one has ever seen him and there is a reasonable certainty that he will never die. He is simply &quot;the guise in which the Party chooses to exhibit itself to the world&quot; since the emotions of love, fear and reverence are more easily focused on an individual (if only a face on the hoardings and a voice on the telescreens) than an organisation. When Winston Smith is later arrested, [[O'Brien (Nineteen Eighty-Four)|O'Brien]] repeats that Big Brother will never die. When Smith asks if Big Brother exists, O'Brien describes him as &quot;the embodiment of the Party&quot; and says that he will exist as long as the Party exists. When Winston asks &quot;Does Big Brother exist the same way I do?&quot; (meaning is Big Brother an actual human being), O'Brien replies &quot;You do not exist&quot; (meaning that Smith is now an [[unperson]]; an example of [[doublethink]]).

=== Cult of personality ===
Big Brother is the subject of a [[cult of personality]]. A spontaneous ritual of devotion to &quot;BB&quot; is illustrated at the end of the [[Two Minutes Hate]] ritual:

{{quote|At this moment the entire group of people broke into a deep, slow, rhythmic chant of 'B-B! . . . B-B! . . . B-B!'—over and over again, very slowly, with a long pause between the first 'B' and the second—a heavy murmurous sound, somehow curiously savage, in the background of which one seemed to hear the stamps of naked feet and the throbbing of tom-toms.  For perhaps as much as thirty seconds they kept it up.  It was a refrain that was often heard in moments of overwhelming emotion.  Partly it was a sort of hymn to the wisdom and majesty of Big Brother, but still more it was an act of self-hypnosis, a deliberate drowning of consciousness by means of rhythmic noise.&lt;ref&gt;Orwell, George (1949). Nineteen Eighty-Four.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Though Oceania's [[Ministry of Truth]], [[Ministry of Plenty]] and [[Ministry of Peace]] each have names with meanings deliberately opposite to their real purpose, the [[Ministry of Love]] is perhaps the most straightforward as &quot;rehabilitated thought criminals&quot; leave the Ministry as loyal subjects who have been [[brainwashing|brainwashed]] into adoring (loving) Big Brother, hence its name.{{citation needed||date=June 2019}}

The term &quot;ministry&quot; implies that each of these ministries is headed by a minister. If so, however, these ministers seem to be shadowy figures, whose names, words and acts are not publicized - public attention being focused solely on Big Brother.

== Film adaptations ==

The character, as represented solely by a single still photograph, was played in the 1954 BBC adaptation by production designer [[Roy Oxley]].

In the film starring [[John Hurt]] released in 1984, the Big Brother photograph was of actor [[Bob Flag]].

In the 1955 film adaptation, Big Brother was represented by an illustration of a stern looking disembodied head.

Both Oxley and Flag sported small moustaches.

== Criticism and use as metaphor ==
{{Global surveillance}}
Since the publication of ''Nineteen Eighty-Four'', the phrase &quot;Big Brother&quot; has come into common use to describe any prying or overly-controlling authority figure and attempts by government to increase surveillance. Big Brother and other [[Orwellian]] imagery are often referenced in the joke known as the [[Russian reversal]].{{citation needed||date=June 2019}}

[[File:Plaza George Orwell, Barcelona..jpg|thumb|left|[[Closed-circuit television|CCTV]] in [[George Orwell]] Square in [[Barcelona]], Spain]]
[[Iain Moncreiffe]] and [[Don Pottinger]] jokingly mentioned in their 1956 book ''Blood Royal'' the sentence: &quot;Without Little Father need for Big Brother&quot;, referring to the [[Russian Revolution]] and the [[Soviet Union]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| author =Iain Moncreiffe &amp; Don Pottinger | title=Blood Royal| date=1956| publisher=Thomas Nelson and Sons| page=18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The worldwide reality television show ''[[Big Brother (TV series)|Big Brother]]'' is based on the novel's concept of people being under constant [[surveillance]]. In 2000, after the [[Big Brother (American TV series)|United States version]] of the [[CBS]] program ''Big Brother'' premiered, the Estate of George Orwell sued CBS and its production company Orwell Productions, Inc. in federal court in Chicago for copyright and trademark infringement. The case was ''Estate of Orwell v. CBS'', 00-c-5034 (ND Ill). On the eve of trial, the case settled worldwide to the parties' &quot;mutual satisfaction&quot;, but the amount that CBS paid to the Orwell Estate was not disclosed. CBS had not asked the Estate for permission. Under current laws, the novel will remain under [[copyright]] protection until 2020 in the European Union and until 2044 in the United States.{{citation needed||date=June 2019}}
 
The December 2002 issue of ''[[Gear (magazine)|Gear]]'' magazine featured a story about technologies and trends that could violate personal privacy moving society closer to a &quot;Big Brother&quot; state and utilised a recreation of the movie poster&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dallmeierart.com/user/cimage/244493fb0.jpg |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2010-09-11 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110511195706/http://www.dallmeierart.com/user/cimage/244493fb0.jpg |archivedate=11 May 2011 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; from the film version of ''1984''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dallmeierart.com/bigbrother.htm|title=Big Brother is Watching You – George Orwell 1984 Movie Prop Print DallmeierArt.com|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100210174430/http://www.dallmeierart.com/bigbrother.htm|archivedate=10 February 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The magazine ''Book'' ranked Big Brother No. 59 on its 100 Best Characters in Fiction Since 1900 list.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Christine Paik |url=https://www.npr.org/programs/totn/features/2002/mar/020319.characters.html |title=100 Best Fictional Characters Since 1900 |publisher=NPR |date=19 March 2002 }}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Wizard (magazine)|Wizard]]'' magazine rated him the 75th greatest villain of all time.&lt;ref&gt;''Wizard'' #177&lt;/ref&gt;

The iconic image of Big Brother (played by David Graham) played a key role in [[Apple Inc.|Apple]]'s &quot;[[1984 (advertisement)|1984]]&quot; television commercial introducing the [[Macintosh]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zdnet.com/news/remembering-the-1984-super-bowl-mac-ad/263647 Remembering the '1984' Super Bowl Mac ad] ZDNet, 23 January 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.bbc.co.uk/blogs/technology/2009/09/iconic_apple_ad_gets_doubletwi.html Apple's 'Big Brother' sequel] BBC News, 30 September 2009&lt;/ref&gt; The Orwell Estate viewed the Apple commercial as a copyright infringement and sent a cease-and-desist letter to Apple and its advertising agency. The commercial was never televised again,&lt;ref&gt;William R. Coulson [http://www.dartmouthlawjournal.org/articles/106-115.pdf ‘Big Brother’ is watching Apple: The truth about the Super Bowl's most famous ad] The Dartmouth Law Journal, 25 June 2009 {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110725220353/http://www.dartmouthlawjournal.org/articles/106-115.pdf |date=25 July 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; though the date mentioned in the ad (24 January) was but two days later, making it unlikely that it would have been re-aired. Subsequent (now posthumous) ads featuring [[Steve Jobs]] (for a variety of products including audio books) have mimicked the format and appearance of that original ad campaign, with the appearance of Jobs nearly identical to that of Big Brother.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Nick |last= Farrell |url=http://www.theinquirer.net/inquirer/news/1558044/steve-jobs-big-brother |title=Steven Jobs is the new Big Brother |publisher= the Inquirer |date=9 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |first=David |last= Gianatasio |url=http://www.adweek.com/adfreak/steve-jobs-once-again-cast-big-brother-11810 |title=Steve Jobs (once again) cast as Big Brother |magazine= AdWeek |date=16 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, ''[[The Simpsons]]'' spoofed Apple's Big Brother commercial in an episode entitled &quot;[[MyPods and Boomsticks|Mypods and Boomsticks]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=MG |last= Siegler |url=https://venturebeat.com/2008/12/01/the-simpsons-apple-spoof-likely-has-many-wondering-what-a-mycube-is/ |title=The Simpsons Apple spoof likely has many wondering what a &quot;myCube&quot; is |work= VentureBeat |date=1 December 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Computer company [[Microsoft]] patented in 2011 a product distribution system with a camera or capture device that monitors the viewers that consume the product, allowing the provider to take &quot;remedial action&quot; if the actual viewers do not match the distribution license.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://appft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO1&amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;d=PG01&amp;p=1&amp;u=%2Fnetahtml%2FPTO%2Fsrchnum.html&amp;r=1&amp;f=G&amp;l=50&amp;s1=%2220120278904%22.PGNR.&amp;OS=DN/20120278904&amp;RS=DN/20120278904 |title=Content distribution regulation by viewing use |publisher=Appft.uspto.gov |date= |accessdate=1 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Kinect|system]] has been compared with ''1984'''s telescreen surveillance system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Robert |last=Evans |url=http://www.i4u.com/42421/kinect-makes-i1984i-reality |title=Kinect Makes 1984 Reality: Well, one part anyway |publisher=I4u.com |date=12 November 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141007090138/http://www.i4u.com/42421/kinect-makes-i1984i-reality |archivedate=7 October 2014 |df=dmy }} .&lt;/ref&gt;

A series of laws intended to implement the European Union [[Data Retention Directive]] in [[Romania]] were nicknamed &quot;the Big Brother laws&quot; by Romanian media and critics as they would have led to blanket storage of citizens' telecommunications data for six months.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url= http://economie.hotnews.ro/stiri-telecom-12503594-traian-basescu-promulgat-asa-numita-39-lege-big-brother-39-care-prevede-stocarea-pentru-sase-luni-datelor-trafic-ale-tuturor-utilizatorilor-telefonie-internet.htm | title=Traian Basescu a promulgat asa numita 'lege Big Brother' care prevede stocarea pentru sase luni a datelor de trafic ale tuturor utilizatorilor de telefonie si internet }}&lt;/ref&gt; All of these laws were struck down as unconstitutional by the [[Constitutional Court of Romania]] and the Directive itself was ultimately invalidated by the [[Court of Justice of the European Union]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.loc.gov/law/help/eu-data-retention-directive/eu.php|title=European Union: ECJ Invalidates Data Retention Directive|last=Papademetriou|first=Theresa|date=June 2014|website=www.loc.gov|access-date=2020-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 2010 video game ''[[Bioshock 2]]'', there is an enemy named the Big Sister. The phrase &quot;Big Sister is watching&quot; is a reference to the 1984 phrase &quot;Big Brother is watching&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=[[Bioshock 2]] |developer=[[2K Games]] |publisher=[[2K Marin]] |date=Feb 9, 2010 |platform=[[Xbox 360]], [[Xbox One]], [[PlayStation 3]], [[PlayStation 4]], [[Personal computer|PC]] |version= |scene= |level= |language= |quote=&quot;Big Sister is Watching&quot; }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[China]]'s [[Social Credit System]] has been described as akin to &quot;Big Brother&quot; by detractors, where citizens and businesses are given or deducted good behavior points depending on their choices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Big brother: China's data-driven Social Credit system sounds like a sci-fi dystopia |url=https://www.thenational.ae/arts-culture/comment/big-brother-china-s-data-driven-social-credit-system-sounds-like-a-sci-fi-dystopia-1.774372 |work=The National |date=September 26, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{commons category|Big Brother}}
* [[Big Brother Awards]]
* [[Little Brother (Doctorow novel)|Little Brother]]
* [[Memory hole]]
* [[New World Order (conspiracy theory)]]
* [[National Security Agency]]
* [[Totalitarianism]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}{{Portal bar|Politics|Literature}}{{Nineteen Eighty-Four}}

[[Category:Mass surveillance]]
[[Category:Nineteen Eighty-Four characters]]
[[Category:Fictional dictators]]
[[Category:Literary characters introduced in 1949]]
[[Category:Fictional governments]]
[[Category:Male literary villains]]
[[Category:Dystopian fiction]]
[[Category:Male characters in literature]]</text>
      <sha1>ajr75esdlrgt8p0a3m2x2b8zh0jjcnc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
