  <page>
    <title>Adam Weishaupt</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2077</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942335900</id>
      <parentid>942298840</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-24T02:09:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bobherry</username>
        <id>14301224</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/92.19.76.10|92.19.76.10]] ([[User talk:92.19.76.10|talk]]) to last version by Bobherry</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{Infobox philosopher
|region = Western Philosophy
|era = [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment era]]
|image = Johann_Adam_Weishaupt.jpg
|caption = 1799 portrait of Weishaupt
|birth_name = Johann Adam Weishaupt
|birth_date = {{birth date|1748|2|6|df=y}}
|birth_place = [[Ingolstadt]], [[Electorate of Bavaria|Bavaria]], [[Holy Roman Empire]]
|death_date = {{death date and age|1830|11|18|1748|2|6|df=y}}
|death_place = [[Gotha (town)|Gotha]], [[Saxe-Coburg and Gotha|Saxe-Coburg-Gotha]], [[German Confederation]]
|school_tradition = [[Empiricism]]
|main_interests = [[Epistemology]], [[Metaphysics]], [[Ethics]]
|influences = [[Scottish Enlightenment]], [[Baron d'Holbach]], [[Johann Georg Heinrich Feder|J.G.H. Feder]]
|influenced = [[Percy Bysshe Shelley]], [[Robert Anton Wilson]]
|notable_ideas =
}}
'''Johann Adam Weishaupt''' ({{IPA-de|ˈjoːhan ˈaːdam ˈvaɪ̯s.haʊ̯pt|}}, 6 February 1748 – 18 November 1830)&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB Vol. 41&quot;&gt;''Allgemeine Deutsche Biographie'' [http://daten.digitale-sammlungen.de/bsb00008399/image_541 Vol. 41, p. 539].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel 1906&quot;&gt;Engel, Leopold. ''Geschichte des Illuminaten-ordens''. Berlin: H. Bermühler Verlag, 1906.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;van Dülmen 1975&quot;&gt;van Dülmen, Richard. ''Der Geheimbund der Illuminaten''. Stuttgart: Frommann-Holzboog, 1975.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stauffer 1918&quot;&gt;Stauffer, Vernon. ''New England and the Bavarian Illuminati''. Columbia University, 1918.&lt;/ref&gt; was a [[Germans|German]] philosopher, law professor, and founder of the [[Illuminati|Order of the Illuminati]], a secret society.

==Early life==
Adam Weishaupt was born on 6 February 1748 in [[Ingolstadt]]&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB Vol. 41&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;&gt;Engel [https://books.google.com/books?id=v72fDHzuMf0C&amp;pg=PR6#PPA22,M1 22].&lt;/ref&gt; in the [[Electorate of Bavaria]]. Weishaupt's father [[Johann Georg Weishaupt]] (1717–1753) died&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt; when Adam was five years old. After his father's death he came under the tutelage of his [[Godparent|godfather]] [[Johann Adam von Ickstatt|Johann Adam Freiherr von Ickstatt]]&lt;ref&gt;''Allgemeine Deutsche Biographie'' [http://daten.digitale-sammlungen.de/bsb00008371/image_742 Vol. 13, pp. 740–741].&lt;/ref&gt; who, like his father, was a professor of law at the [[University of Ingolstadt]].&lt;ref&gt;Freninger, Franz Xaver, ed. ''Das Matrikelbuch der Universitaet Ingolstadt-Landshut-München''. München: A. Eichleiter, 1872. 31.&lt;/ref&gt; Ickstatt was a proponent of the philosophy of [[Christian Wolff (philosopher)|Christian Wolff]] and of the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]],&lt;ref&gt;Hartmann, Peter Claus. ''Bayerns Weg in die Gegenwart''. Regensburg: Pustet, 1989. 262. Also, Bauerreiss, Romuald. ''Kirchengeschichte Bayerns''. Vol. 7. St. Ottilien: EOS Verlag, 1970. 405.&lt;/ref&gt; and he influenced the young Weishaupt with his [[rationalism]]. Weishaupt began his formal education at age seven&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB Vol. 41&quot;/&gt; at a [[Society of Jesus|Jesuit]] school. He later enrolled at the University of Ingolstadt and graduated in 1768&lt;ref&gt;Freninger 47.&lt;/ref&gt; at age 20 with a [[Juris Doctor|doctorate of law]].&lt;ref&gt;Engel [https://books.google.com/books?id=v72fDHzuMf0C&amp;pg=PR6#PPA25,M1 25–28].&lt;/ref&gt; In 1772&lt;ref&gt;Freninger 32.&lt;/ref&gt; he became a professor of law. The following year he married Afra Sausenhofer&lt;ref&gt;Engel [https://books.google.com/books?id=v72fDHzuMf0C&amp;pg=PR6#PPA31,M1 31].&lt;/ref&gt; of [[Eichstätt]].

After [[Pope Clement XIV]]’s [[suppression of the Society of Jesus]] in 1773, Weishaupt became a professor of [[canon law]],&lt;ref&gt;Engel [https://books.google.com/books?id=v72fDHzuMf0C&amp;pg=PR6#PPA33,M1 33]. Also, ''Allgemeine Deutsche Biographie'' [http://daten.digitale-sammlungen.de/bsb00008399/image_542 Vol. 41, p. 540].&lt;/ref&gt; a position that was held exclusively by the [[Society of Jesus|Jesuits]] until that time. In 1775 Weishaupt was introduced&lt;ref&gt;Engel [https://books.google.com/books?id=v72fDHzuMf0C&amp;pg=PR6#PPA61,M1 61–62].&lt;/ref&gt; to the [[Empiricism|empirical]] philosophy of [[Johann Georg Heinrich Feder]]&lt;ref&gt;''Allgemeine Deutsche Biographie'' [http://daten.digitale-sammlungen.de/bsb00008364/image_597 Vol. 6, pp. 595–597].&lt;/ref&gt; of the [[University of Göttingen]]. Both Feder and Weishaupt would later become opponents of [[Immanuel Kant|Kantian]] [[idealism]].&lt;ref&gt;Beiser, Frederick C. ''The Fate of Reason''. Harvard University Press, 1987. [https://books.google.com/books?id=5ihJn9EKCl4C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_summary_r&amp;cad=0#PPA186,M1 186–88].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Founder of the Illuminati==
{{quote|At a time, however, when there was no end of making game of and abusing secret societies, I planned to make use of this human foible for a real and worthy goal, for the benefit of people. I wished to do what the heads of the ecclesiastical and secular authorities ought to have done by virtue of their offices ...&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Schneider |first1=Heinrich |authorlink1= |title=Quest for Mysteries: The Masonic Background for Literature in 18th Century Germany|url= |format= |accessdate= |type= |edition= |series= |date= |year=2005 |month= |origyear=1947 |publisher=Kessinger Publishing |location= |language= |isbn=1419182145 |oclc= |doi= |id= |page=24 n.49 |pages= |at= |chapter= |chapterurl= |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

On 1 May 1776 Johann Adam Weishaupt founded the &quot;Illuminati&quot; in the Electorate of Bavaria. He adopted the name of &quot;Brother [[Spartacus]]&quot; within the order. Even encyclopedia references vary on the goal of the order, such as ''New Advent'' saying the Order was not [[egalitarian]] or democratic internally, but sought to promote the doctrines of equality and freedom throughout society;&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic Encyclopedia&quot;&gt;Catholic Encyclopedia: [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/07661b.htm Illuminati],&lt;/ref&gt; while others like ''Collier's'' have said the aim was to combat religion and foster rationalism in its place.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Couch |first=William |date=1956 |title=Collier's Encyclopedia, Volume 10 |url= |location= |publisher=Crowell-Collier Publishing Company |page=370 |isbn= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The actual character of the society was an elaborate network of spies and counter-spies. Each isolated cell of initiates reported to a superior, whom they did not know: a party structure that was effectively adopted by some later groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic Encyclopedia&quot; /&gt;

Weishaupt was initiated into the [[Masonic lodge]] &quot;Theodor zum guten Rath&quot;, at Munich in 1777. His project of &quot;illumination, enlightening the understanding by the sun of reason, which will dispel the clouds of superstition and of prejudice&quot; was an unwelcome reform.&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic Encyclopedia&quot; /&gt; He used [[Freemasonry]] to recruit for his own quasi-masonic society, with the goal of &quot;perfecting human nature&quot; through re-education to achieve a communal state with nature, freed of government and organized religion. Presenting their own system as pure masonry, Weishaupt and [[Adolph Freiherr Knigge]], who organised his ritual structure, greatly expanded the secret organisation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic Encyclopedia&quot; /&gt;

Contrary to Immanuel Kant's [[Answering the Question: What is Enlightenment?|famous dictum]] that [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] (and Weishaupt's Order was in some respects an expression of the Enlightenment Movement) was the passage by man out of his 'self-imposed immaturity' through daring to 'make use of his own reason, without the guidance of another,' Weishaupt's Order of Illuminati prescribed in great detail everything which the members had obediently to read and think, so that Dr. Wolfgang Riedel has commented that this approach to illumination or enlightenment constituted a degradation and twisting of the Kantian principle of Enlightenment.&lt;ref&gt;Dr. Wolfgang Riedel, 'Aufklaerung und Macht', in ''Die Weimarer Klassik und ihre Geheimbuende'', ed. by W. Mueller-Seidel and W. Riedel, Koenigshausen und Neumann, 2002, p. 112&lt;/ref&gt; Riedel writes:

'The independence of thought and judgement required by Kant ... was specifically prevented by the Order of the Illuminati's rules and regulations. Enlightenment takes place here, if it takes place at all, precisely ''under''  the direction of another, namely under that of the &quot;Superiors&quot; [of the Order].&lt;ref&gt;Dr. Wolfgang Riedel, ''Die Weimarer Klassik und ihre Geheimbuende'',2001, p. 112&lt;/ref&gt;

Weishaupt's radical rationalism and vocabulary were not likely to succeed. Writings that were intercepted in 1784 were interpreted as seditious, and the Society was banned by the government of [[Charles Theodore, Elector of Bavaria|Karl Theodor]], Elector of Bavaria, in 1784. Weishaupt lost his position at the University of Ingolstadt and fled Bavaria.&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic Encyclopedia&quot; /&gt;

==Activities in exile==
He received the assistance of [[Ernest II, Duke of Saxe-Gotha-Altenburg|Duke Ernest II]] of [[Saxe-Gotha-Altenburg]] (1745–1804), and lived in [[Gotha (town)|Gotha]] writing a series of works on illuminism, including ''A Complete History of the Persecutions of the Illuminati in Bavaria'' (1785), ''A Picture of Illuminism'' (1786), ''An Apology for the Illuminati'' (1786), and ''An Improved System of Illuminism'' (1787). Adam Weishaupt died in Gotha on 18 November 1830.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB Vol. 41&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel 1906&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;van Dülmen 1975&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stauffer 1918&quot;/&gt; He was survived by his second wife, Anna Maria (née Sausenhofer), and his children Nanette, Charlotte, Ernst, [[Karl von Weishaupt|Karl]], Eduard, and Alfred.&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel 1906&quot;/&gt; Weishaupt was buried next to his son Wilhelm who preceded him in death in 1802.

After Weishaupt's Order of Illuminati was banned and its members dispersed, it left behind no enduring traces of an influence, not even on its own erstwhile members, who went on in the future to develop in quite different directions.&lt;ref&gt;Dr. Eberhard Weis in ''Die Weimarer Klassik und ihre Geheimbünde'', edited by Professor Walter Müller-Seidel and Professor Wolfgang Riedel, Königshausen und Neumann, 2003, pp. 100-101&lt;/ref&gt;

==Assessment of character and intentions==
[[File:Illuminaten397.jpg|thumb|[[Death mask]] of Adam Weishaupt]]

Weishaupt's character and intentions have been variously assessed. Some took a negative view, such as [[Augustin Barruel]], who despite writing that Weishaupt's goals were that &quot;Equality and Liberty, together with the most absolute independence, are to be the substitutes for all rights and all property&quot; saw this as more dangerous than beneficial, &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.sacred-texts.com/sro/mhj/mhj313.htm|title=Code of the Illuminati, Part III of: Memoirs Illustrating the History of Jacobinism - Abbé Barreul|website=www.sacred-texts.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[John Robison (physicist)|John Robison]] who regarded him as a 'human devil' and saw his mission as one of malevolent destructiveness.  Others took a more positive view, including [[Thomas Jefferson]], who wrote in a letter to [[James Madison]] that &quot;Barruel’s own parts of the book are perfectly the ravings of a Bedlamite&quot; and considered Weishaupt as an &quot;enthusiastic Philanthropist&quot; who believed in the indefinite perfectibility of man and his intention was simply to &quot;reinstate natural religion, and by diffusing the light of his morality, to teach us to govern ourselves&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://founders.archives.gov/documents/Jefferson/01-31-02-0297|title=From Thomas Jefferson to Bishop James Madison, 31 January 1800}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In his defense, Weishaupt wrote a ''Kurze Rechtfertigung meiner Absichten''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.com/books/about/Kurze_Rechtfertigung_meiner_Absichten.html?id=WggXMQAACAAJ&amp;redir_esc=y|title=Kurze Rechtfertigung meiner Absichten - Adam Weishaupt|website=www.books.google.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; in 1787 (A Brief Justification of my Intentions). A translation was done by Dr. Tony Page in which he wrote:

&quot;Weishaupt’s plan was to educate Illuminati followers in the highest levels of humanity and morality (basing his teachings on the supremacy of Reason, allied with the spirit of the Golden Rule of not doing to others what one would not wish done to oneself), so that if Illuminati alumni subsequently attained positions of significance and power (such as in the fields of education and politics), they could exert a benevolent and uplifting influence upon society at large. His project was utopian and naively optimistic, and he himself was certainly not without flaws of character – but neither he nor his plan was evil or violent in and of themselves. It is one of the deplorable and tragic ironies of history that a man who tried to inculcate virtue, philanthropy, social justice and morality has become one of the great hate-figures of 21st-century ‘conspiracy’ thinking.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Dr. Tony Page (translator and editor), ''Supplement to the Justification of My Intentions by Adam Weishaupt'', Justice Publications, Bangkok, Amazon Kindle, 2014, p. 1&lt;/ref&gt;

==Works==

===Philosophical works===
* (1775) ''De Lapsu Academiarum Commentatio Politica''.
* (1786) ''Über die Schrecken des Todes&amp;nbsp;– eine philosophische Rede''.
** {{in lang|fr}} ''Discours Philosophique sur les Frayeurs de la Mort'' (1788). [http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k107838n Gallica]
* (1786) ''Über Materialismus und Idealismus''. [https://web.archive.org/web/20080529080940/http://hal9000.cisi.unito.it/wf/BIBLIOTECH/Umanistica/Biblioteca2/Libri-anti1/Miscellane/imagemar2297.pdf Torino]
* (1788) ''Geschichte der Vervollkommnung des menschlichen Geschlechts''.
* (1788) ''Über die Gründe und Gewißheit der Menschlichen Erkenntniß''.
* (1788) ''Über die Kantischen Anschauungen und Erscheinungen''.
* (1788) ''Zweifel über die Kantischen Begriffe von Zeit und Raum''.
* (1793) ''Über Wahrheit und sittliche Vollkommenheit''.
* (1794) ''Über die Lehre von den Gründen und Ursachen aller Dinge''.
* (1794) ''Über die Selbsterkenntnis, ihre Hindernisse und Vorteile''.
* (1797) ''Über die Zwecke oder Finalursachen''.
* (1802) ''Über die Hindernisse der baierischen Industrie und Bevölkerung''.
* (1804) ''Die Leuchte des Diogenes''.
* (1817) ''Über die Staats-Ausgaben und Auflagen''. [https://books.google.com/books?id=lnxRAAAAMAAJ Google Books]
* (1818) ''Über das Besteuerungs-System''.

===Works relating to the Illuminati===

*(1786) ''Apologie der Illuminaten'', {{ISBN|978-3-7448-1853-7}}.
*(1786) ''Vollständige Geschichte der Verfolgung der Illuminaten in Bayern''.
*(1786) ''Schilderung der Illuminaten''.
*(1787) ''Einleitung zu meiner Apologie''.
*(1787) [''Einige Originalschriften des Illuminatenordens''...]
*(1787) [''Nachtrage von weitern Originalschriften''...] Google Books
*(1787) ''Kurze Rechtfertigung meiner Absichten''.
*(1787) ''Nachtrag zur Rechtfertigung meiner Absichten''.
*(1787) ''Apologie des Mißvergnügens und des Übels''.
*(1787) ''Das Verbesserte System der Illuminaten''.
*(1788) ''Der ächte Illuminat, oder die wahren, unverbesserten Rituale der Illuminaten''.
*(1795) ''Pythagoras, oder Betrachtungen über die geheime Welt- und Regierungs-Kunst''.

===Works by Adam Weishaupt in English translation===

*(2008) ''Diogenes’ Lamp, or an Examination of Our Present Day Morality and Enlightenment'', translated by Amelia Gill, The Masonic Book Club.
*(2014) ''A Brief Justification of My Intentions: Casting Light on the Latest Original Writings'', translated by Dr. Tony Page, Justice Publications, Amazon Kindle.
*(2014) ''Supplement to the Justification of My Intentions'', translated by Dr. Tony Page, Justice Publications, Amazon Kindle.
*(2015) ''The Secret School of Wisdom: The Authentic Rituals and Doctrines of the Illuminati'', translated by Jeva Singh-Anand, edited by Josef Wäges and Reinhard Markner, London: Lewis Masonic, 447 pp.

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Sister project links|voy=no|wikt=no|b=no|n=no|s=no|v=no|commons=Category:Adam Weishaupt}}
* {{in lang|de}} Biography in ''Allgemeine Deutsche Biographie'' [http://daten.digitale-sammlungen.de/bsb00008399/image_541 Vol. 41, pp. 539–550] by Daniel Jacoby.
*[http://freemasonry.bcy.ca/texts/illuminati.html A Bavarian Illuminati primer] by Trevor W. McKeown.
*[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/07661b.htm Illuminati] entry in [[Catholic Encyclopedia|The Catholic Encyclopedia]], hosted by [[New Advent]].

&lt;!-- dummy edit; can be deleted. --&gt;

{{Age of Enlightenment}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Weishaupt, Adam}}
[[Category:1748 births]]
[[Category:1830 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Ingolstadt]]
[[Category:People from the Electorate of Bavaria]]
[[Category:Illuminati members]]
[[Category:Enlightenment philosophers]]
[[Category:German philosophers]]
[[Category:18th-century philosophers]]
[[Category:University of Ingolstadt alumni]]
[[Category:University of Ingolstadt faculty]]
[[Category:German Freemasons]]
[[Category:German male writers]]
[[Category:18th-century male writers]]</text>
      <sha1>b04aaxsl4qpvtf1uirgj6dmsadwge7b</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
