  <page>
    <title>Antonio Canova</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2064</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940810089</id>
      <parentid>939368153</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-14T20:05:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Albecy</username>
        <id>36759859</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Gallery */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Canova}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2019}}

{{Infobox artist
| name          = Antonio Canova
| image         = Antonio Canova Selfportrait 1792.jpg
| imagesize     = 250px
| alt           =
| caption       = Self-portrait, 1792
| birth_name    = Antonio Canova
| birth_date    = 1 November 1757
| birth_place   = [[Possagno]], [[Republic of Venice]]
| death_date    = {{Death date and age|1822|10|13|1757|11|1|df=yes}}
| death_place   = [[Venice]], [[Kingdom of Lombardy–Venetia|Lombardy–Venetia]]
| nationality   = Venetian (before fall)&lt;br /&gt;Austrian (territory ceded to Austria)&lt;ref&gt;The fall of Venice occurred in 1797 but was then ceded later to Austria. [https://www.britannica.com/place/Venice/History#ref24409 Encyclopedia Britannica - Venice]. Accessed 14 May 2018.&lt;/ref&gt;
| field         = Sculpture
| training      =
| movement      = [[Neoclassicism]]
| works         = {{unbulleted list|''[[Psyche Revived by Cupid's Kiss]]''|''[[The Three Graces (sculpture)|The Three Graces]]''|''[[Napoleon as Mars the Peacemaker]]''|''[[Venus Victrix (Canova)|Venus Victrix]]''}}
| patrons       =
| influenced by = [[Michelangelo]]&lt;ref name=&quot;DoA-5&quot; /&gt;
| influenced    =
| awards        =
| elected       =
| website       =
}}

'''Antonio Canova''' ({{IPA-it|anˈtɔːnjo kaˈnɔːva}}; 1 November 1757 – 13 October 1822) was an [[Italians|Italian]] [[Neoclassical sculpture|Neoclassical sculptor]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |mode=cs2 |last=Irwin |first=David |url = http://www.britannica.com/biography/Antonio-Canova-marchese-dIschia |title=Antonio Canova, marchese d'Ischia &amp;#124; Italian sculptor |encyclopedia=Britannica.com |accessdate=1 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |mode=cs2 |url = http://www.treccani.it/enciclopedia/antonio-canova/ |title=Canòva, Antonio nell'Enciclopedia Treccani |publisher=Treccani.it |date= |accessdate=1 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; famous for his [[marble sculpture]]s. Often regarded as the greatest of the Neoclassical artists,&lt;ref name=&quot;DoA-22&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Turner|1996a}}.&lt;/ref&gt; his sculpture was inspired by the [[Baroque]] and the classical revival, and has been characterised as having avoided the [[melodrama]]tics of the former, and the cold artificiality of the latter.&lt;ref name=&quot;GoV&quot;&gt;Jean Martineau &amp; Andrew Robinson, ''The Glory of Venice: Art in the Eighteenth Century.'' Yale University Press, 1994. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{anchor|History|Biography}}

==Life==

===Possagno===
In 1757, Antonio Canova was born in the [[Republic of Venice|Venetian Republic]] city of [[Possagno]] to Pietro Canova, a stonecutter, and Maria Angela Zardo Fantolini.&lt;ref name=&quot;DoA-5&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Turner|1996b}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1761, his father died. A year later, his mother remarried. As such, in 1762, he was put into the care of his paternal grandfather Pasino Canova, who was a [[stonemasonry|stonemason]], owner of a [[quarry]],&lt;ref name=&quot;GoV&quot; /&gt; and was a &quot;sculptor who specialized in altars with statues and low reliefs in late Baroque style&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;DoA-5&quot; /&gt; He led Antonio into the art of sculpting.

Before the age of ten, Canova began making models in clay, and carving marble.&lt;ref name=&quot;CA&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Handley|1913}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Indeed, at the age of nine, he executed two small shrines of [[Carrara marble]], which are still extant.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Rossetti|1911|pp=204–206}}.&lt;/ref&gt; After these works, he appears to have been constantly employed under his grandfather.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot; /&gt;

===Venice===
[[File:Antonio canova, orfeo, 1777, 01.JPG|thumb|250px|right|''[[Orpheus]]'', (1777)]]

In 1770,&lt;ref name=&quot;DoA-5&quot;/&gt; he was an apprentice for two years&lt;ref name=&quot;CA&quot;/&gt; to [[Giuseppe Bernardi]], who was also known as 'Torretto'. Afterwards, he was under the tutelage of [[Giovanni Ferrari (sculptor)|Giovanni Ferrari]] until he began his studies at the [[Accademia di Belle Arti di Venezia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;DoA-5&quot;/&gt; At the Academy, he won several prizes.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; During this time, he was given his first workshop within a monastery by some local monks.&lt;ref name=&quot;CA&quot;/&gt;

The Senator Giovanni Falier commissioned Canova to produce statues of [[Orpheus]] and [[Eurydice]] for his garden – the Villa Falier at [[Asolo]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wga.hu&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wga.hu/html_m/c/canova/1/02orpheu.html|title=Eurydice by CANOVA, Antonio|work=wga.hu}}&lt;/ref&gt; The statues were begun in 1775, and both were completed by 1777. The pieces exemplify the late [[Rococo style]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wga.hu&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wga.hu/html_m/c/canova/1/01orpheu.html|title=Orpheus by CANOVA, Antonio|website=wga.hu}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the year of its completion, both works were exhibited for the [[Feast of the Ascension]] in Piazza S. Marco.&lt;ref name=&quot;GoV&quot;/&gt; Widely praised, the works won Canova his first renown among the Venetian elite.&lt;ref name=&quot;DoA-5&quot;/&gt; Another Venetian who is said to have commissioned early works from Canova was the abate [[Filippo Farsetti]], whose collection at [[Ca' Farsetti]] on the [[Grand Canal (Venice)|Grand Canal]] he frequented.

In 1779, Canova opened his own studio at Calle Del Traghetto at S. Maurizio,.&lt;ref name=&quot;GoV&quot;/&gt; At this time, Procurator Pietro Vettor Pisani commissioned Canova's first marble statue: a depiction of [[Daedalus]] and [[Icarus]].&lt;ref name=&quot;GoV&quot;/&gt; The statue inspired great admiration for his work at the annual art fair;&lt;ref name=&quot;wga.hu1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wga.hu/html_m/c/canova/1/1daedalu.html|title=Daedalus and Icarus by CANOVA, Antonio|work=wga.hu}}&lt;/ref&gt; Canova was paid for 100 gold zecchini for the completed work.&lt;ref name=&quot;GoV&quot;/&gt; At the base of the statue, Daedalus' tools are scattered about; these tools are also an allusion to Sculpture, of which the statue is a personification.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wga.hu/html_m/c/canova/1/1daedalx.html|title=Daedalus and Icarus by CANOVA, Antonio|website=wga.hu}}&lt;/ref&gt; With such an intention, there is suggestion that Daedalus is a portrait of Canova's grandfather Pasino.&lt;ref name=&quot;wga.hu1&quot;/&gt;

===Rome===
Canova arrived in Rome, on 28 December 1780.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot; /&gt; Prior to his departure, his friends had applied to the Venetian senate for a pension.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot; /&gt; Successful in the application, the stipend allotted amounted to three hundred ducats, limited to three years.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

While in Rome, Canova spent time studying and sketching the works of Michelangelo.&lt;ref name=&quot;DoA-5&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Canova - Theseus &amp; Minotaur.jpg|thumb|right|250px|''Theseus and the Minotaur'', [[Victoria and Albert Museum]], London]]

In 1781, Girolamo Zulian – the Venetian ambassador to Rome – hired Canova to sculpt ''Theseus and the Minotaur''.&lt;ref name=&quot;wga.hu2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wga.hu/html_m/c/canova/1/2theseus.html|title=Theseus and the Minotaur by CANOVA, Antonio|work=wga.hu}}&lt;/ref&gt; The statue depicts the victorious [[Theseus]] seated on the lifeless body of a [[Minotaur]]. The initial spectators were certain that the work was a copy of a Greek original, and were shocked to learn it was a contemporary work.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.visual-arts-cork.com/sculpture/antonio-canova.htm|title=Antonio Canova: Neoclassical Sculptor, Biography|work=visual-arts-cork.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; The highly regarded work is now in the collection of the [[Victoria &amp; Albert Museum]], in London.&lt;ref name=&quot;wga.hu2&quot;/&gt;

Between 1783–1785, Canova arranged, composed, and designed a funerary monument dedicated to [[Clement XIV]] for the [[Church of Santi Apostoli]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CA&quot;/&gt; After another two years, the work met completion in 1787.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; The monument secured Canova's reputation as the pre-eminent living artist.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

Canova's earliest significant breakthrough was his self-portrait sculpture, finished in 1790. 

In 1792, he completed another cenotaph, this time commemorating [[Clement XIII]] for [[St. Peter's Basilica]]. Canova harmonized its design with the older Baroque funerary monuments in the basilica.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wga.hu/html_m/c/canova/1/4clemenu.html|title=Tomb of Pope Clement XIII by CANOVA, Antonio|website=wga.hu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1790, he began to work on a funerary monument for Titian, which was eventually abandoned by 1795.&lt;ref name=&quot;DoA-5&quot;/&gt; During the same year, he increased his activity as a painter.&lt;ref name=&quot;GoV&quot;/&gt;

The following decade was extremely productive,&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; beginning works such as ''Hercules and Lichas'', ''Cupid and Psyche'', ''Hebe'', ''Tomb of [[Maria Christina, Duchess of Teschen|Duchess Maria Christina of Saxony-Teschen]]'', and ''The Penitent Magdalene''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.wga.hu/html_m/c/canova/1/index.html |title=Sculptures until 1799 |website = wga.hu }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1797, he went to Vienna,&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot; /&gt; but only a year later, in 1798, he returned to [[Possagno]] for a year.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot; /&gt;{{NoteTag|''The Glory of Venice: Art in the Eighteenth Century'' states (p. 441) that Canova left Venice when it fell, tried to escape to America and then went to Possagno. The fall of Venice was in 1797. There appears to be some gap in knowledge that would correct or amend these accounts. The first reference to Vienna is an online source, the second is the ''Encyclopædia Britannica, 1911'' which has already proven itself incorrect in some areas. ''The Glory of Venice'' has proven itself more accurate, but it is undated, leaving speculation of time frame.}}

===France and England===
By 1800, Canova was the most celebrated artist in Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;DoA-5&quot; /&gt; He systematically promoted his reputation by publishing engravings of his works and having marble versions of plaster casts made in his workshop.&lt;ref name=&quot;Batschmann&quot;&gt;Oskar Batschmann, The Artist in the Modern World: A Conflict Between Market and Self-Expression. DuMont Bunchverlag, 1997. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; He became so successful that he had acquired patrons from across Europe including France, England, Russia, Poland, Austria and Holland, as well as several members from different royal lineages, and prominent individuals.&lt;ref name=&quot;GoV&quot; /&gt; Among his patrons were [[Napoleon I of France|Napoleon]] and his family, for whom Canova produced much work, including several depictions between 1803 and 1809.&lt;ref name=&quot;DoA-22&quot; /&gt; The most notable representations were that of ''[[Napoleon as Mars the Peacemaker]]'', and ''[[Venus Victrix (Canova)|Venus Victrix]]'' which was portrayal of [[Pauline Bonaparte]].

''[[Napoleon as Mars the Peacemaker]]'' had its inception after Canova was hired to make a bust of Napoleon in 1802. The statue was begun in 1803, with Napoleon requesting to be shown in a French General's uniform, Canova rejected this, insisting on an allusion to [[Mars (mythology)|Mars]], the [[Roman mythology|Roman god]] of [[War]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wga.hu3&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wga.hu/html_m/c/canova/2/1mars.html|title=Napoleon as Mars the Peacemaker by CANOVA, Antonio|website=wga.hu}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was completed in 1806.&lt;ref name=&quot;wga.hu4&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wga.hu/html_m/c/canova/2/2mars.html|title=Napoleon as Mars the Peacemaker by CANOVA, Antonio|website=wga.hu}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1811, the statue arrived in Paris, but not installed; neither was its bronze copy in the Foro Napoleonico in Milan.&lt;ref name=&quot;wga.hu3&quot;/&gt; In 1815, the original went to [[Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of Wellington|the Duke of Wellington]], after his victory at [[Battle of Waterloo|Waterloo]] against Napoleon.&lt;ref name=&quot;wga.hu4&quot;/&gt;

{{rquote|right|''If one could make statues by caressing marble, I would say that this statue was formed by wearing out the marble that surrounded it with caresses and kiss''|[[Joséphine de Beauharnais]] on the ''[[Venus Victrix (Canova)|Venus Victrix]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;DoA-5&quot;/&gt;}}

''[[Venus Victrix (Canova)|Venus Victrix]]'' was originally conceived as a robed and recumbent sculpture of [[Pauline Bonaparte|Pauline Borghese]] in the guise of [[Diana (mythology)|Diana]]. Instead, Pauline ordered Canova to make the statue a nude Venus.&lt;ref name=&quot;wga.hu5&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wga.hu/html_m/c/canova/2/3paolina.html|title=Paolina Borghese as Venus Victrix by CANOVA, Antonio|website=wga.hu}}&lt;/ref&gt; The work was not intended for public viewing.&lt;ref name=&quot;wga.hu5&quot;/&gt;

Other works for the Napoleon family include, a bust of Napoleon, a statue of Napoleon's mother, and [[Marie Louise, Duchess of Parma|Marie Louise]] as [[Concordia (mythology)|Concordia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CA&quot;/&gt;

In 1802, Canova was assigned the post of 'Inspector-General of Antiquities and Fine Art of the Papal State', a position formerly held by [[Raphael]].&lt;ref name=&quot;GoV&quot;/&gt; One of his activities in this capacity was to pioneer the restoration of the [[Appian Way]] by restoring the tomb of Servilius Quartus.&lt;ref&gt;Paris, Rita, “Appia, una questione non risolta&quot; in “La via Appia, il bianco e il nero di un patrimonio italiano.” Electa. 2011&lt;/ref&gt; In 1808 Canova became an associated member of the [[Royal Netherlands Academy of Arts and Sciences|Royal Institute of the Netherlands]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://www.dwc.knaw.nl/biografie/pmknaw/?pagetype=authorDetail&amp;aId=PE00004542 |title=A. Canova (1757–1822) |publisher=Royal Netherlands Academy of Arts and Sciences |date= |access-date=5 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1814, he began his ''[[The Three Graces (sculpture)|The Three Graces]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;CA&quot;/&gt;

In 1815, he was named 'Minister Plenipotentiary of the Pope,'&lt;ref name=&quot;GoV&quot;/&gt; and was tasked with recovering various works of art that were taken to Paris by [[Napoleon I of France|Napoleon]].&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

{{rquote|right|''The works of Phidias are truly flesh and blood, like beautiful nature itself''|Antonio Canova&lt;ref name=&quot;GoV&quot;/&gt;}}

Also in 1815, he visited London, and met with [[Benjamin Haydon]]. It was after the advice of Canova that the [[Elgin marbles]] were acquired by the British Museum, with plaster copies sent to Florence, according to Canova's request.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

===Returning to Italy===
In 1816, Canova returned to Rome with some of the art Napoleon had taken. He was rewarded with several marks of distinction: he was appointed President of the [[Accademia di San Luca]], inscribed into the &quot;Golden Book of Roman Nobles&quot; by the Pope's own hands,&lt;ref name=&quot;CA&quot;/&gt; and given the title of Marquis of [[Ischia]], alongside an annual pension of 3000 crowns.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

In 1819, he commenced and completed his commissioned work ''[[Venus Italica]]'' as a replacement for the [[Venus de' Medici]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wga.hu/html_m/c/canova/2/8venus.html|title=Venus Italica by CANOVA, Antonio|work=wga.hu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After his 1814 proposal to build a personified statue of Religion for [[St. Peter's Basilica]] was rejected, Canova sought to build his own temple to house it.&lt;ref name=&quot;DoA-5&quot;/&gt; This project came to be the [[Tempio Canoviano]]. Canova designed, financed, and partly built the structure himself.&lt;ref name=&quot;GoV&quot;/&gt; The structure was to be a testament to Canova's piety.&lt;ref name=&quot;Batschmann&quot;/&gt; The building's design was inspired by combining the [[Parthenon]] and the [[Pantheon, Rome|Pantheon]] together.&lt;ref name=&quot;GoV&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CA&quot;/&gt; On 11 July 1819, Canova laid the foundation stone dressed in red Papal uniform and decorated with all his medals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Batschmann&quot;/&gt; It first opened in 1830, and was finally completed in 1836.&lt;ref name=&quot;Batschmann&quot;/&gt; After the foundation-stone of this edifice had been laid, Canova returned to Rome; but every succeeding autumn he continued to visit Possagno to direct the workmen and encourage them with rewards.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

During the period that intervened between commencing operations at Possagno and his death, he executed or finished some of his most striking works. Among these were the group ''Mars and Venus'', the colossal figure of [[Pius VI]], the [[Pietà]], the ''St John'', and a colossal bust of his friend, the Count Cicognara.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Canova-Washington.JPG|thumb|upright|right|''[[George Washington (Canova)|George Washington]]'', plaster replica on display at the [[North Carolina Museum of History]]]]

In 1820, he made a [[George Washington (Canova)|statue of George Washington]] for the state of [[North Carolina]].&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wga.hu/bio_m/c/canova/biograph.html|title=Biography of CANOVA, Antonio in the Web Gallery of Art|work=wga.hu}}&lt;/ref&gt; As recommended by [[Thomas Jefferson]], the sculptor used the [[George Washington (Ceracchi)|marble bust of Washington]] by [[Giuseppe Ceracchi]] as a model.&lt;ref name=gwunc&gt;{{cite web|title=George Washington Sculpture, North Carolina State Capitol, Raleigh|url=http://docsouth.unc.edu/commland/monument/407/|publisher=[[University of North Carolina]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was delivered on 24 December 1821. The statue and the [[North Carolina State House]] where it was displayed were later destroyed by fire in 1831. A plaster replica was sent by the king of Italy in 1910, now on view at the [[North Carolina Museum of History]]. A marble copy was sculpted by [[Romano Vio]] in 1970, now on view in the rotunda of the [[North Carolina State Capitol|capitol building]].&lt;ref name=gwunc/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Canova Statue|url=https://www.ncsu.edu/ligon/rt/canova/canova.htm|publisher=[[North Carolina State University]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1822, he journeyed to Naples, to superintend the construction of wax moulds for an equestrian statue of [[Ferdinand VII]]. The adventure was disastrous to his health, but soon became healthy enough to return to Rome. From there, he voyaged to Venice; however, on 13 October 1822, he died there at the age of 64.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; As he never married, the name became extinct, except through his stepbrothers' lineage of Satori-Canova.&lt;ref name=&quot;CA&quot;/&gt;

On 12 October 1822, Canova instructed his brother to use his entire estate to complete the Tempio in Possagno.&lt;ref name=&quot;Batschmann&quot;/&gt;

On 25 October 1822, his body was placed in the Tempio Canoviano.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; His heart was interred at the [[Basilica di Santa Maria Gloriosa dei Frari]] in Venice, and his right hand preserved in a vase at the [[Accademia di Belle Arti di Venezia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;DoA-5&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Batschmann&quot;/&gt;

His memorial service was so grand that it rivaled the ceremony that the city of Florence held for Michelangelo in 1564.&lt;ref name=&quot;Batschmann&quot;/&gt;

In 1826, Giovanni Battista Sartori sold Canova's Roman studio and took every plaster model and sculpture to Possagno, where they were installed in the [[Tempio Canoviano]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Batschmann&quot;/&gt;

==Works==
Among Canova's most notable works are:{{Citation needed|date=June 2016}}

===''Psyche Revived by Cupid's Kiss'' (1787)===
[[File:Amore e psiche (1).jpg|thumb|right|250px|Detail of ''[[Psyche Revived by Cupid's Kiss]]'']]
{{Main|Psyche Revived by Cupid's Kiss}}

''[[Psyche Revived by Cupid's Kiss]]'' was commissioned in 1787 by [[John Campbell, 1st Baron Cawdor|Colonel John Campbell]].&lt;ref name=Johns&gt;Johns, C.M.S. (1998) ''Antonio Canova and the Politics of Patronage in Revolutionary and Napoleonic Europe''. Berkeley, CA: [[University of California Press]], p. 149.&lt;/ref&gt; It is regarded as a masterpiece of Neoclassical sculpture, but shows the mythological lovers at a moment of great emotion, characteristic of the emerging movement of [[Romanticism]].  It represents the god [[Cupid]] in the height of love and tenderness, immediately after awakening the lifeless [[Psyche (mortal)|Psyche]] with a kiss.

===''Napoleon as Mars the Peacemaker'' (1802–1806)===
{{Main|Napoleon as Mars the Peacemaker}}

''[[Napoleon as Mars the Peacemaker]]'' had its inception after Canova was hired to make a bust of Napoleon in 1802. The statue was begun in 1802, with Napoleon requesting to be shown in a French General's uniform, Canova rejected this, insisting on an allusion to [[Mars (mythology)|Mars]], the [[Roman mythology|Roman god]] of [[War]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wga.hu3&quot;/&gt; It was completed in 1806.&lt;ref name=&quot;wga.hu4&quot;/&gt; In 1811, the statue arrived in Paris, but not installed; neither was its bronze copy in the Foro Napoleonico in Milan.&lt;ref name=&quot;wga.hu3&quot;/&gt; In 1815, the original went to [[Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of Wellington|the Duke of Wellington]], after his victory at [[Battle of Waterloo|Waterloo]] against Napoleon.&lt;ref name=&quot;wga.hu4&quot;/&gt;

===''Perseus Triumphant'' (1804–1806)===
[[File:Canova - perseu - 39b.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Detail of ''Perseus with the Head of Medusa'']]
''Perseus Triumphant'', sometimes called ''Perseus with the Head of Medusa'', was a statue commissioned by tribune Onorato Duveyriez.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mv.vatican.va/3_EN/pages/x-Schede/MPCs/MPCs_Sala02_05.html|title=Perseus Triumphant|work=vatican.va}}&lt;/ref&gt; It depicts the Greek hero [[Perseus]] after his victory over the [[Gorgon]] [[Medusa]].

The statue was based freely to the [[Apollo Belvedere]] and the [[Medusa Rondanini]].&lt;ref name=&quot;metmuseum.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/works-of-art/67.110.1|title=Antonio Canova: Perseus with the Head of Medusa (67.110.1) – Heilbrunn Timeline of Art History – The Metropolitan Museum of Art|work=metmuseum.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Napoleon]], after his [[Italian campaigns of the French Revolutionary Wars|1796 Italian Campaign]], took the [[Apollo Belvedere]] to Paris. In the statue's absence, [[Pope Pius VII]] acquired Canova's ''Perseus Triumphant'' and placed the work upon the ''Apollo'''s pedestal.&lt;ref&gt;
Christopher M. S. Johns, ''Antonia Canova and the Politics of Patronage in Revolutionary and Napoleonic Europe''. University of California Press, 1998. Web. – p. 25&lt;/ref&gt; The statue was so successful that when the ''Apollo'' was returned, ''Perseus'' remained as a companion piece.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wga.hu/html_m/c/canova/2/2perseu.html|title=Perseus with the Head of Medusa by CANOVA, Antonio|work=wga.hu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One replica of the statue was commissioned from Canova by the Polish countess [[Waleria Tarnowska]]; it's now displayed in the [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]] in [[New York City]].&lt;ref name=&quot;metmuseum.org&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wga.hu/html_m/c/canova/2/2perseus.html|title=Perseus with the Head of Medusa by CANOVA, Antonio|work=wga.hu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Karl Ludwig Fernow]] said of the statue that &quot;every eye must rest with pleasure on the beautiful surface, even when the mind finds its hopes of high and pure enjoyment disappointed.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Padiyar&quot;/&gt;

===''Venus Victrix'' (1805–1808)===
{{Main|Venus Victrix (Canova)}}

''[[Venus Victrix (Canova)|Venus Victrix]]'' ranks among the most famous of Canova's works. Originally, Canova wished the depictation to be of a robed [[Diana (mythology)|Diana]], but [[Pauline Bonaparte|Pauline Borghese]] insisted to appear as a nude Venus.&lt;ref name=&quot;wga.hu5&quot;/&gt; The work was not intended for public viewing.&lt;ref name=&quot;wga.hu5&quot;/&gt;

===''The Three Graces'' (1814–1817)===
[[File:Le tre Grazie.jpg|thumb|250px|''[[The Three Graces (sculpture)|The Three Graces]]'']]
{{Main|The Three Graces (sculpture)}}

[[John Russell, 6th Duke of Bedford|John Russell]], the 6th [[Duke]] of Bedford, commissioned a version of the now famous work.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vam.ac.uk/content/articles/t/the-three-graces/ The Three Graces.] Victoria &amp; Albert Museum, 2013. Retrieved 2 May 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;  He had previously visited Canova in his studio in [[Rome]] in 1814 and had been immensely impressed by a carving of the Graces the sculptor had made for the [[Empress Josephine]].  When the Empress died in May of the same year he immediately offered to purchase the completed piece, but was unsuccessful as Josephine's son [[Eugène de Beauharnais|Eugène]] claimed it (his son [[Maximilian, Duke of Leuchtenberg|Maximilian]] brought it to [[St. Petersburg]], where it can now be found in the [[Hermitage Museum]]). Undeterred, the Duke commissioned another version for himself.

The sculpting process began in 1814 and was completed in 1817.  Finally in 1819 it was installed at the Duke's residence in [[Woburn Abbey]].  Canova even made the trip over to England to supervise its installation, choosing for it to be displayed on a [[pedestal]] adapted from a marble [[plinth]] with a rotating top.  This version is now owned jointly by the [[Victoria and Albert Museum]] and the [[National Galleries of Scotland]], and is alternately displayed at each.

==Artistic process==
{{rquote|right|''Canova's system of work concentrated on the initial idea, and on the final carving of the marble''&lt;ref name=&quot;DoA-5&quot;/&gt;}}

Canova's sculptures fall into three categories: Heroic compositions, compositions of grace, and sepulchral monuments.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; In each of these, Canova's underlying artistic motivations were to challenge, if not compete, with classical statues.&lt;ref name=&quot;GoV&quot;/&gt;

Canova refused to take in pupils and students,&lt;ref name=&quot;DoA-5&quot;/&gt; but would hire workers to carve the initial figure from the marble. He had an elaborate system of comparative pointing so that the workers were able to reproduce the plaster form in the selected block of marble.&lt;ref name=&quot;Padiyar&quot;&gt;Satish Padiyar, Chains: David, Canova, and the Fall of the Public Hero in Postrevolutionary France. Pennsylvania State University Press, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; These workers would leave a thin veil over the entire statue so Canova's could focus on the surface of the statue.&lt;ref name=&quot;Padiyar&quot;/&gt;

While he worked, he had people read to him select literary and historical texts.&lt;ref name=&quot;DoA-5&quot;/&gt;

===Last touch===
{{rquote|right|''The polish throws upon the parts which are lighted so great brilliancy as frequently to make invisible the most laborious diligence; it cannot be seen, because the strong reflected light dazzles the eyes''|Johann Joachim Winckelmann&lt;ref name=&quot;Padiyar&quot;/&gt;}}

During the last quarter of the eighteenth century, it became fashionable to view art galleries at night by torchlight. Canova was an artist that leapt on the fad and displayed his works of art in his studio by candlelight.&lt;ref name=&quot;Batschmann&quot;/&gt; As such, Canova would begin to finalize the statue with special tools by candlelight,&lt;ref name=&quot;DoA-5&quot;/&gt; to soften the transitions between the various parts of the nude.&lt;ref name=&quot;Padiyar&quot;/&gt; After a little recarving, he began to rub the statue down with pumice stone, sometimes for periods longer than weeks or months.&lt;ref name=&quot;Padiyar&quot;/&gt; If that was not enough, he would use [[Rotten stone|tripoli (rottenstone)]] and [[lead]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Padiyar&quot;/&gt;

He then applied a now unknown chemical-composition of [[patina]] onto the flesh of the figure to lighten the skin tone.&lt;ref name=&quot;DoA-5&quot;/&gt; Importantly, his friends also denied any usage of acids in his process.&lt;ref name=&quot;CA&quot;/&gt;

==Criticisms==
Conversations revolving around the justification of art as superfluous usually invoked the name of Canova.&lt;ref name=&quot;Batschmann&quot;/&gt;

[[Karl Ludwig Fernow]] believed that Canova was not [[Kant]]ian enough in his aesthetic, because [[Critique of Judgment|emphasis seemed to have been placed on agreeableness rather than Beauty]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Padiyar&quot;/&gt;

Canova was also faulted for creating works that were artificial in complexity.&lt;ref name=&quot;GoV&quot;/&gt;

==Legacy==
[[File:Asolo-Museum Canoviano.JPG|thumb|right|250px|The ''Museo Canoviano'' located in Possagno near [[Asolo]]]]

{{quote|''The importance and value of Canova's art is now recognized as holding in balance the last echo of the Ancients and the first symptom of the restless experimentation of the modern age''&lt;ref name=&quot;DoA-5&quot;/&gt;}}

Canova spent large parts of his fortune helping young students and sending patrons to struggling sculptors,&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;/&gt; including Sir [[Richard Westmacott]] and [[John Gibson (sculptor)|John Gibson]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-6KvAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA9&amp;lpg=PA9&amp;dq=antonio+canova+patron+richard+westmacott+john+gibson&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=qVFT0_BRpR&amp;sig=r1MWgu763BxVH5nuaAx0yHKiXII&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiWnsuK4a7UAhUHKGMKHYTQB7UQ6AEIUTAM#v=onepage&amp;q=antonio%20canova%20patron%20richard%20westmacott%20john%20gibson&amp;f=false|title=The Lustrous Trade: Material Culture and the History of Sculpture in England and Italy, c. 1700–c. 1860|last=Sicca|first=Cinzia|last2=Yarrington|first2=Alison|date=2001|publisher=A&amp;C Black|year=|isbn=9781441185907|location=|pages=9|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.gibson-trail.uk/maps/canova|title=John Gibson R. A.|website=www.gibson-trail.uk|access-date=8 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He was introduced into various orders of [[chivalry]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CA&quot;/&gt;

The [[Romantic period]] artists buried Canova's name soon after he died, but he is slowly being rediscovered.&lt;ref name=&quot;DoA-5&quot;/&gt;

A number of his works, sketches, and writings are collected in the ''Sala Canoviana'' of the [[Museo Civico of Bassano del Grappa]]. Other works, including plaster casts are the Museo Canoviano in Asolo.

==Literary inspirations==
{{Wikisource|Letitia Elizabeth Landon (L. E. L.) in Fisher's Drawing Room Scrap Book, 1834/Dancing Girl|'The Dancing Girl'&lt;br&gt;a poem by L. E. L.}}
{{Wikisource|Letitia Elizabeth Landon (L. E. L.) in Fisher's Drawing Room Scrap Book, 1834/Hebe|'Hebe',&lt;br /&gt;a poem by L. E. L.}}

Two of Canova's works appear as engravings in ''Fisher's Drawing Room Scrap Book'', 1834, with poetical illustrations by [[Letitia Elizabeth Landon]]. These are of ''The Dancing Girl'' and ''Hebe''.

===Commemorations===
*[[Canova, South Dakota]]
*Via Antonio Canova, in [[Treviso]]

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Antonio Canova from the studio if Canova c.1813.jpg|Antonio Canova from the studio of Canova c. 1813
File:Tomb of Pope Clement XIII Gregorovius.jpg|Tomb of Clement&amp;nbsp;XIII
File:Tomb of Pope Clement XIV Gregorovius.jpg|Tomb of Clement&amp;nbsp;XIV
File:Tomb Monument of Pius VI Gregorovius.jpg|Monument to Pius&amp;nbsp;VI
File:Amor-Psyche-Canova-JBU02.JPG|''[[Psyche Revived by Cupid's Kiss]]'', Louvre
File:Amor-Psyche-Canova-JBU04.JPG|''[[Psyche Revived by Cupid's Kiss]]'', Louvre (detail)
File:Perseus Canova Pio-Clementino Inv969.jpg|''Perseus Triumphant'', Vatican
File:Antonio_Canova_Teseo_defeats_the_centaur.jpg|''Theseus Fighting the Centaur'' (1804–1819), [[Kunsthistorisches Museum]], Vienna{{NoteTag|Napoleon ordered it for the Corso in Milan; Emperor Franz I bought it for the Theseus Temple in the Volksgarten in Vienna; moved to Kunsthistorisches Museum in 1891.}}
File:Jerome &amp; Henrietta busts.jpg|Pair of portrait busts by Canova, c. 1815
File:Napoleon-Canova-London JBU01.jpg|''[[Napoleon as Mars the Peacemaker]]'', [[Apsley House]] London
File:Paolina Borghese (Canova).jpg|[[Pauline Bonaparte]] as ''[[Venus Victrix (Canova)|Venus Victrix]]'', now at the [[Galleria Borghese]]
File:Antonio Canova Cenotaph of Archduchess Maria Christina Augustinerkirche (Wien) panoramic sculpture Austria 2014 photo Paolo Villa August FOTO8412 - FOTO8425auto.jpg|Panorama of Cenotaph to [[Maria Christina, Duchess of Teschen|Maria Christina of Austria]]
File:Frith, Francis (1822-1898) - n. 2340 - Tomb of Marie Christine by Canova - Vienna.jpg|Cenotaph to [[Maria Christina, Duchess of Teschen|Maria Christina of Austria]] in the [[Augustinian Church, Vienna|Augustinerkirche]]
File:Canova-Magdalene 45 degree view.jpg|''The Penitent Magdalene'' ([[Hermitage Museum]], ex-[[Leuchtenberg Gallery]])
File:Italy, Antonio Canova Medal by Putinati.jpg|Antonio Canova Medal by Francesco Putinati
File:Canova-Three Graces 0 degree view.jpg|''[[The Three Graces (sculpture)|The Three Graces]]'', Hermitage
File:Basilica di Santa Maria dei Frari interno - Monumento di Canova.jpg|Monument to Canova in the [[Basilica di Santa Maria Gloriosa dei Frari]], designed by Canova as a [[mausoleum]] for the painter [[Titian]]
File:Canova Vue 2.tif|The bust of Lucrezia D'Este da Antonio Canova&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url = https://hvmc.com/en/auctions/mobilier-et-objets-d-art-dessins-tableaux-anciens-et-xixeme-siecle-collection-de-pendules-extreme-orient-220/antonio-canova-possagno-1757-1822-venezia-188965 |title = Hôtel des Ventes de Monte-Carlo – MOA auction }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== Notes ==
{{NoteFoot}}

== References ==
=== Citations ===
{{Reflist}}

=== Sources ===
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite CE1913 |mode=cs2 |last=Handley |first=Marie Louise Adelaide |wstitle=Antonio Canova |volume=3 }}
* {{EB1911 |mode=cs2 |last=Rossetti |first=William Michael |author-link=William Michael Rossetti |wstitle=Canova, Antonio |volume=5 |pages=204–206 }}
* {{citation |editor-last=Turner |year = 1996a |editor-first=Jane |contribution=Neo-Classical |title=The Dictionary of Art, ''Vol. XXII' |publisher=Grove's Dictionaries |location=New York |ref={{harvid|Turner|1996a}} }}.
* {{citation |editor-last=Turner |date=1996b |editor-first=Jane |contribution=Antonio Canova |title=The Dictionary of Art, ''Vol. XXII''  |publisher=Grove's Dictionaries |location=New York |ref={{harvid|Turner|1996b}} }}.
{{refend}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Antonio Canova}}
* {{cite EB9 |mode=cs2 |last=Rossetti |first=William Michael |authorlink=William Michael Rossetti  |wstitle=Antonio Canova |volume=5 |pages=24–26|short=x}}
* [https://www.flickr.com/photos/65986072@N00/458745957/ Canova's ''Three Graces'' (second version)] in the [[Victoria and Albert Museum]], London (2000). One of three [[Flickr]] photos by ketrin 1407.
* [https://www.flickr.com/photos/65986072@N00/3963111586/ Canova's ''Perseus and Medusa''] in the [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]], New York (2009). Part of [[Flickr]] set by ketrin1407.
*[http://libmma.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/compoundobject/collection/p15324coll10/id/59328/rec/1 ''Europe in the age of enlightenment and revolution''], a catalog from The Metropolitan Museum of Art Libraries (fully available online as PDF), which contains material on Canova (see index)
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20050723014633/http://www.scultura-italiana.com/Galleria/Canova%20Antonio/index.html Antonio Canova: Photo Gallery]
*[http://libweb.princeton.edu/libraries/firestone/rbsc/aids/C0770/ex49.jpg Canova's death mask at Princeton]
*[http://www.museocanova.it/menu.php?name=hom&amp;lang=uk Canova museum and plaster cast gallery]
*[http://www.alessandroronchi.net/2008/canova-exhibition-at-forli-san-domenico-museum/ Canova 2009 Exhibition in Forlì, Italy]

{{-}}
{{Canova |state = expanded }}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Canova, Antonio}}
[[Category:1757 births]]
[[Category:1822 deaths]]
[[Category:People from the Province of Treviso]]
[[Category:18th-century Italian sculptors]]
[[Category:Italian male sculptors]]
[[Category:19th-century Italian sculptors]]
[[Category:Neoclassical sculptors]]
[[Category:Members of the Royal Netherlands Academy of Arts and Sciences]]
[[Category:Artists of the Boston Public Library]]
[[Category:19th-century male artists]]</text>
      <sha1>arwsfkcqiy9hvipqasq0i0nyyqk4dsy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
