  <page>
    <title>Anne Brontë</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2029</id>
    <revision>
      <id>931270527</id>
      <parentid>931160094</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-18T00:18:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelinking 1 books for [[WP:V|verifiability]].) #IABot (v2.1alpha3</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use British English|date=August 2011}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2016}}
{{Infobox writer
| name         = Anne Brontë
| image        = AnneBronte.jpg
| alt          =
| caption      = A sketch of Anne by sister [[Charlotte Brontë|Charlotte]],&lt;br&gt;circa 1834
| pseudonym    = Acton Bell
| birth_name   =
| birth_date   = {{birth date|1820|1|17|df=y}}
| birth_place  = [[Thornton, West Yorkshire|Thornton]], [[West Riding of Yorkshire]], England
| death_date   = {{death date and age|1849|5|28|1820|1|17|df=y}}
| death_place  = [[Scarborough, North Yorkshire|Scarborough]], [[North Riding of Yorkshire]], England
| resting_place = St. Mary's Churchyard, [[Scarborough, North Yorkshire|Scarborough]]
| occupation   = Poet, novelist, governess
| nationality  = English
| citizenship  =
| education    =
| alma_mater   =
| period       = 1836–1849
| language     = English
| genre        = Fiction, poetry
| subject      =
| movement     = [[Realism (arts)|Realism]]
| notableworks = ''[[The Tenant of Wildfell Hall]]''
| spouse       =
| partner      =
| children     =
| relatives    = [[Brontë family]]
| awards       =
| signature    = Anne Brontë's signature.png
| website      =
| portaldisp   =
}}

'''Anne Brontë''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|b|r|ɒ|n|t|i}}, &lt;small&gt;commonly&lt;/small&gt; {{IPAc-en|-|t|eɪ}};&lt;ref&gt;As given by ''Merriam-Webster Encyclopedia of Literature'' (Merriam-Webster, incorporated, Publishers: Springfield, Massachusetts, 1995), p viii: &quot;When our research shows that an author's pronunciation of his or her name differs from common usage, the author's pronunciation is listed first, and the descriptor ''commonly'' precedes the more familiar pronunciation.&quot; See also entries on Anne, Charlotte and Emily Brontë, pp 175–176.&lt;/ref&gt; 17 January 1820 – 28 May 1849) was an English novelist and poet, the youngest member of the [[Brontë family|Brontë literary family]].

The daughter of [[Patrick Brontë]], a poor Irish clergyman in the [[Church of England]], Anne Brontë lived most of her life with her family at the parish of [[Haworth]] on the Yorkshire moors. She also attended a boarding school in [[Mirfield]] between 1836 and 1837. At 19 she left Haworth and worked as a governess between 1839 and 1845. After leaving her teaching position, she fulfilled her literary ambitions. She published a volume of poetry with her sisters (''[[Poems by Currer, Ellis, and Acton Bell]]'', 1846) and two novels. ''[[Agnes Grey]]'', based upon her experiences as a governess, was published in 1847. Her second and last novel, ''[[The Tenant of Wildfell Hall]]'', which is considered to be one of the first sustained [[Feminism|feminist]] novels, appeared in 1848. Like her poems, both her novels were first published under the masculine pen name of '''Acton Bell'''. Anne's life was cut short when she died of what is now suspected to be [[pulmonary tuberculosis]] at the age of 29.

Partly because the re-publication of ''The Tenant of Wildfell Hall'' was prevented by [[Charlotte Brontë]] after Anne's death, she is not as well known as her sisters. However, her novels, like those of her sisters, have become classics of [[English literature]].

==Family background==
[[File:Anne Brontë by Patrick Branwell Brontë restored.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Anne, from a group portrait by her brother [[Branwell Brontë|Branwell]]]]
Anne's father, [[Patrick Brontë]] (1777–1861), was born in a two-room cottage in Emdale, [[Loughbrickland]], [[County Down]], Ireland.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fraser 4&quot;&gt;Fraser, ''The Brontës'', p. 4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 3&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 3&lt;/ref&gt; He was the oldest of ten children born to Hugh Brunty and Eleanor McCrory, poor Irish peasant farmers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 2&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 2&lt;/ref&gt; The family surname ''mac Aedh Ó Proinntigh'' was [[Anglicisation|Anglicised]] as Prunty or Brunty.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fraser 4&quot;/&gt; Struggling against poverty, Patrick learned to read and write and from 1798 taught others. In 1802, at 25, he won a place to study theology at [[St. John's College, Cambridge]] where he changed his name, Brunty, to the more distinguished sounding Brontë. In 1807 he was ordained in the priesthood in the Church of England.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 14&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 14&lt;/ref&gt; He served as a [[curate]] first in Essex and latterly in Wellington, Shropshire. In 1810, he published his first poem ''Winter Evening Thoughts'' in a local newspaper,&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 41&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 41&lt;/ref&gt; followed in 1811 by a collection of moral verse, ''Cottage Poems''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 43&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 43&lt;/ref&gt; In 1811, he became vicar of St. Peter's Church in [[Hartshead]] in Yorkshire.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 36&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 36&lt;/ref&gt; The following year he was appointed an examiner in Classics at [[Woodhouse Grove School]], near [[Bradford]] a [[John Wesley|Wesleyan]] academy where, aged 35, he met his future wife, [[Maria Branwell]], the headmaster's niece.

Anne's mother, Maria Branwell (1783–1821), was the daughter of Thomas Branwell, a successful, property-owning grocer and tea merchant in [[Penzance]] and Anne Carne, the daughter of a silversmith.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fraser 12 -13&quot;&gt;Fraser, ''The Brontës'', pp. 12–13&lt;/ref&gt; The eleventh of twelve children, Maria enjoyed the benefits of belonging to a prosperous family in a small town. After the death of her parents within a year of each other, Maria went to help her aunt administer the housekeeping functions of the school. A tiny, neat woman aged 30, she was well read and intelligent.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fraser 15&quot;&gt;Fraser, ''The Brontës'', p. 15&lt;/ref&gt; Her strong [[Methodist]] faith attracted Patrick Brontë because his own leanings were similar.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 48&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 48&lt;/ref&gt;

Though from considerably different backgrounds, within three months Patrick Brontë and Maria Branwell were married on 29 December 1812.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fraser 16&quot;&gt;Fraser, ''The Brontës'', p. 16&lt;/ref&gt; Their first child, Maria (1814–1825), was born after they moved to [[Hartshead]]. In 1815, Patrick was appointed curate of the chapel in Market Street [[Thornton, West Yorkshire|Thornton]], near [[Bradford]]; a second daughter, Elizabeth (1815–1825), was born shortly after.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 61&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 61&lt;/ref&gt; Four more children followed: [[Charlotte Brontë|Charlotte]], (1816–1855), [[Branwell Brontë|Patrick Branwell]] (1817–1848), [[Emily Brontë|Emily]], (1818–1848) and Anne (1820–1849).

==Early life==
Anne, the youngest of the Brontë children, was born on 17 January 1820, on the outskirts of [[Bradford]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 86&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 86&lt;/ref&gt; where her father was curate and she was baptised there on 25 March 1820. Anne's father was appointed to the perpetual curacy in Haworth, a small town {{convert|7|mi|km|spell=in}} away. In April 1820, the Brontës moved into the five-roomed Haworth Parsonage which became their home for the rest of their lives.

Anne was barely a year old when her mother became ill of what is believed to have been [[uterine cancer]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 102 -104&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', pp. 102–104&lt;/ref&gt; Maria Branwell died on 15 September 1821.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fraser 28&quot;&gt;Fraser, ''The Brontës'', p. 28&lt;/ref&gt; In order to provide a mother for his children, Patrick tried to remarry, but without success.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fraser 30&quot;&gt;Fraser, ''The Brontës'', p. 30&lt;/ref&gt; Maria's sister, Elizabeth Branwell (1776–1842), moved to the parsonage, initially to nurse her dying sister, but she spent the rest of her life there raising the children. She did it from a sense of duty, but she was a stern woman who expected respect, rather than love.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fraser 29&quot;&gt;Fraser, ''The Brontës'', p. 29&lt;/ref&gt; There was little affection between her and the older children, but Anne, according to tradition, was her favourite.

In [[Elizabeth Gaskell]]'s biography of Charlotte, Anne's father remembered her as precocious, reporting that once, when she was four years old, in reply to his question about what a child most wanted, she answered: &quot;age and experience&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot; Fraser 31&quot;&gt;Fraser, ''The Brontës'', p. 31&lt;/ref&gt;

In summer 1824, Patrick sent Maria, Elizabeth, Charlotte and Emily to Crofton Hall in [[Crofton, West Yorkshire]], and subsequently to the Clergy Daughter's School at [[Cowan Bridge]] in Lancashire.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fraser 35&quot;&gt;Fraser, ''The Brontës'', p. 35&lt;/ref&gt; When his eldest daughters died of consumption in 1825, Maria on 6 May and Elizabeth on 15 June, Charlotte and Emily were immediately brought home.&lt;ref name=&quot; Fraser 31&quot;/&gt; The unexpected deaths distressed the family so much that Patrick could not face sending them away again. For the next five years, they were educated at home, largely by their father and aunt.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fraser 44-45&quot;&gt;Fraser, ''The Brontës'', pp. 44–45&lt;/ref&gt; The children made little attempt to mix with others outside the parsonage, but relied on each other for friendship and companionship. The bleak moors surrounding Haworth became their playground. Anne shared a room with her aunt; they were close, which may have influenced Anne's personality and religious beliefs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gérin 35&quot;&gt;Gérin, ''Anne Brontë'', p. 35&lt;/ref&gt;

==Education==
[[File:Anne Bronte.jpg|thumb|Anne Brontë, by [[Charlotte Brontë]], 1834]]
Anne's studies at home included music and drawing. Anne, Emily and Branwell had piano lessons from the Keighley church organist. They had art lessons from John Bradley of Keighley and all drew with some skill.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 150&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 150&lt;/ref&gt; Their aunt tried to teach the girls how to run a household, but their minds were more inclined to literature.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fraser 45&quot;&gt;Fraser, ''The Brontës'', p. 45&lt;/ref&gt; Their father's well-stocked library was a source of knowledge. They read the Bible, [[Homer]], [[Virgil]], [[Shakespeare]], [[John Milton|Milton]], [[Byron]], [[Walter Scott|Scott]], and many others; they examined articles from [[Blackwood's Edinburgh Magazine]], [[Fraser's Magazine]], and The Edinburgh Review and read history, geography and biographies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fraser 45-48&quot;&gt;Fraser, ''The Brontës'', pp. 45–48&lt;/ref&gt;

Reading fed the children's imagination. Their creativity soared after their father presented Branwell with a set of toy soldiers in June 1826. They gave the soldiers names and developed their characters, which they called the &quot;Twelves&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;The soldiers appear in ''[[The Twelve and the Genii]]'', a 1962 children's fantasy novel by [[Pauline Clarke]].&lt;/ref&gt; This led to the creation of an imaginary world: the African kingdom of &quot;[[Angria (fictional country)|Angria]]&quot; which was illustrated with maps and watercolour renderings. The children devised plots about the inhabitants of Angria and its capital city, &quot;Glass Town&quot;, later called Verreopolis or Verdopolis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 154-155&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', pp. 154–155&lt;/ref&gt;

The fantasy worlds and kingdoms gradually acquired the characteristics of the real world—sovereigns, armies, heroes, outlaws, fugitives, inns, schools and publishers. The characters and lands created by the children had newspapers, magazines and chronicles which were written in extremely tiny books, with writing so small it was difficult to read without a magnifying glass. These creations and writings were an apprenticeship for their later, literary talents.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fraser 48-58&quot;&gt;Fraser, ''The Brontës'', pp. 48–58&lt;/ref&gt;

==Juvenilia==
Around 1831, when Anne was eleven, she and Emily broke away from Charlotte and Branwell to create and develop their own fantasy world, &quot;[[Gondal (fictional country)|Gondal]]&quot;. Anne was particularly close to Emily especially after Charlotte's departure for Roe Head School, in January 1831.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fraser 52-53&quot;&gt;Fraser, ''The Brontës'', pp. 52–53&lt;/ref&gt; When Charlotte's friend [[Ellen Nussey]] visited Haworth in 1833, she reported that Emily and Anne were &quot;like twins&quot;, &quot;inseparable companions&quot;. She described Anne:
&quot;Anne, dear gentle Anne was quite different in appearance from the others, and she was her aunt's favourite. Her hair was a very pretty light brown and fell on her neck in graceful curls. She had lovely violet-blue eyes; fine pencilled eyebrows and a clear almost transparent complexion. She still pursued her studies and especially her sewing, under the surveillance of her aunt.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fraser 39&quot;&gt;Fraser, ''A Life of Anne Brontë'', p. 39&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 195&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 195&lt;/ref&gt;
Anne took lessons from Charlotte, after she returned from Roe Head. Charlotte returned to Roe Head as a teacher on 29 July 1835 accompanied by Emily as a pupil; Emily's tuition was largely financed by Charlotte's teaching. Within a few months, Emily unable to adapt to life at school was physically ill from homesickness. She was withdrawn from school by October and replaced by Anne.

Aged 15, it was Anne's first time away from home, and she made few friends at Roe Head. She was quiet and hard working and determined to stay and get the education she needed to support herself.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 237-238&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', pp. 237–238&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fraser 84&quot;&gt;Fraser, ''The Brontës'', p. 84&lt;/ref&gt; She stayed for two years, winning a good-conduct medal in December 1836, and returning home only during Christmas and summer holidays. Anne and Charlotte do not appear to have been close while at Roe Head (Charlotte's letters almost never mention her) but Charlotte was concerned about her sister's health. Sometime before December 1837, Anne became seriously ill with [[gastritis]] and underwent a religious crisis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fraser 113&quot;&gt;Fraser, ''The Brontës'', p. 113&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Moravian Church|Moravian]] minister was called to see her several times during her illness, suggesting her distress was caused, in part, by conflict with the local Anglican clergy. Charlotte wrote to her father who took Anne home where she remained while she recovered.

==Employment at Blake Hall==
[[File:Blake Hall.jpg|thumb|left|Blake Hall, illustration, reproduced from photographs taken at the end of 19th century. It was demolished in 1954.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://wessyman137.wordpress.com/2015/04/19/the-mirfield-murders-1847/|title=The Mirfield Murders  1847|date=19 April 2015|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
In 1839, a year after leaving the school and aged 19, she was seeking a teaching position. As the daughter of a poor clergyman, she needed to earn a living. Her father had no private income and the parsonage would revert to the church on his death. Teaching or working as governess for a family were among the few options available to poor but educated women. In April 1839, Anne started work as a governess for the Ingham family at Blake Hall, near [[Mirfield]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 307&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 307&lt;/ref&gt;

The children in her charge were spoilt and often disobedient.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 308&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 308&lt;/ref&gt; She had great difficulty controlling them and had little success in instilling any education. She was not empowered to inflict punishment, and when she complained about their behaviour she received no support, but was instead criticised for not being capable. The Inghams, dissatisfied with their children's progress, dismissed Anne.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 318&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 318&lt;/ref&gt; She returned home at Christmas, 1839, joining Charlotte and Emily, who had left their positions, and Branwell. The episode at Blake Hall was so traumatic that she reproduced it in almost perfect detail in her novel ''Agnes Grey''.

==William Weightman==
On her return to Haworth, she met William Weightman (1814–1842), her father's new curate, who started work in the parish in August 1839.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alexander &amp; Smith, 531&quot;&gt;Alexander &amp; Smith, '' The Oxford Companion to the Brontës'', p. 531&lt;/ref&gt; Aged 25, he had obtained a two-year licentiate in theology from the [[University of Durham]]. He was welcome at the parsonage. Her acquaintance with him parallels her writing a number of poems, which may suggest she fell in love with him&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 341&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 341&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 407&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 407&lt;/ref&gt; although there is disagreement over this possibility.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 344&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 344&lt;/ref&gt; Little evidence exists beyond a teasing anecdote of Charlotte's to Ellen Nussey in January 1842.

The source of ''Agnes Grey'''s renewed interest in poetry is, however, the curate to whom she is attracted. William Weightman aroused much curiosity. It seems clear he was a good-looking, engaging young man, whose easy humour and kindness towards the sisters made a considerable impression. It is such a character that she portrays in Edward Weston, and that her heroine Agnes Grey finds deeply appealing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gérin 138&quot;&gt;Gérin, ''Anne Brontë'', p. 138&lt;/ref&gt;

If Anne formed an attachment to Weightman it does not imply that he was attracted to her. It is possible that Weightman was no more aware of her, her sisters or their friend Ellen Nussey. Nor does it imply that Anne believed him to be interested in her. If anything, her poems suggest the opposite–they speak of quietly experienced but intensely felt emotions, hidden from others, without any indication of being requited. It is possible that an initially mild attraction to Weightman assumed increasing importance to Anne over time, in the absence of other opportunities for love, marriage and children.

Anne would have seen Weightman on her holidays at home, particularly during the summer of 1842 when her sisters were away. Weightman died of cholera in the same year.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 403&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 403&lt;/ref&gt; Anne expressed her grief for his death in her poem &quot;I will not mourn thee, lovely one&quot;, in which she called him &quot;our darling&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alexander &amp; Smith, 531&quot;/&gt;

==Governess==
[[File:Emily Brontë cropped.jpg|thumb|Disputed portrait made by [[Branwell Brontë]] about 1833; sources are in disagreement over whether this image is of Emily or Anne.&lt;ref name=&quot;Portrait&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.brontesisters.co.uk/The-Profile-Portrait-Emily-or-Anne.html|title=The Bronte Sisters - A True Likeness? - The Profile Portrait - Emily or Anne|website=www.brontesisters.co.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Anne obtained a second post as governess to the children of the Reverend Edmund Robinson and his wife Lydia, at Thorp Green Hall, a comfortable country house near [[York]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 329&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 329&lt;/ref&gt; Anne was employed at Thorp Green Hall from 1840 to 1845.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boroughbridgewalks.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2012/05/BronteTrail.pdf |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130512112951/http://www.boroughbridgewalks.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2012/05/BronteTrail.pdf |url-status=dead |archive-date=12 May 2013 |title=The Brontë Trail |publisher=oroughbridgewalks.org.uk |accessdate=9 October 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The house appeared as Horton Lodge in her novel ''Agnes Grey''. Anne had four pupils: Lydia, aged 15, Elizabeth, aged 13, Mary, aged 12, and Edmund, aged 8.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 330&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 330&lt;/ref&gt; Initially, she encountered similar problems as she had experienced at Blake Hall. Anne missed her home and family, commenting in a diary paper in 1841 that she did not like her situation and wished to leave it. Her quiet, gentle disposition did not help.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gérin 135&quot;&gt;Gérin, ''Anne Brontë'', p. 135&lt;/ref&gt; However, despite her outwardly placid appearance, Anne was determined and with experience, made a success of her position, becoming well-liked by her employers. Her charges, the Robinson girls, became lifelong friends.

For the next five years, Anne spent no more than five or six weeks a year with her family, during holidays at Christmas and in June. The rest of her time was spent with the Robinsons at Thorp Green. She was obliged to accompany them on annual holidays to [[Scarborough, North Yorkshire|Scarborough]]. Between 1840 and 1844, Anne spent around five weeks each summer at the coastal town and loved the place.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 358-359&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', pp. 358–359&lt;/ref&gt; A number of locations in Scarborough were the setting for ''Agnes Grey'''s final scenes and for Linden-Car village in ''The Tenant of Wildfell Hall''.

Whilst working for the Robinsons, Anne and her sisters considered the possibility of setting up a school. Various locations including the parsonage were considered. The project never materialised and Anne chose to return to Thorp Green. She came home on the death of her aunt in early November 1842 while her sisters were in Brussels.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 404&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 404&lt;/ref&gt; Elizabeth Branwell left a £350 legacy (equivalent to £{{formatnum:{{Inflation|UK|350|1842|r=-4}}}} in {{Inflation-year|UK}}){{Inflation-fn|UK|df=y}} for each of her nieces.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 409&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 409&lt;/ref&gt;

It was at the Long Plantation at Thorp Green in 1842 that Anne wrote her three-verse poem ''Lines Composed in a Wood on a Windy Day'', which was published in 1846 under her pen-name of Acton Bell.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.boroughbridgewalks.org.uk/?p=12 |title=The Brontë Trail |publisher=boroughbridgewalks.org.uk |year= |accessdate=9 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Anne returned to Thorp Green in January 1843 where she secured a position for Branwell. He was to take over as tutor to the Robinsons' son, Edmund, who was growing too old to be in Anne's care. Branwell did not live in the house as Anne did. Anne's vaunted calm appears to have been the result of hard-fought battles, balancing deeply felt emotions with careful thought, a sense of responsibility and resolute determination.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gérin 134&quot;&gt;Gérin, ''Anne Brontë'', p. 134&lt;/ref&gt; All three Brontë sisters worked as governesses or teachers, and all experienced problems controlling their charges, gaining support from their employers, and coping with homesickness—but Anne was the only one who persevered and made a success of her work.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oxcomp&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Alexander|first=Christine|author2=Margaret Smith|title=The Oxford Companion to the Brontës|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford|year=2003|isbn=0-19-866218-1|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/oxfordcompaniont0000unse_x4t6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Back at the parsonage==
[[File:Bronte Parsonage Museum.JPG|thumb|[[Brontë Parsonage Museum]]]]
Anne and Branwell taught at Thorp Green for the next three years. Branwell entered into a secret relationship with his employer's wife, Lydia Robinson. When Anne and her brother returned home for the holidays in June 1846, she resigned her position.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 450&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 450&lt;/ref&gt; While Anne gave no reason for leaving Thorp Green, it is thought she wanted to leave on becoming aware of the relationship between her brother and Mrs Robinson.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Ellis|first1=Samantha|title=Anne Brontë: the sister who got there first|url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2017/jan/06/anne-bronte-agnes-grey-jane-eyre-charlotte|accessdate=9 April 2018|work=The Guardian|date=6 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Branwell was dismissed when his employer found out about the relationship. Anne retained close ties to Elizabeth and Mary Robinson, exchanging letters even after Branwell's disgrace. The Robinson sisters came to visit Anne in December 1848.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 574&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 574&lt;/ref&gt;

Anne took Emily to visit some of the places she had come to know and love in the five years spent with the Robinsons. A plan to visit [[Scarborough, North Yorkshire|Scarborough]] fell through and instead the sisters went to [[York]] where Anne showed her sister [[York Minster]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 451&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 451&lt;/ref&gt;

==A book of poems==
[[File:Bronte poems2.jpg|thumb|left|170px|Poems by Currer, Ellis and Acton Bell. First edition]]

During the summer of 1845, the Brontës were at home with their father. None had any immediate prospect of employment. Charlotte came across Emily's poems which had been shared only with Anne, her partner in the world of Gondal. Charlotte proposed that they be published. Anne revealed her own poems but Charlotte's reaction was characteristically patronising: &quot;I thought that these verses too had a sweet sincere pathos of their own&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
 |url         = http://womenshistory.about.com/od/writers19th/a/brontes_by_char.htm
 |title       = About Emily Brontë and Anne Brontë, by Charlotte Brontë
 |publisher   = about.com
 |accessdate  = 8 October 2009
 |url-status     = dead
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20130226084835/http://womenshistory.about.com/od/writers19th/a/brontes_by_char.htm
 |archivedate = 26 February 2013
 |df          = dmy-all
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Eventually the sisters reached an agreement. They told neither Branwell, nor their father, nor their friends about what they were doing. Anne and Emily each contributed 21 poems and Charlotte contributed 19 and with Aunt Branwell's money, they paid to have the collection published.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oxcomp&quot;/&gt;

Afraid their work would be judged differently if they revealed they were women, the book appeared using androgynous [[pen name]]s, the initials of which were the same as their own.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 480&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 480&lt;/ref&gt; Charlotte, Emily, and Anne respectively became Currer, Ellis, and Acton Bell. ''[[Poems by Currer, Ellis, and Acton Bell]]'' was available for sale in May 1846. The cost of publication was about three-quarters of Anne's salary at Thorp Green. On 7 May 1846, the first three copies were delivered to Haworth Parsonage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 491&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 491&lt;/ref&gt; It achieved three somewhat favourable reviews, but was a dismal failure, with only two copies being sold in the first year. Anne, however, found a market for her more recent poetry. The ''Leeds Intelligencer'' and ''Fraser's Magazine'' published her poem &quot;The Narrow Way&quot; under her pseudonym, Acton Bell in December 1848. Four months earlier, in August, Fraser's Magazine had published her poem &quot;The Three Guides&quot;.

&lt;br /&gt;

==Novels==

===''Agnes Grey''===
{{Main|Agnes Grey}}
Even before the fate of the book of poems became apparent, the sisters began work on their first [[novel]]s. Charlotte wrote ''[[The Professor (novel)|The Professor]]'', Emily ''[[Wuthering Heights]]'', and Anne ''Agnes Grey''. By July 1846, a package with the three manuscripts was making the rounds of London publishers.

After a number of rejections, Emily's ''Wuthering Heights'' and Anne's ''Agnes Grey'' were accepted by the publisher [[Thomas Cautley Newby]], but Charlotte's novel was rejected by every publisher to whom it was sent.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 525&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 525&lt;/ref&gt; Charlotte was not long in completing her second novel, ''[[Jane Eyre]]'', which was immediately accepted by [[Smith, Elder &amp; Co.]] and became the first of the sisters' novels to appear in print. While Anne and Emily's novels 'lingered in the press', ''Jane Eyre'' was an immediate and resounding success. Anne and Emily were obliged to pay fifty pounds to help meet their publishing costs. Their publisher, urged on by the success of ''Jane Eyre'', published ''Wuthering Heights'' and ''Agnes Grey'' in December 1847.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 539&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 539&lt;/ref&gt; They sold well, but ''Agnes Grey'' was outshone by Emily's more dramatic ''Wuthering Heights''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 540&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 540&lt;/ref&gt;

===''The Tenant of Wildfell Hall''===
{{Main|The Tenant of Wildfell Hall}}
{{multiple image
|total_width=360
|image1=The Tenant of Wildfell Hall.jpg
|alt1=Title-page of the first edition, 1848
|caption1=Title-page of the first edition, 1848
|width1=969
|height1=1460
|image2=The Tenant of Wildfell Hall American Edition.png
|width2=969
|height2=1460
|alt2=Title-page of the first American edition, 1848
|caption2=Title-page of the first American edition, 1848&lt;ref&gt;Here Acton Bell (Anne Brontë) is mistakenly identified as the author of Wuthering Heights. [[Thomas Cautley Newby]], hoping for higher sales, purposely misled American publishers claiming that all novels from Acton, Currer and Ellis Bell were written by the same person.&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

Anne's second novel, ''[[The Tenant of Wildfell Hall]]'', was published in the last week of June 1848.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 557&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 557&lt;/ref&gt; It was an instant, phenomenal success; within six weeks it was sold out.

''The Tenant of Wildfell Hall'' is perhaps amongst the most shocking of contemporary Victorian novels. In seeking to present the truth in literature, Anne's depiction of alcoholism and debauchery was profoundly disturbing to 19th-century sensibilities. Helen Graham, the tenant of the title, intrigues Gilbert Markham and gradually she reveals her past as an artist and wife of the dissipated Arthur Huntingdon. The book's brilliance lies in its revelation of the position of women at the time, and its multi-layered plot.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.victorianweb.org/authors/bronte/abronte/downey2.html
|title=The Critics of Wildfell Hall
|publisher=www.victorianweb.org
|accessdate=8 October 2009
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

It is easy today to underestimate the extent to which the novel challenged existing social and legal structures. [[May Sinclair]], in 1913, said that the slamming of Helen Huntingdon's bedroom door against her husband reverberated throughout Victorian England.&lt;ref&gt;Brontё, Anne. ''The Tenant of Wildfell Hall''. 1848. Introduction. Winifred Gerin. New York: Penguin. 1979.&lt;/ref&gt; Anne's heroine eventually left her husband to protect their young son from his influence. She supported herself and her son by painting while living in hiding, fearful of discovery. In doing so, she violated not only social conventions, but English law. Until 1870, when the [[Married Women's Property Act 1870|Married Women's Property Act]] was passed, a married woman had no independent legal existence apart from her husband; could not own property, sue for divorce, or control custody of her children. If she attempted to live apart, her husband had the right to reclaim her. If she took their child, she was liable for kidnapping. By living on her own income she was held to be stealing her husband's property, since any property she held or income she made was legally his.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oxcomp&quot;/&gt;

In the second edition of ''The Tenant of Wildfell Hall'', which appeared in August 1848, Anne clearly stated her intentions in writing it. She presented a forceful rebuttal to critics (Charlotte was among them) who considered her portrayal of Huntingdon overly graphic and disturbing.

{{quote|When we have to do with vice and vicious characters, I maintain it is better to depict them as they really are than as they would wish to appear. To represent a bad thing in its least offensive light, is doubtless the most agreeable course for a writer of fiction to pursue; but is it the most honest, or the safest? Is it better to reveal the snares and pitfalls of life to the young and thoughtless traveller, or to cover them with branches and flowers? O Reader! if there were less of this delicate concealment of facts–this whispering 'Peace, peace', when there is no peace,&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleverse||Jeremiah|6:14|NIV}}&lt;/ref&gt; there would be less of sin and misery to the young of both sexes who are left to wring their bitter knowledge from experience.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 532&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 532&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Anne sharply castigated reviewers who speculated on the sex of the authors, and the appropriateness of their writing, in words that do little to reinforce the stereotype of Anne as meek and gentle.

{{quote|I am satisfied that if a book is a good one, it is so whatever the sex of the author may be. All novels are or should be written for both men and women to read, and I am at a loss to conceive how a man should permit himself to write anything that would be really disgraceful to a woman, or why a woman should be censured for writing anything that would be proper and becoming for a man.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 564&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 564&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==London visit==
[[File:Smith Elder Cornhill.jpg|thumb|upright|The offices of Smith, Elder &amp; Co. at No. 65 Cornhill]]
In July 1848, to dispel the rumour that the &quot;Bell brothers&quot; were all the same person, Charlotte and Anne went to London to reveal their identities to Charlotte's publisher [[George Murray Smith|George Smith]]. Emily refused to go with them. The women spent several days in his company. Many years after Anne's death, he wrote in the [[Cornhill Magazine]] his impressions of her, describing her as:
&quot;a gentle, quiet, rather subdued person, by no means pretty, yet of a pleasing appearance. Her manner was curiously expressive of a wish for protection and encouragement, a kind of constant appeal which invited sympathy.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 559&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 559&lt;/ref&gt;

The increasing popularity of the Bells' work led to renewed interest in the ''Poems by Currer, Ellis, and Acton Bell'', originally published by Aylott and Jones. The remaining print run was bought by Smith and Elder, and reissued under new covers in November 1848. It still sold poorly.

==Family tragedies==
Although Anne and her sisters were only in their late twenties, a highly successful literary career appeared a certainty for them. However, an impending tragedy was to engulf the family.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 564&quot;/&gt; Within the next ten months, three of the siblings, including Anne, would be dead.

Branwell's health had deteriorated over two years, but its seriousness was disguised by his persistent drunkenness. He died on the morning of 24 September 1848.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 568&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 568&lt;/ref&gt; His sudden death came as a shock to the family. He was aged 31. The cause was recorded as chronic bronchitis – [[marasmus]]; though it is now believed he was suffering from [[tuberculosis]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Biography of Anne Brontë&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.mick-armitage.staff.shef.ac.uk/anne/annebiog.html
|title=Biography of Anne Brontë
|publisher=www.mick-armitage.staff.shef.ac.uk
|accessdate=8 October 2009
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The family had suffered from coughs and colds during the winter of 1848, and Emily next became severely ill. She deteriorated rapidly over two months, persistently refusing all medical aid until the morning of 19 December, when, being very weak, she declared: &quot;if you will send for a doctor, I will see him now&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 576&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 576&lt;/ref&gt; It was, however, far too late. At about two o'clock that afternoon, after a hard, short conflict in which she struggled desperately to hang on to life, she died, aged 30.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 576&quot;/&gt;

Emily's death deeply affected Anne, and her grief undermined her physical health.&lt;ref&gt;Gaskell EC. The Life of Charlotte Brontë: author of 'Jane Eyre,' 'Shirley,' 'Villette,' 'The Professor,' etc., Elder Smith, 1896, p. 287 [https://archive.org/details/lifecharlottebr04gaskgoog read online or download]&lt;/ref&gt; Over Christmas, Anne caught influenza. Her symptoms intensified, and her father sent for a [[Leeds]] physician in early January. The doctor diagnosed her condition as [[tuberculosis|consumption]] (tuberculosis) and intimated that it was quite advanced, leaving little hope of recovery. Anne met the news with characteristic determination and self-control.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ann&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
 |url=http://www.annebronte.scarborough.co.uk/ 
 |title=Ann Brontë Remembered in Scarborough 
 |publisher=www.annebronte.scarborough.co.uk 
 |accessdate=23 August 2012 
 |url-status=dead 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120728073036/http://www.annebronte.scarborough.co.uk/ 
 |archivedate=28 July 2012 
}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, she expressed her frustration over unfulfilled ambitions in her letter to Ellen Nussey:

{{quote|I have no horror of death: if I thought it inevitable I think I could quietly resign myself to the prospect&amp;nbsp;... But I wish it would please God to spare me not only for Papa's and Charlotte's sakes but because I long to do some good in the world before I leave it. I have many schemes in my head for future practise–humble and limited indeed–but still I should not like them all to come to nothing, and myself to have lived to so little purpose. But God's will be done.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 592&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 592&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Unlike Emily, Anne took all the recommended medicines and followed the advice she was given.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alexander &amp; Smith, 72&quot;&gt;Alexander &amp; Smith, '' The Oxford Companion to the Brontës'', p. 72&lt;/ref&gt; That same month she wrote her last poem, &quot;A dreadful darkness closes in&quot;, in which she deals with being terminally ill.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alexander &amp; Smith, 170&quot;&gt;Alexander &amp; Smith, '' The Oxford Companion to the Brontës'', p. 170&lt;/ref&gt; Her health fluctuated as the months passed, but she progressively grew thinner and weaker.

==Death==
[[Image:Annebronte.jpg|thumb|Anne Brontë's grave at Scarborough. The flowering plants have now been replaced by a slab.]]
In February 1849, Anne seemed somewhat better.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 588&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 588&lt;/ref&gt; She decided to make a return visit to Scarborough in the hope that the change of location and fresh sea air might initiate a recovery.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 587&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 587&lt;/ref&gt; Charlotte was initially against that journey, fearing that it would be too stressful for her sister, but the doctor's approval of this plan and Anne's assurance that it was the last hope, changed her mind.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 592&quot;/&gt; On 24 May 1849, Anne said her goodbyes to her father and the servants at Haworth, and set off for Scarborough with Charlotte and [[Ellen Nussey]]. En route, they spent a day and a night in York, where, escorting Anne around in a wheelchair, they did some shopping, and at Anne's request, visited York Minster. However, it was clear that Anne had little strength left.
[[File:AnnBrontegrave.JPG|left|thumb|Memorial slab lying on the grave of Anne Brontë]]
On Sunday, 27 May, Anne asked Charlotte whether it would be easier if she returned home to die instead of remaining in Scarborough. A doctor, consulted the next day, indicated that death was close. Anne received the news quietly. She expressed her love and concern for Ellen and Charlotte, and seeing Charlotte's distress, whispered to her to &quot;take courage&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 594&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 594&lt;/ref&gt; Conscious and calm, Anne died at about two o'clock in the afternoon, Monday, 28 May 1849 at age 29.

Over the following days, Charlotte made the decision to &quot;lay the flower where it had fallen&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Biography of Anne Brontë&quot;/&gt; Anne was buried, not in Haworth with the rest of her family, but in Scarborough. The funeral was held on Wednesday 30 May which did not allow time for Patrick Brontë to make the {{convert|70|mi|km|adj=on}} journey, had he wished to do so. The former schoolmistress at Roe Head, Miss Wooler, was in Scarborough and she was the only other mourner at Anne's funeral.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 595&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 595&lt;/ref&gt; She was buried in [[St Mary's Church, Scarborough|St Mary's]] churchyard, beneath the castle walls, overlooking the bay. Charlotte commissioned a stone to be placed over her grave, with the simple inscription &quot;Here lie the remains of Anne Brontë, daughter of the Revd P. Brontë, Incumbent of Haworth, Yorkshire. She died Aged 28 May 28th 1849&quot;. When Charlotte visited the grave three years later, she discovered multiple errors on the headstone, and thus it was refaced. However, Anne's age at death was still written as 28 when, in fact, she was 29 when she died.

In 2011, the Brontë Society installed a new plaque at Anne Brontë's grave. Due to weathering and erosion, the original gravestone had become illegible at places and could not be restored. The original stone was left undisturbed, while the new plaque, laid horizontally, interpreted the fading words of the original, and also added a correction to the remaining error on the headstone (Anne's age at death).&lt;ref name=&quot;grave-0&quot;&gt;{{cite news|work=The Scarborough News |url=http://www.thescarboroughnews.co.uk/news/new-memorial-for-bronte-grave-1-4032457 |title=New memorial for Bronte grave|date=5 December 2011|accessdate=16 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April 2013, the Brontë Society held a dedication and blessing service at the gravesite to mark the installation of the new plaque.&lt;ref name=&quot;grave-2&quot;&gt;{{cite news|publisher=The Scarborough News |url=http://www.thescarboroughnews.co.uk/news/bronte-memory-will-live-on-in-scarborough-1-5640021 |title=Bronte memory will live on in Scarborough |date=2 May 2013|accessdate=16 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;grave-1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|publisher=BBC|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-22351887 |title=Anne Brontë's grave error corrected|date= 30 April 2013|accessdate=12 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reputation==
A year after Anne's death, further editions of her novels were reprinted but Charlotte prevented re-publication of ''The Tenant of Wildfell Hall''.&lt;ref name=&quot; Fraser 387&quot;&gt;Fraser, ''The Brontës'', p. 387&lt;/ref&gt; In 1850, Charlotte wrote &quot;''Wildfell Hall'' it hardly appears to me desirable to preserve. The choice of subject in that work is a mistake, it was too little consonant with the character, tastes and ideas of the gentle, retiring inexperienced writer.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker 654&quot;&gt;Barker, ''The Brontës'', p. 654&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequent critics paid less attention to Anne's work, and those such as Lane dismissed her as &quot;a Brontë without genius&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Lane|first1=Margaret|title=The Brontë Story|url=https://archive.org/details/brontstoryrecons0000lane|url-access=registration}}&lt;/ref&gt; and gave her output little consideration.

However, since the mid-20th century, with increasing critical interest in female authors, her life has been re-examined and her work re-evaluated. Her interest in the topic of education has also been explored in publications such as ''The Brontës and Education'', a Bronte Society Conference publication. Biographies by [[Winifred Gérin]] (1959), Elizabeth Langland (1989) and Edward Chitham (1991) as well as Juliet Barker's group biography, ''The Brontës'' (1994; revised edition 2000) and work by critics such as [[Inga-Stina Ewbank]], Marianne Thormählen, Laura C Berry, Jan B Gordon, Mary Summers and Juliet McMaster, has led to her acceptance, not as a minor Brontë, but as a major literary figure in her own right.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ann&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Harrison and Stanford 243—245&quot;&gt;Harrison and Stanford, ''Anne Brontë — Her Life and Work'', стр. 243—245&lt;/ref&gt; Sally McDonald of the Brontë Society said in 2013, &quot;In some ways though she is now viewed as the most radical of the sisters, writing about tough subjects such as women's need to maintain independence and how alcoholism can tear a family apart.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;grave-1&quot;/&gt; In 2016, [[Lucy Mangan]] championed Anne Brontë in the BBC's ''Being the Brontës'', declaring that &quot;her time has come&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2016/mar/23/being-the-brontes-bbc-lucy-mangan-anne-bronte|title=The forgotten genius: why Anne wins the battle of the Brontës|first=Lucy|last=Mangan|date=23 March 2016|publisher=|via=www.theguardian.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[List of feminist literature#1840s|List of feminist literature - 1840s]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|25em}}

==References==
* Alexander, Christine &amp; Smith, Margaret, ''The Oxford Companion to the Brontës'', Oxford University Press, 2006, {{ISBN|0-19-861432-2}}
* [[Juliet Barker|Barker, Juliet]], ''The Brontës'', St. Martin's Pr., {{ISBN|0-312-14555-1}}
* Chitham, Edward, ''A Life of Anne Brontë'', Oxford: Blackwell Publishers, 1991, {{ISBN|0-631-18944-0}}
* Fraser, Rebeca, ''The Brontës: Charlotte Brontë and her family'', Crown Publishers, 1988, {{ISBN|0-517-56438-6}}
* [[Winifred Gérin|Gérin, Winifred]], ''Anne Brontë'', Allen Lane, 1976, {{ISBN|0-7139-0977-3}}
* Harrison, Ada and Stanford, Derek, ''Anne Brontë – Her Life and Work'', Archon Books, 1970 (first published 1959). {{ISBN|0-208-00987-6}}

==Further reading==
* Allott, Miriam, ''The Brontës: The Critical Heritage'', 1984
* [[Juliet Barker|Barker, Juliet]], ''The Brontës'', 2000 (revised edition)
* Chadwick, Ellis, ''In the Footsteps of the Brontës'', 1982
* Chitham, Edward, ''A Life of Anne Brontë'', 1991
* Chitham, Edward, ''A Brontë Family Chronology'', 2003
* [[Terry Eagleton|Eagleton, Terry]], ''Myths of Power'', 1975
* [[Samantha Ellis|Ellis, Samantha]], ''Take Courage: Anne Brontë and the Art of Life'', 2016
* Langland, Elizabeth, ''Anne Brontë: The Other One'', 1989
* [[Winifred Gérin|Gérin, Winifred]], ''Anne Brontë: A Biography'', 1959
* [[Lucasta Miller|Miller, Lucasta]], ''The Brontë Myth'', 2001
* Scott, P. J. M., ''Anne Brontë: A New Critical Assessment'', 1983
* Summers, Mary, ''Anne Brontë Educating Parents'', 2003
* [[Thomas James Wise|Wise, T. J.]] and Symington, J. A. (eds.), ''The Brontës: Their Lives, Friendships and Correspondences'', 1932

==External links==
{{Commons}}
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Wikisource author}}
{{Library resources box|by=yes|onlinebooksby=yes|viaf=14766877}}
*[http://digital.library.upenn.edu/women/bronte/bronte-anne.html Anne Brontë's biography and works] at [http://digital.library.upenn.edu/women/ A Celebration of Women Writers]
*[http://www.annebronte.org/ Anne Brontë – Writer Of Genius], biographical materials on Anne and her family 
*[http://www.mick-armitage.staff.shef.ac.uk/anne/bronte.html Anne Brontë – The Scarborough Connection], biographical materials and complete poems of Anne Brontë
*[https://sites.google.com/a/u.northwestern.edu/anne-bronte-at-northwestern-university/ Anne Bronte at Northwestern University], information about Anne and Victorian society, critical reception of The Tenant of Wildfell Hall
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20130511082949/http://www.annebrontesgrave.co.uk/ Anne Brontë – Her grave in Scarborough]
*{{IBList |type=author|id=73|name=Anne Brontë}}
* [http://www.bronte.org.uk/ Website of the Brontë Society and Brontë Parsonage Museum in Haworth]

===Electronic editions===
* {{Gutenberg author |id=Brontë,+Anne | name=Anne Brontë}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Anne Brontë |sopt=w}}
* {{Librivox author |id=172}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120310192742/http://annebronte.com/ Anne Brontë eText Archive]
* [http://www.reelyredd.com/0307anne_bronte.htm Music On Christmas Morning] – Audio Poem

{{The Tenant of Wildfell Hall}}
{{Brontë sisters}}
{{lists of poets |state=collapsed}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bronte, Anne}}
[[Category:1820 births]]
[[Category:1849 deaths]]
[[Category:19th-century British women writers]]
[[Category:19th-century Christian universalists]]
[[Category:19th-century deaths from tuberculosis]]
[[Category:19th-century English novelists]]
[[Category:Anglican universalists]]
[[Category:Brontë family|Anne]]
[[Category:Burials in North Yorkshire]]
[[Category:Christian writers]]
[[Category:English Anglicans]]
[[Category:English Christian universalists]]
[[Category:English governesses]]
[[Category:English people of Cornish descent]]
[[Category:English people of Irish descent]]
[[Category:English women novelists]]
[[Category:English women poets]]
[[Category:Infectious disease deaths in England]]
[[Category:People from Thornton and Allerton]]
[[Category:Pseudonymous women writers]]
[[Category:Pseudonymous writers]]
[[Category:Victorian novelists]]
[[Category:Victorian women writers]]
[[Category:Women of the Victorian era]]</text>
      <sha1>h444b5p9dw6dkchztbc660ntrcwesbj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
