  <page>
    <title>Government of Barbados</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3514</id>
    <revision>
      <id>930316673</id>
      <parentid>930316663</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-11T17:37:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contribs/209.175.44.54|209.175.44.54]] to version by BarbadosCitizen. [[WP:CBFP|Report False Positive?]] Thanks, [[WP:CBNG|ClueBot NG]]. (3682018) (Bot)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">The '''Government of Barbados''' (GoB), is symbolically headed by [[Monarchy of Barbados|the monarch]], [[Elizabeth II|Queen Elizabeth II]] as Head of State.&lt;ref&gt;Constitution of Barbados: EXECUTIVE POWER (Chapter 6), Section 63. Section 63 of the Constitution says that the executive authority of Barbados shall be vested in Her Majesty the Queen&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; She is represented in the country by the [[Governor General of Barbados|Governor-General]], currently Dame [[Sandra Mason]], G.C.M.G., K.A.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.royal.gov.uk/MonarchAndCommonwealth/TheQueenandBarbados/TheQueensroleinBarbados.aspx The Queen's role in Barbados], Royal.gov.uk {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130116190456/https://www.royal.gov.uk/MonarchAndCommonwealth/TheQueenandBarbados/TheQueensroleinBarbados.aspx |date=January 16, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The country has a [[bicameral]] legislature and a political party system, based on universal adult suffrage and fair elections. The [[Senate (Barbados)|Senate]] has 21 members, appointed by the Governor-General on behalf of the monarch, 12 on the advice of the Prime Minister, two on the advice of the Leader of the Opposition, and seven at the Governor-General’s sole discretion. The [[House of Assembly (Barbados)|House of Assembly]] has 30 members, all elected.   Both houses debate all legislation.  However, the House of Assembly may override Senate's rejection of money bills and other bills except bills amending the Constitution.

Officers of each house (President and Deputy President of the Senate; Speaker, Deputy Speaker, and Chairman of Committees of the Assembly) are elected from the members of the respective houses.

In keeping with the [[Westminster system]] of governance, Barbados has evolved into an independent [[parliamentary democracy]] and [[Constitutional monarchy]], meaning that all [[political power]] rests with the Parliament under a non-political monarch as [[head of state]], which allows [[Monarchy of Barbados#stability|stability]].  Executive authority is vested in the monarch, who normally acts only on the advice of the Prime Minister and Cabinet, who are collectively responsible to Parliament.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.royal.gov.uk/MonarchAndCommonwealth/TheQueenandBarbados/Overview.aspx The Queen and the Commonwealth], Royal.gov.uk {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120229014453/https://www.royal.gov.uk/MonarchAndCommonwealth/TheQueenandBarbados/Overview.aspx |date=February 29, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Barbadian law is rooted in [[English law|English common law]], and the [[Constitution of Barbados]] implemented in 1966, is the supreme [[law of the land]].

Fundamental rights and freedoms of the individual are set out in the Constitution and are protected by a strict legal code.

The [[Cabinet (Barbados)|Cabinet]] is headed by the [[Prime Minister of Barbados|Prime Minister]], who must be an elected member of Parliament, and other ministers are appointed from either chamber by the Governor-General, as advised by the Prime Minister.

The Governor-General appoints as Leader of the Opposition the member of House of Assembly who commands the support of the largest number of members of that House in opposition to the ruling party's government.

The maximum duration of a Parliament is five years from the first sitting. There is a simultaneous dissolution of both Houses of Parliament by the Governor-General, acting on the advice of the Prime Minister.

There is an established non-political [[civil service]]. Also, there are separate constitutional commissions for the Judicial and Legal Service, the Public Service, and the Police Service.

==History==
[[File:Simplification of govt structure of Barbados.gif|thumb|right|300px|A simplified diagram of the Barbados government]]
The government has been chosen by elections since [[Barbadian general election, 1961|1961 elections]], when Barbados achieved full [[Self-governing colony|self-governance]].  Before then, the government was a [[Crown colony]] consisting of either colonial administration solely (such as the [[Executive Council (Commonwealth countries)|Executive Council]]), or a mixture of colonial rule and a partially elected assembly, such as the [[Legislative Council of Barbados|Legislative Council]].   

Since independence the [[Democratic Labour Party (Barbados)|Democratic Labour Party]] (DLP) held office 1966 to 1976, from 1986 to 1994, and from January 2008 to 2018. The [[Barbados Labour Party]] (BLP) governed from 1976 to 1986, from September 1994 – 2008 and has formed the government from 2018-Present.

== Executive branch ==
The Executive Branch of government conducts the ordinary business of government. These functions are called out by the Prime Minister and cabinet ministers. The prime minister chooses the ministers of government they wish to have in the cabinet but they are actually appointed by the governor general.

=== List of Government Ministries, Ministers and Permanent Secretaries ===
{{main|List of Ministers and Permanent Secretaries (Barbados)}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable mw-collapsible&quot;
|+
!Ministry
!Minister Responsible
!Permanent Secretary
|-
|Prime Minister's Office
|[[Mia Mottley|Hon. Mia Mottley, Q.C., M.P (Prime Minister)]]
|Ms. Alies Jordan (acting)
|-
|Ministry of the Public Service
|Hon. Mia Mottley, Q.C., M.P
|Ms. Gail Atkins
|-
|Ministry of Finance, Economic Affairs and Investment
|Hon. Mia Mottley, Q.C., M.P


Hon. Ryan Straughn, M.P (Finance)


Hon. Marsha Caddle, M.P (Economic Affairs and Investment)
|Ms. Nancy Headley (Finance)




Mr. Edison Alleyne (acting) 

Economic Affairs and Investment)
|-
|Ministry of Foreign Affairs and Foreign Trade
|Senator Dr. Jerome Walcott


Hon. Sandra Husbands, M.P (Foreign Trade)
|Ms. Simone Rudder
|-
|Office of the Attorney General and Ministry of Legal Affairs
|[[Dale Marshall (politician)|Hon. Dale Marshall, Q.C., M.P]]
|Ms. Yvette Goddard
|-
|Ministry of Education, Technological and Vocational Training
|Hon. Santia Bradshaw, M.P
|Ms. Janet Phillips 
|-
|Ministry of Home Affairs
|Hon. Edmund Hinkson, M.P
|Ms. Deborah Payne (Acting)
|-
|Ministry of Health and Wellness
|Lt. Colonel Hon. Jeffery Bostic, M.P
|Ms. June Chandler 
|-
|Ministry of Agriculture and Food Security
|Hon. Indar Weir, M.P
|Mr. Terry Bascombe (Acting) 
|-
|[[Ministry of Labour (Barbados)|Ministry of Labour and Social Partnership Relations]]
|Hon. Colin Jordan, M.P
|Mr. Alyson Forte
|-
|Ministry of Housing, Lands and Rural Development
|Hon. George Payne, Q.C., M.P


Hon. Charles Griffith, M.P (Minister in the Ministry)
|Mr. Timothy Maynard
|-
|Ministry of International Business and Industry
|Hon. Ronald Toppin, M.P
|Ms. Sonia Foster (acting) 
|-
|Ministry of Tourism and International Transport
|Hon. Kerrie Symmonds, M.P
|Ms. Donna Cadogan
|-
|Ministry of Youth and Community Empowerment
|Hon. Adrian Forde, M.P
|Ms. Yolande Howard
|-
|Ministry of People Empowerment and Elder Affairs
|[[Cynthia Y. Forde|Hon. Cynthia Forde, J.P, M.P]]
|Ms. Gabrielle Springer
|-
|Ministry of Small Business, Entrepreneurship and Commerce
|Hon. Dwight Sutherland, M.P
|Mr. Patrick McCaskie (acting) 
|-
|Ministry of Environment and National Beautification 
|Hon. Trevor Prescod, M.P
|Ms. Daphne Kellman
|-
|Ministry of Energy and Water Resources
|Hon. Wilfred Abrahams
|Ms. Francine Blackman (Acting)
|-
|Ministry of Transport, Works and Maintenance
|Hon. William Duguid, M.P


Hon. Peter Phillips, M.P (Minister in the Ministry)
|Mr. Mark Cummins (acting)
|-
|Ministry of Creative Economy, Culture and Sports
|Hon. John King, M.P
|Mr. Jehu Wiltshire 
|-
|Ministry of Maritime Affairs and the Blue Economy
|Hon. Kirk Humphrey, M.P
|Mr. Esworth Reid
|-
|Ministry of Innovation, Science and Smart Technology
|Senator Kay McConney
|Mr. Charley Browne (Acting)
|-
|Ministry of Information, Broadcasting and Public Affairs
|Senator Lucille Moe
|Ms. Sandra Phillips
|}

==Law==
The [[Constitution of Barbados]] is the supreme law of the nation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pdba.georgetown.edu/Constitutions/Barbados/barbados66.html The official Constitution of Barbados] (1966) version.&lt;/ref&gt; The Attorney General heads the independent [[judiciary]]. Historically, Barbadian law was based entirely on [[English common law]] with a few local adaptations. At the time of independence, the [[Parliament of the United Kingdom]] lost its ability to legislate for Barbados, but the existing English and British common law and statutes in force at that time, together with other measures already adopted by the [[Barbadian Parliament]], became the basis of the new country's legal system.

Legislation may be shaped or influenced by such organisations as the United Nations, the [[Organization of American States]], or other international bodies to which Barbados has obligatory commitments by treaty. Additionally, through international co-operation, other institutions may supply the Barbados Parliament with key sample legislation to be adapted to meet local circumstances before enacting it as local law.

New acts are passed by the Barbadian Parliament and require [[royal assent]] by the Governor-General to become law.

==Judicial branch ==
{{main|Judiciary of Barbados}}

The Judiciary is the legal system through which punishments are handed out to individuals who break the law. The Judiciary also settles disputes.
The Functions of The judiciary:
°To Enforce Laws
°To interpret Laws
°To conduct court hearings
°To hear court appeals

The local court system of Barbados is made up of:
*Magistrates' Courts: Covering Criminal, Civil, Domestic, Domestic Violence, and Juvenile matters. But can also take up matters dealing with Coroner's Inquests, Liquor Licences, and civil marriages. Further, the Magistrates' Courts deal with Contract and Tort law where claims do not exceed $10,000.00.&lt;ref name=&quot;court&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.lawcourts.gov.bb/Aboutus.html |title=Law Courts of Barbados |publisher=Lawcourts.gov.bb |accessdate=4 July 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090815015349/http://www.lawcourts.gov.bb/Aboutus.html |archivedate=15 August 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The [[Supreme Court of Barbados|Supreme Court]]: is made up of High Court and Court of Appeals.&lt;ref name=&quot;court&quot; /&gt;
**High Court: Consisting of Civil, Criminal, and Family law divisions.
**Court of Appeal: Handles appeals from the High Court and Magistrates' Court. It hears appeals in both the civil, and criminal law jurisdictions. It may consist of a single Justice of Appeal sitting in Chambers; or may sit as a Full Court of three Justices of Appeals.
*The [[Caribbean Court of Justice]] (CCJ), (based in [[Port of Spain]], Trinidad and Tobago), is the court of last resort (final jurisdiction) over Barbadian law. It replaced the London-based [[Judicial Committee of the Privy Council]] (JCPC). The CCJ may resolve other disputed matters dealing with the [[CARICOM Single Market and Economy|Caribbean Single Market and Economy]] (CSME).

==Perception==
[[Transparency International]] ranked Barbados as 17th place (of 179) in the world on its [[Corruption Perceptions Index]] in 2010, with only one nation scoring better in the [[Western Hemisphere|Americas]]. ([http://www.transparency.org/policy_research/surveys_indices/cpi/2010/results])

== See also ==
* [[Politics of Barbados]]
* [[Monarchy of Barbados]]
* [[Parliament of Barbados]]
* [[Prime Minister of Barbados]]
* [[Cabinet of Barbados]]
* [[List of government budgets by country]]
* [[List of countries by tax revenue as percentage of GDP]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book |last1=Dupont |first1=Jerry |authorlink1= |last2= |first2= |editor1-first= |editor1-last= |editor1-link= |others= |title=The common law abroad: constitutional and legal legacy of the British empire|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=pCX660FA5wMC&amp;lpg=PA202&amp;pg=PA199#v=onepage&amp;f=false |accessdate=5 January 2010 |edition= |series= |volume= |date= |year=2001 |month= |publisher=William S. Hein &amp; Co., Inc. |location= |isbn=0-8377-3125-9 |oclc= |doi=  |page= |pages=Pgs. 199–206|chapter= |chapterurl= |ref= |bibcode= }}

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Barbadian Prime Minister's Office.jpg|Office of the Prime Minister
File:Government Headquarters2 (Cabinet Office), Barbados.jpg|The Cabinet Office in the Government Headquarters complex 
File:Government Headquarters (Cabinet Office), Barbados.jpg|Main entrance to the Government Headquarters complex, with a statue of Sir Grantley Adams in the foreground
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== External links ==
*{{dmoz|Regional/Caribbean/Barbados/Government}}
* [http://www.gov.bb/ Barbadian Government Website]
* [http://www.photius.com/countries/barbados/government/system.html The Barbados Governmental System], Photius Coutsoukis
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110706132317/http://www.gov.bb/portal/page/portal/GISMEDIA%20CENTRENEWS%20MANAGEMENT/News%20Archive/Correct%20Forms%20Of%20Address%20Of%20Officials Barbados Government statement on the proper titles for members of Government]
*[http://www.ssa.gov/policy/docs/progdesc/ssptw/2002-2003/americas/barbados.html Social Security provided by the Government of Barbados]
*[http://www.lexadin.nl/wlg/legis/nofr/oeur/lxwebar.htm Laws of Barbados], The World Law Guide
*[http://www.wipo.int/wipolex/en/profile.jsp?code=BB Laws of Barbados], The World Intellectual Property Organization

{{Barbados topics}}
{{Americas topic|Government of|title=Governments of The Americas}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Government Of Barbados}}
[[Category:Executive branches of government|Barbados]]
[[Category:Government of Barbados| ]]
[[Category:Government ministries of Barbados| ]]
[[Category:Barbados-related lists]]</text>
      <sha1>hqy1dy7eap5xyiwa865afvs9efhhgmz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
