  <page>
    <title>Bass (sound)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3727</id>
    <revision>
      <id>933988529</id>
      <parentid>933669372</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-04T02:59:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sr3323</username>
        <id>36854118</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Added more instruments and text about the bass flute being the tenor flute</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Bass voice range.png|thumb|right|[[Bass (voice type)|Bass voice]] range.&lt;ref&gt;Benward &amp; Saker (2003). ''Music in Theory and Practice'', Vol. I, p.168. {{ISBN|978-0-07-294262-0}}.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[Image:Mozart k545 opening.svg|thumb|300px|[[Alberti bass]] in Mozart's ''Piano Sonata, K 545'' opening. {{audio|Mozart k545 opening.mid|Play}}]]

'''Bass''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|b|eɪ|s}} {{respell|BAYSS|'}}) (also called '''bottom end''')&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.emusician.com/gear/how-to-get-great-bottom-end-in-your-mix
|title=How to Get Great Bottom End In Your Mix|website=[[Electronic Musician]]|accessdate=September 14, 2019|last=Cooper|first=Michael|date=August 1, 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; describes [[Pitch (music)|tone]]s of low (also called &quot;deep&quot;) [[frequency]], [[pitch (music)|pitch]] and [[range (music)|range]] from 16 to 256&amp;nbsp;Hz (C&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; to [[middle C]]&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;) and '''bass instruments''' that produce tones in the '''low-pitched''' [[range (music)|range]] C&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;. They belong to different families of [[musical instrument|instruments]] and can cover a wide range of musical roles. Since producing low pitches usually requires a long air column or string, and for stringed instruments, a large hollow body, the string and wind bass instruments are usually the largest instruments in their families or instrument classes.

==Use in composition==
In musical compositions, such as [[song]]s and pieces, these are the lowest-pitched parts of the [[harmony]]. In [[choral music]] without instrumental accompaniment, the bass is supplied by adult male [[bass (voice type)|bass]] singers. For an accompanied choir, the bass is typically provided by [[pipe organ]] or [[piano]] (or if a choir can afford to hire one, by [[orchestra]]). In an orchestra, the [[bassline]]s are played by the [[double bass]] and [[cello]]s, [[bassoon]] or [[contrabassoon]], low [[brass instrument|brass]] such as the [[tuba]] and [[bass trombone]], and the [[timpani]] (kettledrums). In many styles of [[traditional music]] such as [[Bluegrass (music)|Bluegrass]], [[folk music|folk]], and in styles such as [[Rockabilly]] and [[big band]] and [[Bebop]] [[jazz]], the bass role is filled by the [[upright bass]]. In most [[rock music|rock]] and [[popular music|pop]] bands and in [[jazz fusion]] groups, the bass role is filled by the [[electric bass]]. In some 20th and 21st century pop genres, such as 1980s pop, [[hip hop music]] and [[Electronic Dance Music]], the bass role may be filled with a [[bass synthesizer]].

==Musical role==
When bass notes are played in a [[musical ensemble]] such an [[orchestra]], they are frequently used to provide a [[counterpoint]] or counter-[[melody]], in a [[harmony|harmonic]] context either to outline or juxtapose the progression of the [[chord (music)|chord]]s, or with [[Percussion instrument|percussion]] to underline the [[rhythm]].

===Rhythm section ===
In popular music, the bass part, which is called the &quot;[[bassline]]&quot;, typically provides harmonic and rhythmic support to the band. The bass player is a member of the [[rhythm section]] in a band, along with the [[drum kit|drummer]], [[rhythm guitar]]ist, and, in some cases, a [[keyboard instrument]] player (e.g., [[piano]] or [[Hammond organ]]). The bass player emphasizes the root or fifth of the chord in their basslines (and to a lesser degree, the third of the chord) and accents the strong beats.

==Kinds of bass harmony==
In [[classical music]], different forms of bass are: ''basso concertante'', or ''basso recitante''; the bass voice of the chorus; the bass which accompanies the softer passages of a composition, as well as those passages which employ the whole power of the ensemble, generally played by the [[violoncello]]s in orchestral music; ''contrabass'' (“under bass”), is described as that part which is performed by the [[double bass]]es; violoncellos often play the same line an octave higher, or a different melodic or rhythmic part which is not a bassline when double basses are used; ''basso ripieno''; that bass which joins in the full passages of a composition, and, by its depth of tone and energy of stroke, affords a powerful contrast to the lighter and softer passages or movements.&lt;ref name=ea&gt;{{Cite Americana|wstitle=Bass (music)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Basso continuo]] was an approach to writing music during the [[Baroque music]] era (1600-1750). With basso continuo, a written-out bassline served to set out the [[chord progression]] for an entire piece (symphony, concerto, Mass, or other work), with the bassline being played by [[pipe organ]] or [[harpsichord]] and the chords being improvised by players of chordal instruments (theorbo, lute, harpsichord, etc.).

&quot;The bass differs from other voices because of the particular role it plays in supporting and defining harmonic motion. It does so at levels ranging from immediate, chord-by-chord events to the larger harmonic organization of a entire work.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Cadwallader, Allen (1998). ''Analysis of Tonal Music: A Schenkerian Approach'', p. 45. {{ISBN|0195102320}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Instruments==
As seen in the [[musical instrument classification]] article, categorizing instruments can be difficult. For example, some instruments fall into more than one category. The [[cello]] is considered a [[tenor]] instrument in some orchestral settings, but in a [[string quartet]] it is the bass instrument. Also, the Bass Flute is actually the tenor member of the flute family even though it is called the &quot;Bass&quot; Flute.

Examples grouped by general form and playing technique include:
*'''[[Double bass]]''' from the [[viol]] or violin family (usually the instrument referred to as a &quot;bass&quot; in [[European classical music]] and [[jazz]]. Sometimes called a &quot;string bass&quot; to differentiate it from a &quot;brass bass&quot; or &quot;bass horn&quot;, or an &quot;upright bass&quot; to differentiate it from a &quot;bass guitar&quot;)
*'''[[Bass guitar]]''' and '''[[acoustic bass guitar]]''', instruments shaped, constructed and held (or worn) like guitars, that play in the bass range. The electric bass guitar is usually the instrument referred to as a &quot;bass&quot; in [[popular music|pop]] and [[rock music]].
*A '''[[bass horn]]''', such as a [[tuba]], [[Serpent (instrument)|serpent]], and [[sousaphone]] from the wind family and low-tuned versions of specific types of brass and woodwind instruments, such as [[bassoon]], [[bass clarinet]], [[Trombone#Bass trombone|bass trombone]] and [[bass saxophone]], etc. (less common usage)
*'''[[Keyboard bass]]''', a keyboard alternative to the bass guitar or double bass (e.g. the [[Fender Rhodes]] piano bass in the 1960s or 13-note MIDI keyboard controllers in the 2000s)
*'''[[Washtub bass]]''', a simple folk instrument

A [[musician]] playing one of these instruments is often known as a [[bassist]]. Other more specific terms such as 'bass guitarist', 'double bassist', 'bass player', etc. may also be used.

===Keyboards===
*[[Keyboard bass]]
*[[Pedal keyboard]]

===Percussion===
====Unpitched====
*[[Bass drum]]

====Pitched====
*[[Timpani]]

===Stringed===
*[[Double bass]]
*[[Bass guitar]]
*[[Washtub bass]]

===Wind===

==== Woodwind ====

*[[Bass oboe]]

*[[Bassoon]]
*[[Bassoon|Contrabassoon]]
*[[Bass saxophone]]
*[[Bass saxophone|Baritone Saxophone]]
*[[Bass saxophone|Bass clarinet]]
*[[Contrabass flute]] 

====Brass====
*[[Tuba]]
*[[Bass trombone]]
*[[Euphonium]]

==Music shows and dances==

With recorded music playback, for owners of 33&amp;nbsp;rpm LPs and 45&amp;nbsp;singles, the availability of loud ''and'' deep bass was limited by the ability of the [[phonograph record]] stylus to track the groove.&lt;ref name=&quot;aes.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.aes.org/e-lib/browse.cfm?elib=905 |work=AES E-Library |title=Tracking Ability Specifications for Phonograph Cartridges |last=Kogen |first=J. H. |date=October 1967 |publisher=[[Audio Engineering Society]] |accessdate=April 24, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; While some hi-fi aficionados had solved the problem by using other playback sources, such as [[Reel-to-reel audio tape recording|reel-to-reel tape players]] which were capable of delivering accurate, naturally deep bass from acoustic sources, or synthetic bass not found in nature, with the popular introduction of the compact cassette in the late 1960s it became possible to add more low frequency content to recordings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.record-producer.com/learn.cfm?a=44 |work=Record-Producer.com |publisher=Masterclass Professional Learning |date=April 12, 2007 |title=Mastering for vinyl vs. mastering for CD |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070821055003/http://www.record-producer.com/learn.cfm?a=44 |archivedate=August 21, 2007 |accessdate=April 24, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the mid-1970s, 12&quot; vinyl singles, which allowed for &quot;more bass volume&quot;, were used to record disco, reggae, dub and hip-hop tracks; dance club DJs played these records in clubs with subwoofers to achieve &quot;physical and emotional&quot; reactions from dancers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://pitchfork.com/features/oped/9667-drop-the-bass-a-case-against-subwoofers/ |title=Drop the Bass: A Case Against Subwoofers |last=Krukowski |first=Damon |date=17 June 2015 |website=pitchfork.com |publisher=Pitchfork |access-date=31 December 2018 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early 1970s, early [[disco]] [[DJ]]s sought out deeper bass sounds for their dance events. [[David Mancuso]] hired sound engineer Alex Rosner&lt;ref&gt;Brewster, Bill; Broughton, Frank. ''The Record Players: DJ Revolutionaries''. Black Cat. p. 64&lt;/ref&gt; to design additional subwoofers for his disco dance events, along with &quot;tweeter arrays&quot; to &quot;boost the treble and bass at opportune moments&quot; at his private, underground parties at [[The Loft (New York City)|The Loft]].&lt;ref&gt;Lawrence, Tim. “Beyond the Hustle: Seventies Social Dancing, Discotheque Culture and the Emergence of the Contemporary Club Dancer”. In ''Ballroom, Boogie, Shimmy Sham, Shake: A Social and Popular Dance Reader'', ed. Julie Malnig. University of Illinois Press, 2009. p. 204&lt;/ref&gt; The demand for sub-bass sound reinforcement in the 1970s was driven by the important role of &quot;powerful bass drum&quot; in disco, as compared with rock and pop; to provide this deeper range, a third crossover point from 40&amp;nbsp;Hz to 120&amp;nbsp;Hz (centering on 80&amp;nbsp;Hz) was added.&lt;ref&gt;Hill, Adam J.; Hawksford, Malcolm O. J.; Rosenthal, Adam P.; Gand, Gary. &quot;Subwoofer positioning, orientation and calibration for large-scale sound reinforcement&quot;. Audio Engineering Society Convention Paper 7981, presented at the 128th Convention, May 22–25, 2010, London, UK&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Paradise Garage]] [[discotheque]] in [[New York City]], which operated from 1977 to 1987, had &quot;custom designed 'sub-bass' speakers&quot; developed by Alex Rosner's disciple, sound engineer Richard (&quot;Dick&quot;) Long &lt;ref&gt;Brewster, Bill; Broughton, Frank. ''The Record Players: DJ Revolutionaries''. Black Cat. p. 64&lt;/ref&gt; that were called &quot;Levan Horns&quot; (in honor of resident [[DJ]] [[Larry Levan]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://pitchfork.com/features/oped/9667-drop-the-bass-a-case-against-subwoofers/ |title=Drop the Bass: A Case Against Subwoofers |last=Krukowski |first=Damon |date=17 June 2015 |website=pitchfork.com |publisher=Pitchfork |access-date=31 December 2018 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By the end of the 1970s, subwoofers were used in dance venue sound systems to enable the playing of &quot;[b]ass-heavy dance music&quot; that we &quot;do not 'hear' with our ears but with our entire body&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Lawrence, Tim. “Beyond the Hustle: Seventies Social Dancing, Discotheque Culture and the Emergence of the Contemporary Club Dancer”. In ''Ballroom, Boogie, Shimmy Sham, Shake: A Social and Popular Dance Reader'', ed. Julie Malnig. University of Illinois Press, 2009. p. 204&lt;/ref&gt; At the club, Long used four Levan bass horns, one in each corner of the dancefloor, to create a &quot;haptic and tactile quality&quot; in the sub-bass that you could feel in your body.&lt;ref&gt;Papenburg, Jens Gerrit. &quot;Enhanced Bass&quot; in ''Sound as Popular Culture: A Research Companion'', edited by Jens Gerrit Papenburg, Holger Schulze. MIT Press, 2016. p. 210&lt;/ref&gt; To overcome the lack of sub-bass frequencies on 1970s disco records (sub-bass frequencies below 60&amp;nbsp;Hz were removed during mastering), Long added a DBX 100 &quot;Boom Box&quot; [[Subharmonic synthesizer|subharmonic pitch generator]] into his system to synthesize 25&amp;nbsp;Hz to 50&amp;nbsp;Hz sub-bass from the 50 to 100&amp;nbsp;Hz bass on the records.&lt;ref&gt;Papenburg, Jens Gerrit. &quot;Enhanced Bass&quot; in ''Sound as Popular Culture: A Research Companion'', edited by Jens Gerrit Papenburg, Holger Schulze. MIT Press, 2016. p. 210&lt;/ref&gt; In the early 1980s, Long designed a sound system for the [[Warehouse (nightclub)|Warehouse]] dance club, with &quot;huge stacks of subwoofers&quot; which created &quot;deep and intense&quot; bass frequencies that &quot;pound[ed] through your system&quot; and &quot;entire body&quot;, enabling clubgoers to &quot;viscerally experience&quot; the DJs' [[house music]] mixes.&lt;ref&gt;Salkind, Micah. ''Do You Remember House?: Chicago's Queer of Color Undergrounds''. Oxford University Press, 2018 p. 60-61&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Sound System.jpg|thumb|right|200px|A crew sets up a sound system, including large bass bins, in Jamaica in 2009.]]
Deep, heavy bass is central to Jamaican musical styles such as dub and [[reggae]]. In Jamaica in the 1970s and 1980s, sound engineers for reggae [[sound system (Jamaican)|sound system]]s began creating &quot;heavily customized&quot; subwoofer enclosures by adding foam and tuning the cabinets to achieve &quot;rich and articulate speaker output below 100 Hz&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Fink, Robert. &quot;Below 100 Hz: Towards a Musicology of Bass Culture&quot;. In ''The Relentless Pursuit of Tone: Timbre in Popular Music'', eds. Fink, Robert; Latour, Melinda; Wallmark, Zachary.. Oxford University Press, 2018. p. 104-105&lt;/ref&gt; The sound engineers who developed the &quot;bass-heavy signature sound&quot; of sound reinforcement systems have been called &quot;deserving as much credit for the sound of Jamaican music as their better-known music producer cousins&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Henriques, Julian. ''Sonic Bodies: Reggae Sound Systems, Performance Techniques, and Ways of Knowing''. Bloomsbury.&lt;/ref&gt; The sound engineers for [[Stone Love Movement]] (a sound system crew), for example, modified folded horn subwoofers they imported from the US to get more of a bass reflex sound that suited local tone preferences for [[dancehall]] audiences, as the unmodified folded horn was found to be &quot;too aggressive&quot; sounding and &quot;not deep enough for Jamaican listeners&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Fink, Robert. &quot;Below 100 Hz: Towards a Musicology of Bass Culture&quot;. In ''The Relentless Pursuit of Tone: Timbre in Popular Music'', eds. Fink, Robert; Latour, Melinda; Wallmark, Zachary.. Oxford University Press, 2018. p. 104-105&lt;/ref&gt;

In Jamaican sound system culture, there are both &quot;low and high bass bins&quot; in &quot;towering piles&quot; that are &quot;delivered in large trucks&quot; and set up by a crew of &quot;box boys&quot;, and then positioned and adjusted by the sound engineer in a process known as &quot;stringing up&quot;, all to create the &quot;sound of reggae music you can literally feel as it comes off these big speakers&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/music/features/one-love-traditional-sound-systems-stringing-up-in-the-english-countryside-7932228.html |title=One love: Traditional sound systems 'stringing up' in the English countryside |last=Burrell |first=Ian |date=11 July 2012 |website=www.independent.co.uk |publisher=Independent |access-date=1 January 2019 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sound system crews hold '[[sound clash]]' competitions, where each sound system is set up and then the two crews try to outdo each other.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanley&quot;&gt;Stanley Niaah, Sonia (2010) ''DanceHall: From Slave Ship to Ghetto'', University of Ottawa Press, {{ISBN|978-0776607368}}, p. 103&lt;/ref&gt;

==Movies==
The use of subwoofers to provide deep bass in film presentations received a great deal of publicity in 1974 with the movie [[Earthquake (1974 film)|''Earthquake'']] which was released in [[Sensurround]]. Initially installed in 17 U.S. theaters, the Cerwin Vega &quot;Sensurround&quot; system used large subwoofers which were driven by racks of 500 watt amplifiers which were triggered by control tones printed on one of the audio tracks on the film. Four of the subwoofers were positioned in front of the audience under (or behind) the film screen and two more were placed together at the rear of the audience on a platform. Powerful noise energy and loud rumbling in the range of 17&amp;nbsp;Hz to 120&amp;nbsp;Hz was generated at the level of 110–120 decibels of [[Sound pressure|sound pressure level]], abbreviated dB(SPL). The new low frequency entertainment method helped the film become a box office success. More Sensurround systems were assembled and installed. By 1976 there were almost 300 Sensurround systems leapfrogging through select theaters. Other films to use the effect include the WW II naval battle epic [[Midway (1976 film)|''Midway'']] in 1976 and [[Rollercoaster (1977 film)|''Rollercoaster'']] in 1977.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.in70mm.com/newsletter/2004/69/sensurround/about.htm |title=About Sensurround |work=The 70mm Newsletter |publisher=In70mm.com |date=January 26, 2010 |accessdate=April 24, 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100209071217/http://www.in70mm.com/newsletter/2004/69/sensurround/about.htm |archivedate=February 9, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Sub bass]]
*[[Treble (sound)]]
*[[Bass clef]]
*[[Figured bass]]

==Sources==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
*{{Cite book |title = Harvard Dictionary of Music
  |last = Apel
  |first = Willi
  |authorlink = Willi Apel
  |location = Cambridge
  |publisher = [[Harvard University Press]]
  |origyear = 1969|year = 2000
  |edition = 2nd
  |isbn = 0-674-37501-7
  |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=TMdf1SioFk4C
  |accessdate = 12 February 2011
  |ref = harv
  |pages = 83–4
  |quote = Applied to instruments, the term indicates the lowest and consequently largest type of the family, e.g., bass clarinet. &lt;!--(4) --&gt;In musical composition, the lowest of the parts.
}}

==External links==
*{{Commons category-inline|Bass (sound)}}

{{Bass (sound)}}
{{Range (music)}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bass (Sound)}}
[[Category:Bass (sound)| ]]
[[Category:Contrabass instruments]]</text>
      <sha1>3v30sbr5846jbvcl3031jgb8xo7tu3j</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
