  <page>
    <title>Burning glass</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3729</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939156508</id>
      <parentid>929701967</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-04T18:41:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lord Belbury</username>
        <id>32990417</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* History */ add image</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Priestley Burning Lens Replica.jpg|thumb|A replica (on a smaller scale) of the burning lens owned by [[Joseph Priestley]], in his laboratory]]
A '''burning glass''' or '''burning lens''' is a large [[Biconcave lens|convex lens]] that can concentrate the [[sun]]'s rays onto a small area, heating up the area and thus resulting in [[Combustion|ignition]] of the exposed surface. '''Burning mirrors''' achieve a similar effect by using reflecting surfaces to focus the light. They were used in 18th-century chemical studies for burning materials in closed glass vessels where the products of [[combustion]] could be trapped for analysis. The burning glass was a useful contrivance in the days before electrical ignition was easily achieved.

==History==
[[File:OrbisPictus b 162.jpg|thumb|1658 illustration depicting the sun's rays being focused to start a fire]]
Burning glass technology has been known since antiquity, as described by Greek and Roman writers who recorded the use of lenses to start fires for various purposes. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title= Greek and Roman Technology: A Sourcebook of Translated Greek and Roman Texts |last1= Sherwood |first1= Andrew N. |last2= Nikolic |first2= Milorad |last3= Humphrey |first3= John W.|last4= Oleson |first4= John P. |year= 2019 |publisher= [[Routledge]] |page=25 |isbn= 978-1138927896}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pliny the Elder]] noted the use of glass vases filled with water to create a heat intense enough to ignite clothing, as well as concave lenses that were used to [[cauterize]] wounds. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1= Plantzos |first1= Dimitris |date= 1997 |title= Crystals and Lenses in the Graeco-Roman World |journal= American Journal of Archaeology |volume=101 |issue=3 |pages=451-464 |doi=10.2307/507106}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Plutarch]]'' refers to a burning mirror made of joined triangular metal mirrors installed at the temple of the [[Vestal Virgins]]. [[Aristophanes]] mentions the burning lens in his play ''[[The Clouds]]'' (424 BC).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://classics.mit.edu/Aristophanes/clouds.html |title=The Clouds |author=Aristophanes |website=The Internet Classics Archive |publisher=Daniel C. Stevenson, Web Atomics |access-date=21 February 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:&quot;Strepsiades. Have you ever seen a beautiful, transparent stone at the druggists', with which you may kindle fire?&quot;

[[Archimedes]], the renowned mathematician, was said to have used a burning glass as a weapon in 212 BC, when [[Syracuse, Sicily|Syracuse]] was besieged by [[Marcus Claudius Marcellus]]. The [[Roman Navy|Roman fleet]] was supposedly incinerated, though eventually the city was taken and Archimedes was slain.&lt;ref&gt;Meijer, Fik (1986), A History of Seafaring in the Classical World, Routledge, {{ISBN|978-0-7099-3565-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The legend of Archimedes gave rise to a considerable amount of research on burning glasses and lenses until the late 17th century. Various researchers worked with burning glasses, including [[Anthemius of Tralles]] (6th century AD), Proclus (6th century)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The table book: or, Daily recreation and information concerning remarkable men, manners, times, seasons, solemnities, merry-makings, antiquities and novelties, forming a complete history of the year|last=Hone|first=William|publisher=William Tegg and Co|year=1857|isbn=|location=London|pages=813}}&lt;/ref&gt; (who by this means purportedly destroyed the fleet of [[Vitalian (general)|Vitalian]] besieging [[Constantinople]]), [[Ibn Sahl (mathematician)|Ibn Sahl]] in his ''On Burning Mirrors and Lenses'' (10th century), [[Ibn al-Haytham|Alhazen]] in his ''[[Book of Optics]]'' (1021),&lt;ref&gt;Roshdi Rashed (1990), &quot;A Pioneer in Anaclastics: Ibn Sahl on Burning Mirrors and Lenses&quot;, ''[[Isis (journal)|Isis]]'' '''81''' (3), p. 464-491 [464-468].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Roger Bacon]] (13th century), [[Giambattista della Porta]] and his friends (16th century), [[Athanasius Kircher]] and [[Gaspar Schott]] (17th century), and the [[Georges-Louis Leclerc, Comte de Buffon|Comte de Buffon]] in 1740 in Paris.

The pop science TV program ''[[MythBusters]]'' attempted to model Archimedes' feat by using mirrors to ignite a small wooden boat covered with tar, with little success—they found it too difficult to focus light from their hand-held mirrors onto a point small enough to ignite the boat. However, an episode of [[Richard Hammond's Engineering Connections]] relating to the [[Keck Observatory]] (whose reflector glass is based on the Archimedes' Mirror) did successfully use a much smaller curved mirror to burn a wooden model, though not made of the same quality of materials as in the ''MythBusters'' effort.

[[File:Lentilles ardentes Lavoisier.png|360px|thumb|&lt;center&gt;Lavoisier with French Academy of Sciences' ''lentilles ardentes''&lt;/center&gt;]]

Burning lenses were used both by [[Joseph Priestley]] and [[Antoine Lavoisier]] in their experiments to obtain oxides contained in closed vessels under high temperatures. These  included carbon dioxide by burning diamond, and [[Mercury(II) oxide|mercuric oxide]] by heating [[Mercury (element)|mercury]]. This type of experiment contributed to the discovery of [[Phlogiston theory|&quot;dephlogisticated air&quot;]] by Priestley, which became better known as oxygen, following Lavoisier's investigations.&lt;ref&gt;Joseph Priestley, ''Experiments and Observations on Different Kinds of Air'' [[books.google.com/books?id=rk4TaRQTY7cC|Vol.2]] (1776)&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1796, during the [[French Revolution]] and three years after the declaration of war between France and Great Britain, [[Étienne-Gaspard Robert]] met with the French government and proposed the use of mirrors to burn the invading ships of the British [[Royal Navy]].  They decided not to take up his proposal.&lt;ref name=&quot;PreCinema&quot;&gt;Burns, Paul.  &quot;[http://www.precinemahistory.net/1750.htm The History of The Discovery of Cinematography: Chapter Six 1750-1799]&quot;.  Accessed 29 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Chapter 17 of [[William Bates (physician)|William Bates]]' 1920 book ''Perfect Sight Without Glasses'', in which the author argues that observation of the sun is beneficial to those with poor vision, includes a figure of somebody ''&quot;Focussing the Rays of the Sun Upon the Eye of a Patient by Means of a Burning Glass.&quot;''&lt;ref name=&quot;BatesChap17&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last=Bates | first=William H. | title=Perfect Sight Without Glasses | year=1920 | chapter = Chapter 17: Vision Under Adverse Conditions a Benefit to the Eye | pages=183–197 | publisher=New York: Central Fixation Publish Co. | chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=Vl3SiyXmZVMC&amp;pg=PA183&amp;cad=0_0 | isbn=88-900756-3-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Current use==
Burning glasses (often called '''fire lenses''') are still used to light fires in outdoor and primitive settings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.primitivefire.com/Fire-Glass_c_1.html |title=Fire Glass |publisher=Primitivefire.com |date= |accessdate=2012-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Large burning lenses sometimes take the form of [[Fresnel lens]]es, similar to [[lighthouse]] lenses,&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 | journal = Proceedings of the Engineers' Society of Western Pennsylvania
 | title = Light House Lenses
 | author = George A. Macbeth
 | year = 1914
 | page = 245
 | volume = 30
 | url = https://books.google.com/?id=rFTOAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=RA1-PA245&amp;dq=fresnel+%22burning+glass%22&amp;q=fresnel%20%22burning%20glass%22
 }}&lt;/ref&gt; including those for use in [[solar furnace]]s.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
 | title = Solar Energy: Fundamentals and Applications
 | author = H. P. Garg, J. Prakash
 | publisher = Tata McGraw-Hill Education
 | year = 2000
 | isbn = 9780074636312
 | page = 305
 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=-v_LfcIdJxIC&amp;lpg=PA305&amp;dq=lens%20solar%20furnace&amp;pg=PA305#v=onepage&amp;q=lens%20solar%20furnace&amp;f=false
 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Solar furnaces are used in industry to produce extremely high temperatures without the need for fuel or large supplies of electricity. They sometimes employ a large [[Parabolic reflector|parabolic]] array of mirrors (some facilities are several stories high) to focus light to a high intensity.
[[File:Flat flexible plastic sheet lens.JPG|thumb|240px|Close-up view of a flat [[Fresnel lens]]. This thin, light weight, non fragile and low cost lens can be used as burning-glass in emergency situations.]]
The [[Olympic torch]] that is carried around the host country of the [[Olympic Games]] is lit by a burning glass, at the site of ancient [[Olympia, Greece|Olympia]] in [[Greece]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.london2012.com/torch-relay/history/ |publisher=London 2012 Olympic Games |title=Olympic Torch Relay history |url-status=live |accessdate=27 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Diocles (mathematician)]]
* [[Nimrud lens]]
* [[Pyreliophorus]]
* [[Visby lenses]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*Temple, Robert. ''The Crystal Sun'', {{ISBN|0-7126-7888-3}}.

{{Firelighting}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Burning Glass}}
[[Category:Magnifiers]]
[[Category:Lenses]]
[[Category:Ancient weapons]]</text>
      <sha1>ltby6jdy4s4w1fkgd4b8lcjbdjwzii2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
