  <page>
    <title>Beacon</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3731</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942586597</id>
      <parentid>942529188</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-25T16:05:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Magic links bot</username>
        <id>30707369</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Replace [[Help:Magic links|magic links]] with templates per [[Special:Permalink/772743896#Future of magic links|local RfC]] and [[:mw:Requests for comment/Future of magic links|MediaWiki RfC]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses|Beacon (disambiguation)}}
A '''beacon''' is an intentionally conspicuous device designed to attract attention to a [[Geodetic datum|specific location]]. A common example is the [[lighthouse]], which provides a fixed location that can be used to navigate around obstacles or into port. More modern examples include a variety of [[radio beacon]]s that can be read on [[radio direction finder]]s in all weather, and [[Transponder|radar transponder]]s that appear on [[radar]] displays.

Beacons can also be combined with semaphoric or other indicators to provide important [[information]], such as the status of an airport, by the colour and rotational pattern of its [[aerodrome beacon|airport beacon]], or of pending weather as indicated on a [[weather beacon]] mounted at the top of a tall building or similar site. When used in such fashion, beacons can be considered a form of [[Telegraph#Optical telegraph|optical telegraphy]].

== For navigation ==
[[File:Beacon at Orontes Bank.jpg|right|thumb|A navigational beacon denoting the presence of Orontes Bank off [[Port Vincent, South Australia]].]]

Beacons help guide [[navigation|navigators]] to their destinations. Types of navigational beacons include [[radar]] reflectors, [[radio beacons]], sonic and visual signals. Visual beacons range from small, single-pile structures to large [[lighthouse]]s or light stations and can be located on land or on water. Lighted beacons are called ''lights''; unlighted beacons are called ''[[Day beacon|daybeacon]]s''. [[Aerodrome beacon]]s are used to indicate locations of airports and helipads.

Handheld beacons are also employed in [[aircraft marshalling]], and are used by the marshal to deliver instructions to the crew of aircraft as they move around an active airport, heliport or aircraft carrier.

== For defensive communications (historical) ==
[[File:Culmstock, Culmstock Beacon - geograph.org.uk - 213525.jpg|thumb|left|16th-century beacon hut in Culmstock, Devon, England]]

Classically, beacons were fires lit at well-known locations on hills or high places, used either as [[lighthouse]]s for [[navigational aid|navigation at sea]], or for signalling over land that enemy troops were approaching, in order to alert defenses. As signals, beacons are an ancient form of [[optical telegraph]] and were part of a [[relay league]].

Systems of this kind have existed for centuries over much of the world. The ancient Greeks called them ''[[phryctoriae]]'', while  beacons figure on several occasions on the [[column of Trajan]].

In ancient China, sentinels on and near the [[Great Wall|Great Wall of China]] used a sophisticated system of daytime smoke and nightime flame to send signals along long chains of beacon towers.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.travelchinaguide.com/china_great_wall/construction/tower/&lt;/ref&gt;

Legend has it that Zhōu Yōu Wáng, king of the Western Zhou dynasty, played a trick multiple times in order to amuse his often melancholy concubine, ordering beacon towers lit to fool his Marquess and soldiers. At some point, friends became enemies and when enemies, led by [[Shēnhóu|Marquess of Shen]] really arrived at the wall.  But this time, when the towers were lit, no defenders came, leading to Yōu's death and the colapse of the Western Zhou dynasty.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.travelchinaguide.com/china_great_wall/construction/tower/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cambridge History of Ancient China, 1999, pages 546 and 551&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Giles, Herbert A. (1912). The Civilization of China. Tutis Digital Publishing. {{ISBN|81-320-0448-5}}. Chapter 1&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 10th century, during the [[Arab–Byzantine wars]], the [[Byzantine Empire]] used a [[Byzantine beacon system|beacon system]] to transmit messages from the border with the [[Abbasid Caliphate]], across [[Anatolia]] to the [[Great Palace of Constantinople|imperial palace]] in the Byzantine capital, [[Constantinople]]. It was devised by [[Leo the Mathematician]] for Emperor [[Theophilos (emperor)|Theophilos]], but either abolished or radically curtailed by Theophilos' son and successor, [[Michael III]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ODB&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia | last = Foss | first = Clive | authorlink=  | title = Beacon | editor-last=Kazhdan | editor-first=Alexander | editor-link=Alexander Kazhdan |year=1991 | encyclopedia =[[The Oxford Dictionary of Byzantium]] | publisher=Oxford University Press |isbn=978-0-19-504652-6 | pages=273–274}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beacons were later used in Greece as well, while the surviving parts of the beacon system in Anatolia seem to have been reactivated in the 12th century by Emperor [[Manuel I Komnenos]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ODB&quot; /&gt;

In Scandinavia many [[hill fort]]s were part of beacon networks to warn against invading pillagers. In Finland, these beacons were called ''vainovalkeat'', &quot;persecution fires&quot;, or ''vartiotulet'', &quot;guard fires&quot;, and were used to warn Finn settlements of imminent raids by the Vikings.

In [[Wales]], the [[Brecon Beacons]] were named for beacons used to warn of approaching English raiders. In England, the most famous examples are the beacons used in [[Elizabethan England]] to warn of the approaching [[Spanish Armada]]. Many hills in England were named Beacon Hill after such beacons. In England the authority to erect beacons originally lay with the King and later was deligated to the [[List of Lord High Admirals (United Kingdom)|Lord High Admiral]]. The money due for the maintenance of beacons was called ''Beaconagium'' and was levied by the sheriff of each county.&lt;ref&gt;''The National Cyclopaedia of Useful Knowledge'', Vol III, (1847) Charles Knight, London, p.25.&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Scottish border]]s country, a system of beacon fires was at one time established to warn of incursions by the English. [[Hume Castle|Hume]] and Eggerstone castles and Soltra Edge were part of this network.&lt;ref&gt;Ritchie, Leitch (1835). ''Scott and Scotland''. London: Longman, Rees, Orme, Brown, Green, and Longman, p. 53&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Great Wall of China]] is also a beacon network.

In Spain, the border of [[Granada]] in the territory of the [[Crown of Castile]] had a complex beacon network to warn against Moorish raiders and military campaigns.&lt;ref&gt;Els almogávers a la frontera amb el sarrains en el segle XIV. Maria Teresa Ferrer&lt;/ref&gt;

== On vehicles ==
{{Main|Emergency vehicle lighting}}
[[File:Beacon positions.jpg|thumb|Beacon positions on police car]]

Vehicular beacons are rotating or flashing lights affixed to the top of a vehicle to attract the attention of surrounding vehicles and pedestrians. [[Emergency vehicle]]s such as fire engines, ambulances, police cars, tow trucks, construction vehicles, and snow-removal vehicles carry beacon lights.

The color of the lamps varies by jurisdiction; typical colors are blue and/or red for police, fire, and medical-emergency vehicles; amber for hazards (slow-moving vehicles, wide loads, tow trucks, security personnel, construction vehicles, etc.); green for volunteer firefighters or for medical personnel, and violet for funerary vehicles. Beacons may be constructed with [[Automotive lamp types|halogen bulbs]] similar to those used in vehicle [[headlamp]]s, xenon [[flashtube]]s, or [[Light emitting diode|LEDs]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
 |title=Evaluation of Light-Emitting Diode Beacon Light Fixtures 
 |journal=Lighting Research Center – Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute 
 |date=December 2009 
 |first=John 
 |last=Bullough 
 |author2=Nicholas P Skinner 
 |url=https://www.dot.ny.gov/divisions/engineering/technical-services/trans-r-and-d-repository/LRCBeaconReport.pdf 
 |format=PDF 
 |accessdate=2010-06-05 
 |url-status=dead 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130729142629/https://www.dot.ny.gov/divisions/engineering/technical-services/trans-r-and-d-repository/LRCBeaconReport.pdf 
 |archivedate=2013-07-29 
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Incandescent and xenon light sources require the vehicle's engine to continue running to ensure that the battery is not depleted when the lights are used for a prolonged period. The low power consumption of LEDs allows the vehicle's engine to remain turned off while the lights operate nodes.

== Other uses ==
Beacons and [[bonfire]]s are also used to mark occasions and celebrate events.

The Mishna describes a system of fire beacons used by the high court in [[Jerusalem]] to communicate the declaration of a new month to Jews in Israel and Babylon.&lt;ref&gt;Mishna Rosh Hashana 2:1-3&lt;/ref&gt;

Beacons have also allegedly been abused by [[Wrecking (shipwreck)|shipwreckers]]. An illicit fire at a wrong position would be used to direct a ship against [[shoal]]s or [[beach]]es, so that its cargo could be looted after the ship sank or ran aground. There are, however, no historically substantiated occurrences of such intentional shipwrecking.

In wireless networks, a [[Electric beacon#IEEE 802.11 Wi-Fi beacons|beacon]] is a type of [[Frame (networking)|frame]] which is sent by the access point (or WiFi router) to indicate that it is on.

Bluetooth based beacons periodically send out a data packet and this could be used by software to identify the beacon location. This is typically used by [[indoor positioning system|indoor navigation and positioning]] applications.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://kontakt.io/beacon-basics/what-is-a-beacon/ |title=What is a Beacon? - Beacon Basics |website=Kontakt.io |date=2016-09-20 |accessdate=2017-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Beaconing'' is the process that allows a network to self-repair network problems. The stations on the network notify the other stations on the ring when they are not receiving the transmissions. Beaconing is used in Token ring and FDDI networks.

=== In fiction ===
In [[Aeschylus]]' tragedy ''[[Oresteia|Agamemnon]]'',&lt;ref&gt;v. 281 ''et sqq.''&lt;/ref&gt; a chain of eight beacons manned by so-called ''lampadóphoroi'' inform [[Clytemnestra]] in [[Argos]], within a single night's time, that [[Troy]] has just fallen under her husband king Agamemnon's control, after a famous [[Trojan War|ten years siege]].

In [[J. R. R. Tolkien]]'s [[high fantasy]] novel, ''[[The Lord of the Rings]]'', a [[Warning beacons of Gondor|series of beacons]] alerts the entire realm of [[Gondor]] when the kingdom is under attack. These beacon posts were manned by messengers who would carry word of their lighting to either [[Rohan (Middle-earth)|Rohan]] or [[Belfalas]].&lt;ref name=TolkienLotR&gt;{{cite book|last=Tolkien|first=J. R. R.|title=The Lord of the Rings (50th Anniversary Edition)|year=2004|publisher=Houghton Mifflin Company|volume=''[[The Return of the King]]''|pages=747–748}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In [[Peter Jackson]]'s [[The Lord of the Rings: The Return of the King|film adaptation of the novel]], the beacons serve as a connection between the two realms of Rohan and Gondor, alerting one another directly when they require military aid, as opposed to relying on messengers as in the novel.

=== In retail ===
Beacons are sometimes used in retail to send digital coupons or invites to customers passing by.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Peter Lewis |url=https://www.thinkwithgoogle.com/articles/retail-marketing-beacon-technology.html |title=How Beacons Can Reshape Retail Marketing – Think with Google |website=Thinkwithgoogle.com |date=2016-08-19 |accessdate=2017-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;ELON JOURNAL OF UNDERGRADUATE RESEARCH IN COMMUNICATIONS
2015, VOL. 6 NO. 1&lt;/ref&gt;

==Types==
=== Infrared beacon ===
{{Expand section|date=June 2008}}

An infrared beacon (IR beacon) transmits a modulated light beam in the infrared spectrum, which can be identified easily and positively. A line of sight clear of obstacles between the transmitter and the receiver is essential. IR beacons have a number of applications in [[robotics]] and in ''[[Combat Identification]]'' (CID).

Infrared beacons are the key infrastructure for the Universal Traffic Management System (UTMS) in Japan. They perform two-way communication with travelling vehicles based on highly directional infrared communication technology and have a vehicle detecting capability to provide more accurate traffic information.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url=http://www.utms.or.jp/english/beacon/index.html
| publisher=Universal Traffic Management Society of Japan
| title=Infrared Beacon Overview
| accessdate=2008-04-27
| year=2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A contemporary military use of an Infrared beacon is reported in [[Operation Acid Gambit]].

=== Sonar beacon ===
{{Expand section|date=September 2012}}
A sonar beacon is an underwater device which transmits sonic or ultrasonic signals for the purpose of providing bearing information. The most common type is that of a rugged watertight sonar transmitter attached to a submarine and capable of operating independently of the electrical system of the boat. It can be used in cases of emergencies to guide salvage vessels to the location of a disabled submarine.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.elac-nautik.de/_uploads/images/pdf/L-3%20ELAC%20Nautik%20SBE.pdf The ELAC SBE distress sonar beacon]&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Aerodrome beacon]]
* [[Beacon mode service]]
* [[Beacon School]]
* [[Belisha beacon]]
* [[Emergency locator beacon]]
* [[Emergency position-indicating radiobeacon station]] (ELTs, PLBs &amp; EPIRBs)
* [[iBeacon]]
* [[Lantern]]
* [[Leading lights]]
* [[Lighthouse of Alexandria]]
* [[Milestone]]/[[Kilometric point]]
* [[Polaris]]
* [[Strobe beacon]]
* [[Time ball]]
* [[Trail blazing]]
* [[Warning light (disambiguation)]]
* [[Weather beacon]]
* [[Web beacon]]
* [[Beacon Cloud Software]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Morse code}}
{{Telecommunications}}

[[Category:Beacons| ]]
[[Category:Optical communications]]</text>
      <sha1>bbtapduf70eyelkbyeirfcj4c5vxrmi</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
