  <page>
    <title>British Isles</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3736</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942313951</id>
      <parentid>940328523</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-23T23:01:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jdperkins</username>
        <id>13967204</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Group of islands in northwest Europe}}
{{Use British English|date=August 2010}}&lt;!--THIS ARTICLE USES BRITISH ENGLISH because this topic is British related. Please do not edit the British English spelling to American English spelling. The use of &quot;are&quot; in place of &quot;is&quot; in certain instances is considered grammatically correct. See [[American and British English differences#Formal and notional agreement]] for more information--&gt;
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{About|the geographic archipelago|those parts under British sovereignty|British Islands}}
{{Infobox islands
|local_name = 
 {{collapsible list
  |titlestyle = background:transparent; text-align:center; font-size:9pt;
  |liststyle = text-align:center;
  |title = Other native names
  |1 = {{native name|sco|Breetish Isles}}
  |2 = {{native name|cy|Ynysoedd Prydain}}
  |3 = {{native name|kw|Enesow Bretennek}}
  |4 = {{native name|ga|Éire agus an Bhreatain Mhór}}&lt;ref name=tearma&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.tearma.ie/Search.aspx?term=the+British+Isles | title = the British Isles | work = téarma.ie – Dictionary of Irish Terms | publisher = [[Foras na Gaeilge]] and [[Dublin City University]] | accessdate = 18 Nov 2016 | quote = the British Isles ''s'' ''pl'' (Tíreolaíocht · Geography; Polaitíocht · Politics; Stair · History; Logainmneacha » Ceantar/Réigiún · Placenames » Area/Region) Na hOileáin bhriontanacha}}&lt;/ref&gt;
  |5 = {{native name|gd|Eileanan Bhreatainn}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|url=http://www.gla.ac.uk/departments/celtic/duilleagangidhlig/|title=University of Glasgow Department of Celtic}}&lt;/ref&gt;
  |6 = {{native name|gv|Ny h-Ellanyn Goaldagh}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|url=http://www.tynwald.org.im/papers/press/2008/pr33.pdf|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090224221228/http://www.tynwald.org.im/papers/press/2008/pr33.pdf|url-status=dead|archive-date=2009-02-24|title=Office of The President of Tynwald}}&lt;/ref&gt;
  |7 = {{native name|fr|Îles Britanniques}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Règlement (1953) (Amendement) Sur l'importation et l'exportation d'animaux|url=http://www.jerseylaw.je/Law/display.aspx?url=lawsinforce%2fhtm%2fLawFiles%2f1950-1959%2fJersey_Law_17-1953.htm|publisher=States of Jersey|accessdate=2 February 2012|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160129030623/http://www.jerseylaw.je/Law/display.aspx?url=lawsinforce%2fhtm%2fLawFiles%2f1950-1959%2fJersey_Law_17-1953.htm|archive-date=29 January 2016|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 }}
|image_name = MODIS - Great Britain and Ireland - 2012-06-04 during heat wave.jpg
|image_caption = Satellite image, excluding [[Shetland]] and the [[Channel Islands]] (out of frame)
|image_alt = A map of the British Isles and their location in Europe.
|map_image = British Isles (orthographic projection).svg
|map_size = 220
|location = North-western [[Europe]]
|coordinates = {{Coord|54|N|4|W|scale:10000000|display=inline,title}}
|waterbody = [[Atlantic Ocean]]
|area_km2 = 315159
|area_footnotes = &lt;ref name=area&gt;[http://islands.unep.ch/Cindex.htm Country/Territory Index, Island Directory], United Nations Environment Programme. Retrieved 9 August 2015.&lt;br /&gt;[https://www.gov.im/categories/business-and-industries/iom-key-facts-guide/island-facts/ Island Facts] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304050532/https://www.gov.im/categories/business-and-industries/iom-key-facts-guide/island-facts/ |date=4 March 2016 }}, Isle of Man Government. Retrieved 9 August 2015.&lt;br /&gt;According to the UNEP, the Channel Islands have a land area of 194 km², the Republic of Ireland has a land area of 70,282 km², and the United Kingdom has a land area of 244,111 km². According to the Isle of Man Government, the Isle of Man has a land area of 572 km². Therefore, the overall land area of the British Isles is 315,159 km²&lt;/ref&gt;
|total_islands = 6,000+
|highest_mount = {{nowrap|[[Ben Nevis]]}}&lt;ref name=highestpoint&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/blog/2016/03/britains-tallest-mountain-is-taller/|title=Great Britain’s tallest mountain is taller - Ordnance Survey Blog|date=2016-03-18|work=Ordnance Survey Blog|access-date=2018-09-09|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|elevation_m = 1345
|population = 71,891,524
|population_as_of = 2019
|population_footnotes = &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = https://esa.un.org/unpd/wpp/Download/Standard/Population/ |title = World Population Prospects 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|density_km2 = 216
|languages = [[Auregnais]], [[Cornish language|Cornish]], [[English language|English]], [[French language|French]], [[Guernésiais]], [[Irish language|Irish]], [[Jèrriais]], [[Manx language|Manx]], [[Scots language|Scots]], [[Scottish Gaelic]], [[Sercquiais]], [[Shelta]], [[Ulster Scots dialects|Ulster-Scots]], [[Welsh language|Welsh]]
|timezone1 = [[Greenwich Mean Time]] / [[Western European Time]]
|utc_offset1 = ±0{{!}}UTC
|timezone1_DST  = [[Western European Summer Time]]{{ref label|footnote_a|a}}
|utc_offset1_DST  = +1
|additional_info  = {{Infobox |child=yes |label1 = Drives on the |data1 = left }}
|footnotes = {{Ordered list|list_style_type=lower-alpha|item_style=font-size:90%;
  |{{note|footnote_a}} [[Irish Standard Time]] in the Republic of Ireland, [[British Summer Time]] in the United Kingdom and associated territories.
 }}
}}
The '''British Isles''' are a [[archipelago|group of islands]] in the North [[Atlantic Ocean|Atlantic]] off the north-western coast of [[continental Europe]], consisting of the islands of [[Great Britain]], [[Ireland]], the [[Isle of Man]], the [[Hebrides]] and over six thousand smaller isles.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;&quot;British Isles&quot;, ''[[Encyclopædia Britannica]]''&lt;/ref&gt; They have a total area of about {{Convert|315159|km2||abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=area/&gt; and a combined population of almost 72 million, and include two [[sovereign state]]s, the [[Republic of Ireland]] (which covers roughly five-sixths of Ireland),&lt;ref&gt;The diplomatic and constitutional name of the Irish state is simply ''Ireland''. For disambiguation purposes, ''Republic of Ireland'' is often used although technically not the name of the state but, according to the ''[[Republic of Ireland Act]] 1948'', the state &quot;may be described&quot; as such.&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[United Kingdom|United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland]]. The islands of [[Alderney]], [[Jersey]], [[Guernsey]], and [[Sark]], and their neighbouring smaller islands, are sometimes also taken to be part of the British Isles,&lt;ref&gt;Oxford English Dictionary: &quot;British Isles: a geographical term for the islands comprising Great Britain and Ireland with all their offshore islands including the Isle of Man and the Channel Islands.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; even though, as islands off the coast of [[France]], they do not form part of the archipelago.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
  |last1 = Alan
  |first1 = Lew
  |last2 = Colin
  |first2 = Hall
  |last3 = Dallen
  |first3 = Timothy
  |title = World Geography of Travel and Tourism: A Regional Approach
  |publisher=Elsevier
  |place = Oxford
  |year = 2008
  |quote = The British Isles comprise more than 6,000 islands off the northwest coast of continental Europe, including the countries of the United Kingdom of Great Britain (England, Scotland and Wales) and Northern Ireland, and the Republic of Ireland. The group also includes the United Kingdom crown dependencies of the Isle of Man, and by tradition, the Channel Islands (the Bailiwicks of Guernsey and Jersey), even though these islands are strictly speaking an archipelago immediately off the coast of Normandy (France) rather than part of the British Isles.
  |isbn = 978-0-7506-7978-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The oldest rocks in the group are in the north west of [[Scotland]], Ireland, and North Wales and are 2.7 billion years old.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| last=Woodcock| first=Nigel H.|author2=Rob Strachan| title=Geological History of Britain and Ireland| year=2012| publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons| isbn = 978-1-1182-7403-3| pages=49–50}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the [[Silurian]] period, the north-western regions collided with the south-east, which had been part of a separate continental landmass. The topography of the islands is modest in scale by global standards. [[Ben Nevis]] rises to an elevation of only {{convert|1345|m}},&lt;ref name=highestpoint /&gt; and [[Lough Neagh]], which is notably larger than other lakes in the island group, covers {{convert|151|sqmi|km2|order=flip}}. The climate is temperate marine, with cool winters and warm summers. The North Atlantic drift brings significant moisture and raises temperatures {{Convert|11|C-change||abbr=on}} above the global average for the latitude. This led to a landscape which was long dominated by temperate rainforest, although human activity has since cleared the vast majority of forest cover. The region was re-inhabited after the last glacial period of [[Quaternary glaciation]], by 12,000 BC, when Great Britain was still part of a [[Doggerland|peninsula of the European continent]]. Ireland, which became an island by 12,000 BC, was not inhabited until after 8000 BC.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tara.tcd.ie/bitstream/2262/40560/1/Edwards%26Brooks_INJ08_TARA.pdf |title=The Island of Ireland: Drowning the Myth of and Irish Land-Bridge? |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2019-02-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Great Britain became an island by 5600 BC.

[[Gaels|Hiberni]] (Ireland), [[Picts|Pictish]] (northern Britain) and [[Britons (historical)|Britons]] (southern Britain) tribes, all speaking [[Insular Celtic languages|Insular Celtic]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=f899xH_quaMC&amp;pg=PA973|title=Celtic Culture: Aberdeen breviary-celticism|publisher=|isbn=9781851094400|year=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; inhabited the islands at the beginning of the 1st millennium AD. Much of Brittonic-occupied Britain was [[Roman conquest of Britain|conquered by the Roman Empire]] from AD 43. The first [[Anglo-Saxons]] arrived as Roman power waned in the 5th century, and eventually dominated the bulk of what is now England.&lt;ref&gt;British Have Changed Little Since Ice Age, Gene Study SaysJames Owen for National Geographic News, 19 July 2005 [http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2005/07/0719_050719_britishgene.html]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Viking]] invasions began in the 9th century, followed by more permanent settlements and political change, particularly in England. The [[Normans|Norman]] conquest of England in 1066 and the later [[Angevin Empire|Angevin]] partial conquest of Ireland from 1169 led to the imposition of a new Norman ruling elite across much of Britain and parts of Ireland. By the [[Late Middle Ages]], Great Britain was separated into the Kingdom of England and Kingdom of Scotland, while control in Ireland fluxed between [[Gaelic Ireland|Gaelic kingdoms]], [[Hiberno-Norman|Hiberno-Norman lords]] and the English-dominated [[Lordship of Ireland]], soon restricted only to [[The Pale]]. The 1603 [[Union of the Crowns]], [[Acts of Union 1707]] and [[Acts of Union 1800]] aimed to consolidate Britain and Ireland into a single political unit, the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, with the Isle of Man and the Channel Islands remaining as [[Crown Dependencies]]. The expansion of the British Empire and migrations following the [[Great Famine (Ireland)|Irish Famine]] and [[Highland Clearances]] resulted in the dispersal of some of the islands' population and culture throughout the world, and a rapid depopulation of Ireland in the second half of the 19th century. Most of Ireland seceded from the United Kingdom after the [[Irish War of Independence]] and the subsequent [[Anglo-Irish Treaty]] (1919–1922), with six counties remaining in the UK as Northern Ireland.

The term &quot;British Isles&quot; is [[British Isles naming dispute|controversial]] in Ireland,&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=rasBRQwwOIIC&amp;pg=PA7 Social work in the British Isles by Malcolm Payne, Steven Shardlow] When we think about social work in the British Isles, a contentious term if ever there was one, what do we expect to see?&lt;/ref&gt; where there are nationalist objections to its usage.&lt;ref name=&quot;postwarculture&quot;&gt;{{Citation|first1=Alistair|last1=Davies|first2=Alan|last2=Sinfield|title=British Culture of the Postwar: An Introduction to Literature and Society, 1945–1999|publisher=Routledge|year=2000|isbn=978-0-415-12811-7|page=[https://archive.org/details/britishcultureof00adav/page/9 9]|quote=Some of the Irish dislike the 'British' in 'British Isles', while a minority of the Welsh and Scottish are not keen on 'Great Britain'. ... In response to these difficulties, 'Britain and Ireland' is becoming preferred official usage if not in the vernacular, although there is a growing trend amongst some critics to refer to Britain and Ireland as 'the archipelago'.|url=https://archive.org/details/britishcultureof00adav/page/9}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Government of Ireland]] does not officially recognise the term,&lt;ref name=&quot;Written Answers - Official Terms&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.oireachtas-debates.gov.ie/D/0606/D.0606.200509280360.html Written Answers – Official Terms&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121006211200/http://www.oireachtas-debates.gov.ie/D/0606/D.0606.200509280360.html |date=6 October 2012 }}, [[Dáil Éireann]], Volume 606, 28 September 2005. In his response, the Irish Minister for Foreign Affairs stated that &quot;The British Isles is not an officially recognised term in any legal or inter-governmental sense. It is without any official status. The Government, including the Department of Foreign Affairs, does not use this term. Our officials in the Embassy of Ireland, London, continue to monitor the media in Britain for any abuse of the official terms as set out in the Constitution of Ireland and in legislation. These include the name of the State, the President, [[Taoiseach]] and others.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; and its embassy in London discourages its use.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|date=3 October 2006|first=David|last=Sharrock|url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/europe/article658099.ece|work=The Times |location=UK |title=New atlas lets Ireland slip shackles of Britain|accessdate=7 July 2010|quote=A spokesman for the Irish Embassy in London said: “The British Isles has a dated ring to it, as if we are still part of the Empire. We are independent, we are not part of Britain, not even in geographical terms. We would discourage its usage {{sic}}.”}}&lt;/ref&gt; '''Britain and Ireland''' is used as an alternative description,&lt;ref name=&quot;postwarculture&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;reformationBI&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| title = The Reformation in Britain and Ireland: an introduction| isbn = 978-0-567-08280-0 |page = 17| last = Hazlett | first = Ian |year = 2003 | publisher=Continuum International Publishing Group|quote=At the outset, it should be stated that while the expression 'The British Isles' is evidently still commonly employed, its intermittent use throughout this work is only in the geographic sense, in so far as that is acceptable. Since the early twentieth century, that nomenclature has been regarded by some as increasingly less usable. It has been perceived as cloaking the idea of a 'greater England', or an extended south-eastern English imperium, under a common Crown since 1603 onwards. ... Nowadays, however, 'Britain and Ireland' is the more favoured expression, though there are problems with that too. ... There is no consensus on the matter, inevitably. It is unlikely that the ultimate in non-partisanship that has recently appeared the (East) 'Atlantic Archipelago' will have any appeal beyond captious scholars.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|url=https://www.theguardian.com/styleguide/b|title=Guardian Style Guide|work=Guardian |quote=A geographical term taken to mean Great Britain, Ireland and some or all of the adjacent islands such as Orkney, Shetland and the Isle of Man. The phrase is best avoided, given its (understandable) unpopularity in the Irish Republic. The plate in the National Geographic Atlas of the World once titled British Isles now reads Britain and Ireland.|location=London|date=19 December 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and '''Atlantic Archipelago''' has also seen limited use in academia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Acrossthemargins&quot;&gt;{{Citation|first1=Glenda|last1=Norquay|first2=Gerry| last2=Smyth |title=Across the margins: cultural identity and change in the Atlantic archipelago |publisher=Manchester University Press|year=2002|isbn=978-0-7190-5749-6|page=4 |quote=The term we favour here—Atlantic Archipelago—may prove to be of no greater use in the long run, but at this stage it does at least have the merit of questioning the ideology underpinning more established nomenclature.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Archipelagicidentities&quot;&gt;{{Citation|first1=Philip|last1=Schwyzer|first2=Simon| last2=Mealor |title=Archipelagic identities: literature and identity in the Atlantic Archipelago |publisher=Ashgate Publishing|year=2004 |isbn=978-0-7546-3584-0|page=10 |quote=In some ways 'Atlantic Archipelago' is intended to do the work of including without excluding, and while it seems to have taken root in terms of academic conferences and publishing, I don't see it catching on in popular discourse or official political circles, at least not in a hurry.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;EnglishIdentity&quot;&gt;{{Citation|first=Krishan|last=Kumar|title=The Making of English National Identity |publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2003 |isbn=978-0-521-77736-0|page=6 |quote=Some scholars, seeking to avoid the political and ethnic connotations of 'the British Isles', have proposed the 'Atlantic Archipelago' or even 'the East Atlantic Archipelago' (see, e.g. Pocock 1975a: 606; 1995: 292n; Tompson, 1986) Not surprisingly this does not seem to have caught on with the general public, though it has found increasing favour with scholars promoting the new 'British History'.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BritishAtlantic&quot;&gt;{{Citation|author1=David Armitage|author2=[[Michael Braddick]] |title=The British Atlantic world, 1500–1800 |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |year=2002 |isbn=978-0-333-96340-1|page=284 |quote=British and Irish historians increasingly use 'Atlantic archipelago' as a less metro-centric term for what is popularly known as the British Isles.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology==
{{Main|Britain (place name)|British Isles naming dispute|Terminology of the British Isles}}
The earliest known references to the islands as a group appeared in the writings of sea-farers from the ancient Greek colony of [[Massilian|Massalia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceC&quot;&gt;[[#refFoster2001|Foster]], p.&amp;nbsp;1.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; The original records have been lost; however, later writings, e.g. [[Avienus]]'s ''Ora maritima'', that quoted from the [[Massaliote Periplus]] (6th century BC) and from [[Pytheas]]'s ''On the Ocean'' ([[circa]] 325–320 BC)&lt;ref&gt;[[#refHarley1987|Harley]], p.&amp;nbsp;150.&lt;/ref&gt; have survived. In the 1st century BC, [[Diodorus Siculus]] has ''Prettanikē nēsos'',&lt;ref name=&quot;Diodorus(5.21.1)&quot;&gt;Diodorus Siculus' ''Bibliotheca Historica'' Book V. Chapter XXI. Section 1
[http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A2008.01.0540%3Abook%3D5%3Achapter%3D21%3Asection%3D1 Greek text] at the [[Perseus Project]].&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;the British Island&quot;, and ''Prettanoi'',&lt;ref name=&quot;Diodorus(5.21.2)&quot;&gt;Diodorus Siculus' ''Bibliotheca Historica'' Book V. Chapter XXI. Section 2
[http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A2008.01.0540%3Abook%3D5%3Achapter%3D21%3Asection%3D2 Greek text] at the [[Perseus Project]].&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;the Britons&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;[[#refAllen2007|Allen]], p.&amp;nbsp;172–174.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Strabo]] used Βρεττανική (''Brettanike''),&lt;ref name=&quot;Strabo(1.4.2)&quot;&gt;Strabo's ''Geography'' Book I. Chapter IV. Section 2 [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0197%3Abook%3D1%3Achapter%3D4%3Asection%3D2 Greek text] and [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0239%3Abook%3D1%3Achapter%3D4%3Asection%3D2 English translation] at the [[Perseus Project]].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Strabo(4.2.1)&quot;&gt;Strabo's ''Geography'' Book IV. Chapter II. Section 1 [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0197%3Abook%3D4%3Achapter%3D2%3Asection%3D1 Greek text] and [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0239%3Abook%3D4%3Achapter%3D2%3Asection%3D1 English translation] at the [[Perseus Project]].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Strabo(4.4.1)&quot;&gt;Strabo's ''Geography'' Book IV. Chapter IV. Section 1 [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0197%3Abook%3D4%3Achapter%3D4%3Asection%3D1 Greek text] and [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0239%3Abook%3D4%3Achapter%3D4%3Asection%3D1 English translation] at the [[Perseus Project]].&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Marcian of Heraclea]], in his ''Periplus maris exteri'', used αἱ Πρεττανικαί νῆσοι (''the Prettanic Isles'') to refer to the islands.&lt;ref name=MarcianPeriplus&gt;{{cite book|title=Geographi Graeci Minores|volume= 1|chapter-url=https://archive.org/details/geographigraeci03mlgoog|author1=[[Marcian of Heraclea|Marcianus Heracleensis]]|last2=Müller|first2=Karl|authorlink2=Karl Wilhelm Ludwig Müller|chapter=Periplus Maris Exteri, Liber Prior, Prooemium| pages=516–517|editor1-last=Firmin Didot|editor1-first=Ambrosio|location=Paris|year=1855|display-authors=etal}} Greek text and Latin Translation thereof archived at the [[Open Library]] Project.{{DjVulink}}&lt;/ref&gt; Historians today, though not in absolute agreement, largely agree that these Greek and Latin names were probably drawn from native [[Celtic languages|Celtic-language]] names for the archipelago.&lt;ref&gt;[[#refDavies2000|Davies]], p.&amp;nbsp;47.&lt;/ref&gt; Along these lines, the inhabitants of the islands were called the Πρεττανοί (''[[Priteni]]'' or ''Pretani'').&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#refSnyder2003|Snyder]], p.&amp;nbsp;68.&lt;/ref&gt; The shift from the &quot;P&quot; of ''Pretannia'' to the &quot;B&quot; of ''[[Britannia]]'' by the Romans occurred during the time of Julius Caesar.&lt;ref name=&quot;snyder&quot;&gt;[[#refSnyder2003|Snyder]], p.&amp;nbsp;12.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Greeks in Egypt|Greco-Egyptian]] scientist [[Claudius Ptolemy]] referred to the larger island as ''great Britain'' (μεγάλη Βρεττανία ''megale Brettania'') and to Ireland as ''little Britain'' (μικρὰ Βρεττανία ''mikra Brettania'') in his work ''[[Almagest]]'' (147–148 AD).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Claudii Ptolemaei Opera quae exstant omnia|author=Claudius Ptolemy|authorlink=Ptolemy|editor1-last=Heiberg|editor1-first=J.L.|publisher=in aedibus B. G. Teubneri|location=Leipzig|year=1898|volume=vol.1 Syntaxis Mathematica|chapter-url=http://www.wilbourhall.org/pdfs/HeibergAlmagestComplete.pdf|pages=112–113|chapter=Ἕκθεσις τῶν κατὰ παράλληλον ἰδιωμάτων: κβ', κε'}}&lt;/ref&gt; In his later work, ''[[Geography (Ptolemy)|Geography]]'' (c. 150 AD), he gave these islands the names ''[[Albion|Alwion]]'', ''[[Hibernia|Iwernia]]'', and ''Mona'' (the Isle of Man),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Claudii Ptolemaei Geographia|author=Claudius Ptolemy|authorlink=Ptolemy|editor1-last=Nobbe|editor1-first=Carolus Fridericus Augustus|publisher=sumptibus et typis Caroli Tauchnitii|location=Leipzig|year=1843|volume=vol.1|chapter-url=http://www.wilbourhall.org/pdfs/ptolemy/Claudii_Ptolemaei_GeographiaVOL_I.pdf|pages=59, 67|chapter=Book II, Prooemium and chapter β', paragraph 12}}&lt;/ref&gt; suggesting these may have been names of the individual islands not known to him at the time of writing ''Almagest''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Freeman |first=Philip |title=Ireland and the classical world |publisher=University of Texas Press |year=2001 |location=Austin, Texas |page=65 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZSHhfOM-5AEC&amp;pg=PA65 |isbn=978-0-292-72518-8 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The name ''Albion'' appears to have fallen out of use sometime after the Roman conquest of Great Britain, after which ''Britain'' became the more commonplace name for the island called Great Britain.&lt;ref name=&quot;snyder&quot; /&gt;

The earliest known use of the phrase ''Brytish Iles'' in the English language is dated 1577 in a work by [[John Dee]].&lt;ref name=&quot;John Dee 1577. p. 65&quot;&gt;John Dee, 1577. 1577 J. ''Arte Navigation'', p. 65 &quot;The syncere Intent, and faythfull Aduise, of Georgius Gemistus Pletho, was, I could..frame and shape very much of Gemistus those his two Greek Orations..for our Brytish Iles, and in better and more allowable manner.&quot; From the OED, s.v. &quot;British Isles&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Today, this name is seen by some as carrying imperialist overtones&lt;ref name=&quot;reformationBI&quot;/&gt; although it is still commonly used. Other names used to describe the islands include the ''[[Anglo-Celtic]] Isles'',&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=Demography of immigrants and minority groups in the United Kingdom: proceedings of the eighteenth annual symposium of the Eugenics Society, London 1981|volume=Volume 1981|author=D. A. Coleman|publisher=Academic Press|year=1982|isbn=978-0-12-179780-5|page=213|quote=The geographical term ''British Isles'' is not generally acceptable in Ireland, the term ''these islands'' being widely used instead. I prefer ''the Anglo-Celtic Isles'', or ''the North-West European Archipelago''.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=Irish historical studies: Joint Journal of the Irish Historical Society and the Ulster Society for Irish Historical Studies|publisher=Hodges, Figgis &amp; Co.|year=1990|page=98|quote=There is mug to be said for considering the archipelago as a whole, for a history of the British or Anglo-Celtic isles or 'these islands'.}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Atlantic archipelago'', ''British-Irish Isles'',&lt;ref&gt;John Oakland, 2003, [https://books.google.com/books?id=N9tRrtt2o68C&amp;pg=PP1&amp;dq=%22British+Civilization:+A+Student%27s+Dictionary%22&amp;sig=Ub6Y20p_tWpxtK8JHN0cwF4LxZI#PPA22,M1 British Civilization: A Student's Dictionary], Routledge: London
&lt;blockquote&gt;'''British-Irish Isles, the''' (geography) see British Isles&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;'''British Isles, the''' (geography) A geographical (not political or constitutional) term for Engliand, Scotland, Wales, and Ireland (including the Republic of Ireland), together with all offshore islands. A more accurate (and politically acceptable) term today is the British-Irish Isles.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; ''Britain and Ireland'', ''UK and Ireland'', and ''British Isles and Ireland''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blackwellreference.com/public/tocnode?id=g9781405129923_toclevel_ss1-14 |title=Blackwellreference.com |publisher=Blackwellreference.com |accessdate=7 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Owing to political and national associations with the word ''British'', the Government of Ireland does not use the term ''British Isles''&lt;ref name=&quot;Written Answers - Official Terms&quot;/&gt; and in documents drawn up jointly between the British and Irish governments, the archipelago is referred to simply as &quot;these islands&quot;.&lt;ref name=cavendish&gt;{{Citation|title=World and its Peoples: Ireland and United Kingdom|page=8|publisher=Marshall Cavendish|location=London|year=2010|quote=The nomenclature of Great Britain and Ireland and the status of the different parts of the archipelago are often confused by people in other parts of the world. The name British Isles is commonly used by geographers for the archipelago; in the Republic of Ireland, however, this name is considered to be exclusionary. In the Republic of Ireland, the name British-Irish Isles is occasionally used. However, the term British-Irish Isles is not recognized by international geographers. In all documents jointly drawn up by the British and Irish governments, the archipelago is simply referred to as &quot;these islands&quot;. The name British Isles remains the only generally accepted terms for the archipelago off the northwestern coast of mainland Europe.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nonetheless, British Isles is still the most widely accepted term for the archipelago.&lt;ref name=cavendish/&gt;

==Geography==
{{See also|Geography of England|Geography of Wales|Geography of Scotland|Geography of Ireland|Geography of the United Kingdom|Geography of the Isle of Man|Geography of the Channel Islands}}

[[File:British-Isles-NW-European-shelf.png|thumb|right|alt=An image showing the geological shelf of the British Isles.|The British Isles in relation to the north-west [[Geography of Europe|European]] [[continental shelf]].]]

The British Isles lie at the juncture of several regions with past episodes of tectonic mountain building. These [[Orogeny|orogenic belts]] form a complex geology that records a huge and varied span of Earth's history.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| last=Goudie| first=Andrew S.|author2=D. Brunsden| title=The Environment of the British Isles, an Atlas| year=1994| publisher=Clarendon Press| location=Oxford| page=2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of particular note was the [[Caledonian Orogeny]] during the [[Ordovician]] Period, c. 488–444 [[year|Ma]] and [[Llandovery epoch|Early Silurian]] period, when the [[craton]] [[Baltica]] collided with the [[terrane]] [[Avalonia]] to form the mountains and hills in northern Britain and Ireland. Baltica formed roughly the northwestern half of Ireland and Scotland. Further collisions caused the [[Variscan orogeny]] in the [[Devonian]] and [[Carboniferous]] periods, forming the hills of [[Munster]], southwest England, and southern Wales. Over the last 500&amp;nbsp;million years the land that forms the islands has drifted northwest from around 30°S, crossing the [[equator]] around 370&amp;nbsp;million years ago to reach its present northern latitude.&lt;ref&gt;&lt;!--Goudie, ''The Environment of the British Isles, an Atlas''--&gt;Ibid., p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt;

The islands have been shaped by numerous glaciations during the [[Quaternary Period]], the most recent being the [[Devensian]].{{citation needed|date=January 2012}} As this ended, the central Irish Sea was deglaciated and the English Channel flooded, with sea levels rising to current levels some 4,000 to 5,000 years ago, leaving the British Isles in their current form. Whether or not there was a land bridge between Great Britain and Ireland at this time is somewhat disputed, though there was certainly a single ice sheet covering the entire sea.

On the west coasts of Ireland and Scotland that directly face the Atlantic Ocean there are several long peninsulas, and many headlands and bays; the internal and eastern coasts are &quot;smoother&quot;.

There are about [[List of the British Isles by area|136 permanently inhabited islands]] in the group, the largest two being Great Britain and Ireland. Great Britain is to the east and covers {{convert|83,700|sqmi|km2|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;islandsarea&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.worldislandinfo.com/LARGESTV1.html|title=100 Largest Islands of the World|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ireland is to the west and covers {{convert|32,590|sqmi|km2|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;islandsarea&quot;/&gt; The largest of the other islands are to be found in the [[Hebrides]], [[Orkney]] and [[Shetland]] to the north, [[Anglesey]] and the Isle of Man between Great Britain and Ireland, and the [[Channel Islands]] near the coast of France.

The islands are at relatively low altitudes, with central Ireland and southern Great Britain particularly low-lying: the lowest point in the islands is the [[North Slob]] in [[County Wexford]], Ireland, with an elevation of {{convert|-3.0|m|feet}}. The [[Scottish Highlands]] in the northern part of Great Britain are mountainous, with [[Ben Nevis]] being the highest point on the islands at {{convert|1345|m|0|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=highestpoint /&gt; Other mountainous areas include Wales and parts of Ireland, although only seven peaks in these areas reach above {{convert|1000|m|0|abbr=on}}. Lakes on the islands are generally not large, although [[Lough Neagh]] in Northern Ireland is an exception, covering {{Convert|150|sqmi|km2}}.{{citation needed|date=January 2012}} The largest freshwater body in Great Britain (by area) is [[Loch Lomond]] at {{convert|27.5|sqmi|km2|0}}, and [[Loch Ness]], by volume whilst [[Loch Morar]] is the deepest freshwater body in the British Isles, with a maximum depth of {{convert|1017|ft|abbr=on|order=flip}}.&lt;ref name=Gazetteer&gt;[http://www.scottish-places.info/features/featurefirst2408.html Gazetteer for Scotland] Morar, Loch&lt;/ref&gt; There are a number of major rivers within the British Isles. The longest is the [[River Shannon|Shannon]] in Ireland at {{convert|224|mi|0|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.osi.ie/Education/Secondary-Schools/Teacher-Resources/Facts-%281%29.aspx Ordnance Survey (Ireland) Educational Facts]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.britannica.com/place/River-Shannon |title=River Shannon |last1=Ray |first1=Michael |author2=The editors of Encyclopædia Britannica|website=Encyclopædia Britannica |publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica, inc. |access-date=2020-02-11 |quote=&quot;about 161 miles (259 km) in a southerly direction to enter the Atlantic Ocean via a 70-mile (113-kilometre) estuary below Limerick city&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[river Severn]] at {{convert|220|mi|0|abbr=on}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.britannica.com/place/River-Severn |title=River Severn |last1=Wallenfeldt |first1=Jeff |author2=The editors of Encyclopædia Britannica|website=Encyclopædia Britannica |publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica, inc. |access-date=2020-02-11 |quote=&quot;about 180 miles (290 km) long, with the Severn estuary adding some 40 miles (64 km) to its total length&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; is the longest in Great Britain.

===Climate===
The [[climate of the British Isles]] is mild,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bgs.ac.uk/discoveringGeology/geologyOfBritain/iceAge/home.html|title=Ice and our landscape {{!}} Geology of Britain {{!}} British Geological Survey (BGS)|website=www.bgs.ac.uk|access-date=2019-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; moist and changeable with abundant rainfall and a lack of temperature extremes. It is defined as a temperate oceanic climate, or ''Cfb'' on the [[Köppen climate classification]] system, a classification it shares with most of northwest Europe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Peel, M. C. |author2=Finlayson B. L. |author3=McMahon, T. A. | year=2007 | title= Updated world map of the Köppen&amp;ndash;Geiger climate classification | journal=Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci. | volume=11 |issue=5 | pages=1633–1644 | url=http://www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/11/1633/2007/hess-11-1633-2007.html | issn = 1027-5606|doi=10.5194/hess-11-1633-2007}} ''(direct: [http://www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/11/1633/2007/hess-11-1633-2007.pdf Final Revised Paper])''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.met.ie/marine/marine_climatology.asp|title=Marine Climatology|publisher=Met Éireann|accessdate=30 January 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[North Atlantic Current|North Atlantic Drift]] (&quot;Gulf Stream&quot;), which flows from the Gulf of Mexico, brings with it significant moisture and raises temperatures {{Convert|11|C-change||abbr=on}} above the global average for the islands' latitudes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Mayes| first=Julian|author2=Dennis Wheeler| title=Regional Climates of the British Isles| year=1997| publisher=Routledge| location=London| page=13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most Atlantic [[Low-pressure area|depressions]] pass to the north of the islands; combined with the general [[Westerlies|westerly circulation]] and interactions with the landmass, this imposes a general east–west variation in climate.&lt;ref&gt;&lt;!--Mayes, ''Regional Climates of the British Isles''--&gt;Ibid., pp. 13–14.&lt;/ref&gt; There are four distinct climate patterns: south-east, with cold winters, warm and dry summers; south-west, having mild and very wet winters, warm and wet summers; north-west, generally wet with mild winters and cool summers; and north-east with cold winters, cool summers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.rgs.org/CMSPages/GetFile.aspx?nodeguid=4abef83d-916e-4b81-b156-286947cc5de3&amp;lang=en-GB|title=UK Climate Factsheet|last=|first=|date=|website=Royal Geographical Society|publisher=Royal Geographical Society|type=PDF|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/bitesize/guides/zpykxsg/revision/3|website=www.bbc.co.uk|access-date=2019-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Flora and fauna==
{{See also|Fauna of Great Britain|Fauna of Ireland|Trees of Britain and Ireland}}

[[File:Irl-female red deer Killarney.jpg|thumb|right|Some female red deer in [[Killarney National Park]], Ireland.]]

The islands enjoy a mild climate and varied soils, giving rise to a diverse pattern of vegetation. Animal and plant life is similar to that of the northwestern [[European mainland]]. There are however, fewer numbers of species, with Ireland having even less. All native [[flora]] and [[fauna]] in Ireland is made up of species that migrated from elsewhere in Europe, and Great Britain in particular. The only window when this could have occurred was between the end of [[Pleistocene|the last Ice Age]] (about 12,000 years ago) and when the land bridge connecting the two islands was flooded by sea (about 8,000 years ago).

As with most of Europe, prehistoric Britain and Ireland were covered with forest and swamp. Clearing began around 6000 BC and accelerated in medieval times. Despite this, Britain retained its primeval forests longer than most of Europe due to a small population and later development of trade and industry, and wood shortages were not a problem until the 17th century. By the 18th century, most of Britain's forests were consumed for shipbuilding or manufacturing charcoal and the nation was forced to import lumber from Scandinavia, North America, and the Baltic. Most forest land in Ireland is maintained by state forestation programmes. Almost all land outside urban areas is farmland. However, relatively large areas of forest remain in east and north Scotland and in southeast England. Oak, elm, ash and beech are amongst the most common trees in England. In Scotland, pine and birch are most common. Natural forests in Ireland are mainly oak, ash, [[wych elm]], birch and pine. Beech and [[Tilia|lime]], though not native to Ireland, are also common there. Farmland hosts a variety of semi-natural vegetation of grasses and flowering plants. Woods, [[hedgerows]], mountain slopes and marshes host [[Ericaceae|heather]], wild grasses, [[gorse]] and [[bracken]].

Many larger animals, such as wolf, bear and the European elk are today extinct. However, some species such as red deer are protected. Other small mammals, such as rabbits, foxes, [[badger]]s, [[hare]]s, [[hedgehog]]s, and [[stoat]]s, are very common and the European beaver has been reintroduced in parts of Scotland. [[Wild boar]] have also been reintroduced to parts of southern England, following escapes from boar farms and illegal releases. Many rivers contain [[otter]]s and [[Pinniped|seal]]s are common on coasts. Over 200 species of bird reside permanently and another 200 migrate. Common types are the [[common chaffinch]], common blackbird, house sparrow and [[common starling]]; all small birds. Large birds are declining in number, except for those kept for game such as [[pheasant]], [[partridge]], and [[red grouse]]. Fish are abundant in the rivers and lakes, in particular salmon, trout, perch and [[Esox|pike]]. Sea fish include [[Squalidae|dogfish]], cod, [[sole (fish)|sole]], pollock and bass, as well as mussels, crab and oysters along the coast. There are more than 21,000 species of insects.

Few species of reptiles or amphibians are found in Great Britain or Ireland. Only three snakes are native to Great Britain: the [[Vipera berus|common European adder]], the [[Natrix natrix|grass snake]] and the [[Coronella austriaca|smooth snake]];&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = Guide to British Snakes | publisher = Wildlife Britain wildlifebritain.com | url = http://www.wildlifebritain.com/britishsnakes.php | accessdate =17 August 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; none are native to Ireland. In general, Great Britain has slightly more variation and native wild life, with weasels, [[European polecat|polecat]]s, wildcats, most [[shrews]], [[European mole|moles]], [[European water vole|water voles]], [[roe deer]] and common toads also being absent from Ireland. This pattern is also true for birds and insects. Notable exceptions include the [[Kerry slug]] and certain species of woodlouse native to Ireland but not Great Britain.

Domestic animals include the Connemara pony, Shetland pony, English Mastiff, Irish wolfhound and many varieties of cattle and sheep.

==Demographics==
{{See also|Demographics of the Republic of Ireland|Demography of the United Kingdom}}

[[File:British Isles population density 2011 NUTS3.svg|upright|thumb|alt=A map of the British Isles showing the relative population densities across the area.|Population density per km² of the British Isles' [[Nomenclature of Territorial Units for Statistics|regions]].]]

England has a generally high population density, with almost 80% of the total population of the islands. Elsewhere in Great Britain and Ireland, high density of population is limited to areas around a few large cities. The largest urban area by far is the [[Greater London Built-up Area]] with 9 million inhabitants. Other major population centres include the [[Greater Manchester Built-up Area]] (2.4&amp;nbsp;million), [[West Midlands conurbation]] (2.4&amp;nbsp;million) and [[West Yorkshire Urban Area]] (1.6&amp;nbsp;million) in England,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ons.gov.uk/ons/about-ons/what-we-do/publication-scheme/published-ad-hoc-data/population/august-2012/mid-2010-urban-area-syoa-ests-england-and-wales.xls |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2013-06-16 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130605151000/http://www.ons.gov.uk/ons/about-ons/what-we-do/publication-scheme/published-ad-hoc-data/population/august-2012/mid-2010-urban-area-syoa-ests-england-and-wales.xls |archivedate=5 June 2013 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Greater Glasgow]] (1.2&amp;nbsp;million) in Scotland&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gro-scotland.gov.uk/files2/stats/population-estimates/special-area/settlements-localities2010/2010-settlements-table2.pdf Mid-2010 population estimates – Settlements in order of size] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130522082521/http://www.gro-scotland.gov.uk/files2/stats/population-estimates/special-area/settlements-localities2010/2010-settlements-table2.pdf |date=22 May 2013 }} General Register Office for Scotland&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Greater Dublin Area]] (1.9 million) in Ireland.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dubchamber.ie/policy/economic-profile-of-dublin|title=Dublin Region Facts {{!}} Dublin Chamber of Commerce|website=www.dubchamber.ie|language=en|access-date=2017-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The population of England rose rapidly during the 19th and 20th centuries, whereas the populations of Scotland and Wales showed little increase during the 20th century; the population of Scotland has remained unchanged since 1951. Ireland for most of its history had much the same population density as Great Britain (about one third of the total population). However, since the [[Great Famine (Ireland)|Great Irish Famine]], the population of Ireland has fallen to less than one tenth of the population of the British Isles. The famine caused a century-long population decline, drastically reduced the Irish population and permanently altered the demographic make-up of the British Isles. On a global scale, this disaster led to the creation of an [[Irish diaspora]] that numbers fifteen times the current population of the island.

The linguistic heritage of the British Isles is rich,&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=Languages of the British Isles Past and Present|isbn=978-0-233-96666-3|author=WB Lockwood|publisher=Ladysmith|location=British Columbia|year=1975|quote=An introduction to the rich linguistic heritage of Great Britain and Ireland.|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/languagesofbriti0000lock}}&lt;/ref&gt; with twelve languages from six groups across four branches of the [[Indo-European languages|Indo-European]] [[Language family|family]]. The [[Insular Celtic languages]] of the [[Goidelic]] sub-group ([[Irish language|Irish]], [[Manx language|Manx]] and [[Scottish Gaelic]]) and the [[Brittonic languages|Brittonic]] sub-group ([[Cornish language|Cornish]], Welsh and [[Breton language|Breton]], spoken in [[Brittany|north-western France]]) are the only remaining [[Celtic languages]]—the last of their continental relations were extinct before the 7th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|editor-first=Matthew|editor-last=Spriggs|first1=John|last1=Waddel|first2=Jane|last2=Conroy|title=Celts and Other: Maritime Contact and Linguistic Change|work=Archaeology and Language|volume=35|page=127|publisher=Routledge|location=London|year=1999|isbn=978-0-415-11786-9|quote=Continental Celtic includes Gaulish, Lepontic, Hispano-Celtic (or Celtiberian) and Galatian. All were extinct by the seventh century AD.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Norman language]]s of [[Guernésiais]], [[Jèrriais]] and [[Sercquiais]] spoken in the Channel Islands are similar to French. A [[Cant (language)|cant]], called [[Shelta]], is spoken by [[Irish Travellers]], often to conceal meaning from those outside the group.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=Charles G. Leland: The Man &amp; the Myth|first=Gary|last=Varner|year=2008|publisher=Lulu Press|location=Morrisville, North Carolina|isbn=978-1-4357-4394-6|page=41|quote=Shelta does in fact exist as a secret language as is used to conceal meaning from outsiders, used primarily in Gypsy business or negotiations or when speaking around the police.}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, English, including [[Scots language|Scots]], is the dominant language, with few monoglots remaining in the other languages of the region.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=The Encyclopedia of Language and Linguistics|volume=Volume 5|first=R. E. Asher|last=J. M. Y. Simpson|page=2505|publisher=Pergamon Press|location=Oxford|year=1994|isbn= 978-0-08-035943-4|quote=Thus, apart from the very young, there are virtually no monoglot speakers of Irish, Scots Gaelic, or Welsh.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Norn language]] of [[Orkney]] and [[Shetland]] became extinct around 1880.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=The Death of the Irish Language: A Qualified Obituary|first=Reg|last=Hindley|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|location=Oxon|year=1990|isbn=978-0-415-04339-7|page=221|quote=Three indigenous languages have died in the British Isles since around 1780: Cornish (traditionally in 1777), Norn (the Norse language of Shetland: c. 1880), Manx (1974).}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!-- This image might be of interest to keep, but hard to place right now in the article: [[File:BI-langs.svg|thumb|left|alt=A Euler diagram showing the modern languages of the British Isles in and how the related to each other by language branch and typical spoken location.|{{legend|red|Language branches}}{{legend|blue|Modern languages}}{{legend|green|Typical spoken locations}}&lt;hr/&gt;[[Euler diagram]] showing language branches, major languages and typically where they are spoken for [[modern languages]] in the British Isles.]] --&gt;

===Urban areas===

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! Rank
! City
! Population
! Country
|-
! 1
|align=left|[[London]]||9,787,426||[[England]]
|-
! 2
|align=left|[[Manchester]]||2,553,379||[[England]]
|-
! 3
|align=left|[[West Midlands Conurbation|West Midlands]]||2,440,986||[[England]]
|-
! 4
|align=left|[[West Yorkshire Urban Area|West Yorkshire]]||1,777,934||[[England]]
|-
! 5
|align=left|[[Glasgow]]||1,209,143||[[Scotland]]
|-
! 6
|align=left|[[Dublin]]||1,173,179||[[Republic of Ireland]]
|-
! 7
|align=left|[[Liverpool]]||864,122||[[England]]
|-
! 8
|align=left|[[South Hampshire]]||855,569||[[England]]
|-
! 9
|align=left|[[Tyneside]]||774,891||[[England]]
|-
! 10
|align=left|[[Nottingham]]||729,977||[[England]]
|-
! 11
|align=left|[[Sheffield]]||685,386||[[England]]
|-
! 12
|align=left|[[Bristol]]||617,280||[[England]]
|-
! 13
|align=left|[[Belfast]]||595,879||[[Northern Ireland]]
|-
! 14
|align=left|[[Leicester]]||508,916||[[England]]
|-
! 15
|align=left|[[Edinburgh]]||482,005||[[Scotland]]
|-
! 16
|align=left|[[Brighton and Hove]]||474,485||[[England]]
|-
! 17
|align=left|[[Bournemouth]]||466,266||[[England]]
|-
! 18
|align=left|[[Cardiff]]||447,287||[[Wales]]
|-
! 19
|align=left|[[Teesside]]||376,633||[[England]]
|-
! 20
|align=left|[[Stoke-on-Trent]]||372,775||[[England]]
|-
! 21
|align=left|[[Coventry]]||359,262||[[England]]
|-
! 22
|align=left|[[Sunderland]]||335,415||[[England]]
|-
! 23
|align=left|[[Birkenhead]]||325,264||[[England]]
|-
! 24
|align=left|[[Reading, Berkshire|Reading]]||318,014||[[England]]
|-
! 25
|align=left|[[Kingston-upon-Hull]]||314,018||[[England]]
|-
! 26
|align=left|[[Preston, Lancashire|Preston]]||313,322||[[England]]
|-
! 27
|align=left|[[Newport, Wales|Newport]]||306,844||[[Wales]]
|-
! 28
|align=left|[[Swansea]]||300,352||[[Wales]]
|-
! 29
|align=left|[[Southend-on-Sea]]||295,310||[[England]]
|-
! 30
|align=left|[[Derby]]||270,468||[[England]]
|-
! 31
|align=left|[[Plymouth]]||260,203||[[England]]
|-
! 32
|align=left|[[Luton]]||258,018||[[England]]
|-
! 33
|align=left|[[Aldershot]]||252,397||[[England]]
|-
! 34
|align=left|[[Medway]]||243,931||[[England]]
|-
! 35
|align=left|[[Blackpool]]||239,409||[[England]]
|-
! 36
|align=left|[[Milton Keynes]]||229,431||[[England]]
|-
! 37
|align=left|[[Barnsley]]||223,281||[[England]]
|-
! 38
|align=left|[[Northampton]]||215,963||[[England]]
|-
! 39
|align=left|[[Norwich]]||213,166||[[England]]
|-
! 40
|align=left|[[Cork (city)|Cork]]||208,669||[[Republic of Ireland]]
|-
! 41
|align=left|[[Aberdeen]]||207,932||[[Scotland]]
|}

==History==
{{Main|History of the British Isles}}
{{Unreferenced section|date=January 2011}}
At the end of the last ice age, what are now the British Isles were joined to the European mainland as a mass of land extending north west from the modern-day northern coastline of France, Belgium and the Netherlands. Ice covered almost all of what is now Scotland, most of Ireland and Wales, and the hills of northern England. From 14,000 to 10,000 years ago, as the ice melted, sea levels rose separating Ireland from Great Britain and also creating the Isle of Man. About two to four millennia later, Great Britain became separated from the mainland. Britain probably became repopulated with people before the ice age ended and certainly before it became separated from the mainland. It is likely that Ireland became settled by sea after it had already become an island.

At the time of the Roman Empire, about two thousand years ago, various tribes, which spoke [[Celtic languages|Celtic dialects]] of the [[Insular Celtic languages|Insular Celtic]] group, were inhabiting the islands. The Romans expanded their civilisation to control southern Great Britain but were impeded in advancing any further, building [[Hadrian's Wall]] to mark the northern frontier of their empire in 122 AD. At that time, Ireland was populated by a people known as Hiberni, the northern third or so of Great Britain by a people known as Picts and the southern two thirds by Britons.

[[File:Alfred Jewel.jpg|thumb|upright|The [[Alfred Jewel]] (9th century)]]
Anglo-Saxons arrived as [[Fall of Rome|Roman power waned in the 5th century AD]]. Initially, their arrival seems to have been at the invitation of the Britons as mercenaries to repulse incursions by the Hiberni and Picts. In time, Anglo-Saxon demands on the British became so great that they came to culturally dominate the bulk of southern Great Britain, though recent genetic evidence suggests Britons still formed the bulk of the population. This dominance creating what is now England and leaving culturally British enclaves only in [[Hen Ogledd|the north of what is now England]], in [[Cornwall]] and what is now known as Wales. Ireland had been unaffected by the Romans except, significantly, for being [[Christianisation of Ireland|Christianised]]—traditionally by the Romano-Briton, Saint Patrick. As Europe, including Britain, descended into turmoil following the collapse of Roman civilisation, an era known as [[Dark Ages (historiography)|the Dark Ages]], Ireland entered a [[golden age]] and [[Hiberno-Scottish mission|responded with missions]] (first to Great Britain and then to the continent), the founding of monasteries and universities. These were later joined by [[Anglo-Saxon mission]]s of a similar nature.

Viking invasions began in the 9th century, followed by more permanent settlements, particularly along the east coast of Ireland, the west coast of modern-day Scotland and the Isle of Man. Though the Vikings were eventually neutralised in Ireland, their influence remained in the cities of [[Dublin]], [[Cork (city)|Cork]], [[Limerick]], [[Waterford]] and [[Wexford]]. England, however, was slowly conquered around the turn of the first millennium AD, and eventually became a feudal possession of [[Denmark]]. The relations between the descendants of Vikings in England and counterparts in [[Normandy]], in northern France, lay at the heart of a series of events that led to the [[Normans|Norman]] [[Norman conquest of England|conquest of England in 1066]]. The remnants of the [[Duchy of Normandy]], which conquered England, remain associated to the English Crown as the Channel Islands to this day.  A century later, the marriage of the future [[Henry II of England]] to [[Eleanor of Aquitaine]] created the [[Angevin Empire]], partially under the [[List of French monarchs|French Crown]]. At the invitation of [[Diarmait Mac Murchada]], a provincial king, and under [[Laudabiliter|the authority of]] [[Pope Adrian IV]] (the only Englishman to be elected pope), the [[Norman invasion of Ireland|Angevins invaded Ireland]] in 1169. Though initially intended to be kept as an independent kingdom, the failure of [[Ruaidrí Ua Conchobair|the Irish High King]] to ensure the terms of the [[Treaty of Windsor (1175)|Treaty of Windsor]] led Henry II, as King of England, to rule as effective monarch under the title of [[Lord of Ireland]]. This title was granted to his younger son, but when Henry's heir unexpectedly died, the title of [[King of England]] and Lord of Ireland became entwined in one person.

[[File:James I of England by Daniel Mytens.jpg|thumb|upright|James VI of Scotland (James I of England)]]

By the [[Late Middle Ages]], Great Britain was separated into the Kingdoms of [[Kingdom of England|England]] and [[Kingdom of Scotland|Scotland]]. Power in Ireland fluxed between [[Gaelic Ireland|Gaelic kingdoms]], [[Hiberno-Norman|Hiberno-Norman lords]] and the English-dominated [[Lordship of Ireland]]. A similar situation existed in the [[Principality of Wales]], which was slowly being annexed into the Kingdom of England by a series of laws. During the course of the 15th century, the Crown of England would assert a claim to the Crown of France, thereby also releasing the King of England from being [[vassal]] of the [[King of France]]. In 1534, King Henry VIII, at first having been a strong defender of Roman Catholicism in the face of the Reformation, separated from the Roman Church after failing to secure a divorce from the Pope. His response was to place the King of England as &quot;the only Supreme Head in Earth of the [[Church of England]]&quot;, thereby removing the authority of the Pope from the affairs of the English Church. Ireland, which had been held by the King of England as Lord of Ireland, but which strictly speaking had been a feudal possession of the Pope since the Norman invasion was declared [[Kingdom of Ireland|a separate kingdom]] in personal union with England.

Scotland, meanwhile had remained an independent Kingdom. In 1603, that changed when the King of Scotland [[Union of the Crowns|inherited the Crown of England]], and consequently the Crown of Ireland also. The subsequent 17th century was one of political upheaval, religious division and war. English colonialism in Ireland of the 16th century was extended by large-scale Scottish and English colonies in [[Ulster]]. Religious division heightened and the king in England came into conflict with parliament over his tolerance towards Catholicism. The resulting [[English Civil War]] or [[War of the Three Kingdoms]] led to a [[revolutionary republic]] in England. Ireland, largely Catholic was mainly loyal to the king. Following defeat to the parliaments army, large scale land distributions from loyalist Irish nobility to English commoners in the service of the parliamentary army created a new [[Protestant Ascendancy|Ascendancy]] class which obliterated the remnants of Old English (Hiberno-Norman) and Gaelic Irish nobility in Ireland. The new ruling class was Protestant and English, whilst the populace was largely Catholic and Irish. This theme would influence Irish politics for centuries to come. When the monarchy was restored in England, the king found it politically impossible to restore the lands of former land-owners in Ireland. The &quot;[[Glorious Revolution]]&quot; of 1688 repeated similar themes: a Catholic king pushing for religious tolerance in opposition to a Protestant parliament in England. The king's army was defeated at the [[Battle of the Boyne]] and at the militarily crucial [[Battle of Aughrim]] in Ireland. Resistance held out, eventually forcing the guarantee of religious tolerance in the [[Treaty of Limerick]]. However, the terms were never honoured and a new monarchy was installed.

The Kingdoms of England and Scotland were [[Acts of Union 1707|unified in 1707]] creating the [[Kingdom of Great Britain]]. Following an attempted republican [[1798 Rebellion|revolution in Ireland in 1798]], the Kingdoms of Ireland and Great Britain were [[Acts of Union 1800|unified in 1801]], creating the [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|United Kingdom]]. The Isle of Man and the Channel Islands remaining outside of the United Kingdom but with their ultimate good governance being the responsibility of the British Crown (effectively the British government). Although, the colonies of North America that would become the United States of America were lost by the start of the 19th century, the [[British Empire]] expanded rapidly elsewhere. A century later it would cover one third of the globe. Poverty in the United Kingdom remained desperate, however, and industrialisation in England led to terrible condition for the working classes. Mass migrations following the [[Great Famine (Ireland)|Irish Famine]] and [[Highland Clearances]] resulted in the distribution of the islands' population and culture throughout the world and a rapid de-population of Ireland in the second half of the 19th century. Most of Ireland seceded from the United Kingdom after the [[Irish War of Independence]] and the subsequent [[Anglo-Irish Treaty]] (1919–1922), with the six counties that formed Northern Ireland remaining as an autonomous region of the UK.

==Politics==
{{main|Politics in the British Isles}}
{{See also|Ireland–United Kingdom relations|Politics of the United Kingdom|Politics of the Republic of Ireland|Ireland–Isle of Man relations|Politics of the Isle of Man|Politics of Jersey|Politics of Guernsey|Politics of Alderney|Politics of Sark|}}

[[File:British Isles terms.gif|thumb|upright=1.35|left|Subdivisions of the British Isles&lt;br /&gt;See also [//upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/1/1f/British_Isles_Euler_Diagram_13.svg diagrammatic version]]]

There are two sovereign states in the British Isles: [[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]] and the [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland]]. Ireland, sometimes called the Republic of Ireland, governs five sixths of the island of Ireland, with the remainder of the island forming Northern Ireland. Northern Ireland is a part of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland, usually shortened to simply &quot;the United Kingdom&quot;, which governs the remainder of the archipelago with the exception of the Isle of Man and the Channel Islands. The Isle of Man and the two Bailiwicks of the Channel Islands, [[Jersey]] and [[Bailiwick of Guernsey|Guernsey]], are known as the [[Crown dependencies]]. They exercise constitutional rights of self-government and judicial independence;&lt;ref name=&quot;gov.je&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gov.je/Government/JerseyWorld/InternationalAffairs/Pages/RelationshipEUandUK.aspx |title=Jersey's relationship with the UK and EU |publisher=Gov.je |accessdate=7 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; responsibility for international representation rests largely with the UK (in consultation with the respective governments); and responsibility for defence is reserved by the UK. The United Kingdom is made up of four [[Countries of the United Kingdom|constituent parts]]: England, Scotland and Wales, forming Great Britain, and Northern Ireland in the north-east of the island of Ireland. Of these, Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland have [[Devolution|devolved]] governments, meaning that each has its own parliament or assembly and is self-governing with respect to certain matters set down by law. For judicial purposes, Scotland, Northern Ireland and [[English law|England and Wales]] (the latter being one entity) form separate legal jurisdictions, with there being no single law for the UK as a whole.

Ireland, the United Kingdom and the three Crown dependencies are all [[parliamentary democracies]], with their own separate parliaments. All parts of the United Kingdom return [[member of parliament|members]] to [[Parliament of the United Kingdom|parliament in London]]. In addition to this, voters in Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland return members to a [[Scottish Parliament|parliament in Edinburgh]] and to assemblies in [[National Assembly for Wales|Cardiff]] and [[Northern Ireland Assembly|Belfast]] respectively. Governance in the norm is by majority rule; however, Northern Ireland uses a system of [[Consociationalism|power sharing]] whereby [[Unionism in Ireland|unionists]] and [[Irish nationalist|nationalists]] share executive posts proportionately and where the assent of both groups is required for the [[Northern Ireland Assembly]] to make certain decisions. (In the context of Northern Ireland, unionists are those who want Northern Ireland to remain a part of the United Kingdom and nationalists are those who want Northern Ireland to join with the rest of Ireland.) The [[British monarch]] is the head of state of the United Kingdom, while in the Republic of Ireland the head of state is the [[President of Ireland]].

Ireland is part of the European Union (EU) and the UK was part until 31 January 2020.&lt;ref name=&quot;gov.je&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gov.gg/ccm/navigation/about-guernsey/constitution/ |title=States of Guernsey: Constitution |publisher=Gov.gg |accessdate=7 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gov.im/cso/externalrelations/eu.xml |title=Relationship with European Union – Isle of Man Government – Chief Secretarys Office |publisher=Gov.im |accessdate=7 November 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100925081145/http://www.gov.im/cso/externalrelations/eu.xml |archivedate=25 September 2010 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; Neither the United Kingdom or Ireland are part of the [[Schengen Area]], which allows passport-free travel between certain EU member states. However, since the [[partition of Ireland]], an informal free-travel area has existed across the island of Ireland. This area required formal recognition in 1997 during the course of negotiations for the [[Amsterdam Treaty]] of the European Union, and (together with the Crown dependencies) is now known as the [[Common Travel Area]].

Reciprocal arrangements allow British and Irish citizens full voting rights in the two states. Exceptions to this are presidential elections and [[Amendments to the Constitution of Ireland|constitutional referendums]] in the Republic of Ireland, for which there is no comparable franchise in the United Kingdom. In the United Kingdom, these pre-date European Union law, and in both jurisdictions go further than what was required by European Union law. Other EU nationals may only vote in local and European Parliament elections while resident in either the UK or Ireland. In 2008, a [[Ministry of Justice (United Kingdom)|UK Ministry of Justice]] report investigating how to strengthen the British sense of citizenship proposed to end this arrangement, arguing that &quot;the right to vote is one of the hallmarks of the political status of citizens; it is not a means of expressing closeness between countries&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Goldsmith, 2008, [http://www.justice.gov.uk/docs/citizenship-report-full.pdf Citizenship: Our Common Bond], Ministry of Justice: London {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090327121654/http://www.justice.gov.uk/docs/citizenship-report-full.pdf |date=27 March 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition, some civil bodies are organised throughout the islands as a whole—for example the [[Samaritans (charity)|Samaritans]], which is deliberately organised without regard to national boundaries on the basis that a service which is not political or religious should not recognise sectarian or political divisions.{{citation needed|date=April 2013}} The [[Royal National Lifeboat Institution]] (RNLI), a charity that operates a lifeboat service, is also organised throughout the islands as a whole, covering the waters of the United Kingdom, Ireland, the Isle of Man, and the Channel Islands.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20070112024357/http://www.rnli.org.uk/home RNLI.org.uk], The RNLI is a charity that provides a 24-hour lifesaving service around the UK and Republic of Ireland.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Northern Ireland peace process]] has led to a number of unusual arrangements between the Republic of Ireland, Northern Ireland and the United Kingdom. For example, citizens of Northern Ireland are entitled to the choice of Irish or British citizenship or both, and the Governments of Ireland and the United Kingdom consult on matters not devolved to the [[Northern Ireland Executive]]. The Northern Ireland Executive and the Government of Ireland also meet as the [[North/South Ministerial Council]] to develop policies common across the island of Ireland. These arrangements were made following the 1998 [[Good Friday Agreement]].

===British–Irish Council===
{{main|British–Irish Council}}

Another body established under the Good Friday Agreement, the British–Irish Council, is made up of all of the states and territories of the British Isles. The [[British–Irish Parliamentary Assembly]] ({{lang-ga|Tionól Pharlaiminteach na Breataine agus na hÉireann}}) predates the British–Irish Council and was established in 1990. Originally it comprised 25 members of the [[Oireachtas]], the Irish parliament, and 25 members of the [[parliament of the United Kingdom]], with the purpose of building mutual understanding between members of both legislatures. Since then the role and scope of the body has been expanded to include representatives from the [[Scottish Parliament]], the [[National Assembly for Wales]], the [[Northern Ireland Assembly]], the [[States of Jersey]], the [[States of Guernsey]] and the [[High Court of Tynwald]] (Isle of Man).

The Council does not have executive powers, but meets biannually to discuss issues of mutual importance. Similarly, the Parliamentary Assembly has no legislative powers but investigates and collects witness evidence from the public on matters of mutual concern to its members. Reports on its findings are presented to the Governments of Ireland and the United Kingdom. During the February 2008 meeting of the British–Irish Council, it was agreed to set up a standing secretariat that would serve as a permanent 'civil service' for the Council.&lt;ref&gt;[Communiqué of the British-Irish Council], February 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Leading on from developments in the British–Irish Council, the chair of the British–Irish Inter-Parliamentary Assembly, [[Niall Blaney]], has suggested that the body should shadow the British–Irish Council's work.&lt;ref&gt;Martina Purdy, 28 February 2008, [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/northern_ireland/7268911.stm Unionists urged to drop boycott], BBC: London&lt;/ref&gt;

==Culture==
{{See also|Culture of Ireland|Culture of the United Kingdom|Sport in Ireland|Sport in the United Kingdom}}

[[File:Lords match in progress.jpg|thumb|One Day Cricket International at Lord's; England v Australia 10 July 2005]]
[[File:Pádraig Harrington 2007.jpg|thumb|right|[[Pádraig Harrington]] teeing off at [[the Open Championship]] ([[golf]]) [[2007 Open Championship|in 2007]].]]

The United Kingdom and Ireland have separate media, although British television, newspapers and magazines are widely available in Ireland,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.museum.tv/archives/etv/I/htmlI/ireland/ireland.htm |title=Ireland |publisher=Museum.tv |accessdate=17 October 2008 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071214101405/http://www.museum.tv/archives/etv/I/htmlI/ireland/ireland.htm |archive-date=14 December 2007 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; giving people in Ireland a high level of familiarity with cultural matters in the United Kingdom. Irish newspapers are also available in the UK, and Irish state and private television is widely available in Northern Ireland.{{citation needed|date=April 2013}} Certain reality TV shows have embraced the whole of the islands, for example ''[[The X Factor (UK TV series)|The X Factor]]'', seasons 3, 4 and 7 of which featured auditions in Dublin and were open to Irish voters, whilst the show previously known as ''Britain's Next Top Model'' became ''[[Britain and Ireland's Next Top Model]]'' in 2011. A few cultural events are organised for the island group as a whole. For example, the [[Costa Book Awards]] are awarded to authors resident in the UK or Ireland. The [[Mercury Music Prize]] is handed out every year to the best album from a British or Irish musician or group.

Many globally popular sports had modern rules codified in the British Isles, including golf, [[association football]], [[Cricket in the British Isles|cricket]], [[Rugby football|rugby]], [[History of snooker|snooker]] and darts, as well as many minor sports such as [[croquet]], [[bowls]], [[pitch and putt]], [[History of water polo|water polo]] and [[Gaelic handball|handball]]. A number of sports are popular throughout the British Isles, the most prominent of which is association football. While this is organised separately in different national associations, leagues and national teams, even within the UK, it is a common passion in all parts of the islands. [[Rugby union]] is also widely enjoyed across the islands with four national teams from [[England national rugby union team|England]], [[Ireland national rugby union team|Ireland]], [[Scotland national rugby union team|Scotland]] and [[Wales national rugby union team|Wales]]. The [[British and Irish Lions]] is a team chosen from each national team and undertakes tours of the Southern Hemisphere rugby-playing nations every four years. Ireland play as a united team, represented by players from both Northern Ireland and the Republic. These national rugby teams play each other each year for the [[Triple Crown (rugby union)|Triple Crown]] as part of the [[Six Nations Championship]]. Also, since 2001, the professional club teams of Ireland, Scotland, Wales and Italy compete against each other in the [[Pro14]].

The [[Ryder Cup]] in golf was originally played between a United States team and a team representing Great Britain and Ireland. From 1979 onwards this was expanded to include the whole of Europe.

==Transport==
{{See also|Transport in Ireland|Transport in the United Kingdom}}

[[File:MS Stena Explorer Dun Laoghaire.jpg|thumb|[[HSC One World Karadeniz|HSC ''Stena Explorer'']], a large [[High-speed craft|fast ferry]] on the former [[Holyhead]]–[[Dún Laoghaire]] route between Great Britain and Ireland.]]

[[London Heathrow Airport]] is Europe's busiest airport in terms of passenger traffic, and the Dublin-London route is the busiest air route in Europe collectively,&lt;ref&gt;Seán McCárthaigh, [https://web.archive.org/web/20101206210538/http://archives.tcm.ie/irishexaminer/2003/03/31/story437213650.asp Dublin–London busiest air traffic route within EU] Irish Examiner, 31 March 2003&lt;/ref&gt; the busiest route out of Heathrow and the second-busiest international air route in the world. The [[English Channel]] and the southern [[North Sea]] are the busiest seaways in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|first=Jack |last=Hardisty|title=The British Seas: an Introduction to the Oceanography and Resources of the North-west European Continental Shelf|publisher=Routledge|location=London|year=1990|isbn=978-0-415-03586-6|page=5|quote=Not only are the English Channel and the Southern North Sea, in particular, the busiest shipping clearways in the world, but the seas are also sources of the European community's industrial wealth (fisheries, petroleum, aggregates, and power) and sinks for the disposal of refuse from its intensely urbanized and industrialized coats.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Channel Tunnel]], opened in 1994, links Great Britain to France and is the second-longest rail tunnel in the world.

The idea of building a [[Irish Sea tunnel|tunnel under the Irish Sea]] has been raised since 1895,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Tunnel under the Sea&quot;, [[The Washington Post]], 2 May 1897 [https://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/washingtonpost_historical/access/282943272.html?dids=282943272:282943272&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;date=MAY+02%2C+1897&amp;author=&amp;pub=The+Washington+Post&amp;desc=TUNNEL+UNDER+THE+SEA&amp;pqatl=google (Archive link)]&lt;/ref&gt; when it was first investigated. Several potential Irish Sea tunnel projects have been proposed, most recently the ''Tusker Tunnel'' between the ports of [[Rosslare Europort|Rosslare]] and [[Fishguard]] proposed by [[The Institute of Engineers of Ireland]] in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=Tunnel 'vision' under Irish Sea|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/wales/south_west/4121001.stm|publisher=BBC|date=23 December 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; A rail tunnel was proposed in 1997 on a different route, between [[Dublin]] and [[Holyhead]], by British engineering firm Symonds. Either tunnel, at {{convert|50|mi|0|abbr=on}}, would be by far the longest in the world, and would cost an estimated £15&amp;nbsp;billion or €20&amp;nbsp;billion. A proposal in 2007,&lt;ref&gt;BBC News, [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/northern_ireland/6956570.stm From Twinbrook to the Trevi Fountain], 21 August 2007&lt;/ref&gt; estimated the cost of building a bridge from [[County Antrim]] in Northern Ireland to [[Galloway]] in Scotland at £3.5bn (€5bn).

== See also ==

* [[British Islands]]
* [[British Isles fixed sea link connections]]
* [[Extreme points of the British Isles]]
* [[List of islands of the British Isles]]

{{clear}}

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== Further reading ==
{{Refbegin|30em}}
* {{Cite book| first=Stephen| last=Allen| title=Lords of Battle: The World of the Celtic Warrior| publisher=Osprey Publishing| year=2007| isbn=978-1-84176-948-6| url=https://books.google.com/?id=28C63w4vKD8C| ref=refAllen2007}}
* {{Cite book| first=Robin George| last=Collingwood| title=Roman Britain and the English Settlements| publisher=Biblo &amp; Tannen Publishers| year=1998| isbn=978-0-8196-1160-4 | url=https://books.google.com/?id=fMcbnMFn8lcC | ref=refCollingwood1998}}
* {{Cite book| first=Norman| last=Davies| authorlink=Norman Davies| title=The Isles a History| publisher=Macmillan| year=2000| isbn=978-0-333-69283-7 | ref=refDavies2000| title-link=The Isles a History}}
* {{Cite book| first=Niall| last=Ferguson| authorlink=Niall Ferguson| title=Empire| publisher=Basic Books| year=2004| isbn=978-0-465-02329-5| url=https://books.google.com/?id=luSjXeSByHEC| ref=refFergusonEmpire2004| accessdate=22 July 2009}}
* {{Cite book| last = Foster (editor)| first = Robert Fitzroy| author2 = Donnchadh O Corrain| title = The Oxford History of Ireland| publisher=Oxford University Press| date = 1 November 2001| url = https://books.google.com/?id=bD9RFgLaGQkC| isbn = 978-0-19-280202-6| ref=refFoster2001| authorlink2 = Donnchadh O Corrain}}
* {{Cite book| first=John Brian| last=Harley|author2= David Woodward |title=The History of Cartography: Cartography in prehistoric, ancient, and medieval Europe and the Mediterranean| publisher=Humana Press| year=1987| isbn=978-0-226-31633-8| url=https://books.google.com/?id=uJaP4i7-_MIC| ref=refHarley1987}}
* {{Cite book| first=Angus| last=Maddison| title=The World Economy: A Millennial Perspective| publisher=Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development| year=2001| isbn=978-92-64-18654-5| url=https://books.google.com/?id=6D01BTuzScwC| ref=refMaddison2001| accessdate=22 July 2009}}
* {{Cite book| first=Jean| last=Markale| title=King of the Celts| publisher=Bear &amp; Company| year=1994| isbn=978-0-89281-452-7| url=https://books.google.com/?id=-qIzhamrT2kC| ref=refMarkale1994}}
* {{Cite book| first=Christopher| last=Snyder| title=The Britons| publisher=Blackwell Publishing| year=2003| isbn=978-0-631-22260-6 | url=https://books.google.com/?id=QI_-cR_nZYsC | ref=refSnyder2003}}
* [[A History of Britain (book)|A History of Britain]]: At the Edge of the World, 3500 B.C. – 1603 A.D. by [[Simon Schama]], BBC/Miramax, 2000 {{ISBN|978-0-7868-6675-5}}
* A History of Britain—The Complete Collection on DVD by [[Simon Schama]], BBC 2002
* Shortened History of England by [[George Macaulay Trevelyan|G. M. Trevelyan]] Penguin Books {{ISBN|978-0-14-023323-0}}
{{Refend}}

== External links ==
{{Commons|British Isles}}
* An [http://www.bgs.ac.uk/education/makeamap/home.html interactive geological map] of the British Isles.

{{British Isles}}
{{Portal bar|Ireland|United Kingdom}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:British Isles| ]]
[[Category:Geography of Northern Europe]]
[[Category:Geography of Western Europe]]
[[Category:Regions of Europe]]
[[Category:Archipelagoes of Europe]]</text>
      <sha1>5m4l74bxsbv1eq2pfrv8rkxyyw1g7dc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
