  <page>
    <title>De Havilland Mosquito</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9093</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941021439</id>
      <parentid>939446807</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-16T03:46:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ira Leviton</username>
        <id>25046916</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Fixed a typo found with [[Wikipedia:Typo_Team/moss]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2019}}
{{short description|Multi-role combat aircraft}}
{{lowercase|de Havilland Mosquito}}
&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] for recommended layout. --&gt;
{|{{Infobox aircraft begin
  |name= DH.98 Mosquito
  |image= File:De Havilland DH-98 Mosquito ExCC.jpg{{!}}border
  |long caption= Mosquito B Mk IV [[United Kingdom military aircraft serials|serial]] ''DK338'' before delivery to [[No. 105 Squadron RAF|105 Squadron]] – this aircraft was used on several of 105 Squadron's low-altitude daylight bombing operations during 1943.
}}{{Infobox aircraft type
  |type={{plainlist|
*[[Light bomber]]
*[[Fighter-bomber]]
*[[Night fighter]]
*[[Maritime strike aircraft]]
*[[photo-reconnaissance]] aircraft}}
  |manufacturer=[[de Havilland|de Havilland Aircraft Company]]
  |designer=
  |first flight=25 November 1940&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 8.&quot;&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt;
  |introduction=15 November 1941&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.raf.mod.uk/history/raftimeline1941.cfm |title=Archived copy |access-date=11 July 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150708113138/http://www.raf.mod.uk/history/raftimeline1941.cfm |archive-date=8 July 2015 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
  |retired=
  |status= Retired
  |primary user=[[Royal Air Force]]
  |more users = {{plainlist|
*[[Royal Canadian Air Force]]
*[[Royal Australian Air Force]]
*[[United States Army Air Forces]]&lt;!-- Limited to THREE (3) 'more users' here (4 total users). --&gt;}}
  |produced=1940–1950
  |number built=7,781&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 163.&quot;&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 163.&lt;/ref&gt;
  |unit cost=£9,100 (1951) &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com.au/books?id=2sQwBQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA51&amp;lpg=PA51|title=The Political Economy of Aerospace Industries: A Key Driver of Growth and International Competitiveness?|last=Hartley|first=Keith|date=2014-11-28|publisher=Edward Elgar Publishing|isbn=978-1-78254-496-8|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;
  |variants with their own articles=
}}
|}

The '''de Havilland DH.98 Mosquito''' is a British twin-engined, [[shoulder-wing]]ed [[multirole combat aircraft]], introduced during the [[World War II|Second World War]]. Unusual in that its frame is constructed mostly of wood, it was nicknamed the &quot;Wooden Wonder&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Price 2009, p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; or &quot;Mossie&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Hanson, Dave. [http://www.warbirdalley.com/mossie.htm &quot;deHavilland DH 98 Mosquito.&quot;] ''warbirdalley.com''.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Max Aitken, 1st Baron Beaverbrook|Lord Beaverbrook]], Minister of Aircraft Production, nicknamed it &quot;Freeman's Folly&quot;, alluding to Air Chief Marshal Sir [[Wilfrid Freeman]], who defended [[Geoffrey de Havilland]] and his design concept against orders to scrap the project.&lt;ref&gt;Birtles 2017, ch. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1941, it was one of the fastest operational aircraft in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 21.&quot;&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt;

Originally conceived as an unarmed [[fast bomber]], the Mosquito's use evolved during the war into many roles, including low- to medium-altitude daytime [[tactical bomber]], high-altitude [[night bomber]], [[Pathfinder (RAF)|pathfinder]], [[Day fighter|day]] or [[night fighter]], [[fighter-bomber]], [[intruder (air combat)|intruder]], [[maritime strike aircraft|maritime strike]], and [[photo-reconnaissance]] aircraft. It was also used by the [[British Overseas Airways Corporation]]  as a fast transport to carry small, high-value cargo to and from [[Neutrality (international relations)|neutral countries]] through [[German-occupied Europe|enemy-controlled airspace]].&lt;ref&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, p. 338.&lt;/ref&gt; The crew of two, pilot and navigator, sat side by side. A single passenger could ride in the aircraft's bomb bay when necessary.&lt;ref name=Aeroplane0415/&gt;

The Mosquito FBVI was often flown in special raids, such as [[Operation Jericho]] – an attack on Amiens Prison in early 1944, and precision attacks against military intelligence, security, and police facilities (such as [[Gestapo]] headquarters). On 30 January 1943, the 10th anniversary of the [[Nazi Party|Nazis]]' seizure of power, a morning Mosquito attack knocked out the main Berlin broadcasting station while [[Hermann Göring]] was speaking, putting his speech off the air.
 
The Mosquito flew with the [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF) and other air forces in the [[European Theatre of World War II|European]], [[Mediterranean, Middle East and African theatres of World War II|Mediterranean]] and [[Italian Campaign (World War II)|Italian]] theatres. The Mosquito was also operated by the RAF in the [[South-East Asian theatre of World War II|Southeast Asian theatre]] and by the [[Royal Australian Air Force]]  based in [[Maluku Islands|the Halmaheras]] and [[Borneo]] during the [[Pacific War]]. During the 1950s, the RAF replaced the Mosquito with the jet-powered [[English Electric Canberra]].

==Development==
[[File:DH88 Comet G-ACSS Grosvenor House (6741273695).jpg|thumb|Construction concepts pioneered in the [[De Havilland DH.88|DH.88 Comet]] were later used in the Mosquito.]]
By the early to mid-1930s, [[de Havilland]] had a reputation for innovative high-speed aircraft with the [[de Havilland DH.88|DH.88 Comet]] racer. The later [[de Havilland Albatross|DH.91 Albatross]] airliner pioneered the composite wood construction used for the Mosquito. The 22-passenger Albatross could cruise at {{convert|210|mph|km/h}} at {{convert|11000|ft|m}}, {{cvt|100|mph|km/h}} faster than the [[Handley Page H.P.42]] and other biplanes it was replacing.&lt;ref&gt;Stroud 1990, p. 369.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|Part 2 of article is in the July 1990 volume.|group=nb}} The wooden [[monocoque]] construction not only saved weight and compensated for the low power of the [[de Havilland Gipsy Twelve]] engines used by this aircraft, but also simplified production and reduced construction time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 9.&quot;&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Air Ministry bomber requirements and concepts===
On 8 September 1936, the British Air Ministry issued [[list of Air Ministry specifications|Specification]] P.13/36, which called for a twin-engined, medium bomber capable of carrying a bomb load of {{cvt|3,000|lb|kg}} for {{cvt|3000|mi|km}} with a maximum speed of {{cvt|275|mph|km/h|round=5}} at {{cvt|15000|ft|m}}; a maximum bomb load of {{cvt|8000|lb|kg}} that could be carried over shorter ranges was also specified.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharb30&quot;&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, p. 30.&lt;/ref&gt; Aviation firms entered heavy designs with new high-powered engines and multiple defensive turrets, leading to the production of the [[Avro Manchester]] and [[Handley Page Halifax]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharb31&quot;&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 1937, as a comparison to P.13/36, [[George Volkert]], the chief designer of [[Handley Page]], put forward the concept of a fast, unarmed bomber. In 20 pages, Volkert planned an aerodynamically clean, medium bomber to carry {{convert|3000|lb|kg}} of bombs at a cruising speed of {{cvt|300|mph|km/h|round=5}}. Support existed in the RAF and Air Ministry; Captain R N Liptrot, Research Director Aircraft 3, appraised Volkert's design, calculating that its top speed would exceed that of the new [[Supermarine Spitfire]], but counter-arguments held that although such a design had merit, it would not necessarily be faster than enemy fighters for long.&lt;ref&gt;Buttler 2004, pp. 76–77.&lt;/ref&gt; The ministry was also considering using non-[[strategic]] materials for aircraft production, which, in 1938, had led to specification B.9/38 and the [[Armstrong Whitworth Albemarle]] medium bomber, largely constructed from spruce and plywood attached to a steel-tube frame. The idea of a small, fast bomber gained support at a much earlier stage than is sometimes acknowledged, though the Air Ministry likely envisaged it using light alloy components.&lt;ref&gt;Buttler 2004, pp. 74, 77.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Inception of the de Havilland fast bomber===
[[File:Albatross 1938 prototype.jpg|thumb|One of de Havilland's proposals was to adapt the [[de Havilland Albatross]] design to a fast bomber.]]
Based on his experience with the Albatross, Geoffrey de Havilland believed that a bomber with a good aerodynamic design and smooth, minimal skin area, would exceed the P.13/36 specification.&lt;ref name=&quot;Birtles 2017, ch. 2&quot;&gt;Birtles 2017, ch. 2.&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, adapting the Albatross principles could save time. In April 1938, performance estimates were produced for a twin [[Rolls-Royce Merlin]]-powered DH.91, with the [[Bristol Hercules]] ([[radial engine]]) and [[Napier Sabre]] ([[H-engine]]) as alternatives.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharb30&quot;/&gt; On 7 July 1938,  de Havilland wrote to [[Air Marshal]] [[Wilfrid Freeman]], the Air Council's member for Research and Development, discussing the specification and arguing that in war, shortages of aluminium and steel would occur, but supplies of wood-based products were &quot;adequate.&quot;{{refn|Note the use of the word &quot;adequate&quot;. A cypher dated 2 October 1941, cited by Connor&lt;ref name=&quot;Connor-Madison, pp. 2-3.&quot;/&gt; reveals that Britain was desperately short: – &quot;One of four airscrew factories has run out of imported veneers... veneers for air frame plywood would enable... construction to continue till December only... direct contact between Ministry of Supply experts and U.S.A. suppliers of aircraft veneers will be necessary for next three months. Otherwise essential war production... will be further curtailed.&quot; This sheds a new light on the oft-repeated account that the use of wood avoided reliance on scarce materials. One valid claim was that a different sector of workforce was engaged. Furthermore at the time, DH's experience was almost exclusively in the use of timber.&lt;ref&gt;Cypher dated 2 October 1941: – To – British Supply Council in North America. From – Supply Committee. LONUS 13, National Archives. London.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}} Although inferior in [[Tension (physics)|tension]], the [[Specific strength|strength-to-weight ratio]] of wood is equal to or better than light alloys or steel, hence this approach was feasible.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharb30&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Birtles 2017, ch. 2&quot;/&gt;

A follow-up letter to Freeman on 27 July said that the P.13/36 specification could not be met by a twin Merlin-powered aircraft and either the top speed or load capacity would be compromised, depending on which was paramount. For example, a larger, slower, turret-armed aircraft would have a range of {{convert|1500|mi|km}} carrying a 4,000&amp;nbsp;lb bomb load, with a maximum of {{cvt|260|mph|km/h}} at {{convert|19000|ft|m}}, and a cruising speed of {{convert|230|mph|km/h}} at {{convert|18000|ft|m}}. De Havilland believed that a compromise, including eliminating surplus equipment, would improve matters.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharb30&quot;/&gt; On 4 October 1938, de Havilland projected the performance of another design based on the Albatross, powered by two Merlin&amp;nbsp;Xs, with a three-man crew and six or eight forward-firing guns, plus one or two manually operated guns and a tail turret. Based on a total loaded weight of {{convert|19000|lb|kg|abbr=on}}, it would have a top speed of {{convert|300|mph|km/h|abbr=on}} and cruising speed of {{convert|268|mph|km/h|abbr=on}} at {{convert|22500|ft|m|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharb31&quot; /&gt;

Still believing this could be improved, and after examining more concepts based on the Albatross and the new all-metal [[de Havilland Flamingo|DH.95 Flamingo]], de Havilland settled on designing a new aircraft that would be aerodynamically clean, wooden, and powered by the Merlin, which offered substantial future development.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharb31&quot;/&gt; The new design would be faster than foreseeable enemy [[fighter aircraft]], and could dispense with a defensive armament, which would slow it and make interception or losses to antiaircraft guns more likely. Instead, high speed and good manoeuvrability would make  evading fighters and ground fire easier.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharb31&quot;/&gt; The lack of turrets simplified production, reduced drag and reduced production time, with a delivery rate far in advance of competing designs. Without armament, the crew could be reduced to a pilot and navigator. Whereas contemporary RAF design philosophy favoured well-armed heavy bombers, this mode of design was more akin to the German philosophy of the ''[[Schnellbomber]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Batchelor and Lowe 2008, p. 5.&quot;&gt;Batchelor and Lowe 2008, p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt; At a meeting in early October 1938 with Geoffrey de Havilland and Charles Walker (de Havilland's chief engineer), the Air Ministry showed little interest, and instead asked de Havilland to build wings for other bombers as a subcontractor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Batchelor and Lowe 2008, p. 6.&quot;&gt;Batchelor and Lowe 2008, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt;

By September 1939, de Havilland had produced preliminary estimates for single- and twin-engined variations of light-bomber designs using different engines, speculating on the effects of defensive armament on their designs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Buttler, p. 78&quot;&gt;Buttler 2004, p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt; One design, completed on 6 September, was for an aircraft powered by a single {{convert|2000|hp|kW|abbr=on}}  Napier Sabre, with a wingspan of {{cvt|47|ft|m}} and capable of carrying a {{convert|1000|lb|kg|adj=on}} bomb load {{convert|1500|mi|km}}. On 20 September, in another letter to Wilfrid Freeman, de Havilland wrote &quot;...{{nbsp}}we believe that we could produce a twin-engine[d] bomber which would have a performance so outstanding that little defensive equipment would be needed.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Buttler, p. 78&quot;/&gt; By 4 October, work had progressed to a twin-engined light bomber with a wingspan of {{convert|51|ft|m|abbr=on}}, and powered by Merlin or Griffon engines, the Merlin favoured because of availability.&lt;ref name=&quot;Buttler, p. 78&quot;/&gt; On 7 October 1939, a month into the war, the nucleus of a design team under [[Ronald Eric Bishop|Eric Bishop]] moved to the security and secrecy of [[De Havilland Aircraft Heritage Centre#Salisbury Hall|Salisbury Hall]] to work on what was later known as the DH.98.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharb34&quot;&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, p. 34.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|Bishop had worked on the DH.88 Comet and the Albatross under de Havilland's then-chief designer A. E. Hagg.&lt;ref&gt;Bishop 1995,{{page needed|date=January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}} For more versatility, Bishop made provision for four 20&amp;nbsp;mm cannon in the forward half of the [[bomb bay]], under the cockpit, firing via blast tubes and troughs under the fuselage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 11.&quot;&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt;

The DH.98 was too radical for the ministry, which wanted a heavily armed, multirole aircraft, combining medium bomber, reconnaissance, and general-purpose roles, as well as capable of carrying torpedoes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Batchelor and Lowe 2008, p. 6.&quot;/&gt; With outbreak of war, the ministry became more receptive, but still sceptical about an unarmed bomber. It thought the Germans would produce fighters faster than expected.&lt;ref&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, pp. 31–32.&lt;/ref&gt; It suggested two forward- and two rear-firing machine guns for defence.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bow0510&quot;&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt; The ministry also opposed a two-man bomber, wanting at least a third crewman to reduce the work of the others on long flights.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 11.&quot;/&gt; The Air Council added further requirements, such as remotely controlled guns, a top speed of {{convert|275|mph|km/h|abbr=on|round=5}} at 15,000&amp;nbsp;ft on two-thirds engine power, and a range of {{convert|3000|mi|km|abbr=on}} with a 4,000-lb bomb load.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bow0510&quot;/&gt; To appease the ministry, de Havilland built mock-ups with a gun turret just aft of the cockpit, but apart from this compromise, de Havilland made no changes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 11.&quot;/&gt;

On 12 November, at a meeting considering fast-bomber ideas put forward by de Havilland, [[Blackburn Aircraft|Blackburn]], and [[Bristol Aeroplane Company|Bristol]], Air Marshal Freeman directed de Havilland to produce a fast aircraft, powered initially by Merlin engines, with options of using progressively more powerful engines, including the [[Rolls-Royce Griffon]] and the [[Napier Sabre]]. Although estimates were presented for a slightly larger Griffon-powered aircraft, armed with a four-gun tail turret, Freeman got the requirement for defensive weapons dropped, and a draft requirement was raised calling for a high-speed, light-reconnaissance bomber capable of {{convert|400|mph|km/h|abbr=on|round=5}} at 18,000&amp;nbsp;ft.&lt;ref&gt;Buttler 2004, p. 79.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 12 December, the [[Vice-Chief of the Air Staff (United Kingdom)|Vice-Chief of the Air Staff]], Director General of Research and Development, and the [[Air Officer Commanding|Air Officer Commanding-in-Chief]] (AOC-in-C) of [[RAF Bomber Command]] met to finalise the design and decide how to fit it in the RAF's aims. The AOC-in-C would not accept an unarmed bomber, but insisted on its suitability for reconnaissance missions with F8 or [[F24 camera]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 12.&quot;&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt; After company representatives, the ministry, and the RAF's operational commands examined a full-scale mock-up at Hatfield on 29 December 1939, the project received backing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bu80&quot;&gt;Buttler 2004, p. 80.&lt;/ref&gt; This was confirmed on 1 January 1940, when Freeman chaired a meeting with Geoffrey de Havilland, John Buchanan (Deputy of Aircraft Production), and John Connolly (Buchanan's chief of staff). De Havilland claimed the DH.98 was the &quot;fastest bomber in the world...it must be useful&quot;. Freeman supported it for RAF service, ordering a single prototype for an unarmed bomber to specification B.1/40/dh, which called for a light bomber/reconnaissance aircraft powered by two {{convert|1280|hp|kW|abbr=on}} Rolls-Royce RM3SM (an early designation for the Merlin 21) with [[Meredith effect|ducted radiators]], capable of carrying a {{convert|1000|lb|kg|adj=on}} bomb load.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharb34&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 12.&quot;/&gt; The aircraft was to have a speed of {{cvt|400|mph|km/h}} at {{convert|24000|ft|m}} and a cruising speed of {{cvt|325|mph|km/h|round=5}} at {{convert|26500|ft|m}} with a range of {{convert|1500|mi|km}} at {{convert|25000|ft|m}} on full tanks. Maximum service ceiling was to be {{convert|32000|ft|m}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 12.&quot;/&gt;

On 1 March 1940, [[Air Marshal]] [[Roderic Hill]] issued a contract under Specification B.1/40, for 50 bomber-reconnaissance variants of the DH.98; this contract included the prototype, which was given the [[United Kingdom aircraft test serials|factory serial]] ''E0234''.&lt;ref&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Price 2009, p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt; In May 1940, specification F.21/40 was issued, calling for a long-range fighter armed with four 20-mm cannon and four .303 machine guns in the nose, after which de Havilland was authorised to build a prototype of a fighter version of the DH.98. After debate, that this prototype, given the [[United Kingdom military aircraft serials|military serial number]] ''W4052'', was decided to carry [[Radar in World War II#Airborne Intercept|airborne interception]] (AI) Mk&amp;nbsp;IV equipment as a day and night fighter.{{refn|The term [[radar]], which originated in the USA, was not used by the British until later.|group=nb}} By June 1940, the DH.98 had been named &quot;Mosquito&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bu80&quot; /&gt; Having the fighter variant kept the Mosquito project alive, as criticism still remained within the government and Air Ministry of the usefulness of an unarmed bomber, even after the prototype had shown its capabilities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bu80&quot;/&gt;

===Project Mosquito===
[[File:DE HAVILLAND 1943 Advertisement s.jpg|thumb|upright|right|A 1943 advertisement for de Havilland taken from ''[[Flight International|Flight &amp; Aircraft Engineer]]'' magazine highlights the speed of the B Mk IV.]]
With design of the DH.98 started, mock-ups were built, the most detailed at Salisbury Hall, where ''E0234'' was later constructed. Initially, the concept was for the crew to be enclosed in the fuselage behind a [[stepless cockpit|transparent nose]] (similar to the Bristol Blenheim or [[Heinkel He 111]]H), but this was quickly altered to a more solid nose with a conventional canopy.&lt;ref&gt;Thirsk 2006, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt;

The construction of the prototype began in March 1940, but work was cancelled again after the [[Battle of Dunkirk]], when [[Max Aitken, 1st Baron Beaverbrook|Lord Beaverbrook]], as [[Minister of Aircraft Production]], decided no production capacity remained for aircraft like the DH.98, which was not expected to be in service until early 1942.

Beaverbrook told Air Vice-Marshal Freeman that work on the project should stop, but he did not issue a specific instruction, and Freeman ignored the request.&lt;ref&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, p. 37.&lt;/ref&gt; In June 1940, however, Lord Beaverbrook and the Air Staff ordered that production should focus on five existing types, namely the [[Supermarine Spitfire]], [[Hawker Hurricane]] fighter, [[Vickers Wellington]], [[Armstrong-Whitworth Whitley]], and [[Bristol Blenheim]] bombers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 12.&quot; /&gt; Work on the DH.98 prototype stopped. Apparently, the project shut down when the design team were denied materials for the prototype.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jackson 2003, p. 7.&quot;&gt;Jackson 2003, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Mosquito was only reinstated as a priority in July 1940, after de Havilland's general manager, L.C.L. Murray, promised Lord Beaverbrook 50 Mosquitos by December 1941. This was only after Beaverbrook was satisfied that Mosquito production would not hinder de Havilland's primary work of producing [[Tiger Moth]] and [[Airspeed Oxford]] trainers, repairing [[Hawker Hurricanes|Hurricanes]], and manufacturing Merlin engines under licence.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jackson 2003, p. 7.&quot;/&gt; In promising Beaverbrook such a number by the end of 1941, de Havilland was taking a gamble, because they were unlikely to be built in such a limited time. As it transpired, only 20 aircraft were built in 1941, but the other 30 were delivered by mid-March 1942.&lt;ref&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, pp. 35–36, 82.&lt;/ref&gt; During the [[Battle of Britain]], interruptions to production due to air raid warnings caused nearly a third of de Havilland's factory time to be lost.&lt;ref&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, work on the prototype went ahead quickly at Salisbury Hall since ''E0234'' was completed by November 1940.&lt;ref&gt;Thirsk 2006, p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the aftermath of the Battle of Britain, the original order was changed to 20 bomber variants and 30 fighters. Whether the fighter version should have dual or single controls, or should carry a turret, was still uncertain, so three prototypes were built: ''W4052'', ''W4053'', and ''W4073''. The second and third, both turret armed, were later disarmed, to become the prototypes for the T.III trainer.&lt;ref&gt;Thirsk 2006, p. 178.&lt;/ref&gt; This caused some delays, since half-built wing components had to be strengthened for the required higher combat loading. The nose sections also had to be changed from a design with a clear [[Poly(methyl methacrylate)|perspex]] bomb-aimer's position, to one with a solid nose housing four .303 machine guns and their ammunition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Batchelor and Lowe 2008, p. 6.&quot;/&gt;

===Prototypes and test flights===
On 3 November 1940, the aircraft, painted in &quot;prototype yellow&quot; and still coded ''E0234'', was dismantled, transported by road to [[Hatfield, Hertfordshire|Hatfield]] and placed in a small, blast-proof assembly building. Two Merlin 21 two-speed, single-stage supercharged engines were installed, driving three-bladed de Havilland Hydromatic constant-speed [[controllable-pitch propeller]]s. Engine runs were made on 19 November.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 18.&quot;/&gt; On 24 November, taxiing trials were carried out by [[Geoffrey de Havilland Jr.]], the de Havilland [[test pilot]]. On 25 November, the prototype made its first flight, piloted by de Havilland Jr., accompanied by John E. Walker, the chief engine installation designer.{{refn|This first flight was made only 11 months after the start of detailed design work.&lt;ref name=&quot;Batchelor and Lowe 2008, p. 6.&quot; /&gt;|group=nb}}

For this maiden flight, ''E0234'', weighing {{convert|14150|lb|kg}}, took off from the grass airstrip at the Hatfield site. The takeoff was reported as &quot;straightforward and easy&quot; and the undercarriage was not retracted until a considerable altitude was attained.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thir25&quot;&gt;Thirsk 2006, p. 25.&lt;/ref&gt; The aircraft reached {{cvt|220|mph|abbr=on|round=5}}, with the only problem being the undercarriage doors – which were operated by [[bungee cord]]s attached to the main undercarriage legs – that remained open by some {{convert|12|in|mm}} at that speed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thir25&quot;/&gt; This problem persisted for some time. The left wing of ''E0234'' also had a tendency to drag to port slightly, so a [[Bracing (aeronautics)|rigging]] adjustment, i.e., a slight change in the angle of the wing, was carried out before further flights.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 18.&quot;&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|''E0234'' had a wingspan of {{convert|52|ft|2|in|abbr=on}} and was the only Mosquito to be built with Handley Page [[Leading edge slats|slats]] on the outer leading edges of the wings. Test flights showed that these were not needed and they were disconnected and faired over with doped fabric (these slats can still be seen on ''W4050'').&lt;ref&gt;Thirsk 2006, pp. 33, 269.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}}

[[File:De Havilland Mosquito Prototype.jpg|thumb|left|Mosquito prototype ''W4050'' landing after a test flight on 10 January 1941: Four test flights were flown that day.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thirsk 2006, p. 31&quot;&gt;Thirsk 2006, p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
On 5 December 1940, the prototype, with the military serial number ''[[United Kingdom military aircraft serials|W4050]]'', experienced tail buffeting at speeds between {{cvt|240|and|255|mph|round=5}}. The pilot noticed this most in the control column, with handling becoming more difficult. During testing on 10 December, wool tufts were attached to suspect areas to investigate the direction of airflow. The conclusion was that the airflow separating from the rear section of the inner engine [[nacelle]]s was disturbed, leading to a localised [[Stall (flight)|stall]] and the disturbed airflow was striking the tailplane, causing buffeting. To smooth the air flow and deflect it from forcefully striking the tailplane, nonretractable [[Leading edge slot|slots]] fitted to the inner engine nacelles and to the leading edge of the tailplane were tested.&lt;ref&gt;Thirsk 2006, pp. 27–29.&lt;/ref&gt; These slots and wing-root fairings fitted to the forward fuselage and leading edge of the radiator intakes, stopped some of the vibration experienced, but did not cure the tailplane buffeting.&lt;ref&gt;Thirsk 2006, pp. 28–29.&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 1941, buffeting was eliminated by incorporating triangular fillets on the trailing edge of the wings and lengthening the nacelles, the trailing edge of which curved up to fair into the fillet some {{convert|10|in|abbr=on}} behind the wing's trailing edge; this meant the [[Flap (aircraft)|flaps]] had to be divided into inboard and outboard sections.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 19.&quot;&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|On ''W4050'', the nacelle extensions were not as long as those fitted to production Mosquitoes; nacelles of the definitive shape and length were first fitted to the fighter prototype ''W4052''. The extended nacelles and fillets were not fitted to the first nine PR Mk&amp;nbsp;Is, some of which were converted to B Mk&amp;nbsp;IV series 1 bombers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thirsk 2006, p. 31&quot;/&gt;|group=nb}} With the buffeting problems largely resolved, [[John Cunningham (RAF officer)|John Cunningham]] flew ''W4050'' on 9 February 1941. He was greatly impressed by the &quot;lightness of the controls and generally pleasant handling characteristics&quot;. Cunningham concluded that when the type was fitted with AI equipment, it might replace the [[Bristol Beaufighter]] night fighter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 19.&quot;/&gt;

During its trials on 16 January 1941, ''W4050'' outpaced a Spitfire at {{convert|6000|ft|abbr=on}}. The original estimates were that as the Mosquito prototype had twice the surface area and over twice the weight of the [[Supermarine Spitfire (early Merlin powered variants)|Spitfire Mk II]], but also with twice its power, the Mosquito would end up being {{cvt|20|mph|km/h|round=5}} faster. Over the next few months, ''W4050'' surpassed this estimate, easily beating the Spitfire Mk II in testing at [[RAF Boscombe Down]] in February 1941, reaching a top speed of {{cvt|392|mph|km/h}} at {{convert|22000|ft|m}} altitude, compared to a top speed of {{cvt|360|mph|km/h}} at {{convert|19500|ft|m}} for the Spitfire.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 8.&quot;/&gt;

On 19 February, official trials began at the [[Aeroplane and Armament Experimental Establishment]] (AAEE) based at [[MoD Boscombe Down|Boscombe Down]], although the de Havilland representative was surprised by a delay in starting the tests.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharb445&quot;&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, pp. 44–45.&lt;/ref&gt; On 24 February, as ''W4050'' taxied across the rough airfield, the tailwheel jammed leading to the fuselage fracturing. Repairs were made by early March, using part of the fuselage of the photo-reconnaissance prototype ''W4051''.{{refn|This accident occurred because the tailwheel unit was unable to [[caster]] properly, a problem solved in June–July 1941 by fitting a [[Dowty Group|Dowty]] unit.|group=nb}} In spite of this setback, the ''Initial Handling Report 767'' issued by the AAEE stated, &quot;The aeroplane is pleasant to fly ... aileron control light and effective{{nbsp}}...&quot; The maximum speed reached was {{cvt|388|mph|abbr=on}} at {{convert|22000|ft|abbr=on}}, with an estimated maximum ceiling of {{convert|34000|ft|abbr=on}} and a maximum rate of climb of {{convert|2880|ft/min|abbr=on}} at {{convert|11500|ft|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharb445&quot; /&gt;

''W4050'' continued to be used for various test programmes, as the experimental &quot;workhorse&quot; for the Mosquito family.&lt;ref&gt;Thirsk 2006, pp. 15–16.&lt;/ref&gt; In late October 1941, it returned to the factory to be fitted with [[Rolls-Royce Merlin|Merlin 61s]], the first production Merlins fitted with a two-speed, two-stage supercharger. The first flight with the new engines was on 20 June 1942.&lt;ref&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt; ''W4050'' recorded a maximum speed of {{cvt|428|mph|abbr=on}} at {{convert|28500|ft|abbr=on}} (fitted with straight-through air intakes with snow guards, engines in F.S. gear) and {{convert|437|mph|abbr=on}} at {{convert|29200|ft|abbr=on}} without snow guards.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thr34&quot;&gt;Thirsk 2006, p. 34.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|Snowguards were small, oval grids of steel mesh attached in front of the opening of the carburettor air intakes. They were designed to stop ice forming in the mouth of the intake when the aircraft operated in cold weather, or flew in the cold temperatures at high altitude.|group=nb}} In October 1942, in connection with development work on the NF Mk XV, ''W4050'' was fitted with extended wingtips, increasing the span to {{convert|59|ft|2|in|abbr=on}}, first flying in this configuration on 8 December.&lt;ref&gt;Thirsk 2006, p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt; Fitted with high-altitude-rated, two-stage, two-speed Merlin&amp;nbsp;77s, it reached {{cvt|439|mph|km/h}} in December 1943.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 21.&quot; /&gt; Soon after these flights, ''W4050'' was grounded and scheduled to be scrapped, but instead served as an instructional airframe at Hatfield. In September 1958, ''W4050'' was returned to the Salisbury Hall hangar where it was built, restored to its original configuration, and became one of the primary exhibits of the [[de Havilland Aircraft Heritage Centre]].&lt;ref&gt;Thirsk 2006, 36–38.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gfXNXGGNRws Time-lapse footage of restoration work on ''W4050'', 9 January 2011.] Retrieved: 3 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:De Havilland Mosquito - Prototype 1.jpg|thumb|''W4050'' being restored at the [[de Havilland Aircraft Heritage Centre]] near St Albans]]
''W4051'', which was designed from the outset to be the prototype for the photo-reconnaissance versions of the Mosquito, was slated to make its first flight in early 1941. However, the fuselage fracture in ''W4050'' meant that ''W4051's'' fuselage was used as a replacement; ''W4051'' was then rebuilt using a production standard fuselage and first flew on 10 June 1941. This prototype continued to use the short engine nacelles, single-piece trailing-edge flaps, and the {{convert|19|ft|5.5|in|abbr=on}} &quot;No. 1&quot;  tailplane used by ''W4050'', but had production-standard {{convert|54|ft|2|in|abbr=on}} wings and became the only Mosquito prototype to fly operationally.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thirsk 2006, p. 269&quot;&gt;Thirsk 2006, p. 269.&lt;/ref&gt;

Construction of the fighter prototype, ''W4052'', was also carried out at the secret Salisbury Hall facility. It was powered by {{convert|1460|hp|kW|abbr=on}} Merlin&amp;nbsp;21s, and had an altered canopy structure with a flat, bullet-proof windscreen; the solid nose had mounted four .303 British [[M1919 Browning machine gun|Browning]] machine guns and their ammunition boxes, accessible by a large, sideways hinged panel.&lt;ref&gt;Thirsk 2006, p. 125.&lt;/ref&gt; Four 20-mm [[Hispano-Suiza HS.404|Hispano&amp;nbsp;Mk II]] cannon were housed in a compartment under the cockpit floor with the breeches projecting into the bomb bay and the automatic bomb bay doors were replaced by manually operated bay doors, which incorporated cartridge ejector chutes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thirsk 2006, pp. 125, 134&quot;&gt;Thirsk 2006, pp. 125, 134.&lt;/ref&gt;

As a day and night fighter, prototype ''W4052'' was equipped with AI Mk&amp;nbsp;IV equipment, complete with an &quot;arrowhead&quot; transmission aerial mounted between the central Brownings and receiving aerials through the outer wing tips, and it was painted in black RDM2a &quot;Special Night&quot; finish.&lt;ref&gt;Thirsk 2006, pp. 124–127.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|The RDM2a finish was notoriously rough and  hard to maintain; tests later proved that it could cut the top speed of a Mosquito by up to {{cvt|26|mph|abbr=on}}, and by March 1942, was replaced by the black &quot;Night Type S&quot; (smooth) finish.&lt;ref&gt;Thirsk 2006, p. 134.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}} It was also the first prototype constructed with the extended engine nacelles.&lt;ref&gt;Thirsk 2006, p. 126.&lt;/ref&gt; ''W4052'' was later tested with other modifications, including bomb racks, drop tanks, [[barrage balloon]] cable cutters in the leading edge of the wings, Hamilton airscrews and braking propellers, and drooping aileron systems that enabled steep approaches and a larger rudder tab. The prototype continued to serve as a test machine until it was scrapped on 28 January 1946.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 21.&quot; /&gt; ''4055'' flew the first operational Mosquito flight on 17 September 1941.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 20.&quot; /&gt;

During flight testing, the Mosquito prototypes were modified to test a number of configurations. ''W4050'' was fitted with a turret behind the cockpit for drag tests, after which the idea was abandoned in July 1941. ''W4052'' had the first version of the [[Fairey Aviation Company|Youngman Frill]] airbrake fitted to the fighter prototype. The frill was mounted around the fuselage behind the wing and was opened by bellows and [[venturi effect]] to provide rapid deceleration during interceptions and was tested between January and August 1942, but was also abandoned when  lowering the undercarriage was found to have the same effect with less buffeting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 20.&quot;/&gt;
&lt;!--- Something is missing here--- It was used to eliminate problems on ''W4052''. Most of this related to the former's exhaust and armament systems. Flash eliminators had to be fitted to the NF.II to prevent the crew from being blinded by muzzle flash during the firing of the weapons.---&gt;

===Production plans and American interest===
The Air Ministry authorised mass production plans on 21 June 1941, by which time the Mosquito had become one of the world's fastest operational aircraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 21.&quot;/&gt; It ordered 19 photo-reconnaissance (PR) models and 176 fighters. A further 50 were unspecified; in July 1941,  these were confirmed to be unarmed fast bombers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 21.&quot;/&gt; By the end of January 1942, contracts had been awarded for 1,378 Mosquitos of all variants, including 20 T.III trainers and 334 FB.VI bombers. Another 400 were to be built by [[de Havilland Canada]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 24.&quot;&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 20 April 1941, ''W4050'' was demonstrated to Lord Beaverbrook, the [[Minister of Aircraft Production]]. The Mosquito made a series of flights, including one rolling climb on one engine. Also present were US General [[Henry H. Arnold]] and his aide [[Major]] [[Elwood Quesada]], who wrote &quot;I ... recall the first time I saw the Mosquito as being impressed by its performance, which we were aware of. We were impressed by the appearance of the airplane that looks fast usually is fast, and the Mosquito was, by the standards of the time, an extremely well-streamlined airplane, and it was highly regarded, highly respected.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 19.&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=d7pNBSRkEiQ &quot;WWII US Film on Mosquito.&quot;] ''youtube.com.'' Retrieved: 3 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

The trials set up future production plans between Britain, [[Australia]], and [[Canada]]. Six days later, Arnold returned to America with a full set of manufacturer's drawings. As a result of his report, five companies (Beech, [[Curtiss-Wright]], [[Fairchild Aircraft|Fairchild]], Fleetwings, and Hughes) were asked to evaluate the de Havilland data. The report by Beech Aircraft summed up the general view: &quot;It appears as though this airplane has sacrificed serviceability, structural strength, ease of construction and flying characteristics in an attempt to use construction material which is not suitable for the manufacture of efficient airplanes.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Mosquito the Original Multi Role Aircraft|last=Simons|first=Graham M.|publisher=Pen &amp; Sword Aviation|year=2011|isbn=9781844682607}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Americans did not pursue the proposal for licensed production, the consensus arguing that the [[Lockheed P-38 Lightning]] could fulfill the same duties. However, Arnold urged the [[United States Army Air Forces]] (USAAF) to evaluate the design even if they would not adopt it. On 12 December 1941, after the [[attack on Pearl Harbor]], the USAAF requested one airframe for this purpose.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 20.&quot;&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Design and manufacture==
===Overview===
[[File:MossyCloseup42.jpg|thumb|B Mk IV nose closeup showing bombsight and clear nose, plus engine nacelles and undercarriage]]
While timber construction was considered outmoded by some, de Havilland claimed that their successes with techniques used for the DH 91 Albatross could lead to a fast, light bomber using monocoque-sandwich shell construction.&lt;ref&gt;Birtles 2017, chs. 2, 3.&lt;/ref&gt; Arguments in favor of this included speed of prototyping, rapid development, minimisation of jig-building time, and employment of a separate category of workforce. At the same time, they had to fight conservative Air Ministry views on defensive armament. Guns and gun turrets would spoil the streamlining, losing speed and manoeuvrability. The ply-balsa-ply monocoque fuselage and one-piece wings with doped fabric covering gave smooth aerodynamic performance and low weight, combined with strength and stiffness. Whilst submitting these arguments, Geoffrey de Havilland funded his private venture until the eleventh hour. It was a success beyond all expectations. The initial bomber and photo-reconnaissance versions were extremely fast, whilst the armament of subsequent variants might be regarded as primarily offensive.

The most-produced variant, [[British military aircraft designation systems|designated]] the FB Mk VI (Fighter-bomber Mark 6), was powered by two Merlin Mk 23 or Mk 25 engines driving three-bladed de Havilland hydromatic propellers.&lt;!---Both propellers and airscrews have been used, consolidate on one term.---&gt; The typical fixed armament for an FB Mk VI was four Browning .303 machine guns and four 20-mm Hispano cannon, while the offensive load consisted of up to {{convert|2000|lb|kg}} of bombs, or eight RP-3 unguided rockets.&lt;ref&gt;Batchelor and Lowe 2008, p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Performance===
The design was noted for light and effective control surfaces that provided good manoeuvrability, but required that the rudder not be used aggressively at high speeds. Poor aileron control at low speeds when landing and taking off was also a problem for inexperienced crews.&lt;ref&gt;Air Ministry 1945, pp. 28–29. (FB 6 notes)&lt;/ref&gt; For flying at low speeds, the flaps had to be set at 15°, speed reduced to {{cvt|200|mph|km/h}}, and [[Revolutions per minute|rpm]] set to 2,650. The speed could be reduced to an acceptable {{cvt|150|mph|km/h}} for low-speed flying.&lt;ref name=&quot;Air Ministry 1945, p. 29. (FB 6 notes)&quot;/&gt; For cruising, the optimum speed for obtaining maximum range was {{cvt|200|mph|km/h}} at {{convert|17000|lb|abbr=on}} weight.&lt;ref name=&quot;Air Ministry 1945, p. 29. (FB 6 notes)&quot;/&gt;

The Mosquito had a low stalling speed of {{cvt|120|mph|km/h}} with undercarriage and flaps raised. When both were lowered, the stalling speed decreased from {{cvt|120|to|100|mph|km/h}}. Stall speed at normal approach angle and conditions was {{cvt|100|to|110|mph|km/h}}. Warning of the stall was given by buffeting and would occur {{cvt|12|mph|km/h}} before stall was reached. The conditions and impact of the stall were not severe. The wing did not drop unless the control column was pulled back. The nose drooped gently and recovery was easy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Air Ministry 1945, p. 29. (FB 6 notes)&quot;&gt;Air Ministry 1945, p. 29. (FB 6 notes).&lt;/ref&gt;

Early on in the Mosquito's operational life, the intake shrouds that were to cool the exhausts on production aircraft overheated. Flame dampers prevented exhaust glow on night operations, but they had an effect on performance. Multiple ejector and open-ended exhaust stubs helped solve the problem and were used in the PR.VIII, B.IX, and B.XVI variants. This increased speed performance in the B.IX alone by {{cvt|10|to|13|mph|km/h}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 21.&quot;/&gt;

===Fuselage===
The oval-section fuselage was a frameless monocoque shell built in two vertically separate halves formed over a [[mahogany]] or [[concrete]] mould.{{refn| Both types of moulds were used, at certain times and in different factories. |group=nb}} Pressure was applied with [[band clamp]]s. The shell sandwich skins comprised birch three-ply outers, with cores of Ecuadorean [[balsa]].{{refn| This was specially graded for density to a mean of 9 lb. per cu. ft., since this species is highly variable and the cores comprised a significant proportion of the total weight. |group=nb}} In many generally smaller but vital areas, such as around apertures and attachment zones, stronger timbers, including aircraft-quality spruce, replaced the balsa core. The main areas of the sandwich skin were only {{convert|14|mm|in|order=flip}} thick.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aviation, 1944,&quot;&gt;Aviation, May and June 1944, Vol. 43, Nos. 5 &amp; 6, McGraw Hill, New York; Design Analysis No 6, DeHavilland Mosquito, Online PDF courtesy of J.L. McClellan, 2005, [http://legendsintheirowntime.com/LiTOT/Mosquito/Mosquito_draft.pdf accessed 23 August 2017]&lt;/ref&gt; Together with various forms of wood reinforcement, often of laminated construction, the sandwich skin gave great stiffness and torsional resistance. The separate fuselage halves speeded construction, permitting access by personnel working in parallel with others, as the work progressed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 15.&quot;&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;

Work on the separate half-fuselages included installation of control mechanisms and cabling. Screwed inserts into the inner skins that would be under stress in service were reinforced using round shear plates made from a fabric-Bakelite composite.&lt;ref&gt;Aviation, 1944 p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt;
 
Transverse bulkheads were also compositely built-up with several species of timber, plywood, and balsa. Seven vertically halved bulkheads were installed within each moulded fuselage shell before the main &quot;boxing up&quot; operation. Bulkhead number seven was especially strongly built, since it carried the fitments and transmitted the aerodynamic loadings for the tailplane and rudder.&lt;ref&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, p. 378.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn| The full details of bulkhead construction are too complicated to describe concisely in words alone; see the &quot;Aviation&quot; reference for excellent detailed diagrams.&lt;ref&gt;Aviation, 1944 pp. 6–8.&lt;/ref&gt; Bulkhead 7 entailed the use of special four-ply birch with 45° layup, and even some additional strengthening using walnut wood.|group=nb}} The fuselage had a large ventral section cut-out, strongly reinforced, that allowed the fuselage to be lowered onto the wing centre-section at a later stage of assembly.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aviation, 1944 p. 6&quot;&gt;Aviation, 1944 p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt;

For early production aircraft, the structural assembly adhesive was [[casein]]-based. At a later stage, this was replaced by &quot;[[Aerolite (adhesive)|Aerolite]]&quot;, a synthetic [[urea-formaldehyde]] type, which was more durable.&lt;ref&gt;Thirsk 2006, p. 43.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn| Aerolite was developed by Dr. [[Norman de Bruyne]] at [[Aero Research Limited]] (ARL)&lt;ref&gt;[http://uksaa-www.me.ic.ac.uk/awards.html &quot;The De Bruyne Medal.&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131019161418/http://uksaa-www.me.ic.ac.uk/awards.html |date=19 October 2013 }} ''Society for Adhesion and Adhesives'' .&lt;/ref&gt; The de Havilland company also pioneered the use of [[Radio frequency heating|radio-frequency heating]] to accelerate curing of the adhesive.&lt;ref&gt;Mujumdar 1992, p. 131.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}} To provide for the edge joints for the fuselage halves, zones near the outer edges of the shells had their balsa sandwich cores replaced by much stronger inner laminations of birch plywood. For the bonding together of the two halves (&quot;boxing up&quot;), a longitudinal cut was machined into these edges. The profile of this cut was a form of V-groove. Part of the edge bonding process also included adding further longitudinal plywood lap strips on the outside of the shells.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 15.&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aviation, 1944 p. 6&quot;/&gt; The half bulkheads of each shell were bonded to their corresponding pair in a similar way. Two laminated wooden clamps were used in the after portion of the fuselage to provide supports during this complex gluing work. The resulting large structural components had to be kept completely still and held in the correct environment until the glue cured.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 15.&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jackson 2003, p. 8.&quot;&gt;Jackson 2003, p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt;

For finishing, a covering of [[aircraft dope|dope]]d [[madapollam]] (a fine, plain-woven cotton) fabric was stretched tightly over the shell and several coats of red, followed by silver dope, were added, followed by the final camouflage paint.&lt;ref&gt;Thirsk 2006, p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Wing===
[[File:Mosquito nmusaf.jpg|right|thumb|A preserved Mosquito at the U.S. Air Force Museum (former TT Mk 35 which was restored to B Mk XVI configuration).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalmuseum.af.mil/Visit/Museum-Exhibits/Fact-Sheets/Display/Article/196281/de-havilland-dh-98-mosquito/ &quot;De Havilland DH 98 Mosquito&quot;] ''National Museum of the US Air Force™'', 2015. Retrieved: 4 May 2018.&lt;/ref&gt; Note the air and oil coolant radiators in the leading edge of the wing, intake for the two-stage Merlin's intercooler radiator behind the propeller blade, and the carburettor intake with ice guard behind and below.]]
The all-wood wing pairs comprised a single structural unit throughout the wingspan, with no central longitudinal joint.&lt;ref&gt;Aviation, 1944 pp. 11–13.&lt;/ref&gt; Instead, the spars ran from wingtip to wingtip. There was a single continuous main spar and another continuous rear spar. Because of the combination of dihedral with the forward sweep of the trailing edges of the wings, this rear spar was one of the most complex units to laminate and to finish machining after the bonding and curing. It had to produce the correct 3D tilt in each of two planes. Also, it was designed and made to taper from the wing roots towards the wingtips. Both principal spars were of ply box construction, using in general 0.25-in plywood webs with laminated spruce flanges, plus a number of additional reinforcements and special details.

Spruce and plywood ribs were connected with gusset joints. Some heavy-duty ribs contained pieces of ash and walnut, as well as the special five ply that included veneers laid up at 45°. The upper skin construction was in two layers of 0.25-in five-ply birch, separated by Douglas fir stringers running in the span-wise direction.&lt;ref&gt;Aviation, 1944 p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt; The wings were covered with madapollam fabric and doped in a similar manner to the fuselage. The wing was installed into the roots by means of four large attachment points.&lt;ref&gt;Batchelor, John and Malcolm Low. de Havilland Mosquito Manual (Plane Essentials). Victoria, Australia: Publishing Solutions, 2008. {{ISBN|978-1-906589-00-4}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Batchelor and Lowe 2008,&quot;&gt;Batchelor and Lowe 2008, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt; The engine radiators were fitted in the inner wing, just outboard of the fuselage on either side. These gave less drag. The radiators themselves were split into three sections: an oil cooler section outboard, the middle section forming the coolant radiator and the inboard section serving the cabin heater.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jackson 2003, p. 87.&quot;&gt;Jackson 2003, p. 87.&lt;/ref&gt;

The wing contained metal-framed and -skinned [[ailerons]], but the flaps were made of wood and were hydraulically controlled. The nacelles were mostly wood, although for strength, the engine mounts were all metal, as were the undercarriage parts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jackson 2003, p. 9.&quot;&gt;Jackson 2003, p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt; Engine mounts of welded steel tube were added, along with simple landing gear oleos filled with rubber blocks. Wood was used to carry only in-plane loads, with metal fittings used for all triaxially loaded components such as landing gear, engine mounts, control-surface mounting brackets, and the wing-to-fuselage junction.&lt;ref&gt;Miracle and Donaldson 2001, p. 870.&lt;/ref&gt; The outer leading wing edge had to be brought {{convert|22|in|cm}} further forward to accommodate this design.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jackson 2003, p. 87.&quot; /&gt; The main tail unit was all wood built. The control surfaces, the [[rudder]], and [[Elevator (aircraft)|elevator]] were [[aluminium]]-framed and fabric-covered.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jackson 2003, p. 9.&quot; /&gt; The total weight of metal castings and forgings used in the aircraft was only {{convert|280|lb|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;raaf&quot;&gt;[http://www.airforce.gov.au/RAAFMuseum/exhibitions/restoration/dh_98.htm &quot;History of the de Havilland Mosquito.&quot;] ''RAAF Museum Point Cook'', 2007. Retrieved: 13 August 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:DH 98 Mosquito fore.jpg|thumb|left|American F-8 Mosquito nose; [[United States Army Air Forces|USAAF]] markings, [[Air Force blue#Air superiority blue.2FPRU blue|PRU Blue]] finish at the [[National Museum of the United States Air Force]].]]
In November 1944, several crashes occurred in the [[Far East]]. At first,  these were thought to be a result of wing-structure failures. The casein glue, it was said, cracked when exposed to extreme heat and/or monsoon conditions. This caused the upper surfaces to &quot;lift&quot; from the main spar. An investigating team led by Major [[Hereward de Havilland]] travelled to India and produced a report in early December 1944 stating, &quot;the accidents were not caused by the deterioration of the glue, but by shrinkage of the airframe during the wet monsoon season&quot;.{{refn|Many sources repeat the account of the change from casein adhesive to urea formaldehyde adhesive. These nearly always fail to recognise that both types, in the form used, were close-assembly adhesives, employed to bond the air-frame components together, often using the technique of &quot;screw-gluing&quot;. Plywood manufacture, on the other hand, used &quot;WBP- water and boil-proof&quot; (obsolescent BSI term), or ASTM equivalent, right from the start. Most of the adhesives failures in the tropics were due to water penetration into the interior cavities and balsa cores, with consequent swelling-shrinkage cycling. There were warnings, probably ignored in &quot;the exigencies&quot; that aircraft should never be parked permanently in the open. DH had always recognised that casein assembly adhesive was unsuitable for Mosquitos entering Far East service. Bonding additional cover strips over some of the major joints e.g. wing leading edges to main spars, was a stop-gap measure taken by DH Australia.&lt;ref&gt;Federal Aviation Administration, Advisory Circular AC 43.13-1B. &quot;Acceptable Methods, Techniques, And Practices – Aircraft Inspection And Repair&quot; 1998; Chapter 1 – Wood Structure&quot; Page 1-4, states: Phenol-formaldehyde adhesive is commonly used in the manufacturing of aircraft grade plywood. This product is cured at elevated temperature and pressure.&lt;/ref&gt;|group = nb}} However, a later inquiry by Cabot &amp; Myers firmly attributed the accidents to faulty manufacture and this was confirmed by a further investigation team by the Ministry of Aircraft Production at [[RAF Defford|Defford]], which found faults in six Mosquito marks (all built at de Havilland's Hatfield and Leavesden plants). The defects were similar, and none of the aircraft had been exposed to monsoon conditions or termite attack.

The investigators concluded that construction defects occurred at the two plants. They found that the &quot;...{{nbsp}}standard of glueing...left much to be desired.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, pp. 15–16.&quot;&gt;Bowman 2005, pp. 15–16.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bowman 2012, p. 306&lt;/ref&gt; Records at the time showed that accidents caused by &quot;loss of control&quot; were three times more frequent on Mosquitos than on any other type of aircraft. The Air Ministry forestalled any loss of confidence in the Mosquito by holding to Major de Havilland's initial investigation in India that the accidents were caused &quot;largely by climate&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bowman 2012, p. 266&lt;/ref&gt; To solve the problem of seepage into the interior, a strip of plywood was set along the span of the wing to seal the entire length of the skin joint.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, pp. 15–16.&quot; /&gt;

===Systems===
[[File:RAF Museum London 082.jpg|thumb|upright|A view into the bomb bay showing the brick-red coloured twin fuel tanks fitted into the fuselage]]

The fuel systems gave the Mosquito good range and endurance, using up to nine fuel tanks. Two outer wing tanks each contained {{convert|58|impgal|usgal L}} of fuel.&lt;ref name=&quot;Air Ministry 1945, p. 11. (FB 6 notes)&quot;&gt;Air Ministry 1945, p. 11. (FB 6 notes).&lt;/ref&gt; These were complemented by two inner wing fuel tanks, each containing {{cvt|143|impgal|usgal L}}, located between the wing root and engine nacelle. In the central fuselage were twin fuel tanks mounted between bulkhead number two and three aft of the cockpit.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 22.&quot;&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt; In the FB.VI, these tanks contained {{cvt|25|impgal|usgal L}} each,&lt;ref name=&quot;Air Ministry 1945, p. 11. (FB 6 notes)&quot; /&gt; while in the B.IV and other unarmed Mosquitos each of the two centre tanks contained {{cvt|68|impgal|usgal L}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Air Ministry 1943, p. 6. (B IV notes)&quot;&gt;Air Ministry 1943, p. 6. (B IV notes).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Air Ministry 1944, p. 6. (PR VIII, PR IX, B IX, PR XVI, B XVI notes)&quot;&gt;Air Ministry 1944, p. 6. (PR VIII, PR IX, B IX, PR XVI, B XVI notes).&lt;/ref&gt; Both the inner wing, and fuselage tanks are listed as the &quot;main tanks&quot; and the total internal fuel load of {{cvt|452|impgal|usgal L|round=5}} was initially deemed appropriate for the type.&lt;ref name=&quot;Air Ministry 1945, p. 11. (FB 6 notes)&quot; /&gt; In addition, the FB Mk VI could have larger fuselage tanks, increasing the capacity to {{cvt|63|impgal|usgal L}}. Drop tanks of {{cvt|50|impgal|usgal L}} or {{cvt|100|impgal|usgal L}} could be mounted under each wing, increasing the total fuel load to {{cvt|615|or|715|impgal|usgal L}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Air Ministry 1945, p. 11. (FB 6 notes)&quot; /&gt;

The design of the Mark VI allowed for a provisional long-range fuel tank to increase range for action over enemy territory, for the installation of bomb release equipment specific to [[depth charge]]s for strikes against enemy shipping, or for the simultaneous use of rocket projectiles along with a {{cvt|100|impgal|usgal L}} drop tank under each wing supplementing the main fuel cells.&lt;ref&gt;Air Ministry 1945, p. 11. (FB 6 notes)&lt;/ref&gt; The FB.VI had a wingspan of {{cvt|54|ft| 2|in|m}}, a length (over guns) of {{cvt|41|ft|2|in|m}}. It had a maximum speed of {{cvt|378|mph|km/h}} at {{cvt|13200|ft|m}}. Maximum take-off weight was {{convert|22300|lb|kg}} and the range of the aircraft was {{convert|1120|mi|km}} with a service ceiling of {{convert|26000|ft|m}}.&lt;ref&gt;Batchelor and Lowe 2008, pp. 16–17.&lt;/ref&gt;

To reduce fuel vaporisation at the high altitudes of photographic reconnaissance variants, the central and inner wing tanks were pressurised. The pressure venting cock located behind the pilot's seat controlled the pressure valve. As the altitude increased, the valve increased the volume applied by a pump. This system was extended to include field modifications of the fuel tank system.&lt;ref&gt;Air Ministry 1945, pp. 13–14. (FB 6 Notes)&lt;/ref&gt;

The engine oil tanks were in the engine nacelles. Each nacelle contained a {{cvt|15|impgal|usgal l}} oil tank, including a {{cvt|2.5|impgal|usgal l|abbr=on}} air space. The oil tanks themselves had no separate coolant controlling systems. The coolant header tank was in the forward nacelle, behind the propeller. The remaining coolant systems were controlled by the coolant radiators shutters in the forward inner wing compartment, between the nacelle and the fuselage and behind the main engine cooling radiators, which were fitted in the leading edge. Electric-pneumatic operated radiator shutters directed and controlled airflow through the ducts and into the coolant valves, to predetermined temperatures.&lt;ref name=&quot;Air Ministry 1945, p. 14. (FB 6 notes)&quot;&gt;Air Ministry 1945, p. 14. (FB 6 notes).&lt;/ref&gt;

Electrical power came from a 24 volt DC generator on the starboard (No. 2) engine and an alternator on the port engine, which also supplied AC power for radios.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bishop 1995 Appendix 1&quot; /&gt; The radiator shutters, supercharger gear change, gun camera, bomb bay, bomb/rocket release and all the other crew controlled instruments were powered by a 24 V battery.&lt;ref name=&quot;Air Ministry 1945, p. 14. (FB 6 notes)&quot; /&gt; The radio communication devices included [[Very high frequency|VHF]] and HF communications, [[GEE (navigation)|GEE navigation]], and [[Identification friend or foe|IFF]] and G.P. devices. The electric generators also powered the fire extinguishers. Located on the starboard side of the cockpit, the switches would operate automatically in the event of a crash. In flight, a warning light would flash to indicate a fire, should the pilot not already be aware of it. In later models, to save liquids and engine clean up time in case of belly landing, the fire extinguisher was changed to semi-automatic triggers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Air Ministry 1945, p. 44. (FB 6 notes)&quot;&gt;Air Ministry 1945, p. 44. (FB 6 notes).&lt;/ref&gt;

The main landing gear, housed in the nacelles behind the engines, were raised and lowered hydraulically. The main landing gear shock absorbers were de Havilland manufactured and used a system of rubber in compression, rather than hydraulic oleos, with twin pneumatic brakes for each wheel.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bishop 1995 Appendix 1&quot;&gt;Bishop 1995, Appendix 1&lt;/ref&gt; The Dunlop-Marstrand [[Speed wobble|anti-shimmy]] tailwheel was also retractable.

==Operational history==
{{Main|de Havilland Mosquito operational history}}
[[File:Shell-Huset-mosquito.jpg|thumb|[[Operation Carthage|Bombing of the Gestapo headquarters in the Shellhus]], Copenhagen, Denmark in March 1945. A Mosquito pulling away from its bombing run is visible on the extreme left, centre.]]
The de Havilland Mosquito operated in many roles, performing [[medium bomber]], [[Aerial reconnaissance|reconnaissance]], [[Ground-attack aircraft|tactical strike]], [[anti-submarine|anti-submarine warfare]] and shipping attacks and [[night fighter]] duties, until the end of the war.&lt;ref&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt; In July 1941, the first production Mosquito ''W4051'' (a production fuselage combined with some prototype flying surfaces – see Prototypes and test flights) was sent to No. 1 Photographic Reconnaissance Unit (PRU), at [[RAF Benson]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = AirRecce. | title = RAF Reconnaissance Aircraft Part 2 – Photo Reconnaissance Mosquitos. | publisher = Web. | date = 2004–2013 | url = http://www.airrecce.co.uk/WW2/recce_ac/RAFARP2.html | accessdate = 16 December 2013 |url-status=dead| archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20130521001408/http://www.airrecce.co.uk/WW2/recce_ac/RAFARP2.html | archivedate = 21 May 2013 | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The secret reconnaissance flights of this aircraft were the first operational missions of the Mosquito. In 1944, the journal ''[[Flight International|Flight]]''  gave 19 September 1941 as date of the first PR mission, at an altitude &quot;of some 20,000 ft&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; | title = Mosquito Genetics |pages=423–427 | work = Flight | date = 20 April 1944 | url = http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1944/1944%20-%200813.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 15 November 1941, [[No. 105 Squadron RAF|105 Squadron]], RAF, took delivery at RAF Swanton Morley, Norfolk, of the first operational Mosquito Mk. B.IV bomber, serial no. ''W4064''.&lt;ref&gt;Scott 1999, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; Throughout 1942, 105 Squadron, based next at RAF Horsham St. Faith, then from 29 September, RAF Marham, undertook daylight low-level and shallow dive attacks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wooldridge, Frontispiece&quot;&gt;Wooldridge 1993, Frontispiece.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|The main author of &quot;Low Attack,&quot; John de L. Wooldridge, became Wing Commander of No. 105 Squadron in March 1943. First published in 1944, it is a valuable contemporary first-hand account of the daylight low-level, pinpoint raiding phase of the Mosquito operations. The book's frontispiece is a map showing eighteen towns and cities in whose regions the attacks took place – several of these had more than one visit by the squadrons. It contains a commendation of the skill and high courage of the aircrews by Air Chief Marshal Sir Arthur Harris, referring to attacks on targets of first importance to the German war effort. This was at a time when the massed heavy night bomber raids were not yet fully mobilised.|group=nb}} Apart from the Oslo and Berlin raids, the strikes were mainly on industrial and infrastructure targets in occupied Netherlands and Norway, France and northern and western Germany.&lt;ref&gt;Scott 1999, p. v – Foreword by [[Ivor Broom|Air Marshal Sir Ivor Broom]]&lt;/ref&gt; The crews faced deadly flak and fighters, particularly [[Focke-Wulf Fw 190]]s, which they called ''snappers''. Germany still controlled continental airspace and the Fw 190s were often already airborne and at an advantageous altitude. Collisions within the formations also caused casualties. It was the Mosquito's excellent handling capabilities, rather than pure speed, that facilitated those evasions that were successful.&lt;ref&gt;Scott, 1999, pp 25, 32 – 33, 37 – 38&lt;/ref&gt;

The Mosquito was first announced publicly on 26 September 1942 after the [[Oslo Mosquito raid]] of 25 September. It was featured in ''[[The Times]]'' on 28 September and the next day the newspaper published two captioned photographs illustrating the bomb strikes and damage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Our Aeronautical Correspondent. | title = Nazis Stung By 'Mosquitoes'. | work = Times [London, England] | publisher = The Times Digital Archive. Web. 15 December 2013. | date = 28 September 1942 | url = http://find.galegroup.com/ttda/infomark.do?&amp;source=gale&amp;prodId=TTDA&amp;userGroupName=buc_ttda&amp;tabID=T003&amp;docPage=article&amp;searchType=AdvancedSearchForm&amp;docId=CS68762428&amp;type=multipage&amp;contentSet=LTO&amp;version=1.0 | accessdate = 15 December 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Our Aeronautical Correspondent. | title = The R.A.F. Raid on Oslo. | work = Times [London, England] | publisher = The Times Digital Archive. Web. 15 December 2013. | date = 29 September 1942 | url = http://find.galegroup.com/ttda/infomark.do?&amp;source=gale&amp;prodId=TTDA&amp;userGroupName=buc_ttda&amp;tabID=T003&amp;docPage=article&amp;searchType=AdvancedSearchForm&amp;docId=CS135347005&amp;type=multipage&amp;contentSet=LTO&amp;version=1.0 | accessdate = 15 December 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; On 6 December 1942, Mosquitos from Nos. 105 and 139 Squadrons made up part of the bomber force used in [[Operation Oyster (1942)|Operation Oyster]], the large No. 2 Group raid against the [[Philips|Philips works]] at [[Eindhoven]].

From mid-1942 to mid-1943, Mosquito bombers flew high-speed, medium or low-altitude daylight missions against factories, railways and other pinpoint targets in Germany and German-occupied Europe. From June 1943, Mosquito bombers were formed into the [[Pathfinder (RAF)#Light Night Striking Force|Light Night Striking Force]] to guide [[RAF Bomber Command]] heavy bomber raids and as &quot;nuisance&quot; bombers, dropping Blockbuster bombs – [[Blockbuster bomb|{{cvt|4000|lb|kg|sigfig=2}} &quot;cookies&quot;]] – in high-altitude, high-speed raids that German night fighters were almost powerless to intercept.

As a night fighter from mid-1942, the Mosquito intercepted ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' raids on Britain, notably those of [[Operation Steinbock]] in 1944. Starting in July 1942, Mosquito night-fighter units raided ''Luftwaffe'' airfields. As part of [[100 Group RAF|100 Group]], it was flown as a night fighter and as an intruder supporting Bomber Command heavy bombers that reduced losses during 1944 and 1945.&lt;ref name=&quot;Has240&quot;&gt;Hastings 1979, p. 240.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|The Mosquito increased German night-fighter losses to such an extent the Germans were said to have awarded two victories for shooting one down.&lt;ref name=&quot;Has240&quot;/&gt;|group=nb}}

The Mosquito [[fighter-bomber]] served as a [[attack aircraft|strike aircraft]] in the [[Second Tactical Air Force]] (2TAF) from its inception on 1 June 1943.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=''Overlord – 1944'' – Bracknell Paper No 5 – A Symposium on the Normandy Landings; Royal Air Force Historical Society &amp; Royal Air Force Staff College, Bracknell; 25 March 1994|url=https://www.rafmuseum.org.uk/documents/Research/RAF-Historical-Society-Journals/Bracknell-No-5-OVERLORD.pdf|accessdate=1 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The main objective was to prepare for the invasion of occupied Europe a year later. In [[Operation Overlord]] three Mosquito FB VI wings flew close air support for the Allied armies in co-operation with other RAF units equipped with the [[North American B-25 Mitchell]] medium bomber. In the months between the foundation of 2TAF and its duties from [[D day]] onwards, vital training was interspersed with attacks on [[V-1 flying bomb]] launch sites.&lt;ref&gt;Birtles 2017, ch. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;

In another example of the daylight precision raids carried out by the Mosquitos of Nos. 105 and 139 Squadrons, on 30 January 1943, the 10th anniversary of the [[Nazis]]' seizure of power, a morning Mosquito attack knocked out the main Berlin broadcasting station while [[Commander in Chief]] [[Reichsmarschall]] [[Hermann Göring]] was speaking, putting his speech off the air. A second sortie in the afternoon inconvenienced another speech, by Goebbels.&lt;ref&gt;Simons 2011, p. 160.&lt;/ref&gt; Lecturing a group of German aircraft manufacturers, Göring said:

{{quote|In 1940 I could at least fly as far as Glasgow in most of my aircraft, but not now! It makes me furious when I see the Mosquito. I turn green and yellow with envy. The British, who can afford aluminium better than we can, knock together a beautiful wooden aircraft that every piano factory over there is building, and they give it a speed which they have now increased yet again. What do you make of that? There is nothing the British do not have. They have the geniuses and we have the nincompoops. After the war is over I'm going to buy a British radio set – then at least I'll own something that has always worked.&lt;ref name=&quot;Boog et al. 2006, p. 407&quot;&gt;Boog et al. 2006, p. 407.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

During this daylight-raiding phase, Nos. 105 and 139 Squadrons flew 139 combat operations and aircrew losses were high.&lt;ref&gt;Birtles 2017, ch. 10.&lt;/ref&gt; Even the losses incurred in the squadrons' dangerous [[Bristol Blenheim|Blenheim]] era were exceeded in percentage terms. The Roll of Honour shows 51 aircrew deaths from the end of May 1942 to April 1943.&lt;ref&gt;Scott, 1999, pp 197 – 200&lt;/ref&gt; In the corresponding period, crews gained three Mentions in Despatches, two DFMs and three DFCs. The low-level daylight attacks finished on 27 May 1943 with strikes on the Schott glass and Zeiss instrument works, both in [[Jena]]. Subsequently, when low-level precision attacks required Mosquitos, they were allotted to squadrons operating the FB.IV version. Examples include the [[Aarhus Air Raid|Aarhus air raid]] and [[Operation Jericho]].

Since the beginning of the year, the German fighter force had become seriously overstretched.&lt;ref name=&quot;Boog et al 2006, pp 160-166&quot;&gt;Boog et al 2006, pp 160–166.&lt;/ref&gt; In April 1943, in response to &quot;political humiliation&quot; caused by the Mosquito, Göring ordered the formation of special ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' units (''[[Jagdgeschwader 25]]'', commanded by ''[[Oberstleutnant]]'' [[Herbert Ihlefeld]] and ''[[Jagdgeschwader 50]]'', under ''[[Major]]'' [[Hermann Graf]]) to combat the Mosquito attacks, though these units, which were &quot;little more than glorified squadrons&quot;, were unsuccessful against the elusive RAF aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Caldwell and Muller 2007, p. 79.&lt;/ref&gt; Post-war German histories also indicate that there was a belief within the Luftwaffe that Mosquito aircraft &quot;gave only a weak radar signal.&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Boog et al 2006, p166&lt;/ref&gt;{{Refn|The &quot;weak radar signal&quot; comment by Boog applies to all Mosquito roles, including PR and night-fighters as well as bombers. [[Adolf Galland]]&lt;ref&gt;''The First and The Last'' (p. 153)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |last = Galland|first = Adolf| title = The First and The Last: The Rise and Fall of the German Fighter Forces, 1938–1945 |place = New York|publisher = Henry Holt &amp; Co |year=1954}}&lt;/ref&gt; also wrote that the Mosquito left only a faint radar signal. However it should be borne in mind that Göring was by then irrational and enraged, refusing to believe bad news from senior staff, including Galland. No report of a weak radar reflection can be found in primary British sources on Mosquito trials. Also, any modest effect would have been fortuitous – see de Havilland's explanations for the use of timber, where it is not mentioned. Several authors suggest that the Mosquito was a precursor to stealth bombers, but for technical reasons, it could at best have been only a &quot;low profile&quot; aircraft, albeit fast and agile!|group=nb}}

The first Mosquito Squadron to be equipped with [[Oboe (navigation)]] was No. 109, based at RAF Wyton, after working as an experimental unit at [[RAF Boscombe Down]]. They used Oboe in anger for the first time on 31 December 1942 and 1 January 1943, target marking for a force of heavy bombers attacking Düsseldorf.&lt;ref name=&quot;Royal Air Force&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=History- RAF Formations- Historic Squadrons- 109 Squadron.|url=https://www.raf.mod.uk/history/109squadron.cfm|publisher=Royal Air Force|date=3 October 2017|access-date=3 October 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171004040347/https://www.raf.mod.uk/history/109squadron.cfm|archive-date=4 October 2017|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|For some time, RAF 109 Squadron had been working as an R&amp;D unit for trials on radar and radio counter-measures, using Anson and Wellington aircraft. In April 1942 it was ordered to develop Oboe for use in Mosquito bombers. Completing trials in August 1942, the squadron moved to [[RAF Wyton]] as part of No. 8 (Pathfinder Force) Group, to introduce it into operational service. A calibration sortie over enemy territory took place on 20/21 December, using six Mosquitos against a power station at Lutterade in Holland. Then on 31 December/1 January 1943, No. 109 Squadron pioneered Oboe target marking for a force of heavy bombers attacking Düsseldorf.&lt;ref name=&quot;Royal Air Force&quot;/&gt;|group=nb}}. On 1 June, the two pioneering Squadrons joined No. 109 Squadron in the re-formed [[No. 8 Group RAF]] (Bomber Command). Initially they were engaged in moderately high altitude (about {{cvt|10000|ft|m}}) night bombing, with 67 trips during that summer, mainly to Berlin. Soon after, Nos. 105 and 139 Squadron bombers were widely used by the [[Pathfinder (RAF)|RAF Pathfinder Force]], marking targets for the main night-time [[strategic bombing]] force.

In what were, initially, diversionary &quot;nuisance raids,&quot; Mosquito bombers dropped 4,000&amp;nbsp;lb [[Blockbuster bomb]]s or &quot;Cookies.&quot; Particularly after the introduction of [[H2S (radar)]] in some Mosquitos, these raids carrying larger bombs succeeded to the extent that they provided a significant additional form of attack to the large formations of &quot;heavies.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Birtles Chapter 10&lt;/ref&gt; Latterly in the war, there were a significant number of all-Mosquito raids on big German cities involving up to 100 or more aircraft. On the night of 20/21 February 1945, for example, Mosquitos of No. 8 Group mounted the first of 36 consecutive night raids on Berlin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harris Despatch&quot;&gt;Harris 1993, p. 43.&lt;/ref&gt;

From 1943, Mosquitos with [[RAF Coastal Command]] attacked ''[[Kriegsmarine]]'' [[U-boat]]s and intercepted transport ship concentrations. After [[Operation Overlord]], the U-boat threat in the Western Approaches decreased fairly quickly, but correspondingly the Norwegian and Danish waters posed greater dangers. Hence the RAF Coastal Command Mosquitos were moved to Scotland to counter this threat. The Strike Wing at Banff stood up in September 1944 and comprised Mosquito aircraft of No's 143, 144, 235 and 248 Squadrons Royal Air Force and No.333 Squadron Royal Norwegian Air Force. Despite an initially high loss rate, the Mosquito bomber variants ended the war with the lowest losses of any aircraft in [[RAF Bomber Command]] service.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.friends-amis.org/index.php/en/document-repository/english/fact-sheets/39-the-dehavilland-mosquito/file|title=DeHavilland Mosquito Fact Sheet #62|last=Braham|first=M.|editor-last=Spence|editor-first=Hugh|website=Friends of the Canadian War Museum|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=28 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Royal Air Force 1939-1945- Coastal Command C5212.jpg|thumb|A de Havilland Mosquito of the [[RAF Banff]] Strike Wing attacking a convoy evacuating Germans troops in the [[Kattegat]] on 5 April 1945. A [[Vorpostenboot|flak ship]] and a trawler were sunk]]

The Mosquito also proved a very capable [[night fighter]]. Some of the most successful RAF pilots flew these variants. For example, [[Wing Commander (rank)|Wing Commander]] [[Branse Burbridge]] claimed 21 kills, and Wing Commander John Cunningham claimed 19 of his 20 victories at night on Mosquitos.

Mosquitos of [[No. 100 Group RAF]] acted as night intruders operating at high level in support of the Bomber Command &quot;heavies&quot;, to counter the enemy tactic of merging into the bomber stream, which, towards the end of 1943, was causing serious allied losses.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harris Despatch b&quot;&gt;Harris 1993, p. 126.&lt;/ref&gt; These RCM (radio countermeasures) aircraft were fitted with a device called &quot;[[Serrate radar detector|Serrate]]&quot; to allow them to track down German night fighters from their [[Lichtenstein radar#FuG 202 Lichtenstein B/C|''Lichtenstein B/C'']] (low-[[UHF]]-band) and [[Lichtenstein radar#FuG 220 Lichtenstein SN-2|''Lichtenstein SN-2'']] (lower end of the [[VHF]] FM broadcast band) radar emissions, as well as a device named &quot;[[Perfectos]]&quot; that tracked German [[Identification friend or foe|IFF]] signals. These methods were responsible for the destruction of 257 German aircraft from December 1943 to April 1945. Mosquito fighters from all units accounted for 487 German aircraft during the war, the vast majority of which were night fighters.&lt;ref&gt;Boiten 1997, pp. 188–189.&lt;/ref&gt;

One Mosquito is listed as belonging to German secret operations unit ''[[Kampfgeschwader 200]]'', which tested, evaluated and sometimes clandestinely operated captured enemy aircraft during the war. The aircraft was listed on the [[order of battle]] of ''Versuchsverband OKL''{{'}}s, ''2 Staffel'', ''Stab Gruppe'' on 10 November and 31 December 1944. However, on both lists, the Mosquito is listed as unserviceable.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas and Ketley 2003, pp. 178–179.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Mosquito flew its last official European war mission on 21 May 1945, when Mosquitos of 143 Squadron and 248 Squadron RAF were ordered to continue to hunt German submarines that might be tempted to continue the fight; instead of submarines all the Mosquitos encountered were passive [[E-boat]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 119.&lt;/ref&gt;

The last operational RAF Mosquitos were the Mosquito TT.35's, which were finally retired from No. 3 Civilian Anti-Aircraft Co-Operation Unit (CAACU) in May 1963.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1963/1963%20-%200749.html |title=Farewell to the Mosquito |work=[[Flightglobal]]/[[Archive]] Flight International|date=16 May 1963 |accessdate=25 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1947–49, up to 180 Canadian surplus Mosquitoes flew many operations for the Nationalist Chinese under [[Chiang Kai-shek]] in the civil war against Communist forces. Pilots from three squadrons of Mosquitoes claimed to have sunk or damaged 500 ships during one invasion attempt. As the Communists assumed control, the remaining aircraft were evacuated to Formosa, where they flew missions against shipping.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gMyiggraw4s|title=+1000 Mosquito Hours: George Stewart|via=www.youtube.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://weaponsandwarfare.com/2017/03/21/chinese-nationalist-mosquitos/|title=Chinese Nationalist Mosquitos|date=20 March 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Variants==
Until the end of 1942 the RAF always used [[Roman numeral]]s (I, II, ...) for [[British military aircraft designation systems|mark numbers]]; 1943–1948 was a transition period during which new aircraft entering service were given [[Arabic numeral]]s (1, 2, ...) for mark numbers, but older aircraft retained their Roman numerals. From 1948 onwards, Arabic numerals were used exclusively.

===Prototypes===
Three prototypes were built, each with a different configuration. The first to fly was ''W4050'' on 25 November 1940, followed by the fighter ''W4052'' on 15 May 1941 and the photo-reconnaissance prototype ''W4051'' on 10 June 1941. ''W4051'' later flew operationally with [[1 Photographic Reconnaissance Unit]] (1 PRU).

===Photo-reconnaissance===
{{Commons category-inline|De Havilland Mosquito PR}}&lt;br/&gt;
{{Multiple image
|align=right
|direction=horizontal
|header=
|footer=A 1943 RAF photo-reconnaissance picture of [[Test Stand VII]] at the [[Peenemünde]] Army Research Centre, taken by a Mosquito. [[V-2 rocket|V2]] rockets, lying horizontally on transport trolleys, are labelled &quot;B&quot; and &quot;C&quot;.
|width1=220
|image1=Peenemunde-165515.jpg
|alt1=
|caption1=
|width2=135
|image2=Peenemunde-165515_detail.jpg
|alt2=
|caption2=
}}
[[File:Mosquito photo-reconnaissance photoflash bomb loading WWII IWM C 4998.jpg|thumb|Loading [[photoflash bomb]]s onto a PR Mk XVI of [[No. 140 Squadron RAF]] at [[Advanced Landing Ground#Royal Air Force ALGs|B58/Melsbroek]], Belgium, circa 1944–1945]]
A total of 10 '''Mosquito PR Mk Is''' were built, four of them &quot;long range&quot; versions equipped with a {{convert|151|impgal|L}} overload fuel tank in the fuselage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thirsk 2006, p. 269&quot;/&gt; The contract called for 10 of the PR Mk I airframes to be converted to '''B Mk IV Series 1s'''.&lt;ref&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, pp. 41–42, 423.&lt;/ref&gt; All of the PR Mk Is, and the B Mk IV Series 1s, had the original short engine nacelles and short span (19&amp;nbsp;ft 5.5 in) tailplanes. Their engine cowlings incorporated the original pattern of integrated exhaust manifolds, which, after relatively brief flight time, had a troublesome habit of burning and blistering the cowling panels.&lt;ref&gt;Thirsk 2006, pp. 60, 269–270.&lt;/ref&gt; The first operational [[sortie]] by a Mosquito was made by a PR Mk I, '''W4055''', on 17 September 1941; during this sortie the unarmed Mosquito PR.I evaded three [[Messerschmitt Bf 109]]s at {{convert|23000|ft|m}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 27.&quot;&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt; Powered by two Merlin 21s, the PR Mk I had a maximum speed of {{convert|382|mph|km/h}}, a cruise speed of {{convert|255|mph|km/h}}, a ceiling of {{convert|35000|ft|m}}, a range of {{convert|2180|nmi|km}}, and a climb rate of {{convert|2850|ft}} per minute.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 25.&quot;/&gt;

Over 30 Mosquito B Mk IV bombers were converted into the '''PR Mk IV''' photo-reconnaissance aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Thirsk 2006, p. 268.&lt;/ref&gt; The first operational flight by a PR Mk IV was made by ''DK284'' in April 1942.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 164.&quot;&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 164.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Mosquito '''PR Mk VIII''', built as a stopgap pending the introduction of the refined PR Mk IX, was the next photo-reconnaissance version. The five VIIIs were converted from B Mk IVs and became the first operational Mosquito version to be powered by two-stage, two-speed supercharged engines, using {{convert|1565|hp|kW|abbr=on}} Rolls-Royce Merlin 61 engines in place of Merlin 21/22s. The first PR Mk VIII, ''DK324'' first flew on 20 October 1942.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thir272&quot;&gt;Thirsk 2006, p. 272.&lt;/ref&gt; The PR Mk VIII had a maximum speed of {{convert|436|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}, an economical cruise speed of {{convert|295|mph|km/h|abbr=on}} at 20,000&amp;nbsp;ft, and {{convert|350|mph|km/h|abbr=on}} at 30,000&amp;nbsp;ft,&lt;ref name=&quot;avialogs.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.avialogs.com/index.php/en/aircraft/uk/dehavilland/dh-98mosquito/dh-98-de-havilland-mosquito-mks-viii-ix-and-xvi-operational-performance-notes.html|title=D.H. 98 De Havilland Mosquito Mks VIII, IX and XVI – Operational Performance Notes|accessdate=1 October 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171010033940/http://www.avialogs.com/index.php/en/aircraft/uk/dehavilland/dh-98mosquito/dh-98-de-havilland-mosquito-mks-viii-ix-and-xvi-operational-performance-notes.html|archive-date=10 October 2017|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; a ceiling of {{convert|38000|ft|m|abbr=on}}, a range of {{convert|2550|nmi|km|abbr=on}}, and a climb rate of 2,500&amp;nbsp;ft per minute (760 m).&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 25.&quot;&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 25.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Mosquito '''PR Mk IX''', 90 of which were built, was the first Mosquito variant with two-stage, two-speed engines to be produced in quantity; the first of these, ''LR405'', first flew in April 1943.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thir272&quot;/&gt; The PR Mk IX was based on the Mosquito B Mk IX bomber and was powered by two {{convert|1680|hp|kW|abbr=on}} Merlin 72/73 or 76/77 engines. It could carry either two {{convert|50|impgal|L}}, two {{convert|100|impgal|L}} or two {{convert|200|impgal|L}} droppable fuel tanks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 164.&quot;/&gt;

The Mosquito '''PR Mk XVI''' had a pressurised cockpit and, like the Mk IX, was powered by two Rolls-Royce Merlin 72/73 or 76/77 piston engines. This version was equipped with three overload fuel tanks, totalling {{convert|760|impgal|L}} in the bomb bay, and could also carry two {{convert|50|impgal|L}} or {{convert|100|impgal|L}} drop tanks.&lt;ref&gt;Thirsk 2006, pp. 274–275.&lt;/ref&gt; A total of 435 of the PR Mk XVI were built.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 164.&quot;/&gt; The PR Mk XVI had a maximum speed of {{convert|415|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}, a cruise speed of {{convert|250|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}, ceiling of {{convert|38500|ft|m|abbr=on}}, a range of {{convert|2450|nmi|km|abbr=on}}, and a climb rate of 2,900 feet per minute (884 m).&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 25.&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Dh Mosquito PR XVI.jpg|thumb]]

The Mosquito '''PR Mk 32''' was a long-range, high-altitude, pressurised photo-reconnaissance version. It was powered by a pair of two-stage supercharged {{convert|1690|hp|kW|abbr=on}} Rolls-Royce Merlin 113 and Merlin 114 piston engines, the Merlin 113 on the starboard side and the Merlin 114 on the port. First flown in August 1944, only five were built and all were conversions from PR.XVIs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 165.&quot;&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 165.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Mosquito '''PR Mk 34''' and '''PR Mk 34A''' was a very long-range unarmed high altitude photo-reconnaissance version. The fuel tank and cockpit protection armour were removed. Additional fuel was carried in a bulged bomb bay: 1,192 gallons—the equivalent of {{convert|5419|mi|km}}. A further two 200-gallon (910-litre) drop tanks under the outer wings gave a range of {{convert|3600|mi|km}} cruising at {{convert|300|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}. Powered by two {{convert|1690|hp|kW|abbr=on}} Merlin 114s first used in the PR.32. The port Merlin 114 drove a Marshal cabin supercharger. A total of 181 were built, including 50 built by [[Percival Aircraft]] Company at [[Luton]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 165.&quot;/&gt; The PR.34's maximum speed (TAS) was {{convert|335|mi/h|km/h|abbr=on}} at sea level, {{convert|405|mi/h|km/h|abbr=on}} at {{convert|17000|ft|m|abbr=on}} and {{convert|425|mi/h|km/h|abbr=on}} at {{convert|30000|ft|m|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;The latest Mosquitoes.&quot;&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1946/1946%20-%200399.html?tracked=1 &quot;The Latest Mosquitoes.&quot;] ''Flight,'' 28 February 1946 via ''flightglobal.com''. Retrieved: 17 August 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
All PR.34s were installed with four split F52 vertical cameras, two forward, two aft of the fuselage tank and one F24 oblique camera. Sometimes a K-17 camera was used for air surveys. In August 1945, the PR.34A was the final photo-reconnaissance variant with one Merlin 113A and 114A each delivering {{convert|1710|hp|kW|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 166.&quot;&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 166.&lt;/ref&gt;

Colonel Roy M. Stanley II, USAF (RET) wrote: &quot;I consider the Mosquito the best photo-reconnaissance aircraft of the war&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;V Weapons Hunt, p. 35&quot; &gt;Stanley 2010, p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt;

After the end of World War II [[Spartan Air Services]] used 10 ex-RAF Mosquitoes, mostly B.35's plus one of only six PR.35's built, for high-altitude photographic survey work in Canada.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1955/1955%20-%201611.html |title=P.R. Mosquitoes Work Again|work=[[Flightglobal]]/[[Archive]] |date=4 November 1955 |accessdate=25 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bombers===
{{Commons category-inline|De Havilland Mosquito B}}&lt;br/&gt;
[[File:De Havilland Mosquito-DK338-1942.jpg|thumb|Mosquito B Mk IV Series 2, ''DK338'', built in September 1942 and delivered to [[No. 105 Squadron RAF|105 Squadron]], becoming GB-O.&lt;ref&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, pp. 197–198, 423.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
On 21 June 1941 the Air Ministry ordered that the last 10 Mosquitos, ordered as photo-reconnaissance aircraft, should be converted to bombers. These 10 aircraft were part of the original 1 March 1940 production order and became the '''B Mk IV Series 1'''. ''W4052'' was to be the prototype and flew for the first time on 8 September 1941.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, pp. 22–23.&quot;&gt;Bowman 2005, pp. 22–23.&lt;/ref&gt;

The bomber prototype led to the '''B Mk IV''', of which 273 were built: apart from the 10 Series 1s, all of the rest were built as Series 2s with extended nacelles, revised exhaust manifolds, with integrated flame dampers, and larger tailplanes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jackson 2003, p. 15.&quot;&gt;Jackson 2003, p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt; Series 2 bombers also differed from the Series 1 in having an increased payload of four {{convert|500|lb|abbr=on}} bombs, instead of the four {{convert|250|lb|kg}} bombs of Series 1. This was made possible by ''cropping'', or shortening the tail of the {{convert|500|lb|kg}} bomb so that these four heavier weapons could be carried (or a 2,000&amp;nbsp;lb (920;kg) total load).&lt;ref name=&quot;Jackson 2003, p. 15.&quot;/&gt; The B Mk IV entered service in May 1942 with [[No. 105 Squadron RAF|105 Squadron]].

In April 1943 it was decided to convert a B Mk IV to carry a {{convert|4000|lb|kg|abbr=on}} [[Blockbuster bomb]] (nicknamed a Cookie). The conversion, including modified bomb bay suspension arrangements, bulged bomb bay doors and fairings, was relatively straightforward and 54 B.IVs were modified and distributed to squadrons of the Light Night Striking Force.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jackson 2003, p. 15.&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, pp. 306–307&lt;/ref&gt; 27 B Mk IVs were later converted for special operations with the [[Bouncing bomb|Highball]] anti-shipping weapon, and were used by [[No. 618 Squadron RAF|618 Squadron]], formed in April 1943 specifically to use this weapon.&lt;ref&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, pp. 74, 76–78.&lt;/ref&gt; A B Mk IV, ''DK290'' was initially used as a trials aircraft for the bomb, followed by ''DZ471,530 and 533''.&lt;ref&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, pp. 74–75.&lt;/ref&gt; The B Mk IV had a maximum speed of {{convert|380|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}, a cruising speed of {{convert|265|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}, ceiling of {{convert|34000|ft|m|abbr=on}}, a range of {{convert|2040|nmi|km|abbr=on}}, and a climb rate of 2,500&amp;nbsp;ft per minute (762 m).&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 25.&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Royal Air Force Bomber Command, 1942-1945. CH12624.jpg|thumb|left|B Mk IV (modified) of [[No. 692 Squadron RAF|No. 692 Squadron]], showing bulged bomb bay doors to accommodate the [[Blockbuster bomb#4000 lb HC bomb|4,000lb Cookie]].]]
Other bomber variants of the Mosquito included the Merlin 21 powered '''B Mk V''' high-altitude version. Trials with this configuration were made with ''W4057'', which had strengthened wings and two additional fuel tanks, or alternatively, two {{convert|500|lb|kg}} bombs. This design was not produced in Britain, but formed the basic design of the Canadian-built B.VII. Only ''W4057'' was built in prototype form.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jackson 2003, p. 16.&quot;&gt;Jackson 2003, p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt; The Merlin 31 powered '''B Mk VII''' was built by de Havilland Canada and first flown on 24 September 1942. It only saw service in Canada, 25 were built. Six were handed over to the [[United States Army Air Forces]].

'''B Mk IX''' (54 built) was powered by the Merlin 72,73, 76 or 77. The two-stage Merlin variant was based on the PR.IX. The prototype ''DK 324'' was converted from a PR.VIII and first flew on 24 March 1943.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jackson 2003, p. 17.&quot;&gt;Jackson 2003, p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; In October 1943 it was decided that all B Mk IVs and all B Mk IXs then in service would be converted to carry the {{convert|4000|lb|kg}} &quot;Cookie&quot;, and all B Mk IXs built after that date were designed to allow them to be converted to carry the weapon.&lt;ref name=&quot;S&amp;P306&quot;&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, p. 306&lt;/ref&gt; The B Mk IX had a maximum speed of {{convert|408|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}, an economical cruise speed of {{convert|295|mph|km/h|abbr=on}} at 20,000&amp;nbsp;ft, and {{convert|350|mph|km/h|abbr=on}} at 30,000&amp;nbsp;ft,&lt;ref name=&quot;avialogs.com&quot;/&gt; ceiling of {{convert|36000|ft|m|abbr=on}}, a range of {{convert|2450|nmi|km|abbr=on}}, and a climb rate of 2,850 feet per minute (869 m). The IX could carry a maximum load of {{convert|2000|-|4000|lb|kg|abbr=on}} of bombs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 25.&quot;/&gt; A Mosquito B Mk IX holds the record for the most combat operations flown by an Allied bomber in the Second World War. ''LR503'', known as &quot;F for Freddie&quot; (from its squadron code letters, GB*F), first served with [[No. 109 Squadron RAF|No. 109]] and subsequently, [[No. 105 Squadron RAF|No. 105]] RAF squadrons. It flew 213 sorties during the war, only to crash at Calgary airport during the Eighth Victory Loan Bond Drive on 10 May 1945, two days after [[Victory in Europe Day]], killing both the pilot, Flt. Lt. Maurice Briggs, DSO, DFC, DFM and navigator Fl. Off. John Baker, DFC and Bar.&lt;ref&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 70.&lt;/ref&gt;

The '''B Mk XVI''' was powered by the same variations as the B.IX. All B Mk XVIs were capable of being converted to carry the {{convert|4000|lb|kg}} &quot;Cookie&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;S&amp;P306&quot;/&gt; The two-stage powerplants were added along with a pressurised cabin. ''DZ540'' first flew on 1 January 1944. The prototype was converted from a IV (402 built). The next variant, the '''B Mk XX''', was powered by Packard Merlins 31 and 33s. It was the Canadian version of the IV. Altogether, 245 were built. The B Mk XVI had a maximum speed of {{convert|408|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}, an economical cruise speed of {{convert|295|mph|km/h|abbr=on}} at 20,000&amp;nbsp;ft, and {{convert|350|mph|km/h|abbr=on}} at 30,000&amp;nbsp;ft,&lt;ref name=&quot;avialogs.com&quot;/&gt; ceiling of {{convert|37000|ft|m|abbr=on}}, a range of {{convert|1485|nmi|km|abbr=on}}, and a climb rate of 2,800&amp;nbsp;ft per minute (853 m). The type could carry {{convert|4000|lb|kg}} of bombs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 25.&quot;/&gt;

The '''B.35''' was powered by Merlin 113 and 114As. Some were converted to TT.35s (Target Tugs) and others were used as PR.35s (photo-reconnaissance).&lt;ref name=&quot;Jackson 2003, p. 17.&quot;/&gt; The B.35 had a maximum speed of {{convert|422|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}, a cruising speed of {{convert|276|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}, ceiling of {{convert|42000|ft|m|abbr=on}}, a range of {{convert|1750|nmi|km|abbr=on}}, and a climb rate of 2,700&amp;nbsp;ft per minute (823 m).&lt;ref&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt; A total of 174 B.35s were delivered up to the end of 1945. {{refn|RV series 4; TA series 82; TH/TJ series 60; and TK series 19.&lt;ref&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, table p. 90.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}} A further 100 were delivered from 1946 for a grand total of 274, 65 of which were built by Airspeed Ltd.{{refn|The final 100 were: RS series 25; TK series 35; VP series 25; and VR series 15.&lt;ref&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, table p. 94.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 166.&quot; /&gt;

===Fighters===
{{Commons category-inline|De Havilland Mosquito F}}&lt;br/&gt;
[[File:Royal Air Force Operations in the Far East, 1941-1945. CI581.jpg|thumb|right|Mosquito F Mk II in India circa 1943]]
Developed during 1940, the first prototype of the '''Mosquito F Mk II''' was completed on 15 May 1941. These Mosquitos were fitted with four {{convert|20|mm|in|abbr=on}} [[Hispano-Suiza HS.404|Hispano cannon]] in the fuselage belly and four [[.303 British|.303 (7.7 mm)]] [[M1919 Browning machine gun|Browning machine guns]] mounted in the nose. On production Mk IIs the machine guns and ammunition tanks were accessed via two centrally hinged, sideways opening doors in the upper nose section. To arm and service the cannon the bomb bay doors were replaced by manually operated bay doors: the F and NF Mk IIs could not carry bombs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thirsk 2006, pp. 125, 134&quot;/&gt; The type was also fitted with a [[gun camera]] in a compartment above the machine guns in the nose and was fitted with exhaust flame dampers to reduce the glare from the Merlin XXs.&lt;ref&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the summer of 1942, Britain experienced day-time incursions of the high-altitude reconnaissance bomber, the [[Junkers Ju 86|Junkers Ju 86P]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Birtles 2017, ch. 6&quot;&gt;Birtles 2017, ch. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the Ju 86P only carried a light bomb load, it overflew sensitive areas, including Bristol, Bedfordshire and Hertfordshire. Bombs were dropped on Luton and elsewhere, and this particular aircraft was seen from the main de Havilland offices and factory at Hatfield. An attempt to intercept it with a Spitfire from RAF Manston was unsuccessful. As a result of the potential threat, a decision was quickly taken to develop a high-altitude Mosquito interceptor, using the ''MP469'' prototype.

''MP469'' entered the experimental shop on 7 September and made its initial flight on 14 September, piloted by John de Havilland. The bomber nose was altered using a normal fighter nose, armed with four standard [[.303 British|.303 (7.7 mm)]] [[M1919 Browning machine gun|Browning machine guns]]. The low pressure cabin retained a bomber canopy structure and a two-piece windscreen. The control wheel was replaced with a fighter control stick. The wingspan was increased to {{convert|59|ft|m|abbr=on}}. The airframe was lightened by removing armour plating, some fuel tanks and other fitments. Smaller-diameter main wheels were fitted after the first few flights. At a loaded weight of {{convert|16200|lb|abbr=on}} this HA Mk XV was {{convert|2300|lb|abbr=on}} lighter than a standard Mk II. For this first conversion, the engines were a pair of Merlin 61s. On 15 September, John de Havilland reached an altitude of {{convert|43000|ft|m}} in this version. The aircraft was delivered to a High Altitude Flight which had been formed at RAF Northolt. However, the high-level German daylight intruders were no longer to be seen. It was subsequently revealed that only five Ju 86P aircraft had been built and they had only flown 12 sorties. Nevertheless, the general need for high altitude interceptors was recognised – but now the emphasis was to be upon night fighters.

The A&amp;AEE tested the climb and speed of night fighter conversion of MP469 in January 1943 for the Ministry of Aircraft Production.&lt;ref&gt;Aircraft And Armament Experimental Establishment, Boscombe Down, Mosquito NF MkXV MP469, Short performance and handling trials, January 1943; Online PDF, Courtesy of Neil Stirling
[http://www.wwiiaircraftperformance.org/mosquito/mp469.pdf, accessed 14 Aug 2017]&lt;/ref&gt; Wingspan had been increased to {{convert|62|ft|m|abbr=on}}, the Brownings had been moved to a fairing below the fuselage. According to Birtles, an AI radar was mounted in the nose and the Merlins were upgraded to Mk76 type, although Boscombe Down reported Merlin 61s. In addition to MP469, four more B Mk IVs were converted into '''NF MK XVs'''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Birtles 2017, ch. 6&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, pp. 63–67.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Fighter Interception Unit]] at RAF Ford carried out service trials, March 1943, and then these five aircraft went to 85 Squadron, Hunsdon, where they were flown from April until August of that year. The greatest height reached in service was {{convert|44600|ft|m}}.

Apart from the F Mk XV, all Mosquito fighters and fighter bombers featured a modified canopy structure incorporating a flat, single piece [[Bulletproof glass|armoured windscreen]], and the crew entry/exit door was moved from the bottom of the forward fuselage to the right side of the nose, just forward of the wing leading edge.&lt;ref&gt;Scutts 1993, pp. 4–5.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Night fighters===
{{Commons category-inline|De Havilland Mosquito NF}}&lt;br/&gt;
[[File:De Havilland Mosquitoat NF II at RAF Predannack.jpg|thumb|Mosquito NF Mk II ''W4092'' of [[No. 157 Squadron RAF|157 Squadron]], January 1944. Just visible is part of the aerial array for the A.I. Mk IV near the wingtip.]]
At the end of 1940, the Air Staff's preferred turret-equipped night fighter design to [[List of Air Ministry specifications|Operational Requirement O.R. 95]] was the Gloster F.18/40 (derived from [[Gloster F.9/37|their F.9/37]]). However, although in agreement as to the quality of the Gloster company's design, the Ministry of Aircraft Production was concerned that Gloster would not be able to work on the F.18/40 and also the jet fighter design, considered the greater priority. Consequently, in mid-1941 the Air Staff and MAP agreed that the Gloster aircraft would be dropped and the Mosquito, when fitted with a turret would be considered for the night fighter requirement.&lt;ref&gt;Buttler pp. 61–62&lt;/ref&gt;

The first production [[night fighter]] Mosquitos – minus turrets – were designated '''NF Mk II'''. A total of 466 were built with the first entering service with [[No. 157 Squadron RAF|No. 157 Squadron]] in January 1942, replacing the [[A-20 Havoc|Douglas Havoc]]. These aircraft were similar to the F Mk II, but were fitted with the [[AI Mk. IV radar|AI Mk IV]] metric [[wavelength]] [[radar]]. The herring-bone [[transmitter|transmitting]] [[Antenna (radio)|antenna]] was mounted on the nose and the dipole [[receiver (radio)|receiving]] antennae were carried under the outer wings.&lt;ref&gt;Scutts 1993, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt; A number of NF IIs had their radar equipment removed and additional fuel tanks installed in the bay behind the cannon for use as night intruders. These aircraft, designated '''NF II (Special)''' were first used by [[No. 23 Squadron RAF|23 Squadron]] in operations over Europe in 1942.&lt;ref&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, pp. 338–339.&lt;/ref&gt; 23 Squadron was then deployed to Malta on 20 December 1942, and operated against targets in Italy.&lt;ref&gt;Scutts 1993, p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt;

Ninety-seven NF Mk IIs were upgraded with 3.3&amp;nbsp;GHz frequency, low-[[Super high frequency|SHF]]-band [[AI Mk. VIII radar|AI Mk VIII]] radar and these were designated '''NF Mk XII'''. The '''NF Mk XIII''', of which 270 were built, was the production equivalent of the Mk XII conversions. These &quot;centimetric&quot; radar sets were mounted in a solid &quot;thimble&quot; (Mk XII / XIII) or universal &quot;bull nose&quot; (Mk XVII / XIX) radome, which required the machine guns to be dispensed with.
[[File:De Havilland Mosquitoat night takeoff.jpg|thumb|NF Mk XIII of [[No. 256 Squadron RAF|256 Squadron]], with the &quot;bull nose&quot;, caught in the beam of a Chance light on the main runway at [[Foggia]], Italy, before taking off on a night intruder sortie.]]

Four F Mk XVs were converted to the '''NF Mk XV'''. These were fitted with AI Mk VIII in a &quot;thimble&quot; radome, and the .303 Brownings were moved into a gun pack fitted under the forward fuselage.&lt;ref&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, pp. 65–67.&lt;/ref&gt;

''' NF Mk XVII''' was the designation for 99 NF Mk II conversions, with single-stage Merlin 21, 22, or 23 engines, but British AI.X (US SCR-720) radar.

The '''NF Mk XIX''' was an improved version of the NF XIII. It could be fitted with American or British AI radars; 220 were built.

The '''NF Mk 30''' was the final wartime variant and was a high-altitude version, powered by two {{convert|1710|hp|kW|abbr=on}} Rolls-Royce Merlin 76s. The NF Mk 30 had a maximum speed of {{convert|424|mph|km/h|abbr=on}} at {{convert|26500|ft|m|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, p. 434.&lt;/ref&gt; It also carried early [[electronic countermeasures]] equipment. 526 were built.
[[File:DH.98 Mosquito NFXIX MM638 RSwAF RWY 10.49 edited-2.jpg|thumb|right|Swedish Air Force NF.XIX operational in 1949.]]
Other Mosquito night fighter variants planned but never built included the '''NF Mk X''' and '''NF Mk XIV''' (the latter based on the NF Mk XIII), both of which were to have two-stage Merlins. The '''NF Mk 31''' was a variant of the NF Mk 30, but powered by Packard Merlins.&lt;ref&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, pp. 396, 398.&lt;/ref&gt;

After the war, two more night fighter versions were developed:
The '''NF Mk 36''' was similar to the Mosquito NF Mk 30, but fitted with the American-built AI.Mk X radar. Powered by two {{convert|1690|hp|kW|abbr=on}} Rolls-Royce Merlin 113/114 piston engines; 266 built. Max level speeds (TAS) with flame dampers fitted were {{convert|305|mi/h|km/h|abbr=on}} at sea level, {{convert|380|mi/h|km/h|abbr=on}} at {{convert|17000|ft|m|abbr=on}}, and {{convert|405|mi/h|km/h|abbr=on}} at {{convert|30000|ft|m|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;The latest Mosquitoes.&quot;/&gt;

The '''NF Mk 38''', 101 of which were built, was also similar to the Mosquito NF Mk 30, but fitted with the British-built AI Mk IX radar. This variant suffered from stability problems and did not enter RAF service: 60 were eventually sold to Yugoslavia.&lt;ref&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, p. 61.&lt;/ref&gt; According to the Pilot's Notes and Air Ministry 'Special Flying Instruction TF/487', which posted limits on the Mosquito's maximum speeds, the NF Mk 38 had a VNE of 370 knots (425&amp;nbsp;mph), without under-wing stores, and within the altitude range of sea level to {{convert|10000|ft|m|abbr=on}}. However, from 10,000 to {{convert|15000|ft|m|abbr=on}} the maximum speed was 348 knots (400&amp;nbsp;mph). As the height increased other recorded speeds were; 15,000 to {{convert|20000|ft|m|abbr=on}} 320 knots (368&amp;nbsp;mph); 20,000 to {{convert|25000|ft|m|abbr=on}}, 295 knots (339&amp;nbsp;mph); 25,000 to {{convert|30000|ft|m|abbr=on}}, 260 knots (299&amp;nbsp;mph); 30,000 to {{convert|35000|ft|m|abbr=on}}, 235 knots (270&amp;nbsp;mph). With two added 100-gallon fuel tanks this performance fell; between sea level and 15,000 feet 330 knots (379&amp;nbsp;mph); between 15,000 and {{convert|20000|ft|m|abbr=on}} 320 knots (368&amp;nbsp;mph); 20,000 to {{convert|25000|ft|m|abbr=on}}, 295 knots (339&amp;nbsp;mph); 25,000 to {{convert|30000|ft|m|abbr=on}}, 260 knots (299&amp;nbsp;mph); 30,000 to {{convert|35000|ft|m|abbr=on}}, 235 knots (270&amp;nbsp;mph). Little difference was noted above {{convert|15000|ft|m|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;Air Ministry 1945, pp. 38–39. (NF 38 Notes)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Strike (&quot;fighter-bomber&quot;) variants ===
{{Commons category-inline|De Havilland Mosquito FB}}
[[File:Bombing up Mosquito RAF Hunsdon 1944 IWM CH 12407.jpg|thumb|upright|Guns and bombs of an RAAF FB Mk VI]]

The '''FB Mk VI''', which first flew on 1 June 1942, was powered by two, single-stage two-speed, {{convert|1460|hp|kW|abbr=on}} Merlin 21s or {{convert|1635|hp|kW|abbr=on}} Merlin 25s, and introduced a re-stressed and reinforced &quot;basic&quot; wing structure capable of carrying single {{convert|250|or|500|lb|kg|adj=on}} bombs on racks housed in streamlined fairings under each wing, or up to eight [[RP-3|RP-3 25lb or 60 lb rockets]]. In addition fuel lines were added to the wings to enable single {{convert|50|impgal|l|abbr=on}} or {{convert|100|impgal|l|abbr=on}} drop tanks to be carried under each wing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 164.&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stre177&quot;&gt;Streetly 1981, p. 177.&lt;/ref&gt; The usual fixed armament was four 20&amp;nbsp;mm [[Hispano-Suiza HS.404|Hispano Mk.II cannon]] and four .303 (7.7&amp;nbsp;mm) [[M1919 Browning machine gun|Browning machine guns]], while two {{convert|250|or|500|lb|kg|adj=on}} bombs could be carried in the bomb bay.{{refn|The FB Mk VI was built in two sub-series, differentiated by the weight of offensive stores able to be carried: Series i aircraft could only carry {{convert|250|lb|kg}} bombs, while Series ii could carry the {{convert|500|lb|kg}} bombs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stre177&quot;/&gt;|group=nb}}

Unlike the F Mk II, the ventral bay doors were split into two pairs, with the forward pair being used to access the cannon, while the rear pair acted as bomb bay doors.&lt;ref&gt;Thirsk 2006, pp. 50, 208, 216.&lt;/ref&gt; The maximum fuel load was {{convert|719.5|impgal|l}} distributed between {{convert|453|impgal|l}} internal fuel tanks, plus two overload tanks, each of {{convert|66.5|impgal|l}} capacity, which could be fitted in the bomb bay, and two {{convert|100|impgal|l}} drop tanks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stre177&quot;/&gt; All-out level speed is often given as {{convert|368|mi/h|km/h|abbr=on}}, although this speed applies to aircraft fitted with saxophone exhausts. The test aircraft (''HJ679'') fitted with stub exhausts was found to be performing below expectations. It was returned to de Havilland at Hatfield where it was serviced. Its top speed was then tested and found to be {{convert|384|mi/h|km/h|abbr=on}}, in line with expectations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wwiiaircraftperformance.org/mosquito/hj679-dh.pdf &quot;Mosquito FB. Mk. VI HJ.679 – Brief performance trials, A. &amp; A.E.E. Boscombe Down &quot;] via ''wwiiaircraftperformance.org''. Retrieved: 17 August 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; 2,298 FB Mk VIs were built, nearly one-third of Mosquito production.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 164.&quot;/&gt; Two were converted to TR.33 [[aircraft carrier|carrier-borne]], maritime strike prototypes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 164.&quot;/&gt;

The FB Mk VI proved capable of holding its own against [[fighter aircraft]], in addition to strike/bombing roles. For example, on 15 January 1945 Mosquito FB Mk VIs of [[No. 143 Squadron RAF|143 Squadron]] were engaged by 30 [[Focke-Wulf Fw 190]]s from ''[[Jagdgeschwader 5]]'': the Mosquitos sank an armed trawler and two merchant ships, but five Mosquitos were lost (two reportedly to flak),&lt;ref&gt;Bird 2003, pp. 94 – 98.&lt;/ref&gt; while shooting down five Fw 190s.&lt;ref&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 112.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:613 Squadron Mosquito FB.VI at RAF Lasham June 1944.jpg|left|thumb|An FB Mk VI ''NS898'' of [[No. 613 Squadron RAF|613 Squadron]], June 1944, shows full [[invasion stripes]] and is well weathered through operational use.]]

Another fighter-bomber variant was the '''Mosquito FB Mk XVIII''' (sometimes known as the ''[[Tsetse fly|Tsetse]]'') of which one was converted from a FB Mk VI to serve as prototype and 17 were purpose-built. The Mk XVIII was armed with a Molins &quot;6-pounder Class M&quot; cannon: this was a modified [[Ordnance QF 6 pounder|QF 6-pounder (57&amp;nbsp;mm) anti-tank gun]] fitted with an [[auto-loader]] to allow both semi- or fully automatic fire.{{refn|&quot;Molins&quot; refers specifically to the auto-loading mechanism produced by the Molins company.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 165.&quot;/&gt;|group=nb}} 25 rounds were carried, with the entire installation weighing {{convert|1580|lb|kg|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 165.&quot;/&gt; In addition, {{convert|900|lb|kg|abbr=on}} of armour was added within the engine cowlings, around the nose and under the cockpit floor to protect the engines and crew from heavily armed U-boats, the intended primary target of the Mk XVIII.&lt;ref&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, p. 271.&lt;/ref&gt; Two or four .303 (7.7&amp;nbsp;mm) Browning machine guns were retained in the nose and were used to &quot;sight&quot; the main weapon onto the target.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 165.&quot;/&gt;

The [[Air Ministry]] initially suspected that this variant would not work, but tests proved otherwise. Although the gun provided the Mosquito with yet more anti-shipping firepower for use against U-boats, it required a steady approach run to aim and fire the gun, making its wooden construction an even greater liability, in the face of intense anti-aircraft fire. The gun had a muzzle velocity of {{convert|2950|ft/s|m/s|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 165.&quot;/&gt; and an excellent range of some {{convert|1800|–|1,500|yds|m|abbr=off}}. It was sensitive to sidewards movement; an attack required a dive from {{convert|5000|ft|m|abbr=on}} at a 30° angle with the [[turn and bank indicator]] on centre. A move during the dive could jam the gun.&lt;ref&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 105.&lt;/ref&gt; The prototype ''HJ732'' was converted from a FB.VI and was first flown on 8 June 1943.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 165.&quot;/&gt;

The effect of the new weapon was demonstrated on 10 March 1944 when Mk XVIIIs from [[No. 248 Squadron RAF|248 Squadron]] (escorted by four Mk VIs) engaged a German convoy of one U-boat and four destroyers, protected by 10 [[Junkers Ju 88|Ju 88s]]. Three of the Ju 88s were shot down. Pilot Tony Phillips destroyed one Ju 88 with four shells, one of which tore an engine off the Ju 88. The U-boat was damaged. On 25 March, {{GS|U-976||2}} was sunk by Molins-equipped Mosquitos.&lt;ref&gt;Bowman 2005, pp. 106–106.&lt;/ref&gt; On 10 June, {{GS|U-821||2}} was abandoned in the face of intense air attack from No. 248 Squadron, and was later sunk by a [[Consolidated B-24 Liberator|Liberator]] of No. 206 Squadron.&lt;ref&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 108.&lt;/ref&gt; On 5 April 1945 Mosquitos with Molins attacked five German surface ships in the [[Kattegat]] and again demonstrated their value by setting them all on fire and sinking them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 115.&quot;&gt;Bowman 2005, p. 115.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bowman 1997, p. 77.&lt;/ref&gt; A German ''[[Sperrbrecher]]'' (&quot;minefield breaker&quot;) was lost with all hands, with some 200 bodies being recovered by [[Sweden|Swedish]] vessels.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 115.&quot;/&gt; Some 900 German soldiers died in total.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 115.&quot;/&gt; On 9 April, German U-boats {{GS|U-804||2}}, {{GS|U-843||2}} and {{GS|U-1065||2}} were spotted in formation heading for [[Norway]]. All were sunk with rockets.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 115.&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bowman 1997, p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt; {{GS|U-251||2}} and {{GS|U-2359||2}} followed on 19 April and 2 May 1945, also sunk by rockets.&lt;ref&gt;Bowman 2005, pp. 117, 119.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:RAF Mosquito with Molins gun WWII IWM CH 14114.jpg|thumb|Mosquito FB Mk XVIII ''NT225'' of [[No. 248 Squadron RAF|248 Squadron Special Detachment]]. Note the 57&amp;nbsp;mm Molins gun and streamlined blister used to accommodate the automatic loading mechanism.{{refn|On 27 March 1944, the MK XVIIIs of 248 Squadron were formed into the &quot;Special Detachment&quot; unit, which continued through to January 1945.&lt;ref&gt;Sharp and Bowyer 1971, p. 272.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}}]]
Despite the preference for rockets, a further development of the large gun idea was carried out using the even larger, 96&amp;nbsp;mm calibre [[Ordnance QF 32 pounder|QF 32-pounder]], a gun based on the [[QF 3.7-inch AA gun]] designed for tank use, the airborne version using a novel form of [[muzzle brake]]. Developed to prove the feasibility of using such a large weapon in the Mosquito, this installation was not completed until after the war, when it was flown and fired in a single aircraft without problems, then scrapped.

Designs based on the Mk VI were the '''FB Mk 26''', built in Canada, and the '''FB Mk 40''', built in Australia, powered by [[Packard V-1650|Packard Merlins]]. The FB.26 improved from the FB.21 using {{convert|1620|hp|kW|abbr=on}} single stage Packard Merlin 225s. Some 300 were built and another 37 converted to T.29 standard.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 165.&quot;/&gt; 212 FB.40s were built by de Havilland Australia. Six were converted to PR.40; 28 to PR.41s, one to FB.42 and 22 to T.43 trainers. Most were powered by Packard-built Merlin 31 or 33s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 166.&quot;/&gt;

===Trainers===
The Mosquito was also built as the '''Mosquito T Mk III''' two-seat [[Trainer (aircraft)|trainer]]. This version, powered by two Rolls-Royce Merlin 21s, was unarmed and had a modified cockpit fitted with dual control arrangements. A total of 348 of the '''T Mk III''' were built for the RAF and [[Fleet Air Arm]]. [[de Havilland Australia]] built 11 '''T Mk 43''' trainers, similar to the Mk III.

===Torpedo-bombers===
To meet specification [[N.15/44]] for a navalised Mosquito for [[Royal Navy]] use as a torpedo bomber, de Havilland produced a [[aircraft carrier|carrier-borne]] variant. A Mosquito FB.VI was modified as a prototype designated '''Sea Mosquito TR Mk 33''' with folding wings, arrester hook, thimble nose radome, Merlin 25 engines with four-bladed propellers and a new oleo-pneumatic landing gear rather than the standard rubber-in-compression gear. Initial carrier tests of the Sea Mosquito were carried out by [[Eric Brown (pilot)|Eric &quot;Winkle&quot; Brown]] aboard [[HMS Indefatigable (R10)|HMS ''Indefatigable'']], the first landing-on taking place on 25 March 1944. An order for 100 TR.33s was placed although only 50 were built at Leavesden. Armament was four 20&amp;nbsp;mm cannon, two 500&amp;nbsp;lb bombs in the bomb bay (another two could be fitted under the wings), eight 60&amp;nbsp;lb rockets (four under each wing) and a standard torpedo under the fuselage. The first production TR.33 flew on 10 November 1945. This series was followed by six '''Sea Mosquito TR Mk 37'''s, which differed in having ASV Mk XIII radar instead of the TR.33's AN/APS-6.

===Target tugs===

The RAF's target tug version was the '''Mosquito TT Mk 35''', which were the last aircraft to remain in operational service with No 3 CAACU at Exeter, being finally retired in 1963. These aircraft were then featured in the film [[633 Squadron]].
A number of B Mk XVIs bombers were converted into TT Mk 39 target tug aircraft. The Royal Navy also operated the '''Mosquito TT Mk 39''' for target towing.
Two ex-RAF FB.6s were converted to TT.6 standard at [[Manchester Airport|Manchester (Ringway) Airport]] by [[Fairey Aviation]] in 1953–1954, and delivered to the [[Belgian Air Force]] for use as towing aircraft from the [[Sylt]] firing ranges.

===Canadian-built===
[[File:DeHavilland Mosquito NACA 1945.jpg|thumb|B Mk XX, the Canadian version of B Mk IV. One of the 40 USAAF F-8s.]]
A total of 1,032&lt;ref&gt;Birtles 2017, Appendix III&lt;/ref&gt; (wartime 
+ 2 afterwards) Mosquitos were built by De Havilland Canada at [[CFB Downsview|Downsview Airfield]] in Downsview Ontario (now [[Downsview Park]] in Toronto Ontario).
* '''Mosquito B Mk VII''' : Canadian version based on the Mosquito B Mk V bomber aircraft. Powered by two {{convert|1418|hp|kW|abbr=on}} Packard Merlin 31 piston engines; 25 built.
* '''Mosquito B Mk XX''' : Canadian version of the Mosquito B Mk IV bomber aircraft; 145 built, of which 40 were converted into '''F-8''' photo-reconnaissance aircraft for the [[USAAF]].
* '''Mosquito FB Mk 21''' : Canadian version of the Mosquito FB Mk VI fighter-bomber aircraft. Powered by two {{convert|1460|hp|kW|abbr=on}} Rolls-Royce Merlin 31 piston engines, three built.
* '''Mosquito T Mk 22''' : Canadian version of the Mosquito T Mk III training aircraft.
* '''Mosquito B Mk 23''' : Unused designation for a bomber variant.
* '''Mosquito FB Mk 24''' : Canadian fighter-bomber version. Powered by two {{convert|1620|hp|kW|abbr=on}} Rolls-Royce Merlin 301 piston engines; two built.
* '''Mosquito B Mk 25''' : Improved version of the Mosquito B Mk XX Bomber aircraft. Powered by two {{convert|1620|hp|kW|abbr=on}} Packard Merlin 225 piston engines; 400 built.
* '''Mosquito FB Mk 26''' : Improved version of the Mosquito FB Mk 21 fighter-bomber aircraft. Powered by two {{convert|1620|hp|kW|abbr=on}} Packard Merlin 225 piston engines; 338 built.
* '''Mosquito T Mk 27''' : Canadian-built training aircraft.
* '''Mosquito T Mk 29''' : A number of FB Mk 26 fighters were converted into T Mk 29 trainers.

===Australian-built===
[[File:Mosquito bomber (P03823-001).jpg|thumb|Mosquito FB Mk 40 ''A52-50''.]]
* '''Mosquito FB Mk 40''' : Two-seat fighter-bomber version for the [[RAAF]]. Powered by two {{convert|1460|hp|kW|abbr=on}} Rolls-Royce Merlin 31 piston engines. A total of 178 built in Australia.
* '''Mosquito PR Mk 40''' : This designation was given to six FB Mk 40s, which were converted into photo-reconnaissance aircraft.
* '''Mosquito FB Mk 41''' : Two-seat fighter-bomber version for the RAAF. A total of 11 were built in Australia.
* '''Mosquito PR Mk 41''' : Two-seat photo-survey version for the RAAF. A total of 17 were built in Australia.
* '''Mosquito FB Mk 42''' : Two-seat fighter-bomber version. Powered by two Rolls-Royce Merlin 69 piston engines. One FB Mk 40 aircraft was converted into a Mosquito FB Mk 42.
* '''Mosquito T Mk 43''' : Two-seat training version for the RAAF. A total of 11 FB Mk 40s were converted into Mosquito T Mk 43s.

===Highball===
A number of Mosquito IVs were modified by [[Vickers-Armstrongs]] to carry Highball &quot;[[bouncing bomb]]s&quot; and were allocated Vickers Type numbers:
* Type 463 – Prototype Highball conversion of Mosquito IV ''DZ741''.
* Type 465 – Conversion of 33 Mosquito IVs to carry Highball.

==Production==

[[File:MossyPrepare42beautypic.jpg|thumb|B Mk IV ''DK336'' of [[No. 105 Squadron RAF|105 Squadron]] being prepared for [[Operation Oyster]], December 1942.]]

About 5,000 of the total of 7,781 Mosquitos built had major structural components fabricated from wood in [[High Wycombe]], Buckinghamshire, England.&lt;ref&gt;Cole, Roger. High Wycombe – Local History Series. Stroud, Gloucestershire, UK: Tempus Publishing Ltd., 2001. {{ISBN|0-7524-2290-1}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Fuselages, wings and tailplanes were made at furniture companies such as Ronson, [[G-Plan|E. Gomme]], [[Parker Knoll]], Austinsuite and Styles &amp; Mealing. Wing spars were made by J. B. Heath and Dancer &amp; Hearne. Many of the other parts, including flaps, flap shrouds, fins, leading edge assemblies and bomb doors were also produced in the Buckinghamshire town. Dancer &amp; Hearne processed much of the wood from start to finish, receiving timber and transforming it into finished wing spars at their factory in Penn Street on the outskirts of High Wycombe.

Initially much of the specialised yellow birch [[wood veneer]] and finished plywood used for the prototypes and early production aircraft was shipped from firms in Wisconsin, US.&lt;ref name=&quot;Connor-Madison, pp. 2-3.&quot;&gt;Connor-Madison 2007, pp. 2–3.&lt;/ref&gt; Prominent in this role were Roddis Plywood and Veneer Manufacturing in [[Marshfield, Wisconsin|Marshfield]]. In conjunction with the USDA [[Forest Products Laboratory]], Hamilton Roddis had developed new plywood adhesives and hot pressing technology.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foresthistory.org/publications/fht/fhtspringfall2005/fht05_hotr_wisconsin.pdf Forest History, Fall 2005, pp. 65–66] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131004223150/http://www.foresthistory.org/publications/fht/fhtspringfall2005/fht05_hotr_wisconsin.pdf# |date=4 October 2013 }} Retrieved: 30 July 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; {{refn|Local memories are of teams of young women ironing the (unusually thin) strong wood veneer before shipping to the UK.[http://www.marshfieldnewsherald.com/article/20131023/MNH01/310230453/Marshfield-women-recall-building-engineering-marvels-skies &quot;Marshfield women recall building engineering marvels of the skies&quot;]|group=nb}}

===Canada===
In July 1941, it was decided that DH Canada would build Mosquitos at Downsview, Ontario. This was to continue even if Germany invaded Great Britain.&lt;ref&gt;Birtles 2017, ch. 8.&lt;/ref&gt; Packard Merlin engines produced under licence were bench-tested by August and the first two aircraft were built in September. Production was to increase to fifty per month by early 1942. Initially, the Canadian production was for bomber variants; later, fighters, fighter-bombers and training aircraft were also made.{{refn|See &quot;Variants&quot; Section of this Article|group=nb}} DH Chief Production Engineer, Harry Povey, was sent first, then W. D. Hunter followed on an extended stay, to liaise with materials and parts suppliers. As was the case with initial UK production, Tego-bonded plywood and birch veneer was obtained from firms in Wisconsin, principally Roddis Plywood and Veneer Manufacturing, Marshfield.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Connor-Madison, p. 11.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Enemy action delayed the shipping of jigs and moulds and it was decided to build these locally.{{refn|A consequence was that Canada used concrete shell moulds right from the start, rather than the wooden mounds made by pattern makers in England|group=nb}}  During 1942, production improved to over 80 machines per month, as sub-contractors and suppliers became established. A mechanised production line based in part on car building methods started in 1944.&lt;ref&gt;Toronto Air and Space Museum, &quot;Community Memories – Mosquito Aircraft Production at Downsview&quot;,
[http://www.virtualmuseum.ca/sgc-cms/histoires_de_chez_nous-community_memories/pm_v2.php?id=story_line&amp;lg=English&amp;fl=0&amp;ex=00000430&amp;sl=3189&amp;pos=1 Accessed 11 September 2017]&lt;/ref&gt; When flight testing could no longer keep up, this was moved to the Central Aircraft Company airfield, London, Ontario, where the approved Mosquitos left for commissioning and subsequent ferry transfer to Europe.

Ferrying Mosquitos and many other types of WWII aircraft from Canada to Europe was dangerous, resulting in losses of lives and machines, but in the exigencies of war it was regarded as the best option for twin-engine and multi-engine aircraft. In the parlance of the day, among RAF personnel, &quot;it was no piece of cake.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Christie&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Christie|first=Carl A.|title=Ocean Bridge – The history of RAF Ferry Command|year=1995|publisher=Midland Publishing, Leicester, England|pp=245–277}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;A Country by Consent – World War II – Ferry Command, by Carl A. Christie&quot;,
[http://www.canadahistoryproject.ca/1939-45/1939-45-09-ferry-command.html Accessed 11 September 2017]&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|Rumors that were hard to credit circulated, including for example the theory of &quot;auto-explosion&quot;!|group=nb}} Considerable efforts were made by de Havilland Canada to resolve problems with engine and oil systems and an additional five hours of flight testing were introduced before the ferry flight, but the actual cause of some of the losses was unknown. Nevertheless, by the end of the war, nearly 500 Mosquito bombers and fighter-bombers had been ferried successfully by the Canadian operation.&lt;ref&gt;Hotson 1983, pp. 77–87.&lt;/ref&gt;

After DH Canada had been established for the Mosquito, further manufacturing was set up at DH Australia, in Sydney. One of the DH staff who travelled there was the distinguished test pilot, [[Pat Fillingham]]. These production lines added totals of 1,133&lt;ref&gt;Thirsk 2006, p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt; aircraft of varying types from Canada plus 212 aircraft from Australia.{{refn|The latter were fighter-bomber variants, PR aircraft and trainers, all for use in the war against Japan. Arial surveys of Australian territory continued with the PR types until 1953.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Birtles, Chap. 8.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}}

===Exports===
In total, both during the war and after, de Havilland exported 46 FB.VIs and 29 PR. XVIs to Australia; two FB.VI and 18 NF.30s to [[Belgium]]; approximately 250 FB.26, T.29 and T.27s from Canada to [[Republic of China (1912–1949)|Nationalist China]]. A significant number never went into service due to deterioration on the voyage and to crashes during Chinese pilot training, however five were captured by the [[People's Liberation Army]] during the [[Chinese Civil War]];&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Birtles&quot; Chap.8&lt;/ref&gt; 19 FB.VIs to [[Czechoslovakia]] in 1948; 6 FB.VIs to [[Dominica]]; a few B.IVs, 57 FB.VIs, 29 PR.XVIs and 23 NF.XXXs to [[France]]. Some T.IIIs were exported to [[Israel]] along with 60 FB.VIs, and at least five PR.XVIs and 14 naval versions. Four T.IIIs, 76 FB.VIs, one FB.40 and four T.43s were exported to [[New Zealand]]. Three T.IIIs were exported to [[Norway]], and 18 FB.VIs, which were later converted to night fighter standard. [[South Africa]] received two F.II and 14 PR.XVI/XIs and [[Sweden]] received 60 NF.XIXs. [[Turkey]] received 96 FB.VIs and several T.IIIs, and [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]] had 60 NF.38s, 80 FB.VIs and three T.IIIs delivered.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 163.&quot;/&gt;

===Sites===
Total Mosquito production was 7,781, of which 6,710 were built during the war.

 [[File:De Havilland Mosquito IV ExCC.jpg|right|thumb|Factory-fresh Mosquito B.XVIs built by Percival: visible serial numbers are ''PF563'', ''561'' and ''564''.]]
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;
|+Production&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman 2005, p. 163.&quot;/&gt;
|-
! Producer and site
! Number built
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; |de Havilland [[Hatfield, Hertfordshire|Hatfield]], Hertfordshire
| 3,326
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; | de Havilland Leavesden, Hertfordshire
| 1,476
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; | [[Standard Motor Company]] ([[Canley]]), [[Coventry]]
| 1,066
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; | [[Percival Aircraft Company]], [[Luton]]
| 245
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; | [[Airspeed Aircraft]], [[Portsmouth]]
| 122
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; | de Havilland [[Hawarden Airport|Hawarden]], [[Chester]]{{refn|A former Vickers-Armstrong shadow factory|group=nb}}
| 96
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; | [[de Havilland Canada]], [[Toronto]]
| 1,076
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; | [[de Havilland Australia]], [[Sydney]]
| 212
|}

==Civilian accidents and incidents==
A number of Mosquitos were lost in civilian airline service, mostly with [[British Overseas Airways Corporation]] during World War II.
* On 17 August 1943, G-AGGF crashed near [[Glenshee]], [[Perthshire]].&lt;ref name=Aeroplane0415&gt;{{cite magazine |title=BOAC Special |magazine=Aeroplane |issue=April 2015 |pages=26–49 |publisher=Key Publishing |location=Stamford |issn=0143-7240}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On 25 October 1943, G-AGGG crashed near [[RAF Leuchars]].&lt;ref name=Aeroplane0415/&gt;
* On 3 January 1944, de Havilland Mosquito G-AGGD stalled on landing at [[Lidköping-Hovby Airport|Såtenäs]], Sweden and was written off.&lt;ref name=Aeroplane0415/&gt;
* On 19 August 1944, de Havilland Mosquito G-AGKP crashed into the [[North Sea]] off [[Leuchars]], [[Fife]]. All three people on board were killed.&lt;ref name=Aeroplane0415/&gt;
* On 29 August 1944, de Havilland Mosquito G-AGKR disappeared on a flight from [[Gothenburg]], Sweden to RAF Leuchars with the loss of both crew members.&lt;ref name=Aeroplane0415/&gt;
* On 21 March 1945, de Havilland Mosquito G- AGKR Bombed The Institut Jeanne d'Arc, which was a French-language Roman Catholic school at 74 Frederiksberg Allé in the Frederiksberg district of central Copenhagen, Denmark causing the death of 86 children and 18 adults.&lt;ref name=Aeroplane0415/&gt;

==Operators==
{{Main|List of de Havilland Mosquito operators}}
{{Div col|colwidth=22em}}
{{plainlist|
*{{AUS}}
*{{BEL}}
*{{flag|Canada|1921}}
*{{ROC}}
*{{PRC}}
*{{TCH}}
*{{DOM}}
*{{FRA}}
*{{flag|Haiti|1859}}
*{{ISR}}
*{{NZL}}
*{{NOR}}
*{{flag|Poland|1928}}
*{{flag|South Africa|1928}}
*{{USSR}}
*{{SWE}}
*{{SUI}}
*{{TUR}}
*{{UK}}
*{{flag|United States|1912}}
*{{YUG}}
}}
{{Div col end}}

==Surviving aircraft==
{{Main|List of surviving de Havilland Mosquitos}}
[[File:de Havilland Mosquito 11.JPG|right|thumb|De Havilland Mosquito ''KA114'' at the &quot;Wings over Wairarapa&quot; Airshow, Masterton, New Zealand (January 2013)]]
There are approximately 30 non-flying Mosquitos around the world with four airworthy examples, three in the United States and one in Canada. The largest collection of Mosquitos is at the [[de Havilland Aircraft Heritage Centre]] in the United Kingdom, which owns three aircraft, including the first prototype, ''W4050'', the only initial prototype of a Second World War British aircraft design still in existence in the 21st century.

==Specifications (B Mk.XVI)==
[[File:Mosquito PR34 Silh.png|right|300px|Mosquito P.R.34.]]
{{Aircraft specs
|ref=Jane's Fighting Aircraft of World War II,&lt;ref name=Jane-bomber&gt;Bridgman 1946, pp. 115–117.&lt;/ref&gt; World War II Warbirds&lt;ref name=&quot;ww2war&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last1=La Bonne |first1=Frans |title=The de Havilland Mosquito. |url=http://www.ww2warbirds.net/ww2htmls/dehamosqbfn.html |website=World War II Warbirds |accessdate=30 April 2019 |date=9 February 2001 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140908155632/http://www.ww2warbirds.net/ww2htmls/dehamosqbfn.html |archive-date=8 September 2014 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|prime units?=imp
&lt;!--
        General characteristics
--&gt;
|crew=2: pilot, bombardier/navigator
|capacity=
|length ft=44
|length in=6
|length note=
|span ft=54
|span in=2
|span note=
|height ft=17
|height in=5
|height note=
|wing area sqft=454
|wing area note=
|aspect ratio=&lt;!-- sailplanes --&gt;
|airfoil=RAF 34 (modified)&lt;ref name=&quot;Selig&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last1=Lednicer |first1=David |title=The Incomplete Guide to Airfoil Usage |url=https://m-selig.ae.illinois.edu/ads/aircraft.html |website=m-selig.ae.illinois.edu |accessdate=16 April 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|empty weight lb=14300
|empty weight note=
|gross weight lb=18100
|gross weight note=
|max takeoff weight lb=25000
|max takeoff weight note=
|fuel capacity=
|more general=
&lt;!--
        Powerplant
--&gt;
|eng1 number=1
|eng1 name=[[Rolls-Royce Merlin 76]]
|eng1 type=V-12 liquid-cooled piston engine
|eng1 hp=1710
|eng1 note fitted to LHS

|eng2 number=1
|eng2 name=[[Rolls-Royce Merlin 77]]
|eng2 type=V-12 liquid-cooled piston engine
|eng2 hp=1710
|eng2 note= RHS fitted with a blower for cabin pressurisation

|prop blade number=3
|prop name=constant-speed propellers
|prop dia ft=&lt;!-- propeller aircraft --&gt;
|prop dia in=&lt;!-- propeller aircraft --&gt;
|prop dia note=
&lt;!--
        Performance
--&gt;
|max speed mph=415
|max speed note=at {{convert|28000|ft|m|abbr=on}}
|cruise speed mph=
|cruise speed note=
|stall speed mph=
|stall speed note=
|never exceed speed mph=
|never exceed speed note=
|minimum control speed mph=
|minimum control speed note=
|range miles=1300
|range note=
|combat range miles=
|combat range note=
|ferry range miles=
|ferry range note=
|endurance=&lt;!-- if range unknown --&gt;
|ceiling ft=37000
|ceiling note=
|g limits=&lt;!-- aerobatic --&gt;
|roll rate=&lt;!-- aerobatic --&gt;
|climb rate ftmin=2850
|climb rate note=
|time to altitude=
|wing loading lb/sqft=39.9
|wing loading note=
|fuel consumption lb/mi=
|power/mass={{cvt|0.189|hp/lb}}

|more performance=
&lt;!--
        Armament
--&gt;
|bombs={{convert|4000|lb|kg}}
|avionics=* [[GEE (navigation)|GEE]] [[radio-navigation]]
}}

==Notable appearances in media==
&lt;!-- ===============({{NoMoreCruft}})===============--&gt;
&lt;!-- Please READ [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content#Popular culture]] and [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Style guide#Popular culture]] before adding any &quot;Popular culture&quot; items.

Please do not add the many minor appearances of the aircraft. This section is only for major cultural appearances where the aircraft plays a MAJOR part in the story line, or has an &quot;especially notable&quot; role in what is listed. A verifiable source proving the appearance's notability may be required. Random cruft, including ALL Ace Combat, Battlefield, and Metal Gear Solid appearances, and ALL anime/fiction lookalike speculation, WILL BE removed.

If your item has been removed, please discuss it on the talk page FIRST. A verifiable source proving the appearance's notability may be required. If a consensus is reached to include your item, a regular editor of this page will add it back. Thank you for your cooperation.--&gt;
&lt;!-- ===============({{NoMoreCruft}})=============== --&gt;
{{main|Aircraft in fiction#de Havilland Mosquito}}
&lt;!--
READ note at top about notability, major roles and look-a-likes before adding anything; take any potentially contentious submissions to the talk page. See [[CH-53E Super Stallion]] for [[Grindor]] in [[Transformers: Revenge of the Fallen]]. --&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Aviation}}
{{Aircontent
|related=
* [[de Havilland Hornet|de Havilland Hornet/Sea Hornet]]
* [[I.Ae. 24 Calquin]]
|similar aircraft=
* [[Bristol Beaufighter]]
* [[Douglas A-26 Invader]]
* [[Focke-Wulf Ta 154]] ''Moskito'', an all-wood, late war (1943–44) twin-engined German heavy fighter design
* [[Heinkel He 219]]
* [[Junkers Ju 88]]
* [[Kawasaki Ki-102]]
* [[Messerschmitt Me 410]]
* [[Nakajima J1N]]
* [[Saab 18]]
|lists=
* [[List of aircraft of World War II]]
* [[List of aircraft of the United Kingdom in World War II]]
* [[List of fighter aircraft]]
* [[List of bomber aircraft]]
|see also=
'''Notable mosquito missions'''
* [[Oslo Mosquito raid]]
* [[Operation Jericho]]
* [[Operation Carthage]]
* [[Aarhus Air Raid]]
}}

==References==
===Notes===
{{Reflist|group=nb|35em}}

===Citations===
{{Reflist|20em}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin}}
* Air Ministry. Pilot's Notes For Mosquito B IV. London: 1943. A.P.2019D-PN.
* Air Ministry. Pilot's Notes For Mosquito, Marks VIII and IX, Mark XVI. London: 1944. A.P.2653A, B, F, H &amp; J-PN.
* Air Ministry. ''Pilot's Notes For Mosquito FB 6''. London: 1945. {{ISBN|978-0-85979-020-8}}.
* Air Ministry. ''Pilot's Notes For Mosquito NF 38''. London: 1945. {{ISBN|978-0-85979-075-8}}.
* Batchelor, John and Malcolm Low. ''de Havilland Mosquito Manual'' (Plane Essentials). Victoria, Australia: Publishing Solutions, 2008. {{ISBN|978-1-906589-00-4}}.
* Bird, Andrew. ''A Separate Little War''. London, UK: Grub Street, 2003. {{ISBN|1-904010-43-1}}.
* Birtles, Philip. ''De Havilland Mosquito: The Original Multirole Combat Aircraft''. Stroud, England: Fonthill Media, 2017. {{ISBN|978-1-78155-494-4}}.
* Bishop, Edward. ''The Wooden Wonder''. Shrewsbury, UK: Airlife Publishing Ltd., 3rd edition 1995. {{ISBN|1-85310-708-5}}.
* Boiten, Theo. Nachtjagd: the night fighter versus bomber war over the Third Reich, 1939–45. Crowood Press Ltd, 1997 London. {{ISBN|978-1861260864}}
* Boog, Horst, Gerhard Krebs and Detlef Vogel. ''Germany and the Second World War: Volume VII: The Strategic Air War in Europe and the War in the West and East Asia, 1943-1944/5.'' Oxford, UK: Clarendon Press, 2006. {{ISBN|978-0-19822-889-9}}.
* Bowman, Martin. ''de Havilland Mosquito'' (Crowood Aviation series). Ramsbury, Marlborough, Wiltshire, UK: The Crowood Press, 2005. {{ISBN|1-86126-736-3}}.
* Bowman, Martin. ''Mosquito Bomber/Fighter-bomber Units 1942–45''. Oxford, UK: Osprey Publishing, 1997. {{ISBN|1-85532-690-6}}.
* Bowman, Martin. ''Mosquito Fighter/Fighter-bomber Units of World War 2''. Oxford, UK: Osprey Publishing, 1998. {{ISBN|1-85532-731-7}}.
* Bowman, Martin. ''Mosquito Photo-Reconnaissance Units of World War 2''. Oxford, UK: Osprey Publishing, 1999. {{ISBN|1-85532-891-7}}.
* Bowyer, Chaz. ''Mosquito at War''. Shepperton, Surrey, UK: Ian Allan Ltd., 4th impression 1979. {{ISBN|0-7110-0474-9}}.
* Bowyer, Michael J.F., Bryan Philpott and Stuart Howe. ''Mosquito (Classic Aircraft No. 7: Their History and How to Model Them)''. Cambridge, UK: Patrick Stephens Ltd., 1980. {{ISBN|0-85059-432-4}}.
* Bridgman, Leonard, ed. &quot;The D.H.98 Mosquito.&quot; ''Jane’s Fighting Aircraft of World War II''. London: Studio, 1946. {{ISBN|1-85170-493-0}}.
* Buttler, Tony. ''British Secret Projects: Fighters &amp; Bombers 1935–1950''. Hinckley, UK: Midland Publishing, 2004. {{ISBN|1-85780-179-2}}.
* Caldwell, Donald L. and Richard Muller. ''The Luftwaffe Over Germany: Defense of the Reich'' . London: Greenhill MBI Publishing Company, 2007.  {{ISBN|1-85367-712-4}}
* Cole, Roger. ''High Wycombe – Local History Series''. Stroud, Gloucestershire, UK: Tempus Publishing Ltd., 2001. {{ISBN|0-7524-2290-1}}.
* Connor, Sara Witter, Hamilton Roddis Memorial Lecture Series No. 11. ''Wisconsin Flying Trees: Wisconsin Plywood Industry’s Contribution to WWII''. Department of Forest &amp; Wildlife Ecology, Kemp Natural Resources Station, College of Agricultural and Life Sciences, University of Wisconsin – Madison 31 January 2007. [https://web.archive.org/web/20170913190201/http://kemp.wisc.edu/wp-content/uploads/sites/59/2015/08/HRLBConnor2007.pdf Wayback Machine].
* Christie, Carl A. ''Ocean Bridge – The history of RAF Ferry Command'' Midland Publishing, Leicester, England, 1995. {{ISBN|1-85780-029-X}}.
* Harris, Sir Arthur T. et al. ''Despatch on War Operations – 23rd. February 1942 to 8th. May 1945''. Frank Cass, England, 1993. {{ISBN|0-7146-4692-X}}.
* Hotson, Fred. ''The De Havilland Canada Story''. Toronto: CANAV Books, 1983. {{ISBN|0-9690703-2-2}}.
* Malayney, Norman, The 25th Bomb Group (Rcn) History in WWII, Schiffer Publishers Ltd. 2011.{{ISBN|978-07643-3950-9}}.
* Miracle, Daniel B. and Steven L. Donaldson. ''ASM Handbook: Composites''. Cleveland, Ohio: ASM International, 2001. {{ISBN|0-87170-703-9}}.
* Mujumdar, A. S. ''Drying '92: Proceedings of the 8th International Drying Symposium''. Toronto: Elsevier, 1992. {{ISBN|0-444-89393-8}}.
* Rhodes, Tom. ''Stress Without Tears''. Jacobs Publishing, 1st edition 1 December 2008. {{ISBN|978-1-4392-0717-8}}.
* Scott, Stuart R. &quot;Mosquito Thunder: No. 105 Squadron RAF at war 1942-5.&quot; Sutton Publishing, Stroud, Gloucestershire, UK, 1999. {{ISBN|0-7509-1800-4}}.
* Scutts, Jerry. ''Mosquito in Action, Part 2''. Carrollton, Texas: Squadron/Signal Publications Inc., 1993. {{ISBN|0-89747-303-5}}.
* Sharp, C. Martin and Michael J.F. Bowyer. ''Mosquito''. London: Faber &amp; Faber, 1971. {{ISBN|0-571-04750-5}}.
* Sharp, C. Martin and Michael J.F. Bowyer. ''Mosquito (2nd ed.)''. Manchester, UK: Crécy Books Ltd, 1995. {{ISBN|0-947554-41-6}}.
* Simons, Graham M. ''Mosquito: The Original Multi-Role Combat Aircraft''. Barnsley, Yorkshire, UK: Pen &amp; Sword, 2011. {{ISBN|978-18488-442-61}}
* Streetly, Martin. &quot;The Aircraft of 100 Group: Part 14. DH Mosquito, Internal Detail&quot;. ''Scale Models'', Volume 12, Issue 139, April 1981.
* Stroud, John. &quot;Wings of Peace:- de Havilland Albatross.&quot; [http://www.aeroplanemonthly.co.uk/ ''Aeroplane Monthly,''], Volume 18, Issue 206, June 1990.
* Thirsk, Ian.''de Havilland Mosquito: An Illustrated History Volume 2''. Manchester, UK: Crécy Publishing Limited, 2006. {{ISBN|0-85979-115-7}}.
* Thomas, Geoffrey J. and Barry Ketely. ''KG 200: The Luftwaffe's Most Secret Unit''. Tokyo: Hikoki Publications, 2003. {{ISBN|1-902109-33-3}}.
* Wooldridge, John de L. ''Low Attack – The story of two Mosquito squadrons, 1940–1943''. Crecy Books, England, 1993. {{ISBN|0-947554-31-9}}.

===Further reading===
* Birtles, Philip. ''Mosquito: A Pictorial History of the DH98''. London: Jane's Publishing Company Ltd., 1980. {{ISBN|0-531-03714-2}}.
* Birtles, Philip. ''De Havilland Mosquito: The Original Multirole Combat Aircraft''. Stroud, England: Fonthill Media, 2017. {{ISBN|978-1-78155-494-4}}.
* Gilman J.D. and J. Clive. ''KG 200''. London: Pan Books Ltd., 1978. {{ISBN|0-85177-819-4}}.
* Hardy, M.J. ''The de Havilland Mosquito''. Devon, UK/New York: David &amp; Charles (Publishers) Ltd./Arco Publishing, 1977. {{ISBN|0-7153-7367-6}}, (David &amp; Charles) {{ISBN|0-668-04051-3}} (Arco).
* Hinchcliffe, Peter. ''The Other Battle: Luftwaffe Night Aces vs Bomber Command''. London: Zenith Press, 1996. {{ISBN|0-7603-0265-0}}.
* Holliday, Joe. ''Mosquito! The Wooden Wonder Aircraft of World War II''. Toronto: Doubleday, 1970. {{ISBN|0-7701-0138-0}}.
* Howe, Stuart. ''Mosquito Portfolio''. London: Ian Allan Ltd., 1984. {{ISBN|0-7110-1406-X}}.
* Jackson, Robert. ''de Havilland Mosquito'' (Combat Legend). Shrewsbury, UK: Airlife Publishing Ltd., 2003. {{ISBN|1-84037-358-X}}.
* Jones, R.C. ''de Havilland Mosquito: RAF Northern Europe 1936–45''. London: Ducimus Books Ltd., 1970.
* Mason, Francis K. and Richard Ward. ''De Havilland Mosquito in RAF-FAA-RAAF-SAAF-RNZAF-RCAF-USAAF-French &amp; Foreign Service''. Canterbury, Kent, UK: Osprey Publishing Ltd., 1972. {{ISBN|0-85045-043-8}}.
* McKee, Alexander. ''The Mosquito Log''. London: Souvenir Press Ltd., 1988. {{ISBN|0-285-62838-0}}.
* Morgan, Hugh and John Weal. ''German Jet Aces of World War 2''. London: Osprey Publishing Ltd, 1998. {{ISBN|1-85532-634-5}}.
* Price, Nigel (ed.). &quot;Mosquito: A Celebration of de Havilland's 'Wooden Wonder'.&quot; [http://www.flypast.com/ FlyPast Special]. Stamford, Lincolnshire, UK: Key Publishing Ltd., 2009.
* Radinger, Will and Walter Schick. ''Me262'' (German lang. ed.), Berlin: Avantic Verlag GmbH, 1996. {{ISBN|3-925505-21-0}}.
* Sasbye, Kjeld Mahler. ''Operation Carthage''. Copenhagen: Den Danske Luftfartsskole, 1994. {{ISBN|87-985141-0-5}}.
* Scholefield, R.A. ''Manchester Airport''. Stroud, UK: Sutton Publishing, 1998. {{ISBN|0-7509-1954-X}}.
* Scutts, Jerry. ''Mosquito in Action, Part 1''. Carrollton, Texas: Squadron/Signal Publications Inc., 1993. {{ISBN|0-89747-285-3}}.
* Shacklady, Edward. ''De Havilland Mosquito (Classic WWII Aviation, Volume 6)''. Bristol, UK: Cerberus Publishing Ltd., 2003. {{ISBN|1-84145-108-8}}.
* Stanley, Colonel Roy M. II, USAF (Ret). ''V-Weapons Hunt: Defeating German Secret Weapons.'' Barnsley, South Yorkshire, UK: Pen &amp; Sword, 2010. {{ISBN|978-1-84884-259-5}}.
* Sweetman, Bill and Rikyu Watanabe. ''Mosquito''. London: Jane's Publishing Company Ltd., 1981. {{ISBN|0-7106-0131-X}}.

{{refend}}

==External links==
{{commons category|De Havilland DH.98 Mosquito}}
* [https://www.scribd.com/doc/46334495 Manual: (1950) AP 2019E-P.N. Pilot's Notes Mosquito FB6]{{dead link|date=March 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}
* [http://www.mossie.org/ The Mosquito Page at Mossie.org]
* [http://www.dehavillandmuseum.co.uk/ de Havilland Aircraft Heritage Centre a.k.a. Mosquito Aircraft Museum]
* [http://www.calgarymosquitosociety.com Calgary Mosquito Aircraft Preservation Association]
* &lt;!---Mosquito no longer listed at FF---[http://www.fighterfactory.com/restoration/dehavilland-mosquito-aircraft.php de Havilland Mosquito FB Mk 26 Restoration Project]---&gt;
* [http://www.vicair.net Victoria Air Maintenance Ltd. Restoring a Mosquito to flying condition]
* [http://peoplesmosquito.org.uk The People's Mosquito Ltd. UK charity restoring Mosquito RL249 to flight. Website features WW2 colour film of the Mosquito]
* [https://archive.is/20130105071443/http://www.theaviationindex.com/aircraft-types/de-havilland-mosquito de Havilland Mosquito magazine articles and publications]
* [http://warbirdregistry.org/mossieregistry/mossieregistry.html Data at Warbirdregistry.org]
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DDPkwI5-dhM Mosquito restoration project New Zealand (633 Squadron theme)] Retrieved: 3 January 2012.
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c7cVvYdLeek Wartime film of the construction of the Mosquito in Australia] Retrieved: 3 January 2012.
* [https://books.google.com/books?id=fScDAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA100 &quot;Flying Plywood With A Sting&quot;: ''Popular Science'' article, December 1943]
* [http://www.ww2aircraft.net/forum/album/showphoto.php?photo=4925&amp;size=big&amp;cat= A close-up picture of the nose of a Tsetse Mosquito FB Mk XVIII showing the Molins 57&amp;nbsp;mm gun muzzle]
* [http://1000aircraftphotos.com/Contributions/PippinBill/6297.htm A photograph of the Tsetse Mosquito FB Mk XVIII ''NT225'']
* [https://books.google.com/books?id=h98DAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA39 &quot;Mosquito Wars on U-Boats With 6-pound Shells.&quot;: ''Popular Mechanics'' article, February 1945, p.&amp;nbsp;39.]
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=M00f5RxhxLY Wartime footage of Coastal Command 57mm cannon and 60lb rocket-armed Mosquitos]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080528084730/http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafbramptonwytonhenlow/rafcms/mediafiles/9818FCBF_1143_EC82_2ED93F5D8312A0C6.pdf Mosquito Pathfinders, Pathfinder Museum]
* [http://www.627squadron.co.uk/ 627 Squadron RAF Mosquito Pathfinders Based at RAF Woodall Spa]
* [http://www.aaib.gov.uk/cms_resources/dft_avsafety_pdf_501355.pdf Air Accidents Investigation Branch (AAIB) report on the crash of T.III G-ASKH, 1996]
* [http://www.iwm.org.uk/collections/item/object/205210758 IWM Image of Mosquito PR34 ''RG241'', which holds the twin piston-engine Atlantic crossing record.]
* [https://archive.org/details/gov.archives.arc.38937 &quot;America Reports On Aid To Allies etc. (1942).&quot;] ''[[Universal Newsreel]]''
* [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1943/1943%20-%202729.html &quot;Mosquito Makes Base&quot;] a 1943 ''Flight'' article on a Mosquito Intruder's battle damage
* [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1944/1944%20-%201321.html &quot;'Pin-Point' Attack On One House by Mosquitoes&quot;] a 1944 ''Flight'' advertisement
* [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1969/1969%20-%203052.html &quot;The Magnificent Mosquito&quot;] a 1969 ''Flight'' article by Air Commodore [[Allen Wheeler]]

{{Navboxes
|title=Articles and topics related to the de Havilland Mosquito
|state=collapsed
|list1=
{{de Havilland aircraft}}
{{De Havilland Australia aircraft}}
{{De Havilland Canada}}
{{Aircraft manufactured in Canada}}
{{RAF WWII Strategic Bombing}}
{{USAAF reconnaissance aircraft}}
{{Swedish military aircraft}}
}}

[[Category:1940s British bomber aircraft]]
[[Category:De Havilland aircraft|Mosquito]]
[[Category:De Havilland Canada aircraft|Mosquito]]
[[Category:De Havilland Mosquito| ]]
[[Category:Mid-wing aircraft]]
[[Category:Reconnaissance aircraft]]
[[Category:Twin piston-engined tractor aircraft]]
[[Category:World War II British bombers]]
[[Category:World War II British fighter aircraft]]
[[Category:World War II night fighter aircraft]]
[[Category:Aircraft first flown in 1940]]</text>
      <sha1>khviejr6k5q9c6fx758xfosde4gpdv3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
