  <page>
    <title>Dana Plato</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9048</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939023008</id>
      <parentid>938077525</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-03T21:29:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Soetermans</username>
        <id>1289606</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Ce</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|American actress}}
{{Infobox person
| name               = Dana Plato
| image              = Dana Plato on the set of television show 'Diff'rent Strokes' 1983-03-09.jpg
| caption            = Plato in 1983
| birth_name         = Dana Michelle Strain
| birth_date         = {{Birth date|1964|11|07}}
| birth_place        = [[Maywood, California]], U.S.
| death_date         = {{death date and age |1999|05|08|1964|11|07|mf=yes}}&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1999/05/10/arts/dana-plato-34-star-of-diff-rent-strokes.html |title=’Dana Plato, 34, Star of 'Diff'rent Strokes' |date=May 10, 1999 |work=[[The New York Times]] |access-date=2015-08-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| death_place        = [[Moore, Oklahoma]], U.S.
| years_active       = 1975–1999
| death_cause        = Multiple drug intoxication&lt;ref name=&quot;deseret&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=336&amp;dat=19990521&amp;id=79MiAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=GewDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6282,2811386 |title=Death of Actress Dana Plato in Oklahoma Ruled a Suicide |date=May 21, 1999 |work=The Deseret News |access-date=2011-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://lubbockonline.com/stories/052299/ent_052299095.shtml |title=Doctor rules Dana Plato's death suicide |date=May 22, 1999 |website=lubbockonline.com |access-date=2012-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| nationality        = American
| alma mater         = Taft Charter High School
| occupation         = Actress, model
| spouse             = {{marriage|Lanny Lambert|1984|1990}}
| children           = Tyler Lambert (1984–2010)
| signature          = Dana Plato signature.jpeg
}}

'''Dana Michelle Plato''' (born '''Dana Michelle Strain'''; November 7, 1964 – May 8, 1999)&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt; was an American actress and model, who was best known for portraying [[Kimberly Drummond]] on the television [[sitcom]] ''[[Diff'rent Strokes]]'', which aired from 1978 to 1986.  

Plato's other works in television include making appearances on [[Family (1976 TV series)|''Family'']], [[What Really Happened to the Class of '65? (TV series)|''What Really Happened to the Class of '65?'']], ''[[Hello, Larry]]'', [[The Facts of Life (TV series)|''The Facts of Life'']], ''[[CHiPs]]'', and ''[[Growing Pains]]''. She also appeared in the feature [[horror film]] ''[[Exorcist II: The Heretic]]'' (1977) as Sandra Phalor, for which she was uncredited, the adventure-horror film ''[[Return to Boggy Creek]]'' (1977) as Evie Joe, the first of the four films in the series, and the comedy film [[California Suite (film)|''California Suite'']] (1978) as Jenny Warren. Starting from the mid-1980s, Plato worked sporadically in independent films, and also did [[voice actor|voice-over work]]. 

Throughout a personal life receiving much media coverage, Plato struggled with [[substance abuse|substance]] and [[alcohol abuse]], and dealt with legal issues, such as [[robbery]]. In 1999, she died from an overdose of prescription drugs at the age of 34 after years of struggling with drugs and poverty, which was later ruled a [[suicide]].

== Early life ==

Plato was born Dana Michelle Strain on November 7, 1964 in [[Maywood, California]] to Linda Strain, an unwed teenager who already was caring for an 18-month-old child. In June 1965, the seven-month-old Dana was adopted by Dean Plato, who owned a trucking company, and his wife Florine &quot;Kay&quot; Plato. Plato was raised in the [[San Fernando Valley]]. When she was three, her adoptive parents divorced, and she lived with her mother.&lt;ref name=&quot;LittleGirlLost2&quot;&gt;{{Cite magazine|last=Gliatto|first=Tom|date=May 24, 1999|title=Little Girl Lost|url=http://www.people.com/people/archive/article/0,,20128316,00.html|volume=51|issue=19|issn=0093-7673|magazine=[[People (magazine)|People]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

== Career ==

=== 1977–1986: Career beginnings and breakthrough ===
At a very young age, Plato began attending auditions with her mother, and from age seven began appearing in television commercials, reportedly appearing in over 100 commercials.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://news.amomama.com/189860-late-diffrent-strokes-star-dana-plato-on.html|title=Late ‘Diff'Rent Strokes’ Star Dana Plato Once Revealed That Mom Kept Her in a ‘Plastic Bubble’|last=Rivas|first=Aby|date=2020-01-25|website=news.amomama.com|language=en|access-date=2020-01-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; She made her acting debut at the age of 11, making a cameo appearance on the television show ''[[The Six Million Dollar Man]]''. Following this, she starred in the television film ''Beyond the Bermuda Triangle''.

Plato made her feature film debut at the age of 13, starring as Sandra Phalor in the horror film ''[[Exorcist II: The Heretic]]'' (1977), for which she was uncredited. She also starred as Evie Joe in the horror film ''[[Return to Boggy Creek]]'' (1977),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://movies.nytimes.com/movie/41121/Return-to-Boggy-Creek/cast |title=Return to Boggy Creek |work=[[The New York Times]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; which was received negatively, being panned by critics.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://fantasticmoviemusings.com/2016/06/11/return-to-boggy-creek-1977/|title=Return to Boggy Creek (1977)|last=Sindelar|first=Dave|date=2016-06-12|website=Fantastic Movie Musings and Ramblings|language=en|access-date=2020-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://bleedingskull.com/return-to-boggy-creek-1978/|title=Bleeding Skull|last=|first=|date=|website=|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film spawned three sequels, of which she took no part in. Plato next starred as Jenny Warren in ''[[California Suite (film)|California Suite]]'' (1978). The film was a critical success,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.the-numbers.com/movie/California-Suite|title=California Suite (1978) - Financial Information|website=The Numbers|access-date=2020-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; becoming Plato's first and only successful feature film.

In addition to acting, Plato was an accomplished figure skater, and at one point she trained for a possible Olympic team spot. It was during this time that she made a brief appearance on TV's ''[[The Gong Show]]'' and was spotted by a producer who helped her secure what became her most famous acting role as Kimberly Drummond on ''Diff'rent Strokes''. According to Plato, her mother decided she should cut back on her skating in order to focus on the TV role.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.actionnewsjax.com/living/aposdiffaposrent-strokesapos-todd-bridges-is-now-the-last-living-member-of-the-core-cast/807488596/|title='Diff'rent Strokes': Todd Bridges is now the last living member of the core cast|last=Today|first=U. S. A.|website=WJAX|language=en-US|access-date=2020-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[File:Nancyreagandiffrentstrokes.jpg|thumb|The cast of ''Diff'rent Strokes'' on set in 1983]]
''Diff'rent Strokes'' debuted on NBC in 1978, becoming an immediate hit. The show features Phillip Drummond ([[Conrad Bain]]), a wealthy white widower in New York City who adopts two black boys after their parents' deaths. Plato played Kimberly, Drummond's teenage daughter, who at the start of the show becomes the adoptive sister of the two boys, Willis ([[Todd Bridges]]) and Arnold ([[Gary Coleman]]). Plato appeared on the show from 1978 until 1984 and again from 1985 to 1986; during her tenure the show appeared on two different networks.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://movies.nytimes.com/person/57045/Dana-Plato|title=Dana Plato – About This Person – Movies &amp; TV – NYTimes.com|work=[[The New York Times]]|access-date=2015-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the season 8 episode that aired on January&amp;nbsp;17, 1986—Plato's final appearance on the show—Kimberly suffers from the effects of [[bulimia]]. She was nominated for a [[Young Artist Award]] for her work on ''Diff'rent Strokes'', and also was part of two [[TV Land Award]] nominations given to the cast of the show.

In 1981, Plato appeared in the [[television special]] ''A Step In Time''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=A Step in Time|url=http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0324072/|access-date=2020-01-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; For her role, Plato received a Young Artist Award nomination, totaling two Young Artist Award nominations. In 1983, she starred in the [[television film]] ''[[High School U.S.A.]]'' alongside Todd Bridges as Cara Ames, while Bridges starred as Otto Lipton.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=Jf4SAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=5u4DAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2526,626569&amp;dq=high-school-usa&amp;hl=en|title=The Spokesman-Review - Google News Archive Search|website=news.google.com|access-date=2020-01-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; In spite of the film being met with a mixed response from critics and viewers alike,&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=High School U.S.A. (1983)|url=https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/high_school_usa|language=en|access-date=2020-01-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=High School U.S.A.|url=http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0085679/|access-date=2020-01-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; it gained popularity at the time of its premiere, and later attained a DVD release.

=== 1987–1999: Career fluctuations and later work ===
After leaving ''Diff'rent Strokes'', Plato attempted to establish herself as a serious actress, but found it difficult to achieve success. She had breast implants and modeled for a June 1989 ''[[Playboy]]'' pictorial, but her career remained in stagnation, and she started taking roles in such [[B-movie]]s as ''Bikini Beach Race'' (1989) and ''Lethal Cowboy'' (1992). 

In 1992, Plato starred in the video game ''[[Night Trap]]'', being one of the first celebrities to star in a video game. The game was an average success (the majority of the game's video content was actually filmed in 1987 then shelved), but is considered a pioneering title due to it being the first game to use live actors, along with casting a well-known personality.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.mobygames.com/game/sega-cd/night-trap |title=MobyGames Page on Night Trap |website=MobyGames |access-date=2010-08-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though the game received mixed to negative reviews, it is best remembered for the controversy it created over the violence and sexuality, along with that surrounding ''[[Mortal Kombat (1992 video game)|Mortal Kombat]]'', which had eventually led to the creation of the [[Entertainment Software Rating Board]] (ESRB).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://archive.org/details/inventory16films00avcl_0/page/91 |title=Inventory: 16 Films Featuring Manic Pixie Dream Girls, 10 Great Songs Nearly Ruined by Saxophone, and 100 More Obsessively Specific Pop-Culture Lists |last=A.V. Club |last2=Klosterman |first2=Chuck |publisher=Simon and Schuster |year=2009 |isbn=1-4165-9473-6 |page=[https://archive.org/details/inventory16films00avcl_0/page/91 91] |url-access=registration }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Toward the end of her career, Plato chose roles that could be considered [[erotic]], [[softcore pornography]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/movies/movie/172923/Different-Strokes-The-Story-of-Jack-Jill-and-Jill/overview |title=Different Strokes: The Story of Jack &amp; Jill... and Jill (1998) |work=[[The New York Times]] |access-date=2014-02-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; She appeared nude in [[Prime Suspect (1989 film)|''Prime Suspect'']] (1989) and ''Compelling Evidence'' (1995), and in the softcore erotic drama ''[[Different Strokes (film)|Different Strokes: The Story of Jack and Jill...and Jill]]'' (1998), whose title was changed after filming in order to tie it to Plato's past. Following her appearance in the film, in the same year, Plato appeared in a cover story of the lesbian lifestyle magazine ''[[Girlfriends (magazine)|Girlfriends]]''. 

Her last works include appearing as herself ''[[Desperation Boulevard]]'' (1998), of which it seemingly was based on Plato's life, appearing as Emma Jones in ''Silent Scream'' (1999), and appearing as an attorney in ''Pacino Is Missing'' (2002), which was released after her death.

== Personal life ==
In 1995, during an appearance on ''The Marilyn Kagen Show'' along with co-star Todd Bridges, she spoke more of how she was raised, commenting on her mother and how she had not learned &quot;reality and life skills&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt; Plato stated: &quot;My mother made sure that I was normal. The only thing that she did, the mistake she made, was that she kept me in a plastic bubble, So, I didn't learn about reality and life skills.&quot; Marilyn Kagen, the host of the show, told Plato that she may have been used for a free meal ticket, which Plato denied, explaining that her mother's ways were so that she would not become a primadonna.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt;

During her years on ''Diff'rent Strokes'', Plato struggled with drug and alcohol problems. She admitted to drinking alcohol, using [[cannabis (drug)|cannabis]] and [[cocaine]], and suffered an overdose of [[Diazepam]] when she was 14.&lt;ref name=&quot;LittleGirlLost2&quot; /&gt;

In December 1983, Plato moved in with her boyfriend, rock guitarist Lanny Lambert. The couple married on April 24, 1984, and their only child, Tyler Edward Lambert, was born on July 2, 1984. When it was revealed that she was pregnant, she was written off ''Diff'rent Strokes''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.moms.com/20-acting-moms-who-were-written-out-due-to-their-pregnancies/|title=20 Actor Mamas Who Were Written Out Due To Their Pregnancies|date=2018-09-22|website=Moms|language=en-US|access-date=2020-01-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her co-star [[Conrad Bain]] had revealed that she was happy about her baby, and that she would no longer be alone.&lt;ref name=&quot;LittleGirlLost2&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt; Bain stated in an interview with ''[[People (magazine)|People]]'': &quot;She deliberately got pregnant while doing the series, when I spoke to her about it, she was enthusiastic about having done that. ... When I get the baby, I will never be alone again.&quot;

Plato separated from Lambert in January 1988, the same week her mother died of [[scleroderma]]. In desperation over these traumatic events, she signed over [[power of attorney]] to an accountant who disappeared with the majority of her money, leaving her with no more than $150,000. She claimed the accountant was never found nor prosecuted, despite an exhaustive search, and that he had also stolen more than $11 million of other people's money.&lt;ref name=&quot;HowardSternShow&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.sitcomsonline.com/sounds/dana_plato_05-07-99.ra|title=Dana Plato's final interview with Howard Stern|date=May 7, 1999|website=sitcomsonline.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; During her March 1990 divorce, Plato lost custody of her son to Lambert and was given visitation rights.&lt;ref name=&quot;LittleGirlLost2&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;abcnews&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://abcnews.go.com/Entertainment/dana-platos-son-tyler-lambert-commits-suicide-mom/story?id=10629167|title=Growing Pains: The Trials and Tribulations of 1980s TV Child Stars|last1=Fisher|first1=Luchina|date=May 13, 2010|work=ABC News|accessdate=2015-08-23|last2=Marikar|first2=Sheila}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010, her son, Tyler, died of a self-inflicted [[gunshot wound]] at the age of 25.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://people.com/celebrity/son-of-the-late-dana-plato-commits-suicide/|title=Son of the Late Dana Plato Commits Suicide|website=PEOPLE.com|language=en|access-date=2020-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; It had been reported that he had been using drugs around the time of his death.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

=== Legal issues ===
On February 28, 1991, she entered a video store, produced a pellet gun, and demanded the money in the cash register. The clerk called 9-1-1 and said &quot;I've just been robbed by the girl who played Kimberly on ''Diff'rent Strokes''.&quot; Approximately 15 minutes after the robbery, Plato returned to the scene and was immediately arrested. The robbery netted Plato $164.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Sporkin|first=Elizabeth|date=March 24, 1991|title=Diff'rent Strokes, Fallen Stars|url=http://www.people.com/people/archive/article/0,,20114736,00.html|volume=35|issue=11|magazine=[[People (magazine)|People]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Las Vegas entertainer [[Wayne Newton]] posted her $13,000 bail,&lt;ref name=&quot;reelReviews&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.franksreelreviews.com/shorttakes/plato.htm|title=The Death of Dana Plato|work=Morbidly Hollywood}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Plato was given five years probation. Plato made headlines and became a subject of the national debate surrounding troubled child stars, particularly given the difficulties of her ''Diff'rent Strokes'' co-stars [[Gary Coleman]] and [[Todd Bridges]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://news3lv.com/features/video-vault/video-vault-child-actress-dana-plato-robs-a-vegas-video-store-in-1991|title=VIDEO VAULT: Child actress Dana Plato robs a Vegas video store in 1991|last=Group|first=Sinclair Broadcast|date=2015-10-11|website=KSNV|access-date=2020-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://people.com/archive/cover-story-diffrent-strokes-fallen-stars-vol-35-no-11/|title=Diff'rent Strokes, Fallen Stars|website=PEOPLE.com|language=en|access-date=2020-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In January 1992, she was arrested again, this time for forging a prescription for Diazepam.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1999/05/10/arts/dana-plato-34-star-of-diff-rent-strokes.html|title=Dana Plato, 34, Star of 'Diff'rent Strokes'|last=Press|first=The Associated|date=1999-05-10|work=The New York Times|access-date=2020-01-07|language=en-US|issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt; She served 30 days in jail for violating the terms of her probation and immediately entered a drug rehabilitation program.

=== Later life ===
Plato later moved to Las Vegas, where she struggled with poverty and unemployment. At one point she worked at a dry-cleaning store, where customers reported being impressed by her lack of airs.&lt;ref name=&quot;LittleGirlLost2&quot; /&gt; She became engaged to Fred Potts, a filmmaker, but the romance ended.&lt;ref name=&quot;LittleGirlLost2&quot; /&gt; Before her death, she was engaged to her manager Robert Menchaca, with whom she lived in a motor home in [[Navarre, Florida]].&lt;ref name=&quot;reelReviews&quot; /&gt; 

On May 7, 1999, the day before she died, Plato appeared on ''[[The Howard Stern Show]]''. She spoke about her life, discussing her financial problems and past run-ins with the law. She admitted to being a recovering alcoholic and drug addict, but claimed she had been sober for more than 10 years by that point, and was not using any drugs, with the exception of prescribed painkillers due to the recent extraction of her wisdom teeth.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://variety.com/1999/tv/news/diff-rent-strokes-actress-dies-of-apparent-overdose-1117500206/|title=‘Diff’rent Strokes’ actress dies of apparent overdose|date=10 May 1999|website=variety.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many callers insulted her and questioned her sobriety, which provoked a defiant Plato who offered to take a drug test on the air. Some callers, as well as host [[Howard Stern]], came to Plato's defense.&lt;ref name=&quot;HowardSternShow&quot; /&gt; Although she allowed a hair to be cut for the test, Stern later claimed she asked for it back after the interview.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://nypost.com/1999/05/11/stern-dana-tried-desperately-to-dodge-drug-test/|title=STERN: DANA TRIED DESPERATELY TO DODGE DRUG TEST|last=Buffa|first=Denise|date=11 May 1999|website=nypost.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Death ==
On May 8, 1999, Plato and Menchaca were returning to California and stopped at Menchaca's mother's home in [[Moore, Oklahoma]] for a Mother's Day visit.&lt;ref name=&quot;LittleGirlLost2&quot;/&gt; Later on in the visit, Plato revealed that she felt unwell, and took a few doses of painkiller [[Hydrocodone/paracetamol|Lortab]], along with the muscle-relaxant [[Carisoprodol|Soma]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/archive/local/1999/05/10/actress-dana-plato-dies-at-34/c4fa4f99-c90e-455b-bd68-aefd2d79f8b8/?noredirect=on|title=Actress Dana Plato Dies at 34|work=Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt; and went to lie down inside her Winnebago motor home with Menchaca, which was parked outside the house.&lt;ref name=&quot;LittleGirlLost2&quot; /&gt; Upon waking up, Menchaca and their family discovered that Plato had passed away, which they later found out was due to an accidental overdose, which was later ruled a suicide based on Plato's long history of drug abuse.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=O'Neill |first=Anne-Marie |date=June 7, 1999 |title=Seeking Serenity |url=http://www.people.com/people/archive/article/0,,20128431,00.html |volume=51 |issue=20 |magazine=[[People (magazine)|People]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.chicagotribune.com/news/ct-xpm-1999-05-21-9905220016-story.html |title=DEATH OF `DIFF'RENT STROKES' ACTRESS RULED A SUICIDE |website=chicagotribune.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Her body was cremated, and her ashes were scattered in the Pacific Ocean.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Where Are They Buried?: How Did They Die? Fitting Ends and Final Resting Places of the Famous, Infamous, and Noteworthy |last=Benoit |first=Tod |publisher=Black Dog Publishing |year=2009 |isbn=1-57912-822-X |page=211}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

== Legacy ==
Plato's sudden death induced nationwide shock, in which her personal life, though at first controversial, is remembered as a tragedy.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.eonline.com/news/1090311/the-most-heartbreaking-teen-star-tragedies|title=The Most Heartbreaking Teen Star Tragedies|date= 2019-11-07|website=E! Online|language=en-US|accessdate=2020-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2000, [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox]] broadcast a television [[Documentary film|documentary]] based on Plato, titled ''After Diff'rent Strokes: When the Laughter Stopped''. The film was focused on her life and work after the show, including her death. It featured actors who at the time were not famed, as well as Todd Bridges, who made a cameo appearance.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.longislandpress.com/|title=Long Island News From the Long Island Press|website=Long Island News from the Long Island Press|language=en-US|access-date=2020-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006, NBC aired the television film ''Behind the Camera: The Unauthorized Story of Diff'rent Strokes'', which was based on the lives of the child stars who’d worked on the show. In the end of the film, where Bridges and Gary Coleman appeared, they stand near Plato's grave.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.recordonline.com/article/20060904/LIFE/609040312|title=Refried nostalgia, overcooked comedy|last=McDonough|first=Kevin|website=recordonline.com|language=en|access-date=2020-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On what would have been Plato's 55th birthday, Todd Bridges commented on [[Twitter]] about their friendship, leaving a tribute to Plato.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://people.com/tv/todd-bridges-remembers-diffrent-strokes-dana-plato-55th-birthday/|title=Diff'rent Strokes' Todd Bridges Remembers Dana Plato on What Would've Been Her 55th Birthday: 'You're Free My friend'|website=PEOPLE.com|language=en|access-date=2020-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.yahoo.com/entertainment/todd-bridges-remembers-diffrent-strokes-002043315.html|title=Todd Bridges Remembers Diff'rent Strokes Costar Dana Plato on What Would Have Been Her 55th Birthday|website=www.yahoo.com|language=en-US|access-date=2020-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bridges stated: &quot;You were the one person i could always talk to. You were one of my best friends. I will never forget you and love you forever. HAPPY BIRTHDAY Dana Plato R.I.P  you are free my friend.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://mobile.twitter.com/ToddBridges/status/1192444714420588544|title=Twitter|website=mobile.twitter.com|access-date=2020-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Filmography ==

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+Film
|-
! Year !! Title !! Role !! Notes
|-
| 1977 || ''[[Exorcist II: The Heretic]]'' || Sandra Phalor || Uncredited
|-
| 1977 || ''[[Return to Boggy Creek]]'' || Evie Joe ||
|-
| 1978 || ''[[California Suite (film)|California Suite]]'' || Jenny Warren ||
|-
| 1989 || ''[[Prime Suspect (1989 film)|Prime Suspect]]'' || Diana Masters ||
|-
| 1992 || ''Bikini Beach Race'' || J.D. ||
|-
| 1992 || ''The Sounds of Silence'' || Deborah Nichols ||
|-
| 1995 || ''Compelling Evidence'' || Dana Fields ||
|-
| 1995 || ''Lethal Cowboy'' || Elizabeth ||
|-
| 1995 || ''Millenium Day'' || ||
|-
| 1997 || ''Tiger'' || Andrea Baker ||
|-
| 1997 || ''Blade Boxer'' || Rita || [[Direct-to-video]]
|-
| 1998 || ''[[Different Strokes (film)|Different Strokes: The Story of Jack and Jill...and Jill]]'' || Jill Martin ||
|-
| 1998 || ''[[Desperation Boulevard]]'' || Dana Plato ||
|-
| 1999 || ''Silent Scream'' || Emma Jones ||
|-
| 2002 || ''Pacino Is Missing'' || Prosecuting Attorney || Final film role; posthumous release
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+Television
|-
! Year !! Title !! Role !! Notes
|-
| 1975 || ''[[The Six Million Dollar Man]]'' || Girl || Episode: &quot;[[List of The Six Million Dollar Man episodes#Season 2 (1974–1975)|The Bionic Woman]]&quot;
|-
| 1975 || ''Beyond the Bermuda Triangle'' || Wendy || Television film
|-
| 1976 || ''[[Family (1976 TV series)|Family]]'' || Mary Beth Sanders || Episode: &quot;[[List of Family episodes|Home Movie]]&quot;
|-
| 1978 || ''[[What Really Happened to the Class of '65?]]'' || || Episode: &quot;The Most Likely to Succeed&quot;
|-
|1978
|''[[The Gong Show]]''
|Herself
|[[Game show]]
|-
| 1978–86 || ''[[Diff'rent Strokes]]'' ||[[Kimberly Drummond]]|| 140 episodes &lt;br /&gt; Main cast (Seasons 1–6) Recurring role (Seasons 7–8)
|-
| 1979 || ''[[Hello, Larry]]'' || Kimberly Drummond || 3 episodes &lt;br /&gt; Guest star (Season 1–2)
|-
| 1979 || ''[[The Facts of Life (TV series)|The Facts of Life]]'' || Kimberly Drummond || Episode: &quot;Rough Housing&quot;
|-
| 1979–80 || ''[[CHiPs]]'' || Dana Plato || 2 episodes &lt;br /&gt; Guest star (Season 3)
|-
| 1980 || ''Family'' || Debbie || Episode: &quot;[[List of Family episodes|Letting Go]]&quot;
|-
| 1980 || ''[[ABC Afterschool Special]]s'' || Daisy Dallenger || Episode: &quot;[[ABC Afterschool Special#Season Nine (1980–81)|Schoolboy Father]]&quot;
|-
| 1981 || ''A Step in Time'' || || Television film
|-
| 1982 || ''Walt Disney World's 10th Anniversary'' || Daughter || Television special
|-
| 1983 || ''[[High School U.S.A.]]'' || Cara Ames || Television film
|-
| 1984 || ''[[The Love Boat]]'' || Patty Springer || Episode: &quot;[[List of The Love Boat episodes|Paying the Piper/Baby Sister/Help Wanted]]&quot;
|-
| 1985 || ''[[Growing Pains]]'' || Lisa || Episode: &quot;[[List of Growing Pains episodes#Season 1: 1985–1986|Mike's Madonna Story]]&quot;
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+Video Games
|-
! Year
! Title
! Role
! Notes
|-
| 1992
| ''[[Night Trap]]''
| Kelly Medd
| The game became a talking point two years later, in the [[United States Senate|Senate]] video game violence hearings of 1994.
|}

== Awards and nominations ==
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! Year
! Award
! Category
! Work
! Result
!Ref.
|-
| 1981
| [[Young Artist Awards]]
| Best Young Actress in a Television Special
| ''A Step in Time''
| {{nom}}
|&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110402060410/http://www.youngartistawards.org/pastnoms3.htm|title=3rd Annual Awards|date=2011-04-02|website=web.archive.org|access-date=2020-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 1983
| [[Young Artist Awards]]
| Best Young Actress in a Comedy Series
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; |''[[Diff'rent Strokes]]''
| {{nom}}
|&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110403132035/http://www.youngartistawards.org/pastnoms5.htm|title=5th Annual Awards|date=2011-04-03|website=web.archive.org|access-date=2020-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 2003
| [[TV Land Awards]]
| Quintessential Non-Traditional Family &lt;small&gt;(shared with cast)&lt;/small&gt;
| {{nom}}
|&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.imdb.com/event/ev0001221/2003/1/|title=TV Land Awards (2003)|website=IMDb|access-date=2020-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 2004
| [[TV Land Awards]]
| Quintessential Non-Traditional Family &lt;small&gt;(shared with cast)&lt;/small&gt;
| {{nom}}
|&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.imdb.com/event/ev0001221/2004/1/|title=TV Land Awards (2004)|website=IMDb|access-date=2020-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Portal|Biography}}
* {{IMDb name|0686818}}
* {{tcmdb name|id=153179|name=Dana Plato}}
* {{amg name|57045}}
* [https://www.findagrave.com/memorial/5415 Dana Plato] at [[Find a Grave]]
* [http://www.biography.com/people/dana-plato-248617 Dana Plato] on [[The Biography Channel]] first aired on December 29, 2007

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Plato, Dana Michelle}}
[[Category:1964 births]]
[[Category:1999 deaths]]
[[Category:20th-century American actresses]]
[[Category:American child actresses]]
[[Category:American film actresses]]
[[Category:American television actresses]]
[[Category:Actresses from California]]
[[Category:Actresses from Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:American actresses who committed suicide]]
[[Category:American adoptees]]
[[Category:American people convicted of robbery]]
[[Category:American video game actresses]]
[[Category:Drug-related suicides in Oklahoma]]
[[Category:Female suicides]]
[[Category:Forgers]]
[[Category:People from Maywood, California]]
[[Category:People from the San Fernando Valley]]
[[Category:William Howard Taft Charter High School alumni]]</text>
      <sha1>snudavt3214yx227vxnajg5htr32c02</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
