  <page>
    <title>Dictatorship</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9033</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942702273</id>
      <parentid>942702225</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-26T08:51:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Outriggr</username>
        <id>11761454</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WP:SHORTDES|short description]]: &quot;authoritarian form of government&quot;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|authoritarian form of government}}
[[File:Hitlermusso2 edit.jpg|thumb|440x440px|From left to right: [[Benito Mussolini]] and [[Adolf Hitler]].  Hitler's policies and orders both directly and indirectly resulted in the deaths of about [[World War II casualties|50 million people in Europe]].&lt;ref&gt;Del Testa, David W; Lemoine, Florence; Strickland, John (2003). ''Government Leaders, Military Rulers, and Political Activists.'' Greenwood Publishing Group. p. 83. {{ISBN|978-1-57356-153-2}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Together with Mussolini's [[Italian Fascism]] and the [[History of the Soviet Union (1927-1953)|Soviet regime of Joseph Stalin]], they have marked the inception of the  &quot;[[Totalitarianism|totalitarian regime]]s&quot;.]]{{Basic forms of government}} A '''dictatorship''' is an [[Authoritarianism|authoritarian]] form of government, characterized by a single leader or group of leaders and little or no toleration for political pluralism or independent programs or media.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Dictators and dictatorships : understanding authoritarian regimes and their leaders|last=Ezrow|first=Natasha|publisher=Continuum|others=Frantz, Erica|year=2011|isbn=978-1-4411-1602-4|location=New York|pages=|oclc=705538250}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to other definitions, [[Democracy|democracies]] are regimes in which &quot;those who govern are selected through contested elections&quot;; therefore dictatorships are &quot;not democracies&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; With the advent of the 19th and 20th centuries, dictatorships and constitutional democracies emerged as the world's two major [[forms of government]], gradually eliminating [[Monarchy|monarchies]], one of the traditional widespread forms of government of the time. Typically, in a dictatorial regime, the leader of the country is identified with the title of [[dictator]], although their formal title may more closely resemble something similar to &quot;leader&quot;. A common aspect that characterized dictatorship is taking  advantage of their strong personality, usually by suppressing freedom of thought and speech of the masses, in order to maintain complete political and social supremacy and stability. Dictatorships and [[Totalitarianism|totalitarian]] societies generally employ political [[propaganda]] to decrease the influence of proponents of alternative governing systems.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Tucker|first=Robert C.|date=1965|title=The Dictator and Totalitarianism.|journal=World Politics|volume= 17| issue =  4|pages= 555–83|oclc=4907282504|doi=10.2307/2009322|jstor=2009322}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Cassinelli|first=C. W.|date=1960|title=Totalitarianism, Ideology, and Propaganda.|journal=The Journal of Politics|volume= 22| issue =  1|pages= 68–95|oclc=6822391923|doi=10.2307/2126589|jstor=2126589}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Etymology ==
{{Main|Roman dictator}}
The word &quot;dictator&quot; comes from the classical [[Latin]] language word ''dictātor'', [[agent noun]] from ''dictare (dictāt-'', past participial stem of ''dictāre'' [http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/52299#eid6726598 dictate ''v.''] + ''-or'' [http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/132131#eid33232093 -or ''suffix''].)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/52304?p=emailAOE6bjQCOi1ZQ&amp;d=52304|title=Oxford English Dictionary, (the definitive record of the English language)|last=|first=|date=|website=|archive-url=|archive-date=|url-status=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Latin use, a ''dictator'' was a [[Magistratus|judge]] in the [[Roman Republic]] temporarily invested with absolute power.

== Types of dictatorships ==
A dictatorship has been largely defined as a form of government in which the absolute power is concentrated in the hands of a leader (commonly identified as a [[dictator]]), a &quot;small clique&quot;, or a &quot;government organization&quot;, and it aims to abolish political pluralism and civilian mobilization.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Olson|first=Mancur|date=1993|title=Dictatorship, Democracy, and Development.|journal=The American Political Science Review|volume= 87| issue =  3|pages= 567–76|oclc=5104816959|doi=10.2307/2938736|jstor=2938736}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, [[democracy]], which is generally compared to the concept of dictatorship, is defined as a form of government where the supremacy belongs to the population and rulers are elected through contested [[election]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Kurki|first=Milja|date=2010|title=Democracy and Conceptual Contestability: Reconsidering Conceptions of Democracy in Democracy Promotion.|journal=International Studies Review|language=en|volume=12. no. 3|issue=3|pages=362–86|via=|jstor=40931113}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Bermeo|first=Nancy|date=1992|title=Democracy and the Lessons of Dictatorship.|jstor=422133|journal=Comparative Politics|volume= 24| issue =  3|pages= 273–91|doi=10.2307/422133}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A new form of government commonly linked to the concept of dictatorship is known as [[totalitarianism]]. The advent of totalitarianism marked the beginning of a new political era in the 20th century. This form of government is characterized by the presence of a single political party and more specifically, by a powerful leader (a real [[role model]]) who imposes his personal and political prominence. The two fundamental aspects that contribute to the maintenance of the power are: a steadfast collaboration between the government and the police force, and a highly developed ideology. Here, the government has &quot;total control of mass communications and social and economic organizations&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=McLaughlin|first=Neil|date=2010|title=Review: Totalitarianism, Social Science, and the Margins.|jstor=canajsocicahican.35.3.463|journal=The Canadian Journal of Sociology|volume= 35| issue =  3|pages= 463–69|doi=10.29173/cjs8876}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Hannah Arendt]], totalitarianism is a new and extreme form of dictatorship composed of &quot;atomized, isolated individuals&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;:02&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://public.eblib.com/choice/publicfullrecord.aspx?p=661026|title=Dictators and dictatorships: understanding authoritarian regimes and their leaders|last=Ezrow|first=Natasha M|last2=Frantz|first2=Erica|date=2011|publisher=Continuum|isbn=978-1-4411-1602-4|location=New York|pages=|language=English}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, she affirmed that ideology plays a leading role in defining how the entire society should be organized. According to the political scientist [[Juan Linz]], the distinction between an authoritarian regime and a totalitarian one is that while an authoritarian regime seeks to suffocate politics and political mobilization, totalitarianism seeks to control politics and political mobilization.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Totalitarian and authoritarian regimes|last=Linz|first=Juan J|date=2009|publisher=Rienner|isbn=978-1-55587-866-5|location=Boulder, CO|language=English|oclc = 985592359}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, one of the most recent classification of dictatorships does not identify [[Totalitarianism]] as a form of dictatorship. In [[Barbara Geddes (academic)|Barbara Geddes]]'s study, she focused in how elite-leader and elite-mass relations influence [[Authoritarianism|authoritarian]] politics. Geddes typology identifies the key institutions that structure elite politics in dictatorships (i.e. parties and militaries). The study is based on, and directly related to, factors like: the simplicity of the categorizations, cross-national applicability, the emphasis on elites and leaders, and the incorporation of institutions (parties and militaries) as central to shaping politics. According to Barbara Geddes, a dictatorial government may be classified in five typologies: Military Dictatorships, Single-party Dictatorships, Personalist Dictatorships, [[Monarchy|Monarchies]], Hybrid Dictatorships.&lt;ref name=&quot;:02&quot; /&gt;

=== Military dictatorships ===
{{main|Military dictatorship}}
Military dictatorships are regimes in which a group of officers holds power, determines who will lead the country, and exercises influence over policy. High-level [[elite]]s and a [[Leadership|leader]] are the members of the military dictatorship. Military dictatorships are characterized by rule by a professionalized military as an institution. In military regimes, elites are referred to as junta members; they are typically senior officers (and often other high-level officers) in the military.&lt;ref name=&quot;:02&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Friedrich|first=Carl|date=1950|title=Military Government and Dictatorship.|journal=The Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science|volume= 267|pages= 1–7|oclc=5723774494|doi=10.1177/000271625026700102}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Single-party dictatorships ===
{{Main|One-party state}}
Single-party dictatorships are regimes in which one party dominates politics. In single-party dictatorships, a single party has access to political posts and control over policy. In single-party dictatorships, party elites are typically members of the ruling body of the party, sometimes called the [[central committee]], [[politburo]], or [[Secretariat (administrative office)|secretariat]]. These groups of individuals controls the selection of party officials and &quot;organizes the distribution of benefits to supporters and mobilizes citizens to vote and show support for party leaders&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;:02&quot;/&gt;

=== Personalist dictatorships ===
Personalist dictatorships are regimes in which all power lies in the hands of a single individual. Personalist dictatorships differ from other forms of dictatorships in their access to key political positions, other fruits of office, and depend much more on the discretion of the personalist dictator. Personalist dictators may be members of the military or leaders of a political party. Yet, neither the military nor the party exercises power independent from the dictator. In personalist dictatorships, the elite corps is usually made up of close friends or family members of the dictator. These individuals are all typically handpicked to serve their posts by the dictator.&lt;ref name=&quot;:02&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Peceny|first=Mark|date=2003|title=Peaceful Parties and Puzzling Personalists.|journal=The American Political Science Review|volume= 97| issue =  2|pages= 339–42|oclc=208155326|doi=10.1017/s0003055403000716}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to a 2019 study, personalist dictatorships are more repressive than other forms of dictatorship.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Frantz|first=Erica|last2=Kendall-Taylor|first2=Andrea|last3=Wright|first3=Joseph|last4=Xu|first4=Xu|date=2019-08-27|title=Personalization of Power and Repression in Dictatorships|url=https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1086/706049|journal=The Journal of Politics|pages=000–000|doi=10.1086/706049|issn=0022-3816}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Monarchies ===
{{main|Monarchy}}
[[File:Salman of Saudi Arabia (2017-10-05) 2.jpg|thumb|King [[Salman of Saudi Arabia]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.dawn.com/news/1159990 Call them ‘Dictators’, not ‘Kings’]&quot;. ''[[Dawn (newspaper)|Dawn]]''. 28 January 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Monarchic dictatorships are regimes in which &quot;a person of royal descent has inherited the position of head of state in accordance with accepted practice or constitution&quot;. Regimes are not considered dictatorships if the monarch's role is largely ceremonial, but [[absolute monarchy|absolute monarchies]], such as [[Saudi Arabia]], can be considered [[hereditary dictatorship]]s. Real political power must be exercised by the monarch for regimes to be classified as such. Elites in monarchies are typically members of the [[royal family]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:02&quot; /&gt;

=== Hybrid dictatorships ===
Hybrid dictatorships are regimes that blend qualities of personalist, single-party, and military dictatorships. When regimes share characteristics of all three forms of dictatorships, they are referred to as triple threats. The most common forms of hybrid dictatorships are personalist/single-party hybrids and personalist/military hybrids.&lt;ref name=&quot;:02&quot; /&gt;

== Measuring dictatorships ==
[[File:Economist Intelligence Unit Democracy index.svg|thumb|259x259px|[[Democracy Index]] by the [[Economist Intelligence Unit]], 2016.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.yabiladi.com/img/content/EIU-Democracy-Index-2015.pdf|title=Democracy Index 2015|last=|first=|date=21 January 2016|website=Economist Intelligence Unit|publisher=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Blue represents more democratic countries, while yellow and red are considered as [[hybrid regime]] and [[authoritarian]], respectively. Most dictatorships are represented as darker shades of red.]]
One of the tasks in [[political science]] is to measure and classify regimes as either dictatorships or democracies. [[Freedom House]], [[Polity IV]] and [[Democracy-Dictatorship Index]] are three of the most used [[data series]] by political scientists.&lt;ref name=&quot;ClarkGolder2014&quot;&gt;{{cite book|chapter-url=http://college.cqpress.com/sites/principlescp/Home/chapter5.aspx|title=Principles of Comparative Politics|author1=William Roberts Clark|author2=Matt Golder|author3=Sona N Golder|date=23 March 2012|publisher=CQ Press|isbn=978-1-60871-679-1|chapter=5. Democracy and Dictatorship: Conceptualization and Measurement}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Generally, two research approaches exist: the minimalist approach, which focuses on whether a country has continued elections that are competitive, and the substantive approach, which expands the concept of democracy to include human rights, [[freedom of the press]], and the [[rule of law]]. The Democracy-Dictatorship Index is seen as an example of the minimalist approach, whereas the [[Polity data series]], is more substantive.&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoJF-3&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://college.cqpress.com/sites/principlescp/Home/chapter5.aspx |title=Democracy and Dictatorship: Conceptualization and Measurement |website=cqpress.com|date=2017-08-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MøllerSkaaning2012&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first=Jørgen |last=Møller |first2=Svend-Erik |last2=Skaaning |date=2012 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RtWoAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA78 |title=Requisites of Democracy: Conceptualization, Measurement, and Explanation |publisher=Routledge |pages=78– |isbn=978-1-136-66584-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ClarkGolder2009&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first=William Roberts |last=Clark |first2=Matt |last2=Golder |first3=Sona Nadenichek |last3=Golder |date=2009 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RmPuAAAAMAAJ |title=Principles of comparative politics |publisher=CQ Press. |isbn=978-0-87289-289-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoJF-4&quot;&gt;[http://jcr.sagepub.com/content/early/2012/10/12/0022002712459707?patientinform-links=yes&amp;legid=spjcr;0022002712459707v1 Divergent Incentives for Dictators: Domestic Institutions and (International Promises Not to) Torture] [http://faculty.ucmerced.edu/cconrad2/Academic/Research_files/JCRAppendix25March2011.pdf Appendix] &quot;Unlike substantive measures of democracy (e.g., Polity IV and Freedom House), the binary conceptualization of democracy most recently described by Cheibub, Gandhi and Vree-land (2010) focuses on one institution—elections—to distinguish between dictatorships and democracies. Using a minimalist measure of democracy rather than a substantive one better allows for the isolation of causal mechanisms (Cheibub, Gandhi and Vreeland, 2010, 73) linking regime type to human rights outcomes.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
Between the two world wars, four types of dictatorships have been described: Constitutional, Communist (nominally championing the &quot;[[dictatorship of the proletariat]]&quot;), Counterrevolutionary and [[fascism|Fascist]]. Since [[World War II]], a broader range of dictatorships has been recognized, including [[Third World]] dictatorships, theocratic or religious dictatorships and dynastic or family-based dictatorships.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coppa2006&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gTv99LBYSL4C|title=Encyclopedia of Modern Dictators: From Napoleon to the Present|author=Frank J. Coppa|date=1 January 2006|publisher=Peter Lang|isbn=978-0-8204-5010-0|page=xiv|quote=In the period between the two world wars, four types of dictatorships were described by a number of smart people: constitutional, the communist (nominally championing the &quot;dictatorship of the proletariat&quot;), the counterrevolutionary, and the fascist. Many have rightfully questioned the distinctions between these prototypes. In fact, since World War II, we have recognized that the range of dictatorships is much broader than earlier posited and it includes so-called Third World dictatorships in Africa, Asia, Latin America, and the Middle East and religious dictatorships....They are also family dictatorships ....|accessdate=25 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Dictators in the Roman Republic ===
During the [[Roman Republic|Republican phase]] of [[Ancient Rome]], a [[Roman dictator]] was the special magistrate who held well defined powers, normally for six months at a time, usually in combination with a [[Roman consul|consulship]]. Roman dictators were allocated absolute power during times of emergency. In execution, their power was originally neither arbitrary nor unaccountable, being subject to law and requiring retrospective justification. There were no such dictatorships after the beginning of the 2nd century BC and later dictators such as [[Sulla]] and the [[Roman Emperor]]s exercised power much more personally and arbitrarily. As the Roman Emperor was a [[king]] in all but name, a concept that remained anathema to traditional Roman society, the institution was not carried forward into the [[Roman Empire]].

=== 19th-century Latin American caudillos ===
{{main|Caudillo}}
[[File:Santaanna1.JPG|170px|thumb|right|[[Antonio López de Santa Anna]] wearing [[Mexico|Mexican]] military uniform]]
After the collapse of Spanish colonial rule, various dictators came to power in many liberated countries. Often leading a private army, these ''[[caudillo]]s'' or self-appointed political-military leaders, attacked weak national [[government]]s once they controlled a region's political and economic powers, with examples such as [[Antonio López de Santa Anna]] in Mexico and [[Juan Manuel de Rosas]] in Argentina. Such dictators have been also referred to as &quot;[[personalismo]]s&quot;.

The wave of [[military dictatorship]]s in South America in the second half of the twentieth century left a particular mark on [[Latin American culture]]. In [[Latin American literature]], the [[dictator novel]] challenging dictatorship and ''[[caudillo|caudillismo]]'' is a significant genre. There are also many [[films depicting Latin American military dictatorships]].

=== Communism and Fascism in 20th-century dictatorships ===
In the first half of the 20th century, [[Communism|Communist]] and [[Fascism|Fascist]] dictatorships appeared in a variety of scientifically and technologically advanced countries, which are distinct from dictatorships in Latin America and post-colonial dictatorships in Africa and Asia. Leading examples of modern totalitarian dictatorship include:
* [[Adolf Hitler]]'s [[Nazi Germany]], [[Hideki Tojo]]'s [[Empire of Japan|Japan]], [[Benito Mussolini]]'s [[Kingdom of Italy under Fascism (1922-1943)|Italy]], [[Francisco Franco]]'s [[Francoist Spain|Spain]], [[Ion Antonescu]]'s [[Romania]] and other Fascist dictatorships that appeared in South Europe, Southern Africa and other countries;
* [[Joseph Stalin|Stalin]]'s [[Soviet Union]], [[Mao Zedong]] and [[Xi Jinping]]'s [[People's Republic of China]], [[Carrie Lam]]'s [[Hong Kong]], [[Kim dynasty (North Korea)|Kim dynasty]]'s North Korea, [[Ho Chi Minh]]'s [[Vietnam]], [[Nicolae Ceauşescu]]'s [[Romania]] and other Communist dictatorships that appeared after [[World War II]] in Central Europe, Eastern Europe, East Asia and other countries.

===Dictatorships in Africa and Asia after World War II===
[[File:Prins Bernhard in Zaire (voorheen Belgisch Congo), Bernhard en Mobutu, Bestanddeelnr 926-6037.jpg|thumb|170px|[[Mobutu Sese Seko]], Zaire's longtime dictator]]
After World War II, dictators established themselves in the several new states of Africa and Asia, often at the expense or failure of the constitutions inherited from the colonial powers. These constitutions often failed to work without a strong middle class or work against the preexisting autocratic rule. Some elected presidents and prime ministers captured power by suppressing the opposition and installing one-party rule and others established military dictatorships through their armies. Whatever their form, these dictatorships had an adverse impact on economic growth and the quality of political institutions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Papaioannou|first=Kostadis|author2=vanZanden, Jan Luiten|date=2015|title=The Dictator Effect: How long years in office affect economic development|journal=Journal of Institutional Economics|volume=11|issue=1|pages=111–39|doi=10.1017/S1744137414000356|pmid=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dictators who stayed in office for a long period of time found it increasingly difficult to carry out sound economic policies.

The often-cited exploitative dictatorship is the regime of [[Mobutu Sese Seko]], who ruled [[Zaire]] from 1965 to 1997, embezzling over $5&amp;nbsp;billion from his country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://edition.cnn.com/WORLD/9709/07/mobutu.wrap/|title=Mobutu dies in exile in Morocco|author=|date=7 September 1997|work=CNN}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pakistan is another country to have been governed by 3 military dictators for almost 32 years in 7 decades of its existence. Starting with [[Ayub Khan (President of Pakistan)|General Muhammad Ayub Khan]] who ruled from 1958-1969. Next was General [[Muhammad Zia-ul-Haq|Zia-ul-Haq]] who usurped power in 1977 and held on to power the longest until he died in an air crash in 1988. Ten years after Zia, [[Pervez Musharraf|General Pervez Musharraf]] got control after defeat against India in the [[Kargil War|Kargil war]]. He remained in power for 9 years until 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.dandc.eu/en/article/brief-history-military-rule-pakistan|title=A brief history of military rule in Pakistan|website=D+C|language=en|access-date=2019-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Baby Doc.jpg|thumb|210px|[[Jean-Claude Duvalier|Jean-Claude &quot;Baby Doc&quot; Duvalier]] succeeded his father [[François Duvalier|François &quot;Papa Doc&quot; Duvalier]] as the ruler of Haiti after his death in 1971.]]

[[File:Gurbanguly Berdimuhamedow (2017-10-02) 02.jpg|thumb|210px|[[Gurbanguly Berdimuhamedow]], current president of [[Turkmenistan]]]]

=== Democratization ===
The global dynamics of [[democratization]] has been a central question for political scientists.&lt;ref name=&quot;Huntington2012&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=IMjyTFG04JYC|title=The Third Wave: Democratization in the Late 20th Century|author=Samuel P. Huntington|date=6 September 2012|publisher=University of Oklahoma Press|isbn=978-0-8061-8604-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown2011&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=F9LYMp0RyD4C|title=The Dynamics of Democratization: Dictatorship, Development, and Diffusion|author=Nathan J. Brown|date=2011|publisher=JHU Press|isbn=978-1-4214-0088-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Third Wave Democracy]] was said to turn some dictatorships into democracies&lt;ref name=&quot;Huntington2012&quot;/&gt; (see also the contrast between the two figures of the [[Democracy-Dictatorship Index]] in 1988 and 2008).

One of the rationales that the Bush Administration employed periodically during the run-up to the [[2003 invasion of Iraq]] is that deposing Saddam Hussein and [[American democracy promotion in the Middle East and North Africa|installing a democratic government]] in Iraq would promote [[Democracy in the Middle East|democracy in other Middle Eastern countries]].&lt;ref&gt;Wright, Steven. ''The United States and Persian Gulf Security: The Foundations of the War on Terror'', Ithaca Press, 2007 {{ISBN|978-0-86372-321-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, according to ''The Huffington Post'', &quot;The 45 nations and territories with little or no democratic rule represent more than half of the roughly 80 countries now hosting U.S. bases. ...  Research by political scientist [[Kent E. Calder|Kent Calder]] confirms what's come to be known as the &quot;dictatorship hypothesis&quot;: The United States tends to support dictators [and other undemocratic regimes] in nations where it enjoys basing facilities.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=How U.S. Military Bases Back Dictators, Autocrats, And Military Regimes |url=https://www.huffingtonpost.com/entry/how-us-military-bases-back-dictators-autocrats-and-military-regimes_us_591b229ae4b05dd15f0ba8e6?guccounter=1 |work=The Huffington Post]|date=16 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Theories of dictatorship ==
{{expand section|date=December 2017}}
[[Mancur Olson]] suggests that the emergence of dictatorships can be linked to the concept of &quot;roving bandits&quot;, individuals in an atomic system who move from place to place extracting wealth from individuals. These bandits provide a disincentive for investment and production. Olson states that a community of individuals would be better served if that bandit were to establish himself as a stationary bandit to monopolize theft in the form of taxes. Except from the community, the bandits themselves will be better served, according to Olson, by transforming themselves into &quot;stationary bandits&quot;. By settling down and making themselves the rulers of a territory, they will be able to make more profits through taxes than they used to obtain through plunder. By maintaining order and providing protection to the community, the bandits will create a peaceful environment in which their people can maximize their surplus which means a greater taxable base. Thus a potential dictator will have a greater incentive to provide security to a given community from which he is extracting taxes and conversely, the people from whom he extracts the taxes are more likely to produce because they will be unconcerned with potential theft by other bandits. This is the rationality that bandits use in order to justify their transformation from &quot;roving bandits&quot; into &quot;stationary bandits&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Olson|first=Mancur|date=1993|title=Dictatorship, Democracy, and Development|url=|journal=American Political Science Review|volume=87|issue=3|doi=|pmid=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Div col|colwidth=20em}}
* [[Absolute monarchy]]
* [[Autocracy]]
* [[Benevolent dictatorship]]
* [[Military dictatorship#Civil-military dictatorship|Civil-military dictatorship]]
* [[Constitutional dictatorship]]
* [[Stalinism]]
* [[Maoism]]
* [[Juche]]
* [[Dictatorship of the bourgeoisie]]
* [[Dictatorship of the proletariat]]
* [[Elective dictatorship]]
* [[Family dictatorship]]
* ''[[How Democracies Die]]''
* [[Military dictatorship]]
* [[Generalissimo]]
* [[List of titles used by dictators]]
* [[Maximum Leader (disambiguation)|Maximum Leader]]
* [[Mobutism]]
* [[Nazism]]
* [[Fascism]]
* [[People's democratic dictatorship]]
* [[Right-wing dictatorship]]
* [[Selectorate theory]]
* [[Strongman (politics)|Strongman]]
* [[Supreme leader]]
* [[Theocracy]]
{{Div col end}}

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* [http://docupedia.de/zg/Behrends_dictatorship_v2_en_2017 Behrends, Jan C. ''Dictatorship: Modern Tyranny Between Leviathan and Behemoth''], in ''Docupedia Zeitgeschichte'', 14 March 2017
* Dikötter, Frank. ''How to Be a Dictator: The Cult of Personality in the Twentieth Century'' (2019) scholarly analysis of eight despots: Mussolini, Hitler, Stalin and Mao, as well as Kim Il-sung of North Korea; François Duvalier, or Papa Doc, of Haiti; Nicolae Ceaușescu of Romania; and Mengistu Haile Mariam of Ethiopia. [https://www.wsj.com/articles/how-to-be-a-dictator-review-a-poetics-for-tyrants-11575065830 online review]; also [https://www.amazon.com/How-Be-Dictator-Personality-Twentieth/dp/1635573793/ excerpt]
* {{cite book|title=The Dictator's Learning Curve: Inside the Global Battle for Democracy|author=William J. Dobson|isbn=978-0-307-47755-2|year=2013|publisher=Anchor|author-link=William J. Dobson}}
* Finchelstein, Federico. ''The ideological origins of the dirty war: Fascism, populism, and dictatorship in twentieth century Argentina'' (Oxford UP, 2017).
* Fraenkel, Ernst, and Jens Meierhenrich. ''The dual state: A contribution to the theory of dictatorship.'' (Oxford UP, 2018).
* {{cite book|last=Friedrich|first=Carl J.|author2=Brzezinski, Zbigniew K.|authorlink2=Zbigniew Brzezinski|title=Totalitarian Dictatorship and Autocracy|url=https://archive.org/details/totalitariandict0000frie|url-access=registration|publisher=Praeger|edition= 2nd|year=1965}}
* {{cite book|last1=Bueno de Mesquita|first1=Bruce|authorlink=Bruce Bueno de Mesquita|first2=Alastair|last2=Smith|first3=Randolph M.|last3=Siverson|first4=James D.|last4=Morrow|authorlink4=James D. Morrow|title=The Logic of Political Survival|year=2003|publisher=[[The MIT Press]]|isbn=978-0-262-63315-4|title-link=The Logic of Political Survival}}
* {{cite book|title=The Dictator's Handbook: Why Bad Behavior is Almost Always Good Politics|year=2011|page=272|publisher=Random House|author=[[Bruce Bueno de Mesquita]] and [[Alastair Smith]]|isbn=978-1-61039-044-6|oclc=701015473}}
* Ridenti, Marcelo. &quot;The Debate over Military (or Civilian‐Military?) Dictatorship in Brazil in Historiographical Context.&quot; ''Bulletin of Latin American Research'' 37.1 (2018): 33-42.
* Ringen, Stein. ''The perfect dictatorship: China in the 21st century'' (Hong Kong UP, 2016).
* Ward, Christoper Edward, ed. ''The Stalinist Dictatorship'' (Routledge, 2018).
{{Authoritarian types of rule}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2017}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Dictatorship| ]]
[[Category:Forms of government]]
[[Category:Oligarchy]]
[[Category:Authoritarianism]]</text>
      <sha1>elhgvcp1ux4p22qpni738uyc0x0ki5y</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
