  <page>
    <title>Django Reinhardt</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9039</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943361066</id>
      <parentid>943360258</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T12:57:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Peterdjones</username>
        <id>1250872</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* The Second World War */ Add a para explaining how the situation in Paris pivoted, explaining Django's escape attempt,</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Belgian-born Romani French jazz guitarist and composer}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2018}}
{{Infobox musical artist
| name                = Django Reinhardt
| image               = Django Reinhardt (Gottlieb 07301).jpg
| caption             = Reinhardt in 1946
| image_size          = 300px
| landscape           =
| background          = non_vocal_instrumentalist
| birth_name          = Jean Reinhardt
| birth_date          = {{birth date|df=y|1910|1|23}}
| birth_place         = [[Liberchies]], [[Pont-à-Celles]], Belgium
| death_date          = {{death date and age|df=y|1953|5|16|1910|1|23}}
| death_place         = [[Samois-sur-Seine]], France
| instrument          = Guitar, violin, banjo
| genre               = [[Jazz]], [[gypsy jazz]], [[bebop]], [[Romani music]]
| occupation          = Guitarist, composer
| years_active        = 1928–1953
| associated_acts     = [[Stéphane Grappelli]],&lt;ref name=video&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ANArGmr74u4 |title=Django Reinhardt Jattendrai Swing 1939 live |via=YouTube |date=23 November 2015 |accessdate=30 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Quintette du Hot Club de France]]
}}
'''Jean Reinhardt''' (23 January 1910 – 16 May 1953), known by his stage name '''Django Reinhardt''' ({{IPA-fr|dʒãŋɡo ʁɛjnaʁt|lang}} or {{IPA-fr|dʒɑ̃ɡo ʁenɑʁt|}}), was a Belgian-born [[Romani people|Romani]]-French jazz guitarist and composer. He was the first jazz talent to emerge from Europe and remains the most significant.&lt;ref name=Dregni&gt;{{cite book|first=Michael|last=Dregni|title=Django: The Life and Music of a Gypsy Legend|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2004|isbn=0-19-516752-X|pages=|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/djangolifemusico00dreg}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|cover}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Bar&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Baronian|first=Jean-Baptiste|title=Dictionnaire amoureux de la Belgique|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vRihCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT376|accessdate=30 May 2015|date=8 October 2015|publisher=edi8|isbn=978-2-259-24868-6| page=376}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With violinist [[Stéphane Grappelli]],&lt;ref name=video/&gt; Reinhardt formed the Paris-based [[Quintette du Hot Club de France]] in 1934. The group was among the first to play jazz that featured the guitar as a lead instrument.&lt;ref name=&quot;allmusic&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Jurek|first=Thom|title=The Hot Jazz: Le Hot Club de France, Vols. 1–4|url=http://www.allmusic.com/album/the-hot-jazz-le-hot-club-de-france-vols-1-4-r531911/review |website=AllMusic|accessdate=30 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reinhardt recorded in France with many visiting American musicians, including [[Coleman Hawkins]] and [[Benny Carter]], and briefly toured the United States with [[Duke Ellington]]'s orchestra in 1946. He died suddenly of a stroke at the age of 43.

Reinhardt's most popular compositions have become standards within [[gypsy jazz]], including &quot;[[Minor Swing (song)|Minor Swing]]&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gcE1avXFJb4 |title=Django Reinhardt – Minor Swing – HD *1080p |via=YouTube |date=28 March 2013 |accessdate=30 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Daphne&quot;, &quot;Belleville&quot;, &quot;Djangology&quot;, &quot;Swing '42&quot;, and &quot;[[Nuages (song)|Nuages]]&quot;. Jazz guitarist [[Frank Vignola]] claims that nearly every major popular-music guitarist in the world has been influenced by Reinhardt.&lt;ref name=Vignola&gt;&quot;Mainstay presents Frank Vignola,&quot; ''Record Observer'' (Easton, Maryland), 18 March 2010&lt;/ref&gt; Over the last few decades, annual Django festivals have been held throughout Europe and the U.S., and a biography has been written about his life.&lt;ref name=Dregni/&gt; In February 2017, the [[Berlin International Film Festival]] held the world premiere of the French film [[Django (2017 film)|''Django'']].

==Biography==
===Early life===
Reinhardt was born on 23 January 1910 in [[Liberchies]], [[Pont-à-Celles]], Belgium,&lt;ref name=&quot;Balen 2003&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title = Django Reinhardt: Le Génie vagabond|first = Noël|year = 2003|isbn = 978-2268045610|last = Balen}}&lt;/ref&gt; into a Belgian family&lt;ref name=Bar/&gt; of [[Manouche]] Romani descent.&lt;ref name=&quot;Balen 2003&quot;/&gt; His father was Jean Eugene Weiss, but domiciled in Paris with his wife, he went by Jean-Baptiste Reinhardt, his wife's surname, to avoid French military conscription.&lt;ref name=&quot;allaboutjazz.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allaboutjazz.com/php/article.php?id=25499|title=Django Reinhardt and the Illustrated History of Gypsy Jazz|work=All About Jazz|accessdate=3 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; His mother, Laurence Reinhardt, was a dancer.&lt;ref name=&quot;allaboutjazz.com&quot;/&gt; The birth certificate refers to &quot;Jean Reinhart, son of Jean Baptiste Reinhart, artist, and Laurence Reinhart, housewife, domiciled in Paris&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.djangostation.com/IMG/jpg/NaissanceDjango2.jpg|title=Official birth certificate of Jean Reinhardt|work=Django Station|accessdate=3 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A number of authors have repeated the claim that Reinhardt's nickname, Django, is [[Romani language|Romani]] for &quot;I awake&quot;;&lt;ref name=Dregni/&gt;{{rp|4–5}} however, it may also simply have been a diminutive, or local [[Walloon language|Walloon]] version, of &quot;Jean&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.djangobooks.com/blog/sinti-culture-language-the-origin-of-the-name-django/ Denis Chang: ''Sinti culture, language &amp; the origin of the name Django'']&lt;/ref&gt; Reinhardt spent most of his youth in Romani encampments close to Paris, where he started playing the violin, banjo and guitar. He became adept at stealing chickens, which was viewed as a noble skill by the Romani, because part of their means of survival on the road was to steal from the non-Romani world around them.&lt;ref name=Dregni/&gt;{{rp|5}}&lt;ref name=Delaunay&gt;{{cite book|last=Delaunay|first=Charles|title=Django Reinhardt|publisher=Da Capo Press|year=1961|isbn=0-306-80171-X|page=}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|14}} His father reportedly played music in a family band comprising himself and seven brothers; a surviving photograph shows this band including his father on piano.

Reinhardt was attracted to music at an early age, first playing the violin. At the age of 12 he received a [[Guitjo (six-string)|banjo-guitar]] as a gift. He quickly learned to play, mimicking the fingerings of musicians he watched, who would have included local virtuoso players of the day such as Jean &quot;Poulette&quot; Castro and Auguste &quot;Gusti&quot; Malha, as well as from his uncle Guiligou, who played violin, banjo and guitar.&lt;ref name=Dregni/&gt;{{rp|28}} Reinhardt was able to make a living playing music by the time he was 15, busking in cafés, often with his brother Joseph. At this time, he had not started playing Jazz. 

He received little formal education and acquired the rudiments of literacy only in adult life.&lt;ref name=Delaunay/&gt;{{rp|13}}

===Marriage and injury===
At the age of 17 Reinhardt married Florine &quot;Bella&quot; Mayer, a girl from the same Romani settlement, according to Romani custom (although not an official marriage under French law).&lt;ref name=Fogg/&gt;{{rp|9}} The following year he recorded for the first time.&lt;ref name=Fogg&gt;Fogg, Rod. ''Django Reinhardt: Know the Man, Play the Music'', Hal Leonard Corp. (2005)&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|9}} On these recordings, made in 1928, Reinhardt plays the &quot;banjo&quot; (actually the banjo-guitar) accompanying the accordionists Maurice Alexander, Jean Vaissade and Victor Marceau, and the singer Maurice Chaumel. His name was now drawing international attention, such as from British bandleader [[Jack Hylton]], who came to France just to hear him play.&lt;ref name=Fogg/&gt;{{rp|10}} Hylton offered him a job on the spot, and Reinhardt accepted.&lt;ref name=Fogg/&gt;{{rp|10}}

Before he had a chance to start with the band, however, Reinhardt nearly died. On the night of 2 November 1928, Reinhardt was going to bed in the wagon that he and his wife shared in the caravan. Apparently, he knocked over a candle, which ignited the extremely flammable [[celluloid]] that his wife used to make artificial flowers. The wagon was quickly  engulfed in flames. The couple escaped, but Reinhardt suffered extensive burns over half his body.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flatpick.com/category_s/2218.htm |title=Gypsy Jazz and Django Reinhardt |website=Flatpick.com |date=2 November 1928 |accessdate=30 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; During his 18 month hospitalization, doctors apparently recommended amputation for his badly damaged right leg. Reinhardt refused the surgery and was eventually able to walk with the aid of a cane.&lt;ref name=Fogg/&gt;{{rp|10}} 

More crucial to his music, the third finger (ring finger) and fourth finger (pinky) of Reinhardt’s left hand were badly burned. Doctors believed that he would never play guitar again.&lt;ref name=Delaunay/&gt;{{rp|43–44}}  &lt;ref name=Fogg/&gt;{{rp|10}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Pierre|last=Marty|title= Django ressuscité: contribution à l'étude d'une auto-rééducation fonctionnelle en 1925 |publisher= Copédit |year=2005|isbn= 2906030910 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Reinhardt applied himself intensely to relearning his craft, however, making use of a new guitar bought for him by his brother, [[Joseph Reinhardt]], who was also an accomplished guitarist. While he never regained the use of those two fingers, Reinhardt regained his musical mastery by focusing on his left index and middle fingers, using the two injured fingers only for chord work.&lt;ref name=Delaunay/&gt;{{rp|31–35}}

Within a year of the fire, in 1929, Bella Mayer gave birth to their son, [[Lousson Reinhardt|Henri &quot;Lousson&quot; Reinhardt]]. Soon thereafter, the couple split up. The son eventually took the surname of his mother's new husband. As Lousson Baumgartner, the son himself became an accomplished musician who would go on to record with his biological father. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hotclub.co.uk/gypsyworld/index.php?title=Lousson_Reinhardt|title=Lousson Reinhardt|encyclopedia=Gypsy Jazz Encyclopedia|accessdate=7 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Discovery of jazz===
After parting from his wife and son, Reinhardt traveled throughout France, getting occasional jobs playing music at small clubs. He had no definite goals, living a hand-to-mouth existence, apparently spending his earnings as quickly as he made them.&lt;ref name=Fogg/&gt;{{rp|11}} Accompanying him on his travels was his new girlfriend, Sophie Ziegler. Nicknamed &quot;Naguine,&quot; she and Reinhardt were distant cousins. &lt;ref name=Fogg/&gt;{{rp|11}}

During the years after the fire, Reinhardt was rehabilitating and experimenting on the guitar that his brother had given him. After having played a broad spectrum of music, he was introduced to American jazz by an acquaintance, [[Émile Savitry]], whose record collection included such musical luminaries as [[Louis Armstrong]], [[Duke Ellington]], and [[Joe Venuti]] and [[Eddie Lang]]. Hearing their music apparently triggered in Reinhardt a vision and goal of becoming a jazz professional.&lt;ref name=Fogg/&gt;{{rp|12}}

While developing his interest in jazz, Reinhardt met [[Stéphane Grappelli]], a young violinist with similar musical interests. He and Grappelli frequently [[jam session|jammed]] together, accompanied by a loose circle of other musicians.&lt;ref name=Delaunay/&gt;{{rp|26}} 

Reinhardt acquired his first [[Selmer guitar]] in the mid-1930s.

===Formation of the quintet===


From 1934 until the outbreak of World War II in 1939, Reinhardt and Grappelli worked together as the principal soloists of their newly formed [[Quintette du Hot Club de France|Hot Club]], in Paris. It became the most accomplished and innovative European jazz group of the period.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Stephane Grappelli is Europe's gift to jazz&quot;, ''The Ottawa Journal'', 9 June 1980&lt;/ref&gt;

Reinhardt's brother [[Joseph Reinhardt|Joseph]] and [[Roger Chaput]] also played on guitar, and [[Louis Vola]] was on bass.&lt;ref name=Illustrated&gt;{{cite book|first=Michael|last=Dregni|title=Django Reinhardt and the Illustrated History of Gypsy Jazz|publisher=Speck Press|year=2006|isbn=978-1-933108-10-0|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|45–49}} The Quintette was one of the few well-known jazz ensembles composed only of stringed instruments.&lt;ref name=Delaunay/&gt;{{rp|64–66}}

In Paris on 14 March 1933, Reinhardt recorded two takes each of &quot;Parce-que je vous aime&quot; and &quot;Si, j'aime Suzy&quot;, vocal numbers with lots of guitar fills and guitar support. He used three guitarists along with an [[accordion]] lead, violin, and bass. In August 1934, he made other recordings with more than one guitar (Joseph Reinhardt, Roger Chaput, and Reinhardt), including the first recording by the Quintette. In both years the great majority of their recordings featured a wide variety of horns, often in multiples, piano, and other instruments,&lt;ref name=&quot;djangomontreal&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Rousseau|first=François|title=Welcome|url=http://www.djangomontreal.com/Django_Montreal/Welcome.html |publisher=Django Montreal|accessdate=30 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; but the all-string instrumentation is the one most often adopted by emulators of the Hot Club sound.

Decca Records in the United States released three records of Quintette songs with Reinhardt on guitar, and one other, credited to &quot;Stephane Grappelli &amp; His Hot 4 with Django Reinhardt&quot;, in 1935.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.78discography.com/Dec23000.htm |title=DECCA (USA) 78rpm numerical listing discographyL 23000 – 23500 |website=78discography.com |date=26 September 2015 |accessdate=30 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Reinhardt also played and recorded with many American jazz musicians, such as [[Adelaide Hall]], [[Coleman Hawkins]], [[Benny Carter]], and [[Rex Stewart]] (who later stayed in Paris). He participated in a jam session and radio performance with [[Louis Armstrong]]. Later in his career, Reinhardt played with [[Dizzy Gillespie]] in France. Also in the neighborhood was the artistic salon [[R-26 (salon)|R-26]], at which Reinhardt and Grappelli performed regularly as they developed their unique musical style.&lt;ref&gt;Tranchant, Jean (1969). ''La Grande Roue''. Paris: Éditions de la Table Ronde.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1938 Reinhardt's quintet played to thousands at an all-star show held in London's [[Gaumont State Cinema|Kilburn State]] auditorium.&lt;ref name=Delaunay/&gt;{{rp|92}} While playing, he noticed American film actor [[Eddie Cantor]] in the front row. When their set ended, Cantor rose to his feet, then went up on stage and kissed Reinhardt's hand, paying no concern to the audience.&lt;ref name=Delaunay/&gt;{{rp|93}} A few weeks later the quintet played at the [[London Palladium]].&lt;ref name=Delaunay/&gt;{{rp|93}}

===The Second World War ===
When [[World War II]] broke out, the original quintet was on tour in the United Kingdom. Reinhardt returned to Paris at once,&lt;ref name=Delaunay/&gt;{{rp|98–99}} leaving his wife in the UK. Grappelli remained in the United Kingdom for the duration of the war. Reinhardt re-formed the quintet, with [[Hubert Rostaing]] on [[clarinet]] replacing Grappelli.&lt;ref name=&quot;sharp&quot;/&gt;

While he tried to continue with his music, war with the Nazis presented Reinhardt with two potentially catastrophic obstacles. First, he was a Romani. Second, he was a jazz musician.

Beginning in 1933, all [[German Romani]] were barred from living in cities, herded into settlement camps, and routinely sterilized. Romani men were required to wear a brown [[Gypsy ID triangle]] sewn on their chest,&lt;ref name=Dregni/&gt;{{rp|168}} similar to the pink triangle that homosexuals wore, and much like the yellow Star of David that Jews had to subsequently wear.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://s-media-cache-ak0.pinimg.com/564x/94/80/f8/9480f8fce677026b4a66a2f4b8ab30a6.jpg|format=JPG|title=Jews wearing Star of David|website=S-media-cache-ak0.pinimg.com|accessdate=30 May 2017}}]&lt;/ref&gt; During the war, Romani were systematically killed in concentration camps.&lt;ref name=Dregni/&gt;{{rp|169}} In France, they were used as slave labour on farms and in factories.&lt;ref name=Dregni/&gt;{{rp|169}} During the Holocaust an estimated 600,000 to 1.5 million Romani throughout Europe were eventually killed.&lt;ref name=Dregni/&gt;{{rp|154}}

Additionally, the [[German attitude toward jazz]] had been hostile throughout the first half of the 20th century.&lt;ref name=Budds&gt;Budds, Michael J. ''Jazz &amp; the Germans: Essays on the Influence of &quot;hot&quot; American Idioms on 20th Century German Music'', Pendragon Press (2002)&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|82}} Between 1916 and 1920, all jazz had been officially banned throughout Germany. The [[Weimar Republic]] also made efforts to suppress jazz between 1922 and 1933. When Hitler came to power, he banned most jazz music. Apparently, he and [[Joseph Goebbels]] viewed jazz as part of an international conspiracy to undermine Germany's greatness.&lt;ref name=Dregni/&gt;{{rp|154}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://65.media.tumblr.com/93b82b80ad9fe4bfb40ff6db6eef0608/tumblr_mtv5ys4Z3P1stxu8xo1_1280.jpg |format=JPG|title=Nazi poster illustrating the negative aspects of jazz|website=65.media.tumblr.com|accessdate=30 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; It would not be until the mid-1950s that Germany reopened itself to European jazz.&lt;ref name=Budds/&gt;{{rp|82}}

Nonetheless, Goebbels stopped short of a complete ban on Jazz, which now had many fans in Germany and elsewhere.&lt;ref name=Dregni/&gt;{{rp|157}} Official policy towards Jazz was much less strict in occupied France, according to author Andy Fry, with jazz music frequently played on both Radio France, the official station of Vichy France, and Radio Paris, controlled by the Germans. A new generation of French Jazz fans, the [[Zazous]], had arisen and swollen the ranks of the Hot Club.&lt;ref name=Dregni/&gt;{{rp|157}} In addition to the increased interest, many American musicians based in Paris during the thirties had returned to the US at the beginning of the war, leaving more work for French musicians. Reinhardt was the most famous jazz musician in Europe at the time, working steadily during the early war years and earning a great deal of money, yet always under threat.

Reinhardt expanded his musical horizons during this period. Using an early amplification system, he was able to work in more of a big-band format, in large ensembles with horn sections. He also experimented with classical composition, writing a Mass for the Gypsies and a symphony. Since he did not read music,  Reinhardt worked with an assistant to notate what he was improvising. His modernist piece ''Rhythm Futur'' was also intended to be acceptable to the Nazis.

{{quote box||align=right|width=25em|bgcolor = MistyRose|quote=In this [&quot;Nuages&quot;] graceful and eloquent melody, Django evoked the woes of the war that weighed on people's souls{{mdash}}and then transcended it all.|source=Biographer Michael Dregni&lt;ref name=Illustrated/&gt;{{rp|93}}}}

In 1943, Reinhardt officially his long term partner Sophie &quot;Naguine&quot; Ziegler in [[Salbris]]. They had a son, [[Babik Reinhardt]], who later became a respected guitarist in his own right.&lt;ref name=&quot;sharp&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Sharp|first=Fred|title=Babik Reinhardt|url=http://www.hotclub.co.uk/html/babik.html |publisher=The Django Reinhardt Swing Page|accessdate=30 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

1943 also saw the tide of war turning against the Germans, with a considerable darkening of the situation in Paris. Severe rationing was in place, and members of Django's circle were being captured by the Nazis or joining the resistance.

Reinhardt's first attempt at escape from [[Occupied France]] led to capture. Fortunately for him, a jazz-loving German, Luftwaffe Officer Dietrich Schulz-Köhn, allowed him to return to Paris.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Kington|first=Miles|title=Playing a Dangerous Game: Django, Jazz and the Nazis|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/factual/djangoreinhardt.shtml |publisher=BBC|accessdate=30 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reinhardt made a second attempt a few days later, but was stopped in the middle of the night by Swiss border guards, who forced him to return to Paris again.&lt;ref&gt;Kater, Michael H. ''Different Drummers: Jazz in the Culture of Nazi Germany'', Oxford Univ. Press (1992) p. 178&lt;/ref&gt;

Unlike the estimated 600,000 Gypsies who were interned and killed in the [[Porajmos]], Reinhardt survived the war without incident.

One of his songs, 1940's &quot;Nuages&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Fq-t9TVbthc |title=Django Reinhardt – Nuages – Paris, 13.12.1940 |via=YouTube |date=13 December 1940 |accessdate=30 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; became an unofficial anthem in Paris to signify hope for liberation.&lt;ref name=Illustrated/&gt;{{rp|93}} During a concert at the Salle Pleyel, the popularity of the song was such that the crowd made him replay it three times in a row.&lt;ref name=Illustrated/&gt;{{rp|93}} The single sold over 100,000 copies.&lt;ref name=Illustrated/&gt;{{rp|93}}

&lt;!--Reinhardt's post-war poverty, fishing, painting, and wandering, ref Dregni--&gt;

===United States tour===
[[File:Django Reinhardt and Duke Ellington (Gottlieb).jpg|thumb|Reinhardt and Duke Ellington at the Aquarium in New York, c.{{nbsp}}November 1946]]
After the war, Reinhardt rejoined Grappelli in the UK. In the autumn of 1946, he made his first tour in the United States, debuting at [[Cleveland Music Hall]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Meiksins |first=Robin |url=http://clevelandhistorical.org/items/show/525 |title=Django Reinhardt at the Music Hall |publisher=Cleveland Historical |accessdate=30 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; as a special guest soloist with [[Duke Ellington]] and His Orchestra. He played with many notable musicians and composers, such as [[Maury Deutsch]]. At the end of the tour, Reinhardt played two nights at [[Carnegie Hall]] in New York City; he received a great ovation and took six curtain calls on the first night.

Despite his pride in touring with Ellington (one of two letters to Grappelli relates his excitement), he was not fully integrated into the band. He played a few tunes at the end of the show, backed by Ellington, with no special arrangements written for him. After the tour, Reinhardt secured an engagement at Café Society Uptown, where he played four solos a day, backed by the resident band. These performances drew large audiences.&lt;ref name=Delaunay/&gt;{{rp|138–139}} Having failed to bring his usual Selmer Modèle Jazz, he played on a borrowed electric guitar, which he felt hampered the delicacy of his style.&lt;ref name=Delaunay/&gt;{{rp|138}} He had been promised jobs in California, but they failed to develop. Tired of waiting, Reinhardt returned to France in February 1947.&lt;ref name=Delaunay/&gt;{{rp|141}}

===After the quintet===
After his return, Reinhardt re-immersed himself in Romani life, finding it difficult to adjust to the postwar world. He sometimes showed up for scheduled concerts without a guitar or amplifier, or wandered off to the park or beach. On a few occasions he refused to get out of bed. Reinhardt developed a reputation among his band, fans, and managers as extremely unreliable. He skipped sold-out concerts to &quot;walk to the beach&quot; or &quot;smell the dew.&quot;&lt;ref name=Delaunay/&gt;{{rp|145}} During this period he continued to attend the [[R-26 (salon)|R-26]] artistic salon in Montmartre, improvising with his devoted collaborator, Stéphane Grappelli.&lt;ref&gt;Tranchant, Jean: pg. 116, ''La Grande Roue''; Éditions de la Table Ronde, Paris, 1969.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;De Visscher, Éric. R. vingt-six. ''Django Reinhardt – Swing De Paris.'' Musée de la musique (Cité de la musique), Paris. 6 October 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

In Rome in 1949, Reinhardt recruited three Italian jazz players (on bass, piano, and snare drum) and recorded over 60 tunes in an Italian studio. He united with Grappelli, and used his acoustic Selmer-Maccaferri. The recording was issued for the first time in the late 1950s.&lt;ref name=&quot;chester&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Chester|first=Paul Vernon|title=Django in Rome: The 1949–50 Sessions|url=http://www.paulvernonchester.com/DjangoInRome.htm|archive-url=https://archive.is/20120526081338/http://www.paulvernonchester.com/DjangoInRome.htm|url-status=dead|archive-date=26 May 2012|publisher=Manouche Maestro|accessdate=30 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Back in Paris, in June 1950, Reinhardt was invited to join an entourage to welcome the return of [[Benny Goodman]]. He also attended a reception for Goodman, who, after the war ended, had asked Reinhardt to join him in the U.S. Goodman repeated his invitation and, out of politeness, Reinhardt accepted. However, Reinhardt later had second thoughts about what role he could play alongside Goodman, who was the &quot;King of Swing&quot;, and remained in France.&lt;ref name=Dregni/&gt;{{rp|251}}

===Final years===
[[File:Django Reinhardt Plaque Samois.JPG|right|thumb|Plaque commemorating Reinhardt at [[Samois-sur-Seine]]]]
In 1951, Reinhardt retired to [[Samois-sur-Seine]], near [[Fontainebleau]], where he lived until his death. He continued to play in Paris jazz clubs and began playing electric guitar. (He often used a Selmer fitted with an electric pickup, despite his initial hesitation about the instrument.) In his final recordings, made with his Nouvelle Quintette in the last few months of his life, he had begun moving in a new musical direction, in which he assimilated the vocabulary of [[bebop]] and fused it with his own melodic style.&lt;ref name=Givan&gt;{{cite book|first=Benjamin|last=Givan|title=The Music of Django Reinhardt|publisher=University of Michigan Press|year=2010|isbn=978-0-472-03408-6|pages=158–94}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 16 May 1953, while walking from the [[Gare de Fontainebleau–Avon Station]] after playing in a Paris club, he collapsed outside his house from a [[brain hemorrhage]].&lt;ref name=Delaunay/&gt;{{rp|160}}
It was a Saturday, and it took a full day for a doctor to arrive.&lt;ref name=Delaunay/&gt;{{rp|161}} Reinhardt was declared [[dead on arrival]] at the hospital in Fontainebleau, at the age of 43.

==Family==
Reinhardt's second son, [[Babik Reinhardt|Babik]], became a guitarist in the contemporary jazz style. His first son, [[Lousson Reinhardt|Lousson]], was more of a traditionalist. He followed the Romani lifestyle and rarely performed in public.
After Reinhardt died, his brother Joseph at first swore to abandon music, but he was persuaded to perform and record again. Joseph's son Markus Reinhardt is a violinist in the Romani style.

A third generation of direct descendants has developed as musicians: David Reinhardt, Reinhardt's grandson (by his son Babik), leads his own trio. Dallas Baumgartner, a great-grandson by Lousson, is a guitarist who travels with the Romani and keeps a low public profile. A slightly younger distant relative, violinist [[Schnuckenack Reinhardt]], became famous in Germany as a performer of gypsy music and gypsy jazz up to his death in 2006, and also assisted in keeping Reinhardt's legacy alive through the period following his death.

==Legacy==
{{Main|Gypsy jazz}}

Reinhardt is regarded as one of the greatest guitar players of all time, and the first important European jazz musician to make a major contribution with jazz guitar.&lt;ref name=Fetherolf&gt;Fetherolf, Bob. ''The Guitar Story: From Ancient to Modern Times'', BookBaby (2014) e-book&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|Professor of music and guitarist, Mark White, of [[Berklee College]], writes: &quot;Django Reinhardt with his Hot Club of France group was a hotbed of great guitar playing. Eventually, Django would play electric guitar, and become one of the greatest guitar stylists of all time.&quot;&lt;ref name=White&gt;White, Mark. ''The Practical Jazz Guitarist: Essential Tools for Soloing, Comping and Performing'', Hal Leonard Corp. (2012) p. 9&lt;/ref&gt;}} During his career he wrote nearly 100 songs, according to jazz guitarist [[Frank Vignola]].&lt;ref name=Vignola/&gt;

Using a Selmer Guitar in the mid-1930s, his style took on new volume and expressiveness.&lt;ref name=Fetherolf/&gt; Despite his physical disability, he played mainly using his index and middle fingers, and invented a distinctive style of jazz guitar.&lt;ref name=Fetherolf/&gt;

For about a decade after Reinhardt's death, interest in his musical style was minimal. In the fifties, [[bebop]] superseded [[swing music|swing]] in jazz, [[rock and roll]] took off, and electric instruments became dominant in popular music. Since the mid-sixties, there has been a revival of interest in Reinhardt's music, a revival that has extended into the 21st century, with annual festivals and periodic tribute concerts. His devotees included classical guitarist [[Julian Bream]] and country guitarist [[Chet Atkins]], who considered him one of the ten greatest guitarists of the twentieth century.&lt;ref name=Fetherolf/&gt;&lt;ref name=Dregni/&gt;{{rp|cover}}{{efn|[[Jimmy Page]] said &quot;Django Reinhardt was fantastic. he must have been playing all the time to be that good.&quot;&lt;ref name=Guitarworld&gt;Kitts, Jeff; Tolinski, Brad. ''Guitar World Presents the 100 Greatest Guitarists of All Time!'', Hal Leonard Corp. (2002) p. 60&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The [[Allman Brothers Band]] song &quot;Jessica&quot; was written by [[Dickey Betts]] in tribute to Reinhardt.&lt;ref name=Fetherolf/&gt; [[Woody Allen]]'s 1999 film ''[[Sweet and Lowdown]]'', the story of a Django Reinhardt-like character, mentions Reinhardt and includes actual recordings in the film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G_HUtNELvVU;t=13s |title=Sweet and Lowdown scene |via=YouTube |date=16 December 2012 |accessdate=30 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Allen&gt;&quot;Woody Allen movie resurrects music of jazz great Reinhardt&quot;, ''Courier-Post'', (Camden, New Jersey), 18 January 2000&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Django was the definitive genius on the guitar, and the depth of his gift was so spectacular,&quot; says Allen.&lt;ref name=Allen/&gt;

Jazz guitarists in the U.S., such as Charlie Byrd and Wes Montgomery, were influenced by his style. In fact, Byrd, who lived from 1925 to 1999, said that Reinhardt was his primary influence. Guitarist [[Mike Peters (musician)|Mike Peters]] notes that &quot;the word 'genius' is bantered about too much. But in jazz, [[Louis Armstrong]] was a genius, [[Duke Ellington]] was another one, and Reinhardt was also.&quot;&lt;ref name=Allen/&gt; Grisman adds, &quot;As far as I'm concerned, no one since has come anywhere close to Django Reinhardt as an improviser or technician.&quot;&lt;ref name=Allen/&gt;

[[File:30e festival Django Reinhardt Samois-sur-Seine.jpg|thumb|Festival Django Reinhardt in France]]
The popularity of gypsy jazz has generated an increasing number of festivals, such as the [[Festival Django Reinhardt]] held every last weekend of June since 1983 in [[Samois-sur-Seine]] (France),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.festivaldjangoreinhardt.com/spip.php?rubrique26 |title=Archived copy |accessdate=9 August 2016 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160822230621/http://www.festivaldjangoreinhardt.com/spip.php?rubrique26 |archivedate=22 August 2016 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://s-media-cache-ak0.pinimg.com/736x/ac/4a/c6/ac4ac6ba35a8841bdeeb119a68737b2d.jpg|format=JPG|title=Django Reinhardt Festival poster|website=S-media-cache-ak0.pinimg.com|accessdate=30 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; the various [[DjangoFest]]s held throughout Europe&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gypsyjazz.gr/wp-content/uploads/2010/05/poster_festNEW.jpg |format=JPG|title=Poster of Django Reinhardt Fest in Athens|website=Gypsyjazz.gr|accessdate=30 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the US, and Django in June, an annual camp for Gypsy jazz musicians and aficionados.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3WHQ0twHQgo |title=Django Reinhardt New York City Festival – Dark Eyes |via=YouTube |date=21 November 2010 |accessdate=30 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://djangofest.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/DFNW2014Poster.png|format=PNG|title=Poster of DjangoFest in Washington state|website=Djangofest.com|accessdate=30 May 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140816223920/http://djangofest.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/DFNW2014Poster.png|archive-date=16 August 2014|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tributes===
In February 2017, the [[Berlin International Film Festival]] held the world premiere of [[Django (2017 film)|''Django'']], a French film directed by Etienne Comar. The movie covers Django's escape from Nazi-occupied Paris in 1943 and the fact that even under &quot;constant danger, flight and the atrocities committed against his family&quot;, he continued composing and performing.&lt;ref name=usnews&gt;[https://www.usnews.com/news/entertainment/articles/2017-01-04/french-film-django-to-open-berlin-film-festival &quot;French film ''Django'' to open Berlin Film Festival], ''USNews'', 4 January 2017&lt;/ref&gt; Reinhardt's music was re-recorded for the film by the Dutch jazz band [[Rosenberg Trio]] with lead guitarist [[Stochelo Rosenberg]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.berlinale.de/en/presse/pressemitteilungen/alle/Alle-Detail_35156.html &quot;World Premiere of ''Django'' to Open the Berlinale, 2017] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170104234929/https://www.berlinale.de/en/presse/pressemitteilungen/alle/Alle-Detail_35156.html |date=4 January 2017 }}, Press Release, ''Berlinale'', 4 January 2017&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Qtko3F0QkEo;t=22m56s |title=Django Reinhardt documentary |via=YouTube |date=9 January 2016 |accessdate=30 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The documentary film, ''Djangomania!'' was released in 2005. The hour-long film was directed and written by Jamie Kastner, who traveled throughout the world to show the influence of Django's music in various countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0480374/?ref_=fn_al_tt_1|title=''Djangomania!'' (2005)|website=IMDb|accessdate=30 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1984 the [[Kool Jazz Festival]], held in [[Carnegie Hall]] and [[Avery Fisher Hall]], was dedicated entirely to Reinhardt. Performers included Grappelli, [[Benny Carter]], and [[Mike Peters (musician)|Mike Peters]] with his group of seven musicians. The festival was organized by [[George Wein]].&lt;ref&gt;''Asbury Park Press'', (Asbury Park, New Jersey), 27 June 1984&lt;/ref&gt; Reinhardt is celebrated annually in the village of [[Liberchies]], his birthplace.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.djangoliberchies.be/ |title=Accueil |publisher=Djangoliberchies.be |accessdate=13 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Numerous musicians have written and recorded tributes to Reinhardt. The jazz standard &quot;[[Django (composition)|Django]]&quot; (1954) was composed by [[John Lewis (pianist)|John Lewis]] of the [[Modern Jazz Quartet]] in honour of Reinhardt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jazzstandards.com/compositions-2/django.htm|title=Django|publisher=JazzStandards.com|first=Sandra|last=Burlingame|accessdate=19 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ramelton, Co. Donegal, Ireland, each year hosts a festival in tribute to Django called &quot;Django sur Lennon&quot; or &quot;Django on the Lennon&quot; the Lennon being the name of the local river that runs through the village.

Djangofest is an annual music festival in Langley WA.

In coincidence with Django's 110th birth anniversary, a graphic novel depicting his youth years was published under the title &quot;Django Main de Feu&quot;, by writer [[Salva Rubio]] and artist [[Efa]] through Belgian publisher [[Dupuis]]. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Django Main de Feu |publisher=dupuis.com |accessdate=23 January 2020|url=https://www.dupuis.com/django-main-de-feu/bd/django-main-de-feu-django-main-de-feu/82356 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Influence==
{{quote box|align=right|width=25em|bgcolor = LightCyan|quote=The instant I heard Django, I flipped. I chose his style because it spoke to me. He was too far ahead of his time. He was something else.|source=French recording artist, Serge Krief&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Qtko3F0QkEo;t=19m36s |title=Django Reinhardt documentary |via=YouTube |date=9 January 2016 |accessdate=30 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
Many guitar players and other musicians have expressed admiration for Reinhardt or have cited him as a major influence. [[Jeff Beck]] described Reinhardt as &quot;by far the most astonishing guitar player ever&quot; and &quot;quite superhuman&quot;.&lt;ref name=Djangobooks&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.djangobooks.com/forum/viewtopic.php?f=1&amp;t=2725&amp;start=0 |title=Jeff Beck on Django |publisher=Djangobooks.com |accessdate=13 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Grateful Dead]]'s [[Jerry Garcia]] and [[Black Sabbath]]'s [[Tony Iommi]], both of whom lost fingers in accidents, were inspired by Reinhardt's example of becoming an accomplished guitar player despite his injuries. Garcia was quoted in June 1985 in ''Frets Magazine'': 
&lt;blockquote&gt;His technique is awesome! Even today, nobody has really come to the state that he was playing at. As good as players are, they haven't gotten to where he is. There's a lot of guys that play fast and a lot of guys that play clean, and the guitar has come a long way as far as speed and clarity go, but nobody plays with the whole fullness of expression that Django has. I mean, the combination of incredible speed – all the speed you could possibly want – but also the thing of every note have a specific personality. You don't hear it. I really haven't heard it anywhere but with Django.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
[[Denny Laine]] and [[Jimmy McCulloch]], members of [[Paul McCartney]]'s band [[Wings (band)|Wings]], have mentioned him as an inspiration.

{{quote box|align=right|width=25em|bgcolor = MistyRose|quote=Django is still one of my main influences, I think, for lyricism. He can make me cry when I hear him.|source=[[Toots Thielemans]]&lt;ref name=Field&gt;Field, Kim. ''Harmonicas, Harps, and Heavy Breathers: the Evolution of the People's Instrument'', Rowman &amp; Littlefield (1993) pp. 253–255&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[Andrew Latimer]], of the band [[Camel (band)|Camel]], has stated that he was influenced by Reinhardt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hit-channel.com/interviewandy-latimer-camel/55489 |title=Archived copy |accessdate=30 April 2015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141218004333/http://www.hit-channel.com/interviewandy-latimer-camel/55489 |archivedate=18 December 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Willie Nelson]] has been a lifelong Reinhardt fan, stating in his memoir, &quot;This was a man who changed my musical life by giving me a whole new perspective on the guitar and, on an even more profound level, on my relationship with sound...During my formative years, as I listened to Django's records, especially songs like 'Nuages' that I would play for the rest of my life, I studied his technique.  Even more, I studied his gentleness.  I love the human sound he gave his acoustic guitar.&quot;{{sfn|Nelson, Willie; Ritz, David|2016|p=45-47}}

==Reinhardt in popular culture==
*The film ''[[Django (2017 film)|Django]]'', by the French filmmaker [[Étienne Comar]], depicting Reinhardt's life during wartime was released in 2017, with the French actor [[Reda Kateb]] performing the role of Reinhardt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cineuropa.org/nw.aspx?t=newsdetail&amp;l=it&amp;did=305892 |title=Reda Kateb e Cécile de France in Django |website=Cineuropa.org |accessdate=30 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; It opened the [[67th Berlin International Film Festival]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Berlin&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.berlinale.de/en/presse/pressemitteilungen/alle/Alle-Detail_35156.html|title=World Premiere of Django to Open the Berlinale 2017|accessdate=4 January 2017|work=Berlinale|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170104234929/https://www.berlinale.de/en/presse/pressemitteilungen/alle/Alle-Detail_35156.html|archive-date=4 January 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The 2004 film ''[[Head in the Clouds (film)|Head in the Clouds]]'' features guitarist ''[[John Jorgenson]]'' as Django Reinhardt in a cameo role.
*The [[Django (web framework)|Django web framework]] is named after Reinhardt, as is version 3.1 of the blog software [[WordPress]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://codex.wordpress.org/Version_3.1 |title=Version 3.1 &quot; WordPress Codex |publisher=Codex.wordpress.org |date=23 February 2011 |accessdate=13 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The [[Government of Belgium|Belgian government]] issued a commemorative coin in 92.5% sterling silver in 2010 coinciding with the 100th anniversary of his birth. It is a silver 10-Euro coin with a color image of Reinhardt on the reverse side.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.coin-database.com/coins/10-euro-100-birthday-of-of-django-reinhardt-belgium-2010.html |title=10 euro 100. birthday of Django Reinhardt – 2010 – Series: Silver 10 euro coins – Belgium – Collector Coin Database |publisher=Coin-database.com |accessdate=13 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*His legacy is referred to in [[Woody Allen]]'s 1999 ''[[Sweet and Lowdown]]''. This spoof biopic features a fictional American guitarist, Emmet Ray, who is obsessed with Reinhardt, with a soundtrack featuring [[Howard Alden]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Davis |first=Francis |title=Faithful to the Love of His Life: Hot 30's Jazz |newspaper=The New York Times |date=5 December 1999 |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1999/12/05/arts/film-faithful-to-the-love-of-his-life-hot-30-s-jazz.html?pagewanted=all&amp;src=pm |accessdate=21 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
*Reinhardt appears as a character in the fiction novel ''[[The Magic Strings of Frankie Presto]]'' (2015) by American author [[Mitch Albom]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Mitch Albom's 'The Magic Strings of Frankie Presto' On World Cafe | url=https://www.npr.org/sections/world-cafe/2015/11/27/457299249/mitch-alboms-the-magic-strings-of-frankie-presto-on-world-cafe | work=[[World Cafe]] | publisher=[[WXPN]] | date=27 November 2015 | access-date=18 May 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Reinhardt's rendition of &quot;[[La Mer (song)|La Mer]]&quot; appears in the 2007 video game ''[[BioShock]]'' along with other songs from him.

==Discography==

===Releases in his lifetime===

Reinhardt recorded over 900 sides in his recording career, from 1928 to 1953, the majority as sides of the then-prevalent [[78 rpm|78-RPM]] records, with the remainder as acetates, transcription discs, private and off-air recordings (of radio broadcasts), and part of a film soundtrack. Only one session (eight tracks) from March 1953 was ever recorded specifically for album release by Norman Granz in the then-new [[LP record|LP]] format, but Reinhardt died before the album could be released. In his earliest recordings Reinhardt played banjo (or, more accurately, banjo-guitar) accompanying accordionists and singers on dances and popular tunes of the day, with no jazz content, whereas in the last recordings before his death he played amplified guitar in the [[bebop]] idiom with a pool of younger, more modern French musicians.

A full chronological listing of his lifetime recorded output is available from the source cited here,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Hasegawa|first=Hikaru|title=The Complete Django Reinhardt Discography 1928–1953|url=http://www.djangoreinhardt.info/printdiscography.php |accessdate=10 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and an index of individual tunes is available from the source cited here.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=Djangopedia|title=Django's Full Discography|url=http://djangopedia.com/wiki/index.php?title=Django%27s_Full_Discography |accessdate=10 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; A few fragments of film performance (without original sound) also survive, as does one complete performance with sound, of the tune &quot;J'Attendrai&quot; performed with the Quintet in 1938 for the short film ''Le Jazz Hot''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=All About Jazz|title=News: All Known Film Footage of Django Reinhardt Now Available on DVD at Last|url=http://news.allaboutjazz.com/all-known-film-footage-of-django-reinhardt-now-available-on-dvd-at-last.php |accessdate=10 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=Open Culture|title=Jazz 'Hot': The Rare 1938 Short Film with Jazz Legend Django Reinhardt|url=http://www.openculture.com/2013/02/ijazz_hoti_the_rare_1938_short_film_with_jazz_legend_django_reinhardt.html|accessdate=10 December 2015|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151210214318/http://www.openculture.com/2013/02/ijazz_hoti_the_rare_1938_short_film_with_jazz_legend_django_reinhardt.html|archivedate=10 December 2015|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Posthumous compilations ===
Since his death, Reinhardt's music has been released on many compilations. ''Intégrale Django Reinhardt'', volumes 1–20 (40 CDs), released by the French company Frémeaux from 2002 to 2005, tried to include every known track on which he played.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=Fretboard Journal|title=Django Reinhardt's Life on Record|url=http://www.fretboardjournal.com/features/online/django-reinhardt-life-record|accessdate=10 December 2015|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151210214118/http://www.fretboardjournal.com/features/online/django-reinhardt-life-record|archivedate=10 December 2015|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* ''The Great Artistry of Django Reinhardt'' (Clef, 1954)
* ''Parisian Swing'' (GNP Crescendo, 1965)
* ''Quintet of the Hot Club of France'' (GNP Crescendo, 1965)
* ''At Club St. Germain'' (Honeysuckle, 1983)
* ''Swing Guitar'' (Jass, 1991)
* ''Djano Reinhardt in Brussels'' (Verve, 1992)
* ''Django Reinhardt &amp; Stephane Grappelli'' (GNP Crescendo, 1990)
* ''Peche à La Mouche: The Great Blue Star Sessions 1947–1953'' (Verve, 1992)
* ''Django's Music'' (Hep, 1994)
* ''Brussels and Paris'' (DRG, 1996)
* ''Quintet of the Hot Club of France'' (Original Jazz Classics, 1997)
* ''Django with His American Friends'' (DRG, 1998)
* ''The Complete Django Reinhardt HMV Sessions'' (1998)
* ''The Classic Early Recordings in Chronological Order'' (2000)
* ''[[Djangology]]'' (Bluebird, 2002)
* ''Intégrale Django Reinhardt'' (Frémeaux, 2002)
* ''[[Jazz in Paris: Nuages]]'' (2003)
* ''Vol. 2: 1938–1939'' (Naxos, 2001)
* ''Swing Guitars Vol. 3 1936–1937'' (Naxos, 2003)
* ''Nuages Vol. 6 1940'' (Naxos, 2004)
* ''Django on the Radio''(2008)

===Unrecorded compositions===

A small number of waltzes composed by Reinhardt in his youth were never recorded by the composer, but were retained in the repertoire of his associates and several are still played today. They came to light via recordings by [[Matelo Ferret]] in 1960 (the waltzes &quot;Montagne Sainte-Genevieve&quot;, &quot;Gagoug&quot;, &quot;Chez Jacquet&quot; and &quot;Choti&quot;; [[Disques Vogue]] (F)EPL7740) and 1961 (&quot;Djalamichto&quot; and &quot;En Verdine&quot;; Disques Vogue (F)EPL7829). The first four are now available on Matelo's CD ''Tziganskaïa and Other Rare Recordings'', released by Hot Club Records (subsequently reissued as ''Tziganskaïa: The Django Reinhardt Waltzes''); &quot;Chez Jacquet&quot; was also recorded by [[Baro Ferret]] in 1966.

The names &quot;Gagoug&quot; and &quot;Choti&quot; were reportedly conferred by Django's [[widow]] Naguine on request from Matelo, who had learned the tunes without names. Django also worked on composing a Mass for use by the gypsies, which was not completed although an 8-minute extract exists, played by the organist [[Léo Chauliac]] for Reinhardt's benefit, via a 1944 radio broadcast; this can be found on the CD release &quot;Gipsy Jazz School&quot; and also on volume 12 of the &quot;Intégrale Django Reinhardt&quot; CD compilation.{{efn|Here is Lauren Oliver's transcript of the interview from the radio broadcast:
Introduction:
VO: In the Chapel of the National Institute for Blind Children, Django Reinhardt will, for the first time, hear his mass played on the organ, which he has written especially for the gypsies. (Organ begins to play)
Interview:
Announcer: Could you tell me Mr Reinhardt, what has compelled you to write this mass?
DR: All the gypsies in the entire world have made use of foreign masses for many centuries. I have written this mass to be interpreted by choir and organ.
A: And in what surroundings do you isolate yourself in order to write – it's not a question of surroundings. For you certainly cannot do it after a jazz concert?
DR: I prefer to write in the evening very late or in the morning in my bed.
A: And did you notate the music?
DR: No, it's not I who notates the music. It's my clarinetist in the Quintet of the Hot Club of France, Gerard Leveque. I dictate it to him.
A: And is today the first recital of your mass?
DR: It is an extract of my mass. I particularly don't know the ending. It's the first time I have heard the composition on the organ.
A: Certainly you know, Mr Reinhardt, that in the world and particularly in France, it is said that you are the king of the gypsies. Is that accurate?
DR: No, no, no, don't think that. But it might come to pass, perhaps one day. I am very loved by them, and I thank them by offering to them this mass. (Organ continues to play)}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Biography|Music|Jazz}}
{{Div col|colwidth=30em}}
*[[Oscar Alemán]]
*[[Django à Liberchies]] festival
*[[DjangodOr]] (Golden Django)
*[[:fr:Festivals de jazz Django Reinhardt|Festivals de jazz Django Reinhardt]], a French list of worldwide festivals dedicated to the guitarist
*[[List of Belgian bands and artists#R|List of Belgian bands and artists]]
*[[List of Belgians#Musicians and singers|List of Belgian musicians and singers]]
*[[List of compositions by Django Reinhardt]]
*[[List of Romani people]]
*[[R-26 (salon)]]
*[[Jean Sablon]]
*[[Sinti]]
*[[Vernon Story]]
*[[Gábor Szabó]]
*[http://www.cglib.org/complete-works/django-reinhardt-complete-works-integrale-for-classical-guitar/ Django Reinhardt – Complete Works (Integrale) for Classical Guitar]
{{div col end}}

==Notes==
{{Notelist}}

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
*{{Commons inline}}

{{Django Reinhardt}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Reinhardt, Django}}
[[Category:1910 births]]
[[Category:1953 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Hainaut (province)]]
[[Category:Belgian Romani people]]
[[Category:Manouche people]]
[[Category:Musicians from Paris]]
[[Category:Musicians with physical disabilities]]
[[Category:Belgian jazz guitarists]]
[[Category:Continental jazz guitarists]]
[[Category:Gypsy jazz guitarists]]
[[Category:Romani guitarists]]
[[Category:Swing guitarists]]
[[Category:People of Montmartre]]
[[Category:20th-century guitarists]]
[[Category:Quintette du Hot Club de France members]]</text>
      <sha1>skzystrrdv909widpyvj9nli8akpw41</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
