  <page>
    <title>Dhimmi</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9090</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942843229</id>
      <parentid>941640324</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T05:17:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>58.182.176.169</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */ expanded</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2018}}
{{Italic title}}
{{Fiqh |political}}
'''''{{transl|ar|ALA|Dhimmī}}''''' ({{lang-ar|ذمي}} ''{{transl|ar|DIN|ḏimmī}}'', {{IPA-ar|ˈðɪmmiː|IPA}}, collectively {{lang|ar|أهل الذمة}} ''{{transl|ar|DIN|ahl ul-ḏimmah}}/{{transl|ar|ALA|dhimmah}}'' &quot;the people of the ''dhimma''&quot;) is a historical&lt;ref name=Campo/&gt; term referring to non-[[Muslim]]s living in an [[Islamic state]] with legal protection.&lt;ref name=Campo&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |title=dhimmi |encyclopedia=[[Encyclopedia of Islam]] |editor=Juan Eduardo Campo |pages=194–195 |publisher=Infobase Publishing |date=12 May 2010 |quote= Dhimmis are non-Muslims who live within Islamdom and have a regulated and protected status. ... In the modern period, this term has generally has occasionally been resuscitated, but it is generally obsolete.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Modarresi&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Mohammad Taqi al-Modarresi|authorlink=Mohammad Taqi al-Modarresi|title=The Laws of Islam|date=26 March 2016|publisher=Enlight Press|isbn=978-0994240989|url=http://almodarresi.com/en/books/pdf/TheLawsofIslam.pdf|accessdate=22 December 2017|ref=Modarresi|language=English}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|470}} The word literally means &quot;protected person&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/dhimmi|title=Definition of DHIMMI|website=www.merriam-webster.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; referring to the state's obligation under [[sharia]] to protect the individual's life, property, and freedom of religion, in exchange for loyalty to the state and payment of the [[jizya]] tax, which complemented the [[zakat]], or obligatory alms, paid by the Muslim subjects.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Glenn |first= H. Patrick |author-link=H. Patrick Glenn |year=2007 |title=Legal Traditions of the World |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |pages=218–219 |quote=A Dhimmi is a non-Muslim subject of a state governed in accordance to sharia law. The term connotes an obligation of the state to protect the individual, including the individual's life, property, and freedom of religion and worship, and required loyalty to the empire, and a poll tax known as the jizya, which complemented the Islamic tax paid by the Muslim subjects, called Zakat.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dhimmis were exempt from certain duties assigned specifically to Muslims, and did not enjoy certain privileges and freedoms reserved for Muslims, but were otherwise equal under the laws of property, contract, and obligation.&lt;ref&gt;H. Patrick Glenn, ''Legal Traditions of the World''. [[Oxford University Press]], 2007, p. 219.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The French scholar Gustave Le Bon (the author of ''La civilisation des Arabes'') writes &quot;that despite the fact that the incidence of taxation fell more heavily on a Muslim than a non-Muslim, the non-Muslim was free to enjoy equally well with every Muslim all the privileges afforded to the citizens of the state. The only privilege that was reserved for the Muslims was the seat of the caliphate, and this, because of certain religious functions attached to it, which could not naturally be discharged by a non-Muslim.&quot; Mun'im Sirry (2014), ''Scriptural Polemics: The Qur'an and Other Religions'', p.179. [[Oxford University Press]]. {{ISBN|978-0199359363}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Abou El Fadl|first1=Khaled|authorlink=Khaled Abou El Fadl|title=The Great Theft: Wrestling Islam from the Extremists|date=2007|publisher=[[HarperOne]]|isbn=978-0061189036|page=204|quote = According to the dhimma status system, non-Muslims must pay a poll tax in return for Muslim protection and the privilege of living in Muslim territory. Per this system, non-Muslims are exempt from military service, but they are excluded from occupying high positions that involve dealing with high state interests, like being the president or prime minister of the country. In Islamic history, non-Muslims did occupy high positions, especially in matters that related to fiscal policies or tax collection.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under [[sharia]], the dhimmi communities were usually governed by their own laws in place of some of the laws applicable to the Muslim community. For example, the [[Jews|Jewish]] community in Medina was allowed to have its own [[beit din|Halakhic courts]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Cohen&quot;/&gt; and the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] [[millet (Ottoman Empire)|millet system]] allowed its various dhimmi communities to rule themselves under [[Ottoman law|separate legal courts]]. These courts did not cover cases that involved religious groups outside of their own community, or capital offences. Dhimmi communities were also allowed to engage in certain practices that were usually forbidden for the Muslim community, such as the [[Islamic dietary laws|consumption of alcohol and pork]].&lt;ref&gt;Al-Misri, ''Reliance of the Traveler'' (edited and translated by [[Nuh Ha Mim Keller]]), p. 608. Amana Publications, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Al-Misri, ''Reliance of the Traveler'' (ed. and trans. Nuh Ha Mim Keller), pp. 977, 986. Amana Publications, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Ghazi|Kalin|Kamali|2013|pp=240–1}}

Historically, dhimmi status was originally applied to [[Jews]], [[Christians]], and [[Sabians]]. This status later also came to be applied to [[Zoroastrianism|Zoroastrians]], [[Hindu]]s, [[Jainism|Jains]] and [[Buddhism|Buddhists]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Wael B. Hallaq|authorlink = Wael Hallaq|title=Sharī'a: Theory, Practice, Transformations|year=2009|publisher=Cambridge University Press (Kindle edition)|page=327 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Annemarie Schimmel|year=2004|page=[https://archive.org/details/empireofgreatmug00anne/page/107 107]|title=The Empire of the Great Mughals: History, Art and Culture|isbn=978-1861891853|quote=The conqueror [[Muhammad bin Qasim|Muhammad Ibn Al Qasem]] gave both Hindus and Buddhists the same status as the Christians, Jews and Sabaeans the Middle East. They were all &quot;dhimmi&quot; ('protected people')|url=https://archive.org/details/empireofgreatmug00anne/page/107|author-link=Annemarie Schimmel}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=bonner&gt;{{cite book|author=Michael Bonner|title=Jihad in Islamic History|publisher=Princeton University Press (Kindle edition)|year=2008|page= 89}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Moderate Muslims]] generally reject the dhimma system as inappropriate for the age of nation-states and democracies.&lt;ref name=&quot;El Fadl&quot;&gt;&quot;[…] the overwhelming majority of moderate Muslims reject the dhimma system as ahistorical, in the sense that it is inappropriate for the age of nation-states and democracies.&quot; {{cite book|last1=[[Khaled Abou El Fadl|Abou El Fadl]]|first1=[[Khaled Abou El Fadl|Khaled]]|title=The Great Theft: Wrestling Islam from the Extremists|date=23 January 2007|publisher=HarperOne|isbn=978-0061189036|page=214}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is a [[Dhimmi#Views of modern Islamic scholars on the status of non-Muslims in an Islamic society|range of opinions]] among 20th century and contemporary theologians about whether the notion of dhimma is appropriate for modern times, and, if so, what form it should take in an Islamic state.

==The &quot;dhimma contract&quot;==
Based on [[Quran]]ic verses and Islamic traditions, classical sharia distinguishes between Muslims, followers of other [[Abrahamic religions]], and [[Paganism|pagans]] or people belonging to other [[Polytheism|polytheistic]] religions. As [[monotheism|monotheists]], Jews and Christians have traditionally been considered &quot;[[People of the Book]],&quot; and afforded a special status known as ''dhimmi'' derived from a theoretical contract—&quot;dhimma&quot; or &quot;residence in return for taxes&quot;. In Yemenite Jewish sources, a treaty was drafted between Muhammad and his Jewish subjects, known as ''kitāb ḏimmat al-nabi'', written in the 17th year of the [[Hijri year|Hijra]] (638 CE), which gave express liberty to Jews living in Arabia to observe the Sabbath and to grow-out their side-locks, but required them to pay the [[jizya]] (poll-tax) annually for their protection.&lt;ref&gt;[[Shelomo Dov Goitein]], ''The Yemenites – History, Communal Organization, Spiritual Life'' (Selected Studies), editor: Menahem Ben-Sasson, Jerusalem 1983, pp. 288–299. {{ISBN|965-235-011-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are parallels for this in [[Roman law|Roman]] and [[Halakha|Jewish law]].&lt;ref&gt;[[H. Patrick Glenn|Glenn, H. Patrick]] (2007). ''Legal Traditions of the World: Sustainable Diversity in Law'' (3rd edition). New York City; Oxford: [[Oxford University Press]]. {{ISBN|978-0-19-920541-7}}. pp. 217–219.&lt;/ref&gt; Muslim governments in the Indus basin readily extended the dhimmi status to the Hindus and Buddhists of India.&lt;ref&gt;[[Marshall Hodgson]], ''The Venture of Islam Conscience and History in a World Civilization Vol 2''. [[University of Chicago]], 1958, p. 278.&lt;/ref&gt; Eventually, the largest [[Madhhab|school]] of Islamic scholarship applied this term to all non-Muslims living in Islamic lands outside the [[Hejaz|sacred area]] surrounding Mecca, Arabia.&lt;ref&gt;al-Misri, Ahmad ibn Naqib (edited and translated from Arabic (with commentary) by Nuh Ha Mim Keller) (1994 revised edition), p. 603.&lt;/ref&gt;

Classical sharia incorporated the [[religious law]]s and courts of [[Christianity|Christians]], [[Judaism|Jews]] and [[Hinduism|Hindus]], as seen in the early [[caliphate]], [[Al-Andalus]], [[Muslim conquest in the Indian subcontinent|Indian subcontinent]], and the [[Millet (Ottoman Empire)|Ottoman Millet]] system.&lt;ref name=&quot;Weeramantry-138_2&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Weeramantry|1997|p=138}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Sachedina&gt;{{cite book|title=The Islamic Roots of Democratic Pluralism|author=Sachedina, Abdulaziz Abdulhussein |year=2001|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|isbn=978-0-19-513991-4|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=January 2016}} Quoting the Qur'anic statement, &quot;Let Christians judge according to what We have revealed in the Gospel&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{Quran-usc|5|47}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Muhammad Hamidullah]] writes that Islam has decentralized and &quot;communalized&quot; law and justice.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Hamidullah|first=Muhammad|authorlink=Muhammad Hamidullah|date=1986|title=Relations of Muslims with non‐Muslims|journal=Journal of Muslim Minority Affairs|volume=7|issue=1|page=9|doi=10.1080/13602008608715960|issn=0266-6952|url=https://dergipark.org.tr/tr/pub/istem/issue/26528/279243}}&lt;/ref&gt; In medieval Islamic societies, the ''[[qadi]]'' (Islamic judge) usually could not interfere in the matters of non-Muslims unless the parties voluntarily chose to be judged according to Islamic law, thus the dhimmi communities living in Islamic states usually had their own laws independent from the sharia law, as with the Jews who would have their own [[beit din|rabbinical courts]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Cohen&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Under Crescent and Cross: The Jews in the Middle Ages|author=Cohen, Mark R. |publisher=[[Princeton University Press]]|year=1995|isbn=978-0-691-01082-3 |page=74 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=fgbib5exskUC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=cohen+Under+Crescent+and+Cross&amp;q|accessdate=10 April 2010 |ref=harv|author-link=Mark R. Cohen }}&lt;/ref&gt; These courts did not cover cases that involved other religious groups, or capital offences or threats to public order. By the 18th century, however, dhimmis frequently attended the Ottoman Muslim courts, where cases were taken against them by Muslims, or they took cases against Muslims or other dhimmis. Oaths sworn by dhimmis in these courts were tailored to their beliefs.&lt;ref name=&quot;al-Qattan-99&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=al-Qattan, Najwa |title=Dhimmis in the Muslim Court: Legal Autonomy and Religious Discrimination |journal=[[International Journal of Middle East Studies]] |volume=31 |issue=3 |pages=429–444 |year=1999 |issn=0020-7438 |doi=10.1017/S0020743800055501 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Non-Muslims were allowed to engage in certain practices (such as the consumption of alcohol and pork) that were usually forbidden by Islamic law,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first1=Muhammad|last1=Hamidullah|authorlink=Muhammad Hamidullah|date=1970|title=Introduction to Islam|publisher=International Islamic Federation of Student Organizations|page=180}}&lt;/ref&gt; in point of fact, any Muslim who pours away their wine or forcibly appropriates it is liable to pay compensation.{{sfn|Abdel-Haleem|2012|p=73}} Zoroastrian &quot;self-marriages&quot;, that were considered incestuous under sharia, were also tolerated. [[Ibn Qayyim Al-Jawziyya]] (1292–1350) opined that non-Muslims were entitled to such practices since they could not be presented to sharia courts and the religious minorities in question held it permissible. This ruling was based on the precedent that the [[Prophets in Islam|Islamic prophet]] [[Muhammad]] did not forbid such self-marriages among Zoroastrians despite coming into contact with Zoroastrians and knowing about this practice.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, Sherman A. (2005). [https://books.google.com/?id=nprKYM8sleYC&amp;pg=PA144&amp;dq=ankiha+fasida#v=onepage&amp;q p. 144] (via [[Google Books]]). Retrieved 19 September 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Religious minorities were also free to do as they wished in their own homes, provided they did not publicly engage in illicit sexual activity in ways that could threaten public morals.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, Sherman A. (2005). [https://books.google.com/?id=nprKYM8sleYC&amp;pg=PA145&amp;dq=ankiha+fasida#v=onepage&amp;q p. 145] (via [[Google Books]]). Retrieved 19 September 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

However, the classical dhimma contract is no longer enforced. Western influence has been instrumental in eliminating the restrictions and protections of the dhimma contract.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Lewis|first=Bernard|title=The Jews of Islam|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=W0EbKFRxrT4C|year=1984|publisher=Princeton University Press|isbn=978-0-691-00807-3 |page=184}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to law professor [[H. Patrick Glenn]] of [[McGill University]], &quot;[t]oday it is said that the dhimmi are 'excluded from the specifically Muslim privileges, but on the other hand they are excluded from the specifically Muslim duties' while (and here there are clear parallels with western public and private law treatment of aliens—Fremdenrecht, la condition de estrangers), '[f]or the rest, the Muslim and the dhimmi are equal in practically the whole of the law of property and of contracts and obligations'.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[H. Patrick Glenn|Glenn, H. Patrick]] (2007). ''Legal Traditions of the World&amp;: Sustainable Diversity in Law'' (3rd edition). New York City; Oxford: Oxford University Press. {{ISBN|978-0-19-920541-7}}. p. 219.&lt;/ref&gt;

===The dhimma contract and sharia law===
{{Main|Sharia}}
The dhimma contract is an integral part of traditional Islamic sharia. From the 9th century AD, the power to interpret and refine law in traditional Islamic societies was in the hands of the scholars (''[[ulama]]''). This separation of powers served to limit the range of actions available to the ruler, who could not easily decree or reinterpret law independently and expect the continued support of the community.&lt;ref&gt;Basim Musallam, ''The Cambridge Illustrated History of the Islamic World'', edited by [[Francis Robinson]]. Cambridge University Press, 1996, p. 176.&lt;/ref&gt; Through succeeding centuries and empires, the balance between the ulema and the rulers shifted and reformed, but the balance of power was never decisively changed.&lt;ref&gt;Hodgson, ''The Venture of Islam Vol 3'', 1961, pp. 105–108.&lt;/ref&gt; At the beginning of the 19th century, the [[Industrial Revolution]] and the [[French Revolution]] introduced an era of European world hegemony that included the domination of most of the lands of Islam.&lt;ref&gt;Hodgson, ''The Venture of Islam Vol 3'', 1961, pp. 176–177.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sarah Ansari, ''The Cambridge Illustrated History of the Islamic World edited by [[Francis Robinson]]''. Cambridge University Press, 1996, p. 90.&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of the [[World War II|Second World War]], the European powers found themselves too weakened to maintain their empires.&lt;ref&gt;Hodgson, ''The Venture of Islam Vol 3'', 1961, pp. 366–367.&lt;/ref&gt; The wide variety in forms of government, systems of law, attitudes toward modernity and interpretations of sharia are a result of the ensuing drives for independence and modernity in the Muslim world.&lt;ref&gt;Sarah Ansari, ''The Cambridge Illustrated History of the Islamic World edited by [[Francis Robinson]]''. [[Cambridge University Press]], 1996, pp. 103–111.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Marshall Hodgson]], ''[[The Venture of Islam]] Conscience and History in a World Civilization Vol 3''. [[The University of Chicago]], 1961, pp. 384–386.&lt;/ref&gt;

Muslim states, sects, schools of thought and individuals differ as to exactly what sharia law entails.&lt;ref&gt;Otto, Jan Michiel. ''Sharia and National Law in Muslim Countries: Tensions and Opportunities for Dutch and EU Foreign Policy ''. Amsterdam University Press, 2008, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, Muslim states today utilize a spectrum of legal systems. Most states have a mixed system that implements certain aspects of sharia while acknowledging the supremacy of a constitution. A few, such as Turkey, have declared themselves secular.&lt;ref&gt;Otto, ''Sharia and National Law in Muslim Countries'', 2008, pp. 8–9.&lt;/ref&gt; Local and customary laws may take precedence in certain matters, as well.&lt;ref&gt;Otto, ''Sharia and National Law in Muslim Countries'', 2008, p. 29.&lt;/ref&gt; Islamic law is therefore polynormative,&lt;ref&gt;Otto, ''Sharia and National Law in Muslim Countries'', 2008, p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt; and despite several cases of regression in recent years, the trend is towards modernization and liberalization.&lt;ref&gt;Otto, ''Sharia and National Law in Muslim Countries'', 2008, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; Questions of human rights and the status of minorities cannot be generalized with regards to the Muslim world. They must instead be examined on a case-by-case basis, within specific political and cultural contexts, using perspectives drawn from the historical framework.&lt;ref&gt;Otto, ''Sharia and National Law in Muslim Countries'', 2008, pp. 37–39.&lt;/ref&gt;

===The end of the dhimma contract===
The status of the dhimmi &quot;was for long accepted with resignation by the Christians and with gratitude by the Jews&quot; but the rising power of Christendom and the radical ideas of the French Revolution caused a wave of discontent among Christian dhimmis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last= Lewis|first=Bernard|title=The Jews of Islam |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=W0EbKFRxrT4C|year=1984|publisher=Princeton University Press|isbn=978-0-691-00807-3}} p. 62&lt;/ref&gt; The continuing and growing pressure from the European powers combined with pressure from Muslim reformers gradually relaxed the inequalities between Muslims and non-Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last= Lewis|first=Bernard|title=The Jews of Islam|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=W0EbKFRxrT4C|year=1984|publisher=Princeton University Press|isbn=978-0-691-00807-3}} summary of pp. 62–66. See p. 62 (second paragraph), p. 65 (third paragraph)&lt;/ref&gt;

On 18 February 1856, the [[Ottoman Reform Edict of 1856]] (Hatt-i Humayan) was issued, building upon the 1839 edict. It came about partly as a result of pressure from and the efforts of the ambassadors of Great Britain, France, and Austria, whose respective countries were needed as allies in the [[Crimean War]]. It again proclaimed the principle of equality between Muslims and non-Muslims, and produced many specific reforms to this end. For example, the jizya tax was abolished and non-Muslims were allowed to join the army.&lt;ref&gt;Lapidus (1988), p. 599&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lapidus (2002), p. 495&lt;/ref&gt;

===Views of modern Islamic scholars on the status of non-Muslims in an Islamic society===
* The Iranian Ayatollah [[Ruhollah Khomeini]] indicates in his book ''[[Islamic Government: Governance of the Jurist]]'' that non-Muslims should be required to pay the [[Tax per head|poll tax]], in return for which they would profit from the protection and services of the state; they would, however, be excluded from all participation in the political process.&lt;ref&gt;Hukuma Islamiyya, n.p. (Beirut), n.d., pp. 30ff.; Vilayat-i Faqih, n.p., n.d., pp. 35ff.; English version (from the Arabic), ''Islamic Government'' (U.S. Joint Publications Research Service 72663, 1979), pp. 22ff.; French version (from the Persian), Pour un gouvernement islamique (Paris, 1979), pp. 31ff. Another version in Hamid Algar, ''Islam and Revolution: Writings and Declarations of Imam Khomeini'' (Berkeley, 1981), pp. 45ff.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bernard Lewis]] remarks about Khomeini that one of his main grievances against the Shah, [[Mohammad Reza Pahlavi]], was that his legislation allowed the theoretical possibility of non-Muslims exercising political or judicial authority over Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;Bernard Lewis, ''[[The Jews of Islam]]'' notes on page 3&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Egyptian theologian [[Yusuf al-Qaradawi]], chairman of the [[International Union of Muslim Scholars]],&lt;ref name=&quot;chair&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|title=Qatar-based cleric calls for Egypt vote boycott|date=11 May 2014|author=AFP (news agency) |newspaper=Yahoo News|url=https://uk.news.yahoo.com/qatar-based-cleric-calls-egypt-vote-boycott-192234858.html#9K9eVKw|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140616031315/https://uk.news.yahoo.com/qatar-based-cleric-calls-egypt-vote-boycott-192234858.html|archivedate=16 June 2014|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; has stated in his [[Al Jazeera]] program ''Sharia and Life'', which has an estimated audience of 35 to 60 million viewers:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The People Want: A Radical Exploration of the Arab Uprising|author=Gilbert Achcar|year=2013|page=112|publisher=University of California Press|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-CxxOnASaMAC&amp;pg=PA112
|isbn=9780520956544}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;When we say ''dhimmis'' (''ahl al-dhimma'') it means that [...] they are under the covenant of God and His Messenger and the Muslim community and their responsibility (''ḍamān''), and it is everyone's duty to protect them, and this is what is intended by the word. At present many of our brethren are offended by the word ''dhimmis'', and I have stated in what I wrote in my books that I don't see anything to prevent contemporary Islamic [[ijtihad]] from discarding this word ''dhimmis'' and calling them non-Muslim citizens.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;لما نقول أهل الذمة يعني أهل ذمة الله يعني هم في عهد الله وعهد رسوله وعهد جماعة المسلمين وضمانهم، الجميع عليه أن يحميهم، فهذا هو المقصود من الكلمة. الآن يتأذى منها الكثير من أخواننا كلمة أهل الذمة، وأنا ذكرت فيما كتبت في كتبي أنني أنا لا أرى أي مانع أمام الاجتهاد الإسلامي المعاصر أن يحذف كلمة أهل الذمة هذه ونسميهم المواطنون من غير المسلمين [http://www.aljazeera.net/programs/religionandlife/2008/5/6/%D8%BA%D9%8A%D8%B1-%D8%A7%D9%84%D9%85%D8%B3%D9%84%D9%85%D9%8A%D9%86-%D9%81%D9%8A-%D8%A7%D9%84%D9%85%D8%AC%D8%AA%D9%85%D8%B9-%D8%A7%D9%84%D8%A5%D8%B3%D9%84%D8%A7%D9%85%D9%8A Transcript of the 5-6-2008 &quot;Sharia and Life&quot; episode on Al Jazeera's website]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Muhammad Husayn Tabataba'i]], a 20th-century [[Shia Islam|Shia]] scholar, commenting on a [[hadith]] that says that the Quranic verse 9:29&lt;ref&gt;Quran 9:29—&quot;Fight those who do not believe in Allah or in the [[Islamic eschatology|Last Day]] and who do not consider unlawful what Allah and His Messenger have made unlawful and who do not adopt the religion of truth from those who were given the Scripture—fight until they give the jizyah willingly while they are humbled.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; enjoining Muslims to fight dhimmis &quot;until they give the jizyah willingly&quot; had &quot;abrogated&quot; other verses asking for good behaviour toward dhimmis, states that &quot;abrogation&quot; could be understood either in its terminological sense or its literal sense. If &quot;abrogation&quot; is understood in its terminological sense, Muslims should deal with dhimmis strictly in a good and decent manner. If &quot;abrogation&quot; is understood in its literal sense, then it is not in conflict with the verse of fighting. He then points out that uses of words in their literal sense (as opposed to their terminological ones) are common in the &quot;traditions of the Imams&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author1=Muhammad Husayn Tabataba'i|authorlink1=Muhammad Husayn Tabataba'i|title=Surah Al-Baqarah, verses 83-88|url=http://www.almizan.org/|website=almizan.org|accessdate=1 January 2016|language=Arabic, English|quote=as-Sadiq (a.s) said: &quot;Verily Allah sent Muhammad (s.a.w.) with five swords: So (there is) a sword against a dhimmi (free non-Muslim subject of an Islamic country). Allah said: and speak to men good (words); it was revealed about the dhimmis, then it was abrogated by another verse, Fight those who do not believe in Allah... (9:29) (al-'Ayyashi)  The author says: In this tradition the Imam has taken the &quot;speech&quot; to mean behavior. We say: Do not speak to him but good; what we mean is: Do not deal with him but in a good and decent manner. This meaning will apply only if we take the word, &quot;abrogated&quot; in its terminological sense. But it may also be taken in its literal sense (as we shall explain under the verse: Whatever signs We abrogate or cause to be forgotten ...2:106); and in that case this verse will not be in conflict with that of the fighting. It should be pointed out that such uses of words in their literal meanings (as against their terminological ones) are not infrequent in the traditions of the Imams.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Javed Ahmad Ghamidi]], a Pakistani theologian, writes in ''[[Mizan]]'' that certain directives of the Quran were specific only to Muhammad against peoples of his times, besides other directives, the campaign involved asking the polytheists of Arabia for submission to Islam as a condition for exoneration and the others for jizya and submission to the political authority of the Muslims for exemption from [[capital punishment]] and for military protection as the dhimmis of the Muslims. Therefore, after Muhammad and [[Companions of the Prophet|his companions]], there is no concept in Islam obliging Muslims to wage war for propagation or implementation of Islam.&lt;ref&gt;[[Javed Ahmed Ghamidi]], ''[[Mizan]]'', Chapter: The Islamic Law of Jihad, Dar ul-Ishraq, 2001. OCLC: 52901690 [http://www.studying-islam.org/articletext.aspx?id=771]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Misplaced Directives&quot;, [http://www.renaissance.com.pk/ ''Renaissance''] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060813123204/http://www.renaissance.com.pk/ |date=13 August 2006 }}, [[Al-Mawrid Institute]], Vol. 12, No. 3, March 2002.{{cite web |url=http://www.renaissance.com.pk/martitl2y2.html |title=Archived copy |accessdate=5 October 2006 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20061115065145/http://www.renaissance.com.pk/martitl2y2.html |archivedate=15 November 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Iranian Shia jurist Grand Ayatollah [[Naser Makarem Shirazi]] states in ''Selection of the [[Tafsir Nemooneh]]'' that the main philosophy of jizya is that it is only a financial aid to those Muslims who are in the charge of safeguarding the security of the state and dhimmis' lives and properties on their behalf.&lt;ref&gt;[http://library.tebyan.net/books1/1016.htm ''Selection of Tafsir Nemooneh''], Grand Ayatollah Makarim Shirazi, p. 10, volume 2, on verse 9:29 {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061118113944/http://library.tebyan.net/books1/1016.htm |date=18 November 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Prominent Islamic thinkers like [[Fahmi Huwaidi]] and [[Tarek El-Bishry]] have based their justification for full citizenship of non-Muslims in an Islamic states on the precedent set by Muhammad in the [[Constitution of Medina]]. They argue that in this charter the People of Book, have the status of citizens (''muwatinun'') rather than dhimmis, sharing equal rights and duties with Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|author1=Muhammad Muslih|author2=Michaelle Browers|title= Democracy |encyclopedia=The Oxford Encyclopedia of the Islamic World|editor=John L. Esposito|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford|year=2009|url=http://www.oxfordreference.com/view/10.1093/acref/9780195305135.001.0001/acref-9780195305135-e-0185|url-access=subscription|doi=10.1093/acref/9780195305135.001.0001|isbn=9780195305135}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Legal scholar L. Ali Khan also points to the [[Constitution of Medina]] as a way forward for Islamic states in his 2006 paper titled ''The Medina Constitution''. He suggests this ancient document, which governed the status of religions and races in the first Islamic state, in which Jewish tribes are &quot;placed on an equal footing with [...] Muslims&quot; and granted &quot;the freedom of religion,&quot; can serve as a basis for the protection of minority rights, equality, and religious freedom in the modern Islamic state.&lt;ref&gt;Khan, Ali, ''Commentary on the Constitution of Medina'' in ''Understanding Islamic Law: From Classical to Contemporary'', Edited by Aminah Beverly McCloud and Hisham Ramadan, Alta Mira Press, 2006, pp. 205–208.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=The Medina Constitution|first=Ali|last=Khan|date=17 November 2006|ssrn = 945458}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Tariq Ramadan]], Professor of Islamic Studies at the [[University of Oxford]], advocates the inclusion of academic disciplines and Islamic society, along with traditional Islamic scholars, in an effort to reform Islamic law and address modern conditions. He speaks of remaining faithful to the higher objectives of sharia law. He posits universal rights of dignity, welfare, freedom, equality and justice in a [[Religious pluralism|religiously]] and [[Cultural pluralism|culturally pluralistic]] Islamic (or other) society, and proposes a dialogue regarding the modern term &quot;citizenship,&quot; although it has no clear precedent in classical [[fiqh]]. He further includes the terms &quot;non-citizen&quot;, &quot;foreigner&quot;, &quot;resident&quot; and &quot;immigrant&quot; in this dialogue, and challenges not only Islam, but modern civilization as a whole, to come to terms with these concepts in a meaningful way with regards to problems of racism, discrimination and oppression.&lt;ref&gt;Ramadan, Tariq, ''Radical Reform: Islamic Ethics and Liberation'', Oxford University Press, 2009, pp. 268–271.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Dhimmi communities==

Jews and Christians living under early Muslim rule were considered dhimmis, a status that was later also extended to other non-Muslims like Hindus and Buddhists. They were allowed to &quot;practise their religion, subject to certain conditions, and to enjoy a measure of communal autonomy&quot; and guaranteed their personal safety and security of property, in return for paying tribute and acknowledging Muslim rule.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis (1984), pp. 10, 20.&lt;/ref&gt; Islamic law and custom prohibited the enslavement of free dhimmis within lands under Islamic rule.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis (2002), p.92&lt;/ref&gt; Taxation from the perspective of dhimmis who came under the Muslim rule, was &quot;a concrete continuation of the taxes paid to earlier regimes&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cahen&quot;&gt;Cl. Cahen in ''[[Encyclopedia of Islam]]'', Jizya article&lt;/ref&gt; (but lower under the Muslim rule&lt;ref&gt;Lewis 1984 p.18&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis p57&quot;/&gt;). They were also exempted from the [[zakat]] tax paid by Muslims. The dhimmi communities living in Islamic states had their own laws independent from the Sharia law, such as the Jews who had their own [[beit din|Halakhic courts]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Under Crescent and Cross: The Jews in the Middle Ages|author=Mark R. Cohen|publisher=[[Princeton University Press]]|year=1995|isbn=978-0-691-01082-3|page=74|url=https://books.google.com/?id=fgbib5exskUC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=cohen+Under+Crescent+and+Cross&amp;q|accessdate=10 April 2010|author-link=Mark R. Cohen}}&lt;/ref&gt; The dhimmi communities had their own leaders, courts, personal and religious laws,&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis 1984, p. 27&quot;&gt;Lewis (1984), p. 27&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Esposito|1998|p=34|ps=. &quot;They replaced the conquered countries, indigenous rulers and armies, but preserved much of their government, bureaucracy, and culture. For many in the conquered territories, it was no more than an exchange of masters, one that brought peace to peoples demoralized and disaffected by the casualties and heavy taxation that resulted from the years of Byzantine-Persian warfare. Local communities were free to continue to follow their own way of life in internal, domestic affairs. In many ways, local populations found Muslim rule more flexible and tolerant than that of Byzantium and Persia. Religious communities were free to practice their faith to worship and be governed by their religious leaders and laws in such areas as marriage, divorce, and inheritance. In exchange, they were required to pay tribute, a poll tax (''jizya'') that entitled them to Muslim protection from outside aggression and exempted them from military service. Thus, they were called the &quot;protected ones&quot; (''dhimmi''). In effect, this often meant lower taxes, greater local autonomy, rule by fellow Semites with closer linguistic and cultural ties than the hellenized, Greco-Roman élites of Byzantium, and greater religious freedom for Jews and indigenous Christians.&quot;}} and &quot;generally speaking, Muslim tolerance of unbelievers was far better than anything available in Christendom, until the rise of secularism in the 17th century&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Buntzie Ellis Churchill 2008, pp. 146&quot;&gt;Bernard Lewis and Buntzie Ellis Churchill, ''Islam: The Religion and the People'', Wharton School Publishing, 2008, p. 146.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Muslims guaranteed freedom of worship and livelihood, provided that they remained loyal to the Muslim state and paid a poll tax&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;World &quot; /&gt; &quot;Muslim governments appointed Christian and Jewish professionals to their bureaucracies&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;World &quot; /&gt; and thus, Christians and Jews &quot;contributed to the making of the Islamic civilization&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;World &quot; /&gt;

However, dhimmis faced social and symbolic restrictions,&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis 1984, p. 26&quot;&gt;Lewis (1984), p. 26&lt;/ref&gt; and a pattern of stricter, then more lax, enforcement developed over time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis 1984 pp. 49–51&quot;&gt;Lewis (1984) pp. 49–51.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Marshall Hodgson]], a historian of Islam, writes that during the era of the High Caliphate (7th–13th Centuries), zealous Shariah-minded Muslims gladly elaborated their code of symbolic restrictions on the dhimmis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hodgson p488&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Venture of Islam: The classical age of Islam|author=Marshall G.S. Hodgson|publisher=[[University of Chicago Press]]|year=1977|isbn=978-0226346830|page=448|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=18b-K9AMLlwC&amp;printsec=frontcover|accessdate=7 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From an Islamic legal perspective, the pledge of protection granted dhimmis the freedom to practice their religion and spared them [[forced conversion]]s. The dhimmis also served a variety of useful purposes, mostly economic, which was another point of concern to jurists.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis (1984)&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=December 2015}} Religious minorities were free to do whatever they wished in their own homes, but could not &quot;publicly engage in illicit sex in ways that threaten public morals&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Islam and the Blackamerican: Looking Toward the Third Resurrection|author=Sherman A. Jackson|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2005|isbn=978-0-19-518081-7|page=145|url=https://books.google.com/?id=nprKYM8sleYC&amp;pg=PA144&amp;dq=ankiha+fasida#v=onepage&amp;q|accessdate=10 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In some cases, religious practices that Muslims found repugnant were allowed. One example was the Zoroastrian practice of [[incest]]uous &quot;self-marriage&quot; where a man could marry his mother, sister or daughter. According to the famous Islamic legal scholar Ibn Qayyim Al-Jawziyya (1292–1350), non-Muslims had the right to engage in such religious practices even if it offended Muslims, under the conditions that such cases not be presented to Islamic Sharia courts and that these religious minorities believed that the practice in question is permissible according to their religion. This ruling was based on the precedent that Muhammad did not forbid such self-marriages among Zoroastrians despite coming in contact with them and having knowledge of their practices.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, p. 144&lt;/ref&gt;

The Arabs generally established garrisons outside towns in the conquered territories, and had little interaction with the local dhimmi populations for purposes other than the collection of taxes. The conquered Christian, Jewish, Mazdean and Buddhist communities were otherwise left to lead their lives as before.&lt;ref&gt;Hodgson, ''The Venture of Islam Vol 1'', 1958, pp. 227–229.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Christians===
According to historians Lewis and Stillman, local Christians in Syria, Iraq, and Egypt were [[Non-Chalcedonianism|non-Chalcedonians]] and many may have felt better off under early Muslim rule than under that of the [[Greek Orthodox Church|Byzantine Orthodox]] of [[Constantinople]].&lt;ref name=&quot;conseq&quot; &gt;Lewis (1984), pp. 17–18; Stillman (1979), p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1095, [[Pope Urban II]] urged western European Christians to [[First Crusade|come to the aid]] of the Christians of [[Palestine (region)|Palestine]]. The subsequent [[Crusades]] brought [[Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]] Christians into contact with Orthodox Christians whose beliefs they discovered to differ from their own perhaps more than they had realized, and whose position under the rule of the Muslim [[Fatimid Caliphate]] was less uncomfortable than had been supposed. Consequently, the Eastern Christians provided perhaps less support to the Crusaders than had been expected.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;Courbage and Fargues (1995), pp. 44–46.&lt;/ref&gt; When the Arab East came under Ottoman rule in the 16th century, Christian populations and fortunes rebounded significantly. The Ottomans had long experience dealing with Christian and Jewish minorities, and were more tolerant towards religious minorities than the former Muslim rulers, the [[Mamluk]]s of [[Egypt in the Middle Ages|Egypt]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated5&gt;Courbage and Fargues (1995), pp. 57–58.&lt;/ref&gt;

However, Christians living under Islamic rule have suffered certain legal disadvantages and at times [[Persecution of Christians|persecution]]. In the Ottoman Empire, in accordance with the ''dhimmi'' system implemented in [[Islam|Muslim]] countries, they, like all other Christians and also Jews, were accorded certain freedoms. The dhimmi system in the Ottoman Empire was largely based upon the [[Pact of Umar]]. The client status established the rights of the non-Muslims to property, livelihood and freedom of worship but they were in essence treated as [[second-class citizen]]s in the empire and referred to in Turkish as ''[[Giaour|gavours]]'', a pejorative word meaning &quot;[[infidel]]&quot; or &quot;[[unbeliever]]&quot;. The clause of the Pact of Umar which prohibited non-Muslims from building new places of worship was historically imposed on some communities of the Ottoman Empire and ignored in other cases, at discretion of the local authorities. Although there were no laws mandating religious ghettos, this led to non-Muslim communities being clustered around existing houses of worship.&lt;ref name=&quot;́gostonMasters2010&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=A ́goston|first1=Ga ́bor|last2=Alan Masters|first2=Bruce|title=Encyclopedia of the Ottoman Empire|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=QjzYdCxumFcC&amp;pg=PA185|accessdate=15 April 2016|year=2010|publisher=[[Infobase Publishing]]|isbn=978-1-4381-1025-7|pages=185–6}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Balakian&quot;&gt;{{Cite book | authorlink = Peter Balakian | last = Balakian | first = Peter | title = The Burning Tigris: The Armenian Genocide and America's Response | place = New York | publisher = HarperCollins | year = 2003 | isbn = 978-0-06-019840-4 | pages = [https://archive.org/details/burningtigrisarm00bala/page/25 25, 445] | url = https://archive.org/details/burningtigrisarm00bala/page/25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to other legal limitations, Christians were not considered equals to Muslims and several prohibitions were placed on them. Their testimony against Muslims by Christians and Jews was inadmissible in courts of law wherein a Muslim could be punished; this meant that their testimony could only be considered in commercial cases. They were forbidden to carry weapons or ride atop horses and camels. Their houses could not overlook those of Muslims; and their religious practices were severely circumscribed (e.g., the ringing of church bells was strictly forbidden).&lt;ref name=&quot;́gostonMasters2010&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Akçam&quot;&gt;{{Cite book | first = Taner | last = Akçam | authorlink = Taner Akçam | title = A Shameful Act: The Armenian Genocide and the Question of Turkish Responsibility | place = New York | publisher = Metropolitan Books | year = 2006 | isbn = 978-0-8050-7932-6| title-link = A Shameful Act: The Armenian Genocide and the Question of Turkish Responsibility }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Jews===
Because the early Islamic conquests initially preserved much of the existing administrative machinery and culture, in many territories they amounted to little more than a change of rulers for the subject populations, which &quot;brought peace to peoples demoralized and disaffected by the casualties and heavy taxation that resulted from the years of Byzantine-Persian warfare&quot;.{{sfn|Esposito|1998|p=34|ps=. &quot;They replaced the conquered countries, indigenous rulers and armies, but preserved much of their government, bureaucracy, and culture. For many in the conquered territories, it was no more than an exchange of masters, one that brought peace to peoples demoralized and disaffected by the casualties and heavy taxation that resulted from the years of Byzantine-Persian warfare. Local communities were free to continue to follow their own way of life in internal, domestic affairs. In many ways, local populations found Muslim rule more flexible and tolerant than that of Byzantium and Persia. Religious communities were free to practice their faith to worship and be governed by their religious leaders and laws in such areas as marriage, divorce, and inheritance. In exchange, they were required to pay tribute, a poll tax (''jizya'') that entitled them to Muslim protection from outside aggression and exempted them from military service. Thus, they were called the &quot;protected ones&quot; (''dhimmi''). In effect, this often meant lower taxes, greater local autonomy, rule by fellow Semites with closer linguistic and cultural ties than the hellenized, Greco-Roman élites of Byzantium, and greater religious freedom for Jews and indigenous Christians.&quot;}}

[[María Rosa Menocal]], argues that the Jewish dhimmis living under the caliphate, while allowed fewer rights than Muslims, were still better off than in the Christian parts of Europe. Jews from other parts of Europe made their way to [[al-Andalus]], where in parallel to Christian sects regarded as heretical by Catholic Europe, they were not just tolerated, but where opportunities to practice faith and trade were open without restriction save for the prohibitions on proselytization.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.twbookmark.com/books/52/0316566888/press_release.html|title=The Ornament of the World by María Rosa Menocal|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20051109071705/http://www.twbookmark.com/books/52/0316566888/press_release.html|archivedate=9 November 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Bernard Lewis]] states:

{{Quote|Generally, the Jewish people were allowed to practice their religion and live according to the laws and scriptures of their community. Furthermore, the restrictions to which they were subject were social and symbolic rather than tangible and practical in character. That is to say, these regulations served to define the relationship between the two communities, and not to oppress the Jewish population.&lt;ref name=lewis&gt;Lewis, Bernard W (1984). ''The Jews of Islam''&lt;/ref&gt;|}}

Professor of Jewish medieval history at [[Hebrew University of Jerusalem]], [[Hayim Hillel Ben-Sasson]], notes:

{{Quote|The legal and security situation of the Jews in the Muslim world was generally better than in Christendom, because in the former, Jews were not the sole &quot;infidels&quot;, because in comparison to the Christians, Jews were less dangerous and more loyal to the Muslim regime, and because the rapidity and the territorial scope of the Muslim conquests imposed upon them a reduction in persecution and a granting of better possibility for the survival of members of other faiths in their lands.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=On Jewish History in the Middle Ages|last=Ben-Sasson |first=Haim Hillel |year=1969 |location=Tel Aviv |page=36}} Quoted in Mark R. Cohen's ''Under Crescent and Cross: The Jews in the Middle Ages'', Princeton University Press (1995), pp. xvii–xviii (Cohen's translation).&lt;/ref&gt; |}}

According to the French historian [[Claude Cahen]], Islam has &quot;shown more toleration than Europe towards the Jews who remained in Muslim lands.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |last=Cahen |first=Claude |editor=[[P. J. Bearman]] |editor2=Th. Bianquis |editor3=[[Clifford Edmund Bosworth|C.E. Bosworth]] |editor4=E. van Donzel |editor5=[[W. P. Heinrichs]] |editor6=[[Bernard Lewis|B. Lewis]] |editor7=Ch. Pellat |editor8=[[Joseph Schacht|J. Schacht]] |editor9=J. Burton-Page |editor10=C. Dumont |editor11=V.L. Ménage|encyclopedia=[[Encyclopaedia of Islam]] |title=Dhimma|publisher=Brill Academic Publishers |isbn=978-90-04-07026-4|location=Leiden, Netherlands|pages=227–231}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Comparing the treatment of Jews in the [[Islamic Golden Age|medieval Islamic world]] and [[Middle Ages|medieval Christian Europe]], [[Mark R. Cohen]] notes that, in contrast to Jews in Christian Europe, the &quot;Jews in Islam were well integrated into the economic life of the larger society&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;mark.r.cohen&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first=Mark |last=Cohen |title=Under Crescent and Cross: The Jews in the Middle Ages|publisher=Princeton University Press|year=1995|isbn=978-0-691-01082-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that they were allowed to practice their religion more freely than they could do in Christian Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;mark.r.cohen&quot;/&gt;

According to the scholar Mordechai Zaken, [[tribal chief]]tains (also known as aghas) in tribal Muslim societies such as the Kurdish society in [[Kurdistan]] would tax their Jewish subjects. The Jews were in fact civilians protected by their chieftains in and around their communities; in return they paid part of their harvest as dues, and contributed their skills and services to their patron chieftain.&lt;ref&gt;[[Mordechai Zaken]], ''Jewish Subjects and their tribal chieftains in Kurdistan: A Study in Survival'', Brill: Leiden and Boston, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hindus and Buddhists===
{{Main|Persecution of Hindus}}
By the 10th century, the [[Turkic peoples|Turks]] of [[Central Asia]] had invaded the [[Indic plains]], and brought Islam to Northwestern parts of India.&lt;ref&gt;Hodgson, ''The Venture of Islam Vol 2'', 1961, p. 275.&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of the 12th century, the Muslims advanced quickly into the [[Indo-Gangetic Plain|Ganges Plain]].&lt;ref&gt;Hodgson, ''The Venture of Islam Vol 2'', 1961, p. 276.&lt;/ref&gt; In one decade, a Muslim army led by Turkic slaves consolidated resistance around [[Lahore]] and brought northern India, as far as [[Bengal]], under Muslim rule.&lt;ref&gt;Hodgson, ''The Venture of Islam Vol 2'', 1961, p. 278.&lt;/ref&gt; From these Turkic slaves would come sultans, including the founder of the [[Delhi Sultanate|sultanate of Delhi]]. By the 15th century, major parts of Northern India was ruled by Muslim rulers, mostly descended from invaders. In the 16th century, India came under the influence of the [[Mughal Empire|Mughals]] ([[Mongols]]). [[Babur]], a ruler of the Mongol Timuri empire, established a foothold in the north which paved the way for further expansion by his successors.&lt;ref&gt;MHodgson, ''The Venture of Islam Vol 3'', 1961, pp. 24–25.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the Mughal emperor [[Akbar]] has been described as a universalist, most Mughal emperors were oppressive of native Hindu, Buddhist and later Sikh populations.&lt;ref&gt;Hodgson, ''The Venture of Islam Vol 3'', 1961, pp. 65–67.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Aurangzeb]] specifically was inclined towards a highly fundamentalist approach.&lt;ref&gt;Hodgson, ''The Venture of Islam Vol 3'', 1961, p. 60.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Muslim rulers from Turks to Mughals retained their Islamic identities, and made various attempts at conversion and subjugation of native Hindu populations. Under Muslim rule, vandalism, and outright destruction of temples became a widespread phenomenon. In fact, such was the extent of persecution and genocide that there was a decline in population of India during the years of Muslim conquest. Historian [[K. S. Lal]] in his book ''[[Theory and Practice of Muslim State in India]]'' claims that between the years 1000 AD and 1500 AD, the population of the Indian subcontinent decreased from 200 to 170 million.{{citation needed|date=February 2020}} In ''[[Growth of Muslim Population in Medieval India]]'' meanwhile he claimed that it fell from 200 million to 120 million by establishment of the [[Mughal Empire]] because of killings, deportations, dissemination, wars, and famines. He stated that his estimates were tentative and did not claim any finality.{{citation needed|date=February 2020}} [[Will Durant]] called the Muslim conquest of India &quot;probably the bloodiest story in history&quot;.{{citation needed|date=February 2020}}

==Restrictions==
There were a number of restrictions on dhimmis. In a modern sense the dhimmis would be described as second-class citizens.&lt;ref name=Majid&gt;{{cite book |first=Majid |last=Khadduri |authorlink=Majid Khadduri |year=2010 |title=War and Peace in the Law of Islam |isbn=9781616190484 |pages=196–198}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although ''dhimmis'' were allowed to perform their religious rituals, they were obliged to do so in a manner not conspicuous to Muslims. Display of non-Muslim religious symbols, such as crosses or icons, was prohibited on buildings and on clothing (unless mandated as part of distinctive clothing). Loud prayers were forbidden, as were the ringing of church bells and the blowing of the [[shofar]].&lt;ref&gt;Karsh 29.&lt;/ref&gt; They were also not allowed to build or repair churches without Muslim consent.&lt;ref name=&quot;World &quot; /&gt; Moreover, dhimmis were not allowed to seek converts among Muslims.&lt;ref name=&quot;Griffith&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Church in the Shadow of the Mosque: Christians and Muslims in the World of Islam |publisher=Princeton University Press |author=Sidney H. Griffith |year=2010 |isbn=978-0691146287}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=January 2016}} In the [[Mamluk]] Egypt, where non-Mamluk Muslims were not allowed to ride horses and camels, dhimmis were prohibited even from riding donkeys inside cities.&lt;ref&gt;Stillman (1979), p. 471&lt;/ref&gt; Sometimes, Muslim rulers issued regulations requiring dhimmis to attach distinctive signs to their houses.&lt;ref&gt;Al-Tabari, ''Ta'rikh al-Rusul wa 'l-Muluk'', translated in Stillman (1979), p. 167.&lt;/ref&gt;

Most of the restrictions were social and symbolic in nature,&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis 1984, p. 26&quot;/&gt; and a pattern of stricter, then more lax, enforcement developed over time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis 1984 pp. 49–51&quot;/&gt; The major financial disabilities of the dhimmi were the jizya poll tax and the fact dhimmis and Muslims could not inherit from each other.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis 1984, p. 26&quot;/&gt; That would create an incentive to convert if someone from the family had already converted.&lt;ref name=&quot;World &quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Introducing World Christianity |publisher=Wiley-Blackwell |author=Heather J. Sharkey |year=2012 |isbn=978-1-4443-4454-7 |page=10}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ira M. Lapidus]] states that the &quot;payment of the poll tax seems to have been regular, but other obligations were inconsistently enforced and did not prevent many non-Muslims from being important political, business, and scholarly figures. In the late ninth and early tenth centuries, Jewish bankers and financiers were important at the 'Abbasid court.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lapidus&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| last = Lapidus | first = Ira M. | authorlink=Ira M. Lapidus | title = A History of Islamic societies | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]] |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kFJNBAAAQBAJ| year = 2014|pages=155–6| isbn = 9780521514309 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The jurists and scholars of Islamic sharia law called for humane treatment of the dhimmis.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis (1984), p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Jizya tax===
{{Main|Jizya}}
Payment of the ''jizya'' obligated Muslim authorities to protect dhimmis in civil and military matters. Sura 9 ([[At-Tawba]]), [[At-Tawba 29|verse 29]] stipulates that ''jizya'' be exacted from non-Muslims as a condition required for jihad to cease. Failure to pay the ''jizya'' could result in the pledge of protection of a dhimmi's life and property becoming void, with the dhimmi facing the alternatives of conversion, enslavement, death or imprisonment, as advocated by [[Abu Yusuf]], the chief [[qadi]] (Islamic judge) of [[Abbasid]] caliph [[Harun al-Rashid]] who ruled over much of modern-day [[Iraq]].&lt;ref name=&quot;lewis1415&quot;&gt;Lewis (1984), pp. 14–15.&lt;/ref&gt;

Lewis states there are varying opinions among scholars as to how much of a burden jizya was.&lt;ref name=&quot;lewis1415&quot;/&gt; According to [[Norman Stillman]]: &quot;''jizya'' and ''[[kharaj]]'' were a &quot;crushing burden for the non-Muslim peasantry who eked out a bare living in a subsistence economy.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Stillman (1979), p. 28&lt;/ref&gt; Both agree that ultimately, the additional taxation on non-Muslims was a critical factor that drove many dhimmis to leave their religion and accept Islam.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;Lewis (1984), p. 17–18; Stillman (1979), p. 18&lt;/ref&gt; However, in some regions the jizya on populations was significantly lower than the zakat, meaning dhimmi populations maintained an economic advantage.&lt;ref&gt;Klorman (2007), p. 94&lt;/ref&gt; According to Cohen, taxation, from the perspective of dhimmis who came under Muslim rule, was &quot;a concrete continuation of the taxes paid to earlier regimes&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cahen&quot;/&gt;{{page needed|date=January 2016}} [[Bernard Lewis|Lewis]] observes that the change from Byzantine to Arab rule was welcomed by many among the dhimmis who found the new yoke far lighter than the old, both in taxation and in other matters, and that some, even among the Christians of Syria and Egypt, preferred the rule of Islam to that of Byzantines.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis p57&quot;&gt;Lewis (2002) p. 57&lt;/ref&gt; [[William Montgomery Watt|Montgomery Watt]] states, &quot;the Christians were probably better off as dhimmis under Muslim-Arab rulers than they had been under the Byzantine Greeks.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[William Montgomery Watt]], ''Islamic Political Thought: The Basic Concepts'', p. 51. Quote: &quot;The Christians were probably better off as dhimmis under Muslim-Arab rulers than they had been under the Byzantine Greeks.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; In some places, for example Egypt, the jizya was a [[tax incentive]] for Christians to convert to Islam.&lt;ref name=&quot;World &quot; /&gt;

The importance of dhimmis as a source of revenue for the [[Rashidun Caliphate]] is illustrated in a letter ascribed to Umar I and cited by Abu Yusuf: &quot;if we take dhimmis and share them out, what will be left for the Muslims who come after us? By God, Muslims would not find a man to talk to and profit from his labors.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Lewis (1984), pp. 30–31.&lt;/ref&gt;

Islamic jurists required adult, free, healthy males among the dhimma community to pay the jizya, while exempting women, children, the elderly, slaves, those affected by mental or physical handicaps, and travelers who did not settle in Muslim lands.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |editor-last1 = Mirza|editor-first1 =Mahan |editor2=Gerhard Bowering |editor3=Patricia Crone |display-editors=etal|title = The Princeton encyclopedia of Islamic political thought|date = 2013|publisher = [[Princeton University Press]]|location = Princeton, N.J.|isbn = 978-0691134840|page = 283|quote = Free adult males who were not afflicted by any physical or mental illness were required to pay the ''jizya''. Women, children, handicapped, the mentally ill, the elderly, and slaves were exempt, as were all travelers and foreigners who did not settle in Muslim lands.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Alshech|first1=Eli|title=Islamic Law, Practice, and Legal Doctrine: Exempting the Poor from the ''Jizya'' under the Ayyubids (1171-1250)|date=2003|journal=Islamic Law and Society|volume=10|issue=3|quote=...jurists divided the dhimma community into two major groups. The first group consists of all adult, free, sane males among the dhimma community, while the second includes all other dhimmas (i.e., women, slaves, minors, and the insane). Jurists generally agree that members of the second group are to be granted a &quot;blanket&quot; exemption from ''jizya'' payment.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The early Islamic scholars took a relatively humane and practical attitude towards the collection of ''jizya'', compared to the 11th century commentators writing when Islam was under threat both at home and abroad.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis 1984 p. 15&quot;&gt;Lewis (1984), p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;

The jurist Abu Yusuf, the chief judge of the caliph [[Harun al-Rashid]], rules as follows regarding the manner of collecting the jizya &lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis 1984 p. 15&quot; /&gt;

{{Quote|No one of the people of the dhimma should be beaten in order to exact payment of the jizya, nor made to stand in the hot sun, nor should hateful things be inflicted upon their bodies, or anything of that sort. Rather they should be treated with leniency.}}

In the border provinces, dhimmis were sometimes recruited for military operations. In such cases, they were exempted from jizya for the year of service.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Djizya (i)&quot;, ''[[Encyclopaedia of Islam]]'' Online&lt;/ref&gt;

===Administration of law===
Religious pluralism existed in medieval Islamic law and [[Islamic ethics|ethics]]. The religious laws and courts of other religions, including Christianity, Judaism and Hinduism, were usually accommodated within the Islamic legal framework, as exemplified in the [[Caliphate]], [[Al-Andalus]], [[Ottoman Empire]] and Indian subcontinent.&lt;ref name=&quot;Weeramantry-138&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Weeramantry|first=Judge Christopher G.|title=Justice Without Frontiers: Furthering Human Rights|year=1997|publisher=[[Brill Publishers]]|isbn=978-90-411-0241-6|page=138}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Islamic Roots of Democratic Pluralism|first=Abdulaziz Abdulhussein|last=Sachedina|year=2001|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-513991-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; In medieval Islamic societies, the qadi (Islamic judge) usually could not interfere in the matters of non-Muslims unless the parties voluntarily chose to be judged according to Islamic law. The dhimmi communities living in Islamic states usually had their own laws independent from the Sharia law, such as the Jews who had their own Halakha courts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Under Crescent and Cross: The Jews in the Middle Ages|author=Mark R. Cohen|publisher=[[Princeton University Press]]|year=1995|isbn=978-0-691-01082-3|page=74|url=https://books.google.com/?id=fgbib5exskUC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=cohen+Under+Crescent+and+Cross&amp;q|accessdate=10 April 2010|author-link=Mark R. Cohen}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dhimmis were allowed to operate their own courts following their own legal systems. However, dhimmis frequently attended the Muslim courts in order to record property and business transactions within their own communities. Cases were taken out against Muslims, against other dhimmis and even against members of the dhimmi's own family. Dhimmis often took cases relating to marriage, divorce or inheritance to the Muslim courts so these cases would be decided under sharia law. Oaths sworn by dhimmis in the Muslim courts were sometimes the same as the oaths taken by Muslims, sometimes tailored to the dhimmis' beliefs.&lt;ref name=&quot;al-Qattan-99 2&quot;&gt;al-Qattan (1999)&lt;/ref&gt;

Muslim men could generally marry dhimmi women who are considered People of the Book, however Islamic jurists rejected the possibility any non-Muslim man might marry a Muslim woman.&lt;ref&gt;Al-Mawardi (2000), p. 161; Friedmann (2003), p. 161; Lewis (1984), p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt; Bernard Lewis notes that &quot;similar position existed under the laws of Byzantine Empire, according to which a Christian could marry a Jewish woman, but a Jew could not marry a Christian woman under pain of death&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis 1984, p. 27&quot;/&gt;

==Relevant texts==

===Quranic verses as a basis for Islamic policies toward dhimmis===
Lewis states
* The phrase &quot;Let there be no compulsion in religion: ...&quot;, from ''[[sura]]'' 2 ([[Al-Baqara]]), ''[[ayah]]'' 256,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite quran|2|256|s=ns}}&lt;/ref&gt; has sometimes been interpreted in the Islamic legal and theological traditions to mean followers of other religions should not be forced to adopt Islam &lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis14&quot;&gt;Lewis (1984) p. 13&lt;/ref&gt; 
* The phrase &quot;Unto you your religion, and unto me my religion.&quot;, from sura 109 ([[Al-Kafirun]]), ayah 6,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite quran|109|6|s=ns}}&lt;/ref&gt; has been used as a &quot;proof-text for pluralism and coexistence&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis14&quot; /&gt;
* Sura 2 (Al-Baqara), ayah 62&lt;ref&gt;{{cite quran|2|62|s=ns}}&lt;/ref&gt; has served to justify the tolerated position accorded to the followers of [[Christianity]], [[Judaism]], and [[Sabianism]] under Muslim rule.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis14&quot; /&gt;

===Hadith===

A hadith by Muhammad, &quot;Whoever killed a ''Mu'ahid'' (a person who is granted the pledge of protection by the Muslims) shall not smell the fragrance of Paradise though its fragrance can be smelt at a distance of forty years (of traveling).&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{Hadith-usc|bukhari|usc=yes|9|83|49}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tahir-ul-Qadri1&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first1=Muhammad|last1=Tahir-ul-Qadri|authorlink=Muhammad Tahir-ul-Qadri|date=2011|title=Fatwa on Terrorism and Suicide Bombings|page=99|publisher=[[Minhaj-ul-Quran UK|London: Minhaj-ul-Quran]]|isbn=978-0-9551888-9-3|title-link=Fatwa on Terrorism}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first1=Yaser|last1=Ellethy|date=2014|title=Islam, Context, Pluralism and Democracy: Classical and Modern Interpretations ''(Islamic Studies Series)''|publisher=[[Routledge]]|isbn=978-1138800304|pages=124–5}}&lt;/ref&gt;  is considered to be a foundation for the protection of the People of the Book in Muslim ruled countries.{{citation needed|date=June 2018}} Anwar Shah Kashmiri writes in his commentary on [[Sahih al-Bukhari]] ''Fayd al-Bari'' on this hadith: &quot;You know the gravity of sin for killing a Muslim, for its odiousness has reached the point of disbelief, and it necessitates that [the killer abides in Hell] forever. As for killing a non-Muslim citizen [mu'ahid], it is similarly no small matter, for the one who does it will not smell the fragrance of Paradise.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tahir-ul-Qadri1&quot;/&gt;

A similar hadith in regard to the status of the dhimmis: &quot;Whoever wrongs one with whom a compact (treaty) has been made ''[i.e., a dhimmi]'' and lays on him a burden beyond his strength, I will be his accuser.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Majid Khadduri: ''War and Peace in the Law of Islam'', p. 175&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = al-Zuḥaylī | first = Wahbah | authorlink = Wahbah al-Zuhayli | title = ʾĀthar al-ḥarb fī l-fiqh al-Islāmī : dirāsah muqārinah | publisher = Dār al-Fikr | location = [[Damascus]] | year = 1998 | isbn = 978-1-57547-453-3 | page = 708 }} Quote: «» Translation:&lt;/ref&gt;

===Constitution of Medina===

The [[Constitution of Medina]], a formal agreement between Muhammad and all the significant tribes and families of Medina (including Muslims, Jews and pagans), declared that non-Muslims in the [[Ummah]] had the following rights:&lt;ref&gt;Ahmed (1979), pp. 46–7.&lt;/ref&gt;
# The security (''dhimma'') of God is equal for all groups,&lt;ref&gt;Article 15, as quoted in Ahmed (1979), pp. 46–47.&lt;/ref&gt;
# Non-Muslim members have equal political and cultural rights as Muslims. They will have autonomy and freedom of religion.&lt;ref&gt;Article 25, as quoted in Ahmed (1979), pp. 46–47.&lt;/ref&gt;
# Non-Muslims will take up arms against the enemy of the [[Ummah]] and share the cost of war. There is to be no treachery between the two.&lt;ref&gt;Article 37, as quoted in Ahmed (1979), pp. 46–47.&lt;/ref&gt;
# Non-Muslims will not be obliged to take part in religious wars of the Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;Article 45, as quoted in Ahmed (1979), pp. 46–47.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Khaybar agreement===

A precedent for the dhimma contract was established with the agreement between Muhammad and the Jews after the [[Battle of Khaybar]], an oasis near [[Medina]]. [[Khaybar]] was the first territory attacked and conquered by Muslims. When the Jews of Khaybar surrendered to Muhammad after a siege, Muhammad allowed them to remain in Khaybar in return for handing over to the Muslims one half their annual produce.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis&quot;&gt;Lewis (1984), pp. 10–11&lt;/ref&gt;

===Pact of Umar===
{{Main|Pact of Umar}}
The [[Pact of Umar]], traditionally believed to be between caliph [[Umar]] and the conquered Jerusalem Christians in the seventh century, was another source of regulations pertaining to dhimmis. However, Western [[orientalism|orientalists]] doubt the authenticity of the pact, arguing it is usually the victors and not the vanquished who impose rather than propose, the terms of peace, and that it is highly unlikely that the people who spoke no Arabic and knew nothing of Islam could draft such a document. Academic historians believe the Pact of Umar in the form it is known today was a product of later jurists who attributed it to Umar in order to lend greater authority to their own opinions. The similarities between the Pact of Umar and the [[Theodosian dynasty|Theodosian]] and [[Corpus Juris Civilis|Justinian Codes]] of the [[Byzantine Empire|Eastern Roman Empire]] suggest that perhaps much of the Pact of Umar was borrowed from these earlier codes by later Islamic jurists. At least some of the clauses of the pact mirror the measures first introduced by the [[Umayyad Caliphate|Umayyad]] caliph [[Umar II]] or by the early [[Abbasid Caliphate|Abbasid]] caliphs.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis (1984), pp. 24–25.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cultural interactions and cultural differences==
During the Middle Ages, local associations known as ''[[futuwwa]]'' clubs developed across the Islamic lands. There were usually several futuwwah in each town. These clubs catered to varying interests, primarily sports, and might involve distinctive manners of dress and custom. They were known for their hospitality, idealism and loyalty to the group. They often had a militaristic aspect, purportedly for the mutual protection of the membership. These clubs commonly crossed social strata, including among their membership local notables, dhimmi and slaves – to the exclusion of those associated with the local ruler, or [[Emir|amir]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Marshall Hodgson]], ''[[The Venture of Islam]] Conscience and History in a World Civilization Vol 2''. [[The University of Chicago]], 1961, pp. 126–127.&lt;/ref&gt;

Muslims and Jews were sometimes partners in trade, with the Muslim taking days off on Fridays and Jews taking off on Saturdays.&lt;ref&gt;[[Marshall Hodgson]], ''[[The Venture of Islam]] Conscience and History in a World Civilization Vol. 1''. [[The University of Chicago]], 1961, p. 302.&lt;/ref&gt;

Andrew Wheatcroft describes how some social customs such as different conceptions of dirt and cleanliness made it difficult for the religious communities to live close to each other, either under Muslim or under Christian rule.&lt;ref&gt;Wheatcroft (2003) p. 73.&lt;/ref&gt;

== In modern times ==

The dhimma and the jizya poll tax are no longer imposed in Muslim majority countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;El Fadl&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=iwt738&gt;{{cite book|title=Islam in the World Today|date=2010|publisher=Cornell University Press|isbn=978-0801445712|page=738|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-dM4hPlxMw8C&amp;pg=PA738|author=Werner Ende|author2=Udo Steinbach }}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 21st century, jizya is widely regarded as being at odds with contemporary secular conceptions of citizen's civil rights and equality before the law, although there have been occasional reports of religious minorities in conflict zones and areas subject to political instability being forced to pay jizya.&lt;ref name=&quot;ipt-p283&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=The Princeton Encyclopedia of Islamic Political Thought|date=2012|publisher=Princeton University Press|isbn=978-0691134840|pages=283–284|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=q1I0pcrFFSUC&amp;pg=PA283|author=Matthew Long (jizya entry author)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009 it was claimed that a group of militants that referred to themselves as the [[Taliban]] imposed the ''jizya'' on Pakistan's minority [[Sikhs in Pakistan|Sikh community]] after occupying some of their homes and kidnapping a Sikh leader.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tribuneindia.com/2009/20090417/world.htm#6|title=The Tribune, Chandigarh, India - World|website=www.tribuneindia.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As late as 2013, in Egypt ''jizya'' was reportedly being imposed by the Muslim Brotherhood on 15,000 Christian Copts of Dalga village.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2013/sep/10/egypts-muslim-brotherhood-convert-islam-or-pay-jiz/|title=Egypt's Muslim Brotherhood to Coptic Christians: Convert to Islam, or pay 'jizya' tax|first=The Washington Times|last=http://www.washingtontimes.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aina.org/news/20130913143703.htm|title=Two Christians Murdered in Egypt for Refusing to Pay Jizya to Muslims|website=www.aina.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2014, the [[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant]] (ISIL) announced that it intended to extract jizya from Christians in the city of [[Raqqa]], Syria, which it controlled at the time. Christians who refused to accept the dhimma contract and pay the tax were to have to either convert to Islam, leave or be executed. Wealthy Christians would have to pay half an ounce of gold, the equivalent of [[United States dollar|$]]664 twice a year; middle-class Christians were to have to pay half that amount and poorer ones were to be charged one-fourth that amount.&lt;ref name=&quot;raqqa&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://world.time.com/2014/02/28/al-qaeda-in-syria-extorts-christians/|title=Al-Qaeda Rebels in Syria Tell Christians to Pay Up or Die|journal=Time|last1=Baker|first1=Aryn}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June, 2014 the [[Institute for the Study of War]] reported that ISIL claims to have collected jizya and fay.&lt;ref name=&quot;ISWJune30&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Caris|first1=Charlie|title=The Islamic State Announces Caliphate|url=http://iswiraq.blogspot.co.uk/2014/06/the-islamic-state-announces-caliphate.html|publisher=Institute for the Study of War|accessdate=1 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 18 July 2014 the ISIL ordered the Christians in [[Mosul]] to accept the dhimma contract and pay the Jizya or convert to Islam. If they refused to accept either of the options they would be killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-middle-east-28381455 |title=Iraqi Christians flee after Isis issue Mosul ultimatum |date=18 July 2014 |publisher=BBC |accessdate=30 December 2014 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140724045752/http://www.bbc.com/news/world-middle-east-28381455 |archivedate=24 July 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Islam}}
* [[Ger toshav]], in Judaism, a non-Jewish resident alien of a theocratic Jewish state
* [[Millet (Ottoman Empire)]]
* [[Gentile]]
* [[Dhimmitude]], a derogatory political term for the status of dhimmis
* [[Persecution of Christians]]
* [[Persecution of Jews]]
* [[Persecution of Buddhists]]
* [[Persecution of Hindus]]
* [[Persecution of Sikhs]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{Refbegin|30em}}
* {{cite book|last=Ahmad |first=Barakat |authorlink=Barakat Ahmad |year=1979 |title=Muhammad and the Jews |publisher=Vikas Publishing House}}
* {{cite journal|last=Al-Hibri|first=Azizah Y.|year=2003|title=An Islamic Perspective on Domestic Violence|journal=27 Fordham International Law Journal 195}}
* {{Cite journal|first = Muhammad| last=Abdel-Haleem|authorlink=Muhammad Abdel-Haleem |title = The jizya Verse (Q. 9:29): Tax Enforcement on Non-Muslims in the First Muslim State|journal = Journal of Qur'anic Studies|date = 2012|issn = 1465-3591|volume = 14|issue = 2| pages=72–89|doi = 10.3366/jqs.2012.0056|ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal|last=Bravmann |first=Meïr M. |year=1966 |title=The ancient background of the Qur'ānic Concept Al-Ğizyatu 'an Yadin |journal=Arabica |volume=13 |doi=10.1163/157005866X00525 |page=307|issue=3}}
* Bosworth, C. E. (1982). ''The Concept of Dhimma in Early Islam'' In Benjamin Braude and B. Lewis, eds., ''Christians and Jews in the Ottoman Empire: The Functioning of a Plural Society'' 2 vols., New York: Holmes &amp; Meier Publishing. {{ISBN|0-8419-0520-7}}
* {{cite encyclopedia |last=Cahen |first=Claude |editor=P.J. Bearman |editor2=Th. Bianquis |editor3=[[Clifford Edmund Bosworth|C.E. Bosworth]] |editor4=E. van Donzel |editor5= W.P. Heinrichs |encyclopedia=[[Encyclopaedia of Islam]] Online|title=Djizya (i)|publisher=Brill Academic Publishers |issn=1573-3912}}
* {{cite journal|last=Klorman |first=Bat-Zion Eraqi |date=Fall 2007 |title=Muslim Society as an Alternative: Jews Converting to Islam |journal=Jewish Social Studies: History, Culture, Society |volume=14 |issue= 1}}
* {{cite book|first=Mark |last=Cohen |title=Under Crescent and Cross: The Jews in the Middle Ages|publisher=Princeton University Press|year=1995|isbn=978-0-691-01082-3}}
* {{cite book|author1=Courbage, Youssef  |author2=Fargues, Philippe|title=Christians and Jews under Islam |publisher=I.B. Tauris Publishers |location=London |year=1995 |isbn=978-1-86064-285-2}}
* {{cite book|author=Friedmann, Yohanan |title=Tolerance and Coercion in Islam: Interfaith Relations in the Muslim Tradition |publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=2003 |isbn=978-0-521-82703-4|author-link=Yohanan Friedmann }}
* {{cite book|first=Hugh |last=Goddard |title=A History of Christian-Muslim Relations |location=Chicago |publisher=New Amsterdam Books |year=2000 |isbn=978-1-56663-340-6}}
* {{cite book|editor-first=Bat-Zion |editor-last=Eraqi-Klorman |authorlink= |editor2=Reeva Spector Simon |editor3=Michael Menachem Laskier |display-editors = 3 |editor4=Sara Reguer |title=The Jews of the Middle East and North Africa in Modern Times |publisher=Columbia University Press |location=Columbia, NY |year=2003 |isbn=978-0-231-10796-9}}
* {{cite book |last=Karsh |first=Ephraim |title=Islamic Imperialism: A History |publisher=Yale University Press |year=2006 |isbn=978-0-300-10603-9 |url=https://archive.org/details/islamicimperiali00kars }}
* {{cite book|last=Lapidus |first=Ira M. |title=A History of Islamic Societies (2nd Edition)|publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=2002 |isbn=978-0-521-77933-3}}
* {{cite book |first=Bernard |last=Lewis |authorlink=Bernard Lewis |title=The Arabs in History |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford |year=2002 |isbn=978-0-19-280310-8 |url=https://archive.org/details/arabsinhistory00bern }}
* {{cite book|first=Bernard |last=Lewis |title=The Jews of Islam |publisher=Princeton University Press |location=Princeton |year=1984 |isbn=978-0-691-00807-3|title-link=The Jews of Islam }}
* {{cite book | last=Esposito | first=John L. | authorlink= John Esposito | date=1998 | title=Islam: The Straight Path | publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] | isbn=978-0-19-511233-7 | ref=harv| title-link=Islam: The Straight Path }}
* {{cite journal|last=Littman |first=David |authorlink=David Littman (historian) |year=1979 |title=Jews Under Muslim Rule: The Case Of Persia |journal=The Wiener Library Bulletin |volume=XXXII|issue=New series 49/50}}
* {{cite book|author=Al-Mawardi |title=The Ordnances of Government (''Al-Ahkam al-Sultaniyya w'al-Wilayat al-Diniyya'') |publisher=Garnet Publishing |location=Lebanon |year=2000 |isbn=978-1-85964-140-8|author-link=Al-Mawardi }}
* {{cite book|first=Tudor |last=Parfitt |authorlink=Tudor Parfitt |title=Israel and Ishmael : Studies in Muslim-Jewish Relations |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |year=2000 |isbn=978-0-312-22228-4}}
* {{cite book|first=Samantha|last=Power |title=A Problem from Hell: America and the Age of Genocide |publisher=Harper Perennial |location=New York |year=2002 |isbn=978-0-06-054164-4|title-link=A Problem from Hell: America and the Age of Genocide }}
* {{cite journal|first=Najwa |last= al-Qattan |title=Dhimmis in the Muslim Court: Legal Autonomy and Religious Discrimination |journal=International Journal of Middle East Studies |volume=31 |issue=3 |pages=429–444 |year=1999|issn=0020-7438|doi=10.1017/S0020743800055501}}
* {{Cite book|title = War and Peace in Islam: The Uses and Abuses of Jihad|last = [[Prince Ghazi bin Muhammad|H.R.H. Prince]]|first = [[Prince Ghazi bin Muhammad|Ghazi Muhammad]]|publisher = The Islamic Texts Society Cambridge|year = 2013|isbn = 978-1-903682-83-8|last2 = Ibrahim|first2 = Kalin|last3 = [[Mohammad Hashim Kamali|Mohammad Hashim]]|first3 = [[Mohammad Hashim Kamali|Kamali]]|url = http://rissc.jo/books/War-Peace-Islam.pdf | ref=CITEREFGhaziKalinKamali2013}}
* {{cite book|first=Norman |last=Stillman |title=The Jews of Arab Lands: A History and Source Book |url=https://archive.org/details/jewsofarablands00stil |url-access=registration |publisher=Jewish Publication Society of America |location=Philadelphia |year=1979 |isbn=978-1-82760-198-4}}
* {{cite book|first=Arthur S. |last=Tritton |authorlink=Arthur Stanley Tritton|title=The Caliphs and their non-Muslim Subjects: a Critical Study of the Covenant of Umar |publisher=Humphrey Milford/Oxford University Press |location=London |year=1930 }}
* {{cite encyclopedia |last=Viré|first=F |editor=P.J. Bearman |editor2=Th. Bianquis |editor3=[[Clifford Edmund Bosworth|C.E. Bosworth]] |editor4=E. van Donzel |editor5=W.P. Heinrichs |encyclopedia=[[Encyclopaedia of Islam]] Online|title=Kird |publisher=Brill Academic Publishers |issn=1573-3912}}
* {{cite book|last=Waines |first=David |title=An Introduction to Islam |publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=2003 |isbn=978-0-521-53906-7}}
* {{cite book|first=Hans |last=Wehr |title=A Dictionary of Modern Written Arabic |editor=J. Milton Cowan |publisher=Spoken Language Services, Inc. |location=Ithaca, New York |year=1976 |isbn=978-0-87950-001-6}}
* {{cite book|first=Andrew |last=Wheatcroft |title=Infidels: A History of the Conflict between Christendom and Islam |publisher=Penguin Books |year=2003|isbn=978-0-14-025738-0}}
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin|30em}}
* Nabil Luka Babawi: ''Les droits et les devoirs des chrétiens dans l'état islamique et leurs conséquences sur la sécurité nationale'', thèse de doctorat.
* {{cite book | first=Karl | last=Binswanger |title=Untersuchungen zum Status der Nichtmuslime im Osmanischen Reich des 16. Jahrhunderts | journal= Diss. Phil.| language=german| location= München|date= 1977| isbn=978-3-87828-108-5 }}
* {{cite book|first=Jamsheed |last=Choksy |title=Conflict and Cooperation: Zoroastrian Subalterns and Muslim Elites in Medieval Iranian Society |location=New York |year=1997}}
* Mark. R. Cohen: ''Under Crescent and Cross: The Jews in the Middle Ages.'' Princeton University Press, 1994.
* {{cite book|first=Antoine |last=Fattal |title=Le statut légal des non-musulmans en pays d'Islam| language=French |location=Beirut |year=1958}}
* [[Maribel Fierro]] and [[John V. Tolan|John Tolan]], eds, ''The legal status of ḏimmī-s in the Islamic West (second/eighth-ninth/fifteenth centuries)'' (Turnhoult, 2013).
* {{cite journal | first=Yohanan | last=Friedmann | title=Classification of Unbelievers in Sunnī Muslim Law and Tradition | journal=Jerusalem Studies in Arabic and Islam | issue= 22 |date=1998 |ref= pp.&amp;nbsp;163–195 }}
* {{cite book|author=Goitein, S. D. |authorlink=Shelomo Dov Goitein|title=The Mediterranean Society: The Jewish Communities of the Arab World as Portrayed in the Documents of the Cairo Geniza (4 vols.) |location=Berkeley and Los Angeles |year=1967–71}}
* {{cite book |first=Martin |last=Gilbert |authorlink=Martin Gilbert |title=In Ishmael's house: a History of Jews in Muslim Lands|publisher=Yale University Press|location=New Haven, Conn.|year=2010|isbn=978-0300167153}}
* Nicola Melis, &quot;Il concetto di ğihād&quot;, in P. Manduchi (a cura di), ''Dalla penna al mouse. Gli strumenti di diffusione del concetto di ğihād'', Angeli, Milano 2006, pp.&amp;nbsp;23–54.
* Nicola Melis, &quot;Lo statuto giuridico degli ebrei dell'Impero Ottomano&quot;, in M. Contu – N. Melis – G. Pinna (a cura di), ''Ebraismo e rapporti con le culture del Mediterraneo nei secoli XVIII–XX'', Giuntina, Firenze 2003.
* Nicola Melis, ''Trattato sulla guerra. Il Kitāb al-ğihād di Molla Hüsrev'', Aipsa, Cagliari 2002.
* Mohammad Amin Al-Midani: &quot;La question des minorités et le statut des non-musulmans en Islam.&quot; In: ''La religion est-elle un obstacle à l'application des droits de l'homme?.'' colloque tenu les 10–11 décembre 2004 à Lyon.
* M. Levy-Rubin: &quot;Shurut 'Umar and its alternatives: the legal debate on the status of the dhimmis.&quot; In: ''Jerusalem Studies in Arabic and Islam.'' 30/2005
* Pessah Shinar: &quot;Some remarks regarding the colours of male Jewish dress in North Africa and their Arabic-Islamic context.&quot; In: ''[[Jerusalem Studies in Arabic and Islam]].'' 24/2000, pp.&amp;nbsp;380–395
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
* [http://libro.uca.edu/ics/ics5.htm Islamic and Christian Spain in the early Middle Ages. Thomas F. Glick: Chapter 5: Ethnic relations]
* [http://www.guidedones.com/metapage/non_muslims/Qislamtol10.htm Islam and its tolerance level]
* [http://www.archons.org/pdf/issues/DHIMMI.pdf Islamic Teaching On Dhimmi Status Creates An Atmosphere Of Intolerance] from the [http://www.archons.org/issues/religious_freedom/packet.asp Religious Freedom Packet] of the [http://www.archons.org/ Order of Saint Andrew the Apostle]
* [http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/med/lewis1.html Bernard Lewis, ''Race and Slavery in the Middle East'']
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20140724210233/http://www.centerforinquiry.net/isis/islamic_viewpoints/jihad_the_arab_conquests_and_the_position_of_non_muslim_subjects/ Jihad, the Arab Conquests and the Position of Non-Muslim Subjects]

{{Characters and names in the Quran}}
{{Islam topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Religious slurs}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Islam and other religions]]
[[Category:Islamic terminology]]
[[Category:Arabic words and phrases in Sharia]]
[[Category:Religion and politics]]
[[Category:Religious discrimination]]
[[Category:Politics of the Ottoman Empire]]
[[Category:Social history]]</text>
      <sha1>ojxzfp9l544336kh1zfndztf3loz7cy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
