  <page>
    <title>Drop kick</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9051</id>
    <revision>
      <id>930728120</id>
      <parentid>930727754</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-14T14:26:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Frank Anchor</username>
        <id>4659544</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* NFL */  add some context to the Ravens-Chiefs play</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{distinguish|Dropkick}}
A '''drop kick''' is a type of [[Kick (football)|kick]] in various codes of [[football]]. It involves a player dropping the ball and then [[kick (football)|kicking]] it after it bounces off the ground.

Drop kicks are most importantly used as a method of restarting play and scoring points in [[rugby union]] and [[rugby league]]. Also, [[Association football]] [[goalkeeper (association football)|goalkeepers]] often return the ball to play with drop kicks. The kick was once in wide use in both [[Australian rules football]] and [[gridiron football]], but is today rarely seen in either sport.{{citation needed|date=March 2017}}

== Rugby ==
[[File:Pat O'Dea.jpg|thumb|180px|[[Pat O'Dea]]]]

=== Drop kick technique ===
{{See also|Drop goal}}

The drop kick technique in rugby codes is usually to hold the ball with one end pointing downwards in two hands above the kicking leg. The ball is dropped onto the ground in front of the kicking foot, which makes contact at the moment or fractionally after the ball touches the ground, called the ''half-volley''. The kicking foot usually makes contact with the ball slightly on the instep.&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.is/20070623215626/http://www.coachingrugby.com/rugby/coaching/indskills/kicking/drop.htm &quot;Kicking: The Drop Kick&quot;] at www.coachingrugby.com. Retrieved 11 October 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

In a rugby union kick-off, or drop out, the kicker usually aims to kick the ball high but not a great distance, and so usually strikes the ball after it has started to bounce off the ground, so the contact is made close to the bottom of the ball.

=== Rugby league ===
In [[rugby league]], drop kicks are mandatory to restart play from the goal line (called a goal line drop-out) after the defending team is tackled or knocks on in the in-goal area or the defending team causes the ball to go dead or into [[Glossary of rugby league terms#touch in-goal|touch-in-goal]]. Drop kicks are also mandatory to restart play from the 20 metre line after an unsuccessful penalty goal attempt goes dead or into touch-in-goal and to score a [[drop goal]] (sometimes known as a field goal) in open play, which is worth one point.&lt;ref name=&quot;league&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|url=http://www.rlef.eu.com/rugby_laws_book2004.pdf
|title=The International Laws of the Game and Notes on the Laws
|chapter=Section 6: Scoring
|date=2004-03-11
|publisher=[[Rugby League International Federation]]
|format=PDF
|accessdate=2007-09-12
|page=14
|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070919201722/http://www.rlef.eu.com/rugby_laws_book2004.pdf
|archive-date=2007-09-19
|url-status=dead
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Drop kicks are optional for a penalty kick to score a penalty goal (this being done rarely, as place kicks are generally used) and when kicking for touch (the sideline) from a penalty, although the option of a punt kick is usually taken instead.

=== Rugby union ===
In [[rugby union]], a drop kick is used for the kick-off and restarts and to score a [[drop goal]] (sometimes called a field goal). Originally, it was one of only two ways to score points, along with the [[place kick]].

Drop kicks are mandatory from the centre spot to start a half (a kick-off), from the centre spot to restart the game after points have been scored, to restart play from the 22-metre line (called a drop-out) after the ball is touched down or made dead in the in-goal area by the defending team when the attacking team kicked or took the ball into the in-goal area, and to score a drop goal (sometimes called a field goal) in open play, which is worth three points.&lt;ref name=&quot;union&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 |url         = http://www.irb.com/mm/Document/LawsRegs/0/070110LGLAW09red_662.pdf
 |title       = Law 9: Method of Scoring
 |work        = Laws of the Game
 |publisher   = International Rugby Board
 |format      = PDF
 |year        = 2007
 |accessdate  = 2007-09-12
 |url-status     = dead
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20071022213228/http://www.irb.com/mm/Document/LawsRegs/0/070110LGLAW09red_662.pdf
 |archivedate = 2007-10-22
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Drop kicks are optional for a conversion kick after a try has been scored.

=== Rugby sevens ===
The usage of drop kicks in rugby sevens is the same as in rugby union, except that drop kicks are used for all conversion attempts and for penalty kicks, both of which must be taken within 40 seconds of the try being scored or the award of the penalty.{{citation needed|date=March 2017}}

== American and Canadian (gridiron) football ==
In both [[American football|American]] and [[Canadian football]], one method of scoring a [[Field goal (football)|field goal]] or [[extra point]] is by drop-kicking the football through the goal.

[[File:Zach Curlin.png|thumb|left|130px|[[Zach Curlin]] drop kicking.]]

It contrasts with the [[Punt (gridiron football)|punt]], wherein the player kicks the ball without letting it hit the ground first; and the [[place kick]], wherein the player kicks a stationary ball off the ground: &quot;from placement&quot;. A drop kick is significantly more difficult; as [[Jim Thorpe]] once explained, &quot;I regard the place kick as almost two to one safer than the drop kick in attempting a goal from the field.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.newspapers.com/clip/2874126/the_ogden_standardexaminer/|author=[[Billy Evans]]|date=December 3, 1926|page=19|accessdate=July 24, 2015|via=[[Newspapers.com]]|work=The Ogden Standard-Examiner|title=Place Kick Is best Method For Point}} {{Open access}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Brickleydropkick.png|thumb|250px|Brickley's drop kick to defeat Dartmouth in 1912.]]

The drop kick was often used in early football as a [[trick play|surprise tactic]]. The ball would be [[Snap (football)|snapped]] or [[Lateral pass|lateraled]] to a back, who would fake a run or pass, but then would kick the field goal instead. This method of scoring worked well in the 1920s and early 1930s, when the football was rounder at the ends (similar to a modern rugby ball). Early football stars such as [[Charles Brickley]], [[Frank Hudson (American football)|Frank Hudson]], [[Jim Thorpe]], [[Paddy Driscoll]], and [[Al Bloodgood]] were skilled drop-kickers; Driscoll in 1925 and Bloodgood in 1926 hold a tied NFL record of four drop kicked field goals in a single game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.profootballhof.com/hof/release.jsp?release_id=1481 |title=Release » The last dropkick |publisher=Profootballhof.com |date= |accessdate=2013-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Driscoll's 55 yard drop kick in 1924 stood as the unofficial record for [[field goal range]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.profootballresearchers.org/Coffin_Corner/01-07-011.pdf |title=The Coffin Corner : Vol. No. 7 (1979) – A Closer Look: 50-yd DKs |publisher=Profootballresearchers.org |accessdate=2013-10-02 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131004232951/http://www.profootballresearchers.org/Coffin_Corner/01-07-011.pdf |archivedate=2013-10-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt; until [[Bert Rechichar]] kicked a 56-yard field goal (by placekick) in 1953.

In 1934, the ball was made more pointed at the ends. The creation of the pointed football is generally credited to [[Shorty Ray]], at the time a college football official and later the NFL's head of officiating.&lt;ref name=BS&gt;{{cite news|title=Pro Football To Honor Ray: Rules Advisor's Ideas Gave Game Needed Boost|author=Seymour Smith|newspaper=The Sun (Baltimore)|date=September 14, 1966|page=C4|url=https://www.newspapers.com/clip/7676652/pro_football_to_honor_ray/}}&lt;/ref&gt; This made passing the ball easier, as was its intent, but made the drop kick obsolete, as the more pointed ball did not bounce up from the ground reliably. The drop kick was supplanted by the place kick, which cannot be attempted out of a formation generally used as a running or passing set. The drop kick remains in the rules, but is seldom seen, and rarely effective when attempted.
{{citation needed|date=March 2017}}
In Canadian football the drop kick can be taken from any point on the field, unlike placekicks which must be attempted behind the line of scrimmage.

=== NFL ===
Before the [[NFL–AFL merger]], the last successful drop kick in the NFL was executed by [[Scooter McLean]] of the [[Chicago Bears]] in their 37–9 victory over the [[New York Giants]] on December 21, 1941, in the [[NFL Championship Game, 1941|NFL Championship]] game at Chicago's [[Wrigley Field]]. Though it was not part of the NFL at the time, the [[All-America Football Conference]] saw its last drop kick November 28, 1948, when [[Joe Vetrano]] of the [[San Francisco 49ers]] drop kicked an extra point after a muffed snap against the [[Cleveland Browns]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.boston.com/sports/football/patriots/articles/2006/01/29/a_get_rich_kick_scheme_fails/?rss_id=Boston.com+--+New+England+Patriots+news | work=The Boston Globe | title=A get-rich kick scheme fails | date=January 29, 2006 | first1=Ron | last1=Borges}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Eddie Mahan.jpg|thumb|180px|[[Eddie Mahan]] preparing to drop kick.]]
To date, the only successful drop kick in the NFL since the 1940s was by [[Doug Flutie]], the backup [[quarterback]] of the [[New England Patriots]], against the [[Miami Dolphins]] on January 1, 2006, for an [[extra point]] after a touchdown. Flutie had estimated &quot;an 80 percent chance&quot; of making the drop kick,&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Ulman |first=Howard |url=http://www.theledger.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060102/NEWS/601020380/1002/SPORTS |title=Dolphins Win Sixth Straight Despite Flutie's Drop Kick |publisher=TheLedger.com |date= |accessdate=2013-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; which was called to give Flutie, 43 at the time, the opportunity to make a historic kick in his final NFL game; the drop kick was his last play in the NFL. 

[[Dallas Cowboys]] punter [[Mat McBriar]] attempted a maneuver similar to a drop kick during the 2010 [[NFL on Thanksgiving Day|Thanksgiving Day game]] after a botched punt attempt, but the ball bounced several times before the kick and the sequence of events is officially recorded as a fumble, followed by an illegal kick, with the fumble being recovered by the [[New Orleans Saints]] 29 yards downfield from the spot of the kick. The Saints declined the illegal kick penalty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/nfl/playbyplay?gameId=301125006&amp;period=4 |title=New Orleans Saints vs. Dallas Cowboys – Play By Play – November 25, 2010 – ESPN |publisher=Scores.espn.go.com |date=2010-11-25 |accessdate=2013-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nfl.com/gamecenter/2010112501/2010/REG12/saints@cowboys/watch?module=HP_cp2#tab:analyze |title=Watch New Orleans Saints vs. Dallas Cowboys [11/25/2010 |publisher=NFL.com |date= |accessdate=2013-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[New England Patriots]] kicker [[Stephen Gostkowski]] attempted an onside drop kick on a free kick after a safety against the [[Pittsburgh Steelers]] on October 30, 2011. The kick went out of bounds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cbssports.com/mcc/blogs/entry/22475988/33071567 |title=Polamalu punch vs. Patriots was illegal |publisher=CBSSports.com |accessdate=2013-10-02 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131005000814/http://www.cbssports.com/mcc/blogs/entry/22475988/33071567 |archivedate=2013-10-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=England |first=New |url=http://musketfire.com/2011/10/30/patriots-steelers-studs-duds/ |title=Patriots-Steelers Studs &amp; Duds – Musket Fire – A New England Patriots Fan Site – News, Blogs, Opinion and more |publisher=Musket Fire |date=2011-10-30 |accessdate=2013-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[New Orleans Saints]] quarterback [[Drew Brees]], a former teammate of Flutie's, executed a drop kick late on an extra point attempt in the fourth quarter of the [[2012 Pro Bowl]]; the kick fell short.

New England Patriots special teams player [[Nate Ebner]] attempted an onside drop kick on a kickoff after a Patriots touchdown against the [[Philadelphia Eagles]] on December 6, 2015. The kick was recovered by the Eagles at their own 41 yard line.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.bostonglobe.com/sports/2015/12/06/patriots-attempt-unusual-drop-kick-style-kickoff/XFIH51dJek0CSQekn7W4CM/story.html |title=Patriots attempt unusual drop-kick style kickoff |newspaper=The Boston Globe |date=2015-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two weeks later, on December 20, [[Buffalo Bills]] punter [[Colton Schmidt]] executed what is believed to be an unintentional drop kick after a botched punt against the [[Washington Redskins]]; because the Redskins recovered the kick, it was treated as a punt (and not as a field goal attempt, which would have pushed the ball back to the spot of the kick).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ftw.usatoday.com/2015/12/bills-punter-drop-kick-punt-colton-schmidt-redskins-doug-flutie|title=Bills punter somehow turns punt into drop kick through beautiful incompetence|date=20 December 2015|work=usatoday.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Seattle Seahawks]] punter [[Michael Dickson (American football)|Michael Dickson]] drop kicked a kickoff from the 50-yard-line on September 17, 2018 against the [[Chicago Bears]]. The kick landed inside the 5-yard-line and was returned to a spot less far out than a touchback would have been automatically returned to, making it a successful strategy. Dickson made an onside drop kick attempt at the end of the same game, which was unsuccessful (recovered by the Bears). Seahawks coach [[Pete Carroll]] noted that he considers Dickson the team's backup kicker and would kick field goals and extra point attempts with the drop kick should there be an injury to placekicker [[Sebastian Janikowski]].&lt;ref&gt;https://profootballtalk.nbcsports.com/2018/12/26/seahawks-comfortable-with-michael-dickson-drop-kicking-pats-or-fgs/&lt;/ref&gt; Following an injury to Janikowski, Dickson attempted several drop kickoffs on January 5, 2019 against the Dallas Cowboys, including an onside kick which was received normally as a fair catch.

The drop kick came under controversy in [[2019 NFL season|2019]], after [[Justin Tucker]] of the [[Baltimore Ravens]] used the manoeuvre on a kickoff late in a game against the [[Kansas City Chiefs]]. The drop kick was intended to force the Chiefs to [[fair catch]] the ball, preventing them from [[running out the clock]].  As 2:01 was showing on the game clock and a fair-caught kickoff does not run any time off the clock, it would force the Chiefs to run a play before the [[two-minute warning]].  Several weeks after the kick, league offices claimed the maneuver was illegal. Ravens head coach [[John Harbaugh]] disputed this, noting that they had cleared it with the NFL before using the drop kick and weren't penalized by the in-game officials. The NFL's statement falsely claimed that the ball wasn't kicked immediately after the bounce. An article on [[CBS Sports]] claimed that the NFL had made a midseason rule change banning the drop kick, but no statement from the NFL has ever confirmed this.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=John|last=Breech|url=https://www.cbssports.com/nfl/news/nfl-bans-ravens-crazy-kickoff-dropkick-after-watching-baltimore-use-it-just-one-time/|title=NFL bans Ravens' crazy kickoff dropkick after watching Baltimore use it just one time|work=CBS Sports|date=October 10, 2019|access-date=October 10, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== NCAA ===
To date, the last successful drop kick extra point in the NCAA was by Jason Millgan of [[Hartwick College]] on December 11, 1998, [[St. Lawrence University]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VVi6LBcTLOw |title=Hartwick College ESPN Drop Kick Field Goal |publisher=YouTube |date= |accessdate=2013-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Frosty Peters]] of [[Montana State College]] made 17 drop kicks in one game in 1924.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.msubobcats.com/sports/2012/7/26/GEN_0726122140.aspx |title=BOBCAT ATHLETIC TRADITIONS |access-date=August 9, 2016 |publisher=msubobcats.com |url-status=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160809215242/http://www.msubobcats.com/sports/2012/7/26/GEN_0726122140.aspx |archivedate=August 9, 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Canadian football ===
{{unreferenced section|date=March 2017}}
In the Canadian game, the drop kick can be attempted at any time by either team. Any player on the kicking team behind the kicker, and including the kicker, can recover the kick. When a drop kick goes out of bounds, possession on the next scrimmage goes to the non-kicking team.

On September 8, 1974, [[Tom Wilkinson (football player)|Tom Wilkinson]], quarterback for the [[Edmonton Eskimos]], unsuccessfully attempted a drop kick field goal in the final seconds of a 24–2 romp over the [[Winnipeg Blue Bombers]].

During one game in the 1980s, [[Hamilton Tiger-Cats]] wide receiver [[Earl Winfield]] was unable to field a punt properly; in frustration, he kicked the ball out of bounds. The kick was considered a drop kick and led to a change of possession, with the punting team regaining possession of the ball.

=== Arena football ===
In [[arena football]], a drop-kicked extra point counts for two points rather than one and a drop-kicked field goal counts for four points rather than three.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.arenafootball.com/about/afl-rules.html Rules of the Game] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141225033049/http://www.arenafootball.com/about/afl-rules.html |date=December 25, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The most recent conversion of a drop kick was by Geoff Boyer of the [[Pittsburgh Power]] on June 16, 2012; it was the first successful conversion in the now-defunct Arena Football League since 1997.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://thealbanyjournal.com/2011/06/a-drop-kick-into-history/ |title=A drop kick into history|first=Tom |last=Knighton|date=June 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2018, [[Maine Mammoths]] kicker Henry Nell converted a drop kick as a PAT against the [[Massachusetts Pirates]] in the [[National Arena League]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Garven|first=Rich|url=https://www.telegram.com/news/20180513/massachusetts-pirates-savor-ot-win-over-maine-mammoths|title=Massachusetts Pirates savor OT win over Maine Mammoths|newspaper=[[Telegram &amp; Gazette]]|date=May 13, 2018|accessdate=February 28, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Australian rules football ==
Once the preferred method of conveying the ball over long distances, the drop-kick has been superseded by the [[Punt (Australian football)#Drop punt|drop punt]] as a more accurate means of delivering the ball to a fellow player.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Future direction of an evolving art form|first=Andrew|last=Faulkner|newspaper=The Australian|date=11 June 2011|url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/sport/opinion/future-direction-of-an-evolving-art-form/story-e6frg7t6-1226073279442}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Drop goal]]
* [[Grubber kick]]
* [[Bomb (kick)|Bomb kick]]
* [[Glossary of American football]]
* [[Dropped-ball]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}
* {{Cite web|url=https://rugbykicking.com/how-to-do-a-rugby-drop-kick/|title=Drop Kick|website=Rugby Kicking Academy|language=en-US|access-date=2018-08-03}}

{{Gridiron football plays}}
{{Australian rules football terminology}}

[[Category:American football plays]]
[[Category:Rugby union terminology]]
[[Category:Rugby league terminology]]
[[Category:Australian rules football terminology]]

[[fr:Drop (rugby à XV)]]</text>
      <sha1>1xiwqqpcnt71oqvr4dohnajpy7u4oqj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
