  <page>
    <title>Chauvinism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7312</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939926823</id>
      <parentid>939925538</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-09T15:25:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marcocapelle</username>
        <id>14965160</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>moved [[Category:Men and feminism]] to [[Male chauvinism]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Form of extreme patriotism and nationalism and a belief in national superiority and glory}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{Nationalism sidebar}}
{{Populism sidebar}}
'''Chauvinism''' is a form of extreme [[patriotism]] and [[nationalism]] and a  belief in national superiority and glory. It can be also defined as &quot;an irrational belief in the superiority or dominance of one's own group or people&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Global politics|last=Macmillan.|first=Palgrave|date=2015|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|isbn=9781137349262|oclc=979008143}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, the chauvinist's own people are seen as unique and special while the rest of the people are considered weak or inferior.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

According to legend, French soldier [[Nicolas Chauvin]] was badly wounded in the [[Napoleonic Wars]]. He received a pension for his injuries but it was not enough to live on. After [[Napoleon]] abdicated, Chauvin was a fanatical [[Bonapartism|Bonapartist]] despite the unpopularity of this view in [[Bourbon Restoration]] France. His single-minded blind devotion to his cause, despite neglect by his faction and harassment by its enemies, started the use of the term.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chauvinism&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Chauvinism|url=http://www.britannica.com/topic/chauvinism|website=Encyclopædia Britannica}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Chauvinism'' has extended from its original use to include fanatical devotion and undue partiality to any group or cause to which one belongs,  especially when such [[Partisan (political)|partisanship]] includes prejudice against or hostility toward outsiders or rival groups and persists even in the face of overwhelming opposition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chauvinism&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;quickanddirtytips.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=15 Words You Didn't Realize Were Named After People|url=http://www.quickanddirtytips.com/education/grammar/15-words-you-didnt-realize-were-named-after-people|website=Grammar Girl}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;oed.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Chauvinism|url=http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/31017?redirectedFrom=chauvinism#eid|website=The Oxford English Dictionary}}&lt;/ref&gt; This French quality finds its parallel in the British term ''[[jingoism]]'', which has retained the meaning of ''chauvinism'' strictly in its original sense; that is, an attitude of belligerent nationalism.&lt;ref name=&quot;oed.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Jingoism|url=http://www.britannica.com/topic/jingoism|website=Encyclopædia Britannica|accessdate=22 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Jingoism &amp; Chauvinism|url=http://wordhistories.com/2013/06/15/jingoism-chauvinism/|website=Word Histories|accessdate=22 June 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141026055627/http://wordhistories.com/2013/06/15/jingoism-chauvinism/|archive-date=26 October 2014|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In modern English, the word has come to be used in some quarters as shorthand for [[male chauvinism]], a trend reflected in ''[[Merriam-Webster's Dictionary]]'', which, as of 2018, begins its first example of use of the term ''chauvinism'' with &quot;an attitude of superiority toward members of the opposite sex&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;quickanddirtytips.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Chauvinism|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/chauvinism|website=Merriam-Webster's Dictionary}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Columbia Guide to Standard American English |url=http://www.bartleby.com/68/24/1224.html |accessdate=4 December 2008 |quote=''Chauvinism'' is &quot;fanatical, boastful, unreasoning patriotism&quot; and by extension &quot;prejudiced belief or unreasoning pride in any group to which you belong.&quot; Lately, though, the compounds &quot;male chauvinism&quot; and &quot;male chauvinist&quot; have gained so much popularity that some users may no longer recall the patriotic and other more generalized meanings of the words.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==As nationalism==
In 1945, political theorist [[Hannah Arendt]] described the concept thus:
{{quote|Chauvinism is an almost natural product of the national concept in so far as it springs directly from the old idea of the &quot;national mission.&quot; ... [A] nation's mission might be interpreted precisely as bringing its light to other, less fortunate peoples that, for whatever reason, have miraculously been left by history without a national mission. As long as this concept did not develop into the ideology of chauvinism and remained in the rather vague realm of national or even nationalistic pride, it frequently resulted in a high sense of responsibility for the welfare of backward people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Arendt |first=Hannah |date=October 1945 |title=Imperialism, Nationalism, Chauvinism |journal= The Review of Politics |volume=7 |issue=4 |pages=457 |doi=10.1017/s0034670500001649}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Male chauvinism==
{{see also|Sexism|Misogyny|Androcentrism|Machismo|Patriarchy}}
Male chauvinism is the belief that [[men]] are superior to [[women]]. The first documented use of the phrase &quot;male chauvinism&quot; is in the 1935 [[Clifford Odets]] play ''[[Till the Day I Die]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Mansbridge|first=Jane|author2=Katherine Flaster|title=Male Chauvinist, Feminist, Sexist, and Sexual Harassment: Different Trajectories in Feminist Linguistic Innovation|journal=American Speech|year=2005|volume=80|issue=3|page=261|doi=10.1215/00031283-80-3-256|citeseerx=10.1.1.103.8136}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===In the workplace===
The balance of the [[workforce]] changed during [[World War II]]. As men left their positions to enlist in the military and fight in the war, women started replacing them. After the war ended, men returned home to find jobs in the workplace, male chauvinism was on the rise, according to Cynthia B. Lloyd. Previously, men had been the main source of labour, and they expected to come back to their previous employments, but they soon realized women had taken over many of their positions to fill the void, says Lloyd.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lloyd, Cynthia B. 1975&quot;&gt;Lloyd, Cynthia B., ed. ''Sex, Discrimination, and the Division of Labor''. New York: Columbia University Press, 1975. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

Lloyd and Michael Korda have argued that as they integrated back into the workforce, men returned to predominate, holding positions of power while women worked as their secretaries, usually typing dictations and answering telephone calls. This division of labor was understood and expected, and women typically felt unable to challenge their position or male superiors, argue Korda and Lloyd.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lloyd, Cynthia B. 1975&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Korda, Michael 1973&quot;&gt;[[Michael Korda]], ''Male Chauvinism! How It Works''. New York: Random House, 1973. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Causes===
Chauvinism is seen by some as an influential factor in the [[Thematic Apperception Test|TAT]], a psychological personality test. Through cross-examinations, the TAT exhibits a tendency toward chauvinistic stimuli for its questions and has the &quot;potential for unfavorable clinical evaluation&quot; for women.&lt;ref&gt;Potkay, Charles R., Matthew R. Merrens. Sources of Male Chauvinism in the TAT. Journal of Personality Assessment, 39.5 (1975): 471-479. Web. 31 Jan 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

An often cited study done in 1976 by Sherwyn Woods, Some Dynamics of Male Chauvinism, attempts to find the underlying causes of male chauvinism.
{{quote|Male chauvinism was studied in the [[psychoanalytic]] therapy of 11 men. It refers to the maintenance of fixed beliefs and attitudes of male superiority, associated with overt or covert depreciation of women. Challenging chauvinist attitudes often results In anxiety or other symptoms. It is frequently not investigated in psychotherapy because it is ego-syntonic, parallels cultural attitudes, and because therapists often share similar bias or neurotic conflict. Chauvinism was found to represent an attempt to ward off anxiety and shame arising from one or more of four prime sources: unresolved infantile strivings and regressive wishes, hostile envy of women, oedipal anxiety, and power and dependency conflicts related to masculine [[self-esteem]]. [[Mother]]s were more important than fathers in the development of male chauvinism, and resolution was sometimes associated with [[decompensation#Psychology|decompensation]] in wives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Woods|first=Sherwyn M.|title=Some Dynamics of Male Chauvinism|journal=Archives of General Psychiatry|date=January 1976|volume=33|issue=1|pages=63|doi=10.1001/archpsyc.1976.01770010037007 |pmid=1247365}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Female chauvinism==
{{see also|Sexism|Misandry|Gynocentrism|Feminism|Matriarchy}}
Female chauvinism is the belief that women are morally superior to men, and is considered [[anti-feminist]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Brons|first=Lajos|title=On gender chauvinism|url=https://www.academia.edu/23436333/On_gender_chauvinism|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The term has been adopted by critics of some types or aspects of [[feminism]]; second-wave feminist [[Betty Friedan]] is a notable example.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;If I were a man, I would strenuously object to the assumption that women have any moral or spiritual superiority as a class. This is [...] female chauvinism.&quot; Friedan, Betty. 1998. ''It Changed My Life: Writings on the Women's Movement''. Harvard University Press&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ariel Levy (journalist)|Ariel Levy]] used the term in similar, but opposite sense in her book, ''[[Female Chauvinist Pigs]]'', in which she argues that many young women in the United States and beyond are replicating male chauvinism and older [[misogynist]] [[stereotype]]s.&lt;ref&gt;''Female Chauvinist Pigs: Women and the Rise of Raunch Culture'', [[Ariel Levy (journalist)|Ariel Levy]], 2006, {{ISBN|0-7432-8428-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{col div|colwidth=30em}}
* [[American exceptionalism]] 
* [[Avant-garde]]
* [[Blind nationalism]]
* [[Fraternity#University_and_college_fraternities|Boys club]]
* [[Carbon chauvinism]]
* [[Great Russian chauvinism]]
* [[Han chauvinism]]
* [[National symbol]]ism
* [[Planetary chauvinism]]
* [[Romanticism]]
* [[Royal and noble styles]]
* [[Sexism]]
* [[Social chauvinism]]
* [[Supremacism]]
* [[Theocracy]]
* [[Welfare chauvinism]]
{{colend}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
{{Wiktionary}}
{{EB1911 poster|Chauvinism}}

{{Nationalism}}

[[Category:Chauvinism| ]]
[[Category:Nationalism]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]</text>
      <sha1>8brmogxc5uwkiktzece3pixalnvb5eg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
