  <page>
    <title>Cogito, ergo sum</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7344</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942776299</id>
      <parentid>942775745</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-26T19:34:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Paradoctor</username>
        <id>4082870</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 3 edits by [[Special:Contributions/77.127.4.127|77.127.4.127]] ([[User talk:77.127.4.127|talk]]) to last revision by InternetArchiveBot ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{italic title}}
{{Descartes}}
'''{{lang|la|Cogito, ergo sum}}'''{{efn|name=&quot;capitalization and punctuation&quot;}} is a [[Latin]] [[philosophy|philosophical]] [[proposition]] by [[René Descartes]] usually translated into English as &quot;'''I think, therefore I am'''&quot;.{{efn|name= &quot;better translation&quot; | Some sources offer &quot;I am thinking, therefore I am&quot; as a 'better' translation. (See [[Cogito, ergo sum#Translation|§ Translation]].)}} The phrase originally appeared in [[French language|French]] as {{nowrap|'''{{lang|fr|je pense}}}}, {{nowrap|{{lang|fr|donc je suis}}}}''' in his ''[[Discourse on the Method]]'', so as to reach a wider audience than Latin would have allowed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | first = William E. | last = Burns | title = The scientific revolution: an encyclopedia| publisher = ABC-CLIO | location = Santa Barbara, California | year = 2001 | isbn = 978-0-87436-875-8 | page = 84}}&lt;/ref&gt; It appeared in Latin in his later ''[[Principles of Philosophy]]''. As Descartes explained, &quot;we cannot doubt of our existence while we doubt....&quot; A fuller version, articulated by [[Antoine Léonard Thomas]], aptly captures Descartes's intent: {{lang|la|dubito, ergo cogito, ergo sum}} (&quot;I doubt, therefore I think, therefore I am&quot;).{{efn|The {{lang|la|dubito}} is often mistakenly attributed to Descartes. (See [[Cogito ergo sum#Other forms|Other forms]].)}}{{efn|In the posthumously published work cited in the first footnote above, Descartes wrote “'''''dubito, ergo sum''''', vel, quod idem est, '''''cogito, ergo sum'''''&quot; (&quot;'''''I doubt, therefore I am''''' — or what is the same — '''''I think, therefore I am'''''&quot;). (See [[Cogito, ergo sum#The Search for Truth|''The Search for Truth'']].)}} The concept is also sometimes known as '''the cogito'''.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;
[https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/cogito Cogito]&quot;. ''Oxford Dictionaries''. Oxford University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;

This proposition became a fundamental element of [[Western philosophy]], as it purported to form a secure [[epistemology|foundation for knowledge]] in the face of [[Radical skepticism|radical doubt]]. While other knowledge could be a figment of imagination, deception, or mistake, Descartes asserted that the very act of doubting one's own existence served—at minimum—as proof of the reality of one's own mind; there must be a [[Consciousness|thinking entity]]—in this case the [[self]]—for there to be a thought.

The [[#Critique|critique]] against the proposition is the presupposition of an &quot;I&quot; doing the thinking, so that the most Descartes was entitled to say was: &quot;thinking is occurring&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;thinkingisoccurring&quot; /&gt;

==In Descartes's writings==
Descartes first wrote the phrase in French in his 1637 ''[[Discourse on the Method]]''. He referred to it in Latin without explicitly stating the familiar form of the phrase in his 1641 ''[[Meditations on First Philosophy]]''. The earliest written record of the phrase in Latin is in his 1644 ''[[Principles of Philosophy]]'', where, in a margin note (see below), he provides a clear explanation of his intent: &quot;[W]e cannot doubt of our existence while we doubt&quot;. Fuller forms of the phrase are attributable to other authors.

===''Discourse on the Method''===
The phrase first appeared (in French) in Descartes's 1637 ''[[Discourse on the Method]]'' in the first paragraph of its fourth part:

{{quote|(French:) {{lang|fr|Ainsi, à cause que nos sens nous trompent quelquefois, je voulus supposer qu'il n'y avait aucune chose qui fût telle qu'ils nous la font imaginer; Et parce qu'il y a des hommes qui se méprennent en raisonnant, même touchant les plus simples matières de Géométrie, et y font des Paralogismes, jugeant que j'étais sujet à faillir autant qu'aucun autre, je rejetai comme fausses toutes les raisons que j'avais prises auparavant pour Démonstrations; Et enfin, considérant que toutes les mêmes pensées que nous avons étant éveillés nous peuvent aussi venir quand nous dormons, sans qu'il y en ait aucune raison pour lors qui soit vraie, je me résolus de feindre que toutes les choses qui m'étaient jamais entrées en l'esprit n'étaient non plus vraies que les illusions de mes songes. Mais aussitôt après je pris garde que, pendant que je voulais ainsi penser que tout était faux, il fallait nécessairement que moi qui le pensais fusse quelque chose; Et remarquant que cette vérité, '''''{{nowrap|je pense,}} {{nowrap|donc je suis}}''''',{{efn|name=&quot;formatting&quot;}} était si ferme et si assurée, que toutes les plus extravagantes suppositions des Sceptiques n'étaient pas capables de l'ébranler, je jugeai que je pouvais la recevoir sans scrupule pour le premier principe de la Philosophie que je cherchais.|italic=unset}}{{efn|name=&quot;formatting2”|Formatting note: Capitalization as in original; spelling updated from [[Middle French]] to [[Modern French]].}}{{efn|1=See original ''Discours'' manuscript [https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b86069594/f37.item.zoom here].}}}}

{{quote|(English:) Accordingly, seeing that our senses sometimes deceive us, I was willing to suppose that there existed nothing really such as they presented to us; And because some men err in reasoning, and fall into Paralogisms, even on the simplest matters of Geometry, I, convinced that I was as open to error as any other, rejected as false all the reasonings I had hitherto taken for Demonstrations; And finally, when I considered that the very same thoughts (presentations) which we experience when awake may also be experienced when we are asleep, while there is at that time not one of them true, I supposed that all the objects (presentations) that had ever entered into my mind when awake, had in them no more truth than the illusions of my dreams. But immediately upon this I observed that, whilst I thus wished to think that all was false, it was absolutely necessary that I, who thus thought, should be something; And as I observed that this truth, '''''{{nowrap|I think,}} {{nowrap|therefore I am}}''''',{{efn|name=&quot;formatting&quot;}} was so certain and of such evidence that no ground of doubt, however extravagant, could be alleged by the Sceptics capable of shaking it, I concluded that I might, without scruple, accept it as the [[first principle]] of the philosophy of which I was in search.{{efn|This translation, by Veitch in 1850,&lt;ref name=&quot;Veitch1850&quot;&gt;{{cite book | author=Veitch, John | title=Discourse on the Method of Rightly Conducting the Reason, and Seeking Truth in the Sciences, by Descartes | publisher=Sutherland and Knox | year=1850 | location=Edinburgh | pages=74–5 | url = https://archive.org/stream/Descartes1637DiscourseOnTheMethodTrVeitch1850/Descartes%201637%20Discourse%20tr%20Veitch%201850#page/n77/mode/2up/search/Therefore+I+am| author-link=John Veitch (poet) }}&lt;/ref&gt; is modified here as follows: Veitch's &quot;I think, hence I am” is changed to the form by which it is currently best known in English, &quot;I think, therefore I am&quot;, which appeared in the Haldane and Ross 1911 translation,&lt;ref name=Haldane1911/&gt; and as an isolated attributed phrase previously, e.g., in Sullivan (1794);&lt;ref name=Sullivan1794&gt;{{cite book | author=Richard Joseph Sullivan | title=A View of Nature, in Letters to a Traveller among the Alps, with Reflections on Atheistical Philosophy now exemplified in France | year = 1794 | page=129 | url=https://books.google.com/?id=1q00AAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA129 | publisher=printed for T. Becket | location=London| author-link=Richard Joseph Sullivan }}&lt;/ref&gt; in the preceding line, Veitch's &quot;I, who thus thought, should be somewhat” is given here as &quot;… should be something&quot; for clarity (in accord with other translations, e.g., that of Cress&lt;ref name=Cress1986/&gt;); and capitalization was reverted to conform to Descartes's original in French.}}{{efn|The 1637 ''Discours'' was translated to Latin in the 1644 ''Specimina Philosophiae''&lt;ref name=&quot;Descartes1644Specimina&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Descartes, René | title=Specimina philosophiae|publisher=Ludovicus Elzevirius |url=https://archive.org/details/ita-bnc-mag-00001403-001|page=[https://archive.org/details/ita-bnc-mag-00001403-001/page/n68 30] |year=1644}}&lt;/ref&gt; but this is not referenced here because of issues raised regarding translation quality.&lt;ref name=&quot;Vermeulen2006&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Vermeulen, Corinna Lucia|title=René Descartes, ''Specimina philosophiae''. Introduction and Critical Edition|url=http://igitur-archive.library.uu.nl/dissertations/2007-1019-202001/index.htm|year=2006|type=Dissertation, Utrecht University}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}}}

===''Meditations on First Philosophy''===
In 1641, Descartes published (in Latin) ''[[Meditations on first philosophy]]'' in which he referred to the proposition, though not explicitly as &quot;cogito, ergo sum&quot; in Meditation II:

{{quote|(Latin:) {{lang|la|hoc pronuntiatum: '''ego sum, ego existo''',{{efn|name=&quot;formatting&quot;}} quoties a me profertur, vel mente concipitur, necessario esse verum.|italic=unset}}{{efn|1=See original ''Meditiations'' manuscript [https://books.google.com/books?id=r0APAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA4&amp;dq=descartes+1642+meditations&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjc-vvr6cXeAhUtrlkKHSI-C2sQ6AEIKDAA#v=snippet&amp;q=%22ego%20fum%2C%20ego%20exifto%22&amp;f=false here].}}}}

{{quote|(English:) this proposition: '''I am thinking, therefore I am/exist''',{{efn|name=&quot;formatting&quot;}} whenever it is uttered from me, or conceived by the mind, necessarily is true.{{efn|This combines, for clarity and to retain phrase ordering, the Cress&lt;ref name=Cress1986/&gt; and Haldane&lt;ref name=Haldane2007/&gt; translations of the ''Meditations'' with the translation of the “ego cogito, ergo sum” phrase by Suzuki (see [[Cogito, ergo sum#Translation|§ Translation]]).}}}}

===''Principles of Philosophy''===
In 1644, Descartes published (in Latin) his ''[[Principles of Philosophy]]'' where the phrase &quot;ego cogito, ergo sum&quot; appears in Part 1, article 7:

{{quote|(Latin:) {{lang|la|Sic autem rejicientes illa omnia, de quibus aliquo modo possumus dubitare, ac etiam, falsa esse fingentes, facilè quidem, supponimus nullum esse Deum, nullum coelum, nulla corpora; nosque etiam ipsos, non habere manus, nec pedes, nec denique ullum corpus, non autem ideò nos qui talia cogitamus nihil esse: repugnat enim ut putemus id quod cogitat eo ipso tempore quo cogitat non existere. Ac proinde haec cognitio, '''''ego cogito, ergo sum''''',{{efn|name=&quot;formatting&quot;}} est omnium prima &amp; certissima, quae cuilibet ordine philosophanti occurrat.|italic=unset}}{{efn|1=See original ''Principia'' manuscript [https://books.google.com/books?id=nHBTAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA34&amp;dq=editions:d2v_xqzGbjgC&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiW-OnupcbeAhUDtlkKHajMABUQ6AEIKDAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22ego%20cogito%22&amp;f=false here].}}}}

{{quote|(English:) While we thus reject all of which we can entertain the smallest doubt, and even imagine that it is false, we easily indeed suppose that there is neither God, nor sky, nor bodies, and that we ourselves even have neither hands nor feet, nor, finally, a body; but we cannot in the same way suppose that we are not while we doubt of the truth of these things; for there is a repugnance in conceiving that what thinks does not exist at the very time when it thinks. Accordingly, the knowledge,{{efn|A 1647 French translation,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Descartes | title=Principes de la philosophie | year=1647 | translator-first=Abbé Claude | translator-last=Picot | location=Paris| url = https://books.google.com/?id=C7r-GKWF2xoC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=abbe+Claude+Picot#v=snippet&amp;q=%22conclusion%3A%20je%20pense%22&amp;f=false| isbn=9782711622313 }}&lt;/ref&gt; published with Descartes’s enthusiastic approval, substituted 'conclusion' for 'knowledge'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | first1 =Valentine Roger | last1 = Miller | first2 = Reese P. | last2 = Miller | title = Descartes, René. Principles of Philosophy. Translated, with explanatory notes | year = 1983 | isbn = 978-90-277-1754-2 | pages = xi,5}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} '''''I think, therefore I am''''',{{efn|name=&quot;formatting&quot;}} is the first and most certain that occurs to one who philosophizes orderly.{{efn|name=&quot;GutPrinc4391&quot;}}}}

Descartes's [[marginalia|margin note]] for the above paragraph is:

{{quote|(Latin:) {{lang|la|Non posse à nobis dubitari, quin existamus dum dubitamus; atque hoc esse primum, quod ordine philosophando cognoscimus.|italic=unset}}}}

{{quote|(English:) That we cannot doubt of our existence while we doubt, and that this is the first knowledge we acquire when we philosophize in order.{{efn|name=&quot;GutPrinc4391&quot;}}}}

===''The Search for Truth''===
Descartes, in a lesser-known posthumously published work dated as written ca. 1647&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = Gouhier | first = Henri | author-link = Henri Gouhier | title = ''La pensée religieuse de Descartes'' | year = 1924 | page = 319 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=8Dw1AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA319&amp;lpg=PA319#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; and titled {{lang|fr|La Recherche de la Vérité par La Lumiere Naturale}} (''The Search for Truth by Natural Light''),&lt;ref name=&quot;AT&quot;/&gt;{{efn|Titled ''Inquisitio Veritatis per Lumen Naturale'' in a 1683 compendium of posthumously published works.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | author-link = René Descartes | title = ''Regulae ad Directionem Ingenii ut et Inquisitio Veritatis per Lumen Naturale'' | year = 1683 | page = 86 | url = https://books.google.com/?id=XDBnAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=RA2-PA86&amp;dq=%22dubitatio,+quid+cogitatio%22+cogito#v=snippet&amp;q=cogito%20ergo%20fum&amp;f=false| last1 = Descartes | first1 = René }}&lt;/ref&gt;}} wrote:

{{quote|(Latin:) {{lang|la|… [S]entio, oportere, ut quid dubitatio, quid cogitatio, quid exsistentia sit antè sciamus, quàm de veritate hujus ratiocinii : '''''dubito, ergo sum''''', vel, quod idem est, '''''cogito, ergo sum'''''{{efn|name=&quot;formatting&quot;}} : plane simus persuasi.|italic=unset}}}}

{{quote|(English:) … [I feel that] it is necessary to know what doubt is, and what thought is, [what existence is], before we can be fully persuaded of this reasoning — '''''I doubt, therefore I am''''' — or what is the same — '''''I think, therefore I am'''''.{{efn|Translation by Hallam,&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = Hallam | first = Henry | title = Introduction to the Literature of Europe in the 15th, 16th, and 17th Centuries | volume = II | edition = 2nd | page = 451 | year = 1843 | url = https://books.google.com/?id=M4dZUnDvc1kC&amp;pg=PA451&amp;lpg=PA451&amp;dq=%22%27%27%27%27%27I+doubt,+therefore+I+am%27%27%27%27%27,+or+what+is+the+same,+%27%27%27%27%27I+think,+therefore+I+am%27%27%27%27%27,+%22#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; with additions for completeness.}}}}

===Other forms===
The proposition is sometimes given as {{lang|la|dubito, ergo cogito, ergo sum}}. This fuller form was penned by the eloquent French literary critic, [[Antoine Léonard Thomas]], in an award-winning 1765 essay in praise of Descartes, where it appeared as {{lang|fr|&quot;Puisque je doute, je pense; puisque je pense, j'existe.&quot;}} In English, this is &quot;Since I doubt, I think; since I think, I exist&quot;; with rearrangement and compaction, &quot;I doubt, therefore I think, therefore I am&quot;, or in Latin, &quot;dubito, ergo cogito, ergo sum&quot;.{{efn|The 1765 work, ''Éloge de René Descartes'',&lt;ref name=Thomas1765/&gt; by Antoine Léonard Thomas, was awarded the 1765 Le Prix De L'académie Française and republished in the 1826 compilation of Descartes's work, ''Oeuvres de Descartes''&lt;ref name=Cousin1824/&gt; by [[Victor Cousin]]. The French text is available in [http://www.gutenberg.org/files/13846/13846-h/13846-h.htm more accessible format] at Project Gutenberg. The compilation by Cousin is credited with a revival of interest in Descartes.&lt;ref name=Edinburgh1890/&gt;&lt;ref name=Descartes2007/&gt;}}

A further expansion, {{lang|la|dubito, ergo cogito, ergo sum—res cogitans}} (&quot;…—a thinking thing&quot;) extends the ''cogito'' with Descartes's statement in the subsequent Meditation, {{lang|la|&quot;Ego sum res cogitans, id est dubitans, affirmans, negans, pauca intelligens, multa ignorans, volens, nolens, imaginans etiam et sentiens …&quot;}}, or, in English, &quot;I am a thinking (conscious) thing, that is, a being who doubts, affirms, denies, knows a few objects, and is ignorant of many …&quot;.{{efn | This translation by [[John Veitch (poet)|Veitch]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Veitch1880&quot;&gt;{{cite book | author=Veitch, John | title=The Method, Meditations and Selections from the Principles of René Descartes | publisher=William Blackwood and Sons | year=1880 | location=Edinburgh | edition=7th | pages=115 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=TjYCAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA115| author-link=John Veitch (poet) }}&lt;/ref&gt; is the first English translation from Descartes as &quot;I am a thinking thing&quot;.}} This has been referred to as &quot;the expanded ''cogito''&quot;.&lt;ref name=Kline1967/&gt;{{efn|[[Martin Schoock]], who in the 1642–43 controversy between Descartes and [[Gisbertus Voetius]], fiercely attacked Descartes and his philosophy in an essay,&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = Schoockius | first = Martinus | title = Admiranda Methodus Novae Philosophiae Renati Des Cartes | year = 1643 | url = https://books.google.com/books/about/Admiranda_Methodus_Novae_Philosophiae_Re.html?id=1PQGAAAAcAAJ}}&lt;/ref&gt;  
wrote ''cogito, ergo sum, res cogitans'' and ''cogito, inquiro, dubito ergo sum'' as well as '''''cogito, ergo sum''''' (multiple times) in his 1652 ''De Scepticismo''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = Schoockius | first = Martinus | title = De Scepticismo | page = 87 | year = 1652 | url = https://books.google.com/?id=vW5WAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA100&amp;dq=%22cogito+ergo+fum%22+cogito+-%22ego+cogito%22#v=onepage&amp;q=%22res%20cogitans%22&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Translation==
Neither {{nowrap|{{lang|fr|je pense}}}} nor {{lang|la|cogito}} indicate whether the verb form corresponds to the English [[simple present]] or [[Continuous and progressive aspects|progressive aspect]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Pope |first=Rob |date=2013 |title=Textual Intervention: Critical and Creative Strategies for Literary Studies|url=https://books.google.com/?id=HR7YAQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA34&amp;lpg=PA34&amp;dq=%22I+think,+therefore+I+am%22+%22present+tense%22+descartes#v=onepage&amp;q=%22neither%20Descartes’%20French%20version%22&amp;f=false |publisher=Routledge |page=35 |isbn=9781135083281}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|The tense of {{nowrap|{{lang|fr|je pense}}}} is marked {{lang|fr|indicatif présent}} by e.g., [https://www.the-conjugation.com/french/verb/penser.php conjugation.com]; {{lang|la|cōgitō}} is indicative active present per e.g., [[wikt:cogito#Inflection|Wiktionary]].}} Translation needs a larger context to determine [[Grammatical aspect|aspect]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Dunlap |first= J. R. |date= 2006|title= An Answer Key to A Primer of Ecclesiastical Latin: A Supplement to the Text by John F. Collins |publisher=CUA Press |page=18 |isbn=9780813214696}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following [[John Lyons (linguist)|John Lyons]] (1982),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1= Lyons|first1= J.|year= 1982|chapter= Deixis and subjectivity: Loquor, ergo sum? |editor1-last= Jarvella|editor1-first= Rovert J. |editor2-last= Klein|editor2-first= Wolfgang |title= Speech, place, and action: Studies in deixis and related topics |pages= 101–224}}&lt;/ref&gt; Vladimir Žegarac notes, &quot;The temptation to use the simple present is said to arise from the lack of progressive forms in Latin and French, and from a misinterpretation of the meaning of ''cogito'' as habitual or generic.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite thesis |last= Žegarac|first= Vladimir|date= 1991|title= Tense, aspect and relevance |degree=PhD| url= http://discovery.ucl.ac.uk/1349786/1/363483.pdf|pages= 84,85|institution = University of London}}&lt;/ref&gt; (Cf. [[gnomic aspect]].) [[Ann Banfield]] writes (also following Lyons), &quot;In order for the statement on which Descartes's argument depends to represent certain knowledge, … its tense must be a true present—in English, a progressive, … not as 'I think' but as 'I am thinking, in conformity with the general translation of the Latin or French present tense in such nongeneric, nonstative contexts.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last= Banfield|first= A. |date= 1998|title= The Name of the Subject: The &quot;il&quot;? | journal = Yale French Studies | volume = 93| pages = 133–174 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Or in the words of [[Simon Blackburn]],  &quot;Descartes’s premise is not ‘I think’ in the sense of ‘I ski’, which can be true even if you are not at the moment skiing. It is supposed to be parallel to ‘I am skiing’.&quot;&lt;ref name=Blackburn1999&gt;{{cite book | author=Simon Blackburn | title=Think: A compelling introduction to philosophy | year = 1999 | url=https://archive.org/details/thinkcompellingi00bla_kzi | url-access=registration | quote=“am thinking, therefore”. | publisher=Oxford University Press| author-link=Simon Blackburn | isbn=9780199769841 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Fumitaka Suzuki (2012) writes &quot;Taking consideration of Cartesian theory of continuous creation, which theory was developed especially in the Meditations and in the Principles, we would assure that 'I am thinking, therefore I am/exist' is the most appropriate English translation of 'ego cogito, ergo sum'.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://aue.repo.nii.ac.jp/?action=repository_action_common_download&amp;item_id=106&amp;item_no=1&amp;attribute_id=15&amp;file_no=1|title=The Cogito Proposition of Descartes and Characteristics of His Ego Theory|last=Suzuki|first= Fumitaka|date=2012|website=Aporia.byu.edu|publisher= Bulletin of Aichi Univ. of Education|access-date=6 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The similar translation “I am thinking, therefore I exist” of Descartes's correspondence in French (“{{nowrap|{{lang|fr|je pense}}}}, {{nowrap|{{lang|fr|donc je suis}}}}”) appears in ''The Philosophical Writings of Descartes'' by Cottingham et al. (1988).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Philosophical Writings of Descartes |volume=III |translator=Cottingham, J. |translator2=Stoothoff, R. |translator3=Kenny, A. |translator4=Murdoch, D. |year=1991 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Y3RRKISL810C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=%22The+Philosophical+Writings+of+Descartes%22+Cottingham,+Stoothoff,+Murdoch,+and+Kenny&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjAvYanhNLeAhWn5lQKHd9VA4gQ6AEIKDAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22therefore%20I%20exist%22&amp;f=false |section=CSMK III 247}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The earliest known translation as &quot;I am thinking, therefore I am&quot; is from 1872 by [[Charles Porterfield Krauth]].&lt;ref name=Krauth&gt;{{cite journal|last=Krauth |first=Charles Porterfield |title=Notes in Class — Descartes |journal=The Penn Monthly |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=T75OAQAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA11|year=1872|publisher=University Press Company|volume=3|page=11}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|Krauth is not explicitly acknowledged as author of this article, but is so identified the following year by Garretson.&lt;ref name=&quot;Garretson1873&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=James Edmund Garretson|title=Thinkers and Thinking|url=https://archive.org/details/thinkersandthin00garrgoog|quote=descartes he affirmed thinking.|year=1873|publisher=J.B. Lippincott &amp; Company|page=[https://archive.org/details/thinkersandthin00garrgoog/page/n187 182]}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Interpretation==
As put succinctly by Krauth (1872), &quot;That cannot doubt which does not think, and that cannot think which does not exist. I doubt, I think, I exist.&quot;&lt;ref name=Krauth/&gt;

The phrase ''cogito, ergo sum'' is not used in Descartes's ''[[Meditations on First Philosophy]]'' but the term &quot;the ''cogito''&quot; is used to refer to an argument from it.  In the ''Meditations'', Descartes phrases the conclusion of the argument as &quot;that the proposition, ''I am, I exist,'' is [[logical truth|necessarily true]] whenever it is put forward by me or conceived in my mind.&quot; (''Meditation'' II)

At the beginning of the second meditation, having reached what he considers to be the ultimate level of doubt—his argument from the existence of a deceiving god—Descartes examines his beliefs to see if any have survived the doubt. In his belief in his own existence, he finds that it is impossible to doubt that he exists.  Even if there were a deceiving god (or an [[evil demon]]), one's belief in their own existence would be secure, for there is no way one could be deceived unless one existed in order to be deceived.

&lt;blockquote&gt;But I have convinced myself that there is absolutely nothing in the world, no sky, no earth, no minds, no bodies.  Does it now follow that I, too, do not exist? No. If I convinced myself of something [or thought anything at all], then I certainly existed. But there is a deceiver of supreme power and cunning who deliberately and constantly deceives me.  In that case, I, too, undoubtedly exist, if he deceives me; and let him deceive me as much as he can, he will never bring it about that I am nothing, so long as I think that I am something.  So, after considering everything very thoroughly, I must finally conclude that the proposition, ''I am, I exist,'' is necessarily true whenever it is put forward by me or conceived in my mind. (AT VII 25; CSM II 16–17{{efn|name= &quot;abbreviations&quot;}})&lt;/blockquote&gt;

There are three important notes to keep in mind here. First, he claims only the certainty of ''his own'' existence from the first-person point of view — he has not proved the existence of other minds at this point. This is something that has to be thought through by each of us for ourselves, as we follow the course of the meditations. Second, he does not say that his existence is necessary; he says that ''if he thinks'', then necessarily he exists (see the [[instantiation principle]]). Third, this proposition &quot;I am, I exist&quot; is held true not based on a deduction (as mentioned above) or on empirical induction but on the clarity and self-evidence of the proposition. Descartes does not use this first certainty, the ''cogito'', as a foundation upon which to build further knowledge; rather, it is the firm ground upon which he can stand as he works to discover further truths.&lt;ref&gt;''Self, Reason, and Freedom: A New Light on Descartes' Metaphysics'' Andrea Christofidou; chapter 2&lt;/ref&gt;  As he puts it:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Archimedes used to demand just one firm and immovable point in order to shift the entire earth; so I too can hope for great things if I manage to find just one thing, however slight, that is certain and unshakable. (AT VII 24; CSM II 16){{efn|name= &quot;abbreviations&quot;}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

According to many Descartes specialists, including [[Étienne Gilson]], the goal of Descartes in establishing this first truth is to demonstrate the capacity of his criterion — the immediate clarity and distinctiveness of self-evident propositions — to establish true and justified propositions despite having adopted a method of generalized doubt. As a consequence of this demonstration, Descartes considers science and mathematics to be justified to the extent that their proposals are established on a similarly immediate clarity, distinctiveness, and self-evidence that presents itself to the mind. The originality of Descartes's thinking, therefore, is not so much in expressing the ''cogito'' — a feat accomplished by other predecessors, as we shall see — but on using the ''cogito'' as demonstrating the most fundamental epistemological principle, that science and mathematics are justified by relying on clarity, distinctiveness, and self-evidence.
[[Baruch Spinoza]] in &quot;''[[Principia philosophiae cartesianae]]''&quot; at its ''Prolegomenon'' identified &quot;cogito ergo sum&quot; the &quot;''ego sum cogitans''&quot; (I am a thinking being) as the thinking [[substance theory|substance]] with his [[ontology|ontological]] interpretation.

==Predecessors==
Although the idea expressed in ''cogito, ergo sum'' is widely attributed to Descartes, he was not the first to mention it. [[Plato]] spoke about the &quot;knowledge of knowledge&quot; (Greek νόησις νοήσεως ''nóesis noéseos'') and [[Aristotle]] explains the idea in full length:
&lt;blockquote&gt;But if life itself is good and pleasant (...) and if one who sees is conscious that he sees, one who hears that he hears, one who walks that he walks and similarly for all the other human activities there is a faculty that is conscious of their exercise, so that whenever we perceive, we are conscious that we perceive, and whenever we think, we are conscious that we think, and to be conscious that we are perceiving or thinking is to be conscious that we exist... (''[[Nicomachean Ethics]]'', 1170a25 ff.)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In the late sixth or early fifth century BC, [[Parmenides]] is quoted as saying &quot;For to be aware and to be are the same&quot; (B3).  [[Augustine of Hippo]] in ''[[City of God (book)|De Civitate Dei]]'' writes ''Si […] fallor, sum'' (&quot;If I am mistaken, I am&quot;) (book XI, 26), and also anticipates modern refutations of the concept.  Furthermore, in the ''[[Enchiridion of Augustine|Enchiridion]]'' Augustine attempts to refute [[skepticism]] by stating, &quot;[B]y not positively affirming that they are alive, the skeptics ward off the appearance of error in themselves, yet they do make errors simply by showing themselves alive; one cannot err who is not alive. That we live is therefore not only true, but it is altogether certain as well&quot; (Chapter 7 section 20). In 1640 correspondence, Descartes thanked two colleagues for drawing his attention to Augustine and notes similarity and difference. (See CSMK III 159, 161.)

Another predecessor was [[Avicenna]]'s &quot;[[Floating man|Floating Man]]&quot; [[thought experiment]] on human [[self-awareness]] and [[self-consciousness]].&lt;ref name=Leaman&gt;[[Hossein Nasr|Nasr, Seyyed Hossein]] and [[Oliver Leaman|Leaman, Oliver]] (1996), ''History of Islamic Philosophy'', Routledge, p. 315, {{ISBN|0-415-13159-6}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The 8th century Hindu philosopher [[Adi Shankara]] wrote in a similar fashion, No one thinks, 'I am not', arguing that one's existence cannot be doubted, as there must be someone there to doubt.&lt;ref name=Radhakrishnan.S&gt;Radhakrishnan, S. (1948), ''Indian Philosophy, vol II'', p. 476, [[George Allen &amp; Unwin Ltd]],&lt;/ref&gt; The central idea of ''cogito, ergo sum'' is also the topic of [[Mandukya Upanishad]].

Spanish philosopher [[Gómez Pereira]] in his 1554 work ''De Inmortalitate Animae'', published in 1749, wrote &quot;''nosco me aliquid noscere, &amp; quidquid noscit, est, ergo ego sum''&quot; (&quot;I know that I know something, anyone who knows exists, then I exist&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;Gómez Pereira, ''Antoniana Margarita'': &quot;De Immortalitate Animae&quot;, 1749 [1554], p. 277.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Santos López, Modesto (1986). &quot;Gómez Pereira, médico y filósofo medinense&quot;. In: ''Historia de Medina del Campo y su Tierra, volumen I: Nacimiento y expansión'', ed. by Eufemio Lorenzo Sanz, 1986.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Critique ==
=== Use of &quot;I&quot; ===
In ''Descartes, The Project of Pure Enquiry'', [[Bernard Williams]] provides a history and full evaluation of this issue. The first to raise the &quot;I&quot; problem was [[Pierre Gassendi]]. He &quot;points out that recognition that one has a set of thoughts does not imply that one is a particular thinker or another. Were we to move from the observation that there is thinking occurring to the attribution of this thinking to a particular agent, we would simply [[begging the question|assume what we set out to prove]], namely, that there exists a particular person endowed with the capacity for thought&quot;. In other words, &quot;the only claim that is indubitable here is the agent-independent claim that there is cognitive activity present&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/gassendi/|title=Pierre Gassendi|author=Fisher, Saul|date=2005|accessdate=1 December 2014}} from [[Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]&lt;/ref&gt; The objection, as presented by [[Georg Christoph Lichtenberg|Georg Lichtenberg]], is that rather than supposing an entity that is thinking, Descartes should have said: &quot;thinking is occurring.&quot; That is, whatever the force of the ''cogito'', Descartes draws too much from it; the existence of a thinking thing, the reference of the &quot;I,&quot; is more than the ''cogito'' can justify. [[Friedrich Nietzsche]] criticized the phrase in that it presupposes that there is an &quot;I&quot;, that there is such an activity as &quot;thinking&quot;, and that &quot;I&quot; know what &quot;thinking&quot; is. He suggested a more appropriate phrase would be &quot;it thinks&quot; wherein the &quot;it&quot; could be an impersonal subject as in the sentence &quot;It is raining.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;thinkingisoccurring&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.aporia.byu.edu/pdfs/monte-Sum_ergo_cogito.pdf|title=Sum, Ergo Cogito: Nietzsche Re-orders Decartes|last=Monte|first=Jonas|date=2015|website=Aporia.byu.edu|publisher=BYU|access-date=17 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== &lt;span id=&quot;Kierkegaard's critique&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Kierkegaard ===
The Danish philosopher [[Søren Kierkegaard]] calls the phrase a [[Tautology (logic)|tautology]] in his ''[[Concluding Unscientific Postscript]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Kierkegaard, Søren. ''Philosophical Fragments''. Trans. Hong, Princeton, 1985. p. 38-42.&lt;/ref&gt; He argues that the ''cogito'' already presupposes the existence of &quot;I&quot;, and therefore concluding with existence is logically trivial. Kierkegaard's argument can be made clearer if one extracts the premise &quot;I think&quot; into the premises &quot;'x' thinks&quot; and &quot;I am that 'x'&quot;, where &quot;x&quot; is used as a placeholder in order to disambiguate the &quot;I&quot; from the thinking thing.&lt;ref&gt;Schönbaumsfeld, Genia. ''A Confusion of the Spheres''. Oxford, 2007. p.168-170.&lt;/ref&gt;

Here, the ''cogito'' has already assumed the &quot;I&quot;'s existence as that which thinks. For Kierkegaard, Descartes is merely &quot;developing the content of a concept&quot;, namely that the &quot;I&quot;, which already exists, thinks.&lt;ref&gt;Kierkegaard, Søren. ''Philosophical Fragments''. Trans. Hong, Princeton, 1985. p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt; As Kierkegaard argues, the proper logical flow of argument is that existence is already assumed or presupposed in order for thinking to occur, not that existence is concluded from that thinking.&lt;ref&gt;Archie, Lee C., &quot;Søren Kierkegaard, ''God's Existence Cannot Be Proved''&quot;. Philosophy of Religion. Lander Philosophy, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== &lt;span id=&quot;Williams's critique&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Williams ===
Bernard Williams claims that what we are dealing with when we talk of thought, or when we say &quot;I am thinking,&quot; is something conceivable from a [[Grammatical person|third-person]] perspective; namely objective &quot;thought-events&quot; in the former case, and an [[Objectivity (philosophy)|objective]] thinker in the latter. He argues, first, that it is impossible to make sense of &quot;there is thinking&quot; without relativizing it to ''something.''  However, this something cannot be Cartesian egos, because it is impossible to differentiate objectively between things just on the basis of the pure content of consciousness. The obvious problem is that, through [[introspection]], or our experience of [[consciousness]], we have no way of moving to conclude the existence of any third-personal fact, to conceive of which would require something above and beyond just the purely subjective contents of the mind.{{citation needed|date=January 2018}}

=== &lt;span id=&quot;Heidegger's critique&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Heidegger ===
As a critic of Cartesian subjectivity, Heidegger sought to ground human subjectivity in death as that certainty which individualizes and authenticates our being. As he wrote in 1927:

&quot;This certainty, that &quot;I myself am in that I will die,&quot; is the basic certainty of Dasein itself. It is a genuine statement of Dasein, while ''cogito sum'' is only the semblance of such a statement. If such pointed formulations mean anything at all, then the appropriate statement pertaining to Dasein in its being would have to be ''sum moribundus'' [I am in dying], ''moribundus'' not as someone gravely ill or wounded, but insofar as I am, I am ''moribundus''. The ''MORIBUNDUS'' first gives the ''SUM'' its sense.&quot;

=== &lt;span id=&quot;John Macmurray's critique&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; John Macmurray ===
The Scottish philosopher [[John Macmurray]] rejects the ''cogito'' outright in order to place action at the center of a philosophical system he entitles the Form of the Personal. &quot;We must reject this, both as standpoint and as method. If this be philosophy, then philosophy is a bubble floating in an atmosphere of unreality.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Macmurray, John. ''The Self as Agent''. Humanity books, 1991. p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt; The reliance on thought creates an irreconcilable dualism between thought and action in which the [[:wikt:unity|unity]] of experience is lost, thus dissolving the integrity of our selves, and destroying any connection with reality. In order to formulate a more adequate ''cogito'', Macmurray proposes the substitution of &quot;I do&quot; for &quot;I think&quot;,  ultimately leading to a belief in God as an agent to whom all persons stand in relation.

==See also==
{{Portal|Philosophy}}
* [[Floating man]]
* [[List of Latin phrases (full)|List of Latin phrases]]
* [[Solipsism]]
* [[Brain in a vat]]

==Notes==
{{Notelist | refs=
{{efn|name = &quot;capitalization and punctuation&quot;|Descartes wrote this phrase only once, in a posthumously published lesser-known work.&lt;ref name=&quot;AT&quot;&gt;{{Citation | editor-last1 = Adam | editor-first1 = Charles | editor-last2 = Tannery | editor-first2 = Paul | author-link = René Descartes | contribution = La Recherche de la Vérité par La Lumiere Naturale | title = ''Oeuvres de Descartes'' | volume = X | year = 1901 | page = 535 | contribution-url = https://fr.wikisource.org/wiki/Page:Descartes_-_Œuvres,_éd._Adam_et_Tannery,_X.djvu/535}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It appeared there mid-sentence, uncapitalized, and with a comma. (Commas were not used in [[classical Latin]] but were a regular feature of scholastic Latin. Most modern reference works show it with a comma, but it is often presented without a comma in academic work and in popular usage.)

In the primary source, Descartes's [[Principles of Philosophy|''Principia Philosophiae'']], the proposition appears as '''''ego cogito, ergo sum'''''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Descartes1644&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Descartes, René |title=Principia Philosophiae |publisher=apud Ludovicum Elzevirium |url=https://archive.org/details/ita-bnc-mag-00001403-001 |quote=“Ego Cogito ergo sum”. |pages=[https://archive.org/details/ita-bnc-mag-00001403-001/page/n68 30], 31 |year=1644}}&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

{{efn|name = &quot;GutPrinc4391&quot; | Translation from {{Gutenberg | no= 4391 | name=The Principles of Philosophy | bullet=none}}.}}

{{efn |name=&quot;formatting&quot; |Formatting note: ''cogito'' variants in this section are highlighted in boldface to facilitate comparison; italics are used only as in originals.}}
}}

==References==
{{reflist|2|refs=
&lt;ref name=&quot;Cress1986&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Descartes, René | title=Discourse on Method and Meditations on First Philosophy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=r7F27Ra9ecoC&amp;pg=PA65|others=Translated by Donald A. Cress|year=1986|isbn=978-1-60384-551-9|pages=65
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Haldane1911&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Descartes, René | title=The Philosophical Works of Descartes, rendered into English|url=https://archive.org/details/philosophicalwor01desc |others=Translated by Elizabeth S. Haldane and G.R.T. Ross| publisher=Cambridge University Press | year=1911}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Haldane2007&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Descartes, René | title=Meditations on first philosophy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=t4r9iLV2ZXYC&amp;pg=PA29|others=Translated by Elizabeth S. Haldane|year=1960|isbn=978-1-61536-207-3|pages=29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas1765&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Thomas, Antoine Léonard |title=Éloge de René Descartes|publisher=E. van Harrevelt |url=https://archive.org/details/b30386305|page=[https://archive.org/details/b30386305/page/32 32] |year=1765}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Cousin1824&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Cousin, Victor | title=Oeuvres de Descartes|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=m4eiieOMwQIC&amp;pg=PA60|year=1824}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Edinburgh1890&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=The Edinburgh Review for July, 1890 … October, 1890|
page=469|publisher=Leonard Scott Publication Co.|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=fKjPAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA469|year=1890}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Descartes2007&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Descartes, René |title=The Correspondence between Princess Elisabeth of Bohemia and René Descartes|page=5|others=Translated by [[Lisa Shapiro]]|publisher=University of Chicago Press|isbn=978-0226204420|year=2007|title-link=The Correspondence between Princess Elisabeth of Bohemia and René Descartes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Kline1967&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Kline, George L. |title=Naturalism and Historical Understanding |page=85 |chapter=Randall's Interpretation of the Philosophies of Descartes, Spinoza, and Leibniz |editor1=John Peter Anton|publisher=SUNY Press|year=1967}}&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

==Further reading==
* Abraham, W.E. &quot;Disentangling the Cogito&quot;, ''Mind'' 83:329 (1974)
* {{cite book | last = Baird | first = Forrest E. | authorlink = |author2=Walter Kaufmann | title = From Plato to Derrida | publisher = Pearson Prentice Hall | year = 2008 | location = Upper Saddle River, New Jersey | pages = | url = | doi = | id = | isbn = 978-0-13-158591-1 }}* Boufoy-Bastick, Z. ''Introducing 'Applicable Knowledge' as a Challenge to the Attainment of Absolute Knowledge '', ''Sophia Journal of Philosophy'', VIII (2005), pp 39–52.
* Descartes, R. (translated by John Cottingham), ''Meditations on First Philosophy'', in ''The Philosophical Writings of Descartes'' vol. II (edited Cottingham, Stoothoff, and Murdoch; Cambridge University Press, 1984) {{ISBN|0-521-28808-8}}
*Christofidou, A. 'Self, Reason, and Freedom: A New Light on Descartes' Metaphysics' (Roughtledge 2013)
* Hatfield, G. ''Routledge Philosophy Guidebook to Descartes and the Meditations'' (Routledge, 2003) {{ISBN|0-415-11192-7}}
* Kierkegaard, S. ''Concluding Unscientific Postscript'' (Princeton, 1985) {{ISBN|978-0-691-02081-5}}
* Kierkegaard, S. ''Philosophical Fragments'' (Princeton, 1985) {{ISBN|978-0-691-02036-5}}
* Williams, B. ''Descartes, The Project of Pure Enquiry'' (Penguin, 1978) {{Oclc number|4025089}}

==External links==
* {{Cite SEP|url-id=descartes-epistemology|title=Descartes's Epistemology}}

{{metaphysics}}
{{Catholic philosophy footer}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cogito Ergo Sum}}
[[Category:René Descartes|René Descartes ]]
[[Category:Arguments in philosophy of mind]]
[[Category:Cartesianism]]
[[Category:Concepts in epistemology]]
[[Category:Concepts in metaphysics]]
[[Category:Concepts in the philosophy of mind]]
[[Category:Concepts in the philosophy of science]]
[[Category:Epistemology]]
[[Category:Latin philosophical phrases]]
[[Category:Latin quotations]]
[[Category:Latin words and phrases]]
[[Category:Metaphysics]]
[[Category:Metaphysics of mind]]
[[Category:Mind]]
[[Category:Ontology]]
[[Category:Philosophical arguments]]
[[Category:Philosophical concepts]]
[[Category:Philosophical theories]]
[[Category:Qualia]]
[[Category:Self]]
[[Category:Thought]]
[[Category:Words and phrases introduced in the 17th century]]
[[Category:Quotations from literature]]</text>
      <sha1>t7coizidsnk89nm1pw9293q6wz0driz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
