  <page>
    <title>Clement of Alexandria</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7342</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937828952</id>
      <parentid>937408253</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-27T13:33:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>2018 S Classics</username>
        <id>34651155</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Corrected typo 'Hypopotoses' in 'Hypotyposes'</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Christian theologian}}
{{Good Article}}
{{Infobox philosopher
| honorific_prefix  = 
| name              = Clement of Alexandria
| birth _name       = Titus Flavius Clemens
| honorific_suffix  = 
| image             = Clement alexandrin.jpg 
| caption           = Clement from Les vrais pourtraits et vies des hommes illustres grecz, latins et payens (1584) by [[André Thévet]]
| alt               = 
| birth_date        = c. 150
| death_date        = c. 215
| birth_place       = [[Athens]]
| death_place       = [[Jerusalem]]
| notable_works     = ''[[Protrepticus_(Clement)|Protrepticus]]&lt;br&gt;[[Paedagogus]]&lt;br&gt;[[Stromata]]''
| era               = [[Ancient philosophy]]&lt;br&gt;[[Patristic Period]]
| region            = [[Western Philosophy]]&lt;br&gt;
| school_tradition  = [[Middle Platonism]]&lt;br&gt;[[Alexandrian school]]
| other_names       = Clement Alexandrine
| main_interests    = [[Christian theology]]
| institutions      = [[Catechetical School of Alexandria]]
| notable_students  = [[Origen]] and [[Alexander of Jerusalem|Alexander]]
| notable_ideas     = {{Flatlist}}
*[[Thrones]]
*[[Nephilim#Fallen angels|Fallen Nephilim]]
*[[Epistle of Barnabas#Status_for_Christians|Barnabas authorship]]&lt;ref name=Bromiley&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=wo8csizDv0gC&amp;pg=PA206&amp;dq=clement+alexandria+barnabas&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjO5_eo7NnfAhVRuXEKHdEkCdwQ6AEILjAB#v=onepage&amp;q=clement%20alexandria%20barnabas&amp;f=false Geoffrey W. Bromiley (editor), ''The International Standard Bible Encyclopedia'' (Eerdmans 1979), vol. 1, p. 206]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Limbo of the Fathers]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.earlychristianwritings.com/text/clement-stromata-book6.html Stromata, book VI, chapter VI]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Purgatory]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Birth of Purgatory|publisher=	University of Chicago Press|isbn= 9780226470832|quote=to say a few words about the two Greek &quot;inventors&quot; of Purgatory, Clement of Alexandria|page=52}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Endflatlist}}
| influences        = [[Stoics]], [[Pythagoras]], [[Plato]], [[Heraclitus]], [[Pantaenus]], [[Xenophanes]] and [[Homer]] 
| influenced        = Virtually all of subsequent [[Christian philosophy]] and Catholic theology, Including [[Benedict XVI]] and [[Eusebius]]
}}
{{Infobox saint
|name= Saint Clement of Alexandria
|feast_day=4 December ([[Eastern Catholicism]], [[Anglicanism]]) &lt;br&gt; 
5 December ([[Calendar of saints (Episcopal Church in the United States of America)|Episcopal Church]], [[Anglicanism]])
|venerated_in= [[Oriental Orthodoxy]]&lt;br&gt; [[Eastern Catholicism]]&lt;br&gt; [[Anglican Communion]]
&lt;br&gt; 
|image=ClemensVonAlexandrien.jpg
|imagesize=220px
|caption=Icon of Clement of Alexandria
|titles=Church Father, Theologian
|beatified_date=
|beatified_place=
|canonized_date= Pre-congregation
|canonized_place=
|canonized_by=
|attributes=
|patronage=
|major_shrine=
|suppressed_date=1586
|suppressed_by=[[Pope Sixtus V]]
|issues=Regarded as a [[heretic]] by [[Photius]].
}}{{Catholic philosophy}}
'''Titus Flavius Clemens''', also known as '''Clement of Alexandria''' ({{lang-el|Κλήμης ὁ Ἀλεξανδρεύς}}; c. 150 – c. 215),&lt;ref&gt;Buell (1999), [https://books.google.com/books?id=Q850NV-C5fEC&amp;pg=PA10 p. 10]&lt;/ref&gt; was a [[Christian theology|Christian theologian]] and philosopher who taught at the [[Catechetical School of Alexandria]]. A convert to Christianity, he was an educated man who was familiar with [[Ancient Greek philosophy|classical Greek philosophy]] and [[Ancient Greek literature|literature]]. As his three major works demonstrate, Clement was influenced by Hellenistic philosophy to a greater extent than any other Christian thinker of his time, and in particular by [[Plato]] and the [[Stoicism|Stoics]].&lt;ref&gt;Outler (1940), p. 217&lt;/ref&gt; His secret works, which exist only in fragments, suggest that he was also familiar with pre-Christian [[Judaism|Jewish]] esotericism and [[Gnosticism]]. In one of his works he argued that Greek philosophy had its origin among non-Greeks, claiming that both Plato and [[Pythagoras]] were taught by Egyptian scholars.&lt;ref&gt;Press (2003), p. 83&lt;/ref&gt; Among his pupils were [[Origen]] and [[Alexander of Jerusalem]].

Clement is usually regarded as a [[Church Father]]. He is venerated as a [[saint]] in [[Coptic Orthodox Church of Alexandria|Coptic Christianity]], [[Eastern Catholicism]], [[Ethiopian Christianity]] and [[Anglicanism]]. He was previously revered in [[Western Catholicism]], but his name was removed from the [[Roman Martyrology]] in 1586 by [[Pope Sixtus V]] on the advice of [[Baronius]].

== Biography ==
Neither Clement's birthdate or birthplace is known with any degree of certainty. It is conjectured that he was born sometime around 150.   According to [[Epiphanius Scholasticus]], he was born in Athens, but there is also a tradition of an [[Alexandria]]n birth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fer1974-13&quot;&gt;Ferguson (1974), p.&amp;nbsp;13.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Westcott (1877), p.&amp;nbsp;560.&lt;/ref&gt;

His parents were [[paganism|pagans]], and Clement was a convert to Christianity. In the ''[[Protrepticus (Clement)|Protrepticus]]'' he displays an extensive knowledge of Greek mythology and [[Greco-Roman mysteries|mystery religions]], which could only have arisen from the practice of his family's religion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fer1974-13&quot; /&gt;

Having rejected paganism as a young man due to its perceived moral corruption, he travelled in [[Greece]], [[Asia Minor]], [[Syria Palaestina|Palestine]] and [[Egypt]]. Clement's journeys were primarily a religious undertaking. In Greece, he encountered an [[Ionia]]n theologian, who has been identified as [[Athenagoras of Athens]]; while in the east, he was taught by an Assyrian, sometimes identified with [[Tatian]], and a Jew, who was possibly [[Theophilus, bishop of Caesarea|Theophilus of Caesarea]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fer1974-14&quot;&gt;Ferguson (1974), p.&amp;nbsp;14.&lt;/ref&gt;

In around 180, Clement reached [[Alexandria]],&lt;ref&gt;''Stromateis'' 1.1.11.2&lt;/ref&gt; where he met [[Pantaenus]], who taught at the Catechetical School of Alexandria.&lt;ref&gt;Eusebius, ''Eccl. Hist''. 6.13.2; 6.6.1&lt;/ref&gt; [[Eusebius]] suggests that Pantaenus was the head of the school, but it is controversial whether the institutions of the school were formalized in this way before the time of [[Origen]].&lt;ref name=Fer1974-15&gt;Ferguson (1974), p.&amp;nbsp;15.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hägg (2006), pp.&amp;nbsp;56–9.&lt;/ref&gt;{{NoteTag|Proponents of a formalized leadership and succession suggest that Clement succeeded Pantaenus as leader of the school, and was succeeded himself by Origen.&lt;ref&gt;Itter (2009), pp.&amp;nbsp;9–10.&lt;/ref&gt;}}&lt;ref&gt;Osborn (2008), pp.&amp;nbsp;19–24.&lt;/ref&gt; Clement studied under Pantaenus, and was ordained to the priesthood by [[Pope Julian of Alexandria|Pope Julian]] before 189. Otherwise, virtually nothing is known of Clement's life in Alexandria. He may have been married, a conjecture supported by his writings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fer1974-16&quot;&gt;Ferguson (1974), p.&amp;nbsp;16.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Septimius Severus#Religious matters|Severian persecutions]] of 202–203, Clement left Alexandria. In 211, [[Alexander of Jerusalem]] wrote a letter commending him to the Church of [[Antioch]],&lt;ref&gt;Eusebius, ''Eccl. Hist''. 6.14.8&lt;/ref&gt; which may imply that Clement was living in [[Cappadocia]] or Jerusalem at that time. The date and location of his death are unknown.

==Theological works==
[[File:Klementos Alexandreos ta heuriskomena.tif|thumb|''Klementos Alexandreos ta heuriskomena'' (1715)]]

===Trilogy===
Three of Clement's major works have survived in full, and they are collectively referred to as the trilogy:&lt;ref&gt;Osborn (2008), p. 5&lt;/ref&gt;
*the ''[[Protrepticus (Clement)|Protrepticus]]'' (''Exhortation'') – written c. 195.&lt;ref name=Fer197417&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 17&lt;/ref&gt;
*the ''[[Paedagogus]]'' (''Tutor'') – written c. 198.&lt;ref name=Fer197417/&gt;
*the ''[[Stromata]]'' (''Miscellanies'') – written c. 198 – c. 203.&lt;ref name=Fer197417/&gt;

====''Protrepticus''====
{{main|Protrepticus (Clement)}}
[[File:DSC00355 - Orfeo (epoca romana) - Foto G. Dall'Orto.jpg|thumb|right|The [[Orphism (religion)|Orphic mysteries]] are used as an example of the false cults of Greek paganism in the ''Protrepticus''. ]]
The ''Protrepticus'' is, as its title suggests, an exhortation to the pagans of Greece to adopt Christianity, and within it Clement demonstrates his extensive knowledge of pagan mythology and theology. It is chiefly important due to Clement's exposition of religion as an anthropological phenomenon.&lt;ref name=Dro1989138&gt;Droge (1989), p. 138&lt;/ref&gt; After a short philosophical discussion, it opens with a history of Greek religion in seven stages.&lt;ref&gt;Droge (1989), p. 130&lt;/ref&gt; Clement suggests that at first, men mistakenly believed [[Sky deity|the Sun, the Moon and other heavenly bodies]] to be gods. The next development was the worship of the products of agriculture, from which he contends the cults of [[Demeter]] and [[Dionysus]] arose.&lt;ref name=Dro1989131&gt;Droge (1989), p. 131&lt;/ref&gt; Man then paid reverence to revenge, and deified human feelings of [[eros|love]] and [[Phobos (mythology)|fear]], among others. In the following stage, the poets [[Hesiod]] and [[Homer]] attempt to enumerate the Gods; Hesiod's [[Theogony]] giving the number of twelve. Finally, men proclaimed other men, such as [[Asclepius]] and [[Heracles]], deities.&lt;ref name=Dro1989131/&gt; Discussing [[idolatry]], Clement contends that the objects of primitive religion were unshaped wood and stone, and idols thus arose when such natural items were carved.&lt;ref name = Fer197448&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 48&lt;/ref&gt; Following [[Plato]], Clement is critical of all forms of visual art, suggesting that artworks are but illusions and &quot;deadly toys&quot;.&lt;ref name = Fer197448/&gt;

Clement criticizes Greek paganism in the ''Protrepticus'' on the basis that its deities are both false and poor moral examples, and he attacks the mystery religions for their obscurantism and trivial rituals.&lt;ref name = Fer197448/&gt; In particular, the worshippers of [[Dionysus]] are ridiculed for their ritual use of children's [[toy]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Burrus (2011), p. 101&lt;/ref&gt; He suggests at some points that the pagan deities are based on humans, but at others that they are [[misanthropic]] demons, and he cites several classical sources in support of this second hypothesis.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 50&lt;/ref&gt; Clement, like many pre-Nicene fathers, writes favourably about [[Euhemerus]] and other rationalist philosophers, on the grounds that they at least saw the flaws in paganism. However, his greatest praise is reserved for Plato, whose [[Apophatic theology|apophatic]] views of God prefigure Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), pp. 55–6&lt;/ref&gt;

The figure of [[Orpheus]] is prominent throughout the narrative, and Clement contrasts his song, representing pagan superstition, with the divine [[Logos (Christianity)|Logos]] of Christ.&lt;ref&gt;de Jáuregui (2010), p. 132&lt;/ref&gt; According to Clement, through conversion to Christianity alone can man fully participate in the Logos, which is universal truth.&lt;ref&gt;Sharkey (2009), p. 159&lt;/ref&gt;

====''Paedagogus''====
{{main|Paedagogus}}
[[File:Jesus-Christ-from-Hagia-Sophia.jpg|thumb|left|Christ, the Logos incarnate, is the ''Paedagogus'' of the work's title.]]
This work's title, translatable as &quot;tutor&quot;, refers to Christ as the teacher of all mankind, and it features an extended metaphor of Christians as children.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 76&lt;/ref&gt; It is not simply instructional : the author intends to show how the Christian should respond to the Love of God authentically.&lt;ref&gt;Osborn (2008), p. 244&lt;/ref&gt; Clement, following Plato ([[Republic (Plato)|Republic]] 4:441), divides life into three elements: character, actions and passions. The first having been dealt with in the ''Protrepticus'', he devotes the ''Paedagogus'' to reflections on Christ's role in teaching us to act morally and to control our passions.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 69&lt;/ref&gt; Despite its explicitly Christian nature, Clement's work draws on [[Stoicism|Stoic philosophy]] and [[Ancient Greek literature|pagan literature]]; Homer alone is cited over sixty times in the work.&lt;ref&gt;Irvine (2006), p. 164&lt;/ref&gt;

Although Christ, like man, is made in the [[image of God]], he alone shares the likeness of God the Father.&lt;ref&gt;Ogliari (2003), p. 200&lt;/ref&gt; Christ is both [[sinless]] and [[Apatheia|apathetic]], and thus by striving to [[imitation of Christ|imitate Christ]], man can achieve salvation. To Clement, sin is involuntary, and thus irrational [αλόγον], removed only through the wisdom of the Logos.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 71&lt;/ref&gt; God's guidance of us away from sin is thus a manifestation of [[Love of God|God's universal love for mankind]]. The word play on λόγος and αλόγον is characteristic of Clement's writing, and may be rooted in the [[Epicurus|Epicurean]] belief that relationships between words are deeply reflective of relationships between the objects they signify.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 73&lt;/ref&gt;

Clement argues for the [[gender equality|equality of sexes]], on the grounds that salvation is extended to all of mankind equally.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 72&lt;/ref&gt; Unusually, he suggests that Christ is neither male or female, and that God the Father has both male and female aspects: the [[eucharist]] is described as milk from the breast (Christ) of the Father.&lt;ref name=Ma2004184&gt;Gill (2004), p. 184&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Berger (2011), pp. 74–5&lt;/ref&gt; He is supportive of women playing an active role in the leadership of the church, and provides a list of women he considers inspirational, which includes both Biblical and Classical Greek figures. It has been suggested that Clement's progressive views on gender as set out in the ''Paedagogus'' were influenced by [[Gnosticism]].&lt;ref name=Ma2004184/&gt; However, later in the work, he argues against the Gnostics that [[faith]], not esoteric knowledge [γνῶσις], is required for salvation. According to Clement, it is through faith in Christ that we are enlightened and come to know God.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 75&lt;/ref&gt;

In the second book, Clement provides practical rules on living a Christian life. He argues against overindulgence in food and in favour of good [[table manners]].&lt;ref name=Fer197480&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 80&lt;/ref&gt; While prohibiting drunkenness, he promotes the drinking of alcohol in moderation following {{Bibleverse|1|Timothy|5:23|KJV}}.&lt;ref name=Fer197480/&gt; Clement argues for a simple way of life in accordance with the innate simplicity of Christian [[monotheism]]. He condemns elaborate and expensive furnishings and clothing, and argues against overly passionate music and perfumes. But Clement does not believe in the abandoning of worldly pleasures and argues that the Christian should be able to express his joy in God's creation through gaiety and partying.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 82&lt;/ref&gt; He opposes the wearing of garlands, because the picking of the flowers ultimately kills a beautiful creation of God, and the garland resembles the [[crown of thorns]].&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 85&lt;/ref&gt; Clement treats [[sex]] at some length. He argues that both [[promiscuity]] and [[sexual abstinence]] are unnatural, and that the main goal of [[human sexuality]] is procreation.&lt;ref&gt;Kochuthara (2007) , p. 145&lt;/ref&gt; [[Homosexuality]], [[prostitution]], [[concubinage]], [[adultery]] and coitus with pregnant women should all be avoided as they will not act towards the generation of legitimate offspring.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 87&lt;/ref&gt;

The third book continues along a similar vein, condemning [[cosmetics]] on the grounds that it is our souls, not our bodies, that we should seek to beautify.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 91&lt;/ref&gt; Clement also opposes the dyeing of men's hair and male [[depilation]] as [[effeminate|effeminacy]]. He advises choosing one's company carefully, to avoid being corrupted by immoral people, and while arguing that material wealth is no sin in itself, it is too likely to distract one from the infinitely more important spiritual wealth which is found in Christ.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 94&lt;/ref&gt; The work finishes with selections of scripture supporting Clement's argument, and following a prayer, the lyrics of a [[hymn]].&lt;ref&gt;Murphy (1941), p. 32&lt;/ref&gt;

====''Stromata''====
[[File:Alpine flora logan pass.jpg|thumb|right|Clement describes the ''Stromata'' as a work on various subjects, which spring up in the text like flowers in a meadow.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 107&lt;/ref&gt;]]
{{main| Stromata}}
The contents of the ''Stromata'', as its title suggests, are miscellaneous. Its place in the trilogy is disputed – Clement initially intended to write the ''Didasculus'', a work which would complement the practical guidance of the ''Paedagogus'' with a more intellectual schooling in theology.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 106&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Stromata'' is less systematic and ordered than Clement's other works, and it has been theorized by André Méhat that it was intended for a limited, esoteric readership.&lt;ref&gt;Osborn (2008), p. 8&lt;/ref&gt; Although [[Eusebius]] wrote of eight books of the work, only seven undoubtedly survive. [[Photius]], writing in the 9th century, found various text appended to manuscripts of the seven canonical books, which lead [[Daniel Heinsius]] to suggest that the original eighth book is lost, and he identified the text purported to be from the eighth book as fragments of the ''Hypotyposes''.&lt;ref&gt;Kaye (1835), p. 221&lt;/ref&gt;

The first book starts on the topic of Greek philosophy. Consistent with his other writing, Clement affirms that philosophy had a [[propaedeutics|propaedeutic]] role for the Greek, similar to the function of the [[Torah|law]] for [[Judaism|the Jews]].&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), pp. 108–9&lt;/ref&gt; He then embarks on a discussion of the origins of Greek culture and technology, arguing that most of the important figures in the Greek world were foreigners, and (erroneously) that [[Jewish culture]] was the most significant influence on Greece.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), pp. 113–6&lt;/ref&gt; In an attempt to demonstrate the primacy of [[Moses]], Clement gives an extended chronology of the world, wherein he dates the birth of Christ to 25 April or May, 4-2 B.C., and the creation of the world to 5592 B.C. The books ends with a discussion on the origin of languages and the possibility of a Jewish influence on Plato.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), pp. 117–9&lt;/ref&gt;

The second book is largely devoted to the [[Faith in Christianity|respective roles of faith and philosophical argument]]. Clement contends that while both are important, the [[Fear of God (religion)|fear of God]] is foremost, because through faith one receives divine wisdom.&lt;ref&gt;Osborn (1994), p. 3&lt;/ref&gt; To Clement, [[scripture]] is an innately true primitive philosophy which is complemented by human reason through the Logos.&lt;ref&gt;Osborn (1994), p. 4&lt;/ref&gt; Faith is voluntary, and the decision to believe is a crucial fundamental step in becoming closer to God.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 121&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Osborn (1994), p. 7&lt;/ref&gt; It is never irrational, as it is founded on the knowledge of the truth of the Logos, but all knowledge proceeds from faith, as first principles are unprovable outside a systematic structure.&lt;ref&gt;Osborn (1994), pp. 11–12&lt;/ref&gt;

The third book covers [[asceticism]]. He discusses marriage, which is treated similarly in the ''Paedagogus''. Clement rejects the Gnostic opposition to marriage, arguing that only men who are uninterested in women should remain celibate, and that sex is a positive good if performed within marriage for the purposes of procreation.&lt;ref&gt;Heid (2000), p. 65&lt;/ref&gt; However it has not always been so: the Fall occurred because Adam and Eve succumbed to their desire for each other, and copulated before the allotted time.&lt;ref&gt;Seymour (1997), p. 257&lt;/ref&gt; He argues against the idea that Christians should reject their family for an ascetic life, which stems from [[Gospel of Luke|Luke]] {{Bibleverse-nb||Luke|14:25–27|KJV}}, contending that Jesus would not have contradicted the precept to &quot;Honour thy Father and thy Mother&quot; ([[Book of Exodus|Exodus]] {{Bibleverse-nb||Exodus|20:12|KJV}}), one of the [[Ten Commandments]].&lt;ref&gt;Clark (1999), p. 198&lt;/ref&gt; Clement concludes that asceticism will only be rewarded if the motivation is Christian in nature, and thus the asceticism of non-Christians such as the [[gymnosophists]] is pointless.&lt;ref&gt;Clark (1999), p. 17&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Burrus (2011), p. 30&lt;/ref&gt;

Clement begins the fourth book with a belated explanation of the disorganized nature of the work, and gives a brief description of his aims for the remaining three or four books.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 133&lt;/ref&gt; The fourth book focuses on [[martyrdom]]. While all good Christians should be unafraid of death, Clement condemns those who actively seek out a martyr's death, arguing that they do not have sufficient respect for God's gift of life.&lt;ref&gt;Verhey (2011), p. 350&lt;/ref&gt; He is ambivalent whether any believing Christian can become a martyr by virtue of the manner of their death, or whether martyrdom is reserved for those who have lived exceptional lives.&lt;ref&gt;Burrus (2011), p. 82&lt;/ref&gt; [[Marcionism|Marcionites]] cannot become martyrs, because they do not believe in the divinity of God the Father – their sufferings are in vain.&lt;ref&gt;Osborn (1994), p. 8&lt;/ref&gt; There is then a digression to the subject of theological [[epistemology]]. According to Clement, there is no way of empirically testing the [[existence of God|existence of God the Father]], because the Logos has revelatory, not analysable meaning, although Christ was an object of the senses. God had no beginning, and is the universal first principle.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 139&lt;/ref&gt;

The fifth book returns to the subject of faith. Clement argues that truth, justice and goodness can be seen only by the mind, not the eye; faith is a way of accessing the unseeable.&lt;ref&gt;Osborn (1994), p. 9&lt;/ref&gt; He stresses that knowledge of God can only be achieved through faith once one's moral faults have been corrected.&lt;ref name=Osb199410&gt;Osborn (1994), p. 10&lt;/ref&gt; This parallels Clement's earlier insistence that martyrdom can only be achieved by those who practice their faith in Christ through good deeds, not those who simply profess their faith. God transcends matter entirely, and thus the [[materialist]] cannot truly come to know God. Although Christ was God incarnate, it is our spiritual, not physical comprehension of him which is important.&lt;ref name=Osb199410/&gt;

In the beginning of the sixth book, Clement intends to demonstrate that the works of Greek poets were derived from the [[Prophets of Christianity|prophetic books of the Bible]]. In order to reinforce his position that the Greeks were inclined towards plagiarism, he cites numerous instances of such inappropriate appropriation by classical Greek writers, reported second-hand from ''On Plagiarism'', an anonymous 3rd century BC work sometimes ascribed to Aretades.&lt;ref&gt;de Jáuregui (2010), p. 201&lt;/ref&gt; Clement then digresses to the subject of sin and [[Hell in Christianity|hell]], arguing that Adam was not perfect when created, but given the potential to achieve perfection. He espouses broadly [[Universalism in religion|universalist]] doctrine, holding that Christ's promise of salvation is available to all, even those condemned to hell.&lt;ref&gt;Seymour (1997), pp. 262–3&lt;/ref&gt;

The final extant book begins with a description of the nature of Christ, and that of the true Christian, who aims to be as similar as possible to both the Father and the Son. Clement then criticizes the simplistic [[anthropomorphism]] of most ancient religions, quoting [[Xenophanes]]' famous description of African, Thracian and Egyptian deities.&lt;ref&gt;Grant (1988), p. 77&lt;/ref&gt; The Greek gods may also have had their origins in the personification of material objects: [[Ares]] representing iron, and Dionysus wine.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 150&lt;/ref&gt; Prayer, and the relationship between love and knowledge are then discussed. {{BibleVerse|1|Corinthians|13:8|KJV}} seems to contradict the characterization of the true Christian as one who knows; but to Clement knowledge vanishes only in that it is subsumed by the universal love expressed by the Christian in his reverence for his Creator.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 151&lt;/ref&gt; Following [[Socrates]], he argues that vice arises from a state of ignorance, not from intention. The Christian is a &quot;laborer in God's vineyard&quot;, responsible both for his own path to salvation and that of his neighbor. The work ends with an extended passage against the contemporary divisions and heresies within the church.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 152&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other works===
Besides the great trilogy, Clement's only other extant work is the treatise ''Salvation for the Rich'', also known as ''Who is the Rich Man who is Saved?'' Having begun with a scathing criticism of the corrupting effects of money and misguided servile attitudes towards the wealthy, Clement discusses the implications of {{BibleVerse||Mark|10:25|KJV}}.&lt;ref name=Fer1974166&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 166&lt;/ref&gt; The rich are either unconvinced by the promise of eternal life, or unaware of the conflict between the possession of material and spiritual wealth, and the good Christian has a duty to guide them towards a better life through the Gospel.&lt;ref name=Fer1974166/&gt; Jesus' words are not to be taken literally — we should seek the supercelestial [ὑπερουράνιος] meaning in which the true route to salvation is revealed.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 167&lt;/ref&gt; The holding of material wealth in itself is not a wrong, as long as it is used charitably, but men should be careful not to let their wealth dominate their spirit. It is more important to give up sinful passions than external wealth. If the rich man is to be saved, all he must do is to follow the [[Great Commandment|two commandments]], and while material wealth is of no value to God, it can be used to alleviate the suffering of our neighbor.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), pp. 173, 178&lt;/ref&gt;

Other known works exist in fragments alone, including the four eschatological works in the secret tradition: ''Hypotyposes'', ''Excerpta ex Theodoto'', ''Eclogae Propheticae'' and the ''Adumbraetiones''.&lt;ref&gt;Bucar (2006), p. 252&lt;/ref&gt; These cover Clement's celestial hierarchy, a complex schema in which the universe is headed by the Face of God, below which lie seven ''protoctists'', followed by [[archangel]]s, [[angel]]s and humans.&lt;ref&gt;Bucar (2006), p. 255&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Jean Daniélou]], this schema is inherited from a Judaeo-Christian esotericism, followed by the Apostles, which was only imparted orally to those Christians who could be trusted with such mysteries.&lt;ref&gt;Daniélou (1962), p. 262&lt;/ref&gt; The ''proctocists'' are the first beings created by God, and act as priests to the archangels. Clement identifies them both as the &quot;Eyes of the Lord&quot; and with the [[Thrones]].&lt;ref&gt;Bucar (2006), p. 257&lt;/ref&gt; Clement characterizes the celestial forms as entirely different from anything earthly, although he argues that members of each order only seem incorporeal to those of lower orders.&lt;ref name=Buc2006260&gt;Bucar (2006), p. 260&lt;/ref&gt; According to the ''Eclogae Propheticae'', every thousand years every member of each order moves up a degree, and thus men can become angels. Even the ''protoctists'' can be elevated, although their new position in the hierarchy is not clearly defined.&lt;ref name=Buc2006260/&gt; The apparent contradiction between the fact that there can be only seven ''protoctists'' but also a vast number of archangels to be promoted to their order is problematical. The commonest modern explanation is that the number seven is not meant to be taken literally, but has a principally [[numerology|numerological]] significance.&lt;ref&gt;Bucar (2006), pp. 261–3&lt;/ref&gt;

We know the titles of several lost works because of a list in Eusebius' ''[[Church History (Eusebius)|Ecclesiastical History]]'', 6.13.1-3. They include the ''Outlines'', in eight books, and ''Against Judaizers''. Others are known only from mentions in Clement's own writings, including ''On Marriage'' and ''On Prophecy'', although few are attested by other writers and it is difficult to separate works which he intended to write from those which were actually completed.&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson (1974), p. 179&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Mar Saba letter]] was attributed to Clement by [[Morton Smith]], but there remains much debate today over whether it is an authentic letter from Clement, an ancient [[pseudepigraph]] or a modern forgery.&lt;ref&gt;Heine (2010), pp. 117-8, 121&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Osborn (2008), p. 195&lt;/ref&gt; If authentic, its main significance would be in its relating that the Apostle Mark came to Alexandria from Rome and there wrote a more spiritual Gospel, which he entrusted to the Church in Alexandria on his death; if genuine, the letter pushes back the tradition related by Eusebius connecting Mark with Alexandria by a century.&lt;ref&gt;Heine (2010), p. 121.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Legacy ==
[[Eusebius]] is the first writer to provide an account of Clement's life and works, in his ''[[Church History (Eusebius)|Ecclesiastical History]]'', 5.11.1-5, 6.6.1{{NoteTag|Of the two sections dedicated to Clement, ''Eccl. Hist''. 6.6.1 seems decidedly out of place, and [[Henri Valois|Valesius]] argued that this was evidence that Eusebius never revised his work.&lt;ref&gt;McGiffert (1890), p.&amp;nbsp;253.&lt;/ref&gt;}} Eusebius provides a list of Clement's works, biographical information, and an extended quotation from the ''Stromata''.

[[Photios I of Constantinople]] writes against Clement's theology in the ''[[Bibliotheca (Photius)|Bibliotheca]]'', although he is appreciative of Clement's learning and the literary merits of his work.&lt;ref&gt;Ashwin-Siejkowski (2010), p.&amp;nbsp;16.&lt;/ref&gt; In particular, he is highly critical of the ''Hypotyposes'', a work of biblical exegesis of which only a few fragments have survived. Photios compared Clement's treatise, which, like his other works, was highly syncretic, featuring ideas of Hellenistic, Jewish and Gnostic origin, unfavorably against the prevailing orthodoxy of the 9th century.&lt;ref&gt;Ashwin-Siejkowski (2010), pp. 17–8.&lt;/ref&gt; Amongst the particular ideas Photios deemed [[heresy|heretical]] were:
*His belief that matter and thought are eternal, and thus did not originate from God, contradicting the doctrine of ''[[Creatio ex nihilo]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Ashwin-Siejkowski (2010), p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt;
*His belief in [[esoteric cosmology|cosmic cycles]] predating the creation of the world, following [[Heraclitus]], which is extra-Biblical in origin.&lt;ref&gt;Ashwin-Siejkowski (2010), pp. 40–43.&lt;/ref&gt;
*His belief that Christ, as Logos, was in some sense created, contrary to [[John 1]] but following [[Philo]].&lt;ref&gt;Ashwin-Siejkowski (2010), p. 75.&lt;/ref&gt;
*His ambivalence towards [[docetism]], the heretical doctrine that Christ's earthly body was an illusion.&lt;ref&gt;Ashwin-Siejkowski (2010), p. 95.&lt;/ref&gt;
*His belief that [[Eve]] was created from Adam's sperm after he [[ejaculation|ejaculated]] during the night.&lt;ref&gt;Itter (2009), p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt;
*His belief that {{BibleVerse||Genesis|6:2|KJV}} implies that angels indulged in [[coitus]] with human women. In Roman Catholic theology, angels are considered sexless.&lt;ref&gt;Ashwin-Siejkowski (2010), p. 146.&lt;/ref&gt;
* His belief in reincarnation, i.e., the transmigration of souls.&lt;ref&gt;Ashwin-Siejkowski (2010), p. 115.&lt;/ref&gt;

As one of the earliest of the Church fathers whose works have survived, he is the subject of a significant amount of recent academic work, focusing on among other things, his exegesis of scripture, his Logos-theology and pneumatology, the relationship between his thought and non-Christian philosophy and his influence on [[Origen]].&lt;ref&gt;Ashwin-Siejkowski (2015), pp.&amp;nbsp;92&amp;ndash;3.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Veneration ===
Down to the seventeenth century Clement was venerated as a saint in the [[Roman Catholic Church]]. His name was to be found in the martyrologies, and his feast fell on the fourth of December. But when the [[Roman Martyrology]] was revised by Pope [[Clement VIII]] his name was dropped from the [[General Roman Calendar|calendar]] on the advice of Cardinal [[Baronius]]. [[Benedict XIV]] maintained this decision of his predecessor on the grounds that Clement's life was little known, that he had never obtained public [[Cult (religious practice)|cultus]] in the Church, and that some of his doctrines were, if not erroneous, at least suspect.&lt;ref&gt;Havey (1908)&lt;/ref&gt;

Although Clement is not widely venerated in [[Eastern Christianity]], the [[Prologue of Ohrid]] repeatedly refers to him as a saint&lt;ref&gt;https://web.archive.org/web/20170502024636/http://westserbdio.org/en/prologue/505-may-12&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://web.archive.org/web/20170502150734/http://westserbdio.org/en/prologue/644-september-26&lt;/ref&gt;, as do various [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Orthodox]] authorities including the [[Greek Orthodox Church|Greek]] Metropolitan Kallinikos of Edessa.&lt;ref&gt;http://saintandrewgoc.org/home/2015/5/7/fruits-of-healing&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Coptic Christianity|Coptic]] tradition considers Clement a saint.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.copticchurch.net/topics/patrology/schoolofalex/IV-StClement/chapter5.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://www.nationalgeographic.com/archaeology-and-history/magazine/2019/03-04/coptic-christianity-ancient-egypt/&lt;/ref&gt; Saint Clement Coptic Orthodox Christian Academy in Nashville, TN is specifically named after him.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.stclementacademy.com/about_us/our_saint |title=Our Saint |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181127112454/http://www.stclementacademy.com/about_us/our_saint |archive-date=2018-11-27 |access-date=2019-08-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Clement is commemorated in [[Anglicanism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://prayerbook.ca/the-prayer-book-online/57-the-calendar-ix |title=Archived copy |access-date=2013-11-03 |url-status=dead |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20131104172841/http://prayerbook.ca/the-prayer-book-online/57-the-calendar-ix |archive-date=2013-11-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Also, the [[Independent Catholicism|independent]] Universal Catholic Church's cathedral in [[Dallas]] is dedicated to him.

==Works==
===Editions===
{{refbegin}}
*[[Friedrich Sylburg|Sylburg, Friedrich]] (ed.) (1592).  [https://books.google.com/books?id=5GyKqmKb_hEC&amp;pg=PP9#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false ''Clementis Alexandrini Opera Quae Extant''.] Heidelberg: ex typographeio Hieronymi Commelini.
*[[Daniel Heinsius|Heinsius, Daniel]] (ed.) (1616).  [https://books.google.com/books?id=zUJkAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PP5#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false ''Clementis Alexandrini Opera Graece et Latine Quae Extant''.] Leiden: excudit Ioannes Patius academiae typographus.
*[[John Potter (bishop)|Potter, John]] (ed.) (1715). ''Clementis Alexandrini Opera'', 2 vols.  Oxonii: e theatro Sheldoniano. [https://books.google.com/books?id=qWVZAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PP7#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Vol. 1. ''Cohortatio ad gentes.  Paedagogus. Stromatum'' I-IV.] [https://books.google.com/books?id=-iBZAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA641#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Vol. 2. ''Stromatum'' V-VIII. ''Quis dives salvetur. Excerpta Theodoti. Prophetarum ecologiae.  Fragmenta''.]
*[[Reinhold Klotz|Klotz, Reinhold]] (ed.) (1831–34).  ''Titi Flaui Clementis Alexandrini Opera Omnia'', 4 vols.  Leipzig: E. B. Schwickert.  [https://books.google.com/books?id=qCoQAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PR2#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Vol. 1. ''Ρrotrepticus.  Paedagogus''.] [https://books.google.com/books?id=JSsQAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PR2#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Vol. 2. ''Stromatorum'' I-IV.] [https://books.google.com/books?id=RSsQAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PP10#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Vol. 3.'' Stromatourm'' V-VIII. ''Quis dives salvetur''.] [https://books.google.com/books?id=YEROAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PP8#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Vol. 4.  Fragmenta. Scholia. Annotationes. Indices.]
* [[Jacques Paul Migne|Migne, J.-P.]] (ed.) (1857).  ''Clementis Alexandrini Opera Quae Exstant Omnia'', 2 toms. (= PG 8, 9)  Paris: J.-P. Migne.  [https://books.google.com/books?id=FvsUAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA9#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Tom. 1. ''Cohortatio ad gentes. Paedagogus. Stromata'' I-IV.] [https://archive.org/details/patrologiaecurs59hopfgoog Tom. 2. ''Stromata'' V-VIII. ''Quis dives salvetur''. Fragmenta.]
*[[Karl Wilhelm Dindorf|Dindorf, Wilhelm]] (ed.) (1869). ''Clementis Alexandrini Opera'', 4 vols. Oxonni: e typographeo Clarendoniano. [https://books.google.com/books?id=yVk5cJhGjP4C&amp;pg=PR3#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Vol. 1. ''Ρrotrepticus.  Paedagogus''.] [https://books.google.com/books?id=82I9AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PP9#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Vol. 2. ''Stromatum'' I-IV.] [https://books.google.com/books?id=vVmWgVRRBoYC&amp;pg=PP7#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Vol. 3. ''Stromatum'' V-VIII.] [https://books.google.com/books?id=Tdf_fyBznz0C&amp;pg=PP9#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Vol. 4. Annotationes. Interpretum.]
*Barnard, P. Mourdant (ed.) (1897).  [https://archive.org/stream/clementofalexan00clem#page/n7/mode/2up Clement of Alexandria, ''Quis dives salvetur''.] Texts and Studies 5/2.  Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.
*[[:de:Otto Stählin]] (ed.) (1905–36).  ''Clemens Alexandrinus'', 4 bds. (= GCS 12, 15, 17, 39) Leipzig: J. C. Hinrichs. [https://books.google.com/books?id=DTYYAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PR1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Bd. 1. ''Ρrotrepticus'' und ''Paedagogus''.] [https://books.google.com/books?id=n1wPAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PP5#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Bd. 2. ''Stromata'' I-VI.] [https://archive.org/stream/clemensalexandri17clemuoft#page/n7/mode/2up Bd. 3. ''Stromata'' VII-VIII. ''Excerpta ex Theodoto. Eclogae prophetica. Quis dives salvetur''. Fragmente.] [https://archive.org/stream/clemensalexandri04clemuoft#page/n9/mode/2up Bd. 4. Register.]
* [[Miroslav Marcovich|Marcovich, Miroslav]] and Jacobus C. M. van Winden (eds.) (2002). [https://books.google.com/books?id=h-35iALtOD0C&amp;pg=PR3#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Clementis Alexandrini ''Paedagogus''.] Leiden: Brill.  {{ISBN|978-9004124707}}
{{refend}}

===Translations===
{{refbegin}}
*Wilson, William (trans.) (1867).  [https://books.google.com/books?id=xuxYAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA163#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false &quot;The Writings of Clement of Alexandria&quot;.] In ''Ante-Nicene Fathers'', ed. A. Roberts, et al., 2:163-629.  (Reprint 1905) New York: Charles Scribner's Sons.
*Barnard, P. Mourdant (trans.) (1901). [https://books.google.com/books?id=W9sPAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PR1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false ''A Homily of Clement of Alexandria, Entitled: Who is the Rich Man that is being Saved?'']  London: SPCK.
*[[Fenton Hort|Hort, F. J. A.]] and Joseph B. Mayor (eds. &amp; trans.) (1902). [https://books.google.com/books?id=ZMX0ykRov6YC&amp;pg=PR1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false ''Clement of Alexandria, Miscellanies Book VII''.] London: Macmillan. {{ISBN|978-1108007542}}
*Patrick, John (1914). [https://archive.org/stream/clementofalexand00patrrich#page/182/mode/2up ''Clement of Alexandria'', 183-85.] Edinburgh: Wm. Blackwood. (''Exhortation to Endurance, or, To the Newly Baptized''; cf. Butterworth 1919, 371 ff.)
*Butterworth, G. W. (ed. &amp; trans.) (1919). [https://archive.org/stream/clementofalexand00clem#page/n7/mode/2up Clement of Alexandria, ''Exhortation to the Greeks, Rich Man's Salvation'', etc.] (= LCL 92)  Cambridge: Harvard University Press.  {{ISBN|978-0674991033}}
*Casey, Robert Pierce (ed. &amp; trans.) (1936).  ''The Excerpta ex Theodoto of Clement of Alexandria''.  Studies and Documents 1.  London: Christophers.
*Oulton, J. E. L. and [[Henry Chadwick (theologian)|Henry Chadwick]] (trans.) (1954). [https://archive.org/stream/alexandrianchris012826mbp#page/n43/mode/2up ''Alexandrian Christianity'', 40-165.] Philadelphia: Westminster Press. (''Miscellanies'', Books III, VII)  {{ISBN|978-0664241537}}
*Wood, Simon P. (trans.) (1954). [https://books.google.com/books?id=h63vsOCHAGIC&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false ''Clement of Alexandria, Christ the Educator.]  Fathers of the Church 23.  Washington, DC: Catholic University of America Press.  {{ISBN|978-0813215624}}
*Ferguson, John (trans.) (1991). [https://books.google.com/books?id=XWpL1zz5cmoC&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false ''Clement of Alexandria, Stromateis, Books 1-3.]  Fathers of the Church 85.  Washington, DC: Catholic University of America Press.  {{ISBN|978-0813214337}}
{{refend}}

== See also ==
* [[Buddhism and the Roman world#Western knowledge of Buddhism|Buddhism and the Roman world]]

== Notes ==
{{NoteFoot}}

== References ==
=== Citations ===
{{Reflist|20em}}

=== Sources ===
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |last=Ashwin-Siejkowski |first=Piotr |title=Clement of Alexandria on Trial: The Evidence of &quot;Heresy&quot; from Photius' Bibliotheca |year=2010|publisher=BRILL|location=Leiden|isbn=978-90-04-17627-0}}
*{{cite book|last=Ashwin-Siejkowski|first=Piotr|editor-last=Parry|editor-first=Ken|chapter=Clement of Alexandria|title=Wiley Blackwell Companion to Patristics|year=2015|pages=84–97|publisher=Wiley Blackwell|location=Chichester, West Sussex|isbn=978-1118438718}}
*{{cite book|last=Berger|first=Teresa|title=Gender Differences and the Making of Liturgical History: Lifting a Veil on Liturgy's Past|year=2011|publisher=Ashgate Publishing|location=London|isbn=978-1-4094-2698-1}}
*{{cite journal|last=Bucur|first=Bogdan G.|title=The Other Clement of Alexandria: Cosmic Hierarchy and Interiorized Apocalypticism|journal=Vigiliae Christianae|date=2006|volume=60|issue=3|pages=251–268|jstor=20474764|doi=10.1163/157007206778149510}}
*{{cite book|last=Buell|first=Denise Kimber|title=Making Christians: Clement of Alexandria and the Rhetoric of Legitimacy|year=1999|publisher=Princeton University Press|location=Princeton |isbn=0-691-05980-2 }}
*{{cite book|last=Burrus|first=Virginia|title=Late Ancient Christianity|year=2010|publisher=Fortress Press|location=Philadelphia|isbn=978-0-8006-9720-4}}
*{{cite book|last=Clark|first=Elizabeth Ann|title=Reading Renunciation: Asceticism and Scripture in Early Christianity|year=1999|publisher=Princeton University Press|location=Princeton|isbn=978-0-691-00512-6}}
*{{cite journal|last=Daniélou|first=Jean |title=Les traditions secrètes des Apôtres |language = fr |journal=Eranos-Jahrbuch|year=1962|volume=31|pages=261–95}}
*{{cite book|last=Droge|first=Arthur J.|title=Homer or Moses?: Early Christian Interpretations of the History of Culture|year=1989|publisher=Mohr Siebeck|location=Tübingen|isbn=978-3-16-145354-0}}
*{{cite book|last=Ferguson|first=John|title=Clement of Alexandria|year=1974|publisher=Twayne Publishers|location=New York|isbn=0-8057-2231-9|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/clementofalexand00ferg}}
*{{cite book|last=Gill|first=Deborah M.|editor-last=Ma|editor-first=Wonsuk|title=The spirit and spirituality|chapter=The Disappearance of the Female Prophet: Twilight of Christian Prophecy|year=2004|pages=178–93|publisher=T &amp; T Clark|location=New York, NY |isbn=978-0-8264-7162-8}}
*{{cite book|last=Grant|first=Robert McQueen|title=Gods and the One God|year=1988|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|location=Louisville|isbn=978-0-664-25011-9}}
*{{Citation| last =Hägg | first =Henny Fiska | year =2006 | title=Clement of Alexandria and the Beginnings of Christian Apophaticism | publisher =Oxford University Press | location =Oxford | isbn =978-0-199-28808-3}}
*{{cite book|last=Hägg|first=Henny Fiskå|title=Clement of Alexandria and the Beginnings of Christian Apophaticism|year=2006|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford, England |isbn=0-19-928808-9}}
*{{cite book|last=Havey|first=Francis|chapter=Clement of Alexandria|title=The Catholic Encyclopedia |volume=4 |location=New York, NY|publisher=Robert Appleton Company|year=1908 |chapter-url = http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/04045a.htm }} 
*{{cite book|last=Heid|first=Stefan|title=Celibacy in the Early Church: The Beginnings of a Discipline of Obligatory Continence for Clerics in East and West|year=2000|publisher=Ignatius Press|location=San Francisco, CA |isbn=978-0-89870-800-4}}
*{{cite book |last=Heine|first=Ronald E. |editor-last=Young|editor-first=Frances|title=The Cambridge History of Early Christian Literature|chapter=The Alexandrians |year=2010|pages=117–30|location=Cambridge, England |publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0521460835}}
*{{cite book|last=Itter|first=Andrew C.|title=Esoteric Teaching in the Stromateis of Clement of Alexandria|year=2009|publisher=BRILL|location=Leiden|isbn=978-90-04-17482-5}}
*{{cite book|last=Irvine|first=Martin|title=The Making of Textual Culture: 'Grammatica' and Literary Theory 350–1100|year=2006|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Cambridge|isbn=0-521-03199-0 }}
*{{Citation |last=Meredith |first=Anthony |year=2002 |chapter =Patristic spirituality |editor-last1=Byrne |editor-first1=Peter |editor-last2=Houlden |editor-first2 =Leslie |title=Companion Encyclopedia of Theology | publisher =Routledge |url=https://books.google.com/?id=8pBt10wlXv0C|isbn=9781134922017 }}
*{{cite book|last=de Jáuregui|first=Miguel Herrero|title=Orphism and Christianity in Late Antiquity|year=2010|publisher=Walter de Gruyter|location=Berlin|isbn=978-3-11-020633-3}}
*{{cite book|last=Karavites|first=Peter|title=Evil, Freedom, and the Road to Perfection in Clement of Alexandria|year=1999|publisher=BRILL|location=Leiden|isbn=978-90-04-11238-4}}
*{{cite book|last=Kaye|first=John|title=Some Account of the Writings and Opinions of Clement of Alexandria|year=1835|publisher=J. G. &amp; F. Rivington|location=London|url=https://archive.org/details/someaccountwrit00kayegoog}}
*{{cite book|last=Kochuthara|first=Shaji George|title=The Concept of Sexual Pleasure in the Catholic Moral Tradition|year=2007|publisher=Gregorian University Press|location=Rome|isbn=978-88-7839-100-0}}
*{{cite book|last=McGiffert|first=A. C. (trans.)|editor-last=Schaff|editor-first=Philip|title=Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers|chapter=The Church History of Eusebius|year=1890|series=1st series|publisher=Parker|location=Oxford|volume=1|pages=1–403|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=PG07AQAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PR1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}
*{{cite book|last=Murphy|first=Mable Gant|title=Nature Allusions in the Works of Clement of Alexandria|year=1941|publisher=The Catholic University of America Press|location=Washington, D.C.}}
*{{cite book|last=Ogliari|first=Donato|title=Gratia et certamen: The Relationship Between Grace and Free Will in the Discussion of Augustine with the So-called Semipelagians|year=2003|publisher=Peeters|location=Leuven|isbn=90-429-1351-7}}
*{{cite journal|last=Outler|first=Albert C.|title=The &quot;Platonism&quot; of Clement of Alexandria|journal=The Journal of Religion|year=1940|volume=20|issue=3|pages=217–240|doi=10.1086/482574}}
*{{cite journal |last=Osborn|first=Eric|title=Arguments for Faith in Clement of Alexandria |journal=Vigiliae Christianae|year=1994|volume=48|issue=1|pages=1–24|doi=10.1163/157007294x00113}}
*{{cite book|last=Osborn|first=Eric|title=Clement of Alexandria|year=2008|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Cambridge, England |isbn=978-0-521-09081-0}}
*{{cite book|last=Press|first=Gerald A.|title=Development of the Idea of History in Antiquity|year=2003|publisher=McGill-Queen's Press|location=Montreal}}
*{{cite journal|last=Seymour|first=Charles|title=On Choosing Hell|journal=Religious Studies|date=1997|volume=3|issue=33|pages=249–266|jstor=20008103}}
*{{cite book|title=International Theological Commission, Volume 2|year=2009|publisher=Ignatius Press|location=San Francisco|isbn=978-1-58617-226-8|editor-first=Michael|editor-last= Sharkey}}
*{{cite book|last=Verhey|first=Allen|title=The Christian Art of Dying: Learning from Jesus|year=2011|publisher=Eerdmans|location=Grand Rapids|isbn=978-0-8028-6672-1}}
*{{cite book|last=Westcott|first=Brooke Foss|editor-last=Smith|editor-first=Willam|chapter=Clement of Alexandria |title = A Dictionary of Christian Biography, Literature, Sects and Doctrines |year=1877|volume=1|pages=559–67|publisher=John Murray |location=London, England |chapter-url = https://books.google.com/books?id=UfgUAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA560#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false }}
*{{cite book|last=Young|first=Richard A. |title=Is God a Vegetarian?: Christianity, Vegetarianism, and Animal Rights|year=1999|publisher=Open Court Publishing|location=Chicago, IL |isbn=0-8126-9393-0 }}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book | author=Paananen, Timo S. | title=A Study in Authenticity: Admissible Concealed Indicators of Authority and Other Features of Forgeries — A Case Study on Clement of Alexandria, Letter to Theodore, and the Longer Gospel of Mark | publisher=University of Helsinki | year=2019 | type=Ph.D. thesis | isbn=978-951-51-5250-3 | url=http://urn.fi/URN:ISBN:978-952-94-1853-4 }}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote|Clement of Alexandria}}
{{Wikisource|Author:Clement of Alexandria|Clement of Alexandria}}
* {{Internet Archive author |name=Clement of Alexandria}}
* {{Librivox author |id=8393|title=Clement of Alexandria}}
* [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/04045a.htm &quot;Clement of Alexandria&quot;] by Francis P. Havey, in the [[Catholic Encyclopedia]], 1908.
* [http://www.piney.com/MuClement.html#P2694_785619 Clement's Protrepticus]
* [http://www.ccel.org/fathers2/ANF-02/anf02-50.htm#TopOfPage Clement's Stromateis]
* [http://www.ccel.org/fathers2/ANF-02/anf02-52.htm Clement's Paedagogus]
* [http://www.tertullian.org/fathers2/ANF-02/anf02-77.htm#P10196_2863283 Hypotyposes]
* [http://www.bennozuiddam.com/The%20role%20and%20view%20of%20Scripture%20in%20Clemens%20of%20Alexandria.pdf  The role and view of Scripture in Clement of Alexandria]

{{Platonists}}
{{Clement}}
{{Catholic philosophy footer}}
{{Catholic saints}}
{{Coptic saints}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Clement Of Alexandria}}
[[Category:150 births]]
[[Category:215 deaths]]
[[Category:2nd-century Romans]]
[[Category:2nd-century Christian theologians]]
[[Category:3rd-century Christian saints]]
[[Category:2nd-century philosophers]]
[[Category:3rd-century philosophers]]
[[Category:3rd-century Romans]]
[[Category:Amillennialism]]
[[Category:Ancient Greeks]]
[[Category:Christian anti-Gnosticism]]
[[Category:Church Fathers]]
[[Category:Saints from Roman Egypt]]
[[Category:Deans of the Catechetical School of Alexandria]]
[[Category:Egyptian people of Greek descent]]
[[Category:Egyptian theologians]]
[[Category:Egyptian philosophers]]
[[Category:Flavii]]
[[Category:Catholic philosophers]]
[[Category:Christianity and Hellenistic philosophy]]
[[Category:Converts to Christianity from pagan religions]]</text>
      <sha1>tfkf2kasrbfbysowbr7j3txi9bn5ofo</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
