  <page>
    <title>ColecoVision</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7306</id>
    <revision>
      <id>933750213</id>
      <parentid>933744725</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-02T20:56:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>108.168.46.177</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>fixed memory specifications</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox CVG system
| title = ColecoVision
| logo = [[Image:COLECO VISION LOGO.svg|250px]]
| image = [[Image:ColecoVision-wController-L.jpg|300px|center|A ColecoVision unit]]
| manufacturer = [[Coleco Industries, Inc.]]
| type = [[Home video game console]]
| generation = [[Second generation of video game consoles|Second generation]]
| releasedate  = {{vgrelease|NA|August 1982}}{{vgrelease|EU|July 1983}}
| discontinued = 1985
| CPU = [[Zilog Z80]]
| GPU = [[Texas Instruments TMS9918|TMS9928A]]
| sound = [[Texas Instruments SN76489|SN76489]]
| memory       = 1 kB scratchpad RAM&lt;br&gt;16 kB video RAM&lt;br&gt;8kB ROM
| media = [[ROM cartridge]]
| storage = 8/16/24/32 KB
| controllers = Joystick/Numeric Keypad&lt;br /&gt;Roller Controller&lt;br /&gt;Driving Controller&lt;br /&gt;Super Action Controller
| units sold = over 2 million (1982-83) &lt;ref name=&quot;coleco_annual_1983&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |title=Coleco Industries, Inc. 1983 Annual Report |date=1983 |page=3 |url=http://atariage.com/forums/topic/283473-coleco-industries-inc-annual-quarterly-reports-1981-to-1986/ |publisher=Coleco Industries, Inc. |quote=The year's sales of 1.5 million ColecoVision units brought the installed base to over 2 million units worldwide.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| units shipped =
| top game = ''[[Donkey Kong (video game)|Donkey Kong]]'' ([[pack-in game|pack-in]])
| S.R.P. =
| predecessor = [[Telstar (game console)|Telstar series]] (1978)
|
}}

The '''ColecoVision''' is [[Coleco|Coleco Industries]]' [[Second generation of video game consoles|second-generation]] [[home video game console|home video-game console]] that was released in August 1982.  The ColecoVision offered a closer experience to more powerful [[arcade game]] systems, compared to competitors such as the [[Atari 2600]] and [[Atari 5200]], along with the means to expand the system's basic hardware.

The initial catalog of twelve games included [[Nintendo]]'s ''[[Donkey Kong (video game)|Donkey Kong]]'' as the pack-in cartridge, Sega's ''[[Zaxxon]]'', and some lesser known arcade titles that found a larger audience on the console, such as ''[[Lady Bug (video game)|Lady Bug]]'', ''[[Cosmic Avenger]]'', and ''[[Venture (video game)|Venture]]''. Approximately 145 titles in total were published as [[ROM cartridge]]s for the system between 1982 and 1984.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |last=Forster |first=Winnie |authorlink=Winnie Forster |title=The encyclopedia of consoles, handhelds &amp; home computers 1972 - 2005 |year=2005 |publisher=GAMEPLAN |isbn=3-00-015359-4|page=50}}&lt;/ref&gt; Coleco released a series of hardware add-ons and special controllers to expand the capabilities of the console.

The ColecoVision was discontinued in 1985 when Coleco withdrew from the video game market.

== History ==
By Christmas of 1982, Coleco had sold more than 500,000 units,&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | journal=Business Week | title=Coleco hits with home video games | page=31 | date=1983-01-24 | quote=Most of 1982's action was in the second half, when Coleco shipped 550,000 ColecoVision game machines--which sell for $169 to $189--booking orders for nearly that many more.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | publisher=Associated Press | title=Video Game Maker Says 1st-Quarter Profit More Than Tripled | date=1983-04-20 | quote=Arnold C. Greenberg, Coleco's president and chief executive, said more than 500,000 ColecoVision players were shipped during the first quarter, nearly equaling the number shipped in all of 1982.}}&lt;/ref&gt; in part on the strength of ''Donkey Kong'' as its bundled game.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | journal=New York Times | title=Coleco's New Video Challenge | page=1 (Section D) | date=1982-11-11 | quote=Potential Colecovision buyers have also apparently been attracted by Coleco's licensing agreement with Nintendo Inc., the Japanese creator of Donkey Kong, a current arcade hit, and Universal City Studios Inc. One Donkey Kong cartridge comes with each Colecovision unit.}}&lt;/ref&gt; ColecoVision's main competitor was the less commercially successful [[Atari 5200]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | journal=Christian Science Monitor | title=Zap! Pow! Video games sparkle in holiday market | last=Aeppel | first=Timothy | page=7 | date=1982-12-10 | quote=In recent weeks, two particularly hot-selling systems have emerged - the Atari 5200 and ColecoVision. Both are described as powerful 'third wave' machines, the Cadillacs of game systems, and priced accordingly at close to $200...[T]hey are sure to snatch most of the Christmas market.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | journal=New York Times | title=Sigh of Relief on Video Games | last=Harmetz | first=Aljean | page=1 (Section D) | date=1984-01-10 | quote=As for game hardware, many experts said that Atari's...5200 or Coleco's Colecovision would corner the high end.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | journal=New York Times | title=Coleco Strong In Marketing | date=1983-08-01 | quote=Since its introduction last fall, Colecovision has sold about 1.4 million units...Of that total, about 900,000 were sold this year, compared with 800,000 units by Atari and 300,000 by Mattel.}}&lt;/ref&gt; which used the same custom graphics and sound chips developed for the [[Atari 8-bit family]] of computers launched in 1979.

The ColecoVision was distributed by [[CBS Electronics]] outside of [[North America]], and was branded the '''CBS ColecoVision'''. In Europe the console was released in July 1983, nearly one year after the North American release.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.delpher.nl/nl/kranten/view?coll=ddd&amp;identifier=ddd:010593028:mpeg21:a0696 |title=Delpher Kranten - Limburgsch dagblad 31-12-1983 |publisher=Delpher.nl |date=1983-12-31 |accessdate=2019-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sales quickly passed 1 million in early 1983,&lt;ref&gt;Video Game Maker Says 1st-Quarter Profit More Than Tripled, 1983-04-20&lt;/ref&gt; before the [[video game crash of 1983]]. By the beginning of 1984, quarterly sales of the ColecoVision had dramatically decreased.&lt;ref name=&quot;coleco_report&quot;&gt;{{Citation | publisher=PR Newswire | title=Coleco Industries sales report | date=1984-04-17 | quote='First quarter sales of ColecoVision were substantial, although much less {{sic|that}} those for the year ago quarter,' Greenberg said in a prepared statement. He said the company has sold 2 million ColecoVision games since its introduction in 1982.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Over the next 18 months, the Coleco company ramped down its video game division, ultimately withdrawing from the video game market by the end of the summer of 1985.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | journal=New York Times | publisher=Reuters | title=Coleco Reassesses Its Video Games | page=4 (Section D) | date=1985-06-13 | quote=Coleco Industries is assessing its continuing commitment to the video game business...Arnold C. Greenberg, the chief executive, said no timetable had been set for a decision on continuing or dropping the Colecovision products or on whether the software for the games would continue to be produced if hardware production was discontinued. }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | journal=The Globe and Mail (Canada) | title=Video games Coleco may drop out | date=1985-06-21 | quote=Coleco Industries Inc. of West Hartford, Conn., is considering withdrawal from the video game business in both hardware and software.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ColecoVision was officially discontinued by October 1985.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | journal=New York Times | publisher=Associated Press | title=Coleco's Net In Sharp Rise | date=1985-10-19 | quote=Thursday, Coleco said the entire inventory of its troubled Adam personal computer has been sold, along with much of its Colecovision inventory. The company's chairman, Arnold Greenberg, said Coleco expects no more charges against earnings from the two discontinued products.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Total sales of the ColecoVision are uncertain but were ultimately in excess of 2 million units,&lt;ref name=&quot;coleco_annual_1984_1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |title=Coleco Industries, Inc. 1984 Annual Report |date=1984 |page=2 |url=http://atariage.com/forums/topic/283473-coleco-industries-inc-annual-quarterly-reports-1981-to-1986/ |publisher=Coleco Industries, Inc. |quote=Sales in the Consumer Electronics segment were $98.6 million in 1984}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;coleco_annual_1984_2&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |title=Coleco Industries, Inc. 1984 Annual Report |date=1984 |page=22 |url=http://atariage.com/forums/topic/283473-coleco-industries-inc-annual-quarterly-reports-1981-to-1986/ |publisher=Coleco Industries, Inc. |quote=The decline in sales of Consumer Electronics was primarily due to reduced sales of ColecoVision products.  The increase in shipments of the ADAM Family Computer System in 1984 was largely offset by provisions for price reductions and returns recorded in the last half of the year.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;coleco_annual_1984_3&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |title=Coleco Industries, Inc. 1984 Annual Report |date=1984 |page=3 |url=http://atariage.com/forums/topic/283473-coleco-industries-inc-annual-quarterly-reports-1981-to-1986/ |publisher=Coleco Industries, Inc. |quote=the total of ColecoVision inventory and accounts receivable was $40.5 million at December 31, 1984. During 1985 it is expected that accounts receivable will be converted to cash and the balance of ColecoVision inventory sold.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;coleco_annual_1985&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |title=Coleco Industries, Inc. 1985 Annual Report |date=1985 |page=25 |url=http://atariage.com/forums/topic/283473-coleco-industries-inc-annual-quarterly-reports-1981-to-1986/ |publisher=Coleco Industries, Inc. |quote=Consumer Electronics net sales of $56.2 million consisted principally of the ADAM Family Computer and ColecoVision video game systems, accessories and software.}}&lt;/ref&gt; due to the console continuing to sell modestly up until its discontinuation the following year.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | journal=New York Times | last=Kleinfield | first=N. R. | title=Coleco Moves Out Of The Cabbage Patch | page=4 (Section 3) | date=1985-07-21 | quote=Coleco is now debating whether to withdraw from electronics altogether. Colecovision still sells, but it is a shadow of its former self.}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Video game crash of 1983|The video game crash of 1983]] has been cited as the main cause of the ColecoVision's being discontinued less than three years after its launch.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|last= |first= |title=The Next Generation 1996 Lexicon A to Z: ColecoVision|magazine=[[Next Generation (magazine)|Next Generation]]|issue=15 |publisher=[[Imagine Media]]|date=March 1996|page=31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1983 [[Spectravideo]] announced the SV-603 ColecoVision Video Game Adapter for its [[SV-318]] computer. The company stated that the $70 product allowed users to &quot;enjoy the entire library of exciting ColecoVision video-game cartridges&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;softline198303&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.cgwmuseum.org/galleries/index.php?year=1983&amp;pub=6&amp;id=10 | title=Heavy Hardware | work=Softline | date=March 1983 | accessdate=28 July 2014 | page=46}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Hardware ==
[[File:ColecoVision-Controller-FR.jpg|thumb|right|The ColecoVision controller has a number pad that can be fitted with overlays.]]

On NTSC ColecoVision consoles, all first-party cartridges and most third-party software titles feature a 12.7 second pause before presenting the game select screen.&lt;ref name=&quot;eg198306&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=https://archive.org/stream/electronic-games-magazine-1983-06/Electronic_Games_Issue_16_Vol_02_04_1983_Jun#page/n109/mode/2up | title=Q&amp;A | work=Electronic Games | date=June 1983 | accessdate=7 January 2015 | author=[[The Game Doctor]] | page=112}}&lt;/ref&gt;  CBS Electronics reduced this pause in the BIOS to 3.3 seconds for their PAL and SECAM ColecoVision consoles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Game Title Display Duration Analysis |url=https://atariage.com/forums/topic/290923-game-title-display-duration-analysis/ |website=AtariAge |accessdate=6 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Expansion Modules and accessories ===
From its introduction, Coleco touted the ColecoVision's hardware expandability by highlighting the ''Expansion Module Interface'' on the front of the unit.  These hardware expansion modules and accessories were sold separately.

[[File:ColecoVision-ExpMod1-Attached.jpg|thumb|right|Expansion Module#1 allows the ColecoVision to play any Atari 2600 game.]]
[[File:ColecoVision-Expansion2.jpg|thumb|right|Expansion Module#2 is a steering wheel for racing games]]

==== Atari 2600 expansion ====
''Expansion Module #1'' makes the ColecoVision compatible with [[Atari 2600]] cartridges and controllers.&lt;ref name=&quot;eg198306&quot;/&gt; Functionally, this gave the ColecoVision the largest software library of any console of its day. The expansion module prompted legal action from Atari.  Coleco and Atari settled out of court with Coleco becoming licensed under Atari's patents.  The royalty based license also applied to Coleco's [[Coleco Gemini|Gemini game system]], a stand-alone clone of the 2600.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt-pact&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Atari-Coleco Pact|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1983/03/12/business/company-news-atari-coleco-pact.html|website=the New York Times|publisher=the New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Driving controller ====
''Expansion Module #2'' is a driving controller ([[steering wheel]] / gas pedal) that came packaged with the cartridge ''[[Turbo (video game)|Turbo]]''. The gas pedal is merely a simple on/off switch.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.the-liberator.net/site-files/retro-games/hardware/ColecoVision/colecovision-expansion-moduel-no-2-driving-controller.htm |title=Coleco ColecoVision Expansion Module No. 2 Driving Controller Disassembled |publisher=The-liberator.net |date= |accessdate=2014-05-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although Coleco called the driving controller an expansion module, it actually plugs into the controller port, not the ''Expansion Module Interface''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.colecovisionzone.com/photos/accessory/module2%20manual.pdf |title=Expansion Module #2 Operation Manual |publisher= |date= |accessdate=2019-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The driving controller is also compatible with the cartridges ''Destructor'', ''[[Bump 'n' Jump]]'', ''[[Pitstop (video game)|Pitstop]]'', and ''[[The Dukes of Hazzard (video game)|The Dukes of Hazzard]]''.

==== Adam computer expansion ====
''Expansion Module #3'' converts the ColecoVision into the [[Coleco Adam|Adam]] computer, complete with keyboard, digital data pack (DDP) cassette drive, 64 kB RAM, and printer.

==== Roller Controller ====
The ''Roller Controller'' is a [[trackball]] that came packaged with the cartridge ''Slither'', a conversion of the arcade game.&lt;ref name=&quot;eg198306-2&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=https://archive.org/stream/electronic-games-magazine-1983-06/Electronic_Games_Issue_16_Vol_02_04_1983_Jun#page/n23/mode/2up | title=Controller Update: Probing the World of the Exotic | work=Electronic Games | date=June 1983 | accessdate=6 January 2015 | pages=24–28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite AV media |people= |year=2008 |title=Classic Game Room reviews COLECOVISION ROLLER CONTROLLER |trans-title=|medium=YouTube |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MLnkQlMaQ1U |accessdate=April 2, 2014 |format=YouTube |time=4:45 |location= |publisher=Lord Karnage |id= |isbn= |oclc= |quote= |ref= }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The roller controller uses a special power connector that is not compatible with Expansion Module #3 (the Adam computer). Coleco mailed an adapter to owners of both units who complained.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.colecovisionzone.com/photos/accessory/roller%20manual.pdf |title=Roller Controller Operation Manual |publisher= |date= |accessdate=2019-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The other cartridge programmed to use the roller controller is ''Victory''.  A joystick mode switch on the roller controller allows it to be used with all cartridges including [[WarGames (video game)|WarGames]], ''Omega Race'', and Atarisoft's Centipede.

==== Super Action Controller ====
The ''Super Action Controller Set'' is a set of two handheld joystick controllers that came packaged with the cartridge ''Super Action Baseball''. Each controller has a ball-top joystick, four finger triggered action buttons, a 12-button numeric keypad, and a &quot;speed roller&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.colecovisionzone.com/photos/accessory/superaction%20manual.pdf |title=Super Action Controller Set Operation Manual |publisher= |date= |accessdate=2019-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The cartridges ''Super Action Football'', ''[[Rocky]]'' ''Super Action Boxing'', and a conversion of the arcade game ''[[Front Line (arcade game)|Front Line]]'' are also designed to be used with the ''Super Action Controller''.

==== Unreleased ====
Expansion Module #3 was originally the '''Super Game Module'''. It was advertised for an August 1983 release but was ultimately cancelled and replaced with the [[Coleco Adam|Adam]] computer expansion. The Super Game Module added a tape drive known as the [[Exatron Stringy Floppy]] with 128KB capacity, and the additional [[RAM]], said to be 30KB,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.colecovision.dk/sgm.htm|title=The First ColecoVision SGM. Super Game Module 1983. (never released).|website=www.colecovision.dk}}&lt;/ref&gt; to load and execute programs from tape. Games could be distributed on tiny tapes, called ''wafers'', and be much larger than the 16KB or 32KB [[ROM cartridge|ROM]] cartridges of the day. ''Super Donkey Kong'', with all screens and animations, ''Super Donkey Kong Jr'', and ''Super Smurf Rescue'' were demonstrated with the Super Game Module. The Adam computer expansion with its 256KB tape drive and 64KB RAM fulfilled the specifications promised by the Super Game Module.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Brown|first1=William|title=Super Game Module: Million bit baby|journal=Electronic Fun with Computer Games|date=June 1983|volume=1|issue=8|pages=16, 17, 39–43, 94|url=https://archive.org/details/Electronic_Fun_with_Computer_Games_Vol_01_No_08_1983-06_Fun_Games_Publishing_US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.lifewire.com/history-of-colecovision-729731|title=The ColecoVision/Nintendo Partnership and the Atari Clone|first1=D. S. Cohen A. gaming|last1=writer|first2=|last2=developer|first3=|last3=teacher|first4=Video Game|last4=Historian|first5=Gaming Industry|last5=Professional|website=Lifewire}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Games ==
{{Main|List of ColecoVision games}}
{{See also|List of Coleco Adam games}}

== Legacy ==
[[File:Coleco Vision Flashback 2.jpg|thumb|ColecoVision Flashback]]
During the creation of the [[Nintendo Entertainment System]], the ColecoVision was a huge influence. Takao Sawano, chief manager of the project, brought a ColecoVision home to his family, who were impressed by the system's capability to produce smooth graphics, which contrasted with the flickering commonly seen on Atari 2600 games. [[Masayuki Uemura]], head of Famicom development, stated that the ColecoVision set the bar that influenced how he approached the creation of the Famicom.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.glitterberri.com/developer-interviews/how-the-famicom-was-born/deciding-on-the-specs/|title=GlitterBerri's Game Translations » Deciding on the Specs|website=Glitterberri.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1986, [[Bit Corporation]] produced a ColecoVision clone called the [[Dina (video game console)|Dina]], which was sold in the United States by Telegames as the [[Telegames Personal Arcade]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://classicgaming.gamespy.com/View.php?view=ConsoleMuseum.Detail&amp;id=24 |title=ColecoVision - 1982-1984 - Classic Gaming |publisher=Classicgaming.gamespy.com |accessdate=2010-12-20 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111001232609/http://classicgaming.gamespy.com/View.php?view=ConsoleMuseum.Detail&amp;id=24 |archivedate=2011-10-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[IGN]] named the ColecoVision their 12th-best video-game console out of their list of 25, citing &quot;its incredible accuracy in bringing current-generation arcade hits home.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ign.com/top-25-consoles/12.html |title=Colecovision is number 12 |website=[[IGN]] |accessdate=2010-12-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1996, programmer Kevin Horton released the first [[Homebrew (video games)|homebrew]] game for the ColecoVision, a [[Tetris]] clone entitled ''Kevtris''.&lt;ref name=&quot;kevtris&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mobygames.com/game/colecovision/kevtris |title=Kevtris for ColecoVision |publisher=MobyGames |date=2006-11-29 |accessdate=2009-08-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;kevinterview&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gooddealgames.com/interviews/int_horton.html |title=Classic Videogame Games INTERVIEW - Kevin Horton |publisher=Good Deal Games |date= |accessdate=2009-08-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1997, Telegames released ''Personal Arcade Vol. 1'', a collection of ColecoVision games for [[Microsoft Windows]],&lt;ref name=&quot;pav1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mobygames.com/game/personal-arcade-volume-one |title=Personal Arcade Volume One for Windows |publisher=MobyGames |date=2000-05-21 |accessdate=2009-08-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a 1998 follow-up, ''Colecovision Hits Volume One''.&lt;ref name=&quot;cvh1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mobygames.com/game/classic-gamer-colecovision-hits-volume-one |title=Classic Gamer: Colecovision Hits Volume One for Windows |publisher=MobyGames |date=2000-05-30 |accessdate=2009-08-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2012 Opcode Games released their own Super Game Module expansion, which increases RAM from 16KB to 32KB and adds four additional sound channels.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.opcodegames.com/sgm/sgm.html|title=ColecoVision Super Game Module|website=www.opcodegames.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; This expansion brings the ColecoVision close to the MSX architecture standard, allowing MSX software to be more easily ported.

In 2014, AtGames began producing the ColecoVision Flashback console that includes 60 games, but not the original pack-in game, ''[[Donkey Kong]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;atflashback&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.atgames.us/ColecoVision-Flashback-CV450.htm|title=ColecoVision Flashback at AtGames E-Store|access-date=2015-03-08|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150215204801/http://www.atgames.us/ColecoVision-Flashback-CV450.htm|archive-date=2015-02-15|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|ColecoVision}}
* [https://www.lifewire.com/history-of-colecovision-729731] - History of the ColecoVision at Lifewire.
* [http://www.colecovisionzone.com/ ColecoVision Zone] - Comprehensive archive of photos and documents.

{{Second generation game consoles}}
{{Home video game consoles}}

[[Category:Coleco consoles|Vision]]
[[Category:Computer-related introductions in 1982]]
[[Category:Home video game consoles]]
[[Category:Second-generation video game consoles]]
[[Category:1980s toys]]</text>
      <sha1>8vcuq61mhw9qo155r7yu186urunyte9</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
