  <page>
    <title>Anaxarchus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1738</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942747291</id>
      <parentid>942616492</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-26T16:04:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Magic links bot</username>
        <id>30707369</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Replace [[Help:Magic links|magic links]] with templates per [[Special:Permalink/772743896#Future of magic links|local RfC]] and [[:mw:Requests for comment/Future of magic links|MediaWiki RfC]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Anaxarchus''' ({{IPAc-en|ˌ|æ|n|ə|ɡ|ˈ|z|ɑr|k|ə|s}}; {{lang-grc|Ἀνάξαρχος}}; {{circa|380|320 BC}}) was a [[Greek people|Greek]] [[philosopher]] of the school of [[Democritus]]. Together with [[Pyrrho]], he accompanied [[Alexander the Great]] into Asia. The reports of his philosophical views suggest that he was a forerunner of [[Pyrrhonism]]. [[Claudius Aelianus|Aelian]] writes that he was called Eudaemonicus or &quot;Happy Man&quot;({{lang-grc|Εὐδαιμονικὸς}}).&lt;ref name=&quot;Varia_Historia_9.37&quot;&gt;[http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0545.tlg002.perseus-grc1:9.37 Aelian, Varia Historia, 9.37]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Diogenes Laërtius, ''Lives'', ix. 60&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Pyrrhonism sidebar}} 
==Life==
[[File:MacedonEmpire.jpg|thumb|upright=1.5|Map of [[Alexander the Great]]'s empire and the route he and Anaxarchus took to India]]
Anaxarchus was born at [[Abdera, Thrace|Abdera]] in [[Thrace]]. He was the companion and friend of [[Alexander the Great]] in his Asiatic campaigns. According to [[Diogenes Laërtius]], in response to Alexander's claim to have been the son of Zeus-Ammon, Anaxarchus pointed to his bleeding wound and remarked, &quot;See the blood of a mortal, not [[ichor]], such as flows from the veins of the immortal gods.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Laërtius60&quot;&gt;Diogenes Laërtius, ''Lives'', ix. 60&lt;/ref&gt; [[Claudius Aelianus|Aelian]], writes that Anaxarchus laughed at Alexander for making himself a God and said, &quot;The hopes of our God are in a porringer of broth&quot;, when the physician prescribed a broth to Alexander.&lt;ref name=&quot;Varia_Historia_9.37&quot;/&gt;

[[Plutarch]] tells a story that at [[Bactra]], in 327&amp;nbsp;BC in a debate with [[Callisthenes]], he advised all to worship Alexander as a god even during his lifetime, is with greater probability attributed to the Sicilian [[Cleon]].{{citation needed|date=September 2016}}

When Alexander was trying to show that he is divine so that the Greeks and Macedonians would perform [[proskynesis]] to him, Anaxarchus said that Alexander could &quot;more justly be considered a god than Dionysus or Heracles&quot; (Arrian, 104).

Diogenes Laërtius says that [[Nicocreon]], the tyrant of [[Cyprus]], commanded him to be pounded to death in a mortar, and that he endured this torture with fortitude and [[Cicero]] relates the same story.&lt;ref name=&quot;Laërtius58&quot;&gt;Diogenes Laërtius, ''Lives'', ix. 58&lt;/ref&gt;

==Philosophy==
Very little is known about his philosophical views. It is thought that he represents a link between the [[atomism]] of [[Democritus]], and the [[Pyrrhonism|skepticism]] of [[Pyrrho]].

Anaxarchus is said to have studied under Diogenes of Smyrna, whose teachings were said to be the same as those of Democritus' student [[Protagoras]].&lt;ref&gt;Kathleen Freeman, ''Ancilla to the Pre-Socratic Philosophers: A Complete Translation of the Fragments in Diels, Fragmente der Vorsokratiker'' 1983 {{ISBN|0674035011}} p 121&lt;/ref&gt; Diogenes studied under [[Metrodorus of Chios]], who used to declare that he knew nothing, not even the fact that he knew nothing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Laërtius58&quot;/&gt; According to [[Sextus Empiricus]], Anaxarchus &quot;compared existing things to a scene-painting and supposed them to resemble the impressions experienced in sleep or madness.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Sextus Empiricus, ''Against the Logicians'', 7.88.&lt;/ref&gt; Anaxarchus's student Pyrrho is said to have adopted &quot;a most noble philosophy, … taking the form of agnosticism and suspension of judgement.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Diogenes Laërtius, ''Lives'', ix. 61&lt;/ref&gt; Anaxarchus is said to have praised Pyrrho's &quot;indifference and sang-froid.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Diogenes Laërtius, ''Lives'', ix. 63&lt;/ref&gt; Anaxarchus is said to have possessed &quot;fortitude and contentment in life,&quot; which earned him the epithet ''eudaimonikos'' (&quot;fortunate&quot;),&lt;ref name=&quot;Laërtius60&quot;/&gt; which may imply that he held the end of life to be ''[[eudaimonia]].''

[[Plutarch]] reports that he told [[Alexander the Great]] that there was an infinite number of worlds, causing the latter to become dejected because he had not yet conquered even one.&lt;ref&gt;Plutarch's Morals&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*{{cite IEP |url-id=anaxarch |title=Anaxarchus |last=O'Keefe |first=Tim}}
*{{ws|[[Diogenes Laërtius]], ''[[s:Lives of the Eminent Philosophers/Book IX#Anaxarchus|Life of Anaxarchus]]'', translated by [[Robert Drew Hicks]] (1925)}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Anaxarchus}}
[[Category:4th-century BC Greek people]]
[[Category:4th-century BC philosophers]]
[[Category:Abderites]]
[[Category:Ancient Greek atomist philosophers]]
[[Category:Ancient Greeks in Macedon]]
[[Category:Ancient Thracian Greeks]]
[[Category:Hellenistic-era philosophers]]
[[Category:Philosophers and tutors of Alexander the Great]]
[[Category:Ancient Skeptic philosophers]]
[[Category:Executed philosophers]]
[[Category:Pyrrhonism]]
[[Category:Murdered philosophers]]</text>
      <sha1>j5lg8yxlv5u05w2xnm2613vwpo6cpad</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
