  <page>
    <title>Andronikos I Komnenos</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1762</id>
    <revision>
      <id>932277858</id>
      <parentid>929878607</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-24T17:50:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wuffit Mix</username>
        <id>37892354</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rectify formatting inconsistencies</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses|Andronikos Komnenos (disambiguation){{!}}Andronikos Komnenos}}
{{Infobox royalty
|name           =Andronikos I Komnenos
|image= ByzantineBillonTrachy.jpg
|caption        =[[Billon (alloy)|Billon]] ''[[Scyphate|trachy]]'' (a cup-shaped coin) of Andronikos I Komnenos
|succession      = [[List of Byzantine emperors|Emperor]] of the [[Byzantine Empire]]
|reign          =24 September 1183 – 12 September 1185
|coronation     =
|predecessor    =[[Alexios II Komnenos]]
|successor      =[[Isaac II Angelos]]
|spouse         =[[Agnes of France (Byzantine empress)|Anna of France]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Eudokia Komnene&lt;br /&gt;[[Philippa of Antioch]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Theodora Komnene, Queen of Jerusalem|Theodora Komnene]]
|spouse-type=Wife&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Mistresses
|issue          = [[Manuel Komnenos (born 1145)|Manuel Komnenos]]&lt;br /&gt;John Komnenos&lt;br /&gt;Maria Komnene &lt;br /&gt;[[Alexios Komnenos (son of Andronikos I)|Alexios Komnenos]]&lt;br /&gt;Eirene Komnene
|full name      =
|house          =[[Komnenid dynasty|Komnenoi]]
|house-type=Dynasty
|father         =[[Isaac Komnenos (d. 1152)|Isaac Komnenos]]
|mother         =Irene of Galicia or Kata of Georgia
|birth_date  =c. 1118
|birth_place =
|death_date  =12 September 1185&lt;br /&gt;(aged 66–67)
|death_place = [[Constantinople]]
|place of burial =
||title=[[List of Byzantine Emperors|Emperor and Autocrat of the Romans]]}}
'''Andronikos I Komnenos''' ({{lang-grc-gre|Ανδρόνικος Αʹ Κομνηνός}}, {{lang|grc-Latn|Andrónikos I Komnēnós}}; {{c.|lk=no|1118}}&amp;nbsp;– 12 September 1185), usually [[Latinization of names|Latinized]] as '''Andronicus I Comnenus''', was [[Byzantine Emperors|Byzantine Emperor]] from 1183 to 1185. He was the son of [[Isaac Komnenos (d. 1152)|Isaac Komnenos]] and the grandson of the emperor [[Alexios I Komnenos|Alexios I]].
{{TOClimit|2}}

==Biography==

===Early years===
Andronikos Komnenos was born around 1118. He was handsome and eloquent, active, hardy, courageous, a great general and an able politician, but also [[licentious]].{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}} His early years were spent alternately in pleasure and in military service.

In 1141 he was taken captive by the [[Seljuq Turks]] and remained in their hands for a year. On being [[Ransom|ransomed]], he went to [[Constantinople]], where he was held at the court of his [[first cousin]], the Emperor [[Manuel I Comnenus|Manuel I Komnenos]], to whom he was a great favourite. Here the charms of his niece, Eudoxia, attracted him and she became his mistress.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}} In 1152, accompanied by Eudoxia, he set out for an important command in [[Cilicia]]. [[Battle of Mamistra|Failing]] in his principal enterprise, an attack upon [[Mopsuestia]], he returned but was again appointed to the command of a province.  This second post he seems also to have left after a short interval, for he appeared again in Constantinople and narrowly escaped death at the hands of the brothers of Eudoxia.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}}

===Exile===
About 1153, a conspiracy against the Emperor in which Andronikos participated was discovered, and he was imprisoned. After repeated unsuccessful attempts, he escaped in 1165.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}} After passing through many dangers, including captivity in [[Vlach]] territory,{{sfn|Spinei|2009|p=131}} he reached [[Kiev]], where his cousin [[Yaroslav Osmomysl]] of [[Principality of Halych|Galicia]] held court. While under the protection of Yaroslav, Andronikos formed an alliance with the Emperor Manuel I, and with a Galician army he joined Manuel in the invasion of [[Hungary]], assisting at the siege of [[Zemun|Semlin]].{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}} The campaign was successful, and Andronikos returned to Constantinople with Manuel I in 1168; a year later, however, Andronikos refused to take the oath of allegiance to the future king [[Béla III of Hungary]], whom Manuel desired to become his successor. Andronikos was removed from court but received the province of [[Cilicia]].{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}}

Still under the displeasure of the Emperor, Andronikos fled to the court of [[Raymond of Antioch|Raymond]], [[Principality of Antioch|Prince of Antioch]]. While residing here he captivated and seduced the beautiful daughter of the Prince, [[Philippa of Antioch|Philippa]], sister of the Empress [[Maria of Antioch|Maria]]. The Emperor was again angered by this dishonour, and Andronikos was compelled to flee.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}} He took refuge with King [[Amalric I of Jerusalem]], whose favour he gained, and who invested him with the [[Principality of Galilee|Lordship of Beirut]]. In Jerusalem he saw [[Theodora Komnene, Queen of Jerusalem|Theodora Komnene]], the beautiful widow of King [[Baldwin III of Jerusalem|Baldwin III]] and niece of the Emperor Manuel. Although Andronikos was at that time fifty-six years old, age had not diminished his charms, and Theodora became the next victim of his artful seduction.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}} To avoid the vengeance of the Emperor, she fled with Andronikos to the court of [[Nur ad-Din Zangi|Nur ad-Din]], the [[Rulers of Damascus|Sultan of Damascus]]. Feeling unsafe there, they continued their perilous journey through the [[Caucasus]] and [[Anatolia]].{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}} They were well received by King [[George III of Georgia]], whose anonymous sister had probably been the first wife of Andronikos.

Andronikos was granted estates in [[Kakhetia]], in the east of Georgia. In 1173 or 1174, he accompanied the Georgian army on an expedition to [[Shirvan]] up to the [[Caspian Sea|Caspian]] shores, where George recaptured the fortress of [[Shabaran]] from the invaders from [[Derbent|Darband]] for his cousin, the [[Shirvanshah]] [[Akhsitan I ibn Minuchihr III|Akhsitan I]].{{sfn|Minorsky|1945|pp=557–558}} Finally, Andronikos and Theodora settled in the ancestral lands of the Komnenoi at [[Oinaion]], on the shores of the [[Black Sea]], between [[Trabzon|Trebizond]] and [[Sinop, Turkey|Sinope]].&lt;ref&gt;Speros Vryonis Jr., ''The Decline of medieval Hellenism in Asia Minor: and the process of Islamization from the eleventh through the fifteenth century'', (Berkeley: University of California, 1971), p. 127&lt;/ref&gt; While Andronikos was on one of his incursions into Trebizond, his castle was surprised by the governor of that province, and Theodora and her two children were captured and sent to Constantinople. To obtain their release Andronikos in early 1180 made abject submission to the Emperor and, appearing in chains before him, besought pardon. This he obtained, and he was allowed to retire with Theodora into banishment at Oinaion.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}}

===Emperor===
In 1180 the Emperor Manuel died and was succeeded by his ten-year-old son [[Alexius II Comnenus|Alexios II]], who was under the guardianship of his mother, Empress Maria.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}} Her Latin origins and culture led to creeping resentment from her Greek subjects. They had felt insulted by the Western tastes of Manuel, and being ruled by his Western wife built tensions to an explosion of rioting that almost became a full civil war.{{citation needed|date=January 2014}} This gave Andronikos the opportunity to seize the crown for himself, leaving his retirement in 1182 and marching to Constantinople with an army that (according to non-Byzantine sources) included Muslim contingents.&lt;ref&gt;
* [[Ibn Jubayr]] p. 355 Broadhurst (Turks and Arabs);{{full citation needed|date=January 2014}}
* [[William of Tyre]], ''Historia Transmarina'' 22.11 (''innumeras Barbararum nationum secum trahens copias'');{{full citation needed|date=January 2014}}
* [[Walter Map]], ''[[De Nugis Curialium]]'' 2.18 (Turks).{{full citation needed|date=January 2014}}
&lt;/ref&gt; The defection of the commander of the Byzantine navy, ''[[megas doux]]'' [[Andronikos Kontostephanos]], and the general Andronikos Angelos, played a key role in allowing the rebellious forces to enter Constantinople.{{sfn|Angold|1997|p=267}}

The arrival of Andronikos Komnenos was soon followed by a [[Massacre of the Latins|massacre of the city's Latin inhabitants]],{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}} who virtually controlled its economy, resulting in the deaths of thousands of Westerners. He was believed to have arranged the poisoning of Alexios II's elder sister [[Maria Komnene (daughter of Manuel I)|Maria the Porphyrogenita]] and her husband [[Renier of Montferrat]], although Maria herself had encouraged him to intervene; the poisoner was said to be the [[Eunuch (court official)|eunuch]] Pterygeonites.{{citation needed|date=January 2014|reason=for the poisoning and the details}} Soon afterwards Andronikos had the Empress Maria imprisoned and then killed — forcing a signature from the child Emperor Alexios to put his mother to death — by Pterygeonites and the ''[[hetaireiarches]]'' Constantine Tripsychos.{{citation needed|date=January 2014}} Alexios II was compelled to acknowledge Andronikos as colleague in the empire in front of the crowd on the terrace of the [[Arslan Hane, Istanbul|Church of Christ of the Chalkè]] and was then quickly put to death in turn; the killing was carried out by Tripsychos, Theodore Dadibrenos, and [[Stephen Hagiochristophorites]].{{sfn|Choniates|1984|pp=260–274}}

In 1183, sixty-five year old Andronikos married twelve-year-old [[Agnes of France, Empress consort of the Eastern Roman Empire|Agnes of France]],{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}} daughter of King [[Louis VII of France]] and his third wife [[Adèle of Champagne]] — Agnes had been betrothed to Alexios II.{{citation needed|date=January 2014|reason=for the previous betrothal}} By November 1183, Andronikos had associated his younger legitimate son John Komnenos on the throne.{{citation needed|date=January 2014}} In 1184, a Venetian embassy visited Constantinople, and an agreement was reached that compensation of 1,500 gold pieces would be paid for the losses incurred in 1171.{{citation needed|date=January 2014}}

The reign of Andronikos was characterized by his harsh measures. He resolved to suppress many abuses but above all things to check [[feudalism]] and limit the power of the nobles, who were rivals for his throne. The people, who felt the severity of his laws, at the same time acknowledged their justice and found themselves protected from the rapacity of their superiors,{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}} who had grown corrupt under the safety and opulence of Manuel I's rule.{{citation needed|date=January 2014}} Andronikos became increasingly paranoid and violent, however, and the Empire descended into a terror state.{{citation needed|date=January 2014}}. In September 1185, he ordered the execution of all prisoners, exiles, and their families for collusion with the invaders. The aristocrats in turn were infuriated against him,{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}} and there were several revolts.{{citation needed|date=January 2014}}

The stories of chaos led to an invasion by King [[William II of Sicily|William]] of the Norman Sicilians.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}} William landed in [[Despotate of Epirus|Epirus]] with a strong force of 200 ships and 80,000 men, including 5,000 knights,{{citation needed|date=January 2014|reason=for the numbers}} and marched as far as [[Thessalonica]], which he [[Sack of Thessalonica (1185)|took and pillaged]] ruthlessly (7,000 Greeks died).{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}}{{citation needed|date=January 2014|reason=for the numbers and ethnicity}} Andronikos hastily assembled five different armies to stop the Sicilian army from reaching Constantinople, but his forces failed to stand and retreated to the outlying hills. Andronikos also assembled a fleet of 100 ships to stop the Norman fleet from entering the [[Sea of Marmara]]. The invaders were finally driven out in 1186 by his successor, [[Isaac II Angelus|Isaac Angelos]].{{citation needed|date=January 2014|reason=for everything since the last Chisholm 1911 as none of these details are in EB1911 so they need a citation from another source}}

===Death===
[[File:Death of andronic I.png|thumb|250px|A medieval depiction of the death of Andronikos. Original in the Bibliothèque Nationale, France.]]

Andronikos seems then to have resolved to exterminate the aristocracy, and his plans were nearly successful. But on 11 September 1185, during his absence from the capital{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}} Stephen Hagiochristophorites, his lieutenant, moved to arrest [[Isaac II Angelus|Isaac Angelos]], whose loyalty was suspect.{{sfn|Harris|2003|p=136}} Angelos killed Hagiochristophorites and took refuge in the church of [[Hagia Sophia]]. He appealed to the populace, and a tumult arose that spread rapidly over the whole city.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}}

When Andronikos arrived he found that Isaac had been proclaimed emperor.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}} The deposed emperor attempted to escape in a boat with his wife Agnes and his mistress, but they were captured (though some claim that Andronikos survived and managed to escape to the self-proclaimed kingdom of [[Cyprus]]).{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}} Angelos handed him over to the city mob and for three days he was exposed to their fury and resentment,{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}} remaining for that period tied to a post and beaten. His right hand was cut off, his teeth and hair were pulled out, one of his eyes was gouged out, and, among many other sufferings, boiling water was thrown in his face, punishment probably associated with his handsomeness and life of licentiousness.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}} At last he was led to the [[Hippodrome of Constantinople]] and hung by his feet between two pillars. Two Latin soldiers competed as to whose sword would penetrate his body more deeply, and he was, according to the representation of his death, torn apart.{{sfn|Choniates|1984|p=193}} He died on 12 September 1185.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=975}} At the news of the Emperor's death, his son and co-emperor, John, was murdered by his own troops in [[Thrace]].{{sfn|Choniates|1984|p=193}}
Andronikos I was the last of the [[Comnenus|Komnenoi]] to rule Constantinople, although his grandsons [[Alexios I of Trebizond|Alexios]] and [[David Komnenos|David]] founded the [[Empire of Trebizond]] in 1204. Their branch of the dynasty was known as the &quot;Great Komnenoi&quot; (''Megalokomnenoi'').&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Vasiliev | first1 = V. V. | year = 1936 | title = The Foundation of the Empire of Trebizond (1204-1222) | journal = Speculum | volume = 11 | issue = | pages = 3–36 | jstor=2846872 | doi=10.2307/2846872}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Family==
Andronikos I Komnenos was married twice and had numerous mistresses. By his first wife, whose name is not known, he had three children:{{sfn|Varzos|1984a|p=637}}
* [[Manuel Komnenos (son of Andronikos I)|Manuel Komnenos]] (1145 – after 1185), served as an ambassador under Manuel I, and opposed his father's policies when he seized power. Due to this opposition, as well as adherence to the [[AIMA prophecy]], he was not named successor, but awarded the rank of ''[[sebastokrator]]'' instead. Nevertheless, he was blinded by the new regime following the downfall of his father, and disappears from the sources thereafter.{{sfn|Varzos|1984b|pp=511–528}} From his marriage to the [[Kingdom of Georgia|Georgian]] princess [[Rusudan, daughter of George III of Georgia|Rusudan]], he was the father of [[Alexios I of Trebizond|Alexios I]] and [[David Komnenos]], the founders of the [[Empire of Trebizond]] and of the dynasty of the Grand Komnenoi, the only male-line descendants of the Komnenian house.{{sfn|Varzos|1984a|pp=637–638}}{{sfn|Varzos|1984b|p=527}}
* [[John Komnenos (son of Andronikos I)|John Komnenos]] (1159–1185), as a child he accompanied his father during his exile, and after his rise to the throne was crowned co-emperor in November 1183. After the overthrow of Andronikos, he was executed in September 1185. {{sfn|Varzos|1984b|pp=528–532}}
* Maria Komnene (born {{circa|1166}}), married Theodore Synadenos in 1182, but he died shortly after; her second husband was a certain Romanos, whose rapacity and terrorization of the populace during the defence of [[Dyrrhachium]] against the Normans in 1185 contributed to the fall of the city. The fate of Maria and her husband after Andronikos' downfall is unknown.{{sfn|Varzos|1984b|pp=532–535}}

By his niece and mistress [[Theodora Komnene, Queen of Jerusalem|Theodora Komnene]], Andronikos I had the following children:{{sfn|Varzos|1984a|p=638}}
* [[Alexios Komnenos (son of Andronikos I)|Alexios Komnenos]] (1170 – {{circa|1199}}), his early life is obscure, he fled to Georgia after 1185, where he married into the local nobility. The noble family of [[Andronikashvili]] claim descent from him, and he may have been the forefather of the provincial rulers of [[Alastaneli]].{{sfn|Varzos|1984b|pp=532–537}}{{sfn|Williams|2006}}
* Irene Komnene (born 1171), she was married to the ''sebastokrator'' [[Alexios Komnenos (illegitimate son of Manuel I)|Alexios Komnenos]], an illegitimate son of Emperor Manuel I Komnenos, in October 1183. Her husband became involved in a conspiracy against Andronikos and was blinded and imprisoned, while Irene entered a monastery.{{sfn|Varzos|1984b|pp=481, 537–539}}
His second marriage to [[Anna of France]], and his liaisons with his other mistresses, remained childless.{{sfn|Varzos|1984a|p=638}}

== In popular culture ==
{{unreferenced section|date=January 2014}}
Andronikos is the main protagonist in Michael Arnold's ''Against the Fall of Night'' (Garden City, New York: Doubleday 1975), as well as Ange Vlachos' ''Their Most Serene Majesties'' (Vanguard Press, 1964).

He is mentioned in the [[Louis L'Amour]] medieval historical novel, ''[[The Walking Drum]]'', with his gruesome death foreseen by the protagonist in a vision.

He is among the main characters of the historical novel ''Agnes of France'' (1980) by [[Greeks|Greek]] writer [[Kostas Kyriazis]] (b. 1920). The novel describes the events of the reigns of Manuel I, Alexios II and Andronikos I through the eyes of Agnes. The novel ends with the death of Andronikos.

Andronikos was portrayed in the novel ''[[Baudolino]]'' by [[Umberto Eco]], with much detail being given to his grisly end.

==See also==
{{portal|Byzantine Empire}}
*[[Andrey Bogolyubsky]]
*[[List of Byzantine emperors]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
* {{Citation |last=Angold |first=Michael |year=1997 |title=The Byzantine Empire, 1025–1204 |publisher=Longman |isbn=0-582-29468-1}}
* {{EB1911 |mode=cs2 |wstitle=Andronicus I |volume=1 |pages=975–976}}
* {{cite book | last=Jurewicz | first=Oktawiusz | title=Andronikos I. Komnenos | language=German | year=1970 | publisher=Adolf M. Hakkert | location=Amsterdam | oclc=567685925 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal | first = Harry J. | last = Magoulias | title = Andronikos I Komnenos: A Greek Tragedy | journal = Byzantina Symmeikta | volume = 21 | year = 2011 | issn = 1791-4884 | pages = 101–136 | doi = 10.12681/byzsym.1032 | ref=harv}}
*{{Citation |last=Minorsky |first=Vladimir |authorlink=Vladimir Minorsky |title=Khāqānī and Andronicus Comnenus |journal=Bulletin of the School of Oriental and African Studies |publisher=University of London |volume=11 |number=3 |year=1945 |pages=557–558 |doi=10.1017/s0041977x0007227x}}
* {{Citation |last=Spinei |first=Victor |year=2009 |title=The Romanians and the Turkic Nomads North of the Danube Delta from the Tenth to the Mid-Thirteenth century |publisher=Koninklijke Brill NV |isbn=978-90-04-17536-5}}
* {{Citation |first=Niketas |last=Choniates |authorlink=Niketas Choniates |year=1984 |translator=Magoulias |title=O City of Byzantium |publisher=Wayne State University Press}}
* {{citation |last=Williams |first=Kelsey Jackson |year=2006 |url=http://fmg.ac/FMG/Journal/02-03.htm#A%20Genealogy%20of%20the%20Grand%20Komnenoi%20of%20Trebizond |title=A Genealogy of the Grand Komnenoi of Trebizond |journal=Foundations – the Journal of the Foundation for Medieval Genealogy |volume=2 |number=3 |hdl=10023/8570 |access-date=2007-07-24 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120207185450/http://fmg.ac/FMG/Journal/02-03.htm#A%20Genealogy%20of%20the%20Grand%20Komnenoi%20of%20Trebizond |archive-date=2012-02-07 |url-status=dead }}
* {{Citation | last=Harris | first=Jonathan | year=2003| title=Byzantium and the Crusades| publisher=Bloomsbury Academic}}
* {{Η Γενεαλογία των Κομνηνών | volume = A1 | ref={{harvid|Varzos1984a}} }}
* {{Η Γενεαλογία των Κομνηνών | volume = B | ref={{harvid|Varzos1984b}} }}

==Further reading==
{{Commons category|Andronikos I Komnenos}}
* Gibbon, Edward. ''The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire'', Chapter 48.
* Grünbart, Michael, 'Die Macht des Historiographen – Andronikos (I.) Komnenos und sein Bild', in ''Zbornik Radova Vizantinoloskog Instituta'' 48, 2011, pp.&amp;nbsp;75–85
* Harris, Jonathan, ''Byzantium and the Crusades'', Bloomsbury, 2nd ed., 2014. {{ISBN|978-1-78093-767-0}}
* Harris, Jonathan, 'Collusion with the infidel as a pretext for military action against Byzantium', in ''Clash of Cultures: the Languages of Love and Hate'', ed. Sarah Lambert and Helen Nicholson, Brepols, 2012, pp.&amp;nbsp;99–117. {{ISBN|978 2503 520643}}
* ''The [[Oxford Dictionary of Byzantium]]'', Oxford University Press, 1991.
* Mihai Tiuliumeanu, ''Andronic I Comnenul'', [[Iași]], 2000. {{in lang|ro}}
* Treadgold, Warren, ''A History of the Byzantine State and Society'', Stanford University Press, 1997
* Eustathios of Thessaloniki 'The Capture of Thessaloniki' (Byzantina Australiensia 8), [[Canberra]] 1988.
* The full text of a lecture by John Melville-Jones on the life of this emperor is located at:   [https://web.archive.org/web/20120111042205/http://home.vicnet.net.au/~byzaus/conferences/16th2010/andronicus.html]. It is accompanied by an extensive bibliography.

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou|[[Komnenos|Komnenian]] dynasty||1118|12 September|1185}}
{{s-reg|}}
{{s-bef
| before = [[Alexios II Komnenos]]
}}
{{s-ttl
| title = [[List of Byzantine Emperors|Byzantine Emperor]]
| years = 24 September 1183 – 12 September 1185
}}
{{s-aft
| after = [[Isaac II Angelos]]
}}
{{s-end}}

{{Roman Emperors}}
{{Komnenoi}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Komnenos, Andronikos I}}
[[Category:Komnenos dynasty|Andronikos 01]]
[[Category:Christians of the Crusades]]
[[Category:12th-century Byzantine emperors]]
[[Category:1118 births|Andronikos Komnenos]]
[[Category:1185 deaths|Andronikos Komnenos]]
[[Category:Eastern Orthodox monarchs]]
[[Category:Executed Byzantine people]]
[[Category:Executed monarchs]]
[[Category:Byzantine people of the Byzantine–Seljuq Wars]]
[[Category:People executed by dismemberment]]
[[Category:Lynching deaths]]
[[Category:12th-century executions by the Byzantine Empire]]</text>
      <sha1>i0gfmodt8vut1p6wiam8n6ujwrn2z8x</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
