  <page>
    <title>Ambrosians</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1717</id>
    <revision>
      <id>841503377</id>
      <parentid>826900266</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-05-16T07:33:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2600:8800:1880:91E:5604:A6FF:FE38:4B26</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */ [[WP:SEEALSO]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Ambrosians''' are members of one of the religious brotherhoods which at various times since the 14th century have sprung up in and around [[Milan]] and also a 16th-century sect of [[Anabaptist Ambrosians]].

==Orders==
[[File:AmbroseOfMilan.jpg|thumb|225px|Late Antique Mosaic of Saint Ambrose (~337-397) in [[Sant'Ambrogio]] church, [[Milan]], [[Lombardy]], [[Italy]], possibly an actual portrait made in his lifetime]]

Only the oldest of the Catholic Ambrosians, the Fratres S. Ambrosii ad Nemus, had anything more than a very local significance. This order is known from a [[Papal bull|bull]] of [[Pope Gregory XI]] addressed to the [[monk]]s of the church of St Ambrose outside Milan.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;&gt;{{EB1911|inline=y|wstitle=Ambrosians|volume=1|page=800}} This further references Herzog-Hauck's [[Schaff–Herzog Encyclopedia of Religious Knowledge|''Realencyklopadie'']], i. 439.&lt;/ref&gt;

Saint [[Ambrose]], Bishop of Milan, certainly did not found [[Religious orders#Catholic tradition|religious orders]], though he took an interest in the [[Christian monasticism|monastic life]] and watched over its beginnings in his [[diocese]], providing for the needs of a [[monastery]] outside the walls of Milan, as [[Augustine of Hippo|Saint Augustine]] recounts in his ''[[Confessions (St. Augustine)|Confessions]]''. Ambrose also made successful efforts to improve the moral life of women in the Milan of his time by promoting the permanent institution of Virgins, as also of widows. His exhortations and other interventions have survived in various writings: ''De virginibus'', ''De viduis'', ''De virginitate'', ''De institutione virginis'', ''De exhortatione virginitatis'', and ''De lapsu virginis consecratae''. Ambrose was the only Father of the Church to leave behind so many writings on the subject and his attentions naturally enough led to the formation of communities which later became formal monasteries of women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic&quot;&gt;{{Catholic|wstitle=Ambrosians|inline=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is against this background that two religious orders or congregations—one of men and one of women, when founded in the Milan area during the 13th and 15th centuries—took Saint Ambrose as their patron and hence adopted his name.&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic&quot;/&gt;

===Order of St Ambrose===
The first of these groups was formed in a wood outside Milan by three noble Milanese, Alexander Grivelli, Antonio Petrasancta, and Albert Besuzzi, who were joined by others, including some  priests. In 1375 [[Pope Gregory XI]] gave them the Rule of St Augustine, with set of constitutions. As a canonically recognized order they took the name &quot;Fratres Sancti Ambrosii ad Nemus&quot; and adopted a habit consisting of a brown [[tunic]], [[scapular]], and hood. The brethren elected a superior with the title of [[prior]] who was then instituted by the [[Archbishop of Milan]]. The priests of the congregation undertook preaching and other tasks of the ministry but were not allowed to accept charge parishes. In the liturgy they followed the [[Ambrosian Rite]]. Various monasteries were founded on these lines, but without any formal bond between them. In 1441 [[Pope Eugene IV]] merged them into one congregation called &quot;Congregatio Sancti Ambrosii ad Nemus&quot;, made the original house the main seat, and laid down a system of government whereby a general chapter met every three years, elected the priors who stayed in office till the next chapter. There was a rector, or superior general, who was assisted by two &quot;visitors&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic&quot;/&gt;

Saint Charles Borromeo, Archbishop of Milan, successfully reformed their discipline, grown lax, in 1579. In 1589 [[Pope Sixtus V]] united to the Congregation of St Ambrose the monasteries of a group known as the &quot;Brothers of the Apostles of the Poor Life&quot; (or  &quot;Apostolini&quot; or &quot;Brothers of St. Barnabas&quot;), whose houses were in the province of Genoa and in the March of Ancona. This was an order that had been founded by Giovanni Scarpa at the end of the 15th century. The union  was confirmed by [[Pope Paul V]] in 1606, at which time the congregation added the name of St. Barnabas to its title, adopted new constitutions, divided its houses into four provinces, two of them, St Clement's and St Pancras's, being in Rome. Published works have survived from the pen of Ascanio Tasca and Michele Mulozzani, each of whom was superior-general, and of Zaccaria Visconti, Francesco-Maria Guazzi and Paolo Fabulotti. Although various Ambrosians were given the title of Blessed in recognition of their holiness: Antonio Gonzaga of Mantua, Filippo of Fermo, and Gerardo of Monza, the order was eventually dissolved by [[Pope Innocent X]] in 1650.&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic&quot;/&gt;

===Nuns===
The Nuns of St Ambrose (Ambrosian Sisters) wore a habit of the same colour as the Brothers of St Ambrose, conformed to their constitutions, and followed the [[Ambrosian Rite]], but were independent in government. [[Pope Sixtus IV]] gave the nuns canonical status in 1474. Their one monastery was on the top of Monte Varese, near Lago Maggiore, on the spot where their foundress, the Blessed Catarina Morigia (or Catherine of Palanza), had first led a solitary life.  Other early nuns were the Blessed Juliana of Puriselli, Benedetta Bimia, and Lucia Alciata. The nuns were esteemed by St Charles Borromeo.&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic&quot;/&gt;

Another group of cloistered &quot;Nuns of St Ambrose&quot;, also called the Annunciatae (Italian: ''Annunziate'') of Lombardy or &quot;Sisters of St Marcellina&quot;, were founded in 1408 by three young women of Pavia, Dorothea Morosini, Eleonora Contarini, and Veronica Duodi. Their houses, scattered throughout Lombardy and Venetia, were united into a congregation by St Pius V, under the Rule of St Augustine with a mother-house, residence of the prioress general, at Pavia. One of the nuns in this group was Saint [[Catharine Fieschi Adorno]], who died on September 14, 1510.&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic&quot;/&gt;

===Oblates of St. Ambrose and of St. Charles===
{{Main|Oblates of Saints Ambrose and Charles}}
In some sense also &quot;Ambrosians&quot; are the members of a diocesan religious society founded by St [[Charles Borromeo]], Archbishop of Milan. All priests or destined to become priests, they took a simple vow of obedience to their bishop. The model for this was a society that already existed at Brescia, under the name of &quot;Priests of Peace&quot;. In August 1578 the new society was inaugurated, being entrusted with the church of the Holy Sepulchre and given the name of &quot;Oblates of St. Ambrose.&quot; They later received the approbation of Gregory XIII. St Charles died in 1584. These Oblates were dispersed by [[Napoleon I]] in 1810, while another group called the Oblates of Our Lady of Rho escaped this fate. In 1848 they were reorganized and given the name of &quot;Oblates of St. Charles&quot; and reassigned the house of the Holy Sepulchre. In the course of the 19th century similar groups were founded in a number of countries, including the &quot;Oblates of St Charles&quot;, established in London by Cardinal Nicholas Wiseman.&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic&quot;/&gt;

==See also==
*[[St. Ambrose University]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Anabaptism]]
[[Category:Baptism]]
[[Category:Premillennialism]]</text>
      <sha1>24z6qjvx2aqywrp88qvhn8m07c1kbxr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
