  <page>
    <title>Abu Bakr</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1715</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943198212</id>
      <parentid>943197923</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T13:26:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Serols</username>
        <id>9929111</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/86.98.118.212|86.98.118.212]] ([[User talk:86.98.118.212|talk]]) ([[WP:HG|HG]]) (3.4.9)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{For|other people with the name|Abu Bakr (name)}}
{{short description|First Muslim Caliph and the best friend/companion of the Prophet Muhammad}} 
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2019}}
{{Infobox royalty
| name         = Abu Bakr&lt;br/&gt;{{Nobold|{{lang|ar|أَبُو بَكْرٍ}}}}
| module = {{Infobox person | child=yes
| native_name  = {{lang-ar|أَبُو بَكْر}}
}}
| image        = Rashidun Caliph Abu Bakr as-Șiddīq (Abdullah ibn Abi Quhafa) - أبو بكر الصديق عبد الله بن عثمان التيمي القرشي أول الخلفاء الراشدين.svg
| title        = Al-Siddiq&lt;br&gt;
Atiq&lt;br&gt;
| caption      = Abū Bakr as-Ṣiddīq
| succession   = 1st [[Caliph]] of the [[Rashidun Caliphate]]
| moretext     = 
| reign        = 8 June 632{{snd}}23 August 634
| reign-type   = Caliphate
| coronation   =
| cor-type     = [[Coronation|Bayah]]
| predecessor  = ''Established position''
| pre-type     = [[Prophet|Caliph]]
| successor    = [[Umar ibn Al-Khattab]]
| suc-type     = Successor
| spouse       = {{plainlist|
*[[Qutaylah bint Abd-al-Uzza]] (divorced)
*[[Umm Ruman|Umm Rumān]]
*[[Asma bint Umais]]
*Habibah bint Kharijah}}
| spouse-type  = Spouses
| consort      = &lt;!-- yes or no --&gt;
| issue        = '''Sons'''{{plainlist|
*[[Abdullah ibn Abi Bakr]]
*[[Abdul-Rahman ibn Abi Bakr]]
*[[Muhammad ibn Abi Bakr]]
}}
{{plainlist|
'''Daughters'''
*[[Asma bint Abi Bakr]]
*[[Aisha bint Abi Bakr]]
*[[Umm Khultum bint Abi Bakr]]
}}
| issue-link   = 
| issue-pipe   = 
| full name    = Abu Bakr Abdullah ibn Uthman Abu Quhafa&lt;br/&gt;({{lang-ar|links=no|أَبُو بَكْرٍ عَبْدُ ٱللهِ بْنُ عُثْمَانَ أَبِي قُحَافَةَ}})
| father      = [[Uthman Abu Quhafa]]
| mother       = [[Salma Umm al-Khair]]
{{Infobox|child=yes
| label1 = Brothers
| data1 = {{plainlist|
* Mu'taq (presumably the middle)
* Utaiq (presumably the youngest)
* Quhafah
}}
| label2 = Sisters
| data2 = 
{{plainlist|
* Fadra
* Qareeba
* Umm Amir
}}
| label3 = Tribe
| data3 = [[Quraysh]] ([[Banu Taym]])
| label4 = Descendants
| data4 = [[Siddiqui]]
}}
| birth_date   = {{Birth date|573|10|27|df=y}}
| birth_place  = [[Mecca]], [[Hejaz]], [[Arabian Peninsula|Arabia]]
| death_date   = {{date of death and age|634|8|23|573|10|27|df=y}}
| death_place  = [[Medina]], Hejaz, [[Rashidun Empire]]
| burial_date  = 
| burial_place = [[Al-Masjid an-Nabawi]], Medina
| occupation   = Businessman&lt;br/&gt;
administrator
economist
| signature_type = 
| signature    = 
| religion     = [[Islam]]
}}

'''Abu Bakr Abdullah ibn Uthman''' ({{lang-ar|أَبُو بَكْرٍ عَبْدُ ٱللهِ بْنِ عُثْمَانَ}}; {{circa}} 573 CE{{snd}}23 August 634 CE),{{efn|name=&quot;AbuBakr-IE2&quot;|{{cite encyclopedia |quote=His father was Abu Quhafa ..., and he is therefore sometimes known as Ibn Abi Quhafa. ... The names ''‘Abd Allah'' and ''‘Atiq'' ('freed slave') are attributed to him as well as Abu Bakr, but the relation of these names to one another and their original significance is not clear. ... He was later known by sunni muslims as ''al-Siddiq'', the truthful, the upright, or the one who counts true |encyclopedia=[[Encyclopedia of Islam]] |edition=2nd |title=Abu Bakr}}}} was a [[Sahabah|companion]] and, through his daughter [[Aisha]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Campo&quot;&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=OZbyz_Hr-eIC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Juan Eduardo Campo, ''Encyclopedia of Islam'', Infobase Publishing, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; a father-in-law of the [[Prophets and messengers in Islam|Islamic prophet]] [[Muhammad]], as well as the first of the [[Rashidun Caliphate|Rashidun Caliphs]].

Initially a rich and respected businessman, Abu Bakr later became one of the first converts to [[Islam]] and extensively contributed his wealth in support of Muhammad's work. He was among Muhammad's closest companions,&lt;ref name=Saritoprak&gt;{{cite web |last1=Saritoprak |first1=Zeki |title=Abu Bakr Al-Siddiq |url=http://www.oxfordbibliographies.com/view/document/obo-9780195390155/obo-9780195390155-0221.xml |website=Oxford Bibliographies |publisher=Oxford University Press |accessdate=12 December 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; accompanying him on his [[Hegira|migration to Medina]] and being present at a number of his military conflicts, such as the battles of [[Battle of Badr|Badr]] and [[Battle of Uhud|Uhud]].

Following Muhammad's death in 632, Abu Bakr [[Succession to Muhammad|succeeded in the leadership]] of the Muslim community as the first Rashidun [[Caliph]].&lt;ref name=&quot;brit&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/2153/Abu-Bakr|title=Abu Bakr - Muslim caliph|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; During his reign, he overcame a number of uprisings, collectively known as the [[Ridda wars]], as a result of which he was able to consolidate and expand the rule of the Muslim state over the entire [[Arabian peninsula]]. He also commanded the initial incursions into the neighbouring [[Sassanian Empire|Sassanian]] and [[Byzantine empire]]s, which in the years following his death, would eventually result in the Muslim [[Muslim conquest of Persia|conquests of Persia]] and [[Muslim conquest of the Levant|the Levant]]. Abu Bakr died of illness after a reign of 2 years, 2 months and 14 days.

==Lineage and title==
{{See also|Family tree of Abu Bakr}}
[[File:Abubakr'sreign.png|thumb|Rashidun Caliphate during the reign of Abu Bakr.]]
Abu Bakr's full name was Abdullah ibn [[Uthman Abu Quhafa|Uthman]] ibn Amir ibn Amr ibn Ka'b ibn Sa'd ibn [[Banu Taym|Taym]] ibn Murrah ibn Ka'b ibn Lu'ayy Ghalib ibn Fihr.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ibn Sa'd#The Major Classes|Tabaqat ibn Sa'd]] 3/ 169&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Arabic]], the name ''Abd Allah'' means &quot;servant of [[Allah]]&quot;. One of his early titles, preceding his conversion to [[Islam]], was ''Ateeq'', meaning &quot;saved one&quot;. Muhammad later restated this title when he said that Abu Bakr is the &quot;Ateeq&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Abi Na'eem, &quot;Ma'arifat al-sahaba&quot;, no. 60&lt;/ref&gt; He was called ''Al-Siddiq'' (the truthful)&lt;ref name=&quot;Campo&quot;/&gt; by Muhammad after he believed him in the event of [[Isra and Mi'raj]] when other people didn't, and [[Ali]] confirmed that title several times.&lt;ref&gt;Abi Na'eem, &quot;Ma'arifat al-sahaba&quot;, no. 64, 65&lt;/ref&gt; He was also reportedly referred to in the [[Quran]] as the &quot;second of the two in the cave&quot; in reference to the event of [[Hijra (Islam)|hijra]], where with Muhammad he hid in the cave in [[Jabal Thawr]] from the [[Mecca]]n party that was sent after them.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=focLrox-frUC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Cyril Glassé, Huston Smith, ''The new encyclopedia of Islam'', Rowman Altamira, 2003] {{ISBN|0-7591-0190-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
Abu Bakr was born in [[Mecca]] sometime in 573 CE, to a rich family in the [[Banu Taym]] tribe of the [[Quraysh (tribe)|Quraysh]] tribal confederacy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Islamic Thought: From Mohammed to September 11, 2001 |last=Al-Jubouri |first=I.M.N. |year=2010 |location=Berlin |pages=53 |url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=owqY-90imMIC&amp;pg=PA53 |via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; His father's name was [[Uthman Abu Quhafa|Uthman]] and given the [[Arabic name#Laqab|laqab]] ''Abu Quhafa'', and his mother was [[Salma Umm-ul-Khair|Salma bint Sakhar]] who was given the laqab of  ''Umm ul-Khair''.&lt;ref name=Saritoprak/&gt;

He spent his early childhood like other [[Arab]] children of the time, among the [[Bedouin]]s who called themselves ''Ahl-i-Ba'eer''- the people of the [[camel]], and developed a particular fondness for camels. In his early years he played with the camel calves and goats, and his love for camels earned him the nickname (''[[Kunya (Arabic)|kunya]]'') &quot;''Abu Bakr''&quot;, the father of the camel's calf.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Islam for Nerds – 500 Questions and Answers |last=Drissner |first=Gerald |publisher=createspace |year=2016 |isbn=978-1530860180 |location=Berlin |pages=432 |quote= |via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''War and Peace in the Law of Islam'' by [[Majid Khadduri]]. Translated by Muhammad Yaqub Khan Published 1951 Ahmadiyyah Anjuman Ishaat Islam. Original from the [[University of Michigan]]. Digitized 23 October 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

Like other children of the rich Meccan merchant families, Abu Bakr was literate and developed a fondness for [[Arabic poetry|poetry]]. He used to attend the annual fair at [[Souk Okaz|Ukaz]], and participate in poetical symposia. He had a very good memory and had a good knowledge of the [[genealogy]] of the Arab tribes, their stories and their politics.&lt;ref&gt;Al-zarkali, &quot;al-a'alam&quot;, dar al'ilm lil'malayeen, 15th edition, May 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

A story is preserved that once when he was a child, his father took him to the [[Kaaba]], and asked him to pray before the [[Idolatry|idols]]. His father went away to attend to some other business, and Abu Bakr was left alone. Addressing an idol, Abu Bakr said &quot;O my God, I am in need of beautiful clothes; bestow them on me&quot;. The idol remained indifferent. Then he addressed another idol, saying, &quot;O God, give me some delicious food. See that I am so hungry&quot;. The idol remained cold. That exhausted the patience of young Abu Bakr. He lifted a stone, and, addressing an idol, said, &quot;Here I am aiming a stone; if you are a god protect yourself&quot;. Abu Bakr hurled the stone at the idol and left the [[Kaaba]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=Sidiq-i-Akbar Hazrat Abu Bakr | author=Masud-ul-Hasan | page=2 | publisher=A. Salam, Ferozsons Ltd | location=Lahore}}&lt;/ref&gt; Regardless, it recorded that prior to converting to Islam, Abu Bakr practised as a ''[[hanif]]'' and never worshipped idols.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.oxfordbibliographies.com/view/document/obo-9780195390155/obo-9780195390155-0221.xml|title=Abu Bakr Al-Siddiq – Islamic Studies – Oxford Bibliographies – obo|access-date=13 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Acceptance of Islam==
On his return from a business trip in [[Yemen]], friends informed him that in his absence, Muhammad had declared himself the [[Prophets and messengers in Islam|Messenger of God]] and proclaimed a new religion. The historian [[Al-Tabari]], in his ''[[History of the Prophets and Kings|Ta'rikh al-Tabari]]'', quotes from Muhammad ibn Sa'd ibn Abi Waqqas, who said: 
{{quote|I asked [[Sa'd ibn Abi Waqqas|my father]] whether Abu Bakr was the first of the Muslims. He said, 'No, more than fifty people embraced Islam before Abu Bakr; but he was superior to us as a Muslim. And [[Umar ibn Khattab]] had embraced Islam after forty-five men and twenty-one women. As for the foremost one in the matter of Islam and faith, it was [[Ali ibn Abi Talib]].'&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.al-islam.org/peshawar/6.1.html |title=Sixth Session, Tuesday night, 28th Rajab 1345 A.H. }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tarikh al-tabari vol.2-page 60&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Other [[Sunni]] and all [[Shi'a]] Muslims maintain that the second person to publicly accept Muhammed as the Messenger of God was Ali ibn Abi Talib, the first being Muhammad's wife [[Khadija bint Khuwaylid|Khadija]].&lt;ref&gt;M. Th. Houtsma et al., eds., ''E.J. Brill's first [[Encyclopaedia of Islam]], 1913–1936,'' Leiden: E. J. Brill, 8 vols. with Supplement (vol. 9), 1991. {{ISBN|90-04-09796-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ibn Kathir]], in his ''Al Bidaya Wal Nihayah'', disregards this. He stated that the first woman to embrace Islam was Khadijah. [[Zayd ibn Harithah]] was the first freed slave to embrace Islam. Ali ibn Abi Talib was the first child to embrace Islam, for he has not even reached the age of puberty at that time, while Abu Bakr was the first free man to embrace Islam.&lt;ref name=&quot;archive.org&quot;&gt;[https://archive.org/stream/TheBiographyOfAbuBakrAsSiddeeq/TheBiographyOfAbuBakrAs-siddeeq#page/n53/mode/2up The Biography Of Abu Bakr As Siddeeq] by Dr. Ali Muhammad As-Sallaabee (Published 2007)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Subsequent life in Mecca===
{{Islam|expanded=history}}
His wife [[Qutaylah bint Abd-al-Uzza]] did not accept Islam and he divorced her. His other wife, [[Um Ruman]], became a Muslim. All his children accepted Islam except [[Abdul-Rahman ibn Abi Bakr|Abdul-Rahman]], from whom Abu Bakr disassociated himself. His conversion also brought many people to Islam. He persuaded his intimate friends to convert,&lt;ref&gt;[[Al-Bidayah wa al-Nihayah|al-Bidayah wa'an-Nihayah]] 3/26&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Merriam-Webster]]'s ''Encyclopedia of World Religions'' by Wendy Doniger {{ISBN|978-0-87779-044-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; and presented Islam to other friends in such a way that many of them also accepted the faith. Those who converted to Islam at the insistence of Abu Bakr were:&lt;ref name=&quot;Ashraf&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Ashraf |first1=Shahid |title=Encyclopaedia Of Holy Prophet And Companion (Set Of 15 Vols.) |date=2004 |publisher=Anmol Publications Pvt. Limited |isbn=978-81-261-1940-0 |url=https://books.google.ca/books?id=QWqctAEACAAJ&amp;dq=isbn:8126119403&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwi8ysCKr5PmAhXR6Z4KHZXZBkMQ6AEIKTAA |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Uthman Ibn Affan]] (who would become the 3rd Caliph)
* [[Zubayr ibn al-Awam|Al-Zubayr]] (who played a part in the [[Muslim conquest of Egypt]])
* [[Talhah|Talha Ibn Ubayd-Allah]]
* [[Abdur Rahman bin Awf]] (who would remain an important part of the [[Rashidun Caliphate]])
* [[Sa`d ibn Abi Waqqas]] (who played a part in the [[Islamic conquest of Persia]])
* [[Abu Ubaidah ibn al-Jarrah]] (who remained commander in chief of the [[Rashidun army]] in Syria )
* [[Abu Salama]] (Abdullah bin Abdul Asad)
* [[Khalid ibn Sa`id]]
* [[Abu Hudhaifah ibn al-Mughirah]]

Abu Bakr's acceptance proved to be a milestone in Muhammad's mission. [[Islamic views on slavery|Slavery]] was common in Mecca, and many slaves accepted Islam. When an ordinary free man accepted Islam, despite opposition, he would enjoy the protection of his tribe. For slaves, however, there was no such protection and they commonly experienced persecution. Abu Bakr felt compassion for slaves, so he purchased eight (four men and four women) and then freed them, paying 40,000 [[dinar]] for their freedom.&lt;ref&gt;[[The Book of the Major Classes|Tabaqat ibn Sa'd]] 3/ 169, 174&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[History of the Prophets and Kings|Tarikh ar-Rusul wa al-Muluk]] 3/ 426&lt;/ref&gt;

The men were
* [[Bilal ibn Ribah]]
* [[Abu Fakih]]
* [[Ammar ibn Yasir]]
* [[Abu Fuhayra]]
The women were:
* [[Lubaynah]]
* [[Al-Nahdiah]]
* [[Umm Ubays]]
* [[Harithah bint al-Muammil]]

Most of the slaves liberated by Abu Bakr were either women or old and frail men.&lt;ref&gt;''The Mohammedan Dynasties: Chronological and Genealogical Tables with Historical Introductions (1894)'' by [[Stanley Lane-Poole]], published by Adamant Media Corporation {{ISBN|978-1-4021-6666-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; When the father of Abu Bakr asked him why he didn't liberate strong and young slaves, who could be a source of strength for him, Abu Bakr replied that he was freeing the slaves for the sake of [[Allah|God]], and not for his own sake.

===Persecution by the Quraysh, 613===
{{Main|Persecution of Muslims by the Meccans}}
For three years after the birth of Islam, Muslims kept their faith secret. In 613, according to Islamic tradition, Muhammad was commanded by God to call people to Islam openly. The first public address inviting people to offer allegiance to Muhammad was delivered by Abu Bakr.&lt;ref&gt;Muslim persecution of heretics during the marwanid period(64-132/684-750), Judd Steven, Al-Masq:Islam &amp; the medieval Mediterranean.Apr.2011, Vol.23 Issue 1 pg1-14.14p.&lt;/ref&gt; In a fit of fury, the young men of the [[Quraysh (tribe)|Quraysh]] tribe rushed at Abu Bakr and beat him till he lost consciousness.&lt;ref&gt;''Abu Bakr'' by Atta Mohy-ud-Din, published 1968 S. Chand Original from the University of Michigan, digitized 6 January 2006, [[Amazon Standard Identification Number|ASIN]] B0006FFA0O.&lt;/ref&gt; Following this incident, Abu Bakr's mother converted to Islam. Abu Bakr was persecuted many times by the Quraysh. Though Abu Bakr's beliefs would have been defended by his own clan, it would not be so for the entire Quraysh tribe.

===Last years in Mecca===
In 617, the Quraysh enforced a boycott against the [[Banu Hashim]]. Muhammad along with his supporters from Banu Hashim, were cut off in a pass away from [[Mecca]]. All social relations with the Banu Hashim were cut off and their state was that of imprisonment.{{clarify|date=March 2019}} Before it many Muslims migrated to [[Ethiopia|Abyssinia]] (now Ethiopia). Abu Bakr, feeling distressed, set out for Yemen and then to Abyssinia from there. He met a friend of his named Ad-Dughna (chief of the Qarah tribe) outside Mecca, who invited Abu Bakr to seek his protection against the Quraysh. Abu Bakr went back to Mecca, it was a relief for him, but soon due to the pressure of Quraysh, Ad-Dughna was forced to renounce his protection. Once again the Quraysh were free to persecute Abu Bakr.

In 620, Muhammad's uncle and protector, [[Abu Talib ibn Abd al-Muttalib]], and Muhammad's wife [[Khadija]] died. Abu Bakr's daughter [[Aisha]] was engaged to Muhammad, however it was decided that the actual marriage ceremony would be held later. In 620 Abu Bakr was the first person to testify to Muhammad's [[Isra and Mi'raj]] (Night Journey).&lt;ref&gt;''Islam (Exploring Religions)'' by Anne Geldart, published by [[Heinemann (book publisher)|Heinemann Library]], 28 September 2000. {{ISBN|978-0-431-09301-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Migration to Medina==
{{Main|Hijra (Islam)}}


In 622, on the invitation of the Muslims of [[Medina]], Muhammad ordered Muslims to migrate to Medina. The migration began in batches. Ali was the last to remain in Mecca, entrusted with responsibility for settling any loans the Muslims had taken out, and famously slept in the bed of Muhammad when the Quraysh, led by Ikrima, attempted to murder Muhammad as he slept. Meanwhile, Abu Bakr accompanied Muhammad to Medina. Due to the danger posed by the Quraysh, they did not take the road, but moved in the opposite direction, taking refuge in a cave in [[Jabal Thawr]], some five miles south of Mecca. [[`Abdullah ibn Abi Bakr]], the son of Abu Bakr, would listen to the plans and discussions of the Quraysh, and at night he would carry the news to the fugitives in the cave. [[Asma bint Abi Bakr]], the daughter of Abu Bakr, brought them meals every day.&lt;ref&gt;''Islamic Culture'' by the Islamic Cultural Board Published 1927 s.n. Original from the University of Michigan, digitized 27 March 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Aamir, a servant of Abu Bakr, would bring a flock of goats to the mouth of the cave every night, where they were milked. The Quraysh sent search parties in all directions. One party came close to the entrance to the cave, but was unable to see them. Due to this, [[Qur'an]] verse {{cite quran|9|40 |s=ns |b=n}} was revealed. [[Aisha]], [[Abu Sa‘id al-Khudri]] and [[Abdullah ibn Abbas]] in [[Tafsir|interpreting]] this verse said that Abu Bakr was the companion who stayed with Muhammad in the cave.

After staying at the cave for three days and three nights, Abu Bakr and Muhammad proceed to [[Medina]], staying for some time at Quba, a suburb of Medina.

===Life in Medina===
In Medina, Muhammad decided to construct a mosque. A piece of land was chosen and the price of the land was paid for by Abu Bakr. The Muslims, including Abu Bakr, constructed a mosque named [[Al-Masjid al-Nabawi]] at the site. Abu Bakr was paired with Khaarij ah bin Zaid Ansari (who was from Medina) as a [[Brotherhood among the Sahaba|brother in faith]]. Abu Bakr's relationship with Khaarijah was most cordial, which was further strengthened when Abu Bakr married Habiba, a daughter of Khaarijah.{{Citation needed|date=September 2019}} Khaarijah bin Zaid Ansari lived at Sunh, a suburb of Medina, and Abu Bakr also settled there. After Abu Bakr's family arrived in Medina, he bought another house near Muhammad's.&lt;ref&gt;[[Hazrat]] ''Abu Bakr, the First Caliph of Islam'' by Muhammad Habibur Rahman Khan Sherwani, published 1963 Sh. Muhammad Ashraf. Original from the University of Michigan. Digitized 14 November 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

While the climate of Mecca was dry, the climate of Medina was damp and because of this, most of the migrants fell sick on arrival. Abu Bakr contracted a fever for several days, during which time he was attended to by Khaarijah and his family. In Mecca, Abu Bakr was a wholesale trader in cloth and he started the same business in Medina. He opened his new store at Sunh, and from there cloth was supplied to the market at Medina. Soon his business flourished. Early in 623, Abu Bakr's daughter Aisha, who was already engaged to Muhammad, was handed over to Muhammad in a simple marriage ceremony, further strengthening relations between Abu Bakr and Muhammad.&lt;ref name=&quot;Maghazi&quot;&gt;Tabqat ibn al-Saad book of Maghazi, page no:62&lt;/ref&gt;

==Military campaigns under Muhammad==
{{Campaignbox Campaigns of Muhammad}}
{{Sunni Islam|Rightly Guided Caliphs}}

===Battle of Badr===
{{Main|Battle of Badr}}
In 624, Abu Bakr was involved in the first battle between the Muslims and the Quraysh of Mecca, known as the [[Battle of Badr]], but did not fight, instead acting as one of the guards of Muhammad's tent. In relation to this, Ali allegedly later asked his associates as to who they thought was the bravest among men. Everyone stated that Ali was the bravest of all men. Ali then replied:

{{quote|No. Abu Bakr is the bravest of men. In the [[Battle of Badr]] we had prepared a pavillion for the prophet, but when we were asked to offer ourselves for the task of guarding it none came forward except Abu Bakr. With a drawn sword he took his stand by the side of Prophet of Allah and guarded him from the infidels by attacking those who dared to proceed in that direction. He was therefore the bravest of men.&lt;ref&gt;Sidiq-i-Akbar Hazrat Abu Bakr by Prof. Masud-ul-Hasan Page 31. Printed and published by A. Salam, Ferozsons Ltd 60 Shahrah-e-Quaid-e-Azam, Lahore&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In Sunni accounts, during one such attack, two discs from Abu Bakr's shield penetrated into Muhammad's cheeks. Abu Bakr went forward with the intention of extracting these discs but [[Abu Ubaidah ibn al-Jarrah]] requested he leave the matter to him, losing his two [[incisor]]s during the process. In these stories subsequently Abu Bakr, along with other companions, led Muhammad to a place of safety.&lt;ref name=&quot;Maghazi&quot;/&gt;

===Battle of Uhud===
{{Main|Battle of Uhud}}
In 625, he participated in the [[Battle of Uhud]], in which the majority of the Muslims were routed and he himself was wounded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Morgan |first=Diane |title=Essential Islam: A Comprehensive Guide to Belief and Practice |publisher=ABC-CLIO |year=2010 |page=[https://archive.org/details/essentialislamco0000morg/page/126 126] |url=https://archive.org/details/essentialislamco0000morg |url-access=registration |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Before the battle had begun, his son [[Abdul-Rahman ibn Abi Bakr|Abdul-Rahman]], at that time still non-Muslim and fighting on the side of the Quraysh, came forward and threw down a challenge for a duel. Abu Bakr accepted the challenge but was stopped by Muhammad.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Sherwani |first=Muhammad Habibur Rahman Khan |title=Hazrat Abu Bakr, the First Caliph of Islam |year=1963 |page=23 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later, Abdul-Rahman approached his father and said to him &quot;You were exposed to me as a target, but I turned away from you and did not kill you.&quot; To this Abu Bakr replied &quot;However, if you had been exposed to me as a target I would not have turned away from you.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Al-Jubouri |first=I.M.N. |title=History of Islamic Philosophy: With View of Greek Philosophy and Early History of Islam |year=2004 |page=119 |url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=3xJjNG5CNdwC&amp;pg=PA119 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In the second phase of the battle, [[Khalid ibn al-Walid]]’s cavalry attacked the Muslims from behind, changing a Muslim victory to defeat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Watt, W. Montgomery |authorlink=W. Montgomery Watt |title=Muhammad: Prophet and Statesman |location=United Kingdom |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=1974 |isbn=0-19-881078-4 |pages=[https://archive.org/details/muhammadprophets00watt/page/138 138–39] |url=https://archive.org/details/muhammadprophets00watt/page/138 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Uhud&quot;, ''Encyclopedia of Islam Online''&lt;/ref&gt; Many fled from the battlefield, including Abu Bakr. However, according to his own account, he was &quot;the first to return&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvtxt|Al-Jubouri|2004|p=120|loc=[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=3xJjNG5CNdwC&amp;pg=PA120]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Battle of the Trench===
{{main|Battle of the Trench}}
In 627 he participated in the Battle of the Trench and also in the [[Invasion of Banu Qurayza]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Maghazi&quot;/&gt; In the Battle of the Trench, Muhammad divided the ditch into a number of sectors and a contingent was posted to guard each sector. One of these contingents was under the command of Abu Bakr. The enemy made frequent assaults in an attempt to cross the ditch, all of which were repulsed. To commemorate this event a mosque, later known as 'Masjid-i-Siddiq',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=Sidiq-i-Akbar Hazrat Abu Bakr | author=Masud-ul-Hasan | page=36 | publisher=A. Salam, Ferozsons Ltd | location=Lahore}}&lt;/ref&gt; was constructed at the site where Abu Bakr had repulsed the charges of the enemy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Maghazi&quot;/&gt;

===Battle of Khaybar===
{{main|Battle of Khaybar}}
Abu Bakr took part in the Battle of Khaybar. Khaybar had eight fortresses, the strongest and most well-guarded of which was called Al-Qamus. Muhammad sent Abu Bakr with a group of warriors to attempt to take it, but they were unable to do so. Muhammad also sent Umar with a group of warriors, but Umar could not conquer Al-Qamus either.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Razwy |first1=Sayed Ali Asgher |title=A Restatement of the History of Islam &amp; Muslims |page=192}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Ibn Ishaq |title=The Life of the Messenger of God}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Life of Mohammed&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Irving |first1=Washington |title=The Life of Mohammed}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Haykal |first1=Muhammad Husayn |title=The Life of Muhammad |date=1935 |location=Cairo |quote=As the days went by, the Prophet sent Abu Bakr with a contingent and a flag to the fortress of Na'im; but he was not able to conquer it despite heavy fighting. The Prophet then sent Umar bin al-Khattab on the following day, but he fared no better than Abu Bakr.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some other Muslims also attempted to capture the fort, but they were unsuccessful as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Razwy |first1=Sayed Ali Asgher |title=A Restatement of the History of Islam &amp; Muslims |pages=192–193 |quote=Some other captains also tried to capture the fortress but they also failed.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Finally, Muhammad sent Ali, who defeated the enemy leader, Marhab.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Life of Mohammed&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Razwy |first1=Sayed Ali Asgher |title=A Restatement of the History of Islam &amp; Muslims |page=193}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Military campaigns during final years of Muhammad===
{{Main|Expedition of Amr ibn al-As|Conquest of Mecca|Battle of Tabouk}}

In 629 Muhammad sent [['Amr ibn al-'As]] to Zaat-ul-Sallasal, followed by [[Abu Ubaidah ibn al-Jarrah]] in response to a call for reinforcements. Abu Bakr and Umar commanded an army under al-Jarrah, and they attacked and defeated the enemy.&lt;ref&gt;Sahih-al-Bhukari book of Maghazi, Ghazwa Saif-al-Jara&lt;/ref&gt;

In 630, when [[Conquest of Mecca|the Muslims conquered Mecca]], Abu Bakr was part of the army.{{citation needed|date=March 2019}} Before the conquest of Mecca his father [[Uthman Abu Quhafa]] converted to Islam.{{citation needed|date=March 2019}}

====Battles of Hunayn and Ta'if====
{{main|Battle of Hunayn|Siege of Ta'if}}
In 630, the Muslim army [[Battle of Hunayn|was ambushed]] by archers from the local tribes as it passed through the valley of Hunayn, some eleven miles northeast of [[Mecca]]. Taken unaware, the advance guard of the Muslim army fled in panic. There was considerable confusion, and the camels, horses and men ran into one another in an attempt to seek cover. Muhammad, however, stood firm. Only nine companions remained around him, including Abu Bakr. Under Muhammad's instruction, [[Abbas ibn Abdul Muttalib|Abbas]] shouted at the top of his voice, &quot;O Muslims, come to the Prophet of Allah&quot;. The call was heard by the Muslim soldiers and they gathered beside Muhammad. When the Muslims had gathered in sufficient number, Muhammad ordered a charge against the enemy. In the hand-to-hand fight that followed the tribes were routed and they fled to [[Autas]].

Muhammad posted a contingent to guard the Hunayn pass and led the main army to Autas. In the confrontation at Autas the tribes could not withstand the Muslim onslaught. Believing continued resistance useless, the tribes broke camp and retired to Ta'if.

Abu Bakr was commissioned by Muhammad to lead the [[Siege of Ta'if|attack against Ta'if]]. The tribes shut themselves in the fort and refused to come out in the open. The Muslims employed catapults, but without tangible result. The Muslims attempted to use a testudo formation, in which a group of soldiers shielded by a cover of cowhide advanced to set fire to the gate. However, the enemy threw red hot scraps of iron on the testudo, rendering it ineffective.

The siege dragged on for two weeks, and still there was no sign of weakness in the fort. Muhammad held a council of war. Abu Bakr advised that the siege might be raised and that God make arrangements for the fall of the fort. The advice was accepted, and in February 630, the siege of Ta'if was raised and the Muslim army returned to [[Mecca]]. A few days later Malik bin Auf, the commander, came to [[Mecca]] and became a Muslim.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=Sidiq-i-Akbar Hazrat Abu Bakr | author=Masud-ul-Hasan | page=46 | publisher=A. Salam, Ferozsons Ltd | location=Lahore}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Abu Bakr as Amir-ul-Hajj===
In 631 AD, Muhammad sent from Medina a delegation of three hundred Muslims to perform the [[Hajj]] according to the new Islamic way and appointed Abu Bakr as the leader of the delegation. The day after Abu Bakr and his party had left for the Hajj, Muhammad received a new revelation: Surah Tawbah, the ninth chapter of the Qur'an.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Razwy |first1=Sayed Ali Asgher |title=A Restatement of the History of Islam &amp; Muslims |page=255}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is related that when this revelation came, someone suggested to Muhammad that he should send news of it to Abu Bakr. Muhammad said that only a man of his house could proclaim the revelation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=ibn Ishaq |first1=Muhammad |title=The Life of the Messenger of God}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Muhammad summoned Ali, and asked him to proclaim a portion of Surah Tawbah to the people on the day of sacrifice when they assembled at [[Mina, Saudi Arabia|Mina]]. Ali went forth on Muhammad's slit-eared camel, and overtook Abu Bakr. When Ali joined the party, Abu Bakr wanted to know whether he had come to give orders or to convey them. Ali said that he had not come to replace Abu Bakr as Amir-ul-Hajj, and that his only mission was to convey a special message to the people on behalf of Muhammad.

At Mecca, Abu Bakr presided at the Hajj ceremony, and Ali read the proclamation on behalf of Muhammad. The main points of the proclamation were:

#Henceforward the non-Muslims were not to be allowed to visit the [[Kaaba]] or perform the pilgrimage.
#No one should circumambulate the Kaaba naked.
#[[Polytheism]] was not to be tolerated. Where the Muslims had any agreement with the polytheists such agreements would be honoured for the stipulated periods. Where there were no agreements a grace period of four months was provided and thereafter no quarter was to be given to the polytheists.

From the day this proclamation was made a new era dawned, and Islam alone was to be supreme in Arabia.

===Military campaigns as commander===
{{Main|Expedition of Abu Bakr As-Siddiq}}
{{Cleanup rewrite|2=section|date=March 2019}}
Abu Bakr also led one military campaign as commander, known as the [[Expedition of Abu Bakr As-Siddiq]],&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.co.uk&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=mZmBkoDa9fcC&amp;pg=PA205 |title=Atlas Al-sīrah Al-Nabawīyah |date=1 January 2004 |publisher=Darussalam |via=Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt; which took place in [[Najd|Nejd]], in July 628 (3rd Month 7AH in the [[Islamic calendar]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.co.uk&quot;/&gt; Abu Bakr led a large platoon in Nejd on the order of Muhammad. Many were killed and taken prisoner.&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.org/details/bub_gb_Feo9AAAAYAAJ/page/n102 &lt;!-- pg=83 --&gt; The life of Mahomet and history of Islam, Volume 4, By Sir William Muir, Pg 83] See bottom of page, notes section&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Sunni Islam|Sunni]] [[Hadith]] collection ''[[Sunan Abu Dawud]]'' mentions the event.&lt;ref&gt;{{Hadith-usc|usc=yes|abudawud|14|2632}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Expedition of Usama bin Zayd===
{{Main|Expedition of Usama bin Zayd}}
In 632, during the final weeks of his life, Muhammad ordered an expedition into Syria to avenge the defeat of the Muslims in the [[Battle of Mu'tah]] some years previously. Leading the campaign was [[Usama ibn Zayd]], whose father, Muhammad's erstwhile adopted son [[Zayd ibn Harithah]], had been killed in the earlier conflict.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Ahmad |first=Fazl |title=Heroes of Islam Series: Abu Bakr, the first caliph of Islam |year=1961 |pages=42 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; No more than twenty years old, inexperienced and untested, Usama's appointment was controversial, becoming especially problematic when veterans such as Abu Bakr, [[Abu Ubaidah ibn al-Jarrah]] and [[Sa'd ibn Abi Waqqas]] were placed under his command.&lt;ref name=PowersP27&gt;{{Cite book |last=Powers |first=David S. |title=Muhammad Is Not the Father of Any of Your Men: The Making of the Last Prophet |year=2011 |pages=27 |url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=KH2FUBSOQ8kC&amp;pg=PA27 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | first=Hasan M. |last=Balyuzi |authorlink=Hasan M. Balyuzi |title=Muḥammad and the Course of Islám|year=1976 |pages=151 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, the expedition was dispatched, though soon after setting off, news was received of Muhammad's death, forcing the army to return to Medina.&lt;ref name=PowersP27/&gt; The campaign was not reengaged until after Abu Bakr's ascension to the caliphate, at which point he chose to reaffirm Usama's command, which ultimately led to its success.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Ahmed |first=Nazeer |title=Islam in Global History: Volume One: From the Death of Prophet Muhammed to the First World War |year=2000 |pages=27 |url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=UavBlPQfuagC&amp;pg=PA27 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Death of Muhammad==
There are a number of traditions regarding Muhammad's final days which have been used to reinforce the idea of the great friendship and trust which is said to have existed between him and Abu Bakr. In one such episode, as Muhammad was nearing death, he found himself unable to lead prayers as he usually would. He instructed Abu Bakr to take his place, ignoring concerns from Aisha that her father was too emotionally delicate for the role. Abu Bakr subsequently took up the position, and when Muhammad entered the prayer hall one morning during [[Fajr prayer]]s, Abu Bakr attempted to step back to let him to take up his normal place and lead. Muhammad however, allowed him to continue. In a related incident, around this time, Muhammad ascended the pulpit and addressed the congregation, saying &quot;God has given his servant the choice between this world and that which is with God and he has chosen the latter.&quot; Abu Bakr, understanding this to mean that Muhammad did not have long to live, responded &quot;Nay, we and our children will be your ransom.&quot; Muhammad consoled his friend and ordered that all the doors leading to [[Al-Masjid an-Nabawi|the mosque]] be closed aside from that which led from Abu Bakr's house, &quot;for I know no one who is a better friend to me than he.&quot;&lt;ref name=FitzpatrickWalkerP2-3&gt;{{cite book |first1=Coeli |last1=Fitzpatrick |first2=Adam Hani |last2=Walker |title=Muhammad in History, Thought, and Culture: An Encyclopedia of the Prophet of God |year=2014|pages=2–3|url= https://books.google.com/books?id=2AtvBAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA2 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|Such incidents are used by some [[Sunni]]s to justify Abu Bakr's later ascension to the caliphate as they display the regard with which Muhammad held the former. However, several other companions had held similar positions of authority and trust, including the leading of prayers. Such honours may therefore not hold much importance in matters of succession.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=M.A. |last=Shaban |title=Islamic History: a New Interpretation |year=1971|page=[https://archive.org/details/IslamicHistoryANewInterpretationVol.1/page/n178 16]|url= https://archive.org/details/IslamicHistoryANewInterpretationVol.1 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Upon Muhammad's death, the Muslim community was unprepared for the loss of its leader and many experienced a profound shock. [[Umar]] was particularly effected, instead declaring that Muhammad had gone to consult with God and would soon return, threatening anyone who would say that Muhammad was dead.&lt;ref name=PhippsP70&gt;{{cite book |first=William E. |last=Phipps |title=Muhammad and Jesus: A Comparison of the Prophets and Their Teachings |year=2016|page=70|url= https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=DR_mDAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA70 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Abu Bakr, having returned to Medina,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first1=Muzaffar Husain|last1=Syed |first2=Syed Saud |last2=Akhtar |first3=B. D. |last3=Usmani |title=Concise History of Islam |year=2011|page=27|url= https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=eACqCQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA27|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; calmed Umar by showing him Muhammad's body, convincing him of his death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Ingrid |last=Mattson |authorlink=Ingrid Mattson |title=The Story of the Qur'an: Its History and Place in Muslim Life |year=2013|page=185 |url= https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=_-eUnDh_OWgC&amp;pg=PA185 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; He then addressed those who had gathered at the mosque, saying &quot;If anyone worships Muhammad, Muhammad is dead. If anyone worships God, God is alive, immortal&quot;, thus putting an end to any idolising impulse in the population. He then concluded with a verse from the [[Quran]]: &quot;Muhammad is no more than an apostle, and many apostles have passed away before him.&quot;&lt;ref name=PhippsP70/&gt;{{Cite Quran|3|144}}

==Saqifa==
{{Main|Succession to Muhammad|Saqifa}}
{{see also|List of Sahaba not giving bay'ah to Abu Bakr}}

In the immediate aftermath of the death of Muhammad, a gathering of the [[Ansar (Islam)|Ansar]] (natives of [[Medina]]) took place in the ''Saqifah'' (courtyard) of the [[Banu Sa'ida]] clan.&lt;ref name=FitzpatrickWalkerP3&gt;{{harvtxt|Fitzpatrick, Walker|2014|page=3}}&lt;/ref&gt; The general belief at the time was that the purpose of the meeting was for the Ansar to decide on a new leader of the [[Ummah|Muslim community]] among themselves, with the intentional exclusion of the [[Muhajirun]] (migrants from [[Mecca]]), though this has later become the subject of debate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Wilferd |last=Madelung |title=The Succession to Muhammad |year=1997|page=[https://archive.org/details/TheSuccessionToMuhammadByWilferdMadelung/page/n50 31]|url= https://archive.org/details/TheSuccessionToMuhammadByWilferdMadelung }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Nevertheless, Abu Bakr and [[Umar]], upon learning of the meeting, became concerned of a potential coup and hastened to the gathering. Upon arriving, Abu Bakr addressed the assembled men with a warning that an attempt to elect a leader outside of Muhammad's own tribe, the [[Quraysh]], would likely result in dissension, as only they can command the necessary respect among the community. He then took Umar and another companion, [[Abu Ubaidah ibn al-Jarrah]], by the hand and offered them to the Ansar as potential choices. [[Habab ibn Mundhir]], a veteran from the [[Battle of Badr]], countered with his own suggestion that the Quraysh and the Ansar choose a leader each from among themselves, who would then rule jointly. The group grew heated upon hearing this proposal and began to argue amongst themselves.&lt;ref name=MadelungP30-31&gt;{{harvtxt|Madelung|1997|page=30–31}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[oriental studies|orientalist]] [[William Muir]] gives the following observation of the situation:&lt;ref&gt;William Muir, ''The Caliphate: Its Rise, Decline, and Fall'' (1891), p. 2&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|The moment was critical. The unity of the Faith was at stake. A divided power would fall to pieces, and all might be lost. The mantle of the Prophet must fall upon one Successor, and on one alone. The sovereignty of Islam demanded an undivided Caliphate; and Arabia would acknowledge no master but from amongst Koreish.}}

Umar hastily took Abu Bakr's hand and swore his own allegiance to the latter, an example followed by the gathered men. The meeting broke up when a violent scuffle erupted between Umar and the chief of the Banu Sa'ida, [[Sa'd ibn Ubadah]]. This may indicate that the choice of Abu Bakr may not have been unanimous, with emotions running high as a result of the disagreement.&lt;ref name=MandelungP32&gt;{{harvtxt|Madelung|1997|page=32}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Abu Bakr was near-universally accepted as head of the Muslim community (under the title of [[Caliphate|Caliph]]) as a result of Saqifah, though he did face contention because of the rushed nature of the event. Several companions, most prominent among them being [[Ali ibn Abi Talib]], initially refused to acknowledge his authority.&lt;ref name=FitzpatrickWalkerP3/&gt; Among Shi'ites, it is also argued that Ali had [[Event of Ghadir Khumm|previously been appointed]] as Muhammad's heir, with the election being seen as in contravention to the latter's wishes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first1=Bernhard |last1=Platzdasch|first2=Johan |last2= Saravanamuttu|title=Religious Diversity in Muslim-majority States in Southeast Asia: Areas of Toleration and Conflict|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7ThpBgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA364|date=6 August 2014|publisher=Institute of Southeast Asian Studies|isbn=978-981-4519-64-9|page=364}}&lt;/ref&gt; Abu Bakr later sent Umar to confront Ali, resulting in [[Umar at Fatimah's house|an altercation]] which may have involved violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvtxt|Fitzpatrick, Walker|2014|page=186}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, after six months the group made peace with Abu Bakr and Ali offered him his allegiance.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvtxt|Fitzpatrick, Walker|2014|page=4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reign==
After assuming the office of [[Caliph]], Abu Bakr's first address was as follows:

{{quote|I have been given the authority over you, and I am not the best of you. If I do well, help me; and if I do wrong, set me right. Sincere regard for truth is loyalty and disregard for truth is treachery. The weak amongst you shall be strong with me until I have secured his rights, if God wills; and the strong amongst you shall be weak with me until I have wrested from him the rights of others, if God wills. Obey me so long as I obey God and His Messenger. But if I disobey God and His Messenger, you owe me no obedience. Arise for your prayer, God have mercy upon you. (Al-Bidaayah wan-Nihaayah 6:305, 306)}}

Abu Bakr's reign lasted for 27 months, during which he crushed the rebellion of the Arab tribes throughout the [[Arabian Peninsula]] in the successful [[Ridda Wars]]. In the last months of his rule, he sent Khalid ibn al-Walid on conquests [[Muslim conquest of Persia|against the Sassanid Empire]] in [[Mesopotamia]] and [[Muslim conquest of the Levant|against the Byzantine Empire]] in Syria. This would set in motion a historical trajectory&lt;ref name=&quot;Donner&quot;&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=qBzRj7OajmEC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Fred M. Donner, ''Muhammad and the Believers: At the Origins of Islam'', Harvard University Press, 2010] {{ISBN|978-0-674-05097-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; (continued later on by [[Umar]] and [[Uthman ibn Affan]]) that in just a few short decades would lead to one of the [[List of largest empires|largest empires in history]]. He had little time to pay attention to the administration of state, though state affairs remained stable during his Caliphate. On the advice of Umar and Abu Ubaidah ibn al-Jarrah, he agreed to draw a salary from the state treasury and discontinue his cloth trade.

===Ridda wars===
[[File:Caliph Abu Bakr's empire at its peak 634-mohammad adil rais.PNG|thumb|300px|Caliph Abu Bakr's empire at its peak in August 634.]]
{{main|Ridda wars}}
Troubles emerged soon after Abu Bakr's succession, with several Arab tribes launching revolts, threatening the unity and stability of the new community and state. These insurgencies and the caliphate's responses to them are collectively referred to  as the [[Ridda wars]] (&quot;Wars of Apostasy&quot;).&lt;ref name=DonnerP85&gt;{{cite book |last=Donner |first=Fred M. |authorlink=Fred Donner |title=The Early Islamic Conquests |publisher=Princeton University Press |year=1981 |page=85 |url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=l5__AwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA85 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The opposition movements came in two forms. One type challenged the political power of the nascent caliphate as well as the religious authority of Islam with the acclamation of rival ideologies, headed by political leaders who claimed the mantle of prophethood in the manner that Muhammad had done. These rebellions include:&lt;ref name=DonnerP85/&gt;
*that of the [[Banu Asad ibn Khuzaymah]] headed by [[Tulayha ibn Khuwaylid ibn Nawfal al-Asadi|Tulayha ibn Khuwaylid]]
*that of the [[Banu Hanifa]] headed by [[Musaylimah]]
*those from among the [[Banu Taghlib]] and the [[Bani Tamim]] headed by [[Sajah]]
*that of the [[Al-Ansi]] headed by [[Al-Aswad Al-Ansi]]
These leaders are all denounced in Islamic histories as &quot;false prophets&quot;.&lt;ref name=DonnerP85/&gt;

The second form of opposition movement was more strictly political in character. Some of the revolts of this type took the form of tax rebellions in [[Najd]] among tribes such as the [[Banu Fazara]] and [[Banu Tamim]]. Other dissenters, while initially allied to the Muslims, used Muhammad's death as an opportunity to attempt to restrict the growth of the new Islamic state. They include some of the [[Rabīʿa]] in [[Bahrayn]], the [[Azd]] in [[Oman proper|Oman]], as well as among the [[Kindah]] and Khawlan in [[Greater Yemen|Yemen]].&lt;ref name=DonnerP85/&gt;

Abu Bakr, likely understanding that maintaining firm control over the disparate tribes of Arabia was crucial to ensuring the survival of the state, suppressed the insurrections with military force. He dispatched [[Khalid ibn Walid]] and a body of troops to subdue the uprisings in Najd as well as that of Musaylimah, who posed the most serious threat. Concurrent to this, [[Shurahbil ibn Hasana]] and [[Al-Ala'a Al-Hadrami]] were sent to Bahrayn, while [[Ikrimah ibn Abi Jahl]], [[Hudhayfah al-Bariqi]] and [[Arfaja al-Bariqi]] were instructed to conquer Oman. Finally, [[Al-Muhajir ibn Abi Umayya]] and [[Khalid ibn Asid]] were sent to Yemen to aid the local governor in re-establishing control. Abu Bakr also made use of diplomatic means in addition to military measures. Like Muhammad before him, he utilised marriage alliances and financial incentives to bind former enemies to the caliphate. For instance, a member of the Banu Hanifa who had sided with the Muslims was rewarded with the granting of a land estate. Similarly, a Kindah rebel named [[Al-Ash'ath ibn Qays]], after repenting and re-joining Islam, was later given land in Medina as well as the hand of Abu Bakr's sister Umm Farwa in marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvtxt|Donner|1981|pages=86–87}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At their heart, the Ridda movements were challenges to the political and religious supremacy of the Islamic state. Through his success in suppressing the insurrections, Abu Bakr had in effect continued the political consolidation which had begun under Muhammad's leadership with relatively little interruption. By wars' end, he had established an Islamic hegemony over the entirety of the [[Arabian peninsula]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvtxt|Donner|1981|page=86}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Expeditions into Persia and Syria===
With Arabia having united under a single centralised state with a formidable military, the region could now be viewed as a potential threat to the neighbouring [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine]] and [[Sasanian empire]]s. It may be that Abu Bakr, reasoning that it was inevitable that one of these powers would launch a pre-emptive strike against the youthful caliphate, decided that it was better to deliver the first blow himself. Regardless of the caliph's motivations, in 633, small forces were dispatched into [[Iraq]] and [[Palestine (region)|Palestine]], capturing several towns. Though the Byzantines and Sassanians were certain to retaliate, Abu Bakr had reason to be confident. The two empires were militarily exhausted after centuries of war against each other, making it likely that any forces sent to Arabia would be diminished and weakened.&lt;ref name=NardoP32&gt;{{cite book |last=Nardo |first=Don |authorlink=Don Nardo |title=The Islamic Empire |publisher=Lucent Books |year=2011 |pages=[https://archive.org/details/islamicempire0000nard/page/30 30], 32 |url=https://archive.org/details/islamicempire0000nard |url-access=registration |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;
  
A more pressing advantage though was the effectiveness of the Muslim fighters as well as their zeal, the latter of which was partially based on their certainty of the righteousness of their cause. Additionally, the general belief among the Muslims was that the community must be defended at all costs. Historian [[Theodor Nöldeke]] gives the somewhat controversial opinion that this religious fervour was intentionally used to maintain the enthusiasm and momentum of the ''[[ummah]]'':&lt;ref name=NardoP32/&gt;

{{Quote|It was certainly good policy to turn the recently subdued tribes of the wilderness towards an external aim in which they might at once satisfy their lust for booty on a grand scale, maintain their warlike feeling, and strengthen themselves in their attachment to the new faith… Muhammad himself had already sent expeditions across the [Byzantine] frontier, and thereby had pointed out the way to his successors. To follow in his footsteps was in accordance with the innermost being of the youthful Islam, already grown great amid the tumult of arms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Nöldeke |first=Theodore |authorlink=Theodor Nöldeke |title=Sketches from Eastern History |url=https://archive.org/details/in.gov.ignca.21089 |year=1892 |page=[https://archive.org/details/in.gov.ignca.21089/page/n85 73] |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Though Abu Bakr had started these initial conflicts which eventually resulted in the Islamic [[Muslim conquest of Persia|conquests of Persia]] and [[Muslim conquest of the Levant|the Levant]], he did not live to see any real fighting, instead leaving the task to his successors.&lt;ref name=NardoP32/&gt;

===Preservation of the Quran===
{{Main|History of the Quran}}
Abu Bakr was instrumental in preserving the [[Quran]] in written form. It is said that after the hard-won victory over Musaylimah in the [[Battle of Yamama]] in 632, [[Umar]] saw that some five hundred of the Muslims who had [[Hafiz (Quran)|memorised the Quran]] had been killed. Fearing that it may become lost or corrupted, Umar requested that Abu Bakr authorise the compilation and preservation of the scriptures in written format. The caliph was initially hesitant, being quoted as saying  &quot;how can we do that which the Messenger of Allah, may Allah bless and keep him, did not himself do?&quot; He eventually relented however, and appointed [[Zayd ibn Thabit]], who had previously served as Muhammad's secretary, for the task of gathering the scattered verses. The fragments were recovered from every quarter, including from the ribs of palm branches, scraps of leather, stone tablets and &quot;from the hearts of men&quot;. The collected work was transcribed onto sheets and verified through comparison with Quran memorisers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Fernhout |first1=Rein |last2=Jansen |first2=Henry |last3=Jansen-Hofland |first3=Lucy |title=Canonical Texts. Bearers of Absolute Authority. Bible, Koran, Veda, Tipitaka: a Phenomenological Study |year=1994 |page=62 |url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=BIIk_73ImdsC&amp;pg=PA62 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Herlihy |first=John |title=Islam for Our Time: Inside the Traditional World of Islamic Spirituality |year=2012 |page=76 |url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=lcb5AAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA76 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; The finished codex, termed the ''[[Mus'haf]]'', was presented to Abu Bakr, who prior to his death, bequeathed it to his successor Umar.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Azmayesh |first=Seyed Mostafa |authorlink= Seyed Mostafa Azmayesh |title=New Researches on the Quran: Why and how two versions of Islam entered the history of mankind |year=2015 |publisher=Mehraby Publishing House |page=75 |url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=ED1lCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA75 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Upon Umar's own death, the ''Mus'haf'' was left to his daughter [[Hafsa bint Umar|Hafsa]], who had been one of the wives of Muhammad. It was this volume, borrowed from Hafsa, which formed the basis of [[Uthman]]'s legendary prototype, which became the definitive text of the Quran. All later editions are derived from this original.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvtxt|Herlihy|2012|page=76–77}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|Many early sources, especially but not exclusively [[Shia|Shi'ite]], believe that there was also a version of the Quran which had been compiled by Ali, but which has since been lost.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvtxt|Herlihy|2012|page=77}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Death==

[[File:Abu Bakr dying.jpg|thumb|Abu Bakr dying beside [[Ali]]]]

On 23 August 634, Abu Bakr fell sick and did not recover. He developed a high fever and was confined to bed. His illness was prolonged, and when his condition worsened, he felt that his end was near. Realising this, he sent for [[Ali]] and requested him to perform his [[ghusl]] since Ali had also done it for Muhammad.

Abu Bakr felt that he should nominate his successor so that the issue should not be a cause of dissension among the Muslims after his death, though there was already controversy over Ali not having been appointed.&lt;ref&gt;''Sidiq-i-Akbar Hazrat Abu Bakr'' by Masudul Hasan. Lahore: Ferozsons, 1976. {{OCLC|3478821}}&lt;/ref&gt; He appointed Umar for this role after discussing the matter with some companions. Some of them favoured the nomination and others disliked it, due to the tough nature of Umar.

Abu Bakr thus dictated his last testament to [[Uthman ibn Affan]] as follows:

{{Quote|In the name of Most Merciful God. This is the last will and testament of Abu Bakr bin Abu Quhafa, when he is in the last hour of the world, and the first of the next; an hour in which the infidel must believe, the wicked be convinced of their evil ways, I nominate Umar bin al Khattab as my successor. Therefore, hear to him and obey him. If he acts right, confirm his actions. My intentions are good, but I cannot see the future results. However, those who do ill shall render themselves liable to severe account hereafter. Fare you well. May you be ever attended by the Divine favor of blessing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.alim.org/library/biography/khalifa/content/KAB/18/2 |title=Khalifa Abu Bakr - Death of Abu Bakr - Alim.org }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Appearance==
The historian [[Al-Tabari]], in regards to Abu Bakr's appearance, records the following interaction between Aisha and her paternal nephew, Abdullah ibn Abdul-Rahman ibn Abi Bakr:&lt;ref name=TabariBlankinshipP138-39&gt;{{cite book |last1=Al-Tabari |first1=Muhammad ibn Jarir |last2=Blankinship |first2=Khalid Yahya |authorlink1=Al-Tabari |authorlink2=Khalid Yahya Blankinship |title=The History of al-Tabari, Volume XI: The Challenge to the Empires
|year=1993 |pages=138–39 |url=https://archive.org/stream/TabariEnglish/Tabari_Volume_11#page/n175/mode/2up |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
When she was in her [[howdah]] and saw a man from among the Arabs passing by, she said, &quot;I have not seen a man more like Abu Bakr than this one.&quot; We said to her, &quot;Describe Abu Bakr.&quot; She said, &quot;A slight, white man, thin-bearded and bowed. His waist wrapper would not hold but would fall down around his loins. He had a lean face, sunken eyes, a bulging forehead, and trembling knuckles.&quot;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Referencing another source, Al-Tabari further describes him as being &quot;white mixed with yellowness, of good build, slight, 
bowed, thin, tall like a male palm tree, hook-nosed, lean-faced, sunken-eyed, thin-shanked, and strong-thighed. He used to dye himself with [[henna]] and black dye.&quot;&lt;ref name=TabariBlankinshipP138-39/&gt;

==Legacy==
Though the period of his caliphate covers only two years, two months and fifteen days, it included successful invasions of the two most powerful empires of the time: the [[Sassanid Empire]] and [[Byzantine Empire]].

Abu Bakr had the distinction of being the first Caliph in the history of Islam and also the first Caliph to nominate a successor. He was the only Caliph in the history of Islam who refunded to the state treasury at the time of his death the entire amount of the allowance that he had drawn during the period of his caliphate.&lt;ref name=&quot;archive.org&quot;/&gt;

He has the distinction of purchasing the land for [[Al-Masjid al-Nabawi]].{{citation needed|date=March 2019}}

===Sunni view===
[[Sunni Islam|Sunni]] Muslims believe that Abu Bakr is the best man of all the human beings after the prophets. They also consider Abu Bakr as one of [[Hadith of the ten promised paradise|The Ten Promised Paradise]] (''al-‘Ashara al-Mubashshara'') whom Muhammad had testified were destined for Paradise. He is regarded as the &quot;Successor of Allah's Messenger&quot; (''Khalifa Rasulullah''), and first of the Rightly Guided Caliphs – i.e. [[Rashidun]]—and as the rightful successor to Muhammad. Abu Bakr had always been the closest friend and confidant of Muhammad throughout his life, being beside Muhammad at every major event. It was Abu Bakr's wisdom that Muhammad always honored. Abu Bakr is regarded among the best of Muhammad's followers; as Umar ibn Khattab stated, &quot;If the faith of Abu Bakr was weighed against the faith of the people of the earth, the faith of Abu Bakr would outweigh the others.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Narrated by al-Bayhaqi in ‘al-Jamia’ lashu’ab al-Eemaan’ (1:18) and its narrators are trustworthy.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Shia view===
{{See also|Umar at Fatimah's house|Succession to Muhammad}}

The [[Twelver]] [[Shia]] (as the main branch of Shia Islam, with 85% of all Shias)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.worldatlas.com/articles/shia-islam-s-holiest-sites.html |title=Shia Islam's Holiest Sites }}&lt;/ref&gt; believe that Ali ibn Abi Talib was supposed to assume the [[Caliphate]], and that he had been publicly and unambiguously appointed by Muhammad as his successor at [[Hadith of the pond of Khumm|Ghadir Khumm]]. It is also believed that Abu Bakr and Umar conspired to take over power in the Muslim nation after Muhammad's death, in a coup d'état against Ali. The Twelver Shi'a do not believe that Abu Bakr's being with Muhammad in the cave when the two fled Mecca was a meritorious act, and, indeed, find significant criticism of Abu Bakr in the Qur'anic verse of the cave.

Most Twelver Shia&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.al-islam.org/shiite-encyclopedia-ahlul-bayt-dilp-team/usurping-land-fadak |title=Usurping the Land of Fadak |website=Al-Islam.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.al-islam.org/the-message-ayatullah-jafar-subhani/chapter-44-story-fadak |title=Chapter 44: The Story of Fadak |website=Al-Islam.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.twelvershia.net/2014/05/08/fadak-prophetic-inheritance-qa/ |title=Fadak and Inheritance Q&amp;A |last=twelvershia.net |date=8 May 2014 |website=TwelverShia.net}}&lt;/ref&gt; criticize Abu Bakr because, after Muhammad's death, Abu Bakr refused to grant Muhammad's daughter, [[Fatimah]], the lands of the village of [[Fadak]] which she claimed her father had given to her as a gift before his death. He refused to accept the testimony of her witnesses, so she claimed the land would still belong to her as inheritance from her deceased father. However, Abu Bakr replied by saying that Muhammad had told him that the prophets of God do not leave as inheritance any worldly possessions and on this basis he refused to give her the lands of Fadak.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.al-islam.org/fatima-the-gracious-abu-muhammad-ordoni/abu-bakr-versus-fatima-az-zahra-sa al-islam.org], ''Fatima the Gracious'', by Abu – Muhammad Ordoni, 1987.  Section entitled ''Abu Bakr Versus Fatima az-Zahra (sa)''.&lt;br&gt;See also ''Sahih Al Bukhari'' Volume 5, Book 57, Number 60, which says: &quot;Fatima sent somebody to Abu Bakr asking him to give her her inheritance from the Prophet from what Allah had given to His Apostle through Fai (i.e. booty gained without fighting). She asked for the Sadaqa (i.e. wealth assigned for charitable purposes) of the Prophet at Medina, and Fadak, and what remained of the Khumus (i.e., one-fifth) of the Khaibar booty.&quot; Abu Bakr said, &quot;Allah's Apostle said, 'We (Prophets), our property is not inherited, and whatever we leave is Sadaqa, but Muhammad's Family can eat from this property, i.e. Allah's property, but they have no right to take more than the food they need.' By Allah! I will not bring any change in dealing with the Sadaqa of the Prophet (and will keep them) as they used to be observed in his (i.e. the Prophet's) life-time, and I will dispose with it as Allah's Apostle used to do,&quot; Then 'Ali said, &quot;I testify that None has the right to be worshipped but Allah, and that Muhammad is His Apostle,&quot; and added, &quot;O Abu Bakr! We acknowledge your superiority.&quot; Then he (i.e. 'Ali) mentioned their own relationship to Allah's Apostle and their right. Abu Bakr then spoke saying, &quot;By Allah in Whose Hands my life is. I love to do good to the relatives of Allah's Apostle rather than to my own relatives&quot; Abu Bakr added: Look at Muhammad through his family.&quot;
&lt;br&gt;See also ''Sahih Al Bukhari'' Volume 8, Book 80, Number 722, which says:  &quot;Aisha said, 'When Allah's Apostle died, his wives intended to send 'Uthman to Abu Bakr asking him for their share of the inheritance.' Then &quot;Aisha said to them, 'Didn't Allah's Apostle say, Our (Apostles') property is not to be inherited, and whatever we leave is to be spent in charity?'&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; However, as Sayed Ali Asgher Razwy notes in his book ''A Restatement of the History of Islam &amp; Muslims'', Muhammad inherited a maid servant, five camels, and ten sheep. This proves that prophets can receive inheritance, and can pass on inheritance to others as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Razwy |first1=Ali Asgher |title=A Restatement of the History of Islam &amp; Muslims |pages=34–35}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, Shias claim that Muhammad had given Fadak to Fatimah during his lifetime,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Jalālī |first1=Ḥusaynī |title=Fadak wa l-ʿawālī |page=141}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Fadak was therefore a gift to Fatimah, not inheritance. This view has also been supported some Sunnis, such as the Abbasid ruler [[Al-Ma'mun]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Shahīdī |title=Zindigānī-yi Fātima-yi Zahrā |page=117}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Twelver Shia accuse him of participating in [[Umar at Fatimah's house|the burning of the house of Ali and Fatima]].&lt;ref&gt;Ibn Qutayba al Dinawari. Al Imama Wa'l Siyasa.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Twelver Shia believe that Abu Bakr sent [[Khalid ibn Walid]] to crush those who were in favour of [[Ali]]'s caliphate (''see [[Ridda Wars]]''). The Twelver Shia strongly refute the idea that Abu Bakr or Umar were instrumental in the collection or preservation of the ''Qur'an'', claiming that they should have accepted the copy of the book in the possession of Ali.&lt;ref&gt;[http://al-islam.org/encyclopedia/chapter8/4.html al-islam.org], ''The Quran Compiled by Imam Ali (AS)''&lt;/ref&gt;

After the death of Abu Bakr, Ali raised [[Muhammad ibn Abi Bakr]]. The Twelver Shia view Muhammad ibn Abi Bakr as one of the companions of Ali.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;Nahj al-Balagha Sermon 71, Letter 27, Letter 34, Letter 35&lt;/ref&gt; When Muhammad ibn Abi Bakr was killed by the [[Ummayads]],&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt; Aisha, the wife of Muhammad and also a renowned scholar of her time, raised and taught her nephew [[Qasim ibn Muhammad ibn Abu Bakr]]. Qasim ibn Muhammad ibn Abu Bakr's mother was from Ali's family and Qasim's daughter [[Farwah bint al-Qasim]] was married to [[Muhammad al-Baqir]] and was the mother of [[Jafar al-Sadiq]]. Therefore, Qasim ibn Muhammad ibn Abu Bakr was the grandson of Abu Bakr and the grandfather of Jafar al-Sadiq. [[Zaidiyyah|Zaydis]], the largest group amongst the Shia before the [[Safavid Dynasty]] and currently the second-largest group (although its population is only about 5% of all Shia Muslims),&lt;ref&gt;[https://2009-2017.state.gov/documents/organization/208632.pdf www.state.gov]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stephen W. Day (2012). Regionalism and Rebellion in Yemen: A Troubled National Union. Cambridge University Press. p. 31. {{ISBN|9781107022157}}.
Jump up&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Mapping the Global Muslim Population: A Report on the Size and Distribution of the World's Muslim Population&quot;. Pew Research Center. 7 October 2009. Retrieved 25 August 2010.
^ Jump up to: a b c d e f g&lt;/ref&gt; believe that on the last hour of [[Zayd ibn Ali]] (the uncle of Jafar al-Sadiq), he was betrayed by the people in Kufa who said to him: &quot;May God have mercy on you! What do you have to say on the matter of Abu Bakr and Umar ibn al-Khattab?&quot; Zayd ibn Ali said, &quot;I have not heard anyone in my family renouncing them both nor saying anything but good about them...when they were entrusted with government they behaved justly with the people and acted according to the Qur'an and the Sunnah&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Najeebabadi&quot;&gt;Akbar Shah Najeebabadi, The history of Islam. B0006RTNB4.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The waning of the Umayyad caliphate by Tabarī, Carole Hillenbrand, 1989, p37, p38&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Encyclopedia of Religion Vol.16, Mircea Eliade, Charles J. Adams, Macmillan, 1987, p243. &quot;They were called Rafida by the followers of Zayd&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Wikipedia books
 |1=Sahabah
}}
{{Portal|Islam}}
* [[Bodla]]
* [[Laqit bin Malik Al-Azdi]], opponent
* [[List of Sahaba]]
* [[Sunni view of the Sahaba]]
* [[Muadh ibn Jabal]]
* [[Sermon of Fadak]]

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
{{refbegin|33em}}
* Walker, Adam, Abu Bakr al-Siddiq, in ''Muhammad in History, Thought, and Culture: An Encyclopedia of the Prophet of God'' (2 vols.), Edited by C. Fitzpatrick and A. Walker, Santa Barbara, ABC-CLIO, 2014.
* {{citation |author=[[Barnaby Rogerson]] |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ExbdVf5fFmUC&amp;dq |volume=|pages=|first=|title=The Heirs of the Prophet Muhammad: And the Roots of the Sunni-Shia Schism |date=4 November 2010 |publisher=Little, Brown Book Group |isbn=978-0-74-812470-1 |ref={{sfnref|Barnaby Rogerson|2010}}}}
* {{citation |author=Barnaby Rogerson |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qzyBPwAACAAJ&amp;dq |volume=|first=|title=The Heirs of Muhammad: Islam's First Century and the Origins of the Sunni-Shia Split |pages=|year=2008 |publisher=Overlook |isbn=978-1-59-020022-3 |ref={{sfnref|Barnaby Rogerson|2008}}}}
* {{citation |author=Wilferd Madelung |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2QKBUwBUWWkC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq |volume=|pages=|first=|title=The Succession to Muhammad: A Study of the Early Caliphate |date=15 October 1998 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=978-0-52-164696-3 |ref={{sfnref|Wilferd Madelung|1998}}}}
{{refend}}{{Citation|last=Huthayfa|first=Abu|title=Abu Bakr: The First Caliph|url=https://books.google.com.bd/books?id=xZ4bnQEACAAJ&amp;dq=abu+bakr&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiN8eqeiNnmAhWhyDgGHbARBn0Q6AEIQjAE|volume=|pages=|publication-date=2013|isbn=9780958172035}}

==External links==
{{Wikisource author}}
{{Wikiquote}}
{{EB1911 poster|Abu-Bekr}}
* Muslim:
**[http://quilliampress.com/the-khilafa-of-abu-bakr/ QuilliamPress.com: Abu Bakr]
** [http://www.abubakr.com/ AbuBakr.com]
** [http://twelvershia.net/2015/01/27/book-virtues-hazrat-abu-bakr/ Virtues of Hazrat Abu Bakr]
** [http://www.sunnah.org/publication/khulafa_rashideen/caliph1.htm Detailed Life of Abu Bakr as-Siddiq]
** [https://web.archive.org/web/20060422024023/http://anwary-islam.com/companion/abu_bakr_siddiq.htm Abu Bakr's life]
** [https://web.archive.org/web/20070629171307/http://www.naqshbandi.org/chain/2.htm Naqshbandi-Haqqani Sufi Order biography of Abu Bakr as-Siddiq]
** [https://web.archive.org/web/20070928145511/http://www.quransunnah.com/modules.php?name=Lectures&amp;d_op=savelink2&amp;lid=812 Greatness of Abu Bakr]
** Biography of Abu Bakr as-Siddiq by Adam Walker [https://web.archive.org/web/20160304055853/http://www.alislam.org/topics/khilafat/Hadhrat-Abu-Bakr-20080304MN.pdf]
Urdu Audio
** [https://web.archive.org/web/20060318152950/http://www.quransunnah.com/modules.php?name=Lectures&amp;d_op=savelink2&amp;lid=112 Virtues of Abu Bakr] Urdu Audio
** [http://www.searchtruth.com/searchHadith.php?keyword=abu+bakr&amp;translator=2&amp;search=1&amp;book=&amp;start=0&amp;records_display=100&amp;search_word=exact Abu Bakr appearing in Narrations/Hadith recorded by Imam Bukhari] – www.SearchTruth.com
** [https://www.scribd.com/doc/15804089/Did-Umar-Burn-Fatimas-House Abu bakr's appointment as Khalifah]
** [https://archive.today/20130420124152/http://www.happy-books.co.uk/muhammad-ibn-abdullah-lineage-and-family-tree/family-tree-diagram-of-lineage-and-relatives-of-prophets-and-companions-in-muslim-history.php?id=245 Searchable Family tree of Abu Bakr as-Siddeeq] by Happy Books
* Non-Muslim:
** [https://web.archive.org/web/20060815014003/http://www.ucalgary.ca/applied_history/tutor/islam/caliphate/abuBakr.html Abu Bakr]
* Unclassified:
** [https://web.archive.org/web/20050217023944/http://www.ymofmd.com/books/abas/chapter2.htm Abu Bakr]
** [https://web.archive.org/web/20060219221438/http://www.islamonline.net/English/NewHijriYear/HijrahHeroes/1426/04.shtml Abu Bakr from Islamonline]
** [https://web.archive.org/web/20070930163549/http://www.lailahailallah.net/Khutbahs/Khutbah17.asf Sirah of Abu Bakr (Radia'Allahuanhu) Part 1] by [[Muhammad bin Yahya al-Ninowy|Shaykh Sayyed Muhammad bin Yahya Al-Husayni Al-Ninowy]].
* Shia:
**[http://www.seratonline.com/23486/is-there-any-virtue-for-abu-bakr-in-the-incident-of-the-cave/ Incident of the cave]
**[http://www.abubakr.org/ Abu Bakr]

{{S-start}}
{{S-hou|[[Banu Taim]]||October 573||22 August 634|[[Quraysh (tribe)|Quraysh]]}}
{{S-rel|su}}
{{S-new|creation}}
{{S-ttl|title=First [[Caliphate|Caliph of Islam]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Rashidun Caliph]]|years=8 June 632{{snd}}22 August 634}}
{{S-aft|after=[[Umar ibn Al-Khattab]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{Rashidun Caliphs}}
{{Ten companions of Muhammad}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:573 births]]
[[Category:634 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Mecca]]
[[Category:Abu Bakr| ]]
[[Category:Rashidun caliphs]]
[[Category:Abu Bakr family| ]]
[[Category:Converts to Islam]]
[[Category:7th-century caliphs]]
[[Category:Sahabah participated in battle of Uhud]]
[[Category:Sahabah participated in battle of Badr]]
[[Category:Male Sahabah]]
[[Category:People of the Muslim conquest of the Levant]]</text>
      <sha1>3njta511130b9a1fe0cycpnui10kd7g</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
