  <page>
    <title>Alcuin</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1408</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940680337</id>
      <parentid>940680016</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-14T00:04:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AManWithNoPlan</username>
        <id>12416903</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>fix template</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|English scholar and abbot}}
{{About|the scholar Alcuin of York|the [[Colleges of the University of York|college of the University of York]], which bears his name|Alcuin College}}
{{Redirect|Alcuinus|the sixteenth century French theologian who used it as a pseudonym|John Calvin}}
{{EngvarB|date=September 2013}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2013}}
{{Infobox academic
| name               = Alcuin of York
| image              = Raban-Maur Alcuin Otgar.jpg
| occupation         = [[Deacon]] of the [[Catholic Church]]
|birth_place=[[York]], [[Northumbria]]
|death_place=[[Tours]], [[France]]
| notable_works      = ''[[Propositiones ad Acuendos Juvenes]]'', [[Carolingian minuscule]]
|caption=A Carolingian manuscript, c. 831. [[Rabanus Maurus]] (left), with Alcuin (middle), dedicating his work to Archbishop [[Odgar]] of Mainz (right)
| era                = [[Medieval philosophy]]&lt;br&gt;[[Carolingian Renaissance]]
| main_interests     = [[Mathematic]]&lt;br&gt;[[Philosophy]]&lt;br&gt;[[Christian theology]]&lt;br&gt;[[Poetry]]
|birth_date={{circa|735}}
|death_date=19 May 804
}}
'''Alcuin of York''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|æ|l|k|w|ɪ|n}};&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.lexico.com/definition/alcuin|title=Alcuin &amp;#124; Meaning of Alcuin by Lexico|website=Lexico Dictionaries &amp;#124; English}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{lang-la|Flaccus Albinus Alcuinus}}; {{circa}} 735 – 19 May 804 AD)&amp;nbsp;– also called '''Ealhwine''', '''Alhwin''' or '''Alchoin'''&amp;nbsp;– was an English scholar, clergyman, poet and teacher from [[York]], [[Northumbria]]. He was born around 735 and became the student of [[Ecgbert (Archbishop of York)|Archbishop Ecgbert]] at York. At the invitation of [[Charlemagne]], he became a leading scholar and teacher at the [[Carolingian dynasty|Carolingian court]], where he remained a figure in the 780s and '90s. During this period he invented [[Carolingian minuscule]], an easily read manuscript hand using a mixture of upper and lower case letters.&lt;ref name=Marcia&gt;{{cite book|last1=Colish|first1=Marcia L.|title=Medieval Foundations of the Western Intellectual Tradition, 400–1400|series=The Yale Intellectual History of the West|publisher=[[Yale University Press]]|year=1999|volume=|page=67|isbn = 9780300078527 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Alcuin wrote many theological and dogmatic treatises, as well as a few grammatical works and a number of poems. He was made Abbot of [[Tours]] in 796, where he remained until his death. &quot;The most learned man anywhere to be found&quot;, according to [[Einhard]]'s ''[[Vita Karoli Magni|Life of Charlemagne]]''&lt;ref&gt;Einhard, ''Life of Charlemagne'', §25.&lt;/ref&gt; (''ca.'' 817-833), he is considered among the most important architects of the [[Carolingian Renaissance]]. Among his pupils were many of the dominant intellectuals of the Carolingian era.

==Biography==
===Background===
[[File:AT 13763 Roof figures at the Kunsthistorisches Museum, Vienna-8.jpg|thumb|upright|Alcuin, roof figure, Museum of History of Arts, Vienna.]]
Alcuin was born in [[Northumbria]], presumably sometime in the 730s. Virtually nothing is known of his parents, family background, or origin.{{sfn|Bullough |2004|p= 164}} In common hagiographical fashion, the ''Vita Alcuini'' asserts that Alcuin was 'of noble English stock,' and this statement has usually been accepted by scholars. Alcuin's own work only mentions such collateral kinsmen as Wilgils, father of the missionary saint [[Willibrord]]; and [[Beornrad (archbishop of Sens)|Beornrad]] (also spelled Beornred), abbot of Echternach and bishop of Sens.{{sfn|Bullough |2004|pp= 146–47, 165}} Willibrord, Alcuin and Beornrad were all related by blood.{{sfn|Mayr-Harting|2016|page=212}}{{sfn|Stenton|2001|page=219}}

In his ''Life'' of St Willibrord, Alcuin writes that Wilgils, called a ''paterfamilias'', had founded an oratory and church at the mouth of the [[Humber]], which had fallen into Alcuin's possession by inheritance. Because in early Anglo-Latin writing ''paterfamilias'' (&quot;head of a family, householder&quot;) usually referred to a [[churl|ceorl]], [[Donald A. Bullough]] suggests that Alcuin's family was of [[churl|cierlisc]] status: ''i.e.,'' free but subordinate to a noble lord, and that Alcuin and other members of his family rose to prominence through beneficial connections with the aristocracy.{{sfn|Bullough |2004|pp= 146–47, 165}} If so, Alcuin's origins may lie in the southern part of what was formerly known as [[Deira]].{{sfn|Bullough |2004|p=165}}

===York===
The young Alcuin came to the [[cathedral church]] of [[York]] during the golden age of Archbishop [[Ecgbert, Archbishop of York|Ecgbert]] and his brother, the Northumbrian King [[Eadberht of Northumbria|Eadberht]]. Ecgbert had been a disciple of the [[Bede|Venerable Bede]], who urged him to raise York to an [[archbishopric]]. King Eadberht and Archbishop Ecgbert oversaw the re-energising and re-organisation of the [[History of the Church of England|English church]], with an emphasis on reforming the clergy and on the tradition of learning that Bede had begun. Ecgbert was devoted to Alcuin, who thrived under his tutelage.

The York school was renowned as a centre of learning in the liberal arts, literature, and science, as well as in religious matters.{{sfn|Hutchison|2006}} It was from here that Alcuin drew inspiration for the school he would lead at the [[Franks|Frankish]] court. He revived the school with the [[Trivium (education)|trivium]] and [[quadrivium]] disciplines,{{sfn|Burns|1907}} writing a [[codex]] on the trivium, while his student [[Rabanus Maurus|Hraban]] wrote one on the quadrivium.

Alcuin graduated to become a teacher during the 750s. His ascendancy to the headship of the York school, the ancestor of [[St Peter's School, York|St Peter's School]], began after [[Ethelbert of York|Aelbert]] became Archbishop of York in 767. Around the same time Alcuin became a [[deacon]] in the church. He was never ordained a priest. Though there is no real evidence that he took monastic vows, he lived as if he had.

In 781, King [[Ælfwald I of Northumbria|Elfwald]] sent Alcuin to Rome to petition the Pope for official confirmation of York's status as an archbishopric and to confirm the election of the new archbishop, [[Eanbald I]]. On his way home he met Charlemagne (whom he had met once before), this time in the Italian city of [[Parma]].{{efn|{{harvnb|Mayr-Harting|2016|page=207}} asserts Charlemagne met Alcuin – for the second time – at Parma in 781}}{{efn|{{harvnb|Story|2005|p=137}} reports that Alcuin had previously been sent to Charlemagne by Ethelbert.}}

===Charlemagne===
{{Scholasticism}}
Alcuin's intellectual curiosity allowed him to be reluctantly persuaded to join Charlemagne's court. He joined an illustrious group of scholars that Charlemagne had gathered around him, the mainsprings of the [[Carolingian Renaissance]]: [[Peter of Pisa]], [[Saint Paulinus II|Paulinus of Aquileia]], Rado, and [[Saint Fulrad|Abbot Fulrad]]. Alcuin would later write that &quot;the Lord was calling me to the service of King Charles.&quot;

Alcuin became Master of the [[Charlemagne's Palace in Aachen|Palace]] School of Charlemagne in [[Aachen]] (''Urbs Regale'') in 782.{{sfn|Burns|1907}} It had been founded by the king's ancestors as a place for the education of the royal children (mostly in manners and the ways of the court). However, Charlemagne wanted to include the [[liberal arts]] and, most importantly, the study of religion. From 782 to 790, Alcuin taught Charlemagne himself, his sons [[Pepin the Hunchback|Pepin]] and [[Louis the Pious|Louis]], as well as young men sent to be educated at court, and the young clerics attached to the [[Palatine Chapel in Aachen|palace chapel]]. Bringing with him from York his assistants Pyttel, Sigewulf, and Joseph, Alcuin revolutionised the educational standards of the Palace School, introducing Charlemagne to the liberal arts and creating a personalised atmosphere of scholarship and learning, to the extent that the institution came to be known as the 'school of Master Albinus'.

In this role as adviser, he took issue with the emperor's policy of forcing pagans to be baptised on pain of death, arguing, &quot;Faith is a free act of the will, not a forced act. We must appeal to the conscience, not compel it by violence. You can force people to be baptised, but you cannot force them to believe.&quot; His arguments seem to have prevailed – Charlemagne abolished the death penalty for paganism in 797.{{sfn|Needham|2000|p=52}}

Charlemagne gathered the best men of every land in his court, and became far more than just the king at the centre. It seems that he made many of these men his closest friends and counsellors. They referred to him as 'David', a reference to the Biblical king [[David (biblical king)|David]]. Alcuin soon found himself on intimate terms with Charlemagne and the other men at court, where pupils and masters were known by affectionate and jesting nicknames.{{sfn|Wilmot-Buxton|1922|p=93}} Alcuin himself was known as 'Albinus' or 'Flaccus'. While at [[Aachen]], Alcuin bestowed pet names upon his pupils – derived mainly from [[Virgil]]'s ''[[Eclogues]]''.{{sfn|Jaeger|1999|p=38}} According to the ''Encyclopædia Britannica'', &quot;He loved Charlemagne and enjoyed the king's esteem, but his letters reveal that his fear of him was as great as his love.&lt;ref name=EB/&gt;

===Return to Northumbria and back to Francia===
In 790 Alcuin returned from the court of Charlemagne to England, to which he had remained attached. He dwelt there for some time, but Charlemagne then invited him back to help in the fight against the [[Adoptionism|Adoptionist]] heresy which was at that time making great progress in [[Toledo, Spain|Toledo]], the old capital of the [[Visigoths]] and still a major city for the Christians under [[Al-Andalus|Islamic rule in Spain]]. He is believed to have had contacts with [[Beatus of Liébana]], from the [[Kingdom of Asturias]], who fought against Adoptionism. At the [[Council of Frankfurt]] in 794, Alcuin upheld the orthodox doctrine against the views expressed by [[Felix, Bishop of Urgel|Felix of Urgel]], an [[heresiarch]] according to the Catholic Encyclopaedia.{{sfn|Burns|1907}} Having failed during his stay in Northumbria to influence King [[Æthelred I of Northumbria|Æthelred]] in the conduct of his reign, Alcuin never returned home.

He was back at Charlemagne's court by at least mid-792, writing a series of letters to Æthelred, to Hygbald, Bishop of [[Lindisfarne]], and to [[Æthelhard]], [[Archbishop of Canterbury]] in the succeeding months, dealing with the [[Viking]] attack on Lindisfarne in July 793. These letters and Alcuin's poem on the subject, ''De clade Lindisfarnensis monasterii'', provide the only significant contemporary account of these events. In his description of the Viking attack, he wrote: &quot;''Never before has such terror appeared in Britain. Behold the church of [[St Cuthbert]], splattered with the blood of God's priests, robbed of its ornaments''.&quot;

===Tours and death===
{{Infobox saint
|name=Alcuin of York
|feast_day=20 May
|work =
|venerated_in=[[Anglican Communion]], [[Roman Catholic Church]], as a blessed
|image=Raban-Maur Alcuin Otgar.jpg
|imagesize=
|titles= Deacon, Scholar
|beatified_date=
|beatified_place=
|beatified_by=
|canonized_date=
|canonized_place=
|canonized_by=
|attributes=
|patronage=
|major_shrine=
|suppressed_date=
}}
In 796 Alcuin was in his sixties. He hoped to be free from court duties and upon the death of Abbot Itherius of Saint Martin at Tours, Charlemagne put [[Marmoutier Abbey, Tours|Marmoutier Abbey]] into Alcuin's care, with the understanding that he should be available if the king ever needed his counsel. There he encouraged the work of the monks on the beautiful [[Carolingian minuscule]] script, ancestor of modern Roman typefaces.&lt;ref name=EB&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.britannica.com/biography/Alcuin|title=Alcuin &amp;#124; Anglo-Saxon scholar|website=Encyclopedia Britannica}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Alcuin died on 19 May 804, some ten years before the emperor, and was buried at St. Martin's Church under an epitaph that partly read:
{{quote|Dust, worms, and ashes now&amp;nbsp;...&lt;br /&gt; Alcuin my name, wisdom I always loved,&lt;br /&gt; Pray, reader, for my soul.}}

The majority of details on Alcuin's life come from his letters and poems. There are also autobiographical sections in Alcuin's poem on York and in the ''Vita Alcuini'', a ''[[hagiography|Life]]'' written for him at Ferrières in the 820s, possibly based in part on the memories of Sigwulf, one of Alcuin's pupils.

==Carolingian Renaissance figure and legacy==
===Mathematician===
{{Main|Propositiones ad acuendos juvenes}}
The collection of mathematical and logical word problems entitled ''Propositiones ad acuendos juvenes'' (&quot;Problems to Sharpen Youths&quot;){{sfn|Alcuin|n.d.}} is sometimes attributed to Alcuin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Peterson-2005&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.maa.org/mathland/mathtrek_11_21_05.html|title=Ivars Peterson's MathTrek Nov 21, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Atkinson|2005|pp=354–62}} In a 799 letter to Charlemagne the scholar claimed to have sent &quot;certain figures of arithmetic for the joy of cleverness,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Epistola'' 172, MGH ''Epistolae'' 4.2: 285: &quot;aliquas figuras arithmeticae subtilitatis laetitiae causa&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; which some scholars have identified with the ''Propositiones.''{{sfn|Jullien|Perelman|1994|p=482–83}}
{{efn|A more skeptical attitude toward Alcuin's authorship of this text and others is taken by {{harvnb|Gorman|2002|p=101–30}} }}
The text contains about 53 mathematical word problems (with solutions), in no particular pedagogical order. Among the most famous of these problems are: four that involve [[river crossing problem|river crossings]], including the [[Jealous husbands problem|problem of three anxious brothers]], each of whom has an unmarried sister whom he cannot leave alone with either of the other men lest she be defiled&lt;ref name=&quot;3-brothers&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://logica.ugent.be/albrecht/alcuin.pdf|title=Latin title and English text of the problem}}&lt;/ref&gt; (Problem 17); the [[Fox, goose and bag of beans puzzle|problem of the wolf, goat, and cabbage]] (Problem 18); and the problem of &quot;the two adults and two children where the children weigh half as much as the adults&quot; (Problem 19). [[Alcuin's sequence]] is the solution to one of the problems of that book.

===Literary influence===
Alcuin made the abbey school into a model of excellence and many students flocked to it. He had many manuscripts copied using outstandingly beautiful [[calligraphy]], the [[Carolingian minuscule]] based on round and legible [[uncial]] letters. He wrote many letters to his English friends, to [[Arno of Salzburg|Arno, bishop of Salzburg]] and above all to [[Charlemagne]]. These letters (of which 311 are extant) are filled mainly with pious meditations, but they form an important source of information as to the literary and social conditions of the time and are the most reliable authority for the history of [[humanism]] during the [[Carolingian]] age. Alcuin trained the numerous monks of the abbey in piety, and it was in the midst of these pursuits that he died.

Alcuin is the most prominent figure of the [[Carolingian Renaissance]], in which three main periods have been distinguished: in the first of these, up to the arrival of Alcuin at the court, the Italians occupy a central place; in the second, Alcuin and the [[Anglo-Saxons]] are dominant; in the third (from 804), the influence of [[Theodulf of Orléans|Theodulf, the Visigoth]] is preponderant.

Alcuin also developed manuals used in his educational work – a [[grammar]] and works on [[rhetoric]] and [[dialectics]]. These are written in the form of [[dialogues]], and in two of them the interlocutors are Charlemagne and Alcuin. He wrote several [[theological]] treatises: a ''De fide Trinitatis'', and commentaries on the Bible.{{sfn|Page|1909|p=15}} Alcuin is credited with inventing the first known [[question mark]], though it didn't resemble the modern symbol.{{sfn|Truss|2003|p=76}}

Alcuin transmitted to the [[Franks]] the knowledge of Latin culture which had existed in Anglo-Saxon England. A number of his works still exist. Besides some graceful epistles in the style of [[Venantius Fortunatus]], he wrote some long poems, and notably he is the author of a history (in verse) of the church at York, ''Versus de patribus, regibus et sanctis Eboracensis ecclesiae''. At the same time, he is noted for making one of the only explicit comments on [[Old English poetry]] surviving from the early Middle Ages, in a letter to one Speratus, the bishop of an unnamed English [[Episcopal see|see]] (possibly [[Unwona]] of Leicester): 'verba Dei legantur in sacerdotali convivio: ibi decet lectorem audiri, non citharistam, sermones patrum, non carmina gentilium. Quid [[Hinieldus]] cum Christo?' ('Let God's words be read at the episcopal dinner-table. It is right that a reader should be heard,  not  a harpist,  patristic  discourse, not  pagan  song.  What  has  [[Hinield]] to do with Christ?').&lt;ref&gt;Donald A. Bullough, 'What has Ingeld to do with Lindisfarne?', ''Anglo-Saxon England'', 22 (1993), 93-125 (p. 93 for the Latin [quoted from ''Epistolae Karolini Aevi II'', ed. by E. Dummler, Monumenta Germaniae Historica, Epistula 4 (Berlin, 1895), p. 183 (no. 12)]; p. 124 for the translation); {{DOI|10.1017/S0263675100004336}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Use of homo-erotic language in writings ===
According to David Clark, passages in some of Alcuin's writings display homosocial desire, even possibly homoerotic imagery. However, Clark says it is not possible to determine whether they were the result of an outward expression of erotic feelings, &quot;...nor is the question important or productive.&quot;{{sfn|Clark|2009|p=80}} Historian [[John Boswell]]{{sfn|Boswell|2015|p=254}}{{not in source given|date=September 2019}}{{sfn|Bromell|2002|p=16}} cited this as a personal outpouring of Alcuin's internalized [[homosexual]] feelings. Others agree that Alcuin at times &quot;comes perilously close to communicating openly his same sex desires&quot;, and this reflects the erotic subculture of the [[Carolingian]] monastic school, but also perhaps a 'queer space' where &quot;erotic attachment and affections may be safely articulated&quot;.{{sfn|Coon|2011|p=18}}

Erotic and religious love are intertwined in Alcuin's writings, and he frequently &quot;eroticizes his personal relationships to his beloved friends&quot;. Alcuin's friendships also extended to the ladies of the court, especially the queen mother and the king's daughters, though David Bromell is of the opinion that Alcuin's relationships with these women never reached the intense level of those of the men around him.{{sfn|Bromell|2002|p=16}}{{not in source given|date=September 2019}}

Alcuin was a close friend of Charlemagne's sister [[Gisela, Abbess of Chelles]], whom he &quot;hailed as a noble sister in the bond of sweet love&quot;.{{sfn|Dales|2012|p=90}} He wrote to Charlemagne's daughters Rotrudis and Bertha that &quot;the devotion of my heart specially tends towards you both because of the familiarity and dedication you have shown me.&quot;{{sfn|Dales|2012|p=91}} His nickname for Gisela was ''Julia'', for Rotrudis ''Columba''. He dedicated the last two books of his commentary on John's gospel to them both.{{sfn|Dales|2012|p=91}}

The interpretation of homosexual desire has been disputed by [[Allen Frantzen]],{{sfn|Frantzen|1998|p=198}}{{efn |See also {{harvnb|Jaeger|1991}} }} who identifies Alcuin's language with that of medieval Christian ''amicitia'' or friendship. Karl Liersch, in his 1880 inaugural dissertation, cites several passages from poems by [[Theodulf of Orleans]]. In these poems Theodulf reports that Alcuin had a female muse named Delia at the king's court (she was probably Charlemagne's daughter). Delia is also the addressee of several poems by Alcuin.{{sfn|Liersch|1880|pp=49-50}}

Douglas Dales and [[Rowan Williams]] say &quot;the use of language drawn [by Alcuin] from the ''Song of Songs'' transforms apparently erotic language into something within Christian friendship – 'an ordained affection'.&quot;{{sfn|Dales|Williams|2013|p=228}}

Despite inconclusive evidence of Alcuin's personal passions, he was clear in his own writings that the men of [[Sodom and Gomorrah|Sodom]] had been punished with fire for &quot;sinning against nature with men&quot;&amp;nbsp;– a view commonly held by the Church at the time.  Such sins, argued Alcuin, were therefore more serious than lustful acts with women, for which the earth was cleansed and revivified by the water of the [[Genesis flood narrative|Flood]], and merit to be &quot;withered by flames unto eternal barrenness.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |chapter=Interrogationes Sigewulfi in Genesin |editor= J.-P. Migne |author=Alcuin |chapter-url=https://archive.org/stream/patrologiaecurs171unkngoog#page/n276/mode/2up |title=Patrologiae Cursus Completus| volume=100|at= col. 543. Question 191|date=1863}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
In several churches of the [[Anglican Communion]], Alcuin is celebrated on 20 May, the first available day after the day of his death (as [[Dunstan]] is celebrated on 19 May).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.churchintouraine.org/?page_id=2|title=Why Alcuin – Church in Touraine|website=www.churchintouraine.org|language=en-GB|access-date=2017-11-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Alcuin College]], one of the [[colleges of the University of York]], England, is named after him.

In January 2020 Alcuin was the subject of the [[BBC Radio 4]] programme ''[[In Our Time (radio series)|In Our Time]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/m000dqy8|title=BBC Radio 4 - In Our Time, Alcuin|website=BBC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Quotations==
* &quot;Quadpropter potius animam curare memento, quam carnem, quoniam haec manet, illa perit.&quot;:{{sfn|Gaskoin|1966|p=133}} 'Remember to care for the soul more than the body, since the former remains, the latter perishes.'{{sfn|Ellsberg|2016|p=286}}
* &quot;Nec audiendi qui solent dicere, Vox populi, vox Dei, quum tumultuositas vulgi semper insaniae proxima sit.&quot;: 'And do not listen to those who keep saying, 'The voice of the people is the voice of God.' because the tumult of the crowd is always close to madness.'&lt;ref&gt;Works, Epistle 127.&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;In the morning, at the height of my powers, I sowed the seed in Britain, now in the evening when my blood is growing cold I am still sowing in France, hoping both will grow, by the grace of God, giving some the honey of the holy scriptures, making others drunk on the old wine of ancient learning...&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;MacTutor&quot;&gt;{{MacTutor Biography|id=Alcuin}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Selected works==
For a complete census of Alcuin's works, see Marie-Hélène Jullien and Françoise Perelman, eds., ''Clavis scriptorum latinorum medii aevi: Auctores Galliae 735–987. Tomus II: Alcuinus.'' Turnhout: Brepols, 1999.

;Poetry
* ''Carmina'', ed. [[Ernst Dümmler]], MGH ''Poetae Latini aevi Carolini'' I. Berlin: Weidmann, 1881. 160–351.
** Godman, Peter, tr., ''Poetry of the Carolingian Renaissance''. Norman, University of Oklahoma Press, 1985. 118–49.
** Stella, Francesco, tr., comm., ''La poesia carolingia'', Firenze: Le Lettere, 1995, pp.&amp;nbsp;94–96, 152–61, 266–67, 302–07, 364–71, 399–404, 455–57, 474–77, 503–07.
** Isbell, Harold, tr.. ''The Last Poets of Imperial Rome''. Baltimore: Penguin, 1971.
* Poem on York, ''Versus de patribus, regibus et sanctis Euboricensis ecclesiae'', ed. and tr. Peter Godman, ''The Bishops, Kings, and Saints of York.'' Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1982.
* ''De clade Lindisfarnensis monasterii'', &quot;On the destruction of the monastery of Lindisfarne&quot; (''Carmen'' 9, ed. Dümmler, pp.&amp;nbsp;229–35.)

;''Epistolae'' (Letters)
Of Alcuin's letters, just over 310 have survived.
* ''Epistolae'', ed. Ernst Dümmler, MGH ''Epistolae'' IV.2. Berlin: Weidmann, 1895. 1–493.
* Jaffé, Philipp, Ernst Dümmler, and W. Wattenbach, eds. ''Monumenta Alcuiniana''. Berlin: Weidmann, 1873. 132–897.
* [[Colin Robert Chase|Chase, Colin]], ed. ''Two Alcuin Letter-books''. Toronto: Pontifical Institute of Mediaeval Studies, 1975.
** Allott, Stephen, tr. ''Alcuin of York, c. AD 732 to 804. His life and letters''. York: William Sessions, 1974.
** Sturgeon, Thomas G., tr. ''The Letters of Alcuin: Part One, the Aachen Period (762–796)''. Harvard University Ph.D. Thesis, 1953.

;Didactic works
* ''[[Ars grammatica#Alcuin's Ars Grammatica|Ars grammatica]]''. PL 101: 854–902.
* ''De orthographia'', ed. H. Keil, ''Grammatici Latini'' VII, 1880. 295–312; ed. Sandra Bruni, ''Alcuino de orthographia''. Florence: SISMEL, 1997.
* ''De dialectica''. PL 101: 950–76.
* ''Disputatio regalis et nobilissimi juvenis Pippini cum Albino scholastico'' &quot;Dialogue of Pepin, the Most Noble and Royal Youth, with the Teacher Albinus&quot;, ed. L.W. Daly and W. Suchier, ''Altercatio Hadriani Augusti et Epicteti Philosophi''. Urbana, IL: University of Illinois Press, 1939. 134–46; ed. Wilhelm Wilmanns, &quot;Disputatio regalis et nobilissimi juvenis Pippini cum Albino scholastico.&quot; ''Zeitschrift für deutsches Altertum'' 14 (1869): 530–55, 562.
* ''Disputatio de rhetorica et de virtutibus sapientissimi regis Carli et Albini magistri'', ed. and tr. Wilbur Samuel Howell, ''The Rhetoric of Alcuin and Charlemagne.'' New York: Russell and Russell, 1965 (1941); ed. C. Halm, ''Rhetorici Latini Minores''. Leipzig: Teubner, 1863. 523–50.
* ''De virtutibus et vitiis'' (moral treatise dedicated to [[Count Wido]] of Brittany, 799 x 800). PL 101: 613–39 ([http://www.documentacatholicaomnia.eu/04z/z_0735-0804__Alcuinus__De_Virtutibus_Et_Vitiis_Liber_Ad_Widonem_Comitem__MLT.pdf.html transcript available online]). A new critical edition is being prepared for the ''Corpus Christianorum, Continuatio Medievalis''.
* ''De animae ratione (ad Eulaliam virginem)'' (written for Gundrada, Charlemagne's cousin). PL 101: 639–50.
* ''De Cursu et Saltu Lunae ac Bissexto'', astronomical treatise. PL 101: 979–1002.
* (?) ''[[Propositiones ad Acuendos Juvenes|Propositiones ad acuendos iuvenes]]'', ed. Menso Folkerts, &quot;Die alteste mathematische Aufgabensammlung in lateinischer Sprache: Die Alkuin zugeschriebenen ''Propositiones ad acuendos iuvenes''; Überlieferung, Inhalt, Kritische Edition,&quot; in ''idem'', ''Essays on Early Medieval Mathematics: The Latin Tradition.'' Aldershot: Ashgate, 2003.

;Theology
* ''Compendium in Canticum Canticorum'': Alcuino, ''Commento al Cantico dei cantici – con i commenti anonimi Vox ecclesie e Vox antique ecclesie'', ed. Rossana Guglielmetti, Firenze, SISMEL 2004
* ''[[Quaestiones in Genesim]]''. PL 100: 515–66.
* ''De Fide Sanctae Trinitatis et de Incarnatione Christi; Quaestiones de Sancta Trinitate'' ed. E. Knibbs &amp; E. Ann Matter (Corpus Christianorum – Continuatio Mediaevalis 249: Brepols, 2012)

;Hagiography
* ''Vita II Vedastis episcopi Atrebatensis''. Revision of the earlier ''Vita Vedastis'' by [[Jonas of Bobbio]]. ''Patrologia Latina'' 101: 663–82.
* ''[[Richarius|Vita Richarii confessoris Centulensis]]''. Revision of an earlier anonymous life. MGH Scriptores Rerum Merovingicarum 4: 381–401.
* ''Vita Willibrordi archiepiscopi Traiectensis'', ed. W. Levison, ''Passiones vitaeque sanctorum aevi Merovingici''. MGH Scriptores Rerum Merovingicarum 7: 81–141.

==See also==
{{Portal|Saints}}
* [[Propositiones ad Acuendos Juvenes]]
* [[Carolingian art]]
* [[Carolingian Empire]]
* [[:Category:Carolingian period|Category: Carolingian period]]
* [[Correctory]]
* [[Codex Vindobonensis 795]]

==Notes==
{{notelist}}
{{Reflist}}

==Sources==
{{refbegin|2|indent=yes}}
*{{cite book|url=http://www.intratext.com/X/LAT0602.HTM | title =Propositiones Alcuini Doctoris Caroli Magni Imperatoris ad Acuendes Juvenes|lang=la|trans-title=Propositions of Alcuin, A Teacher of Emperor Charlemagne, for Sharpening Youths|date=n.d.|ref=harv|author=Alcuin}}
* Allott, Stephen. ''Alcuin of York, his life and letters'' {{ISBN|0-900657-21-9}}
*{{cite journal|last1=Atkinson|first1=Leigh|title=When the Pope was a Mathematician|journal=The College Mathematics Journal|volume=36|issue=5|year=2005|pages=354–362|issn=0746-8342|doi=10.1080/07468342.2005.11922149|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Boswell|first=John |authorlink=John Boswell|title=Christianity, Social Tolerance, and Homosexuality: Gay People in Western Europe from the Beginning of the Christian Era to the Fourteenth Century|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3kzgCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA254|year=2015|publisher=University of Chicago Press|isbn=978-0-226-34536-9}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Bromell|first=David|editor1-first=Robert |editor1-last=Aldrich  |editor2-first=Garry|editor2-last=Wotherspoon|title=Who's who in Gay and Lesbian History: From Antiquity to World War II|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=zLWTqBmifh0C&amp;pg=PA16|year=2002|publisher=Psychology Press|isbn=978-0-415-15983-8|chapter=Alcuin}}
* {{Cite book |last=Browne |first=G.F. |year=1908 |title=Alcuin of York |publisher=Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge |publication-date=1908 |location=London |url=https://books.google.com/?id=ho8QGIF5py8C}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|last=Bullough|first=Donald A |title=Alcuin: Achievement and Reputation |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Y5F0AAAAIAAJ|series=Being Part of the Ford Lectures Delivered in Oxford in Hilary Term 1980|year=2004|publisher=Brill|isbn=978-90-04-12865-1}}
* {{cite ODNB|last=Bullough |first=Donald |date = 2010|origyear=2004 |title=Alcuin (c. 740–804) |id=298}}
*{{cite CE1913|last=Burns|first= James Aloysius|volume=1|wstitle=Alcuin|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Clark|first=David |title=Between Medieval Men: Male Friendship and Desire in Early Medieval English Literature|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=m19Gbl6VKQUC&amp;pg=PA79|year=2009|publisher=OUP |location=Oxford|isbn=978-0-19-156788-9}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Coon|first=Lynda L. |title=Dark Age Bodies: Gender and Monastic Practice in the Early Medieval West|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=mndRCyKkWt0C&amp;pg=PA18|year=2011|publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press|isbn=978-0-8122-0491-9}}
* Dales, Douglas J. 'Accessing Alcuin: A Master Bibliography' (James Clarke &amp; Co., Cambridge, 2013), {{ISBN|978-0227901977}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|last=Dales|first=Douglas |title=Alcuin: His Life and Legacy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=V5kABAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA91|year=2012|publisher=James Clarke &amp; Co|isbn=978-0-227-17346-6}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|last1=Dales|first1=Douglas |last2=Williams|first2=Rowan  |authorlink2=Rowan  Williams|title=Alcuin: Theology and Thought|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gpsABAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA228|year=2013|publisher=James Clarke &amp; Co|isbn=978-0-227-17394-7|chapter=Ch. 24 The Poet at Work}}
* Diem, Albrecht, ‘The Emergence of Monastic Schools. The Role of Alcuin’, in: Luuk A. J. R. Houwen and Alasdair A. McDonald (eds.), ''Alcuin of York. Scholar at the Carolingian Court'', Groningen 1998 (Germania Latina, vol. 3), pp. 27-44.
* Duckett, Eleanor Shipley. ''Alcuin, Friend of Charlemagne,'' (1951)
* Duckett, Eleanor Shipley. ''Carolingian Portraits'', (1962)
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Ellsberg|first=Robert |title=Blessed Among Us: Day by Day with Saintly Witnesses|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=osC5DAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA286|year=2016|publisher=Liturgical Press|isbn=978-0-8146-4745-5}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Frantzen|first=Allen J. |authorlink=Allen Frantzen|title=Before the Closet: Same-Sex Love from &quot;Beowulf&quot; to &quot;Angels in America&quot;|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZPq0sITjL8QC&amp;pg=PA198|year=1998|publisher=University of Chicago Press|isbn=978-0-226-26092-1}}
* Ganshof, F.L. ''The Carolingians and the Frankish Monarchy'' {{ISBN|0-582-48227-5}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Gaskoin|first=Charles Jacinth Bellairs |title=Alcuin: His Life and His Work|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sTM9AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA133|year=1966|publisher=Cambridge University Press|id=GGKEY:9CL47HJX2L5}}
* Godman, Peter. ''Poetry of the Carolingian Renaissance'' {{ISBN|0-7156-1768-0}}
*{{cite journal|last1=Gorman|first1=Michael|title=Alcuin before Migne|journal=Revue Bénédictine|volume=112|issue=1–2|year=2002|pages=101–130|issn=0035-0893|doi=10.1484/J.RB.5.100616|ref=harv}}
*{{cite web|first=Fred|last=Hutchison|date=1 June 2006|title=A cure for the educational crisis: Learn from the extraordinary educational heritage of the West |work=RenewAmerica |url=http://www.renewamerica.us/analyses/060601hutchison.htm |accessdate=2 June 2006 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060602171225/http://www.renewamerica.us/analyses/060601hutchison.htm |archivedate=2 June 2006 |url-status=dead |ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal|last1=Jaeger|first1=C. Stephen|title=L'Amour des Rois: Structure Sociale D'Une Forme de Sensibilité Aristocratique|journal=Annales. Histoire, Sciences Sociales|volume=46|issue=3|year=1991|pages=547–571|issn=0395-2649|doi=10.3406/ahess.1991.278964}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Jaeger|first=C. Stephen |title=Ennobling Love: In Search of a Lost Sensibility|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VC9vLpHlYY4C&amp;pg=PR9|year=1999|publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press|isbn=0-8122-1691-1}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|editor1-first=Marie-Hélène |editor1-last=Jullien|title=Clavis scriptorum Latinorum Medii Aevi: auctores Galliae, 735-987|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=oDQEoQEACAAJ|year=1994|publisher=Brepols|location=Turnhout |oclc=610811296|lang=la|editor2-first=Françoise |editor2-last=Perelman|volume=Tomus II: Alcuinus}}
*{{cite book|last=Liersch|first= Karl|url=http://www.mgh.de/bibliothek/opac/?wa72ci_url=/cgi-bin/mgh/regsrchindex.pl?wert%3Dgedichte+theodulfs,+bischofs+von+orleans&amp;recnums=195542&amp;index=1&amp;db=opac |title=Die Gedichte Theodulfs, Bischofs von Orleans|lang=de|location= Halle|date= 1880|ref=harv}}
* Lorenz, Frederick. ''[https://archive.org/details/lifeofalcuin00lorerich The life of Alcuin]'' (Thomas Hurst, 1837).
* {{cite book|last=Mayr-Harting|first=Henry|authorlink=Henry Mayr-Harting|chapter=Alcuin, Charlemagne and the problem of sanctions|title=Early Medieval Studies in Memory of Patrick Wormald|publisher=Routledge|year=2016|isbn=978-0754663317|ref=harv| editor-given1 = Stephen | editor-surname1 = Baxter | editor-given2 = Catherine | editor-surname2 = Karkov |editor-link2=Catherine Karkov|editor-given3 = Janet L. | editor-surname3 = Nelson |editor-link3=Janet Nelson| editor-given4 = David | editor-surname4 = Pelteret }}
* McGuire, Brian P. ''Friendship, and Community: The Monastic Experience'' {{ISBN|0-87907-895-2}}
* Murphy, Richard E. ''Alcuin of York: De Virtutibus et Vitiis, Virtues and Vices.'' {{ISBN|978-0-9966967-0-8}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Needham|first=N. R.|title=2,000 Years of Christ's Power|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=SYP8SAAACAAJ|volume=Part Two: The Middle Ages|year=2000|publisher=Grace Publications Trust|isbn=978-0-946462-56-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Page|first= Rolph Barlow|url=https://archive.org/details/lettersofalcuin00pagerich |title=The Letters of Alcuin|location=New York|publisher= Forest Press|date= 1909|ref=harv}}
* Stehling, Thomas. ''Medieval Latin Love Poems of Male Love and Friendship''.
* Stella, Francesco, &quot;Alkuins Dichtung&quot;  in ''Alkuin von York und die geistige Grundlegung Europas '', Sankt Gallen, Verlag am Klosterhof, 2010, pp.&amp;nbsp;107–28.
* {{cite book |last1=Stenton |first1=F.M. |authorlink1=Frank Stenton |title=Anglo-Saxon England |date=2001 |publisher=Oxford University Press |isbn=978-0192801395 |edition=3|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|title=Charlemagne: Empire and Society|first=Joanna|last=Story|publisher=Manchester University Press|year=2005|isbn=978-0719070891|page=137|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vTbvq_8HFPUC&amp;pg=PA137|ref=harv}}
* Throop, Priscilla, trans. ''Alcuin: His Life; On Virtues and Vices; Dialogue with Pepin'' (Charlotte, VT: MedievalMS, 2011)
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Truss|first=Lynne |title=Eats, Shoots &amp; Leaves: The Zero Tolerance Approach to Punctuation|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=_-BgAAAAMAAJ|year=2003|publisher=Profile Books|isbn=978-1-86197-612-3}}
* [[West, Andrew Fleming]]. ''[https://archive.org/details/alcuinriseofchri00westiala Alcuin and the Rise of the Christian Schools]'' (C. Scribner's Sons, 1912) {{ISBN|0-8371-1635-X}}
*{{cite book|last=Wilmot-Buxton|first=E.M.|title=Alcuin|year=1922|publisher=P.J. Kenedy &amp; Sons|location=New York|ref=harv|url=https://archive.org/stream/alcuin__00wilm#page/92/mode/2up}}
* {{wikisource-inline|list=
** {{cite EB1911|wstitle=Alcuin|volume=1 |short=x |noicon=x}}
** {{cite CE1913|wstitle=Alcuin|volume=1 |short=x |noicon=x}}
** {{cite NSRW|wstitle=Alcuin|volume=1 |short=x |noicon=x}}
** {{cite SBDEL|wstitle=Alcuin or Ealhwine |short=x |noicon=x}}
** {{cite DNB|wstitle=Alcuin |volume=1 |short=x |noicon=x}}
}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{wikisource-author}}
{{wikiquote}}
{{Wikisource|Scriptor:Alcuinus|Alcuinus|lang=la}}
{{commonscat}}
* {{PASE|1142|Alcuin 1}}
* [http://logica.ugent.be/albrecht/alcuin.pdf Alcuin's book, ''Problems for the Quickening of the Minds of the Young'']
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20081205163439/http://www.bu.edu/english/levine/alcend.htm Introduction to Alcuin's writings by Robert Levine and Whitney Bolton]
* [http://www.alcuinsociety.com/ ''The Alcuin Society'']
* [http://www.historyofyork.org.uk/timeline/anglo-saxon ''Anglo-Saxon York on History of York site'']
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20081118194921/http://www.corpuschristianorum.org/series/cccm_preparation.html Corpus Christianorum, Continuatio Mediaevalis: new critical editions in preparation]
* [https://archive.is/20121204163129/http://kaali.linguist.jussieu.fr/CGL/index.jsp Corpus Grammaticorum Latinorum: complete texts and full bibliography]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20130502224321/http://cristoraul.com/ENGLISH/readinghall/GalleryofHistory/ALCUIN/Alcuin-Door.html The Life of Alcuin by Dr. Frederick Lorenz]
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Alcuin}}
* {{Librivox author |id=1121}}
* {{DNB-Portal|118502026}}
* {{DDB|Person|118502026}}
* {{Geschichtsquellen Person|118502026}}
* {{Hl-Lex|b|Alkuin.htm}}

{{Catholic philosophy footer}}
{{Medieval Philosophy}}
{{History of Catholic theology}}
{{Carolingians footer}}
{{Carolingian Empire}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:735 births]]
[[Category:804 deaths]]
[[Category:8th-century astronomers]]
[[Category:8th-century Christian theologians]]
[[Category:8th-century English writers]]
[[Category:8th-century Frankish writers]]
[[Category:8th-century Latin writers]]
[[Category:8th-century mathematicians]]
[[Category:8th-century philosophers]]
[[Category:8th-century poets]]
[[Category:9th-century Christian monks]]
[[Category:9th-century Christian theologians]]
[[Category:9th-century English writers]]
[[Category:9th-century philosophers]]
[[Category:Anglo-Saxon poets]]
[[Category:Anglo-Saxon saints]]
[[Category:Anglo-Saxon writers]]
[[Category:Carolingian poets]]
[[Category:Christian hagiographers]]
[[Category:Deacons]]
[[Category:English monks]]
[[Category:Grammarians of Latin]]
[[Category:Homosexuality and Catholicism]]
[[Category:Latin texts of Anglo-Saxon England]]
[[Category:Medieval chancellors (government)]]
[[Category:Medieval English mathematicians]]
[[Category:Medieval English theologians]]
[[Category:Medieval Latin poets]]
[[Category:Medieval LGBT history]]
[[Category:Medieval linguists]]
[[Category:People from York]]
[[Category:Saints of the Carolingian Empire]]
[[Category:Scholastic philosophers]]
[[Category:Sources on Germanic paganism]]
[[Category:Writers of the Carolingian Empire]]</text>
      <sha1>625no00glwtabd3ra4zq4pek6phkyth</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
