  <page>
    <title>Absolute zero</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1418</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938171921</id>
      <parentid>938007760</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-29T15:25:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>LilyKitty</username>
        <id>10521907</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>about Charles's law</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|The lowest  attainable temperature}}
{{About|the minimum temperature possible|other uses|Absolute Zero (disambiguation)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2012}}
[[File:CelsiusKelvin.svg|thumb|right|150px|Zero kelvins (−273.15&amp;nbsp;°C) is defined as absolute zero.]]

'''Absolute zero''' is the lowest limit of the [[thermodynamic temperature]] scale, a state at which the [[enthalpy]] and [[entropy]] of a cooled [[ideal gas]] reach their minimum value, taken as zero [[kelvin]]s. The fundamental particles of nature have minimum vibrational motion, retaining only quantum mechanical, [[zero-point energy]]-induced particle motion. The theoretical temperature is determined by extrapolating the [[ideal gas law]]; by international agreement, absolute zero is taken as −273.15° on the [[Celsius]] scale ([[International System of Units]]),&lt;ref name=sib2115&gt;{{cite web|title=Unit of thermodynamic temperature (kelvin) |work=SI Brochure, 8th edition |at=Section 2.1.1.5 |url=http://www.bipm.org/en/publications/si-brochure/kelvin.html |publisher=Bureau International des Poids et Mesures |date=13 March 2010 |origyear=1967 |access-date=20 June 2017 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141007053944/http://www.bipm.org/en/publications/si-brochure/kelvin.html |archivedate=7 October 2014 }} '''Note''': The triple point of water is 0.01 °C, not 0 °C; thus 0 K is −273.15 °C, not −273.16 °C.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;arora&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Thermodynamics|first1=C. P.|last1=Arora|publisher=Tata McGraw-Hill |year=2001|isbn=978-0-07-462014-4|at=Table 2.4 page 43|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=w8GhW3J8RHIC&amp;pg=PA43}}&lt;/ref&gt; which equals −459.67° on the [[Fahrenheit]] scale ([[United States customary units]] or [[Imperial units]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.smithsonianmag.com/science-nature/absolute-zero-200801.html|last1=Zielinski|first1=Sarah|date=1 January 2008|title=Absolute Zero|publisher=Smithsonian Institution|accessdate=2012-01-26|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130401180715/http://www.smithsonianmag.com/science-nature/absolute-zero-200801.html|archive-date=1 April 2013|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; The corresponding Kelvin and [[Rankine scale|Rankine]] temperature scales set their zero points at absolute zero by definition.

It is commonly thought of as the lowest temperature possible, but it is not the lowest ''enthalpy'' state possible, because all real substances begin to depart from the ideal gas when cooled as they approach the change of state to liquid, and then to solid; and the sum of the [[enthalpy of vaporization]] (gas to liquid) and [[enthalpy of fusion]] (liquid to solid) exceeds the ideal gas's change in enthalpy to absolute zero. In the [[quantum mechanics|quantum-mechanical]] description, matter (solid) at absolute zero is in its [[ground state]], the point of lowest [[internal energy]].

The [[laws of thermodynamics]] indicate that absolute zero cannot be reached using only thermodynamic means, because the temperature of the substance being cooled approaches the temperature of the cooling agent [[asymptotically]],&lt;ref&gt;{{ Citation | last = Masanes | first = Lluís | last2 = Oppenheim | first2 = Jonathan | author2-link = Jonathan Oppenheim | date = 14 March 2017 | title = A general derivation and quantification of the third law of thermodynamics | journal = Nature Communications | volume = 8 | pages = 14538 | number = 14538 | doi = 10.1038/ncomms14538 | pmid = 28290452 | pmc = 5355879 | bibcode = 2017NatCo...814538M }}&lt;/ref&gt; and a system at absolute zero still possesses [[quantum mechanics|quantum mechanical]] zero-point energy, the energy of its ground state at absolute zero. The [[kinetic energy]] of the ground state cannot be removed. 
 
Scientists and technologists routinely achieve temperatures close to absolute zero, where matter exhibits [[Bose–Einstein condensate|quantum effects]] such as [[superconductivity]] and [[superfluidity]].

==Thermodynamics near absolute zero==
At temperatures near {{convert|0|K|C F}}, nearly all molecular motion ceases and Δ''S''&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;0 for any [[adiabatic process]], where ''S'' is the [[entropy]]. In such a circumstance, pure substances can (ideally) form [[perfect crystal]]s as ''T'' → 0. [[Max Planck]]'s strong form of the [[third law of thermodynamics]] states the [[entropy]] of a perfect crystal vanishes at absolute zero in which a perfect crystal is gone. The original [[Walther Nernst|Nernst]] ''[[Nernst heat theorem|heat theorem]]'' makes the weaker and less controversial claim that the entropy change for any [[isothermal process]] approaches zero as ''T'' → 0:
:&lt;math&gt; \lim_{T \to 0} \Delta S = 0 &lt;/math&gt;

The implication is that the entropy of a perfect crystal approaches a constant value.

&lt;blockquote&gt;The [[Third law of thermodynamics|Nerst postulate]] identifies the [[isothermal process|isotherm]] T&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;0 as coincident with the [[adiabat]] S&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;0, although other isotherms and adiabats are distinct. As no two adiabats intersect, no other adiabat can [[Line–line intersection|intersect]] the T&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;0 isotherm. Consequently no adiabatic process initiated at nonzero temperature can lead to zero temperature. (≈&amp;nbsp;Callen, pp.&amp;nbsp;189–190)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

A perfect crystal is one in which the internal [[lattice (group)|lattice]] structure extends uninterrupted in all directions. The perfect order can be represented by translational [[symmetry]] along three (not usually [[orthogonality|orthogonal]]) [[Cartesian coordinate system|axes]]. Every lattice element of the structure is in its proper place, whether it is a single atom or a molecular grouping. For [[chemical substance|substances]] that exist in two (or more) stable crystalline forms, such as diamond and [[graphite]] for [[carbon]], there is a kind of ''chemical degeneracy''. The question remains whether both can have zero entropy at ''T''&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;0 even though each is perfectly ordered.

Perfect crystals never occur in practice; imperfections, and even entire amorphous material inclusions, can and do get &quot;frozen in&quot; at low temperatures, so transitions to more stable states do not occur.

Using the [[Debye model]], the [[specific heat capacity|specific heat]] and entropy of a pure crystal are proportional to ''T''&lt;sup&gt;&amp;nbsp;3&lt;/sup&gt;, while the [[enthalpy]] and [[chemical potential]] are proportional to ''T''&lt;sup&gt;&amp;nbsp;4&lt;/sup&gt;. (Guggenheim, p.&amp;nbsp;111) These quantities drop toward their ''T''&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;0 limiting values and approach with ''zero'' slopes. For the specific heats at least, the limiting value itself is definitely zero, as borne out by experiments to below 10&amp;nbsp;K. Even the less detailed [[Einstein solid|Einstein model]] shows this curious drop in specific heats. In fact, all specific heats vanish at absolute zero, not just those of crystals. Likewise for the coefficient of [[thermal expansion]]. [[Maxwell relations|Maxwell's relations]] show that various other quantities also vanish. These [[phenomenon|phenomena]] were unanticipated.

Since the relation between changes in [[Gibbs free energy]] (''G''), the enthalpy (''H'') and the entropy is

:&lt;math&gt; \Delta G = \Delta H - T \Delta S \,&lt;/math&gt;

thus, as ''T'' decreases, Δ''G'' and Δ''H'' approach each other (so long as Δ''S'' is bounded). Experimentally, it is found that all spontaneous processes (including [[chemical reaction]]s) result in a decrease in ''G'' as they proceed toward [[thermodynamic equilibrium|equilibrium]]. If Δ''S'' and/or ''T'' are small, the condition Δ''G''&amp;nbsp;&lt;&amp;nbsp;0 may imply that Δ''H''&amp;nbsp;&lt;&amp;nbsp;0, which would indicate an [[exothermic]] reaction. However, this is not required; [[endothermic]] reactions can proceed spontaneously if the ''T''Δ''S'' term is large enough.

Moreover, the slopes of the [[derivative]]s of Δ''G'' and Δ''H'' converge and are equal to zero at ''T''&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;0. This ensures that Δ''G'' and Δ''H'' are nearly the same over a considerable range of temperatures and justifies the approximate [[empiricism|empirical]] Principle of Thomsen and Berthelot, which states that ''the equilibrium state to which a system proceeds is the one that evolves the greatest amount of heat'', i.e., an actual process is the ''most exothermic one''. (Callen, pp.&amp;nbsp;186–187)

One model that estimates the properties of an [[electron]] gas at absolute zero in metals is the [[Fermi gas]]. The electrons, being [[Fermion]]s, must be in different quantum states, which leads the electrons to get very high typical [[velocities]], even at absolute zero. The maximum energy that electrons can have at absolute zero is called the [[Fermi energy]]. The Fermi temperature is defined as this maximum energy divided by Boltzmann's constant, and is of the order of 80,000 K for typical electron densities found in metals. For temperatures significantly below the Fermi temperature, the electrons behave in almost the same way as at absolute zero. This explains the failure of the classical [[equipartition theorem]] for metals that eluded classical physicists in the late 19th century.

==Relation with Bose–Einstein condensate==
{{Main|Bose–Einstein condensate}}

[[File:Bose Einstein condensate.png|left|thumb|Velocity-distribution data of a gas of [[rubidium]] atoms at a temperature within a few billionths of a degree above absolute zero. Left: just before the appearance of a Bose–Einstein condensate. Center: just after the appearance of the condensate. Right: after further evaporation, leaving a sample of nearly pure condensate.]]
A [[Bose–Einstein condensate]] (BEC) is a [[state of matter]] of a dilute gas of weakly interacting [[boson]]s confined in an external potential and cooled to temperatures very near absolute zero. Under such conditions, a large fraction of the bosons occupy the lowest [[quantum state]] of the external potential, at which point quantum effects become apparent on a [[macroscopic scale]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|journal=Nature|volume=412|pages=295–299|year=2001|title=Dynamics of collapsing and exploding Bose–Einstein condensates|pmid=11460153|issue=6844|doi=10.1038/35085500|arxiv = cond-mat/0105019 |bibcode = 2001Natur.412..295D|last1=Donley|first1=Elizabeth A.|last2=Claussen|first2=Neil R.|last3=Cornish|first3=Simon L.|last4=Roberts|first4=Jacob L.|last5=Cornell|first5=Eric A.|last6=Wieman|first6=Carl E.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This state of matter was first predicted by [[Satyendra Nath Bose]] and [[Albert Einstein]] in 1924–25. Bose first sent a paper to Einstein on the [[quantum statistics]] of light quanta (now called [[photon]]s). Einstein was impressed, translated the paper from English to German and submitted it for Bose to the ''[[Zeitschrift für Physik]]'', which published it. Einstein then extended Bose's ideas to material particles (or matter) in two other papers.&lt;ref&gt;Clark, Ronald W. &quot;Einstein: The Life and Times&quot; (Avon Books, 1971) pp. 408–9 {{ISBN|0-380-01159-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Seventy years later, in 1995, the first gaseous [[Bose–Einstein condensate|condensate]] was produced by [[Eric Allin Cornell|Eric Cornell]] and [[Carl Wieman]] at the [[University of Colorado at Boulder]] [[NIST]]-[[JILA]] lab, using a gas of [[rubidium]] atoms cooled to 170&amp;nbsp;[[kelvin (unit)|nanokelvins]] (nK)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=New State of Matter Seen Near Absolute Zero |url=http://physics.nist.gov/News/Update/950724.html |publisher=NIST |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100601175245/http://physics.nist.gov/News/Update/950724.html |archivedate=1 June 2010 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; ({{val|1.7|e=-7|u=K}}).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last = Levi|first = Barbara Goss|title = Cornell, Ketterle, and Wieman Share Nobel Prize for Bose–Einstein Condensates|work = Search &amp; Discovery|publisher = Physics Today online| year = 2001|url = http://www.physicstoday.org/pt/vol-54/iss-12/p14.html|accessdate =2008-01-26 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20071024134547/http://www.physicstoday.org/pt/vol-54/iss-12/p14.html |archivedate =2007-10-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A record cold temperature of 450&amp;nbsp;±80&amp;nbsp;picokelvins (pK) ({{val|4.5|e=-10|u=K}}) in a BEC of sodium atoms was achieved in 2003 by researchers at [[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]] (MIT).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.dsf.unica.it/~michele/michele/picokelvin.pdf|title=Cooling Bose–Einstein Condensates Below 500 Picokelvin|doi=10.1126/science.1088827|volume=301|issue=5639|pages=1513–1515 |journal=Science|year=2003|last1=Leanhardt|first1=A. E.|pmid=12970559|last2=Pasquini|first2=TA|last3=Saba|first3=M|last4=Schirotzek|first4=A|last5=Shin|first5=Y|last6=Kielpinski|first6=D|last7=Pritchard|first7=DE|last8=Ketterle|first8=W|bibcode = 2003Sci...301.1513L }}&lt;/ref&gt; The associated [[black-body]] (peak emittance) wavelength of 6,400 kilometers is roughly the radius of Earth.

==Absolute temperature scales==
Absolute, or [[thermodynamic temperature|thermodynamic]], temperature is conventionally measured in [[kelvin]]s ([[Celsius]]-scaled increments) and in the [[Rankine scale]] ([[Fahrenheit]]-scaled increments) with increasing rarity. Absolute temperature measurement is uniquely determined by a multiplicative constant which specifies the size of the ''degree'', so the ''ratios'' of two absolute temperatures, ''T''&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;/''T''&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, are the same in all scales. The most transparent definition of this standard comes from the [[Maxwell–Boltzmann distribution]]. It can also be found in [[Fermi–Dirac statistics]] (for particles of half-integer [[spin (physics)|spin]]) and [[Bose–Einstein statistics]] (for particles of integer spin). All of these define the relative numbers of particles in a system as decreasing [[exponential function]]s of energy (at the particle level) over ''kT'', with ''k'' representing the [[Boltzmann constant]] and ''T'' representing the temperature observed at the [[macroscopic]] level.&lt;ref name=&quot;sib2115&quot;/&gt;

==Negative temperatures==
{{Main|Negative temperature}}

Temperatures that are expressed as negative numbers on the familiar Celsius or Fahrenheit scales are simply colder than the zero points of those scales. Certain [[Thermodynamic system|systems]] can achieve truly negative temperatures; that is, their [[thermodynamic temperature]] (expressed in kelvins) can be of a [[Negative number|negative]] quantity. A system with a truly negative temperature is not colder than absolute zero. Rather, a system with a negative temperature is hotter than ''any'' system with a positive temperature, in the sense that if a negative-temperature system and a positive-temperature system come in contact, heat flows from the negative to the positive-temperature system.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chase&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Chase|first=Scott|title=Below Absolute Zero -What Does Negative Temperature Mean?|url=http://www.phys.ncku.edu.tw/mirrors/physicsfaq/ParticleAndNuclear/neg_temperature.html|work=The Physics and Relativity FAQ|accessdate=2010-07-02|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110815144418/http://www.phys.ncku.edu.tw/mirrors/physicsfaq/ParticleAndNuclear/neg_temperature.html|archive-date=15 August 2011|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Most familiar systems cannot achieve negative temperatures because adding energy always increases their [[entropy]]. However, some systems have a maximum amount of energy that they can hold, and as they approach that maximum energy their entropy actually begins to decrease. Because temperature is defined by the relationship between energy and entropy, such a system's temperature becomes negative, even though energy is being added.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chase&quot;/&gt; As a result, the Boltzmann factor for states of systems at negative temperature increases rather than decreases with increasing state energy. Therefore, no complete system, i.e. including the electromagnetic modes, can have negative temperatures, since there is no highest energy state,{{citation needed|date=October 2016}} so that the sum of the probabilities of the states would diverge for negative temperatures. However, for quasi-equilibrium systems (e.g. spins out of equilibrium with the electromagnetic field) this argument does not apply, and negative effective temperatures are attainable.

On 3 January 2013, physicists announced that for the first time they had created a quantum gas made up of potassium atoms with a negative temperature in motional degrees of freedom.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1038/nature.2013.12146|title=Quantum gas goes below absolute zero|journal=Nature|year=2013|last1=Merali|first1=Zeeya}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[File:Robert Boyle 0001.jpg|thumb|right|upright|[[Robert Boyle]] pioneered the idea of an absolute zero]]
One of the first to discuss the possibility of an absolute minimal temperature was [[Robert Boyle]]. His 1665 ''New Experiments and Observations touching Cold'', articulated the dispute known as the ''primum frigidum''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=8vRaAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA651|title=The Stanford Dictionary of Anglicised Words and Phrases|authorlink=John Frederick Stanford|last=Stanford|first=John Frederick|year=1892 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The concept was well known among naturalists of the time. Some contended an absolute minimum temperature occurred within earth (as one of the four [[classical element]]s), others within water, others air, and some more recently within [[nitre]]. But all of them seemed to agree that, &quot;There is some body or other that is of its own nature supremely cold and by participation of which all other bodies obtain that quality.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Boyle|first=Robert|title=New Experiments and Observations touching Cold|year=1665}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Limit to the &quot;degree of cold&quot;===
The question whether there is a limit to the degree of coldness possible, and, if so, where the zero must be placed, was first addressed by the French physicist [[Guillaume Amontons]] in 1702, in connection with his improvements in the [[gas thermometer|air thermometer]]. His instrument indicated temperatures by the height at which a certain mass of air sustained a column of mercury—the volume, or &quot;spring&quot; of the air varying with temperature. Amontons therefore argued that the zero of his thermometer would be that temperature at which the spring of the air was reduced to nothing. He used a scale that marked the boiling point of water at +73 and the melting point of ice at +{{frac|51|1|2}}, so that the zero was equivalent to about −240 on the Celsius scale.&lt;ref name=AS2016&gt;{{Cite EB1911|wstitle=Cold}}&lt;/ref&gt; Amontons held that the absolute zero cannot be reached, so never attempted to compute it explicitly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Talbot |first1=G.R. |last2=Pacey |first2=A.C. |date=1972 |title=Antecedents of thermodynamics in the work of Guillaume Amontons |journal=Centaurus |volume=16 |issue=1 |pages=20–40 |doi=10.1111/j.1600-0498.1972.tb00163.x|bibcode=1972Cent...16...20T }}&lt;/ref&gt;
The value of −240&amp;nbsp;°C, or &quot;431 divisions [in Fahrenheit's thermometer] below the cold of freezing water&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Google books|tSm2Ws6bg0oC|Essays Medical and Philosophical|page=PA291}}&lt;/ref&gt; was published by [[George Martine (physician)|George Martine]] in 1740.

This close approximation to the modern value of −273.15&amp;nbsp;°C&lt;ref name=&quot;sib2115&quot;/&gt; for the zero of the air thermometer was further improved upon in 1779 by [[Johann Heinrich Lambert]], who observed that {{convert|-270|C|F K}} might be regarded as absolute cold.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Lambert|first=Johann Heinrich|title=Pyrometrie|location=Berlin|year=1779|oclc=165756016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Values of this order for the absolute zero were not, however, universally accepted about this period. [[Pierre-Simon Laplace]] and [[Antoine Lavoisier]], in their 1780 treatise on heat, arrived at values ranging from 1,500 to 3,000 below the freezing point of water, and thought that in any case it must be at least 600 below. [[John Dalton]] in his ''Chemical Philosophy'' gave ten calculations of this value, and finally adopted −3,000&amp;nbsp;°C as the natural zero of temperature.

===Lord Kelvin's work===
After [[James Prescott Joule]] had determined the mechanical equivalent of heat, [[William Thomson, 1st Baron Kelvin|Lord Kelvin]] approached the question from an entirely different point of view, and in 1848 devised a scale of absolute temperature that was independent of the properties of any particular substance and was based on [[Nicolas Léonard Sadi Carnot|Carnot]]'s theory of the Motive Power of Heat and data published by [[Henri Victor Regnault]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Thomson|first1=William|authorlink1=Lord Kelvin|title=On an Absolute Thermometric Scale founded on Carnot's Theory of the Motive Power of Heat, and calculated from Regnault's observations.|journal=Proceedings of the Cambridge Philosophical Society|date=1848|volume=1|pages=66–71|url=https://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/87114#page/72/mode/2up}}&lt;/ref&gt; It followed from the principles on which this scale was constructed that its zero was placed at −273&amp;nbsp;°C, at almost precisely the same point as the zero of the air thermometer.&lt;ref name=&quot;AS2016&quot;/&gt; This value was not immediately accepted; values ranging from {{convert|-271.1|C}} to {{convert|-274.5|C}}, derived from laboratory measurements and observations of [[Atmospheric refraction#Astronomical refraction|astronomical refraction]], remained in use in the early 20th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = Newcomb | first = Simon | author-link = Simon Newcomb | date = 1906 | title = A Compendium of Spherical Astronomy | publisher = The Macmillan Company | place = New York | page = 175 | oclc = 64423127}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===The race to absolute zero===
{{see also|Timeline of low-temperature technology}}
[[File:Leiden116.JPG|thumb|Commemorative plaque in Leiden]]
With a better theoretical understanding of absolute zero, scientists were eager to reach this temperature in the lab.&lt;ref name=&quot;MyUser_YouTube_November_23_2016c&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mTFRgosx4aQ&amp;t=894s |title=ABSOLUTE ZERO – PBS NOVA DOCUMENTARY (full length) |newspaper=YouTube |date= |author= |accessdate= November 23, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 1845, [[Michael Faraday]] had managed to liquefy most gases then known to exist, and reached a new record for lowest temperatures by reaching {{convert|-130|C|F K}}. Faraday believed that certain gases, such as oxygen, nitrogen, and hydrogen, were permanent gases and could not be liquefied.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scienceclarified.com/Co-Di/Cryogenics.html Cryogenics]. Scienceclarified.com. Retrieved on 2012-07-22.&lt;/ref&gt; Decades later, in 1873 Dutch theoretical scientist [[Johannes Diderik van der Waals]] demonstrated that these gases could be liquefied, but only under conditions of very high pressure and very low temperatures. In 1877, [[Louis Paul Cailletet]] in France and [[Raoul Pictet]] in Switzerland succeeded in producing the first droplets of [[liquid air]] {{convert|-195|C|F K}}. This was followed in 1883 by the production of liquid oxygen {{convert|-218|C|F K}} by the Polish professors [[Zygmunt Wróblewski]] and [[Karol Olszewski]].

Scottish chemist and physicist [[James Dewar]] and Dutch physicist [[Heike Kamerlingh Onnes]] took on the challenge to liquefy the remaining gases, hydrogen and helium. In 1898, after 20 years of effort, Dewar was first to liquefy hydrogen, reaching a new low-temperature record of {{convert|-252|C|F K}}. However, Kamerlingh Onnes, his rival, was the first to liquefy helium, in 1908, using several precooling stages and the [[Hampson–Linde cycle]]. He lowered the temperature to the boiling point of helium {{convert|-269|C|F K}}. By reducing the pressure of the liquid helium he achieved an even lower temperature, near 1.5 K. These were the [[Lowest temperature recorded on Earth|coldest temperatures achieved on Earth]] at the time and his achievement earned him the [[Nobel Prize]] in 1913.&lt;ref name=&quot;nobel&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/physics/laureates/1913/onnes-bio.html|title=The Nobel Prize in Physics 1913: Heike Kamerlingh Onnes|publisher=Nobel Media AB|accessdate=24 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kamerlingh Onnes would continue to study the properties of materials at temperatures near absolute zero, describing [[superconductivity]] and [[superfluids]] for the first time.

==Very low temperatures==
[[File:Boomerang nebula.jpg|thumb|right|The rapid expansion of gases leaving the [[Boomerang Nebula]], a bi-polar, filamentary, likely proto-planetary nebula in Centaurus, causes the lowest-observed temperature outside a laboratory: 1 K]]
The average temperature of the universe today is approximately {{convert|2.73|K|C F|abbr=out}}, based on measurements of [[cosmic microwave background]] radiation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.abc.net.au/science/articles/2003/09/25/947116.htm |title=Coldest Place in the Universe 1 |author = Kruszelnicki, Karl S. |date=25 September 2003 |publisher=Australian Broadcasting Corporation |accessdate=2012-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.straightdope.com/columns/read/2172/whats-the-temperature-of-space |title= What's the temperature of space? |date= 3 August 2004 |publisher=The Straight Dope |accessdate=2012-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Absolute zero cannot be achieved, although it is possible to reach temperatures close to it through the use of [[cryocooler]]s, [[dilution refrigerator]]s, and [[Magnetic refrigeration#Nuclear demagnetization|nuclear adiabatic demagnetization]]. The use of [[laser cooling]] has produced temperatures less than a billionth of a kelvin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Cosmos Online – Verging on absolute zero |url=http://www.cosmosmagazine.com/features/online/2176/verging-absolute-zero |date=2008-09-04 |author=Catchpole, Heather |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081122144155/http://www.cosmosmagazine.com/features/online/2176/verging-absolute-zero |archivedate=22 November 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; At very low temperatures in the vicinity of absolute zero, matter exhibits many unusual properties, including [[superconductivity]], [[superfluidity]], and [[Bose–Einstein condensate|Bose–Einstein condensation]]. To study such [[phenomena]], scientists have worked to obtain even lower temperatures.
* The current world record was set in 1999 at 100 picokelvins (pK), or 0.0000000001 of a kelvin, by cooling the nuclear spins in a piece of [[rhodium]] metal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://ltl.tkk.fi/wiki/LTL/World_record_in_low_temperatures|title = World record in low temperatures|accessdate =2009-05-05| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20090618075820/http://ltl.tkk.fi/wiki/LTL/World_record_in_low_temperatures| archivedate=2009-06-18| url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In November 2000, [[nuclear spin]] temperatures below 100&amp;nbsp;pK were reported for an experiment at the [[Helsinki University of Technology]]'s Low Temperature Lab in [[Espoo]], [[Finland]]. However, this was the temperature of one particular [[Degrees of freedom (physics and chemistry)|degree of freedom]]—a [[quantum]] property called nuclear spin—not the overall average [[thermodynamic temperature]] for all possible degrees in freedom.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Knuuttila |first=Tauno |url=http://www.hut.fi/Yksikot/Kirjasto/Diss/2000/isbn9512252147 |title=Nuclear Magnetism and Superconductivity in Rhodium |location=Espoo, Finland |publisher=Helsinki University of Technology |year=2000 |isbn=978-951-22-5208-4 |accessdate=2008-02-11 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20010428173229/http://www.hut.fi/Yksikot/Kirjasto/Diss/2000/isbn9512252147/ |archivedate=28 April 2001 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|title=Low Temperature World Record|url=http://ltl.hut.fi/Low-Temp-Record.html|publisher=Low Temperature Laboratory, Teknillinen Korkeakoulu|date=8 December 2000|accessdate=2008-02-11| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080218053521/http://ltl.hut.fi/Low-Temp-Record.html| archivedate=2008-02-18| url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In February 2003, the [[Boomerang Nebula]] was observed to have been releasing gases at a speed of {{Convert|500000|km/h|abbr=on}} for the last 1,500 years. This has cooled it down to approximately 1&amp;nbsp;K, as deduced by astronomical observation, which is the lowest natural temperature ever recorded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last = Sahai|first = Raghvendra|author2 = Nyman, Lars-Åke|year = 1997|title = The Boomerang Nebula: The Coldest Region of the Universe?|journal = The Astrophysical Journal|volume = 487|pages = L155–L159|doi = 10.1086/310897|bibcode=1997ApJ...487L.155S|issue = 2|hdl = 2014/22450}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In May 2005, the [[European Space Agency]] proposed research in space to achieve [[femto-]]kelvin temperatures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.esf.org/fileadmin/Public_documents/Publications/Scientific_Perspectives_for_ESA_s_Future_Programme_in_Life_and_Physical_Sciences_in_Space.pdf|title=Scientific Perspectives for ESA's Future Programme in Life and Physical sciences in Space|work=esf.org|access-date=28 March 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141006024523/http://www.esf.org/fileadmin/Public_documents/Publications/Scientific_Perspectives_for_ESA_s_Future_Programme_in_Life_and_Physical_Sciences_in_Space.pdf|archive-date=6 October 2014|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In May 2006, the Institute of Quantum Optics at the [[University of Hannover]] gave details of technologies and benefits of femto-kelvin research in space.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Atomic Quantum Sensors in Space|url=http://www.physics.ucla.edu/quantum_to_cosmos/q2c06/Ertmer.pdf|work=University of California, Los Angeles}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In January 2013, physicist Ulrich Schneider of the [[University of Munich]] in Germany reported to have achieved temperatures formally below absolute zero (&quot;[[negative temperature]]&quot;) in gases. The gas is artificially forced out of equilibrium into a high potential energy state, which is, however, cold. When it then emits radiation it approaches the equilibrium, and can continue emitting despite reaching formal absolute zero; thus, the temperature is formally negative.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.livescience.com/25959-atoms-colder-than-absolute-zero.html|title=Atoms Reach Record Temperature, Colder than Absolute Zero|work=livescience.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In September 2014, scientists in the [[CUORE]] collaboration at the [[Laboratori Nazionali del Gran Sasso]] in Italy cooled a copper vessel with a volume of one cubic meter to {{convert|0.006|K|C F|sigfig=6|abbr=out}} for 15 days, setting a record for the lowest temperature in the known universe over such a large contiguous volume.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=CUORE: The Coldest Heart in the Known Universe.|url=http://www.interactions.org/cms/?pid=1034217|accessdate=21 October 2014|publisher=INFN Press Release}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In June 2015, experimental physicists at [[MIT]] cooled molecules in a gas of sodium potassium to a temperature of 500 nanokelvins, and it is expected to exhibit an exotic state of matter by cooling these molecules a bit further.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=MIT team creates ultracold molecules|url=https://newsoffice.mit.edu/2015/ultracold-molecules-0610|work=Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Massachusetts, Cambridge}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 2017, [[Cold Atom Laboratory]] (CAL), an experimental instrument is developed for launch to the [[International Space Station]] (ISS) in 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2017/09/coolest-science-ever-headed-space-station|title=Coolest science ever headed to the space station|date=2017-09-05|work=Science {{!}} AAAS|access-date=2017-09-24|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; The instrument will create extremely cold conditions in the [[microgravity]] environment of the ISS leading to the formation of [[Bose–Einstein condensate]]s that are a magnitude colder than those that are created in laboratories on Earth. In a space-based laboratory, up to 20-second interaction times and as low as 1 picokelvin (&lt;math&gt;10^{-12}&lt;/math&gt; K) temperatures are achievable, and it could lead to exploration of unknown [[Quantum mechanics|quantum mechanical]] phenomena and test some of the most fundamental [[laws of physics]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NASA Cold Atom Laboratory Mission&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://coldatomlab.jpl.nasa.gov/mission/ |title=Cold Atom Laboratory Mission |work=Jet Propulsion Laboratory |publisher=NASA |date=2017 |accessdate=2016-12-22 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CALnasa&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/station/research/news/cold_atom_lab/ |title=Cold Atom Laboratory Creates Atomic Dance |work=NASA News |date=26 September 2014 |accessdate=2015-05-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Physics}}
{{Div col|colwidth=22em}}
* [[Absolute hot]]
* [[Charles's law]]
* [[Heat]]
* [[International Temperature Scale of 1990]]
* [[Orders of magnitude (temperature)]]
* [[Planck temperature]]
* [[Thermodynamic temperature]]
* [[Triple point]]
* [[Ultracold atom]]
* [[Kinetic energy]]
* [[Entropy]]
{{colend}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book|author=Herbert B. Callen|title=Thermodynamics|chapter-url=https://archive.org/details/thermodynamicsin00call|chapter-url-access=registration|chapter=Chapter 10|location=New York|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|year=1960|oclc=535083|isbn=978-0-471-13035-2}}
* {{cite book|author=Herbert B. Callen|title=Thermodynamics and an Introduction to Thermostatistics|edition=Second| location=New York|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|year=1985|isbn= 978-0-471-86256-7}}
* {{cite book|author=E.A. Guggenheim|title=Thermodynamics: An Advanced Treatment for Chemists and Physicists|edition=Fifth|location=Amsterdam|publisher=North Holland Publishing|year=1967|oclc=324553|isbn=978-0-444-86951-7}}
* {{cite book|author=George Stanley Rushbrooke|title=Introduction to Statistical Mechanics|url=https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.476050|location=Oxford|publisher=Clarendon Press|year=1949|oclc=531928}}

==External links==
* [https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/zero/ &quot;Absolute zero&quot;]: a two part ''[[Nova (American TV series)|NOVA]]'' episode [[List of NOVA episodes#Season 35: 2007–2008|originally aired January 2008]]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080509100512/http://www.pa.msu.edu/~sciencet/ask_st/012992.html &quot;What is absolute zero?&quot;] ''Lansing State Journal''

{{DEFAULTSORT:Absolute Zero}}
[[Category:Cold]]
[[Category:Cryogenics]]
[[Category:Temperature]]</text>
      <sha1>t8jnbexsiosvxpvmmxwgclz20fpil36</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
