  <page>
    <title>Politics of Bulgaria</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3670</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940884264</id>
      <parentid>939628158</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-15T06:10:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DemonDays64</username>
        <id>34607323</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Updated</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Political system of Bulgaria}}
{{Politics of Bulgaria}}

The '''politics of Bulgaria''' take place in a framework of a [[parliamentary system|parliamentary]] [[representative democracy|representative democratic]] [[republic]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vks.bg/english/vksen_p04_01.htm Constitution of the Republic of Bulgaria] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140311164232/http://www.vks.bg/english/vksen_p04_01.htm |date=2014-03-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt; whereby the [[Prime Minister of Bulgaria|Prime minister]] is the [[head of government]], and of a [[multi-party system]].&lt;ref name=&quot;LCCS Government&quot;&gt;Bulgaria Library of Congress Country Study, ''Government and politics - overview'', p. 16&lt;/ref&gt; [[Executive power]] is exercised by the government. [[Legislative power]] is vested in both the [[Forms of government|government]] and the [[National Assembly of Bulgaria|National Assembly]]. The [[Judiciary]] is independent of the executive and the legislature.

After 1989, after forty-five years of single party system, Bulgaria had an unstable party system, dominated by democratic parties and opposition to socialists - the [[Union of Democratic Forces (Bulgaria)|Union of Democratic Forces]] and several personalistic parties and the post-communist [[Bulgarian Socialist Party]] or its creatures,  which emerged for a short period of time in the past decade, personalistic parties could be seen as the governing [[Simeon Saxe-Coburg-Gotha|Simeon II]]'s [[NDSV]] party and [[Boyko Borisov]]'s [[GERB]] party.

Bulgaria has generally good [[freedom of speech]] and [[human rights]] records as reported by the US Library of Congress Federal Research Division in 2006,&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| author = Library of Congress – Federal Research Division
| authorlink = Federal Research Division
| title = Country Profile: Bulgaria
| url = http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/profiles/Bulgaria.pdf
| publisher = Library of Congress
| pages = '''18''', 23
| format = PDF
|date=October 2006
| accessdate = 4 September 2009
| quote = Mass Media: In 2006 Bulgaria’s print and broadcast media generally were considered unbiased, although the government dominated broadcasting through the state-owned Bulgarian National Television (BNT) and Bulgarian National Radio (BNR) and print news dissemination through the largest press agency, the Bulgarian Telegraph Agency. [...]Human Rights: In the early 2000s, Bulgaria '''generally has been rated highly on the issue of human rights'''. However, some exceptions exist. Although the media have a record of unbiased reporting, Bulgaria’s lack of specific legislation protecting the media from state interference is a theoretical weakness.
}}{{US government sources}}
&lt;/ref&gt; while [[Freedom House]] listed it as &quot;free&quot; in 2011, giving it scores of 2 for political rights and 2 for civil liberties.&lt;ref&gt;
– [http://www.freedomhouse.org/template.cfm?page=22&amp;year=2008&amp;country=7361 Bulgaria country report for 2008], freedomhouse.org
&lt;/ref&gt; However, in 2014, there is some concern that the proposed new Penal Code would limit freedom of the press and assembly,&lt;ref&gt;https://online.wsj.com/news/articles/SB10001424052702304856504579336590405697378&lt;/ref&gt; and as a consequence freedom of speech. {{Democracy Index rating|Bulgaria|flawed democracy|2019}}

== Developments since 1990 ==

=== Parliamentary ===
After the fall of the communism in 1989, the [[Bulgarian Communist Party|former communist party]] was restructured and succeeded by the [[Bulgarian Socialist Party]] (BSP), which won the first post-communist elections for the Constitutional Assembly in [[Bulgarian Constitutional Assembly election, 1990|1990]] with a small majority. Meanwhile, [[Zhelyu Zhelev]], a communist-era dissident from the new democratic party - [[Union of Democratic Forces (Bulgaria)|Union of Democratic Forces]] (abbreviated in Bulgarian as SDS), was elected President by the Assembly in 1990. In the first years after the change of regime, Bulgarian politics had to (re)establish the foundations of a democratic society in the country after nearly fifty years of de facto totalitarian communism. The so-called period of transition (from a Soviet socialist model to an economic structure focused on development through economic growth) began in the early 1990s. The politics of Bulgaria was aimed at joining the European Union and the NATO fold, as the alliances were recognised to have political agendas similar to the goals of the new Bulgarian democracy.

In contemporary Bulgaria, the government and its leader - the Prime Minister, have more political influence and significance than the President. Thus, the parliamentary elections set the short-term social and political environment in the country since the cabinet (chosen by the Prime Minister and approved by the parliament) decides how the country is governed while the President can only make suggestions and impose vetoes.

In the first parliamentary elections held under the new [[constitution of Bulgaria]], in [[Bulgarian parliamentary election, 1991|October 1991]], the [[Union of Democratic Forces (Bulgaria)|Union of Democratic Forces]] (SDS) party won a plurality of the seats, having won 110 out of the 240 seats, and created a cabinet alone with the support of the [[Movement for Rights and Freedoms]] — a liberal party  (in Bulgarian abbreviated: DPS) which is widely perceived as a party of the ethnic Turks minority in Bulgaria. Yet, their government collapsed in late 1992, and was succeeded by a technocratic team put forward by the [[Bulgarian Socialist Party]] (BSP), which served until 1994 when it also collapsed. The President dissolved the government and appointed a provisional one to serve until early parliamentary elections could be held in December.

BSP won convincingly these elections in [[Bulgarian parliamentary election, 1994|December 1994]] with a majority of 125 seats out of the 240. Due to the severe economic crisis in Bulgaria during their government, BSP's cabinet collapsed and in 1997 a caretaker cabinet was appointed by the President, again, to serve until early parliamentary elections could be held in April 1997.

The [[Bulgarian parliamentary election, 1997|April 1997]] elections resulted in a landslide victory for the SDS, winning a majority of 137 seats in parliament, and allowing them to form the [[Kostov Government|next government]]. This proved to be the first post-communist government that did not collapse and served its full 4-year term until 2001.

In [[Bulgarian parliamentary election, 2001|2001]], the former monarch of Bulgaria [[Simeon Saxe-Coburg-Gotha]] returned to power, this time as Prime Minister with his [[National Movement Simeon II]] (in Bulgarian abbreviated: NDSV), having won half (120) of the seats. His party entered a [[Sakskoburggotski Government|coalition]] with the DPS and invited two functionaries of the BSP (who sat as independents). In opposition were the two previously governing parties - the Socialist Party and the Union of Democratic Forces. In the four years in opposition the SDS suffered the defection of numerous splinter groups. The ruling party NDSV itself [[Sakskoburggotski Government#Changes on February 23, 2005|ruptured]] into a pro-right core and a pro-liberal [[New Time (Bulgarian political party)|fringe]] group. Bulgaria entered [[NATO]] in 2004.

In the aftermath, the BSP won the parliamentary elections in [[Bulgarian parliamentary election, 2005|2005]] with 82 out of the 240 seats, but as it didn't get the majority of the seats, a [[Stanishev Government|coalition government]] was formed by the three biggest parties - BSP, NDSV and DPS. The elections also put in parliament some of the right-wing parties, as well as the extreme-right nationalist coalition led by the party [[Attack (political party)|Ataka]] as an answer to the former coalition government of NDSV with DPS. Bulgarian entered the [[European Union]] in 2007.

In the parliamentary elections of [[Bulgarian parliamentary election, 2009|2009]], the centre-right party of the mayor of [[Sofia]], [[GERB]], won with 117 seats. The party formed a [[First Borisov Government|minority government]] with the support of the right-wing parties. Once the governing party - the [[National Movement Simeon II]] did not amass enough votes to enter the parliament. The austerity measures required in the stagnation of the [[Financial crisis of 2007–08|Global Financial Crisis]] led to [[2013 Bulgarian protests against the Borisov cabinet|massive protests]] and the resignation of the cabinet in early 2013, months before the end of GERB's term.

In the early [[Bulgarian parliamentary election, 2013|elections]] the former leading party GERB received highest vote from the people. This was the first time since 1989 that a ruling party was re-elected; in the past painful and unpopular reforms had to be implemented. However, as GERB received only 97 of the 240 seats, and failed to make a coalition, they refused the mandate, handing it down to the next party BSP. The socialist party chose the non-party former Minister of Finance [[Plamen Oresharski]] to form a [[Oresharski Government|cabinet]]. His cabinet was supported by the BSP and the DPS, opposed by GERB, while Ataka was absent.

Only two weeks after its initial formation the Oresharski government came under criticism and had to deal with [[2013–14 Bulgarian protests against the Oresharski cabinet|large-scale protests]] some with more than 11 000 participants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Bulgarians protest government of 'oligarchs'|url=http://www.dw.de/bulgarians-protest-government-of-oligarchs/a-16909751|accessdate=30 March 2014|newspaper=Deutsche Welle|date=26 June 2013|author=Seiler Bistra|author2=Emiliyan Lilov}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of the main reasons for these protests was the controversial appointment of media mogul [[Delyan Peevski]] as a chief of the National Security State Agency.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Birth of a civil society|url=https://www.economist.com/news/europe/21586571-will-bulgarians-daily-protests-have-lasting-impact-birth-civil-society|accessdate=30 March 2014|newspaper=The Economist|date=21 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The protests continued over the lifetime of the Oresharski government. In all, the government survived 5 [[vote of confidence|votes of no-confidence]] before voluntarily resigning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Timeline of Oresharski's Cabinet: A Government in Constant Jeopardy|url=http://www.novinite.com/articles/162221/Timeline+of+Oresharski%27s+Cabinet%3A+A+Government+in+Constant+Jeopardy|website=Novinite.com|publisher=Sofia News Agency|accessdate=29 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following an agreement from the three largest parties (GERB, BSP and DPS) to hold early parliamentary elections for 5 October 2014,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=President Plevneliev Urges Outgoing Parliament to Review Budget|url=http://www.novinite.com/articles/161878/President+Plevneliev+Urges+Outgoing+Parliament+to+Review+Budget|website=Novinite.com|publisher=Sofia News Agency|accessdate=9 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; the cabinet agreed to resign by the end of July,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Bulgarian Gov't to Resign between July 23, 25 - PM Oresharski|url=http://www.novinite.com/articles/161825/Bulgarian+Gov%27t+to+Resign+between+July+23%2C+25+-+PM+Oresharski|website=Novinite.com|publisher=Sofia News Agency|accessdate=9 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; with the resignation of the cabinet becoming a fact on 23 July 2014.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Bulgaria's PM Plamen Oresharski Resigns|url=http://www.novinite.com/articles/162217/Bulgaria%27s+PM+Plamen+Oresharski+Resigns|website=Novinite.com|publisher=Sofia News Agency|accessdate=25 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The next day parliament voted 180-8 (8 abstained and 44 were absent) to accept the government's resignation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Bulgarian Parliament Approves Government Resignation|url=http://www.novinite.com/articles/162218/Bulgarian+Parliament+Approves+Government+%3Cb%3EResignation%3C/b%3E|website=Novinite.com|publisher=Sofia News Agency|accessdate=25 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the vote, President Plevneliev offered the mandate to GERB to try and form government, but it was refused.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=GERB Leader Boiko Borisov Returns Mandate|url=http://www.novinite.com/articles/162247/GERB+Leader+Boiko+Borisov+Returns+Mandate|website=Novinite.com|publisher=Sofia News Agency|accessdate=25 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The next day the BSP returned the mandate as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Bulgarian Socialist Party Returns Mandate|url=http://www.novinite.com/articles/162268/Bulgarian+Socialist+Party+Returns+Mandate|website=Novinite.com|publisher=Sofia News Agency|accessdate=25 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 30 July, the DPS refused the mandate as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Bulgaria's 3rd Biggest Party, DPS, Rejects Mandate to Form Govt|url=http://www.novinite.com/articles/162370/Bulgaria%27s+3rd+Biggest+Party%2C+DPS%2C+Rejects+Mandate+to+Form+Govt|website=Novinite.com|publisher=Sofia News Agency|accessdate=30 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Finally, on 6 August, a [[Bliznashki Government|caretaker government]] led by [[Georgi Bliznashki]] was sworn into office and the Oresharski government was officially dissolved.

As agreed, [[Bulgarian parliamentary election, 2014|parliamentary elections]] were held on 5 October 2014 to elect the 43rd [[National Assembly (Bulgaria)|National Assembly]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Sofia News Agency&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Bulgaria's 42nd Parliament Dissolved, Elections on October 5|url=http://www.novinite.com/articles/162542/Bulgaria%27s+42nd+Parliament+Dissolved%2C+Elections+on+October+5|website=Novinite.com|publisher=Sofia News Agency|accessdate=9 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[GERB]] remained the largest party, winning 84 of the 240 seats with around a third of the vote. A total of eight parties won seats, the first time since the beginning of democratic elections in 1990 that more than seven parties entered parliament.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Petrov|first1=Angel|title=Bulgaria's Grand Parliament Chessboard Might Be Both Ailment and Cure|url=http://www.novinite.com/articles/163898/Bulgaria%27s+Grand+Parliament+Chessboard+Might+Be+Both+Ailment+and+Cure|website=Novinite.com|publisher=Sofia News Agency|accessdate=7 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; After being tasked by [[List of heads of state of Bulgaria|President]] [[Rosen Plevneliev]] to form a government, Borisov's GERB [[Second Borisov Government|formed a coalition]] with the [[Reformist Bloc]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Bulgaria: EPP President welcomes new coalition government led by Boyko Borissov (EN+BG) |url=http://www.epp.eu/bulgaria-epp-president-welcomes-new-coalition-government-led-boyko-borissov-enbg |website=http://www.epp.eu/ |accessdate=13 November 2014 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141113184541/http://www.epp.eu/bulgaria-epp-president-welcomes-new-coalition-government-led-boyko-borissov-enbg |archivedate=November 13, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Bulgarian parties approve coalition agreement, cabinet|url=http://www.euractiv.com/sections/elections/bulgarian-parties-agree-coalition-agreement-cabinet-309849|website=http://www.euractiv.com/|publisher=EurActiv|accessdate=13 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=GERB and Reformist block finally sign a coalition agreement, the new cabinet to be voted today|url=http://www.ffbh.bg/en/news/gerb-and-reformist-block-finally-sign-a-coalition-agreement-the-new-cabinet-to-be-voted-today|website=www.ffbh.bg|publisher=FFBH|accessdate=13 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; had a partnership agreement for the support of the [[Alternative for Bulgarian Revival]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.novinite.com/articles/164583/Bulgaria's+GERB+Party+Signs+Partnership+Deal+with+Left-Wing+ABV Bulgaria's GERB Party Signs Partnership Deal with Left-Wing ABV]&lt;/ref&gt; and also had the outside support of the [[Patriotic Front (Bulgaria)|Patriotic Front]]. The cabinet of twenty ministers was approved by a majority of 136-97 (with one abstention).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Bulgarian MPs Approve New Cabinet, Ministers Sworn In|url=http://www.novinite.com/articles/164611/Bulgarian+MPs+Approve+New+Cabinet%2C+Ministers+Sworn+In|website=Novinite.com|publisher=Sofia News Agency|accessdate=7 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Borisov was then chosen as prime minister by an even larger vote of 149-85.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Bulgaria's Parliament Approves New Government|url=http://abcnews.go.com/International/wireStory/bulgarias-parliament-approves-government-26753557|website=abcnews.go.com|publisher=ABC News Internet Ventures|accessdate=7 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Borisov become the first person to be elected twice as Prime Minister in the [[History of Bulgaria since 1989|recent history of Bulgaria]]. With the support of the coalition partner (the Reformist Bloc) members of the parties in the Bloc ([[Democrats for a Strong Bulgaria|Democrats for a Strong Bulgaria (DSB)]], [[Union of Democratic Forces (Bulgaria)|Union of Democratic Forces (SDS)]], [[Bulgaria for Citizens Movement|Bulgaria for Citizens Movement (DBG)]] and [[Bulgarian Agrarian National Union|Bulgarian Agrarian National Union (BZNS)]]) were chosen for Minister positions. The vice chairman of the [[Alternative for Bulgarian Revival]] party [[Ivaylo Kalfin]] was voted for Depute Prime Minister and Minister of Labor and Social Policy.

=== Presidential ===
In 1992 Zhelev won Bulgaria's first presidential [[Bulgarian presidential election, 1992|elections]] and served as President until 1997. The [[Bulgarian presidential election, 1996|second]] President was another member of the Union of Democratic Forces - [[Petar Stoyanov]], who served until 2002. In [[Bulgarian presidential election, 2001|2001]] leader of the [[Bulgarian Socialist Party]] - [[Georgi Parvanov]] defeated Stoyanov and took office in 2002 and served until 2012; becoming the only president to be reelected after his successful [[Bulgarian presidential election, 2006|2006]] campaign. In [[Bulgarian presidential election, 2011|2011]] GERB candidate [[Rosen Plevneliev]] was elected to serve as President from 2012 until January, 2017.

== Executive branch ==
The [[president of Bulgaria]] is directly elected for a 5-year term with the right to one re-election. The president serves as the [[head of state]] and commander in chief of the armed forces. The President's main duties are to schedule elections and referendums, represent Bulgaria abroad, conclude international treaties, and head the Consultative Council for National Security. The President may return legislation to the National Assembly for further debate—a kind of veto—but the legislation can be passed again by an absolute majority vote.

The Council of Ministers is the principal organ of the executive branch. It is usually formed by the majority party in Parliament, if one exists, or by the largest party in Parliament along with coalition partners. Chaired by the Prime Minister, it is responsible for carrying out state policy, managing the state budget, and maintaining law and order. The Council must resign if the National Assembly passes a vote of no confidence in the Council or the Prime Minister or rejects a vote of confidence.
The current [[Government of Bulgaria|government]] is a coalition between the center-right GERB party and the populist nationalist United Patriots.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.politico.eu/article/bulgarias-borisov-is-back-but-coalition-may-be-shaky/|title=Bulgaria’s Borisov is back — but coalition may be shaky|last=GEORGIEV|first=OGNYAN|date=|website=Politico.EU|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Legislative branch ==
[[File:National Assembly of Bulgaria Sofia TB.jpg|thumb|350px|The National Assembly]]
The Bulgarian [[unicameral]] [[parliament]], the National Assembly or [[Narodno Sabranie]], consists of 240 deputies who are elected for 4-year-terms by popular vote. The votes are for party or coalition lists of candidates for each of the 28 administrative divisions. A party or coalition must garner a minimum of 4% of the vote in order to enter parliament. Parliament is responsible for enactment of laws, approval of the budget, scheduling of presidential elections, selection and dismissal of the [[prime Minister of Bulgaria|prime minister]] and other ministers, declaration of war, deployment of troops outside of Bulgaria, and ratification of international treaties and agreements.

== Elections ==
{{main|Elections in Bulgaria}}
[[File:BG Parliamentary 2013 pie EN.png|right|400px|thumb|Distribution of votes by constituency]]
{{Bulgarian parliamentary election, 2013}}
{{Bulgarian presidential election, 2016}}

== Judicial branch ==
The Bulgarian judicial system consists of regional, district and appeal courts, as well as a [[Supreme Court of Cassation of Bulgaria|Supreme Court of Cassation]] and one Specialized Criminal Court.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.spcc.bg&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, there is a [[Supreme Administrative Court of Bulgaria|Supreme Administrative Court]] and a system of military courts. The Presidents of the Supreme Court of Cassation and the Supreme Administrative Court as well as the [[Prosecutor General]] are elected by a qualified majority of two-thirds from all the members of the Supreme Judicial Council and are appointed by the President of the Republic. The Supreme Judicial Council is in charge of the self-administration and organisation of the Judiciary.

A qualified majority of two-thirds of the membership of the Supreme Judicial Council elects the Presidents of the Supreme Court of Cassation and of the Supreme Administrative Court, as well as the Prosecutor General, from among its members; the President of the Republic then appoints those elected.

The Supreme Judicial Council has charge of the self-administration and organization of the Judiciary.

The [[Constitutional Court of Bulgaria]] supervises the review of the constitutionality of laws and statutes brought before it, as well as the compliance of these laws with international treaties that the Government has signed. Parliament elects the 12 members of the Constitutional Court by a two-thirds majority. The members serve for a nine-year term.

== Administrative divisions ==
The territory of the Republic of Bulgaria is divided into provinces and municipalities. In all Bulgaria has 28 provinces, each headed by a provincial governor appointed by the government. In addition, there are 263 municipalities.

== International relations ==
{|
|-
|
* [[Agence de Coopération Culturelle et Technique|ACCT]]
* [[Australia Group]]
* [[Organization of the Black Sea Economic Cooperation|BSEC]]
* [[Council of Europe|CE]]
* [[Central European Initiative|CEI]]
* [[CERN]]
* [[Euro-Atlantic Partnership Council|EAPC]]
* [[European Bank for Reconstruction and Development|EBRD]]
* [[United Nations Economic Commission for Europe|ECE]]
* [[European Union|EU]]
* [[Food and Agriculture Organization|FAO]]
* [[Group of 9|G-9]]
* [[International Atomic Energy Agency|IAEA]]
* [[International Bank for Reconstruction and Development|IBRD]]
* [[International Civil Aviation Organization|ICAO]]
* [[International Criminal Court|ICCt]]
* [[International Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement|ICRM]]
* [[International Finance Corporation|IFC]]
* [[International Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement|IFRCS]]
* [[International Hydrographic Organization|IHO]] (pending member)
* [[International Labour Organization|ILO]]
* [[International Monetary Fund|IMF]]
* [[International Maritime Organization|IMO]]
* [[Interpol (organization)|Interpol]]
* [[IOC]]
* [[International Organization for Migration|IOM]]
* [[International Organization for Standardization|ISO]]
* [[International Telecommunication Union|ITU]]
* [[International Trade Union Confederation|ITUC]]
|
* [[Non-Aligned Movement|NAM]] (guest)
* [[NATO]]
* [[Nuclear Suppliers Group|NSG]]
* [[Organization of American States|OAS]] (observer)
* [[Organisation for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons|OPCW]]
* [[Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe|OSCE]]
* [[Permanent Court of Arbitration|PCA]]
* [[Partnership for Peace|PFP]]
* [[Southeast European Cooperative Initiative|SECI]]
* [[United Nations|UN]]
* [[United Nations Conference on Trade and Development|UNCTAD]]
* [[UNESCO]]
* [[United Nations Industrial Development Organization|UNIDO]]
* [[United Nations Mission in Ethiopia and Eritrea|UNMEE]]
* [[United Nations Mission in Bosnia and Herzegovina|UNMIBH]]
* [[United Nations Interim Administration Mission in Kosovo|UNMIK]]
* [[United Nations Mission of Observers in Prevlaka|UNMOP]]
* [[Universal Postal Union|UPU]]
* [[World Customs Organization|WCO]]
* [[Western European Union|WEU]] (associate partner)
* [[World Federation of Trade Unions|WFTU]]
* [[World Health Organization|WHO]]
* [[World Intellectual Property Organization|WIPO]]
* [[World Meteorological Organization|WMO]]
* [[World Tourism Organization|WToO]]
* [[World Trade Organization|WTrO]]
* [[Zangger Committee|ZC]]
|}

== Other data ==
'''Political pressure groups and leaders:'''
* [[Confederation of Independent Trade Unions of Bulgaria]] or CITUB
* [[Confederation of Labour Podkrepa]]
* numerous regional, ethnic, and national interest groups with various agendas

==See also==

* [[Prime Minister of Bulgaria]]
* [[List of Prime Ministers of Bulgaria]]
* [[List of heads of state of Bulgaria]]
* [[List of ministries of Bulgaria]]
* [[Foreign relations of Bulgaria]]
* [[Flag of Bulgaria]]

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

{{Bulgaria topics}}
{{Politics of Europe}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Politics Of Bulgaria}}
[[Category:Politics of Bulgaria| ]]</text>
      <sha1>8g5lhxsmldztdmnnj4kpa1e1shaqs1u</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
