  <page>
    <title>Politics of Burundi</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3697</id>
    <revision>
      <id>933201153</id>
      <parentid>932533861</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-30T15:09:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GünniX</username>
        <id>237572</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reflist</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{More references|date=August 2008}}
{{Politics of Burundi}}
'''Politics of Burundi''' takes place in a framework of a transitional [[presidential system|presidential]] [[representative democracy|representative democratic]] [[republic]], whereby the [[President of Burundi]] is both [[head of state]] and [[head of government]], and of a [[multi-party system]]. [[Executive power]] is exercised by the government. [[Legislative power]] is vested in both the [[Forms of government|government]] and the two chambers of parliament, the [[Senate of Burundi|Senate]] and the [[National Assembly of Burundi|National Assembly]].

==Political landscape after the civil war==
The political landscape of Burundi has been dominated in recent years by the [[civil war]] and a long [[Peacebuilding|peace process]] and move to [[democracy]].  The current [[President of Burundi]] is [[Pierre Nkurunziza]], a former rebel leader of the [[Hutu]] [[National Council for the Defense of Democracy-Forces for the Defense of Democracy]] who was [[Burundian presidential election, 2005|elected unopposed]] as the new [[Rulers and heads of state of Burundi|President of Burundi]] by the [[Parliament of Burundi|parliament]] on 19 August 2005.  Nkurunziza was the first president chosen through democratic means since the start of the [[Burundi Civil War|civil war]] in 1993 and was sworn in on 26 August, replacing transitional president [[Domitien Ndayizeye]].

In November 1995, the presidents of [[Burundi]], [[Rwanda]], [[Uganda]], and [[Zaire]] (currently [[Democratic Republic of Congo]]) announced a regional initiative for a negotiated peace in Burundi facilitated by former Tanzanian President [[Julius Nyerere]]. In July 1996, former Burundian President [[Pierre Buyoya|Buyoya]] returned to power in a [[1996 Burundian coup d'état|bloodless coup]]. He declared himself president of a transitional republic, even as he suspended the National Assembly, banned opposition groups, and imposed a nationwide curfew. Widespread condemnation of the coup ensued, and regional countries imposed economic sanctions pending a return to a constitutional government. Buyoya agreed in 1996 to liberalize political parties. Nonetheless, fighting between the army and [[Hutu]] militias continued. In June 1998, Buyoya promulgated a transitional constitution and announced a partnership between the government and the opposition-led National Assembly. After facilitator Julius Nyerere's death in October 1999, the regional leaders appointed [[Nelson Mandela]] as [[Facilitator]] of the [[Arusha]] peace process. Under Mandela the peace process has revived and important progress has taken place.

In April 2015 the [[2015 Burundian unrest]] broke out after the ruling party announced President [[Pierre Nkurunziza]] would seek a third term in office. Protests in the capital lasted over a week, and while President Nkurunziza was in Tanzania for talks at resolving the situation, Major General [[Godefroid Niyombare]] declared a coup, leading to gun battles in the capital for control of key locations.

Elections are scheduled to take place in 2020 (see main article [[2020 Burundian general election]]). Despite concerns that these elections would be severely compromised&lt;ref&gt;https://www.africanews.com/2019/09/05/un-outlines-8-reasons-why-2020-burundi-vote-is-risky&lt;/ref&gt;, following the announcement that the President would not seek reelection, the opposition announced that they would be taking part in the election&lt;ref&gt;https://www.voanews.com/africa/burundis-exiled-main-opposition-alliance-plans-participate-2020-vote&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Executive branch==
{{office-table}}
|[[Rulers and heads of state of Burundi|President]]
|[[Pierre Nkurunziza]]
|[[National Council for the Defense of Democracy-Forces for the Defense of Democracy|CNDD-FDD]]
|26 August 2005
|-
|rowspan=2 valign=top|[[Vice-President of Burundi|Vice-presidents]]
|[[Thérence Sinunguruza]]
|[[Union for National Progress|UPRONA]]
|29 August 2010
|-
|[[Gervais Rufyikiri]]
|
|29 August 2010 
|}
The president is elected by the people. He nominates two vice-presidents, who form together with the [[Ministers of the Burundian Government|Council of Ministers]] the executive branch.

==Legislative branch==
The '''[[National Assembly of Burundi|National Assembly]]''' (''Assemblée nationale'') has 118 members, elected for a five-year term by [[proportional representation]] with a 2% barrier. The '''[[Senate of Burundi|Senate]]''' (''Sénat'') has 49 members, elected for a five-year term by electoral colleges of communal councilors. Extra seats in both chambers can be added to ensure that ethnic and gender quotas are met. Burundi has a [[multi-party]] system, with two or three strong parties and a third party that is electorally successful. Parties are usually based on ethnic background.

==Political parties and elections==
{{elect|List of political parties in Burundi|Elections in Burundi}}

==Administrative divisions==
Burundi has 18 provinces: [[Bubanza Province|Bubanza]], [[Bujumbura Mairie Province|Bujumbura Mairie]], [[Bujumbura Rural Province|Bujumbura Rural]], [[Bururi Province|Bururi]], [[Cankuzo Province|Cankuzo]], [[Cibitoke Province|Cibitoke]], [[Gitega Province|Gitega]], [[Karuzi Province|Karuzi]], [[Kayanza Province|Kayanza]], [[Kirundo Province|Kirundo]], [[Makamba Province|Makamba]], [[Muramvya Province|Muramvya]], [[Muyinga Province|Muyinga]], [[Mwaro Province|Mwaro]], [[Ngozi Province|Ngozi]], [[Rutana Province|Rutana]], [[Rumonge Province|Rumonge]] and [[Ruyigi Province|Ruyigi]].

==International relations==
Burundi is member of ACCT, ACP, AfDB, CCC, CEEAC, CEPGL, ECA, FAO, G-77, IBRD, ICAO, ICRM, IDA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, ILO, IMF, Intelsat (nonsignatory user), Interpol, IOC, ITU, NAM, OAU, OPCW, [[Port Management Association of Eastern and Southern Africa|PMAESA]], UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNIDO, UPU, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WToO, WTrO.

== See also ==

{{Empty section|date=August 2019}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
*[https://archive.is/20130414211600/http://report.globalintegrity.org/burundi Global Integrity Report: Burundi] reports on Burundi's anti-corruption efforts.

{{Africa in topic|Politics of}}
{{Burundi topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Politics Of Burundi}}
[[Category:Politics of Burundi| ]]</text>
      <sha1>7xb6gkky50xif7eaex7g1krhiyi80kl</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
