  <page>
    <title>Politics of Burkina Faso</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3679</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940884318</id>
      <parentid>924549904</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-15T06:10:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DemonDays64</username>
        <id>34607323</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Updated</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Political system of Burkina Faso}}
{{Use American English|date=January 2019}}{{Short description|Politics and government of the country
}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2019}}{{Multiple issues|{{Update|inaccurate=yes|date=September 2015}}
{{More citations needed|date=December 2016}}
{{Missing information|the political history of Burkina Faso before 1990|date=January 2018}}}}

{{Politics of Burkina Faso}}
The '''Politics of Burkina Faso''' takes place in a framework of a [[Semi-presidential system|semi-presidential]] [[republic]], whereby the [[Prime Minister of Burkina Faso]] is the [[head of government]], and of a [[multi-party system]]. The [[President of Burkina Faso]] is the [[head of state]]. [[Executive power]] is exercised by both the President and the Government. [[Legislative power]] is vested in both the [[Forms of government|government]] and parliament. The party system was dominated by the [[Congress for Democracy and Progress]] (CDP) until the [[2014 Burkinabé uprising]]. Since then, the CDP has lost influence. The [[Judiciary]] is independent of the executive and the legislature. {{Democracy Index rating|Burkina Faso|hybrid regime|2019}}

==Political history==
[[File:Blaise Compaoré 2014 White House.png|thumb|President [[Blaise Compaoré]] ruled Burkina Faso from a coup d'état in 1987 to his resignation in 2014.]]
In 1990, the [[Popular Front (Burkina Faso)|Popular Front]] held its first National Congress, which formed a committee to draft a national constitution. The constitution was approved by referendum in 1991. In 1992, [[Blaise Compaoré]] was elected president, running unopposed after the opposition boycotted the election because of Compaoré's refusal to accede to demands of the opposition such as a Sovereign National Conference to set modalities. The opposition did participate in the following year's legislative elections, in which the [[ODP/MT]] won a majority of the seats contested for.

The government of the Fourth Republic includes a strong presidency, a prime minister, a Council of Ministers presided over by the president, a National Assembly, and the judiciary. The legislature and judiciary are independent but remain susceptible to outside influence.

In 1995, Burkina held its first multiparty municipal elections since it gained independence. The president's ODP/MT won over 1,100 of some 1,700 councilor seats being contested.

In February 1996, the ruling ODP/MT merged with several small opposition parties to form the [[Congress for Democracy and Progress]] (CDP). This effectively co-opted much of what little viable opposition to Compaoré existed. The remaining opposition parties regrouped in preparation for 1997 legislative elections and the 1998 presidential election. The 1997 legislative elections, which international observers pronounced to be substantially free, fair, and transparent, resulted in a large CDP majority—101 to 111 seats.

==Government==

===Executive branch===
{{Office-table}}
|[[List of heads of state of Burkina Faso|President]]
|[[Roch Marc Christian Kaboré]]
|[[People's Movement for Progress]]
|29 December 2015
|-
|[[List of heads of government of Burkina Faso|Prime Minister]]
|[[Christophe Joseph Marie Dabiré]]
|[[People's Movement for Progress]]
|24 January 2019
|}

The president is elected by popular vote for a five-year term and may serve up to two terms. The prime minister is appointed by the president with the consent of the legislature.  The constitution of June 2, 1991, established a semi-presidential government with a parliament ({{Lang-fr|Assemblée}}) which can be dissolved by the President of the Republic, who is elected for a term of 5 years. The year 2000 saw a constitutional amendment reducing the presidential term from 7 to 5 years, which was enforced during the 2005 elections. Another change according to the amendment would have prevented sitting president [[Blaise Compaoré]] from being re-elected. However, notwithstanding a challenge by other presidential candidates, in October 2005, the constitutional council ruled that because Compaoré was already a sitting president in 2000, the amendment would not apply to him until the end of his second term in office, thereby clearing the way for his candidacy in [[Burkina Faso presidential elections, 2005|the 2005 election]]. On November 13 Compaoré was reelected in a landslide due to a divided political opposition. In 2010, Compaoré was once again re-elected, and the term limit requirement was held to not apply to him. A proposed constitutional amendment in 2014 would have permitted him to run again, but public resistance led to the [[2014 Burkinabé uprising]], and Compaoré resigned on 31 October 2014. A transitional government headed by President [[Michel Kafondo]] and Prime Minister [[Isaac Zida]] took power for a one-year mandate. Elections were to have been held in October 2015, but members of the [[Regiment of Presidential Security]] launched [[2015 Burkinabé coup d'état|a coup]] on 16 September 2015, detaining President Kafando and Prime Minister Zida. RSP commander [[Gilbert Diendéré]] named himself the head of the new [[military junta]], but popular resistance, backed by army and gendarmerie forces not aligned with the RSP, forced his resignation and the restoration of the transitional government a week later.

===Legislative branch===

According to the constitution, the Parliament  votes on the law, consents to taxation, and controls the actions of the government under provisions of the constitution. The Parliament, which is made up of the National Assembly and Senate, meets each year in two ordinary sessions, each of which may not exceed ninety days. The first session opens on the first Wednesday of March and the second the last Wednesday of September. If either of these days lands on a holiday, the session opens the next first working day. Each chamber of Parliament meets in extraordinary session on request of the President, demand of the Prime Minister, or of an absolute majority of half of the Deputies or Senators on a specific agenda and closes at the completion of said agenda.&lt;ref name=BurkinaFasoConst&gt;{{cite web|title=Constitution of Burkina Faso|url=https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Burkina_Faso_2012.pdf|website=constituteproject.org|accessdate=4 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[National Assembly of Burkina Faso|National Assembly]] (''Assemblée Nationale'') has 111 members, named Deputies, and are elected for a five-year term by [[proportional representation]].

The [[Senate of Burkina Faso|Senate]], as described in the Constitution of Burkina Faso, would consist of representatives from local government divisions, customary and religious authorities, workers, employers, Burkinabes abroad and people appointed by the President of Burkina Faso and serve a term of six years. The constitution requires that anyone elected or appointed must be 45 years old by the day of the ballot.&lt;ref name=BurkinaFasoConst /&gt;

In May 2013, then President Compaoré announced the establishment of a new Senate with 89 members, 29 of which would be selected by the president themselves, and the rest appointed by local officials.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Burkina Faso - Country report|url=https://freedomhouse.org/report/freedom-world/2014/burkina-faso#.VdSRA5ZvKxM.cleanprint|website=freedomhouse.org|publisher=Freedom House|accessdate=4 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; With Senate elections being held in July 2013, government opposition groups warned against a legislative body with a majority of handpicked sympathizers by the president. Compaoré was successful in appointing 1/3rd of the Senate, prompting protesters rallying in the streets of [[Bobo-Dioulasso]] and the capital [[Ouagadougou]] to protest the establishment of the Senate, which has since been postponed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Barrios|first1=Cristina|last2=Luengo-Cabrera|first2=José|title=Burkina Faso: a crisis foretold|url=http://www.iss.europa.eu/uploads/media/Alert_46_Burkina_Faso.pdf|website=European Union Institute for Security Studies|publisher=European Union Institute for Security Studies|accessdate=4 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Presidents of both the Senate and National Assembly are elected for the duration of the legislator by an absolute majority of half the chamber in the first round of voting, or a simple majority in the second round. Their functions can be terminated during the course of a legislature at the demand of two-fifths and a vote of the absolute majority of the members of the Assembly. In the case of vacancy of the presidency of either chamber of Parliament by death, resignation, or other reason, said chamber elects a new President by the same method. Each chamber has financial autonomy, with the President of the said chamber managing the credits allocated to them for the functioning of the chamber, but with a vote of the absolute majority, the chamber can dismiss the President for incompetence in managing finances.&lt;ref name=BurkinaFasoConst /&gt;

Unless discovered ''[[in flagrante delicto]]'', any member of Parliament can only be prosecuted or arrested in a penal or criminal matter with the authorization of at least one-third members of the chamber which they reside.&lt;ref name=BurkinaFasoConst /&gt;

==Political parties and elections==
{{Elect|List of political parties in Burkina Faso|Elections in Burkina Faso}}

==Political pressure groups==
Burkinabé General Confederation of Labor (CGTB); Burkinabé Movement for Human Rights (HBDHP); Group of 14 February; National Confederation of Burkinabé Workers (CNTB); National Organization of Free Unions (ONSL); watchdog/political action groups throughout the country in both organizations and communities

==Administrative divisions==
Burkina Faso is divided into 13 regions and 45 provinces:

[[Regions of Burkina Faso|Regions]]:
* [[Boucle du Mouhoun Region|Boucle du Mouhoun]], [[Cascades Region|Cascades]], [[Centre Region (Burkina Faso)|Centre]], [[Centre-Est Region|Centre-Est]], [[Centre-Nord Region|Centre-Nord]], [[Centre-Ouest Region|Centre-Ouest]], [[Centre-Sud Region|Centre-Sud]], [[Est Region (Burkina Faso)|Est]], [[Hauts-Bassins Region|Hauts-Bassins]], [[Nord Region (Burkina Faso)|Nord]], [[Plateau-Central Region|Plateau-Central]], [[Sahel Region|Sahel]], [[Sud-Ouest Region (Burkina Faso)|Sud-Ouest]]

[[Provinces of Burkina Faso|Provinces]]: 
*[[Bale Province, Burkina Faso|Balé]], [[Bam Province|Bam]], [[Banwa]], [[Bazega]], [[Bougouriba]], [[Boulgou]], [[Boulkiemde]], [[Comoé Province|Comoé]], [[Ganzourgou]], [[Gnagna]], [[Gourma]], [[Houet]], [[Ioba]], [[Kadiogo]], [[Kenedougou (province)|Kenedougou]], [[Komondjari]], [[Kompienga]], [[Kossi Province|Kossi]], [[Koulpelogo]], [[Kouritenga]], [[Kourweogo]], [[Leraba]], [[Loroum Province|Loroum]], [[Mouhoun Province|Mouhoun]], [[Namentenga]], [[Nahouri]], [[Nayala Province|Nayala]], [[Noumbiel]], [[Oubritenga]], [[Oudalan]], [[Passore]], [[Poni Province|Poni]], [[Sanguie]], [[Sanmatenga]], [[Séno Province|Séno]], [[Sissili]], [[Soum Province|Soum]], [[Sourou Province|Sourou]], [[Tapoa Province|Tapoa]], [[Tuy (province)|Tuy]], [[Yagha]], [[Yatenga]], [[Ziro Province|Ziro]], [[Zondoma]], [[Zoundweogo]]

==International organization participation==
[[Agence de Coopération Culturelle et Technique|ACCT]], [[ACP (Lomé Convention)|ACP]], [[AfDB]], [[African Union|AU]], [[United Nations Economic Commission for Africa|ECA]], [[Economic Community of West African States|ECOWAS]], [[Conseil de l'Entente|Entente]], [[Food and Agriculture Organization|FAO]], [[Group of 77|G-77]], [[International Atomic Energy Agency|IAEA]], [[World Bank|IBRD]], [[International Civil Aviation Organization|ICAO]], [[International Criminal Court|ICC]], [[International Trade Union Confederation|ITUC]], [[International Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement|ICRM]], [[International Development Association|IDA]], [[Islamic Development Bank|IDB]], [[International Fund for Agricultural Development|IFAD]], [[International Finance Corporation|IFC]], [[International Federation of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies|IFRCS]], [[International Labour Organization|ILO]], [[International Monetary Fund|IMF]], [[Intelsat]], [[Interpol (organization)|Interpol]], [[International Olympic Committee|IOC]], [[International Telecommunication Union|ITU]], [[Non-Aligned Movement|NAM]], [[Organization of African Unity|OAU]], [[Organisation of Islamic Cooperation|OIC]], [[Organisation for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons|OPCW]], [[Permanent Court of Arbitration|PCA]], [[United Nations|UN]], [[United Nations Conference on Trade and Development|UNCTAD]], [[United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization|UNESCO]], [[United Nations Industrial Development Organization|UNIDO]], [[Universal Postal Union|UPU]], [[West African Development Bank|WADB]], WADB (regional), [[WAEMU]], [[World Customs Organization|WCO]], [[World Federation of Trade Unions|WFTU]], [[World Health Organization|WHO]], [[World Intellectual Property Organization|WIPO]], [[World Meteorological Organization|WMO]], [[World Tourism Organization|WToO]], [[World Trade Organization|WTrO]]

==International relationships==
The ambassador of Burkina Faso to Canada is [[Juliette Bonkoungou]].

The ambassador of Burkina Faso to Mexico is Jonathan Hodgson

The former ambassador of Burkina Faso to the United States was [[Tertius Zongo]], he left his post when appointed Prime Minister in July 2007; the US Ambassador to Burkina Faso is Andrew Robert Young.

==See also==

* [[2019 Burkina Faso government resignation]]
{{Africa in topic|Politics of}}
{{Burkina Faso topics}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Politics Of Burkina Faso}}
[[Category:Politics of Burkina Faso| ]]</text>
      <sha1>jxsh6xowd73vy17gmg6dmg211c4eji6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
