  <page>
    <title>Geography of Burkina Faso</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3677</id>
    <revision>
      <id>932447662</id>
      <parentid>898586354</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-26T00:52:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead.) #IABot (v2.0</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=February 2013}}
[[Image:Burkina Faso Map.jpg|right|thumb|280px|Map Of Burkina Faso]]
[[File:LocationBurkinaFaso.svg|thumb|Location of Burkina Faso]]
{{MapLibrary|Burkina_sat.png|Burkina Faso}}
[[Image:Burkina Faso Topography.png|thumb|Topography of Burkina Faso]]

[[Burkina Faso]] (formerly Upper Volta) is a landlocked [[Sahel]] country that shares borders with six nations. It lies between the [[Sahara]] desert and the [[Gulf of Guinea]], south of the loop of the [[Niger River]], mostly between latitudes 9° and 15°N (a small area is north of 15°), and longitudes 6°W and 3°E. The land is green in the south, with forests and fruit trees, and desert in the north. Most of central Burkina Faso lies on a [[savanna]] plateau, {{convert|198|-|305|m|ft|0}} above sea level, with fields, brush, and scattered trees. Burkina Faso's game preserves—the most important of which are [[Arli National Park|Arly]], [[Nazinga Game Ranch|Nazinga]], and [[W National Park]]&amp;mdash;contain [[Panthera leo|lion]]s, [[elephant]]s, [[hippopotamus]], [[monkey]]s, [[common warthog]]s, and [[antelope]]s. Previously the endangered [[painted hunting dog]], ''Lycaon pictus'' occurred in Burkina Faso, but, although the last sightings were made in [[Arli National Park]],&lt;ref&gt;C. Michael Hogan. 2009. [http://globaltwitcher.auderis.se/artspec_information.asp?thingid=35993 ''Painted Hunting Dog: Lycaon pictus'', GlobalTwitcher.com, ed. N. Stromberg] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101209234758/http://globaltwitcher.auderis.se/artspec_information.asp?thingid=35993 |date=December 9, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; the species is considered [[Local extinction|extirpated]] from Burkina Faso. 

==Area==
Burkina Faso has a total area of 274,200&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, of which 273,800&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; is land and 400&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; water. Comparatively, it is slightly larger than [[New Zealand]] and [[Colorado]]. Its borders total 3,611&amp;nbsp;km: [[Benin]] 386&amp;nbsp;km, [[Ivory Coast]] 545&amp;nbsp;km, [[Ghana]] 602&amp;nbsp;km, [[Mali]] 1,325&amp;nbsp;km, [[Niger]] 622&amp;nbsp;km, and [[Togo]] 131&amp;nbsp;km. It has no coastline or maritime claims.

=== Extreme points ===
This is a list of the extreme points of [[Burkina Faso]], the points that are farther north, south, east or west than any other location.

* Northernmost point – unnamed location on the border with [[Mali]], [[Sahel Region]]
* Easternmost point – unnamed location on the border with [[Benin]] immediately south of the Burkina Faso-Benin-Niger [[tripoint]], [[Est Region (Burkina Faso)|Est Region]]
* Southernmost point – unnamed location on the border with [[Ivory Coast]] immediately south of the village of [[Kpuere]], [[Sud-Ouest Region, Burkina Faso|Sud-Ouest Region]]
* Westernmost point - the [[tripoint]] with Mali and Ivory Coast, [[Cascades Region]]

==Terrain==
It is made up of two major types of countryside. The larger part of the country is covered by a [[peneplain]], which forms a gently undulating landscape with, in some areas, a few isolated hills, the last vestiges of a Precambrian massif. The southwest of the country, on the other hand, forms a sandstone massif, where the highest peak, [[Ténakourou]], is found at an elevation of {{convert|749|m|ft|abbr=off}}. The massif is bordered by sheer cliffs up to {{convert|150|m|ft|abbr=off|sp=us}} high. The average altitude of Burkina Faso is {{convert|400|m|ft|abbr=off|sp=us}} and the difference between the highest and lowest terrain is no greater than {{convert|600|m|ft|abbr=off}}. Burkina Faso is therefore a relatively flat country. Its elevation extremes are a lowest point at the [[Mouhoun River|Mouhoun]] ([[Black Volta]]) River (200 m) and highest point at [[Tena Kourou]] (749 m).

==Administrative divisions==
[[File:Burkina_Faso_Provinces.png|thumb|200px|Provinces of Burkina Faso]]
[[File:Burkina Faso departments.png|thumb|left|200px|Departments of Burkina Faso]]
The country is divided into [[Regions of Burkina Faso|13 administrative regions]]. These regions encompass [[Provinces of Burkina Faso|45 provinces]] and [[Departments of Burkina Faso|351 departments]].

==Hydrography==
The country owes its former name of Upper Volta to three rivers which cross it: the Black Volta (or Mouhoun), the White Volta (Nakambé) and the Red Volta (Nazinon). The Black Volta is one of the country's only two rivers which flow year-round, the other being the Komoé, which flows to the southwest. The basin of the Niger River also drains 27% of the country's surface.

The Niger's tributaries – the Béli, the Gorouol, the Goudébo and the Dargol – are seasonal streams and flow for only four to six months a year. They still, however, can cause large floods. The country also contains numerous lakes – the principal ones are Tingrela, Bam and Dem. The country contains large ponds, as well, such as Oursi, Béli, Yomboli and Markoye. Water shortages are often a problem, especially in the north of the country.

==Climate==
{{See also|Burkina Faso#Geography and climate}}
[[File:Koppen-Geiger Map BFA present.svg|thumb|250px|Köppen climate classification map of Burkina Faso]]
Burkina Faso has a primarily tropical climate with two very distinct seasons. In the rainy season, the country receives between 600 and 900 millimetres (23.6 and 35.4 in) of rainfall; in the dry season, the [[harmattan]] – a hot dry wind from the Sahara – blows. The rainy season lasts approximately four months, May/June to September, and is shorter in the north of the country. Three climatic zones can be defined: the Sahel, the Sudan-Sahel, and the Sudan-Guinea. The Sahel in the north typically receives less than {{convert|600|mm|in|abbr=off|sp=us}} of rainfall per year and has high temperatures, {{convert|5|–|47|C|F|abbr=off}}.

A relatively dry tropical savanna, the Sahel extends beyond the borders of Burkina Faso, from the Horn of Africa to the Atlantic Ocean, and borders the Sahara to its north and the fertile region of the Sudan to the South. Situated between 11°3' and 13°5' north latitude, the Sudan-Sahel region is a transitional zone with regards to rainfall and temperature. Further to the south, the Sudan-Guinea zone receives more than {{convert|900|mm|in|abbr=off|sp=us}} of rain each year and has cooler average temperatures.

==Resources and environment==
Burkina Faso's natural resources include manganese, limestone, marble, phosphates, pumice, salt and small deposits of [[Mining in Burkina Faso|gold]]. 21.93% of its land is arable, and 0.26% has permanent crops as of 2012. As of 2003, 250&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; were irrigated. Its total renewable water resources as of 2011 were 12.5 m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;{{Clarify|date=December 2015|reason=Should this be &quot;km&quot;? Meters is too small.}}, with a total freshwater withdrawal of 0.72&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;/yr (46% domestic, 3% industrial, 51% agricultural; this amounts to a per-capita withdrawal of 54.99 m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;/yr.

Burkina Faso's fauna and flora are protected in two national parks and several reserves: see [[List of national parks in Africa]], [[Nature reserves of Burkina Faso]].

Recurring [[drought]]s and [[flood]]s are a significant natural hazard.&lt;ref&gt;Heavy floods caused loss of life and widespread damage in 2007 and 2009. See also [[2007 African floods]] and [[2009 West Africa floods#Burkina Faso|2009 West Africa floods]].&lt;/ref&gt; Current environmental issues include: recent droughts and [[desertification]] severely affecting agricultural activities, population distribution, and the economy; [[overgrazing]]; [[soil degradation]]; [[deforestation]].

Burkina Faso is party to the following international environmental agreements: [[Biodiversity]], [[United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change|Climate Change]], [[Desertification]], [[Endangered Species]], [[Hazardous Wastes]], [[Marine Life Conservation]], [[Ozone Layer Protection]], [[Wetlands]]. It has signed, but not ratified, the [[Law of the Sea]] and the [[Nuclear Test Ban]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www4.unfccc.int/ndcregistry/PublishedDocuments/Burkina%20Faso%20First/INDC%20Burkina_ENG.%20version_finale.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.catsg.org/cheetah/04_country-information/North-African-regions/burkina-faso.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[2010 Sahel famine]]
*[[:Category:Treaties of Burkina Faso]]

==Line note references==
{{CIA World Factbook}}
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* Soil Maps of Burkina Faso [https://web.archive.org/web/20070905063706/http://eusoils.jrc.it/esdb_archive/EuDASM/africa/lists/cbf.htm European Digital Archive on the Soil Maps of the world]

{{Geography of Africa}}
{{Africa topic|Climate of}}
{{Burkina Faso topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Geography Of Burkina Faso}}
[[Category:Geography of Burkina Faso| ]]</text>
      <sha1>t74qq24vfs259f3c1fi4zggdud4i6ca</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
