  <page>
    <title>Geography of Botswana</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3613</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943066350</id>
      <parentid>942541249</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T16:34:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kku</username>
        <id>5846</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>link desertification</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{Infobox country geography
|name = Botswana
|map = [[File:Botswana Map.jpg|250px]]&lt;br&gt;[[File:LocationBotswana.svg|240px]]
|map size = 250px
|continent = [[Africa]]
|region = [[Southern Africa]]
|coordinates = {{coord|22|00|S|24|00|E|type:country}}
|area ranking = 48th
|km area = 581730
|percent land = 97.42
|percent water = 2.58
|km coastline = 0
|borders = [[Land borders|Total land borders]]: {{convert|4374.15|km|mi|abbr=on}}&lt;br /&gt;[[Namibia]]: {{convert|1544|km|mi|abbr=on}}&lt;br /&gt;[[South Africa]]: {{convert|1969|km|mi|abbr=on}}&lt;br /&gt;[[Zambia]]: {{convert|0.15|km|mi|abbr=on}}&lt;br /&gt;[[Zimbabwe]]: {{convert|834|km|mi|abbr=on}}
|highest point = [[Tsodilo|Tsodilo Hills]] {{convert|1489|m|ft|0|abbr=on}}
|lowest point = Junction of the [[Limpopo River|Limpopo]] and [[Shashe River]]s {{convert|513|m|ft|0|abbr=on}}
|longest river = 
|largest lake = 
}}
[[File:Botswana map of Köppen climate classification.svg|thumb|300px|Botswana map of Köppen climate classification zones]]
{{MapLibrary|Botswana_sat.png|Botswana}}
[[Image:Botswana Topography.png|thumb|Elevation map of Botswana]]

'''[[Botswana]]''' is a landlocked country located in Southern [[Africa]], north of [[South Africa]].  [[Botswana]] occupies an area of {{Convert|581730|km2|mi2}}, of which {{Convert|566730|km2|mi2|abbr=on}} are land.  Botswana has land boundaries of combined length {{Convert|4347.15|km|mi}}, of which the constituent boundaries are shared with [[Namibia]], for {{Convert|1544|km|mi|abbr=on}}; South Africa {{Convert|1969|km|mi|abbr=on}}; [[Zimbabwe]], {{Convert|834|km|mi|abbr=on}} and [[Zambia]], {{Convert|0.15|km|mi|abbr=on}}.  Much of the population of Botswana is concentrated in the eastern part of the country.

Sunshine totals are high all year round although winter is the sunniest period. The whole country is windy and dusty during the dry season.&lt;ref name=&quot;Landsberg&quot;&gt;General Survey of Climatology, Landsberg (ed.),Elsevier, 2001&lt;/ref&gt;

==Climate==

Botswana is semi-arid, due to the short rain season. However, the relatively high altitude of the country and its continental situation gives it a subtropical climate. The country is remote from moisture-laden air flows for most of the year. The dry season lasts from April to October in the south and to November in the north where, however, rainfall totals are higher. The south of the country is most exposed to cold winds during the winter period (early May to late August) when average temperatures are around {{convert|14|°C|1}}. The whole country has hot summers with average temperatures around {{convert|26|°C|1}}. Sunshine totals are high all year round although winter is the sunniest period. The whole country is windy and dusty during the dry season.&lt;ref name=&quot;Landsberg&quot; /&gt;

==Geography==
The land is predominantly flat to gently undulating [[tableland]], although there is some hilly country, where mining is carried out. The [[Kalahari Desert]] is in the central and the southwest.  The [[Okavango Delta]], one of the world's largest inland deltas, is in the northwest and the [[Makgadikgadi Pans]], a large [[Salt pan (geology)|salt pan]] lies in the north-central area.  The Makgadikgadi has been established as an early habitation area for primitive man; This large seasonal [[wetland]] is composed of several large component pans, the largest being [[Nwetwe Pan]], [[Sua Pan]] and [[Nxai Pan]].&lt;ref&gt;C. Michael Hogan (2008) [http://www.megalithic.co.uk/article.php?sid=22373&amp;mode=&amp;order=0 ''Makgadikgadi'', Megalithic Portal, ed. A.Burnham]&lt;/ref&gt; Botswana's lowest elevation point is at the junction of the [[Limpopo River|Limpopo]] and Shashe Rivers, at a height of {{Convert|513|m|ft|abbr=on}}.  The highest point is [[Monalanong Hill]], at {{Convert|1494|m|ft|abbr=on}}.
The country is divided into four drainage regions, which are sometimes indistinct due to the arid nature of the climate:
* the [[Chobe River]] on the border with the [[Caprivi Strip]] of Namibia together with a small adjacent swampy area is part of the [[Zambezi]] basin;
* most of the north and central region of the country is part of the [[Okavango Basin|Okavango]] inland drainage basin;
* the easternmost part of the country falls into the [[Limpopo]] drainage basin;
* the southern and southwestern regions, which are the driest of all, are drained by the Molopo river along the South African border and the [[Nossob River|Nossob river]] through the [[Kgalagadi Transfrontier Park|Kalahari Gemsbok National Park]], and are technically part of the basin of the [[Orange River]]. None of these rivers normally flows as far as the Orange, however. (The last recorded confluence was in the 1880s.)&lt;ref&gt;Times Comprehensive Atlas, (2007), Times Books, London&lt;/ref&gt;
Except for the Chobe, Okavango, [[Boteti]] and [[Limpopo river]]s, most of Botswana's rivers cease to flow during the dry and early rainy seasons.

==Natural hazards==
Botswana is affected by periodic droughts, and seasonal August winds blow from the west, carrying sand and dust, which can obscure visibility.

==Environment==

Current environmental issues in Botswana are [[overgrazing]], [[desertification]] and the existence of only limited fresh water resources.

Research from scientists has found that the common practice of [[Grazing#Disadvantages|overstocking cattle]] to cope with drought losses actually depletes scarce [[biomass]], making ecosystems more vulnerable. The study of the district predicts that by 2050 the cycle of mild drought is likely to become shorter —18 months instead of two years—due to [[climate change]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scidev.net/en/sub-suharan-africa/news/sub-saharan-africa-news-in-brief-10-22-april-2008.html Sub-Saharan Africa news in brief: 10–22 April 2008 - SciDev.Net&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==International agreements==
Botswana is a party to the following international agreements: Biodiversity, Climate Change, Desertification, Endangered Species, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Nuclear Test Ban, Ozone Layer Protection and Wetlands.

== Extreme points ==

This is a list of the extreme points of [[Botswana]], the points that are farther north, south, east or west than any other location.

* Northernmost point - the [[tripoint]] with [[Zambia]] and [[Namibia]], [[Ngamiland District]]
* Easternmost point - the [[tripoint]] with [[South Africa]] and [[Zimbabwe]], [[Central District (Botswana)|Central District]]
* Southernmost point - [[Bokspits]], [[Kgalagadi District]]
* Westernmost point - the western section of the border with [[Namibia]]*
* ''Note: Botswana does not have a westernmost point as the western section is formed by the 22nd meridian of longitude east of Greenwich.''

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

{{Botswana topics}}
{{Geography of Africa}}
{{Africa topic|Climate of}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Geography Of Botswana}}
[[Category:Geography of Botswana| ]]</text>
      <sha1>gtz28wvq8pe7czr2w820hb5kptfdgd1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
