  <page>
    <title>Geography of Bosnia and Herzegovina</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3604</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941495755</id>
      <parentid>940430329</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-18T22:37:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Santasa99</username>
        <id>6518807</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Rivers */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=February 2013}}
{{Country geography 
| name= Bosnia and Herzegovina 
| map =Bosnia and Herzegovina topographic map.svg
| continent =[[Europe]] 
| region =[[Southeastern Europe]]
| coordinates ={{Coord|44|N|18|E|display=inline,title}} 
| km area =51197 
| percent land= 99.8 
| km coastline =20  
| borders =[[Land borders|Total land borders]]:&lt;br/&gt;1,538&amp;nbsp;km
| highest point= [[Maglić mountain|Maglić]]&lt;br/&gt;2,386&amp;nbsp;m
| lowest point= [[Adriatic Sea]]&lt;br /&gt;0 m
| longest river= [[Bosna River]]
| largest lake=
}}
[[File:Bk-map.png|240px|thumb]]
[[Bosnia and Herzegovina]] is located in [[Southeastern Europe]], in the western [[Balkans]]. It has a {{Convert|932|km||abbr=on|adj=on}} border with [[Croatia]] to the north and southwest, a {{Convert|357|km||abbr=on|adj=on}} border with [[Serbia]] to the east, and a {{Convert|249|km||abbr=on|adj=on}} border with [[Montenegro]] to the southeast.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.fzs.ba/BihB/opcistatpodaciobih.htm |title=Archived copy |access-date=2016-04-07 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160306022545/http://www.fzs.ba/BihB/opcistatpodaciobih.htm |archive-date=2016-03-06 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; It borders the Adriatic Sea along its 20&amp;nbsp;km (12.42&amp;nbsp;mi) coastline.

The most striking features of the local terrain are valleys and mountains which measure up to {{Convert|2386|m||abbr=on}} in height. The country is mostly mountainous, encompassing the central [[Dinaric Alps]]. The northeastern parts reach into the [[Pannonian plain|Pannonian basin]], while in the south it borders the [[Adriatic Sea]].

The country's natural resources include coal, iron ore, bauxite, manganese, nickel, clay, gypsum, salt, sand, timber and hydropower.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/docs/notesanddefs.html#287|title=References :: Definitions and Notes — The World Factbook - Central Intelligence Agency|website=www.cia.gov|access-date=2019-11-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Regions==

The country's name comes from the two regions [[Bosnia (region)|Bosnia]] and [[Herzegovina]], which have a very vaguely defined border between them. Bosnia occupies the northern areas which are roughly four fifths of the entire country, while Herzegovina occupies the rest in the southern part of the country.

The major cities are the capital [[Sarajevo]], [[Banja Luka]] and [[Bihać]] in the northwest region known as [[Bosanska Krajina]], [[Tuzla]] in the northeast, [[Zenica]] in the [[Central Bosnia|central part of Bosnia]] and [[Mostar]] is the capital of [[Herzegovina]].

The south part of Bosnia has Mediterranean climate and a great deal of agriculture. Central Bosnia is the most mountainous part of Bosnia featuring prominent mountains [[Vlašić (Bosnian mountain)|Vlašić]], [[Čvrsnica]], and [[Prenj]]. Eastern Bosnia also features mountains like [[Trebević]], [[Jahorina]], [[Igman]], [[Bjelašnica]] and [[Treskavica]]. It was here that the [[1984 Winter Olympics]] were held.

Eastern Bosnia is heavily forested along the river Drina, and overall close to 50% of Bosnia and Herzegovina is forested. Most forest areas are in Central, Eastern and Western parts of Bosnia. Northern Bosnia contains very fertile agricultural land along the river Sava and the corresponding area is heavily farmed. This farmland is a part of the Parapannonian Plain stretching into neighbouring Croatia and Serbia. The river Sava and corresponding [[Posavina]] river basin hold the cities of Brčko, Bosanski Šamac, Bosanski Brod and Bosanska Gradiška.

The northwest part of Bosnia is called [[Bosanska Krajina]] and holds the cities of [[Banja Luka]], [[Prijedor]], [[Sanski Most]], [[Jajce]], Cazin, Velika Kladuša and [[Bihać]]. [[Kozara National Park]] and Mrakovica World War II monument is located in this region.

The country has only {{convert|20|km|mi|1}} of coastline,&lt;ref name=&quot;coastline&quot;&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/fields/2060.html Field Listing – Coastline], ''[[The World Factbook]]'', 2006-08-22&lt;/ref&gt; around the town of [[Neum]] in the Herzegovina-Neretva Canton, although surrounded by Croatian peninsulas it is possible to get to the middle of the Adriatic from Neum. By United Nations law, Bosnia has a right of passage to the outer sea. Neum has many hotels and is an important tourism destination.
==Rivers==
[[File:Sliv Neretve.gif|thumb|right|Watersheds in Bosnia and Herzegovina]]
&lt;!-- [[File:Croatia Bosnia Herzegovina Drainage basins.svg|thumb|right|Watersheds in Bosnia and Herzegovina and Croatia]] --&gt;
[[File:Vrelo Bosne 3.JPG|thumb|left|[[Bosna (river)|Bosna]] river, [[Ilidža]]]]
There are seven major rivers of Bosnia and Herzegovina:

*The [[Una (Sava)|Una]] in the northwest part of Bosnia flows along the northern and western border of Bosnia and Croatia and through the Bosnian city of Bihać. It is popular for rafting and adventure sports.
*The [[Sana River|Sana]] flows through the city of Sanski Most and Prijedor and is a tributary of the river Una in the north.
*The [[Vrbas (river)|Vrbas]] flows through the cities of Gornji Vakuf – Uskoplje, Bugojno, Jajce, Banja Luka, Srbac and reaches the river Sava in the north. The Vrbas flows through the central part of Bosnia and flows outwards to the North.
*The [[Bosna (river)|Bosna]] is the longest river in Bosnia and is fully contained within the country as it stretches from its source near Sarajevo to the river Sava in the north. It gave its name to the country.
*The [[Drina River|Drina]] flows through the eastern part of Bosnia, at many places in the border between Bosnia and Serbia. The Drina flows through the cities of Foča, Goražde Višegrad and Zvornik.
*The [[Neretva]] is the longest river in Herzegovina, flowing from Jablanica south to the Adriatic Sea. The river is famous as it flows through the city of Mostar.
*[[File:Affected People by Floods 2005 2015 Europe.png|thumb|Percent of population affected by Flood Disasters in Europe by country from 2005–2015.]]
The [[Sava]] is the largest river in Bosnia and Herzegovina but not the largest river that is flowing through Bosnia and Herzegovina.{{Clarify|reason=|date=November 2019}} The Sava flows through Serbia, Bosnia and Herzegovina and Croatia. The Sava is used as a natural border between Bosnia and Herzegovina and Croatia and towns like Brčko, Bosanski Šamac, Bosanska Gradiška lies on the river.

==Phytogeography==

[[Phytogeography|Phytogeographically]], Bosnia and Herzegovina belongs to the [[Boreal Kingdom]] and is shared between the Illyrian province of the [[Circumboreal Region]] and Adriatic province of the [[Mediterranean Region]]. According to the [[World Wide Fund for Nature|WWF]], the territory of Bosnia and Herzegovina can be subdivided into three [[ecoregion]]s: the [[Pannonian mixed forests]], [[Dinaric Mountains mixed forests]] and [[Illyrian deciduous forests]].

== Climate ==
{{Expand section|date=July 2010}}

The southern parts of the country have a [[Mediterranean climate]]. The Western and the Central parts experience hot and arid summers reaching up to {{Convert|40|C||abbr=}} while in the winter, temperatures are below freezing with lots of snow. The north-eastern region has a typical continental climate.

== Mining industry ==
[[File:Calcite Crystal from Trebević.JPG|thumb|200px|left| [[Calcite]] Crystal found at [[Trebević]] mountain around [[Sarajevo]]; Bosnia and Herzegovina on display at [[National Museum of Bosnia and Herzegovina]].]] 
Various archaeological artifacts including relicts of mining activities and tools belonging to similar age groups, provide an indication of the geographical distribution, scale and methods of mining activities in Bosnia and Herzegovina during the [[Paleolithic]] to [[Roman era]].

Most important of these is the so-called area of “central Bosnian mountains” located between the rivers [[Vrbas (river)|Vrbas]], [[Lašva]], [[Neretva]], [[Rama]] and their tributaries. The second one is the area of western Bosnia, bordered by the Vrbas and [[Una (Sava)|Una]] rivers, with its main orebearing formations found in the river-valleys of [[Sana River|Sana]] and [[Japra]], and their tributaries. The third area is eastern Bosnia, around the river [[Drina]] between the towns of [[Foča]] and [[Zvornik]], the principal mining activity centered around [[Srebrenica]].

Ores of various metals, including iron, are found in these areas and exploitation has been going on for more than 5000 years – from the period of prehistoric human settlers, through [[Illyrians|Illyrian]], Roman, Slavic, [[Turkish people|Turkish]] and Austrian rulers, into the present.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.anubih.ba/vanserijska/Minerali-1.pdf|title=Minerali Bosne i Hercegovine|date=1 September 2015|website=Anubih.ba}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Land use ==
*'''[[Arable land]]:''' 19.73%
*'''Permanent crops:''' 2.06%
*'''Other:''' 78.22% (2012 est.)

'''[[Irrigated land]]:''' {{Convert|30|km2||abbr=on}} (2003)

'''Total renewable water resources:''' {{Convert|37.5|km3||abbr=on}} (2011)

== Environment ==

'''Natural hazards:'''
*Destructive earthquakes

'''Current issues:'''
*Air pollution from metallurgical plants
*Sites for disposing of urban waste are limited
*Widespread casualties, water shortages, and destruction of infrastructure because of the 1992–95 [[Bosnian War|war]]
*Deforestation

'''International agreements:'''
*Party to: Air Pollution, Biodiversity, Climate Change, Desertification, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Life Conservation, Nuclear Test Ban, [[Ozone Layer]] Protection, Wetlands
*Signed, but not ratified: none

== Gallery ==
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Mountain Vlašić - Bosnia and Herzegovina.jpg|[[Vlašić (Bosnian mountain)|Vlašić]], part of [[Dinaric Alps]]
File:KozarackiKamen.jpg|A part of [[Kozara National Park]] near Prijedor in [[Bosanska Krajina]].
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

==See also==
*[[Geography of Europe]]
*[[List of cities in Bosnia and Herzegovina]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{commons category|Geography of Bosnia and Herzegovina}}

{{Bosnia and Herzegovina topics}}
{{Geography of Europe}}
{{Europe topic|Climate of}}

{{CIA World Factbook|year=2005}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Geography Of Bosnia And Herzegovina}}
[[Category:Geography of Bosnia and Herzegovina| ]]</text>
      <sha1>4xiuicc9ml5dspxwlgje27t0yrlsqjt</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
