  <page>
    <title>Economy of the British Virgin Islands</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3652</id>
    <revision>
      <id>923677211</id>
      <parentid>917208717</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-10-30T02:05:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Danielkueh</username>
        <id>612714</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>[[MOS:BOLDAVOID]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2012}}
{{Use British English|date=November 2013}}
{{Infobox economy
|country = British Virgin Islands
|image = Roadtown, Tortola.jpg
|width = 225px
|caption = Road Town, Tortola
|currency = [[United States dollar|U.S. dollar]] (USD)
|year = 1 Apr - 31 Mar
|organs = [[CARICOM]] (Associate member)
|gdp rank = [[List of countries by GDP (nominal)|177th]] (nominal) / [[List of countries by GDP (PPP)|190th]] (PPP)
|gdp = $1.027 billion (2017 est.)&lt;ref name=2017Budget&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bvi.gov.vg/pub/2017%20Budget%20Estimates.pdf|title=2017 Budget estimates|publisher=Government of the Virgin Islands|accessdate=22 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|growth = 3.2% (2017 est.)&lt;ref name=2017Budget /&gt;
|per capita = $34,246 (2017 est.)&lt;ref name=2017Budget /&gt;
|sectors = agriculture: 1.8%, industry: 6.2%, services: 92% (2005 est.)
|inflation = 0.85% (2015 est.)&lt;ref name=2017Budget /&gt; 
|poverty = NA% (2004)
|labor = 12,770 (2004)
|occupations = agriculture: 0.6%, industry: 40%, services: 59.4% (2005 est.)
|unemployment = 8.7% (2010 est.)
|industries = [[tourism]], [[Offshore financial centre|financial services]]
|exports = $38.5 million (2011 est.)
|export-goods = rum, fresh fish, fruits, animals; gravel, sand
|export-partners = [[United States Virgin Islands]], [[Puerto Rico]], US (2004)
|imports = $275.1 million (2011 est.)
|import-goods = building materials, automobiles, foodstuffs, machinery
|import-partners = [[United States Virgin Islands]], [[Puerto Rico]], US (2004)
|debt = $173.3 million (2017 est.)&lt;ref name=2017Budget /&gt; 
|revenue = $310,470,000 (2016 est.)&lt;ref name=2017Budget /&gt; 
|expenses = $288,640,000 (2016 est.)&lt;ref name=2017Budget /&gt;
|aid = ''recipient'': $NA (2004)
|cianame = vi
|Additional information not from CIA World Factbook taken from [http://www.bvi.org.uk/news_item.asp?news_id=639 BVI Government Press releases]
}}

The '''economy of the British Virgin Islands''' is one of the most prosperous in the [[Caribbean]]. Although tiny in absolute terms, because of the very small population of the [[British Virgin Islands]], in 2010 the Territory had the 19th highest [[Gross domestic product|GDP per capita]] in the world according to the [[CIA World factbook]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/vi.html CIA - The World Factbook - Virgin Islands]&lt;/ref&gt; In global terms the size of the Territory's GDP measured in terms of purchasing power is ranked as 215th out of a total of 229 countries.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/rankorder/2001rank.html?countryname=British%20Virgin%20Islands&amp;countrycode=vi&amp;regionCode=cam&amp;rank=215#vi CIA Factbook - GDP by country]&lt;/ref&gt; The economy of the Territory is based upon the &quot;twin pillars&quot; of [[Offshore financial centre|financial services]], which generates approximately 60% of government revenues,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www2.bviplatinum.com/news.php?module=news&amp;page=Article&amp;articleID=1268586|title=New Company Incorporations Down But Premier Remains Optimistic|date=14 March 2010|accessdate=2010-03-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[tourism]], which generates nearly all of the rest.

Historically the British Virgin Islands has normally produced a Government budget surplus, but during the [[financial crisis of 2007–2008]] the Territory began to run at a deficit, which continued after the global recession receded.  In 2011 the Territory had its largest ever budget deficit, of US$29 million (approximately 2.6% of GDP).&lt;ref name=&quot;2013 Budget Address&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bvi.org.uk/files/2013_Budget_Address.pdf|title=2013 Budget Address|publisher=BVI Government|access-date=13 November 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141225142346/http://www.bvi.org.uk/files/2013_Budget_Address.pdf|archive-date=25 December 2014|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;  By 2012 public debt had quadrupled from pre-crisis levels to approximately US$113 million (approximately 10.3% of GDP).&lt;ref name=&quot;Public Debt&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://bvinews.com/bvi/national-debt-grows-by-73m-over-last-decade-public-sector-too-big-financial-secretary/|title=National debt grows by $73M over last decade; public sector too big – Financial Secretary|work=BVI News|date=24 January 2013}}{{Dead link|date=August 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Nearly 84% of that public debt was attributable to a [[Peebles Hospital|new public hospital]] built in [[Road Town]] between 2003 and 2014.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://caribbeanmedicalnews.com/2013/04/new-hospital-responsible-for-nearly-84-of-national-debt/|title=New hospital responsible for nearly 84% of national debt|publisher=Caribbean Medical News|date=26 April 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  ''[[The Economist]]'' argued that deteriorating economic conditions in the British Virgin Islands were caused &quot;not [by] sagging revenues but public-sector profligacy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.economist.com/news/americas/21578418-britains-caribbean-dependencies-have-been-hurt-economic-stagnation-war-tax-havens-and|title=Treasure islands in trouble|newspaper=[[The Economist]]|date=25 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  By 2014 public debt had been reduced to US$106 million and the annual deficit reduced to US$25 million (including budgeted capital expenditure).&lt;ref name=&quot;2014 Budget Estimates&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.finance.gov.vg/Portals/0/2014%20Budget%20Estimates.pdf|title=2014 Budget Estimates|publisher=Government of the Virgin Islands|accessdate=21 November 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141129041815/http://www.finance.gov.vg/Portals/0/2014%20Budget%20Estimates.pdf|archive-date=29 November 2014|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By 2016, the Government had returned to a [[primary surplus|primary budget surplus]],&lt;ref name=&quot;2016 Budget&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bviplatinum.com/news.php?articleId=1454934927|title=Update: Gov't Presents Whopping $330M Budget; Largest In History|publisher=BVI Platinum|date=8 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; but public debt had increased to approximately US$141 million&lt;ref name=&quot;2016 Debt&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bviplatinum.com/news.php?articleId=1455018124|title=Some Will Have You Believe We Have No Money - Premier Smith|publisher=BVI Platinum|date=9 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; and debt service accounted for over US$12 million of the primary surplus.  However, because of an ongoing aggressive capital investment programme, and budget overruns on key public projects,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bviplatinum.com/news.php?articleId=1453736757|title=Pier Project Balloons To $82.9M|publisher=BVI Platinum|date=25 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Government ran dangerously low on available cash.  Cash in the consolidated fund fell below US$7 million (with average monthly expenditure at nearly US$30 million), and Government accrued over US$13 million in due but unpaid invoices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://bvinews.com/new/national-debt-is-141m/|title=National debt is $141M, unpaid invoices $13M|work=BVI News|date=5 January 2016|access-date=9 February 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160206083055/http://bvinews.com/new/national-debt-is-141m/|archive-date=6 February 2016|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Business environment==
In 2015, British Virgin Islands has been assessed as the 34th in terms of global financial centres.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.longfinance.net/images/GFCI17_23March2015.pdf|title=The Global Financial Centres Index|publisher=Qatar Financial Centre|date=31 March 2015|access-date=9 April 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150414052808/http://www.longfinance.net/images/GFCI17_23March2015.pdf|archive-date=14 April 2015|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This was the highest ranking of any [[offshore financial centre]], and of any Latin American country.  The Territory scored strongly in areas such as [[taxation in the British Virgin Islands|local taxation]], [[rule of law]], regulatory environment and quality of law for human resources.  It scored less highly on infrastructure, access to capital and access to labour.
The [[G-20]] considers it a [[tax haven]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Islands resent crackdown of the tax havens by G-20|url=http://www.timesherald.com/articles/2009/05/09/business/doc4a04ef4f516e1869586320.txt|first=Ben |last= Fox|agency=[[Associated Press]]|date= 2009-05-09 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20090515010825/http://www.timesherald.com/articles/2009/05/09/business/doc4a04ef4f516e1869586320.txt |archive-date= 2009-05-15 |access-date=2016-04-02 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; and its banking system is described as 'opaque'.&lt;ref name=smh2013&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.smh.com.au/business/leighton-holdings-linked-to-corrupt-fees-for-iraq-pipeline-contracts-20131117-2xp8b.html |title= Leighton Holdings linked to 'corrupt' fees for Iraq pipeline contracts |work= [[The Australian]] |first1= Nick |last1= McKenzie |first2= Richard |last2= Baker |date= 2013-11-18 |accessdate= 2016-04-02}}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==2017 Government Budget==
The most recent national budget to be delivered was the 2017 budget (the Territory's fiscal year runs from 1 April to 31 March).&lt;ref name=2017Budget /&gt;  That budget presented a picture of declining revenues and increasing costs.  It was also delivered prior to the devastating effects of [[Hurricane Irma]] later in the year, which is likely to have an deleterious effect on the economy and on Government revenues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.virginislandsnewsonline.com/en/news/economy-bust-layoffs-continue-following-hurricane-irma |title=Economy ‘bust’? Layoffs continue following Hurricane Irma |publisher=Virgin Islands News Online|date=4 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2017 budget predicted that 2016 final revenue figures of $310,470,000 which was a decrease of 6.2% from the year before.  It also predicted recurrent expenditure for 2016 at $288,640,000 which was an increase of 3.6% on the preceding year.  That would mean a primary budget surplus of $21,830,000 which would be a decrease of 56.6% from the preceding year.&lt;ref name=2017Budget /&gt;  

In addition there was an estimated $21,000,000 of capital expenditure in 2016 (down 38.3% from the previous year), and debt service of $20,200,000 leaving a [[Government_budget_balance#Primary_deficit,_total_deficit,_and_debt|primary deficit]] of $19,370,000.  In 2017, after accounting for transfers to reserves, there is budgeted to be a [[Government_budget_balance#Structural_deficits,_cyclical_deficits,_and_the_fiscal_gap|structural deficit]] of $31,674,000.  This was to be financed by new borrowing and transfers from the consolidated fund.&lt;ref name=2017Budget /&gt;

The Government's total borrowings were $106.5 million, but the Government has also underwritten significant loans made to the BVI Electricity Corporation and the BVI Ports Authority, meaning that the Government's total loan exposure is $178.3 million.&lt;ref name=2017Budget /&gt;

Much of the Government's increased expenditure arose from staffing costs.  Staffing consumes 37.7% of Government expenditure, and increased in 2016 by 10.2% from the year before.  The budget calls for it to increase again, but only by 2.6% in 2017.&lt;ref name=2017Budget /&gt;

The bulk of Government revenues (60%) comes from taxes on goods and services.  The next largest segment is payroll taxes, which account for a further 16%.  Property taxes account for less than 1% of revenue.&lt;ref name=2017Budget /&gt;

==Tourism==
In 2015, a total of 922,372 people visited the islands (of whom 529,354 were cruise ship passengers and 393,018 were overnight visitors), mainly from the United States.&lt;ref name=2017Budget /&gt; The bulk of the tourism income in the British Virgin Islands is generated by the [[yacht]] [[charter]]ing industry. The Territory has relatively few large [[hotel]]s compared to other tourism centres in the Caribbean. The British Virgin Islands also entertain [[cruise ship]]s, although these generate relatively little revenue. However, cruise ship passengers are an important source of revenue for [[Taxicab|taxi]] drivers, who represent a politically important voice in the Territory.

Between 2007 and 2011, tourist visitors to be the British Virgin Islands declined by approximately 12.4%, largely due to the global recession which particularly affected North America, a key source of visitors for the Territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;2013 Budget Address&quot; /&gt;  However, by November 2013 tourist numbers had begun to recover.&lt;ref name=&quot;2014 Budget Address&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.bvi.org.uk/files/2014_Budget_Address.pdf|title=2014 Budget Address|publisher=Government of the Virgin Islands|accessdate=8 June 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160306032319/http://www.bvi.org.uk/files/2014_Budget_Address.pdf|archive-date=6 March 2016|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the [[World Travel and Tourism Council]]:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wttc.org/-/media/files/reports/economic%20impact%20research/country%20reports/british_virgin_islands2014.pdf|title=Travel &amp; Tourism Economic impact 2014 - British Virgin Islands|publisher=[[World Travel and Tourism Council]]|accessdate=8 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* In 2013, the ''direct'' contribution of travel and tourism to the Territory's GDP was US$274 million (accounting for 27.0% of total GDP), and was forecast to rise by 2.8% in 2014, and to rise by 2.7% per annum for the period 2014-2024.
* The ''total'' contribution of travel and tourism to GDP was US$780.8 million (76.9% of GDP) in 2013, and is forecast to rise by 3.2% in 2014, and to rise by 2.6% per annum for the period 2014-2024.
* In 2013, travel and tourism ''directly'' supported 3,300 jobs in the Territory (33.2% of total employment).  This was expected to remain unchanged in 2014 and fall by 0.3% per annum to 3,000 jobs (29.6% of total employment) by 2024.
* The ''total'' contribution to employment in 2013 (which includes jobs indirectly supported by the industry, was 90.1% of total employment (8,850 jobs).  This was expected to rise by 1.9% in 2014 to 9,050 jobs, but fall by 0.2% per annum to 9,000 jobs in 2024 (80.9% of total).
* Travel and tourism investment in 2013 was US$35.8 million, or 14.8% of total investment.  This was expected to rise by 10.1% in 2014, and rise by 2.0% per annum over the next ten years to a total of US$48.2 million in 2024.
However, these statistics include travel as well as tourism, and so non-tourist related travel (i.e. travel relating to domestic consumption and other industries and services) are included and inflate the figures.

==Financial services==
In the mid-1980s, the government began offering offshore registration to companies wishing to incorporate in the islands, and incorporation fees now generate an estimated 51.4% of Government revenues. As of 2019, it costs $450 to form a company with fewer than 50,000 shares and another $450 a year to maintain registration.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.bloomberg.com/news/features/2019-07-03/the-bvi-s-struggle-to-protect-its-dark-offshore-economy|title=Sun, Sand, and the $1.5 Trillion Dark Offshore Economy|last=Baker|first=Stephanie|date=2019-07-03|work=|access-date=2019-07-06|language=en|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to official statistics 447,801 BVI companies were 'active' (i.e. incorporated and not yet struck-off, liquidated or dissolved) as at 30 June 2012.&lt;ref name=&quot;bvifsc.vg&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bvifsc.vg/News/tabid/160/articleType/ArticleView/articleId/1267/language/en-US/Q2-2012-BVIFSC-Statistical-Bulletin.aspx|title=Q2 2012 BVIFSC Statistical Bulletin}}&lt;/ref&gt;  There are no recent official statistics on total numbers of incorporations (including struck, liquidated and dissolved companies) but these are estimated at approximately 950,000.  Many of these companies were originally formed under the [[International Business Companies Act]], 1984, but have now been consolidated into the [[BVI Business Companies Act]], 2004.  

In 2000, [[KPMG]] were commissioned by the British Government to produce a report on the offshore financial industry generally, and the report indicated that nearly 45% of the offshore companies in the world were formed in the British Virgin Islands.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Review of Financial Regulation in the Crown Dependencies (Cmnd Paper 4855 of 2000) |url=https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/review-of-financial-regulation-in-the-crown-dependencies--2 |publisher=[[Office of Public Sector Information|HMSO]] |at=Part III, paragraph 1.3 |isbn=0 10 148554 9 |accessdate=19 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The British Virgin Islands is now one of the [[Offshore financial centre#List of main offshore financial centres|world's leading offshore financial centres]], and boasts one of the highest incomes per capita in the Caribbean.

In addition to basic company incorporations, the British Virgin Islands also forms limited partnerships and trusts (including signature &quot;VISTA&quot; trusts) but these have not proved to be as popular as companies.

On 12 April 2007, the ''[[Financial Times]]'' reported that the British Virgin Islands was the second largest source of [[foreign direct investment]] in the world (behind [[Hong Kong]]) with over US$123,000,000,000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ft.com/cms/s/2aec1ac0-e893-11db-b2c3-000b5df10621,_i_email=y.html FT.com / Lex - The Russians are coming&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]{{Dead link|date=August 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; Almost all of these sums are directly attributable to investment through the Territory's [[Offshore financial centre|offshore finance industry]].

The British Virgin Islands also promotes a number of regulated financial services products.  The most important of these is the formation and regulation of [[offshore fund|offshore investment funds]].  The Territory is also the second largest domicile for formation of offshore investment funds (behind the [[Cayman Islands]]) with 2,422 licensed [[Open-end fund|open-ended funds]] as at 30 June 2012&lt;ref name=&quot;bvifsc.vg&quot;/&gt; (there is no official statistics for [[Closed-end fund|closed-ended funds]] which are not regulated in the British Virgin Islands).

The British Virgin Islands also operates as a domicile for [[captive insurance]] services, but a prolonged period of overzealous Government regulation combined with the Government's increasing pressure to hire only locals (&quot;[[Belonger status|belongers]]&quot;) in the insurance industry decimated the industry.  Official reports from the Financial Services Commission reflect as of 30 June 2012 only 161 captives remain registered in the jurisdiction.&lt;ref name=&quot;bvifsc.vg&quot;/&gt;

===History of financial services===
Former president of the BVI's [[British Virgin Islands Financial Services Commission|Financial Services Commission]], [[Michael Riegels]], recites the anecdote that the offshore finance industry commenced on an unknown date in the 1970s when a lawyer from a firm in New York telephoned him with a proposal to incorporate a [[company]] in the British Virgin Islands to take advantage of a [[double taxation]] [[tax treaty|relief treaty]] with the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.harneys.com/files/the-ibc-act-the-building-of-a-nation-%282%29.pdf|title=The IBC Act – the building of a nation|publisher=[[Harney Westwood &amp; Riegels|Harneys]]|accessdate=19 September 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170823013048/http://www.harneys.com/files/the-ibc-act-the-building-of-a-nation-(2).pdf|archive-date=23 August 2017|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Within the space of a few years, hundreds of such companies had been incorporated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=|title=British Virgin Islands Commercial Law|last=|first=|publisher=[[Sweet &amp; Maxwell]]|year=2011|isbn=978-962-661-462-4|location=|page=5|authorlink=|coauthors=}}&lt;!--|accessdate=2011-12-16--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

This eventually came to the attention of the United States government, who unilaterally revoked the Treaty in 1981.&lt;ref&gt;The British Virgin Islands was not alone in this regard; this was part of a policy of mass-repeal by the United States of double tax relief treaties with &quot;[[microstate]]s&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1984, the British Virgin Islands, trying to recapture some of the lost offshore business, enacted a new form of companies legislation, the [[International Business Companies Act]], under which an [[offshore company]] which was exempt from local taxes could be formed. The development was only a limited success until 1991, when the United States invaded [[Panama]] to oust General [[Manuel Noriega]]. At the time Panama was one of the largest providers of offshore financial services in the world, but the business fled subsequent the invasion, and the British Virgin Islands was one of the main beneficiaries.

==Agriculture==
[[Livestock]] raising is the most important agricultural activity; poor soils limit the islands' ability to meet domestic food requirements.  Fewer than 0.6% are estimated to work in agriculture.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Times&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bcg.thetimes.co.uk/North_America/British_Virgin_Islands#workforce|title=British Virgin Islands - workforce|author=''[[The Times]]''|accessdate=2012-03-19}}{{cite web|url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/vi.html|title=CIA Factbook: the British Virgin Islands|accessdate=2012-12-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Despite its tiny economic impact, agriculture has its own dedicated Government minister (unlike financial services).

==Dollarisation==
{{Further|Dollarisation}}

Because of traditionally close links with the [[United States Virgin Islands|U.S. Virgin Islands]], the British Virgin Islands has used the US dollar as its currency since 1959.&lt;ref&gt;Legal Tender (Adoption of United States Currency) Act, 1959&lt;/ref&gt;

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist}}

== See also ==
* [[List of Commonwealth of Nations countries by GDP]]
* [[List of Latin American and Caribbean countries by GDP (nominal)]]
* [[List of Latin American and Caribbean countries by GDP (PPP)]]

{{Caricom}}
{{Caribbean in topic|Economy of}}
{{EU Dependent economies|state=collapsed}}
{{Americas topic|Economy of}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Economy of the British Virgin Islands}}
[[Category:Economy of the British Virgin Islands| ]]</text>
      <sha1>s6f3nre46ycij0gj1r1orcj6797h2qk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
