  <page>
    <title>Burkina Faso Armed Forces</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3683</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943126728</id>
      <parentid>943126530</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T00:37:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>FOX 52</username>
        <id>17622016</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox national military
| name = Burkina Faso Armed Forces
| image = [[File:Burkina Faso Coat of arms (vectored).svg|180px]]
| caption = Coat of arms of Burkina Faso
| native_name = Forces armées du Burkina Faso
| headquarters = [[Ouagadougou]]
| commander-in-chief = [[Roch Marc Christian Kaboré]] 
| commander-in-chief_title = [[President (government title)|President]]
| minister = Roch Marc Christian Kaboré
| minister_title = Minister of Defense and Veteran Affairs
| commander = Brigadier General Moise Minoungou 
| commander_title = Chief of General Staff
| deployed = 
| budget = $40.1 million (FY01)
| percent_GDP = 1.2% (2006)&lt;ref name=CIA&gt;{{cite web|title=CIA World Factbook|url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/uv.html|publisher=CIA|accessdate=22 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Update-inline|date=June 2018}}
| founded = 
| current_form = 1985
| disbanded =
| branches = [[Burkina Faso Army|Army]]&lt;br&gt;[[Air Force of Burkina Faso|Air Force]]&lt;br&gt;[[National Gendarmerie (Burkina Faso)|National Gendarmerie]]&lt;br&gt;[[People's Militia (Burkina Faso)|People's Militia]]
| manpower_age = 
| active = 11,200 (IISS estimate 2012: Army 6,400, Air 600, Gendarmerie 4,200)
| reserve = 
| domestic_suppliers = 
| foreign_suppliers = 
| exports = 
| imports = 
| history = [[Agacher Strip War]]&lt;br&gt;[[Sierra Leone Civil War]]&lt;br&gt;[[Insurgency in the Maghreb (2002–present)|Insurgency in the Maghreb]] 
| ranks = [[Military ranks of Burkina Faso]]
}}

The '''Burkina Faso Armed Forces''' ([[French language|French]]: Forces armées du Burkina Faso) is the term used for the national military of [[Burkina Faso]]. The service branches of the armed forces include its [[Burkina Faso Army|Army]], [[Air Force of Burkina Faso|Air Force]], [[National Gendarmerie (Burkina Faso)|National Gendarmerie]] and [[People's Militia (Burkina Faso)|People's Militia]]. Being a landlocked country, Burkina Faso has no [[navy]].

==History==
In 1966 a [[1966 Upper Voltan coup d'état|military coup]] deposed the first president of [[Republic of Upper Volta|Upper Volta]], [[Maurice Yaméogo]], suspended the constitution, dissolved the National Assembly, and placed Lieutenant Colonel [[Sangoulé Lamizana]] at the head of a government of senior army officers. The army remained in power for 4 years; on June 14, 1970, the Voltans ratified a new constitution that established a 4-year transition period toward complete civilian rule. Lamizana remained in power throughout the 1970s as president of military or mixed civil-military governments. After conflict over the 1970 constitution, a new constitution was written and approved in 1977, and Lamizana was reelected by open elections in 1978.

Lamizana's government faced problems with the country's traditionally powerful trade unions and on November 25, 1980, Colonel [[Saye Zerbo]] overthrew President Lamizana in a bloodless coup. Colonel Zerbo established the Military Committee of Recovery for National Progress as the supreme governmental authority, thus eradicating the 1977 constitution.

Colonel Zerbo also encountered resistance from trade unions and was overthrown two years later on November 7, 1982, by Major Dr. [[Jean-Baptiste Ouédraogo]] and the Council of Popular Salvation (CSP). The CSP continued to ban political parties and organisations, yet promised a transition to civilian rule and a new constitution.

Factional infighting developed between moderates in the CSP and radicals led by Captain [[Thomas Sankara]], who was appointed prime minister in January 1983. The internal political struggle and Sankara's leftist rhetoric led to his arrest and subsequent efforts to bring about his release, directed by Captain [[Blaise Compaoré]]. This release effort resulted in yet another military coup d'état on August 4, 1983. Compaoré came to power in a 1987 coup that led to the death of Sankara.

On February 15, 2011, [[2011 Burkinabé protests|soldiers mutinied]] in [[Ouagadougou]] over unpaid housing allowances.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/africa/soldiers-go-on-rampage-over-pay-in-burkina-faso-2268641.html|accessdate=2011-04-17|title=Soldiers go on rampage over pay in Burkina Faso|publisher=&quot;The Independent&quot;|location=London|date=16 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On April 18, 2011, it was reported that the mutiny had spread to [[Kaya, Burkina Faso|Kaya]] after demonstrations in [[Pô]] and [[Tenkodogo]].&lt;ref&gt;Stratfor.com, [https://www.stratfor.com/situation-report/burkina-faso-army-mutiny-spreads 'Burkina Faso: Army Mutiny Spreads'], April 18, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; On April 29, 2011, the army said the mutiny would end after Compaoré promised to improve the military's housing, clothing and food allowances,&lt;ref&gt;[https://af.reuters.com/article/commoditiesNews/idAFLDE73S1RJ20110429 Burkina president says army vows to end protests]&lt;/ref&gt; though there were later protests by soldiers.&lt;ref&gt;Gongo, Simon (25 May 2011). [https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2011-05-24/burkina-faso-troops-resume-protests-halt-traffic-fire-in-air &quot;Three Killed, 136 Injured in Burkina Faso Protest, Fasozine Says&quot;]. Bloomberg.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gongo, Simon (2 June 2011).[https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2011-06-01/burkina-faso-soldiers-protest-in-the-city-of-bobo-diolousso-fire-shots &quot;Burkina Faso Soldiers Protest, Fire Shots and Loot Shops in Bobo Dioulasso&quot;]. Bloomberg. Retrieved 3 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

After [[2015 Burkinabe coup d'état|a coup]] by members of the [[Regiment of Presidential Security]] on September 16, 2015, army units marched on Ouagadougou to oppose the coup, resulting in the restoration of Burkina Faso's transitional government (which was appointed after the [[2014 Burkinabe uprising]]) on September 23, 2015.

==Ground forces==
[[File:Defense.gov photo essay 100501-F-3745E-033.jpg|thumb|Soldiers from Burkina Faso before deployment to an exercise in [[Mali]] (2010)]]
The Army of Burkina Faso (''Armée de Terre'' – Ground Forces) is a skeletonised force structure of some 5,800–6,000 officers and men, augmented by a conscript force or ''[[People's Militia (Burkina Faso)|People's Militia]]'' of some 45,000 men and women. Unlike the police and security forces, the Army and the People's Militia are organised along Soviet/Chinese models and precepts. The Army is equipped with light wheeled armoured cars, some mounting cannon.

The [[International Institute for Strategic Studies]] estimated in 2011–12 that Burkina Faso had 6,400 personnel in the ''Armee de Terre'' in three military regions, one tank battalion (two tank platoons), five infantry regiments that may be under-strength, and an airborne regiment. Artillery and engineer battalions are also listed.&lt;ref&gt;IISS Military Balance 2012, 423–424.&lt;/ref&gt;

In recent years, the United States has begun providing military assistance and training to Burkina Faso's ground forces. It has trained three 750-man battalions for peace support operations in Darfur. During a recent UN inspection, a [[U.S. Department of Defense]] evaluation team found Burkina's ''Laafi'' battalion fit to deploy to Sudan. Using a small Department of Defense International Military Education and Training (IMET) budget, the U.S. Embassy has established English-language courses at an LAT military base, and has brought LAT officers to attend officer basic training courses in the U.S. The government of Burkina Faso has also accepted additional U.S. training assistance in counter-terrorism tactics and humanitarian assistance. Burkina Faso has recently become a member of the [[Trans-Saharan Counterterrorism Initiative|Trans-Sahara Counterterrorism Partnership]] (TSCTP).&lt;ref&gt;U.S. Dept. of State, ''[https://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2834.htm Background Note: Burkina Faso – Profile]'' June 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

Three years of increasingly frequent and deadly attacks, by various jihadist groups, prompted the replacement of the Army Chief of Staff, General Oumarou Sadou, appointed three years ago with the same mandate, with General Moise Minoungou on 6 January 2019.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Burkina Faso: Moise Minoungou appointed Army chief of staff |url=http://apanews.net/index.php/en/news/burkina-faso-moise-minoungou-appointed-army-chief-of-staff |website=(in English) APA news (Agence de Presse Africaine) |accessdate=12 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Burkina army chief sacked as jihadist attacks continue |url=https://www.pulse.com.gh/news/world/burkina-army-chief-sacked-as-jihadist-attacks-continue/9w0l5q2 |website=pulse.com.gh (Ghana) |accessdate=12 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There is a multi-national training camp in [[Loumbila Department]], staffed by Czech and Polish instructors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2019/03/01/world/africa/africa-terror-attacks.html |quote=At an Army training range in Loumbila, 15 miles northeast of Ouagadougou, Malian and Burkinabe commandos practiced marksmanship with AK-47 rifles and Beretta pistols under the watchful eye of Czech and Polish trainers barking out instructions in French. |title=Where Terrorism Is Rising in Africa and the U.S. Is Leaving |date=March 1, 2019 |first=Eric |last=Schmitt |newspaper=[[The New York Times]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Equipment==
===Small arms===
[[File:Close quarter combat training in Burkina Faso during Flintlock 2017 170308-A-ZF167-147.jpg|thumb|A Burkinabé soldier with an AKM during an exercise.]]
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#aabccc;&quot;|Name
! style=&quot;text-align: center; background:#aabccc;&quot;|Origin
! style=&quot;text-align:l center; background:#aabccc;&quot;|Type
! style=&quot;text-align:l center; background:#aabccc;&quot;|Variant
! style=&quot;text-align: center; background:#aabccc;&quot;|Notes
|-
| [[Walther PP]]&lt;ref name=&quot;jones2009&quot;&gt;Jones, Richard D. Jane's Infantry Weapons 2009/2010. Jane's Information Group; 35 edition (January 27, 2009). {{ISBN|978-0710628695}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
| [[Germany]]
| [[Semi-automatic pistol|Semi-auto pistol]]
|
|
|-
| [[Heckler &amp; Koch G3|HK G3]]&lt;ref name=&quot;jones2009&quot;/&gt;
| [[Germany]]
| [[Assault rifle]]
|
|
|-
| [[AK-47]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Armyrecognition.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.armyrecognition.com/burkina_faso_army_land_forces_ranks_combat_uniform/burkina_faso_army_defence_force_ranks_military_pattern_camouflage_combat_field_uniforms_dress_grades.html|title=Burkina Faso Army defence force ranks military pattern camouflage combat field uniforms dress grades - Army Recognition - Army Recognition|publisher=Armyrecognition.com|accessdate=23 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| [[Russia]]
| [[Assault rifle]]
| [[AKM]], [[AK-103]], [[AK-12]]
|
|-
| [[FN MAG]]&lt;ref name=&quot;jones2009&quot;/&gt;
| [[Belgium]]
| [[General purpose machine gun]]
|
|
|-
| [[SIG SG 540]]&lt;ref name=&quot;jones2009&quot;/&gt;
| [[Switzerland]]
| [[Assault rifle]]
|
|
|-
| [[M2 Browning]]&lt;ref name=&quot;jones2009&quot;/&gt;
| [[United States]]
| [[Heavy machine gun]]
| [[M2 Browning#Variants and derivatives|M2HB]]
| 
|-
| [[RPG-7]]&lt;ref name=&quot;jones2009&quot;/&gt;
| [[Soviet Union]]
| [[Rocket-propelled grenade]]
|
|
|}

===Armour===
[[File:Pick-up Armee Burkina Faso.png|thumb|right|A Burkinabé [[ACMAT ALTV]].]]
[[File:Blindé loyaliste.png|thumb|right|A Burkinabé [[ACMAT Bastion|Bastion APC]].]]
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#aabccc;&quot;|Name
! style=&quot;text-align: center; background:#aabccc;&quot;|Origin
! style=&quot;text-align:l center; background:#aabccc;&quot;|Type
! style=&quot;text-align:l center; background:#aabccc;&quot;|In service
! style=&quot;text-align: center; background:#aabccc;&quot;|Notes
|-
! style=&quot;align: center; background: lavender;&quot; colspan=&quot;7&quot; | [[Armoured fighting vehicle]]
|-
|[[ACMAT Bastion]]
| [[France]]
| Armored personnel carrier
|100+&lt;ref name=&quot;NMAA&quot;&gt;{{cite web|first1=Jeremy|last1=Binnie|first2=Erwan|last2=de Cherisey|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170622123315/http://www.janes.com/images/assets/520/71520/New-model_African_armies.pdf|title=New-model African armies|publisher=Jane's|date=2017|archive-date=22 June 2017|url=http://www.janes.com/images/assets/520/71520/New-model_African_armies.pdf|url-status=dead|access-date=18 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|
|- 
| [[Panhard M3]]
| [[France]]
| [[Armoured personnel carrier|APC]]
| 13&lt;ref name=&quot;Military Balance&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=The Military Balance 2016|date=February 2016|volume=116|isbn=9781857438352 |publisher=Routlegde|ref={{harvid|Military Balance 2016}}|author=International Institute for Strategic Studies|author-link=International Institute for Strategic Studies|pages=432-433|chapter-url=https://www.offiziere.ch/wp-content/uploads-001/2016/10/2016-Chapter-Nine-Sub-Saharan-Africa.pdf|chapter=Chapter Nine: Sub-Saharan Africa|doi=10.1080/04597222.2016.1127636}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|
|-
| [[PUMA M26-15]]
| [[South Africa]]
| [[MRAP]]
| 31&lt;ref name=&quot;Military Balance&quot;/&gt;
|
|-
| [[Gila MBPV|Gila]]
| [[South Africa]]
| [[V-hull|MBPV]]
| 6&lt;ref name=&quot;armstrade.sipri&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://armstrade.sipri.org/armstrade/page/trade_register.php|title=Arms Trade Register|publisher=SIPRI|accessdate=22 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|
|-
| [[Eland Mk7|Eland-90]]
| [[South Africa]]
| [[Armored car (military)|Armoured car]]
| 4&lt;ref name=&quot;armstrade.sipri&quot; /&gt;
|
|-
| [[Panhard AML 60]]
| [[France]]
| [[Armored car (military)|Armoured car]]
| 15&lt;ref name=&quot;armstrade.sipri&quot; /&gt;
|of which 13 were [[Panhard AML#Variants|AML 90]]
|-
| [[EE-9 Cascavel]]
| [[Brazil]]
| [[Armored car (military)|Armoured car]]
|24&lt;ref name=&quot;Military Balance&quot;/&gt;
|
|-
| [[M8 Greyhound]]
| [[United States]]
| [[Armored car (military)|Armoured car]]
|10
|including 2 M20 armoured utility car&lt;ref name=&quot;Military Balance&quot;/&gt;
|-
| [[Ferret armoured car]]
| [[United Kingdom]]
| [[Armored car (military)|Armoured car]]
|30&lt;ref name=&quot;Military Balance&quot;/&gt;
|
|-
|[[ACMAT ALTV]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.acmat.fr/en/news/248-laltv-dacmat-remporte-une-nouvelle-commade-a-lexportation The ACMAT ALTV secures another export order] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131005041905/http://www.acmat.fr/en/news/248-laltv-dacmat-remporte-une-nouvelle-commade-a-lexportation |date=October 5, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| [[France]]
| Tactical vehicle
|10+&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Burkina Faso: Du matériel roulant et de transmissions pour l'armée burkinabè|date=6 October 2011|url=https://fr.allafrica.com/stories/201110070279.html|newspaper=[[AllAfrica.com]]|language=fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|
|}

==Air Force==
[[File:Roundel of Burkina Faso.svg|thumb|150px|left|thumb| The [[roundel]] used by the Air Force]]
The Air Force was founded in 1964 as the ''Escadrille de la République de Haute-Volta'' (EHV) or the Republic of Upper Volta Air Squadron, a subordinate unit of the Army. That year, a transient air support base was created with the assistance of the [[French Air Force]]. After acquiring an initial fleet of utility and transport aircraft, the squadron was attached to an inter-army support regiment. In 1970, the ''Escadrille'' was renamed the ''Force Aérienne de Haute-Volta'', or FAHV, and in 1977 became an autonomous force. In October 1985, the ''Force Aérienne de Burkina Faso'', or FABF, was officially inaugurated.

The EHV was initially formed with two [[Douglas C-47]] Skytrain and three [[Max Holste Broussard|MH.1521M Broussard]] aircraft. These were later followed by two [[Aérospatiale Alouette III|Alouette III SA.316 B]] helicopters, used mostly for liaison purposes, one twin-engined [[Aero Commander 500 family|Aero Commander 500]] light utility aircraft, two [[Hawker Siddeley HS 748|Hawker-Siddeley HS.748-2A]] twin turboprop transport aircraft, and two [[Aérospatiale N 262|Nord 262]] twin turboprop transport aircraft. Two ''escadrilles'' (squadrons) or sub-formations were created: the ''Escadrille de Transport'' (Transport Unit), and the ''Escadrille d'Hélicoptères'' (Helicopter Unit). Later, the ''Escadrille d'Entraînement'' (Training Unit) was added. All squadrons were initially based at Ouagadougou.

In mid-1984, Libyan military aid brought eight [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-21]] jet fighters, along with two MiG-21U combat trainer versions. These ex-[[Libyan Air Force]]' [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-21|MiG-21]] Fishbed' fighters were based in [[Ouagadougou]], although they were actually operated by the Libyan Air Force on loan by Libya, and were removed in 1985 without seeing combat. A single MiG-17F Fresco that was also operated by the FABF did see combat service in the [[Agacher Strip War]] in 1985–86.
In 1985, the FABF also acquired two ex-Soviet [[Mil Mi-4|Mi-4]] transport helicopters from an unknown supplier, followed by an additional two Mi-4s. The Mi-4s were operated by the FABF until the late 1980s, when they were taken out of service. Five [[Mil Mi-8|Mi-8]]/17 transport helicopters were later added to the ''Escadrille d'Hélicoptères''. While supervising the ceasefire after the [[Agacher Strip War]], an FABF SA.316B Alouette III crashed at Kouni on 14 January 1986, leaving only one SA.316B still in service with the ''Escadrille d'Hélicoptères''.

In 1986, the FABF formed a new unit, the ''Escadrille de Chasse'' (EdC) (Attack Unit). In mid-1986 six ex-Philippine Air Force [[Aermacchi SF.260|SF.260WP Warrior]] armed trainers/light strike aircraft were acquired from a dealer in Belgium, which offered the FABF a much simpler and less expensive alternative in tactical air support to the expensive MiGs. The Warriors were not only used for pilot training, but also as light strike aircraft, and a number of them were employed by the FABF's ''Escadrille de Chasse'' (EdC). Four additional SF.260WPs were subsequently bought directly from Italy. The six ex-Philippine SF.260WP aircraft were taken out of service in 1993 and returned to their previous owner, although the four newly built SF.260WP aircraft were retained in service, and stationed at Bobo Dioulasso air base.

Most of the other light aircraft acquired by the FABF in the 1970s and 1980s have also now been retired along with the Mi-4 helicopters, but some recent acquisitions have been made, including a [[Beech Aircraft|Beechcraft]] ''[[Beechcraft King Air|King Air]]'', a Piper [[Piper PA-34 Seneca|PA-34 ''Seneca'']], a [[Apex Aircraft|CEAPR]] ''Robin'' light training aircraft, and a single [[Air Tractor]] ''[[Air Tractor AT-802|AT-802]]'' aerial sprayer aircraft for spraying insecticides, purchased after the northern part of the country suffered heavy crop damage from a 2004 invasion of swarming [[Migratory locust|locusts]]. In 2009, two Xenon Gyroplane autogyros were purchased for use by police and security forces.

In late 2005, the FABF acquired two [[Mil Mi-35]] 'Hind' attack helicopters from Russia in apparent response by moves by neighbouring [[Ivory Coast]] to bolster its own air attack capabilities during the [[First Ivorian Civil War|Ivorian Civil War]].

===Aircraft===
[[File:SIAI-Marchetti SF-260WL Warrior (modified).jpg|thumb|An SF 260C in France, painted in the Burkina Faso Air Force livery]]
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#acc;&quot;|Aircraft
! style=&quot;text-align: center; background:#acc;&quot;|Origin
! style=&quot;text-align:l center; background:#acc;&quot;|Type
! style=&quot;text-align:left; background:#acc;&quot;|Variant
! style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#acc;&quot;|In service
! style=&quot;text-align: center; background:#acc;&quot;|Notes
|-
! style=&quot;align: center; background: lavender;&quot; colspan=&quot;7&quot; | [[Military aircraft#Combat aircraft|Combat Aircraft]]
|-
| [[Embraer EMB 314 Super Tucano|Embraer EMB-314]]
| [[Brazil]]
| light attack 
|
| 3&lt;ref name=&quot;World Air Forces 2020&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last = |first = |url= https://www.flightglobal.com/reports/world-air-forces-2020/135665.article|title = World Air Forces 2020|work= |publisher= Flightglobal Insight |year= 2020 |doi = |accessdate= 10 February 2020|url-access=registration}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|
|-
! style=&quot;align: center; background: lavender;&quot; colspan=&quot;7&quot; | [[Military transport aircraft |Transport]]
|-
| [[Beechcraft Super King Air]]
| [[United States]]
| transport
| [[Beechcraft Super King Air#Variants|200]]
| 1&lt;ref name=&quot;World Air Forces 2020&quot;/&gt;
|
|-
! style=&quot;align: center; background: lavender;&quot; colspan=&quot;7&quot; | [[Helicopters]]
|-
| [[Mil Mi-17]]
| [[Russia]]
| utility
|Mi-171
| 3
|2 on order&lt;ref name=&quot;World Air Forces 2020&quot;/&gt;
|-
| [[Mil Mi-24]]
| [[Russia]]
| attack
|
| 2&lt;ref name=&quot;World Air Forces 2020&quot;/&gt;
|
|-
| [[Bell UH-1 Iroquois|Bell UH-1]]
| [[United States]] 
| utility
| [[Bell UH-1 Iroquois variants#UH-1H|UH-1H]]
| 2&lt;ref name=&quot;World Air Forces 2020&quot;/&gt;
| donated by the Government of [[Taiwan]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Cherisey, de|first1=Erwan|title=Burkina Faso receives Taiwanese Hueys|url=http://www.janes.com/article/71282/|website=IHS Jane's 360|accessdate=12 June 2017|archiveurl=https://archive.today/20170612153635/http://www.janes.com/article/71282/burkina-faso-receives-taiwanese-hueys|archivedate=12 June 2017|location=Paris|date=9 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Eurocopter AS350]]
| [[France]]
| utility 
|
|1&lt;ref name=&quot;World Air Forces 2020&quot;/&gt;
|
|-
! style=&quot;align: center; background: lavender;&quot; colspan=&quot;7&quot; | [[Trainer (aircraft)|Trainer Aircraft]]
|-
|[[SIAI-Marchetti SF.260]]
| [[Italy]]
| basic trainer 
|
|4&lt;ref name=&quot;World Air Forces 2020&quot;/&gt;
| 
|}

==Notes==

{{reflist}}

==References==
*''World aircraft information files Brightstar publishing London File 338 sheet 4

==Further reading==
{{commons category}}
*Alan Bryden, Boubacar N'Diaye, 'Security Sector Governance in Francophone West Africa: Realities and Opportunities,' DCAF/Lit Verlag, 2011.
*Cooper, Tom &amp; Weinert, Peter (2010). African MiGs: Volume I: Angola to Ivory Coast. Harpia Publishing LLC. {{ISBN|978-0-9825539-5-4}}.

{{Military of Africa}}
{{Burkina Faso topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Military Of Burkina Faso}}
[[Category:Military of Burkina Faso| ]]</text>
      <sha1>ha6cyfjgveljy98iirxbbp34z0eam9e</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
