  <page>
    <title>Telecommunications in Burkina Faso</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3681</id>
    <revision>
      <id>932737959</id>
      <parentid>915027692</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-27T22:56:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Monkbot</username>
        <id>20483999</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* External links */[[User:Monkbot/task 15: normalize lang icon templates|Task 15]]:  language icon template(s) replaced (1×);</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Telecommunications in Burkina Faso''' include radio, television, fixed and mobile telephones, and the Internet.

Radio is the country's most popular communications medium. Use of telecommunications in [[Burkina Faso]] are extremely low, limited due to the low penetration of electricity, even in major cities. There were just 141,400 fixed line phones in use in 2012, in a country with a population of 17.4 million. Use of mobile phones has skyrocketed from 1.0 million lines in 2006 to 10 million in 2012. Internet use is also low, with only 3.7 users per 100 inhabitants in 2012, just over 643,000 users total. The Internet penetration rate in Africa as a whole was 16 users per 100 inhabitants in 2013.

==Regulation and control==

The constitution and law provide for [[freedom of speech]] and of the [[freedom of the press|press]], and the government generally respects these rights in practice.&lt;ref name=USDOS-CRHRP-BurkinaFaso-2012/&gt;

All media are under the administrative and technical supervision of the Ministry of Communications, which is responsible for developing and implementing government policy on information and communication. The Superior Council of Communication (SCC), a semiautonomous body under the Office of the President, monitors the content of radio and television programs, newspapers, and Internet [[Web sites]] to ensure compliance with professional ethics standards and government policy. The SCC may summon journalists and issue warnings for subsequent violations. Hearings may concern alleged libel, disturbing the peace, inciting violence, or violations of state security.&lt;ref name=USDOS-CRHRP-BurkinaFaso-2012/&gt;

Journalists occasionally face criminal [[libel]] prosecutions and other forms of harassment and intimidation. In addition to the prohibition against insulting the head of state, the law also prohibits the publication of shocking images and lack of respect for the deceased. Although the government does not attempt to impede criticism, some journalists practice [[self-censorship]].&lt;ref name=USDOS-CRHRP-BurkinaFaso-2012/&gt;

The Burkinabé government, in its telecommunications development strategy, has stated its aim to make telecommunications a [[universal service]] accessible to all. A large portion of this strategy is the privatization of the National Telecommunications Office (ONATEL), with an additional focus on a rural telephony promotion project. In 2006 the government sold a 51 percent stake in the national telephone company, ONATEL, and ultimately planned to retain only a 23 percent stake in the company.&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-BurkinaFaso-2014/&gt;

==Radio and television==

* [[Radio broadcasting|Radio stations]]: 2 AM, 26 FM, and 3 shortwave stations;&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-BurkinaFaso-2008&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20080611045303/https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/uv.html &quot;Communications: Burkina Faso&quot;], ''World Factbook'', U.S. Central Intelligence Agency, 15 May 2008. Retrieved 11 February 2014 via the Internet Archive.&lt;/ref&gt; state-owned radio runs a national and regional network; substantial number of privately owned radio stations; transmissions of several international broadcasters available in Ouagadougou (2007).&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-BurkinaFaso-2014&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/uv.html &quot;Communications: Burkina Faso&quot;], ''World Factbook'', U.S. Central Intelligence Agency, 28 January 2014. Retrieved 11 February 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Television broadcasting|Television stations]]: 1 state-owned and 1 privately owned (2007).&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-BurkinaFaso-2014/&gt;

Radio is the country's most popular communications medium. Dozens of private and community radio stations and a handful of private TV channels operate alongside their state-run counterparts. The [[BBC World Service]], [[Voice of America]], and [[Radio France Internationale]] are all on the air in the capital, [[Ouagadougou]].&lt;ref name=BBCNews-BurkinaFasoProfile-2012&gt;[https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-13072778 &quot;Burkina Faso profile&quot;], ''BBC News'', 14 August 2012. Retrieved 11 February 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Telephones==

* [[Calling code]]: +226&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-BurkinaFaso-2014/&gt; 
* [[List of international call prefixes|International call prefix]]: 00&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.itu.int/dms_pub/itu-t/opb/sp/T-SP-E.164C-2011-PDF-E.pdf ''Dialing Procedures (International Prefix, National (Trunk) Prefix and National (Significant) Number) (in Accordance with ITY-T Recommendation E.164 (11/2010))], Annex to ITU Operational Bulletin No. 994-15.XII.2011, International Telecommunication Union (ITU, Geneva), 15 December 2011. Retrieved 2 January 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Main lines: 
** 141,400 lines in use (2012);&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-BurkinaFaso-2014/&gt;
** &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;94,800 lines in use, 144th in the world (2006).&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-BurkinaFaso-2008/&gt;
* Mobile cellular: 
** 10.0 million lines, 79th in the world (2012);&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-BurkinaFaso-2014/&gt;
** &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;1.0 million lines, 123rd in the world (2006).&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-BurkinaFaso-2008/&gt;
* Telephone system: system includes [[microwave radio relay]], open-wire, and [[radiotelephone]] communication stations; fixed-line connections stand at less than 1 per 100 persons; mobile-cellular usage, fostered by multiple providers, is increasing rapidly from a low base (2011).&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-BurkinaFaso-2014/&gt;
* [[Communications satellite|Satellite earth stations]]: 1 [[Intelsat]] (Atlantic Ocean) (2011).&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-BurkinaFaso-2014/&gt;
* [[List of international submarine communications cables|Communications cables]]: Burkina Faso is linked to the global submarine cable network and the international Internet backbone through Senegal's Sonatel fibre-optic transmission network.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.itu.int/ITU-D/finance/work-cost-tariffs/events/tariff-seminars/Geneva-IIC/pdf/Session4_Drame_presentation_en.pdf &quot;Internet connectivity in Senegal&quot;], slide 15, Aminata Drame, ITU workshop on &quot;Apportionment of revenues and international Internet connectivity&quot;, Geneva, Switzerland, 23–24 January 2012. Retrieved 11 February 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

Use of mobile phones has skyrocketed in the last decade, growing from 2,700 subscribers in 1998,  to 1.0 million in 2006,&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-BurkinaFaso-2008/&gt; to 10.0 million in 2012.&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-BurkinaFaso-2014/&gt; Competition was introduced to the mobile telephone segment in 2000 between operators [[Celtel]] (now [[Bharti Airtel]]), Télécel Faso (now Moov), and Telmob (ONATEL). This pushed rates down even as density and coverage area increased.{{citation needed |date=February 2014}} Mobile phone users utilize &quot;flashing&quot; which allows extremely low-cost operations and Burkina Faso's ancient oral tradition and [[talking drum]] culture have harmonized well the introduction of mobile phone technologies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Burkina Faso 2013&quot;&gt;Historical Dictionary of Burkina Faso, by Lawrence Rupley, Lamissa Bangali, Boureima Diamitani, (see '''Telecommunications''') 2013, Third edition, Scarecrow Press, Inc. {{ISBN|978-0-8108-6770-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, mobile phone owners have acquired status by being able to loan their phones to others in their communities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Burkina Faso 2013&quot;/&gt;

ONATEL, majority-owned by [[Maroc Telecom]], operates the country's fixed-line network, a [[CDMA2000]] wireless network, a fibre optic backbone, and a [[GSM]] mobile network, Telmob.&lt;ref name=Budde-BurkinaFaso-2014/&gt;

==Internet==

* [[Top-level domain]]: [[.bf]]&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-BurkinaFaso-2014/&gt;
* [[List of countries by number of Internet users|Internet users]]: 
**  643,504 users, 127th in the world; 3.7% of the population, 194th in the world (2012);&lt;ref name=NIUCalc&gt;Calculated using penetration rate and population data from [https://www.census.gov/population/international/data/idb/rank.php &quot;Countries and Areas Ranked by Population: 2012&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170329060848/https://www.census.gov/population/international/data/idb/rank.php |date=2017-03-29 }}, Population data, International Programs,  U.S. Census Bureau, retrieved 26 June 2013&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ITU-IndividualsUsingTheInternet&gt;[http://www.itu.int/en/ITU-D/Statistics/Documents/statistics/2013/Individuals_Internet_2000-2012.xls &quot;Percentage of Individuals using the Internet 2000-2012&quot;], International Telecommunications Union (Geneva), June 2013, retrieved 22 June 2013&lt;/ref&gt;
** 178,100 users, 144th in the world (2009);&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-BurkinaFaso-2014/&gt;
** &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;80,000, 146th in the world (2006).&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-BurkinaFaso-2008/&gt;
* [[List of countries by number of broadband Internet subscriptions|Fixed broadband]]: 14,166 subscriptions, 139th in the world; 0.1% of population, 169th in the world (2012).&lt;ref name=NIUCalc/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;FixedBroadbandITUDynamic2012&quot;&gt;[http://www.itu.int/ITU-D/ICTEYE/Reporting/DynamicReportWizard.aspx &quot;Fixed (wired)-broadband subscriptions per 100 inhabitants 2012&quot;], Dynamic Report, ITU ITC EYE, [[International Telecommunication Union]]. Retrieved on 29 June 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[List of countries by number of broadband Internet subscriptions|Wireless broadband]]: Unknown (2012).&lt;ref name=&quot;MobleBroadbandITUDynamic2012&quot;&gt;[http://www.itu.int/ITU-D/ICTEYE/Reporting/DynamicReportWizard.aspx &quot;Active mobile-broadband subscriptions per 100 inhabitants 2012&quot;], Dynamic Report, ITU ITC EYE, [[International Telecommunication Union]]. Retrieved on 29 June 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[List of countries by number of Internet hosts|Internet hosts]]:
** 1,795, 164th in the world (2012);&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-BurkinaFaso-2014/&gt; 
** &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;193 hosts, 178th in the world (2007).&lt;ref name=CIAWFB-BurkinaFaso-2008/&gt;
* [[List of countries by IPv4 address allocation|IPv4]]: 32,512 addresses allocated, less than 0.05% of the world total, 1.9 addresses per 1000 people (2012).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.countryipblocks.net/country-blocks/select-formats/ Select Formats] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090513033601/http://www.countryipblocks.net/country-blocks/select-formats/ |date=2009-05-13 }}, Country IP Blocks. Accessed on 2 April 2012. Note: Site is said to be updated daily.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/fields/2119.html Population], [[The World Factbook]], [[United States]] [[Central Intelligence Agency]]. Accessed on 2 April 2012. Note: Data are mostly for 1 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Internet Service Provider]]s: 1 ISP (1999).{{update after|2014|2|11}}

Internet use is low, but the sector began to improve following installation of a 22 Mbit/s [[fiber optic]] international link, a vast improvement over the previous 128 kbit/s link. Secondary access nodes began to appear in major cities, and [[cybercafé]]s were providing Internet access to a broader spectrum of end users.{{citation needed |date=February 2014}}

ONATEL's FasoNet is the country's leading wired Internet service provider, dominating the broadband market with its [[ADSL]] and [[EV-DO]] fixed-wireless offerings.&lt;ref name=Budde-BurkinaFaso-2014&gt;[http://www.budde.com.au/Research/Burkina-Faso-Telecoms-Mobile-and-Broadband.html &quot;Burkina Faso - Telecoms, Mobile and Broadband&quot;], BuddeComm, 29 January 2014. Retrieved 11 February 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

The mobile operators are offering data services using [[GPRS]] and [[EDGE]] technology, and [[3G|third generation]] (3G) mobile broadband technology was not introduced until 2013 by Bharti Airtel.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.itnewsafrica.com/2013/05/airtel-launches-first-3-75-g-service-in-burkina-faso/ &quot;Airtel launches first 3.75 G service in Burkina Faso&quot;], IT News Africa, 28 May 2013. Retrieved 19 April 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

A March 2013 ITU ''Study on international Internet connectivity in sub-Saharan Africa'' reports that the Burkina Faso &quot;Internet market is not sufficiently dynamic and competitive&quot; and that the high costs for Internet capable mobile phones (more than six times the cost of a basic mobile phone) and mobile Internet subscriptions (up to seven times the cost for basic mobile) limit the number of Internet users.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.itu.int/en/ITU-D/Regulatory-Market/Documents/IIC_Africa_Final-en.pdf ''Study on international Internet connectivity in sub-Saharan Africa''], Abossé Akue-Kpakpo, International Telecommunications Union (ITU), March 2013. Retrieved 11 February 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Internet censorship and surveillance===

There are no government restrictions on access to the Internet; however, the Superior Council of Communication (SCC) monitors Internet [[Web sites]] and [[discussion forums]] to ensure compliance with existing regulations. For example, in May 2012 the SCC issued a warning to a Web site on which a user had allegedly insulted [[Blaise Compaoré|President Compaore]] in an Internet forum.&lt;ref name=USDOS-CRHRP-BurkinaFaso-2012&gt;[https://2009-2017.state.gov/j/drl/rls/hrrpt/humanrightsreport/index.htm?year=2012&amp;dlid=204094 &quot;Burkina Faso&quot;], ''Country Reports on Human Rights Practices for 2012'', Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights and Labor, U.S. Department of State, 18 April 2013. Retrieved 11 February 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

The constitution and law provide for [[freedom of speech]] and of the [[freedom of the press|press]], and the government generally respects these rights in practice. The law prohibits persons from insulting the head of state or using derogatory language with respect to the office; however, individuals criticize the government publicly or privately without reprisal.&lt;ref name=USDOS-CRHRP-BurkinaFaso-2012/&gt;

The constitution and law prohibit arbitrary interference with privacy, family, home, or correspondence, and the government generally respects these prohibitions in practice. In cases of national security, however, the law permits surveillance, searches, and monitoring of telephones and private correspondence without a warrant.&lt;ref name=USDOS-CRHRP-BurkinaFaso-2012/&gt;

==See also==

* [[Radio Télévision du Burkina]], national broadcaster of Burkina Faso.
* [[Telephone numbers in Burkina Faso]]
* [[Maroc Telecom]], a 51% owner of ONATEL since December 2006.
* [[List of terrestrial fibre optic cable projects in Africa]]
* [[Media in Burkina Faso]]
* [[Economy of Burkina Faso]]
* [[Burkina Faso]]

==References==

* {{CIA World Factbook}}
* {{US DOS |year=2012}}
{{reflist |30em}}

==External links==
* [http://www.artel.bf/ ''Autorité de régulation des communications électroniques''] (ARCE, Regulatory authority for electronic communications) {{in lang|fr}}, registrar for the .bf domain.

{{Clear}}
{{Africa topic|Telecommunications in}}
{{Telecommunications}}
{{Internet censorship by country}}
{{Economy of Burkina Faso}}
{{Burkina Faso topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Telecommunications In Burkina Faso}}
[[Category:Telecommunications in Burkina Faso| ]]</text>
      <sha1>ph6h3ilx1cnvt58yt99g5aechyctmxy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
