  <page>
    <title>Politics of Botswana</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3615</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940884165</id>
      <parentid>924496770</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-15T06:09:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DemonDays64</username>
        <id>34607323</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Updated</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Political system of Botswana}}
{{More citations needed|date=April 2008}}

{{Politics of Botswana}}
'''Politics of Botswana''' takes place in a framework of a [[parliamentary system|parliamentary]] [[representative democracy|representative democratic]] [[republic]], whereby the [[President of Botswana]] is both [[head of state]] and [[head of government]], and of a  [[multi-party system]]. [[Executive power]] is exercised by the government. [[Legislative power]] is vested in both the [[Forms of government|government]] and the [[Parliament of Botswana]]. The party system has been dominated by the [[Botswana Democratic Party]] (BDP), which has never lost power since independence. The [[Judiciary]] is independent of the executive and the legislature.

[[Botswana]] is formally a multiparty constitutional democracy. Each of the elections since independence in September 1966 has been freely and fairly contested and has been held on schedule. The country's small white minority and other minorities participate freely in the political process. There are two main rival parties and a number of smaller parties. General elections are held at least every five years.&lt;ref&gt;[https://2009-2017.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/1830.htm Background Note: Botswana]&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Democracy Index rating|Botswana|flawed democracy|2019}}

==Legislative branch==

[[File:BotswanaParliament.jpg|thumb|left|[[National Assembly (Botswana)|National Assembly of Botswana]].]]
The National Assembly has 57 elected and 4 appointed members;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bartleby.com/151/fields/59.html]&lt;/ref&gt; it is expanded following each census (every 10 years). After elections, the party that wins the majority elects the State  President. The President then appoints the Vice President, but the appointment is subject to endorsement by the National Assembly.

There are 57 [[Parliamentary constituencies of Botswana|parliamentary constituencies]] in Botswana.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.parliament.gov.bw/pgcontent.php?UID=615|title=Constituencies|publisher=Parliament of Botswana|accessdate=2010-08-03|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110706163056/https://www.parliament.gov.bw/pgcontent.php?UID=615|archivedate=2011-07-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The advisory House of Chiefs represents the eight principal subgroups of the [[Batswana]] people, and four other members are elected by the subchiefs of four of the districts. A draft of any National Assembly bill of tribal concern must be referred to the House of Chiefs for advisory opinion. Chiefs and other leaders preside over customary, traditional courts, though all persons have the right to request that their case be considered under the formal British-based legal system.{{citation needed| date= October 2017}}

==Local government==

Local government is administered by nine district councils and five town councils. District commissioners have executive authority and are appointed by the central government and assisted by elected and nominated district councilors and district development committees. There has been ongoing debate about the political, social, and economic marginalization of the [[San people|San]] (Bushmen). The government's policies for remote area dwellers continue to spark controversy and may be revised in response to domestic and donor concerns.{{Citation needed|date=April 2008}}

==Political parties and elections==
{{elect|List of political parties in Botswana|Elections in Botswana}}
{{Main|Botswana general election, 2014}}

==Judicial branch==
The highest court of Botswana is the [[Court of Appeal (Botswana)|Court of Appeal]], which is constituted under section 99 of these Constitution and consists of a President and such number of Justices of Appeal as may be prescribed by Parliament.&lt;ref name=&quot;constitution&quot;&gt;[http://www.chr.up.ac.za/undp/domestic/docs/c_Botswana.pdf Constitution of Botswana]&lt;/ref&gt; There are currently eight judges of the Court of Appeal, who are all expatriates drawn from different parts of the [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth]]. To date, no Motswana has ever been appointed to the Court of Appeal.&lt;ref name=&quot;hierarchy&quot;&gt;[http://www.gov.bw/en/Ministries--Authorities/Ministries/Administration-of-Justice-AOJ/About-AOJ1/The-Hierarchy-of-the-Courts/ Republic of Botswana: The Hierarchy of the Courts]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[High Court (Botswana)|High Court]] is a superior court of record with unlimited original jurisdiction to hear and determine any criminal and civil cases under any law. The High Court is constituted under section 95 of the Constitution, and consists of a Chief Justice and such number of other judges of the High Court as may be prescribed by Parliament.&lt;ref name=&quot;constitution&quot; /&gt; There are currently sixteen permanent judges of the High Court. Until 1992, the judges of the High Court were expatriate judges who were appointed on short-term contracts of two to three years. In 1992 the first citizen judges were appointed to the bench. There are three High Court divisions in [[Lobatse]], [[Gaborone]] and [[Francistown]].&lt;ref name=&quot;hierarchy&quot; /&gt;

There are also [[Magistrates' Courts]] in Botswana. These courts are subordinate to the High Court and hear a range of civil, criminal and family law matters. There are nineteen Magistrates' Courts in the country, with fifty magistrates of whom seventeen are expatriate.&lt;ref name=&quot;hierarchy&quot; /&gt;

Judges are appointed by the president and may be removed only for cause and after a hearing.

[http://www.saflii.org/bw/cases/BWCA/ Judgments of the Botswana Court of Appeal]

[http://www.saflii.org/bw/cases/BWHC/ Judgments of the Botswana High Court]

==International organization participation==
ACP, AfDB, C, ECA, FAO, G-77, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, [[International Criminal Court|ICCt]], ICFTU, ICRM, IDA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, ILO, IMF, Interpol, IOC, ISO, ITU, NAM, OAU, OPCW, SACU, SADC, UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNIDO, UPU, WCO, WFTU, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO, WT. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://fortuneofafrica.com/botswana/2014/01/23/membership-of-international-organisations-of-botswana/ | title= Membership of international organisations of Botswana |accessdate= October 23, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Politics}}
* [[Botswana Prison Service]]
* [http://www.gov.bw/ Republic of Botswana - Government portal]

==References==
{{Reflist}}
{{Africa in topic|Politics of}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Politics Of Botswana}}
[[Category:Politics of Botswana| ]]</text>
      <sha1>qovh3a0u5iw783q1oa77ggomet82b3w</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
