  <page>
    <title>Bogie</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4640</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939528031</id>
      <parentid>938943746</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-07T00:54:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead.) #IABot (v2.0</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{other uses}}
{{About|wheeled wagons and trolleys|other uses of &quot;bogie&quot; or &quot;bogey&quot;|Bogey (disambiguation){{!}}Bogey}}
{{Redirect|Bogi|the Hungarian singer|Bogi (singer)|the Tamil festival|Bhogi}}
{{Distinguish|Boogie}}
{{Globalize|date=February 2015}}
{{Use British English|date=November 2014}}
{{Train topics}}
[[File:Bogie Vehicle Schematic-en.svg|thumb|400px|right|Bogies allow the [[Wheelset (rail transport)|wheelsets]] to more closely follow the direction of the rails when travelling around a curve in the railroad.]]
[[File:Railroad truck, FM55-20.Fig8-8.png|thumb|right|400px|A diagram of an American-style truck showing the names of its parts and showing the [[journal box]]es to be integral parts of the [[Truck side frame|side frame]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://patents.google.com/patent/US1924237A/en|title=Bogie truck for railway and like vehicles|website=google.com|accessdate=8 May 2018|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20180508093532/https://patents.google.com/patent/US1924237A/en|archivedate=8 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;col&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SCT&quot; /&gt; The journal boxes house [[plain bearing]]s]]

A '''bogie''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|b|oʊ|ɡ|i}} {{Respell|BOH|ghee}})&lt;!-- Sound does not work. --&gt; (in some [[Word sense|senses]] called a '''truck''' in North American English) is a [[chassis]] or framework that carries a [[Wheelset (rail transport)|wheelset]], attached to a vehicle—a [[Modularity|modular]] subassembly of [[Railroad wheel|wheels]] and [[axle]]s. Bogies take various forms in various modes of transport. A bogie may remain normally attached (as on many [[railroad car]]s and [[semi-trailer]]s) or be quickly detachable (as the [[dolly (trailer)|dolly]] in a [[road train]] or in railway [[bogie exchange]]); it may contain a [[Suspension (vehicle)|suspension]] within it (as most rail and trucking bogies do), or be solid and in turn be suspended (as most bogies of [[continuous track|tracked]] vehicles are); it may be mounted on a [[swivel]], as traditionally on a railway carriage or locomotive, additionally jointed and sprung (as in the [[landing gear]] of an [[airliner]]), or held in place by other means (centreless bogies).

While ''bogie'' is the preferred spelling and first-listed variant in various dictionaries,&lt;ref name=&quot;MWCD&quot;&gt;{{Citation | author = Merriam-Webster | authorlink = Merriam-Webster | title = Merriam-Webster's Collegiate Dictionary | publisher = Merriam-Webster |url=http://unabridged.merriam-webster.com/collegiate/bogie |postscript=.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AHD5&quot;&gt;{{Citation |author=Houghton Mifflin Harcourt |authorlink=Houghton Mifflin Harcourt |title=American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language |edition=5th |publisher=Houghton Mifflin Harcourt |url=https://ahdictionary.com/word/search.html?q=bogie&amp;submit.x=0&amp;submit.y=0 |postscript=. |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150714054614/https://ahdictionary.com/word/search.html?q=bogie&amp;submit.x=0&amp;submit.y=0 |archivedate=2015-07-14 |access-date=2014-11-24 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;OxfordDictionaries&quot;&gt;{{Citation | author = Oxford Dictionaries Online | authorlink = OxfordDictionaries.com | title = Oxford Dictionaries Online | publisher = [[Oxford University Press]] | url = http://www.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/bogie?searchDictCode=all | postscript = . | url-status = live | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20141202033058/http://www.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/bogie?searchDictCode=all | archivedate = 2014-12-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt; '''bogey''' and '''bogy''' are also used.&lt;ref name=&quot;MWCD&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AHD5&quot; /&gt;


== Railway ==
A ''bogie'' in the UK, or a ''railroad truck'', ''wheel truck'', or simply ''truck'' in North America, is a structure underneath a [[railway vehicle]] (wagon, coach or locomotive) to which axles (and, hence, wheels) are attached through [[Bearing (mechanical)|bearing]]s. In [[Indian English]], ''bogie'' may also refer to an entire [[railway carriage]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oxfordadvancedlearnersdictionary.com/dictionary/bogie|title=Oxford Learner's Dictionaries - Find definitions, translations, and grammar explanations at Oxford Learner's Dictionaries|website=www.oxfordadvancedlearnersdictionary.com|accessdate=8 May 2018|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110807101435/http://www.oxfordadvancedlearnersdictionary.com/dictionary/bogie|archivedate=2011-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[South Africa]], the term ''bogie'' is often alternatively used to refer to a freight or goods wagon (shortened from ''[[bogie wagon]]'').

The first standard gauge British railway to build coaches with bogies, instead of rigidly mounted axles, was the [[Midland Railway]] in 1874.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Jenkinson |first=David |authorlink=David Jenkinson |title=British Railway Carriages of the 20th Century - Volume 1: The end of an era, 1901-22 |year=1988 |publisher=Guild Publishing |location=London |id=CN 8130 |page=10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Purpose===
Bogies serve a number of purposes:&lt;ref name=&quot;how&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | author = Isao Okamoto | date = December 1998 | title = How Bogies Work | journal = Japan Railway &amp; Transport Review | issue = 18 | pages = 52–61 | url = http://www.jrtr.net/jrtr18/pdf/f52_technology.pdf | url-status = dead | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070927202523/http://www.jrtr.net/jrtr18/pdf/f52_technology.pdf | archivedate = 2007-09-27 | access-date = 2018-11-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Support of the rail vehicle body
* Stability on both straight and curved track
* Improve [[ride quality]] by absorbing vibration and minimizing the impact of centrifugal forces when the train runs on curves at high speed
* Minimizing generation of track irregularities and rail abrasion

Usually, two bogies are fitted to each [[Railroad car|carriage]], wagon or [[locomotive]], one at each end. Another configuration is often used in [[articulated vehicle]]s, which places the bogies (often [[Jacobs bogie]]s) under the connection between the carriages or wagons.

Most bogies have two axles,&lt;ref name=&quot;how&quot; /&gt; but some cars designed for heavy loads have more axles per bogie. Heavy-duty cars may have more than two bogies using [[span bolster]]s to equalize the load and connect the bogies to the cars.

Usually, the train floor is at a level above the bogies, but the floor of the car may be lower between bogies, such as for a [[bilevel rail car]] to increase interior space while staying within [[Loading gauge|height restrictions]], or in easy-access, stepless-entry, low-floor trains.

===Components===
{{Main| List of railroad truck parts}}
Key components of a bogie include:&lt;ref name=&quot;how&quot; /&gt;
* The bogie frame: This can be of inside frame type where the main frame and bearings are between the wheels, or (more commonly) of outside frame type where the main frame and bearings are outside the wheels.
* [[suspension (vehicle)|Suspension]] to absorb shocks between the bogie frame and the rail vehicle body. Common types are [[coil spring]]s, [[leaf spring]]s and [[rubber]] [[Air suspension|airbags]]. 
* At least one [[Wheelset (rail transport)|wheelset]], composed of an axle with [[Bearing (mechanical)|bearings]] and a wheel at each end.
* The [[List of railroad truck parts#Truck bolster|bolster]], the main crossmember, connected to the bogie frame through the secondary suspension. The railway car is supported at the pivot point on the bolster.
* Axle box suspensions absorb shocks between the axle bearings and the bogie frame. The axle box suspension usually consists of a spring between the bogie frame and axle bearings to permit up-and-down movement, and sliders to prevent lateral movement. A more modern design uses solid rubber springs.
* [[Brake (railway)|Brake equipment]]: Two main types are used: [[brake shoe]]s that are pressed against the tread of the wheel, and [[Disc brake#Railroad and tram use|disc brakes]] and pads.
* In powered vehicles, some form of [[Transmission (mechanics)|transmission]], usually electrically powered [[traction motor]]s or a hydraulically powered [[torque converter]].

The connections of the bogie with the rail vehicle allow a certain degree of rotational movement around a vertical axis pivot (bolster), with side bearers preventing excessive movement. More modern, bolsterless bogie designs omit these features, instead taking advantage of the sideways movement of the suspension to permit rotational movement.&lt;ref name=&quot;how&quot; /&gt;

=== Examples ===

==== Commonwealth bogie ====
[[File:Commonwealth bogie.jpg|thumb|Commonwealth bogie as used on BR Mark 1 and CIE Park Royals]]

The Commonwealth bogie was manufactured by the [[English Steel Corporation]] under licence from the [[Commonwealth Steel Company]] in [[Illinois]], United States. Fitted with [[SKF]] or [[Timken Company|Timken]] bearings, it was introduced in the late 1950s for all [[BR Mark 1]] vehicles. It was a heavy, cast-steel design weighing about {{convert|6.5|LT|t ST|lk=on}},&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Parkin |first=Keith |title=British Railways Mark 1 Coaches |year=1991 |publisher=Pendragon |location=Penryn |isbn=0-906899-49-4 |page=35 |ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; with sealed roller bearings on the axle ends, avoiding the need to maintain [[axle box]] oil levels.

The [[leaf spring]]s were replaced by coil springs (one per wheel) running vertically rather than horizontally. The advanced design gave a better ride quality than the BR1, being rated for {{convert|100|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}.

The side frame of the bogie was usually of bar construction, with simple horn guides attached, allowing the axle boxes vertical movements between them.  The axle boxes had a cast-steel equaliser beam or bar resting on them.  The bar had two steel coil springs placed on it and the bogie frame rested on the springs.  The effect was to allow the bar to act as a compensating lever between the two axles and to use both springs to soften shocks from either axle.  The bogie had a conventional bolster suspension with swing links carrying a spring plank.

==== B4 bogie ====
[[File:Bogie BT4.JPG|thumb|B4 bogie as used on BR Mark 2 and Irish Cravens]]

The B4 bogie was introduced in 1963.  It was a fabricated steel design versus cast iron and was lighter than the Commonwealth, weighing in at {{convert|5|LT|t ST|2}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Parkin|1991|p=37}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also had a speed rating of {{convert|100|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}.

Axle to spring connection was again  fitted with roller bearings.  However, now two coil springs rather than one were fitted per wheel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wsr.org.uk/bogies.htm|title=WSR :: West Somerset Railway :: Bogies|website=www.wsr.org.uk|accessdate=8 May 2018|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20171103043931/http://www.wsr.org.uk/bogies.htm|archivedate=3 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Only a very small number of Mark 1 stock was fitted with the B4 bogie from new, it being used on the Mark 1 only to replace worn BR1 bogies.  The [[British Rail Mark 2]] coach, however, carried the B4 bogies from new. A heavier-duty version, the B5, was standard on Southern Region Mk1-based EMUs from the 1960s onwards. Some Mark 1 catering cars had mixed bogies—a B5 under the kitchen end, and a B4 under the seating end. Some of the B4-fitted Mark 2s, as well as many B4-fitted Mark 1 [[Brake Gangwayed|BGs]] were allowed to run at {{convert|110|mph}} with extra maintenance, particularly of the wheel profile, and more frequent inspection.

==== BT10 bogie ====
[[File:Bogie BT10.JPG|thumb|BT10 high-speed bogie as used on MK3]]

The BT10 bogie was introduced on the [[British Rail Mark 3]] coach in the 1970s. Each wheel is separately connected to the bogie by a swing-arm axle.

There is dual suspension:
* Primary suspension via a coil spring and damper mounted on each axle
* Secondary suspension via two air springs mounted on the pivot plank, this is connected to the bogie by pendulum links.  A constant coach height is maintained by air valves.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uctc.net/papers/114.pdf ''Roger Barnett'' - British Rail’s InterCity 125 and 225] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080529152114/http://www.uctc.net/papers/114.pdf |date=2008-05-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Locomotives ====

===== Diesel and electric =====
{{Main|UIC classification of locomotive axle arrangements|AAR wheel arrangement}}

[[Image:BNSF 6371 EMD SD40-2.jpg|right|thumb|280px|EMD#HT-C Trucks on&lt;br&gt;EMD#SD40-2 ~ BNSF#6731]]

Modern [[diesel locomotive|diesel]] and [[electric locomotive|electric]] locomotives are mounted on bogies.  Those commonly used in the North America include [[AAR type A switcher truck|Type A]], [[Blomberg B|Blomberg]], HT-C and [[Flexicoil]] trucks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hosam.com/emd/emd6a.html|title=trucks|website=www.hosam.com|accessdate=8 May 2018|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160409141649/http://www.hosam.com/emd/emd6a.html|archivedate=9 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===== Steam =====
On a [[steam locomotive]], the [[Leading wheel|leading]] and [[trailing wheel]]s may be mounted on bogies like [[pony truck]]s or [[Bissel bogie]]s.  [[Articulated locomotive]]s (e.g. [[Fairlie locomotive|Fairlie]], [[Garratt]] or [[Mallet locomotive|Mallet]] locomotives) have '''power bogies''' similar to those on diesel and electric locomotives.

==== Rollbock ====
A [[rollbock]] is a specialized type of bogie that is inserted under the wheels of a rail wagon/car, usually to convert for another [[track gauge]]. [[Transporter wagon]]s carry the same concept to the level of a [[flatcar]] specialized to take other cars as its load.

==== Archbar bogies ====
In archbar or diamond frame bogies, the [[List of railroad truck parts#Truck side frame|side frames]] are [[metal fabrication|fabricated]] rather than [[cast steel|cast]].
&lt;gallery mode=packed heights=&quot;160px&quot;&gt;
File:Oigawa-Archbar-Truck.jpg|Japanese archbar bogie with [[axlebox]]es
File:Diamond Frame bogie (elliptical).jpg|Diamond frame bogie, [[elliptical spring]]s and American style [[journal box]]es
File:Diamond Frame bogie (coil).JPG|Diamond frame bogie, [[coil spring]]s and [[journal box]]es
File:archbar ACL143.JPG |Archbar bogie with [[journal bearing]]s in American style journal boxes, as used on some steam locomotive tenders. Archbar bogies (trucks) were also used on [[Railway car#Freight cars|freight cars]].
File:Oigawa-Archbar-Truck.jpg |Japanese archbar truck with [[axlebox]]es
&lt;/gallery&gt;

=== Tramway ===

==== Modern ====
[[File:Septa PCC car truck.jpg|thumb|Side view of a [[SEPTA]] K-Car bogie]]

[[Tram]] bogies are much simpler in design because of their axle load, and the tighter curves found on tramways mean tram bogies almost never have more than two axles. Furthermore, some tramways have steeper gradients and vertical, as well as horizontal, curves, which means tram bogies often need to pivot on the horizontal axis, as well.

Some [[articulated tram]]s have bogies located under articulations, a setup referred to as a [[Jacobs bogie]]. Often, [[low-floor tram]]s are fitted with nonpivoting bogies and many [[tramway enthusiast]]s see this as a retrograde step, as it leads to more wear of both track and wheels and also significantly reduces the speed at which a tram can round a curve.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.railway2007.fd.cvut.cz/proceedings/Capek+Kolar.pdf |title=ČVUT.cz - Čapek, Kolář |format=PDF |accessdate=2010-05-12 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110718170646/http://www.railway2007.fd.cvut.cz/proceedings/Capek+Kolar.pdf |archivedate=2011-07-18 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Historic ====
In the past, many different types of bogie (truck) have been used under tramcars (e.g. [[J. G. Brill and Company|Brill]], Peckham, maximum traction).  A maximum traction truck has one driving axle with large wheels and one nondriving axle with smaller wheels.  The bogie pivot is located off-centre, so more than half the weight rests on the driving axle.

[[File:Crich-Bogie-wyrdlight-812322.jpg|thumb|upright|Workers maintaining an electro-mechanical bogie from a tram at [[National Tramway Museum|Crich Tramway Village]]]]

=== Hybrid systems ===
[[File:Bogie-metro-Meteor-p1010692.jpg|thumb|left|[[Mockup]] of the pneumatic bogie system of a [[MP 89]] carriage used on the [[Paris Métro Line 14|''Meteor'' metro]], showing the two [[Wheelset (rail transport)#Special wheelsets|special wheelsets]]]]
The retractable stadium roof on Toronto's [[Rogers Centre]] used modified off-the-shelf train bogies on a circular rail. The system was chosen for its proven reliability.

[[Rubber-tyred metro]] trains use a specialised version of railway bogies. Special flanged steel wheels are behind the rubber-tired running wheels, with additional horizontal guide wheels in front of and behind the running wheels, as well. The unusually large flanges on the steel wheels guide the bogie through standard [[railroad switch]]es, and in addition keep the train from [[derailment|derailing]] in case the tires deflate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.infovisual.info/05/050_en.html|title=Truck (bogie) - Visual Dictionary|first=Bernard|last=Dery|website=www.infovisual.info|accessdate=8 May 2018|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160616154008/http://infovisual.info/05/050_en.html|archivedate=16 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Variable gauge axles ===
{{main|Variable gauge}}
To overcome [[break of gauge|breaks of gauge]] some bogies are being fitted with variable gauge axles (VGA) so that they can operate on two different gauges.  These include the [[SUW 2000]] system from [[ZNTK Poznań]].

=== Cleminson system ===
The Cleminson system is not a true bogie, but serves a similar purpose. It was based on a patent of 1883 by James Cleminson,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.icevirtuallibrary.com/docserver/fulltext/imotp.1897.19461.pdf?expires=1315520526&amp;id=id&amp;accname=guest&amp;checksum=AD521ED02561C3CF38D1772ECF1ACA2B {{dead link|date=November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was once popular on narrow-gauge rolling stock, e.g. on the [[Isle of Man Railway rolling stock|Isle of Man]] and [[Manx Northern Railway]]s.  The vehicle would have three axles and the outer two could pivot to adapt to curvature of the track.  The pivoting was controlled by levers attached to the third (centre) axle, which could slide sideways.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.festipedia.org.uk/wiki/Cleminson_Flexible_Six-Wheeled_Waggon|title=Cleminson flexible six-wheeled waggon - Festipedia|website=www.festipedia.org.uk|accessdate=8 May 2018|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160317160428/https://www.festipedia.org.uk/wiki/Cleminson_Flexible_Six-Wheeled_Waggon|archivedate=17 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Tracked vehicles ==
Some [[tank]]s and other [[Caterpillar track|tracked]] vehicles have bogies as external suspension components (see [[suspension (vehicle)#Armoured fighting vehicle suspension|armoured fighting vehicle suspension]]). This type of bogie usually has two or more road wheels and some type of sprung suspension to smooth the ride across rough terrain. Bogie suspensions keep much of their components on the outside of the vehicle, saving internal space. Although vulnerable to [[antitank]] fire, they can often be repaired or replaced in the field.

== Articulated bogie ==
An '''articulated bogie''' is any one of a number of bogie designs that allow [[railway]] equipment to safely turn sharp corners, while reducing or eliminating the &quot;screeching&quot; normally associated with metal wheels rounding a bend in the rails. There are a number of such designs, and the term is also applied to train sets that incorporate articulation in the vehicle, as opposed to the bogies themselves.

If one considers a single bogie &quot;up close&quot;, it resembles a small rail car with axles at either end. The same effect that causes the bogies to rub against the rails at longer radius causes each of the pairs of wheels to rub on the rails and cause the screeching. Articulated bogies add a second pivot point between the two [[axle]]s ([[Wheelset (rail transport)|wheelsets]]) to allow them to rotate to the correct angle even in these cases.

== Articulated lorries (tractor-trailers) ==
&lt;!-- This section has absolutely nothing to do with [[locomotives]] or other [[railroad car]]s and no such article should be redirected to this section --&gt;
In [[Road transport#Trucking and hauling|trucking]], a bogie is the subassembly of axles and wheels that supports a [[semi-trailer]], whether permanently attached to the frame (as on a single trailer) or making up the [[dolly (trailer)|dolly]] that can be hitched and unhitched as needed when hitching up a second or third semi-trailer (as when [[semi-trailer|pulling doubles]] or [[road train|triples]]).

== Bogie (aircraft) ==
{{Main|Landing gear}}
[[File:Boeing-777-300 chassis .jpg|thumb|upright=1.14|Main landing gear leg and six-wheel '''bogie''' of a [[Boeing 777|Boeing 777-300]]]]
{{clear}}

== Images gallery ==

&lt;gallery class=&quot;center centered&quot; style=&quot;line-height:120%&quot; widths=220 heights=120 caption=&quot;Bogie images pool&quot;&gt;
 File:Wheelbase and Track.png |[[Axle track#Rail|Track = wheel gauge]] (measured between the gauge or flange reference lines of the [[flange]]s of [[Train wheel|railroad wheels]])

 File:Drehgestell SBB EC Waggon.jpg |Bogie of an [[Swiss Federal Railways|SBB]] [[Eurocity]] passenger car, as seen from underneath

 File:Reefers-shorty-Anheuser-Busch-Malt-Nutrine ACF builders photo pre-1911.jpg | [[Anheuser-Busch]] refrigerated rail car on [[archbar freight truck]]s

 File:Bettendorf truck at Illinois Railway Museum.JPG |North American [[William P. Bettendorf#Later career|''Bettendorf'']]-style &quot;Three Piece Bogie&quot; freight car &quot;truck&quot; with (now obsolete) [[journal bearing]]s in (now obsolete) [[journal box]]es&lt;ref name=&quot;col&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SCT&quot; /&gt; displayed at the [[Illinois Railway Museum]]. It has [[coil spring]]s.

 File:Journal box.png |A [[journal box]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Railroad Dictionary: J |url=http://www.csx.com/index.cfm/about-csx/company-overview/railroad-dictionary/?i=J |publisher=CSX Corporation |website=CSX.com |year=2012 |accessdate=15 November 2014 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140729221255/http://www.csx.com/index.cfm/about-csx/company-overview/railroad-dictionary/?i=J |archivedate=29 July 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; (no longer used on North American railways)&lt;ref name=&quot;col&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=AAR M-1003 Certified Truck Component Manufacturing|url=http://www.columbuscastings.com/bolster_frames.html|website=ColumbusCastings.com|publisher=Columbus Castings|location=Columbus, Ohio|accessdate=19 November 2014|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141019033202/http://www.columbuscastings.com/bolster_frames.html|archivedate=2014-10-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SCT&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=General Information |url=http://www.sctco.com/pdf/sect_1.pdf |website=SCTCO.com |publisher=Standard Car Truck Company |format=PDF |date=January 2000 |accessdate=19 November 2014 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304045504/http://www.sctco.com/pdf/sect_1.pdf |archivedate=4 March 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;)
File:JacobsBogieArticulatedWellCarCanadianPacificTrainBoltonON.jpg|Closeup of a bogie with specially adapted [[List of railroad truck parts#Side bearing|side bearings]]&lt;!-- Not a [[Jacobs bogie]] --&gt; between two sections of an [[Articulated car|articulated]] [[well car]]. The axle bearings are not enclosed by an axle box.
File:Seitenkipper-Ua4201-Drehgestell.jpg|[[William P. Bettendorf#Later career|''Bettendorf'']]-style &quot;Three Piece Bogie&quot; with [[axle box]]es, [[Pseudonym|aka]]. ''&quot;truck&quot;'' in the [[United States]]
File:SARCAST bogie.jpg|A sarcast bogie complete with [[journal box]]es
&lt;/gallery&gt;

&lt;gallery class=&quot;center centered&quot; style=&quot;line-height:120%&quot; widths=220 heights=100 caption=&quot;Bogie extra images pool imported from [[:de:Drehgestell]]&quot;&gt;

 Drehgestell 1845.jpg |[[:de:Dreh&amp;shy;ge&amp;shy;stell]] Würt&amp;shy;tem&amp;shy;ber&amp;shy;ger Bau&amp;shy;art von 1845

 2007-07 Halle (Saale) 21.jpg |Dia&amp;shy;mond-Dreh&amp;shy;ge&amp;shy;stell ei&amp;shy;nes Per&amp;shy;so&amp;shy;nen&amp;shy;wa&amp;shy;gens der [[:de:Mecklenburgisch-Pommersche Schmalspurbahn|MPSB]] um 1890

 Drehgestell 01 KMJ.jpg |Dreh&amp;shy;ge&amp;shy;stell Typ Y25 ge&amp;shy;schweißt mit 22,5-t-Radsätzen (häu&amp;shy;fig&amp;shy;stes Gü&amp;shy;ter&amp;shy;wa&amp;shy;gen&amp;shy;dreh&amp;shy;gestell in Eu&amp;shy;ro&amp;shy;pa)

 Y25-Drehgestell-an-Res-der-PKP.jpg |Das von der [[:de:Internationaler Eisenbahnverband|UIC]] stan&amp;shy;dar&amp;shy;di&amp;shy;sier&amp;shy;te [[:de:Drehgestell Bauart Y25|Y25-Dreh&amp;shy;ge&amp;shy;stell]] mit 1,80&amp;nbsp;m [[Radstand|Achs&amp;shy;stand]], hier an ei&amp;shy;nem [[Flachwagen#R: Flach&amp;shy;wa&amp;shy;gen in Re&amp;shy;gel&amp;shy;bau&amp;shy;art mit Dreh&amp;shy;ge&amp;shy;stel&amp;shy;len|Res-Wagen]] der [[Polskie Koleje Państwowe|PKP]]

 TVP 2007.jpg|Dreh&amp;shy;ge&amp;shy;stell des Typs TVP 2007 mit durch Kreuz&amp;shy;anker ge&amp;shy;steu&amp;shy;er&amp;shy;ten ra&amp;shy;dial ein&amp;shy;stell&amp;shy;ba&amp;shy;ren 25-t-Radsätzen. Die Bau&amp;shy;art ist aus dem Y25 ab&amp;shy;ge&amp;shy;lei&amp;shy;tet.

 Drehgestell-BA652-an-Shimmns-u-708.jpg |Das Dreh&amp;shy;ge&amp;shy;stell der [[Deutsche Bundesbahn|DB]]-Bau&amp;shy;art&amp;nbsp;652 mit [[Parabelfeder|Pa&amp;shy;ra&amp;shy;bel&amp;shy;fe&amp;shy;dern]] wurde von [[Linke-Hofmann-Busch|LHB]] ent&amp;shy;wickelt und ab 1986 ge&amp;shy;baut

&lt;/gallery&gt;

== See also ==
===Articles on bogies and trucks===
{{Div col|colwidth=20em}}
* [[Arnoux system]]
* [[Bissel bogie]]
* [[Blomberg B]]
* [[Gölsdorf axle]]
* [[ICF Bogie]]
* [[Jacobs bogie]]
* [[Krauss-Helmholtz bogie]]
* [[Lateral motion device]]
* [[Mason Bogie]]
* [[Pony truck]]
* [[Radial steering truck]]
* [[Rocker-bogie]]
* [[Scheffel bogie]]
* [[Schwartzkopff-Eckhardt II bogie]]
* [[Syntegra]]
{{div col end}}

===Related topics===
{{Div col|colwidth=20em}}
* [[Dolly (trailer)|Dolly]]
* [[Flange]]
* [[List of railroad truck parts]]
* [[Luttermöller axle]]
* [[Road–rail vehicle]]
* [[Spring (device)]]
* [[Timmis system]], an early form of coil spring used on railway axles.
* [[Trailing wheel]]
* [[Wheel arrangement]]
* [[Wheelset (rail transport)|Wheelset]]
{{Div col end}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Further reading ==
* {{cite book|last=Baur|first=Karl Gerhard|title=Drehgestelle - Bogies|year=2006|publisher=EK-Verlag|location=Freiburg i.B.|isbn=978-3-88255-147-1}} {{in lang|de|en}}

== External links ==
{{commons category|Bogies of rail vehicles|Bogie}}
* {{Wiktionary-inline|bogie}}
* {{cite EB1911|wstitle=Bogie |volume=4 |short=x}}
* [http://www.infovisual.info/05/050_en.html Truck (bogie) with tyres]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060823034931/http://www.rtu.mmu.ac.uk/pubs/Iwnicki%20Grassie%20Kik%20-%20Track%20Settlement%20prediction%20using%20computer%20simulation%20tools.pdf   Track modelling]
* [http://www.railway-technical.com/trains/rolling-stock-index-l/bogies.html Bogies/Trucks]

{{Locomotive running gear}}

[[Category:Bogie| ]]
[[Category:Locomotive parts]]
[[Category:Rail technologies]]
[[Category:Vehicle technology]]</text>
      <sha1>csw916jar9klsk2tuywazz10oaf8ugh</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
