  <page>
    <title>Boxing Day</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4681</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941816411</id>
      <parentid>941771817</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-20T21:17:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>NekoKatsun</username>
        <id>23242057</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted 1 pending edit by [[Special:Contributions/111.65.45.250|111.65.45.250]] to revision 941674379 by FlightTime: Source?</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Christmas box|the genus of shrubs|Sarcococca|other uses|Boxing Day (disambiguation)}}
{{short description|Public or bank holiday on 26 December, or the first or second weekday after Christmas Day}}
{{pp-pc|small=yes}}
{{EngvarB|date=December 2016}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2020}}
{{Infobox holiday
| holiday_name = Boxing Day
| nickname     = Offering Day&lt;ref name=&quot;Robb1984&quot;/&gt;
| longtype     = [[Bank holiday]], [[public holiday]]
| image        =
| caption      =
| observedby   = [[Member states of the Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth nations]]
| duration     = 1 day
| frequency    = Annual
| date         = 26 December
| relatedto    = Day of Goodwill&lt;br /&gt;[[Saint Stephen's Day]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Christmastide|Second Day of Christmastide]]
}}

'''Boxing Day''' is a holiday celebrated the day after [[Christmas Day]], thus being the [[twelve Days of Christmas|second day]] of [[Christmastide]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Robb1984&quot;/&gt; It originated in the United Kingdom and is celebrated in a number of countries that previously formed part of the [[British Empire]]. Boxing Day is on 26 December, although the attached [[bank holiday]] or [[public holiday]] may take place either on that day or two days later.&lt;!-- Do not expand this in the Lead; it is explained correctly in the Date sub-section--&gt;

In parts of Europe,&lt;!-- please add only sourced countries/regions --&gt; such as [[Romania]], [[Hungary]], Germany, [[Poland]], the [[Netherlands]], the [[Czech Republic]], and [[Scandinavia]], 26 December is celebrated as a Second Christmas Day.&lt;ref name=&quot;Second Christmas Day&quot;&gt;{{cite book|pages=21|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6w6u6YTsDdcC&amp;pg=PA21|title=Christmas Facts, Figures &amp; Fun: Facts, Figures and Fun|isbn=978-1-904332-27-5|author1=Brown|first1=Cameron|date=28 August 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Etymology ==
There are competing theories for the origins of the term, none of which is definitive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.snopes.com/holidays/christmas/boxingday.asp|title=snopes.com: Boxing Day Origins|website=[[Snopes.com]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The European tradition of giving money and other gifts to those in need and in service positions has been dated to the [[Middle Ages]], but the exact origin is unknown. It is believed to be in reference to the [[alms box|Alms Box]] placed in the [[narthex]] of Christian churches to collect donations to the poor. The tradition may come from a custom in the late Roman/early Christian era wherein alms boxes placed in churches were used to collect special offerings tied to the [[Saint Stephen's Day|Feast of Saint Stephen]],&lt;ref&gt;Collins, 2003, p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt; which in the [[Western Christianity|Western Christian Churches]] falls on the same day as Boxing Day, the second day of [[Christmastide]]. On this day, it is customary in some localities for the alms boxes to be opened and distributed to the poor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Robb1984&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Robb |first1=Nancy |title=Mid-winter festivals: anthology of stories, traditions, and poems |date=1984 |publisher=S.E. Clapp |page=27 |language=English |quote=St. Stephen's Day or Boxing Day: Boxing Day, or Offering Day as it is sometimes called, derives its name from the ancient practice of giving boxes of money at the midwinter holiday season to all those who had given good service throughout the year. Boxing Day, December 26, was the day the boxes were opened. Later, it was the day on which the alms boxes, located in the churches on Christmas Day, were opened and the contents given to the poor.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;FaustSach2002&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Faust |first1=Jessica |last2=Sach |first2=Jacky |title=The Book of Christmas |date=2002 |publisher=Citadel Press |isbn=978-0-8065-2368-2 |language=English |quote=Yet another legend is that Boxing Day started the tradition of opening the alms boxes placed in churches during the Christmas season. The contents of the alms boxes were then distributed amongst the poor of he parish.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'' gives the earliest attestations from Britain in the 1830s, defining it as &quot;the first weekday after Christmas day, observed as a holiday on which postmen, errand boys, and servants of various kinds expect to receive a Christmas box&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Boxing-day, ''n''.&quot;, ''OED Online'', 1st ed. (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1887).&lt;/ref&gt;

The term &quot;Christmas box&quot; dates back to the 17th century, and among other things meant:

&lt;blockquote&gt;A present or gratuity given at Christmas: in Great Britain, usually confined to gratuities given to those who are supposed to have a vague claim upon the donor for services rendered to him as one of the general public by whom they are employed and paid, or as a customer of their legal employer; the undefined theory being that as they have done offices for this person, for which he has not directly paid them, some direct acknowledgement is becoming at Christmas.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Christmas-box, ''n''.&quot;, ''OED Online'', 1st edn (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1889), sense 3.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In Britain, it was a custom for tradesmen to collect &quot;Christmas boxes&quot; of money or presents on the first weekday after Christmas as thanks for good service throughout the year.&lt;ref&gt;''Encyclopædia Britannica'', 1953 &quot;Boxing day&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; This is mentioned in [[Samuel Pepys]]' diary entry for 19 December 1663.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pepysdiary.com/diary/1663/12/19/ |title=Saturday 19&amp;nbsp;December 1663 (Pepys' Diary) |publisher=Pepysdiary.com |accessdate=26 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; This custom is linked to an older British tradition where the servants of the wealthy were allowed the next day to visit their families since they would have to serve their masters on Christmas Day. The employers would give each servant a box to take home containing gifts, bonuses, and sometimes leftover food. Until the late 20th century there continued to be a tradition among many in the UK to give a Christmas gift, usually cash, to vendors although not on Boxing Day as many would not work on that day.

In South Africa, vendors who normally have little interaction with those they serve are accustomed to knock on their doors asking for a &quot;Christmas box&quot;, being a small cash donation, in the weeks before or after Christmas. This practice has become controversial and some municipalities have banned their staff from asking for Christmas boxes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.iol.co.za/capeargus/news/christmas-box-requests-by-citys-waste-management-staff-prohibited-18195445|title=Christmas box requests by City’s waste management staff prohibited {{!}} Cape Argus|website=www.iol.co.za|language=en|access-date=27 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Date ==
Boxing Day is a [[secular holiday]] traditionally celebrated on 26 December, the day after Christmas Day. 26 December is also [[Saint Stephen's Day]], a [[religious holiday]].&lt;ref&gt;''American Heritage Dictionary'', Fourth Edition – 'Boxing Day'&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Oxford English''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/pressoffice/pressreleases/stories/2004/11_november/17/radio4_sun26.shtml |title=BBC Radio 4 schedule, 3&amp;nbsp;December 2004 |date = 17 November 2004 |accessdate =17 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Status by country==
In the UK, Boxing Day has been a [[bank holiday]] since 1871. When 26 December falls on a Saturday, the public holiday is on the following Monday. If 26 December falls on a Sunday, the public holiday is the following Tuesday.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.year-planner-calendar.co.uk/2010-public-holidays.htm|title=Year Planner Calendar; 2010 |publisher=hraconsulting-ltd.co.uk |date=2010 |accessdate=22 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In [[Scotland]], Boxing Day has been specified as an additional bank holiday since 1974,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.london-gazette.co.uk/issues/46377/pages/9343 |title=London Gazette, 18&amp;nbsp;October 1974 |publisher=London-gazette.co.uk |date=18 October 1974 |accessdate=26 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; by [[Royal Proclamation]] under the [[Banking and Financial Dealings Act 1971]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.scotland.gov.uk/Topics/People/bank-holidays/FAQs|title=Bank Holidays in Scotland – Frequently Asked Questions|publisher=|accessdate=21 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Hong Kong, despite the [[Handover of Hong Kong|transfer of sovereignty]] from the UK to China in 1997, Boxing Day continues to be a public holiday.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.gov.hk/en/about/abouthk/holiday/&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; If Boxing Day falls on a Sunday, a compensation day is given on the next weekday.

In Ireland, when the entire island [[History of Ireland (1801–1922)|was part of]] the [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|United Kingdom]], the [[Bank Holidays Act 1871]] established the feast day of [[Saint Stephen]] as a non-moveable public holiday on 26 December.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.berr.gov.uk/whatwedo/employment/bank-public-holidays/bank-public-holidays/page18882.html|title=History of Bank &amp; Public Holidays|publisher=Department for Business Enterprise &amp; Regulatory Reform|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081207051825/http://www.berr.gov.uk/whatwedo/employment/bank-public-holidays/bank-public-holidays/page18882.html|archivedate=7 December 2008|accessdate=14 December 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following [[Partition of Ireland|partition in 1920]], [[Northern Ireland]] reverted to the British name, Boxing Day. In East [[County Donegal|Donegal]] and [[Inishowen]], the day is also popularly known as Boxing Day.

In Australia, Boxing Day is a public holiday in all jurisdictions except the state of [[South Australia]], where a public holiday known as [[Proclamation Day (South Australia)|Proclamation Day]] is celebrated on the first weekday after Christmas Day or the Christmas Day holiday.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Public holidays |url=https://www.safework.sa.gov.au/law-compliance/laws-regulations/public-holidays |website=SafeWork SA |publisher=Government of South Australia |accessdate=26 December 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In New Zealand, Boxing Day is a statutory holiday. On these holidays, people who must work receive 1 1/2 times their salaries and a day in lieu is provided to employees who work.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.govt.nz/browse/work/public-holidays-and-work/working-on-public-holidays/ | title=Working on public holidays | publisher=New Zealand Government | accessdate=25 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Canada, Boxing Day ({{lang-fr|link=no|le Lendemain de Noel}}) is a federal statutory holiday. Government offices, banks and post offices/delivery are closed. In some Canadian provinces, Boxing Day is a statutory holiday&lt;ref name=&quot;Manitoba&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.gov.mb.ca/labour/standards/doc,gen-holidays-after-april-30-07,factsheet.html#q13 |title = Fact Sheet |author = Manitoba Employment Standards Branch |date = 27 November 2009 |accessdate =17 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; that is always celebrated on 26 December. In Canadian provinces where Boxing Day is a statutory holiday and it falls on a Saturday or Sunday, compensation days are given in the following week.&lt;ref name=&quot;Manitoba&quot; /&gt;

While not generally observed in the United States, on 5 December 1996, [[Massachusetts]] Gov. [[William F. Weld]] declared 26 December as Boxing Day in [[Massachusetts]] in response to the efforts of a local coalition of British citizens to &quot;transport the English tradition to the United States&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1914&amp;dat=19961224&amp;id=W9QgAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=7WoFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5966,3916623&amp;hl=en &quot;Massachusetts celebrates Boxing Day&quot;, Associated Press, ''Sun-Journal'', Lewiston, Maine, 26 December 1996].&lt;/ref&gt; but not as an employee holiday.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Massachusetts Federal and State Holidays 2017|url=https://publicholidays.us/massachusetts/|publisher=Public Holidays Global Pty Ltd|accessdate=1 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Nigeria, Boxing Day is a public holiday for working people and students. When it falls on a Saturday or Sunday, there is always a holiday on Monday.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Holidays in Nigeria in 2017|url=https://www.timeanddate.com/holidays/nigeria/|website=Time and Date|accessdate=1 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Trinidad and Tobago]], Boxing Day is a public holiday.

In Singapore, Boxing Day was a public holiday for working people and students; when it fell on a Saturday or Sunday, there was a holiday on Monday. However, in recent years this tradition has ceased in Singapore.

In South Africa, Boxing Day is a public holiday. Many South Africans spend the day at the beach. 

In the British overseas territory of [[Bermuda]], the costumed [[Gombey]] dancers perform throughout the mid-Atlantic island on Boxing Day, a tradition believed to date back to the 18th century when slaves were permitted to gather at Christmastime.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston-Barnes, Owain. [http://royalgazette.com/news/article/20171226/gombeys-dance-on-boxing-day Gombeys dance on Boxing Day], [[The Royal Gazette (Bermuda)|The Royal Gazette]] (26 December 2017). Accessed 27 December 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Shopping ==
[[File:Boxing Day at the Toronto Eaton Centre.jpg|thumb|right|Boxing Day crowds shopping at the [[Toronto Eaton Centre]] in Canada, 2007]]
In the UK,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/this-britain/boxing-day-sales-soar-as-shoppers-flock-to-malls-429935.html |title = Boxing Day sales soar as shoppers flock to malls |author = Terry Kirby |date = 27 December 2006 |accessdate =17 December 2009 | location=London |work=The Independent }}&lt;/ref&gt; Canada,&lt;ref name=&quot;ctv.ca&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ctv.ca/CTVNews/CTVNewsAt11/20051226/boxing_day_051226/ |title=Boxing Day expected to rake in $1.8&amp;nbsp;billion |author=CTV.ca News Staff |date=26 December 2005 |accessdate=17 December 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101228163816/http://www.ctv.ca/CTVNews/CTVNewsAt11/20051226/boxing_day_051226 |archivedate=28 December 2010  }}&lt;/ref&gt; Australia,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.sbs.com.au/news/article/2014/12/26/boxing-day-sales-top-2bn-retailers | title = Boxing Day sales to top $2bn: retailers | date=26 December 2014|accessdate =26 December 2014 | publisher =[[Special Broadcasting Service]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Trinidad and Tobago, and New Zealand,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://i.stuff.co.nz/business/75337680/boxing-day-still-big-for-bargain-hunters-despite-prechristmas-retail-sales | title = Boxing Day still big for bargain hunters despite pre-christmas retail sales | date=21 December 2015 |accessdate =22 December 2015 | publisher=Stuff}}&lt;/ref&gt; Boxing Day is primarily known as a shopping holiday. Boxing Day sales are common and shops often allow dramatic price reductions. For many merchants, Boxing Day has become the day of the year with the greatest revenue. In the UK in 2009 it was estimated that up to 12 million shoppers appeared at the sales (a rise of almost 20% compared to 2008, although this was also affected by the fact that the [[VAT]] was about to revert to 17.5% from 1 January, following the temporary reduction to 15%).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/business/8432144.stm |title=Boxing Day sales attract 'record' number of shoppers |work=BBC News |date=28 December 2009 |accessdate=26 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many retailers open very early (typically 5&amp;nbsp;am or even earlier) and offer [[doorbuster]] deals and [[loss leader]]s to draw people to their stores. It is not uncommon for long queues to form early in the morning of 26 December, hours before the opening of shops holding the big sales, especially at [[Big-box store|big-box consumer electronics]] retailers.&lt;ref name=&quot;ctv.ca&quot; /&gt; Many stores have a limited quantity of big draw or deeply discounted items.&lt;ref name=&quot;toronto.ctv.ca&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://toronto.ctv.ca/servlet/an/local/CTVNews/20071213/boxing_day_071213?hub=EdmontonHome |title = How to become a Boxing Day shopping pro |date = 25 December 2007 |author = Ashleigh Patterson |accessdate =17 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because of the shoulder-to-shoulder crowds, many choose to stay at home and avoid the hectic shopping experience. Local media often covers the event, mentioning how early the shoppers began queuing up, and showing video of shoppers queuing and later leaving with their purchased items.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ctv.ca/CTVNews/Canada/20071226/Boxing_Day_071226/ |title=Boxing Day begins with early rush of bargain hunters |author=toronto.ctv.ca |date=26 December 2007 |accessdate=17 December 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120106173035/http://www.ctv.ca/CTVNews/Canada/20071226/Boxing_Day_071226/ |archivedate=6 January 2012  }}&lt;/ref&gt; Many retailers have implemented practices aimed at managing large numbers of shoppers. They may limit entrances, restrict the number of patrons in a store at a time, provide tickets to people at the head of the queue to guarantee them a hot ticket item, or canvass queued-up shoppers to inform them of inventory limitations.&lt;ref name=&quot;toronto.ctv.ca&quot; /&gt;

In some areas of Canada, particularly in [[Atlantic Canada]] and parts of [[Northern Ontario]], most retailers are prohibited from opening on Boxing Day, either by provincial law or by municipal [[bylaw]], or by informal agreement among major retailers, in order to provide a day of relaxation following Christmas Day. In these areas, sales otherwise scheduled for 26 December are moved to the 27th.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.geschenkhexe.ch/media/archive/Boxing-Day-The-Debate-Continues.html|title=Boxing Day, The Debate Continues|author=soonews.ca|date=22 December 2007|accessdate=26 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.google.com/hostednews/canadianpress/article/ALeqM5hAtdtyDSIeYttaUmCcZLT_bGhGzg|title=Boxing Day madness: shoppers descend on stores looking for deals|author=The Canadian Press|date=26 December 2009|accessdate=26 December 2009}}{{dead link|date=December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The city council of [[Greater Sudbury]], Ontario, which was the largest city in Canada to maintain this restriction as of the early 2010s, formally repealed its store hours bylaw on 9 December 2014.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thesudburystar.com/2014/12/09/council-repeals-sudburys-store-hours-byline &quot;Council repeals Sudbury's store hours bylaw&quot;]. ''[[Sudbury Star]]'', 10 December 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

While Boxing Day is 26 December, many retailers will run the sales for several days before or after 26 December, often up to New Year's Eve, branding it as &quot;[[Boxing Week]]&quot;. Notably, in [[Late 2000s recession|the recession of late 2008]], a record number of retailers held early promotions due to a weak economy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ctv.ca/CTVNews/TopStories/20081221/Shopping_Deals_081222/|title=Boxing Day comes early as shoppers search for deals|author=CTV.ca News Staff|date=21 December 2008|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120106141332/http://www.ctv.ca/CTVNews/TopStories/20081221/Shopping_Deals_081222/|archivedate=6 January 2012|accessdate=17 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, many retailers with both online and [[High Street]] stores launched their online sales on Christmas Eve and their High Street sales on Boxing Day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.geschenkhexe.ch/media/archive/IMRG-Press-Release-120m-to-be-spent-Online-on-Christmas-Day-2009.html|title=Many retailers' sales to start on Christmas Eve|author=IMRG|date=22 December 2009|accessdate=22 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/topics/christmas/6858609/Boxing-Day-sales-start-on-Christmas-Eve.html|title=Boxing Day sales start on Christmas Eve|author=Telegraph|date=22 December 2009|work=The Daily Telegraph|accessdate=22 December 2009|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Decline ===
The tradition has been compared to the U.S. phenomenon of [[Black Friday (shopping)|Black Friday]] — the Friday following the [[Thanksgiving (United States)|Thanksgiving]] holiday in late-November — which is usually considered the first day of the Christmas shopping season. In the late-2000's when the [[Canadian dollar|Canadian]] and [[United States dollar|U.S. dollar]] were near parity, Canadian retailers began to hold Black Friday promotions to attract consumers who would otherwise travel across the border to visit U.S. stores. This has lessened the appeal of Boxing Day in Canada somewhat, as it was overtaken by Black Friday in terms of sales by 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://financialpost.com/news/retail-marketing/inside-the-shopping-extravaganza-that-black-friday-has-become-in-canada|title=Inside the shopping extravaganza that Black Friday has become in Canada|last=|first=|last2=|first2=|date=23 November 2016|website=Financial Post|language=en-CA|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=7 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In the 2010's, many British retailers also began to import the Black Friday tradition, led primarily by retailers with American ownership such as [[Amazon (company)|Amazon]] and [[Asda]] (the latter owned by the U.S.-based [[Walmart]]). In 2015, British retail sales in November overtook sales in December for the first time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/business-46260739|title=Have eight years of Black Friday changed the UK?|last=Jones|first=Lora|date=21 November 2018|work=BBC News|access-date=7 January 2020|url-status=live|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/business/2015/nov/26/what-is-black-friday-biggest-uk-shopping-day|title=What is Black Friday and who's to blame for it?|last=Ruddick|first=Graham|date=26 November 2015|work=The Guardian|access-date=7 January 2020|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2019, a retail analysis firm estimated that there was a 9.8% drop in British store traffic on Boxing Day in comparison to 2018 (the largest year-over-year drop since 2010), citing several factors, such as the weather, the increased prominence of [[online shopping]], uncertainties in the wake of the [[2019 United Kingdom general election|general election]], and the growing prominence of Black Friday sales.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/business/2019/dec/26/boxing-day-footfall-dip-blamed-on-poor-weather-and-black-friday|title=Boxing Day sales dip blamed on poor weather and Black Friday|last=Wood|first=Zoe|date=26 December 2019|work=The Guardian|access-date=7 January 2020|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Neither Boxing Day or Boxing Day sales are a prominent tradition in the United States, although many retailers often begin post-Christmas promotions that day, and in any case, it is typically the earliest starting day after Christmas for people to return unwanted gifts for exchanges or refunds.

== Sport ==
[[File:MCG stands.jpg|thumb|[[Boxing Day Test]] at the [[Melbourne Cricket Ground]], 2006]]
[[File:Keswick Boxing Day hunt 1962.jpg|thumb|right|Boxing Day Meet of the Blencathra Foxhounds in Keswick, 1962]]

In the United Kingdom, it is traditional for all top-tier [[Association football|football]] leagues in England, [[Scotland]], and [[Northern Ireland]] – the [[Premier League]], the [[Scottish Premiership]], and the [[NIFL Premiership]] – and the lower ones, as well as the [[Rugby union|rugby]] leagues, to hold a full programme of [[association football|football]] matches on Boxing Day. Originally, matches on Boxing Day were played against [[local derby|local rivals]] to avoid teams and their fans having to travel a long distance to an away game on the day after Christmas Day.{{cn|date=December 2019}} Prior to the formation of leagues, a number of traditional [[rugby union]] fixtures took place on Boxing Day each year, notably [[Llanelli RFC|Llanelli]] v [[London Welsh RFC|London Welsh]] and [[Leicester Tigers|Leicester]] v [[Barbarian F.C.|The Barbarians]].

In Italy, Boxing Day football was played for the first time in the [[2018–19 Serie A|2018/19 Serie A season]]. The experiment was successful, with Italian stadiums 69% full on average – more than any other matchday in December 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://sporvision.com/2019/italys-boxing-day/ | title=Italy's Boxing Day | publisher=Sporvision.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[rugby league]], festive fixtures were a staple of the traditional winter season. Since the transition to a summer season in the 1990s, no formal fixtures are now arranged on Boxing Day but some clubs, such as [[Wakefield Trinity]], arrange a traditional [[local derby]] friendly fixture instead.

In Australia, New Zealand and South Africa, [[Test cricket]] matches are played on Boxing Day. For more details see [[Boxing Day Test]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.hindustantimes.com/cricket/boxing-day-test-grand-year-end-event-with-rich-cricket-history/story-nr0LCfb1cRO9I3XhKe8ybO.html | title=Boxing Day Test: Grand year-end event with rich cricket history | first=S Pervez | last=Qaiser | date=25 December 2017 | work=[[Hindustan Times]] | accessdate=25 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Australia, the first day of the [[Boxing Day Test]] in [[Melbourne]] and the start of the [[Sydney to Hobart Yacht Race]] are on Boxing Day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://rolexsydneyhobart.com/about-the-race/ | title=About the Race | publisher=Rolex Sydney Hobart Yacht Race | accessdate=25 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In horse racing, there is the [[King George VI Chase]] at [[Kempton Park Racecourse]] in Surrey, England. It is the second most prestigious [[National Hunt racing|chase]] in Britain, after the [[Cheltenham Gold Cup]]. In addition to the prestigious race at Kempton, in Britain, it is usually the day with the highest number of racing meetings of the year, with eight in 2016, in addition to three more in Ireland.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Racecards – 26th December 2016|url=http://www.racingpost.com/horses2/cards/home.sd?r_date=2016-12-26|website=Racing Post}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Barbados, the final day of horse racing is held on Boxing Day at The Historic Garrison Savannah, a UNESCO world heritage site. This tradition has been going on for decades in this former British colony.

Boxing Day is one of the main days in the hunting calendar for [[list of foxhound packs of the United Kingdom|hunts]] in the UK and US, with most hunts (both mounted foxhound or harrier packs and foot packs of beagles or bassets) holding meets, often in town or village centres.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/earth/countryside/10538429/Hundreds-of-thousands-turn-out-for-Boxing-Day-hunts.html |title=Hundreds of thousands turn out for Boxing Day hunts|date=26 December 2013 |work=[[The Daily Telegraph]] |location=London |accessdate=21 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several [[ice hockey]] contests are associated with the day. The [[IIHF World U20 Championship]] typically begins on 26 December, while the [[Spengler Cup]] also begins on 23 December in [[Davos]], Switzerland; the Spengler Cup competition includes [[HC Davos]], [[Canada men's national ice hockey team|Team Canada]], and other top European Hockey teams. The [[National Hockey League]] traditionally had close to a full slate of games (10 were played in 2011&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=NHL Hockey Schedule for December 26, 2011|url=http://www.nhl.com/ice/schedulebyday.htm?date=12/26/2011|accessdate=27 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;), following the league-wide days off given for Christmas Eve and Christmas Day. However, the 2013 collective bargaining agreement (which followed [[2012-13 NHL lockout|a lock-out]]) extended the league mandate of Christmas Eve and Christmas Day off to include Boxing Day, except when it falls on a Saturday, in which case the league can choose to make 23 December a league-wide off day instead for that year.&lt;ref name=&quot;NHL CBA&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=National Hockey League CBA|url=http://www.nhl.com/nhl/en/v3/ext/CBA2012/NHL_NHLPA_2013_CBA.pdf |page=101—not digital page 101 but the printed 101 |publisher=[[National Hockey League]] |accessdate=27 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In some African [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth]] nations, particularly Ghana, Uganda, Malawi, Zambia and Tanzania, [[professional boxing]] contests are held on Boxing Day. This practice has also been followed for decades in Guyana and Italy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB126179017496705483 | title = Season's Beatings: 'Boxing Day' Takes a Pugilistic Turn | accessdate =14 November 2011 | last = Millman | first = Joel | date = 28 December 2009 | newspaper = [[The Wall Street Journal]] |edition=Asia}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A notable tradition in Sweden is ''{{lang|sv|[[Saint Stephen's Day bandy|Annandagsbandy]]}}'', which formerly marked the start of the [[bandy]] season and always draws large crowds. Games traditionally begin at 1:15&amp;nbsp;pm.&lt;ref name=&quot;annandagsbandy&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first= Berndt |last= Rosqvist |title= Festligt och fullsatt på stora bandydagen |url=http://www.dn.se/sport/festligt-och-fullsatt-pa-stora-bandydagen |work=Dagens Nyheter |date=22 December 2003 |accessdate=4 February 2010 |language=Swedish |trans-title=Festive and packed with great bandy day}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Boxing Day}}
* [http://www.snopes.com/holidays/christmas/boxingday.asp Snopes: The Origins of Boxing Day]

{{Christmas}}
{{Navboxes|list1=
{{Australia Holidays}}
{{Canada Holidays}}
{{Hong Kong Holidays}}
{{New Zealand Holidays}}
{{South Africa Holidays}}
{{UK Holidays}}
}}
{{Portal bar|Christianity|Australia|Canada|Hong Kong|New Zealand|South Africa|United Kingdom}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Boxing Day]]
[[Category:Christmastide]]
[[Category:Christmas events and celebrations]]
[[Category:Public holidays in Australia]]
[[Category:Public holidays in Canada]]
[[Category:Public holidays in New Zealand]]
[[Category:Public holidays in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:December observances]]
[[Category:Public holidays in Denmark]]
[[Category:Public holidays in the Netherlands]]</text>
      <sha1>j1lv1ek821gfwpnhjf94wtmiqdi1qj0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
