  <page>
    <title>Boy band</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4673</id>
    <revision>
      <id>934819214</id>
      <parentid>933589899</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-08T17:50:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Superspongebobbros</username>
        <id>31881866</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Early history */  I checked, and the original article misspelled Ringo Starr's last name (using one &quot;r&quot; as opposed to two), so here's your free [''sic'']</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{pp|small=yes}}
{{short description|Vocal group consisting of young males}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=July 2017}}

A '''boy band''' (or '''boyband''') is loosely defined as a [[vocal group]] consisting of young male singers, usually in their teenage years or in their twenties at the time of formation,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Hickey|first1=Walt|title=Boy Bands: More Like Man Bands|url=http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/boy-bands-more-like-man-bands/|website=FiveThirtyEight|accessdate=June 7, 2014|date=June 4, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; singing love songs marketed towards young women. Being vocal groups, most boy band members do not play [[musical instrument]]s, either in recording sessions or on stage, making the term something of a [[misnomer]].{{Non sequitur|date=August 2019}} However, exceptions do exist. Many boy bands dance as well as sing, usually giving highly choreographed performances.

Some such bands form on their own. They can evolve out of church choral or [[gospel music]] groups, but are often created by [[talent manager]]s or record producers who hold auditions. Due to this and their general commercial orientation towards a female audience of [[preteen]]s, [[teenybopper]]s, or teens, the term may be used with negative connotations in [[music journalism]]. Boy bands are similar in concept to their counterparts, [[girl group]]s. Boy bands' popularity peaked four times: in the 1960s (e.g., [[The Jackson 5]]), in the 1990s and early 2000s when acts such as the [[Backstreet Boys]], [[NSYNC|*NSYNC]], [[A1 (band)|A1]] and [[Westlife]], among others, dominated the top of the ''[[Billboard charts|Billboard]]'' and pop charts, in the early 2010s with the emergence of new boy bands such as [[JLS]], [[Big Time Rush (band)|Big Time Rush]] and [[One Direction]], and in the late 2010s with pop groups such as [[BTS (band)|BTS]] and [[Brockhampton (band)|Brockhampton]].

==History==

===Early history===
The earliest forerunner of boy band music began in the late 19th century as [[a cappella]] [[barbershop quartets]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.barbershop.org/web/groups/public/documents/pages/pub_cb_00016.hcsp |title=Definition of the Barbershop Style, from the Contest and Judging Handbook |date=July 11, 2002 |accessdate=June 6, 2007 |publisher=Barbershop Harmony Society |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070607170531/http://www.barbershop.org/web/groups/public/documents/pages/pub_cb_00016.hcsp |archivedate=June 7, 2007 |url-status=dead |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt; They were usually a group of males and sang in [[Four-part harmony|four-part harmonies]]. Barbershop quartets were popular into the earlier part of the 20th century. A revival of the male vocal group took place in the late 1940s and 1950s with the use of [[doo-wop]] music. Doo-wop bands sang about topics such as love and other themes used in [[pop music]]. The earliest traces of boy bands were in the mid-1950s although the term boy band was not used. [[African American]] vocal group [[The Ink Spots]] was one of the first of what would now be called boy bands. The term boy band was not established until the late 1980s as before that they were called male vocal groups or &quot;hep harmony singing groups&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://didyouknow.org/boybands/ |title=Boy bands |publisher=Did you know |accessdate=June 29, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although generally described as a rock band, the highest-selling band in history [[The Beatles]] are considered by a number or journalists &quot;the first&quot; or &quot;the original&quot; boyband, &quot;before anyone had thought of the term.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/music/news/faintings-stage-invasions-how-the-beatles-invented-the-cult-of-f/ |title=Faintings, stage invasions: how the Beatles invented the cult of female fandom |last=Brown |first=Mick |date=September 6, 2016 |work=[[The Daily Telegraph]] |access-date=March 12, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|text=The Liverpool quartet known as [[The Beatles]] were not only the quintessential rock band, but many considered John Lennon, Paul McCartney, George Harrison and Ringo Star [''sic''] to be the original boy band – especially in the early 1960s when young girls would scream at the top of their lungs and pass out upon first sight of the “Fab Four.&quot;|author=''[[The Hollywood Reporter]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;THR&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/gallery/boy-bands-wanted-one-direction-nsync-beatles-backstreet-boys-306859/1-the-beatles |title=The Beatles to The Wanted: The Evolution of Boy Bands |last=Medina |first=Portia|last2=Hermon|first2=James|last3=James |first3=Kyleen |date=April 4, 2012 |work=The Hollywood Reporter |access-date=March 13, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The Beatles inspired the production of the 1966 television series ''[[The Monkees (TV series)|The Monkees]]'',&lt;ref name=&quot;Star Tribune&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.startribune.com/from-beatles-to-the-wanted-a-history-of-boy-bands-at-a-glance/215232031/ |title=From Beatles to the Wanted: A history of boy bands at a glance |last=Tillotson |first=Kristin |date=July 15, 2013 |work=[[Star Tribune]] |access-date=March 12, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; which spawned [[The Monkees|the music group of the same name]], formed by the four starring actors. The rock and pop band started a career in music after their songs from the TV series were released as successful records.&lt;ref name=&quot;THR&quot;/&gt;

===Late 1960s and 1970s: The Jackson 5 and the Osmonds===
[[File:The-Osmonds.jpg|thumb|The Osmonds]]
Although the term &quot;boy band&quot; was not commonly used yet, the earliest predecessors of this format were groups such as [[the Jackson 5]] and [[the Osmonds]] which helped form the template for boy bands.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fuse&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.fuse.tv/galleries/2014/11/history-famous-boy-bands |title=Photo History of Boy Bands: 31 Essential Acts |last1=Benjamin |first1=Jeff |last2=Nuñez |first2=Jatnna |date=November 17, 2014 |work=Fuse |access-date=March 14, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Star Tribune&quot;/&gt; The Jackson 5 were a siblings group that established many musical conventions that boy bands follow. For instance, their music featured [[close harmony|close harmonies]] from [[soul music]] and catchy pop hooks influenced as much as they were by [[Motown]] and acts like [[the Supremes]]. The group also incorporated choreographed dance moves to their performances. All members of the band sang, which is a common convention of a boy band, as opposed to having a front man and the rest on instruments; thus, no one person dominated the stage.{{citation needed|date=March 2018}} Also a siblings group, The Osmonds first started singing [[barbershop music]] for local audiences, before being hired to perform at [[Disneyland]] early in their career. Their appearance in a televised Disney special earned them additional TV spots, such as ''[[The Andy Williams Show]]'' and ''[[The Jerry Lewis Show]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;THR&quot;/&gt;

===Late 1970s and 1980s: Menudo, New Edition, and New Kids on the Block===
Other antecedents (apart from those already mentioned) exist throughout the history of pop music. The genre has been copied into languages and cultures other than the Anglo-American. The Puerto Rican boy band [[Menudo (band)|Menudo]], appealing to young [[Latina]] audiences, was founded in 1977. Menudo had a convention unique among boy bands: when a member turned 16, became too tall, or their voice changed, they were replaced.  The members of Menudo were generally aged 12–16.

The [[Bay City Rollers]] were a [[Scotland|Scottish]] pop band who were most popular in the mid-1970s. The ''[[British Hit Singles &amp; Albums]]'' noted that they were &quot;[[tartan]] teen sensations from [[Edinburgh]]&quot;, and were &quot;the first of many acts heralded as the 'Biggest Group since [[The Beatles]]' and one of the most screamed-at teeny-bopper acts of the 1970s&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;British Hit Singles &amp; Albums&quot;&gt;{{cite book| first= David| last= Roberts| year= 2006| title= British Hit Singles &amp; Albums|edition= 19th|publisher= Guinness World Records |location= London|isbn= 1-904994-10-5|page = 45}}&lt;/ref&gt;  For a fairly brief but fervent period (nicknamed &quot;Rollermania&quot;), they were worldwide [[teen idol]]s.  The group were one of the first bands, like The Monkees before them, to take the formula shown by The Beatles and apply it to a teen market. The group achieved the same amount of success but for a limited period of time. At the peak of their popularity in the UK, comparisons were being made to The Beatles. Also by this time, Bay City Roller [[fan (person)|fans]] had a completely distinctive style of dress, the main elements of which were ankle-length [[tartan]] trousers and tartan [[scarf|scarves]], the group using the benefit of merchandise and promotion.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Great Rock Discography&quot;&gt;{{cite book| first= Martin C | last = Strong| year = 2000| title = The Great Rock Discography | edition = 5th|publisher= Mojo |location= Edinburgh|pages= 2–3|isbn= 1-84195-017-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The German boy band ''The Teens'' formed in [[West Berlin]] [[1976]] and had a couple of hits targeting young females. The band resolved in [[1982]]. &lt;ref&gt;https://www.discogs.com/artist/262798-The-Teens&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:NKOTB 2008-11-06.jpg|thumb|left|[[New Kids on the Block]] in concert, November 2008]]
In the US, the [[Cleveland, Ohio|Cleveland]]-based [[power pop]] group [[Raspberries (band)|Raspberries]] was generally interpreted as a &quot;teen act&quot;, although all the band members played their own music. Vocalist [[Eric Carmen]] later commented, &quot;It was not hip for people to like us, because their little sister liked us.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = Knopper | first = Steve | contribution = Raspberries | title = Contemporary Musicians | publisher = Gale | year = 2004 | series = Encyclopedia | accessdate = December 26, 2009 | url = http://www.encyclopedia.com/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Boston group [[New Edition]] was formed in 1978 and reached their height of popularity in the 1980s, meaning they are often credited for starting the boy-band trend, even though the term &quot;boy band&quot; did not exist until the 1990s. [[Maurice Starr]] was influenced by New Edition and popularized it with his [[Mentorship|protégé]] [[New Kids on the Block]], the first commercially successful modern boy band, who formed in 1984 and found international success in 1988. Starr's idea was to take the traditional template from the R&amp;B genre (in this case his teenage band New Edition) and apply it to a pop genre.

[[Bros]] (abbreviation of the word &quot;brothers&quot;) were a British boy band active in the late 1980s and early 1990s, consisting of twin brothers [[Matt Goss|Matt]] and [[Luke Goss]] along with [[Craig Logan]]. Formed in 1986, they scored multiple top 10 hits between 1987 and 1989 and in 1988 became the first modern era–style boy band to have a multiple platinum-selling album in the UK, with ''[[Push (Bros album)|Push]]'', still one of the most successful boy-band albums in the UK. Other big boy bands in Britain during the late 1980s were [[Big Fun (boyband)|Big Fun]] and [[Brother Beyond]].

===1990s: Boyz II Men, Take That, Backstreet Boys, NSYNC, and Westlife===

[[File:Take That London Olympics 2012. by Rory.jpg|thumb|right|230px|[[Take That]] performing “[[Rule the World (Take That song)|Rule the World]]” at the [[2012 Summer Olympics closing ceremony|2012 Olympic Games closing ceremony]] in London]]
Some managers in Europe soon created their own acts after being inspired by New Kids on the Block, beginning with [[Nigel Martin-Smith]]'s [[Take That]] in the UK (formed in 1990) and followed by [[Tom Watkins (music manager)|Tom Watkins]], who had success with [[Bros]] in the late 1980s and formed [[East 17]] in 1991. Bros were marketed and pitted against Take That as rivals with a harsher attitude, style and sound. Since reforming in 2006 after a decade-long hiatus, Take That have become one of the most successful groups in British music chart history and their albums and singles have also charted internationally, especially in Europe. Irish music manager [[Louis Walsh]], who had witnessed the impact of these British boy bands, put out an advert for an &quot;Irish Take That&quot;, thereby creating [[Boyzone]] in 1993. [[Let Loose]] (formed in 1993), [[MN8]] and [[911 (UK band)|911]] (formed in 1995), and [[Damage (British band)|Damage]] (formed in 1996) were also successful boy bands in Britain; however, by the late 1990s all these bands had run their course and split up.

All these artists were very successful on both the singles and albums charts domestically and internationally; however, with the emergence of [[Britpop]] and the commercial co-option of [[indie rock]], many boy bands were ridiculed by the British music press as having no artistic credibility, although some, such as East 17 and Take That, did write most of their own material. The media attention was then placed on the &quot;Battle of Britpop&quot;, and the bands [[Oasis (band)|Oasis]] and [[Blur (band)|Blur]] replaced the importance and rivalry of Take That and East 17 as the two new biggest bands in Britain. However, boy bands continued to find success in the late 1990s, such as [[Five (band)|Five]], [[Another Level (band)|Another Level]], [[Point Break (band)|Point Break]] and [[Westlife]]. In 1995 successful German music manager [[Frank Farian]], who had been manager of [[Boney M]] and [[Milli Vanilli]], put together [[Latin American]] band [[No Mercy (pop band)|No Mercy]] who scored a few worldwide hits during the mid-90s.

Although being American and the sons of [[Tito Jackson]], a member of [[The Jackson 5]], [[3T]] had several hits singles across Europe in the mid-1990s, despite limited success in the US, and finished the second biggest selling act of 1996 in Europe behind the [[Spice Girls]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.sortmusic.com/_0/3t-biography,len.html |title=3T Biography |publisher=Sort music |accessdate=August 5, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; With the success of North American boy bands like [[New Kids on the Block]] in East Asia, Japanese entertainment company [[Johnny &amp; Associates]] formed [[SMAP]] in 1992. The group enjoyed tremendous success, selling over 35 million records.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.oricon.co.jp/news/2049025/full/|title= 【オリコン】SMAP新曲が32作目首位 総売上3500万枚突破 |date= February 24, 2015|accessdate= January 4, 2017|work= Oricon Style|publisher= [[Oricon]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; It paved the way for more Asian boy bands such as [[Arashi]].

[[File:Backstreet Boys 2005.jpg|thumb|left|[[Backstreet Boys]] sold over 100 million records.&lt;ref name=&quot;bsb&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.smh.com.au/entertainment/backstreet-boys-are-back-20100106-ltvn.html|title=Backstreet Boys are back|first=Katherine|last=Feeney|work=[[The Sydney Morning Herald]] |date=January 6, 2010 |accessdate=January 21, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
In the early 1990s in North America, with New Kids on the Block's continued success and [[Color Me Badd]] also having success, boy bands became a continued staple of the Billboard charts. Continuing this success in the mid-1990s, most prominent boy bands were African American and had R&amp;B and gospel elements, such as the groups [[All-4-One]] (formed in 1993) and [[Boyz II Men]] (formed in 1988). Boyz II Men are also the most successful boy band act on the [[U.S. Hot 100]] as well as the [[Australian Singles Chart]]. Although they had success on the Billboard charts, they were not marketed towards youth but more towards adults. It was not until 1997 and the change to pop-oriented groups such as [[Backstreet Boys]], [[98 Degrees]], [[NSYNC]], [[The Moffatts]], and [[Hanson (band)|Hanson]] that boy bands exploded commercially and dominated the market in the United States. This late 1990s marked the height of boy band popularity in North America, which has not been seen since.

Arguably the most successful boy band manager from the U.S. was [[Lou Pearlman]], who founded commercially successful acts such as the [[Backstreet Boys]] in 1993, [[NSYNC]] and [[LFO (group)|LFO]] in 1995, [[O-Town (band)|O-Town]] in 2000, and [[US5]] in 2005. Backstreet Boys and NSYNC became the two biggest boy bands in the late 1990s until the early 2000s, and Backstreet Boys went on to tie [[The Jackson 5]] as the best-selling boy bands in history with over 100 million records sold.&lt;ref name=&quot;bsb&quot;/&gt;

In the late 1990s in the UK, producer [[Simon Cowell]] (noted in the U.S. for the ''American Idol/X Factor'' franchise) is also known for having managed British boyband [[Five (band)|Five]] (formed in 1997) and Irish boyband [[Westlife]] (formed in 1998). Westlife was created by Irishman [[Louis Walsh]] as a replacement for [[Boyzone]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://uk.tv.yahoo.com/x-factor/judges/louis-walsh.html | work = Press Association | title = Louis Walsh Profile | publisher= Yahoo! |accessdate= January 9, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was initially managed by a former member of the band [[Ronan Keating]]. Westlife would eventually overtake Take That in number one's tally in the UK although Take That's overall UK sales are still higher. In 2012, the [[Official Charts Company]] revealed the biggest selling singles artists in British music chart history with Take That placed 15th overall and the highest selling boyband act (9.3 million), followed by Boyzone at 29 (7.1 million) and Westlife at 34 (6.8 million).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.officialcharts.com/chart-news/the-official-top-20-biggest-selling-groups-of-all-time-revealed-1682/ | title = The Official Top 20 biggest selling groups of all time revealed!|publisher=Official charts |accessdate=November 3, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.officialcharts.com/chart-news/the-official-singles-charts-biggest-selling-artists-of-all-time-revealed-1431/ |title=Official Singles Charts' biggest selling artists of all time revealed | publisher =Official charts |accessdate=October 30, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.officialcharts.com/chart-news/take-thats-top-40-biggest-selling-songs-3313/ | title = Take That's Top 40 Biggest Selling Songs|publisher=Official charts |accessdate=November 29, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even though Cowell is known to have managed several successful boy bands, he is also infamous for passing on signing two of the biggest boybands to emerge from the 1990s and 2000s, Take That and [[Busted (band)|Busted]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| first =Alasdair | last = Glennie |url = http://www.dailymail.co.uk/tvshowbiz/article-2118414/Simon-Cowell-admits-turned-Take-That-overweight-Gary-Barlow.html | title =Simon Cowell admits that he turned down Take That because of 'overweight' Gary Barlow |work=Daily Mail |date = March 22, 2012 |accessdate=June 29, 2012 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bebo.com/BlogView.jsp?MemberId=7322368642&amp;BlogId=7651779757 |title=Blog |publisher=Bebo |accessdate=June 29, 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180915184945/https://bebo.com/BlogView.jsp?MemberId=7322368642&amp;BlogId=7651779757 |archive-date=September 15, 2018 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2000s: Backstreet Boys, NSYNC, Westlife, Jonas Brothers and F4===
[[File:JonasBrothers.JPG|thumb|upright|[[Jonas Brothers]] are described as pop boy band]]
With the continued success of [[Backstreet Boys]] and [[NSYNC|*NSYNC]], American and British groups like [[98 Degrees]], [[Westlife]], [[O-Town (band)|O-Town]], [[A1 (band)|A1]], [[Blue (English band)|Blue]], and [[Busted (band)|Busted]] gained quick popularity both domestically and internationally. International boy bands would also occasionally spring up, such as the [[Moldova]]n band [[O-Zone]] (better known today as an [[Numa Numa (video)|Internet meme]]), and [[Overground (band)|Overground]]. American Christian boy band [[Plus One (band)|Plus One]] also enjoyed brief remarkable success during this time.

At the height of boy band popularity in [[North America]], MTV created their own parody boyband, [[2gether (band)|2gether]]. Like [[The Monkees]] in the 1960s, they were a manufactured act composed of actors. 2gether played off of the idea that every successful boy band must have five distinct personality types: the bad boy, the shy one, the young one, the older brother type, and a heart throb.

Since 2001, the dominance of traditional boy bands on pop charts began to fade in the western hemisphere, although Gil Kaufman of [[MTV.com|MTV]] has described &quot;new boy bands&quot; that are &quot;more likely to resemble [[My Chemical Romance]], [[Sum 41]], and [[Simple Plan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mtv.com/bands/b/boy_bands/050207/|title=The New Boy Bands|accessdate=November 8, 2007|publisher=MTV|year=2007|first=Gil|last=Kaufman|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071019051548/http://www.mtv.com/bands/b/boy_bands/050207/|archivedate=October 19, 2007|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2001, Taiwanese boy band [[F4 (band)|F4]] (called JVKV since 2007)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first = Vivien | last = Wang | title = Boy band changes name F4 into JVKV | url = http://www.chinadaily.com.cn/lifestyle/2007-04/29/content_863824.htm | work = [[China Daily]] | date = April 29, 2007 | accessdate =May 31, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; blew up big as a result of the success of their TV drama [[Meteor Garden]]. Their popularity spread throughout Asia.{{citation needed|date=September 2015}} With their success, many other Taiwanese boy bands emerged around this time, such as [[5566]] and [[Fahrenheit (Taiwanese band)|Fahrenheit]]. In South Korea, [[Shinhwa]] also spread [[hallyu]] wave throughout Asia such as [[Japan]], [[Thailand]], [[Singapore]], [[Taiwan]], [[Hong Kong]] and [[China]]. Also in 2001, a new all-male pop band and dance group boyband hailing from Japan called [[Exile (Japanese band)|Exile]] debuted under Avex Group's label [[Rhythm Zone]] with 14 members, putting them on par with [[Super Junior]], a South Korean boy band, who had 13 members at its peak.{{citation needed|date=September 2015}}

Japanese boy band [[Arashi]] has sold over 30 million copies of their records since their first release in 1999.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.oricon.co.jp/news/2052992/full/|title= 【オリコン】嵐、相葉主演月9主題歌1位 CD総売上3000万枚突破|date= May 19, 2015|accessdate= January 4, 2017|work= Oricon Style|publisher= [[Oricon]]|language= Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt; They had the [[List of best-selling singles in Japan#Best-selling singles by year|yearly best-selling single in Japan]] in 2008&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.oricon.co.jp/music/special/081211_01_01.html|title= 年間ランキング特集『2008年 オリコン年間ランキング大発表！』|accessdate= January 4, 2017|work= Oricon Style|publisher= [[Oricon]]|language= Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt; and 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://contents.oricon.co.jp/music/special/091218_01_01.html|title= 年間ランキング特集『オリコン2009年年間ランキング大発表！』|accessdate= January 4, 2017|work= Oricon Style|publisher= [[Oricon]]|language= Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2003 [[SMAP]] released the single &quot;[[Sekai ni Hitotsu Dake no Hana]]&quot; that has become the [[List of best-selling singles in Japan#List of best-selling singles in Japan (1968-present)|third best-selling single ever in Japan]], with over 3 million copies sold.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.oricon.co.jp/news/2082827/full/ |script-title=ja:SMAP「世界に一つだけの花」300万枚突破 ファンの「購買運動」目標達成 |date=9 December 2016 |accessdate=2 December 2017 |publisher=Oricon News |language=Japanese |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20171202132949/https://www.oricon.co.jp/news/2082827/full/ |archivedate=2 December 2017 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In North America, the [[Jonas Brothers]] rose to fame from promotion on the [[Disney Channel]] in 2008. Other boy bands like [[JLS]] and [[Mindless Behavior]] also emerged and experienced remarkable success around this time. However, apart from them, boy bands have not seen the commercial boom experienced in the genre from the mid to late nineties in North America.

The mid 2000s, especially the United Kingdom and the rest of Europe, saw the continued longevity of nineties boy bands such as [[Backstreet Boys]] and [[Westlife]] (before they disbanded in 2012), and the successful comeback of [[Take That]] in 2005, [[Boyzone]] in 2007, and [[New Kids on the Block]] in 2008. Some sections of the press have referred to these acts, particularly those who have reformed after a previous split, such as Take That, Boyzone, and [[98 Degrees]], as 'man bands'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=98 Degrees reunites as 'man band' on 'Today' show| work = The Los Angeles Times | url= http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/gossip/la-et-mg-98-degrees-reunites-today-show-20120817,0,3400710.story |accessdate=September 14, 2012|date=August 17, 2012|first=Christie|last=D'Zurilla}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2010s: Big Time Rush, One Direction and rise of K-pop ===
[[File:One Direction Sydney 6.jpg|thumb|[[One Direction]] rose to fame in 2011.]]
In the early 2010s, there was somewhat of a resurgence of boy band popularity in countries where the trend had not maintained, with the emergence of new boy bands like [[Big Time Rush (band)|Big Time Rush]], [[The Wanted]], and [[One Direction]] and the formation of [[Supergroup (music)|supergroup]] [[NKOTBSB]] which comprised members of New Kids on the Block and Backstreet Boys.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hamptonroads.com/2012/04/rise-and-return-boy-band|title=The rise and return of the boy band|publisher=Hampton Roads|date=April 29, 2012|accessdate=June 29, 2012|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120510171444/http://hamptonroads.com/2012/04/rise-and-return-boy-band|archivedate=May 10, 2012|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; NKOTBSB's success inspired boy bands who were fairly popular during the 1990s and 2000s to make a comeback, such as A1, [[Blue (English band)|Blue]], 98 Degrees, [[Five (band)|Five]], [[911 (UK band)|911]], and O-Town. Like [[2gether (band)|2gether]] and [[The Monkees]], Big Time Rush was a manufactured act created for a television show.

In Southeast Asia, local boy bands also emerged as a result of the continued success of Korean and Japanese boy bands such as [[SMAP]], [[Shinhwa]], [[TVXQ!]], [[Arashi]], [[Exile (Japanese band)|Exile]], [[Super Junior]], [[Big Bang (South Korean band)|Big Bang]], [[SHINee]], [[EXO (band)|EXO]], and [[BTS (band)|BTS]]. One of the boy bands who emerged as a result of [[Hallyu]] (Korean wave) is Indonesia's [[SM*SH]] who enjoyed prominent success domestically. In the Philippines, a major boy band has been formed by bringing the first reality boy band search of the country called [[Pinoy Boyband Superstar]] which held mid [[Pinoy Boyband Superstar|2016]], after all the series of auditions, rigorous training and competition, the winners formed as a group called [[Boyband PH]] a five-piece Pinoy boy band which managed by [[Star Magic]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title='Pinoy Boyband Superstar': Winners revealed!|url=http://www.rappler.com/entertainment/news/155190-pinoy-boyband-superstar-winners|accessdate=December 11, 2016|work=Rappler|date=December 11, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In South Korea, boy bands have been commercially successful. On the [[Gaon Music Chart]] year-end albums chart of 2016, nine of the top 10 and 17 of the top 20 albums are by boy bands or by subunits/members of boy bands. [[BIGBANG]], [[EXO (band)|EXO]] had the second and third best-selling albums. Other boy bands with albums in the yearly top 20 of 2016 are [[BTS (band)|BTS]], [[SHINee]], [[GOT7]], [[Seventeen (South Korean band)|Seventeen]], [[Infinite (band)|INFINITE]] and [[VIXX]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://gaonchart.co.kr/main/section/chart/album.gaon?nationGbn=T&amp;serviceGbn=&amp;targetTime=2016&amp;hitYear=2016&amp;termGbn=year|title= 2016년 Album Chart|accessdate= January 13, 2017|work= gaonchart.co.kr|language= Korean}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In 2013 Billboard started covering music releases in kpop, though kpop had been entering the charts as early as 2009, signifying the growth of the hallyu wave in America.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.billboard.com/articles/columns/k-town/8532755/k-pop-billboard-20-years|title=Looking Back at How 'K-Pop' Came to Billboard 20 Years Ago|website=Billboard|access-date=2019-12-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 2017, BTS crossed into the international music market, furthering the [[Korean Wave]] in the United States and becoming the first Korean group to receive a certification by the [[Recording Industry Association of America]] (RIAA) with their single &quot;[[Mic Drop (song)|Mic Drop]]&quot;. The band is the first Korean act to top the U.S. ''Billboard'' 200 with their studio album ''[[Love Yourself: Tear]]'' (2018) and have since hit the top of the U.S. charts with their albums ''[[Love Yourself: Answer]]'' (2018) and ''[[Map of the Soul: Persona]]'' (2019). ''Love Yourself: Answer'' also broke South Korea's [[Gaon Album Chart]]'s all-time monthly record previously set by ''Love Yourself: Tear'' and became the first Korean album certified Gold in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.riaa.com/gold-platinum/?tab_active=default-award&amp;ar=BTS&amp;ti=&amp;lab=&amp;genre=&amp;format=&amp;date_option=release&amp;from=&amp;to=&amp;award=&amp;type=&amp;category=&amp;adv=SEARCH#search_section|title=RIAA: BRS certifications|access-date=September 22, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[SuperM|Super M]] later became the first kpop group to debut at #1 in the U.S. ''Billboard'' 200.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.capitolrecords.com/with-the-1st-mini-album-superm-ep-the-super-group-becomes-first-debut-k-pop-artist-to-enter-billboard-200-at-no-1/|website=www.capitolrecords.com|access-date=2019-12-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Japan, [[Arashi]] continue to be very successful, being the best-selling music artist in Japan from 2013 through 2017&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.oricon.co.jp/special/50550/ |script-title=ja:【第50回 オリコン年間ランキング 2017】嵐が総合売上5年連続首位、AKB48がシングル年間V8達成! |date=December 23, 2017 |accessdate=November 6, 2018 |publisher=[[Oricon]] |language=ja }}&lt;/ref&gt; by value of sales and also having the yearly best-selling album in the country in 2010, 2011, 2013, 2015 and 2016.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.oricon.co.jp/music/special/2010/musicrank1220/index04.html |script-title=ja:年間ランキング特集『2010年、ヒットしたシングル、アルバム、DVDは？』 |date=December 20, 2010 |accessdate=November 6, 2018 |publisher=[[Oricon]] |language=ja }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.oricon.co.jp/music/special/2011/musicrank1219/index03.html |script-title=ja:年間ランキング特集『AKB48が5作ミリオン突破の快挙！2011年オリコン年間CD＆DVDランキングを大発表！』 |date=December 19, 2011 |accessdate=November 6, 2018 |publisher=[[Oricon]] |language=ja }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.oricon.co.jp/music/special/2013/musicrank1215/index05.html |script-title=ja:オリコン2013年　年間　音楽＆映像ランキング |date=December 15, 2013 |accessdate=November 6, 2018 |publisher=[[Oricon]] |language=ja }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.oricon.co.jp/special/48546/4/|script-title=ja:2015年 年間音楽ランキングを発表！|date= December 23, 2015|accessdate= January 4, 2017|work= Oricon Style|publisher= [[Oricon]]|language= Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.oricon.co.jp/special/49664/4/|script-title=ja:【2016年 年間音楽＆映像ランキング】嵐が前人未到の記録達成！AKB48がシングル年間V7!!|date= December 24, 2016|accessdate= January 4, 2017|work= Oricon Style|publisher= [[Oricon]]|language= Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other successful Japanese boy bands in this decade include [[Sandaime J Soul Brothers]], the second best-selling music artist of 2016 in the country and [[Kanjani Eight]], the fifth best-selling music artist of that year in Japan.&lt;ref name=&quot;oricon&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.oricon.co.jp/special/49664/6/|script-title=ja: 【2016年 年間音楽＆映像ランキング】嵐が前人未到の記録達成！AKB48がシングル年間V7!!|date= December 24, 2016|accessdate= January 4, 2017|work= Oricon Style|publisher= [[Oricon]]|language= Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Key factors of the concept==
Seen as important to a &quot;boy band&quot; group's commercial success is the group's [[Reputation|image]], carefully controlled by managing all aspects of the group's attire,  promotional materials (which are frequently supplied to [[teen magazine]]s), and music videos. The key factor of a boy band is being trendy. This means that the band conforms to the most recent fashion and musical trends in the popular music scene. Typically, each member of the group will have some distinguishing feature and be portrayed as having a particular personality stereotype, such as &quot;the baby,&quot; &quot;the bad boy,&quot; or &quot;the shy one.&quot;  While managing the portrayal of popular musicians is as old as [[popular music]], the particular pigeonholing of band members is a defining characteristic of boy and girl bands.

In most cases, their music is written, arranged and produced by a producer who works with the band at all times and controls the group's sound – if necessary, to the point of hiring [[session singers]] to record guide vocals for each member of the group to sing individually if the members cannot harmonize well together. However, for clarity of each voice, recording each voice individually is most commonly the norm with most modern vocal groups.  In recent years [[auto-tune]] has become a popular tool for boy bands who are unable to sing to a high standard. Some boy bands have come under fire for this issue of using auto-tune. Some have also come under fire for [[lip syncing]] in their performances as well, for example [[New Kids on the Block]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = New Kids' Performance Was Dubbed, Critic Says | url = http://articles.orlandosentinel.com/1992-03-04/news/9203040523_1_mcpherson-new-kids-starr |newspaper = Orlando Sentinel | accessdate =August 15, 2012|date=March 4, 1992}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A typical boy band performance features elaborately choreographed dancing, with the members taking turns singing and/or rapping. Boy bands generally do not compose or produce their own material, unless the members lobby hard enough for creative control. However, some bands were created around the talent of a songwriter within the group like [[Gary Barlow]] of [[Take That]] or [[Tony Mortimer]] of [[East 17]]. It is not uncommon to find extra songs on an album written by one or more of the band members; however, their producers rarely use these as singles.

Since the 21st century, however, boy bands have been expected to write or at least contribute in some part lyrically to songs. Apart from the groups mentioned above who all had at least one primary songwriter from their beginning, other groups soon caught up.  From the late nineties, members of [[Backstreet Boys]] who had previously used writers like [[Max Martin]] during their early albums began writing their own songs. Newer groups from late 2000s such as [[JLS]] have all made a point from early interviews that they write their own songs and hold their own image as this is an important part of marketing. Some bands like [[The Wanted]] have even spent time learning the craft of songwriting.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/music/news/a329584/the-wanted-go-to-songwriting-camp-to-write-new-album.html |title=The Wanted go to songwriting camp to write new album |work=Digital Spy |date=July 13, 2011 | place = [[United Kingdom|UK]] | accessdate=June 29, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Individuals can also go on to achieve greater success as a solo artist coming out of a boy band having used the groups popularity to build on. Usually this signals the end of the group until potential future reunions. Examples of this include [[Michael Jackson]] from [[The Jackson 5]], [[Donny Osmond]] from [[The Osmonds]], [[Ricky Martin]] from [[Menudo (band)|Menudo]], [[Justin Timberlake]] from *NSYNC, and [[Ronan Keating]] from [[Boyzone]]. Sometimes the most successful solo star from a band is not the most popular member such as [[Robbie Williams]] as opposed to lead singer [[Gary Barlow]] from [[Take That]]. Some boy band members have gone on to successful careers elsewhere in the media. [[Michael Dolenz]] of [[The Monkees]] went on to become a successful television producer, working for [[ITV (TV channel)|ITV]] franchises such as [[LWT]] and [[Television South]].

==Music genres==
Although most boy bands consist of [[Rhythm and blues|R&amp;B]] or pop influences, other [[music genre]]s, most notably [[country music]] and [[folk music]], are also represented. [[South 65]] and [[Marshall Dyllon]], for example, were both country music boy bands. [[Il Divo]], created by [[Simon Cowell]] in 2004, are a vocal group that performs [[operatic pop]] in several (mainly Italian) languages. Since then operatic/classical boy bands have become quite popular and common, especially in the UK. Since 2001 there has been some crossover with [[power pop]] and [[pop punk]] from bands that play live instruments. Just recently some boy bands decided to go back to their original doo-wop roots, most notably, [[The Overtones]].

==Controversy==
Since the 2000s, groups such as [[Backstreet Boys]] and [[LFO (group)|LFO]] have disliked the term &quot;boy band&quot; and have preferred to be known as a &quot;male vocal group&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = I would be the dessert because I’m satisfying | url = http://www.popjustice.com/interviewsandfeatures/backstreet-boys-interview/49849/|publisher= Pop Justice | accessdate = August 16, 2012|date=October 24, 2007|quote=We were never a boyband. We always thought of ourselves as a white vocal harmony group, we didn’t model ourselves on Take That or anything.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Not Just Another Boy Band|place=[[Canada|CA]]|url=http://www.music.yahoo.ca/read/interview/12057784|accessdate=August 16, 2012|date=January 18, 2000|quote=As long as you like my music, buy the record, come to the shows, fact of the matter is, if you see us, you'll know we're not a boy band.|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://archive.is/20130101071044/http://www.music.yahoo.ca/read/interview/12057784|archivedate=January 1, 2013|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Being categorized among boy bands was also the main reason [[The Moffatts]] split up.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| last= McCoy| first= Heath| title= The Moffatts have left the building| url= http://www.scottmoffatt.nu/cs/media/articles/breakuparticle.html| newspaper= The Calgary Herald| accessdate= August 16, 2012| quote= Being young, there's this (boy band) stigma you pick up and they all thought it was very unjust.| url-status= dead| archiveurl= https://archive.is/20130223103952/http://www.scottmoffatt.nu/cs/media/articles/breakuparticle.html| archivedate= February 23, 2013| df= mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Boy bands have been accused by the music press of emphasizing the appearance and marketing of the group above the quality of music, deliberately trying to appeal to a [[preadolescence|preteen]] audience and for conforming to trends instead of being original. Such criticisms can become extremely scathing. Boy bands are often seen as being short lived,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Hickey|first1=Walt|title=’90s Boy Bands: A Numerical Retrospective|url=http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/90s-boy-bands-a-numerical-retrospective/|website=FiveThirtyEight|accessdate=June 7, 2014|date=June 4, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; although some acts such as [[The Jackson 5]], [[Backstreet Boys]], [[Human Nature (band)|Human Nature]], [[New Edition]], [[SMAP]], [[Shinhwa]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://koreatimes.co.kr/www/news/culture/2013/07/135_140160.html |title=Shinhwa's longevity introduced in US magazine |publisher=Koreatimes.co.kr |date=July 29, 2013 |accessdate=June 4, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Westlife]] (before they split up in 2012) have sustained lasting careers.

==Best-selling boy bands==
The following is a list of the best-selling boy bands based on claimed sales figures of over 40 million records:&lt;!-- PLEASE READ THIS: Do NOT use fansites/forums/the artist's or their record company's official sites as references. It's against the Wikipedia police of reliable sources (https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Potentially_unreliable_sources, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:But_it%27s_true!, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Party_and_person) Thank you--&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:150px;&quot;| Name
! style=&quot;width:75px;&quot;| Nationality
! style=&quot;width:100px;&quot;| Number of members
! Years active
! style=&quot;width:100px;&quot;| Genre
! style=&quot;width:100px;&quot;| Studio albums
! style=&quot;width:100px;&quot;| Claimed sales
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|[[Backstreet Boys]]
| United States
| 5 → 4 → 5
| 1993–present &lt;small&gt;(26 years)&lt;/small&gt;
| Pop
| 9
| 100 million&lt;ref name=&quot;bsb&quot;/&gt;
&lt;!-- PLEASE DO NOT EDIT THIS UNTIL THIS ISSUE IS RESOLVED IN THE TALK SECTION --&gt;
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|[[New Kids on the Block]]
| United States
| 5 → 4 → 5
| 1984–1994, 2008–present &lt;small&gt;(21 years)&lt;/small&gt;
| Pop
| 6
| 80 million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Interview: New Kids on the Block's Jordan Knight pictures life as a teenage boy band in 2012|url=http://articles.chicagotribune.com/2012-01-26/entertainment/chi-interview-new-kids-on-the-block-jordan-knight-20120126_1_boy-band-tour-bus-nkotb|work=Chicago Tribune|accessdate=June 29, 2012|date=January 26, 2012|archivedate=June 6, 2014 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140606220523/http://articles.chicagotribune.com/2012-01-26/entertainment/chi-interview-new-kids-on-the-block-jordan-knight-20120126_1_boy-band-tour-bus-nkotb}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|[[The Osmonds]]
| United States
| 5
| 1958–1980 &lt;small&gt;(22 years)&lt;/small&gt;
| Pop
| 22
| 77 million&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.oprah.com/oprahshow/an-osmond-family-tribute |title=An Osmond Family Tribute |work=[[Harpo Productions|Oprah.com]] |access-date=March 9, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|[[The Jackson 5]]
| United States
| 5 → 6 → 4
| 1964–1990, 2001, 2012–2013 &lt;small&gt;(29 years)&lt;/small&gt;
| Pop/R&amp;B
| 18
| 75 million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Joe Jackson, father of superstar Michael Jackson, dies aged 89|url=https://www.canberratimes.com.au/entertainment/music/joe-jackson-father-of-superstar-michael-jackson-dies-aged-89-20180628-p4zo66.html|newspaper=[[The Canberra Times]]|first=Michael|last=Idato|date=June 28, 2018|accessdate=June 30, 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|[[Bay City Rollers]]
| {{nowrap|United Kingdom}}
| 5
| 1966–1981 &lt;small&gt;(15 years)&lt;/small&gt;
| Pop
| 16
| 70 million&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/life-style/in-the-rollers-id-just-say-i-want-that-house-then-id-move-in-1612884.html |last=Picardie |title='In the Rollers, I'd just say: I want that house. Then I'd move in'|first=Justine |date=March 26, 1995 |work=The Independent |access-date=March 9, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|[[NSYNC|*NSYNC]]
| United States
| 5
| 1995–2002 &lt;small&gt;(7 years)&lt;/small&gt;
| Pop
| 4
| 70 million&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite magazine |last=Newman |first=Melinda |date=November 14, 2017 |title=*NSYNC And Epic Rights Join Together For Merchandise Line to Celebrate Band's 20th Anniversary: Exclusive |url=https://www.billboard.com/articles/news/8031516/nsync-and-epic-rights-join-together-for-merchandise-line-to-celebrate-bands |magazine=Billboard |access-date=March 9, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|[[Boyz II Men]]
| United States
| 5 → 4 → 3
| 1988–present &lt;small&gt;(31 years)&lt;/small&gt;
| R&amp;B
| 11
| 60 million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/tv/showtracker/la-et-st-boyz-ii-men-to-play-teen-angels-in-foxs-grease-live-20160106-story.html |title= Boyz II Men to play teen angels in Fox's 'Grease: Live' |work=Los Angeles Times |date=January 6, 2016 |accessdate=June 25, 2017|first=Libby |last=Hill}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|[[Westlife]]
| Ireland
| 5 → 4
| 1998–2012; 2018–present &lt;small&gt;(16 years)&lt;/small&gt;
| Pop
| 11
| 55 million&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.irishexaminer.com/breakingnews/entertainment/westlife-announce-second-croke-park-gig-due-to-phenomenal-demand-881048.html |title=Westlife announce second Croke Park gig 'due to phenomenal demand's |date=October 25, 2018 |work=[[Irish Examiner]] |access-date=January 18, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news  | url = https://www.belfasttelegraph.co.uk/entertainment/music/musical-comebacks-to-watch-out-for-in-2019-from-westlife-to-rihanna-37700271.html |title= Musical comebacks to watch out for in 2019 – from Westlife to Rihanna|work= [[Belfast Telegraph]] |accessdate=January 18, 2019 |date=January 11, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news  | url = https://www.telegraph.co.uk/tv/2018/06/08/dont-laugh-louis-walsh-successful-judge-x-factor-will-ever/ |title=Don't laugh at Louis Walsh – he's the most successful judge the X Factor will ever see|work= Telegraph |accessdate=January 18, 2019 |date=June 8, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|[[One Direction]]
| United Kingdom/Ireland
| 5 → 4
| 2010–2016 &lt;small&gt;(6 years; on hiatus)&lt;/small&gt;
| Pop
| 5
| 50 million&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.ndtv.com/world-news/one-direction-bands-louis-tomlinson-arrested-in-airport-tussle-1666249 |title=One Direction Band's Louis Tomlinson Arrested In Airport Tussle |date=9 March 2018 |work=[[Agence France-Presse]] |accessdate=5 March 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news  | url = http://www.digitalspy.com/tv/the-x-factor/feature/a669626/the-x-factors-5-biggest-selling-acts-ever-little-mix-and-one-direction-battle-for-chart-supremacy/ |title= The X Factor's 5 biggest selling acts ever – Little Mix and One Direction battle for chart supremacy
|work= Digital Spy |accessdate=June 27, 2017 |date=September 25, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news  | url = http://www.abc.net.au/news/2015-03-26/the-rise-of-pop-boy-band-one-direction/6349186 |title= One Direction: The rise of the inescapable pop boy band|work= ABC Australia |accessdate=June 27, 2017 |date=March 26, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|[[Take That]]
| United Kingdom
| 5 → 4 → 5 → 3
| 1990–1996, 2005–present &lt;small&gt;(20 years)&lt;/small&gt;
| Pop
| 8
| 45 million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news  | url = https://www.bbc.com/news/entertainment-arts-22353613 |title= Mark Owen swaps Take That for Doing Nothing|work= BBC |accessdate=November 30, 2018 |date=May 3, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news  | url = https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/music/music-news/9411546/Gary-Barlow-to-receive-music-industry-honour.html |title= Gary Barlow to receive music industry honour|work= Telegraph |accessdate=November 30, 2018 |date=July 19, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

==See also==
* [[All-female band]]
* [[Girl group]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
&lt;!-- Don't add links to individual bands sites --&gt;
* [http://www.boybandsradio.com Boybands Radio – Only boy bands 24/7]
* [http://top40.about.com/od/top10lists/tp/boyband10.htm Top 10 Boy Bands]
* [https://www.rollingstone.com/music/pictures/readers-poll-the-best-boy-bands-of-all-time-20120328 Rolling Stone's The Best Boy Bands of All Time]
* [http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2012/apr/29/list-best-boy-bands/ Washington Times' Best Boy Bands]
* [http://www.billboard.com/articles/list/502728/10-biggest-boy-bands-1987-2012 Billboard's 10 Biggest Boy Bands (1987–2012)]

{{Pop music}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Boy bands| ]]
[[Category:Pop music genres]]
[[Category:Types of musical groups]]</text>
      <sha1>gw42tkp77lsd06uxsqouxtag1phhy0k</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
