  <page>
    <title>Aga Khan III</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1546</id>
    <revision>
      <id>931607979</id>
      <parentid>931438198</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-19T23:55:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Citation bot</username>
        <id>7903804</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Alter: title, others, issue, pages. Add: date. Removed URL that duplicated unique identifier. Removed parameters. Formatted [[WP:ENDASH|dashes]]. | You can [[WP:UCB|use this bot]] yourself. [[WP:DBUG|Report bugs here]].| Activated by [[User:Headbomb]] | via #UCB_webform</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|48th Imam of the Nizari Ismaili community}}
{{Use British English|date=March 2013}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2013}}
{{Infobox religious biography
| honorific prefix = Prince
| name = Aga Khan III
| title = Aga Khan III
| native_name_lang = 
| image = HH the AGA KHAN 1936.jpg
| successor = [[Aga Khan IV]]
| caption = The Aga Khan III in 1936
| predecessor = [[Aga Khan II]]
| religion = [[Shia Islam]]
| denomination = [[Isma'ilism]]
| school = [[Nizari]] [[Ismaili]]
| lineage = [[Fatimid]]
| other_name = Sultan Mahomed Shah
| dharma_names = &lt;!-- or: | dharma_name = --&gt;
| monastic_name = 
| pen_name = 
| posthumous_name = 
| nationality = 
| home_town = 
| ethnicity = 
| birth_name = 
| birth_date = {{birth date|1877|11|02|df=y}}&lt;ref name=Britannica&gt;https://www.britannica.com/biography/Aga-Khan-III, Biography of Aga Khan III on Encyclopedia Britannica, Updated 18 September 2003, Retrieved 31 March 2017&lt;/ref&gt;
| birth_place = [[Karachi]], [[Bombay Presidency]], [[British India]] (now [[Pakistan]])
| death_date = {{death date and age|1957|07|11| 1877|11|02|df=y}}&lt;ref name=Britannica/&gt;
| death_place = Versoix, near [[Geneva]], [[Switzerland]]
| resting_place = [[Mausoleum of Aga Khan]], [[Aswan]], Egypt
| resting_place_coordinates = &lt;!-- {{coord|latitude|longitude|type:landmark|display=inline,title}} --&gt;
| alma_mater = 
| spouse = {{Plainlist|
* Shahzadi Begum
* Cleope Teresa Magliano
* Andrée Joséphine Carron
* [[Begum Om Habibeh Aga Khan]] (birth name, Yvonne Blanche Labrousse)
}}
| children = {{Plainlist|
* Giuseppe Mahdi Khan
* [[Prince Aly Khan|Aly Salman Aga Khan]]
* [[Sadruddin Aga Khan]]
}}
| parents = {{Plainlist|
* [[Aga Khan II|Aqa Ali Shah]] (father)
* Shams al-Muluk (mother)
}}
| profession = 
| education  = 
| initiation = 1885
| post       = 48th [[Nizari]] Imām
}}

'''Sir Sultan Mahomed Shah, Aga Khan III''' {{postnominals|country=GBR|GCSI|GCMG|GCIE|GCVO|PC}} (2 November 1877{{snd}}11 July 1957) was the 48th [[Shia Imam|Imam]] of the [[Nizari]] [[Ismaili]] religion. He was one of the founders and the first president of the [[All-India Muslim League]] (AIML). His goal was the advancement of Muslim agendas and protection of Muslim rights in [[India]]. The League, until the late 1930s, was not a large organisation but represented the landed and commercial Muslim interests of the British-ruled 'United Provinces' (as of today [[Uttar Pradesh]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=John Keay|title=India: A History|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3aeQqmcXBhoC&amp;pg=PA468|year=2001|publisher=Grove Press|page=468|isbn=9780802137975}}&lt;/ref&gt; He shared Sir [[Syed Ahmad Khan]]'s  belief that Muslims should first build up their [[social capital]] through advanced education before engaging in politics. Aga Khan called on the [[British Raj]] to consider Muslims to be a separate nation within India, the so-called 'Two Nation Theory'. Even after he resigned as president of the AIML in 1912, he still exerted major influence on its policies and agendas. He was nominated to represent India to the League of Nations in 1932 and served as President of the [[League of Nations]] from 1937–38.&lt;ref name=findpk/&gt;

==Early life==
Sir Sultan Mahomed Shah was born in [[Karachi]], the capital of [[Sindh]] province in British [[India]], (now [[Pakistan]]) to [[Aga Khan II]] and his third wife,&lt;ref name=&quot;Daftary-Ismailis&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=The Ismā'īlīs: Their History and Doctrines| last=Daftary| first=Farhad| year=1990| page=518| publisher=Cambridge University Press| location=Cambridge |isbn=0-521-42974-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nawab A'lia Shamsul-Muluk, who was a granddaughter of [[Fath Ali Shah]] of [[Persia]] ([[Qajar dynasty]]).

Under the care of his mother, he was given not only that religious and Oriental education which his position as the religious leader of the [[Ismailis]] made indispensable, but also sound European training, an opportunity denied to his father and paternal grandfather.{{sfn|Bhownagree|1911}} He also attended [[Eton College|Eton]] and the [[University of Cambridge]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Aga Khan, Fashionable Londoner, Holds Enormous Power in Islam&quot;, The New York Times,8 July 1923, p. XX5.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Career==
In 1885, at the age of eight, he succeeded his father as [[Shia Imam|Imam]] of the [[Shi'a]] [[Isma'ili]] Muslims.&lt;ref name=Britannica/&gt;&lt;ref name=findpk/&gt;

The Aga Khan travelled in distant parts of the world to receive the homage of his followers, and with the objective either of settling differences or of advancing their welfare by financial help and personal advice and guidance. The distinction of a [[Order of the Indian Empire|Knight Commander of the Indian Empire]] (KCIE) was conferred upon him by [[Queen Victoria]] in 1897; and he was promoted to a Knight Grand Commander (GCIE) in the [[1902 Coronation Honours]] list,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite newspaper The Times |articlename=The Coronation Honours |day_of_week=Thursday |date=26 June 1902 |page_number=5 |issue=36804| }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LG27448&quot; /&gt; and invested as such by King [[Edward VII]] at Buckingham Palace on 24 October 1902.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite newspaper The Times |articlename=Court Circular |day_of_week=Saturday |date=25 October 1902 |page_number=8 |issue=36908| }}&lt;/ref&gt; He was made a Knight Grand Commander of the Order of the Star of India (GCSI) by George V (1912), and appointed a GCMG in 1923. He received like recognition for his public services from the German Emperor, the Sultan of Turkey, the Shah of Persia and other potentates.{{sfn|Bhownagree|1911}}

In 1906, the Aga Khan was a founding member and first president of the [[All India Muslim League]], a political party which pushed for the creation of an independent Muslim nation in the north west regions of India, then under British colonial rule, and later established the country of Pakistan in 1947.

During the three [[Round Table Conferences (India)]] in London from 1930–32, he played an important role to bring about Indian constitutional reforms.&lt;ref name=Britannica/&gt;

In 1934, he was made a member of the [[Privy Council of the United Kingdom|Privy Council]] and served as a member of the [[League of Nations]] (1934–37), becoming the President of the League of Nations in 1937.&lt;ref name=findpk/&gt;

==Imamate==
{{Ismailism|collapsed=1}}
Under the  leadership of Sir Sultan Mahomed Shah, Aga Khan III, the first half of the 20th century was a period of significant development for the Ismā'īlī community. Numerous institutions for social and economic development were established in the Indian Subcontinent and in East Africa.&lt;ref name=&quot;DaftaryShort1998p199&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Daftary |first=Farhad |title=A Short History of the Ismailis |year=1998 |publisher=Edinburgh University Press |location=Edinburgh, UK |isbn=0-7486-0687-4 |pages=199–206}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ismailis have marked the Jubilees of their Imāms with public celebrations, which are symbolic affirmations of the ties that link the [[Ismāʿīlī]] Imām and his followers. Although the Jubilees have no religious significance, they serve to reaffirm the Imamat's worldwide commitment to the improvement of the quality of human life, especially in the developing countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;DaftaryShort1998p199&quot;/&gt;

The Jubilees of Sir Sultan Mahomed Shah, Aga Khan III, are well remembered. During his 72 years of Imamat (1885–1957), the community celebrated his Golden (1937), Diamond (1946) and Platinum (1954) Jubilees. To show their appreciation and affection, the Ismā'īliyya weighed their Imam in gold, diamonds and, symbolically, in platinum, respectively, the proceeds of which were used to further develop major social welfare and development institutions in Asia and Africa.

In [[British Raj|India]] and later in [[Pakistan]], social development institutions were established, in the words of Aga Khan III, &quot;for the relief of humanity&quot;. They included institutions such as the Diamond Jubilee Trust and the Platinum Jubilee Investments Limited which in turn assisted the growth of various types of cooperative societies. ''Diamond Jubilee High School for Girls'' were established throughout the remote Northern Areas of what is now Pakistan. In addition, scholarship programs, established at the time of the Golden Jubilee to give assistance to needy students, were progressively expanded. In East Africa, major social welfare and economic development institutions were established. Those involved in social welfare included the accelerated development of schools and community centres, and a modern, fully equipped [[Aga Khan University Hospital, Nairobi|hospital]] in [[Nairobi]]. Among the economic development institutions established in East Africa were companies such as the Diamond Jubilee Investment Trust (now Diamond Trust of Kenya) and the Jubilee Insurance Company, which are quoted on the Nairobi Stock Exchange and have become major players in national development.

Sir Sultan Mahomed Shah also introduced organizational forms that gave Ismāʿīlī communities the means to structure and regulate their own affairs.&lt;ref name=&quot;DaftaryShort1998p199&quot;/&gt; These were built on the Muslim tradition of a communitarian ethic on the one hand, and responsible individual conscience with freedom to negotiate one's own moral commitment and destiny on the other. In 1905 he ordained the first Ismā'īlī Constitution for the social governance of the community in East Africa. The new administration for the Community's affairs was organised into a hierarchy of councils at the local, national, and regional levels. The constitution also set out rules in such matters as marriage, divorce and inheritance, guidelines for mutual cooperation and support among Ismā'īlīs, and their interface with other communities. Similar constitutions were promulgated in India, and all were periodically revised to address emerging needs and circumstances in diverse settings.&lt;ref name=&quot;DaftaryShort1998p199&quot;/&gt;

Following the [[Second World War]], far-reaching social, economic and political changes profoundly affected a number of areas where Ismāʿīlīs resided. In 1947, British rule in the Indian Subcontinent was replaced by the sovereign, independent nations of [[India]], [[Pakistan]] and later [[Bangladesh]], resulting in the migration of millions people and significant loss of life and property. In the Middle East, the [[Suez crisis]] of 1956 as well as the preceding crisis in Iran, demonstrated the sharp upsurge of nationalism, which was as assertive of the region's social and economic aspirations as of its political independence. Africa was also set on its course to [[decolonisation]], swept by what [[Harold Macmillan]], the then British prime minister, termed the &quot;wind of change&quot;. By the early 1960s, most of East and Central Africa, where the majority of the [[Ismāʿīlī]] population on the continent resided, including [[Tanganyika]], [[Kenya]], [[Uganda]], [[Madagascar]], Rwanda, Burundi and [[Zaire]], had attained their political independence.

==Religious and Social Views==
The Aga Khan was deeply influenced by the views of [[Syed Ahmad Khan|Sir Sayyid Ahmad Khan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Aga Khan Case: Religion and Identity in Colonial India|last=Purohit|first=Teena|publisher=Harvard University Press|year=2012|isbn=978-0-674-06639-7|location=Cambridge, MA|pages=111}}&lt;/ref&gt; Along with Sir Sayyid, the Aga Khan was one of the backers and founders of the [[Muhammadan Anglo-Oriental College|Aligarh University]], for which he tirelessly raised funds for and donated large sums of his own money to.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Ismailism and Islam in Modern South Asia: Community and Identity in the Age of Religious Internationals|last=Mukherjee|first=Soumen|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2017|isbn=978-1-107-15408-7|location=Cambridge, UK|pages=131}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Aga Khan himself can be considered an [[Islamic Modernism|Islamic modernist]] and an intellectual of the [[Aligarh Movement|Aligarh movement]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Shi'a in modern South Asia : religion, history and politics|publisher=|others=Jones, Justin, 1980-, Qasmi, Ali Usman|year=|isbn=9781316258798|location=Delhi, India|pages=53|oclc=927147288}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From a religious standpoint, the Aga Khan followed a [[Islamic Modernism|modernist]] approach to Islam.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt; He believed there to be no contradiction between religion and modernity, and urged Muslims to embrace [[modernity]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Shi'i Islam : an introduction|last=Haider, Najam Iftikhar, 1974-|publisher=|isbn=9781107031432|location=New York, NY|pages=193|oclc=874557726|date = 11 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although he opposed a wholesale replication of Western society by Muslims, the Aga Khan did believe increased contact with the West would be overall beneficial to Muslim society.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt; He was intellectually open to [[Western philosophy]] and ideas, and believed engagement with them could lead to a revival and renaissance within Islamic thought.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Aga Khan III : selected speeches and writings of Sir Sultan Muhammad Shah|last=Aga Khan III, 1877-1957.|date=1998|publisher=Kegan Paul International|others=Aziz, Khursheed Kamal.|isbn=0710304277|location=London|pages=1067|oclc=39678354}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Like many other Islamic modernists, the Aga Khan held a low opinion of the traditional religious establishment (the [[Ulama|ʿUlamāʾ]]) as well as what he saw as their rigid formalism, legalism, and literalism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Rattansi|first=Diamond|date=August 1981|title=The Nizari Isma'ilis of Pakistan: Isma'ilism, Islam and Westernism Viewed Through the Firmans: 1936-1980|url=http://ismaili.net/heritage/node/29247|journal=McGill University|volume=|pages=65|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Instead, he advocated for renewed [[Ijtihad|ijtihād]] (independent reasoning) and [[Ijma|ijmāʿ]] (consensus), the latter of which he understood in a modernist way to mean consensus-building.&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot; /&gt; According to him, Muslims should go back to the original sources, especially the [[Quran|Qurʾān]], in order to discover the true essence and spirit of Islam.&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot;&gt;Aga Khan III 1998, p. 1183&lt;/ref&gt; Once the principles of the faith were discovered, they would seen to be universal and modern.&lt;ref&gt;Aga Khan III 1998, pp. 1345-1346&lt;/ref&gt; Islam, in his view, had an underlying liberal and democratic spirit.&lt;ref&gt;Aga Khan III 1998, p. 211&lt;/ref&gt; He also called for full civil and religious liberties,&lt;ref&gt;Aga Khan III 1998, p. 876&lt;/ref&gt; peace and disarmament, and an end to all wars.&lt;ref&gt;Aga Khan III 1998, p. 1415&lt;/ref&gt;

The Aga Khan opposed [[sectarianism]], which he believed to sap the strength and unity of the Muslim community.&lt;ref&gt;Aga Khan III 1998, pp. 210, 803&lt;/ref&gt; In specific, he called for a rapprochement between [[Sunni Islam|Sunnism]] and [[Shia Islam|Shīʿism]].&lt;ref&gt;Aga Khan III 1998, p. 1184&lt;/ref&gt; This did not mean that he thought religious differences would go away, and he himself instructed his [[Isma'ilism|Ismāʿīlī]] followers to be dedicated to their own teachings.&lt;ref name=&quot;:5&quot;&gt;Aga Khan III 1998, p. 1407&lt;/ref&gt; However, he believed in unity through accepting diversity, and by respecting differences of opinion.&lt;ref name=&quot;:5&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Aga Khan III 1998, pp. 842 &amp; 1063&lt;/ref&gt; On his view, there was strength to be found in the diversity of Muslim traditions.&lt;ref&gt;Rattansi 1981, p. 207&lt;/ref&gt;

The Aga Khan called for social reform of Muslim society, and he was able to implement them within his own Ismāʿīlī community.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Voices of Islam|date=2007|publisher=Praeger Publishers|others=Cornell, Vincent J.|isbn=9780313051166|location=Westport, Conn.|pages=235|oclc=230345942}}&lt;/ref&gt; As he believed Islam to essentially be a humanitarian religion, the Aga Khan called for the reduction and eradication of poverty.&lt;ref&gt;Aga Khan III 1998, p. 216&lt;/ref&gt; Like Sir Sayyid, the Aga Khan was concerned that Muslims had fallen behind the Hindu community in terms of education.&lt;ref&gt;Aga Khan III 1998, p. 235&lt;/ref&gt; According to him, education was the path to progress.&lt;ref&gt;Aga Khan III 1998, p. 208&lt;/ref&gt; He was a tireless advocate for compulsory and universal primary education,&lt;ref&gt;Aga Khan III 1998, p. 217&lt;/ref&gt; and also for the creation of higher institutions of learning.&lt;ref&gt;Aga Khan III 1998, pp. 212-213&lt;/ref&gt;

In terms of women's rights, the Aga Khan was more progressive in his views than Sir Sayyid and many other Islamic modernists of his time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Forging the ideal educated girl : the production of desirable subjects in Muslim South Asia|last=Khoja-Moolji, Shenila, 1982-|publisher=|isbn=9780520970533|location=Oakland, California|pages=27|oclc=1022084628|date = June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Aga Khan framed his pursuit of women's rights not simply in the context of women being better mothers or wives, but rather, for women's own benefit.&lt;ref&gt;Khoja-Moolji 2018, p. 31&lt;/ref&gt; He endorsed the spiritual equality of men and women in Islam, and he also called for full political equality.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Culture, transnationalism, and civil society : Aga Khan social service initiatives in Tanzania|last=Kaiser, Paul J.|date=1996|publisher=Praeger|isbn=0275955281|location=Westport, Conn.|pages=51|oclc=34545670}}&lt;/ref&gt; This included the right to vote&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Aga Khan III 1998, pp. 593 &amp; 645&lt;/ref&gt; and the right to an education.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aga Khan III 1998, p. 586&quot;&gt;Aga Khan III 1998, p. 586&lt;/ref&gt; In regards to the latter issue, he endorsed compulsory primary education for girls.&lt;ref&gt;Aga Khan III 1998, p. 1117&lt;/ref&gt; He also encouraged women to pursue higher university-level education,&lt;ref name=&quot;Aga Khan III 1998, p. 586&quot;/&gt; and saw nothing wrong with co-educational institutions.&lt;ref&gt;Aga Khan III 1998, p. 587&lt;/ref&gt; Whereas Sir Sayyid prioritized the education of boys over girls, the Aga Khan instructed his followers that if they had a son and daughter, and if they could only afford to send one of them to school, they should send the daughter over the boy.&lt;ref&gt;Aga Khan III 1998, p. 1211-1212&lt;/ref&gt;

The Aga Khan campaigned against the institution of [[Purdah|purda]] and [[Zenana|zenāna]], which he felt were oppressive and un-Islamic institutions.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt; He completely banned the [[Purdah|purda]] and the face veil for his Ismāʿīlī followers.&lt;ref&gt;Khoja-Moolji 2018, p. 32&lt;/ref&gt; The Aga Khan also restricted polygamy, encouraged marriage to widows, and banned child marriage.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/muslimsinuniteds0000leon/page/68|title=Muslims in the United States : the state of research|last=Leonard, Karen Isaksen, 1939-|date=2003|publisher=Russell Sage Foundation|isbn=9781610443487|location=New York|pages=[https://archive.org/details/muslimsinuniteds0000leon/page/68 68]|oclc=794701243|url-access=registration}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also made marriage and divorce laws more equitable to women.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt; Overall, he encouraged women to take part in all national activities and to agitate for their full religious, social, and political rights.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

Today, in large part due to the Aga Khan's reforms, the Ismāʿīlī community is one of the most progressive, peaceful, and prosperous branches of Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Twaddle|first=Michael|date=July 1995|title=Asians in East Africa Quest for Equality: Asian Politics in East Africa, 1900–1967. By Robert G. Gregory. Hyderabad and London: Orient Longman and Sangam Books (57 London Fruit Exchange, London E1 6EP, UK), 1993. Pp. xvi + 231. £14.95 (ISBN 0-86311-208-0).|journal=The Journal of African History|volume=36|issue=2|pages=335–336|doi=10.1017/s0021853700034289|issn=0021-8537}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Racehorse ownership and equestrianism==
He was an owner of thoroughbred racing horses, including a record equalling five winners of [[Epsom Derby|The Derby]] ([[Blenheim (horse)|Blenheim]], [[Bahram (horse)|Bahram]], [[Mahmoud (horse)|Mahmoud]], [[My Love (horse)|My Love]], [[Tulyar (horse)|Tulyar]]) and a total of sixteen winners of [[British Classic Races]]. He was [[British flat racing Champion Owner]] thirteen times.  According to [[Ben Pimlott]], biographer of Queen [[Elizabeth II]], the Aga Khan presented Her Majesty with a [[filly]] called ''Astrakhan'', who won at [[Hurst Park Racecourse]] in 1950.

In 1926, the Aga Khan gave a cup (the [[Aga Khan Trophy]]) to be awarded to the winners of an international team [[show jumping]] competition held at the annual horse show of the [[Royal Dublin Society]] in Dublin, Ireland every first week in August.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dublinhorseshow.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=22&amp;Itemid=34 The Aga Khan Trophy], Dublin Horse Show, accessed 9 July 2007&lt;/ref&gt; It attracts competitors from all of the main show jumping nations and is carried live on Irish national television.

==Marriages and children==
* He married, on 2 November 1896, in [[Pune]], India, Shahzadi Begum, his first cousin and a granddaughter of [[Aga Khan I]].
* He married 1908,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ismaili.net/histoire/history08/history833.html |title=Marriages of the Aga Khan III |publisher=Ismaili.net |date= |accessdate=2014-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cleope Teresa Magliano (1888–1926). They had two sons: Prince Giuseppe Mahdi Khan (d. February 1911) and [[Prince Aly Khan]] (1911–1960). She died in 1926, following an operation on 1 December 1926.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Aga Khan's Wife Dies As He Buys Big Gem&quot;, The New York Times, 2 December 1926, p.&amp;nbsp;2&lt;/ref&gt;
* He married, on 7 December 1929 (civil), in [[Aix-les-Bains]], France, and 13 December 1929 (religious), in [[Mumbai|Bombay]], India, ''Andrée Joséphine Carron'' (1898–1976). A co-owner of a dressmaking shop in Paris, she became known as Princess Andrée Aga Khan. By this marriage, he had one son, Prince [[Sadruddin Aga Khan]] (1933–2003).&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Aga Khan Again a Father&quot;, The New York Times, 18 January 1933, p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt; The couple were divorced in 1943.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Princess Andrée&quot;, The New York Times, 30 December 1976, p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt;
* He married, on 9 October 1944, in [[Geneva]], Switzerland, [[Begum Om Habibeh Aga Khan]] (Yvonne Blanche Labrousse) (15 February 1906{{snd}}1 July 2000). According to an interview she gave to an Egyptian journalist, her first name was Yvonne, though she is referred to as Yvette in most published references. The daughter of a tram conductor and a dressmaker, she was working as the Aga Khan's social secretary at the time of their marriage. She converted to Islam and became known as ''Om Habibeh'' (Little Mother of the Beloved). In 1954, her husband bestowed upon her the title &quot;Mata Salamat&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Begum Aga Khan III&quot;, Daily Telegraph, Issue 45115, 3 July 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Publications==
He wrote a number of books and papers two of which are of immense importance, namely (1) '''''India in Transition''''', about the prepartition politics of India and (2) '''''The Memoirs of Aga Khan: World Enough and Time''''', his autobiography.

[[File:Assuan 9785.JPG|thumb|Mausoleum of Aga Khan – [[Aswan]], Egypt.]]
[[File:Assuan 9932.JPG|thumb|Mausoleum of Aga Khan, on the [[Nile]].]]

==Death and succession==
Aga Khan III was succeeded as Aga Khan by his grandson [[Aga Khan IV|Karim Aga Khan]], who is the present [[Shia Imam|Imam]] of the [[Ismaili]] Muslims. At the time of his death on 11 July 1957, his family members were in [[Versoix]]. A solicitor brought the will of the Aga Khan III from London to Geneva and read it before the family:

&lt;blockquote&gt;“Ever since the time of my ancestor Ali, the first Imam, that is to say over a period of thirteen hundred years, it has always been the tradition of our family that each Imam chooses his successor at his absolute and unfettered discretion from amongst any of his descendants, whether they be sons or remote male issue and in these circumstances and in view of the fundamentally altered conditions in the world in very recent years due to the great changes which have taken place including the discoveries of atomic science, I am convinced that it is in the best interest of the Shia Muslim Ismailia Community that I should be succeeded by a young man who has been brought up and developed during recent years and in the midst of the new age and who brings a new outlook on life to his office as Imam. For these reasons, I appoint my grandson Karim, the son of my own son, [[Prince Aly Khan|Aly Salomone Khan]] to succeed to the title of Aga Khan and to the Imam and Pir of all Shia Ismailian followers”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

He is buried in at the [[Mausoleum of Aga Khan]], on the [[Nile]] in [[Aswan]], Egypt. {{coord|24.088254|32.878722}}

==Legacy==
[[Pakistan Post]] issued a special 'Birth Centenary of Agha Khan III' postage stamp in his honor in 1977.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://pakistanphilately.com/1977.htm|title=Pakistan Philately|website=pakistanphilately.com|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Pakistan Post]] again issued a postage stamp in his honor in its 'Pioneers of Freedom' series in 1990.&lt;ref name=&quot;findpk&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://findpk.com/pof/agha_khan_iii.html|title=Agha Khan III|website=findpk.com|access-date=2019-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Honours==
*1 January 1934 Appointed a member of [[Her Majesty's Most Honourable Privy Council|His Majesty's Most Honourable Privy Council]] by King [[George V]]&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette |issue=34010 |date=1 January 1934 |page=1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*21 May 1898 [[Order of the Indian Empire|Knight Commander of the Order of the Indian Empire]], KCIE&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette |issue=26969 |date=21 May 1898 |page=3230 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*26 June 1902 [[Order of the Indian Empire|Knight Grand Commander of the Order of the Indian Empire]], GCIE&lt;ref name=LG27448&gt;{{London Gazette |issue=27448 |date=26 June 1902 |page=4197 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*12 December 1911 [[Order of the Star of India|Knight Grand Commander of the Order of the Star of India]], GCSI&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette |issue=28559 |date=12 December 1911 |page=9357 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*30 May 1923 [[Royal Victorian Order|Knight Grand Cross of the Royal Victorian Order]], GCVO – ''on the occasion of the King's birthday''&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette |issue=32830 |date=2 June 1923 |page=3947 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*1 January 1955 [[Order of St Michael and St George|Knight Grand Cross of the Order of St Michael and St George]], GCMG –&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette |issue=40366 |date=1 January 1955 |page=4 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*1901 [[Order of the Crown (Prussia)|First Class of the Royal Prussian Order of the Crown]] – ''in recognition of the valuable services rendered by His Highness to the Imperial German Government in the settlement of various matters with the Mohammedan population of German East Africa''&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette |issue=27291 |date=5 March 1901 |page=1576 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|33em}}

==Sources==
* {{EB1911 |last=Bhownagree |first=Mancherjee Merwanjee |authorlink=Mancherjee Bhownagree|wstitle=Aga Khan I. |display=Aga Khan I. s.v. Aga Khan III.|volume=1|page=363}}
* {{cite EB1922|wstitle=Aga Khan III|last=Brown |first=Frank Herbert}}
* Daftary, F., &quot;The Isma'ilis: Their History and Doctrines&quot;, Cambridge University Press, 1990.
* Naoroji M. Dumasia, ''A Brief History of the Aga Khan'' (1903).
* Aga Khan III, &quot;The Memoirs of Aga Khan: World Enough and Time&quot;, London: Cassel &amp; Company, 1954; published the same year in the United States by Simon &amp; Schuster.
* [[Anne Edwards|Edwards, Anne]] (1996). &quot;Throne of Gold: The Lives of the Aga Khans&quot;, New York: William Morrow, 1996
* Naoroji M. Dumasia, &quot;The Aga Khan and his ancestors&quot;, New Delhi: Readworthy Publications (P) Ltd., 2008
*Valliani, Amin; &quot;Aga Khan's Role in the Founding and Consolidation of the All India Muslim League&quot;, ''Journal of the Pakistan Historical Society'' (2007) 55# 1/2, pp 85–95.

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Commons+cat|Aga Khan III}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20071025075211/http://www.history.com/media.do?action=clip&amp;id=tdih_0712 Video Clip] from the [[History (U.S. TV channel)|History Channel]] website
* [http://www.iis.ac.uk/view_article.asp?ContentID=104628  Institute of Ismaili Studies: Selected speeches of Sir Sultan Mahomed Shah Aga Khan III]
* [http://www.theismaili.org]  The Official Ismaili Website
* [http://www.akdn.org]  Official Website of Aga Khan Development Network
* [http://www.saadigitalarchive.org/search/aga%20khan Aga Khan materials in the South Asian American Digital Archive (SAADA)]
* {{PM20|FID=pe/012379}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou|branch=Clan|name='''Aga Khan III'''&lt;br&gt;of the [[Ahl al-Bayt]]|[[Banu Hashim]]|1877|CE|1957|CE|[[Quraysh (tribe)|Banu Quraish]]}}
{{s-rel|sh}}
{{s-bef|before = [[Aga Khan II|Aqa Ali Shah]]}}
{{s-ttl|title = 48th [[Imamah (Shi'a Ismaili doctrine)|Imam]] of [[Nizari]] [[Ismailism]]|years = 1885–1957}}
{{s-aft|after = [[Aga Khan IV|Karim al-Hussayni]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{Pakistan Movement}}
{{LoNPresidents}}
{{Nizārī}}
{{Agha Khans}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Aga Khan 3}}
[[Category:1877 births]]
[[Category:1957 deaths]]
[[Category:Qajar dynasty]]
[[Category:Aga Khan Development Network]]
[[Category:British racehorse owners and breeders]]
[[Category:Owners of Epsom Derby winners]]
[[Category:Pakistani racehorse owners and breeders]]
[[Category:Pakistani philanthropists]]
[[Category:Pakistani religious leaders]]
[[Category:Indian philanthropists]]
[[Category:Leaders of the Pakistan Movement]]
[[Category:Pakistan Movement]]
[[Category:Hashemite people]]
[[Category:Fatimid dynasty]]
[[Category:Indian members of the Privy Council of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Presidents of the Assembly of the League of Nations]]
[[Category:People educated at Eton College]]
[[Category:Knights Grand Commander of the Order of the Indian Empire]]
[[Category:Knights Grand Commander of the Order of the Star of India]]
[[Category:Knights Grand Cross of the Order of St Michael and St George]]
[[Category:Knights Grand Cross of the Royal Victorian Order]]
[[Category:Indian knights]]
[[Category:Indian Ismailis]]
[[Category:Iranian Ismailis]]
[[Category:Pakistani Ismailis]]
[[Category:Nizari imams]]
[[Category:Indian imams]]
[[Category:Iranian imams]]
[[Category:Pakistani imams]]
[[Category:20th-century imams]]
[[Category:Founders of Indian schools and colleges]]
[[Category:People from Karachi]]
[[Category:Pakistani people of Iranian descent]]
[[Category:Owners of Prix de l'Arc de Triomphe winners]]</text>
      <sha1>29bus58mzgw8sm37u5pk7hymknq3iwn</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
