  <page>
    <title>Ahmed III</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1529</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941713172</id>
      <parentid>941713045</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-20T05:35:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Keivan.f</username>
        <id>14604687</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* top */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Sultan of the Ottoman Empire from 1703 to 1730}}
{{Infobox royalty
| name         = Ahmed III&lt;br /&gt;احمد ثالث
| title        = [[Sultan of the Ottoman Empire]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Caesar (title)#Ottoman Empire|Kayser-i Rûm]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Custodian of the Two Holy Mosques]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Ottoman Caliphate|Ottoman Caliph]]
| titletext    = 
| more         = 
| type         = 
| image        =  III. Ahmet.jpg
| alt          = 
| caption      = 
| moretext     = 
| succession   = 23rd [[List of sultans of the Ottoman Empire|Ottoman Sultan]] ([[Padishah|Emperor]])
| reign        = 22 August 1703{{snd}}1 October 1730
| coronation   = 
| cor-type     = 
| predecessor  = [[Mustafa II]]
| regent       = 
| reg-type     = 
| successor    = [[Mahmud I]]
| spouse       = [[Mihrişah Kadın]] &lt;br&gt; [[Emine Muslı Kadın]] &lt;br&gt;[[Şermi Kadın]] &lt;br&gt; among [[Ahmed III#Consorts|others]]
| spouse-type  = Consorts
| issue        = see [[Ahmed III#Family|below]]
| full name    = Ahmed bin Mehmed
| house        = [[Ottoman dynasty|Ottoman]]
| house-type   = Dynasty
| father       = [[Mehmed IV]]
| mother       = [[Gülnuş Sultan]]
| birth_date   = 30 December 1673
| birth_place  = [[Dobrich|Hacıoğlu Pazarcık]], [[Ottoman Empire]] &lt;br&gt; (present day [[Dobrich]], [[Bulgaria]])
| death_date   = {{death date and age|1736|7|1|1673|12|30|df=yes}}
| death_place  = [[Constantinople]], Ottoman Empire &lt;br&gt; (present day [[Istanbul]], [[Turkey]])
| burial_date  = 
| burial_place = [[Tomb of Turhan Sultan]], Istanbul
| signature_type = [[Tughra]]
| religion     = [[Sunni Islam]]
| signature    = Tughra of Ahmed III.JPG
}}
'''Ahmed III''' ([[Ottoman Turkish language|Ottoman Turkish]]: احمد ثالث, ''Aḥmed-i &lt;u&gt;s&lt;/u&gt;āli&lt;u&gt;s&lt;/u&gt;'') &lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;(30 December 1673{{snd}}1 July 1736)&lt;/span&gt; was [[Sultan]] of the [[Ottoman Empire]] and a son of Sultan [[Mehmed IV]] (r. 1648–87). His mother was [[Gülnuş Sultan]], originally named Evmenia Voria, who was an ethnic Greek.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author = Freely, John |title=The lost Messiah |publisher=Viking |year=2001 |page=132 |isbn=0-670-88675-0 |quote= He set up his harem there, his favourite being Rabia Giilniis Ummetiillah, a [[Greeks|Greek]] girl from Rethymnon on Crete }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author = Bromley, J. S. |title= The New Cambridge Modern History |publisher= University Press |location= University of California |year= 1957 |page=554 |isbn=0-521-22128-5 |quote= the mother of Mustafa II and Ahmed III was a [[Greeks|Greek]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author = Sardo, Eugenio Lo |title=Tra greci e turchi: fonti diplomatiche italiane sul Settecento ottomano |publisher=Consiglio nazionale delle ricerche |year=1999 |page=82 |isbn= 88-8080-014-0 |quote= Their mother, a [[Greeks|Greek]], lady named Rabia Gülnûş, continued to wield influence as the [[Valide Sultan]] - mother of the reigning sultan  }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |authors = Library Information and Research Service |title= The Middle East |publisher= Library Information and Research Service |year= 2005 |page= 91 |quote= She was the daughter of a [[Greeks|Greek]] family and she was the mother of Mustafa II (1664–1703), and Ahmed III (1673–1736). }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |authors = Baker, Anthony E - Freely, John |title=The Bosphorus |publisher=Redhouse Press |year=1993 |page=146 |isbn=975-413-062-0 |quote= The Valide Sultan was born Evmania Voria, daughter of a [[Greeks|Greek]] priest in a village near [[Rethymnon]] on Crete. She was captured by the Turks when they took [[Rethymnon]] in 1645. }}&lt;/ref&gt; He was born at [[Dobrich|Hacıoğlu Pazarcık]], in [[Dobruja]]. He succeeded to the throne in 1703 on the abdication of his brother [[Mustafa II]] (1695–1703).&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;&gt;{{EB1911|inline=1|wstitle=Ahmed III.|volume=1|page=431}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Nevşehirli Damat İbrahim Pasha]] and the Sultan's daughter, [[Fatma Sultan (daughter of Ahmed III)|Fatma Sultan]] (wife of the former) directed the government from 1718 to 1730, a period referred to as the ''[[Tulip Era in the Ottoman Empire|Tulip Era]]''.

The first days of Ahmed III's reign passed with efforts to appease the janissaries who were completely disciplined.  However, he was not effective against the janissaries who made him sultan. Çorlulu Ali Pasha, who Ahmed brought to the Grand Vizier, tried to help him in administrative matters, made new arrangements for the treasury and Sultan III.  He supported Ahmed in his fight with his rivals.

==Early life and education==
Sultan Ahmed was born on 30 December 1673. His father was Sultan [[Mehmed IV]], and his mother was [[Gülnuş Sultan]], originally named Evmenia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author= Baker, Anthony E |title=The Bosphorus |publisher=Redhouse Press |year=1993 |page=146 |isbn=975-413-062-0 |quote= The Valide Sultan was born Evmania Voria, daughter of a Greek priest in a village near Rethymnon on Crete. She was captured by the Turks when they took Rethymnon in 1645. }}&lt;/ref&gt; His birth occurred in Hacıoğlupazarı, where Mehmed stayed to hunt on his return from Poland in 1673, while Gülnuş was pregnant at that time.{{sfn|Sakaoğlu|2015|p=295}} In 1675, He and his brother, Prince Mustafa (future [[Mustafa II]]) were circumcised. During the same ceremony their sisters [[Hatice Sultan (daughter of Mehmed IV)|Hatice Sultan]] and Fatma Sultan were married to Musahip Mustafa Pasha and [[Kara Mustafa Pasha]] respectively.{{sfn|Uluçay|2011|p=110}} The celebrations lasted 20 days.{{sfn|Sakaoğlu|2015|p=286}}

He grew up in the [[Edirne Palace]]. His schooling began during one of the sporadic visits of the court to Istanbul, following a courtly ceremony called ''bad-i basmala'', which took place on 9 August 1679 in the Istavroz Palace. He was brought up in the imperial harem in Edirne with a traditional princely education, studying the Qur’an, the hadiths (traditions of Prophet Muhammad), and the fundamentals of Islamic sciences, history, poetry and music under the supervision of private tutors.{{sfn|Keskiner|2012|p=47}} One of his tutors was chief mufti Feyzullah Efendi.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Jane|last=Hathaway|title=The Chief Eunuch of the Ottoman Harem: From African Slave to Power-Broker|publisher=Cambridge University Press|date=August 30, 2018|pages=133|isbn=978-1-107-10829-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ahmed was apparently curious and intellectual in nature, spending most of his time reading and practising calligraphy. The poems that he wrote manifest his profound knowledge of poetry, history, Islamic theology and philosophy. He was also interested in calligraphy, which he had studied with the leading court calligraphers, primarily with Hafız
Osman Efendi (died 1698), who influenced his art immensely, and, therefore, practiced it because of the influence of his elder brother, the future Sultan [[Mustafa II]], who also became a notable calligrapher.{{sfn|Keskiner|2012|p=47}}

During his princehood in Edirne, Ahmed made friends
with a bright officer-scribe, [[Nevşehirli Damat Ibrahim Pasha|Ibrahim]], from the city of [[Nevşehir]], who was to become one of the outstanding Grand Viziers of his future reign. From 1687, following the deposition of his father, he lived in isolation for sixteen years in the palaces of Edirne and Istanbul. During this period he dedicated 
himself to calligraphy and intellectual activities.{{sfn|Keskiner|2012|p=47-8}}{{sfn|Sakaoğlu|2015|p=296}}

== Reign ==
[[File:Een ambassadeur op audiëntie bij sultan Ahmed III Rijksmuseum SK-A-4080.jpeg|thumb|250px|right|Ahmed III in the Imperial Darbar of Topkapi Palace.]]

===Accession===
{{Main|Edirne event}}
Ahmed succeeded to the throne on 22 August 1703 when his brother [[Mustafa II]] was deposed from the throne and announced his withdrawal of the throne. The first Friday salute was held in Bayezid Mosque.&lt;ref&gt;Sakaoğlu, Necdet (2015) ''Bu mülkün sultanları''&lt;/ref&gt; Istanbul, which has been out of control for a long time, was not a peaceful and safe environment.  As the confusions, arrests and executions continued, theft and robbery incidents were common.  {{sfn|Sakaoğlu|2015|p=297}}

===Russo-Ottoman War of 1710–11===
{{Main|Pruth River Campaign}}
Ahmed III cultivated good relations with France, doubtless in view of [[Imperial Russia|Russia]]'s menacing attitude. He afforded refuge in Ottoman territory to [[Charles XII of Sweden]] (1682–1718) after the Swedish defeat at the hands of [[Peter I of Russia]] (1672–1725) in the [[Battle of Poltava]] of 1709.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911}} In 1710 Charles XII convinced Sultan Ahmed III to declare war against Russia, and the Ottoman forces under [[Baltacı Mehmet Pasha]] won a major victory at the [[Pruth River Campaign|Battle of Prut]]. In the aftermath, Russia returned [[Azov]] back to the Ottomans, agreed to demolish the fortress of [[Taganrog]] and others in the area, and to stop interfering in the affairs of the [[Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth]].

Forced against his will into war with Russia, Ahmed III came nearer than any Ottoman sovereign before or since to breaking the power of his northern rival, whose armies his [[grand vizier]] [[Nevşehirli Damat İbrahim Pasha]] succeeded in completely surrounding at the Pruth River Campaign in 1711.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; The subsequent Ottoman victories against Russia enabled the Ottoman Empire to advance to Moscow, had the Sultan wished. However, this was halted as a report reached [[Istanbul]] that the [[Safavid dynasty|Safavids]] were invading the Ottoman Empire, causing a period of panic, turning the Sultan's attention away from Russia.

===Wars with Venice and Austria===
[[File:Jean-Baptiste van Mour 006.jpg|thumb|Sultan Ahmed III receives French ambassador Vicomte d'Andrezel at [[Topkapı Palace]].]]
[[File:Marquis de Bonnac being received by Sultan Ahmed III.jpg|thumb|French ambassador [[Marquis de Bonnac]] being received by Sultan Ahmed III.]]
[[File:Ahmet III 1720.jpg|thumb|Sultan Ahmed III at a reception, painted in 1720]]
On 9 December 1714, war was declared on Venice, and an army under [[Silahdar Damat Ali Pasha]]'s command, {{sfn|Keskiner|2012|p=56}} the Ottomans managed to recover the whole Morea (Peloponnese) from Venice through coordinated operations of the army and navy.{{sfn|Ágoston|Masters|2009|p=25}}

This success alarmed Austria and in April 1716, Emperor [[Charles VI, Holy Roman Emperor|Charles VI]] provoked the Porte into a declaration of war. The unsuccessful battle, also 
commanded by Silahdar Ali Pasha, ended with the treaty of Passarovitz, signed on 21 July 1718, according to which Belgrade, Banat, and little Wallachia were ceded to Austria. This failure was a real disappointment for Ahmed and after the bad conditions imposed by this treaty, Istanbul's economy suffered from increased inflation and all of its attendant evils.{{sfn|Keskiner|2012|p=57}}

Ibrahim Pasha who was the second leading figure of the empire after Ahmed had joined the Morea campaign in 1715, and was appointed as the city of Nish's minister of finance the following year. This post helped him realize the downturn of the state's finances and, due to his insight of this sensitive financial situation he avoided war as much as possible during his vizierate. Ibrahim Pasha's policy of peace suited Ahmed as well since he had no wish to lead any military campaigns, in addition to the fact that his interest in art and culture made him reluctant to leave his Istanbul.{{sfn|Keskiner|2012|p=57}}

===Character of Ahmed's rule===
While shooting competitions were held in Okmeydanı with the idea of increasing the morale of the soldiers and the people, a new warship was launched in Tersane-i Amir.  He tried three grand viziers at short intervals.  Instead of Hasan Pasha, he appointed Kalaylikoz Ahmed Pasha on 24 September 1704, and Baltacı Mehmed Pasha on 25 December 1704. {{sfn|Sakaoğlu|2015|p=297}} It was a great pleasure that the ambassadors of Iran and Austria, who came from 1706–1707.  In 1707, the conspiracy led by Eyüplü Ali Ağa was unearthed to bring the sultan off the throne.  Necks were cut in front of the Bab-I-Hümayun . Ahmed III left the finances of the [[Ottoman Empire]] in a flourishing condition, which had remarkably been obtained without excessive taxation or extortion procedures. He was a cultivated [[Patronage|patron]] of literature and art, and it was in his time that the first [[printing press]] authorized to use the Arabic or Turkish languages was set up in Istanbul, operated by [[Ibrahim Muteferrika]] (while the printing press had been introduced to Constantinople in 1480, all works published before 1729 were in Greek, Armenian, or Hebrew).

[[File:Levni 002 detail.jpg|thumb|A [[Portrait miniature|miniature]] of Sultan Ahmed III by [[Abdulcelil Levni|Levni]]]]
It was in this reign that an important change in the government of the [[Danubian Principalities]] was introduced: previously, the [[Ottoman Porte|Porte]] had appointed [[Hospodar]]s, usually native [[Moldavia]]n and [[Wallachia]]n [[boyar]]s, to administer those provinces; after the [[Pruth River Campaign|Russian campaign]] of 1711, during which [[Peter I of Russia|Peter the Great]] found an ally in [[Moldavia]] [[List of rulers of Moldavia|Prince]] [[Dimitrie Cantemir]], the Porte began overtly deputizing [[Phanariotes|Phanariote]] [[Greeks]] in that region, and extended the system to [[Wallachia]] after [[List of rulers of Wallachia|Prince]] [[Stefan Cantacuzino]] established links with [[Prince Eugene of Savoy|Eugene of Savoy]]. The Phanariotes constituted a kind of ''[[Dhimmi]]'' nobility, which supplied the Porte with functionaries in many important departments of the state.

In 1714, an Egyptian galleon standing near the Gümrük (Eminönü) Pier caught fire and burned, and two hundred people died.{{sfn|Sakaoğlu|2015|p=299}}

===Relations with the Mughal Empire===

====Jahandar Shah====
In the year 1712, the [[Mughal Emperor]] [[Jahandar Shah]], the grandson of [[Aurangzeb]] sent gifts to the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] [[Sultan]] Ahmed III and referred to himself as the Ottoman Sultan's devoted admirer.&lt;ref name=&quot;google&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Mughal-Ottoman relations: a study of political &amp; diplomatic relations between Mughal India and the Ottoman Empire, 1556-1748|author =Farooqi, N.R.|date=1989|publisher=Idarah-i Adabiyat-i Delli|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=uB1uAAAAMAAJ}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Farrukhsiyar====
The [[Mughal Emperor]] [[Farrukhsiyar]] a grandson of [[Aurangzeb]], is also known to have sent a letter to the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottomans]] but this time it was received by the [[Grand Vizier]] [[Nevşehirli Damad Ibrahim Pasha]] providing a graphic description of the efforts of the [[Mughal Empire|Mughal]] commander [[Sayyid Brothers|Syed Hassan Ali Khan Barha]] against the [[Rajput]] and [[Maratha]] rebellion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=uB1uAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=Farrukhsiyar |title=Mughal-Ottoman relations: a study of political &amp; diplomatic relations ... - Naimur Rahman Farooqi |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=2012-04-29|year=1989 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Architecture===
Ahmed III built water claps, fountain and park waterfalls. Ahmed, who built three libraries, one inside the Topkapı Palace, and one of the famous lines of his period.  Ahmed was a master in the writings on plates.  Some plates and inscriptions have survived.  The “Basmala” at the Topkapi Palace apartment door with its plates in the 
Üsküdar Yeni Mosque are among them.{{sfn|Sakaoğlu|2015|p=307}}

Topkapı Palace and its buildings have been the subject of many researches and publications.  Among these researches, many different scope studies are also noticed together with postgraduate theses.  Consequently, they provide rich information about the palace, which provides a long list of highly qualified scientific articles and books, guides and brochures promoting the palace and museum.  However, Topkapi Palace and its units still have aspects to be explored and details to be discussed.  Among them Ahmed III library can also be counted. {{sfn|Uysal|2019|p=333}}

===Deposition===
{{Main|Patrona Halil}}
Sultan Ahmed III had become unpopular by reason of the excessive pomp and costly luxury in which he and his principal officers indulged; on 20 September 1730, a mutinous riot of seventeen [[Janissaries]], led by the [[Albanians|Albanian]] [[Patrona Halil]], was aided by the citizens as well as the military until it swelled into an insurrection in front of which the Sultan was forced to give up the throne.

Ahmed voluntarily led his nephew [[Mahmud I]] (1730–54) to the seat of sovereignty and paid allegiance to him as Sultan of the Empire. He then retired to the [[Kafes]] previously occupied by Mahmud and died at [[Topkapı Palace]] after six years of confinement.

==Disasters in his reign==
===Fire of 1718===
While [[Nevşehirli Damat Ibrahim Pasha]] continued his preparations for return to Istanbul, a fire broke out in Istanbul.  Unkapanı, Azapkapı, [[Zeyrek]], [[Fatih]], Saraçhane, Horhor, Etmeydanı, Molla Gürani, Altımermer, Ayazma Gate, Kantarcılar, Vefa, Vez neciler, Old Rooms, Acemioğlanlar Barracks, Çukur Çeşme, Langa, Davudpaşa districts were burned from the fire. {{sfn|Sakaoğlu|2015|p=300}}

===Earthquake of 1719===
However, this festivity went astringent as it came just after the three-minute big earthquake on 14 May 1719.  While the city walls of Istanbul were destroyed in the earthquake, 4000 people died in [[Izmit]] and Yalova was destroyed.  After the earthquake, reconstruction work started in Istanbul.  The most meaningful element that reflects the cultural aspect or weight of these works until today is the Topkapı Palace Enderun Library, which was built that year.  A rich foundation was established for this institution, which is also known as Sultan Ahmed-i Salis Library, which has a face-to-face with its architectural and valuable manuscripts. {{sfn|Sakaoğlu|2015|p=301}}

==Family==
;Consorts
* Emetullah Kadın (died 1739, buried in [[Eyüp Sultan Mosque]]);
* Rukiye Kadın;
* [[Mihrişah Kadın|Emine Mihrişah Kadın]] (died 1732, buried in [[New Mosque (Istanbul)|New Mosque]], [[Istanbul]]);
* [[Şermi Kadın|Rabia Şermi Kadın]] (died 1732, buried in New Mosque, Istanbul);
* Ümmügülsüm Kadın (died 1768, buried in New Mosque, Istanbul);
* Hatice Kadın (died 1722, buried in New Mosque, Istanbul);
* Fatma Kadın (died 1732, buried in New Mosque, Istanbul);
* [[Emine Muslı Kadın]] (died 1750, buried in New Mosque, Istanbul);
* Hanife Kadın (died 1750, buried in New Mosque, Istanbul);
* Zeynep Kadın (died 1757, buried in New Mosque, Istanbul);
* Şahin Kadın (died 1732, buried in New Mosque, Istanbul);
* Hace Hanım Kadın;

;Sons
* Şehzade Mehmed (26 November 1705 - died young);
* Şehzade Isa (23 February 1706 - 25 May 1706);
* Şehzade Ali (18 June 1706 - 12 September 1706); 
* Şehzade Selim (8 September 1707 - 5 May 1708);
* Şehzade Murad (2 February 1708 - 10 April 1708);
* Şehzade Abdülmelik (12 December 1709 - 23 March 1711);
* Şehzade Süleyman (25 August 1710 - 11 December 1732), son of Mihrişah Kadın; 
* Şehzade Mehmed (20 October 1712 – 15 July 1713);
* Şehzade Mehmed  (29 June 1713- 11 August 1713);  {{sfn|Sakaoğlu|2015|p=307}}
* Şehzade Mehmed (14 January 1717 {{sfn|Sakaoğlu|2015|p=307}}{{sfn|Aktaş|2008|p=99}} - murdered 22 December 1756){{sfn|Aktaş|2008|p=99}}{{sfn|Sakaoğlu|2015|p=307}}
* [[Mustafa III]] (28 January 1717 - 21 January 1774), son of Mihrişah Kadın;
* Şehzade Mahmud (12 August 1717- 1756); {{sfn|Sakaoğlu|2015|p=307}}
* Şehzade Bayezid (4 October 1718 - 25 January 1771); 
* Şehzade Abdullah (18 December 1719 - 19 December 1719); 
* Şehzade Selim (29 June 1720- 17 September 1742); {{sfn|Sakaoğlu|2015|p=307}}
* Şehzade Ibrahim (8 January 1721 - 4 April 1721, buried in New Mosque, Istanbul);
* Şehzade Numan (22 February 1723{{sfn|Aktaş|2008|p=13-4}} - 29 December 1764);
* [[Abdul Hamid I]] (20 March 1725{{sfn|Aktaş|2008|p=112}} - 7 April 1789), son of Şermi Kadın;
* Şehzade Seyfeddin (3 February 1728{{sfn|Aktaş|2008|p=255-6}} – 13 October 1732);

;Daughters 
* [[Fatma Sultan (daughter of Ahmed III)|Fatma Sultan]] (22 September  1704{{sfn|Râşid|2013|p=735}}{{snd}}4 January 1733), daughter of Emetullah Kadın.
* Hatice Sultan (21 January 1707{{sfn|Râşid|2013|p=773}}{{snd}}8 December 1708);{{sfn|Râşid|2013|p=788}}
* Rukiye Sultan (10 May 1707{{sfn|Râşid|2013|p=777}}{{snd}}29 August 1707);{{sfn|Râşid|2013|p=785}}
* Zeynep Sultan (8 February 1708{{snd}}5 October 1708);{{sfn|Râşid|2013|p=796}}
* [[Ümmügülsüm Sultan]] (11 February 1708{{snd}}28 November 1732);&lt;ref name=&quot;subhi&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first=Subhi Mehmed|last=Efendi|first2=Mesut|last2=Aydıner|first3=Hüseyin|last3=Şâkir|title=Subhî tarihi: Sâmî ve Şâkir tarihleri ile birlikte 1730-1744 (inceleme ve karşılaştırmalı metin)|publisher=Kitabevi|year=2007|pages=178|isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Zeyneb Sultan (5 January 1710{{sfn|Râşid|2013|p=829}}{{snd}}1 August 1710);{{sfn|Râşid|2013|p=838}}
* [[Hatice Sultan (daughter of Ahmed III)|Hatice Sultan]] (4 October  1710{{sfn|Râşid|2013|p=842}}{{snd}}1738), daughter of Rukiye Kadın;
* [[Atike Sultan (daughter of Ahmed III)|Atike Sultan]] (29 March 1712{{snd}}2 April 1738);
* Rukiye Sultan (6 March 1712{{snd}}26 November 1714);
* [[Zeynep Sultan]] (8 April 1714{{snd}}25 March 1774);
* [[Saliha Sultan (daughter of Ahmed III)|Saliha Sultan]] (21 March 1715{{sfn|Râşid|2013|p=898}}{{snd}}11 October 1778), daughter of Hace Hanım Kadın;
* [[Ayşe Sultan (daughter of Ahmed III)|Ayşe Sultan]] (24 November 1718{{snd}}3 October 1776), daughter of Emine Muslıhe Kadın; 
* Rabia Sultan (19 November 1719{{sfn|Râşid|2013|p=1170}}{{snd}}died in infancy)
* Emetullah Sultan (23 December 1719{{snd}}5 February 1720);
* Emetullah Sultan (29 September 1723{{sfn|Râşid|2013|p=1334}}{{sfn|Aktaş|2008|p=32}}{{snd}}28 July 1724);{{sfn|Râşid|2013|p=1387}}{{sfn|Aktaş|2008|p=80}}
* Naile Sultan (15 February 1725{{sfn|Râşid|2013|p=1422}}{{sfn|Aktaş|2008|p=111}}{{snd}}10 December 1726);{{sfn|Râşid|2013|p=1529}}{{sfn|Aktaş|2008|p=205}}
* Nazife Sultan (31 May 1725{{sfn|Râşid|2013|p=1437}}{{sfn|Aktaş|2008|p=125}}1 September 1726);
* [[Esma Sultan (daughter of Ahmed III)|Esma Sultan]] (14 March 1726{{sfn|Râşid|2013|p=1483}}{{sfn|Aktaş|2008|p=164-5}}{{snd}}13 August 1788), daughter of Hanife Kadın;
* Sabiha Sultan (26 November 1726{{snd}}3 December 1726);{{sfn|Râşid|2013|p=1422}}{{sfn|Aktaş|2008|p=199}}
* Rebia Sultan (4 August 1727{{sfn|Râşid|2013|p=1564}}{{sfn|Aktaş|2008|p=236}}{{snd}}4 April 1728);{{sfn|Râşid|2013|p=1589}}{{sfn|Aktaş|2008|p=258}}
* [[Zübeyde Sultan]] (29 March 1728{{sfn|Aktaş|2008|p=257}} - 4 June 1756), daughter of Emine Muslıhe Kadın;
* Ümmüseleme Sultan (died 1732);&lt;ref name=&quot;subhi&quot;/&gt;
* Emine Sultan (died 1732);&lt;ref name=&quot;subhi&quot;/&gt;

==Death==
Ahmed lived in Kafes of the Topkapi Palace for six years following his deposition. Where he fall ill and died on 1 July 1736. He was buried in his grandmother's tomb in [[Tomb of Turhan Sultan|Turhan Sultan Mausoleum]] in New Mosque, at Eminönü in Istanbul.{{sfn|Sakaoğlu|2015|p=306}}

==In fiction==
In [[Voltaire]]'s ''[[Candide]]'', the eponymous main character meets the deposed Ahmed III on a ship from [[Venice]] to [[Constantinople]]. The Sultan is in the company of five other deposed European monarchs, and he tells Candide, who initially doubts his credentials:

&lt;blockquote&gt;I am not jesting, my name is Achmet III. For several years I was Sultan; I dethroned my brother; my nephew dethroned me; they cut off the heads of my viziers; I am ending my days in the old seraglio; my nephew, Sultan Mahmoud, sometimes allows me to travel for my health, and I have come to spend the Carnival at Venice.&quot; [https://archive.org/stream/candideotherroma00voltuoft/candideotherroma00voltuoft_djvu.txt]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

This episode was taken up by the modern Turkish writer [[Nedim Gürsel]] as the setting of his 2001 novel ''Le voyage de Candide à Istanbul''.

In fact, there is no evidence of the deposed Sultan being allowed to make such foreign travels, nor did Voltaire (or Gürsel) assert that it had any actual historical foundation.

== See also ==
* [[Fountain of Ahmed III]]
* [[Fountain of Ahmed III (Üsküdar)]]
* [[Ibrahim Muteferrika]]
* [[Esma Sultan (1726-1788)|Esma Sultan]], daughter of Ahmed III

== References ==
{{Reflist|3}}

==Sources==
* This article incorporates text from the ''History of Ottoman Turks'' (1878)
* {{cite book|title=Târîh-i Râşid ve Zeyli (Râşid Mehmed Efendi ve Çelebizâde İsmaîl Âsım Efendi) (1071-1141/1660-1729) Cilt I-III|publisher=|year=2013|isbn=978-6-055-24512-2}}
* {{cite book|first=Ali|last=Aktaş|title=ÇELEBİZÂDE ÂSIM TARİHİ: Transkripsiyonlu metin|publisher=|year=2008|isbn=}}
* {{cite book|author=[[Silahdar Findiklili Mehmed Agha]]|title=Nusretnâme: Tahlil ve Metin (1106-1133/1695-1721)|publisher=|year=2001|isbn=}}
*{{cite book|first=Necdet|last=Sakaoğlu|title=Bu Mülkün Sultanları|publisher=Alfa Yayıncılık|year=2015|isbn=978-6-051-71080-8}}
*{{cite book|first=Zekiye|last=Uysal|title= Topkapı Sarayındaki III. Ahmet Kütüphanesi’nin Alçı Bezemeleri |publisher=|year=2019|isbn=}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category-inline}}+

{{wikisource author-inline}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou|[[Ottoman Dynasty|House of Osman]]||30 December 1673||1 July 1736}}[aged 62]
{{s-reg|}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Mustafa II]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[List of sultans of the Ottoman Empire|Sultan of the Ottoman Empire]]|years=22 August 1703{{snd}}1 October 1730}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Mahmud I]]}}
{{s-rel|su}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Mustafa II]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[List of caliphs|Caliph of the Ottoman Caliphate]]|years=22 August 1703{{snd}}1 October 1730}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Mahmud I]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{Sultans of the Ottoman Empire}}
{{Sons of the Ottoman Sultans}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:People of Turkic descent]]
[[Category:Turkic rulers]]
[[Category:Turkish male poets]]
[[Category:1673 births]]
[[Category:1736 deaths]]
[[Category:18th-century Ottoman sultans]]
[[Category:Ottoman sultans born to Greek mothers]]
[[Category:Turks of the Ottoman Empire]]
[[Category:Custodian of the Two Holy Mosques]]
[[Category:Ottoman dynasty]]</text>
      <sha1>bovo8sju5lxwgnaoskgb07c8cuv5iak</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
