  <page>
    <title>Alaric I</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1570</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942580640</id>
      <parentid>942580538</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-25T15:21:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Richard Keatinge</username>
        <id>1179038</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Death and funeral */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|4th and 5th-century King of the Visigoths}}
{{Infobox monarch
| name            = Alaric
| title           = King of the [[Visigoths]]
| image= Alaric entering Athens.jpg
| caption         = Imaginary 1920s depiction of Alaric parading through [[Athens]] after conquering the city in 395
| reign           = 395–410
| coronation      = 395
| predecessor     = [[Athanaric]]
| successor       = [[Ataulf]]
| issue           =
| dynasty         = [[Balt dynasty|Balt]]
| father          = Unknown&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Herwig |last=Wolfram |title=The Roman Empire and Its Germanic Peoples |location= |publisher=University of California Press |year=1997 |isbn=0-520-08511-6 |url={{Google books |plainurl=yes |id=tOnQDfRU-poC |page=90 }} |page=90 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| mother          =
| birth_date      = 370 (or 375)
| birth_place     = [[Peuce Island]], [[Dobruja]] (present-day Romania)
| death_date      = 410
| death_place     = [[Cosenza]], [[Calabria]], [[Italy]]
| place of burial = [[Busento River]], [[Calabria]], [[Italy]]
| religion        = [[Arianism]]
}}

'''Alaric I''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|æ|l|ər|ɪ|k}}; {{lang-got|Alareiks, 𐌰𐌻𐌰𐍂𐌴𐌹𐌺𐍃}}, &quot;ruler of all&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;Kelsie B. Harder, ''Names and their varieties: a collection of essays in onomastics'', American Name Society, University Press of America, 1984, pp. 10–11&lt;/ref&gt; {{lang-la|Alaricus}}; 370 (or 375){{snd}}410 AD) was the first [[Germanic Kingship|king]] of the [[Visigoths]] from 395–410, son (or paternal grandson) of chieftain [[Rothestes]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Settipani|first=Christian|authorlink=Christian Settipani|date=1993|title=La Préhistoire des Capétiens, 481–987, Première Partie|url=|location=Villeneuve d'Ascq|publisher=|page=Tableau 1|isbn=|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is best known for his [[sack of Rome (410)|sack of Rome]] in 410, which marked a decisive event in the [[fall of the Western Roman Empire|decline]] of the [[Western Roman Empire]].

Alaric began his career under the Gothic soldier [[Gainas]], and later joined the Roman army.  He first appeared as leader of a mixed band of [[Goths]] and allied peoples, who invaded [[Thrace]] in 391 but were stopped by the half-[[Vandal]] Roman General [[Stilicho]]. In 394, he led a Gothic force of 20,000 that helped [[Roman Emperor]] [[Theodosius I|Theodosius]] defeat the [[Franks|Frankish]] usurper [[Arbogast (general)|Arbogast]] at the [[Battle of Frigidus]]. Despite sacrificing around 10,000 of his men, Alaric received little recognition from the emperor. Disappointed, he left the army, was elected [[reiks]] of the [[Visigoths]] in 395 and marched toward [[Constantinople]] until he was diverted by Roman forces. He then moved southward into [[Greece]], where he sacked [[Piraeus]] (the port of [[Athens]]) and destroyed [[Corinth]], [[Megara]], [[Argos]] and [[Sparta]]. Nonetheless, the [[Eastern Roman Emperor|Eastern emperor]] [[Arcadius]] appointed Alaric [[magister militum]] (&quot;master of the soldiers&quot;) in [[Praetorian prefecture of Illyricum|Illyricum]].

In 401 Alaric invaded Italy, but was defeated by [[Stilicho]] at [[Battle of Pollentia|Pollentia]] (modern Pollenza) on April{{nbsp}}6, 402. A second invasion that same year also ended in defeat at the [[Battle of Verona (402)|Battle of Verona]], although he did force the [[Roman Senate]] to pay a large subsidy to the Visigoths. During [[Radagaisus]]' Italian invasion in 406, he remained idle in [[Illyria]]. In 408, [[Western Emperor]] [[Honorius (emperor)|Honorius]] ordered the execution of Stilicho and his family, in response to rumors that the general had made a deal with Alaric. Honorius then incited the Roman population to massacre tens of thousands of wives and children of [[foederati]] Goths serving in the Roman military. The Gothic soldiers then defected to Alaric, increasing the size of his force to around 30,000 men, and joined his march on Rome to avenge their murdered families.&lt;ref name=Heather&gt;{{cite book |last=Heather |first=Peter |authorlink=Peter Heather|date=2006 |title=The Fall of the Roman Empire: A New History |publisher= Pan Books|page= 224|isbn=978-0-330-49136-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Moving swiftly along [[Roman road]]s, Alaric sacked the cities of [[Aquileia]] and [[Cremona]] and ravaged the lands along the [[Adriatic Sea]]. The Visigothic leader thereupon laid siege to Rome in 408, but eventually the Senate granted him a substantial subsidy. In addition, he forced the Senate to liberate all 40,000 [[Goths|Gothic]] slaves in Rome. Honorius, however, refused to appoint Alaric as the commander of the Western Roman Army, and in 409 the Visigoths again surrounded Rome. Alaric lifted his blockade after proclaiming [[Priscus Attalus|Attalus]] [[Western Emperor]]. Attalus appointed him [[magister utriusque militiae]] (&quot;master of both services&quot;), but refused to allow him to send an army into [[Africa]]. Negotiations with Honorius broke down, after which Alaric deposed Attalus in the summer of 410 and besieged Rome for the third time. Allies within the capital opened the gates for him on August{{nbsp}}24, and for three days his troops [[sack of Rome (410)|sacked the city]]. Although the Visigoths plundered Rome, they treated its inhabitants humanely and burned only a few buildings. Having abandoned a plan to occupy [[Sicily]] and [[North Africa]] after the destruction of his fleet in a storm, Alaric died as the Visigoths were marching northward.

==Early life==
{{unreferenced section|date=August 2018}}
[[File:Alarich steel engraving.jpg|right|thumb|Imaginary portrait of Alaric in C. Strahlheim, ''Das Welttheater'', 4. Band, Frankfurt a.M., 1836]]
Born on [[Peuce Island]] at the mouth of the [[Danube Delta]] in present-day [[Romania]], Alaric belonged to the noble [[Balti dynasty]] of the [[Thervingi|Tervingian]] [[Goths]]. The Goths suffered setbacks against the [[Huns]], made a mass migration across the [[Danube]], and fought a [[Gothic War (376–382)|war with Rome]]. Alaric was probably a child during this period.

==In Roman service==
During the fourth century, the [[Roman emperors]] commonly employed ''[[foederati]]'': [[irregular military|irregular troops]] under Roman command, but organized by tribal structures. To spare the provincial populations from excessive taxation and to save money, emperors began to employ units recruited from Germanic tribes.  The largest of these contingents was that of the Goths, who in 382 (376 in some sources), had been allowed to settle within the imperial boundaries, keeping a large degree of autonomy.

In 394 Alaric served as a leader of ''foederati'' under [[Theodosius I]] in the campaign which crushed the usurper [[Arbogast (general)|Arbogast]]. As the [[Battle of the Frigidus]], which terminated this campaign, was fought at the passes of the [[Julian Alps]], Alaric probably learned the weakness of [[Italy]]'s natural defences on its northeastern frontier at the head of the [[Adriatic Sea]].{{sfn|Hodgkin|1911|p=470}}

Theodosius died in 395, leaving the Empire to be divided between his two sons [[Arcadius]] and [[Flavius Augustus Honorius|Honorius]], the former taking [[Byzantine Empire|the eastern]] and the latter [[Western Roman Empire|the western portion]] of the Empire.{{sfn|Hodgkin|1911|p=470}} Arcadius showed little interest in ruling, leaving most of the actual power to his [[Praetorian Prefect]] [[Rufinus (Byzantine official)|Rufinus]]. Honorius was still a minor; as his guardian, Theodosius had appointed the ''[[magister militum]]'' [[Stilicho]]. Stilicho also claimed to be the guardian of Arcadius, causing much rivalry between the western and eastern courts.

According to [[Edward Gibbon]] in ''[[The History of the Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire]]'', during the shifting of offices that took place at the beginning of the new reigns, Alaric apparently hoped he would be promoted from a mere commander to the rank of general in one of the regular armies. He was denied the promotion, however. Among the Visigoths settled in Lower [[Moesia]] (now part of Bulgaria and Romania), the situation was ripe for rebellion. They had suffered disproportionately great losses at Frigidus. According to rumour, exposing the Visigoths in battle was a convenient way of weakening the Gothic tribes. This, combined with their post-battle rewards, prompted them to raise Alaric &quot;on a shield&quot; and proclaim him king; according to [[Jordanes]], a 6th-century Roman bureaucrat of Gothic origin who later turned his hand to history, both the new king and his people decided &quot;rather to seek new kingdoms by their own work, than to slumber in peaceful subjection to the rule of others.&quot;{{sfn|Hodgkin|1911|p=470}}

==In Greece==
[[File:Ludwig Thiersch - Alaric à Athènes.jpg|300px|right|thumb|Alaric in Athens by [[Ludwig Thiersch]], 1894]]
Alaric struck first at the eastern empire. He marched to the neighborhood of [[Constantinople]] but, finding himself unable to undertake a siege, retraced his steps westward and then marched southward through [[Thessaly]] and the unguarded pass of [[Thermopylae]] into [[Greece]].{{sfn|Hodgkin|1911|p=470}}

The armies of the eastern empire were occupied with [[Huns|Hunnic]] incursions in [[Asia Minor]] and [[Syria]]. Instead, Rufinus attempted to negotiate with Alaric in person, which only aroused suspicions in Constantinople that Rufinus was in league with the Goths. Stilicho now marched east against Alaric. According to [[Claudian]], Stilicho was in a position to destroy the Goths when he was ordered by Arcadius – influenced by Rufinus – to leave [[Praetorian prefecture of Illyricum|Illyricum]]. Soon after, Rufinus' own soldiers hacked him to death. Power in Constantinople now passed to the eunuch Chamberlain [[Eutropius (Byzantine official)|Eutropius]].

Rufinus' death and Stilicho's departure gave free rein to Alaric's movements; he ravaged [[Attica]] but spared [[Athens]], which capitulated at once to the conqueror. In 396, he wiped out the last remnants of the [[Eleusinian Mysteries|Mysteries at Eleusis]] in Attica, ending a tradition of esoteric religious ceremonies that had lasted since the [[Bronze Age]]. Then he penetrated into the [[Peloponnesus]] and captured its most famous cities—[[Corinth, Greece|Corinth]], [[Argos]], and [[History of Sparta|Sparta]]—selling many of their inhabitants into slavery.{{sfn|Hodgkin|1911|p=470}}

Here, however, his victorious career suffered a serious setback. In 397 Stilicho crossed the sea to Greece and succeeded in trapping the Goths in the mountains of [[Pholoe]], on the borders of [[Elis]] and [[Arcadia]] in the peninsula. From there Alaric escaped with difficulty, and not without some suspicion of connivance by Stilicho, who supposedly had again received orders to depart. Alaric then crossed the [[Gulf of Corinth]] and marched with the plunder of [[Greece]] northward to [[Despotate of Epirus|Epirus]].{{sfn|Hodgkin|1911|pp=470–471}} Here his rampage continued until the eastern government appointed him ''magister militum per Illyricum'', giving him the Roman command he had desired, as well as the authority to resupply his men from the imperial arsenals.

==First invasion of Italy==
{{Campaignbox Gothic War (401-403)}}
It was probably in 401 that Alaric made his first invasion of Italy, originally with the intention to petition for a position closer to Rome. Alaric had a fascination for the 'golden age' of Rome and insisted on his tribesmen calling him 'Alaricus'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=William N. |last=Bayless |title=The Visigothic Invasion of Italy in 401 |journal=The Classical Journal |volume=72 |issue=1 |year=1976 |pages=65–67 |jstor=3296883 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Marcel |last=Brion |title=Alaric the Goth |location= |publisher=R. M. McBride &amp; Co. |year=1930 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Supernatural influences were not lacking to urge him to this great enterprise. Some lines of the Roman poet [[Claudian]] inform us that he heard a voice proceeding from a [[sacred grove]], &quot;Break off all delays, Alaric. This very year thou shalt force the Alpine barrier of Italy; thou shalt penetrate to the city.&quot; But the prophecy was not to be fulfilled at this time. After spreading desolation through northern [[Italy]] and striking terror into the citizens of Rome, Alaric was met by [[Stilicho]] at [[Pollentia]], today in [[Piedmont (Italy)|Piedmont]]. The [[Battle of Pollentia|battle]] which followed on April 6, 402 (coinciding with Easter), was a costly victory for Rome, but it effectively halted the Goths' progress.{{sfn|Hodgkin|1911|p=471}}

Stilicho's enemies later reproached him for having gained his victory by taking impious advantage of the great Christian festival. Alaric, too, was outwardly a Christian, though an [[Arianism|Arian]] rather than [[Chalcedonian Christianity|Orthodox]], though he continued to practice the pagan rituals of his ancestors as well as observing Christian ritual practices. He had trusted to the sanctity of Easter for immunity from attack.{{sfn|Hodgkin|1911|p=471}}

Alaric's wife was reportedly taken prisoner after this battle; it is not unreasonable to suppose that he and his troops were hampered by the presence of large numbers of women and children, which gave his invasion of Italy the character of a [[human migration]].{{sfn|Hodgkin|1911|p=471}}

After another [[Battle of Verona (402)|defeat]] before [[Verona, Italy|Verona]], Alaric left Italy, probably in 403. He had not &quot;penetrated to the city&quot; but his invasion of Italy had produced important results. It caused the imperial residence to be transferred from [[Milan]] to [[Ravenna]], and necessitated the withdrawal of [[Legio XX Valeria Victrix|Legio XX ''Valeria Victrix'']] from Britain.{{sfn|Hodgkin|1911|p=471}}

==Second invasion of Italy==
Alaric became the friend and ally of his erstwhile opponent, [[Stilicho]]. By 407, the estrangement between the eastern and western courts had become so bitter that it threatened civil war. Stilicho actually proposed using Alaric's troops to enforce Honorius' claim to the [[prefecture]] of Illyricum. The death of Arcadius in May 408 caused milder counsel to prevail in the western court, but Alaric, who had actually entered Epirus, demanded in a somewhat threatening manner that if he were thus suddenly requested to desist from war, he should be paid handsomely for what modern language would call the &quot;expenses of [[mobilization]]&quot;. The sum which he named was a large one, 4,000&amp;nbsp;pounds of gold. Under strong pressure from Stilicho, the Roman Senate consented to promise its payment.{{sfn|Hodgkin|1911|p=471}}

But three months later, Stilicho and the chief ministers of his party were treacherously slain on Honorius' orders. In the unrest that followed throughout Italy, the wives and children of the foederati were slain.&lt;ref name=Heather/&gt; Consequently, these 30,000 men flocked to Alaric's camp, clamouring to be led against their cowardly enemies. He accordingly led them across the Julian Alps and, in September 408, stood before the walls of [[Rome]] (now with no capable general like Stilicho as a defender) and began a strict blockade.{{sfn|Hodgkin|1911|p=471}}

No blood was shed this time; Alaric relied on hunger as his most powerful weapon. When the ambassadors of the [[Roman Senate|Senate]], entreating for peace, tried to intimidate him with hints of what the despairing citizens might accomplish, he laughed and gave his celebrated answer: &quot;The thicker the hay, the easier mowed!&quot; After much bargaining, the famine-stricken citizens agreed to pay a ransom of 5,000 pounds of gold, 30,000 pounds of silver, 4,000 silken tunics, 3,000 hides dyed scarlet, and 3,000 pounds of pepper.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nor&quot;&gt;J. Norwich, ''Byzantium: The Early Centuries'', 134&lt;/ref&gt; Along came 40,000 freed [[Goths|Gothic]] slaves. Thus ended Alaric's first siege of Rome.{{sfn|Hodgkin|1911|p=471}} The combined value of the gold and silver in pure coinage would have been worth 7000 pounds in gold or 1.028&amp;nbsp;million solidi—enough to provide the basic needs of 200,000 adults and children for a year or equip 30,000 Roman infantry and cavalry.

===Second siege of Rome===
[[File:Sack of Rome by the Visigoths on 24 August 410 by JN Sylvestre 1890.jpg|thumb|[[Sack of Rome (410)|The Sack of Rome]] by the Visigoths on 24 August 410 by [[Joseph-Noël Sylvestre|J-N Sylvestre]] (1890)]]
Throughout his career, Alaric's primary goal was not to undermine the Empire, but to secure for himself a regular and recognized position within the Empire's borders. His demands were certainly grand: the concession of a block of territory 200&amp;nbsp;miles long by 150 wide between the [[Danube]] and the Gulf of [[Venice]] (to be held probably on some terms of nominal dependence on the Empire) and the title of commander-in-chief of the Imperial Army. As outrageous as his terms were, the emperor would have been well-advised to grant them. Honorius, however, refused to see beyond his own safety, guaranteed by the dikes and marshes of [[Ravenna]]. As all attempts to conduct a satisfactory negotiation with this emperor failed, Alaric, after instituting a second siege and blockade of [[Rome]] in 409, came to terms with the Senate. With their consent, he set up a rival emperor, the prefect of the city, a Greek named [[Priscus Attalus]].{{sfn|Hodgkin|1911|p=471}}

===Third siege of Rome===
{{main|Sack of Rome (410)}}
Alaric cashiered his ineffectual puppet emperor after eleven months and again tried to reopen negotiations with Honorius. These negotiations might have succeeded had it not been for the influence of another Goth, [[Sarus (Goth)|Sarus]], an [[Amali]], and therefore hereditary enemy of Alaric and his house. Alaric, again outwitted by an enemy's machinations, marched southward, and began his third siege of Rome. Apparently, defense was impossible; there are hints, not well substantiated, of treachery; surprise is a more likely explanation. However, this may be—for our information at this point of the story is meager—on August 24, 410, Alaric and his Visigoths burst in by the [[Porta Salaria]] on the northeast of the city. Rome, for so long victorious against its enemies, was now at the mercy of its foreign conquerors.{{sfn|Hodgkin|1911|p=471}}

The contemporary [[Ecclesiology|ecclesiastics]] recorded with wonder many instances of the Visigoths' clemency: Christian churches saved from ravage; protection granted to vast multitudes both of pagans and Christians who took refuge therein; vessels of gold and silver which were found in a private dwelling, spared because they &quot;belonged to St. Peter&quot;; at least one case in which a beautiful Roman matron appealed, not in vain, to the better feelings of the Gothic soldier who attempted her dishonor. But even these exceptional instances show that Rome was not entirely spared the horrors which usually accompany the storming of a besieged city. Nonetheless, the written sources do not mention damages wrought by fire, save the [[Gardens of Sallust]], which were situated close to the gate by which the Goths had made their entrance; nor is there any reason to attribute any extensive destruction of the buildings of the city to Alaric and his followers.{{sfn|Hodgkin|1911|p=471}} The [[Basilica Aemilia]] in the [[Roman Forum]] did burn down, which perhaps can be attributed to Alaric: the archaeological evidence was provided by coins dating from 410 found melted in the floor. 

===Death and funeral===
[[Image:Death of Alaric.jpg|thumb|right|300px|The burial of Alaric in the bed of the [[Busento River]]. 1895 wood engraving.]]

Alaric, having penetrated the city, marched southwards into [[Calabria]]. He desired to invade Africa, which, thanks to its grain, had become the key to holding Italy. But a storm battered his ships into pieces and many of his soldiers drowned. Alaric died soon after in [[Cosenza]], probably of fever,&lt;ref&gt;Erik Durschmied, ''From Armageddon to the Fall of Rome'', p. 401, ch. 17, 2002, London: Coronet.&lt;/ref&gt; and his body was, according to legend, buried under the riverbed of the [[Busento]] in accordance with the pagan practices of the Visigothic people.

Scholars have often wondered about the cause of King Alaric's death. Recently, Francesco Galassi and his colleagues pored over all the historical, medical and epidemiological sources they could find about the king's death, and concluded that the underlying cause was malaria.&lt;ref&gt;The sudden death of Alaric I (c. 370–410 AD), the vanquisher of Rome: A tale of malaria and lacking immunity. Francesco M. Galassi, Raffaella Bianucci, Giacomo Gorini, Giacomo M. Paganottie, Michael E. Habicht, Frank J. Rühli. European Journal of Internal Medicine June 2016 Volume 31, Pages 84–87. https://www.ejinme.com/article/S0953-6205(16)00067-4/abstract&lt;/ref&gt;

The stream was temporarily turned aside from its course while the grave was dug, wherein the Gothic chief and some of his most precious spoils were interred. When the work was finished, the river was turned back into its usual channel and the captives by whose hands the labor had been accomplished were put to death that none might learn their secret.{{sfn|Hodgkin|1911|pp=471–472}} A similar story is told of the [[Decebalus Treasure]], [[buried treasure|buried]] under a river in 106 AD. These burials repeat [[Scythian]] models from the Lower Danube and the Black Sea.&lt;ref name=&quot;DBE&quot;&gt;[http://dbe.rah.es/biografias/5926/alarico-i Alarico I] {{in lang|es}}, ''[[Diccionario biográfico español]]'', [[Luis Agustín García Moreno]], [[Real Academia de la Historia]].&lt;/ref&gt;

Alaric was succeeded in the command of the Gothic army by his brother-in-law, [[Ataulf]],{{sfn|Hodgkin|1911|p=472}} who married Honorius' sister [[Galla Placidia]] three years later.

==Sources==
The chief authorities on the career of Alaric are: the historian [[Paulus Orosius|Orosius]] and the poet [[Claudian]], both contemporary, neither disinterested; [[Zosimus]], a historian who lived probably about half a century after Alaric's death; and [[Jordanes]], a Goth who wrote the history of his nation in 551, basing his work on [[Cassiodorus]]'s ''[[Gothic History]]''. The legend of Alaric's burial in the Buzita River comes from Jordanes.

==See also==
* [[Alaric II]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
* Henry Bradley, ''The Goths: from the Earliest Times to the End of the Gothic Dominion in Spain'', chapter 10. Second edition, 1883, New York: G.P. Putnam's Sons.
* {{EB1911|wstitle=Alaric|volume=1|pages=470–472|first=Thomas|last=Hodgkin|authorlink=Thomas Hodgkin (historian)}}
* Peter Heather, ''The Fall of the Roman Empire: A New History of Rome and the Barbarians'', Oxford University Press (2006)pg.151
* Ammianus Marcellinus, ''The Later Roman Empire: AD 354–378 Book XXXI''
* {{cite book |last=Kulikowski |first=Michael |authorlink=Michael Kulikowski |date=2006 |title=Rome's Gothic Wars: From the Third Century to Alaric |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=QXM9SH4EALgC |location= |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |page= |isbn=1139458094 |accessdate=30 November 2014}}

==External links==
{{wikisource author}}
{{Commons category|Alaric I}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070602165920/http://www.worldhistoryblog.com/2006/08/alaric-i.html Alaric I]
* Edward Gibbon, ''History of the Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire'', [https://web.archive.org/web/20040923080132/http://etext.library.adelaide.edu.au/g/g43d/chapter30.html Chapter 30] and [https://web.archive.org/web/20040914234518/http://etext.library.adelaide.edu.au/g/g43d/chapter31.html Chapter 31].
* [http://lostfort.blogspot.com/2006/04/legend-of-alarics-burial.html The Legend of Alaric's Burial]
* For a modern-day novel exploring the historical sources relating to Alaric's riverbed grave see [http://www.troubador.co.uk/book_info.asp?bookid=3194 Alaric's Gold by Robert Fortune]

{{S-start}}
{{S-hou|[[Balti dynasty]]||370||410|name=King Alaric I of the Visigoths}}
{{S-reg|}}
|-
{{S-vac|last=[[Athanaric]]}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[King of the Visigoths]]|years=395–410}}
{{S-aft|after=[[Ataulf]]}}
{{s-end}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Alaric 01}}
[[Category:410 deaths]]
[[Category:5th-century Visigothic monarchs]]
[[Category:Balt dynasty]]
[[Category:People from Tulcea County]]
[[Category:5th-century Arian Christians]]
[[Category:Greece in the Roman era]]
[[Category:Ancient Italian history]]
[[Category:Gothic warriors]]
[[Category:4th-century monarchs in Europe]]
[[Category:Year of birth unknown]]
[[Category:4th-century Gothic people]]
[[Category:390s in the Byzantine Empire]]</text>
      <sha1>gskswh3jqo3e6sig7kca4l9gwpy16wh</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
