  <page>
    <title>American Chinese cuisine</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1558</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941461301</id>
      <parentid>939754545</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-18T18:45:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2601:541:4500:1760:4C29:796A:B10F:7303</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>fix link</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">
{{American cuisine}}
{{Cuisine of China}}
{{use American English|date=February 2019}}

'''American Chinese cuisine''' is a style of [[Chinese cuisine]] developed by [[Chinese Americans]]. The dishes served in many North American [[Chinese restaurant]]s are adapted to American tastes and often differ significantly from those found in China.

==History==

[[File:Theodore Wores - Chinese Restaurant.jpg|thumb|A Chinese restaurant in San Francisco's Chinatown in 1884]]

Chinese immigrants arrived in the United States seeking employment as miners and railroad workers. As larger groups of [[Chinese emigration|Chinese immigrants]] arrived, laws were put in place preventing them from owning land. They mostly lived together in ghettos, individually referred to as &quot;[[Chinatowns in the United States|Chinatown]]&quot;. Here the immigrants started their own small businesses, including restaurants and [[Laundry#Chinese laundries in North America|laundry services]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; By the 19th century, the Chinese community in [[San Francisco]] operated sophisticated and sometimes luxurious restaurants patronized mainly by Chinese. The restaurants in smaller towns (mostly owned by Chinese immigrants) served food based on what their customers requested, anything ranging from pork chop sandwiches and apple pie, to beans and eggs. Many of these small-town restaurant owners were self-taught family cooks who improvised on different cooking methods and whatever ingredients were available.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title = The Globalization of Chinese Food|last1 = Wu|first1 = David Y. H.|last2 = Cheung|first2 = Sidney C. H.|publisher = Curzon Press|year = 2002|isbn = 978-0-8248-2582-9|location = Great Britain|page = 57}}&lt;/ref&gt; These smaller restaurants were responsible for developing American Chinese cuisine, where the food was modified to suit a more American palate. First catering to miners and railroad workers, they established new eateries in towns where Chinese food was completely unknown, adapting local ingredients and catering to their customers' tastes.&lt;ref&gt;Ch Six, &quot;The Globalization of Chinese Food: The Early Stages&quot;, in J. A. G. Roberts. ''China to Chinatown: Chinese Food in the West'' (London: Reaktion, 2002) {{ISBN|1-86189-133-4}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Even though the new flavors and dishes meant they were not strictly Chinese cuisine, these Chinese restaurants have been cultural ambassadors to Americans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Perceptions of Chinese restaurants in the U.S.: What affects customer satisfaction and behavioral intentions? |url=|journal=International Journal of Hospitality Management |date=2009-09-01 |pages=338–348 |volume=28 |issue=3 |doi=10.1016/j.ijhm.2008.10.008 |first=Yinghua |last=Liu |first2=SooCheong (Shawn) |last2=Jang}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Chinese restaurants in the United States began during the [[California Gold Rush]], which brought twenty to thirty thousand immigrants across from the [[Canton Province, China|Canton]] (Guangdong) region of China. By 1850, there were five Chinese  restaurants in San Francisco. Soon after, significant amounts of food were being imported from China to America's west coast. The trend spread steadily eastward with the growth of the American railways, particularly to [[Chinese Americans in New York City|New York City]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith2009&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Smith|first=Andrew F.|title=Eating history: 30 turning points in the making of American cuisine|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=1514y0UnSdQC&amp;pg=PA47|accessdate=22 June 2011|date=1 October 2009|publisher=Columbia University Press|isbn=978-0-231-14092-8|page=47}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Chinese Exclusion Act]] allowed merchants to enter the country, and in 1915, restaurant owners became eligible for merchant visas. This fueled the opening of Chinese restaurants as an immigration vehicle.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Godoy |first1=Maria |title=Lo Mein Loophole: How U.S. Immigration Law Fueled A Chinese Restaurant Boom |url= https://www.npr.org/sections/thesalt/2016/02/22/467113401/lo-mein-loophole-how-u-s-immigration-law-fueled-a-chinese-restaurant-boom |accessdate=23 February 2016 |work=[[NPR]] |date=23 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;  {{asof|2015}}, the United States had 46,700 Chinese restaurants.&lt;ref name=&quot;passy20150826&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url= https://www.wsj.com/articles/meet-the-pilot-who-doubles-as-block-islands-chinese-food-delivery-guy-1440636389 | title= Meet the Pilot Who Doubles as Block Island’s Chinese-Food Delivery Guy | work=The Wall Street Journal | date= 2015-08-26 | accessdate=26 August 2015 | author= Passy, Charles | pages=A1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Along the way, cooks adapted southern Chinese dishes such as [[chop suey]] and developed a style of Chinese food not found in China. Restaurants (along with Chinese laundries) provided an ethnic niche for small businesses at a time when the Chinese people were excluded from most jobs in the wage economy by ethnic discrimination or lack of language fluency.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coe Chop Suey&quot;&gt;Andrew Coe ''Chop Suey: A Cultural History of Chinese Food in the United States'' (New York: Oxford University Press, 2009).&lt;/ref&gt; By the 1920s, this cuisine, particularly chop suey, became popular among middle-class Americans. However, after World War II it began to be dismissed for not being &quot;authentic&quot;. Late 20th century tastes have been more accommodating. {{sfnb|Hayford|2011| p = 11-12}} Take-out food became popular amongst Americans, Chinese food becoming a favorite option. By this time it became evident that Chinese restaurants no longer catered mainly for Chinese customers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = China to Chinatown|url = http://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/distributed/C/bo3536662.html|website = University of Chicago Press|accessdate = 2015-12-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
There has been a consequential component of [[Chinese emigration]] of illegal origin, most notably [[Fuzhou Americans|Fuzhou people]] from [[Fujian Province]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=16356755|title=Chinese Immigrants Chase Opportunity in America|last=|first=|date=November 19, 2007|website=|publisher=NPR Morning Edition|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|accessdate=2011-07-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Wenzhounese]] from [[Zhejiang Province]] in Mainland China, specifically destined to work in Chinese restaurants in New York City, beginning in the 1980s. Adapting Chinese cooking techniques to local produce and tastes has led to the development of American Chinese cuisine. Many of the Chinese restaurant [[menu]]s in the U.S. are printed in [[Chinatown, Manhattan]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/12/nyregion/thecity/the-kings-of-sweet-and-sour.html|title=The Kings of Sweet and Sour|publisher=The New York Times|accessdate=January 2, 2020|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170928181102/https://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/12/nyregion/thecity/the-kings-of-sweet-and-sour.html?_r=1|archive-date=September 28, 2017|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; which has a strong [[Chinese Americans in New York City|Chinese American]] demographic.

In 2011, the [[Smithsonian National Museum of American History]] displayed some of the historical background and cultural artefacts of American Chinese cuisine in its exhibit entitled, ''Sweet &amp; Sour: A Look at the History of Chinese Food in the United States''.&lt;ref name=&quot;SNMAH&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Sweet &amp; Sour: A Look at the History of Chinese Food in the United States |url=http://apanews.si.edu/2011/03/04/sweet-and-sour-showcase/ |work=Smithsonian Asian Pacific American Center |publisher=Smithsonian National Museum of American History |accessdate=March 20, 2013 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130414162829/http://apanews.si.edu/2011/03/04/sweet-and-sour-showcase/ |archivedate=April 14, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Differences from other regional cuisines in China==
{{multiple issues|section=yes|
{{refimprove section|date=July 2016}}
{{Original research section|date=July 2016}}
}}
American Chinese food builds from styles and food habits brought from the southern province of [[Guangdong]], often from the [[Toisan]] district of Toisan, the origin of most Chinese immigration before the [[Immigration Act of 1924|closure of immigration from China]] in 1924. These Chinese families developed new styles and used readily available ingredients, especially in California. The type of Chinese American cooking served in restaurants was different from the foods eaten in Chinese American homes. {{sfnb|Hom|1997|}}{{sfnb|Hayford|2011| p = 11-12}} Of the various [[Chinese cuisine#Regional cuisines|regional cuisines in China]], [[Cantonese cuisine]] has been the most influential in the development of American Chinese food.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chapius&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Complete Asian Cookbook|first=Charmaine|last=Solomon|page= 281 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=Mdfacqx2UaQC&amp;pg=PA368 |isbn=9780804837576 |date=April 15, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=RParkinson&gt;{{cite news|last1=Parkinson|first1=Rhonda|title=Regional Chinese Cuisine|url=http://chinesefood.about.com/od/regionalchinesecuisine/ss/cookingstyles.htm|accessdate=July 8, 2014|publisher=About.com|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070217160414/http://chinesefood.about.com/od/regionalchinesecuisine/ss/cookingstyles.htm|archive-date=2007-02-17|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Among the common differences is to treat [[vegetable]]s as a side dish or [[garnish (food)|garnish]], while traditional cuisines of China emphasize vegetables. This can be seen in the use of [[carrot]]s and [[tomato]]es.  Cuisine in China makes frequent use of Asian [[leaf vegetable]]s like [[bok choy]] and [[kai-lan]] and puts a greater emphasis on fresh [[meat]] and [[seafood]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Oxford&quot;&gt;{{cite book   | title = The Oxford Companion to American Food and Drink | author= Andrew F. Smith |publisher = Oxford University Press | location=   |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=GZVweuXhZlkC&amp;pg=PA120&amp;dq=american+chinese+compared+to+traditional+chinese+dishes&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjo6qLYhe7LAhUD9mMKHcXwCmsQ6AEISDAI#v=onepage&amp;q=american%20chinese%20compared%20to%20traditional%20chinese%20dishes&amp;f=false | date = 2007  | pages =  119–122 | isbn = 9780199885763 | accessdate = 1 April 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Chinese buffet2.jpg|left|thumb|A [[Chinese cuisine|Chinese]] [[buffet]] restaurant in the United States]]
[[Stir frying]], [[pan frying]], and [[deep frying]] tend to be the most common [[Chinese cooking techniques]] used in American Chinese cuisine, which are all easily done using a [[wok]] (a Chinese frying pan with bowl-like features and which accommodates very high temperatures). The food also has a reputation for high levels of [[Monosodium glutamate|MSG]] to enhance the flavor. Market forces and customer demand have encouraged many restaurants to offer &quot;MSG Free&quot; or &quot;No MSG&quot; menus, or to omit this ingredient on request.&lt;ref name = &quot;Oxford&quot;/&gt;

[[File:FriedWonton.jpg|thumb|Carryout Chinese food is commonly served in a paper carton with a wire bail, known as an [[oyster pail]].]]
American Chinese cuisine makes use of ingredients not native to and very rarely used in China. One such example is the common use of Western [[broccoli]] ({{zh|t=西蘭|p=xīlán}}) instead of Chinese broccoli ([[Gai-lan]], {{zh|t=芥蘭|p=jièlán|labels=no}}) in American Chinese cuisine. Occasionally, Western broccoli is also referred to as ''{{lang|yue|{{tonesup|sai1 laan4 fa1}}}}'' in Cantonese ({{zh|t=西蘭花|labels=no}}) in order not to confuse the two styles of broccoli. Among Chinese speakers, however, it is typically understood that one is referring to the leafy vegetable unless otherwise specified.

This is also the case with the words for [[carrot]] (''luo buo'' or ''lo baak,'' or ''hong luo buo'', ''hong'' meaning &quot;red&quot;) and [[onion]] (''yang cong''). ''Lo baak'', in [[Cantonese]], can refer to several types of rod-shaped root vegetable including carrot, [[daikon]], green radish, or an umbrella term for all of them. The orange Western carrot is known in some areas of China as &quot;foreign [[radish]]&quot; (or more properly ''hung lo baak'' in Cantonese, ''hung'' meaning &quot;red&quot;). When the word for onion, ''cong'', is used, it is understood that one is referring to &quot;green onions&quot; (otherwise known to English-speakers as &quot;[[scallion]]s&quot; or &quot;spring onions&quot;). The larger, many-layered onion [[bulb]] common in the United States is called ''yang cong''. This translates as &quot;foreign onion&quot;. These names make it evident that the American broccoli, carrot, and onion are not indigenous to China, and therefore are less common in the traditional cuisines of China.

[[Yeung Chow Fried Rice|Egg fried rice]] in American Chinese cuisine is also prepared differently, with more soy sauce added for more flavor whereas the traditional egg fried rice uses less soy sauce. Some food styles, such as [[dim sum]], were also modified to fit American palates, such as added batter for fried dishes and extra soy sauce.&lt;ref name = &quot;Oxford&quot;/&gt;

[[Salad]]s containing raw or uncooked ingredients are rare in traditional Chinese cuisine, as are Japanese style [[sushi]] or [[sashimi]].  However, an increasing number of American Chinese restaurants, including some upscale establishments, have started to offer these items in response to customer demand.

[[Ming Tsai]], the owner of the Blue Ginger restaurant in [[Wellesley, Massachusetts]], and host of [[PBS]] culinary show ''[[Simply Ming]]'', said that American Chinese restaurants typically try to have food representing 3-5 regions of China at one time, have [[chop suey]], or have &quot;fried vegetables and some protein in a thick sauce&quot;, &quot;eight different sweet and sour dishes&quot;, or &quot;a whole page of 20 different chow meins or fried rice dishes&quot;. Tsai said &quot;Chinese-American cuisine is 'dumbed-down' Chinese food. It's adapted... to be blander, thicker and sweeter for the American public&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[https://cnneatocracy.wordpress.com/2011/01/19/chef-ming-tsai-wants-you-to-have-a-chinese-friend/ Chef Ming Tsai wants you to have a Chinese friend]&quot;. [[CNN]]. January 19, 2011. Retrieved on January 19, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Most American Chinese establishments cater to non-Chinese customers with menus written in English or containing pictures. If separate Chinese-language menus are available, they typically feature items such as [[liver (food)|liver]], [[chicken feet]], or other meat dishes that might deter American customers.  In [[Chinatown, Manhattan]],&lt;!-- intentional link to DAB page, discuss before changing --&gt; the restaurants were known for having a &quot;phantom&quot; menu with food preferred by ethnic Chinese, but believed to be disliked by non-Chinese Americans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=5:46 pm |url=http://newyork.grubstreet.com/2009/02/anthony_bourdain_plays_it_safe.html |title=Anthony Bourdain Plays It Safe at Hop Kee, Shuns ‘Phantom Menu’ - Grub Street New York |publisher=Newyork.grubstreet.com |date=2009-02-20 |accessdate=2018-04-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Chopsueywithrice.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Chop suey, made with garlic chicken and peapods, on [[fried rice]]]]
[[File:Fortune cookie.jpg|200px|thumb|An unopened fortune cookie]]

==Dishes==

===American Chinese restaurant menu items===
Dishes that often appear on American Chinese restaurant menus include:
* [[Almond chicken]] - chicken breaded in batter containing ground almonds, fried and served with almonds and onions.{{sfnb|Jung|2010| p = [https://books.google.com/books?id=P99LCAAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q=almond%20chicken&amp;f=false 197 etc.]}}
* [[General Tso's chicken]] – chunks of chicken that are dipped in a batter, deep-fried, and seasoned with ginger, garlic, sesame oil, scallions, and hot [[chili pepper]]s. Believed to be named after [[Qing Dynasty]] statesman and military leader [[Zuo Zongtang]], often referred to as General Tso.
* [[Sesame chicken]] – boned, marinated, battered, and deep-fried chicken which is then dressed with a translucent red or orange, sweet and mildly spicy sauce, made from soy sauce, corn starch, vinegar, chicken broth, and sugar.
* [[Chinese chicken salad]] – usually contains sliced or shredded chicken, uncooked leafy greens, crispy noodles (or fried wonton skins) and sesame dressing. Some restaurants serve the salad with [[mandarin orange]]s.
* [[Chop suey]] – connotes &quot;assorted pieces&quot; in Chinese. It is usually a mix of vegetables and meat in a brown sauce but can also be served in a white sauce.
* [[Crab rangoon]] – fried [[wonton]] skins stuffed with (usually) artificial [[crab]] meat ([[surimi]]) and [[cream cheese]].
[[File:Wonton Strips.jpg|thumb|[[Wonton strips]] are commonly served complimentary along with [[duck sauce]] and hot mustard]]
* [[Fortune cookie]] – invented in [[California]] as a Westernized version of the Japanese [[omikuji]] [[senbei]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2008/01/16/dining/16fort.html?_r=1 |work=[[The New York Times]] |title=Solving a Riddle Wrapped in a Mystery Inside a Cookie |date=January 16, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; fortune cookies have become sweetened and found their way to many American Chinese restaurants. 
* [[Royal beef]] – deep-fried sliced beef, doused in a wine sauce and often served with steamed broccoli.
* [[Pepper steak]] – consists of sliced steak, green bell peppers, tomatoes, and white or green onions stir-fried with salt, sugar, and soy sauce. [[Bean sprout]]s are a less common addition
* [[Mongolian beef]] - fried beef with scallions or white onions in a spicy and often sweet brown sauce
* [[Fried wontons]] – somewhat similar to crab rangoon, a filling, (most often pork), is wrapped in a wonton skin and deep fried.&lt;ref&gt;[http://chinesefood.about.com/od/dimsumwonton/r/friedwonton.htm Fried Wonton], ''About.com''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogchef.net/fried-wontons-recipe/ Fried Wontons Recipe], ''BlogChef.net''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thaitable.com/thai/recipe/fried-wontons Fried Wontons Recipe], ''ThaiTable.com''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chow.com/recipes/28056-fried-wontons-zha-yuntun Fried Wontons (Zhá Yúntūn)], ''Chow.com''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fromaway.com/cooking/chinese-new-year-fried-wontons Chinese New Year: Fried Wontons], ''FromAway.com''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://rasamalaysia.com/chinese-recipe-fried-wontons/ Fried Wontons Recipe], ''RasaMalaysia.com''&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Beef &amp; Broccoli]] - [[flank steak]] cut into small pieces, stir-fried with broccoli, and covered in a dark sauce made with [[soy sauce]] and [[oyster sauce]] and thickened with [[cornstarch]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=New University |url=http://www.newuniversity.org/2008/06/features/history_and_culture_chinese156/ |title=History and Culture: Chinese Food |publisher=New University |date= |accessdate=2018-04-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.canyoustayfordinner.com/2010/06/30/beef-and-broccoli/ |title=Beef and Broccoli &amp;#124; Can You Stay For Dinner? |publisher=Canyoustayfordinner.com |date= |accessdate=2018-04-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://chinese.food.com/recipe/the-best-easy-beef-and-broccoli-stir-fry-99476|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120910210447/http://chinese.food.com/recipe/the-best-easy-beef-and-broccoli-stir-fry-99476|url-status=dead|title=The Best Easy Beef And Broccoli Stir-Fry Recipe - Food.com - 99476&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;|archivedate=September 10, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[youtiao|Sweet roll]] - yeast rolls, typically fried, covered in granulated sugar or powdered sugar. Some variants are stuffed with [[cream cheese]] or icing.
* [[Sushi]] - despite being served in the Japanese and American styles, some American Chinese restaurants serve various types of sushi, usually on buffets.
* [[Wonton strips]] – commonly served complimentary along with [[duck sauce]] and hot mustard, or with soup when ordering take-out

====Other American Chinese dishes====
Authentic restaurants with Chinese-language menus may offer &quot;[[yellow-hair chicken]]&quot; ({{zh|t=黃毛雞|j=wong4 mou4 gai1|p=huángmáo jī|l=yellow-feather chicken|links=no}}), essentially a [[free range|free-range]] chicken, as opposed to typical American mass-farmed chicken. Yellow-hair chicken is valued for its flavor, but needs to be cooked properly to be tender due to its lower fat and higher muscle content. This dish usually does not appear on the English-language menu.

[[Dau Miu]] ({{zh|c=豆苗|p=dòumiáo|labels=no}}) is a Chinese vegetable that has become popular since the early 1990s, and now not only appears on English-language menus, usually as &quot;pea shoots&quot;, but is often served by upscale non-Asian restaurants as well. Originally it was only available during a few months of the year, but it is now grown in greenhouses and is available year-round.

===North American versions found in China===
[[File:Egg foo young.JPG|thumb|Egg foo young]]
[[File:Beef with broccoli.JPG|thumb|Beef with broccoli]]
* [[Cashew chicken]] – Stir fried tender chicken pieces with cashews.
* [[Chow mein]] – literally means &quot;stir-fried [[noodle]]s&quot;. Chow mein consists of fried crispy noodles with bits of meat and vegetables. It can come with chicken, pork, shrimp or beef.
* [[Egg foo young]] – a Chinese-style omelet with vegetables and meat, usually served with a brown gravy. While some restaurants in North America deep-fry the omelet, versions found in Asia are more likely to fry in the wok.
* [[Egg roll]] – while [[spring roll]]s have a thin, light beige crispy skin that flakes apart, and is filled with mushrooms, [[bamboo]], and other vegetables inside, the American-style egg roll has a thicker, chewier, dark brown bubbly skin stuffed with cabbage and usually bits of meat or seafood (such as pork or shrimp), but no egg.
* [[Fried rice]] – fried rice dishes are popular offerings in American Chinese food due to the speed and ease of preparation and their appeal to American tastes. Fried rice is generally prepared with rice cooled overnight, allowing restaurants to put leftover rice to good use (freshly cooked rice is actually less suitable for fried rice). The Chinese American version of this dish typically uses more soy sauce than the versions found in China. Fried rice is offered with different combinations of meat (pork, chicken and shrimp are the most popular) and vegetables.
* [[Ginger beef]] – ({{zh|t=生薑牛肉|p=shēngjiāng niúròu|labels=no}}) Tender beef cut in chunks, mixed with ginger and Chinese mixed vegetables.
* [[Ginger fried beef]] – ({{zh|t=乾炒牛肉絲|p=gānchǎo niúròu-sī|labels=no}}) Tender beef cut in strings, battered, deep dried, then re-fried in a wok mixed with a sweet sauce, a variation of a popular Northern Chinese dish.
* [[Hulatang]] – a Chinese traditional soup with hot spices, often called &quot;spicy soup&quot; on menus
* [[Kung Pao chicken]] – The [[Sichuan cuisine|Sichuan]] dish is spicy hot, but the versions served in North America tend to be less so if at all, and sometimes leave out the [[Sichuan pepper]] that is a fundamental part of the original dish. 
* [[Lo mein]] (&quot;stirred noodles&quot;). These noodles are frequently made with eggs and flour, making them chewier than simply using water. Thick, spaghetti shaped noodles are pan fried with vegetables (mainly bok choy and Chinese cabbage ([[Napa cabbage|napa]])) and meat. Sometimes this dish is referred to as &quot;chow mein&quot; (which literally means &quot;stir-fried noodles&quot; in Cantonese).
* [[Mei Fun]] (see [[Rice vermicelli]] dishes)
* [[Moo shu pork]] – The original version uses more typically Chinese ingredients (including [[Cloud ear fungus|wood ear]] fungi and [[daylily]] buds) and thin flour pancakes while the American version uses vegetables more familiar to Americans, and thicker pancakes. This dish is quite popular in Chinese restaurants in the United States, but not so popular in China.
* [[Orange chicken]] – chopped, battered, fried chicken with a sweet orange flavored chili sauce that is thickened and glazed. The traditional version consists of stir-fried chicken in a light, slightly sweet soy sauce that is flavored with dried orange peels.
* [[Wonton soup]] – In most American Chinese restaurants, only wonton dumplings in broth are served, while versions found in China may come with noodles. In Canton, Wonton Soup can be a full meal in itself, consisting of thin egg noodles and several pork and prawn wontons in a pork or chicken soup broth or noodle broth. Especially in takeout restaurants, wonton are often made with thicker dough skins.
* [[Beijing beef]] – In China, this dish uses ''[[gai lan]]'' (Chinese broccoli) rather than American [[broccoli]].

==Regional variations==

===New York City===
The [[New York metropolitan area]] is home to Chinese populations representing the largest Chinese population outside of Asia,&lt;ref name=&quot;NYCLargestChinesePopulation&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2015/02/23/nyregion/in-new-york-indictment-of-officer-peter-liang-divides-chinese-americans.html|title=Indictment of New York Officer Divides Chinese-Americans|author=Vivian Yee|newspaper=The New York Times|date=February 22, 2015|accessdate=February 23, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;queensbuzz&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.queensbuzz.com/flushing-neighborhood-corona-neighborhood-cms-302|title=Chinese New Year 2012 in Flushing|publisher=QueensBuzz.com|date=January 25, 2012|accessdate=February 23, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; constituting the largest metropolitan [[Asian Americans in New York City|Asian American]] group in the United States, and the largest Asian-national metropolitan [[diaspora]] in the [[Western Hemisphere]]. The [[Chinese in New York City|Chinese American]] population of the New York City metropolitan area was an estimated 893,697 as of 2017;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://factfinder.census.gov/bkmk/table/1.0/en/ACS/17_1YR/S0201/330M400US408/popgroup~016|title=SELECTED POPULATION PROFILE IN THE UNITED STATES 2017 American Community Survey 1-Year Estimates New York-Newark, NY-NJ-CT-PA CSA Chinese alone|publisher=[[United States Census Bureau]]|accessdate=January 27, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; and given the New York metropolitan area's status as the leading gateway for Chinese immigrants to the United States, greater than San Francisco and Los Angeles combined,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.dhs.gov/sites/default/files/publications/immigration-statistics/yearbook/2013/LPR/immsuptable2d.xls |title=Persons Obtaining Lawful Permanent Resident Status by Leading Core Based Statistical Areas (CBSAs) of Residence and Region and Country of Birth: Fiscal Year 2013 |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |year=2013 |website=Yearbook of Immigration Statistics: 2013 |publisher=Department of Homeland Security |accessdate=January 3, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; all popular styles of regional Chinese cuisine have commensurately become ubiquitously accessible in [[Chinese in New York City|New York City]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2008/07/30/dining/30flushing.html|title=Let the Meals Begin: Finding Beijing in Flushing|author=Julia Moskin|work=The New York Times|accessdate=November 26, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; including [[Hakka cuisine|Hakka]], [[Taiwanese cuisine|Taiwanese]], [[Shanghai cuisine|Shanghainese]], [[Hunan cuisine|Hunanese]], [[Szechuan cuisine|Szechuan]], [[Cantonese cuisine|Cantonese]], [[Fujianese cuisine|Fujianese]], [[Xinjiang cuisine|Xinjiang]], [[Zhejiang cuisine|Zhejiang]], and [[Korean Chinese cuisine]]. Even the relatively obscure [[Northeastern Chinese cuisine|Dongbei]] style of cuisine indigenous to [[Northeast China]] is now available in [[Flushing, Queens]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2010/02/10/dining/10chine.html?scp=1&amp;sq=dongbei%20cuisine&amp;st=cse|title=Northeast China Branches Out in Flushing|date=2010-02-09|accessdate=2011-05-09| work=The New York Times | first=Julia | last=Moskin}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as [[Mongolian cuisine]] and [[Uyghur cuisine]].&lt;ref name=DiverseCuisineFlushingChinatownTimesSquare&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2018/08/25/dining/food-queens-us-open.html?action=click&amp;module=Editors%20Picks&amp;pgtype=Homepage|title=A World of Food, Outside the U.S. Open Gates|author=Max Falkowitz|newspaper=The New York Times|date=August 25, 2018|accessdate=August 25, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The availability of the regional variations of Chinese cuisine originating from throughout the different [[provinces of China]] is most apparent in the city's [[Chinatowns in Queens]], particularly the [[Chinatown, Flushing|Flushing Chinatown (法拉盛華埠)]], but is also notable in the city's [[Chinatowns in Brooklyn]] and [[Chinatown, Manhattan|Manhattan]].

====Kosher preparation of Chinese food====
{{Main|Chinese cuisine in New York City Jewish culture}}
[[Kosher]] preparation of Chinese food is also widely available in New York City, given the metropolitan area's large [[Jews in New York City|Jewish]] and particularly [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox Jewish]] populations. The perception that American Jews eat at Chinese restaurants on [[Christmas|Christmas Day]] is documented in media as a common [[stereotype]] with a basis in fact.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theatlantic.com/national/archive/2014/12/why-american-jews-eat-chinese-food-on-christmas/384011/ |title=Why Do American Jews Eat Chinese Food on Christmas? — The Atlantic |publisher=Theatlantic.com |date=2014-12-23 |accessdate=2018-04-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.haaretz.com/jewish-world/jewish-world-features/1.633512 |title='Tis the season: Why do Jews eat Chinese food on Christmas? - Jewish World Features - Israel News |newspaper=Haaretz |date=2014-12-24 |accessdate=2018-04-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/isaac-zablocki/the-jewish-christmas-trad_b_6272972.html |title=Movies and Chinese Food: The Jewish Christmas Tradition &amp;#124; Isaac Zablocki |publisher=Huffingtonpost.com |date=2017-12-06 |accessdate=2018-04-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; The tradition may have arisen from the lack of other open restaurants on Christmas Day, as well as the close proximity of Jewish and Chinese immigrants to each other in New York City, and the absence of [[Milk and meat in Jewish law|dairy foods combined with meat]]. Kosher Chinese food is usually prepared in New York City, as well as in other large cities with Orthodox Jewish neighborhoods, under strict [[rabbi]]nical supervision as a prerequisite for Kosher certification.

===Los Angeles County===
Chinese populations in [[Los Angeles]] represent at least 21 of the 34 provincial-level administrative units of China, making greater Los Angeles home to a diverse population of Chinese in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.vice.com/en_us/article/8qzz5b/the-best-chinese-restaurants-in-la-according-to-chinese-people|title=The Best Chinese Restaurants in LA, According to Chinese People|first=Clarissa|last=Wei|date=April 28, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chinese American cuisine in the [[Greater Los Angeles area]] is concentrated in Chinese ethnoburbs rather than traditional Chinatowns. The oldest Chinese ethnoburb is Monterey Park, considered to be the nation's first suburban Chinatown.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1987-04-06-mn-135-story.html|title=Monterey Park : Nation's 1st Suburban Chinatown|date=April 6, 1987|website=Los Angeles Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although [[Chinatown]] in Los Angeles is still a significant commercial center for Chinese immigrants, the majority have relocated to the areas with significant Chinese immigrant populations is the [[San Gabriel Valley]], stretching from Monterey Park into the cities of Alhambra, San Gabriel, Rosemead, San Marino, South Pasadena, West Covina, Walnut, City of Industry, Diamond Bar, Arcadia, and Temple City. The Valley Boulevard corridor is the main artery of Chinese restaurants in the San Gabriel Valley. Another hub with a significant Chinese population is [[Irvine, California|Irvine]] ([[Orange County, California|Orange County]]). More than 525,000 [[Asian American]]s live in the San Gabriel Valley alone, with over 67% of them being foreign born.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.scpr.org/news/2018/02/21/80976/report-on-sgv-s-asian-americans-shows-two-thirds-a/|title=Two-thirds of San Gabriel Valley's Asian-Americans are immigrants|first=Southern California Public|last=Radio|date=February 21, 2018|website=Southern California Public Radio}}&lt;/ref&gt; The valley has become a brand-name tourist destination famous in China.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.latimes.com/local/lanow/la-xpm-2014-feb-13-la-me-ln-san-gabriel-chinese-tourists-20140212-story.html|title=San Gabriel becomes brand-name destination for Chinese tourists|date=February 13, 2014|website=Los Angeles Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of the ten cities in the United States with the highest proportions of Chinese Americans, the top eight are located in the San Gabriel Valley, making it one the largest concentrated hubs for Chinese-Americans in North America.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://imdiversity.com/villages/asian/history-of-asians-in-the-san-gabriel-valley/|title=History of Asians in the San Gabriel Valley – IMDiversity|website=imdiversity.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some regional styles of Chinese cuisine include [[Beijing]], [[Chengdu]], [[Chonqing]], [[Dalian]], [[Hangzhou]], [[Hong Kong]], [[Hunan]], [[Mongolia]]n hot pot, [[Nanjing]], [[Shanghai]], [[Shanxi]], [[Shenyang]], [[Wuxi]], [[Xinjiang]], [[Yunnan]], and [[Wuhan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.latimes.com/food/la-xpm-2013-feb-15-la-dd-jonathan-gold-best-chinese-restaurants-in-los-angeles-20130215-story.html|title=Jonathan Gold's best Chinese restaurants in L.A., by regional cuisine|date=February 15, 2013|website=Los Angeles Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===San Francisco Bay Area===
Since the early 1990s, many American Chinese restaurants influenced by [[California cuisine]] have opened in the San Francisco Bay Area. The trademark dishes of American Chinese cuisine remain on the menu, but there is more emphasis on fresh vegetables, and the selection is vegetarian-friendly. This new cuisine has exotic ingredients like [[mango]]s and [[portobello mushroom]]s. [[Brown rice]] is often offered as an alternative to [[white rice]]. Some restaurants substitute grilled wheat flour [[tortilla]]s for the rice pancakes in [[mu shu]] dishes. This occurs even in some restaurants that would not otherwise be identified as California Chinese, both the more Westernized places and the more authentic places. There is a [[Mexico|Mexican]] bakery that sells some restaurants thinner tortillas made for use with mu shu. Mu shu purists do not always react positively to this trend.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |title=Mu Shu Tortilla Flats: Chinese restaurant needs better mu shu wraps |date= February 27, 2004 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071007080309/http://news.asianweek.com/news/view_article.html?article_id=5b6c82e1ca42c0c4a952c682acd5b192 |archivedate=October 7, 2007 |work=AsianWeek |quote=Everything was well and good with one huge exception: The mu shu wrappers were flour tortillas!|url=http://news.asianweek.com/news/view_article.html?article_id=5b6c82e1ca42c0c4a952c682acd5b192 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition, many restaurants serving more native-style Chinese cuisines exist, due to the high numbers and proportion of ethnic Chinese in the San Francisco Bay Area. Restaurants specializing in Cantonese, Sichuanese, Hunanese, Northern Chinese, Shanghainese, Taiwanese, and Hong Kong traditions are widely available, as are more specialized restaurants such as seafood restaurants, [[Hong Kong-style Western cuisine|Hong Kong-style diners and cafes]], also known as ''[[Cha chaan teng]]'' ({{zh|t=茶餐廳|p=chácāntīng|labels=no}}), [[dim sum]] teahouses, and [[hot pot]] restaurants. Many Chinatown areas also feature [[Chinese bakery products|Chinese bakeries]], [[boba milk tea]] shops, [[siu mei|roasted meat]], [[Chinese Buddhist cuisine|vegetarian cuisine]], and specialized dessert shops. [[Chop suey]] is not widely available in [[San Francisco]], and the area's chow mein is different from [[Midwestern United States|Midwestern]] chow mein.

===Boston===
Chinese cuisine in [[Boston]] reflects a [[mélange]] of multiple influential factors. The growing [[Chinatown, Boston|Boston Chinatown]] accommodates [[Chinatown bus lines|Chinese-owned bus lines]] shuttling an increasing number of passengers to and from the numerous [[Chinese Americans in New York City|Chinatowns in New York City]], and this has led to some commonalities in the local Chinese cuisine derived from Chinese food in New York. A large immigrant [[Fujianese people|Fujianese]] immigrant population has made a home in Boston, leading to [[Fuzhou cuisine]] being readily available in Boston. An increasing [[Vietnamese people|Vietnamese]] population has also been exerting an influence on Chinese cuisine in [[Greater Boston]]. Finally, innovative dishes incorporating chow mein and chop suey as well as [[farm-to-table|locally farmed]] produce and regionally procured [[seafood]] ingredients are found in Chinese as well as non-Chinese food in and around Boston.

[[Joyce Chen (chef)|Joyce Chen]] introduced northern Chinese (Mandarin) and Shanghainese dishes to Boston in the 1950s, including [[Peking duck]], [[moo shu pork]], [[hot and sour soup]], and [[potstickers]], which she called &quot;Peking Ravioli&quot; or &quot;Ravs&quot;.&lt;ref name=Mennies&gt;{{cite web|last1=Mennies|first1=Leah|title=The Story of Peking Ravioli|url=http://luckypeach.com/the-story-of-peking-ravioli|website=Lucky Peach|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150317230442/http://luckypeach.com/the-story-of-peking-ravioli/|archive-date=March 17, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her restaurants would be frequented by early workers on the [[ARPANET]],&lt;ref&gt;[[Katie Hafner|Hafner, K.]], &amp; Lyon, M. (1996). ''Where wizards stay up late: The origins of the Internet.'' New York: Simon and Schuster, p. 112.&lt;/ref&gt; [[John Kenneth Galbraith]], [[James Beard]], [[Julia Child]], [[Henry Kissinger]], [[Beverly Sills]], and [[Danny Kaye]].&lt;ref name=NYT-Obit&gt;{{cite news|title=Joyce Chen, 76, U.S. Popularizer Of Mandarin Cuisine|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1994/08/26/obituaries/joyce-chen-76-us-popularizer-of-mandarin-cuisine.html|accessdate=April 12, 2019|newspaper=New York Times|date=August 26, 1994|agency=Associated Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; A former [[Harvard University]] president called her eating establishment &quot;not merely a restaurant, but a cultural exchange center&quot;.&lt;ref name=Robertson&gt;{{cite web|last=Robertson|first=Rain|title=Joyce Chen|url=http://cambridgehistory.org/discover/culinary/joycechen.html|work=Culinary Cambridge|publisher=Cambridge Historical Society|accessdate=12 June 2013|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150410033814/http://cambridgehistory.org/discover/culinary/joycechen.html|archivedate=April 10, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Philadelphia===
The evolving American Chinese scene in [[Philadelphia]] exhibits commonalities with the Chinese cuisine scenes in both New York City and Boston. Similarly to Boston, Philadelphia is experiencing significant [[Chinese emigration|Chinese immigration]] from [[Chinese in New York City|New York City]], 95 miles to the north,&lt;ref name=ChineseNYCtoPhiladelphia&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2018/07/20/nyregion/philadelphia-new-york-migration-immigrants.html|title=Leaving New York to Find the American Dream in Philadelphia|author=Matt Katz|newspaper=The New York Times|date=July 20, 2018|accessdate=April 18, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; and from China, the top country of birth by a significant margin sending immigrants to Philadelphia.&lt;ref name=PhiladelphiaChineseForeignBorn&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.philly.com/news/immigrants-philly-population-growth-foreign-born-20190510.html|title=Welcome to Philly: Percentage of foreign-born city residents has doubled since 1990|author=Jeff Gammage|newspaper=The Philadelphia Inquirer|date=May 10, 2019|accessdate=May 10, 2019|quote=China is, far and away, the primary sending country, with 22,140 city residents who make up about 11 percent of the foreign-born population, according to a Pew Charitable Trusts analysis of Census data. Next is the Dominican Republic with 13,792, followed by Jamaica, 13,500; India, 11,382; and Vietnam, 10,132...About 230,000 Philadelphians are foreign-born. More than a quarter of residents are immigrants or have a foreign-born parent, Pew reported, and 23 percent speak a foreign language at home.}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is a growing Fujianese community in Philadelphia as well, and Fuzhou cuisine is readily available in the [[Chinatown, Philadelphia|Philadelphia Chinatown]]. Also like Boston, the emerging [[Vietnamese cuisine]] scene in Philadelphia is contributing to the milieu of Chinese cuisine.

===Hawaii===
Hawaiian-Chinese food developed somewhat differently from Chinese cuisine in the [[continental United States]]. Owing to the diversity of [[Pacific Ocean|Pacific]] ethnicities in Hawaii and the history of the [[Chinese immigration to Hawaii|Chinese influence in Hawaii]], resident Chinese cuisine forms a component of the [[cuisine of Hawaii]], which is a [[fusion cuisine|fusion]] of different culinary traditions. Some Chinese dishes are typically served as part of [[plate lunch]]es in Hawaii. The names of foods are different as well, such as ''[[Manapua]]'', from the Hawaiian contraction of &quot;Mea ono pua'a&quot; or &quot;delicious [[pork]] item&quot; from the dim sum ''bao'', though the meat is not necessarily pork.

===Other regional American Chinese dishes===
* [[Chow mein sandwich]] – sandwich of chow mein and gravy ([[Southeastern Massachusetts]]; [[Rhode Island]])
* [[Chop suey sandwich]] – sandwich of chicken chop suey on a hamburger bun ([[North Shore (Massachusetts)|North Shore]] of [[Massachusetts]])
* [[St. Paul sandwich]] – [[egg foo young]] patty in plain white [[sandwich bread]] ([[St. Louis, Missouri]])
* [[Springfield-style cashew chicken]] – a style of cashew chicken that combines breaded deep [[fried chicken]], cashews, and oyster sauce ([[Springfield, Missouri]])
* [[War/wor sue gai]] – [[Almond boneless chicken]] – bite-sized Southern-style fried chicken with yellow sauce [[Columbus, Ohio]] 
* [[Yaka mein]] – Chinese-Creole food found in [[New Orleans]] that evolved from [[beef noodle soup]]

==American Chinese chain restaurants==
[[File:Typical Panda Meal.jpg|thumb|A typical [[Panda Express]] meal: Kung Pao chicken, orange chicken, chow mein and steamed vegetables]]

* [[China Coast]] – Closed in 1995; owned by [[General Mills]] Corporation, formerly 52 locations throughout the United States
* [[Chinese Gourmet Express]] – throughout the United States
* [[Leeann Chin]] – Minnesota and North Dakota; owned at one time by General Mills Corp.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.pri.org/stories/2016-05-16/how-chinese-restaurant-americas-midwest-won-sean-connerys-heart|title=How a Chinese restaurant in America's Midwest won Sean Connery's heart|work=Public Radio International|access-date=2017-06-05|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Manchu Wok]] – Throughout the United States and Canada, as well as Guam, Korea and Japan
* [[Panda Express]] – Throughout the United States, with some locations in Mexico&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pandarg.com/About/ |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2013-04-21 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130518210601/http://www.pandarg.com/About/ |archivedate=2013-05-18 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Pei Wei Asian Diner]] – Throughout the United States; a subsidiary of P.F. Chang's
* [[P. F. Chang's China Bistro]] – Throughout the United States; featuring California-Chinese fusion cuisine
* [[Pick Up Stix]] – California, Arizona, and Nevada
* The Great Wall – Delaware, New Jersey, Maryland, Virginia, New York, West Virginia, South Carolina, Louisiana, Kansas
* [[Stir Crazy (restaurant)|Stir Crazy]] - Illinois, Missouri, Wisconsin, Minnesota, New York, Florida, Indiana, Texas, and Ohio

==Popular culture==
Many American films (for example:''[[The Godfather]]''; ''[[Ghostbusters]]''; ''[[Crossing Delancey]]''; ''[[Paid in Full (2002 film)|Paid in Full]]''; ''[[Inside Out (2015 film)|Inside Out]]'') involve scenes where Chinese take-out food is eaten from [[oyster pail]]s, a &quot;consistent choice of cuisine in all these cases, however, might just be an indicator of its popularity&quot;. A running gag in ''[[Dallas (1978 TV series)|Dallas]]'' is [[Cliff Barnes]]' fondness for inexpensive Chinese take-out food, as opposed to nemesis [[J. R. Ewing]] frequenting fine restaurants.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.thehindu.com/todays-paper/tp-miscellaneous/tp-others/an-american-story/article22640790.ece|title=AN AMERICAN STORY|first=Sucheta|last=Chakraborty|date=February 3, 2018|via=www.thehindu.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Among the numerous American television series and films that feature Chinese restaurants as a setting include ''[[Seinfeld]]'' (particularly the episode ''[[The Chinese Restaurant]]''), ''[[Year of the Dragon (film)|Year of the Dragon]]'', ''[[Lethal Weapon 4]]'', ''[[Mickey Blue Eyes]]'', ''[[Rush Hour 2]]'', and ''[[Men in Black 3]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;scoutingny.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.scoutingny.com/why-everyone-films-at-the-same-new-york-chinese-restaurant/|title=Why Everyone Films At The Same Damn New York Chinese Restaurant - Scouting NY|website=www.scoutingny.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;thespruceeats.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.thespruceeats.com/top-movies-featuring-chinese-food-694794|title=10 Binge-Worthy Movies to Watch With Chinese Take-Out|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In most cases it is not an actual restaurant but a [[Set construction|movie set]] that typifies the stereotypical American Chinese eatery, featuring &quot;paper lanterns and intricate woodwork&quot;, with &quot;numerous fish tanks and detailed [red] wallpaper [with gold designs]&quot; and &quot;golden dragons&quot;, plus &quot;[[Siu mei|hanging ducks]] in the window&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;scoutingny.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;thespruceeats.com&quot;/&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Food|United States}}
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [[Canadian Chinese cuisine]]
* [[Chinese bakery products]]
* [[Chinese cuisine]]
* [[Cuisine of the United States|American cuisine]]
* [[Fortune Cookie]]
* [[List of Chinese restaurants]]
* [[Oyster pail]]
{{div col end}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|30em}}

==References and further reading==

===Studies===
* {{cite book |last = Chen |first = Yong |year = 2014 |title = Chop Suey, USA: The Story of Chinese Food in America |publisher = Columbia University Press |location = New York |isbn = 9780231168922 |ref =  |url-access = registration |url = https://archive.org/details/chopsueyusastory0000chen }}
* {{cite book |last = Coe |first =  Andrew | year = 2009 |title = Chop Suey: A Cultural History of Chinese Food in the United States |publisher = Oxford University Press| location = New York |isbn = 9780195331073 |ref = }}
* {{cite journal |last=Hayford |first=Charles |title=Who's Afraid of Chop Suey? |journal=Education About Asia |volume=16 |issue=3 |pages=7–12 |date=2011 |url=http://www.asian-studies.org/eaa/Hayford_16-3.pdf |ref=harv |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120617022910/http://asian-studies.org/eaa/Hayford_16-3.pdf |archivedate=2012-06-17 }} Free download: 
* {{cite book |last = Jung|first =  John|year = 2010 |title = Sweet and Sour: Life in Chinese Family Restaurants |publisher = Yin and Yang Press| location = Cypress, CA |isbn = 9780615345451|ref = harv}}
* {{cite book |last = Lee, Jennifer 8.  |first =  |year = 2008 |title = The Fortune Cookie Chronicles: Adventures in the World of Chinese Food |publisher = Twelve| location = New York |isbn = 9780446580076|ref = }}
* {{cite book |last = Roberts, J. A. G. |first =  |year = 2002 |title = China to Chinatown: Chinese Food in the West |publisher = Reaktion |location = London |isbn = 1861891334 |ref =  |url = https://archive.org/details/chinatochinatown00robe }}
* {{cite book |last1 = Wu|first1 =David Y. H. |first2 = Sidney C. H. |last2 = Cheung  |year = 2002 |title = The Globalization of Chinese Food |publisher = Curzon| location = Richmond, Surrey |isbn = 0700714030|ref = }}

===Cookbooks===
* Sara Bosse, [[Winnifred Eaton (writer)|Onoto Watanna]], with an Introduction by [[Jacqueline M. Newman]]. ''Chinese-Japanese Cook Book.'' (1914; reprinted, Bedford, MA: Applewood Books,  2006).  {{ISBN|1-55709-371-7}}. {{ISBN|978-1-55709-371-4}}.
* {{cite book |last = Hom |first = Ken |year = 1997 |title = Easy Family Recipes from a Chinese American Childhood |publisher = Knopf |location = New York |isbn = 0-394-58758-8 |ref = harv |url = https://archive.org/details/easyfamilyrecipe00homk }}
* Eileen Yin-Fei Lo and Alexandra Grablewski. ''The Chinese Kitchen: Recipes, Techniques and Ingredients, History, and Memories from America's Leading Authority on Chinese Cooking.'' (New York: William Morrow, 1999).  {{ISBN|0-688-15826-9}}.

==External links==
{{Commons category|American Chinese cuisine}}
* &quot;Chinese food in America History&quot; (The Food Timeline) [http://www.foodtimeline.org/restaurants.html#chineserestaurants The Food Timeline: history notes--restaurants, chefs &amp; foodservice]
* [https://viuspace.viu.ca/handle/10613/2699 Imogen Lim Restaurant Menu Collection: American menus]. Vancouver Island University Library.

{{Chinese American|state=collapsed}}
{{Cuisine of the United States|state=collapsed}}
{{cuisine|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Chinese-American history|Cuisine]]
[[Category:American Chinese cuisine| ]]
[[Category:Chinese-American culture|Cuisine]]
[[Category:Chinese cuisine]]
[[Category:Hawaiian cuisine]]
[[Category:American cuisine|Chinese]]</text>
      <sha1>8hdl94q376l6xpksywwdo1fpurryygg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
