  <page>
    <title>Albertus Magnus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1573</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941874177</id>
      <parentid>941624291</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-21T04:57:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Freddiem</username>
        <id>1575274</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>updated link</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Dominican friar}}
{{Redirect|Albertus|others with the same given name|Albertus (given name)|the typeface|Albertus (typeface)}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=September 2019}}
{{Infobox scientist
| image           = AlbertusMagnus.jpg
| caption         = ''Saint Albertus Magnus'', &lt;small&gt;a fresco by [[Tommaso da Modena]] (1352), Church of San Nicolò, [[Treviso]], [[Italy]]&lt;/small&gt; 
| birth_date      = before 1200
| birth_place     = [[Lauingen]], [[Duchy of Bavaria]]
| death_date      = November 15, 1280 (aged over 80)
| death_place     = [[Cologne]], [[Holy Roman Empire]]
| nationality       = [[Germans|German]]
| doctoral_students = 
| other_names      = ''Albertus Teutonicus'', ''Albertus Coloniensis'', Albert the Great, Albert of Cologne
| fields            = {{Flatlist}}
*[[Natural science]]
*[[Alchemy]]
*[[Jurisprudence]]
*[[Diplomacy]]
*[[Theology]]
*[[Natural philosophy]]
{{Endflatlist}}
| known_for         = Systematic study of [[minerals]]&lt;br /&gt;discovery of the element [[arsenic]]
| module           = {{Infobox philosopher
| embed             = yes
| region           = [[Western philosophy]]
| era              = [[Medieval philosophy]]
| name             = Albertus Magnus
| alma_mater       = [[University of Padua]]
| institutions      = [[University of Paris]]
| school_tradition = 
{{Flatlist}}
*[[Scholasticism]]
*[[Aristotelianism]]
*[[Medieval realism]]&lt;ref&gt;Hilde de Ridder-Symoens (ed.). ''A History of the University in Europe: Volume 1, Universities in the Middle Ages'', Cambridge University Press, 1991, p. 439.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Endflatlist}}
| main_interests   = {{Flatlist}}
*[[Philosophy]]
*[[Physiology]]
*[[Mineralogy]]
*[[Astrology]]
*[[Geography]]
*[[Astronomy]]
*[[Physiology]]
*[[Music theory]]
{{Endflatlist}}
| notable_students = [[Thomas Aquinas]]
| notable_ideas    = 
{{Flatlist}}
*[[Natural law]]
*[[Aevum]]&lt;ref&gt;Albertus Magnus, ''De IV coaequaevis'', tract. 2, qu. 3.&lt;/ref&gt;  
{{Endflatlist}}
| influences       = [[Plato]],&lt;ref&gt;Henricus Bate, Helmut Boese, Carlos Steel, On Platonic Philosophy, Leuven: Leuven University Press, 1990, p. xvi.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Aristotle]], [[Avicenna]], [[Plotinus]], [[Proclus|Proclian]], [[Pseudo-Dionysius]], [[Al-Farabi]], [[Averroes]], [[Avicebron]], [[Maimonides]], [[Jordan of Saxony]]&lt;ref&gt;Irven Resnick (ed.), ''A Companion to Albert the Great: Theology, Philosophy, and the Sciences'', BRILL, 2012, p. 4; Thomas F. Glick, Steven Livesey, Faith Wallis (eds.), ''Medieval Science, Technology, and Medicine: An Encyclopedia'', Routledge, 2014, p. 15; [[Pope Benedict XVI]], ''Great Christian Thinkers: From the Early Church Through the Middle Ages'', Fortress Press, 2011, p. 281.&lt;/ref&gt;
| influenced       = [[Thomas Aquinas]] and later [[Scholasticism]] in general; indirectly [[Meister Eckhart]], [[Nicholas of Cusa]]
| module             = {{Infobox clergy 
|child=yes
| ordained         = {{circa}}. 1245 &lt;ref&gt;[https://romantic-circles.org/editions/frankenstein/V1notes/albertus ALBERTUS MAGNUS]&lt;/ref&gt;
| offices_held     = [[Bishop of Regensburg]]
 | religion         = [[Christianity]]
| church           = [[Catholic Church]]
}}}}}}
{{Infobox saint
| name            = [[Saint]]&lt;br /&gt; Albertus Magnus, [[Dominican Order|OP]]
| image           = Alchemia02.jpg
| caption         = 
| titles          = [[religious order|Religious]], [[Bishop in the Catholic Church|Bishop]], and [[Doctor of the Church]]
| feast_day       = November 15
| venerated_in    = [[Roman Catholic Church]]
| beatified_date  = 1622
| beatified_place = [[Rome]], [[Papal States]],
| beatified_by    = [[Pope Gregory XV]]
| canonized_date  = 1931
| canonized_place = [[Vatican City]],
| canonized_by    = [[Pope Pius XI]]
| major_shrine    = [[St. Andrew's Church, Cologne]], Germany
| attributes      = 
| patronage       = medical technologists/technicians; natural sciences; philosophers; scientists; students; City of Cincinnati (Ohio)
}}
{{Catholic philosophy}}

'''Albertus Magnus'''&lt;ref&gt;{{lang-la|Albertus Teutonicus, Albertus Coloniensis}}.&lt;/ref&gt; (before 1200 – November 15, 1280), also known as '''Saint Albert the Great''' and '''Albert of Cologne''', was a [[Germans|German]] [[Catholic]] [[Dominican Order|Dominican]] [[friar]] and [[Bishop in the Catholic Church|bishop]]. Later [[Canonization|canonised]] as a [[Catholic saint]], he was known during his lifetime as ''Doctor universalis'' and ''Doctor expertus'' and, late in his life, the [[sobriquet]] ''[[List of people known as &quot;the Great&quot;|Magnus]]'' was appended to his name.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |editor-last=Weisheipl |editor-first=James A. |last=Weisheipl |first=James A. |title=Albertus Magnus and the Sciences: Commemorative Essays |place=Toronto |publisher=Pontifical Institute of Mediaeval Studies |series=Studies and texts |volume=49 |year=1980 |chapter=The Life and Works of St. Albert the Great |page=46 |isbn=978-0-88844-049-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Scholars such as James A. Weisheipl and Joachim R. Söder have referred to him as the greatest German philosopher and theologian of the [[Middle Ages]].&lt;ref&gt;Joachim R. Söder, &quot;Albert der Grosse – ein staunen- erregendes Wunder,&quot; Wort und Antwort 41 (2000): 145; J.A. Weisheipl, &quot;Albertus Magnus,&quot; Joseph Strayer ed., Dictionary of the Middle Ages 1 (New York: Scribner, 1982) 129.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Catholic Church]] distinguishes him as one of the 36 [[Doctor of the Church|Doctors of the Church]].

==Biography==
It seems likely that Albert was born sometime before 1200, given well-attested evidence that he was aged over 80 on his death in 1280. Two later sources say that Albert was about 87 on his death, which has led 1193 to be commonly given as the date of Albert's birth, but this information has not enough evidence.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; Albert was probably born in Lauingen (now in [[Duchy of Bavaria|Bavaria]]), since he called himself 'Albert of Lauingen', but this might simply be a family name. Most probably his family was of ''ministerial'' class; his familiar connection with (being son of the count) the Bollstädt noble family is almost certainly mere conjecture by 15th c. [[Hagiography|hagiographers]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;Tugwell, Simon. ''Albert and Thomas,'' New York Paulist Press, 1988, p. 3, 96–7&lt;/ref&gt;{{failed verification|date=June 2016}}

Albert was probably educated principally at the [[University of Padua]], where he received instruction in [[Aristotle]]'s writings. A late account by Rudolph de Novamagia refers to Albertus' encounter with the [[Blessed Virgin Mary]], who convinced him to enter [[Holy Orders]]. In 1223 (or 1229){{sfn|Tugwell|1988|pp=4–5}} he became a member of the [[Dominican Order]], and studied [[theology]] at [[Bologna]] and elsewhere. Selected to fill the position of lecturer at Cologne, Germany, where the Dominicans had a house, he taught for several years there, as well as in [[Regensburg]], [[Freiburg]], [[Strasbourg]], and [[Hildesheim]]. During his first tenure as lecturer at Cologne, Albert wrote his ''Summa de bono'' after discussion with [[Philip the Chancellor]] concerning the transcendental properties of being.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kovach, Francs 1980, p.X&quot;&gt;Kovach, Francs, and Rober Shahan. Albert the Great: Commemorative Essays . Norman, Oklahoma: University of Oklahoma Press, 1980, p.X&lt;/ref&gt; In 1245, Albert became [[master of theology]] under Gueric of Saint-Quentin, the first German Dominican to achieve this distinction. Following this turn of events, Albert was able to teach theology at the [[University of Paris]] as a full-time professor, holding the seat of the Chair of Theology at the College of St. James.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kovach, Francs 1980, p.X&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hampden, ''The Life'', p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt; During this time [[Thomas Aquinas]] began to study under Albertus.&lt;ref name=Kennedy&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/01264a.htm Kennedy, Daniel. &quot;St. Albertus Magnus.&quot; The Catholic Encyclopedia. Vol. 1. New York: Robert Appleton Company, 1907. 10 Sept. 2014]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Vincenzo onofri, sant'alberto magno, 1493.JPG|thumb|left|Bust of Albertus Magnus by [[Vincenzo Onofri]], c. 1493]]

Albert was the first to comment on virtually all of the writings of [[Aristotle]], thus making them accessible to wider academic debate. The study of Aristotle brought him to study and comment on the teachings of Muslim academics, notably [[Avicenna]] and [[Averroes]], and this would bring him into the heart of academic debate.

In 1254 Albert was made [[provincial superior|provincial]] of the Dominican Order,&lt;ref name=Kennedy /&gt; and fulfilled the duties of the office with great care and efficiency. During his tenure he publicly defended the Dominicans against attacks by the secular and regular faculty of the University of Paris, commented on [[John the Evangelist]], and answered what he perceived as errors of the [[Early Islamic philosophy|Islamic philosopher]] Averroes.

In 1259 Albert took part in the General Chapter of the Dominicans at [[Valenciennes]] together with Thomas Aquinas, masters Bonushomo Britto,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Histoire littéraire de la France: XIIIe siècle |volume=19 |page=103 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=LIYNAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA103&amp;lpg=PA103&amp;dq=bonushomo#v=onepage&amp;q=bonushomo&amp;f=false |accessdate=October 27, 2012|last1=Grange |first1=Antoine Rivet de la |last2=Clément |first2=François |last3=(Dom) |first3=Charles Clémencet |last4=Daunou |first4=Pierre Claude François |last5=Clerc |first5=Joseph Victor Le |last6=Hauréau |first6=Barthélemy |last7=Meyer |first7=Paul |year=1838 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Florentius,&lt;ref&gt;Probably Florentius de Hidinio, a.k.a. Florentius Gallicus, [https://books.google.com/books?id=LIYNAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA103#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false ''Histoire littéraire de la France: XIIIe siècle''], Volume 19, p. 104, Accessed October 27, 2012&lt;/ref&gt; and Peter (later [[Pope Innocent V]]) establishing a ''ratio studiorum'' or program of studies for the Dominicans&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=pf4hAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA701#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false ''Encyclopaedia of Religion and Ethics''], Volume 10, p. 701. Accessed 9 June 2011&lt;/ref&gt; that featured the study of philosophy as an innovation for those not sufficiently trained to study theology. This innovation initiated the tradition of Dominican scholastic philosophy put into practice, for example, in 1265 at the Order's ''[[studium provinciale]]'' at the convent of [[Santa Sabina]] in Rome, out of which would develop the [[Pontifical University of Saint Thomas Aquinas]], the &quot;Angelicum&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.domcentral.org/study/opstudy.htm Weisheipl O.P., J. A., &quot;The Place of Study In the Ideal of St. Dominic&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101229185458/http://www.domcentral.org/study/opstudy.htm |date=2010-12-29 }}, 1960.  Accessed 19 March 2013&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:2004 Köln Sarkophag Albertus Magnus.JPG|thumb|Roman [[sarcophagus]] containing the relics of Albertus Magnus in the crypt of [[St. Andrew's Church, Cologne]], Germany]]

In 1260 [[Pope Alexander IV]] made him [[bishop of Regensburg]], an office from which he resigned after three years. During the exercise of his duties he enhanced his reputation for humility by refusing to ride a horse, in accord with the dictates of the Order, instead traversing his huge diocese on foot. This earned him the affectionate sobriquet &quot;boots the bishop&quot; from his parishioners. In 1263 [[Pope Urban IV]] relieved him of the duties of bishop and asked him to preach the [[eighth Crusade]] in German-speaking countries.&lt;ref name=Markus&gt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/archives/win2014/entries/albert-great/ Führer, Markus, &quot;Albert the Great&quot;, The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy (Winter 2014 Edition), Edward N. Zalta (ed.),]&lt;/ref&gt;  After this, he was especially known for acting as a mediator between conflicting parties. In Cologne he is not only known for being the founder of Germany's oldest university there, but also for &quot;the big verdict&quot; (der Große Schied) of 1258, which brought an end to the conflict between the citizens of Cologne and the archbishop. Among the last of his labors was the defense of the orthodoxy of his former pupil, Thomas Aquinas, whose death in 1274 grieved Albert (the story that he travelled to Paris in person to defend the teachings of Aquinas can not be confirmed).

Albert was a scientist, philosopher, astrologer, theologian, spiritual writer, ecumenist, and diplomat. Under the auspices of Humbert of Romans, Albert molded the curriculum of studies for all Dominican students, introduced Aristotle to the classroom and probed the work of [[Neoplatonists]], such as [[Plotinus]]. Indeed, it was the thirty years of work done by Aquinas and himself that allowed for the inclusion of Aristotelian study in the curriculum of Dominican schools.

After suffering a collapse of health in 1278, he died on November 15, 1280, in the Dominican convent in Cologne, [[Germany]]. Since November 15, 1954, his relics are in a Roman sarcophagus in the [[crypt]] of the Dominican St. [[Andreas]] Church in Cologne.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://gemeinden.erzbistum-koeln.de/st_andreas_koeln/albertusMagnus/ |title=Zeittafel |publisher=Gemeinden.erzbistum-koeln.de |date= |accessdate=2013-08-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although his body was discovered to be [[Incorruptibility|incorrupt]] at the first exhumation three years after his death, at the exhumation in 1483 only a skeleton remained.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cruz 1977&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Incorruptibles: A Study of the Incorruption of the Bodies of Various Catholic Saints and Beati |last=Carroll Cruz |first=Joan |publisher=TAN Books |location=[[Charlotte, NC]] |year=1977 |isbn=978-0-89555-066-8 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/incorruptiblesst00cruz }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Albert was [[beatified]] in 1622. He was [[canonized]] and proclaimed a Doctor of the Church on December 16, 1931, by [[Pope Pius XI]]&lt;ref name=Markus /&gt; and the patron saint of natural scientists in 1941. St. Albert's [[feast day]] is November 15.

==Writings==
[[File:Albertus Magnus-Denkmal.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Albertus Magnus monument at the [[University of Cologne]]]]

Albert's writings collected in 1899 went to thirty-eight volumes. These displayed his prolific habits and encyclopedic knowledge of topics such as [[logic]], [[theology]], [[botany]], [[geography]], [[astronomy]], [[astrology]], [[mineralogy]], [[alchemy]], [[zoology]], [[physiology]], [[phrenology]], [[justice]], [[law]], [[friendship]], and [[love]]. He digested, interpreted, and systematized the whole of Aristotle's works, gleaned from the Latin translations and notes of the Arabian commentators, in accordance with Church doctrine. Most modern knowledge of Aristotle was preserved and presented by Albert.&lt;ref name=Kennedy /&gt;

His principal theological works are a commentary in three volumes on the Books of the Sentences of [[Peter Lombard]] (''Magister Sententiarum''), and the ''[[Summa Theologiae]]'' in two volumes. The latter is in substance a more didactic repetition of the former.

Albert's activity, however, was more philosophical than theological (see [[Scholasticism]]). The philosophical works, occupying the first six and the last of the 21 volumes, are generally divided according to the [[Aristotelianism|Aristotelian]] scheme of the sciences, and consist of interpretations and condensations of Aristotle's relative works, with supplementary discussions upon contemporary topics, and occasional divergences from the opinions of the master. Albert believed that Aristotle's approach to natural philosophy did not pose any obstacle to the development of a Christian philosophical view of the natural order.&lt;ref name=Markus /&gt;

[[File:Firenze, alberto magno, de animalibus, 1450-1500 ca. cod fiesolano 67, 01.JPG|thumb|250px|''De animalibus'' (1450–1500 ca., cod. fiesolano 67, [[Biblioteca Medicea Laurenziana]])]]

Albert's knowledge of natural science was considerable and for the age remarkably accurate. His industry in every department was great: not only did he produce commentaries and paraphrases of the entire Aristotelian corpus, including his scientific works, but Albert also added to and improved upon them. His books on topics like botany, zoology, and minerals included information from ancient sources, but also results of his own empirical investigations. These investigations pushed several of the special sciences forward, beyond the reliance on classical texts. In the case of embryology, for example, it has been claimed that little of value was written between Aristotle and Albert, who managed to identify organs within eggs.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|date=2004-09-01|title=Much more from the chicken's egg than breakfast – a wonderful model system|journal=Mechanisms of Development|language=en|volume=121|issue=9|pages=1015–1017|doi=10.1016/j.mod.2004.04.021|pmid=15296967|issn=0925-4773|last1=Wolpert|first1=Lewis}}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, Albert also effectively invented entire special sciences, where Aristotle has not covered a topic. For example, prior to Albert, there was no systematic study of minerals.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt; For the breadth of these achievements, he was bestowed the name ''Doctor Universalis.''

Much of Albert's empirical contributions to the natural sciences have been superseded, but his general approach to science may be surprisingly modern. For example, in ''De Mineralibus'' (Book II, Tractate ii, Ch. 1) Albert claims, &quot;For it is [the task] of natural science not simply to accept what we are told but to inquire into the causes of natural things.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/308059821ALBERTUSMAGNUSTheBookOfMinerals|title=Book of Minerals|last=Wyckoff|first=Dorothy|publisher=Clarendon Press|year=1967|isbn=|location=Oxford|pages=Preface}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Alchemy===
[[File:Liebig Company Trading Card Ad 01.12.003 front.tif|thumb|left|250px| Albertus Magnus, Chimistes Celebres, [[Liebig's Extract of Meat Company]] Trading Card, 1929]]

In the centuries since his death, many stories arose about Albert as an [[Alchemy|alchemist]] and magician. &quot;Much of the modern confusion results from the fact that later works, particularly the alchemical work known as the ''Secreta Alberti'' or the ''Experimenta Alberti'', were falsely attributed to Albertus by their authors to increase the prestige of the text through association.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Katz, David A., &quot;An Illustrated History of Alchemy and Early Chemistry&quot;, 1978&lt;/ref&gt; On the subject of alchemy and chemistry, many treatises relating to alchemy have been attributed to him, though in his authentic writings he had little to say on the subject, and then mostly through commentary on Aristotle. For example, in his commentary, ''De mineralibus'', he refers to the power of stones, but does not elaborate on what these powers might be.&lt;ref&gt;Georg Wieland, &quot;Albert der Grosse.  Der Entwurf einer eigenständigen Philosophie,&quot; Philosophen des Mittelalters (Darmstadt: Primus, 2000) 124-39.&lt;/ref&gt; A wide range of Pseudo-Albertine works dealing with alchemy exist, though, showing the belief developed in the generations following Albert's death that he had mastered alchemy, one of the fundamental sciences of the Middle Ages. These include ''Metals and Materials''; the ''Secrets of Chemistry''; the ''Origin of Metals''; the ''Origins of Compounds'', and a ''Concordance ''which is a collection of ''Observations on the [[philosopher's stone]]''; and other alchemy-chemistry topics, collected under the name of ''Theatrum Chemicum''.&lt;ref&gt;Walsh, John, ''The Thirteenth, Greatest of Centuries.'' 1907:46 ([https://books.google.com/books?id=_rofAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=RA2-PA46&amp;dq=albertus+magnus+gold+minerals#PRA2-PA46,M1 available online]).&lt;/ref&gt; He is credited with the discovery of the element [[arsenic]]&lt;ref name=&quot;BuildingBlocks451-3&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Emsley |first=John |title=Nature's Building Blocks: An A-Z Guide to the Elements |year=2001 |isbn=978-0-19-850341-5 |pages=43,513,529 |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |location=Oxford}}&lt;/ref&gt; and experimented with photosensitive chemicals, including [[silver nitrate]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Davidson |first=Michael W. |author2=National High Magnetic Field Laboratory at The Florida State University |title=Molecular Expressions: Science, Optics and You&amp;nbsp;— Timeline&amp;nbsp;— Albertus Magnus |publisher=The Florida State University |date=2003-08-01 |url=http://micro.magnet.fsu.edu/optics/timeline/people/magnus.html |accessdate=2009-11-28 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100330045629/http://micro.magnet.fsu.edu/optics/timeline/people/magnus.html |archivedate=2010-03-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Szabadváry |first=Ferenc |title=History of analytical chemistry |publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis |year=1992 |location= |page=17 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=53APqy0KDaQC |isbn=978-2-88124-569-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; He did believe that stones had occult properties, as he related in his work ''De mineralibus''. However, there is scant evidence that he personally performed alchemical experiments.

According to legend, Albert is said to have discovered the philosopher's stone and passed it on to his pupil Thomas Aquinas, shortly before his death. Albert does not confirm he discovered the stone in his writings, but he did record that he witnessed the creation of gold by &quot;transmutation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Julian Franklyn and Frederick E. Budd. ''A Survey of the Occult.'' Electric Book Company. 2001. p. 28-30. {{ISBN|1-84327-087-0}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Given that Thomas Aquinas died six years before Albert's death, this legend as stated is unlikely.

===Astronomy===
Albert was deeply interested in [[astronomy]], as has been articulated by scholars such as Paola Zambelli&lt;ref&gt;Paola Zambelli, &quot;The Speculum Astronomiae and its Enigma&quot; Dordrecht.&lt;/ref&gt; and Scott Hendrix.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt; Throughout the Middle Ages&amp;nbsp;–and well into the early modern period– astrology was widely accepted by scientists and intellectuals who held the view that life on earth is effectively a microcosm within the macrocosm (the latter being the cosmos itself). It was believed that correspondence therefore exists between the two and thus the celestial bodies follow patterns and cycles analogous to those on earth. With this worldview, it seemed reasonable to assert that astrology could be used to predict the probable future of a human being. Albert argued that an understanding of the celestial influences affecting us could help us to live our lives more in accord with Christian precepts.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;Scott E. Hendrix, How Albert the Great's Speculum Astronomiae Was Interpreted and Used by Four Centuries of Readers (Lewiston: 2010), 44-46.&lt;/ref&gt; The most comprehensive statement of his astrological beliefs is to be found in a work he authored around 1260, now known as the ''[[Speculum astronomiae]]''. However, details of these beliefs can be found in almost everything he wrote, from his early ''De natura boni'' to his last work, the ''Summa theologiae''.&lt;ref&gt;Hendrix, 195.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Matter and form===
Albert believed that all natural things were compositions of matter and form, he referred to it as ''quod est'' and ''quo est''. Albert also believed that God alone is the absolute ruling entity. Albert's version of [[hylomorphism]] is very similar to the [[Aristotelianism|Aristotelian]] doctrine.

===Music===
Albert is known for his commentary on the musical practice of his times. Most of his written musical observations are found in his commentary on Aristotle's ''Poetics''. He rejected the idea of &quot;[[Musica universalis|music of the spheres]]&quot; as ridiculous: movement of astronomical bodies, he supposed, is incapable of generating sound. He wrote extensively on proportions in music, and on the three different subjective levels on which [[plainchant]] could work on the human soul: purging of the impure; illumination leading to contemplation; and nourishing perfection through contemplation. Of particular interest to 20th-century music theorists is the attention he paid to silence as an integral part of music.

===Metaphysics of morals===
Both of his early treatises, ''De natura boni'' and ''De bono'', start with a metaphysical investigation into the concepts of the good in general and the physical good. Albert refers to the physical good as ''bonum naturae''. Albert does this before directly dealing with the moral concepts of metaphysics. In Albert's later works, he says in order to understand human or moral goodness, the individual must first recognize what it means to be good and do good deeds. This procedure reflects Albert's preoccupations with neo-Platonic theories of good as well as the doctrines of [[Pseudo-Dionysius]].&lt;ref&gt;Cunningham, Stanley. Reclaiming Moral Agency: The Moral Philosophy of Albert the Great. Washington, D.C.: The Catholic University Of America Press, 2008 p. 93&lt;/ref&gt; Albert's view was highly valued by the Catholic Church and his peers.

===Natural law===
Albert devoted the last tractatus of ''De Bono'' to a theory of justice and [[natural law]]. Albert places God as the pinnacle of justice and natural law. God legislates and divine authority is supreme. Up until his time, it was the only work specifically devoted to natural law written by a theologian or philosopher.&lt;ref&gt;Cunningham, Stanley. Reclaiming Moral Agency: The Moral Philosophy of Albert the Great. Washington, D.C.: The Catholic University Of America Press, 2008 p.207&lt;/ref&gt;

===Friendship===
Albert mentions friendship in his work, ''De bono'', as well as presenting his ideals and morals of friendship in the very beginning of ''Tractatus II''. Later in his life he published ''Super Ethica''.&lt;ref&gt;Cunningham, Stanley. Reclaiming Moral Agency: The Moral Philosophy of Albert the Great. Washington, D.C.: The Catholic University Of America Press, 2008 p.242&lt;/ref&gt; With his development of friendship throughout his work it is evident that friendship ideals and morals took relevance as his life went on. Albert comments on Aristotle's view of friendship with a quote from [[Cicero]], who writes, &quot;friendship is nothing other than the harmony between things divine and human, with goodwill and love&quot;. Albert agrees with this commentary but he also adds in harmony or agreement.&lt;ref&gt;Cunningham, Stanley. Reclaiming Moral Agency: The Moral Philosophy of Albert the Great. Washington, D.C.: The Catholic University Of America Press, 2008 p.243&lt;/ref&gt; Albert calls this harmony, ''consensio'', itself a certain kind of movement within the human spirit. Albert fully agrees with Aristotle in the sense that friendship is a virtue. Albert relates the inherent metaphysical contentedness between friendship and moral goodness. Albert describes several levels of goodness; the useful (''utile''), the pleasurable (''delectabile'') and the authentic or unqualified good (''honestum''). Then in turn there are three levels of friendship based on each of those levels, namely friendship based on usefulness (''amicitia utilis''), friendship based on pleasure (''amicitia delectabilis''), and friendship rooted in unqualified goodness (''amicitia honesti''; ''amicitia quae fundatur super honestum'').&lt;ref&gt;Cunningham, Stanley. Reclaiming Moral Agency: The Moral Philosophy of Albert the Great. Washington, D.C.: The Catholic University Of America Press, 2008 p.244&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cultural references==
[[File:France Strasbourg Cathedral Tympanum.jpg|thumb|The [[tympanum (architecture)|tympanum]] and [[archivolt]]s of [[Strasbourg Cathedral]], with iconography inspired by Albertus Magnus]]

The [[iconography]] of the [[pediment|tympanum]] and [[archivolt]]s of the late 13th-century [[gate|portal]] of [[Notre Dame de Strasbourg|Strasbourg Cathedral]] was inspired by Albert's writings.&lt;ref&gt;''France: A Phaidon Cultural Guide'', Phaidon Press, 1985, {{ISBN|0-7148-2353-8}}, p. 705&lt;/ref&gt; Albert is frequently mentioned by [[Dante Alighieri|Dante]], who made his doctrine of [[free will]] the basis of his ethical system. In his ''[[Divine Comedy]]'', Dante places Albertus with his pupil Thomas Aquinas among the great lovers of wisdom (''Spiriti Sapienti'') in the Heaven of the Sun. Albert is also mentioned, along with [[Heinrich Cornelius Agrippa|Agrippa]] and [[Paracelsus]], in [[Mary Shelley]]'s ''[[Frankenstein]]'', in which his writings influence a young [[Victor Frankenstein]].

In ''[[The Concept of Anxiety]]'', [[Søren Kierkegaard]] wrote that Albert, &quot;arrogantly boasted of his speculation before the deity and suddenly became stupid.&quot; Kierkegaard cites [[Gotthard Oswald Marbach]] whom he quotes as saying &quot;''Albertus repente ex asino factus philosophus et ex philosopho asinus''&quot; [Albert was suddenly transformed from an ass into a philosopher and from a philosopher into an ass].&lt;ref&gt;''The Concept of Anxiety'', [[Princeton University Press]], 1980, {{ISBN|0-691-02011-6}}, pp. 150–151&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Johann Eduard Erdmann]] considers Albert greater and more original than his pupil [[Aquinas]].&lt;ref&gt;Erdmann - History of Philosophy vol 1 trans Hough - London 1910. p. 422&lt;/ref&gt;

==Influence and tribute==
[[File:Albertus Magnus Painting by Joos van Gent.jpeg|thumb|left|upright|Painting by [[Joos van Wassenhove|Joos (Justus) van Gent]], [[Urbino]], c. 1475]]

A number of schools have been named after Albert, including [[Albertus Magnus High School]] in [[Bardonia, New York]];&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.albertusmagnus.net/?AspxAutoDetectCookieSupport=1 |title=Albertus Magnus High School |publisher=Albertusmagnus.net |date= |accessdate=2013-08-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Albertus Magnus Lyceum in [[River Forest, Illinois]]; and [[Albertus Magnus College]] in [[New Haven, Connecticut]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.albertus.edu/ |title=Albertus Magnus College |publisher=Albertus.edu |date= |accessdate=2013-08-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Albertus Magnus Science Hall at [[Thomas Aquinas College]], in Santa Paula, California, is named in honor of Albert.  The main science buildings at [[Providence College]] and [[Aquinas College (Michigan)|Aquinas College]] in Grand Rapids, Michigan, are also named after him.

The central square at the campus of the [[University of Cologne]] features a statue of Albert and is named after him.

The [[Academy for Science and Design]] in [[New Hampshire]] honored Albert by naming one of its four houses Magnus House.

As a tribute to the scholar's contributions to the law, the [[University of Houston Law Center]] displays a statue of Albert.  It is located on the campus of the [[University of Houston]].

The Albertus-Magnus-Gymnasien is found in Rottweil, Germany.

In [[Managua]], Nicaragua, the Albertus Magnus International Institute, a business and economic development research center, was founded in 2004.

[[File:University of Santo Tomas.jpg|thumb|University of Santo Tomas in the Philippines]]

In [[The Philippines]], the Albertus Magnus Building at the [[University of Santo Tomas]] that houses the Conservatory of Music, College of Tourism and Hospitality Management, College of Education, and UST Education High School is named in his honor. [[Saint Albert the Great Science Academy|The Saint Albert the Great Science Academy]] in [[San Carlos, Pangasinan|San Carlos City]], [[Pangasinan]], which offers preschool, elementary and high school education, takes pride in having St. Albert as their patron saint. Its main building was named Albertus Magnus Hall in 2008. [[San Alberto Magno Academy]] in [[Tubao]], [[La Union]] is also dedicated in his honor. This century-old Catholic high school continues to live on its vision-mission up to this day, offering Senior High school courses.
Due to his contributions to natural philosophy, the plant species ''[[Alberta magna]]'' and the asteroid [[20006 Albertus Magnus]] were named after him.

Numerous Catholic elementary and secondary schools are named for him, including schools in Toronto; Calgary; Cologne; and Dayton, Ohio.

The [[Albertus (typeface)|Albertus typeface]] is named after him.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | url=https://books.google.com/?id=UiM108dzif0C&amp;pg=PA116&amp;lpg=PA116&amp;dq=albertus+magnus+typeface#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title = The Visual Dictionary of Typography|isbn = 9782940411184|last1 = Ambrose|first1 = Gavin|last2 = Harris|first2 = Paul|date = 2010-10-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;
At the [[University of Notre Dame]] du Lac in [[South Bend, Indiana]], USA, the [[Zahm Hall (University of Notre Dame)|Zahm House]] Chapel is dedicated to St. Albert the Great. [[John Augustine Zahm|Fr. John Zahm, C.S.C.]], after whom the men's residence hall is named, looked to St. Albert's example of using religion to illumine scientific discovery. Fr. Zahm's work with the Bible and evolution is sometimes seen as a continuation of St. Albert's legacy.

The second largest student's fraternity of the [[Netherlands]], located in the city of [[Groningen]], is named [https://www.albertus.nl Albertus Magnus], in honor of the saint. 

The Colegio Cientifico y Artistico de San Alberto, Hopelawn, New Jersey, USA with a sister school in Nueva Ecija, Philippines was founded in 1986 in honor of him who thought and taught that religion, the sciences and the arts may be advocated as subjects which should not contradict each other but should support one another to achieve wisdom and reason.

The Vosloorus catholic parish (located in Vosloorus Extension One, Ekurhuleni, Gauteng, South Africa) is named after the saint.

The [https://www.kath-ka-hardt.de/html/st_antonius_egg_leo.html catholic parish] in Leopoldshafen, near [[Karlsruhe]] in Germany is also named after him also considering the huge research center of the [[Karlsruhe Institute of Technology]] nearby, as he is the patron saint of scientists.

Since the death of [[Albert I of Belgium|King Albert I]], the [[King's Feast]] is celebrated in [[Belgium]] on Albert's feast day.

Edinburgh's Catholic Chaplaincy serving the city's universities is named after St Albert.

==Bibliography==

===Translations===
* ''On the Body of the Lord,'' translated by Sr. Albert Marie Surmanski, OP, (Washington DC: Catholic University of America Press: 2017).
* ''On the Causes of the Properties of the Elements'', translated by Irven M. Resnick, (Milwaukee: Marquette University Press, 2010) [translation of ''Liber de causis proprietatum elementorum'']
* ''Questions concerning Aristotle's on Animals'', translated by Irven M Resnick and Kenneth F Kitchell, Jr, (Washington, DC: Catholic University of America Press, 2008) [translation of ''Quaestiones super De animalibus'']
* ''The Cardinal Virtues: Aquinas, Albert, and Philip the Chancellor'', translated by RE Houser, (Toronto: Pontifical Institute of Mediaeval Studies, 2004) [contains translations of ''Parisian Summa, part six: On the good'' and ''Commentary on the Sentences of Peter Lombard'', book 3, dist. 33 &amp; 36]
* ''The Commentary of Albertus Magnus on Book 1 of Euclid's Elements of Geometry'', edited by Anthony Lo Bello, (Boston: Brill Academic Publishers, 2003) [translation of ''Priumus Euclidis cum commento Alberti'']
* ''On Animals: A Medieval Summa Zoologica'', translated by Kenneth F Kitchell, Jr. and Irven Michael Resnick, (Baltimore; London: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1999) [translation of ''De animalibus'']
* Paola Zambelli, ''The Speculum Astronomiae and Its Enigma: Astrology, Theology, and Science in Albertus Magnus and His Contemporaries'', (Dordrecht; Boston: Kluwer Academic Publishers, 1992) [includes Latin text and English translation of ''Speculum astronomiae'']
* ''Albert &amp; Thomas: Selected Writings'', translated by Simon Tugwell, Classics of Western Spirituality, (New York: Paulist Press, 1988) [contains translation of ''Super Dionysii Mysticam theologiam'']
* ''On Union with God'', translated by a Benedictine of Princethorpe Priory, (London: Burns Oates &amp; Washbourne, 1911) [reprinted as (Felinfach: Llanerch Enterprises, 1991) and (London: Continuum, 2000)] [translation of ''De adherendo Deo'']

==See also==
* [[Christian mysticism]]
* [[List of Catholic saints]]
* [[List of Roman Catholic scientist-clerics]]
* [[Portal:Catholic Church/Patron Archive/November 15|Saint Albert the Great, patron saint archive]]
* [[Thomism|River Forest Thomism]]
* [[Science in the Middle Ages]]

==References==

===Citations===
{{Reflist}}

===Sources===
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |last = Tugwell |first = Simon |title = Albert and Thomas |publisher = Paulist Press |location = New York |year=1988 |ref = harv }}
* {{Cyclopaedia 1728}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
* Collins, David J. &quot;Albertus, Magnus or Magus?: Magic, Natural Philosophy, and Religious Reform in the Late Middle Ages.&quot; ''Renaissance Quarterly'' 63, no. 1 (2010): 1–44.
* Honnefelder, Ludger (ed.) ''Albertus Magnus and the Beginnings of the Medieval Reception of Aristotle in the Latin West. From Richardus Rufus to Franciscus de Mayronis'', (collection of essays in German and English), Münster : Aschendorff, 2005.
* Jong, Jonathan. [https://www.theschooloftheology.org/posts/essay/st-albertus-magnus-patron-of-science/ &quot;Albert the Great: Patron Saint of Scientists&quot;], in: St Mary Magdalen School of Theology, Thinking Faithfully.
* Kovach, Francis J. &amp; Shahan, Robert W. ''Albert the Great. Commemorative Essays'', Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1980.
* Miteva, Evelina. [https://web.archive.org/web/20140714223403/http://philosophy-e.com/the-soul-between-body-and-immortality-the-13th-century-debate-on-the-definition-of-the-human-rational-soul-as-form-and-substance/ &quot;The Soul between Body and Immortality: The 13th Century Debate on the Definition of the Human Rational Soul as Form and Substance&quot;], in: Philosophia: E-Journal of Philosophy and Culture, 1/2012. {{ISSN|1314-5606}}.
* Resnick, Irven (ed.), ''A Companion to Albert the Great: Theology, Philosophy, and the Sciences'', Leiden, Brill, 2013.
* Resnick, Irven e Kitchell Jr, Kenneth (eds.), ''Albert the Great: A Selective Annotated Bibliography'', (1900–2000), Tempe, Arizona Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies, 2004.
* {{Cite encyclopedia |first=William A. |last=Wallace |title=Albertus Magnus, Saint |url=http://www.u.arizona.edu/~aversa/scholastic/Dictionary%20of%20Scientific%20Biography/Albertus%20Magnus%20(Wallace).pdf |publisher=Scribner &amp; American Council of Learned Societies |isbn=978-0-684-10114-9 |editor-last=Gillispie |editor-first=Charles |encyclopedia=[[Dictionary of Scientific Biography]] |volume=1 |pages=99–103 |location=New York |year=1970}}

==External links==
{{commons}}
{{wikisource author}}
{{wikiquote}}
{{EB1911 poster|Albertus Magnus}}
* {{Gutenberg author | id=Magnus,+Albertus | name=Albertus Magnus}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Albertus Magnus}}
* {{Internet Archive author |name=Albert the Great}}
* {{Librivox author |id=5669}}
* {{cite SEP |url-id=albert-great |title=Albert the Great |last=Führer |first=Markus}}
* {{Cite CE1913| wstitle=St. Albertus Magnus |last=Kennedy |first=D.J. |short=x}}
* [http://www.albertusmagnus.uwaterloo.ca/ Alberti Magni Works in Latin Online]
* [http://www.renaissanceastrology.com/albertusmagnus.html Albertus Magnus on Astrology &amp; Magic]
* [http://www.skyscript.co.uk/magnus.html &quot;Albertus Magnus &amp; Prognostication by the Stars&quot;]
* [http://www.farlang.com/gemstones/magnus-virtue-stones/page_001 Albertus Magnus: &quot;Secrets of the Virtues of Herbs, Stones and Certain Beasts&quot;] London, 1604, full online version.
* [http://www.saintsbooks.net/books/St.%20Albert%20the%20Great%20-%20On%20Cleaving%20to%20God%20-%20De%20Adhaerendo%20Deo%20-%20Latin%20and%20English%20Edition.html ''Albertus Magnus – De Adhaerendo Deo – On Cleaving to God]
* [http://hos.ou.edu/galleries/03Medieval/AlbertusMagnus/ Online Galleries, History of Science Collections, University of Oklahoma Libraries] High resolution images of works by Albertus Magnus in .jpg and .tiff format.
* [http://roderic.uv.es/handle/10550/2407/browse?value=Albert%2C+Magne%2C+sant%2C+1193%3F-1280&amp;type=author Albertus Magnus works] at [http://roderic.uv.es/handle/10550/43 SOMNI] in the collection of the [[Ferdinand, Duke of Calabria|Duke of Calabria]].
** [http://roderic.uv.es/handle/10550/22005 Alberti Magni De laudibus beate Mariae Virginis], [[Italy|Italian]] digitized codex of 1476 with a completed transcription of his work &quot;Liber de laudibus gloriosissime Dei genitricis Marie&quot;
** [http://roderic.uv.es/uv_ms_0390 Albertus Magnus De mirabili scientia Dei], [[Italy|Italian]] digitized codex of 1484 with a transcription of the first part of his ''Summa Theologicae''.
* [http://digitalna.kniznica.info/s/HoYowef4Qb ''Compendium theologicae veritatis'']. [s.l.] : [s.n.], 1480. 322 p. - available online at [[University Library in Bratislava Digital Library]]

{{Aristotelianism}}
{{Medieval Philosophy}}
{{Catholic philosophy footer}}
{{Catholic saints}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Albertus Magnus}}
[[Category:1280 deaths]]
[[Category:13th-century Roman Catholic bishops]]
[[Category:13th-century Christian mystics]]
[[Category:13th-century philosophers]]
[[Category:13th-century Christian saints]]
[[Category:13th-century Roman Catholic theologians]]
[[Category:Aristotelian philosophers]]
[[Category:Medieval German chemists]]
[[Category:Medieval German theologians]]
[[Category:People from Lauingen]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic bishops of Regensburg]]
[[Category:Dominican bishops]]
[[Category:Natural philosophers]]
[[Category:Discoverers of chemical elements]]
[[Category:Doctors of the Church]]
[[Category:German Dominicans]]
[[Category:University of Padua alumni]]
[[Category:University of Paris faculty]]
[[Category:German alchemists]]
[[Category:German astrologers]]
[[Category:13th-century astrologers]]
[[Category:German entomologists]]
[[Category:German music theorists]]
[[Category:German philosophers]]
[[Category:Canonizations by Pope Pius XI]]
[[Category:German Roman Catholic saints]]
[[Category:Latin commentators on Aristotle]]
[[Category:Catholic philosophers]]
[[Category:Scholastic philosophers]]
[[Category:Catholic clergy scientists]]
[[Category:Dominican mystics]]
[[Category:Dominican saints]]
[[Category:Incorrupt saints]]
[[Category:Year of birth unknown]]
[[Category:German male non-fiction writers]]
[[Category:Alsatian saints]]
[[Category:13th-century German writers]]
[[Category:13th-century Latin writers]]
[[Category:13th-century alchemists]]
[[Category:13th-century jurists]]
[[Category:Provincial superiors]]</text>
      <sha1>ckqcyv35hi8p8dcaxaovwb25ioqupsr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
