  <page>
    <title>Abner</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1526</id>
    <revision>
      <id>922567336</id>
      <parentid>922567218</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-10-22T22:51:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>108.183.41.199</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Biblical narrative */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
[[File:Maciejowski Bible Leaf 37 3.jpg|thumb|Illustration from the [[Morgan Bible]] of Abner (in green) taking [[Michal]] away from [[Palti, son of Laish|Paltiel]].]]

In the [[Hebrew Bible]], '''Abner'''  ({{lang-he-n|אַבְנֵר}} ''’Avner'') was the cousin of [[Saul the King|King Saul]] and the commander-in-chief of his army ({{bibleverse|1 Samuel|14:50|KJV}}, {{bibleverse-nb|1 Samuel|20:25|KJV}}). His name also appears as {{Hebrew|אבינר בן נר}} &quot;Abiner son of [[List of minor biblical figures, L-Z#N|Ner]]&quot;, where the longer form Abiner means &quot;my father is Ner&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://biblehub.com/interlinear/1_samuel/14-50.htm|title=1 Samuel 14:50 Interlinear: and the name of the wife of Saul is Ahinoam, daughter of Ahimaaz; and the name of the head of his host is Abner son of Ner, uncle of Saul;|website=biblehub.com|access-date=2018-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biblical narrative==
Abner is initially mentioned incidentally in Saul's history ({{bibleverse|1 Samuel|14:50|KJV}}, {{bibleverse-nb|1 Samuel|17:55|KJV}}, {{bibleverse-nb|1 Samuel|26:5|KJV}}), first appearing as the son of Ner, Saul's uncle, and the commander of Saul's army. He then comes to the story again as the commander who introduced [[David (biblical king)|David]] to Saul following David's killing of [[Goliath]]. He is not mentioned in the account of the disastrous [[battle of Gilboa]] when Saul's power was crushed. Seizing the youngest but only surviving of Saul's sons, [[Ish-bosheth]], also called Eshbaal, Abner set him up as king over [[Kingdom of Israel (united monarchy)|Israel]] at [[Mahanaim]], east of the [[Jordan River|Jordan]]. [[David (biblical king)|David]], who was accepted as king by [[Kingdom of Judah|Judah]] alone, was meanwhile reigning at [[Hebron]], and for some time war was carried on between the two parties.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;&gt;{{EB1911|inline=1|wstitle=Abner|volume=1|page=66}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The only engagement between the rival factions which is told at length is noteworthy, inasmuch as it was preceded by an encounter at [[Gibeon (ancient city)|Gibeon]] between twelve chosen men from each side, in which the whole twenty-four seem to have perished ({{bibleverse|2 Samuel|2:12|KJV}}).{{efn|According to Chisholm (1911), [t]he object of the story of the encounter is to explain the name Helkath-hazzurim, the meaning of which is doubtful (''Ency. Bib.'' col. 2006; Batten in ''Zeit. f. alt-test. Wissens.'' 1906, pp. 90 sqq.).}} In the general engagement which followed, Abner was defeated and put to flight. He was closely pursued by [[Asahel]], brother of [[Joab]], who is said to have been &quot;light of foot as a wild roe&quot; ({{bibleverse|2 Samuel|2:18|KJV}}). As Asahel would not desist from the pursuit, though warned, Abner was compelled to slay him in self-defence. This originated a deadly [[feud]] between the leaders of the opposite parties, for Joab, as next of kin to Asahel, was by the law and custom of the country the avenger of his blood.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; However, according to Josephus, in Antiquities, Book 7, Chapter 1, Joab had forgiven Abner for the death of his brother, Asahel, the reason being that Abner had slain Asahel honorably in combat after he had first warned Asahel and had no other choice but to kill him out of self-defense. This battle was part of a civil war between David and Ish-bosheth, the son of Saul. After this battle Abner switched to the side of David and granted him control over the tribe of Benjamin. This act put Abner in David's favor.

For some time afterward the war was carried on, the advantage being invariably on the side of David. At length, Ish-bosheth lost the main prop of his tottering cause by accusing Abner of sleeping with [[Rizpah]] (cf. {{bibleverse|2 Samuel|3:7|KJV}}), one of Saul's [[concubine]]s, an alliance which, according to contemporary notions, would imply pretensions to the [[throne]] (cf. {{bibleverse|2 Samuel|16:21|KJV}}ff.).

Abner was indignant at the rebuke, and immediately opened negotiations with David, who welcomed him on the condition that his wife [[Michal]] should be restored to him. This was done, and the proceedings were ratified by a feast. Almost immediately after, however, Joab, who had been sent away, perhaps intentionally returned and slew Abner at the gate of Hebron. The ostensible motive for the [[assassination]] was a desire to avenge Asahel, and this would be a sufficient justification for the deed according to the moral standard of the time (although Abner should have been safe from such a revenge killing in Hebron, which was a [[Cities of Refuge|City of Refuge]]). The conduct of David after the event was such as to show that he had no complicity in the act, though he could not venture to punish its perpetrators ({{bibleverse|2 Samuel|3:31-39|KJV}}; cf. {{bibleverse|1 Kings|2:31|KJV}}ff.).&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;
[[File:David and the tomb of Abner.jpg|thumb|David and the tomb of Abner. Artist unknown. 19th century.]]
David had Abner buried in [[Hebron]], as it states in {{bibleverse|2 Samuel|3:31-32|KJV}}, &quot;And David said to all the people who were with him, 'Rend your clothes and gird yourselves with sackcloth, and wail before Abner.' And King David went after the bier. And they buried Abner in Hebron, and the king raised his voice and wept on Abner's grave, and all the people wept.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Shmuel II - Chapter 3|url = http://www.chabad.org/library/bible_cdo/aid/15863|website = www.chabad.org|accessdate = 2016-01-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Shortly after Abner's death, Ish-bosheth was assassinated as he slept ({{bibleverse|2 Samuel|4:5-12|KJV}}), and David became king of the reunited kingdoms ({{bibleverse|2 Samuel|5:1-5|KJV}}).

==Tomb of Abner==
The site known as the Tomb of Abner is located not far from the [[Cave of the Patriarchs]] in Hebron and receives visitors throughout the year. Many travelers have recorded visiting the tomb over the centuries.

[[Benjamin of Tudela]], who began his journeys in 1165, wrote in the journal, &quot;The valley of Eshkhol is north of the mountain upon which Hebron stood, and the cave of Makhpela is east thereof. A bow-shot west of the cave is the sepulchre of Abner the son of Ner.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = The Itinerary of Benjamin of Tudela: Travels in the Middle Ages|url = https://www.amazon.com/The-Itinerary-Benjamin-Tudela-Travels/dp/0911389091|publisher = NightinGale Resources|date = 2004-03-01|location = New York|isbn = 9780911389098}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A rabbi in the 12th century records visiting the tomb as reprinted in [[Elkan Nathan Adler]]'s book ''Jewish Travellers in the Middle Ages: 19 Firsthand Accounts''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Jewish Travellers in the Middle Ages: 19 Firsthand Accounts|url = https://archive.org/details/jewishtravellers00elka|publisher = Dover Publications|date = 2011-11-30|location = New York|isbn = 9780486253978|editor-first = Elkan Nathan|editor-last = Adler|url-access = registration}}&lt;/ref&gt; The account states, &quot;I, Jacob, the son of R. Nathaniel ha Cohen, journeyed with much difficulty, but God helped me to enter the Holy Land, and I saw the graves of our righteous Patriarchs in Hebron and the grave of Abner the son of Ner.&quot; Adler postulates that the visit must have occurred prior to [[Saladin]]'s capture of [[Jerusalem]] in 1187.

Rabbi [[Moses ben Mordecai Bassola|Moses Basola]] records visiting the tomb in 1522. He states, &quot;Abner's grave is in the middle of Hebron; the Muslims built a mosque over it.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = In Zion and Jerusalem: The Itinerary of Rabbi Moses Basola 1512-1523|url = https://www.amazon.com/In-Zion-Jerusalem-Itinerary-1512-1523/dp/9652229261|publisher = C G Gundation|date = 1999-12-31|location = Jerusalem|isbn = 9789652229267|first = David|last = Avraham}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another visitor in the 1500s states that &quot;at the entrance to the market in Hebron, at the top of the hill against the wall, Abner ben Ner is buried, in a church, in a cave.&quot; This visit was recorded in Sefer Yihus ha-Tzaddiqim (Book of Genealogy of the Righteous), a collection of [[Travelogues of Ottoman Palestine|travelogues]] from 1561. Abraham Moshe Lunz reprinted the book in 1896.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/14604-uri-ori-ben-simeon|title = URI (ORI) BEN SIMEON|date = |accessdate = January 5, 2015|website = History and Anthropology in Jewish Studies|publisher = Penn Libraries|last = Ochser|first = Schulim}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Menahem Mendel of Kamenitz, considered the first hotelier in the Land of Israel,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = The first Holy Land hotelier|url = http://www.jpost.com/Local-Israel/In-Jerusalem/The-first-Holy-Land-hotelier|website = The Jerusalem Post {{!}} JPost.com|accessdate = 2016-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; wrote about the Tomb of Abner is his 1839 book ''Korot Ha-Itim'', which was translated into English as ''The Book of the Occurrences of the Times to Jeshurun in the Land of Israel.'' He states'', &quot;''Here I write of the graves of the righteous to which I paid my respects. Hebron – Described above is the character and order of behavior of those coming to pray at the Cave of ha-Machpelah. I went there, between the stores, over the grave of Avner ben Ner and was required to pay a Yishmaeli – the grave was in his courtyard – to allow me to enter.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = &quot;Book of the Occurrences of the Times to Jeshurun in the Land of Israel&quot; by David G. Cook and Sol P. Cohen|url = http://repository.upenn.edu/miscellaneous_papers/10/|website = repository.upenn.edu|accessdate = 2016-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The author and traveler [[J. J. Benjamin]] mentioned visiting the tomb in his book ''Eight Years in Asia and Africa'' (1859, Hanover). He states, &quot;On leaving the Sepulchre of the Patriarchs, and proceeding on the road leading to the Jewish quarter, to the left of the courtyard, is seen a Turkish dwelling house, by the side of which is a small grotto, to which there is a descent of several steps. This is the tomb of Abner, captain of King Saul. It is held in much esteem by the Arabs, and the proprietor of it takes care that it is always kept in the best order. He requires from those who visit it a small gratuity.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Eight years in Asia and Africa from 1846-1855 : Israel Joseph Benjamin : Free Download &amp; Streaming|url = https://archive.org/details/eightyearsinasi00benjgoog|website = Internet Archive|accessdate = 2016-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The British scholar [[Israel Abrahams]] wrote in his 1912 book ''The Book of Delight and Other Papers'', &quot;Hebron was the seat of David’s rule over Judea. Abner was slain here by Joab, and was buried here – they still show Abner’s tomb in the garden of a large house within the city. By the pool at Hebron were slain the murderers of Ishbosheth...&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = The Book of Delight and Other Papers|url = https://www.amazon.com/Book-Delight-Other-Papers/dp/152323332X/|publisher = CreateSpace Independent Publishing Platform|date = 2016-01-05|isbn = 9781523233328|first = Israel|last = Abrahams}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Abner ben Ner.jpg|thumb|Tomb of Abner]]
Over the years the tomb fell into disrepair and neglect. It was closed to the public in 1994. In 1996, a group of 12 Israeli women filed a petition with the Supreme Court requesting the government to reopen the Tomb of Abner.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Google Groups|url = https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/shamash.eretz-yisrael/rhK1h_a_RSo|website = groups.google.com|accessdate = 2016-01-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; More requests were made over the years &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Articles by David Wilder: The Mystery of the Tomb of Avner ben Ner or Understanding Uzi’'s Whims|url = http://davidwilder.blogspot.co.il/1997/05/mystery-of-tomb-of-avner-ben-ner-or.html|website = davidwilder.blogspot.co.il|accessdate = 2016-01-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; and eventually arrangements were made to have the site open to the general public{{dubious|a) The source is a biased blog; b) It says that JEWS are allowed in on 10 days o.t.y., not &quot;the gen. public&quot;. Prove or amend.|date=August 2016}} on ten days throughout the year corresponding to the ten days that the Isaac Hall of the Cave of the Patriarchs is open.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.machpela.com/english/content.asp?pageid=26|title = Machpela website|date = |accessdate = |website = |publisher = |last = |first = |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20110714013035/http://www.machpela.com/english/content.asp?pageid=26|archive-date = 2011-07-14|url-status = dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; In early 2007 new [[Mezuzah|mezuzot]] were affixed to the entrance of the site.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://shturem.org/index.php?section=news&amp;id=11883|title = Shturem|date = |accessdate = |website = |publisher = |last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In popular culture==
*1960, [[David and Goliath (1960 film)|''David and Goliath'']] (film) – Abner portrayed by [[Massimo Serato]]. In this version, Abner tries to murder David (Ivica Pajer) when he returns in triumph after killing [[Goliath]]. However, here Abner is slain by King Saul ([[Orson Welles]]). 
*1961, ''[[A Story of David]]'' (film) – Abner portrayed by Welsh actor [[David Davies (actor born 1906)|David Davies]]. 
*1976, ''[[The Story of David]]'' (television series) – Younger version of Abner portrayed by Israeli actor Yehuda Efroni. Older version of Abner portrayed by British actor [[Brian Blessed]]. 
*1985, [[King David (film)|''King David'']] (film) – Abner portrayed by English actor [[John Castle]]. King David portrayed by [[Richard Gere]]. 
*1997, [[King David (musical)|''King David'']] (musical) – written by [[Tim Rice]] and [[Alan Menken]]. Abner portrayed by American actor Timothy Shew. 
*1997, ''David'' (television drama) – Abner portrayed by Richard Ashcroft.
*2009, [[Kings (U.S. TV series)|''Kings'']] (television series) – Abner portrayed by [[Wes Studi]] as General Linus Abner. The series is set in a multi-ethnic Western culture similar to that in the present-day United States, but with characters drawn from the Bible.
*2012, ''[[Rei Davi]]'' (Brazilian television series) – Abner portrayed by Iran Malfitano.

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
*{{commonscatinline}}
* [http://hebron.web.aplus.net/english/article.php?id=240 Pictures of Avner ben Ner's Tomb in Hebron]
* [http://en.hebron.org.il/history/235 Tomb of Abner page on Hebron.com website].
* David, Abraham (ed.) (1999). ''In Zion and Jerusalem: The Itinerary of Rabbi [[Moses ben Mordecai Bassola|Moses Basola]] (1521–1523)'' C. G. Foundation Jerusalem Project Publications of the Martin (Szusz) Department of Land of Israel Studies of Bar-Ilan University {{ISBN|9652229261}}. Reference is made to visiting the tomb of Abner. ([https://web.archive.org/web/20160304132346/http://courses.umass.edu/juda373/outlines/Basola,%20through%20p.148.pdf p.&amp;nbsp;77]).
* [http://www.imagekind.com/Prayer-at-Cave-of-Avner-ben-Ner_art?IMID=f2c778c4-bcb1-4446-9ef4-c8489643a845 Photo of prayer at the Tomb of Abner from Imagekind]. 
* [http://www.picjew.com/en/photos/holy-places/avner-ben-ner-tomb/3803 Photo of prayer at the Tomb of Abner from PicJew].
* Photos of Tomb of Abner Ben Ner from the book ''Sites in Hebron'' by [[David Wilder (activist)|David Wilder]]. ASIN: B00ALHB89Y. [https://www.amazon.com/dp/B00ALHB89Y/ref=rdr_kindle_ext_tmb]

[[Category:Hebrew Bible people]]
[[Category:Biblical murder victims]]
[[Category:Warriors of Asia]]
[[Category:Kingdom of Israel (united monarchy)]]

[[ca:Llista de personatges bíblics#Abner]]</text>
      <sha1>nn6u4rm70rprsxbc11r6e104bqk7cnf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
