  <page>
    <title>Dodo (Alice's Adventures in Wonderland)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1500</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942774275</id>
      <parentid>942773936</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-26T19:21:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Randy Kryn</username>
        <id>4796325</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>italics</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2013}}
{{DISPLAYTITLE:Dodo (''Alice's Adventures in Wonderland'')}}
{{Infobox character
| name               = Dodoa Long Tale&quot;. An illustration from ''Alice's Adventures in Wonderland''.
| image              = Alice par John Tenniel 09.png
| caption            = [[John Tenniel]]'s illustration of the Dodo in &quot;A Caucus-Race and 
| first              = ''[[Alice's Adventures in Wonderland]]''
| creator            = [[Lewis Carroll]]
| species            = [[Dodo]]
| occupation         = Bird
| gender             = Male
}}
'''The Dodo''' is a [[fictional character]] appearing in Chapters 2 and 3 of the 1865 book ''[[Alice's Adventures in Wonderland]]'' by [[Lewis Carroll]] (Charles Lutwidge Dodgson). The Dodo is a caricature of the author. A popular but unsubstantiated belief is that Dodgson chose the particular animal to represent himself because of his stammer, and thus would accidentally introduce himself as &quot;Do-do-dodgson&quot;.

Historically, the [[Dodo]] was a non-flying bird that lived on the island of [[Mauritius]], east of [[Madagascar]] in the Indian Ocean. It became extinct in the mid 17th century during the colonisation of the island by the Dutch.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dead as a&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|doi = 10.1080/08912960802376199|last1 = Turvey|first1 = S. T.|last2 = Cheke|first2 = A. S.|year = 2008|title = Dead as a dodo: The fortuitous rise to fame of an extinction icon|journal = Historical Biology|volume = 20|issue = 2|pages = 149–163|pmid = |pmc = |ref = harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==''Alice's Adventures in Wonderland''==
[[File:Alice in Wonderland by Arthur Rackham - 03 - But who has won?.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Depiction by [[Arthur Rackham]], 1907]] 
In this passage Lewis Carroll incorporated references to the original boating expedition of 4 July 1862 during which Alice's Adventures were first told, with [[Alice (Alice's Adventures in Wonderland)|Alice]] as herself, and the others represented by birds: the [[Lory (Alice's Adventures in Wonderland)|Lory]] was Lorina Liddell, [[Eaglet (Alice's Adventures in Wonderland)|the Eaglet]] was Edith Liddell, the Dodo was Dodgson, and the [[Duck (Alice's Adventures in Wonderland)|Duck]] was Rev. [[Robinson Duckworth]].  In order to get dry after a swim, the Dodo proposes that everyone run a Caucus race – where the participants run in patterns of any shape, starting and leaving off [[equality of outcome|whenever they like, so that everyone wins]].  At the end of the race, Alice distributes [[comfits]] from her pocket to all as prizes. However this leaves no prize for herself.  The Dodo inquires what else she has in her pocket.  As she has only a [[thimble]], the Dodo requests it from her and then awards it to Alice as her prize.  The Caucus Race, as depicted by Carroll, is a [[satire]] on the [[politics|political]] [[caucus]] system, mocking its lack of clarity and decisiveness.

==Interpretations==

===Disney animated film version===
{{Main|Alice in Wonderland (1951 film)}}
{{Infobox character
| name       = Capt. Dodo
| image      = Dodo-alice.wonderland.disney.jpg
| first      = ''[[Alice in Wonderland (1951 film)|Alice in Wonderland]]''
| creator    = [[Lewis Carroll]]
| portrayer  = [[Bill Thompson (voice actor)|Bill Thompson]]
| nickname   = Dodo
| species    = [[Dodo]]
| occupation = Sailor
| gender     = Male
}}
In the Disney film, the Dodo plays a much greater role in the story. He is merged with the character of [[Pat (Alice's Adventures in Wonderland)|Pat the Gardener]], which leads to him sometimes being nicknamed Pat the Dodo, but this name is never mentioned in the film. The Dodo is also the leader of the caucus race. He has the appearance and personality of a sea captain. The Dodo is voiced by [[Bill Thompson (voice actor)|Bill Thompson]] and animated by [[Milt Kahl]].

Dodo is first seen as [[Alice (Alice's Adventures in Wonderland)|Alice]] is floating on the sea in a bottle. Dodo is seen singing, but when Alice asks him for help, he does not notice her. On shore, Dodo is seen on a rock, organizing a caucus race. This race involves running around until one gets dry, but the attempts are hampered by incoming waves.
Dodo is later summoned by the [[White Rabbit]], when the rabbit believes a monster, actually Alice having magically grown to a giant size, is inside his home. Dodo brings [[Bill the Lizard]], and attempts to get him to go down the chimney. Bill refuses at first, but Dodo is able to convince him otherwise. However, the soot causes Alice to sneeze, sending Bill high up into the sky. Dodo then decides to burn the house down, much to the chagrin of the White Rabbit. He begins gathering wood, such as the furniture, for this purpose. However, Alice is soon able to return to a smaller size and exit the house.

The White Rabbit soon leaves, while Dodo asks for matches, not realizing that the situation has been resolved. He then asks Alice for a match, but when she doesn't have any, Dodo complains about the lack of cooperation and uses his pipe to light the fire.

The Dodo later appears briefly at the end of the film, conducting another Caucus Race.
{{Clear}}

===Tim Burton's ''Alice in Wonderland'' version===
{{Main|Alice in Wonderland (2010 film)}}
{{Infobox character
| name       = Uilleam
| series     = Alice in Wonderland
| image      = Dodoalice.wonderland.2010.jpg
| first      = ''[[Alice in Wonderland (2010 film)|Alice in Wonderland]]''
| creator    = [[Lewis Carroll]]/[[Tim Burton]]
| portrayer  = [[Michael Gough]]
| species    = [[Dodo]]
| occupation = Adviser&lt;br/&gt;Caddy
| gender     = Male
}}
In [[Tim Burton]]'s adaptation of [[Alice in Wonderland (2010 film)|Alice in Wonderland]], the Dodo's appearance retains the subtle apparent nature from [[John Tenniel]]'s illustration. He bears a down of brilliant blue and wears a blue coat and white spats along with glasses and a cane. He is one of Alice's good-willed advisers, taking first note of her abilities as the true Alice. He is also one of the oldest inhabitants. His name is '''Uilleam''', and he is portrayed by Michael Gough. He goes with the [[White Rabbit]], [[Tweedledee and Tweedledum]], and [[Dormouse (Alice's Adventures in Wonderland)|Dormouse]] to take Alice to [[Caterpillar (Alice's Adventures in Wonderland)|Caterpillar]] to decide whether Alice is the real one. He is later captured by the [[Red Queen (Through the Looking Glass)|Red Queen]]'s forces. When Alice came to the Red Queen's castle, he was seen at the Red Queen's castle yard as a caddy for the Queen's croquet game. After the Red Queen orders the release of the [[Jubjub bird]] to kill all her subjects from rebelling, he is then seen briefly running from it when the Tweedles went to hide from it and escaped but was snatched by the Jubjub and was never seen again throughout the film.

His name may be based on a lecture on [[William the Conqueror]] from Chapter Three of the original novel. The character is voiced by [[Michael Gough]] in his final feature film role before his death in 2011. Gough came out of retirement to appear in the film but the character only speaks three lines, so Gough managed to record in one day.

==''Pandora Hearts''==
In the anime and manga series ''[[Pandora Hearts]]'' Dodo is the chain of Rufus Barma one of the four dukedoms.

==References==
{{Reflist}}
{{commons category}}

{{Alice|state=expanded}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dodo (Alice's Adventures in Wonderland)}}
[[Category:Lewis Carroll characters]]
[[Category:Fictional flightless birds]]
[[Category:Literary characters introduced in 1865]]</text>
      <sha1>ruftui0hyscwi0uqne5czvjp5b1v3xm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
