  <page>
    <title>Alexander III of Russia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1592</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943149526</id>
      <parentid>943096463</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T04:15:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MeyerBen33</username>
        <id>38660883</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Fixed two incorrect dates according to the citation.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox royalty
| name         = Alexander III
| succession   = [[Emperor of All Russia|Emperor of Russia]]

| image        = Alexander III, Emperor of Russia (1845-94).png
| reign        = 13 March 1881{{snd}}{{nowrap|1 November 1894}}
| coronation   = 27 May 1883
| cor-type     = [[Coronation of the Russian monarch|Coronation]]
| predecessor  = [[Alexander II of Russia|Alexander II]]
| successor    = [[Nicholas II of Russia|Nicholas II]]
| spouse       = {{marriage|[[Maria Feodorovna (Dagmar of Denmark)]]|9 November 1866}}
| issue        = {{plain list|
* [[Nicholas II of Russia]]
* [[Grand Duke Alexander Alexandrovich of Russia|Grand Duke Alexander]]
* [[Grand Duke George Alexandrovich of Russia|Grand Duke George]]
* [[Grand Duchess Xenia Alexandrovna of Russia|Grand Duchess Xenia]]
* [[Grand Duke Michael Alexandrovich of Russia|Grand Duke Michael]]
* [[Grand Duchess Olga Alexandrovna of Russia|Grand Duchess Olga]]
}}
| issue-link   = #Issue
| issue-pipe   =
| full name    = Alexander Alexandrovich Romanov
| house        = [[Holstein-Gottorp-Romanov]]
| father       = [[Alexander II of Russia]]
| mother       = [[Maria Alexandrovna (Marie of Hesse)]]
| birth_date   = {{Birth date|1845|3|10|df=y}}
| birth_place  = [[Winter Palace]], [[Saint Petersburg]], [[Russian Empire]]
| death_date   = {{Death date and age|1894|11|1|1845|3|10|df=y}}
| death_place  = [[Maley Palace]], [[Livadiya, Ukraine|Livadia]], [[Taurida Governorate]], Russian Empire
| burial_date  = 18 November 1894
| burial_place = [[Peter and Paul Cathedral]], Saint Petersburg, Russian Empire
| signature    = SignatureAlexanderIII.jpg
| religion     = [[Russian Orthodox Church|Russian Orthodox]]}}

'''Alexander III''' ({{lang-rus|Алекса́ндр III Алекса́ндрович|r=Aleksandr III Aleksandrovich}}; 10 March 1845{{snd}}1 November 1894)&lt;ref&gt;10 March [O.S. 26 February] 1845 – 1 November [O.S. 20 October] 1894&lt;/ref&gt; was [[Emperor of All Russia|Emperor of Russia]], [[List of Polish monarchs|King of Poland]] and [[Grand Duke of Finland]] from 13 March 1881 until his death on 1 November 1894.&lt;ref&gt;13 March  [O.S. 1 March] 1881{{snd}}1 November [O.S. 20 October] 1894.&lt;/ref&gt; He was highly reactionary and reversed some of the liberal reforms of his father, [[Alexander II of Russia|Alexander II]]. Under the influence of [[Konstantin Pobedonostsev]] (1827–1907) he opposed any reform that limited his autocratic rule. During his reign, Russia fought no major wars; he was therefore styled &quot;'''The Peacemaker'''&quot; ({{lang-rus|Миротво́рец|Mirotvórets|p=mʲɪrɐˈtvorʲɪt͡s}}).

==Early life==

===Disposition===
[[File:Tsarevitch Alexander later Alexander III 1865 by Sergei Levitsky.jpg|thumb|150px|right|Alexander III as [[Tsesarevich]], by [[Sergei Lvovich Levitsky]], 1865]]

Grand Duke Alexander Alexandrovich was born on 10 March 1845 at the [[Winter Palace]] in [[Saint Petersburg]], [[Russian Empire]], the second son and third child of [[Emperor of Russia#Emperors of Russia|Emperor]] [[Alexander II of Russia|Alexander II]] and his first wife [[Maria Alexandrovna (Marie of Hesse)|Maria Alexandrovna]] (née Princess Marie of Hesse).

In disposition Alexander bore little resemblance to his soft-hearted, liberal father, and still less to his refined, philosophic, sentimental, chivalrous, yet cunning great-uncle [[Emperor Alexander I]], who could have been given the title of &quot;the first gentleman of [[Europe]]&quot;. Although an enthusiastic amateur musician and patron of the [[ballet]], Alexander was seen as lacking refinement and elegance. Indeed, he rather relished the idea of being of the same rough texture as some of his subjects. His straightforward, abrupt manner savoured sometimes of gruffness, while his direct, unadorned method of expressing himself harmonized well with his rough-hewn, immobile features and somewhat sluggish movements. His education was not such as to soften these peculiarities.{{sfn|Wallace|1911|pp=561-562}} More than six feet tall (about 1.9&amp;nbsp;m), he was also noted for his immense physical strength. A [[sebaceous cyst]] on the left side of his nose caused him to be mocked by some of his contemporaries, and he sat for photographs and portraits with the right side of his face most prominent.

An account from the memoirs of the artist [[Alexander Benois]] gives one impression of Alexander III:

&lt;blockquote&gt;After a performance of the ballet ''[[Tsar Kandavl or Le Roi Candaule|Tsar Kandavl]]'' at the [[Mariinsky Theatre]], I first caught sight of the Emperor. I was struck by the size of the man, and although cumbersome and heavy, he was still a mighty figure. There was indeed something of the [[muzhik]] ''[Russian peasant]'' about him. The look of his bright eyes made quite an impression on me. As he passed where I was standing, he raised his head for a second, and to this day I can remember what I felt as our eyes met. It was a look as cold as steel, in which there was something threatening, even frightening, and it struck me like a blow. The Tsar's gaze! The look of a man who stood above all others, but who carried a monstrous burden and who every minute had to fear for his life and the lives of those closest to him. In later years I came into contact with the Emperor on several occasions, and I felt not the slightest bit timid. In more ordinary cases Tsar Alexander III could be at once kind, simple, and even almost homely.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Education===
Though he was destined to be a strongly counter-reforming emperor, Alexander had little prospect of succeeding to the throne during the first two decades of his life, as he had an elder brother, [[Grand Duke Nicholas Alexandrovich of Russia|Nicholas]], who seemed of robust constitution. Even when Nicholas first displayed symptoms of delicate health, the notion that he might die young was never taken seriously, and he was betrothed to [[Dagmar of Denmark (Maria Feodorovna)|Princess Dagmar of Denmark]], daughter of [[King Christian IX of Denmark]] and [[Louise of Hesse-Kassel|Queen Louise of Denmark]], and whose siblings included [[King Frederick VIII of Denmark]], [[Queen Alexandra of the United Kingdom]] and [[King George I of Greece]]. Great solicitude was devoted to the education of Nicholas as [[tsesarevich]], whereas Alexander received only the training of an ordinary Grand Duke of that period. This included acquaintance with [[French language|French]], English and [[German language|German]], and [[military drill]].{{sfn|Wallace|1911|p=562}}

===As tsesarevich===
[[File:Alexander III and Maria Fedorovna's coronation by G.Becker (1888, Hermitage).jpg|thumb|right|300px|Grand painting by artist Georges Becker of the coronation of Emperor Alexander III and [[Maria Feodorovna (Dagmar of Denmark)|Empress Maria Fyodorovna]], which took place on {{OldStyleDate|27 May|1883|15 May}} at the [[Cathedral of the Dormition|Uspensky Sobor]] of the [[Moscow Kremlin]]. On the left of the [[dais]] can be seen his young son and heir, [[Nicholas II of Russia|the Tsarevich Nicholas]], and behind Nicholas can be seen a young [[Grand Duke George Alexandrovich of Russia|Grand Duke George]].]]
Alexander became [[tsesarevich]] upon Nicholas's sudden death in 1865; it was then that he began to study the principles of law and administration under [[Konstantin Pobedonostsev]], then a professor of [[Civil law (legal system)|civil law]] at [[Moscow State University]] and later (from 1880) [[chief procurator]] of the [[Holy Synod]] of the Orthodox Church in Russia. Pobedonostsev instilled into the young man's mind the belief that zeal for [[Russian Orthodox Church|Russian Orthodox]] thought was an essential factor of Russian [[patriotism]] to be cultivated by every right-minded emperor. While he was [[heir apparent]] from 1865 to 1881 Alexander did not play a prominent part in public affairs, but allowed it to become known that he had ideas which did not coincide with the principles of the existing government.{{sfn|Wallace|1911|p=562}}

On his deathbed the previous tsesarevich was said to have expressed the wish that his fiancée, Princess Dagmar of Denmark, should marry his successor.{{sfn|Wallace|1911|p=562}} This wish was swiftly realized when on {{OldStyleDate|9 November|1866|28 October}} in the [[Grand Church of the Winter Palace]] in [[St. Petersburg]], Alexander wed Dagmar, who converted to Orthodox Christianity and took the name [[Maria Feodorovna (Dagmar of Denmark)|Maria Feodorovna]]. The union proved a happy one to the end; unlike nearly all of his predecessors since Peter I, there was no adultery in his marriage. The couple spent their wedding night at the Tsarevich's private dacha known as &quot;My Property&quot;.

Later on the Tsarevich became estranged from his father; this was due to their vastly differing political views, as well was his resentment towards Alexander II's long-standing relationship with [[Catherine Dolgorukov]] (with whom he had several illegitimate children) while his mother, the [[Marie Alexandrovna, Tsarina of Russia|Empress]], was suffering from chronic ill-health.&lt;ref&gt;Van Der Kiste, John ''The Romanovs: 1818–1959 ''(Sutton Publishing, 2003) p. 94&lt;/ref&gt; To the scandal of many at court, including the Tsarevich himself, Alexander II married Catherine a mere month after Marie Alexandrovna's death in 1880.

==Reign==
On 13 March 1881 (N.S.) Alexander's father, [[Alexander II of Russia|Alexander II]], was [[Assassination of Alexander II of Russia|assassinated]] by members of the [[terrorism|terrorist]] organization [[Narodnaya Volya]]. As a result, he ascended to the Russian imperial throne in [[Ninasi|Nennal]]. He and Maria Feodorovna were officially crowned and anointed at the [[Assumption Cathedral in Moscow]] on 27 May 1883. Alexander's ascension to the throne was followed by an outbreak of [[Pogroms in the Russian Empire#1881|anti-Jewish riots]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/1132-alexander-iii-alexandrovich-emperor-of-russia|title=ALEXANDER III., ALEXANDROVICH, Emperor of Russia - JewishEncyclopedia.com|website=www.jewishencyclopedia.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://anno.onb.ac.at/cgi-content/annoshow?call=dib|18830607|1|100.0|0 &quot;Die Judenverfolgung in Rußland in der Krönungswoche&quot;] (in German), ''[[Das interessante Blatt]]'', 7 June 1883.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://timesmachine.nytimes.com/timesmachine/1883/06/01/102825816.pdf &quot;Rioting and Politics in Russia&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', 1 June 1883.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yivoencyclopedia.org/article.aspx/Pogroms|title=YIVO - Pogroms|website=www.yivoencyclopedia.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Alexander-Maria.jpg|thumb|Alexander and his wife [[Maria Feodorovna (Dagmar of Denmark)|Empress Maria Fyodorovna]] on holiday in [[Copenhagen]] in 1893]]

Alexander III disliked the extravagance of the rest of his family. It was also expensive for the Crown to pay so many grand dukes each year. Each one received an annual salary of 250,000 rubles, and grand duchesses received a dowry of a million when they married. He limited the title of grand duke and duchess to only children and male-line grandchildren of emperors. The rest would bear a princely title and the style of [[Serene Highness]]. He also forbade [[morganatic marriage]]s, as well as those outside of the Orthodoxy.&lt;ref&gt;Sebag Montefiore, p. 668&lt;/ref&gt;

===Domestic policies===
[[File:Alexander III reception by Repin.jpg|thumb|upright=1.3|left|Alexander receiving rural district elders in the yard of [[Petrovsky Palace]] in Moscow; painting by [[Ilya Repin]]]]

On the day of his assassination Alexander II had signed an [[ukaz]] setting up consultative commissions to advise the monarch. On ascending to the throne, however, Alexander III took Pobedonostsev's advice and cancelled the policy before its publication. He made it clear that his [[autocracy]] would not be limited.

All of Alexander III's internal reforms aimed to reverse the liberalization that had occurred in his father's reign. The new Emperor believed that remaining true to Russian [[Orthodoxy, Autocracy, and Nationality]] (the ideology introduced by his grandfather, emperor [[Nicholas I of Russia|Nicholas I]]) would save Russia from revolutionary agitation.{{citation needed|date=August 2019}}

Alexander weakened the power of the ''[[zemstvo]]'' (elective local administrative bodies) and placed the administration of peasant communes under the supervision of land-owning proprietors appointed by his government. These &quot;land captains&quot; (''zemskiye nachalniki'') were feared and resented throughout the Empire's peasant communities. These acts weakened the nobility and the peasantry and brought Imperial administration under the Emperor's personal control. In such policies Alexander III followed the advice of  [[Konstantin Pobedonostsev]], who retained control of the Church in Russia through his long tenure as Procurator of the Holy Synod (from 1880 to 1905) and who became tutor to Alexander's son and heir, Nicholas. (Pobedonostsev appears as &quot;Toporov&quot; in Tolstoy's novel ''Resurrection''.) Other conservative advisors included Count [[Dmitry Tolstoy|D. A. Tolstoy]] (minister of education, and later of internal affairs) and [[Ivan Durnovo|I. N. Durnovo]] (D. A. Tolstoy's successor in the latter post). [[Mikhail Katkov]] and other journalists supported the emperor in his autocracy.{{citation needed|date=August 2019}}
[[File:5 Roubles à l'effigie du Tsar d'Alexandre III, 1888.jpg|thumb|5-ruble coin of Alexander III, 1888]]
The [[Russian famine of 1891–92]], which caused 375,000 to 500,000 deaths, and the ensuing cholera epidemic permitted some liberal activity, as the Russian government could not cope with the crisis and had to allow zemstvos to help with relief (among others, [[Leo Tolstoy]] helped organize soup-kitchens, and [[Anton Chekhov|Chekhov]] directed anti-cholera precautions in several villages).

Alexander's political ideal was a nation composed of a single nationality, language, and religion, all under one form of administration. Through the teaching of the [[Russification|Russian language in Russian schools in Germany, Poland, and Finland]], the destruction of the remnants of German, Polish, and Swedish institutions in the respective provinces, and the patronization of [[Eastern Orthodox]]y, he attempted to realize this ideal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |last=Florinsky |first=Michael T. |encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Brittanica |title=Alexander III |url=https://www.britannica.com/biography/Alexander-III-emperor-of-Russia |access-date=2019-09-05 |date=2019-03-06 |publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica, inc.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Alexander was hostile to Jews; His reign witnessed a sharp deterioration in the Jews' economic, social, and political condition. His policy was eagerly implemented by tsarist officials in the &quot;[[May Laws]]&quot; of 1882.&lt;ref&gt;I. Michael Aronson,  &quot;The Attitudes of Russian Officials in the 1880s toward Jewish Assimilation and Emigration.&quot; ''Slavic Review'' 34.1 (1975): 1-18. [https://www.jstor.org/stable/2495871 online]&lt;/ref&gt; They banned Jews from inhabiting rural areas and [[shtetl]]s (even within the [[Pale of Settlement]]) and restricted the occupations in which they could engage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title =This day, May 15, in Jewish history|url= http://www.clevelandjewishnews.com/cjnconnect/blogs/article_057a78b4-3f44-5375-a20d-a850a62b2194.html|newspaper= Cleveland Jewish News}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;I. Michael Aronson,  &quot;The Prospects for the Emancipation of Russian Jewry during the 1880s.&quot; ''Slavonic and East European Review'' (1977): 348-369. [https://www.jstor.org/stable/4207496 online]&lt;/ref&gt;

Encouraged by its successful assassination of Alexander II, the [[Narodnaya Volya]] movement began planning the murder of Alexander III. The [[Okhrana]] uncovered the plot and five of the conspirators, including [[Alexander Ulyanov]], the older brother of [[Vladimir Lenin]], were captured and hanged in May 1887.

===Foreign policy===
[[File:Borki cathedral.jpg|thumb|The Borki Cathedral was one of many churches built to commemorate the Tsar's &quot;miraculous&quot; survival in the train crash.]]
{{Main|Foreign policy of the Russian Empire}}

The general negative consensus about the tsar's foreign policy follows the conclusions of the British Prime Minister Lord Salisbury in 1885:
:It is very difficult to come to any satisfactory conclusion as to the real objects of Russian policy. I am more inclined to believe there are none; that the Emperor is really his own Minister, and so bad a Minister that no consequent or coherent policy is pursued; but that each influential person, military or civil, snatches from him as opportunity offers the decisions which such person at the moment wants and that the mutual effect of these decisions on each other is determined almost exclusively by chance.&lt;ref&gt;Margaret Maxwell, &quot;A Re-examination of the Role of N. K. Giers as Russian Foreign Minister under Alexander III&quot; pp 352–53.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=S. C. M. Paine|title=Imperial Rivals: China, Russia, and Their Disputed Frontier|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=zMrx5Rw5n0AC&amp;pg=PA248|year=1996|page=248}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In foreign affairs Alexander III was a man of peace, but not at any price, and held that the best means of averting war is to be well-prepared for it. Diplomat [[Nikolay Girs]], scion of a rich and powerful family, served as his Foreign Minister from 1882 to 1895 and established the peaceful policies for which Alexander has been given credit. Girs was an architect of the [[Franco-Russian Alliance]] of 1891, which was later expanded into the [[Triple Entente]] with the addition of Great Britain. That alliance brought France out of diplomatic isolation, and moved Russia from the German orbit to a coalition with France, one that was strongly supported by French financial assistance to Russia's economic modernization. Girs was in charge of a diplomacy that featured numerous negotiated settlements, treaties and conventions. These agreements defined Russian boundaries and restored equilibrium to dangerously unstable situations. The most [[Panjdeh incident|dramatic success came in 1885]], settling [[The Great Game|long-standing tensions]] with Great Britain, which was fearful that Russian expansion to the South would be a threat to India.&lt;ref&gt;Raymond A. Mohl, &quot;Confrontation in Central Asia, 1885,&quot; ''History Today'' (1969) 119#3 pp 176-183.&lt;/ref&gt; Girs was usually successful in restraining the aggressive inclinations of Tsar Alexander convincing him that the very survival of the czarist system depended on avoiding major wars. With a deep insight into the tsar's moods and views, Girs was usually able to shape the final decisions by outmaneuvering hostile journalists, ministers, and even the czarina, as well as his own ambassadors. His Russia fought no wars.&lt;ref&gt;Margaret Maxwell,  &quot;A Re-examination of the Rôle of N.K. Giers as Russian Foreign Minister under Alexander III.&quot; ''European Studies Review'' 1.4 (1971): 351-376.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Russo-French alliance.jpg|thumb|left|180px|Alexander III and French President [[Marie François Sadi Carnot]] forge an alliance]]
Though Alexander was indignant at the conduct of German chancellor [[Otto von Bismarck]] towards Russia, he avoided an open rupture with Germany&amp;mdash;even reviving the [[League of Three Emperors]] for a period of time and in 1887, signed the [[Reinsurance Treaty]] with the Germans. However, in 1890, the expiration of the treaty coincided with the dismissal of Bismarck by the new German emperor, [[Kaiser Wilhelm II]] (for whom the Tsar had an immense dislike), and the unwillingness of Wilhelm II's government to renew the treaty. In response Alexander III then began cordial relations with France, eventually entering into an [[Franco-Russian Alliance|alliance]] with the French in 1892.&lt;ref&gt;Van Der Kiste, John ''The Romanovs: 1818–1959 ''(Sutton Publishing; 2003) p. 162&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite chilly relations with Berlin, the Tsar nevertheless confined himself to keeping a large number of troops near the German frontier. With regard to Bulgaria he exercised similar self-control. The efforts of [[Alexander, Prince of Bulgaria|Prince Alexander]] and afterwards of [[Stefan Stambolov|Stambolov]] to destroy Russian influence in the principality roused his indignation, but he vetoed all proposals to intervene by force of arms.&lt;ref&gt;Charles Jelavich, &quot;Russo-Bulgarian relations, 1892-1896: with particular reference to the problem of the bulgarian succession.&quot; ''Journal of Modern History'' 24.4 (1952): 341-351. [https://www.jstor.org/stable/2936115 Online]&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Central Asia]]n affairs he followed the traditional policy of gradually extending Russian domination without provoking conflict with the [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|United Kingdom]] (see [[Panjdeh Incident]]), and he never allowed the bellicose partisans of a forward policy to get out of hand. His reign cannot be regarded as an eventful period of [[History of Russia|Russian history]]; but under his hard rule the country made considerable progress.{{sfn|Wallace|1911|p=563}}

Alexander and his wife regularly spent their summers at [[Langinkoski]] manor near [[Kotka]] on the [[Finland|Finnish]] coast, where their children were immersed in a Scandinavian lifestyle of relative modesty.

Alexander deprecated foreign influence, German influence in particular, thus the adoption of local national principles was off in all spheres of official activity, with a view to realizing his ideal of a Russia homogeneous in language, administration and religion. These ideas conflicted with those of his father, who had German sympathies despite being a patriot; Alexander II often used the German language in his private relations, occasionally ridiculed the [[Slavophiles]] and based his foreign policy on the Prussian alliance.{{sfn|Wallace|1911|p=562}}
[[File:France-russe1896.jpg|thumb|Alexander III and Nicholas II on French stamps, c. 1896]]
Some differences between father and son had first appeared during the [[Franco-Prussian War]], when Alexander II supported the cabinet of [[Berlin]] while the [[Tsesarevich]] made no effort to conceal his sympathies for the French. These sentiments would resurface during 1875-1879, when the [[Eastern Question]] excited Russian society. At first the Tsesarevich was more Slavophile than the government, but his [[phlegmatic]] nature restrained him from many exaggerations, and any popular illusions he may have imbibed were dispelled by personal observation in [[Bulgaria]], where he commanded the left wing of the invading army. Never consulted on political questions, Alexander confined himself to military duties and fulfilled them in a conscientious and unobtrusive manner. After many mistakes and disappointments, the army reached [[Constantinople]] and the [[Treaty of San Stefano]] was signed, but much that had been obtained by that important document had to be sacrificed at the [[Congress of Berlin]].{{sfn|Wallace|1911|p=562}}

[[Otto von Bismarck|Bismarck]] failed to do what was expected of him by the Russian emperor. In return for the Russian support which had enabled him to create the [[German Empire]], {{Citation needed|date=June 2007}} it was thought that he would help Russia to solve the Eastern question in accordance with Russian interests, but to the surprise and indignation of the cabinet of Saint Petersburg he confined himself to acting the part of &quot;honest broker&quot; at the Congress, and shortly afterwards contracted an alliance with [[Austria-Hungary]] for the purpose of counteracting Russian designs in [[Eastern Europe]].{{sfn|Wallace|1911|p=562}}

The Tsesarevich could refer to these results as confirmation of the views he had expressed during the Franco-Prussian War; he concluded that for Russia, the best thing was to recover as quickly as possible from her temporary exhaustion, and prepare for future contingencies by military and naval reorganization. In accordance with this conviction, he suggested that certain reforms should be introduced.{{sfn|Wallace|1911|p=562}}

=== Family life ===
[[File:Tzar Alexander III and members of the Royal family.jpg|thumb|Left to Right: Emperor Alexander III, Prince George (later [[George V|George V of the United Kingdom]]), [[Maria Feodorovna (Dagmar of Denmark)|Marie Feodorovna]], [[Princess Maria of Greece and Denmark|Maria of Greece]], Tsesarevich Nicholas (Later Emperor [[Nicholas II of Russia]]). Probably taken on the imperial yacht near Denmark, {{c.}} 1893.]]

Following his father's assassination, Alexander III was advised that it would be difficult for him to be kept safe at the Winter Palace. As a result, Alexander relocated his family to the [[Gatchina Palace]], located twenty miles south of St. Petersburg, making it his primary residence. Under heavy guard he would make occasional visits into St. Petersburg, but even then he would stay in the [[Anichkov Palace]], as opposed to the Winter Palace.{{citation needed|date=August 2019}}

In the 1860s Alexander fell madly in love with his mother's lady-in-waiting, Princess Maria Elimovna Meshcherskaya. Dismayed to learn that Prince Wittgenstein had proposed to her in early 1866, he told his parents that he was prepared to give up his rights of succession in order to marry his beloved &quot;Dusenka&quot;. On 19 May 1866, Alexander II informed his son that Russia had come to an agreement with the parents of Princess Dagmar of Denmark, his fourth cousin. Before then, she had been the fiancée of his late elder brother Nicholas. At first Alexander refused to travel to Copenhagen, declaring that he did not love Dagmar and wanted to marry Maria. In response the enraged emperor ordered Alexander to go straight to Denmark and propose to Princess Dagmar. The Tsesarevich then realised that he was not a free man and that duty had to come first and foremost; the only thing left to do was to write in his diary &quot;Farewell, dear Dusenka.&quot; Maria was forced to leave Russia, accompanied by her aunt, Princess Chernyshova. Almost a year after her first appearance in Paris, [[Pavel Pavlovich Demidov, 2nd Prince of San Donato|Pavel Pavlovich Demidov, 2nd Prince di San Donato]], fell in love with her and the couple married in 1867. Maria would die giving birth to her son [[Elim Pavlovich Demidov, 3rd Prince of San Donato|Elim Pavlovich Demidov, 3rd Prince di San Donato]]. Alexander's reaction to the news of her death and the birth of her child is unknown.{{citation needed|date=August 2019}}

Alexander soon grew fond of Dagmar and had six children by her, five of whom survived into adulthood: [[Nicholas II of Russia|Nicholas]] (b. 1868), [[Grand Duke George Alexandrovich of Russia|George]] (b. 1871), [[Grand Duchess Xenia Alexandrovna of Russia|Xenia]] (b. 1875), [[Grand Duke Michael Alexandrovich of Russia|Michael]] (b. 1878) and [[Grand Duchess Olga Alexandrovna of Russia|Olga]] (b. 1882). Of his five surviving children, he was closest to his youngest two. In 1885 it was Alexander who commissioned [[Peter Carl Fabergé]] to produce the first of what were to become a series of jeweled Easter eggs (now called &quot;[[Fabergé egg]]s&quot;) for her as an Easter gift, the [[First Hen egg]], which delighted her immensely and became an annual Easter tradition for Alexander and, upon his succession, for his son Nicholas as well.{{citation needed|date=August 2019}}

[[File:Marble Palace (oriental frontage).jpg|thumb|left|The equestrian statue of Alexander III, by Prince [[Paolo Troubetzkoy]], shows the Emperor sitting heavily on the back of a ponderous horse]]

Each summer his parents-in-law, [[King Christian IX of Denmark|King Christian IX]] and [[Louise of Hesse-Kassel|Queen Louise]], held family reunions at the Danish royal palaces of [[Fredensborg Palace|Fredensborg]] and [[Bernstorff Palace|Bernstorff]], bringing Alexander, Maria and their children to Denmark.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;Van Der Kiste, John ''The Romanovs: 1818–1959 ''(Sutton Publishing, 2003), p. 151&lt;/ref&gt; His sister-in-law, the [[Queen Alexandra|Princess of Wales]], would come from Great Britain with some of her children, and his brother-in-law, [[King George I of Greece]], his wife, [[Queen Olga of Greece|Queen Olga]], who was a first cousin of Alexander and a Romanov Grand Duchess by birth, came with their children from Athens.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; In contrast to the strict security observed in Russia, Alexander and Maria revelled in the relative freedom that they enjoyed in Denmark, Alexander once commenting to the Prince and Princess of Wales near the end of a visit that he envied them being able to return to a happy home in England, while he was returning to his Russian prison.&lt;ref name=&quot;Van Der Kiste, p. 152&quot;&gt;Van Der Kiste, p. 152&lt;/ref&gt; In Denmark, he was able to enjoy joining his children in muddy ponds looking for tadpoles, sneaking into his father-in-law's orchard to steal apples, and playing pranks, such as turning a water hose on the visiting [[Oscar II of Sweden|King Oscar II of Sweden]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Van Der Kiste, p. 152&quot;/&gt;

As Tsesarevich&amp;mdash;and then as Tsar&amp;mdash;Alexander had an extremely poor relationship with his brother [[Grand Duke Vladimir Alexandrovich of Russia|Grand Duke Vladimir]]. This tension was reflected in the rivalry between Maria Feodorovna and Vladimir's wife, [[Marie of Mecklenburg-Schwerin (Maria Pavlovna of Russia)|Grand Duchess Marie Pavlovna]].&lt;ref&gt;Van Der Kiste, p. 141&lt;/ref&gt; Alexander had better relationships with his other brothers: [[Grand Duke Alexei Alexandrovich of Russia|Alexei]] (whom he made rear admiral and then a grand admiral of the Russian Navy), [[Grand Duke Sergei Alexandrovich of Russia|Sergei]] (whom he made governor of Moscow) and [[Grand Duke Paul Alexandrovich of Russia|Paul]].

Despite the antipathy that Alexander had towards his stepmother, [[Catherine Dolgorukov|Princess Catherine Dolgorukov]], he nevertheless allowed her to remain in the Winter Palace for some time after his father's assassination and to retain various keepsakes of him. These included Alexander II's blood-soaked uniform that he died wearing, and his reading glasses.&lt;ref&gt;
Van Der Kiste, p. 118&lt;/ref&gt;

On {{OldStyleDate|29 October|1888|17 October}} the Imperial train [[derailment|derailed]] in an [[Borki train disaster|accident]] at [[Borki, Kharkiv Oblast|Borki]]. At the moment of the crash, the imperial family was in the dining car. Its roof collapsed, and Alexander held its remains on his shoulders as the children fled outdoors. The onset of Alexander's kidney failure was later attributed to the blunt trauma suffered in this incident.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.alexanderpalace.org/palace/alexbio.html|title=Diaries and Letters - Alexander III|author=Scott Malsom|work=Alexander Palace Time Machine|access-date=1 February 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Illness and death==
[[File:Valentin Serov - Alexander III in Danish Royal Life Guards Uniform.jpg|thumb|Alexander III in the uniform of the Danish Royal Life Guards, 1894]]
In 1894, Alexander III became ill with terminal kidney disease ([[nephritis]]). Maria Fyodorovna's sister-in-law, Queen Olga of Greece, offered her villa of [[Mon Repos, Corfu|Mon Repos]], on the island of [[Corfu]], in the hope that it might improve the Tsar's condition.&lt;ref&gt;King, Greg ''The Court of the Last Tsar: Pomp, Power and Pageantry in the Reign of Nicholas II ''(John Wiley &amp; Sons, 2006) p. 325&lt;/ref&gt; By the time that they reached [[Crimean Peninsula|Crimea]], they stayed at the Maly Palace in [[Livadia Palace|Livadia]], as Alexander was too weak to travel any further.&lt;ref&gt;King, p. 325&lt;/ref&gt; Recognizing that the Tsar's days were numbered, various imperial relatives began to descend on Livadia. Even the famed clergyman [[John of Kronstadt]] paid a visit and administered Communion to the Tsar.&lt;ref&gt;John Perry &amp; Constantine Pleshakov ''The Flight of the Romanovs: a Family Saga ''(Basic Books, 1999) p. 62&lt;/ref&gt; On 21 October, Alexander received Nicholas's fiancée, Princess Alix, who had come from her native Darmstadt to receive the Tsar's blessing.&lt;ref&gt;King, p. 326&lt;/ref&gt; Despite being exceedingly weak, Alexander insisted on receiving Alix in full dress uniform, an event that left him exhausted.&lt;ref&gt;King, p. 327&lt;/ref&gt; Soon after, his health began to deteriorate more rapidly. He died in the arms of his wife, and in the presence of his physician, [[Ernst Viktor von Leyden]], at Maly Palace in Livadia on the afternoon of {{OldStyleDate|1 November|1894|20 October}} at the age of forty-nine, and was succeeded by his eldest son Tsesarevich Nicholas, who took the throne as [[Nicholas II of Russia|Nicholas II]]. After leaving Livadia on 6 November and traveling to St. Petersburg by way of Moscow, his remains were interred on 18 November at the [[Peter and Paul Fortress]].

==Issue==
[[File:1888. Семья императора Александра III.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Alexander III with his wife and their children]]

Alexander III had six children (five of whom survived to adulthood) of his marriage with [[Maria Feodorovna (Dagmar of Denmark)|Princess Dagmar of Denmark]], also known as Marie Feodorovna.

(Note: all dates prior to 1918 are in the [[Old Style]] Calendar)

{| border=1 style=&quot;border-collapse: collapse;&quot;
|- bgcolor=cccccc
!Name!!Birth!!Death!!Notes
|-
|[[Nicholas II of Russia|Emperor Nicholas II of Russia]]&lt;!-- (Last Czar of Russia) --&gt;||18 May 1868||17 July 1918||married 26 November 1894, [[Alexandra Feodorovna (Alix of Hesse)|Princess Alix of Hesse]] (1872–1918); had five children
|-
|[[Grand Duke Alexander Alexandrovich of Russia]]||7 June 1869||2 May 1870||died of [[meningitis]], aged 10 months and 26 days
|-
|[[Grand Duke George Alexandrovich of Russia]]||9 May 1871||9 August 1899||died of [[tuberculosis]], aged 28; had no issue
|-
|[[Grand Duchess Xenia Alexandrovna of Russia]]||6 April 1875||20 April 1960||married 6 August 1894, [[Grand Duke Alexander Mikhailovich of Russia]] (1866–1933); sep. 11 April 1919; had seven children
|-
|[[Grand Duke Michael Alexandrovich of Russia]]||4 December 1878||13 June 1918||married 16 October 1912, [[Natalia Brasova|Natalia Sergeyevna Wulfert]] (1880–1952); had one child
|-
|[[Grand Duchess Olga Alexandrovna of Russia]]||13 June 1882||24 November 1960||married 9 August 1901, [[Duke Peter Alexandrovich of Oldenburg]] (1868–1924); div. 16 October 1916; had no issue.
married 16 November 1916, [[Nikolai Kulikovsky|Colonel Nikolai Kulikovsky]] (1881–1958); had two children
|}

==Ancestors==
{{ahnentafel
| collapsed=yes |align=center
| boxstyle_1=background-color: #fcc;
| boxstyle_2=background-color: #fb9;
| boxstyle_3=background-color: #ffc;
| boxstyle_4=background-color: #bfc;
| boxstyle_5=background-color: #9fe;
| 1= 1. '''Alexander III of Russia'''
| 2= 2. [[Alexander II of Russia]]
| 3= 3. [[Maria Alexandrovna (Marie of Hesse)|Princess Marie of Hesse and by Rhine]]
| 4= 4. [[Nicholas I of Russia]]
| 5= 5. [[Alexandra Feodorovna (Charlotte of Prussia)|Princess Charlotte of Prussia]]
| 6= 6. [[Louis II, Grand Duke of Hesse|Louis II, Grand Duke of Hesse and by Rhine]]
| 7= 7. [[Princess Wilhelmine of Baden]]
| 8= 8. [[Paul I of Russia]]
| 9= 9. [[Maria Feodorovna (Sophie Dorothea of Württemberg)|Duchess Sophie Dorothea of Württemburg]]
| 10= 10. [[Frederick William III of Prussia]] 
| 11= 11. [[Louise of Mecklenburg-Strelitz|Duchess Louise of Mecklenburg-Strelitz]] 
| 12= 12. [[Louis I, Grand Duke of Hesse|Louis I, Grand Duke of Hesse and by Rhine]]
| 13= 13. [[Princess Louise of Hesse-Darmstadt (1761–1829)|Princess Louise of Hesse-Darmstadt]]
| 14= 14. [[Charles Louis, Hereditary Prince of Baden]]
| 15= 15. [[Princess Amalie of Hesse-Darmstadt]]
}}

==Monuments==
[[File:The monument of Russian Emperor Alexander III.jpg|thumb|left|Memorial dedicated to Alexander III in Pullapää, [[Estonia]]]]
In 1909, a bronze [[equestrian statue]] of Alexander III sculpted by [[Paolo Troubetzkoy]] was placed in [[Znamenskaya Square]] in front of the [[Moskovsky Rail Terminal (Saint Petersburg)|Moscow Rail Terminal]] in [[St. Petersburg]]. Both the horse and rider were sculpted in massive form, leading to the nickname of &quot;hippopotamus&quot;. Troubetzkoy envisioned the statue as a [[caricature]], jesting that he wished &quot;to portray an animal atop another animal&quot;, and it was quite controversial at the time, with many, including the members of the Imperial Family, opposed to the design, but it was approved because the [[Maria Feodorovna (Dagmar of Denmark)|Empress Dowager]] unexpectedly liked the monument. Following the Revolution of 1917 the statue remained in place as a symbol of tsarist autocracy until 1937 when it was placed in storage. In 1994 it was again put on public display, in front of the [[Marble Palace]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Orlando|last=Figes|page=15|title=A People's Tragedy|ISBN=0-7126-7327-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Another memorial is located in the city of [[Irkutsk]] at the [[Angara River|Angara]] embankment.

On 18 November 2017, Vladimir Putin unveiled a bronze monument to Alexander III on the site of the former Maly Livadia Palace in Crimea. The four-meter monument by Russian sculptor [[Andrey Kovalchuk]] depicts Alexander III sitting on a stump, his stretched arms resting on a sabre. An inscription repeats his alleged saying “''Russia has only two allies: the Army and the Navy.''”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://tass.com/society/976333|title=Putin unveils monument to Russia’s Tsar Alexander III in Crimea |date=18 November 2017 |work= |publisher=TASS |accessdate=19 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Titles, styles, honours and arms==
{{infobox hrhstyles
| royal name=Alexander III of Russia
| dipstyle=[[His Imperial Majesty]]
| offstyle=Your Imperial Majesty
| altstyle=Sir
| image=Coat of Arms of Russian Empire.svg
| image_size=75}}

===Titles and styles===
* '''10 March 1845{{snd}}2 March 1865''': ''His Imperial Highness'' Grand Duke Alexander Alexandrovich of Russia
* '''2 March 1865{{snd}}13 March 1881''': ''His Imperial Highness'' The Tsesarevich of Russia
* '''13 March 1881{{snd}}1 November 1894''': ''His Imperial Majesty'' The Emperor and Autocrat of All the Russias

===Honours===
;Domestic&lt;ref name=&quot;Army&quot;&gt;[http://regiment.ru/bio/A/3.htm Russian Imperial Army - Emperor Alexander III of Russia] (In Russian)&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Order of St. Andrew|Order of St. Andrew the Apostle the First-called]], Knight, ''10 March 1845''
* [[Order of St. Alexander Nevsky]], Knight, ''10 March 1845''
* [[Order of St. Anna]], Knight 1st Class, ''10 March 1845''
* [[Order of the White Eagle (Russian Empire)|Order of the White Eagle]], Knight, ''10 March 1845''
* [[Order of St. Vladimir]], Knight 4th Class, ''1864''; 3rd Class, ''1870''
* [[Order of Saint Stanislaus (Imperial House of Romanov)|Order of St. Stanislaus]], Knight 1st Class, ''1865''
* [[Order of St. George]], 2nd Class, ''1877''

;Foreign&lt;ref name=&quot;Army&quot;/&gt;
{{columns-list|colwidth=25em|
* {{flagcountry|Austrian Empire}}: [[Order of St. Stephen of Hungary|Royal Hungarian Order of St. Stephen]], Grand Cross, ''1866''&lt;ref&gt;[http://tornai.com/rendtagok.htm &quot;A Szent István Rend tagjai&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101222022855/http://tornai.com/rendtagok.htm|date=22 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Bavaria}}: [[Order of St. Hubert]], Knight, ''1865''&lt;ref name=&quot;Bayern1867&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Bayern|title=Hof- und Staatshandbuch des Königreichs Bayern: 1867|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=nTBRAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA10|year=1867|publisher=Landesamt|page=10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Belgium}}: [[Order of Leopold (Belgium)|Royal Order of Leopold]], Grand Cordon, ''11 June 1865''
* {{flagcountry|Empire of Brazil}}:
** [[Order of the Southern Cross]], Grand Cross, ''14 January 1866''
** [[Order of Pedro I]], Grand Cross, ''15 September 1868''
* {{flag|Denmark}}:&lt;ref name=&quot;DanskStatskalender&quot;&gt;{{cite book |year=1880 |orig-year=1st pub.:1801 |editor1-last=Bille-Hansen |editor1-first=A. C. |editor2-last=Holck |editor2-first=Harald |title=Statshaandbog for Kongeriget Danmark for Aaret 1880 |trans-title=State Manual of the Kingdom of Denmark for the Year 1880 |url=https://dis-danmark.dk/bibliotek/910093.pdf |format=PDF |series=Kongelig Dansk Hof- og Statskalender |language=da |location=Copenhagen |publisher=J.H. Schultz A.-S. Universitetsbogtrykkeri |page=4 |access-date=16 September 2019 |via=[[:da:DIS Danmark]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Order of the Elephant]], Knight, ''29 June 1865''
** [[Cross of Honour of the Order of the Dannebrog]], ''3 July 1866''
* {{Flagicon|Saxe-Coburg and Gotha}} {{flagicon|Saxe-Altenburg}} {{flagicon|Saxe-Meiningen}} [[Ernestine duchies]]: [[Saxe-Ernestine House Order]], Grand Cross, ''1884''&lt;ref&gt;''[https://zs.thulb.uni-jena.de/rsc/viewer/jportal_derivate_00243753/Sachsen_Coburg_Gotha_166999342_1890_0057.tif?logicalDiv=jportal_jparticle_00484309 Staatshandbücher für das Herzogtum Sachsen-Coburg und Gotha]'' (1890), &quot;Herzogliche Sachsen-Ernestinischer Hausorden&quot; p. 46&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagcountry|French Third Republic}}: [[Légion d'Honneur]], Grand Cross, ''9 June 1878''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| author = M. &amp; B. Wattel. | chapter = | chapter-url = | format = | url =  | title = Les Grand'Croix de la Légion d'honneur de 1805 à nos jours. Titulaires français et étrangers | orig-year = | agency =  | edition =   |location= Paris |date = 2009 |publisher= Archives &amp; Culture |at=  |volume=  | pages = | page = 516 | series =  | isbn = 978-2-35077-135-9| ref = M. et B. Wattel}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|Greece|royal}} [[Kingdom of Greece|Greece]]: [[Order of the Redeemer]], Grand Cross, ''15 July 1866''
* {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Hanover}}:
** [[Order of St. George (Hanover)|Order of St. George]], Knight, ''1865''&lt;ref&gt;''Hof- und Staats-Handbuch des Königreich Hannover'' (1865), &quot;Königliche Orden und Ehrenzeichen&quot; p. 38&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Royal Guelphic Order]], Grand Cross, ''16 May 1865''
* {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Hawaii}}: [[Royal Order of Kamehameha I (decoration)|Order of Kamehameha]], Grand Cross, ''1881''&lt;ref&gt;Kalakaua to his sister, 12 July 1881, quoted in Greer, Richard A. (editor, 1967) &quot;[https://evols.library.manoa.hawaii.edu/bitstream/10524/186/JL05085.pdf The Royal Tourist—Kalakaua's Letters Home from Tokio to London]&quot;, ''Hawaiian Journal of History'', vol. 5, p. 96&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon image|Flagge Großherzogtum Hessen ohne Wappen.svg}} [[Hesse and by Rhine]]: [[Ludwig Order]], Grand Cross, ''8 June 1857''&lt;ref&gt;''Hof- und Staats-Handbuch des Großherzogtum Hessen'' (1879), &quot;Großherzogliche Orden und Ehrenzeichen&quot; [https://archive.org/details/hofundstaatshan00gergoog/page/n36 p. 11]&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Italy}}: [[Supreme Order of the Most Holy Annunciation|Order of the Annunciation]], Knight, ''5 July 1865''&lt;ref&gt;''Calendario reale per l'anno 1887'', Vincenzo Bona, Torino, 1886, p. 136.&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Sovereign Military Order of Malta}}: Bailiff Grand Cross of Honour and Devotion, ''12 January 1876''
* {{flagcountry|Empire of Japan}}: [[Order of the Rising Sun]], Grand Cordon, ''28 August 1879''
* {{Flagicon image|Flagge Großherzogtümer Mecklenburg.svg}} [[Mecklenburg]]:
** [[House Order of the Wendish Crown]], Grand Cross with Crown in Ore, ''1865''&lt;ref&gt;Corston, Daniel [https://mecklenburg-strelitz.org/the-house/order-of-the-wendish-crown/ mecklenburg-strelitz.org] &quot;Unofficial website dedicated to the Grand Ducal House of Mecklenburg-Strelitz&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
** Order for Distinction in War ([[Grand Duchy of Mecklenburg-Schwerin|Mecklenburg-Schwerin]]), ''3 December 1877''
* {{flagcountry|Second Mexican Empire}}: [[Mexican Imperial Orders#Order of the Mexican Eagle|Order of the Mexican Eagle]], Grand Cross, ''10 April 1866''
* {{flagcountry|Principality of Montenegro}}: [[Order of Danilo I]], Grand Cross, ''4 January 1867''
* {{flag|Netherlands}}: [[Order of the Netherlands Lion]], Grand Cross, ''19 May 1865''
* {{flag|Ottoman Empire}}:
** [[Order of Osmanieh]], 1st Class, ''1 April 1866''
** [[Order of Distinction (Ottoman Empire)|Order of Distinction]], ''3 December 1884''
* {{flagicon image|Amir Kabir Flag.svg}} [[Qajar Iran|Persia]]: Order of the August Portrait, ''15 December 1869''
* {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Portugal|1830}}:
** [[Order of the Tower and Sword]], Grand Cross, ''14 August 1865''&lt;ref name = &quot;TowerAndSword&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://geneall.net/en/title/25080/grand-crosses-of-the-order-of-the-tower-and-sword/|title=Grand Crosses of the Order of the Tower and Sword|website=geneall.net}} Retrieved 2018-08-09.&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Sash of the Two Orders|United Orders]] of [[Order of Christ (Portugal)|Christ]] and [[Order of Aviz|Aviz]], Grand Cross, ''19 August 1873''
* {{flagicon image|Flag of the Kingdom of Prussia (1803-1892).svg}} [[Kingdom of Prussia|Prussia]]:
** [[Order of the Black Eagle]], Knight, ''27 July 1857''&lt;ref name=&quot;p87&quot;&gt;Justus Perthes, ''Almanach de Gotha'' (1894) [https://archive.org/details/almanachdegotha00unse_73/page/n121 p. 87]&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Pour le Mérite]], ''3 December 1877''
* {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Romania}}:
** [[Order of the Star of Romania]], Grand Cross, ''15 November 1877''
** [[Military Virtue Medal]], ''17 January 1878''
** Crossing of the Danube Medal, ''10 May 1879''
* {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Saxony}}: [[Order of the Rue Crown]], Knight, ''1866''&lt;ref&gt;''Staatshandbuch für den Freistaat Sachsen (1867)'' (in German), &quot;Königliche Ritter-Orden&quot;, p. 4&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Saxe-Weimar-Eisenach}}: [[Order of the White Falcon]], Grand Cross, ''1865''&lt;ref&gt;''[https://zs.thulb.uni-jena.de/rsc/viewer/jportal_derivate_00184031/Staatshandbuch_Film_Nr_15_0241.tif Staatshandbuch für das Großherzogtum Sachsen / Sachsen-Weimar-Eisenach]'' (1891), &quot;Großherzogliche Hausorden&quot; p. 15&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[File:Flag of Serbia (1835-1882).svg|25px]] [[Principality of Serbia|Serbia]]:
** [[Order of the Cross of Takovo]], Grand Cross, ''26 March 1878''
** Bronze Medal Commemorating the Russo-Turkish War, ''17 April 1878''
** [[Order of the White Eagle (Serbia)|Royal Order of the White Eagle]], Grand Cross, ''29 April 1883''
* {{Flagicon|Thailand|1855}} [[Siam]]: [[Order of the Royal House of Chakri]], Knight, ''15 July 1891''
* {{flag|Spain|1785}}: [[Order of the Golden Fleece]], Knight, ''6 September 1865''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite publication|url=http://hemerotecadigital.bne.es/issue.vm?id=0000941464&amp;search=&amp;lang=es|chapter=Caballeros de la insigne orden del toisón de oro|title=Guía Oficial de España|last=|first=|date=1887|journal=|accessdate=21 March 2019|page=146|doi=|pmid=|language=es}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|Sweden|1844}} {{flagicon|Norway|1844}} [[Sweden-Norway]]:
** [[Order of the Seraphim]], Knight, ''2 June 1865''&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Sveriges och Norges Statskalender |year=1866|page=435|url=http://runeberg.org/sonkal/1866/0471.html|via=runeberg.org|accessdate=2019-02-20|language=sv}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Order of St. Olav]], Grand Cross, ''25 August 1879''&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Norges Statskalender |year=1890|page=595|url=http://runeberg.org/norkal/1890/0356.html|via=runeberg.org|accessdate=2018-01-06|language=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagcountry|United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland}}: [[Order of the Garter]], Knight, ''2 April 1881''&lt;ref name=p60&gt;Shaw, Wm. A. (1906) ''The Knights of England'', '''I''', London, [https://archive.org/stream/cu31924092537418#page/n155/mode/2up p. 66]&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Württemberg}}:
** [[Military Merit Order (Württemberg)|Military Merit Order]], Knight, ''25 December 1850''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Württemberg|title=Königlich-Württembergisches Hof- und Staats-Handbuch: 1854|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3VsAAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA63|year=1854|publisher=Guttenberg|page=63}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Order of the Crown (Württemberg)|Order of the Württemberg Crown]], Grand Cross, ''1864''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Hof- und Staats-Handbuch des Königreichs Württemberg: 1866|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=R1wAAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA31|year=1866|page=31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

===Arms===
[[File:Lesser CoA of the empire of Russia.svg|230px|center|thumb|Lesser Coat of Arms of the Empire of Russia]]

==See also==
* [[Tsars of Russia family tree]]

==References==

{{reflist}}
* {{EB1911|wstitle=Alexander III. (tsar)|display=Alexander III.|volume=1|pages=561-563|first=Donald Mackenzie|last=Wallace|authorlink=Donald Mackenzie Wallace}}

==Bibliography==
* Dorpalen, Andreas. &quot;Tsar Alexander III and the Boulanger Crisis in France.&quot; ''Journal of Modern History'' 23.2 (1951): 122-136. [https://www.jstor.org/stable/1872056 online]
* Etty, John. &quot;Alexander III, Tsar of Russia 1881-1889.&quot; ''History Review'' 60 (2008): 1-5. [https://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;pid=sites&amp;srcid=ZGVmYXVsdGRvbWFpbnxpYmhpc3RvcnlydXNzaWF8Z3g6N2I4ZmVlMzkwM2RkNzU5ZQ online]
* Hutchinson, John F. ''Late Imperial Russia: 1890–1917''
* Lincoln, W. Bruce. ''The Romanovs : autocrats of all the Russias'' (1981) [https://archive.org/details/romanovsautocr00linc online free to borrow]
* Lowe, Charles.  ''Alexander III of Russia'' (1895) [https://archive.org/details/cu31924068919814 online free] full-length old biography
* Polunov, A. Iu. &quot;Konstantin Petrovich Pobedonostsev—Man and Politician&quot;. ''Russian Studies in History'' 39.4 (2001): 8-32. [http://www.academia.edu/download/31220668/Pobed.pdf online], by a leading scholar
*Polunov, A. Iu. &quot;The Orthodox Church in the Baltic Region and the Policies of Alexander Ill's Government.&quot; ''Russian Studies in History'' 39.4 (2001): 66-76. [http://www.academia.edu/download/31220675/Baltic.pdf online]
* Suny,  Ronald Grigor.  &quot;Rehabilitating Tsarism: The Imperial Russian State and Its Historians. A Review Article&quot; '' Comparative Studies in Society and History'' 31#1 (1989)  pp.&amp;nbsp;168–179 [https://www.jstor.org/stable/178799 online]
* Thomson, Oliver. ''Romanovs: Europe's Most Obsessive Dynasty'' (2008) ch 13
* Whelan, Heide W. ''Alexander III &amp; the State Council: bureaucracy &amp; counter-reform in late imperial Russia'' (Rutgers UP, 1982).

==External links==
{{Commons category|Alexander III of Russia}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20170503063351/http://diaryrh.ru/historical-photos/alexander-iii/ Alexander III. Historical photos.]
* [http://www.alexanderpalace.org/palace/alexbio.html A short biography]
*{{YouTube|zM297O4V6Sg|Romanovs. The eighth film. Alexander III; Nicholas II.}} – Historical reconstruction &quot;The Romanovs&quot;. StarMedia. Babich-Design(Russia, 2013)

{{s-start}}
{{S-hou|[[House of Romanov|House of Holstein-Gottorp-Romanov]]|10 March|1845|1 November|1894|[[House of Oldenburg]] }}
{{S-reg}}
{{S-bef|before=[[Alexander II of Russia|Alexander II]]}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[Emperor of Russia]]&lt;br&gt;[[Grand Duke of Finland]]|years=1881–1894}}
{{S-aft|after=[[Nicholas II of Russia|Nicholas II]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{Russian emperors}}
{{Russian tsareviches}}
{{Russian grand dukes}}
{{Russification}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2011}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Alexander 03 Of Russia}}
[[Category:1845 births]]
[[Category:1894 deaths]]
[[Category:19th-century Russian monarchs]]
[[Category:19th-century Polish monarchs]]
[[Category:People from Saint Petersburg]]
[[Category:People from Saint Petersburg Governorate]]
[[Category:Rulers of Finland]]
[[Category:House of Holstein-Gottorp-Romanov]]
[[Category:Eastern Orthodox monarchs]]
[[Category:Russian military personnel of the Russo-Turkish War (1877–78)]]
[[Category:Russian grand dukes]]
[[Category:19th-century monarchs in Europe]]
[[Category:Knights of Malta]]
[[Category:Knights of the Golden Fleece]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of the Black Eagle]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Bravery]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Royal Order of Kamehameha I]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of St. George of the Second Degree]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of St. Andrew]]
[[Category:Grand Crosses of the House Order of the Wendish Crown]]
[[Category:Knights Grand Cross of the Military Order of William]]
[[Category:Extra Knights Companion of the Garter]]
[[Category:Grand Commanders of the Order of the Dannebrog]]
[[Category:Deaths from nephritis]]
[[Category:Burials at Peter and Paul Cathedral]]
[[Category:Alexander III of Russia]]
[[Category:Failed assassination attempts]]
[[Category:Tsesarevichs of Russia]]</text>
      <sha1>dxy2aitogd2kq3szzc8t5doot4r69d6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
