  <page>
    <title>Ajax the Great</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1568</id>
    <revision>
      <id>926060753</id>
      <parentid>913716254</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-11-14T00:38:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Move 1 url. [[User:GreenC/WaybackMedic_2.5|Wayback Medic 2.5]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Aias|other uses|AIAS (disambiguation)|and|Ajax (disambiguation)}}
[[File:(11) Flaxman Ilias 1795, Zeichnung 1793, 186 x 283 mm.jpg|thumb|Ajax battling Hektor, engraving by [[John Flaxman]], 1795]]
{{Trojan War}}

'''Ajax''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|eɪ|dʒ|æ|k|s}}) or '''Aias''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|aɪ|.|ə|s}}; {{lang-grc|Αἴας|Aíās}} {{IPA-grc|aí̯.aːs|}}, {{abbr|gen.|genitive}} {{lang|grc|Αἴαντος}} ''Aíantos''; [[Archaic Greek alphabets|archaic]] {{lang|grc|ΑΣϜΑϺ}} {{IPA-grc|aí̯.waːs|}}){{efn|Inscription on the so-called [[:File:The Suicide of Ajax.svg|Eurytios Krater]], a Corinthian black-figured column-krater dated ca. 600 BC, using the [[Archaic Greek alphabets#Corinthian|Corinthian iota]] shaped like Σ.}} is a [[Greek mythology|Greek mythological]] [[Greek hero cult|hero]], the son of King [[Telamon]] and [[Periboea]], and the half-brother of [[Teucer]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.salamina.gr/english/index.htm &quot;Salamis The Island&quot;] ''Salamis The Island&amp;nbsp;– Salamina Municipality&amp;nbsp;– Greek Island''&lt;/ref&gt; He plays an important role, and is portrayed as a towering figure and a warrior of great courage in [[Homer]]'s ''[[Iliad]]'' and in the [[Epic Cycle]], a series of [[epic poems]] about the [[Trojan War]]. He is also referred to as &quot;'''Telamonian Ajax'''&quot; ({{lang|grc|Αἴας ὁ Τελαμώνιος}}, in [[Etruscan language|Etruscan]] recorded as ''Aivas Tlamunus''), &quot;'''Greater Ajax'''&quot;, or &quot;'''Ajax the Great'''&quot;, which distinguishes him from Ajax, son of Oileus ([[Ajax the Lesser]]).

==Family==
Ajax is the son of [[Telamon]], who was the son of [[Aeacus]] and grandson of [[Zeus]], and his first wife Periboea. He is the cousin of [[Achilles]], and is the elder [[Sibling|half-brother]] of [[Teucer]]. His given name is derived from the root of {{lang|grc|αἰάζω}} &quot;to lament&quot;, translating to &quot;one who laments; mourner&quot;. Hesiod, however includes a story in &quot;The Great Eoiae&quot; that indicates Aias received his name when Heracles prayed to Zeus that a son might be born to Telemon and Eriboea. Zeus sent an eagle (aietos - αετός) as a sign. Heracles then bade the parents call their son Aias after the eagle. Many illustrious [[Athenians]], including [[Cimon]], [[Miltiades the Younger|Miltiades]], [[Alcibiades]] and the historian [[Thucydides]], traced their descent from Ajax. On an Etruscan tomb dedicated to Racvi Satlnei in Bologna (5th century BC) there is an inscription that says, ''aivastelmunsl'' which means &quot;[family] of Telamonian Ajax&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Papachristos, Maria. ''Miti e Leggende. Volume 5 of Miti e Leggende dell'antica Grecia''. Edizioni R.E.I. (2015). {{ISBN|9782372971621}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Description==
[[File:The Belvedere Torso depicting Ajax.jpg|thumb|The [[Belvedere Torso]], a marble sculpture carved in the first Century BC depicting Ajax.]]
In Homer's ''Iliad'' he is described as of great stature, colossal frame and strongest of all the [[Achaeans (Homer)|Achaeans]]. Known as the &quot;bulwark of the Achaeans&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Homer, ''Iliad'' [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Hom.+Il.+6.5 6.5].&lt;/ref&gt; he was trained by the [[centaur]] [[Chiron]] (who had trained Ajax's father Telamon and Achilles's father [[Peleus]] and would later die of an accidental wound inflicted by [[Heracles]], whom he was at the time training), at the same time as Achilles. He was described as fearless, strong and powerful but also with a very high level of combat intelligence. Ajax commands his army wielding a huge shield made of seven cow-hides with a layer of bronze. Most notably, Ajax is not wounded in any of the battles described in the ''Iliad'', and he is the only principal character on either side who does not receive substantial assistance from any of the gods (except for Agamemnon) who take part in the battles, although, in book 13, Poseidon strikes Ajax with his staff, renewing his strength. Unlike [[Diomedes]], [[Agamemnon]], and [[Achilles]], Ajax appears as a mainly defensive warrior, instrumental in the defence of the Greek camp and ships and that of [[Patroclus]]' body. When the Trojans are on the offensive, he is often seen covering the retreat of the Achaeans. Significantly, while one of the deadliest heroes in the whole poem, Ajax has no [[aristeia]] depicting him on the offensive.

===Trojan War===
In the ''Iliad'', Ajax is notable for his abundant strength and courage, seen particularly in two fights with [[Hector]]. In Book 7, Ajax is chosen by lot to meet Hector in a duel which lasts most of a whole day. Ajax at first gets the better of the encounter, wounding Hector with his spear and knocking him down with a large stone,&lt;ref&gt;''[[Iliad]]'', 7.268–272.&lt;/ref&gt; but Hector fights on until the [[herald]]s, acting at the direction of Zeus, call a draw, with the two combatants exchanging gifts, Ajax giving Hector a purple sash and Hector giving Ajax his sharp sword.

The second fight between Ajax and Hector occurs when the latter breaks into the Mycenaean camp, and fights with the Greeks among the ships. In Book 14, Ajax throws a giant rock at Hector which almost kills him.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Iliad]]'', 14.408–417.&lt;/ref&gt; In Book 15, Hector is restored to his strength by [[Apollo]] and returns to attack the ships. Ajax, wielding an enormous spear as a weapon and leaping from ship to ship, holds off the [[Troy|Trojan]] armies virtually single-handedly. In Book 16, Hector and Ajax duel once again.  Hector then disarms Ajax (although Ajax is not hurt) and Ajax is forced to retreat, seeing that Zeus is clearly favoring Hector. Hector and the Trojans succeed in burning one Greek ship, the culmination of an assault that almost finishes the war. Ajax is responsible for the death of many Trojan lords, including [[Phorcys (Trojan War)|Phorcys]].

Ajax often fought in tandem with his brother Teucer, known for his skill with the bow.  Ajax would wield his magnificent shield, as Teucer stood behind picking off enemy Trojans.

Achilles was absent during these encounters because of his feud with Agamemnon. In Book 9, Agamemnon and the other Mycenaean chiefs send Ajax, [[Odysseus]] and [[Phoenix (son of Amyntor)|Phoenix]] to the tent of Achilles in an attempt to reconcile with the great warrior and induce him to return to the fight. Although Ajax speaks earnestly and is well received, he does not succeed in convincing Achilles.

When Patroclus is killed, Hector tries to steal his body. Ajax, assisted by [[Menelaus]], succeeds in fighting off the Trojans and taking the body back with his chariot; however, the Trojans have already stripped Patroclus of Achilles' armor. Ajax's prayer to Zeus to remove the fog that has descended on the battle to allow them to fight or die in the light of day has become proverbial.  According to [[Hyginus]], in total, Ajax killed 28 people at Troy.&lt;ref&gt;Hyginus, ''[[Fabulae]]'' [http://www.theoi.com/Text/HyginusFabulae3.html 114].&lt;/ref&gt;

====Death====
[[File:Ajax (Carstens).jpg|thumb|''Sorrowful Ajax'' (Asmus Jacob Carstens, ca. 1791)]]
As the ''Iliad'' comes to a close, Ajax and the majority of other Greek warriors are alive and well. When Achilles dies, killed by [[Paris (mythology)|Paris]] (with help from Apollo), Ajax and Odysseus are the heroes who fight against the Trojans to get the body and bury it with his companion, Patroclus.&lt;ref&gt;Homer, [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Hom.+Od.+24.2 ''Odyssey''].&lt;/ref&gt; Ajax, with his great shield and spear, manages to recover the body and carry it to the ships, while Odysseus fights off the Trojans.&lt;ref&gt;Arctinus Miletus, &quot;Aethiopis&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; After the burial, each claims Achilles' magical armor, which had been forged on [[Mount Olympus]] by the smith-god [[Hephaestus]], for himself as recognition for his heroic efforts. A competition is held to determine who deserves the armor. Ajax argues that because of his strength and the fighting he has done for the Greeks, including saving the ships from Hector, and driving him off with a massive rock, he deserves the armor.&lt;ref&gt;Ovid, ''Metamorphoses'', translated by Rolfe Humphries (Indianapolis: Indiana University, 1955), Book XIII, pp. 305–309)&lt;/ref&gt;  However, Odysseus proves to be more eloquent, and with the aid of Athena, the council gives him the armor. Ajax, &quot;Unconquered&quot;, and furious, becomes crazed and slaughters the Achaians' herds of captured livestock, believing them to be his enemies through a trick of Athena. Unable to deal with this dual dishonor, he falls upon his own sword, &quot;conquered by his [own] sorrow&quot;, and commits suicide.&lt;ref&gt;''Metamorphoses'', trans. Humphries, p.&amp;nbsp;318&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lesches of Mitylene, &quot;The Little Iliad (Ilias Mikra)&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;  
The [[Belvedere Torso]], a marble torso now in the Vatican Museums, is considered to depict Ajax &quot;in the act of contemplating his [[Suicide of Ajax vase|suicide]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mv.vatican.va/3_EN/pages/x-Schede/MPCs/MPCs_Sala06_01.html|title=The Belvedere Torso; Cat. 1192|publisher=[[Vatican Museums]]|accessdate=29 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Sophocles' play ''[[Ajax (Sophocles)|Ajax]]'', a famous retelling of Ajax's demise, after the armor is awarded to Odysseus, Ajax feels so insulted that he wants to kill Agamemnon and Menelaus. Athena intervenes and clouds his mind and vision, and he goes to a flock of sheep and slaughters them, imagining they are the Achaean leaders, including Odysseus and Agamemnon. When he comes to his senses, covered in blood, he realizes that what he has done has diminished his honor, and decides that he prefers to kill himself rather than live in shame. He does so with the same sword which Hector gave him when they exchanged presents.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Iliad]],'' 7.303&lt;/ref&gt; From his blood sprang a red flower, as at the death of [[Hyacinth (mythology)|Hyacinthus]], which bore on its leaves the initial letters of his name ''Ai,'' also expressive of lament.&lt;ref&gt;[[Pausanias (geographer)|Pausanias]] 1.35.4&lt;/ref&gt; His ashes were deposited in a golden urn on the [[Rhoiteion#The Tomb of Ajax|Rhoetean]] promontory at the entrance of the [[Hellespont]].&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;&gt;{{EB1911|inline=y|wstitle=Ajax (son of Telamon)|display=Ajax |volume=1 |page=452}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ajax's half-brother Teucer stood trial before his father for not bringing Ajax's body or famous weapons back. Teucer was acquitted for responsibility but found guilty of negligence. He was disowned by his father and was not allowed to return to his home, the island of [[Salamis Island|Salamis]] off the coast of Athens.

Homer is somewhat vague about the precise manner of Ajax's death but does ascribe it to his loss in the dispute over Achilles' armor; when Odysseus visits [[Hades]], he begs the soul of Ajax to speak to him, but Ajax, still resentful over the old quarrel, refuses and descends silently back into [[Erebus]].

Like Achilles, he is represented (although not by Homer) as living after his death on the [[Snake Island (Black Sea)|island of Leuke]] at the mouth of the [[Danube]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Pausanias (geographer)|Pausanias]], ''[http://www.theoi.com/Text/Pausanias3B.html Description of Greece]'' iii. 19. § 13&lt;/ref&gt; Ajax, who in the post-Homeric legend is described as the grandson of Aeacus and the great-grandson of Zeus, was the [[tutelary deity|tutelary hero]] of the island of Salamis, where he had a temple and an image, and where a festival called ''Aianteia'' was celebrated in his honour.&lt;ref&gt;Pausanias 1.35&lt;/ref&gt; At this festival a couch was set up, on which the [[panoply]] of the hero was placed, a practice which recalls the Roman [[Lectisternium]]. The identification of Ajax with the family of Aeacus was chiefly a matter which concerned the Athenians, after Salamis had come into their possession, on which occasion [[Solon]] is said to have inserted a line in the ''[[Iliad]]'' (2.557–558),&lt;ref&gt;[[Homer]], ''[[Iliad]]'' [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text;jsessionid=0AE5CEA2E5E28FE965FF802C44870114?doc=Hom.+Il.+2.557 2.557–258].&lt;/ref&gt; for the purpose of supporting the Athenian claim to the island. Ajax then became an [[Attica|Attic]] hero; he was worshiped at Athens, where he had a statue in the market-place, and the tribe ''Aiantis'' was named after him.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; Pausanias also relates that a gigantic skeleton, its kneecap {{convert|5|in|cm}} in diameter, appeared on the beach near [[Sigeion]], on the Trojan coast; these bones were identified as those of Ajax.

&lt;gallery widths=&quot;200px&quot; heights=&quot;200px&quot;&gt;
File:Ajax suicide BM F480.jpg|The suicide of Ajax. Etrurian red-figured calyx-krater, ca. 400–350 BC.
File:Antimenes Painter - Black-figure Amphora with Ajax Carrying the Dead Achilles - Walters 4817 - Side A.jpg|A Black-figure Amphora with Ajax Carrying the Dead [[Achilles]]. [[Walters Art Museum]], [[Baltimore]].
File:Achilles Ajax dice Louvre MNB911 n2.jpg|[[Achilles]] and Ajax play a game of dice on this early 5th-century BC [[lekythos]], a type of oil-storing vessel associated with funeral rites
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Palace==
In 2001, Yannos Lolos began excavating a [[Mycenaean Greece|Mycenaean]] palace on the island of Salamis which he theorized to be the home of the mythological Aiacid dynasty.  The ruins have been excavated at a site near the village of Kanakia of Salamis, a few miles off the coast of Athens. The multi-story structure covers {{convert|750|m2|sqft|abbr=on}} and had perhaps 30 rooms. The palace appears to have been abandoned at the height of the Mycenaean civilization, roughly the same time the Trojan War may have occurred. (see discussion of [[Troy VII]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.thetimes.co.uk/tto/arts/article2407551.ece | location=London | work=The Times | title=Palace of Homers hero rises out of the myths | first=John | last=Carr | date=2006-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Corpus vasorum antiquorum]]
* [[List of suicides in fiction]]

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Sources==
* Homer. ''Iliad'', 7.181–312.
* Homer, ''Odyssey'' [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text;jsessionid=32D8E739DAB152D0549392B735061727?doc=Hom.+Od.+11.543&amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0136 11.543–67].
* ''[[Bibliotheca (Pseudo-Apollodorus)|Bibliotheca]]''. ''Epitome'' III, 11-V, 7.
* Ovid. ''Metamorphoses'' 12.620–13.398.
* [[Friedrich Schiller]], ''[https://web.archive.org/web/20070311231522/http://www.autoren-gedichte.de/schiller/das-siegesfest.htm Das Siegerfest]''.
* [[Pindar]]'s ''Nemeans'', 7, 8; ''Isthmian 4''

==External links==
{{Commons category|Ajax the Great}}
* A translation of the debate and Ajax's death. http://classics.mit.edu/Ovid/metam.13.thirteenth.html
* {{cite web
  | first=Nicholas
  | last= Paphitis
  | url=http://www.nbcnews.com/id/12080932
  | title=Archaeologist links palace to legendary Ajax
  | publisher=[[NBC News]]
  | date=2006-03-30
  | accessdate=2006-03-31
}}

{{Characters in the Odyssey}}
{{Characters in the Iliad}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ajax (Mythology)}}
[[Category:Suitors of Helen]]
[[Category:Achaean Leaders]]
[[Category:Kings of Argos]]
[[Category:People of the Trojan War]]
[[Category:Characters in the Iliad]]
[[Category:Characters in the Odyssey]]
[[Category:Characters in Greek mythology]]
[[Category:Suicides in Greek mythology]]
[[Category:Ancient Salamis]]
[[Category:Tutelary deities]]</text>
      <sha1>k8g45mahkoinn5im7bp25935w148420</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
