  <page>
    <title>Agrippina the Younger</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1557</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943197396</id>
      <parentid>943197011</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T13:19:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2001:569:7154:2A00:A88A:5FA3:A29B:A5BA</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Family */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Roman empress}}
{{Infobox royalty
|name        =Agrippina the Younger
|image       =Rome Agrippina Minor.jpg
|caption     =A bust at the [[National Museum, Warsaw]]
|title       = [[Augusta (honorific)|Augusta]]
|succession  =[[List of Roman empresses|Empress of the Roman Empire]]
|reign       =1 January AD 49 – 13 October AD 54
|reign-type  =
|spouse      =[[Gnaeus Domitius Ahenobarbus (consul 32)|Gnaeus Domitius Ahenobarbus]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Gaius Sallustius Crispus Passienus]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Claudius]]
|issue       =[[Nero]]
|house       =[[Julio-Claudian dynasty|Julio-Claudian Dynasty]]
|father      =[[Germanicus]]
|mother      =[[Agrippina the Elder]]
|birth_date  =6 November AD 15
|birth_place =[[Cologne|Oppidum Ubiorum]] ([[Cologne]])
|death_date  =23 March AD 59 (aged 43)
|death_place =[[Misenum]]
|place of burial =[[Misenum]]
|}}
{{Julio-Claudian dynasty}}
'''Agrippina the Younger''' ([[Latin language|Latin]]: ''Julia Agrippina''; 6 November AD 15 – 23 March AD 59), also referred to as '''Agrippina Minor''' (&quot;smaller&quot;, often used to mean &quot;younger&quot;),&lt;ref&gt;{{Aut|E. Groag, A. Stein, L. Petersen – e.a.}} (edd.), ''Prosopographia Imperii Romani saeculi I, II et III'' ('''PIR'''), Berlin, 1933 – I 641&lt;/ref&gt; was a [[List of Roman and Byzantine Empresses|Roman empress]] and one of the more prominent women in the [[Julio-Claudian dynasty]]. Her father was [[Germanicus]], a popular general and one-time heir apparent to the [[Roman Empire]] under [[Tiberius]]; and her mother was [[Agrippina the Elder]], a granddaughter of the first [[Roman emperor]] [[Augustus]]. She was also the younger sister of [[Caligula]], and the niece and fourth wife of [[Claudius]].

Both ancient and modern sources describe Agrippina's personality as ruthless, ambitious, violent and domineering. Physically she was a beautiful and reputable woman; according to [[Pliny the Elder]], she had a double canine in her upper right jaw, a sign of good fortune. Many ancient historians accuse Agrippina of poisoning her husband Claudius, though accounts vary.&lt;ref name = &quot;yyroia&quot;&gt;Tacitus, ''Annals'' XII.66; Cassius Dio, ''Roman History'' LXI.34; Suetonius, ''The Lives of Twelve Caesars'', Life of Claudius 44; Josephus is less sure, Josephus, ''Antiquities of the Jews'' XX.8.1&lt;/ref&gt; She briefly served as the de facto ruler of [[Rome]] during the reign of her son, emperor [[Nero]]. In AD 59 Agrippina was executed on the orders of Nero.

==Family==
{{Further|Julio-Claudian family tree}}
Agrippina was the first daughter and fourth living child of [[Agrippina the Elder]] and [[Germanicus]]. She had three elder brothers, [[Nero (son of Germanicus)|Nero Caesar]], [[Drusus Caesar]] and the future Emperor [[Caligula]], and two younger sisters, [[Julia Drusilla]] and [[Julia Livilla]]. Agrippina's two eldest brothers and her mother were victims of the intrigues of the Praetorian Prefect [[Lucius Aelius Sejanus]].

She was the namesake of her mother. Agrippina the Elder was remembered as a modest and heroic matron, who was the second daughter and fourth child of [[Julia the Elder]] and the statesman [[Marcus Vipsanius Agrippa]]. The father of Julia the Elder was the Emperor [[Augustus]], and Julia was his only natural child from his second marriage to [[Scribonia (wife of Augustus)|Scribonia]], who had close blood relations with [[Pompey the Great]] and [[Lucius Cornelius Sulla]].

Germanicus, Agrippina's father, was a very popular general and politician. His mother was [[Antonia Minor]] and his father was the general [[Nero Claudius Drusus]]. He was Antonia Minor's first child. Germanicus had two younger siblings; a sister, named [[Livilla (sister of Claudius)|Livilla]], and a brother, the future Emperor [[Claudius]]. Claudius was Agrippina's paternal uncle and third husband.

Antonia Minor was a daughter to [[Octavia the Younger]] by her second marriage to triumvir [[Mark Antony]], and Octavia was the second eldest sister and full-blooded sister of Augustus. Germanicus' father, [[Nero Claudius Drusus|Drusus the Elder]], was the second son of the Empress [[Livia]] Drusilla by her first marriage to praetor [[Tiberius Nero]], and was the Emperor [[Tiberius]]'s younger brother and Augustus's stepson. In the year 9, Augustus ordered and forced Tiberius to adopt Germanicus, who happened to be Tiberius's nephew, as his son and heir. Germanicus was a favorite of his great-uncle Augustus, who hoped that Germanicus would succeed his uncle Tiberius, who was Augustus's own adopted son and heir. This in turn meant that Tiberius was also Agrippina's adoptive grandfather in addition to her paternal great-uncle.

==Birth and early life==
Agrippina was born on 6 November in AD 15, or possibly 14, at Oppidum Ubiorum, a Roman outpost on the [[Rhine]] River located in present-day [[Cologne]], [[Germany]].&lt;ref&gt;Gaius Stern, &quot;Caligula's Three Sisters&quot; suggests that the sisters of Caligula were born at two-year intervals – Agrippina in 14, Drusilla in 16, and Livilla in 18, ''contra'' Suetonius &quot;the girls were born in three consecutive years.&quot;  Tac. ''Ann'' 2.54 disproves Suetonius' claim, placing Livilla's birthday in 18.  Note the births of Agrippina the Younger and Drusilla are only 10 months apart if Suetonius is correct.  But Drusilla was clearly born in 18.&lt;/ref&gt; A second sister Julia [[Drusilla]] was born on 16 September 16, also in Germany.&lt;ref&gt;Lindsay Powell ''Germanicus'' (Pen and Sword 2013), 116, cites {{CIL|6|5201}} = ''ILS'' 1837, {{CIL|5|5722}} = ''ILS'' 194, {{CIL|12|1026}} = ''ILS'' 195, for the birth and location of Julia Drusilla.&lt;/ref&gt;  As a small child, Agrippina travelled with her parents throughout Germany (15–16) until she and her siblings (apart from Caligula) returned to Rome to live with and be raised by their maternal grandmother Antonia.  Her parents departed for [[Syria]] in 18 to conduct official duties, and, according to Tacitus, the third and youngest sister was born en route on the island of Lesbos, namely [[Julia Livilla]], probably in March 18.&lt;ref&gt;Tac. ''Ann''. 2.54.  See also local inscriptions found by Lindsay Powell ''Germanicus'' (Pen and Sword 2013), p. 132 n. 96, {{CIL|6|3998}}, {{CIL|6|10563}} and others, as well as local coins.&lt;/ref&gt; In October of AD 19, Germanicus died suddenly in [[Antioch]] (modern [[Antakya]], [[Turkey]]).

Germanicus' death caused much public grief in Rome, and gave rise to rumors that he had been [[murder]]ed by [[Gnaeus Calpurnius Piso]] and [[Munatia Plancina]] on the orders of Tiberius, as his widow Agrippina the Elder returned to Rome with his ashes. Agrippina the Younger was thereafter supervised by her mother, her paternal grandmother Antonia Minor, and her great-grandmother, [[Livia]], all of them notable, influential, and powerful figures from whom she learnt how to survive. She lived on the [[Palatine Hill]] in [[Rome]]. Her great-uncle [[Tiberius]] had already become emperor and the head of the family after the death of [[Augustus]] in 14.

==Marriage to Gnaeus Domitius Ahenobarbus==
[[File:Domizio enobarbo, padre di nerone, busto di restauro, inv. 2222.JPG|thumb|left|upright=0.9|Bust of [[Gnaeus Domitius Ahenobarbus (consul 32)|Gnaeus Domitius Ahenobarbus]]]]
After her thirteenth birthday in 28, Tiberius arranged for Agrippina to marry her paternal first cousin once removed [[Gnaeus Domitius Ahenobarbus (consul 32)|Gnaeus Domitius Ahenobarbus]] and ordered the marriage to be celebrated in [[Rome]].&lt;ref&gt;Tac. ''Ann''. 4.75.&lt;/ref&gt; Domitius came from a distinguished family of [[Ahenobarbus|consular rank]]. Through his mother [[Antonia Major]], Domitius was a great nephew of Augustus, first cousin to Claudius, and first cousin once removed to Agrippina and Caligula. He had two sisters; [[Domitia Lepida the Elder]] and [[Domitia Lepida the Younger]]. Domitia Lepida the Younger was the mother of the Empress [[Valeria Messalina]].

Antonia Major was the elder sister to Antonia Minor, and the first daughter of Octavia Minor and Mark Antony. According to Suetonius, Domitius was a wealthy man with a despicable and dishonest character, who, according to Suetonius, was &quot;a man who was in every aspect of his life detestable&quot; and served as consul in 32. Agrippina and Domitius lived between [[Antium]] (modern [[Anzio]] and [[Nettuno]]&lt;ref&gt;Paola Brandizzi Vittucci, ''Antium: Anzio e Nettuno in epoca romana'', Roma, Bardi, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;) and Rome. Not much is known about the relationship between them.

==Reign of Caligula==
[[File:Caligula sestertius RIC 33 680999.jpg|thumb|right|upright=1.4|During the reign of [[Caligula]], coins like the one pictured here were issued depicting his three sisters, Drusilla, Livilla, and Agrippina the Younger]]

Tiberius died on March 16, AD 37, and Agrippina's only surviving brother, [[Caligula]], became the new emperor. Being the emperor's sister gave Agrippina some influence.

Agrippina and her younger sisters [[Drusilla (sister of Caligula)|Julia Drusilla]] and [[Livilla (sister of Caligula)|Julia Livilla]] received various honours from their brother, which included but were not limited to

* receiving the rights of the [[Vestal Virgin]]s, such as the freedom to view public games from the upper seats in the stadium;
* being honored with coins of a type never issued before, depicting images of Caligula and his sisters on opposite faces;
* having their names added to motions, including loyalty oaths (e.g., &quot;I will not value my life or that of my children less highly than I do the safety of the Emperor and his sisters&quot;) and consular motions (e.g., &quot;Good fortune attend to the Emperor and his sisters)&quot;.

Around the time that Tiberius died, Agrippina had become pregnant. Domitius had acknowledged the paternity of the child. On December 15, AD 37, in the early morning, in Antium, Agrippina gave birth to a son. Agrippina and Domitius named their son Lucius Domitius Ahenobarbus, after Domitius' recently deceased father. This child would grow up to become the Emperor [[Nero]]. Nero was Agrippina's only natural child. Suetonius states that Domitius was congratulated by friends on the birth of his son, whereupon he replied &quot;I don't think anything produced by me and Agrippina could possibly be good for the state or the people&quot;.

Caligula and his sisters were accused of having incestuous relationships. On June 10, AD 38, Drusilla died, possibly of a fever, rampant in Rome at the time. He was particularly fond of Drusilla, claiming to treat her as he would [[Lollia Paulina|his own wife]], even though Drusilla had a [[Marcus Aemilius Lepidus (executed 39)|husband]]. Following her death Caligula showed no special love or respect toward the surviving sisters and was said to have gone insane.

In 39, Agrippina and Livilla, with their maternal cousin, Drusilla's widower [[Marcus Aemilius Lepidus (executed 39)|Marcus Aemilius Lepidus]], were involved in a failed plot to murder Caligula, a plot known as the ''Plot of the Three Daggers'', which was to make Lepidus the new emperor. Lepidus, Agrippina and Livilla were accused of being lovers. Not much is known concerning this plot and the reasons behind it. At the trial of Lepidus, Caligula felt no compunction about denouncing them as adulteresses, producing handwritten letters discussing how they were going to kill him.

=== Exile ===
Lepidus was executed. Agrippina and Livilla were exiled by their brother to the [[Pontine Islands]]. Caligula sold their furniture, jewellery, slaves and freedmen. In January of AD 40, Domitius died of [[edema]] (dropsy) at Pyrgi. Lucius had gone to live with his second paternal aunt [[Domitia Lepida the Younger]] after Caligula had taken his inheritance away from him.

Caligula, his wife [[Milonia Caesonia]] and their daughter [[Julia Drusilla (daughter of Caligula)|Julia Drusilla]] were murdered on January 24, 41. Agrippina's paternal uncle, [[Claudius]], brother of her father [[Germanicus]], became the new Roman Emperor.

==Reign of Claudius==

===Return from exile===
[[File:Messalinaandbritannicus.jpg|thumb|upright=1.2|[[Messalina]] holding her son [[Britannicus]] ([[Musée du Louvre|Louvre]])]]
[[Claudius]] lifted the exiles of Agrippina and Livilla. Livilla returned to her husband, while Agrippina was reunited with her estranged son. After the death of her first husband, Agrippina tried to make shameless advances to the future emperor [[Galba]], who showed no interest in her and was devoted to his wife [[Aemilia Lepida]]. On one occasion, Galba's mother-in-law gave Agrippina a public reprimand and a slap in the face before a whole bevy of married women.&lt;ref&gt;[http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Suetonius/12Caesars/Galba*.html C. Suetonius Tranquillus] Suetonius. Twelve Caesars: Galba.&lt;/ref&gt;

Claudius had Lucius' inheritance reinstated. Lucius became more wealthy despite his youth shortly after [[Gaius Sallustius Crispus Passienus]] divorced Lucius' aunt, [[Domitia Lepida the Elder]] (Lucius' first paternal aunt) so that Crispus could marry Agrippina. They married, and Crispus  became a step-father to Lucius. Crispus was a prominent, influential, witty, wealthy and powerful man, who served twice as consul. He was the adopted grandson and biological great-great-nephew of the historian [[Sallust]]. Little is known on their relationship, but Crispus soon died and left his estate to Nero.

In the first years of Claudius' reign, Claudius was married to the infamous Empress [[Valeria Messalina]]. Although Agrippina was very influential, she kept a very low profile and stayed away from the imperial palace and the court of the emperor. Messalina was Agrippina's second paternal cousin. Among the victims of Messalina's intrigues were Agrippina's surviving sister Livilla, who was charged with having adultery with [[Seneca the Younger]]. Seneca was later called back from exile to be a tutor to Nero.

Messalina considered Agrippina's son a threat to her son's position and sent assassins to strangle Lucius during his siesta. The assassins fled in terror when they saw a snake suddenly dart from beneath Lucius' pillow—but it was only a sloughed-off snake-skin in his bed, near his pillow.

In 47, Crispus died, and at his funeral, the rumor spread around that Agrippina poisoned Crispus to gain his estate. After being widowed a second time, Agrippina was left very wealthy. Later that year at the [[Secular Games]], at the performance of the Troy Pageant, Messalina attended the event with her son Britannicus. Agrippina was also present with Lucius. Agrippina and Lucius received greater applause from the audience than Messalina and [[Britannicus]] did. Many people began to show pity and sympathy to Agrippina, due to the unfortunate circumstances in her life. Agrippina wrote a memoir that recorded the misfortunes of her family (casus suorum) and wrote an account of her mother's life.

===Rise to power===
After Messalina was executed in 48 for conspiring with [[Gaius Silius]] to overthrow her husband, Claudius considered remarrying for the fourth time. Around this time, Agrippina became the mistress to one of Claudius' advisers, the Greek [[freedman]], [[Pallas (freedman)|Marcus Antonius Pallas]]. At that time Claudius' advisers were discussing which noblewoman Claudius should marry. Claudius had a reputation that he was easily persuaded. In more recent times, it has been suggested that the Senate may have pushed for the marriage between Agrippina and Claudius to end the feud between the Julian and Claudian branches.&lt;ref&gt;Scramuzza (1940) pp.&amp;nbsp;91–92. See also Tac. ''Ann.'' XII 6, 7; Suet. ''Claud.'' 26.&lt;/ref&gt; This feud dated back to Agrippina's [[Agrippina the Elder|mother's]] actions against Tiberius after the death of Germanicus, actions which Tiberius had gladly punished.

Claudius made references to her in his speeches: &quot;my daughter and foster child, born and bred, in my lap, so to speak&quot;. When Claudius decided to marry her, he persuaded a group of senators that the marriage should be arranged in the public interest. In Roman society, an uncle (Claudius) marrying his niece (Agrippina) was considered incestuous and immoral.

==== Marriage to Claudius ====
Agrippina and Claudius married on New Year's Day, 49. This marriage caused widespread disapproval. This was a part of Agrippina's scheming plan to make her son Lucius the new emperor. Her marriage to Claudius was not based on love, but on power. She quickly eliminated her rival [[Lollia Paulina]]. Shortly after marrying Claudius, Agrippina charged Paulina with [[black magic]]. Paulina did not receive a hearing. Her property was confiscated.  She left Italy and, on Agrippina's orders, committed suicide.

In the months leading up to her marriage to Claudius, Agrippina's maternal second cousin, the [[praetor]] [[Lucius Junius Silanus Torquatus]], was betrothed to Claudius' daughter [[Claudia Octavia]]. This betrothal was broken off in 48, when Agrippina, scheming with the consul [[Lucius Vitellius the Elder]], the father of the future Emperor [[Aulus Vitellius]], falsely accused Silanus of incest with his sister [[Junia Calvina]]. Agrippina did this hoping to secure a marriage between Octavia and her son. Consequently, Claudius broke off the engagement and forced Silanus to resign from public office.

Silanus committed suicide on the day that Agrippina married her uncle, and Calvina was exiled from [[Italy]] in early 49. Calvina was called back from exile after the death of Agrippina. Towards the end of 54, Agrippina would order the murder of Silanus' eldest brother [[Marcus Junius Silanus Torquatus (consul  46)|Marcus Junius Silanus Torquatus]] without Nero's knowledge, so that he would not seek revenge against her over his brother's death.

==Empress of Rome==

On the day that Agrippina married her uncle Claudius as her third husband/his fourth wife, she became an Empress and the most powerful woman in the [[Roman Empire]]. She also was a stepmother to [[Claudia Antonia]], Claudius' daughter and only child from his second marriage to [[Aelia Paetina]], and to the young [[Claudia Octavia]] and [[Britannicus]], Claudius' children with Valeria Messalina. Agrippina removed or eliminated anyone from the palace or the imperial court who she thought was loyal and dedicated to the memory of the late Messalina. She also eliminated or removed anyone who she considered was a potential threat to her position and the future of her son, one of her victims being Lucius' second paternal aunt and Messalina's mother [[Domitia Lepida the Younger]].

In 49, Agrippina was seated on a dais at a parade of captives when their leader the [[Celts|Celtic]] King [[Caratacus]] bowed before her with the same homage and gratitude as he accorded the emperor. In 50, Agrippina was granted the honorific title of [[Augusta (honorific)|Augusta]]. She was only the third Roman woman ([[Livia]] Drusilla and [[Antonia Minor]] received this title) and only the second living Roman woman (the first being Antonia) to receive this title.

Also that year, Claudius had founded a Roman colony and called the colony ''Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensis'' or ''Agrippinensium'', today known as [[Cologne]], after Agrippina who was born there. This colony was the only Roman colony to be named after a Roman woman. In 51, she was given a ''carpentum'' which she used. A carpentum was a sort of ceremonial carriage usually reserved for priests, such as the [[Vestal Virgin]]s, and sacred statues. That same year she appointed [[Sextus Afranius Burrus]] as the head of the [[Praetorian Guard]], replacing the previous head of the Praetorian Guard, [[Rufrius Crispinus]].

Ancient sources claim that Agrippina successfully influenced Claudius into adopting her son and making him his successor. Lucius Domitius Ahenobarbus was adopted by his great maternal uncle and stepfather in 50. Lucius' name was changed to ''[[Nero]] Claudius Caesar Drusus Germanicus'' and he became Claudius's adopted son, heir and recognised successor. Agrippina and Claudius betrothed Nero to Octavia, and Agrippina arranged to have [[Seneca the Younger]] return from exile to tutor the future emperor. Claudius chose to adopt Nero because of his Julian and Claudian lineage.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annals'' XII.25&lt;/ref&gt;

Agrippina deprived Britannicus of his heritage and further isolated him from his father and succession for the throne in every way possible. For instance, in 51, Agrippina ordered the execution of Britannicus' tutor Sosibius because he had confronted her and was outraged by Claudius' adoption of Nero and his choice of Nero as successor, instead of choosing his own son Britannicus.&lt;ref&gt;Some compare this to when Tiberius had chosen Caligula and the other grandson [[Tiberius Gemellus]] &quot;without any approbation.&quot;  Why would there be any approbation?  Tiberius had few descendants and Gemellus was the youngest of all of them.  First Tiberius designated the older brothers of Caligula (his adopted son's sons) as his successors. Later he accused and imprisoned them.  All he had left was Caligula (by then over 20) and Gemellus (under 10).  There would be more approbation for overlooking Caligula in Gemellus' favor.&lt;/ref&gt;

Nero and Octavia were married on June 9, 53. Claudius later repented of marrying Agrippina and adopting Nero, began to favor Britannicus, and started preparing him for the throne. His actions allegedly gave Agrippina a motive to eliminate Claudius. The ancient sources say she poisoned Claudius on October 13, 54 (a Sunday) with a plate of deadly [[mushroom]]s at a banquet, thus enabling [[Nero]] to quickly take the throne as emperor. Accounts vary wildly with regard to this private incident and according to more modern sources, it is possible that Claudius died of natural causes; Claudius was 63 years old.&lt;ref name = &quot;yyroia&quot;/&gt;

==Reign of Nero==

===Power struggle between mother and son===
[[File:Nerón y Agripina.jpg|thumb|upright=0.8|Sculpture of Agrippina crowning her young son Nero (c. 54–59&amp;nbsp;AD)]]
[[File:Nero Palatino Inv618.jpg|thumb|left|upright=0.8|Marble bust of [[Nero]]. Antiquarium of the Palatine.]]
Agrippina was named a priestess of the cult of the deified Claudius. She was allowed to visit senate meetings, watching and hearing the meetings from behind a curtain. 

In the first months of Nero's reign, Agrippina had influence over her son and the Empire. She started losing influence over Nero when he began to have an affair with the freed woman [[Claudia Acte]], which Agrippina strongly disapproved of and violently scolded him for. Agrippina began to support [[Britannicus]] in her attempt to make him emperor. Britannicus was secretly poisoned on Nero's orders during his own banquet in February 55. The power struggle between Agrippina and her son had begun.&lt;ref&gt;''Rome: Agrippina the Younger – Background and Rise to Prominence'', by Lily Ophelia&lt;/ref&gt;

Agrippina between 55 and 58 became very watchful and had a critical eye over her son. In 55, Agrippina was forced out of the palace by her son to live in imperial residence. Nero deprived his mother of all honors and powers, and even removed her Roman and German bodyguards. Nero even threatened his mother he would abdicate the throne and would go to live on the Greek Island of [[Rhodes]], a place where [[Tiberius]] had lived after divorcing [[Julia the Elder]]. Pallas also was dismissed from the court. The fall of Pallas and the opposition of Burrus and Seneca, contributed to Agrippina's loss of authority.&lt;ref name=power&gt;Simon Hornblower, Antony Spawforth – E.A. (edd.), [[Oxford Classical Dictionary]], [[Oxford University Press]], [[Oxford]], 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

Towards 57, Agrippina was expelled from the palace and went to live in a riverside estate in [[Misenum]]. While Agrippina lived there or when she went on short visits to Rome, Nero sent people to annoy her. Although living in Misenum, she was still very popular, powerful and influential. Agrippina and Nero would see each other on short visits. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Wallbrecht |first1=Colonel Donald A. |title=Ad Britannia Ii: First Century Roman Britannia |date=2017 |publisher=Trafford Publishing |isbn=9781490783871}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Death and aftermath===
The circumstances that surround Agrippina's death are uncertain due to historical contradictions and anti-Nero bias. All surviving stories of Agrippina's death contradict themselves and each other, and are generally fantastical.

====Tacitus's account====
According to [[Tacitus]], in 58, Nero became involved with the noble woman [[Poppaea Sabina]]. With the reasoning that a divorce from Octavia and a marriage to Poppaea was not politically feasible with Agrippina alive, Nero decided to kill Agrippina.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annals'' XIV.1&lt;/ref&gt; Yet, Nero did not marry Poppaea until 62, calling into question this motive.&lt;ref&gt;See Dawson, Alexis, &quot;Whatever Happened to Lady Agrippina?&quot; ''The Classical Quarterly'' (1969) p. 264&lt;/ref&gt;  Additionally, [[Suetonius]] reveals that Poppaea's husband, [[Otho]], was not sent away by Nero until after Agrippina's death in 59, making it highly unlikely that already married Poppaea would be pressing Nero.&lt;ref&gt;Suetonius, ''The Lives of Caesars'', Life of Otho 3&lt;/ref&gt; Some modern historians theorize that Nero's decision to kill Agrippina was prompted by her plot to replace him with either Gaius [[Rubellius Plautus]] (Nero's maternal second cousin) or [[Britannicus]] (Claudius' biological son).&lt;ref&gt;Rogers, Robert. ''Heirs and Rivals to Nero'', Transactions and Proceedings of the American Philological Association, Vol. 86. (1955), p. 202. Silana accuses Agrippina of plotting to bring up Plautus in 55, Tacitus, ''Annals'' XIII.19; Silana is recalled from exile after Agrippina's power waned, Tacitus, ''Annals'' XIV.12; Plautus is exiled in 60, Tacitus, ''Annals'' XIV.22&lt;/ref&gt;

Tacitus claims that Nero considered poisoning or stabbing her, but felt these methods were too difficult and suspicious, so he settled on – after the advice of his former tutor [[Anicetus (freedman)|Anicetus]] – building a self-sinking boat.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annals'' XIV.3&lt;/ref&gt; Though aware of the plot, Agrippina embarked on this boat and was nearly crushed by a collapsing lead ceiling only to be saved by the side of a sofa breaking the ceiling's fall.&lt;ref name = &quot;lpygle&quot;&gt;Tacitus, ''Annals'' XIV.5&lt;/ref&gt; Though the collapsing ceiling missed Agrippina, it crushed her attendant who was outside by the helm.&lt;ref name = &quot;lpygle&quot;/&gt;

The boat failed to sink from the lead ceiling, so the crew then sank the boat, but Agrippina swam to shore.&lt;ref name = &quot;lpygle&quot;/&gt; Her friend, [[Acerronia Polla]], was attacked by oarsmen while still in the water, and was either bludgeoned to death or drowned, since she was exclaiming that she was Agrippina, with the intention of being saved. She did not know, however, that this was an assassination attempt, not a mere accident. Agrippina was met at the shore by crowds of admirers.&lt;ref name = &quot;eezojs&quot;&gt;Tacitus, ''Annals'' XIV.8&lt;/ref&gt; News of Agrippina's survival reached Nero so he sent three assassins to kill her.&lt;ref name = &quot;eezojs&quot;/&gt;

====Suetonius's account====
Suetonius says that Agrippina's 'over-watchful' and 'over-critical' eye that she kept over Nero drove him to murdering her. After months of attempting to humiliate her by depriving her of her power, honour and her bodyguards, he also expelled her from the [[Palatine]] followed by the people he sent to 'pester' her with lawsuits and 'jeers and catcalls'. 

When he eventually turned to murder, he first tried poison, three times in fact. She prevented her death by taking the antidote in advance. Afterwards, he rigged up a machine in her room which would drop her ceiling tiles onto her as she slept, however, she once again escaped her death after she received word of the plan. Nero's final plan was to get her in a boat which would collapse and sink. 

He sent her a friendly letter asking to reconcile and inviting her to celebrate the Quinquatrus at [[Baiae]] with him. He arranged an &quot;accidental&quot; collision between her galley and one of his captains. When returning home, he offered her his collapsible boat, as opposed to her damaged galley. 

The next day, Nero received word of her survival after the boat sank from her freedman Agermus. Panicking, Nero ordered a guard to 'surreptitiously' drop a blade behind Agermus and Nero immediately had him arrested on account of attempted murder. Nero ordered the assassination of Agrippina. He made it look as if Agrippina had committed suicide after her plot to kill Nero had been uncovered. 

After Agrippina's death, Suetonius says that Nero examined Agrippina's corpse and discussed her good and bad points. 

It is said that Nero believed Agrippina to haunt him after her death.

====Cassius Dio's account====
The tale of [[Cassius Dio]] is also somewhat different. It starts again with Poppaea as the motive behind the murder.&lt;ref&gt;Cassius Dio, ''Roman History'' LXIII.11&lt;/ref&gt;  Nero designed a ship that would open at the bottom while at sea.&lt;ref name = &quot;hltdlf&quot;&gt;Cassius Dio, ''Roman History'' LXIII.12&lt;/ref&gt;  Agrippina was put aboard and after the bottom of the ship opened up, she fell into the water.&lt;ref name = &quot;hltdlf&quot;/&gt; Agrippina swam to shore so Nero sent an assassin to kill her.&lt;ref&gt;Cassius Dio, ''Roman History'' LXIII.13&lt;/ref&gt;  Nero then claimed Agrippina had plotted to kill him and committed suicide.&lt;ref&gt;Cassius Dio, ''Roman History'' LXIII.14&lt;/ref&gt; Her reputed [[last words]], uttered as the assassin was about to strike, were &quot;Smite my womb&quot;, the implication here being she wished to be destroyed first in that part of her body that had given birth to so &quot;abominable a son.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Norman Davies, ''Europe: A history'', p. 687&lt;/ref&gt;

====Burial====
After Agrippina's death, Nero viewed her corpse and commented how beautiful she was, according to some.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annals'' XIV.9&lt;/ref&gt; Her body was cremated that night on a dining couch. At his mother's funeral, Nero was witless, speechless and rather scared. When the news spread that Agrippina had died, the Roman army, senate and various people sent him letters of congratulations that he had been saved from his mother's plots.

====Aftermath====
During the remainder of Nero's reign, Agrippina's grave was not covered or enclosed. Her household later on gave her a modest tomb in [[Misenum]]. Nero would have his mother's death on his conscience. He felt so guilty he would sometimes have nightmares about his mother. He even saw his mother's ghost and got [[Persia]]n magicians to scare her away. Years before she died, Agrippina had visited [[astrologer]]s to ask about her son's future. The astrologers had rather accurately predicted that her son would become emperor and would kill her. She replied, &quot;Let him kill me, provided he becomes emperor,&quot; according to [[Tacitus]].

===== Agrippina's alleged victims =====
* '''47'''
** ''Passienus Crispus'': Agrippina's 2nd husband, poisoned (Suet.).
* '''49'''
** ''Lollia Paulina'': as she was a rival for Claudius' hand in marriage as proposed by the freedman Callistus (Tac. &amp; Dio).
** ''Lucius Silanus'': betrothed to Octavia, Claudius' daughter before his marriage of Agrippina. He committed suicide on their wedding day.
** ''Sosibius'': Britannicus' tutor, executed for plotting against Nero.
** ''Calpurnia'': banished (Tac.) and/or executed (Dio) because Claudius had commented on her beauty.
* '''53'''
** ''Statilius Taurus'': forced to commit suicide because Agrippina wanted his gardens (Tac.).
* '''54'''
** ''Claudius'': her husband, poisoned (Tac., Sen., Juv., Suet., Dio).
** ''Domitia Lepida'': mother of Messalina, executed (Tac.).
** ''Marcus Junius Silanus'': potential rival to Nero, poisoned (Pliny, Tac., Dio).
** ''Cadius Rufus'': executed on the charge of extortion.

==Ancestry==
{{ahnentafel
|collapsed=yes |align=center
|boxstyle_1=background-color: #fcc;
|boxstyle_2=background-color: #fb9;
|boxstyle_3=background-color: #ffc;
|boxstyle_4=background-color: #bfc;
|boxstyle_5=background-color: #9fe;
|1= 1. '''Agrippina the Younger'''
|2= 2. [[Germanicus]]
|3= 3. [[Agrippina the Elder]]
|4= 4. [[Nero Claudius Drusus]]
|5= 5. [[Antonia Minor]]
|6= 6. [[Marcus Vipsanius Agrippa]]
|7= 7. [[Julia the Elder]]
|8= 8. [[Tiberius Claudius Nero (praetor 42 BC)|Tiberius Claudius Nero]]
|9= 9. [[Livia Drusilla]]
|10= 10. [[Mark Antony]]
|11= 11. [[Octavia Minor]]
|12= 12. [[Lucius Vipsanius Agrippa]]
|13=
|14= 14. [[Augustus]]
|15= 15. [[Scribonia (wife of Augustus)|Scribonia]]
}}&lt;ref&gt;https://www.roman-emperors.org/aggieii.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cultural references==

=== In music and literature ===
*''Agrippina: Trauerspiel'' (1665), a German baroque tragedy by [[Daniel Casper von Lohenstein]]
*G.F. Handel's 1709 opera ''[[Agrippina (opera)|Agrippina]]'' with a libretto by [[Vincenzo Grimani]]
*''Empress of Rome'' (1978), a novel by Robert DeMaria (Vineyard Press edition, 2001, {{ISBN|1-930067-05-4}})

=== In film, television, and radio ===
* The 1911 Italian film ''[[Agrippina (film)|Agrippina]]''
*''[[I, Claudius (television series)|I, Claudius]]'' (1976) played by [[Barbara Young (actress)|Barbara Young]] (here called Agrippinilla).
*''[[Caligula (film)|Caligula]]'' (1979) and also ''[[Messalina, Messalina]]'' (1977) played by [[Lori Wagner]].
*''[[A.D. (miniseries)|A.D.]]'' (1985 miniseries) played by [[Ava Gardner]].
*''[[Boudica (film)|Boudica]]'' (2003) played by [[Frances Barber]].
*''[[Imperium: Nero]]'' (2005) played by [[Laura Morante]].
*''[[Ancients Behaving Badly]]'' (2009), History Channel documentary. Episode ''Nero''.
*''[[Roman Empire]]'' (2016), Netflix, played by [[Teressa Liane]].
* Agrippina the Younger was portrayed by [[Betty Lou Gerson]] in the August 31st, 1953, episode of the [[CBS]] radio program ''[[Crime Classics]]'' that was entitled &quot;Your Loving Son, Nero.&quot; The episode chronicles the killing of Agrippina by her son [[Nero]] who was portrayed by [[William Conrad]].

==Perspectives on Agrippina's personality==

===Ancient===
Most ancient Roman sources are quite critical of Agrippina the Younger. [[Tacitus]] considered her vicious and had a strong disposition against her. Other sources are [[Suetonius]] and [[Cassius Dio]].

===Modern===
* {{in lang|fr}} Girod, Virginie, ''Agrippine, sexe, crimes et pouvoir dans la Rome impériale '', Paris, Tallandier, 2015, 300 p.
*{{in lang|fr}} Minaud, Gérard, ''Les vies de 12 femmes d'empereur romain – Devoirs, Intrigues &amp; Voluptés '', Paris, L'Harmattan, 2012, ch. 3, '' La vie d'Agrippine, femme de Claude'', p.&amp;nbsp;65-96.
* {{Aut|E. Groag, A. Stein, L. Petersen – e.a.}} (edd.), ''Prosopographia Imperii Romani saeculi I, II et III'', Berlin, 1933 –. ('''''PIR&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;''''')
* [[Howard Hayes Scullard|Scullard]]: A critical view of Agrippina, suggesting she was ambitious and unscrupulous and a depraved sexual [[Psychopathy|psychopath]]. &quot;Agrippina struck down a series of victims; no man or woman was safe if she suspected rivalry or desired their wealth.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Aut|H. H. Scullard}}, ''From the Gracchi to Nero: History of Rome from 133 B.C.to A.D. 68'', London, 1982&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;, p. 303.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Guglielmo Ferrero|Ferrero]]: Sympathetic and understanding, suggesting Agrippina has been judged harshly by history. Suggesting her marriage to Claudius was to a weak emperor who was, because of his hesitations and terrors, a threat to the imperial authority and government. She saw it her duty to compensate for the innumerable deficiencies of her strange husband through her own intelligence and strength of will. Pages [[s:The Women of the Caesars/The sisters of Caligula and the marriage of Messalina|212ff.]]; [[s:The Women of the Caesars/Agrippina, the mother of Nero|276ff.]]
* Barrett: A reasonable view, comparing Scullard's criticisms to Ferrero's apologies. (See Barrett, Anthony A., Agrippina: Sex, Power and Politics in the Early Roman Empire, Yale University Press, New Haven, 1996.)
* Annelise Freisenbruch, ''The first ladies of Rome''
* {{cite journal|doi=10.2307/506945|jstor=506945|title=Diva Drusilla Panthea and the Sisters of Caligula|journal=American Journal of Archaeology|volume=99|issue=3|pages=457–482|year=1995|last1=Wood|first1=Susan}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.2307/282970|jstor=282970|title=The Conspiracy of Agrippina|journal=Transactions and Proceedings of the American Philological Association|volume=62|pages=141–168|year=1931|last1=Rogers|first1=Robert Samuel}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1086/361706|title=A Note on the Marriage of Claudius and Agrippina|journal=Classical Philology|volume=29|issue=2|pages=143–145|year=1934|last1=Godolphin|first1=F. R. B.}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1017/S0009838800003657|title=On the Mushroom that Deified the Emperor Claudius|journal=The Classical Quarterly|volume=41|pages=178–182|year=1991|last1=Grimm-Samuel|first1=Veronika}}
* {{cite journal|doi=10.1017/S0009838800018814|title=Bauli the Scene of the Murder of Agrippina|journal=The Classical Quarterly|volume=4|issue=2|pages=96–102|year=1910|last1=McDaniel|first1=Walton Brooks}}
* McDaniel, W. B. &quot;Bauli the Scene of the Murder of Agrippina&quot;. ''The Classical Quarterly'', Vol. 4, No. 2 (April 1910)
* [[Jessica Amanda Salmonson|Salmonson, Jessica Amanda]]. (1991) ''The Encyclopedia of Amazons''. Paragon House. Pages 4–5.
* Donna Hurley, [http://www.roman-emperors.org/aggieii.htm Agrippina the Younger (Wife of Claudius)].
* {{Aut|L. Foubert}}, ''Agrippina. Keizerin van Rome'', Leuven, 2006.
* Opera by [[G.F. Handel]]: ''[[Agrippina (opera)|Agrippina]]''

==Notes==
{{reflist|30em}}

==References==
*{{Cite book |last = Graves |first= Robert
|title= Claudius, the god and his wife Messalina: the troublesome reign of Tiberius Claudius Caesar, Emperor of the Romans (born B.C. 10, died A.D. 54), as described by himself: also his murder at the hands of the notorious Agrippina (mother of the Emperor Nero) and his subsequent deification, as described by other |OCLC=178197}}
*Tacitus, ''Annales  xii.1–10, 64–69, xiv.1–9''
*Suetonius, ''De vita Caesarum'' – ''Claudius v.44'' and ''Nero vi.5.3, 28.2, 34.1–4

==External links==
{{Commons category|Agrippina Minor}}

{{S-start}}
{{S-roy}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Valeria Messalina]]}} 
{{s-ttl|title=[[Empress of Rome]]|years= 49–54}} 
{{s-aft|after=[[Claudia Octavia]]}}
{{S-end}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Agrippina the Younger}}
[[Category:15 births]]
[[Category:59 deaths]]
[[Category:Murdered Roman empresses]]
[[Category:Julii]]
[[Category:People from Cologne]]
[[Category:1st-century Romans]]
[[Category:People executed by the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:1st-century executions]]
[[Category:1st-century Roman women]]
[[Category:Executed Roman empresses]]
[[Category:Augustae]]
[[Category:Claudius]]
[[Category:Incest]]
[[Category:Wives of Claudius]]
[[Category:Children of Germanicus]]</text>
      <sha1>9fxhy99387whbi2zswmj8jpxle8r403</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
