  <page>
    <title>Ahmed I</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1527</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942223269</id>
      <parentid>941717862</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-23T11:15:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Narky Blert</username>
        <id>22041646</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Link to DAB page repaired</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Sultan of the Ottoman Empire from 1603 until 1617}}
{{Redirect|Ahmad I|others named Ahmed I and Ahmad I|Ahmad I (disambiguation)}}
{{more citations needed|date=September 2016}}
{{Infobox royalty
| name         = Ahmed I&lt;br /&gt;احمد اول
| title        = [[Sultan of the Ottoman Empire]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Caesar (title)#Ottoman Empire|Kayser-i Rûm]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Custodian of the Two Holy Mosques]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Ottoman Caliphate|Ottoman Caliph]]
| titletext    = 
| more         = 
| type         = 
| image        = File:Sultan I. Ahmet.jpg
| image_size   = 
| alt          = 
| caption      = 
| moretext     = 
| reign        = 22 December 1603 &amp;ndash; {{nowrap|22 November 1617}}
| coronation   = 23 December 1603
| cor-type     = {{nowrap|[[Sword of Osman|Sword girding]]}}
| predecessor  = [[Mehmed III]]
| successor    = [[Mustafa I]]
| succession   = 14th [[List of sultans of the Ottoman Empire|Ottoman Sultan]] ([[Padishah|Emperor]])
| spouse       = [[Mahfiruz Hatun]]&lt;br&gt;[[Kösem Sultan]] 
| spouse-type  = Consorts
| issue        = See [[Ahmed I#Family|below]]
| full name    = Ahmed bin Mehmed
| house        = [[Ottoman dynasty|Ottoman]]
| house-type   = Dynasty
| father       = [[Mehmed III]]
| mother       = [[Handan Sultan]]
| birth_date   = 18/{{birth date|1590|04|19|df=yes}}
| birth_place  = Manisa Palace, [[Manisa]], [[Ottoman Empire]]
| death_date   = {{death date and age|1617|11|22|1590|04|18|df=yes}}
| death_place  = [[Topkapı Palace]], [[Istanbul]], Ottoman Empire
| burial_date  = 
| burial_place = [[Sultan Ahmed Mosque]], Istanbul
| signature_type = [[Tughra]]
| religion     = [[Sunni Islam]]
| signature    = Tughra of Ahmed I.JPG
}}
'''Ahmed I''' ({{lang-ota|احمد اول}} ''{{transl|ota|Aḥmed-i evvel}}''; {{lang-tr|I. Ahmed}}; 18/19 April 1590 – 22 November 1617) was the [[Sultan of the Ottoman Empire]] from 1603 until his death in 1617. Ahmed's reign is noteworthy for marking the end of the Ottoman tradition of royal fratricide; henceforth Ottoman rulers would no longer execute their brothers upon accession to the throne.&lt;ref name=&quot;Peirce 1993 99&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Peirce |first=Leslie |title=The Imperial Harem: Women and Sovereignty in the Ottoman Empire |publisher=Oxford University Press |pages=[https://archive.org/details/imperialharemwom00peir/page/99 99] |date=1993 |ISBN=0-19-508677-5 |url=https://archive.org/details/imperialharemwom00peir/page/99 }}&lt;/ref&gt; He is also well known for his construction of the [[Sultan Ahmed Mosque|Blue Mosque]], one of the most famous mosques in Turkey.

==Early life==
Ahmed was probably born in April 1590&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Günhan|last=Börekçi|title=İnkırâzın Eşiğinde Bir Hanedan: III. Mehmed, I. Ahmed, I. Mustafa ve 17. Yüzyıl Osmanlı Siyasî Krizi - A Dynasty at the Threshold of Extinction: Mehmed III, Ahmed I, Mustafa I and the 17th-Century Ottoman Political Crisis|publisher=|year=|pages=81 n. 75|isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Günhan|last=Börekçi|title=Factions And Favorites At The Courts Of Sultan Ahmed I (r. 1603-17) And His Immediate Predexessors|publisher=|year=2010|pages=85 n. 17|isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt; at the Manisa Palace, [[Manisa]], when his father [[Şehzade]] Mehmed was still a prince and the governor of the [[Sanjak]] of Manisa. His mother was [[Handan Sultan]]. After his grandfather [[Murad III]]'s death in 1595, his father came to Constantinople and ascended the throne as Sultan [[Mehmed III]].  Mehmed ordered the execution of nineteen of his own brothers and half brothers. Ahmed's elder brother [[Şehzade Mahmud (son of Mehmed III)|Şehzade Mahmud]] was also executed by his father Mehmed on 7 June 1603, just before Mehmed's own death on 22 December 1603. Mahmud was buried along with his mother in a separate mausoleum built by Ahmed in [[Şehzade Mosque]], Constantinople.

==Reign==
Ahmed ascended the throne after his father's death in 1603, at the age of thirteen, when his powerful grandmother [[Safiye Sultan (wife of Murad III)|Safiye Sultan]] was still alive. A far lost uncle of Ahmed, [[Sultan Yahya|Yahya]], resented his accession to the throne and spent his life scheming to become Sultan. Ahmed broke with the traditional fratricide following previous enthronements and did not order the execution of his brother [[Mustafa I|Mustafa]]. Instead Mustafa was sent to live at the old palace at Bayezit along with their grandmother Safiye Sultan. This was most likely due to Ahmed's young age - he had not yet demonstrated his ability to sire children, and Mustafa was then the only other candidate for the Ottoman throne. His brother's execution would have endangered the dynasty, and thus he was spared.&lt;ref name=&quot;Peirce 1993 99&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Peirce |first=Leslie |title=The Imperial Harem: Women and Sovereignty in the Ottoman Empire |publisher=Oxford University Press |pages=[https://archive.org/details/imperialharemwom00peir/page/99 99] |date=1993 |ISBN=0-19-508677-5 |url=https://archive.org/details/imperialharemwom00peir/page/99 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the earlier part of his reign Ahmed I showed decision and vigor, which were belied by his subsequent conduct.{{citation needed|date=September 2016}} The wars in [[Ottoman Hungary|Hungary]] and [[Safavid Dynasty|Persia]], which attended his accession, terminated unfavourably for the empire. Its prestige was further tarnished in the [[Treaty of Sitvatorok|Treaty of Zsitvatorok]], signed in 1606, whereby the annual tribute paid by [[Archduchy of Austria|Austria]] was abolished. Following the crushing defeat in the [[Ottoman–Safavid War (1603–18)]] against the neighbouring rivals [[Safavid Empire]], led by Shah [[Abbas the Great]], Georgia, Azerbaijan and other vast territories in the Caucasus were ceded back to Persia per the [[Treaty of Nasuh Pasha]] in 1612, territories that had been temporarily conquered in the [[Ottoman–Safavid War (1578–90)]]. The new borders were drawn per the same line as confirmed in the [[Peace of Amasya]] of 1555.&lt;ref&gt;Ga ́bor A ́goston,Bruce Alan Masters [https://books.google.nl/books?id=QjzYdCxumFcC&amp;pg=PA23&amp;dq=treaty+of+nasuh+pasha+same+border+peace+of+amasya&amp;hl=nl&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=2IJHVY2KH8TuaImmgfAP&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=treaty%20of%20nasuh%20pasha%20same%20border%20peace%20of%20amasya&amp;f=false ''Encyclopedia of the Ottoman Empire''] pp 23 Infobase Publishing, 1 jan. 2009 {{ISBN|1438110251}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Ottoman-Safavid War: 1604–06 ===

The [[Ottoman–Safavid War (1603–18)|Ottoman–Safavid War]] had begun shortly before the death of Ahmed's father Mehmed III.  Upon ascending the throne, Ahmed I appointed [[Cigalazade Yusuf Sinan Pasha]] as the commander of the eastern army. The army marched from Constantinople on 15 June 1604, which was too late, and by the time it had arrived on the eastern front on 8 November 1604, the [[Safavid]] army had captured [[Yerevan]] and entered the [[Kars Eyalet]], and could only be stopped in [[Akhaltsikhe]]. Despite the conditions being favourable, Sinan Pasha decided to stay for the winter in [[Van, Turkey|Van]], but then marched to [[Erzurum]] to stop an incoming Safavid attack. This caused unrest within the army and the year was practically wasted for the Ottomans.&lt;ref name=islamans&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |url=http://www.islamansiklopedisi.info/dia/pdf/c02/c020017.pdf| title=Ahmed I |encyclopedia=İslam Ansiklopedisi |publisher=Türk Diyanet Vakfı |pages=30–33 |year=1989 | volume=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1605, Sinan Pasha marched to take [[Tabriz]], but the army was undermined by [[Köse Sefer Pasha]], the [[Beylerbey]] of Erzurum, marching independently from Sinan Pasha and consequently being taken prisoner by the Safavids. The Ottoman army was routed at [[Battle of Urmia (1604)|Urmia]] and had to flee firstly to Van and then to [[Diyarbakır|Diyarbekir]]. Here, Sinan Pasha sparked a rebellion by executing the Beylerbey of [[Aleppo]], [[Canbulatoğlu Hüseyin Pasha]], who had come to provide help, upon the pretext that he had arrived too late. He soon died himself and the Safavid army was able to capture [[Ganja, Azerbaijan|Ganja]], [[Shirvan]] and [[Shamakhi]] in Azerbaijan.&lt;ref name=islamans/&gt;

=== War with the Habsburgs: 1604–06 ===
The [[Long Turkish War]] between the Ottomans and the [[Habsburg Monarchy]] had been going on for over a decade by the time Ahmed ascended the throne.  Grand Vizier [[Malkoç Ali Pasha]] marched to the western front from Constantinople on 3 June 1604 and arrived in [[Belgrade]], but died there, so [[Lala Mehmed Pasha]] was appointed as the Grand Vizier and the commander of the western army. Under Mehmed Pasha, the western army recaptured [[Pest, Hungary|Pest]] and [[Vác]], but failed to capture [[Esztergom]] as the siege was lifted due to unfavourable weather and the objections of the soldiers. Meanwhile, the Prince of [[Transylvania]], [[Stephen Bocskay]], who struggled for the region's independence and had formerly supported the Habsburgs, sent a messenger to the Porte asking for help. Upon the promise of help, his forces also joined the Ottoman forces in Belgrade. With this help, the Ottoman army besieged Esztergom and captured it on 4 November 1605. Bocskai, with Ottoman help, captured [[Nové Zámky]] (Uyvar) and forces under [[Tiryaki Hasan Pasha]] took [[Veszprém]] and [[Várpalota|Palota]]. [[Sarhoş İbrahim Pasha]], the Beylerbey of [[Nagykanizsa]] (Kanije), attacked the Austrian region of [[Istria]].&lt;ref name=islamans/&gt;
[[File:Sultan Ahmed I.jpg|thumb|[[Ottoman miniature]] of Ahmed I. ]]
However, with Jelali revolts in Anatolia more dangerous than ever and a defeat in the eastern front, Mehmed Pasha was called to Constantinople. Mehmed Pasha suddenly died there, whilst preparing to leave for the east. [[Kuyucu Murad Pasha]] then negotiated the [[Peace of Zsitvatorok]], which abolished the tribute of 30,000 ducats paid by Austria and addressed the Habsburg emperor as the equal of the Ottoman sultan. The Jelali revolts were a strong factor in the Ottomans' acceptance of the terms. This signaled the end of Ottoman growth in Europe.&lt;ref name=islamans/&gt;

=== Jelali revolts ===
Resentment over the war with the Habsburgs and heavy taxation, along with the weakness of the Ottoman military response, combined to make the reign of Ahmed I the zenith of the [[Jelali revolts]]. Tavil Ahmed launched a revolt soon after the coronation of Ahmed I and defeated [[Nasuh Pasha]] and the Beylerbey of Anatolia, Kecdehan Ali Pasha. In 1605, Tavil Ahmed was offered the position of the Beylerbey of [[Shahrizor]] to stop his rebellion, but soon afterwards he went on to capture [[Harput]]. His son, Mehmed, obtained the governorship of [[Baghdad]] with a fake [[firman]] and defeated the forces of Nasuh Pasha sent to defeat him.&lt;ref name=islamans/&gt;

Meanwhile, Canbulatoğlu Ali Pasha united his forces with the [[Druze]] Sheikh Ma'noğlu Fahreddin to defeat the Amir of [[Tripoli, Lebanon|Tripoli]] Seyfoğlu Yusuf. He went on to take control of the [[Adana]] area, forming an army and issuing coins. His forces routed the army of the newly appointed Beylerbey of Aleppo, Hüseyin Pasha. Grand Vizier [[Boşnak Dervish Mehmed Pasha]] was executed for the weakness he showed against the Jelalis. He was replaced by Kuyucu Murad Pasha, who marched to Syria with his forces to defeat the 30,000-strong rebel army with great difficulty, albeit with a decisive result, on 24 October 1607. Meanwhile, he pretended to forgive the rebels in Anatolia and appointed the rebel Kalenderoğlu, who was active in [[Manisa]] and [[Bursa]], as the [[sanjakbey]] of [[Ankara]]. Baghdad was recaptured in 1607 as well. Canbulatoğlu Ali Pasha fled to Constantinople and asked for forgiveness from Ahmed I, who appointed him to [[Timișoara]] and later Belgrade, but then executed him due to his misrule there. Meanwhile, Kalenderoğlu was not allowed in the city by the people of Ankara and rebelled again, only to be crushed by Murad Pasha's forces. Kalenderoğlu ended up fleeing to Persia. Murad Pasha then suppressed some smaller revolts in Central Anatolia and suppressed other Jelali chiefs by inviting them to join the army.&lt;ref name=islamans/&gt;

Due to the widespread violence of the Jelali revolts, a great number of people had fled their villages and a lot of villages were destroyed. Some military chiefs had claimed these abandoned villages as their property. This deprived the Porte of tax income and on 30 September 1609, Ahmed I issued a letter guaranteeing the rights of the villagers. He then worked on the resettlement of abandoned villages.&lt;ref name=islamans/&gt;

=== Ottoman-Safavid War: Peace and continuation ===
[[File:Savary Franco Ottoman Capitulations 1615.jpg|thumb|200px|Bilingual Franco-Turkish translation of the 1604 [[Franco-Ottoman alliance|Franco-Ottoman Capitulations]] between Ahmed I and [[Henry IV of France]], published by [[François Savary de Brèves]] in 1615&lt;ref name=&quot;Bosworth&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=PvwUAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA799 |title='&amp;#39;The Encyclopaedia of Islam: Fascicules 111-112 : Masrah Mawlid'&amp;#39; by Clifford Edmund Bosworth p.799 |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=2012-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The new Grand Vizier, Nasuh Pasha, did not want to fight with the Safavids. The Safavid Shah also sent a letter saying that he was willing to sign a peace, with which he would have to send 200 loads of [[silk]] every year to Constantinople. On 20 November 1612, the [[Treaty of Nasuh Pasha]] was signed, which ceded all the lands the Ottoman Empire had gained in the war of 1578–90 back to Persia and reinstated the 1555 boundaries.&lt;ref name=islamans/&gt;

However, the peace ended in 1615 when the Shah did not send the 200 loads of silk. On 22 May 1615, Grand Vizier [[Öküz Mehmed Pasha]] was assigned to organize an attack on Persia. Mehmed Pasha delayed the attack till the next year, until when the Safavids made their preparations and attacked Ganja. In April 1616, Mehmed Pasha left Aleppo with a large army and marched to Yerevan, where he failed to take the city and withdrew to Erzurum. He was removed from his post and replaced by [[Damat Halil Pasha]]. Halil Pasha went for the winter to Diyarbekir, while the Khan of Crimea, [[Canibek Giray]], attacked the areas of [[Ganja, Azerbaijan|Ganja]], [[Nakhchivan (city)|Nakhichevan]] and [[Julfa, Azerbaijan (city)|Julfa]].&lt;ref name=islamans/&gt;

=== Capitulations and trade treaties ===
Ahmed I renewed trade treaties with England, France and Venice. In July 1612, the first ever trade treaty with the [[Dutch Republic]] was signed. He expanded the [[Capitulations of the Ottoman Empire|capitulations]] given to France, specifying that merchants from [[Habsburg Spain|Spain]], [[Republic of Ragusa|Ragusa]], [[Republic of Genoa|Genoa]], [[Ancona]] and [[Grand Duchy of Tuscany|Florence]] could trade under the French flag.&lt;ref name=islamans/&gt;

=== Architect and service to Islam ===
{{unreferenced section|date=October 2016}}
[[File:Madina trip 200.jpg|thumb|Ahmed I plate at Masjid al-Nabawi marking Bab al-Tawba]]


Sultan Ahmed constructed the Sultan Ahmed Mosque, the magnum opus of the Ottoman architecture,{{According to whom|date=December 2017}} across from the [[Hagia Sophia]]. The sultan attended the breaking of the ground with a golden pickaxe to begin the construction of the mosque complex. An incident nearly broke out after the sultan discovered that the Blue Mosque contained the same number of minarets as the grand mosque of Mecca. Ahmed became furious at this fault and became remorseful until the Shaykh-ul-Islam recommended that he should erect another minaret at the grand mosque of Mecca and the matter was solved.

[[File:Blue Mosque.jpg|thumb|275px|The [[Sultan Ahmed Mosque]]]]

Ahmed became delightedly involved in the eleventh comprehensive renovations of the [[Kaaba]], which had just been damaged by flooding. He sent craftsmen from Constantinople, and the golden rain gutter that kept rain from collecting on the roof of the Ka’ba was successfully renewed. It was again during the era of Sultan Ahmed that an iron web was placed inside the [[Zamzam Well]] in Mecca. The placement of this web about three feet below the water level was a response to lunatics who jumped into the well, imagining a promise of a heroic death.

In Medina, the city of the Prophet [[Muhammad]], a new pulpit made of white marble and shipped from Istanbul arrived in the mosque of the prophet and substituted the old, worn-out pulpit. It is also known that Sultan Ahmed erected two more mosques in Uskudar on the Asian side of Istanbul; however, neither of them has survived.

The sultan had a crest carved with the footprint of Muhammad that he would wear on Fridays and festive days and illustrated one of the most significant examples of affection to the prophet in Ottoman history. Engraved inside the crest was a poem he composed:
{{quote|“If only could I bear over my head like my turban forever thee, If only I could carry it all the time with me, on my head like a crown, the Footprint of the Prophet Muhammad, which has a beautiful complexion, Ahmed, go on, rub your face on the feet of that rose.“}}

==Character==
Sultan Ahmed was known for his skills in fencing, poetry, horseback riding, and fluency in several languages.

Ahmed was a poet who wrote a number of political and lyrical works under the name Bahti. But while supportive of poetry, he displayed an aversion to artistry and continued his father's neglect of [[Ottoman miniature|miniature painting]]. {{Citation needed|reason=&quot;Works of fiction are not reliable sources, no matter how excellent&quot;|date=December 2013}} This was connected to a devout religiosity that declared depiction of living things in art an immoral rivalry to [[Allah]]'s creation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Heilbrunn&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/hd/figs/hd_figs.htm |title=Figural Representation in Islamic Art &amp;#124; Thematic Essay &amp;#124; Heilbrunn Timeline of Art History &amp;#124; The Metropolitan Museum of Art |publisher=Metmuseum.org |date= |accessdate=2012-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Accordingly, Ahmed patronized scholars, calligraphers, and pious men. Hence he commissioned a book entitled ''The Quintessence of Histories'' to be worked upon by calligraphers. He also attempted to enforce conformance to Islamic laws and traditions, restoring the old regulations that prohibited alcohol and he attempted to enforce attendance at [[Jumu'ah|Friday prayers]] and paying alms to the poor in the proper way.

He was responsible for the destruction of the musical clock organ that [[Elizabeth I of England]] sent to the court during the reign of his father.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jardine&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Jardine |first=Lisa |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/magazine/7155903.stm |title=UK &amp;#124; Magazine &amp;#124; An eye for detail |work=BBC News |date=2007-12-21 |accessdate=2012-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; The reason for this may have been Ahmed's religious objection to figurative art.
[[File:Arolsen Klebeband 02 323.jpg|thumb|262px|Ahmed I by Arolsen Klebeband]]
==Death==
[[File:Istanbul - Tomba Ahmet I.JPG|thumb|262px|Ahmed I's [[türbe]]]]

Ahmed I died of [[typhus]] and gastric bleeding on 22 November 1617 at the [[Topkapı Palace]], [[Istanbul]]. He was buried in Ahmed I Mausoleum, [[Sultan Ahmed Mosque]]. He was succeeded by his younger brother Şehzade Mustafa as Sultan [[Mustafa I]]. Later three of Ahmed's sons ascended to the throne: [[Osman II]] (r. 1618–22), [[Murad IV]] (r. 1623–40) and [[Ibrahim of the Ottoman Empire|Ibrahim]] (r. 1640–48).

==Family==
;Consorts
* [[Mahfiruz Hatun]]; 
* [[Kösem Sultan]]; 

;Sons
*Sultan [[Osman II]] (3 November 1604, Constantinople, Topkapı Palace – murdered by janissaries and by Kara Davud Pasha, 20 May 1622, Constantinople, Topkapı Palace, buried in Ahmed I Mausoleum, Sultan Ahmed Mosque), with Mahfiruz,&lt;ref name=&quot;Şefika&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Şefika Şule Erçetin|title=Women Leaders in Chaotic Environments:Examinations of Leadership Using Complexity Theory|pages=77|publisher=Springer|date=November 28, 2016|isbn=978-3-319-44758-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Uluçay&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Mustafa Çağatay Uluçay|title=Padışahların Kadınları ve Kızları|publisher=Ötüken, Ankara|year=2011|pages=78|isbn=978-9-754-37840-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sultan of the Ottoman Empire;
* [[Şehzade Mehmed (son of Ahmed I)|Şehzade Mehmed]] (1605, Constantinople, Topkapı Palace – murdered by Osman II, 12 January 1621, Istanbul, Topkapı Palace, buried in Ahmed I Mausoleum, Sultan Ahmed Mosque) with Kösem;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Tezcan|first=Baki|title=The Debut of Kösem Sultan's Political Career|journal=Turcica|volume=39–40|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=GBs_AQAAIAAJ|year=2007|publisher=Éditions Klincksieck|ref=harv|pages=350–351}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Sultan [[Murad IV]] (27 July 1612, Constantinople – 8 February 1640, Constantinople, Topkapı Palace, buried in Ahmed I Mausoleum, Sultan Ahmed Mosque), with Kösem,&lt;ref name=&quot;Şefika&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Naima&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Mustafa Naima|title=Annals of the Turkish Empire: From 1591 to 1659 ..., Volume 1|publisher=Oriental Translation Fund, &amp; sold by J. Murray|year=1832|pages=452–3|isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;issue&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Singh, Nagendra Kr|title=International encyclopaedia of Islamic dynasties ''(reproduction of the article by M. Cavid Baysun &quot;Kösem Walide or Kösem Sultan&quot; in ''The Encyclopaedia of Islam vol V)|publisher=Anmol Publications PVT |year=2000|pages=423–424|isbn=81-261-0403-1|quote=Through her beauty and intelligence, Kösem Walide was especially attractive to Ahmed I, and drew ahead of more senior wives in the palace. She bore the sultan four sons – Murad, Süleyman, Ibrahim and Kasim – and three daughters – 'Ayşe, Fatma and Djawharkhan. These daughters she subsequently used to consolidate her political influence by strategic marriages to different viziers.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kosem-children1&quot;&gt;{{citation|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=L6-VRgVzRcUC&amp;pg=PA365&amp;dq=hanzade+sultan&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0CB8Q6AEwAWoVChMI876PrcL7yAIVybsUCh3eEwAh#v=onepage&amp;q=hanzade%20sultan&amp;f=false|title=The Imperial Harem: Women and Sovereignty in the Ottoman Empire|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|first=Leslie P.|last=Peirce|authorlink=Leslie P. Peirce |year=1993|isbn=0195086775|page=232}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sultan of the Ottoman Empire;
* Şehzade Bayezid (November 1612 – murdered by Murad IV, 27 July 1635, Constantinople, Topkapı Palace, buried in Ahmed I Mausoleum, Sultan Ahmed Mosque), with Mahfiruz;&lt;ref name=&quot;Şefika&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Uluçay&quot; /&gt;
* Şehzade Süleyman (1613, Istanbul – murdered by Murad IV, 27 July 1635, Constantinople, Topkapı Palace, buried in Ahmed I Mausoleum, Sultan Ahmed Mosque), with Kösem;&lt;ref name=&quot;Şefika&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Uluçay&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;issue&quot; /&gt;
* Şehzade Selim (1613, Istanbul – murdered by Murad IV, 27 July 1635, Constantinople, Topkapı Palace,&lt;ref&gt;Alderson, 1956, table XXXIV&lt;/ref&gt; buried in Ahmed I Mausoleum, Sultan Ahmed Mosque), with Kösem;&lt;ref&gt;Gülru Neci̇poğlu, Julia Bailey (2008). ''Frontiers of Islamic Art and Architecture: Essays in Celebration of Oleg Grabar's Eightieth Birthday ; the Aga Khan Program for Islamic Architecture Thirtieth Anniversary Special Volume''. BRILL. p. 324. {{ISBN|978-9-004-17327-9}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Şehzade Hüseyin (November 1614, Constantinople – after 1622, Constantinople, Topkapı Palace, buried in Mehmed III Mausoleum, Hagia Sophia Mosque); with Mahfiruz;&lt;ref name=&quot;Şefika&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Uluçay&quot; /&gt;
* Şehzade Kasım (1614, Constantinople – murdered by Murad IV, 17 February 1638, Constantinople, Topkapı Palace, buried in Murad III Mausoleum, [[Hagia Sophia]] Mosque), with Kösem;&lt;ref name=&quot;Şefika&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Naima&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=issue/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kosem-children1&quot;/&gt;
* Sultan [[Ibrahim of the Ottoman Empire|Ibrahim]] (5 November 1615, Constantinople – murdered by janissaries, 18 August 1648, Constantinople, Topkapı Palace, buried in Mustafa I Mausoleum, Hagia Sophia Mosque), with Kösem,&lt;ref name=&quot;Şefika&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Naima&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=issue/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kosem-children1&quot;/&gt; Sultan of the Ottoman Empire.

;Daughters
*[[Gevherhan Sultan (daughter of Ahmed I)|Gevherhan Sultan]] (c. 1608 - 1660, buried in Ahmed I Mausoleum, Sultan Ahmed Mosque), with Kösem,&lt;ref&gt;Singh, Nagendra Kr (2000). ''International encyclopaedia of Islamic dynasties'' (reproduction of the article by M. Cavid Baysun &quot;Kösem Walide or Kösem Sultan&quot; in ''The Encyclopaedia of Islam vol V)''. Anmol Publications PVT. pp. 423–424. {{ISBN|81-261-0403-1}}. &quot;Through her beauty and intelligence, Kösem Walide was especially attractive to Ahmed I, and drew ahead of more senior wives in the palace. She bore the sultan four sons – Murad, Süleyman, Ibrahim and Kasim – and three daughters – 'Ayşe, Fatma and Djawharkhan. These daughters she subsequently used to consolidate her political influence by strategic marriages to different viziers.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Leslie P. Peirce|Peirce, Leslie P.]] (1993), [https://books.google.com/books?id=L6-VRgVzRcUC&amp;pg=PA365&amp;dq=hanzade+sultan&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0CB8Q6AEwAWoVChMI876PrcL7yAIVybsUCh3eEwAh#v=onepage&amp;q=hanzade%20sultan&amp;f=false ''The Imperial Harem: Women and Sovereignty in the Ottoman Empire''], [[Oxford University Press]], p. 365, {{ISBN|0195086775}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Ayşe Sultan (daughter of Ahmed I)|Ayşe Sultan]] (1605/08 – 1657, Constantinople, buried in Ahmed I Mausoleum, Sultan Ahmed Mosque), with Kösem,&lt;ref&gt;Singh, Nagendra Kr (2000). ''International encyclopaedia of Islamic dynasties'' (reproduction of the article by M. Cavid Baysun &quot;Kösem Walide or Kösem Sultan&quot; in ''The Encyclopaedia of Islam vol V)''. Anmol Publications PVT. pp. 423–424. {{ISBN|81-261-0403-1}}. &quot;Through her beauty and intelligence, Kösem Walide was especially attractive to Ahmed I, and drew ahead of more senior wives in the palace. She bore the sultan four sons – Murad, Süleyman, Ibrahim and Kasim – and three daughters – 'Ayşe, Fatma and Djawharkhan. These daughters she subsequently used to consolidate her political influence by strategic marriages to different viziers.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Fatma Sultan (daughter of Ahmed I)|Fatma Sultan]] ({{circa}}1606 – 1670, Constantinople, buried in Ahmed I Mausoleum, Sultan Ahmed Mosque), with Kösem;&lt;ref name=&quot;issue&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kosem-children2&quot;&gt;{{citation|last=Peirce|first=Leslie P.|title=The Imperial Harem: Women and Sovereignty in the Ottoman Empire|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=L6-VRgVzRcUC&amp;pg=PA365&amp;dq=hanzade+sultan&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0CB8Q6AEwAWoVChMI876PrcL7yAIVybsUCh3eEwAh#v=onepage&amp;q=hanzade%20sultan&amp;f=false|year=1993|authorlink=Leslie P. Peirce|page=365|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|isbn=0195086775}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Hanzade Sultan]] (1607 – 23 September 1650, Constantinople, buried in Ibrahim I Mausoleum, Hagia Sophia Mosque), with Kösem;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kosem-children2&quot;/&gt;
*[[Atike Sultan (daughter of Ahmed I)|Atike Sultan]] (1613 – 1674, buried in Ibrahim I Mausoleum, Hagia Sophia Mosque);{{sfn|Uluçay|2011|p=52}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Sakaoğlu&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first=Necdet|last=Sakaoğlu|title=Bu mülkün kadın sultanları: Vâlide sultanlar, hâtunlar, hasekiler, kadınefendiler, sultanefendiler|publisher=Oğlak Yayıncılık|year=2008|page=235|isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ancestry==
{{ahnentafel
|collapsed=yes |align=center
|boxstyle_1=background-color: #fcc;
|boxstyle_2=background-color: #fb9;
|boxstyle_3=background-color: #ffc;
|boxstyle_4=background-color: #bfc;
|boxstyle_5=background-color: #9fe;
| 1 = 1. '''Ahmed I'''
| 2 = 2. [[Mehmed III]]
| 3 = 3. [[Handan Sultan]]
| 4 = 4. [[Murad III]]
| 5 = 5. [[Safiye Sultan (wife of Murad III)|Safiye Sultan]]
| 6 = 
| 7 = 
| 8 = 8. [[Selim II]]
| 9 = 9. [[Nurbanu Sultan]]
| 10 = 
| 11 = 
| 12 = 
| 13 = 
| 14 = 
| 15 = 
| 16 = 16. [[Suleiman the Magnificent|Suleiman I]]
| 17 = 17. [[Hurrem Sultan]]
| 18 =  
| 19 = 
| 20= 
| 21= 
| 22= 
| 23= 
| 24 = 
| 25 = 
| 28 = 
| 29 = 
| 30 = 
| 31 = 
}}

==Legacy==
Today, Ahmed I is remembered mainly for the construction of the [[Sultan Ahmed Mosque]] (also known as the Blue Mosque), one of the masterpieces of [[Islamic architecture]]. The area in [[Fatih]] around the Mosque is today called Sultanahmet. He died at [[Topkapı Palace]] in [[Constantinople]] and is buried in a mausoleum right outside the walls of the famous mosque.

==In popular culture==
In the 2015 TV series ''[[Muhteşem Yüzyıl: Kösem]]'', Ahmed I is portrayed by Turkish actor [[Ekin Koç]].

==See also==
*[[Transformation of the Ottoman Empire]]
* [[Abbas I's Kakhetian and Kartlian campaigns]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Commonscat-inline|Ahmed I}}

{{wikisource author-inline}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou|[[Ottoman Dynasty|House of Osman]]||April 18, 1590||November 22, 1617}}[aged 27]
{{s-reg|}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Mehmed III]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[List of sultans of the Ottoman Empire|Sultan of the Ottoman Empire]]|years=December 22, 1603 – November 22, 1617}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Mustafa I]]}}
{{s-rel|su}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Mehmed III]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[List of caliphs|Caliph of the Ottoman Caliphate]]|years=December 22, 1603 – November 22, 1617}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Mustafa I]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{Sultans of the Ottoman Empire}}
{{Sons of the Ottoman Sultans}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:1590 births]]
[[Category:1617 deaths]]
[[Category:Deaths from typhus]]
[[Category:Modern child rulers]]
[[Category:Ottoman people of the Ottoman–Persian Wars]]
[[Category:Infectious disease deaths in the Ottoman Empire]]
[[Category:17th-century Ottoman sultans]]
[[Category:Turks of the Ottoman Empire]]
[[Category:Greeks of the Ottoman Empire]]
[[Category:People of the Ottoman Empire of Greek descent]]
[[Category:Custodian of the Two Holy Mosques]]
[[Category:Ottoman dynasty]]</text>
      <sha1>012f3ughp1oowg1vvrxvirlyazuxf6w</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
