  <page>
    <title>Absalon</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1874</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937267579</id>
      <parentid>934276243</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-23T22:58:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Finlay McWalter</username>
        <id>22619</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Early life */ ill for Esbern Snare, for whom there is a dk article and who looks notable enough for one here, in time</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses|Absalon (disambiguation)}}

{{Infobox Bishop
| name = Absalon
| title = [[Bishop of Roskilde]]&lt;br&gt;[[Archbishop of Lund]]
| image = Copenhagen statue of Absalon.jpg
| imagesize = 235px
| caption = Statue of Absalon in Copenhagen
| diocese = [[Diocese of Roskilde]] (1158–1192)&lt;br&gt;[[Diocese of Lund|Archdiocese of Lund]] (1178–1201)
| predecessor = [[Asser of Roskilde]]&lt;br&gt;[[Eskil of Lund]]
| successor = [[Peder Sunesen]] (Roskilde)&lt;br&gt;[[Anders Sunesen]] (Lund)
| consecration =
| birth_name = Absalon
| birth_date = {{c.|1128}}
| birth_place = near [[Sorø]]
| death_date = {{death date and age|1201|3|21|1128|df=y}}
| death_place = [[Sorø]]
| buried = [[Sorø Abbey]]
}}
'''Absalon''' or '''Axel'''&lt;ref name=&quot;ea&quot;&gt;{{cite Americana|wstitle=Axel}}&lt;/ref&gt; ({{circa|1128}}{{snd}}21 March 1201) was a [[Denmark|Danish]] [[archbishop]] and statesman, who was the [[Bishop of Roskilde]] from 1158 to 1192 and [[Archbishop of Lund]] from 1178 until his death. He was the foremost politician and churchfather of Denmark in the second half of the 12th century, and was the closest advisor of King [[Valdemar I of Denmark]]. He was a key figure in the Danish policies of territorial expansion in the [[Baltic Sea]], [[Europeanization]] in close relationship with the [[Holy See]], and reform in the relation between the Church and the public. He combined the ideals of [[Gregorian Reform]] with loyal support of a strong [[monarch]]ical power.

Absalon was born into the powerful ''[[Hvide]]'' clan, and owned great land possessions. He endowed several church institutions, most prominently his family's [[Sorø Abbey]]. He was granted lands by the crown, and built the first fortification of the city that evolved into modern-day [[Copenhagen]]. His titles were passed on to his nephews [[Anders Sunesen]] and [[Peder Sunesen]]. He died in 1201, and was interred at Sorø Abbey.

==Early life==
Absalon was born around 1128 near [[Sorø]], [[Zealand (Denmark)|Zealand]].&lt;ref name=ea/&gt; Due to his name being unusual in Denmark, it is speculated that he was baptized on the Danish &quot;Absalon&quot; [[name day]], October 30.&lt;ref name=&quot;bricka&quot;/&gt; He was the son of [[Asser Rig]], a [[magnate]] of the ''[[Hvide]]'' clan from Fjenneslev on [[Zealand (Denmark)|Zealand]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;&gt;{{EB1911|inline=1|wstitle=Absalon|volume=1|pages=73–74}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Inger Eriksdotter]]. He was also a kinsman of [[Eskil of Lund|Archbishop Eskil of Lund]].&lt;ref name=&quot;bricka&quot;&gt;[[Carl Frederik Bricka]] (ed.), ''Dansk Biografisk Lexikon'', vol. I [Aaberg – Beaumelle], 1887. A.D. Jørgensen, &quot;Absalon&quot; [http://runeberg.org/dbl/1/0088.html pp.70–81]&lt;/ref&gt; He grew up at the castle of his father, and was brought up alongside his older brother {{ill|Esbern Snare|dk}} and the young prince Valdemar, who later became King [[Valdemar I of Denmark]].&lt;ref name=&quot;gyldendal&quot;/&gt; During the civil war following the death of [[Eric III of Denmark]] in 1146, Absalon travelled abroad to study [[theology]] in [[Paris]], while Esbern fought for Valdemar's ascension to the throne. At Paris, he was influenced by the [[Gregorian Reform]] ideals of churchly independence from Monarchical rule.&lt;ref name=&quot;gad&quot;&gt;&quot;Gads Historieleksikon&quot;, 3rd edition, 2006. Paul Ulff-Møller, &quot;''Absalon''&quot;, p.10. {{ISBN|978-87-12-04259-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also befriended the canon [[William of Æbelholt]] at the [[Abbey of St Genevieve]], whom he later made abbott of [[Eskilsø Abbey]].&lt;ref name=&quot;bricka&quot;/&gt;

Absalon first appears in [[Saxo Grammaticus]]'s contemporary chronicle ''[[Gesta Danorum]]'' at the end of the civil war, at the brokering of the peace agreement between [[Sweyn III of Denmark|Sweyn III]] and Valdemar at [[St. Alban's Priory, Odense]].&lt;ref name=&quot;bricka&quot;/&gt; He was a guest at the following [[Roskilde]] banquet given in 1157 by Sweyn to his rivals [[Canute V of Denmark|Canute V]] and Valdemar. Both Absalon and Valdemar narrowly escaped assassination at the hands of Sweyn on this occasion, and escaped to [[Jutland]], whither Sweyn followed them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;/&gt; Absalon probably did not take part in the following [[battle of Grathe Heath]] in 1157, in which Sweyn was defeated and slain, which led to Valdemar ascending to the Danish throne. On [[Good Friday]] 1158, bishop [[Asser of Roskilde]] died, and Absalon was eventually elected [[Roskilde (titular see)|bishop of Roskilde]] on Zealand with the help of Valdemar,&lt;ref name=&quot;bricka&quot;/&gt; as the king's reward for the ''Hvide'' family support.&lt;ref name=&quot;pajung&quot;&gt;Stefan Pajung, [http://www.danmarkshistorien.dk/leksikon-og-kilder/vis/materiale/absalon-ca-1128-1201/ Artikel: Absalon ca. 1128–1201], [[Aarhus University]], June 20, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==Bishop and advisor==
Absalon was a close counsellor of Valdemar, and chief promoter of the Danish [[crusade]]s against the [[Wends]].&lt;ref name=&quot;gyldendal&quot;/&gt; During the Danish civil war, Denmark had been open to coastal raids by the Wends.&lt;ref name=&quot;pajung&quot;/&gt; It was Absalon's intention to clear the [[Baltic Sea]] of the Wendish pirates who inhabited its southern [[littoral zone]] which was later called [[Pomerania]]. The pirates had raided the Danish coasts during the civil war of Sweyn III, Canute V, and Valdemar, to the point where at the accession of Valdemar one-third of Denmark lay wasted and depopulated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;/&gt; Absalon formed a guardian fleet, built coastal defenses, and led several campaigns against the Wends.&lt;ref name=&quot;pajung&quot;/&gt; He even advocated forgiving the earlier enemies of Valdemar, which helped stabilize Denmark internally.&lt;ref name=&quot;bricka&quot;/&gt;

===Wendish campaigns===
[[File:Bishop Absalon topples the god Svantevit at Arkona.PNG|266px|thumb|right|[[Laurits Tuxen]]: Bishop Absalon topples the god Svantevit at Arkona in 1169.]]
The first expedition against the [[Wends]], that was conducted by Absalon in person, set out in 1160.&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;/&gt; These expeditions were successful, but brought no lasting victories.&lt;ref name=&quot;bricka&quot;/&gt; What started out as mere retribution, eventually evolved into full-fledged campaigns of expansion with religious motives.&lt;ref name=&quot;pajung&quot;/&gt; In 1164 began twenty years of crusades against the Wends, sometimes with the help of German duke [[Henry the Lion]], sometimes in opposition to him.&lt;ref name=&quot;bricka&quot;/&gt;

In 1168 the chief Wendish fortress at [[Cape Arkona|Arkona]] in [[Rügen]], containing the sanctuary of their god [[Svetovid|Svantevit]], was conquered. The Wends agreed to accept Danish suzerainty and the [[Christian religion]] at the same time. From Arkona, Absalon proceeded by sea to [[Charenza]], in the midst of Rügen, the political capital of the Wends and an all but impregnable stronghold. But the unexpected fall of Arkona had terrified the garrison, which surrendered unconditionally at the first appearance of the Danish ships. Absalon, with only [[Sweyn of Aarhus|Bishop Sweyn of Aarhus]] and twelve &quot;[[housecarl]]s&quot;, thereupon disembarked, passed between a double row of Wendish warriors, 6000 strong, along the narrow path winding among the morasses, to the gates of the fortress, and, proceeding to the temple of the seven-headed god [[Rugiewit|Rugievit]], caused the idol to be hewn down, dragged forth and burnt. The whole population of [[Garz/Rügen|Garz]] was then baptized, and Absalon laid the foundations of twelve churches in the isle of Rügen.&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;/&gt; Rügen was then subjected to Absalon's Bishopric of Roskilde.&lt;ref name=&quot;pajung&quot;/&gt;

The destruction of this chief sally-port of the Wendish pirates enabled Absalon considerably to reduce the Danish fleet. But he continued to keep a watchful eye over the Baltic, and in 1170 destroyed another pirate stronghold, farther eastward, at [[Dziwnów]] on the isle of [[Wolin]]. Absalon's last military exploit came in 1184, off [[Stralsund]] at [[Whitsun]], when he soundly defeated a Pomeranian fleet that had attacked Denmark's vassal, [[Jaromar I, Prince of Rügen|Jaromar of Rügen]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;/&gt;

===Policies===
Absalon's main political goal was to free Denmark from entanglements with the [[Holy Roman Empire]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;/&gt; Absalon reformed the Danish church organisation to closer match [[Holy See]] praxis, and worked to keep Denmark a close ally of the Holy See.&lt;ref name=&quot;gyldendal&quot;/&gt; However, during the [[Schism (religion)|schism]] between [[Pope Alexander III]] and [[Antipope Victor IV (1159–1164)|Antipope Victor IV]], Absalon stayed loyal to Valdemar even as he joined the Holy Roman Emperor [[Frederick I, Holy Roman Emperor|Frederick Barbarossa]] in supporting Victor IV.&lt;ref name=&quot;pajung&quot;/&gt; This caused a split within the Danish church, as it possibly forced Eskil into exile around 1161,&lt;ref name=&quot;gyldendal&quot;/&gt; despite Abaslon's attempts to keep the Danish church united.&lt;ref name=&quot;bricka&quot;/&gt; It was contrary to Absalon's advice and warnings that Valdemar I rendered [[fealty]] to the emperor Frederick Barbarossa at [[Dole, Jura|Dole]] in 1162.&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;/&gt; When Valdemar returned to Denmark, he was convinced into strengthening the [[Danevirke]] fortifications at the German border, with the support of Absalon.&lt;ref name=&quot;bricka&quot;/&gt;

Absalon built churches and monasteries, supporting international religious orders like the [[Cistercians]] and [[Augustinians]], founding schools and doing his utmost to promote civilization and enlightenment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;/&gt; In 1162, Absalon transformed the [[Sorø Abbey]] of his family from [[Benedictine]] to Cistercian, granting it lands from his personal holdings. In 1167, Absalon was granted the land around the city of &quot;Havn&quot; (English: Harbour), and built there a castle in the coastal defense against the Wends.&lt;ref name=&quot;gyldendal&quot;/&gt; Havn quickly expanded as one of [[Scandinavia]]'s most important centers of trade, and eventually evolved into modern-day [[Copenhagen]].&lt;ref name=&quot;bricka&quot;/&gt; It was also Absalon who held the first Danish [[Synod]] at [[Lund]] in 1167.&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;/&gt; He was also interested in history and culture, and commissioned [[Saxo Grammaticus]] to write ''[[Gesta Danorum]]'', a comprehensive chronicle of the history of the Danes.&lt;ref name=&quot;pajung&quot;/&gt; In 1171, Absalon issued the &quot;Zealand church law&quot; ({{lang-da|Sjællandske Kirkelov}}), which reduced the number of [[Canonical Law]] offenses for which the church could fine the public, while instituting the [[tithe]] payment system. Violation of the law was specified as subject to a secular legal process.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.denstoredanske.dk/Samfund%2c_jura_og_politik/Jura/Retshistorie/kirkelove Kirkelove] at Gyldendals Åbne Encyklopædi&lt;/ref&gt;

==Archbishop of Lund==
Archbishop Eskil returned from exile in 1167. Eskil agreed on [[canonization|canonizing]] Valdemar's father [[Knud Lavard]] in 1170, with Absalon assisting him at the feast. When Eskil stepped down as Archbishop of Lund in 1177, he chose Absalon as his successor.&lt;ref name=&quot;pajung&quot;/&gt; Absalon initially resisted the new position, as he did not want to lose his power position on Zealand, but complied with Papal orders to do so in 1178.&lt;ref name=&quot;bricka&quot;/&gt; By a unique Papal dispensation, Absalon was allowed to simultaneously maintain his post as Bishop of Roskilde.&lt;ref name=&quot;gyldendal&quot;/&gt; As the Archbishop of Lund, Absalon utilized [[ombudsman|ombudsmen]] from Zealand, demanded [[unfree labour]] from the [[peasantry]], and instituted tithes.&lt;ref name=&quot;pajung&quot;/&gt; He was a harsh and effective ruler, who cleared all [[Orthodox Christian]] [[Liturgy|liturgical]] remnants in favour of Papal standards.&lt;ref name=&quot;gyldendal&quot;/&gt; A rebellion in the [[Scania]]n peasantry forced him to flee to Zealand in 1180, from where he returned and subdued the Scanians with the help of Valdemar.&lt;ref name=&quot;pajung&quot;/&gt;

When Valdemar died in 1182, his son succeeded him as [[Canute VI of Denmark|Canute VI]], and Absalon served as Canute VI's counsellor.&lt;ref name=&quot;pajung&quot;/&gt; Under Canute VI, Absalon was the chief policymaker in Danish politics.&lt;ref name=&quot;gad&quot;/&gt; Absalon kept his hostile attitude to the Holy Roman Empire. On the accession of Canute VI in 1182, an imperial ambassador arrived at Roskilde to get the new king to swear fealty to Frederick Barbarossa, but Absalon resolutely withstood him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;/&gt;

===Death===
[[File:Absalons ligsten.jpg|thumb|200px|right|Absalon's gravestone in Sorø Abbey.]]
When Absalon retired from military service in 1184 at the age of fifty-seven, he resigned the command of fleets and armies to younger men, like Duke Valdemar, the later king [[Valdemar II of Denmark|Valdemar II]]. He instead confined himself to the administration of the Danish empire.&lt;ref name=&quot;bricka&quot;/&gt; In 1192, Absalon made his nephew [[Peder Sunesen]] his successor as Bishop of Roskilde, while his other nephew [[Anders Sunesen]] was named the [[chancellor]] of Canute VI.&lt;ref name=&quot;pajung&quot;/&gt; Absalon died at Sorø Abbey on March 21, 1201, 73 years old, with his last will granting his personal holdings to the Abbey, apart from Fjenneslev which went to Esbern Snarre. He had already given Copenhagen to the Bishopric of Roskilde.&lt;ref name=&quot;bricka&quot;/&gt; Absalon was interred at  [[Sorø Klosterkirke|Sorø Abbey]],&lt;ref name=&quot;pajung&quot;/&gt; and was succeeded as Archbishop of Lund by Anders Sunesen.&lt;ref name=&quot;gyldendal&quot;/&gt;

==Legacy==
Saxo Grammaticus' ''Gesta Danorum'' was not finished until after the death of Absalon,&lt;ref name=&quot;gyldendal&quot;/&gt; but Absalon was one of the chief heroic figures of the chronicle, which was to be the main source of knowledge about early Danish history.&lt;ref name=&quot;pajung&quot;/&gt; Absalon left a legacy as the foremost politician and churchfather of Denmark in the 12th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;gyldendal&quot;&gt;[http://www.denstoredanske.dk/Danmarks_geografi_og_historie/Danmarks_historie/Danmark_f%C3%B8r_Reformationen/Absalon Absalon] at Gyldendals Åbne Encyklopædi&lt;/ref&gt; Absalon was equally great as churchman, statesman, and warrior. His policy of expansion was to give Denmark the dominion of the Baltic for three generations. That he enjoyed warfare there can be no doubt; yet he was not like the ordinary fighting bishops of the [[Middle Ages]], whose sole indication of their religious role was to avoid the ''shedding of blood'' by using a [[Mace (bludgeon)|mace]] in battle instead of a sword. Absalon never neglected his ecclesiastical duties.&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;/&gt;

In the 2000s, &quot;Absalon&quot; was adopted as the name for a class of [[Royal Danish Navy]] vessels, and the lead vessel of the class. [[HDMS Absalon (L16)]] and ''Esbern Snare'' (L17) were launched and commissioned by [[Denmark]] in 2004 and 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://forsvaret.dk/2ESK/ENHEDER/FS/ABSL/Pages/default.aspx |title=Forsvaret.dk |accessdate=2010-03-25 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090210080938/http://forsvaret.dk/2ESK/Enheder/FS/ABSL/Pages/default.aspx |archivedate=2009-02-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.naval-technology.com/projects/absalon/absalon2.html Absalon Class Combat / Flexible Support Ship, Denmark] naval-technology.com  {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080915103734/http://www.naval-technology.com/projects/absalon/absalon2.html |date=September 15, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* Saxo, ''[[Gesta Danorum]],'' ed. Holder (Strassburg, 1886), books xvi.
* Steenstrup, ''Danmarks Riges Historie. Oldtiden og den ældre Middelalder,'' pp.&amp;nbsp;570–735 (Copenhagen, 1897–1905).
* Absalon's ''Testamentum,'' in [[Jacques Paul Migne|Migne]], ''[[Patrologia Latina]]'' 209,18.

==External links==
* {{cite NIE|wstitle=Axel |year=1905 |short=x}}
* {{cite AmCyc|wstitle=Absalon |short=x}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Absalon}}
[[Category:Roman Catholic archbishops of Lund]]
[[Category:1120s births]]
[[Category:1201 deaths]]
[[Category:12th-century Roman Catholic archbishops]]
[[Category:Burials at Sorø Abbey]]
[[Category:Royal Danish Navy]]
[[Category:12th-century Danish people]]</text>
      <sha1>mgyxbmkr4p1ph21xehkr9swuhtlka9l</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
