  <page>
    <title>Alexander Kerensky</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2543</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942019293</id>
      <parentid>940616887</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-22T02:26:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Epicgenius</username>
        <id>17859592</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>fix link to St. Luke's–Roosevelt Hospital Center which was split into two hospitals</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|the Russian politician|the fictional character|List of BattleTech characters#Aleksandr Kerensky}}
{{Short description|Russian politician}}
{{EngvarB|date=March 2015}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2015}}

{{Infobox officeholder
| name = Alexander Kerensky
| native_name = {{lang|ru|Алекса́ндр Ке́ренский}}
| image = Karenskiy AF 1917.jpg
| caption = 
| nationality = Russian
| office = [[Prime Minister of Russia|Minister-Chairman]] of the [[Russian Provisional Government]]
| term_start = 21 July 1917
| term_end = 7 November 1917&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;[8 July – 26 October 1917 [[Old Style]]]&lt;/small&gt;
| monarch = Vacant
| predecessor = [[Georgy Lvov]]
| successor = ''Office abolished''&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;([[Vladimir Lenin]] as [[Chairman of the Council of People's Commissars]])&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[Nikolai Avksentiev]] as Chairman of the [[Provisional All-Russian Government]]
| office1 = Minister of War and Navy of the Russian Provisional Government
| term_start1 = 18 May 1917
| term_end1 = 14 September 1917&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;[5 May – 1 September 1917 Old Style]&lt;/small&gt;
| primeminister1 = [[Georgy Lvov]]&lt;br/&gt;Himself
| predecessor1 = [[Alexander Guchkov]]
| successor1 = [[Aleksandr Verkhovsky]]
| office2 = Minister of Justice of the Russian Provisional Government
| term_start2 = 16 March 1917
| term_end2 = 1 May 1917&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;[3 March – 18 April 1917 Old Style]&lt;/small&gt;
| primeminister2 = Georgy Lvov
| predecessor2 = ''Office established''&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;Nikolai [[Dobrovolsky]] as [[List of Ministers of Justice of Imperial Russia|Minister of Justice]] of the Russian Empire&lt;/small&gt;
| successor2 = [[Pavel Pereverzev]]
| birth_name = Alexander Fyodorovich Kerensky
| birth_date = 4 May 1881
| birth_place = [[Ulyanovsk|Simbirsk]], [[Simbirsk Governorate]], [[Russian Empire]]
| death_date = 11 June 1970 (aged 89)
| death_place = [[New York City]], United States
| restingplace = [[Putney Vale Cemetery]], [[London]], England
| education = [[Saint Petersburg State University]]
| profession = Lawyer, politician
| party = [[Socialist Revolutionary Party|Socialist Revolutionary]] ([[Trudovik]] Parliamentary breakaway group)
| children = [[Oleg Kerensky]], Gleb Karensky
| signature = Kerensky autograph.svg
}}
'''Alexander Fyodorovich Kerensky''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|k|ɛ|r|ə|n|s|k|i|,_|k|ə|ˈ|r|ɛ|n|s|k|i}} {{respell|KERR|ən|skee|,_|kə|REN|skee}}; {{lang-ru|link=no|Алекса́ндр Фёдорович Ке́ренский}}, {{IPA-ru|ɐlʲɪkˈsandr ˈkʲerʲɪnskʲɪj|IPA}}; [[Reforms of Russian orthography|original spelling]]: {{lang|ru|Александръ Ѳедоровичъ Керенскій}}; {{OldStyleDate|4 May|1881|22 April}} – 11 June 1970) was a Russian lawyer and [[revolutionary]] who was a key political figure in the [[Russian Revolution]] of 1917. After the [[February Revolution|February Revolution of 1917]], he joined the newly formed [[Russian Provisional Government]], first as [[Justice ministry|Minister of Justice]], then as [[Minister of War]], and after July as the government's [[List of heads of government of Russia#Russian Provisional Republic|second]] [[Prime Minister of Russia|Minister-Chairman]]. A leader of the moderate-socialist [[Trudovik]] faction of the [[Socialist Revolutionary Party]], he was also vice-chairman of the powerful [[Petrograd Soviet]]. On 7 November, his government was overthrown by the [[Vladimir Lenin|Lenin]]-led [[Bolshevik]]s in the [[October Revolution]]. He spent the remainder of his life in exile, in Paris and New York City, and worked for the [[Hoover Institution]].

==Early life and activism==
Alexander Kerensky was born in Simbirsk (now [[Ulyanovsk]]) on the [[Volga River]] on 4 May 1881 and was the eldest son in the family.&lt;ref name=wwi&gt;{{cite web|title=Alexander Kerenski|url=http://www.firstworldwar.com/bio/kerenski.htm|publisher=First World War|accessdate=1 April 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; His father, Fyodor Mikhailovich Kerensky, was a teacher&lt;ref name=wwi/&gt; and director of the local [[gymnasium (school)|gymnasium]] and was later promoted to be an inspector of public schools. His maternal grandfather was head of the Topographical Bureau of the [[Kazan]] [[Military district (Russian Empire)|Military District]]. His mother, Nadezhda Aleksandrovna (née Adler),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=N. Magill |first=Frank |date=5 March 2014 |title=The 20th Century Go-N: Dictionary of World Biography, Volume 8 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=I3sBAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA1944 |location= |publisher=Routledge |page=1941 |isbn=978-1-317-74060-5 |author-link= }}&lt;/ref&gt; was the granddaughter of a former [[serf]] who had managed to purchase his freedom before [[Emancipation reform of 1861|serfdom was abolished in 1861]]. He subsequently embarked upon a mercantile career, in which he prospered. This allowed him to move his business to Moscow, where he continued his success, and became a wealthy Moscow merchant.&lt;ref name=eternal&gt;{{cite web|title=Александр Федорович Керенский |url=http://eternaltown.com.ua/%D0%B1%D0%B8%D0%BE%D0%B3%D1%80%D0%B0%D1%84%D0%B8%D0%B8/2920/ |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140725092037/http://eternaltown.com.ua/%D0%B1%D0%B8%D0%BE%D0%B3%D1%80%D0%B0%D1%84%D0%B8%D0%B8/2920/ |url-status = dead|archive-date=2014-07-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://mega.km.ru/bes_2004/encyclop.asp?TopicNumber=31562&amp;search=%EA%E5%F0%E5%ED%F1%EA%E8%E9 Encyclopedia of Cyril and Method]{{dead link|date=July 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kerensky's father was the teacher of [[Vladimir Lenin|Vladimir Ulyanov (Lenin)]], and members of the Kerensky and Ulyanov families were friends. In 1889, when Kerensky was eight, the family moved to [[Tashkent]], where his father had been appointed the main inspector of public schools (superintendent). Alexander graduated with honours in 1899. The same year he entered [[St. Petersburg University]], where he studied history and [[philology]]. The next year he switched to law. He earned his law degree in 1904 and married Olga Lvovna Baranovskaya, the daughter of a Russian general, the same year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stanfordalumni.org/news/magazine/2001/janfeb/features/kerensky.html A Doomed Democracy] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070311025735/http://www.stanfordalumni.org/news/magazine/2001/janfeb/features/kerensky.html# |date=11 March 2007 }} Bernard Butcher, Stanford Magazine, January/February 2001&lt;/ref&gt; Kerensky joined the [[Narodnik]] movement and worked as a legal counsel to victims of the [[Revolution of 1905]]. At the end of 1904, he was jailed on suspicion of belonging to a militant group. Afterwards he gained a reputation for his work as a defence lawyer in a number of political trials of revolutionaries.&lt;ref&gt;Political Figures of Russia, 1917, Biographical Dictionary, Large Russian Encyclopedia, 1993, p. 143.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1912, Kerensky became widely known when he visited the goldfields at the [[Lena River]] and published material about the [[Lena Minefields incident]].&lt;ref&gt;The Lena Goldfields Massacre and the Crisis of the Late Tsarist State by Michael Melancon [https://books.google.com/books?id=ymYJfA3mx2kC&amp;pg=PA112]&lt;/ref&gt; In the same year, Kerensky was elected to the [[Fourth Duma]] as a member of the [[Trudoviks]], a moderate, non-Marxist [[Labour movement|labour party]] founded by [[Alexis Theodorovich Aladin|Alexis Aladin]] that was associated with the [[Socialist-Revolutionary Party]], and joined a [[Freemason]] society uniting the anti-monarchy forces that strived for the democratic renewal of Russia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://russiapedia.rt.com/prominent-russians/politics-and-society/aleksandr-kerensky/ | title=Prominent Russians: Aleksandr Kerensky | publisher=RT|location=Russia | accessdate=23 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://digital.library.okstate.edu/oas/oas_pdf/v51/p127_130.pdf |title=Alexander Fedorovich Kerensky |author=Medlin, Virgil D. |journal=Proceedings of the Oklahoma Academy of Science |year=1971 |volume=51 |pages=128 |url-status = dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304051142/http://digital.library.okstate.edu/oas/oas_pdf/v51/p127_130.pdf |archivedate=4 March 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.omolenko.com/en/rasputin/tatyana-mironova-belied-life-belied-death.htm|title=Grigori Rasputin: Belied Life - Belied Death|website=www.omolenko.com|accessdate=20 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, the Socialist Revolutionary Party bought Kerensky a house, as he otherwise wouldn't be elective for the Duma, according to the Russian property-laws. He then soon became a significant Duma member of the ''Progressive Block'', which included several Socialist Parties, [[Mensheviks]], and Liberals - but not the [[Bolsheviks]].&lt;ref&gt;TV-documentary &quot;Russian Revolution seen from Russia&quot; aired at Danish [[DR K]] 11.June.2018&lt;/ref&gt; He was a brilliant orator and skilled parliamentary leader of the socialist opposition to the government of Tsar [[Nicholas II of Russia|Nicholas II]].

During the 4th Session of the Fourth Duma in spring 1915, Kerensky appealed to [[Rodzianko]] with a request from the Council of elders to inform the Tsar that to succeed in war he must:
1) change his domestic policy,
2) proclaim a General Amnesty for political prisoners,
3) restore the Constitution of Finland,
4) declare the autonomy of Poland,
5) provide national minorities autonomy in the field of culture,
6) abolish restrictions against Jews,
7) end religious intolerance,
8) stop the harassment of legal trade union organizations.

Kerensky was an active member of the irregular [[Freemasonic]] lodge, the [[Grand Orient of Russia's Peoples]],&lt;ref name=&quot;mason&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
|url= http://freemasonry.bcy.ca/texts/russia/russian_masons.html
|title= Noteworthy members of the Grand Orient of France in Russia and the Supreme Council of the Grand Orient of Russia's People
|date= 15 October 2017
|work= Grand Lodge of British Columbia and Yukon
|page=  
}}&lt;/ref&gt; which derived from the [[Grand Orient of France]]. Kerensky was Secretary General of the Grand Orient of Russia's Peoples and stood down following his ascent to government in July 1917. He was succeeded by the Menshevik, [[Alexander Halpern]].

==Rasputin==
In response to bitter resentments held against the imperial favourite [[Grigori Rasputin]] in the midst of Russia's failing effort in [[World War I]], Kerensky, at the opening of the Duma on 2 November 1916, called the imperial ministers &quot;hired assassins&quot; and &quot;cowards&quot;, and alleged that they were &quot;guided by the contemptible Grishka Rasputin!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''The Russian Provisional Government, 1917'': Documents, Volume 1, p. 16 by Robert Paul Browder, Aleksandr Fyodorovich Kerensky [https://books.google.com/books?id=LzWsAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA16]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Grand Duke Nicholas Mikhailovich of Russia|Grand Duke Nikolai Mikhailovich]], [[Georgy Lvov|Prince Lvov]], and general [[Mikhail Alekseyev]] attempted to persuade the emperor [[Nicholas II of Russia|Nicholas II]] to send away the Empress [[Alexandra Feodorovna (Alix of Hesse)|Alexandra Feodorovna]], Rasputin's steadfast patron, either to the [[Livadia Palace]] in Yalta or to England.&lt;ref&gt;A. Kerensky (1965) ''Russia and History's turning point'', p. 150.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mikhail Rodzianko]], [[Zinaida Yusupova]] (the mother of [[Felix Yusupov]]), Alexandra's sister [[Princess Elisabeth of Hesse and by Rhine (1864–1918)|Elisabeth]], [[Princess Victoria Melita of Saxe-Coburg and Gotha|Grand Duchess Victoria]] and the empress's mother-in-law [[Maria Feodorovna (Dagmar of Denmark)|Maria Feodorovna]] also tried to influence and pressure the imperial couple&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.alexanderpalace.org/realtsaritsa/1chap5.html|title=Alexandra Feodorovna and Romanov Russia, The Real Tsaritsa witten by Lili Dehn - Part One - Old Russia - Chapter V|website=www.alexanderpalace.org|accessdate=20 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; to remove Rasputin from his position of influence within the imperial household, but without success.&lt;ref&gt;''The Russian Provisional Government, 1917'': Documents, Volume 1, p. 18 by Robert Paul Browder, Aleksandr Fyodorovich Kerensky [https://books.google.com/books?id=LzWsAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA18]&lt;/ref&gt; According to Kerensky, Rasputin had terrorised the empress by threatening to return to his native village.&lt;ref&gt;A. Kerensky (1965) ''Russia and History's turning point'', p. 163.&lt;/ref&gt;

Monarchists murdered Rasputin in December 1916, burying him near the imperial residence in [[Tsarskoye Selo]]. Shortly after the [[February Revolution]] of 1917, Kerensky ordered soldiers to re-bury the corpse at an unmarked spot in the countryside. However, the truck broke down or was forced to stop because of the snow on Lesnoe Road outside of St. Petersburg. It is likely the corpse was incinerated (between 3 and 7 in the morning) in the [[cauldron]]s of the nearby boiler shop&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.encspb.ru/object/2804023731?lc=en Rasputin G. E. (1869–1916)]. A.G. Kalmykov in the Saint Petersburg encyclopaedia.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Nelipa|Nelipa]], pp. 454–455, 457–459.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Moe|Moe]], p. 627.&lt;/ref&gt; of the [[Saint Petersburg State Polytechnical University]], including the coffin, without leaving a single trace.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nlr.ru/petersburg/spbpcards/photos/lo000000328_1_m.jpg|title=The boiler-building – Images of St Petersburg – National Library of Russia|publisher=|accessdate=20 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Russian Provisional Government of 1917 ==
[[File:Kerensky war minister.jpeg|thumb|Kerensky as Minister of War (sitting second from the right)]]

When the [[February Revolution]] broke out in 1917, Kerensky - together with [[Pavel Milyukov]] - was one of its most prominent leaders. As one of the [[Duma]]'s most well-known speakers against the monarchy and as a lawyer and defender of many revolutionaries, Kerensky became a member of the [[Provisional Committee of the State Duma]] and was elected vice-chairman of the newly formed [[Petrograd Soviet]]. These two bodies, the Duma and the Petrograd Soviet, or - rather - their respective executive committees, soon became each other's antagonists on most matters except regarding the end of the Tsar's autocracy.

The Petrograd Soviet grew to include 3000 to 4000 members, and their meetings could drown in a blur of everlasting orations. At the meeting of {{OldStyleDate|12 March|1917|27 February}} to {{OldStyleDate|13 March|1917|28 February}} the '''Executive Committee of the Petrograd Soviet''' or [[Ispolkom]] formed - a self-appointed committee, with (eventually) three members from each of the parties represented in the Soviet. Kerensky became one of the members representing the [[Socialist Revolutionary Party|Social Revolutionary party]] (the SRs).&lt;ref&gt;Richard Pipes,1995, &quot;The Russian Revolution&quot;, p104-106,s ''Swedish'' {{ISBN|91-27-09935-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On {{OldStyleDate|14 March|1917|1 March}}, without any consultation with the government, the Ispolkom of the Soviet issued the infamous [[Petrograd Soviet Order No. 1|Order No. 1]], intended only for the 160,000-strong Petrograd garrison, but soon interpreted as applicable to all soldiers at the front. The order stipulated that all military units should form committees like the Petrograd Soviet. This led to confusion and &quot;stripping of officers' authority&quot;; further, &quot;Order No. 3&quot; stipulated that the military was subordinate to Ispolkom in the political hierarchy. The ideas came from a group of Socialists and aimed to limit the officers' power to military affairs. The socialist intellectuals believed the officers to be the most likely counterrevolutionary elements. Kerensky's role in these orders are unclear, but he participated in the decisions. But just as before the revolution he had defended many who disliked the Tsar, he now saved the lives of many{{quantify|date=March 2019}} of the Tsar's civil servants about to be lynched by mobs.&lt;ref&gt;Pipes, p.110&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, the Duma formed an executive committee which eventually became the so-called [[Russian Provisional Government]]. As there was little trust between Ispolkom and this Government (and as he was about to accept the office of Attorney General in the Provisional Government), Kerensky gave a most passionate speech, not just to the Ispolkom, but to the entire Petrograd Soviet. He then swore, as Minister, never to violate democratic values, and ended his speech with the words &quot;I cannot live without the people. In the moment you begin to doubt me, then kill me.&quot; The huge majority (workers and soldiers) gave him great applause, and Kerensky now became the first and ''the only one''{{citation needed|date=March 2019}} who participated in both the Provisional Government and the Ispolkom. As a link between Ispolkom and the Provisional Government, the quite ambitious Kerensky stood to benefit from this position.&lt;ref&gt;Pipes, p. 110&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1970/06/12/archives/alexander-kerensky-dies-here-at-89-alexander-kerensky-who-led-first.html|title=Alexander Kerensky Dies Here at 89|last=Whitman|first=Alden|date=12 June 1970|website=The New York Times|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
After the first government crisis over [[Pavel Milyukov]]'s secret note re-committing Russia to its original war-aims on 2–4 May, Kerensky became the [[Minister of War]] and the dominant figure in the newly-formed socialist-liberal coalition government. On 10 May ([[Julian calendar]]), Kerensky started for the front and visited one division after another, urging the men to do their duty. His speeches were impressive and convincing for the moment, but had little lasting effect.{{citation needed|date=March 2019}} Under [[Allies of World War I|Allied]] pressure to continue the war, he launched what became known as the [[Kerensky Offensive]] against the Austro-Hungarian/German South Army on {{OldStyleDate|1 July|1917|18 June}}.&lt;ref&gt;Preclík, Vratislav. Masaryk a legie (Masaryk and legions), váz. kniha, 219 pages, first issue vydalo nakladatelství Paris Karviná, Žižkova 2379 (734 01 Karvina, Czech Republic) ve spolupráci s Masarykovým demokratickým hnutím (Masaryk Democratic Movement, Prague), 2019, {{ISBN|978-80-87173-47-3}}, pages 36 - 39, 41 - 42, 111-112, 124–125, 128, 129, 132, 140–148, 184–199.&lt;/ref&gt;  At first successful, the offensive soon met strong resistance and the [[Central Powers]] riposted with a strong counter-attack. The Russian army retreated and suffered heavy losses, and it became clear from the many incidents of desertion, sabotage, and mutiny that the army was no longer willing to attack.

[[File:KéresnkiEnUnDiscursoALosSoldadosDelFrenteMayo1917.png|thumb|left|Kerensky in May 1917]]

The military heavily criticised Kerensky for his liberal policies, which included stripping officers of their mandates and handing over control to revolutionary-inclined &quot;soldier committees&quot; ({{lang-ru |солдатские комитеты | translit = soldatskie komitety}}) instead; the abolition of the death penalty; and allowing revolutionary agitators to be present at the front. Many officers jokingly referred to commander-in-chief Kerensky as the &quot;persuader-in-chief&quot;

On 2 July 1917 the Provisional Government's first coalition collapsed over the question of [[Ukraine]]'s autonomy. Following the [[July Days]] unrest in Petrograd  (3–7 July [16–20 July, N.S.] 1917) and the official suppression of the Bolsheviks, Kerensky succeeded [[Georgy Lvov|Prince Lvov]] as Russia's Prime Minister on {{OldStyleDate| 21 July|1917| 8 July}}. Following the [[Kornilov Affair]], an attempted military [[coup d'état]] at the end of August, and the resignation of the other ministers, he appointed himself Supreme [[Commander-in-Chief]] as well.

On 15 September Kerensky proclaimed Russia a republic, which was contrary to the non-socialists' understanding that the Provisional Government should hold power only until a [[Russian Constituent Assembly|Constituent Assembly]] should meet to decide Russia's form of government, but which was in line with the long-proclaimed aim of the Socialist Revolutionary Party.&lt;ref&gt;Party manifesto listed in McCauley, M ''Octobrists to Bolsheviks: Imperial Russia 1905‐1917'' (1984)&lt;/ref&gt; He formed a five-member Directory, which consisted of himself, Minister of Foreign Affairs [[Mikhail Tereshchenko]], Minister of War General {{Interlanguage link|Aleksandr Verkhovsky|ru|Верховский, Александр Иванович}}, Minister of the Navy Admiral [[Dmitry Verderevsky]] and Minister of Posts and Telegraphs {{Interlanguage link|Aleksei Nikitin (politician)|ru|Никитин, Алексей Максимович|lt=Aleksei Nikitin}}. He retained his post in the final coalition government in October 1917 until the Bolsheviks overthrew it on {{OldStyleDate|7 November|1917|26 October}}.

[[File:Kerensky.jpg|thumb|upright|Kerensky in office]]
Kerensky faced a major challenge: three years of participation in World War had exhausted Russia, while the provisional government offered little motivation for a victory outside of continuing Russia's obligations towards its allies. Russia's continued involvement in the war was not popular among the lower and middle classes, and especially not popular among the soldiers. They had all believed that Russia would stop fighting when the Provisional Government took power,{{citation needed|date=March 2019}} and subsequently felt deceived. Furthermore, [[Vladimir Lenin]] and his [[Bolshevik]] party were promising &quot;peace, land, and bread&quot; under a communist system. The [[Russian Army (1917)|Russian army]], war-weary, ill-equipped, dispirited and ill-disciplined, was disintegrating, with soldiers deserting in large numbers. By autumn 1917, an estimated two million men had unofficially left the army.

Kerensky and the other political leaders continued Russia's involvement in World War I, thinking that nothing but a glorious victory was the only road forward,&lt;ref&gt;Pipes p.121&lt;/ref&gt; and fearing that the economy, already under huge stress from the war effort, might become increasingly unstable if vital supplies from France and from the United Kingdom ceased flowing. The dilemma of whether to withdraw was a great one, and Kerensky's inconsistent and impractical policies further destabilised the army and the country at large.

Furthermore, Kerensky adopted a policy that isolated the right-wing conservatives, both democratic and monarchist-oriented. His philosophy of &quot;no enemies to the left&quot; greatly empowered the Bolsheviks and gave them a free hand, allowing them to take over the military arm or &quot;voyenka&quot; ({{lang-ru |Военка}}) of the Petrograd and Moscow Soviets.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Russian Moderates and the Crisis of Tsarism 1914 – 1917|last=Pearson|first=Raymond|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan UK|year=1977|isbn=978-1-349-03385-0|pages=126–127}}&lt;/ref&gt; His arrest of [[Lavr Kornilov]] and other officers left him without strong allies against the Bolsheviks, who ended up being Kerensky's strongest and most determined adversaries, as opposed to the right wing, which evolved into the [[White movement]].

==October Revolution of 1917==
During the [[Kornilov Affair]], Kerensky had distributed arms to the [[Petrograd]] workers, and by November most of these armed workers had gone over to the Bolsheviks.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Estonians; The long road to independence|last=Faure and Mensing|first=Gunter and Teresa|publisher=Lulu|year=2012|isbn=1105530035|pages=161}}&lt;/ref&gt; On {{OldStyleDateNY|6–7 November|25–26 October}} 1917, the Bolsheviks launched the [[October Revolution|second Russian revolution]] of the year. Kerensky's government in Petrograd had almost no support in the city. Only one small force, a subdivision of the 2nd company of the [[Women's Battalion#1st Petrograd Women.27s Battalion|First Petrograd Women's Battalion]], also known as The Women's Death Battalion, was willing to fight for the government against the Bolsheviks, but this force was overwhelmed by the numerically superior pro-Bolshevik forces, defeated, and captured.&lt;ref name=gwar&gt;{{cite web|title=Women Soldiers in Russia's Great War|url=http://russiasgreatwar.org/media/military/women_soldiers.shtml|publisher=Great War|accessdate=1 April 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Bolsheviks overthrew the government rapidly by seizing governmental buildings and the Winter Palace.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The History Book: Big Ideas Simply Explained|last=DK|publisher=DK|year=2016|isbn=1465445102|pages=278}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kerensky escaped the Bolsheviks and fled to [[Pskov]], where he rallied some loyal troops for an [[Kerensky–Krasnov uprising|attempt to re-take the city]]. His troops managed to capture [[Tsarskoe Selo]] but were beaten the next day at [[Pulkovo Heights|Pulkovo]]. Kerensky narrowly escaped, and he spent the next few weeks in hiding before fleeing the country, eventually arriving in France. During the [[Russian Civil War]], he supported neither side, as he opposed both the Bolshevik regime and the [[White Movement]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bl.uk/people/alexander-kerensky|title=Alexander Kerensky|website=British Library|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
[[File:Alexander Kerensky LOC hec 24462.jpg|thumb|upright|Kerensky at the [[National Press Club (USA)|National Press Club]] in 1938]]
Kerensky was married to Olga Lvovna Baranovskaya and they had two sons, [[Oleg Kerensky|Oleg]] and Gleb, who both went on to become engineers. Kerensky's grandson (also named Oleg), according to IMDb.com, played his grandfather's role in the 1981 film ''[[Reds (film)|Reds]]''. Kerensky and Olga were divorced in 1939 and soon after he settled in Paris, and while visiting the United States he met and married, in 1939, the Australian former journalist [[Lydia Ellen Tritton|Lydia Ellen &quot;Nell&quot; Tritton]] (1899–1946). The marriage took place in [[Martins Creek, Pennsylvania]].

When [[Battle of France|Germany invaded France in 1940]], they emigrated to the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://adb.anu.edu.au/biography/tritton-lydia-ellen-nell-11879|title=Australian Dictionary of Biography|first=Judith|last=Armstrong|publisher=National Centre of Biography, Australian National University|accessdate=20 January 2019|via=Australian Dictionary of Biography}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the [[Operation Barbarossa|Axis invasion of the Soviet Union]] in 1941, Kerensky offered his support to [[Joseph Stalin]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=gEwEAAAAMBAJ&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA76 Soviet's Chances]. By Alexander Kerensky. ''[[Life (magazine)|Life]]'', 14 July 1941, pp. 76-78, 81.&lt;/ref&gt; When his wife Nell became terminally ill in 1945, Kerensky travelled with her to [[Brisbane]], Australia, and lived there with her family. She suffered a stroke in February 1946, and he remained there until her death on 10 April 1946. Kerensky then returned to the United States, where he spent the rest of his life.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.abc.net.au/lateline/content/2003/hc40.htm|title=Lateline - 22/09/2003: The Half-Hearted Revolutionary In Paradise . Australian Broadcasting Corp|website=www.abc.net.au|access-date=2017-03-20|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160731094019/http://www.abc.net.au/lateline/content/2003/hc40.htm|archive-date=31 July 2016|url-status = dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kerensky eventually settled in New York City, living on the [[Upper East Side]] on [[91st Street (Manhattan)|91st Street]] near [[Central Park]]&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1970/06/12/archives/alexander-kerensky-dies-here-at-89-alexander-kerensky-who-led-first.html?mcubz=3|title=Alexander Kerensky Dies Here at 89|newspaper=New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; but spent much of his time at the [[Hoover Institution]] at [[Stanford University]] in California, where he both used and contributed to the Institution's huge archive on [[Russian history]], and where he taught graduate courses. He wrote and broadcast extensively on Russian politics and history.

[[File:Alexander Kerensky grave Putney Vale 2014.jpg|thumb|alt=Two white marble gravestones surmounted by Orthodox crosses|The graves of Alexander Kerensky (left), and of his first wife, Olga, and his son Oleg and Oleg's wife,  Mary, at [[Putney Vale Cemetery]], London, 2014]]
Kerensky died  of [[arteriosclerotic heart disease]]&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes&quot; /&gt; at [[Mount Sinai Morningside|St. Luke's Hospital]]  in New York City&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes&quot; /&gt; in 1970, one of the last surviving major participants in the turbulent events of 1917. The [[Russian Orthodox Church Outside Russia|local Russian Orthodox Church]]es in New York City refused to grant Kerensky burial because of his association with [[Freemasonry]], and because they saw him as largely responsible for the Bolsheviks seizing power. A [[Serbian Orthodox Church]] also refused burial. Kerensky's body was flown to London, where he was buried at the non-denominational [[Putney Vale Cemetery]].

==Works==
* [https://archive.org/details/preludetobolshev008537mbp ''The Prelude to Bolshevism''] (1919). {{ISBN|0-8383-1422-8}}.
* [https://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/kerensky/1927/catastrophe/index.htm ''The Catastrophe''] (1927)
* ''The Crucifixion of Liberty'' (1934)
* ''Russia and History's Turning Point'' (1965)

==In popular culture==
*Kerensky was portrayed in the 1971 film ''[[Nicholas and Alexandra]]'' by [[John McEnery]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1971/12/14/archives/nicholas-and-alexandra-depicts-fall-of-romanovs.html|title=' Nicholas and Alexandra' Depicts Fall of Romanovs|first=Vincent|last=Canby|date=14 December 1971|publisher=|accessdate=20 January 2019|via=NYTimes.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*In the 2008 film [[The Admiral (2008 film)|''The Admiral'']], Kerensky is portrayed by [[Viktor Verzhbitsky]].
* In the 2019 [[Netflix]] series &quot;The Last Czars&quot; Kerensky is portrayed by Kestutis Cicenas

==See also==
* [[Jailbirds of Kerensky]]

==References==
{{Reflist|33em}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |first=Richard |last=Abraham |title=Kerensky: First Love of the Revolution |location= |publisher=Columbia University Press |year=1987 |isbn=0-231-06108-0 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/alexanderkerensk00abra_0 }}
* Lipatova, Nadezhda V. &quot;On the Verge of the Collapse of Empire: Images of Alexander Kerensky and Mikhail Gorbachev.&quot; ''Europe-Asia Studies'' 65.2 (2013): 264-289.
* Thatcher, Ian D. &quot;Post-Soviet Russian Historians and the Russian Provisional Government of 1917.&quot; ''Slavonic &amp; East European Review'' 93.2 (2015): 315-337. [https://www.academia.edu/download/37716650/slaveasteurorev2.93.2.0315.pdf online]{{Dead link|date=July 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}
* Thatcher, Ian D. &quot;Memoirs of the Russian Provisional Government 1917.&quot; ''Revolutionary Russia'' 27.1 (2014): 1-21.

==External links==
{{Commons category|Alexander Kerensky}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Alexander Kerensky}}
*[https://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/kerensky/ Alexander Kerensky Archive] at [[marxists.org]]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20070311025735/http://www.stanfordalumni.org/news/magazine/2001/janfeb/features/kerensky.html An account of Kerensky at Stanford in the 1950s]
*{{IMDb name|0449292}}
&lt;!--*[http://www.kerensky.org.uk/ Alexander Kerensky Museum in London]--&gt;
* {{PM20|FID=pe/009425}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-off}}
{{s-bef|before = [[Georgy Lvov]]}}
{{s-ttl|title = [[Prime Minister of Russia|Minister-Chairman of the Russian Provisional Government]]|years = 21 July 1917 – 8 November 1917}}
{{s-aft|after = [[Vladimir Lenin]]&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;{{nobold|([[List of leaders of the Soviet Union|Chairman of the Council of People's Commissars]])}}&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br/&gt;[[Lev Kamenev]]&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;{{nobold|(Chairman of the [[All-Russian Central Executive Committee]])}}&lt;/small&gt;}}
{{s-end}}
{{Prime Ministers of Russia}}
{{Russian Revolution 1917}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Kerensky, Alexander}}
[[Category:1881 births]]
[[Category:1970 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Ulyanovsk]]
[[Category:People from Simbirsk Governorate]]
[[Category:Trudoviks]]
[[Category:Burials at Putney Vale Cemetery]]
[[Category:Commanders-in-chief of the Russian Army]]
[[Category:Defence ministers of Russia]]
[[Category:Democratic socialists]]
[[Category:Hoover Institution people]]
[[Category:Imperial Russian politicians]]
[[Category:Justice ministers of Russia]]
[[Category:Members of the State Duma (Russian Empire)]]
[[Category:People of the Russian Revolution]]
[[Category:Heads of government of the Russian Provisional Government]]
[[Category:Russian Constituent Assembly members]]
[[Category:Imperial Russian emigrants to Australia]]
[[Category:Imperial Russian emigrants to the United States]]
[[Category:Russian anti-communists]]
[[Category:Russian people of World War I]]
[[Category:Socialist-Revolutionary Party members]]
[[Category:Russian revolutionaries]]
[[Category:Russian socialists]]
[[Category:Stanford University faculty]]
[[Category:Leaders ousted by a coup]]
[[Category:Imperial Russian emigrants to France]]</text>
      <sha1>aeiz06b6ur7x847s1rbsh5v944yxejx</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
