  <page>
    <title>Ab urbe condita</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2553</id>
    <revision>
      <id>936251084</id>
      <parentid>935866288</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-17T17:14:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JCW-CleanerBot</username>
        <id>31737083</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>clean up, replaced: Chronique d'Egypte → Chronique d'Égypte</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about|the year numbering system|the book|Ab Urbe Condita Libri}}
{{short description|Ancient Roman year-numbering system}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2013}}
{{italic title}}
[[Image:Antoninianus-Pacatianus-1001-RIC 0006cf.jpg|thumb|300px|[[Antoninianus]] of [[Pacatianus]], [[Roman usurper|usurper]] of Roman emperor [[Philip the Arab|Philip]] in 248. It reads ''ROMAE AETER[NAE] AN[NO] MIL[LESIMO] ET PRIMO'', &quot;To eternal Rome, in its one thousand and first year&quot;.]]

'''''Ab urbe condita''''' ({{IPA-la|ab ˈʊrbɛ ˈkɔndɪtaː}}), or '''''Anno urbis conditae''''' (&lt;small&gt;in [[Latin]] with normal [[elision]]:&lt;/small&gt; {{IPA-la|ˈan.n&lt;sup&gt;o̯&lt;/sup&gt;‿ʊrbɪs ˈkɔndɪtae̯|}}), often abbreviated as AUC, is an expression used in antiquity and by [[Classicist|classical historians]] to refer to a given year in [[Ancient Rome]]. ''Ab urbe condita'' is rendered into idiomatic English as &quot;from the [[founding of Rome|founding of the City]]&quot;, while ''anno urbis conditae'' likewise translates to &quot;in the year since the City's founding&quot;.{{NoteTag|In literal grammar translation, ''ab urbe condita'' becomes English &quot;from the founded city&quot;, and ''anno urbis conditae'' becomes &quot;in the year of the founded city&quot;. While this produces odd-sounding English syntax, in Latin this manner of expression is valid, and in particular usual for the word ''condo'' (&quot;to found&quot;, etc.) in the [[Classical Latin|Classical]] language; it conveys a tone that is somewhat more archaic and lofty.}} Therefore, the traditional year of the foundation of Rome, 753 BC, would be written AUC 1, while [[AD 1]] would be AUC 754. The foundation of the [[Roman Empire|Empire]] in 27 BC would be AUC 727.

Usage of the term was more common during the [[Renaissance]], when editors sometimes added AUC to Roman manuscripts they published, giving the false impression that the convention was commonly used in antiquity. In reality, the dominant method of identifying years in Roman times was to name the two [[Roman consul|consul]]s who held office that year. In late antiquity, [[regnal years]] were also in use, as was the [[Diocletian era]] in Roman Egypt after AD 293, and in the [[Byzantine Empire]] after AD 537, following a decree by [[Justinian]].

==Significance==
The traditional date for the founding of Rome, 21 April 753 BC, is due to  [[Marcus Terentius Varro]] (1st century BC). Varro may have used the consular list (with its mistakes) and called the year of the first consuls &quot;''ab urbe condita'' 245&quot;, accepting the 244-year interval from [[Dionysius of Halicarnassus]] for the kings after the foundation of Rome. The correctness of this calculation has not been confirmed, but it is still used worldwide.

From the time of [[Claudius]] (ruled AD 41 to AD 54) onward, this calculation superseded other contemporary calculations. Celebrating the anniversary of the city became part of imperial [[propaganda]]. Claudius was the first to hold magnificent celebrations in honor of the anniversary of the city, in AD 48, the eight hundredth year from the founding of the city.{{citation needed|date=June 2016}} [[Hadrian]] and [[Antoninus Pius]] held similar celebrations, in AD 121, and in AD 147 and AD 148, respectively.

In AD 248, [[Philip the Arab]] celebrated Rome's first [[millennium]], together with [[Ludi saeculares]] for Rome's alleged tenth [[saeculum]]. [[Coin]]s from his reign commemorate the celebrations. A coin by a contender for the imperial throne, [[Pacatianus]], explicitly states &quot;[y]ear one thousand and first&quot;, which is an indication that the citizens of the empire had a sense of the beginning of a new era, a ''Sæculum Novum''.

==Calendar era==
{{see|Calendar era}}
The [[Anno Domini]] (AD) year numbering was developed by a monk named [[Dionysius Exiguus]] in Rome in AD 525, as a result of his work on calculating the date of Easter. Dionysius did not use the AUC convention, but instead based his calculations on the [[Diocletian era]]. This convention had been in use since AD 293, the year of the [[tetrarchy]], as it became impractical to use regnal years of the current emperor.&lt;ref&gt;J. David Thomas, &quot;On Dating by Regnal Years of Diocletian, Maximian and the Caesars&quot;, ''Chronique d'Égypte'' 46.91 (1971),  173&amp;ndash;179, [https://doi.org/10.1484/J.CDE.2.308234 doi:10.1484/J.CDE.2.308234].&lt;/ref&gt; In his Easter table, the year AD 532 was equated with the 248th regnal year of  Diocletian. The table counted the years starting from the presumed birth of Christ, rather than the accession of the emperor [[Diocletian]] on 20 November AD 284, or as stated by Dionysius: ''&quot;sed magis elegimus ab incarnatione Domini nostri Jesu Christi annorum tempora praenotare&quot;'' (&quot;but rather we choose to name the times of the years from the incarnation of our Lord Jesus Christ&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;''Liber de Paschate'', [[Jacques Paul Migne|Migne]], ''[[Patrologia Latina]]'', [https://books.google.com/books?vid=OCLC12663742&amp;id=LcEYeL-4ZuEC&amp;pg=PP10&amp;lpg=PP10&amp;dq=%22in+hoc+tomo+LXVII#PRA1-PT165,M1 Volume 67, page 481, note f]&lt;/ref&gt; Blackburn and Holford-Strevens review interpretations of Dionysius which place the [[Incarnation (Christianity)|Incarnation]] in 2 BC, 1 BC, or AD 1.&lt;ref&gt;Blackburn, B. &amp; Holford-Strevens, L, ''The Oxford Companion to the Year'' (Oxford University Press, 2003 corrected reprinting, originally 1999), pp. 778–780.&lt;/ref&gt;

The year AD 1 corresponds to AUC 754, based on the epoch of Varro.

Thus,

* AUC 1 = 753 BC
* AUC 753 = 1 BC
* AUC 754 = AD 1 
* AUC 1000 = AD 247
*AUC 1229 = [[Fall of the Western Roman Empire|AD 476]]
*AUC 2206 = [[Fall of Constantinople|AD 1453]]
* AUC 2753 = AD 2000
* AUC {{#expr:{{CURRENTYEAR}}+753}} = AD {{CURRENTYEAR}}
* AUC {{#expr:{{NEXTYEAR}}+753}} = AD {{NEXTYEAR}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Ancient Rome}}
* {{annotated link|List of Latin phrases}}

== Notes ==
{{NoteFoot}}

== Citations ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* {{wiktionary inline}}

{{Ancient Rome topics}}
{{Chronology}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:ab urbe condita}}
[[Category:1st-century BC establishments in the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:8th century BC in the Roman Kingdom]]
[[Category:Calendar eras]]
[[Category:Chronology]]
[[Category:Latin words and phrases]]
[[Category:Roman calendar]]</text>
      <sha1>3j6agqqpxdgwzi0phk9jixzno461a46</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
