  <page>
    <title>Arthur Phillip</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2563</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942861281</id>
      <parentid>942855582</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T09:11:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Chewings72</username>
        <id>12824384</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverting]] [[Wikipedia:Vandalism|vandalism]] or test edit</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|18th and 19th-century British naval officer, Governor of New South Wales}}
{{EngvarB|date=April 2014}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2014}}

{{Infobox governor
|name= Arthur Phillip
|image= Arthur Phillip - Wheatley ML124.jpg
|caption= Captain Arthur Phillip, 1786, by [[Francis Wheatley (painter)]]
|order = 1st
|office = Governor of New South Wales
|term_start = 7 February 1788
|term_end = 10 December 1792
|monarch = [[George III of the United Kingdom|George III]]
|predecessor = ''Position Established''
|successor = [[John Hunter (Royal Navy officer)|John Hunter]]
|birth_date = {{Birth date|df=yes|1738|10|11}}
|birth_place = [[Cheapside]], [[London]], England
|death_date = {{Death date and age|df=yes|1814|8|31|1738|10|11}}
|death_place = [[Bath, Somerset]], England
|nickname=
|allegiance= [[Kingdom of Great Britain]]
|branch= [[Royal Navy]]
|serviceyears=
|rank= [[Admiral (Royal Navy)|Admiral]]
|commands=
|unit=
|battles = {{unbulleted list|[[Seven Years' War]] | [[Spanish–Portuguese War (1776–77)|Spanish-Portuguese War]] | [[American Revolutionary War]] }} [[Australian Frontier Wars]]
|awards =
}}

'''[[Admiral]] Arthur Phillip''' (11 October 1738 – 31 August 1814) was a [[Royal Navy]] officer and the first [[Governor of New South Wales]] who led the British settlement and colonization of Australia. Establishing a British penal colony that later became the city of [[Sydney]], Australia.&lt;ref name=LifeMagazine1944-05-22&gt;{{cite magazine |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=bk8EAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA91&amp;dq=%22Thomas+Gilbert%22+captain+pacific&amp;num=100#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Thomas%20Gilbert%22%20captain%20pacific&amp;f=false
|title=The Gilberts &amp; Marshalls: A distinguished historian recalls the past of two recently captured Pacific groups |magazine=[[Life Magazine]] |date=22 May 1944 |last=Morison |first=Samuel Eliot |author-link=Samuel Eliot Morison |accessdate=1 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After much experience at sea, Phillip led the [[First Fleet]] as Governor-designate in the Australian settlement of [[New South Wales]]. In January 1788, he selected its location to be [[Port Jackson]] (encompassing Sydney Harbour).&lt;ref name=&quot;On this day&quot;&gt;{{cite web|publisher=[[Australian Geographic]] |title=On this day: Arthur Phillip born|author=Leila Berney |url=http://www.australiangeographic.com.au/blogs/on-this-day/2014/10/on-this-day-arthur-phillip-born|accessdate=5 March 2015|date=2014-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Phillip was a far-sighted governor who soon saw that New South Wales would need a civil administration and a system for emancipating the convicts. But his plan to bring skilled tradesmen on the voyage had been rejected, and he faced immense problems of labour, discipline and supply. 

The arrival of the [[Second Fleet (Australia)|Second]] and [[Third Fleet (Australia)|Third]] Fleets placed new pressures on the scarce local resources, but by the time Phillip sailed home in December 1792, the colony was taking shape, with official land-grants and systematic farming and water-supply.

Phillip retired in 1805, but continued to correspond with his friends in New South Wales and to promote the colony's interests.

== Early life ==
Captain Arthur Phillip was born on 11 October 1738, the youngest of two children to Jacob Phillip and Elizabeth Breach. His father Jacob was born in [[Frankfurt]], Germany. He was a languages teacher who may also have served in the Royal Navy as an [[able seaman]] and purser's steward. His mother Elizabeth was the widow of an [[ordinary seaman]], John Herbert, who had served in Jamaica aboard HMS ''Tartar'' and died of disease on 13 August 1732. At the time of Arthur Phillip's birth, his family maintained a modest existence as tenants near [[Cheapside]] in the [[City of London]].&lt;ref&gt;Pembroke 2013, p.5&lt;/ref&gt;

There are no surviving records of Phillip's early childhood. His father Jacob died in 1739, after which the Phillip family may have fallen on hard times.&lt;ref&gt;Parker 2009, pp.2–3&lt;/ref&gt; On 22 June 1751 he was accepted into the [[Royal Hospital School|Greenwich Hospital School]], a [[charity school]] for the sons of indigent seafarers.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;Pembroke 2013, p.9&lt;/ref&gt; In keeping with the school's curriculum, his education was focused on literacy, arithmetic and navigational skills, including cartography. He was a competent student and something of a perfectionist. His headmaster, Reverend Francis Swinden observed that in personality Phillip was &quot;unassuming, reasonable, business-like to the smallest degree in everything he undertakes&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Correspondence, Rev. Francis Swinden, 22 June 1753, cited in Pembroke 2013, p.12&lt;/ref&gt;

Phillip remained at the Greenwich School for two and a half years, considerably longer than the average student stay of twelve months.&lt;ref&gt;Parker 2009, p.4&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of 1753 he was granted a seven-year indenture as an apprentice aboard ''Fortune'', a 210-ton whaling vessel commanded by merchant mariner Wiliam Readhead. He left the Greenwich School on 1 December and spent the winter aboard the ''Fortune'' awaiting the commencement of the 1754 whaling season.&lt;ref&gt;Pembroke 2013, p.12&lt;/ref&gt;

==First voyages==
{{further|Great Britain in the Seven Years' War}}
Phillip spent the summer of 1754 hunting whales near [[Svalbard]] in the [[Barents Sea]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Tink30&quot;&gt;Tink 2009, pp. 30–31&lt;/ref&gt; As an apprentice, his responsibilities included [[flensing|stripping blubber]] from whale carcasses and helping to pack it into barrels.&lt;ref&gt;Pembroke 2013, p.15&lt;/ref&gt; Food was scarce and ''Fortune''{{'}}s thirty crew members supplemented their diet with bird's eggs, [[scurvy grass]] and where possible, reindeer.&lt;ref&gt;Frost 1987, p.16&lt;/ref&gt; The ship returned to England on 20 July 1754. The whaling crew were paid off and replaced with twelve sailors for a winter voyage to the Mediterranean. As an apprentice, Phillip remained aboard as ''Fortune'' undertook an outward trading voyage to Barcelona and Livorno carrying salt and raisins, returning via Rotterdam with a cargo of grains and citrus.&lt;ref&gt;Frost 1987, p.22&lt;/ref&gt; The ship returned to England in April 1755 and sailed immediately for Svalbard for that year's whale hunt. Phillip was still a member of the crew, but abandoned his apprenticeship when the ship returned to England on 27 July.&lt;ref&gt;Frost 1987, p.25&lt;/ref&gt; On 16 October he enlisted in the Royal Navy and was assigned the rank of ordinary seaman aboard the 68-gun {{HMS|Buckingham|1751|6}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Parker5&quot;&gt;Parker 2009, p.&amp;nbsp;5.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:HMSBuckingham.jpg|250px|thumb|left|HMS ''Buckingham'', Phillip's first posting after joining the Navy in 1755. Vessel pictured on the stocks at Deptford Dockyard, c. 1751. Painting by [[John Cleveley the Elder]]. [[National Maritime Museum]], London.]]
As a member of ''Buckingham''{{'}}s crew, Phillip saw action in the [[Seven Years' War]], including the [[Battle of Minorca (1756)|Battle of Minorca]] in 1756. By 1762 he had transferred to {{HMS|Stirling Castle|1742|6}}, and was promoted to Lieutenant in recognition of active service in the [[Battle of Havana (1762)|Battle of Havana]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Tink30&quot;/&gt; The War ended in 1763 and Phillip returned to England on half pay. In July 1763 he married Margaret Denison, a widow 16 years his senior, and moved to [[Glasshayes]] in [[Lyndhurst, Hampshire]], establishing a farm there. The marriage was unhappy, and the couple separated in 1769 when Phillip returned to the Navy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tink30&quot; /&gt; The following year he was posted as second lieutenant aboard {{HMS|Egmont|1768|6}}, a newly built 74-gun [[ship of the line]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Tink30&quot;/&gt;

In 1774 Phillip joined the [[Portuguese Navy]] as a captain, serving in the [[Spanish-Portuguese War, 1776-1777|War against Spain]]. While with the Portuguese Navy, Phillip commanded a frigate, the ''Nossa Senhora do Pilar.'' On this ship he took a detachment of troops from [[Rio de Janeiro]] to [[Colonia del Sacramento|Colonia do Sacramento]] on the [[Río de la Plata]] (opposite [[Buenos Aires]]) to relieve the garrison there. This voyage also conveyed a consignment of convicts assigned to carry out work at Colonia. During a storm encountered in the course of the voyage, the convicts assisted in working the ship and, on arrival at Colonia, Phillip recommended that they be rewarded for saving the ship by remission of their sentences.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com.au/books?id=51BTAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PT164&amp;dq=%22Gazeta+de+Lisboa%22+Philips&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=_3OXVbGROKXWmAXOsYD4CA&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Gazeta%20de%20Lisboa%22%20Philips&amp;f=false ''Gazeta de Lisboa,'' 3 de Abril de 1787:] Maurine Goldston-Morris, OAM, ''The Life of Admiral Arthur Phillip, RN, 1738–1814,'' Naval Historical Society of Australia Monograph No.58, Garden Island [1997].&lt;/ref&gt; A garbled version of this eventually found its way into the English press when Phillip was appointed in 1786 to lead the expedition to Sydney.&lt;ref&gt;See for example, ''The World,'' 16 April 1789: &quot;BOTANY BAY.— Mr. ''Philip,'' who has this command, has the aid of experience. He had a similar expedition entrusted him by PORTUGAL, to carry convicts to South America.&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; Phillip played a leading part in the capture of the [[Spanish ship San Agustín (1768)|Spanish ship San Agustín]], on 19 April 1777, off Santa Catarina. The ''San Agustin'' was commissioned into the Portuguese Navy as the ''Santo Agostinho'', and command of her was given to Phillip. The action was reported in the English press: &lt;blockquote&gt;
Madrid, Aug. 28. Letters from Lisbon bring the following Account from Rio Janeiro: That the St. Augustine, of 70 Guns, having been separated from the Squadron of M. Casa Tilly, was attacked by two Portugueze Ships, against which they defended themselves for a Day and a Night, but being next Day surrounded by the Portugueze Fleet, was obliged to surrender.&lt;ref&gt;''The St. James's Chronicle, The London Chronicle, The Daily Advertiser, The Gazetteer and The Public Advertiser,'' 16 September 1777.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In 1778 Britain was again at war, and Phillip was recalled to active service, and in 1779 obtained his first command, HMS ''Basilisk''. He was promoted to [[post-captain]] on 30 November 1781 and given command of {{HMS|Europa|1765|6}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title =East India Trade | work =The World | page =3 | publisher =B. MIllan, London | date =1 April 1787 | url =http://find.galegroup.com.simsrad.net.ocs.mq.edu.au/bncn/retrieve.do?sgHitCountType=None&amp;scale=0.33&amp;orientation=&amp;sort=DateAscend&amp;docLevel=FASCIMILE&amp;prodId=BBCN&amp;tabID=T012&amp;subjectParam=Locale%2528en%252C%252C%2529%253AFQE%253D%2528tx%252CNone%252C12%2529Port%2BJackson%2524&amp;searchId=R1&amp;resultListType=RESULT_LIST&amp;searchType=AdvancedSearchForm&amp;currentPosition=2&amp;qrySerId=Locale%28en%2C%2C%29%3AFQE%3D%28tx%2CNone%2C12%29Port+Jackson%24&amp;retrieveFormat=MULTIPAGE_DOCUMENT&amp;subjectAction=DISPLAY_SUBJECTS&amp;inPS=true&amp;userGroupName=mqu_trial&amp;sgCurrentPosition=0&amp;docId=Z2001513504&amp;currentPosition=2&amp;workId=&amp;relevancePageBatch=Z2001513504&amp;contentSet=LTO&amp;callistoContentSet=UBER2&amp;resultListType=RESULT_LIST&amp;reformatPage=N&amp;docPage=browseissue&amp;retrieveFormat=MULTIPAGE_DOCUMENT&amp;scale=0.33&amp;pageIndex=6&amp;orientation=&amp;docPage=browseissue&amp;enlarge=true&amp;recNum= |url-access=subscription  | accessdate =12 September 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite speech
|first=Robert J.
|last=King
|title=Arthur Phillip Defensor de Colónia, Governador de Nova Gales do Sul
|trans-title=Arthur Phillip: Defender of Colônia, Governor of New South Wales
|publisher=[[Vancouver Island University]]
|event=V Simpósio de HistóriaMarítimo e Naval Iber-americano 
|date=25–29 October 1999
|location=Ilha Fiscal, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil
|url=http://web.viu.ca/black/amrc/index.htm?Research/Papers/PHILLIP2.HTM&amp;2
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote box|width=25em|quote=[Phillip] is an officer of education and principle, he gives way to reason and does not, before doing so fall into exaggerated and unbearable excesses of temper ... he is very clean-handed; is an officer of great truth and very brave; and is no flatterer, saying what he thinks but without temper or want of respect.&lt;ref&gt;Correspondence, Luís de Almeida Portugal Soares de Alarcão d'Eça e Melo Silva Mascarenhas, 2nd Marquess of Lavradio, 1778. Cited in Tink 2009, p.31&lt;/ref&gt;|source=Correspondence of [[Luís de Almeida Portugal Soares de Alarcão d'Eça e Melo Silva Mascarenhas, 2nd Marquess of Lavradio|Luís, 2nd Marquis Lavradio]], Viceroy of Brazil, 1778.}}

In July 1782, in a change of government, [[Thomas Townshend, 1st Viscount Sydney|Thomas Townshend]] became Secretary of State for Home and American Affairs, and assumed responsibility for organising an expedition against Spanish America. Like his predecessor, Lord Germain, he turned for advice to Arthur Phillip.&lt;ref&gt;Viscount Keppel, First Lord of the Admiralty, to Townshend, 25 September 1782; Clements Library (Ann Arbor), Sydney Papers, 9; British Library, India and Oriental, H 175, f.237. Cited in Frost 1995, p.114&lt;/ref&gt; A letter from Phillip to Sandwich of 17 January 1781 records Phillip's loan to Sandwich of his charts of the Plata and Brazilian coasts for use in organising the expedition.&lt;ref&gt;Phillip to Sandwich, 17 January 1781; National Maritime Museum (Greenwich), ''Sandwich Papers,'' F/26/23.&lt;/ref&gt; Phillip's plan was for a squadron of three ships of the line and a frigate to mount a raid on Buenos Aires and Monte Video, then to proceed to the coasts of Chile, Peru and Mexico to maraud, and ultimately to cross the Pacific to join the British Navy's East India squadron for an attack on Manila.&lt;ref&gt;Blankett to Shelburne, August 1782; Clements Library (Ann Arbor), Sydney Papers, 9; quoted in Frost 1987, p.114.&lt;/ref&gt; The expedition, consisting of the ''Grafton,'' 70 guns, ''Elizabeth,'' 74 guns, ''Europe,'' 64 guns, and the frigate ''Iphigenia'', sailed on 16 January 1783, under the command of Commodore Robert Kingsmill.&lt;ref&gt;Admiralty Lords to Kingsmill, 17 December 1782, National Archives, Kew, ADM 2/113: 522–3; Kingsmill to Admiralty Lords, 1 January 1783, National Archives, Kew, ADM 1/2015; Keppel to Middleton, 17 December 1782, National Archives, Kew, HO 28/2: 410–1; quoted in Alan Frost 1987, p.114.&lt;/ref&gt; Phillip was given command of the 64-gun {{HMS|Europa|1765|6}}, or ''Europe''.&lt;ref&gt;National Archives, Kew, ADM 51/354; ADM 2/113; quoted in Alan Frost 1987, p.114. The departure of the squadron from Portsmouth was reported in ''The General Evening Post, The London Chronicle,'' 18 January, ''The Morning Post,''  20 January 1783; Phillip's return to Portsmouth in the ''Europe'' was reported in ''The Whitehall Evening Post,'' 24 April 1784.&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly after sailing, an armistice was concluded between Great Britain and Spain. Phillip learnt of this in April when he put in for storm repairs at Rio de Janeiro. Phillip wrote to Townshend from Rio de Janeiro on 25 April 1783, expressing his disappointment that the ending of the American War had robbed him of the opportunity for naval glory in South America.&lt;ref&gt;India Office Records, H 175, f.237; quoted in ''Alan Frost, Convicts &amp; Empire: A Naval Question, 1776 1811,'' Melbourne, Oxford University Press, 1980, p.209. Phillip used the contemporary Portuguese spelling for Montevideo.&lt;/ref&gt;

After his return to England from India in April 1784, Phillip remained in close contact with Townshend, now Lord Sydney, and the Home Office Under Secretary, Evan Nepean. From October 1784 to September 1786 he was employed by Nepean, who was in charge of the Secret Service relating to the Bourbon Powers, France and Spain, to spy on the French naval arsenals at Toulon and other ports.&lt;ref&gt;Frost 1987, pp. 129–133&lt;/ref&gt; There was fear that Britain would soon be at war with these powers as a consequence of the [[Batavian Revolution]] in the Netherlands.&lt;ref&gt;Frost 1980, pp.115–116, 129&lt;/ref&gt;

Portraits of the time depict Phillip as shorter than average, with an olive complexion, dark eyes and a &quot;smooth pear of a skull&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tink30&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hughes66&quot;&gt;Hughes 1986, p.66&lt;/ref&gt; His features were dominated by a large and fleshy nose, and by a pronounced lower lip.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hughes66&quot;/&gt;

==Colonial service==
{{refimprove section|date=January 2011}}
At this time, [[Earl of Sandwich|Lord Sandwich]], together with the President of the Royal Society, Sir [[Joseph Banks]], was advocating establishment of a British colony in New South Wales.&lt;ref&gt;James Matra to Banks, 28 July 1783, British Library Additional MS 33979: 206. Cited in Frost 1995, p.110&lt;/ref&gt; A colony there would be of great assistance to the British Navy in facilitating attacks on the Spanish possessions in Chile and Peru, as Banks's collaborators, James Matra, Captain Sir George Young and Sir John Call pointed out in written proposals on the subject. The British Government took the decision to settle what is now Australia and found the [[Botany Bay]] colony in August 1786.&lt;ref name=&quot;HistNSWgovPhillip1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author1=George Burnett Barton |title=History of New South Wales From the Records, Volume I - Governor Phillip - Chapter 1.4 |url=http://gutenberg.net.au/ebooks12/1204171h.html#ch-07 |website=Project Gutenberg of Australia |publisher=Charles Potter, Government Printer |accessdate=25 April 2019 |date=1889}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lord Sydney, as Secretary of State for the Home Office, was the minister in charge, and in September 1786 he appointed Phillip commodore of the fleet which was to transport the convicts and soldiers who were to be the new settlers to Botany Bay. Upon arrival there, Phillip was to assume the powers of Captain General and Governor in Chief of the new colony. A subsidiary colony was to be founded on [[Norfolk Island]], as recommended by Sir John Call, to take advantage for naval purposes of that island's native flax ([[harakeke]]) and timber.

In October 1786, Phillip was appointed captain of {{HMS|Sirius|1786|6}} and named Governor-designate of [[New South Wales]], the proposed British colony on the east coast of Australia, by [[Thomas Townshend, 1st Viscount Sydney|Lord Sydney]], the [[Home Secretary]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB2&quot;&gt;{{Australian Dictionary of Biography|last=Fletcher|first=B.H.|year=1967|volume=2|id2=http://adb.anu.edu.au/biography/phillip-arthur-2549|title= Phillip, Arthur (1738–1814)|accessdate=25 April 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=1790 HMS Sirius Anchor and Cannon |url=http://www.migrationheritage.nsw.gov.au/exhibition/objectsthroughtime/sirius-anchor-cannon/index.html |website=Objects Through Time |publisher=Migration Heritage Centre NSW |accessdate=25 April 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Phillip had a very difficult time assembling the fleet which was to make the eight-month sea voyage to Australia. Everything a new colony might need had to be taken, since Phillip had no real idea of what he might find when he got there. There were few funds available for equipping the expedition. His suggestion that people with experience in farming, building and crafts be included was rejected. Most of the 772 convicts (of whom 732 survived the voyage) were petty thieves from the London slums. Phillip was accompanied by a contingent of [[Royal Marines|marines]] and a handful of other officers who were to administer the colony.

The 11 ships of the [[First Fleet]] set sail from [[Portsmouth]] on 13 May 1787.&lt;ref name=&quot;projGutenbergoz&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=The First Fleet |url=http://gutenberg.net.au/first-fleet.html |website=Project Gutenberg Australia |accessdate=25 April 2019 |date=2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GovPhillipVoyage1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author1=Arthur Phillip |title=The Voyage Of Governor Phillip To Botany Bay with An Account Of The Establishment Of The Colonies Of Port Jackson and Norfolk Island - Chapter II |url=http://www.gutenberg.org/files/15100/15100-h/15100-h.htm#chapter-02 |website=Project Gutenberg |accessdate=25 April 2019 |date=1789}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The fleet called at [[Rio de Janeiro]] for supplies from 6 August to 4 September.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.australiaonthemap.org.au/news/ Robert J. King, “Arthur Phillip and the First Fleet at Rio de Janeiro”, ''Map Matters'', Issue 35, Spring 2018, pp.10-16. ] &lt;/ref&gt; The leading ship, {{HMS|Supply|1759|6}} reached [[Botany Bay]] setting up camp on the [[Cronulla sand dunes|Kurnell Peninsula]], on 18 January 1788.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/15100 The Voyage of Governor Phillip to Botany Bay] With an Account of the Establishment of the Colonies of [[Port Jackson]] and [[Norfolk Island]] (1789) – from [[Project Gutenberg]]&lt;/ref&gt; Phillip soon decided that this site, chosen on the recommendation of [[Joseph Banks|Sir Joseph Banks]], who had accompanied [[James Cook]] in 1770, was not suitable, since it had poor soil, no secure anchorage and no reliable water source. After some exploration Phillip decided to go on to Port Jackson, and on 26 January the marines and convicts landed at [[Sydney Cove]], which Phillip named after Lord Sydney.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Geographical Names Register Extract - Sydney |url=http://www.gnb.nsw.gov.au/place_naming/placename_search/extract?id=TRlpoerXGH |website=Place Name Search |publisher=Geographical Names Board of New South Wales |accessdate=25 April 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Governor of New South Wales ===
Shortly after landing and establishing the settlement at Port Jackson, on 15 February 1788, Phillip sent Lieutenant [[Philip Gidley King]] with eight free men and a number of convicts to establish the second British colony in the Pacific at [[Norfolk Island]]. This was partly in response to a perceived threat of losing Norfolk Island to the French and partly to establish an alternative food source for the mainland colony.

[[File:Arthur Phillip - Project Gutenberg eText 12992.jpg|thumbnail|left|Arthur Phillip]]

The early days of the settlement in [[New South Wales]] were chaotic and difficult. With limited supplies, the cultivation of food was imperative, but the soils around Sydney were poor, the climate was unfamiliar, and moreover very few of the convicts had any knowledge of agriculture. The colony was on the verge of outright [[starvation]] for an extended period. The marines, poorly disciplined themselves in many cases, were not interested in convict discipline. Almost at once, therefore, Phillip had to appoint overseers from among the ranks of the convicts to get the others working. This was the beginning of the process of convict emancipation which was to culminate in the reforms of [[Lachlan Macquarie]] after 1811.

Phillip showed in other ways that he recognised that New South Wales could not be run simply as a prison camp. Lord Sydney, often criticised as an ineffectual incompetent, had made one fundamental decision about the settlement that was to influence it beneficially from the start. Instead of just establishing it as a military prison, he provided for a civil administration, with courts of law. Two convicts, [[Henry Kable|Henry]] and Susannah Kable, sought to sue Duncan Sinclair, the captain of [[Alexander (1783 ship)|''Alexander'']], for stealing their possessions during the voyage. Convicts in Britain had no right to sue, and Sinclair had boasted that he could not be sued by them. Despite this, the court found for the plaintiffs and ordered the captain to make restitution for the loss of their possessions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.law.mq.edu.au/research/colonial_case_law/nsw/cases/case_index/1788/cable_v_sinclair/ |title = Cable v. Sinclair [1788] NSWKR 7; [1788] NSWSupC 7 |publisher=Macquarie University Law School |accessdate=1 July 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Further, soon after Lord Sydney appointed him governor of New South Wales Arthur Phillip drew up a detailed memorandum of his plans for the proposed new colony. In one paragraph he wrote: &quot;The laws of this country [England] will of course, be introduced in [New] South Wales, and there is one that I would wish to take place from the moment his Majesty's forces take possession of the country: That there can be no slavery in a free land, and consequently no slaves.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Britton (ed.) 1978, p. 53&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, Phillip believed in severe discipline; floggings and hangings were commonplace, although Philip commuted many death sentences.

Phillip also had to adopt a policy towards the [[Eora]] [[Australian Aborigine|Aboriginal people]], who lived around the waters of [[Port Jackson|Sydney Harbour]].&lt;ref name=&quot;On this day&quot;/&gt; Phillip ordered that they must be well treated, and that anyone killing Aboriginal people would be hanged. Phillip befriended an Eora man called [[Bennelong]],&lt;ref name=&quot;On this day&quot;/&gt; and later took him to England. On the beach at [[Manly, New South Wales|Manly]], a misunderstanding arose and Phillip was speared in the shoulder: but he ordered his men not to retaliate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Governors of New South Wales|last=Tink|first=Andrew|publisher=The Federation Press|year=2009|isbn=9781862877436|pages=42–43|editor=Cavalier, Rodney}}&lt;/ref&gt; Phillip went some way towards winning the trust of the Eora, although they remained wary of the settlers. Soon, a virulent disease, smallpox that was believed to be on account of the white settlers, and other European-introduced epidemics, ravaged the Eora population.

The Governor's main problem was with his own military officers, who wanted large grants of land, which Phillip had not been authorised to grant. [[Scurvy]] broke out, and in October 1788 Phillip had to send ''Sirius'' to [[Cape Town]] for supplies, and strict rationing was introduced, with thefts of food punished by hanging. He recorded:  &quot;The living conditions need to improve or my men won't work as hard, so I have come to a conclusion that I must hire surgeons to fix the convicts.&quot;{{cn|date=December 2018}}

===Stabilising the colony===
Phillip insisted that no retaliation be taken to avenge his own non-fatal spearing. Convict John MacIntyre had been fatally speared during a hunting expedition by unknown Aboriginal people apparently without provocation. MacIntyre swore on his death bed that he had done them no harm, but marine officer [[Watkin Tench]] was suspicious of the claim.  Tench was sent on a punitive expedition but finding no Aboriginal people other than [[Bennelong]] took no action.&lt;ref name=tench&gt;{{cite book |title=A Complete Account of the Settlement at Port Jackson |author=Watkin Tench | url=http://setis.library.usyd.edu.au/ozlit/pdf/p00044.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Phillip, growing frustrated with the burdens of upholding a colony and his health suffering, resigned soon after this episode.&lt;ref name=&quot;sbs.com.au&quot;&gt;{{cite video |url=http://www.sbs.com.au/firstaustralians/ |title=First Australians |publisher=[[Blackfella Films]], SBS, and Screen Australia |year=2008 |accessdate=26 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[[Watkin Tench]], 1788'' (ed: [[Tim Flannery]]), 1996, {{ISBN|1-875847-27-8}}, p. 167&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1790 the situation had stabilised. The population of about 2,000 was adequately housed and fresh food was being grown. Phillip assigned a convict, [[James Ruse]], land at [[Rose Hill, New South Wales|Rose Hill]] (now [[Parramatta, New South Wales|Parramatta]]) to establish proper farming, and when Ruse succeeded he received the first land grant in the colony. Other convicts followed his example. ''Sirius'' was wrecked in March 1790 at the satellite settlement of [[Norfolk Island]], depriving Phillip of vital supplies. In June 1790 the Second Fleet arrived with hundreds more convicts, most of them too sick to work.

[[File:ArthurPhillipStatueSydney gobeirne.jpg|thumb|left|Statue of Arthur Phillip in the [[Royal Botanic Gardens, Sydney]]]]
By December 1790 Phillip was ready to return to England, but the colony had largely been forgotten in London and no instructions reached him, so he carried on. In 1791 he was advised that the government would send out two convoys of convicts annually, plus adequate supplies. But July, when the vessels of the [[Third Fleet (Australia)|Third Fleet]] began to arrive, with 2,000 more convicts, food again ran short, and he had to send the ship ''[[Atlantic (1783 ship)|Atlantic]]'' to [[Calcutta]] for supplies.&lt;ref&gt;Hunter, Chapter XXIII&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1792 the colony was well established, though Sydney remained an unplanned huddle of wooden huts and tents. The [[whaling|whaling industry]] was established, ships were visiting Sydney to trade, and convicts whose sentences had expired were taking up farming. [[John Macarthur (wool pioneer)|John Macarthur]] and other officers were importing sheep and beginning to grow wool. The colony was still very short of skilled farmers, craftsmen and tradesmen, and the convicts continued to work as little as possible, even though they were working mainly to grow their own food.

In late 1792, Phillip, whose health was suffering, relinquished his governorship and sailed for England on the ship ''[[Atlantic (1783 ship)|Atlantic]]'', taking with him many specimens of plants and animals. He also took Bennelong and his friend [[Yemmerrawanne]], another young Indigenous Australian who, unlike Bennelong, would succumb to English weather and disease and not live to make the journey home. The European population of New South Wales at his departure was 4,221, of whom 3,099 were convicts. The early years of the colony had been years of struggle and hardship, but the worst was over, and there were no further famines in New South Wales. Phillip arrived in London in May 1793. He tendered his formal resignation and was granted a pension of £500 a year.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Pembroke, ''Arthur Phillip – Sailor, Mercenary, Governor, Spy,'' Melbourne, Hardie Grant Books, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Later life, and death==
Phillip's estranged wife, Margaret, had died in 1792 and was buried in St Beuno's Churchyard, [[Llanycil]], [[Bala, Gwynedd|Bala]], [[Merionethshire]].&lt;ref&gt;Michael Flynn, &quot;New perspectives on Arthur Phillip, first Governor of New South Wales [Series of parts]: Part 1: Wives, graves and ghosts.&quot;  Descent, Volume 43 Issue 2 (June 2013) : 65–81.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1794 Phillip married Isabella Whitehead, and lived for a time at [[Bath, Somerset|Bath]]. His health gradually recovered and in 1796 he went back to sea, holding a series of commands and responsible posts in the wars against the French. In January 1799 he became a Rear-Admiral. In 1805, aged 67, he retired from the Navy with the rank of [[Admiral of the Blue]], and spent most of the rest of his life in Bath. He continued to correspond with friends in New South Wales and to promote the colony's interests with government officials. He died in Bath in 1814.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Broughton |first=W. |title=Sydney: Sitting Magistrate W. Broughton Esq. |work=The Sydney Gazette and New South Wales Advertiser |page=2 |publisher=G. Howe |date=1 April 1815 |url=http://trove.nla.gov.au/newspaper/article/629090 |accessdate=11 August 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; His Last Will and Testament has been transcribed and is online.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.spanglefish.com/admiralarthurphillip|title=The Last Will and Testament of Admiral Arthur Phillip a.k.a. Governor Arthur Phillip|website=spanglefish.com|accessdate=11 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Phillip was buried in [[Church of St Nicholas, Bathampton|St Nicholas's Church]], [[Bathampton]]. Forgotten for many years, the grave was discovered in 1897&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stnicholasandstmarys.org.uk/ St Nicholas Church, Bathampton], Burial place of Arthur Phillip&lt;/ref&gt; and the Premier of New South Wales, [[Henry Parkes|Sir Henry Parkes]], had it restored. An annual service of remembrance is held here around Phillip's birthdate by the [[Britain–Australia Society]] to commemorate his life.

In 2007, [[Geoffrey Robertson|Geoffrey Robertson QC]] alleged that Phillip's remains are no longer in St Nicholas Church, Bathampton and have been lost: &quot;Captain Arthur Phillip is not where the ledger stone says he is: it may be that he is buried somewhere outside, it may simply be that he is simply lost. But he is not where Australians have been led to believe that he now lies.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;lostplot&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Lost the plot - story transcript |url=http://sixtyminutes.ninemsn.com.au/article.aspx?id=262243&amp;_cobr=optus |website=60 Minutes |publisher=Ninemsn |accessdate=25 April 2019 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080130050212/http://sixtyminutes.ninemsn.com.au/article.aspx?id=262243&amp;_cobr=optus |archivedate=30 January 2008 |date=22 April 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
[[File:australia.chapel.bathampton.arp.jpg|thumb|right|The Australia Chapel in St Nicholas Church, [[Bathampton]], near Bath, England. The memorial to the first governor of [[New South Wales]], Arthur Phillip, is on the right hand wall]]
[[File:Admiral Arthur Phillip monument bust south from One New Change.jpg|thumb|Admiral Arthur Phillip monument bust in the [[City of London]]]]
A number of places in Australia bear Phillip's name, including [[Port Phillip]], [[Phillip Island]] (Victoria), [[Phillip Island (Norfolk Island)]], [[Phillip Street, Sydney|Phillip Street]] in Sydney, the [[Division of Phillip|federal electorate of Phillip]] (1949–1993), the [[Phillip, Australian Capital Territory|suburb of Phillip]] in [[Canberra]], the [[Governor Phillip Tower]] building in Sydney, and many streets, parks and schools including a state [[Arthur Phillip High School|high school]] in Parramatta. A monument to Phillip in [[Bath Abbey]] Church was unveiled in 1937. Another was unveiled at [[St Mildred, Bread Street|St Mildred's Church]], Bread St, London, in 1932; that church was destroyed in the [[London Blitz]] in 1940, but the principal elements of the monument were re-erected at the west end of Watling Street, near [[Saint Paul's Cathedral]], in 1968. A different bust and memorial is inside the nearby church of [[St Mary-le-Bow]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stmarylebow.co.uk/?International_Links:Australia Details of move]&lt;/ref&gt; There is a statue of him in the [[Royal Botanical Gardens, Sydney|Botanic Gardens, Sydney]]. There is a portrait of him by Francis Wheatley in the [[National Portrait Gallery, London]].

[[Percival Serle]] wrote of Phillip in his ''Dictionary of Australian Biography'': 
{{quote|Steadfast in mind, modest, without self seeking, Phillip had imagination enough to conceive what the settlement might become, and the common sense to realize what at the moment was possible and expedient. When almost everyone was complaining he never himself complained, when all feared disaster he could still hopefully go on with his work. He was sent out to found a convict settlement, he laid the foundations of a great dominion.&lt;ref name=ps-dab&gt;{{cite web |last=Serle |first=Percival |title=Phillip, Arthur (1738–1814), admiral, and first governor of New South Wales |url=http://gutenberg.net.au/ebooks15/1500721h/0-dict-biogP-Q.html#phillip1 |work=Dictionary of Australian Biography |publisher=Project Gutenberg Australia |accessdate=3 March 2011 |year=1949}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Michael Pembroke's biography of Phillip adds that he was also a highly skilled international spy employed by the British government.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pembroke2013&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Pembroke|first=Michael|title=Arthur Phillip: Sailor, Mercenary, Governor, Spy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZbE6AAAAQBAJ|location=Melbourne|publisher=Hardie Grant|year=2013|isbn=978-1-74358-066-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===200th anniversary===
As part of a series of events on the bicentenary of his death, a memorial was dedicated in [[Westminster Abbey]] on 9 July 2014.&lt;ref name=Abbey&gt;{{cite web|title=Westminster Abbey honours father of modern Australia|url=http://www.westminster-abbey.org/press/news/news/2014/july/westminster-abbey-honours-father-of-modern-australia|website=Westminster Abbey|publisher=Westminster Abbey|accessdate=15 July 2014|date=9 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Peerless Pilgrimage&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Withington|first1=Ron|title=Peerless Pilgrimage|url=http://www.fellowshipfirstfleeters.org.au/images/journal6.pdf|publisher=Britain-Australia Society|accessdate=28 November 2016|date=2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the service the [[Dean of Westminster]], [[John Hall (priest)|Very Reverend Dr John Hall]], described Phillip as: &quot;This modest, yet world-class seaman, linguist, and patriot, whose selfless service laid the secure foundations on which was developed the Commonwealth of Australia, will always be remembered and honoured alongside other pioneers and inventors here in the [[Nave]]: [[David Livingstone]], [[Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald|Thomas Cochrane]], and [[Isaac Newton]].&quot;&lt;ref name=Abbey/&gt;&lt;ref name=Connections0814&gt;{{cite journal|title=Westminster Abbey honours the father of modern Australia|journal=St James' Parish Connections|date=August–September 2014|page=10|url=http://sjks.org.au/wp-content/uploads/Parish-Connections-AugSep14.pdf|accessdate=31 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A similar memorial was unveiled by the outgoing 37th [[Governor of New South Wales]], [[Marie Bashir]], in [[St James' Church, Sydney]] on 31 August 2014.&lt;ref name=Connections10814&gt;{{cite journal|title=Arthur Phillip Memorial Service|journal=St James' Parish Connections|date=October–November 2014|pages=12–14|url=http://www.youblisher.com/p/992397-Parish-Connections-October-November-2014|accessdate=24 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A bronze bust was installed at the [[Museum of Sydney]]&lt;ref name=&quot;SMHbronze&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last1=Decent |first1=Tom |title=Arthur Phillip, NSW's first governor, memorialised with bronze bust |url=https://www.smh.com.au/national/nsw/arthur-phillip-nsws-first-governor-memorialised-with-bronze-bust-20140828-109iey.html |newspaper=[[The Sydney Morning Herald]] |accessdate=25 April 2019 |date=28 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;, and a full-day symposium planned on his contributions to the founding of modern Australia.&lt;ref name=MoS&gt;{{cite web|title=The First Governor – A Bicentenary Symposium on Arthur Phillip|url=http://sydneylivingmuseums.com.au/events/first-governor-bicentenary-symposium-arthur-phillip|publisher=Museum of Sydney|accessdate=31 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In popular culture==
Phillip is a prominent character in [[Timberlake Wertenbaker]]'s play ''[[Our Country's Good]]'', in which he commissions Lieutenant [[Ralph Clark]] to stage a production of ''[[The Recruiting Officer]]''. He is shown as compassionate and just, but receives little support from his fellow officers. He is also prominent in ''[[Banished (TV series)|Banished]]'' and is played by [[David Wenham]].

Phillip is referred to in the [[John Williamson (singer)|John Williamson]] song &quot;Chains around my ankle&quot;.

Phillip is a prominent character in a 2005 film ''[[The Incredible Journey of Mary Bryant]]'' where he is portrayed by [[Sam Neill]].

[[Kate Grenville]]'s 2008 novel ''[[The Lieutenant (novel)|The Lieutenant]]'' portrays Phillip through the character Commodore James Gilbert.

Phillip is a prominent character in the 2015 mini-series &quot;[[Banished (TV series)]]&quot; where he is portrayed by [[David Wenham]].

==Memorials==
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:arthur.phillips.memorial.at.bathampton.arp.jpg|The Arthur Phillip memorial on the wall of the Australia Chapel, [[Bathampton]]
Image:Arthur-Phillip P1010024.JPG|Tomb of Arthur Phillip in St Nicholas Church, Bathampton
Bust of Arthur Phillip in Mary-le-Bow Church - Diliff.jpg|Bust of Phillip at [[St Mary-le-Bow]] Church in London.
File:Phillip Memorial - St James' Church, Sydney.JPG|Memorial plaque to Governor Phillip in [[St James' Church, Sydney]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== See also ==
* ''[[Historical Records of Australia]]''
* [[Journals of the First Fleet]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== Bibliography ==
* {{cite book |last1=Becke |first1=Louis |author1-link=Louis Becke |last2=Jeffery |first2=Walter |title=Admiral Phillip: the founding of New South Wales |series=Builders of Great Britain |year=1899 |publisher=T. Fisher Unwin |location=London, England |title-link=s:Admiral Phillip: the founding of New South Wales }}
*{{cite book |title = Historical records of New South Wales. Vol. 1, part 2. Phillip, 1783–1792. | editor = Britton, Alex R. | month = | year = 1978 | publisher =Lansdown Slattery &amp; Co. | page =56 | url = | oclc=219911274 }}
* {{cite book | title =Convicts and empire : a naval question, 1776–1811 | first =Alan | last =Frost | year =1980 | publisher =Oxford University Press | isbn =9780195542554 | url-access =registration | url =https://archive.org/details/convictsempiren00fros }}
*{{cite book |title =Arthur Phillip, 1738–1814 : his voyaging | first =Alan | last = Frost | year =1987 | publisher =Oxford University Press | isbn =9780195547016 }}
* {{cite book |title =The precarious life of James Mario Matra : voyager with Cook, American loyalist, servant of empire | first =Alan | last =Frost | first2=Isabel |last2=Moutinho | year =1995 | publisher =The Miegunyah Press | isbn = 9780522846676 }}
* {{Citation
 | last=Hunter|first= John |authorlink=John Hunter (Royal Navy officer)
 | title=An Historical Journal of the Transactions at Port Jackson and Norfolk Island
 | date=1793
 | publisher=Printed for John Stockdale
 | location = London, England
 | url = https://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/15662
 | oclc=154257649
 | ol=8025878W
}}
* {{cite book |title =Arthur Phillip: Australia's first governor | first =Derek | last = Parker | year = 2009 | publisher =Woodslane Press | isbn =9781921203992 }}
* {{cite book |title = Arthur Phillip: sailor, mercenary, governor, spy | first =Michael | last = Pembroke | year = 2013 | publisher =Hardie Grant Books | isbn =9781742705088}}
* {{cite book |title =The Governors of New South Wales | first = Andrew | last = Tink |editor-last = Cavalier |editor-first = Rodney | year = 2009 | publisher = The Federation Press | isbn = 9781862877436 }}

== External links ==
{{Wikisource author}}
{{Commons category|Arthur Phillip}}
* {{Gutenberg author |id = Phillip,+Arthur |name = Arthur Phillip }}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname = Arthur Phillip |sopt = t }}
* [http://www.aphs.nsw.edu.au/ Arthur Phillip High School], [[Parramatta, New South Wales|Parramatta]] – state high (years 7–12) school named for Phillip
* [http://www.adb.online.anu.edu.au/biogs/A020292b.htm B. H. Fletcher, 'Phillip, Arthur (1738–1814)', [[Australian Dictionary of Biography]], Volume 2, [[Melbourne University Press]], 1967, pp 326–333.]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120607054600/http://www.royal-navy.org/lib/index.php?title=Biographical_Memoir_of_Arthur_Phillip%2C_Esq. Royal Navy History] Biographical Memoir of Arthur Phillip, Esq.
*[http://collectionsearch.nma.gov.au/ce/Arthur%20Phillip#Arthur%20Phillip?object=60388&amp;_suid=143217283491707996225246297326/ The Voyage of Governor Phillip to Botany Bay] – National Museum of Australia

{{-}}
{{S-start}}
{{S-gov}}
{{s-new |district}}
{{s-ttl |title=[[Governors of New South Wales|Governor of New South Wales]] |years=1788–1792}}
{{S-aft|after=[[John Hunter (New South Wales)|John Hunter]]}}
{{S-end}}

{{NewSouthWales Governors}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Phillip, Arthur}}
[[Category:Governors of New South Wales]]
[[Category:City founders]]
[[Category:Royal Navy admirals]]
[[Category:1738 births]]
[[Category:1814 deaths]]
[[Category:Australian penal colony administrators]]
[[Category:Royal Navy personnel of the Seven Years' War]]
[[Category:Royal Navy personnel of the American Revolutionary War]]
[[Category:People from Fulham]]
[[Category:English people of German descent]]
[[Category:Port Phillip]]
[[Category:18th-century Australian people]]
[[Category:People educated at the Royal Hospital School]]
[[Category:Colony of New South Wales people]]
[[Category:Sea captains]]</text>
      <sha1>6d0cc7zqgpgs3c2bc3i7t4o7j3c75qx</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
