  <page>
    <title>Ansgar</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2544</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939973143</id>
      <parentid>935233469</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-09T20:30:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Alexander Tendler</username>
        <id>6012192</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Death and legacy */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{other uses}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2015}}
{{Infobox saint
|name=Saint Ansgar
|birth_date=8 September 801
|death_date={{death date and age|df=yes|865|2|3|801|9|8}}
|feast_day=3 February
|venerated_in=[[Catholic Church]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Eastern Orthodox Church]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Anglican Communion]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://diobeth.typepad.com/files/holy-women-holy-men.pdf |title=Holy Men and Holy Women |website=Churchofengland.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br/&gt;[[Lutheranism]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.resurrectionpeople.org/saints.html |title=Notable Lutheran Saints |website=Resurrectionpeople.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|image=Bendixen Ansgar.jpg
|imagesize=
|caption=A depiction of Saint Ansgar from the Church Trinitatis, in [[Hamburg]], Germany
|birth_place=[[Corbie]]
|death_place=[[Bremen (city)|Bremen]]
|titles=Apostle of the North
|beatified_date=
|beatified_place=
|beatified_by=
|canonized_date=
|canonized_place=
|canonized_by=[[Pope Nicholas I]]
|attributes=Dressed in archbishop's attire with a model of the church
||suppressed_date=
|issues=
|prayer=
|prayer_attrib=
}}
'''Saint Ansgar''' (8 September 801 – 3 February 865), also known as '''Anskar''',&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = https://www.churchofengland.org/prayer-worship/worship/texts/festivals/lesser-festivals/anskar.aspx|title = Common Worship texts: Festivals|date = |accessdate = 2015-02-03|website = The Church of England|publisher = |last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt; '''Saint Anschar''' or '''Oscar''', was [[Archbishopric of Bremen|Archbishop of Hamburg-Bremen]] in the northern part of the '''Kingdom of the East Franks'''. Ansgar became known as the &quot;Apostle of the North&quot; because of his travels and the [[See of Hamburg]] received the missionary mandate to bring Christianity to Northern Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;ce&quot;&gt;{{CathEncy|wstitle=St. Anschar}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=SHMI&gt;{{cite book|author=Fr. Paolo O. Pirlo, SHMI|title=My First Book of Saints|year=1997|publisher=Sons of Holy Mary Immaculate – Quality Catholic Publications|isbn=971-91595-4-5|pages=41|chapter=St. Ansgar}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Life==
Ansgar was the son of a noble [[Franks|Frankish]] family, born near [[Amiens]].&lt;ref name=SHMI /&gt;&lt;ref name=dictionary&gt;{{cite book|last=Farmer|first=David Hugh|title=The Oxford dictionary of saints|year=1997|publisher=Oxford Univ. Press|location=Oxford [u.a.]|isbn=0-19-280058-2|page=25|edition=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; After his mother's early death, Ansgar was brought up in [[Corbie Abbey]], and was educated at the [[Order of Saint Benedict|Benedictine monastery]] in Picardy.&lt;ref name=SHMI /&gt; According to the ''[[Vita Ansgari]]i'' (&quot;Life of Ansgar&quot;), when the little boy learned in a vision that his mother was in the company of [[Saint Mary]], his careless attitude toward spiritual matters changed to seriousness.&lt;ref&gt;Rimbert, &quot;Life of Ansgar&quot; at p. 1, English translation available at https://sourcebooks.fordham.edu/basis/anskar.asp&lt;/ref&gt; His pupil, successor, and eventual biographer [[Rimbert]] considered the visions (of which this was the first) to have been Ansgar's main life motivator.

Ansgar was a product of the phase of Christianization of [[Duchy of Saxony|Saxony]] (present day [[Northern Germany]]) begun by [[Charlemagne]] and continued by his son and successor, [[Louis the Pious]]. In 822 Ansgar became one of many missionaries sent to found the abbey of [[Corvey]] (New Corbie) in [[Westphalia]], where he became a teacher and preacher. A group of monks including Ansgar were sent further north to [[Jutland]] with the king [[Harald Klak]], who had received baptism during his exile. With Harald's downfall in 827 and Ansgar's companion Autbert having died, their school for the sons of courtiers closed and Ansgar returned to Germany. Then in 829, after the Swedish king [[Björn at Hauge]] requested missionaries for his [[Swedes]], King Louis sent Ansgar, now accompanied by friar Witmar from New Corbie as his assistant. Ansgar preached and made converts, particularly during six months at [[Birka]], on Lake [[Mälaren]], where the wealthy widow [[Mor Frideborg]] extended hospitality. Ansgar organized a small congregation with her and the king's steward, Hergeir, as its most prominent members.

In 831 Ansgar returned to Louis' court at [[Worms, Germany|Worms]] and was appointed to the [[Archbishopric of Bremen]]. This was a new archbishopric, combining the bishoprics of Bremen and [[Verden, Germany|Verden]] and with the right to send missions into all the northern lands, as well as to consecrate bishops for them. Ansgar received the mission of evangelizing pagan [[Denmark]], [[Norway]] and [[Sweden]]. The King of Sweden decided to cast lots as to whether to admit the Christian missionaries into his kingdom. Ansgar recommended the issue to the care of God, and the lot was favorable.&lt;ref name=SHMI /&gt; Ansgar was consecrated as a bishop in November 831, with the approval of [[Pope Gregory IV|Gregory IV]]. Before traveling north once again, Ansgar traveled to Rome to receive the [[pallium]] directly from the pope's hands, and was formally named legate for the northern lands. [[Ebbo, Archbishop of Reims]] had previously received a similar commission, but would be deposed twice before his death in 851, and never actually traveled so far north, so the jurisdiction was divided by agreement, with Ebbo retaining Sweden for himself. For a time Ansgar devoted himself to the needs of his own diocese, which was still missionary territory and had few churches. He founded a monastery and a school in Hamburg. Although intended to serve the Danish mission further north, it accomplished little.

After [[Louis the Pious]] died in 840, his empire was divided and Ansgar lost the abbey of [[Torhout|Turholt]], which Louis had given to endow Ansgar's work. Then in 845, the [[Danes]] unexpectedly raided Hamburg, destroying all the church's treasures and books. Ansgar now had neither see nor revenue, and many helpers deserted him. The new king, Louis' third son, [[Louis the German]], did not re-endow Turholt to Ansgar, but in 847 he named the missionary to the vacant diocese of Bremen, where Ansgar moved in 848. However, since Bremen had been [[suffragan]] to the Bishop of Cologne, combining the sees of Bremen and Hamburg presented canonical difficulties. After prolonged negotiations, [[Pope Nicholas I]] would approve the union of the two dioceses in 864.

Through this political turmoil, Ansgar continued his northern mission. The Danish civil war compelled him to establish good relations with two kings, [[Horik I|Horik the Elder]] and his son, [[Horik II]]. Both assisted him until his death; Ansgar was able to secure permission to build a church in [[Hedeby|Sleswick]] north of Hamburg and recognition of Christianity as a tolerated religion.&lt;ref&gt;Wood, Ian. The Missionary Life: Saints and the Evangelisation of Europe, 400–1050. Great Britain: Longman, 2001. pp. 124–125&lt;/ref&gt; Ansgar did not forget the Swedish mission, and spent two years there in person (848–850), averting a threatened pagan reaction. In 854, Ansgar returned to Sweden when king [[Olof (I) of Sweden|Olof]] ruled in Birka. According to Rimbert, he was well disposed to Christianity. On a Viking raid to [[Apuole]] (current village in [[Lithuania]]) in [[Courland]], the Swedes plundered the [[Curonians]].

==Death and legacy==

Ansgar was buried in [[Bremen (city)|Bremen]] in 865. His successor as archbishop, [[Rimbert]], wrote the ''[[Vita Ansgari]]i''. He noted that Ansgar wore a rough hair shirt, lived on bread and water, and showed great charity to the poor. Adam of Bremen attributed the ''Vita et miracula of Willehad'' (first bishop of Bremen) to Ansgar in ''Gesta Hammenburgensis ecclesiæ''; Ansgar is also the reputed author of a collection of brief prayers ''Pigmenta'' (ed. J. M. Lappenberg, Hamburg, 1844).&lt;ref&gt;Samuel Macauley, ed. (1914). &quot;Ansgar&quot;. [[New Schaff–Herzog Encyclopedia of Religious Knowledge]] (third ed.). London and New York: Funk and Wagnalls&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pope Nicholas I]] declared Ansgar a saint shortly after the missionary's death. The first actual missionary in Sweden and the [[Nordic countries]] (and organizer of the Catholic church therein), Ansgar was later declared &quot;Patron of [[Scandinavia]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=SHMI /&gt;

Relics are located in [[Hamburg]] in two places: St. Mary's Cathedral (Ger.: Domkirche St. Marien) and St. Ansgar's and St. Bernard's Church (Ger.: St. Ansgar und St. Bernhard Kirche).{{citation needed|date=August 2018}}
Statues of Bishop Ansgar stand in [[Hamburg]], [[Copenhagen]] and [[Ribe]], as well as a stone cross at [[Birka]]. A [[Impact crater|crater]] on the [[Moon]], [[Ansgarius (crater)|Ansgarius]], has been named for him. His [[Calendar of saints|feast day]] is 3 February.

==Visions==
[[File:Erzbischof Ansgar 01 KMJ.jpg|thumb|upright|Saint Ansgar statue in Hamburg]]
Although a historical document and primary source written by a man whose existence can be proven historically, the ''[[Vita Ansgari]]i'' (&quot;The Life of Ansgar&quot;) aims above all to demonstrate Ansgar's sanctity. It is partly concerned with Ansgar's visions, which, according to the author Rimbert, encouraged and assisted Ansgar's remarkable missionary feats.

Through the course of this work, Ansgar repeatedly embarks on a new stage in his career following a vision.  According to Rimbert, his early studies and ensuing devotion to the ascetic life of a monk were inspired by a vision of his mother in the presence of Saint Mary.  Again, when the Swedish people were left without a priest for some time, he begged King Horik to help him with this problem; then after receiving his consent, consulted with Bishop Gautbert to find a suitable man. The two together sought the approval of King Louis, which he granted when he learned that they were in agreement on the issue. Ansgar was convinced he was commanded by heaven to undertake this mission and was influenced by a vision he received when he was concerned about the journey, in which he met a man who reassured him of his purpose and informed him of a prophet that he would meet, the [[abbot]] [[Adalard of Corbie|Adalhard]], who would instruct him in what was to happen.  In the vision, he searched for and found Adalhard, who commanded, &quot;Islands, listen to me, pay attention, remotest peoples&quot;, which Ansgar interpreted as God's will that he go to the Scandinavian countries as &quot;most of that country consisted of islands, and also, when 'I will make you the light of the nations so that my salvation may reach to the ends of the earth' was added, since the end of the world in the north was in Swedish territory&quot;.&lt;ref name=rimbert&gt;{{cite web|last=Rimbert|title=Life of Anskar, the Apostle of the North, 801–865|url=http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/basis/anskar.asp|work=Medieval Sourcebook|publisher=New York: Fordham University|accessdate=2012-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==

{{Portal|Saints}}
*[[List of Catholic saints]]
*[[List of Eastern Orthodox saints]]
*[[Calendar of saints (Episcopal Church)]]
* [[Hochkirchlicher Apostolat St. Ansgar]]
*''[[Vita Ansgari]]i''

==References==
{{Reflist}}
==Further reading==
* Jakobsson, Sverrir. ''Mission Miscarried: The Narrators of the Ninth-Century Missions to Scandinavia and Central Europe''. Bulgaria Medievalis 2 (2011), 49–69.
* Palmer, James T., ''Rimbert's Vita Anskarii and the Scandinavian Mission in the Ninth Century''. Journal of Ecclesiastical History 55/2 (2004), 235–56.
* Pryce, Mark. ''Literary Companion to the Festivals: A Poetic Gathering to Accompany Liturgical Celebrations of Commemorations and Festivals.''  Minneapolis: Fortress Press, 2003.
* Tschan, Francis J. ''History of the Archbishops of Hamburg-Bremen''.  New York: Columbia University Press, 1959.

==External links==
{{commons category|Saint Ansgar}}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20000309135829/http://www.skolinternet.telia.se/TIS/birka/texteng/hist.htm Ansgar at Birka History of Birka]
*[[Vita Ansgari]], English translation from [http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/basis/anskar.html Medieval sourcebook]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20051102144454/http://www.uni-heidelberg.de/subject/hd/fak7/hist/c1/de/gen/gen/grmnhist/log.started920201/mail-16.html German History Forum]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20130313011358/http://www.cristoraul.com/ENGLISH/readinghall/GalleryofHistory/ANSKAR/Anskar-DOOR.html ANSKAR The Apostle of the North (801–865). Translated from the Vita Anskarii by Bishop Rimbert his fellow missionary and successor. BY CHARLES H. ROBINSON. Im BTM format]
&lt;br&gt;
{{s-start}}
{{s-hou||8 September|801 in Amiens or 796 in Corbie|3 February|865 in Bremen}}
{{s-rel|ca}}
{{s-new|diocese|reason=}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Archbishop of Hamburg]]|years=834–865}}
{{s-aft|rows=2|after=[[Rimbert]]}}
|-
{{s-bef|before=Leuderich}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Archbishops of Bremen|Bishop of Bremen]]|years=848–865}}
{{s-end}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ansgar}}
[[Category:801 births]]
[[Category:865 deaths]]
[[Category:Diplomats of the Holy See]]
[[Category:French people of German descent]]
[[Category:Danish Roman Catholic saints]]
[[Category:Medieval Swedish saints]]
[[Category:9th-century bishops]]
[[Category:Archbishops of Hamburg-Bremen]]
[[Category:Viking Age clergy]]
[[Category:9th-century Christian saints]]
[[Category:Saints from East Francia]]
[[Category:9th-century people from East Francia]]
[[Category:Christian missionaries in Denmark]]
[[Category:Christian missionaries in Sweden]]
[[Category:Medieval Danish saints]]
[[Category:9th-century Latin writers]]
[[Category:Writers of the Carolingian Empire]]</text>
      <sha1>0olerz68q4oammj6zbigrvmz1g3zfqu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
