  <page>
    <title>Dance</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7885</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938284110</id>
      <parentid>932017808</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-30T06:19:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>FrescoBot</username>
        <id>9021902</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Bot: [[User:FrescoBot/galleries|galleries with nonexistent images]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|A performing art consisting of movement of the body}}
{{pp-semi-indef}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{other uses}}
{{redirect-multi|2|Dancer|Dancing}}

{{Performing arts}}
[[File:Two dancers.jpg|alt=A man and woman, mid-leap|thumb|Two [[modern dance]]rs]]
[[File:Dancers leaping.jpg|thumb|Members of a dance routine.]]

'''Dance''' is a [[performing art]] [[art form|form]] consisting of purposefully selected sequences of [[kinesiology|human movement]]. This movement has [[aesthetic]] and [[symbolism (arts)|symbolic]] value, and is acknowledged as dance by performers and observers within a particular [[culture]].{{refn|group=nb|Many definitions of dance have been proposed. This definition is based on the following:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;Dance is human movement created and expressed for an aesthetic purpose.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fraleigh1987&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Sondra Horton Fraleigh|title=Dance and the Lived Body: A Descriptive Aesthetics|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=K4FN1lOcR-wC&amp;pg=PA43|year=1987|publisher=University of Pittsburgh Pre|isbn=978-0-8229-7170-2|page=49}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;Dance is a transient mode of expression performed in a given form and style by the human body moving in space. Dance occurs through purposefully selected and controlled rhythmic movements; the resulting phenomenon is recognized as dance both by the performer and the observing members of a given group.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Joann Kealinohomoku|editor1-last=Copeland|editor1-first=Roger|editor2-last=Cohen|editor2-first=Marshall|title=An Anthropologist Looks at Ballet as a Form of Ethnic Dance|work=What is Dance? Readings in Theory and Criticism|date=1970|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=New York|edition=1983|url=http://lodev.wesleyan.edu/wespress/acceleratedmotion/primary_sources/texts/ecologiesofbeauty/anthro_ballet.pdf|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110104220818/http://lodev.wesleyan.edu/wespress/acceleratedmotion/primary_sources/texts/ecologiesofbeauty/anthro_ballet.pdf|url-status=dead|archive-date=2011-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;Dance is human behaviour composed (from the dancer’s perspective, which is usually shared by the audience members of the dancer’s culture) of purposeful (individual choice and social learning play a role), intentionally rhythmical, and culturally patterned sequences of nonverbal body movement mostly other than those performed in ordinary motor activities. The motion (in time, space, and with effort) has an inherent and aesthetic value (the notion of appropriateness and competency as viewed by the dancer’s culture) and symbolic potential.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Judith Lynne Hanna|title=The performer-audience connection: emotion to metaphor in dance and society|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ze8TAQAAIAAJ|year=1983|publisher=University of Texas Press|isbn=978-0-292-76478-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} Dance can be categorized and described by its [[choreography]], by its repertoire of movements, or by its [[History of dance|historical period]] or [[List of ethnic, regional, and folk dances by origin|place of origin]].

An important distinction is to be drawn between the contexts of [[Concert dance|theatrical]] and [[Participation dance|participatory]] dance,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.artsalive.ca/en/dan/dance101/forms.asp Canadian National Arts Centre – Dance Forms: An Introduction]&lt;/ref&gt; although these two categories are not always completely separate; both may have special functions, whether [[Social dance|social]], [[ceremonial dance|ceremonial]], [[competitive dance|competitive]], [[erotic dance|erotic]], [[war dance|martial]], or [[sacred dance|sacred]]/[[liturgical dance|liturgical]]. Other forms of human movement are sometimes said to have a dance-like quality, including [[martial arts]], [[gymnastics]], [[cheerleading]], [[figure skating]], [[synchronised swimming]], marching bands, and many other forms of athletics.

==Performance and participation==
[[File:GDC onlywayaround.jpg|thumb|right|upright=1.35|Members of an American jazz dance company perform a formal group routine in a concert dance setting]]

Theatrical dance, also called performance or concert dance, is intended primarily as a spectacle, usually a [[performance]] upon a [[Stage (theater)|stage]] by [[virtuoso]] dancers. It often tells a [[narrative|story]], perhaps using [[Mime artist|mime]], [[Dance costumes|costume]] and [[Theatrical scenery|scenery]], or else it may simply [[Interpretive dance|interpret the musical accompaniment]], which is often specially composed. Examples are western [[ballet]] and [[modern dance]], [[Classical Indian dance]] and Chinese and Japanese song and dance dramas. Most classical forms are centred upon dance alone, but performance dance may also appear in [[opera]] and other forms of [[musical theatre]].

Participatory dance, on the other hand, whether it be a [[folk dance]], a [[social dance]], a [[group dance]] such as a [[Line dance|line]], [[Circle dance|circle]], [[Medieval dance#Other Chain Dances|chain]] or [[square dance]], or a [[partner dance]] such as is common in western [[Ballroom dance|Western ballroom dancing]], is undertaken primarily for a common purpose, such as [[social interaction]] or [[exercise]], of participants rather than onlookers. Such dance seldom has any narrative. A group dance and a ''[[corps de ballet]]'', a social partner dance and a ''[[pas de deux]]'', differ profoundly. Even a [[solo dance]] may be undertaken solely for the satisfaction of the dancer. Participatory dancers often all employ the same movements and steps but, for example, in the [[rave culture]] of [[electronic dance music]], vast crowds may engage in [[free dance]], uncoordinated with those around them. On the other hand, some cultures lay down strict rules as to the particular dances in which, for example, men, women and children may or must participate.

==Origins==
{{Main|History of Dance}}
[[File:Dancing painting at Bhimbetka.jpg|thumb|left|Mesolithic dancers at Bhimbetka]]

[[archeology|Archeological]] evidence for early dance includes 9,000-year-old paintings in [[India]] at the [[Rock Shelters of Bhimbetka]], and [[ancient Egypt|Egyptian]] tomb paintings depicting dancing figures, dated c. 3300 BC. It has been proposed that before the invention of written languages, dance was an important part of the oral and performance methods of passing stories down from one generation to the next.&lt;ref name=&quot;lecomte&quot;&gt;Nathalie Comte. &quot;Europe, 1450 to 1789: Encyclopedia of the Early Modern World&quot;. Ed. Jonathan Dewald. Vol. 2. New York: Charles Scribner's Sons, 2004. pp&amp;nbsp;94–108.&lt;/ref&gt; The use of dance in [[Ecstasy (emotion)|ecstatic]] [[altered state of consciousness|trance states]] and healing rituals (as observed today in many contemporary &quot;primitive&quot; cultures, from the Brazilian [[rainforest]] to the [[Kalahari Desert]]) is thought to have been another early factor in the social development of dance.&lt;ref name=&quot;guenther&quot;&gt;Guenther, Mathias Georg. 'The San Trance Dance: Ritual and Revitalization Among the Farm Bushmen of the Ghanzi District, Republic of Botswana.' Journal, South West Africa Scientific Society, v. 30, 1975–76.&lt;/ref&gt;

References to dance can be found in very early recorded history; [[Greek dance]] (''[[horos]]'') is referred to by [[Plato]], [[Aristotle]], [[Plutarch]] and [[Lucian]].&lt;ref&gt;Raftis, Alkis, ''The World of Greek Dance'' Finedawn, Athens (1987) p25.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Bible]] and [[Talmud]] refer to many events related to dance, and contain over 30 different dance terms.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Kadman|first=Gurit|date=1952|title=Yemenite Dances and Their Influence on the New Israeli Folk Dances|jstor=835838|journal=Journal of the International Folk Music Council|volume=4|pages=27–30|doi=10.2307/835838}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[History of Chinese classical dance|Chinese]] pottery as early as the [[Neolithic]] period, groups of people are depicted dancing in a line holding hands,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://en.chnmuseum.cn/Default.aspx?TabId=549&amp;AntiqueLanguageID=3002|title=Basin with design of dancers|publisher=National Museum of China|language=en-US|access-date=2017-05-23|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170811060221/http://en.chnmuseum.cn/(S(qskmzwqsztmrds45bof052bh))/Default.aspx?TabId=549&amp;AntiqueLanguageID=3002|archive-date=2017-08-11|url-status=dead}} Pottery from the [[Majiayao culture]] (3100 BC to 2700 BC)&lt;/ref&gt; and the earliest Chinese word for &quot;dance&quot; is found written in the [[oracle bones]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The history of Chinese dance|last=Kʻo-fen|first=Wang|date=1985|publisher=Foreign Languages Press|isbn=978-0-8351-1186-7|oclc=977028549|page=7}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dance is further described in the ''[[Lüshi Chunqiu]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;aesthetic tradition&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=d1eZuB2xwYwC&amp;pg=PA5|title=The Chinese aesthetic tradition|first=Zehou|last=Li|first2=Maija Bell|last2=Samei|date=2010|publisher=University of Hawaiʻi Press|isbn=978-0-8248-3307-7|oclc=960030161|page=5}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://ctext.org/dictionary.pl?if=en&amp;id=23281|title=Lü Shi Chun Qiu|last=Sturgeon|first=Donald|website=Chinese Text Project Dictionary|language=Chinese|access-date=2017-05-23|quote=Original text: 昔葛天氏之樂，三人操牛尾，投足以歌八闋}}&lt;/ref&gt; Primitive dance in ancient China was associated with sorcery and shamanic rituals.
[[File:Bronze Statuette of a Veiled and Masked Dancer 1.jpg|thumb|left|upright=0.8|Greek bronze statuette of a veiled and masked dancer, 3rd–2nd century BC, Alexandria, Egypt.]]
During the first millennium [[common era|BCE]] in India, many texts were composed which attempted to codify aspects of daily life. [[Bharata Muni]]'s ''[[Natyashastra]]'' (literally ''&quot;the text of dramaturgy&quot;'') is one of the earlier texts. It mainly deals with drama, in which dance plays an important part in Indian culture. It categorizes dance into four types – secular, ritual, abstract, and, interpretive – and into four regional varieties. The text elaborates various hand-gestures (''[[mudras]]'') and classifies movements of the various limbs, steps and so on. A strong continuous tradition of dance has since continued in India, through to modern times, where it continues to play a role in culture, ritual, and, notably, the [[Bollywood]] entertainment industry. Many other [[contemporary dance]] forms can likewise be traced back to [[Historical dance|historical]], [[Traditional dance|traditional]], [[Ceremonial dance|ceremonial]], and [[List of dances sorted by ethnicity|ethnic]] dance.

==Dance and music==
{{main|Dance music}}
[[File:Dancing girls in concert.jpg|thumb|right|Dancing girls in pop-concert, Sofia, Bulgaria.]]
Dance is generally, though not exclusively, performed with the accompaniment of music and may or may not be performed ''in [[time signature|time]]'' to such music. Some dance (such as [[tap dance]]) may provide its own audible accompaniment in place of (or in addition to) music. Many early forms of music and dance were created for each other and are frequently performed together. Notable examples of traditional dance/music couplings include the [[jig]], [[waltz]], [[Tango music|tango]], [[disco]], and [[Salsa (dance)|salsa]]. Some [[musical genre]]s have a parallel dance form such as [[baroque music]] and [[baroque dance]]; other varieties of dance and music may share nomenclature but developed separately, such as [[Classical music era|classical music]] and [[classical ballet]].

== Dance and rhythm ==
[[Rhythm]] and dance are deeply linked in history and practice. The American dancer [[Ted Shawn]] wrote; &quot;The conception of rhythm which underlies all studies of the dance is something about which we could talk forever, and still not finish.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Shawn 50&quot;&gt;Shawn, Ted, ''Dance We Must'', 1946, Dennis Dobson Ltd., London, p. 50&lt;/ref&gt; A musical rhythm requires two main elements; first, a regularly-repeating [[pulse (music)|pulse]] (also called the &quot;beat&quot; or &quot;tactus&quot;) that establishes the [[tempo]] and, second, a pattern of [[Accent (music)|accents]] and [[Rest (music)|rests]] that establishes the character of the [[Meter (music)|metre or basic rhythmic pattern]]. The basic pulse is roughly equal in duration to a simple step or gesture.
[[File:Tango rhythm.svg|thumb|A basic tango rhythm]]
Dances generally have a characteristic tempo and rhythmic pattern. The tango, for example, is usually danced in {{music|time|2|4}} time at approximately 66 beats per minute. The basic slow step, called a &quot;slow&quot;, lasts for one beat, so that a full &quot;right–left&quot; step is equal to one {{music|time|2|4}} measure. The basic forward and backward walk of the dance is so counted – &quot;slow-slow&quot; – while many additional figures are counted &quot;slow – quick-quick.&lt;ref&gt;Imperial Society of Teachers of Dancing, ''Ballroom Dancing'', Teach Yourself Books, Hodder and Stoughton, 1977, p. 38&lt;/ref&gt;

Just as musical rhythms are defined by a pattern of strong and weak beats, so repetitive body movements often depends on alternating &quot;strong&quot; and &quot;weak&quot; muscular movements.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kirstein 4&quot;&gt;Lincoln Kirstein, ''Dance'', Dance Horizons Incorporated, New York, 1969, p. 4&lt;/ref&gt; Given this alternation of left-right, of forward-backward and rise-fall, along with the [[Symmetry in biology|bilateral symmetry]] of the human body, it is natural that many dances and much music are in [[duple and quadruple meter]]. However, since some such movements require more time in one phase than the other – such as the longer time required to lift a hammer than to strike – some dance rhythms fall equally naturally into [[triple metre]].&lt;ref&gt;Shawn, Ted, ''Dance We Must'', 1946, Dennis Dobson Ltd., London, p. 49&lt;/ref&gt; Occasionally, as in [[Music of Southeastern Europe|the folk dances of the Balkans]], dance traditions depend heavily on more complex rhythms. Further, complex dances composed of a fixed sequence of steps always require phrases and melodies of a certain fixed length to accompany that sequence.

[[File:Lululaund - The Dancing Girl (painting and silk cloth. A.L. Baldry 1901, before p.107).jpg|thumb|left|upright=0.6|''Lululaund – The Dancing Girl'' (painting and silk cloth. A.L. Baldry 1901, before p. 107), The inscription reads; &quot;Dancing is a form of rhythm/ Rhythm is a form of music/ Music is a form of thought/ And thought is a form of divinity.&quot;]]
The very act of dancing, the steps themselves, generate an &quot;initial skeleton of rhythmic beats&quot; that must have preceded any separate musical accompaniment, while dance itself, as much as music, requires time-keeping&lt;ref&gt;Lincoln Kirstein, ''Dance'', Dance Horizons Incorporated, New York, 1969, p. 3&lt;/ref&gt; just as utilitarian repetitive movements such as walking, hauling and digging take on, as they become refined, something of the quality of dance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kirstein 4&quot;/&gt;

Musical accompaniment therefore arose in the earliest dance, so that ancient Egyptians attributed the origin of the dance to the divine Athotus, who was said to have observed that music accompanying religious rituals caused participants to move rhythmically and to have brought these movements into proportional measure. The same idea, that dance arises from musical rhythm, is still found in [[renaissance]] Europe in the works of the dancing master [[Guglielmo Ebreo da Pesaro]] who speaks of dance as a physical movement that arises from and expresses inward, spiritual motion agreeing with the &quot;measures and perfect concords of harmony&quot; that fall upon the human ear,&lt;ref name=&quot;Kirstein 4&quot;/&gt; while, earlier, [[Mechthild of Magdeburg]], seizing upon dance as a symbol of the holy life foreshadowed in Jesus' saying &quot;I have piped and ye have not danced&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Matthew 11:17&lt;/ref&gt; writes;

{{quote|I can not dance unless thou leadest. If thou wouldst have me spring aloft, sing thou and I will spring, into love and from love to knowledge and from knowledge to ecstasy above all human sense&lt;ref&gt;Lincoln Kirstein, ''Dance'', Dance Horizons Incorporated, New York, 1969, p. 108&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[Thoinot Arbeau]]'s celebrated 16th century dance-treatise ''Orchésographie'', indeed, begins with definitions of over eighty distinct drum-rhythms.&lt;ref&gt;Lincoln Kirstein, ''Dance'', Dance Horizons Incorporated, New York, 1969, p. 157&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Dancing with Helen Moller; her own statement of her philosophy and practice and teaching formed upon the classic Greek model, and adapted to meet the aesthetic and hygienic needs of to-day, with (14784705065).jpg|thumb|right|Helen Moller]]
As has been shown above, dance has been represented through the ages as having emerged as a response to music yet, as [[Lincoln Kirstein]] implied, it is at least as likely that primitive music arose from dance. Shawn concurs, stating that dance &quot;was the first art of the human race, and the matrix out of which all other arts grew&quot; and that even the &quot;[[Meter (poetry)|metre]] in our poetry today is a result of the accents necessitated by body movement, as the dancing and reciting were performed simultaneously&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Shawn 50&quot;/&gt; – an assertion somewhat supported by the common use of the term &quot;foot&quot; to describe the fundamental rhythmic units of poetry.

[[Percy Scholes|Scholes]], not a dancer but a musician, offers support for this view, stating that the steady measures of music, of two, three or four beats to the bar, its equal and balanced phrases, regular cadences, contrasts and repetitions, may all be attributed to the &quot;incalculable&quot; influence of dance upon music.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Scholes |first=Percy A. |authorlink1= Percy Scholes |title= The Oxford Companion to Music |edition= 10 |year= 1977 |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |location= |isbn= |chapter=Dance |ref= CITEREFScholes1977}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Émile Jaques-Dalcroze]], primarily a musician and teacher, relates how a study of the physical movements of pianists led him &quot;to the discovery that musical sensations of a rhythmic nature call for the muscular and nervous response of the whole organism&quot;, to develop &quot;a special training designed to regulate nervous reactions and effect a co-ordination of muscles and nerves&quot; and ultimately to seek the connections between &quot;the art of music and the art of dance&quot;, which he formulated into his system of [[Dalcroze Eurhythmics|eurhythmics]].&lt;ref&gt;Émile Jaques-Dalcroze, ''Rhythm, Music and Education'', 1973, The Dalcroze Society, London, p. viii&lt;/ref&gt; He concluded that &quot;musical rhythm is only the transposition into sound of movements and dynamisms spontaneously and involuntarily expressing emotion&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Émile Jaques-Dalcroze, ''Rhythm, Music and Education'', 1973, The Dalcroze Society, London, p. 181&lt;/ref&gt;

Hence, though doubtless, as Shawn asserts, &quot;it is quite possible to develop the dance without music and... music is perfectly capable of standing on its own feet without any assistance from the dance&quot;, nevertheless the &quot;two arts will always be related and the relationship can be profitable both to the dance and to music&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Shawn, Ted, ''Dance We Must'', 1946, Dennis Dobson Ltd., London, p. 54&lt;/ref&gt; the precedence of one art over the other being a moot point. The [[Common metre|common ballad measures]] of hymns and folk-songs takes their name from dance, as does the [[Carol (music)|carol]], originally a [[circle dance]]. Many purely musical pieces have been named &quot;[[waltz]]&quot; or &quot;[[minuet]]&quot;, for example, while many [[concert dance]]s have been produced that are based upon abstract musical pieces, such as ''[[2 and 3 Part Inventions]], [[Adams Violin Concerto]]'' and ''[[Andantino (ballet)|Andantino]]''. Similarly, poems are often structured and named after dances or musical works, while dance and music have both drawn their conception of &quot;measure&quot; or &quot;metre&quot; from poetry.

Shawn quotes with approval the statement of Dalcroze that, while the art of musical rhythm consists in differentiating and combining time durations, pauses and accents &quot;according to physiological law&quot;, that of &quot;plastic rhythm&quot; (i.e. dance) &quot;is to designate movement in space, to interpret long time-values by slow movements and short ones by quick movements, regulate pauses by their divers successions and express sound accentuations in their multiple nuances by additions of bodily weight, by means of muscular innervations&quot;.

Shawn nevertheless points out that the system of musical time is a &quot;man-made, artificial thing.... a manufactured tool, whereas rhythm is something that has always existed and depends on man not at all&quot;, being &quot;the continuous flowing time which our human minds cut up into convenient units&quot;, suggesting that music might be revivified by a return to the values and the time-perception of dancing.&lt;ref&gt;Shawn, Ted, ''Dance We Must'', 1946, Dennis Dobson Ltd., London, pp. 50–51&lt;/ref&gt;

The early-20th-century American dancer Helen Moller stated simply that &quot;it is rhythm and form more than harmony and color which, from the beginning, has bound music, poetry and dancing together in a union that is indissoluble.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Moller, Helen and Dunham, Curtis, ''Dancing with Helen Moller'', 1918, John Lane (New York and London), p. 74&lt;/ref&gt;

==Approaches to dance==

===Concert dance===
Concert dance, like [[opera]], generally depends for its large-scale form upon a [[narrative]] [[dramatic structure]]. The movements and gestures of the [[choreography]] are primarily intended to [[mime]] the personality and aims of the characters and their part in the plot.&lt;ref&gt;Laban, Rudolf, ''The Mastery of Movement'', MacDonald and Evans, London, 1960, p. 2&lt;/ref&gt; Such theatrical requirements tend towards longer, freer movements than those usual in non-narrative dance styles. On the other hand, the ''[[ballet blanc]]'', developed in the 19th century, allows interludes of rhythmic dance that developed into entirely &quot;plotless&quot; ballets in the 20th century&lt;ref&gt;Minden, Eliza Gaynor, [https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=S-RuSzcrBnAC&amp;dq=%22ballet+blanc%22&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s ''The Ballet Companion: A Dancer's Guide''], Simon and Schuster, 2007, p. 92&lt;/ref&gt; and that allowed fast, rhythmic dance-steps such as those of the ''petit allegro''. A well-known example is ''[[Danse des petits cygnes|The Cygnets' Dance]]'' in act two of ''[[Swan Lake]]''.

The [[ballet]] developed out of courtly dramatic productions of 16th- and 17th-century France and Italy and for some time dancers performed dances developed from those familiar from the musical suite,&lt;ref&gt;Thoinot Arbeau, ''Orchesography'', trans. by Mary Stewart Evans, with notes by Julia Sutton, New York: Dover, 1967&lt;/ref&gt; all of which were defined by definite rhythms closely identified with each dance. These appeared as [[character dance]]s in the era of [[romantic nationalism]].

Ballet reached widespread vogue in the romantic era, accompanied by a larger orchestra and grander musical conceptions that did not lend themselves easily to rhythmic clarity and by dance that emphasised dramatic mime. A broader concept of rhythm was needed, that which [[Rudolf Laban]] terms the &quot;rhythm and shape&quot; of movement that communicates character, emotion and intention,&lt;ref&gt;Laban, Rudolf, ''The Mastery of Movement'', MacDonald and Evans, London, 1960, pp. 2, 4 ''et passim''&lt;/ref&gt; while only certain scenes required the exact synchronisation of step and music essential to other dance styles, so that, to Laban, modern Europeans seemed totally unable to grasp the meaning of &quot;primitive rhythmic movements&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Laban, Rudolf, ''The Mastery of Movement'', MacDonald and Evans, London, 1960, p. 86&lt;/ref&gt; a situation that began to change in the 20th century with such productions as [[Igor Stravinsky]]'s ''[[The Rite of Spring]]'' with its new rhythmic language evoking primal feelings of a primitive past.&lt;ref&gt;Abigail Wagner, [https://www.lawrence.edu/mfhe/www_web_student/Everyone/A%20Different%20Type%20of%20Rhythm.pdf ''A Different Type of Rhythm''], Lawrence University, Wisconsin&lt;/ref&gt;

Indian classical dance styles, like ballet, are often in dramatic form, so that there is a similar complementarity between narrative expression and &quot;pure&quot; dance. In this case, however, the two are separately defined, though not always separately performed. The rhythmic elements, which are abstract and technical, are known as ''nritta''. Both this and expressive dance ''(nritya)'', though, are closely tied to the rhythmic system (''[[Tala (music)|tala]]''). Teachers have adapted the spoken rhythmic mnemonic system called ''[[Bol (music)|bol]]'' to the needs of dancers.

Japanese classical dance-theatre styles such as [[Kabuki]] and [[Noh]], like Indian dance-drama, distinguish between narrative and abstract dance productions. The three main categories of kabuki are ''[[jidaimono]]'' (historical), ''[[sewamono]]'' (domestic) and ''[[shosagoto]]'' (dance pieces).&lt;ref name=&quot;Kabuki MIT Global Shakespeares&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://globalshakespeares.mit.edu/glossary/kabuki/ | title=Kabuki « MIT Global Shakespeares | accessdate=April 8, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Somewhat similarly, Noh distinguishes between ''Geki Noh'', based around the advancement of plot and the narration of action, and ''Furyū Noh'', dance pieces involving acrobatics, stage properties, multiple characters and elaborate stage action.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ortolani&quot;&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ge8cWl8OT3gC&amp;pg=PA132&amp;dq=mugen-no+Genzai-no+waki-no#v=onepage&amp;q=mugen-no%20Genzai-no%20waki-no&amp;f=false |page=132 |title=The Japanese theatre: from shamanistic ritual to contemporary pluralism |first=Benito |last=Ortolani| publisher=Princeton University Press|year=1995 |isbn=978-0-691-04333-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Participatory and social dance===
[[Social dances]], those intended for participation rather than for an audience, may include various forms of mime and narrative, but are typically set much more closely to the rhythmic pattern of music, so that terms like [[waltz]] and [[polka]] refer as much to musical pieces as to the dance itself. The rhythm of the dancers' feet may even form an essential part of the music, as in [[tap dance]]. African dance, for example, is rooted in fixed basic steps, but may also allow a high degree of rhythmic interpretation: the feet or the trunk mark the basic pulse while cross-rhythms are picked up by shoulders, knees, or head, with the best dancers simultaneously giving plastic expression to all the elements of the [[polyrhythm]]ic pattern.&lt;ref&gt;Ayansu, E.S. and Whitfield, P. (eds.), ''The Rhythms Of Life'', Marshall Editions, 1982, p. 161&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cultural traditions==

===Africa===
[[File:Kuduro - One of the Angolan National Dances.webm|thumb|&quot;[[Kuduro]]&quot; (Angolan dance)]]
[[File:Cultural celebrations resumed with the end of the LRA conflict in Northern Uganda (7269658432).jpg|thumb|right|upright=1.3|[[Uganda]]n youth dance at a cultural celebration of peace]]
{{main|African dance}}

Dance in Africa is deeply integrated into society and major events in a community are frequently reflected in dances: dances are performed for births and funerals, weddings and wars.&lt;ref name=&quot;WelshHanley2010&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Kariamu Welsh|author2=Elizabeth A. Hanley|author3=Jacques D'Amboise|title=African Dance|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=eXDWJiRr0PYC|date=1 January 2010|publisher=Infobase Publishing|isbn=978-1-60413-477-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|13}} Traditional dances impart cultural morals, including religious traditions and sexual standards; give vent to repressed emotions, such as [[grief]]; motivate community members to cooperate, whether fighting wars or grinding grain; enact spiritual rituals; and contribute to [[structural cohesion|social cohesiveness]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Hanna1973&quot; &gt;{{cite journal|last1=Hanna|first1=Judith Lynne|title=African Dance: the continuity of change|journal=Yearbook of the International Folk Music Council|date=1973|volume=5|pages=165–174|jstor=767501|doi=10.2307/767501}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Thousands of dances are performed around the continent. These may be divided into traditional, neotraditional, and classical styles: [[folklore|folkloric]] dances of a particular society, dances created more recently in imitation of traditional styles, and dances transmitted more formally in schools or private lessons.&lt;ref name=&quot;WelshHanley2010&quot; /&gt;{{rp|18}} African dance has been altered by many forces, such as European [[missionaries]] and [[colonialist]] governments, who often suppressed local dance traditions as licentious or distracting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hanna1973&quot; /&gt; Dance in contemporary African cultures still serves its traditional functions in new contexts; dance may celebrate the inauguration of a hospital, build community for rural migrants in unfamiliar cities, and be incorporated into Christian church ceremonies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hanna1973&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Nandini Ghosal.jpg|thumb|left|An Indian classical dancer]]

===Asia===

All [[Classical Indian dance|Indian classical dances]] are to varying degrees rooted in the ''[[Natyashastra]]'' and therefore share common features: for example, the ''mudra''s (hand positions), some body positions, and the inclusion of dramatic or expressive acting or [[abhinaya]]. Indian classical music provides accompaniment and dancers of nearly all the styles wear bells around their ankles to counterpoint and complement the percussion.

There are now many regional varieties of [[Indian classical dance]]. Dances like ''&quot;Odra Magadhi&quot;'', which after decades long debate, has been traced to present day Mithila, [[Odisha]] region's dance form of [[Odissi]] (Orissi), indicate influence of dances in cultural interactions between different regions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.exoticindiaart.com/article/dance Exoticindiaart.com], Dance: The Living Spirit of Indian Arts, by Prof. P.C. Jain and Dr. Daljeet.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Punjab region|Punjab]] area overlapping India and [[Pakistan]] is the place of origin of [[Bhangra (dance)|Bhangra]]. It is widely known both as a style of music and a dance. It is mostly related to ancient harvest celebrations, love, patriotism or social issues. Its music is coordinated by a musical instrument called the 'Dhol'. Bhangra is not just music but a dance, a celebration of the harvest where people beat the dhol (drum), sing Boliyaan (lyrics) and dance. It developed further with the Vaisakhi festival of the [[Sikh]]s.

The [[dances of Sri Lanka]] include the devil dances (''yakun natima''), a carefully crafted ritual reaching far back into Sri Lanka's pre-Buddhist past that combines ancient &quot;[[Ayurvedic]]&quot; concepts of disease causation with [[psychological manipulation]] and combines many aspects including Sinhalese cosmology. Their influence can be seen on the [[classical dances of Sri Lanka]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lankalibrary.com/rit/yakun%20natuma.htm Lankalibrary.com], &quot;The yakun natima&amp;nbsp;— devil dance ritual of Sri Lanka&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:NutcrackerSnowPas.JPG|thumb|right|Two classical ballet dancers perform a sequence of ''[[The Nutcracker]]'', one of the best known works of classical dance]]
[[File:Dance-At-Bougival.jpg|thumb|''[[Dance at Bougival]]'' by [[Pierre-Auguste Renoir]] (1883)]]
The [[Middle Eastern dance|dances of the Middle East]] are usually the traditional forms of [[circle dance|circle dancing]] which are modernized to an extent. They would include [[dabke]], [[tamzara]], [[Assyrian folk dance]], [[Kurdish dance]], [[Armenian dance]] and [[Turkish dance]], among others.&lt;ref name=&quot;Badley 2000. pp 391-395&quot;&gt;Badley, Bill and Zein al Jundi. &quot;Europe Meets Asia&quot;. 2000. In Broughton, Simon and Ellingham, Mark with McConnachie, James and Duane, Orla (Ed.), World Music, Vol. 1: Africa, Europe and the Middle East, pp. 391–395. Rough Guides Ltd, Penguin Books.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Recep Albayrak Hacaloğlu. Azeri Türkçesi dil kilavuzu. Hacaloğlu, 1992; p. 272.&lt;/ref&gt; All these forms of dances would usually involve participants engaging each other by holding hands or arms (depending on the style of the dance). They would make rhythmic moves with their legs and shoulders as they curve around the dance floor. The head of the dance would generally hold a [[Walking stick|cane]] or [[handkerchief]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Badley 2000. pp 391-395&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Subhi Anwar Rashid, Mesopotamien, Abb 137&lt;/ref&gt;

===Europe and North America===
{{Main|Concert dance}}
[[Folk dance]]s vary across Europe and may date back hundreds or thousands of years, but many have features in common such as [[group dance|group participation]] led by a [[Caller (dancing)|caller]], hand-holding or arm-linking between participants, and fixed musical forms known as caroles.&lt;ref name=&quot;lee&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Ballet in Western Culture: A History of Its Origins and Evolution|pages=10–11|year=2002|isbn=978-0-415-94257-7|author=Carol Lee}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some, such as the [[maypole]] dance are common to many nations, while others such as the [[céilidh]] and the [[polka]] are deeply-rooted in a single culture. Some European folk dances such as the [[square dance]] were brought to the [[New World]] and subsequently became part of American culture.

[[Ballet]] developed first in Italy and then in France from lavish court spectacles that combined music, drama, poetry, song, costumes and dance. Members of the court nobility took part as performers. During the reign of [[Louis XIV]], himself a dancer, dance became more codified. Professional dancers began to take the place of court amateurs, and ballet masters were licensed by the French government. The first ballet dance academy was the Académie Royale de Danse (Royal Dance Academy), opened in Paris in 1661. Shortly thereafter, the first institutionalized ballet troupe, associated with the Academy, was formed; this troupe began as an all-male ensemble but by 1681 opened to include women as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;lecomte&quot;/&gt;

[[20th century concert dance]] brought an explosion of innovation in dance style characterized by an exploration of freer technique. Early pioneers of what became known as [[modern dance]] include [[Loie Fuller]], [[Isadora Duncan]], [[Mary Wigman]] and [[Ruth St. Denis]]. The relationship of music to dance serves as the basis for [[Eurhythmics]], devised by [[Emile Jaques-Dalcroze]], which was influential to the development of Modern dance and modern ballet through artists such as [[Marie Rambert]]. [[Eurythmy]], developed by [[Rudolf Steiner]] and [[Marie Steiner-von Sivers]], combines formal elements reminiscent of traditional dance with the new freer style, and introduced a complex new vocabulary to dance. In the 1920s, important founders of the new style such as [[Martha Graham]] and [[Doris Humphrey]] began their work. Since this time, a wide variety of dance styles have been developed; see [[Modern dance]].

[[African American dance]] developed in everyday spaces, rather than in dance studios, schools or companies. [[Tap dance]], [[disco]], [[jazz dance]], [[swing dance]], [[hip hop dance]], the [[lindy hop]] with its relationship to [[rock and roll|rock and roll music]] and [[rock and roll (dance)|rock and roll dance]] have had a global influence. Dance styles fusing classical ballet technique with African-American dance have also appeared in the 21st century, including [[Hiplet (dance style)|Hiplet]].&lt;ref name=kourlas&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2016/09/04/arts/dance/hiplet-an-implausible-hybrid-plants-itself-on-pointe.html|title=Hiplet: An Implausible Hybrid Plants Itself on Pointe|last=Kourlas|first=Gia|date=2016-09-02|newspaper=The New York Times|issn=0362-4331|access-date=2016-12-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Latin America===
[[File:HK TST night 柏麗購物大道 Park Lane Shopper's Boulevard 巴西 Brasil 森巴舞娘 Samba female dancers Nov-2010 02.JPG|thumb|left|upright=1.1| [[samba school|Street samba]] dancers perform in carnival parades and contests]]
Dance is central to [[Latin America]]n social life and culture. Brazilian [[Samba (Brazilian dance)|Samba]], Argentinian [[tango]], and Cuban [[salsa (dance)|salsa]] are internationally popular partner dances, and other national dances—[[merengue (dance)|merengue]], [[cueca]], [[plena]], [[jarabe]], [[joropo]], [[marinera]], [[cumbia]], [[Bachata (dance)|bachata]] and others—are important components of their respective countries' cultures.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chasteen2004&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=John Charles Chasteen|title=National Rhythms, African Roots: The Deep History of Latin American Popular Dance|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=yBvvvrydCNwC&amp;pg=PR8|date=1 January 2004|publisher=UNM Press|isbn=978-0-8263-2941-7|pages=8–14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Traditional [[Carnival]] festivals incorporate these and other dances in enormous celebrations.&lt;ref name=&quot;MusmonHanley2010&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Margaret Musmon|author2=Elizabeth A. Hanley|author3=Jacques D'Amboise|title=Latin and Caribbean Dance|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qIZq7jgqXE8C|year=2010|publisher=Infobase Publishing|isbn=978-1-60413-481-0|pages=20–23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dance has played an important role in forging a collective identity among the many cultural and ethnic groups of [[Latin America]].&lt;ref name=&quot;DelgadoMuñoz1997&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Celeste Fraser Delgado|author2=José Esteban Muñoz|title=Everynight Life: Culture and Dance in Latin/o America|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gefjk07Y9kEC&amp;pg=PA3|year=1997|publisher=Duke University Press|isbn=978-0-8223-1919-1|pages=9–41}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dance served to unite the many African, European, and indigenous peoples of the region.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chasteen2004&quot;/&gt; Certain dance genres, such as [[capoeira]], and body movements, especially the characteristic ''[[quebrada (dance)|quebrada]]s'' or [[pelvis]] swings, have been variously banned and celebrated throughout Latin American history.&lt;ref name=&quot;DelgadoMuñoz1997&quot;/&gt;{{clear}}

===United States===
[[Hip hop]] originated in New York, specifically in the area known as the Bronx. It was created for those who struggled in society and didn't seem to have a voice in the community that surrounded them because of their lack of wealth. It helped those in the same situation come together and speak about difficult topics by using movement and feeling.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://thoughteconomics.com/the-role-of-hip-hop-in-culture/|title=The Role of Hip Hop in Culture |date=2015-11-03|work=Thought Economics|access-date=2017-12-12|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Dance education==

Dance studies are offered through the [[The Arts|arts]] and [[humanities]] programs of many higher education institutions. Some universities offer [[Bachelor of Arts]] and higher [[academic degree]]s in Dance. A dance study curriculum may encompass a diverse range of courses and topics, including dance practice and performance, choreography, [[ethnochoreology]], [[kinesiology]], [[dance notation]], and [[dance therapy]].

[[File:Gibney Dance.jpg|thumb|right|upright=1.25|A dancer practices in a [[dance studio]], the primary setting for training in classical dance and many other styles]]

==Occupations==
{{Main|List of dance occupations}}

===Professional dancers===
Professional dancers are usually employed on contract or for particular performances or productions. The professional life of a dancer is generally one of constantly changing work situations, strong competitive pressure and low pay. Consequently, professional dancers often must supplement their incomes to achieve financial stability. In the U.S. many professional dancers belong to unions (such as the [[American Guild of Musical Artists]], [[Screen Actors Guild]] and [[Actors' Equity Association]]) that establish working conditions and minimum salaries for their members. Professional dancers must possess large amounts of athleticism. To lead a successful career, it is advantageous to be versatile in many styles of dance, have a strong technical background and to utilize other forms of physical training to remain fit and healthy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Sagolla|first=Lisa|date=April 24, 2008|title=Untitled|url=http://web.a.ebscohost.com/ehost/detail/detail?sid=fa35d8ae-239b-4764-b82f-f58a07a15475%40sessionmgr4006&amp;vid=11&amp;hid=4104&amp;bdata=JnNpdGU9ZWhvc3QtbGl2ZQ%3d%3d#AN=32038206&amp;db=ibh|journal=International Bibliography of Theatre &amp; Dance with Full Text|volume= 15| issue = 17 |page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Dance teachers===
Dance teachers typically focus on teaching dance performance, or coaching competitive dancers, or both. They typically have performance experience in the types of dance they teach or coach. For example, [[dancesport]] teachers and coaches are often tournament dancers or former dancesport performers. Dance teachers may be self-employed, or employed by [[dance school]]s or general education institutions with dance programs. Some work for university programs or other schools that are associated with professional classical dance (e.g., ballet) or modern dance companies. Others are employed by smaller, privately owned dance schools that offer dance training and performance coaching for various types of dance.

===Choreographers===
[[Choreography (dance)|Choreographers]] are the ones that design the dancing movements within a dance, they are often university trained and are typically employed for particular projects or, more rarely may work on contract as the resident choreographer for a specific dance company.

==Competitions==
[[File:MIT 2006 Standard Prechamp Final 2.jpg|thumb|right|upright=1.45|An amateur dancesport competition, featuring the [[Viennese Waltz]]]]

A '''dance competition''' is an organized event in which contestants perform dances before a judge or judges for awards, and in some cases, monetary prizes. There are several major types of dance competitions, distinguished primarily by the style or styles of dances performed. Major types of dance competitions include:
* '''[[Competitive dance]]''', in which a variety of theater dance styles, such as [[acro dance|acro]], [[ballet]], [[jazz dance|jazz]], [[hip-hop]], [[lyrical dance|lyrical]], and [[tap dance|tap]], are permitted.
* '''Open''' competitions, that permit a wide variety of dance styles. An example of this is the TV program ''[[So You Think You Can Dance]]''.
* '''[[Dancesport]]''', which is focused exclusively on [[ballroom dance|ballroom]] and [[latin dance]]. Examples of this are TV programs ''[[Dancing with the Stars]]'' and ''[[Strictly Come Dancing]]''.
* '''Single-style''' competitions, such as; [[Scottish highland dance|highland dance]], [[dance squad|dance team]], and [[Irish dance]], that only permit a single dance style.

In addition, there are numerous dance competitions shows [[Dance on television|presented on television]] and other mass media.
{{clear}}

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery mode=&quot;packed-hover&quot; heights=&quot;182px&quot;&gt;
File:Irish dancers in team costume, Davis Academy, USA.jpg|'''Folk dance''' – a trio of [[Irish Stepdance]]rs performing in competition
File:TÜRKA Vanemuise suures majas -- tants Kodukotus.JPG|[[Folk dance]] in [[Estonia]]
File:NwFusionAngelaLeap.jpg|A contemporary dancer performs a stag split leap
File:NWFusion7.jpg|'''[[Dance partnering]]''' – a male dancer assists a female dancer in performing an [[arabesque (ballet position)|arabesque]], as part of a classical [[pas de deux]]
File:FrontAerial.gif|'''Acrobatic dance''' – an [[acro dance]]r performs a [[front aerial]]
File:ToeRise.jpg|A dancer performs a &quot;toe rise&quot;, in which she rises from a kneeling position to a standing position on the tops of her feet
File:Jitterbug Wolcott FSA.jpg|'''Social dance''' – dancers at a [[juke joint]] dance the [[Jitterbug]], an early 20th century dance that would go on to influence [[Swing dance|swing]], [[jive (dance)|jive]], and [[jazz dance]]
File:Tanzturnier_28.JPG|Latin Ballroom ballroom dancers perform the [[Tango]]
File:Bootsa.jpg|[[Gumboot dance]] evolved from the stomping signals used as coded communication between labourers in South African mines
File:Harlekin Columbine Tivoli Denmark.jpg|[[Harlequin]] and [[Columbina]] from the mime theater in [[Copenhagen, Denmark]]
File:Popping dancer.gif|A [[hip-hop dance]]r demonstrates [[popping (dance)|popping]]
File:Striptease pole dancing in Belovskaya, Belgorodskaya Oblast, Russia.jpg|'''[[Erotic dance]]''' – a [[pole dancer]] performs a routine
File:Spark Fire Dance in Art on Ice 2014-3.jpg|'''Prop dance''' – a [[fire dance]]r performance
File:Imdt01.jpg|'''Modern dance''' – a female dancer performs a [[splits|leg split]] while balanced on the back of her partner
File:Belogolovtsev Abderahman.jpg|'''Stage dance''' – a professional dancer at the [[Bolshoi Theatre]]
File:La bailaora Josefa Vargas (1840).jpg|A nineteenth century artist's representation of a Flamenco dancer
File:Պար_Գառնում.jpg|'''Ritual dance''' – Armenian folk dancers celebrate a [[neo-pagan]] new year
File:Samba Atlason Jakobsdottir 0509.JPG|A latin ballroom couple perform a [[Samba (ballroom dance)|Samba]] routine at a dancesport event
File:Polonezkoy_08859_nevit.jpg|'''Folk dance''' – some dance traditions travel with immigrant communities, as with this festival dance performed by a Polish community in Turkey
File:Fuori asse alla seconda.jpg|A ballet dancer performs a standing [[Splits|side split]]
File:Breakdancer - Faneuil Hall cropped.jpg|'''Street dance''' – a [[Breakdance]]r performs a handstand trick
File:Odissi Performance DS.jpg|[[Indian classical dance]]r
File:Ballet Class 3 (237261875).jpeg|Ballet class of young girls wearing leotards and skirts in 2017
File:Tari Kebagh, 2017.jpg|''Kebagh'' dance from [[Pagar Alam]], [[Indonesia]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
* [[Art]]
* [[Outline of performing arts]]
* [[Outline of dance]]
* [[Index of dance articles]]
* [[List of dance awards]]
*[[Human body]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=nb}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Abra, Allison. &quot;Going to the palais: a social and cultural history of dancing and dance halls in Britain, 1918–1960.&quot; ''Contemporary British History'' (Sep 2016) 30#3 pp.&amp;nbsp;432–433.
* Blogg, Martin. ''Dance and the Christian Faith: A Form of Knowing'', The Lutterworth Press (2011), {{ISBN|978-0-7188-9249-4}}
* Carter, A. (1998) ''The Routledge Dance Studies Reader''. Routledge. {{ISBN|0-415-16447-8}}.
* Cohen, S, J. (1992) ''Dance As a Theatre Art: Source Readings in Dance History from 1581 to the Present''. Princeton Book Co. {{ISBN|0-87127-173-7}}.
* Daly, A. (2002) ''Critical Gestures: Writings on Dance and Culture''. [[Wesleyan University Press]]. {{ISBN|0-8195-6566-0}}.
* Miller, James, L. (1986) ''Measures of Wisdom: The Cosmic Dance in Classical and Christian Antiquity'', [[University of Toronto Press]]. {{ISBN|0-8020-2553-6}}.

==External links==
&lt;!-- links added here should only relate to dance in general rather than specific dances or styles --&gt;
{{Sister project links|commons=Dance|s=Portal:Dance}}
* {{Cite EB1911|wstitle=Dance}}
* [http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/17289 Historic illustrations of dancing from 3300 BC to 1911 AD] from [[Project Gutenberg]]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060820155540/http://www.dancemuseum.org/ United States National Museum of Dance and Hall of Fame]
&lt;!--spacing--&gt;

{{Dance|state=collapsed}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Dance| ]]
[[Category:Entertainment occupations]]
[[Category:Theatrical occupations]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]</text>
      <sha1>62yva8sq1oy5ie0zrm36t0dgf35uc9h</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
