  <page>
    <title>Charcot–Marie–Tooth disease</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7845</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941657902</id>
      <parentid>940341682</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-19T22:47:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Timtempleton</username>
        <id>11385089</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */ added CMT Research Foundation to external links section</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Neuromuscular disease that is characterized by a slowly progressive degeneration of the muscles of the foot, lower leg, hand and forearm}}
{{For|other diseases|Charcot disease (disambiguation)}}
{{redirect|CMT2|the aerodrome with this LID|Mont-Tremblant (Lac Maskinongé) Water Aerodrome}}
{{Infobox medical condition (new)
| pronounce       = {{IPA-fr|ʃaʁko maʁi tuːθ|}}
| image           = Charcot-marie-tooth foot.jpg
| caption         = The foot of a person with Charcot–Marie–Tooth disease: The lack of muscle, a [[pes cavus|high arch]], and [[hammer toe|claw toes]] are signs of this genetic disease.
| synonyms        = Charcot–Marie–Tooth neuropathy, peroneal muscular atrophy
| field           = [[Neurology]]
| symptoms        =
| complications   =
| onset           =
| duration        =
| types           =
| causes          =
| risks           =
| diagnosis       =
| differential    =
| prevention      =
| treatment       =
| medication      =
| prognosis       =
| frequency       =
| deaths          =
}}
'''Charcot–Marie–Tooth disease''' ('''CMT''') is one of the [[hereditary motor and sensory neuropathies]] of the [[peripheral nervous system]] characterized by progressive loss of [[muscle tissue]] and touch sensation across various parts of the body. Currently incurable, this disease is the most commonly inherited [[neurological disorder]], and affects about one in 2,500 people.&lt;ref name=&quot;Krajewski&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Medscape&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://emedicine.medscape.com/article/315260-overview |title=Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation for Charcot–Marie–Tooth Disease: Background, Pathophysiology, Epidemiology |website=Emedicine.medscape.com |date= |accessdate=2016-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; CMT was previously classified as a subtype of [[muscular dystrophy]].&lt;ref name=Krajewski&gt;{{cite journal |pages=1516–27 |doi=10.1093/brain/123.7.1516 |title=Neurological dysfunction and axonal degeneration in Charcot–Marie–Tooth disease type 1A |year=2000 |last1=Krajewski |first1=K. M. |journal=Brain |volume=123 |issue=7 |pmid=10869062}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Signs and symptoms==
Symptoms of CMT usually begin in early childhood or early adulthood, but can begin later. Some people do not experience symptoms until their early 30s or 40s. Usually, the initial symptom is [[foot drop]] early in the course of the disease. This can also cause [[hammer toe]], where the toes are always curled. Wasting of muscle tissue of the lower parts of the legs may give rise to a &quot;stork leg&quot; or &quot;inverted champagne bottle&quot; appearance. Weakness in the hands and forearms occurs in many people as the disease progresses.

Loss of touch sensation in the feet, ankles, and legs, as well as in the hands, wrists, and arms occurs with various types of the disease. Early- and late-onset forms occur with 'on and off' painful spasmodic muscular contractions that can be disabling when the disease activates.  High-arched feet ([[pes cavus]]) or flat-arched feet ([[pes planus]]) are classically associated with the disorder.&lt;ref name=&quot;LeBhushan2014&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Le|first1=Tao|last2=Bhushan|first2=Vikas|title=First Aid for the USMLE Step 1 2014|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3yJ-mgEACAAJ|accessdate=4 September 2014|date=6 January 2014|publisher=McGraw-Hill Education|isbn=9780071831420|quote=Typically autosomal dominant inheritance pattern associated with scoliosis and foot deformities (high or flat arches).}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sensory and proprioceptive nerves in the hands and feet are often damaged, while unmyelinated pain nerves are left intact. Overuse of an affected hand or limb can activate symptoms including numbness, spasm, and painful cramping.

Symptoms and progression of the disease can vary. Involuntary [[bruxism|grinding of teeth]] and squinting are prevalent, and often go unnoticed by the person affected. Breathing can be affected in some, as can hearing, vision, and neck and shoulder muscles. [[Scoliosis]] is common, causing hunching and loss of height. [[Acetabulum|Hip sockets]] can be malformed. Gastrointestinal problems can be part of CMT,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.lindacrabtree.com/cmt/basics/basics_article1.html |title=CMT News |website=Lindacrabtree.com |date= |accessdate=2016-11-13 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160805074627/http://www.lindacrabtree.com/cmt/basics/basics_article1.html |archive-date=2016-08-05 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Soykan I, McCallum RW |title=Gastrointestinal involvement in neurologic disorders: Stiff-man and Charcot–Marie–Tooth syndromes |journal=The American Journal of the Medical Sciences |volume=313 |issue=1 |pages=70–73 |date=January 1997 |pmid=9001170 |doi=10.1097/00000441-199701000-00012}}&lt;/ref&gt; as can difficulty chewing, swallowing, and speaking (due to atrophy of [[vocal cords]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ninds.nih.gov/disorders/charcot_marie_tooth/detail_charcot_marie_tooth.htm#265923092 |title=Charcot-Marie-Tooth Disease Fact Sheet |website=Ninds.nih.gov |date=2016-01-14 |accessdate=2016-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[tremor]] can develop as muscles waste. [[Pregnancy]] has been known to exacerbate CMT, as well as severe emotional stress. Patients with CMT must avoid periods of prolonged immobility such as when recovering from a secondary injury, as prolonged periods of limited mobility can drastically accelerate symptoms of CMT.&lt;ref name=cmtausaTreat&gt;{{cite press release |title=Treatment and Management of CMT |publisher=Charcot-Marie-Tooth Association |date=October 6, 2010 |url=http://www.cmtausa.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=74&amp;catid=10&amp;Itemid=51 |accessdate=August 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Pain]] due to postural changes, skeletal deformations, muscle fatigue, and cramping is fairly common in people with CMT. It can be mitigated or treated by physical therapies, surgeries, and corrective or assistive devices. [[Analgesic]] medications may also be needed if other therapies do not provide relief from pain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://patient.info/doctor/charcot-marie-tooth-disease|title=Charcot-Marie-Tooth Syndrome. CMT information. |work=Patient}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Neuropathic pain]] is often a symptom of CMT, though, like other symptoms of CMT, its presence and severity vary from case to case. For some people, pain can be significant to severe and interfere with daily life activities. However, pain is not experienced by all people with CMT. When neuropathic pain is present as a symptom of CMT, it is comparable to that seen in other [[peripheral neuropathies]], as well as [[postherpetic neuralgia]] and [[complex regional pain syndrome]], among other diseases.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carter&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |pages=1560–64 |doi=10.1016/S0003-9993(98)90421-X |title=Neuropathic pain in Charcot-Marie-tooth disease |year=1998 |journal=Archives of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation |volume=79 |issue=12 |pmid=9862301 |first1=Gregory T. |last1=Carter |first2=Mark P. |last2=Jensen |first3=Bradley S. |last3=Galer |first4=George H. |last4=Kraft |first5=Linda D. |last5=Crabtree |first6=Ruth M. |last6=Beardsley |first7=Richard T. |last7=Abresch |first8=Thomas D. |last8=Bird}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Causes==
[[File:Human male karyotpe high resolution - Chromosome 17 cropped.png|thumb|[[Chromosome 17]]]]
Charcot–Marie–Tooth disease is caused by genetic [[mutation]]s that cause defects in neuronal proteins. Nerve signals are conducted by an [[axon]] with a [[myelin]] sheath wrapped around it. Most mutations in CMT affect the myelin sheath, but some affect the axon.

===Classification===
{{further|Charcot–Marie–Tooth disease classifications}}
CMT is a [[heterogeneous disease]] and the mutations linked to it may occur in a number of different genes.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid26527893&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal | doi=10.2147/TACG.S69969| pmid=26527893| pmc=4621202| title=The genetics of Charcot–Marie–Tooth disease: Current trends and future implications for diagnosis and management| journal=The Application of Clinical Genetics| volume=8| pages=235–43| year=2015| last1=Arnold| first1=W. David| last2=Isfort| first2=Michael| last3=Roggenbuck| first3=Jennifer| last4=Hoyle| first4=J. Chad}}&lt;/ref&gt; Based on the affected gene, CMT is categorized into several types and subtypes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lupski2010&quot; /&gt;

====Chromosome 17====

The most common cause of CMT (70–80% of the cases) is the duplication of a large region on the short arm of [[chromosome 17]] that includes the gene ''[[PMP22]]''. 

Some mutations affect the gene ''[[MFN2]]'', on [[chromosome 1]], which codes for a mitochondrial protein. Mutated ''MFN2'' causes the mitochondria to form large clusters, or clots, which are unable to travel down the axon towards the [[synapses]]. This prevents the synapses from functioning.&lt;ref name=&quot;Baloh&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |pages=422–30 |doi=10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4798-06.2007 |title=Altered Axonal Mitochondrial Transport in the Pathogenesis of Charcot-Marie-Tooth Disease from Mitofusin 2 Mutations |year=2007 |last1=Baloh |first1=R. H. |last2=Schmidt |first2=R. E. |last3=Pestronk |first3=A. |last4=Milbrandt |first4=J. |journal=Journal of Neuroscience |volume=27 |issue=2 |pmid=17215403|pmc=6672077 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====X linked CMT and Schwann cells====

CMT can also be produced by X-linked mutations, and is named X-linked CMT (CMTX). In CMTX, mutated [[connexon]]s create non-functional gap junctions that interrupt molecular exchange and signal transport.&lt;ref name=Berger/&gt;&lt;ref name=JournalOfNeuroscience&gt;{{cite journal|title=The Role of Gap Junctions in Charcot-Marie-Tooth Disease|date=December 2011 |first1=Kleopas |last1=Kleopa |first2=James R. |last2=Lupski |journal=Journal of Neuroscience |volume=31 |issue=49 |pages=17753–17760 |doi=10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4824-11.2011|pmid=22159091 |pmc=6634164 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=EuropeanJournalOfGenetics&gt;{{cite journal|title=Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease|date=April 2009 |first1=Kinga |last1=Szigeti |first2=James R. |last2=Lupski |journal=European Journal of Human Genetics |pages=703–710 |volume=17 |issue=6 |doi=10.1038/ejhg.2009.31|pmid=19277060 |pmc=2947101 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The mutation can appear in [[GJB1]] coding for [[connexin 32]], a gap junction protein expressed in Schwann cells. Because this protein is also present in [[oligodendrocytes]], demyelination can appear in the CNS.&lt;ref&gt;Georgios Koutsi et al. X linked Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease and multiple sclerosis: emerging evidence for an association, Neurogenetics, doi: https://doi.org/10.1136/jnnp-2018-319014&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Schwann cell]]s create the myelin sheath, by wrapping its plasma membrane around the axon.&lt;ref name=Berger&gt;{{cite journal |pages=1–15 |doi= 10.1007/s10048-002-0130-z |title=Molecular cell biology of Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease |year=2002 |last1=Berger |first1=Philipp |last2=Young |first2=Peter |last3=Suter |first3=Ueli |journal=Neurogenetics |volume=4 |pmid=12030326 |issue=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Neurons, Schwann cells, and [[fibroblast]]s work together to create a functional nerve. Schwann cells and neurons exchange molecular signals by [[gap junction]]s that regulate survival and differentiation. 

Demyelinating Schwann cells causes abnormal axon structure and function. They may cause axon degeneration, or they may simply cause axons to malfunction.&lt;ref name=Krajewski/&gt;

The myelin sheath allows nerve cells to conduct signals faster. When the myelin sheath is damaged, nerve signals are slower, and this can be measured by a common neurological test, [[electromyography]]. When the axon is damaged, though, this results in a reduced compound muscle [[action potential]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Yiu |first=Eppie M. |last2=Burns |first2=Joshua |last3=Ryan |first3=Monique M. |last4=Ouvrier |first4=Robert A. |year=2008 |title=Neurophysiologic abnormalities in children with Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 1A |journal=Journal of the Peripheral Nervous System |volume=13 |issue=3 |pages=236–41 |doi=10.1111/j.1529-8027.2008.00182.x |pmid=18844790}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Diagnosis==
CMT can be diagnosed through three different forms of tests: measurement of the speed of nerve impulses ([[nerve conduction studies]]), a [[biopsy]] of the nerve, and DNA testing. DNA testing can give a definitive diagnosis, but not all the [[genetic marker]]s for CMT are known.  CMT is first most noticed when someone develops lower leg weakness, such as foot drop, or foot deformities, including hammertoes and high arches, but signs alone do not lead to diagnosis.  Patients must be referred to a physician specialising in neurology or rehabilitation medicine. To see signs of muscle weakness, the neurologist may ask patients to walk on their heels or to move part of their leg against an opposing force.  To identify sensory loss, the neurologist tests for deep-tendon reflexes, such as the knee jerk, which are reduced or absent in CMT. The doctor may also ask the patients family history since CMT is hereditary.  The lack of family history does not rule out CMT, but is helpful to rule out other causes of neuropathy, such as diabetes or exposure to certain chemicals or drugs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.charcot-marie-tooth.org/about_cmt/diagnosis.php |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2010-11-03 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100227100912/http://www.charcot-marie-tooth.org/about_cmt/diagnosis.php |archivedate=2010-02-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010, CMT was one of the first diseases where the genetic cause of a particular patient's disease was precisely determined by sequencing the whole genome of an affected individual.  This was done by the scientists employed by the Charcot Marie Tooth Association (CMTA)&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT2010&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2010/03/11/health/research/11gene.html |title=Disease Cause Is Pinpointed With Genome |first=Nicholas |last=Wade |newspaper=New York Times |date=2010-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lupski2010&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |pages=1181–91 |doi=10.1056/NEJMoa0908094 |title=Whole-Genome Sequencing in a Patient with Charcot–Marie–Tooth Neuropathy |year=2010 |last1=Lupski |first1=James R. |last2=Reid |first2=Jeffrey G. |last3=Gonzaga-Jauregui |first3=Claudia |last4=Rio Deiros |first4=David |last5=Chen |first5=David C.Y. |last6=Nazareth |first6=Lynne |last7=Bainbridge |first7=Matthew |last8=Dinh |first8=Huyen |last9=Jing |first9=Chyn |last10=Wheeler |first10=David A. |last11=McGuire |first11=Amy L. |last12=Zhang |first12=Feng |last13=Stankiewicz |first13=Pawel |last14=Halperin |first14=John J. |last15=Yang |first15=Chengyong |last16=Gehman |first16=Curtis |last17=Guo |first17=Danwei |last18=Irikat |first18=Rola K. |last19=Tom |first19=Warren |last20=Fantin |first20=Nick J. |last21=Muzny |first21=Donna M. |last22=Gibbs |first22=Richard A. |journal=New England Journal of Medicine |volume=362 |issue=13 |pmid=20220177|display-authors=8 |pmc=4036802}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two mutations were identified in a gene, ''SH3TC2'', known to cause CMT.  Researchers then compared the affected patient's genome to the genomes of the patient's mother, father, and seven siblings with and without the disease. The mother and father each had one normal and one mutant copy of this gene, and had mild or no symptoms. The offspring who inherited two mutant genes presented fully with the disease.

===Histology===
[[File:Denervation atrophy - atp94 - intermed mag.jpg|thumb|[[Denervation]] [[atrophy]] of type II [[muscle fibers]]]]
The constant cycle of [[demyelination]] and [[remyelination]], which occurs in CMT, can lead to the formation of layers of [[myelin]] around some nerves, termed an &quot;onion bulb&quot;.  These are also seen in [[chronic inflammatory demyelinating polyneuropathy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Midroni|first1=Gyl|last2=Bilbao|first2=Juan M.|last3=with the technical assistance of Cohen|first3=Sandra M.|title=Biopsy diagnosis of peripheral neuropathy|date=1995|publisher=Butterworth-Heinemann|location=Boston|isbn=9780750695527|pages=75–103}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Muscles show fiber type grouping, a similarly nonspecific finding that indicates a cycle of [[denervation]]/[[reinnervation]].  Normally, type I and type II [[muscle fibers]] show a checkerboard-like random distribution.  However, when reinnervation occurs, the group of fibers associated with one nerve are of the same type.  The standard for indicating fiber type is histoenzymatic adenosine triphosphatase (ATPase at pH 9.4).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Dubowitz|first1=Victor|last2=Sewry|first2=Caroline A.|last3=toxic|first3=Anders Oldfors; with contribution on|last4=Lane|first4=drug-induced myopathies by Russell|title=Muscle biopsy : a practical approach|date=2013|publisher=Saunders/Elsevier|location=Philadelphia|isbn=978-0702043406|edition=Fourth}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Management==
[[File:Ankle Foot Orthosis leg brace worn on the left foot with ankle hinge.jpg|thumb|[[Ankle-foot orthosis]]]]
Often, the most important goal for patients with CMT is to maintain movement, muscle strength, and flexibility. Therefore, an interprofessional team approach with occupational therapy, physical therapy, orthotist, podiatrist, and or orthopedic surgeon is recommended.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Charcot-Marie-Tooth Disease Fact Sheet {{!}} National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke|url=https://www.ninds.nih.gov/Disorders/Patient-Caregiver-Education/Fact-Sheets/Charcot-Marie-Tooth-Disease-Fact-Sheet|website=www.ninds.nih.gov|accessdate=24 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; PT typically focuses on muscle-strength training, muscle stretching, and aerobic exercise, while OT can provide education on energy conservation strategies and activities of daily living. Physical therapy should be involved in designing an exercise program that fits a person's personal strengths and flexibility. Bracing can also be used to correct problems caused by CMT. An orthotist may address gait abnormalities by prescribing the use of [[ankle-foot orthoses]]. These orthoses help control foot drop and ankle instability and often provide a better sense of balance for patients. Appropriate footwear is also very important for people with CMT, but they often have difficulty finding well-fitting shoes because of their high arched feet and hammer toes. Due to the lack of good sensory reception in the feet, CMT patients may also need to see a podiatrist for assistance in trimming nails or removing calluses that develop on the pads of the feet. Lastly, patients can also decide to have surgery performed by a podiatrist or an orthopedic surgeon. Surgery may help to stabilize the patients' feet or correct progressive problems. These procedures include straightening and pinning the toes, lowering the arch, and sometimes, fusing the ankle joint to provide stability.&lt;ref name=cmtausaTreat/&gt; CMT patients must take extra care to avoid falling as fractures take longer to heal in someone with an underlying disease process. Additionally, the resulting inactivity may cause the CMT to worsen.&lt;ref name=cmtausaTreat/&gt; The Charcot–Marie–Tooth Association classifies the [[chemotherapy]] drug [[vincristine]] as a &quot;definite high risk&quot; and states, &quot;vincristine has been proven hazardous and should be avoided by all CMT patients, including those with no symptoms.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.charcot-marie-tooth.org/med_alert.php |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2007-08-21 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070702234917/http://www.charcot-marie-tooth.org/med_alert.php |archivedate=2007-07-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Several corrective surgical procedures  can be done to improve the physical condition of the affected individuals.&lt;ref&gt;Anand N, [[David B. Levine, M.D.|Levine, DB]], Burke S, Bansal M. Neuopathic spinal atrophy in Charcot–Marie–Tooth disease. J Bone Joint Surg. 1997; 79-A:1235–39.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Prognosis ==
The severity of symptoms varies widely even for the same type of CMT. Cases of [[twin|monozygotic twins]] with varying levels of disease severity have been reported, showing that identical [[genotype]]s are associated with different levels of severity (see [[penetrance]]). Some patients are able to live a normal life and are almost or entirely asymptomatic.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Pareyson|first=Davide|last2=Marchesi|first2=Chiara|date=2009-07-01|title=Diagnosis, natural history, and management of Charcot–Marie–Tooth disease|journal=The Lancet. Neurology|volume=8|issue=7|pages=654–667|doi=10.1016/S1474-4422(09)70110-3|issn=1474-4422|pmid=19539237}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2007 review stated that, &quot;life expectancy is not known to be altered in the majority of cases.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Aboussouan|first=Loutfi S.|last2=Lewis|first2=Richard A.|last3=Shy|first3=Michael E.|date=2007-02-09|title=Disorders of Pulmonary Function, Sleep, and the Upper Airway in Charcot-Marie-Tooth Disease|journal=Lung|language=en|volume=185|issue=1|pages=1–7|doi=10.1007/s00408-006-0053-9|pmid=17294338|issn=0341-2040}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
{{multiple image
 | width = 100
 | footer = 
 | image1 = Jean-Martin Charcot.jpg
 | alt1 = Jean-Martin Charcot
 | caption1 = [[Jean-Martin Charcot]]
 | image2 = PierreMarie.jpg
 | alt2 = Pierre Marie
 | caption2 = [[Pierre Marie]]
 | image3 = Howard-Henry-Tooth.jpg
 | alt3 = Howard Henry Tooth
 | caption3 = [[Howard Henry Tooth]]
}}
The disease is named after those who classically described it: [[Jean-Martin Charcot]] (1825–1893), his pupil [[Pierre Marie]] (1853–1940)  ({{cite journal |title=Sur une forme particulière d'atrophie musculaire progressive, souvent familiale débutant par les pieds et les jambes et atteignant plus tard les mains |journal=Revue Médicale |volume=6 |pages=97–138 |year=1886 }}), and [[Howard Henry Tooth]] (1856–1925) (&quot;The peroneal type of progressive muscular atrophy&quot;, dissertation, London, 1886).

== See also ==
* [[Palmoplantar keratoderma and spastic paraplegia]]
* [[Hereditary motor and sensory neuropathies]]
* [[Hereditary motor neuropathies]]
* [[Low copy repeats]]
* ''[[Christina's World]]''

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Medical resources
|  DiseasesDB     = 5815
|  DiseasesDB_mult= {{DiseasesDB2|2343}} 
|  ICD10          = {{ICD10|G|60|0|g|60}} 
|  ICD9           = {{ICD9|356.1}} 
|  OMIM           = 311860
|  OMIM_mult      =  {{OMIM2|611566}} {{OMIM2|311070}} {{OMIM2|605588}} {{OMIM2|311850}} (X Type 5)&lt;br /&gt;{{OMIM2|302800}} {{OMIM2|304040}} (X Type 1)
|  MedlinePlus    = 000727
|  GeneReviewsNBK  = NBK1358
|  GeneReviewsName = Charcot-Marie-Tooth Hereditary Neuropathy Overview
|  GeneReviewsNBK2 = NBK1205
|  GeneReviewsName2= Charcot-Marie-Tooth Neuropathy Type 1
|  GeneReviewsNBK3 = NBK1876
|  GeneReviewsName3= Charcot-Marie-Tooth Neuropathy X Type 5
|  GeneReviewsNBK4 = NBK1374
|  GeneReviewsName4= Charcot-Marie-Tooth Neuropathy X Type 1
|  GeneReviewsNBK5 = NBK1242
|  GeneReviewsName5= GARS-Associated Axonal Neuropathy, Charcot-Marie-Tooth Neuropathy Type 2D, Distal Spinal Muscular Atrophy V
| GeneReviewsName6 = 
| GeneReviewsName7 = 
|  ICDO           = 
|  eMedicineSubj  = orthoped
|  eMedicineTopic = 43
|  eMedicine_mult = {{eMedicine2|pmr|29}} 
|  MeshID         = D002607
}}
* {{DMOZ|Health/Conditions_and_Diseases/Neurological_Disorders/Peripheral_Nervous_System/Charcot-Marie-Tooth_Disease/}}
* [https://cmtrf.org/ CMT Research Foundation]

{{PNS diseases of the nervous system}}
{{Inherited disorders of trafficking}}
{{Cytoskeletal defects}}
{{Cell membrane protein disorders}}
{{Deficiencies of intracellular signaling peptides and proteins}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Charcot-Marie-Tooth Disease}}
[[Category:Peripheral nervous system disorders]]
[[Category:Cytoskeletal defects]]
[[Category:Syndromes affecting the nervous system]]</text>
      <sha1>4xmwugw7uzjcpoydk3l8qywnhzejjaq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
