  <page>
    <title>Click consonant</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7816</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943087404</id>
      <parentid>939158386</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T19:15:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>CrystalBlacksmith</username>
        <id>36432512</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>delinting</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Manner of articulation}}
'''Click consonants''', or clicks, are speech sounds that occur as [[consonants]] in many languages of [[Southern Africa]] and in three languages of [[East Africa]]. Examples familiar to English-speakers are the ''[[Tut-tut]]'' (British spelling) or ''Tsk! Tsk!'' (American spelling) used to express disapproval or pity, the ''[[lateral click|tchick!]]'' used to spur on a horse, and the ''[[alveolar click|clip-clop!]]'' sound children make with their tongue to imitate a horse trotting.

Technically, clicks are [[obstruent]]s articulated with two closures (points of contact) in the mouth, one forward and one at the back. The enclosed pocket of air is [[rarefaction|rarefied]] by a sucking action of the tongue (in technical terminology, clicks have a [[Airstream mechanism|lingual ingressive airstream mechanism]]). The forward closure is then released,&lt;ref group=note&gt;This is the case for all clicks that constitute consonants in words. Paralinguistically, however, there are other methods of making clicks: ''under'' the tongue and by releasing the rear occlusion first. See [[#Places of articulation]].&lt;/ref&gt; producing what may be the loudest consonants in the language, but in some languages such as [[Hadza language|Hadza]] and [[Sandawe language|Sandawe]], clicks can be more subtle and may even be mistaken for [[ejective consonant|ejectives]].

==Notation and sound description==
{{IPA non-pulmonic consonants|ejectives=no|implosives=no|audio=yes|class=infobox}}

Click consonants occur at six principal places of articulation. The [[International Phonetic Alphabet (IPA)]] may represent a click by placing the assigned symbol for five of the places of articulation (there is as yet no dedicated symbol for the sixth) adjacent to a symbol for a non-click sound at the rear place of articulation, or the click symbol may be combined with diacritics for voicing, nasalization, etc. The IPA symbols are used in writing most [[Khoisan languages]], but [[Bantu languages]] such as [[Zulu language|Zulu]] typically use [[Latin script|Latin]] {{angbr|c}}, {{angbr|x}} and {{angbr|q}} for dental, lateral and alveolar clicks respectively.
* The easiest clicks for English speakers are the [[dental click]]s written with a single pipe, {{IPA|ǀ}}. They are all sharp (high-pitched) squeaky sounds made by sucking on the front teeth. A simple dental click is used in English to express pity or to shame someone, and sometimes to call an animal, and is written ''tut!'' in British English and ''tsk!'' in American English. In Italian this sound means &quot;no&quot; used as an answer to a direct question, while it is used to call cats when repeated several times.
* Next most familiar to English speakers are the [[lateral click]]s written with a double pipe, {{IPA|ǁ}}. They are also squeaky sounds, though less sharp than {{IPA|ǀ}}, made by sucking on the molars on either side (or both sides) of the mouth. A simple lateral click is made in English to get a horse moving, and is conventionally written ''tchick!''
* Then there are the [[labial click]]s, written with a bull's eye, {{IPA|ʘ}}. These are lip-smacking sounds, but without the pursing of the lips found in a kiss.

The above clicks sound like [[affricate]]s, in that they involve a lot of friction. The other two families are more abrupt sounds that do not have this friction.
* With the [[alveolar click]]s, written with an exclamation mark, {{IPA|ǃ}}, the tip of the tongue is pulled down abruptly and forcefully from the roof of the mouth, sometimes using a lot of jaw motion, and making a hollow ''pop!'' like a cork being pulled from an empty bottle. These sounds can be quite loud.
* Finally, for most languages, the [[palatal click]]s, {{IPA|ǂ}}, are made with a flat tongue, and are sharper popping sounds than the {{IPA|ǃ}} clicks, like sharply snapped fingers.

==Languages with clicks==

=== Southern Africa ===
Clicks occur in all three [[Khoisan languages|Khoisan language families]] of [[southern Africa]], where they may be the most numerous consonants. To a lesser extent they occur in three neighbouring groups of [[Bantu languages]]—which [[Sprachbund|borrowed them]], directly or indirectly, from Khoisan. In the southeast, in eastern [[South Africa]], [[Swaziland]], [[Lesotho]], [[Zimbabwe]] and southern [[Mozambique]], they were adopted from a [[Tuu languages|Tuu language]] or languages by the languages of the Nguni cluster (especially [[Zulu language|Zulu]], [[Xhosa language|Xhosa]] and [[Phuthi language|Phuthi]], but also to a lesser extent [[Swati language|Swazi]] and [[Southern Ndebele language|Ndebele]]), and spread from them in a reduced fashion to the Zulu-based [[pidgin]] [[Fanagalo]], [[Sesotho language|Sesotho]], [[Tsonga language|Tsonga]], [[Ronga language|Ronga]], the Mzimba dialect of [[Tumbuka language|Tumbuka]] and more recently to [[Ndau language|Ndau]] and urban varieties of [[Pedi language|Pedi]], where the spread of clicks continues. The second point of transfer was near the [[Caprivi Strip]] and the [[Okavango River]] where, apparently, the [[Yeyi language]] borrowed the clicks from a [[Khoe languages|West Kalahari Khoe language]]; a separate development led to a smaller click inventory in the neighbouring [[Mbukushu language|Mbukushu]], [[Kwangali language|Kwangali]], [[Gciriku language|Gciriku]], [[Kuhane language|Kuhane]] and [[Fwe language|Fwe]] languages in [[Angola]], [[Namibia]], [[Botswana]] and [[Zambia]].&lt;ref&gt;Derek Nurse &amp; Gérard Philippson (2003) ''The Bantu languages,'' pp 31–32&lt;/ref&gt; These sounds occur not only in borrowed vocabulary, but have spread to native Bantu words as well, in the case of Nguni at least partially due to a type of word taboo called [[hlonipha]]. Some [[creolised]] varieties of Afrikaans, such as [[Oorlams Creole|Oorlams]], retain clicks in Khoekhoe words.

=== East Africa ===
Three languages in [[East Africa]] use clicks: [[Sandawe language|Sandawe]] and [[Hadza language|Hadza]] of [[Tanzania]], and [[Dahalo language|Dahalo]], an endangered South [[Cushitic languages|Cushitic language]] of [[Kenya]] that has clicks in only a few dozen words. It is thought the latter may remain from an episode of [[language shift]].

=== Damin ===
The only non-African language known to have clicks as regular speech sounds is [[Damin]], a ritual code once used by speakers of [[Lardil language|Lardil]] in [[Australia]]. One of the clicks in Damin is actually an [[Egressive sound|egressive]] click, using the tongue to compress the air in the mouth for an outward (egressive) &quot;spurt&quot;.

===Spread of clicks from loanwords===
Once clicks are borrowed into a language as regular speech sounds, they may spread to native words, as has happened due to ''[[hlonipa]]'' word-taboo in the [[Nguni languages]]. In [[Gciriku language|Gciriku]], for example, the European loanword ''tomate'' (tomato) appears as ''cumáte'' with a click ''c'', though it begins with a ''t'' in all neighbouring languages.

=== Marginal usage of clicks ===
Scattered clicks are found in [[ideophone]]s and mimesis in other languages, such as [[Kongo language|Kongo]] {{IPA|/ᵑǃ/}}, [[Mijikenda language|Mijikenda]] {{IPA|/ᵑǀ/}} and Hadza {{IPA|/ʘ̃ʷ/}} (Hadza does not otherwise have labial clicks). Ideophones often use phonemic distinctions not found in normal vocabulary.

English and many other languages may use bare clicks in [[interjection]]s, without the accompaniment of vowels, such as the dental &quot;tsk-tsk&quot; sound used to express disapproval, or the lateral ''tchick'' used with horses. In [[Armenian language|Armenian]], [[Bulgarian language|Bulgarian]], [[Greek language|Greek]], [[Levantine Arabic]], [[Maltese language|Maltese]], [[Persian language|Persian]], [[Romanian language|Romanian]], [[Turkish language|Turkish]], occasionally in [[French language|French]], as well as southern Italian languages such as [[Sicilian language|Sicilian]], in which a bare dental click accompanied by tipping the head upwards signifies &quot;no&quot;. [[Libyan Arabic]] apparently has three such sounds.

Clicks occasionally turn up elsewhere, as in the special [[register (sociolinguistics)|registers]] twins sometimes develop with each other. In [[West Africa]], clicks have been reported allophonically, and similarly in French and German, faint clicks have been recorded in rapid speech where consonants such as {{IPA|/t/}} and {{IPA|/k/}} overlap between words.&lt;ref name=germ&gt;{{cite conference|first=Sussanne|last=Fuchs|first2=Laura|last2=Koenig|first3=Ralf|last3=Winkler|title=Weak clicks in German|format=pdf|conference=Proceedings of the 16th International Congress of Phonetic Sciences|pages=449–452|year=2007|location=Saarbrücken|url=http://www.icphs2007.de/conference/Papers/1678/1678.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Rwanda language|Rwanda]], the sequence {{IPA|/mŋ/}} may be pronounced either with an epenthetic vowel, {{IPA|[mᵊŋ]}}, or with a light bilabial click, {{IPA|[mʘ̃ŋ]}}—often by the same speaker.

Speakers of [[Gan Chinese]] from [[Ningdu]] county, as well as speakers of Mandarin from Beijing and [[Jilin]] and presumably people from other parts of the country, produce flapped nasal clicks in nursery rhymes with varying degrees of competence, in the words for 'goose' and 'duck', both of which begin with {{IPA|/ŋ/}} in Gan and until recently began with {{IPA|/ŋ/}} in Mandarin as well. In Gan, the nursery rhyme is,
:''tʰien i tsʰak ᵑǃ¡o'' 'a goose in the sky'
:''ti ha i tsʰak ᵑǃ¡a'' 'a duck on the ground'
:''ᵑǃ¡o saŋ ᵑǃ¡o tʰan, ᵑǃ¡o pʰau ᵑǃ¡o'' 'a goose lays a goose egg, a goose hatches a goose'
:''ᵑǃ¡a saŋ ᵑǃ¡a tʰan, ᵑǃ¡a pʰau ᵑǃ¡a'' 'a duck lays a duck egg, a duck hatches a duck'
where the {{IPA|/ŋ/}} onsets are all pronounced {{IPA|[ǃ̃¡]}}.&lt;ref&gt;Geoffrey Nathan, 'Clicks in a Chinese Nursery Rhyme', JIPA (2001) 31/2.&lt;/ref&gt;

Occasionally other languages are claimed to have click sounds in general vocabulary. This is usually a misnomer for [[ejective consonant]]s, which are found across much of the world.

=== Position in word ===
For the most part, the Southern African [[Khoisan languages]] only use [[root word|root]]-initial clicks.&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot;&gt;Exceptions occurs in words borrowed from Bantu languages, which may have click in the middle.&lt;/ref&gt; Hadza, Sandawe and several [[Bantu languages]] also allow [[syllable]]-initial clicks within roots. In no language does a click close a syllable or end a word, but then the languages that happen to have clicks have mostly CV syllables and allow at most only a limited set of consonants (such as a nasal or a glottal stop) to close a syllable or end a word, most consonants share the distribution of clicks in these languages.

=== Types of clicks used ===
The Khoesan families (Tuu, Kxʼa and Khoe) all have at least four click types, {{IPA|{ǀ ǁ ǃ ǂ}}} or variants thereof. A few have five, with bilabial {{IPA|{ʘ}}} or retroflex {{IPA|{‼}}}. Hadza and Sandawe have three, {{IPA|{ǀ ǁ ǃ}}}. Yeyi is the only Bantu language with four, {{IPA|{ǀ ǁ ǃ ǂ}}}, while Xhosa and Zulu have three, {{IPA|{ǀ ǁ ǃ}}}, and most Bantu languages with clicks have fewer than that.

==Types of clicks==
Like other consonants, clicks can be described using four parameters: [[place of articulation]], [[manner of articulation]], [[phonation]] (including glottalisation) and [[airstream mechanism]]. As noted above, clicks necessarily involve at least two closures, which in some cases operate partially independently: an anterior articulation traditionally represented by the special click symbol in the IPA—and a posterior articulation traditionally described as oral or [[nasal consonant|nasal]], voiced or voiceless, etc. The literature also describes a contrast between [[velar consonant|velar]] and [[uvular consonant|uvular]] rear articulations for some languages.

However, recent work shows that in languages that make this distinction, all clicks have a uvular, or even pharyngeal, rear closure—and the clicks explicitly described as uvular are in fact clusters/contours of a click plus a pulmonic or ejective component, in which the cluster/contour has two release bursts, the forward (click) and then the rearward (uvular) component. &quot;Velar&quot; clicks in these languages have only a single release burst, that of the forward click release, and the release of the rear articulation isn't separately audible (Miller 2011).

Nonetheless, in most of the literature the stated place of the click is the anterior articulation (called the ''release'' or ''influx),'' whereas the manner is ascribed to the posterior articulation (called the ''accompaniment'' or ''efflux).'' The anterior articulation defines the ''click type'' and is written with the IPA letter for the click (dental {{angbr IPA|ǀ}}, alveolar {{angbr IPA|ǃ}}, etc.), whereas the traditional term 'accompaniment' conflates the categories of manner (nasal, affricated), phonation (voiced, aspirated, breathy voiced, glottalised), as well as any change in the airstream with the release of the posterior articulation (pulmonic, ejective), all of which are transcribed with additional letters or diacritics, as in the ''nasal alveolar click'', {{angbr IPA|ǃŋ}} or {{angbr IPA|ᵑǃ}} or—to take an extreme example—the ''voiced (uvular) ejective alveolar click'', {{angbr IPA|ᶢǃ͡qʼ}}.

The size of click inventories ranges from as few as three (in [[Sesotho phonology#Consonants|Sesotho]]) or four (in [[Dahalo language|Dahalo]]), to dozens in the [[Kxʼa languages|Kxʼa]] and [[Tuu languages|Tuu]] (Northern and Southern Khoisan) languages. [[Taa language|Taa]], the last vibrant language in the latter family, has 45 to 115 click phonemes, depending on analysis (clusters vs. contours), and over 70% of words in the dictionary of this language begin with a click.&lt;ref&gt;L&amp;M 1996, p 246&lt;/ref&gt;

Clicks appear more [[stop consonant|stop]]-like (sharp/abrupt) or [[affricate]]-like (noisy) depending on their place of articulation: In southern Africa, clicks involving an [[apical consonant|apical]] [[alveolar consonant|alveolar]] or [[laminal consonant|laminal]] [[postalveolar consonant|postalveolar]] closure are acoustically abrupt and sharp, like stops, whereas [[labial consonant|labial]], [[dental consonant|dental]] and [[lateral consonant|lateral]] clicks typically have longer and acoustically noisier click types that are superficially more like affricates. In East Africa, however, the alveolar clicks tend to be [[flap consonant|flapped]], whereas the lateral clicks tend to be more sharp.

==Transcription==
{{further|click letter}}
The five click places of articulation with dedicated symbols in the [[International Phonetic Alphabet]] (IPA) are [[labial click|labial]] {{IPA|ʘ}}, [[dental click|dental]] {{IPA|ǀ}}, [[palatal click|palatal]] (&quot;palato-alveolar&quot;) {{IPA|ǂ}}, [[postalveolar click|(post)alveolar]] (&quot;retroflex&quot;) {{IPA|ǃ}} and [[lateral click|lateral]] {{IPA|ǁ}}. In most languages, the alveolar and palatal types are abrupt; that is, they are sharp popping sounds with little frication (turbulent airflow). The labial, dental and lateral types, on the other hand, are typically noisy: they are longer, lip- or tooth-sucking sounds with turbulent airflow, and are sometimes called affricates. (This applies to the forward articulation; both may also have either an affricate or non-affricate rear articulation as well.) The [[apical consonant|apical]] places, {{IPA|ǃ}} and {{IPA|ǁ}}, are sometimes called &quot;grave&quot;, because their pitch is dominated by low frequencies; whereas the [[laminal consonant|laminal]] places, {{IPA|ǀ}} and {{IPA|ǂ}}, are sometimes called &quot;acute&quot;, because they are dominated by high frequencies. (At least in the [[Nǁng language]] and [[Juǀʼhoan language|Juǀʼhoan]], this is associated with a difference in the placement of the rear articulation: &quot;grave&quot; clicks are [[uvular consonant|uvular]], whereas &quot;acute&quot; clicks are [[pharyngeal consonant|pharyngeal]].) Thus the alveolar click {{IPA|/ǃ/}} sounds something like a cork pulled from a bottle (a low-pitch pop), at least in Xhosa; whereas the dental click {{IPA|/ǀ/}} is like English ''tsk! tsk!,'' a high-pitched sucking on the incisors. The lateral clicks are pronounced by sucking on the molars of one or both sides. The labial click {{IPA|/ʘ/}} is different from what many people associate with a kiss: the lips are pressed more-or-less flat together, as they are for a {{IPA|[p]}} or an {{IPA|[m]}}, not rounded as they are for a {{IPA|[w]}}.

The most populous languages with clicks, Zulu and Xhosa, use the letters ''c, q, x,'' by themselves and in [[digraph (orthography)|digraphs]], to write click consonants. Most Khoisan languages, on the other hand (with the notable exceptions of [[Naro language|Naro]] and [[Sandawe language|Sandawe]]), use a more iconic system based on the [[Vertical bar|pipe]] {{angbr|&lt;nowiki&gt;|&lt;/nowiki&gt;}}. (The exclamation point for the &quot;retroflex&quot; click was originally a pipe with a subscript dot, along the lines of ''ṭ, ḍ, ṇ'' used to transcribe the retroflex consonants of India.) There are also two main conventions for the second letter of the digraph as well: voicing may be written with ''g'' and uvular affrication with ''x'', or voicing with ''d'' and affrication with ''g'' (a convention of Afrikaans). In two orthographies of Juǀʼhoan, for example, {{IPA|/ǃ̬/}} is written ''g!'' or ''dq'', and {{IPA|/ǃ͡χ/}} ''!x'' or ''qg''. In languages without {{IPA|/ǃ͡χ/}}, such as Zulu, {{IPA|/ǃ̬/}} may be written ''gq''.

{| class=wikitable
|+ Competing orthographies
!rowspan=2| !!rowspan=2|labial!!colspan=2|laminal!!colspan=2|apical !!subapical
|-
!dental!!palatal!!alveolar!!lateral!!retroflex
|- align=center
! Lepsius (1855)
| ||{{IPA|ǀ}}||{{IPA|ǀ́ }}||{{IPA|ǀ̣ }}||{{IPA|ǀǀ}}||
|- align=center
! Doke (1926)
|{{IPA|ɋ}}||{{IPA|ʇ}}||ↆ {{ref|doke}}||{{IPA|ʗ}}||{{IPA|ʖ}}||{{IPA|ψ}}
|- align=center
! Beach (1938)
|{{IPA|ʘ}}||{{IPA|ʇ}}||{{IPA|&lt;s&gt;ʄ&lt;/s&gt;}} ||{{IPA|ʗ}}||{{IPA|ʖ}}||
|- align=center
! Bantu
| {{IPA|pc}} ||{{IPA|c}}|| ''{{IPA|v ç tc&lt;br/&gt;qc}}'' {{ref|pal}} ||{{IPA|q}}||{{IPA|x}}||
|- align=center
! Khoikhoi
| ||{{IPA|ǀ}}||{{IPA|ǂ}}||{{IPA|ǃ}}||{{IPA|ǁ}}||
|}
# {{note|doke}} {{angbr|ↆ}} was proposed by [[Clement Martyn Doke|Clement Doke]],&lt;ref&gt;Clement M Doke, 1926 (1969), ''The phonetics of the Zulu language''. Johannesburg: University of the Witwatersrand Press&lt;/ref&gt; and {{IPA|&lt;s&gt;ʄ&lt;/s&gt;}} by [[Douglas Martyn Beach|Beach]],&lt;ref&gt;Douglas Martyn Beach, 1938, ''The phonetics of the Hottantot language''. W. Heffer &amp; sons. ltd.&lt;/ref&gt; but did not catch on, and are not supported by Unicode. (Doke's character resembles a down arrow and is here represented by the old [[Roman numeral]] for 50;&lt;ref group=note&gt;{{angbr IPA|ɋ}}, {{angbr IPA|ʇ}}, {{angbr IPA|ʗ}} have descenders; {{angbr IPA|ↆ}}, {{angbr IPA|ʖ}} have ascenders.&lt;/ref&gt; Beach is a double-barred [[esh (letter)|esh]].) Three of these, {{angbr IPA|ʇ}}, {{angbr IPA|ʗ}} and {{angbr IPA|ʖ}}, were adopted into the IPA, though eventually abandoned. Doke and Beach used [[click letters|additional or modified letters]] for voiced and nasal clicks, but they did not catch on.
# {{note|pal}} The labial and palatal clicks do not occur in written Bantu languages. However, the palatal clicks have been romanised in Naron, [[Juǀʼhoan language|Juǀʼhõasi]] and !Xun,{{which|date=December 2012}} where they have been written {{angbr|tc}}, {{angbr|ç}} and {{angbr|qc}}, respectively. In the 19th century, they were sometimes written {{angbr|v}}, which might be source of the Doke letter {{angbr|ↆ}}.

There are a few less-well-attested articulations. &lt;!--Note: the 2nd lateral click in Mangetti Dune could not be reproduced, and the authors have retracted their claim (vd. Miller &amp; Shah 2009). Former text: ''such as a noisy laminal denti-alveolar lateral articulation ({{angbr IPA|⦀}} in an ''ad hoc'' transcription), which contrasts with an apical postalveolar lateral in Mangetti Dune !Kung;''--&gt; A reported subapical retroflex articulation {{angbr IPA|‼}} in Grootfontein !Kung&lt;ref group=note&gt;{{angbr|⦀}} (a triple pipe) in Cole (1966) may have been the same thing. The Doke letter resembled {{angbr|ψ}}, or more precisely an inverted {{angbr|⋔}} (descender only).&lt;/ref&gt; turns out to be alveolar with lateral release, {{angbr IPA|ǃ&lt;sup&gt;ǁ&lt;/sup&gt;}}; Ekoka !Kung has a fricated alveolar click with an s-like release, provisionally transcribed {{angbr IPA|ǃ͡s}}; and Sandawe has a &quot;slapped&quot; alveolar click, provisionally transcribed {{angbr IPA|ǃ¡}} (in turn, the lateral clicks in Sandawe are more abrupt and less noisy than in southern Africa). However, the Khoisan languages are poorly attested, and it is quite possible that, as they become better described, more click articulations will be found.

Formerly when a click consonant was transcribed, two symbols were used, one for each articulation, and connected with a tie bar. This is because a click such as {{IPA|[ŋ͡ǂ]}} was analysed as a nasal velar rear articulation {{IPA|[ŋ]}} pronounced simultaneously with the forward ingressive release {{IPA|[ǂ]}}. The symbols may be written in either order, depending on the analysis: {{angbr IPA|ŋ͡ǂ}} or {{angbr IPA|ǂ͡ŋ}}. However, a tie bar was not often used in practice, and when the manner is [[tenuis consonant|tenuis]] (a simple {{IPA|[k]}}), it was often omitted as well. That is, {{angbr IPA|ǂ}} = {{angbr IPA|kǂ}} = {{angbr IPA|ǂk}} = {{angbr IPA|k͡ǂ}} = {{angbr IPA|ǂ͡k}}. Regardless, elements that do not overlap with the forward release are usually written according to their temporal order: Prenasalisation is always written first ({{angbr IPA|ŋɡ͡ǂ}} = {{angbr IPA|ŋǂ͡ɡ}} = {{angbr IPA|ŋǂ̬}}), and the non-lingual part of a contour is always written second ({{angbr IPA|k͡ǂʼqʼ}} = {{angbr IPA|ǂ͡kʼqʼ}} = {{angbr IPA|ǂ͡qʼ}}).

However, it has become standard to analyse clicks as simplex segments, as research has shown that the front and rear articulations are not independent, and to use click symbols to cover the rear articulation as well, with diacritics rather than digraphs for the accompaniments. At first this tended to be {{angbr IPA|ǂ, ᶢǂ, ᵑǂ}} for {{angbr IPA|k͡ǂ, ɡ͡ǂ, ŋ͡ǂ}}, based on the belief that the rear articulation was velar; but as it has become clear that the rear articulation of both &quot;velar&quot; and &quot;uvular&quot; clicks is actually uvular or even pharyngeal, voicing and nasalisation diacritics more in keeping with the IPA have started to appear: {{angbr IPA|ǂ, ǂ̬, ǂ̃, ŋǂ̬}} for {{angbr IPA|ǂ, ᶢǂ, ᵑǂ, ŋᶢǂ}}.

{| class=&quot;wikitable IPA&quot;
|+Evolution of accompaniment transcription
|-
! !! Tenuis !! Aspirated !! Voiced !! Nasalised !! &quot;Uvular&quot;
|-
! Coarticulation &lt;br&gt;analysis
| k͡ǂ ~ ǂ͡k &lt;br&gt;(kǂ ~ ǂk) || k͡ǂʰ ~ ǂ͡kʰ &lt;br&gt;(kǂʰ ~ ǂkʰ) || ɡ͡ǂ ~ ǂ͡ɡ &lt;br&gt;(ɡǂ ~ ǂɡ) || ŋ͡ǂ ~ ǂ͡ŋ &lt;br&gt;(ŋǂ ~ ǂŋ) || q͡ǂ ~ ǂ͡q &lt;br&gt;(qǂ ~ ǂq)
|-
! Unified, velar
| ǂ || ǂʰ || ᶢǂ || ᵑǂ || &lt;sup&gt;q&lt;/sup&gt;ǂ
|-
! Full IPA
| ǂ || ǂʰ || ǂ̬ || ǂ̃ || ǂ͡q
|}

In practical orthography, the voicing or nasalisation is sometimes given the anterior place of articulation: ''dc'' for {{IPA|ᶢǀ}} and ''mʘ'' for {{IPA|ᵑʘ}}, for example.

In the literature on Damin, the clicks are transcribed as {{angbr|m!, nh!, n!, rn!}}.

==Places of articulation==
{{main|bilabial click|dental click|palatal click|alveolar click|lateral click|retroflex click|velar click}}

[[Place of articulation|Places of articulation]] are often called click ''types, releases,'' or ''influxes,'' though 'release' is also used for the accompaniment/efflux. There are seven or eight known places of articulation, not counting slapped or egressive clicks. These are ''(bi)labial affricated'' {{IPA|ʘ}}, or &quot;(bi)labial&quot;; ''laminal denti-alveolar affricated'' {{IPA|ǀ}}, or &quot;dental&quot;; ''apical (post)alveolar plosive'' {{IPA|ǃ}}, or &quot;alveolar&quot;; ''laminal postalveolar (palato-alveolar) plosive'' {{IPA|ǂ}}, or &quot;palatal&quot;; ''laminal postalveolar (palato-alveolar) affricated'' {{IPA|ǂᶴ}} (known only from [[Ekoka !Kung]]); ''subapical postalveolar ([[Retroflex click|retroflex]])'' {{IPA|‼}} (only known from [[Central !Kung]] and Damin); and ''apical postalveolar lateral'' {{IPA|ǁ}}.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+Basic oral clicks
|-
!Labial||Dental||Alveolar||Retroflex||Domed||Palatal||Lateral||Velar
|-align=center
|{{IPA|ʘ ʘ̬}}||{{IPA|ǀ ǀ̬}}||{{IPA|ǃ ǃ̬}}||{{IPA|‼ ‼̬}}||{{IPA|ǂᶴ ǂ̬ᶴ}}||{{IPA|ǂ ǂ̬}}||{{IPA|ǁ ǁ̬}}||{{IPA|ʞ ʞ̬}}
|}

Languages illustrating each of these articulations are listed below. Given the poor state of documentation of Khoisan languages, it is quite possible that additional places of articulation will turn up. No language is known to contrast more than five.

{| class=wikitable
! Click place&lt;br&gt;inventory !! Languages !! Notes
|-
| dental {{IPA|ǀ}} only || [[Dahalo language|Dahalo]] || Various nasal clicks only.
|-
| 1 release, variable {{IPA|ǀ ~ ǃ ~ ǁ}} || [[Sotho language|Sotho]], [[Gciriku language|Gciriku]], [[Mbukushu language|Mbukushu]] || In Sotho the clicks tend to be alveolar, in Gciriku and Mbukushu dental.
|-
| 2 releases, {{IPA|ǀ}}, {{IPA|ǂ}} || [[Kwadi language|Kwadi]] || {{IPA|ǂ}} not found with all manners
|-
| 2 releases, {{IPA|ǀ}}, {{IPA|ǁ}} || [[ǁXegwi language|ǁXegwi]] || {{IPA|ǃ}} reacquired in loans
|-
| 3 releases, {{IPA|ǀ}}, {{IPA|ǃ}}, {{IPA|ǁ}} || [[Sandawe language|Sandawe]], [[Hadza language|Hadza]], [[Xhosa language|Xhosa]], [[Zulu language|Zulu]] || In Hadza and Sandawe, {{IPA|ǃ}} is often &quot;slapped&quot;.
|-
| 4 releases, {{IPA|ǀ}}, {{IPA|ǂ}}, {{IPA|ǃ}}, {{IPA|ǁ}} || [[Korana language|Korana]], [[Khoekhoe language|Khoekhoe]], [[Yeyi language|Yeyi]], [[Juǀʼhoan dialect|Juǀʼhoan]] ||
|-
| 4 releases, {{IPA|ǀ}}, {{IPA|ǂᶴ}}, {{IPA|ǃ}}, {{IPA|ǁ}} || [[Ekoka !Kung]] || 
|-
| 5 releases, {{IPA|ʘ}}, {{IPA|ǀ}}, {{IPA|ǂ}}, {{IPA|ǃ}}, {{IPA|ǁ}} || [[ǂHoan language|ǂHõã]], [[Nǁng language|Nǀu]], [[ǀXam language|ǀXam]], [[Taa language|Taa]] ||
|-
| 5 releases, {{IPA|ǀ}}, {{IPA|ǂ}}, {{IPA|ǃ}}, {{IPA|‼}}, {{IPA|ǁ}} || [[Grootfontein !Kung]] ||
|-
| 5 releases, {{IPA|ʘ}}, {{IPA|ʘ↑}}, {{IPA|ǀ}}, {{IPA|ǃ}}, {{IPA|‼}} || [[Damin]] || Aside from {{IPA|/ʘ↑/}}, all are nasal.
|}

Extra-linguistically, [[Coatlán Zapotec]] of [[Mexico]] uses a [[linguolabial]] click, {{IPA|[ǀ̼ʔ]}}, as [[mimesis]] for a pig drinking water,&lt;ref name=Azcona&gt;Rosemary Beam de Azcona, ''Sound Symbolism.'' Available at http://www.linguistics.berkeley.edu/~rosemary/55-fall2003-onomatopoeia.pdf {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070623145306/http://www.linguistics.berkeley.edu/~rosemary/55-fall2003-onomatopoeia.pdf |date=23 June 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and several languages, such as [[Wolof language|Wolof]], use a [[velar click]] {{IPA|[ʞ]}}, long judged to be physically impossible, for [[Backchannel (linguistics)|backchanneling]] and to express approval.&lt;ref&gt;Lenore Grenoble (2014) &quot;Verbal gestures: Toward a field-based approach to language description&quot;. In Plungian et al. (eds.), ''Language. Constants. Variables: In memory of A. E. Kibrik'', 105–118. Aleteija:  Saint Petersburg.&lt;/ref&gt; A [[sublingual click]] (&quot;[[sucking-teeth]]&quot;) is found across West Africa, the Caribbean and into the United States.

===Names found in the literature===

The terms for the click types were originally developed by Bleek in 1911. Since then there has been some conflicting variation. Here are the terms used in some of the main references.

{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Click type !! Bantu letters !! Also known as
|-
| {{IPA|ǀ}} dental || ''c'' || dental affricative/affricated/with friction; alveolar affricated; denti-alveolar; apico-lamino-dental; denti-pharyngeal
|-
| {{IPA|ǂ}} palatal || ''ç (tc, qc)'' || palato-alveolar; alveolar; alveolar instantaneous; denti-alveolar implosive; palato-pharyngeal; dental
|-
| {{IPA|ǃ}} alveolar || ''q'' || cerebral; (post-) alveolar implosive; palato-alveolar; palato-alveolar instantaneous; palatal; retroflex; palatal retroflex; apico-palatal; central alveo-uvular
|-
| {{IPA|ǁ}} lateral || ''x'' || lateral affricative/with friction; alveolar lateral affricated; post-alveolar lateral; lateral apico-alveo-palatal; lateral alveo-uvular
|-
| {{IPA|ʘ}} bilabial || ''(pc)'' || labial
|}

The dental, lateral and bilabial clicks are rarely confused. However, the palatal and alveolar clicks frequently have the opposite names in older literature, and they were not distinguished in the IPA until 1989. However, since Ladefoged &amp; Traill (1984) clarified the places of articulation, the terms in the left column above have become standard.&lt;ref group=note&gt;A current exception is [[Unicode]], which still calls the palatal clicks 'alveolar' and the alveolar clicks 'retroflex'.&lt;/ref&gt;

==The back-vowel constraint==
[[Image:Clicks and the BVC.svg|thumb|The shape of the tongue in Nama when articulating an alveolar click (blue) and a palatal click (red) [throat to the right]. The articulation of the vowel {{IPA|[i]}} is slightly forward of the red line, with its peak coinciding with the dip of the blue line.]]
In several languages, including [[Nama language|Nama]] and [[Juǀʼhoan dialect|Juǀʼhoan]], the alveolar click types {{IPA|[ǃ]}} and {{IPA|[ǁ]}} only occur, or preferentially occur, before [[back vowel]]s, whereas the dental and palatal clicks occur before any vowel. The effect is most noticeable with the high front vowel {{IPA|[i]}}. In Nama, for example, the diphthong {{IPA|[əi]}} is common but {{IPA|[i]}} is rare after alveolar clicks, whereas the opposite is true after dental and palatal clicks. This is a common effect of [[uvular consonant|uvular]] or uvularised consonants on vowels in both click and non-click languages. In [[Taa language|Taa]], for example, the back-vowel constraint is triggered by both alveolar clicks and uvular stops, but not by palatal clicks or velar stops: sequences such as {{IPA|*/ǃi/}} and {{IPA|*/qi/}} are rare to non-existent, whereas sequences such as {{IPA|/ǂi/}} and {{IPA|/ki/}} are common. It is also triggered by labial clicks, though not by labial stops. Clicks subject to this constraint involve a sharp [[retracted tongue root|retraction]] of the tongue during release.

{|class=&quot;wikitable IPA&quot;
! !!Abrupt &lt;br&gt;release!!Noisy &lt;br&gt;release
|-
|ballistic tongue retraction&lt;br&gt;&amp; back-vowel constraint
|align=center|ǃ||align=center|ǁ, ʘ
|-
|no retraction, no constraint
|align=center|ǂ||align=center|ǀ
|}

Miller and colleagues (2003) used [[ultrasound imaging]] to show that the rear articulation of the alveolar clicks ({{IPA|[ǃ]}}) in Nama is substantially different from that of palatal and dental clicks. Specifically, the shape of the body of the tongue in palatal clicks is very similar to that of the vowel {{IPA|[i]}}, and involves the same tongue muscles, so that sequences such as {{IPA|[ǂi]}} involved a simple and quick transition. The rear articulation of the alveolar clicks, however, is several centimetres further back, and involves a different set of muscles in the uvular region. The part of the tongue required to approach the palate for the vowel {{IPA|[i]}} is deeply retracted in {{IPA|[ǃ]}}, as it lies at the bottom of the air pocket used to create the vacuum required for click airstream. This makes the transition required for {{IPA|[ǃi]}} much more complex and the timing more difficult than the shallower and more forward tongue position of the palatal clicks. Consequently, {{IPA|[ǃi]}} takes 50 [[millisecond|ms]] longer to pronounce than {{IPA|[ǂi]}}, the same amount of time required to pronounce {{IPA|[ǃəi]}}.

Languages do not all behave alike. In [[Nǁng language|Nǀuu]], the simple clicks {{IPA|/ʘ, ǃ, ǁ/}} trigger the {{IPA|[əi]}} and {{IPA|[æ]}} allophones of {{IPA|/i/}} and {{IPA|/e/}}, whereas {{IPA|/ǀ, ǂ/}} do not. All of the affricated contour clicks, such as {{IPA|/ǂ͡χ/}}, do as well, as do the uvular stops {{IPA|/q, χ/}}. However, the occlusive contour clicks pattern like the simple clicks, and {{IPA|/ǂ͡q/}} does not trigger the back-vowel constraint. This is because they involve tongue-root raising rather than [[Advanced and retracted tongue root|tongue-root retraction]] in the uvular-pharyngeal region. However, in [[Gǀwi dialect|Gǀwi]], which is otherwise largely similar, both {{IPA|/ǂ͡q/}} and {{IPA|/ǂ͡χ/}} trigger the back-vowel constraint (Miller 2009).

==Manners of articulation==
{{main|nasal click|glottalised click|pulmonic-contour click|ejective-contour click}}
Click manners are often called click ''accompaniments'' or ''effluxes'', but both terms have met with objections on theoretical grounds.

There is a great variety of click manners, both simplex and complex, the latter variously analysed as consonant [[consonant cluster|clusters]] or [[contour (linguistics)|contours]]. With so few click languages, and so little study of them, it is also unclear to what extent clicks in different languages are equivalent. For example, the {{IPA|[ǃkˀ]}} of Khoekhoe, {{IPA|[ǃkˀ ~ ŋˀǃk]}} of Sandawe and {{IPA|[ŋ̊ǃˀ ~ ŋǃkˀ]}} of Hadza may be essentially the same phone; no language distinguishes them, and the differences in transcription may have more to do with the approach of the linguist than with actual differences in the sounds. Such suspected allophones/allographs are listed on a common row in the table below.

Some Khoisan languages are [[Linguistic typology|typologically]] unusual in allowing mixed [[phonation|voicing]] in non-click consonant clusters/contours, such as {{IPA|dt͡sʼk͡xʼ}}, so it is not surprising that they would allow mixed voicing in clicks as well. This may be an effect of epiglottalised voiced consonants, because voicing is incompatible with epiglottalisation.

===Phonation===
As do other consonants, clicks vary in [[phonation]]. Oral clicks are attested with four phonations: [[tenuis consonant|tenuis]], [[aspirated consonant|aspirated]], [[voiced consonant|voiced]] and [[breathy voice]]d (murmured). Nasal clicks may also vary, with plain voiced, breathy voiced / murmured nasal, aspirated and unaspirated voiceless clicks attested (the last only in Taa). The aspirated nasal clicks are often said to have 'delayed aspiration'; there is nasal airflow throughout the click, which may become voiced between vowels, though the aspiration itself is voiceless. A few languages also have pre-glottalised nasal clicks, which have very brief prenasalisation&lt;!--creaky-voiced nasal?--&gt; but have not been phonetically analysed to the extent that other types of clicks have.

All languages have nasal clicks, and all but [[Dahalo language|Dahalo]] and [[Damin]] also have oral clicks. All languages but Damin have at least one phonation contrast as well.

===Complex clicks===
Clicks may be pronounced with a third place of articulation, glottal. A [[glottal stop]] is made during the hold of the click; the (necessarily voiceless) click is released, and then the glottal hold is released into the vowel. Glottalised clicks are very common, and they are generally nasalised as well. The nasalisation cannot be heard during the click release, as there is no pulmonic airflow, and generally not at all when the click occurs at the beginning of an utterance, but it has the effect of nasalising preceding vowels, to the extent that the glottalised clicks of Sandawe and Hadza are often described as prenasalised when in medial position. Two languages, [[Gǀwi dialect|Gǀwi]] and [[Yeyi language|Yeyi]], contrast plain and nasal glottalised clicks, but in languages without such a contrast, the glottalised click is nasal. Miller (2011) analyses the glottalisation as phonation, and so considers these to be simple clicks.

Various languages also have prenasalised clicks, which may be analysed as consonant sequences. [[Sotho language|Sotho]], for example, allows a syllabic nasal before its three clicks, as in ''nnqane'' 'the other side' (prenasalised nasal) and ''seqhenqha'' 'hunk'.

There is ongoing discussion as to how the distinction between what were historically described as 'velar' and 'uvular' clicks is best described. The 'uvular' clicks are only found in some languages, and have an extended pronunciation that suggests that they are more complex than the simple ('velar') clicks, which are found in all. Nakagawa (1996) describes the extended clicks in [[Gǀwi dialect|Gǀwi]] as [[consonant cluster]]s, sequences equivalent to English ''st'' or ''pl'', whereas Miller (2011) analyses similar sounds in several languages as click–non-click [[contour (linguistics)|contours]], where a click transitions into a pulmonic or ejective articulation within a single segment, analogous to how English ''ch'' and ''j'' transition from occlusive to fricative but still behave as unitary sounds. With ejective clicks, for example, Miller finds that although the ejective release follows the click release, it is the rear closure of the click that is ejective, not an independently articulated consonant. That is, in a simple click, the release of the rear articulation is not audible, whereas in a contour click, the rear (uvular) articulation is audibly released after the front (click) articulation, resulting in a double release.

These contour clicks may be ''linguo-pulmonic'', that is, they may transition from a click (lingual) articulation to a normal pulmonic consonant like {{IPAblink|q}} (e.g. {{IPA|[ǂ͡q]}}); or ''linguo-glottalic'' and transition from lingual to an ejective consonant like {{IPAblink|qʼ}} (e.g. {{IPA|[ǂ͡qʼ]}}): that is, a sequence of ingressive (lingual) release + egressive (pulmonic or glottalic) release. In some cases there is a shift in place of articulation as well, and instead of a uvular release, the uvular click transitions to a velar or [[Epiglottal consonant|epigottal]] release (depending on the description, {{IPA|[ǂ͡kxʼ]}} or {{IPA|[ǂᴴ]}}). Although [[homorganic]] {{IPA|[ǂ͡χʼ]}} does not contrast with heterorganic {{IPA|[ǂ͡kxʼ]}} in any known language, they are phonetically quite distinct (Miller 2011).

Apart from Dahalo, Damin and many of the Bantu languages (Yeyi and Xhosa being exceptions), 'click' languages have glottalised clicks. Contour clicks are restricted to southern Africa, but are very common there: they are found in all members of the Tuu, Kxʼa and Khoe families, as well as in the Bantu language Yeyi.

===Variation among languages===
In a comparative study of clicks across various languages, using her own field work as well as phonetic descriptions and data by other field researchers, Miller (2011) posits 21 types of clicks that contrast in manner or airstream.&lt;ref group=note&gt;Not counting the egressive &quot;spurt&quot; in Damin, and tree additional voiced manners in Western ǃXoo, which pair up with voiceless manners.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[homorganic]] and heterorganic affricated ejective clicks do not contrast in any known language, but are judged dissimilar enough to keep separate. Miller's conclusions differ from those of the primary researcher of a language; see the individual languages for details.
* [[Taa language|Taa]] (ǃXóõ) and [[Nǁng language|Nǁng]] (Nǀuu) are [[Tuu languages]], from the two branches of that family.
* [[ǂʼAmkoe language|ǂʼAmkoe]] (ǂHoan) and [[Juǀʼhoan language|Juǀʼhoan]] (ǃKung) are [[Kxʼa languages]], from the two branches of that family.
* [[Korana language|Korana]] and [[Gǀwi language|Gǀui]] (Gǁana) are [[Khoe languages]], from the two branches of that family.
(all spoken primarily in [[South Africa]], [[Namibia]] and [[Botswana]]; [[Khoekhoe language|Khoekhoe]] is like Korana except it has lost ejective {{IPA|/Ʞ͡χʼ/}})
* [[Sandawe language|Sandawe]] and [[Hadza language|Hadza]] are [[language isolate]]s spoken in [[Tanzania]]
* [[Dahalo language|Dahalo]] is a [[Cushitic languages|Cushitic]] language of [[Kenya]]
* [[Xhosa language|Xhosa]] and [[Yeyi language|Yeyi]] are [[Bantu languages]], from the two geographic areas of that family that have acquired clicks.
([[Zulu language|Zulu]] is like Xhosa apart from not having {{IPA|/ᵑꞰˀ/}})
* [[Damin]] was an initiation jargon in northern [[Australia]].

Each language below is illustrated with Ʞ as a placeholder for the different click types. Under each language are the orthography (in italics, with old forms in parentheses), the researchers' transcription (in {{angbr|angle brackets}}), or allophonic variation (in [brackets]). Some languages also have labialised&lt;!--not just Dahalo--&gt; or prenasalised clicks as well as those listed below.

{| class=wikitable
! colspan=3 rowspan=2 | &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Language ||  colspan=2| Tuu ||  colspan=2| Kxʼa ||  colspan=2| Khoe || rowspan=2| Sandawe || rowspan=2| Hadza|| Cushitic || colspan=2| Bantu || Australian
|-
! Taa || Nǁng || ǂʼAmkoe || Juǀʼhoan&lt;ref group=note&gt;Ekoka ǃKung has an additional manner, {{IPA|ˀᵑꞰ}}. Grootfontein and Mangetti Dune ǃKung, on the other hand, have a substantially smaller inventory: {{IPA|Ʞ, ᶢꞰ, Ʞʰ, ᵑꞰ, ᵑ̊Ʞʱ, ᵑꞰˀ, Ʞ͡χ, Ʞ͡kxʼ}}.&lt;/ref&gt; || Korana || Gǀui || Dahalo || Xhosa || Yeyi || Damin
|-
! colspan=3 | Manner&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
| colspan=3 align=center bgcolor=&quot;#f2f2f2&quot; | {{IPA|ʘ, ǂ, ǃ, ǁ, ǀ}} || colspan=3 align=center bgcolor=&quot;#f2f2f2&quot; | {{IPA|ǂ, ǃ, ǁ, ǀ}} || colspan=2 align=center bgcolor=&quot;#f2f2f2&quot; | {{IPA|ǃ, ǁ, ǀ}} || align=center bgcolor=&quot;#f2f2f2&quot; | {{IPA|ǀ}} || align=center bgcolor=&quot;#f2f2f2&quot; | {{IPA|ǃ, ǁ, ǀ}} || align=center bgcolor=&quot;#f2f2f2&quot; | {{IPA|ǂ, ǃ, ǁ, ǀ}} || align=center bgcolor=&quot;#f2f2f2&quot; | {{IPA|ʘ, ‼, ǃ, ǀ}}
|-
|rowspan=4|Simple&lt;br&gt;oral&lt;br&gt;click
| ''[[Tenuis consonant|Tenuis]]''|| bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/Ʞ/}}
&lt;!-- !Xoo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|Ʞ}}*
&lt;!-- N/uu --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|Ʞ}}
&lt;!-- =Hoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|[Ʞ]}}
&lt;!-- Ju/hoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''Ʞ (c, ç, q, x)''
&lt;!-- Korana --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''Ʞg''
&lt;!-- G/ui --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|kꞰ}}
&lt;!-- Sandawe --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''c, q, x''
&lt;!-- Hadza --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''c, q, x (Ʞ)'' || 
&lt;!-- Xhosa --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''c, q, x''
&lt;!-- Yeyi --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|Ʞ}} ||
|-
| ''Voiced''|| bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/ᶢꞰ/}}
&lt;!-- !Xoo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|gꞰ}}*
&lt;!-- N/uu --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|ᶢꞰ}}
&lt;!-- =Hoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|[ᶢꞰ]}}
&lt;!-- Ju/hoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''gꞰ (dq etc.)'' || 
&lt;!-- G/ui --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|gꞰ}}
&lt;!-- Sandawe --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''gq etc.''&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[ᶢꞰ}} ~ {{IPA|ŋᶢꞰ]}} ||  ||  || 
&lt;!-- Yeyi --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|gꞰ}} ||
|-
| ''Aspirated''|| bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/Ʞʰ/}}
&lt;!-- !Xoo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|Ʞh}}*
&lt;!-- N/uu --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|Ʞʰ}}
&lt;!-- =Hoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|[Ʞʰ]}}
&lt;!-- Ju/hoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''Ʞh (qh etc.)''
&lt;!-- Korana --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''Ʞkh''
&lt;!-- G/ui --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|kꞰh}}
&lt;!-- Sandawe --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''qh etc.''
&lt;!-- Hadza --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''qh etc. (Ʞh)'' || 
&lt;!-- Xhosa --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''qh etc.''
&lt;!-- Yeyi --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|Ʞh}} (= Ʞx ?) ||
|-
| ''Breathy-voiced''|| bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/ᶢꞰʱ/}}
&lt;!-- !Xoo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|gꞰh}}* ||  || 
&lt;!-- Ju/hoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''gꞰh (dqh etc.)''&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[ᶢꞰʱ ~ ᶢꞰˠ]}} ||  ||  ||  ||  || 
&lt;!-- Xhosa --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''gq etc.''{{refn|Perhaps better described as [[slack voice]]. Tone-depressor effect.&lt;ref&gt;Jessen &amp; Roux, 2002. ''[https://web.archive.org/web/20140703113602/http://www.phonetik.uni-muenchen.de/~hoole/kurse/hslarynx/jessenroux_jphon_30_2002.pdf Voice quality differences associated with stops and clicks in Xhosa]''&lt;/ref&gt;|group=note}} || ||
|-
|rowspan=4|[[Nasal click consonant|Simple&lt;br&gt;nasal&lt;br&gt;click]]
| ''Voiceless''|| bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/ᵑ̊Ʞ/}}
&lt;!-- !Xoo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|nhꞰ}}*&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[ŋ̊ᵑꞰ]}} ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  || ||
|-
| ''Voiced''|| bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/ᵑꞰ/}}
&lt;!-- !Xoo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|nꞰ}}* &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[ŋ̈ᵑꞰ]}}
&lt;!-- N/uu --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|ᵑꞰ}}
&lt;!-- =Hoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|[ᵑꞰ]}}
&lt;!-- Ju/hoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''nꞰ (nq etc.)''
&lt;!-- Korana --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''Ʞn''
&lt;!-- G/ui --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|ŋꞰ}}
&lt;!-- Sandawe --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''nq etc.''
&lt;!-- Hadza --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''nq etc. (nꞰ)''
&lt;!-- Dahalo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/ᵑǀ/}}
&lt;!-- Xhosa --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''nq etc.''
&lt;!-- Yeyi --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|ŋꞰ}}
&lt;!-- Damin --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|Nǃ}}
|-
| ''(Delayed) aspiration&lt;br/&gt;(prenasalised between vowels)''|| bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/ᵑ̊Ʞʱ/}}
&lt;!-- !Xoo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|Ʞhh}}&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[ŋ̊↓Ʞh]}}
&lt;!-- N/uu --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|ᵑ̊Ʞʰ}}
&lt;!-- =Hoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|[ᵑ̊Ʞʱ ~ ŋᵑ̊Ʞʱ]}}
&lt;!-- Ju/hoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''Ʞʼh (qʼh etc.)''
&lt;!-- Korana --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''Ʞh''
&lt;!-- G/ui --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|ŋꞰh}} ||  ||  ||  ||  || ||
|-
| ''Breathy-voiced''|| bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/ᵑꞰʱ/}}
&lt;!-- !Xoo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|nꞰhh}} ||  || 
&lt;!-- Ju/hoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''nꞰh (nqh etc.)'' ||  ||  ||  ||  || 
&lt;!-- Xhosa --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''ngq etc.''&lt;ref group=note&gt;Tone-depressor effect. Sometimes a prenasalized click with a short, voiced oral occlusion, but usually without.&lt;/ref&gt; || ||
|-
| colspan=2| ''Preglottalised nasal click''|| bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/ˀᵑꞰ/}} &lt;!--Not placed under glottalized because the lingual airstream is not glottalized--&gt;
&lt;!-- !Xoo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|ʼnꞰ}}*  || 
&lt;!-- =Hoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|[ʔᵑꞰ]}} || align=center | (in Ekoka) ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  || ||
|-
|rowspan=4|[[Glottalised click|Glottalised&lt;br&gt;click]]
| ''Oral / velar ejective'' || bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/Ʞʼ/}}
&lt;!-- !Xoo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|Ʞʼ}}* || || || || |
&lt;!-- G/ui --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|kꞰʼ}} || || || ||
&lt;!-- Yeyi --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|Ʞʼ}} ||
|-
| ''Creaky-voiced oral'' || bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/ᶢꞰʼ/}}
&lt;!-- !Xoo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|gꞰʼ}}* ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  || ||
|-
| ''Nasal (silent initially,&lt;br/&gt;prenasalised after vowels)''|| bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/ᵑ̊Ʞˀ/}}
&lt;!-- !Xoo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|Ʞʼʼ}}
&lt;!-- N/uu --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|ᵑ̊Ʞˀ}}
&lt;!-- =Hoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|[Ʞˀ ~ ŋˀꞰ]}}
&lt;!-- Ju/hoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''Ʞʼ (qʼ etc.)''&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(w/ nasal vowels)&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;!-- Korana --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''Ʞ''
&lt;!-- G/ui --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|kꞰʔ}} ({{IPA|ŋ̊Ʞʔ}})
&lt;!-- Sandawe --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''qʼ etc.''&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[Ʞˀʔ}} ~ {{IPA|ŋʔꞰˀ]}}
&lt;!-- Hadza --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''qq etc.''&lt;br&gt;''(Ʞʼ ~ nꞰʼ)''
&lt;!-- Dahalo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/ᵑǀˀ/}}
&lt;!-- Xhosa --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''nkq etc.'' ?&lt;ref&gt;According to Nurse &amp; Philippson (2003:616). This is typically transcribed as a prenasalized click, and is not included in Miller.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- Yeyi --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|ŋꞰʼ}} ||
|-
| ''Nasal (prenasalised initially) ''|| bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/ᵑꞰˀ/}}
&lt;!-- !Xoo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|nꞰʼʼ}} ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  || ||
|-
|rowspan=6 bgcolor=&quot;#f2f2f2&quot; |[[Pulmonic-contour click consonant|Pulmonic&lt;br&gt;contour]]
| bgcolor=&quot;#f2f2f2&quot; |''Tenuis stop''|| bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/Ʞ͡q/}}
&lt;!-- !Xoo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|Ʞq}}
&lt;!-- N/uu --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|Ʞq}}
&lt;!-- =Hoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|[Ʞq]}}
!  || 
&lt;!-- G/ui --&gt;|  bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|qꞰ}}
!  ||  ||  ||  || ||
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#f2f2f2&quot; |''Voiced (and prenasalised)''|| bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/ᶢꞰ͡ɢ/}}
&lt;!-- !Xoo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|gꞰq}}&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[ᶰꞰɢ ~ Ʞɢ]}}
&lt;!-- N/uu --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|[Ʞɢ]}}&lt;ref group=note&gt;not prenasalized&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- =Hoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ({{IPA|[ᶰꞰɢ]}})&lt;ref group=note&gt;perhaps borrowed from Gǀui&lt;/ref&gt;
!  || 
&lt;!-- G/ui --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|ɢꞰ}}&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[ᶰꞰɢ]}}
!  ||  ||  ||  || ||
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#f2f2f2&quot; |''Aspirated stop''|| bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/Ʞ͡qʰ/}}
&lt;!-- !Xoo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|Ʞqh}}
&lt;!-- N/uu --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|Ʞqʰ}}
&lt;!-- =Hoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|[Ʞqʰ]}}
!  || 
&lt;!-- G/ui --&gt;|  bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|qꞰh}}
!  ||  ||  ||  || ||
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#f2f2f2&quot; |''Breathy-voiced ''|| bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/ᶢꞰ͡ɢʱ/}}
&lt;!-- !Xoo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|gꞰqh}}
!  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  || ||
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#f2f2f2&quot; |''Voiceless fricative ''|| bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/Ʞ͡χ/}}
&lt;!-- !Xoo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|Ʞx}}
&lt;!-- N/uu --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|Ʞχ}}
&lt;!-- =Hoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|[Ʞq͡χ]}}
&lt;!-- Ju/hoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''Ʞx (qg etc.)''
!
&lt;!-- G/ui --&gt;|  bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|qꞰχ}}
!  ||  ||  || 
&lt;!-- Yeyi --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|Ʞx}} (?)
!
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#f2f2f2&quot; |''Voiced fricative (prenasalised) ''|| bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/ᶢꞰ͡ʁ/}}
&lt;!-- !Xoo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|gꞰx}}&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[ᶢꞰ͡χ ~ ɴᶢꞰ͡ʁ]}}
!  || 
&lt;!-- Ju/hoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''gꞰx (dqg etc.)''
!  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||
|-
|rowspan=5 bgcolor=&quot;#f2f2f2&quot; |[[Ejective-contour click consonant|Ejective&lt;br&gt;contour]]
| bgcolor=&quot;#f2f2f2&quot; |''Ejective stop''|| bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/Ʞ͡qʼ/}}
&lt;!-- !Xoo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|Ʞqʼ}}
&lt;!-- N/uu --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|[Ʞqʼ]}}
&lt;!-- ǂHoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|[Ʞqʼ]}}
!  || 
&lt;!-- G/ui --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|qꞰʼ}}
!  ||  ||  ||  || ||
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#f2f2f2&quot; |''Voiced ejective stop'' || bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/ᶢꞰ͡qʼ/}}
&lt;!-- !Xoo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|gꞰqʼ}}
!  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  || ||
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#f2f2f2&quot; |''Ejective fricative''|| bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/Ʞ͡χʼ/}}
!
&lt;!-- N/uu --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|Ʞχʼ}}
&lt;!-- ǂHoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|[Ʞq͡χʼ]}}
!
&lt;!-- Korana --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center rowspan=2 | ''Ʞkhʼ''
! ||  ||  ||  || 
&lt;!-- Yeyi --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|Ʞqʼ}}&lt;!--affricated per Miller--&gt;
!
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#f2f2f2&quot; |''Heterorganic affricate /&lt;br&gt; epiglottalised''|| bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/Ʞ͡kxʼ/}}
&lt;!-- !Xoo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|Ʞqxʼ}}
!  || 
&lt;!-- Ju/hoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''Ʞk (qgʼ etc.)''&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[Ʞᵸ]}}
&lt;!-- G/ui --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|qꞰχʼ}}
!  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#f2f2f2&quot; |''Voiced heterorganic &lt;br&gt;affricate / epiglottalised''|| bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/ᶢꞰ͡kxʼ/}}
&lt;!-- !Xoo --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|gꞰqxʼ}}
!  || 
&lt;!-- Ju/hoan --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | ''gꞰk (dqgʼ etc.)''&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[ᶢꞰˤ]}}
!  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||
|-
| Egressive&lt;ref group=note&gt;Not technically a click, but the only other attested sound with a lingual airstream mechanism.&lt;/ref&gt; || ''(Voiceless &quot;spurt&quot;; labial only)'' || bgcolor=&quot;#c0c0f0&quot; align=center | {{IPA|/ʘ↑/}}
|  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  ||  || 
&lt;!-- Damin --&gt;| bgcolor=&quot;#f0c0c0&quot; align=center | {{angbr|pʼ}}
|-
! colspan=2 |  || IPA || Taa || Nǁng || ǂʼAmkoe || Juǀʼhoan || Korana || Gǀui || Sandawe || Hadza || Dahalo || Xhosa || Yeyi || Damin
|}
Yeyi also has prenasalised {{IPA|/ŋᶢꞰ/}}. The original researchers believe that {{IPA|[Ʞʰ]}} and {{IPA|[Ʞχ]}} are allophones.

A DoBeS (2008) study of the Western ǃXoo dialect of Taa found several new manners: creaky voiced (the voiced equivalent of glottalised oral), breathy-voiced nasal, prenasalised glottalised (the voiced equivalent of glottalised) and a (pre)voiced ejective. These extra voiced clicks reflect Western ǃXoo morphology, where many nouns form their plural by voicing their initial consonant. DoBeS analyses most Taa clicks as clusters, leaving nine basic manners (marked with asterisks in the table). This comes close to Miller's distinction between simple and contour clicks, shaded light and medium grey in the table.

==Phonotactics==
Languages of the southern African Khoisan families only permit clicks at the beginning of a word root. However, they also restrict other classes of consonant, such as [[ejective consonant|ejectives]] and [[affricate]]s, to root-initial position. The Bantu languages, Hadza and Sandawe allow clicks within roots.

In some languages, all click consonants within known roots are the same phoneme, as in Hadza ''cikiringcingca'' {{IPA|/ǀikiɺiN.ǀiN.ǀa/}} 'pinkie finger', which has three [[tenuis dental click]]s. Other languages are known to have the occasional root with different clicks, as in Xhosa ''ugqwanxa'' {{IPA|/uᶢ̊ǃʱʷaᵑǁa/}} '[[Olea capensis|black ironwood]]', which has a slack-[[voiced alveolar click]] and a [[nasal lateral click]].

Like other articulatorily complex consonants, clicks tend to be found in [[lexical words]] rather than in [[grammatical word]]s, but this is only a tendency. In [[Nǁng language|Nǁng]], for example, there are two sets of [[personal pronoun]]s, a full one without clicks and a partial set with clicks (''ńg'' 'I', ''á'' 'thou', ''í'' 'we all', ''ú'' 'you', vs. ''nǀǹg'' 'I', ''gǀà'' 'thou', ''gǀì'' 'we all', ''gǀù'' 'you'), as well as other grammatical words with clicks such as ''ǁu'' 'not' and ''nǀa'' 'with, and'.

==Click genesis and click loss==
One genetic study concluded that clicks, which occur in the languages of the genetically divergent populations Hadza and !Kung, may be an ancient element of human language.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Tishkoff |first=S. A. |last2=Gonder |first2=M. K. |last3=Henn |first3=B. M. |last4=Mortensen |first4=H. |last5=Knight |first5=A. |last6=Gignoux |first6=C. |last7=Fernandopulle |first7=N. |displayauthors=3 |year=2007 |title=History of click-speaking populations of Africa inferred from mtDNA and Y chromosome genetic variation |journal=Molecular Biology and Evolution |volume=24 |issue=10 |pages=2180–95 |doi=10.1093/molbev/msm155 |pmid=17656633 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, this conclusion relies on several dubious assumptions (see [[Hadza language]]), and most linguists{{citation needed|date=June 2019}} assume that clicks, being quite complex consonants, arose relatively late in human history. How they arose is not known, but it is generally assumed that they developed from sequences of non-click consonants, as they are found allophonically for [[doubly articulated consonant]]s in West Africa,{{sfn|Ladefoged|1968}} where {{IPA|/tk/}} sequences overlap at word boundaries in German,&lt;ref name=germ /&gt; and for the sequence {{IPA|/mw/}} in [[Ndau language|Ndau]] and [[Tonga language (Zambia)|Tonga]].&lt;ref group=note&gt;Here the labial {{IPA|[m]}} may have assimilated to the velar place of the {{IPA|[w]}}, as {{IPA|[m͡ŋw]}}, with the release of the labial before the velar later generating a click {{IPA|[ᵐʘw]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Such developments have also been posited in historical reconstruction. For example, the [[Sandawe language|Sandawe]] word for 'horn', {{IPA|/tɬana/}}, with a lateral affricate, may be a cognate with the root {{IPA|/ᵑǁaː/}} found throughout the [[Khoe languages|Khoe family]], which has a lateral click. This and other words suggests that at least some Khoe clicks may have formed from consonant clusters when the first vowel of a word was lost; in this instance *{{IPA|[tɬana]}} &gt; *{{IPA|[tɬna]}} &gt; {{IPA|[ǁŋa] ~ [ᵑǁa]}}.

On the other side of the equation, several non-endangered languages in vigorous use demonstrate click loss. For example, the [[Khoe languages|East Kalahari languages]] have lost clicks from a large percentage of their vocabulary, presumably due to [[Bantu languages|Bantu]] influence. As a rule, a click is replaced by a consonant with close to the [[manner of articulation]] of the click and the [[place of articulation]] of the forward release: alveolar click releases (the {{IPA|[ǃ]}} family) tend to mutate into a velar stop or affricate, such as {{IPA|[k], [ɡ], [ŋ], [k͡x]}}; palatal clicks ({{IPA|[ǂ]}} ''etc.'') tend to mutate into a palatal stop such as {{IPA|[c], [&amp;thinsp;ɟ], [&amp;thinsp;ɲ], [cʼ]}}, or a post-alveolar affricate {{IPA|[tʃ], [dʒ]}}; and dental clicks ({{IPA|[ǀ]}} ''etc.'') tend to mutate into an alveolar affricate {{IPA|[ts]}}.{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}}

==Difficulty==
Clicks are often presented as difficult sounds to articulate within words. However, children acquire them readily; a two-year-old, for example, may be able to pronounce a word with a lateral click {{IPA|[ǁ]}} with no problem, but still be unable to pronounce {{IPA|[s]}}.&lt;ref&gt;Kirk Miller, 'Highlights of Hadza fieldwork'. ''LSA'', San Francisco, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lucy Lloyd]] reported that after long contact with the Khoi and San, it was difficult for her to refrain from using clicks when speaking English.&lt;ref&gt;Beach (1938), p 269.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Div col||colwidth=20em}}
* [[Dental click]]s
* [[Alveolar click]]s
* [[Fricated alveolar click]]s
* [[Retroflex click]]s
* [[Lateral click]]s
* [[Palatal click]]s
* [[Labial click]]s
* [[Nasal click]]s
* [[Glottalised click]]s
* [[Pulmonic-contour click]]s
* [[Ejective-contour click]]s
* [[Click letter]]s
* [[List of phonetics topics]]
* [[Sublaminal lower alveolar click]]
{{div col end}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=note}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite book|last=Ladefoged|first=Peter|year=1968|title=A phonetic study of West African languages: An auditory-instrumental survey|edition= 2nd|ISBN=0-521-06963-7|ref=harv}}
* {{SOWL}}
* Amanda Miller, Levi Namaseb, Khalil Iskarous. 2003. ''Tongue Body constriction differences in click types.''
* Amanda Miller, 2011. &quot;The Representation of Clicks&quot;. In Oostendorp et al. eds., ''The Blackwell Companion to Phonology.''
* Traill, Anthony &amp; Rainer Vossen. 1997. ''Sound change in the Khoisan languages: new data on click loss and click replacement''. J African Languages and Linguistics 18:21–56.

==External links==
* [http://homepage.ntu.edu.tw/~karchung/Phonetics%20II%20page%20four.htm Collection of click-language links and audio samples].
* [http://www.ling.su.se/fon/perilus/2003_21.pdf Hartmut Traunmüller (2003) &quot;Clicks and the idea of a human protolanguage&quot;, ''Phonum 9:'' 1 – 4 (Umeå University, Dept. of Philosophy and Linguistics)]
* [http://esciencenews.com/articles/2009/07/15/classifying.clicks Classifying clicks]
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6FQM4D1OvtA A Chinese nursery rhyme with flapped clicks] (or search for videos with the words 天上一隻鵝)

{{IPA navigation}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2011}}

[[Category:Click consonants| ]]</text>
      <sha1>9qufjw4untnlnq519vy6x63xi9m66it</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
