  <page>
    <title>Dramaturge</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8584</id>
    <revision>
      <id>923099838</id>
      <parentid>899392128</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-10-26T10:42:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mike Peel</username>
        <id>214232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Changing the Commons category from &quot;Category:Playwrights&quot; to &quot;Category:Dramaturges&quot;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">A '''dramaturge''' or '''dramaturg''' is a literary adviser or editor in a [[theatre]], [[opera]], or film company who researches, selects, adapts, edits, and interprets scripts, libretti, texts, and printed programmes (or helps others with these tasks), consults with authors, and does [[public relations]] work.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ahdictionary.com/word/search.html?q=dramaturge|title=The American Heritage Dictionary entry: dramaturge|first=Houghton Mifflin Harcourt Publishing|last=Company|website=Ahdictionary.com|accessdate=23 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.collinsdictionary.com/dictionary/english/dramaturge|title=Dramaturge definition and meaning - Collins English Dictionary|website=Collinsdictionary.com|accessdate=23 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/us/dramaturge|title=dramaturge - Definition of dramaturge in US English by Oxford Dictionaries|website=Oxford Dictionaries - English|accessdate=23 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its modern-day function was originated by the innovations of [[Gotthold Ephraim Lessing]], an 18th-century German [[playwright]], [[philosopher]], and [[dramatic theory|theatre theorist]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last= Schecter| page=27|editor=Cardullo, Bert|first=Joel|year=1995|title=What is Dramaturgy?|isbn=978-0-8204-2177-3|publisher=American University Press| quote= While at the Hamburg National Theatre, Lessing wrote Hamburg Dramaturgy, a collection of essays on theatre which popularized dramaturgy as both a word and a practice.  Today Lessing's successors&amp;nbsp;— resident theatre critics throughout Germany and Austria&amp;nbsp;— are called dramaturg(e)s.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Responsibilities==
One of the dramaturge's contributions is to categorize and discuss the various types of plays or [[opera]]s, their interconnectedness and their styles.  The responsibilities of a dramaturge vary from one theatre or opera company to the next.  They might include the hiring of actors, the development of a season of plays or operas with a sense of coherence among them, assistance with and editing of new plays or operas by resident or guest playwrights or composers/librettists, the creation of programmes or accompanying educational services, helping the director with rehearsals, and serving as elucidator of history or spokesperson for deceased or otherwise absent playwrights or composers. At larger theatres or opera houses, the dramaturge works on the historical and cultural research into the play or opera and its setting.

In theatre companies, a dramaturge will create a workbook for the director and actors (usually these are different) and work extensively with the director prior to the first rehearsal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Proehl|first=Geoffrey S|year=2008|isbn=978-0-8386-4112-5|publisher=Associated University Press|title=Toward a Dramaturgical Sensibility:landscape and journey|page=19|quote=dramaturgy is the name given to that set of elements necessary to the working of a play at any moment in its passage from imagination to embodiment&amp;nbsp;...}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[File:Gotthold Lessing.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Gotthold Ephraim Lessing]]]]
[[Gotthold Ephraim Lessing]] was hired by the [[Hamburg National Theatre]] in 1767, to serve as the theatre's critic of plays and acting, a position which would later be named dramaturge. This position grew over time to what it is today, encompassing the wide variety of tasks seen by modern dramaturgies.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=|first=|date=October 2018|title=Gotthold Ephraim Lessing|url=http://go.galegroup.com/ps/retrieve.do?tabID=Biographies&amp;resultListType=RESULT_LIST&amp;searchResultsType=MultiTab&amp;searchType=PersonSearchForm&amp;currentPosition=2&amp;docId=GALE%7CK1631003917&amp;docType=Biography&amp;sort=Relevance&amp;contentSegment=&amp;prodId=BIC&amp;contentSet=GALE%7CK1631003917&amp;searchId=R1&amp;userGroupName=colu91149&amp;inPS=true#|journal=Encyclopedia of World Biography.|volume=Online ed. 1998|pages=|via=GALE Biography in Context}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=|first=|date=October 2018|editor-last=Dewald|editor-first=Jonathan|editor-link=|title=Gotthold Ephraim Lessing|url=http://link.galegroup.com/apps/doc/K3404900636/BIC?u=colu91149&amp;sid=BIC&amp;xid=65e42d3b|journal=Europe, 1450 to 1789: Encyclopedia of the Early Modern World|volume=2004|pages=|via=GALE Biography in Context}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Discrepancies with definition==
The modern definition of ''dramaturge'' is often debated as to what specific tasks this job does, with some defining it as the bridge between the director and the actors, others defining it as one who determines the meaning of plays and shows for the actors, and others claiming that even they don’t quite have a complete definition for their job. This discrepancy between dramaturgies is likely due to the lack of an official historical definition, and the wide variety of tasks that dramaturgies could be asked to work on, depending on the theatre, director, the show being produced, and the actors. Since Gotthold Ephraim Lessing didn't create an official definition for his own position at the Hamburg National Theatre, modern dramaturgies have to infer their tasks based on what Lessing did during his career, and adapt to the current needs of modern [[theatre]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/12/theater/arts-in-america-dramaturges-take-a-while-to-define-themselves.html|title=ARTS IN AMERICA; Dramaturges Take a While to Define Themselves|last=Honan|first=William H.|access-date=2018-10-25|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.americantheatre.org/2015/09/29/the-dramaturg-is-in/|title=The Dramaturg Is In|date=2015-09-29|work=AMERICAN THEATRE|access-date=2018-10-25|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Recent growth of dramaturgies==
Since the year 2000, the number of dramaturgies working around the world has increased, albeit it still remains a fairly rare job to have. In 2000, 400 dramaturgies were recorded to be active in the United States, with that number growing. There are various possibilities for what is causing this growth, but some dramaturgies attribute the growth to the fact that dramaturgy combines two popular studies for young students: the [[liberal arts education|liberal arts]] and theatre. Some dramaturgies are worried, however, that this growth may slow down, due to a decrease in the number of modern plays being written.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; 

==See also==
{{Portal|Theatre}}
* [[Dramaturgy]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Dramaturges}}
* [http://www.lmda.org/ Literary Managers &amp; Dramaturgs of the Americas], official website of the organization of these professionals in North America

{{Authority control}}

{{Use British English Oxford spelling|date=May 2019}}

[[Category:Dramaturges]]
[[Category:Theatrical occupations]]


{{job-stub}}
{{theatre-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>kqptzwz0lwwnc38v0b2nam50dywwp6v</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
