  <page>
    <title>Dyson sphere</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8586</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940978139</id>
      <parentid>940978039</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-15T21:13:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Solomonfromfinland</username>
        <id>11874933</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>[[Category:Solar power]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Hypothetical megastructure originally described by Freeman Dyson}}
[[File:A Dyson Swarm Superstructure (21983905140).png|thumb|3D rendering of a Dyson sphere utilizing large, orbiting panels]]
A '''Dyson sphere''' is a hypothetical [[megastructure]] that completely encompasses a [[star]] and captures a large percentage of its power output. The concept is a [[thought experiment]] that attempts to explain how a [[spacefaring]] civilization would meet its energy requirements once those requirements exceed what can be generated from the home planet's resources alone. Only a tiny fraction of a star's energy emissions reach the surface of any orbiting [[planet]]. Building structures encircling a star would enable a [[civilization]] to harvest far more energy.

The first contemporary description of the structure was by [[Olaf Stapledon]] in his science fiction novel ''[[Star Maker]]'' (1937), in which he described &quot;every solar system... surrounded by a gauze of light traps, which focused the escaping solar energy for intelligent use.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Tate|first1=Karl|title=Dyson Spheres: How Advanced Alien Civilizations Would Conquer the Galaxy|url=https://www.space.com/24276-dyson-spheres-how-advanced-alien-civilizations-would-conquer-the-galaxy-infographic.html|website=space.com|accessdate=January 14, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The concept was later popularized by [[Freeman Dyson]] in his 1960 paper &quot;Search for Artificial Stellar Sources of [[Infrared Radiation]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;search&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|journal=[[Science (journal)|Science]]|year= 1960 |url=http://www.islandone.org/LEOBiblio/SETI1.HTM |title=Search for Artificial Stellar Sources of Infra-Red Radiation|author= Freemann J. Dyson|pages= 1667–1668 |volume =131 |doi= 10.1126/science.131.3414.1667|pmid=17780673|issue=3414|bibcode = 1960Sci...131.1667D |author-link= Freeman Dyson }}&lt;/ref&gt; Dyson speculated that such structures would be the logical consequence of the escalating energy needs of a technological civilization and would be a necessity for its long-term survival. He proposed that searching for such structures could lead to the detection of advanced, intelligent [[extraterrestrial life]]. Different types of Dyson spheres and their energy-harvesting ability would correspond to levels of technological advancement on the [[Kardashev scale]].

Since then, other variant designs involving building an artificial structure or series of structures to encompass a star have been proposed in [[exploratory engineering]] or described in [[science fiction]] under the name &quot;Dyson sphere&quot;. These later proposals have not been limited to solar-power stations, with many involving [[space habitat|habitation]] or [[industry|industrial]] elements. Most fictional depictions describe a solid [[#Dyson shell|shell of matter]] enclosing a star, which is considered by Dyson himself the least plausible variant of the idea. In May 2013, at the Starship Century Symposium in San Diego, Dyson repeated his comments that he wished the concept had not been named after him.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://starshipconf.ucsd.edu/|title=STARSHIP CENTURY SYMPOSIUM, MAY 21 - 22, 2013|date=7 July 2013|accessdate=31 August 2017|url-status=bot: unknown|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130707123030/http://starshipconf.ucsd.edu/|archivedate=7 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Origin of concept ==
{{see also|Energy development}}[[File:Freeman Dyson.jpg|thumb|[[Freeman Dyson]] in 2005]]The concept of the Dyson sphere was the result of a [[thought experiment]] by physicist and mathematician [[Freeman Dyson]], when he theorized that all technological civilizations constantly increased their demand for energy. He reasoned that if human civilization expanded energy demands long enough, there would come a time when it demanded the ''total'' energy output of the [[Sun]]. He proposed a system of orbiting structures (which he referred to initially as a ''shell'') designed to intercept and collect all energy produced by the Sun. Dyson's proposal did not detail how such a system would be constructed, but focused only on issues of energy collection, on the basis that such a structure could be distinguished by its unusual emission spectrum in comparison to a star. His 1960 paper &quot;Search for Artificial Stellar Sources of Infra-Red Radiation&quot;, published in the journal ''[[Science (journal)|Science]]'', is credited with being the first to formalize the concept of the Dyson sphere.&lt;ref name=&quot;search&quot;/&gt;

However, Dyson was not the first to advance this idea. He was inspired by the 1937 [[science fiction]] novel ''[[Star Maker]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Disturbing the Universe |last=Dyson |first=Freeman |year=1979 |publisher=Basic Books |isbn=978-0-465-01677-8 |page=211 |quote=Some science fiction writers have wrongly given me the credit of inventing the artificial biosphere. In fact, I took the idea from Olaf Stapledon, one of their own colleagues}}&lt;/ref&gt; by [[Olaf Stapledon]], and possibly by the works of [[J. D. Bernal]], [[Raymond Z. Gallun]], and [[Edgar Rice Burroughs]], who seem to have explored similar concepts in their work.&lt;ref name = dsfaq-as-first-2012-01&gt;{{Cite web
| url = http://www.aleph.se/Nada/dysonFAQ.html#FIRST
| title = Dyson FAQ
| at = § 3. Was Dyson First?
| last = Sandberg
| first = Anders
| author-link = Anders Sandberg
| date = 2012-01-02&lt;!-- taken from page info mod date --&gt;
| location = [[Stockholm]], [[Sweden]]
| archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20121121142408/http://www.aleph.se/Nada/dysonFAQ.html
| archive-date = 2012-11-21
| url-status = live
| access-date = 2015-04-23
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Feasibility ==
Although such megastructures are theoretically possible, building a stable Dyson sphere system is currently beyond humanity's engineering capacity. The number of craft required to obtain, transmit, and maintain a complete Dyson sphere exceeds present-day industrial capabilities. [[George Dvorsky]] has advocated the use of [[self-replicating robots]] to overcome this limitation in the relatively near term.&lt;ref name=dvorsky2012&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sentientdevelopments.com/2012/03/how-to-build-dyson-sphere-in-five.html |title=How to build a Dyson sphere in five (relatively) easy steps |last1=Dvorsky |first1=George |date=2012-03-20 |access-date=2016-10-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some have suggested that such habitats could be built around [[white dwarf]]s&lt;ref&gt;{{cite arxiv |title=Dyson Spheres around White Dwarfs|eprint=1503.04376|last1=Semiz|first1=İbrahim|last2=Oğur|first2=Salim|class=physics.pop-ph|year=2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and even [[pulsar]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Osmanov | first1 = Z. | year = 2015| title = On the search for artificial Dyson-like structures around pulsars | arxiv = 1505.05131| journal = Int. J. Astrobiol. | volume =  15| issue = 2| pages =  127–132| doi = 10.1017/S1473550415000257 |bibcode = 2016IJAsB..15..127O }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Variants ==
In fictional accounts, the Dyson-sphere concept is often interpreted as an artificial hollow [[sphere]] of [[matter]] around a star. This perception is based on a literal interpretation of Dyson's original short paper introducing the concept. In response to letters prompted by some papers, Dyson replied, &quot;A solid shell or ring surrounding a star is mechanically impossible. The form of 'biosphere' which I envisaged consists of a loose collection or swarm of objects traveling on independent orbits around the star.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| journal= [[Science (journal)|Science]]|volume= 132|year= 1960|pages= 250–253|title= Letters and Response, Search for Artificial Stellar Sources of Infrared Radiation|author= [[Freeman Dyson|F. J. Dyson]], J. Maddox, P. Anderson, E. A. Sloane|doi= 10.1126/science.132.3421.252-a|pmid= 17748945| issue= 3421}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Dyson swarm ===
[[File:Dyson Ring.PNG|thumb|A '''Dyson ring'''—the simplest form of the Dyson swarm—to scale. Orbit is 1 [[Astronomical unit|AU]] in radius, collectors are 1.0{{e|7}} km in diameter (10 [[Gigametre|Gm]] or ≈25 times the [[Lunar distance (astronomy)|Earth–Moon distance]]), spaced 3 degrees from center to center around the orbital circle.]]
[[File:Dyson Swarm.png|thumb|A relatively simple arrangement of multiple Dyson rings of the type pictured above, to form a more complex Dyson swarm. Rings' orbital radii are spaced 1.5{{e|7}} km with regard to one another, but average orbital radius is still 1 [[Astronomical unit|AU]]. Rings are rotated 15 degrees relative to one another, around a common axis of rotation.]]

The variant closest to Dyson's original conception is the &quot;Dyson swarm&quot;. It consists of a large number of independent constructs (usually [[solar power satellite]]s and [[Space colonization|space habitats]]) orbiting in a dense formation around the star. This construction approach has advantages: components could be sized appropriately, and it can be constructed incrementally.&lt;ref name=&quot;canbuild&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.nada.kth.se/~asa/dysonFAQ.html#BUILT| title= Dyson FAQ: Can a Dyson sphere be built using realistic technology? | accessdate=2006-09-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Various forms of [[wireless energy transfer]] could be used to transfer energy between swarm components and a planet.

Disadvantages resulting from the nature of [[Astrodynamics|orbital mechanics]] would make the arrangement of the orbits of the swarm extremely complex. The simplest such arrangement is the ''Dyson ring'', in which all such structures share the same orbit. More-complex patterns with more rings would intercept more of the star's output, but would result in some constructs eclipsing others periodically when their orbits overlap.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.aleph.se/Trans/Tech/Megascale/dyson_page.html|title= Some Sketches of Dyson Spheres|accessdate= 2007-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another potential problem is that the increasing loss of orbital stability when adding more elements increases the probability of orbital perturbations.

Such a cloud of collectors would alter the light emitted by the star system (see [[Dyson sphere#Search for megastructures|below]]). However, the disruption compared to a star's overall natural emitted spectrum would most likely be too small for Earth-based astronomers to observe.&lt;ref name=&quot;search&quot;/&gt;

=== Dyson bubble ===
[[File:Dyson Bubble.png|thumb|A '''Dyson bubble''': an arrangement of [[statite]]s around a star, in a non-orbital pattern. As long as a satellite has an unobstructed line-of-sight to its star, it can hover at any point in space near its star. This relatively simple arrangement is only one of an infinite number of possible statite configurations, and is meant as a contrast for a Dyson swarm only. Statites are pictured as the same size as the collectors pictured above, and arranged at a uniform 1 [[Astronomical unit|AU]] distance from the star.
]]

A second type of Dyson sphere is the &quot;Dyson bubble&quot;. It would be similar to a Dyson swarm, composed of many independent constructs and likewise could be constructed incrementally.

Unlike the Dyson swarm, the constructs making it up are not in orbit around the star, but would be [[statite]]s—satellites suspended by use of enormous [[light sail]]s using [[radiation pressure]] to counteract the star's pull of gravity. Such constructs would not be in danger of collision or of eclipsing one another; they would be totally stationary with regard to the star, and independent of one another. Because the ratio of [[radiation pressure]] to the force of gravity from a star is constant regardless of the distance (provided the satellite has an unobstructed line-of-sight to the surface of its star&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.grc.nasa.gov/WWW/K-12/Numbers/Math/Mathematical_Thinking/sunlight_exerts_pressure.htm| title= Sunlight Exerts Pressure| accessdate=2006-03-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;), such satellites could also vary their distance from their central star.

The practicality of this approach is questionable with modern [[material science]], but cannot yet be ruled out. A 100% reflective satellites deployed around the Sun would have an overall [[density]] of 0.78 grams per square meter of sail.&lt;ref name=&quot;stable&quot;/&gt; To illustrate the low mass of the required materials, consider that the total mass of a bubble of such material 1 AU in radius would be about 2.17{{e|20}} kg, which is about the same mass as the asteroid [[2 Pallas|Pallas]].&lt;ref name=&quot;FAQ enough&quot;/&gt; Another illustration: Regular printing [[paper]] has a density of around 80 g/m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;.

Such a material has not yet been produced in the form of a working light sail. The lightest carbon-fiber [[light sail|light-sail]] material currently produced has a density—without payload—of 3 g/m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, or about four times as heavy as would be needed to construct a solar statite.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.space.com/businesstechnology/technology/carbonsail_000302.html |title=SPACE.com Exclusive: Breakthrough In Solar Sail Technology |first=Greg |last=Clark |publisher=Space.com |year=2000 |accessdate=2006-03-02 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060114020015/http://www.space.com/businesstechnology/technology/carbonsail_000302.html |archivedate=2006-01-14 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A single sheet of [[graphene]], the two-dimensional form of carbon, has a density of only 0.37&amp;nbsp;mg per square meter,&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | first = Mitali | last = Kakran | contribution = Graphene: The New Wonder Material!!! | title = IET present around the world | date = 2011 | url = http://conferences.theiet.org/patw/-documents/mitali-kakran-slides.cfm | format = PDF | accessdate = 2013-03-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; making such a single sheet of graphene possibly effective as a solar sail. However, as of 2015 graphene has not been fabricated in large sheets, and it has a relatively high rate of radiation absorption, about 2.3% (i.e., still about 97.7% will be transmitted).&lt;ref name=&quot;Graphene properties&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.graphene-battery.net/graphene-properties.htm |title=Graphene properties | publisher=www.graphene-battery.net | date=2014-05-29 |accessdate=2014-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;{{cite arxiv |eprint=1201.3071|last1=Apell|first1=S. P|title=High optical absorption in graphene|last2=Hanson|first2=G. W|last3=Hägglund|first3=C|class=physics.optics|year=2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;   For frequencies in the upper GHz and lower THz range, the absorption rate is as high as 50–100% due to voltage bias and/or doping.&lt;ref name=&quot;Graphene properties&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;/&gt;

Ultra-light [[carbon nanotube]]s meshed through [[molecular manufacturing]] techniques have densities between 1.3 g/m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; to 1.4 g/m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;. By the time a civilization is ready to use this technology, the [[carbon nanotube]]'s manufacturing might be optimised enough for them to have a density lower than the necessary 0.7 g/m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, and the average sail density with [[rigging]] might be kept to 0.3 g/m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; (a &quot;[[Solar sail#Investigated sail designs|spin stabilized]]&quot; light sail requires minimal additional mass in [[rigging]]). If such a sail could be constructed at this [[areal density]], a [[space habitat]] the size of the [[L5 Society]]'s proposed [[O'Neill cylinder]]—500&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, with room for over 1 million inhabitants, massing 3{{e|6}} [[ton]]s—could be supported by a circular light sail 3,000&amp;nbsp;km in diameter, with a combined sail/habitat mass of 5.4{{e|9}} kg.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://thespacereview.com/article/317/1| title=The Space Review: The high risk frontier | first=Sam| last=Dinkin| publisher=Thespacereview.com| year=2006| accessdate=2006-03-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; For comparison, this is just slightly smaller than the diameter of [[Jupiter]]'s moon [[Europa (moon)|Europa]] (although the sail is a flat disc, not a sphere), or the distance between [[San Francisco]] and [[Kansas City, Missouri|Kansas City]]. Such a structure would, however, have a mass quite a lot less than many asteroids. Although the construction of such a massive habitable statite would be a gigantic undertaking, and the required material science behind it is early stage, there are other engineering feats and required materials proposed in other Dyson sphere variants.

In theory, if enough satellites were created and deployed around their star, they would compose a non-rigid version of the Dyson shell mentioned below. Such a shell would not suffer from the drawbacks of massive compressive pressure, nor are the mass requirements of such a shell as high as the rigid form. Such a shell would, however, have the same optical and thermal properties as the rigid form, and would be detected by searchers in a similar fashion (see [[#Search for extra-terrestrial intelligence|below]]).

=== Dyson shell ===
[[Image:Dyson Sphere Diagram-en.svg|thumb|A cut-away diagram of an idealized Dyson shell, a variant on Dyson's original concept, with a radius of 1 [[Astronomical unit|AU]]]]
The variant of the Dyson sphere most often [[Dyson spheres in fiction|depicted in fiction]] is the &quot;Dyson shell&quot;: a uniform solid shell of matter around the star.&lt;ref name=&quot;what&quot;/&gt; Such a structure would completely alter the emissions of the central star, and would intercept 100% of the star's energy output. Such a structure would also provide an immense surface that many envision would be used for habitation, if the surface could be made habitable.

A spherical shell Dyson sphere in the Solar System with a radius of one [[astronomical unit]], so that the interior surface would receive the same amount of sunlight as Earth does per unit [[solid angle]], would have a surface area of approximately {{convert|2.8e17|sqkm|sqmi|abbr=on}}, or about 550 million times the surface area of Earth. This would intercept the full 384.6 [[yotta]][[watt]]s (3.846 × 10&lt;sup&gt;26&lt;/sup&gt; watts)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nssdc.gsfc.nasa.gov/planetary/factsheet/sunfact.html|title=NASA Sun Fact Sheet|accessdate=2011-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; of the Sun's output. Non-shell designs would intercept less, but the shell variant represents the maximum possible energy captured for the Solar System at this point of the Sun's [[stellar evolution|evolution]].&lt;ref name=&quot;what&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.nada.kth.se/~asa/dysonFAQ.html#WHAT| title= Dyson FAQ: What is a Dyson Sphere? | accessdate=2007-07-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is approximately 33 [[10^18|trillion]] times the power consumption of humanity in 1998, which was 12 terawatts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.inference.phy.cam.ac.uk/sustainable/oomm.html|title=Order of Magnitude Morality|accessdate=2007-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are several serious theoretical difficulties with the solid shell variant of the Dyson sphere:

Such a shell would have no net gravitational interaction with its englobed star (see [[shell theorem]]), and could drift in relation to the central star. If such movements went uncorrected, they could eventually result in a collision between the sphere and the star—most likely with disastrous results. Such structures would need either some form of propulsion to counteract any drift, or some way to repel the surface of the sphere away from the star.&lt;ref name=&quot;stable&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nada.kth.se/~asa/dysonFAQ.html#STABLE|title=Dyson Sphere FAQ: Is a Dyson sphere stable?|accessdate=2007-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For the same reason, such a shell would have no net gravitational interaction with anything else inside it. The contents of any biosphere placed on the inner surface of a Dyson shell would not be attracted to the sphere's surface and would simply fall into the star. It has been proposed that a biosphere could be contained between two concentric spheres, placed on the interior of a rotating sphere (in which case, the force of artificial &quot;gravity&quot; is perpendicular to the axis of rotation, causing all matter placed on the interior of the sphere to pool around the equator, effectively rendering the sphere a [[Niven ring]] for purposes of habitation, but still fully effective as a radiant-energy collector) or placed on the outside of the sphere where it would be held in place by the star's gravity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Todd|last=Drashner|author2=Steve Bowers |author3=Mike Parisi |author4=M. Alan Kazlev |url=http://www.orionsarm.com/civ/Dyson_Spheres.html|title=Dyson Sphere|work=Orion's Arm|accessdate=2007-10-07|archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20071007231438/http://www.orionsarm.com/civ/Dyson_Spheres.html |archivedate = October 7, 2007|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Viorel|last=Badescu|author2=Richard B. Cathcart|url=http://www.astronomytoday.com/exploration/solartravel.html|title=Space travel with solar power and a dyson sphere|work=Astronomy Today|accessdate=2007-10-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; In such cases, some form of illumination would have to be devised, or the sphere made at least partly transparent, because the star's light would otherwise be completely hidden.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aliens.monstrous.com/fermi_conclusions.htm |title=Fermi Conclusions |accessdate=2007-10-06 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070923204726/http://aliens.monstrous.com/fermi_conclusions.htm |archivedate=2007-09-23 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

If assuming a radius of 1- [[Astronomical unit|AU]], then the compressive strength of the material forming the sphere would have to be immense to prevent implosion due to the star's gravity. Any arbitrarily selected point on the surface of the sphere can be viewed as being under the pressure of the base of a dome 1 AU in height under the Sun's gravity at that distance. Indeed, it can be viewed as being at the base of an infinite number of arbitrarily selected domes, but because much of the force from any one arbitrary dome is counteracted by those of another, the net force on that point is immense, but finite. No known or theorized material is strong enough to withstand this pressure, and form a rigid, static sphere around a star.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.nada.kth.se/~asa/dysonFAQ.html#STRENGTH| title= Dyson FAQ: How strong does a rigid Dyson shell need to be? | accessdate=2006-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has been proposed by [[Paul Birch (writer)|Paul Birch]] (in relation to smaller &quot;Supra-Jupiter&quot; constructions around a large planet rather than a star) that it may be possible to support a Dyson shell by dynamic means similar to those used in a [[space fountain]].&lt;ref&gt;Search [https://archive.org/web/web.php WaybackMachine] for the 14th of June 2011 copy of  &lt;nowiki&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.paulbirch.net/SupramundanePlanets.zip |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2006-03-02 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060627074700/http://www.paulbirch.net/SupramundanePlanets.zip |archivedate=2006-06-27 }}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; Masses travelling in circular tracks on the inside of the sphere, at velocities significantly greater than orbital velocity, would press outwards on [[magnetic bearing]]s due to [[centrifugal force]]. For a Dyson shell of 1-AU radius around a star with the same mass as the Sun, a mass travelling ten times the orbital velocity (297.9&amp;nbsp;km/s) would support 99 (a=v&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;/r) times its own mass in additional shell structure.

Also if assuming a radius of one AU, then there may not be sufficient building material in the Solar System to construct a Dyson shell. [[Anders Sandberg]] estimates that there is 1.82{{e|26}} kg of easily usable building material in the Solar System, enough for a 1-AU shell with a mass of 600&amp;nbsp;kg/m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;—about 8–20&amp;nbsp;cm thick on average, depending on the density of the material. This includes the hard-to-access cores of the gas giants; the inner planets alone provide only 11.79{{e|24}} kg, enough for a 1-AU shell with a mass of just 42&amp;nbsp;kg/m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;ref name=&quot;FAQ enough&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.nada.kth.se/~asa/dysonFAQ.html#ENOUGH| title= Is there enough matter in the Solar System to build a Dyson shell?| work=Dyson Sphere FAQ| first=Anders| last= Sandberg| accessdate=2006-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The shell would be vulnerable to impacts from interstellar bodies, such as [[comet]]s, [[meteoroid]]s, and material in [[interstellar space]] that is currently being deflected by the Sun's [[bow shock]]. The [[heliosphere]], and any protection it theoretically provides, would cease to exist.

=== Other types ===

==== Dyson net ====
Another possibility is the &quot;Dyson net&quot;, a web of cables strung about the star that could have power or heat collection units strung between the cables. The Dyson net reduces to a special case of Dyson shell or bubble, however, depending on how the cables are supported against the sun's gravity.

==== Bubbleworld ====
A bubbleworld is an artificial construct that consists of a shell of living space around a sphere of hydrogen gas. The shell contains air, people, houses, furniture, etc. The idea was conceived to answer the question, &quot;What is the largest space colony that can be built?&quot;&lt;ref name = &quot;tuwyau&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.nada.kth.se/~asa/dysonFAQ.html#OTHER| title= Other Dyson Sphere-Like Concepts| work=Dyson Sphere FAQ| first=Anders| last= Sandberg| accessdate=2006-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, most of the volume is not habitable and there is no power source.

Theoretically, any [[gas giant]] could be enclosed in a solid shell; at a certain radius the surface gravity would be terrestrial, and energy could be provided by tapping the thermal energy of the planet.&lt;ref name = &quot;tuwyau&quot;/&gt; This concept is explored peripherally in the novel ''[[Accelerando (book)|Accelerando]]'' (and the short story ''Curator'', which is incorporated into the novel as a chapter) by [[Charles Stross]], in which [[Saturn]] is converted into a human-habitable world.

==== Stellar engine ====
[[Stellar engine]]s are a class of hypothetical [[megastructure]]s whose purpose is to extract useful energy from a star, sometimes for specific purposes. For example, [[Matrioshka brain]]s extract energy for purposes of computation; [[Stellar engine#Class A (Shkadov thruster)|Shkadov thrusters]] extract energy for purposes of propulsion. Some of the proposed stellar engine designs are based on the Dyson sphere.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.daviddarling.info/encyclopedia/S/stellar_engine.html|title=Stellar engine|encyclopedia=The Internet Encyclopedia of Science|accessdate=2007-10-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[black hole]] could be the power source instead of a star in order to increase the matter-to-energy conversion efficiency. A black hole would also be smaller than a star. This would decrease communication distances that would be important for computer-based societies as those described above.&lt;ref name = &quot;tuwyau&quot;/&gt;

== Search for megastructures ==
In Dyson's original paper, he speculated that sufficiently advanced extraterrestrial civilizations would likely follow a similar power-consumption pattern to that of humans, and would eventually build their own sphere of collectors. Constructing such a system would make such a civilization a Type II [[Kardashev scale|Kardashev civilization]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Nikolai Kardashev|Kardashev, Nikolai]]. &quot;[http://articles.adsabs.harvard.edu/cgi-bin/nph-iarticle_query?1985IAUS..112..497K On the Inevitability and the Possible Structures of Supercivilizations]&quot;, The search for extraterrestrial life: Recent developments; Proceedings of the Symposium, Boston, MA, June 18–21, 1984 (A86-38126 17–88). Dordrecht, D. Reidel Publishing Co., 1985, p. 497–504.&lt;/ref&gt;

The existence of such a system of collectors would alter the light emitted from the star system. Collectors would absorb and reradiate energy from the star.&lt;ref name=&quot;search&quot;/&gt; The wavelength(s) of radiation emitted by the collectors would be determined by the [[emission spectrum|emission spectra]] of the substances making them up, and the temperature of the collectors. Because it seems most likely that these collectors would be made up of heavy elements not normally found in the emission spectra of their central star—or at least not radiating light at such relatively &quot;low&quot; energies compared to what they would be emitting as energetic free nuclei in the [[stellar atmosphere]]—there would be atypical wavelengths of light for the star's [[spectral type]] in the light spectrum emitted by the star system. If the percentage of the star's output thus filtered or transformed by this absorption and reradiation was significant, it could be detected at interstellar distances.&lt;ref name=&quot;search&quot;/&gt;

Given the amount of energy available per square meter at a distance of 1 [[Astronomical unit|AU]] from the [[Sun]], it is possible to calculate that most known substances would be reradiating energy in the [[infrared]] part of the [[electromagnetic spectrum]]. Thus, a Dyson sphere, constructed by life forms not dissimilar to humans, who dwelled in proximity to a [[Solar analog|Sun-like star]], made with materials similar to those available to humans, would most likely cause an increase in the amount of infrared radiation in the star system's emitted spectrum. Hence, Dyson selected the title &quot;Search for Artificial Stellar Sources of Infrared Radiation&quot; for his published paper.&lt;ref name=&quot;search&quot;/&gt;

[[SETI]] has adopted these assumptions in their search, looking for such &quot;infrared heavy&quot; spectra from [[solar analog]]s. {{As of|2005}} [[Fermilab]] has an ongoing survey for such spectra by analyzing data from the [[IRAS|Infrared Astronomical Satellite (IRAS)]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://home.fnal.gov/~carrigan/infrared_astronomy/Fermilab_search.htm| title=Fermilab Dyson Sphere search program| year=2006| accessdate=2006-03-02| first=D.| last=Carrigan| archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060306222359/http://home.fnal.gov/~carrigan/Infrared_Astronomy/Fermilab_search.htm| archive-date=2006-03-06| url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Full citation needed|date=January 2016}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Shostak |first=Seth |date=Spring 2009 |journal=Engineering &amp; Science |title=When Will We Find the Extraterrestrials? |volume=72 |number=1 |pages=12–21 |issn=0013-7812 |url=http://archive.seti.org/pdfs/Shostak-spring2009-EnS.pdf &lt;!-- permalink to official source with abstract &amp; alternate PDF link: http://resolver.caltech.edu/CaltechES:72.1.Extraterrestrials --&gt; |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150415115307/http://archive.seti.org/pdfs/Shostak-spring2009-EnS.pdf |archivedate=2015-04-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Identifying one of the many infrared sources as a Dyson sphere would require improved techniques for discriminating between a Dyson sphere and natural sources.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=''Dyson sphere'' at Scholarpedia|journal=Scholarpedia|volume=4|issue=5|pages=6647|doi=10.4249/scholarpedia.6647|date=2009-05-15|last1=Carrigan|first1=Richard|last2=Dyson|first2=Freeman J.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fermilab discovered 17 potential &quot;ambiguous&quot; candidates, of which four have been named &quot;amusing but still questionable&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://home.fnal.gov/~carrigan/Infrared_Astronomy/Fermilab_search.htm| title=Fermilab Dyson Sphere search program| year=2012| accessdate=2012-01-15| first=D.| last=Carrigan| archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060306222359/http://home.fnal.gov/~carrigan/Infrared_Astronomy/Fermilab_search.htm| archive-date=2006-03-06| url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Full citation needed|date=January 2016}} Other searches also resulted in several candidates, which are, however, unconfirmed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Dick Carrigan |url=http://home.fnal.gov/~carrigan/infrared_astronomy/Other_searches.htm |title=Dyson Sphere Searches |publisher=Home.fnal.gov |date=2010-12-16 |accessdate=2012-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/alien-supercivilizations-absent-from-100-000-nearby-galaxies|title=Alien Supercivilizations Absent from 100,000 Nearby Galaxies|first=Lee|last=Billings|publisher=|accessdate=31 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;econ2015&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal
| title = Infra digging: Looking for aliens: The search for extraterrestrials goes intergalactic
| journal = The Economist
| date = 2015-04-18
| accessdate = 2015-04-19
| url = https://www.economist.com/news/science-and-technology/21648607-search-extraterrestrials-goes-intergalactic-infra-digging
| quote = Fifty [galaxies] were red enough to be hosting aliens gobbling up half or more of their starlight.
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Postulated explanations===
On 14 October 2015, [[Planet Hunters]]' citizen scientists discovered unusual light fluctuations of the star [[KIC 8462852]], captured by the [[Kepler Space Telescope]]. The star was nicknamed &quot;Tabby's Star&quot; after [[Tabetha S. Boyajian]] — the initial study's lead author. The phenomenon raised speculation that a Dyson sphere may have been discovered.&lt;ref name=&quot;ATL-20151013&quot;&gt;{{cite web| last1=Andersen| first1=Ross| title=The Most Mysterious Star in Our Galaxy| url=https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2015/10/the-most-interesting-star-in-our-galaxy/410023/ |date=13 October 2015 |work=[[The Atlantic]]| accessdate=13 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;IND-20151015&quot;&gt;{{cite web| last1=Williams| first1=Lee| title=Astronomers may have found giant alien 'megastructures' orbiting star near the Milky Way| url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/forget-water-on-mars-astronomers-may-have-just-found-giant-alien-megastructures-orbiting-a-star-near-a6693886.html |date=15 October 2015 |work=[[The Independent]]| accessdate=15 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In February 2016, Boyajian gave a [[TED (Conference)|TED talk]] where she explained the story of how her research on the star quickly took a turn into the mysterious. However, she was skeptical and in the talk she reminded everyone that skepticism is the best policy whenever delving into alien territory. Her exact quote is as follows:

{{quote|Extraordinary claims require extraordinary evidence, and it is my job, my responsibility, as an astronomer to remind people that alien hypotheses should always be a last resort.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Most Mysterious Star in the Universe |url=https://www.ted.com/talks/tabetha_boyajian_the_most_mysterious_star_in_the_universe |date= February 2016 |work= [[TED (Conference)]] |accessdate=2 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Wanting to understand the strange light pattern, [[Tabetha S. Boyajian]] put several hypotheses to the test. The first general assumption was an exoplanet [[Transit (astronomy)|transiting]] (eclipsing) its massive star, but the dips in light lasted between 5 and 80 days and were erratically spaced apart, thus ruling out any kind of an orbit for one celestial object.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|arxiv=1509.03622 |last1=Boyajian |first1=T. S |title=Planet Hunters X. KIC 8462852 - Where's the Flux? |journal=Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society |volume=457 |issue=4 |pages=3988 |last2=LaCourse |first2=D. M |last3=Rappaport |first3=S. A |last4=Fabrycky |first4=D |last5=Fischer |first5=D. A |last6=Gandolfi |first6=D |last7=Kennedy |first7=G. M |last8=Korhonen |first8=H |last9=Liu |first9=M. C |last10=Moor |first10=A |last11=Olah |first11=K |last12=Vida |first12=K |last13=Wyatt |first13=M. C |last14=Best |first14=W. M. J |last15=Brewer |first15=J |last16=Ciesla |first16=F |last17=Csak |first17=B |last18=Deeg |first18=H. J |last19=Dupuy |first19=T. J |last20=Handler |first20=G |last21=Heng |first21=K |last22=Howell |first22=S. B |last23=Ishikawa |first23=S. T |last24=Kovacs |first24=J |last25=Kozakis |first25=T |last26=Kriskovics |first26=L |last27=Lehtinen |first27=J |last28=Lintott |first28=C |last29=Lynn |first29=S |last30=Nespral |first30=D |display-authors=29 |year=2015 |doi=10.1093/mnras/stw218 |bibcode=2016MNRAS.457.3988B }}&lt;/ref&gt;
A dust cloud was proposed but the star showed no signs of being young so a dust cloud was highly improbable. Lastly, a comet shower was hypothesized. However, as Boyajian pointed out in her TED talk this was also highly improbable. 
&quot;It would take hundreds of comets to reproduce what we're observing. And these are only the comets that happen to pass between us and the star. And so in reality, we're talking thousands to tens of thousands of comets.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Most Mysterious Star in the Universe |url=https://www.ted.com/talks/tabetha_boyajian_the_most_mysterious_star_in_the_universe/transcript#t-429568 |date= February 2016 |work= [[TED (Conference)]] |accessdate=3 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

So after all the natural explanations turned up weak, her team decided to send off their research to SETI ([[Search for extraterrestrial life]]) to rule out alien structures. After reviewing the research, the [[SETI Institute]] was so intrigued that they decided to study the star themselves and pointed their [[Allen Telescope Array]] (ATA) at the star &quot;with hopes of catching a tell-tale signal that might reveal a technological civilization.&quot;&lt;ref name='SETI 2017'&gt;{{cite web|title=What's Up with Tabby's Star? |url=https://www.seti.org/whats-up-with-tabby-star | date=23 May 2017 | work= [[Search for extraterrestrial life]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[SETI Institute]] mentioned that what caught their interest was that &quot;the timing of the present dip (in light) suggests that whatever this material is, it is situated at just the right distance from the star to be in the [[Circumstellar habitable zone|habitable zone]], where we believe life like ours could develop as it has on Earth.&quot;&lt;ref name='SETI 2017'/&gt;

Being skeptical as Boyajian was, she finally decided to take SETI's approach and allow herself to have a bit of fun in hypothesizing what the light pattern could have been. In her Ted Talk she joked: &quot;Another idea that's one of my personal favorites is that we had just witnessed an interplanetary space battle and the catastrophic destruction of a planet. Now, I admit that this would produce a lot of dust that we don't observe. But if we're already invoking aliens in this explanation, then who is to say they didn't efficiently clean up all this mess for recycling purposes?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Most Mysterious Star in the Universe| url=https://www.ted.com/talks/tabetha_boyajian_the_most_mysterious_star_in_the_universe/transcript |date= February 2016|work= [[TED (Conference)]] |accessdate=2 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The search for answers to [[KIC 8462852]] is still ongoing.

On August 25, 2016, a similar phenomenon was reported for another stellar object: [[EPIC 204278916]],&lt;ref name='EPIC'&gt;{{cite journal|title=The peculiar dipping events in the disk-bearing young-stellar object EPIC 204278916|journal=Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society|volume=463|issue=2|pages=2265|arxiv=1608.07291|bibcode = 2016MNRAS.463.2265S |doi = 10.1093/mnras/stw2155 |year=2016|last1=Scaringi|first1=S|last2=Manara|first2=C. F|last3=Barenfeld|first3=S. A|last4=Groot|first4=P. J|last5=Isella|first5=A|last6=Kenworthy|first6=M. A|last7=Knigge|first7=C|last8=MacCarone|first8=T. J|last9=Ricci|first9=L|last10=Ansdell|first10=M}}&lt;/ref&gt; a young M-type pre-main-sequence star with a resolved disk. Dimmings of up to 65% for 25 consecutive days (out of 79 total observation) were observed. The variability is highly periodic and attributed to stellar rotation.&lt;ref name='EPIC'/&gt; The researchers hypothesize that the irregular dimmings are caused by either a warped inner-disk edge or transiting cometary-like objects in either circular or eccentric orbits.&lt;ref name='EPIC'/&gt;

== Fiction ==
{{main|Dyson spheres in popular culture}}
&lt;!-- PLEASE DO NOT ADD SPECIFIC EXAMPLES OF THE DYSON SPHERE IN FICTION TO THIS SECTION. YOU ARE MORE THAN WELCOME TO ADD SUCH EXAMPLES TO THE ARTICLE 'DYSON SPHERES IN FICTION', WHICH WAS CREATED FOR THAT PURPOSE. THANK YOU. --&gt;
The Dyson sphere originated in fiction,&lt;ref&gt;[[Olaf Stapledon]]. ''[[Star Maker]]''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[J. D. Bernal]], [http://www.quarkweb.com/foyle/WorldFleshDevil.pdf ''The World, the Flesh &amp; the Devil: An Enquiry into the Future of the Three Enemies of the Rational Soul'']&lt;/ref&gt; and it is a concept that has appeared often in [[science fiction]] since then. In fictional accounts, Dyson spheres are most often depicted as a ''Dyson shell'' with the gravitational and engineering difficulties of this variant noted above largely ignored.&lt;ref name=&quot;what&quot;/&gt;
&lt;!-- PLEASE DO NOT ADD SPECIFIC EXAMPLES OF THE DYSON SPHERE IN FICTION TO THIS SECTION. YOU ARE MORE THAN WELCOME TO ADD SUCH EXAMPLES TO THE ARTICLE 'DYSON SPHERES IN FICTION', WHICH WAS CREATED FOR THAT PURPOSE. THANK YOU. --&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Science Fiction}}
{{div col}}
* {{annotated link|Alderson disk}}
* {{annotated link|Dyson spheres in popular culture}}
* {{annotated link|Globus Cassus}}
* {{annotated link|Kardashev scale}}
* {{annotated link|Klemperer rosette}}
* {{annotated link|Matrioshka brain}}
* {{annotated link|Megascale engineering}}
* {{annotated link|Planetary engineering}}
* {{annotated link|Ringworld}}
* {{annotated link|Star lifting}}
* {{annotated link|Stellar engineering}}
* {{annotated link|Tensegrity}}
* {{annotated link|Terraforming}}
{{div col end}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
{{Wiktionary|Dyson sphere}}
{{Commons category|Dyson sphere}}
{{Spoken Wikipedia|Dyson Sphere.ogg|2012-05-07}}
* [http://www.nada.kth.se/~asa/dysonFAQ.html Dyson sphere FAQ]
* [http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?DysonSphere Dyson sphere]
* [http://burtleburtle.net/bob/scifi/dyson.html Toroidal Dyson swarms simulations using Java applets]
* [http://iopscience.iop.org/0004-637X/698/2/2075/pdf/0004-637X_698_2_2075.pdf FermiLab: IRAS-based whole sky upper limit on Dyson spheres], with a notable appendix on Dyson sphere engineering
{{Memory Alpha|Dyson sphere}}
* {{tvtropes|DysonSphere}}

{{Space stations}}
{{good article}}

{{Use American English|date=January 2014}}

[[Category:Freeman Dyson|Sphere]]
[[Category:Astronomy projects]]
[[Category:Exploratory engineering]]
[[Category:History of science]]
[[Category:Hypothetical astronomical objects]]
[[Category:Hypothetical technology]]
[[Category:Megastructures]]
[[Category:Philosophy of science]]
[[Category:Philosophy of technology]]
[[Category:Energy development]]
[[Category:Solar power]]
[[Category:Proposed space stations]]
[[Category:Science fiction themes]]
[[Category:Search for extraterrestrial intelligence]]
[[Category:Space colonization]]
[[Category:Thought experiments]]</text>
      <sha1>tbneuxw5jonjwg6oqxflu3l3dp6zgbs</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
