  <page>
    <title>Damascus steel</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8593</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942833541</id>
      <parentid>937266833</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T03:34:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>70.54.134.81</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>removed a link to the page and section the link was in (why would you do this)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About||Damascus Twist barrels|Skelp|the
album of the same name|Damascus Steel (album)|Operation Damascus Steel|Rif Dimashq offensive (February–April 2018)}}

[[File:Watered pattern on sword blade1.Iran.JPG|thumb|300px|Close-up of a 13th-century Persian-forged Damascus steel sword]]
'''Damascus steel''' was the forged [[steel]] of the blades of swords smithed in the [[Near East]] from [[Ingot|ingots]] of [[Wootz steel]]&lt;ref name=pace/&gt; imported from [[Southern India]] and [[Tamraparni]]. These swords are characterized by distinctive patterns of banding and mottling reminiscent of flowing water, or in a &quot;ladder&quot; or &quot;teardrop&quot; pattern. Such blades were reputed to be tough, resistant to shattering, and capable of being honed to a sharp, resilient edge.&lt;ref name=Figiel&gt;{{cite book |last=Figiel |first=Leo S. |title=On Damascus Steel |publisher=Atlantis Arts Press |year=1991 |pages=10–11 |isbn= 978-0-9628711-0-8 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The steel is named after [[Damascus]], the capital city of [[Syria]] and one of the largest cities in the ancient [[Levant]]. It may either refer to swords made or sold in Damascus directly, or it may just refer to the aspect of the typical patterns, by comparison with  [[Damask]] fabrics (also named for Damascus).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Goddard |first=Wayne |title=The Wonder of Knifemaking |year=2000 |publisher=Krause Publications |location=Iola, WI |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=asN5YfC2_AcC&amp;pg=PA137 |pages=137–145 |isbn=978-0-87341-798-3  }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Williams&gt;{{cite book |last=Williams |first=Alan R. |title=The knight and the blast furnace: a history of the metallurgy of armour in the Middle Ages &amp; the early modern period |volume=12 |series=History of warfare |publisher=BRILL |location=Leiden |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=GpVbnsqAzxIC&amp;pg=PA11 |year= 2003 |pages=11–15 |isbn=978-90-04-12498-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The original method of producing Wootz steel is not known. Modern attempts to duplicate the metal have not been entirely successful due to differences in raw materials and manufacturing techniques. Several individuals in modern times have claimed that they have rediscovered the methods by which the original Damascus steel was produced.&lt;ref name=Verhoeven98&gt;{{Cite journal |first=J.D. |last=Verhoeven |first2=A.H. |last2=Pendray |last3=Dauksch |first3=W.E. | year=1998 | title=The key role of impurities in ancient damascus steel blades |doi=10.1007/s11837-998-0419-y |bibcode=1998JOM....50i..58V | journal=Journal of Metallurgy | volume=50 | issue=9 | page=58 | url= http://www.tms.org/pubs/journals/JOM/9809/Verhoeven-9809.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Wadsworth80/&gt;&lt;ref name=Verhoeven2016&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20180811042707/https://www.mse.iastate.edu/news/john-verhoeven/ John Verhoeven: Mystery of Damascus Steel Swords Unveiled]&lt;/ref&gt;

The reputation and history of Damascus steel has given rise to many legends, such as the ability to cut through a rifle barrel or to cut a hair falling across the blade.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Becker |first=Otto Matthew |title=High-speed steel: the development, nature, treatment, and use of high-speed steels, together with some suggestions as to the problems involved in their use |url=https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.33026 |publisher=McGraw-Hill |year= 1910 |location= New York |pages=10–14}}&lt;/ref&gt; A research team in [[Germany]] published a report in 2006 revealing [[nanowires]] and [[carbon nanotubes]] in a blade forged from Damascus steel.&lt;ref name=Reibold06&gt;{{cite journal |title=Materials: Carbon nanotubes in an ancient Damascus sabre |doi=10.1038/444286a |journal=Nature |year=2006 |last1=Reibold |first1=M. |last2=Paufler |first2=P. |last3=Levin |first3=A. A. |last4=Kochmann |first4=W. |last5=Pätzke |first5=N. |last6=Meyer |first6=D. C. |volume=444 |issue=7117 |pages=286 |pmid=17108950 |bibcode=2006Natur.444..286R |lay-url=https://www.newscientist.com/article/dn10604-secrets-out-for-saracen-sabres/ |laysource=New Scientist}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=NatGeo06&gt;{{cite magazine |title=Legendary Swords' Sharpness, Strength From Nanotubes, Study Says |date=2010-10-28 |magazine=National Geographic |url=http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2006/11/061116-nanotech-swords.html |access-date=19 November 2006 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061118060943/http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2006/11/061116-nanotech-swords.html |archive-date=18 November 2006 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Fountain |first=Henry |date=2006-11-28 |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/28/science/28observ.html |title=Antique Nanotubes |work=New York Times |accessdate=2011-11-13 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Although many types of modern steel outperform ancient Damascus alloys, chemical reactions in the production process made the blades extraordinary for their time, as Damascus steel was [[superplasticity|superplastic]] and very hard at the same time. During the [[smelting]] process to obtain Wootz steel ingots, woody [[Biomass (ecology)|biomass]] and leaves are known to have been used as [[carburizing]] additives along with certain specific types of iron rich in [[Microalloyed steel|microalloying]] elements. These ingots would then be further forged and worked into Damascus steel blades. Research now shows that carbon nanotubes can be derived from plant fibers,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Goodell, B, Xie, X., Qian, Y., Daniel, G., Peterson, M., and J. Jellison |year= 2008 |title=Carbon nanotubes produced from natural cellulosic materials |journal= Journal of Nanoscience and Nanotechnology |volume= 8 |pages= 2472–4 |doi=10.1166/jnn.2008.235 |pmid=18572666}}&lt;/ref&gt; suggesting how the nanotubes were formed in the steel. Some experts expect to discover such nanotubes in more relics as they are analyzed more closely.&lt;ref name=NatGeo06/&gt;

==History==
{{see also|Wootz steel}}
[[File:Damascus bladesmith.jpg|thumb|A bladesmith from Damascus, c. 1900]]
Damascus blades were first manufactured in the [[Near East]] from [[ingot]]s of [[wootz steel]] that were imported from [[Southern India]] ([[Tamilakam]] present day [[Tamil Nadu]] and [[Kerala]])&lt;ref name=pace&gt;{{cite book |last=Pacey |first=Arnold |title=Technology in World Civilization: A Thousand-year History |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=X7e8rHL1lf4C&amp;pg=PA80 |year=1991 |publisher=MIT Press |isbn=978-0-262-66072-3 |page=80}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Tamraparni]] (ancient Sri Lanka).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |author=Juleff, G. |title=An ancient wind powered iron smelting technology in Sri Lanka |journal=Nature |volume=379 |page=60 |year=1996 |doi= 10.1038/379060a0 |issue=6560 |bibcode=1996Natur.379...60J}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Arabs introduced the wootz steel to Damascus, where a weapons industry thrived.&lt;ref name=&quot;SR_IISc&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author1= Sharada Srinivasan |author2= Srinivasa Ranganathan |title= India's Legendary Wootz Steel: An Advanced Material of the Ancient World |year= 2004 |publisher= National Institute of Advanced Studies |oclc= 82439861 |url= http://materials.iisc.ernet.in/~wootz/heritage/WOOTZ.htm |access-date= 2014-08-12 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20190211082829/http://materials.iisc.ernet.in/~wootz/heritage/WOOTZ.htm |archive-date= 2019-02-11 |url-status= dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; From the 3rd century to the 17th century, steel ingots were being shipped to the [[Middle East]] from India.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last= Sinopoli |first= Carla M. |title= The Political Economy of Craft Production: Crafting Empire in South India, c. 1350–1650 |publisher= Cambridge University Press |year= 2003 |page= 192 |isbn= 0-521-82613-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Loss of the technique===
Production of these patterned swords gradually declined, ceasing by around 1750. Some gunsmiths during the 18th and 19th century used this technique for gunbarrel but the technique ended in the 1900s. Several modern theories have ventured to explain this decline, including the breakdown of trade routes to supply the needed metals, the lack of trace impurities in the metals, the possible loss of knowledge on the crafting techniques through secrecy and lack of transmission, suppression of the industry in India by the [[British Raj]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last= Burton |first= Sir Richard Francis |authorlink= Richard Francis Burton |date= 1884 |title= The Book of the Sword |url= https://archive.org/details/booksword00unkngoog/page/n152 |publisher= Chatto and Windus |location= London |page=111 |isbn= 1605204366 }}&lt;/ref&gt; or a combination of all the above.&lt;ref name=Verhoeven98/&gt;&lt;ref name=Wadsworth80 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Milgrom09&gt;{{cite web |last=Milgrom |first=Lionel |title=Carbon nanotubes: Saladin's secret weapon |url=http://www.rsc.org/chemistryworld/News/2006/November/15110602.asp |date=15 November 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The original [[wootz steel|wootz]] was imported to Damascus, where Middle Eastern bladesmiths forged them into swords.&lt;ref name=Verhoeven98/&gt;&lt;ref name=Wadsworth80 /&gt; Due to the distance of trade for this steel, a sufficiently lengthy disruption of the trade routes could have ended the production of Damascus steel and eventually led to the loss of the technique. As well, the need for key trace impurities of [[tungsten]] or [[vanadium]] within the materials needed for the production of the steel may be absent if this material was acquired from different production regions or smelted from ores lacking these key trace elements.&lt;ref name=Verhoeven98/&gt; The technique for controlled thermal cycling after the initial forging at a specific temperature could also have been lost, thereby preventing the final damask pattern in the steel from occurring.&lt;ref name=Verhoeven98/&gt;&lt;ref name=Wadsworth80 /&gt;

The discovery of [[carbon nanotube]]s in the Damascus steel's composition supports this hypothesis, since the precipitation of carbon nanotubes probably resulted from a specific process that may be difficult to replicate should the production technique or raw materials used be significantly altered.&lt;ref name=Milgrom09/&gt;

== Reproduction ==
Recreating Damascus steel has been attempted by archaeologists using [[experimental archaeology]]. Many have attempted to discover or [[Reverse engineering|reverse-engineer]] the process by which it was made.

=== Moran: billet welding ===
[[File:DamaszenerKlinge crop.jpg|thumb|upright=1.0|Pattern on modern &quot;Damascus knife&quot;]]
Since the well-known technique of [[pattern welding]] - the forge-welding of a blade from several differing pieces - produced surface patterns similar to those found on Damascus blades, some modern blacksmiths were erroneously led to believe that the original Damascus blades were made using this technique. However today, the difference between wootz steel and pattern welding is fully documented and well understood.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Maryon |first=Herbert |author-link=Herbert Maryon |date=1948 |title=A Sword of the Nydam Type from Ely Fields Farm, near Ely |journal=Proceedings of the Cambridge Antiquarian Society |volume=XLI |pages=73–76 |doi=10.5284/1034398 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Maryon |first=Herbert |author-link=Herbert Maryon |date=February 1960 |title=Pattern-Welding and Damascening of Sword-Blades—Part 1: Pattern-Welding |journal=Studies in Conservation |volume=5 |issue=1 |pages=25–37 |doi=10.2307/1505063 |jstor=1505063 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Maryon |first=Herbert |author-link=Herbert Maryon |date=May 1960 |title=Pattern-Welding and Damascening of Sword-Blades—Part 2: The Damascene Process |journal=Studies in Conservation |volume=5 |issue=2 |pages=52–60 |doi=10.2307/1504953 |jstor=1504953 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Pattern-welded steel has been referred to as &quot;Damascus steel&quot; since 1973 when [[Bladesmith]] [[William F. Moran]] unveiled his &quot;Damascus knives&quot; at the [[Knifemakers' Guild]] Show.&lt;ref name=&quot;GD&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Lewis |first=Jack |authorlink=Jack Lewis (screenwriter) |author2=Roger Combs |title=Gun digest book of knives |publisher=DBI |year=1992 |pages=58–64 |isbn=978-0-87349-129-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=taotk&gt;{{cite book |last=Kertzman |first=Joe  |title=Art of the Knife |publisher=Krause Publications |year=2007  |pages=224–6 |isbn=978-0-89689-470-9  }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

This &quot;Modern Damascus&quot; is made from several types of steel and iron slices [[welded]] together to form a [[billet (semi-finished product)]], and currently, the term &quot;Damascus&quot; (although technically incorrect) is widely accepted to describe modern pattern-welded steel blades in the trade.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Loveless |first=Robert|authorlink=Bob Loveless |first2=Richard |last2=Barney |title=How to Make Knives  |origyear=1977 |year=1995 |publisher=Knife World Publications |page=169 |isbn=0-695-80913-X }}&lt;/ref&gt; The patterns vary depending on how the smith works the billet.&lt;ref name=taotk/&gt; The billet is drawn out and folded until the desired number of layers are formed.&lt;ref name=taotk/&gt;  To attain a Master Smith rating with the [[American Bladesmith Society]] that Moran founded, the smith must forge a Damascus blade with a minimum of 300 layers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=ABS Testing Rules and Guidelines for the Master Smith Rating |url=http://www.americanbladesmith.com/uploads/file/Testing/MS%20Test%20FINAL%204-24-2010.pdf |format=PDF |accessdate=2011-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Verhoeven and Pendray: crucible ===
J. D. Verhoeven and A. H. Pendray published an article on their attempts to reproduce the elemental, structural, and visual characteristics of Damascus steel.&lt;ref name=Verhoeven98/&gt; They started with a cake of steel that matched the properties of the original [[wootz]] steel from India, which also matched a number of original Damascus swords that Verhoeven and Pendray had access to. The wootz was in a soft, [[Annealing (metallurgy)|annealed]] state, with a grain structure and beads of pure [[iron carbide]], which resulted from its [[Eutectoid|hypereutectoid]] state. Verhoeven and Pendray had already determined that the grains on the surface of the steel were grains of iron carbide—their goal was to reproduce the iron carbide patterns they saw in the Damascus blades from the grains in the wootz.

Although such material could be worked at low temperatures to produce the striated Damascene pattern of intermixed [[Allotropes of iron|ferrite]] and [[cementite]] bands in a manner identical to pattern-welded Damascus steel, any heat treatment sufficient to dissolve the carbides would permanently destroy the pattern. However, Verhoeven and Pendray discovered that in samples of true Damascus steel, the Damascene pattern could be recovered by aging at a moderate temperature. They found that certain carbide forming elements, one of which was vanadium, did not disperse until the steel reached higher temperatures than those needed to dissolve the carbides. Therefore, a high heat treatment could remove the visual evidence of patterning associated with carbides but did not remove the underlying patterning of the carbide forming elements; a subsequent lower-temperature heat treatment, at a temperature at which the carbides were again stable, could recover the structure by the binding of carbon by those elements.

=== Anosov, Wadsworth and Sherby: bulat ===
In Russia, chronicles record the use of a material known as [[bulat steel]] to make highly valued weapons, including swords, knives, and axes. Tsar [[Michael of Russia]] reportedly had a bulat helmet made for him in 1621. The exact origin or the manufacturing process of the bulat is unknown, but it was likely imported to Russia via Persia and Turkestan, and it was similar and possibly the same as Damascus steel. Pavel Petrovich Anosov made several attempts to reproduce the process in the mid-19th century. Wadsworth and Sherby also researched &lt;ref name=Wadsworth80&gt;{{cite journal |first=Jeffrey |last=Wadsworth |first2=Oleg D. |last2=Sherby |title=On the Bulat – Damascus Steel Revisited |journal=Prog. Mater. Sci. |doi=10.1016/0079-6425(80)90014-6 |volume=25 |issue=1 |pages=35–68 |year=1980}}&lt;/ref&gt; the reproduction of bulat steel and published their results in 1980.
[[File:Kristallstruktur Zementit.png|thumb|Cementite crystal structure. Iron atoms are in blue, carbon atoms are  in black.]]

=== Additional research ===
A team of researchers based at the [[Technische Universität Dresden|Technical University of Dresden]] that used [[x-ray]]s and [[electron microscopy]] to examine Damascus steel discovered the presence of [[cementite]] [[nanowires]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |first=W. |last=Kochmann |year=2004 |title=Nanowires in ancient Damascus steel |journal=Journal of Alloys and Compounds |volume=372 |pages=L15–L19 |doi=10.1016/j.jallcom.2003.10.005 |issn=0925-8388 |last2=Reibold |first2=Marianne |last3=Goldberg |first3=Rolf |last4=Hauffe |first4=Wolfgang |last5=Levin |first5=Alexander A |last6=Meyer |first6=Dirk C |last7=Stephan |first7=Thurid |last8=Müller |first8=Heide |last9=Belger |first9=André |last10=Paufler |first10=Peter}}&lt;br&gt;{{Cite journal |first=A. A. |last=Levin |year=2005 |title=Microstructure of a genuine Damascus sabre |journal=Crystal Research and Technology |volume=40 |issue=9 |pages=905–916 |doi=10.1002/crat.200410456 |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060315222306/http://www.crystalresearch.com/crt/ab40/905_a.pdf |format=PDF |last2=Meyer |first2=D. C. |last3=Reibold |first3=M. |last4=Kochmann |first4=W. |last5=Pätzke |first5=N. |last6=Paufler |first6=P.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[carbon nanotube]]s.&lt;ref name=Reibold06/&gt; Peter Paufler, a member of the Dresden team, says that these nanostructures are a result of the forging process.&lt;ref name=NatGeo06/&gt;&lt;ref name=Sanderson06/&gt;

Sanderson proposes that the process of forging and [[Annealing (metallurgy)|annealing]] accounts for the nano-scale structures.&lt;ref name=Sanderson06&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Sanderson |first=K. |title=Sharpest cut from nanotube sword |journal=Nature |volume=444 |year=2006 |page=286 |doi=10.1038/news061113-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===In gunmaking===
Prior to the early 20th century, all shotgun barrels were forged by heating narrow strips of iron and steel and shaping them around a [[mandrel]].&lt;ref name=Simpson03&gt;{{Cite book |last=Simpson |first=Layne |title=Shotguns &amp; Shotgunning |publisher=Krause Publications |year=2003 |page=[https://archive.org/details/shotgunsshotgunn0000simp/page/256 256] |isbn=978-0-87349-567-7 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/shotgunsshotgunn0000simp/page/256 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Matunas03&gt;{{Cite book |last= Matunas |first=Edward A. |title=Do-It-Yourself Gun Repair |publisher=Woods N' Water |year=2003 |page=240 |isbn=978-0-9722804-2-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; This process was referred to as &quot;laminating&quot; or &quot;Damascus&quot;.&lt;ref name=Simpson03/&gt;&lt;ref name=Matunas03/&gt; These types of barrels earned a reputation for weakness and were never meant to be used with modern smokeless powder, or any kind of moderately powerful explosive.&lt;ref name=Matunas03/&gt; Because of the resemblance to Damascus steel, higher-end barrels were made by Belgian and British gun makers.&lt;ref name=Simpson03/&gt;&lt;ref name=Matunas03/&gt; These barrels are [[Proof test|proof marked]] and meant to be used with light pressure loads.&lt;ref name=Simpson03/&gt; Current gun manufacturers make slide assemblies and small parts such as triggers and safeties for [[Colt M1911]] pistols from powdered Swedish steel resulting in a swirling two-toned effect; these parts are often referred to as &quot;Stainless Damascus&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Hopkins |first=Cameron |title=Damascus Knight .45 |journal=American Handgunner Magazine |year=2000 |volume=20 |issue=4 |page=128 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Popular culture==
The exceptionally strong fictitious Valyrian steel mentioned in the television series ''[[Game of Thrones]]'', as well as [[George R. R. Martin|George R. R. Martin's]] book series ''[[A Song of Ice and Fire]]'', appears to have been inspired by Damascus steel, but with a magic twist.&lt;ref name=&quot;telegraph1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/tv/0/game-thrones-things-didnt-know/real-life-equivalent-valyrian-steel/|title=There's a real-life equivalent to Valyrian Steel|accessdate=19 September 2018|author=[[The Daily Telegraph]]|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20180919004701/https://www.telegraph.co.uk/tv/0/game-thrones-things-didnt-know/real-life-equivalent-valyrian-steel/|archivedate=19 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Just like Damascus/Wootz steel, Valyrian steel also seems to be a lost art from an ancient civilization. Unlike Damascus steel, however, Valyrian steel blades require no maintenance and cannot be damaged through normal combat.

==See also==
*[[Noric steel]]
*[[Bulat steel]]
*[[Wootz steel]]
*[[Tungsten carbide]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
*[http://www.tf.uni-kiel.de/matwis/amat/def_en/kap_5/advanced/t5_1_1.html &quot;Damascene Technique in Metal Working&quot;]
*{{cite journal |last=Verhoeven |first=J.D. |last2=Pendray |first2=A.H. |last3=Dauksch |first3=W.E. |title=The continuing study of damascus steel: Bars from the Alwar Armory |journal=JOM |date=September 2004 |volume=56 |number=9 |pages=17–20 |doi=10.1007/s11837-004-0193-4 |bibcode=2004JOM....56i..17V }}
*{{cite journal |first=J.D. |last=Verhoeven |title=Pattern Formation in Wootz Damascus Steel Swords and Blades |journal=Indian Journal of History of Science |volume=42 |issue=4 |pages=559–574 |year=2007 |format=PDF |url=http://insa.nic.in/writereaddata/UpLoadedFiles/IJHS/Vol42_4_2_JVerhoeven.pdf}}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20180811042707/https://www.mse.iastate.edu/news/john-verhoeven/ John Verhoeven: Mystery of Damascus Steel Swords Unveiled]
*{{Cite AV media |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OP8PCkcBZU4 |title=The Secrets of Wootz Damascus Steel |first=Mike |last=Loades |authorlink=Mike Loades |first2=Al |last2=Pendray |date=21 November 2017 |work=YouTube}}
*{{cite patent |country=US |title=Method of making &quot;Damascus&quot; blades |number=5185044 |url=https://www.google.com/patents/US5185044 |invent1=Verhoeven, J.D. |invent2=Pendray, A.H. |pubdate=9 February 1993}}
{{Iron and steel production}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Damascus Steel}}
[[Category:Steels]]
[[Category:Steelmaking]]
[[Category:History of Damascus]]
[[Category:Metalworking]]
[[Category:Lost inventions]]
[[Category:Arab inventions]]</text>
      <sha1>fm0y0u1p6coivpxmnrkb734tgl2jm0v</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
