  <page>
    <title>Book of Deuteronomy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8547</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939517461</id>
      <parentid>939517408</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-06T23:24:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>1980fast</username>
        <id>12136076</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Influence on Judaism and Christianity */ Caption punctuation adjustment, per WP:CAPFRAG</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Fifth book of the Torah and Christian Old Testament}}
{{Tanakh OT |Torah |Pentateuch}}
{{Redirect|Deuteronomy}}
The '''Book of Deuteronomy''' (literally &quot;second law&quot; from Greek ''deuteros'' + ''nomos''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dictionary.com/browse/deuteronomy &quot;Deuteronomy&quot;] ''Dictionary.com''.&lt;/ref&gt;) is the fifth book of the Jewish [[Torah]], where it is called ''Devarim'' (Heb. דברים), &quot;the words [of Moses]&quot;.

Chapters 1–30 of the book consist of three sermons or speeches delivered to the [[Israelites]] by [[Moses]] on the plains of [[Moab]], shortly before they enter the [[Promised Land]]. The first sermon recounts the [[Moses#The years in the wilderness|forty years of wilderness wanderings]] which had led to that moment, and ends with an exhortation to observe the law (or teachings), later referred to as the [[Law of Moses]]; the second reminds the Israelites of the need to follow [[Yahweh]] and the laws (or teachings) he has given them, on which their possession of the land depends; and the third offers the comfort that even should Israel prove unfaithful and so lose the land, with [[repentance]] all can be restored.&lt;ref&gt;Phillips, pp.1–2&lt;/ref&gt; The final four chapters (31–34) contain the [[Song of Moses]], the [[Blessing of Moses]], and narratives recounting the passing of the mantle of leadership from Moses to [[Joshua]] and, finally, the death of Moses on [[Mount Nebo]].

Virtually all secular scholars reject its [[Mosaic authorship|attribution to Moses]] and date the book much later, between the 7th and 5th centuries BC.{{sfn|Bos|2013|p=133}} Chapters 12-26, containing the Deuteronomic Code, are the earliest section, followed by the second prologue (Ch. 5-11), and then the first prologue (Ch. 1-4); the chapters following 26 are similarly layered.{{sfn|Van Seters|2015|pp=79-82}} Most scholars believe that the Deuteronomic Code was composed during the late monarchic period, around the time of [[Josiah|King Josiah]] (late 7th century BC), although some scholars have argued for a later date, either during the [[Babylonian captivity]] (597-539 BC) or during the [[Yehud Medinata|Persian period]] (539-332 BC).{{sfn|Pakkala|2009|p=391}}{{sfn|Davies|2013|p=101-103|ps=, &quot;In short, the belief of most biblical scholars that a scroll depriving the monarch of all real powers (and in effect destroying the institution of monarchy) is a plausible product of seventh-century Judah is astonishing and can only be explained by assuming that such scholarship is taking the fact for granted and thus either ignoring the absurdity or fabricating an implausible rationalization for it... the fifth century BCE provides a plausible context...&quot;}} Many scholars see the book as reflecting the economic needs and social status of the [[Levite]] caste, who are believed to have provided its authors;{{sfn|Sommer|2015|p=18}} those likely authors are collectively referred to as the [[Deuteronomist]].

One of its most significant verses is {{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|6:4|HE}}, the [[Shema Yisrael]], which has become the definitive statement of [[Jewish identity]]: &quot;Hear, O Israel: the [[Tetragrammaton|{{LORD}}]] our God, the {{LORD}} is one.&quot; Verses 6:4–5 were also quoted by [[Jesus]] in {{bibleverse||Mark|12:28–34}} as part of the [[Great Commandment]].

==Structure==
Patrick D. Miller in his commentary on Deuteronomy suggests that different views of the structure of the book will lead to different views on what it is about.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller&quot;&gt;Miller, p.10&lt;/ref&gt; The structure is often described as a series of three speeches or sermons (chapters 1:1–4:43, 4:44–29:1, 29:2–30:20) followed by a number of short appendices&lt;ref name=&quot;Christensen&quot;&gt;Christensen, p.211&lt;/ref&gt;&amp;nbsp;– Miller refers to this as the &quot;literary&quot; structure; alternatively, it is sometimes seen as a ring-structure with a central core (chapters 12–26, the [[Deuteronomic Code]]) and an inner and an outer frame (chapters 4–11/27–30 and 1–3/31–34)&lt;ref name=&quot;Christensen&quot;/&gt;&amp;nbsp;– Miller calls this the covenantal substructure;&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller&quot;/&gt; and finally the theological structure revealed in the theme of the exclusive worship of [[Yahweh]] established in the first of the [[Ten Commandments]] (&quot;Thou shalt have no other god before me&quot;) and the [[Shema Yisrael|Shema]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller&quot;/&gt;

==Summary==
[[File:Karolingischer Buchmaler um 840 002.jpg|thumb|250px|Moses receiving the Law (top) and reading the Law to the Israelites (bottom)]]
''(The following &quot;literary&quot; outline of Deuteronomy is from [[John Van Seters]];{{sfn|Van Seters|1998|pp=15–17}} it can be contrasted with Alexander Rofé's &quot;covenantal&quot; analysis in his ''Deuteronomy: Issues and Interpretation''.&lt;ref&gt;Rofé, pp.1–4&lt;/ref&gt;)''

*Chapters 1–4: The journey through the wilderness from Horeb (Sinai) to Kadesh and then to Moab is recalled.
*Chapters 4–11: After a second introduction at 4:44–49 the events at [[Mount Horeb]] are recalled, with the giving of the Ten Commandments. Heads of families are urged to instruct those under their care in the law, warnings are made against serving gods other than [[Yahweh]], the land promised to Israel is praised, and the people are urged to obedience.
*Chapters 12–26, the Deuteronomic code: Laws governing Israel's worship (chapters 12–16a), the appointment and regulation of community and religious leaders (16b–18), social regulation (19–25), and confession of identity and loyalty (26).
*Chapters 27–28: Blessings and curses for those who keep and break the law.
*Chapters 29–30: Concluding discourse on the covenant in the land of Moab, including all the laws in the Deuteronomic code (chapters 12–26) after those given at Horeb; Israel is again exhorted to obedience.
*Chapters 31–34: [[Joshua]] is installed as Moses's successor, Moses delivers the law to the Levites (a priestly caste), and ascends [[Mount Nebo]] or Pisgah, where he dies and is buried by God. The narrative of these events is interrupted by two poems, the [[Song of Moses]] and the [[Blessing of Moses]].
The final verses, Deuteronomy 34:10–12, &quot;never again did there arise in Israel a prophet like Moses,&quot; make a claim for the authoritative Deuteronomistic view of theology and its insistence that the worship of the Hebrew God as the sole deity of Israel was the only permissible religion, having been sealed by the greatest of prophets.&lt;ref&gt;Tigay, pp.137ff.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Deuteronomic code===
{{Main article|Deuteronomic Code}}
{{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|12–26|HE}}, the [[Deuteronomic Code]], is the oldest part of the book and the core around which the rest developed.{{sfn|Van Seters|1998|p=16}} It is a series of [[mitzvot]] (''commands'') to the Israelites regarding how they ought to conduct themselves in [[Canaan]], the land promised by [[Yahweh]], God of Israel. The following list organizes most of the laws into thematic groups:

====Laws of religious observance====
*All sacrifices are to be brought and vows are to be made at a central sanctuary (12:1–28).
*[[Ancient Canaanite religion|The worship of Canaanite gods]] [[Religious persecution|is forbidden]]. The order is given to destroy their [[Place of worship|places of worship]] (12:29–31) and to commit [[genocide]] against Canaanites and others with &quot;detestable&quot; religious beliefs (20:16-18).
*Native mourning practices such as deliberate disfigurement are forbidden (14:1–2).
*The procedure for tithing produce or donating its equivalent is given (14:22–29).
*A catalogue of which animals are permitted and which forbidden for consumption is given (14:3–20).
*The consumption of animals which are found dead and have not been slaughtered is prohibited (14:21).
*Sacrificed animals must be without blemish (15:21, 17:1).
*First-born male livestock must be sacrificed (15:19–23).
*The Pilgrimage Festivals of [[Passover]], [[Shavuot]], and [[Sukkot]] are instituted (16:1–17).
*The worship at [[Asherah]] groves and setting up of ritual pillars are forbidden (16:21–22).
*Prohibition of mixing kinds (22:9-11).
*[[Tzitzit]] are obligatory (22:12).

====Laws concerning officials====
*Judges are to be appointed in every city (16:18).
*Judges are to be impartial and bribery is forbidden (16:19–20).
*A central tribunal is established (17:8–13).
*Should the Israelites choose to be ruled by a King, regulations for the office are given (17:14–20).
*Regulations of the rights, and revenue, of the Levites are given (18:1–8).
*Concerning the future (unspecified) prophet (18:9–22).
*Regulations for the priesthood are given (23:1–8).

====Civil law====
*Debts are to be [[The Lord's Release|released]] in the seventh year (15:1–11).
*Regulations of the institution of slavery and the procedure for freeing slaves (15:12–18).
*Regulations for the treatment of foreign wives taken in war (21:10-14)
*Regulations permitting taking slaves and plunder in war (20:14)
*Lost property, once found, is to be restored to its owner (22:1–4).
*Marriages between women and their stepsons are forbidden (22:30).
*The camp is to be kept clean (23:9–14).
*Usury is forbidden except for foreigners (23:19–20).
*Regulations for vows and pledges are given (23:21–23, 24:6, 24:10–13).
*The procedure for [[tzaraath]] (a disfigurative condition) is given (24:8–9).
*Hired workers are to be paid fairly (24:14–15).
*Justice is to be shown towards strangers, widows, and orphans (24:17–18).
*Portions of crops are to be given to the poor (24:19–22).

====Criminal law====
*The rules for witnesses are given (19:15–21).
*The procedure for a bride who has been slandered is given (22:13–21).
*Various laws concerning adultery and rape are given (22:22–29).
*Kidnapping is forbidden (24:7).
*Just weights and measures are obligatory (25:13–16).

==Composition==
[[File:Tissot Moses Sees the Promised Land from Afar.jpg|thumb|200px|Moses viewing the Promised Land, Deuteronomy 34:1–5 ([[James Tissot]])]]

===Composition history===
Since the idea was first put forward by [[Wilhelm Martin Leberecht de Wette|W.M.L de Wette]] in 1805, most scholars have accepted that the core of Deuteronomy was composed in Jerusalem in the 7th century BC in the context of religious reforms advanced by King [[Josiah]] (reigned 641–609&amp;nbsp;BC).&lt;ref&gt;Rofé, pp.4–5&lt;/ref&gt; The history of Deuteronomy is seen in the following general terms:{{sfn|Rogerson|2003}}
*In the late 8th century BC both [[kingdom of Judah|Judah]] and [[Kingdom of Israel (Samaria)|Israel]] were vassals of [[Assyria]]. Israel rebelled and was destroyed c.722&amp;nbsp;BC. Refugees fleeing to Judah brought with them a number of new traditions (new to Judah, at least). One of these was that the god Yahweh, already known and worshiped in Judah, was not merely the most important of the gods, but the only god who should be served. This outlook influenced the Judahite landowning [[elite]], who became extremely powerful in court circles after they placed the eight-year-old Josiah on the throne following the murder of his father, [[Amon of Judah]].
*By the eighteenth year of Josiah's reign, Assyrian power was in rapid decline, and a pro-independence movement gathered strength in the court. This movement expressed itself in a state theology of loyalty to Yahweh as the sole god of Israel. With Josiah's support, they launched a full-scale reform of worship based on an early form of Deuteronomy 5–26, which takes the form of a covenant (i.e., treaty) between Judah and Yahweh to replace that between Judah and Assyria. This covenant was formulated as an address by Moses to the Israelites (Deut.5:1).
*The next stage took place during the [[Babylonian captivity]]. The destruction of the [[Kingdom of Judah]] by Babylon in 586&amp;nbsp;BC and the end of kingship was the occasion of much reflection and theological speculation among the Deuteronomistic elite, now in exile in the city of [[Babylon]]. They explained the disaster as Yahweh's punishment of their failure to follow the law and created a history of Israel (the books of Joshua through Kings) to illustrate this.
*At the end of the Exile, when the [[Achaemenid Empire|Persians]] agreed that the Jews could return and rebuild the [[Temple in Jerusalem]], chapters 1–4 and 29–30 were added and Deuteronomy was made the introductory book to this history, so that a story about a people about to enter the Promised Land became a story about a people about to return to the land. The legal sections of chapters 19–25 were expanded to meet new situations that had arisen, and chapters 31–34 were added as a new conclusion.

===Sources===
The prophet [[Isaiah]], active in Jerusalem about a century before [[Josiah]], makes no mention of [[the Exodus]], covenants with God, or disobedience to God's laws; in contrast Isaiah's contemporary [[Hosea]], active in the northern [[Kingdom of Israel (Samaria)|kingdom of Israel]], makes frequent reference to the Exodus, the wilderness wanderings, a covenant, the danger of foreign gods and the need to worship Yahweh alone; this has led scholars to the view that these traditions behind Deuteronomy have a northern origin.{{sfn|Van Seters|1998|p=17}} Whether the Deuteronomic code – the set of laws at chapters 12–26 which form the original core of the book – was written in [[Josiah]]'s time (late 7th century) or earlier is subject to debate, but many of the individual laws are older than the collection itself.&lt;ref&gt;Knight, p.66&lt;/ref&gt; The two poems at chapters 32–33 – the [[Song of Moses]] and the [[Blessing of Moses]] were probably originally independent.{{sfn|Van Seters|1998|p=17}}

===Position in the Hebrew Bible===
Deuteronomy occupies a puzzling position in the Bible, linking the story of the Israelites' wanderings in the wilderness to the story of their history in Canaan without quite belonging totally to either. The wilderness story could end quite easily with Numbers, and the story of Joshua's conquests could exist without it, at least at the level of the plot; but in both cases there would be a thematic (theological) element missing. Scholars have given various answers to the problem. The Deuteronomistic history theory is currently the most popular (Deuteronomy was originally just the law code and covenant, written to cement the religious reforms of Josiah, and later expanded to stand as the introduction to the full history); but there is an older theory which sees Deuteronomy as belonging to Numbers, and Joshua as a sort of supplement to it. This idea still has supporters, but the mainstream understanding is that Deuteronomy, after becoming the introduction to the history, was later detached from it and included with Genesis-Exodus-Leviticus-Numbers because it already had Moses as its central character. According to this hypothesis, the death of Moses was originally the ending of Numbers, and was simply moved from there to the end of Deuteronomy.&lt;ref&gt;Bandstra, pp.190–191&lt;/ref&gt;

==Themes==

===Overview===
Deuteronomy stresses the uniqueness of God, the need for drastic centralisation of worship, and a concern for the position of the poor and disadvantaged.&lt;ref&gt;McConville&lt;/ref&gt; Its many themes can be organised around the three poles of Israel, Israel's God, and the covenant which binds them together.

===Israel===
The themes of Deuteronomy in relation to Israel are election, faithfulness, obedience, and God's promise of blessings, all expressed through the covenant: &quot;obedience is not primarily a duty imposed by one party on another, but an expression of covenantal relationship.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Block, p.172&lt;/ref&gt; Yahweh has chosen (&quot;elected&quot;) Israel as his special property (Deuteronomy 7:6 and elsewhere),&lt;ref&gt;McKenzie, p.266&lt;/ref&gt; and Moses stresses to the Israelites the need for obedience to God and covenant, and the consequences of unfaithfulness and disobedience.&lt;ref&gt;Bultman, p.135&lt;/ref&gt; Yet the first several chapters of Deuteronomy are a long retelling of Israel's past disobedience – but also God's gracious care, leading to a long call to Israel to choose life over death and blessing over curse (chapters 7–11).

===God===
Deuteronomy's concept of God changed over time. The earliest 7th century layer is [[Monolatrism|monolatrous]], not denying the reality of other gods but enforcing the worship of Yahweh in Jerusalem alone. In the later, Exilic layers from the mid-6th century, especially chapter 4, this becomes [[monotheism]], the idea that only one god exists.&lt;ref&gt;Romer (1994), p.200-201&lt;/ref&gt; God is simultaneously present in the Temple and in heaven – an important and innovative concept called &quot;name theology.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;McKenzie, p.265&lt;/ref&gt;

After the review of Israel's history in chapters 1 to 4, there is a restatement of the Ten Commandments in chapter 5. This arrangement of material highlights God's sovereign relationship with Israel prior to the giving of establishment of the Law.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson, ''Deuteronomy'', 112.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Covenant===
The core of Deuteronomy is the [[Covenant (biblical)|covenant]] that binds Yahweh and Israel by oaths of fidelity (Yahweh and Israel each faithful to the other) and obedience (Israel obedient to Yahweh).&lt;ref&gt;Breuggemann, p.53&lt;/ref&gt; God will give Israel blessings of the land, fertility, and prosperity so long as Israel is faithful to God's teaching; disobedience will lead to curses and punishment.&lt;ref&gt;Laffey, p.337&lt;/ref&gt; But, according to the Deuteronomists, Israel's prime sin is lack of faith, [[apostasy]]: contrary to the first and fundamental commandment (&quot;Thou shalt have no other gods before me&quot;) the people have entered into relations with other gods.&lt;ref&gt;Phillips, p.8&lt;/ref&gt;

The covenant is based on seventh-century Assyrian suzerain-vassal treaties by which the Great King (the Assyrian suzerain) regulated relationships with lesser rulers; Deuteronomy is thus making the claim that Yahweh, not the Assyrian monarch, is the Great King to whom Israel owes loyalty.&lt;ref&gt;Vogt, p.28&lt;/ref&gt; The terms of the treaty are that Israel holds the land from Yahweh, but  Israel's tenancy of the land is conditional on keeping the covenant, which in turn necessitates tempered rule by state and village leaders who keep the covenant: &quot;These beliefs&quot;, says Norman Gottwald, &quot;dubbed biblical Yahwism, are widely recognised in biblical scholarship as enshrined in Deuteronomy and the Deuteronomistic History (Joshua through Kings).&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Gottwald&lt;/ref&gt;

Dillard and Longman in their ''Introduction to the Old Testament'' stress the living nature of the covenant between Yahweh and Israel as a nation:  The people of Israel are addressed by Moses as a unity, and  their allegiance to the covenant is not one of obeisance, but comes out of a pre-existing relationship between God and Israel, established with Abraham and attested to by the Exodus event, so that the laws of Deuteronomy set the nation of Israel apart, signaling the unique [[Predestination|status]] of the Jewish nation.&lt;ref&gt;Dillard &amp; Longman, p.102.&lt;/ref&gt; The land is God's gift to Israel, and many of the laws, festivals and instructions in Deuteronomy are given in the light of Israel's occupation of the land. Dillard and Longman note that &quot;In 131 of the 167 times the verb &quot;give&quot; occurs in the book, the subject of the action is Yahweh.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Dillard &amp; Longman, p.117.&lt;/ref&gt; Deuteronomy makes the Torah the ultimate authority for Israel, one to which even the king is subject.&lt;ref&gt;Vogt, p.31&lt;/ref&gt;

==Weekly Torah portions==
{{main article|Weekly Torah portion}}

*''[[Devarim (parsha)|Devarim]]'', on Deuteronomy 1–3: Chiefs, scouts, Edom, Ammonites, Sihon, Og, land for two and a half tribes
*''[[Va'etchanan]]'', on Deuteronomy 3–7: Cities of refuge, Ten Commandments, Shema, exhortation, conquest instructions
*''[[Eikev]]'', on Deuteronomy 7–11: Obedience, taking the land, golden calf, Aaron's death, Levites’ duties
*''[[Re'eh]]'', on Deuteronomy 11–16: Centralized worship, diet, tithes, sabbatical year, pilgrim festivals
*''[[Shofetim (parsha)|Shofetim]]'', on Deuteronomy 16–21: Basic societal structure for the Israelites
*''[[Ki Teitzei]]'', on Deuteronomy 21–25: Miscellaneous laws on civil and domestic life
*''[[Ki Tavo]]'', on Deuteronomy 26–29: First fruits, tithes, blessings and curses, exhortation
*''[[Nitzavim]]'', on Deuteronomy 29–30:  covenant, violation, choose blessing and curse
*''[[Vayelech]]'', on Deuteronomy 31: Encouragement, reading and writing the law
*''[[Haazinu]]'', on Deuteronomy 32: Punishment, punishment restrained, parting words
*''[[V'Zot HaBerachah]]'', on Deuteronomy 33–34: Farewell blessing and death of Moses

==Influence on Judaism and Christianity==

===Judaism===
[[File:The Book of Deuteronomy, Debarim. Hebrew with translation in Judo-Arabic, transcribed in Hebrew letters. From Livorno, 1894 CE. Moroccan Jewish Museum, Casablanca.jpg|thumb|The Book of Deuteronomy, Debarim. Hebrew with translation into Judeo-Arabic, transcribed in Hebrew letters. From Livorno, 1894 CE. Moroccan Jewish Museum, Casablanca.]]
Deuteronomy 6:4–5: &quot;Hear, O Israel (''shema Yisra'el''), the {{LORD}} is our God, the {{LORD}} is one!&quot; has become the basic credo of [[Judaism]], the [[Shema Yisrael]], and its twice-daily recitation is a [[mitzvah]] (religious commandment). It continues, &quot;Thou shalt love the {{LORD}} thy God with all thy heart and all thy soul and all thy might&quot;;  it has therefore also become identified with the central Jewish concept of the love of God, and the rewards that come as a consequence.

===Christianity===
{{main article|Christian views on the Old Covenant}}
In the [[Gospel of Matthew]], [[Jesus]] cited Deuteronomy 6:5 as a [[Great Commandment]]. The [[List of early Christian writers|earliest Christian authors]] interpreted Deuteronomy's prophecy of the restoration of Israel as having been fulfilled (or [[Supersessionism|superseded]]) in Jesus Christ and the establishment of the [[Christian Church]] (Luke 1–2, Acts 2–5), and Jesus was interpreted to be the &quot;one (i.e., prophet) like me&quot; predicted by Moses in Deuteronomy 18:15 (Acts 3:22–23). While the exact position of [[Paul the Apostle and Judaism]] is still debated, a common view is that in place of the elaborate code of laws (''[[mitzvah]]'') set out in Deuteronomy, [[Paul the Apostle]], drawing on {{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|30:11–14}}, claimed that the keeping of the [[Mosaic covenant]] was superseded by faith in Jesus and the gospel (the [[New Covenant]]).&lt;ref&gt;McConville, p.24&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[613 commandments]]
* [[Documentary hypothesis]]
* [[Hebrew Bible]]
* [[Kashrut]]
* [[Mosaic authorship]]
* [[Old Deuteronomy]]
* [[Papyrus Rylands 458]] – the oldest Greek manuscript of Deuteronomy

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==

===Translations===
* [http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Deuteronomy+1&amp;version=NIV Deuteronomy in NIV]
* [https://www.sefaria.org/Deuteronomy.1?lang=bi&amp;aliyot=0 Deuteronomy in Tanakh (Hebrew Bible)]

===Commentaries===
* {{Cite book|last=Craigie|first=Peter C|author-link=Peter Craigie|title=The Book of Deuteronomy|publisher=Eerdmans|year=1976|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=PAslX-YsNagC |isbn=9780802825247}}
* {{Cite book|last=Miller|first=Patrick D|title=Deuteronomy|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=1990|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-yoFvN_QOjYC |isbn=9780664237370}}
* {{Cite book|last=Phillips|first=Anthony|title=Deuteronomy|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|year=1973|url=https://books.google.com/?id=LRA4AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PR7 |isbn=9780521097727}}
*[[Gunther Plaut|Plaut, W. Gunther]] (1981). ''The Torah: A Modern Commentary''. {{ISBN|0-8074-0055-6}}
* {{Cite book|first=Avigdor|last=Miller|title=Fortunate Nation: Comments and notes on DVARIM|year=2001|author-link=Avigdor Miller}}

===General===
* {{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jK-8CgAAQBAJ |title = The Deuteronomist's History: The Role of the Deuteronomist in Historical-Critical Research into Genesis-Numbers|isbn = 9789004307049|last1 = Ausloos|first1 = Hans|date = 2015-10-22}}
* {{Cite book|last=Bandstra|first=Barry L|title=Reading the Old Testament: An Introduction to the Hebrew Bible|publisher=Wadsworth|year=2004|url=https://books.google.com/?id=vRY9mTUZKJcC |isbn=9780495391050}}
* {{Cite book|last=Block|first=Daniel I|chapter=Deuteronomy|editor=Kevin J. Vanhoozer|title=Dictionary for Theological Interpretation of the Bible |publisher=Baker Academic|year=2005}}
*{{Cite book|last=Bos|first=James M.|title=Reconsidering the Date and Provenance of the Book of Hosea|publisher=Bloomsbury|year=2013|url=https://books.google.com/?id=buoRBwAAQBAJ |isbn=978-0-567-06889-7 |ref=harv }}
* {{Cite book|last=Braulik|first=G|title=The Theology of Deuteronomy: Collected Essays of Georg Braulik|publisher=D&amp;F Scott Publishing|year=1998|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=KEnlAAAAMAAJ |isbn=9780941037303}}
* {{Cite book|last=Brueggemann|first=Walter|title=Reverberations of Faith: A Theological Handbook of Old Testament Themes|publisher=Westminster John Knox|year=2002|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dBJQ71RIpdMC |isbn=9780664222314}}
* {{Cite book|last=Bultman|first=Christoph|chapter=Deuteronomy|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3surkLVdw3UC|editor=John Barton|editor2=John Muddiman|title=Oxford Bible Commentary|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2001|isbn=9780198755005|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/oxfordbiblecomme0000unse}}
* {{Cite book|last=Christensen|first=Duane L|chapter=Deuteronomy|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=goq0VWw9rGIC |editor=Watson E. Mills |editor2=Roger Aubrey Bullard|title=Mercer Dictionary of the Bible|publisher=Mercer University Press|year=1991|isbn=9780865543737}}
* Clements, Ronald (1968). ''God's Chosen People: A Theological Interpretation of the Book of Deuteronomy''. In series, ''Religious Book Club'', 182. London: S.C.M. Press.
* {{cite book |last=Davies |first=Philip R. |author-link=Philip R. Davies |title=Rethinking Biblical Scholarship |series=Changing Perspectives |volume=4 |year=2013 |publisher=Routledge |location=New York |isbn=978-1-84465-727-8 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=QFdsBAAAQBAJ |ref=harv }}
* Gottwald, Norman, review of [https://web.archive.org/web/20060518122526/http://www.interpretation.org/reviews/apr-06/index.htm Stephen L. Cook, ''The Social Roots of Biblical Yahwism'', Society of Biblical Literature, 2004]
* {{Cite book|last=Knight|first=Douglas A|chapter=Deuteronomy and the Deuteronomists|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=SNLN1nEEys0C |editor=James Luther Mays |editor2=David L. Petersen |editor3=Kent Harold Richards|title=Old Testament Interpretation|publisher=T&amp;T Clark|year=1995|isbn=9780567292896}}
* [https://www.academia.edu/38405785/Kugler_Moses_died_and_the_people_moved_on_-_a_hidden_narrative_in_Deuteronomy.pdf Gili Kugler, Kugler, Moses died and the people moved on - a hidden narrative in Deuteronomy]
* {{Cite book|last=Laffey|first=Alice L|chapter=Deuteronomistic Theology|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/?id=k85JKr1OXcQC&amp;pg=PR7 |editor=Orlando O. Espín |editor2=James B. Nickoloff|title=An Introductory Dictionary of Theology and Religious Studies|publisher=Liturgical Press|year=2007|isbn=9780814658567}}
* {{Cite journal|last=Markl|first=Dominik|title=Moses' Praise and Blame – Israel's Honour and Shame: Rhetorical Devices in the Ethical Foundations of Deuteronomy|volume=34|issue=2|publisher=34|year=2013|doi=10.4102/ve.v34i2.861|journal=Verbum et Ecclesia}}
* {{Cite book|last=Mendenhall|first=George E|title=Covenant Forms in Israelite Tradition|publisher=Biblical Archeology 3/17|date=September 1, 1954}}
* {{Cite book|last=McConville|first=J.G|chapter=Deuteronomy|chapter-url=http://www.ivpress.com/title/exc/1781-X.pdf|editor=T. Desmond Alexander|editor2=David W. Baker|title=Dictionary of the Old Testament: The Pentateuch|publisher=Eisenbrauns|year=2002|access-date=2007-11-02|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080413215334/http://www.ivpress.com/title/exc/1781-X.pdf|archive-date=2008-04-13|url-status=dead}}
* {{Cite book|last=McKenzie|first=Steven L|chapter=Postscript|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=_Uji4Y3isn0C&amp;pg=PA265 |editor=Linda S. Schearing |editor2=Steven L McKenzie|title=Those Elusive Deuteronomists: The Phenomenon of Pan-Deuteronomism|publisher=T&amp;T Clark|year=1995|isbn=9780567563361}}
* {{cite journal |last=Pakkala |first=Juha |year=2009 |title=The date of the oldest edition of Deuteronomy |journal=[[Zeitschrift für die Alttestamentliche Wissenschaft]] |volume=121 |issue=3 |pages=388–401 |doi=10.1515/ZAW.2009.026 |ref=harv }}
* {{Cite book|last=Richter|first=Sandra L|title=The Deuteronomistic History and the Name Theology|publisher=Walter de Gruyter|year=2002|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WY_OfDvGXssC |isbn=9783110173765}}
* {{Cite book|last=Rofé|first=Alexander|title=Deuteronomy: Issues and Interpretation|publisher=T&amp;T Clark|year=2002|url=https://books.google.com/?id=ATDWInu5VCwC&amp;pg=PR7 |isbn=9780567087546}}
* {{Cite book|last=Rogerson|first=John W.|chapter=Deuteronomy|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2Vo-11umIZQC&amp;pg=PA153 |editor=James D. G. Dunn |editor2=John William Rogerson|title=Eerdmans Commentary on the Bible|publisher=Eerdmans|year=2003|isbn=9780802837110}}
* {{Cite book|last=Romer|first=Thomas|chapter=Deuteronomy In Search of Origins|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CoHhPAKgETkC&amp;pg=PA112 |editor=Gary N. Knoppers |editor2=J. Gordon McConville|title=Reconsidering Israel and Judah: Recent Studies on the Deuteronomistic History|publisher=Eisenbrauns|year=2000|isbn=9781575060378}}
* {{Cite book|last=Romer|first=Thomas|chapter=The Book of Deuteronomy|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3gnxJjuqld0C&amp;pg=PA178 |editor=Steven L. McKenzie |editor2=Matt Patrick Graham|title=The history of Israel's Traditions: The Heritage of Martin Noth|publisher=Sheffield Academic Press|year=1994|isbn=9780567230355}}
* {{cite book |last=Sommer |first=Benjamin D. |date=June 30, 2015 |title=Revelation and Authority: Sinai in Jewish Scripture and Tradition |url= |location= |series=Anchor Yale Bible Reference Library| publisher= |isbn= |author-link= }}
* {{Cite book|last=Tigay|first=Jeffrey|chapter=The Significance of the End of Deuteronomy|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jvFrWwau-1oC |editor=Michael V. Fox |display-editors=etal |title=Texts, Temples, and Traditions: A Tribute to Menahem Haran|publisher=Eisenbrauns|year=1996|isbn=9781575060033}}
* {{Cite book|last=Van Seters|first=John|chapter=The Pentateuch|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=owwhpmIVgSAC |editor=Steven L. McKenzie|editor2=Matt Patrick Graham|title=The Hebrew Bible Today: An Introduction to Critical Issues|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|year=1998|isbn=9780664256524|url=https://archive.org/details/hebrewbibletoday0000unse}}
* {{cite book|last=Van Seters|first=John|title=The Pentateuch: A Social-Science Commentary|year=2015|publisher=Bloomsbury T&amp;T Clark|url=https://books.google.com/?id=42-_CQAAQBAJ |isbn=978-0-567-65880-7 |ref=harv }}
* {{Cite book|last=Vogt|first=Peter T|title=Deuteronomic Theology and the Significance of Torah: A Reappraisal|publisher=Eisenbrauns|year=2006|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=bQRpj-GxN_AC&amp;pg=PR3 |isbn=9781575061078}}

==External links==
{{wikisource|Deuteronomy (Bible)}}
{{wikiquote}}
* [http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Deuteronomy+1&amp;version=NIV Deuteronomy] at Bible Gateway
* {{Cite EB1911|wstitle=Deuteronomy|first=James Alexander |last=Paterson |short=x}}
* {{Cite NIE |last=Jastrow |first=Morris |authorlink=Morris Jastrow |wstitle=Deuteronomy |year=1905 |short=x}}
* [[Judaism|Jewish]] translations:
** [http://www.mechon-mamre.org/e/et/et0501.htm Deuteronomy at Mechon-Mamre] (modified Jewish Publication Society translation)
** [http://bible.ort.org/books/pentd2.asp?ACTION=displaypage&amp;BOOK=5&amp;CHAPTER=1 Deuteronomy (The Living Torah)] Rabbi [[Aryeh Kaplan]]'s translation and commentary at Ort.org
** [http://www.chabad.org/article.asp?AID=8164 Devarim – Deuteronomy (Judaica Press)] translation [with [[Rashi]]'s commentary] at Chabad.org
** [http://www.mechon-mamre.org/p/pt/pt0501.htm דְּבָרִים ''Devarim'' – Deuteronomy] ([[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] – English at Mechon-Mamre.org)
* [[Christianity|Christian]] translations:
** [http://www.gospelhall.org/bible/bible.php?passage=Deut+1 ''Online Bible'' at GospelHall.org] ([[Authorized King James Version|King James Version]])
** [http://bible.oremus.org/?ql=56784112 ''oremus Bible Browser''] ([[New Revised Standard Version]])
** [http://bible.oremus.org/?ql=56784148 ''oremus Bible Browser''] (''Anglicized'' [[New Revised Standard Version]])
** [[s:Bible, King James, Deuteronomy|''Deuteronomy'' at Wikisource]] ([[Authorized King James Version]])
** {{librivox book | title=Deuteronomy}} Various versions

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou | [[Torah|Pentateuch]]|||}}
{{s-bef | before= [[Book of Numbers|Numbers]] | rows = 2 }}
{{s-ttl | title = [[Tanakh|Hebrew Bible]] }}
{{s-aft | after = [[Book of Joshua|Joshua]] | rows= 2 }}
{{s-ttl | title = [[Christianity|Christian]]&lt;br&gt;[[Old Testament]] }}
{{s-end}}

{{Book of Deuteronomy}}
{{Books of the Bible|state=collapsed}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Book of Deuteronomy| ]]
[[Category:7th-century BC books]]
[[Category:6th-century BC books]]
[[Category:Torah books|5]]
[[Category:Non-fiction books about genocide]]</text>
      <sha1>lsn22zllqbjt1f0dwah5m2trjns3gmg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
