  <page>
    <title>Dmitri Shostakovich</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8520</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943241879</id>
      <parentid>942870709</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T19:01:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelink 2 books for [[Wikipedia:Verifiability|verifiability]]. [goog]) #IABot (v2.0) ([[User:GreenC bot|GreenC bot]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2019}}
{{Redirect|Shostakovich|the conductor and son of Dmitri Shostakovich|Maxim Shostakovich}}
{{short description|Soviet composer and pianist}}
{{Eastern Slavic name|Dmitriyevich|Shostakovich}}
	
&lt;!-- Please do not add an infobox without discussion on the talk page, per [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Classical music/Style guidelines#Biographical infoboxes]] --&gt;
[[File:Dmitri Shostakovich credit Deutsche Fotothek adjusted.jpg|thumb|212px|{{center|Shostakovich, {{c.|1950}}&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Shostakovich signature.svg|87px|alt=Shostakovich's signature]]}}]]

'''Dmitri Dmitriyevich Shostakovich''' ({{lang-rus|{{audio|Ru-Dmitri Dmitrievich Shostakovich.ogg|Дми́трий Дми́триевич Шостако́вич}}|Dmitriy Dmitrievich Shostakovich}}, {{IPA-ru|ˈdmʲitrʲɪj ˈdmʲitrʲɪjɪvʲɪtɕ ʂəstɐˈkovʲɪtɕ|pron}}; {{OldStyleDate|25 September|1906|12 September}}{{spaced ndash}}9 August 1975) was a Russian [[composer]] and [[pianist]]. He is regarded as one of the major composers of the 20th century, with a unique harmonic language and a historic importance due to his years of work under [[Stalin]].&lt;ref name=grove&gt;{{cite web |author1=Fay, Laurel |author2=Fanning, David |title=Shostakovich, Dmitry |website=Grove Music Online |publisher=Oxford University Press |url=http://www.oxfordmusiconline.com/subscriber/article/grove/music/52560 |url-access=subscription |access-date=30 April 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Paragraph 1: career and his relationship with authority --&gt;
Shostakovich achieved fame in the [[Soviet Union]] under the patronage of Soviet chief of staff [[Mikhail Tukhachevsky]], but later had a complex and difficult relationship with the government. Nevertheless, he received accolades and state awards and served in the [[Supreme Soviet of the RSFSR]] (1947) and the [[Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union]] (from 1962 until his death).

&lt;!-- Paragraph 2: musical style --&gt;
A [[polystylism|polystylist]], Shostakovich developed a hybrid voice, combining a variety of different musical techniques into his works. His music is characterized by sharp contrasts, elements of the [[grotesque]], and [[Ambivalence|ambivalent]] [[tonality]]; he was also heavily influenced by the [[Neoclassicism (music)|neoclassical]] style pioneered by [[Igor Stravinsky]], and (especially in his symphonies) by the late Romanticism of [[Gustav Mahler]].

&lt;!-- Paragraph 3: overview of compositions --&gt;
Shostakovich's orchestral works include 15 [[symphony|symphonies]] and six [[concerti]]. His chamber output includes 15 [[string quartet]]s, a [[piano quintet]], two [[piano trio]]s, and two pieces for [[string octet]]. His solo piano works include two [[sonata]]s, an early set of [[prelude (music)|preludes]], and a later set of [[24 Preludes and Fugues (Shostakovich)|24 preludes and fugues]]. Other works include three [[opera]]s, several [[song cycle]]s, [[ballet]]s, and a substantial quantity of [[film score|film music]]; especially well known is ''The Second Waltz'', Op. 99, music to the film ''[[The First Echelon]]'' (1955–1956),&lt;ref&gt;{{imdb title|0048482|Pervyy eshelon}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the suites of music composed for ''[[The Gadfly (1955 film)|The Gadfly]]''.

== Biography ==
=== Early life ===
[[File:Shostakovichbirthplaque.JPG|thumb|right|Birthplace of Shostakovich (now School No. 267). Commemorative plaque at left]]Born at Podolskaya Street in [[Saint Petersburg]], [[Russian Empire|Russia]], Shostakovich was the second of three children of Dmitri Boleslavovich Shostakovich and Sofiya Vasilievna Kokoulina. Shostakovich's paternal grandfather, originally surnamed Szostakowicz, was of [[Poles|Polish]] [[Roman Catholic]] descent (his family roots trace to the region of the town of [[Vileyka]] in today's [[Belarus]]), but his immediate forebears came from [[Siberia]].{{sfnp|Fay|2000|p=7}} A Polish revolutionary in the [[January Uprising]] of 1863–4, Bolesław Szostakowicz was exiled to [[Narym]] (near [[Tomsk]]) in 1866 in the crackdown that followed [[Dmitry Karakozov|Dmitri Karakozov]]'s assassination attempt on [[Alexander II of Russia|Tsar Alexander II]].&lt;ref name=Wilson2000_4&gt;{{harvp|Wilson|2006|p=4}}.&lt;/ref&gt; When his term of exile ended, Szostakowicz decided to remain in Siberia. He eventually became a successful banker in [[Irkutsk]] and raised a large family. His son Dmitri Boleslavovich Shostakovich, the composer's father, was born in exile in Narim in 1875 and studied physics and mathematics at [[Saint Petersburg University]], graduating in 1899. He then went to work as an engineer under [[Dmitri Mendeleev]] at the Bureau of Weights and Measures in Saint Petersburg. In 1903 he married another Siberian transplant to the capital, Sofiya Vasilievna Kokoulina, one of six children born to a Russian [[Siberian]] native.{{r|Wilson2000_4}}

Their son, Dmitri Dmitriyevich Shostakovich, displayed significant musical talent after he began piano lessons with his mother at the age of nine. On several occasions he displayed a remarkable ability to remember what his mother had played at the previous lesson, and would get &quot;caught in the act&quot; of playing the previous lesson's music while pretending to read different music placed in front of him.&lt;ref&gt;Fay (2000), p. 9&lt;/ref&gt; In 1918 he wrote a funeral march in memory of two leaders of the [[Constitutional Democratic party|Kadet party]] murdered by [[Bolshevik]] sailors.&lt;ref&gt;Fay (2000), p. 12&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1919, at age 13, Shostakovich was admitted to the [[Saint Petersburg Conservatory|Petrograd Conservatory]], then headed by [[Alexander Glazunov]], who monitored his progress closely and promoted him.&lt;ref&gt;Fay (2000), p. 17&lt;/ref&gt; Shostakovich studied piano with [[Leonid Nikolayev (pianist)|Leonid Nikolayev]] after a year in the class of Elena Rozanova, composition with [[Maximilian Steinberg]], and [[counterpoint]] and [[fugue]] with [[Nikolay Sokolov (composer)|Nikolay Sokolov]], with whom he became friends.&lt;ref&gt;Fay (2000), p. 18&lt;/ref&gt; He also attended [[Alexander Ossovsky]]'s music history classes.&lt;ref&gt;Fairclough &amp; Fanning (2008), p. 73&lt;/ref&gt; Steinberg tried to guide Shostakovich on the path of the great Russian composers, but was disappointed to see him 'wasting' his talent and imitating [[Igor Stravinsky]] and [[Sergei Prokofiev]]. Shostakovich also suffered for his perceived lack of political zeal, and initially failed his exam in [[Marxism|Marxist]] methodology in 1926. His first major musical achievement was the [[Symphony No. 1 (Shostakovich)|First Symphony]] (premiered 1926), written as his graduation piece at the age of 19. This work brought him to the attention of [[Mikhail Tukhachevsky]], who helped Shostakovich find accommodation and work in Moscow, and sent a driver around in &quot;a very stylish automobile&quot; to take him to a concert.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=McSmith |first1=Andy |title=Fear and the Muse Kept Watch, the Russian Masters – from Akhmativa and Pasternak to Shostakoviich and Eisenstein – under Stalin |date=2015 |publisher=New Press |location=New York |isbn=978-1-62097-079-9 |page=171}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Early career ===
[[File:Dmitrij Dmitrijevič Šostakovič (Дми́трий Дми́триевич Шостако́вич).jpg|thumb|upright|Shostakovich in 1925]]
After graduation, Shostakovich initially embarked on a dual career as concert pianist and composer, but his dry playing style was often unappreciated (his American biographer, Laurel Fay, comments on his &quot;emotional restraint&quot; and &quot;riveting rhythmic drive&quot;). He won an &quot;honorable mention&quot; at the First [[International Chopin Piano Competition]] in Warsaw in 1927 and attributed the disappointing result to suffering from appendicitis and the jury being all Polish. He had his appendix removed in April 1927.{{sfnp|The New Grove|2001|}} After the competition Shostakovich met the conductor [[Bruno Walter]], who was so impressed by the composer's [[Symphony No. 1 (Shostakovich)|First Symphony]] that he conducted it at its Berlin premiere later that year. [[Leopold Stokowski]] was equally impressed and gave the work its U.S. premiere the following year in Philadelphia. Stokowski also made the work's first recording.{{sfnp|Hulme|2010|p=19}}{{sfnp|Hulme|2010|p=20}}

Shostakovich concentrated on composition thereafter and soon limited his performances primarily to his own works. In 1927 he wrote his [[Symphony No. 2 (Shostakovich)|Second Symphony]] (subtitled ''To October''), a patriotic piece with a pro-Soviet choral finale. Owing to its [[avant-garde|experimental nature]], as with the subsequent [[Symphony No. 3 (Shostakovich)|Third Symphony]], it was not critically acclaimed with the enthusiasm given to the First.{{sfnp|Meyer|1995|p=143}}

1927 also marked the beginning of Shostakovich's relationship with [[Ivan Sollertinsky]], who remained his closest friend until the latter's death in 1944. Sollertinsky introduced the composer to Mahler's music, which had a strong influence on Shostakovich from the [[Symphony No. 4 (Shostakovich)|Fourth Symphony]] onward.{{sfnp|Ivashkin|2016|p=20}}

While writing the Second Symphony, Shostakovich also began work on his [[satire|satirical]] opera ''[[The Nose (opera)|The Nose]]'', based on the story by [[Nikolai Gogol]]. In June 1929, against the composer's wishes, the opera was given a concert performance; it was ferociously attacked by the [[Russian Association of Proletarian Musicians]] (RAPM).&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (2006), p. 84&lt;/ref&gt; Its stage premiere on 18 January 1930 opened to generally poor reviews and widespread incomprehension among musicians.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (2006), p. 85&lt;/ref&gt;

In the late 1920s and early 1930s, Shostakovich worked at [[Workers' Youth Theatre|TRAM]], a [[proletariat|proletarian]] youth theatre. Although he did little work in this post, it shielded him from ideological attack. Much of this period was spent writing his opera ''[[Lady Macbeth of the Mtsensk District (opera)|Lady Macbeth of the Mtsensk District]]'', which was first performed in 1934. It was immediately successful, on both popular and official levels. It was described as &quot;the result of the general success of Socialist construction, of the correct policy of the Party&quot;, and as an opera that &quot;could have been written only by a Soviet composer brought up in the best tradition of Soviet culture&quot;.{{sfnp|Shostakovich/Grigoryev &amp; Platek|1981|p=33}}

Shostakovich married his first wife, Nina Varzar, in 1932. Difficulties led to a divorce in 1935, but the couple soon remarried when Nina became pregnant with their first child, [[Galina Dmitrievna Shostakovich|Galina]].&lt;ref&gt;Fay (2000), p. 80&lt;/ref&gt;

=== First denunciation ===
On 17 January 1936, [[Joseph Stalin]] paid a rare visit to the opera for a performance of a new work, ''Quiet Flows the Don'', based on the novel by [[Mikhail Sholokhov]], by the little-known composer [[Ivan Dzerzhinsky]], who was called to Stalin's box at the end of the performance and told that his work had &quot;considerable ideological-political value&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=McSmith|first1=Andy|title=Fear and the Muse Kept Watch|page=172}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 26 January, Stalin revisited the opera, accompanied by [[Vyacheslav Molotov]], [[Andrei Zhdanov]] and [[Anastas Mikoyan]], to hear ''Lady Macbeth of the Mtsensk District''. He and his entourage left without speaking to anyone. Shostakovich had been forewarned by a friend that he should postpone a planned concert tour in [[Arkhangelsk]] in order to be present at that particular performance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Classical Music |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/music/classicalmusic/3613515/When-opera-was-a-matter-of-life-or-death.html |title=When opera was a matter of life or death |newspaper=[[The Daily Telegraph]] |date=8 March 2004 |accessdate=7 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eyewitness accounts testify that Shostakovich was &quot;white as a sheet&quot; when he went to take his bow after the third act.{{sfnp|Wilson|2006b|pp=128–9}} In letters to Sollertinsky, Shostakovich recounted the horror with which he watched as Stalin shuddered every time the brass and percussion played too loudly. Equally horrifying was the way Stalin and his companions laughed at the lovemaking scene between Sergei and Katerina. The next day, Shostakovich left for Arkhangelsk, and was there when he heard on 28 January that ''[[Pravda]]'' had published a tirade titled ''Muddle Instead of Music'', complaining that the opera was a &quot;deliberately dissonant, muddled stream of sounds...[that] quacks, hoots, pants and gasps.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Fay |first1=Laurel |title=Shostakovich |pages=84–85}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was the signal for a nationwide campaign, during which even Soviet music critics who had praised the opera were forced to recant in print, saying they &quot;failed to detect the shortcomings of ''Lady Macbeth'' as pointed out by ''Pravda''&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Downes, Olin. [https://www.nytimes.com/1936/04/12/archives/changes-in-the-soviet-shostakovich-affair-shows-shift-in-point-of.html &quot;Shostakovich Affair shows shift in point of view in the U.S.S.R.&quot;], ''The New York Times''. 12 April 1936. p. X5.&lt;/ref&gt; There was resistance from those who admired Shostakovich, including Sollertinsky, who turned up at a composers' meeting in Leningrad called to denounce the opera and praised it instead. Two other speakers supported him. When Shostakovich returned to Leningrad, he had a telephone call from the commander of the Leningrad Military District, who had been asked by Marshal Mikhail Tukhachevsky to make sure that he was all right. When the writer [[Isaac Babel]] was under arrest four years later, he told his interrogators that &quot;it was common ground for us to proclaim the genius of the slighted Shostakovich.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=McSmith |first1=Andy |title=Fear and the Muse Kept Watch |pages=175–176}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 6 February, Shostakovich was again attacked in ''Pravda'', this time for his light comic ballet ''The Limpid Stream'', which was denounced because &quot;it jangles and expresses nothing&quot; and did not give an accurate picture of peasant life on a collective farm.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (2006), p. 130&lt;/ref&gt; Fearful that he was about to be arrested, Shostakovich secured an appointment with the Chairman of the USSR State Committee on Culture, [[Platon Kerzhentsev]], who reported to Stalin and [[Vyacheslav Molotov|Molotov]] that he had instructed the composer to &quot;reject formalist errors and in his art attain something that could be understood by the broad masses&quot;, and that Shostakovich had admitted being in the wrong and had asked for a meeting with Stalin, which was not granted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=McSmith |first1=Andy |title=Fear and the Muse Kept Watch |pages=174–5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As a result of this campaign, commissions began to fall off, and Shostakovich's income fell by about three-quarters. His Fourth Symphony was due to receive its premiere on 11 December 1936, but he withdrew it from the public, possibly because it was banned, and the symphony was not performed until 1961. ''Lady Macbeth of the Mtsensk District'' was also suppressed. A bowdlerised version was eventually performed under a new title, ''Katerina Izmailova'', on 8 January 1963. The anti-Shostakovich campaign also served as a signal to artists working in other fields, including art, architecture, the theatre and cinema, with the writer [[Mikhail Bulgakov]], the director [[Sergei Eisenstein]], and the theatre director [[Vsevolod Meyerhold]] among the prominent targets. More widely, 1936 marked the beginning of the [[Great Purge|Great Terror]], in which many of the composer's friends and relatives were imprisoned or killed. These included Tukhachevsky (shot months after his arrest); his brother-in-law [[Vsevolod Frederiks]] (a distinguished physicist, who was eventually released but died before he got home); his close friend [[Nikolai Zhilyayev (musicologist)|Nikolai Zhilyayev]] (a musicologist who had taught Tukhachevsky; shot shortly after his arrest); his mother-in-law, the astronomer Sofiya Mikhaylovna Varzar (sent to a camp in [[Karaganda]]); his friend the Marxist writer Galina Serebryakova (20 years in camps); his uncle Maxim Kostrykin (died); and his colleagues [[Boris Kornilov]] and [[Adrian Piotrovsky]] (executed).&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (2006), pp. 145–6&lt;/ref&gt; His only consolation in this period was the birth of his daughter Galina in 1936;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Riley |first=John |date=2005 |title=Dmitri Shostakovich: A Life in Film |url=https://books.google.de/books?id=4r8I9NUzKm8C&amp;pg=PA32 |publisher=I.B.Tauris |page=32 |isbn=9781850434849}}&lt;/ref&gt; his son [[Maxim Shostakovich|Maxim]] was born two years later.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Charles |first=Eleanor |date=3 February 1985 |title=Shostakovich Orchestra Role |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1985/02/03/nyregion/shostakovich-orchestra-role.html |work=[[The New York Times]] |location=New York City |access-date=25 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Withdrawal of the Fourth Symphony ====
The publication of the ''Pravda'' editorials coincided with the composition of Shostakovich's [[Symphony No. 4 (Shostakovich)|Fourth Symphony]]. The work marked a great shift in style, owing to the substantial influence of Mahler and a number of Western-style elements. The symphony gave Shostakovich compositional trouble, as he attempted to reform his style into a new idiom. He was well into the work when the ''Pravda'' article appeared. He continued to compose the symphony and planned a premiere at the end of 1936. Rehearsals began that December, but after a number of rehearsals, for reasons still debated today, decided to withdraw the symphony from the public. A number of his friends and colleagues, such as [[Isaak Glikman]], have suggested that it was an official ban that Shostakovich was persuaded to present as a voluntary withdrawal.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (2006), pp. 143–4&lt;/ref&gt; Whatever the case, it seems possible that this action saved the composer's life: during this time Shostakovich feared for himself and his family. Yet he did not repudiate the work; it retained its designation as his Fourth Symphony. A piano reduction was published in 1946,{{sfnp|Hulme|2010|p=167}} and the work was finally premiered in 1961, well after Stalin's death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Fay |first=Laurel E. |date=6 April 2003 |title=Music; Found: Shostakovich's Long-Lost Twin Brother |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/06/arts/music-found-shostakovich-s-long-lost-twin-brother.html |work=[[The New York Times]] |location=New York City |access-date=25 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During 1936 and 1937, in order to maintain as low a profile as possible between the Fourth and Fifth symphonies, Shostakovich mainly composed [[film music]], a genre favored by Stalin and lacking in dangerous personal expression.{{sfnp|Shostakovich/Volkov|1979|p=59}}

==== Fifth Symphony and return to favor ====
The composer's response to his denunciation was the [[Symphony No. 5 (Shostakovich)|Fifth Symphony]] of 1937, which was musically more conservative than his earlier works. Premiered on 21 November 1937 in Leningrad, it was a phenomenal success. The Fifth brought many to tears and welling emotions.{{sfnp|Volkov|2004|p=150}} Later, Shostakovich's purported memoir, ''[[Testimony (Volkov book)|Testimony]]'', stated: &quot;I'll never believe that a man who understood nothing could feel the Fifth Symphony. Of course they understood, they understood what was happening around them and they understood what the Fifth was about.&quot;{{sfnp|Shostakovich/Volkov|2000|p=135}}

The success put Shostakovich in good standing once again. Music critics and the authorities alike, including those who had earlier accused him of formalism, claimed that he had learned from his mistakes and become a true Soviet artist. In a newspaper article published under Shostakovich's name, the Fifth was characterized as &quot;A Soviet artist's creative response to just criticism.&quot;{{sfnp|Taruskin|2009|p=304}} The composer [[Dmitry Kabalevsky]], who had been among those who disassociated themselves from Shostakovich when the ''Pravda'' article was published, praised the Fifth and congratulated Shostakovich for &quot;not having given in to the seductive temptations of his previous 'erroneous' ways.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (2006), p. 152.&lt;/ref&gt;

It was also at this time that Shostakovich composed the first of his [[string quartet]]s. His [[Chamber music|chamber]] works allowed him to experiment and express ideas that would have been unacceptable in his more public symphonies. In September 1937 he began to teach composition at the Leningrad Conservatory, which provided some financial security.{{sfnp|Fay|2000|p=97}}

=== Second World War ===
In 1939, before [[Winter War|Soviet forces attempted to invade Finland]], the Party Secretary of Leningrad [[Andrei Zhdanov]] commissioned a celebratory piece from Shostakovich, the ''[[Suite on Finnish Themes]]'', to be performed as the marching bands of the [[Red Army]] paraded through Helsinki. The [[Winter War]] was a bitter experience for the Red Army, the parade never happened, and Shostakovich never laid claim to the authorship of this work.{{sfnp|Edwards|2006|p=98}} It was not performed until 2001.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mtv3.fi/uutiset/arkisto.shtml/arkistot/kulttuuri/2001/09/78462 MTV3: Shostakovitshin kiistelty teos kantaesitettiin] (in Finnish)&lt;/ref&gt; After the outbreak of [[Eastern Front (World War II)|war between the Soviet Union and Germany]] in 1941, Shostakovich initially remained in Leningrad. He tried to enlist in the military but was turned away because of his poor eyesight. To compensate, he became a volunteer for the Leningrad Conservatory's firefighter brigade and delivered a radio broadcast to the Soviet people ''{{Audio|ShostakovichRadio1941.ogg|listen}}''. The photograph for which he posed was published in newspapers throughout the country.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (2006), p. 171.&lt;/ref&gt;

His greatest and most famous wartime contribution was the [[Symphony No. 7 (Shostakovich)|Seventh Symphony]]. The composer wrote the first three movements in Leningrad and completed the work in [[Kuybyshev, Russia|Kuibyshev]] (now [[Samara, Russia|Samara]]), where he and his family had been evacuated. It remains unclear whether Shostakovich really conceived the idea of the symphony with the [[siege of Leningrad]] in mind. It was officially claimed as a representation of the people of Leningrad's brave resistance to the German invaders and an authentic piece of patriotic art at a time when morale needed boosting. The symphony was first premiered by the Bolshoi Theatre orchestra in Kuibyshev and was soon performed abroad in London and the United States. The most compelling performance was the [[Leningrad première of Shostakovich's Symphony No. 7|Leningrad premiere]] by the Radio Orchestra in the besieged city. The orchestra had only 14 musicians left, so the conductor Karl Eliasberg had to recruit anyone who could play an instrument to perform.{{sfnp|Blokker|1979|p=31}}

The family moved to Moscow in spring 1943. At the time of the [[Symphony No. 8 (Shostakovich)|Eighth Symphony]]'s premiere, the tide had turned for the Red Army. As a consequence, the public, and most importantly the authorities, wanted another triumphant piece from the composer. Instead, they got the Eighth Symphony, perhaps the ultimate in sombre and violent expression in Shostakovich's output. In order to preserve Shostakovich's image (a vital bridge to the people of the Union and to the West), the government assigned the name &quot;Stalingrad&quot; to the symphony, giving it the appearance of mourning of the dead in the bloody [[Battle of Stalingrad]]. But the piece did not escape criticism. Its composer is reported to have said: &quot;When the Eighth was performed, it was openly declared counter-revolutionary and anti-Soviet. They said, 'Why did Shostakovich write an optimistic symphony at the beginning of the war and a tragic one now? At the beginning, we were retreating and now we're attacking, destroying the Fascists. And Shostakovich is acting tragic, that means he's on the side of the fascists.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Shostakovich/Volkov (2000), p.162.&lt;/ref&gt; The work was unofficially but effectively banned until 1956.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (2006), p. 203.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Symphony No. 9 (Shostakovich)|Ninth Symphony]] (1945), in contrast, was much lighter in tone. [[Gavriil Nikolayevich Popov|Gavriil Popov]] wrote that it was &quot;splendid in its joie de vivre, gaiety, brilliance, and pungency!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Fay (2000): p. 147.&lt;/ref&gt; But by 1946 it too was the subject of criticism. Israel Nestyev asked whether it was the right time for &quot;a light and amusing interlude between Shostakovich's significant creations, a temporary rejection of great, serious problems for the sake of playful, filigree-trimmed trifles.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Fay (2000): p. 152.&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[New York World-Telegram]]'' of 27 July 1946 was similarly dismissive: &quot;The Russian composer should not have expressed his feelings about the defeat of Nazism in such a childish manner&quot;. Shostakovich continued to compose chamber music, notably his [[Piano Trio No. 2 (Shostakovich)|Second Piano Trio]] (Op. 67), dedicated to the memory of Sollertinsky, with a bittersweet, Jewish-themed ''[[totentanz]]'' finale. In 1947, the composer was made a deputy to the [[Supreme Soviet of the RSFSR]].{{sfnp|Hulme|2010|p=xxiv}}

=== Second denunciation ===
[[File:Prokofiev shostakovich khachaturian.jpg|thumb|right|''Left to right'', 1945:{{sfnp|Shostakovich/Volkov|2004|p=86}} [[Sergei Prokofiev]], Shostakovich, [[Aram Khachaturian]]]]
In 1948, Shostakovich, along with many other composers, was again denounced for [[Formalism (music)|formalism]] in the [[Zhdanov Doctrine|Zhdanov decree]]. Andrei Zhdanov, Chairman of the [[RSFSR Supreme Soviet]], accused the composers (including [[Sergei Prokofiev]] and [[Aram Khachaturian]]) of writing inappropriate and formalist music. This was part of an ongoing anti-formalism campaign intended to root out all Western compositional influence as well as any perceived &quot;non-Russian&quot; output. The conference resulted in the publication of the Central Committee's Decree &quot;On V. Muradeli’s opera ''[[The Great Friendship]]'',&quot; which targeted all Soviet composers and demanded that they write only &quot;proletarian&quot; music, or music for the masses. The accused composers, including Shostakovich, were summoned to make public apologies in front of the committee.{{sfnp|Blokker|1979|pp=33–4}}&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (2006), p. 241.&lt;/ref&gt; Most of Shostakovich's works were banned, and his family had privileges withdrawn. [[Yuri Lyubimov]] says that at this time &quot;he waited for his arrest at night out on the landing by the lift, so that at least his family wouldn't be disturbed.&quot;{{sfnp|Wilson|1994|p=183}}

The decree's consequences for composers were harsh. Shostakovich was among those dismissed from the Conservatory altogether. For him, the loss of money was perhaps the largest blow. Others still in the Conservatory experienced an atmosphere thick with suspicion. No one wanted his work to be understood as formalist, so many resorted to accusing their colleagues of writing or performing anti-proletarian music.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (1994), p. 252&lt;/ref&gt;

In the next few years, Shostakovich composed three categories of work: film music to pay the rent, official works aimed at securing official [[rehabilitation (Soviet)|rehabilitation]], and serious works &quot;for the desk drawer&quot;. The latter included the [[Violin Concerto No. 1 (Shostakovich)|Violin Concerto No. 1]] and the song cycle ''[[From Jewish Folk Poetry]]''. The cycle was written at a time when the postwar [[anti-Semitic]] campaign was already under way, with widespread arrests, including that of Dobrushin and Yiditsky, the compilers of the book from which Shostakovich took his texts.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (2006), p. 269.&lt;/ref&gt;

The restrictions on Shostakovich's music and living arrangements were eased in 1949, when Stalin decided that the Soviets needed to send artistic representatives to the Cultural and Scientific Congress for World Peace in [[New York City]], and that Shostakovich should be among them. For Shostakovich, it was a humiliating experience, culminating in a New York press conference where he was expected to read a prepared speech. [[Nicolas Nabokov]], who was present in the audience, witnessed Shostakovich starting to read &quot;in a nervous and shaky voice&quot; before he had to break off &quot;and the speech was continued in English by a suave radio baritone&quot;.{{sfnp|Nabokov|1951|p=204}} Fully aware that Shostakovich was not free to speak his mind, Nabokov publicly asked him whether he supported the then recent denunciation of Stravinsky's music in the Soviet Union. A great admirer of Stravinsky who had been influenced by his music, Shostakovich had no alternative but to answer in the affirmative. Nabokov did not hesitate to write that this demonstrated that Shostakovich was &quot;not a free man, but an obedient tool of his government.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Nabokov (1951), p. 205.&lt;/ref&gt; Shostakovich never forgave Nabokov for this public humiliation.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (2006), p. 274.&lt;/ref&gt; That same year he was obliged to compose the [[cantata]] ''[[Song of the Forests]]'', which praised Stalin as the &quot;great gardener&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Knight |first=David B. |date=2006 |title=Landscapes in Music: Space, Place, and Time in the World's Great Music |url=https://books.google.de/books?id=jVYdAAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA84 |publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers |page=84 |isbn=9781461638599}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Stalin's death in 1953 was the biggest step toward Shostakovich's rehabilitation as a creative artist, which was marked by his [[Symphony No. 10 (Shostakovich)|Tenth Symphony]]. It features a number of [[musical quotations]] and codes (notably the [[DSCH (Dmitri Shostakovich)|DSCH]] and Elmira motifs, Elmira Nazirova being a pianist and composer who had studied under Shostakovich in the year before his dismissal from the Moscow Conservatory),&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (2006), p. 304.&lt;/ref&gt; the meaning of which is still debated, while the savage second movement, according to ''[[Testimony (Volkov book)|Testimony]]'', is intended as a musical portrait of Stalin. The Tenth ranks alongside the Fifth and Seventh as one of Shostakovich's most popular works. 1953 also saw a stream of premieres of the &quot;desk drawer&quot; works.

During the forties and fifties, Shostakovich had close relationships with two of his pupils, [[Galina Ustvolskaya]] and Elmira Nazirova. In the background to all this remained Shostakovich's first, open marriage to Nina Varzar until her death in 1954. He taught Ustvolskaya from 1937 to 1947. The nature of their relationship is far from clear: [[Mstislav Rostropovich]] described it as &quot;tender&quot;. Ustvolskaya rejected a proposal of marriage from him after Nina's death.&lt;ref&gt;Fay (2000), p. 194.&lt;/ref&gt; Shostakovich's daughter, Galina, recalled her father consulting her and Maxim about the possibility of Ustvolskaya becoming their stepmother.&lt;ref&gt;Fay (2000), p. 194; Wilson (2006), p. 297.&lt;/ref&gt; Ustvolskaya's friend Viktor Suslin said that she had been &quot;deeply disappointed&quot; in Shostakovich by the time of her graduation in 1947. The relationship with Nazirova seems to have been one-sided, expressed largely in his letters to her, and can be dated to around 1953 to 1956. He married his second wife, [[Komsomol]] activist Margarita Kainova, in 1956; the couple proved ill-matched, and divorced five years later.{{sfnp|Meyer|1995|p=392}}

In 1954, Shostakovich wrote the [[Festive Overture (Shostakovich)|Festive Overture, opus 96]]; it was used as the theme music for the [[1980 Summer Olympics]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web  |title=1980 Summer Olympics Official Report from the Organizing Committee, vol. 2 |p=283 |url=http://www.la84foundation.org/5va/reports_frmst.htm |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060622162855/http://www.la84foundation.org/5va/reports_frmst.htm |archivedate=22 June 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; (His '&quot;Theme from the film ''[[Pirogov (film)|Pirogov]]'', Opus 76a: Finale&quot; was played as the cauldron was lit at the [[2004 Summer Olympics]] in Athens, Greece.){{Citation needed|date=September 2019}}

In 1959, Shostakovich appeared on stage in Moscow at the end of a concert performance of his Fifth Symphony, congratulating [[Leonard Bernstein]] and the [[New York Philharmonic Orchestra]] for their performance (part of a concert tour of the Soviet Union). Later that year, Bernstein and the Philharmonic recorded the symphony in Boston for [[Columbia Records]].&lt;ref&gt;{{OCLC|1114176116}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=North |first=James H. |date=2006 |title=New York Philharmonic: The Authorized Recordings, 1917–2005 |url=https://books.google.de/books?id=t0ayG9YhQAQC&amp;pg=PA117 |publisher=Scarecrow Press |page=117 |isbn=9780810862395}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Joining the Party ===
The year 1960 marked another turning point in Shostakovich's life: he joined the [[Communist Party of the Soviet Union|Communist Party]]. The government wanted to appoint him General Secretary of the Composers' Union, but in order to hold that position he was required to attain Party membership. It was understood that [[Nikita Khrushchev]], the First Secretary of the Communist Party from 1953 to 1964, was looking for support from the intelligentsia's leading ranks in an effort to create a better relationship with the Soviet Union's artists.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (1994), pp. 373–80.&lt;/ref&gt; This event has variously been interpreted as a show of commitment, a mark of cowardice, the result of political pressure, or his free decision. On the one hand, the [[Apparatchik|apparat]] was undoubtedly less repressive than it had been before Stalin's death. On the other, his son recalled that the event reduced Shostakovich to tears,{{sfnp|Ho|Feofanov|1998|p=390}} and that he later told his wife Irina that he had been blackmailed.&lt;ref&gt;Manashir Yakubov, ''Programme notes'' for the 1998 Shostakovich seasons at the [[Barbican Centre|Barbican]], London).&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lev Lebedinsky]] has said that the composer was suicidal.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (1994), p. 340.&lt;/ref&gt; From 1962, he served as a delegate in the Supreme Soviet of the USSR.{{sfnp|Hulme|2010|p=xxvii}} Once he joined the Party, several articles he did not write denouncing individualism in music were published under his name in ''Pravda''. By joining the party, Shostakovich also committed himself to finally writing the homage to Lenin that he had promised before. His [[Symphony No. 12 (Shostakovich)|Twelfth Symphony]], which portrays the [[Bolshevik Revolution]] and was completed in 1961, was dedicated to Lenin and called &quot;The Year 1917.&quot;{{sfnp|MacDonald|2006|p=247}} Around this time, his health began to deteriorate.{{Citation needed|date=September 2019}}

[[File:Fotothek df roe-neg 0002796 004 Portrait Dmitri Dmitrijewitsch Schostakowitchs im Publikum der Bachfeier.jpg|thumb|upright|Shostakovich in 1950]]

Shostakovich's musical response to these personal crises was the [[String Quartet No. 8 (Shostakovich)|Eighth String Quartet]], composed in only three days. He subtitled the piece &quot;To the victims of fascism and war&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Blokker (1979), 37.&lt;/ref&gt; ostensibly in memory of the [[Bombing of Dresden in World War II|Dresden fire bombing]] that took place in 1945. Yet like the Tenth Symphony, the quartet incorporates [[Musical quotation|quotations]] from several of his past works and his musical monogram. Shostakovich confessed to his friend Isaak Glikman, &quot;I started thinking that if some day I die, nobody is likely to write a work in memory of me, so I had better write one myself.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Letter dated 19 July 1960, reprinted in Glikman: pp. 90–91&lt;/ref&gt; Several of Shostakovich's colleagues, including Natalya Vovsi-Mikhoels&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (2006), p. 263.&lt;/ref&gt; and the cellist Valentin Berlinsky,&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (2006), p. 281.&lt;/ref&gt; were also aware of the Eighth Quartet's biographical intent. Peter J. Rabinowitz has also pointed to covert references to Richard Strauss's ''[[Metamorphosen]]'' in it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Rabinowitz |first1=Peter J. |title=The Rhetoric of Reference; or, Shostakovich's Ghost Quartet |journal=Narrative |date=May 2007 |volume=15 |issue=2 |pages=239–256 |jstor=30219253 |url=https://www.academia.edu/630315 |accessdate=5 December 2017|doi=10.1353/nar.2007.0013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1962 Shostakovich got married for the third time, to Irina Supinskaya. In a letter to Glikman, he wrote, &quot;her only defect is that she is 27 years old. In all other respects she is splendid: clever, cheerful, straightforward and very likeable.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Shostakovich/Glikman (2001), p. 102.&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Galina Vishnevskaya]], who knew the Shostakoviches well, this marriage was a very happy one: &quot;It was with her that Dmitri Dmitriyevich finally came to know domestic peace... Surely, she prolonged his life by several years.&quot;{{sfnp|Vishnevskaya|1985|p=274}} In November he made his only venture into conducting, conducting a couple of his own works in [[Nizhny Novgorod|Gorky]];&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (2006), pp. 426–7.&lt;/ref&gt; otherwise he declined to conduct, citing nerves and ill health.{{Citation needed|date=September 2019}}

That year saw Shostakovich again turn to the subject of anti-Semitism in his [[Symphony No. 13 (Shostakovich)|Thirteenth Symphony]] (subtitled ''[[Babi Yar]]''). The symphony sets a number of poems by [[Yevgeny Yevtushenko]], the first of which commemorates a massacre of Ukrainian Jews during the Second World War. Opinions are divided as to how great a risk this was: the poem had been published in Soviet media, and was not banned, but remained controversial. After the symphony's premiere, Yevtushenko was forced to add a stanza to his poem that said that Russians and Ukrainians had died alongside the Jews at Babi Yar.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Sheldon |first=Richard |date=25 August 1985 |title=Neither Yevtushenko Nor Shostakovich Should Be Blamed |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1985/08/25/opinion/l-neither-yevtushenko-nor-shostakovich-should-be-blamed-213537.html |work=[[The New York Times]] |location=New York City |access-date=27 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1965 Shostakovich raised his voice in defence of poet [[Joseph Brodsky]], who was sentenced to five years of exile and hard labor. Shostakovich co-signed protests with Yevtushenko, fellow Soviet artists [[Kornei Chukovsky]], [[Anna Akhmatova]], [[Samuil Marshak]], and the French philosopher [[Jean-Paul Sartre]]. After the protests the sentence was commuted, and Brodsky returned to Leningrad.{{Citation needed|date=September 2019}}

=== Later life, and death ===
In 1964 Shostakovich composed the music for the Russian film ''[[Hamlet (1964 film)|Hamlet]]'', which was favourably reviewed by ''[[The New York Times]]'': &quot;But the lack of this aural stimulation—of Shakespeare's eloquent words—is recompensed in some measure by a splendid and stirring musical score by Dmitri Shostakovich. This has great dignity and depth, and at times an appropriate wildness or becoming levity&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Crowther, Bosley, in ''New York Times'', 15 September 1964.&lt;/ref&gt;

In later life, Shostakovich suffered from chronic ill health, but he resisted giving up cigarettes and [[vodka]]. Beginning in 1958 he suffered from a debilitating condition that particularly affected his right hand, eventually forcing him to give up piano playing; in 1965 it was diagnosed as [[poliomyelitis]]. He also suffered [[myocardial infarction|heart attacks]] the following year and again in 1971, and several falls in which he broke both his legs; in 1967 he wrote in a letter: &quot;Target achieved so far: 75% (right leg broken, left leg broken, right hand defective). All I need to do now is wreck the left hand and then 100% of my extremities will be out of order.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Shostakovich/Glikman (2001), p. 147.&lt;/ref&gt;

A preoccupation with his own mortality permeates Shostakovich's later works, such as the later quartets and the [[Symphony No. 14 (Shostakovich)|Fourteenth Symphony]] of 1969 (a song cycle based on a number of poems on the theme of death). This piece also finds Shostakovich at his most extreme with musical language, with 12-tone themes and dense polyphony throughout. He dedicated the Fourteenth to his close friend [[Benjamin Britten]], who conducted its Western premiere at the 1970 [[Aldeburgh Festival]]. The [[Symphony No. 15 (Shostakovich)|Fifteenth Symphony]] of 1971 is, by contrast, melodic and retrospective in nature, quoting [[Richard Wagner|Wagner]], [[Gioachino Rossini|Rossini]] and the composer's own Fourth Symphony.{{Citation needed|date=September 2019}}

Shostakovich died of [[lung cancer]] on 9 August 1975. A civic funeral was held; he was interred in [[Novodevichy Cemetery]], Moscow.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1975/08/11/archives/dmitri-shostakovich-dead-at-68-after-hospitalization-in-moscow.html|title=Dmitri Shostakovich Dead at 68 After Hospitalization in Moscow|date=11 August 1975|work=The New York Times|language=en-US|issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even before his death he had been commemorated with the naming of the [[Shostakovich Peninsula]] on [[Alexander Island]], [[Antarctica]].,&lt;ref&gt;[https://geonames.usgs.gov/apex/f?p=gnispq:5:0::NO::P5_ANTAR_ID:13773 Shostakovich Peninsula] [[United States Geological Survey|USGS]] 01-JAN-75&lt;/ref&gt; Despite suffering from Motor Neurone Disease (or ALS) from as early as the 1960s, Shostakovich insisted upon writing all his own correspondence and music himself, even when his right hand was virtually unusable.

[[File:Shostakovich.jpg|thumb|right|Shostakovich voting in the election of the Council of Administration of Soviet Musicians in Moscow in 1974]]
He was survived by his third wife, Irina; his daughter, Galina; and his son, [[Maxim Shostakovich|Maxim]], a pianist and conductor who was the dedicatee and first performer of some of his father's works. Shostakovich himself left behind several recordings of his own piano works; other noted interpreters of his music include [[Emil Gilels]], [[Mstislav Rostropovich]], [[Tatiana Nikolayeva]], [[Maria Yudina]], [[David Oistrakh]], and members of the [[Beethoven Quartet]].{{Citation needed|date=September 2019}}

His last work was his [[Viola Sonata (Shostakovich)|Viola Sonata]], which was first performed officially on 1 October 1975.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wilson2011&quot;&gt;{{harvp|Wilson|2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Page needed|date=November 2019}}

Shostakovich's musical influence on later composers outside the former Soviet Union has been relatively slight, although [[Alfred Schnittke]] took up his eclecticism and his contrasts between the dynamic and the static, and some of [[André Previn]]'s music shows clear links to Shostakovich's style of orchestration. His influence can also be seen in some Nordic composers, such as [[Lars-Erik Larsson]].&lt;ref&gt;Musicweb International. [http://www.musicweb-international.com/classrev/2003/Aug03/Larsson_concertinos.htm Lars-Erik Larsson.] Retrieved on 18 November 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; Many of his Russian contemporaries, and his pupils at the [[Saint Petersburg Conservatory|Leningrad Conservatory]] were strongly influenced by his style (including [[German Okunev]], [[Sergei Slonimsky]], and [[Boris Tishchenko]], whose 5th Symphony of 1978 is dedicated to Shostakovich's memory). Shostakovich's conservative idiom has grown increasingly popular with audiences both within and outside Russia, as the avant-garde has declined in influence and debate about his political views has developed.{{Citation needed|date=September 2019}}

== Music ==
{{For|a complete list of Shostakovich's compositions|List of compositions by Dmitri Shostakovich}}
{{For|a thematical selection of works by Shostakovich|Category:Compositions by Dmitri Shostakovich}}

=== Overview ===
Shostakovich's works are broadly [[Tonality|tonal]] and in the [[Romantic music|Romantic]] tradition, but with elements of [[atonality]] and [[Chromatic scale|chromaticism]]. In some of his later works (e.g., the [[String Quartet No. 12 (Shostakovich)|Twelfth Quartet]]), he made use of [[tone row]]s. His output is dominated by his cycles of symphonies and string quartets, each totaling 15. The symphonies are distributed fairly evenly throughout his career, while the quartets are concentrated towards the latter part. Among the most popular are the [[Symphony No. 5 (Shostakovich)|Fifth]] and [[Symphony No. 7 (Shostakovich)|Seventh]] Symphonies and the [[String Quartet No. 8 (Shostakovich)|Eighth]] and [[String Quartet No. 15 (Shostakovich)|Fifteenth]] Quartets. Other works include the operas ''[[Lady Macbeth of the Mtsensk District (opera)|Lady Macbeth of Mtsensk]]'', ''[[The Nose (opera)|The Nose]]'' and the unfinished ''The Gamblers,'' based on the comedy by Gogol; six concertos (two each for piano, violin and cello); two piano trios; and a large quantity of film music.{{Citation needed|date=September 2019}}

Shostakovich's music shows the influence of many of the composers he most admired: [[Johann Sebastian Bach|Bach]] in his [[fugue]]s and [[passacaglia]]s; [[Ludwig van Beethoven|Beethoven]] in the late [[quartet]]s; [[Gustav Mahler|Mahler]] in the symphonies; and [[Alban Berg|Berg]] in his use of musical codes and [[Musical quotation|quotations]]. Among Russian composers, he particularly admired [[Modest Mussorgsky]], whose operas ''[[Boris Godunov (opera)|Boris Godunov]]'' and ''[[Khovanshchina]]'' he [[Orchestration|reorchestrated]]; Mussorgsky's influence is most prominent in the wintry scenes of ''Lady Macbeth'' and the [[Symphony No. 11 (Shostakovich)|Eleventh Symphony]], as well as in satirical works such as &quot;[[Rayok (Shostakovich)|Rayok]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Fay (2000), pp. 119, 165, 224.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sergei Prokofiev|Prokofiev]]'s influence is most apparent in the earlier piano works, such as the first sonata and [[Piano Concerto No. 1 (Shostakovich)|first concerto]].{{sfnp|The New Grove|2001|pp=288, 290}} The influence of Russian church and folk music is evident in his works for unaccompanied choir of the 1950s.{{Citation needed|date=September 2019}}

Shostakovich's relationship with Stravinsky was profoundly ambivalent; as he wrote to Glikman, &quot;Stravinsky the composer I worship. Stravinsky the thinker I despise.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Shostakovich/Glikman (2001), p. 181.&lt;/ref&gt; He was particularly enamoured of the [[Symphony of Psalms|''Symphony of Psalms'']], presenting a copy of his own piano version of it to Stravinsky when the latter visited the USSR in 1962. (The meeting of the two composers was not very successful; observers commented on Shostakovich's extreme nervousness and Stravinsky's &quot;cruelty&quot; to him.)&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (1994), pp. 375–7.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many commentators have noted the disjunction between the experimental works before the 1936 denunciation and the more conservative ones that followed; the composer told Flora Litvinova, &quot;without 'Party guidance'&amp;nbsp;... I would have displayed more brilliance, used more sarcasm, I could have revealed my ideas openly instead of having to resort to camouflage.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (1994), p. 426.&lt;/ref&gt; Articles Shostakovich published in 1934 and 1935 cited [[Alban Berg|Berg]], [[Arnold Schoenberg|Schoenberg]], [[Ernst Krenek|Krenek]], [[Paul Hindemith|Hindemith]], &quot;and especially Stravinsky&quot; among his influences.&lt;ref&gt;Fay (2000), p. 88.&lt;/ref&gt; Key works of the earlier period are the [[Symphony No. 1 (Shostakovich)|First Symphony]], which combined the academicism of the conservatory with his progressive inclinations; ''[[The Nose (opera)|The Nose]]'' (&quot;The most uncompromisingly modernist of all his stage-works&quot;&lt;ref&gt;The New Grove (2001), p. 289.&lt;/ref&gt;); ''[[Lady Macbeth of the Mtsensk District (opera)|Lady Macbeth]]'', which precipitated the denunciation; and the [[Symphony No. 4 (Shostakovich)|Fourth Symphony]], described in Grove's Dictionary as &quot;a colossal synthesis of Shostakovich's musical development to date&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;The New Grove (2001), p. 290.&lt;/ref&gt; The Fourth was also the first piece in which Mahler's influence came to the fore, prefiguring the route Shostakovich took to secure his rehabilitation, while he himself admitted that the preceding two were his least successful.&lt;ref&gt;Shostakovich/Glikman (2001), p. 315.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the years after 1936, Shostakovich's symphonic works were outwardly musically conservative, regardless of any subversive political content. During this time he turned increasingly to [[chamber music|chamber]] works, a field that allowed him to explore different and often darker ideas without scrutiny.&lt;ref&gt;See also The New Grove (2001), p. 294.&lt;/ref&gt; While his chamber works were largely tonal, they gave Shostakovich an outlet for sombre reflection not welcomed in his more public works. This is most apparent in the late chamber works, which portray what Grove's Dictionary calls &quot;world of [[Purgatory|purgatorial]] numbness&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;The New Grove (2001), p. 300.&lt;/ref&gt; in some of these he included [[tone row]]s, although he treated these as melodic themes rather than [[serialism|serially]]. Vocal works are also a prominent feature of his late output, setting texts often concerned with love, death and art.{{Citation needed|date=September 2019}}

=== Jewish themes ===
Even before the Stalinist anti-Semitic campaigns in the late 1940s and early 1950s, Shostakovich showed an interest in Jewish themes. He was intrigued by [[Jewish music]]'s &quot;ability to build a jolly melody on sad intonations&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (1994), p. 268.&lt;/ref&gt; Examples of works that included Jewish themes are the [[String Quartet No. 4 (Shostakovich)|Fourth String Quartet]] (1949), the [[Violin Concerto No. 1 (Shostakovich)|First Violin Concerto]] (1948), and the ''Four Monologues on Pushkin Poems'' (1952), as well as the [[Piano Trio No. 2 (Shostakovich)|Piano Trio in E minor]] (1944). He was further inspired to write with Jewish themes when he examined [[Moshe Beregovski|Moisei Beregovski]]'s 1944 thesis on Jewish folk music.{{sfnp|Tentser|2014|p=5}}

In 1948, Shostakovich acquired a book of Jewish folk songs, from which he composed the song cycle ''[[From Jewish Folk Poetry]]''. He initially wrote eight songs meant to represent the hardships of being Jewish in the Soviet Union. To disguise this, he added three more meant to demonstrate the great life Jews had under the Soviet regime. Despite his efforts to hide the real meaning in the work, the [[Union of Composers]] refused to approve his music in 1949 under the pressure of the anti-Semitism that gripped the country. ''From Jewish Folk Poetry'' could not be performed until after Stalin's death in March 1953, along with all the other works that were forbidden.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (1994), pp. 267–9.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Self-quotations ===
Throughout his compositions, Shostakovich demonstrated a controlled use of musical quotation. This stylistic choice had been common among earlier composers, but Shostakovich developed it into a defining characteristic of his music. Rather than quoting other composers, Shostakovich preferred to quote himself. Musicologists have connected his works through their quotations.{{Citation needed|date=September 2019}}

One example is the main theme of Katerina's aria, ''Seryozha, khoroshiy moy'', from the fourth act of ''Lady Macbeth of the Mtsensk District''. It accompanies Katerina as she reunites with her lover Sergei. The aria's beauty comes as a breath of fresh air in the intense, overbearing tone of the scene. This goes well with the dialogue, as Katerina visits her lover in prison. The theme is made tragic when Sergei betrays her and finds a new lover upon blaming Katerina for his incarceration.{{Citation needed|date=September 2019}}

More than 25 years later, Shostakovich quoted this theme in his eighth string quartet. In the midst of this quartet's oppressive and somber themes, the only light and cheerful moment is when the cello introduces the Seryozha theme about three minutes into the fourth movement. The quotation uses Katerina's hope amid misery as a means to demonstrate the hope of those oppressed by fascists.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
 |url= http://www.quartets.de/compositions/ssq08.html
 |title= Quartet No. 8
 |last= Harris
 |first= Stephen
 |date= 9 April 2016
 |website= Shostakovich: The String Quartets
 |accessdate= 18 February 2018
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This theme emerges once again in his 14th string quartet. As in the eighth, the cello introduces the theme, but for an entirely different purpose. The last in Shostakovich's &quot;quartet of quartets&quot;, the fourteenth serves to honor the cellist of the Beethoven String Quartet, Sergei Shirinsky. Rather than reflecting the original theme's intentions, the quotation serves as a dedication to Shirinsky.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
 |url= http://www.quartets.de/compositions/ssq14.html
 |title= Quartet No. 14
 |last= Harris
 |first= Stephen
 |date= 24 August 2015
 |website= Shostakovich: The String Quartets
 |accessdate= 18 February 2018
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Posthumous publications ===
In 2004, the musicologist Olga Digonskaya discovered a trove of Shostakovich manuscripts at the Glinka State Central Museum of Musical Culture in Moscow. In a cardboard file were some &quot;300 pages of musical sketches, pieces and scores&quot; in Shostakovich's hand. &quot;A composer friend bribed Shostakovich's housemaid to regularly deliver the contents of Shostakovich's office waste bin to him, instead of taking it to the garbage. Some of those cast-offs eventually found their way into the Glinka. ... The Glinka archive 'contained a huge number of pieces and compositions which were completely unknown or could be traced quite indirectly,' Digonskaya said.&quot;{{r|LATimes20111127}}

Among these were Shostakovich's piano and vocal sketches for a prologue to an opera, [[Orango (opera)|''Orango'' (1932)]]. They were orchestrated by the British composer [[Gerard McBurney]] and premiered in December 2011 by the Los Angeles Philharmonic.&lt;ref name=LATimes20111127&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://articles.latimes.com/2011/nov/27/entertainment/la-ca-orango-opera-20111127
 | title = Shostakovich's 'Orango' found, finished, set for Disney Hall
 | last1 = Loiko | first1 = Sergei L. | last2 = Johnson | first2 = Reed
 | date = 27 November 2011
 | work = Los Angeles Times
 | accessdate = 17 February 2012
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Ayala |first=Ted |url=http://www.crescentavalleyweekly.com/leisure/12/07/2011/no-monkey-business-with-lapo's-world-premiere-of-shostakovich’s-'orango'/|title=No Monkey Business with LAPO's World Premiere of Shostakovich's 'Orango' |publisher=Crescenta Valley Weekly |date=7 December 2011 |accessdate=10 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
 |last              = Sirén
 |first             = Vesa
 |publication-date  = 6 April 2009
 |title             = Šostakovitšin apinaooppera löytyi
 |trans-title       = The ape opera by Shostakovich was found
 |periodical        = Helsingin Sanomat
 |publication-place = Helsinki
 |publisher         = Sanoma Oy
 |language          = fi
 |pages             = C1
 |url               = http://www.hs.fi/kulttuuri/artikkeli/%C5%A0ostakovit%C5%A1in+kadonnut+apina-ooppera+kes%C3%A4ll%C3%A4+esityskuntoon/1135244971728
 |accessdate        = 6 April 2009
 |url-status           = dead
 |archiveurl        = https://web.archive.org/web/20090408124116/http://www.hs.fi/kulttuuri/artikkeli/%C5%A0ostakovit%C5%A1in+kadonnut+apina-ooppera+kes%C3%A4ll%C3%A4+esityskuntoon/1135244971728
 |archivedate       = 8 April 2009
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |date=21 March 2009 |title=Unknown Shostakovich Opera Discovered |website=Artsjournal |via=[[Le Devoir]] |url=http://www.artsjournal.com/artsjournal1/2009/03/unknown_shostak.shtml |access-date=5 April 2009 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090903111745/http://www.artsjournal.com/artsjournal1/2009/03/unknown_shostak.shtml|archivedate=3 September 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Philadelphia Orchestra program|date=27 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Criticism ===
According to McBurney, opinion is divided on whether Shostakovich's music is &quot;of visionary power and originality, as some maintain, or, as others think, derivative, trashy, empty and second-hand&quot;.{{sfnp|McBurney|2002|p=283}} [[William Walton]], his British contemporary, described him as &quot;the greatest composer of the 20th century&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''British Composers in Interview'' by R Murray Schafer (Faber 1960).&lt;/ref&gt; Musicologist [[David Fanning (musicologist)|David Fanning]] concludes in Grove's Dictionary that &quot;Amid the conflicting pressures of official requirements, the mass suffering of his fellow countrymen, and his personal ideals of humanitarian and public service, he succeeded in forging a musical language of colossal emotional power.&quot;{{sfnp|The New Grove|2001|p=280}}

Some modern composers have been critical. [[Pierre Boulez]] dismissed Shostakovich's music as &quot;the second, or even third [[Olive oil extraction#Traditional method: olive press|pressing]] of [[Gustav Mahler|Mahler]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;McBurney (2002), p. 288.&lt;/ref&gt; The Romanian composer and [[Anton Webern|Webern]] disciple [[Philip Gershkovich]] called Shostakovich &quot;a&amp;nbsp;hack in a trance&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;McBurney (2002), p. 290.&lt;/ref&gt; A related complaint is that Shostakovich's style is vulgar and strident: [[Igor Stravinsky|Stravinsky]] wrote of ''[[Lady Macbeth of the Mtsensk District (opera)|Lady Macbeth]]'': &quot;brutally hammering&amp;nbsp;... and monotonous&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;McBurney (2002), p. 286.&lt;/ref&gt; English composer and musicologist [[Robin Holloway]] described his music as &quot;battleship-grey in melody and harmony, factory-functional in structure; in content all rhetoric and coercion.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Holloway |first=Robin |date=26 August 2000 |title=Shostakovich horrors |journal=[[The Spectator]] |p=41 |url=http://archive.spectator.co.uk/article/26th-august-2000/41/music |access-date=29 June 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1980s, the Finnish conductor and composer [[Esa-Pekka Salonen]] was critical of Shostakovich and refused to conduct his music. For instance, he said in 1987:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Shostakovich is in many ways a polar counter-force for Stravinsky. [...] When I have said that the 7th symphony of Shostakovich is a dull and unpleasant composition, people have responded: &quot;Yes, yes, but think of the background of that symphony.&quot; Such an attitude does no good to anyone.&lt;ref&gt;Salonen, Esa-Pekka &amp; Otonkoski, Lauri: ''Kirja – puhetta musiikitta'', p. 73. Helsinki: Tammi. {{ISBN|951-30-6599-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Salonen has since performed and recorded several of Shostakovich's works, including the Piano Concertos Nos. 1 and 2 (1999),&lt;ref&gt;{{OCLC|920558136}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Violin Concerto No. 1 (2010),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://theartsdesk.com/node/4355/view |title=BBC Proms: Batiashvili, Philharmonia Orchestra, Salonen |last=Brown |first=Ismene |date=17 August 2011 |website=theartsdesk.com |publisher=The Arts Desk Ltd. |location=Esher |access-date=25 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Prologue to ''Orango'' and the Symphony No. 4 (2012).&lt;ref&gt;{{OCLC|809867885}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is certainly true that Shostakovich borrows extensively from the material and styles both of earlier composers and of [[popular music]]; the vulgarity of &quot;low&quot; music is a notable influence on this &quot;greatest of eclectics&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Haas, ''Shostakovich's Eighth: C minor Symphony against the Grain'' p. 125.&lt;/ref&gt; McBurney traces this to the [[avant-garde]] artistic circles of the early Soviet period in which Shostakovich moved early in his career, and argues that these borrowings were a deliberate technique to allow him to create &quot;patterns of contrast, repetition, exaggeration&quot; that gave his music large-scale structure.&lt;ref&gt;McBurney (2002), p. 295.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Personality ==
[[File:ShostakovichwithIvan Sollertinsky.jpg|thumb|Shostakovich with close friend [[Ivan Sollertinsky]]]]
Shostakovich was in many ways an obsessive man: according to his daughter he was &quot;obsessed with cleanliness&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Ardov,''Memories of Shostakovich'' p. 139.&lt;/ref&gt; He synchronised the clocks in his apartment and regularly sent himself cards to test how well the postal service was working. [[Elizabeth Wilson (cellist)|Elizabeth Wilson]]'s ''Shostakovich: A Life Remembered'' indexes 26 references to his nervousness. Mikhail Druskin remembers that even as a young man the composer was &quot;fragile and nervously agile&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (1994), pp. 41–5.&lt;/ref&gt; Yuri Lyubimov comments, &quot;The fact that he was more vulnerable and receptive than other people was no doubt an important feature of his genius.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (1994), p. 183.&lt;/ref&gt; In later life, [[Krzysztof Meyer]] recalled, &quot;his face was a bag of tics and grimaces.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (1994), p. 462.&lt;/ref&gt;

In Shostakovich's lighter moods, sport was one of his main recreations, although he preferred spectating or umpiring to participating (he was a qualified [[referee (association football)|football referee]]). His favourite football club was [[Zenit Leningrad]] (now Zenit Saint Petersburg), which he would watch regularly.&lt;ref&gt;Mentioned in his personal correspondence (Shostakovich, tr. Phillips (2001)), as well as other sources.&lt;/ref&gt; He also enjoyed [[card game]]s, particularly [[Patience (game)|patience]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Wilson2011&quot; /&gt;{{Page needed|date=November 2019}}

Shostakovich was fond of [[satirical]] writers such as [[Gogol]], [[Anton Chekhov|Chekhov]] and [[Mikhail Zoshchenko]]. Zoshchenko's influence in particular is evident in his letters, which include wry parodies of Soviet [[officialese]]. Zoshchenko noted the contradictions in the composer's character: &quot;he is&amp;nbsp;... frail, fragile, withdrawn, an infinitely direct, pure child&amp;nbsp;... [but also] hard, acid, extremely intelligent, strong perhaps, despotic and not altogether good-natured (although cerebrally good-natured).&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in Fay (2000), p. 121.&lt;/ref&gt;

Shostakovich was diffident by nature: Flora Litvinova has said he was &quot;completely incapable of saying 'No' to anybody.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (1994), p. 162.&lt;/ref&gt; This meant he was easily persuaded to sign official statements, including a denunciation of [[Andrei Sakharov]] in 1973.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fay263&quot;/&gt; His widow later told [[Helsingin Sanomat]] that his name was included without his permission.&lt;ref&gt;Vesa Sirén: &quot;Mitä setämies sai sanoa Neuvostoliitossa?&quot; in [[Helsingin Sanomat]] on page A 6, 2 November 2018&lt;/ref&gt; But he was willing to try to help constituents in his capacities as chairman of the Composers' Union and Deputy to the Supreme Soviet. [[Oleg Prokofiev]] said, &quot;he tried to help so many people that&amp;nbsp;... less and less attention was paid to his pleas.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (1994), p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fay263&quot;/&gt; When asked if he believed in God, Shostakovich said &quot;No, and I am very sorry about it.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fay263&quot;&gt;Fay (2000), p. 263.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Orthodoxy and revisionism ==
[[File:DSCH motif.svg|thumb|Shostakovich represented himself in some works with the [[DSCH motif]], consisting of D-E{{flat}}-C-B.]]
{{Main|Testimony (Volkov book)}}
Shostakovich's response to official criticism and whether he used music as a kind of covert dissidence is a matter of dispute. He outwardly conformed to government policies and positions, reading speeches and putting his name to articles expressing the government line.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (2006), pp. 369–70.&lt;/ref&gt; But it is evident he disliked many aspects of the regime, as confirmed by his family, his letters to Isaak Glikman, and the satirical [[cantata]] &quot;[[Rayok (Shostakovich)|Rayok]]&quot;, which ridiculed the &quot;anti-formalist&quot; campaign and was kept hidden until after his death.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (2006), p. 336.&lt;/ref&gt; He was a close friend of [[Marshal of the Soviet Union]] [[Mikhail Tukhachevsky]], who was executed in 1937 during the [[Great Purge]].{{Citation needed|date=September 2019}}

It is also uncertain to what extent Shostakovich expressed his opposition to the state in his music. The [[Historical revisionism|revisionist]] view was put forth by [[Solomon Volkov]] in the 1979 book ''[[Testimony (Volkov book)|Testimony]]'', which claimed to be Shostakovich's memoirs dictated to Volkov. The book alleged that many of the composer's works contained coded anti-government messages, placing Shostakovich in a tradition of Russian artists outwitting censorship that goes back at least to [[Alexander Pushkin]]. He incorporated many [[Musical quotation|quotations]] and [[motif (music)|motifs]] in his work, most notably his musical [[musical cryptogram|signature]] [[DSCH motif|DSCH]].&lt;ref&gt;This appears in several of his works, including the ''Pushkin Monologues'', Symphony No. 10, and String Quartets Nos 5, 8 &amp; 11.&lt;/ref&gt; His longtime musical collaborator [[Yevgeny Mravinsky]] said, &quot;Shostakovich very often explained his intentions with very specific images and connotations.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Wilson (1994), p. 139.&lt;/ref&gt;

The revisionist perspective has subsequently been supported by his children, Maxim and Galina, although Maxim said in 1981 that Volkov's book was not his father's work.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Shostakovich's son says moves against artists led to defection|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1981/05/14/world/shostakovich-s-son-says-moves-against-artists-led-to-defection.html|accessdate=31 March 2017|work=The New York Times|date=14 May 1981|location=New York|language=English|quote=Asked about the authenticity of a book published in the West after his father's death, and described as his memoirs, Mr. Shostakovich replied: ''These are not my father's memoirs. This is a book by Solomon Volkov. Mr. Volkov should reveal how the book was written.'' Mr. Shostakovich said language in the book attributed to his father, as well as several contradictions and inaccuracies, led him to doubt the book's authenticity.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Volkov has further argued, both in ''Testimony'' and in ''Shostakovich and Stalin'', that Shostakovich adopted the role of the ''[[yurodivy]]'' or [[holy fool]] in his relations with the government. Other prominent revisionists are [[Ian MacDonald]], whose book ''The New Shostakovich'' put forward further revisionist interpretations of his music, and Elizabeth Wilson, whose ''Shostakovich: A Life Remembered'' provides testimony from many of the composer's acquaintances.{{Citation needed|date=September 2019}}

Musicians and scholars including Laurel Fay&lt;ref&gt;Fay (2000), p. 4. &quot;Whether ''Testimony'' faithfully reproduces Shostakovich's confidences ... in a form and context he would have recognized and approved for publication remains doubtful. Yet even were [its] claim to authenticity not in doubt, it would still furnish a poor source for the serious biographer.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Richard Taruskin]] contest the authenticity and debate the significance of ''Testimony'', alleging that Volkov compiled it from a combination of recycled articles, gossip, and possibly some information directly from the composer. Fay documents these allegations in her 2002 article 'Volkov's ''Testimony'' reconsidered',{{sfnp|Fay|2002}} showing that the only pages of the original ''Testimony'' manuscript that Shostakovich had signed and verified are word-for-word reproductions of earlier interviews he gave, none of which are controversial. Against this, Allan B. Ho and Dmitry Feofanov have pointed out that at least two of the signed pages contain controversial material: for instance, &quot;on the first page of chapter 3, where [Shostakovich] notes that the plaque that reads 'In this house lived [[Vsevolod Meyerhold|[Vsevolod] Meyerhold]]' should also say 'And in this house his wife was brutally murdered'.&quot;{{sfnp|Ho|Feofanov|1998|p=211}}

== Recorded legacy ==
[[File:Russia-2000-stamp-Dmitri Shostakovich.jpg|thumb|A Russian stamp in Shostakovich's memory, published in 2000]]
In May 1958, during a visit to Paris, Shostakovich recorded his two piano concertos with [[André Cluytens]], as well as some short piano works. These were issued by [[EMI]] on an LP, reissued by [[Seraphim Records]] on LP, and eventually digitally remastered and released on CD. Shostakovich recorded the two concertos in stereo in Moscow for [[Melodiya]]. Shostakovich also played the piano solos in recordings of the Cello Sonata, Op. 40 with cellist [[Daniil Shafran]] and also with [[Mstislav Rostropovich]]; the Violin Sonata, Op. 134, with violinist [[David Oistrakh]]; and the Piano Trio, Op. 67 with violinist David Oistrakh and cellist [[Miloš Sádlo]]. There is also a short sound film of Shostakovich as soloist in a 1930s concert performance of the closing moments of his first piano concerto. A colour film of Shostakovich supervising one of his operas, from his last year, was also made.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C5P4x2POjSM |title=Dmitri Shostakovich filmed in 1975 during rehearsals |publisher=YouTube |date=9 January 2008 |accessdate=7 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A major achievement was EMI's recording of the original, unexpurgated opera ''Lady Macbeth of Mtsensk''. There was at least one recording of the cleaned-up version, ''Katerina Ismailova'', that Shostakovich had made to satisfy Soviet censorship. But when conductor Mstislav Rostropovich and his wife, soprano [[Galina Vishnevskaya]] were finally allowed to emigrate to the West, the composer begged them to record the full original score, which they did in April 1978. It features Vishnevskaya as Katerina, [[Nicolai Gedda]] as Sergei, Dimiter Petkov as Boris Ismailov and a brilliant supporting cast under Rostropovich's direction.&lt;ref&gt;{{OCLC|42448562}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Awards ==
Belgium: Member of the [[Royal Academy of Science, Letters and Fine Arts of Belgium]] (1960)&lt;ref&gt;Index biographique des membres et associés de l'Académie royale de Belgique (1769–2005). (in French)&lt;/ref&gt;

Denmark: [[Léonie Sonning Music Prize]] (1973)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sonningmusic.org/the-music-prize/1973-dmitrij-sjostakovitj.aspx |title=Léonie Sonning Prize 1973 Dmitri Sjostakovitj |last= |first= |date=2019 |website=sonningmusic.org |publisher=The Léonie Sonning Music Foundation |access-date=25 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Finland: [[Wihuri Sibelius Prize]] (1958){{sfnp|Hulme|2010|p=xxvi}}

Soviet Union:
: [[File:HeroOfSocialistLabour.jpg|10px]] [[Hero of Socialist Labor]] (1966)&lt;ref&gt;''[https://archive.org/details/shostakovichlife0000fayl &lt;!-- quote=prize. --&gt; Shostakovich: A Life]'', Laurel E. Fay, p. 249&lt;/ref&gt;
: [[File:Order of Lenin ribbon bar.png|25px]] [[Order of Lenin]] (1946, 1956, 1966)&lt;ref&gt;''[https://archive.org/details/shostakovichlife0000fayl &lt;!-- quote=prize. --&gt; Shostakovich: A Life]'', Laurel E. Fay, pp. 153; 198; 249&lt;/ref&gt;
: [[File:Order october revolution rib.png|25px]] [[Order of the October Revolution]] (1971){{sfnp|Hulme|2010|p=xxix}}
: [[File:Orderredbannerlabor rib.png|25px]] [[Order of the Red Banner of Labour]] (1940){{sfnp|Hulme|2010|p=xxii}}
: [[File:People Artist of the USSR1.jpg|10px]] [[People's Artist of the USSR]] (1954){{sfnp|Hulme|2010|p=xxv}}
: [[File:Narodny artist RSFSR.jpg|10px]] People's Artist of the [[RSFSR]] (1948){{sfnp|Hulme|2010|p=xxiv}}
: [[World Peace Council prizes|International Peace Prize]] (1954){{sfnp|Hulme|2010|p=xxv}}
: [[File:Lenin Prize Medal.JPG|10px]] [[Lenin Prize]] (1958 – for the 11th symphony &quot;1905&quot;){{sfnp|Hulme|2010|p=xxvi}}
: [[File:Stalin Medal.png|10px]] [[File:Stalin Medal.png|10px]] [[File:Stalin Medal.png|10px]] [[File:Stalin Medal.png|10px]] [[File:Stalin Medal.png|10px]] [[State Stalin Prize|State Prize]] (1941 – for Piano Quintet; 1942 – for the [[Symphony No. 7 (Shostakovich)|7th (&quot;Leningrad&quot;) Symphony]]; 1946 – for Piano Trio no. 2; 1950 – for ''[[Songs of the Forest]]''; 1952 – for 10 poems for chorus){{sfnp|Hulme|2010|pp=xxiii–xxv}}
: [[Glinka State Prize of the RSFSR]] (1968 – for the poem &quot;The Execution of Stepan Razin&quot; for bass, chorus and orchestra){{sfnp|Hulme|2010|p=xxviii}}
: Glinka State Prize of the RSFSR (1974 – for the 14th string quartet and choral cycle &quot;Fidelity&quot;){{sfnp|Hulme|2010|p=xxix}}

United Kingdom: Gold Medal of the [[Royal Philharmonic Society]] (1966)&lt;ref&gt;{{Britannica|541847|Dmitry Shostakovich}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==

* [[Music written in all major and/or minor keys]]
* [[Sinyavsky–Daniel trial#Internal reaction|Sinyavsky–Daniel trial]]
* ''[[The Noise of Time]]'' – a novel concerning Shostakovich by English author [[Julian Barnes]].

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|25em}}

== References ==
{{Refbegin|30em}}
* {{Cite book
 | last = Ardov
 | first = Michael
 | year = 2004
 | title = Memories of Shostakovich
 | publisher=Short Books
 | isbn = 978-1-904095-64-4
 }}
* {{Cite book |last1=Blokker |first1=Roy |year=1979 |title=The Music of Dmitri Shostakovich, the Symphonies |series=The great composers |publisher=Associated Univ Press |isbn=978-083861948-3 |ref=harv |url=https://archive.org/details/musicofdmitrisho0000blok }}
* {{Cite book |last1=Edwards |first1=Robert |year=2006 |title=White Death: Russia's War on Finland 1939–40 |location=London |publisher=Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson |isbn=978-0-297-84630-7 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book |editor-last1=Fairclough |editor-first1=Pauline |editor-last2=Fanning |editor-first2=David |date=November 2008 |title=The Cambridge Companion to Shostakovich |edition=1st |series=[[Cambridge Companions to Music]] |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=9780521603157
}}
* {{Cite book
 | last1 = Fanning
 | first1 = David
 | last2 = Fay
 | first2 = Laurel
 | year = 2001
 | chapter = Dmitri Shostakovich
 | editor-last1=Sadie |editor-first1=Stanley |editor-link1=Stanley Sadie
 | editor-last2=Tyrrell |editor-first2=John |editor-link2=John Tyrrell (musicologist)
 | title = The New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians
 | edition=2nd
 | publisher=Macmillan
 | ref=CITEREFThe New Grove2001
 | title-link = The New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians
 }}
* {{Cite book
 | last = Fay
 | first = Laurel
 | year = 2000
 | title = Shostakovich: A Life
 | publisher = Oxford University Press
 | isbn = 978-0-19-513438-4
 | ref = harv
 | url = https://archive.org/details/shostakovichlife00fayl
 }}
* {{Cite book
 | last = Fay
 | first = Laurel
 | year = 2002
 | chapter = Volkov's ''Testimony'' Reconsidered
 | pages=22–66
 | chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-bn4yMWnpOAC&amp;pg=PA22&amp;sqi=2
 | editor-last= Hamrick Brown |editor-first=Malcolm
 | title = A Shostakovich Casebook
 | publisher=Indiana University Press
 | isbn = 978-0-253-21823-0 |ref=harv
 }}
* {{Cite book
 | last = Haas
 | first = David
 | chapter = Shostakovich's Eighth: C minor Symphony against the Grain
 | editor-last=Bartlett |editor-first=Rosamund
 | editorlink = Rosamund Bartlett
 | title = Shostakovich in Context
 }}
* {{Cite book
 |last1=Ho |first1=Allan
 |last2=Feofanov |first2=Dmitry 
 | year = 1998
 | title = Shostakovich Reconsidered
 | publisher=Toccata Press
 | isbn = 978-0-907689-56-0 |ref=harv
 }}
* {{cite book
 | first=Derek C.
 | last=Hulme
 | title=Dmitri Shostakovich Catalogue: The First Hundred Years and Beyond
 | year=2010
 | origyear=2002
 | edition=4th
 | publisher=Scarecrow Press
 | location=Lanham, Maryland
 | isbn=978-0-8108-7264-6 |ref=harv
 }}
* {{cite book
 |last=Ivashkin
 |first=Alexander
 |editor-last1=Kirkman
 |editor-first1=Andrew
 |editor-last2=Ivashkin
 |editor-first2=Alexander
 |date=2016
 |title=Contemplating Shostakovich: Life, Music and Film
 |chapter=Shostakovich, Old Believers and New Minimalists
 |url=https://books.google.de/books?id=MCspDAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA20
 |publisher=Routledge
 |isbn=9781317161028
 |ref=harv
 }}
* {{Cite book
 | editor-last = Kovnatskaya
 | editor-first = Liudmila
 | editorlink = Liudmila Kovnatskaya
 | year = 1996
 | title = D. D. Shostakovich: Collections to the 90th anniversary
 | publisher=St Petersburg: Kompozitor
 }}
* {{Cite book
 | editor-last = Kovnatskaya
 | editor-first = Liudmila
 | year = 2000
 | title = D. D. Shostakovich: Between the moment and Eternity. Documents. Articles. Publications
 | publisher=St Petersburg: Kompozitor
 }}
* {{Cite book
 | last = MacDonald
 | first = Ian
 | authorlink = Ian MacDonald
 | year = 2006
 | orig-year = 1990
 | title = The New Shostakovich
 | publisher=Pimlico
 | isbn = 978-184595064-4 |ref=harv
 }}
* {{cite web
 | last = MacDonald
 | first = Ian
 | title = Shostakovichiana
 | work=Music Under Soviet Rule
 | url = http://www.siue.edu/~aho/musov/dmitri.html
 | accessdate =17 August 2005 |ref=harv
 }}
* {{Cite book
 | last = McBurney
 | first = Gerard
 | year = 2002
 | chapter = Whose Shostakovich?
 | editor-last= Hamrick Brown |editor-first=Malcolm
 | title = A Shostakovich Casebook
 | publisher=Indiana University Press
 | isbn = 978-0-253-21823-0 |ref=harv
 }}
* {{cite book
 |last=Meyer
 |first=Krzysztof
 |author-link=Krzysztof Meyer
 |date=1995
 |title=Schostakowitsch – Sein Leben, sein Werk, seine Zeit
 |publisher=Gustav Lübbe Verlag
 |location=Bergisch Gladbach
 |isbn=978-3785707722
 |language=de
 |ref=harv
 ||postscript=. [Orig. in Polish 1973.]
}}
* {{Cite book
 | last = Nabokov
 | first = Nicolas
 | year = 1951
 | title = Old Friends and New Music
 | publisher=Hamish Hamilton
 | ref=harv
 }}
* {{cite web
 |last=van Rijen 
 |first=Onno 
 |title=Opus by Shostakovich 
 |work=Shostakovich &amp; Other Soviet Composers 
 |url=http://home.wanadoo.nl/ovar/shosopus/shosopus.htm 
 |accessdate=17 August 2005 
 |url-status=dead  |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20050905065218/http://home.wanadoo.nl/ovar/shosopus/shosopus.htm |archivedate=5 September 2005 
 }}
* {{Cite book
 | last = Sheinberg
 | first = Esti
 | date=29 December 2000
 | title = Irony, satire, parody and the grotesque in the music of Shostakovich
 | publisher=Ashgate
 | location= UK
 | page=378
 | isbn = 978-0-7546-0226-2
 }}
* {{ cite book |author=Shostakovich, Dmitri |others=Compiled by L. Grigoryev and Y.. Platek. Translated by Angus and Neilian Roxburgh |year=1981 |title=Shostakovich: About Himself and His Times  |location=Moscow |publisher=Progress Publishers |ref=CITEREFShostakovich/Grigoryev &amp; Platek1981
}}
* {{Cite book
 | author1= Shostakovich, Dmitri
 |others=Compiled and edited by [[Solomon Volkov]]
 | title = Testimony: The Memoirs of Dmitri Shostakovich
 | postscript=:
 |title-link=Testimony (Volkov book)
 }}
:: {{Cite book |title=- |edition=1st |year=1979 |publisher=Faber and Faber |isbn=978-0-571-11829-8 |ref=CITEREFShostakovich/Volkov1979
}}
:: {{Cite book |title=- |edition=7th |year=2000 |publisher=Proscenium |isbn=978-0-87910-021-6 |ref=CITEREFShostakovich/Volkov2000
}}
:: {{Cite book |title=- |edition=25th |year=2004 |publisher=[[Hal Leonard Corporation|Hal Leonard]] |isbn=978-161774771-7 |ref=CITEREFShostakovich/Volkov2004
}}
* {{Cite book
 | author1= Shostakovich, Dmitri
 | author2=Glikman, Isaak |translator=Phillips, Anthony
 | year = 2001
 | title = Story of a Friendship: The Letters of Dmitry Shostakovich to Isaak Glikman
 | publisher=Cornell University Press
 | isbn = 978-0-8014-3979-7
 }}
* {{cite book
 | last=Tentser
 | first=Alexander
 | editor-last=Tentser
 | editor-first=Alexander
 | date=2014
 | title=The Jewish Experience in Classical Music: Shostakovich and Asia
 | chapter=Dmitri Shostakovich and Jewish Music: The Voice of an Oppressed People
 | url=https://www.cambridgescholars.com/download/sample/60924
 | publisher=Cambridge Scholars Publishing
 | isbn=978-1-4438-5467-2
 | ref = harv
}}
* {{Cite book
 | authorlink = Richard Taruskin
 | last = Taruskin
 | first = Richard
 | year = 2009
 | title = On Russian Music
 | publisher = University of California Press
 | isbn = 978-0-520-24979-0 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |last=Vishnevskaya
 |first=Galina
 |author-link=Galina Vishnevskaya
 |year=1985
 |translator=Guy Daniels
 |title=Galina, A Russian Story
 |edition=1st
 |publisher=[[Harcourt Brace Jovanovich]]
 |isbn=978-0156343206
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{Cite book
 | last = Volkov
 | first = Solomon
 | year = 2004
 | title = Shostakovich and Stalin: The Extraordinary Relationship Between the Great Composer and the Brutal Dictator
 | publisher=Knopf
 | isbn = 978-0-375-41082-6 |ref=harv
 }}
* {{Cite book
 | last = Wilson
 | first = Elizabeth
 | title = Shostakovich: A Life Remembered
 | postscript=:
}}
:: {{Cite book |title=- |edition=1st |year=1994 |publisher=Princeton University Press |isbn=978-069102971-9 |ref=CITEREFWilson1994}}
:: {{Cite book |title=- |edition=2nd |year=2006 |publisher=Faber and Faber |isbn=978-057122050-2 |ref=CITEREFWilson2006}}
:: {{Cite book |title=- |edition=2nd |year=2006b |publisher=Princeton University Press |isbn=978-0691128863 |ref=CITEREFWilson2006b }}
:: - (2nd ed. - Kindle) Faber and Faber. 2010. {{ISBN|978-057126115-4}}.
:: {{Cite book |title=- |edition=New |year=2011 |publisher=Faber and Faber |isbn=9780571261154 |ref=CITEREFWilson2011}}
{{Refend}}

== External links ==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Commons category}}
* {{Britannica|541847|Dmitry Shostakovich}}
* [http://www.sikorski.de/media/files/1/12/190/249/336/8953/schostakowitsch_werkverzeichnis.pdf Complete catalogue of works, with many additional comments] by [[Hans Sikorski|Sikorski]]
* [http://www.siue.edu/~aho/musov/deb/deb.html The Shostakovich Debate: Interpreting the composer's life and music]
* [http://www.brightlightsfilm.com/76/76testimony_grossman_morse.php One Resurrected Drunkard: A Dialogue on Tony Palmer's ''Testimony''] Article on Palmer's Shostakovich film in ''Bright Lights Film Journal''
* [http://arshakandriasov.com/dmitry-shostakovich-about-iosif-andriasov/ Dmitry Shostakovich about Iosif Andriasov]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070103011523/http://www.scribemedia.org/2006/11/07/shostakovich/ Journey of Dmitri Shostakovich] – an interview with filmmaker Helga Landauer
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20040223030309/http://www.epitonic.com/artists/dimitrishostakovich.html Epitonic.com: Dimitri Shostakovich] featuring tracks from ''Written with the Heart's Blood''
* {{YouTube|mjK7Hnxpmsg|Video of Shostakovich}}, at a rehearsal of his opera ''[[The Nose (opera)|The Nose]]'' in 1975
* {{BBC composer page|shostakovich|Shostakovich}}
* [http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio3/shostakovich/feature.shtml BBC Presenter Stephen Johnson on Shostakovich and Depression]
* [https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0174463/ ''Altovaya sonata. Dmitriy Shostakovich (1981)'' (''Sonata for Viola'')], documentary film on Shostakovich's life, and difficulties with [[Tikhon Khrennikov|Khrennikov]] and Stalin
* [http://dsch1975.web.fc2.com/dsch-e.html Complete opus list, comprehensive discography, bibliography, filmography, list of first performances and links] by Yosuke Kudo
* [http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio3/discoveringmusic/listeninglibrary.shtml#s Archive of BBC's &quot;Discovering Music&quot; radio show], featuring Shostakovich's Symphony No. 5, Symphony No. 10, String Quartet No. 8, and Cello Concerto No. 1.
* [http://www.classicalarchives.com/main/s.html#SHOSTAKOVICH Various pieces by Shostakovich in streaming media by Classical Music Archives]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110713102123/http://www.jeroenriemsdijk.com/212/index.php?100 Shostakovich: the 24 preludes Op. 34]
* [http://listserv.uh.edu/archives/dsch-l.html University of Houston Moderated Discussion List: Dmitri Shostakovich and other Russian Composers]
* [http://www.quartets.de/ Shostakovich: the string quartets]
* [http://uiuc.libguides.com/shostakovich Shostakovich: the quartets in context]
* [http://www.bruceduffie.com/shostakovich.html Interview with the composer's son, conductor Maxim Shostakovich] by Bruce Duffie, 10 July 1992
* {{cite web|url=http://www.cpgb.org.uk/article.php?article_id=1000592 |title=Shostakovich: Revolutionary life, revolutionary legacy |author=Paterson, Harry |date=21 December 2000 |work=Weekly Worker |accessdate=31 August 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110608062100/http://www.cpgb.org.uk/article.php?article_id=1000592 |archivedate=8 June 2011 }}
* [http://www.azer.com/aiweb/categories/magazine/ai111_folder/111_articles/111_shostokovich_elmira.html &quot;Shostakovich's Tenth Symphony: The Azerbaijani Link – Elmira Nazirova&quot;] by Aida Huseinova, in Azerbaijan International, Vol. 11:1 (Spring 2003), pp.&amp;nbsp;54–59.
* {{cite web |url=http://www.siue.edu/~aho/ShostakovichWars/SW.pdf |title=The Shostakovich Wars |author1=Ho, Allan B.  |author2=Feofanov, Dmitry |year=2011 |publisher=Southern Illinois University – Edwardsville|accessdate=31 August 2011}}
* {{IMDb name|id=0006291}}

{{Dmitri Shostakovich}}
{{Modernist composers}}
{{Wihuri Sibelius Prize}}
{{Léonie Sonning Music Prize laureates}}

{{Featured article}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Shostakovich, Dmitri}}
[[Category:Dmitri Shostakovich| ]]
[[Category:1906 births]]
[[Category:1975 deaths]]
[[Category:20th-century classical composers]]
[[Category:20th-century classical pianists]]
[[Category:Burials at Novodevichy Cemetery]]
[[Category:Deaths from cancer in the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Communist Party of the Soviet Union members]]
[[Category:Russian ballet composers]]
[[Category:Composers for piano]]
[[Category:Composers for viola]]
[[Category:Deaths from lung cancer]]
[[Category:Heroes of Socialist Labour]]
[[Category:Jazz-influenced classical composers]]
[[Category:Lenin Prize winners]]
[[Category:Male film score composers]]
[[Category:Male opera composers]]
[[Category:Members of the Serbian Academy of Sciences and Arts]]
[[Category:Members of the Royal Academy of Belgium]]
[[Category:Modernist composers]]
[[Category:People from Saint Petersburg]]
[[Category:People from Saint Petersburg Governorate]]
[[Category:People's Artists of the USSR]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Decoration for Services to the Republic of Austria]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Léonie Sonning Music Prize]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Friendship of Peoples]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Lenin]]
[[Category:Recipients of the USSR State Prize]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Shevchenko National Prize]]
[[Category:Royal Philharmonic Society Gold Medallists]]
[[Category:Russian anti-fascists]]
[[Category:Russian atheists]]
[[Category:Russian classical pianists]]
[[Category:Russian film score composers]]
[[Category:Russian male classical composers]]
[[Category:Russian opera composers]]
[[Category:Russian people of Belarusian descent]]
[[Category:Russian people of Polish descent]]
[[Category:Saint Petersburg Conservatory alumni]]
[[Category:Soviet film score composers]]
[[Category:Soviet male classical composers]]
[[Category:Soviet opera composers]]
[[Category:Stalin Prize winners]]
[[Category:String quartet composers]]
[[Category:Male classical pianists]]
[[Category:Soviet classical pianists]]
[[Category:World Peace Prize laureates]]</text>
      <sha1>bbcg82h50hjxyrydosfkbbp58xmbvk2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
