  <page>
    <title>Design</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8560</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943088539</id>
      <parentid>943087173</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T19:23:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Freshacconci</username>
        <id>1843750</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/2600:1014:B028:A2CD:C83F:48A1:8E5E:B8FF|2600:1014:B028:A2CD:C83F:48A1:8E5E:B8FF]] ([[User talk:2600:1014:B028:A2CD:C83F:48A1:8E5E:B8FF|talk]]): Not really anything to do with design as a practice ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{other uses}}
{{short description|Drafting of a plan or convention for the construction of an object or of a system; process of creation; act of creativity and innovation}}

A '''design''' is a plan or specification for the construction of an object or system or for the implementation of an activity or process, or the result of that plan or specification in the form of a [[prototype]], product or [[process]]. The verb ''to design'' expresses the process of developing a design. In some cases, the direct construction of an object without an explicit prior plan (such as in craftwork, some engineering, coding, and graphic design) may also be considered to be a design activity. The design usually has to satisfy certain [[goal]]s and constraints, may take into account aesthetic, functional, economic, or socio-political considerations, and is expected to interact with a certain [[Environment (systems)|environment]]. Major examples of designs include [[blueprint|architectural blueprints]], [[engineering drawing]]s, [[business process]]es, [[circuit diagram]]s, and [[Pattern (sewing)|sewing patterns]].&lt;ref&gt;Dictionary meanings in the [//dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/english/design Cambridge Dictionary of American English], at [//www.dictionary.com/browse/design Dictionary.com] (esp. meanings 1–5 and 7–8) and at [//en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/design AskOxford] (especially verbs).&lt;/ref&gt;

The person who produces a design is called a ''designer'', which is a term generally used for people who work professionally in one of the various design areas—usually specifying which area is being dealt with (such as a [[textile design]]er, [[fashion design]]er, [[product design]]er, [[concept design]]er, [[web design]]er ([[website design]]er) or [[interior design]]er), but also others such as architects and engineers. A designer's sequence of activities is called a design process, possibly using [[design methods]]. The process of creating a design can be brief (a quick sketch) or lengthy and complicated, involving considerable research, negotiation, reflection, [[Conceptual model|modeling]], interactive adjustment and re-design.

==Design as a process{{anchor|Process}}==
Substantial disagreement exists concerning how designers in many fields, whether amateur or professional, alone or in teams, produce designs. Kees Dorst and Judith Dijkhuis, both designers themselves, argued that &quot;there are many ways of describing design processes&quot; and discussed &quot;two basic and fundamentally different ways&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1016/0142-694X(94)00012-3|title=Comparing paradigms for describing design activity|journal=Design Studies|volume=16|issue=2|pages=261–274|year=1995|last1=Dorst|first1=Kees|last2=Dijkhuis|first2=Judith|url=http://cumincad.architexturez.net//doc/oai-cumincadworks-id-d0f1}}&lt;/ref&gt; both of which have several names. The prevailing view has been called &quot;the rational model&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Brooks&quot;/&gt; &quot;technical problem solving&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schön 1983&quot;/&gt; and &quot;the reason-centric perspective&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ralph 2010&quot;/&gt; The alternative view has been called &quot;reflection-in-action&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Schön 1983&quot;/&gt; &quot;co-evolution&quot;,&lt;ref name=DC/&gt; and &quot;the action-centric perspective&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ralph 2010&quot;/&gt;

===The rational model===
The rational model was independently developed by [[Herb Simon|Herbert A. Simon]],&lt;ref&gt;Newell, A., and Simon, H. (1972) ''Human problem solving'', Prentice-Hall, Inc.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Simon&gt;Simon, H.A. (1996) [https://books.google.com/books?id=k5Sr0nFw7psC&amp;printsec=frontcover The sciences of the artificial], MIT Press, Cambridge, MA, USA. p. 111. {{ISBN|0-262-69191-4}}.&lt;/ref&gt; an American scientist, and Gerhard Pahl and Wolfgang Beitz, two German engineering design theorists.&lt;ref&gt;Pahl, G., and Beitz, W. (1996) [https://books.google.com/books?id=8fuhesYeJmkC&amp;printsec=frontcover ''Engineering design: A systematic approach''], Springer-Verlag, London. {{ISBN|3-540-19917-9}}.&lt;/ref&gt; It posits that:
# Designers attempt to [[Optimization (mathematics)|optimize]] a design candidate for known [[constraint optimization|constraints]] and [[Goal|objectives]].
# The design process is plan-driven.
# The design process is understood in terms of a discrete sequence of stages.

The rational model is based on a [[Rationalism|rationalist philosophy]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Brooks&quot; /&gt; and underlies the [[waterfall model]],&lt;ref name=Royce/&gt; [[systems development life cycle]],&lt;ref name=Bourque/&gt; and much of the [[engineering design]] literature.&lt;ref&gt;Pahl, G., Beitz, W., Feldhusen, J., and Grote, K.-H. (2007 ) [https://books.google.com/books?id=qsKNwB2gL5wC&amp;printsec=frontcover Engineering design: A systematic approach], (3rd ed.), Springer-Verlag, {{ISBN|1-84628-318-3}}.&lt;/ref&gt; According to the rationalist philosophy, design is informed by research and knowledge in a predictable and controlled manner.

====Example sequence of stages====
Typical stages consistent with the rational model include the following:

* Pre-production design
**[[Design brief]] or ''[[Parti pris]]''&amp;nbsp;– an early (often the beginning) statement of design goals
**[[Analysis]]&amp;nbsp;– analysis of current design goals
**[[Research]]&amp;nbsp;– investigating similar design solutions in the field or related topics
**[[Specification]]&amp;nbsp;– specifying requirements of a design solution for a product ([[product design specification]])&lt;ref&gt;Cross, N., (2006). ''T211 Design and Designing: Block 2'', p. 99. Milton Keynes: The Open University.&lt;/ref&gt; or service.
**[[Problem solving]]&amp;nbsp;– [[wikt:conceptualize|conceptualizing]] and [[document]]ing design solutions
**[[Presentation]]&amp;nbsp;– presenting design solutions
* Design during production
**[[Product development|Development]]&amp;nbsp;– continuation and improvement of a designed solution
** Testing&amp;nbsp;– ''[[in situ]]'' testing of a designed solution
* Post-production design feedback for future designs
**[[Implementation]]&amp;nbsp;– introducing the designed solution into the environment
**[[Evaluation]] and [[logical consequence|conclusion]]&amp;nbsp;– summary of process and results, including [[constructive criticism]] and suggestions for future improvements
* Redesign&amp;nbsp;– any or all stages in the design process repeated (with corrections made) at any time before, during, or after production.

Each stage has many associated [[best practices]].&lt;ref&gt;Ullman, David G. (2009) ''The Mechanical Design Process'', Mc Graw Hill, 4th edition {{ISBN|0-07-297574-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Criticism of the rational model====
The rational model has been widely criticized on two primary grounds:

# Designers do not work this way&amp;nbsp;– extensive empirical evidence has demonstrated that designers do not act as the rational model suggests.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schön 1983&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ralph 2010&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Cross/&gt;
# Unrealistic assumptions&amp;nbsp;– goals are often unknown when a design project begins, and the requirements and constraints continue to change.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brooks&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1145/1005937.1005943|url=http://www.deepdyve.com/lp/association-for-computing-machinery/life-cycle-concept-considered-harmful-WXRCv45NVM|author1=McCracken, D.D. |author2=Jackson, M.A. |title=Life cycle concept considered harmful|journal= ACM SIGSOFT Software Engineering Notes |volume=7|issue=2|year= 1982|pages = 29–32}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===The action-centric model===
The action-centric perspective is a label given to a collection of interrelated concepts, which are antithetical to the rational model.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ralph 2010&quot;/&gt; It posits that:

# Designers use [[creativity]] and [[emotion]] to generate design candidates.
# The design process is [[Improvisation|improvised]].
# No universal sequence of stages is apparent&amp;nbsp;– analysis, design and implementation are contemporary and inextricably linked.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ralph 2010&quot;/&gt;

The action-centric perspective is based on an [[Empiricism|empiricist philosophy]] and broadly consistent with the [[Agile software development|agile approach]]&lt;ref name=Beck/&gt; and amethodical development.&lt;ref name=Truex/&gt; Substantial empirical evidence supports the veracity of this perspective in describing the actions of real designers.&lt;ref name=Cross/&gt; Like the rational model, the action-centric model sees design as informed by research and knowledge. However, research and knowledge are brought into the design process through the judgment and common sense of designers&amp;nbsp;– by designers &quot;thinking on their feet&quot;&amp;nbsp;– more than through the predictable and controlled process stipulated by the rational model.

====Descriptions of design activities====
At least two views of design activity are consistent with the action-centric perspective. Both involve three basic activities.

In the [[Reflective practice|reflection-in-action paradigm]], designers alternate between &quot;[[Framing (social sciences)|framing]]&quot;, &quot;making moves&quot;, and &quot;evaluating moves&quot;. &quot;Framing&quot; refers to conceptualizing the problem, i.e., defining goals and objectives. A &quot;move&quot; is a tentative design decision. The evaluation process may lead to further moves in the design.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schön 1983&quot;/&gt;

In the sensemaking–coevolution–implementation framework, designers alternate between its three titular activities. [[Sensemaking (information science)|Sensemaking]] includes both framing and evaluating moves. Implementation is the process of constructing the design object. Coevolution is &quot;the process where the design agent simultaneously refines its mental picture of the design object based on its mental picture of the context, and vice versa&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ralph 2010&quot;/&gt;

The concept of the [[design cycle]] is understood as a circular time structure,&lt;ref&gt;Fischer, Thomas &quot;Design Enigma. A typographical metaphor for enigmatic processes, including designing&quot;, in: T. Fischer, K. De Biswas, J.J. Ham, R. Naka, W.X. Huang, ''Beyond Codes and Pixels: Proceedings of the 17th International Conference on Computer-Aided Architectural Design Research in Asia'', p. 686&lt;/ref&gt; which may start with the thinking of an idea, then expressing it by the use of visual or verbal means of communication (design tools), the sharing and perceiving of the expressed idea, and finally starting a new cycle with the critical rethinking of the perceived idea. Anderson points out that this concept emphasizes the importance of the means of expression, which at the same time are means of perception of any design ideas.&lt;ref&gt;Anderson, Jane (2011) ''Architectural Design'', Basics Architecture 03, Lausanne, AVA academia, p. 40. {{ISBN|978-2-940411-26-9}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Philosophies of design ==
[[Philosophy of design]] is the study of definitions of design, and the assumptions, foundations, and implications of design. There are also countless informal or personal philosophies for guiding design as design values and its accompanying aspects within modern design vary, both between different schools of thought{{which|date=February 2018}} and among practicing designers.&lt;ref&gt;Holm, Ivar (2006). ''Ideas and Beliefs in Architecture and Industrial design: How attitudes, orientations and underlying assumptions shape the built environment''. Oslo School of Architecture and Design. {{ISBN|82-547-0174-1}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Design philosophies are usually for determining design goals.

In this sense, design philosophies are fundamental guiding principles that dictate how a designer approaches his/her practice. Reflections on [[material culture]] and environmental concerns ([[sustainable design]]) can guide a design philosophy. An example is the [[First Things First 2000 manifesto|First Things First manifesto]] which was launched within the graphic design community and states &quot;We propose a reversal of priorities in favor of more useful, lasting and democratic forms of communication&amp;nbsp;– a mindshift away from product marketing and toward the exploration and production of a new kind of meaning. The scope of debate is shrinking; it must expand. Consumerism is running uncontested; it must be challenged by other perspectives expressed, in part, through the visual languages and resources of design.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;maxbruinsma.nl&quot;&gt;[http://maxbruinsma.nl/index1.html?ftf2000.htm First Things First 2000 a design manifesto] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111219160927/http://maxbruinsma.nl/index1.html?ftf2000.htm |date=2011-12-19 }}. manifesto published jointly by 33 signatories in: Adbusters, the AIGA journal, Blueprint, Emigre, Eye, Form, Items fall 1999/spring 2000&lt;/ref&gt;

===Approaches to design===
A design approach is a general philosophy that may or may not include a guide for specific methods. Some are to guide the overall goal of the design. Other approaches are to guide the tendencies of the designer.

Some of these approaches include:
* [[Sociotechnical system]] design, a philosophy and tools for participative designing of work arrangements and supporting processes – for organizational purpose, quality, safety, economics and customer requirements in core work processes, the quality of peoples experience at work and the needs of society
* [[User-centered design]], which focuses on the needs, wants, and limitations of the end user of the designed artifact.
* [[Critical design]] uses designed artifacts as an embodied critique or commentary on existing values, morals, and practices in a culture.
* [[Service design]] designing or organizing the experience around a product and the service associated with a product's use.
* [[Transgenerational design]], the practice of making products and environments compatible with those physical and sensory impairments associated with human aging and which limit major activities of daily living.
* [[Participatory design|Participatory Design]] (originally co-operative design, now often co-design) is the practice of collective creativity to design, attempting to actively involve all stakeholders (e.g. employees, partners, customers, citizens, end users) in the design process to help ensure the result meets their needs and is usable. Participatory design is an approach which is focused on processes and procedures of design and is not a design style&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://studiolab.ide.tudelft.nl/manila/gems/contextmapping/PreprintDraft.pdf|title=Co-creation and the new landscape of design|last=|first=|date=|website=|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Types==
Design can broadly be applied to various fields such as art, engineering and production.
[[File:M-T4.jpg|thumb|166px|left|The new terminal at [[Barajas airport]] in [[Madrid]], [[Spain]]]]

===Design and art===
Today, the term design is generally used for what was formerly called the [[applied arts]].  The new term, for a very old thing, was perhaps initiated by [[Raymond Loewy]] and teachings at the [[Bauhaus]] and [[Ulm School of Design]] (HfG Ulm) in Germany during the 20th century.

The boundaries between art and design are blurred, largely due to a range of applications both for the term 'art' and the term 'design'. [[Applied arts]] can include [[industrial design]], [[graphic design]], [[fashion design]], and the [[decorative arts]] which traditionally includes craft objects. In [[graphic art]]s (2D image making that ranges from photography to illustration), the distinction is often made between [[fine art]] and [[commercial art]], based on the context within which the work is produced and how it is traded.

To a degree, some methods for creating work, such as employing intuition, are shared across the disciplines within the [[applied arts]] and [[fine art]]. Mark Getlein, writer, suggests the principles of design are &quot;almost instinctive&quot;, &quot;built-in&quot;, &quot;natural&quot;, and part of &quot;our sense of 'rightness'.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Getlein, Mark (2008) ''Living With Art'', 8th ed. New York, p. 121.&lt;/ref&gt; However, the intended application and context of the resulting works will vary greatly.

[[File:Booster-Layout.jpg|thumb|A drawing for a booster engine for [[steam locomotive]]s. Engineering is applied to design, with emphasis on function and the utilization of mathematics and science.]]

===Design and engineering===
In [[engineering]], design is a component of the engineering process. Many overlapping methods and processes can be seen when comparing [[Product design]], [[Industrial design]] and [[Engineering]]. The [[American Heritage Dictionary]] defines design as: ''&quot;To conceive or fashion in the mind; invent,&quot;'' and ''&quot;To formulate a plan&quot;'', and defines engineering as: ''&quot;The application of scientific and mathematical principles to practical ends such as the design, manufacture, and operation of efficient and economical structures, machines, processes, and systems.&quot;''.&lt;ref&gt;American Psychological Association (APA): [http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/design design] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070108172005/http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/design |date=2007-01-08 }}. The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language, Fourth Edition. Retrieved January 10, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;American Psychological Association (APA): [http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/engineering engineering] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070102052421/http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/engineering |date=2007-01-02 }}. The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language, Fourth Edition. Retrieved January 10, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; Both are forms of problem-solving with a defined distinction being the application of &quot;scientific and mathematical principles&quot;. The increasingly scientific focus of engineering in practice, however, has raised the importance of more new &quot;human-centered&quot; fields of design.&lt;ref name=Faste/&gt; How much science is applied in a design is a question of what is considered &quot;[[science]]&quot;. Along with the question of what is considered science, there is [[social science]] versus [[natural science]]. Scientists at [[Xerox PARC]] made the distinction of design versus engineering at &quot;moving minds&quot; versus &quot;moving atoms&quot; (probably in contradiction to the origin of term &quot;engineering – engineer&quot; from Latin &quot;in genio&quot; in meaning of a &quot;genius&quot; what assumes existence of a &quot;mind&quot; not of an &quot;atom&quot;).

[[File:Aluminium MacBook.png|thumb|166px|left|[[Jonathan Ive]] has received several awards for his design of [[Apple Inc.]] products like this MacBook. In some design fields, [[personal computer]]s are also used for both design and production]]

===Design and production===
The relationship between design and [[Manufacturing|production]] is one of planning and executing. In theory, the plan should anticipate and compensate for potential problems in the execution process. Design involves problem-solving and [[creativity]]. In contrast, production involves a routine or pre-planned process. A design may also be a mere plan that does not include a production or engineering processes although a working knowledge of such processes is usually expected of designers. In some cases, it may be unnecessary or impractical to expect a designer with a broad [[multidisciplinary]] knowledge required for such designs to also have a detailed [[Division of labour|specialized]] knowledge of how to produce the product.

Design and production are intertwined in many [[creative professional]] careers, meaning problem-solving is part of execution and the reverse. As the cost of rearrangement increases, the need for separating design from production increases as well. For example, a high-budget project, such as a [[skyscraper]], requires separating (design) [[architect]]ure from (production) [[construction]]. A Low-budget project, such as a [[Multifunction printer|locally printed]] office party invitation [[Flyer (pamphlet)|flyer]], can be rearranged and printed dozens of times at the low cost of a few sheets of paper, a few drops of ink, and less than one hour's pay of a [[desktop publishing|desktop publisher]].

This is not to say that production never involves problem-solving or creativity, nor that design always involves creativity. Designs are rarely perfect and are sometimes repetitive. The imperfection of a design may task a production position (e.g. [[production artist]], [[construction worker]]) with utilizing creativity or problem-solving skills to compensate for what was overlooked in the design process. Likewise, a design may be a simple repetition (copy) of a known preexisting solution, requiring minimal, if any, creativity or problem-solving skills from the designer.

[[File:BPMN-DiscussionCycle.jpg|thumb|An example of a business workflow process using [[Business Process Model and Notation]].]]

===Process design===
{{See also|Business process management|Method engineering}}
&quot;Process design&quot; (in contrast to &quot;design process&quot; mentioned [[#Design as a process|above]]) is to the planning of routine steps of a process aside from the expected result. Processes (in general) are treated as a product of design, not the method of design. The term originated with the industrial [[Process design (chemical engineering)|designing of]] [[chemical process]]es. With the increasing complexities of the [[information age]], consultants and executives have found the term useful to describe the [[Business process modeling|design of business processes]] as well as [[manufacturing|manufacturing processes]].

==Design disciplines==
{{Columns-list|colwidth=15em|
* [[Applied arts]]
* [[Architecture]]
* [[Automotive design]]
* [[Synthetic biology|Biological design]]
* [[Configuration design]]
* [[Communication design]]
* [[Costume design]]
* [[Design management]]
* [[Engineering design process|Engineering design]]
* [[Experience design]]
* [[Fashion design]]
* [[Floral design]]
* [[Game design]]
* [[Graphic design]]
* [[Information architecture]]
* [[Information design]]
* [[Industrial design]]
* [[Instructional design]]
* [[Interaction design]]
* [[Interior design]]
* [[Landscape architecture]]
* [[Lighting designer|Lighting design]]
* [[Modular design]]
* [[Motion graphic design]]
* [[Organizational architecture|Organization design]]
* [[Product design]]
* [[Process design]]
* [[Property designer|Property design]]
* [[Scenic design]]
* [[Service design]]
* [[Social design]]
* [[Software design]]
* [[Sound design]]
* [[Spatial design]]
* [[Strategic design]]
* [[Systems architecture]]
* [[Systems design]]
* [[Systems modeling]]
* [[Urban design]]
* [[User experience design]]
* [[User interface design]]
* [[Web design]]
}}

==See also==
* [[Design elements and principles]]
* [[Design-based learning]]
* [[Design theory]]
* [[Design thinking]]
* [[Evidence-based design]]
* [[List of design awards]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em|refs=
&lt;ref name=Beck&gt;Beck, K., Beedle, M., van Bennekum, A., Cockburn, A., Cunningham, W., Fowler, M., Grenning, J., Highsmith, J., Hunt, A., Jeffries, R., Kern, J., Marick, B., Martin, R.C., Mellor, S., Schwaber, K., Sutherland, J., and Thomas, D. (2001) [http://www.agilemanifesto.org/ Manifesto for agile software development].&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Bourque&gt;Bourque, P., and Dupuis, R. (eds.) (2004) [http://webyes.com.br/wp-content/uploads/ebooks/book_SWEBOK.pdf Guide to the software engineering body of knowledge] (SWEBOK). IEEE Computer Society Press, {{ISBN|0-7695-2330-7}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Brooks&quot;&gt;Brooks, F.P. (2010) ''The design of design: Essays from a computer scientist'', Addison-Wesley Professional. {{ISBN|0-201-36298-8}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Cross&gt;Cross, N., Dorst, K., and Roozenburg, N. (1992) ''Research in design thinking'', Delft University Press, Delft. {{ISBN|90-6275-796-0}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=DC&gt;{{Cite journal |doi = 10.1016/S0142-694X(01)00009-6|title = Creativity in the design process: Co-evolution of problem–solution|journal = Design Studies|volume = 22|issue = 5|pages = 425–437|year = 2001|last1 = Dorst|first1 = Kees|last2 = Cross|first2 = Nigel|url = http://oro.open.ac.uk/3278/1/Creativity_-_coevolution.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Faste&gt;{{cite journal|doi=|author=Faste, R.|url=http://www.ijee.ie/articles/Vol17-4and5/Ijee1230.pdf|title=The Human Challenge in Engineering Design|journal= International Journal of Engineering Education|volume= 17|year= 2001|issue=4–5|pages= 327–331}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Ralph 2010&quot;&gt;Ralph, P. (2010) &quot;Comparing two software design process theories&quot;. International Conference on Design Science Research in Information Systems and Technology (DESRIST 2010), Springer, St. Gallen, Switzerland, pp.&amp;nbsp;139–153. {{DOI|10.1007/978-3-642-13335-0_10}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Royce&gt;Royce, W.W. (1970) [http://www-scf.usc.edu/~csci201/lectures/Lecture11/royce1970.pdf &quot;Managing the development of large software systems: Concepts and techniques,&quot;] Proceedings of Wescon.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Schön 1983&quot;&gt;Schön, D.A. (1983) ''The reflective practitioner: How professionals think in action'', Basic Books, USA.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Truex&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1016/S0959-8022(99)00009-0|author1=Truex, D. |author2=Baskerville, R. |author3=and Travis, J. |title=Amethodical systems development: The deferred meaning of systems development methods|journal=Accounting, Management and Information Technologies |volume=10|issue=1|pages=53–79|year=2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==Bibliography==

{{Wiktionary|design}}
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Commons category|Design}}
{{Library resources box
|by=no
|onlinebooks=no
|others=no
|about=yes
|label=Design }}

{{Design}}

{{Portal bar|engineering}}

{{Authority control}}

&lt;!--Categories--&gt;
[[Category:Design| ]]
[[Category:Architectural design| ]]
[[Category:Arts]]
[[Category:Creativity]]
[[Category:Innovators]]
[[Category:Innovation economics]]
[[Category:Innovation]]
[[Category:Problem solving skills]]
[[Category:Product development]]</text>
      <sha1>pwnldhyev9wkfniw00bthi151qqhkot</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
