  <page>
    <title>Binary prefix</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4077</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943200221</id>
      <parentid>942746370</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T13:44:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dondervogel 2</username>
        <id>12240634</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Other standards bodies and organizations */ not T</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Unit prefix for multiples of units in data processing, data transmission, and digital information, notably the bit and the byte, to indicate multiplication by a power of 2}}
{{Selfref|For guidelines on using binary prefixes on Wikipedia, see [[Wikipedia:Manual of Style/Dates and numbers#Quantities of bytes and bits|Wikipedia:Manual of Style/Dates and numbers § Quantities of bytes and bits]].}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2019|cs1-dates=y}}
{{Bit and byte prefixes}}
A '''binary prefix''' is a [[unit prefix]] for multiples of [[Units of measurement|unit]]s in data processing, data transmission, and digital information, notably the [[bit]] and the [[byte]], to indicate multiplication by a [[Exponentiation|power]] of 2.

The computer industry has historically used the units ''kilobyte'', ''megabyte'', and ''gigabyte'', and the corresponding symbols KB, MB, and GB, in at least two slightly different measurement systems. In citations of main memory ([[Random access memory|RAM]]) capacity, ''gigabyte'' customarily means {{val|1073741824}} bytes. As this is a power of 1024, and 1024 is a [[power of two]] (2&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;), this usage is referred to as a [[Binary number|binary]] measurement.

In most other contexts, the industry uses the multipliers ''kilo'', ''mega'', ''giga'', etc., in a manner consistent with their meaning in the [[International System of Units]] (SI), namely as powers of 1000. For example, a 500 gigabyte hard disk holds {{val|500000000000}} bytes, and a 1 Gbit/s (gigabit per second) [[Ethernet]] connection transfers data at nominal speed of {{val|1000000000}} bit/s. In contrast with the ''binary prefix'' usage, this use is described as a ''decimal prefix'', as 1000 is a [[Powers of 10|power of 10]] (10&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;).

The use of the same unit prefixes with two different meanings has caused confusion. Starting around 1998, the [[International Electrotechnical Commission]] (IEC) and several other standards and trade organizations addressed the ambiguity by publishing standards and recommendations for a set of binary prefixes that refer exclusively to powers of 1024.  Accordingly, the US [[National Institute of Standards and Technology]] (NIST) requires that [[SI prefix]]es only be used in the decimal sense:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url=http://physics.nist.gov/cuu/Units/prefixes.html
 | title = SI prefixes
 |author=&lt;!--Not stated--&gt; 
 | website = The NIST Reference on Constants, Units, and Uncertainty: International System of Units (SI)
 | publisher = [[National Institute of Standards and Technology]]
 | access-date = 2017-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[kilobyte]] and [[megabyte]] denote one thousand bytes and one million bytes respectively (consistent with SI), while new terms such as [[kibibyte]], [[mebibyte]] and [[gibibyte]], having the symbols KiB, MiB, and GiB, denote 1024 bytes, {{val|1048576}} bytes, and {{val|1073741824}} bytes, respectively.&lt;ref name=&quot;NIST-biprefix&quot;/&gt;  In 2008, the IEC prefixes were incorporated into the international standard [[Units of measurement#Systems of units|system of units]] used alongside the [[International System of Quantities]] (see [[ISO/IEC 80000#Information science and technology|ISO/IEC 80000]]).

==History==
===Main memory===
Early computers used one of two addressing methods to access the system memory; binary (base 2) or decimal (base 10).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
|title = A Third Survey of Domestic Electronic Digital Computing Systems: Chapter III Analysis and Trends
|quote = Of 187 different relevant systems, 131 utilize a straight binary system internally, whereas 53 utilize the decimal system (primarily binary coded decimal) and 3 systems utilize a binary coded alphanumeric system of notation.
|journal = Ballistic Research Laboratories Report No. 1115
| first = Martin H. 
|last = Weik
|date=March 1961
|page = 1027
|url = http://ed-thelen.org/comp-hist/BRL61analysis.html#STORAGE
}} This lengthy report describes many of the early computers.&lt;/ref&gt;
For example, the [[IBM 701]] (1952) used binary and could address 2048 [[Word (data type)|words]] of 36 [[bit]]s each, while the [[IBM 702]] (1953) used decimal and could address ten thousand 7-bit words.

By the mid-1960s, binary addressing had become the standard architecture in most computer designs, and main memory sizes were most commonly powers of two. This is the most natural configuration for memory, as all combinations of their address lines map to a valid address, allowing easy aggregation into a larger block of memory with contiguous addresses.

Early computer system documentation would specify the memory size with an exact number such as 4096, 8192, or 16384 words of storage. These are all [[Power of two|powers of two]], and furthermore are small multiples of 2&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;, or 1024. As storage capacities increased, several different methods were developed to abbreviate these quantities.

The method most commonly used today uses prefixes such as kilo, mega, giga, and corresponding symbols K, M, and G, which the computer industry originally adopted from the [[metric system]]. The prefixes ''kilo-'' and ''mega-'', meaning 1000 and {{val|1000000}} respectively, were commonly used in the electronics industry before World War II.&lt;ref&gt;Hunting Trouble on 28 Megacycles, A. L. Blais, QST, January 1930.&lt;/ref&gt; 
Along with ''giga-'' or G-, meaning {{val|1000000000}}, they are now known as [[SI prefixes]]&lt;ref group=&quot;defn.&quot; name=&quot;d.SIp&quot;/&gt; after the [[International System of Units]] (SI), introduced in 1960 to formalize aspects of the metric system.

The International System of Units does not define units for digital information but notes that the SI prefixes may be applied outside the contexts where base units or derived units would be used. But as computer main memory in a 
binary-addressed system is manufactured in sizes that were easily expressed as multiples of 1024, ''kilobyte'', when applied to computer memory, came to be used to mean 1024 bytes instead of 1000.  This usage is not consistent with the SI.  Compliance with the SI requires that the prefixes take their 1000-based meaning, and that they are not to be used as placeholders for other numbers, like 1024.&lt;ref&gt;{{SIbrochure8th|page=121}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The use of K in the binary sense as in a &quot;32K core&quot; meaning {{nowrap|32 × 1024}} words, i.e., {{val|32768}} words, can be found as early as 1959.&lt;ref
name = &quot;32K 1959&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal
| last = Real | first = P.
| title = A generalized analysis of variance program utilizing binary logic.
| journal = ACM '59: Preprints of Papers Presented at the 14th National Meeting of the Association for Computing Machinery
| pages = 78–1–78–5 |date=September 1959 | doi = 10.1145/612201.612294 | publisher = ACM Press
|quote = On a 32K core size 704 computer, approximately {{val|28000}} data may be analyzed, ... without resorting to auxiliary tape storage.}} Note: the IBM 704 core memory units had 4096 36-bit words. Up to {{val|32768}} words could be installed&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref
name = &quot;32K 1960&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal
| last =Gruenberger | first =Fred
| title =Letters to the Editor
| journal =Communications of the ACM
| volume =3 | issue =10 |date=October 1960
| doi = 10.1145/367415.367419 | last2 =Burgess | first2 =C. R. | last3 =Gruenberger | first3 =Fred}} &quot;The 8K core stores were getting fairly common in this country in 1954. The 32K store started mass production in 1956; it is the standard now for large machines and at least 200 machines of the size (or its equivalent in the character addressable machines) are in existence today (and at least 100 were in existence in mid-1959).&quot; Note: The [[IBM 1401]] was a character addressable computer.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Gene Amdahl]]'s seminal 1964 article on [[IBM System/360]] used &quot;1K&quot; to mean 1024.&lt;ref
name=&quot;IBM360&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal
| last =Amdahl | first = Gene M. | authorlink = Gene Amdahl
| title = Architecture of the IBM System/360
| journal =IBM Journal of Research and Development
| volume =8 | issue =2 | publisher = IBM | year = 1964
| url = http://www.research.ibm.com/journal/rd/441/amdahl.pdf
| doi = 10.1147/rd.82.0087 | pages=87–101}} Figure 1 gives storage (memory) capacity ranges of the various models in &quot;Capacity 8-bit bytes, 1&amp;nbsp;K = 1024&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
This style was used by other computer vendors, the [[CDC 7600]] ''System Description'' (1968) made extensive use of K as 1024.&lt;ref
name = &quot;CDC7600&quot;&gt;{{Cite book
| author = Control Data Corporation
| title = Control Data 7600 Computer System: Preliminary System Description
|date=November 1968
| url = http://archive.computerhistory.org/resources/text/CDC/CDC.7600.1968.102646087.pdf
|quote = One type, designated as the small core memory (SCM) is a many bank coincident current type memory with a total of 64K words of 60 bit length (K=1024).
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Thus the first binary prefix was born.&lt;ref group=&quot;defn.&quot; name=&quot;d.binpref&quot;/&gt;

Another style was to truncate the last three digits and append K, essentially using K as a decimal prefix&lt;ref group=&quot;defn.&quot; name=&quot;d.decpref&quot;/&gt; similar to [[SI prefixes|SI]], but always truncating to the next lower whole number instead of rounding to the nearest. The exact values {{val|32768}} words, {{val|65536}} words and {{val|131072}} words would then be described as &quot;32K&quot;, &quot;65K&quot; and &quot;131K&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;CDC6600&quot;&gt;{{Cite book
 |author       = Control Data Corporation
 |title        = Control Data 6400/6500/6600 Computer Systems Reference Manual
 |year         = 1965–1967
 |pages        = 2–1
 |edition      = Pub No. 60100000
 |url          = http://ed-thelen.org/comp-hist/CDC-6600-R-M.html#TOC/
 |quote        = Central Memory is organized into 32K, 65K, or 131K words (60-bit) in 8, 16, or 32 banks of 4096 words each.
 |access-date  = 2013-11-07
 |archive-url  = https://web.archive.org/web/20140102194752/http://ed-thelen.org/comp-hist/CDC-6600-R-M.html#TOC/
 |archive-date = 2014-01-02
 |url-status     = dead
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
(If these values had been rounded to nearest they would have become 33K, 66K, and 131K, respectively.)
This style was used from about 1965 to 1975.

These two styles (K = 1024 and truncation) were used loosely around the same time, sometimes by the same company. In discussions of binary-addressed memories, the exact size was evident from context. (For memory sizes of &quot;41K&quot; and below, there is no difference between the two styles.) The [[HP 2100|HP 21MX]] real-time computer (1974) denoted {{val|196608}} (which is 192×1024) as &quot;196K&quot; and {{val|1048576}} as &quot;1M&quot;,&lt;ref
name =&quot;HP21MX&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal
| last =Frankenberg | first =Robert
| title =All Semiconductor Memory Selected for New Minicomputer Series
| journal = Hewlett-Packard Journal
| volume =26 | issue =2 | pages = pg 15–20 | publisher = Hewlett-Packard |date=October 1974
| url = http://www.hpl.hp.com/hpjournal/pdfs/IssuePDFs/1974-10.pdf
| accessdate = 2007-06-18
| quote = 196K-word memory size
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
while the [[HP 3000]] business computer (1973) could have &quot;64K&quot;, &quot;96K&quot;, or &quot;128K&quot; bytes of memory.&lt;ref
name=&quot;HP3000&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal
| last = Hewlett-Packard
| title =HP 3000 Configuration Guide
| journal = HP 3000 Computer System and Subsystem Data
| page = pg 59 |date = November 1973
| url = http://www.bitsavers.org/pdf/hp/3000/hp3000/5952-4500_optionsBrochure_Nov73.pdf
|accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The &quot;truncation&quot; method gradually waned. Capitalization of the letter K became the ''de facto'' standard for binary notation, although this could not be extended to higher powers, and use of the lowercase k did persist.&lt;ref name=&quot;wnwtd&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title=The ACS style guide: a manual for authors and editors|author=Janet S. Dodd|page=124|publisher=[[American Chemical Society]]|year=1997|isbn=9780841234611|quote=kB (kilobyte; actually 1024 bytes) KB (kilobyte; kB is preferred)}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title=Information Technology: Agent of Change|author=F. J. M. Laver|page=35|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|isbn=978-0521350358|quote=when describing the performance of IT systems the larger units 'kilobytes' (kB) [...] Strictly speaking, k means the 'binary thousand' 1024}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, the practice of using the SI-inspired &quot;kilo&quot; to indicate 1024 was later extended to &quot;megabyte&quot; meaning 1024&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; ({{val|1048576}}) bytes, and later &quot;gigabyte&quot; for 1024&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; ({{val|1073741824}}) bytes. For example, a &quot;512 megabyte&quot; RAM module is 512×1024&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; bytes (512 × {{val|1048576}}, or {{val|536870912}}), rather than {{val|512000000}}.

The symbols Kbit, Kbyte, Mbit and Mbyte started to be used as &quot;binary units&quot;—&quot;bit&quot; or &quot;byte&quot; with a multiplier that is a power of 1024—in the early 1970s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mbyte1972&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Lin |first=Yeong |title=Cost-performance evaluation of memory hierarchies |journal=IEEE Transactions on Magnetics |volume=8 |issue=3 |pages=390–392 |publisher=IEEE |date=September 1972 |quote=Also, random access devices are advantageous over serial access devices for backing store applications only when the memory capacity is less than 1&amp;nbsp;Mbyte. For capacities of 4&amp;nbsp;Mbyte and 16&amp;nbsp;Mbyte serial access stores with shift register lengths of 256 bit and 1024 bit, respectively, look favorable. |doi=10.1109/TMAG.1972.1067329 |last2=Mattson |first2=R. |bibcode=1972ITM.....8..390L}}&lt;/ref&gt;
For a time, memory capacities were often expressed in K, even when M could have been used: The IBM System/370 Model 158 brochure (1972) had the following: &quot;Real storage capacity is available in 512K increments ranging from 512K to 2,048K bytes.&quot;&lt;ref
name=&quot;IBM370&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal
| last =IBM| title = System/370 Model 158 brochure | publisher = IBM | year = 1972
| url = http://archive.computerhistory.org/resources/text/IBM/IBM.370Mod158.1972.102646258.pdf
| quote = All-monolithic storage ... (1024-bit NMOS) This new improvement of processor storage makes system expansion more economical. Real storage capacity is available in 512K increments ranging from 512K to 2,048K bytes.
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Megabyte was used to describe the 22-bit addressing of DEC [[PDP-11]]/70 (1975)&lt;ref
name=&quot;PDP11&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal
| last = Bell | first = Gordon
| title = Computer structures: What have we learned from the PDP-11?
| journal = ISCA '76: Proceedings of the 3rd Annual Symposium on Computer Architecture
| pages = pg 1–14 | publisher = ACM Press |date=November 1975
| url = http://research.microsoft.com/~gbell/Digital/Bell_Strecker_What_we%20_learned_fm_PDP-11c%207511.pdf | doi = 10.1145/800110.803541
| quote = memory size (8k bytes to 4 megabytes).
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
and gigabyte the 30-bit addressing DEC [[VAX-11/780]] (1977).

In 1998, the [[International Electrotechnical Commission]] IEC introduced the binary prefixes kibi, mebi, gibi ... to mean 1024, 1024&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, 1024&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; etc., so that 1048576 bytes could be referred to unambiguously as 1 [[mebibyte]].  The IEC prefixes were defined for use alongside the [[International System of Quantities]] (ISQ) in [[ISO 80000-1|2009]].

===Disk drives===
The disk drive industry has followed a different pattern. Disk drive capacity is generally specified with unit prefixes with decimal meaning, in accordance to SI practices. Unlike computer main memory, disk architecture or construction does not mandate or make it convenient to use binary multiples. Drives can have any practical number of platters or surfaces, and the count of tracks, as well as the count of sectors per track may vary greatly between designs.

The first commercially sold disk drive, the [[IBM 350]], had fifty physical disk platters containing a total of 50,000 sectors of 100 characters each, for a total quoted capacity of 5 million characters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www-03.ibm.com/ibm/history/exhibits/storage/storage_350.html
|work=IBM Archives
|title=IBM 350 disk storage unit
|author=IBM Corporation|date=23 January 2003
}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was introduced in September 1956.

In the 1960s most disk drives used IBM's variable block length format, called [[Count Key Data]] (CKD).&lt;ref&gt;IBM invented the disk drive in 1956 and until the late 1960s its drives and their clones were dominant. See, e.g. [http://www.hagley.lib.de.us/1980.htm US vs. IBM antitrust litigation (Jan 1969)] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080507065825/http://www.hagley.lib.de.us/1980.htm |date=May 7, 2008 }}, especially IBM analyses of Memorex and other disk drive companies.&lt;/ref&gt;
Any block size could be specified up to the maximum track length.  Since the block headers occupied space, the usable capacity of the drive was dependent on the block size.  Blocks (&quot;records&quot; in IBM's terminology) of 88, 96, 880 and 960 were often used because they related to the fixed block size of 80- and 96-character punch cards. The drive capacity was usually stated under conditions of full track record blocking. For example, the 100-megabyte 3336 disk pack only achieved that capacity with a full track block size of 13,030 bytes.

[[Floppy disk#3.C2.BD-inch floppy disk|Floppy disks]] for the IBM PC and compatibles quickly [[List of floppy disk formats#Known disk logical formats|standardized on 512-byte sectors]], so two sectors were easily referred to as &quot;1K&quot;.  The 3.5-inch &quot;360&amp;nbsp;KB&quot; and &quot;720&amp;nbsp;KB&quot; had 720 (single-sided) and 1440 sectors (double-sided) respectively.  When the High Density &quot;1.44&amp;nbsp;MB&quot; floppies came along, with 2880 of these 512-byte sectors, that terminology represented a hybrid binary-decimal definition of &quot;1&amp;nbsp;MB&quot; = 2&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt; × 10&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; = 1&amp;thinsp;024&amp;thinsp;000 bytes.

In contrast, [[hard disk]] drive manufacturers used ''megabytes'' or ''MB'', meaning 10&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; bytes, to characterize their products as early as 1974.&lt;ref&gt;The [http://www.bitsavers.org/pdf/cdc/discs/brochures/ProductLine_Oct74.pdf CDC Product Line Card] unambiguously uses MB to characterize HDD capacity in millions of bytes&lt;/ref&gt;  By 1977, in its first edition, Disk/Trend, a leading hard disk drive industry marketing consultancy segmented the industry according to MBs (decimal sense) of capacity.&lt;ref&gt;1977 Disk/Trend Report – Rigid Disk Drives, published June 1977&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the earliest hard disk drives in personal computing history, the Seagate [[ST-412]], was specified as ''Formatted: 10.0 Megabytes''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 |url          = http://maben.homeip.net/static/S100/seagate/disks/Seagate%20ST412%20OEM%20Manual%201982.pdf
 |title        = ST506/412 OEM Manual
 |author       = Seagate Corporation
 |date         = April 1982
 |page         = 3
 |access-date  = 2016-09-06
 |archive-url  = https://web.archive.org/web/20161008003923/http://maben.homeip.net/static/S100/seagate/disks/Seagate%20ST412%20OEM%20Manual%201982.pdf
 |archive-date = 2016-10-08
 |url-status     = dead
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The drive contains four heads and active surfaces (tracks per cylinder), 306 cylinders. When formatted with a sector size of 256 bytes and 32 sectors/track it has a capacity of {{val|10027008|u=bytes}}. This drive was one of several types installed in the [[IBM PC/XT]]&lt;ref&gt;IBM Tells MiniScribe It Is Cutting Back On Winchester Orders, Computer System News, Jan 1, 1984, p. 1&lt;/ref&gt; and extensively advertised and reported as a &quot;10&amp;nbsp;MB&quot; (formatted) hard disk drive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Mellor |first=Chris |url=https://www.theregister.co.uk/2011/04/06/oldest_seagate_drive_in_uk/ |title=It's the oldest working Seagate drive in the UK |publisher=Theregister.co.uk |date=2011-04-06 |accessdate=2012-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The cylinder count of 306 is not conveniently close to any power of 1024; operating systems and programs using the customary binary prefixes show this as 9.5625&amp;nbsp;MB. Many later drives in the personal computer market used 17 sectors per track; still later, [[zone bit recording]] was introduced, causing the number of sectors per track to vary from the outer track to the inner.

The hard drive industry continues to use decimal prefixes for drive capacity, as well as for transfer rate. For example, a &quot;300&amp;nbsp;GB&quot; hard drive offers slightly more than {{val|300|e=9}}, or {{val|300000000000}}, bytes, not {{nowrap|300 × 2&lt;sup&gt;30&lt;/sup&gt;}} (which would be about {{val|322|e=9}}).  Operating systems such as [[Microsoft Windows]] that display hard drive sizes using the customary binary prefix &quot;GB&quot; (as it is used for RAM) would display this as &quot;279.4&amp;nbsp;GB&quot; (meaning {{nowrap|279.4 × 1024&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;}} bytes, or {{nowrap|279.4 × {{val|1073741824|u=B}}}}). On the other hand, [[macOS]] has since version 10.6 shown hard drive size using decimal prefixes (thus matching the drive makers' packaging). (Previous versions of Mac OS X used binary prefixes.)

However, other usages still occur. Seagate has specified data transfer rates in select manuals of some hard drives in ''both'' IEC and decimal units.&lt;ref name=savvio&gt;
[http://www.seagate.com/staticfiles/support/docs/manual/enterprise/savvio/10K.5/100628561d.pdf Seagate Savvio 10K.5 SAS Product Manual], 100628561, Rev D, March 2011, sec 5.2.3, p. 10 (18th page of the pdf), states the drive's sustained transfer speed as &quot;89 to 160 [[MiB]]/s&quot; on one line, and &quot;93 to 168&amp;nbsp;MB/s&quot; on the next line.&lt;/ref&gt; 
&quot;Advanced Format&quot; drives using 4096-byte sectors are described as having &quot;4K sectors.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Marketing Bulletin: Advanced Format 4K Sector Transition Frequently Asked Questions|url=http://www.seagate.com/docs/pdf/whitepaper/mb604_4k_transition_faq.pdf|publisher=[[Seagate Technology]]|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100715030704/http://www.seagate.com/docs/pdf/whitepaper/mb604_4k_transition_faq.pdf|archivedate=15 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Information transfer and clock rates===
Computer [[Clock signal|clock]] frequencies are always quoted using SI prefixes in their decimal sense. For example, the internal clock frequency of the original [[IBM PC]] was 4.77&amp;nbsp;MHz, that is {{val|4770000|u=Hz}}.
Similarly, digital information transfer rates are quoted using decimal prefixes:
* The ATA-100 disk interface refers to {{val|100000000}} bytes per second
* A &quot;56K&quot; modem refers to {{val|56000}} bits per second
* SATA-2 has a raw bit rate of 3&amp;nbsp;Gbit/s = {{val|3000000000}} bits per second
* PC2-6400 [[Random access memory|RAM]] transfers {{val|6400000000}} bytes per second
* Firewire 800 has a raw rate of {{val|800000000}} bits per second
* In 2011, Seagate specified the sustained transfer rate of some hard disk drive models with both decimal and IEC binary prefixes.&lt;ref name=savvio/&gt;

===Standardization of dual definitions===
By the mid-1970s it was common to see K meaning 1024 and the occasional M meaning {{val|1048576}} for words or bytes of main memory (RAM) while K and M were commonly used with their decimal meaning for disk storage. In the 1980s, as capacities of both types of devices increased, the SI prefix G, with SI meaning, was commonly applied to disk storage, while M in its binary meaning, became common for computer memory. In the 1990s, the prefix G, in its binary meaning, became commonly used for computer memory capacity. The first terabyte (SI prefix, {{val|1000000000000}} bytes) hard disk drive was introduced in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.pcworld.com/article/id,128400-page,1/article.html
|title=Hitachi Introduces 1-Terabyte Hard Drive
|work=PC World
|date=2007-01-04
|accessdate=2010-02-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The dual usage of the kilo (K), mega (M), and giga (G) prefixes as both powers of 1000 and powers of 1024 has been recorded in standards and dictionaries. For example, the 1986 ANSI/IEEE Std 1084-1986&lt;ref name=&quot;IEEE1084&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=ANSI/IEEE Std 1084-1986 IEEE Standard Glossary of Mathematics of Computing Terminology |date=30 October 1986 |quote=kilo (K). (1) A prefix indicating 1000. (2) In statements involving size of computer storage, a prefix indicating 2&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;, or 1024. mega (M). (1) A prefix indicating one million. (2) In statements involving size of computer storage, a prefix indicating 2&lt;sup&gt;20&lt;/sup&gt;, or 1048576. |doi=10.1109/IEEESTD.1986.79649 |isbn=0-7381-4541-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
defined dual uses for kilo and mega.
{{quote|
kilo (K).&lt;!--it should be checked if they used k or K--&gt; (1) A prefix indicating 1000. (2) In statements involving size of computer storage, a prefix indicating 2&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;, or 1024.

mega (M). (1) A prefix indicating one million. (2) In statements involving size of computer storage, a prefix indicating 2&lt;sup&gt;20&lt;/sup&gt;, or 1048576.}} The binary units Kbyte and Mbyte were formally defined in ANSI/IEEE Std 1212-1991.&lt;ref name=&quot;IEEE1212&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=ANSI/IEEE Std 1212-1991 IEEE Standard Control and Status Register (CSR) Architecture for Microcomputer Buses |date=22 July 1992 |quote=Kbyte. Kilobyte. Indicates 2&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt; bytes. Mbyte. Megabyte. Indicates 2&lt;sup&gt;20&lt;/sup&gt;bytes. Gbyte is used in the Foreword. |doi=10.1109/IEEESTD.1992.106981 |isbn=0-7381-4336-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many dictionaries have noted the practice of using traditional prefixes to indicate binary multiples.&lt;ref name=&quot;webster&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.m-w.com/dictionary/Megabyte|title=Definition of megabyte|website=M-w.com|accessdate=30 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref
name=&quot;metadict&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/Megabyte|title=Definitions of Megabyte|website=Dictionary.reference.com|accessdate=30 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Oxford online dictionary defines, for example, megabyte as: &quot;Computing: a unit of information equal to one million or (strictly) {{val|1048576}} bytes.&quot;&lt;ref
name=&quot;oxford&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.askoxford.com/concise_oed/megabyte?view=uk|title=AskOxford: megabyte|website=Askoxford.com|accessdate=30 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The units Kbyte, Mbyte, and Gbyte are found in the trade press and in IEEE journals. Gigabyte was formally defined in IEEE Std 610.10-1994 as either {{val|1000000000}} or 2&lt;sup&gt;30&lt;/sup&gt; bytes.&lt;ref
name = &quot;IEEE610&quot;&gt;{{Cite book
| title= IEEE Std 610.10-1994 IEEE Standard Glossary of Computer Hardware Terminology
|date=24 June 1994
| quote= gigabyte (gig, GB). This term may mean either a) {{val|1000000000}} bytes or b) 2&lt;sup&gt;30&lt;/sup&gt; bytes. ... As used in this document, the terms kilobyte (kB) means 2&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt; or 1024 bytes, megabyte (MB) means 1024 kilobytes, and gigabyte (GB) means 1024 megabytes.|doi=10.1109/IEEESTD.1995.79522
|isbn=1-55937-492-6
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Kilobyte, Kbyte, and KB are equivalent units and all are defined in the obsolete standard, IEEE 100-2000.&lt;ref name=&quot;IEEE100&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers |authorlink=Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers |title=The Authoritative Dictionary of IEEE Standards Terms |publisher=IEEE Computer Society Press |year=2000 |isbn=978-0-7381-2601-2 |doi=10.1109/IEEESTD.2000.322230 }} &quot;kB See kilobyte.&quot; &quot;Kbyte Kilobyte. Indicates 2&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt; bytes.&quot; &quot;Kilobyte Either 1000 or 2&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt; or 1024 bytes.&quot; The standard also defines megabyte and gigabyte with a note that an alternative notation for base 2 is under development.&lt;/ref&gt;

The hardware industry measures system memory (RAM) using the binary meaning while magnetic disk storage uses the SI definition. However, many exceptions exist. Labeling of [[diskette]]s uses the megabyte to denote 1024×1000 bytes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Microsoft 121839&quot;/&gt; In the optical disks market, [[compact disc]]s use ''MB'' to mean 1024&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; bytes while [[DVD]]s use ''GB'' to mean 1000&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; bytes.&lt;ref name=&quot;cdromcap&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;dvdcap&quot;/&gt;

==Inconsistent use of units==

===Deviation between powers of 1024 and powers of 1000===
Computer storage has become cheaper per unit and thereby larger, by many orders of magnitude since &quot;K&quot; was first used to mean 1024. 
Because both the SI and &quot;binary&quot; meanings of kilo, mega, etc., are based on [[Exponentiation|powers]] of 1000 or 1024 rather than simple multiples, the difference between 1M &quot;binary&quot; and 1M &quot;decimal&quot; is proportionally larger than that between 1K &quot;binary&quot; and 1k &quot;decimal,&quot; and so on up the scale.
The relative difference between the values in the binary and decimal interpretations increases, when using the SI prefixes as the base, from 2.4% for kilo to nearly 21% for the yotta prefix.

[[File:Binaryvdecimal.svg|thumb|right|200px|Linear-log graph of percentage of the difference between decimal and binary interpretations of the unit prefixes versus the storage size.]]
{| style=&quot;margin:auto;&quot;  class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|- style=&quot;background:#ccf;&quot;
! Prefix
! colspan=&quot;2&quot;|Binary ÷ Decimal
! colspan=&quot;2&quot;|Decimal ÷ Binary
|- id=&quot;binary vs decimal kilo&quot;
| [[kilo-|kilo]]
| 1.024  &amp;nbsp; (+2.4%)      ||class=nowrap|&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:102.4px;background:#000&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:100px;background:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
| 0.9766 &amp;nbsp; (&amp;minus;2.3%)||class=nowrap|&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:100px;background:#ccc;&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:97.7px;background:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
|- id=&quot;binary vs decimal mega&quot;
| [[mega-|mega]]
| 1.049  &amp;nbsp; (+4.9%)      ||class=nowrap|&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:104.9px;background:#000;&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:100px;background:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
| 0.9537 &amp;nbsp; (&amp;minus;4.6%)||class=nowrap|&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:100px;background:#ccc;&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:95.4px;background:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
|- id=&quot;binary vs decimal giga&quot;
| [[giga-|giga]]
| 1.074  &amp;nbsp; (+7.4%)      ||class=nowrap|&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:107.4px;background:#000;&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:100px;background:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
| 0.9313 &amp;nbsp; (&amp;minus;6.9%)||class=nowrap|&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:100px;background:#ccc;&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:93.1px;background:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
|- id=&quot;binary vs decimal tera&quot;
| [[tera-|tera]]
| 1.100  (+10.0%)            ||class=nowrap|&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:110px;background:#000;&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:100px;background:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
| 0.9095 &amp;nbsp; (&amp;minus;9.1%)||class=nowrap|&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:100px;background:#ccc;&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:90.9px;background:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
|- id=&quot;binary vs decimal peta&quot;
| [[peta-|peta]]
| 1.126  (+12.6%)            ||class=nowrap|&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:112.6px;background:#000;&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:100px;background:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
| 0.8882 (&amp;minus;11.2%)      ||class=nowrap|&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:100px;background:#ccc;&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:88.8px;background:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
|- id=&quot;binary vs decimal exa&quot;
| [[exa-|exa]]
| 1.153  (+15.3%)            ||class=nowrap|&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:115.3px;background:#000;&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:100px;background:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
| 0.8674 (&amp;minus;13.3%)      ||class=nowrap|&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:100px;background:#ccc;&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:86.7px;background:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
|- id=&quot;binary vs decimal zeta&quot;
| [[zetta-|zetta]]
| 1.181  (+18.1%)            ||class=nowrap|&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:118.1px;background:#000;&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:100px;background:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
| 0.8470 (&amp;minus;15.3%)      ||class=nowrap|&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:100px;background:#ccc;&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:84.7px;background:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
|- id=&quot;binary vs decimal yota&quot;
| [[yotta-|yotta]]
| 1.209  (+20.9%)            ||class=nowrap|&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:120.9px;background:#000;&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:100px;background:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
| 0.8272 (&amp;minus;17.3%)      ||class=nowrap|&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:100px;background:#ccc;&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;display:inline-block;width:82.7px;background:#666;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
|}

===Consumer confusion===
In the early days of computers (roughly, prior to the advent of personal computers) there was little or no [[consumer confusion]] because of the technical sophistication of the buyers and their familiarity with the products. In addition, it was common for computer manufacturers to specify their products with capacities in full precision.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www-03.ibm.com/ibm/history/exhibits/mainframe/mainframe_PP2075.html |title=System/360 Model 75 |publisher=[[IBM]]|accessdate=2015-03-10|work=IBM Archives|quote=up to 1,048,576 characters of information}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the personal computing era, one source of consumer confusion is the difference in the way many operating systems display hard drive sizes, compared to the way hard drive manufacturers describe them. [[#Disk drives|Hard drives]] are specified and sold using &quot;GB&quot; and &quot;TB&quot; in their decimal meaning: one billion and one trillion bytes. Many operating systems and other software, however, display hard drive and file sizes using &quot;MB&quot;, &quot;GB&quot; or other SI-looking prefixes in their binary sense, just as they do for displays of RAM capacity. For example, many such systems display a hard drive marketed as &quot;160&amp;nbsp;GB&quot; as &quot;149.05&amp;nbsp;GB&quot;. The earliest known presentation of hard disk drive capacity by an operating system using &quot;KB&quot; or &quot;MB&quot; in a binary sense is 1984;&lt;ref&gt;Apple [[Macintosh]] which began using &quot;KB&quot; in a binary sense to report HDD capacity beginning 1984.&lt;/ref&gt; earlier operating systems generally presented the hard disk drive capacity as an exact number of bytes, with no prefix of any sort, for example, in the output of the MS-DOS or PC&amp;nbsp;DOS [[CHKDSK]] command.

===Legal disputes===
The different interpretations of disk size prefixes has led to class action lawsuits against digital storage manufacturers.
These cases involved both flash memory and hard disk drives.

====Recent Cases:====

The most recent cases (2019+) did not settle and ended in favor of the manufacturers, with courts holding that the legal definition of [[gigabyte]] or GB is 1 GB = 1,000,000,000 (10&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;) bytes (the decimal definition) rather than the binary definition (2&lt;sup&gt;30&lt;/sup&gt;) for commercial transactions.     Specifically, the courts held that &quot;the U.S. Congress has deemed the decimal definition of gigabyte to be the 'preferred' one for the purposes of 'U.S. trade and commerce' .... The California Legislature has likewise adopted the decimal system for all 'transactions in this state.'”&lt;ref name=&quot;Order Granting Motion to Dismiss&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | url = https://www.courthousenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/01/flashdrives.pdf
  | title = Order Granting Motion to Dismiss
  | publisher = [[United States District Court]]
  | accessdate = 2020-01-24
  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Early Cases:====

Earlier cases (2004-2007) were settled prior to any court ruling with the manufacturers admitting no wrongdoing but agreeing to clarify the storage capacity of their products on the consumer packaging.
Accordingly, many flash memory and hard disk manufacturers have disclosures on their packaging and web sites clarifying the formatted capacity of the devices
or defining MB as 1 million bytes and 1&amp;nbsp;GB as 1 billion bytes.&lt;ref name=&quot;wdc-CaviarSE16&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | url = http://www.wdc.com/en/products/Products.asp?DriveID=301
  | title = WD Caviar SE16 SATA Hard Drives
  | work = Western Digital: Products
  | publisher = [[Western Digital Corporation]]
  | accessdate = 2007-09-09
  | url-status = dead
  | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070902080558/http://www.wdc.com/en/products/products.asp?driveid=301
  | archivedate = 2007-09-02
  }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | url = http://forum.corsair.com/v3/showthread.php?t=33071
  | title = Jack Flash F.A.Q.
  | publisher = [[Corsair Memory]]
  | accessdate = 2014-06-20
  | quote = [...] the industry-standard definition of a megabyte (MByte) for flash devices is one million (1,000,000) bytes, where the operating system uses two to the twentieth power, or 1,048,576 bytes. Similarly, for a gigabyte (GByte), the number is 1,000,000,000 and 1,073,741,824 respectively.
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sandisk_cf_datasheet&quot;&gt;{{cite web 
 |url=http://www.sandisk.com/media/416788/80-11-01707_rev1_datasheet_ultracf_r1.pdf 
 |title=SanDisk Ultra® CompactFlash® cards 
 |publisher=[[SanDisk Corporation]] 
 |accessdate=2014-06-20 
 |url-status=dead 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130810032314/http://www.sandisk.com/media/416788/80-11-01707_rev1_datasheet_ultracf_r1.pdf 
 |archivedate=2013-08-10 
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sd-cap-disclaimer&quot;/&gt;

====Willem Vroegh v. Eastman Kodak Company====
On 20 February 2004, [[Willem Vroegh v. Eastman Kodak Company|Willem Vroegh filed a lawsuit]] against Lexar Media, Dane–Elec Memory, [[Fujifilm|Fuji Photo Film USA]], [[Eastman Kodak]] Company, Kingston Technology Company, Inc., [[Memorex]] Products, Inc.; [[PNY Technologies]] Inc., [[SanDisk|SanDisk Corporation]], [[Verbatim Corporation]], and [[Viking Interworks]] alleging that their descriptions of the capacity of their [[flash memory]] cards were false and misleading.

Vroegh claimed that a 256&amp;nbsp;MB Flash Memory Device had only 244&amp;nbsp;MB of accessible memory. &quot;Plaintiffs allege that Defendants marketed the memory capacity of their products by assuming that one megabyte equals one million bytes and one gigabyte equals one billion bytes.&quot;
The plaintiffs wanted the defendants to use the traditional values of 1024&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; for megabyte and 1024&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; for gigabyte.
The plaintiffs acknowledged that the IEC and IEEE standards define a MB as one million bytes but stated that the industry has largely ignored the IEC standards.&lt;ref name=&quot;Vreogh-3rd&quot;&gt;{{cite web|date=10 March 2005 |url=https://www.pddocs.com/FlashMemory/Documents/Vroegh%20Third%20Amended%20Complaint.pdf |title=Vreogh Third Amended Complaint (Case No. GCG-04-428953) |work=pddocs.com |publisher=Poorman-Douglas Corporation |accessdate=2007-09-09 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080309143513/https://www.pddocs.com/FlashMemory/Documents/Vroegh%20Third%20Amended%20Complaint.pdf |archivedate=March 9, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The parties agreed that manufacturers could continue to use the decimal definition so long as the definition was added to the packaging and web sites.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sandisk.com/Assets/Categories/Products/sd_capacitydisclaimer.pdf|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120413100902/http://www.sandisk.com/Assets/Categories/Products/sd_capacitydisclaimer.pdf|url-status=dead|archive-date=13 April 2012|title=Wayback Machine|date=13 April 2012|website=Sandisk.com|accessdate=30 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The consumers could apply for &quot;a discount of ten percent off a future online purchase from Defendants' Online Stores Flash Memory Device&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;FMsettle-faq&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Safier |first=Seth A. |url=https://www.pddocs.com/FlashMemory/faq.aspx |title=Frequently Asked Questions |work=Flash Memory Settlement |publisher=Poorman-Douglas Corporation |accessdate=2007-09-09 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070928013731/https://www.pddocs.com/FlashMemory/faq.aspx |archivedate=September 28, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Orin Safier v. Western Digital Corporation====
On 7 July 2005, an action entitled ''Orin Safier v. [[Western Digital]] Corporation, et al.'' was filed in the Superior Court for the City and County of San Francisco, Case No. CGC-05-442812.
The case was subsequently moved to the Northern District of California, Case No. 05-03353 BZ.&lt;ref name=&quot;wdc-safier-complaint&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | last = Gutride
  | first = Adam
  | author2 = Seth A. Safier
  | date = 29 March 2006
  | url = http://www.wdc.com/settlement/docs/complaint.htm
  | title = Class Action Complaint
  | work = Orin Safier v. Western Digital Corporation
  | publisher = [[Western Digital Corporation]]
  | accessdate = 2007-09-09
  | url-status = dead
  | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20071016171124/http://wdc.com/settlement/docs/complaint.htm
  | archivedate = 16 October 2007
  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although Western Digital maintained that their usage of units is consistent with &quot;the indisputably correct industry standard for measuring and describing storage capacity&quot;, and that they &quot;cannot be expected to reform the software industry&quot;, they agreed to settle in March 2006 with 14 June 2006 as the Final Approval hearing date.&lt;ref name=&quot;wdc-safier-settle&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | last = Zimmerman
  | first = Bernard
  | year = 2006
  | url = http://www.wdc.com/settlement/docs/longform.htm
  | title = Notice of Class Action and Proposed Settlement
  | work = Orin Safier v. Western Digital Corporation
  | publisher = [[Western Digital Corporation]]
  | accessdate = 2007-09-09
  | url-status = dead
  | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070922234210/http://www.wdc.com/settlement/docs/longform.htm
  | archivedate = 2007-09-22
  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Western Digital offered to compensate customers with a free download of backup and recovery software valued at US$30. They also paid $500,000 in fees and expenses to San Francisco lawyers Adam Gutride and Seth Safier, who filed the suit.
The settlement called for Western Digital to add a disclaimer to their later packaging and advertising.&lt;ref
name=&quot;betanews&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.betanews.com/article/Western_Digital_Settles_Capacity_Suit/1151510648|title=Western Digital Settles Capacity Suit|website=Betanews.com|accessdate=30 December 2017|date=28 June 2006}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=https://arstechnica.com/old/content/2006/06/7174.ars
|title=Western Digital settles drive size lawsuit
|author=Jeremy Reimer
|date=2006-06-30
|publisher=Ars Technica LLC
|accessdate=2010-02-10
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.wdc.com/settlement/docs/longform.htm
|title=NOTICE OF CLASS ACTION AND PROPOSED SETTLEMENT (&quot;NOTICE&quot;)
|author=Western Digital Corporation
|year=2006
|accessdate=2010-02-10
|url-status=dead
|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100507132711/http://www.wdc.com/settlement/docs/longform.htm
|archivedate=2010-05-07
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--- I think that to end on this bit is overly POV. I'll leave it to someone else to add. – jeh---&gt;
&lt;!---
Western Digital had this footnote in their settlement. &quot;Apparently, Plaintiff believes that he could sue an egg company for fraud for labeling a carton of 12 eggs a &quot;dozen,&quot; because some bakers would view a &quot;dozen&quot; as including 13 items.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Baskin-2006-02-01&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | last = Baskin
  | first = Scott D.
  | date = 1 February 2006
  | url = http://www.wdc.com/settlement/docs/document20.htm
  | title = &quot;Defendant Western Digital Corporation's Brief in Support of Plaintiff's Motion for Preliminary Approval&quot;
  | work = ''Orin Safier v. Western Digital Corporation''
  | publisher = [[Western Digital Corporation]]
  | accessdate = 2007-09-09
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
---&gt;

==== Cho v. Seagate Technology (US) Holdings, Inc. ====
A lawsuit (Cho v. Seagate Technology (US) Holdings, Inc., San Francisco Superior Court, Case No.  CGC-06-453195) was filed against [[Seagate Technology]], alleging that Seagate overrepresented the amount of usable storage by 7% on hard drives sold between March 22, 2001 and September 26, 2007.  The case was settled without Seagate admitting wrongdoing, but agreeing to supply those purchasers with free backup software or a 5% refund on the cost of the drives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | url = http://www.harddrive-settlement.com
  | title = Settlement Website for Cho v. Seagate Technology (US) Holdings, Inc.
  | accessdate = 2011-04-12
  | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20190118155341/http://www.harddrive-settlement.com/
  | archive-date = 18 January 2019
  | url-status = dead
  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Unique binary prefixes==

===Early suggestions===
While early computer scientists typically used k to mean 1000, some recognized the convenience that would result from working with multiples of 1024 and the confusion that resulted from using the same prefixes for two different meanings.

Several proposals for unique binary prefixes&lt;ref group=&quot;defn.&quot; name=&quot;d.binpref&quot;&gt;A '''binary prefix''' is a prefix that denotes a power of 1024. For example, in the computer industry's customary practice, one &quot;megabyte&quot; of RAM is 1024&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; bytes of RAM, one &quot;gigabyte&quot; of RAM is 1024&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; bytes of RAM, and so on. In the IEC system, these would be expressed as one &quot;mebibyte&quot; and one &quot;gibibyte,&quot; respectively. Both are &quot;binary prefixes&quot; in these usages.&lt;/ref&gt; were made in 1968. Donald Morrison proposed to use the Greek letter kappa ([[κ]]) to denote 1024, κ&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; to denote 1024&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, and so on.&lt;ref
name=&quot;Morrison&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal
|title=Letters to the editor: Abbreviations for computer and memory sizes
|author= Donald R. Morrison, [[Sandia National Laboratories|Sandia Corporation]]
|journal= Communications of the ACM
|volume=11 |issue=3 |date=March 1968 |page=150 |doi=10.1145/362929.362962}}&lt;/ref&gt;
(At the time, memory size was small, and only K was in widespread use.)
[[Wallace Givens]] responded with a proposal to use bK as an abbreviation for 1024 and bK2 or bK&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; for 1024&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, though he noted that neither the Greek letter nor lowercase letter b would be easy to reproduce on computer printers of the day.&lt;ref name=&quot;Givens&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal
|title=Letters to the editor: proposed abbreviation for 1024: bK
|author= Wallace Givens, Applied National Lab
|journal= Communications of the ACM
|volume=11 |issue=6 |date=June 1968 |page=391 |doi=10.1145/363347.363351}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Bruce Alan Martin]] of [[Brookhaven National Laboratory]] further proposed that the prefixes be abandoned altogether, and the letter [[binary scientific notation|B]] be used for base-2 exponents, similar to [[E notation|E]] in [[decimal scientific notation]], to create shorthands like 3B20 for 3×2&lt;sup&gt;20&lt;/sup&gt;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Martin_1968&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | title=Letters to the editor: On binary notation | first=Bruce Alan | last=Martin | publisher=[[Associated Universities Inc.]] | journal=[[Communications of the ACM]] | volume=11 | issue=10 | date=October 1968 | page=658 | doi=10.1145/364096.364107}}&lt;/ref&gt; a convention still used on some calculators to present binary floating point-numbers today.&lt;ref name=&quot;HP16C-Lib&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=HP16C Emulator Library for the HP48S/SX|first1=Jake|last1=Schwartz|first2=Rick|last2=Grevelle|date=2003-10-20|orig-year=1993&lt;!-- 1993-04 --&gt;|edition=1|version=1.20|url=http://www.pahhc.org/mul8r.htm|accessdate=2015-08-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

None of these gained much acceptance, and capitalization of the letter K became the ''de facto'' standard for indicating a factor of 1024 instead of 1000, although this could not be extended to higher powers.

As the discrepancy between the two systems increased in the higher-order powers, more proposals for unique prefixes were made.
In 1996, [[Markus Kuhn (computer scientist)|Markus Kuhn]] proposed a system with ''di'' prefixes, like the &quot;dikilobyte&quot; (K₂B or K2B).&lt;ref name=&quot;Kuhn&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/~mgk25/information-units.txt
|title=Standardized units for use in information technology
|author-first=Markus |author-last=Kuhn|author-link=Markus Kuhn (computer scientist)
|date=December 29, 1996}}
&lt;/ref&gt; [[Donald Knuth]], who uses decimal notation like 1&amp;nbsp;MB = 1000&amp;nbsp;kB,&lt;ref name=&quot;Knuth&quot;&gt;''[http://www-cs-staff.stanford.edu/~knuth/fasc1.ps.gz The Art of Computer Programming] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160305014709/http://www-cs-staff.stanford.edu/~knuth/fasc1.ps.gz |date=2016-03-05 }}'' Volume 1, [[Donald Knuth]], pp. 24 and 94&lt;/ref&gt; expressed &quot;astonishment&quot; that the IEC proposal was adopted, calling them &quot;funny-sounding&quot; and opining that proponents were assuming &quot;that standards are automatically adopted just because they are there.&quot; Knuth proposed that the powers of 1024 be designated as &quot;large kilobytes&quot; and &quot;large megabytes&quot; (abbreviated KKB and MMB, as &quot;doubling the letter connotes both binary-ness and large-ness&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;Knuth-webpage&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www-cs-staff.stanford.edu/~knuth/news99.html |title=Knuth: Recent News (1999) |publisher=Cs-staff.stanford.edu |accessdate=2012-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Metric prefix#Double prefixes|Double prefixes]] were already abolished from SI, however, having a multiplicative meaning (&quot;MMB&quot; would be equivalent to &quot;TB&quot;), and this proposed usage never gained any traction.

==={{anchor|kibi|mebi|gibi|tebi|pebi|exbi|zebi|yobi|IEC standard prefixes}}IEC prefixes===
The set of binary prefixes that were eventually adopted, now referred to as the &quot;IEC prefixes&quot;,&lt;ref group=&quot;defn.&quot; name=&quot;d.iecpref&quot;&gt;The term '''IEC binary prefix''' or '''IEC prefix''' refers to the prefixes such as kibi, mebi, gibi, etc., or their corresponding symbols Ki, Mi, Gi, etc., first adopted by the [[International Electrotechnical Commission]] (IEC). Such prefixes are only used with the units bits or bytes (or compound units derived from them such as bytes/second) and always denote powers of 1024; that is, they are always used as binary prefixes. Thus 1 mebibyte of RAM is 1024&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; bytes of RAM, one gibibyte or 1&amp;nbsp;GiB of RAM is 1024&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; bytes, and so on.&lt;/ref&gt; were first proposed by the [[International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry]]'s (IUPAC) Interdivisional Committee on Nomenclature and Symbols (IDCNS) in 1995. At that time, it was proposed that the terms kilobyte and megabyte be used only for 10&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; bytes and 10&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; bytes, respectively. The new prefixes ''kibi'' (kilobinary), ''mebi'' (megabinary), ''gibi'' (gigabinary) and ''tebi'' (terabinary) were also proposed at the time, and the proposed symbols for the prefixes were kb, Mb, Gb and Tb respectively, rather than Ki, Mi, Gi and Ti.&lt;ref name=&quot;iucr-95&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ww1.iucr.org/cexec/rep95/idcns.htm |title=International Union of CRYSTALLOGRAPHY |publisher=Ww1.iucr.org |accessdate=2012-01-26 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090827091437/http://ww1.iucr.org/cexec/rep95/idcns.htm |archive-date=27 August 2009 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; The proposal was not accepted at the time.

The [[Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers]] (IEEE) began to collaborate with the [[International Organization for Standardization]] (ISO) and [[International Electrotechnical Commission]] (IEC) to find acceptable names for binary prefixes. IEC proposed ''kibi'', ''mebi'', ''gibi'' and ''tebi'', with the symbols Ki, Mi, Gi and Ti respectively, in 1996.&lt;ref name=&quot;iucr-96&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.chester.iucr.org/iucr-top/cexec/rep96/idcns.htm |title=1996 IUCr IUPAC Interdivisional Committee on Nomenclature and Symbols (IDCNS) report |publisher=Chester.iucr.org |accessdate=2012-01-26 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130613121942/http://www.chester.iucr.org/iucr-top/cexec/rep96/idcns.htm |archivedate=2013-06-13 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- The preceding reference is weak as it merely consists of IUPAC noting IEC's proposal, but it is apparently the only thing we have. Would be better to have a ref for the actual proposal --&gt;

The names for the new prefixes are derived from the original SI prefixes combined with the term ''binary'', but contracted, by taking the first two letters of the SI prefix and &quot;bi&quot; from binary. The first letter of each such prefix is therefore identical to the corresponding SI prefixes, except for &quot;K&quot;, which is used interchangeably with &quot;k&quot;, whereas in SI, only the lower-case k represents 1000.

The IEEE decided that their standards would use the prefixes ''kilo'', etc. with their metric definitions, but allowed the binary definitions to be used in an interim period as long as such usage was explicitly pointed out on a case-by-case basis.&lt;ref name=&quot;ieee-standards&quot;&gt;Bruce Barrow, &quot;A Lesson in Megabytes&quot;, ''IEEE Standards Bearer'', January 1997, page 5&lt;/ref&gt;

===Adoption by IEC, NIST and ISO===
In January 1999, the IEC published the first international standard ([[IEC 60027-2]] Amendment 2) with the new prefixes, extended up to ''pebi'' (Pi) and ''exbi'' (Ei).&lt;ref&gt;&quot;These prefixes for binary multiples, which were developed by IEC Technical Committee (TC) 25, Quantities and units, and their letter symbols, with the strong support of the International Committee for Weights and Measures (CIPM) and the IEEE, were adopted by the IEC as Amendment 2 to IEC International Standard IEC 60027-2: Letter symbols to be used in electrical technology – Part 2: Telecommunications and electronics.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--- the preceding reference really needs more than just a quote. From what is it quoting? ---&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;iucr-99&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://journals.iucr.org/a/issues/2000/06/00/es0288/es0288bdy.html#SEC15.1 |title=IUCR 1999 report on IUPAC Interdivisional Committee on Nomenclature and Symbols |publisher=Journals.iucr.org |accessdate=2012-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--- this reference is weak as it merely consists of the International Union of Crystallography reporting on IUPAC's reporting on the IEC standard(!) ---&gt;

The IEC 60027-2 Amendment 2 also states that the IEC position is the same as that of BIPM (the body that regulates the SI system); the SI prefixes retain their definitions in powers of 1000 and are never used to mean a power of 1024.

In usage, products and concepts typically described using powers of 1024 would continue to be, but with the new IEC prefixes. For example, a memory module of {{val|536870912}} bytes ({{nowrap|512 × {{val|1048576}}}}) would be referred to as 512&amp;nbsp;MiB or 512 mebibytes instead of 512&amp;nbsp;MB or 512 megabytes. Conversely, since hard drives have historically been marketed using the SI convention that &quot;giga&quot; means {{val|1000000000}}, a &quot;500&amp;nbsp;GB&quot; hard drive would still be labeled as such. According to these recommendations, operating systems and other software would also use binary and SI prefixes in the same way, so the purchaser of a &quot;500&amp;nbsp;GB&quot; hard drive would find the operating system reporting either &quot;500&amp;nbsp;GB&quot; or &quot;466&amp;nbsp;GiB&quot;, while {{val|536870912}} bytes of RAM would be displayed as &quot;512&amp;nbsp;MiB&quot;.

The second edition of the standard, published in 2000,&lt;ref 
name=&quot;iec-2000&quot;&gt;IEC 60027-2 (2000-11) Ed. 2.0
&lt;/ref&gt; defined them only up to ''exbi'',&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal
|title=Prefixes for binary multiples
|author=A.J.Thor
|journal=Metrologia
|year=2000
|volume=37
|issue=81
|url=http://ej.iop.org/links/rDo33k,Nb/lrUHtuYE3BGiff6cav5vpA/me0112.pdf
|doi=10.1088/0026-1394/37/1/12
|page=81
|bibcode=2000Metro..37...81T
}}{{dead link|date=July 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--- again an indirect reference ---&gt; but in 2005, the third edition added prefixes ''zebi'' and ''yobi'', thus matching all SI prefixes with binary counterparts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|date=2005-08-15 |title=HERE COME ZEBI AND YOBI |publisher=International Electrotechnical Commission |url=http://www.iec.ch/news_centre/release/nr2005/nr2005.htm |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://archive.today/20070611071833/http://www.iec.ch/news_centre/release/nr2005/nr2005.htm |archivedate=June 11, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The harmonized [[International Organization for Standardization|ISO]]/[[International Electrotechnical Commission|IEC]] [[IEC 80000-13|IEC 80000-13:2008]] standard cancels and replaces subclauses 3.8 and 3.9 of IEC 60027-2:2005 (those defining prefixes for binary multiples). The only significant change is the addition of explicit definitions for some quantities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.niso.org/publications/newsline/2008/newslinemay2008.htm#Spec4 |title=niso, New Specs and Standards |publisher=Niso.org |accessdate=2012-01-26 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081208131408/http://www.niso.org/publications/newsline/2008/newslinemay2008.htm#Spec4 |archive-date=2008-12-08 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--- once again, a link to a cite to the document, not to the actual ISO/IEC document. This is unavoidable as the documents in question are *not* freely available  ---&gt;  In 2009, the prefixes kibi-, mebi-, etc. were defined by [[ISO 80000-1]] in their own right, independently of the kibibyte, mebibyte, and so on.

The BIPM standard JCGM 200:2012 &quot;International vocabulary of metrology – Basic and general concepts and associated terms (VIM), 3rd edition&quot; lists the IEC binary prefixes and states &quot;SI prefixes refer strictly to powers of 10, and should not be used for powers of 2.  For example, 1 kilobit should not be used to represent {{val|1024}} bits (2&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt; bits), which is 1 kibibit.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bipm.org/utils/common/documents/jcgm/JCGM_200_2012.pdf|title=International vocabulary of metrology - Basic and general concepts and associated terms (VIM)|edition=3rd|website=Bipm.org|accessdate=30 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| style=&quot;margin:auto;&quot;  class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+ Specific units of IEC 60027-2 A.2 and ISO/IEC 80000
|-
!colspan=&quot;2&quot;|IEC prefix
!colspan=&quot;4&quot;|Representations
!colspan=&quot;3&quot;|Customary prefix
|-
! Name
! Symbol
! Base 2
! Base 1024
! Value
!| Base 10
! Name
! Symbol
|-
| kibi
| Ki
| 2&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;
| 1024&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;
|align=&quot;right&quot;| {{val|1024}}
| = {{val|1.024|e=3}}
| [[Kilo-|kilo]]
| k&lt;ref name=&quot;wnwtd&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Webster's New World Telecom Dictionary|author=Ray Horak|page=271|publisher=[[John Wiley &amp; Sons]]|year=2008|isbn=9780471774570|quote=In computing and storage systems, a kB (kiloByte) is actually 1,024 (2^10) bytes, since the measurement is based on a base 2, or binary, number system. The term kB comes from the fact that 1,024 is nominally, or approximately, 1,000.}}
&lt;/ref&gt; or K
|- style=&quot;background:#ff9;&quot;
| mebi
| Mi
| 2&lt;sup&gt;20&lt;/sup&gt;
| 1024&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
|align=&quot;right&quot;| {{val|1048576}}
| ≈ {{val|1.049|e=6}}
| [[Mega-|mega]]
| M
|-
| gibi
| Gi
| 2&lt;sup&gt;30&lt;/sup&gt;
| 1024&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;
|align=&quot;right&quot;| {{val|1073741824}}
| ≈ {{val|1.074|e=9}}
| [[Giga-|giga]]
| G
|- style=&quot;background:#ff9;&quot;
| tebi
| Ti
| 2&lt;sup&gt;40&lt;/sup&gt;
| 1024&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;
|align=&quot;right&quot;| {{val|1099511627776}}
| ≈ {{val|1.100|e=12}}
| [[Tera-|tera]]
| T
|-
| pebi
| Pi
| 2&lt;sup&gt;50&lt;/sup&gt;
| 1024&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;
|align=&quot;right&quot;| {{val|1125899906842624}}
| ≈ {{val|1.126|e=15}}
| [[Peta-|peta]]
| P
|- style=&quot;background:#ff9;&quot;
| exbi
| Ei
| 2&lt;sup&gt;60&lt;/sup&gt;
| 1024&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;
|align=&quot;right&quot;| {{val|1152921504606846976}}
| ≈ {{val|1.153|e=18}}
| [[Exa-|exa]]
| E
|-
| zebi
| Zi
| 2&lt;sup&gt;70&lt;/sup&gt;
| 1024&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;
|align=&quot;right&quot;| {{val|1180591620717411303424}}
| ≈ {{val|1.181|e=21}}
| [[Zetta-|zetta]]
| Z
|- style=&quot;background:#ff9;&quot;
| yobi
| Yi
| 2&lt;sup&gt;80&lt;/sup&gt;
| 1024&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;
|align=&quot;right&quot;| {{val|1208925819614629174706176}}
| ≈ {{val|1.209|e=24}}
| [[Yotta-|yotta]]
| Y
|}

===Other standards bodies and organizations===
The IEC standard binary prefixes are now supported by other standardization bodies and technical organizations.

The United States [[National Institute of Standards and Technology]] (NIST) supports the ISO/IEC standards for
&quot;Prefixes for binary multiples&quot; and has a [http://physics.nist.gov/cuu/Units/binary.html web site] documenting them, describing and justifying their use. NIST suggests that in English, the first syllable of the name of the binary-multiple prefix should be pronounced in the same way as the first syllable of the name of the corresponding SI prefix, and that the second syllable should be pronounced as ''bee''.&lt;ref name=&quot;NIST-biprefix&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | url = http://physics.nist.gov/cuu/Units/binary.html
  | title = International System of Units (SI): Prefixes for binary multiples
  | work = The NIST Reference on Constants, Units, and Uncertainty
  | publisher = [[National Institute of Science and Technology]]
  | accessdate = 2007-09-09
}}&lt;/ref&gt; NIST has stated the SI prefixes &quot;refer strictly to powers of 10&quot; and that the binary definitions &quot;should not be used&quot; for them.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
|author=Barry N. Taylor &amp; Ambler Thompson Ed.
|title=The International System of Units (SI)
|url=http://physics.nist.gov/Pubs/SP330/sp330.pdf
|accessdate=2010-04-27
|publisher=National Institute of Standards and Technology
|location= Gaithersburg, MD
|page=29
|year= 2008
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The microelectronics industry standards body [[JEDEC]] describes the IEC prefixes in its online dictionary.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=mega (M) (as a prefix to units of semiconductor storage capacity)|url=http://www.jedec.org/standards-documents/dictionary/terms/mega-m-prefix-units-semiconductor-storage-capacity|website=JEDEC - Global Standards for the Microelectronics Industry|accessdate=7 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The JEDEC standards for semiconductor memory use the customary prefix symbols K, M and G in the binary sense.&lt;ref name=&quot;JESD209-4&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title = Low Power Double Data Rate 4 (LPDDR4) JESD209-4 | publisher = JEDEC Solid State Technology Association | date = August 2014 | page = 7 | url = http://www.jedec.org/standards-documents/results/jesd79-4%20ddr4 | quote = These devices contain the following number of bits: 4Gb has 4,294,967,296 bits … 32Gb has 34,359,738,368 bits}}  Free registration required to download the standard.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 19 March 2005, the IEEE standard [[IEEE 1541-2002]] (&quot;Prefixes for Binary Multiples&quot;) was elevated to a full-use standard by the IEEE Standards Association after a two-year trial period.&lt;ref name=&quot;IEEE1541&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|doi=10.1109/IEEESTD.2003.94236 |title=IEEE Std 1541-2002: IEEE Trial-Use Standard for Prefixes for Binary Multiples |url=http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/servlet/opac?punumber=8450 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121014151530/http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpl/mostRecentIssue.jsp?reload=true&amp;punumber=8450 |archive-date=2012-10-14 |accessdate=2007-07-29 |date=12 February 2003 |version=Reaffirmed 27 March 2008 |quote=This standard is prepared with two goals in mind: (1) to preserve the SI prefixes as unambiguous decimal multipliers and (2) to provide alternative prefixes for those cases where binary multipliers are needed. The first goal affects the general public, the wide audience of technical and nontechnical persons who use computers without much concern for their construction or inner working. These persons will normally interpret kilo, mega, etc., in their proper decimal sense. The second goal speaks to specialists – the prefixes for binary multiples make it possible for persons who work in the information sciences to communicate with precision. |isbn=978-0-7381-3385-0}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://standards.ieee.org/board/rev/305agenda.html |title=IEEE-SA Standards Board Standards Review Committee (RevCom) Meeting Agenda |accessdate=2007-02-25 |date=2005-03-19 |quote='''1541-2002''' (SCC14) IEEE Trial-Use Standard for Prefixes for Binary Multiples ''[No negative comments received during trial-use period, which is now complete; Sponsor requests elevation of status to full-use.]'' &lt;u&gt;Recommendation&lt;/u&gt;: Elevate status of standard from trial-use to full-use. Editorial staff will be notified to implement the necessary changes. The standard will be due for a maintenance action in 2007. |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070922215418/http://standards.ieee.org/board/rev/305agenda.html |archivedate=September 22, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, {{As of|2008|4|lc=on}}, the IEEE Publications division does not require the use of IEC prefixes in its major magazines such as ''Spectrum''&lt;ref name=Spectrum2008&gt;{{Cite journal
|last=Wallich
|first=Paul
|title=Tools &amp; toys: Hacking the Nokia N800
|journal=IEEE Spectrum
|volume=45
|issue=4
|page=25
|date=April 2008
|doi=10.1109/MSPEC.2008.4476441
}} ''&quot;A lot can happen in a decade. You can hold the Nokia N800 in your hand, yet it's a near-exact match for a high-end desktop PC from 10 years ago. It has a 320-megahertz processor, 128 megabytes of RAM, and a few gigabytes of available mass storage.&quot;''&lt;/ref&gt; or ''Computer''.&lt;ref name = &quot;Computer June 2007&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal
|last=Gschwind
|first=Michael
|title=An Open Source Environment for Cell Broadband Engine System Software
|journal=Computer
|volume=40
|issue=6
|pages=37–47
|publisher=IEEE Computer Society
|date=June 2007
|doi = 10.1109/MC.2007.192
|last2=Erb
|first2=David
|last3=Manning
|first3=Sid
|last4=Nutter
|first4=Mark
|url=http://www.research.ibm.com/people/m/mikeg/papers/2007_ieeecomputer.pdf
}} &quot;The processor has a memory subsystem with separate first-level 32-Kbyte instruction and data caches, and a 512-Kbyte unified second-level cache.&quot; Authors are with IBM.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!-- and many of the IEEE technical journals allow the authors to select the units in their papers.{{Citation needed|date=May 2008}}--&gt;

The [[International Bureau of Weights and Measures]] (BIPM), which maintains the [[International System of Units]] (SI), expressly prohibits the use of SI prefixes to denote binary multiples, and recommends the use of the IEC prefixes as an alternative since units of information are not included in SI.&lt;ref name=&quot;bipm-SI&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.bipm.org/en/si/prefixes.html
|title=BIPM – SI prefixes|website=Bipm.org|accessdate=30 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bipm-book&quot;&gt;{{Cite book
|title=The International System of Units (SI)
|chapter-url=http://www1.bipm.org/utils/common/pdf/si_brochure_8.pdf
|accessdate=2007-02-25
|edition=8th
|year=2006
|publisher=STEDI Media
|location=Paris
|language=French, English
|isbn=978-92-822-2213-3
|page=127
|chapter=§3.1 SI prefixes
|quote=[Side note:] These SI prefixes refer strictly to powers of 10. They should not be used to indicate powers of 2 (for example, one kilobit represents 1000 bits and not 1024 bits). The IEC has adopted prefixes for binary powers in the international standard IEC 60027-2: 2005, third edition, ''Letter symbols to be used in electrical technology – Part 2: Telecommunications and electronics''. The names and symbols for the prefixes corresponding to 2&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;, 2&lt;sup&gt;20&lt;/sup&gt;, 2&lt;sup&gt;30&lt;/sup&gt;, 2&lt;sup&gt;40&lt;/sup&gt;, 2&lt;sup&gt;50&lt;/sup&gt;, and 2&lt;sup&gt;60&lt;/sup&gt; are, respectively: kibi, Ki; mebi, Mi; gibi, Gi; tebi, Ti; pebi, Pi; and exbi, Ei. Thus, for example, one kibibyte would be written: 1&amp;nbsp;KiB = 2&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;nbsp;B = 1024&amp;nbsp;B, where B denotes a byte. Although these prefixes are not part of the SI, they should be used in the field of information technology to avoid the incorrect usage of the SI prefixes.
|author=Bureau International des Poids et Mesures.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Society of Automobile Engineers|Society of Automotive Engineers]] (SAE) prohibits the use of SI prefixes with anything but a power-of-1000 meaning, but does not recommend or otherwise cite the IEC binary prefixes.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAE&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sae.org/standardsdev/tsb/tsb003.pdf#page=33|format=PDF|title=Rules for SAE Use of SI (Metric) Units] – Section C.1.12 – SI prefixes|website=Sae.org|accessdate=30 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The European Committee for Electrotechnical Standardization ([[CENELEC]]) adopted the IEC-recommended binary prefixes via the harmonization document HD&amp;nbsp;60027-2:2003-03.&lt;ref name=&quot;EUHD&quot;&gt;[https://archive.today/20130213052907/http://www.cenelec.eu/dyn/www/f?p=104:110:1546953662480229::::FSP_PROJECT,FSP_LANG_ID:15306,25]&lt;/ref&gt;
The European Union (EU) has required the use of the IEC binary prefixes since 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.today/20120722151947/http://www.cenelec.eu/dyn/www/f?p=104:110:6177007965168887::::FSP_PROJECT,FSP_LANG_ID:20776,25]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Current practice==
Most computer hardware uses [[SI prefixes]]&lt;ref group=&quot;defn.&quot; name=&quot;d.SIp&quot;/&gt; to state capacity and define other performance parameters such as data rate. [[Main memory|Main]] and [[cache memory|cache]] memories are notable exceptions.

Capacities of [[main memory]] and [[cache memory]] are usually expressed with customary binary prefixes&lt;ref group=&quot;defn.&quot; name=&quot;d.cbp&quot;&gt;As used in this article, the term '''customary binary prefix''' or similar refers to prefixes such as kilo, mega, giga, etc., borrowed from the similarly named [[SI prefix]]es but commonly used to denote a power of 1024.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://welcome.hp.com/country/us/en/welcome.html |title=Hewlett-Packard |publisher=Welcome.hp.com |accessdate=2012-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sonystyle.com/webapp/wcs/stores/servlet/CategoryDisplay?catalogId=10551&amp;storeId=10151&amp;langId=-1&amp;categoryId=16155&amp;SR=nav:shop:computers:desktops:ss&amp;ref=http://www.sony.com/index.php|title=Consumer Electronics - Sony US|website=Sonystyle.com|accessdate=30 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.4allmemory.com/index.cfm?fuseaction=search.rdram_rambus_pc1066 |title=4AllMemory.com |publisher=4AllMemory.com |accessdate=2012-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
On the other hand, [[flash memory]], like that found in solid state drives, mostly uses [[SI prefixes]]&lt;ref group=&quot;defn.&quot; name=&quot;d.SIp&quot;/&gt; to state capacity.

Some operating systems and other software continue to use the customary binary prefixes in displays of memory, disk storage capacity, and file size, but SI prefixes&lt;ref group=&quot;defn.&quot; name=&quot;d.SIp&quot;&gt;The term '''SI prefix''' or similar refers to prefixes such as kilo, mega, giga, etc., defined by the [[International System of Units|SI system]] of units and ''always'' used to denote a power of 1000; in other words, always as decimal prefixes.&lt;/ref&gt; in other areas such as network communication speeds and processor speeds.

In the following subsections, unless otherwise noted, examples are first given using the common prefixes used in each case, and then followed by interpretation using other notation where appropriate.

===Operating systems===
Prior to the release of [[Classic Mac OS|Macintosh System Software]] (1984), file sizes were typically reported by the operating system without any prefixes.{{Citation needed|date=August 2008}} Today, most operating systems report file sizes with prefixes.

* The [[Linux kernel]] uses binary prefixes when booting up.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://www.annodex.net/cgi-bin/man/man2html?units+7 
 |title=Units 
 |accessdate=2007-05-20 
 |date=2001-12-22 
 |work=[[Manual page (Unix)|Linux Programmer's Manual]] 
 |quote=When the Linux kernel boots and says &lt;code&gt;hda: 120064896 sectors (61473&amp;nbsp;MB) w/2048KiB Cache&lt;/code&gt; the MB are megabytes and the KiB are kibibytes. 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070902124532/http://www.annodex.net/cgi-bin/man/man2html?units+7 
 |archivedate=2007-09-02 
 |url-status=live 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://lwn.net/2002/0103/a/esr-kibi.php3 |title=ESR post on LKML |publisher=Lwn.net |accessdate=2012-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, many [[Unix-like]] system utilities, such as the [[ls]] command, use powers of 1024 indicated as K/M (customary binary prefixes) if called with the ‘‘-h’’ option or give the exact value in bytes otherwise. The GNU versions will also use powers of 10 indicated with k&lt;!--deliberately lowercase--&gt;/M if called with the ‘‘--si’’ option.
** The [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] [[Linux distribution]] uses the IEC prefixes for base-2 numbers as of the 10.10 release.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.neowin.net/news/ubuntu-implements-units-policy-will-switch-to-base-10-units-in-future-release |title=Ubuntu implements units policy, will switch to base-10 units in future release |publisher=Neowin.net |accessdate=2012-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://wiki.ubuntu.com/UnitsPolicy |title=UnitsPolicy - Ubuntu Wiki |publisher=Wiki.ubuntu.com |accessdate=2012-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Microsoft Windows]] reports file sizes and disk device capacities using the customary binary prefixes or, in a &quot;Properties&quot; dialog, using the exact value in bytes.
* Since [[Mac OS X Snow Leopard]], (version 10.6), Apple's [[Mac OS X]] reports sizes using [[SI prefix|SI decimal prefixes]] (1&amp;nbsp;MB = {{val|1000000}} bytes).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine
|url=http://www.macworld.co.uk/mac/news/index.cfm?RSS&amp;NewsID=27034
|title= Snow Leopard's new maths
|magazine=Macworld 
|date=2009-08-28 
|accessdate=2011-04-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://support.apple.com/kb/TS2419 
|title=How Mac OS X reports drive capacity 
|publisher=Apple Inc 
|date=2009-08-27 
|accessdate=2009-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Software===
{{As of|February 2010}}, most software does not distinguish symbols for binary and decimal prefixes.&lt;ref group=&quot;defn.&quot; name=&quot;d.decpref&quot;&gt;A '''decimal prefix''' is a prefix that denotes a [[Exponentiation|power]] of 1000. For example, &quot;kilo&quot; denotes 1000, &quot;mega&quot; denotes 1000&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; or one million, &quot;giga&quot; denotes 1000&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; or one billion, and so on. SI prefixes are decimal prefixes.&lt;/ref&gt;
The [[International Electrotechnical Commission|IEC]] binary naming convention has been adopted by a few, but this is not used universally.

One of the stated goals of the introduction of the IEC prefixes was &quot;to preserve the SI prefixes as unambiguous decimal multipliers.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;IEEE1541&quot;/&gt; Programs such as [[fdisk]]/[[cfdisk]], [[parted]], and [[apt-get]] use SI prefixes with their decimal meaning.

&lt;gallery perrow=&quot;6&quot;&gt;
Image:GParted 0.3.5 -- 2008, 06.png|[[GNOME]]'s partition editor uses IEC prefixes to display partition sizes.  The total capacity of the 120×10&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;-byte disk is displayed as &quot;111.79&amp;nbsp;[[GiB]]&quot;
Image:GNOME System Monitor memory size and network rate.png|GNOME's system monitor uses IEC prefixes to show memory size and networking data rate.
Image:Bittornado screenshot showing use of IEC and SI prefixes.png|[[BitTornado]] uses standard SI prefixes for data rates and IEC prefixes for file sizes
Image:Deluge_using_Si_prefix_for_wiki_CD.png|[[Deluge (BitTorrent client)]] uses IEC prefixes for data rates as well as file sizes
&lt;/gallery&gt;

Example of the use of IEC binary prefixes in the [[Linux]] operating system displaying traffic volume on a network interface in kibibytes (KiB) and mebibytes (MiB), as obtained with the [[ifconfig]] utility:
&lt;pre&gt;
eth0      Link encap:Ethernet  HWaddr 00:14:A0:B0:7A:42
          inet6 addr: 2001:491:890a:1:214:a5ff:febe:7a42/64 Scope:Global
          inet6 addr: fe80::214:a5ff:febe:7a42/64 Scope:Link
          UP BROADCAST RUNNING MULTICAST  MTU:1500  Metric:1
          RX packets:254804 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 frame:0
          TX packets:756 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 carrier:0
          collisions:0 txqueuelen:1000
          RX bytes:18613795 (17.7&amp;nbsp;MiB)  TX bytes:45708 (44.6&amp;nbsp;KiB)
&lt;/pre&gt;

Software that uses standard SI prefixes for powers of 1000, but ''not'' IEC binary prefixes for powers of 1024, includes:

* Mac OS X v10.6 and later for hard drive and file sizes&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.macprime.ch/news/article/snow-leopard-1-gb-1000-mb/ 
|title=News – Snow Leopard: 1&amp;nbsp;GB = 1000&amp;nbsp;MB 
|publisher=macprime.ch 
|date=2009-06-19 
|accessdate=2009-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web 
| url = http://support.apple.com/kb/TS2419 
| title = How Mac OS X reports drive capacity 
| publisher = Apple 
| date = 2009-08-27 
| accessdate = 2009-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Software that supports decimal prefixes for powers of 1000 ''and'' binary prefixes for powers of 1024 (but does not follow SI or IEC nomenclature for this) includes:

* [[4DOS]] (uses lowercase letters as decimal and uppercase letters as binary prefixes)&lt;ref name=&quot;4DOS_4.00_HELP&quot;&gt;{{citation |title=4DOS.DOC 4.00 |title-link=4DOS 4.00 |author-first1=Hardin |author-last1=Brothers |author-first2=Tom |author-last2=Rawson |author-first3=Rex C. |author-last3=Conn |date=1991-11-01 |version=4.00}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;4DOS_8.00_HELP&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=4DOS 8.00 online help |title-link=4DOS 8.00 |author-first1=Hardin |author-last1=Brothers |author-first2=Tom |author-last2=Rawson |author-link2=Tom Rawson |author-first3=Rex C. |author-last3=Conn |author-link3=Rex C. Conn |author-first4=Matthias R. |author-last4=Paul |author-first5=Charles E. |author-last5=Dye |author-first6=Luchezar I. |author-last6=Georgiev |date=2002-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Software that uses IEC binary prefixes for powers of 1024 ''and'' uses standard SI prefixes for powers of 1000 includes:

{{col-begin}}
{{col-3}}
* [[GNU Core Utilities]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=https://www.gnu.org/software/coreutils/manual/html_node/Block-size.html#Block-size
|title=2.2 Block size
|accessdate=2007-05-20
|date=2002-12-28
|work=[[GNU Core Utilities]] manual
|publisher=[[Free Software Foundation]]
|quote=Integers may be followed by suffixes that are upward compatible with the [http://www.bipm.fr/enus/3_SI/si-prefixes.html SI prefixes] for decimal multiples and with the [http://physics.nist.gov/cuu/Units/binary.html IEC 60027-2 prefixes for binary multiples].
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[GParted]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://sourceforge.net/project/shownotes.php?release_id=389304&amp;group_id=115843
|title=gparted-0.2 changelog
|accessdate=2007-05-20
|date=2006-01-30
|work=[[SourceForge]]
|quote=changed KB/MB/GB/TB to KiB/MiB/GiB/TiB after reading http://www.iec.ch/zone/si/si_bytes.htm
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[FreeDOS#FreeDOS-32|FreeDOS-32]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://freedos-32.sourceforge.net/showdoc.php?page=standards FreeDOS-32 – Standards Compliance] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090112230144/http://freedos-32.sourceforge.net/showdoc.php?page=standards |date=January 12, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[ifconfig]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://www.annodex.net/cgi-bin/man/man2html?8+ifconfig 
 |title=IFCONFIG 
 |accessdate=2007-05-20 
 |date=2005-06-30 
 |work=[[Manual page (Unix)|Linux Programmer's Manual]] 
 |quote=Since net-tools 1.60-4 ifconfig is printing byte counters and human readable counters with IEC 60027-2 units. So 1&amp;nbsp;KiB are 2^10 byte. 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070216045538/http://www.annodex.net/cgi-bin/man/man2html?8+ifconfig 
 |archivedate=2007-02-16 
 |url-status=live 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[GNOME]] Network&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://projects.gnome.org/gnome-network/index.shtml |title=GNOME Network |publisher=Gnome.org |accessdate=2012-01-26 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130121122842/http://projects.gnome.org/gnome-network/index.shtml |archivedate=21 January 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{col-3}}
* [[SLIB]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://swissnet.ai.mit.edu/~jaffer/SLIB.html |title=SLIB |publisher=Swissnet.ai.mit.edu |date=2010-06-30 |accessdate=2012-01-26 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080807042947/http://swissnet.ai.mit.edu/~jaffer/SLIB.html |archive-date=2008-08-07 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Cygwin/X]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cygwin.com/xfree/ |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20011110203935/http://cygwin.com/xfree/ |archivedate=2001-11-10 |title=Cygwin/XFree86 |date=2001-11-10 |accessdate=2012-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[HTTrack]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://forum.httrack.com/readmsg/3011/3006/index.html |title=Re: minor typo – HTTrack Website Copier Forum |publisher=Forum.httrack.com |accessdate=2012-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Pidgin (IM client)]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://developer.pidgin.im/ticket/1684 |title=Developer discussion |publisher=Developer.pidgin.im |accessdate=2012-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Deluge (software)|Deluge]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://dev.deluge-torrent.org/changeset/527
|archive-url=https://archive.today/20130414141307/http://dev.deluge-torrent.org/changeset/527
|url-status=dead
|archive-date=2013-04-14
|title=Deluge changeset
|accessdate=2007-06-13
|quote=proper prefix for size
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{col-3}}
* [[yafc]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sourceforge.net/project/shownotes.php?release_id=240228&amp;group_id=11340 |title=Files |publisher=SourceForge.net |accessdate=2012-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[tnftp]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://archive.netbsd.se/?ml=pkgsrc-changes&amp;m=4873558 archive.netbsd.se] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090826161925/http://archive.netbsd.se/?ml=pkgsrc-changes&amp;m=4873558 |date=August 26, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[WinSCP]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://winscp.net/eng/docs/history |title=Recent Version History |publisher=WinSCP |accessdate=2012-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[MediaInfo]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| author =
| title = MediaInfo
| quote =
| publisher = MediaInfo main site
| pages =
| url = http://mediainfo.sourceforge.net/
| accessdate = 2010-03-01
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{col-end}}

===Computer hardware===
Hardware types that use powers-of-1024 multipliers, such as memory, continue to be marketed with customary binary prefixes.

====Computer memory====
[[File:Elixir M2U51264DS8HC3G-5T 20060320.jpg|thumb|The {{val|536870912}} byte (512×2&lt;sup&gt;20&lt;/sup&gt;) capacity of these RAM modules is stated as &quot;512&amp;nbsp;MB&quot; on the label.]]

Measurements of most types of electronic [[computer memory|memory]] such as [[Random Access Memory|RAM]] and [[Read-only memory|ROM]] are given using customary binary prefixes (kilo, mega, and giga).  This includes some [[flash memory]], like [[EEPROM]]s. For example, a &quot;512-megabyte&quot; memory module is 512×2&lt;sup&gt;20&lt;/sup&gt; bytes (512 × {{val|1048576}}, or {{val|536870912}}).

JEDEC Solid State Technology Association, the semiconductor engineering standardization body of the Electronic Industries Alliance (EIA), continues to include the customary binary definitions of kilo, mega and giga in their ''Terms, Definitions, and Letter Symbols'' document,&lt;ref name=&quot;JEDEC-terms&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
    | author     = JEDEC Solid State Technology Association
    | title      = JEDEC Standard No. 100B.01 – Terms, Definitions, and Letter Symbols for Microcomputers, Microprocessors, and Memory Integrated Circuits
    | date       = December 2002
    | page       = 8
    | url        = http://www.jedec.org/download/search/JESD100B01.pdf
    | accessdate = 2010-03-07
    | quote      = The definitions of kilo, giga, and mega based on powers of two are included only to reflect common usage. IEEE/ASTM SI 10-1997 states “This practice frequently leads to confusion and is deprecated.”
}} (Requires free registration and login.)&lt;/ref&gt;
and uses those definitions in later memory standards&lt;ref name=&quot;JEDEC-ddr3&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|title=DDR3 SDRAM Standard
|author=JEDEC
|date = September 2009|accessdate=2010-02-04
|url=http://www.jedec.org/standards-documents/docs/jesd-79-3d
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JEDEC-ddr2&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
|title=DDR2 SDRAM Standard
|author=JEDEC
|date = November 2009|accessdate=2010-02-04
|url=http://www.jedec.org/standards-documents/docs/jesd-79-2e
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JEDEC-configs&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
|title=Memory Configurations
|author=JEDEC
|accessdate=2010-02-04
|url=http://www.jedec.org/standards-documents/technology-focus-areas/memory-configurations-jesd21-c
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JEDEC-configs-toc&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
|title=Memory Configurations Table of Contents
|author=JEDEC
|accessdate=2010-02-04
|url=http://www.jedec.org/sites/default/files/21C_TOCR18.pdf
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JEDEC-configs-terms&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
|title=Terms and Definitions
|author=JEDEC
|accessdate=2010-02-04
|url=http://www.jedec.org/sites/default/files/2_00R19.pdf
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
(See also [[JEDEC memory standards]].)

Many computer programming tasks reference memory in terms of [[Power of two|powers of two]] because of the inherent binary design of current hardware addressing systems. For example, a 16-bit processor register can reference at most 65,536 items (bytes, words, or other objects); this is conveniently expressed as &quot;64K&quot; items.  An operating system might map memory as 4096-byte [[Page (computing)|pages]], in which case exactly 8192 pages could be allocated within {{val|33554432}} bytes of memory: &quot;8K&quot; (8192) pages of &quot;4 kilobytes&quot; (4096 bytes) each within &quot;32 megabytes&quot; (32&amp;nbsp;MiB) of memory.

====Hard disk drives====
All [[hard disk]] drive manufacturers state capacity using [[SI prefixes]].&lt;ref group=&quot;defn.&quot; name=&quot;d.SIp&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hitachigst.com/tech/techlib.nsf/techdocs/B259B4A73296DA628625751600058A80/$file/ProductBrochureMarch2009.pdf]{{dead link|date=October 2015}}{{cbignore}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.samsung.com/global/business/hdd/faqView.do?b2b_bbs_msg_id=167 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110616021347/http://www.samsung.com/global/business/hdd/faqView.do?b2b_bbs_msg_id=167 |archive-date=2011-06-16 |title=FAQs|website=Samsung.com |accessdate=30 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.seagate.com/docs/pdf/whitepaper/storage_solutions_guide.pdf |title=Storage Solutions Guide |website=Seagate |accessdate=2010-03-04 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100331115539/http://www.seagate.com/docs/pdf/whitepaper/storage_solutions_guide.pdf |archivedate=2010-03-31 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |url=http://sdd.toshiba.com/techdocs/MKxx33GSG_MK1235GSL_r1.pdf |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20091122075109/http://sdd.toshiba.com/techdocs/MKxx33GSG_MK1235GSL_r1.pdf |archive-date=22 November 2009 |title=Toshiba Introduces Two 1.8-inch Hard Disk Drive Families For Both High Performance and Long Battery Life in Mobile Computing Applications |publisher=Toshiba |date=4 November 2009 |access-date=30 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wdc.com/en/library/2579-001028.pdf |accessdate=2013-06-08 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130613220438/http://www.wdc.com/en/library/2579-001028.pdf |archive-date=13 June 2013 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Flash drives====
[[USB flash drive]]s, flash-based memory cards like [[CompactFlash]] or [[Secure Digital]], and flash-based [[Solid-state drive|SSDs]] use [[SI prefixes]];&lt;ref group=&quot;defn.&quot; name=&quot;d.SIp&quot;/&gt;
for example, a &quot;256 MB&quot; flash card provides at least 256 million bytes ({{val|256000000}}), not 256×1024×1024 ({{val|268435456}}).&lt;ref name=&quot;sd-cap-disclaimer&quot;&gt;{{cite web 
 |url=http://www.sandisk.com/Assets/Categories/Products/card_capacitydisclaimer.pdf 
 |title=Secure Digital Capacity Disclaimer 
 |work=sandisk.com 
 |publisher=[[SanDisk|SanDisk Corporation]] 
 |accessdate=2014-06-20 
 |url-status=dead 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130227015453/http://www.sandisk.com/Assets/Categories/Products/card_capacitydisclaimer.pdf 
 |archivedate=2013-02-27 
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
The flash memory chips inside these devices contain considerably more than the quoted capacities, but much like a traditional hard drive, some space is reserved for internal functions of the flash drive. These include [[wear leveling]], error correction, sparing, and metadata needed by the device's internal firmware.

====Floppy drives====
[[Floppy disk]]s have existed in numerous physical and logical [[List of floppy disk formats|formats]], and have been sized inconsistently.  In part, this is because the end user capacity of a particular disk is a function of the controller hardware, so that the same disk could be formatted to a variety of capacities.  In many cases, the media are marketed without any indication of the end user capacity, as for example, DSDD, meaning double-sided double-density.

The last widely adopted diskette was the 3½-inch high density. This has a formatted capacity of {{val|1474560}} bytes or 1440&amp;nbsp;KB (1440 × 1024, using &quot;KB&quot; in the customary binary sense). These are marketed as &quot;HD&quot;, or &quot;1.44&amp;nbsp;MB&quot; or both. This usage creates a third definition of &quot;megabyte&quot; as 1000×1024 bytes.

Most operating systems display the capacity using &quot;MB&quot; in the customary binary sense, resulting in a display of &quot;1.4&amp;nbsp;MB&quot; ({{val|1.40625|u=MiB}}). Some users have noticed the missing 0.04&amp;nbsp;MB and both Apple and Microsoft have support bulletins referring to them as 1.4&amp;nbsp;MB.&lt;ref
 name=&quot;Microsoft 121839&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 | last = Microsoft
 | title = Determining Actual Disk Size: Why 1.44&amp;nbsp;MB Should Be 1.40&amp;nbsp;MB
 | work = Article ID: 121839
 | publisher =Microsoft
 | date = 2003-05-06
 | url = http://support.microsoft.com/kb/121839
 | accessdate = 2007-07-07
}} &quot;The 1.44-megabyte (MB) value associated with the 3.5-inch disk format does not represent the actual size or free space of these disks. Although its size has been popularly called 1.44&amp;nbsp;MB, the correct size is actually 1.40&amp;nbsp;MB.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

The earlier &quot;1200&amp;nbsp;KB&quot; (1200×1024 bytes) 5¼-inch diskette sold with the [[PC AT|IBM PC AT]] was marketed as &quot;1.2&amp;nbsp;MB&quot; ({{val|1.171875|u=MiB}}).  The largest 8-inch diskette formats could contain more than a megabyte, and the capacities of those devices were often irregularly specified in megabytes, also without controversy.

Older and smaller diskette formats were usually identified as an accurate number of (binary) KB, for example the [[Disk II|Apple Disk II]] described as &quot;140KB&quot; had a 140×1024-byte capacity, and the original &quot;360KB&quot; double sided, double density disk drive used on the IBM PC had a 360×1024-byte capacity.

In many cases diskette hardware was marketed based on unformatted capacity, and the overhead required to format sectors on the media would reduce the nominal capacity as well (and this overhead typically varied based on the size of the formatted sectors), leading to more irregularities.

====Optical discs====
The capacities of most [[optical disc]] storage media like [[DVD]], [[Blu-ray Disc]], [[HD DVD]] and [[Magneto-optical drive|magneto-optical (MO)]]  are given using SI decimal prefixes.
A &quot;4.7&amp;nbsp;GB&quot; DVD has a nominal capacity of about 4.38&amp;nbsp;[[GiB]].&lt;ref name=&quot;dvdcap&quot;&gt;[http://www.osta.org/technology/pdf/dvdqa.pdf#page=20 Understanding Recordable and Rewritable DVD] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110102065839/http://www.osta.org/technology/pdf/dvdqa.pdf#page=20 |date=January 2, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, [[compact disc|CD]] capacities are always given using customary binary prefixes. Thus a &quot;700-MB&quot; (or &quot;80-minute&quot;) CD has a nominal capacity of about 700&amp;nbsp;[[MiB]] (approx 730&amp;nbsp;MB).&lt;ref name=&quot;cdromcap&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.videohelp.com/forum/userguides/135642.php |title=Data capacity of CDs |publisher=Videohelp.com |accessdate=2012-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Tape drives and media====
Tape drive and media manufacturers use SI decimal prefixes to identify capacity.&lt;ref&gt;[ftp://ftp.software.ibm.com/common/ssi/pm/sp/n/tsd00063usen/TSD00063USEN.PDFIBM]{{dead link|date=November 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/files/ECMA-ST/Ecma-319.pdf|title=Data Interchange on 12,7 mm 384-Track Magnetic Tape Cartridges – Ultrium-1 Format|website=Ecma-international.org|accessdate=30 December 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130917015428/http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/files/ECMA-ST/Ecma-319.pdf|archive-date=2013-09-17|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Data transmission and clock rates====
Certain units are always used with SI decimal prefixes even in computing contexts.
Two examples are [[hertz]] (Hz), which is used to measure the [[clock rate]]s of electronic components, and bit/s, used to measure [[bit rate|data transmission speed]].
* A 1-GHz processor receives {{val|1000000000}} clock ticks per second.
* A sound file sampled at {{val|44.1|u=kHz}} has {{val|44100}} samples per second.
* A {{val|128|u=kbit/s}} [[MP3]] stream consumes {{val|128000}} bits (16 kilobytes, {{val|15.6|u=KiB}}) per second.
* A {{val|1|u=Mbit/s}} Internet connection can transfer {{val|1000000}} bits per second ({{val|125000}} bytes per second ≈ {{val|122|u=KiB/s}}, assuming an 8-bit byte and no overhead)
* A {{val|1|u=Gbit/s}} Ethernet connection can transfer at nominal speed of {{val|1000000000}} bits per second ({{val|125000000}} bytes per second ≈ {{val|119|u=MiB/s}}, assuming an 8-bit byte and no overhead)
* A [[56k]] modem transfers {{val|56000}} bits per second ≈ {{val|6.8|u=KiB/s}}.

[[Computer bus|Bus]] clock speeds and therefore bandwidths are both quoted using SI decimal prefixes.

* [[DDR SDRAM|PC3200]] memory on a [[double data rate]] bus, transferring 8 bytes per cycle with a clock speed of {{val|200|u=MHz}} ({{val|200000000}} cycles per second) has a bandwidth of {{nowrap|{{val|200000000}} × 8 × 2}} = {{val|3200000000}} B/s = {{val|3.2|u=GB/s}} (about {{val|3.0|u=GiB/s}}).
* A [[PCI-X]] bus at {{val|66|u=MHz}} ({{val|66000000}} cycles per second), 64 bits per transfer, has a bandwidth of {{val|66000000}} transfers per second × 64 bits per transfer = {{val|4224000000}} bit/s, or {{val|528000000}} B/s, usually quoted as {{val|528|u=MB/s}} (about {{val|503|u=MiB/s}}).

===Use by industry===
IEC prefixes are used by [[Toshiba]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.toshiba-tdmt.com.tw/english/products/overview.aspx|title=Client : Client HDD - Toshiba|website=Toshiba-tdmt.com.tw|accessdate=30 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[IBM]], [[Hewlett-Packard|HP]] to advertise or describe some of their products.  According to one HP brochure, [http://h20566.www2.hp.com/portal/site/hpsc/template.BINARYPORTLET/public/kb/docDisplay/resource.process/?spf_p.tpst=kbDocDisplay_ws_BI&amp;spf_p.rid_kbDocDisplay=docDisplayResURL&amp;javax.portlet.begCacheTok=com.vignette.cachetoken&amp;spf_p.rst_kbDocDisplay=wsrp-resourceState%3DdocId%253Demr_na-c02022732-1%257CdocLocale%253D&amp;javax.portlet.endCacheTok=com.vignette.cachetoken]{{dead link|date=January 2020|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}} &quot;[t]o reduce confusion, vendors are pursuing one of two remedies: they are changing SI prefixes to the new binary prefixes, or they are recalculating the numbers as powers of ten.&quot;  The [[IBM Data Center]] also uses IEC prefixes to reduce confusion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pic.dhe.ibm.com/infocenter/etc/cust/index.jsp?topic=/com.ibm.storage.etc.doc/etc_data_storage_values.html|title=IBM Knowledge Center|website=Pic.dhe.ibm.com|accessdate=30 December 2017}}{{Dead link|date=February 2020 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The IBM Style Guide reads&lt;ref&gt;DeRespinis, F., Hayward, P., Jenkins, J., Laird, A., McDonald, L., &amp; Radzinski, E. (2011). The IBM style guide: conventions for writers and editors. IBM Press.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt;To help avoid inaccuracy (especially with the larger prefixes) and potential ambiguity, the International Electrotechnical Commission (IEC) in 2000 adopted a set of prefixes specifically for binary multipliers (See IEC 60027-2).  Their use is now supported by the United States National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) and incorporated into ISO 80000.  They are also required by EU law and in certain contexts in the US.

However, most documentation and products in the industry continue to use SI prefixes when referring to binary multipliers. In product documentation, follow the same standard that is used in the product itself (for example, in the interface or firmware). Whether you choose to use IEC prefixes for powers of 2 and SI prefixes for powers of 10, or use SI prefixes for a dual purpose ... be consistent in your usage and explain to the user your adopted system. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

==See also==
* [[Binary engineering notation]]
* [[ISO/IEC 80000]]
* [[Nibble]]
* [[Octet (computing)|Octet]]
* [[Orders of magnitude (data)|Orders of magnitude]]
* [[Timeline of binary prefixes]]

==Definitions==
{{Reflist|group=&quot;defn.&quot;}}

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite web|url=http://www.iec.ch/zone/si/si_bytes.htm|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090403051731/http://www.iec.ch/zone/si/si_bytes.htm|archivedate=2009-04-03|title=When is a kilobyte a kibibyte? And an MB an MiB?|publisher=International Electrotechnical Commission|date=2007-02-12}} – An introduction to binary prefixes
* {{cite web|url=http://physics.nist.gov/cuu/Units/binary.html|title=Prefixes for binary multiples|publisher=[[NIST]]}}
* {{Cite press release|url=https://www.nist.gov/public_affairs/techbeat/tb9903.htm#Information%20Technology|title=Get Ready for the mebi, gibi and tebi|publisher=[[NIST]]|date=1999-03-02}}
* {{cite web|url=http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/~mgk25/information-units.txt|title=What is a Megabyte ...?|author-first=Markus |author-last=Kuhn|author-link=Markus Kuhn (computer scientist)|date=1996-12-29}}&amp;mdash;a 1996&amp;ndash;1999 paper on bits, bytes, prefixes and symbols
* {{cite web|url=http://jdebp.eu./FGA/1mb44-is-not-a-standard-floppy-disc-size.html|author-first=Jonathan|author-last=de Boyne Pollard|title=There is no such thing as a 1.44&amp;nbsp;MB standard format floppy disc|work=Frequently Given Answers|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20161007222128/https://jdebp.eu/FGA/1mb44-is-not-a-standard-floppy-disc-size.html|archivedate=2016-10-07}}
* {{cite web|url=http://www.quinion.com/words/turnsofphrase/tp-kib1.htm|title=Kibibyte|date=1999-08-21|author=Michael Quinion|work=World Wide Words}}&amp;mdash;Another description of binary prefixes
* {{Cite journal|url=http://www.wiebetech.com/pressreleases/BillionEqualBillion.pdf|title=When One Billion does not equal One Billion, or: Why your computer's disk drive capacity doesn't appear to match the stated capacity|author=James Wiebe|date=2003-10-09|accessdate=2010-01-22}}&amp;mdash;White-paper on the controversy over drive capacities

==External links==
* [http://lpar.ath0.com/2008/07/15/si-unit-prefixes-a-plea-for-sanity/ A plea for sanity]
* [https://alexey.chernyak.id.au/prefBin.xhtml A summary of the organizations, software, and so on that have implemented the new binary prefixes]
* [http://www.lyberty.com/encyc/articles/kb_kilobytes.html KiloBytes vs. kilobits vs. Kibibytes (Binary prefixes)]
* [http://converter.50webs.com/ SI/Binary Prefix Converter]
* [http://knowledge.seagate.com/articles/en_US/FAQ/002046en?language=en_US Storage Capacity Measurement Standards]

{{Computer Storage Volumes}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Binary Prefix}}
[[Category:Measurement]]
[[Category:Naming conventions]]
[[Category:Binary prefixes| ]]
[[Category:Units of information]]
[[Category:Numeral systems]]</text>
      <sha1>lr278zyij5cqnx4uxjwqmme90bso3w2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
