  <page>
    <title>Bartolomeo Ammannati</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4091</id>
    <revision>
      <id>916967024</id>
      <parentid>916966990</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-09-21T16:12:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Taromsky</username>
        <id>9710872</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added [[Category:Italian Mannerist architects]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{more footnotes|date=February 2012}}

[[File:Fountains of Neptune.JPG|thumb|The ''[[Fountain of Neptune, Florence|Fountain of Neptune]]'' (''Fontana del Nettuno'') on the [[Piazza della Signoria]] in [[Florence]], [[Italy]]]]
'''Bartolomeo Ammannati''' (18 June 1511{{snd}}13 April 1592) was an Italian [[architect]] and [[Sculpture|sculptor]], born at [[Settignano]], near [[Florence]]. He studied under [[Baccio Bandinelli]] and [[Jacopo Sansovino]] (assisting on the design of the Library of St. Mark's, the ''[[Biblioteca Marciana]]'', Venice) and closely imitated the style of [[Michelangelo]].&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

He was more distinguished in architecture than in sculpture. He worked in [[Rome]] in collaboration with [[Giacomo Barozzi da Vignola|Vignola]] and [[Giorgio Vasari|Vasari]]),&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; including designs for the [[Villa Giulia]], but also for works and at [[Lucca]].  He labored during 1558–1570, in the refurbishment and enlargement of [[Pitti Palace]], creating the courtyard consisting of three wings with rusticated facades, and one lower portico leading to the amphitheatre in the Boboli Gardens. His design mirrored the appearance of the main external façade of Pitti. He was also named ''Consul'' of [[Accademia delle Arti del Disegno]] of Florence, which had been founded by the Duke Cosimo I in 1563.
[[File:Boboli-gardens-from-palazzo.jpg|thumb|Garden entrance of the Ammannati Courtyard in the Pitti Palace.]]

In 1569, Ammanati was commissioned to build the [[Ponte Santa Trinita]], a bridge over the Arno River. The three arches are elliptic, and though very light and elegant, has survived, when floods had damaged other Arno bridges at different times.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; Santa Trinita was destroyed in 1944, during World War II, and rebuilt in 1957.

Ammannati designed what is considered a prototypic [[mannerist]] sculptural ensemble in the ''[[Fountain of Neptune, Florence|Fountain of Neptune]]'' (''Fontana del Nettuno''), prominently located in the [[Piazza della Signoria]] in the center of Florence.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; The assignment was originally given to the aged [[Bartolommeo Bandinelli]]; however when Bandinelli died, Ammannati's design, bested the submissions of [[Benvenuto Cellini]] and [[Vincenzo Danti]], to gain the commission. From 1563 and 1565, Ammannati and his assistants, among them [[Giambologna]], sculpted the block of marble that had been chosen by Bandinelli. He took Grand Duke [[Cosimo I]] as model for Neptune's face. The statue was meant to highlight Cosimo's goal of establishing a Florentine Naval force. The ungainly sea god was placed at the corner of the Palazzo Vecchio within sight of Michelangelo’s David statue, and the then 87-year-old sculptor is said to have scoffed at Ammannati— saying that he had ruined a beautiful piece of marble— with the ditty: &quot;Ammannati, Ammanato, che bel marmo hai rovinato!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=Y2OThzu08lMC Isabella de' Medici], by Caroline P. Murphy, page 76. Murphy only mentions the phrase ''Ammannati Ruinati'' as Michelangelo's words. It appears the statue received a cool public welcome relative to the David.&lt;/ref&gt; Ammannati continued work on this fountain for a decade, adding around the perimeter a cornucopia of demigod figures: bronze reclining river gods, laughing [[satyr]]s and marble sea horses emerging from the water. 

In 1550 Ammannati married [[Laura Battiferri]], an elegant poet and an accomplished woman.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; Later in his life he had a religious crisis, influenced by [[Counter-Reformation]] piety, which resulted in condemning his own works depicting [[nudity]], and he left all his possessions to the [[Jesuits]].

He died in Florence in 1592.

==Other Sculptures==
* ''Victory'' (1540), marble, [[Museo Nazionale del Bargello]], Florence.
* ''[[Leda (mythology)|Leda]] with the Swan'', marble, also in Bargello, Florence.
* ''[[Venus (mythology)|Venus]]'' (1558–59), marble, [[Prado Museum]], [[Madrid]].
* ''Parnassus'' (1563), marble, Museo Nazionale del Bargello, Florence.
* ''Allegory of Winter'' (1563–65), stone, [[Villa Medici]], Castello.
* ''Goddess Opi'' (1572–75), bronze, [[Palazzo Vecchio]], Florence.

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Pigna - Collegio romano 1080166.JPG|The [[Collegio Romano|Jesuit College]] in Rome, 1582–84, was one of Ammannati's later designs
File:Venus by Baccio Bandinelli (Prado, E-171) 01.jpg|''Venus'', a variation on the classical type known as [[Aphrodite of Cnidus|Venus Pudica]]. However, the arms are the result of an 18th-century restoration, as the original had the arms cut off in order to allow water to flow out.
File:Bartolomeo ammannati (attr.), vasca con arme busdraghi e dragone, 04.JPG|Dragon
File:Parco di Castello, fontana del Gennaio 1.JPG|Parco di Villa Reale di Castello (Villa di Castello) ''Fountain of January'' (''Fontana del Gennaio'') in Florence Italy
File:Da bartolomeo ammannati, giustizia, firenze tardo 16mo secolo.JPG|Justice
File:Cristo e la cananea di Alessandro Allori detail.jpg|Christ and Canaanite woman by [[Alessandro Allori]]. Commissioned by Ammannati for funeral of his wife poet [[Laura Battiferri]] (painted as old woman with the book).
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==References==
&lt;references&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;&gt;{{EB1911|inline=1|wstitle=Ammanati, Bartolomeo|volume=1|page=859}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/references&gt;
{{Commons category|Bartolomeo Ammannati}}
*[http://www.all-art.org/history230-15-7a.html Bartolomeo Ammannati in the &quot;History of Art&quot;]

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ammannati, Bartolomeo}}
[[Category:1511 births]]
[[Category:1592 deaths]]
[[Category:People from the Province of Florence]]
[[Category:16th-century Italian architects]]
[[Category:16th-century Italian sculptors]]
[[Category:Italian male sculptors]]
[[Category:Italian Mannerist sculptors]]
[[Category:Italian Mannerist architects]]</text>
      <sha1>aftt4ea3btkhbiso5utr2flv5k31j1h</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
