  <page>
    <title>Bordeaux</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4097</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942581829</id>
      <parentid>942537400</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-25T15:30:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Domdeparis</username>
        <id>21263205</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Notable people */ Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/77.92.236.164|77.92.236.164]] ([[User talk:77.92.236.164|talk]]): Possible vandalism ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|the city in France|the wine|Bordeaux wine|other functions|Bordeaux (disambiguation)}}
{{redirect|Burdigala|the ocean liner|SS Burdigala}}
{{short description|Prefecture and commune in Nouvelle-Aquitaine, France}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2015}}
{{Infobox French commune
 |name               = Bordeaux
 |common name        = Bordeaux
| demonym            = Bordelais
 |commune status     = [[Prefectures of France|Prefecture]] and [[Communes of France|commune]]
 |image              = Montage Bordeaux.jpg
 |image size         = 250
 |caption            = Clockwise from top: [[Place de la Bourse]] by the [[Garonne]], Allées du Tourny and Maison de Vin, [[Pont de pierre (Bordeaux)|Pierre Bridge]] on the Garonne, Meriadeck Commercial Centre, front of Palais Rohan Hotel, and [[Bordeaux Cathedral|Saint-André Cathedral]] with the [[Bordeaux tramway]]
 |image coat of arms = Coat of Arms of Bordeaux.svg
 |city motto         = ''Lilia sola regunt lunam undas castra leonem.''&lt;br/&gt;&quot;The [[fleur-de-lis]] alone rules over the moon, the waves, the castle, and the lion&quot; (in French: « Les lys règnent seuls sur la lune, les ondes, la forteresse et le lion. ») &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bordeaux.fr/ebx/pgPresStand8.psml?_nfpb=true&amp;_pageLabel=pgPresStand8&amp;classofcontent=presentationStandard&amp;id=6931|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130120062743/http://www.bordeaux.fr/ebx/pgPresStand8.psml?_nfpb=true&amp;_pageLabel=pgPresStand8&amp;classofcontent=presentationStandard&amp;id=6931|url-status=dead|archive-date=20 January 2013|title=Bordeaux : Découvrir Bordeaux - Histoire de Bordeaux|date=20 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |coordinates        = {{coord|44.84|-0.58|format=dms|display=inline,title}}
 |INSEE              = 33063
 |arrondissement     = Bordeaux
 |canton             = [[Cantons of Bordeaux|5 cantons]]
 |intercommunality   = [[Bordeaux Métropole]]
 |mayor              = Nicolas Florian
 |party              = [[The Republicans (France)|LR]]
 |term               = 2019–2020
 |area km2           = 49.36
 |population         = {{France metadata Wikidata|population_total}}
 |population date    = {{France metadata Wikidata|population_as_of}}
|population footnotes   = {{France metadata Wikidata|population_footnotes}}
 |population ranking = [[List of communes in France with over 20,000 inhabitants|9th in France]]
 |urban area km2     = 1172.79
 |urban area date    = 2010
 |urban pop          = 760,933 &lt;ref&gt;''Séries historiques des résultats du recensement – Unité urbaine 2010 de Bordeaux (33701)'', INSEE.Retrieved 2 August 2014&lt;/ref&gt;
 |urban pop date     = January 2011
 |metro area km2     = 5613.41
 |metro area date    = 2010
 |metro area pop     = 1,195,335&lt;ref name=&quot;AU10_pop&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://insee.fr/fr/themes/tableau_local.asp?ref_id=TER&amp;millesime=2011&amp;typgeo=AU2010&amp;typesearch=territoire&amp;codgeo=Bordeaux+%28006%29&amp;territoire=OK |title=Séries historiques des résultats du recensement – Aire urbaine 2010 de Bordeaux (006)|publisher=INSEE |accessdate=2 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |metro area pop date= 2013
 |website            = {{URL|www.bordeaux.fr}}
 {{Infobox UNESCO World Heritage Site
  |child         = yes
  |Official_name = Bordeaux, Port of the Moon
  |ID            = 1256
  |Criteria      = Cultural: ii, iv
  |Year          = 2007
  |Area          = 1,731 ha
  |Buffer_zone   = 11,974 ha
}}
}}
'''Bordeaux''' ({{IPA-fr|bɔʁdo|-|Fr.Bordeaux.ogg}}; [[Gascon language|Gascon]] {{lang-oc|Bordèu}} {{IPA-oc|buɾˈðɛw|}}) is a port city on the [[Garonne]] in the [[Gironde]] [[Departments of France|department]] in Southwestern [[France]].

The municipality ([[Communes of France|commune]]) of Bordeaux proper has a population of 257,804 (2019). Bordeaux is the centre of the [[Bordeaux Métropole]] that has a population of 783,081 (2017) and includes its [[suburb]]s and close [[satellite town]]s. With 1,195,335 in the metropolitan area, it is the sixth-largest in France, after Paris, Marseille, Lyon, Toulouse, and Lille. It is the capital of the [[Nouvelle-Aquitaine]] region, as well as the [[Prefectures in France|prefecture]] of the Gironde department. Its inhabitants are called ''&quot;Bordelais&quot;'' (for men) or ''&quot;Bordelaises&quot;'' (women). The term &quot;Bordelais&quot; may also refer to the city and its surrounding region.

Being at the center of a major wine-growing and wine-producing region, Bordeaux remains a prominent powerhouse and exercises significant influence on the world wine industry although no wine production is conducted within the city limits. It is home to the world's main wine fair, [[Vinexpo]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vinexpo.com/en/a-propos/historique |title=Archived copy |accessdate=20 August 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090706075152/http://www.vinexpo.com/en/a-propos/historique/ |archivedate=6 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the wine economy in the metro area takes in 14.5&amp;nbsp;billion euros each year. [[Bordeaux wine]] has been produced in the region since the 8th century. The historic part of the city is on the [[World Heritage Site|UNESCO World Heritage List]] as &quot;an outstanding urban and architectural ensemble&quot; of the 18th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/in_pictures/6249110.stm |title=In pictures: New World Heritage sites |work=BBC News |date=28 June 2007 |accessdate=5 May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; After Paris, Bordeaux has the highest number of preserved historical buildings of any city in France.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.commanderie.org/showRegion.action|title=Commanderie|website=commanderie.org|access-date=2018-02-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
{{See also|Timeline of Bordeaux}}
[[File:Bituriges Vivisci.jpg|thumb|left|Coins of the [[Bituriges Vivisci]], 5th–1st century BC, derived from the coin designs of [[Greeks in pre-Roman Gaul]]. [[Cabinet des Médailles]].]]

Around 300 BC the region was the settlement of a [[List of Celtic tribes|Celtic tribe]], the [[Bituriges Vivisci]], named the town '''Burdigala''', probably of [[Aquitanian language|Aquitanian]] origin.

In 107 BC the [[Battle of Burdigala]] was fought by the Romans who were defending the [[Allobroges]], a [[Gauls|Gallic tribe]] allied to Rome, and the [[Tigurini]] led by [[Divico]]. The Romans were defeated and their commander, the [[Roman consul|consul]] [[Lucius Cassius Longinus (consul 107 BC)|Lucius Cassius Longinus]], was killed in battle.

The city came under [[ancient Rome|Roman]] rule around 60 BC, and it became an important commercial centre for [[tin]] and [[lead]]. It continued to flourish, especially during the [[Severan dynasty]] (3rd century), and acquired the status of capital of [[Gallia Aquitania|Roman Aquitaine]]. In 276 it was sacked by the [[Vandals]]. The Vandals attacked again in 409, followed by the [[Visigoths]] in 414, and the [[Franks]] in 498, and afterwards the city fell into a period of relative obscurity.

[[File:Merovingian tremisses minted in Bordeaux by the Church of Saint Etienne late 6th century.jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[Merovingian dynasty|Merovingian]] [[Tremissis|tremisses]] minted in Bordeaux by the Church of Saint-Étienne, late 6th century. [[British Museum]].]]
In the late 6th century the city re-emerged as the seat of a county and an archdiocese within the [[Merovingian dynasty|Merovingian]] [[Francia|kingdom of the Franks]], but royal Frankish power was never strong. The city started to play a regional role as a major urban center on the fringes of the newly founded Frankish [[Duchy of Vasconia]]. Around 585 Gallactorius was made count of [[County of Bordeaux|Bordeaux]] and fought the Basques.

In 732 the city was plundered by the troops of [[Abdul Rahman Al Ghafiqi|Abd er Rahman]] who stormed the fortifications and overwhelmed the Aquitanian garrison. [[Odo the Great|Duke Eudes]] mustered a force to engage the [[Umayyad Caliphate|Umayyads]], eventually engaging them in the [[Battle of the River Garonne]] somewhere near the river Dordogne. The battle had a high death toll, and although Eudes was defeated he had enough troops to engage in the [[Battle of Tours|Battle of Poitiers]] and so retain his grip on Aquitaine.

In 735 following his father Eudes's death, the Aquitanian [[Hunald I|duke Hunald]] led a rebellion to which [[Charles]] responded by launching an expedition that captured Bordeaux.  However, it was not retained for long, during the following year the Frankish commander clashed in battle with the Aquitanians but then left to take on hostile Burgundian authorities and magnates. In 745 Aquitaine faced another expedition where Charles's sons Pepin and Carloman challenged Hunald's power and defeated him. Hunald's son [[Waiofar|Waifer]] replaced him and confirmed Bordeaux as the capital city (along with Bourges in the north).

During the last stage of the [[Pepin the Short#Expansion of the Frankish realm|war against Aquitaine]] (760–768), it was one of Waifer's last important strongholds to fall to the troops of King [[Pepin the Short]].  Charlemagne built the fortress of Fronsac (''Frontiacus'', ''Franciacus'') near Bordeaux on a hill across the border with the Basques (''Wascones''), where Basque commanders came and pledged their loyalty (769).

In 778 [[Seguin I of Gascony|Seguin (or Sihimin)]] was appointed count of Bordeaux, probably undermining the power of the Duke [[Lupo II of Gascony|Lupo]], and possibly leading to the [[Battle of Roncevaux Pass]]. In 814 Seguin was made Duke of [[Duchy of Vasconia|Vasconia]], but was deposed in 816 for failing to suppress a Basque rebellion. Under the [[Carolingian dynasty|Carolingians]], sometimes the [[Count of Bordeaux|Counts of Bordeaux]] held the title concomitantly with that of [[Duke of Gascony|Duke of Vasconia]]. They were to keep the Basques in check and defend the mouth of the Garonne from the [[Viking]]s when they appeared in c. 844. In Autumn 845 the Vikings were raiding Bordeaux and Saintes, count [[Seguin II of Gascony|Seguin II]] marched on them but was captured and executed. 

Although the port of Bordeaux was a buzzing trade center, the stability and success of the city was constantly threatened by Germanic and Norman invasions. It wasn’t until the marriage of Eleanor of Aquitaine and Henry Plantagenet in 1152 established some sort of protection, as it provided a connection with the English. After this union, Bordeaux suddenly had access to naval protection, which made the attacks from the nomadic groups few and far between. &lt;ref&gt;https://www.bordeaux-port.fr/en/port-bordeaux/history&lt;/ref&gt;

From the 12th to the 15th century Bordeaux regained importance following the marriage of Duchess [[Eleanor of Aquitaine|Eléonore]] of [[Duchy of Aquitaine|Aquitaine]] to the French-speaking Count Henri Plantagenet, born in [[Le Mans]], who within months of their wedding became King [[Henry II of England]]. The city flourished, primarily due to the wine trade, and the [[Bordeaux Cathedral|cathedral of St. André]] was built. After granting a tax-free trade status with England, King Henry II was adored by the locals as they could be even more profitable in the wine trade, their main source of income. The city cathedral St. Cathédrale St-André was built in 1227, incorporating the artisan quarter of Saint-Paul. &lt;ref&gt;https://www.lonelyplanet.com/france/bordeaux/background/history/a/nar/5e51aa7a-15f6-47ad-8ad8-719613858dc0/359293&lt;/ref&gt;. It was also the capital of an independent state under [[Edward, the Black Prince]] (1362–1372), but after the [[Battle of Castillon]] (1453) it was annexed by France, and so extended its territory. 

In 1462 Bordeaux created a local parliament. However, it only regained its importance during the 16th century when it became a major trading centre for sugar and slaves from the [[Caribbean|West Indies]], along with its traditional wine exports.&lt;ref&gt;''[[The Washington Post|Washington Post]]'', &quot;Bordeaux struggles with slave past&quot;, 28 September 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Bordeaux adhered to the [[Fronde]], being effectively annexed to the [[Kingdom of France]] only in 1653, when the army of [[Louis XIV of France|Louis XIV]] entered the city.
[[File:Edouard Manet 026.jpg|thumb|[[Édouard Manet]]: ''Harbour at Bordeaux'', 1871]]
[[File:Bordeaux rue Sainte-Catherine avril 1905.jpg|thumb|right|Rue Sainte-Catherine in 1905]]

The 18th century saw another golden age of Bordeaux. Many downtown buildings (about 5,000), including those on the quays, are from this period. [[Victor Hugo]] found the town so beautiful he said: &quot;Take [[Versailles, Yvelines|Versailles]], add [[Antwerp]], and you have Bordeaux&quot;. [[Baron Haussmann]], a long-time prefect of Bordeaux, used Bordeaux's 18th-century large-scale rebuilding as a model when he was asked by Emperor [[Napoleon III of France|Napoleon III]] to transform a then still quasi-medieval [[Paris]] into a &quot;modern&quot; capital that would make France proud.

Towards the end of the [[Peninsula war]] on 12 March 1814, the [[Duke of Wellington]] sent [[William Beresford, 1st Viscount Beresford|William Beresford]] with two divisions and seized Bordeaux encountering little resistance. Bordeaux was largely anti-[[Bonapartism|Bonapartist]] and the majority supported the [[House of Bourbon|Bourbons]], so the British troops were treated as liberators.

In 1870, at the beginning of the [[Franco-Prussian war]] against [[Kingdom of Prussia|Prussia]], the French government temporarily relocated to Bordeaux from Paris. This recurred during the [[World War I|First World War]] and again very briefly during the [[World War II|Second World War]], when it became clear that Paris would fall into German hands. However, on the last of these occasions the French capital was soon moved again to [[Vichy]]. In May and June 1940, Bordeaux was the site of the life-saving actions of the Portuguese consul-general, [[Aristides de Sousa Mendes]], who illegally granted thousands of Portuguese visas, which were needed to pass the Spanish border, to refugees fleeing the German Occupation.

From 1940 to 1943, the [[Regia Marina|Italian Royal Navy]] (''[[Regia Marina]] Italiana'') established [[BETASOM]], a submarine base at Bordeaux. Italian submarines participated in the [[Battle of the Atlantic]] from this base, which was also a major base for German [[U-boat]]s as headquarters of [[12th U-boat Flotilla]]. The massive, reinforced concrete U-boat pens have proved impractical to demolish and are now partly used as a cultural center for exhibitions.

== Geography ==
Bordeaux is located close to the European [[Atlantic Ocean|Atlantic]] coast, in the southwest of France and in the north of the Aquitaine region. It is around {{convert|500|km|mi|abbr=on}} southwest of Paris. The city is built on a bend of the river Garonne, and is divided into two parts: the right bank to the east and left bank in the west. Historically the left bank is more developed because when flowing outside the bend, the water makes a furrow of the required depth to allow the passing of merchant ships, which used to offload on this side of the river. But, today, the right bank is developing, including new urban projects. In Bordeaux, the Garonne River is accessible to [[ocean liner]]s. The right bank of the Garonne is a low-lying, often marshy plain.

=== Climate ===
Bordeaux's climate is classified as a temperate [[oceanic climate]] ([[Köppen climate classification]] ''Cfb''), or in the [[Trewartha climate classification]] system as temperate oceanic or Do climate. Bordeaux lies close to the humid subtropical climate zone, its summers not quite warm enough for that classification.

Winters are cool because of the prevalence of westerly winds from the Atlantic. Summers are warm and long due to the influence from the Bay of Biscay (surface temperature reaches {{convert|21|to|22|°C|°F|0|abbr=on}}). The average seasonal winter temperature is {{convert|7.1|°C|°F|abbr=on}}, but recent winters have been warmer than this. Frosts in the winter occur several times during a winter, but snowfall is very rare, occurring only once every three years. The average summer seasonal temperature is {{convert|20.7|°C|°F|abbr=on}}. The [[2003 European heat wave|summer of 2003]] set a record with an average temperature of {{convert|23.3|°C|°F|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;GHCN climate, GISS world climate averages, 1971–2000&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Bordeaux weatherbox}}

== Economy ==
Bordeaux is a major centre for business in France as it has the sixth largest metropolitan population in France. It serves as a major regional center for trade, administration, services and industry.

{{As of|2014}}, the GDP of Bordeaux is €32.7 Billion.

=== Wine ===
{{Main|Bordeaux wine}}

The wine was introduced to the Bordeaux region by the Romans, probably in the mid-first century, to provide wine for local consumption, and wine production has been continuous in the region since.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Johnson |first=Hugh |title=World Atlas of Wine |edition=4th|year=1994 |place=London |publisher=Octopus Publishing Group Ltd |page=13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bordeaux wine growing area has about {{convert|116160|ha|acre}} of [[vineyard]]s, 57 [[appellations]], 10,000 wine-producing estates (châteaux) and 13,000 grape growers. With an annual production of approximately 960 million bottles,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.intowine.com/bordeaux.html|title=Bordeaux Wine Region in France: World's Most Famous Fine Wine Region|publisher=IntoWine.com|accessdate=23 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Bordeaux area produces large quantities of everyday wine as well as some of the most expensive wines in the world. Included among the latter are the area's five ''premier cru'' ([[First Growth|first growth]]) red wines (four from Médoc and one, Château Haut-Brion, from Graves), established by the [[Bordeaux Wine Official Classification of 1855]]:

Both red and [[Wine|white wines]] are made in the Bordeaux region. Red Bordeaux wine is called [[claret]] in the United Kingdom. Red wines are generally made from a blend of grapes, and may be made from [[Cabernet Sauvignon]], [[Merlot]], [[Cabernet Franc]], [[Petit verdot]], [[Malbec]], and, less commonly in recent years, [[Carménère]].

White Bordeaux is made from [[Sauvignon blanc]], [[Sémillon]], and [[Muscadelle]]. [[Graves (wine region)|Sauternes]] is a sub-region of Graves known for its intensely sweet, white, [[dessert wine]]s such as [[Château d'Yquem]].

Because of a wine glut ([[wine lake]]) in the generic production, the price squeeze induced by an increasingly strong international competition, and [[vine pull schemes]], the number of growers has recently dropped from 14,000 and the area under vine has also decreased significantly. In the meantime, the global demand for first growths and the most famous labels markedly increased and their prices skyrocketed.

The [[Cité du Vin]], a [[museum]] as well as a place of exhibitions, shows, movie projections and [[Academia|academic]] [[seminar]]s on the theme of [[wine]] opened its doors in June 2016.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|language=fr|url=http://www.sudouest.fr/2016/02/19/la-cite-du-vin-cernee-par-les-chantiers-2278033-2780.php|title=Bordeaux : la Cité du vin cernée par les chantiers|date=19 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Others ===
The [[Laser Mégajoule]] will be one of the most powerful lasers in the world, allowing [[Research|fundamental research]] and the development of the [[laser]] and [[plasma (physics)|plasma]] technologies. This project, carried by the [[Minister of Defence (France)|French Ministry of Defence]], involves an investment of 2&amp;nbsp;billion euros. The &quot;Road of the lasers&quot;, a major project of [[regional planning]], promotes regional investment in optical and laser related industries leading to the Bordeaux area having the most important concentration of optical and laser expertise in Europe.

Some 20,000 people work for the aeronautic industry in Bordeaux. The city has some of the biggest companies including [[Dassault Aviation|Dassault]], [[EADS Sogerma]], [[Snecma]], [[Thales Group|Thales]], SNPE, and others. The [[Dassault Aviation|Dassault Falcon]] private jets are built there as well as the [[military aircraft]] [[Dassault Rafale|Rafale]] and [[Dassault Mirage 2000|Mirage 2000]], the [[Airbus A380]] [[cockpit]], the [[Booster (rocketry)|boosters]] of [[Ariane 5]], and the [[M51 (missile)|M51 SLBM]] [[missile]].

Tourism, especially [[wine tourism]], is a major industry. Globelink.co.uk mentioned Bordeaux as the best tourist destination in Europe in 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.globelink.co.uk/articles/country-information/france/3-best-places-to-retire-in-france.html|title=3 Best Places to Retire in France|publisher=Globelink.co.uk|accessdate=2 August 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Access to the port from the Atlantic is via the [[Gironde estuary]]. Almost nine million tonnes of goods arrive and leave each year.

=== Major companies ===
This list includes indigenous Bordeaux-based companies and companies that have major presence in Bordeaux, but are not necessarily headquartered there.

*[[Arena (swimwear)|Arena]]
*[[Cdiscount]]
*
*[[Dassault Group|Dassault]]
*
*
*
*
*
*
*[[Marie Brizard et Roger International|Marie Brizard]]
*[[McKesson Corporation]]
*[[Oxbow (surfwear)|Oxbow]]
*[[Pernod Ricard|Ricard]]
*[[Sanofi-Aventis|Sanofi Aventis]]
*[[Smurfit Kappa]]
*[[Snecma|SNECMA]]
*
*[[Solectron]]
*[[Thales Group]]
*
{{Div col end}}

== Population ==
At the January 2011 census, there were 239,399 inhabitants in the city proper (commune) of Bordeaux. Bordeaux in its hey day had a population of 262,662 in 1968.&lt;ref name=&quot;commune_pop2&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.insee.fr/fr/themes/tableau.asp?reg_id=0&amp;ref_id=nattef01214|title=Taille des communes les plus peuplées en 2012 |publisher=INSEE |accessdate=10 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of the population is French, but there are sizable groups of [[Italian people|Italians]], [[Spanish people|Spaniards]] (Up to 20% of the Bordeaux population claim some degree of Spanish heritage), [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]], [[Turkish people|Turks]], [[Germans]]. https://www.citypopulation.de/php/france-gironde.php?cityid=33063.

The built-up area has grown for more than a century beyond the municipal borders of Bordeaux due to [[urban sprawl]], so that by the January 2011 census there were 1,140,668 people living in the overall [[Metropolitan Area (France)|metropolitan area]] of Bordeaux,&lt;ref name=&quot;AU10_pop&quot;/&gt; only a fifth of whom lived in the city proper.

{{Table Population Town}}

{{Chart Population Town}}

Largest communities of foreigners :

{|
|+
|{{flag|Portugal}}|| 10,709
|-
|{{flag|Morocco}}|| 7,215
|-
|{{flag|Algeria}}|| 4,770
|-
|{{flag|Spain}}|| 3,911
|-
|{{flag|Turkey}}|| 3,743
|-
|{{flag|UK}}|| 1,379
|-
|{{flag|Tunisia}}|| 1,366
|-
|{{flag|Senegal}}|| 1,126
|-
|{{flag|China}}|| 1,043
|-
|{{flag|Germany}}|| 922
|-
|{{flag|Belgium}}|| 902
|-
|{{flag|Italy}}|| 894
|-
|{{flag|Romania}}|| 885
|-
|{{flag|Republic of the Congo}}|| 841
|}

== Politics ==
At the 2007 presidential election, the Bordelais gave 31.37% of their votes to [[Ségolène Royal]] of the Socialist Party against 30.84% to [[Nicolas Sarkozy]], president of the UMP. Then came [[Francois Bayrou]] with 22.01%, followed by [[Jean-Marie Le Pen]] who recorded 5.42%. None of the other candidates exceeded the 5% mark. Nationally, Nicolas Sarkozy led with 31.18%, then Ségolène Royal with 25.87%, followed by François Bayrou with 18.57%. After these came Jean-Marie Le Pen with 10.44%, none of the other candidates exceeded the 5% mark. In the second round, the city of Bordeaux gave Ségolène Royal 52.44% against 47.56% for Nicolas Sarkozy, the latter being elected [[President of the Republic]] with 53.06% against 46.94% for Ségolène Royal. The abstention rates for Bordeaux were 14.52% in the first round and 15.90% in the second round. This is an earthquake in Bordeaux, a city deeply rooted right traditions{{Citation needed|date=February 2018}}.

In the parliamentary elections of 2007, the left won eight constituencies against only three for the right. It should be added that after the partial 2008 elections, the eighth district of Gironde switched to the left, bringing the count to nine. In Bordeaux, the left was for the first time in its history the majority as it held two of three constituencies following the elections. In the first division of the Gironde, the outgoing UMP MP [[Chantal Bourragué]] was well ahead with 44.81% against 25.39% for the Socialist candidate [[Beatrice Desaigues]]. In the second round, it was [[Chantal Bourragué]] who was re-elected with 54.45% against 45.55% for his socialist opponent. In the second district of Gironde the UMP mayor and all new Minister of Ecology, Energy, Sustainable Development and the Sea [[Alain Juppé]] confronted the General Counsel PS Michèle Delaunay. In the first round, Alain Juppé was well ahead with 43.73% against 31.36% for [[Michèle Delaunay]]. In the second round, it was finally Michèle Delaunay who won the election with 50.93% of the votes against 49.07% for Alain Juppé, the margin being only 670 votes. The defeat of the so-called constituency &quot;Mayor&quot; showed that Bordeaux was rocking increasingly left. Finally, in the third constituency of the Gironde, Noël Mamère was well ahead with 39.82% against 28.42% for the UMP candidate Elizabeth Vine. In the second round, Noël Mamère was re-elected with 62.82% against 37.18% for his right-wing rival.

In 2008 municipal elections saw the clash between mayor of Bordeaux, Alain Juppé and the President of the Regional Council of Aquitaine Socialist [[Alain Rousset]]. The PS had put up a Socialist heavyweight in the Gironde and had put great hopes in this election after the victory of Ségolène Royal and [[Michèle Delaunay]] in 2007. However, after a rather exciting campaign it was Alain Juppé who was widely elected in the first round with 56.62%, far ahead of Alain Rousset who has managed to get 34.14%. At present, of the eight cantons that has Bordeaux, five are held by the PS and three by the UMP, the left eating a little each time into the right's numbers.

In the European elections of 2009, Bordeaux voters largely voted for the UMP candidate Dominique Baudis, who won 31.54% against 15.00% for PS candidate Kader Arif. The candidate of Europe Ecology José Bové came second with 22.34%. None of the other candidates reached the 10% mark. The 2009 European elections were like the previous ones in eight constituencies. Bordeaux is located in the district &quot;Southwest&quot;, here are the results:

UMP candidate Dominique Baudis: 26.89%. His party gained four seats. PS candidate Kader Arif: 17.79%, gaining two seats in the European Parliament. Europe Ecology candidate Bove: 15.83%, obtaining two seats. MoDem candidate Robert Rochefort: 8.61%, winning a seat. Left Front candidate Jean-Luc Mélenchon: 8.16%, gaining the last seat. At regional elections in 2010, the Socialist incumbent president Alain Rousset won the first round by totaling 35.19% in Bordeaux, but this score was lower than the plan for Gironde and Aquitaine. Xavier Darcos, Minister of Labour followed with 28.40% of the votes, scoring above the regional and departmental average. Then came Monique De Marco, Green candidate with 13.40%, followed by the member of Pyrenees-Atlantiques and candidate of the MoDem Jean Lassalle who registered a low 6.78% while qualifying to the second round on the whole Aquitaine, closely followed by Jacques Colombier, candidate of the National Front, who gained 6.48%. Finally the candidate of the Left Front Gérard Boulanger with 5.64%, no other candidate above the 5% mark. In the second round, Alain Rousset had a tidal wave win as national totals rose to 55.83%. If Xavier Darcos largely lost the election, he nevertheless achieved a score above the regional and departmental average obtaining 33.40%. Jean Lassalle, who qualified for the second round, passed the 10% mark by totaling 10.77%. The ballot was marked by abstention amounting to 55.51% in the first round and 53.59% in the second round.

&lt;small&gt;''Only candidates obtaining more than 5% are listed''&lt;/small&gt;
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;
|+ 2007 Presidential Election&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.interieur.gouv.fr/Elections/Les-resultats/Presidentielles/elecresult__presidentielle_2007/%28path%29/presidentielle_2007/072/033/33063.html Résultat de l'élection présidentielle de 2007 à Bordeaux] sur le site du ministère de l'intérieur.&lt;/ref&gt;
!rowspan=2|Candidate !!colspan=2|Ist round !!colspan=2|IInd round
|-
!Bordeaux !! National
!Bordeaux !! National
|-
|align=left|'''[[Nicolas Sarkozy]]'''||30.84%||'''31.18%'''||47.56%||'''53.06%'''
|-
|align=left|[[Ségolène Royal]]||'''31.37%'''||25.87%||'''52.44%'''||46.94%
|-
|align=left|[[François Bayrou]]||22.01%||18.57%||||
|-
|align=left|[[Jean-Marie Le Pen]]||5.42%||10.44%||||
|-
|align=left|Total votes||85.48%||83.77%||84.10%||83.97%
|}

{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;
|+ 2012 Presidential Election&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.interieur.gouv.fr/Elections/Les-resultats/Presidentielles/elecresult__PR2012/%28path%29/PR2012/072/033/033063.html Résultat de l'élection présidentielle de 2012 à Bordeaux] sur le site du ministère de l'intérieur.&lt;/ref&gt;
!rowspan=2|Candidate !!colspan=2|Ist round !!colspan=2|IInd round
|-
!Bordeaux !! National
!Bordeaux !! National
|-
|align=left|'''[[François Hollande]]'''||'''33.05%'''||'''28.63%'''||'''57.18%'''||'''51.64%'''
|-
|align=left|[[Nicolas Sarkozy]]||28.68%||27.18%||42.82%||48.36%
|-
|align=left|[[Jean-Luc Mélenchon]]||12.16%||11.10%||||
|-
|align=left|[[François Bayrou]]||10.91%||9.13%||||
|-
|align=left|[[Marine Le Pen]]||8.22%||17.90%||||
|-
|align=left|Total votes||79.25%||79.48%||80.44%||80.35%
|}

=== Municipal administration ===
The Mayor of the city is Nicolas Florian.

[[Virginie Calmels]] is Deputy Mayor of Bordeaux in charge of the Economy, Employment and Sustainable Growth and Vice-President of the Urban Community of Bordeaux.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.informazione.it/c/22FF78F3-5D9D-45BF-A731-AD6F19FC51C0/ASSYSTEM-Virginie-Calmels-joins-the-Assystem-Board-of-Directors|title=ASSYSTEM : Virginie Calmels joins the Assystem Board of Directors|work=Informazione - Comunicati Stampa|access-date=2017-09-19|language=it-IT}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bordeaux is the capital of five cantons and the Prefecture of the [[Gironde]] and [[Aquitaine]].

The town is divided into three districts, the first three of Gironde. The headquarters of Urban Community of Bordeaux Mériadeck is located in the neighbourhood and the city is at the head of the Chamber of Commerce and Industry that bears his name.

The number of inhabitants of Bordeaux is greater than 199,999 and less than 250,000 and so the number of municipal councilors is 61. They are divided according to the following composition:
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Party !! President !! Seats !! Status
|-
| [[Les Republicains|LR]] – [[Nouveau Centre]] – [[Mouvement démocrate (France)|Modem]]  ||Hugues Martin ||50 ||majority
|-
| [[Parti socialiste (France)|PS]] – [[Verts (France)|Verts]] – [[Parti communiste français|PCF]] ||Matthieu Rouveyre ||11 ||opposition
|}

=== Mayors of Bordeaux ===
Since 1947, there have been 5 mayors of Bordeaux:

{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;
|align=left|1947–1995||[[Jacques Chaban-Delmas]]||RPR
|-
|align=left|1995–2004||[[Alain Juppé]]||RPR/UMP
|-
|align=left|2004–2006||Hugues Martin||UMP
|-
|align=left|2006–2019||Alain Juppé||UMP/LR
|-
|align=left|2019–present||Nicolas Florian||LR
|}

*RPR was renamed to UMP in 2002 which was later renamed to Les Republicains in 2015

== Education ==
=== University ===
{{Main|University of Bordeaux}}
The university was created by the archbishop [[Pey Berland]] in 1441 and was abolished in 1793, during the [[French Revolution]], before reappearing in 1808 with [[Napoleon I of France|Napoleon I]]. Bordeaux accommodates approximately 70,000 students on one of the largest campuses of Europe (235&amp;nbsp;ha).&lt;ref&gt;{{in lang|fr}} Université de Bordeaux website: [http://www.univ-bordeaux.fr/ www.univ-bordeaux.fr]; retrieved 7 December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
The University of Bordeaux is divided into four:

*The University Bordeaux 1, (Maths, Physical sciences and Technologies), 10,693 students in 2002
*The University Bordeaux 2, Bordeaux Segalen (Medicine and Life sciences), 15,038 students in 2002
*The University Bordeaux 3, Michel de Montaigne ([[Liberal arts|Liberal Arts]], Humanities, Languages, History), 14,785 students in 2002
*The University Bordeaux 4, Montesquieu (Law, Economy and Management), 12,556 students in 2002
*[[Institut d'études politiques de Bordeaux|Institut of Political Sciences of Bordeaux]]. Although technically a part of the fourth university, it largely functions autonomously.

=== Schools ===&lt;!-- [[BEM]] links here (for Bordeaux école de management) --&gt;
Bordeaux has numerous public and private schools offering undergraduate and postgraduate programs.

Engineering schools:
*[[Arts et Métiers ParisTech]], graduate school of industrial and mechanical engineering
*[[ESME-Sudria]], graduate school of engineering
*École d'ingénieurs en modélisation mathématique et mécanique
*École nationale supérieure d'électronique, informatique, télécommunications, mathématique et mécanique de Bordeaux (ENSEIRB-MATMECA)
*École supérieure de technologie des biomolécules de Bordeaux
*École nationale d'ingénieurs des travaux agricoles de Bordeaux
*[[École nationale supérieure de chimie et de physique de Bordeaux|École nationale supérieure de chimie et physique de Bordeaux]]
*[[École pour l'informatique et les nouvelles technologies]]
*Institut des sciences et techniques des aliments de Bordeaux
*[[Institut de cognitique]]
*École supérieure d'informatique
*[[EPSI|École privée des sciences informatiques]]

Business and management schools:
*The Bordeaux MBA (International College of Bordeaux)
*IUT Techniques de Commercialisation of Bordeaux (business school)
*[[INSEEC]] Business School ([[Institut des hautes études économiques et commerciales]])
*[[KEDGE Business School]] (former BEM – Bordeaux Management School)
*Vatel Bordeaux International Business School
*[[E-Artsup]]
*[[Institut supérieur européen de gestion group]]
*[[Institut supérieur européen de formation par l'action]]

Other:
*[[French National School for the Judiciary|École nationale de la magistrature]] (National school for the judiciary)
*{{lang|fr|École d'architecture et de paysage de Bordeaux}}
*{{lang|fr|École des beaux-arts de Bordeaux}}
*{{lang|fr|École française des attachés de presse et des professionnels de la communication}} (EFAP)
*{{lang|fr|Conservatoire national des arts et métiers d'Aquitaine}} (CNAM)
*{{lang|fr|École des Avocats ALIENOR de Bordeaux}} (law school)

=== Weekend education ===
The ''École Compleméntaire Japonaise de Bordeaux'' (ボルドー日本語補習授業校 ''Borudō Nihongo Hoshū Jugyō Kō''), a [[Hoshuko|part-time Japanese supplementary school]], is held in the ''Salle de L'Athenee Municipal'' in Bordeaux.&lt;ref name=MEXTEuropeHoshuko&gt;&quot;[https://web.archive.org/web/20140330190146/http://www.mext.go.jp/a_menu/shotou/clarinet/002/006/001/002/004.htm 欧州の補習授業校一覧（平成25年4月15日現在）]&quot; ([https://web.archive.org/web/20140330190146/http://www.mext.go.jp/a_menu/shotou/clarinet/002/006/001/002/004.htm Archive]). [[Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology]] (MEXT). Retrieved on 10 May 2014. &quot;Salle de L'Athenee Municipal Place St. Christoly, 33000 Bordeaux, FRANCE&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

== Main sights ==
[[File:Bordeaux - Juillet 2012 (71).JPG|thumb|Porte Cailhau]]
[[File:Bordeaux foire quinconces.jpg|thumb|Column of the Girondins on the Esplanade des Quinconces]]
[[File:Bordeaux Saint Pierre.jpg|thumb|The church of St Pierre]]
[[File:FacadeSainteCroixBordeauxsoir.jpg|thumb|Façade of the Church of the Holy Cross]]
[[File:Bordeaux place de la bourse with tram.JPG|thumb|Place de la Bourse at night with the [[Miroir d'eau]] and tram]]
[[File:Rue Sainte-Catherine (Bordeaux) 2005.JPG|thumb|[[Sainte-Catherine Street (Bordeaux)|Rue Sainte-Catherine]]]]

Bordeaux is classified &quot;City of Art and History&quot;. The city is home to 362 ''[[monuments historiques]]'' (only Paris has more in France) with some buildings dating back to Roman times. Bordeaux has been inscribed on [[World Heritage Site|UNESCO World Heritage List]] as ''&quot;an outstanding urban and architectural ensemble&quot;''.

Bordeaux is home to one of Europe's biggest 18th-century architectural urban areas, making it a sought-after destination for tourists and cinema production crews. It stands out as one of the first French cities, after [[Nancy, France|Nancy]], to have entered an era of [[urbanism]] and metropolitan big scale projects, with the team Gabriel father and son, architects for King [[Louis XV of France|Louis XV]], under the supervision of two intendants (Governors), first [[Nicolas-François Dupré de Saint-Maur]] then the Marquis de Tourny.

=== Buildings ===
Main sights include:
* ''[[Place des Quinconces]]'', the largest square in France.
* ''Monument aux Girondins''
* ''[[Grand Théâtre de Bordeaux|Grand Théâtre]]'', a large neoclassical theater built in the 18th century.
* ''Allées de Tourny''
* ''Cours de l'Intendance''
* ''Place du Chapelet''
* ''[[Place de la Bourse]]''(1730–1775), designed by the Royal architect [[Ange-Jacques Gabriel|Jacques Ange Gabriel]] as landscape for an [[equestrian statue]] of Louis XV.
* ''Place du Parlement''
* ''Place Saint-Pierre''
*''[[Pont de pierre (Bordeaux)|Pont de pierre]]''
* ''Saint-André Cathedral'', consecrated by [[Pope Urban II]] in 1096. Of the original Romanesque edifice only a wall in the nave remains. The Royal Gate is from the early 13th century, while the rest of the construction is mostly from the 14th and 15th centuries.
* ''[[Tour Pey-Berland]]'' (1440–1450), a massive, quadrangular Gothic tower annexed to the cathedral.
* ''[[Église Sainte-Croix]]'' (Church of the Holy Cross). It lies on the site of a 7th-century abbey destroyed by the Saracens. Rebuilt under the Carolingians, it was again destroyed by the Normans in 845 and 864. It is annexed to a Benedictine abbey founded in the 7th century, and was built in the late 11th and early 12th centuries. The façade is in [[Romanesque architecture|Romanesque style]]
* The Gothic ''[[Basilica of St. Michael, Bordeaux|Basilica of Saint Michael]]'', constructed between the end of the 14th century and the 16th century.
* Basilica of ''Saint-Seurin'', the most ancient church in Bordeaux. It was built in the early 6th century on the site of a palaeochristian necropolis. It has an 11th-century [[portico]], while the [[apse]] and [[transept]] are from the following century. The 13th-century nave has chapels from the 11th and the 14th centuries. The ancient crypt houses sepulchres of the Merovingian family.
* ''Église Saint-Pierre'', gothic church
* ''Église Saint-Éloi'', gothic church
* ''Église Saint-Bruno'', baroque church decorated with frescoes
* ''Église Notre-Dame'', baroque church
* ''Église Saint-Paul-Saint-François-Xavier'', baroque church
* ''Palais Rohan'' (Exterior:&lt;ref&gt;{{in lang|de}} http://www.artemisia.no/arc/historisk/bordeaux/1700/bilder/hotel.de.ville.ii.jpg&lt;/ref&gt;)
* ''Palais Gallien'', the remains of a late 2nd-century [[Ancient Rome|Roman]] [[amphitheatre]]
* ''Porte Cailhau'', a medieval gate of the old city walls.
* ''La Grosse Cloche'' (15th century), the second remaining gate of the Medieval walls. It was the belfry of the old Town Hall. It consists of two {{convert|40|m|ft|0|adj=mid|abbr=off|-high}} circular towers and a central [[bell tower]] housing a [[bell (instrument)|bell]] weighing {{convert|7800|kg}}. The watch is from 1759.
* ''[[Sainte-Catherine Street (Bordeaux)|Rue Sainte-Catherine]]'', the longest pedestrian street of France
* The [[BETASOM]] submarine base

Saint-André Cathedral, Saint-Michel Basilica and Saint-Seurin Basilica are part of the [[World Heritage Sites of the Routes of Santiago de Compostela in France]].

=== Contemporary architecture ===
*Fire Station, ''la Benauge'', Claude Ferret/Adrien Courtois/Yves Salier, 1951–1954
*[[Tribunal d'instance|Court of first instance]], [[Richard Rogers]], 1998
*CTBA, wood and furniture research center, A. Loisier, 1998
*Hangar 14 on the ''Quai des Chartrons'', 1999
*The Management Science faculty on the Bastide, Anne Lacaton/Jean-Philippe Vassal, 2006
*The ''[[Jardin botanique de la Bastide]]'', Catherine Mosbach/Françoise Hélène Jourda/[[Pascal Convert]], 2007
*The Nuyens School complex on the Bastide, Yves Ballot/Nathalie Franck, 2007
*Seeko'o Hotel on the Quai des Chartrons, King Kong architects, 2007

=== Museums ===
*[[Musée des beaux-arts de Bordeaux|Musée des Beaux Arts]] (''Fine arts museum''), one of the finest painting galleries in France with paintings by painter such as [[Tiziano]], [[Paolo Veronese|Veronese]], [[Rubens]], [[Van Dyck]], [[Frans Hals]], [[Claude Lorrain|Claude]], [[Jean-Baptiste-Siméon Chardin|Chardin]], [[Eugène Delacroix|Delacroix]], [[Renoir]], [[Seurat]], [[Matisse]] and [[Picasso]].
*[[Musée d'Aquitaine]] (archeological and history museum)
*Musée du Vin et du Négoce (museum of the wine trade)
*Musée des Arts Décoratifs (museum of decorative arts)
*Musée d'Histoire Naturelle (natural history museum)
*[[CAPC musée d'art contemporain de Bordeaux]] (contemporary art museum)
*[[Musée national des douanes]]
*Vinorama
*Musée Goupil
*Casa de [[Francisco Goya|Goya]]
*[[:fr:Cap Sciences|Cap Sciences]]
*Centre Jean Moulin

=== Parks and gardens ===
*''[[Jardin botanique de Bordeaux]]''
*''[[Jardin botanique de la Bastide]]''
*''La Maison des Chameaux (Camel Park)''
&quot;Le Jardin Public&quot; is a park in the heart of the city.

=== Pont Jacques Chaban-Delmas ===
Europe's longest-span [[vertical-lift bridge]], the [[Pont Jacques Chaban-Delmas]], was opened in 2013 in Bordeaux, spanning the River Garonne. The central lift span is {{convert|117|m|ft|0|adj=mid|abbr=off|-long}} and can be lifted vertically up to {{convert|53|m|ft|0|abbr=off}} to let tall ships pass underneath. The €160 million bridge was inaugurated by President [[François Hollande]] and Mayor Alain Juppé on 16 March 2013. The bridge was named after the late [[Jacques Chaban-Delmas]], who was a former Prime Minister and [[Mayor (France)|Mayor]] of Bordeaux.

=== Shopping ===
Bordeaux has many shopping options. In the heart of Bordeaux is ''[[Sainte-Catherine Street (Bordeaux)|Rue Sainte-Catherine]]''. This pedestrian-only shopping street has {{convert|1.2|km|mi|sp=us}} of shops, restaurants and cafés; it is also one of the longest shopping streets in Europe. ''Rue Sainte-Catherine'' starts at ''Place de la Victoire'' and ends at ''Place de la Comédie'' by the ''Grand Théâtre''. The shops become progressively more upmarket as one moves towards ''Place de la Comédie'' and the nearby ''Cours de l'Intendance'' is where one finds the more exclusive shops and boutiques.

== Culture ==
[[File:GrandTheatreBordeaux2.jpg|thumb|Maison de l’Économie Créative et de la Culture en Aquitaine]]
[[File:RB 20200222 Bordeaux-11.jpg|thumb|Maison de l’Économie Créative et de la Culture en Aquitaine]]
Bordeaux is also the first city in France to have created, in the 1980s, an architecture exhibition and research centre, ''[[Arc en rêve]]''.{{citation needed |date=January 2018}} Bordeaux offers a large number of cinemas, theatres, and is the home of the [[Grand Théâtre de Bordeaux|Opéra national de Bordeaux]]. There are many music venues of varying capacity. The city also offers several festivals throughout the year.

== Transport ==
=== Road ===
Bordeaux is an important road and [[Interchange (road)|motorway junction]]. The city is connected to Paris by the [[A10 autoroute (France)|A10]] motorway, with Lyon by the [[A89 autoroute|A89]], with Toulouse by the [[A62 autoroute|A62]], and with Spain by the [[A63 autoroute|A63]]. There is a {{convert|45|km|mi|abbr=on}} [[Beltway|ring road]] called the &quot;Rocade&quot; which is often very busy. Another ring road is under consideration.

Bordeaux has five road bridges that cross the [[Garonne]], the Pont de pierre built in the 1820s and three modern bridges built after 1960: the Pont Saint Jean, just south of the Pont de pierre (both located downtown), the [[Pont d'Aquitaine]], a suspended bridge downstream from downtown, and the Pont François Mitterrand, located upstream of downtown. These two bridges are part of the ring road around Bordeaux. A fifth bridge, the [[Pont Jacques-Chaban-Delmas]], was constructed in 2009–2012 and opened to traffic in March 2013. Located halfway between the Pont de pierre and the Pont d'Aquitaine and serving downtown rather than highway traffic, it is a [[vertical-lift bridge]] with a height comparable to the Pont de pierre in closed position, and to the Pont d'Aquitaine in open position. All five road bridges, including the two highway bridges, are open to cyclists and pedestrians as well.
Another bridge, the Pont Jean-Jacques Bosc, is to be built in 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lacub.fr/grands-projets/pont-jean-jacques-bosc |title=Pont Jean-Jacques Bosc – La CUB |date=24 October 2013 |work=archive.org |url-status=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131024224845/http://www.lacub.fr/grands-projets/pont-jean-jacques-bosc |archivedate=24 October 2013 |df=dmy}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lacking any steep hills, Bordeaux is relatively friendly to cyclists. Cycle paths (separate from the roadways) exist on the highway bridges, along the riverfront, on the university campuses, and incidentally elsewhere in the city. [[Bike lane|Cycle lanes]] and [[bus lane]]s that explicitly allow cyclists exist on many of the city's boulevards. A paid [[bicycle-sharing system]] with automated stations has been established in 2010.

=== Rail ===
The main railway station, [[Gare de Bordeaux Saint-Jean]], near the center of the city, has 12&amp;nbsp;million passengers a year. It is served by the French national ([[SNCF]]) railway's high speed train, the [[TGV]], that gets to Paris in two hours, with connections to major European centers such as [[Lille]], Brussels, [[Amsterdam]], [[Cologne]], Geneva and London. The TGV also serves [[Toulouse]] and [[Irun]] (Spain) from Bordeaux. A regular train service is provided to [[Nantes]], Nice, [[Marseille]] and [[Lyon]]. The Gare Saint-Jean is the major hub for regional trains ([[Transport express régional|TER]]) operated by the SNCF to [[Arcachon]], [[Limoges]], [[Agen]], [[Périgueux]], [[Langon, Gironde|Langon]], [[Pau, Pyrénées-Atlantiques|Pau]], Le Médoc, Angoulême and [[Bayonne]].

Historically the train line used to terminate at a station on the right bank of the river Garonne near the Pont de Pierre, and passengers crossed the bridge to get into the city. Subsequently, a double-track steel railway bridge was constructed in the 1850s, by [[Gustave Eiffel]], to bring trains across the river direct into Gare de Bordeaux Saint-Jean. The old station was later converted and in 2010 comprised a cinema and restaurants.

The two-track Eiffel bridge with a speed limit of {{convert|30|km/h|0|abbr=on}} became a bottleneck and a new bridge was built, opening in 2009. The new bridge has four tracks and allows trains to pass at {{convert|60|km/h|0|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;[http://aquitaine.fr/politiques-regionales/transports/pont-ferroviaire-de-bordeaux.html Pont Ferroviaire de Bordeaux] on aquitaine.fr&lt;/ref&gt; During the planning there was much lobbying by the Eiffel family and other supporters to preserve the old bridge as a footbridge across the Garonne, with possibly a museum to document the history of the bridge and Gustave Eiffel's contribution. The decision was taken to save the bridge, but by early 2010 no plans had been announced as to its future use. The bridge remains intact, but unused and without any means of access.

Since July 2017, the [[LGV Sud Europe Atlantique]] is fully operational and makes Bordeaux city 2h04 from Paris.

=== Air ===
Bordeaux is served by [[Bordeaux–Mérignac Airport]], located {{convert|8|km|mi|abbr=on}} from the city centre in the suburban city of [[Mérignac, Gironde|Mérignac]].

[[File:Aéroport Bx Mérignac.JPG|thumb|[[Bordeaux–Mérignac Airport]]]]

=== Trams, buses and boats ===
[[File:Bordeaux-lawn-track-&amp;-vines1.jpg|thumb|Tramway in Bordeaux]]
Bordeaux has an important public transport system called [[Transports Bordeaux Métropole]] (TBM). This company is run by the Keolis group. The network consists of:
* 4 [[Tramway de Bordeaux|tram lines]] ([[Bordeaux Tramway Line A|A]], [[Bordeaux Tramway Line B|B]], [[Bordeaux Tramway Line C|C]] and [[Bordeaux Tramway Line D|D]])
* 75 [[Bus lines in Bordeaux|bus routes]], all connected to the tramway network (from 1 to 96)
* 13 night bus routes (from 1 to 16)
* An [[Trolleybus|electric bus]] shuttle in the city centre
* A boat shuttle on the Garonne river
This network is operated from 5&amp;nbsp;am to 2&amp;nbsp;am.

There had been several plans for a subway network to be set up, but they stalled for both geological and financial reasons. Work on the [[Tramway de Bordeaux]] system was started in the autumn of 2000, and services started in December 2003 connecting Bordeaux with its suburban areas. The tram system uses ground-level power supply technology [[Ground-level power supply|(APS)]], a new cable-free technology developed by French company [[Alstom]] and designed to preserve the aesthetic environment by eliminating overhead cables in the historic city. Conventional overhead cables are used outside the city. The system was controversial for its considerable cost of installation, maintenance and also for the numerous initial technical problems that paralysed the network. Many streets and squares along the tramway route became pedestrian areas, with [[Limited-access road|limited access]] for cars.

The planned Bordeaux tramway system is to link with the airport to the city centre towards the end of 2019.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.francebleu.fr/infos/transports/bordeaux-voici-le-trace-du-tramway-qui-va-desservir-l-aeroport-1461940859|title=Bordeaux : voici le tracé du tramway qui va desservir l'aéroport|date=29 April 2016|website=France Bleu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Taxis ===
There are more than 400 [[taxicab]]s in Bordeaux.

===Public transportation statistics===
The average amount of time people spend commuting with public transit in Bordeaux, for example to and from work, on a weekday is 51 min. 12.% of public transit riders, ride for more than 2 hours every day. The average amount of time people wait at a stop or station for public transit is 13 min, while 15.5% of riders wait for over 20 minutes on average every day. The average distance people usually ride in a single trip with public transit is {{convert|7|km|abbr=on}}, while 8% travel for over {{convert|12|km|abbr=on}} in a single direction.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.moovitapp.com/insights/en/Moovit_Insights_Public_Transit_Index_France_Bordeaux-924|title=Bordeaux Public Transportation Statistics|publisher=Global Public Transit Index by Moovit|accessdate=June 19, 2017}} [[File:CC-BY_icon.svg|50x50px]] Material was copied from this source, which is available under a [[creativecommons:by/4.0/|Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License]].&lt;/ref&gt;

== Sport ==
[[File:Bordeaux Stade Lescure entrée.JPG|thumb|Entrance to the Stade Chaban-Delmas]]{{Unreferenced section|date=March 2018}}

The 41,458-capacity [[Nouveau Stade de Bordeaux]] is the largest stadium in Bordeaux. The stadium was opened in 2015 and replaced the [[Stade Chaban-Delmas]], which was a venue for the [[FIFA World Cup]] in 1938 and 1998, as well as the [[2007 Rugby World Cup]]. In the [[1938 FIFA World Cup]], it hosted a violent quarter-final known as the [[Battle of Bordeaux (football)|Battle of Bordeaux]]. The ground was formerly known as the ''Stade du Parc Lescure'' until 2001, when it was renamed in honour of the city's long-time mayor, [[Jacques Chaban-Delmas]].

There are two major sport teams in Bordeaux, [[FC Girondins de Bordeaux|Girondins de Bordeaux]] is the [[association football|football]] team, playing in [[Ligue 1]] in the [[Football in France|French football]] championship. [[Union Bordeaux Bègles]] is a [[rugby union|rugby]] team in the [[Top 14]] in the [[National Rugby League (France)|Ligue Nationale de Rugby]].
Skateboarding, rollerblading, and BMX biking are activities enjoyed by many young inhabitants of the city. Bordeaux is home to a beautiful quay which runs along the Garonne river. On the quay there is a skate-park divided into three sections. One section is for Vert tricks, one for street style tricks, and one for little action sports athletes with easier features and softer materials. The skate-park is very well maintained by the municipality.

Bordeaux is also the home to one of the strongest [[cricket]] teams in France and are champions of the South West League.

There is a {{convert|250|m|ft|abbr=on}} wooden [[velodrome]], Vélodrome du Lac, in Bordeaux which hosts international cycling competition in the form of [[UCI Track Cycling World Cup Classics|UCI Track Cycling World Cup]] events.

The 2015 Trophee Eric Bompard was in Bordeaux. But the Free Skate was cancelled in all of the divisions due to the Paris bombing(s) and aftermath. The Short Program occurred hours before the bombing. French skaters Chafik Besseghier (68.36) in 10th place, Romain Ponsart (62.86) in 11th. Mae-Berenice-Meite (46.82) in 11th and Laurine Lecavelier (46.53) in 12th. Vanessa James/Morgan Cipres (65.75) in 2nd.

Between 1951 and 1955, an annual Formula 1 motor race was held on a 2.5-kilometre circuit which looped around the Esplanade des Quinconces and along the waterfront, attracting drivers such as [[Juan Manuel Fangio]], [[Stirling Moss]], [[Jean Behra]] and [[Maurice Trintignant]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Pike |first1=Tim |title=When Bordeaux city centre became a Formula 1 racing track |url=http://invisiblebordeaux.blogspot.com/2014/07/when-bordeaux-city-centre-became.html |website=invisiblebordeaux.blogspot.com |accessdate=6 September 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Notable people ==
[[File:Michel-eyquem-de-montaigne 1.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Michel de Montaigne]]]]
{{Div col|colwidth=35em}}
* [[Jean Alaux]] (1786–1864), painter
*[[Bertrand Andrieu]] (1761–1822), engraver
*[[Jean Anouilh]] (1910–1987), dramatist
*[[Yvonne Arnaud]] (1892–1958), pianist, singer and actress
*[[Ausonius|Decimus Magnus Ausonius]] (c. 310–395), Roman poet and rhetorician
*[[Floyd Ayité]], (born 1988), Togolese footballer
*[[Jonathan Ayité]], (born 1985), Togolese footballer
*[[Christine Barbe]], winemaker
*[[Gérard Bayo]] (born 1936), writer and poet,
*[[François Bigot]] (1703–1778), last &quot;Intendant&quot; of New France
*[[Grégory Bourdy]], (born 1982), golfer
*[[Samuel Boutal]], (born 1969), footballer
*[[Edmond de Caillou]] (died c. February 1316) Gascon knight fighting in Scotland
*[[Gérald Caussé]], Presiding Bishop of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints
*[[René Clément]] (1913–1996), actor, director, writer
*[[Jean-René Cruchet]] (1875–1959), pathologist
*[[Marie-Louise Damien|Damia]] (1899–1978), singer and actress
*[[Étienne Noël Damilaville]] (1723–1768), [[Encyclopédistes|encyclopédiste]]
*[[Lili Damita]] (1901–1994), actress
*[[Frédéric Daquin]], (born 1978), footballer
*[[Danielle Darrieux]] (born 1917), actress
*[[Bernard Delvaille]] (1931–2006), poet, essayist
*[[David Diop]], (1927–1960), poet
*[[Jean-Francois Domergue]], footballer
*[[Jacques Ellul]] (1912–1994), sociologist, theologian, Christian anarchist
*[[Marie Fel]] (1713–1794), opera singer
*[[Jean-Luc Fournet]] (1965), papyrologist
* [[Pierre-Jean Garat]] (1762–1823), singer
*[[Armand Gensonné]] (1758–1793), politician
*[[Stephen Girard]] (1750–1831), merchant, banker, and [[Philadelphia]] philanthropist
*[[Jérôme Gnako]], (born 1968), footballer
*[[Eugène Goossens, fils|Eugène Goossens]] (1867–1958), conductor, violinist
*[[Anna Hamilton]] (1864-1935), doctor, superintendent of the Protestant Hospital at Bordeaux (1901-1934)
*[[Léopold Lafleurance]] (1865–1953), flautist
*[[Joseph Henri Joachim Lainé]] (1767–1835), statesman
*[[Lucenzo]] (born 1983), singer
*[[Jean-Jacques Magendie]] (1766–1835), officer
*[[François Magendie]] (1783–1855), physiologist
*[[Bruno Marie-Rose]], (born 1965), athlete (sprinter)
*[[François Mauriac]] (1885–1970), writer, Nobel laureate 1952
*[[Édouard Molinaro]] (1928–2013), film director, screenwriter
*[[Michel de Montaigne]] (1533–1592), essayist
*[[Olivier Mony]] (1966–), writer and literary critic
*[[Étienne Marie Antoine Champion de Nansouty]] (1768–1815), general
*[[Pierre Palmade]] (born 1968), actor and comedian
*[[Paulinus of Nola|St. Paulinus of Nola]] (354–431), educator, religious figure
* [[Émile Péreire]] (1800–1875), banker and industrialist
*[[Albert Pitres]] (1848–1928), neurologist
*[[Georges Rayet|Georges Antoine Pons Rayet]] (1839–1906), astronomer, discoverer of the Wolf-Rayet stars, &amp; founder of the Bordeaux Observatory
*[[Odilon Redon]], (1840–1916), painter
*[[Richard II of England]] (1367–1400), king
*[[Pierre Rode]] (1774–1830), violinist
*[[Olinde Rodrigues]] (1795–1851), mathematician, banker and social reformer
*[[Marie-Sabine Roger]] (born 1957), writer
*[[Bernard Sarrette]] (1765–1858), conductor and music pedagogue
*[[Jean-Jacques Sempé]] (born 1932), cartoonist
*[[Florent Serra]], (born 1981), tennis player
*[[Philippe Sollers]], (born 1936), writer
*[[Wilfried Tekovi]], (born 1989), Togolese footballer
*[[Kap Bambino]], group
*[[Arnaud Binard]], (born 1971), actor and producer
*[[Elie Okobo]], basketball player

{{div col end}}

== International relationship ==
{{See also|List of twin towns and sister cities in France}}
[[File:Alain Juppé, Parc Bordeaux Ashdod, Israel.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Alain Juppé]], [[Mayor (France)|Mayor]] of Bordeaux, visiting the twin town of [[Ashdod]]]]

===Twin towns - sister cities===
Bordeaux is [[Twin towns and sister cities|twinned]] with:&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bordeaux.fr/p63778/europe%C2%A0et%C2%A0international|title=Bordeaux – Rayonnement européen et mondial|accessdate=29 July 2013|work=Mairie de Bordeaux|language=French|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130207154903/http://www.bordeaux.fr/p63778/europe%C2%A0et%C2%A0international|archivedate =7 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings 2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cncd.fr/frontoffice/bdd-recherche-resultat.asp?searchField=bordeaux&amp;x=36&amp;y=14|title=Bordeaux-Atlas français de la coopération décentralisée et des autres actions extérieures |accessdate=29 July 2013|work=Délégation pour l'Action Extérieure des Collectivités Territoriales (Ministère des Affaires étrangères)|language=French|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130207152951/http://www.cncd.fr/frontoffice/bdd-recherche-resultat.asp?searchField=bordeaux&amp;x=36&amp;y=14|archivedate=7 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings 3&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cncd.fr/frontoffice/bdd-region.asp?action=getRegion&amp;id=2#tabs3 |archive-url=https://archive.today/20131008010503/http://www.cncd.fr/frontoffice/bdd-region.asp?action=getRegion&amp;id=2 |url-status=dead |archive-date=8 October 2013 |title=National Commission for Decentralised cooperation |accessdate=26 December 2013 |work=Délégation pour l'Action Extérieure des Collectivités Territoriales (Ministère des Affaires étrangères) |language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Div col|colwidth=35em}}
*{{flagicon|ISR}} [[Ashdod]], Israel, since 1984&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;
*{{flagicon|ESP}} [[Bilbao]], Spain&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;
*{{flagicon|AZE}} [[Baku]], Azerbaijan, since 1985&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Azerbaijan twinnings&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.azerbaijans.com/content_1719_en.html|title=Twin-cities of Azerbaijan|accessdate=9 August 2013|work=Azerbaijans.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{flagicon|UK}} [[Bristol]], United Kingdom, since 1947&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bristol&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bristol.gov.uk/ccm/navigation/leisure-and-culture/tourism-and-travel/town-twinning/ |title=Bristol City – Town twinning |publisher= Bristol City Council |date=17 July 2009 |accessdate=15 March 2013 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110728075325/http://www.bristol.gov.uk/ccm/navigation/leisure-and-culture/tourism-and-travel/town-twinning/ |archivedate=28 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Archant twinning&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.completefrance.com/language-culture/twin-towns |title=British towns twinned with French towns |accessdate=11 July 2013 |work=Archant Community Media Ltd |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130705094933/http://www.completefrance.com/language-culture/twin-towns |archivedate=5 July 2013 |df=dmy}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{flagicon|MAR}} [[Casablanca]], Morocco, since 1988&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;
*{{flagicon|JPN}} [[Fukuoka]], Japan, since 1982&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;
*{{flagicon|PER}} [[Lima]], Peru, since 1957&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;
*{{flagicon|USA}} [[Los Angeles]], [[California]] United States, since 1968&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Los Angeles sisters&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sistercities.lacity.org/ |title=Sister Cities of Los Angeles|publisher=sistercities.lacity.org|accessdate=29 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{flagicon|ESP}} [[Madrid]], Spain, since 1984&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;
*{{flagicon|GER}} [[Munich]], Germany, since 1964&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Munich twinnings&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Partnerstädte|url=http://www.muenchen.de/rathaus/Stadtpolitik/Partnerstaedte.html|work=muenchen.de|accessdate=3 April 2013|language=German}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{flagicon|ALG}} [[Oran]], Algeria, since 2003&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;
*{{flagicon|POR}} [[Porto]], Portugal, since 1978&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Porto International&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cm-porto.pt/document/449218/481584.pdf |title=International Relations of the City of Porto |publisher=2006–2009 Municipal Directorateofthe PresidencyServices InternationalRelationsOffice |accessdate=10 July 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100215200138/http://www.cm-porto.pt/document/449218/481584.pdf |archivedate=15 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{flagicon|CAN}} [[Quebec City]],  [[Quebec]] Canada, since 1962&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;
*{{flagicon|LVA}} [[Riga]], Latvia&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.riga.lv/EN/Channels/Riga_Municipality/Twin_cities_of_Riga/default.htm |title=Twin cities of Riga |publisher=[[Riga City Council]] |accessdate=15 March 2013 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081204021323/http://www.riga.lv/EN/Channels/Riga_Municipality/Twin_cities_of_Riga/default.htm |archivedate=4 December 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{flagicon|RUS}} [[Saint Petersburg]], Russia, since 1993&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;saint_petersburg&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://eng.gov.spb.ru/figures/ities |title=Saint Petersburg in figures – International and Interregional Ties |publisher=Saint Petersburg City Government |accessdate=23 March 2008 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://archive.today/20090224073839/http://eng.gov.spb.ru/figures/ities |archivedate=24 February 2009 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{flagicon|PRC}} [[Wuhan]], China, since 1998&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;
*{{flagicon|PSE}} [[Ramallah]], Palestine&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;
*{{flagicon|POL}} [[Kraków]], Poland, since 1993&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kraków partnerships&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.krakow.pl/otwarty_na_swiat/2531,kat,0,5,miasta_partnerskie.html|title=Kraków – Miasta Partnerskie|accessdate=10 August 2013|work=Miejska Platforma Internetowa Magiczny Kraków|language=Polish|trans-title=Kraków -Partnership Cities|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130702010825/http://www.krakow.pl/otwarty_na_swiat/2531%2Ckat%2C0%2C5%2Cmiasta_partnerskie.html|archivedate=2 July 2013|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Div col end}}

===Partnerships===
{{Div col|colwidth=35em}}
*{{flagicon|TUR}} [[Samsun]], Turkey, since 2010&lt;ref name=&quot;Bordeaux twinnings 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.haberexen.com/news_detail.php?id=26638 |title=Samsun- Bordeaux işbirliği sözleşmesini imzalandı |publisher=HaberExen.com |accessdate=22 November 2010 |language=Turkish}}{{dead link|date=June 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Div col end}}

== See also ==
*[[Bordeaux wine regions]]
*[[Bordeaux–Paris]], a former professional [[road bicycle racing]]
*The [[Burdigalian]] Age of the [[Miocene]] Epoch is named for Bordeaux
*[[Canelé]], a local [[pastry]]
*[[Communes of the Gironde department]]
*[[Dogue de Bordeaux]], a [[Dog breed|breed]] of dog originally bred for [[dog fighting]]
*[[French wine]]
*[[List of mayors of Bordeaux]]
*[[Operation Frankton]], a British [[Combined Operations Headquarters|Combined Operations]] raid on shipping in the harbour at Bordeaux, in December 1942, during World War II
*[[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Bordeaux]]
*[[Girondins]]
* [[Atlantic history]]
* [[Triangular trade]]
* [[History of slavery]]

== References ==
{{INSEE}}
{{reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
{{See also|Timeline of Bordeaux#Bibliography|l1=Bibliography of the history of Bordeaux}}

== External links ==
{{Commons|Bordeaux}}
{{Wikivoyage|Bordeaux}}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20130306023822/http://www.france.fr/en/regions-and-cities/bordeaux-world-capital-wine Bordeaux : the world capital of wine] – Official French website (in English)
*{{Official website|1=www.bordeaux.fr|2=Bordeaux city council website}}
*[http://www.bordeaux-tourisme.com/ Tourist office website]
*[http://www.phonebookofbordeaux.com/ Phonebook of Bordeaux]
*[https://archive.today/20130205005719/http://www.uboat-bases.com/en/Bordeaux/la-base-de-u-boote-de-bordeaux.html Bordeaux submarine base : history, description, photos]
*[http://www.girondins.com/ Official Girondins de Bordeaux website]
*[http://www.sciencespo.fr/ Sciences Po Bordeaux]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20060421221321/http://www.infotbc.com/ Tram and bus maps and schedules]
*[http://www.bordeaux.com/ Bordeaux Wine official website]
*[http://www.bordeaux-gironde.fr/ Map &amp; City guide website]
*[http://www.battlefieldsww2.com/Bordeaux_u-boat_bunker.html German submarine base in Bordeaux]
*[https://www.bordeaux-port.fr/en/port-bordeaux/history]
{{Cities in France}}
{{Gironde communes}}
{{Urban Community of Bordeaux}}
{{World Heritage Sites in France}}
{{Higher Education in Bordeaux}}
{{Prefectures of departments of France}}
{{Prefectures of regions of France}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Bordeaux| ]]&lt;!--leave the empty space as standard--&gt;
[[Category:Communes of Gironde]]
[[Category:Port cities and towns on the French Atlantic coast]]
[[Category:Prefectures in France]]
[[Category:World Heritage Sites in France]]
[[Category:Cities in France]]
[[Category:Gironde]]
[[Category:Guyenne]]</text>
      <sha1>prp28nzozn69htluckg3i6lnkul6p4b</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
