  <page>
    <title>Brísingamen</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4063</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941494052</id>
      <parentid>941493992</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-18T22:24:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>24.108.87.71</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Borr the sons of Odin */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Torc or necklace in Norse mythology}}
[[Image:Freya and Heimdall by Blommer.jpg|thumb|Heimdall returns Brisingamen to Freyja, in an anachronistic painting centuries after the era of the myth's popularity.]]

In [[Norse mythology]], '''''Brísingamen''''' (or '''''Brísinga men''''') is the [[torc]] or [[necklace]] of the goddess [[Freyja]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Henry Adams Bellows (businessman)|Bellows, Henry Adams]] (Trans.) ''The Poetic Edda'', Princeton University Press, 1936. p. 158.&lt;/ref&gt; The name is an [[Old Norse]] compound ''brísinga-men'' whose second element is ''men'' &quot;(ornamental) neck-ring (of precious metal), torc&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Faulkes, Anthony and Barnes, Michael (compilers) ''A New Introduction to Old Norse''. Part III: ''Glossary and Index of Names''. Fourth ed. Viking Society for Northern Research, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The etymology of the first element is uncertain. It has been derived from Old Norse ''brísingr'', a poetic term for &quot;fire&quot; or &quot;amber&quot; mentioned in the anonymous versified word-lists (''þulur'') appended to many manuscripts of the [[Prose Edda]],&lt;ref&gt;[[Guðbrandur Vigfússon|Vigfusson, Gudbrand]] and [[Frederick York Powell|Powell, F. York]] (eds. &amp; trans.) ''Corpus Poeticum Boreale: The Poetry of the Old Northern Tongue''.  Vol. II: ''Court Poetry''. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1883. p. 435, l. 534.&lt;/ref&gt; making Brísingamen &quot;gleaming torc&quot;, &quot;sunny torc&quot;, or the like. However, ''Brísingr'' can also be an [[ethnonym]], in which case ''Brísinga men'' is &quot;torque of the Brísings&quot;; the [[Old English]] parallel in ''Beowulf'' supports this derivation, though who the Brísings (Old Norse ''Brísingar'') may have been remains unknown.&lt;ref&gt;[[John Lindow|Lindow, John]]. ''Handbook of Norse Mythology''. ABC-CLIO, 2001, s.v. ''Brísinga men''.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Attestations==


===''Beowulf''===
Brísingamen is referred to in the Anglo-Saxon epic ''[[Beowulf]]'' as ''Brosinga mene''. The brief mention in ''Beowulf'' is as follows (trans. by Howell Chickering, 1977):
{{quote|[S]ince Hama bore off&lt;br/&gt;to the shining city the Brosings' necklace, &lt;br/&gt;Gem-figured filigree. He gained the hatred&lt;br/&gt;Of Eormanric the Goth, chose eternal reward.}}
This seems to confuse
different stories as the ''Beowulf''  poet is clearly referring to the [[legends about Theoderic the Great]]. The ''[[Legends about Theoderic the Great#The Thidrekssaga|Þiðrekssaga]]'' tells that the warrior [[Háma|Heime]] (''Háma'' in Old English) takes sides against [[Ermanaric]] (&quot;Eormanric&quot;), king of the [[Goths]], and has to flee his kingdom after robbing him; later in life, Hama enters a monastery and gives them all his stolen treasure. However, this saga makes no mention of the great necklace. Possibly the ''Beowulf'' poet was confused, or invented the addition of the necklace to give him an excuse to drag in a mention of Eormanric. In any case, the necklace given to Beowulf in the story is not the Brísingamen itself; it is only being compared to it.

===''Poetic Edda'' and ''Prose Edda''===
In the poem ''[[Þrymskviða]]'' of the ''[[Poetic Edda]]'', [[Þrymr]], the king of the [[Jötunn|jǫtnar]], steals [[Thor]]'s hammer, [[Mjölnir]]. Freyja lends [[Loki]] her falcon cloak to search for it; but upon returning, Loki tells Freyja that Þrymr has hidden the hammer and demanded to marry her in return. Freyja is so wrathful that all the [[Æsir]]’s halls beneath her are shaken and the necklace Brísingamen breaks off from her neck. Later Thor borrows Brísingamen when he dresses up as Freyja to go to the wedding at [[Jötunheimr|Jǫtunheimr]].

''[[Húsdrápa]]'', a [[skald]]ic poem partially preserved in the ''[[Prose Edda]]'', relates the story of the theft of Brísingamen by [[Loki]]. One day when Freyja wakes up and finds Brísingamen missing, she enlists the help of [[Heimdallr]] to help her search for it. Eventually they find the thief, who turns out to be [[Loki]] who has transformed himself into a seal. Heimdallr turns into a seal as well and fights Loki. After a lengthy battle at [[Singasteinn]], Heimdallr wins and returns Brísingamen to Freyja.

[[Snorri Sturluson]] quoted this old poem in ''[[Skáldskaparmál]]'', saying that because of this legend Heimdallr is called &quot;Seeker of Freyja's Necklace&quot; (''Skáldskaparmál'', section 8) and Loki is called &quot;Thief of Brísingamen&quot; (''Skáldskaparmál'', section 16). A similar story appears in the later ''Sörla þáttr'', where Heimdallr does not appear.

==Borr the sons of [[Odin]]==

Brís - the joined meaning of [[Borr]] plus the word [[son]]

inge - The meaning of [[Inge]] is &quot;foremost one&quot;. 

men - the meaning of [[men]] is &quot;men&quot;.

Borr is mentioned in the fourth verse of the ''[[Völuspá]]'', a poem contained in the ''[[Poetic Edda]]'', and in the sixth chapter of ''[[Gylfaginning]]'', the second section of the ''[[Prose Edda]]''.

===''Sörla þáttr''===
[[Sörla þáttr]] is a short story in the later and extended version of the ''[[Flateyjarbók|Saga of Olaf Tryggvason]]''&lt;ref&gt;The ''[[Younger Edda]]''. [[Rasmus B. Anderson]] transl. (1897) Chicago: Scott, Foresman &amp; Co. (1901).&lt;/ref&gt; in the manuscript of the ''[[Flateyjarbók]]'', which was written and compiled by two Christian [[priest]]s, Jon Thordson and Magnus Thorhalson, in the late 14th century.&lt;ref name=RAMUS&gt;[[Rasmus B. Anderson]], Introduction to the ''[[Flateyjarbók|Flatey Book]]''. [[Norrœna Society]], London (1908). &quot;The priest Jon Thordson wrote the story of Erik Vidforle and both the Olaf Sagas; but the priest Magnus Thorhalson wrote what follows and also what goes before, and revised the whole, thus dedicating the work: &quot;May God Almighty and the Virgin Mary bless both the one that wrote and the one that dictated!&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; In the end of the story, the arrival of [[Christianity]] dissolves the old curse that traditionally was to endure until [[Ragnarök]].
{{quote|Freyja was a human in Asia and was the favorite [[concubinage|concubine]] of Odin, King of Asialand. When this woman wanted to buy a golden necklace (no name given) forged by four dwarves (named Dvalinn, Alfrik, Berling, and Grer), she offered them gold and silver but they replied that they would only sell it to her if she would lie a night by each of them. She came home afterward with the necklace and kept silent as if nothing happened. But a man called Loki somehow knew it, and came to tell Odin. King Odin commanded Loki to steal the necklace, so Loki turned into a fly to sneak into Freyja's bower and stole it. When Freyja found her necklace missing, she came to ask king Odin. In exchange for it, Odin ordered her to make two kings, each served by twenty kings, fight forever unless some [[Baptism|christened]] men so brave would dare to enter the battle and slay them. She said yes, and got that necklace back. Under the spell, king Högni and king Heðinn battled for one hundred and forty-three years, as soon as they fell down they had to stand up again and fight on. But in the end, the Christian lord [[Olaf Tryggvason]], who has a great fate and luck, arrived with his christened men, and whoever slain by a Christian would stay dead. Thus the pagan curse was finally dissolved by the arrival of Christianity. After that, the noble man, king Olaf, went back to his realm.&lt;ref&gt;This short story is also known as &quot;The Saga of Högni and Hedinn&quot;. English translation can be found at [http://www.northvegr.org/lore/love/00401.php Northvegr: Three Northern Love Stories and Other Tales.] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080424041149/http://www.northvegr.org/lore/love/00401.php |date=2008-04-24 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The battle of Högni and Heðinn is recorded in several medieval sources, including the skaldic poem ''[[Ragnarsdrápa]]'', ''Skáldskaparmál'' (section 49), and ''[[Gesta Danorum]]'': king Högni's daughter, Hildr, is kidnapped by king Heðinn. When Högni comes to fight Heðinn on an island, Hildr comes to offer her father a necklace on behalf of Heðinn for peace; but the two kings still battle, and [[Hildr]] resurrects the fallen to make them fight until Ragnarök.&lt;ref name=BRODEURPROSE&gt;{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Brodeur|first=Arthur Gilchrist|authorlink=Arthur Gilchrist Brodeur|title=The Prose Edda|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=_T1cAAAAMAAJ|year=1916|publisher=American-Scandinavian Foundation}}&lt;/ref&gt; None of these earlier sources mentions Freyja or king Olaf Tryggvason, the historical figure who [[Christianize]]d Norway and Iceland in the 10th Century.

==Archaeological record==
[[Image:Freyja in silver.jpg|thumb|right|120px|The pendant, in the [[Swedish Museum of National Antiquities]] in [[Stockholm]].]]
[[Völva]] was buried {{circa|1000}} with considerable splendour in Hagebyhöga in [[Östergötland]]. In addition to being buried with her [[wand]], she had received great riches which included horses, a wagon and an Arabian bronze pitcher. There was also a silver pendant, which represents a woman with a broad necklace around her neck. This kind of necklace was only worn by the most prominent women during the Iron Age and some have interpreted it as [[Freyja]]'s necklace Brísingamen. The pendant may represent Freyja herself.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harrison58&quot;&gt;Harrison, D. &amp; Svensson, K. (2007). ''Vikingaliv''. Fälth &amp; Hässler, Värnamo. {{ISBN|978-91-27-35725-9}} p.58&lt;/ref&gt;

==Modern influence==
[[Alan Garner]] wrote a children's [[fantasy]] novel called ''[[The Weirdstone of Brisingamen]]'' about an enchanted teardrop bracelet.

[[Diana L. Paxson|Diana Paxson's]] novel ''Brisingamen'' features Freyja and her bracelet.

[[Black Phoenix Alchemy Lab]] has a perfumed oil scent named Brisingamen.

Freyja's necklace Brisingamen features prominently in [[Betsy Tobin]]'s novel ''Iceland'', where the necklace is seen to have significant protective powers.

[[J. R. R. Tolkien]]'s ''[[The Silmarillion]]'' includes a treasure called the Nauglamír, which was made by the dwarves of [[Eriador]] for the elvish king [[Finrod Felagund]]. However, the necklace was brought out a dragon's hoard by [[Túrin Turambar]] and given to King [[Thingol]] of [[Doriath]]. This king asks a group of dwarves to set a [[Silmaril]] into the necklace for his wife Melian to wear. The dwarves fall under the spell of the Silmaril and they claim the Nauglamir as their own – with the Silmaril attached. They kill Thingol and make off with the necklace. It is eventually recovered and is an heirloom of Thingol's descendants, eventually leading [[Eärendil]] to [[Valinor]] and resulting in the return of the [[Vala (Middle-earth)|Valar]] into the affairs of [[Middle-earth]]. This is clearly intended to be the equivalent in his mythology to the Brísingamen.{{OR|date=November 2018}}

The Brisingamen feature as a major item in [[Joel Rosenberg (science fiction author)|Joel Rosenberg]]'s [[Joel Rosenberg (science fiction author)#Keepers of the Hidden Ways|Keepers of the Hidden Ways]] series of books. In it, there are seven jewels that were created for the necklace by the Dwarfs and given to the Norse goddess. She in turn eventually split them up into the seven separate jewels and hid them throughout the realm, as together they hold the power to shape the universe by its holder. The book's plot is about discovering one of them and deciding what to do with the power they allow while avoiding Loki and other Norse characters.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.kirkusreviews.com/book-reviews/joel-rosenberg/the-fire-duke/|title=THE FIRE DUKE by Joel Rosenberg {{!}} Kirkus Reviews|language=en-us}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Christopher Paolini]]'s ''[[Inheritance Cycle]]'', the word &quot;brisingr&quot; means fire. This is probably a distillation of the word ''brisinga''.

[[Ursula Le Guin]]'s short story ''[[Semley's Necklace]]'', the first part of her novel ''[[Rocannon's World]]'', is a retelling of the Brisingamen story on an alien planet.

Brisingamen is represented as a card in the [[Yu-Gi-Oh! Trading Card Game|''Yu-Gi-Oh!'' Trading Card Game]], &quot;Nordic Relic Brisingamen&quot;.

Brisingamen was part of MMORPG ''[[Ragnarok Online]]'' lore, which is ranked as &quot;God item&quot;. The game is heavily based from Norse mythology.

In the ''Firefly Online'' game, one of the planets of the [[Himinbjörg]] system (which features planets named after figures from Germanic mythology) is named Brisingamen.  It is third from the star, and has moons named Freya, Beowulf, and [[Alberich]].

The Brisingamen is an item that can be found and equipped in the game ''[[Castlevania: Lament of Innocence]]''.

==See also==
* [[Necklace of Harmonia]], a necklace owned by the Greek goddess Harmonia, a daughter of Aphrodite

== References ==
{{Reflist}}
{{Norse mythology}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Brisingamen}}
[[Category:Artifacts in Norse mythology]]
[[Category:Freyja]]
[[Category:Torcs]]
[[Category:Mythological clothing]]
[[Category:Individual necklaces]]</text>
      <sha1>oocdfh0tjzyw1keosapzrhaztax01se</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
