  <page>
    <title>Battle of Pharsalus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4005</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940148454</id>
      <parentid>933385568</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-10T20:33:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Aforst1</username>
        <id>36246437</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added sources and updated numbers, casualty figures and information on Pompey's army</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{For|other battles that took place at Pharsalus|Battle of Pharsalus (disambiguation)}}
{{more footnotes|date=August 2013}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Pharsalus
| width       = 
| partof      = [[Caesar's Civil War]]
| image       = Battle of Pharsalus, 48 BC.gif
| image_size  = 300px
| alt         =
| caption     = 
| date        = 9 August 48 BC
| place       = [[Farsala|Palaeopharsalos]] (Greece)
| coordinates = &lt;!--Use the {{coord}} template --&gt;
| result      = Decisive Caesarian victory
| combatant1  = Caesarians
| combatant2  = Pompeians
| commander1  = [[Julius Caesar]]&lt;br&gt;[[Mark Antony]]&lt;br&gt;[[Gnaeus Domitius Calvinus]]&lt;br&gt;[[Publius Cornelius Sulla]]
| commander2  = [[Pompey]]&lt;br&gt;[[Titus Labienus]]&lt;br&gt;[[Metellus Scipio]]&lt;br&gt;[[Lucius Domitius Ahenobarbus (consul 54 BC)|Domitius Ahenobarbus]]{{KIA}}&lt;br&gt;[[Lucius Afranius (consul)|Lucius Afranius]]
| strength1   = 22,000 [[Legionary|legionaries]]&lt;br&gt;1,000 cavalry
| strength2   = 40,000 legionaries{{sfn|Fields|2008|pp=55, 62}}{{sfn|Brunt|1971|pp=691–692}}{{sfn|Delbrück|1975|p=545}}&lt;br&gt;3,000–6,700 cavalry
| strength3   = Uncounted amounts of [[auxilia]]ry and allied infantry
| casualties1 = 230–1,200 killed{{sfn|Appian|loc=2.82}}
| casualties2 = 6,000 killed ([[Gaius Asinius Pollio (consul 40 BC)|Pollio]]){{sfn|Goldsworthy|2006|p=430}}&lt;br&gt;Surrender of most troops
}}
{{Campaignbox Caesar's Civil War}}

The '''Battle of Pharsalus''' was the decisive battle of [[Caesar's Civil War]]. On 9 August 48 BC at [[Pharsalus]] in central Greece, [[Julius Caesar|Gaius Julius Caesar]] and his allies formed up opposite the army of the [[Roman Republic|republic]] under the command of [[Pompey|Gnaeus Pompeius Magnus]] (&quot;Pompey the Great&quot;). Pompey had the backing of a majority of the [[Roman Senate|senators]], of whom many were [[optimate]]s, and his army significantly outnumbered the veteran Caesarian legions.

The two armies confronted each other over several months of uncertainty, Caesar being in a much weaker position than Pompey.
The former found himself isolated in a hostile country with only 22,000 men and short of provisions, while on the other side of the river he was faced by Pompey with an army about twice as large in number. Pompey wanted to delay, knowing the enemy would eventually surrender from hunger and exhaustion. Pressured by the senators present and by his officers, he reluctantly engaged in battle and suffered an overwhelming defeat, ultimately fleeing the camp and his men, disguised as an ordinary citizen. However, Pompey was later assassinated in [[Ptolemaic Egypt]] by orders of [[Ptolemy XIII]].

==Prelude==
{{unreferenced section|date=July 2014}}
A dispute between Caesar and the ''optimates'' faction in the Senate of Rome culminated in Caesar marching his army on Rome and forcing Pompey, accompanied by much of the [[Roman Senate]], to flee in 49 BC from Italy to Greece, where he could better conscript an army to face his former ally. Caesar, lacking a fleet to immediately give chase, solidified his control over the western Mediterranean – Spain specifically – before assembling ships to follow Pompey. [[Marcus Calpurnius Bibulus]], whom Pompey had appointed to command his 600-ship fleet, set up a massive blockade to prevent Caesar from crossing to Greece and to prevent any aid to Italy. Caesar, defying convention, chose to cross the Adriatic during the winter, with only half his fleet at a time. As Pontifex Maximus, Caesar was responsible for adjusting the Roman calendar at the end of each year to align it with the rotation of the Earth around the sun. As Caesar had been in Gaul and then occupied by the civil war for years, he had not been able to make this yearly change and over time, the difference between the Earth's rotation and the calendar that Rome operated on had grown to such an extent that Bibulus, along with the others who had fled to Greece, believed that it was months later than when Caesar knew it was. As such, this move surprised Bibulus, who believed it was winter, and the first wave of ships managed to run the blockade easily. Now prepared, Bibulus managed to prevent any further ships from crossing, but died soon afterwards.

Caesar was now in a precarious position, holding a beachhead at [[Epirus]] with only half his army, no ability to supply his troops by sea, and limited local support, as the Greek cities were mostly loyal to Pompey. Caesar's only choice was to fortify his position, forage what supplies he could, and wait on his remaining army to attempt another crossing. Pompey by now had a massive international army; however, his troops were mostly untested raw recruits, while Caesar's troops were hardened veterans. Realizing Caesar's difficulty in keeping his troops supplied, Pompey decided to simply mirror Caesar's forces and let hunger do the fighting for him. Caesar began to despair and used every channel he could think of to pursue peace with Pompey. When this was rebuffed he made an attempt to cross back to Italy to collect his missing troops, but was turned back by a storm. Finally, [[Mark Antony]] rallied the remaining forces in Italy, fought through the blockade and made the crossing, reinforcing Caesar's forces in both men and spirit. Now at full strength, Caesar felt confident to take the fight to Pompey.

Pompey was camped in a strong position just south of [[Battle of Dyrrhachium (48 BC)|Dyrrhachium]] with the sea to his back and surrounded by hills, making a direct assault impossible. Caesar ordered a wall to be built around Pompey's position in order to cut off water and pasture land for his horses. Pompey built a parallel wall and in between a kind of no man's land was created, with fighting comparable to the trench warfare of [[World War&amp;nbsp;I]]. Ultimately the standoff was broken when a traitor in Caesar's army informed Pompey of a weakness in Caesar's wall. Pompey immediately exploited this information and forced Caesar's army into a full retreat, but ordered his army not to pursue, fearing Caesar's reputation for setting elaborate traps. This caused Caesar to remark, &quot;Today the victory had been the enemy's, had there been any one among them to gain it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Plutarch]] ''Pompey'' [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A2008.01.0058%3Achapter%3D65%3Asection%3D5 65.5], Dryden translation: [https://books.google.com/books?id=QScSAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA465&amp;lpg=PA465 p. 465].&lt;/ref&gt; Pompey continued his strategy of mirroring Caesar's forces and avoiding any direct engagements.  After trapping Caesar in [[Thessaly]], the prominent senators in Pompey's camp began to argue loudly for a more decisive victory. Although Pompey was strongly against it — he wanted to surround and starve Caesar's army instead — he eventually gave in and accepted battle from Caesar on a field near Pharsalus.

Excerpt from Cassius Dio's &quot;Roman History&quot; gives a more ancient flavor of his take on the prelude to the &quot;Battle of Pharsalus&quot;: [41.56] &quot;As a result of these circumstances and of the very cause and purpose of the war a most notable struggle took place. For the city of Rome and its entire empire, even then great and mighty, lay before them as the prize, since it was clear to all that it would be the slave of him who then conquered. When they reflected on this fact and furthermore thought of their former deeds [...41.57] they were wrought up to the highest pitch of excitement....they now, led by their insatiable lust of power, hastened to break, tear, and rend asunder. Because of them Rome was being compelled to fight both in her own defense and against herself, so that even if victorious she would be vanquished.&quot;

==Date==
The date of the actual decisive battle is given as 9 August 48 BC according to the republican calendar.{{citation needed|date=July 2014}} According to the Julian calendar however, the date was either 29 June (according to Le Verrier's chronological reconstruction) or possibly 7 June (according to Drumann/Groebe).{{where?|date=July 2014}}{{citation needed|date=July 2014}} As Pompey was assassinated on 3 September 48 BC, the battle must have taken place in the true month of August, when the harvest was becoming ripe (or Pompey's strategy of starving Caesar would not be plausible).{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}

==Location==
The location of the battlefield was for a long time the subject of controversy among scholars. Caesar himself, in his [[Commentarii de Bello Civili]], mentions few place-names;&lt;ref&gt;''Bellum Civile'' 3.81–98&lt;/ref&gt; and although the battle is called after Pharsalos by modern authors, four ancient writers – the author of the ''Bellum Alexandrinum'' (48.1), [[Frontinus]] (''Strategemata'' 2.3.22), [[Eutropius (historian)|Eutropius]] (20), and [[Orosius]] (6.15.27) – place it specifically at ''Palae''pharsalus (&quot;Old&quot; Pharsalus). [[Strabo]] in his ''Geographica'' (''Γεωγραφικά'') mentions both old and new Pharsaloi, and notes that the Thetideion, the temple to [[Thetis]] south of Scotoussa, was near both. In 198 BC, in the [[Second Macedonian War]], [[Philip V of Macedon]] sacked Palaepharsalos ([[Livy]], ''[[Ab Urbe Condita Libri (Livy)|Ab Urbe Condita]]'' 32.13.9), but left new Pharsalos untouched. These two details perhaps imply that the two cities were not close neighbours. Many scholars, therefore, unsure of the site of Palaepharsalos, followed [[Appian]] (2.75) and located the battle of 48 BC south of the Enipeus or close to Pharsalos (today's [[Pharsala]]).&lt;ref&gt;Map with conjectured locations, ''Annual of the British School at Athens'', No. XXIV, 1921 [https://www.jstor.org/stable/30102514?seq=21]&lt;/ref&gt; Among the scholars arguing for the south side are Béquignon (1928), Bruère (1951), and Gwatkin (1956).

An increasing number of scholars, however, have argued for a location on the north side of the river. These include Perrin (1885), Holmes (1908), Lucas (1921), Rambaud (1955), Pelling (1973), Morgan (1983), and Sheppard (2006). John D. Morgan in his definitive “Palae-pharsalus – the Battle and the Town”,&lt;ref&gt;''The American Journal of Archaeology'', Vol. 87, No. 1, Jan. 1983&lt;/ref&gt; shows that Palaepharsalus cannot have been at Palaiokastro, as Béquignon thought (a site abandoned c. 500 BC), nor the hill of Fatih-Dzami within the walls of Pharsalus itself, as Kromayer (1903, 1931) and Gwatkin thought; and Morgan argues that it is probably also not the hill of Khtouri (Koutouri), some 7 miles north-west of Pharsalus on the south bank of the Enipeus, as Lucas and Holmes thought, although that remains a possibility.  However, Morgan believes it is most likely to have been the hill just east of the village of Krini (formerly Driskoli) very close to the ancient highway from Larisa to Pharsalus.&lt;ref&gt;See Google maps.&lt;/ref&gt; This site is some six miles (10km) north of Pharsalus, and three miles north of the river Enipeus, and not only has remains dating back to neolithic times but also signs of habitation in the 1st century BC and later. The identification seems to be confirmed by the location of a place misspelled &quot;Palfari&quot; or &quot;Falaphari&quot; shown on a medieval route map of the road just north of Pharsalus. Morgan places Pompey's camp a mile to the west of Krini, just north of the village of Avra (formerly Sarikayia), and Caesar's camp some four miles to the east-south-east of Pompey's. According to this reconstruction, therefore, the battle took place not between Pharsalus and the river, as Appian wrote, but between Old Pharsalus and the river.

An interesting side-note on Palaepharsalus is that it was sometimes identified in ancient sources with [[Phthia]], the home of [[Achilles]].&lt;ref&gt;Holmes (1908), p. 275; cf. Strabo, ''Geography'', 9.5.6; [[Little Iliad]] frag. 19; Euripides ''Andromache'' 16ff.&lt;/ref&gt; Near Old and New Pharsalus was a [[Thetidium|&quot;Thetideion&quot;]], or temple dedicated to Thetis, the mother of Achilles. However, Phthia, the kingdom of Achilles and his father [[Peleus]], is more usually identified with the lower valley of the [[Spercheios]] river, much further south.&lt;ref&gt;Allen, T. W. (1906). [https://www.jstor.org/stable/694919 &quot;Μυρμιδόνων Πόλις&quot;]. ''The Classical Review'', Vol. 20, No. 4 (May, 1906), pp. 193-201; cf. p. 196.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://referenceworks.brillonline.com/entries/brill-s-new-pauly/phthia-e924400 Phthia] in Brill's New Paully encyclopaedia.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Name of the battle==
Although it is often called the Battle of Pharsalus by modern historians, this name was rarely used in the ancient sources. Caesar merely calls it the ''proelium in Thessaliā'' (&quot;battle in Thessalia&quot;); Cicero and [[Aulus Hirtius|Hirtius]] call it the ''Pharsālicum proelium'' (&quot;Pharsalic battle&quot;) or ''pugna Pharsālia'' (&quot;Pharsalian battle&quot;), and similar expressions are also used in other authors. But Hirtius (if he is the author of the [[de Bello Alexandrino]]) also refers to the battle as having taken place at ''Palaepharsalus'', and this name also occurs in [[Strabo]], [[Frontinus]], [[Eutropius (historian)|Eutropius]], and [[Orosius]]. [[Lucan]] in his poem about the Civil War regularly uses the name ''Pharsālia'', and this term is also used by the epitomiser of Livy and by Tacitus.&lt;ref&gt;Morgan (1983), p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt; The only ancient sources to refer to the battle as being at Pharsalus are a certain calendar known as the [[List of ancient Roman fasti|Fasti Amiternini]] and the Greek authors [[Plutarch]], [[Appian]], and [[Polyaenus]].&lt;ref&gt;Morgan (1983), p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt; It has therefore been argued by some scholars that &quot;Pharsalia&quot; would be a more accurate name for the battle than Pharsalus.&lt;ref&gt;Postgate (1905); Bruère (1951).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Opposing armies==
{{multiple issues|section=yes|
{{expand section|date=November 2013}}
{{refimprove section|date=July 2014}}
}}

===Caesarian army===

Caesar gives his own numbers as 22,000 men in eighty [[Cohort (Roman)|cohorts]] (it should be remembered that these numbers refer to legionaries, and do not include non-Roman infantry) and 1,000 cavalry (mainly Germanic and Gallic auxiliaries).&lt;ref name=LBC&gt;John Leach, ''Pompey the Great'', p. 204; P. A. Brunt, ''Italian Manpower'', p. 691; Julius Caesar, ''Commentarii de Bello Civili'', III, 89.2.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Caesar had the following legions with him:{{citation needed|date=July 2014}}

* Legions of veterans from the [[Gallic Wars]] – Caesar's favourite legion, [[Legio X Equestris|X ''Equestris'']], and those later known with the names of [[Legio VIII Augusta|VIII ''Augusta'']], [[Legio IX Hispana|IX ''Hispana'']], and [[Legio XII Fulminata|XII ''Fulminata'']]
* Legions levied for the civil war – legions later known as [[Legio I Germanica|I ''Germanica'']], [[Legio III Gallica|III ''Gallica'']], and [[Legio IV Macedonica|IV ''Macedonica'']]

However, all of these legions were understrength. Some only had about a thousand men at the time of Pharsalus, due partly to losses at Dyrrhachium and partly to Caesar's wish to rapidly advance with a picked body as opposed to a ponderous movement with a large army.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://militaryhistory.about.com/od/battleswarsto1000/p/pharsalus.htm|title=Battle of Pharsalus |publisher=militaryhistory.com |date= |accessdate=2013-06-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Pompeian army===
Aside from 5 legions Pompey had brought over from Italy, he had one from [[Cilicia]], one from Greece, and acquired two more from [[Asia (Roman province)|Asia]] raised by the consul [[Lucius Cornelius Lentulus Crus|Lentulus]].{{sfn|Sheppard|2006|p=37}} He distributed amongst them a number of veteran re-enlistees from Greece, as well as the elements of 15 cohorts captured from Caesar's supporter [[Gaius Antonius (brother of Mark Antony)|Gaius Antonius]] in [[Illyria]].{{sfn|Sheppard|2006|pp=37–38}} Pompey at some point was reinforced by some cohorts which had fled [[Battle of Ilerda|Caesar's onslaught in Spain]],{{sfn|Fields|2008|p=62}} and was awaiting another two legions from [[Syria (Roman province)|Syria]] to be brought by his father-in-law, [[Metellus Scipio]].{{sfn|Sheppard|2006|p=38}} This brought the army's strength to a total of 11 legions, of which 88 cohorts were fielded at Pharsalus, comprising altogether some 40,000 heavy infantry.{{sfnm|1a1=Fields|1y=2008|1pp=55, 62|2a1=Brunt|2y=1971|2pp=691–692|3a1=Delbrück|3y=1975|3p=545}}{{efn|Caesar put the strength of Pompey's legionaries at 45,000 regular soldiers plus 2,000 [[Evocatus|re-enlisted veterans]] in 110 cohorts (11 legions), but neglected to subtract 7 cohorts left to guard the camp and failed to mention altogether another 15 left behind at Dyrrachium on garrison duty.{{sfn|Fields|2008|pp=55, 62}}{{sfn|Brunt|1971|pp=691–692}}{{sfn|Delbrück|1975|p=545}} The figure of 40,000 legionaries in 88 cohorts, which tallies with the number of cohorts detached (22 from 110), is given by [[Eutropius (historian)|Eutropius]] and [[Orosius]],{{sfnm|1a1=Eutropius|1loc=6.20|2a1=Orosius|2loc=6.15.23}} following [[Livy]] and probably, ultimately, Caesar's officer [[Gaius Asinius Pollio (consul 40 BC)|Gaius Asinius Pollio]]. Brunt suggested that Caesar's figure of 47,000 corresponds to the whole of Pompey's army, not all of which fought at Pharsalus.{{sfn|Brunt|1971|pp=691–692}}{{sfn|Delbrück|1975|p=545}} }} Pompey's auxiliary infantry and cavalry outnumbered Caesar's own by far (though their exact amount is unclear) and were remarkably diverse, including a handful of Gallic and Germanic cavalry and all polyglot peoples of the east – [[Phoenicians]], [[Crete|Cretan]] slingers and other [[Greeks]], [[Jews]], [[Arabs]], [[Anatolia]]ns, [[Armenians]], and others – to which heterogeneous force Pompey added horsemen conscripted from his own slaves.{{sfn|Sheppard|2006|pp=38, 60–61}} Many of the foreigners were serving under their own rulers, for more than a dozen [[Despotism|despot]]s and petty kings under Roman influence in the east were Pompey's personal clients and some elected to attend in person, or send proxies.{{sfn|Sheppard|2006|pp=38, 60–61}}{{efn|Caesar mentions that Pompey raised 7,000 cavalry, 3,000 archers and two 600-strong cohorts of [[Sling (weapon)|sling]]ers (before Dyrrachium),{{sfn|Caesar|loc=3.88}} but many of these men would be used for garrisoning and other non-combat-related duties.{{sfn|Appian|loc=2.49}} }} Of Pompey's cavalry specifically, Sheppard suggests that Pompey still had 6,700 men with him at Pharsalus,{{sfn|Sheppard|2006|p=61}} but [[Hans Delbrück]] believed the number to be much lower, 3,000 by his speculation.{{sfn|Delbrück|1975|p=549}}

==Battle==

===Deployment===
[[File:BattlePharsalus-LIX.png|thumb|Initial deployment of forces at the Battle of Pharsalus, August 48 BC]]

{{unreferenced section|date=July 2014}}
On the Pharsalian plain, Pompey deployed his infantry in the traditional three lines of 10 men deep, thusly: Legions I and III were on the left with Pompey himself; at his center were the legions from Syria commanded by [[Quintus Caecilius Metellus Pius Scipio Nasica|Scipio]], and on the right, against the Enipeus River, were legions from Cilicia and Spanish auxiliaries. Pompey's cavalry, which greatly outnumbered Caesar's, were commanded by [[Titus Labienus|Labienus]], a brilliant cavalry commander and Caesar's old lieutenant during the [[Gallic Wars]]. They were massed in a single body on Pompey's left flank, together with his auxiliary archers and slingers. Pompey's tactical plan was to allow Caesar's legions to charge while his own stood their ground, reasoning that the enemy would fatigue by charging the double distance, and that his own men would better withstand the [[pilum]] toss while stationary. Simultaneously his cavalry would overwhelm the enemy's and then take the legions in the flank and rear — a classic [[hammer and anvil]] tactic.

Caesar also deployed his men in three lines, but, being outnumbered, had to thin his ranks to a depth of only six men, in order to match the frontage presented by Pompey. His left flank, resting on the Enipeus River, consisted of his [[Battle of Dyrrhachium (48 BC)|battle worn]] IX&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; legion supplemented by the VIII&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; legion, these commanded by [[Mark Antony]]. The center was commanded by [[Gnaeus Domitius Calvinus|Domitius]] and upon his right he placed his favored X&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; legion, giving [[Publius Cornelius Sulla|Sulla]] command of this flank — Caesar himself took his stand on the right, across from Pompey. Upon seeing the disposition of Pompey's army Caesar grew discomforted, and further thinned his third line in order to form a fourth line on his right: this to counter the onslaught of the enemy cavalry, which he knew his numerically inferior cavalry could not withstand. He gave this new line detailed instructions for the role they would play, hinting that upon them would rest the fortunes of the day, and gave strict orders to his third line not to charge until specifically ordered.

=== Progress of the battle ===
{{refimprove section|date=July 2014}}
There was significant distance between the two armies, according to Caesar.&lt;ref&gt;Caesar, BC III 92,1.&lt;/ref&gt; Pompey ordered his men not to charge, but to wait until Caesar's legions came into close quarters; Pompey's adviser [[Gaius Triarius]] believed that Caesar's infantry would be fatigued and fall into disorder if they were forced to cover twice the expected distance of a battle march. Also, stationary troops were expected to be able to defend better against [[Pilum|pila]] throws.&lt;ref&gt;Caesar, BC III, 92,2.&lt;/ref&gt; Seeing that Pompey's army was not advancing, Caesar's infantry under [[Mark Antony]] and [[Gnaeus Domitius Calvinus]] started the advance. As Caesar's men neared throwing distance, without orders, they stopped to rest and regroup before continuing the charge;&lt;ref&gt;Caesar, BC III, 93,1.&lt;/ref&gt; Pompey's right and centre line held as the two armies collided.

As Pompey's infantry fought, [[Labienus]] ordered the Pompeian cavalry on his left flank to attack Caesar's cavalry; as expected they successfully pushed back Caesar's cavalry. Caesar then revealed his hidden fourth line of infantry and surprised Pompey's cavalry charge; Caesar's men were ordered to leap up and use their [[Pilum|pila]] to thrust at Pompey's cavalry instead of throwing them. Pompey's cavalry panicked and suffered hundreds of casualties. After failing to reform, the rest of the cavalry retreated to the hills, leaving the left wing of Pompey's legions exposed. Caesar then ordered in his third line, containing his most battle-hardened veterans, to attack. This broke Pompey's left wing troops, who fled the battlefield.&lt;ref name=&quot;academia1&quot;&gt;https://www.academia.edu/19860273/48_BC_The_Battle_of_Pharsalus&lt;/ref&gt;

After routing Pompey's cavalry, Caesar threw in his last line of reserves&lt;ref&gt;Caesar, BC III, 93,4&lt;/ref&gt; —a move which at this point meant that the battle was more or less decided.{{citation needed|date=July 2014}} Pompey lost the will to fight as he watched both cavalry and legions under his command break formation and flee from battle, and he retreated to his camp, leaving the rest of his troops at the centre and right flank to their own devices. He ordered the garrisoned auxiliaries to defend the camp as he gathered his family, loaded up gold, and threw off his general's cloak to make a quick escape.{{citation needed|date=July 2014}} As the rest of Pompey's army were left confused, Caesar urged his men to end the day by routing the rest of Pompey's troops and capturing the Pompeian camp. They complied with his wishes; after finishing off the remains of Pompey's men, they furiously attacked the camp walls. The Thracians and the other auxiliaries who were left in the Pompeian camp, in total seven cohorts, defended bravely, but were not able to fend off the assault.&lt;ref name=&quot;academia1&quot;/&gt;

Caesar had won his greatest victory, claiming to have only lost about 200 soldiers and 30 centurions.&lt;ref&gt;Caesar, BC III 99,1.&lt;/ref&gt; In his history of the war, Caesar would praise his own men's discipline and experience, and remembered each of his [[centurion]]s by name. He also questioned Pompey's decision not to charge.&lt;ref&gt;Caesar, BC III, 92,3.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
{{unreferenced section|date=July 2014}}
Pompey fled from Pharsalus to [[Egypt]], where he was assassinated on the order of [[Ptolemy XIII]]. Ptolemy XIII sent Pompey's head to Caesar in an effort to win his favor, but instead secured him as a furious enemy.  Ptolemy, advised by his regent, the eunuch [[Pothinus]], and his rhetoric tutor [[Theodotus of Chios]], had failed to take into account that Caesar was granting amnesty to a great number of those of the [[Optimates|senatorial]] faction in their defeat. Even men who had been bitter enemies were allowed not only to return to Rome but to assume their previous positions in Roman society.

Pompey's assassination had deprived Caesar of his ultimate public relations moment — pardoning his most ardent rival. The Battle of Pharsalus ended the wars of the [[First Triumvirate]]. The Roman Civil War, however, was not ended. Pompey's two sons, [[Gnaeus Pompeius (son of Pompey the Great)|Gnaeus Pompeius]] and [[Sextus Pompey]], and the Pompeian faction, led now by Metellus Scipio and Cato, survived and fought for their cause in the name of Pompey the Great. Caesar spent the next few years 'mopping up' remnants of the [[Optimates|senatorial faction]].  After seemingly vanquishing all his enemies and bringing peace to Rome, he was [[Assassination of Julius Caesar|assassinated]] in 44 BC by friends, in a conspiracy organized by [[Marcus Junius Brutus]] and [[Gaius Cassius Longinus]].

==Importance==
[[File:Niccolò da Bologna 01.jpg|thumb|right|250px|An [[Anachronism|Anachronic]] 14th century miniature by [[Niccolò da Bologna]] showing Caesar, the victor over Pompey at the Battle of Pharsalus]]
[[Paul K. Davis (historian)|Paul K. Davis]] wrote that &quot;Caesar's victory took him to the pinnacle of power, effectively ending the Republic.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Paul K. Davis, ''100 Decisive Battles from Ancient Times to the Present: The World’s Major Battles and How They Shaped History'' (Oxford: [[Oxford University Press]], 1999), 59.&lt;/ref&gt; The battle itself did not end the civil war but it was decisive and gave Caesar a much needed boost in legitimacy. Until then much of the Roman world outside Italy supported Pompey and his allies due to the extensive list of clients he held in all corners of the Republic.  After Pompey's defeat former allies began to align themselves with Caesar as some came to believe the gods favored him, while for others it was simple self-preservation.  The ancients took great stock in success as a sign of favoritism by the gods.{{citation needed|date=June 2014}}  This is especially true of success in the face of almost certain defeat — as Caesar experienced at Pharsalus.  This allowed Caesar to parlay this single victory into a huge network of willing clients to better secure his hold over power and force the Optimates into near exile in search for allies to continue the fight against Caesar.

== In popular culture ==
The battle gives its name to the following artistic, geographical, and business concerns:

* ''[[Pharsalia]]'', a poem by [[Marcus Annaeus Lucanus|Lucan]]
* [[Pharsalia, New York]], U.S.
* [[Pharsalia Technologies]], Inc.

In [[Alexander Dumas]]' ''[[The Three Musketeers]]'', the author makes reference to Caesar's purported order that his men try to cut the faces of their opponents - their vanity supposedly being of more value to them than their lives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Dumas |first=Alexander |date=2009 |title=The Three Musketeers |url= |location= |publisher=Oxford University Press |page=620 |isbn=0199538468 |author-link= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{notelist}}
{{Reflist}}

==References==
===Ancient sources===
* {{cite |author=[[Appian]] |title=The Civil Wars |series=Roman History |volume=books 13–17 |url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Appian/Civil_Wars/2*.html}}
* {{cite |last=Caesar |first=Julius |title=[[Commentarii de Bello Civili]] |volume=[https://sacred-texts.com/cla/jcsr/civ3.htm 3]}}
* {{cite |author=Eutropius |title=Abridgement of Roman History |url=https://www.forumromanum.org/literature/eutropius/ |authorlink=Eutropius (historian)}}
* {{cite |author=[[Orosius]] |title=Seven Books of History against the Pagans |url={{googlebooks|s49zf3smkwwC|pg=295|plainurl=y}} }}

===Modern sources===
* {{cite book |last=Brunt |year=1971 |first=P.A. |title=Italian Manpower 225 B.C. – A.D. 14 |publisher=Clarendon Press |place=Oxford |isbn=0-19-814283-8 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Delbrück |date=1975 |first=Hans |title=History of the Art of War volume 1: Warfare in Antiquity |translator=Walter J. Renfroe Jr. |edition=3rd |publisher=University of Nebraska Press |place=Lincoln |origyear=1900 |isbn=0-8032-6584-0 |url={{googlebooks|MP2k4rx-Q_UC|plainurl=y}} |authorlink=Hans Delbrück |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Fields |date=2008 |first=Nic |title=The Roman Army: the Civil Wars 88–31 BC |publisher=Osprey Publishing |place=Oxford&lt;!-- |publicationdate=2008-10-10--&gt; |isbn=978-1-84603-262-2 |url= |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Goldsworthy |year=2006 |first=Adrian |title=Caesar: The Life of a Colossus |publisher=Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson |place=London |isbn=0-297-84620-5 |authorlink=Adrian Goldsworthy |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Sheppard |year=2006 |first=Simon |title=Pharsalus 48 BC: Caesar and Pompey – Clash of the Titans |publisher=Osprey Publishing |place=Oxford&lt;!-- |publicationdate=2006-09-06--&gt; |isbn=1-84603-002-1 |url= |ref=harv}}

==Further reading==
* Bruère, Richard Treat, (1951). [https://www.jstor.org/stable/265967 &quot;Palaepharsalus, Pharsalus, Pharsalia&quot;]. ''Classical Philology'', Vol. 46, No. 2 (Apr., 1951), pp. 111-115.
* Gwatkin, William E. (1956). [https://www.jstor.org/stable/283876 &quot;Some Reflections on the Battle of Pharsalus&quot;], ''Transactions and Proceedings of the American Philological Association'', Vol. 87.
* James, Steven (2016). [https://www.academia.edu/19860273/48_BC_The_Battle_of_Pharsalus, &quot;48 BC: The Battle of Pharsalus&quot;]. Non-peer-reviewed publication.
* Holmes, T. Rice (1908). [https://www.jstor.org/stable/636174 &quot;The Battle-Field of Old Pharsalvs&quot;] (The Battle-Field of Old Pharsalus). ''The Classical Quarterly'', Vol. 2, No. 4 (Oct., 1908), pp. 271-292.
* Lucas, Frank Laurence (1921). [https://www.jstor.org/stable/30102514?seq=1  &quot;The Battlefield of Pharsalos&quot;], ''Annual of the British School at Athens'', No. XXIV, 1919–21.
* Morgan, John D. (1983). [https://www.jstor.org/stable/504663?seq=1 &quot;Palae-pharsalus – the Battle and the Town&quot;], ''The American Journal of Archaeology'', Vol. 87, No. 1, Jan. 1983.
* Nordling, John G. (2006). [https://www.jstor.org/stable/30038647 &quot;Caesar's Pre-Battle Speech at Pharsalus (B.C. 3.85.4): ''Ridiculum Acri Fortius ... Secat Res''&quot;]. ''The Classical Journal'', Vol. 101, No. 2 (Dec. - Jan., 2005/2006), pp. 183-189.
* Pelling, C. B. R. (1973). [https://www.jstor.org/stable/4435333 &quot;Pharsalus&quot;]. ''Historia: Zeitschrift für Alte Geschichte''. Bd. 22, H. 2 (2nd Qtr., 1973), pp. 249-259.
* Perrin, B. (1885). [https://www.jstor.org/stable/287135 &quot;Pharsalia, Pharsalus, Palaepharsalus&quot;]. ''The American Journal of Philology'', Vol. 6, No. 2 (1885), pp. 170-189.
* Postgate, J. P. (1905). [https://www.jstor.org/stable/696412 &quot;Pharsalia Nostra&quot;]. ''The Classical Review'', Vol. 19, No. 5 (Jun., 1905), pp. 257-260.
* Rambaud, Michel (1955). [https://www.jstor.org/stable/4434412 &quot;Le Soleil de Pharsale&quot;], ''Historia: Zeitschrift für Alte Geschichte '', Vol.3, No.4.
* Searle, Arthur (1907). [https://www.jstor.org/stable/310555 &quot;Note on the Battle of Pharsalus&quot;]. ''Harvard Studies in Classical Philology'', Vol. 18 (1907), pp. 213-218.
* Wylie, Graham (1992). [https://www.jstor.org/stable/41541372 &quot;The Road to Pharsalus&quot;]. ''Latomus'', T. 51, Fasc. 3 (Juillet-Septembre 1992), pp. 557-565.

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Battle of Pharsalus}}
* [http://www.livius.org/pha-phd/pharsalus/battle.html Caesar's account of the battle]

{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Pharsalus, Battle of}}
[[Category:48 BC]]
[[Category:40s BC conflicts]]
[[Category:1st-century BC battles]]
[[Category:1st century BC in Greece]]
[[Category:Battles in ancient Thessaly|Pharsalus]]
[[Category:Battles involving the Roman Republic|Pharsalus]]
[[Category:Battles of Caesar's Civil War]]
[[Category:Roman civil wars]]
[[Category:Roman Macedonia]]</text>
      <sha1>0rh1p64hnuvflaythfqwoic1t9abbvc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
