  <page>
    <title>Puzzle Bobble</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4098</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942938659</id>
      <parentid>942937522</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T20:28:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MrOllie</username>
        <id>6908984</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 938451660 by [[Special:Contributions/192.162.141.171|192.162.141.171]] ([[User talk:192.162.141.171|talk]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Bust-a-Move|other uses|Bust a Move (disambiguation)}}
{{Infobox video game
 |title = Puzzle Bobble
 |image = Puzzle Bobble arcade flyer.jpg
 |developer ={{collapsible list|title=[[Taito]]|titlestyle=font-weight:normal;font-size:inherit;background:transparent;text-align:left|[[Microcabin]] &lt;small&gt;(3DO)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Santos &lt;small&gt;(Game Gear)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Kinesoft]] &lt;small&gt;(Windows)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Yoshidayama Workshop&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;(WonderSwan)&lt;/small&gt;}}
 |publisher ={{collapsible list|title=Taito|titlestyle=font-weight:normal;font-size:inherit;background:transparent;text-align:left|GiG Electronics &lt;small&gt;(Super NES)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[SNK]] &lt;small&gt;(Neo Geo CD)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Panasonic]] &lt;small&gt;(3DO)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Sega]] &lt;small&gt;(Game Gear)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;'''Windows'''{{vgrelease|JP|[[SB Creative|GameBank]]|NA|[[Interplay Productions]]|EU|[[Atari, Inc. (Atari, SA subsidiary)|GT Interactive Software]]|AU|[[Infogrames]]}} [[Sunsoft]] &lt;small&gt;(WonderSwan)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Hamster Corporation|HAMSTER Corporation]] &lt;small&gt;(PS4/Switch/Xbox One)&lt;/small&gt;}}
 |designer = Kazuhiro Kinoshita&lt;br /&gt;Seiichi Nakakuki
 |programmer = Yasuo Tsumori
 |composer = Kazuko Umino&lt;br /&gt;Yasuko Yamada
 |series = ''Puzzle Bobble''
 |platforms ={{collapsible list|title=[[Arcade game|Arcade]]|titlestyle=font-weight:normal;font-size:inherit;background:transparent;text-align:left|[[3DO Interactive Multiplayer]], [[Game Gear]], [[Microsoft Windows]], [[Neo Geo CD]], [[Neo Geo (system)|Neo Geo MVS]], [[Nintendo Switch]], [[PlayStation 4]], [[Super Nintendo Entertainment System]], [[WonderSwan]], [[Xbox One]]}}
 |released ={{collapsible list|title=1994|titlestyle=font-weight:normal;font-size:inherit;background:transparent;text-align:left|'''Arcade'''{{vgrelease|JP|June 1994&lt;ref name=&quot;ah&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.arcade-history.com/?n=puzzle-bobble&amp;page=detail&amp;id=21224|title=Puzzle Bobble|website=arcade-history.com|accessdate=2019-06-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} '''Neo Geo MVS'''{{vgrelease|WW|21 December 1994}} '''Super NES'''{{vgrelease|JP|13 January 1995|NA|March 1995|EU|1995}} '''Neo Geo CD'''{{vgrelease|EU|27 April 1995|JP|2 May 1995}} '''3DO'''{{vgrelease|JP|22 November 1995|NA|1995}} '''Game Gear'''{{vgrelease|JP|2 August 1996|NA|1996}} '''Windows'''{{vgrelease|NA|1999}} '''WonderSwan'''{{vgrelease|JP|1 July 1999}} '''Nintendo Switch'''{{vgrelease|WW|20 December 2018}} '''PlayStation 4'''{{vgrelease|JP|20 December 2018|NA|3 January 2019|EU|27 February 2020}} '''Xbox One'''{{vgrelease|WW|20 December 2018}}}}
 |genre = [[Puzzle video game|Puzzle]]
 |modes = [[Single-player video game|Single-player]], [[Multiplayer video game|multiplayer]]
 |cabinet = [[Arcade cabinet#Upright cabinets|Upright]]
 |arcade system = [[Taito B System]]
 |cpu = [[Motorola 68000|68000]] (@ 12 [[MHz]])
 |sound = Sound CPU:&lt;br /&gt;[[Zilog Z80|Z80]] (@ 4 MHz),&lt;br /&gt;[[Sound chip]]s:&lt;ref name=&quot;ah&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;s16&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.system16.com/hardware.php?id=660&amp;page=1#1643|title=Taito B System Hardware (Taito)|website=system16.com|accessdate=2019-06-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[YM2610B]] (@ 8 MHz), MB87078
 |display = [[Raster graphics|Raster]], 320 × 224 pixels (Horizontal), 4096 [[color]]s
}}

{{nihongo foot|'''''Puzzle Bobble'''''|パズルボブル|''Pazuru Boburu''}} (also known as '''''Bust-a-Move''''' in North America) is a 1994 [[Tile-matching video game|tile-matching]] [[Arcade game|arcade]] [[puzzle video game]] for one or two players created by [[Taito Corporation]]. It is based on Taito's popular 1986 arcade game ''[[Bubble Bobble]]'', featuring characters and themes from that game. Its characteristically [[Kawaii|cute]] [[Anime|Japanese animation]] and music, along with its play mechanics and level designs, made it successful as an arcade title and spawned several sequels and ports to home gaming systems.

The characters and theme of the game are based on the 1986 arcade game ''[[Bubble Bobble]]''. An arrangement of the original ''Bubble Bobble'' background music is played in the game's end credits.

==Gameplay==
[[File:ARC Puzzle Bobble (Bust-a-Move).png|thumb|left|Arcade version screenshot.]]
At the start of each round, the rectangular playing arena contains a prearranged pattern of colored &quot;bubbles&quot;. (These are actually referred to in the translation as &quot;balls&quot;; however, they were clearly intended to be bubbles, since they pop, and are taken from ''Bubble Bobble''.) At the bottom of the screen, the player controls a device called a &quot;pointer&quot;, which aims and fires bubbles up the screen. The color of bubbles fired is randomly generated and chosen from the colors of bubbles still left on the screen.

The fired bubbles travel in straight lines (possibly bouncing off the sidewalls of the arena), stopping when they touch other bubbles or reach the top of the arena. If a bubble touches identically-colored bubbles, forming a group of three or more, those bubbles—as well as any bubbles hanging from them—are removed from the field of play, and points are awarded.

After every few shots, the &quot;ceiling&quot; of the playing arena drops downwards slightly, along with all the bubbles stuck to it. The number of shots between each drop of the ceiling is influenced by the number of bubble colors remaining. The closer the bubbles get to the bottom of the screen, the faster the music plays and if they cross the line at the bottom then the game is over.

The objective of the game is to clear all the bubbles from the arena without any bubble crossing the bottom line. Bubbles will fire automatically if the player remains idle. After clearing the arena, the next round begins with a new pattern of bubbles to clear. The game consists of 32 levels.

==Release==
Two different versions of the original game were released. ''Puzzle Bobble'' was originally released in Japan only in June 1994 by Taito Corporation, running on Taito's [[Taito B System|B System]] hardware (with the preliminary title &quot;Bubble Buster&quot;). Then, 6 months later in December, the international Neo Geo version of ''Puzzle Bobble'' was released. It was almost identical aside from being in [[Stereophonic sound|stereo]] and having some different sound effects and translated text.

When set to the US region, the Neo Geo version displays the alternative title &quot;Bust a Move&quot; and features [[Winners Don't Use Drugs|anti-drugs]] and anti-littering messages in the title sequence. The Bust-a-Move title was used for all subsequent games in the series in the United States and Canada, as well as for some (non-Taito published) console releases in Europe.

===Scoring system===
As with many popular arcade games, experienced players (who can complete the game relatively easily) become much more interested in the secondary challenge of obtaining a high score (which involves a lot more skill and strategy). ''Puzzle Bobble'' caters to this interest very well, featuring an exponential scoring system that allows extremely high scores to be achieved.

&quot;Popped&quot; bubbles (that is, bubbles of the same color which disappear) are worth 10 points each. However, ''dropped'' bubbles (that is, bubbles that were hanging from popped bubbles), are worth far more: one dropped bubble scores 20 points; two scores 40; threescore 80. This figure continues doubling for each bubble dropped, up to 17 or more bubbles which scores 1,310,720 points. It is possible to achieve this maximum on most rounds (sometimes twice or more), resulting in a potential total score of 30 million and beyond.

Bonus points are also awarded for completing a round quickly. The maximum 50,000-point bonus is awarded for clearing a round in 5 seconds or less; this bonus then drops down to zero over the next minute, after which no bonus is awarded.

===Two player mode===
There are no rounds in the two-player game. Both players have an arena each (both visible on screen) and an identical arrangement of colored bubbles in each arena. When a player removes a large group (four bubbles or more) some of those removed are transferred to the opponent's arena, usually delaying their efforts to remove all the bubbles from their individual arena. In some versions, the two-player game can also be played by one player against a computer opponent.

==Reception==
{{Video game reviews
 | EGM = 7.8/10 &lt;small&gt;(SNES)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;EGM68&quot;/&gt;
 | NGen = {{rating|4|5}} &lt;small&gt;(SNES and 3DO)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NG5&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NGen14&quot;/&gt;
}}

Reviewing the Super NES version, Mike Weigand of ''[[Electronic Gaming Monthly]]'' called it &quot;a thoroughly enjoyable and incredibly addicting puzzle game&quot;. He considered the two player mode the highlight, but also said that the one player mode provides a solid challenge.&lt;ref name=&quot;EGM68&quot;&gt;{{cite magazine|last= |first= |title=Review Crew: Bust A Move|magazine=[[Electronic Gaming Monthly]]|issue=68|publisher=Sendai Publishing|date=March 1995|page=34}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[GamePro]]'' gave it a generally negative review, saying it &quot;starts out fun but ultimately lacks intricacy and longevity.&quot; They elaborated that in one player mode all the levels feel the same, and that two player matches are over too quickly to build up any excitement. They also criticized the lack of any 3D effects in the graphics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|last= |first= |title=ProReview: Bust-A-Move|magazine=[[GamePro]]|issue=69 |publisher=[[International Data Group|IDG]]|date=April 1995|page=68}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Next Generation (magazine)|Next Generation]]'' reviewed the SNES version of the game, and stated that &quot;It's very simple, using only the control pad and one button to fire, and it's addictive as hell.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;NG5&quot;&gt;{{cite magazine|last=|first=|title=Finals|magazine=[[Next Generation (magazine)|Next Generation]]|issue=5|publisher=[[Future US|Imagine Media]]|date=May 1995|page=101}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A reviewer for ''[[Next Generation (magazine)|Next Generation]]'', while questioning the continued viability of the action puzzle genre, admitted that the game is &quot;very simple and ''very'' addictive&quot;. He remarked that though the 3DO version makes no significant additions, none are called for by a game with such simple enjoyment.&lt;ref name=&quot;NGen14&quot;&gt;{{cite magazine|last= |first= |title=Bust a Move|magazine=[[Next Generation (magazine)|Next Generation]]|issue=14 |publisher=[[Imagine Media]] |date=February 1996|page=167}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''GamePro''{{'}}s brief review of the 3DO version commented, &quot;The move-and-shoot controls are very responsive and the simple visuals and music are well done. This is one puzzler that isn't a bust.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|last= |first= |title=Quick Hits: Bust-A-Move|magazine=[[GamePro]]|issue=93|publisher=[[International Data Group|IDG]]|date=March 1996|page=72}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Clones==
The simplicity of the concept has led to many clones, both commercial and otherwise. 1996's ''[[Snood (video game)|Snood]]'' replaced the bubbles with small creatures and has been successful in its own right. ''[[Worms Blast]]'' was Team 17's take on the concept. Mobile clones include ''Bubble Witch Saga'' and ''[[Bubble Shooter]]''. ''[[Frozen Bubble]]'' is a [[free software]] clone.

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*{{moby game|id=/bust-a-move__}}
*{{moby game|id=/bust-a-move|name=''Bust A-Move (Ports)''}}
* [https://www.giantbomb.com/bust-a-move/3030-14228/ ''Bust-a-Move''] at [[Giant Bomb]]
*{{KLOV game|9169}}

{{Bubble Bobble series}}
{{Portal bar|1990s|Japan|Video games}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Puzzle Bobble}}
[[Category:1994 video games]]
[[Category:3DO Interactive Multiplayer games]]
[[Category:ACA Neo Geo games]]
[[Category:Arcade games]]
[[Category:Square Enix franchises]]
[[Category:Bubble Bobble]]
[[Category:Head-to-head arcade games]]
[[Category:IOS games]]
[[Category:Kinesoft games]]
[[Category:Mobile games]]
[[Category:Multiplayer and single-player video games]]
[[Category:Neo Geo games]]
[[Category:Neo Geo CD games]]
[[Category:Puzzle video games]]
[[Category:Sega Game Gear games]]
[[Category:SNK games]]
[[Category:Split-screen multiplayer games]]
[[Category:Super Nintendo Entertainment System games]]
[[Category:Taito games]]
[[Category:Video games developed in Japan]]
[[Category:Video games scored by Tamayo Kawamoto]]
[[Category:Windows games]]
[[Category:WonderSwan games]]
[[Category:Xbox 360 Live Arcade games]]
[[Category:Taito arcade games]]</text>
      <sha1>k0v134tr4y7158n1r33t4bjk15u273j</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
