  <page>
    <title>BCG vaccine</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4191</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942879146</id>
      <parentid>942879072</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T12:37:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GameEnd</username>
        <id>36083290</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 942879072 by [[Special:Contributions/2409:4051:200A:6E1C:3E9C:922B:EDE:9990|2409:4051:200A:6E1C:3E9C:922B:EDE:9990]] ([[User talk:2409:4051:200A:6E1C:3E9C:922B:EDE:9990|talk]]) (reverting</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Drugbox
| image = Mycobacterium bovis BCG ZN.jpg
| caption = Microscopic image of the Calmette-Guérin bacillus, [[Ziehl–Neelsen stain]],  magnification:1,000nn
&lt;!-- Vaccine data --&gt;
| type = vaccine
| target = [[Tuberculosis]]
| vaccine_type = live
&lt;!-- Clinical data --&gt;
| Drugs.com = {{drugs.com|pro|bcg-vaccine}}
| pregnancy_AU = &lt;!-- A / B1 / B2 / B3 / C / D / X --&gt;
| pregnancy_US = C
| pregnancy_category = 
| legal_AU = &lt;!-- S2, S3, S4, S5, S6, S7, S8, S9 or Unscheduled --&gt;
| legal_CA = &lt;!-- Schedule I, II, III, IV, V, VI, VII, VIII --&gt;
| legal_UK = &lt;!-- GSL, P, POM, CD, or Class A, B, C --&gt;
| legal_US = Rx-only
| legal_status = 
| routes_of_administration = Percutaneous
&lt;!-- Identifiers --&gt;
| CAS_number = 
| ATC_prefix = J07
| ATC_suffix = AN01
| PubChem = 
| DrugBank = DB12768
| ChemSpiderID = none
}}
&lt;!-- Definition and medical uses --&gt;
'''Bacillus Calmette–Guérin''' ('''BCG''') '''vaccine''' is a [[vaccine]] primarily used against [[tuberculosis]] (TB).&lt;ref name=WHO2018&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = ((World Health Organization)) | title = BCG vaccines: WHO position paper – February 2018 | journal = Weekly Epidemiological Record | date = February 2018 | volume = 93 | issue = 8 | pages = 73–96 | pmid = 29474026 | hdl = 10665/260307 | author-link = World Health Organization | lay-url = https://www.who.int/immunization/policy/position_papers/PP_BCG_summary_2018.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt; In countries where tuberculosis or [[leprosy]] is common, one dose is recommended in healthy babies as close to the time of birth as possible.&lt;ref name=WHO2018/&gt; In areas where tuberculosis is not common, only children at high risk are typically immunized, while suspected cases of tuberculosis are individually tested for and treated.&lt;ref name=WHO2018/&gt; Adults who do not have tuberculosis and have not been previously immunized but are frequently exposed may be immunized as well.&lt;ref name=WHO2018/&gt; BCG also has some effectiveness against [[Buruli ulcer]] infection and other [[nontuberculous mycobacteria]] infections.&lt;ref name=WHO2018 /&gt; Additionally it is sometimes used as part of the treatment of [[bladder cancer]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Green |first1=James |last2=Fuge |first2=Oliver |last3=Allchorne |first3=Paula |last4=Vasdev |first4=Nikhil |title=Immunotherapy for bladder cancer |journal=Research and Reports in Urology |volume=7 |date=May 2015 |pages=65–79 |pmid=26000263 |pmc=4427258 |doi=10.2147/RRU.S63447 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Houghton |first1=Baerin B. |last2=Chalasani |first2=Venu |last3=Hayne |first3=Dickon |last4=Grimison |first4=Peter |last5=Brown |first5=Christopher S. B. |last6=Patel |first6=Manish I. |last7=Davis |first7=Ian D. |last8=Stockler |first8=Martin R. |title=Intravesical chemotherapy plus bacille Calmette-Guérin in non-muscle invasive bladder cancer: a systematic review with meta-analysis |journal=BJU International |date=May 2013 |volume=111 |issue=6 |pages=977–83 |pmid=23253618 |doi=10.1111/j.1464-410X.2012.11390.x }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Effectiveness and administration --&gt;
Rates of protection against tuberculosis infection vary widely and protection lasts up to twenty years.&lt;ref name=WHO2018 /&gt; Among children it prevents about 20% from getting infected and among those who do get infected it protects half from developing disease.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Roy|first1=A|last2=Eisenhut|first2=M|last3=Harris|first3=RJ|last4=Rodrigues|first4=LC|last5=Sridhar|first5=S|last6=Habermann|first6=S|last7=Snell|first7=L|last8=Mangtani|first8=P|last9=Adetifa|first9=I|last10=Lalvani|first10=A|last11=Abubakar|first11=I|title=Effect of BCG vaccination against Mycobacterium tuberculosis infection in children: systematic review and meta-analysis.|journal=BMJ |date=5 August 2014|volume=349|pages=g4643|pmid=25097193|doi=10.1136/bmj.g4643|pmc=4122754}}&lt;/ref&gt; The vaccine is given by injection into the [[skin]].&lt;ref name=WHO2018 /&gt; Additional doses are not supported by evidence.&lt;ref name=WHO2018 /&gt;

&lt;!-- Safety and manufacture--&gt;
Serious side effects are rare. Often there is redness, swelling, and mild pain at the site of injection.&lt;ref name=WHO2018 /&gt; A small [[ulcer]] may also form with some scarring after healing.&lt;ref name=WHO2018 /&gt; Side effects are more common and potentially more severe in those with [[immunosuppressed|poor immune function]].&lt;ref name=WHO2018 /&gt; It is not safe for use during [[pregnancy]].&lt;ref name=WHO2018 /&gt; The vaccine was originally developed from ''[[Mycobacterium bovis]]'' which is commonly found in cows.&lt;ref name=WHO2018 /&gt; While it has been weakened, it is still [[live vaccine|live]].&lt;ref name=WHO2018 /&gt;

&lt;!-- History, society and culture --&gt;
The BCG vaccine was first used medically in 1921.&lt;ref name=WHO2018 /&gt; It is on the [[World Health Organization's List of Essential Medicines]], the safest and most effective medicines needed in a [[health system]].&lt;ref name=&quot;WHO21st&quot;&gt;{{cite book | vauthors = ((World Health Organization)) | title = World Health Organization model list of essential medicines: 21st list 2019 | year = 2019 | hdl = 10665/325771 | author-link = World Health Organization | publisher = World Health Organization | location = Geneva | id = WHO/MVP/EMP/IAU/2019.06. License: CC BY-NC-SA 3.0 IGO }}&lt;/ref&gt; Between 2011 and 2014 the wholesale price was US$0.16 to US$1.11 a dose in the [[developing world]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Vaccine, Bcg|url=http://mshpriceguide.org/en/single-drug-information/?DMFId=788&amp;searchYear=2014|website=International Drug Price Indicator Guide|accessdate=6 December 2015}}{{dead link|date=September 2017 |bot=Level C |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Vaccine, Bcg|url=http://mshpriceguide.org/en/single-drug-information/?DMFId=788&amp;searchYear=2014|website=ERC|accessdate=13 June 2016|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20180122071918/http://mshpriceguide.org/en/single-drug-information/?DMFId=788&amp;searchYear=2014|archivedate=22 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States it costs US$100 to US$200.&lt;ref name=Ric2015&gt;{{cite book|last1=Hamilton|first1=Richart|title=Tarascon Pocket Pharmacopoeia 2015 Deluxe Lab-Coat Edition|date=2015|publisher=Jones &amp; Bartlett Learning|isbn=9781284057560|page=312}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2004 the vaccine is given to about 100 million children per year globally.&lt;ref name=WHO2004&gt;{{cite journal|date=Jan 23, 2004|title=BCG Vaccine: WHO position paper|url=http://www.who.int/wer/2004/en/wer7904.pdf|journal=Weekly Epidemiological Record|volume=4|issue=79|pages=25–40|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150921165240/http://www.who.int/wer/2004/en/wer7904.pdf|archivedate=2015-09-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{TOC limit}}

==Medical uses==

===Tuberculosis===
{{see also|Tuberculosis vaccines}}

The main use of BCG is for vaccination against [[tuberculosis]]. BCG vaccine can be administered after birth intradermally.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tbsymptoms.net/2013/03/bcg-vaccin/ |title=BCG Vaccine &amp;#124; TB Symptoms &amp;#124; Tuberculin Skin Test &amp;#124; PPD &amp;#124; TB Signs |publisher=TB Symptoms |date=2013-01-18 |accessdate=2014-02-02 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131029204615/http://tbsymptoms.net/2013/03/bcg-vaccin/ |archivedate=2013-10-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  BCG vaccination can cause a [[false positive]] [[Mantoux test]], although a very high-grade reading is usually due to active disease.

The most controversial aspect of BCG is the variable efficacy found in different clinical trials, which appears to depend on geography.  Trials conducted in the UK have consistently shown a protective effect of 60 to 80%, but those conducted elsewhere have shown no protective effect, and efficacy appears to fall the closer one gets to the equator.&lt;ref name=Colditz/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Fine PEM|title=Variation in protection by BCG: implications of and for heterologous immunity|journal=Lancet|year=1995|volume=346|issue=8986|pages=1339–45|doi=10.1016/S0140-6736(95)92348-9|pmid=7475776}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 1994 systematic review found that BCG reduces the risk of getting TB by about 50%.&lt;ref name=Colditz&gt;{{cite journal | doi=10.1001/jama.1994.03510330076038 | title=Efficacy of BCG Vaccine in the Prevention of Tuberculosis | year=1994 | last1=Colditz | first1=Graham A. | journal=JAMA | volume=271 | issue=9 | pages=698–702 | pmid=8309034 | last2=Brewer | first2=TF | last3=Berkey | first3=CS | last4=Wilson | first4=ME | last5=Burdick | first5=E | last6=Fineberg | first6=HV | last7=Mosteller | first7=F}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are differences in effectiveness, depending on region, due to factors such as genetic differences in the populations, changes in environment, exposure to other bacterial infections, and conditions in the lab where the vaccine is grown, including genetic differences between the strains being cultured and the choice of growth medium.&lt;ref name=&quot;Venkataswamy&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Fine&gt;{{cite journal|last=FINE|first=P|title=Variation in protection by BCG: implications of and for heterologous immunity|journal=The Lancet|date=1 November 1995|volume=346|issue=8986|pages=1339–1345|doi=10.1016/S0140-6736(95)92348-9|pmid=7475776}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A systematic review and meta analysis conducted in 2014 demonstrated that the BCG vaccine reduced infections by 19–27% and reduced progression to active TB by 71%.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid25097193&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Roy A, Eisenhut M, Harris RJ, Rodrigues LC, Sridhar S, Habermann S, Snell L, Mangtani P, Adetifa I, Lalvani A, Abubakar I |title=Effect of BCG vaccination against Mycobacterium tuberculosis infection in children: systematic review and meta-analysis |journal=BMJ |volume=349 |issue= |pages=g4643 |year=2014 |pmid=25097193 |pmc=4122754 |doi= 10.1136/bmj.g4643|url=|display-authors=3}}&lt;/ref&gt; The studies included in this review were limited to those that used [[interferon gamma release assay]].

The duration of protection of BCG is not clearly known. In those studies showing a protective effect, the data are inconsistent. The MRC study showed protection waned to 59% after 15 years and to zero after 20 years; however, a study looking at Native Americans immunized in the 1930s found evidence of protection even 60 years after immunization, with only a slight waning in efficacy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Aronson NE, Santosham M, Comstock GW | title=Long-term efficacy of BCG vaccine in American Indians and Alaska Natives: A 60-year follow-up study | journal=JAMA | year=2004 | volume=291 | issue=17 | pages=2086–91 | pmid=15126436 | doi=10.1001/jama.291.17.2086 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

BCG seems to have its greatest effect in preventing [[Miliary tuberculosis|miliary TB]] or TB meningitis, so it is still extensively used even in countries where efficacy against pulmonary tuberculosis is negligible.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Rodrigues LC, Diwan VK, Wheeler JG | title=Protective Effect of BCG against Tuberculous Meningitis and Miliary Tuberculosis: A Meta-Analysis | journal=Int J Epidemiol | year=1993 | volume=22 | pages=1154–8 | doi=10.1093/ije/22.6.1154 | pmid=8144299 | issue=6 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Reasons====
A number of possible reasons for the variable efficacy of BCG in different countries have been proposed. None have been proven, some have been disproved, and none can explain the lack of efficacy in both low-TB burden countries (US) and high-TB burden countries (India). The reasons for variable efficacy have been discussed at length in a [[World Health Organization]] (WHO) document on BCG.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | vauthors = Fine PE, Carneiro IA, Milstein JB, Clements CJ | chapter = Chapter 8: Reasons for variable efficacy | title = Issues relating to the use of BCG in immunization programmes | chapter-url = http://whqlibdoc.who.int/hq/1999/WHO_V&amp;B_99.23.pdf | year = 1999 | publisher = World Health Organization | location = Geneva, Switzerland | url-status = live | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20110220232037/http://whqlibdoc.who.int/hq/1999/WHO_V%26B_99.23.pdf | archivedate = 2011-02-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
#Genetic variation in BCG strains:  Genetic variation in the BCG strains used may explain the variable efficacy reported in different trials.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Brosch R, Gordon SV, Garnier T, Eiglmeier K | title=Genome plasticity of BCG and impact on vaccine efficacy | year=2007 | journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | doi=10.1073/pnas.0700869104 | volume=104 | pages=5596–601 | pmid=17372194 | issue=13 | pmc=1838518 | bibcode=2007PNAS..104.5596B }}&lt;/ref&gt;
#Genetic variation in populations:  Differences in genetic make-up of different populations may explain the difference in efficacy.  The Birmingham BCG trial was published in 1988.  The trial, based in [[Birmingham]], United Kingdom, examined children born to families who originated from the Indian Subcontinent (where vaccine efficacy had previously been shown to be zero).  The trial showed a 64% protective effect, which is very similar to the figure derived from other UK trials, thus arguing against the genetic variation hypothesis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors=Packe GE, Innes JA | title=Protective effect of BCG vaccination in infant Asians: a case-control study | volume=63 | pages=277–281 | year=1988 | pmid=3258499 | doi=10.1136/adc.63.3.277 | journal=Archives of Disease in Childhood | issue=3 | pmc=1778792 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
#Interference by nontuberculous mycobacteria: Exposure to environmental mycobacteria (especially ''M. avium'', ''M. marinum'' and ''M. intracellulare'') results in a nonspecific immune response against mycobacteria.  Administering BCG to someone who already has a nonspecific immune response against mycobacteria does not augment the response already there.  BCG will therefore appear not to be efficacious, because that person already has a level of immunity and BCG is not adding to that immunity.  This effect is called masking, because the effect of BCG is masked by environmental mycobacteria.  Clinical evidence for this effect was found in a series of studies performed in parallel in adolescent school children in the UK and Malawi.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Black GF, Weir RE, Floyd S | title=BCG-induced increase in interferon-gamma response to mycobacterial antigens and efficacy of BCG vaccination in Malai and the UK: two randomized controlled studies | journal=Lancet | volume=359 | issue=9315 | pages=1393–401 | doi=10.1016/S0140-6736(02)08353-8 | year=2002 | pmid=11978337 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  In this study, the UK school children had a low baseline cellular immunity to mycobacteria which was increased by BCG; in contrast, the Malawi school children had a high baseline cellular immunity to mycobacteria and this was not significantly increased by BCG.  Whether this natural immune response is protective is not known.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | title=Effects of infection with atypical mycobacteria on BCG vaccination and tuberculosis | journal=Am Rev Respir Dis | year=1966 | pages=553–68 |vauthors=Palmer CE, Long MW }}&lt;/ref&gt;  An alternative explanation is suggested by mouse studies; immunity against mycobacteria stops BCG from replicating and so stops it from producing an immune response.  This is called the block hypothesis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Brandt L, Feino Cunha J, Weinreich Olsen A | title=Failure of ''Mycobacterium bovis'' BCG vaccine: some species of environmental mycobacteria block multiplication of BCG and induction of protective immunity to tuberculosis | journal=Infection and Immunity | year=2002 | volume=70 | pages=672–78 | doi=10.1128/IAI.70.2.672-678.2002 | pmid=11796598 | issue=2 | pmc=127715 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
#Interference by concurrent parasitic infection: In another hypothesis, simultaneous infection with parasites changes the immune response to BCG, making it less effective.  As  [[T helper cell|Th1]] response is required for an effective immune response to tuberculous infection, concurrent infection with various parasites produces a simultaneous Th2 response, which blunts the effect of BCG.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Rook GAW | author2=Dheda K | author3=Zumla A. | authorlink3=Alimuddin Zumla | title=Do successful tuberculosis vaccines need to be immunoregulatory rather than merely Th1-boosting? | journal=Vaccine | volume=23 | issue=17–18 | year=2005 | pages=2115–20 | doi=10.1016/j.vaccine.2005.01.069 | pmid=15755581 | url=http://discovery.ucl.ac.uk/295/1/Rook_VACCINE_paper.pdf | url-status=live | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170922153759/http://discovery.ucl.ac.uk/295/1/Rook_VACCINE_paper.pdf | archivedate=2017-09-22 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Mycobacteria ===
BCG has protective effects against some non-tuberculosis mycobacteria.
*Leprosy:  BCG has a protective effect against leprosy in the range of 20 to 80%.&lt;ref name=WHO2018 /&gt; 
*[[Mycobacterium ulcerans|Buruli ulcer]]: BCG may protect against or delay the onset of Buruli ulcer.&lt;ref name=WHO2018 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Tanghe, A. |author2=J. Content |author3=J. P. Van Vooren|author4= F. Portaels |author5= K. Huygen|year=2001|title=Protective efficacy of a DNA vaccine encoding antigen 85A from Mycobacterium bovis BCG against Buruli ulcer | doi = 10.1128/IAI.69.9.5403-5411.2001|journal=Infection and Immunity|volume=69|pmc=98650|issue=9|pages=5403–11|pmid=11500410}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Cancer ===
{{see also|Cancer immunotherapy|Cancer vaccine|Coley's toxins}}
[[Image:Granulomatous inflammation of bladder neck.jpg|thumb|right|[[Micrograph]] showing [[granuloma]]tous [[inflammation]] of bladder neck tissue due to Bacillus Calmette-Guérin used to treat [[bladder cancer]], [[H&amp;E stain]]]]

BCG has been one of the most successful immunotherapies.&lt;ref name=&quot;BDG_2016&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |title=Bacillus Calmette-Guérin Strain Differences Have an Impact on Clinical Outcome in Bladder Cancer Immunotherapy  |first1=Cyrill A. |last1=Rentsch |first2=Frédéric D. |last2=Birkhäuser |first3=Claire |last3=Biot |first4=Joël R. |last4=Gsponer |first5=Aurélie |last5=Bisiaux |first6=Christian |last6=Wetterauer |first7= Micheline |last7=Lagranderie |first8=Gilles |last8=Marchal |first9=Mickael |last9=Orgeur |first10=Christiane |last10=Bouchier |first11= Alexander |last11=Bachmann |first12= Molly A. |last12=Ingersoll |first13= Roland |last13=Brosch |first14=Matthew L. |last14=Albert |first15=George N. |last15=Thalmann |journal=European Urology |volume=66 |number=4 |pages=677–688 |date=1 October 2014 |doi=10.1016/j.eururo.2014.02.061|pmid=24674149 }}&lt;!--|accessdate=29 January 2016 --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; BCG vaccine has been the &quot;standard of care for patients with bladder cancer (NMIBC)&quot; since 1977.&lt;ref name=&quot;BDG_2016&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BCG_success_2007&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |first1= S. |last1=Brandau |first2=H. |last2=Suttmann |title=Thirty years of BCG immunotherapy for non-muscle invasive bladder cancer: a success story with room for improvement |journal=Biomed Pharmacother |date=2007 |volume=61 |issue=6 |pages=299–305 |doi=10.1016/j.biopha.2007.05.004|pmid=17604943 }}&lt;!--|accessdate=29 January 2016 --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; By 2014 there were more than eight different considered biosimilar agents or strains used for the treatment of non–muscle-invasive bladder cancer (NMIBC).&lt;ref name=&quot;BDG_2016&quot; /&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;BCG_success_2007&quot; /&gt;

*A number of [[cancer vaccine]]s use BCG as an additive to provide an initial stimulation of the person's immune systems.
*BCG is [[BCG as a treatment for bladder cancer|used in the treatment]] of superficial forms of bladder cancer. Since the late 1970s, evidence has become available that instillation of BCG into the bladder is an effective form of [[immunotherapy]] in this disease.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | doi=10.1056/NEJM199110243251703 |vauthors=Lamm DL, Blumenstein BA, Crawford ED | title=A randomized trial of intravesical doxorubicin and immunotherapy with bacille Calmette-Guerin for transitional-cell carcinoma of the bladder | journal=N Engl J Med | year=1991 | volume=325 | pages=1205–9 | pmid=1922207 | issue=2 }}&lt;/ref&gt; While the mechanism is unclear, it appears a local immune reaction is mounted against the tumor. Immunotherapy with BCG prevents recurrence in up to 67% of cases of superficial bladder cancer.
* BCG has been evaluated in a number of studies as a therapy for [[colorectal cancer]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Mosolits S, Nilsson B, Mellstedt H | title=Towards therapeutic vaccines for colorectal carcinoma: a review of clinical trials | journal=Expert Rev Vaccines | year=2005 | volume=4 | pages=329–50 | pmid=16026248 | doi=10.1586/14760584.4.3.329 | issue=3 | title-link=therapeutic vaccine }}&lt;/ref&gt; The US biotech company [[Vaccinogen]] is evaluating BCG as an adjuvant to autologous tumour cells used as a cancer vaccine in stage II [[colon cancer]].

===Method of administration===
[[Image:BCG apparatus ja2.jpg|thumb|An apparatus (4–5 cm length, with 9 short needles) used for BCG vaccination in Japan, shown with ampules of BCG and saline]]
Except in neonates, a [[tuberculin skin test]] should always be done before administering BCG.  A reactive tuberculin skin test is a contraindication to BCG.  Someone with a positive tuberculin reaction is not given BCG, because the risk of severe local inflammation and scarring is high, not because of the common misconception that tuberculin reactors &quot;are already immune&quot; and therefore do not need BCG.  People found to have reactive tuberculin skin tests should be screened for active tuberculosis. BCG is also contraindicated in certain people  who have IL-12 receptor pathway defects.

BCG is given as a single [[intradermal]] injection at the insertion of the [[Deltoid muscle|deltoid]].  If BCG is accidentally given [[Subcutaneous injection|subcutaneous]]ly, then a local abscess may form (a &quot;BCG-oma&quot;) that can sometimes ulcerate, and may require treatment with antibiotics immediately, otherwise without treatment it could spread the infection causing severe damage to vital organs. An abscess is not always associated with incorrect administration, and it is one of the more common complications that can occur with the vaccination. Numerous medical studies on treatment of these abscesses with antibiotics have been done with varying results, but the consensus is once pus is aspirated and analysed, provided no unusual bacilli are present, the abscess will generally heal on its own in a matter of weeks.&lt;ref&gt;Nick Makwana and Andrew Riordan (2004), &quot;Is medical therapy effective in the treatment of BCG abscesses?&quot;, Birmingham Heartlands Hospital {{cite web |url=http://www.bestbets.org/cgi-bin/bets.pl?record=00797 |title=BestBets: Is medical therapy effective in the treatment of BCG abscesses? |accessdate=2007-04-01 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070216053220/http://www.bestbets.org/cgi-bin/bets.pl?record=00797 |archivedate=2007-02-16 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The characteristic raised scar that BCG immunization leaves is often used as proof of prior immunization. This scar must be distinguished from that of [[smallpox vaccination]], which it may resemble.

==Adverse effects==
BCG immunization generally causes some pain and scarring at the site of injection.  The main adverse effects are [[keloid]]s&amp;mdash;large, raised scars.  The insertion of deltoid is most frequently used because the local complication rate is smallest when that site is used. Nonetheless, the buttock is an alternative site of administration because it provides better cosmetic outcomes.

BCG vaccine should be given intradermally. If given subcutaneously, it may induce local infection and spread to the regional lymph nodes, causing either suppurative and nonsuppurative lymphadenitis. Conservative management is usually adequate for nonsuppurative lymphadenitis. If suppuration occurs, it may need needle aspiration. For nonresolving suppuration, surgical excision may be required. Evidence for the treatment of these complications is scarce.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Treating BCG-induced disease in children|journal = The Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews|date = 2013-01-01|issn = 1469-493X|pmid = 23440826|pages = CD008300|volume = 1|issue = 1|doi = 10.1002/14651858.CD008300.pub2|first = Carlos A.|last = Cuello-García|first2 = Giordano|last2 = Pérez-Gaxiola|first3 = Carlos|last3 = Jiménez Gutiérrez|pmc = 6532703}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Uncommonly, breast and gluteal abscesses can occur due to haematogenous and lymphangiomatous spread. Regional bone infection (BCG osteomyelitis or osteitis) and disseminated BCG infection are rare complications of BCG vaccination, but potentially life-threatening. Systemic antituberculous therapy may be helpful in severe complications.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Govindarajan KK, Chai FY | title=BCG adenitis — need for increased awareness | journal=Malaysian Journal of Medical Sciences | year=2011 | volume=18 | issue=2 | pages=67–70| pmid=22135589 }} [http://www.mjms.usm.my/default.asp?tag=14&amp;kod_volume=48 Malaysian Journal of Medical Sciences] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120326140134/http://www.mjms.usm.my/default.asp?tag=14&amp;kod_volume=48 |date=2012-03-26 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

If BCG is accidentally given to an immunocompromised patient (e.g., an infant with [[severe combined immune deficiency|SCID]]), it can cause disseminated or life-threatening infection.  The documented incidence of this happening is less than one per million immunizations given.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Centers for Disease Control and Prevention | title=The role of BCG vaccine in the prevention and control of tuberculosis in the United States: a joint statement of the Advisory Council for the Elimination of Tuberculosis and the Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices | journal=MMWR Recomm Rep | year=1996 | volume=45 | issue=RR-4 | pages=1–18 | pmid=8602127 | url=https://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/PDF/rr/rr4504.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2007, The [[World Health Organization]] (WHO) stopped recommending BCG for infants with [[Human immunodeficiency virus|HIV]], even if there is a high risk of exposure to TB,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|vauthors=((World Health Organization))|title=Revised BCG vaccination guidelines for infants at risk for HIV infection|journal=Weekly Epidemiological Record|year=2007|volume=82|pages=193–6|pmid=17526121|issue=21|hdl=10665/240940 }}&lt;/ref&gt; because of the risk of disseminated BCG infection (which is approximately 400 per 100,000 in that higher risk context).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|vauthors=Trunz BB, Fine P, Dye C |title=Effect of BCG vaccination on childhood tuberculous meningitis and miliary tuberculosis worldwide: a meta-analysis and assessment of cost-effectiveness|journal=Lancet|year=2006|volume=367|issue=9517|pages=1173–80|doi=10.1016/S0140-6736(06)68507-3|pmid=16616560}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|vauthors=Mak TK, Hesseling AC, Hussey GD, Cotton MF |title=Making BCG vaccination programs safer in the HIV era|journal=Lancet|year=2008|volume=372|issue=9641|pages=786–7|doi=10.1016/S0140-6736(08)61318-5|pmid=18774406}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Usage==
The age of the person and the frequency with which BCG is given has always varied from country to country.

*WHO BCG policy: The [[World Health Organization]] (WHO) recommends BCG be given to all children born in countries with a high incidence of TB and/or high leprosy burden.&lt;ref name=WHO2018 /&gt;
*Brazil: Brazil introduced universal BCG immunization in 1967–1968, and the practice continues until now. According to Brazilian law, BCG is given again to professionals of the health sector and to people close to patients with tuberculosis or [[leprosy]].
*Central and South America: Most countries in Central and South America have universal BCG immunizations. In Ecuador, a child cannot receive their birth certificate without having the BCG vaccine in their medical record along with other vaccinations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.siise.gob.ec/siiseweb/PageWebs/SALUD/ficsal_S21.htm |title=Ficha metodológica |accessdate=2015-03-12 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150402152751/http://www.siise.gob.ec/siiseweb/PageWebs/SALUD/ficsal_S21.htm |archivedate=2015-04-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*France: The BCG was mandatory for school children between 1950 and 2007,&lt;ref&gt;Loi n° 50-7 du 5 janvier 1950&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;décret n° 2007-1111 du 17 juillet 2007&lt;/ref&gt; and for healthcare professionals between 1947 and 2010. Vaccination is still available for French healthcare professionals and social workers but is now decided on a case by case basis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hcsp.fr/docspdf/avisrapports/hcspa20100305_BCG.pdf |title=relatif à l'obligation de vaccination par le BCG des professionnels listés aux articles L |accessdate=2014-02-02 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120730010610/http://www.hcsp.fr/docspdf/avisrapports/hcspa20100305_BCG.pdf |archivedate=2012-07-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Hong Kong: BCG is given to all newborns.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.fhs.gov.hk/english/main_ser/child_health/child_health_recommend.html|title=Child health - Immunisation|accessdate=2020-01-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*India and Pakistan:  India and Pakistan introduced BCG mass immunization in 1948, the first countries outside Europe to do so.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Mahler HT, Mohamed Ali P |title=Review of mass B.C.G. project in India |year=1955 |journal=Ind J Tuberculosis |volume=2 |issue=3 |pages=108–16 |url=http://openmed.nic.in/804/ |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070213202749/http://openmed.nic.in/804/ |archivedate=2007-02-13 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Japan: In Japan, BCG is administered between five and eight months after birth, and no later than a child's first birthday. BCG was administered no later than the fourth birthday until 2005, and no later than six months from birth from 2005 to 2012; the schedule was changed in 2012 due to reports of [[osteitis]] side effects from vaccinations at 3–4 months. Some municipalities recommend an earlier immunization schedule.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.mhlw.go.jp/seisakunitsuite/bunya/kenkou_iryou/kenkou/kekkaku-kansenshou/bcg/|title=結核とBCGワクチンに関するQ&amp;A｜厚生労働省|website=mhlw.go.jp|language=ja|access-date=2017-07-10|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170416183326/http://www.mhlw.go.jp/seisakunitsuite/bunya/kenkou_iryou/kenkou/kekkaku-kansenshou/bcg/|archivedate=2017-04-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Mongolia: All newborns are vaccinated with BCG. Previously, the vaccine was also given at ages 8 and 15, although this is no longer common practice.{{citation needed|date=October 2017}}
* Norway: In Norway the BCG vaccine was mandatory from 1947 to 1995. It is still available and recommended for high-risk groups.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.fhi.no/eway/default.aspx?pid=239&amp;trg=Content_6493&amp;Main_6157=6287:0:25,5501&amp;MainContent_6287=6493:0:25,6826&amp;Content_6493=6441:68710::0:6446:1:::0:0#eHandbook687100 {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160307230111/http://www.fhi.no/eway/default.aspx?pid=239&amp;trg=Content_6493&amp;Main_6157=6287%3A0%3A25%2C5501&amp;MainContent_6287=6493%3A0%3A25%2C6826&amp;Content_6493=6441%3A68710%3A%3A0%3A6446%3A1%3A%3A%3A0%3A0 |date=2016-03-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Philippines: BCG vaccine started in the Philippines in 1979 with the [[Expanded Program on Immunization (Philippines)|Expanded Program on Immunization]]
* South Africa: In South Africa, the BCG Vaccine is given routinely at birth, to all newborns, except those with clinically symptomatic AIDS. The vaccination site in the right shoulder.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.doh.gov.za/docs/programmes/2006/bcg.pdf ] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130511100236/http://www.doh.gov.za/docs/programmes/2006/bcg.pdf |date=May 11, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Sri Lanka: In Sri Lanka, The National Policy of Sri Lanka is to give BCG vaccination to all newborn babies immediately after birth. BCG vaccination is carried out under the Expanded Programme of Immunisation (EPI).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://203.94.76.60/TBWeb/web/PreventionofTB-1.html |website=The National Programme for TB Control &amp; Chest Diseases. |title=Role Of BC Vaccination |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130606083222/http://203.94.76.60/TBWeb/web/PreventionofTB-1.html |archivedate=2013-06-06 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Thailand: In Thailand, the BCG Vaccine is given routinely at birth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pidst.net/A385.html|website=Thai Pediatrics|title=Thai Pediatrics|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151119183506/http://www.pidst.net/A385.html|archivedate=2015-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*United Kingdom: The UK introduced universal BCG immunization in 1953, and until July 2005, the UK policy was to immunize all school children between 10 and 14 years of age, and all neonates born into high-risk groups. The injection was given only once during an individual's lifetime (as there is no evidence of additional protection from more than one vaccination). BCG was also given to protect people who had been exposed to tuberculosis.  The peak of tuberculosis incidence is in adolescence and early adulthood, and the MRC trial showed efficacy lasted a maximum of 15 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Styblo|first1=K|last2=Meijer|first2=J|title=Impact of BCG vaccination programmes in children and young adults on the tuberculosis problem.|journal=Tubercle|date=March 1976|volume=57|issue=1|pages=17–43|pmid=1085050|doi=10.1016/0041-3879(76)90015-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Routine immunization with BCG for all school children was scrapped in July 2005 because of falling cost-effectiveness: whereas in 1953, 94 children would have to be immunized to prevent one case of TB, by 1988, the annual incidence of TB in the UK had fallen so much, 12,000 children would have to be immunized to prevent one case of TB.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=School 'TB jabs' to be scrapped|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/health/4655355.stm|work=BBC News|accessdate=24 September 2014|date=July 2005|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120306040753/http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/health/4655355.stm|archivedate=6 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The vaccine is still given to certain healthcare professionals, however.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nhs.uk/conditions/vaccinations/pages/bcg-tuberculosis-tb-vaccine.aspx |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2016-03-27 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160401103926/http://www.nhs.uk/Conditions/vaccinations/Pages/bcg-tuberculosis-TB-vaccine.aspx |archivedate=2016-04-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*United States: The US has never used mass immunization of BCG, relying instead on the detection and treatment of [[latent tuberculosis]].
*Other countries: In some countries, such as the former [[Soviet Union]], BCG was given regularly throughout life.  In [[South Korea]], [[Singapore]], [[Taiwan]] and [[Malaysia]], BCG was given at birth and again at age 12. But in Malaysia and Singapore, from 2001, this policy was changed to once only at birth. South Korea also stopped the re-vaccination in 2008.  In the Canadian province of Quebec, the BCG vaccine was provided to children until the early 1960s.

==Manufacturer==
BCG is prepared from a strain of the attenuated ([[virulence]]-reduced) live bovine tuberculosis bacillus, ''[[Mycobacterium bovis]]'', that has lost its ability to cause disease in humans. Because the living bacilli evolve to make the best use of available nutrients, they become less well-adapted to human blood and can no longer induce disease when introduced into a human host.  Still, they are similar enough to their wild ancestors to provide some degree of immunity against human tuberculosis.  The BCG vaccine can be anywhere from 0 to 80% effective in preventing tuberculosis for a duration of 15 years; however, its protective effect appears to vary according to geography and the lab in which the vaccine strain was grown.&lt;ref name=&quot;Venkataswamy&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Venkataswamy |first=Manjunatha M. |last2=Goldberg |first2=Michael F. |last3=Baena |first3=Andres |last4=Chan |first4=John |last5=Jacobs |first5=William R., Jr. |last6=Porcelli |first6=Steven A. |date=1 February 2012 |title=''In vitro'' culture medium influences the vaccine efficacy of ''Mycobacterium bovis'' BCG |journal=Vaccine |volume=30 |issue=6 |pages=1038–1049 |pmc=3269512 |accessdate=|doi=10.1016/j.vaccine.2011.12.044 |pmid=22189700 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A number of different companies make BCG, sometimes using different genetic strains of the bacterium. This may result in different product characteristics. OncoTICE, used for bladder instillation for bladder cancer, was developed by Organon Laboratories (since acquired by Schering-Plough,  and in turn acquired by [[Merck &amp; Co.]]). Pacis BCG, made from the Montréal (Institut Armand-Frappier) strain,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rxmed.com/b.main/b2.pharmaceutical/b2.1.monographs/CPS-%20Monographs/CPS-%20%28General%20Monographs-%20P%29/PACIS.html |title=Pharmaceutical Information - PACIS |publisher=RxMed |accessdate=2014-02-02 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140222020626/http://www.rxmed.com/b.main/b2.pharmaceutical/b2.1.monographs/CPS-%20Monographs/CPS-%20%28General%20Monographs-%20P%29/PACIS.html |archivedate=2014-02-22 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  was first marketed by Urocor in about 2002.  Urocor was since acquired by Dianon Systems. Evans Vaccines (a subsidiary of PowderJect Pharmaceuticals). [[Statens Serum Institut]] in Denmark markets BCG vaccine prepared using Danish strain 1331.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ssi.dk/English/Vaccines/BCG%20Vaccine%20Danish%20Strain%201331.aspx |title=BCG Vaccine Danish Strain 1331 - Statens Serum Institut |publisher=Ssi.dk |date=2013-09-19 |accessdate=2014-02-02 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140218233417/http://www.ssi.dk/English/Vaccines/BCG%20Vaccine%20Danish%20Strain%201331.aspx |archivedate=2014-02-18 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Japan BCG Laboratory markets its vaccine, based on the Tokyo 172 substrain of Pasteur BCG, in 50 countries worldwide.

According to a [[UNICEF]] report published in December 2015 on BCG vaccine supply security, global demand increased in 2015 from 123 to 152.2 million doses. In order to improve security and to [diversify] sources of affordable and flexible supply,&quot; UNICEF awarded seven new manufacturers contracts to produce BCG. Along with supply availability from existing manufacturers, and a &quot;new WHO prequalified vaccine&quot; the total supply will be &quot;sufficient to meet both suppressed 2015 demand carried over to 2016, as well as total forecast demand through 2016-2018.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;UNICEF_2015&quot;&gt;{{citation |title=Bacillus Calmette-Guérin Vaccine Supply &amp; Demand Outlook |work=UNICEF Supply Division |date=December 2015 |accessdate=29 January 2016 |url=http://www.unicef.org/supply/files/BCG_Supply_Status_December_2015.pdf |pages=5 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160205111702/http://www.unicef.org/supply/files/BCG_Supply_Status_December_2015.pdf |archivedate=5 February 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===BCG supply shortage 2012–2017===
&lt;!-- Any change to this section title should be reflected in its linking at [[Sanofi Pasteur#2012 BCG supply shortage]] --&gt;
In the fall of 2011, the [[Sanofi Pasteur]] plant flooded causing problems with mold.&lt;ref name=&quot;FDA_2012&quot;&gt;{{citation |url=https://www.fda.gov/BiologicsBloodVaccines/CellularGeneTherapyProducts/ApprovedProducts/ucm310376.htm |series=Vaccines, Blood &amp; Biologics |title=April 2012 Inspectional Observations (form 483) |work=U.S. Food and Drug Administration |date=12 April 2012 |accessdate=29 January 2016 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160206161441/https://www.fda.gov/BiologicsBloodVaccines/CellularGeneTherapyProducts/ApprovedProducts/ucm310376.htm |archivedate=6 February 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The facility, located in Toronto, Ontario, Canada, produced BCG vaccine products, made with substrain Connaught, such as a tuberculosis vaccine ImmuCYST, a BCG Immunotherapeutic – a bladder cancer drug.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Sanofi Pasteur Product Monograph - Immucyst|url=https://www.vaccineshoppecanada.com/document.cfm?file=immucyst_e.pdf|website=Sanofi Pasteur Canada|accessdate=11 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; By April 2012 the FDA had found dozens of documented problems with sterility at the plant including mold, nesting birds and rusted electrical conduits.&lt;ref name=&quot;FDA_2012&quot; /&gt; The resulting closure of the plant for over two years resulting in shortages of bladder cancer and tuberculosis vaccines.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanofi_2014_BCG_vaccine&quot;&gt;{{citation |title=Merck again shipping BCG cancer treatment but Sanofi still is not: Shortages of bladder cancer and tuberculosis treatment have persisted for two years |date=10 September 2014 |first=Eric |last=Palmer |accessdate=|work=FiercePharma}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanofi_2012_BCG_vaccine&quot;&gt;{{citation |title=Merck again shipping BCG cancer treatment but Sanofi still is not: Shortages of bladder cancer and tuberculosis treatment have persisted for two years |date=12 July 2012|first=Eric |last=Palmer |work=FiercePharma |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; On October 29, 2014 [[Health Canada]] gave the permission for Sanofi to resume production of BCG.&lt;ref name=&quot;FiercePharma_mar_2015&quot;&gt;{{citation |title=Sanofi Canada vax plant again producing ImmuCyst bladder cancer drug |url=http://www.fiercepharmamanufacturing.com/story/sanofi-vaccine-plant-canada-again-producing-immucyst-bladder-drug/2015-03-31 |date=31 March 2015 |accessdate=29 January 2016 |first=Eric |last=Palmer |work=FiercePharma |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160205081244/http://www.fiercepharmamanufacturing.com/story/sanofi-vaccine-plant-canada-again-producing-immucyst-bladder-drug/2015-03-31 |archivedate=5 February 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The global supply situation was analyzed in 2017 and concluded that the global supply is sufficient to meet forecasted BCG vaccine demand but risks for shortages remain mainly due to supply concentration.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid29254839&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Cernuschi T, Malvolti S, Nickels E, Friede M | title = Bacillus Calmette-Guérin (BCG) vaccine: A global assessment of demand and supply balance | journal = Vaccine | volume = 36 | issue = 4 | pages = 498–506 | date = January 2018 | pmid = 29254839 | pmc = 5777639 | doi = 10.1016/j.vaccine.2017.12.010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Preparation===
A weakened strain of bovine tuberculosis bacillus, ''[[Mycobacterium bovis]]'' is specially subcultured in a culture medium, usually [[Middlebrook 7H9 Broth|Middlebrook 7H9]].

===Dried===
Some BCG vaccines are [[freeze drying|freeze dried]] and become fine powder. Sometimes the powder is sealed with vacuum in a glass ampoule. Such a glass ampoule has to be opened slowly to prevent the airflow from blowing out the powder. Then the powder has to be diluted with saline water before injecting.

==History==
[[File:BCG advert.jpg|thumb|French poster promoting the BCG vaccine]]
The history of BCG is tied to that of [[smallpox]].  [[Jean Antoine Villemin]] first recognized bovine tuberculosis in 1854 and transmitted it, and [[Robert Koch]] first distinguished ''Mycobacterium bovis'' from ''[[Mycobacterium tuberculosis]]''.  Following the success of [[vaccination]] in preventing smallpox, established during the 18th century, scientists thought to find a corollary in tuberculosis by drawing a parallel between bovine tuberculosis and [[cowpox]]:  it was hypothesized that infection with bovine tuberculosis might protect against infection with human tuberculosis.  In the late 19th century, clinical trials using ''M. bovis'' were conducted in Italy with disastrous results, because ''M. bovis'' was found to be just as virulent as ''M. tuberculosis''.

[[Albert Calmette]], a French physician and bacteriologist, and his assistant and later colleague, [[Camille Guérin]], a veterinarian, were working at the [[Institut Pasteur de Lille]] ([[Lille]], France) in 1908.  Their work included subculturing virulent strains of the tuberculosis bacillus and testing different culture media. They noted a glycerin-bile-potato mixture grew bacilli that seemed less virulent, and changed the course of their research to see if repeated subculturing would produce a strain that was attenuated enough to be considered for use as a vaccine. The BCG strain was isolated after subculturing 239 times during 13 years from virulent strain on glycerine potato medium.  The research continued throughout World War I until 1919, when the now avirulent bacilli were unable to cause tuberculosis disease in research animals.  Calmette and Guerin transferred to the Paris [[Pasteur Institute]] in 1919.  The BCG vaccine was first used in humans in 1921.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |vauthors=Fine PE, Carneiro IA, Milstein JB, Clements CJ | title=Issues relating to the use of BCG in immunization programs | publisher=[[World Health Organization]] (WHO) | year=1999 | location=Geneva }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Public acceptance was slow, and one disaster, in particular, did much to harm public acceptance of the vaccine. In the summer of 1930 in [[Lübeck]], 240 infants were vaccinated in the first 10 days of life; almost all developed tuberculosis and 72 infants died. It was subsequently discovered that the BCG administered there had been contaminated with a virulent strain that was being stored in the same incubator, which led to legal action against the manufacturers of the vaccine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Rosenthal SR. | title=BCG vaccination against tuberculosis | publisher=Little, Brown &amp; Co. | location=Boston | year=1957 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Dr. R.G. Ferguson]], working at the [[Fort San, Saskatchewan|Fort Qu'Appelle Sanatorium]] in Saskatchewan, was among the pioneers in developing the practice of vaccination against tuberculosis. In 1928, BCG was adopted by the Health Committee of the [[League of Nations]] (predecessor to the [[World Health Organization]] (WHO)).  Because of opposition, however, it only became widely used after World War II.  From 1945 to 1948, relief organizations (International Tuberculosis Campaign or Joint Enterprises) vaccinated over 8 million babies in [[eastern Europe]] and prevented the predicted typical increase of TB after a major war.

BCG is very efficacious against [[tuberculous meningitis]] in the pediatric age group, but its efficacy against pulmonary tuberculosis appears to be variable. As of 2006, only a few countries do not use BCG for routine vaccination. Two countries that have never used it routinely are the United States and the Netherlands (in both countries, it is felt that having a reliable [[Mantoux test]] and therefore being able to accurately detect active disease is more beneficial to society than vaccinating against a condition that is now relatively rare there).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.cdc.gov/tb/publications/factsheets/prevention/bcg.htm |title=Fact Sheets: BCG Vaccine |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |date=28 October 2011 |publisher=Centers for Disease Control and Prevention |accessdate=18 July 2013 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130720080800/http://www.cdc.gov/tb/publications/factsheets/prevention/BCG.htm |archivedate=20 July 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |date=17 March 2011 |title=Vaccination of young children against tuberculosis |issue=2011/04 |publisher=The Hague:Health Council of the Netherlands |isbn=978-90-5549-844-4 |url=http://www.gezondheidsraad.nl/sites/default/files/Summary_vaccine_tegen_tuberculose.pdf |accessdate=12 July 2013 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140219093821/http://www.gezondheidsraad.nl/sites/default/files/Summary_vaccine_tegen_tuberculose.pdf |archivedate=19 February 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other names include &quot;Vaccin Bilié de Calmette et Guérin vaccine&quot; and &quot;Bacille de Calmette et Guérin vaccine&quot;.

== Research ==
Tentative evidence exists for a beneficial [[non-specific effect of vaccines|non-specific effect]] of  BCG vaccination on overall mortality in low income countries, or for its reducing other health problems including [[sepsis]] and respiratory infections when given early,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Aaby|first1=P|last2=Roth|first2=A|last3=Ravn|first3=H|last4=Napirna|first4=BM|last5=Rodrigues|first5=A|last6=Lisse|first6=IM|last7=Stensballe|first7=L|last8=Diness|first8=BR|last9=Lausch|first9=KR|last10=Lund|first10=N|last11=Biering-Sørensen|first11=S|last12=Whittle|first12=H|last13=Benn|first13=CS|title=Randomized trial of BCG vaccination at birth to low-birth-weight children: beneficial nonspecific effects in the neonatal period?|journal=The Journal of Infectious Diseases|date=15 July 2011|volume=204|issue=2|pages=245–52|pmid=21673035|doi=10.1093/infdis/jir240}}&lt;/ref&gt; with greater benefit the earlier it is used.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Biering-Sørensen|first1=S|last2=Aaby|first2=P|last3=Napirna|first3=BM|last4=Roth|first4=A|last5=Ravn|first5=H|last6=Rodrigues|first6=A|last7=Whittle|first7=H|last8=Benn|first8=CS|title=Small randomized trial among low-birth-weight children receiving bacillus Calmette-Guérin vaccination at first health center contact.|journal=The Pediatric Infectious Disease Journal|date=March 2012|volume=31|issue=3|pages=306–8|pmid=22189537|doi=10.1097/inf.0b013e3182458289}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[rhesus macaque]]s, BCG shows improved rates of protection when given [[intravenous injection|intravenously]].&lt;ref name=rh-iv&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Darrah PA, Zeppa JJ, Maiello P, Hackney JA, Wadsworth MH, Hughes TK, Pokkali S, Swanson PA, Grant NL, Rodgers MA, Kamath M, Causgrove CM, Laddy DJ, Bonavia A, Casimiro D, Lin PL, Klein E, White AG, Scanga CA, Shalek AK, Roederer M, Flynn JL, Seder RA |title=Prevention of tuberculosis in macaques after intravenous BCG immunization |journal=Nature |date=January 2020 |volume=577 |issue=7788 |pages=95–102 |doi=10.1038/s41586-019-1817-8 |doi-access=free|display-authors=3|lay-url=https://www.pittwire.pitt.edu/news/researchers-find-more-effective-way-administer-tuberculosis-vaccine}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors=Behar SM, Sassetti C | title=Tuberculosis vaccine finds an improved route | journal=Nature | volume=577 | issue=7788 | date=January 2020 | doi=10.1038/d41586-019-03597-y | pages=31–32 | url=https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-03597-y }}&lt;/ref&gt;

BCG vaccine is in the early stages of being studied{{when|date=January 2020}} in [[type 1 diabetes]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Long-term reduction in hyperglycemia in advanced type 1 diabetes: the value of induced aerobic glycolysis with BCG vaccinations|vauthors=Kühtreiber WM, Tran L, Kim T, Dybala M, Nguyen B, Plager S, Huang D, Janes S, Defusco A, Baum D, Zheng H, Faustman DL|journal=NPJ Vaccines|volume=3|pages=23|year=2018|doi=10.1038/s41541-018-0062-8|pmid=29951281|pmc=6013479|display-authors=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Kowalewicz-Kulbat |first1=M |last2=Locht |first2=C |title=BCG and protection against inflammatory and auto-immune diseases. |journal=Expert Review of Vaccines |date=July 2017 |volume=16 |issue=7 |pages=699–708 |doi=10.1080/14760584.2017.1333906 |pmid=28532186}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* {{cite web | title=BCG Vaccine | website=U.S. [[Food and Drug Administration]] (FDA) | date=22 July 2017 | url=http://www.fda.gov/vaccines-blood-biologics/vaccines/bcg-vaccine }}
* [http://www.priory.com/cmol/bcg.htm Frequently Asked Questions about BCG] Professor P D O Davies, Tuberculosis Research Unit, Cardiothoracic Centre, Liverpool, UK.
* [http://www.bcgatlas.org BCG World Atlas] BCG policy by country, past and present.
* {{MeshName|BCG Vaccine}}

{{vaccines}}
{{portal bar | Pharmacy and pharmacology | Medicine}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bacillus Calmette-Guerin}}
[[Category:Cancer vaccines]]
[[Category:Live vaccines]]
[[Category:Tuberculosis vaccines]]
[[Category:Schering-Plough brands]]
[[Category:Merck &amp; Co. brands]]
[[Category:World Health Organization essential medicines (vaccines)]]
[[Category:RTT]]</text>
      <sha1>797r3p7m2reeaaffzr82l0jcrsjegxw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
