  <page>
    <title>Boeing 767</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4165</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942438553</id>
      <parentid>942438158</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-24T17:57:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Fnlayson</username>
        <id>1216158</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Revert unexplained &amp; undiscussed main image change</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Wide-body twin-engine jet airliner family}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=September 2011}}
{{featured article}}
&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] for recommended layout, guidelines. --&gt;
{|{{Infobox aircraft begin
| name = Boeing 767
| image = File:Delta Air Lines B767-332 N130DL.jpg &lt;!-- In flight images are preferred for aircraft. Please do not change this image without a talk page discussion. --&gt;
| caption = A Boeing 767-300 of [[Delta Air Lines]], the largest operator of the 767
| alt = A side/underneath view of a Boeing 767-300 in Delta Air Lines' white, blue and red color during climbout. The main undercarriage doors are retracting.
}}{{Infobox aircraft type
| type = [[Wide-body aircraft|Wide-body]] [[jet airliner]]
| national origin = United States
| manufacturer = [[Boeing Commercial Airplanes]]
| first flight = {{Start date|1981|09|26}}
| introduced = September 8, 1982, with [[United Airlines]]
| retired = 
| status = In service&lt;!-- Status of the program. See produced years for production status. --&gt;
| primary user = [[Delta Air Lines]]&lt;!--Limit one (1) primary user. Top 4 users listed in 'primary user' and 'more users' fields based on number of their fleets as cited in Operators section. --&gt;
| more users = [[FedEx Express]] &lt;br /&gt;[[UPS Airlines]] &lt;br /&gt;[[United Airlines]]&lt;!--Limit is three (3) TOTAL in 'more users' field (4 total users). Listed in by number in use, i.e. top users listed in Operators section. Please separate with &lt;br /&gt;.--&gt;
| produced = 1981–present
| number built = 1,178 as of 31 January 2020&lt;ref name=767_O_D_summ/&gt;
| unit cost = (2019 US$ million) -300ER: 217.9, -300F: 220.3&lt;ref name=prices&gt;{{cite web |title= About Boeing Commercial Airplanes: Prices |url= http://www.boeing.com/company/about-bca/#/prices |publisher= Boeing}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| developed from = 
| variants with their own articles = {{Plainlist|
* [[Boeing E-767]]
* [[Boeing KC-46 Pegasus]]
* [[Boeing KC-767]]
* [[Northrop Grumman E-10 MC2A]]}}
| developed into = 
}}
|}

The '''Boeing 767''' is a mid- to large-size, [[flight length|mid- to long-range]], [[Wide-body aircraft|wide-body]] [[Twinjet|twin-engine]] [[jet airliner]] developed and manufactured by [[Boeing Commercial Airplanes]]. It was Boeing's first wide-body [[twinjet]] and its first airliner with a two-crew [[glass cockpit]]. The aircraft has two [[turbofan]] engines, a conventional [[empennage|tail]], and, for reduced [[aerodynamic drag]], a [[supercritical airfoil|supercritical wing]] design. Designed as a smaller wide-body airliner than earlier aircraft such as the [[Boeing 747|747]], the 767 has a seating capacity for 181 to 375 people, and a [[Range (aeronautics)|design range]] of {{Convert|3850|to|6385|nmi|mi km|lk=in}}, depending on variant. Development of the 767 occurred in tandem with a [[Narrow-body aircraft|narrow-body]] twinjet, the [[Boeing 757|757]], resulting in shared design features which allow pilots to obtain a common [[type rating]] to operate both aircraft.

The 767 is produced in three [[fuselage]] lengths. The original 767-200 entered service in 1982, followed by the 767-300 in 1986 and the 767-400ER, an extended-range (ER) variant, in 2000. The extended-range 767-200ER and 767-300ER models entered service in 1984 and 1988, respectively, while a production [[Cargo aircraft|freighter]] version, the 767-300F, debuted in 1995. Conversion programs have modified passenger 767-200 and 767-300 series aircraft for cargo use, while military derivatives include the [[Boeing E-767|E-767]] [[Airborne early warning and control|surveillance]] aircraft, the [[Boeing KC-767|KC-767]] and [[Boeing KC-46|KC-46]] aerial [[aerial refueling|tankers]], and VIP transports. Engines featured on the 767 include the [[General Electric CF6]], [[Pratt &amp; Whitney JT9D]] and [[Pratt &amp; Whitney PW4000|PW4000]], and [[Rolls-Royce RB211]] turbofans.

[[United Airlines]] first placed the 767 in commercial service in 1982. The aircraft was initially flown on domestic and [[Transcontinental flight across the United States|transcontinental]] routes, during which it demonstrated the reliability of its twinjet design. The 767 became the first twin-engined airliner to be used on extended overseas flights in 1985. The aircraft was then used to expand [[Non-stop flight|non-stop]] service on [[Flight length|medium- to long-haul]] intercontinental routes. In 1986, Boeing initiated studies for a higher-capacity 767, ultimately leading to the development of the [[Boeing 777|777]], a larger wide-body twinjet. In the 1990s, the 767 became the most frequently used airliner for [[transatlantic flight]]s between [[North America]] and [[Europe]].

The 767 is the first twinjet wide-body type to reach 1,000 aircraft delivered. {{as of|2019|August||df=}}, Boeing has received 1,254 orders for the 767 from 74 customers with 1,161 delivered.&lt;ref name=767_O_D_summ/&gt; A total of 742 of these aircraft were in service in July 2018.&lt;ref name=FI_Airlines_2018&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.flightglobal.com/asset/24536|title=World Airline Census 2018|last=|first=|date=|website=Flightglobal.com|language=en-GB|access-date=2018-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The most popular variant is the 767-300ER with 583 delivered. [[Delta Air Lines]] is the largest operator with 77 aircraft. Competitors have included the [[Airbus A300]], [[Airbus A310|A310]], and [[Airbus A330|A330-200]]. Non-passenger variants of the 767 remain in production {{as of|2019||df=|lc=y|since=}} while the passenger variant's successor, the [[Boeing 787 Dreamliner|787]], entered service in 2011.

==Development==

===Background===
In 1970, Boeing's 747 became the first wide-body jetliner to enter service.&lt;ref name=Eden_p102/&gt; The 747 was the first passenger jet wide enough to feature a twin-aisle cabin.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Sutter|2006|p=103}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two years later, the manufacturer began a development study, code-named 7X7, for a new wide-body aircraft intended to replace the [[Boeing 707|707]] and other early generation narrow-body jets.&lt;ref name=n157/&gt;&lt;ref name=saver/&gt; The aircraft would also provide twin-aisle seating, but in a smaller fuselage than the existing 747, [[McDonnell Douglas DC-10]], and [[Lockheed L-1011 TriStar]] wide-bodies.&lt;ref name=n157/&gt; To defray the high cost of development, Boeing signed risk-sharing agreements with Italian corporation [[Aeritalia]] and the Civil Transport Development Corporation (CTDC), a consortium of Japanese aerospace companies.&lt;ref name=n156&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|1998|p=156}}&lt;/ref&gt; This marked the manufacturer's first major international joint venture, and both Aeritalia and the CTDC received supply contracts in return for their early participation.&lt;ref name=n156/&gt; The initial 7X7 was conceived as a [[STOL|short take-off and landing]] airliner intended for short-distance flights, but customers were unenthusiastic about the concept, leading to its redefinition as a mid-size, transcontinental-range airliner.&lt;ref name=n157&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|1998|pp=156–57.}}&lt;/ref&gt; At this stage the proposed aircraft featured two or three engines, with possible configurations including over-wing engines and a [[T-tail]].&lt;ref name=Eden_p102&gt;{{harvnb|Eden|2008|pp=102–03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Delta Air Lines Boeing 767-232 Farnborough 1982 Fitzgerald.jpg|thumb|The 7X7 made its [[Farnborough Airshow]] debut in 1982 as the 767-200.|alt=Side view of twin-engine jet touching down on runway, with deployed flaps and thrust reversers]]
By 1976, a twinjet layout, similar to the one which had debuted on the [[Airbus A300]], became the baseline configuration.&lt;ref name=no20/&gt; The decision to use two engines reflected increased industry confidence in the reliability and economics of new-generation jet powerplants.&lt;ref name=no20&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|1999|pp=20–21}}&lt;/ref&gt; While airline requirements for new wide-body aircraft remained ambiguous,&lt;ref name=no20/&gt; the 7X7 was generally focused on mid-size, high-density markets.&lt;ref name=Eden_p102/&gt; As such, it was intended to transport large numbers of passengers between major cities.&lt;ref name=Eden_p103&gt;{{harvnb|Eden|2008|p=103}}&lt;/ref&gt; Advancements in civil aerospace technology, including [[high-bypass turbofan|high-bypass-ratio turbofan]] engines, new flight deck systems, [[aerodynamic]] improvements, and lighter construction materials were to be applied to the 7X7.&lt;ref name=n157/&gt;&lt;ref name=no19&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|1999|pp=18–19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many of these features were also included in a parallel development effort for a new mid-size narrow-body airliner, code-named 7N7, which would become the 757.&lt;ref name=no19/&gt; Work on both proposals proceeded through the airline industry upturn in the late 1970s.&lt;ref name=davies103&gt;{{harvnb|Davies|2000|p=103}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=n143/&gt;

In January 1978, Boeing announced a major extension of its [[Boeing Everett Factory|Everett factory]]—which was then dedicated to manufacturing the 747—to accommodate its new wide-body family.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Birtles|1999|p=8}}&lt;/ref&gt; In February 1978, the new jetliner received the 767 model designation,&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Becher|1999|p=24}}&lt;/ref&gt; and three variants were planned: a 767-100 with 190 seats, a 767-200 with 210 seats, and a [[trijet]] 767MR/LR version with 200 seats intended for intercontinental routes.&lt;ref name=no20/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Donald|1997|page=173}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 767MR/LR was subsequently renamed 777 for differentiation purposes.&lt;ref name=n159&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|1998|pp=159–60}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |url= https://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1978/1978%20-%200788.html |title= Boeing 767 and 777 |magazine= Flight International |date= 13 May 1978}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 767 was officially launched on July 14, 1978, when United Airlines ordered 30 of the 767-200 variant, followed by 50 more 767-200 orders from [[American Airlines]] and Delta Air Lines later that year.&lt;ref name=n159/&gt; The 767-100 was ultimately not offered for sale, as its capacity was too close to the 757's seating,&lt;ref name=n159/&gt; while the 777 trijet was eventually dropped in favor of standardizing around the twinjet configuration.&lt;ref name=no20/&gt;

===Design effort===
In the late 1970s, [[operating cost]] replaced capacity as the primary factor in airliner purchases.&lt;ref name=saver/&gt; As a result, the 767's design process emphasized [[fuel efficiency]] from the outset.&lt;ref name=n157/&gt; Boeing targeted a 20 to 30&amp;nbsp;percent cost saving over earlier aircraft, mainly through new engine and wing technology.&lt;ref name=saver&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1981/1981%20-%202612.html|title=Boeing 767: The new fuel saver|date=August 8, 1981|last=Velupillai|first=David|work=Flight International|accessdate=July 30, 2011|pages=436–37, 439, 440–41, 445–48, 453}}&lt;/ref&gt; As development progressed, engineers used [[computer-aided design]] for over a third of the 767's design drawings,&lt;ref name=saver/&gt; and performed 26,000 hours of [[wind tunnel]] tests.&lt;ref name=n159/&gt; Design work occurred concurrently with the 757 twinjet, leading Boeing to treat both as almost one program to reduce risk and cost.&lt;ref name=no19/&gt;&lt;ref name=n143&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|1998|p=143}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both aircraft would ultimately receive shared design features, including [[avionics]], [[flight management system]]s, instruments, and handling characteristics.&lt;ref name=no23/&gt; Combined development costs were estimated at $3.5 to $4&amp;nbsp;billion.&lt;ref name=saver/&gt;

[[File:Continental Airlines Boeing 767-400ER Wallner.jpg|thumb|left|Forward view of a [[Continental Airlines]] 767-400ER, showing fuselage profile, [[Dihedral (aircraft)|wing dihedral]], and [[General Electric CF6|CF6]] engines|alt=Forward view of aircraft, showing fuselage profile, two circular engines]]
Early 767 customers were given the choice of [[Pratt &amp; Whitney JT9D]] or [[General Electric CF6]] turbofans, marking the first time that Boeing had offered more than one engine option at the launch of a new airliner.&lt;ref name=no22/&gt; Both jet engine models had a maximum output of {{convert|48000|lbf|kN}} of [[Jet engine#Thrust|thrust]].&lt;ref name=Eden_p103/&gt; The engines were mounted approximately one-third the length of the wing from the fuselage, similar to previous wide-body trijets.&lt;ref name=saver/&gt; The larger wings were designed using an [[Supercritical airfoil|aft-loaded]] shape which reduced aerodynamic drag and distributed [[lift (force)|lift]] more evenly across their surface span than any of the manufacturer's previous aircraft.&lt;ref name=saver/&gt;&lt;ref name=n160/&gt; The wings provided higher-altitude [[Cruise (flight)|cruise]] performance, added fuel capacity, and expansion room for future stretched variants.&lt;ref name=n159/&gt; The initial 767-200 was designed for sufficient range to fly across North America or across the northern Atlantic,&lt;ref name=Sutter_p241&gt;{{harvnb|Sutter|2006|pp=241–46}}&lt;/ref&gt; and would be capable of operating routes up to {{convert|3850|nmi|km}}.&lt;ref name=h43&gt;{{harvnb|Haenggi|2003|pp=43–44}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 767's fuselage width was set midway between that of the 707 and the 747 at {{convert|16.5|ft|m|sigfig=3}}.&lt;ref name=n157/&gt; While it was narrower than previous wide-body designs, seven abreast seating with two aisles could be fitted, and the reduced width produced less aerodynamic drag.&lt;ref name=Eden_p103/&gt;&lt;ref name=no22&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|1999|pp=21–22}}&lt;/ref&gt; The fuselage was not wide enough to accommodate two standard LD3 wide-body [[unit load device]]s side-by-side,&lt;ref name=Haenggi_p29&gt;{{harvnb|Haenggi|2003|p=29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Birtles|1999|p=14}}&lt;/ref&gt; so a smaller container, the LD2,&lt;ref name=767_airport_report/&gt; was created specifically for the 767.&lt;ref name=n158&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|1998|p=158}}&lt;/ref&gt; Using a conventional tail design also allowed the rear fuselage to be tapered over a shorter section,&lt;ref name=no22/&gt; providing for parallel aisles along the full length of the passenger cabin, and eliminating irregular seat rows toward the rear of the aircraft.&lt;ref name=saver/&gt;&lt;ref name=no22/&gt;

[[File:Boeing 767 over Mount Rainier, circa 1980s.jpg|thumb|The first {{nowrap|767-200}} built, N767BA, in flight near [[Mount Rainier]] in the 1980s.|alt=Boeing twin engine jetliner in flight near a snow-capped mountain]]
The 767 was the first Boeing wide-body to be designed with a two-crew digital glass cockpit.&lt;ref name=no23&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|1999|p=23}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cathode ray tube]] (CRT) color displays and new electronics replaced the role of the [[flight engineer]] by enabling the pilot and co-pilot to monitor aircraft systems directly.&lt;ref name=no23/&gt; Despite the promise of reduced crew costs, United Airlines initially demanded a conventional three-person cockpit, citing concerns about the risks associated with introducing a new aircraft.&lt;ref name=2crew/&gt; The carrier maintained this position until July 1981, when a US presidential task force determined that a crew of two was safe for operating wide-body jets.&lt;ref name=2crew&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boeing.com/commercial/767family/pf/pf_fltdeck.html|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110807182604/http://www.boeing.com/commercial/767family/pf/pf_fltdeck.html|archivedate=2011-08-07|title=History of the 767 Two-Crew Flight Deck|publisher=Boeing|accessdate=July 29, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Becher|1999|p=32}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A three-crew cockpit remained as an option and was fitted to the first production models.&lt;ref name=becher33&gt;{{Harvnb|Becher|1999|p=33}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ansett Australia]] ordered 767s with three-crew cockpits due to union demands; it was the only airline to operate 767s so configured.&lt;ref name=becher33/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Wilson|2002|p=117}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 767's two-crew cockpit was also applied to the 757, allowing pilots to operate both aircraft after a short conversion course,&lt;ref name=n160&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|1998|p=160.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and adding incentive for airlines to purchase both types.&lt;ref name=intro/&gt; Although nominally similar in control design, flying the 767 feels different from the 757. The 757's controls are heavy, similar to the 727 and 747; the control yoke can be rotated to 90 degrees in each direction. The 767 has far lighter control feel in pitch and roll, and the control yoke has approximately 2/3 the rotation travel.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Bednar|2016|p=17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Production and testing===
To produce the 767, Boeing formed a network of subcontractors which included domestic suppliers and international contributions from Italy's Aeritalia and Japan's CTDC.&lt;ref name=n156/&gt; The wings and cabin floor were produced in-house, while Aeritalia provided control surfaces, [[Boeing Rotorcraft Systems|Boeing Vertol]] made the [[leading edge]] for the wings, and [[Spirit AeroSystems|Boeing Wichita]] produced the forward fuselage.&lt;ref name=saver/&gt; The CTDC provided multiple assemblies through its constituent companies, namely [[Fuji Heavy Industries]] ([[Aircraft fairing|wing fairings]] and gear doors), [[Kawasaki Heavy Industries]] (center fuselage), and [[Mitsubishi Heavy Industries]] (rear fuselage, doors, and tail).&lt;ref name=n156/&gt; Components were integrated during final assembly at the Everett factory.&lt;ref name=saver/&gt; For expedited production of wing [[Spar (aviation)|spars]], the main structural member of aircraft wings, the Everett factory received [[robot]]ic machinery to automate the process of drilling holes and inserting [[fastener]]s.&lt;ref name=saver/&gt; This method of wing construction expanded on techniques developed for the 747.&lt;ref name=saver/&gt; Final assembly of the first aircraft began in July 1979.&lt;ref name=Eden_p102/&gt;

[[File:Boeing 767 Everett, Washington production view.jpg|thumb|left|Final assembly of a 767-300F at Boeing's [[Boeing Everett Factory|Everett factory]], which was expanded for 767 production in 1978|alt=Airplane assembly hall, featuring an unpainted metallic twin-jet aircraft, a presentation podium, and arranged audience chairs]]
The prototype aircraft, [[aircraft registration|registered]] N767BA and equipped with JT9D turbofans, rolled out on August 4, 1981.&lt;ref name=Shaw_twins&gt;{{harvnb|Shaw|1999|page=64}}&lt;/ref&gt; By this time, the 767 program had accumulated 173 firm orders from 17 customers, including [[Air Canada]], [[All Nippon Airways]], [[Britannia Airways]], [[Transbrasil]], and [[Trans World Airlines]] (TWA).&lt;ref name=saver/&gt; On September 26, 1981, the prototype took its [[maiden flight]] under the command of company test pilots Tommy Edmonds, Lew Wallick, and John Brit.&lt;ref name=n161/&gt; The maiden flight was largely uneventful, save for the inability to retract the [[landing gear]] because of a [[Hydraulics|hydraulic]] fluid leak.&lt;ref name=n161/&gt; The prototype was used for subsequent flight tests.&lt;ref name=b17/&gt;

The 10-month 767 flight test program utilized the first six aircraft built.&lt;ref name=Eden_p102/&gt;&lt;ref name=b17/&gt; The first four aircraft were equipped with JT9D engines, while the fifth and sixth were fitted with CF6 engines.&lt;ref name=Eden_p103/&gt;&lt;ref name=b50&gt;{{Harvnb|Birtles|1999|pp=49–52}}&lt;/ref&gt; The test fleet was largely used to evaluate avionics, flight systems, handling, and performance,&lt;ref name=b50/&gt; while the sixth aircraft was used for route-proving flights.&lt;ref name=testing/&gt; During testing, pilots described the 767 as generally easy to fly, with its maneuverability unencumbered by the bulkiness associated with larger wide-body jets.&lt;ref name=testing&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1982/1982%20-%200710.html|title=Boeing tests the twins|last=Sweetman|first=Bill|date=March 20, 1982|work=Flight International|accessdate=July 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following 1,600 hours of flight tests, the JT9D-powered 767-200 received certification from the US [[Federal Aviation Administration]] (FAA) and the UK [[Civil Aviation Authority (United Kingdom)|Civil Aviation Authority]] (CAA) in July 1982.&lt;ref name=n161&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|1998|pp=161–62}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=b17&gt;{{harvnb|Birtles|1999|pp=16–18, 27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first delivery occurred on August 19, 1982, to United Airlines.&lt;ref name=n161/&gt; The CF6-powered 767-200 received certification in September 1982, followed by the first delivery to Delta Air Lines on October 25, 1982.&lt;ref name=Eden_p103/&gt;

===Service entry and operations===
The 767 entered service with United Airlines on September 8, 1982.&lt;ref name=&quot;Haenggi_p31-5&quot;/&gt; The aircraft's first commercial flight used a JT9D-powered 767-200 on the Chicago-to-Denver route.&lt;ref name=&quot;Haenggi_p31-5&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Haenggi|2003|pp=31–5}}&lt;/ref&gt; The CF6-powered 767-200 commenced service three months later with Delta Air Lines.&lt;ref name=Eden_p102/&gt; Upon delivery, early 767s were mainly deployed on domestic routes, including US transcontinental services.&lt;ref name=b49/&gt; American Airlines and TWA began flying the 767-200 in late 1982, while Air Canada, [[China Airlines]], and [[El Al]] began operating the aircraft in 1983.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Birtles|1999|pp=55–58}}&lt;/ref&gt; The aircraft's introduction was relatively smooth, with few operational glitches and greater [[Dispatch (logistics)|dispatch]] [[Reliability engineering|reliability]] than prior jetliners.&lt;ref name=smooth&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1983/1983%20-%200561.html|title=Boeing 767 moves smoothly into service|last=Lynn|first=Norman|date=April 2, 1983|work=Flight International|accessdate=January 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In its first year, the 767 logged a 96.1&amp;nbsp;percent dispatch rate, which exceeded the industry average for new aircraft.&lt;ref name=smooth/&gt; Operators reported generally favorable ratings for the twinjet's sound levels, interior comfort, and economic performance.&lt;ref name=smooth/&gt; Resolved issues were minor and included the recalibration of a leading edge sensor to prevent false readings, the replacement of an [[evacuation slide]] latch, and the repair of a [[tailplane]] pivot to match production specifications.&lt;ref name=smooth/&gt;

[[File:TWA Boeing 767-200 N610TW Proctor.jpg|thumb|[[Trans World Airlines|TWA]] began operating the first {{nowrap|767-200}} [[ETOPS]] flights in May 1985. |alt=TWA jetliner in red and white livery during takeoff, with landing gears still down.]]
Seeking to capitalize on its new wide-body's potential for growth, Boeing offered an extended-range model, the 767-200ER, in its first year of service.&lt;ref name=no163&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|1998|p=163}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ethiopian Airlines]] placed the first order for the type in December 1982.&lt;ref name=no163/&gt;&lt;ref name=Boe_767_back&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boeing.com/commercial/767family/background.html|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110821194025/http://www.boeing.com/commercial/767family/background.html|archivedate=2011-08-21|title=Boeing 767 Program Background|publisher=Boeing|accessdate=July 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Featuring increased [[gross weight]] and greater fuel capacity, the extended-range model could carry heavier [[Payload (air and space craft)|payloads]] at distances up to {{convert|6385|nmi|km}},&lt;ref name=762specs&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boeing.com/commercial/767family/pf/pf_200prod.html|title=767-200ER Technical Characteristics|publisher=Boeing|accessdate=October 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was targeted at overseas customers.&lt;ref name=Eden_p103/&gt; The 767-200ER entered service with [[El Al]] Airline on March 27, 1984.&lt;ref name=Boe_767_back/&gt; The type was mainly ordered by international airlines operating medium-traffic, long-distance flights.&lt;ref name=Eden_p103/&gt;

In the mid-1980s, the 767 spearheaded the growth of twinjet flights across the northern Atlantic under extended-range twin-engine operational performance standards ([[ETOPS]]) regulations, the FAA's safety rules governing transoceanic flights by aircraft with two engines.&lt;ref name=no163/&gt; Before the 767, overwater flight paths of twinjets could be no more than 90 minutes away from [[diversion airport]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;haenggi_p38-40&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Haenggi|2003|pp=38–40.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In May 1985, the FAA granted its first approval for 120-minute ETOPS flights to 767 operators, on an individual airline basis starting with TWA, provided that the operator met flight safety criteria.&lt;ref name=&quot;haenggi_p38-40&quot;/&gt; This allowed the aircraft to fly overseas routes at up to two hours' distance from land.&lt;ref name=&quot;haenggi_p38-40&quot;/&gt; The larger safety margins were permitted because of the improved reliability demonstrated by the twinjet and its turbofan engines.&lt;ref name=&quot;haenggi_p38-40&quot;/&gt; The FAA lengthened the ETOPS time to 180 minutes for CF6-powered 767s in 1989, making the type the first to be certified under the longer duration,&lt;ref name=b49&gt;{{Harvnb|Birtles|1999|pp=49–53}}&lt;/ref&gt; and all available engines received approval by 1993.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Becher|1999|pp= 150, 154–55}}&lt;/ref&gt; Regulatory approval spurred the expansion of transoceanic 767 flights and boosted the aircraft's sales.&lt;ref name=no163/&gt;&lt;ref name=haenggi_p42&gt;{{harvnb|Haenggi|2003|p=42}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Stretched derivatives===
Forecasting airline interest in larger-capacity models, Boeing announced the stretched 767-300 in 1983 and the extended-range 767-300ER in 1984.&lt;ref name=no163/&gt;&lt;ref name=Eden_p104/&gt; Both models offered a 20&amp;nbsp;percent passenger capacity increase,&lt;ref name=767_airport_report/&gt; while the extended-range version was capable of operating flights up to {{convert|5990|nmi|km}}.&lt;ref name=763specs&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boeing.com/commercial/767family/pf/pf_300prod.html|title=767-300ER Technical Characteristics|publisher=Boeing|accessdate=October 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Japan Airlines]] placed the first order for the 767-300 in September 1983.&lt;ref name=no163/&gt; Following its first flight on January 30, 1986,&lt;ref name=Eden_p104&gt;{{harvnb|Eden|2008|pp=103–04.}}&lt;/ref&gt; the type entered service with Japan Airlines on October 20, 1986.&lt;ref name=Boe_767_back/&gt; The 767-300ER completed its first flight on December 9, 1986,&lt;ref name=Boe_767_back/&gt; but it was not until March 1987 that the first firm order, from American Airlines, was placed.&lt;ref name=Eden_p104/&gt; The type entered service with American Airlines on March 3, 1988.&lt;ref name=Boe_767_back/&gt; The 767-300 and 767-300ER gained popularity after entering service, and came to account for approximately two-thirds of all 767s sold.&lt;ref name=no163/&gt;

After the debut of the first stretched 767s, Boeing sought to address airline requests for greater capacity by proposing larger models, including a partial double-deck version informally named the &quot;Hunchback of Mukilteo&quot; (from a town near Boeing's Everett factory) with a 757 body section mounted over the aft main fuselage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090601173533/http://www.aiaa.org/sections/cl/what/mckinzie.htm|archivedate=June 1, 2009|url=http://www.aiaa.org/sections/cl/what/mckinzie.htm|title=How United Airlines Helped Design The World's Most Remarkable Airliner|publisher=American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics|last=McKinzie|first=Gordon|accessdate=July 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Norris_Wagner_777_p11-13&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|2001|pages=11–13, 15}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1986, Boeing proposed the 767-X, a revised model with extended wings and a wider cabin, but received little interest.&lt;ref name=&quot;Norris_Wagner_777_p11-13&quot;/&gt; By 1988, the 767-X had evolved into an all-new twinjet, which revived the [[Boeing 777|777]] designation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Norris_Wagner_777_p11-13&quot;/&gt; Until the 777's 1995 debut, the 767-300 and 767-300ER remained Boeing's second-largest wide-bodies behind the 747.&lt;ref name=Eden_p104/&gt;

[[File:Osaka KIX JAL 767-346 JA8986 and ANA 767-381ER JA612A.jpg|thumb|left|A [[Japan Airlines|JAL]] 767-300 lands in front of an [[All Nippon Airways|ANA]] 767-300ER at [[Kansai International Airport|Kansai Airport]]. The −300 and −300ER variants account for almost two-thirds of all 767s sold.|alt=A white and red-tailed Japan Airlines aircraft above runway, with landing gears down, and an All Nippon Airways in blue and white livery taxiing]]
Buoyed by a recovering global economy and ETOPS approval, 767 sales accelerated in the mid-to-late 1980s; 1989 was the most prolific year with 132 firm orders.&lt;ref name=no163/&gt;&lt;ref name=haenggi_p42/&gt; By the early 1990s, the wide-body twinjet had become its manufacturer's annual best-selling aircraft, despite a slight decrease due to economic recession.&lt;ref name=no163/&gt; During this period, the 767 became the most common airliner for transatlantic flights between North America and Europe.&lt;ref name=airl_777&gt;{{harvnb|Smil|1998|p=28}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of the decade, 767s crossed the Atlantic more frequently than all other aircraft types combined.&lt;ref name=davies89&gt;{{harvnb|Davies|2000|pp=88–89}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 767 also propelled the growth of [[Point-to-point transit|point-to-point]] flights which bypassed major [[airline hub]]s in favor of [[direct flight|direct routes]].&lt;ref name=Sutter_p241/&gt;&lt;ref name=p2p&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|2009|p=12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Taking advantage of the aircraft's lower operating costs and smaller capacity, operators added non-stop flights to secondary population centers, thereby eliminating the need for connecting flights.&lt;ref name=Sutter_p241/&gt; The increased number of cities receiving non-stop services caused a paradigm shift in the airline industry as point-to-point travel gained prominence at the expense of the traditional [[Spoke-hub distribution paradigm|hub-and-spoke]] model.&lt;ref name=Sutter_p241/&gt;&lt;ref name=p2p/&gt;

In February 1990, the first 767 equipped with [[Rolls-Royce RB211]] turbofans, a 767-300, was delivered to [[British Airways]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Birtles|1999|pp=27–28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Six months later, the carrier temporarily grounded its entire 767 fleet after discovering cracks in the [[hardpoint|engine pylons]] of several aircraft.&lt;ref name=b64&gt;{{Harvnb|Birtles|1999|p=64}}&lt;/ref&gt; The cracks were related to the extra weight of the RB211 engines, which are {{convert|2205|lb|kg}} heavier than other 767 engines.&lt;ref name=b64/&gt; During the grounding, interim repairs were conducted to alleviate stress on engine pylon components, and a parts redesign in 1991 prevented further cracks.&lt;ref name=b64/&gt; Boeing also performed a structural reassessment, resulting in production changes and modifications to the engine pylons of all 767s in service.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/boeing-acts-to-solve-757767-pylon-cracks-25909/|title=Boeing acts to solve 757/767 pylon cracks|first=Guy|last=Norris|work=Flight International|date=May 24, 1995|accessdate=December 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Boeing 767-400ER Rollout Proctor.jpg|thumb|The Boeing 767-400ER was publicly unveiled on August 26, 1999.&lt;ref name=Boe_767_back/&gt;|alt=Side quarter view of twin-engine jetliner in front of hangar, with surrounding crowds]]
In January 1993, following an order from [[UPS Airlines]],&lt;ref name=Eden_p105&gt;{{harvnb|Eden|2008|p=105}}&lt;/ref&gt; Boeing launched a freighter variant, the 767-300F, which entered service with UPS on October 16, 1995.&lt;ref name=Boe_767_back/&gt; The 767-300F featured a main deck cargo hold, upgraded landing gear, and strengthened wing structure.&lt;ref name=f63/&gt; In November 1993, the Japanese government launched the first 767 military derivative when it placed orders for the {{nowrap|E-767}}, an [[Airborne Early Warning and Control]] (AWACS) variant based on the 767-200ER.&lt;ref name=b39/&gt; The first two {{nowrap|E-767s}}, featuring extensive modifications to accommodate surveillance [[radar]] and other monitoring equipment, were delivered in 1998 to the [[Japan Self-Defense Forces]].&lt;ref name=aw33/&gt;&lt;ref name=poise/&gt;

In November 1995, after abandoning development of a smaller version of the 777, Boeing announced that it was revisiting studies for a larger 767.&lt;ref name=no117/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Becher|1999|p=125}}&lt;/ref&gt; The proposed 767-400X, a second stretch of the aircraft, offered a 12&amp;nbsp;percent capacity increase versus the 767-300,&lt;ref name=767_airport_report/&gt; and featured an upgraded flight deck, enhanced interior, and greater wingspan.&lt;ref name=no117&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|1999|pp=116–21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The variant was specifically aimed at Delta Air Lines' pending replacement of its aging Lockheed L-1011 TriStars, and faced competition from the A330-200, a shortened derivative of the Airbus A330.&lt;ref name=no117/&gt; In March 1997, Delta Air Lines launched the 767-400ER when it ordered the type to replace its L-1011 fleet.&lt;ref name=Boe_767_back/&gt;&lt;ref name=no117/&gt; In October 1997, [[Continental Airlines]] also ordered the 767-400ER to replace its McDonnell Douglas DC-10 fleet.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Birtles|1999|p=40}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/continental-goes-boeing-13833/|title=Continental goes Boeing|first=Ramon|last=Lopez|work=Flight International|date=June 18, 1997|accessdate=December 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The type completed its first flight on October 9, 1999, and entered service with Continental Airlines on September 14, 2000.&lt;ref name=Boe_767_back/&gt;

===Dreamliner introduction===
[[File:Austrian Airlines B767-3Z9ER (OE-LAE) departing Vienna International Airport.jpg|thumb|left|[[Austrian Airlines]] 767-300ER with blended [[winglet]]s, which reduce [[lift-induced drag]]|alt=Rear quarter view of an Austrian Airlines 767, with red winglets]]

In the early 2000s, cumulative 767 deliveries approached 900, but new sales declined during an airline industry downturn.&lt;ref name=long&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/long-players-163582/|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130925055155/http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/long-players-163582/|archivedate=2013-09-25|title=Long players|date=January 4, 2003|work=Flight International|first=Guy|last=Norris|author2=Kingsley-Jones, Max|accessdate=July 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2001, Boeing dropped plans for a longer-range model, the 767-400ERX, in favor of the proposed [[Boeing Sonic Cruiser|Sonic Cruiser]], a new jetliner which aimed to fly 15&amp;nbsp;percent faster while having comparable fuel costs to the 767.&lt;ref name=sonic&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/2001/2001%20-%201119.html|title=Boeing Sonic Cruiser Ousts 747X|date=April 3, 2001|work=Flight International|first=Guy|last=Norris|author2=Kelly, Emma|accessdate=August 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Sonic Cruiser seeks mission definition|date=July 2001|journal=Interavia Business &amp; Technology|volume=56|issue=655|page=25|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P3-77659773.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150924204757/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P3-77659773.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=2015-09-24|access-date=June 30, 2015|via=[[HighBeam]]|url-access=subscription}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following year, Boeing announced the [[Boeing KC-767#International programs|KC-767 Tanker Transport]], a second military derivative of the 767-200ER.&lt;ref name=kc767&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2006/07/11/207660/pumped-for-action.html|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070704203818/http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2006/07/11/207660/pumped-for-action.html|archivedate= 2007-07-04|title=Pumped for action|date=November 7, 2006|work=Flight International|first=Guy|last=Norris|accessdate=August 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Launched with an order in October 2002 from the [[Italian Air Force]], the KC-767 was intended for the dual role of refueling other aircraft and carrying cargo.&lt;ref name=kc767/&gt; The Japanese government became the second customer for the type in March 2003.&lt;ref name=kc767/&gt; In May 2003, the [[United States Air Force]] (USAF) announced its intent to lease KC-767s to replace its aging [[Boeing KC-135 Stratotanker|KC-135]] tankers.&lt;ref name=kcxchrono&gt;{{cite news|url=http://uk.reuters.com/article/2011/02/24/usa-tanker-idUKN2315169720110224|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121113153241/http://uk.reuters.com/article/2011/02/24/usa-tanker-idUKN2315169720110224|archivedate=2012-11-13|title=Pentagon nears new contract in air tanker saga|work=Reuters|last=Shalal-Esa|first=Andrea|date=February 24, 2010|accessdate=December 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=kc-x&gt;McCarthy, John; Price, Wayne. (March 9, 2010). &quot;Northrop pulls out of tanker bidding war.&quot; ''Florida Today,'' p. A1&lt;/ref&gt; The plan was suspended in March 2004 amid a [[conflict of interest]] [[Boeing KC-767#USAF lease and cancellation|scandal]],&lt;ref name=kcxchrono/&gt; resulting in multiple US government investigations and the departure of several Boeing officials, including [[Philip M. Condit|Philip Condit]], the company's [[chief executive officer]], and [[chief financial officer]] Michael Sears.&lt;ref name=kcxstall&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seattlepi.com/business/article/Stalled-767-deal-may-cost-jobs-1137579.php|title=Stalled 767 deal may cost jobs|work=Seattle Post-Intelligencer|date=February 20, 2004|last=Wallace|first=James|accessdate=December 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first KC-767s were delivered in 2008 to the Japan Self-Defense Forces.&lt;ref name=kc767j/&gt;

In late 2002, after airlines expressed reservations about its emphasis on speed over cost reduction,&lt;ref name=n2009/&gt; Boeing halted development of the Sonic Cruiser.&lt;ref name=n2009&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|2009|pp=32–35}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following year, the manufacturer announced the 7E7, a mid-size 767 successor made from [[composite material]]s which promised to be 20&amp;nbsp;percent more fuel efficient.&lt;ref name=dream&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2007/07/07/209212/everything-about-the-boeing-787-dreamliner.html|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110906121739/http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2007/07/07/209212/everything-about-the-boeing-787-dreamliner.html|archivedate=2011-09-06|title=Boeing 787 Dreamliner Aircraft Profile|work=Flight International|year=2011|accessdate=July 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The new jetliner was the first stage of a replacement aircraft initiative called the [[Boeing Yellowstone Project]].&lt;ref name=n2009/&gt; Customers embraced the 7E7, later renamed 787 Dreamliner, and within two years it had become the fastest-selling airliner in the company's history.&lt;ref name=dream/&gt; In 2005, Boeing opted to continue 767 production despite record Dreamliner sales, citing a need to provide customers waiting for the 787 with a more readily available option.&lt;ref name=reprieve&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/767-earns-reprieve-as-787-ramp-up-considered-199772/ |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20121105133912/http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/767-earns-reprieve-as-787-ramp-up-considered-199772/|archivedate=2012-11-05|title=767 earns reprieve as 787 ramp-up considered|work=Flight International|date=June 5, 2005|accessdate=July 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequently, the 767-300ER was offered to customers affected by 787 delays, including All Nippon Airways and Japan Airlines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=JAL to take 11 767s and 777s in 787-delay compensation deal|first=Nicholes|last=Ionides|work=Flight International|date=September 17, 2008|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2008/09/17/316096/jal-to-take-11-767s-and-777s-in-787-delay-compensation.html|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080921035755/http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2008/09/17/316096/jal-to-take-11-767s-and-777s-in-787-delay-compensation.html|archivedate=2008-09-21|accessdate=September 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some aging 767s, exceeding 20 years in age, were also kept in service past planned retirement dates due to the delays.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.heraldsun.com.au/businessold/ageing-jets-to-fly-on-due-to-delay-in-boeing-dreamliner/story-e6frfh4f-1225991529905|title=Ageing jets to fly on due to delay in Boeing Dreamliner|work=Herald Sun|accessdate=January 19, 2011|date=September 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; To extend the operational lives of older aircraft, airlines increased heavy maintenance procedures, including [[Aircraft maintenance checks|D-check]] teardowns and inspections for [[corrosion]], a recurring issue on aging 767s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timco.aero/content/articles/checking-767-mro-management.html|title=Checking Up on the 767|first=Ian|last=Goold|work=MRO Management|date=June 2010|accessdate=2015-07-03|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120426072500/http://www.timco.aero/content/articles/checking-767-mro-management.html|archivedate=2012-04-26|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first 787s entered service with All Nippon Airways in October 2011, 42 months behind schedule.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://atwonline.com/aircraft-engines-components/news/finally-787-enters-service-1026|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111227100805/http://atwonline.com/aircraft-engines-components/news/finally-787-enters-service-1026|archivedate=2011-12-27|title=Finally&amp;nbsp;... the 787 enters service|first=Karen|last=Walker|work=Air Transport World|date=October 27, 2011|accessdate=December 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Continued production ===
[[File:UPS Airlines B767-300F (N328UP) landing at San Jose International Airport.jpg|thumb|[[UPS Airlines|UPS]], the largest 767-300F operator, placed additional orders in 2007.|alt=Side quarter view of UPS twin-engine freighter in flight, with extended gear]]

In 2007, the 767 received a production boost when UPS and [[DHL Aviation]] placed a combined 33 orders for the 767-300F.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seattlepi.com/business/article/UPS-order-revives-767-line-1227427.php|title=UPS order revives 767 line|work=Seattle Post-Intelligencer|date=February 5, 2007|accessdate=August 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.marketwatch.com/story/dhl-orders-6-boeing-767-freighters|title=DHL orders 6 Boeing 767 freighters|publisher=MarketWatch|first=Padraic|last=Cassidy|date=March 8, 2007|accessdate=August 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Renewed freighter interest led Boeing to consider enhanced versions of the 767-200 and 767-300F with increased gross weights, 767-400ER wing extensions, and 777 avionics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://atwonline.com/aircraftenginescomponents/news/boeing-considering-new-767-freighter-counter-a330-200f-0309|title=Boeing considering new 767 freighter to counter A330-200F|work=Aviation Week &amp; Space Technology|first=Geoffrey|last=Thomas|date=March 2, 2007|accessdate=July 29, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Net orders for the 767 declined from 24 in 2008 to just three in 2010.&lt;ref name=Boeing_yearly_orders&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boeing.com/commercial/#/orders-deliveries|title=Boeing Company Annual Orders Summary|last=|first=|date=|website=|publisher=Boeing|accessdate=July 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the same period, operators upgraded aircraft already in service; in 2008, the first 767-300ER retrofitted with blended [[Wingtip device|winglets]] from [[Aviation Partners Inc.|Aviation Partners Incorporated]] debuted with American Airlines.&lt;ref name=winglets_debut/&gt; The manufacturer-sanctioned winglets, at {{convert|11|ft|m|sigfig=3}} in height, improved fuel efficiency by an estimated 6.5&amp;nbsp;percent.&lt;ref name=winglets_debut&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Ranson|first=Lori|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2008/07/22/225951/blended-winglets-debut-on-boeing-767.html|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080725005222/http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2008/07/22/225951/blended-winglets-debut-on-boeing-767.html|archivedate=2008-07-25|title=Blended winglets debut on Boeing 767|work=Flight International|date=July 22, 2008|accessdate=August 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other carriers including All Nippon Airways and Delta Air Lines also ordered winglet kits.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Yeo|first=Ghim-Lay|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2010/07/23/344919/farnborough-hainan-and-ana-to-equip-boeing-aircraft-with.html|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100726235136/http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2010/07/23/344919/farnborough-hainan-and-ana-to-equip-boeing-aircraft-with.html|archivedate=2010-07-26|title=Farnborough: Hainan and ANA to equip Boeing aircraft with winglets|work=Flight Daily News|date=July 23, 2010|accessdate=August 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/delta-takes-tips-from-aviation-partners-214967/|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131003082816/http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/delta-takes-tips-from-aviation-partners-214967/|archivedate=2013-10-03|title=Delta takes tips from Aviation Partners|work=Flight Daily News|date=June 20, 2007|accessdate=August 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On February 2, 2011, the 1,000th 767 rolled out, destined for All Nippon Airways.&lt;ref name=FG_1000th_rollout/&gt; The aircraft was the 91st 767-300ER ordered by the Japanese carrier, and with its completion the 767 became the second wide-body airliner to reach the thousand-unit milestone after the 747.&lt;ref name=FG_1000th_rollout&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2011/02/03/352770/picture-boeing-unveils-1000th-767.html|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110206155704/http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2011/02/03/352770/picture-boeing-unveils-1000th-767.html|archivedate=2011-02-06|title=Boeing unveils 1,000th 767|author=Ostrower, Jon|work=Air Transport Intelligence|date=February 3, 2011|accessdate=February 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/thousandth-767-etches-twinjet39s-place-in-history-351792/|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140228224819/http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/thousandth-767-etches-twinjet39s-place-in-history-351792/|archivedate=2014-02-28|title=Thousandth 767 etches twinjet's place in history|date=December 1, 2010|work=Flight International|accessdate=January 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 1,000th aircraft also marked the last model produced on the original 767 assembly line.&lt;ref name=herald/&gt; Beginning with the 1,001st aircraft, production moved to another area in the Everett factory which occupied about half of the previous floor space.&lt;ref name=herald/&gt; The new assembly line made room for 787 production and aimed to boost manufacturing efficiency by over twenty percent.&lt;ref name=herald/&gt;

At the inauguration of its new assembly line, the 767's order backlog numbered approximately 50, only enough for production to last until 2013.&lt;ref name=herald&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.heraldnet.com/article/20110306/BIZ/703069951/1122/news01|title=767 now built faster and in less space|first=Michelle|last=Dunlop|work=The Weekly Herald|date=March 6, 2011|accessdate=July 30, 2011|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120615055418/http://www.heraldnet.com/article/20110306/BIZ/703069951/1122/news01|archivedate=June 15, 2012|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the reduced backlog, Boeing officials expressed optimism that additional orders would be forthcoming.&lt;ref name=herald/&gt; On February 24, 2011, the USAF announced its selection of the KC-767 Advanced Tanker, an upgraded variant of the KC-767,&lt;ref name=kc767at&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.upi.com/Business_News/Security-Industry/2008/01/03/Boeing-presents-KC-767-proposal-to-USAF/UPI-86481199401085/|title=Boeing presents KC-767 proposal to USAF|publisher=United Press International|date=January 3, 2008|accessdate=December 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; for its [[KC-X]] fleet renewal program.&lt;ref name=herald/&gt; The selection followed two rounds of tanker competition between Boeing and [[Airbus]] parent [[EADS]], and came eight years after the USAF's original 2003 announcement of its plan to lease KC-767s.&lt;ref name=kcxchrono/&gt; The tanker order encompassed 179 aircraft and was expected to sustain 767 production past 2013.&lt;ref name=herald/&gt;

In December 2011, [[FedEx Express]] announced a 767-300F order for 27 aircraft to replace its DC-10 freighters, citing the USAF tanker order and Boeing's decision to continue production as contributing factors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thestreet.com/story/11350825/2/boeing-767-removed-from-life-support.html|title=Boeing 767 Removed From Life Support |publisher=The Street|first=Ted|last=Reed|date=December 20, 2011|accessdate=December 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; FedEx Express agreed to buy 19 more of the −300F variant in June 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=FedEx Express Plans to Acquire 19 Boeing 767-300F Aircraft and Convert Four 777 Freighter Orders|url=http://news.van.fedex.com/node/18533|publisher=FedEx Express press release|date=June 29, 2012|accessdate=July 2, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|agency=Associated Press|title=FedEx to buy additional aircraft from Boeing|url=http://www.businessweek.com/ap/2012-06-29/fedex-to-buy-additional-aircraft-from-boeing|work=Businessweek|date=June 29, 2012 |accessdate=2015-07-03|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120703070730/http://www.businessweek.com/ap/2012-06-29/fedex-to-buy-additional-aircraft-from-boeing |archivedate=2012-07-03 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2015, FedEx said it was accelerating retirements of planes both to reflect demand and to modernize its fleet, recording charges of $276 million.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Wall Street Journal&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.wsj.com/articles/fedex-to-buy-as-many-as-100-boeing-767-freighters-1437522505 |title= FedEx to Buy as Many as 100 Boeing 767 Freighters|work=The Wall Street Journal|date=21 July 2015|accessdate=21 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; On July 21, 2015 FedEx announced an order for 50 767-300F with options on another 50, the largest order for the type.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.streetinsider.com/Corporate+News/FedEx+Express+(FDX)+Will+Acquire+Addtional+50+Boeing+(BA)+767-300F+Aircraft/10739876.html|title=FedEx Express (FDX) Will Acquire Additional 50 Boeing (BA) 767-300F Aircraft|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; With the announcement FedEx confirmed that it has firm orders for 106 of the freighters for delivery between 2018 and 2023.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Wall Street Journal&quot;/&gt; In February 2018, UPS announced an order for 4 more 767-300Fs to increase the total on order to 63.&lt;ref name=UPS2018Order&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boeing.com/commercial/customers/ups/747-8-767-order.page|title=Boeing: UPS Orders 14 Additional 747-8 Freighters, Plus Four 767 Freighters|website= boeing.com|access-date=2018-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With its successor, the [[Boeing New Midsize Airplane]], that was planned for introduction in 2025 or later, and the 787 being much larger, Boeing could restart a passenger 767-300ER production to bridge the gap.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= https://leehamnews.com/2017/08/14/boeings-tactical-option-for-mom-sector/ |title= Boeing's tactical option for MOM sector |date= Aug 14, 2017 |work= Leeham}}&lt;/ref&gt; A demand for 50 to 60 aircraft could have to be satisfied.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= https://leehamnews.com/2017/10/19/boeing-ponders-restart-767-300er-passenger-line/ |title= Boeing ponders restart of 767-300ER passenger line |date= Oct 19, 2017 |work= Leeham}}&lt;/ref&gt; Having to replace its 40 767s, [[United Airlines]] requested a price quote for other widebodies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/united-requests-pricing-data-on-767-other-widebodie-442921/ |title= United requests pricing data on 767, other widebodies |date= 6 Nov 2017 |author= Stephen Trimble |work= Flightglobal}}&lt;/ref&gt; In November 2017, Boeing CEO [[Dennis Muilenburg]] cited interest beyond military and freighter uses.&lt;!--&lt;ref name=Flight5mar2018&gt;--&gt; However, in early 2018 Boeing Commercial Airplanes VP of marketing Randy Tinseth stated that the company did not intend to resume production of the passenger variant.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-boeing-airplanes/boeing-executive-rules-out-reviving-767-passenger-jet-idUSKBN1GH311|title=Boeing executive rules out reviving 767 passenger jet|date=5 March 2018|author=Tim Hepher|work=Reuters}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Flight5mar2018&gt;{{cite news |url= https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/boeing-unlikely-to-resume-passenger-767-production-446453/ |title= Boeing unlikely to resume passenger 767 production |date= 5 March 2018 |author= Edward Russell |work= Flightglobal}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In its first quarter of 2018 [[earnings]] report, Boeing plan to increase its production from 2.5 to 3 monthly beginning in January 2020 due to increased demand in the [[cargo aircraft|cargo]] market, as FedEx had 56 on order, UPS has four, and an unidentified customer has three on order.&lt;!--&lt;ref name=Leeham25apr2018&gt;--&gt; This rate could rise to 3.5 per month in July 2020 and 4 per month in January 2021, before decreasing to 3 per month in January 2025 and then 2 per month in July 2025.&lt;ref name=Leeham25apr2018&gt;{{cite news |url= https://leehamnews.com/2018/04/25/boeing-to-hike-767f-production-may-be-only-first-of-several/ |title= Boeing to hike 767F production; may be only first of several |date= April 25, 2018 |work= Leeham News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Re-engined 767-XF ===
Boeing is studying a re-engined 767-XF for around 2025, based on the 767-400ER with an extended landing gear to accommodate [[General Electric GEnx]] turbofans.&lt;!--ref name=Flight10oct2019--&gt;
The cargo market is the main target, but a passenger version could be a cheaper alternative to the proposed [[Boeing New Midsize Airplane|New Midsize Airplane]].&lt;ref name=Flight10oct2019&gt;{{cite news |url= https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/boeing-examines-genx-powered-767-x-for-cargo-and-pa-461386/ |title= Boeing examines GEnx-powered 767-X for cargo and passenger roles |date= 10 Oct 2019 |work= Flightglobal}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Design==
[[File:Asia Atlantic Airlines 767-300 (HS-AAC) Narita International Airport.jpg|thumb|The 767 is a [[widebody aircraft|widebody]] with a [[low wing]], [[twinjet|twin]] underwing [[turbofan]]s, and a conventional tail]]

===Overview===

The 767 is a low-wing [[Cantilever wing|cantilever monoplane]] with a conventional tail unit featuring a single fin and rudder. The wings are swept at 31.5 degrees and optimized for a cruising speed of [[Mach number|Mach]] 0.8 ({{cvt|533|mph|sigfig=3|disp=or}}).&lt;ref name=no22/&gt; Each wing features a [[supercritical airfoil]] cross-section and is equipped with six-panel [[leading edge slat]]s, single- and double-slotted [[Flap (aircraft)|flaps]], inboard and outboard [[aileron]]s, and six [[Spoiler (aeronautics)|spoilers]].&lt;ref name=saver/&gt;&lt;ref name=b15&gt;{{Harvnb|Birtles|1999|pp=15–16.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[airframe]] further incorporates [[Carbon-fiber-reinforced polymer]] [[composite material]] wing surfaces, [[Kevlar]] [[Aircraft fairing|fairings]] and access panels, plus improved [[aluminium alloy|aluminum alloys]], which together reduce overall weight by {{convert|1900|lb|kg}} versus preceding aircraft.&lt;ref name=saver/&gt;

To distribute the aircraft's weight on the ground, the 767 has a retractable [[tricycle landing gear]] with four wheels on each main gear and two for the nose gear.&lt;ref name=saver/&gt; The original wing and gear design accommodated the stretched 767-300 without major changes.&lt;ref name=no163/&gt; The 767-400ER features a larger, more widely spaced main gear with 777 wheels, tires, and brakes.&lt;ref name=no119&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|1999|pp=119, 121}}&lt;/ref&gt; To prevent damage if the tail section contacts the runway surface during takeoff, 767-300 and 767-400ER models are fitted with a retractable [[tailstrike|tailskid]].&lt;ref name=no119/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boeing.com/news/frontiers/archive/2004/december/i_tt.html |title=Striking out tailstrikes|first=Katherine |last=Sopranos|work=Frontiers|date=December 2004|accessdate=August 21, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 767 has left-side exit doors near the front and rear of the aircraft.&lt;ref name=767_airport_report/&gt;

[[File:Boeing 767 Nose Section 41.jpg|thumb|The 767 has the same cockpit windows as the [[Boeing 757]]|alt=Close up view of a green Section 41, the nose section of a 767. Installation is not yet complete for the window panes.]]

In addition to shared avionics and computer technology, the 767 uses the same [[auxiliary power unit]], electric power systems, and hydraulic parts as the 757.&lt;ref name=intro&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1982/1982%20-%200014.html|title=Boeing 757: introducing the big-fan narrowbody|date=January 2, 1983|last=Velupillai|first=David|work=Flight International|accessdate=February 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A raised cockpit floor and the same forward cockpit windows result in similar pilot viewing angles.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|1996|p=69}}&lt;/ref&gt; Related design and functionality allows 767 pilots to obtain a common [[type rating]] to operate the 757 and share the same [[seniority]] roster with pilots of either aircraft.&lt;ref name=no23/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Wells|Clarence|2004|p=252}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Flight systems===
[[File:B767-322 flight deck.jpg|thumb|The early 767 flight deck with [[Electronic flight instrument system|EFIS]] and [[Electronic flight instrument system#Engine indications and crew alerting system (EICAS) / electronic centralized aircraft monitoring (ECAM)|EICAS]] screens allowed two-crew operations, later 767-400 had larger displays, while earlier models could be upgraded]]

The original 767 flight deck uses six [[Rockwell Collins]] CRT screens to display [[Electronic flight instrument system]] (EFIS) and [[Electronic flight instrument system#Engine indications and crew alerting system (EICAS) / electronic centralized aircraft monitoring (ECAM)|engine indication and crew alerting system]] (EICAS) information, allowing pilots to handle monitoring tasks previously performed by the flight engineer.&lt;ref name=no23/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Birtles|1999|pp=20, 25}}&lt;/ref&gt; The CRTs replace conventional [[electromechanics|electromechanical]] instruments found on earlier aircraft.&lt;ref name=no23/&gt; An enhanced flight management system, improved over versions used on early 747s,&lt;ref name=no23/&gt; automates navigation and other functions, while an [[Autoland|automatic landing]] system facilitates [[Instrument landing system|CAT IIIb]] instrument landings in low visibility situations.&lt;ref name=saver/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Young, David (June 17, 1982). &quot;767's maiden O'Hare landing is automatic&quot;. ''Chicago Tribune'', p. 3&lt;/ref&gt; The 767 became the first aircraft to receive CAT IIIb certification from the FAA for landings with {{convert|980|ft|m|sp=us}} minimum visibility in 1984.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://fsims.faa.gov/wdocs/8900.1/v04%20ac%20equip%20&amp;%20auth/chapter%2002/04_002_001.htm|title=FAA Order 8900.1 Flight Standards Information Management System (FSIMS), Volume 4 Aircraft Equipment and Operational Authorizations|publisher=Federal Aviation Administration|date=September 13, 2007|accessdate=July 29, 2011|quote=RVR 300, Runway Visual Range 300 meters}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the 767-400ER, the cockpit layout is simplified further with six Rockwell Collins [[liquid crystal display]] (LCD) screens, and adapted for similarities with the 777 and the [[Boeing 737 Next Generation|Next Generation 737]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|1999|p=117}}&lt;/ref&gt; To retain operational [[Fleet commonality|commonality]], the LCD screens can be programmed to display information in the same manner as earlier 767s.&lt;ref name=f63/&gt; In 2012, Boeing and Rockwell Collins launched a further 787-based cockpit upgrade for the 767, featuring three landscape-format LCD screens that can display two windows each.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aviationweek.com/Blogs.aspx?plckPostId=Blog:c757984d-8899-488d-bc38-5d2824ba71b3Post:893ca4a0-c2c6-41f5-afb9-4040e430dce7|title=Boeing's KC-46A Tanker Sparks 767 Cockpit Upgrade|first=Graham|last=Warwick|work=Aviation Week &amp; Space Technology|date=July 10, 2012|accessdate=2015-07-04|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140221221440/http://www.aviationweek.com/Blogs.aspx?plckPostId=Blog%3Ac757984d-8899-488d-bc38-5d2824ba71b3Post%3A893ca4a0-c2c6-41f5-afb9-4040e430dce7|archivedate=February 21, 2014|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 767 is equipped with three redundant hydraulic systems for operation of control surfaces, landing gear, and utility actuation systems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://papers.sae.org/831488/ |title=Waterman, A. '&amp;#39;The Boeing 767 Hydraulic System'&amp;#39;, SAE International |publisher=Papers.sae.org |date=1983-10-03 |accessdate=2018-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Each engine powers a separate hydraulic system, and the third system uses electric pumps.&lt;ref name=b24&gt;{{harvnb|Birtles|1999|p=24}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[ram air turbine]] provides power for basic controls in the event of an emergency.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Birtles|1999|p=50}}&lt;/ref&gt; An early form of [[fly-by-wire]] is employed for spoiler operation, utilizing electric signaling instead of traditional control cables.&lt;ref name=saver/&gt; The fly-by-wire system reduces weight and allows independent operation of individual spoilers.&lt;ref name=saver/&gt;

===Interior===
[[File:Japan Airlines 767-300 Economy cabin.jpg|thumb|[[Economy class]] with two aisles and seven seats per row in 2–3–2 layout]]

The 767 features a twin-aisle cabin with a typical configuration of six abreast in [[business class]] and seven across in [[economy class|economy]].&lt;ref name=767_airport_report/&gt; The standard seven abreast, 2–3–2 economy class layout places approximately 87&amp;nbsp;percent of all seats at a window or aisle.&lt;ref name=kane553&gt;{{harvnb|Kane|2003|p=553}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, the aircraft can be largely occupied before center seats need to be filled,&lt;ref name=saver/&gt; and each passenger is no more than one seat from the aisle.&lt;ref name=kane553/&gt; It is possible to configure the aircraft with extra seats for up to an eight abreast configuration,&lt;ref name=767_airport_report/&gt; but this is less common.&lt;ref name=Haenggi_p34&gt;{{harvnb|Haenggi|2003|p=34}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 767 interior introduced larger [[Airliner#Overhead bins|overhead bins]] and more lavatories per passenger than previous aircraft.&lt;ref name=reshaped/&gt; The bins are wider to accommodate [[garment bag]]s without folding, and strengthened for heavier carry-on items.&lt;ref name=reshaped&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1981/05/24/travel/how-airline-cabins-are-being-reshaped.html|title=How Airline Cabins are being Reshaped|work=The New York Times|date=May 24, 1981|last=Pace|first=Eric|accessdate=February 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A single, large [[Galley (kitchen)|galley]] is installed near the aft doors, allowing for more efficient meal service and simpler ground resupply.&lt;ref name=reshaped/&gt; Passenger and service doors are an overhead [[Plug door|plug]] type, which retract upwards,&lt;ref name=767_airport_report/&gt; and commonly used doors can be equipped with an [[electric motor|electric-assist]] system.&lt;ref name=saver/&gt;

In 2000, a 777-style interior, known as the Boeing Signature Interior, debuted on the 767-400ER.&lt;ref name=hit&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boeing.com/news/frontiers/archive/2003/april/i_ca2.html|title=Boeing Signature Interior a hit with flying public|work=Frontiers|author=Davis, Elizabeth|date=April 2003|accessdate=August 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequently, adopted for all new-build 767s, the Signature Interior features even larger overhead bins, indirect lighting, and sculpted, curved panels.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|1999|p=122}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 767-400ER also received larger windows derived from the 777.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/2000/2000-1%20-%200316.html|title=Stretching and Testing|first=Guy|last=Norris|work=Flight International|accessdate=August 19, 2011|date=July 24, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; Older 767s can be retrofitted with the Signature Interior.&lt;ref name=hit/&gt; Some operators have adopted a simpler modification known as the Enhanced Interior, featuring curved ceiling panels and indirect lighting with minimal modification of cabin architecture,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://boeing.mediaroom.com/2005-03-09-Thomsonfly.com-Launches-Enhanced-Interior-Package-for-Boeing-757-200-and-767-200|title=Thomsonfly.com Launches Enhanced Interior Package for Boeing 757-200 and 767-200|publisher=Boeing|date=March 9, 2005|accessdate=2015-07-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as aftermarket modifications such as the NuLook 767 package by Heath Tecna.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.heath.com/Capabilities/Product-Showcase/B767-IUS/Description.aspx|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111001002558/http://www.heath.com/Capabilities/Product-Showcase/B767-IUS/Description.aspx|archivedate=2011-10-01|title=B767 Interior Upgrade Systems|publisher=Heath Tecna|accessdate=August 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Variants==
[[File:G-BNWA British Airways B767-300 planform.jpg|thumb|Planform view of a 767-300, showing its 156&amp;nbsp;ft 1 in (47.57 m) wide wing with a 3,050&amp;nbsp;ft² (283.3 m²) area and a 31.5° [[wing sweep|sweepback]],&lt;ref name=civilJetAircraftDesign/&gt; for a {{#expr:47.57/(283.3/47.57)round2}}:1 [[wing aspect ratio|aspect ratio]]|alt=Underside view of a jet in-flight. Each wing of the two wings have an engine. Towards the left are the horizontal stabilizers.]]

The 767 has been produced in three fuselage lengths.&lt;ref name=767_airport_report/&gt; These debuted in progressively larger form as the 767-200, 767-300, and 767-400ER.&lt;ref name=767_airport_report/&gt;&lt;ref name=e45&gt;{{harvnb|Eden|2008|pp=104–05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Longer-range variants include the 767-200ER and 767-300ER,&lt;ref name=e45/&gt; while cargo models include the 767-300F, a production freighter,&lt;ref name=k555/&gt; and conversions of passenger 767-200 and 767-300 models.&lt;ref name=faa/&gt;

When referring to different variants, Boeing and airlines often collapse the model number (767) and the variant designator, e.g. –200 or –300, into a truncated form, e.g. &quot;762&quot; or &quot;763&quot;.&lt;ref name=aafleet&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.aa.com/i18n/aboutUs/ourPlanes/ourPlanes.jsp |title=Our Planes |publisher=American Airlines |year=2011 |accessdate=August 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequent to the capacity number, designations may append the range identifier,&lt;ref name=aafleet/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.continental.com/web/en-US/content/travel/inflight/aircraft/762.aspx |title=Boeing 767-200ER |publisher=Continental Airlines |year=2011 |accessdate=2015-07-04 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110805082240/http://www.continental.com/web/en-US/content/travel/inflight/aircraft/762.aspx |archivedate=2011-08-05 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; though -200ER and -300ER are company marketing designations and not certificated as such.&lt;ref name=faa&gt;{{cite web |url=http://rgl.faa.gov/Regulatory_and_Guidance_Library/rgMakeModel.nsf/0/05d3a0b75a0d480086257847004ffb2f/$FILE/A1NM%20Rev%2030.pdf |publisher=Federal Aviation Administration |date=March 4, 2011 |title=Federal Aviation Administration Type Certificate Data Sheet A1NM |accessdate=December 26, 2011 |pages=6–8}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[International Civil Aviation Organization]] (ICAO) aircraft type designator system uses a similar numbering scheme, but adds a preceding manufacturer letter;&lt;ref name=ICAOcode/&gt; all variants based on the 767-200 and 767-300 are classified under the codes &quot;B762&quot; and &quot;B763&quot;; the 767-400ER receives the designation of &quot;B764&quot;.&lt;ref name=ICAOcode&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.icao.int/publications/DOC8643/ |title=ICAO Document 8643 |publisher=International Civil Aviation Organization |accessdate=December 10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===767-200===
The 767-200 was the original model and entered service with [[United Airlines]] in 1982.&lt;ref name=Eden_p102/&gt; The type has been used primarily by [[Mainline (flight)|mainline]] U.S. carriers for domestic routes between major hub centers such as Los Angeles to Washington.&lt;ref name=Eden_p102/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;davies89&quot;/&gt; The 767-200 was the first aircraft to be used on transatlantic [[ETOPS]] flights, beginning with TWA on February 1, 1985 under 90-minute diversion rules.&lt;ref name=&quot;haenggi_p38-40&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=davies89/&gt; Deliveries for the variant totaled 128 aircraft.&lt;ref name=767_O_D_summ/&gt; There were 52 passenger and freighter conversions of the model in commercial service {{as of|2018|July|lc=y}}.&lt;ref name=FI_Airlines_2018 /&gt;&lt;!-- Updates require a newer reference. --&gt; The type's competitors included the Airbus A300 and A310.&lt;ref name=Becher_p175&gt;{{Harvnb|Becher|1999|p=175}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 767-200 was produced until 1987 when production switched to the extended-range 767-200ER.&lt;ref name=no163/&gt; Some early 767-200s were subsequently upgraded to extended-range specification.&lt;ref name=davies89/&gt; In 1998, Boeing began offering 767-200 conversions to 767-200SF (Special Freighter) specification for cargo use,&lt;ref name=762SF&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/boeing-enters-ups-bidding-with-767-special-freighter-36199/ |title=Boeing enters UPS bidding with 767 'Special Freighter' |first=Guy |last=Norris |work=Flight International |date=April 22, 1998 |accessdate=December 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Israel Aerospace Industries]] has been licensed to perform cargo conversions since 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://easa.europa.eu/certification/type-certificates/docs/supplemental/EASA-TCDS-AS.00632_(IM)_IAI_B767--200SF_(Special_Freighter_Conversion)-03-23022011.pdf |title=Supplemental Type-Certificate Data Sheet |publisher=European Aviation Safety Agency |date=February 23, 2011 |accessdate=August 18, 2011 |page=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; The conversion process entails the installation of a side cargo door, strengthened main deck floor, and added freight monitoring and safety equipment.&lt;ref name=faa/&gt; The 767-200SF was positioned as a replacement for [[Douglas DC-8]] freighters.&lt;ref name=762SF/&gt;

===767-2C===
{{main|Boeing KC-46 Pegasus}}

A commercial freighter version of the Boeing 767-200 with wings from the -300 series and an updated flightdeck was first flown on 29 December 2014.&lt;ref name=ff2c&gt;{{cite web |last=Trimble |first=Stephen |url=http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/boeing-completes-first-flight-of-new-freighter-and-tanker-407472/ |title=Boeing completes first flight of new freighter and tanker |work=[[Flightglobal]] |publisher=Reed Business Information |date=28 December 2014 |accessdate=30 December 2014 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141230230129/http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/boeing-completes-first-flight-of-new-freighter-and-tanker-407472/ |archivedate=December 30, 2014 |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; A military tanker variant of the Boeing 767-2C is being developed for the USAF as the KC-46.&lt;ref name=ff2c/&gt; Boeing is building two aircraft as commercial freighters which will be used to obtain Federal Aviation Administration certification, a further two Boeing 767-2Cs will be modified as military tankers.&lt;ref name=ff2c/&gt; {{as of|2014}}, Boeing does not have customers for the freighter.&lt;ref name=ff2c/&gt;

===767-200ER===
[[File:American Airlines 767-200 N324AA.jpg|thumb|An [[American Airlines]] 767-200ER departing [[Los Angeles International Airport]]|alt=Sideview of 767 on climbout against a pale blue sky. A blue, white and red cheat-line runs the full length of the fuselage, above which says &quot;American&quot;. The vertical tail sports two &quot;A&quot;s, between which is a simplified eagle.]]

The 767-200ER was the first extended-range model and entered service with [[El Al]] in 1984.&lt;ref name=Boe_767_back/&gt; The type's increased range is due to an additional center fuel tank and a higher [[maximum takeoff weight]] (MTOW) of up to {{cvt|395000|lb|sigfig=3}}.&lt;ref name=no163/&gt;&lt;ref name=762specs/&gt; The type was originally offered with the same engines as the 767-200, while more powerful [[Pratt &amp; Whitney PW4000]] and [[General Electric CF6]] engines later became available.&lt;ref name=no163/&gt; The 767-200ER was the first 767 to complete a non-stop [[Transatlantic flight|transatlantic]] journey, and broke the flying distance record for a twinjet airliner on April 17, 1988 with an [[Air Mauritius]] flight from Halifax, [[Nova Scotia]] to Port Louis, [[Mauritius]], covering {{cvt|8727|nmi|sigfig=3}}.&lt;ref name=Eden_p102/&gt; The 767-200ER has been acquired by international operators seeking smaller wide-body aircraft for long-haul routes such as New York to Beijing.&lt;ref name=Eden_p102/&gt;&lt;ref name=762specs/&gt; Deliveries of the type totaled 121 with no unfilled orders.&lt;ref name=767_O_D_summ/&gt; As of July 2018, 21 examples of passenger and freighter conversion versions were in airline service.&lt;ref name=FI_Airlines_2018 /&gt;&lt;!-- Updates require a newer reference. --&gt; The type's main competitors of the time included the [[Airbus A300-600]]R and the [[Airbus A310-300|A310-300]].&lt;ref name=Eden_p104/&gt;

===767-300===
The 767-300, the first stretched version of the aircraft, entered service with [[Japan Airlines]] in 1986.&lt;ref name=Boe_767_back/&gt; The type features a {{convert|21.1|ft|m|sigfig=3|adj=on}} fuselage extension over the 767-200, achieved by additional sections inserted before and after the wings, for an overall length of {{cvt|180.25|ft|sigfig=3}}.&lt;ref name=no163/&gt; Reflecting the growth potential built into the original 767 design, the wings, engines, and most systems were largely unchanged on the 767-300.&lt;ref name=no163/&gt; An optional mid-cabin exit door is positioned ahead of the wings on the left,&lt;ref name=767_airport_report/&gt; while more powerful Pratt &amp; Whitney PW4000 and [[Rolls-Royce RB211]] engines later became available.&lt;ref name=Eden_p104/&gt; The 767-300's increased capacity has been used on high-density routes within Asia and Europe.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Birtles|1999|pp=62, 90–95}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 767-300 was produced from 1986 until 2000. Deliveries for the type totaled 104 aircraft with no unfilled orders remaining.&lt;ref name=767_O_D_summ/&gt; As of July 2018, 34 of the variant were in airline service.&lt;ref name=FI_Airlines_2018 /&gt;&lt;!-- Updates require a newer reference. --&gt; The type's main competitor was the Airbus A300.&lt;ref name=Eden_p104/&gt;

===767-300ER===
[[File:C-FMXC_YVR_(23641586872).jpg|thumb|An [[Air Canada Rouge]] 767-300ER|alt=Side quarter view of twin-engine jetliner in flight, with extended gear; white with red tail paint scheme.]]

The 767-300ER, the extended-range version of the 767-300, entered service with American Airlines in 1988.&lt;ref name=Boe_767_back/&gt; The type's increased range was made possible by greater fuel tankage and a higher MTOW of {{cvt|407000|lb|sigfig=3}}.&lt;ref name=Eden_p104/&gt; Design improvements allowed the available MTOW to increase to {{cvt|412000|lb|sigfig=3}} by 1993.&lt;ref name=Eden_p104/&gt; Power is provided by Pratt &amp; Whitney PW4000, General Electric CF6, or Rolls-Royce RB211 engines.&lt;ref name=Eden_p104/&gt; the 767-300ER comes in three exit configurations: the baseline configuration has four main cabin doors and four over-wing window exits, the second configuration has six main cabin doors and two over-wing window exits; and the third configuration has six main cabin doors, as well as two smaller doors that are located behind the wings.&lt;ref name=&quot;767_airport_report&quot; /&gt; Typical routes for the type include [[Los Angeles International Airport|Los Angeles]] to [[Frankfurt Airport|Frankfurt]].&lt;ref name=763specs/&gt; The combination of increased capacity and range offered by the 767-300ER has been particularly attractive to both new and existing 767 operators.&lt;ref name=e45/&gt; It is the most successful version of the aircraft, with more orders placed than all other variants combined.&lt;ref name=300ER&gt;{{harvnb|Haenggi|2003|p=43}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{as of|2017|November|}}, 767-300ER deliveries stand at 583 with no unfilled orders.&lt;ref name=767_O_D_summ/&gt; There were 376 examples in service {{as of|2018|July|lc=y}}.&lt;ref name=FI_Airlines_2018 /&gt;&lt;!-- Updates require a newer reference. --&gt; The type's main competitor is the [[Airbus A330-200]].&lt;ref name=FlugA330-200&gt;{{cite web |title=Airbus A330-200 |work=Flug Revue |date=July 18, 2000 |url=http://www.flug-revue.rotor.com/frtypen/FRA33020.htm |accessdate=August 18, 2011 |archivedate=February 18, 2001 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20010218184251/http://www.flug-revue.rotor.com/frtypen/FRA33020.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At its 1990s peak, a new 767-300ER was valued at $85 million, dipping to around $12 million in 2018 for a 1996 build.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.aircraftvaluenews.com/b767-300er-historical-value-behavior-defy-expectations/ |title= B767-300ER Historical Value Behavior Defy Expectations |publisher= Aircraft Value News |date= October 29, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===767-300F===
The 767-300F, the production freighter version of the 767-300ER, entered service with UPS Airlines in 1995.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Becher|1999|p=178}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 767-300F can hold up to 24 standard {{convert|88|by|125|in|cm|adj=on}} [[pallet]]s on its main deck and up to 30 LD2 [[unit load device]]s on the lower deck,&lt;ref name=767_airport_report/&gt; with a total cargo volume of {{convert|15469|cuft|sigfig=3}}.&lt;ref name=763Fspecs&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.boeing.com/commercial/767family/pf/pf_300f_prod.html |title=767-300F Technical Characteristics |publisher=Boeing |accessdate=October 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The freighter has a main deck cargo door and crew exit,&lt;ref name=k555&gt;{{harvnb|Kane|2003|p=555}}&lt;/ref&gt; while the lower deck features two starboard-side cargo doors and one port-side cargo door.&lt;ref name=767_airport_report/&gt; A general market version with onboard freight-handling systems, [[refrigeration]] capability, and crew facilities was delivered to [[Asiana Airlines]] on August 23, 1996.&lt;ref name=Eden_p105/&gt; {{as of|2019|August||df=}}, 767-300F deliveries stand at 161 with 61 unfilled orders.&lt;ref name=767_O_D_summ/&gt; Airlines operated 222 examples of the freighter variant and freighter conversions in July 2018.&lt;ref name=FI_Airlines_2018 /&gt;&lt;!-- Updates require a newer reference. --&gt;

In June 2008, All Nippon Airways took delivery of the first 767-300BCF (Boeing Converted Freighter), a modified passenger-to-freighter model.&lt;ref name=bcf&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2008/06/16/224718/st-aero-delivers-worlds-first-767-300bcf-to-all-nippon.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080619071946/http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2008/06/16/224718/st-aero-delivers-worlds-first-767-300bcf-to-all-nippon.html |archivedate=2008-06-19 |title=ST Aero delivers world's first 767-300BCF to All Nippon Airways |first=Leithen |last=Francis |work=Flight International |date=June 16, 2008 |accessdate=August 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The conversion work was performed in Singapore by [[ST Aerospace#Subsidiaries/Divisions|ST Aerospace Services]], the first supplier to offer a 767-300BCF program,&lt;ref name=bcf/&gt; and involved the addition of a main deck cargo door, strengthened main deck floor, and additional freight monitoring and safety equipment.&lt;ref name=faa/&gt; Since then, Boeing, Israel Aerospace Industries, and Wagner Aeronautical have also offered passenger-to-freighter conversion programs for 767-300 series aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2010/10/21/348813/wagner-plans-to-launch-767-cargo-conversion-programme.html |title=Wagner plans to launch 767 cargo conversion programme |work=Air Transport Intelligence |author=Sobie, Brendan |date=October 21, 2010 |accessdate=October 31, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===767-400ER===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Boeing 747]] --&gt;
[[File:Continental Airlines Boeing 767-400ER Wedelstaedt.jpg|thumb|right|The 767-400ER entered service with [[Continental Airlines]] in 2000|alt=Twin-engine airliner with landing gear almost retracted and flaps extended]]

The 767-400ER, the first Boeing wide-body jet resulting from two fuselage stretches,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|1999|p=114}}&lt;/ref&gt; entered service with Continental Airlines in 2000.&lt;ref name=Boe_767_back/&gt; The type features a {{convert|21.1|ft|m|abbr=off|sigfig=3|adj=on}} stretch over the 767-300, for a total length of {{convert|201.25|ft|m|sigfig=3}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|1999|p=120}}&lt;/ref&gt; The wingspan is also increased by {{convert|14.3|ft|m|sigfig=3}} through the addition of [[raked wingtips]].&lt;ref name=Eden_p105/&gt; The exit configuration uses six main cabin doors and two smaller exit doors behind the wings, similar to certain 767-300ER's.&lt;ref name=&quot;767_airport_report&quot; /&gt; Other differences include an updated cockpit, redesigned landing gear, and 777-style Signature Interior.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|1999|pp=119–120, 123}}&lt;/ref&gt; Power is provided by uprated General Electric CF6 engines.&lt;ref name=faa/&gt;

The FAA granted approval for the 767-400ER to operate 180-minute [[ETOPS]] flights before it entered service.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Boeing 767-400ER gets FAA clearance |work=Flight International |url=http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/boeing-767-400er-gets-faa-clearance-68337/ |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130929164638/http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/boeing-767-400er-gets-faa-clearance-68337/ |archivedate=2013-09-29 |date=July 25, 2000 |accessdate=February 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because its fuel capacity was not increased over preceding models, the 767-400ER has a range of {{convert|5625|nmi|km}},&lt;ref name=764specs&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.boeing.com/commercial/aeromagazine/aero_03/textonly/ps01txt.html |title=Introducing the 767-400 Extended Range Airplane |work=AERO Magazine |publisher=Boeing |date=July 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt; less than previous extended-range 767s.&lt;ref name=long/&gt; No 767-400 version was developed.

The longer-range 767-400ERX was offered in July 2000&lt;ref name=Boeing26july2000/&gt; before being cancelled a year later,&lt;ref name=sonic/&gt; leaving the 767-400ER as the sole version of the largest 767.&lt;ref name=f63&gt;{{harvnb|Frawley|2001|p=63}}&lt;/ref&gt; Boeing dropped the 767-400ER and the -200ER from its pricing list in 2014.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://airwaysnews.com/blog/2013/09/19/boeing-drops-the-767-200er-and-767-400er-from-its-pricing-lists-the-end-of-an-era/ |title=Boeing Drops the 767-200ER and 767-400ER from its Pricing List: the End of an Era - Airchive |date=2013-09-19 |language=en-US |access-date=2016-07-17 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160708121139/http://airwaysnews.com/blog/2013/09/19/boeing-drops-the-767-200er-and-767-400er-from-its-pricing-lists-the-end-of-an-era/ |archivedate=July 8, 2016 |df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A total of 37 767-400ERs were delivered to the variant's two airline customers, [[Continental Airlines]] (now merged with [[United Airlines]]) and [[Delta Air Lines]], with no unfilled orders.&lt;ref name=767_O_D_summ/&gt; All 37 examples of the -400ER were in service in July 2018.&lt;ref name=FI_Airlines_2018 /&gt;&lt;!-- Updates require a newer reference. --&gt; One additional example was produced as a military testbed, and later sold as a VIP transport.&lt;ref name=vip764&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Sarsfield |first=Kate |url=http://flightglobal.com/articles/2009/01/27/321681/bahrain-acquires-767-400er-testbed-for-vip-use.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090130070223/http://flightglobal.com/articles/2009/01/27/321681/bahrain-acquires-767-400er-testbed-for-vip-use.html |archivedate=2009-01-30 |title=Bahrain acquires 767-400ER testbed for VIP use |work=Flight International |date=January 27, 2009 |accessdate=January 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The type's closest competitor is the Airbus A330-200.&lt;ref name=Flug767-400&gt;{{cite web |title=Boeing 767-400ER |work=Flug Revue |date=March 4, 2002 |url=http://www.flug-revue.rotor.com/Frtypen/FR767400.htm |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080513172529/http://www.flug-revue.rotor.com/Frtypen/FR767400.htm |archivedate= May 13, 2008 |accessdate=August 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Military and government===
Versions of the 767 serve in a number of military and government applications, with responsibilities ranging from airborne surveillance and refueling to cargo and VIP transport. Several military 767s have been derived from the 767-200ER,&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Birtles|1999|pp=39–46}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ap_20070212/&gt; the longest-range version of the aircraft.&lt;ref name=762specs/&gt;&lt;ref name=k555/&gt;
* '''Airborne Surveillance Testbed''' – the Airborne Optical Adjunct (AOA) was modified from the prototype 767-200 for a [[United States Army]] program, under a contract signed with the [[Strategic Air Command]] in July 1984.&lt;ref name=gao&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dtic.mil/cgi-bin/GetTRDoc?AD=ADA344571 |title=Strategic Defense Initiative Program: Status of Airborne Optical Adjunct and Terminal Imaging Radar |date=June 1986 |publisher=United States Government Accountability Office |accessdate=December 28, 2011 |pages=1, 9, 10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Intended to evaluate the feasibility of using airborne optical sensors to detect and track hostile [[intercontinental ballistic missile]]s, the modified aircraft first flew on August 21, 1987.&lt;ref name=&quot;Janes89&quot;&gt;{{harvnb |Taylor|1989|pp=373–74}}&lt;/ref&gt; Alterations included a large &quot;[[cupola]]&quot; or hump on the top of the aircraft from above the cockpit to just behind the [[trailing edge]] of the wings,&lt;ref name=gao/&gt; and a pair of ventral fins below the rear fuselage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Janes89&quot;/&gt; Inside the cupola was a suite of infrared seekers used for tracking theater ballistic missile launches.&lt;ref name=&quot;Becher_p183-4&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Becher|1999|pp=183–84}}&lt;/ref&gt; The aircraft was later renamed as the Airborne Surveillance Testbed (AST).&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Norris|Wagner|1996|p=87}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the end of the AST program in 2002, the aircraft was retired for scrapping.&lt;ref name=ast&gt;Chism, Neal (March 20, 2006) &quot;Correspondence: Save the First Boeing 767&quot;. ''Aviation Week &amp; Space Technology'', Volume 164, Issue 12, pp. 6–8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- The aircraft was removed from the FAA registry in 2007 and ultimately scrapped.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://registry.faa.gov/aircraftinquiry/NNum_Results.aspx?NNumbertxt=N767BA |title=FAA Registry – Aircraft – N767BA |publisher=FAA |accessdate=February 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Roach, J.R. and Eastwood, A.B. (June 2008). &quot;Jet Airliner Production List Vol. 1: Boeing.&quot; ''Key Publishing'', Aviation Hobby Shop.&lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;

[[File:E-767 Japan AWACS 112010 view.jpg|thumb|[[Japan Self-Defense Forces]] E-767 AWACS|alt=Side view of Japan military reconnaissance aircraft on airport runway, with dorsal mounted sensor pallet]]
* '''[[Boeing E-767|E-767]]''' – the Airborne Early Warning and Control (AWACS) platform for the Japan Self-Defense Forces; it is essentially the [[Boeing E-3 Sentry]] mission package on a 767-200ER platform.&lt;ref name=b39&gt;{{Harvnb|Birtles|1999|pp=44–5}}&lt;/ref&gt; E-767 modifications, completed on 767-200ERs flown from the Everett factory to [[Boeing Defense, Space &amp; Security|Boeing Integrated Defense Systems]] in Wichita, Kansas, include strengthening to accommodate a dorsal surveillance radar system, engine [[nacelle]] alterations, as well as electrical and interior changes.&lt;ref name=poise&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1994/1994%20-%202806.html |title=Boeing poised to fly first 767 AWACS |first=Norris |last=Guy |work=Flight International |date=November 16, 1994 |accessdate=August 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Japan operates four E-767s. The first E-767s were delivered in March 1998.&lt;ref name=aw33&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1998/1998%20-%201967.html |title=Military Aircraft Directory: Boeing |date=July 29, 1998 |work=Flight International |accessdate=December 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:KC-767 Aeronautica Militare tanker refueler 2007.jpg|thumb|right|[[Italian Air Force]] KC-767A tanker|alt=A mostly-gray KC-767, with refueling probe extended, transferring fuel to a B-52 in the left-bottom hand corner]]
* '''[[Boeing KC-767#International programs|KC-767 Tanker Transport]]''' – the 767-200ER-based aerial refueling platform operated by the Italian Air Force (Aeronautica Militare),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.aeronautica.difesa.it/Mezzi/velivoliDotazione/Pagine/KC_767A.aspx |title=Il portale dell'Aeronautica Militare – KC-767A |work=difesa.it |accessdate=April 1, 2015|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150325201519/https://www.aeronautica.difesa.it/Mezzi/velivoliDotazione/Pagine/KC_767A.aspx|archivedate=March 25, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Japan Self-Defense Forces.&lt;ref name=kc767j/&gt; Modifications conducted by Boeing Integrated Defense Systems include the addition of a fly-by-wire refueling boom, strengthened flaps, and optional auxiliary fuel tanks, as well as structural reinforcement and modified avionics.&lt;ref name=kc767/&gt; The four KC-767Js ordered by Japan have been delivered.&lt;ref name=kc767j&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2010/01/14/337167/picture-japan-receives-last-boeing-kc-767-tanker.html|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100118123227/http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2010/01/14/337167/picture-japan-receives-last-boeing-kc-767-tanker.html|archivedate=2010-01-18 |title=Japan receives last Boeing KC-767 tanker |first=Craig |last=Hoyle |work=Flight International |date=January 14, 2010 |accessdate=August 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Aeronautica Militare received the first of its four KC-767As in January 2011.&lt;ref name=kc767a&gt;{{cite web |last=Kington |first=Tom |url=http://www.defensenews.com/story.php?i=5559911&amp;c=EUR&amp;s=AIR|archive-url=https://wayback.archive-it.org/all/20161207155632/http://www.defensenews.com/error-404|url-status=dead|archive-date=December 7, 2016 |title=Italian Air Force Receives 1st Tanker From Boeing |work=Defense News |date=January 27, 2011 |accessdate=January 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''[[Boeing KC-767|KC-767 Advanced Tanker]]''' – the 767-200ER-based aerial tanker developed for the USAF [[KC-X]] tanker competition.&lt;ref name=&quot;kc-x&quot;/&gt; It is an updated version of the KC-767, originally selected as the USAF's new tanker aircraft in 2003, designated KC-767A,&lt;ref name=DoD_4120&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dtic.mil/whs/directives/corres/pdf/412015l.pdf |title=DoD 4120-15L, Model Designation of Military Aerospace Vehicles |publisher=US Department of Defense |date=May 12, 2004|page=30}}&lt;/ref&gt; and then dropped amid conflict of interest allegations.&lt;ref name=&quot;kc-x&quot;/&gt; The KC-767 Advanced Tanker is derived from studies for a longer-range cargo version of the 767-200ER,&lt;ref name=ap_20070212&gt;{{cite news |last=Borak |first=Donna |url=http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/businesstechnology/2003568484_webtanker12.html |title=Boeing unveils tanker for $40&amp;nbsp;billion deal |work=Seattle Times |date=February 12, 2007 |accessdate=January 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;boeing_KC-767Adv&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.boeing.com/news/releases/2007/q1/070212b_nr.html |title=Boeing Offers KC-767 Advanced Tanker to US Air Force |publisher=Boeing |date=February 12, 2007 |accessdate=2015-07-04|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070214105112/http://www.boeing.com/news/releases/2007/q1/070212b_nr.html|archivedate=2007-02-14|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; and features a fly-by-wire [[refueling boom]], a [[Computer stereo vision|remote vision]] refueling system, and a 767-400ER-based flight deck with LCD screens and [[head-up display]]s.&lt;ref name=kc767at/&gt;
* '''[[Boeing KC-46 Pegasus|KC-46]]''' - a 767-based tanker, not derived from the KC-767, awarded as part of the KC-X contract for the USAF.&lt;ref name=herald/&gt;
* '''[[Boeing KC-767#Variants|Tanker conversions]]''' – the 767 MMTT or Multi-Mission Tanker Transport is a 767-200ER-based aircraft operated by the [[Colombian Air Force]] (''Fuerza Aérea Colombiana'') and modified by Israel Aerospace Industries.&lt;ref name=mmtt&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.flightglobal.com/Articles/2010/09/06/347025/pictures-iai-tests-colombias-new-767-tanker.html|archiveurl=https://archive.today/20100909031501/http://www.flightglobal.com/Articles/2010/09/06/347025/pictures-iai-tests-colombias-new-767-tanker.html|archivedate=2010-09-09 |title=IAI tests Colombia's new 767 tanker |first=Arie |last=Egozi |work=Flight International |date=June 9, 2010 |accessdate=September 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2013, the [[Brazilian Air Force]] ordered two 767-300ER tanker conversions from IAI for its KC-X2 program.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.upi.com/Business_News/Security-Industry/2013/03/15/IAI-wins-Brazilian-KC-X-competition/UPI-98451363366032/%E2%89%A5 |title=Israel Aerospace Industries to work in Brazilian tank program |publisher=UPI.com |date=March 15, 2013 |accessdate=June 2, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''[[Northrop Grumman E-10|E-10 MC2A]]''' - the Northrop Grumman E-10 was to be a 767-400ER-based replacement for the USAF's 707-based E-3 Sentry AWACS, [[Northrop Grumman E-8 Joint STARS]], and [[Boeing RC-135|RC-135]] [[SIGINT]] aircraft.&lt;ref name=e10&gt;{{cite web |last=Tirpak |first=John |url=http://www.airforce-magazine.com/MagazineArchive/Pages/2007/October%202007/1007squeeze.aspx |title=The big squeeze |work=Air Force Magazine |date=October 2007 |accessdate=August 30, 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090725003810/http://www.airforce-magazine.com/MagazineArchive/Pages/2007/October%202007/1007squeeze.aspx |archivedate=July 25, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The E-10 would have included an all-new AWACS system, with a powerful [[active electronically scanned array]] (AESA) that was also capable of jamming enemy aircraft or missiles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://aviationweek.com/awin/e-10-radar-secretly-designed-jam-missiles |title=E-10 Radar Secretly Designed To Jam Missiles |first=David |last=Fulghum |work=Aviation Week &amp; Space Technology |date=July 26, 2004 |accessdate=August 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; One 767-400ER aircraft was built as a testbed for systems integration, but the program was terminated in January 2009 and the prototype was later sold to Bahrain as a VIP transport.&lt;ref name=vip764/&gt;

===Undeveloped variants===

====767-X====
{{see also|Boeing 777#Background}}
In 1986, Boeing announced plans for a partial double-deck Boeing 767 design. The aircraft would have combined the Boeing 767-300 with a Boeing 757 cross section mounted over the rear fuselage. The Boeing 767-X would have also featured extended wings and a wider cabin. The 767-X did not get enough interest from airlines to launch and the model was shelved in 1988 in favor of the [[Boeing 777]].&lt;ref&gt;https://secure.boeingimages.com/archive/Boeing-767-X-Concept--1986-2JRSXLJ8PSVI.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://www.skytamer.com/Boeing_767-300.html&lt;/ref&gt;

====767-400ERX====
In March 2000, Boeing was to launch the 259-seat 767-400ERX with an initial order for three from [[Kenya Airways]] with deliveries planned for 2004, as it was proposed to [[Lauda Air]].&lt;!--ref name=Flight20march2000--&gt;
Increased [[MTOW|gross weight]] and a [[tailplane]] fuel tank would have boosted its range by {{cvt|1110 to 12025|km|nmi|-1}}, and GE could offer its {{cvt|65000-68000|lbf|kN}} [[CF6]]-80C2/G2.&lt;ref name=Flight20march2000&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/2000/2000%20-%200694.html |title=Lauda and Kenya eye heavy 767 |last=Norris |first=Guy |work=Flight International |date=March 20, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Rolls-Royce offered its {{cvt|68,000-72,000|lbf|kN}} [[Rolls-Royce Trent#Second Trent 600|Trent 600]] for the 767-400ERX and the [[Boeing 747#747X and 747X Stretch|Boeing 747X]].&lt;ref name=Flight25July2000&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/2000/2000-1%20-%200364.html |title=R-R offers Trent 600 for 767-400ERX and 747X |work=Flight International |author=Julian Moxon, Guy Norris |date=July 25, 2000 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Offered in July, the longer-range -400ERX would have a strengthened wing, fuselage and landing gear for a 15,000&amp;nbsp;lb (6.8 t) higher [[Maximum takeoff weight|MTOW]], up to 465,000&amp;nbsp;lb (210.92 t).&lt;!--ref name=Boeing26july2000--&gt;
Thrust would rise to {{cvt|72,000|lbf|kN}} for better takeoff performance, with the Trent 600 or the General Electric/Pratt &amp; Whitney [[Engine Alliance]] GP7172, also offered on the 747X.&lt;!--ref name=Boeing26july2000--&gt;
Range would increase by 525 nmi (950&amp;nbsp;km) to 6,150 nmi (11,390&amp;nbsp;km), with an additional fuel tank of 2,145 gallons (8,120 l) in the horizontal tail.&lt;!--ref name=Boeing26july2000--&gt;
The 767-400ERX would offer the capacity of the [[Airbus A330-200]] with 3% lower fuel burn and costs.&lt;ref name=Boeing26july2000&gt;{{cite press release |url= https://boeing.mediaroom.com/2000-07-26-The-Newest-Boeing-767-Is-Inspired-By-The-Future-Introducing-The-Boeing-767-400ER |title= The Newest Boeing 767 Is Inspired By The Future - Introducing The Boeing 767-400ER |date= 2000-07-26 |publisher= Boeing}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Boeing cancelled the variant development in 2001.&lt;ref name=sonic/&gt;
Kenya Airways then switched its order to the 777-200ER.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=Wallace |first=James |url=http://www.seattlepi.com/default/article/Kenya-Airways-sticks-to-Boeing-1083149.php |title=Kenya Airways sticks to Boeing |work=Seattle Post-Intelligencer |date=March 19, 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operators==
[[File:Boeing 767-316-ER, LAN Airlines AN1667933.jpg|thumb|right|[[LAN Airlines]] 767-300ER in anniversary scheme at [[Madrid–Barajas Airport]] in 2009|alt=Side angle view of twin-jet aircraft in flight]]
{{Main|List of Boeing 767 operators}}

In July 2018, 742 aircraft were in airline service: 73 -200s, 632 -300 and 37 -400 with 65 -300F on order; the largest operators are [[Delta Air Lines]] (77), [[FedEx Express|FedEx]] (60; largest cargo operator), [[UPS Airlines]] (59), [[United Airlines]] ({{#expr:35+16}}), [[Japan Airlines]] (35), [[All Nippon Airways]] (34).&lt;ref name=FI_Airlines_2018 /&gt;  The type's competitors included the Airbus A300 and A310.&lt;ref name=Becher_p175/&gt;

The largest customers are Delta Air Lines with 117 orders, [[FedEx Express]] (126), All Nippon Airways (96), American Airlines (88), and United Airlines (82).&lt;ref name=767_O_D_summ/&gt; Delta and United are the only customers of all -200, -300 and -400 passenger variants.&lt;ref name=767_O_D_summ/&gt; In July 2015, FedEx placed a firm order for 50 Boeing 767 freighters with deliveries from 2018 to 2023.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.wsj.com/articles/fedex-to-buy-as-many-as-100-boeing-767-freighters-1437522505|title=FedEx to Buy as Many as 100 Boeing 767 Freighters|work=The Wall Street Journal|date=July 21, 2015|accessdate=July 21, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Orders and deliveries===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:right; font-size:96%;&quot;
|-
! Year !! Total !! 2020 !! 2019 !! 2018 !! 2017 !! 2016 !! 2015 !! 2014 !! 2013 !! 2012 !! 2011 !! 2010 !! 2009 !! 2008 !! 2007 !! 2006 !! 2005 !! 2004 !! 2003 !! 2002 !! 2001 !! 2000 !! 1999 !! 1998
|-
! Orders
|'''1,270''' || — || 26 || 40 || 15 || 26 || 49 || 4 || 2 || 22 || 42|| 3|| 7|| 24|| 36|| 10|| 19|| 8|| 11|| 8|| 40|| 9|| 30|| 38
|-
! Deliveries
|'''1,178''' || 2 || 43 || 27 || 10 || 13 || 16 || 6 || 21 || 26 || 20|| 12|| 13|| 10|| 12|| 12|| 10|| 9|| 24|| 35|| 40|| 44|| 44|| 47
|}
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:right; font-size:96%;&quot;
|-
! Year !! 1997 !! 1996 !! 1995 !! 1994 !! 1993 !! 1992 !! 1991 !! 1990 !! 1989 !! 1988 !! 1987 !! 1986 !! 1985 !! 1984 !! 1983 !! 1982 !! 1981 !! 1980 !! 1979 !! 1978
|-
! Orders
| 79||43||22||17||54||21||65||52||100||83||57||23||38||15||20||2||5||11||45||49
|-
! Deliveries
| 42||43||37||41||51||63||62||60||37||53||37||27||25||29||55||20||—||—||—||—
|}
'''Boeing 767 orders and deliveries (cumulative, by year):''' &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;!--------------------------------------------------------------&gt;
&lt;!-- GRAPH OF ORDERS AND DELIVERIES, CUMULATIVE------------------&gt;
&lt;!--------------------------------------------------------------&gt;
&lt;timeline&gt;
ImageSize  = width:auto height:250 barincrement:28
PlotArea   = left:35 bottom:15 top:10 right:18
AlignBars  = justify
DateFormat = yyyy
Period     = from:0 till:1300
TimeAxis   = orientation:vertical
ScaleMajor = unit:year increment:100 start:0

PlotData=
  color:skyblue width:28
  bar:1978 from:start till:49 text:49 align:center
  bar:1979 from:start till:94 text:94 align:center
  bar:1980 from:start till:105 text:105 align:center
  bar:1981 from:start till:110 text:110 align:center
  bar:1982 from:20 till:112 text:112 align:center
  bar:1983 from:75 till:135 text:132 align:center
  bar:1984 from:104 till:147 text:147 align:center
  bar:1985 from:129 till:185 text:185 align:center
  bar:1986 from:156 till:208 text:208 align:center
  bar:1987 from:193 till:265 text:265 align:center
  bar:1988 from:246 till:348 text:348 align:center
  bar:1989 from:283 till:448 text:448 align:center
  bar:1990 from:343 till:500 text:500 align:center
  bar:1991 from:405 till:565 text:565 align:center
  bar:1992 from:468 till:586 text:586 align:center
  bar:1993 from:519 till:640 text:640 align:center
  bar:1994 from:560 till:657 text:657 align:center
  bar:1995 from:597 till:679 text:679 align:center
  bar:1996 from:640 till:722 text:722 align:center
  bar:1997 from:682 till:801 text:801 align:center
  bar:1998 from:729 till:839 text:839 align:center
  bar:1999 from:773 till:869 text:869 align:center
  bar:2000 from:817 till:878 text:878 align:center
  bar:2001 from:857 till:918 text:918 align:center
  bar:2002 from:892 till:926 text:926 align:center
  bar:2003 from:916 till:937 text:937 align:center
  bar:2004 from:925 till:945 text:945 align:center
  bar:2005 from:935 till:964 text:964 align:center
  bar:2006 from:947 till:974 text:974 align:center
  bar:2007 from:959 till:1010 text:1010 align:center
  bar:2008 from:969 till:1034 text:1034 align:center
  bar:2009 from:982 till:1041 text:1041 align:center
  bar:2010 from:994 till:1044 text:1044 align:center
  bar:2011 from:1014 till:1086 text:1086 align:center
  bar:2012 from:1040 till:1108 text:1108 align:center
  bar:2013 from:1061 till:1110 text:1110 align:center
  bar:2014 from:1067 till:1114 text:1114 align:center
  bar:2015 from:1083 till:1163 text:1163 align:center
  bar:2016 from:1096 till:1189 text:1189 align:center
  bar:2017 from:1106 till:1204 text:1204 align:center
  bar:2018 from:1133 till:1244 text:1244 align:center
  bar:2019 from:1176 till:1270 text:1270 align:center
  color:powderblue width:28
  bar:2020 from:1178 till:1270 text:1270 align:center

 color:green width:28–
  bar:1982 from:start till:20 text:20 align:center
  bar:1983 from:start till:75 text:75 align:center
  bar:1984 from:start till:104 text:104 align:center
  bar:1985 from:start till:129 text:129 align:center
  bar:1986 from:start till:156 text:156 align:center
  bar:1987 from:start till:193 text:193 align:center
  bar:1988 from:start till:246 text:246 align:center
  bar:1989 from:start till:283 text:283 align:center
  bar:1990 from:start till:343 text:343 align:center
  bar:1991 from:start till:405 text:405 align:center
  bar:1992 from:start till:468 text:468 align:center
  bar:1993 from:start till:519 text:519 align:center
  bar:1994 from:start till:560 text:560 align:center
  bar:1995 from:start till:597 text:597 align:center
  bar:1996 from:start till:640 text:640 align:center
  bar:1997 from:start till:682 text:682 align:center
  bar:1998 from:start till:729 text:729 align:center
  bar:1999 from:start till:773 text:773 align:center
  bar:2000 from:start till:817 text:817 align:center
  bar:2001 from:start till:857 text:857 align:center
  bar:2002 from:start till:892 text:892 align:center
  bar:2003 from:start till:916 text:916 align:center
  bar:2004 from:start till:925 text:925 align:center
  bar:2005 from:start till:935 text:935 align:center
  bar:2006 from:start till:947 text:947 align:center
  bar:2007 from:start till:959 text:959 align:center
  bar:2008 from:start till:969 text:969 align:center
  bar:2009 from:start till:982 text:982 align:center
  bar:2010 from:start till:994 text:994 align:center
  bar:2011 from:start till:1014 text:1014 align:center
  bar:2012 from:start till:1040 text:1040 align:center
  bar:2013 from:start till:1061 text:1061 align:center
  bar:2014 from:start till:1067 text:1067 align:center
  bar:2015 from:start till:1083 text:1083 align:center
  bar:2016 from:start till:1096 text:1096 align:center
  bar:2017 from:start till:1106 text:1106 align:center
  bar:2018 from:start till:1133 text:1133 align:center
  bar:2019 from:start till:1176 text:1176 align:center
  bar:2020 from:start till:1178 text:1178 align:center
&lt;/timeline&gt;
{{Timeline Legend|colour=skyblue|text=Orders}} {{Timeline Legend|colour=green|text=Deliveries}}
* Data through January 31, 2020.&lt;ref name=&quot;767_O_D_summ&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://active.boeing.com/commercial/orders/displaystandardreport.cfm?cboCurrentModel=767&amp;optReportType=AllModels&amp;cboAllModel=767&amp;ViewReportF=View+Report|title=767 Model Summary (orders and deliveries)|last=|first=|date=January 2019|website=|publisher=Boeing|accessdate=February 11, 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Boeing_yearly_orders/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Boeing_recent_orders&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://active.boeing.com/commercial/orders/index.cfm|title=Boeing Recent Orders|last=|first=|date=August 2018|website=|publisher=Boeing|accessdate=October 18, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Boeing_current_year_deliveries&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://active.boeing.com/commercial/orders/index.cfm?content=displaystandardreport.cfm&amp;RequestTimeout=20000&amp;optReportType=CurYrDelv&amp;pageid=m15520|title=Boeing Company Current Deliveries|last=|first=|date=August 2018|website=|publisher=Boeing|accessdate=October 18, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Boe_O_D_search&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://active.boeing.com/commercial/orders/index.cfm?content=userdefinedselection.cfm&amp;pageid=m15527|title=Orders and Deliveries search page|last=|first=|date=September 2018|website=|publisher=Boeing|accessdate=October 18, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Model summary===
[[File:UR-GEA LLBG 06-12-2013-1.jpg|thumb|[[Ukraine International Airlines]] 767-300ER at [[Ben Gurion Airport]] with optional winglets|alt=Ventral view of twin-jet aircraft in flight]]

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center; font-size:96%;&quot;
|-
! Model Series!!|[[International Civil Aviation Organization|ICAO]] code&lt;ref name=ICAOcode/&gt;||Orders||Deliveries||Unfilled orders
|-
!767-200
|B762
|128||128||—
|-
!767-200ER
|B762
|121||121||—
|-
!767-2C (KC-46)
|B762
|73||35||38
|-
!767-300
|B763
|104||104||—
|-
!767-300ER
|B763
|583||583||—
|-
!767-300F
|B763
|223||169||54
|-
!767-400ER
|B764
|38||38||—
|-
!colspan=2 style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | Total
!1,270||1,178||92
|}
* Data through January 2020.&lt;ref name=767_O_D_summ/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;UPS2018Order&quot; /&gt;

==Accidents and notable incidents==
[[File:Air Canada 767 C-GAUN Gimli Glider.jpg|thumb|The &quot;[[Gimli Glider]]&quot; parked at [[Mojave Air and Space Port]] in February 2008|alt=Side view of a parked Air Canada twin-engine jet in the desert, with stairs mounted next to the aircraft's forward door]]

{{As of|2019|February}}, the Boeing 767 has been in 60 [[Aviation accidents and incidents|aviation occurrences]],&lt;ref name=ASN_767_occur&gt;{{cite web |url=http://aviation-safety.net/database/dblist.php?Type=106 |title=Boeing 767 occurrences |publisher=Aviation Safety Network |date=May 25, 2017 |access-date=May 25, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; including 19 [[hull loss|hull-loss]] accidents.&lt;ref name=&quot;ASN_767_hull-losses&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://aviation-safety.net/database/dblist.php?field=typecode&amp;var=106%&amp;cat=%1&amp;sorteer=datekey&amp;page=1resulting |title=Boeing 767 hull-losses |publisher=Aviation Safety Network |date=May 25, 2017 |access-date=May 25, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Seven fatal crashes, including three [[Aircraft hijacking|hijackings]], have resulted in a total of 854 occupant fatalities.&lt;ref name=&quot;ASN_767_hull-losses&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=ASN_767_stats&gt;{{cite web |url=http://aviation-safety.net/database/type/type-stat.php?type=106 |title=Boeing 767 Statistics |publisher=Aviation Safety Network |date=September 27, 2015 |access-date=September 27, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 767's first incident was [[Gimli Glider|Air Canada Flight 143]], a 767-200, on July 23, 1983. The airplane ran out of fuel in-flight and had to glide with both engines out for almost {{convert|43|nmi|km}} to an emergency landing at [[Gimli, Manitoba]], Canada. The pilots used the aircraft's [[ram air turbine]] to power the [[Hydraulics|hydraulic]] systems for aerodynamic control. There were no fatalities and only minor injuries. This aircraft was nicknamed &quot;Gimli Glider&quot; after its landing site. The aircraft, registered C-GAUN, continued flying for [[Air Canada]] until its retirement in January 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;gimli&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/national/storied-gimli-glider-on-final-approach/article666567/ |title=Storied 'Gimli Glider' on final approach |date=January 24, 2008 |work=Globe and Mail |access-date=August 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The airliner's first fatal crash, [[Lauda Air Flight 004]], occurred near Bangkok on May 26, 1991, following the in-flight deployment of the left engine [[Thrust reversal|thrust reverser]] on a 767-300ER; none of the 223 aboard survived; as a result of this accident all 767 thrust reversers were deactivated until a redesign was implemented.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=James |first=Barry |author-link=Barry James |title=U.S. Orders Thrust Reversers Deactivated on 767s |newspaper=The New York Times |date=August 17, 1991 |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1991/08/17/news/17iht-thru.html |access-date=August 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Investigators determined that an electronically controlled valve, common to late-model Boeing aircraft, was to blame.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://community.seattletimes.nwsource.com/archive/?date=19910901&amp;slug=1303053 |title=Air Disasters: Critics Question FAA's Response |work=Seattle Times |first=Byron |last=Acohido |date=September 1, 1991 |access-date=December 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A new locking device was installed on all affected jetliners, including 767s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://community.seattletimes.nwsource.com/archive/?date=19920526&amp;slug=1493776 |title=New Locks Installed For Boeing Reversers |work=Seattle Times |first=Polly |last=Lane |date=May 26, 1992 |access-date=December 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 31, 1999, [[EgyptAir Flight 990]], a 767-300ER, crashed off [[Nantucket]], Massachusetts, in [[international waters]] killing all 217 people on board.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Accident description |publisher=Aviation Safety Network |date=July 27, 2004 |url=http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=19991031-0 |access-date=January 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The United States [[National Transportation Safety Board]] (NTSB) concluded &quot;not determined&quot;, but determined the probable cause to be due to a deliberate action by the first officer; Egypt disputed this conclusion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Ellison |first=Michael |title=US and Egypt split on fatal plane crash |url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2000/jun/09/egyptaircrash.usa |access-date=August 18, 2011 |newspaper=The Guardian |date=June 9, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
On April 15, 2002, [[Air China Flight 129]], a 767-200ER, [[controlled flight into terrain|crashed into a hill]] amid inclement weather while trying to land at [[Gimhae International Airport]] in Busan, South Korea. The crash resulted in the death of 129 of the 166 people on board, and the cause was attributed to [[pilot error]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Accident description |publisher=Aviation Safety Network |date=August 27, 2005 |url=http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=20020415-0 |access-date=January 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 767 has been involved in six hijackings, three resulting in loss of life,&lt;ref name=ASN_767_occur/&gt; for a combined total of 282 occupant fatalities.&lt;ref name=ASN_767_stats/&gt; On November 23, 1996, [[Ethiopian Airlines Flight 961]], a 767-200ER, was hijacked and crash-landed in the [[Indian Ocean]] near the [[Comoro Islands]] after running out of fuel, killing 125 out of the 175 persons on board;&lt;ref name=ey961&gt;{{cite web |url=http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=19961123-0 |title=Hijacking description |publisher=Aviation Safety Network |date=March 7, 2009 |access-date=January 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; survivors have been rare among instances of land-based aircraft ditching on water.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://edition.cnn.com/2009/US/01/16/air.crash.ditching/index.html |title=Previous jet ditchings yielded survival lessons |publisher=CNN |author=Lendon, Brad |date=January 16, 2009 |access-date=February 5, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://articles.nydailynews.com/2009-01-15/local/17913592_1_plane-st-maarten-pilot |title=A very rare happy ending in Hudson River plane crash |work=New York Daily News |first=Dave |last=Goldiner |date=January 15, 2009 |access-date=August 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two 767s were involved in the [[September 11 attacks]] on the [[World Trade Center (1973–2001)|World Trade Center]] in 2001, resulting in the [[Collapse of the World Trade Center|collapse of its two main towers]]. [[American Airlines Flight 11]], a 767-200ER, crashed into the North Tower, killing all 92 people on board, and [[United Airlines Flight 175]], a 767-200, crashed into the South Tower, with the death of all 65 on board. In addition, more than 2,600 people were killed in the towers or on the ground.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/23/world/threats-responses-excerpts-report-sept-11-commission-unity-purpose.html |title=Threats and Responses; Excerpts from the Report of the Sept. 11 Commission: 'A Unity of Purpose' |work=The New York Times |date=July 23, 2004 |access-date=January 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A foiled [[2001 shoe bomb attempt]] that December involved an American Airlines 767-300ER.&lt;ref name=NYTimes_Shoe_Bomber_sentenced&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/31/us/threats-responses-bomb-plot-unrepentant-shoe-bomber-given-life-sentence-for.html |title=Threats and Responses: The Bomb Plot: Unrepentant Shoe Bomber Is Given a Life Sentence |last=Belluck |first=Pam |date=January 31, 2003 |work=The New York Times |access-date=August 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.tsa.gov/travelers/airtravel/screening/index.shtm |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110511230241/http://www.tsa.gov/travelers/airtravel/screening/index.shtm |archivedate=2011-05-11 |title=TSA Travel Assistant |publisher=US Transportation Security Administration |date=September 26, 2006 |access-date=January 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 1, 2011, [[LOT Polish Airlines Flight 16]], a 767-300ER, safely landed at [[Warsaw Chopin Airport]] in Warsaw, Poland after a mechanical failure of the landing gear forced an emergency landing with the landing gear retracted. There were no injuries, but the aircraft involved was damaged and subsequently written off.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/warsaw-airport-still-closed-after-lot-gear-up-landing-364195/ |title=Warsaw Airport still closed after LOT gear-up landing |work=Flight International |date=November 2, 2011 |access-date=December 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=circuit /&gt;&lt;ref name=checklist&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/lot-767-gear-up-crash-probe-advises-checklist-changes-378418/ |title=LOT 767 gear-up crash probe advises checklist changes |first=David |last=Kaminski-Morrow |work=Flight International |date=November 1, 2012 |access-date=August 20, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the time of the incident, aviation analysts speculated that it may have been the first instance of a complete landing gear failure in the 767's service history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/1111/01/ebo.01.html |title=CNN Transcript - Erin Burnett OutFront |publisher=CNN |date=November 1, 2011 |access-date=December 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequent investigation determined that while a damaged hose had disabled the aircraft's primary landing gear extension system, an otherwise functional backup system was inoperative due to an accidentally deactivated [[circuit breaker]].&lt;ref name=circuit&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/circuit-breaker-at-heart-of-lot-767-gear-up-landing-probe-365584/ |title=Circuit-breaker at heart of LOT 767 gear-up landing probe |work=Flight International |last=Kaminski-Morrow |first=David |date=December 5, 2011 |access-date=December 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=checklist /&gt;

In January 2014, the U.S. [[Federal Aviation Administration]] issued a directive that ordered inspections of the elevators on more than 400 767s beginning in March 2014; the focus was on [[fastener]]s and other parts that can fail and cause the elevators to jam. The issue was first identified in 2000 and has been the subject of several Boeing service bulletins. The inspections and repairs are required to be completed within six years.&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.today/20140421065713/http://online.wsj.com/news/articles/SB20001424052702303277704579344782977995904] Pasztor, Andy. ''FAA orders safety checks on Boeing 767s''. The Wall Street Journal, January 27, 2014, p. B3&lt;/ref&gt; The aircraft has also had multiple occurrences of &quot;uncommanded escape slide inflation&quot; during maintenance or operations,&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.wsj.com/articles/faa-proposes-fixes-to-boeing-767-emergency-escape-slides-1451607836 &quot;FAA Proposes Fixes to Boeing 767 Emergency Escape Slides&quot;]. The Wall Street Journal&lt;/ref&gt; and during flight.&lt;ref&gt;[https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=888&amp;dat=19821026&amp;id=CrlaAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=yl0DAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2611,2550054 ]. St. Petersburg Times&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://edition.cnn.com/2014/06/30/travel/united-airlines-slide-deploy/index.html &quot;Evacuation slide deploys midair on United flight&quot;]. CNN, July 1, 2014&lt;/ref&gt; In late 2015, the FAA issued a preliminary directive to address the issue.&lt;ref&gt;[http://skift.com/2016/01/03/faa-targets-767-escape-slides-that-deploy-when-they-arent-supposed-to/ FAA Targets 767 Escape Slides That Deploy When They Aren't Supposed To] (Skift)&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 28, 2016, [[American Airlines Flight 383 (2016)|American Airlines Flight 383]], a 767-300ER with 161 passengers and 9 crew members, aborted takeoff at Chicago O'Hare Airport following an [[Uncontained engine failure|uncontained failure]] of the right GE CF6-80C2 engine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=GE alerts airlines about engine part after American Airlines fire |url=https://www.reuters.com/article/chicago-airplane-letter-idUSL1N1D60EH |website=Reuters |access-date= November 6, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The engine failure, which hurled fragments over a considerable distance, caused a fuel leak, resulting in a fire under the right wing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=US blames American Airlines fire on engine failure |url=https://www.cnbc.com/2016/11/04/us-blames-american-airlines-fire-on-engine-failure.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fire and smoke entered the cabin. All passengers and crew evacuated the aircraft, with 20 passengers and one flight attendant sustaining minor injuries using the evacuation slides.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Unusual Failure in American Airlines' Jet Engine Prompts Investigation |url=https://www.wsj.com/articles/disc-in-engine-turbine-failed-on-american-airlines-jetliner-1477864909}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://thedailyvoicenews.com/2016/10/28/american-airlines-boeing-767-fire-chicago-engine-failure-rejected-takeoff/ |title=American Airlines Jet Catches Fire at Chicago, No Fatalities |website=The Daily Voice |date=October 28, 2016 |access-date=October 29, 2016 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161029113105/http://thedailyvoicenews.com/2016/10/28/american-airlines-boeing-767-fire-chicago-engine-failure-rejected-takeoff/ |archive-date=October 29, 2016 |url-status=dead |df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On February 23, 2019, [[Atlas Air Flight 3591]], a Boeing 767-300ERF air freighter operating for [[Amazon Air]], crashed into [[Trinity Bay (Texas)|Trinity Bay]] near Houston, Texas, while on descent into [[George Bush Intercontinental Airport]]; both pilots and the single passenger were killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.ntsb.gov/investigations/Pages/DCA19MA086.aspx|title=Atlas Air #3591 crashed into Trinity Bay DCA19MA086|website=www.ntsb.gov|access-date=2019-06-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- Only notable incidents and accidents here --&gt;

==Retirement and display==
[[File:The Spirit of Delta Boeing 767-200.jpg|thumb|&quot;The Spirit of Delta&quot;&lt;!-- retired 767-200 --&gt; at the [[Delta Heritage Museum|Delta Air Lines Air Transport Heritage Museum]]|alt=Side view of a parked Delta Air Lines twin-engine jet in hangar, with stairs mounted next to the aircraft's forward door]]

As new 767s roll off the assembly line, older models have been retired and stored or scrapped. One complete aircraft, N102DA{{mdash}}the first 767-200 to operate for Delta Air Lines and the twelfth example built, is currently on display.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Birtles|1999|pp=55, 116}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=spirit/&gt; It was withdrawn from use and stored at [[Hartsfield–Jackson Atlanta International Airport]] in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.planespotters.net/airframe/Boeing/767/N102DA-Delta-Air-Lines/2xwkcLRE|title=N102DA Delta Air Lines Boeing 767-200|website=Planespotters.net|accessdate=August 25, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The exhibition aircraft, named &quot;The Spirit of Delta&quot; by the employees who helped purchase it in 1982, underwent restoration at the [[Delta Flight Museum]] in Atlanta, Georgia. The restoration was completed in 2010.&lt;ref name=spirit&gt;{{cite web|url=http://deltamuseum.org/M_ExhibitsEvents_SpiritofDelta.htm|title=December 15, 1982: A Special Day for Delta Air Lines|publisher=Delta Air Lines Air Transport Heritage Museum|accessdate=May 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Clear}}

==Specifications==
{|class=wikitable style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;
|+767 Airplane Characteristics
|-
! Variant
! 767-200(ER)
! 767-300(ER/F)
! 767-400ER
|-
! Cockpit crew
| colspan=3| Two
|-
! 3-class seats&lt;ref name=acap-seats&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.boeing.com/assets/pdf/commercial/airports/acaps/767.pdf |title=767 Airplane Characteristics for Airport Planning |publisher=Boeing |date=May 2011 |pages=23–29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| 174 (15{{abbr|F|First class}}, 40{{abbr|J|Business class}}, 119{{abbr|Y|Economy class}})
| 210 (18F, 42J, 150Y)
| 243 (16F, 38J, 189Y)
|-
! 2-class seats&lt;ref name=acap-seats/&gt;
| 214 (18J, 196Y)
| 261 (24J, 237Y)
| 296 (24J, 272Y)
|-
! 1-class&lt;ref name=acap-seats/&gt; (limit&lt;ref name=&quot;rgl.faa.gov&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.airweb.faa.gov/Regulatory_and_Guidance_Library/rgMakeModel.nsf/0/b9e61e631046f10186257fd900588ed4/$FILE/A1NM_Rev35.pdf |title=Type Certificate Data Sheet No. A1NM |date=June 20, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;)
| 245Y (290)
| 290Y (351)
| 409Y (375)
|-
! Cargo&lt;ref name=acap-weights/&gt;
| 3,070&amp;nbsp;ft³ / 86.9 m³
| 4,030&amp;nbsp;ft³ / 114.1 m³{{efn|-300F: 15,469 ft³ / 438 m³, 24 88×108 in pallets&lt;ref name=backgrounder&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.boeing.com/farnborough2014/pdf/BCA/bck-767_5_13_2014.pdf |title=767 Backgrounder |publisher=Boeing Commercial Airplanes |date=February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
| 4,905&amp;nbsp;ft³ / 138.9 m³
|-
! {{abbr|[[Unit load device|ULD]]|Unit load device}}&lt;ref name=767_airport_report&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.boeing.com/assets/pdf/commercial/airports/acaps/767.pdf |title=767 Airplane Characteristics for Airport Planning |publisher=Boeing |date=May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|pages=32–36}}
| 22 LD2s
| 30 LD2s
| 38 LD2s
|-
! Length&lt;ref name=acap-size&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.boeing.com/assets/pdf/commercial/airports/acaps/767.pdf |title=767 Airplane Characteristics for Airport Planning |publisher=Boeing |date=May 2011 |pages=15–18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| 159&amp;nbsp;ft 2 in / 48.51 m
| 180&amp;nbsp;ft 3 in / 54.94 m
| 201&amp;nbsp;ft 4 in / 61.37 m
|-
! Wingspan&lt;ref name=acap-size/&gt;
|colspan=2| 156&amp;nbsp;ft 1 in / 47.57 m
| 170&amp;nbsp;ft 4 in / 51.92 m
|-
! Wing
|colspan=2| 3,050&amp;nbsp;ft² / 283.3 m², 31.5° sweepback&lt;ref name=civilJetAircraftDesign&gt;{{cite web |url=http://booksite.elsevier.com/9780340741528/appendices/data-a/table-3/table.htm |title=Aircraft Data File: Boeing Aircraft |publisher=Elsevier |work=civil jet aircraft design |date=1999}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| 3,130&amp;nbsp;ft² / 290.7 m²&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.flugzeuginfo.net/acdata_php/acdata_7674_en.php |title= Boeing 767-400 |work= Flugzeuginfo |author= Karsten Palt}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! Fuselage
|colspan=3| Exterior: 17&amp;nbsp;ft 9 in / 5.41 m height, 16&amp;nbsp;ft 6 in / 5.03 m width;&lt;ref name=acap-size/&gt; Cabin width: 186 in/ 4.72 m&lt;ref name=767_airport_report/&gt;{{rp|page=30}}
|-
! [[Maximum takeoff weight|MTOW]]&lt;ref name=acap-weights&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.boeing.com/assets/pdf/commercial/airports/acaps/767.pdf |title=767 Airplane Characteristics for Airport Planning |publisher=Boeing |date=May 2011 |pages=9–14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| std: 315,000&amp;nbsp;lb / 142,882&amp;nbsp;kg &lt;br/&gt;ER: 395,000&amp;nbsp;lb / 179,169&amp;nbsp;kg
| std: 350,000&amp;nbsp;lb / 158,758&amp;nbsp;kg &lt;br/&gt;ER/F: 412,000&amp;nbsp;lb / 186,880&amp;nbsp;kg
| 450,000&amp;nbsp;lb / 204,116&amp;nbsp;kg
|-
! Max. [[payload]]&lt;ref name=acap-weights/&gt;&lt;!--MZFW-OEW--&gt;
| {{cvt|{{#expr:250000-176650}}|lb|kg|0}} &lt;br/&gt;ER: {{cvt|{{#expr:260000-181610}}|lb|kg|0}}
| {{cvt|{{#expr:278000-189750}}|lb|kg|0}} &lt;br/&gt;ER: {{cvt|{{#expr:295000-198440}}|lb|kg|0}}{{efn|-300F: {{cvt|{{#expr:309000-190000}}|lb|kg|0}}}}
| {{cvt|{{#expr:330000-229000}}|lb|kg|0}}
|-
! [[Operating empty weight|OEW]]&lt;ref name=acap-weights/&gt;
| 176,650&amp;nbsp;lb / 80,127&amp;nbsp;kg &lt;br/&gt;ER: 181,610&amp;nbsp;lb / 82,377&amp;nbsp;kg
| 189,750&amp;nbsp;lb / 86,069&amp;nbsp;kg &lt;br/&gt;ER: 198,440&amp;nbsp;lb / 90,011&amp;nbsp;kg{{efn|-300F: 190,000&amp;nbsp;lb / 86,183&amp;nbsp;kg}}
| 229,000&amp;nbsp;lb / 103,872&amp;nbsp;kg
|-
! Fuel capacity&lt;ref name=acap-weights/&gt;
|colspan=3| std: 16,700 US gal / 63,217 L (111,890&amp;nbsp;lb / 50,753&amp;nbsp;kg ), ER: 24,140 US gal / 91,380 L (161,740&amp;nbsp;lb / 73,364&amp;nbsp;kg)
|-
! Range&lt;ref name=767specs&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.boeing.com/assets/pdf/commercial/startup/pdf/767_perf.pdf |title=767 performance summary |publisher=Boeing |date=2006 |url-status=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150415224410/http://www.boeing.com/assets/pdf/commercial/startup/pdf/767_perf.pdf |archivedate=April 15, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| std: {{cvt|3,900|nmi|km}}{{efn|216 pax, 176,100 lb / 79,878 kg OEW, ISA}}&lt;ref name=767_airport_report/&gt;{{rp|page=47}} &lt;br/&gt;ER: 6,590 nmi / 12,200&amp;nbsp;km{{efn|181 pax (15F/40J/126Y), CF6}}
| std: {{cvt|3,900|nmi|km}}{{efn|269 pax, 187,900 lb / 85235 kg OEW, ISA}}&lt;ref name=767_airport_report/&gt;{{rp|page=49}} &lt;br/&gt;ER: 5,980 nmi / 11,070&amp;nbsp;km{{efn|218 pax (18F/46J/154Y), PW4000}}{{efn|-300F: 3,225 nmi / 6,025&amp;nbsp;km{{efn|52.7 tonnes payload}}&lt;ref name=backgrounder/&gt;}}
| 5,625 nmi / 10,415&amp;nbsp;km{{efn|245 pax (20F/50J/175Y), CF6}}
|-
! Cruise speed
|colspan=3| Long range: {{cvt|459|kn|km/h}}, Maximum: {{cvt|486|kn|km/h}} at {{cvt|39,000|ft|m}},&lt;ref name=civilJetAircraftDesign/&gt; Ceiling: {{cvt|43,100|ft|m}}&lt;ref name=&quot;rgl.faa.gov&quot;/&gt;
|-
! Takeoff &lt;br /&gt;distance{{efn|MTOW, SL, 30 °C / 86 °F}}&lt;ref name=767specs/&gt;
| std: {{cvt|6,300|ft}}&lt;ref name=767_airport_report/&gt;{{rp|page=58}} &lt;br/&gt;ER: 2,480 m / 8,150&amp;nbsp;ft
| {{cvt|9,200|ft}}&lt;ref name=767_airport_report/&gt;{{rp|page=64}} &lt;br/&gt;ER/F: 2,650 m / 8,700&amp;nbsp;ft
| 3,290 m / 10,800&amp;nbsp;ft
|-
! Engines (×2)&lt;ref name=acap-weights/&gt;
| std: [[Pratt &amp; Whitney JT9D|P&amp;W JT9D]] / [[Pratt &amp; Whitney PW4000|PW4000]] / [[GE CF6]]-80 &lt;br/&gt;ER: [[RB211]]-524
| ER/F: PW4000 / GE CF6-80 / RB211-524 &lt;br/&gt;std: P&amp;W JT9D
| GE CF6-80 / PW4000
|-
! Thrust (×2)&lt;ref name=acap-weights/&gt;
| std: {{cvt|48,000-52,500|lbf|kN|0}} &lt;br/&gt;ER: {{cvt|48,000-60,600|lbf|kN|0}}
| std: {{cvt|48,000-60,600|lbf|kN|0}} &lt;br/&gt;ER/F: {{cvt|56,750-61,500|lbf|kN|0}}
| {{cvt|60,600|lbf|kN|0}}
|}

==See also==
{{Portal|Aviation|United States}}
{{aircontent
|see also= &lt;!-- other related articles that have not already linked: --&gt;
* [[Competition between Airbus and Boeing]]
|related= &lt;!-- designs developed into or from this aircraft: --&gt;
* {{annotated link|Boeing 757}}&lt;ref name=no20/&gt;
* {{annotated link|Boeing E-767}}&lt;ref name=b39/&gt;
* {{annotated link|Boeing KC-46 Pegasus}}&lt;ref name=herald/&gt;
* {{annotated link|Boeing KC-767}}&lt;ref name=kc767/&gt;
* {{annotated link|Northrop Grumman E-10 MC2A}}&lt;ref name=e10/&gt;
|similar aircraft= &lt;!-- aircraft that are of similar Role, Era, and Capability this design: --&gt;
* {{annotated link|Airbus A300}}&lt;ref name=Becher_p175/&gt;
* {{annotated link|Airbus A310}}&lt;ref name=Becher_p175/&gt;
* {{annotated link|Airbus A330-200}}&lt;ref name=FlugA330-200/&gt;
* {{annotated link|Boeing Business Jet}}
* {{annotated link|Boeing 777}}
* {{annotated link|Boeing 787 Dreamliner}}
* {{annotated link|McDonnell Douglas DC-10}}
|lists= &lt;!-- Relevant lists that this aircraft appears in. --&gt;
* [[List of jet airliners]]
* [[List of civil aircraft]]
&lt;!-- See [[WP:Air/PC]] for more explanation of these fields. --&gt;
}}

==References==
===Notes===
{{notelist}}

===Citations===
{{Reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin|40em}}
* {{Cite book|last=Becher|first=Thomas|title=Boeing 757 and 767|publisher=Crowood Press|location=Marlborough, Wiltshire|year=1999|isbn=1-86126-197-7|ref={{harvid|Becher|1999}}}}
* {{Cite book|last=Birtles|first=Philip|title=Modern Civil Aircraft: 6, Boeing 757/767/777. ''3rd ed.''|publisher=Ian Allan Publishing|location=London|year=1999|isbn=0-7110-2665-3|ref={{harvid|Birtles|1999}}}}
* {{Cite book|last1= Davies |first1= R.E.G. |title=TWA: an airline and its aircraft|publisher=Paladwr Press|year=2000|location=McLean, Virginia|isbn=1-888962-16-X|ref={{harvid|Davies|2000}}}}
* {{Cite book|editor-last=Donald|editor-first=David|title=The Complete Encyclopedia of World Aircraft|publisher=Barnes &amp; Noble Books|location=New York, NY|year=1997|isbn=0-7607-0592-5|ref={{harvid|Donald|1997}}}}
* {{Cite book|editor-last=Eden|editor-first=Paul |title=Civil Aircraft Today: The World's Most Successful Commercial Aircraft|publisher=Amber Books Ltd|location= Silverdale, Washington|year=2008|isbn=1-84509-324-0|ref={{harvid|Eden|2008}}}}
* {{Cite book|last1=Frawley|first1= Gerard |title=The International Directory of Civil Aircraft|year=2001|publisher=Aerospace Publications|location=Weston Creek, Australian Capital Territory|isbn=1-875671-52-8|ref={{harvid|Frawley|2001}}}}
* {{Cite book|last=Haenggi|first=Michael|title=767 Transatlantic Titan. ''&quot;Boeing Widebodies&quot; series''|publisher=Motorbooks International|location=Osceola, Wisconsin|year=2003|isbn=0-7603-0842-X|ref={{harvid|Haenggi|2003}}|url=https://archive.org/details/boeingwidebodies00mich}}
* {{Cite book|last1=Kane|first1=Robert M.|title=Air Transportation 1903–2003. ''14th ed.''|year=2003|publisher=Kendall Hunt Publishing|location=Dubuque, Iowa|isbn=978-0-7872-8881-5|ref={{harvid|Kane|2003}}}}
* {{Cite book|last1=Norris|first1=Guy|last2= Wagner|first2=Mark|title=Boeing Jetliners|year=1996|publisher=MBI Publishing|location=Osceola, Wisconsin|isbn=0-7603-0034-8|ref={{harvid|Norris|Wagner|1996}}}}
* {{Cite book|last1=Norris|first1=Guy|last2=Wagner|first2=Mark|title=Boeing|publisher=MBI Publishing|year=1998|location=Osceola, Wisconsin|isbn=0-7603-0497-1|ref={{harvid|Norris|Wagner|1998}}}}
* {{Cite book|last1=Norris|first1=Guy|last2=Wagner|first2=Mark|chapter=767: Stretching and Growing|title=Modern Boeing Jetliners|publisher=Zenith Imprint|location=Osceola, Wisconsin|year=1999|isbn=0-7603-0717-2|ref={{harvid|Norris|Wagner|1999}}}}
* {{Cite book|last1=Norris|first1=Guy|last2=Wagner|first2=Mark|title=Boeing 777, The Technological Marvel|publisher=Zenith Press|location=Osceola, Wisconsin|year=2001|isbn=0-7603-0890-X|ref={{harvid|Norris|Wagner|2001}}}}
* {{Cite book|last1=Norris|first1=Guy|last2=Wagner|first2=Mark|title=Boeing 787 Dreamliner|location= Osceola, Wisconsin|publisher=Zenith Press|year=2009|isbn=978-0-7603-2815-6|ref={{harvid|Norris|Wagner|2009}}}}
* {{Cite book|last=Shaw|first=Robbie|title=Boeing 757 &amp; 767, Medium Twins|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=Reading, Pennsylvania|year=1999|isbn=1-85532-903-4|ref={{harvid|Shaw|1999}}}}
* {{Cite book|last=Smil|first=Vaclav|title=Transforming the Twentieth Century: Technical Innovations and Their Consequences|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford, Oxfordshire|year=1998|isbn=0-19-516875-5|ref={{harvid|Smil|1998}}}}
* {{Cite book|last=Sutter|first=Joe|authorlink=Joe Sutter|title=747: Creating the World's First Jumbo Jet and Other Adventures from a Life in Aviation|location=Washington, D.C.|publisher=Smithsonian Books|year=2006|isbn=0-06-088241-7|ref={{harvid|Sutter|2006}}|url=https://archive.org/details/747creatingworld00sutt}}
* {{cite book|editor-last=Taylor|editor-first=John W.R.|title=Jane's All the World's Aircraft 1989–90|year=1989|publisher=Jane's Yearbooks|location=London|isbn=0-7106-0896-9|ref={{harvid|Taylor|1989}}}}
* {{Cite book|last1=Wells|first1=Alexander T.|last2=Rodrigues|first2=Clarence C.|title=Commercial Aviation Safety|publisher=McGraw-Hill Professional|location= New York, NY|year=2004|isbn=0-07-141742-7|ref={{harvid|Wells|Clarence|2004}}}}
* {{Cite book|last=Wilson|first=Stewart|title=Ansett: The Story of the Rise and Fall of Ansett, 1936–2002|publisher=Aerospace Publications|year=2002|isbn=978-1-875671-57-1|location= Weston Creek, Australian Capital Territory|ref={{harvid|Wilson|2002}}}}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category}}
{{external media | topic = Flight International cutaway diagrams
|image1 = [https://web.archive.org/web/20110414123006/http://www.flightglobal.com/airspace/media/civilaviation1949-2006cutaways/images/7825/boeing-757-767-cutaway.jpg Boeing 757/767]
|image2 = [https://web.archive.org/web/20110414123018/http://www.flightglobal.com/airspace/media/civilaviation1949-2006cutaways/images/7827/boeing-767-400er-cutaway.jpg Boeing 767-400ER]}}
* {{Official website}}
* {{cite web|url=http://www.boeing.com/commercial/aeromagazine/aero_03/ps/ps01/index.html|title=Introducing the 767-400ER|publisher=Boeing|work=Aero Magazine|date=July 1998}}
* {{cite news|url=https://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1999/1999%20-%202521.html|title=Strategic stretch|work=Flight International|date=25 August 1999}}
* {{cite web|url=http://www.boeing.com/resources/boeingdotcom/company/about_bca/startup/pdf/freighters/767BCF.pdf|title=767-300BCF converted freighter|publisher=Boeing|date=2007|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160705064012/http://www.boeing.com/resources/boeingdotcom/company/about_bca/startup/pdf/freighters/767BCF.pdf|archivedate=July 5, 2016|df=mdy-all}}

{{Boeing 767 related}}
{{Boeing airliners}}
{{Boeing 7x7 timeline}}
{{Boeing model numbers}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Boeing aircraft|767]]
[[Category:Twinjets]]
[[Category:1980s United States airliners]]
[[Category:Boeing 767]]
[[Category:Aircraft first flown in 1981]]</text>
      <sha1>ljgtv87tj67epxt80iirwdk5b69il1t</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
