  <page>
    <title>Battle of Lostwithiel</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4160</id>
    <revision>
      <id>936429149</id>
      <parentid>931410507</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-18T20:21:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Gazamp</username>
        <id>34220856</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* See also */ Added [[Portal:Cornwall]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2014}}
{{Use British English|date=September 2014}}
{{No footnotes|date=April 2008}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict=Battle of Lostwithiel
| partof=the [[First English Civil War]]
| date=13 August – 2 September 1644
| place= near [[Lostwithiel]] in [[Cornwall]]
| coordinates={{Coord|50.408|-4.667|display=inline,title|region:GB_scale:20000}}
| result=Royalist victory
| combatant1=[[Cavalier|Royalists]]
| combatant2=[[Roundhead|Parliamentarians]]
| commander1=[[File:Coat of Arms of England (1603-1649).svg|25px]][[Charles I of England]]
| commander2=[[Robert Devereux, 3rd Earl of Essex|Earl of Essex]]
| strength1=
| strength2=
| casualties1= 
| casualties2=
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox First English Civil War}}
}}

The '''Battles of Lostwithiel''' or '''Lostwithiel Campaign''', took place near [[Lostwithiel]] and [[Fowey]] in Cornwall during the [[First English Civil War]] in 1644. They resulted in victory for the Royalists commanded by [[Charles I of England|King Charles]] over the Parliamentarians commanded by the [[Robert Devereux, 3rd Earl of Essex|Earl of Essex]].

==Prelude==
After defeating the army of Sir [[William Waller]] at the [[Battle of Cropredy Bridge]], King Charles marched west in pursuit of the Parliamentarian army of the Earl of Essex, who was invading the Royalist stronghold of [[Cornwall]].

Essex had been misled into believing that he could expect substantial support from the people of Cornwall. When he had reached [[Bodmin]] on 28 July, he found that there was no chance of supplies or recruits, and he also learned that the Royalist army was at [[Launceston, Cornwall|Launceston]], close to his rear. He withdrew to [[Lostwithiel]], covering the port of [[Fowey]]. Essex had previously arranged to rendezvous at Fowey with the Parliamentarian fleet under the [[Robert Rich, 2nd Earl of Warwick|Earl of Warwick]], but no ships appeared. Warwick was unable to leave [[Portsmouth]] because of westerly winds.

Charles's army had been reinforced as it marched, and outnumbered that of Essex by nearly two to one. The first clashes took place on 2 August, but little action took place for several days, as the King waited for all his forces to arrive and Essex waited for the fleet.

==Battle==
On 13 August, the Royalists began to attack in earnest, occupying several outposts on the east bank of the [[River Fowey]], making it even more difficult for help to reach Essex. A half-hearted Parliamentarian attempt to send a relieving force under Lieutenant General [[John Middleton, 1st Earl of Middleton|Middleton]] was defeated at [[Bridgwater]] in [[Somerset]].

On 21 August, the Royalists attacked Essex's positions north of Lostwithiel, capturing the ruins of [[Restormel Castle]]. Royalist cavalry threatened to cut the Parliamentarians off from Fowey. Essex realised that there was no hope of relief and ordered his cavalry to break out of the encirclement. Under Sir [[William Balfour (general)|William Balfour]], they broke through the Royalist lines on the night of 31 August, and although closely pursued they eventually reached safety at the Parliamentary garrison of [[Plymouth]] thirty miles to the east.

The increasingly demoralised Parliamentarian infantry fell back towards Fowey in pouring rain. They were forced to abandon several guns which became bogged down in the muddy roads. On 1 September, the pursuing Royalists captured [[Castle Dore]], an Iron Age hillfort, which the Parliamentarians were using to anchor their lines. Essex left Sir [[Philip Skippon]], his Sergeant Major General of Foot, in command while he himself escaped to Plymouth in a fishing boat.

On 2 September, Skippon, having been told that his infantry were unable to break out as the cavalry had done, and having been offered generous terms by the King, surrendered 6,000 infantry and all his army's guns and train.

==Aftermath==
The disarmed soldiers marched eastward to Portsmouth in continuing bad weather, being continually robbed and threatened by local people. About 1,000 died of exposure and hunger, and 1,000 more deserted or fell sick.

Charles meanwhile wheeled about and marched towards London.

This setback for Parliament in [[Cornwall]], and the last major victory for the Royalists, was reversed by [[Sir Thomas Fairfax]] leading the [[New Model Army]] at or near [[Tresillian|Tresillian Bridge]], close to [[Truro]] on 12 March 1645.

==See also==
{{Portal|Cornwall}}
*[[Battle of Braddock Down]] which took place in January 1643 a few miles from Lostwithiel.
*[[Cornwall in the English Civil War]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
* ''Cornwall in the Great Civil War and Interregnum 1642 – 1660''; by Mary Coate. Oxford : Clarendon Press, 1933.
* ''Battles Royal – Charles I and the Civil War in Cornwall and the West''; by H. Miles Brown. Libra Books, 1982 {{ISBN|0-9508009-0-2}}
* ''The Civil War in South-West England 1642–1646''; by John Barratt {{ISBN|978-1-84415-146-2}}
* ''Civil War Battles in Cornwall, 1642 to 1646''; by [[Richard Holmes (military historian)|Richard Holmes]], Mercia, 1989 {{ISBN|0-948087-32-3}}
* ''Faction and Faith: politics and religion of the Cornish gentry before the Civil War''; by [[Anne Duffin]]. University of Exeter, 1996 {{ISBN|978-0-85989-435-7}}
* ''Carew: A Story of Civil War in the West Country''; by Dennis Russell. Aidan Ellis Publishing, 2001 {{ISBN|0-85628-298-7}}
* {{Cite book|date=2004|title=Lostwithiel 1644: the Campaign and the Battles |first=Stephen |last=Ede-Borrett |publisher=The Pike and Shot Society |oclc=63144022}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Lostwithiel, Battle of 1644}}
[[Category:Battles of the English Civil Wars]]
[[Category:Military history of Cornwall]]
[[Category:1644 in England]]
[[Category:Battles involving the Cornish]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1644]]
[[Category:17th century in Cornwall]]
[[Category:Lostwithiel|Battle of]]</text>
      <sha1>3d3w266zsqfu8a2b1n2tsuptu6imd68</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
