  <page>
    <title>Bouldering</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4113</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943369744</id>
      <parentid>941892893</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T14:19:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelink 2 books for [[Wikipedia:Verifiability|verifiability]]. [goog]) #IABot (v2.0) ([[User:GreenC bot|GreenC bot]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Form of rock climbing}}
{{good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2013}}
{{Climbing sidebar|image=Bouldering.jpg|caption=Bouldering in [[Idyllwild, California]]}}

'''Bouldering''' is a form of [[rock climbing]] that is performed on small rock formations or artificial [[climbing wall|rock walls]] without the use of ropes or [[Climbing harness|harnesses]]. While bouldering can be done without any equipment, most climbers use [[climbing shoe]]s to help secure footholds, [[Magnesium carbonate|chalk]] to keep their hands dry and to provide a firmer grip, and [[bouldering mat]]s to prevent injuries from falls. Unlike [[free solo climbing]], which is also performed without ropes, bouldering problems (the sequence of moves that a climber performs to complete the climb) are usually less than 6 meters (20&amp;nbsp;ft.) tall. Traverses, which are a form of boulder problem, require the climber to climb horizontally from one end to another.&lt;ref name=&quot;Access2006&quot;/&gt;{{rp|3}} [[Indoor climbing|Artificial climbing walls]] allow boulderers to train indoors in areas without natural boulders. In addition, [[Competition climbing|bouldering competitions]] take place in both indoor and outdoor settings.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.stonecountry.co.uk/page11.html ''The Boulder: A Philosophy for Bouldering'' (Stone Country Press)] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130816065033/http://www.stonecountry.co.uk/page11.html |date=16 August 2013 }}, by Francis Sanzaro, for a more on bouldering movement, and its relation to other sports. I also found [https://drive.google.com/file/d/0By3ygZspcP4WcDZsYnU2alpRLUk/edit this article] from Sanzaro on bouldering philosophy and landscape, called &quot;[https://drive.google.com/file/d/0By3ygZspcP4WcDZsYnU2alpRLUk/edit When the Earth Enters You – Movement Aesthetics].&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

The sport was originally a method of training for roped climbs and [[mountaineering]], so climbers could practice specific moves at a safe distance from the ground. Additionally, the sport served to build stamina and increase finger strength &lt;ref&gt;Banaszczyk J., &quot;Eva López MaxHangs Hangboard Routine for finger strength&quot;, ''StrengthClimbing.com'', Apr. 29, 2019. https://strengthclimbing.com/eva-lopez-maxhangs/&lt;/ref&gt;.  Throughout the 20th century, bouldering evolved into a separate discipline.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hill|first=Pete|title=The Complete Guide to Climbing and Mountaineering|year=2008|publisher=David&amp;Charles|location=Cincinnati, OH 45236|isbn=978-0-7153-2842-2|page=94}}&lt;/ref&gt; Individual problems are assigned ratings based on difficulty. Although there have been various [[Grade (bouldering)|rating systems]] used throughout the history of bouldering, modern problems usually use either the V-scale or the [[Fontainebleau rock climbing|Fontainebleau]] scale.

The growing popularity of bouldering has caused several environmental concerns, including soil [[erosion]] and trampled vegetation, as climbers hike off-trail to reach bouldering sites. This has caused some landowners to restrict access or prohibit bouldering altogether.

== Outdoor bouldering ==
[[File:Hueco Tanks - Baby Martini - V6.webm|thumb|Bouldering in [[Hueco Tanks]]: ''Baby Martini'' (V6)]][[File:The Cliffs at DUMBO.jpg|thumb|right|The largest outdoor bouldering gym in North America, The Cliffs at DUMBO, is located in [[Brooklyn Bridge Park]].&lt;ref&gt;https://dumbo.is/hometo/cliffs-at-dumbo&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://www.timeout.com/newyork/news/the-largest-outdoor-climbing-gym-in-the-country-is-returning-to-brooklyn-bridge-park-050718&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The characteristics of boulder problems depend largely on the type of rock being climbed. For example, [[granite]] often features long [[Crack climbing|cracks]] and [[slab climbing|slab]]s while [[sandstone]] rocks are known for their steep overhangs and frequent horizontal breaks. [[Limestone]] and [[volcanic rock]] are also used for bouldering.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lourens2005&quot;/&gt;{{rp|21–22}}

There are many prominent bouldering areas throughout the United States, including [[Hueco Tanks]] in Texas, [[Mount Evans]] in Colorado, and [[The Buttermilks]] in [[Bishop, California]]. [[Squamish, British Columbia]] is one of the most popular bouldering areas in Canada.&lt;ref name=&quot;Robinson2013&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Rock Climbing |year=2013 |author= Robinson, Victoria |publisher=ABC-CLIO |isbn=9780313378621 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3OkUEt8CuXQC }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|80–81}} Europe also hosts a number of bouldering sites, such as [[Fontainebleau]] in France, [[Albarracín]] in Spain, and various mountains throughout [[Switzerland]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.climb-europe.com/areas.htm|title=Rock climbing in Europe |publisher=Climb Europe |year=2013 |accessdate=10 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Africa's most prominent bouldering areas include the more established Rocklands in South Africa, the newer Oukaimeden in Morocco or more recently opened areas like Chimanimani in Zimbabwe.

== Indoor bouldering ==
{{details|Indoor climbing}}
[[File:ボルダリング (7955003588).jpg|alt=An indoor bouldering gym|thumb|An indoor bouldering gym]]
Artificial climbing walls are used to simulate boulder problems in an indoor environment, usually at [[climbing gym]]s. These walls are constructed with wooden panels, [[polymer]] cement panels, [[concrete]] shells, or precast molds of actual rock walls.&lt;ref name=&quot;StiehlRamsey2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Climbing Walls |author1=Stiehl, Jim  |author2=Ramsey, Tim B.  |lastauthoramp=yes |year=2005 |publisher=Human Kinetics |isbn=9780736048316 |url=https://archive.org/details/climbingwallscom0000stie|url-access=registration }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|49–51}} Holds, usually made of [[plastic]], are then bolted onto the wall to create problems.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lourens2005&quot;/&gt;{{rp|18}} The walls often feature steep overhanging surfaces which force the climber to employ highly technical movements while supporting much of their weight with their upper body strength.&lt;ref name=&quot;Burbach2005&quot;/&gt;{{rp|133}} However, in more recent times, many problems set on flat walls now require the climber to execute a series of coordinated movements in order to complete the route. These routes were likely to have originated at the Stuntwerk&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.stuntwerk-koeln.de/shop_en|title=Trainingsgeräte Klettern, Parkour und Ninja Warrior im Stuntwerk|website=www.stuntwerk-koeln.de|language=de|access-date=2019-12-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; gym in Germany, and the style of climbing can be said to closely resemble the sport of [[Parkour]]. The [[IFSC Climbing World Championships]] have noticeably included more of such problems in their competitions as of late.

Climbing gyms often feature multiple problems within the same section of wall. In the US the most common method routesetters use to designate the intended problem is by placing colored tape next to each hold. For example, red tape would indicate one bouldering problem while green tape would be used to set a different problem in the same area.&lt;ref name=&quot;Burbach2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=Gym Climbing |author=Burbach, Matt |publisher=The Mountaineers Books |year=2005 |isbn=9781594854804 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=48IYcqzwfHoC}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|48}} Across much of the rest of the world problems and grades are usually designated using a set color of plastic hold to indicate problems and their difficulty levels. Using colored holds to set has certain advantages, the most notable of which are that it makes it more obvious where the holds for a problem are, and that there is no chance of tape being accidentally kicked off footholds. Smaller, resource-poor climbing gyms may prefer taped problems because large, expensive holds can be used in multiple routes by marking them with more than one color of tape.

== Grading ==
[[File:Indoor Bouldering V3 Rock Spot.webm|right|thumb|150px|A climber completing an indoor V3 problem]]

{{Main|Grade (bouldering)}}

Bouldering problems are assigned numerical difficulty ratings by routesetters and climbers. The two most widely used rating systems are the V-scale and the Fontainebleau system.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hill2008&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Complete Guide to Climbing and Mountaineering |author=Hill, Pete |publisher=David &amp; Charles |year=2008 |isbn=9780715328422 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=OsL2ifP6JucC }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|234}}

The V-scale, which originated in the United States, is an open-ended rating system with higher numbers indicating a higher [[degree of difficulty]]. The V1 rating indicates that a problem can be completed by a novice climber in good physical condition after several attempts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sherman2001&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=Sherman Exposed | author=Sherman, John | publisher=The Mountaineers Books |year=2001 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Tp7eUBRn4M4C |isbn=9781594853968}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|66}} The scale begins at V0, and as of 2013, the highest V rating that has been assigned to a bouldering problem is V17.&lt;ref name=first9Aboulder /&gt; Some climbing gyms also use a VB grade to indicate beginner problems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.spadout.com/wiki/index.php/Climbing_Grades |title=Climbing Grades |publisher=Spadout |accessdate=4 August 2013 |year=2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131029194956/http://www.spadout.com/wiki/index.php/Climbing_Grades |archivedate=29 October 2013 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Fontainebleau scale follows a similar system, with each numerical grade divided into three ratings with the letters ''a'', ''b'', and ''c''. For example, Fontainebleau 7A roughly corresponds with V6, while Fontainebleau 7C+ is equivalent to V10.&lt;ref name=&quot;Horan2008&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Falcon Guides Bouldering Colorado |author=Horan, Bob |publisher=Globe Pequot |year=2008 |isbn=9780762736386 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=UqWepPShgIoC}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|3}} In both systems, grades are further differentiated by appending &quot;+&quot; to indicate a small increase in difficulty. Despite this level of specificity, ratings of individual problems are often controversial, as ability level is not the only factor that affects how difficult a problem may be for a particular climber. Height, arm length, [[flexibility]], and other body characteristics can also be relevant to perceived difficulty.&lt;ref name=&quot;Horst2012&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Learning to Climb Indoors |author=Horst, Eric J. |edition =2nd | year=2012 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wrekMmogxqoC |isbn=9780762780051 |publisher=Globe Pequot}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|11–12}}

== Highball bouldering ==
Highball bouldering is simply climbing high, difficult, long, and tall boulders. Using the same protection as standard bouldering climbers venture up house-sized rocks that test not only their physical skill and strength but mental focus. Highballing, like most of climbing, is open to interpretation. Most climbers say anything above 15 feet is a highball and can range in height up to 35–40 feet where highball bouldering then turns into [[free soloing]].

Highball bouldering may have begun in 1961 when [[John Gill (climber)|John Gill]], without top-rope rehearsal, bouldered a steep face on a 37-foot (11 meter) granite spire called &quot;''The Thimble''&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.mountainproject.com/area/105714549/the-thimble|title=Rock Climbing in Custer State Park|website=Mountain Project|access-date=2018-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.redbull.com/int-en/episodes/AP-1M8AK3NFD2111|title=High &amp; Mighty: Part 1}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[File:The_Thimble.jpg|thumb|right|150px|Climber on the Thimble in the 1960s]]The difficulty level of this ascent (V4/5 or 5.12a), when considered a rock climb, was extraordinary for that period.&lt;ref&gt;''Climbing Magazine'', Millennium Special, March (2000)&lt;/ref&gt;  Gill's achievement initiated a wave of climbers making ascents of large boulders. Later, with the introduction and evolution of crash pads, climbers were able to push the limits of highball bouldering ever higher.

In 2002 [[Jason Kehl]] completed the first highball at double-digit V-difficulty, called Evilution, a 55-foot (18 meter) boulder in the Buttermilks of California, earning the grade of V12.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.mountainproject.com/route/105908296/evilution|title=Climb Evilution, Sierra Eastside|website=Mountain Project|access-date=2018-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; This climb marked the beginning of a new generation of highball climbing that pushed not only height, but great difficulty.{{Citation needed|date=August 2019}}It is not unusual for climbers to rehearse such risky problems on top-rope, although this practice is not a settled issue.

Groundbreaking ascents in this style include; ''Ambrosia'', a 55-foot (18 meter) boulder in Bishop, California, climbed by [[Kevin Jorgeson]] in 2015 sporting the grade of V11.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.mountainproject.com/route/110088205/ambrosia|title=Climb Ambrosia, Sierra Eastside|website=Mountain Project|access-date=2018-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Too Big to Flail,'' V10, another 55 foot (18 meter) line in Bishop, California, climbed by [[Alex Honnold]] in 2016.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.mountainproject.com/route/111711154/too-big-to-flail|title=Climb Too Big To Flail, Sierra Eastside|website=Mountain Project|access-date=2018-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Livin' Large'', a 35-foot V15 in Rocklands, South Africa, found and established by [[Nalle Hukkataival]] in 2009, which has been repeated by only one person, [[Jimmy Webb (climber)|Jimmy Webb]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.hardclimbs.info/climbs/livin-large|title=HardClimbs.info {{!}} Ascents for Livin' Large|website=www.hardclimbs.info|access-date=2018-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''The Process'' is a 55-foot V16 in Bishop, California, first climbed by [[Daniel Woods]] in 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/daniel-woods-climbs-process-v16-highball-bishop-ca-david-clifford|title=Daniel Woods climbs &quot;The Process&quot; a V16 highball in Bishop, CA.|date=2015-02-02|access-date=2018-03-28|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; The line was worked with another climber, Dan Beal, but a hold broke after Woods's top and the climb has yet to see a second ascent as of Sep 28, 2017. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.outsideonline.com/2237961/12-great-moments-bouldering-history|title=12 Great Moments in Bouldering History|website=www.outsideonline.com|access-date=2020-01-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Competitions ==
Traditionally, competition in bouldering was informal, with climbers working out problems near the limits of their abilities, then challenging their peers to repeat these accomplishments. However, modern climbing gyms allow for a more formal competitive structure.

The [[International Federation of Sport Climbing]] (IFSC) employs an indoor format (although competitions can also take place in an outdoor setting&lt;ref name=&quot;Lourens2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Guide to Climbing |author=Lourens, Tony |publisher=Stackpole Books |year=2005 |isbn=9780811701525 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=mdQcBNKK1iIC}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|18}}) that breaks the competition into three rounds: qualifications, semi-finals, and finals. The rounds feature different sets of four to six boulder problems, and each competitor has a fixed amount of time to attempt each problem. At the end of each round, competitors are ranked by the number of completed problems with ties settled by the total number of attempts taken to solve the problems.&lt;ref name=&quot;IFSC Rules&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=IFSC Rules 2013 |url=https://climbgearhub.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/IFSC_Rules_2013_V1-2.pdf |format=PDF |publisher=International Federation of Sport Climbing |date=March 2013 |accessdate=25 June 2013 }}{{dead link|date=July 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some competitions only permit climbers a fixed number of attempts at each problem with a timed rest period in between.
&lt;ref name=&quot;Hague2011&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Redpoint |author1=Hague, Dan  |author2=Hunter, Douglas  |lastauthoramp=yes |year=2011 |publisher=Stackpole Books |isbn=9780811745079 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|175}} In an open-format competition, all climbers compete simultaneously, and are given a fixed amount of time to complete as many problems as possible. More points are awarded for more difficult problems, while points are deducted for multiple attempts on the same problem.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmid2011&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Climbing – Philosophy for Everyone |author = Schmid, Stephen E. |publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons |year=2011 |isbn=9781444341461 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Ilq1usRiD2EC}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|201}}

[[File:BW 2012-08-26 Dorothea Karalus GER 0541.JPG|right|thumb|150px|A competitor at the 2012 Boulder World Cup]]

In 2012, the IFSC submitted a proposal to the [[International Olympic Committee]] (IOC) to include [[lead climbing]] in the [[2020 Summer Olympics]]. The proposal was later revised to an &quot;overall&quot; competition, which would feature bouldering, lead climbing, and [[speed climbing]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.climbing.com/news/new-olympic-plan-climbers-must-compete-in-bouldering-lead-and-speed/ |title=New Olympic Plan: Climbers Must Compete in Bouldering, Lead, and Speed |last=MacDonald |first=Dougald |publisher=Climbing.com |date=20 March 2013 |accessdate=9 July 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2013, the IOC announced that climbing would not be added to the 2020 Olympic program.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.climbing.com/news/climbing-out-of-the-olympic-games-running/ |title=Climbing Out of the Running for Olympic Games |date=29 May 2013 |accessdate=9 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2016, the [[International Olympic Committee]] (IOC) officially approved climbing as an Olympic sport &quot;in order to appeal to younger audiences.&quot; The Olympics will feature the earlier proposed overall competition. Medalists will be competing in all three categories for a best overall score.&lt;ref&gt;Corrigan, Kevin. http://www.climbing.com/news/climbing-officially-approved-for-2020-olympics/ N.p., 3 Aug. 2016. Web. 12 Nov. 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; The score will be calculated by the multiplication of the positions that the climbers have attained in each discipline of climbing.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.climbing.com/competition/a-guide-to-the-olympic-climbing-format/|title=A Guide to the Tokyo 2020 Olympic Climbing Format|last=Burgman|first=John|website=Climbing Magazine|language=en-us|access-date=2019-12-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
Rock climbing first appeared as a sport in the late-1800s. Early records describe climbers engaging in what is now referred to as bouldering, not as a separate discipline, but as a playful form of training for larger ascents. It was during this time that the words &quot;bouldering&quot; and &quot;problem&quot; first appeared in British climbing literature. [[Oscar Eckenstein]] was an early proponent of the activity in the British Isles.&lt;ref&gt;The Origins of Bouldering. http://www.johngill.net&lt;/ref&gt; In the early 20th century, the [[Fontainebleau]] area of [[France]] established itself as a prominent climbing area, where some of the first dedicated ''bleausards'' (or &quot;boulderers&quot;) emerged. One of those athletes, [[Pierre Allain]], invented the specialized shoe used for rock climbing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Beal2011&quot;/&gt;{{rp|ch.&amp;nbsp;1}}

[[File:Gill_on_The_Scab_,_1963_,_The_Needles_of_the_Balck_Hills,_SD.jpg|thumb|165px|Gill on the Scab in the Needles of the Black Hills 1963]]
In the late 1950s through the 1960s, American mathematician [[John Gill (climber)|John Gill]] pushed the sport further and contributed several important innovations, distinguishing bouldering as a separate discipline in the process.&lt;ref name=Master&gt;Ament, Pat (1998). ''John Gill:Master of Rock. Climbing Classics #2'', Stackpole Books&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube|8FdMLil9lNU}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gill previously pursued [[gymnastics]], a sport which had an established scale of difficulty for movements and body positions, and shifted the focus of bouldering from reaching the summit to navigating a set of holds.&lt;ref name=&quot;Beal2011&quot;/&gt;{{rp|ch.&amp;nbsp;1}} Gill developed a rating system that was closed-ended: B1 problems were as difficult as the most challenging roped routes of the time, B2 problems were more difficult, and B3 problems had been completed once.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sherman2001&quot;/&gt;{{rp|64–65}}

Gill introduced [[magnesium carbonate|chalk]] as a method of keeping the climber's hands dry, promoted a dynamic climbing style, and emphasized the importance of [[strength training]] to complement skill.&lt;ref&gt;For more on Gill's bouldering philosophy, see [http://www.stonecountry.co.uk/page11.html ''The Boulder: A Philosophy for Bouldering'' (Stone Country Press)] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130816065033/http://www.stonecountry.co.uk/page11.html |date=16 August 2013 }}, by Francis Sanzaro (Stone Country press, 2013).&lt;/ref&gt;  As Gill improved in ability and influence, his ideas became the norm.&lt;ref name=&quot;Beal2011&quot;/&gt;{{rp|ch.&amp;nbsp;1}}

In the 1980s, two important training tools emerged. One important training tool was [[bouldering mat]]s, also referred to as &quot;crash pads,&quot; which protected against injuries from falling and enabled boulderers to climb in areas that would have been too dangerous otherwise. The second important tool was indoor climbing walls, which helped spread the sport to areas without outdoor climbing and allowed serious climbers to train year-round.&lt;ref name=&quot;Beal2011&quot;/&gt;{{rp|ch.&amp;nbsp;1}}

As the sport grew in popularity, new bouldering areas were developed throughout Europe and the United States, and more athletes began participating in bouldering competitions. The visibility of the sport greatly increased in the early 2000s, as [[YouTube]] videos and climbing [[blog]]s helped boulderers around the world to quickly learn techniques, find hard problems, and announce newly completed projects.&lt;ref name=&quot;Beal2011&quot;/&gt;{{rp|ch.&amp;nbsp;1}}

[[File:Christian Core on Gioia.jpg|thumb|[[Christian Core]] on ''Gioia'' ([[Varazze]], [[Italy|ITA]]), first {{Boulder grade|8C+}} boulder in history, 2008]]
[[File:Midnight Lightning yosemite.jpg|thumb|Michael Rael Armas on ''Midnight Lightning'', [[Camp 4 (Yosemite)|Camp 4]] ([[Yosemite National Park]], [[United States|USA]]), one of the world's most famous bouldering problems]]

=== Notable ascents ===
{{Main|Notable first free ascents}}
{{Boulder grade|9A}} (unconfirmed):

:*''Burden of Dreams'' – Lappnor ([[Finland|{{ISO 3166 code-3|Finland}}]]) – October 2016 – Grade proposed by Nalle Hukkataival after several years of trials. During these years, Hukkataival &quot;very quickly&quot; solved several 8C and 8C+ boulder problems throughout the world, including ''Gioia'' (see below). Compared to these other problems, ''Burden of Dreams'' felt &quot;way way harder&quot;.&lt;ref name=first9Aboulder&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.planetmountain.com/en/news/climbing/nalle-hukkataival-climbs-burden-of-dreams-and-proposes-worlds-first-9a-boulder-problem.html|title=Nalle Hukkataival climbs Burden of Dreams and proposes world's first 9a boulder problem|date=24 October 2016|editor=Planet Mountain|accessdate=25 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4DQf7aGO1uU|title=Interview: Nalle Hukkataival – Burden of Dreams (9A bloc)|publisher=Relais Vertical|accessdate=2 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:* ''No Kapote Only'' - Fontainebleau ([[France|FR]]) - December 2018 - First ascent by [[Charles Albert (climber)]]; world's second 9A (unconfirmed).&lt;ref name=NoKapoteOnly1&gt;{{web cite|url=https://www.planetmountain.com/en/news/climbing/charles-albert-at-fontainebleau-climbs-world-s-second-9a-boulder-problem.html|title=Charles Albert at Fontainebleau climbs world's second 9A boulder problem|editor=planetmountain.com|accessdate=7 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Boulder grade|8C+}}:

:*''Gioia'' – [[Varazze]] ([[Italy|ITA]]) – 2008 – First ascent by Italian boulderer [[Christian Core]], who first proposed 8C, &quot;to play things safe&quot;. In 2011, [[Adam Ondra]] repeated the ascent and wholeheartedly proposed the 8C+ grade, describing the boulder as one of the hardest in the world, together with ''Terranova'' (see below).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.planetmountain.com/en/news/climbing/adam-ondra-the-pure-gioia-interview.html|title=Adam Ondra, the pure Gioia interview|publisher=Planetmountain|date=7 December 2011 |accessdate=1 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:* ''Terranova'' – [[Holstejn]] ([[Moravsky Kras]], [[Czech Republic|CZE]]) – 10 November 2011 – First ascent by Adam Ondra.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.planetmountain.com/en/news/climbing/adam-ondra-frees-terranova-8c-.html|title=Adam ondra frees Terranova 8C+|date=15 November 2011 |accessdate=1 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ukclimbing.com/news/item.php?id=64987|title=8C+ boulder by Ondra|work=UKClimbing.com|last=Pohl|first=Björn|accessdate=7 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Boulder grade|8C}}:

:*''The story of two worlds'' – [[Cresciano]] ([[Switzerland|SUI]]) – January 2005 – First confirmed 8C in history, by [[Dave Graham (climber)|Dave Graham]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news |url=http://www.freakclimbing.com/modules.php?name=News&amp;file=article&amp;sid=389|title=Dave Graham, 'The story of two worlds' his new 8C and his new grading philosophy|publisher=FreakClimbing|date=19 January 2005|accessdate=1 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Five years earlier, [[Fred Nicole]] had proposed 8C for ''Dreamtime'', on the other side of the same boulder, but most repeaters downgraded it to 8b+ (see below).
:* ''The Game'' – [[Boulder, Colorado]] ([[United States|USA]]) – 2010 – First ascent by Daniel Woods, who originally graded it {{Boulder grade|8C+}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.planetmountain.com/english/News/shownews1.lasso?l=2&amp;keyid=37243 |title=Daniel Woods plays The Game Fb8C+ |publisher=PlanetMountain |date=12 February 2010 |accessdate=11 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Second ascent in 2013 by Carlo Traversi, who proposed {{Boulder grade|8C}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://climbingnarc.com/2011/03/carlo-traversi-repeats-the-game-v15-in-boulder-canyon/|title=Carlo Traversi repeats The Game (V15) in boulder canyon|publisher=Climbing Narc|date= 12 March 2011|accessdate=1 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.dpmclimbing.com/articles/view/carlo-traversi-sends-game-v1516 |title=Carlo Traversi Sends The Game (V15/16) |publisher=DPM Climbing |date=12 March 2011 |accessdate=11 August 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140201221735/http://www.dpmclimbing.com/articles/view/carlo-traversi-sends-game-v1516 |archive-date=1 February 2014 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
:* ''Lucid Dreaming'' – [[Bishop, California]] ([[United States|USA]]) – 2010 – First ascent by [[Paul Robinson (climber)|Paul Robinson]], who initially graded it {{Boulder grade|8C+}},&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.planetmountain.com/english/News/shownews1.lasso?l=2&amp;keyid=37330 |title=Lucid Dreaming, new extreme boulder problem at the Buttermilks, Bishop |publisher=PlanetMountain |date=31 March 2010 |accessdate=11 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and later downgraded it. In 2010, together with ''The game'' (see above), this was considered to be one of the world's most challenging boulders. Second ascent by Daniel Woods, who confirmed the {{Boulder grade|8C}} grade.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://climbingnarc.com/2014/01/daniel-woods-does-repeat-lucid-dreaming/ |title=Daniel Woods Does Repeat Lucid Dreaming |publisher=Climbing Narcissist |date=28 January 2014 |accessdate=30 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:* ''Horizon'' - Mount Hiei ([[Japan|JPN]]) - 22 March 2016 - Second ascent and first female ascent by [[Ashima Shiraishi]]; world's first female 8C ascent. At the time, Ashima Shiraishi was the youngest person to send 8C. First ascent by [[Dai Koyamada]] in 2015.&lt;ref name=Horizon1&gt;{{web cite|url=https://rockandice.com/climbing-news/ashima-shiraishi-on-horizon-v15-sleepy-rave-v15-young-guns/|title=Ashima Shiraishi on Horizon (V15), Sleepy Rave (V15) &amp; &quot;Young Guns&quot;|editor=Rock and Ice|accessdate=7 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:* ''Sleepy Rave'' - Hollow Mountain Cave, Grampians ([[Australia|AUS]]) - 2 August 2016 - First female ascent by Ashima Shiraishi; world's second female 8C ascent. First ascent by Dai Koyamada in 2004.&lt;ref name=SleepyRave1&gt;{{web cite|url=https://rockandice.com/climbing-news/ashima-tops-second-v15-sleepy-rave-grampians-australia/|title=Ashima Tops Second V15, Sleepy Rave, Grampians, Australia|editor=Rock and Ice|accessdate=7 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some suggest this problem's rating is really V14.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.nationalgeographic.com/adventure/adventurers-of-the-year/2017/ashima-shiraishi-sport-climber-boulderer/|title=Could This 15-Year-Old Redefine Rock Climbing?|date=2016-11-03|access-date=2017-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.hardclimbs.info/climbs/sleepy-rave|title=HardClimbs.info {{!}} Ascents for Sleepy Rave|website=www.hardclimbs.info|access-date=2017-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:* ''Kryptos'' - Morchelstock, Balsthal ([[Switzerland|SUI]]) - June, 2018 - First female ascent by [[Kaddi Lehmann]]; world's third female 8C ascent. First ascent by Franz Widmer in 2008.&lt;ref name=Kryptos1&gt;{{web cite|url=https://onbouldering.com/kaddi-lehmann-repeats-kryptos-8c-v15-becomes-the-second-woman-to-climb-the-grade/|title=Kaddi Lehmann repeats Kryptos 8C|editor=onbouldering.com|accessdate=7 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:* ''Byaku-dou'' - Mt. Hourai ([[Japan|JPN]]) - May, 2019 - First female ascent by [[Mishka Ishi]]; world's fourth female 8C ascent. To date, Mishka Ishi is the youngest person to send 8C. First ascent by Dai Koyamada in 2003.&lt;ref name=Byakudou1&gt;{{web cite|url=https://rockandice.com/climbing-news/mishka-ishi-13-becomes-youngest-ever-to-send-v15/|title=Mishka Ishi, 13, Becomes Youngest Ever to Send V15!|editor=Rock and Ice|accessdate=7 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Boulder grade|8b+}}:

:*''Dreamtime'' – [[Cresciano]] ([[Switzerland|SUI]]) – 28 October 2000 – First ascent by Fred Nicole, who proposed an 8C rating, making it the first unconfirmed 8C boulder in history. In 2002, Dave Graham repeated it by finding a different solution. He used a [[Glossary of climbing terms#heel hook|heel-hook]] to make the brutal start sequence easier, and downgraded the problem to easy 8b+. Most of the following repeaters, including Adam Ondra, [[Chris Sharma]], and Daniel Woods adopted Graham's solution and agreed with him about the grade.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.99boulders.com/hardest-boulder-problems|title=Hardest boulder problems|publisher=99boulders|date=26 October 2016|accessdate=1 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Dreamtime&gt;{{cite news |url=https://community.mammut.ch/t5/Mammut-Magazine/The-Classics-Dreamtime/ba-p/2875|title=The classics – Dreamtime|magazine=Mammut Magazine|date=5 July 2017|accessdate=1 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Notable exceptions are [[Jan Hojer]] and [[Christian Core]], who confirmed the 8C rating.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.8a.nu/?IncPage=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.8a.nu%2Fuser%2FProfile.aspx%3FUserId%3D16898 Hojer Comments about Dreamtime on 8a.nu]&lt;/ref&gt;
:* ''Catharsis'' - Shiobara ([[Japan|JPN]]) - October, 2012 - First female ascent by [[Tomoko Ogawa]]; world's first female 8B+ ascent. First ascent by Dai Koyamada.&lt;ref name=Catharsis1&gt;{{web cite|url=https://www.ukclimbing.com/news/2012/10/tomoko_ogawa_first_woman_to_boulder_8b+-67550|title=INTERVIEW: Tomoko Ogawa, first woman to boulder 8B+|editor=UKC|accessdate=7 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Boulder grade|7B+}}:

:*''[[Midnight Lightning (bouldering)|Midnight Lightning]]'' – [[Camp 4 (Yosemite)|Camp 4]] ([[Yosemite National Park]], [[United States|USA]]) – 1978 – First ascent by [[Ron Kauk]]. First female ascent by [[Lynn Hill]], 1998.&lt;ref name=natgeo&gt;
{{cite magazine |url=http://adventure.nationalgeographic.com/2008/09/yosemite/climbing-photosynth-text |title=Yosemite in 3-D |last=Rich |first=Corey |date=August 2008 |accessdate=9 May 2013 |magazine=National Geographic}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=SI1986&gt;
{{Cite web |url=http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/vault/article/magazine/MAG1064893/5/index.htm |title=On The Rocks, Kauk Is It |last=Moses |first=Sam |work=Sport Illustrated |date=2 June 1986 |accessdate=9 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=difficulty&gt;
{{Cite web |url=https://www.mountainproject.com/v/midnight-lightning/105835104 |title=Midnight Lightning – Mountain Project}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thirty-nine years after its solution, it has been described as one of the world's most famous bouldering problems, together with ''Dreamtime'' (see above).&lt;ref name=Dreamtime /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite web |url=http://www.planetmountain.com/english/News/shownews1.lasso?l=2&amp;keyid=40853 |title=Midnight Lightning bolt, the icon of free climbing in Yosemite disappears for a day |publisher=planetmountain.com |date=7 May 2013 |accessdate=9 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Equipment ==
{{Main|Rock-climbing equipment}}

Unlike other climbing sports, bouldering can be performed safely and effectively with very little equipment, an aspect which makes the discipline highly appealing, but opinions differ.&lt;ref name=&quot;Beal2011&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= Bouldering: Movement, Tactics, and Problem Solving |author = Beal, Peter | year=2011 | publisher = The Mountaineers Books | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=Ei5GEfWDrKYC | isbn=9781594855016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|ch.&amp;nbsp;2}} While bouldering pioneer [[John Sherman (climber)|John Sherman]] asserted that &quot;The only gear really needed to go bouldering is boulders,&quot; others suggest the use of climbing shoes and a chalkbag – a small pouch where ground-up chalk is kept – as the bare minimum, and more experienced boulderers typically bring multiple pairs of climbing shoes, chalk, brushes, crash pads, and a skincare kit.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sherman2011&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= Better Bouldering | author = Sherman, John | edition = 2nd | year = 2011 | publisher = Globe Pequot | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=AqYzRslaVYAC | isbn=9780762775583 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|1}} &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.nomadcolorado.com/best-beginner-bouldering-areas-near-denver/|title=Best Beginner Bouldering Areas Near Denver - Nomad Colorado|date=2017-04-21|work=Nomad Colorado|access-date=2017-06-07|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Beal2011&quot; /&gt;{{rp|ch.&amp;nbsp;2}}

[[File:Quechua climbing shoes.jpg|right|thumb|150px|A modern climbing shoe manufactured by [[Quechua (brand)|Quechua]] ]]

Climbing shoes have the most direct impact on performance. Besides protecting the climber's feet from rough surfaces, climbing shoes are designed to help the climber secure footholds. Climbing shoes typically fit much tighter than other athletic footwear and often curl the toes downwards to enable precise footwork. They are manufactured in a variety of different styles to perform in different situations. For example, High-top shoes provide better protection for the ankle, while low-top shoes provide greater flexibility and freedom of movement. Stiffer shoes excel at securing small edges, whereas softer shoes provide greater sensitivity. The front of the shoe, called the &quot;toe box,&quot; can be asymmetric, which performs well on overhanging rocks, or symmetric, which is better suited for vertical problems and [[slab climbing|slabs]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Sherman2011&quot;/&gt;{{rp|1}}&amp;thinsp;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kidd2009&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= Rock Climbing |author1=Kidd, Timothy W.  |author2=Hazelrigs, Jennifer  |lastauthoramp=yes |year=2009 |publisher=Human Kinetics |isbn=9781450409001 |url=https://archive.org/details/rockclimbingoutd00wild |url-access= registration }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|116}}&amp;thinsp;&lt;ref name=&quot;Beal2011&quot;/&gt;{{rp|ch.&amp;nbsp;2}}

To absorb sweat, most boulderers use [[magnesium carbonate|gymnastics chalk]] on their hands, stored in a chalkbag, which can be tied around the waist (also called sport climbing chalkbags), allowing the climber to reapply chalk during the climb.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kidd2009&quot;/&gt;{{rp|119}} There are also versions of floor chalkbags (also called bouldering chalkbags), which are usually bigger than sport climbing chalkbags and are meant to be kept on the floor while climbing; this is because boulders do not usually have so many movements as to require chalking up more than once. Different sizes of [[brush]]es are used to remove excess chalk and debris from boulders in between climbs; they are often attached to the end of a long straight object in order to reach higher holds.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sherman2011&quot;/&gt;{{rp|6}} Crash pads, also referred to as [[bouldering mat]]s, are foam cushions placed on the ground to protect climbers from falls.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sherman2011&quot;/&gt;{{rp|6–7}}

== Safety ==
[[File:Joshue Tree National Park - Manx Boulder - 6.jpg|thumb|227x227px|Climber with crash pad and spotters for safety]]
Boulder problems are generally shorter than {{convert|20|ft|m}} from ground to top.&lt;ref name=&quot;Access2006&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.accessfund.org/atf/cf/%7B1F5726D5-6646-4050-AA6E-C275DF6CA8E3%7D/BoulderingPaper.pdf |format=PDF |title=Bouldering: Understanding and Managing Climbing on Small Rock Formations |year=2006 |accessdate=4 August 2013 |publisher=The Access Fund |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131029190025/http://www.accessfund.org/atf/cf/%7B1F5726D5-6646-4050-AA6E-C275DF6CA8E3%7D/BoulderingPaper.pdf |archivedate=29 October 2013 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|3}} This makes the sport significantly safer than [[free solo climbing]], which is also performed without ropes, but with no upper limit on the height of the climb.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hattingh2000&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Rock and Wall Climbing | author = Hattingh, Garth | publisher = Stackpole Books | year = 2000 | isbn = 9780811729161 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=-RZvVKB4600C }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|10–11}} However, minor injuries are common in bouldering, particularly [[sprained ankle]]s and [[sprained wrist|wrists]]. Two factors contribute to the frequency of injuries in bouldering: first, boulder problems typically feature more difficult moves than other climbing disciplines, making falls more common. Second, without ropes to arrest the climber's descent, every fall will cause the climber to hit the ground.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sherman2001&quot;/&gt;

To prevent injuries, boulderers position [[bouldering mat|crash pads]] near the boulder to provide a softer landing, as well as one or more [[Spotting (climbing)|spotters]] (people watching out for the climber to fall in convenient position) to help redirect the climber towards the pads.&lt;ref name=&quot;Access2006&quot;/&gt;{{rp|3}} Upon landing, boulderers employ falling techniques similar to those used in [[gymnastics]]: spreading the impact across the entire body to avoid [[bone fracture]]s, and positioning limbs to allow joints to move freely throughout the impact.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Bouldering Safety |url=http://www.mec.ca/AST/ContentPrimary/Learn/Climbing/IntroToClimbing/SaferBouldering.jsp |publisher= Mountain Equipment Co-op |author1=Thomson, Jeff  |author2=Bourdon, Marc  |lastauthoramp=yes |accessdate=4 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Technique ==
Although every type of rock climbing requires a high level of technique and strength, bouldering - the most dynamic form of the sport -  requires the highest level of power, and thus places considerable strain on the body. Training routines that strengthen fingers and forearms are useful in preventing injuries such as [[tendonitis]] and ruptured ligaments.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://rockandice.com/rock-climbing-training/injury-free-bouldering-15-tips-to-keep-you-healthy-and-strong/|title=Injury-Free Bouldering: 15 Tips to Keep You Healthy and Strong|website=Rock and Ice|language=en-US|access-date=2020-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, as with other forms of climbing, bouldering technique begins with proper footwork. [[Leg muscles]] are significantly stronger than [[arm|arm muscles]]; thus, proficient boulderers use their arms to maintain balance and body positioning as much as possible, relying on their legs to push them up the rock.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sherman2011&quot;/&gt;{{rp|52}} Boulderers also keep their arms straight with their shoulders engaged whenever feasible, allowing their bones to support their body weight rather than their muscles.&lt;ref name=&quot;Long1997&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=Sport Climbing | author=Long, John | year=1997 | edition = 3rd | publisher = Globe Pequot | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=YZSAnneM-OkC | isbn = 9781575400785}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|60–61}}

Bouldering movements are described as either &quot;static&quot; or &quot;dynamic.&quot; Static movements are those that are performed slowly, with the climber's position controlled by maintaining contact on the boulder with the other three limbs. Dynamic movements use the climber's [[momentum]] to reach holds that would be difficult or impossible to secure statically, with an increased risk of falling if the movement is not performed accurately.&lt;ref name=&quot;Humi2002&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Coaching Climbing |author=Humi, Michelle |year=2002 |publisher=Globe Pequot |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=giNqB3LifocC |isbn=9780762725342}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|70}}

== Environmental impact ==
Bouldering can damage vegetation that grows on rocks, such as [[moss]]es and [[lichen]]s. This can occur as a result of the climber intentionally cleaning the boulder, or unintentionally from repeated use of handholds and footholds. Vegetation on the ground surrounding the boulder can also be damaged from overuse, particularly by climbers laying down crash pads. [[Soil erosion]] can occur when boulderers trample vegetation while hiking off of established trails, or when they unearth small rocks near the boulder in an effort to make the landing zone safer in case of a fall.&lt;ref name=&quot;Access2006&quot;/&gt;{{rp|4–6}} The repeated use of white climbing chalk can damage the rock surface of boulders and cliffs, particularly sandstone and other porous rock types, and the scrubbing of rocks to remove chalk can also degrade the rock surface.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.thoughtco.com/use-colored-chalk-to-leave-no-trace-755626|title=Use Colored Climbing Chalk to Leave No Trace|work=ThoughtCo|access-date=2017-10-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; For avoiding chalk damaging the surface of the rock, it is important to remove it gently with a brush after a rock climbing session. Other environmental concerns include [[littering]], improperly disposed [[feces]], and [[graffiti]]. These issues have caused some land managers to prohibit bouldering, as was the case in Tea Garden, a popular bouldering area in [[Rocklands, South Africa]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.planetmountain.com/english/News/shownews1.lasso?l=2&amp;keyid=41107 |title=Rocklands bouldering at risk |date=31 July 2013 |accessdate= 4 August 2013 |publisher=PlanetMountain}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}
{{Commons category|Bouldering}}

{{Climbing navbox}}
{{Extreme sports}}

[[Category:Types of climbing]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Sport climbing]]</text>
      <sha1>bub2qilpcjix2t0cs327t6bjxhlttnf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
