  <page>
    <title>Boston Herald</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4171</id>
    <revision>
      <id>936767112</id>
      <parentid>928954520</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-20T21:50:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Toohool</username>
        <id>1648777</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Awards */ link to the 1924 prize-winning editorial at wikisource</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|US newspaper}}
{{Use American English|date = September 2019}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=May 2016}}
{{Infobox newspaper
| name = Boston Herald
| logo = Boston-herald.svg
| image = Boston Herald (cover).jpg
| image_size=283px
| caption =
| type = [[Daily newspaper]]
| format = [[Tabloid (newspaper format)|Tabloid]]
| foundation = 1846
| owners = [[Digital First Media]]
| publisher = Kevin Corrado&lt;ref name=march19/&gt;
| editor = Joe Sciacca
| circulation = 40,000 weekdays in 2018&lt;br /&gt;73,913 Saturdays in Q1–2 FY2013&lt;br /&gt;45,833  Sundays
| headquarters =  100 Grossman Dr. 4th Floor&lt;br /&gt;[[Braintree, Massachusetts]] 02184&lt;br /&gt;[[United States]]
| website = [http://www.bostonherald.com/ www.BostonHerald.com]
| ISSN = 0738-5854
|}}

The '''''Boston Herald''''' is an American [[daily newspaper]] whose primary market is [[Boston]], [[Massachusetts]] and its surrounding area. It was founded in 1846 and is one of the oldest daily newspapers in the United States. It has been awarded eight [[Pulitzer Prize]]s in its history, including four for editorial writing and three for [[photography]] before it was converted to [[Tabloid (newspaper format)|tabloid]] format in 1981. The ''Herald'' was named one of the &quot;10 Newspapers That 'Do It Right'{{-&quot;}} in 2012 by ''[[Editor &amp; Publisher]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Kristina Ackermann, &quot;[http://www.editorandpublisher.com/Archive/10-Newspapers-That-Do-It-Right-2012  10 Newspapers That 'Do It Right' 2012]&quot;. ''Editor &amp; Publisher'', March 12, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 2017, the ''Herald'' filed for [[bankruptcy]]. On February 14, 2018, [[Digital First Media]] successfully bid $11.9 million to purchase the company in a bankruptcy auction;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Digital First wins Boston Herald auction with $11.9M bid|url=http://www.bostonherald.com/business/business_markets/2018/02/digital_first_wins_boston_herald_auction_with_119m_bid|newspaper=Boston Herald}}&lt;/ref&gt; the acquisition was completed on March 19, 2018.&lt;ref name=march19&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.bostonherald.com/business/business_markets/2018/03/digital_first_media_acquires_the_boston_herald |title=Digital First Media acquires the Boston Herald |newspaper=Boston Herald |date=March 19, 2018 |accessdate=March 19, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of August 2018, the paper employs approximately 110 total employees now, compared to about 225 before the sale.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Carlock |first=Catherine |url=https://www.bizjournals.com/boston/news/2018/08/28/boston-herald-publisher-announces-move-to.html |title=Boston Herald publisher announces move to Braintree |work=[[Boston Business Journal]] |date=2018-08-29 |accessdate=2018-08-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
The ''Herald''{{'s}} history can be traced back through two lineages, the ''[[Boston Daily Advertiser|Daily Advertiser]]'' and the old ''Boston Herald'', and two media moguls, [[William Randolph Hearst]] and [[Rupert Murdoch]].

[[Image:Old Boston Herald Building.png|thumb|left|The old Herald headquarters at 255 Washington Street (built 1878)]]

===The original ''Boston Herald''===
The original ''Boston Herald'' was founded in 1846 by a group of Boston printers jointly under the name of John A. French &amp; Company. The paper was published as a single two-sided sheet, selling for one cent. Its first editor, [[William O. Eaton]], just 22 years old, said &quot;The ''Herald'' will be independent in politics and religion; liberal, industrious, enterprising, critically concerned with literacy and dramatic matters, and diligent in its mission to report and analyze the news, local and global.&quot;

In 1847, the ''Boston Herald'' absorbed the Boston ''American Eagle'' and the Boston ''Daily Times''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = King | first = Moses | title =  King's Hand-book of Boston ...: Profusely Illustrated |  pages = 268–269| publisher = Moses King | location = Cambridge, Ma | year = 1881}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''The Boston Herald and Boston Journal''===
In October 1917, John H. Higgins, the publisher and treasurer of the Boston Herald&lt;ref&gt;''The New York Times'' &quot;James H. Higgins, Retired Publisher; Also Was Treasurer of Boston Herald for 10 Years After Merger With Traveler DIES AT CENTRAL VALLEY In 1917 He Bought ''[[The Boston Journal]]'' and Consolidated It With The Herald&quot;.  ''The New York Times'', page 13, August 1, 1938.&lt;/ref&gt; bought out its next door neighbor ''[[The Boston Journal]]'' and created ''The Boston Herald and Boston Journal''&lt;ref&gt;''The New York Times'' &quot;Boston Papers Merged.; Herald Absorbs The Journal and Will Use the Joint Title&quot;. ''The New York Times'', page 12, October 6, 1917.&lt;/ref&gt;

===''The American Traveler''===
Even earlier than the ''Herald'', the weekly ''American Traveler'' was founded in 1825 as a bulletin for [[stagecoach]] listings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanwood 1886 104&quot;&gt;{{Citation | last = Stanwood | first = Edward | title =  Boston Illustrated: Containing Full Descriptions of the City and Its Immediate Suburbs, Its Public Buildings and Institutions, Business Edifices, Parks and Avenues, Statues, Harbor and Islands, Etc., Etc. With Numerous Historical Allusions |  page = 104| publisher = Houghton, Mifflin and Co, The Riverside Press | year = 1886| location = Boston, Ma, New York, N.Y., Cambridge, Ma}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===The ''Boston Evening Traveller''===
{{Main|Boston Evening Traveller}}
The ''Boston Evening Traveler'' was founded in 1845. The '' Boston Evening Traveler'' was the successor to the weekly ''American Traveler'' and the semi-weekly ''Boston Traveler''.&lt;ref name=&quot;King 1881 267&quot;&gt;{{Citation | last = King | first = Moses | title =  King's Hand-book of Boston ...: Profusely Illustrated |  page = 267| publisher = Moses King | location = Cambridge, Ma | year = 1881}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1912, the ''Herald'' acquired the ''Traveler'', continuing to publish both under their own names. For many years, the newspaper was controlled by many of the investors in United Shoe Machinery Co. After a newspaper strike in 1967, Herald-Traveler Corp. suspended the afternoon ''Traveler'' and absorbed the evening edition into the Herald to create the ''Boston Herald Traveler.''

===''The Boston Daily Advertiser''===
[[Image:Boston Advertiser Building.png|thumb|right| The old ''Boston Advertiser'' Building]]
The ''Boston Daily Advertiser'' was established in 1813 in Boston by [[Nathan Hale (journalist)|Nathan Hale]]. The paper grew to prominence throughout the 19th century, taking over other Boston area papers. In 1832 The Advertiser took over control of ''The Boston Patriot'', and then in 1840 it took over and absorbed ''The Boston Gazette''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title =  The Encyclopædia Britannica: A Dictionary of Arts, Sciences, Literature and General Information |  volume = 19|  page = 567| publisher = Encyclopædia Britannica | location = New York, NY | year = 1911}}&lt;/ref&gt; The paper was purchased by [[William Randolph Hearst]] in 1917. In 1920 the ''Advertiser'' was merged with ''The Boston Record'', initially the combined newspaper was called the ''Boston Advertiser'' however when the combined newspaper became an illustrated tabloid in 1921 it was renamed ''The Boston American''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | first = Frederic | last = Hudson | title =  American Journalism, 1690-1940 | pages = 661–662| publisher = Routledge | location = New York, N.Y. | year = 2000 | ISBN=0-415-22894-8 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Hearst Corp. continued using the name ''Advertiser'' for its Sunday paper until the early 1970s.

===''The Boston Record''===
On September 3, 1884, ''The Boston Evening Record'' was started by the ''Boston Advertiser'' as a campaign newspaper. The ''Record'' was so popular that it was made a permanent publication.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanwood 1886 104&quot; /&gt;

===''The Boston American''===
In 1904, William Randolph Hearst began publishing his own newspaper in Boston called ''The American''. Hearst ultimately ended up purchasing the ''Daily Advertiser'' in 1917. By 1938, the ''Daily Advertiser'' had changed to the ''Daily Record'', and ''The American'' had become the ''Sunday Advertiser''. A third paper owned by Hearst, called the ''Afternoon Record'', which had been renamed the ''Evening American'', merged in 1961 with the ''Daily Record'' to form the ''Record American''. The ''Sunday Advertiser'' and ''Record American'' would ultimately be merged in 1972 into ''The Boston Herald Traveler'' a line of newspapers that stretched back to the old ''Boston Herald''.

===''The Boston Herald Traveler''===
In 1946, Herald-Traveler Corporation acquired Boston radio station [[WEEI (AM)|WHDH]]. Two years later, WHDH-FM was licensed, and on November 26, 1957, [[WHDH-TV (defunct)|WHDH-TV]] made its début as an [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] affiliate on channel 5. In 1961, WHDH-TV's affiliation switched to [[CBS]]. Herald-Traveler Corp. operated for years beginning some time after under temporary authority from the [[Federal Communications Commission]] stemming from controversy over luncheon meetings the newspaper's chief executive purportedly had with [[John C. Doerfer]], chairman of the FCC between 1957 and 1960, who served as a commissioner during the original licensing process. (Some Boston broadcast historians accuse ''[[The Boston Globe]]'' of being covertly behind the proceeding as a sort of vendetta for not getting a license—The ''Herald Traveler'' was Republican in sympathies, and the ''Globe'' then had a firm policy of not endorsing political candidates, although Doerfer's history at the FCC also lent suspicions) The FCC ordered comparative hearings, and in 1969 a competing applicant, Boston Broadcasters, Inc., was granted a construction permit to replace WHDH-TV on channel 5. Herald-Traveler Corp. fought the decision in court—by this time, revenues from channel 5 were all but keeping the newspaper afloat—but its final appeal ran out in 1972, and on March 19 WHDH-TV was forced to surrender channel 5 to the new [[WCVB-TV]].

===''The Boston Herald Traveler and Record American''===
Without a television station to subsidize the newspaper, the ''Herald Traveler'' was no longer able to remain in business, and the newspaper was sold to [[Hearst Corporation]], which published the rival all-day newspaper, the ''Record American''. The two papers were merged to become an all-day paper called the ''Boston Herald Traveler and Record American'' in the morning and ''Record-American and Boston Herald Traveler'' in the afternoon. The first editions published under the new combined name were those of June 19, 1972. The afternoon edition was soon dropped and the unwieldy name shortened to ''Boston Herald American'', with the Sunday edition called the ''Sunday Herald Advertiser''. The ''Herald American'' was printed in [[broadsheet]] format, and failed to target a particular readership; where the ''Record American'' had been a typical city [[Tabloid (newspaper format)|tabloid]], the ''Herald Traveler'' was a [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]] paper.

===Murdoch purchases ''The Herald American''===
The ''Herald American'' converted to [[Tabloid (newspaper format)|tabloid]] format in September 1981, but Hearst faced steep declines in circulation and advertising. The company announced it would close the ''Herald American''—making Boston a one-newspaper town—on December 3, 1982. When the deadline came, Australian media baron [[Rupert Murdoch]] was negotiating to buy the paper and save it. He closed on the deal after 30 hours of talks with Hearst and newspaper unions—and five hours after Hearst had sent out notices to newsroom employees telling them they were terminated. The newspaper announced its own survival the next day with a full-page headline: &quot;You Bet We're Alive!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;NEPA&quot;&gt;&quot;Purcell Toasts 25th Anniversary of Herald's Survival&quot;. [https://wayback.archive-it.org/all/20080216031818/http://www.nepa.org/Bulletin%20Archives/NEPA_Bulletin_Dec07.pdf ''NEPA Bulletin'']  (Boston, Mass.), December 2007, page 11.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== The ''Boston Herald'' once again ===

Murdoch changed the paper's name back to the ''Boston Herald''. The ''Herald'' continued to grow, expanding its coverage and increasing its circulation until 2001, when nearly all newspapers fell victim to declining circulations and revenue.

===Independent ownership===
In February 1994, Murdoch's [[News Corporation (1980–2013)|News Corporation]] was forced to sell the paper, in order that its subsidiary [[Fox Television Stations]] could legally consummate its purchase of [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox]] affiliate [[WFXT-TV|WFXT]] (Channel 25) because Massachusetts Senator [[Ted Kennedy]] included language in an appropriations barring one company from owning a newspaper and television station in the same market.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Gold|first=Allan R.|title=Kennedy vs. Murdoch: Test of Motives|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1988/01/11/us/kennedy-vs-murdoch-test-of-motives.html?pagewanted=all|accessdate=November 22, 2012|newspaper=The New York Times|date=January 11, 1988}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Gold|first=Allan R.|title=Kennedy and Paper Battle in Boston|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1988/01/07/us/kennedy-and-paper-battle-in-boston.html|accessdate=November 22, 2012|newspaper=The New York Times|date=January 7, 1988}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Lenzner|first=Robert|title=Rupert Murdoch,The Boston Globe, And Me|url=https://www.forbes.com/sites/robertlenzner/2011/08/06/rupert-murdochthe-boston-globe-and-me/|work=Forbes|accessdate=November 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Patrick J. Purcell]], who was the publisher of the ''Boston Herald'' and a former [[News Corporation (1980–2013)|News Corporation]] executive, purchased the ''Herald'' and established it as an independent newspaper. Several years later, Purcell would give the ''Herald'' a suburban presence it never had by purchasing the money-losing [[Community Newspaper Company]] from [[Fidelity Investments]]. Although the companies merged under the banner of Herald Media, Inc., the suburban papers maintained their distinct editorial and marketing identity.

After years of operating profits at Community Newspaper and losses at the ''Herald'', Purcell in 2006 sold the suburban chain to newspaper conglomerate Liberty Group Publishing of Illinois, which soon after changed its name to [[GateHouse Media]]. The deal, which also saw GateHouse acquiring ''[[The Patriot Ledger]]'' and ''[[The Enterprise (Brockton)|The Enterprise]]'' respectively in south suburban [[Quincy, Massachusetts|Quincy]] and [[Brockton, Massachusetts|Brockton]], netted $225 million for Purcell, who vowed to use the funds to clear the ''Herald''&lt;nowiki&gt;'s&lt;/nowiki&gt; debt and reinvest in the Paper.&lt;ref&gt;Bailey, Steve, and Robert Gavin. [http://www.boston.com/news/local/articles/2006/05/06/heralds_owner_to_sell_suburban_papers_deal_is_put_at_225m/ &quot;Herald's Owner to Sell Suburban Papers&quot;]. ''The Boston Globe'', May 6, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Boston Herald Radio===
On August 5, 2013, the ''Herald'' launched an internet radio station named Boston Herald Radio which includes radio shows by much of the Herald staff.&lt;ref&gt;Joe Dwinell. [http://www.bostonherald.com/business/media_marketing/2013/07/herald_internet_radio_to_get_boston_connected]. ''The Boston Herald'', July 29, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Alyssa Martino [http://commonwealthmagazine.org/politics/012-bostons-online-radio-frontier/]. ''CommonWealth Magazine'', August 7, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; The station's morning lineup is simulcast on 830 AM [[WCRN]] from 10 AM Eastern time to 12 noon Eastern time.

===Bankruptcy===
In December 2017, the ''Herald'' announced plans to sell itself to [[GateHouse Media]] after filing for [[Chapter 11, Title 11, United States Code|chapter 11 bankruptcy]] protection. The deal was scheduled to be completed by February 2018, with the new company streamlining and having layoffs in coming months.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Staff |first=Writer |url=https://www.usatoday.com/story/money/business/2017/12/08/boston-herald-declares-bankruptcy-agrees-sold/936185001/ |title=Boston Herald declares bankruptcy, agrees to be sold |work=[[USA Today]] |publisher=[[Associated Press]] |date=2017-12-08 |accessdate=2017-12-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Dowling |first=Brian |url=http://www.bostonherald.com/business/business_markets/2017/12/judge_approves_herald_to_continue_business_as_usual |title=Judge approves Herald to continue business as usual |work=Boston Herald |date=2017-12-14 |accessdate=2017-12-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in early January 2018, another potential buyer, Revolution Capital Group of Los Angeles, filed a bid with the federal bankruptcy court; the ''Herald'' reported in a press release that &quot;the court requires BHI [Boston Herald, Inc.] to hold an auction to allow all potential buyers an opportunity to submit competing offers.&quot;&lt;ref name=SecondBidder&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.bostonherald.com/business/business_markets/2018/01/second_potential_buyer_makes_offer_for_boston_herald |title=Second potential buyer makes offer for Boston Herald |first=Brian |last=Dowling |newspaper=Boston Herald |date=January 2, 2018 |accessdate=January 2, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Digital First Media acquisition ===
In February 2018, acquisition of the ''Herald'' by [[Digital First Media]] for almost $12 million was approved by the bankruptcy court judge in Delaware. The new owner, DFM, said they would be keeping 175 of the approximately 240 employees the ''Herald'' had when it sought bankruptcy protection in December 2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Chesto |first=Jon |url=https://www.bostonglobe.com/business/2018/02/16/boston-herald-sale-digital-first-media-blessed-bankruptcy-court/Ihni8jDK5GMkO4CLRCd6cL/story.html |title=Boston Herald sale to Digital First Media blessed by bankruptcy court |work=[[The Boston Globe]] |date=2018-02-16 |accessdate=2018-02-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The acquisition was completed on March 19, 2018.&lt;ref name=march19/&gt;

The Herald and parent DFM were criticized for ending the ten-year printing contract&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Herald, Globe agree to printing deal |url=http://www.bostonherald.com/business/media_marketing/2013/06/herald_globe_agree_to_printing_deal |website=Boston Herald |accessdate=16 August 2018 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; with competitor ''[[The Boston Globe]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Seiffert |first1=Don |last2=Ryan |first2=Greg |title=After sale to Digital First, Boston Herald will end Globe print deal |url=https://www.bizjournals.com/boston/news/2018/03/17/after-sale-to-digital-first-boston-herald-will-end.html |website=Boston Business Journal |accessdate=16 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; moving printing from [[Taunton, Massachusetts]], to [[Rhode Island]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Glatter |first1=Hayley |title=The Herald Will Stop Relying on the Globe for Printing |url=https://www.bostonmagazine.com/news/2018/03/19/boston-herald-globe-printing/ |website=Boston Magazine |accessdate=16 August 2018 |date=19 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Seiffert |first1=Don |last2=Ryan |first2=Greg |title=Boston Business Journal |url=https://www.bizjournals.com/boston/news/2018/03/17/after-sale-to-digital-first-boston-herald-will-end.html |website=www.bizjournals.com |accessdate=16 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; and its &quot;dehumanizing cost-cutting efforts&quot; in personnel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=DeCosta-Klipa |first1=Nik |title=Inside the ‘dehumanizing’ cost-cutting efforts by new ownership at the Boston Herald |url=https://www.boston.com/news/media/2018/05/15/boston-herald-digital-first-media |website=Boston.com |accessdate=16 August 2018 |date=15 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June, some design and advertising layoffs were expected, with work moving to a sister paper, ''[[The Denver Post]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Ryan |first1=Greg |title=Digital First planning additional layoffs at Boston Herald |url=https://www.bizjournals.com/boston/news/2018/06/13/digital-first-planning-additional-layoffs-at.html |website=Boston Business Journal |accessdate=16 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The &quot;consolidation&quot; took effect in August, with nine jobs eliminated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Seifert |first1=Don |title=Boston Business Journal |url=https://www.bizjournals.com/boston/news/2018/08/16/boston-herald-lays-off-most-of-its-advertising.html |website=www.bizjournals.com |accessdate=16 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In late August 2018, it was announced that the ''Herald''  would move its offices from Boston's Seaport District to [[Braintree, Massachusetts]], in late November or early December.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.boston.com/news/media/2018/08/28/the-boston-herald-is-moving-to-braintree |title=The Boston Herald is moving to Braintree |newspaper=[[The Boston Globe]] |via=[[Boston.com]] |date=August 28, 2018 |accessdate=August 29, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards==

* 1924. [[Pulitzer Prize for Editorial Writing|Pulitzer Prizes for Editorial Writing]],&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.pulitzer.org/prize-winners-by-category/247|title=Editorial Writing|last=|first=|date=|website=pulitzer.org|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{Interlanguage link|Frank W. Buxton|fr||WD=}}, « [[s:Who Made Coolidge?|Who Made Coolidge?]] »
* 1927. [[Pulitzer Prize for Editorial Writing|Pulitzer Prizes for Editorial Writing]],&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; [[F. Lauriston Bullard]], « We Submit »
* 1948. [[Pulitzer Prize for Photography|Pulitzer Prizes for Photography]],&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.pulitzer.org/prize-winners-by-category/271|title=Photography|last=|first=|date=|website=pulitzer.org|language=en|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2018-09-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Frank Cushing, « Boy Gunman and Hostage »
* 1949. [[Pulitzer Prize for Editorial Writing|Pulitzer Prizes for Editorial Writing]],&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; John H. Crider
* 1954. [[Pulitzer Prize for Editorial Writing|Pulitzer Prizes for Editorial Writing]],&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; [[Donald Murray (writer)|Don Murray]], series of editorials on the “New Look” in National Defense
* 1957. [[Pulitzer Prize for Photography|Pulitzer Prizes for Photography]],&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt; Harry A. Trask. The sinking of the liner {{SS|Andrea Doria}} in July 1956 (the pictures were taken from an airplane flying at a height of 75 feet 9 minutes before the ship plunged to the bottom. The second picture in the sequence is cited as the key photograph.
* 1976. [[Pulitzer Prize for Spot News Photography|Pulitzer Prizes for Spot News Photography]],&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.pulitzer.org/prize-winners-by-category/274|title=Spot News Photography|last=|first=|date=|website=pulitzer.org|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Stanley Forman]], for ''[[Fire Escape Collapse]]'', a dramatic shot of a young woman and child falling as the fire escape to which they had fled during an apartment house fire collapsed on July 22, 1975
* 1977. [[Pulitzer Prize for Spot News Photography|Pulitzer Prizes for Spot News Photography]],&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt; [[Stanley Forman]], for ''[[The Soiling of Old Glory]]'', as [[Ted Landsmark]], an [[African American]] civil rights lawyer, was charged at by a protester with an [[flag of the United States|American flag]] during the [[Boston busing crisis]]
* 1979. [[Pulitzer Prize for Feature Photography|Pulitzer Prizes for Feature Photography]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.pulitzer.org/prize-winners-by-category/217|title=Feature Photography|last=|first=|date=|website=pulitzer.org|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; staff photographers, for photographic coverage of [[1978 Northeastern United States blizzard|The Blizzard of 1978]]
*2006. [[Society of American Business Editors and Writers]] (SABEW) Award as &quot;Business winners&quot; for « overall excellence » coverage&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://sabew.org/2006/03/2006-news-sabew-best-in-business-winners-announced/|title=2006 News: SABEW Best in Business Winners Announced « SABEW|website=sabew.org|access-date=2019-01-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot;&gt;Boston Herald staff, &quot;Herald named `best in business'&quot;. ''Boston Herald'', Finance page 31, April 5, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
*2006. [[Society of American Business Editors and Writers]] (SABEW) Award as &quot;Business winners&quot; for « Breaking News » coverage of the takeover of the Boston-based [[Gillette (brand)|Gillette Company]] by [[Procter &amp; Gamble]]&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt;

==Columnists==
* [[Bill Cunningham (sports writer)]] (1895-1961), highest paid sportswriter of his time&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|url=https://books.google.fr/books?id=qEwEAAAAMBAJ&amp;lpg=PA76&amp;ots=uabv7cYKXf&amp;dq=bill%20cunningham%20boston%20herald&amp;hl=fr&amp;pg=PA76#v=onepage&amp;q=bill%20cunningham%20boston%20herald&amp;f=false|title=Highest paid sportswriter, Bill Cunningham goes to Boston Herald|magazine=[[Life (magazine)|Life]]|date=April 14, 1941}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Joe Sciacca]] is the paper's editor-in-chief. Sciacca is a former political reporter and columnist.
* [[Warren T. Brookes]] was an economics reporter at ''The Herald'' from 1975 until 1985, when he moved to the ''t based in [[Washington, D.C.]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1991/12/30/obituaries/warren-brookes-62-syndicated-columnist.html|title=Warren Brookes, 62, Syndicated Columnist|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|date=December 30, 1991|accessdate=November 24, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Howie Carr]] writes extensively on local politics and is a radio talk show host and frequent TV commentator.
* [[Peter Gelzinis]] is a longtime metro columnist, as is Joe Fitzgerald, who was formerly a sports columnist.
* Joe Battenfeld is the ''Herald''{{'}}s political columnist and multi-media reporter.
* [[Michael Graham (radio personality)|Michael Graham]] is an op-ed columnist for the ''Boston Herald''.
* [[Gerry Callahan]] is a sports columnist and talk show host for [[WEEI (AM)|WEEI]].
* [[Steve Buckley (journalist)|Steve Buckley]] was a longtime sports columnist.
* [[George Edward Kimball]] was a sports columnist best known for his coverage of boxing.
* Olivia Vanni writes the ''Herald''{{'}}s Inside Track&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bostonherald.com/track/ Inside Track | Boston Herald&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and covers celebrity news.
* Bob McGovern was the ''Herald''{{'}}s legal columnist and also worked as a reporter.
* Peter Lucas was a longtime political columnist and reporter
* [[Ron Borges]] was a sports columnist.

== ''Boston Herald'' in Education Program ==

The Boston Herald Newspapers in Education (NIE) program provides teachers with classroom newspapers and educational materials designed to help students of all ages and abilities excel. This is made possible through donations from Herald readers and other sponsors. The ''Boston Herald'' is available in two formats: the print edition and the online e-Edition. The website can be found at http://bostonheraldnie.com/

==See also==

* ''The [[Boston Daily Advertiser]]''
* ''[[The Boston Journal]]''
* ''[[The Boston News-Letter]]''
* ''The [[Boston Evening Transcript]]''
* ''[[The Boston Globe]]''
* ''[[The Boston Post]]''
* [[Lillian A. Lewis]], Boston's first African-American woman journalist
* [[Frances Sweeney]] of the ''Boston Herald'' Rumor Clinic
* ''[[Murphy v. Boston Herald, Inc., et al.]]''

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* {{Citation|title=The Boston Herald and Its History|year=1878|author=Perry, Edwin A. |publisher=The Herald}}
* Sterling Quinlan, ''The Hundred Million Dollar Lunch'' (Chicago, J.P. O'Hara, 1974), {{ISBN|0-87955-310-3}}.

==External links==
{{Commons category|Boston Herald}}
* {{official website|http://www.bostonherald.com|mobile=http://www.bostonherald.com/mobile}}
* [http://www.boston.com/business/articles/2005/11/08/heralds_circulation_declines/ ''Herald'''s circulation declines]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20111126034119/http://www.heraldmedia.com/heraldMedia/history.html Company History]
* {{ITunes Preview App|398366739|Boston Herald}}
* {{BlackBerry App World|17069|Boston Herald}}

{{Digital First Media}}
{{Newspapers in Massachusetts}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Boston Herald}}
[[Category:1846 establishments in Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Newspapers published in Boston]]
[[Category:Publications established in 1846]]
[[Category:Former News Corporation subsidiaries]]
[[Category:Boston Herald|*]]
[[Category:Websites utilizing paywalls]]</text>
      <sha1>t19rr201iywfjbyk8891wytjfr5673h</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
