  <page>
    <title>Wikipedia:Building Wikipedia membership/Another sample solicitation</title>
    <ns>4</ns>
    <id>4138</id>
    <revision>
      <id>275979382</id>
      <parentid>66301437</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-03-09T06:08:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Graham87</username>
        <id>194203</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>fix link</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{historical}}

I am only now starting to publicize Wikipedia, a wiki-based free (open
content) encyclopedia project.  We started last January and already have
about 10,000 articles.  Perhaps you have seen us by now--we're located at
http://www.wikipedia.com . I'm the person responsible for organizing and
leading Wikipedia, as well as Nupedia (which has been moving *much* more
slowly).

First things first: it would be fantastic if you would like to link to any
or all of our articles.  They're free, of course.  I'd like to make this
as easy as possible for you, if you're interested.

If you have any free articles we can use, I would like to know about it!

More interestingly, perhaps, for you, is the idea that you can actually
use our content as part of your website.  It's free.  The cream of the
crop can be found at http://www.wikipedia.com/wiki.cgi?Brilliant_prose ,
but there's a *lot* more than that.  Also, the quality of Nupedia articles
is guaranteed; see http://www.nupedia.com/newest.phtml .  (There just
isn't much there yet.)

One thing we're working on is a program that will make it extremely easy
to mirror Wikipedia's content.  We're not done with that yet--but is that
something you might be interested in?

I certainly would like to hear back from you about how we might be able to
support each other.  I do not regard your website as a competitor in any
sense at all.

:''See also :'' [[Wikipedia:Building Wikipedia membership|Building Wikipedia membership]]</text>
      <sha1>q43ng1u1sse4h3er0o8kn4pwccv6we3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
