  <page>
    <title>Bus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4146</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942192555</id>
      <parentid>934444558</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-23T05:02:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ranjithsiji</username>
        <id>13289863</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Public transport */ add picture</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Large road vehicle for transporting people}}
{{about|the road vehicles designed to carry many passengers|other uses|Bus (disambiguation)}}
{{pp-vandalism|small=yes}}
[[File:LT 471 (LTZ 1471) Arriva London New Routemaster (19522859218).jpg|thumb|A [[New Routemaster]] [[double-decker bus]], operating for [[Arriva London]] on [[London Buses]] route 73]]
[[File:Toronto Flyer E700A trolleybus in 1987.jpg|thumb|A [[Toronto Transit Commission bus system]] [[trolleybus]] in [[Toronto]]]]
[[File:George William Joy - The Bayswater Omnibus.jpg|thumb|[[George William Joy]]'s depiction of the interior of a late 19th Century omnibus]]
[[File:Connexxion 9238, Utrecht CS-Oost (9952048314).jpg|thumb|right|A bus in [[Utrecht]], [[Netherlands]]]]
A '''bus''' (contracted from '''omnibus''',&lt;ref name=EB1911&gt;{{cite EB1911 |wstitle=Omnibus |volume=20 |page=104}}&lt;/ref&gt; with variants '''multibus''', '''motorbus''', '''autobus''', etc.) is a [[road vehicle]] designed to carry many [[passenger]]s. Buses can have a capacity as high as 300 passengers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jongo News&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.jongo.com/articles/07/0315/9180/OTE4MAmXAYhbF0.html |title=China's longest bus unveiled in Shanghai |publisher=Jongo.com |date=15 March 2007 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110930181821/http://news.jongo.com/articles/07/0315/9180/OTE4MAmXAYhbF0.html |archivedate=30 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The most common type is the [[single-deck bus|single-deck]] [[rigid bus]], with larger loads carried by [[double-decker bus|double-decker]] and [[articulated bus]]es, and smaller loads carried by [[midibus]]es and [[minibus]]es while [[coach (vehicle)|coaches]] are used for longer-distance services. Many types of buses, such as city transit buses and inter-city coaches, charge a fare. Other types, such as elementary or secondary school buses or shuttle buses within a post-secondary education campus do not charge a fare. In many jurisdictions, [[bus driver]]s require a special licence above and beyond a regular [[driver's licence]].

Buses may be used for [[Public transport bus service|scheduled bus transport]], [[Coach (scheduled transport)|scheduled coach transport]], [[school transport]], private hire, or [[Tour bus service|tourism]]; promotional buses may be used for [[political campaign]]s and others are privately operated for a wide range of purposes, including rock and pop band tour vehicles.

[[Horsebus|Horse-drawn buses]] were used from the 1820s, followed by [[steam bus]]es in the 1830s, and electric [[trolleybus]]es in 1882. The first [[internal combustion engine]] buses, or motor buses, were used in 1895.&lt;ref name= Eckermann2001/&gt; Recently, interest has been growing in [[hybrid electric bus]]es, [[fuel cell bus]]es, and [[electric bus]]es, as well as buses powered by [[compressed natural gas]] or [[biodiesel]]. As of the 2010s, [[bus manufacturing]] is increasingly [[globalisation|globalised]], with the same designs appearing around the world.

==Name==
[[File:Omnibus - Project Gutenberg eText 16943.jpg|thumb|An early horse-drawn omnibus]]

Bus is a [[clipping (morphology)|clipped]] form of the Latin [[adjective|adjectival form]]  ''omnibus'' (&quot;for all&quot;), the [[dative]] plural of ''omnis-e'' (&quot;all&quot;).&lt;ref name=Cassell&gt;{{cite dictionary |encyclopedia=Cassell's Latin Dictionary |editor-first1=J.R.V. |editor-last1=Marchant |editor-first2=Joseph F. |editor-last2=Charles |year=1928 |edition=Revised}}&lt;/ref&gt; The theoretical full name is in French ''voiture omnibus''&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; (&quot;vehicle for all&quot;). The name originates from a mass-transport service started in 1823 by a French corn-mill owner named {{ill|Stanislas Baudry|fr}} in [[Richebourg, Nantes|Richebourg]], a suburb of [[Nantes]]. A by-product of his mill was hot water, and thus next to it he established a spa business. In order to encourage customers he started a horse-drawn transport service from the city centre of Nantes to his establishment. The first vehicles stopped in front of the shop of a hatter named Omnés, which displayed a large sign inscribed  &quot;Omnes Omnibus&quot;, a pun on his Latin-sounding surname, ''omnes'' being the male and female nominative, vocative and accusative form of the Latin adjective ''omnis-e'' (&quot;all&quot;),&lt;ref name=Cassell/&gt; combined with ''omnibus'', the dative plural form meaning &quot;for all&quot;, thus giving his shop the name &quot;Omnés for all&quot;, or &quot;everything for everyone&quot;. His transport scheme was a huge success, although not as he had intended as most of his passengers did not visit his spa. He turned the transport service into his principal lucrative business venture and closed the mill and spa.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://amtuir.org/03_htu_generale/htu_1_avant_1870/htu_1.htm |title=La préhistoire des transports urbains |trans-title=The prehistory of urban transport |publisher=Transportation Museum |language=French |location=Chelles, Seine-et-Marne, France}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nantes citizens soon gave the nickname &quot;omnibus&quot; to the vehicle.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; Having invented the successful concept Baudry moved to Paris and launched the first omnibus service there in April 1828.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; A similar service was introduced in London in 1829.{{Sfn|Fierro|1996|page=1031}}&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite dictionary
 |title=Omnibus (n.)
 |url=http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=omnibus&amp;allowed_in_frame=0
 |dictionary=Online Etymology Dictionary
 |accessdate=30 March 2013
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;amtuir&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://www.amtuir.org/03_htu_generale/htu_1_avant_1870/htu_1.htm
 |title=Histoire générale des transports
 |publisher=French transportations Museum Website
 |accessdate=16 September 2010
 |language=fr
 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110718154641/http://www.amtuir.org/03_htu_generale/htu_1_avant_1870/htu_1.htm
 |archive-date=18 July 2011
 |url-status=dead
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

&lt;!--
That are horse coaches and not a bus
===Early history===
A short-lived early [[Public transport bus service|public bus line]] (known as a &quot;carriage&quot; at that time) was launched by [[Blaise Pascal]] in Paris in 1662; it was quite popular until fares were increased and access to the service was restricted to high-society members by regulation and law. Services ceased after 15 years&lt;ref name=&quot;amtuir&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.herodote.net/histoire/evenement.php?jour=18260810 |title=Le temps de révolutions |publisher=Herodote.net |accessdate=16 September 2010 |language=fr}}  Retrieved 13 June 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and no further such services were known until the 1820s.

===First horse omnibus serves===
[[John Greenwood (bus operator)|John Greenwood]] is said by some historians to have established the first modern omnibus service in 1824. As the keeper of a toll gate in [[Pendleton, Greater Manchester|Pendleton]] on the [[Manchester]]-to-Liverpool [[Turnpike road|turnpike]], he purchased a horse and a cart with several seats, and began an omnibus service between those two locations. His pioneering idea was to offer a service where, unlike with a [[Stagecoaches|stagecoach]], no prior booking was necessary and the driver would pick up or set down passengers anywhere on request.  Later on, he added daily services to [[Buxton]], [[Chester]], and [[Sheffield]]. His line immediately sparked fierce competition and a dense network of omnibus services quickly sprouted in the area, often acting as feeders to the railways. In 1865, Greenwood's company and its competitors amalgamated into the [[Manchester Carriage and Tramways Company|Manchester Carriage Company]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.gmts.co.uk/explore/history/history.html |title=A Short History of Public Transport in Greater Manchester}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Plan de la ville de Paris représentant les nouvelles voitures publiques - Entreprise générale des Dames Blanches.jpg|thumb|right|upright=1.35|A Paris omnibus in 1828]]

The Paris omnibus was started in 1828 by a businessman named Stanislas Baudry, who had begun the first French omnibus line in [[Nantes]] in 1826. The name was said to come from the station of the first line in Nantes, in front of the store of a hat-maker named Omnes, who had a large sign on his building saying &quot;Omnes Omnibus&quot;  (&quot;All for all&quot; in Latin).  Following success in Nantes, Baudry moved to Paris and founded the Enterprise des Omnibus on rue de Lancre, with workshops on the quai de Jemmapes.   In 1827 he commissioned an English coach-maker, [[George Shillibeer]], to design a vehicle that could be stable and carry a large number of passengers. Shillibeer's design worked, On 28 April 1828, the first Paris omnibus began service, running every fifteen minutes between La Madeleine and la Bastille.  Before long, there were one hundred omnibuses in service, with eighteen different itineraries.  A journey cost twenty-five centimes.  The omnibuses circulated between seven in the morning and seven in the evening; each omnibus could carry between twelve and eighteen passengers.  The busiest line was that along the Grand Boulevards; it ran from eight in the morning until midnight. {{sfn|Fierro|1996|pages=1031–1032}}

The Paris omnibus service was an immediate popular success, with more than two and a half million passengers in the first six months.  However, there was no reliable way to collect money from the passengers, or the fare collectors kept much of the money for themselves; In its first years the company was continually on the verge of bankruptcy, and in despair, Baudry committed suicide in February 1830.   Baudry's partners reorganized the company and managed to keep it in business.{{sfn|Fierro|1996|pages=1031–1032}}

In September 1828, a competing company, les Dames-Blanches, had started running its own vehicles.  In 1829 and the following years, more companies with poetic names entered the business; les Citadines, les Tricycles, les Orléanises, les Diligentes, les Écossaises, les Béarnaises, les Carolines, les Batignollaises, les Parisiennes, les Hirondelles, les Joséphines, les Excellentes, les Sylphides, les Constantines, les Dames-Françaises, les Algériennes, les Dames-Réunies, and les Gazelles.  The omnibus had a profound effect on Parisian life, making it possible for Parisians to work and have a social life outside their own neighborhoods.{{sfn|Héron de Villefosse|1959|page=317}}

By 1845, there were thirteen companies in Paris operating twenty-twenty three omnibus lines. In 1855, [[Napoleon III]] had them combined into a single company, the Compagnie générale des omnibus, with a monopoly on Paris public transportation. Beginning in 1873, they were gradually replaced by tramways, and, beginning in 1906, by the ''omnibus automobile'', or motor bus. The last horse-drawn Paris omnibus ran on 11 January 1913, from Saint-Sulpice to La Villette. {{sfn|Fierro|1996|pages=1031–1032}}

[[File:Shillibeer's first omnibus.png|thumb|left|upright=1.35|Shillibeer's first London Omnibus (1829)]]

Shillibeer built another bus for the [[Quaker]] [[Newington Academy for Girls]] near London; this had a total of 25 seats, and entered history as the first [[school bus]].
Shillibeer saw the success of the Paris omnibus in service and concluded that operating similar vehicles in London, for the fare-paying public with multiple stops, would be a paying enterprise, so he returned to his native city. His first London &quot;Omnibus&quot;, using the same design and name as the Paris vehicle, took up service on 4 July 1829 on the route between [[Paddington]] (The [[Yorkshire Stingo]]) and &quot;Bank&quot; ([[Bank of England]]) via the &quot;[[New Road (eighteenth century north London turnpike road)|New Road]]&quot; (now [[Marylebone Road|Marylebone Rd]]), [[Somers Town, London|Somers Town]] and [[City Road]]. Four services were provided in each direction daily. Shillibeer's success prompted many competitors to enter the market, and for a time buses were referred to as 'Shillibeers'.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://knowledgeoflondon.com/buses.html |title=The London Omnibus}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:omnibus - Project Gutenberg eText 16943.jpg|right|thumb|Parisian omnibus, late 19th century]]

Although passenger-carrying carriages had operated for many years, the new 'omnibus' pioneered a new service of picking up and setting down customers all along a particular route without the need to book in advance. Buses soon expanded their capacity, with additional seats for a few extra passengers provided alongside the driver. By 1845, passengers were being accommodated on the curved roofs, seated back to back in a configuration known as 'knife-board'. In 1852, Greenwood's in Manchester introduced the double-decker vehicle that could seat up to 42.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.petergould.co.uk/local_transport_history/generalhistories/general/horsebus.htm |title=The Horse Bus: 1662–1932}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Germany, the first bus service was established in Berlin in 1825, running from [[Brandenburger Tor]] to [[Charlottenburg]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.textagentur-grimm.de/kremser.html |title=Simon Kremser |first=TextAgentur |last=Grimm |publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1850, [[Thomas Tilling]] started [[horse bus]] services in London,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.petergould.co.uk/local_transport_history/pioneers/people/tilling.htm |title=Thomas Tilling Ltd: 1849–1969 |publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in 1855, the [[London General Omnibus Company]] was founded to amalgamate and regulate the horse-drawn omnibus services then operating in London.&lt;ref name=&quot;ltm1829&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=From omnibus to ecobus, 1829–1850 |url=http://www.ltmuseum.co.uk/learning/online_resources/ecobus_omnibus/pg/1829.htm |publisher=[[London's Transport Museum]] |accessdate=3 July 2007 |archiveurl=//web.archive.org/web/20070609023652/http://www.ltmuseum.co.uk/learning/online_resources/ecobus_omnibus/pg/1829.htm |archivedate=9 June 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By the 1880s, bus services were a commonplace in England, continental Europe, and North America; one company in London was operating over 220 horse-buses. Horse-bus use declined with the advent of steam-buses and motor-buses; the last horse bus in London stopped operation in 1914.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.museumoflondon.org.uk/postcodes/places/SE15.html |title=Riding on a knifeboard |work=London Museum |quote=Thomas Tilling started his bus service in the 1840s. By 1901 he had a total of 220 horse-drawn buses... The last recorded horse omnibus in London was a Tilling bus. It ran its last journey between Peckham and Honor Oak Tavern on 4 August 1914.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
--&gt;

===Steam buses===
[[File:Obeissante.jpg|thumb|[[Amédée Bollée]]'s ''L'Obéissante'' (1875)]]

Regular intercity bus services by steam-powered buses were pioneered in England in the 1830s by [[Walter Hancock]] and by associates of [[Goldsworthy Gurney|Sir Goldsworthy Gurney]], among others, running reliable services over road conditions which were too hazardous for horse-drawn transportation.

The first mechanically propelled omnibus appeared on the streets of London on 22 April 1833.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Centenarxy of the Omnibus |newspaper=The Times |date=28 April 1933 |p=16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Steam carriages were much less likely to overturn, they travelled faster than horse-drawn carriages, they were much cheaper to run, and caused much less damage to the road surface due to their wide tyres.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |chapter=The Rise and Fall of Non-Government Roads in the United Kingdom |pages=263–264 |title=Street Smart: Competition, Entrepreneurship and the Future of Roads |author=Benson, Bruce L.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, the heavy road [[Toll road|tolls]] imposed by the [[turnpike trusts]] discouraged steam road vehicles and left the way clear for the horse bus companies, and from 1861 onwards, harsh legislation virtually eliminated mechanically propelled vehicles from the roads of Great Britain for 30 years, the [[Locomotive Act]] of that year imposing restrictive speed limits on &quot;road locomotives&quot; of 5&amp;nbsp;mph in towns and cities, and 10&amp;nbsp;mph in the country.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=RMgDAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA388&amp;vq=locomotives+on+turnpike&amp;source=gbs_search_r&amp;cad=1_1 Locomotives Act, 1861] Pratt's ''Law of Highways'' Edition 10, Shaw &amp; Sons (1865) p. 388&lt;/ref&gt;

===Trolleybuses===
{{main|Trolleybus}}
[[File:First Trolleybuss of Siemens in Berlin 1882.gif|thumb|World's first trolleybus, Berlin 1882]]

In parallel to the development of the bus was the invention of the electric trolleybus, typically fed through [[trolley pole]]s by [[Overhead line|overhead wires]]. The Siemens brothers, [[William Siemens|William]] in England and [[Ernst Werner von Siemens|Ernst Werner]] in Germany, collaborated on the development of the trolleybus concept. Sir William first proposed the idea in an article to the ''[[Royal Society of Arts|Journal of the Society of Arts]]'' in 1881 as an &quot;...arrangement by which an ordinary omnibus...would have a suspender thrown at intervals from one side of the street to the other, and two wires hanging from these suspenders; allowing contact rollers to run on these two wires, the current could be conveyed to the tram-car, and back again to the dynamo machine at the station, without the necessity of running upon rails at all.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.trolleybus.co.uk/history1.htm |title=Trolleybus history – current collector design}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first such vehicle, the [[Electromote]], was made by his brother Dr. Ernst Werner von Siemens and presented to the public in 1882 in [[Halensee]], [[German Empire|Germany]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.siemens.com/history/en/innovations/transportation.htm#toc-2 ''Elektromote''] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160729124510/http://www.siemens.com/history/en/innovations/transportation.htm#toc-2 |date=29 July 2016 }}, Siemens History website. Retrieved 2011-08-28&lt;/ref&gt; Although this experimental vehicle fulfilled all the technical criteria of a typical trolleybus, it was dismantled in the same year after the demonstration.&lt;ref name=&quot;CSDunbar&quot;&gt;Charles S. Dunbar, ''Buses, Trolleys and Trams'', (Paul Hamlyn Ltd, 1967, no ISBN) p. 81 ''et seq''.&lt;/ref&gt;

Max Schiemann opened a passenger-carrying trolleybus in 1901 near [[Dresden]], in Germany. Although this system operated only until 1904, Schiemann had developed what is now the standard trolleybus current collection system. In the early days, a few other methods of current collection were used. [[Leeds]] and [[Bradford]] became the first cities to put trolleybuses into service in Great Britain on 20 June 1911.

===Motor buses===
[[File:Erste Benzin-Omnibus der Welt.jpg|thumb|The first internal combustion omnibus of 1895 ([[Siegen]] to [[Netphen]])]]

In [[Siegerland]], Germany, two passenger bus lines ran briefly, but unprofitably, in 1895 using a six-passenger motor carriage developed from the 1893 [[Benz Viktoria]].&lt;ref name= Eckermann2001/&gt; Another commercial bus line using the same model Benz omnibuses ran for a short time in 1898 in the rural area around [[Llandudno]], Wales.&lt;ref name=Ward1974/&gt;

[[Daimler Motoren Gesellschaft|Daimler]] also produced one of the earliest motor-bus models in 1898, selling a double-decker bus to the Motor Traction Company which was first used on the streets of London on 23 April 1898.&lt;ref name=&quot;Daimler&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://media.daimler.com/marsMediaSite/en/instance/ko/1898-The-worlds-first-bus-series-launched-by-Daimler--a-mile.xhtml?oid=9913455 |title=1898: The world's first bus series launched by Daimler – a milestone for passenger transport – marsMediaSite |publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The vehicle had a maximum speed of {{convert|18|kph|mph|1|abbr=on}} and accommodated up to 20 passengers, in an enclosed area below and on an open-air platform above. With the success and popularity of this bus, Daimler expanded production, selling more buses to companies in London and, in 1899, to [[Stockholm]] and [[Speyer]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Daimler&quot; /&gt; Daimler also entered into a partnership with the British company Milnes and developed a new double-decker in 1902 that became the market standard.

[[File:B43OleBillatIWMLondon.jpg|thumb|left|Early [[LGOC B-type]]]]

The first mass-produced bus model was the [[LGOC B-type|B-type]] [[double-decker bus]], designed by [[Frank Searle (1874-1948)|Frank Searle]] and operated by the [[London General Omnibus Company]] – it entered service in 1910, and almost 3,000 had been built by the end of the decade. Hundreds saw military service on the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]] during the [[First World War]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=G. J. |last=Robbins |author2=Atkinson, J. B. |title=The London B-Type Motor Omnibus |edition=3rd |location=Twickenham |publisher=World of Transport |year=1991 |isbn=1-871979-04-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Daimler CC Bus (1912).jpg|thumb|Daimler CC Bus 1912. One of five Daimler buses exported to Australia]]

The [[Yellow Coach Manufacturing Company]], which rapidly became a major manufacturer of buses in the US, was founded in Chicago in 1923 by [[John D. Hertz]]. [[General Motors]] purchased a majority stake in 1925 and changed its name to the Yellow Truck and Coach Manufacturing Company. They then purchased the balance of the shares in 1943 to form the [[GMC (Truck)|GM Truck and Coach Division]].

Models expanded in the 20th century, leading to the widespread introduction of the contemporary recognizable form of full-sized buses from the 1950s. The [[AEC Routemaster]], developed in the 1950s, was a pioneering design and remains an icon of London to this day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.aecsouthall.co.uk/ |title=AEC Southall Enthusiast page |publisher=Aecsouthall.co.uk |accessdate=19 April 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The innovative design used lightweight aluminium and techniques developed in aircraft production during [[World War II]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.londonbooks.co.uk/shop/page.php?xPage=articles.html&amp;articleID=1 |publisher=Londonbooks.co.uk |title=he Bus We Loved book description, 12 September 2006 |access-date=6 October 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140221214815/http://www.londonbooks.co.uk/shop/page.php?xPage=articles.html&amp;articleID=1 |archive-date=21 February 2014 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; As well as a novel weight-saving integral design, it also introduced for the first time on a bus [[independent suspension|independent front suspension]], [[power steering]], a fully [[automatic gearbox]], and [[Hydraulic brake|power-hydraulic braking]].&lt;ref name=routemasterorghome&gt;[http://www.routemaster.org.uk/ Routemaster.org] home page&lt;/ref&gt;

==Types==
[[File:Athens bus interior in 2013.jpg|thumb|Interior of a bus]]

Formats include [[single-decker bus]], double-decker bus (both usually with a [[rigid bus|rigid chassis]]) and [[articulated bus]] (or 'bendy-bus') the prevalence of which varies from country to country. High-capacity [[bi-articulated bus]]es are also manufactured, and passenger-carrying trailers—either towed behind a [[rigid bus]] (a [[Trailer (vehicle)|bus trailer]]) or hauled as a trailer by a truck (a [[trailer bus]]). Smaller [[midibus]]es have a lower capacity and [[open-top bus]]es are typically used for leisure purposes. In many new fleets, particularly in local transit systems, a shift to [[low-floor bus]]es is occurring, primarily for easier accessibility. [[Coach (bus)|Coaches]] are designed for longer-distance travel and are typically fitted with individual high-backed reclining seats, seat belts, toilets, and [[audio-visual]] entertainment systems, and can operate at higher speeds with more capacity for luggage. Coaches may be single- or double-deckers, articulated, and often include a separate luggage compartment under the passenger floor. [[Guided bus]]es are fitted with technology to allow them to run in designated guideways, allowing the controlled alignment at bus stops and less space taken up by guided lanes than conventional roads or [[bus lane]]s.

[[Bus manufacturing]] may be by a single company (an integral manufacturer), or by one manufacturer's building a bus body over a chassis produced by another manufacturer.

==Design==
[[File:Inside Bus W.jpg|alt=|thumb|304x304px|Interior of a bus]]

===Accessibility===
[[File:Praha, DOD 2006 Hostivař, Plošina autobusu Karosa pro invalidy.JPG|thumb|Bus with [[wheelchair lift]] extended]]

[[Transit bus]]es used to be mainly [[high-floor]] vehicles.  However, they are now increasingly of [[low-floor bus|low-floor]] design and optionally also 'kneel' [[air suspension]] and have electrically or hydraulically extended under-floor ramps to provide level access for [[wheelchair]] users and people with [[baby transport|baby carriages]]. Prior to more general use of such technology, these wheelchair users could only use specialist [[paratransit]] mobility buses.

Accessible vehicles also have wider entrances and interior gangways and space for wheelchairs. Interior fittings and [[rollsign|destination displays]] may also be designed to be usable by the [[visually impaired]]. Coaches generally use [[wheelchair lift]]s instead of low-floor designs. In some countries, vehicles are required to have these features by [[Disability discrimination act|disability discrimination laws]].

===Configuration===
Buses were initially configured with an engine in the front and an entrance at the rear. With the transition to one-man operation, many manufacturers moved to mid- or rear-engined designs, with a single door at the front or multiple doors. The move to the low-floor design has all but eliminated the mid-engined design, although some coaches still have mid-mounted engines. Front-engined buses still persist for niche markets such as American school buses, some minibuses, and buses in less developed countries, which may be derived from truck chassis, rather than purpose-built bus designs. Most buses have two [[axles]], articulated buses have three.

===Guidance===
[[Guided bus]]es are fitted with technology to allow them to run in designated guideways, allowing the controlled alignment at bus stops and less space taken up by guided lanes than conventional roads or [[bus lane]]s. Guidance can be mechanical, optical, or electromagnetic. &lt;!-- explain abbr. Guidance is often, but not exclusively, employed as part of a BRT scheme. --&gt; Extensions of the guided technology include the [[Bombardier Guided Light Transit|Guided Light Transit]] and [[Translohr]] systems, although these are more often termed 'rubber-tyred trams' as they have limited or no mobility away from their guideways.

===Liveries===
[[Transit bus]]es are normally painted to identify the operator or a route, function, or to demarcate low-cost or premium service buses. Liveries may be painted onto the vehicle, applied using adhesive [[vinyl (fabric)|vinyl]] technologies, or using [[decal]]s. Vehicles often also carry [[bus advertising]] or part or all of their visible surfaces (as [[mobile billboard]]). [[Campaign bus]]es may be decorated with key campaign messages; these can be to promote an event or initiative.

===Propulsion===
[[File:Ride On 5312 at Glenmont.jpg|thumb|[[Ride On (bus)|Ride On]] [[hybrid electric bus]] with appropriate livery]]
[[File:ASEAG 999 Seite.jpg|thumb|Articulated bus powered with [[Lithium-ion battery|lithium-ion batteries]]]]

The most common power source since the 1920s has been the [[diesel engine]]. Early buses, known as trolleybuses, were powered by electricity supplied from [[overhead lines]]. Nowadays, electric buses often carry their own battery, which is sometimes [[Phileas (public transport)|recharged on stops/stations]] to keep the size of the battery small/lightweight. Currently, interest exists in [[hybrid electric bus]]es, [[fuel cell bus]]es, [[electric bus]]es, and ones powered by [[compressed natural gas]] or [[biodiesel]]. [[Gyrobus]]es, which are powered by the momentum stored by a [[flywheel]], were tried in the 1940s.

===Dimensions===

United Kingdom and European Union:

:Maximum Length: Single rear axle {{convert|13.5|m|ftin|sp=us|frac=8}}. Twin rear axle {{convert|15|m|ftin|sp=us|frac=8}}.
:Maximum Width: {{convert|2.55|m|ftin|sp=us|frac=8}}

United States, Canada and Mexico:

:Maximum Length: None
:Maximum Width: {{convert|2.6|m|ftin|sp=us|frac=8}}

==Manufacture==
{{Main|Bus manufacturing}}
Early bus manufacturing grew out of carriage [[coachbuilding]], and later out of automobile or truck manufacturers. Early buses were merely a bus body fitted to a truck chassis. This body+chassis approach has continued with modern specialist manufacturers, although there also exist integral designs such as the [[Leyland National]] where the two are practically inseparable. Specialist builders also exist and concentrate on building buses for special uses or modifying standard buses into specialised products.

Integral designs have the advantages that they have been well-tested for strength and stability, and also are [[Commercial off-the-shelf|off-the-shelf]]. However, two incentives cause use of the chassis+body model. First, it allows the buyer and manufacturer both to shop for the best deal for their needs, rather than having to settle on one fixed design—the buyer can choose the body and the chassis separately. Second, over the lifetime of a vehicle (in constant service and heavy traffic), it will likely get minor damage now and again, and being able easily to replace a body panel or window etc. can vastly increase its [[service life]] and save the cost and inconvenience of removing it from service.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}

As with the rest of the [[automotive industry]], into the 20th century, bus manufacturing increasingly became globalized, with manufacturers producing buses far from their intended market to exploit labour and material cost advantages. As with the cars, new models are often exhibited by manufacturers at prestigious industry shows to gain new orders.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}  A typical city bus costs almost US$450,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gross&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last1=Gross |first1=Daniel |title=Further |url=http://www.slate.com/articles/technology/the_juice/2014/09/electric_buses_proterra_wants_to_rid_america_of_emission_spewing_buses.html |website=[[Slate (magazine)|Slate]] |publisher=[[The Slate Group]] |accessdate=5 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Uses==

===Public transport===
[[File:Sydney Buses (mo 1298) Custom Coaches 'Citaro' bodied Mercedes-Benz O405NH CNG on Loftus Street in Circular Quay (cropped).jpg|thumb|A [[Mercedes-Benz O405|Mercedes-Benz O405NH CNG]] public transit bus in [[Sydney]], Australia]]
[[File:Double Decker Bus Angamaly BUS STAND.JPG|thumb|A double decker bus used for public transit in [[Kerala]], [[India]]]]
{{Main|Public transport bus service}}

[[Transit bus]]es, used on [[public transport bus service]]s, have utilitarian fittings designed for efficient movement of large numbers of people, and often have multiple doors. Coaches are used for longer-distance routes. High-capacity [[bus rapid transit]] services may use the bi-articulated bus or tram-style buses such as the [[Wright StreetCar]] and the [[Iveco Bus|Irisbus]] Civis.

Buses and coach services often operate to a predetermined published [[public transport timetable]] defining the route and the timing, but smaller vehicles may be used on more flexible [[demand responsive transport]] services.

===Tourism===
[[File:Foxity à Louvre-Rivoli par Cramos (cropped).JPG|thumb|right|Tour bus being used in France]]

Buses play a major part in the tourism industry. [[Tour bus]]es around the world allow tourists to view local attractions or scenery. These are often [[open-top bus]]es, but can also be regular buses or coaches.

In local [[sightseeing]], [[City Sightseeing]] is the largest operator of local tour buses, operating on a franchised basis all over the world. Specialist tour buses are also often owned and operated by [[safari park]]s and other [[Amusement park|theme parks or resorts]]. Longer-distance tours are also carried out by bus, either on a turn up and go basis or through a [[tour operator]], and usually allow disembarkation from the bus to allow touring of sites of interest on foot. These may be day trips or longer [[excursion]]s incorporating hotel stays. Tour buses often carry a tour guide, although the driver or a recorded [[audio commentary]] may also perform this function. The tour operator may be a subsidiary of a company that operates buses and coaches for other uses or an independent company that charters buses or coaches. [[Commuter]] transport operators may also use their coaches to conduct tours within the target city between the morning and evening commuter transport journey.

Buses and coaches are also a common component of the wider [[package holiday]] industry, providing private airport transfers (in addition to general [[airport bus]]es) and organised tours and day trips for holidaymakers on the package.

Tour buses can also be hired as chartered buses by groups for sightseeing at popular holiday destinations. These private tour buses may offer specific stops, such as all the historical sights, or allow the customers to choose their own itineraries. Tour buses come with professional and informed staff and insurance, and maintain state governed safety standards. Some provide other facilities like entertainment units{{clarify|date=May 2019}}, luxurious reclining seats, large scenic windows, and even lavatories.

Public long-distance coach networks are also often used as a low-cost method of travel by students or young people travelling the world. Some companies such as [[Topdeck Travel]] were set up specifically to use buses to drive the [[hippie trail]] or travel to places such as North Africa.

In many tourist or travel destinations, a bus is part of the [[tourist attraction]], such as the North American [[tourist trolley]]s, London's [[AEC Routemaster]] [[London Buses heritage routes (disambiguation)|heritage route]]s, or the [[customised buses]] of Malta, Asia, and the Americas. Another example of tourist stops is the homes of [[celebrities]], such as tours based near [[Hollywood]]. There are several such services between 6000 and 7000 Hollywood Boulevard in Los Angeles.

===Student transport===
[[File:HCS bus49.JPG|thumb|US [[school bus]]]]
{{Main|Student transport}}

In some countries, particularly the US and Canada, buses used to transport schoolchildren have evolved into a specific design with specified mandatory features. American states have also adopted laws regarding motorist conduct around school buses, including large fines and possibly prison for passing a stopped school bus in the process of loading or offloading children passengers. These [[school bus]]es may have [[school bus yellow]] livery and [[School bus crossing arm|crossing guards]]. Other countries may mandate the use of [[seat belts]]. As a minimum, many countries require a bus carrying students to display a [[:Commons:Category:School bus signs|sign]], and may also adopt yellow liveries. Student transport often uses older buses cascaded from service use, retrofitted with more seats or seatbelts. Student transport may be operated by local authorities or private contractors. Schools may also own and operate their own buses for other transport needs, such as class [[field trip]]s, or transport to associated sports, music, or other school events.

===Private charter===
Due to the costs involved in owning, operating, and driving buses and coaches, many bus and coach use a [[private hire]] of vehicles from [[charter]] bus companies, either for a day or two or a longer contract basis, where the charter company provides the vehicles and qualified drivers.

[[File:BCI bodied Mercedes-Benz OC 500 RF BusWest 01.jpg|thumb|right|An example of a private bus operating for BusWest in [[Perth]]]]

Charter bus operators may be completely independent businesses, or charter hire may be a subsidiary business of a public transport operator that might maintain a separate fleet or use surplus buses, coaches, and dual-purpose coach-seated buses. Many private [[taxicab]] companies also operate larger [[minibus]] vehicles to cater for group fares. Companies, private groups, and social clubs may hire buses or coaches as a cost-effective method of transporting a group to an event or site, such as a group meeting, [[racing]] event, or organised recreational activity such as a [[summer camp]]. Schools often hire charter bus services on regular basis for transportation of children to and from their homes. Chartered buses are also used by education institutes for transport to [[convention (meeting)|convention]]s, exhibitions, and [[field trips]]. Entertainment or event companies may also hire temporary shuttles buses for transport at events such as festivals or [[academic conference|conference]]s. [[Party bus]]es are used by companies in a similar manner to [[limousine]] hire, for luxury private transport to social events or as a touring experience. [[Sleeper bus]]es are used by bands or other organisations that tour between entertainment venues and require mobile rest and recreation facilities. Some couples hire preserved buses for their wedding transport, instead of the traditional car. Buses are often hired for [[parade]]s or [[procession]]s. [[Victory parade]]s are often held for triumphant sports teams, who often tour their home town or city in an [[open-top bus]]. Sports teams may also contract out their transport to a team bus, for travel to [[Road (sports)|away games]], to a [[Sports competition|competition]] or to a [[Final (competition)|final event]]. These buses are often specially decorated in a livery matching the team colours. Private companies often contract out private shuttle bus services, for transport of their customers or patrons, such as hotels, [[amusement park]]s, [[university campus]]es, or [[airport bus|private airport transfer]] services. This shuttle usage can be as transport between locations, or to and from [[parking lot]]s. High specification luxury coaches are often chartered by companies for [[Executive officer|executive]] or [[Very Important Person|VIP]] transport. Charter buses may also be used in tourism and for promotion (See Tourism and Promotion sections).

===Private ownership===
[[File:Taipei Taiwan Police-bus-01.jpg|thumb|right|Police bus]]

Many organisations, including the police, [[not for profit]], social or charitable groups with a regular need for group transport may find it practical or cost-effective to own and operate a bus for their own needs. These are often [[minibus]]es for practical, tax and driver licensing reasons, although they can also be full-size buses. [[Cadet]] or [[Scouting|scout]] groups or other youth organizations may also own buses. Specific charities may exist to fund and operate bus transport, usually using specially modified mobility buses or otherwise accessible buses (See Accessibility section). Some use their contributions to buy vehicles and provide volunteer drivers.

Airport operators make use of special airside [[airport bus]]es for crew and passenger transport in the secure [[Airside (airport)|airside]] parts of an airport. Some public authorities, police forces, and military forces make use of [[armoured bus]]es where there is a special need to provide increased passenger protection.  The [[United States Secret Service]] acquired two in 2010 for transporting dignitaries needing special protection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Robert Farley |title=Obama's Canadian-American Bus |url=http://www.factcheck.org/2011/08/obamas-canadian-american-bus/ |work=FactCheck |date=25 August 2011 |accessdate=17 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Police department]]s make use of [[police bus]]es for a variety of reasons, such as [[Prisoner transport vehicle|prisoner transport]], [[police officer|officer]] transport, temporary detention facilities, and as [[command post|command and control vehicles]]. Some [[fire department]]s also use a converted bus as a command post&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://cityofchesapeake.net/services/depart/fire/bus.shtml |title=Chesapeake Fire Department |publisher=Cityofchesapeake.net |date=1 May 1998 |accessdate=12 October 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101121035613/http://cityofchesapeake.net/services/depart/fire/bus.shtml |archivedate=21 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; while those in cold climates might retain a bus as a heated shelter at fire scenes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=City of Winnipeg Corporate Web Services |url=http://www.winnipeg.ca/fps/Services/Operations/MIRV.stm |title=Winnipeg Fire Department |publisher=Winnipeg.ca |accessdate=12 October 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100106020819/http://www.winnipeg.ca/fps/Services/Operations/MIRV.stm |archivedate=6 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many are drawn from retired school or service buses.

===Promotion===
Buses are often used for advertising, [[political campaign]]ing, [[:Category:Public service announcements|public information campaigns]], [[public relation]]s, or [[Promotion (marketing)|promotional]] purposes. These may take the form of temporary charter hire of service buses, or the temporary or permanent conversion and operation of buses, usually of [[Used good|second-hand]] buses. Extreme examples include converting the bus with displays and decorations or [[awning]]s and fittings. Interiors may be fitted out for exhibition or information purposes with special equipment or [[audio visual]] devices.

[[File:AVBWU237 641(KMB) 14-09-2018.jpg|thumb|Advertisement on a bus]]

[[Bus advertising]] takes many forms, often as interior and exterior adverts and all-over advertising liveries. The practice often extends into the exclusive private hire and use of a bus to promote a brand or product, appearing at large public events, or touring busy streets. The bus is sometimes staffed by promotions personnel, giving out free gifts. [[Campaign bus]]es are often specially decorated for a [[political campaign]] or other social awareness information campaign, designed to bring a specific message to different areas, or used to transport campaign personnel to local areas/meetings. Exhibition buses are often sent to public events such as [[fair]]s and festivals for purposes such as recruitment campaigns, for example by private companies or the [[armed force]]s. Complex [[urban planning]] proposals may be organised into a mobile exhibition bus for the purposes of public consultation.

===Goods transport===
{{Main|Bruck (vehicle)}}
In some sparsely populated areas, it is common to use brucks, buses with a cargo area to transport both passengers and cargo at the same time. They are especially common in the [[Nordic countries]].

==Around the world==
[[File:CamelitoLaHavane 01.jpg|thumb|right|Trailer bus]]
[[File:Knight Bus 3.jpg|thumb|300px|The Knight Bus, seen in the [[Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban (film)|''Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban'' film]], at [[Warner Bros. Studios, Leavesden]].]]
{{See also|Category:Bus transport by country|List of buses}}

Historically, the types and features of buses have developed according to local needs. Buses were fitted with technology appropriate to the local climate or passenger needs, such as air conditioning in Asia, or [[Bicycle|cycle]] mounts on North American buses. The bus types in use around the world where there was little mass production were often sourced second hand from other countries, such as the [[Malta bus]], and buses in use in Africa. Other countries such as Cuba required novel solutions to import restrictions, with the creation of the &quot;camellos&quot; ([[Transport in Cuba#Urban buses|camel bus]]), a specially manufactured [[trailer bus]]. 

After the Second World War, manufacturers in Europe and the Far East, such as [[Mercedes-Benz buses]] and [[Mitsubishi Fuso Truck and Bus Corporation|Mitsubishi Fuso]] expanded into other continents influencing the use of buses previously served by local types. Use of buses around the world has also been influenced by colonial associations or political alliances between countries. Several of the [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth nations]] followed the British lead and sourced buses from British manufacturers, leading to a prevalence of [[double-decker bus]]es. Several [[Eastern Bloc]] countries adopted trolleybus systems, and their manufacturers such as [[Trolza]] exported trolleybuses to other friendly states.{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}} In the 1930s, Italy designed the world's only{{dubious|Triple decker bus|date=March 2013}} triple decker bus for the busy route between Rome and Tivoli that could carry eighty-eight passengers.  It was unique not only in being a triple decker but having a separate smoking compartment on the third level.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=7-EDAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA286&amp;dq=popular+mechanics+1932+the+president+of+a+big&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=JIgVTcvHIM2AnQf50_3fDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCYQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true &quot;Three Decker Auto Bus Carries 88 Persons&quot;] ''Popular Mechanics'', August 1932&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Knight Bus]] in [[Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban]] is a full-sized triple decker bus used only as a prop for the movie.

The buses to be found in countries around the world often reflect the quality of the local road network, with high floor resilient truck-based designs prevalent in several less developed countries where buses are subject to tough operating conditions. Population density also has a major impact, where dense urbanisation such as in Japan and the far east has led to the adoption of high capacity long [[multi-axle bus]]es, often double-deckers while South America and China are implementing large numbers of [[articulated bus]]es for [[bus rapid transit]] schemes.

===Bus expositions===
Euro Bus Expo is a [[Trade fair|trade show]], which is held [[wikt:Special:Search/biennial|biennially]] at the UK's [[National Exhibition Centre]] in Birmingham. As the official show of the [[Confederation of Passenger Transport]], the UK's trade association for the bus, coach and light rail industry, the three-day event offers visitors from Europe and beyond the chance to see and experience the very latest vehicles and product and service innovations right across the industry.

Busworld Kortrijk in [[Kortrijk]], Belgium, is the leading bus trade fair in Europe. It is also held biennially.

==Use of retired buses==
[[File:GMBus.jpg|thumb|left|Retired [[General Motors|GM]] bus]]
[[File:EM-leyland-tow-truck-1.jpg|thumb|right|Retired bus in Israel used as a tow truck]]

Most public or private buses and coaches, once they have reached the end of their service with one or more operators, are sent to the [[wrecking yard]] for breaking up for [[scrap]] and [[spare part]]s. Some buses which are not economical to keep running as service buses are often converted for use other than revenue-earning transport. Much like old cars and trucks, buses often pass through a [[Car dealership|dealership]] where they can be bought privately or at auction.

Bus operators often find it economical to convert retired buses to use as permanent [[training bus]]es for driver training, rather than taking a regular service bus out of use. Some large operators have also converted retired buses into tow bus vehicles, to act as [[tow truck]]s. With the outsourcing of maintenance staff and facilities, the increase in company [[health and safety]] regulations, and the increasing [[curb weight]]s of buses, many operators now contract their towing needs to a professional [[vehicle recovery]] company.

Some retired buses have been converted to static or mobile cafés, often using historic buses as a [[tourist attraction]]. There are also catering buses: buses converted into a mobile [[Canteen (place)|canteen]] and [[Coffee break|break room]]. These are commonly seen at external [[filming location]]s to feed the cast and crew, and at other large events to feed staff. Another use is as an emergency vehicle, such as high-capacity [[ambulance bus]] or mobile [[command center]].

Some organisations adapt and operate [[playbus]]es or learning buses to provide a [[playground]] or learning environments to children who might not have access to proper play areas. An ex-London [[AEC Routemaster]] bus has been converted to a mobile theatre and [[Runway (fashion)|catwalk fashion show]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/stage/2008/aug/16/theatre.londonlistings1 Event preview: Fashion Bus On The Square, London] ''The Guardian'', 16 August 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

Some buses meet a destructive end by being entered in [[banger racing|banger races]] or at [[demolition derby]]s. A larger number of old retired buses have also been converted into mobile holiday homes and campers.

===Bus preservation===
[[File:MTT-AECRegalVI-BPSWA.JPG|thumb|right|A preserved AEC Regal VI operated formerly by the MTT in Perth]]

Rather than being [[wikt:scrapped|scrapped]] or converted for other uses, sometimes retired buses are saved for preservation. This can be done by individuals, volunteer preservation groups or charitable trusts, museums, or sometimes by the operators themselves as part of a [[heritage fleet]]. These buses often need to be [[vehicle restoration|restored]] to their original condition and will have their livery and other details such as internal notices and [[rollsign]]s restored to be authentic to a specific time in the bus's history. Some buses that undergo preservation are rescued from a state of great disrepair, but others enter preservation with very little wrong with them. As with other historic vehicles, many preserved buses either in a working or static state form part of the collections of [[List of transport museums|transport museums]]. Working buses will often be exhibited at rallies and events, and they are also used as charter buses. While many preserved buses are quite old or even vintage, in some cases relatively new examples of a bus type can enter restoration. In-service examples are still in use by other operators. This often happens when a change in design or operating practice, such as the switch to one person operation or low floor technology, renders some buses redundant while still relatively new.

==Modification as railway vehicles==
{{Main|Railbus}}

==See also==
{{portal|Buses|Transport}}
{{div col|colwidth=22em}}
* [[Coach (bus)]]
* [[Bicycle carrier]] (bus mounted bike racks)
* [[Bus spotting]]
* [[Bus station]]
* [[Cutaway bus]]
* [[Dollar van]]
* [[Horsebus]]
* [[Intercity bus]]
* [[Intercity bus driver]]
* [[List of fictional buses]]
* [[Public light bus]]
* [[Trackless train]]
* [[Transit bus]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em|refs=
&lt;ref name=Ward1974&gt;{{Citation |title=The World of Automobiles: An Illustrated Encyclopedia of the Motor Car |volume=15 |first=Ian |last=Ward |publisher=Orbis |year=1974 |page=1773}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name= Eckermann2001&gt;{{Citation |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=yLZeQwqNmdgC&amp;pg=PA687#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=World History of the Automobile |first=Erik |last=Eckermann |publisher=SAE |year=2001 |ISBN=9780768008005 |pages=67–68 |accessdate=6 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==Bibliography==
*{{cite book |last=Combeau |first=Yvan |title=Histoire de Paris |year=2013 |publisher=Presses Universitaires de France |location=Paris |ISBN=978-2-13-060852-3}}
*{{cite book |last=Fierro |first=Alfred |title=Histoire et dictionnaire de Paris |year=1996 |publisher=Robert Laffont |ISBN=2-221-07862-4 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Héron de Villefosse |first=René |title=HIstoire de Paris |year=1959 |publisher=Bernard Grasset}}

==External links==
* {{Commons and category-inline|Bus|Bus transport}}
* {{Wiktionary-inline}}
* [http://www.buses.org American Bus Association]

{{buses}}
{{public transport}}
{{bus rapid transit}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2012}}

{{authority control}}

[[Category:Bus transport| ]]
[[Category:Buses| ]]
[[Category:French inventions]]</text>
      <sha1>nl2ftfqx1iq7bzteblsh16cy8us9xni</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
