  <page>
    <title>Barge</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4177</id>
    <revision>
      <id>936858791</id>
      <parentid>936858426</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-21T12:54:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>PBS</username>
        <id>26801</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Types */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|flat-bottomed boat, built mainly for river, canal transport of heavy goods, usually towed by tugboats}}
{{Other uses}}

[[File:Barge on River Thames, London - Dec 2009.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Barges towed by a tugboat on the [[River Thames]] in [[London]], [[England]], [[UK]]]]

A '''barge''' is a [[Draft (hull)|shoal-draft]] flat-bottomed [[boat]], built mainly for [[river]] and [[canal]] transport of bulk goods. Originally barges were towed by draft horses on an adjacent [[towpath]]. Today, barges may be self-propelled, usually with a slow-revving diesel engine and a large-diameter fixed-pitch [[propeller]]. Otherwise, &quot;dumb barges&quot; must be towed by [[tug]]s, or pushed by [[Pusher (boat)|pusher boats]]. Compared to a towed barge, a pusher system has improved handling and is more efficient, as the pushing tug becomes &quot;part of the unit&quot; and it contributes to the momentum of the whole.

==History==
In Great Britain, during the [[Industrial Revolution]], a substantial network of narrow canals was developed from 1750 onwards; but from 1825 competition from the [[railway]]s eventually [[history of the British canal system|took over from canal traffic]] due to the higher speed, falling costs and route flexibility of [[rail transport]]. Barges carrying bulk and heavy cargoes continue to be viable. Originally, British canals had locks only {{convert|7|ft|spell=in||}} wide, so [[narrowboats]] could be no more than 6'10&quot; wide if they were to be able to navigate the system. It was soon realised that narrow locks were too limiting, and later locks were doubled in width to {{convert|14|ft|spell=in||}}. Accordingly, on the [[Canals of Great Britain|British canal system]] the term 'barge' is used to describe a &quot;[[Thames sailing barge|Thames [sailing barge]]], [[Dutch barge|Duch [barge]]], or other styles of [[barge]]&quot; (the people who move barges are often known as [[lightermen]]),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=All craft great and small |website=Canal &amp; River Trust |date=28 January 2019 |url=https://canalrivertrust.org.uk/enjoy-the-waterways/boating/getting-afloat/all-craft-great-and-small |ref={{sfnref|''Canal &amp; River Trust''|2019}}|access-date=21 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; and does not include [[Narrowboat]]s and [[Widebeam]]s (see also [[canal craft]]).{{sfn|''Canal &amp; River Trust''|2019}}

In the United States, deckhands perform the labor and are supervised by a leadman or the mate. The captain and pilot steer the towboat, which pushes one or more barges held together with rigging, collectively called 'the tow'. The crew live aboard the towboat as it travels along the inland river system or the intracoastal waterways. These towboats travel between ports and are also called line-haul boats.&lt;ref&gt;[https://maritimelawcenter.com/html/non-self_propelled_vessels.html Maritime law center,  Non-self propelled vessels]&lt;/ref&gt;

Poles are used on barges to fend off the barge as it nears other vessels or a wharf. These are often called 'pike poles'. (The long pole used to maneuver or propel a barge has given rise to the saying &quot;I wouldn't touch that with a barge pole&quot;.)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title = Speeches of Lord Randolph Churchill | editor = H. W. Lucy | author = Randolph Henry Spencer Churchill | year = 1885 | quote = &quot;...never was land so easily and cheaply in the grasp of the capitalist as it is now, if he chose to put out his hand, and yet there is not a capitalist in his senses who would touch it with a barge pole.&quot; | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=Kn4MAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA51 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology==
[[Image:PénicheRecyclageFerrailles2008Deûle2.jpg|thumb|right|A barge carrying recycling material on Deûle channel in [[Lambersart]], [[France]]]]
&quot;Barge&quot; is attested from 1300, from [[Old French]] ''barge'', from [[Vulgar Latin]] ''barga''. The word originally could refer to any small boat; the modern meaning arose around 1480. ''[[barque|Bark]]'' &quot;small ship&quot; is attested from 1420, from Old French ''barque'', from Vulgar Latin ''barca'' (400 AD). The more precise meaning &quot;three-masted ship&quot; arose in the 17th century, and often takes the French spelling for disambiguation. Both are probably derived from the [[Latin]] ''barica'', from [[Greek language|Greek]] ''baris'' &quot;Egyptian boat&quot;, from [[Coptic language|Coptic]] ''bari'' &quot;small boat&quot;, [[hieroglyphic]] Egyptian &lt;small&gt;&lt;hiero&gt;D58-G29-M17-M17-D21-P1&lt;/hiero&gt;&lt;/small&gt; and similar ''ba-y-r'' for &quot;basket-shaped boat&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=8cMWickoS6oC&amp;pg=PA202&amp;lpg=PA202&amp;dq=egyptian+word+for+boat+Bairi+&amp;source=web&amp;ots=HyFttihvZr&amp;sig=x11WDJZ-M-mACFmJCF-KKanlHvg&amp;hl=en ''An Egyptian hieroglyphic dictionary: with an index of English words''] by Sir Ernest Alfred Wallis Budge from [[Google Books]]&lt;/ref&gt; By extension, the term &quot;embark&quot; literally means to board the kind of boat called a &quot;barque&quot;.

The long pole used to maneuver or propel a barge have given rise to the saying &quot;I wouldn't touch that [subject/thing] with a barge pole.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title = Speeches of Lord Randolph Churchill | editor = H. W. Lucy | author = Randolph Henry Spencer Churchill | year = 1885 | quote = &quot;...never was land so easily and cheaply in the grasp of the capitalist as it is now, if he chose to put out his hand, and yet there is not a capitalist in his senses who would touch it with a barge pole.&quot; | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=Kn4MAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA51&amp;dq=touch+it+with+a+barge+pole&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=b831UYL7F6f5iwKU14DgDg&amp;ved=0CC4Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=touch%20it%20with%20a%20barge%20pole&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Types==
{{Div col|colwidth=22em}}
* Accommodation barge = Hotel &quot;Ships&quot;
* Admiral's barge
* [[Articulated tug and barge]]
* [[Barracks barge]] (houseboat)
* Bin barge
* [[Day Peckinpaugh (canal motorship)|Canal motorship]]
* [[Car float]]
* [[Type_B_ship#Concrete_Barge|Concrete Barge]]
* [[Crane barge]]
* [[Dredges]]
* Deck barge
* [[Dutch barge]]
* [[Dry bulk cargo barge]]
* [[Hopper barge]]
* [[Hotel barge]]
* [[Horse-drawn boat]]
* [[Jackup barge]]
* [[Landing craft|Landing barge]]
* [[Lighter (barge)|Lighter]] and Dumb steel lighter
* [[Liquid cargo barge]]
* Log barge
* Notch barge
* [[Narrowboat]]
* [[Norfolk wherry]]
* [[Autonomous spaceport drone ship|Rocket landing barge]]
* Oil barge and Dumb steel oil barge
* [[Paddle barge]]
* [[Péniche (barge)|Péniche]] or Spitz barge
* [[Pleasure barge]]
* [[Power barge]]
* Row barge
* [[Royal barge]]
* Sand barge
* Severn [[trow]]
* [[Tank barge]]
* [[Thames sailing barge]]
* [[Tom Pudding]]
* [[Tub boat]]
* Vehicular barge
* [[Whaleback barge]]
* [[Widebeam]]
{{Div col end}}

==Modern use==
[[File:Chicago River towboat and barge 080405.jpg|thumb|right|Towboat pushing a barge on the [[Chicago River]]]]
Barges are used today for low-value bulk items, as the cost of hauling goods by barge is very low. Barges are also used for very heavy or bulky items; a typical American barge measures {{convert|195|x|35|ft|m|sigfig=3}}, and can carry up to about {{convert|1500|ST|t}} of cargo. The most common European barge measures {{convert|76.5|x|11.4|m|ft|order=flip}} and can carry up to about {{convert|2450|t|ST}}.

As an example, on June 26, 2006, a {{convert|565|ST|t|adj=on}} [[Cracking (chemistry)|catalytic cracking]] unit reactor was shipped by barge from the [[Tulsa Port of Catoosa]] in [[Oklahoma]] to a refinery in [[Pascagoula, Mississippi]]. Extremely large objects are normally shipped in sections and assembled onsite, but shipping an assembled unit reduced costs and avoided reliance on construction labor at the delivery site (which in this case was still recovering from [[Hurricane Katrina]]). Of the reactor's {{convert|700|mi|adj=on}} journey, only about {{convert|40|miles|km}} were traveled overland, from the final port to the refinery.

Self-propelled barges may be used as such when traveling downstream or upstream in placid waters; they are operated as an unpowered barge, with the assistance of a tugboat, when traveling upstream in faster waters. Canal barges are usually made for the particular canal in which they will operate.

Many barges, primarily [[Dutch barge]]s, which were originally designed for carrying cargo along the canals of Europe, are no longer large enough to compete in this industry with larger newer vessels. Many of these barges have been renovated and are now used as luxury [[hotel barge]]s carrying holidaymakers along the same canals on which they once carried grain or coal.

==Dumb barges in the United States==
[[File:Cumberland River barge traffic.jpg|thumb|Multiple barges pushed around a tight bend on the [[Cumberland River]]]]
In primitive regions today and in all pre-development (lacking highways or railways) regions worldwide in times before industrial development and highways, barges were the predominant and most efficient means of inland transportation in many regions. This holds true today, for many areas of the world.

In such pre-industrialized, or poorly developed infrastructure regions, many barges are purpose-designed to be powered on waterways by long slender poles – thereby becoming known on American waterways as '''poleboats''' as the extensive west of North America was settled using the vast tributary river systems of the [[Mississippi River|Mississippi]] [[drainage basin]]. Poleboats use muscle power of &quot;walkers&quot; along the sides of the craft pushing a pole against the streambed, canal or lake bottom to move the vessel where desired. In settling the American west it was generally faster to navigate downriver from [[Brownsville, Pennsylvania]], to the [[Ohio River]] confluence with the [[Mississippi River|Mississippi]] and then pole upriver against the current to St. Louis than to travel overland on the rare primitive dirt roads for many decades after the [[American Revolution]].

Once the New York Central and Pennsylvania Railroads reached Chicago, that time dynamic changed, and American poleboats became less common, relegated to smaller rivers and more remote streams. On the Mississippi riverine system today, including that of other sheltered waterways, industrial barge trafficking in bulk raw materials such as coal, coke, timber, iron ore and other minerals is extremely common; in the developed world using huge '''cargo barges''' that connect in groups and trains-of-barges in ways that allow cargo volumes and weights considerably greater than those used by pioneers of modern barge systems and methods in the [[Victorian era]].
[[File:The tugboat, Herbert P. Brake.jpg|thumb|[[Towboat]] ''Herbert P. Brake'' of New York pushes a new barge east on the [[Erie Canal]] in [[Fairport, New York|Fairport]], [[New York City|New York]], United States]]

Such barges need to be towed by [[tugboat]]s or pushed by [[towboat]]s. Canal barges, towed by draft animals on a waterway adjacent [[towpath]] were of fundamental importance in the early [[Industrial Revolution]], whose major early engineering projects were efforts to build [[viaduct]]s, [[navigable aqueduct|aqueducts]] and especially canals to fuel and feed raw materials to nascent factories in the early industrial takeoff (18th century) and take their goods to ports and cities for distribution.

The barge and canal system contended favourably with the [[railway]]s in the early [[Industrial Revolution]] before around the 1850s&amp;ndash;1860s; for example, the [[Erie Canal]] in [[New York (state)|New York]] state is credited by economic historians with giving the growth boost needed for [[New York City]] to eclipse [[Philadelphia]] as America's largest port and city – but such canal systems with their locks, need for maintenance and dredging, pumps and sanitary issues [[history of the British canal system|were eventually outcompeted]] in the carriage of high-value items by the railways due to the higher speed, falling costs and route flexibility of [[rail transport]]. Barge and canal systems were nonetheless of great, perhaps even primary, economic importance until after the [[World War I|First World War]] in Europe, particularly in the more developed nations of the [[Low Countries]], [[France]], [[Germany]] and especially [[UK|Great Britain]] which more or less made the system characteristically its own.

Nowadays, custom built special purpose equipment called modular barges are extensively used in surveying, mapping, laying and burial of subsea optic fibre cables worldwide and other support services.

==Image gallery==
&lt;gallery class=center&gt;
File:Barge with cars.jpg|Self-propelled car barge on the [[River Danube]]
File:Péniches sur le Canal du Midi.jpg|Barges near [[Toulouse]], France
File:Andromeda (ship, 1958) Hannover Mittellandkanal 2006 by-RaBoe.jpg|Self-propelled barge ''Andromeda'' in canal at [[Hanover]], Germany
File:Messina_Karden_Bug.jpg|Tank barge on the [[River Moselle]], Germany
File:CrushedStoneBarge.jpg|Self-propelled barge carrying bulk crushed stone
File:IjmuidenBarge.jpg|Self-propelled barge in the port of [[IJmuiden]], Netherlands
File:Pegasus_barge_being_moved_by_Freedom_Star_and_towboat_American_2.jpg|Barge carrying the [[Space Shuttle]] external tank for STS-119 under tow to [[Port Canaveral]], [[Florida]], United States
File:Yangzhou-Modern-Grand-Canal-boats-3351.JPG|Self-propelled barges on the [[Grand Canal of China]] near [[Yangzhou]], [[Jiangsu]], China
File:CoalbargePittsburgh.JPG|Coal barges passing [[Heinz Field]] in [[Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania]] on the [[Ohio River]]
File:Suphannahongsa-docked.jpg|Royal Barge ''Suphannahong'' docked at [[Wat Arun]] [[pier]], one of the [[Thailand|Thai]] royal barges featured in the [[Royal Barge Procession|royal barge ceremony]]
Image:Donna York.jpg|[[Towboat]] ''Donna York'' pushing barges of coal up the Ohio River at [[Louisville, Kentucky|Louisville]], [[Kentucky]], United States
File:Ilya Repin - Barge Haulers on the Volga - Google Art Project.jpg|''[[Barge Haulers on the Volga]]'' (1870–73), by [[Ilya Repin]]
File:Kapal tongkang.jpg|''Tongkang'' or car barge, landed on Ketapang Port, Banyuwangi, Indonesia
File:slipway at portland.JPG|[[Slipway]] at [[Portland Harbour]], [[Dorset]], [[England]], holding a [[hopper barge|split dump barge]] (on right)
File:Barge on Mosel by Kues (1).jpg|Barge on the river [[Moselle|Mosel]] in [[Germany]].
File:Water_Barge_YW-59.jpg|US Navy Water [[Type B ship]] Barge, YW-59, launched August 29, 1941 
File:YFN-958-Covered_Lighter_Barge-Non-Self-Propelled.jpg|YFN-958 a covered lighter barge, non-Self-propelled. Built by Mare Island Navy Shipyard in 1944. 
File:Concrete Barge - Erie Canal - Lock 13 - 3.jpg|[[Ferrocement]] Barge, US-102, in the Erie Canal
File:Ww2 concrete barge, National Waterway Museum.jpg|WW2 concrete barge at the [[National Waterways Museum]], Ellesmere Port, Cheshire, UK
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Transport}}
{{Div col|colwidth=23em}}
* [[American Waterways Operators]]
* [[Burlak]]
* [[Ross Barlow|Canal boat ''Ross Barlow'']]
* [[Car float]]
* [[Chain boat]]
* [[Container on barge]]
* [[Dory]]
* [[Float (nautical)]]
* ''[[Hughes Mining Barge]]''
* [[Lighter (barge)|Lighter]]
* [[Mobro 4000]]
* [[Pusher (boat)]]
* [[Shallop]]
* [[Tub boat]]
* [[Type B ship]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{reflist}}
 
==External links==
{{Wiktionary|barge|bargee}}
{{Commons category|Barges}}
* [http://www.waterfrontmuseum.org/ Barge Lehigh Valley 79 at the Waterfront Museum], [[Brooklyn]], [[New York City|New York]], [[United States]]
* [http://www.waterscape.com/ Britain's Official guide to canals, rivers and lakes]
* {{Cite EB1911|wstitle=Barge}}
* [http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/systems/ship/bd.htm Crane Barge 89 Ton Design 264B]
* [http://www.barges.org/ DBA The Barge Association]
* [http://www.americanwaterways.com/ The American Waterways Operators]

{{ModernMerchantShipTypes}}
{{MARCOMships}}
{{WWIIUSShips}}

{{authority control}}

[[Category:Barges| ]]
[[Category:Shipping]]</text>
      <sha1>btw4nyxc5akhmlgqzwhmvumzywphpus</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
