  <page>
    <title>Foreign relations of the Dominican Republic</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8071</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938154342</id>
      <parentid>938154097</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-29T13:04:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mentatus</username>
        <id>96370</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Europe */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{more citations needed|date=February 2013}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{Politics of the Dominican Republic}}
The [[Dominican Republic]] has a close relationship with the United States and with the other states of the Inter-American system. It has accredited diplomatic missions in most [[Western Hemisphere]] countries and in principal European capitals.

==Bilateral relations==

{{Empty section|date=June 2019}}

==Africa==
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal Relations Began
! style=&quot;width:50%;&quot;| Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Egypt}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Cairo]].
* Egypt is accredited to the Dominican Republic from its embassy in Havana, Cuba.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Morocco}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Morocco has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Rabat]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|South Africa}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* South Africa is accredited to the Dominican Republic from its high commission in Kingston, Jamaica.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Pretoria]].
|}

==Americas==
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal Relations Began
! style=&quot;width:50%;&quot;| Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Argentina}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Argentina has an embassy in [[Santo Domingo]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://edomi.cancilleria.gov.ar/ Embassy of Argentina in Santo Domingo (in Spanish)]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Buenos Aires]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.embajadadominicana.com.ar/|title=Embajada de la República Dominicana en Argentina – Información consular y general para ciudadanos dominicanos en territorio argentino|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Belize}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Belize has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic is accredited to Belize from its embassy in Tegucigalpa, Honduras.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Brazil}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Brazil has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Brasilia]] and two consulates-general in [[Rio de Janeiro]] and [[São Paulo]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Canada}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Canada has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Ottawa]] and two consulates-general in [[Montreal]] and [[Toronto]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Chile}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Chile has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Santiago]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Colombia}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Colombia has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Bogotá]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Costa Rica}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Costa Rica has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[San José, Costa Rica|San José]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Cuba}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

The Dominican Republic and Cuba recently established consular relations, and there is contact in fields such as commerce, culture, and sports.
* Cuba has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Havana]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Ecuador}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Ecuador has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Quito]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|El Salvador}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* El Salvador has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[San Salvador]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Guatemala}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Guatemala has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Guatemala City]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Guyana}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;19 October 1970||
*Both countries established diplomatic relations on October 19, 1970.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.minfor.gov.gy/diplomatic-relations/|title=Countries with which Guyana has Establishment Diplomatic Relations – Ministry of Foreign Affairs - Co-operative Republic of Guyana|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
*Both countries are full members of the [[Organization of American States]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Haiti}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||See [[Dominican Republic–Haiti relations]]

* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Port-au-Prince]] and several consulates-generals throughout the country.
* Haiti has an embassy in Santo Domingo and several consulates-general throughout the country.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Honduras}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Honduras has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Tegucigalpa]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Jamaica}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Jamaica has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Kingston, Jamaica|Kingston]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Mexico}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;23 July 1888||See [[Dominican Republic–Mexico relations]]

Diplomatic relations between the Dominican Republic and Mexico were established on 23 July 1888.
* Mexico has an embassy in Santo Domingo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://embamex.sre.gob.mx/republicadominicana/|title=Inicio|website=embamex.sre.gob.mx}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Mexico City]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://embadom.org/|title=embadom – Otro sitio realizado con WordPress|publisher=|access-date=28 May 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190527171403/https://embadom.org/|archive-date=27 May 2019|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Nicaragua}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Nicaragua has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Managua]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Panama}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Panama has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Panama City]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Paraguay}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Paraguay has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Asuncion]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Peru}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Peru has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Lima]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Puerto Rico}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

The Dominican Republic has very strong ties and relations with Puerto Rico. Although a [[Commonwealth (United States insular area)|United States Commonwealth]], the island is the Dominican Republic's largest trading partner. While relations between the islands have had difficulties, mainly due the huge exodus of [[Dominican immigration to Puerto Rico|illegal immigrants]] from the Dominican Republic due to the nation's history of economic woes, the islands still, with the assistance of the [[United States Coast Guard]] and the [[Military of the Dominican Republic|Dominican Navy]] have worked hard to reduce the number of Dominicans crossing the [[Mona Passage]] in recent years. Puerto Rico is home to an estimated 485,000 Dominicans,&lt;ref&gt;[http://foro.univision.com/univision/board/message?board.id=puertorico&amp;message.id=175806 '' El 10% de la población de Puerto Rico es dominicana''] from ''Univision'' 10 December 2008&lt;/ref&gt; and the Dominican Republic maintains consulates in the cities of [[San Juan, Puerto Rico|San Juan]] and [[Mayagüez, Puerto Rico|Mayagüez]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Trinidad and Tobago}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Trinidad and Tobago is accredited to the Dominican Republic from its high commission in Kingston, Jamaica.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Port-of-Spain]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|United States}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||See [[Dominican Republic–United States relations]]

The Dominican Republic's standing as the largest Caribbean economy, second-largest country in terms of population and land mass, with large bilateral trade with the United States, and its proximity to the United States and other smaller Caribbean nations make the Dominican Republic an important partner in hemispheric affairs. The Embassy estimates that 100,000 U.S. citizens live in the Dominican Republic; many are dual nationals. An important element of the relationship between the two countries is the fact that more than 1 million individuals of Dominican origin reside in the United States, most of them in the metropolitan Northeast and some in [[Florida]].

U.S. relations with the Dominican Republic are excellent. The Dominican Government has been supportive of many U.S. initiatives in the United Nations and related agencies. The two governments cooperate in the fight against the traffic in illegal substances. The Dominican Republic has worked closely with U.S. law enforcement officials on issues such as the extradition of fugitives and measures to hinder illegal migration.

The United States supports efforts to improve Dominican competitiveness, to attract foreign private investment, to fight corruption, and to modernize the tax system. Bilateral trade is important to both countries. U.S. firms, mostly manufacturers of apparel, footwear, and light electronics, as well as U.S. energy companies, account for much of the foreign private investment in the Dominican Republic.

Exports from the United States, including those from Puerto Rico and the [[U.S. Virgin Islands]], to the Dominican Republic in 2005 totaled $5.3 billion, up 11% from the previous year. The Dominican Republic exported $4.5 billion to the United States in 2006, equaling some 75% of its export revenues. The Dominican Republic is the 47th-largest commercial partner of the U.S. The U.S. Embassy works closely with U.S. business firms and Dominican trade groups, both of which can take advantage of the new opportunities in this growing market. At the same time, the embassy is working with the Dominican Government to resolve a range of ongoing commercial and investment disputes.

The Embassy counsels U.S. firms through its Country Commercial Guide and informally via meetings with business persons planning to invest or already investing in the Dominican Republic. This is a challenging business environment for U.S. firms, especially for medium to smaller sized businesses.

The U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) mission is focused on improving access of underserved populations to quality health care and combating HIV/AIDS and tuberculosis; promoting economic growth through policy reform, support for [[CAFTA-DR]] implementation, and technical assistance to small producers and tourism groups; environmental protection and policy reform initiatives; improved access to quality primary, public education and assistance to at-risk youth; a model rural electrification program; and improving participation in democratic processes, while strengthening the judiciary and combating corruption across all sectors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://2009-2017.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/35639.htm|title=Dominican Republic|website=U.S. Department of State}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* United States has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Washington, D.C.]] and consulates-general in [[Boston]], [[Chicago]], [[Los Angeles]], [[Miami]], [[New Orleans]], [[New York City]], [[San Juan, Puerto Rico|San Juan]] and [[Mayagüez, Puerto Rico|Mayagüez]].
{{course assignment | course = Education Program:Manhattanville College/International Trade (Spring 2015) | term = Spring 2015 }}
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Uruguay}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||See [[Dominican Republic–Uruguay relations]]

* Uruguay has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Montevideo]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Venezuela}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

The Dominican Republic and Venezuela have kept a very close relationship throughout the early 2000s. Currently,{{when|date=July 2018}} Venezuela is the biggest seller of oil to the Dominican Republic. In 2003, Venezuela was selling to the Dominican Republic approximately 110,000 barrels of oil per day, making for more than 75% of the daily oil consumption in the country, including cars, factories, and electrical plants. Today, the Dominican Republic gets around 50,000 barrels of oil a day from Venezuela under the [[Petrocaribe]] agreement, which includes most of the Caribbean countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ipsnews.net/2003/09/venezuela-dominican-republic-oil-a-pawn-in-bilateral-relations/|title=VENEZUELA-DOMINICAN REPUBLIC: Oil a Pawn in Bilateral Relations - Inter Press Service|website=www.ipsnews.net}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Due to the Dominican economy, the country cannot afford all this oil through cash, so to pay Venezuela for the oil, the Dominican Government makes payments not only in cash, but also by exporting goods like black beans to Venezuela and other things like selling bonds. The Dominican Government has to export so many beans to Venezuela, Over 10,000 tons, that it had to start to import some beans from foreign countries to provide the population with beans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.csmonitor.com/World/Americas/2013/0327/Petrocaribe-Paying-beans-for-Venezuelan-oil|title=Petrocaribe: Paying beans for Venezuelan oil|date=27 March 2013|publisher=|via=Christian Science Monitor}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2015, the Dominican Government raised almost 2 billion dollars to pay off part of the debt they owed to Venezuela.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bloomberg.com/tosv2.html?vid=&amp;uuid=28fdffa0-1f20-11e9-8f80-abbff1d49d24&amp;url=L25ld3MvYXJ0aWNsZXMvMjAxNS0wMS0zMC9kb21pbmljYW4tcmVwdWJsaWMtdGFwcy0xLTktYmlsbGlvbi10by1wYXktdmVuZXp1ZWxhbi1vaWwtZGVidA==|title=Bloomberg - Are you a robot?|website=www.bloomberg.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Dominican Republic currently represents a 1.5 billion dollar year revenue to Venezuela just in the oil business itself, which is the reason why the Dominican Republic and Venezuela government have such a strong connection now that both countries are getting what they need from each other.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Caracas]].
* Venezuela has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
|}

==Asia==
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal Relations Began
! style=&quot;width:50%;&quot;| Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Armenia}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;9 October 2007||

Both countries established diplomatic relations on 9 October 2007.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|China}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;1 May 2018||See [[China–Dominican Republic relations]] and [[Dominican Republic–Taiwan relations]]

The Dominican Republic used to keep official relations with Taiwan, officially the Republic of China (ROC). On May 1, 2018, the Dominican Republic's government announced that diplomatic relations with Taiwan is severed and diplomatic ties with People's Republic of China is established, and recognize Taiwan as an “inalienable part of Chinese territory&quot;.
* China has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Beijing]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|India}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||See [[Dominican Republic–India relations]]

* India has an honorary consulate in Santo Domingo.&lt;ref&gt;[http://mea.gov.in/indian-mission.htm?60/60/0 Indian Honorary Consulate in Dominican Republic]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Dominican Republic maintains an embassy in [[New Delhi]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dr-embassy-india.com/|title=Dominican Republic|website=www.dr-embassy-india.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Israel}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Israel has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Tel Aviv]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Japan}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Japan has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Tokyo]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Philippines}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Dominican Republic is accredited to the Philippines from its embassy in New Delhi, India.
* Philippines is accredited to the Philippines from its embassy in Mexico City, Mexico.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Qatar}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Qatar has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Doha]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|South Korea}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;6 June 1962||

The establishment of diplomatic relations between the Republic of Korea and the Dominican Republic began on 6 June 1962.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.mofa.go.kr/ENG/countries/latinamerica/countries/20070803/1_24576.jsp?menu=m_30_30 |title=Archived copy |access-date=14 July 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150714115656/http://www.mofa.go.kr/ENG/countries/latinamerica/countries/20070803/1_24576.jsp?menu=m_30_30 |archive-date=14 July 2015 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
* South Korea has an embassy in Santo Domingo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://overseas.mofa.go.kr/do-ko/index.do|title=주 도미니카공화국 대한민국 대사관|website=overseas.mofa.go.kr}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Seoul]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.embadomcorea.com/|title=Embassy of the Dominican Republic in Korea|website=Embassy of the Dominican Republic in Korea}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Turkey}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Turkey has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic is accredited to Turkey from its embassy in Berlin, Germany.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|United Arab Emirates}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* United Arab Emirates is accredited to the Dominican Republic from its Permanent Mission to the United Nations in New York City.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Abu Dhabi]].
|}

==Europe==
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal Relations Began
! style=&quot;width:50%;&quot;| Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Andorra}}||&lt;!-- Start date --&gt;14 September 2000||

* Andorra does not have an accreditation to the Dominican Republic.
* Dominican Republic is accredited to Andorra from its embassy in Madrid, Spain and maintains an honorary consulate in [[Andorra la Vella]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Austria}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Austria has an embassy office in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Vienna]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Belgium}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Belgium is accredited to the Dominican Republic from its embassy in Kingston, Jamaica.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Brussels]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|France}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* France has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Paris]] and two consulates-general in [[Marseilles]] and [[Pointe-à-Pitre]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Germany}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Germany has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Berlin]] and a consulate-general in [[Hamburg]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Greece}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Greece is accredited to the Dominican Republic from its embassy in Havana, Cuba.
* Dominican Republic has a consulate-general in [[Athens]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Holy See}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Holy See has an Apostolic Nunciature in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Rome]] to the Holy See.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Italy}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Italy has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Rome]] and consulates-general in [[Genoa]] and [[Milan]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Netherlands}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Netherlands has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[The Hague]] and consulates-general in [[Amsterdam]], [[Willemstad]] and [[Philipsburg, Sint Maarten|Philipsburg]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Poland}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Dominican Republic is accredited to Poland from its embassy in Brussels, Belgium.
* Poland is accredited to the Dominican Republic from its embassy in Panama City, Panama.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Portugal}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Portugal is accredited to the Dominican Republic from its embassy in Mexico City, Mexico.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Lisbon]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Romania}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Dominican Republic is accredited to Romania from its embassy in Rome, Italy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.mirex.gob.do/medios/noticias/embajadora-peggy-cabral-presento-cartas-credenciales-ante-rumania|title=Embajadora Peggy Cabral presentó Cartas Credenciales ante Rumanía|publisher=Dominican Ministry of Foreign Affairs|language=Spanish|accessdate=29 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Romania is accredited to the Dominican Republic from its embassy in Bogotá, Colombia, and has a honorary consulate in Santo Domingo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mae.ro/en/romanian-missions#854|title=Romanian Missions – Dominican Republic|publisher=[[Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Romania)|Romanian Ministry of Foreign Affairs]]|accessdate=29 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Russia}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Russia is accredited to the Dominican Republic from its embassy in Caracas, Venezuela.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Moscow]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Spain}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;1855||See [[Dominican Republic–Spain relations]]

* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Madrid]], and two consulates-general in [[Barcelona]] and [[Santa Cruz de Tenerife]] and two consulates in [[Seville]] and [[Valencia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.embajadadominicana.es/|title=Coming Soon|website=www.embajadadominicana.es}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Spain has an embassy in Santo Domingo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.exteriores.gob.es/embajadas/santodomingo/es/Paginas/inicio.aspx|title=Páginas - Embajada de España en República Dominicana|website=www.exteriores.gob.es}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Sweden}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Sweden is accredited to the Dominican Republic from a non-resident ambassador based in Stockholm.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Stockholm]].
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Switzerland}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[Bern]].
* Switzerland has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|United Kingdom}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* United Kingdom has an embassy in Santo Domingo.
* Dominican Republic has an embassy in [[London]].
|}

==Oceania==
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Country
! style=&quot;width:12%;&quot;| Formal Relations Began
! style=&quot;width:50%;&quot;| Notes
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|{{flag|Australia}}||&lt;!--Date started--&gt;||

* Australia is accredited to the Dominica República from its embassy in Mexico City, Mexico.
* Dominican Republic is accredited to Australia from its embassy in London, United Kingdom.
|}

==Multilateral relations==
The Dominican Republic is a founding member of the [[United Nations]] and many of its specialized and related agencies, including the [[World Bank]], [[International Labour Organization]], [[International Atomic Energy Agency]], and [[International Civil Aviation Organization]]. It also is a member of the [[Organization of American States|OAS]], [[World Trade Organization]], [[World Health Organization]], World Customs Organization the [[Inter-American Development Bank]], [[Central American Integration System]], and ACP Group.

==See also==
*[[List of diplomatic missions in the Dominican Republic]]
*[[List of diplomatic missions of the Dominican Republic]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.mirex.gob.do/servicios/directorio/embajadas-exterior?page=2 Dominican Ministry of Foreign Affairs]

{{Foreign relations of the Dominican Republic}}
{{Dominican Republic topics}}
{{Americas topic|Foreign relations of|title=Foreign relations in the Americas}}

[[Category:Foreign relations of the Dominican Republic| ]]</text>
      <sha1>sms4dharlcgal8a96id7u2oz80542p0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
