  <page>
    <title>Day of the Tentacle</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8090</id>
    <revision>
      <id>929399890</id>
      <parentid>927501739</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-05T16:01:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Alistair1978</username>
        <id>86816</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>typo (via [[WP:JWB]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2017}}
{{Good article}}
{{Infobox video game
| title     = Day of the Tentacle
| image     = Day of the Tentacle artwork.jpg
| caption   = The cover artwork by Peter Chan depicts the three playable characters (Bernard, Hoagie and Laverne) running from the titular antagonist.
| developer = [[LucasArts]]{{efn|name=fn1|The remastered version was developed and published by [[Double Fine Productions]].}}
| publisher = LucasArts{{efn|name=fn1|The remastered version was developed and published by [[Double Fine Productions]].}}
| director  = {{Unbulleted list|[[Dave Grossman (game developer)|Dave Grossman]]|[[Tim Schafer]]}}
| producer  = {{Unbulleted list|Dave Grossman|Tim Schafer}}
| designer  = {{Unbulleted list|Tim Schafer|Dave Grossman}}
| artist    = [[Peter Chan (artist)|Peter Chan]]
| writer    = {{Unbulleted list|Tim Schafer|Dave Grossman|[[Ron Gilbert]]|[[Gary Winnick (game developer)|Gary Winnick]]}}
| composer  = {{Unbulleted list|[[Clint Bajakian]]|[[Peter McConnell]]|[[Michael Land]]}}
| engine    = [[SCUMM]]
| platforms = {{Unbulleted list|[[Classic Mac OS|Mac OS]]|[[MS-DOS]]|[[Microsoft Windows]]|[[OS X]]|[[PlayStation 4]]|[[PlayStation Vita]]|[[iOS]]|[[Linux]]}}
| released  = {{Collapsible list|titlestyle=font-weight:normal;background:transparent;text-align:left;|title=June 25, 1993|'''Mac OS''', '''MS-DOS'''{{Video game release|NA|June 25, 1993&lt;ref name=&quot;retrodiary&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |title=Retroradar: Retrodiary |journal=[[Retro Gamer]] |issue=91 |date=June 2011 |page=15 |publisher=[[Imagine Publishing]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}'''Win''', '''OS X''', '''PS4''', '''Vita'''{{Video game release|WW|March 22, 2016}}'''iOS''', '''Linux'''{{Video game release|WW|July 11, 2016}}}}
| genre     = [[Point-and-click adventure]]
| modes     = [[Single-player]]
}}

'''''Day of the Tentacle''''', also known as '''''Maniac Mansion II: Day of the Tentacle''''',&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.lucasarts.com/20th/history_2.htm |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060623025112/http://www.lucasarts.com/20th/history_2.htm |title=20th Anniversary |publisher=[[LucasArts Entertainment Company LLC]] |archivedate=June 23, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.lucasarts.com/games/platform.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101206060115/http://www.lucasarts.com/games/platform.html |archivedate=December 6, 2010 |title=Games by Platform |publisher=[[LucasArts Entertainment Company LLC]] |url-status=dead |df=mdy}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a 1993 [[graphic adventure game]] developed and published by [[LucasArts]]. It is the sequel to the 1987 game ''[[Maniac Mansion]]''. The game's plot follows Bernard Bernoulli and his friends Hoagie and Laverne as they attempt to stop the evil Purple Tentacle—a sentient, disembodied tentacle—from taking over the world. The player takes control of the trio and solves puzzles while using time travel to explore different periods of history.

[[Dave Grossman (game developer)|Dave Grossman]] and [[Tim Schafer]] co-led the game's development, their first time in such a role. The pair carried over a limited number of elements from ''Maniac Mansion'' and forwent the character selection aspect to simplify development. Inspirations included [[Chuck Jones]] cartoons and the [[history of the United States]]. ''Day of the Tentacle'' is the eighth LucasArts title to use the [[SCUMM]] engine.

The game was released simultaneously on [[floppy disk]] and [[CD-ROM]] to critical acclaim and commercial success. Critics focused on its cartoon-style visuals and comedic elements. ''Day of the Tentacle'' has featured regularly in lists of &quot;top&quot; games published more than two decades after its release, and aspects have been referenced in popular culture. A remaster of ''Day of the Tentacle'' was developed by Schafer's current studio, [[Double Fine Productions]], and released on March 22, 2016, for the [[PlayStation 4]], [[PlayStation Vita]], [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]] and [[OS X]].

== Gameplay ==
''Day of the Tentacle'' follows the [[point-and-click]] two-dimensional [[adventure game]] formula, first established by the original ''[[Maniac Mansion]]''. Players direct the controllable characters around the game world by clicking with the [[computer mouse]]. To interact with the game world, players choose from a set of nine commands arrayed on the screen (such as &quot;pick up&quot;, &quot;use&quot;, or &quot;talk to&quot;) and then on an object in the world. This was the last [[SCUMM]] game to use the original interface of having the bottom of the screen being taken up by a verb selection and inventory; starting with the next game to use the [[SCUMM]] engine, ''[[Sam &amp; Max Hit the Road]]'', the engine was modified to scroll through a more concise list of verbs with the right mouse button and having the inventory on a separate screen.&lt;ref name=&quot;GamesTm-Retro-2&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |magazine=[[GamesTM]] |publisher=[[Imagine Publishing]] |title=Hall of Fame: Guybrush Threepwood |year=2010 |issue=3 |pages=188–189 |series=The Ultimate Retro Companion |issn=1448-2606 |oclc=173412381}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |year=2005 |title=Sam &amp; Max Hit the Road |journal=[[GamesTM]] |series=Retro Micro Games Action |volume=1 |pages=128–129 |publisher=Highbury Entertainment |issn=1448-2606 |oclc=173412381}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Day of the Tentacle'' uses [[time travel]] extensively; early in the game, the three main protagonists are separated across time by the effects of a faulty [[Time travel|time machine]]. The player, after completing certain puzzles, can then freely switch between these characters, interacting with the game's world in the separate time periods. Certain small inventory items can be shared by placing the item into the &quot;Chron-o-Johns&quot;, modified [[portable toilet]]s that instantly transport objects to the other time period, while other items are shared by simply leaving the item in a past time period to be picked up by a character in a future period. Changes made to a past time period will affect a future one, and many of the game's puzzles are based on the effect of time travel, aging of certain items, and alterations of the time stream. For example, one puzzle requires the player, while in the future era where Purple Tentacle has succeeded, to send a [[medical chart]] of a Tentacle back to the past, having it used as the design of the [[Flag of the United States|American flag]], then collecting one such flag in the future to be used as a Tentacle disguise to allow that character to roam freely.&lt;ref name=&quot;digitialspy retro&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.digitalspy.com/gaming/levelup/a245962/retro-corner-day-of-the-tentacle-pc.html |title=Retro Corner: 'Day Of The Tentacle' (PC) |first=Mark |last=Langshaw |date=July 22, 2010 |accessdate=July 22, 2010 |website=[[Digital Spy]] |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100724152822/http://www.digitalspy.com/gaming/levelup/a245962/retro-corner-day-of-the-tentacle-pc.html |archivedate=July 24, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The whole original ''Maniac Mansion'' game can be played on a computer resembling a [[Commodore 64]] inside the ''Day of the Tentacle'' game; this practice has since been repeated by other game developers, but at the time of ''Day of the Tentacle's'' release, it was unprecedented.&lt;ref name=&quot;GSGG&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gamespot.com/gamespot/features/all/greatestgames/p-48.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20041124031943/http://www.gamespot.com/gamespot/features/all/greatestgames/p-48.html |archivedate=November 24, 2004 |title=The Greatest Games of All Time: The Only Good Tentacle Is a Green Tentacle |website=[[GameSpot]] |date=April 30, 2004 |accessdate=February 13, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Plot ==
Five years after the events of ''Maniac Mansion'', Purple Tentacle—a mutant monster and lab assistant created by [[mad scientist]] Dr. Fred Edison—drinks toxic sludge from a river behind Dr. Fred's laboratory. The sludge causes him to grow a pair of flipper-like arms, develop vastly increased intelligence, and a thirst for global domination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Day of the Tentacle |developer=LucasArts |date=June 1993 |platform=DOS |quote='''Purple Tentacle:''' It makes me feel great! Smarter! More aggressive! I feel like I could... like I could... like I could... TAKE ON THE WORLD!!!}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dr. Fred plans to resolve the issue by killing Purple Tentacle and his harmless, friendly brother Green Tentacle, but Green Tentacle sends a plea of help to his old friend, the [[nerd]] Bernard Bernoulli. Bernard travels to the Edison family motel with his two housemates, deranged [[medical student]] Laverne and [[roadie]] Hoagie, and frees the tentacles. Purple Tentacle escapes to resume his quest to take over the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Day of the Tentacle |developer=LucasArts |date=June 1993 |platform=DOS |quote='''Bernard:''' Ok, you're free to go.&lt;br /&gt;'''Green Tentacle:''' Thanks Bernard!&lt;br /&gt;'''Purple Tentacle:''' Yes, thank you, naive human! Now I can finish taking over the world! Ha ha ha!&lt;br /&gt;'''Green Tentacle:''' Wait!&lt;br /&gt;'''Bernard:''' Oh, yeah. Now I remember. He's incredibly evil, isn't he?&lt;br /&gt;'''Green Tentacle:''' Uh... I'll try to talk him out of it.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Day of the Tentacle Founding Fathers.jpg|thumb|left|240px|alt=A horizontal rectangular video game screenshot that is a digital representation of domestic room. Four characters stand around a table in the middle of the room. A list of words and icons are below the scene.|The game displays the [[point-and-click]] interface below the scene. Time travel and interaction with cartoon versions of figures from American colonial history, such as [[John Hancock]], [[Thomas Jefferson]] and [[George Washington]], are key to gameplay.]]

Since Purple Tentacle's plans are flawless and unstoppable, Dr. Fred decides to use his Chron-o-John time machines to send Bernard, Laverne, and Hoagie to the day before to turn off his Sludge-o-Matic machine, thereby preventing Purple Tentacle's exposure to the sludge.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Day of the Tentacle |developer=LucasArts |date=June 1993 |platform=DOS |quote='''Dr. Fred:''' Our only hope now is to turn off my Sludge-O-Matic machine and prevent the toxic mutagen from entering the river!&lt;br /&gt;'''Bernard:''' Isn't it a little late for that, Doctor?&lt;br /&gt;'''Dr. Fred:''' Of course! That's why I'll have to do it... YESTERDAY! To the time machine!}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, because Dr. Fred used an [[imitation diamond]] rather than a real diamond as a power source for the time machine, the Chron-o-Johns break down in operation. Laverne is sent 200 years in the future, where humanity has been enslaved and Purple Tentacle rules the world from the Edison mansion, while Hoagie is dropped 200 years in the past, where the motel is being used by the [[Founding Fathers of the United States|Founding Fathers]] as a retreat to write the [[United States Constitution]]. Bernard is returned to the present. To salvage Dr. Fred's plan, Bernard must acquire a replacement diamond for the time machine, while both Hoagie and Laverne must restore power to their respective Chron-o-John pods by plugging them in.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Day of the Tentacle |developer=LucasArts |date=June 1993 |platform=DOS |quote='''Dr. Fred:''' My dials say that the larger specimen landed two hundred years in the past and the other is stuck two hundred years in the future!&lt;br /&gt;'''Bernard:''' Well, hurry up and bring them back! &lt;br /&gt;'''Dr. Fred:''' I will, as soon as I get a new diamond! Then all your buddies have to do is plug in their respective Chron-o-Johns and—&lt;br /&gt;'''Bernard:''' Plug them in?!? Where is Hoagie going to find an electrical outlet two hundred years in the past!?!&lt;br /&gt;'''Dr. Fred:''' Yes... well... He'll be needing my patented superbattery then, won't he?}}&lt;/ref&gt; To overcome the lack of electricity in the past, Hoagie recruits the help of [[Benjamin Franklin]] and Dr. Fred's ancestor, Red Edison, to build a [[Battery (electricity)|superbattery]] to power his pod, while Laverne evades capture by the tentacles long enough to run an [[extension cord]] to her unit. The three send small objects back and forth in time through the Chron-o-Johns and make changes to history to help the others complete their tasks.

Eventually, Bernard uses Dr. Fred's family fortune of [[royalties]] from the ''[[Maniac Mansion (TV series)|Maniac Mansion]]'' TV series to purchase a real diamond, while his friends manage to power their Chron-o-Johns. Soon, the three are reunited in the present. Purple Tentacle arrives, hijacks a Chron-o-John, and takes it to the previous day to prevent them from turning off the sludge machine; he is pursued by Green Tentacle in another pod.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Day of the Tentacle |developer=LucasArts |date=June 1993 |platform=DOS |quote='''Purple Tentacle:''' You can't turn off the machine if I get there first!&lt;br /&gt;'''Laverne:''' Uh-oh!&lt;br /&gt;'''Green Tentacle:''' Don't worry guys! This time I know I can stop him!}}&lt;/ref&gt; With only one Chron-o-John pod left, Bernard, Hoagie, and Laverne use it to pursue the tentacles to the previous day, while Dr. Fred uselessly tries to warn them of using the pod together, referencing the film ''[[The Fly (1958 film)|The Fly]]''. Upon arriving, the trio exit the pod only to discover that they have been turned into a three-headed monster, their bodies merging into one during the transfer. Meanwhile, Purple Tentacle has used the time machine to bring countless versions of himself from different moments in time to the same day to prevent the Sludge-o-Matic from being deactivated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Day of the Tentacle |developer=LucasArts |date=June 1993 |platform=DOS |quote='''Purple Tentacle:''' You see, I've been busy. These are all versions of myself from the future. I've been bringing them back here using the Chron-o-John. Together we will conquer the world!!}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bernard and his friends defeat the Purple Tentacles guarding the Sludge-o-Matic, turn off the machine, and prevent the whole series of events from ever happening. Returning to the present, Dr. Fred discovers that the three have not been turned into a monster at all but have just gotten stuck in the same set of clothes; they are then ordered by Dr. Fred to get out of his house. The game ends with the credits rolling over a tentacle-shaped American flag, one of the more significant results of their tampering in history.

== Development ==
{{Further|Maniac Mansion#Development}}
{{Multiple image
| footer = Tim Schafer and Dave Grossman co-led development of the sequel to ''Maniac Mansion'', their first time directing a game.
| image1 = Tim Schafer.jpg
| alt1 = A close-up picture of a man facing left
| caption1 = &lt;center&gt;[[Tim Schafer]] in 2001&lt;/center&gt;
| width1 = 200
| image2 = Dave Grossman - 920448657 - barret.jpg
| alt2 = A close-up picture of a man facing front.
| caption2 = &lt;center&gt;[[Dave Grossman (game developer)|Dave Grossman]] in 2007&lt;/center&gt;
| width2 = 195
}}

Following a string of successful adventure games, LucasArts assigned [[Dave Grossman (game developer)|Dave Grossman]] and [[Tim Schafer]] to lead development of a new game. The two had previously assisted [[Ron Gilbert]] with the creation of ''[[The Secret of Monkey Island]]'' and ''[[Monkey Island 2: LeChuck's Revenge]]'', and the studio felt that Grossman and Schafer were ready to manage a project. The company believed that the pair's humor matched well with that of ''Maniac Mansion'' and suggested working on a sequel. The two developers agreed and commenced production.&lt;ref name=&quot;GamesTm-Retro&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |magazine=[[GamesTM]] |publisher=[[Imagine Publishing]] |title=Behind the Scenes: Maniac Mansion + Day of the Tentacle |year=2010 |issue=3 |pages=22–27 |series=The Ultimate Retro Companion |issn=1448-2606 |oclc=173412381}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gilbert and [[Gary Winnick (game developer)|Gary Winnick]], the creators of ''Maniac Mansion'', collaborated with Grossman and Schafer on the initial planning and writing.&lt;ref name=&quot;GamesTm-Retro&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RetroGamer&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |magazine=Retro Gamer |publisher=Imagine Publishing |location=[[retrogamer]] |title=The Making of Day of the Tentacle |url=http://www.retrogamer.net/retro_games90/the-making-of-day-of-the-tentacle/ |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150626165120/http://www.retrogamer.net/retro_games90/the-making-of-day-of-the-tentacle/ |archivedate=June 26, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The total budget for the game was about $600,000, according to Schafer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.eurogamer.net/articles/2012-02-10-double-fine-adventure-passes-day-of-the-tentacle-budget |title=Double Fine Adventure passes Day of the Tentacle budget |first=Fred |last=Dutton |date=February 10, 2012 |accessdate=February 10, 2012 |website=[[Eurogamer]] |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130314075902/http://www.eurogamer.net/articles/2012-02-10-double-fine-adventure-passes-day-of-the-tentacle-budget |archivedate=March 14, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Creative design ===
In planning the plot, the four designers considered a number of concepts, eventually choosing an idea of Gilbert's about time travel that they believed was the most interesting. The four discussed what time periods to focus on, settling on the Revolutionary War and the future. The Revolutionary War offered opportunities to craft many puzzles around that period, such as changing the Constitution to affect the future. Grossman noted the appeal of the need to make wide-sweeping changes such as the Constitution just to achieve a small personal goal, believing this captured the essence of adventure games.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgamer design&quot;/&gt; The future period allowed them to explore the nature of cause and effect without any historical bounds.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgamer design&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.usgamer.net/articles/day-of-the-tentacle-the-oral-history |title=Day of the Tentacle: The Oral History |first=Bob |last=Mackey |date=March 7, 2016 |accessdate=March 7, 2016 |work=[[USgamer]] |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160309215914/http://www.usgamer.net/articles/day-of-the-tentacle-the-oral-history |archivedate=March 9, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Grossman and Schafer decided to carry over previous characters that they felt were the most entertaining. The two considered the Edison family &quot;essential&quot; and chose Bernard because of his &quot;unqualified nerdiness&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;GamesTm-Retro&quot;/&gt; Bernard was considered &quot;everyone's favorite character&quot; from ''Maniac Mansion'', and was the clear first choice for the protagonists.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgamer design&quot;/&gt; The game's other protagonists, Laverne and Hoagie, were based on a [[Mexican people|Mexican]] ex-girlfriend of Grossman's and a [[Megadeth]] roadie named Tony that Schafer had met, respectively.&lt;ref name=&quot;Edge&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |title=Master of Unreality: The life and times of Tim Schafer, from metal to LucasArts and Double Fine—and back to metal... |journal=[[Edge (magazine)|Edge]] |pages=82–87 |date=August 2009 |issue='''204''' |publisher=[[Future Publishing]] |location=United Kingdom}}&lt;/ref&gt; Schafer and Grossman planned to use a character selection system similar to the first game, but felt that it would have complicated the design process and increased production costs. Believing that it added little to the gameplay, they removed it early in the process and reduced the number of player characters from six to three.&lt;ref name=&quot;GamesTm-Retro&quot;/&gt; The dropped characters included Razor, a female musician from the previous game; Moonglow, a short character in baggy clothes; and Chester, a black [[Beat Generation|beat]] poet. Ideas for Chester, however, morphed into new twin characters in the Edison family.&lt;ref name=&quot;RetroMaking&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |magazine=Retro Gamer |publisher=Imagine Publishing |location=[[Bournemouth]] |title=The Making of Day of the Tentacle |first=Kim |last=Wild |issue=81 |date=September 2010 |pages=84–87 |url=http://www.nowgamer.com/features/1171/making-of-day-of-the-tentacle?o=2 |accessdate=February 25, 2011 |issn=1742-3155 |oclc=489477015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150603075642/http://www.nowgamer.com/features/1171/making-of-day-of-the-tentacle?o=2 |archivedate=June 3, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The smaller number of characters reduced the strain on the game's engine in terms of [[Scripting language|scripting]] and [[Computer animation|animation]].&lt;ref name=&quot;GamesTm-Retro-2&quot;/&gt;

The staff collaboratively designed the characters. They first discussed the character personalities, which Larry Ahern used to create concept art. Ahern wanted to make sure that the art style was consistent and the character designs were established early, in contrast to what had happened with ''Monkey Island 2'', in which various artists came in later to help fill in necessary art assets as necessary, creating a disjointed style.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgamer art&quot;/&gt; [[Looney Tunes]] animation shorts, particularly the [[Chuck Jones]]-directed ''[[Rabbit of Seville]]'', ''[[What's Opera, Doc?]]'' and ''[[Duck Dodgers in the 24½th Century]]'' inspired the artistic design. The cartoonish style also lent itself to providing larger visible faces to enable more expressive characters.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgamer art&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.usgamer.net/articles/behind-the-art-of-day-of-the-tentacle |title=Behind the Art of Day of the Tentacle |first=Bob |last=Mackey |date=March 7, 2016 |accessdate=March 7, 2016 |work=[[USgamer]] |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160309214035/http://www.usgamer.net/articles/behind-the-art-of-day-of-the-tentacle |archivedate=March 9, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Peter Chan (artist)|Peter Chan]] designed backgrounds, spending around two days to progress from concept sketch to final art for each background.&lt;ref name=&quot;RetroMaking&quot;/&gt; Chan too used [[Looney Tunes]] as influence for the backgrounds, trying to emulate the style of Jones and [[Maurice Noble]]. Ahern and Chan went back and forth with character and background art to make sure both styles worked together without too much distraction. They further had Jones visit their studio during development to provide input into their developing art.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgamer art&quot;/&gt; The choice of art style inspired further ideas from the designers. Grossman cited cartoons featuring [[Pepé Le Pew]], and commented that the gag involving a painted white stripe on [[Penelope Pussycat]] inspired a puzzle in the game.  The artists spent a year creating the in-game animations.&lt;ref name=&quot;RetroMaking&quot;/&gt;

The script was written in the evening, when fewer people were in the office.&lt;ref name=&quot;GamesTm-Retro&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RetroMaking&quot;/&gt; Grossman considered it the easiest aspect of production, but encountered difficulties when writing with others around.&lt;ref name=&quot;GamesTm-Retro&quot;/&gt;

{{quote box
| quoted = true
| width = 35%
| salign = center
| quote = With a time travel story, I leave a bottle of wine somewhere, and it causes a bottle of vinegar to appear in the same place four hundred years later. Same basic idea: I do X over here, and it causes Y over there. Whether ‘over there’ means in the next room or 400 years in the future is irrelevant. I will say that it was really fun to think about the effects of large amounts of time on things like wine bottles and sweaters in dryers, and to imagine how altering fundamentals of history like the Constitution and the flag could be used to accomplish petty, selfish goals like the acquisition of a vacuum and a tentacle costume. We definitely enjoyed ourselves designing that game.
| source = Dave Grossman on designing the game's puzzles&lt;ref name=&quot;RetroMaking&quot;/&gt;
}}

Grossman and Schafer brainstormed regularly to devise the time travel puzzles, and collaborated with members of the development team as well as other LucasArts employees. They would identify puzzle problems and work towards a solution similar to how the game plays. Most issues were addressed prior to programming, but some details were left unfinished to work on later.&lt;ref name=&quot;GamesTm-Retro&quot;/&gt; The staff conceived puzzles involving the [[History of the United States (1776–1789)|U.S.'s early history]] based on their memory of their compulsory education, and using the more legendary aspects of history, such as George Washington cutting down a cherry tree to appeal to international audiences.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgamer design&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RetroMaking&quot;/&gt; To complete the elements, Grossman researched the period to maintain historical accuracy, visiting libraries and contacting reference librarians. The studio, however, took [[Artistic license|creative license]] towards facts to fit them into the game's design.&lt;ref name=&quot;GamesTm-Retro&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RetroMaking&quot;/&gt;

''Day of the Tentacle'' features a four-minute long animated opening credit sequence, the first LucasArts game to have such. Ahern noted that their previous games would run the credits over primarily still shots which would only last for a few minutes, but with ''Tentacle'', the team had grown so large that they worried this approach would be boring to players.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgamer art&quot;/&gt; They assigned [[Kyle Balda]], an intern at CalArts, to create the animated sequence, with Chan helping to create minimalist backgrounds to aid in the animation.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgamer art&quot;/&gt; Originally this sequence was around seven minutes long, and included the three characters arriving at the mansion and releasing Purple Tentacle. Another LucasArts designer, Hal Barwood, suggested they cut it in half, leading to the shortened version as in the released game, and having the player take over when they arrive at the mansion.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgamer art&quot;/&gt;

=== Technology and audio ===
''Day of the Tentacle'' uses the [[SCUMM]] engine developed for ''Maniac Mansion''.&lt;ref name=&quot;GamesTm-Retro&quot;/&gt; LucasArts had gradually modified the engine since its creation. For example, the number of input verbs was reduced and items in the character's inventory are represented by icons rather than text.&lt;ref name=&quot;GamesTm-Retro-2&quot;/&gt; While implementing an animation, the designers encountered a problem later discovered to be a limitation of the engine. Upon learning of the limitation, Gilbert reminisced about the file size of the first game. The staff then resolved to include it in the sequel.&lt;ref name=&quot;GamesTm-Retro&quot;/&gt;

The title was the first LucasArts adventure game to incorporate voice work on release.{{efn|''[[Indiana Jones and the Fate of Atlantis]]'' predates ''Day of the Tentacle'' by a month, but did not have voice work until an enhanced version released a year later in 1993.}} The game was not originally planned to include voice work, as at the time, the install base for CD-ROM was too low.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgamer design&quot;/&gt; As they neared the end of 1992, CD-ROM sales grew significantly. The general manager of LucasArts, Kelly Flock, recognizing that the game would not be done in time by the end of the year to make the holiday release, suggested that the team include voice work for the game, giving them more time to complete the title.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgamer design&quot;/&gt;

Voice director Tamlynn Barra managed that aspect of the game.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgamer design&quot;/&gt;   Schafer and Grossman described how they imagined the characters' voices and Barra sought audition tapes of voice actors to meet the criteria. She presented the best auditions to the pair. Schafer's sister Ginny was among the auditions, and she was chosen for Nurse Edna. Schafer opted out of the decision for her selection to avoid [[nepotism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;GamesTm-Retro&quot;/&gt; Grossman and Schafer encountered difficulty selecting a voice for Bernard.&lt;ref name=&quot;GamesTm-Retro&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RetroMaking&quot;/&gt; To aid the process, Grossman commented that the character should sound like [[Les Nessman]] from the television show ''[[WKRP in Cincinnati]]''. Barra responded that she knew the agent of the character's actor, [[Richard Sanders (actor)|Richard Sanders]], and brought Sanders on the project.&lt;ref name=&quot;GamesTm-Retro&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Magic&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Magic of Interactive Entertainment |publisher=Sams |first1=Mike |last1=Morrison |first2=Sandie |last2=Morrison |chapter=Interactive Entertainment Today |page=19 |isbn=978-0-672-30590-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Denny Delk]] and [[Nick Jameson]] were among those hired, and provided voice work for around five characters each.&lt;ref name=&quot;GamesTm-Retro&quot;/&gt; Recording for the 4,500&amp;nbsp;lines of dialog occurred at Studio 222 in Hollywood. Barra directed the voice actors separately from a sound production booth. She provided context for each line and described aspects of the game to aid the actors.&lt;ref name=&quot;CGW-108&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |magazine=[[Computer Gaming World]] |publisher=Russell Sipe |issue=108 |date=July 1993 |title=Lights, Camera, Interaction |page=44}}&lt;/ref&gt; The voice work in Day of the Tentacle was widely praised for its quality and professionalism in comparison to Sierra's talkie games of the period which suffered from poor audio quality and limited voice acting (some of which consisted of Sierra employees rather than professional talent).

The game's music was composed by [[Peter McConnell]], [[Michael Land]] and [[Clint Bajakian]].&lt;ref name=&quot;usgamer music&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.usgamer.net/articles/day-of-the-tentacle-composer-peter-mcconnell-on-communicating-cartooniness |title=Day of the Tentacle Composer Peter McConnell on Communicating Cartooniness |work=[[USgamer]] |first=Bob |last=Mackey |date=March 7, 2016 |accessdate=March 7, 2016 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160308193716/http://www.usgamer.net/articles/day-of-the-tentacle-composer-peter-mcconnell-on-communicating-cartooniness |archivedate=March 8, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The three had worked together to share the duties equally of composing the music for ''Monkey Island 2'' and ''Fate of Atlantis'', and continued this approach for ''Day of the Tentacle''.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgamer music&quot;/&gt; According to McConnell, he had composed most of the music taking place in the game's present, Land for the future, and Bajakian for the past, outside of Dr. Fred's theme for the past which McConnell had done.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgamer music&quot;/&gt; The music was composed around the cartoonist nature of the game play, further drawing on Looney Tunes' use of parodying classical works of music, and playing on set themes for all of the major characters in the game.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgamer music&quot;/&gt; Many of these themes had to be composed to take into account different processing speeds of computers at the time, managed by the [[iMUSE]] music interface; such themes would include shorter repeating patterns that would play while the game's screen scrolled across, and then once the screen was at the proper place, the music would continue on to a more dramatic phrase.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgamer music&quot;/&gt;

''Day of the Tentacle'' was one of the first games concurrently released on CD-ROM and floppy disk.&lt;ref name=&quot;CGW-108&quot;/&gt; A floppy disk version was created to accommodate consumers that had yet to purchase CD-ROM drives. The CD-ROM format afforded the addition of audible dialog. The capacity difference between the two formats necessitated alterations to the floppy disk version. Grossman spent several weeks reducing files sizes and removing files such as the audio dialog to fit the game onto six diskettes.&lt;ref name=&quot;RetroMaking&quot;/&gt;

== Reception ==
{{Video game reviews
| GR = 95%&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.gamerankings.com/pc/564903-maniac-mansion-day-of-the-tentacle/index.html |title=Maniac Mansion: Day of the Tentacle for PC |website=[[GameRankings]] |publisher=[[CBS Interactive]] |accessdate=August 17, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| MC = 93/100&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.metacritic.com/game/pc/maniac-mansion-day-of-the-tentacle |title=Maniac Mansion: Day of the Tentacle for PC Reviews |website=[[Metacritic]] |publisher=[[CBS Interactive]] |accessdate=August 17, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| award1Pub = ''[[PC Gamer US]]''
| award1 = #46, The Best Games of All Time{{r|pcgamerustop40}}
| award2Pub = ''[[Computer Gaming World]]''
| award2 = Adventure Game of the Year, June 1994{{r|cgw199406}}&lt;br&gt;#34, 150 Best Games of All Time{{r|cgw199611best}}
| award3Pub = [[Adventure Gamers]]
| award3 = #1, Top 20 Adventure Games of All Time{{r|dickens20040402}}
| award4Pub = [[IGN]]
| award4 = #60, Top 100 Games (2005){{r|IGNtop05}}&lt;br&gt;#84, Top 100 Games (2007){{r|IGNtop07}}&lt;br&gt;#82, Top 100 Videogame Villains (Purple Tentacle{{r|IGNtopvillains}}
| award7Pub = ''[[PC Gamer UK]]''
| award7 = #30, The Top 100{{r|pcgameruktop100}}
}}

''Day of the Tentacle'' was a moderate commercial success; according to ''[[Edge (magazine)|Edge]]'', it sold roughly 80,000 copies by 2009. Tim Schafer saw this as an improvement over his earlier projects, the ''Monkey Island'' games, which had been commercial flops.&lt;ref name=edgesales&gt;{{cite journal |title=Master of Unreality |journal=[[Edge (magazine)|Edge]] |author=Staff | pages=82–87 |date=August 2009 |issue=204 |publisher=[[Future Publishing]] |location=United Kingdom}}&lt;/ref&gt; The game was critically acclaimed. [[Charles Ardai]] of ''[[Computer Gaming World]]'' wrote in September 1993, &quot;Calling ''Day of the Tentacle'' a sequel to ''Maniac Mansion''&amp;nbsp;... is a little like calling the space shuttle a sequel to the slingshot&quot;. He enjoyed the game's humor and interface, and praised the designers for removing &quot;dead end&quot; scenarios and [[player character]] death. Ardai lauded the voice acting, writing that it &quot;would have done the late [[Mel Blanc]] proud&quot;, and compared the game's humor, animation, and camera angles to &quot;[[Looney Tunes|Looney Toons]] {{sic}} gems from the 40s and 50s&quot;. He concluded, &quot;I expect that this game will keep entertaining people for quite some time to come&quot;.&lt;ref name=cgwreview&gt;{{cite journal |last=Ardai |first=Charles |date=September 1993 |url=http://www.cgwmuseum.org/galleries/index.php?year=1993&amp;pub=2&amp;id=110 |title=There's A Sucker Born Every Minute |work=[[Computer Gaming World]] |issue=110 |pages=46–47, 80 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140716220247/http://www.cgwmuseum.org/galleries/index.php?year=1993&amp;pub=2&amp;id=110 |archivedate=July 16, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April 1994 the magazine said of the CD version that Sanders's Bernard was among &quot;many other inspired performances&quot;, concluding that &quot;[[Chuck Jones]] would be proud&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;cgw199404&quot;&gt;{{Cite magazine |last= |first= |date=April 1994 |title=Invasion Of The Data Stashers |department= |url=http://www.cgwmuseum.org/galleries/index.php?year=1994&amp;pub=2&amp;id=117 |magazine=Computer Gaming World |pages=20–42}}&lt;/ref&gt; In May 1994 the magazine said of one multimedia kit [[bundled software|bundling]] the CD version that &quot;it packs more value into the kit than the entire software packages of some of its competitors&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;weksler199406&quot;&gt;{{Cite magazine |last=Weksler |first=Mike |author= |last2= |first2= |date=June 1994 |title=CDs On A ROMpage |department= |url=http://www.cgwmuseum.org/galleries/index.php?year=1994&amp;pub=2&amp;id=118 |magazine=Computer Gaming World |pages=36–40 |type=}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sandy Petersen]] of ''[[Dragon (magazine)|Dragon]]'' stated that its graphics &quot;are in a stupendous cartoony style&quot;, while praising its humor and describing its sound and music as &quot;excellent&quot;. Although the reviewer considered it &quot;one of the best&quot; graphic adventure games, he noted that, like LucasArts' earlier ''[[Loom (video game)|Loom]]'', it was extremely short; he wrote that he &quot;felt cheated somehow when I finished the game&quot;. He ended the review, &quot;Go, Lucasfilm! Do this again, but do make the next game longer!&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dragon199&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |title=Eye of the Monitor |authorlink=Sandy Petersen |last=Petersen |first=Sandy |journal=Dragon |issue=199 |date=November 1993 |pages=56–64}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Phil LaRose of ''[[The Advocate (Louisiana)|The Advocate]]'' called it &quot;light-years ahead of the original&quot;, and believed that its &quot;improved controls, sound and graphics are an evolutionary leap to a more enjoyable gaming experience&quot;. He praised the interface, and summarized the game as &quot;another of the excellent LucasArts programs that place a higher premium on the quality of entertainment and less on the technical knowledge needed to make it run&quot;.&lt;ref name=advocate&gt;{{cite news |last=LaRose |first=Phil |date=December 31, 1993 |title=''Maniac'' Sequel Fights Influence of Long Arm of Purple Tentacle |newspaper=[[The Advocate (Louisiana)|The Advocate]] |at=FUN; Pg. 32}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[Boston Herald]]''{{'}}s Geoff Smith noted that &quot;the animation of the cartoonlike characters is of TV quality&quot;, and praised the removal of dead ends and character death. He ended, &quot;It's full of lunacy, but for anyone who likes light-hearted adventure games, it's well worth trying&quot;.&lt;ref name=bostonherald&gt;{{cite news |last=Smith |first=Geoff |date=November 28, 1993 |title=COMPUTER GAMES; 'Tentacle' Grabs Your Attention |newspaper=[[Boston Herald]] |at=LIFESTYLE; Pg. 057}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Theodore Beale|Vox Day]] of ''[[The Blade (Toledo)|The Blade]]'' called its visuals &quot;well done&quot; and compared them to those of ''[[The Ren &amp; Stimpy Show]]''. The writer praised the game's humor, and stated that &quot;both the music and sound effects are hilarious&quot;; he cited the voice performance of Richard Sanders as a high point. He summarized the game as &quot;both a good adventure and a funny cartoon&quot;.&lt;ref name=toledoblade&gt;{{cite news |url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1350&amp;dat=19940929&amp;id=gUExAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=WwMEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2376,8197006 |author=Vox Day |date=September 29, 1994 |title=''Day of the Tentacle'' |newspaper=[[The Blade (Toledo)|The Blade]] |at=Pg. 16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lim Choon Wee of the ''[[New Straits Times]]'' highly praised the game's humor, which he called &quot;brilliantly funny&quot;. The writer commented that the game's puzzles relied on &quot;trial and error&quot; with &quot;no underlying logic&quot;, but stated that the game &quot;remains fun&quot; despite this issue, and concluded that ''Day of the Tentacle'' was &quot;definitely the comedy game of the year&quot;.&lt;ref name=newstraits&gt;{{cite news |last=Wee |first=Lim Choon |title=The Fun Continues in ''Maniac Mansion 2'' |date=July 29, 1993 |newspaper=[[The New Straits Times]] |url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1309&amp;dat=19930729&amp;id=NGs0AAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=2hMEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5752,3778852 |at=LEISURE; Pg. 18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Daniel Baum of ''[[The Jerusalem Post]]'' called it &quot;one of the funniest, most entertaining and best-programmed computer games I have ever seen&quot;, and lauded its animation. He wrote that the game provided &quot;a more polished impression&quot; than either ''[[The Secret of Monkey Island]]'' or ''[[Monkey Island 2: LeChuck's Revenge]]''. The writer stated that its high [[system requirements]] were its only drawback, and believed that a [[Sound Blaster]] card was required to fully appreciate the game.&lt;ref name=jerusalem&gt;{{cite news |last=Baum |first=Daniel |date=March 20, 1994 |title=Stop the Tentacle From Taking Over the World |newspaper=[[The Jerusalem Post]] |at=SCIENCE; Pg. 05}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a retrospective review, [[Adventure Gamers]]' Chris Remo wrote, &quot;If someone were to ask for a few examples of games that exemplify the best of the graphic adventure genre, ''Day of the Tentacle'' would certainly be near the top&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;AGR&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adventuregamers.com/article/id,497 |title=Day of the Tentacle review |author=Remo, Chris |publisher=[[Adventure Gamers]] |date=March 11, 2005 |accessdate=July 31, 2007 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070703155049/http://www.adventuregamers.com/article/id%2C497/ |archivedate=July 3, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Day of the Tentacle'' has been featured regularly in lists of &quot;top&quot; games. In 1994, ''[[PC Gamer US]]'' named ''Day of the Tentacle'' the 46th best computer game ever.&lt;ref name=pcgamerustop40&gt;{{cite journal |author=Staff |journal=[[PC Gamer US]] |title=''PC Gamer'' Top 40: The Best Games of All Time; The Ten Best Games that Almost Made the Top 40 |date=August 1994 |issue=3 |pages=42}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 1994 it and ''[[Gabriel Knight: Sins of the Fathers]]'' won ''Computer Gaming World''{{'}}s Adventure Game of the Year award. The editors stated that &quot;''Day of the Tentacle''{{'}}s fluid animation sequences underscore a strong script and solid game play ... story won out over technological innovation in this genre&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;cgw199406&quot;&gt;{{Cite magazine |last= |first= |author= |last2= |first2= |date=June 1994 |title=Announcing The New Premier Awards |department= |url=http://www.cgwmuseum.org/galleries/index.php?year=1994&amp;pub=2&amp;id=118 |magazine=Computer Gaming World |pages=51–58 |type=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1996, the magazine ranked it as the 34th best game of all time, writing: &quot;''DOTT'' completely blew away its ancestor, ''Maniac Mansion'', with its smooth animated sequences, nifty plot and great voiceovers.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;cgw199611best&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cgwmuseum.org/galleries/index.php?year=1996&amp;pub=2&amp;id=148 |title=150 Best Games of All Time |work=Computer Gaming World |date=November 1996 |accessdate=March 25, 2016 |pages=64–80 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160408023915/http://cgwmuseum.org/galleries/index.php?year=1996&amp;pub=2&amp;id=148 |archivedate=April 8, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Adventure Gamers]] included the game as the top entry on its 20 Greatest Adventure Games of All Time List in 2004,&lt;ref name=dickens20040402&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adventuregamers.com/article/id,186 |title=Top 20 Adventure Games of All-Time |author=Dickens, Evan |publisher=[[Adventure Gamers]] |date=April 2, 2004 |accessdate=July 31, 2007 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070824085814/http://www.adventuregamers.com/article/id%2C186/ |archivedate=August 24, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; and placed it sixth on its Top 100 All-Time Adventure Games in 2011.&lt;ref name=top100&gt;{{cite web | author=AG Staff | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120604021011/http://www.adventuregamers.com/articles/view/18643 | url=http://www.adventuregamers.com:80/articles/view/18643 | title=Top 100 All-Time Adventure Games | date=December 30, 2011 | archivedate=June 4, 2012 | work=[[Adventure Gamers]] | url-status=live | access-date=July 19, 2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The game has appeared on several [[IGN]] lists. The website rated it number 60 and 84 on its top 100 games list in 2005 and 2007, respectively.&lt;ref name=IGNtop05&gt;{{cite web |url=http://top100.ign.com/2005/051-060.html |title=IGN's Top 100 Games |website=[[IGN]] |accessdate=July 31, 2007 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080930003331/http://top100.ign.com/2005/051-060.html |archivedate=September 30, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;IGNtop07&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://top100.ign.com/2007/ign_top_game_84.html |title=IGN Top 100 Games 2007: 84 |website=IGN |year=2007 |accessdate=March 11, 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110713004742/http://top100.ign.com/2007/ign_top_game_84.html |archivedate=July 13, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; IGN named ''Day of the Tentacle'' as part of their top 10 LucasArts adventure games in 2009,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://pc.ign.com/articles/104/1046144p1.html |title=Top 10 LucasArts Adventure Games |website=IGN |date=November 17, 2009 |accessdate=February 23, 2011 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120130165356/http://pc.ign.com/articles/104/1046144p1.html |archivedate=January 30, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ranked the Purple Tentacle 82nd in a list of top 100 videogame villains in 2010.&lt;ref name=IGNtopvillains&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ign.com/videogame-villains/82.html |title=Top 100 Videogame Villains – Purple Tentacle is number 82 |website=IGN.com |accessdate=February 25, 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110301093554/http://www.ign.com/videogame-villains/82.html |archivedate=March 1, 2011 |df=mdy}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[ComputerAndVideoGames.com]] ranked it at number 30 in 2008,&lt;ref name=pcgameruktop100&gt;{{cite magazine |url=http://www.computerandvideogames.com/article.php?id=194504 |title=PC Gamer's Top 100 |magazine=[[Computer and Video Games]] |accessdate=July 18, 2009 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081218163022/http://www.computerandvideogames.com/article.php?id=194504 |archivedate=December 18, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and GameSpot also listed ''Day of the Tentacle'' as one of the greatest games of all time.&lt;ref name=&quot;GSGG&quot;/&gt;

== Legacy ==
Fans of ''Day of the Tentacle'' created a [[webcomic]], ''The Day After the Day of the Tentacle'', using the game's graphics.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGNtop07&quot;/&gt; The 1993 LucasArts title ''[[Zombies Ate My Neighbors]]'' features a stage dedicated to ''Day of the Tentacle''. The artists for ''Day of the Tentacle'' shared office space with the ''Zombies Ate My Neighbors'' development team. The team included the homage after frequently seeing artwork for ''Day of the Tentacle'' during the two games' productions.&lt;ref name=&quot;GamesTm-Retro-3&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |magazine=[[GamesTM]] |publisher=[[Imagine Publishing]] |title=Behind the Scenes: Zombies Ate My Neighbors |year=2010 |issue=3 |page=46 |series=The Ultimate Retro Companion |issn=1448-2606 |oclc=173412381}}&lt;/ref&gt; In describing what he considered &quot;the most rewarding moment&quot; of his career, Grossman stated that the game's writing and use of spoken and subtitled dialog assisted a learning-disabled child in learning how to read.&lt;ref name=&quot;GamesTm-Retro&quot;/&gt; [[Telltale Games]] CEO Dan Connors commented in 2009 that an [[Episodic video game|episodic game]] based on ''Day of the Tentacle'' would be &quot;feasible&quot;. However, he cautioned that such an endeavor would hinge on the sales of the ''Monkey Island'' titles released that year.{{efn|Telltale Games co-developed the 2009 game ''[[Tales of Monkey Island]]'' with LucasArts}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.videogamer.com/news/telltale_wants_to_make_episodic_day_of_the_tentacle.html |title=Telltale wants to make episodic Day of the Tentacle |publisher=VideoGamer.com |first=Wesley |last=Yin-Poole |date=June 19, 2009 |accessdate=June 19, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2018, a fan-made sequel entitled ''Return of the Tentacle'' was released for free by a team from Germany.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.pcgamer.com/part-one-of-fan-made-day-of-the-tentacle-sequel-available-to-download/|title=Part one of fan-made Day of the Tentacle sequel available to download|last=Horti|first=Samuel|date=2018-07-22|website=PC Gamer|language=en-US|access-date=2019-10-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.gamestar.de/artikel/return-of-the-tentacle-fan-fortsetzung-des-lucasarts-klassikers-erschienen,3332646.html|title=Return of the Tentacle - Kostenlose Fan-Fortsetzung des Klassikers|last=Dietrich|first=Martin|date=July 23, 2018|website=[[GameStar]]|language=de|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2019-10-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; The game imitates the art-style of the ''Remastered'' edition and features full voice-acting.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.pcgamesn.com/day-of-the-tentacle-remastered/day-of-the-tentacle-2-return-of-the-tentacle|title=Fan-made Day of the Tentacle sequel released for free|last=Watts|first=Rachel|date=|website=PCGamesN|language=en-GB|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2019-10-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://kotaku.com/fans-create-day-of-the-tentacle-sequel-and-its-pretty-1827817840|title=Fans Create Day Of The Tentacle Sequel, And It's Pretty Much Perfect|last=Plunkett|first=Luke|date=July 23, 2018|website=Kotaku|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2019-10-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Remasters ==

=== ''Special Edition'' ===
According to [[Kotaku]], a remastered version of ''Day of the Tentacle'' was in the works at LucasArts Singapore before the sale of LucasArts to Disney in 2012. Though never officially approved, the game used a pseudo-3D art style and was nearly 80% complete, according to one person close to the project, but was shelved in the days before the closure of LucasArts.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://kotaku.com/how-lucasarts-fell-apart-1401731043 |title=How LucasArts Fell Apart |publisher=[[Kotaku]] |date=September 27, 2013 |accessdate=September 27, 2013 |first=Jason |last=Schreier |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130929195214/http://kotaku.com/how-lucasarts-fell-apart-1401731043 |archivedate=September 29, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== ''Remastered'' ===
[[File:Day of the tentacle hd screenshot.png|thumb|right|The remastered version of ''Day of the Tentacle'' retains the cartoon-style animation but uses more detailed characters and backgrounds.]]
At [[PlayStation Experience]] 2014, Schafer announced that a remastered version of ''Day of the Tentacle'', simply titled ''Day of the Tentacle Remastered'', was being developed by his studio, [[Double Fine Productions]]. The remaster was released on March 22, 2016, for [[PlayStation 4]], [[PlayStation Vita]], Microsoft Windows and [[OS X]],&lt;ref name=&quot;eugamer hd screens&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.destructoid.com/day-of-the-tentacle-remastered-is-coming-to-ps4-march-2016-324574.phtml |title=Day of the Tentacle Remastered is coming to PS4 March 2016 |first=Zach |last=Furniss |date=December 5, 2015 |accessdate=December 5, 2015 |work=[[Destructoid]] |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151206084604/http://www.destructoid.com/day-of-the-tentacle-remastered-is-coming-to-ps4-march-2016-324574.phtml |archivedate=December 6, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://kotaku.com/day-of-the-tentacle-remastered-hits-pc-on-march-22-1763479013 |title=Day of the Tentacle Remastered Arrives on March 22 |first=Andres |last=Neltz |date=March 8, 2016 |accessdate=March 8, 2016 |work=[[Kotaku]] |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160308223828/http://kotaku.com/day-of-the-tentacle-remastered-hits-pc-on-march-22-1763479013 |archivedate=March 8, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; with a [[Linux]] version released at July 11&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://support.doublefine.com/forums/300498-day-of-the-tentacle-remastered/suggestions/13074864-linux-version |title=Linux version? |access-date=July 16, 2016 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160822022503/http://support.doublefine.com/forums/300498-day-of-the-tentacle-remastered/suggestions/13074864-linux-version |archivedate=August 22, 2016 |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; together with a mobile port for iOS.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.doublefine.com/news/comments/day_of_the_tentacle_remastered_is_out_now_on_ios/ |title=Double Fine™  – Action News |website=www.doublefine.com |access-date=July 14, 2016 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160717112534/http://www.doublefine.com/news/comments/day_of_the_tentacle_remastered_is_out_now_on_ios/ |archivedate=July 17, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Schafer credited both LucasArts and Disney for help in creating the remaster, which follows from a similar remastering of ''[[Grim Fandango]]'', as well by Double Fine, in January 2015. Schafer said when they originally were about to secure the rights to ''Grim Fandango'' from LucasArts to make the remaster, they did not originally have plans to redo the other LucasArts adventure games, but with the passionate response they got on the news of the ''Grim Fandango'' remaster, they decided to continue these efforts. Schafer described getting the rights to ''Day of the Tentacle'' a &quot;miracle&quot; though aided by the fact that many of the executives in the legal rights chain had fond memories of playing these games and helped to secure the rights.&lt;ref name=&quot;polygon dott remastered&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.polygon.com/2014/12/8/7354949/tim-schafer-day-of-the-tentacle-remastered-ps4-vita-pc |title=Tim Schafer's plans for Day of the Tentacle Remastered, revisiting more LucasArts classics |first=Michael |last=McWhertor |date=December 8, 2014 |accessdate=December 8, 2014 |website=[[Polygon (website)|Polygon]] |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141209082940/http://www.polygon.com/2014/12/8/7354949/tim-schafer-day-of-the-tentacle-remastered-ps4-vita-pc |archivedate=December 9, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Schafer has expressed interest in continuing to restore these older titles, listing ''[[Full Throttle (1995 video game)|Full Throttle]]'' as his next goal, which is also confirmed to release in the future.&lt;ref name=&quot;polygon dott remastered&quot; /&gt; [[2 Player Productions]], which has worked before with Double Fine to document their game development process, also created a mini-documentary for ''Day of the Tentacle Remastered'', which included a visit to the [[Skywalker Ranch]], where LucasArts games were originally developed, where much of the original concept art and digital files for the game and other LucasArts adventure games were archived.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://kotaku.com/the-skywalker-ranch-has-a-treasure-trove-of-old-lucasar-1766427870 |title=The Skywalker Ranch Has A Treasure Trove Of Old LucasArts Games |first=Jason |last=Schreier |date=March 22, 2016 |accessdate=March 23, 2016 |work=[[Kotaku]] |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160322200643/http://kotaku.com/the-skywalker-ranch-has-a-treasure-trove-of-old-lucasar-1766427870 |archivedate=March 22, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Day of the Tentacle Remastered'' retains its two-dimensional cartoon-style art, redrawn at higher resolution for modern computers.&lt;ref name=&quot;polygon dott remastered&quot; /&gt; The high resolution character art was updated by a team led by Yujin Keim with consultation of Ahern and Chan. Keim's team used many of the original sketches of characters and assets from the two and emulated their style with improvements for modern graphics systems.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgamer art&quot;/&gt; Matt Hansen worked on recreating the background assets in high resolution.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgamer design&quot;/&gt; As with the ''Grim Fandango'' remaster, the player can switch back and forth between the original graphics and the high-resolution version.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgamer design&quot;/&gt; The game includes a more streamlined interaction menu, a command wheel akin to the approach used in ''[[Broken Age]]'', but the player can opt to switch back to the original interface.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgamer design&quot;/&gt; The game's soundtrack has been redone within [[MIDI]] adapted to work with the iMUSE system.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgamer design&quot;/&gt; There is an option to listen to commentary from the original creators, including Schafer, Grossman, Chan, McConnell, Ahern, and Bajakian. The remaster contains the fully playable version of the original ''Maniac Mansion'', though no enhancements have been made to that game-within-a-game.&lt;ref name=&quot;eugamer hd screens&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.eurogamer.net/articles/2015-10-23-day-of-the-tentacle-remastered-debuts-screenshots |title=Day of the Tentacle Remastered debuts in-game screenshots |first=Jeffrey |last=Matulef |date=October 23, 2015 |accessdate=October 24, 2015 |work=[[Eurogamer]] |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20151025125651/http://www.eurogamer.net/articles/2015-10-23-day-of-the-tentacle-remastered-debuts-screenshots |archivedate=October 25, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Day of the Tentacle: Remastered'' has received positive reviews, with the PC version having an aggregate review score of 87/100 tallied by ''[[Metacritic]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.metacritic.com/game/pc/day-of-the-tentacle-remastered |title=Day of the Tentacle: Remastered (pc) |accessdate=March 23, 2016 |work=[[Metacritic]] |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160323044726/http://www.metacritic.com/game/pc/day-of-the-tentacle-remastered |archivedate=March 23, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reviewers generally praised the title as having not lost its charm since its initial release, but found some aspects of the remastering to be lackluster. Richard Corbett for ''[[Eurogamer]]'' found the game &quot;every bit as well crafted now as it was in 1993&quot;, but found the processes used to provide high-definition graphics from the original 16-bit graphics to making some of the required shortcuts taken in 1993 for graphics, such as background dithering and low animation framerates, more obvious on modern hardware.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.eurogamer.net/articles/2016-03-21-day-of-the-tentacle-remastered-review |title=Day of the Tentacle Remastered review |work=[[Eurogamer]] |date=March 21, 2016 |accessdate=March 23, 2016 |first=Richard |last=Corbett |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160323081149/http://www.eurogamer.net/articles/2016-03-21-day-of-the-tentacle-remastered-review |archivedate=March 23, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[IGN]]''{{'}}s Jared Petty also found the remastered to still be enjoyable, and found the improvement on the graphics to be &quot;glorious&quot;, but worried that the lack of a hint system, as was added in ''[[The Secret of Monkey Island]]'' remastered version, would put off new players to the game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ign.com/articles/2016/03/21/day-of-the-tentacle-remastered-review |title=Day of the Tentacle Remastered Review |first=Jared |last=Petty |work=[[IGN]] |date=March 21, 2016 |accessdate=March 23, 2016 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160322203941/http://www.ign.com/articles/2016/03/21/day-of-the-tentacle-remastered-review |archivedate=March 22, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bob Mackey for ''[[USgamer]]'' found that while past remastered adventure games have highlighted how much has changed in gamers' expectations since the heyday of adventure games in the 1990s, ''Day of the Tentacle Remastered'' &quot;rises above these issues to become absolutely timeless&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.usgamer.net/articles/day-of-the-tentacle-remastered-pc-review-time-after-time |title=Day of the Tentacle Remastered PC Review: Time After Time |first=Bob |last=Mackey |date=March 22, 2016 |accessdate=March 23, 2016 |work=[[USgamer]] |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160325075309/http://www.usgamer.net/articles/day-of-the-tentacle-remastered-pc-review-time-after-time |archivedate=March 25, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Notes ==
{{Notelist}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
{{Wikiquote}}
* {{MobyGames|/maniac-mansion-day-of-the-tentacle}}

{{portal bar|1990s|Speculative fiction|Video games}}
{{LucasArts adventure games}}
{{Tim Schafer}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:1993 video games]]
[[Category:Cultural depictions of Benjamin Franklin]]
[[Category:Cultural depictions of George Washington]]
[[Category:Cultural depictions of John Hancock]]
[[Category:Cultural depictions of Thomas Jefferson]]
[[Category:DOS games]]
[[Category:LucasArts games]]
[[Category:Mac OS games]]
[[Category:Point-and-click adventure games]]
[[Category:Science fiction video games]]
[[Category:SCUMM games]]
[[Category:ScummVM supported games]]
[[Category:Video game sequels]]
[[Category:Video games about extraterrestrial life]]
[[Category:Video games about time travel]]
[[Category:Video games developed in the United States]]
[[Category:Video games featuring female protagonists]]
[[Category:Video games scored by Peter McConnell]]
[[Category:Video games set in the United States]]
[[Category:Video games with commentaries]]</text>
      <sha1>j7qnrkwn30r5pw4mnbrgdsjzfilsdfr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
