  <page>
    <title>Geography of the Democratic Republic of the Congo</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8023</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938522756</id>
      <parentid>936084636</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-31T18:49:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>WhatamIdoing</username>
        <id>1998764</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* '''Freshwater withdrawal (domestic/industrial/agricultural):''' */ Formatting</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">The '''Democratic Republic of the Congo''' forms part of the [[Congo Basin|Congo River Basin]], which covers an area of almost {{convert|1000000|km2}}. The country's only outlet to the [[Atlantic Ocean]] is a narrow strip of land on the north bank of the [[Congo River]].

The vast, low-lying central area is a plateau-shaped basin sloping toward the west, covered by [[tropical rainforest]] and criss-crossed by rivers, a large area of this has been categorized by the [[World Wildlife Fund]] as the [[Central Congolian lowland forests]] [[ecoregion]]. The forest center is surrounded by mountainous terraces in the west, plateaus merging into savannas in the south and southwest. 

Dense grasslands extend beyond the Congo River in the north. High mountains of the [[Ruwenzori Range]] (some above {{convert|5000|m|ft|abbr=on|disp=or}}) are found on the eastern borders with [[Rwanda]] and [[Uganda]] (see [[Albertine Rift montane forests]] for a description of this area).

== Climate ==
[[File:Koppen-Geiger Map COD present.svg|thumb|300px|Democratic Republic of the Congo map of Köppen climate classification zones]]
The Democratic Republic of the Congo lies on the [[equator]], with one-third of the country to the north and two-thirds to the south. The climate is hot and humid in the river basin and cool and dry in the southern highlands, with a cold, alpine climate in the [[Rwenzori Mountains]].

South of the equator, the rainy season lasts from October to May and north of the Equator, from April to November. Along the Equator, rainfall is fairly regular throughout the year. During the wet season, thunderstorms often are violent but seldom last more than a few hours. The average rainfall for the entire country is about {{convert|1070|mm|in|abbr=on}}. 

The Democratic Republic of Congo has a hot and wet climate because it lies in the equatorial region. It is hot because it receives direct sunlight and the seas evaporate faster because of the heat and that is the reason for humidity and rainfall. The hot and wet climate of DRC is known as the equatorial climate.

== Data ==
'''Location of Congo:'''
Central [[Africa]], north of [[Zambia]], south of [[Central African Republic]]

'''[[Geographic coordinates]]:''' {{coord|0|00|N|25|00|E|type:country}}

'''Continent:'''
Africa

'''Area:'''
&lt;br/&gt;''total:''
2,344,858&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;''land:''
2,267,048&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;''water:''
77,810&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;

'''Area - comparative:'''
Smaller than Russia, but bigger than the Vatican

'''Land boundaries:'''
&lt;br/&gt;''total:''
10,481&amp;nbsp;km
&lt;br/&gt;''border countries:''
&quot;[[Angola]] 2,646&amp;nbsp;km, [[Burundi]] 236&amp;nbsp;km, [[Central African Republic]] 1,747&amp;nbsp;km, [[Republic of the Congo]] 1,229&amp;nbsp;km, [[Rwanda]] 221&amp;nbsp;km, [[South Sudan]] 714&amp;nbsp;km, [[Tanzania]] 479&amp;nbsp;km, [[Uganda]] 877&amp;nbsp;km, [[Zambia]] 2,332&amp;nbsp;km&quot;

'''Coastline:'''
{{convert|37|km|mi|abbr=on}}.

'''Maritime claims:'''
&lt;br/&gt;''territorial sea:''
{{convert|12|nmi|km|abbr=on|lk=in}}
&lt;br/&gt;''exclusive economic zone:''
boundaries with neighbors

'''Climate:'''
tropical; hot and humid in equatorial river basin; cooler and drier in southern highlands; cooler-cold and wetter in eastern highlands and the Ruwenzori Range; north of Equator - wet season April to October, dry season December to February; south of [[Equator]] - wet season November to March, dry season April to October
[[File:LocationDRCongo.png|250px|thumb|Location of the DRC on a world map]]

'''Terrain:'''
vast central plateau covered by tropical rainforest, surrounded by mountains in the west, plains and savanna in the south/southwest, and grasslands in the north. The high mountains of the [[Ruwenzori Range]] on the eastern borders.

'''Elevation extremes:'''
&lt;br/&gt;''lowest point:''
[[Atlantic Ocean]] 0&amp;nbsp;m
&lt;br/&gt;''highest point:''
Pic Marguerite on [[Mont Ngaliema]] (Mount Stanley) 5,110&amp;nbsp;m

'''Natural resources:'''
[[cobalt]], [[copper]], [[niobium]], [[petroleum]], industrial and gem [[diamond]]s, [[gold]], [[silver]], [[zinc]], [[manganese]], [[tin]], [[uranium]], [[coal]], [[hydropower]], timber

'''Land use:'''
&lt;br/&gt;''arable land:''
3.09% 
&lt;br/&gt;''permanent crops:''
0.36%
96.55 (2012 est.)

'''Irrigated land:'''
105&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; (2003)

'''Total renewable water resources:'''
1,283 km&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; (2011)

==Freshwater withdrawal (domestic/industrial/agricultural)==

''total:''
0.68 km&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;/yr (68%/21%/11%)

''per capita:''
11.25 m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;/yr (2005)

'''Natural hazards:'''

periodic [[drought]]s in south; [[Congo River]] floods (seasonal); in the east, in the [[Albertine Rift]], there are active [[volcano]]es

'''Environment - current issues:'''

[[Poaching]] threatens wildlife populations (for example, the [[painted hunting dog]], ''Lycaon pictus'', is now considered [[Local extinction|extirpated]] from the Congo&lt;ref&gt;C. Michael Hogan. 2009&lt;/ref&gt; due to [[human overpopulation]] and poaching); water pollution; deforestation (chiefly due to land conversion to agriculture by indigenous farmers&lt;ref&gt;Anne Welsbacher. 2008&lt;/ref&gt;); refugees responsible for significant deforestation, soil erosion, and wildlife poaching; mining of minerals ([[coltan]] &amp;mdash; a mineral used in creating capacitors, diamonds, and gold) causing environmental damage

'''Environment - international agreements:'''

''party to:''
[[Biodiversity]], [[Climate Change]], [[Desertification]], Endangered Species, Hazardous Wastes, [[Law of the Sea]], Marine Dumping, Nuclear Test Ban, Ozone Layer Protection, [[Tropical Timber 83]], [[Tropical Timber 94]], Wetlands
&lt;br/&gt;''signed, but not ratified:''
Environmental Modification

'''Geography:'''

D.R. Congo is one of six African states that straddles the [[equator]]; it's the largest African state that has the equator passing through it. Very narrow strip of land that controls the lower [[Congo River]] and is the only outlet to South [[Atlantic Ocean]]; dense tropical [[rainforest]] in the central river basin and eastern highlands.

== Extreme points ==

This is a list of the extreme points of the [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]], the points that are farther north, south, east or west than any other location.

* Northernmost point - unnamed location on the border with the [[Central African Republic]] in the [[Bomu river]] immediately west of the town of [[Mbaga]] in CAR, [[Orientale Province]]
* Easternmost point - at the point where the northern section of the border with Uganda enters [[Lake Albert (Africa)|Lake Albert]] immediately west of [[Mahagi Port]], [[Oritentale Province]]
* Southernmost point - unnamed location on the border with [[Zambia]] immediately to north-west of the Zambian town of [[Ndabala]], [[Katanga Province|Katanga province]]
* Westernmost point - the point at which the border with [[Cabinda Province|Cabinda]] enters the [[Atlantic Ocean]], [[Bas-Congo]] province

==See also==
* [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]]
* [[Former place names in the Democratic Republic of the Congo]]

==References==
{{reflist}}{{CIA World Factbook}}
[[Category:Geography of the Democratic Republic of the Congo| ]]{{Geography of Africa}}</text>
      <sha1>27pakg79z98crujqzomroyjn3yb9iss</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
