  <page>
    <title>Djibouti Armed Forces</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8048</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941557737</id>
      <parentid>928319529</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-19T08:25:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ckfasdf</username>
        <id>30911873</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Component forces and their organization */ add ref on organization</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox national military
|name=Djibouti Armed Forces
|native_name={{lang-ar|الجيش الجيبوتي}}&lt;br&gt;{{lang-so|Ciidanka Jabuuti}}&lt;br&gt;{{lang-fr|Forces Armees Djiboutiennes}}
|country=Djibouti
|image = Emblem of the Djiboutian Armed Force.png
|caption = Emblem of the Djiboutian Armed Force
|founded = 6 June 1977 (42 years)
|branches = [[File:Logo of the Djiboutian Army.PNG|20px]] [[Djiboutian Army|Army]]&lt;br&gt;[[File:Roundel of Djibouti.svg|20px]] [[Djibouti Air Force|Air Force]]&lt;br&gt;[[File:Logo of the Djiboutian Navy.png|20px]] [[Djiboutian Navy|Navy]]&lt;br&gt;[[Djiboutian National Gendarmerie|Gendarmerie]]&lt;!-- list wikilinked branch names separated by BR --&gt;
|motto = Guul ama Dhimasho
|nickname = FAD or DNF
|active = 20,470 &lt;small&gt;(2018 est.)&lt;/small&gt;
|reserve = 12,220 &lt;small&gt;(2018 est.)&lt;/small&gt;
|age = 18–49 years old
|manpower_age = 18–49
|manpower_data = 2010 est.
|available = 391,797
|fit = 268,730
|commander-in-chief = [[President (government title)|President]] [[Ismaïl Omar Guelleh]]
|commander-in-chief_title = Commander in Chief
|commander = [[General]] Zakaria Cheikh Ibrahim
|commander_title = Chairman of the Chiefs of Staff
|reaching =
|amount = $3.6 million (2011 est.)
|percent_GDP = 3.7 (2011 est.)
|foreign_suppliers = {{flagu|United States}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagu|France}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagu|Italy}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagu|Japan}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagu|China}}
|history = '''[[List of wars involving Djibouti|Military history of Djibouti]]:'''
[[Djiboutian Civil War]]&lt;br&gt;[[Djiboutian–Eritrean border conflict]]&lt;br/&gt;[[United Nations–African Union Mission in Darfur]]&lt;br&gt;[[African Union Mission to Somalia]]
|deployed = {{Flag|Somalia}} – 3,000&lt;ref name=&quot;Ahmed Soliman and David Styan&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://allafrica.com/stories/201604180304.html|title=Connecting the Horn of Africa and the Gulf|author=Ahmed Soliman and David Styan|date=15 April 2016|work=allafrica|accessdate=15 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;{{Flag|Sudan}} – 151 police
| ranks = [[Military ranks of Djibouti]]
}}

The '''Djibouti Armed Forces''' ('''DJAF''') ({{lang-ar|الجيش الجيبوتي}}, {{lang-so|Ciidanka Jabuuti}}) are the military forces of [[Djibouti]]. They consist of the '''[[Djiboutian Army]]''' and its sub-branches the [[Djibouti Air Force]] and [[Djiboutian Navy]]. As of 2018, the Djibouti Armed Forces consists of 20,470 (2018 est.) ground troops, which are divided into several [[regiment]]s and [[battalion]]s garrisoned in various areas throughout the country. Djibouti Armed Forces are an important player in the [[Bab-el-Mandeb]] and [[Red Sea]].

In 2015 General Zakaria Chiek Imbrahim was ''chief d'etat-major general'' (chief of staff) of the ''Forces Armees Djiboutiennes''. He assumed command in November 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.hoa.africom.mil/story/7830/djiboutian-armed-forces-top-leader-retires-changes-command |title=Archived copy |access-date=2015-07-05 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150924030836/http://www.hoa.africom.mil/story/7830/djiboutian-armed-forces-top-leader-retires-changes-command |archive-date=2015-09-24 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Djibouti has always been a very active member in the African Union and the Arab League.

==History==
{{main|Military history of Djibouti}}
Historically, Somali society accorded prestige to the warrior (''waranle'') and rewarded military prowess. Except for men of religion (''wadaad''), who were few in number, all Somali males were considered potential warriors.
Djibouti's many [[Sultan]]ates each maintained regular troops. In the early Middle Ages, the conquest of [[Shewa]] by the [[Ifat Sultanate]] ignited a rivalry for supremacy with the [[Solomonic Dynasty]].
[[File:Djibarmgen.jpg|thumb|left|180px|A Djibouti Armed Forces commander.]]
Many similar battles were fought between the succeeding [[Sultanate of Adal]] and the Solomonids, with both sides achieving victory and suffering defeat. During the protracted [[Ethiopian-Adal War]] (1529–1559), [[Imam]] [[Ahmad ibn Ibrihim al-Ghazi]] defeated several [[Emperor of Ethiopia|Ethiopian Emperors]] and embarked on a conquest referred to as the ''Futuh Al-Habash'' (&quot;Conquest of Abyssinia&quot;), which brought three-quarters of Christian Abyssinia under the power of the [[Muslim]] Adal Sultanate.&lt;ref&gt;Saheed A. Adejumobi, ''The History of Ethiopia'', (Greenwood Press: 2006), p.178&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopædia Britannica, inc, Encyclopædia Britannica, Volume 1, (Encyclopædia Britannica: 2005), p.163&lt;/ref&gt; Al-Ghazi's forces and their [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] allies came close to extinguishing the ancient Ethiopian kingdom, but the Abyssinians managed to secure the assistance of [[Cristóvão da Gama]]'s [[Portugal|Portuguese]] troops and maintain their domain's autonomy. However, both polities in the process exhausted their resources and manpower, which resulted in the contraction of both powers and changed regional dynamics for centuries to come.

The [[Ogaden War]] (13 July 1977 – 15 March 1978) was a conflict fought between the [[Ethiopia|Ethiopian government]] and [[Somalia|Somali government]]. The Djibouti government supported Somalia with [[military intelligence]]. In a notable illustration of the nature of Cold War alliances, the [[Soviet Union]] switched from supplying aid to Somalia to supporting Ethiopia, which had previously been backed by the [[United States]]. This in turn prompted the U.S. to later start supporting [[Somalia]]. The war ended when Somali forces retreated back across the border and a truce was declared.

The first war which involved the Djiboutian armed forces was the [[Djiboutian Civil War]] between the Djiboutian government, supported by [[France]], and the [[Front for the Restoration of Unity and Democracy]] (''FRUD''). The war lasted from 1991 to 2001, although most of the hostilities ended when the moderate factions of FRUD signed a peace treaty with the government after suffering an extensive military setback when the government forces captured most of the rebel-held territory. A radical group continued to fight the government, but signed its own peace treaty in 2001. The war ended in a government victory, and FRUD became a political party.

[[File:Djiboutian troops and Light armoured cars near the border.jpg|thumb|Djiboutian troops with light armoured cars near the border of [[Eritrea]]]]
Djibouti has fought in clashes against [[Eritrea]] over the [[Ras Doumeira]] peninsula, which both countries claim to be under their sovereignty. The first clash occurred in 1996 after a nearly two-months stand-off. In 1999, a political crisis occurred when both sides accused each other for supporting its enemies. In 2008, the countries clashed again when Djibouti refused to return Eritrean deserters and Eritrea responded by firing at the Djiboutian forces. In the following battles, some 44 Djiboutian troops and some estimated 100 Eritreans were killed.

In 2011, Djibouti troops also joined the [[African Union Mission to Somalia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Sdpaimtja&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Somalia: Djibouti Peacekeepers Arrive in Mogadishu to Join Amisom|url=http://allafrica.com/stories/201112211223.html|accessdate=22 March 2013|newspaper=Garowe Online|date=21 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of 2013, the Djibouti Armed Forces (DJAF) are composed of three branches: the Djibouti National Army, which consists of the Coastal Navy, the Djiboutian Air Force (Force Aerienne Djiboutienne, FAD), and the National Gendarmerie (GN). The Army is by far the largest, followed by the Air Force and Navy. The Commander-in-Chief of the DJAF is the President of Djibouti and the Minister of Defence oversees the DJAF on a day-to-day basis.

==Component forces and their organization==
Refer to decree No 2003-0166/PR/MDN on organization of Djibouti armed forces.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite act|url=https://www.presidence.dj/PresidenceOld/jo/2003/decr0166pr03.php|title=Décret n°2003-0166/PR/MDN Portant réorganisation des Forces Armées Djiboutiennes|trans-title=Decree No. 2003-0166/PR/MDN Reorganizing the Djibouti Armed Forces| type = Decree | index = 2003-0166/PR/MDN|date=2003|lang=fr }}&lt;/ref&gt; The armed forces consist of:
* The General Staff of the Armed Forces.
* A Defense Staff.
* An infantry force: one rapid action regiment, two paratrooper battalions, one combined arms regiment at Obock, one combined arms regiment at Tadjourah, one combined arms regiment in Dikhil, one combined arms battalion in Ali-Sabieh and one reinforced company in Damerjog.
* Specific forces and fire support: one armored regiment, one artillery regiment and one group of combat engineer.
* The Navy
* The Air Force
* The Schools Command.
* The Headquarters Regiment.
* The Central Material Directorate.
* The Health Service.


===Djiboutian Army===
{{Main|Djiboutian Army}}
[[File:Guam national guardsmen train Djiboutian soldiers DVIDS80736.jpg|thumb|right|Djiboutian army soldiers conduct a patrol on the border.]]

The [[Djiboutian Army]] is the largest branch of the Djibouti Armed Forces. Djibouti maintains a modest military force of approximately 20,470 troops; the army is made of 18,600 troops (IISS 2018). The latter are divided into several [[regiment]]s and [[battalion]]s garrisoned in various areas throughout the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pdfad&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Présentation des forces armées djiboutiennes|url=http://www.diplomatie.gouv.fr/fr/politique-etrangere-de-la-france/defense-et-securite/cooperation-de-securite-et-de/revue-partenaires-securite-defense/archives-revue-freres-d-armes/les-anciens-numeros/freres-d-armes-253-dossier/dossier-republique-de-djibouti/article/presentation-des-forces-armees|publisher=Ministère des Affaires étrangères (France)|accessdate=23 March 2013}}{{dead link|date=September 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Army has four military districts (the Tadjourah, Dikhil, Ali-Sabieh and Obock districts).&lt;ref name=IISS_2012_432&gt;{{cite book|last=International Institute for Strategic Studies (IISS)|title=The Military Balance 2012|year=2012|publisher=IISS|location=London|page=432|issn=0459-7222}}&lt;/ref&gt; Clashes with the [[Military of Eritrea]], in 2008, demonstrated the superior nature of the Djiboutian forces’ training and skills, but also highlighted the fact that the small military would be unable to counter the larger, if less well-equipped forces of its neighbours. The army has concentrated on mobility in its equipment purchases, suitable for patrol duties and counterattacks but ill-suited for armoured warfare. The [[Djiboutian–Eritrean border conflict|2008 border clashes]] at least temporarily swelled the ranks of the Djiboutian army, with retired personnel being recalled, but the military’s size and capabilities are much reduced since the 1990s. The army to address more effectively its major defense disadvantage: [[Strategic depth|lack of strategic depth]]. Thus in the early 2000s it looked outward for a model of army organization that would best advance defensive capabilities by restructuring forces into smaller, more mobile units instead of traditional divisions. The official tasks of the armed forces include strengthening the country against external attack, and maintaining border security. Djiboutian troops continue to monitor its borders with [[Eritrea]], in the case of an attack. The Djiboutian Army is one of the small professional advanced armies in [[East Africa]].
{{Location map many | Djibouti
| width = 300
| float = right
| caption = &lt;center&gt;'''Djiboutian Army Infantry Regiments'''&lt;/center&gt;
| label1 = &lt;small&gt;Ali Sabieh Infantry Regiment &lt;/small&gt;
  | pos = right
  | bg = white
  | mark = Red pog.svg
  | lat_deg = 11 | lat_min = 09
  | lon_deg = 42 | lon_min = 43
| label2 = &lt;small&gt;Dikhil Infantry Regiment &lt;/small&gt;
  | pos2 = left
  | bg2 = white
  | mark2 = Red pog.svg
  | lat2_deg = 11 | lat2_min = 06
  | lon2_deg = 42 | lon2_min = 22
| label3 = &lt;small&gt;Obock Infantry Regiment &lt;/small&gt;
  | pos3 = left
  | bg3 = white
  | mark3 = Red pog.svg
  | lat3_deg = 11 | lat3_min = 58
  | lon3_deg = 43 | lon3_min = 17
| label4 = &lt;small&gt;Tadjoura Infantry Regiment &lt;/small&gt;
  | pos4 = left
  | bg4 = white
  | mark4 = Red pog.svg
  | lat4_deg = 11 | lat4_min = 47
  | lon4_deg = 42 | lon4_min = 53
| label5 = &lt;small&gt;Djibouti City Rapid Reaction Regiment &lt;/small&gt;
  | pos5 = right
  | bg5 = white
  | mark5 = Red pog.svg
  | lat5_deg = 11 | lat5_min = 35
  | lon5_deg = 43 | lon5_min = 08
| label6 = &lt;small&gt;One Demining Company&lt;/small&gt;
  | pos6 = left
  | bg6 = white
  | mark6 = Red pog.svg
  | lat6_deg = 11 | lat6_min = 31
  | lon6_deg = 42 | lon6_min = 06
}}

Its maneuver units are:
*One armoured regiment (comprising a reconnaissance squadron, three armoured squadrons and an anti-smuggling squadron)&lt;ref name=IISS_2012_432 /&gt;
*Four infantry regiments (each comprising three to four infantry companies and a support company)&lt;ref name=IISS_2012_432 /&gt; 
**Regiment interarmées de Tadjourah&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lanationdj.com/fad-regiments-interarmes-de-tadjourah-et-obock-de-jeunes-soldats-recoivent-leurs-premieres-instructions-militaires/{{Dead link|date=August 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;
**Regiment interarmees de Obock
**Two other infantry regiments
*One rapid reaction regiment (comprising four infantry companies and a support company)&lt;ref name=IISS_2012_432 /&gt; 
*One Republican Guard regiment&lt;ref name=IISS_2012_432 /&gt; 
*One artillery regiment&lt;ref name=IISS_2012_432 /&gt; 
*One demining company&lt;ref name=IISS_2012_432 /&gt; 
*One signals regiment&lt;ref name=IISS_2012_432 /&gt; 
*One computer and information systems section&lt;ref name=IISS_2012_432 /&gt; 
*One logistics regiment&lt;ref name=IISS_2012_432 /&gt; 
*One maintenance company&lt;ref name=IISS_2012_432 /&gt;

[[Italy]] delivered 10 howitzers M-109L (in 2013), tens IVECO trucks (ACM90, cranes, tankers, etc.), some IVECO armoured car Puma 4X4 and IVECO utility vehicles VM90.

In reforming the Djiboutian Army, most of the available financial resources have been directed to the development of the Land Forces. Over the years, Djiboutian Army has established partnerships with militaries in [[France]], [[Egypt]], [[Saudi Arabia]], [[Morocco]] and the [[United States]]. Currently, the amount allocated to defense represents the largest single entry in the country’s budget.

===Djiboutian Navy===
[[File:Djiboutian Navy.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Djiboutian Navy at naval base in [[Djibouti City]].]]
{{Main|Djiboutian Navy}}
The Djiboutian Navy is the naval service branch of the Djibouti Armed Forces. The Djiboutian Navy has about 1,000 regular personnel as of 2013, to protect national maritime rights and to support the nation's foreign policies. It is responsible for securing Djibouti's territorial waters and 314&amp;nbsp;km seaboard. The force was launched two years after Djibouti gained its independence in 1977. Initially, it comprised the remnants of the Gendarmerie and was focused on port safety and traffic monitoring. This is an area known to have considerable fish stocks, sustaining an active fisheries industry. The acquisition of several boats from the US in 2006 considerably increased the navy's ability to patrol over longer distances and to remain at sea for several days at a time. Cooperation with the US and Yemeni navies is also increasing in an effort to protect and maintain the safety and security of the Sea Lanes of Communication (SLOC). In 2004
[[Italy]] delivered 2 former [[Corps of the Port Captaincies – Coast Guard|Italian Coast Guard]] ''[[:it:Classe Super Speranza|Classe 200]]'' patrol boats (ex CP 230 and CP 234 ) and 2 new type ''CP 500'' motorboats.

===Djiboutian Air Force===
{{Main|Djibouti Air Force}}

The Djiboutian Air Force (DAF) (French: Force Aérienne du Djibouti (FADD) was established as part of the Djibouti Armed Forces after the country obtained its independence on June 27, 1977. Its first aircraft included three Nord N.2501 Noratlas transport aircraft and an Allouette II helicopter presented to it by the French. In 1982, the Djibouti Air Force was augmented by two Aerospatiale AS.355F Ecureuil 2 helicopters and a Cessna U206G Stationair, this was followed in 1985 by a Cessna 402C Utiliner. In 1985, the Allouette II was withdrawn from use and put on display at Ambouli Air Base at Djibouti's airport. In 1987, the three N.2501 Noratlas were also retired and subsequently returned to France. New equipment came, in 1991, in the form of a Cessna 208 Caravan, followed by Russian types in the early nineties. These included four Mil Mi 2, six Mil Mi 8 and two Mil Mi 17 helicopters and a single Antonov An 28 light transport aircraft. Pilot training for the 360 men of the DAF, if necessary, is conducted in France with continued on type flight training at home. The DAF has no units of its own and forms in whole a part of the Army, its sole base is Ambouli.

===Doctrine===
[[File:Djibouti Homeland Defense Medal.jpg|thumb|200px|The Homeland Defense Medal's was awarded to Djiboutian forces for duties related to the [[Djiboutian Civil War]] raids between 1991 and 1993.]]
The main doctrine consists of the following principles:

* Djibouti cannot afford to lose a war
* A small standing army with good capabilities.
* Desire to avoid war by political means.

=== Personnel ===
The size and structure of the Djibouti Armed Forces is continually evolving.
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;margin:auto; width:100%;&quot;
|+ '''Historical personnel of the Djibouti Armed Forces'''
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
! style=&quot;width:50px; text-align:center;&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|
! style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; colspan=&quot;10&quot;| [[File:Flag of Djibouti.svg|35px]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[Republic of Djibouti]]
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
!1977
!1979
!1982
!1985
!1989
!1992
!1998
!2000
!2007
!2015
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
||'''Regular'''
||2,800
||4,000
||6,800
||8,000
||9,000
||20,000
||13,000
||12,900
||10,500
||16,000
|-
|  style=&quot;border-bottom:1px solid black; text-align:center;&quot;|'''Army&amp;nbsp;Reserve'''
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; border-bottom:1px solid black; text-align:right; background:gray;&quot;|
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; border-bottom:1px solid black; text-align:right; background:gray;&quot;|1,000
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; border-bottom:1px solid black; text-align:right; background:gray;&quot;|1,500
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; border-bottom:1px solid black; text-align:right; background:gray;&quot;|2,200
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; border-bottom:1px solid black; text-align:right; background:gray;&quot;|4,000
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; border-bottom:1px solid black; text-align:right; background:gray;&quot;|500
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; border-bottom:1px solid black; text-align:right; background:gray;&quot;|4,500
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; border-bottom:1px solid black; text-align:right; background:gray;&quot;|6,000
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; border-bottom:1px solid black; text-align:right; background:gray;&quot;|8,000
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; border-bottom:1px solid black; text-align:right; background:gray;&quot;|9,500
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|  style=&quot;border-top:1px solid black; &quot;|'''Total'''
|  style=&quot;border-top:1px solid black; &quot;|'''2,800'''
|  style=&quot;border-top:1px solid black; &quot;|'''5,000'''
|  style=&quot;border-top:1px solid black; &quot;|'''8,200'''
|  style=&quot;border-top:1px solid black; &quot;|'''10,200'''
|  style=&quot;border-top:1px solid black; &quot;|'''13,000'''
|  style=&quot;border-top:1px solid black; &quot;|'''20,500'''
|  style=&quot;border-top:1px solid black; &quot;|'''17,500'''
|  style=&quot;border-top:1px solid black; &quot;|'''18,900'''
|  style=&quot;border-top:1px solid black; &quot;|'''18,500'''
|  style=&quot;border-top:1px solid black; &quot;|'''25,500'''
|}

As of 2018, Djibouti Armed Forces were reported to have 18,000–20,000 active personnel, 10,500–11,000 reserve personnel.

&lt;center&gt;
{| width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;border:0px solid #8888aa; background-color:white; padding:5px; font-size:100%; margin: 0px 0px 0px 0px;&quot;
|- bgcolor=&quot;#dadada&quot;
|'''Component'''||'''in service'''||'''Reserve'''
|-
|{{nowrap|[[File:Logo of the Djiboutian Army.PNG|25px]] [[Djiboutian Army]]}}||18,600 ||11,000
|-
|{{nowrap|[[File:Roundel of Djibouti.svg|25px]] [[Djibouti Air Force|Djiboutian Air Force]]}}||370 ||220
|-
|{{nowrap|[[File:Logo of the Djiboutian Navy.png|25px]] [[Djiboutian Navy]]}}||1,500 ||1,000
|- style=&quot;background:gray; color:White&quot;
|'''Totals'''||'''20,470'''||'''12,220'''
|}
&lt;/center&gt;

==Peacekeeping==
Djibouti has committed to strengthening international action through the [[African Union]] to achieve collective security and uphold the goals enshrined in the Purposes and Principles of the UN Charter and the Constitutive Act of the African Union. Deployed in 2 countries in [[Somalia]] and [[Sudan]]. Djibouti’s first contribution to UN peacekeeping was in 2010 in the Darfur, [[Sudan]].
[[File:Djiboutian forces artillery ready to fire on Al-Shabaab militants near the town of Buula Burde, Somalia.jpg|thumb|right|Djiboutian forces artillery ready to fire on Al-Shabaab militants near the town of [[Buloburde]], [[Somalia]].]]
{| style=&quot;border:1px solid black; background-color:#efe8ff; font-size:96%;&quot; align=left
|-
! [[Country]]
! [[List of United Nations peacekeeping missions|Mission]]
! Number of personnel
|-
| {{flagicon|Sudan}} [[Sudan]]
| [[United Nations–African Union Mission in Darfur|UNAMID]]
| 151 police officers
|-
| {{flagicon|Somalia}} [[Somalia]]
| [[African Union Mission to Somalia|AMISOM]]
| 2,000 peacekeeping troops
|-
|}
{{Clear}}

==Foreign military within Djibouti==
[[File:Djibouti U.S. Army Africa Soldiers offer first responder course 090806 (3819691775).jpg|thumb|right|Djibouti troops in first responder course with [[United States Army]] soldiers.]]

===China===
The [[Chinese naval support base in Djibouti]] began construction in 2016&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |magazine=[[The Diplomat]] |url=http://thediplomat.com/2016/02/confirmed-construction-begins-on-chinas-first-overseas-military-base-in-djibouti/ |title=Confirmed: Construction Begins on China's First Overseas Military Base in Djibouti |first=Ankit |last=Panda |date=February 29, 2016 |access-date=May 17, 2017 |quote=Last week, China’s Ministry of Defense confirmed for the first time that construction on “support facilities” for the People’s Liberation Army-Navy (PLAN) in Djibouti, on the Horn of Africa, has started. Colonel Wu Qian, a spokesperson for the Chinese defense ministry, said on Thursday that “construction of infrastructure for the support facilities has started, and the Chinese side has dispatched personnel to Djibouti for relevant work.” |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170514232104/http://thediplomat.com/2016/02/confirmed-construction-begins-on-chinas-first-overseas-military-base-in-djibouti/ |archive-date=May 14, 2017 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://eng.mod.gov.cn/Press/2016-02/25/content_4644801.htm |title=Defense Ministry's regular press conference on Feb.25 |date=February 15, 2016 |publisher=[[Ministry of National Defense of the People's Republic of China]] |quote=Through friendly consultations between China and Djibouti, the two sides have reached consensus for China to build support facilities in Djibouti. The facilities will mainly be used for logistical support and personnel recuperation of the Chinese armed forces conducting such missions as maritime escort in the Gulf of Aden and waters off the Somali coast, peacekeeping and humanitarian assistance. Currently, construction of infrastructure for the support facilities has started, and the Chinese side has dispatched personnel to Djibouti for relevant work. |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170518022718/http://eng.mod.gov.cn/Press/2016-02/25/content_4644801.htm |archive-date=May 18, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was officially opened in 2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |magazine=[[The Diplomat]] |title=China Officially Sets Up Its First Overseas Base in Djibouti |first=Charlotte |last=Gao |date=July 12, 2017 |quote=In the early morning of July 11, China held an official ceremony in the port of Zhanjiang, south China’s Guangdong province. The commander of China’s People’s Liberation Army Navy (PLAN), Shen Jinlong, “read an order on constructing the base in Djibouti, and conferred military flag on the fleets.” Then Shen ordered, “Set off!” and the ships carrying Chinese military personnel departed the port, reported Xinhua. |url=http://thediplomat.com/2017/07/china-officially-sets-up-its-first-overseas-base-in-djibouti/ |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170712013933/http://thediplomat.com/2017/07/china-officially-sets-up-its-first-overseas-base-in-djibouti/ |archive-date=July 12, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.xinhuanet.com/english/2017-07/11/c_136435716.htm |title=China sets up base in Djibouti |date=July 11, 2017 |publisher=[[Xinhua News Agency]] |editor=An |quote=Ships carrying Chinese military personnel departed Zhanjiang in southern China's Guangdong Province on Tuesday to set up a support base in Djibouti. |archive-date=July 12, 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170712014323/http://news.xinhuanet.com/english/2017-07/11/c_136435716.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===France===
France's [[5th Overseas Interarms Regiment|5e RIAOM]] are currently stationed in Djibouti.

===Italy===
The Italian ''Base Militare Nazionale di Supporto'' (National Support Military Base) is capable to host 300 troops and some [[UAVs]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oceanuslive.org/main/viewnews.aspx?uid=00000591]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://mobile.ilsole24ore.com/solemobile/main?fn=srchFd&amp;id=SEARCH/NEWS24/ABnNDIZ |title=Archived copy |access-date=2014-09-12 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140912225323/http://mobile.ilsole24ore.com/solemobile/main?fn=srchFd&amp;id=SEARCH%2FNEWS24%2FABnNDIZ |archive-date=2014-09-12 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://eunavfor.eu/italian-air-force-completes-its-first-remote-controlled-aircraft-sortie-for-operation-atalanta/]&lt;/ref&gt;

{{anchor|Deployment Airforce for Counter-Piracy Enforcement}}

===Japan===
The [[Japan Self-Defense Force Base Djibouti]] was established in 2011.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chinadaily.com.cn/world/2015-01/20/content_19353950.htm Japan eyes first overseas SDF long-term base in Djibouti January 20, 2015] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170803085912/http://www.chinadaily.com.cn/world/2015-01/20/content_19353950.htm |date=August 3, 2017 }} ''[[China Daily]]'' Retrieved November 23, 2016&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Deployment Airforce for Counter-Piracy Enforcement'' (DAPE): Established in 2011 with approximately 600 deployed personnel from the [[Japan Maritime Self-Defense Force]], on a rotational basis, operating naval vessels and maritime patrol aircraft. Japan reportedly pays $30 million per year for the military facilities, from which it conducts anti-piracy operations in the region. The base also acts as a hub for operations throughout the East African coastline.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.chathamhouse.org/sites/files/chathamhouse/public/Research/Africa/0413bp_djibouti.pdf Djibouti: Changing Influence in the Horn’s Strategic Hub] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170202001040/https://www.chathamhouse.org/sites/files/chathamhouse/public/Research/Africa/0413bp_djibouti.pdf |date=2017-02-02 }}, chathamhouse.org, David Styan, April 2013 (&quot;''Having temporarily used US facilities, a Japanese base, situated close to [[Camp Lemonnier]], opened in July 2011. Around 600 members of its Maritime Self-Defence Forces rotate between Japan’s naval vessels operating from the port of Djibouti and the camp. Naval units protecting Japanese shipping in the region had operated out of the US base prior to 2011. Japan is reported to pay an annual rent of $30 million for the facilities, similar to the sums paid for either of the far larger US and French bases. This has led to an expansion of Japan’s civilian aid programme to Djibouti, which has also become a hub for wider development activities in the Horn by the Japan International Cooperation Agency.''&quot;)&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States of America===
There is also [[Combined Joint Task Force - Horn of Africa]], a U.S. force of more than 3,500, currently deployed in the country at [[Camp Lemonnier]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.answers.com/topic/deployments-of-the-united-states-military|title=United States military deployments: Information from Answers.com|work=Answers.com|accessdate=23 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{commons category|Military of Djibouti}}
{{Reflist}}

{{Military of Djibouti}}
{{Djibouti topics}}
{{Military of Africa}}
{{Military of the Arab world}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Military Of Djibouti}}
[[Category:Government of Djibouti]]
[[Category:Military of Djibouti|Armed Forces]]
[[Category:Anti-piracy]]</text>
      <sha1>6wp5wc48ms34ay2j5q8pfmfiw2xwuce</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
