  <page>
    <title>Economy of the Democratic Republic of the Congo</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8025</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942285185</id>
      <parentid>938746305</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-23T19:25:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>CaribDigita</username>
        <id>60840</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{Infobox economy
|country         = Democratic Republic of Congo
|image           = Kinshasa by night (23769991270).jpg
|image_size      = 310px
|caption         = [[Kinshasa]], capital and economic center of the [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]]
|currency        = [[Congolese Franc]] (CDF)
|fixed exchange  =
|year            = Calendar Year
|organs          = [[African Union|AU]], [[African Continental Free Trade Agreement|AfCFTA]] (signed), [[African Development Bank|AfDB]], [[Southern African Development Community|SADC]], [[Common Market for Eastern and Southern Africa|COMESA]], [[Economic Community of Central African States|ECCAS]], [[Southern African Development Community|SADC]], [[World Trade Organization|WTO]], [[Group of 77]]
|gdp = {{plainlist|
*{{increase}} $47.099 billion (nominal, 2018)&lt;ref name=&quot;IMFWEOCD&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/weo/2019/02/weodata/weorept.aspx?pr.x=61&amp;pr.y=6&amp;sy=2017&amp;ey=2021&amp;scsm=1&amp;ssd=1&amp;sort=country&amp;ds=.&amp;br=1&amp;c=636&amp;s=NGDPD%2CPPPGDP%2CNGDPDPC%2CPPPPC%2CPCPIPCH&amp;grp=0&amp;a= |title=World Economic Outlook Database, October 2019 |publisher=[[International Monetary Fund]] |website=IMF.org |access-date=6 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{increase}} $78.297 billion ([[Purchasing power parity|PPP]], 2018)&lt;ref name=&quot;IMFWEOCD&quot;/&gt;}}
|growth          = {{plainlist|
*3.7%&amp;nbsp;(2017) 5.8%&amp;nbsp;(2018)
*4.3%&amp;nbsp;(2019e) 3.9%&amp;nbsp;(2020f)&lt;ref name=&quot; World Bank&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://openknowledge.worldbank.org/bitstream/handle/10986/33044/9781464814693.pdf |title=Global Economic Prospects, January 2020 : Slow Growth, Policy Challenges |page=147 |publisher=[[World Bank]] |website=openknowledge.worldbank.org |access-date=23 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
|per capita      = {{plainlist|
*{{increase}} $496 (nominal, 2018 est.)&lt;ref name=&quot;IMFWEOCD&quot;/&gt;
*{{increase}} $824 ([[Purchasing power parity|PPP]], 2018 est.)&lt;ref name=&quot;IMFWEOCD&quot;/&gt;}}
|components      =
|sectors         = [[agriculture]] (44.2%) [[industry]] (22.6%) [[Service (economics)|services]] (33.1%) (2012 est.)
|inflation       = 29.266% (2018)&lt;ref name=&quot;IMFWEOCD&quot;/&gt;
|poverty         = 70% (2011 est.)
|gini            = 
|hdi             = {{plainlist|
*{{increase}} 0.459 {{color|red|low}} (2018)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://hdr.undp.org/en/indicators/137506 |title=Human Development Index (HDI) |publisher=[[Human Development Report|HDRO (Human Development Report Office)]] [[United Nations Development Programme]] |website=hdr.undp.org |access-date=11 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; ([[List of countries by Human Development Index|179th]])
*0.316 [[List of countries by inequality-adjusted HDI|IHDI]] (2018)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://hdr.undp.org/en/content/table-3-inequality-adjusted-human-development-index-ihdi |title=Inequality-adjusted Human Development Index (IHDI) |publisher=[[Human Development Report|HDRO (Human Development Report Office)]] [[United Nations Development Programme]] |website=hdr.undp.org |access-date=11 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
|edbr            = {{increase}} [[Ease of doing business index#Ranking|183rd (below average, 2020)]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.doingbusiness.org/data/exploreeconomies/congo-dem-rep |title=Ease of Doing Business in Congo, Dem Rep |publisher=Doingbusiness.org |accessdate=2017-01-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|labor           = 35.86 million (2012 est.)
|occupations     = N/A
|unemployment    = N/A 
|industries      = [[mining]] ([[copper]], [[cobalt]], [[gold]], [[diamond]]s, [[coltan]], [[zinc]], [[tin]], [[tungsten]]), [[mineral processing]], [[consumer products]] (including [[textile]]s, [[plastic]]s, [[footwear]], [[cigarette]]s, [[processed food]]s, [[beverage]]s), [[metal]] products, [[lumber]], [[cement]], commercial [[ship]] repair
|exports         = {{Increase}} $8.872 billion (2012 est.)
|export-goods    = [[gold]], [[diamond]]s, [[copper]], [[cobalt]], [[coltan]], [[zinc]], [[tin]], [[tungsten]], [[crude oil]], [[wood]] products, [[coffee]]
|export-partners = {{plainlist|
*{{flag|China}} 53.4%
*{{flag|Zambia}} 24.5%
*{{flag|Belgium}} 5.6%
*(2012 est.)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/fields/2050.html#cg|title=Export Partners of Democratic Republic of Congo|publisher=[[CIA World Factbook]]|year=2012|accessdate=2013-07-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
|imports         = {{Increase}} $8.187 billion (2012 est.) 
|import-goods    = [[machinery]], [[transport]]ation equipment, [[fuel]], [[food]]
|import-partners = {{plainlist|
*{{flag|South Africa}} 21.4%
*{{flag|China}} 15.1%
*{{flag|Belgium}} 7.9%
*{{flag|Zambia}} 7.5%
*{{flag|Zimbabwe}} 6.1%
*{{flag|Kenya}} 5.1%
*{{flag|France}} 4.9%
*(2012 est.)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/fields/2061.html#cg|title=Import Partners of Democratic Republic of Congo|publisher=[[CIA World Factbook]]|year=2012|accessdate=2013-07-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
|gross external debt = {{increase}} $6.089 billion (31 December 2012 est.)
|FDI             =
|debt            = 
|revenue         = $4.943 billion (2018 est.) 
|expenses        = $5.198 billion (2018 est.) 
|aid             = 
|credit          =
|reserves        = {{Increase}} $1.633 billion (31 December 2012 est.)
|cianame         = cg
|spelling        =
}}

The '''economy of the Democratic Republic of the Congo''' has declined drastically since the mid-1980s,&lt;ref name=CENADEP&gt;
{{cite report |title=Province orientale :le diamant et l'or quelle part dans la reconstruction socio - économique de la Province ?  |author=Centre National d'Appui au Développement et à la Participation Paysanne CENADEP |date=2009-10-23 |url=http://www.societecivile.cd/node/4243 |url-status=dead | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091125042436/http://www.societecivile.cd/node/4243 |archivedate=25 November 2009 |df=dmy}}&lt;/ref&gt; despite being home to vast potential in natural resources and [[mineral]] wealth. 

At the time of its independence in 1960, the [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]] was the second most industrialized country in Africa after [[South Africa]]. It boasted a thriving mining sector and its agriculture sector was relatively productive.&lt;ref name=&quot;CENADEP&quot;/&gt; Since then, corruption, war and political instability have been a severe detriment to further growth, today leaving DRC with a [[List of countries by GDP (PPP) per capita|GDP per capita]] and a [[Human Development Index|HDI]] rating that rank among the world's lowest and make the DRC one of the [[Least Developed Countries|least developed countries in the world]].

Despite this the DRC is quickly modernizing; it tied with Malaysia for the largest positive change in HDI development in 2016. Government projects include strengthening the health system for maternal and child health, expansion of electricity access, water supply reconstructions, and urban and social rehabilitation programs.

==Economic implications of conflicts==
The two recent conflicts (the [[First Congo War|First]] and [[Second Congo War]]s), which began in 1996, have dramatically reduced national output and government revenue, have increased external debt, and have resulted in deaths of more than five million people from war, and associated [[famine]] and disease. [[Malnutrition]] affects approximately two thirds of the country's population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite report
 |title       = Governance Crisis and Conflict in the Democratic Republic of Congo
 |series      = Working Paper No. 6
 |author      = Seema Shekhawat
 |publisher   = Centre for African Studies, University of Mumbai
 |location    = Mumbai
 |date        = January 2009
 |url         = http://www.mu.ac.in/arts/social_science/african_studies/seemawp6.pdf
 |format      = PDF
 |accessdate  = 23 March 2013
 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20140706061102/http://www.mu.ac.in/arts/social_science/african_studies/seemawp6.pdf
 |archivedate = 6 July 2014
 |url-status     = dead
 |df          = dmy-all
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Agriculture]] is the mainstay of the [[economy]], accounting for 57.9% of [[Gross domestic product|GDP]] in 1997. In 1996, agriculture employed 66% of the work force.

Rich in minerals, the Democratic Republic of the Congo has a difficult history of predatory [[Mining industry of the Democratic Republic of the Congo|mineral extraction]], which has been at the heart of many struggles within the country for many decades, but particularly in the 1990s. The economy of the second largest country in [[Africa]] relies heavily on mining. However, much economic activity occurs in the [[informal sector]] and is not reflected in [[GDP]] data.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dublin - Research and Markets&quot;&gt;[http://www.researchandmarkets.com/research/e074e9/democratic_republi Dublin - Research and Markets]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006 [[Transparency International]] ranked the Democratic Republic of the Congo 156 out of 163 countries in the [[Corruption Perception Index]], tying [[Bangladesh]], [[Chad]], and [[Sudan]] with a 2.0 rating.&lt;ref name=e&gt;{{cite web|author=J. Graf Lambsdorff|year=2006|url=http://www.transparency.org/policy_research/surveys_indices/cpi/2006|title=Corruption Perceptions Index 2006|publisher=Transparency International|accessdate=2008-01-21|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110416023729/http://www.transparency.org/policy_research/surveys_indices/cpi/2006|archivedate=16 April 2011|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[President of the Democratic Republic of the Congo|President]] [[Joseph Kabila]] established the Commission of Repression of Economic Crimes upon his ascension to power in 2001.&lt;ref name=d&gt;{{cite book|last=Werve|first=Jonathan|year=2006|title=The Corruption Notebooks 2006|page=57}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The conflicts in the DRC were over water, minerals, and other resources. Political agendas have worsened the economy, as in times of crisis, the elite benefit while the general populace suffers. This is worsened as a result of corrupt national and international corporations. The corporations instigate and allow the fighting for resources because they benefit from it. A large proportion of fatalities in the country are attributed to a lack of basic services{{citation needed|date=March 2019}}. The influx of refugees since the war in 1998 only serves to worsen the issue of poverty. Money of the taxpayers in the DRC is often misappropriated by the corrupt leaders of the country, who use the money to benefit themselves instead of the citizens of the DRC. The [[Democratic Republic of the Congo|DRC]] is consistently rated the lowest on the UN Human Development Index.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = The Democratic Republic of Congo — Global Issues|url = http://www.globalissues.org/article/87/the-democratic-republic-of-congo|website = www.globalissues.org|accessdate = 2015-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economic history==
[[File:Democratic Republic of the Congo GDP evolution-fr.svg|thumb|450px|Evolution of the DRC's GDP.]]

=== After Leopold ===
Forced labor was important for the rural sector. The corporations that dominated the economy were mostly owned by [[Belgium]], but [[United Kingdom|British]] capital also played an important role. The 1950s were a period of rising income and expectations. Congo was said to have the best public health system in Africa, but there was also a huge wealth disparity. Belgian companies favored workers in certain areas more and exported them to work in different areas, restricting opportunities for others. Favored groups also received better education and were able to secure jobs for people in the same ethnic group which increased tensions. In 1960 there were only 16 university graduates out of a population of 20 million. [[Belgium]] still had economic power and independence gave little opportunity for improvement. Common refrains included &quot;no elite, no trouble&quot; and &quot;before independence = after independence&quot;. When the Belgians left, most of the government officials and educated residents left with them. Before independence there were just 3 out of 5000 government jobs held by Congolese people.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Joe Trapido: Africa’s Leaky Giant. New Left Review 92, March-April 2015.|url = http://newleftreview.org/II/92/joe-trapido-africa-s-leaky-giant|website = newleftreview.org|accessdate = 2015-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; The resulting loss of institutional knowledge and human capital crippled the government.[[File:2006Congo(Zaire) exports.PNG|thumb|350px|Congolese exports in 2006.]]

===Zaire===

After the [[Congo crisis]], [[Mobutu]] arose as the country's sole ruler and stabilized the country politically. Economically, however, the situation continued to decline, and  by 1979, the purchasing power was only 4% of that from 1960.&lt;ref name=dvr&gt;{{cite book| author=[[David van Reybrouck]]| title=[[Congo: The Epic History of a People]]| publisher=[[HarperCollins]], 2012 |page=374ff |isbn=978-0-06-220011-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Starting in 1976 the [[IMF]] provided stabilizing loans to the dictatorship. Much of the money was embezzled by Mobutu and his circle.&lt;ref name=dvr/&gt; This was not a secret as the 1982 report by IMF's envoy [[Erwin Blumenthal]] documented.  He stated,  it is &quot;alarmingly clear that the corruptive system in Zaire with all its wicked and ugly manifestations, its mismanagement and fraud will destroy all endeavors of international institutions, of friendly governments, and of the commercial banks towards recovery and rehabilitation of Zaire’s economy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Georges Nzongola-Ntalaja |title=The Crisis in Zaire: Myths and Realities| publisher=[[Africa World Press]], 1986 |page=226 |isbn =0-86543-023-3 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ceGn_ScbcU8C&amp;pg=PA226&amp;lpg=PA226&amp;dq=blumenthal+report+zaire&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=5VTQEXdb7-&amp;sig=lcp3pQvMIYYVkzWadieeYYdAopY&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=irgVVdSsB4nDggSYl4TIAQ&amp;ved=0CDIQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=blumenthal%20report%20zaire&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Blumenthal indicated that there was &quot;no chance&quot;  that creditors would ever recover their loans. Yet the IMF and the [[World Bank]] continued to lend money that was either embezzled, stolen, or &quot;wasted on elephant projects&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.modernghana.com/news/219270/50/imf-and-world-bank-agents-of-povert.html |author=Aikins Adusei |title=IMF and World Bank: Agents of Poverty or Partners of Development?| publisher=Modern Ghana |date=30 May 2009 |accessdate=30 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Structural adjustment programmes&quot; implemented as a condition of IMF loans cut support for health care, education, and infrastructure.&lt;ref name=dvr/&gt;

===1990s===
[[International Bank for Reconstruction and Development]] (IBRD) Trust Fund for the Congo.
Poor [[infrastructure]], an uncertain legal framework, corruption, and lack of openness in government economic policy and financial operations remain a brake on investment and growth. A number of [[International Monetary Fund]] (IMF) and [[World Bank]] missions have met with the new government to help it develop a coherent economic plan but associated reforms are on hold.

Faced with continued currency depreciation, the government resorted to more drastic measures and in January 1999 banned the widespread use of U.S. dollars for all domestic commercial transactions, a position it later adjusted. The government has been unable to provide foreign exchange for economic transactions, while it has resorted to printing money to finance its expenditure. Growth was negative in 2000 because of the difficulty of meeting the conditions of international donors, continued low prices of key exports, and post-coup instability.
Although depreciated, congolese francs have been stable for few years (Ndonda, 2014)

===2000s===
Conditions improved in late 2002 with the withdrawal of a large portion of the invading foreign troops. A number of IMF and World Bank missions have met with the government to help it develop a coherent economic plan, and President Kabila has begun implementing reforms.

====Special Economic Zone====
The DRC is embarking on the establishment of [[special economic zone]]s (SEZ) to encourage the revival of its industry. The first SEZ was planned to come into being in 2012 in N'Sele, a commune of Kinshasa, and will focus on agro-industries. The Congolese authorities also planned to open another zone dedicated to mining (Katanga) and a third dedicated to cement (in the Bas-Congo).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lecho.be/actualite/economie_-_politique_international/Congo-_Le_-paradis-_ou_le_droit_fera_la_loi.8989989-3164.art] Le &quot;paradis&quot; où le droit fera la loi, L'Echo, novembre 2010 {{in lang|fr}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are three phases to the program that each have their own objectives. Phase I was the precursor to the actual investment in the Special Economic Zone where policymakers agreed to the framework, the framework was studied for its establishment, and to predict the potential market demand for the land. Stage one of Phase II involved submitting laws for the Special Economic Zone, finding good sites for businesses, and currently there is an effort to help the government attract foreign investment. Stage two of Phase II hasn't been started yet and it involves assisting the government in creating framework for the country, creating an overall plan for the site, figuring out what the environmental impact of the project will be, and guessing how much it will cost and what the return can be made on the investment. Phase III involves the World Bank creating a transaction phase that will keep everything competitive. The program is looking for options to hand over the program to the World Bank which could be very beneficial for the western part of the country.

== Data ==
The following table shows the main economic indicators in 1980–2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Report for Selected Countries and Subjects|url=https://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/weo/2018/01/weodata/weorept.aspx?pr.x=79&amp;pr.y=9&amp;sy=1980&amp;ey=2023&amp;scsm=1&amp;ssd=1&amp;sort=country&amp;ds=.&amp;br=1&amp;c=636&amp;s=NGDP_RPCH,PPPGDP,PPPPC,PCPIPCH,GGXWDG_NGDP&amp;grp=0&amp;a=|accessdate=2018-08-25|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
!Year
!1980
!1985
!1990
!1995
!2000
!2005
!2006
!2007
!2008
!2009
!2010
!2011
!2012
!2013
!2014
!2015
!2016
!2017
|-
|GDP in $&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;(PPP)&lt;/small&gt;
|19.62 bn.
|27.16 bn.
|31.58 bn.
|24.37 bn.
|20.34 bn.
|27.55 bn.
|29.90 bn.
|32.61 bn.
|35.33 bn.
|36.62 bn.
|39.70 bn.
|43.30 bn.
|47.22 bn.
|52.05 bn.
|58.01 bn.
|62.70 bn.
|65.02 bn.
|68.45 bn.
|-
|GDP per capita in $&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;(PPP)&lt;/small&gt;
|683
|804
|795
|522
|388
|453
|478
|506
|532
|535
|563
|597
|632
|676
|732
|768
|773
|790
|-
|GDP growth&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;(real)&lt;/small&gt;
|2.4 %
|0.5 %
|−6.6 %
|2.8 %
|−8.1 %
|6.1 %
|5.3 %
|6.3 %
|6.2 %
|2.9 %
|7.1 %
|6.9 %
|7.1 %
|8.5 %
|9.5 %
|6.9 %
|2.4 %
|3.4 %
|-
|Inflation&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;(in Percent)&lt;/small&gt;
|40.0 %
|23.5 %
|81.3 %
|541.8 %
|550.0 %
|21.5 %
|12.8 %
|16.7 %
|18.0 %
|46.1 %
|23.5 %
|15.0 %
|0.9 %
|0.9 %
|1.2 %
|1.0 %
|18.2 %
|41.5 %
|-
|Government debt&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;(in % of GDP)&lt;/small&gt;
|...
|...
|...
|...
|135 %
|101 %
|104 %
|87 %
|74 %
|85 %
|31 %
|25 %
|23 %
|20 %
|18 %
|16 %
|17 %
|16 %
|}

==Economic implications of instability==
Ongoing conflicts dramatically reduced government [[revenue]] and increased external debt. As Reyntjens wrote, &quot;Entrepreneurs of insecurity are engaged in extractive activities that would be impossible in a stable state environment. The criminalization context in which these activities occur offers avenues for considerable factional and personal enrichment through the trafficking of arms, illegal drugs, toxic products, mineral resources and dirty money.&quot; Ethnic rivalries were made worse because of economic interests and [[looting]] and coltan smuggling took place. Illegal [[monopoly|monopolies]] formed in the country where they used forced labor for children to mine or work as soldiers. National parks were overrun with people looking to exploit minerals and resources. Increased poverty and hunger from the war and that increased the hunting of rare wildlife. Education was denied when the country was under foreign control and very few people make money off the minerals in the country. The national resources are not the root cause for the continued fighting in the region, however, the competition has become an incentive to keep fighting.[1] The DRC's level of economic freedom is one of the lowest in the world, putting it in the repressed category. The armed militias fight with the government in the eastern section of the country over the mining sector or the corruption of the government, and weak policies lead to the instability of the economy. [[Human rights]] abuses also ruin economic activity; the DRC has a 7% unemployment rate, but still has one of the lowest GDP's per capita in the world. A major problem for people trying to start their own companies is that the minimum amount of capital needed to launch the company is 5 times the average annual income, and prices are regulated by the government, which almost forces people to have to work for the larger, more corrupt businesses; otherwise, they won't have work. It is hard for the DRC to encourage foreign trade because of the regulatory barriers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Democratic Republic of Congo  Economy: Population, GDP, Inflation, Business, Trade, FDI, Corruption|url = http://www.heritage.org/index/country/democraticrepubliccongo|website = www.heritage.org|accessdate = 2017-02-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==International Relations==
[[International Bank for Reconstruction and Development]] (IBRD) Trust Fund for the Congo.
Poor [[infrastructure]], an uncertain legal framework, corruption, and lack of openness in government economic policy and financial operations remain a brake on investment and growth. A number of [[International Monetary Fund]] (IMF) and [[World Bank]] missions have met with the new government to help it develop a coherent economic plan but associated reforms are on hold.

Faced with continued currency depreciation, the government resorted to more drastic measures and in January 1999 banned the widespread use of U.S. dollars for all domestic commercial transactions, a position it later adjusted. The government has been unable to provide foreign exchange for economic transactions, while it has resorted to printing money to finance its expenditure. Growth was negative in 2000 because of the difficulty of meeting the conditions of international donors, continued low prices of key exports, and post-coup instability. 125 companies in 2003 contributed to the conflict in DRC showing the corruption.

===World Bank===
With the help of the [[The World Bank in the Democratic Republic of the Congo|International Development Association]] the DRC has worked toward the reestablishment of social services. This is done by giving 15 million people access to basic health services and giving bed nets to prevent malaria from spreading to people. With the Emergency Demobilization and Reintegration Program more than 107,000 adults and 34,000 child soldiers stood down their militarized posture. The travel time from Lubumbashi to Kasomeno in Katanga went down from seven days to two hours because of the improved roads which led to the decrease of prices of main goods by 60%. With the help of the IFC, KfW, and the EU the DRC improved its businesses by reducing the time it took to create a business by 51%, reducing the time it took to get construction permits by 54%, and reducing the number of taxes from 118 to 30. Improvements in health have been noticeable specifically that deliveries attended by trained staff jumped from 47 to 80%. In education 14 million textbooks were provided to children, completion rates of school have increased, and higher education was made available to students that chose to pursue it.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = News &amp; Broadcast - Democratic Republic of Congo: Country Results Profile|url = http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/NEWS/0,,contentMDK:23169309~menuPK:141310~pagePK:34370~piPK:34424~theSitePK:4607,00.html|website = web.worldbank.org|accessdate = 2015-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Ease of Doing Business Rank (EDBR)====
The Democratic Republic of Congo ranks 183 on the low end of the ease of doing business scale as ranked by the World Bank. This measures the difficulties of starting a business, enforcing contracts, paying taxes, resolving insolvency, protecting investors, trading across borders, getting credit, getting electricity, dealing with construction permits and registering property (World Bank 2014:8).&lt;ref name=WorldBank2013&gt;{{cite report
 |url         = http://www.doingbusiness.org/~/media/giawb/doing%20business/documents/profiles/country/ZAR.pdf
 |title       = Economy Profile: Democratic Republic of Congo
 |publisher   = [World Bank: The International Bank for Reconstruction and Development www.worldbank.org]
 |location    = Washington, DC
 |date        = 2013
 |accessdate  = 2013
 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20130220020302/http://doingbusiness.org/~/media/giawb/doing%20business/documents/profiles/country/ZAR.pdf
 |archivedate = 20 February 2013
 |url-status     = dead
 |df          = dmy-all
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===International Monetary Fund===
The IMF plans on giving the DRC a $1 billion loan after its two-year suspension after it failed to give details about a mining deal from one of its state owned mines and an Israeli billionaire, Dan Gertler. The loan may be necessary for the country because there will be elections in December 2016 for the next president and the cost of funding this would range around $1.1 billion. The biggest problem with the vote is getting a country of 68 million people the size of Western Europe to polling stations with less than 1,860 miles of paved roads.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = IMF Ready to Lend $1 Billion to Democratic Republic of Congo|url = https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2015-02-18/imf-willing-to-lend-1-billion-to-democratic-republic-of-congo|website = Bloomberg.com|accessdate = 2015-12-13|first = Malcolm|last = Beith|first2 = Paul|last2 = Richardson}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sectors==

===Agriculture===
{{Main|Agriculture in the Democratic Republic of the Congo}}
Agriculture is the mainstay of the economy, accounting for 57.9% of the GDP in 1997. Main cash crops include [[coffee]], [[palm oil]], [[rubber]], [[cotton]], [[sugar]], [[tea]], and [[Cocoa bean|cocoa]]. Food crops include [[cassava]], [[Plantain (cooking)|plantains]], [[maize]], [[Bambara groundnut|groundnuts]], and [[rice]]. In 1996, agriculture employed 66% of the work force.

===Fishing===
The Democratic Republic of Congo also possesses 50 percent of Africa's forests and a river system that could provide [[hydro-electric]] power to the entire continent, according to a [[United Nations]] report on the country's strategic significance and its potential role as an economic power in [[central Africa]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stripes.com/article.asp?section=104&amp;article=69718 Democratic Republic of the Congo economic and strategic significance]&lt;/ref&gt; Fish are the single most important source of animal protein in the DRC. Total production of marine, river, and lake fisheries in 2003 was estimated at 222,965 tons, all but 5,000 tons from inland waters. PEMARZA, a state agency, carries on marine fishing.

===Forestry===
{{See also|Deforestation in the Democratic Republic of the Congo}}

Forests cover 60 percent of the total land area. There are vast [[timber]] resources, and commercial development of the country's 61 million hectares (150 million acres) of exploitable wooded area is only beginning. The [[Mayumbe area]] of [[Bas-Congo]] was once the major center of timber exploitation, but forests in this area were nearly
depleted. The more extensive forest regions of the central cuvette and of the [[Ubangi River]] valley have increasingly been tapped.

Roundwood removals were estimated at 72,170,000 m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; in 2003, about 95 percent for fuel. Some 14 species are presently being harvested. Exports of forest products in 2003 totalled $25.7 million. Foreign capital is necessary in order for forestry to expand, and the government recognizes that changes in tax structure and export procedures will be needed to facilitate economic growth.

===Mining===
{{Main|Mining industry of the Democratic Republic of the Congo}}

[[File:Tree map exports 2009 DRCongo.jpeg|thumb|350px|Graphical depiction of DRCongo's product exports in 28 color-coded categories.]]
Rich in minerals, the DRC has a difficult history of predatory [[Mining industry of the Democratic Republic of the Congo|mineral extraction]], which has been at the heart of many struggles within the country for many decades, but particularly in the 1990s. Although the economy of the Democratic Republic of the Congo, the second largest country in [[Africa]] who has historically relied heavily on mining, is no longer reflected in the [[GDP]] data as the mining industry has suffered from long-term &quot;uncertain legal framework, corruption, and a lack of transparency in government policy.&quot; The [[informal sector]] .&lt;ref name=&quot;Dublin - Research and Markets&quot;/&gt;

In her book entitled ''The Real Economy of Zaire'', MacGaffey described a second, often illegal economy, &quot;system D,&quot; which is outside the official economy (MacGaffey 1991:27).&lt;ref name=MacGaffey&gt;
{{cite book
|author=Janet MacGaffey
|title=The Real Economy of Zaire: The Contribution of Smuggling and Other Unofficial Activities to National Wealth 
|location=London
|publisher=James Currey
|year=1991
|pages=175
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and therefore is not reflected in the GDP.

exploitation of mineral substances as MIBA EMAXON and De Beers 
The economy of the second largest country in Africa relies heavily on mining. The Congo is the world's largest producer of [[cobalt]] ore,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.indexmundi.com/en/commodities/minerals/cobalt/cobalt_t8.html |title = Cobalt: World Mine Production, By Country |accessdate = 2008-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a major producer of [[copper]] and industrial [[diamond]]s. The Congo has 70% of the world's [[coltan]], and more than 30% of the world's diamond reserves.,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/5209428.stm DR Congo poll crucial for Africa]&quot; BBC News. 16 November 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; mostly in the form of small, industrial diamonds. The [[coltan]] is a major source of [[tantalum]], which is used in the fabrication of electronic components in computers and mobile phones. In 2002, [[tin]] was discovered in the east of the country, but, to date, mining has been on a small scale.

Smuggling of the [[conflict minerals]], [[coltan]] and [[cassiterite]] (ores of [[tantalum]] and [[tin]], respectively), has helped fuel the war in the Eastern Congo.&lt;ref name=NYTLootedRiches&gt;
{{cite news
|url = https://www.nytimes.com/2008/11/16/world/africa/16congo.html?scp=2&amp;sq=congo&amp;st=nyt
| title = Congo's Riches, Looted by Renegade Troops
| work=The New York Times 
| first=Lydia 
| last=Polgreen 
| date=16 November 2008 
| accessdate=27 March 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Copper and Cobalt===
[[Katanga Mining|Katanga Mining Limited]], a London-based company, owns the Luilu Metallurgical Plant, which has a capacity of 175,000 tonnes of copper and 8,000 tonnes of cobalt per year, making it the largest cobalt refinery in the world. After a major rehabilitation program, the company restarted copper production in December 2007 and cobalt production in May 2008.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url = http://www.katangamining.com/kat/media/newsreleases/news2008/2008-08-12/ 
|title = Katanga Project Update and 2Q 2008 Financials, Katanga Mining Limited, 
|date=8 12 08
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Informal sector===
Much economic activity occurs in the informal sector and is not reflected in GDP data.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dublin - Research and Markets&quot;/&gt;

==Transport==
[[File:First train in Kindu, DRC.jpg|thumb|250px|All aboard - a train from [[Lubumbashi]] arriving in [[Kindu]] on a newly refurbished line.]]
{{Main|Transport in the Democratic Republic of the Congo}}

Ground transport in the Democratic Republic of Congo has always been difficult. The terrain and climate of the [[Congo Basin]] present serious barriers to road and rail construction, and the distances are enormous across this vast country. Furthermore, chronic economic mismanagement and internal conflict has led to serious under-investment over many years.

On the other hand, the Democratic Republic of Congo has thousands of kilometres of [[navigable]] [[waterway]]s, and traditionally water transport has been the dominant means of moving around approximately two-thirds of the country.

==See also==
{{Portal|Democratic Republic of the Congo|Economy}}
*[[Democratic Republic of the Congo]]
* [[List of companies based in the Democratic Republic of the Congo]]
*[[Mining industry of the Democratic Republic of the Congo]]
* [[United Nations Economic Commission for Africa]]

==References==
*{{CIA World Factbook}}
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*{{cite book
|author=Janet MacGaffey
|title=The Real Economy of Zaire: The Contribution of Smuggling and Other Unofficial Activities to National Wealth 
|location=London
|publisher=James Currey
|year=1991
|pages=175
}}
*{{cite report
 |title       = Governance Crisis and Conflict in the Democratic Republic of Congo
 |series      = Working Paper No. 6
 |author      = Seema Shekhawat
 |publisher   = Centre for African Studies, University of Mumbai
 |location    = Mumbai
 |date        = January 2009
 |url         = http://www.mu.ac.in/arts/social_science/african_studies/seemawp6.pdf
 |format      = PDF
 |accessdate  = 23 March 2013
 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20140706061102/http://www.mu.ac.in/arts/social_science/african_studies/seemawp6.pdf
 |archivedate = 6 July 2014
 |url-status     = dead
 |df          = dmy-all
}}
*{{dmoz|Regional/Africa/Congo,_Democratic_Republic_of_the/Business_and_Economy/Economic_Development}}
*[http://www.trademap.org/open_access/Index.aspx?proceed=true&amp;reporter=180 Democratic Republic of the Congo latest trade data on ITC Trade Map]
*[http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,1912594,00.html?xid=rss-topstories First Blood Diamonds, Now Blood Computers?] by Elizabeth Dias, ''Time Magazine'', 24 July 2009
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110512004925/http://congoeconomie.org/growth%20accounting%20%20drc%20version%20WP-DT2-2010.pdf Oasis Kodila Tedika et Francklin Kyayima Muteba, The sources of growth in DRC before independence. A cointegration analysis, CRE Working paper, n°02/10, juin 2010]
* [http://econpapers.repec.org/paper/innwpaper/2007-31.htm Exenberger, Andreas/Hartmann, Simon (2007): The Dark Side of Globalization. The Vicious Cycle of Exploitation from World Market Integration: Lesson from the Congo, Working Papers in Economics and Statistics 31-2007] 7yjmyry
*{{cite report
|url= http://www.doingbusiness.org/data/exploreeconomies/congo,-dem~-rep~/
|title= Doing Business in Congo, Dem. Rep. 2013
|publisher=[[World Bank]]
|accessdate=2013-03-25}}
*{{cite news
|url = https://www.nytimes.com/2008/11/16/world/africa/16congo.html?scp=2&amp;sq=congo&amp;st=nyt
| title = Congo's Riches, Looted by Renegade Troops
| work=The New York Times 
| first=Lydia 
| last=Polgreen 
| date=16 November 2008 
| accessdate=27 March 2010
}}

{{DRC topics}}
{{Africa in topic|Economy of}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Economy Of The Democratic Republic Of The Congo}}
[[Category:African Union member economies|Congo, Democratic Republic of the]]
[[Category:World Trade Organization member economies|Congo, Democratic Republic of the]]
[[Category:Economy of the Democratic Republic of the Congo| ]]</text>
      <sha1>gex7rzf0gjydv5q72fzw9yowzy68dvv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
