  <page>
    <title>Collective noun</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7148</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941312272</id>
      <parentid>941312028</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-17T21:04:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sandstein</username>
        <id>359256</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* top */ ce</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Type of noun referring to collections as a unit}}
{{Grammatical categories}}
{{Distinguish|mass noun|collective number|collective numeral}}
In [[linguistics]], a '''collective noun''' is a collection of things taken as a whole. Most collective nouns in everyday speech are ''not'' specific to one kind of thing, such as the word &quot;group&quot;, which can be applied to people (&quot;a group of people&quot;) or dogs (&quot;a group of dogs&quot;) or other things. Some collective nouns are specific to one kind of thing, especially [[#Terms of venery|terms of venery]], which identify groups of specific animals. For example, &quot;pride&quot; as a term of venery always refers to lions, never to dogs or cows. Other examples come from [[popular culture]] such as a group of owls, which is called a &quot;parliament&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=An unkindness of ravens: a book of collective nouns.|last=Rhodes|first=Chloe|publisher=Michael O'Mara Books|year=2014|isbn=978-1-78243-308-8|location=London|pages=131}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2014/sep/19/ten-best-collective-nouns|title=Ten of the best collective nouns|last=Rhodes|first=Chloe|date=19 September 2014|work=The Guardian|access-date=23 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Different forms of English handle verb [[Agreement (linguistics)|agreement]] with collective [[count noun]]s differently. For example, users of [[British English]] generally accept that collective nouns take either singular or plural verb forms depending on context and the [[metonymy|metonymic]] shift that it implies.

== Derivation ==
[[Morphological derivation]] accounts for many collective words and various languages have common [[affix]]es for denoting collective nouns. Because derivation is a slower and less productive [[word formation]] process than the more overtly [[syntax|syntactical]] morphological methods, there are fewer collectives formed this way. As with all derived words, derivational collectives often differ [[Semantics|semantically]] from the original words, acquiring new [[connotation]]s and even new [[denotation]]s.

== Affixes ==

=== Proto-Indo-European===
Early Proto-Indo-European used the suffix *eh₂ to form collective nouns, which evolved into the Latin neuter plural ending -a. Late Proto-Indo-European used the ending *t, which evolved into the English ending -th, as in &quot;youth&quot;.

=== English ===
The English endings ''-age'' and ''-ade'' often signify a collective. Sometimes, the relationship is easily recognizable: ''baggage, drainage, blockade''. Though the [[etymology]] is plain to see, the derived words take on a distinct meaning. This is a [[Productive (linguistics)|productive]] ending, as evidenced in the recent [[Coined word|coin]], &quot;[[signage]]&quot;.

===German===
[[German language|German]] uses the [[prefix]] ''[[wikt:ge-#German|ge]]-'' to create collectives. The root word often undergoes [[I-mutation|umlaut]] and [[suffix]]ation as well as receiving the ''ge-'' prefix. Nearly all nouns created in that way are of [[neuter gender]]:
* ''{{lang|de|das Gebirge}}'', &quot;group of hills, mountain range&quot; {{abbr|&lt;|from}} ''{{lang|de|der Berg}}'', &quot;mountain&quot; or &quot;hill&quot;
* ''{{lang|de|das Gepäck}}'', &quot;luggage, baggage&quot; &lt; ''{{lang|de|der Pack}}'', &quot;pack, bundle, pile&quot;
* ''{{lang|de|das Geflügel}}'', &quot;poultry, fowl (birds)&quot; &lt; late [[Middle High German|MHG]] ''{{lang|gmh|gevlügel(e)}}'', under the influence of ''{{lang|de|der Flügel}}'', &quot;wing&quot; &lt; MHG ''{{lang|gmh|gevügel}}'' &lt; [[Old High German|OHG]] ''{{lang|goh|gifugili}}'' = collective formation of ''{{lang|goh|fogal}}'', &quot;bird&quot;
* ''{{lang|de|das Gefieder}}'', &quot;plumage&quot; &lt; ''{{lang|de|die Feder}}'', &quot;feather&quot;
* ''{{lang|de|das Geschwisterkind}}'', &quot;sibling&quot; &lt; ''{{lang|de|die Schwester}}'', &quot;sister&quot;
* ''{{lang|de|die Geschwister}}'', &quot;siblings&quot; &lt; ''{{lang|de|die Schwester}}'', &quot;sister&quot;
* &quot;Der Gebirgszug&quot; and &quot;die Bergkette&quot; also mean &quot;mountain range&quot;, drawing on the words &quot;der Zug&quot; = train, and &quot;die Kette&quot; = chain.
There are also several endings that can be used to create collectives, such as &quot;welt&quot; and &quot;masse&quot;.

=== Dutch ===
[[Dutch language|Dutch]] has a similar pattern but sometimes uses the (unproductive) [[circumfix]] ''{{linktext|ge- -te}}'':&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Morphology of Dutch|last=Booij|first=Geert|date=2002|publisher=Oxford University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''{{lang|nl|berg}}'' 'mountain' &gt; ''{{lang|nl|gebergte}}'' 'mountain range'
* ''{{lang|nl|been}}'' 'bone' &gt; ''{{lang|nl|gebeente}}'' 'skeleton'
* ''{{lang|nl|vogel}}'' 'bird' &gt; ''{{lang|nl|gevogelte}}'' 'poultry'
* ''{{lang|nl|blad}}'' 'leaf' &gt; ''{{lang|nl|gebladerte}}'' 'foliage'

=== Swedish ===
The following [[Swedish language|Swedish]] example has different words in the collective form and in the individual form:
* An individual mosquito is a ''{{lang|sv|[[wikt:mygga|mygga]]}}'' (plural: ''{{lang|sv|[[wikt:myggor|myggor]]}}''), but mosquitos as a collective is ''{{lang|sv|[[wikt:mygg|mygg]]}}''.

=== Esperanto ===
[[Esperanto]] uses the collective infix -''[[wikt:-ar#Esperanto|ar]]'' to produce a large number of derived words:
* ''monto'' 'mountain' &gt; ''montaro'' 'mountain range'
* ''birdo'' 'bird' &gt; ''birdaro'' 'flock'
* ''arbo'' 'tree' &gt; ''arbaro'' 'forest'
* ''ŝipo'' 'ship' &gt; ''ŝiparo'' 'fleet'
* ''manĝilo'' 'eating utensil' &gt; ''manĝilaro'' 'silverware', 'cutlery'

== Metonymic merging of grammatical number ==
{{Main|Synesis|Plurale tantum}}
{{Unreferenced section|date=December 2016}}

Two good examples of collective nouns are &quot;team&quot; and &quot;government&quot;, which are both words referring to groups of (usually) people. Both &quot;team&quot; and &quot;government&quot; are [[count noun]]s (consider: &quot;one team&quot;, &quot;two teams&quot;, &quot;most teams&quot;; &quot;one government&quot;, &quot;two governments&quot;, &quot;many governments&quot;).

=== Agreement in different forms of English ===
{{Main|American and British English grammatical differences#Subject-verb agreement}}

Confusion often stems from the way that different forms of English handle [[Agreement (linguistics)|agreement]] with collective nouns—specifically, whether or not to use the '''collective singular''': the singular verb form with a collective noun. The [[plural verb]] forms are often used in [[British English]] with the singular forms of these [[count noun]]s (e.g., &quot;The team ''have'' finished the project.&quot;). Conversely, in the English language as a whole, singular verb forms can often be used with nouns ending in &quot;-s&quot; that were once considered plural (e.g., &quot;Physics ''is'' my favorite academic subject&quot;). This apparent &quot;number mismatch&quot; is a natural and logical feature of human language, and its mechanism is a subtle [[metonymy|metonymic]] shift in the concepts underlying the words.

In British English, it is generally accepted that collective nouns can take either singular or plural verb forms depending on the context and the [[metonymy|metonymic]] shift that it implies. For example, &quot;the team ''is'' in the dressing room&quot; (''[[formal agreement]]'') refers to ''the team'' as an ensemble, while &quot;the team ''are'' fighting among themselves&quot; (''[[notional agreement]]'') refers to ''the team'' as individuals. That is also the British English practice with names of countries and cities in sports contexts (e.g., &quot;[[Newcastle United F.C.|Newcastle]] ''have'' won the competition.&quot;).

In [[American English]], collective nouns almost always take singular verb forms (formal agreement). In cases that a metonymic shift would be revealed nearby, the whole sentence should be recast to avoid the metonymy. (For example, &quot;The team are fighting among themselves&quot; may become &quot;the team ''members'' are fighting among themselves&quot; or simply &quot;The team is infighting.&quot;) Collective [[proper noun]]s are usually taken as singular (&quot;[[Apple Inc.|Apple]] is expected to release a new phone this year&quot;), unless the plural is explicit in the proper noun itself, in which case it is taken as plural (&quot;The [[Green Bay Packers]] are scheduled to play the [[Minnesota Vikings]] this weekend&quot;). More explicit examples of collective proper nouns include &quot;[[General Motors]] is once again the world's largest producer of vehicles,&quot; and &quot;[[Texas Instruments]] is a large producer of [[electronics]] here,&quot; and &quot;[[British Airways]] is an airline company in Europe.&quot; Furthermore, &quot;[[American Telephone &amp; Telegraph]] is a [[telecommunications]] company in North America.&quot; Such phrases might look plural, but they are not.

=== Examples of metonymic shift ===
A good example of such a metonymic shift in the singular-to-plural direction (which, generally, occurs only in British English) is the following sentence: &quot;The team have finished the project.&quot; In that sentence, the underlying thought is of the individual members of the team working together to finish the project. Their accomplishment is collective, and the emphasis is not on their individual identities, but they are still discrete individuals; the word choice &quot;team have&quot; manages to convey both their collective and discrete identities simultaneously. A good example of such a metonymic shift in the plural-to-singular direction is the following sentence: &quot;Mathematics is my favorite academic subject.&quot; The word &quot;mathematics&quot; may have originally been plural in concept, referring to mathematic endeavors, but metonymic shift (the shift in concept from &quot;the endeavors&quot; to &quot;the whole set of endeavors&quot;) produced the usage of &quot;mathematics&quot; as a singular entity taking singular verb forms. (A true [[mass noun|mass-noun]] sense of &quot;mathematics&quot; followed naturally.)

Nominally singular pronouns can be collective nouns taking plural verbs, according to the same rules that apply to other collective nouns. For example, it is correct usage in both British English and American English usage to say: &quot;None are so fallible as those who are sure they're right.&quot; In that case, the plural verb is used because the context for &quot;none&quot; suggests more than one thing or person.&lt;ref&gt;Strunk &amp; White, The Elements of Style (4th ed., 2000), p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt;

Other examples include:

* &quot;[[Creedence Clearwater Revival]] ''was'' founded in [[El Cerrito, California]]&quot;.
* &quot;[[Nintendo]] ''is'' a [[video game]] company headquartered in Japan&quot;.

This does not, however, affect the tense later in the sentence:

* &quot;Cream ''is'' a [[psychedelic rock]] band who ''were'' primarily popular in the 1960s.

Exceptions to the rule{{which|date=March 2013}} include singular group names preceded by an article:

* &quot;The Who ''are'' a rock band from Great Britain.&quot;

This exception does not apply to artists whose name is preceded by an article, but ends in a singular:

* &quot;The Band ''is'' a band primarily performing roots rock.&quot;

Abbreviations provide other &quot;exceptions&quot; in American usage concerning plurals:

* &quot;Runs Batted In&quot; becomes &quot;RBIs&quot;. &quot;Smith had 10 RBIs in the last three games.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Garner|first=Bryan|title=Garner's Modern American Usage|year=2009|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford; New York|isbn=978-0-19-538275-4|page=638}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;Revised Statutes Annotated&quot; or RSAs.  &quot;The RSAs contain our laws.&quot;

When only the name is plural but not the object, place, or person:

* &quot;[[Decompression sickness|The bends]] ''is'' a deadly disease mostly affecting SCUBA divers.&quot;
* &quot;''[[Hot Rocks]]'' ''is'' a greatest hits compilation by [[The Rolling Stones]]&quot;

== Terms of venery ==
{{further|List of animal names}}
The tradition of using &quot;terms of venery&quot; or &quot;nouns of assembly&quot;, collective nouns that are specific to certain kinds of animals, stems from an [[Kingdom of England|English]] [[medieval hunting|hunting tradition]] of the [[Late Middle Ages]]. The fashion of a consciously developed hunting language came to England from [[medieval France|France]]. It was marked by an extensive proliferation of specialist vocabulary, applying different names to the same feature in different animals. The elements can be shown to have already been part of French and English hunting terminology by the beginning of the 14th century. In the course of the 14th century, it became a courtly fashion to extend the vocabulary, and by the 15th century, the tendency had reached exaggerated proportions.

''[[The Treatise (Walter of Bibbesworth)|The Treatise]]'', written by [[Walter of Bibbesworth]] in the mid-1200s, is the earliest source for collective nouns of animals in any European vernacular (and also the earliest source for animal noises).&lt;ref&gt;William Sayers, &quot;Animal vocalization and human polyglossia in Walter of Bibbesworth's 13th-century domestic treatise in Anglo-Norman French&quot; in Sign System Studies (Tartu, 2009) pp. 173–187&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Venerie'' of Twiti (early 14th century) distinguished three types of [[droppings]] of animals, and three different terms for [[herd]]s of animals. [[Gaston Phoebus]] (14th century) had five terms for droppings of animals, which were extended to seven in the ''Master of the Game'' (early 15th century). The focus on collective terms for groups of animals emerged in the later 15th century. Thus, a list of collective nouns in Egerton MS 1995, dated to c. 1452 under the heading of &quot;termis of venery &amp;c.&quot;, extends to 70 items,&lt;ref&gt;David Dalby, ''Lexicon of the Mediaeval German Hunt: A Lexicon of Middle High German Terms (1050–1500), Associated with the Chase, Hunting with Bows, Falconry, Trapping and Fowling'', Walter de Gruyter, 1965, {{ISBN|978-3-11-081860-4}}, p. xli.&lt;/ref&gt; and the list in the ''[[Book of Saint Albans]]'' (1486) runs to 164 items, many of which, even though introduced by &quot;the compaynys of beestys and fowlys&quot;, relate not to venery but to human groups and professions and are clearly humorous, such as &quot;a Doctryne of doctoris&quot;'', &quot;''a Sentence of Juges&quot;'', &quot;''a Fightyng of beggers&quot;'', &quot;''an uncredibilite of Cocoldis&quot;'', &quot;''a Melody of harpers&quot;'', &quot;''a Gagle of women&quot;'', &quot;''a Disworship of Scottis&quot;, etc.&lt;ref&gt;1901 facsimile reprint, E. Stock, London ([https://archive.org/stream/bokeofsaintalban00bernuoft#page/114/mode/2up pp. 115-117).]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Transactions of the Philological Society
Volume 26, Issue 3, pages 79–175, August 1909&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Book of Saint Albans'' became very popular during the 16th century and was reprinted frequently. [[Gervase Markham]] edited and commented on the list in his ''The Gentleman's Academic'', in 1595. The book's popularity had the effect of perpetuating many of these terms as part of the [[Standard English]] lexicon even if they have long ceased to have any practical application.&lt;ref name=&quot;Todd&amp;Hancock&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Todd | first = Loreto |author2=Hancock, Ian | year = 1986 | title = International English Usage | publisher = Psychology Press | pages = 133–134 | isbn = 0-415-05102-9 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=iccd5KAUnYQC&amp;pg=PA133 | accessdate = 2011-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Even in their original context of medieval venery, the terms were of the nature of [[kenning]]s, intended as a mark of erudition of the gentlemen able to use them correctly rather than for practical communication.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=An Exaltation of Larks|last=Lipton|first=James|publisher=Penguin|year=1993|isbn=978-0140170962|location=|pages=8}}&lt;/ref&gt; The popularity of the terms in the modern period has resulted in the addition of numerous lighthearted, humorous or facetious&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Harris|first=Theodore L.|title=The Literacy Dictionary|author2=Hodges, Richard E.|publisher=International Reading Association|year=1995|isbn=0-87207-138-3|page=271}}&lt;!--| accessdate = 2011-04-04--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; collective nouns.

== See also ==
;Linguistics concepts
* [[Grammatical number]]
* [[Mass noun]]
* [[Measure word]]s
* [[Plural]]
* [[Plurale tantum]]
* [[Synesis]]

;{{anchor|Lists}}Lists
* [[List of animal names]], including names for groups
* [[List of English terms of venery, by animal]]

;Interdisciplinary
* [[Social unit]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* Hodgkin, John. &quot;Proper Terms: An attempt at a rational explanation of the meanings of the Collection of Phrases in 'The Book of St Albans', 1486, entitled 'The Compaynys of beestys and fowlys' and similar lists&quot;, ''Transactions of the Philological Society 1907–1910'' Part III, pp. 1–187, Kegan, Paul, Trench &amp; Trübner &amp; Co, Ltd, London, 1909.
* Shulman, Alon. ''A Mess of Iguanas... A Whoop of Gorillas: An Amazement of Animal Facts''. Penguin. (First published Penguin 2009.) {{ISBN|978-1-84614-255-0}}.
* [[James Lipton|Lipton, James]]. ''An Exaltation of Larks, or The &quot;Veneral&quot; Game''. Penguin. (First published Grossman Publishers 1968.) (Penguin first reprint 1977 {{ISBN|0-14-004536-8}}); in 1993 it was republished in Penguin with ''The Ultimate Edition'' as part of the title with the {{ISBN|0-14-017096-0}} (paperback), {{ISBN|978-0-670-30044-0}} (hardcover)
* PatrickGeorge. ''A filth of starlings''. PatrickGeorge. (First published 2009.) {{ISBN|978-0-9562558-1-5}}.
* PatrickGeorge. ''A drove of bullocks''. PatrickGeorge. (First published 2009.) {{ISBN|978-0-9562558-0-8}}.
* Fanous, Samuel (2014). ''A Conspiracy of Ravens: a compendium of collective nouns for birds''. Oxford: Bodleian Library. {{ISBN|9781851244096}}.
* Fanous, Samuel (2015). ''A Barrel of Monkeys: a compendium of collective nouns for animals''. Oxford: Bodleian Library. {{ISBN|9781851244454}}.

==External links==
{{Wiktionary pipe|Appendix:Collective nouns|the appendix of collective nouns}}
* [http://www.chompchomp.com/terms/collectivenoun.htm Collective Nouns]
* [https://quod.lib.umich.edu/e/eebo/A16392.0001.001/1:5.6?rgn=div2;view=fulltext &quot;The companyes of bestys &amp; foules&quot; (section from the ''Book of St Albans'')]

{{lexical categories|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Nouns by type]]
[[Category:Rhetoric]]
[[Category:Grammatical number]]</text>
      <sha1>oub0k6v6og1d7avj54xv2fru5d1ka8q</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
