  <page>
    <title>Content-control software</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7144</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939038189</id>
      <parentid>938373625</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-03T23:39:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2601:703:200:990:CDBE:A0F0:49F6:3C56</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Content-control software''', commonly referred to as an '''Internet filter''', is [[software]] that restricts or controls the content an Internet user is capable to access, especially when utilised to restrict material delivered over the [[Internet]] via the [[World Wide Web|Web]], [[e-mail]], or other means. Content-control software determines what content will be available or be blocked.

Such restrictions can be applied at various levels: a government can attempt to apply them nationwide (see [[Internet censorship]]), or they can, for example, be applied by an [[ISP]] to its clients, by an employer to its personnel, by a school to its students, by a library to its visitors, by a parent to a child's computer, or by an [[self-censorship|individual user to their own computer]].

The motive is often to prevent access to content which the computer's owner(s) or other authorities may consider objectionable. When imposed without the consent of the user, content control can be characterised as a form of internet censorship. Some content-control software includes time control functions that empowers parents to set the amount of time that child may spend accessing the Internet or playing games or other computer activities.

In some countries, such software is ubiquitous. [[Censorship in Cuba#Internet|In Cuba]], if a computer user at a government-controlled [[Internet cafe]] types certain words, the [[word processor program|word processor]] or [[web browser]] is automatically closed, and a &quot;state security&quot; warning is given.&lt;ref name=&quot;cubaonline&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://rsf.org/sites/default/files/rapport_gb_md_1.pdf|title=Going online in Cuba: Internet under surveillance|publisher=Reporters Without Borders|year=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Terminology==
The term &quot;content control&quot; is used on occasion by [[CNN]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://edition.cnn.com/2005/WORLD/asiapcf/04/27/eyeonchina.internet/ |title=Young, angry ... and wired - May 3, 2005 |publisher=Edition.cnn.com |date=3 May 2005 |accessdate=25 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Playboy]]'' magazine,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.multichannel.com/policy/playboy-preaches-control/12883 |title=Playboy Preaches Control |first=R. Thomas |last=Umstead |newspaper=Multichannel News |date=20 May 2006 |accessdate=25 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; the ''[[San Francisco Chronicle]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/news/archive/2002/10/25/financial1400EDT0155.DTL&amp;type=printable |title=Web sites go blank to protest strict new Internet law |website=[[San Francisco Chronicle|sfgate.com]] |publisher=[[Associated Press]] |first=Daniel |last=Woolls |date=October 25, 2002 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20030708220938/http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=%2Fnews%2Farchive%2F2002%2F10%2F25%2Ffinancial1400EDT0155.DTL&amp;type=printable |archivedate=8 July 2003 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[The New York Times]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Bickerton |first=Derek |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1997/11/30/books/digital-dreams.html |title=Digital Dreams - The |newspaper=New York Times |date=30 November 1997 |accessdate=25 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, several other terms, including &quot;content filtering software&quot;, &quot;filtering proxy servers&quot;, &quot;secure web gateways&quot;, &quot;censorware&quot;, &quot;content security and control&quot;, &quot;web filtering software&quot;, &quot;content-censoring software&quot;, and &quot;content-blocking software&quot;, are often used. &quot;Nannyware&quot; has also been used in both product marketing and by the media. Industry research company [[Gartner]] uses &quot;secure web gateway&quot; (SWG) to describe the market segment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gartner&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gartner.com/it-glossary/secure-web-gateway/ |title=IT Glossary: Secure Web Gateway |publisher=[[Gartner]] |accessdate=27 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Companies that make products that selectively block Web sites do not refer to these products as censorware, and prefer terms such as &quot;Internet filter&quot; or &quot;URL Filter&quot;; in the specialized case of software specifically designed to allow parents to monitor and restrict the access of their children, &quot;parental control software&quot; is also used. Some products log all sites that a user accesses and rates them based on content type for reporting to an &quot;accountability partner&quot; of the person's choosing, and the term [[accountability software]] is used. Internet filters, parental control software, and/or accountability software may also be combined into one product.

Those critical of such software, however, use the term &quot;censorware&quot; freely: consider the Censorware Project, for example.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://censorware.net/ |title=Censorware Project |publisher=censorware.net |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150620042654/http://www.censorware.net/ |archivedate=20 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The use of the term &quot;censorware&quot; in editorials criticizing makers of such software is widespread and covers many different varieties and applications: [[Xeni Jardin]] used the term in a 9 March 2006 editorial in ''The New York Times'' when discussing the use of American-made filtering software to suppress content in China; in the same month a high school student used the term to discuss the deployment of such software in his school district.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://159.54.226.83/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060319/COLUMN0203/603190309/1064 |title=159.54.226.83/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20060319/COLUMN0203/603190309/1064 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071019020114/http://159.54.226.83/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=%2F20060319%2FCOLUMN0203%2F603190309%2F1064 |archivedate=19 October 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://sethf.com/anticensorware/hearing_dc.php |title=DMCA 1201 Exemption Transcript, April 11 - Censorware |publisher=Sethf.com |date=11 April 2003 |accessdate=25 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In general, outside of editorial pages as described above, traditional newspapers do not use the term &quot;censorware&quot; in their reporting, preferring instead to use less overtly controversial terms such as &quot;content filter&quot;, &quot;content control&quot;, or &quot;web filtering&quot;; ''The New York Times'' and the ''[[Wall Street Journal]]'' both appear to follow this practice. On the other hand, Web-based newspapers such as [[CNET]] use the term in both editorial and journalistic contexts, for example &quot;Windows Live to Get Censorware.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.techbeta.org/news/windows-live-to-get-censorware/ |title=Windows Live to get censorware - ZDNet.co.uk |publisher=News.zdnet.co.uk |date=14 March 2006 |accessdate=25 October 2009 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081205010436/http://www.techbeta.org/news/windows-live-to-get-censorware/ |archive-date=5 December 2008 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Types of filtering==
Filters can be implemented in many different ways: by software on a personal computer, via network infrastructure such as [[proxy server]]s, [[Domain Name System|DNS]] servers, or [[Firewall (computing)|firewall]]s that provide Internet access. No solution provides complete coverage, so most companies deploy a mix of technologies to achieve the proper content control in line with their policies.

;Browser based filters
: Browser based content filtering solution is the most lightweight solution to do the content filtering, and is implemented via a third party [[browser extension]].

;E-mail filters
: E-mail filters act on information contained in the mail body, in the mail headers such as sender and subject, and e-mail attachments to classify, accept, or reject messages. [[Bayesian spam filtering|Bayesian filters]], a type of statistical filter, are commonly used. Both client and server based filters are available.

;Client-side filters
:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nap.edu/netsafekids/pro_fm_filter.html |title=Client-side filters |work=NetSafekids |publisher=National Academy of Sciences |year=2003 |accessdate=24 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; This type of filter is installed as software on each computer where filtering is required.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://windows.microsoft.com/en-us/windows-vista/Protecting-your-kids-with-Family-Safety|title=Protecting Your Kids with Family Safety|date=|accessdate=10 July 2012|publisher=[[Microsoft]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This filter can typically be managed, disabled or uninstalled by anyone who has administrator-level privileges on the system.

;Content-limited (or filtered) ISPs
:Content-limited (or filtered) ISPs are Internet service providers that offer access to only a set portion of Internet content on an opt-in or a mandatory basis. Anyone who subscribes to this type of service is subject to restrictions. The type of filters can be used to implement government,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pam2011.gatech.edu/papers/pam2011--Xu.pdf|title=Internet Censorship in China: Where Does the Filtering Occur?|first=Xueyang|last=Xu|first2=Z. Morley|last2=Mao|first3=J. Alex|last3=Halderman|publisher=[[University of Michigan]]|date=5 Jan 2011|access-date=10 July 2012|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120324172922/http://pam2011.gatech.edu/papers/pam2011--Xu.pdf|archive-date=24 March 2012|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; regulatory&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/technology/broadband/9242729/The-Pirate-Bay-cut-off-from-millions-of-Virgin-Media-customers.html |title=The Pirate Bay cut off from millions of Virgin Media customers |author= Christopher Williams |date=3 May 2012 |accessdate=8 May 2012 |work=The Telegraph}}&lt;/ref&gt; or parental control over subscribers.

;Network-based filtering
:This type of filter is implemented at the [[transport layer]] as a [[transparent proxy]], or at the [[application layer]] as a [[proxy server|web proxy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.websense.com/content/support/library/web/v75/wcg_deploy/WCG_Deploy.1.3.aspx|title=Explicit and Transparent Proxy Deployments|publisher=Websense|accessdate=30 March 2012|year=2010|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120418150020/http://www.websense.com/content/support/library/web/v75/wcg_deploy/WCG_Deploy.1.3.aspx|archivedate=18 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Filtering software may include [[data loss prevention software|data loss prevention]] functionality to filter outbound as well as inbound information.  All users are subject to the access policy defined by the institution.  The filtering can be customized, so a school district's high school library can have a different filtering profile than the district's junior high school library.

;DNS-based filtering
:This type of filtering is implemented at the DNS layer and attempts to prevent lookups for domains that do not fit within a set of policies (either parental control or company rules). Multiple free [[Public_recursive_name_server|public DNS services]] offer filtering options as part of their services.

;Search-engine filters
:Many search engines, such as Google and Bing offer users the option of turning on a safety filter. When this safety filter is activated, it filters out the inappropriate links from all of the search results. If users know the actual URL of a website that features explicit or adult content, they have the ability to access that content without using a search engine. Some providers offer child-oriented versions of their engines that permit only children friendly websites.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nap.edu/netsafekids/pro_fm_filter.html |title=Filtering |work=NetSafekids |publisher=National Academy of Sciences |year=2003 |accessdate=22 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reasons for filtering==
{{main article|Internet censorship}}
The Internet does not intrinsically provide content blocking, and therefore there is much content on the Internet that is considered unsuitable for children, given that much content is given certifications as suitable for adults only, e.g. 18-rated games and movies.

[[Internet service provider]]s (ISPs) that block material containing [[pornography]], or controversial religious, political, or news-related content en route are often utilized by parents who do not permit their children to access content not conforming to [[indoctrination|their personal beliefs]]. Content filtering software can, however, also be used to block [[malware]] and other content that is or contains hostile, intrusive, or annoying material including [[adware]], [[Spam (electronic)|spam]], [[computer virus]]es, [[computer worm|worms]], [[Trojan horse (computing)|trojan horses]], and [[spyware]].

Most content control software is marketed to organizations or parents. It is, however, also marketed on occasion to facilitate self-censorship, for example by people struggling with addictions to [[online pornography]], gambling, chat rooms, etc. Self-censorship software may also be utilised by some in order to avoid viewing content they consider immoral, inappropriate, or simply distracting.  A number of [[accountability software]] products are marketed as ''self-censorship'' or ''accountability software''. These are often promoted by religious media and at [[place of worship|religious gatherings]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.urbanministry.org/wiki/accountability-software |title=Accountability Software: Accountability and Monitoring Software Reviews |work=TechMission, Safe Families |publisher=UrbanMinistry.org |date= |accessdate=25 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Criticism ==

===Filtering errors===

==== Overblocking ====
Utilizing a filter that is overly zealous at filtering content, or mislabels content not intended to be censored can result in over blocking, or over-censoring. Over blocking can filter out material that should be acceptable under the filtering policy in effect, for example health related information may unintentionally be filtered along with [[pornography|porn]]-related material because of the [[Scunthorpe problem]].  Filter administrators may prefer to err on the side of caution by accepting over blocking to prevent any risk of access to sites that they determine to be undesirable.  Content-control software was mentioned as blocking access to Beaver College before its name change to [[Arcadia University]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=00/03/01/2230240&amp;tid=146 |title=Web Censors Prompt College To Consider Name Change  |publisher=Slashdot |date=2 March 2000 |accessdate=22 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another example was the filtering of [[Horniman Museum]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theregister.co.uk/2004/10/08/horniman_museum_filtered/ |title=Porn filters have a field day on Horniman Museum |author=Lester Haines |date=8 October 2004 |newspaper=The Register}}&lt;/ref&gt; As well, over-blocking may encourage users to bypass the filter entirely.

==== Underblocking ====
Whenever new information is uploaded to the Internet, filters can under block, or under-censor, content if the parties responsible for maintaining the filters do not update them quickly and accurately, and a blacklisting rather than a whitelisting filtering policy is in place.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.stat.berkeley.edu/~stark/Preprints/filter07.pdf |title=The Effectiveness of Internet Content Filters |first=Philip B. |last=Stark |publisher=[[University of California, Berkeley]] |date=10 November 2007 |accessdate=22 November 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Morality and opinion===
Many&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.arnnet.com.au/article/340550/microsoft_google_yahoo_speak_isp_filter_consultation/?fp=16&amp;fpid=1 |title=Microsoft, Google and Yahoo! speak out in ISP filter consultation
 |first=Spandas |last=Lui |date=23 March 2010 |publisher=arnnet.com |accessdate=22 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; would not be satisfied with government filtering viewpoints on moral or political issues, agreeing that this could become support for [[propaganda]]. Many&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/technology/8517829.stm | work=BBC News | title=Google and Yahoo raise doubts over planned net filters | date=16 February 2010 | accessdate=30 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; would also find it unacceptable that an ISP, whether by law or by the ISP's own choice, should deploy such software without allowing the users to disable the filtering for their own connections. In the United States, the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution]] has been cited in calls to criminalise forced internet censorship. (See [[Content-control software#Legal actions|section below]])

Without adequate governmental supervision, content-filtering software could enable private companies to censor as they please. (See [[#Religious or political censorship|Religious or political censorship]], below). Government utilisation or encouragement of content-control software is a component of [[Internet Censorship]] (not to be confused with [[Computer and network surveillance|Internet Surveillance]], in which content is monitored and not necessarily restricted). The governments of countries such as [[Internet Censorship in China|the People's Republic of China]], and [[Internet censorship in Cuba|Cuba]] are current examples of countries in which this ethically controversial activity is alleged to have taken place.

===Legal actions===
In 1998, a United States federal district court in Virginia ruled ([[Loudoun v. Board of Trustees of the Loudoun County Library]]) that the imposition of mandatory filtering in a public library violates the First Amendment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tomwbell.com/NetLaw/Ch04/Loudoun.html |title=Mainstream Loudon v. Board of Trustees of the Loudon County Library, 24 F. Supp. 2d 552 (E.D. Va. 1998) |publisher=Tomwbell.com |date= |accessdate=25 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1996 the US Congress passed the [[Communications Decency Act]], banning indecency on the Internet. Civil liberties groups challenged the law under the First Amendment, and in 1997 the [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] ruled in their favor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/521/844/case.html |title=Reno v. American Civil Liberties Union - 521 U.S. 844 (1997) |work=U.S. Reports |date=26 June 1997 |publisher=Justia.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Part of the civil liberties argument, especially from groups like the [[Electronic Frontier Foundation]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.eff.org/legal-victories|title=Legal Victories|website=Electronic Frontier Foundation|language=en|access-date=2019-02-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; was that parents who wanted to block sites could use their own content-filtering software, making government involvement unnecessary&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.justice.gov/criminal-ceos/children-internet-safety|title=Children Internet Safety|date=2015-05-26|website=www.justice.gov|language=en|access-date=2019-02-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

In the late 1990s, groups such as the Censorware Project began reverse-engineering the content-control software and decrypting the blacklists to determine what kind of sites the software blocked. This led to legal action alleging violation of the &quot;Cyber Patrol&quot; [[EULA|license agreement]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://w2.eff.org/legal/cases/Microsystems_v_Scandinavia_Online/?f=20000316_verif_complaint.html |title=Microsystems v Scandinavia Online, Verified Complaint |work=Civil No. 00CV10488, United States District Court, District of Massachusetts |author=Attorneys for Microsystems Software, Inc. and Mattel, Inc. |publisher=Electronic Frontier Foundation |date=15 March 2000 |accessdate=25 October 2009 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090212065108/http://w2.eff.org/legal/cases/Microsystems_v_Scandinavia_Online/?f=20000316_verif_complaint.html |archive-date=12 February 2009 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; They discovered that such tools routinely blocked unobjectionable sites while also failing to block intended targets.

Some content-control software companies responded by claiming that their filtering criteria were backed by intensive manual checking. The companies' opponents argued, on the other hand, that performing the necessary checking would require resources greater than the companies possessed and that therefore their claims were not valid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www7.nationalacademies.org/itas/whitepaper_1.html |title=Electronic Frontier Foundation White Paper 1 for NRC project on Tools and Strategies for Protecting Kids from Pornography and Their Applicability to Other Inappropriate Internet Content |author1=Seth Finkelstein |author2=Lee Tien |lastauthoramp=yes |publisher=National Academy of Sciences |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20060419190143/http://www7.nationalacademies.org/itas/whitepaper_1.html |archivedate=19 April 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Motion Picture Association]] successfully obtained a UK ruling enforcing ISPs to use content-control software to prevent [[copyright infringement]] by their subscribers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Sky, Virgin Media Asked to Block Piracy Site Newzbin2|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-15653434 |work=[[BBC News]] |date=9 November 2011  |accessdate=26 March 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Religious, anti-religious, and political censorship ===
Many types of content-control software have been shown to block sites based on the religious and political leanings of the company owners. Examples include blocking several religious sites&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Kelly Wilson |url=http://hometown.aol.com/Mjolnir13/test.htm |title=Hometown Has Been Shutdown - People Connection Blog: AIM Community Network |publisher=Hometown.aol.com |date=2008-11-06 |accessdate=2009-10-25 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080509055959/http://hometown.aol.com/Mjolnir13/test.htm |archive-date=2008-05-09 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://members.tripod.com/~Trifold/NOTICE.html |title=Notice!! |publisher=Members.tripod.com |date= |accessdate=2009-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; (including the Web site of the Vatican), many political sites, and homosexuality-related sites.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.glaad.org/media/archive_detail.php?id=103&amp; |title=www.glaad.org/media/archive_detail.php?id=103&amp; |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080607224912/http://www.glaad.org/media/archive_detail.php?id=103&amp; |archivedate=June 7, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; ''X-Stop'' was shown to block sites such as the [[Quaker Oats Company|Quaker]] web site, the [[National Journal of Sexual Orientation Law]], [[The Heritage Foundation]], and parts of [[The Ethical Spectacle]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.spectacle.org/cs/burt.html |title=The Mind of a Censor |publisher=Spectacle.org |date= |accessdate=2009-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; CYBERsitter blocks out sites like [[National Organization for Women]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.spectacle.org/alert/peace.html |title=CYBERsitter: Where do we not want you to go today? |publisher=Spectacle.org |date= |accessdate=2009-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nancy Willard, an academic researcher and attorney, pointed out that many U.S. public schools and libraries use the same filtering software that many Christian organizations use.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.csriu.org/onlinedocs/documents/religious2.html |title=See: Filtering Software: The Religious Connection |publisher=Csriu.org |accessdate=2009-10-25 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080705102418/http://csriu.org/onlinedocs/documents/religious2.html |archive-date=2008-07-05 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; Cyber Patrol, a product developed by The Anti-Defamation League and Mattel's The Learning Company,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adl.org/presrele/mise_00/3081-00.asp |title=See: ADL and The Learning Company Develop Educational Software |publisher=adl.org |accessdate=2011-08-26 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110209112430/http://www.adl.org/PresRele/Mise_00/3081-00.asp |archive-date=2011-02-09 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; has been found to block not only political sites it deems to be engaging in 'hate speech' but also human rights web sites, such as Amnesty International's web page about Israel and gay-rights web sites, such as glaad.org.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.peacefire.org/censorware/Cyber_Patrol/ |title=See: Cyber Patrol Examined |publisher=peacefire.org |date= |accessdate=2011-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Content labeling==
Content labeling may be considered another form of content-control software. In 1994, the [[Internet Content Rating Association]] (ICRA) &amp;mdash; now part of the [[Family Online Safety Institute]] &amp;mdash; developed a content rating system for online content providers. Using an online questionnaire a webmaster describes the nature of their web content. A small file is generated that contains a condensed, computer readable digest of this description that can then be used by content filtering software to block or allow that site.

ICRA labels come in a variety of formats.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fosi.org/icra/#tech |title=ICRA: Technical standards used |accessdate=2008-07-04 |publisher=FOSI |date= }}&lt;/ref&gt; These include the World Wide Web Consortium's [[Resource Description Framework]] (RDF) as well as [[Platform for Internet Content Selection]] (PICS) labels used by [[Microsoft]]'s [[Internet Explorer]] Content Advisor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.microsoft.com/windows/ie/ie6/using/howto/security/contentadv/config.mspx |title=Browse the Web with Internet Explorer 6 and Content Advisor |accessdate= |publisher=Microsoft |date=March 26, 2003 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

ICRA labels are an example of self-labeling. Similarly, in 2006 the [[Association of Sites Advocating Child Protection (ASACP)]] initiated the Restricted to Adults self-labeling initiative. ASACP members were concerned that various forms of legislation being proposed in the [[United States]] were going to have the effect of forcing adult companies to label their content.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.asacp.org/page.php?content=news&amp;item=511 |title=ASACP Participates in Financial Coalition Against Child Pornography  |accessdate=2008-07-04 |publisher= |date=November 20, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The RTA label, unlike ICRA labels, does not require a webmaster to fill out a questionnaire or sign up to use. Like ICRA the RTA label is free. Both labels are recognized by a [[List of Content Control Software|wide variety of content-control software]].

The [[Voluntary Content Rating]] (VCR) system was devised by [[Solid Oak Software]] for their [[CYBERsitter]] filtering software, as an alternative to the PICS system, which some critics deemed too complex. It employs [[HTML]] [[meta element|metadata]] tags embedded within web page documents to specify the type of content contained in the document. Only two levels are specified, ''mature'' and ''adult'', making the specification extremely simple.

==Use in public libraries==

===United States===
The use of Internet filters or content-control software varies widely in public libraries in the United States, since Internet use policies are established by the local library board. Many libraries adopted Internet filters after Congress conditioned the receipt of universal service discounts on the use of Internet filters through the [[Children's Internet Protection Act]] (CIPA). Other libraries do not install content control software, believing that acceptable use policies and educational efforts address the issue of children accessing [[age-inappropriate]] content while preserving adult users' right to freely access information. Some libraries use Internet filters on computers used by children only. Some libraries that employ content-control software allow the software to be deactivated on a case-by-case basis on application to a librarian; libraries that are subject to CIPA are required to have a policy that allows adults to request that the filter be disabled without having to explain the reason for their request.

Many legal scholars believe that a number of legal cases, in particular ''[[Reno v. American Civil Liberties Union]]'', established that the use of content-control software in libraries is a violation of the First Amendment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.spectacle.org/cs/library.bak |title=Purchase of blocking software by public libraries is unconstitutional |accessdate= |last=Wallace |first=Jonathan D. |date=November 9, 1997 |publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Children's Internet Protection Act [CIPA] and the June 2003 case ''[[United States v. American Library Association]]'' found CIPA constitutional as a condition placed on the receipt of federal funding, stating that First Amendment concerns were dispelled by the law's provision that allowed adult library users to have the filtering software disabled, without having to explain the reasons for their request. The plurality decision left open a future &quot;as-applied&quot; Constitutional challenge, however.

In November 2006, a lawsuit was filed against the North Central Regional Library District (NCRL) in Washington State for its policy of refusing to disable restrictions upon requests of adult patrons, but CIPA was not challenged in that matter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.aclu-wa.org/detail.cfm?id=557 |title=ACLU Suit Seeks Access to Information on Internet for Library Patrons |publisher=ACLU of Washington |date=November 16, 2006 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061205220253/http://www.aclu-wa.org/detail.cfm?id=557 |archive-date=December 5, 2006 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2010, the Washington State Supreme Court provided an opinion after it was asked to certify a question referred by the United States District Court for the Eastern District of Washington: “Whether a public library, consistent with Article I, § 5 of the Washington Constitution, may filter Internet access for all patrons without disabling Web sites containing constitutionally-protected speech upon the request of an adult library patron.” The Washington State Supreme Court ruled that NCRL’s internet filtering policy did not violate Article I, Section 5 of the Washington State Constitution. The Court said: “It appears to us that NCRL’s filtering policy is reasonable and accords with its mission and these policies and is viewpoint neutral. It appears that no article I, section 5 content-based violation exists in this case. NCRL’s essential mission is to promote reading and lifelong learning. As NCRL maintains, it is reasonable to impose restrictions on Internet access in order to maintain an environment that is conducive to study and contemplative thought.” The case returned to federal court.

In March 2007, Virginia passed a law similar to CIPA that requires public libraries receiving state funds to use content-control software. Like CIPA, the law requires libraries to disable filters for an adult library user when requested to do so by the user.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Michael |last=Sluss |title=Kaine signs library bill: The legislation requires public libraries to block obscene material with Internet filters |url=http://www.roanoke.com/politics/wb/wb/xp-109919 |newspaper=The Roanoke Times |date=March 23, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Australia===
The Australian Internet Safety Advisory Body has information about &quot;practical advice on Internet safety, parental control and filters for the protection of children, students and families&quot; that also includes public libraries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pcw.vic.edu.au/Our%20School/Parents%20Guide%20to%20Internet%20Safety.pdf |title=NetAlert: Parents Guide to Internet Safety |publisher=Australian Communications and Media Authority |date=2 August 2007 |accessdate=24 June 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130419184113/http://www.pcw.vic.edu.au/Our%20School/Parents%20Guide%20to%20Internet%20Safety.pdf |archive-date=19 April 2013 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

NetAlert, the software made available free of charge by the Australian government, was allegedly cracked by a 16-year-old student, Tom Wood, less than a week after its release in August 2007. Wood supposedly bypassed the $84 million filter in about half an hour to highlight problems with the government's approach to Internet content filtering.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.smh.com.au/news/National/Teenager-cracks-govts-84m-porn-filter/2007/08/25/1187462562907.html |title=Teenager cracks govt's $84m porn filter |agency=Australian Associated Press (AAP) |work=Sydney Morning Herald |publisher=Fairfax Digital |date=25 August 2007 |accessdate=24 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Australian Government has introduced legislation that requires ISP's to &quot;restrict access to age restricted content (commercial MA15+ content and R18+ content) either hosted in Australia or provided from Australia&quot; that was due to commence from 20 January 2008, known as [[Cleanfeed (content blocking system)|Cleanfeed]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.acma.gov.au/webwr/_assets/main/lib310563/ras_declaration_2007.pdf |title=Restricted Access Systems Declaration 2007 |publisher=Australian Communications and Media Authority (ACMA) |year=2007 |accessdate=24 June 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120324222418/http://acma.gov.au/webwr/_assets/main/lib310563/ras_declaration_2007.pdf |archive-date=24 March 2012 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cleanfeed is a proposed mandatory ISP level content filtration system. It was proposed by the [[Kim Beazley|Beazley]] led [[Australian Labor Party]] opposition in a 2006 press release, with the intention of protecting children who were vulnerable due to claimed parental computer illiteracy. It was announced on 31 December 2007 as a policy to be implemented by the [[Kevin Rudd|Rudd]] ALP government, and initial tests in [[Tasmania]] have produced a 2008 report. Cleanfeed is funded in the current budget, and is moving towards an Expression of Interest for live testing with ISPs in 2008. Public opposition and criticism have emerged, led by the [[Electronic Frontiers Australia|EFA]] and gaining irregular mainstream media attention, with a majority of Australians reportedly &quot;strongly against&quot; its implementation.&lt;ref name=&quot;nocleanfeed.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://nocleanfeed.com/learn.html |title=Learn - No Clean Feed - Stop Internet Censorship in Australia |publisher=Electronic Frontiers Australia |accessdate=25 October 2009 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100107170517/http://nocleanfeed.com/learn.html |archive-date=7 January 2010 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; Criticisms include its expense, inaccuracy (it will be impossible to ensure only illegal sites are blocked) and the fact that it will be compulsory, which can be seen as an intrusion on free speech rights.&lt;ref name=&quot;nocleanfeed.com&quot;/&gt; Another major criticism point has been that although the filter is claimed to stop certain materials, the underground rings dealing in such materials will not be affected. The filter might also provide a false sense of security for parents, who might supervise children less while using the Internet, achieving the exact opposite effect.{{original research inline|date=June 2013}} Cleanfeed is a responsibility of [[Stephen Conroy|Senator Conroy's]] portfolio.

===Denmark===
In Denmark it is stated policy that it will &quot;prevent inappropriate Internet sites from being accessed from children's libraries across Denmark.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.prnewswire.com/cgi-bin/stories.pl?ACCT=104&amp;STORY=/www/story/07-27-2006/0004404991&amp;EDATE= |title=Danish Ministry of Culture Chooses SonicWALL CMS 2100 Content Filter to Keep Children's Libraries Free of Unacceptable Material |publisher=Prnewswire.com |date= |accessdate=2009-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;'It is important that every library in the country has the opportunity to protect children against pornographic material when they are using library computers. It is a main priority for me as Culture Minister to make sure children can surf the net safely at libraries,' states Brian Mikkelsen in a press-release of the Danish Ministry of Culture.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.saferinternet.org/ww/en/pub/insafe/news/articles/0606/dk.htm |title=Danish Minister of Culture offers Internet filters to libraries |publisher=Saferinternet.org |date= |accessdate=2009-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== United Kingdom ===
{{#section:Web blocking in the United Kingdom|lib}}

== Bypassing filters ==
{{Main article |Internet censorship circumvention}}

Content filtering in general can &quot;be bypassed entirely by tech-savvy individuals.&quot; Blocking content on a device &quot;[will not]...guarantee that users won't eventually be able to find a way around the filter.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;techsoup&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cityvision.edu/wiki/understanding-content-filtering-faq-nonprofits |title=Understanding Content Filtering: An FAQ for Nonprofits |last=Satterfield |first=Brian |date=4 June 2007 |publisher=Techsoup.org |accessdate=24 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some software may be bypassed successfully by using alternative protocols such as [[File Transfer Protocol|FTP]] or [[telnet]] or [[HTTPS]], conducting searches in a different language, using a [[proxy server]] or a circumventor such as [[Psiphon]]. Also cached web pages returned by Google or other searches could bypass some controls as well. Web syndication services may provide alternate paths for content. Some of the more poorly designed programs can be shut down by killing their processes: for example, in [[Microsoft Windows]] through the Windows [[Task Manager]], or in [[Mac OS X]] using Force Quit or [[Activity Monitor (macOS)|Activity Monitor]]. Numerous workarounds and counters to workarounds from content-control software creators exist.
[[Google]] services are often blocked by filters, but these may most often be bypassed by using ''https://'' in place of ''http://'' since content filtering software is not able to interpret content under secure connections (in this case SSL).

An encrypted [[VPN]] can be used as means of bypassing content control software, especially if the content control software is installed on an Internet gateway or firewall.

There many other ways in which to bypass a content control filter that include translation sites, establishing a remote connection with another computer that has no content control filter on it and altering the proxy settings of the browser.&lt;ref name=&quot;comdodome&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://cdome.comodo.com/bypass-avoid-internet-filters.php |title=Is It Possible To Easily Avoid Internet Filters? |last=|first=|date=4 June 2007 |publisher=comodo.com |accessdate=2 October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Products and services==
{{See also|List of content-control software|Category:Content-control software}}
Some ISPs offer [[parental control]] options. Some offer security software which includes parental controls. [[Mac OS X v10.4]] offers parental controls for several applications ([[Mail (OS X)|Mail]], [[Macintosh Finder|Finder]], [[iChat]], [[Safari (web browser)|Safari]] &amp; [[Dictionary (software)|Dictionary]]). Microsoft's [[Windows Vista]] operating system also includes content-control software.

Content filtering technology exists in two major forms: [[Application-level gateway|application gateway]] or [[Deep packet inspection|packet inspection]]. For HTTP access the application gateway is called a web-proxy or just a proxy. Such web-proxies can inspect both the initial request and the returned web page using arbitrarily complex rules and will not return any part of the page to the requester until a decision is made. In addition they can make substitutions in whole or for any part of the returned result. Packet inspection filters do not initially interfere with the connection to the server but inspect the data in the connection as it goes past, at some point the filter may decide that the connection is to be filtered and it will then disconnect it by injecting a TCP-Reset or similar faked packet. The two techniques can be used together with the packet filter monitoring a link until it sees an HTTP connection starting to an IP address that has content that needs filtering. The packet filter then redirects the connection to the [[Proxy server#Intercepting proxy server|web-proxy]] which can perform detailed filtering on the website without having to pass through all unfiltered connections. This combination is [[Cleanfeed (content blocking system)|quite popular]] because it can significantly reduce the cost of the system.

Gateway-based content control software may be more difficult to bypass than desktop software as the user does not have physical access to the filtering device. However, many of the techniques in the [[Content-control software#Bypassing filters|Bypassing filters]] section still work.

==See also==
{{Wiktionary|censorware}}
*[[Adultism]]
*[[Ad filtering]]
*[[Comparison of content-control software and providers]] (incl. parental control software)
*[[Computer and network surveillance]]
*[[David Burt (filtering advocate)|David Burt]], a former librarian and advocate for content-control software
*[[Deep content inspection]]
*[[Egress filtering]], control of outbound network traffic
*[[Financial Coalition Against Child Pornography]]
*[[Internet censorship]]
*[[Internet censorship circumvention]]
*[[Internet safety]]
*[[Opposition to pornography]]
*[[Parental controls]]
*[[Peacefire]], a U.S.-based website dedicated to &quot;preserving First Amendment rights for Internet users, particularly those younger than 18&quot;
*[[Russian State Duma Bill 89417-6]] - a proposed bill that would mandate content control software
*[[Wordfilter]], generic name for scripts typically used on Internet forums or chat rooms that automatically scans users' posts or comments as they are submitted and automatically changes or censors particular words or phrases

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

{{Censorship}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Content-Control Software}}
[[Category:Content-control software| ]]
[[Category:Web browsers]]
[[Category:Internet censorship]]
[[Category:Digital rights management]]</text>
      <sha1>e3rsp7ijiqv5ecnfhkp7rzakvx5ae8c</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
