  <page>
    <title>Cairn</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7196</id>
    <revision>
      <id>927168823</id>
      <parentid>927166088</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-11-20T20:09:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Dating maintenance tags: {{Cn}}</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about|man-made stone mounds|the Australian city|Cairns|other uses|Cairn (disambiguation)}}
{{redirect|Rock pile|other uses|rockpile (disambiguation)}}
{{Refimprove|date=August 2014}}[[File:Cairn at Garvera, Surselva, Graubuenden, Switzerland.jpg|right|thumb|200px|A cairn marking a mountain summit in [[Graubünden]], [[Switzerland]] ]]
A '''cairn''' is a man-made pile (or stack) of stones. The word ''cairn'' comes from the {{lang-gd|càrn}} {{IPA-gd|ˈkʰaːrˠn̪ˠ||}} (plural {{lang|gd|càirn}} {{IPA-gd|ˈkʰaːrˠɲ||}}).&lt;ref&gt;Peter Drummond, ''Scottish Hill Names'', Scottish Mountaineering Trust (2010), {{ISBN|978-0-907521-95-2}}, page 25&lt;/ref&gt;

Cairns have been and are used for a broad variety of purposes, from prehistoric times to the present.

In [[modern time]]s, cairns are often erected as [[landmark]]s, a use they have had since [[ancient times]]. However, since [[prehistory]], they have also been built and used as [[Sepulchre|burial]] monuments; for defense and hunting; for ceremonial purposes, sometimes relating to  [[astronomy]]; to locate buried items, such as caches of food or objects; and to mark trails, among other purposes.

[[File:Cairn Northumberland and Durham.jpg|thumb|Cairn at the boundary of Counties Durham and Northumberland UK]]

Cairns are used as [[Trail blazing|trail markers]] in many parts of the world, in [[Upland (geology)|uplands]], on  [[moorland]],   on  [[Summit (topography)|mountaintops]], near [[waterway]]s and on [[sea cliff]]s, as well as in barren [[desert]]s and [[tundra]]s. They vary in size from small stone markers to entire artificial hills, and in complexity from loose conical rock piles to delicately balanced sculptures and elaborate feats of [[megalith]]ic engineering. Cairns may be painted or otherwise decorated, whether for increased visibility or for religious reasons. An ancient example is the [[inuksuk]] (plural inuksuit), used by the [[Inuit]], [[Inupiat]], [[Kalaallit]], [[Yupik peoples|Yupik]], and other peoples of the [[Arctic]] region of North America.  Inuksuit are found from [[Alaska]] to [[Greenland]]. This region, above the [[Arctic Circle]], is dominated by the tundra [[biome]] and has areas with few natural [[landmark]]s.

==Modern cairns==
[[File:Lion's Head snow.JPG|right|thumb|upright=1.2|Line of cairns used to mark the way above the treeline on [[Mount Washington (New Hampshire)|Mount Washington, New Hampshire]], US]]
Different types of cairns exist from rough piles of stones to interlocking dry stone round cylinders.  The most important cairns commonly used around the world are interlocking stone survey cairns constructed around a central survey mark about every 30&amp;nbsp;km on the tallest peaks across a nation. These physical survey mark cairn systems are the basis for national survey grids to interconnect individual land survey measurements for entire nations. On occasion these permanent interlocking stone cairns are taken down then reconstructed to re-mark measurements to increase the accuracy of the national survey grid. They can also be used in unpopulated countries as emergency location points.  In North America and Northern Europe  any type of cairn can be used to mark [[mountain bike]] and hiking trails and other cross-country [[trail blazing]], especially in mountain regions at or above the [[tree line]]. For example, the extensive trail network maintained by the DNT, the [[Norwegian Trekking Association]], extensively uses cairns in conjunction with T-painted rock faces to mark trails.  Other examples of these can be seen in the lava fields of [[Hawaii Volcanoes National Park|Volcanoes National Park]] to mark several hikes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nps.gov/havo/planyourvisit/hike_bc.htm |title=Backcountry Hikes - Hawai'i Volcanoes National Park |publisher=Nps.gov |date=2012-04-26 |accessdate=2012-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Placed at regular intervals, a series of cairns can be used to indicate a path across stony or barren terrain, even across [[glacier]]s. Such cairns are often placed at junctions or in places where the trail direction is not obvious. They may also be used to indicate an obscured danger such as a sudden drop, or a noteworthy point such as the summit of a mountain.  Most trail cairns are small, usually being a foot or less in height. However, they may be built taller so as to protrude through a layer of snow. Hikers passing by often add a stone, as a small bit of maintenance to counteract the erosive effects of severe weather. North American trail marks are sometimes called &quot;ducks&quot; or &quot;duckies&quot;, because they sometimes have a &quot;beak&quot; pointing in the direction of the route. The expression &quot;two rocks do not make a duck&quot; reminds hikers that just one rock resting upon another could be the result of accident or nature rather than intentional trail marking.

The building of cairns for recreational purposes along trails, to mark one's personal passage through the area, can result in an overabundance of rock piles. This distracts from cairns used as genuine navigational guides, and also conflicts with the [[Leave No Trace]] ethic. This ethic of outdoor practice advocates for leaving the outdoors undisturbed and in its natural condition.
[[File:Isandlwanamassgrave.JPG|left|thumb|200px|One of many cairns marking British mass graves at the site of the [[Battle of Isandlwana]] (1879), [[South Africa]]]]
Coastal cairns, or &quot;sea marks&quot;, are also common in the northern latitudes, especially in the island-strewn waters of [[Scandinavia]] and eastern [[Canada]]. Often indicated on navigation charts, they may be painted white or lit as beacons for greater visibility offshore.

Modern cairns may also be erected for historical or memorial commemoration or simply for decorative or artistic reasons. One example is a series of many cairns marking British soldiers' [[mass graves]] at the site of the [[Battle of Isandlwana]], South Africa. Another is the [[Matthew Flinders]] Cairn on the side of [[Arthur's Seat, Victoria|Arthur's Seat]], a small mountain on the shores of [[Port Phillip Bay]], Australia. A large cairn, commonly referred to as &quot;the igloo&quot; by the locals, was built atop a hill next to the [[I-476]] highway in [[Radnor, Pennsylvania]] and is a part of a series of large rock sculptures initiated in 1988 to symbolize the township's [[Wales|Welsh]] heritage and to beautify the visual imagery along the highway.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.radnor.com/department/division.asp?fDD=9-108 Radnor Township website] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070820120212/http://www.radnor.com/department/division.asp?fDD=9-108 |date=2007-08-20 }}, Gateway Enhancement Strategy.&lt;/ref&gt; Some are merely places where farmers have collected stones removed from a field. These can be seen in the [[Catskill Mountains]], [[North America]] where there is a strong Scottish heritage, and may also represent places where livestock were lost. In locales exhibiting fantastic rock formations, such as the [[Grand Canyon]], tourists often construct simple cairns in reverence of the larger counterparts.&lt;ref&gt;[[:commons:File:Cairns at Grand Canyon North Rim 2013.jpg]]{{Better source|date=December 2016|reason=[[WP:CIRCULAR]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; By contrast, cairns may have a strong aesthetic purpose, for example in the art of [[Andy Goldsworthy]].

==History==
{{Clear}}

===Europe===
The building of cairns for various purposes goes back into [[prehistory]] in [[Eurasia]], ranging in size from small rock sculptures to substantial man-made hills of stone (some built on top of larger, natural hills). The latter are often relatively massive [[Bronze Age]] or earlier structures which, like kistvaens and [[dolmen]]s, frequently contain burials; they are comparable to [[Tumulus|tumuli]] ([[kurgan]]s), but of stone construction instead of [[Earthworks (engineering)|earthworks]]. ''Cairn'' originally could more broadly refer to various types of hills and natural stone piles, but today is used exclusively of artificial ones.
[[File:Cairn Gavrinis exterieur.jpg|thumb|Cairn of the [[Neolithic]]-era [[passage grave]] on [[Gavrinis]] island, [[Brittany]]]]
The word ''cairn'' derives from [[Scots language|Scots]] {{lang|gd|cairn}} (with the same meaning), in turn from [[Scottish Gaelic]] {{lang|gd|càrn}}, which is essentially the same as the corresponding words in other native [[Celtic language]]s of [[Great Britain|Britain]], [[Ireland]] and [[Brittany]], including [[Welsh language|Welsh]] {{lang|cy|carn}} (and {{lang|cy|carnedd}}), [[Breton language|Breton]] {{lang|br|karn}}, [[Irish language|Irish]] {{lang|ga|carn}}, and [[Cornish language|Cornish]] {{lang|kw|karn}} or {{lang|kw|carn}}.  Cornwall ({{lang|kw|Kernow}}) itself may actually be named after the cairns that dot its landscape, such as Cornwall's highest point, [[Brown Willy Cairns|Brown Willy Summit Cairn]], a 5&amp;nbsp;m (16&amp;nbsp;ft) high and 24&amp;nbsp;m (79&amp;nbsp;ft) diameter mound atop [[Brown Willy]] hill in [[Bodmin Moor]], an area with many ancient cairns.  Burial cairns and other [[megalith]]s are the subject of a variety of legends and folklore throughout Britain and Ireland. In [[Scotland]], it is traditional to carry a stone up from the bottom of a hill to place on a cairn at its top. In such a fashion, cairns would grow ever larger. An old Scottish Gaelic blessing is {{lang|gd|Cuiridh mi clach air do chàrn}}, &quot;I'll put a stone on your stone&quot;.  In Highland folklore it is recounted that before Highland clans fought in a battle, each man would place a stone in a pile. Those who survived the battle returned and removed a stone from the pile. The stones that remained were built into a cairn to honour the dead. Cairns in the region were also put to vital practical use. For example, [[Dún Aonghasa]], an all-stone [[Iron Age]] Irish [[hill fort]] on [[Inishmore]] in the [[Aran Islands]], is still surrounded by small cairns and strategically placed jutting rocks, used collectively as an alternative to [[Defensive wall|defensive earthworks]] because of the [[karst]] landscape's lack of soil.
[[File:BorderPost272 - Norway and Sweden.jpg|thumb|The [[Stone Cairn (Riksrösen)|Riksrösen]] divide Norway and Sweden.]]
In [[Scandinavia]], cairns have been used for centuries as trail and sea marks, among other purposes. In [[Iceland]], cairns were often used as markers along the numerous single-file roads or paths that crisscrossed the island; many of these ancient cairns are still standing, although the paths have disappeared. In [[Norse Greenland]], cairns were used as a hunting implement, a game-driving &quot;lane&quot;, used to direct reindeer towards a [[game jump]].&lt;ref&gt;Arneborg 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

In the mythology of ancient Greece, cairns were associated with [[Hermes]], the god of overland travel. According to one legend, Hermes was put on trial by [[Hera]] for slaying her favorite servant, the monster [[Argus Panoptes|Argus]]. All of the other gods acted as a jury, and as a way of declaring their verdict they were given pebbles, and told to throw them at whichever person they deemed to be in the right, Hermes or Hera. Hermes argued so skillfully that he ended up buried under a heap of pebbles, and this was the first cairn.
In [[Croatia]], in areas of ancient [[Dalmatia]], such as [[Herzegovina]] and the [[Krajina]], they are known as ''gromila''.

In [[Portugal]] a cairn is called  a {{lang|pt|moledro}}. In a legend the moledros are enchanted soldiers, and if one stone is taken from the pile and put under a pillow, in the morning a soldier will appear for a brief moment, then will change back to a stone and magically return to the pile.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=A Genética e a Teoria da Continuidade Paleolítica aplicada à Lenda da Fundação de Portugal e Escócia Apenas Livros|year=2008|isbn=978-989-618-180-2|url=http://www.continuitas.org/texts/morais_genetica.pdf|language=pt}}&lt;/ref&gt; The cairns that mark the place where someone died or cover the graves alongside the roads where in the past people were buried are called {{lang|pt|Fiéis de Deus}}. The same name given to the stones was given to  the dead whose identity was unknown.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=SoUyAQAAMAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Diccionario+da+lingua+portugueza:+recopilado+dos+vocabularios+impressos#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=Diccionario da lingua portugueza:recopilado dos vocabularios impressos até agora, e nesta segunda edição novamente emendado, e muito accrescentado, Volume 2. pg 31 |publisher=Books.google.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2013-05-30|year=1813 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The {{lang|gl|Fieis de Deus}} or {{lang|gl|Fes de Deus}} are, in the Galician legends, spirits of the night. The word &quot;Fes&quot; or &quot;Fieis&quot; is thought to mean [[fairy]], the same root as &quot;fate&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://sli.uvigo.es/ddd/ddd_pescuda.php?pescuda=fes&amp;tipo_busca=lema ''Dicionario de Dicionarios. Corpus lexicográfico da lingua galega'']. ''Dicionario de Dicionarios''. &quot;Entienden por éstos o estas fes los espíritus nocturnos, fantasmas, espectros, etc. Acaso serán lo mismo que las fees en francés, y todo de fata.&quot; Retrieved January 26, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; (''fado''), that can take the same meaning as the proto-Celtic *bāsto-, *bāsso-, meaning &quot;death&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://en.m.wiktionary.org/wiki/b%C3%A1s}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===North and northeast Africa===
[[File:Qableh3.JPG|thumb|right|150px|Ancient cairns in [[Qa’ableh]], [[Somalia]]]]
Cairns (''taalo'') are a common feature at [[El Ayo]], [[Haylan]], [[Qa’ableh]], [[Qombo'ul]], [[Heis (town)|Heis]], [[Salweyn]] and [[Macajilayn]], among other places. Northern [[Somalia]] in general is home to a lot of such historical settlements and [[archaeological site]]s wherein are found numerous ancient ruins and buildings, many of obscure origins. However, many of these old structures have yet to be properly explored, a process which would help shed further light on local history and facilitate their preservation for posterity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hodd&quot;&gt;Michael Hodd, ''East African Handbook'', (Trade &amp; Travel Publications: 1994), p.640.&lt;/ref&gt;

Since [[Neolithic]] times, the climate of [[North Africa]] has become drier. A reminder of the [[desertification]] of the area is provided by [[megalith]]ic remains, which occur in a great variety of forms and in vast numbers in presently arid and uninhabitable wastelands: cairns (''kerkour''), [[dolmen]]s and circles like [[Stonehenge]], underground cells excavated in rock, [[Long barrow|barrows]] topped with huge slabs, and step [[pyramid]]-like mounds.

===Asia and the Pacific===
Starting in the [[Bronze Age]], burial [[cist]]s were sometimes interred into cairns, which would be situated in conspicuous positions, often on the skyline above the village of the deceased. Though most often found in the British Isles, evidence of Bronze Age cists have been found in [[Mongolia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Houle |first1=Jean-Luc |title=Bronze Age Mongolia |url=https://www.oxfordhandbooks.com/view/10.1093/oxfordhb/9780199935413.001.0001/oxfordhb-9780199935413-e-20 |website=Oxford Handbooks Online |publisher=Oxford University Press |accessdate=14 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The stones may have been thought to deter grave robbers and scavengers. Another explanation is that they were to [[Revenant (folklore)|stop the dead from rising]]. There remains a [[Judaism|Jewish]] tradition of placing small stones on a person's grave as a token of respect, though this is generally to relate the longevity of stone to the eternal nature of the soul and is not usually done in a cairn fashion. [[Stupa]]s in India and [[Tibet]] probably started out in a similar fashion, although they now generally contain the ashes of a [[Buddhism|Buddhist]] saint or [[lama]].

[[File:TallOvoo.JPG|thumb|right|200px|A Mongolian ceremonial cairn (''[[ovoo]]'')]]A traditional and often decorated, heap-formed cairn called an ''[[ovoo]]'' is made in [[Mongolia]]. It primarily serves religious purposes, and finds use in both [[Tengriism|Tengriist]] and [[Buddhism|Buddhist]] ceremonies.

In [[Hawaii]], cairns, called by the [[Hawaiian language|Hawaiian]] word {{lang|haw|ahu}} are still being built today.  Though in other cultures the cairns were typically used as trail markers and sometimes funerary sites, the ancient Hawaiians also used them as alters or security tower. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=A Cultural History of Three Traditional Hawaiian Sites on the West Coast of Hawai'i Island |url=https://www.nps.gov/parkhistory/online_books/kona/historyg.htm |website=National Parks Service |accessdate=14 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Hawaiian people are still building these cairns today, using them as the focal points for ceremonies honoring their ancestors and spirituality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=About UH Mānoa Campus’ Ahu |url=https://manoa.hawaii.edu/hshk/the-school/about-us/about-uh-manoa-campus-ahu/ |website=Hawai‘inuiākea School of Hawaiian Knowledge |publisher=Hawai‘inuiākea School of Hawaiian Knowledge |accessdate=14 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

In [[South Korea]] cairns are quite prevalent, often found along roadsides and trails, up on mountain peaks, and adjacent to Buddhist temples.  Hikers frequently add stones to existing cairns trying to get just one more on top of the pile, to bring good luck.  This tradition has its roots in the worship of San-shin, or Mountain Spirit, so often still revered in Korean culture.&lt;ref name=&quot;san&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=Spirit of the Mountains - Korea's San-Shin and Traditions of Mountain Worship| last=Mason| first=David| year=1999| page=41| publisher=Hollym International Corp.| location=Seoul, South Korea and Elizabeth, New Jersey| isbn=1-56591-107-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===The Americas===
[[File:Flag of Nunavut.svg|thumb|An inuksuk on the [[flag of Nunavut]]]]
Throughout what today are the [[continental United States]] and Canada, some [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas]] have built structures similar to cairns. In some cases these are general trail markers, and in other cases they mark game-driving &quot;lanes&quot;, such as those leading to [[buffalo jump]]s, some of which may date to 12,000 years ago.{{cn|date=November 2019}} 

Peoples from some of the Indigenous cultures of arctic North America (i.e. northern Canada, [[Alaska]] and [[Greenland]]) have built carefully constructed stone sculptures called [[Inuksuk|{{lang|iu|inuksuit|nocat=yes}} and {{lang|iu|inunnguat|nocat=yes}}]], which serve as landmarks and directional markers. The oldest of these structures are very old and pre-date [[European colonization of the Americas|contact with Europeans]]. They are iconic of the region (an {{lang|iu|inuksuk}} even features on the flag of the Canadian far-northeastern territory, [[Nunavut]]), and are increasingly used as a symbol of Canadian national identity.&lt;ref name=BBCNHSC&gt;{{cite web
 | title = British Block Cairn National Historic Site of Canada
 | url = https://www.historicplaces.ca/en/rep-reg/place-lieu.aspx?id=14944
 | website = Canada's Historic Places
 | date = December 23, 2009 | access-date = November 14, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cairns have been used throughout what is now [[Latin America]], since [[pre-Columbian]] times, to mark trails. Even today, in the [[Andes]] of [[South America]], the [[Quechuan]] peoples build cairns as part of their spiritual and religious traditions.&lt;ref name=APC&gt;{{cite web
 | title = Apachetas of Chivay
 | url = https://www.atlasobscura.com/places/apachetas-of-alto-de-chivay
 | website = Atlas Obscura
 | date = 2019
 | access-date = November 14, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear|left}}

==Anthropomorphism==
Although the practice is not common in [[Modern English language|English]], cairns are sometimes referred to by their [[Anthropomorphism|anthropomorphic]] qualities. In [[German language|German]] and [[Dutch language|Dutch]], a cairn is known as {{lang|de|Steinmann}} and {{lang|nl|steenman}} respectively, meaning literally &quot;stone man&quot;.  A form of the [[Inuit]] {{lang|iu|[[inuksuk]]}} is also meant to represent a human figure, and is called an {{lang|iu|inunguak}} (&quot;imitation of a person&quot;). In Italy, especially the [[Italian Alps]], a cairn is an {{lang|it|ometto}}, or a &quot;small man&quot;.
&lt;!--Don't need this yet: {{clear|right}}--&gt;

==Sea cairns==
[[File:Kummel Korpo 2009.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Sea mark]] in [[Finland|Finnish]] coastal waters]]
Coastal cairns called [[sea mark]]s are also common in the northern latitudes, and are placed along shores and on islands and islets. Usually painted white for improved offshore visibility, they serve as [[Navigational aid|navigation aid]]s. In [[Sweden]] they are called {{lang|sv|kummel}}, in Norway {{lang|no|varde}}, and are indicated in navigation charts and maintained as part of the nautical marking system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |url=http://portal.fma.fi/portal/page/portal/589032C37AAC7314E040B40A0A016368 |title=Legend (INT Symbology) |format=PDF |location=[[Helsinki]] |publisher=Finnish Transport Agency and Finnish Transport Safety Agency (TraFi) |work=Merenkulku.fi |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120126004546/http://portal.fma.fi/portal/page/portal/589032C37AAC7314E040B40A0A016368 |archivedate=2012-01-26 }} Three-language key to reading Finnish navigation charts.&lt;/ref&gt; Inversely, they are used on land as sea cliff warnings in rugged and hilly terrain in the foggy [[Faroe Islands]]. In the [[Maritimes|Canadian Maritimes]], cairns have been used as beacons like small [[lighthouse]]s to guide boats, as depicted in the novel ''[[The Shipping News]]''.

==Other types==
*[[Chambered cairn]]
*[[Clava cairn]]
*[[Court cairn]]
*[[Ring cairn]]
*[[Unchambered long cairn]]
*[[Clearance cairn]]

==See also==
*[[Crug (disambiguation)]]
* [[Dry stone]]
* [[Dolmen]]
* [[Hörgr]]
* [[Kerb (archaeology)]]
* [[Ovoo]]
* [[Rujm]]
* [[Seonangdang]]
* [[Stele]]
* [[Stupa]]

==References==
{{EB1911|wstitle=Cairn}}
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Cairns (rock stack landmarks)}}
{{Wikisource1911Enc|Cairn}}
{{Wiktionary|cairn}}
*[http://www.dswa.org.uk/userfiles/file/Leaflets/cairn-building.pdf Notes on Building a Cairn (pdf)], by Dave Goulder for the [http://www.dswa.org.uk/ DSWA], Dry Stone Walling Association of Great Britain. Practical notes to help those embarking on a cairn-building project.
*[http://hcn.org/articles/a-call-for-an-end-to-cairns-leave-the-stones-alone Stop the rock-stacking, High Country News' Writers on the Range opinion-editorial article, by Robyn Martin], suggesting folks stop  building &quot;ego cairns.&quot;

{{Prehistoric technology}}

[[Category:Artificial hills]]
[[Category:Monument types]]
[[Category:Stone buildings]]
[[Category:Archaeology of death]]
[[Category:Burial monuments and structures]]
[[Category:Death customs]]
[[Category:Hiking]]
[[Category:Landscape history]]
[[Category:Navigation]]</text>
      <sha1>4ows0txpcrhbhk97iqudzxzq00wwi1n</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
