  <page>
    <title>Crannog</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7122</id>
    <revision>
      <id>936743234</id>
      <parentid>929565770</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-20T19:01:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>46.7.91.7</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>removed rivers. the current of rivers would easily knock down the stilts of crannógs.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[File:Crannog - geograph.org.uk - 35551.jpg|thumb|Reconstructed crannog near [[Kenmore, Perth and Kinross]], on [[Loch Tay]], [[Scotland]]]]

A '''crannog'''&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Sullivan 2000&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=O'Sullivan |first=A. |date=2000 |title=Crannogs: Lake Dwellings of Ireland |publisher=Irish Treasure Series |location=Dublin}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Lynn&gt;{{cite journal|last=Lynn |first=C. J. |date=1983 |title=Some 'early' ring forts and crannogs |journal=Journal of Irish Archaeology |volume=1 |pages=47–58}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dixon 2004&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first=Nicholas |last=Dixon |title=The Crannogs of Scotland: An underwater archaeology |publisher=Tempus Publishing, Limited |date=2004 |isbn=0-7524-3151-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|k|r|æ|n|ə|ɡ}}; {{lang-ga|crannóg}} {{IPA-ga|ˈkɾˠan̪ˠoːɡ|}}; {{lang-gd|crannag}} {{IPA-gd|ˈkʰɾan̪ˠak|}}) is typically a partially or entirely [[artificial island]], usually built in [[lake]]s, and [[estuary|estuarine]] waters of [[Scotland]], [[Wales]], and [[Ireland]]. Unlike the [[prehistoric pile dwellings around the Alps]] that were built on the shores and were inundated only later on, crannogs were built in the water, thus forming artificial islands.

Crannogs were used as dwellings over five millennia, from the [[Neolithic#Europe|European Neolithic Period]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Armit 2003&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Armit |first=Ian |date=2003 |chapter=The Drowners: permanence and transience in the Hebridean Neolithic |editor1-first=I. |editor1-last=Armit |editor2-first=E. |editor2-last=Murphy |editor3-first=D. |editor3-last=Simpson |title=Neolithic Settlement in Ireland and Western Britain |publisher=Oxbow |location=Oxford}}&lt;/ref&gt; to as late as the 17th/early 18th century,&lt;ref name=&quot;Dixon 2004&quot; /&gt; although in Scotland there is currently no convincing evidence in the archaeological record of Early and Middle [[Bronze Age]] or [[Scandinavian Scotland|Norse Period]] use. The [[radiocarbon dating]] obtained from key sites such as Oakbank and Redcastle indicates at a 95.4 per cent [[confidence level]] that they date to the Late Bronze Age to [[Early Iron Age]]. The date ranges fall ''after'' around 800 BC and so could be considered Late Bronze Age by only the narrowest of margins.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dixon 2004&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Henderson 1998&quot; /&gt; Crannogs have been variously interpreted as free-standing wooden structures, as at Loch Tay,&lt;ref name=&quot;Dixon 2004&quot; /&gt; although more commonly they exist as brush, stone or timber mounds that can be [[revetment|revetted]] with timber piles. However, in areas such as the [[Outer Hebrides]] of Scotland, timber was unavailable from the Neolithic era onwards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |editor1-last= Edwards |editor1-first= K. J. |editor2-last=Ralston |editor2-first=I. |date=1997 |title= Scotland After the Ice Age: Environment, Archaeology and History, 8000 BC–1000 AD |publisher= Wiley &amp; Sons |location= New York}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, completely stone crannogs supporting drystone architecture are common there.&lt;ref name=&quot;Armit 1996&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Armit |first=Ian |date=1996 |title=The Archaeology of Skye and the Western Isles |publisher= Edinburgh University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today, crannogs typically appear as small, circular islets, often {{convert|10|to|30|m |sigfig=1}} in diameter, covered in dense vegetation due to their inaccessibility to grazing livestock.

==Etymology and uncertain meanings==
The Irish word {{lang|ga|crannóg}} derives from [[Old Irish]] {{lang|sga|crannóc}},&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|date=2009 |chapter=crannog |title=American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language |publisher=Houghton Mifflin |chapter-url= http://education.yahoo.com/reference/dictionary/entry/crannog |url-status=dead |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20120926104237/http://education.yahoo.com/reference/dictionary/entry/crannog |archive-date=26 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; which referred to a wooden structure or vessel, stemming from ''crann'', which means &quot;tree&quot;, plus a [[diminutive]] ending—literally &quot;young tree&quot;.&lt;ref name=Fredengren&gt;{{cite book |last=Fredengren |first=Christina |date=2002 |title=Crannogs: A Study of People's Interaction with Lakes, with Special Reference to Loch Gara in the North West of Ireland |publisher=Wordwell |location=Bray}}&lt;/ref&gt; The modern sense of the term first appears sometime around the 12th century; its popularity spread in the medieval period along with the terms ''isle'', ''ylle'', ''inis'', ''eilean'' or ''oileán''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morrison&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Landscape with Lake Dwellings |last=Morrison |first=I. |publisher=Edinburgh University Press |date=1985}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= A New History of Ireland: Prehistoric and early Ireland |first1=Dáibhí |last1=Ó Cróinín |author-link1=Dáibhí Ó Cróinín |first2=Theodore William |last2=Moody |author-link2=Theodore William Moody |publisher=Oxford University Press |date=2005 |isbn=0-19-821737-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is some confusion on what the term ''crannog'' originally referred to, as the structure atop the island or the island itself.&lt;ref name=Morrison /&gt; The additional meanings of Irish {{lang|ga|crannóg}} can be variously related as 'structure/piece of wood', including '[[crow's nest]]', '[[pulpit]]', or 'driver's box on a coach'; 'vessel/box/chest' more generally; and 'wooden pin'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Dinneen |first=Patrick |author-link=Patrick S. Dinneen |title=Foclóir Gaedhilge agus Béarla |date=1927 |publisher= [[Irish Texts Society]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Scottish Gaelic]] form is {{lang|gd|crannag}} and has the additional meanings of 'pulpit' and '[[Butter churn|churn]]'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Mark |first=C. |date=2003 |title=The Gaelic English Dictionary |publisher=[[Routledge]] |isbn=0-203-22259-8 |page=175}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, there is no real consensus on what the term ''crannog'' actually implies, although the modern adoption in the English language broadly refers to a partially or completely artificial islet that saw use from the prehistoric to the Post-Medieval period in Ireland and Scotland.&lt;ref name=Morrison /&gt;

==Location==
Crannogs are widespread in [[Ireland]], with an estimated 1,200 examples,&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Sullivan 1998&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last= O'Sullivan |first=A. |date=1998 |title=The Archaeology of Lake Settlement in Ireland |publisher= Discovery Programme |location= Dublin}}&lt;/ref&gt; while [[Scotland]] has 347 sites officially listed as such.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://canmore.rcahms.gov.uk/en/results/?sitename=&amp;site_type_term=CRANNOG+&amp;site_discipline=1&amp;numlink=&amp;mapno=&amp;site=&amp;council_code=&amp;parish=&amp;region_code=&amp;district_code=&amp;county_code=&amp;ngr=&amp;locat_xy_radius_m=&amp;collection_name=&amp;biblio_surname=&amp;biblio_inits=&amp;biblio_title=&amp;biblio_date=&amp;biblio_journal=&amp;site_country=1&amp;submit=Search |title=Canmore Database/Royal Commission on Ancient and Historic Monuments Scotland |access-date=18 January 2011 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121021173247/http://canmore.rcahms.gov.uk/en/results/?sitename=&amp;site_type_term=CRANNOG+&amp;site_discipline=1&amp;numlink=&amp;mapno=&amp;site=&amp;council_code=&amp;parish=&amp;region_code=&amp;district_code=&amp;county_code=&amp;ngr=&amp;locat_xy_radius_m=&amp;collection_name=&amp;biblio_surname=&amp;biblio_inits=&amp;biblio_title=&amp;biblio_date=&amp;biblio_journal=&amp;site_country=1&amp;submit=Search |archive-date=21 October 2012 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; The actual number in Scotland varies considerably depending on definition—between about 350 to 500, due to the use of the term &quot;island dun&quot; for well over one hundred Hebridean examples—a distinction that has created a divide between mainland Scottish crannog and Hebridean islet settlement studies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harding 2000&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last= Harding |first=D. W. |date=2000 |title=Crannogs and island duns: Classification, dating and function |journal=Oxford Journal of Archaeology |volume=19 |number=3 |pages=301–17 |doi= 10.1111/1468-0092.00111}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Harding |first=D. W. |date=2007 |chapter=Crannogs and island duns: An aerial perspective |editor1-last=Barber |editor1-first=J. |editor2-last=Clarke |editor2-first=C. |editor3-last=Crone |editor3-first=A. |editor4-last=Hale |editor4-first=A. |editor5-last=Henderson |editor5-first=J. |editor6-last=Housley |editor6-first=R. |editor7-last=Sands |editor7-first=R. |editor8-last=Sheridan |editor8-first=A. |title=Archaeology from the Wetlands: Proceedings of the 11th WARP Conference, Edinburgh 2007 |publisher=Society of Antiquaries of Scotland |pages=267–73}}&lt;/ref&gt; Previously unknown crannogs in Scotland and Ireland are still being found as underwater surveys continue to investigate loch beds for completely submerged examples.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Lenfert |first=Robert |date=2009 |title=Uist Island Dun Investigation – Dun Borosdale, Western Isles (South Uist parish), preliminary investigation |series= Discovery Excav Scot, New |volume=10 |publisher= Cathedral Communications Limited |location= Wiltshire, England}}&lt;/ref&gt; The largest concentrations of crannogs in Ireland are found in the Drumlin Belt of the Midlands, North and Northwest. In Scotland, crannogs are mostly found on the western coast, with high concentrations in [[Argyll]] and [[Dumfries and Galloway]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Henderson 1998&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last= Henderson |first=J. C. |date=1998 |title=Islets through time: the definition, dating and distribution of Scottish crannogs |journal= Oxford Journal of Archaeology |volume=17 |number=2 |pages=227–44 |doi=10.1111/1468-0092.00060}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Henderson |first= J. C. |date=2000 |chapter= Shared traditions? The drystone settlement records of Atlantic Scotland and Ireland 700 BC – AD 200 |editor-first=J. C. |editor-last=Henderson |title=BAR 861 |location= Oxford |pages=117–54}}&lt;/ref&gt; In reality, the Western Isles contain the highest density of lake-settlements in Scotland, yet they are recognised under varying terms besides &quot;crannog&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Armit 1992&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Armit |first=Ian |date=1992 |title=The Later Prehistory of the Western Isles of Scotland |location=Oxford |series=BAR Brit Ser. 221}}&lt;/ref&gt; One lone Welsh example at [[Llangorse Lake]] exists, likely a product of Irish influence across the Irish Sea.&lt;ref name=&quot;Redknap &amp; Lane&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Redknap |first1=Mark |first2=Alan |last2=Lane |date=1994 |title=The early medieval crannog at Llangors, Powys: an interim statement on the 1989–1993 seasons |journal= International Journal of Nautical Archaeology |volume=23 |number=3 |pages=189–205 |doi= 10.1111/j.1095-9270.1994.tb00460.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Reconstructed Irish crannógs are located in [[Craggaunowen]], [[County Clare]], [[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]]; the [[Irish National Heritage Park]], in [[Wexford, Ireland]]; and in Scotland at the &quot;Scottish Crannog Centre&quot; at Loch Tay, Perthshire. This centre offers guided tours and hands-on activities, including wool-spinning, wood-turning and making fire, holds events to celebrate wild cooking and crafts, and hosts yearly [[Midsummer]], [[Lughnasadh]] and [[Samhain]] festivals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crannog.co.uk &quot;The Scottish Crannog Centre&quot;]. www.crannog.co.uk. Retrieved 16 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Types and problems with definition==
[[File:Crannog Loch Tay.jpg|thumb|right|upright|Replica crannóg on [[Loch Tay]]]]Crannogs took on many different forms and methods of construction based on what was available in the immediate landscape. The classic image of a prehistoric crannog stems from both post-medieval illustrations&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Sullivan 1998&quot; /&gt; and highly influential excavations such as Milton Loch in Scotland by C. M. Piggot after [[World War II]].&lt;ref name=Piggott&gt;{{cite journal|last=Piggott |first=C. M. |date=1953 |title=Milton Loch Crannog: a native house of the second century AD in Kirkcudbrightshire |journal=Proceedings of the Society of Antiquaries of Scotland |volume=87 |pages=134–52}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Milton Loch interpretation is of a small islet surrounded or defined at its edges by timber piles and a gangway, topped by a typical Iron Age roundhouse. The choice of a small islet as a home may seem odd today, yet waterways were the main channels for both communication and travel until the 19th century in much of Ireland and especially Highland Scotland. Crannogs are traditionally interpreted as simple prehistorical farmsteads. They are also interpreted as boltholes in times of danger, as status symbols with limited access and as inherited locations of power that imply a sense of legitimacy and ancestry towards ownership of the surrounding landscape.

A strict definition of a crannog, which has long been debated, requires the use of timber.&lt;ref name=Lynn /&gt; Sites in the Western Isles do not satisfy this criterion, although their inhabitants shared the common habit of living on water.&lt;ref name=Lynn /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Harding 2000&quot; /&gt; If not classed as &quot;true&quot; crannogs, small occupied islets (often at least partially artificial in nature) may be referred to as &quot;island duns&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Armit 1996&quot; /&gt; although rather confusingly, 22 islet-based sites are classified as &quot;proper&quot; crannogs due to the different interpretations of the inspectors or excavators who drew up field reports.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://canmore.rcahms.gov.uk/en/results/?sitename=&amp;site_type_term=CRANNOG+&amp;site_discipline=1&amp;numlink=&amp;mapno=&amp;site=&amp;council_code=410&amp;parish=&amp;region_code=&amp;district_code=&amp;county_code=&amp;ngr=&amp;locat_xy_radius_m=&amp;collection_name=&amp;biblio_surname=&amp;biblio_inits=&amp;biblio_title=&amp;biblio_date=&amp;biblio_journal=&amp;site_country=1&amp;submit=Search |title=Canmore search for crannog in the Western Isles |access-date=18 January 2011 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121021173514/http://canmore.rcahms.gov.uk/en/results/?sitename=&amp;site_type_term=CRANNOG+&amp;site_discipline=1&amp;numlink=&amp;mapno=&amp;site=&amp;council_code=410&amp;parish=&amp;region_code=&amp;district_code=&amp;county_code=&amp;ngr=&amp;locat_xy_radius_m=&amp;collection_name=&amp;biblio_surname=&amp;biblio_inits=&amp;biblio_title=&amp;biblio_date=&amp;biblio_journal=&amp;site_country=1&amp;submit=Search |archive-date=21 October 2012 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; Hebridean island dwellings or crannogs were commonly built on both natural and artificial islets, usually reached by a stone causeway. The visible structural remains are traditionally interpreted&lt;ref name=&quot;Beveridge, E 1911&quot;&gt;Beveridge, E. 1911. North Uist: Its Archaeology and Topography, William Brown, Edinburgh.&lt;/ref&gt; as [[dun]]s, or in more recent terminology as &quot;Atlantic roundhouses&quot;. This terminology has recently become popular when describing the entire range of robust, drystone structures that existed in later prehistoric Atlantic Scotland.&lt;ref name=&quot;Armit 1992&quot; /&gt;

The majority of crannog excavations were poorly conducted (by modern standards) in the late 19th and early 20th centuries by early antiquarians, or were indeed purely accidental finds as lochs were drained during the improvements to increase usable farmland or pasture.&lt;ref name=&quot;Munro Ancient&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Ancient Scottish Lake Dwellings, or Crannogs|url=https://archive.org/details/ancientscottish00munrgoog|last=Munro|first=R.|publisher=David Douglas|date=1882|location=Edinburgh}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wilde, W. R. 1840. &quot;Antiquities recently discovered at Dunshanghlin&quot;. ''Proceedings of the Royal Irish Academy'', vol. 1 pp.420-426.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, G. 1873. &quot;Notes on the crannogs and lake dwellings of Wigtownshire&quot;, ''Proceedings of the Society of Antiquaries of Scotland'', vol. 9, pp. 368&amp;ndash;378.&lt;/ref&gt; In some early digs, labourers merely hauled away tons of materials with little regard to anything that was not of immediate economic value. Conversely, the vast majority of early attempts at proper excavation failed to accurately measure or record [[stratigraphy]], thereby failing to provide a secure context for artefact finds. Thus only extremely limited interpretations are possible. Preservation and conservation techniques for waterlogged materials such as logboats or structural material were all but non-existent, and a number of extremely important finds perished as a result: in some instances dried out for firewood.&lt;ref name=&quot;Munro Ancient&quot; /&gt; From about 1900 to the late 1940s there was very little crannog excavation in Scotland, while Ireland did witness some important and highly influential contributions.&lt;ref&gt;Hencken, H. O.1937. &quot;Ballinderry Crannog 1&quot;, ''Proceedings of the Royal Irish Academy'', vol. 43, pp. 103&amp;ndash;239.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hencken, H. O. 1942 &quot;Ballinderry Crannog 2&quot; in ''Proceedings of the Royal Irish Academy'' 47Ci (1942) 1&amp;ndash;76.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hencken, H.O 1950&quot;&gt;Hencken, H.O. 1950. &quot;Lagore Crannog: an Irish royal residence of the seventh to tenth century AD&quot;, in ''Proceedings of the Royal Irish Academy'' 53C, 1&amp;ndash;248.&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast, relatively few crannogs have been excavated since the Second World War, although this number has steadily grown, especially since the early 1980s, and may soon surpass pre-war totals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crone, B. A 2000&quot;&gt;Crone, B. A. 2000. &quot;The History of a Scottish Lowland Crannog: Excavations at Buiston, Ayrshire&quot;, 1989&amp;ndash;90, STAR Monograph 4, AOC/Historic Scotland, Edinburgh.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Sullivan &amp; Sands&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1= O'Sullivan |first1=A. |last2=Sands |first2=R. |chapter= Impressive, well-appointed, rich and enigmatic: Collure Demense crannog, Lough Derravaragh, County Westmeath |editor1-last=Barber |editor1-first=J. |editor2-last=Clarke |editor2-first=C. |editor3-last=Crone |editor3-first=A. |editor4-last=Hale |editor4-first=A. |editor5-last=Henderson |editor5-first=J. |editor6-last=Housley |editor6-first=R. |editor7-last=Sands |editor7-first=R. |editor8-last=Sheridan |editor8-first=A. |title= Archaeology from the Wetlands: Proceedings of the 11th WARP Conference |location= Edinburgh |date=2005 |publisher= Society of Antiquaries for Scotland |pages=303–11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Scott, J. 1960. &quot;Loch Glashan&quot;, ''Discovery and Excavation in Scotland'' no. 354.&lt;/ref&gt; The overwhelming majority of crannogs show multiple phases of occupation and re-use, often extending over centuries. Thus the re-occupiers may have viewed crannogs as a legacy that remained alive in local tradition and memory. Crannog reoccupation is important and significant, especially in the many instances of crannogs built near natural islets that were often completely unused. This long chronology of use has been verified both by [[radiocarbon dating]] and more precisely by [[dendrochronology]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Crone, B. A 2000&quot;/&gt; Interpretations of crannog function are not static through time; instead they appear to change in both the archaeological and historic records. Rather than largely simple domestic residences in prehistory, the medieval crannogs were increasingly seen as strongholds of the upper class or regional political players such as Gaelic chieftains like the O'Boylans and McMahons in [[County Monaghan]] and the Kingdom of [[Airgíalla]] until the 17th century. In Scotland, their medieval and post-medieval use is also documented into the early 18th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dixon 2004&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=Morrison /&gt; Whether this increase in status is real, or just a by-product of increasingly complex material assemblages, remains to be convincingly validated.&lt;ref name=Fredengren /&gt;

==History==
The earliest known construction of a crannog is the completely artificial Neolithic islet of [[Eilean Dòmhnuill]], Loch Olabhat on [[North Uist]] in Scotland. Eilean Domhnuill&lt;ref name=&quot;Armit 1996&quot; /&gt; has produced radiocarbon dates ranging from 3650 to 2500 BC&lt;ref name=&quot;Armit 2003&quot; /&gt; while Irish crannogs appear from middle [[Bronze Age]] layers at [[Ballinderry]] (1200–600 BC).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=National Handbook of Underwater Archaeology | publisher=Springer | author=Carol Ruppé, Jan Barstad | date=2002 | isbn=0-3064-6345-8 | series=The Springer Series in Underwater Archaeology}}&lt;/ref&gt; Recent [[radiocarbon]] dating of worked timber found in Loch Bhorghastail on the [[Isle of Lewis]] has produced evidence of crannogs as old as 3380-3630 BC.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Garrow |first=D. |date =2019 |title=Neolithic crannogs: Rethinking settlement, monumentality and deposition in the Outer Hebrides and beyond |journal=[[Antiquity (journal)|Antiquity]] |volume=93 |number=369 |pages=664–684 |doi=10.15184/aqy.2019.41}}&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to the [[Bronze Age]], the existence of artificial island settlement in Ireland is not as clear. While lakeside settlements are evident in Ireland from 4500 BC, these settlements are not crannogs as they were not intended to be islands. Despite having a tremendous chronology, their use was not at all consistent or unchanging. Crannog construction and occupation was at its peak in Scotland from about 800 BC to AD 200.&lt;ref name=&quot;Henderson 1998&quot; /&gt; Not surprisingly, crannogs have useful defensive properties, although there appears to be more significance to prehistoric use than simple defense, as very few weapons or evidence for destruction appear in excavations of prehistoric crannogs. In Ireland, crannogs were at their zenith during the Early Historic period,&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Sullivan 2000&quot; /&gt; when they were the homes and retreats of kings, lords, prosperous farmers and occasionally socially marginalised groups such as monastic hermits or metalsmiths who could work in isolation. However, despite earlier concepts of a strict Early Historic evolution,&lt;ref name=Lynn /&gt; Irish excavations are increasingly uncovering examples, which date from the &quot;missing&quot; Iron Age in Ireland.&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Sullivan &amp; Sands&quot; /&gt;

==Construction==
[[File:Loughbrickland Crannog.jpg|thumb|[[Loughbrickland Crannóg]] in [[Northern Ireland]].]]
The construction techniques for a crannog (prehistoric or otherwise) are as varied as the multitude of finished forms witnessed in the archaeological record. Island settlement in Scotland and Ireland is manifest through the entire range of possibilities ranging from entirely natural, small islets to completely artificial islets, therefore definitions will invariably remain contentious. For crannogs in the strict sense, typically this effort began on a shallow reef or rise in the lochbed.

When timber was available, many were surrounded by a circle of wooden [[Deep foundation|piles]] with axe-sharpened bases that were driven into the bottom, forming a circular enclosure that helped to retain the main mound and prevent erosion. The piles could also be joined together by [[mortise and tenon]], or large holes cut to carefully accept specially shaped timbers designed to interlock and provide structural rigidity. On other examples, interior surfaces were built up with any mixture of clay, peat, stone, timber or brush – whatever was available. In some instances, more than one structure was built on crannogs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Armit 2003&quot; /&gt;

Other types of crannogs saw the occupants add large stones to the waterline of small natural islets, extending and enlarging them over successive phases of renewal. Larger crannogs could be occupied by extended families or communal groups, and access was either by logboats or coracles while evidence for timber or stone causeways exists on a large number of crannogs. The causeways themselves may have been slightly submerged; this has been interpreted as a device to make access difficult&lt;ref name=&quot;Beveridge, E 1911&quot;/&gt; but may also simply be a by-product of loch level fluctuations over the ensuing centuries or indeed millennia. Organic remains are often found in excellent condition on these water-logged sites. The bones of [[cattle]], [[deer]], and [[Pig|swine]] have been found in excavated crannogs while remains of wooden utensils and even dairy products can remain completely preserved for several millennia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dixon 2004&quot; /&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist|30em}}

==References==
* {{cite book
|last=Burnett |first=George
|title=The Family of Burnett of Leys
|url=https://archive.org/details/familyofburnetto00burn |editor-last=Allardyce |editor-first=J.
|publisher=New Spalding Club
|location=Aberdeen
|date=1901
}}
* {{cite book
|first=Ian |last=Armit
|title=Scotland's Hidden History
|publisher=[[Tempus Publishing]]
|date=2000
|isbn=0-7524-1400-3
}}
* {{cite book
|last=Crone |first=A.
|date=2000
|title=The History of a Scottish Lowland Crannog: Excavations at Buiston
|publisher=AOC/STAR
|series=Monographs |issue=4
|location=Edinburgh
}}
* {{cite book
|last=Halsall |first=Guy
|date=2003
|title=Warfare and Society in the Barbarian West, 450–900
|location=London
|publisher=Routledge.
}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Crannogs}}
* [http://crannogs.weebly.com/] &quot;Living On Water: Scottish Crannogs and Island Dwellings&quot;.
* [http://www.crannog.co.uk/ Crannog.co.uk], The Scottish Crannog Centre Reconstruction of a crannog.
* [http://www.mcmahonsofmonaghan.org/crannogs.html McMahonsOfMonaghan.org], Crannog illustration showing attack in [[Monaghan]], [[Ireland]] in the 16th century.
* [http://www.channel4.com/history/timeteam/snapshot_crannogs.html Channel4.com], Time Team on Crannogs.
* [http://www.channel4.com/history/timeteam/2004_migdale.html Channel4.com], Time Team excavation at Loch Migdale, January 2004.
* [http://www.rcahms.gov.uk Canmore], Royal Commission on the Ancient and Historical Monuments of Scotland's Canmore database, a searchable database of archaeological and architectural sites in Scotland, including crannogs.
* [http://archaeology.about.com/od/lterms/qt/llangorse_crann.htm About.com], Llangors Crannog.

{{Prehistoric Scotland}}
{{Scottish architecture}}
{{Fortifications}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2012}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Crannog}}
[[Category:Fortifications by type]]
[[Category:Archaeology of Ireland]]
[[Category:Archaeology of Northern Ireland]]
[[Category:Archaeology of Scotland]]
[[Category:Stone Age sites in Scotland]]
[[Category:Stone Age Europe]]
[[Category:Bronze Age Scotland]]
[[Category:Iron Age Scotland]]
[[Category:Crannógs]]
[[Category:Prehistoric Ireland]]
[[Category:Neolithic Scotland]]
[[Category:Forts in Scotland]]
[[Category:Forts in Ireland]]
[[Category:House types]]
[[Category:Ancient Ireland]]
[[Category:Medieval Ireland]]</text>
      <sha1>9dqfs6bhhdblhk4a44povzhpmzz1x11</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
