  <page>
    <title>Cartoon</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7165</id>
    <revision>
      <id>925620106</id>
      <parentid>923950291</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-11-11T07:26:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelink 1 book for [[WP:V|verifiability]].) #IABot (v2.0) ([[User:GreenC bot|GreenC bot]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Form of two-dimensional illustrated visual art}}
{{pp|small=yes}} 
{{Other uses}}
{{sprotect|small=yes}}

[[File:Dr. Seuss WikiWorld.png|thumb|300px|Example of a modern cartoon. The text was excerpted by cartoonist Greg Williams from the Wikipedia article on [[Dr. Seuss]].|alt=A cartoon shows a bearded man with a red bow tie holding numerous items. He holds the hat from Dr. Seuss's &quot;The Cat in the Hat&quot; and balances a fishbowl on his left index finger.]]
A '''cartoon''' is a type of [[illustration]], possibly animated, typically in a non-[[realism (arts)|realistic]] or semi-realistic style. The specific meaning has evolved over time, but the modern usage usually refers to either: an image or series of images intended for [[satire]], [[caricature]], or [[humor]]; or a motion picture that relies on a sequence of illustrations for its animation. Someone who creates cartoons in the first sense is called a ''[[cartoonist]]'',&lt;ref&gt;[[Webster's Dictionary|Merriam-Webster's Dictionary]].&lt;/ref&gt; and in the second sense they are usually called an ''[[animator]]''.

The concept originated in the [[Middle Ages]], and first described a preparatory drawing for a piece of art, such as a painting, [[fresco]], [[tapestry]], or [[stained glass]] window. In the 19th century, beginning in ''[[Punch (magazine)|Punch]]'' magazine in 1843, cartoon came to refer – ironically at first – to humorous illustrations in magazines and newspapers. In the early 20th century, it began to refer to [[Animated cartoon|animated]] films which resembled print cartoons.&lt;ref name=Becker&gt;{{harvnb|Becker|1959}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Fine art==
{{Main article|Modello}}
A cartoon (from {{Lang-it|cartone}} and {{Lang-nl|karton}}—words describing strong, heavy paper or pasteboard) is a full-size drawing made on sturdy [[paper]] as a study or ''[[modello]]'' for a [[painting]], [[stained glass]], or [[tapestry]]. Cartoons were typically used in the production of [[fresco]]es, to accurately link the component parts of the composition when painted on damp [[plaster]] over a series of days (''giornate'').{{sfn|Constable|1954|page=115}}

Such cartoons often have pinpricks along the outlines of the design so that a bag of soot patted or &quot;pounced&quot; over a cartoon, held against the wall, would leave black dots on the plaster (&quot;pouncing&quot;). Cartoons by [[Painting|painter]]s, such as the [[Raphael Cartoons]] in London, and examples by [[Leonardo da Vinci]], are highly prized in their own right. Tapestry cartoons, usually colored, were followed with the eye by the [[weaving|weavers]] on the [[loom]].&lt;ref name=Becker/&gt;{{sfn|Adelson|1994|page=330}}

==Print media==
&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Stoke-on-Trent]] --&gt;
[[File:SubstanceandShadow.jpg|left|250px|thumb|[[John Leech (caricaturist)|John Leech]], ''Cartoon no.1: Substance and Shadow'', 1843, satirized preparatory cartoons for frescoes in the Palace of Westminster, creating the modern meaning of &quot;cartoon&quot;.|alt=A detailed black-and-white illustration is vignetted in the center showing people of various sizes looking at pictures framed on the left and back walls.]]

In print media, a cartoon is an illustration or series of illustrations, usually humorous in intent. This usage dates from 1843, when ''[[Punch (magazine)|Punch]]'' magazine applied the term to satirical drawings in its pages,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Punch.co.uk|title=History of the Cartoon|url=http://punch.co.uk/cartoonhistory02.html|access-date=2007-11-01|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071111013522/http://www.punch.co.uk/cartoonhistory02.html|archive-date=2007-11-11|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; particularly sketches by [[John Leech (caricaturist)|John Leech]].{{sfn|Adler|Hill|2008|p=30}} The first of these parodied the preparatory cartoons for grand historical frescoes in the then-new [[Palace of Westminster]]. The original title for these drawings was ''Mr Punch's face is the letter Q'' and the new title &quot;cartoon&quot; was intended to be ironic, a reference to the self-aggrandizing posturing of Westminster politicians.

Cartoons can be divided into gag cartoons, which include editorial cartoons, and comic strips.

Modern single-panel [[gag cartoon|''gag cartoons'']], found in magazines, generally consist of a single drawing with a typeset caption positioned beneath, or—less often—a [[speech balloon]].{{sfn|Bishop|2009|p=92}} Newspaper syndicates have also distributed single-panel gag cartoons by [[Mel Calman]], [[Bill Holman (cartoonist)|Bill Holman]], [[Gary Larson]], [[George Lichty]], [[Fred Neher]] and others. Many consider ''[[The New Yorker|New Yorker]]'' cartoonist [[Peter Arno]] the father of the modern gag cartoon (as did Arno himself).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |last1=Maslin |first1=Michael |title=The Peter Arno Cartoons That Help Rescue The New Yorker |url=https://www.newyorker.com/books/page-turner/the-peter-arno-cartoons-that-helped-rescue-the-new-yorker |magazine=The New Yorker |accessdate=2018-09-16 |date=May 5, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The roster of magazine gag cartoonists includes [[Charles Addams]], [[Charles Barsotti]], and [[Chon Day]].

[[Bill Hoest]], [[Jerry Marcus]], and [[Virgil Partch]] began as magazine gag cartoonists and moved to syndicated [[comic strips]]. [[Richard Thompson (cartoonist)|Richard Thompson]] illustrated numerous feature articles in ''[[The Washington Post]]'' before creating his ''[[Cul de Sac (comic strip)|Cul de Sac]]'' comic strip. The sports section of newspapers usually featured cartoons, sometimes including syndicated features such as Chester &quot;Chet&quot; Brown's ''[[All in Sport]]''.

''[[Editorial cartoons]]'' are found almost exclusively in news publications and news websites. Although they also employ humor, they are more serious in tone, commonly using [[irony]] or [[satire]]. The art usually acts as a visual metaphor to illustrate a point of view on current social or political topics. Editorial cartoons often include speech balloons and sometimes use multiple panels. [[Editorial cartoonist]]s of note include [[Herblock]], [[David Low (cartoonist)|David Low]], [[Jeff MacNelly]], [[Mike Peters (cartoonist)|Mike Peters]], and [[Gerald Scarfe]].&lt;ref name=Becker/&gt;

''Comic strips'', also known as ''cartoon strips'' in the United Kingdom, are found daily in newspapers worldwide, and are usually a short series of cartoon illustrations in sequence. In the United States, they are not commonly called &quot;cartoons&quot; themselves, but rather &quot;comics&quot; or &quot;[[Sunday comics|funnies]]&quot;. Nonetheless, the creators of comic strips—as well as [[comic book]]s and [[graphic novel]]s—are usually referred to as &quot;[[cartoonist]]s&quot;. Although humor is the most prevalent subject matter, adventure and drama are also represented in this medium. Some noteworthy cartoonists of humorous comic strips are [[Scott Adams]], [[Steve Bell (cartoonist)|Steve Bell]], [[Charles Schulz]], [[E. C. Segar]], [[Mort Walker]] and [[Bill Watterson]].&lt;ref name=Becker/&gt;

===Political cartoons===
{{main article|Editorial cartoon}}

Political cartoons are like illustrated editorial that serve visual commentaries on political events. They offer subtle criticism which are cleverly quoted with humour and satire to the extent that the criticized does not get embittered.

The pictorial satire of [[William Hogarth]] is regarded as a precursor to the development of political cartoons in 18th century England.{{sfn|Press|1981|page=34}} [[George Townshend, 1st Marquess Townshend|George Townshend]] produced some of the first overtly political cartoons and caricatures in the 1750s.{{sfn|Press|1981|page=34}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thefreelibrary.com/Birth+of+England%27s+pocket+cartoon%3B+LOCAL+HISTORY+Smile+awhile+through...-a0153110971| title=Birth of England's pocket cartoon|author=Chris Upton|publisher=The Free Library}}&lt;/ref&gt; The medium began to develop in the latter part of the 18th century under the direction of its great exponents, [[James Gillray]] and [[Thomas Rowlandson]], both from London. Gillray explored the use of the medium for lampooning and [[caricature]], and has been referred to as the father of the political cartoon.{{sfn|Rowson|2015}} By calling the king, prime ministers and generals to account for their behaviour, many of Gillray's satires were directed against [[George III of the United Kingdom|George III]], depicting him as a pretentious buffoon, while the bulk of his work was dedicated to ridiculing the ambitions of [[revolutionary France]] and [[Napoleon]].{{sfn|Rowson|2015}} [[George Cruikshank]] became the leading cartoonist in the period following Gillray, from 1815 until the 1840s. His career was renowned for his social caricatures of English life for popular publications.

[[File:Tammany Ring, Nast crop.jpg|thumb|250px|Nast depicts the [[Tweed Ring]]: &quot;Who stole the people's money?&quot; / &quot;'Twas him.&quot;|alt=A cartoon showing a circle of men pointing their fingers at the man to their right with grimaces on their faces.]]

By the mid 19th century, major political newspapers in many other countries featured cartoons commenting on the politics of the day. [[Thomas Nast]], in New York City, showed how realistic German drawing techniques could redefine American cartooning.{{sfn|Adler|Hill|2008|p=24}} His 160 cartoons relentlessly pursued the criminal characteristic of the [[William M. Tweed|Tweed machine]] in New York City, and helped bring it down. Indeed, Tweed was arrested in Spain when police identified him from Nast's cartoons.{{sfn|Adler|Hill|2008|pp=49–50}} In Britain, Sir [[John Tenniel]] was the toast of London.{{sfn|Morris|Tenniel|2005|p=344}} In France under the [[July Monarchy]], [[Honoré Daumier]] took up the new genre of political and social [[La Caricature (1830–1843)|caricature]], most famously lampooning the rotund [[Louis Philippe I|King Louis Philippe]].

Political cartoons can be humorous or satirical, sometimes with piercing effect. The target of the humor may complain, but can seldom fight back. Lawsuits have been very rare; the first successful lawsuit against a cartoonist in over a century in Britain came in 1921, when [[J. H. Thomas]], the leader of the [[National Union of Railwaymen]] (NUR), initiated libel proceedings against the magazine of the [[British Communist Party]]. Thomas claimed defamation in the form of cartoons and words depicting the events of &quot;Black Friday&quot;, when he allegedly betrayed the locked-out [[Miners' Federation of Great Britain|Miners' Federation]]. To Thomas, the framing of his image by the far left threatened to grievously degrade his character in the popular imagination. Soviet-inspired communism was a new element in European politics, and cartoonists unrestrained by tradition tested the boundaries of libel law. Thomas won the lawsuit and restored his reputation.&lt;ref&gt;Samuel S.  Hyde, &quot;'Please, Sir, he called me “Jimmy!' Political Cartooning before the Law: 'Black Friday,' J.H. Thomas, and the Communist Libel Trial of 1921,&quot; ''Contemporary British History'' (2011) 25#4 pp 521-550&lt;/ref&gt;

===Scientific cartoons===
Cartoons such as ''[[xkcd]]'' have also found their place in the world of [[science]], [[mathematics]], and [[technology]]. For example, the cartoon ''Wonderlab'' looked at daily life in the chemistry lab.  In the U.S., one well-known cartoonist for these fields is [[Sidney Harris (cartoonist)|Sidney Harris]]. Many of [[Gary Larson]]'s cartoons have a scientific flavor.

===Comic books&lt;!--'Humor comics' and 'Humour comics' redirect here--&gt;===
{{Main|Comic book}}
 
Books with cartoons are usually magazine-format &quot;comic books,&quot; or occasionally [[Comics collection|reprints of newspaper cartoons]].

In Britain in the 1930s adventure magazines became quite popular, especially those published by [[DC Thomson]]; the publisher sent observers around the country to talk to boys and learn what they wanted to read about. The story line in magazines, comic books and cinema that most appealed to boys was the glamorous heroism of British soldiers fighting wars that were exciting and just.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ernest Sackville Turner]], ''Boys Will Be Boys: The Story of Sweeney Todd, Deadwood Dick, Sexton Blake, Billy Bunter, Dick Barton et al.'' (3rd ed. 1975).&lt;/ref&gt;  D.C. Thomson issued the first [[The Dandy|''The Dandy Comic'']] in December 1937. It had a revolutionary design that broke away from the usual children's comics that were published broadsheet in size and not very colourful.  Thomson capitalized on its success with a similar product ''[[The Beano]]''  in 1938.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=M. Keith Booker|title=Comics through Time: A History of Icons, Idols, and Ideas &amp;#91;4 volumes&amp;#93;: A History of Icons, Idols, and Ideas|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=hnuQBQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA74|year=2014|page=74|isbn=9780313397516}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On some occasions, new gag cartoons have been created for book publication, as was the case with ''[[Think Small]]'', a 1967 promotional book distributed as a giveaway by [[Volkswagen]] dealers. [[Bill Hoest]] and other cartoonists of that decade drew cartoons showing Volkswagens, and these were published along with humorous automotive essays by such humorists as [[H. Allen Smith]], [[Roger Price (comedy)|Roger Price]] and [[Jean Shepherd]]. The book's design juxtaposed each cartoon alongside a photograph of the cartoon's creator.

==Animation==
[[File:Animhorse.gif|thumb|200px|An [[animated cartoon]] horse, drawn by [[rotoscoping]] from [[Eadweard Muybridge]]'s 19th-century photos|alt=a running horse (animated)]]
{{Main article|Animated cartoon}}
Because of the stylistic similarities between comic strips and early animated movies, ''cartoon'' came to refer to [[animation]], and the word ''cartoon'' is currently used in reference to both animated cartoons and gag cartoons.{{sfn|Walasek|2009|p=116}}  While ''animation'' designates any style of illustrated images seen in rapid succession to give the impression of movement, the word &quot;cartoon&quot; is most often used as a descriptor for television programs and short films aimed at children, possibly featuring [[Anthropomorphism|anthropomorphized]] animals,{{sfn|Wells|2008|p=41}} [[superhero]]es, the adventures of child protagonists or related themes.

In the 1980s, ''cartoon'' was shortened to ''toon'', referring to characters in animated productions. This term was popularized in 1988 by the combined live-action/animated film ''[[Who Framed Roger Rabbit]]'', followed in 1990 by the animated TV series ''[[Tiny Toon Adventures]]''.

==See also==
{{portal|Cartoon|Comics|Arts|Visual arts|Film}}
*[[Billy Ireland Cartoon Library &amp; Museum]]
*[[Caricature]]
*[[Comics]]
*[[Comics studies]]
*[[Editorial cartoon]]
*''[[Histoire de M. Vieux Bois]]''
*[[List of comic strips]]
*[[List of cartoonists]]
*[[List of editorial cartoonists]]
*[[Teen humor comics]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

=== Bibliography ===
{{refbegin|30em}}
* {{cite book
 |first=Candace
 |last=Adelson
 |title=European tapestry in the Minneapolis Institute of Arts
 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qjPrAAAAMAAJ
 |year=1994
 |publisher=Minneapolis Institute of Arts
 |location=Minnesota
 |ref=harv
|isbn=9780810932623
 }}
* {{cite book|first1=John|last1=Adler|first2=Draper|last2=Hill|title=Doomed by Cartoon: How Cartoonist Thomas Nast and the New York Times Brought Down Boss Tweed and His Ring of Thieves|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=z6YjB5FnKgwC|year=2008|publisher=[[Morgan James Publishing]]|isbn=978-1-60037-443-2|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last1=Becker|first1=Stephen D.|first2=Rube|last2=Goldberg|title=Comic Art in America: A Social History of the Funnies, the Political Cartoons, Magazine Humor, Sporting Cartoons, and Animated Cartoons|publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster|year=1959|ref={{SfnRef|Becker|1959}} }}
* {{cite book|last=Bishop|first=Franklin|title=Cartoonist's Bible: An Essential Reference for Practicing Artist|year=2009|location=London|publisher=Chartwell Books|isbn=978-0-7858-2085-7|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book
 |editor-last=Blackbeard
 |editor-first=Bill
 |title=The Smithsonian Collection of Newspaper Comics
 |year=1977
 |publisher=Smithsonian Inst. Press
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |first=William George
 |last=Constable
 |title=The Painter's Workshop
 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jz6xYIn0_oQC&amp;pg=PA115
 |accessdate=20 January 2013
 |year=1954
 |publisher=Courier Dover Publications
 |ref=harv
|isbn=9780486238364
 }}
* {{cite book
 |authorlink1=Maurice Horn
 |last=Horn
 |first=Maurice
 |title=The World Encyclopedia of Comics
 |url=https://archive.org/details/worldencyclopedi00horn
 |url-access=registration
 |year=1976
 |publisher=[[Chelsea House]]
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |first1=Frankie
 |last1=Morris
 |first2=Sir John
 |last2=Tenniel
 |title=Artist Of Wonderland: The Life, Political Cartoons, And Illustrations Of Tenniel
 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=iO1l532dx_YC
 |year=2005
 |publisher=University of Virginia Press
 |ref=harv
|isbn=9780813923437
 }}
* {{cite book
 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=fwzWAAAAMAAJ
 |title=The Political Cartoon
 |first=Charles
 |last=Press
 |year=1981
 |publisher=Fairleigh Dickinson University Press
 |ref=harv
|isbn=9780838619018
 }}
* {{cite book|last=Robinson|first=Jerry|title=The Comics: An Illustrated History of Comic Strip Art|year=1974|publisher=[[G.P. Putnam's Sons]]|ref=harv}}
* {{cite news|title=Satire, sewers and statesmen: why James Gillray was king of the cartoon|url=https://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/2015/mar/21/satire-sewers-and-statesmen-james-gillray-king-of-cartoon|agency=The Guardian|last=Rowson|first=Martin|date=21 March 2015|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Walasek |first=Helen |year=2009 |title=The Best of Punch Cartoons: 2,000 Humor Classics |location=England |publisher=Overlook Press |isbn=978-1-5902-0308-8|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book
 |last=Wells
 |first=Paul
 |title=The Animated Bestiary: Animals, Cartoons, and Culture
 |date=November 28, 2008
 |publisher=Rutgers University Press
 |isbn=978-0-8135-4643-8
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book|last=Yockey|first=Steve|title=Cartoon|year=2008|publisher=Samuel French|isbn=978-0-573-66383-3|ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{commonscat|Cartoons}}
{{Wiktionary}}
* [http://xroads.virginia.edu/~MA96/PUCK/intro.html Dan Becker, History of Cartoons]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110225195334/http://historyproject.ucdavis.edu/ic/index.php?region=-1&amp;topic=-1&amp;standard_cal=-1&amp;collection=-1&amp;index=0&amp;per_page=24&amp;query=cartoon Marchand collection] cartoons and photos
* [http://www.learner.org/biographyofamerica/prog04/index.html Stamp Act 1765] with British and American cartoons
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20100731045026/http://www.harpweek.com/ ''Harper's Weekly''] 150 cartoons on elections 1860-1912; Reconstruction topics; Chinese exclusion; plus American Political Prints from the Library of Congress, 1766–1876
* [http://graphicwitness.org/ineye/sitemap.htm &quot;Graphic Witness&quot; political caricatures in history]
* [http://graphicwitness.org/group/keppler.htm Keppler cartoons]
* [http://cnn.com/ALLPOLITICS/analysis/ current editorial cartoons]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20091210212540/http://www.libraries.psu.edu/waringcollections/cartoons/toon.html#index Index of cartoonists in the Fred Waring Collection]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20080517145807/http://www.hnu.edu/ishs/index.htm International Society for Humor Studies]
*{{cite web
 |ref          = {{SfnRef|Fiore|2010}}
 |first        = R.
 |last         = Fiore
 |title        = Adventures in Nomenclature: Literal, Liberal and Freestyle
 |work         = [[The Comics Journal]]
 |publisher    = [[Fantagraphics Books]]
 |url          = http://classic.tcj.com/blog/adventures-in-nomenclature-literal-liberal-and-freestyle/
 |date         = 2010-01-31
 |accessdate   = 2013-02-05
 |archive-url  = https://web.archive.org/web/20150206170000/http://classic.tcj.com/blog/adventures-in-nomenclature-literal-liberal-and-freestyle/
 |archive-date = 2015-02-06
 |url-status   = dead
}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Cartooning| ]]
[[Category:Art genres]]
[[Category:Film and video terminology]]
[[Category:Film genres]]
[[Category:1843 introductions]]</text>
      <sha1>rtg8ljzgny272kb7dayg2jev8oo71k3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
