  <page>
    <title>Charles Evers</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7131</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941090557</id>
      <parentid>941090505</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-16T15:08:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Hitcher vs. Candyman</username>
        <id>20192397</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Media portrayal */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=December 2019}}
{{Infobox officeholder
|birth_name=James Charles Evers
|image = Charles Evers.jpg
|office1 = Mayor of [[Fayette, Mississippi]]
|term_start1 = 1985
|term_end1 = 1989
|successor1 = Kennie Middleton 
|predecessor1 = Kennie Middleton
|term_start2 = 1969
|term_end2 = 1981
|successor2 = Kennie Middleton
|predecessor2 = R. J. Allen 
|birth_date={{birth date and age|1922|09|11}}
|birth_place=[[Decatur, Mississippi|Decatur]], Mississippi, U.S.
|death_date=
|death_place=
|resting_place=
|occupation=[[Civil rights]] activist
|party = [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]] (1978–present)
|otherparty= [[Independent politician|Independent]] (1969–1978)&lt;br /&gt;[[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic]] (before 1960s)
|religion=
|relations=[[Medgar Evers]], [[Myrlie Evers-Williams]]
|alma_mater=[[Alcorn State University]]
|residence=[[Jackson, Mississippi|Jackson]], Mississippi, U.S.
|footnotes=
|allegiance = United States
|branch = [[File:Seal of the United States Department of War.png|25px]] [[United States Army]]
|battles      = [[World War II]]
}}

'''James Charles Evers''' (born September 11, 1922) is an American civil rights activist, disc jockey and former politician. Evers was known for his role in the [[civil rights movement]] along with his younger brother [[Medgar Evers]].&lt;ref name=&quot;biography&quot;/&gt; After serving in [[World War II]], Evers began his career as a disc jockey at WHOC in [[Philadelphia, Mississippi]]. In 1954, he was made the [[National Association for the Advancement of Colored People]] (NAACP) State Voter Registration chairman. After his brother's assassination in 1963, Evers took over his position as field director of the NAACP in Mississippi. As field director, Evers organized and led many demonstrations for the rights of African Americans.&lt;ref name=&quot;biography&quot;/&gt;

In 1969, Evers was named &quot;Man of the Year&quot; by the NAACP.&lt;ref name=&quot;PBS&quot;/&gt; On June 3, 1969, Evers was elected in [[Fayette, Mississippi]], as the first African-American mayor of a ''biracial'' town in the state in the post-[[Reconstruction era (United States)|Reconstruction era]], following passage of the [[Voting Rights Act of 1965]] which enforced constitutional rights for citizens.&lt;ref name=&quot;PBS&quot;/&gt; (The town of [[Mound Bayou, Mississippi|Mound Bayou]] had been incorporated in 1898 as a Negro-only municipality and had had black mayors and council members throughout the 20th century; challenger Earl Lucas was elected the Mound Bayou mayor, defeating incumbent Wesley Liddell on the same day that Evers was elected in Fayette&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Republicans gain in statewide municipal elections&quot;, ''Delta Democrat-Times'' (Greenville MS), June 4, 1969, p1&lt;/ref&gt;)

At the time of Evers's election as mayor, the town of Fayette had a population of 1,600 of which 75% was African-American and almost 25% White; the white officers on the Fayette city police &quot;resigned rather than work under a black administration&quot;, according to the Associated Press. Evers told reporters &quot;I guess we will just have to operate with an all-black police department for the present.  But I am still looking for some whites to join us in helping Fayette grow.&quot;  Evers then outlawed the carrying of firearms within city limits.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;A new day dawns in the Old South&quot;, ''Miami News'', July 7, 1969, p1&lt;/ref&gt;

He unsuccessfully ran for [[Governor of Mississippi|governor]] in 1971 and the [[List of United States Senators from Mississippi|United States Senate]] in 1978, both times as an [[Independent (politician)|Independent]] candidate. In 1989, Evers was defeated for re-election after serving sixteen years as mayor.&lt;ref name=Lost/&gt; After his political career ended, he returned to radio and hosted his own show, &quot;Let’s Talk.&quot;

==Early life and education==
Evers was born in [[Decatur, Mississippi|Decatur]] in [[Newton County, Mississippi|Newton County]] in east central Mississippi, Evers was reared by devoutly Christian parents, Jesse (Wright) and James Evers.&lt;ref name=&quot;MCP&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blackpast.org/aah/evers-james-charles-1922 |title=Evers, James Charles (1922– ) &amp;#124; The Black Past: Remembered and Reclaimed |publisher=Blackpast.org |date=September 11, 1922 |accessdate=March 13, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; He had a younger brother Medgar, with whom he was close. They attended segregated public schools, which were typically underfunded in Mississippi following the exclusion of African Americans from the political system by [[Disfranchisement after Reconstruction era|disenfranchisement]] after 1890.&lt;ref name=&quot;biography&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mswritersandmusicians.com/mississippi-writers/charles-evers|title=Biography of Charles Evers|publisher=msWritersandMusicians.com|accessdate=January 14, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Evers graduated from [[Alcorn State University]] in [[Lorman, Mississippi]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NNDB&quot;/&gt;

==Career==
During [[World War II]], Charles and Medgar Evers both served in the [[United States Army]].&lt;ref name=&quot;biography&quot;/&gt; Charles fell in love with a [[Filipino people|Philippine]] woman while stationed overseas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jacksonfreepress.com/news/2014/jun/11/charles-evers/|title=Charles Evers|publisher=Jacksonfreepress.com|accessdate=January 14, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; He could not marry her and bring her home to his native Mississippi because the state's constitution prohibited interracial marriages.&lt;ref name=&quot;PBS&quot;/&gt;

Before and after the war, Evers participated in bootlegging operations, prostitution, and numbers in Mississippi and Chicago. He revealed this part of his past in 1971 prior to his campaign for governor.&lt;ref name=&quot;biography&quot;/&gt; He said he was not proud of it, but was proud that he had changed his life and left such crime activities far behind.&lt;ref name=&quot;MCP&quot;/&gt;

In 1949, Evers began a career in radio as a [[disc jockey]] at WHOC in [[Philadelphia, Mississippi]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://blues.org/blues_kba_winner/charles-evers-wmpr-jackson-mississippi/|title=Charles Evers, WMPR, Jackson, Mississippi|first=|date=|website=Blues Foundation|language=en-US|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Civil rights activism===
In Mississippi about 1951, brothers Charles and Medgar Evers grew interested in African freedom movements. They were interested in [[Jomo Kenyatta]] and the rise of the [[Kikuyu people|Kikuyu]] tribal resistance to colonialism in [[Kenya]], known as the [[Mau Mau uprising]] as it moved to open violence.&lt;ref name=&quot;PBS&quot;/&gt; Along with his brother, Charles became active in the [[Regional Council of Negro Leadership]] (RCNL), a civil rights organization that promoted self-help and business ownership.&lt;ref name=&quot;Medgar&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.naacp.org/pages/naacp-history-medgar-evers|title=NAACP History: Medgar Evers|publisher=NAACP.org|accessdate=January 14, 2016|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131004234230/http://www.naacp.org/pages/naacp-history-medgar-evers|archivedate=October 4, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Between 1952 and 1955, Evers often spoke at the RCNL's annual conferences in [[Mound Bayou, Mississippi|Mound Bayou]], a town founded by freedmen, on such issues as voting rights.&lt;ref name=AP/&gt;
[[File:JFK and Charles Evers.jpg|right|thumb|220px|Evers (far right) with President [[John F. Kennedy]], June 1963]]
Around 1956, Evers' entrepreneurial gifts and his civil rights activism landed him in trouble in [[Philadelphia, Mississippi|Philadelphia]], Mississippi.&lt;ref name=&quot;biography&quot;/&gt; He left town and moved to Chicago, Illinois. There, he fell into a life of hustling, running numbers for [[organized crime]], and managing prostitutes.&lt;ref name=AP&gt;{{cite news|last=Associated Press|title=Evers Isn't Proud of Past History|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=rpUyAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=HucFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5995,5745001&amp;dq=evers+prostitutes&amp;hl=en|accessdate=November 25, 2012|newspaper=Lawrence Journal-World|date=April 14, 1971}}&lt;/ref&gt; His brother Medgar continued to be involved in civil rights, becoming field secretary and head of the NAACP in Mississippi.&lt;ref name=&quot;Medgar&quot;/&gt;

On June 12, 1963, [[Byron De La Beckwith]], a member of a [[Ku Klux Klan]] chapter, fatally shot Evers' brother, Medgar, in Mississippi as he arrived home from work.&lt;ref name=&quot;Assas&quot;/&gt; Evers died at the hospital in Jackson.&lt;ref name=&quot;Assas&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.history.com/this-day-in-history/medgar-evers-assassinated|title=Medgar Evers Assassinated – Jun 12, 1963|publisher=History.com|accessdate=January 14, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Evers was working in Chicago at the time of his brother's death.&lt;ref name=&quot;PBS&quot;/&gt; He was shocked and deeply upset by his brother's assassination.&lt;ref name=&quot;biography&quot;/&gt; Over the opposition of more establishment figures in the [[National Association for the Advancement of Colored People]] (NAACP) such as [[Roy Wilkins]], Evers took over his brother's post as head of the [[NAACP]] in Mississippi.&lt;ref name=&quot;PBS&quot;/&gt; A decade after his death, Evers and blues musician [[B.B. King]] created the Medgar Evers Homecoming Festival, an annual three-day event held the first week of June in Mississippi.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://mississippiencyclopedia.org/entries/evers-medgar-homecoming-celebration/|title=Medgar Evers Homecoming Celebration|last=|first=|date=|website=Mississippi Encyclopedia|language=en-US|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mayor of Fayette===
In 1969, following passage of the federal [[Voting Rights Act of 1965]], which authorized federal enforcement of the right to vote, Evers was elected mayor of [[Fayette, Mississippi]]. He was the first African-American mayor elected in his state since [[Reconstruction era of the United States|Reconstruction]].&lt;ref name=&quot;PBS&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.pbs.org/wnet/jimcrow/stories_people_evers.html|title=Charles Evers|publisher=[[PBS]]|accessdate=January 14, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a rural area dominated by cotton plantations, Fayette had a majority of black residents.&lt;ref name=Lost/&gt; Its minority white community was known to be hostile toward blacks.&lt;ref name=Lost/&gt;

Evers' election as mayor had great symbolic significance statewide and attracted national attention. The NAACP named Evers the 1969 Man of the Year. Author [[John Updike]] mentioned Evers in his popular novel ''[[Rabbit Redux]]'' (1971).&lt;ref name=&quot;CRP&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mscivilrightsproject.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=360:charles-evers&amp;Itemid=59|title=Charles Evers|publisher=CivilRightsProject.com|accessdate=January 14, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Evers popularized the slogan, &quot;Hands that picked cotton can now pick the mayor.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;CRP&quot;/&gt;

Evers served many terms as mayor of Fayette.&lt;ref name=biography/&gt; Admired by some, he alienated others with his inflexible stands on various issues. Evers did not like to share or delegate power. Evers lost the Democratic primary for mayor in 1981 to [[Kennie Middleton]]. Four years later, Evers defeated Middleton in the primaries and won back the office of mayor. In 1989, Evers lost the nomination once again to political rival Kennie Middleton.&lt;ref name=Lost&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1989/05/05/us/evers-is-defeated-in-fifth-term-bid.html|title=EVERS IS DEFEATED IN FIFTH-TERM BID|work= [[The New York Times]] |accessdate=January 14, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In his response to the defeat, Evers accepted his defeating citing that he was tired and that: &quot;Twenty years is enough. I'm tired of being out front. Let someone else be out front.&quot;&lt;ref name=Lost/&gt;

===Political influence===
Evers endorsed [[Ronald Reagan]] for President of the United States during the [[1980 United States presidential election]].&lt;ref name=&quot;GOP&quot;/&gt; Evers later attracted controversy for his support of judicial nominee [[Charles W. Pickering]], a Republican, who was nominated by President [[George H. W. Bush]] for a seat on the U.S. Court of Appeals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/CHRG-107shrg83959/html/CHRG-107shrg83959.htm|title=NOMINATION OF CHARLES W. PICKERING|publisher=GPO.org|accessdate=January 14, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Evers criticized the NAACP and other organizations for opposing Pickering, as he said the candidate had a record of supporting the civil rights movement in Mississippi.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://votesmart.org/public-statement/24121/nomination-of-charles-w-pickering-sr-of-mississippi-to-be-united-states-circuit-judge-for-the-fifth-circuit-continued|title=Nomination of Charles W. Pickering, Sr., of Mississippi, to be United States Circuit Judge for the Fifth Circuit (continued)|publisher=Vote Smart.com|accessdate=January 14, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Evers has befriended a range of people from [[sharecropper]]s to presidents. He was an informal adviser to politicians as diverse as [[Lyndon B. Johnson]], [[George Wallace|George C. Wallace]], [[Ronald Reagan]] and [[Robert F. Kennedy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;PBS&quot;/&gt; On the other hand, Evers has severely criticized such national leaders as [[Roy Wilkins]], [[Stokely Carmichael]], [[H. Rap Brown]] and [[Louis Farrakhan]] over various issues.&lt;ref name=&quot;PBS&quot;/&gt;

In recent years, Evers has been a member of the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Obama&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msnewsnow.com/story/9677096/evers-comments-on-obama-becoming-1st-african-american-president|title=Evers comments on Obama becoming 1st African-American president|publisher=MSNewsnow.com|accessdate=January 14, 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180615111003/http://www.msnewsnow.com/story/9677096/evers-comments-on-obama-becoming-1st-african-american-president|archive-date=June 15, 2018|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, however, he spoke warmly of the rise of [[Barack Obama]] as the first Black U.S. President.&lt;ref name=&quot;Obama&quot;/&gt;
In 2016, Evers returned to the GOP to support [[Donald Trump presidential campaign, 2016|Donald Trump]] for the presidential nomination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.hattiesburgamerican.com/story/news/politics/2016/03/04/charles-evers-endorses-trump/81341810/|title=Brother of Medgar Evers endorses Trump|author=Bracey Harris|newspaper=[[Hattiesburg American]]|accessdate=March 5, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Electoral campaigns===
In 1968 Evers employed volunteer, armed guards to protect his Jackson residence during the campaign when he competed with six white candidates for the vacant congressional seat which became open when John Bell Williams was elected governor.&lt;ref&gt;Watts, James. (March 4, 1968). &quot;16-year-old questioned in gun incident&quot;. Jackson Daily News. (Jackson, Miss.).&lt;/ref&gt;
In 1971 Evers ran in the gubernatorial general election but was defeated by Democrat [[Bill Waller|William &quot;Bill&quot; Waller]], 601,222 (77 percent) to 172,762 (22.1 percent).&lt;ref name=&quot;crimson&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thecrimson.com/article/1971/12/14/evers-for-everybody-plast-month-charles/|title=Evers For Everybody|publisher=The Crimson.com|accessdate=January 14, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Waller had prosecuted the murder case of suspect Byron De La Beckwith.&lt;ref name=&quot;crimson&quot;/&gt; When Waller gave a victory speech on election night, Evers drove across town to a local TV station to congratulate him. A reporter later wrote that

&lt;blockquote&gt;Waller's aides learned Evers was in the building and tried to hustle the governor-elect out of the studio as soon as the interview ended. They were not quite quick enough. Surrounded by photographers, reporters, and television crews, Evers approached Waller's car just as it was about to pull out. Waller and his wife were in the back seat. &quot;I just wanted to congratulate you,&quot; said Evers. &quot;Whaddya say, Charlie?&quot; boomed Waller. His wife leaned across with a stiff smile and shook the loser's hand. During the campaign Evers told reporters that his main purpose in running was to encourage registration of black voters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Thomas |last=Powers |title=Letter from a Lost Campaign |work=Harper's Magazine |issue=March 1972}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In 1978, Evers ran as an Independent for the U.S. Senate seat vacated by Democrat [[James O. Eastland]].&lt;ref name=&quot;GOP&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.clarionledger.com/story/news/2014/07/11/gates-charles-evers-rich-part-states-history/12560811/|title=Gates: Charles Evers rich part of states history|publisher=Clarion Ledger.com|accessdate=January 14, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; He finished in third place behind his opponents, Democrat [[Maurice Dantin]] and Republican [[Thad Cochran]]. He received 24 percent of the vote, likely siphoning off African-American votes that would have otherwise gone to Dantin.&lt;ref name=&quot;GOP&quot;/&gt; Cochran won the election with a plurality of 45 percent of the vote. With the shift in white voters moving into the Republican Party in the state (and the rest of the South), Cochran was continuously re-elected to his Senate seat.&lt;ref name=&quot;GOP&quot;/&gt; After his failed Senate race, Evers briefly switched political parties and became a [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]].&lt;ref name=&quot;GOP&quot;/&gt;

In 1983, Evers ran as an [[Independent (politics)|Independent]] for governor of Mississippi but lost to the Democrat [[Bill Allain]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Govrace&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=799&amp;dat=19711103&amp;id=jo9PAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=7lEDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=1748,2187362&amp;hl=en|title=The Bryan Times Edition 1983|publisher=Google|accessdate=January 14, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Republican [[Leon Bramlett]] of [[Clarksdale, Mississippi|Clarksdale]], also known as a college [[All-American]] football player, finished second with 39 percent of the vote.&lt;ref name=&quot;Govrace&quot;/&gt;

===Books===
Evers has written two autobiographies or memoirs: ''Evers'' (1971), written with Grace Halsell and self-published; and ''Have No Fear,'' written with [[Andrew Szanton]] and published by [[John Wiley &amp; Sons]] (1997).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3dXw6gR2GgkC&amp;pg=PA284&amp;lpg=PA284&amp;dq=charles+evers+book+evers+1971&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=0-cQXWqvmK&amp;sig=EXeku0RjxVJiFCaDn4gwJtH84hA&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjgud6RrajKAhVHYiYKHfYMAeQQ6AEITzAL#v=onepage&amp;q=charles%20evers%20book%20evers%201971&amp;f=false|title=African American Lives|page=284|via=Google Books|accessdate=January 14, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.publishersweekly.com/978-0-471-12251-7|title=Have No Fear: The Charles Evers Story|publisher=Publisher Weekly.com|accessdate=January 14, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
Evers was briefly married to Christine Evers until their marriage ended in [[annulment]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NNDB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nndb.com/people/827/000164335/|title=Charles Evers|publisher=[[NNDB]]|accessdate=January 14, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1951, Evers married Nannie Laurie.&lt;ref name=&quot;NNDB&quot;/&gt; They moved to [[Philadelphia, Mississippi]]. The couple filed for divorce in June 1974.&lt;ref name=&quot;NNDB&quot;/&gt; Evers has three daughters; Charlene, Pat and Carolyn.&lt;ref name=&quot;NNDB&quot;/&gt; He now lives in [[Jackson, Mississippi]].&lt;ref name=&quot;MCP&quot;/&gt; He is currently the station manager of radio station WMPR 90.1 FM in Jackson, Mississippi.&lt;ref name=&quot;MCP&quot;/&gt;

==Media portrayal==
Evers was portrayed by [[Bill Cobbs]] in the 1996 film ''[[Ghosts of Mississippi]]'' (1996).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CBInl8GHNcEC&amp;pg=PA56&amp;lpg=PA56&amp;dq=bill+cobbs+charles+evers&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=8DTR0DvpZS&amp;sig=ACfU3U10x-O8hqyyzD4abxM9S4LEWXufXQ&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwjwybKuq9bnAhWZHc0KHa2LBUAQ6AEwEHoECA0QAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=bill%20cobbs%20charles%20evers&amp;f=false|title=Whoopi Goldberg and Alec Baldwin Star in Medgar Evers film 'Ghosts of Mississippi'|date=30 December 1996|publisher=[[Jet (magazine)]]|accessdate=16 February 2020|quote=Bill Cobbs portrays Medgar Evers' brother, Charlie Evers}}page 58&lt;/ref&gt;

== Honors ==
* 1969: Evers was named &quot;Man of the Year&quot; by the [[NAACP]].&lt;ref name=&quot;PBS&quot; /&gt; 
* 2012: Evers was honored with a marker on the [[Mississippi Blues Trail]] in Fayette.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://themississippilink.com/2012/04/30/black-disc-jockeys-honored-with-blues-marker/|title=Black disc jockeys honored with blues marker {{!}} The Mississippi Link|last=|first=|date=April 30, 2012|website=The Mississippi Link|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://msbluestrail.org/blues-trail-markers/charles-evers|title=Charles Evers|last=|first=|date=|website=Mississippi Blues Trail|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2017: Evers was inducted into the [[Rhythm and Blues Music Hall of Fame|Rhythm &amp; Blues Hall of Fame]].

==See also==
{{Portal|Biography|Mississippi}}
* [[List of civil rights leaders]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* Charles Evers and [[Andrew Szanton]], ''Have No Fear, Have No *'' {{cite book | last=Beito  | first=David and Linda | author2= | title=Black Maverick: T.R.M. Howard's Fight for Civil Rights and Economic Power | location=Urbana | publisher=University of Illinois Press | year=2009 | isbn=978-0-252-03420-6}}
* {{cite book | last=Dittmer | first=John | author2= | title=Local People: the Struggle for Civil Rights in Mississippi | location=Urbana | publisher=University of Illinois Press | year=1994 | isbn=0-252-02102-9 | url-access=registration | url=https://archive.org/details/localpeoplestrug00ditt }}.
* Charles M. Payne, ''I've Got the Light of Freedom: The Organizing Tradition and the Mississippi Freedom Struggle'' (1945 book).

==External links==
* ''The Rise and Fall of Jim Crow'', PBS [https://www.pbs.org/wnet/jimcrow/stories_people_evers.html]
* 90.1 WMPR, [https://web.archive.org/web/20070722182147/http://www.wmpr901.com/c_evers.php] Jackson Mississippi, Charles Evers station manager : [[blues]], [[urban contemporary gospel]], talk, variety
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20100611144930/http://www.lbjlib.utexas.edu/johnson/archives.hom/oralhistory.hom/Evers-C/evers-c.asp Oral History Interview with Charles Evers, from the Lyndon Baines Johnson Library]
* {{C-SPAN|charlesevers}}

{{Civil rights movement}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Evers, Charles}}
[[Category:African-American mayors]]
[[Category:African-American people in Mississippi politics]]
[[Category:1922 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Activists for African-American civil rights]]
[[Category:Mayors of places in Mississippi]]
[[Category:American army personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:United States Army soldiers]]
[[Category:Alcorn State University alumni]]
[[Category:Mississippi Independents]]
[[Category:Mississippi Republicans]]
[[Category:People from Decatur, Mississippi]]
[[Category:People from Fayette, Mississippi]]
[[Category:Politicians from Chicago]]
[[Category:20th-century African-American activists]]
[[Category:20th-century African-American people]]
[[Category:20th-century American politicians]]
[[Category:African-American DJs]]
[[Category:Radio personalities from Mississippi]]
[[Category:Mississippi Blues Trail]]</text>
      <sha1>tvd9kuwqbug121xxa9mcqwranrfclpr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
