  <page>
    <title>Chambered cairn</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7145</id>
    <revision>
      <id>927694014</id>
      <parentid>924939679</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-11-24T04:47:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>C1614</username>
        <id>7021207</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Bargrennan */ distinguished</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Burial monument, usually constructed during the Neolithic, consisting of a sizeable (usually stone) chamber around and over which a cairn of stones was constructed}}
[[File:Maes Howe Cross Sections.gif|thumb|Cross sections of [[Maeshowe]]]]
A '''chambered cairn''' is a burial monument, usually constructed during the [[Neolithic]], consisting of a sizeable (usually stone) chamber around and over which a [[cairn]] of stones was constructed. Some chambered cairns are also [[passage grave|passage-graves]]. They are found throughout [[Prehistoric Britain|Britain]] and [[Ireland]], with the largest number in [[Scotland]].

Typically, the chamber is larger than a [[cist]], and will contain a larger number of interments, which are either [[Excarnation|excarnated]] bones or inhumations (cremations). Most were situated near a settlement, and served as that community's &quot;graveyard&quot;.

==Scotland==
[[File:Cairn Holy, Galloway.JPG|thumb|200px|left|Cairn Holy I., Galloway]]

===Background===
During the early Neolithic (4000–3300 BC) architectural forms are highly regionalised with timber and earth monuments predominating in the east and stone-chambered cairns in the west. During the later Neolithic (3300–2500 BC) massive circular enclosures and the use of [[grooved ware]] and [[Unstan ware]] pottery emerge.&lt;ref&gt;Noble (2006) p. 15&lt;/ref&gt; Scotland has a particularly large number of chambered cairns; they are found in various different types described below. Along with the excavations of settlements such as [[Skara Brae]], [[Links of Noltland]], [[Barnhouse Settlement|Barnhouse]], [[Rinyo]] and [[Balfarg]] and the complex site at [[Ness of Brodgar]] these cairns provide important clues to the character of civilization in Scotland in the Neolithic.&lt;ref&gt;Barclay (2005) pp. 41, 46&lt;/ref&gt; However the increasing use of [[cropmark]]s to identify Neolithic sites in [[Central Lowlands|lowland]] areas has tended to diminish the relative prominence of these cairns.&lt;ref&gt;Barclay, Gordon &quot;The Neolithic&quot; in Edwards and Ralston (2003) p. 131&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early phases bones of numerous bodies are often found together and it has been argued that this suggests that in death at least, the status of individuals was played down.&lt;ref&gt;Barclay (2005) p. 20&lt;/ref&gt; During the late Neolithic [[henge]] sites were constructed&lt;ref&gt;Barclay (2005) p. 29&lt;/ref&gt; and single burials began to become more commonplace;  by the [[Bronze Age]] it is possible that even where chambered cairns were still being built they had become the burial places of prominent individuals rather than of communities as a whole.&lt;ref name=B5255&gt;Barclay (2005) pp. 52, 55&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Barclay, Gordon &quot;The Neolithic&quot; in Edwards and Ralston (2003) pp. 132–33&lt;/ref&gt;

===Clyde-Carlingford court cairns===
{{Main|Court cairn}}
[[File:Cairnholy2.JPG|right|thumb|200px|[[Cairnholy|Cairnholy II]] – a chambered cairn near [[Newton Stewart]].]]
The Clyde or Clyde-Carlingford type are principally found in northern and western [[Ireland]] and southwestern Scotland. They first were identified as a separate group in the [[Firth of Clyde]] region, hence the name. Over 100 have been identified in Scotland alone. Lacking a significant passage, they are a form of [[gallery grave]]. The burial chamber is normally located at one end of a rectangular or trapezoidal cairn, while a roofless, semi-circular forecourt at the entrance provided access from the outside (although the entrance itself was often blocked), and gives this type of chambered cairn its alternate name of [[Court tomb|court tomb or court cairn]]. These forecourts are typically fronted by large stones and it is thought the area in front of the cairn was used for public rituals of some kind. The chambers were created from large stones set on end, roofed with large flat stones and often sub-divided by slabs into small compartments. They are generally considered to be the earliest in Scotland.&lt;ref&gt;Noble (2006) pp. 104–05&lt;/ref&gt;

Examples include [[Cairnholy|Cairn Holy I and Cairn Holy II]] near [[Newton Stewart]],&lt;ref&gt;Noble (2006) pp. 111–12&lt;/ref&gt; a cairn at [[Port Charlotte, Islay|Port Charlotte]], [[Islay]], which dates to 3900–4000 BC,&lt;ref name=N108&gt;Noble (2006) p. 108&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://canmore.rcahms.gov.uk/en/site/37313/details/islay+port+charlotte/ &quot;Islay, Port Charlotte&quot;]. Canmore. Retrieved 7 August 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; and Monamore, or Meallach's Grave, [[Isle of Arran|Arran]], which may date from the early fifth millennium BC.&lt;ref name=N108/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://canmore.rcahms.gov.uk/en/site/40086/details/arran+monamore+meallach+s+grave/ &quot;Arran, Monamore, Meallach's Grave&quot;]. Canmore. Retrieved 7 August 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Orkney-Cromarty===
[[File:Unstan chambered cairn entrance by Bruce McAdam.jpg|thumb|right|Entrance to [[Unstan Chambered Cairn]], [[Orkney]]]]
The Orkney-Cromarty group is by far the largest and most diverse. It has been subdivided into Yarrows, Camster and Cromarty subtypes but the differences are extremely subtle. The design is of dividing slabs at either side of a rectangular chamber, separating it into compartments or stalls.&lt;ref name=Ritch29&gt;Ritchie, Graham &quot;The Early Peoples&quot; in Omand (2003) p. 29&lt;/ref&gt; The number of these compartments ranges from 4 in the earliest examples to over 24 in an extreme example on [[Orkney]]. The actual shape of the cairn varies from simple circular designs to elaborate 'forecourts' protruding from each end, creating what look like small [[amphitheatres]]. It is likely that these are the result of cultural influences from mainland [[Europe]], as they are similar to designs found in [[France]] and [[Spain]].

Examples include [[Midhowe Chambered Cairn|Midhowe]] on [[Rousay]] and [[Unstan Chambered Cairn]] from the [[Mainland, Orkney|Orkney Mainland]], both of which date from the mid 4th millennium BC and were probably in use over long periods of time. When the latter was excavated in 1884, grave goods were found that gave their name to [[Unstan ware]] pottery.&lt;ref name=Ritch29/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.orkneyjar.com/history/tombs/midhowe/index.html &quot;The Midhowe Stalled Cairn, Rousay&quot;]. Orkneyjar. Retrieved 13 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Fraser13/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historic-scotland.gov.uk/propertyresults/propertydetail.htm?PropID=PL_296&amp;PropName=Unstan%20Chambered%20Cairn &quot;Unstan Chambered Cairn&quot;]. Historic Scotland. Retrieved 21 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wickham-Jones 2007 p. 48&quot;&gt;Wickham-Jones (2007) p. 48&lt;/ref&gt; [[Blackhammer Chambered Cairn|Blackhammer]] cairn on Rousay is another example dating from the 3rd millennium BC.&lt;ref&gt;Wickham-Jones (2007) p. 56&lt;/ref&gt;

The Grey Cairns of Camster in [[Caithness]] are examples of this type from mainland Scotland.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.megalithic.co.uk/article.php?sid=10839 &quot;Grey Cairns of Camster&quot;]. Megalithic Portal. Retrieved 21 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historic-scotland.gov.uk/index/places/propertyresults/propertydetail.htm?PropID=PL_146&amp;PropName=Grey%20Cairns%20Of%20Camster &quot;Grey Cairns of Camster&quot;]. Historic Scotland. Retrieved 21 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Tomb of the Eagles]] on [[South Ronaldsay]] is a stalled cairn that shows some similarities with the later Maeshowe type. It was in use for 800 years or more and numerous bird bones were found here, predominantly [[white-tailed sea eagle]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tomboftheeagles.co.uk/ &quot;Tomb of the Eagles&quot;] tomboftheeagles.co.uk. Retrieved 11 February 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hedges, J. 1990. Tomb of the Eagles: Death and Life in a Stone Age Tribe. New Amsterdam Books. {{ISBN|0-941533-05-0}} p. 73&lt;/ref&gt;

===Maeshowe===
[[File:PicMaesEntrance.jpg|thumb|The interior of [[Maeshowe]]]]
The [[Maeshowe]] group, named after the famous Orkney monument, is among the most elaborate. They appear relatively late and only in Orkney&lt;ref name=Ritch29/&gt; and it is not clear why the use of cairns continued in the north when their construction had largely ceased elsewhere in Scotland. They consist of a central chamber from which lead small compartments, into which burials would be placed. The central chambers are tall and steep-sided and have [[Corbel arch|corbelled]] roofing faced with high quality stone.&lt;ref&gt;Barclay (2005) pp. 40–41&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Vinquoy chambered tomb - geograph.org.uk - 190143.jpg|thumb|left| The entrance to the Vinquoy cairn on [[Eday]]]]
In addition to Maeshowe itself, which was constructed c. 2700 BC, there are various other examples from the Orkney Mainland. These include [[Quanterness]] chambered cairn (3250 BC) in which the remains of 157 individuals were found when excavated in the 1970s,&lt;ref name=Fraser13&gt;Fraser, David (1980) ''Investigations in Neolithic Orkney''. Glasgow Archaeological Journal. '''7''' p. 13. {{ISSN|1471-5767}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wickham-Jones (2007) p. 50&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wickham-Jones (2007) pp. 56–57&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cuween Hill]] near [[Finstown]] which was found to contain the bones of men, dogs and oxen&lt;ref name=&quot;Wickham-Jones 2007 p. 48&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Cuween Hill Cairn, Firth&quot;&gt;[http://www.orkneyjar.com/history/tombs/cuween/index.html &quot;The Cuween Hill Cairn, Firth&quot;]. Orkneyjar. Retrieved 21 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historic-scotland.gov.uk/propertyresults/propertydetail.htm?PropID=PL_084&amp;PropName=Cuween &quot;Cuween Hill Chambered Cairn&quot;]. Historic Scotland. Retrieved 21 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Wideford Hill]] cairn, which dates from 2000 BC.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Cuween Hill Cairn, Firth&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wickham-Jones (2007) pp. 48–49&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://canmore.rcahms.gov.uk/en/site/2483/details/wideford+hill/ &quot;Wideford Hill&quot;]. Canmore. Retrieved 5 August 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

Examples from elsewhere in Orkney are the Vinquoy cairn, found at an elevated location on the north end of the island of  [[Eday]]&lt;ref&gt;Wickham-Jones (2007) p. 58&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Quoyness]] on [[Sanday, Orkney|Sanday]] constructed about 2900 BC and which is surrounded by an arc of Bronze Age mounds.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.orkneyjar.com/history/tombs/quoyness/index.html &quot;The Quoyness Cairn, Sanday&quot;]. Orkneyjar. Retrieved 19 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The central chamber of [[Holm of Papa|Holm of Papa Westray]] South cairn is over 20 metres long.&lt;ref&gt;Wickham-Jones (2007) pp. 62–63&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bookan===
[[File:Huntersquoy chambered cairn, Eday - geograph.org.uk - 224640.jpg|thumb|Huntersquoy chambered cairn, [[Eday]]]]
The Bookan type is named after a cairn found to the north-west of the [[Ring of Brodgar]] in Orkney, which is now a dilapidated oval mound, about 16 metres in diameter.  Excavations in 1861 indicated a rectangular central chamber surrounded by five smaller chambers. Because of the structure's unusual design, it was originally presumed to be an early form. However, later interpretations and further excavation work in 2002 suggested that they have more in common with the later Maeshowe type rather than the stalled Orkney-Cromarty cairns.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.orkneyjar.com/history/worldheritagesite/bookancairn.htm &quot;The Bookan Chambered Cairn, Sandwick&quot;]. Orkneyjar. Retrieved 5 August 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

Huntersquoy cairn on [[Eday]] is a Bookan type cairn with an upper and lower storey.&lt;ref&gt;Haswell-Smith (2004) p. 388&lt;/ref&gt;

===Shetland===
[[File:Chambered Cairn, Muckle Ward, Vementry Isle - geograph.org.uk - 886701.jpg|thumb|The [[Vementry]] cairn]]
The [[Shetland]] or Zetland group are relatively small passage graves, that are [[round cairn|round]] or [[heel-shaped cairn|heel-shaped]] in outline.  The whole chamber is cross or [[trefoil]]-shaped and there are no smaller individual compartments. An example is to be found on the uninhabited island  of [[Vementry]] on the north side of the West [[Mainland, Shetland|Mainland]], where it appears that the cairn may have originally been circular and its distinctive heel shape added as a secondary development, a process repeated elsewhere in Shetland. This probably served to make the cairn more distinctive and the forecourt area more defined.&lt;ref name=N123&gt;Noble (2006) p. 123&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hebridean===
[[File:Chambered Cairn at Rubh' an Dunain - geograph.org.uk - 180698.jpg|thumb|left|Chambered cairn at [[Rubha an Dùnain]]]]
Like the Shetland cairn the [[Hebrides|Hebridean]] group appear relatively late in the Neolithic. They are largely found in the [[Outer Hebrides]], although a mixture of cairn types are found here.&lt;ref name=N123/&gt; These passage graves are usually larger than the Shetland type and are round or have funnel-shaped forecourts, although a few are long cairns – perhaps originally circular but with later tails added.&lt;ref&gt;Noble (2006) p. 124&lt;/ref&gt; They often have a polygonal chamber and a short passage to one end of the cairn.

The [[Rubha an Dùnain]]  peninsula on the island of  [[Skye]] provides an example from the 2nd or 3rd millennium BC.&lt;ref&gt;Armit (1996) p. 73&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://canmore.rcahms.gov.uk/en/site/11028/details/skye+rubh+an+dunain+viking+canal// &quot;Skye, Rubh' An Dunain, 'Viking Canal' &quot;]. Canmore. Retrieved 7 May 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Barpa Langass]] on [[North Uist]] is the best preserved chambered cairn in the Hebrides.&lt;ref&gt;[http://canmore.rcahms.gov.uk/en/site/10236/details/north+uist+barpa+langass/ &quot;North Uist, Barpa Langass&quot;]. Canmore. Retrieved 18 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Armit  (1996) p. 71&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}&lt;br /&gt;

=== Bargrennan ===
{{Main|Bargrennan chambered cairn}}
Bargrennan chambered cairns are a class of passage graves found only in south-west Scotland, in western [[Dumfries and Galloway]] and southern [[Ayrshire]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=iaumAwAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=SA4-PA22&amp;dq=bargrennan&amp;pg=SA4-PA22#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=A View from the West: The Neolithic of the Irish Sea Zone|last=Cummings|first=Vicki|publisher=Oxbow books|year=2009|isbn=978-1842173626|location=Oxford|pages=337}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Cummings|first=Vicki|date=2003|title=Monuments and Landscape: Encounters at cairnholy|url=http://www.dgnhas.org.uk/tdgnhas/3077.pdf#page=29|journal=Transactions of the Dumfriesshire and Galloway Natural History and Antiquarian Society|volume=77|pages=25|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190729192353/http://www.dgnhas.org.uk/tdgnhas/3077.pdf|archive-date=29 July 2019|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; As well as being structurally different to the nearby Clyde cairns, Bargrennan cairns are distinguished by their siting and distribution; they are found in upland, inland areas of Galloway and Ayrshire.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

===Bronze Age===
[[File:Corrimony Chambered Cairn - 3 - 29042008.JPG|thumb|Corrimony chambered cairn]]
In addition to the increasing prominence of individual burials,&lt;ref name=B5255/&gt; during the Bronze Age regional differences in architecture in Scotland became more pronounced.&lt;ref&gt;Barclay (2005) p. 49&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Clava cairn]]s date from this period, with about 50 cairns of this type in the [[Inverness]] area.&lt;ref&gt;Barclay, Gordon &quot;The Neolithic&quot; in Edwards &amp; Ralston (2003) p. 136&lt;/ref&gt; [[Corrimony chambered cairn]] near [[Drumnadrochit]] is an example dated to 2000 BC or older. The only surviving evidence of burial was a stain indicating the presence of a single body. The cairn is surrounded by a circle of 11 standing stones.&lt;ref&gt;Barclay (2005) p. 55&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.glenaffric.org/corrimony.html &quot;Corrimony Chambered Cairn &amp; RSPB Nature Reserve&quot;]. Glen Affric.org. Retrieved 21 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historic-scotland.gov.uk/propertyresults/propertydetail.htm?PropID=PL_073&amp;PropName=Corrimony%20Chambered%20Cairn &quot;Corrimony Chambered Cairn&quot;]. Historic Scotland. Retrieved 21 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The cairns at [[Balnuaran of Clava]] are of a similar date. The largest of three is the north-east cairn, which was partially reconstructed in the 19th century and the central cairn may have been used as a funeral pyre.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;A Visitors’ Guide to Balnuaran of Clava: A prehistoric cemetery.'' (2012) Historic Scotland.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bradley, Richard (1996) ''Excavation at Balnuaran of Clava, 1994 and 1995''. Highland Council.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theheritagetrail.co.uk/early%20ages/clava_cairns.htm &quot;The Cairns of Clava, Scottish Highlands&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120625153004/http://www.theheritagetrail.co.uk/early%20ages/clava_cairns.htm |date=2012-06-25 }}. The Heritage Trail. Retrieved 19 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

Glebe cairn in [[Kilmartin Glen]] in [[Argyll]] dates from 1700 BC and has two stone cists inside one of which a jet necklace was found during 19th century excavations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.saintsandstones.net/stones-glebe-journey.htm &quot;Glebe cairn&quot;]. Saints and Stones. Retrieved 4 August 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://canmore.rcahms.gov.uk/en/site/39537/details/kilmartin+glebe/ &quot;Kilmartin Glebe&quot;]. Canmore. Retrieved 4 August 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; There are numerous prehistoric sites in the vicinity including Nether Largie North cairn, which was entirely removed and rebuilt during excavations in 1930.&lt;ref&gt;[http://canmore.rcahms.gov.uk/en/site/39482/details/nether+largie+north/ &quot;Nether Largie North&quot;]. Canmore. Retrieved 5 August 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Wales==
[[File:Parc le Breos, Gwyr y cwrt.JPG|right|thumb|&lt;center&gt;[[Parc Cwm long cairn]] forecourt – from the south east&lt;/center&gt;|alt=A short dry-stone wall retains boulders to form a cairn. The wall is missing at the front, right section, where the rubble has tumbled out, leaving a (previously covered) orthostat exposed. The wall forms a courtyard at the cromlech's entrance. Flat ground of short grass surrounds the cairn. The background is of shaded trees, mainly in leaf.]]
[[File:MaenyBardd.jpg|thumb|Chambered cairn at Maen y Bardd, Conwy, Wales]]

===Chambered long cairns===
There are 18 SAM{{clarify|date=October 2012}} listed:
*[[Siambr gladdu Din Dryfol]], [[Aberffraw]]
*[[Carnedd gellog hir Pen y Wyrlod]], [[Talgarth]]
*[[Llety'r Filiast|Siambr gladdu Llety'r Filiast]], [[Llandudno]]
*[[Siambr gladdu Bachwen]], [[Clynnog]]
*[[Siambr gladdu Rhiw]], [[Aberdaron]]
*[[Siambr gladdu Maen y Bardd]], [[Caerhun]]
*[[Siambr gladdu Ystum-Cegid]], [[Llanystumdwy]]
*[[Siambr gladdu Caer-Dynni]], [[Cricieth]]
*[[Siambr gladdu Capel Garmon]], [[Bro Garmon]], [[Conwy]]
*[[Siambr gladdu Tyddyn Bleiddyn]], [[Cefn Meiriadog]]
*[[Siambr gladdu Hendre-Waelod]], [[Llansanffraid Glan Conwy]]
*[[Parc Cwm long cairn]], [[Parc le Breos]], [[Gower Peninsula]]
*[[Siambr gladdu Cefn Bryn]], [[Llanilltud Gŵyr]]
*[[Siambr gladdu Dyffryn]], [[Dyffryn Ardudwy]]
*[[Siambr gladdu Carneddau Hengwm]], [[Dyffryn Ardudwy]]
*[[Siambr gladdu Cors-y-Gedol]], [[Dyffryn Ardudwy]]
*[[Siambr gladdu Tan-y-Coed]], [[Llandrillo, Denbighshire|Llandrillo]]
*[[Siambr gladdu Gorllewin Bron-y-Foel]], [[Dyffryn Ardudwy]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.whatdotheyknow.com/request/15714/response/38315/attach/html/2/SAMs%20by%20UA.xls.html CADW all Wales Data]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Chambered round cairns===
* [[Siambr gladdu]] [[Bryn yr Hen Bobl]], [[Llanddaniel Fab]], [[Môn]]
* [[Siambr gladdu Gelli]], [[Llanfair-ar-y-bryn]], [[Sir Gaerfyrddin]]
* [[Siambr gladdu Cefnamwlch]], [[Tudweiliog]], [[Gwynedd]]
* [[Siambr galddu Afon y Dolau Gwynion]], uwch ben [[Llyn Llanwddyn]], [[Llanwddyn]], [[Powys]]

==See also==
* [[Unchambered long cairn]]
* [[Oldest buildings in Scotland]]
* [[Heart of Neolithic Orkney]] World Heritage Site
* [[Prehistoric Orkney]]
* [[Severn-Cotswold tomb]], a type of [[chambered long barrow]] found in England and Wales
* [[Heel-shaped cairn]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
* Armit, Ian (1996) ''The archaeology of Skye and the Western Isles''. Edinburgh University Press/Historic Scotland.
* Barclay, Gordon (2005) ''Farmers, Temples and Tombs: Scotland in the Neolithic and Early Bronze Age''. Birlinn/Historic Scotland. {{ISBN|1841583804}}
* Edwards, Kevin J. &amp; Ralston, Ian B.M. (Eds) (2003) ''Scotland After the Ice Age: Environment, Archaeology and History, 8000 BC – AD 1000''. Edinburgh. Edinburgh University Press. {{ISBN|0-7486-1736-1}}
* {{Haswell-Smith}}
* Noble, Gordon (2006) ''Neolithic Scotland: Timber, Stone, Earth and Fire.'' Edinburgh University Press. {{ISBN|0-7486-2338-8}}
* Omand, Donald (ed.) (2003) ''The Orkney Book''. Edinburgh. Birlinn. {{ISBN|1-84158-254-9}}
* Wickham-Jones, Caroline (2007) ''Orkney: A&lt;!--sic--&gt; Historical Guide''. Edinburgh. [[Birlinn Limited|Birlinn]]. {{ISBN|1841585963}}

{{Prehistoric Scotland}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Chambered Cairn}}
[[Category:Chambered cairns| ]]</text>
      <sha1>sf8d8yoq6xvwxhssq2latoc8bo9zjng</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
