  <page>
    <title>William Kidd</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7119</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943121669</id>
      <parentid>940413046</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T23:53:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2A02:C7F:AE1C:CB00:DEF:311E:324E:1160</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>It wasn't assassin's creed 4 it was 3, and only four missions focused on finding the map pieces, not the navel missions.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Scottish sailor who was tried and executed for piracy after returning from a voyage to the Indian Ocean}}
{{about|the 17th-century pirate|the 15th-century pirate|William Kyd|the outlaw in the American West|Billy the Kid|other people with the same birth name|William Kidd (disambiguation)}}
{{redirects|Captain Kidd}}
{{Use British English|date=May 2012}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2020}}
{{Infobox pirate
|name = William Kidd
|birth_date = c. 1655
|death_date = {{death date and age|df=yes|1701|5|23|1654|1|22}}
|image = William Kidd.jpg
|caption=
|nickname=
|type= [[Pirate]] / [[Privateer]]
|birth_place = Dundee, Scotland
|death_place = [[Wapping]], England
|allegiance= {{flag|Kingdom of Scotland}}
|relatives = Shea Dauphinée, Michael Dauphinée, James Dauphinée 
| serviceyears = 
| base of operations = 
| rank = 
| commands = ''Blessed William''&lt;br/&gt;''[[Adventure Galley]]''
| battles = 
| wealth = 
| laterwork = 
| signature = 
| signature_alt = 
| signature_size = 
}}
'''William Kidd''', also known as '''Captain William Kidd''' or simply '''Captain Kidd''' ([[circa|c.]] 1655 – 23 May 1701),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Johnson|first1=Ben|title=Captain William Kidd|url=http://www.historic-uk.com/HistoryUK/HistoryofScotland/Captain-William-Kidd/|website=Historic UK|accessdate=28 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; was a Scottish sailor who was tried and executed for [[piracy]] after returning from a voyage to the [[Indian Ocean]]. Some modern historians, for example Sir Cornelius Neale Dalton (see [[#Books|Books]]), deem his piratical reputation unjust.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.historytoday.com/archive/months-past/execution-captain-kidd|title=Execution of Captain Kidd {{!}} History Today|website=www.historytoday.com|access-date=19 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biography==
===Early life and education===
Kidd was born in [[Dundee]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.historic-uk.com/HistoryUK/HistoryofScotland/Captain-William-Kidd/|title=Captain William Kidd|accessdate=28 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Scotland]].  [[Greenock]] was given as his place of birth (although some say it was [[Dundee]]),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.undiscoveredscotland.co.uk/usbiography/k/williamkidd.html|title=William Kidd: Biography on Undiscovered Scotland|website=www.undiscoveredscotland.co.uk|access-date=19 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; and his age as 41 in testimony under oath at the High Court of the Admiralty in October 1694 or 1695.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/africaandindianocean/madagascar/11590638/Captain-William-Kidd-privateer-or-pirate.html|title=Captain William Kidd: privateer or pirate?|last=Laing|first=Aislinn|date=7 May 2015|access-date=19 November 2019|language=en-GB|issn=0307-1235}}&lt;/ref&gt; A local society supported the family financially after the death of the father.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.angelfire.com/mi4/polcrt/Kidd.html|title=Courtly Lives – The Kidd Family|website=www.angelfire.com|access-date=19 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The myth that his &quot;father was thought to have been a [[Church of Scotland]] minister&quot; has been discounted, insofar as there is no mention of the name in comprehensive [[Church of Scotland]] records for the period. Others still hold the contrary view.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Pirates: William Kidd |publisher=Genealogy &amp; Family History Achievements Heraldry and Research |url=http://www.achievements.co.uk/articles/william_kidd.html |accessdate=13 December 2007 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071217032212/http://www.achievements.co.uk/articles/william_kidd.html |archivedate=17 December 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author = Hawkins, Paul | date = 2002 | title = Captain William Kidd Web Site: History | format = self-published historical site | url = http://www.captainkidd.pwp.blueyonder.co.uk/  | access-date = 7 January 2017 | url-status = dead | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20081023184854/http://www.captainkidd.pwp.blueyonder.co.uk/ | archive-date = 23 October 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Early voyages===
Kidd later settled in the newly anglicized [[New York City]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://boroughsofthedead.com/captain-kidd-new-york-city/|title=Captain Kidd in New York City {{!}} Boroughs of the Dead|language=en-US|access-date=19 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; where he befriended many prominent colonial citizens, including three governors.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.boweryboyshistory.com/2010/01/infamous-captain-kidd-and-his-swanky.html|title=Captain Kidd and his swanky New York waterfront home|last=Boys|first=Bowery|date=27 January 2010|website=The Bowery Boys: New York City History|language=en|access-date=19 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some published information suggests that he was a seaman's [[apprentice]] on a pirate ship during this time, before partaking in his more famous seagoing exploits.

By 1689, Kidd was a member of a French–English pirate crew sailing the [[Caribbean Sea|Caribbean]] under Captain [[Jean Fantin]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://ferminiatures.com/shop/magna-historica/jean-fantin-st-kitts-1689-limited-edition/|title=Jean Fantin, St. Kitts, 1689 LIMITED EDITION|website=Ferminiatures.com|language=en-US|access-date=19 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; During one of their voyages, Kidd and other crew members mutinied, ousting the captain and sailing to the British colony of [[Nevis]].&lt;ref name=&quot;The Pirate Hunter&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Zacks|first1=Richard|title=The Pirate Hunter: The True Story of Captain Kidd|date=2003|publisher=Hachette Books|location=New York|isbn=9781401398187|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=TbqZAAAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|accessdate=31 August 2017|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; There they renamed the ship ''[[Blessed William]]'', and Kidd became captain either as a result of election by the ship's crew, or by appointment of [[Christopher Codrington]], governor of the island of Nevis.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/2017/05/23/day-1701-pirate-caribbean-william-captain-kidd-meets-end-execution/|title=On this day in 1701: Pirate of the Caribbean, William 'Captain' Kidd, meets his end at Execution Dock|last=Selwood|first=Dominic|date=23 May 2017|work=The Telegraph|access-date=19 November 2019|language=en-GB|issn=0307-1235}}&lt;/ref&gt; Captain Kidd, an experienced leader and sailor by that time, and the ''Blessed William'' became part of Codrington's small fleet assembled to defend Nevis from the French, with whom the English were at war.&lt;ref name=Hubbard&gt;{{cite book|last1=Hubbard|first1=Vincent|title=A History of St. Kitts|date=2002|publisher=Macmillan Caribbean|isbn=9780333747605|page=[https://archive.org/details/historyofstkitts00vinc/page/52 52]|url=https://archive.org/details/historyofstkitts00vinc/page/52}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Vincent&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Hubbard|first1=Vincent|title=Swords, Ships &amp; Sugar|date=2002|publisher=Premiere Editions International, Inc.|location=Corvallis|isbn=9781891519055|pages=104–105}}&lt;/ref&gt; The governor did not pay the sailors for their defensive services, telling them instead to take their pay from the French. Kidd and his men attacked the French island of [[Marie-Galante]], destroying its only town and looting the area, and gathering for themselves around 2,000 pounds sterling.
Later, during the [[War of the Grand Alliance]], on commissions from the provinces of [[Province of New York|New York]] and [[Province of Massachusetts Bay|Massachusetts Bay]], Kidd captured an enemy [[privateer]] off the [[New England]] coast.&lt;ref name=EB1911&gt;{{cite EB1911| wstitle =Kidd, William| volume=15 |page=783–784}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly afterwards, he was awarded [[Pound sterling|£]]150 for successful privateering in the [[Caribbean]], and one year later, [[Robert Culliford|Captain Robert Culliford]], a notorious pirate, stole Kidd's ship while he was ashore at [[Antigua]] in the [[West Indies]]. In 1695, [[William III of England]] appointed [[Richard Coote, 1st Earl of Bellomont]], governor in place of the corrupt [[Benjamin Fletcher]], who was known for accepting bribes to allow illegal trading of pirate loot.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | date = 2001 | title = The Columbia Encyclopedia | chapter = Bellomont, Richard Coote, Earl of | edition = 6th | url = http://www.bartleby.com/65/be/Bellomon.html | access-date = 13 December 2007 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20070618070500/http://bartleby.com/65/be/Bellomon.html | archive-date = 18 June 2007 | url-status = dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[New York City]], Kidd was active in the building of [[Trinity Church, New York]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.trinitywallstreet.org/history/?timeline|title=History|date=26 March 2016|work=trinitywallstreet.org|accessdate=8 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;trinity kidd blog&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.trinitywallstreet.org/news/blogs/the-archivists-mailbag/question-of-the-day-trinitys-very-own-pirate | title=Question of the Day: Trinity's Very Own Pirate? | publisher=Trinity Church | work=The Archivist's Mailbag | date=19 November 2008 | access-date=18 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 16 May 1691, Kidd married Sarah Bradley Cox Oort,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.wired.com/beyond-the-beyond/2018/02/mrs-captain-kidd-shore-side-piratess/|title=Mrs. Captain Kidd, shore-side piratess|last=Sterling|first=Bruce|date=2 February 2018|work=Wired|access-date=19 November 2019|language=en-US|issn=1059-1028}}&lt;/ref&gt; an English woman in her early twenties, who had already been twice widowed and was one of the wealthiest women in New York, largely because of her inheritance from her first husband.&lt;ref&gt;Zacks, pp. 82–83, 86.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Preparing his expedition===
[[File:Captain Kidd in New York Harbor cph.3f06373.jpg|thumb|250px|''Captain Kidd in New York Harbor'', in a c. 1920 painting by [[Jean Leon Gerome Ferris]]]]
On 11 December 1695, Bellomont was governing New York, [[Massachusetts]], and [[New Hampshire]], and he asked the &quot;trusty and well beloved Captain Kidd&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hamilton, 1961 p&quot;&gt;Hamilton, (1961) p.?&lt;/ref&gt; to attack [[Thomas Tew]], John Ireland, Thomas Wake, William Maze, and all others who associated themselves with pirates, along with any enemy French ships. It would have been viewed as disloyalty to the crown to turn down this request, carrying much social stigma, making it difficult for Kidd to say no. The request preceded the voyage which established Kidd's reputation as a pirate and marked his image in history and [[folklore]].

Four-fifths of the cost for the venture was paid for by noble lords, who were among the most powerful men in England: the [[Edward Russell, 1st Earl of Orford|Earl of Orford]], the Baron of Romney, the [[Charles Talbot, 1st Duke of Shrewsbury|Duke of Shrewsbury]], and [[John Somers, 1st Baron Somers|Sir John Somers]]. Kidd was presented with a [[letter of marque]], signed personally by King [[William III of England]]. This letter reserved 10% of the loot for the Crown, and Henry Gilbert's ''The Book of Pirates'' suggests that the King may have fronted some of the money for the voyage himself. Kidd and his acquaintance Colonel [[Robert Livingston the Elder|Robert Livingston]] orchestrated the whole plan; they sought additional funding from a merchant named [[Blackham baronets|Sir Richard Blackham]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.gilderlehrman.org/content/secret-agreement-between-pirate-hunters-1696 |title=A secret agreement between pirate hunters, 1696 |publisher=[[Gilder Lehrman Institute of American History]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kidd also had to sell his ship ''Antigua'' to raise funds.

The new ship, ''[[Adventure Galley]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title =Buccaneers and Pirates of Our Coasts&quot; &quot;The Real Captain Kidd| author =Frank R. Stockton| publisher =The Baldwin Online Children's Literature Project| url =http://www.mainlesson.com/display.php?author=stockton&amp;book=buccaneers&amp;story=kidd| accessdate =13 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; was well suited to the task of catching pirates, weighing over 284 [[Builder's Old Measurement|tons burthen]] and equipped with 34 [[Naval artillery in the Age of Sail|cannon]], oars, and 150 men. The oars were a key advantage, as they enabled ''Adventure Galley'' to manoeuvre in a battle when the winds had calmed and other ships were dead in the water. Kidd took pride in personally selecting the crew, choosing only those whom he deemed to be the best and most loyal officers.

{{quote|As the Adventure Galley sailed down the [[Thames]], Kidd unaccountably failed to salute a Navy yacht at Greenwich, as custom dictated. The Navy yacht then fired a shot to make him show respect, and Kidd's crew responded with an astounding display of impudence – by turning and slapping their backsides in [disdain].&lt;ref&gt;Botting (1978) p.106&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Because of Kidd's refusal to salute, the Navy vessel's captain retaliated by [[impressment|pressing]] much of Kidd's crew into [[Royal Navy|naval service]], despite rampant protests. Thus short-handed, Kidd sailed for New York City, capturing a French vessel en route (which was legal under the terms of his commission). To make up for the lack of officers, Kidd picked up replacement crew in New York, the vast majority of whom were known and hardened criminals, some undoubtedly former pirates.

Among Kidd's officers was his [[quartermaster]] [[Hendrick van der Heul]]. The quartermaster was considered &quot;second in command&quot; to the captain in pirate culture of this era. It is not clear, however, if van der Heul exercised this degree of responsibility, because Kidd was nominally a privateer. Van der Heul is also noteworthy because he may have been African or of African descent. A contemporary source describes him as a &quot;small black Man&quot;. If van der Heul was indeed of African ancestry, this fact would make him the highest ranking black pirate so far identified. Van der Heul went on to become a [[master's mate]] on a merchant vessel, and was never convicted of piracy.

===Hunting for pirates===
In September 1696, Kidd [[Weigh anchor|weighed anchor]] and set course for the [[Cape of Good Hope]]. A third of his crew died on the [[Comoros]] due to an outbreak of [[cholera]], the brand-new ship developed many leaks, and he failed to find the pirates whom he expected to encounter off [[Madagascar]].

As it became obvious that his ambitious enterprise was failing, Kidd became desperate to cover its costs. But, once again, he failed to attack several ships when given a chance, including a Dutchman and a New York privateer. Some of the crew deserted Kidd the next time that ''Adventure Galley'' anchored offshore, and those who decided to stay on made constant open threats of [[mutiny]].

[[File:Pyle pirate relaxing2.jpg|left|thumb|180px|Howard Pyle's fanciful painting of Kidd and his ship, ''Adventure Galley'', in [[New York Harbor]]]]
[[File:Pyle pirates burying2.jpg|left|thumb|180px|Howard Pyle's fanciful painting of Kidd burying treasure]]
Kidd killed one of his own crewmen on 30 October 1697. Kidd's gunner William Moore was on deck sharpening a [[chisel]] when a Dutch ship appeared. Moore urged Kidd to attack the Dutchman, an act not only piratical but also certain to anger Dutch-born King William. Kidd refused, calling Moore a lousy dog. Moore retorted, &quot;If I am a lousy dog, you have made me so; you have brought me to ruin and many more.&quot; Kidd snatched up and heaved an ironbound bucket at Moore. Moore fell to the deck with a [[Skull fracture|fractured skull]] and died the following day.&lt;ref&gt;Cordingly (1995), p.183&lt;/ref&gt;

Seventeenth-century English [[admiralty law]] allowed captains great leeway in using violence against their crew, but outright murder was not permitted. Yet Kidd seemed unconcerned, later explaining to his surgeon that he had &quot;good friends in England, that will bring me off for that&quot;.

===Accusations of piracy===
Acts of savagery on Kidd's part were reported by escaped prisoners, who told stories of being hoisted up by the arms and &quot;drubbed&quot; (thrashed) with a drawn [[cutlass]]. On one occasion, crew members ransacked the trading ship ''Mary'' and tortured several of its crew members while Kidd and the other captain, Thomas Parker, conversed privately in Kidd's cabin. When Kidd found out what had happened, he was outraged and forced his men to return most of the stolen property.{{citation needed|date=April 2018}}

Kidd was declared a pirate very early in his voyage by a Royal Navy officer, to whom he had promised &quot;thirty men or so&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hamilton, 1961 p&quot;/&gt; Kidd sailed away during the night to preserve his crew, rather than subject them to Royal Navy [[impressment]].{{citation needed|date=April 2018}}

On 30 January 1698, Kidd raised French colours and took his greatest prize, the 400-ton ''[[Quedagh Merchant]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Pirates of the High Seas – Capt. William Kidd |url=http://library.thinkquest.org/05aug/01841/kidd.html |accessdate=13 December 2007 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110728104918/http://library.thinkquest.org/05aug/01841/kidd.html |archivedate=28 July 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title =&quot;Quedagh Merchant&quot; (ship)| publisher =Encyclopedia Online| url =http://www.britannica.com/eb/topic-486764/Quedagh-Merchant| accessdate =13 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; an Indian ship hired by [[Armenia]]n merchants that was loaded with [[satin]]s, [[muslin]]s, gold, silver, an incredible variety of [[East India]]n [[merchandise]], as well as extremely valuable silks. The captain of ''Quedagh Merchant'' was an Englishman named Wright, who had purchased passes from the French East India Company promising him the protection of the French Crown. After realising the captain of the taken vessel was an Englishman, Kidd tried to persuade his crew to return the ship to its owners,{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} but they refused, claiming that their prey was perfectly legal, as Kidd was commissioned to take French ships, and that an Armenian ship counted as French, if it had French passes. In an attempt to maintain his tenuous control over his crew, Kidd relented and kept the prize. When this news reached England, it confirmed Kidd's reputation as a pirate, and various naval commanders were ordered to &quot;pursue and seize the said Kidd and his accomplices&quot; for the &quot;notorious piracies&quot; they had committed.&lt;ref&gt;Hamilton, (1961)&lt;/ref&gt;

Kidd kept the French sea passes of the ''Quedagh Merchant'', as well as the vessel itself. While the passes were at best a dubious defence of his capture, British admiralty and vice-admiralty courts (especially in North America) heretofore had often winked at privateers' excesses into piracy, and Kidd may have been hoping that the passes would provide the legal fig leaf that would allow him to keep ''Quedagh Merchant'' and her cargo. Renaming the seized merchantman ''Adventure Prize'', he set sail for [[Madagascar]].{{citation needed|date=April 2018}}

On 1 April 1698, Kidd reached Madagascar. After meeting privately with trader [[Tempest Rogers]] (who would later be accused of trading and selling Kidd's looted East India goods),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Office|first1=Great Britain Public Record|title=Calendar of State Papers: Colonial Series ...|date=1908|publisher=Longman|location=London|pages=486–487|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=LBQFAAAAYAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|accessdate=16 August 2017|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; he found the first pirate of his voyage, [[Robert Culliford]] (the same man who had stolen Kidd's ship years before) and his crew aboard ''Mocha Frigate''. Two contradictory accounts exist of how Kidd reacted to his encounter with Culliford. According to ''The General History of the Pirates'', published more than 25 years after the event by an author whose identity remains in dispute, Kidd made peaceful overtures to Culliford: he &quot;drank their Captain's health&quot;, swearing that &quot;he was in every respect their Brother&quot;, and gave Culliford &quot;a Present of an Anchor and some Guns&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Charles Johnson (1728). ''The History of the Pyrates'', p. 75.&lt;/ref&gt; This account appears to be based on the testimony of Kidd's crewmen Joseph Palmer and Robert Bradinham at his trial. The other version was presented by Richard Zacks in his 2002 book ''The Pirate Hunter: The True Story of Captain Kidd''. According to Zacks, Kidd was unaware that Culliford had only about 20 crew with him, and felt ill-manned and ill-equipped to take ''Mocha Frigate'' until his two prize ships and crews arrived, so he decided not to molest Culliford until these reinforcements came. After ''Adventure Prize'' and ''Rouparelle'' came in, Kidd ordered his crew to attack Culliford's ''Mocha Frigate''. However, his crew, despite their previous eagerness to seize any available prize, refused to attack Culliford and threatened instead to shoot Kidd. Zacks does not refer to any source for his version of events.&lt;ref&gt;Zacks, p. 185-86.&lt;/ref&gt;

Both accounts agree that most of Kidd's men now abandoned him for Culliford. Only 13 remained with ''Adventure Galley''. Deciding to return home, Kidd left the ''[[Adventure Galley]]'' behind, ordering her to be burnt because she had become worm-eaten and leaky. Before burning the ship, he was able to salvage every last scrap of metal, such as hinges. With the loyal remnant of his crew, he returned to the Caribbean aboard the ''Adventure Prize''.{{citation needed|date=April 2018}} Some of his crew later returned to America on their own as passengers aboard [[Giles Shelley]]'s ship ''Nassau''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jameson - Privateering and Piracy&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Jameson|first1=John Franklin|title=Privateering and Piracy in the Colonial Period by J. Franklin Jameson|date=1923|publisher=Macmillan|location=New York|url=http://www.gutenberg.org/files/24882/24882-h/24882-h.htm|accessdate=26 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Trial and execution===
[[File:Hanging of William Kidd.jpg|thumb|upright|Captain Kidd, [[Gibbeting|gibbeted]], following his execution in 1701.]]
Prior to returning to New York City, Kidd knew that he was a wanted pirate, and that several English [[men-of-war]] were searching for him. Realizing that ''Adventure Prize'' was a marked vessel, he cached it in the [[Caribbean Sea]], sold off his remaining plundered goods through pirate and fence [[William Burke (pirate)|William Burke]],&lt;ref name=&quot;The Danish West Indies&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Westergaard|first1=Waldemar|title=The Danish West Indies Under Company Rule (1671–1754): With a Supplementary Chapter, 1755–1917|date=1917|publisher=Macmillan|location=New York|pages=115–118|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=EzoYAAAAYAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|accessdate=11 July 2017|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; and continued toward New York aboard a sloop. He deposited some of his treasure on [[Gardiners Island]], hoping to use his knowledge of its location as a bargaining tool.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://longislandgenealogy.com/pirates.html|title=Long Island Genealogy|website=longislandgenealogy.com|access-date=29 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kidd found himself in [[Oyster Bay (hamlet), New York|Oyster Bay]], as a way of avoiding his mutinous crew who gathered in New York. In order to avoid them, Kidd sailed {{convert|120|nmi}} around the eastern tip of Long Island, and then doubled back {{convert|90|nmi}} along the Sound to Oyster Bay. He felt this was a safer passage than the highly trafficked [[The Narrows|Narrows]] between [[Staten Island]] and [[Brooklyn]].&lt;ref&gt;Richard Zacks, The Pirate Hunter: The True Story of Captain Kidd (Hyperion, 2003)&lt;/ref&gt;

Bellomont (an investor) was away in Boston, Massachusetts. Aware of the accusations against Kidd, Bellomont was justifiably afraid of being implicated in piracy himself, and knew that presenting Kidd to England in chains was his best chance to save himself. He lured Kidd into Boston with false promises of clemency,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title =The Quest for the Armenian Vessel, Quedagh Merchant| publisher =AYAS Nautical Research Club| url =http://www.amarasonline.com/amaras/events/cillicia-flyer-1.pdf|format=PDF| accessdate =13 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; then ordered him arrested on 6 July 1699. Kidd was placed in [[Boston Gaol (Massachusetts)|Stone Prison]], spending most of the time in [[solitary confinement]]. His wife, Sarah, was also imprisoned. The conditions of Kidd's imprisonment were extremely harsh, and appear to have driven him at least temporarily insane.{{citation needed|date=May 2011}} By then, Bellomont had turned against Kidd and other pirates, writing that the inhabitants of [[Long Island]] were &quot;a lawless and unruly people&quot; protecting pirates who had &quot;settled among them&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newsday.com/community/guide/lihistory/ny-hs324,0,7442594.story|title=Legend of Capt. Kidd|date=12 April 2009|work=Legend of Capt. Kidd|publisher=Newsday|access-date=16 February 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080515231149/http://www.newsday.com/community/guide/lihistory/ny-hs324,0,7442594.story|archive-date=15 May 2008|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After over a year, Kidd was sent to England for questioning by the [[Parliament of England]].{{citation needed|date=January 2017}} The new Tory ministry hoped to use Kidd as a tool to discredit the Whigs who had backed him, but Kidd refused to name names, naively confident his patrons would reward his loyalty by interceding on his behalf. There is speculation that he probably would have been spared had he talked. Finding Kidd politically useless, the Tory leaders sent him to stand trial before the [[Admiralty court|High Court of Admiralty]] in London, for the charges of piracy on high seas and the murder of William Moore. Whilst awaiting trial, Kidd was confined in the infamous [[Newgate Prison]], and wrote several letters to King William requesting clemency.{{citation needed|date=April 2018}}

Kidd had two lawyers to assist in his defence.&lt;ref&gt;Zacks, p. 364.&lt;/ref&gt; He was shocked to learn at his trial that he was charged with murder. He was found guilty on all charges (murder and five counts of piracy) and sentenced to death. He was hanged in a public execution on 23 May 1701, at [[Execution Dock]], [[Wapping]], in London.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; He was hanged two times. On the first attempt, the hangman's rope broke and Kidd survived. Although some in the crowd called for Kidd's release, claiming the breaking of the rope was a sign from God, Kidd was hanged again minutes later, this time successfully. His body was [[gibbet]]ed over the [[River Thames]] at Tilbury Point – as a warning to future would-be pirates – for three years.{{citation needed|date=November 2018}}

Kidd's associates Richard Barleycorn, Robert Lamley, William Jenkins, Gabriel Loffe, Able Owens, and Hugh Parrot were also convicted, but pardoned just prior to hanging at Execution Dock.{{citation needed|date=April 2018}}

Kidd's [[British Whig Party|Whig]] backers were embarrassed by his trial. Far from rewarding his loyalty, they participated in the effort to convict him by depriving him of the money and information which might have provided him with some legal defence. In particular, the two sets of French passes he had kept were missing at his trial. These passes (and others dated 1700) resurfaced in the early twentieth century, misfiled with other government papers in a London building.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| author = Ralph Delahaye Paine| title = The Book of Buried Treasure: Being a True History of the Gold, Jewels, and Plate of Pirates, Galleons, Etc., which are Sought for to this Day| url = https://books.google.com/?id=XW0iYCM4q7QC&amp;pg=PA124| year = 1911| publisher = Heinemann| page = 124 }}&lt;/ref&gt; These passes call the extent of Kidd's guilt into question. Along with the papers, many goods were brought from the ships and soon auctioned off as &quot;pirate plunder&quot;. They were never mentioned in the trial.{{citation needed|date=April 2018}}

As to the accusations of murdering Moore, on this he was mostly sunk on the testimony of the two former crew members, Palmer and Bradinham, who [[Approver|testified against him in exchange for pardon]]s. A deposition Palmer gave, when he was captured in Rhode Island two years earlier, contradicted his testimony and may have supported Kidd's assertions, but Kidd was unable to obtain the deposition.{{citation needed|date=April 2018}}

A [[Broadside (music)|broadside song]] &quot;Captain Kidd's Farewell to the Seas, or, the Famous Pirate's Lament&quot; was printed shortly after his execution and popularised the common belief that Kidd had confessed to the charges.&lt;ref name=CompleteWords&gt;The complete words of the original broadside song &quot;Captain Kid's Farewel to the Seas, or, the Famous Pirate's Lament, to the tune of Coming Down&quot; are at ''davidkidd.net''. {{cite web|url=http://www.davidkidd.net/Captain_Kidd_Lyrics.html |title=Captain Kidd Lyrics. The lyrics of Captain Kidd from 1701 to today |date=23 July 2011 |url-status=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110723082022/http://www.davidkidd.net/Captain_Kidd_Lyrics.html |archivedate=23 July 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Captain Kidd, Burying Treasure, from the Pirates of the Spanish Main series (N19) for Allen &amp; Ginter Cigarettes MET DP835020.jpg|thumb|Captain Kidd, Burying Treasure, from the Pirates of the Spanish Main series (N19) for Allen &amp; Ginter Cigarettes MET DP835020.]]

==Mythology and legend==
The belief that Kidd had left [[buried treasure]] contributed considerably to the growth of his legend. The 1701 [[Broadside (music)|broadside]] song &quot;[[Captain Kidd (song)|Captain Kid's Farewell to the Seas, or, the Famous Pirate's Lament]]&quot; lists &quot;Two hundred bars of gold, and [[Rixdollar|rix dollars]] manifold, we seized uncontrolled&quot;.&lt;ref name=CompleteWords/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The genealogy of the historic tune can also be found at ''davidkidd.net''.&lt;/ref&gt; This belief made its contributions to literature in [[Edgar Allan Poe]]'s &quot;[[The Gold-Bug]]&quot;; [[Washington Irving]]'s &quot;[[The Devil and Tom Walker]]&quot;; [[Robert Louis Stevenson]]'s ''[[Treasure Island]]'' and [[Nelson DeMille]]'s ''[[Plum Island (novel)|Plum Island]]''.{{citation needed|date=January 2017}} It also gave impetus to the constant treasure hunts conducted on [[Oak Island]] in Nova Scotia; in [[Suffolk County, New York|Suffolk County]], [[Long Island]] in New York where [[Gardiner's Island]] is located; [[Charles Island]] in Milford, [[Connecticut]]; the [[Thimble Islands]] in [[Connecticut]]; [[Norwalk Islands#Cockenoe Island|Cockenoe Island]] in [[Westport, Connecticut]];&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://blog.ctnews.com/kantor/2011/04/27/cockenoe-island-farm-distillery-power-plant-buried-treasure/|title = Cockenoe Island: Farm? Distillery? Power plant? Buried Treasure?|date = 27 April 2011|access-date = 25 July 2013|first = Matt|last = Kanaga}}&lt;/ref&gt; and on the island of [[Grand Manan]] in the [[Bay of Fundy]].{{citation needed|date=January 2017}}

Captain Kidd did bury a small cache of treasure on [[Gardiners Island]] in a spot known as Cherry Tree Field; however, it was removed by Governor Bellomont and sent to England to be used as evidence against Kidd.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| title =The Pirate Hunter: The True Story of Captain Kidd| first =Richard| last =Zacks| publisher =Hyperion| isbn =0786884517| url =https://books.google.com/?id=8bu7WAHrd9kC&amp;pg=PA241&amp;lpg=PA241&amp;vq=gardiners+island&amp;dq=pirate+hunter |  accessdate =14 December 2007| year =2002 | pages = 241–243 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| author = Ralph Delahaye Paine| title = The Book of Buried Treasure: Being a True History of the Gold, Jewels, and Plate of Pirates, Galleons, Etc., which are Sought for to this Day| url = https://books.google.com/?id=tmFDAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA304| year = 1911| publisher = Heinemann| page = 304 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kidd also visited [[Block Island]] around 1699, where he was supplied by Mrs. Mercy (Sands) Raymond, daughter of the mariner James Sands. The story has it that, for her hospitality, Mrs. Raymond was bid to hold out her apron, into which Kidd threw gold and jewels until it was full. After her husband Joshua Raymond died, Mercy moved with her family to northern [[New London, Connecticut]] (later Montville), where she bought much land. The Raymond family was thus said to have been &quot;enriched by the apron&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=History of New London, Connecticut |url=https://archive.org/details/historynewlondo00caulgoog |last=Caulkins |first=Frances Manwaring |year=1852 |page=293 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On [[Grand Manan]] in the [[Bay of Fundy]], as early as 1875, reference{{examples|date=July 2014}} was made to searches on the west side of the island for treasure allegedly buried by Kidd during his time as a [[privateer]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Money Cove&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title= Grand Manan – Captain Kidd's Money Cove|url=http://pennystockjournal.blogspot.co.uk/2015/07/grand-manan-captain-kidds-money-cove.html |website=pennystockjournal.blogspot.co.uk|publisher=Penny Stock Journal|accessdate=16 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; For nearly 200 years, this remote area of the island has been called &quot;Money Cove&quot;.

In 1983, [[Cork Graham]] and Richard Knight went looking for Captain Kidd's buried treasure off the [[Vietnam]]ese island of [[Phú Quốc]]. Knight and Graham were caught, convicted of [[Illegal entry|illegally landing]] on Vietnamese territory, and assessed each a $10,000 [[fine (penalty)|fine]]. They were imprisoned for 11 months until they paid the fine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Post12may&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Tracking Captain Kidd's Treasure Puts Pair in Vietnamese Captivity|last=Branigin|first=William|date=12 May 1984|work=The Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==''Quedagh Merchant'' found==
For years, people and treasure hunters have tried to locate ''[[Quedagh Merchant]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title =Captain Kidd (1645–1701)| publisher =PortCities London| url =http://www.portcities.org.uk/london/server/show/ConFactFile.3/Captain-Kidd.html| accessdate =13 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was reported on 13 December 2007 that &quot;wreckage of a pirate ship abandoned by Captain Kidd in the 17th century has been found by divers in shallow waters off the [[Dominican Republic]].&quot; The waters in which the ship was found were less than ten feet deep and were only {{convert|70|ft|m}} off [[Catalina Island, Dominican Republic|Catalina Island]], just to the south of [[La Romana, Dominican Republic|La Romana]] on the Dominican coast. The ship is believed to be &quot;the remains of ''Quedagh Merchant''&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| date =13 December 2007| title =Captain Kidd Ship Found| publisher =Yahoo News| url =https://news.yahoo.com/s/livescience/20071213/sc_livescience/captainkiddshipfound| accessdate =13 December 2007 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20071215091704/http://news.yahoo.com/s/livescience/20071213/sc_livescience/captainkiddshipfound &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 15 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| date =13 December 2007| title =Captain Kidd's Shipwreck Of 1699 Discovered| website =Science Daily| url =https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2007/12/071213162036.htm| accessdate =13 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Charles Beeker, the director of Academic Diving and Underwater Science Programs in [[Indiana University (Bloomington)]]'s School of Health, Physical Education, and Recreation, was one of the experts leading the [[Indiana University]] diving team. He said that it was &quot;remarkable that the wreck has remained undiscovered all these years given its location,&quot; and given that the ship has been the subject of so many prior failed searches.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=13 December 2007 |title=IU team finds fabled pirate ship |publisher=INDYSTAR.COM |url=http://www.indystar.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20071213/LOCAL/712130548 |accessdate=13 December 2007 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071217202520/http://www.indystar.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=%2F20071213%2FLOCAL%2F712130548 |archivedate=17 December 2007 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Captain Kidd's cannon]], an artifact from the shipwreck, was added to a permanent exhibit at [[The Children's Museum of Indianapolis]] in 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;TCMPR&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Falkenstein|first=Jaclyn|title=Children's Museum Reveals First Major Component of National Geographic Treasures of the Earth|url=http://www.childrensmuseum.org/node/34902|accessdate=13 May 2011|newspaper=The Children's Museum of Indianapolis Press Release|date=16 March 2010|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110928224450/http://www.childrensmuseum.org/node/34902|archivedate=28 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==False find==
In May 2015, a {{convert|50|kg|lb|adj=on}} ingot expected to be silver was found in a wreck off the coast of [[Île Sainte-Marie]] in [[Madagascar]] by a team led by marine archaeologist [[Barry Clifford]], and was believed to be part of Captain Kidd's treasure.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 |url = https://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-32621444
 |title = Pirate Captain Kidd's 'treasure' found in Madagascar
 |publisher = BBC
 |date = 7 May 2015
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/may/07/captain-kidd-treasure-found-madagascar|title='Captain Kidd's treasure' found off Madagascar|first=Jessica|last=Elgot|date=7 May 2015|accessdate=8 January 2017|via=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cnn.com/2015/05/07/world/feat-captain-kidd-treasure-madagascar-barry-clifford/index.html|title=Capt. Kidd's treasure found off Madagascar, report says|first=Todd |last=Leopold|work=cnn.com|accessdate=8 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Clifford handed the booty to [[Hery Rajaonarimampianina]], President of Madagascar.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/newstopics/howaboutthat/11588969/Captain-Kidds-treasure-found-in-Madagascar.html|title=Captain Kidd's treasure 'found' in Madagascar|work=telegraph.co.uk|accessdate=8 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pressreader.com/india/the-times-of-india-new-delhi-edition/20150509/282200829487839/TextView|title=PressReader.com – Connecting People Through News|work=pressreader.com|accessdate=8 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in July 2015, a [[UNESCO]] scientific and technical advisory body revealed that the ingot consisted of 95% lead, and speculated that the wreck in question might be a broken part of the Sainte-Marie port constructions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Mission to Madagascar|url=http://www.unesco.org/new/en/culture/themes/underwater-cultural-heritage/advisory-body/mission-to-madagascar/|website=UNESCO Scientific and Technical Advisory Body assists Madagascar|access-date=14 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Portrayals in popular culture==
[[Edgar Allan Poe]] uses the legend of Kidd's buried treasure in his seminal detective story [[The Gold Bug]].
 
[[Charles Laughton]] played Kidd twice on film, first in 1945 in ''[[Captain Kidd (film)|Captain Kidd]]'', then in 1952 in ''[[Abbott and Costello Meet Captain Kidd]]''.

Kidd is mentioned in the 1945 song &quot;Captain Kidd&quot; by singer [[Ella Mae Morse]] with [[Billy May]] and his orchestra.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.discogs.com/Ella-Mae-Morse-With-Billy-May-And-His-Orchestra-Captain-Kidd-Ya-Betcha-/release/8542320&lt;/ref&gt;

[[John Crawford (actor)|John Crawford]] played Kidd in the 1953 Columbia film serial ''[[The Great Adventures of Captain Kidd]]''.

The most recent film portrayal was by Love Nystrom in the 2006 mini-series ''[[Blackbeard (2006 film)|Blackbeard]]''.

Captain Kidd is mentioned in [[Bob Dylan]]'s song [[Bob Dylan's 115th Dream]] from his fifth album [[Bringing It All Back Home]].

Captain Kidd appears in ''[[Persona 5]]'', as one of the eponymous Personas belonging to Ryuji Sakamoto. The game's theme is about outcasts/outlaws, as well as rebellion against the established order/society, and portrays several individuals (mostly from fiction) that fit this theme, such as [[Arsene Lupin]], [[Pope Joan]] and [[Ishikawa Goemon]].

Captain Kidd appears in ''[[The Devil and Daniel Webster]]''.

The 1957 children's book ''Captain Kidd's Cat'' by [[Robert Lawson (author)|Robert Lawson]] is a largely fictionalized account of Kidd's last voyage, trial and execution, told from the point of view of his loyal ship's cat. The book portrays Kidd as an innocent privateer who was framed by corrupt officials as a scapegoat for their own crimes.

The song &quot;Ballad of William Kidd&quot; by heavy metal band [[Running Wild (band)|Running Wild]] is based on Kidd's life, particularly the events surrounding his trial and execution.

A version of &quot;Ballad of William Kidd&quot; is sung by Commander Klaes Ashford in Seasons 3 and 4 of &quot;The Expanse&quot;

''[[Doraemon: Nobita's Great Adventure in the South Seas]]'' portrays a highly fictionalized version of Captain Kidd as a pirate in the Pacific with more of an American accent then a Scottish one who comes across the [[Doraemon]] and his friends that were caught in a time distortion. The combined group finds an island with secret treasure and is being used by a business from the future for his own benefit. Eventually the businessman is captured by the Time Patrol and Kidd continues his voyage.
 
The band [[Scissorfight]] had a song called &quot;The Gibbeted Captain Kidd&quot; on their 1998 album ''[[Balls Deep (album)|Balls Deep]]''.

In the manga and anime series ''[[One Piece]]'', there is a character named Eustass &quot;Captain&quot; Kid, whose name and epithet are inspired by the real life Captain Kidd.

Four missions in [[Assassin's Creed III]]￼￼ involve finding map pieces that Captain Kidd had given to four of his crew members for safe keeping. Finding all four pieces would reveal the location of Kidd's treasure, which in the Assassin's Creed series is a Piece of Eden that gives the player the ability to repel bullets. 

==See also==
* [[Joseph Bradish]], a pirate who sailed in Kidd's company&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=i7NLrJnuzHQC&amp;pg=PA80|title=Under the Black Flag: Exploits of the Most Notorious Pirates|last=Seitz|first=Don Carlos|date=1 March 2002|publisher=Courier Corporation|isbn=9780486421315|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[George Dew]], buccaneer, pirate, and privateer who briefly sailed alongside Kidd in 1691 near the [[Piscataqua River]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Marley&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Marley|first1=David|title=Pirates of the Americas|date=2010|publisher=ABC-CLIO|location=Santa Barbara CA|isbn=9781598842012|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=bU6ML_VnXTwC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|accessdate=30 July 2017|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Captain Kidd's Cannon]]
* [[Gardiners Island]]
* [[Oak Island]]
* ''[[Treasure Island]]''

== References and notes ==
{{reflist|25em}}

==Bibliography==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book| author = Botting, Douglas | year = 1978 | title = The Pirates | location =Boston, MA| publisher = Little Brown &amp; Company | isbn = 0316848948 | url = https://books.google.com/books?isbn=0316848948 | access-date = 7 January 2017 }}
* {{cite book| author = Cordingly, David | year = 1995 | title = Under The Black Flag : The Romance and the Reality of Life Among the Pirates | publisher = Harcourt Brace &amp; Company | access-date =  }}{{full citation needed|date=January 2017}}
* {{cite book| author = Hamilton, Cochran | year = 1961 | title = Pirates of the Spanish Main | edition = 1st | series = American Heritage Junior Library  | location = New York | publisher = American Heritage | isbn = 0060213469 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=3iIYAAAAYAAJ | access-date = 7 January 2017 }}{{full citation needed|date=January 2017}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
===Books===
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* Campbell (1853). ''An Historical Sketch of Robin Hood and Captain Kid''. New York.
* Dalton, Sir Cornelius Neale (1911). ''The Real Captain Kidd: A Vindication''. New York: Duffield.
* Gilbert, H. (1986). ''The Book of Pirates''. London: Bracken Books.
* {{Cite book |year=1701 |editor-last=Howell |editor-first=T. B. |contribution=The Trial of Captain William Kidd and Others, for Piracy and Robbery |title=A Complete Collection of State Trials and Proceedings for High Treason and Other Crimes and Misdemeanors |volume=XIV |publisher=Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme, and Brown |publication-date=1816 |publication-place=London |pages=147–234 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=JENPSU6dlqoC |access-date=27 August 2008 }}
* Ritchie, Robert C. (1986). ''Captain Kidd and the War against the Pirates''. Cambridge: Harvard University Press.
* Wilkins, Harold T. (1937). ''Captain Kidd and His Skeleton Island''. New York: Liveright Publishing Corp.
* Zacks, Richard (2002). ''The Pirate Hunter: The True Story of Captain Kidd''. Hyperion Books. {{ISBN|0-7868-8451-7}}.
* Konstam, Angus (2008). ''The Complete History of Piracy''. (Osprey Publishing).
{{div col end}}

===Articles===
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060219051952/http://www.bio.umass.edu/biology/conn.river/kidd.html Captain Kidd] Pirate's Treasure Buried in the Connecticut River
* [http://thomastew.steventew.co.uk/kings_commission.htm The King's Commission to William Kidd for the Capture of Captain Thomas Tew and Others]
* [http://www.piratesinfo.com/biography/biography.php?article_id=36 Biography at piratesinfo.com]
* [http://web.me.com/daverust/profile/blog/blog.html Dave's Blog] Blog, observer with the Indiana University expedition to the Quedagh Merchant (ongoing)
* [http://yourarchives.nationalarchives.gov.uk/index.php?title=Captain_William_Kidd%2C_Pirate National Archives – Article listing Records held concerning Captain Kidd]
* [http://www.lordshiphistory.com/PIRATEwebpage.html Pirates and the history of Lordship, Connecticut]
* [https://memory.loc.gov/service/lawlib/law0001/2010/201000302205929/201000302205929.pdf?title=The Arraignment, Tryal and Condemnation of Captain William Kidd] The court documents of the trial of William Kidd, in Early Modern English.
{{div col end}}

==External links==
{{Appletons' Poster|Kidd, William|William Kidd|year=1892}}
* [http://www.whatsinwapping.co.uk/captain-kidd-pub-12012011/ Captain Kidd pub], What's in Wapping? Local community website
{{Pirates of the Modern Age}}
{{Pirates}}

{{Authority control}}

/ref&gt; However, in July 2015, a [[UNESCO]] scientific and technical advisory body revealed that the ingot consisted of 95% lead, and speculated that the wreck in question might be a broken part of the Sainte-Marie port constructions.

{{DEFAULTSORT:Kidd, William}}
[[Category:1645 births]]
[[Category:1701 deaths]]
[[Category:17th-century Scottish people]]
[[Category:18th-century Scottish people]]
[[Category:17th-century American people]]
[[Category:18th-century American people]]
[[Category:17th-century pirates]]
[[Category:American folklore]]
[[Category:Kingdom of Scotland emigrants to the Thirteen Colonies]]
[[Category:Executed Scottish people]]
[[Category:People executed for murder]]
[[Category:People executed for piracy]]
[[Category:People executed by Stuart England]]
[[Category:People from Dundee]]
[[Category:Military personnel from New York City]]
[[Category:People of colonial New York]]
[[Category:People associated with Inverclyde]]
[[Category:Privateers]]
[[Category:Scottish murderers]]
[[Category:Scottish pirates]]
[[Category:History of New York City]]
[[Category:People executed by the Kingdom of England by hanging]]
[[Category:People from Grand Manan]]
[[Category:Maritime folklore]]
[[Category:Wrongful executions]]
[[Category:Murder convictions without a body]]
[[Category:Mutineers]]
[[Category:British military personnel of the Nine Years' War]]</text>
      <sha1>cx8i4fkof46s4c4gapxion6g0jebdrs</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
