  <page>
    <title>Analog signal</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>993</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940767147</id>
      <parentid>940767126</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-14T14:01:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Red Phoenix</username>
        <id>5170388</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/Wikikiealia|Wikikiealia]] ([[User talk:Wikikiealia|talk]]) ([[WP:HG|HG]]) (3.4.9)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2013}}
{{Use American English|date=July 2018}}
{{Broader|Signal}}

{{refimprove|date=September 2015}}

An '''analog signal'''  is any [[continuous signal]] for which the time-varying feature (variable) of the signal is a representation of some other time varying quantity, i.e., ''analogous'' to another time varying signal. For example, in an analog [[audio signal]], the instantaneous [[voltage]] of the signal varies continuously with the [[Sound pressure|pressure]] of the sound waves. It differs from a [[Digital signal (signal processing)|digital signal]], in which the continuous quantity is a representation of a sequence of [[discrete space|discrete values]] which can only take on one of a finite number of values.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.st-andrews.ac.uk/~www_pa/Scots_Guide/info/signals/digital/digital.htm|title=Digital signals|publisher=University of St. Andrews |author=Jim Lesurf |access-date=2018-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://learn.sparkfun.com/tutorials/analog-vs-digital/digital-signals|title=Analog vs. Digital|publisher=Sparkfun |date=2018-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The term ''analog signal'' usually refers to [[electrical signal]]s; however, [[Classical mechanics|mechanical]], [[pneumatic]], [[hydraulic]], human speech, and other systems may also convey or be considered analog signals.

==Representation==
An analog signal uses some property of the medium to convey the signal's information. For example, an [[aneroid barometer]] uses rotary position as the signal to convey pressure information.  In an electrical signal, the [[voltage]], [[Electric current|current]], or [[frequency]] of the signal may be varied to represent the information.
   
Any information may be conveyed by an analog signal; often{{specify|date=July 2018}} such a signal is a measured response to changes in physical phenomena, such as [[sound]], [[light]], [[temperature]], position, or [[pressure]].  The physical variable is converted to an analog signal by a [[transducer]].   For example, sound striking the diaphragm of a [[microphone]] induces corresponding fluctuations in the current produced by a coil in an electromagnetic microphone or the voltage produced by a [[condenser microphone]].  The voltage or the current is said to be an &quot;analog&quot; of the sound.

==Noise==
{{See also|Comparison of analog and digital recording}}
An analog signal is subject to [[Noise (electronic)|electronic noise]] and [[distortion]] introduced by [[communication channel]]s and [[signal processing]] operations, which can progressively degrade the [[signal-to-noise ratio]] (SNR).  In contrast, digital signals have a finite resolution.  Converting an analog signal to digital form introduces a low-level [[quantization noise]] into the signal, but once in digital form the signal can be processed or transmitted without introducing significant additional noise or distortion. In analog systems, it is difficult to detect when such degradation occurs.  However, in digital systems, degradation can not only be detected but corrected as well.

The most serious disadvantage of analog signals compared to digital transmission is that analog transmissions always contain [[Noise (physics)|noise]]. As the signal is copied, transmitted, or processed, the unavoidable noise introduced in the signal path will accumulate as a [[generation loss]], progressively and irreversibly degrading the signal-to-noise ratio, until in extreme cases, the signal can be overwhelmed. Noise can show up as &quot;hiss&quot; and [[intermodulation distortion]] in audio signals, or &quot;snow&quot; in video signals. Generation loss is irreversible as there is no reliable method to distinguish the noise from the signal, partly because amplifying the signal to recover attenuated parts of the signal amplifies the noise as well. Digital signals can be transmitted, stored and processed without introducing noise. 

In electrical analog signals, noise can be minimized by shielding, good connections and the use of certain cable types such as [[Coaxial cable|coaxial]] or [[twisted pair]].

==See also==
{{div col|colwidth=20em}}
* [[Analog computer]]
* [[Analog device]]
* [[Analog recording]]
* [[Analog signal processing]]
* [[Analog video]]
* [[Analog-to-digital converter]]
* [[Digital audio]]
* [[Digital video]]
* [[Magnetic tape]]
* [[Videotape]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Telecommunications}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Analog Signal}}
[[Category:Analog circuits]]
[[Category:Electronic design]]
[[Category:Television terminology]]
[[Category:Video signal]]</text>
      <sha1>9fycm1ch9a38va01wjzenajeo3w6kx1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
