  <page>
    <title>Ada Lovelace</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>974</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941163663</id>
      <parentid>941163164</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-16T23:50:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Xxanthippe</username>
        <id>1267919</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted [[WP:AGF|good faith]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/Xxanthippe|Xxanthippe]] ([[User talk:Xxanthippe|talk]]): Self revert ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{pp-vand|small=yes}}
{{short description|English mathematician, computer programming pioneer}}
{{EngvarB|date=November 2019}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2019}}
{{Infobox scientist
| name             = The Countess of Lovelace
| honorific_prefix = [[The Right Honourable]]
| image            = Ada Byron daguerreotype by Antoine Claudet 1843 or 1850 - cropped.png
| caption          = A {{circa}} 1843 [[daguerreotype]] by [[Antoine Claudet]]&lt;ref name=blogbutfromboldian&gt;
{{Cite web|url=https://blogs.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/adalovelace/2015/10/14/only-known-photographs-of-ada-lovelace-in-bodleian-display/|title=Only known photographs of Ada Lovelace in Bodleian Display|year=2015|website=Bodleian|access-date=10 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| birth_name       = The Hon. Augusta Ada Byron
| birth_date       = {{birth date|df=y|1815|12|10}}
| birth_place      = London, England
| death_date       = {{death date and age|df=y|1852|11|27|1815|12|10}}
| death_place      = [[Marylebone]], London, England
| resting_place    = [[Church of St. Mary Magdalene, Hucknall]], Nottingham, England
| children         =
{{plainlist |
* [[Byron King-Noel, Viscount Ockham]] and 12th Baron Wentworth
* [[Anne Blunt, 15th Baroness Wentworth]]
* [[Ralph King-Milbanke, 2nd Earl of Lovelace]]}}
| known_for        = Mathematics, [[computing]]
| spouse           = {{marriage|[[William King-Noel, 1st Earl of Lovelace]]&lt;br&gt;|1835}}
}}
'''Augusta Ada King, Countess of Lovelace''' (''née'' '''Byron'''; 10 December 1815&amp;nbsp;– 27 November 1852) was an English mathematician and writer, chiefly known for her work on [[Charles Babbage]]'s proposed mechanical general-purpose computer, the [[Analytical Engine]]. She was the first to recognise that the machine had applications beyond pure calculation, and published the first [[algorithm]] intended to be carried out by such a machine. As a result, she is sometimes regarded as the first to recognise the full potential of a &quot;[[computing machine]]&quot; and one of the first computer [[programmer]]s.{{Sfn|Fuegi|Francis|2003}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Phillips|first=Ana Lena|date=November–December 2011|title=Crowdsourcing Gender Equity: Ada Lovelace Day, and its companion website, aims to raise the profile of women in science and technology|url=https://www.americanscientist.org/article/crowdsourcing-gender-equity|journal=American Scientist|volume=99|issue=6|page=463}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lovelace Google&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2012/dec/10/ada-lovelace-honoured-google-doodle|title=Ada Lovelace honoured by Google doodle|date=10 December 2012|newspaper=[[The Guardian]]|accessdate=10 December 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Augusta Byron was the only legitimate child of poet [[Lord Byron]] and his wife [[Lady Byron]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.biography.com/people/ada-lovelace-20825323|title=Ada Lovelace Biography|website=biography.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; All of [[Lord Byron#Children|Byron's other children]] were born out of wedlock to other women.&lt;ref name= ABCL/&gt; Byron separated from his wife a month after Ada was born and left England forever four months later. He commemorated the parting in a poem that begins, &quot;Is thy face like thy mother's my fair child! ADA! sole daughter of my house and heart?&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.bartleby.com/205/20.html|title=Last leaving England. I. Personal, Lyric, and Elegiac. Lord Byron. 1881. Poetry of Byron|website=bartleby.com|access-date=31 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; He died of disease in the [[Greek War of Independence]] when Ada was eight years old. Her mother remained bitter and promoted Ada's interest in mathematics and logic in an effort to prevent her from developing her father's perceived [[insanity]]. Despite this, Ada remained interested in Byron, naming her two sons Byron and Gordon. Upon her eventual death, she was buried next to him at her request. Although often ill in her childhood, Ada pursued her studies assiduously. She married [[William King-Noel, 1st Earl of Lovelace|William King]] in 1835. King was made Earl of Lovelace in 1838, Ada thereby becoming Countess of Lovelace.

Her educational and social exploits brought her into contact with scientists such as [[Andrew Crosse]], [[Charles Babbage]], [[David Brewster|Sir David Brewster]], [[Charles Wheatstone]], [[Michael Faraday]] and the author [[Charles Dickens]], contacts which she used to further her education. Ada described her approach as &quot;poetical science&quot;{{Sfn|Toole|1998|pp=234–235}} and herself as an &quot;Analyst (&amp; Metaphysician)&quot;.{{Sfn|Toole|1998|pp=156–157}}

When she was a teenager, her mathematical talents led her to a long working relationship and friendship with fellow British mathematician [[Charles Babbage]], who is known as &quot;the father of computers&quot;. She was in particular interested in Babbage's work on the Analytical Engine. Lovelace first met him in June 1833, through their mutual friend, and her private tutor, [[Mary Somerville]].

Between 1842 and 1843, Ada translated an article by Italian military engineer [[Luigi Menabrea]] on the calculating engine, supplementing it with an elaborate set of notes, simply called ''Notes''. These notes contain what many consider to be the first computer program—that is, an algorithm designed to be carried out by a machine. Other historians reject this perspective and point out that Babbage's personal notes from the years 1836/1837 contain the first programs for the engine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Ventana al Conocimiento |url=https://www.bbvaopenmind.com/en/ada-lovelace-original-and-visionary-but-no-programmer/ |title=Ada Lovelace: Original and Visionary, but No Programmer |date=9 December 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Lovelace's notes are important in the early [[history of computers]]. She also developed a vision of the capability of computers to go beyond mere calculating or number-crunching, while many others, including Babbage himself, focused only on those capabilities.{{Sfn|Fuegi|Francis|2003|pp=19, 25}} Her mindset of &quot;poetical science&quot; led her to ask questions about the Analytical Engine (as shown in her notes) examining how individuals and society relate to technology as a collaborative tool.&lt;ref name=ABCL&gt;{{Citation|last=Toole|first=Betty Alexandra|title=Poetical Science|journal=The Byron Journal|volume=15|year=1987|pages=55–65|doi=10.3828/bj.1987.6}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

She died of [[uterine cancer]] in 1852 at the age of 36.

==Biography==
===Childhood===
[[File:Miniature of Ada Byron.jpg|thumb|Ada Byron, aged four]]
[[Lord Byron]] expected his child to be a &quot;glorious boy&quot; and was disappointed when [[Lady Byron]] gave birth to a girl.{{Sfn|Turney|1972|p=35}} The child was named after Byron's half-sister, [[Augusta Leigh]], and was called &quot;Ada&quot; by Byron himself.{{Sfn|Stein|1985|p=17}} On 16 January 1816, at Lord Byron's command, Lady Byron left for her parents' home at [[Kirkby Mallory]], taking their five-week-old daughter with her.{{Sfn|Turney|1972|p=35}} Although English law at the time granted full custody of children to the father in cases of separation, Lord Byron made no attempt to claim his parental rights,{{Sfn|Stein|1985|p=16}} but did request that his sister keep him informed of Ada's welfare.{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|p=80}}

[[File:Ada Lovelace child portrait Somerville College.jpg|thumb|Ada Byron, aged seven, by [[Alfred d'Orsay]], 1822, [[Somerville College, Oxford]].]]
On 21 April, Lord Byron signed the [[deed of separation]], although very reluctantly, and left England for good a few days later.{{Sfn|Turney|1972|pp=36–38}} Aside from an acrimonious separation, Lady Byron continued throughout her life to make allegations about her husband's immoral behaviour.{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|pp=74–77}} This set of events made Lovelace infamous in Victorian society. She did not have a relationship with her father. He died in 1824 when she was eight years old. Her mother was the only significant parental figure in her life.&lt;ref name=&quot;Turney p. 138&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Turney|1972|p=138}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Lovelace was not shown the family portrait of her father until her 20th birthday.{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|p=10}}

Lovelace did not have a close relationship with her mother. She was often left in the care of her maternal grandmother Judith, Hon. Lady Milbanke, who doted on her. However, because of societal attitudes of the time—which favoured the husband in any separation, with the welfare of any child acting as mitigation—Lady Byron had to present herself as a loving mother to the rest of society. This included writing anxious letters to Lady Milbanke about her daughter's welfare, with a cover note saying to retain the letters in case she had to use them to show maternal concern.{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|pp=85–87}} In one letter to Lady Milbanke, she referred to her daughter as &quot;it&quot;: &quot;I talk to it for your satisfaction, not my own, and shall be very glad when you have it under your own.&quot;{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|p=86}} Lady Byron had her teenage daughter watched by close friends for any sign of moral deviation. Lovelace dubbed these observers the &quot;Furies&quot; and later complained they exaggerated and invented stories about her.{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|p=119}}

[[File:Ada Byron aged seventeen (1832).jpg|thumb|left|upright=0.9|Ada Byron, aged seventeen, 1832]]
Lovelace was often ill, beginning in early childhood. At the age of eight, she experienced headaches that obscured her vision.{{Sfn | Stein|1985|p=17}} In June 1829, she was paralysed after a bout of [[measles]]. She was subjected to continuous bed rest for nearly a year, something which may have extended her period of disability. By 1831, she was able to walk with crutches. Despite the illnesses, she developed her mathematical and technological skills.

{{Quote|text=When Ada was twelve years old, this future &quot;Lady Fairy&quot;, as Charles Babbage affectionately called her, decided she wanted to fly. Ada Byron went about the project methodically, thoughtfully, with imagination and passion. Her first step, in February 1828, was to construct wings. She investigated different material and sizes. She considered various materials for the wings: paper, oilsilk, wires, and feathers. She examined the [[anatomy of birds]] to determine the right proportion between the wings and the body. She decided to write a book, ''Flyology,'' illustrating, with plates, some of her findings. She decided what equipment she would need; for example, a compass, to &quot;cut across the country by the most direct road&quot;, so that she could surmount mountains, rivers, and valleys. Her final step was to integrate steam with the &quot;art of flying&quot;.&lt;ref name=ABCL/&gt;}}

Ada Byron had an affair with a tutor in early 1833. She tried to elope with him after she was caught, but the tutor's relatives recognised her and contacted her mother. Lady Byron and her friends covered the incident up to prevent a public scandal.{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|pp=120–21}} Lovelace never met her younger half-sister, [[Allegra Byron|Allegra]], the daughter of Lord Byron and [[Claire Clairmont]]. Allegra died in 1822 at the age of five. Lovelace did have some contact with [[Elizabeth Medora Leigh]], the daughter of Byron's half-sister Augusta Leigh, who purposely avoided Lovelace as much as possible when introduced at court.{{Sfn|Turney|1972|p=155}}
{{clear}}

===Adult years===
[[File:Ada Lovelace portrait.jpg|thumb|right|Watercolour portrait of Ada King, Countess of Lovelace, circa 1840, possibly by [[Alfred Edward Chalon]]]]
Lovelace became close friends with her tutor [[Mary Somerville]], who introduced her to Charles Babbage in 1833. She had a strong respect and affection for Somerville,{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|pp=138–40}} and they corresponded for many years. Other acquaintances included the scientists [[Andrew Crosse]], [[David Brewster|Sir David Brewster]], [[Charles Wheatstone]], [[Michael Faraday]] and the author [[Charles Dickens]]. She was [[debutante|presented at Court]] at the age of seventeen &quot;and became a popular belle of the season&quot; in part because of her &quot;brilliant mind.&quot;{{Sfn|Turney|1972|p=138}} By 1834 Ada was a regular at Court and started attending various events. She danced often and was able to charm many people, and was described by most people as being dainty, although [[John Hobhouse, 1st Baron Broughton|John Hobhouse]], Byron's friend, described her as &quot;a large, coarse-skinned young woman but with something of my friend's features, particularly the mouth&quot;.{{Sfn|Turney|1972|pp=138–39}} This description followed their meeting on 24 February 1834 in which Ada made it clear to Hobhouse that she did not like him, probably due to her mother's influence, which led her to dislike all of her father's friends. This first impression was not to last, and they later became friends.{{Sfn|Turney|1972|p=139}}

On 8 July 1835, she married [[William King, 1st Earl of Lovelace|William, 8th Baron King]], becoming Lady King.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.thepeerage.com/p2744.htm#i27434|title=Hon. Ada Augusta Byron|work=The Peerage |date=31 January 2012&lt;!--citing Burke's Peerage, Baronetage &amp; Knightage, 107th edition, vol 1, 2003 p630--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; They had three homes: [[Ockham Park]], Surrey; a Scottish estate on [[Torridon|Loch Torridon]] in [[Ross-shire]]; and a house in London. They spent their honeymoon at Worthy Manor in Ashley Combe near [[Porlock Weir]], Somerset. The Manor had been built as a hunting lodge in 1799 and was improved by King in preparation for their honeymoon. It later became their summer retreat and was further improved during this time. From 1845, the family's main house was [[East Horsley]] Towers, rebuilt in the [[Victorian Gothic]] fashion by the architect of the Houses of Parliament, [[Charles Barry]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://www.british-history.ac.uk/vch/surrey/vol3/pp349-352|title=A History of the County of Surrey: Volume 3. Parishes: East Horsley|accessdate=26 February 2017|quote=Horsley Towers is a large house standing in a park of 300 acres, the seat of the Earl of Lovelace. The old house was rebuilt about 1745. The present house was built by Sir Charles Barry for Mr. Currie on a new site, between 1820 and 1829, in Elizabethan style. Mr. Currie, who owned the combined manors, 1784–1829, rebuilt most of the houses in the village and restored the church.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Andrew Crosse and the mite that shocked the world: The life and work of an electrical pioneer |last=Wright |first=Brian |isbn=9781784624385|page=262 |date=28 October 2015 |publisher=Matador}}&lt;/ref&gt;

They had three children: [[Byron King-Noel, Viscount Ockham|Byron]] (born 12 May 1836); [[Lady Anne Blunt|Anne Isabella]] (called Annabella; born 22 September 1837); and [[Ralph King-Milbanke, 2nd Earl of Lovelace|Ralph Gordon]] (born 2 July 1839). Immediately after the birth of Annabella, Lady King experienced &quot;a tedious and suffering illness, which took months to cure.&quot;{{Sfn|Turney|1972|p=139}} Ada was a descendant of the extinct [[Baron Lovelace|Barons Lovelace]] and in 1838, her husband was made [[Earl of Lovelace]] and Viscount Ockham,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Lovelace, Earl of|url=http://www.cracroftspeerage.co.uk/online/content/lovelace1838.htm|publisher=Cracroft's Peerage|year=2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; meaning Ada became the Countess of Lovelace.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |via=[[NewspaperArchive.com]] |url=https://newspaperarchive.com/entertainment-clipping-apr-09-1841-1422479/ |work=[[Macon Georgia Telegraph]] |location=[[Macon, Georgia]] |date=9 April 1841 |page=3 |title=New York Fifty Years Ago }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1843–44, Ada's mother assigned [[William Benjamin Carpenter]] to teach Ada's children and to act as a &quot;moral&quot; instructor for Ada.{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|pp=285–86}} He quickly fell for her and encouraged her to express any frustrated affections, claiming that his marriage meant he would never act in an &quot;unbecoming&quot; manner. When it became clear that Carpenter was trying to start an affair, Ada cut it off.{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|pp=289–96}}

In 1841, Lovelace and [[Elizabeth Medora Leigh|Medora Leigh]] (the daughter of Lord Byron's half-sister Augusta Leigh) were told by Ada's mother that her father was also Medora's father.{{Sfn|Turney|1972|p=159}} On 27 February 1841, Ada wrote to her mother: &quot;I am not in the least ''astonished''. In fact, you merely ''confirm'' what I have for ''years and years'' felt scarcely a doubt about, but should have considered it most improper in me to hint to you that I in any way suspected.&quot;{{Sfn|Turney|1972|p=160}} She did not blame the incestuous relationship on Byron, but instead blamed Augusta Leigh: &quot;I fear she is more inherently wicked than he ever was.&quot;{{Sfn|Moore|1961|p=431}} In the 1840s, Ada flirted with scandals: firstly, from a relaxed approach to extra-marital relationships with men, leading to rumours of affairs;{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|p=302}} and secondly, from her love of gambling. She apparently lost more than £3,000 on the horses during the later 1840s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrc.wmin.ac.uk/theory-babbagesdancer-print.html|title=Babbage's Dancer|first=Simon|last=Schaffer|publisher=the hypermedia research centre|access-date=4 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The gambling led to her forming a syndicate with male friends, and an ambitious attempt in 1851 to create a mathematical model for successful large bets. This went disastrously wrong, leaving her thousands of pounds in debt to the syndicate, forcing her to admit it all to her husband.{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|pp=340–42}} She had a shadowy relationship with Andrew Crosse's son John from 1844 onwards. John Crosse destroyed most of their correspondence after her death as part of a legal agreement. She bequeathed him the only heirlooms her father had personally left to her.{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|pp=336–37}} During her final illness, she would panic at the idea of the younger Crosse being kept from visiting her.{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|p=361}}

===Education===
Throughout her illnesses, she continued her education.{{Sfn|Stein|1985|pp=28–30}} Her mother's obsession with rooting out any of the insanity of which she accused Byron was one of the reasons that Ada was taught mathematics from an early age. She was privately schooled in mathematics and science by [[William Frend (social reformer)|William Frend]], [[William King (physician)|William King]],&lt;ref name=williamkings group=lower-alpha&gt;William King, her tutor, and William King, her future husband, were not related.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Mary Somerville]], the noted 19th-century researcher and scientific author. One of her later tutors was the mathematician and logician [[Augustus De Morgan]]. From 1832, when she was seventeen, her mathematical abilities began to emerge,{{Sfn|Turney|1972|p=138}} and her interest in mathematics dominated the majority of her adult life. In a letter to Lady Byron, De Morgan suggested that her daughter's skill in mathematics could lead her to become &quot;an original mathematical investigator, perhaps of first-rate eminence&quot;.{{Sfn|Stein|1985|p=82}}

Lovelace often questioned basic assumptions by integrating poetry and science. While studying [[differential calculus]], she wrote to De Morgan:
&lt;blockquote&gt;I may remark that the curious transformations many formulae can undergo, the unsuspected and to a beginner apparently impossible identity of forms exceedingly dissimilar at first sight, is I think one of the chief difficulties in the early part of mathematical studies. I am often reminded of certain sprites and fairies one reads of, who are at one's elbows in ''one'' shape now, and the next minute in a form most dissimilar{{Sfn|Toole|1998|p=99}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Lovelace believed that intuition and imagination were critical to effectively applying mathematical and scientific concepts. She valued [[metaphysics]] as much as mathematics, viewing both as tools for exploring &quot;the unseen worlds around us&quot;.{{Sfn|Toole|1998|pp=91–100}}

===Death===
[[File:Ada Lovelace in 1852.jpg|thumb|Painting of Lovelace seated at a piano, by [[Henry Wyndham Phillips|Henry Phillips]] (1852). Although in great pain at the time, she agreed to sit for the painting as her father, [[Lord Byron]], had been painted by Phillips' father, [[Thomas Phillips]].]]
Lovelace died at the age of 36&amp;nbsp;– the same age at which her father had died&amp;nbsp;– on 27 November 1852,&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|publisher=GRO|title=Register of Deaths|contribution=December 1852 1a * MARYLEBONE&amp;nbsp;– Augusta Ada Lovelace}}.&lt;/ref&gt; from [[uterine cancer]] probably exacerbated by [[bloodletting]] by her physicians.{{Sfn|Baum|1986|pp=99–100}} The illness lasted several months, in which time Annabella took command over whom Ada saw, and excluded all of her friends and confidants. Under her mother's influence, she had a religious transformation and was coaxed into repenting of her previous conduct and making Annabella her executor.{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|p=370}} She lost contact with her husband after confessing something to him on 30 August which caused him to abandon her bedside. It is not known what she told him.{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|p=369}} She was buried, at her request, next to her father at the [[Church of St. Mary Magdalene, Hucknall|Church of St. Mary Magdalene]] in Hucknall, Nottinghamshire. A memorial plaque in Latin to her and her father is in the chapel attached to Horsley Towers.

==Work==
Throughout her life, Lovelace was strongly interested in scientific developments and fads of the day, including [[phrenology]]{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|p=198}} and [[mesmerism]].{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|pp=232–33}} After her work with Babbage, Lovelace continued to work on other projects. In 1844 she commented to a friend Woronzow Greig about her desire to create a mathematical model for how the brain gives rise to thoughts and nerves to feelings (&quot;a calculus of the nervous system&quot;).{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|p=305}} She never achieved this, however. In part, her interest in the brain came from a long-running pre-occupation, inherited from her mother, about her 'potential' madness. As part of her research into this project, she visited the electrical engineer Andrew Crosse in 1844 to learn how to carry out electrical experiments.{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|pp=310–14}} In the same year, she wrote a review of a paper by Baron [[Karl von Reichenbach]], ''Researches on Magnetism'', but this was not published and does not appear to have progressed past the first draft.{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|pp=315–17}} In 1851, the year before her cancer struck, she wrote to her mother mentioning &quot;certain productions&quot; she was working on regarding the relation of maths and music.{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|p=335}}

[[File:Ada Lovelace.jpg|thumb|left|Portrait of Ada by British painter [[Margaret Sarah Carpenter]] (1836)]]
Lovelace first met [[Charles Babbage]] in June 1833, through their mutual friend Mary Somerville. Later that month Babbage invited Lovelace to see the prototype for his [[difference engine]].{{Sfn|Toole|1998|pp=36–38}} She became fascinated with the machine and used her relationship with Somerville to visit Babbage as often as she could. Babbage was impressed by Lovelace's intellect and analytic skills. He called her &quot;The Enchantress of Number&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Number&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://blog.stephenwolfram.com/2015/12/untangling-the-tale-of-ada-lovelace/ |first=Stephen |last=Wolfram |authorlink=Stephen Wolfram |title=Untangling the Tale of Ada Lovelace |date=10 December 2015 |quote=Then, on Sept. 9, Babbage wrote to Ada, expressing his admiration for her and (famously) describing her as 'Enchantress of Number' and 'my dear and much admired Interpreter'. (Yes, despite what's often quoted, he wrote 'Number' not 'Numbers'.)}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=enchantress group=lower-alpha&gt;Some writers give it as &quot;Enchantress of Numbers&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1843 he wrote to her:

{{Quote|Forget this world and all its troubles and if possible its multitudinous Charlatans—every thing in short but the Enchantress of Number.&lt;ref name=&quot;Number&quot;/&gt;&lt;!--part of quote in Wolfram's text, full quote in picture below, of Ada's letter--&gt;}}

{{anchor|Ada Byron's notes on the analytical engine}}
During a nine-month period in 1842–43, Lovelace translated the Italian mathematician [[Luigi Menabrea]]'s article on Babbage's newest proposed machine, the [[Analytical Engine]]. With the article, she appended a set of notes.{{Sfn|Menabrea|1843}} Explaining the Analytical Engine's function was a difficult task, as even many other scientists did not really grasp the concept and the British establishment had shown little interest in it.{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|p=265}} Lovelace's notes even had to explain how the Analytical Engine differed from the original Difference Engine.{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|p=267}} Her work was well received at the time; the scientist [[Michael Faraday]] described himself as a supporter of her writing.{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|p = 307}}

The notes are around three times longer than the article itself and include (in ''Note G''),&lt;ref name=&quot;fourmilab.ch&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.fourmilab.ch/babbage/sketch.html|title=Sketch of ''The Analytical Engine'', with notes upon the Memoir by the Translator|publisher=fourmilab.ch|place=Switzerland|date=October 1842|accessdate=28 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; in complete detail, a method for calculating a sequence of [[Bernoulli numbers]] using the Analytical Engine, which might have run correctly had it ever been built&lt;ref name=&quot;adaslegacy&quot; /&gt; (only Babbage's Difference Engine has been built, completed in London in 2002).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.computerhistory.org/babbage|title=The Babbage Engine|publisher=Computer History Museum|year=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Based on this work, Lovelace is now widely considered to be the first computer programmer{{Sfn|Fuegi|Francis|2003}} and her method is recognised as the world's first computer program.&lt;ref&gt;Gleick, J. (2011) ''[[The Information: A History, a Theory, a Flood]]'', London, Fourth Estate, pp. 116–118.&lt;/ref&gt;

''Note G'' also contains Lovelace's dismissal of [[artificial intelligence]]. She wrote that &quot;The Analytical Engine has no pretensions whatever to ''originate'' anything. It can do ''whatever we know how to order it'' to perform. It can follow analysis; but it has no power of anticipating any analytical relations or truths.&quot; This objection has been the subject of much debate and rebuttal, for example by [[Alan Turing]] in his paper &quot;[[Computing Machinery and Intelligence]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CEMYUU_HFMAC&amp;pg=PA67&amp;f=false |journal=The Turing Test: Verbal Behavior as the Hallmark of Intelligence |editor=Stuart Shieber |title=Computing Machinery and Intelligence |author=Turing, Alan |pages=67–104 |publisher=MIT Press |year=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lovelace and Babbage had a minor falling out when the papers were published, when he tried to leave his own statement (criticising the government's treatment of his Engine) as an unsigned preface, which could have been mistakenly interpreted as a joint declaration. When [[Richard Taylor (editor)|Taylor]]'s ''[[Scientific Memoirs]]'' ruled that the statement should be signed, Babbage wrote to Lovelace asking her to withdraw the paper. This was the first that she knew he was leaving it unsigned, and she wrote back refusing to withdraw the paper. The historian [[Benjamin Woolley]] theorised that: &quot;His actions suggested he had so enthusiastically sought Ada's involvement, and so happily indulged her&amp;nbsp;... because of her 'celebrated name'.&quot;{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|pp=277–80}} Their friendship recovered, and they continued to correspond. On 12 August 1851, when she was dying of cancer, Lovelace wrote to him asking him to be her executor, though this letter did not give him the necessary legal authority. Part of the terrace at Worthy Manor was known as ''Philosopher's Walk'', as it was there that Lovelace and Babbage were reputed to have walked while discussing mathematical principles.{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|p=307}}

===First computer program===
[[File:Diagram for the computation of Bernoulli numbers.jpg|thumb|Lovelace's diagram from &quot;note G&quot;, the first published computer [[algorithm]]]]
In 1840, Babbage was invited to give a seminar at the [[University of Turin]] about his Analytical Engine. [[Luigi Menabrea]], a young Italian engineer and the future [[Prime Minister of Italy]], transcribed Babbage's lecture into French, and this transcript was subsequently published in the [[Bibliothèque universelle de Genève]] in October 1842.
Babbage's friend [[Charles Wheatstone]] commissioned Ada Lovelace to translate Menabrea's paper into English. She then augmented the paper with notes, which were added to the translation. Ada Lovelace spent the better part of a year doing this, assisted with input from Babbage. These notes, which are more extensive than Menabrea's paper, were then published in the September 1843 edition of Taylor's ''[[Scientific Memoirs]]'' under the [[initialism]] ''AAL''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Green|first=Christopher|url=http://www.yorku.ca/christo/papers/Babbage-CogSci.htm|title=Charles Babbage, the Analytical Engine, and the Possibility of a 19th-Century Cognitive Science|publisher=York University|year=2001|accessdate=2 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ada Lovelace's notes were labelled alphabetically from A to G. In note G, she describes an [[algorithm]] for the Analytical Engine to compute [[Bernoulli number]]s. It is considered to be the first published algorithm ever specifically tailored for implementation on a computer, and Ada Lovelace has often been cited as the first computer programmer for this reason.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Simonite|first=Tom|url=https://www.newscientist.com/blogs/shortsharpscience/2009/03/ada-lovelace-day.html|title=Short Sharp Science: Celebrating Ada Lovelace: the 'world's first programmer'| work= [[New Scientist]]|date=24 March 2009|archive-date=27 March 2009 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090327073325/https://www.newscientist.com/blogs/shortsharpscience/2009/03/ada-lovelace-day.html |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Parker|first1=Matt|title=Things to Make and Do in the Fourth Dimension|date=2014|publisher=Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux|isbn=0374275653|page=261}}&lt;/ref&gt; The engine was never completed so her program was never tested.{{sfn|Kim|Toole|1999}}

In 1953, more than a century after her death, Ada Lovelace's notes on Babbage's Analytical Engine were republished as an appendix to [[B.V. Bowden]]'s ''Faster than Thought: A Symposium on Digital Computing Machines''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |editor = Bowden, B.V.|date = 1953 |title = Faster than Thought: A Symposium on Digital Computing Machines  |url = https://archive.org/details/fasterthanthough00bvbo |publisher = Pitman |place = London |oclc = 1053355 |ol = 13581728M }}&lt;/ref&gt; The engine has now been recognised as an early model for a computer and her notes as a description of a computer and software.&lt;ref name=&quot;adaslegacy&quot;&gt;{{cite book |editor-first1= Robin |editor-last1= Hammerman |editor-first2=Andrew L. |editor-last2= Russell| title=Ada's Legacy: Cultures of Computing from the Victorian to the Digital Age |publisher=Morgan &amp; Claypool |year=2015 |isbn=978-1-97000-149-5 |doi=10.1145/2809523}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Insight into potential of computing devices===
In her notes, Lovelace emphasised the difference between the Analytical Engine and previous calculating machines, particularly its ability to be programmed to solve problems of any complexity.{{Sfn|Toole|1998|pp=175–82}} She realised the potential of the device extended far beyond mere number crunching. In her notes, she wrote:
{{Quote|[The Analytical Engine] might act upon other things besides ''number'', were objects found whose mutual fundamental relations could be expressed by those of the abstract science of operations, and which should be also susceptible of adaptations to the action of the operating notation and mechanism of the engine...Supposing, for instance, that the fundamental relations of pitched sounds in the science of harmony and of musical composition were susceptible of such expression and adaptations, the engine might compose elaborate and scientific pieces of music of any degree of complexity or extent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Lovelace|first1=Ada|last2=Menabrea|first2=Luigi|title=Sketch of the Analytical Engine invented by Charles Babbage Esq.|year=1842|journal=[[Scientific Memoirs]]|publisher=Richard Taylor|page=694}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Hooper|first=Rowan|url=https://www.newscientist.com/article/dn22385-ada-lovelace-my-brain-is-more-than-merely-mortal.html|title=Ada Lovelace: My brain is more than merely mortal|work=New Scientist|date=16 October 2012|accessdate=16 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

This analysis was an important development from previous ideas about the capabilities of computing devices and anticipated the implications of modern computing one hundred years before they were realised. [[Walter Isaacson]] ascribes Lovelace's insight regarding the application of computing to ''any'' process based on logical symbols to an observation about textiles: &quot;When she saw some mechanical looms that used [[punched cards|punchcards]] to direct the weaving of beautiful [[pattern]]s, it reminded her of how Babbage's engine used punched cards to make calculations.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Isaacson&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://fortune.com/2014/09/18/walter-isaacson-the-women-of-eniac/ |title=Walter Isaacson on the Women of ENIAC |last=Isaacson |first=Walter |date=18 September 2014 |work=[[Fortune (magazine)|Fortune]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; This insight is seen as significant by writers such as Betty Toole and Benjamin Woolley, as well as the programmer [[John Graham-Cumming]], whose project Plan 28 has the aim of constructing the first complete Analytical Engine.{{Sfn|Toole|1998|pp=2–3, 14}}{{Sfn|Woolley|1999|pp=272–77}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Kent|first=Leo|url=http://www.humansinvent.com/#!/8947/the-10-year-plan-to-build-babbages-analytical-engine|title=The 10-year-plan to build Babbage's Analytical Engine|publisher=Humans Invent|date=17 September 2012|accessdate=16 October 2012|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121014123843/http://www.humansinvent.com/#!/8947/the-10-year-plan-to-build-babbages-analytical-engine|archive-date=14 October 2012|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the historian of computing and Babbage specialist [[Doron Swade]]: &lt;blockquote&gt;Ada saw something that Babbage in some sense failed to see. In Babbage's world his engines were bound by number...What Lovelace saw—what Ada Byron saw—was that number could represent entities other than quantity. So once you had a machine for manipulating numbers, if those numbers represented other things, letters, musical notes, then the machine could manipulate symbols of which number was one instance, according to rules. It is this fundamental transition from a machine which is a number cruncher to a machine for manipulating symbols according to rules that is the fundamental transition from calculation to computation—to general-purpose computation—and looking back from the present high ground of modern computing, if we are looking and sifting history for that transition, then that transition was made explicitly by Ada in that 1843 paper.{{Sfn|Fuegi|Francis|2003}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Controversy over her actual contribution===
Though Lovelace is referred to as the first computer programmer, some biographers, computer scientists and historians of computing claim otherwise.

[[Allan Bromley (historian)|Allan G. Bromley]], in the 1990 article ''Difference and Analytical Engines'':
{{quote|All but one of the programs cited in her notes had been prepared by Babbage from three to seven years earlier. The exception was prepared by Babbage for her, although she did detect a 'bug' in it. Not only is there no evidence that Ada ever prepared a program for the Analytical Engine, but her correspondence with Babbage shows that she did not have the knowledge to do so.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Bromley |first=Allan G. |authorlink=Allan G. Bromley |contribution=Difference and Analytical Engines |title=Computing Before Computers |editor-first=William |editor-last=Aspray |publisher=Iowa State University Press |location=Ames |pages=59–98 |chapter-url=http://ed-thelen.org/comp-hist/CBC-Ch-02.pdf |chapter-format=pdf|date=1990 |isbn=0-8138-0047-1}} p. 89.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Bruce Collier, who later wrote a biography of Babbage, wrote in his 1970 [[Harvard University]] PhD thesis that Lovelace &quot;made a considerable contribution to publicizing the Analytical Engine, but there is no evidence that she advanced the design or theory of it in any way&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite thesis |last=Collier |first=Bruce |title=The Little Engines That Could've: The Calculating Machines of Charles Babbage |type=PhD |publisher=Harvard University |year=1970 |url=http://robroy.dyndns.info/collier |accessdate=18 December 2015}} Chapter 3.&lt;/ref&gt;

Eugene Eric Kim and Betty Alexandra Toole consider it &quot;incorrect&quot; to regard Lovelace as the first computer programmer, as Babbage wrote the initial programs for his Analytical Engine, although the majority were never published.{{sfn|Kim|Toole|1999|p=76}} Bromley notes several dozen sample programs prepared by Babbage between 1837 and 1840, all substantially predating Lovelace's notes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Bromley |first=Allan G. |date=July–September 1982 |title=Charles Babbage's Analytical Engine, 1838 |journal=IEEE Annals of the History of Computing |url=http://athena.union.edu/~hemmendd/Courses/cs80/an-engine.pdf |pages=197–217 |volume=4 |issue=3 |doi=10.1109/mahc.1982.10028 |format=pdf}} p. 197.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Dorothy K. Stein]] regards Lovelace's notes as &quot;more a reflection of the mathematical uncertainty of the author, the political purposes of the inventor, and, above all, of the social and cultural context in which it was written, than a blueprint for a scientific development&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Stein |first=Dorothy K. |year=1984 |title=Lady Lovelace's Notes: Technical Text and Cultural Context |journal=Victorian Studies |pages=33–67 |volume=28 |issue=1}} p. 34.&lt;/ref&gt;

In his book, ''Idea Makers'', [[Stephen Wolfram]] defends Lovelace's contributions. While acknowledging that Babbage wrote several unpublished algorithms for the Analytical Engine prior to Lovelace's notes, Wolfram argues that &quot;there's nothing as sophisticated—or as clean—as Ada's computation of the Bernoulli numbers. Babbage certainly helped and commented on Ada's work, but she was definitely the driver of it.&quot; Wolfram then suggests that Lovelace's main achievement was to distill from Babbage's correspondence &quot;a clear exposition of the abstract operation of the machine—something which Babbage never did.&quot;{{citation needed|date=August 2019}}

[[Doron Swade]], a specialist on [[history of computing]] known for his work on Babbage, analysed four claims about Lovelace during a lecture on Babbage's analytical engine:
#She was a mathematical genius
#She made an influential contribution to the analytical engine
#She was the first computer programmer
#She was a prophet of the computer age

According to him, only the fourth claim had &quot;any substance at all&quot;. He explained that Ada was only a &quot;promising beginner&quot; instead of genius in mathematics, that she began studying basic concepts of mathematics five years after Babbage conceived the analytical engine so she could not have made important contributions to it, and that she only published the first computer program instead of actually writing it. But he agrees that Ada was the only person to see the potential of the analytical engine as a machine capable of expressing entities other than quantities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite speech |last=Swade |first=Doron |author-link=Doron Swade |title=Charles Babbage and Difference Engine No. 2 |event=Talks at Google |date=12 May 2008 |location=Mountain View, CA |publisher=Talks at Google via YouTube |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7K5p_tBcrd0&amp;t=36m29s |access-date=29 November 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In popular culture==
[[File:Ada Lovelace color.svg|thumb|upright|An illustration inspired by the [[A. E. Chalon]] portrait created for the [[Ada Initiative]], which supported open technology and women]]
===1810s===
Lord Byron wrote in 1816 the poem [[Fare Thee Well (poem)|Fare Thee Well]]  to his wife [[Lady Byron]] after their separation after the birth of [[Ada Lovelace]] (born in 10 December 1815), about her he wrote in the poem:

And when thou wouldst solace gather,	
When our child’s first accents flow,	
Wilt thou teach her to say ‘Father!’	       
Though his care she must forego?	
 
When her little hands shall press thee,	
When her lip to thine is press’d,	
Think of him whose prayer shall bless thee,	
Think of him thy love had bless’d!	        40
 
Should her lineaments resemble	
Those thou never more may’st see,	
Then thy heart will softly tremble	
With a pulse yet true to me.&lt;ref&gt;https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Works_of_Lord_Byron_(ed._Coleridge,_Prothero)/Poetry/Volume_3/Poems_of_the_Separation#Fare_Thee_Well&lt;/ref&gt;

===1970s===
Lovelace has been portrayed in [[Romulus Linney (playwright)|Romulus Linney]]'s 1977 play ''[[Childe Byron]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Theatre in review: A lusty Byron in Rockland|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1984/05/13/nyregion/theater-in-review-a-lusty-byron-in-rockland.html|first=Alvin|last=Klein|authorlink=Alvin Klein|date=13 May 1984}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

===1990s===

In the 1990 [[steampunk]] novel ''[[The Difference Engine]]'' by [[William Gibson]] and [[Bruce Sterling]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|contribution=The Future Looms: Weaving Women and Cybernetics|first=Sadie|last=Plant|pages=45–64|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZXU5aoJL0-QC&amp;pg=PA45|title=Cyberspace/Cyberbodies/Cyberpunk: Cultures of Technological Embodiment|editor1-first=Mike|editor1-last=Featherstone|editor2-first=Roger|editor2-last=Burrows|publisher=SAGE Publications, in association with Theory, Culture &amp; Society, School of Human Studies, University of Teesside|year=1995|isbn=9781848609143}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ada Lovelace delivers a lecture on the &quot;punched cards&quot; programme that proves [[Gödel's incompleteness theorems|two theorems]], the discovery that, in reality, would not be made until 1931 by [[Kurt Gödel]].

In the 1997 film ''[[Conceiving Ada]],''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title='Conceiving Ada': Calling Byron's Daughter, Inventor of a Computer|url=https://www.nytimes.com/library/film/022699ada-film-review.html|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|first=Stephen|last=Holden|authorlink=Stephen Holden|date=26 February 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt; a computer scientist obsessed with Countess Ada Lovelace finds a way of communicating with Lovelace in the past by means of &quot;undying information waves&quot;.

In [[Tom Stoppard]]'s 1993 play ''[[Arcadia (play)|Arcadia]]'', the precocious teenage genius Thomasina Coverly (a character &quot;apparently based&quot; on Ada Lovelace—the play also involves [[Lord Byron]]) comes to understand [[chaos theory]], and theorises the [[second law of thermodynamics]], before either is officially recognised.&lt;ref name=&quot;newyorker13&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.newyorker.com/books/page-turner/tom-stoppards-arcadia-at-twenty |title=Tom Stoppard's 'Arcadia,' at Twenty |first=Brad |last=Leithauser |date=8 August 2013 |work=[[The New Yorker]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tomw.net.au/arcadia.txt Profile], Gale Edwards, 1994, Director of &quot;Arcadia&quot; for the Sydney Theatre Company&lt;/ref&gt; 

===2010s===

In [[John Crowley (author)|John Crowley]]'s 2005 novel ''Lord Byron's Novel: The Evening Land'', where she is featured as an unseen character whose personality is forcefully depicted in her annotations and anti-heroic efforts to archive her father's lost novel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Byron's heir|newspaper=[[Los Angeles Times]]|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2005/jun/05/books/bk-straub5|first=Peter|last=Straub|authorlink=Peter Straub|date=5 June 2005 |archive-date=10 November 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131110092446/https://articles.latimes.com/2005/jun/05/books/bk-straub5 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2015 play ''[[Ada and the Memory Engine]]'' by [[Lauren Gunderson]] portrays Lovelace and Charles Babbage in unrequited love, and it imagines a post-death meeting between Lovelace and her father.&lt;ref name=&quot;kqed&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://ww2.kqed.org/arts/the-do-list/ada-and-the-memory-engine/ | title=Ada and the Memory Engine | publisher=[[KQED]] | archive-date=6 September 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150906141059/https://ww2.kqed.org/arts/the-do-list/ada-and-the-memory-engine/ |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sfweekly&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.sfweekly.com/exhibitionist/2015/10/22/ada-and-the-memory-engine-love-by-the-numbers | title=Ada and the Memory Engine: Love by the Numbers |work=SF Weekly | date=22 October 2015 | accessdate=14 November 2015 | author=Costello, Elizabeth}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lovelace and Babbage are the main characters in [[Sydney Padua]]'s webcomic and graphic novel ''[[The Thrilling Adventures of Lovelace and Babbage]]''. The comic features extensive footnotes on the history of Ada Lovelace, and many lines of dialogue are drawn from actual correspondence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Doctorow|first1=Cory|title=Comic about Ada Lovelace and Charles Babbage|url=http://boingboing.net/2009/10/05/comic-about-ada-love.html|website=BoingBoing|accessdate=10 October 2014|date=5 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lovelace and [[Mary Shelley]] as teenagers are the central characters in [[Jordan Stratford]]'s steampunk series, ''The Wollstonecraft Detective Agency''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Moyer|first1=Edward|title=Can Jane Austen + steampunk spark girls' science fire?|url=https://www.cnet.com/uk/news/can-jane-austen-steampunk-spark-girls-science-fire/|accessdate=26 February 2017|date=13 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lovelace, identified as Ada Augusta Byron, is portrayed by Lily Lesser in the second season of ''[[The Frankenstein Chronicles]]''.  She is employed as an &quot;analyst&quot; to provide the workings of a life-sized humanoid automaton.  The brass workings of the machine are reminiscent of Babbage's analytical engine.  Her employment is described as keeping her occupied until she returns to her studies in advanced mathematics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.imdb.com/name/nm7104940/|title=Lily Lesser|access-date=29 November 2018|publisher=IMDb}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of November 2015, all new British passports have included an illustration of Lovelace and Babbage on pages 46 and 47.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/473495/HMPO_magazine.pdf|title=Introducing the new UK passport design|publisher=HM Passport Office|access-date=20 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/gallery/2015/nov/03/new-uk-passport-design-in-pictures|title=New UK passport design – in pictures|first=All photographs: HM Passport|last=Office|date=3 November 2015|website=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2017, a [[Google Doodle]] honoured her on [[International Women's Day]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.google.com/doodles/international-womens-day-2017|title=International Women's Day|access-date=8 March 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lovelace and Babbage appear as characters in the second season of the ITV series ''[[Victoria (UK TV series)|Victoria]]'' (2017). [[Emerald Fennell]] portrays Lovelace in the episode, &quot;The Green-Eyed Monster&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt6327804/|title=The Green-Eyed Monster|date=14 January 2018|publisher=IMDb}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Cardano platform uses ADA as the name for their cryptocurrency and Lovelace as the smallest sub-unit of an ADA.&lt;ref&gt;[https://cardanodocs.com/technical/wallet/api/v1/#section/Monetary-Denomination-and-Units Cryptocurrency named after Ada Lovelace]&lt;/ref&gt;

On 2 February 2018, [[Satellogic]], a high-resolution [[Earth observation]] imaging and analytics company, launched a [[ÑuSat]] type [[Small satellite|micro-satellite]] named in honour of Ada Lovelace.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://spaceflightnow.com/2018/02/02/china-lofts-earthquake-research-craft-with-cluster-of-smaller-satellites/|title=China lofts earthquake research craft with cluster of smaller satellites – Spaceflight Now|website=spaceflightnow.com|access-date=4 February 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2020s===
On 5 January 2020, actress Sylvie Briggs played 1834 Lovelace (the year before her marriage), alongside characterizations of Charles Babbage and 1943 [[Noor Inayat Khan]] (the year before her murder), in &quot;[[Spyfall (Doctor Who)|Spyfall, Part 2]]&quot;, the second episode of [[Doctor Who (series 12)|''Doctor Who'', series 12]].

==Commemoration&lt;!--'Ada Lovelace Day' redirects here--&gt;==
[[File:AdaLovelaceplaque.JPG|thumb|left|upright|[[Blue plaque]] to Lovelace in [[St. James's Square]], London]]
The computer language [[Ada (programming language)|Ada]], created on behalf of the [[United States Department of Defense]], was named after Lovelace.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.ithistory.org/honor-roll/mrs-augusta-ada-king-countess-lovelace|title=Mrs. Augusta Ada King, Countess of Lovelace|date=21 December 2015|work=IT History Society|access-date=21 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The reference manual for the language was approved on 10 December 1980 and the [[United States Military Standard|Department of Defense Military Standard]] for the language, ''MIL-STD-1815'', was given the number of the year of her birth.

In 1981, the [[Association for Women in Computing]] inaugurated its [[Ada Lovelace Award]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6z0aAQAAMAAJ&amp;q=the+Augusta+Ada+Lovelace+Award+by+the+Association+for+Women+in+Computing&amp;dq=the+Augusta+Ada+Lovelace+Award+by+the+Association+for+Women+in+Computing&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiHup7Q_vHdAhUG24MKHb1PArM4ChDoAQgoMAA |title=Awards, Honors &amp; Prizes: United States and Canada |last=Webster |first=Valerie J. |date=2000 |publisher=Gale Group |isbn=9780787634018 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name =Award&gt;{{cite web
 | url =http://awc-hq.org/ada-lovelace-awards.html | title = Association for Women in Computing | access-date = 1 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since 1998, the [[British Computer Society]] (BCS) has awarded the [[Lovelace Medal]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bcs.org/server.php?show=nav.5822|title=Lovelace Lecture &amp; Medal|publisher=[[British Computer Society|BCS]] |archive-date=26 August 2006 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060826081022/https://www.bcs.org/server.php?show=nav.5822 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in 2008 initiated an annual competition for women students.&lt;ref name=BCSWomen /&gt; [[BCSWomen]] sponsors the Lovelace Colloquium, an annual conference for women undergraduates.&lt;ref name=BCSWomen&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.aber.ac.uk/en/cs/lovelace-colloquium/ | location = UK | title= BCSWomen Lovelace Colloquium }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ada College]] is a further-education college in [[Tottenham Hale]], London, focused on digital skills.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Davis|first1=Anna|title=New college in north London 'will boost women in tech sector'|url=https://www.standard.co.uk/news/education/new-college-in-north-london-will-boost-women-in-tech-sector-a3200201.html|website=London Evening Standard|accessdate=16 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ada Lovelace Day is an annual event celebrated on the second Tuesday of October,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://findingada.com/|title=Celebrating women in STEM |publisher=Finding Ada | accessdate= 11 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; which began in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/life-style/women/ada-lovelace-day-first-computer-programmer-forgotten-women-a8557416.html|title=Ada Lovelace Day: We should never forget the first computer programmer|date=8 October 2018|website=The Independent|access-date=27 February 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its goal is to &quot;...&amp;nbsp;raise the profile of women in science, technology, engineering, and maths,&quot; and to &quot;create new role models for girls and women&quot; in these fields. Events have included Wikipedia [[edit-a-thons]] with the aim of improving the representation of women on Wikipedia in terms of articles and editors to reduce unintended [[gender bias on Wikipedia]]. The [[Ada Initiative]] was a non-profit organisation dedicated to increasing the involvement of women in the [[free culture movement|free culture]] and [[Open-source software movement|open source movements]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=https://lwn.net/Articles/471813/ |title=An update on the Ada Initiative |work = LWN | last=Aurora | first=Valerie |date=13 December 2011 | accessdate= 5 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Engineering in Computer Science and Telecommunications College building in [[Zaragoza University]] is called the Ada Byron Building.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Ada Byron Building | url=http://wikimapia.org/1641862/Ada-Byron-Building}}&lt;/ref&gt; The computer centre in the village of [[Porlock]], near where Lovelace lived, is named after her. Ada Lovelace House is a council-owned building in [[Kirkby-in-Ashfield]], Nottinghamshire, near where Lovelace spent her infancy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.chad.co.uk/news/town-centre-landmark-renovated-to-boost-kirkby-s-economy-1-8538257|title=Town-centre landmark renovated to boost Kirkby's economy|date=11 May 2017|work=Mansfield and Ashfield Chad|access-date=29 November 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://woodhead-construction.co.uk/ada-lovelace-house-officially-opened/|title=Ada Lovelace House Is Officially Opened|date=18 October 2017|publisher=Woodhead Construction|access-date=29 November 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

She is also the inspiration and influence for the Ada Developers Academy in Seattle, Washington. The academy is a non-profit that seeks to increase diversity in tech by training women, trans and non-binary people to be software engineers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://adadevelopersacademy.org/|title=Ada Developers Academy|website=adadevelopersacademy.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2018, ''[[The New York Times]]'' published a belated obituary for Ada Lovelace.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2018/obituaries/overlooked-ada-lovelace.html|title=A gifted mathematician who is now recognized as the first computer programmer|first=Claire Cain|last=Miller|date=8 March 2018|work=[[The New York Times]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 27 July 2018, [[Ron Wyden|Senator Ron Wyden]] submitted, in the [[United States Senate]], the designation of 9 October 2018 as National Ada Lovelace Day: &quot;To honor the life and contributions of Ada Lovelace as a leading woman in science and mathematics&quot;. The resolution (S.Res.592)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.congress.gov/bill/115th-congress/senate-resolution/592|title=S.Res.592 – 115th Congress (2017–2018): A resolution designating October 9, 2018, as &quot;National Ada Lovelace Day&quot; and honoring the life and legacy of Ada Lovelace, the first computer programmer.|last=Ron|first=Wyden|date=25 July 2018|website=congress.gov|access-date=9 October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; was considered, and agreed to without amendment and with a preamble by unanimous consent.

==Bicentenary==
The [[Anniversary|bicentenary]] of Ada Lovelace's birth was celebrated with a number of events, including:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://findingada.com/ | title=Ada Lovelace Day: Celebrating the achievements of women in science, technology, engineering and maths | date=13 October 2015 | website=FindingAda.com | accessdate=11 January 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

* ''The Ada Lovelace Bicentenary Lectures on [[Computability]]'', [[Israel Institute for Advanced Studies]], 20 December 2015 – 31 January 2016.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://findingada.com/event/ada-lovelace-bicentenary-lectures-on-computability/ | title=Ada Lovelace Bicentenary Lectures on Computability | date=20 December 2015 – 31 January 2016 | work=Ada Lovelace Day | publisher=FindingAda.com | accessdate=11 January 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.as.huji.ac.il/adalovelacelectures | title=The Ada Lovelace Bicentenary Lectures on Computability | date=20 December 2015 – 31 January 2016 | publisher=Israel Institute for Advanced Studies | accessdate=11 January 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Ada Lovelace Symposium'', [[University of Oxford]], 13–14 October 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://podcasts.ox.ac.uk/series/ada-lovelace-symposium-celebrating-200-years-computer-visionary | title=Ada Lovelace Symposium – Celebrating 200 Years of a Computer Visionary | work=Podcasts | publisher=University of Oxford | location=UK | accessdate=11 January 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''Ada.Ada.Ada'', a one-woman show about the life and work of Ada Lovelace (using an LED dress), premiered at [[Edinburgh International Science Festival]] on 11 April 2015,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.sciencefestival.co.uk/brochure-downloads|title=Brochure Downloads|website=[[Edinburgh International Science Festival]]|access-date=9 October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; and continues to touring internationally to promote diversity on STEM at technology conferences,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://elpais.com/tecnologia/2018/04/19/actualidad/1524125257_350138.html|title=4.400 bombillas para la silenciada historia de la mujer que escribió la primera 'app' en 1843|trans-title=4,400 light bulbs for the silenced story of the woman who wrote the first 'app' in 1843|last=Busquets|first=Jordi Pueyo|date=19 April 2018|work=[[El País]]|access-date=9 October 2018|language=es|issn=1134-6582}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.siliconrepublic.com/discovery/ada-lovelace-day-zoe-philpott-inspirefest|title=Meet the woman bringing the magic of Ada Lovelace to the masses|last=Gorey|first=Colm|date=11 October 2016|website=Silicon Republic|access-date=9 October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; businesses, government and educational organisations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://adatheshow.com/ |title=Ada.Ada.Ada. |year=2016 |website=adatheshow.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Scratchweb|title=Ada.Ada.Ada|date=16 May 2017|url=https://vimeo.com/217701947|access-date=9 October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Special exhibitions were displayed by the [[Science Museum, London|Science Museum]] in London, England&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.sciencemuseum.org.uk/visitmuseum/Plan_your_visit/exhibitions/ada-lovelace | title=Ada Lovelace |publisher=Science Museum, London | location=UK | accessdate=11 January 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Weston Library]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=https://www.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/weston/news/2015/oct-09 | title=Bodleian Libraries celebrates Ada Lovelace's 200th birthday with free display and Wikipedia editathons | publisher=[[Bodleian Libraries]] | location=UK | accessdate=11 January 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; (part of the [[Bodleian Library]]) in [[Oxford]], England.

==Publications==
* Lovelace, Ada King. ''Ada, the Enchantress of Numbers: A Selection from the Letters of Lord Byron's Daughter and her Description of the First Computer''. Mill Valley, CA: Strawberry Press, 1992. {{ISBN|9780912647098}}.
*{{cite book |last1=Menabrea |first1=Luigi Federico |last2=Lovelace |first2=Ada |editor=Richard Taylor |title=Scientific Memoirs |date=1843 |volume=3 |pages=666–731 |chapter=Sketch of the Analytical Engine invented by Charles Babbage... with notes by the translator. Translated by Ada Lovelace |chapter-url=http://www.fourmilab.ch/babbage/sketch.html |location=London |publisher=Richard and John E. Taylor}}

== Publication history ==
Six copies of the 1843 first edition of ''Sketch of the Analytical Engine'' with Ada Lovelace's ''Notes''&lt;ref name=&quot;fourmilab.ch&quot; /&gt; have been located. Three are held at Harvard University, one at the University of Oklahoma, and one at the United States Air Force Academy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://id.lib.harvard.edu/alma/990030757610203941/catalog|title=Sketch of the analytical engine invented by Charles Babbage, Esq.|website=Harvard University Library|access-date=9 April 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 20 July 2018, the sixth copy was sold at auction to an anonymous buyer for £95,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181010011141/https://www.mooreallen.co.uk/group/news-events/rare-book-by-worlds-first-computer-programmer-sells-for-95000 |archive-date=10 October 2018 |url=https://www.mooreallen.co.uk/group/news-events/rare-book-by-worlds-first-computer-programmer-sells-for-95000|title=Rare book by world's first computer programmer sells for £95,000|date=23 July 2018|website=mooreallen.co.uk|access-date=9 April 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; A digital facsimile of one of the copies in the Harvard University Library is available online.

==See also==
{{Portal|Computer programming|Biography}}
* ''[[Code: Debugging the Gender Gap]]''
* {{section link|Great Lives|Series 31, August – October 2013|display=''Great Lives''}} — the episode aired on 17 September 2013 was dedicated to the story of Ada Lovelace&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b03b0ydy |title=Series 31, Konnie Huq on Ada Lovelace |work=[[Great Lives]] |publisher=[[BBC Radio 4]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[List of pioneers in computer science]]
* [[Timeline of women in science]]
* [[Women in computing]]
* [[Women in STEM fields]]
* [[Ai-Da (robot)]]

==Notes==
{{Notelist}}
{{Reflist|group=note}}

== References ==
{{Reflist |30em}}

==Sources==
{{refbegin|30em}}
* {{Citation | last = Baum | first = Joan | title = The Calculating Passion of Ada Byron | publisher = Archon | year = 1986 | isbn = 978-0-208-02119-9 | url = https://archive.org/details/calculatingpassi00baum }}.
* {{Citation | last1 = Elwin | first1 = Malcolm | title = Lord Byron's Family | publisher = John Murray | year = 1975}}.
* {{Citation | last = Essinger | first = James | title = Ada's algorithm: How Lord Byron's daughter Ada Lovelace launched the digital age | publisher = Melville House Publishing | year = 2014 | isbn = 978-1-61219-408-0}}.
* {{Citation | last1 = Fuegi | first1 = J | last2 = Francis | first2 = J | title = Lovelace &amp; Babbage and the creation of the 1843 'notes' | journal = Annals of the History of Computing | volume = 25 | pages = 16–26 | number = 4 |date=October–December 2003 | doi=10.1109/MAHC.2003.1253887}}.
* {{Citation | last1 = Hammerman | first1 = Robin | last2 = Russell | first2 = Andrew L. | title = Ada's Legacy: Cultures of Computing from the Victorian to the Digital Age  | publisher = Association for Computing Machinery and Morgan &amp; Claypool  |year = 2015 | doi = 10.1145/2809523| isbn = 9781970001518 }}.
* {{Citation | last=Isaacson | first=Walter |year=2014 | title= The Innovators: How a Group of Hackers, Geniuses, and Geeks Created the Digital Revolution | publisher = Simon &amp; Schuster}}.
* {{Cite journal | last1 = Kim | first1 = Eugene | last2 = Toole | first2 = Betty Alexandra | title = Ada and the First Computer | journal = Scientific American | volume = 280 | issue = 5 | pages = 76–81 |year=1999 | bibcode = 1999SciAm.280e..76E | doi = 10.1038/scientificamerican0599-76 |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite journal | last = Lewis | first = Judith S. | title = Princess of Parallelograms and her daughter: Math and gender in the nineteenth century English aristocracy | journal = [[Women's Studies International Forum]] | volume = 18 | issue = 4 | pages = 387–394 | doi = 10.1016/0277-5395(95)80030-S | date = July–August 1995 | ref = harv }}
* {{Citation | last1 = Marchand | first1 = Leslie | title = Byron A Portrait | publisher = John Murray | year = 1971}}.
* {{Citation |last=Menabrea |first= Luigi Federico |authorlink= Federico Luigi Menabrea |year= 1843 | title = Sketch of the Analytical Engine Invented by Charles Babbage | journal= [[Scientific Memoirs]] | volume = 3 | url = http://www.fourmilab.ch/babbage/sketch.html | accessdate = 29 August 2008 | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20080915134651/http://www.fourmilab.ch/babbage/sketch.html | archivedate = 15 September 2008 | url-status = live}} With notes upon the memoir by the translator.
* Miller, Clair Cain. [https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2018/obituaries/overlooked-ada-lovelace.html &quot;Ada Lovelace, 1815–1852,&quot;] ''New York Times,'' 8 March 2018.
* {{Citation | last1 = Moore | first1 = Doris Langley | title = Ada, Countess of Lovelace | publisher = John Murray | year = 1977|isbn=0 7195 3384 8}}.
* {{Citation |last=Moore |first=Doris Langley |title=The Late Lord Byron |year= 1961 |publisher=Lippincott | location =Philadelphia |oclc=358063 |isbn=978-0-06-013013-8}}.
* {{Citation |last=Stein |first=Dorothy |title=Ada: A Life and a Legacy |year=1985 |publisher=The MIT Press |location=Cambridge, [[Massachusetts|MA]] |series=MIT Press Series in the History of Computing |isbn=978-0-262-19242-2 |url=https://archive.org/details/adalifeandlegacy00stei }}.
* {{Citation | first = Betty Alexandra | last = Toole | title = Ada, the Enchantress of Numbers: A Selection from the Letters of Ada Lovelace, and her Description of the First Computer | year = 1992 | publisher = Strawberry Press | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=wlZQAAAAMAAJ | isbn = 978-0912647098}}.
* {{Citation | first = Betty Alexandra | last = Toole | title = Ada, the Enchantress of Numbers: Prophet of the Computer Age | year = 1998 | publisher = Strawberry Press | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=gnvZAAAAMAAJ | isbn = 978-0912647180}}.
* {{Citation | first = Catherine | last = Turney | title = Byron's Daughter: A Biography of Elizabeth Medora Leigh | year = 1972 | publisher = Scribner | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=eE1aAAAAMAAJ | isbn = 978-0684127538}}
* {{Citation | last=Woolley | first=Benjamin |date=February 1999 | title= The Bride of Science: Romance, Reason, and Byron's Daughter | publisher = Pan Macmillan | place = AU | url= https://books.google.com/books?id=K8-sQgAACAAJ | accessdate= 7 April 2013 | isbn = 978-0-333-72436-1}}.
* {{Citation | last=Woolley | first=Benjamin |date=February 2002 | origyear=1999  | title= The Bride of Science: Romance, Reason, and Byron's Daughter | publisher = McGraw-Hill Ryerson | url= https://books.google.com/books?id=VGMFAAAACAAJ | accessdate= 7 April 2013 | isbn = 978-0-07138860-3}}.
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
* [[Jenny Uglow]], &quot;Stepping Out of Byron's Shadow&quot; (review of [[Miranda Seymour]], ''In Byron's Wake:  The Turbulent Lives of Byron's Wife and Daughter:  Annabella Milbanke and Ada Lovelace'', Pegasus, 2018, 547 pp.; and [[Christopher Hollings]], [[Ursula Martin]], and [[Adrian Rice]], ''Ada Lovelace: The Making of a Computer Scientist'', Bodleian Library, 2018, 114 pp.), ''[[The New York Review of Books]]'', vol. LXV, no. 18 (22 November 2018), pp.&amp;nbsp;30–32.

==External links==
{{Commons}}{{Wikiquote}}

* [https://www.siliconrepublic.com/video/adas-army-zoe-philpott &quot;Ada's Army gets set to rewrite history at Inspirefest 2018&quot;] by Luke Maxwell, 4 August 2018
*{{OL author|776398A}}
* &quot;[http://blog.stephenwolfram.com/2015/12/untangling-the-tale-of-ada-lovelace/ Untangling the Tale of Ada Lovelace]&quot; by [[Stephen Wolfram]], December 2015
* {{Cite web | url = http://www.sdsc.edu/ScienceWomen/lovelace.html | title = Ada Lovelace: Founder of Scientific Computing | work = Women in Science| publisher = SDSC }}
* {{Cite web | url = http://www.agnesscott.edu/lriddle/women/love.htm | title = Ada Byron, Lady Lovelace | work = Biographies of Women Mathematicians | publisher = [[Agnes Scott College]]}}
* {{Cite web | url = http://archive.wikiwix.com/cache/20120424131314/http://archiveshub.ac.uk/data/gb161dep.lovelacebyron1-460 | title = Papers of the Noel, Byron and Lovelace families | publisher = Archives hub | place = UK |format=archive }}
* {{Cite web | url = http://www.computerhistory.org/babbage/adalovelace/ | work = Babbage | title = Ada Lovelace &amp; The Analytical Engine | publisher = Computer History}}
* {{Cite web | url = https://web.archive.org/web/20090810090713/http://net.educause.edu/apps/er/review/reviewArticles/31240.html | title = Ada &amp; the Analytical Engine | publisher = Educause |format=archive}}
* {{Cite web | url = http://www.g4tv.com/techtvvault/features/27659/Ada_Lovelace_Countess_of_Controversy.html | work = Tech TV vault | title = Ada Lovelace, Countess of Controversy | publisher = G4 TV}}
* {{Cite web | url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/history/inourtime/inourtime_20080306.shtml | work = In Our Time | publisher = The BBC (Radio 4) | title = Ada Lovelace | format = streaming | type = audio | place = UK | date = 6 March 2008}}
* {{Cite web | url = http://www.cs.yale.edu/homes/tap/Files/ada-lovelace-notes.html | title = Ada Lovelace's Notes and The Ladies Diary | publisher = Yale}}
* {{Cite web | url = https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hRmEYMiphoU | title = The fascinating story Ada Lovelace | publisher = Sabine Allaeys (Youtube)}}
* {{Cite web | url = http://www.brainpickings.org/index.php/2013/12/10/ada-lovelace-science-religion-letter/ | title = Ada Lovelace, the World's First Computer Programmer, on Science and Religion | publisher = Maria Popova (Brain) }}
* {{Cite web | url = http://www.brainpickings.org/2014/12/10/ada-lovelace-walter-isaacson-innovators/ | title = How Ada Lovelace, Lord Byron's Daughter, Became the World's First Computer Programmer | publisher = Maria Popova (Brain) }}
* {{MacTutor Biography|id=Lovelace}}

{{Lord Byron}}
{{Timelines of computing}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Lovelace, Ada King, Countess Of}}
[[Category:1815 births]]
[[Category:1852 deaths]]
[[Category:19th-century English mathematicians]]
[[Category:19th-century women scientists]]
[[Category:19th-century British women writers]]
[[Category:19th-century British writers]]
[[Category:Ada (programming language)]]
[[Category:British computer scientists]]
[[Category:British countesses]]
[[Category:Burials in Nottinghamshire]]
[[Category:Byron family]]
[[Category:Deaths from cancer in England]]
[[Category:Computer designers]]
[[Category:Daughters of barons]]
[[Category:Deaths from uterine cancer]]
[[Category:English computer programmers]]
[[Category:English computer scientists]]
[[Category:English people of Scottish descent]]
[[Category:English scientists]]
[[Category:English women poets]]
[[Category:Lord Byron]]
[[Category:British women computer scientists]]
[[Category:Women in engineering]]
[[Category:British women mathematicians]]
[[Category:Women of the Victorian era]]
[[Category:19th-century inventors]]
[[Category:Mathematicians from London]]</text>
      <sha1>8ou1624u5851m8ab0pefi3pfj3yf0ca</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
