  <page>
    <title>Anglican Communion</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>909</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940439970</id>
      <parentid>940015503</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-12T15:15:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Esprit15d</username>
        <id>379272</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>date formats per [[MOS:DATEFORMAT]] by [[WP:MOSNUMscript|script]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|churches in full communion with the Archbishop of Canterbury|the Christian tradition originating in the Church of England|Anglicanism}}
{{Redirect|The Anglican Church||Anglican Church (disambiguation)}}
{{short description|International association of churches}}
{{Use British English|date=June 2016}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2020}}
{{Infobox Christian denomination
| name = Anglican Communion
| icon                = Anglican rose.svg
| icon_width          = 25px
| image               = Canterbury-cathedral-wyrdlight.jpg
| imagewidth          = 200px
| alt                 = 
| caption = [[Canterbury Cathedral]]
| main_classification = [[Anglican]]
| orientation = 
| polity = [[Episcopal polity|Episcopal]]
| type = [[Communion (Christian)|Communion]]
| founder = [[Charles Longley]]
| founded_date = 1867
| founded_place = [[Lambeth Conference]], [[London]], [[England]]
| leader_title1 = Primate&lt;br /&gt;of All England
| leader_name1 = [[Archbishop of Canterbury]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Justin Welby]]
| leader_title2 = General Secretary
| leader_name2 = [[Josiah Idowu-Fearon]]
| headquarters = [[Canterbury Cathedral]], [[Canterbury]], [[England]]
| separated_from = 
| parent = 
| merger = 
| separations = [[Continuing Anglican movement]] (1977) &lt;br /&gt; [[Anglican realignment]] (2002)
| area = 
| congregations = 
| members = 86,650,000
| website = {{official URL}}
| footnotes = 
}}

{{AnglicanCommunion}}

The '''Anglican Communion''' is the [[List of Christian denominations by number of members|fourth largest]] Christian denomination. Founded in 1867 in London, [[England]], the communion currently has 85 million members&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.anglicancommunion.org/tour/index.cfm The Anglican Communion official website – &quot;Provincial Registry&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Worsley|2015}} within the [[Church of England]] and other national and regional churches in [[full communion]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.stfrancisooltewah.org/id4.html |title=St Francis of Assisi Episcopal Church History |date=20 July 2012 |access-date=11 August 2011 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120815131203/http://www.stfrancisooltewah.org/id4.html |archive-date=15 August 2012 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; The traditional origins of [[Anglican doctrine]]s are summarised in the [[Thirty-nine Articles]] (1571). The [[Archbishop of Canterbury]] (currently [[Justin Welby]]) in England acts as a focus of unity, recognised as ''[[primus inter pares]]'' (&quot;first among equals&quot;), but does not exercise authority in Anglican provinces outside of the Church of England.

The Anglican Communion was founded at the [[Lambeth Conference]] in 1867 in London, England, under the leadership of [[Charles Longley]], Archbishop of Canterbury. The churches of the Anglican Communion consider themselves to be part of the [[Four Marks of the Church|one, holy, catholic and apostolic church]], and to be both [[Catholic (term)|catholic]] and [[Reformation|reformed]]. Although aligned with the Church of England, the communion has a multitude of beliefs, [[liturgies]], and practices, including [[Evangelicalism|evangelical]], [[Liberal Christianity|liberal]] and [[Anglo-Catholic]]. Each retains their own legislative process and [[episcopal polity]] under the leadership of local [[Primate (bishop)|primates]]. For some adherents, [[Anglicanism]] represents a non-[[Pope|papal]] [[Catholicity|Catholicism]], for others a form of [[Protestantism]] though without guiding figure such as [[Martin Luther|Luther]], [[John Knox|Knox]], [[John Calvin|Calvin]], [[Huldrych Zwingli|Zwingli]] or [[John Wesley|Wesley]],{{sfn|Avis|1998|pp=417–419}} or for yet others a combination of the two.

Most of its 85 million members live in the [[Anglosphere]] of former British territories. Full participation in the sacramental life of each church is available to all communicant members. Due to their historical link to England (''Ecclesia Anglicana'' means &quot;English Church&quot;), some of the member churches are known as &quot;Anglican&quot;, such as the [[Anglican Church of Canada]]. Others, for example the [[Church of Ireland]], the [[Scottish Episcopal Church|Scottish]] and [[Episcopal Church (United States)|American]] Episcopal churches have official names which do not include &quot;Anglican&quot;. (Additionally, there are now breakaway churches called &quot;Anglican&quot; which are not of the Communion.)

==Ecclesiology, polity and ethos==
{{Main|Anglican doctrine}}
{{Unreferenced section|date=June 2010}}
The Anglican Communion has no official legal existence nor any governing structure which might exercise authority over the member churches. There is an Anglican Communion Office in London, under the aegis of the Archbishop of Canterbury, but it only serves in a supporting and organisational role. The communion is held together by a shared history, expressed in its [[ecclesiology]], [[polity]] and [[ethos]] and also by participation in international consultative bodies.

Three elements have been important in holding the communion together: first, the shared ecclesial structure of the component churches, manifested in an [[episcopal polity]] maintained through the [[apostolic succession]] of bishops and [[synod]]ical government; second, the principle of belief expressed in worship, investing importance in approved prayer books and their rubrics; and third, the historical documents and the writings of early Anglican [[divinity (academic discipline)|divines]] that have influenced the ethos of the communion.

Originally, the Church of England was self-contained and relied for its unity and identity on its own history, its traditional legal and episcopal structure and its status as an [[established church]] of the state. As such Anglicanism was, from the outset, a movement with an explicitly [[episcopal polity]], a characteristic which has been vital in maintaining the unity of the communion by conveying the episcopate's role in manifesting visible catholicity and ecumenism.

Early in its development, Anglicanism developed a vernacular prayer book, called the [[Book of Common Prayer]]. Unlike other traditions, Anglicanism has never been governed by a [[magisterium]] nor by appeal to one founding [[theology|theologian]], nor by an extra-credal summary of doctrine (such as the [[Westminster Confession]] of the [[Presbyterian]] churches). Instead, Anglicans have typically appealed to the Book of Common Prayer (1662) and its offshoots as a guide to Anglican theology and practise. This had the effect of inculcating the principle of ''[[lex orandi, lex credendi]]'' ([[Latin language|Latin]] loosely translated as &quot;the law of praying [is] the law of believing&quot;) as the foundation of Anglican identity and confession.

Protracted conflict through the 17th century with radical [[Protestant]]s on the one hand and Catholics who recognised the primacy of the [[Pope]] on the other, resulted in an association of churches that were both deliberately vague about doctrinal principles, yet bold in developing parameters of acceptable deviation. These parameters were most clearly articulated in the various [[rubric]]s of the successive prayer books, as well as the [[Thirty-Nine Articles]] of Religion (1563). These articles have historically shaped and continue to direct the ethos of the communion, an ethos reinforced by their interpretation and expansion by such influential early theologians such as [[Richard Hooker (theologian)|Richard Hooker]], [[Lancelot Andrewes]] and [[John Cosin]].

With the expansion of the [[British Empire]], and hence the growth of Anglicanism outside Great Britain and Ireland, the communion sought to establish new vehicles of unity. The first major expression of this were the [[Lambeth Conference]]s of the communion's bishops, first convened in 1867 by [[Charles Longley]], the Archbishop of Canterbury. From the beginning, these were not intended to displace the autonomy of the emerging provinces of the communion, but to &quot;discuss matters of practical interest, and pronounce what we deem expedient in resolutions which may serve as safe guides to future action.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Davidson, R. T. (Ed.). (1889). ''The Lambeth Conferences of 1867, 1878, and 1888: With the Official Reports and Resolutions Together with the Sermons Preached at the Conferences''. Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Chicago Lambeth Quadrilateral==
One of the enduringly influential early resolutions of the conference was the so-called [[Chicago-Lambeth Quadrilateral]] of 1888. Its intent was to provide the basis for discussions of reunion with the Roman Catholic and Orthodox churches, but it had the ancillary effect of establishing parameters of Anglican identity. It establishes four principles with these words:

: That, in the opinion of this Conference, the following Articles supply a basis on which approach may be by God's blessing made towards Home Reunion:

: (a) The Holy Scriptures of the Old and New Testaments, as &quot;containing all things necessary to salvation,&quot; and as being the rule and ultimate standard of faith.
: (b) The [[Apostles' Creed]], as the Baptismal Symbol; and the [[Nicene Creed]], as the sufficient statement of the Christian faith.
: (c) The two Sacraments ordained by Christ Himself – Baptism and the [[Eucharist|Supper of the Lord]] – ministered with unfailing use of Christ's [[Words of Institution]], and of the elements ordained by Him.
: (d) The [[Historic Episcopate]], locally adapted in the methods of its administration to the varying needs of the nations and peoples called of God into the Unity of His Church.&lt;ref&gt;''The Book of Common Prayer of the Episcopal Church'', Seabury Press, 1979, p. 877&lt;/ref&gt;

==Instruments of communion==
{{More citations needed section|date=June 2010}}

As mentioned above, the Anglican Communion has no international juridical organisation. The Archbishop of Canterbury's role is strictly symbolic and unifying and the communion's three international bodies are consultative and collaborative, their resolutions having no legal effect on the autonomous provinces of the communion. Taken together, however, the four do function as &quot;instruments of communion&quot;, since all churches of the communion participate in them. In order of antiquity, they are:

[[File:Canterburycathedralthrone.jpg|thumb|The [[Chair of St Augustine]] (the episcopal throne in [[Canterbury Cathedral]], Kent), seat of the Archbishop of Canterbury in his role as head of the Anglican Communion{{NoteTag|The [[Chair of St Augustine]] is the seat of the [[Archbishop of Canterbury]] in his role as head of the Anglican Communion. Archbishops of Canterbury are enthroned twice: firstly as diocesan ordinary (and Metropolitan and Primate of the [[Church of England]]) in the archbishop's throne, by the [[Archdeacon of Canterbury]]; and secondly as leader of the worldwide church in the Chair of St Augustine by the senior (by length of service) Archbishop of the Anglican Communion. The stone chair is therefore of symbolic significance throughout Anglicanism.}}]]

# The Archbishop of Canterbury functions as the spiritual head of the communion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title = Anglican Communion |url = http://www.archbishopofcanterbury.org/pages/anglican-communion.html |website = www.archbishopofcanterbury.org |access-date = 4 October 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The archbishop is the focus of unity, since no church claims membership in the Communion without being in communion with him. The present archbishop is [[Justin Welby]].
# The [[Lambeth Conference]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Bodies&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title = Anglican international bodies|url = http://www.archbishopofcanterbury.org/pages/instruments-of-communion.html |website = www.archbishopofcanterbury.org |access-date = 4 October 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt; (first held in 1867) is the oldest international consultation. It is a forum for bishops of the communion to reinforce unity and collegiality through manifesting the [[historical episcopate|episcopate]], to discuss matters of mutual concern, and to pass resolutions intended to act as guideposts. It is held roughly every 10 years and invitation is by the Archbishop of Canterbury.
# The [[Anglican Consultative Council]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Bodies&quot; /&gt; (first met in 1971) was created by a 1968 Lambeth Conference resolution, and meets usually at three-yearly intervals. The council consists of representative bishops, other clergy and laity chosen by the 38 provinces. The body has a permanent secretariat, the Anglican Communion Office, of which the Archbishop of Canterbury is president.
# The [[Anglican Communion Primates' Meeting|Primates' Meeting]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Bodies&quot; /&gt; (first met in 1979) is the most recent manifestation of international consultation and deliberation, having been first convened by Archbishop [[Donald Coggan]] as a forum for &quot;leisurely thought, prayer and deep consultation&quot;.{{Citation needed|date=July 2018}}

Since there is no binding authority in the Anglican Communion, these international bodies are a vehicle for consultation and persuasion. In recent times, persuasion has tipped over into debates over conformity in certain areas of doctrine, discipline, worship and ethics. The most notable example has been the objection of many provinces of the communion (particularly in Africa and Asia) to the changing acceptance of LGBTQ+ individuals in the North American churches (e.g., by [[same-sex unions|blessing same-sex unions]] and ordaining and consecrating same-sex relationships) and to the process by which changes were undertaken. (See [[Anglican realignment]])

Those who objected condemned these actions as unscriptural, unilateral, and without the agreement of the communion prior to these steps being taken. In response, the [[Episcopal Church in the United States of America|American Episcopal Church]] and the [[Anglican Church of Canada]] answered that the actions had been undertaken after lengthy scriptural and theological reflection, legally in accordance with their own [[canon law|canons and constitutions]] and after extensive consultation with the provinces of the communion.

The Primates' Meeting voted to request the two churches to withdraw their delegates from the 2005 meeting of the Anglican Consultative Council. Canada and the United States decided to attend the meeting but without exercising their right to vote. They have not been expelled or suspended, since there is no mechanism in this voluntary association to suspend or expel an independent province of the communion. Since membership is based on a province's communion with Canterbury, expulsion would require the Archbishop of Canterbury's refusal to be in communion with the affected jurisdictions. In line with the suggestion of the [[Windsor Report]], [[Rowan Williams]] (the then Archbishop of Canterbury) established a working group to examine the feasibility of an Anglican covenant which would articulate the conditions for communion in some fashion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060714012659/http://www.anglicancommunion.org/acns/articles/41/50/acns4164.cfm|archive-date=14 July 2006|url=http://www.anglicancommunion.org/acns/articles/41/50/acns4164.cfm |title=Archbishop of Canterbury: address to General Synod on the Anglican Communion|publisher=ACNS|date=7 July 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Organisation==

===Provinces===
[[File:AnglicanCommunionProvinces.png|thumb|left|upright=3.65|&lt;center&gt;A world map showing the provinces of the Anglican Communion:

{| border=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;
|-
|
{{legend|#128FE2|Autonomous churches}}
{{legend|#FFF30A|Episcopal Church of the United States}}
{{legend|#23A63B|Church in the Province of the West Indies}}
{{legend|#1BC66A|Anglican Church in Central America}}
{{legend|#A8E518|Anglican Church of the Southern Cone of America}}
{{legend|#E5001C|Anglican Church of Southern Africa}}
{{legend|#FD9BBD|Church of the Province of Central Africa}}
{{legend|#FB00FF|Church of the Province of West Africa}}
| |
{{legend|#903093|Episcopal Church in Jerusalem and the Middle East}}
{{legend|#BCAFE1|Church of the Province of the Indian Ocean}}
{{legend|#FC691F|Anglican Church in Aotearoa, New Zealand and Polynesia}}
{{legend|#FEBF10|Church of the Province of Melanesia}}
{{legend|#89D1E5|[[Diocese in Europe]] of the Church of England}}
{{legend|#A30017|Extra-provincial to the Archbishop of Canterbury}}
{{legend|#FB006D|Church of the Province of South East Asia}}
{{legend|#D9D9D9|No organised Anglican presence}}
|}

Note that the ''Church of Ireland'' serves both Northern Ireland and the Republic of Ireland and the ''Anglican Church of Korea'' serves South Korea and, theoretically, North Korea. Indian Anglicanism is divided into a Church of North India and a Church of South India. The Diocese in Europe (formally the Diocese of Gibraltar in Europe), in the Province of Canterbury, is also present in Portugal and Spain. The Episcopal Church, USA affiliated Convocation of Episcopal Churches in Europe has affiliates in France, Belgium, Austria, Switzerland, Italy and Kazakhstan.&lt;/center&gt;]]

{{clear}}

The Anglican communion consists of forty autonomous [[Ecclesiastical Province#Anglican Communion|provinces]] each with its own [[primate (bishop)|primate]] and governing structure. These provinces may take the form of national churches (such as in Canada, Uganda, or Japan) or a collection of nations (such as the [[West Indies]], [[Central Africa]], or [[Southeast Asia]]).

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%;&quot;
|-
!  Provinces
!  Territorial Jurisdiction
! data-sort-type=&quot;number&quot;|  Membership (in thousands of people)
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;New Zealand&quot; | [[Anglican Church in Aotearoa, New Zealand and Polynesia]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Aotearoa]] [[New Zealand]], [[Cook Islands]], [[Fiji]], [[Samoa]], [[Tonga]]
|469&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsNewZealand&quot; /&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Australia&quot;| [[Anglican Church of Australia]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Australia]]
|3,100&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsAustralia&quot; /&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Bangladesh&quot;| [[Church of Bangladesh]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Bangladesh]]
|16&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.oikoumene.org/en/member-churches/church-of-bangladesh|title=Church of Bangladesh — World Council of Churches|website=www.oikoumene.org|language=en|access-date=14 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Brazil&quot;| [[Anglican Episcopal Church of Brazil]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Brazil]]
|120&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsBrazil&quot; /&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Burundi&quot;| [[Province of the Anglican Church of Burundi]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Burundi]]
|800&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.oikoumene.org/en/member-churches/anglican-church-of-burundi|title=Anglican Church of Burundi — World Council of Churches|website=www.oikoumene.org|language=en|access-date=14 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Canada&quot;| [[Anglican Church of Canada]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Canada]]
|359&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsCanada&quot; /&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Central Africa&quot;| [[Church of the Province of Central Africa]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Botswana]], [[Malawi]], [[Zambia]], [[Zimbabwe]]
|900&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.oikoumene.org/en/member-churches/church-of-the-province-of-central-africa|title=Church of the Province of Central Africa — World Council of Churches|website=www.oikoumene.org|language=en|access-date=14 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Central America&quot;| [[Anglican Church in Central America]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Costa Rica]], [[El Salvador]], [[Guatemala]], [[Nicaragua]], [[Panama]]
|35

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Chile&quot;| [[Anglican Church of Chile]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Chile]]
|NA

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Congo&quot;| [[Province of the Anglican Church of the Congo]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]], [[Republic of Congo]]
|500&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.oikoumene.org/en/member-churches/church-of-christ-in-congo-anglican-community-of-congo|title=Church of Christ in Congo – Anglican Community of Congo — World Council of Churches|website=www.oikoumene.org|language=en|access-date=14 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;England&quot;| [[Church of England]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[England]], [[Guernsey]], [[Isle of Man]], [[Jersey]], [[Diocese in Europe|Europe]]
|26,000&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsEngland&quot; /&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Hong Kong&quot;| [[Hong Kong Sheng Kung Hui]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Hong Kong]], [[Macau]]
|29&lt;ref name=&quot;How Big?&quot;/&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Indian Ocean&quot;| [[Church of the Province of the Indian Ocean]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Madagascar]], [[Mauritius]], [[Seychelles]]
|505

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Ireland&quot;| [[Church of Ireland]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Republic of Ireland]], [[Northern Ireland]]
|375&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title = The Church of Ireland - About Us |url = https://www.ireland.anglican.org/about/about-us |website = ireland.anglican.org |publisher = The Church of Ireland |access-date = 7 January 2020 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Japan&quot;| [[Nippon Sei Ko Kai]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Japan]]
|32&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nskk.org/province/en_index.html |title=About Nippon Sei Ko Kai |website=nskk.org |access-date=9 January 2020 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Jerusalem&quot;| [[Episcopal Church in Jerusalem and the Middle East]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Algeria]], [[Bahrain]], [[Cyprus]], [[Djibouti]], [[Egypt]], [[Ethiopia]], [[Eritrea]], [[Iran]], [[Iraq]], [[Israel]], [[Jordan]], [[Kuwait]], [[Lebanon]], [[Libya]], [[Oman]], [[State of Palestine|Palestine]], [[Qatar]], [[Saudi Arabia]], [[Somalia]], [[Syria]], [[Tunisia]], [[United Arab Emirates]], [[Yemen]]
|40&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.oikoumene.org/en/member-churches/episcopal-church-in-jerusalem-and-the-middle-east|title=Episcopal Church in Jerusalem and the Middle East — World Council of Churches|website=www.oikoumene.org|language=en|access-date=14 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Kenya&quot;| [[Anglican Church of Kenya]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Kenya]]
|5,000&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsKenya&quot; /&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Korea&quot;| [[Anglican Church of Korea]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[South Korea]], [[North Korea]]
|65&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsKorea&quot; /&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Melanesia&quot;| [[Anglican Church of Melanesia]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[New Caledonia]], [[Solomon Islands]], [[Vanuatu]]
|200&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.oikoumene.org/en/member-churches/church-of-melanesia|title=Church of Melanesia — World Council of Churches|website=www.oikoumene.org|language=en|access-date=14 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Mexico&quot;| [[Anglican Church of Mexico]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Mexico]]
|100&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsMexico&quot; /&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Myanmar&quot;| [[Church of the Province of Myanmar]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Myanmar]]
|62&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.oikoumene.org/en/member-churches/church-of-the-province-of-myanmar|title=Church of the Province of Myanmar — World Council of Churches|website=www.oikoumene.org|language=en|access-date=14 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Nigeria&quot;| [[Church of Nigeria]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Nigeria]]
|18,000&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsNigeria&quot; /&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;North India&quot;| [[Church of North India]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Bhutan]], [[India]]
|1,500&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsNorthIndia&quot; /&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Pakistan&quot; | [[Church of Pakistan]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Pakistan]]
|500&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.oikoumene.org/en/member-churches/church-of-pakistan|title=Church of Pakistan — World Council of Churches|website=www.oikoumene.org|language=en|access-date=14 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Papua New Guinea&quot;| [[Anglican Church of Papua New Guinea]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Papua New Guinea]]
|167

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Philippines&quot;| [[Episcopal Church in the Philippines]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Philippines]]
|125&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://archived.oikoumene.org/en/member-churches/regions/asia/philippines/episcopal-church-in-the-philippines.html|title=Episcopal Church in the Philippines|website=archived.oikoumene.org|access-date=14 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Rwanda&quot;| [[Province of the Anglican Church of Rwanda]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Rwanda]]
|1,000&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.oikoumene.org/en/member-churches/province-of-the-episcopal-church-in-rwanda|title=Province of the Anglican Church in Rwanda — World Council of Churches|website=www.oikoumene.org|language=en|access-date=14 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Scotland&quot;| [[Scottish Episcopal Church]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Scotland]]
|29&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=36th Annual Report|url=https://www.scotland.anglican.org/wp-content/uploads/36th-Annual-Report-Final-2.pdf|website=The Scottish Episcopal Church|accessdate=10 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;South America&quot;| [[Anglican Church of South America]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Argentina]], [[Bolivia]], [[Paraguay]], [[Peru]], [[Uruguay]]
|23&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.oikoumene.org/en/member-churches/anglican-church-of-south-america|title=Anglican Church of South America — World Council of Churches|website=www.oikoumene.org|language=en|access-date=14 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;South East Asia&quot;| [[Church of the Province of South East Asia]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Brunei]], [[Cambodia]], [[Indonesia]], [[Laos]], [[Malaysia]], [[Nepal]], [[Singapore]], [[Thailand]], [[Vietnam]]
|98

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;South India&quot;| [[Church of South India]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[India]], [[Sri Lanka]]
|3,800&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsSouthIndia&quot; /&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;South Sudan&quot;| [[Province of the Episcopal Church of South Sudan]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[South Sudan]]
|3,500

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Southern Africa&quot;| [[Anglican Church of Southern Africa]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Angola]], [[Lesotho]], [[Mozambique]], [[Namibia]], [[Saint Helena]], [[South Africa]], [[Swaziland]]
|3,000 – 4,000&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsSouthernAfrica&quot; /&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Sudan&quot;| [[Province of the Episcopal Church of Sudan]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Sudan]]
|1,100

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Tanzania&quot;| [[Anglican Church of Tanzania]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Tanzania]]
|2,000&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsTanzania&quot; /&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Uganda&quot;| [[Church of the Province of Uganda]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Uganda]]
|8,000&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsEngland&quot;/&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;United States&quot;| [[Episcopal Church (United States)|The Episcopal Church]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[British Virgin Islands]], [[Colombia]], [[Cuba]], [[Dominican Republic]], [[Ecuador]], [[Convocation of Episcopal Churches in Europe|Europe]], [[Guam]], [[Haiti]], [[Honduras]], [[Northern Mariana Islands]], [[Puerto Rico]], [[Taiwan]], [[United States]], [[United States Virgin Islands]], [[Venezuela]]
|1,836&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsUSA&quot; /&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;Wales&quot;| [[Church in Wales]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Wales]]
| 46&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.walesonline.co.uk/news/wales-news/church-wales-spend-10m-breathe-14681635 Church in Wales will spend £10m to 'breathe new life' into its churches] 20 May 2018 WalesOnline&lt;/ref&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;West Africa&quot;| [[Church of the Province of West Africa]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Cameroon]], [[Cape Verde]], [[Gambia]], [[Ghana]], [[Guinea]], [[Liberia]], [[Senegal]], [[Sierra Leone]]
|300&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.oikoumene.org/en/member-churches/church-of-the-province-of-west-africa|title=Church of the Province of West Africa — World Council of Churches|website=www.oikoumene.org|language=en|access-date=14 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; data-sort-value=&quot;West Indies&quot;| [[Church in the Province of the West Indies]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Anguilla]], [[Antigua and Barbuda]], [[Aruba]], [[The Bahamas|Bahamas]], [[Barbados]], [[Belize]], [[Cayman Islands]], [[Dominica]], [[Grenada]], [[Guyana]], [[Jamaica]], [[Montserrat]], [[Saba]], [[Saint Barthélemy]], [[Saint Kitts and Nevis]], [[Saint Lucia]], [[Saint Martin]], [[Saint Vincent and the Grenadines]], [[Sint Eustatius]], [[Trinidad and Tobago]], [[Turks and Caicos Islands]]
|770&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.oikoumene.org/en/member-churches/church-in-the-province-of-the-west-indies|title=Church in the Province of the West Indies — World Council of Churches|website=www.oikoumene.org|language=en|access-date=14 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

===Extraprovincial churches===

In addition to the forty provinces, there are five extraprovincial churches under the [[metropolitan bishop|metropolitical]] authority of the Archbishop of Canterbury.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width: 50%;&quot; | Extra-Provincial Church
! style=&quot;width: 50%;&quot; | Territorial Jurisdiction

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Anglican Church of Bermuda]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Bermuda]]

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Church of Ceylon]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Sri Lanka]]

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Parish of the Falkland Islands]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Falkland Islands]]

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Lusitanian Catholic Apostolic Evangelical Church]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Portugal]]

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Spanish Reformed Episcopal Church]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Spain]]
|}

===Former provinces===

{{Expand list|date=January 2019}}

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%;&quot;
|-
! Province
! Territorial Jurisdiction
! Year Established
! Year Dissolved

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Chung Hua Sheng Kung Hui]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Republic of China (1912–1949)|China]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | 1912
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | 1949

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Church of Hawaii]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Hawaii]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | 1862
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | 1902

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top; | [[Church of India, Burma and Ceylon|Church of India, Pakistan, Burma and Ceylon]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Bangladesh]], [[India]], [[Myanmar]], [[Pakistan]], [[Sri Lanka]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | 1930
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | 1970

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top; | [[Protestant Episcopal Church in the Confederate States of America]]{{citation needed|date=June 2019}}
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Confederate States of America]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | 1861
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | 1865

|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[Church of Ireland#19th to 20th centuries|United Church of England and Ireland]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | [[England]], [[Wales]], [[Ireland]]
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | 1800
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | 1871

|}

===Churches in full communion===

In addition to other member churches, the churches of the Anglican Communion are in [[full communion]] with the [[Old Catholic]] churches of the [[Union of Utrecht (Old Catholic)|Union of Utrecht]] and the [[Scandinavia]]n [[Lutheran]] churches of the [[Porvoo Communion]] in Europe, the India-based [[Mar Thoma Church|Malankara Mar Thoma Syrian]] and [[Malabar Independent Syrian Church|Malabar Independent Syrian]] churches and the [[Philippine Independent Church]], also known as the Aglipayan Church.

== History ==
{{Main|History of the Anglican Communion}}

{{more citations needed section|date=November 2014}}

The Anglican Communion traces much of its growth to the older mission organisations of the Church of England such as the [[Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge]] (founded 1698), the [[Society for the Propagation of the Gospel in Foreign Parts]] (founded 1701) and the [[Church Missionary Society]] (founded 1799).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.cms-uk.org/Whoweare/AboutCMS/History/tabid/181/language/en-US/Default.aspx |title = A brief history of CMS |year = 1999 |publisher = Church Mission Society |access-date = 2 December 2012 |quote = Much of what we call the Anglican Communion today traces its origins to CMS work.}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{NoteTag|Efforts to grow and develop the church in lands outside the British Isles began with the [[Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge]] (1698) and the [[Society for the Propagation of the Gospel in Foreign Parts]] (1701) but received a significant boost from the [[Church Mission Society]] (1799).{{sfn|Melton|2005|p=28}} }}{{NoteTag|The Church Missionary Society, originally called the Society for Missions to Africa and the East, was founded in 1799... Though later in date than the S.P.C.K. and the S.P.G. it became the first effective organ of the C. of E. for missions to the heathen... Its theology has been consistently Evangelical.{{sfn|Cross|1957|p=305}} }} The [[Church of England]] (which until the 20th century included the [[Church in Wales]]) initially separated from the Roman Catholic Church in 1534 in the reign of [[Henry VIII of England|King Henry VIII]], reunited in 1555 under [[Mary I of England|Queen Mary I]] and then separated again in 1570 under [[Elizabeth I of England|Queen Elizabeth I]] (the Roman Catholic Church excommunicated Elizabeth I in 1570 in response to the [[Act of Supremacy 1559]]).

The Church of England has always thought of itself not as a new foundation but rather as a reformed continuation of the ancient &quot;English Church&quot; (''Ecclesia Anglicana'') and a reassertion of that church's rights. As such it was a distinctly national phenomenon. The [[Church of Scotland]] was formed as a separate church from the Roman Catholic Church as a result of the [[Scottish Reformation]] in 1560 and the later formation of the [[Scottish Episcopal Church]] began in 1582 in the reign of [[James VI and I|James VI of Scotland]] over disagreements about the role of bishops.

The oldest-surviving Anglican church building outside the British Isles (Britain and Ireland) is [[St. Peter's Church, St. George's|St Peter's Church]] in [[St. George's, Bermuda|St. George's]], [[Bermuda]], established in 1612 (though the actual building had to be rebuilt several times over the following century). This is also the oldest surviving non-Roman Catholic church in the [[New World]]. It remained part of the Church of England until 1978 when the [[Anglican Church of Bermuda]] separated. The Church of England was the established church not only in England, but in its trans-Oceanic colonies.

Thus the only member churches of the present Anglican Communion existing by the mid-18th century were the Church of England, its closely linked sister church the [[Church of Ireland]] (which also separated from Roman Catholicism under Henry VIII) and the Scottish Episcopal Church which for parts of the 17th and 18th centuries was partially underground (it was suspected of [[Jacobitism|Jacobite]] sympathies).

===Global spread of Anglicanism===
The enormous expansion in the 18th and 19th centuries of the [[British Empire]] brought Anglicanism along with it. At first all these colonial churches were under the jurisdiction of the [[Bishop of London]]. After the [[American Revolution]], the parishes in the newly independent country found it necessary to break formally from a church whose [[supreme governor]] was (and remains) the [[Monarchy of the United Kingdom|British monarch]]. Thus they formed their own dioceses and national church, the [[Episcopal Church in the United States of America]], in a mostly amicable separation.

At about the same time, in the colonies which remained linked to the crown, the Church of England began to appoint colonial bishops. In 1787 a bishop of [[Nova Scotia]] was appointed with a jurisdiction over all of British North America; in time several more colleagues were appointed to other cities in present-day Canada. In 1814 a bishop of [[Calcutta]] was made; in 1824 the first bishop was sent to the [[West Indies]] and in 1836 to Australia. By 1840 there were still only ten colonial bishops for the Church of England; but even this small beginning greatly facilitated the growth of Anglicanism around the world. In 1841 a &quot;Colonial Bishoprics Council&quot; was set up and soon many more dioceses were created.

In time, it became natural to group these into provinces and a [[metropolitan bishop|metropolitan]] was appointed for each province. Although it had at first been somewhat established in many colonies, in 1861 it was ruled that, except where specifically established, the Church of England had just the same legal position as any other church. Thus a colonial bishop and colonial diocese was by nature quite a different thing from their counterparts back home. In time bishops came to be appointed locally rather than from England and eventually national synods began to pass ecclesiastical legislation independent of England.

A crucial step in the development of the modern communion was the idea of the [[Lambeth Conference]]s (discussed above). These conferences demonstrated that the bishops of disparate churches could manifest the unity of the church in their episcopal collegiality despite the absence of universal legal ties. Some bishops were initially reluctant to attend, fearing that the meeting would declare itself a council with power to legislate for the church; but it agreed to pass only advisory resolutions. These Lambeth Conferences have been held roughly every 10 years since 1878 (the second such conference) and remain the most visible coming-together of the whole Communion.

The Lambeth Conference of 1998 included what has been seen by [[Philip Jenkins]] and others as a &quot;watershed in global Christianity&quot;. The 1998 Lambeth Conference considered the issue of the theology of same-sex attraction in relation to human sexuality. At this 1998 conference for the first time in centuries the Christians of developing regions, especially, Africa, Asia, and Latin America, prevailed over the bishops of more prosperous countries (many from the US, Canada, and the UK) who supported a redefinition of Anglican doctrine. Seen in this light 1998 is a date that marked the shift from a West-dominated Christianity to one wherein the growing churches of the two-thirds world are predominant,{{sfnm |1a1=Jenkins |1y=2002 |1pp=202–203 |2a1=Miller |2y=2014 |2p=68}} but the [[Homosexuality and the Anglican Communion#Gay bishop controversy|gay bishop controversy]] in subsequent years led to the reassertion of Western dominance, this time of the liberal variety.{{citation needed|date=July 2015}}

==Ecumenical relations==
{{details|topic=the ongoing dialogue between Anglicanism and the wider Church|Anglican Communion and ecumenism}}

==Historic episcopate==
The churches of the Anglican Communion have traditionally held that ordination in the [[historic episcopate]] is a core element in the validity of clerical ordinations.{{sfn|Whipple|Gilbert|Nichols|Wright|1896|p=}} The Roman Catholic Church, however, does not recognise Anglican orders (see ''[[Apostolicae curae]]'').{{sfn|O'Riordan|1907}} Some [[Eastern Orthodox]] churches have issued statements to the effect that Anglican orders could be accepted, yet have still reordained former Anglican clergy; other Eastern Orthodox churches have rejected Anglican orders altogether. Orthodox bishop [[Kallistos Ware]] explains this apparent discrepancy as follows:

{{quote|Anglican clergy who join the Orthodox Church are reordained; but [some Orthodox churches hold that] if Anglicanism and Orthodoxy were to reach full unity in the faith, perhaps such reordination might not be found necessary. It should be added, however, that a number of individual Orthodox theologians hold that under no circumstances would it be possible to recognise the validity of Anglican Orders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fatheralexander.org/booklets/english/history_timothy_ware_2.htm |title=Excerpts from the Orthodox Church by Bishop Kallistos Ware |publisher=Fatheralexander.org |date= |accessdate=20 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Controversies==
{{See also|Homosexuality and Anglicanism|Anglican realignment}}

One effect of the communion's dispersed authority has been that conflict and controversy can arise over the effect divergent practices and doctrines in one part of the Communion have on others.{{sfn|McKinnon|Trzebiatowska|Brittain|2011|pp=355–37}} Disputes that had been confined to the Church of England could be dealt with legislatively in that realm, but as the Communion spread out into new nations and disparate cultures, such controversies multiplied and intensified. These controversies have generally been of two types: liturgical and social.{{sfn|Chapman|2006|p=}}

===Anglo-Catholicism===
The first such controversy of note concerned that of the growing influence of the [[Catholic Revival]] manifested in the [[tractarian]] and so-called [[Ritualism in the Church of England|ritualism]] controversies of the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries.{{sfn|Pickering|2008|p=}} This controversy produced the [[Free Church of England]] and, in the United States and Canada, the [[Reformed Episcopal Church]].

===Social changes===
Later, rapid social change and the dissipation of British [[cultural hegemony]] over its former colonies contributed to disputes over the role of women, the parameters of marriage and divorce, and the practices of [[contraception]] and [[abortion]].{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}} In the late 1970s, the [[Continuing Anglican movement]] produced a number of new church bodies in opposition to [[Ordination of women in the Anglican Communion|women's ordination]], prayer book changes, and the new understandings concerning marriage.

===Same-sex unions and LGBT clergy===
More recently, disagreements over homosexuality have strained the unity of the communion as well as its relationships with other Christian denominations, leading to another round of withdrawals from the Anglican Communion.{{sfn|Brittain|McKinnon|2011}} Some churches were founded outside the Anglican Communion in the late 20th and early 21st centuries, largely in opposition to the ordination of openly homosexual bishops and other clergy and are usually referred to as belonging to the [[Anglican realignment]] movement, or else as &quot;orthodox&quot; Anglicans.{{sfn|Brittain|McKinnon|2011}} These disagreements were especially noted when the [[Episcopal Church (United States)|Episcopal Church (US)]] consecrated an openly gay bishop in a same-sex relationship, [[Gene Robinson]], in 2003, which led some Episcopalians to defect and found the [[Anglican Church in North America|Anglican Church in North America (ACNA)]]; then, the debate re-ignited when the [[Church of England]] agreed to allow clergy to enter into same-sex [[civil partnerships]] in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/england/beds/bucks/herts/5236132.stm|title=BBC NEWS {{!}} UK {{!}} England {{!}} Beds/Bucks/Herts {{!}} Gay cleric's 'wedding' to partner|website=news.bbc.co.uk|access-date=21 June 2017|date=August 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Church of Nigeria]] opposed the Episcopal Church's decision as well as the Church of England's approval for civil partnerships.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.christiantoday.com/article/revd.akinolas.response.to.church.of.england.civil.partnerships.stance/3642.htm|title=Revd Akinola's Response to Church of England Civil Partnerships Stance {{!}} Christian News on Christian Today|website=www.christiantoday.com|language=en|access-date=21 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;The more liberal provinces that are open to changing Church doctrine on marriage in order to allow for same-sex unions include [[Anglican Episcopal Church of Brazil|Brazil]], [[Anglican Church of Canada|Canada]], [[Anglican Church in Aotearoa, New Zealand and Polynesia|New Zealand]], [[Scottish Episcopal Church|Scotland]], [[Church of South India|South India]], [[Anglican Church of Southern Africa|South Africa]], the [[Episcopal Church (United States)|US]] and [[Church in Wales|Wales]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Church split over homosexuality would be a failure – Welby|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-35278124|publisher=BBC|accessdate=11 April 2016|work=BBC News|date=11 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Church of England does not allow same-gender marriages or blessing rites, but does permit special prayer services for same-sex couples following a civil marriage or partnership.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/religion/10640144/Church-offers-prayers-after-same-sex-weddings-but-bans-gay-priests-from-marrying.html|title=Church offers prayers after same-sex weddings – but bans gay priests from marrying|website=Telegraph.co.uk|access-date=14 June 2016|date=15 February 2014|last1=Bingham|first1=John}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Church of England also permits clergy to enter into same-sex civil partnerships.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/feb/11/anglican-synod-gay-pension-rights|title=Church of England General Synod extends pension rights for gay partners|last=Bates|first=Stephen|date=11 February 2010|website=The Guardian|access-date=16 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Church of Ireland]] has no official position on civil unions, and one senior cleric has entered into a same-sex civil partnership.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-northern-ireland-14787854|title=Minister Rev Tom Gordon civil partnership 'welcomed' – BBC News|language=en-GB|access-date=16 June 2016|date=5 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Church of Ireland recognised that it will &quot;treat civil partners the same as spouses.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.irishtimes.com/opinion/listening-process-vital-to-bring-gay-lesbian-clergy-in-from-margins-1.945021|title=Listening process vital to bring gay, lesbian clergy in from margins|work=The Irish Times|access-date=21 June 2017|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Anglican Church of Australia]] does not have an official position on homosexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/in_depth/3226753.stm|title=BBC NEWS {{!}} Special Reports {{!}} Anglican Church around the world|website=news.bbc.co.uk|language=en-GB|access-date=21 June 2017|date=15 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The conservative Anglican churches, encouraging the realignment movement, are more concentrated in the Global South. For example, the [[Anglican Church of Kenya]], the Church of Nigeria and the [[Church of Uganda]] have opposed homosexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jan/14/anglican-church-sanctions-against-liberal-us-church-same-sex-marriage|title=Anglican church avoids split over gay rights – but liberals pay price|last=Sherwood|first=Harriet|date=14 January 2016|website=The Guardian|access-date=16 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[GAFCON]], a fellowship of conservative Anglican churches, has appointed &quot;missionary bishops&quot; in response to the disagreements with the perceived liberalisation in the Anglican churches in North America and Europe.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.churchtimes.co.uk/articles/2017/28-april/news/uk/gafcon-considers-a-missionary-bishop-for-uk|title=GAFCON considers a missionary bishop for UK|website=www.churchtimes.co.uk|access-date=21 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Debates about social theology and ethics have occurred at the same time as debates on prayer book revision and the acceptable grounds for achieving full communion with non-Anglican churches.{{sfn|Ward|2006|p=}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Christianity}}
{{col div|colwidth=30em}}
* [[Affirming Catholicism]]
* [[Anglican ministry]]
* [[Anglicans Online]]
* [[Anglo-Catholicism]]
* [[Church Mission Society]]
* [[Church's Ministry Among Jewish People]]
* [[Compass rose]]
* [[Flag of the Anglican Communion]]
* [[Liberal Anglo-Catholicism]]
* [[Reform (Anglican)]]
* [[List of the largest Protestant bodies]]
{{col div end}}

== Notes ==
{{NoteFoot}}

==References==
===Citations===
{{Reflist
|refs =
&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsNigeria&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url = http://anglican-nig.org/anglican-heritage-with-emphasis-on-the-church-of-nigeria-anglican-communion/ |title=Anglican Heritage With Emphasis on The Church of Nigeria (Anglican Communion) |date=15 August 2013|website=anglican-nig.org|publisher=Church of Nigeria|access-date=3 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsEngland&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cambridge.org/catalogue/catalogue.asp?isbn=9780521008662&amp;ss=exc|title = A History of Global Anglicanism – Cambridge University Press|website=www.cambridge.org|access-date=3 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsKenya&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oikoumene.org/en/member-churches/anglican-church-of-kenya|title=Anglican Church of Kenya — World Council of Churches|website=www.oikoumene.org|language=en|access-date=3 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsSouthernAfrica&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.anglicanchurchsa.org/view.asp?pg=about|title=Anglican Church of Southern Africa (ACSA)|website=www.anglicanchurchsa.org|access-date=3 May 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160321235240/http://anglicanchurchsa.org/view.asp?pg=about|archive-date=21 March 2016|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsSouthIndia&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.csimichigan.org/ChurchofSouthIndia.html|title=CSI Christ Church – Location Map|website=www.csimichigan.org|access-date=6 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsAustralia&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tma.melbourneanglican.org.au/news/anglicans-fall-in-census-280617 |title=Number of Australian Anglicans falls by 580,000 in five years: Census 2016 |publisher=tma.melbourneanglican.org.au |date=28 June 2017 |accessdate=6 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsTanzania&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.oikoumene.org/en/member-churches/anglican-church-of-tanzania|title=Anglican Church of Tanzania — World Council of Churches|website=www.oikoumene.org|language=en|access-date=3 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsUSA&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.episcopalchurch.org/files/documents/2018_table_of_statistics.pdf |title=Table of Statistics of the Episcopal Church (2018) |publisher=episcopalchurch.org |date= |accessdate=10 September 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsCanada&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.anglican.ca/help/faq/number-of-anglicans/|title=Number of Canadian Anglicans, Parishes and Congregations – Anglican Church of Canada|website=Anglican Church of Canada|language=en-US|access-date=6 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsNorthIndia&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.oikoumene.org/en/member-churches/church-of-north-india|title=Church of North India — World Council of Churches|website=www.oikoumene.org|language=en|access-date=3 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsNewZealand&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.anglican.org.nz/About|title=About / Home – Anglican Church in Aotearoa, New Zealand and Polynesia|last=Polynesia|first=Anglican Church in Aotearoa, New Zealand and|website=www.anglican.org.nz|access-date=6 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;How Big?&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://churchsociety.org/issues_new/communion/iss_communion_howbig.asp|title=Church Society – Issues – Anglican Communion – How Big?|website=churchsociety.org|access-date=3 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsBrazil&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oikoumene.org/en/member-churches/episcopal-anglican-church-of-brazil|title=Episcopal Anglican Church of Brazil — World Council of Churches|website=www.oikoumene.org|language=en|access-date=3 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsMexico&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cronica.com.mx/notas/2009/467560.html|title=Anglicanos mexicanos rechazan unirse a la Iglesia católica|website=www.cronica.com.mx|access-date=3 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;StatsKorea&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.oikoumene.org/en/member-churches/anglican-church-of-korea|title=Anglican Church of Korea — World Council of Churches|website=www.oikoumene.org|language=en|access-date=3 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

=== Sources ===
{{refbegin|40em|indent=yes}}
: {{cite book
|last=Avis
|first=Paul
|year=1998
|chapter=What is 'Anglicanism'?
|editor1-last=Booty
|editor1-first=John E.
|editor2-last=Sykes
|editor2-first=Stephen
|editor2-link=Stephen Sykes
|editor3-last=Knight
|editor3-first=Jonathan
|title=The Study of Anglicanism
|edition=rev.
|location=London
|publisher=SPCK
|publication-date=2004
|pages=417–419
|isbn=978-1-4514-1118-8
|ref=harv
}}
: {{cite journal
|last1=Brittain
|first1=Christopher Craig
|last2=McKinnon
|first2=Andrew
|year=2011
|title=Homosexuality and the Construction of &quot;Anglican Orthodoxy&quot;: The Symbolic Politics of the Anglican Communion
|journal=Sociology of Religion
|volume=72
|issue=3
|pages=351–373
|issn=1069-4404
|doi=10.1093/socrel/srq088
|hdl=2164/3055
|ref=harv
|url=http://aura.abdn.ac.uk/bitstream/2164/3055/1/Anglican_Communion_Conflict_revision_01102010.pdf
}}
: {{cite book
|last=Chapman
|first=Mark
|year=2006
|title=Anglicanism: A Very Short Introduction
|location=Oxford
|publisher=Oxford University Press
|isbn=978-0-19-157819-9
|ref=harv
}}
: {{cite book
|year=1957
|editor-last=Cross
|editor-first=F. L.
|editor-link=Frank Leslie Cross
|title=The Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church
|location=London
|publisher=Oxford University Press
|ref=harv
}}
: {{cite book
|last=Jenkins
|first=Philip
|author-link=Philip Jenkins
|year=2002
|title=The Next Christendom: The Coming of Global Christianity
|location=Oxford
|publisher=Oxford University Press
|isbn=978-0-19-803341-7
|ref=harv
}}
: {{cite journal
|last1=McKinnon
|first1=Andrew M.
|last2=Trzebiatowska
|first2=Marta
|last3=Brittain
|first3=Christopher Craig
|year=2011
|title=Bourdieu, Capital, and Conflict in a Religious Field: The Case of the 'Homosexuality' Conflict in the Anglican Communion
|journal=Journal of Contemporary Religion
|volume=26
|issue=3
|pages=355–370
|issn=1353-7903
|doi=10.1080/13537903.2011.616033
|hdl=2164/4260
|ref=harv
|url=http://aura.abdn.ac.uk/bitstream/2164/4260/1/Religiousfields_author_non_format.pdf
}}
: {{cite book
|year=2005
|chapter=Anglican Communion/Anglican Consultative Council
|chapter-url=https://books.google.ca/books?id=bW3sXBjnokkC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA27
|editor-last=Melton
|editor-first=J. Gordon
|editor-link=J. Gordon Melton
|title=Encyclopedia of Protestantism
|series=Encyclopedias of World Religions
|location=New York
|publisher=Facts on File
|pages=27–29
|isbn=978-0-8160-6983-5
|access-date=11 October 2017
|ref=harv
}}
: {{cite journal
|last=Miller
|first=Duane Alexander
|year=2014
|title=The Bricolage of Global Anglicanism
|url=https://www.academia.edu/6408119
|journal=Anglican and Episcopal History
|volume=83
|issue=1
|pages=67–73
|issn=0896-8039
|jstor=43049823
|accessdate=2 February 2015
|ref=harv
}}
: {{cite Catholic Encyclopedia
|last=O'Riordan
|first=Michael
|authorlink=Michael O'Riordan (priest)
|wstitle=Apostolicae Curae
|volume=1
|pages=644–645
|noicon=1
|ref=harv
}}
: {{cite book
|last=Pickering
|first=W. S. F.
|year=2008
|title=Anglo-Catholicism: A Study in Religious Ambiguity
|edition=rev.
|location=Cambridge, England
|publisher=James Clarke &amp; Co.
|isbn=978-0-227-67988-3
|ref=harv
}}
: {{cite book
|last=Ward
|first=Kevin
|year=2006
|title=A History of Global Anglicanism
|location=Cambridge, England
|publisher=Cambridge University Press
|isbn=978-0-521-00866-2
|ref=harv
}}
: {{cite book
|last1=Whipple
|first1=H. B.
|author1-link=Henry Benjamin Whipple
|last2=Gilbert
|first2=M. N.
|last3=Nichols
|first3=Harry P.
|last4=Wright
|first4=John
|last5=Faude
|first5=John J.
|last6=Ten Broeck
|first6=Wm. P.
|year=1896
|title=Unity and the Lambeth Declaration: Lectures Under the Auspices of the Minnesota Church Club, 1896
|url=http://anglicanhistory.org/usa/whipple/unity1896/
|location=Milwaukee, Wisconsin
|publisher=The Young Churchman
|access-date=11 October 2017
|ref=harv
}}
: {{cite encyclopedia
|last=Worsley
|first=Howard
|year=2015
|title=Anglican Church Christian Education
|editor1-last=Kurian
|editor1-first=George Thomas
|editor2-last=Lamport
|editor2-first=Mark A.
|encyclopedia=Encyclopedia of Christian Education
|volume=1
|location=London
|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield
|page=50
|isbn=978-0-8108-8493-9
|ref=harv
}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin|35em|indent=yes}}
: Buchanan, Colin. ''Historical Dictionary of Anglicanism'' (2nd ed. 2015) [https://www.amazon.com/Historical-Dictionary-Anglicanism-Dictionaries-Philosophies/dp/1442250151 excerpt]
: {{cite book|ref=harv|last1=D'Arcy|first1=Charles Frederick |last2=Jayne|first2=Francis John |last3=Paige Cox|first3=W.L. |title=Anglican Essays: A Collective Review of the Principles and Special Opportunities of the Anglican Communion as Catholic and Reformed : with Extracts from the Pastorals of the Late Bishop Jayne &amp;#91;Francis John Jayne&amp;#93;|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Bi0LSQAACAAJ|year=1923|publisher=Macmillan}}
: {{cite book|ref=harv|editor1-first=Erwin |editor1-last=Fahlbusch |editor2-first=Geoffrey William |editor2-last=Bromiley|title=The Encyclopedia of Christianity|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=znyunAEACAAJ|volume=Vol. 1|year=1999|publisher=Eerdmans|isbn=978-90-04-11316-9|pages=57–59}}
: Hebert, A. G. ''The Form of the Church''. London: Faber and Faber, 1944.
: Wild, John. ''What is the Anglican Communion?,'' in series, ''The Advent Papers''. Cincinnati, Ohio: Forward Movement Publications, [196-]. ''Note''.: Expresses the &quot;Anglo-Catholic&quot; viewpoint.
{{refend}}

==External links==
* {{official website}}
* [http://www.anglicansonline.org/ Anglicans Online]
* [http://anglican.org/church/NoCentral.html Decentralised nature of worldwide Anglicanism]
* [http://anglicanhistory.org Project Canterbury] Anglican historical documents from around the world
* [http://www.anglicannews.org/news/1997/01/aco-the-anglican-communion.aspx Brief description and history of the Anglican Communion]

{{Anglican Communion Churches}}
{{Anglicanism (footer)}}
{{Christianity footer}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Anglican Communion| ]]
[[Category:1867 establishments in England]]
[[Category:Religious organizations established in 1867]]
[[Category:Religion in the British Empire]]</text>
      <sha1>s3ktleftpqloebaz2a96hi4osvkunpj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
