  <page>
    <title>Atom</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>902</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942994692</id>
      <parentid>942949610</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T05:03:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kurzon</username>
        <id>166614</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* First evidence-based theory */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|smallest unit of a chemical element}}
{{Other uses}}
{{pp-semi-indef|small=yes}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2013}}
{{Infobox atom}}

An '''atom''' is the smallest constituent unit of ordinary [[matter]] that constitutes a [[chemical element]]. Every [[solid]], [[liquid]], [[gas]], and [[plasma (physics)|plasma]] is composed of neutral or [[ionized]] atoms. Atoms are extremely small; typical sizes are around 100&amp;nbsp;[[picometer]]s ({{val|1e-10|u=m}}, a ten-millionth of a millimeter, or 1/254,000,000 of an inch). They are [[microscopic scale|so small]] that accurately predicting their behavior using [[classical physics]]&amp;nbsp;– as if they were [[billiard ball]]s, for example&amp;nbsp;– is not possible. This is due to [[quantum mechanics|quantum effects]]. Current atomic models now use [[#Further developments in quantum physics|quantum principles]] to better explain and predict this behavior.

Every atom is composed of a [[atomic nucleus|nucleus]] and one or more [[electron]]s bound to the nucleus. The nucleus is made of one or more [[proton]]s and a number of [[neutron]]s. Only the most common variety of [[hydrogen]] has no neutrons. Protons and neutrons are called [[nucleon]]s. More than 99.94% of an atom's [[mass]] is in the nucleus. The protons have a positive [[electric charge]] whereas the electrons have a negative electric charge. The neutrons have no electric charge. If the number of protons and electrons are equal, then the atom is electrically neutral. If an atom has more or fewer electrons than protons, then it has an overall negative or positive charge, respectively. These atoms are called [[ion|ions]].

The electrons of an atom are attracted to the protons in an atomic nucleus by the [[electromagnetic force]]. The protons and neutrons in the nucleus are attracted to each other by the [[nuclear force]]. This force is usually stronger than the electromagnetic force that repels the positively charged protons from one another. Under certain circumstances, the repelling electromagnetic force becomes stronger than the nuclear force. In this case, the nucleus shatters and [[nuclear transmutation|leaves behind different elements]]. This is a kind of [[nuclear decay]]. All electrons, nucleons, and nuclei alike are [[subatomic particle]]s. The behavior of electrons in atoms is [[wave–particle duality|closer to a wave than a particle]].

The number of protons in the nucleus, called the ''[[atomic number]]'', defines to which chemical element the atom belongs. For example, each [[copper]] atom contains 29 protons. The number of neutrons defines the [[isotope]] of the element. Atoms can attach to one or more other atoms by [[chemical bond]]s to form [[chemical compound]]s such as [[molecule]]s or [[crystal]]s. The ability of atoms to associate and dissociate is responsible for most of the physical changes observed in nature. [[Chemistry]] is the discipline that studies these changes.

==History of atomic theory==
{{Main|Atomic theory}}

===Atoms in philosophy===
{{Main|Atomism}}
The idea that matter is made up of discrete units is a very old idea, appearing in many ancient cultures such as Greece and India. The word ''atomos'', meaning &quot;uncuttable&quot;, was coined by the [[Ancient Greek philosophy|ancient Greek philosophers]] [[Leucippus]] and his pupil [[Democritus]] ({{circa}} 460 – {{circa}} 370 BC).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Pullman|first1=Bernard|title=The Atom in the History of Human Thought|date=1998|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford, England|isbn=978-0-19-515040-7|pages=31–33|url=https://books.google.com/?id=IQs5hur-BpgC&amp;pg=PA56&amp;dq=Leucippus+Democritus+atom#v=onepage&amp;q=Leucippus%20Democritus%20atom&amp;f=false|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kenny2004&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Kenny|first=Anthony|authorlink=Anthony Kenny|date=2004|title=Ancient Philosophy|url=https://books.google.com/?id=cpYUDAAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Anthony+Kenny+Ancient+Philosophy#v=onepage&amp;q=Democritus&amp;f=false|series=A New History of Western Philosophy|volume=1|location=Oxford, England|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-875273-8|pages=26–28|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GraftonMostSettis2010&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Pyle|first=Andrew|authorlink=Andrew Pyle (philosopher)|date=2010|chapter=Atoms and Atomism|title=The Classical Tradition|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=LbqF8z2bq3sC&amp;q=Epicurus#v=snippet&amp;q=Atoms&amp;f=false|editor1-last=Grafton|editor1-first=Anthony|editor1-link=Anthony Grafton|editor2-last=Most|editor2-first=Glenn W.|editor2-link=Glenn W. Most|editor3-last=Settis|editor3-first=Salvatore|publisher=The Belknap Press of Harvard University Press|location=Cambridge, Massachusetts and London|isbn=978-0-674-03572-0|pages=103–104|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CohenLefebvre2017&quot;&gt;{{cite book|editor1-last=Cohen|editor1-first=Henri|editor2-last=Lefebvre|editor2-first=Claire|title=Handbook of Categorization in Cognitive Science|date=2017|publisher=Elsevier|location=Amsterdam, The Netherlands|isbn=978-0-08-101107-2|page=427|edition=Second|url=https://books.google.com/?id=zIrCDQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA427&amp;dq=Leucippus+Democritus+atom#v=onepage&amp;q=Leucippus%20Democritus%20atom&amp;f=false|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Democritus taught that atoms were infinite in number, uncreated, and eternal, and that the qualities of an object result from the kind of atoms that compose it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kenny2004&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GraftonMostSettis2010&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CohenLefebvre2017&quot;/&gt; Democritus's atomism was refined and elaborated by the later philosopher [[Epicurus]] (341–270 BC).&lt;ref name=&quot;GraftonMostSettis2010&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CohenLefebvre2017&quot;/&gt; During the [[Early Middle Ages]], atomism was mostly forgotten in western Europe, but survived among some groups of Islamic philosophers.&lt;ref name=&quot;GraftonMostSettis2010&quot;/&gt; During the twelfth century, atomism became known again in western Europe through references to it in the newly-rediscovered writings of [[Aristotle]].&lt;ref name=&quot;GraftonMostSettis2010&quot;/&gt;

In the fourteenth century, the rediscovery of major works describing atomist teachings, including [[Lucretius]]'s ''[[De rerum natura]]'' and [[Diogenes Laërtius]]'s ''[[Lives and Opinions of Eminent Philosophers]]'', led to increased scholarly attention on the subject.&lt;ref name=&quot;GraftonMostSettis2010&quot;/&gt; Nonetheless, because atomism was associated with the philosophy of [[Epicureanism]], which contradicted orthodox Christian teachings, belief in atoms was not considered acceptable.&lt;ref name=&quot;GraftonMostSettis2010&quot;/&gt; The French Catholic priest [[Pierre Gassendi]] (1592–1655) revived Epicurean atomism with modifications, arguing that atoms were created by God and, though extremely numerous, are not infinite.&lt;ref name=&quot;GraftonMostSettis2010&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CohenLefebvre2017&quot;/&gt; Gassendi's modified theory of atoms was popularized in France by the physician [[François Bernier]] (1620–1688) and in England by the natural philosopher [[Walter Charleton]] (1619–1707).&lt;ref name=&quot;GraftonMostSettis2010&quot;/&gt; The chemist [[Robert Boyle]] (1627–1691) and the physicist [[Isaac Newton]] (1642–1727) both defended atomism and, by the end of the seventeenth century, it had become accepted by portions of the scientific community.&lt;ref name=&quot;GraftonMostSettis2010&quot;/&gt;

===First evidence-based theory===
[[File:Daltons symbols.gif|right|thumb|Various atoms and molecules as depicted in [[John Dalton]]'s ''A New System of Chemical Philosophy'' (1808).]]
In the early 1800s, [[John Dalton]] used the concept of atoms to explain why [[Chemical element|elements]] seemed to combine in ratios of small whole numbers (the [[law of multiple proportions]]). For instance, there are two types of [[tin oxide (disambiguation)|tin oxide]]: one is 88.1% tin and 11.9% oxygen, and the other is 78.7% tin and 21.3% oxygen. This means that 100g of tin will combine either with 13.5g or 27g of oxygen. 13.5 and 27 form a ratio of 1:2, a ratio of small whole numbers. Similarly, there are two common types of [[iron oxide]]: 112g of iron can combine with either 32g or 48g of oxygen, which is a ratio of 2:3. This common pattern in chemistry suggested that elements react in multiples of discrete units, which Dalton concluded were atoms. In the case of tin oxides, for every one tin atom, there are either one or two oxygen atoms ([[tin(II) oxide|SnO]] and [[tin dioxide|SnO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;]]). In the case of iron oxides, for every two iron atoms, there are either two or three oxygen atoms ([[iron(II) oxide|FeO]] and [[iron(III) oxide|Fe&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;]]).&lt;ref&gt;[[#refMelsen1952|Melsen (1952). ''From Atomos to Atom'']], p. 137&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#refMillington1906|Millington (1906). ''John Dalton'']], p. 113&lt;/ref&gt;

Dalton also believed atomic theory could explain why water absorbs different gases in different proportions. For example, he observed that water absorbs [[carbon dioxide]] far better than it absorbs [[nitrogen]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Dalton_1803_paper&quot;&gt;Dalton, John. &quot;[http://web.lemoyne.edu/~GIUNTA/dalton52.html On the Absorption of Gases by Water and Other Liquids] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110611205519/http://web.lemoyne.edu/~giunta/dalton52.html |date=11 June 2011 }}&quot;, in ''Memoirs of the Literary and Philosophical Society of Manchester''. 1803. Retrieved on August 29, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Dalton hypothesized this was due to the differences in the mass and configuation of the particles. Indeed, carbon dioxide molecules (CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) are heavier and larger than nitrogen molecules (N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;).

===Brownian motion===
In 1827, [[Botany|botanist]] [[Robert Brown (Scottish botanist from Montrose)|Robert Brown]] used a microscope to look at dust grains floating in water and discovered that they moved about erratically, a phenomenon that became known as &quot;[[Brownian motion]]&quot;. This was thought to be caused by water molecules knocking the grains about. In 1905, [[Albert Einstein]] proved the reality of these molecules and their motions by producing the first [[statistical physics]] analysis of [[Brownian motion]].&lt;ref name=adp322_8_549/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|last=Mazo|first=Robert M.|year=2002
|title=Brownian Motion: Fluctuations, Dynamics, and Applications
|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-851567-8
|oclc=48753074|pages=1–7}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=lee_hoon1995/&gt; French physicist [[Jean Perrin]] used Einstein's work to experimentally determine the mass and dimensions of atoms, thereby conclusively verifying [[Dalton's atomic theory]].&lt;ref name=e31_2_50/&gt;

===Discovery of the electron===
[[File:Geiger-Marsden experiment expectation and result.svg|thumb|right|The '''[[Geiger–Marsden experiment]]'''&lt;br /&gt; ''Left:'' Expected results: alpha particles passing through the plum pudding model of the atom with negligible deflection.&lt;br /&gt; ''Right:'' Observed results: a small portion of the particles were deflected by the concentrated positive charge of the nucleus.]]
The physicist [[J.J. Thomson]] measured the mass of [[cathode ray]]s, showing they were made of particles, but were around 1800 times lighter than the lightest atom, [[hydrogen]]. Therefore, they were not atoms, but a new particle, the first ''[[subatomic particle|subatomic]]'' particle to be discovered, which he originally called &quot;''[[wikt:corpuscle|corpuscle]]''&quot; but was later named ''electron'', after particles postulated by [[George Johnstone Stoney]] in 1874. He also showed they were identical to particles given off by [[Photoelectric effect|photoelectric]] and radioactive materials.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomson&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Thomson|first=J.J.|title=On bodies smaller than atoms|journal=The Popular Science Monthly|volume=|issue= |pages=323–335|date=August 1901|url=https://books.google.com/?id=3CMDAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA323|doi= |id= |accessdate=2009-06-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was quickly recognized that they are the particles that carry [[electric current]]s in metal wires, and carry the negative electric charge within atoms. Thomson was given the 1906 [[Nobel Prize in Physics]] for this work. Thus he overturned the belief that atoms are the indivisible, ultimate particles of matter.&lt;ref name=nobel1096/&gt; Thomson also incorrectly postulated that the low mass, negatively charged electrons were distributed throughout the atom in a uniform sea of positive charge. This became known as the [[plum pudding model]].

===Discovery of the nucleus===
{{main|Geiger-Marsden experiment}}
In 1909, [[Hans Geiger]] and [[Ernest Marsden]], under the direction of [[Ernest Rutherford]], bombarded a metal foil with [[alpha particle]]s to observe how they scattered. They expected all the alpha particles to pass straight through with little deflection, because Thomson's model said that the charges in the atom are so diffuse that their electric fields could not affect the alpha particles much. However, Geiger and Marsden spotted alpha particles being deflected by angles greater than 90°, which was supposed to be impossible according to Thomson's model. To explain this, Rutherford proposed that the positive charge of the atom is concentrated in a tiny nucleus at the center of the atom.&lt;ref name=pm21_669/&gt;

===Discovery of isotopes===
While experimenting with the products of [[radioactive decay]], in 1913 [[radiochemistry|radiochemist]] [[Frederick Soddy]] discovered that there appeared to be more than one type of atom at each position on the [[periodic table]].&lt;ref name=npc1921/&gt; The term [[isotope]] was coined by [[Margaret Todd (doctor)|Margaret Todd]] as a suitable name for different atoms that belong to the same element. J.J. Thomson created a technique for [[isotope separation]] through his work on [[ionized gas]]es, which subsequently led to the discovery of [[stable isotope]]s.&lt;ref name=prsA_89_1_1913/&gt;

===Bohr model===
[[File:Bohr atom animation 2.gif|right|thumb|The Bohr model of the atom, with an electron making instantaneous &quot;quantum leaps&quot; from one orbit to another. This model is obsolete.]]
{{main|Bohr model}}

In 1913 the physicist [[Niels Bohr]] proposed a model in which the electrons of an atom were assumed to orbit the nucleus but could only do so in a finite set of orbits, and could jump between these orbits only in discrete changes of energy corresponding to absorption or radiation of a photon.&lt;ref name=stern20050516/&gt; This quantization was used to explain why the electrons orbits are stable (given that normally, charges in acceleration, including circular motion, lose kinetic energy which is emitted as electromagnetic radiation, see ''[[synchrotron radiation]]'') and why elements absorb and emit electromagnetic radiation in discrete spectra.&lt;ref name=bohr19221211/&gt;

Later in the same year [[Henry Moseley]] provided additional experimental evidence in favor of [[Bohr model|Niels Bohr's theory]]. These results refined [[Ernest Rutherford]]'s and [[Antonius Van den Broek]]'s model, which proposed that the atom contains in its [[atomic nucleus|nucleus]] a number of positive [[nuclear charge]]s that is equal to its (atomic) number in the periodic table. Until these experiments, [[atomic number]] was not known to be a physical and experimental quantity. That it is equal to the atomic nuclear charge remains the accepted atomic model today.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pais&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|last=Pais|first=Abraham|year=1986|location=New York|title=Inward Bound: Of Matter and Forces in the Physical World|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-851971-3|pages=[https://archive.org/details/inwardboundofmat00pais_0/page/228 228–230]|url=https://archive.org/details/inwardboundofmat00pais_0/page/228}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Chemical bonding explained===
[[Chemical bond]]s between atoms were now explained, by [[Gilbert Newton Lewis]] in 1916, as the interactions between their constituent electrons.&lt;ref name=jacs38_4_762/&gt; As the [[Chemical property|chemical properties]] of the elements were known to largely repeat themselves according to the [[periodic law]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Scerri|first=Eric R.|title=The periodic table: its story and its significance|publisher=Oxford University Press US|year=2007|isbn=978-0-19-530573-9|pages=[https://archive.org/details/periodictableits0000scer/page/205 205–226]|url=https://archive.org/details/periodictableits0000scer/page/205}}&lt;/ref&gt; in 1919 the American chemist [[Irving Langmuir]] suggested that this could be explained if the electrons in an atom were connected or clustered in some manner. Groups of electrons were thought to occupy a set of [[electron shell]]s about the nucleus.&lt;ref name=jacs41_6_868/&gt;

===Further developments in quantum physics===
The [[Stern–Gerlach experiment]] of 1922 provided further evidence of the quantum nature of atomic properties. When a beam of silver atoms was passed through a specially shaped magnetic field, the beam was split in a way correlated with the direction of an atom's angular momentum, or [[spin (physics)|spin]]. As this spin direction is initially random, the beam would be expected to deflect in a random direction. Instead, the beam was split into two directional components, corresponding to the atomic [[spin (physics)|spin]] being oriented up or down with respect to the magnetic field.&lt;ref name=fop17_6_575/&gt;

In 1925 [[Werner Heisenberg]] published the first consistent mathematical formulation of quantum mechanics ([[Matrix Mechanics]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Pais&quot;/&gt; One year earlier, in 1924, [[Louis de Broglie]] had proposed that all particles behave to an extent like waves and, in 1926, [[Erwin Schrödinger]] used this idea to develop a mathematical model of the atom (Wave Mechanics) that described the electrons as three-dimensional [[waveform]]s rather than point particles.

A consequence of using waveforms to describe particles is that it is mathematically impossible to obtain precise values for both the [[Point (geometry)|position]] and [[momentum]] of a particle at a given point in time; this became known as the [[uncertainty principle]], formulated by [[Werner Heisenberg]] in 1927.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pais&quot;/&gt; In this concept, for a given accuracy in measuring a position one could only obtain a range of probable values for momentum, and vice versa.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Chad Orzel|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TQKELOE9eY4|title=What is the Heisenberg Uncertainty Principle?|website=TED-Ed|date=16 September 2014|via=YouTube|access-date=26 October 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150913185956/https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TQKELOE9eY4|archive-date=13 September 2015|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;
This model was able to explain observations of atomic behavior that previous models could not, such as certain structural and [[Spectral line|spectral]] patterns of atoms larger than hydrogen. Thus, the planetary model of the atom was discarded in favor of one that described [[atomic orbital]] zones around the nucleus where a given electron is most likely to be observed.&lt;ref name=brown2007/&gt;&lt;ref name=harrison2000/&gt;

===Discovery of the neutron===
The development of the [[mass spectrometry|mass spectrometer]] allowed the mass of atoms to be measured with increased accuracy. The device uses a magnet to bend the trajectory of a beam of ions, and the amount of deflection is determined by the ratio of an atom's mass to its charge. The chemist [[Francis William Aston]] used this instrument to show that isotopes had different masses. The [[atomic mass]] of these isotopes varied by integer amounts, called the [[whole number rule]].&lt;ref name=pm39_6_449/&gt; The explanation for these different isotopes awaited the discovery of the [[neutron]], an uncharged particle with a mass similar to the [[proton]], by the physicist [[James Chadwick]] in 1932. Isotopes were then explained as elements with the same number of protons, but different numbers of neutrons within the nucleus.&lt;ref name=chadwick1935/&gt;

===Fission, high-energy physics and condensed matter===
In 1938, the German chemist [[Otto Hahn]], a student of Rutherford, directed neutrons onto uranium atoms expecting to get [[transuranium element]]s. Instead, his chemical experiments showed [[barium]] as a product.&lt;ref name=Bowden/&gt;&lt;ref name=CHF/&gt; A year later, [[Lise Meitner]] and her nephew [[Otto Frisch]] verified that Hahn's result were the first experimental ''nuclear fission''.&lt;ref name=nature143_3615_239/&gt;&lt;ref name=schroeder/&gt; In 1944, Hahn received the [[Nobel prize]] in chemistry. Despite Hahn's efforts, the contributions of Meitner and Frisch were not recognized.&lt;ref name=pt50_9_26/&gt;

In the 1950s, the development of improved [[particle accelerator]]s and [[particle detector]]s allowed scientists to study the impacts of atoms moving at high energies.&lt;ref name=kullander2001/&gt; Neutrons and protons were found to be [[hadron]]s, or composites of smaller particles called [[quark]]s. The [[standard model of particle physics]] was developed that so far has successfully explained the properties of the nucleus in terms of these sub-atomic particles and the forces that govern their interactions.&lt;ref name=npp1990/&gt;

===Video of atoms bonding===
In January 2020, for the first time, scientists reported a video of atoms bonding and separating.&lt;ref name=&quot;SA-20200117&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Cao, Kecheng |display-authors=et al. |title=Imaging an unsupported metal–metal bond in dirhenium molecules at the atomic scale |url=https://advances.sciencemag.org/content/6/3/eaay5849 |date=17 January 2020 |journal=[[Science Advances]] |volume=6 |number=3 |doi=10.1126/sciadv.aay5849 |accessdate=23 January 2020 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;YN-20200122&quot;&gt;{{cite news |author=Staff |title=Scientists Capture First-Ever Video of Atoms Bonding and Separating |url=https://www.yahoo.com/news/scientists-capture-first-ever-video-104058305.html |date=22 January 2020 |work=[[Yahoo News]] |accessdate=23 January 2020 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Structure==
===Subatomic particles===
{{Main|Subatomic particle}}
Though the word ''atom'' originally denoted a particle that cannot be cut into smaller particles, in modern scientific usage the atom is composed of various [[subatomic particle]]s. The constituent particles of an atom are the [[electron]], the [[proton]] and the [[neutron]]; all three are [[fermion]]s. However, the [[hydrogen|hydrogen-1]] atom has no neutrons and the [[hydron (chemistry)|hydron ion]] has no electrons.

The electron is by far the least massive of these particles at {{val|9.11|e=-31|u=kg}}, with a negative [[Electric charge|electrical charge]] and a size that is too small to be measured using available techniques.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Demtröder|first=Wolfgang|year=2002|title=Atoms, Molecules and Photons: An Introduction to Atomic- Molecular- and Quantum Physics|publisher=Springer|edition=1st|isbn=978-3-540-20631-6|oclc=181435713|pages=39–42}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was the lightest particle with a positive rest mass measured, until the discovery of [[neutrino]] mass. Under ordinary conditions, electrons are bound to the positively charged nucleus by the attraction created from opposite electric charges. If an atom has more or fewer electrons than its atomic number, then it becomes respectively negatively or positively charged as a whole; a charged atom is called an [[ion]]. Electrons have been known since the late 19th century, mostly thanks to [[J.J. Thomson]]; see [[history of subatomic physics]] for details.

Protons have a positive charge and a mass 1,836 times that of the electron, at {{val|1.6726|e=-27|u=kg}}. The number of protons in an atom is called its [[atomic number]]. [[Ernest Rutherford]] (1919) observed that nitrogen under alpha-particle bombardment ejects what appeared to be hydrogen nuclei. By 1920 he had accepted that the hydrogen nucleus is a distinct particle within the atom and named it [[proton]].

Neutrons have no electrical charge and have a free mass of 1,839 times the mass of the electron, or {{val|1.6749|e=-27|u=kg}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Woan|first=Graham|year=2000|title=The Cambridge Handbook of Physics|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-57507-2|oclc=224032426|page=[https://archive.org/details/cambridgehandboo0000woan/page/8 8]|url=https://archive.org/details/cambridgehandboo0000woan/page/8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;2014 CODATA&quot;&gt;Mohr, P.J.; Taylor, B.N. and Newell, D.B. (2014), [http://physics.nist.gov/constants &quot;The 2014 CODATA Recommended Values of the Fundamental Physical Constants&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://www.webcitation.org/65cjrPoqR?url=http://physics.nist.gov/cuu/Constants/index.html |date=21 February 2012 }} (Web Version 7.0). The database was developed by J. Baker, M. Douma, and S. Kotochigova. (2014). National Institute of Standards and Technology, Gaithersburg, Maryland 20899.&lt;/ref&gt; Neutrons are the heaviest of the three constituent particles, but their mass can be reduced by the [[nuclear binding energy]]. Neutrons and protons (collectively known as [[nucleon]]s) have comparable dimensions—on the order of {{val|2.5|e=-15|u=m}}—although the 'surface' of these particles is not sharply defined.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=MacGregor|first=Malcolm H.|year=1992|title=The Enigmatic Electron|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-521833-6|oclc=223372888|pages=[https://archive.org/details/astronomyencyclo0000unse/page/33 33–37]|url=https://archive.org/details/astronomyencyclo0000unse/page/33}}&lt;/ref&gt; The neutron was discovered in 1932 by the English physicist [[James Chadwick]].

In the [[Standard Model]] of physics, electrons are truly elementary particles with no internal structure. However, both protons and neutrons are composite particles composed of [[elementary particle]]s called [[quark]]s. There are two types of quarks in atoms, each having a fractional electric charge. Protons are composed of two [[up quark]]s (each with charge +{{sfrac|2|3}}) and one [[down quark]] (with a charge of −{{sfrac|1|3}}). Neutrons consist of one up quark and two down quarks. This distinction accounts for the difference in mass and charge between the two particles.&lt;ref name=pdg2002/&gt;&lt;ref name=schombert2006/&gt;

The quarks are held together by the [[strong interaction]] (or strong force), which is mediated by [[gluon]]s. The protons and neutrons, in turn, are held to each other in the nucleus by the [[nuclear force]], which is a residuum of the strong force that has somewhat different range-properties (see the article on the nuclear force for more). The gluon is a member of the family of [[gauge boson]]s, which are elementary particles that mediate physical forces.&lt;ref name=pdg2002/&gt;&lt;ref name=schombert2006/&gt;

===Nucleus===
{{Main|Atomic nucleus}}
[[File:Binding energy curve - common isotopes.svg|thumb|The [[binding energy]] needed for a nucleon to escape the nucleus, for various isotopes]]&lt;!-- A brief explanation is provided here because 'binding energy' is not explained until the end of the section. --&gt;

All the bound protons and neutrons in an atom make up a tiny [[atomic nucleus]], and are collectively called [[nucleon]]s. The radius of a nucleus is approximately equal to 1.07&amp;nbsp;{{radic|''A''|3}}&amp;nbsp;[[femtometre|fm]], where ''A'' is the total number of nucleons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Jevremovic|first=Tatjana|year=2005|title=Nuclear Principles in Engineering|publisher=Springer|isbn=978-0-387-23284-3|oclc=228384008|page=63}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is much smaller than the radius of the atom, which is on the order of 10&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;nbsp;fm. The nucleons are bound together by a short-ranged attractive potential called the [[residual strong force]]. At distances smaller than 2.5 fm this force is much more powerful than the [[electrostatic force]] that causes positively charged protons to repel each other.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Pfeffer|first=Jeremy I.|last2=Nir|first2=Shlomo|year=2000|title=Modern Physics: An Introductory Text|publisher=Imperial College Press|isbn=978-1-86094-250-1|oclc=45900880|pages=330–336}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Atoms of the same [[chemical element|element]] have the same number of protons, called the [[atomic number]]. Within a single element, the number of neutrons may vary, determining the [[isotope]] of that element. The total number of protons and neutrons determine the [[nuclide]]. The number of neutrons relative to the protons determines the stability of the nucleus, with certain isotopes undergoing [[radioactive decay]].&lt;ref name=wenner2007/&gt;

The proton, the electron, and the neutron are classified as [[fermion]]s. Fermions obey the [[Pauli exclusion principle]] which prohibits ''[[identical particles|identical]]'' fermions, such as multiple protons, from occupying the same quantum state at the same time. Thus, every proton in the nucleus must occupy a quantum state different from all other protons, and the same applies to all neutrons of the nucleus and to all electrons of the electron cloud.&lt;ref name=&quot;raymond&quot;/&gt;

A nucleus that has a different number of protons than neutrons can potentially drop to a lower energy state through a radioactive decay that causes the number of protons and neutrons to more closely match. As a result, atoms with matching numbers of protons and neutrons are more stable against decay. However, with increasing atomic number, the mutual repulsion of the protons requires an increasing proportion of neutrons to maintain the stability of the nucleus, which slightly modifies this trend of equal numbers of protons to neutrons.&lt;ref name=&quot;raymond&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Wpdms physics proton proton chain 1.svg|right|thumb|upright|Illustration of a nuclear fusion process that forms a deuterium nucleus, consisting of a proton and a neutron, from two protons. A [[positron]] (e&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;)—an [[antimatter]] electron—is emitted along with an electron [[neutrino]].]]

The number of protons and neutrons in the atomic nucleus can be modified, although this can require very high energies because of the strong force. [[Nuclear fusion]] occurs when multiple atomic particles join to form a heavier nucleus, such as through the energetic collision of two nuclei. For example, at the core of the Sun protons require energies of 3–10 keV to overcome their mutual repulsion—the [[coulomb barrier]]—and fuse together into a single nucleus.&lt;ref name=mihos2002/&gt; [[Nuclear fission]] is the opposite process, causing a nucleus to split into two smaller nuclei—usually through radioactive decay. The nucleus can also be modified through bombardment by high energy subatomic particles or photons. If this modifies the number of protons in a nucleus, the atom changes to a different chemical element.&lt;ref name=lbnl20070330/&gt;&lt;ref name=makhijani_saleska2001/&gt;

If the mass of the nucleus following a fusion reaction is less than the sum of the masses of the separate particles, then the difference between these two values can be emitted as a type of usable energy (such as a [[gamma ray]], or the kinetic energy of a [[beta particle]]), as described by [[Albert Einstein]]'s [[mass–energy equivalence]] formula, &lt;math&gt;E=mc^2&lt;/math&gt;, where &lt;math&gt;m&lt;/math&gt; is the mass loss and &lt;math&gt;c&lt;/math&gt; is the [[speed of light]]. This deficit is part of the [[binding energy]] of the new nucleus, and it is the non-recoverable loss of the energy that causes the fused particles to remain together in a state that requires this energy to separate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Shultis|first1=J. Kenneth|last2=Faw|first2=Richard E.|title=Fundamentals of Nuclear Science and Engineering|year=2002|publisher=CRC Press|isbn=978-0-8247-0834-4|oclc=123346507|pages=10–17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The fusion of two nuclei that create larger nuclei with lower atomic numbers than [[iron]] and [[nickel]]—a total nucleon number of about 60—is usually an [[exothermic reaction|exothermic process]] that releases more energy than is required to bring them together.&lt;ref name=ajp63_7_653/&gt; It is this energy-releasing process that makes nuclear fusion in [[star]]s a self-sustaining reaction. For heavier nuclei, the binding energy per [[nucleon]] in the nucleus begins to decrease. That means fusion processes producing nuclei that have atomic numbers higher than about 26, and [[atomic mass]]es higher than about 60, is an [[endothermic reaction|endothermic process]]. These more massive nuclei can not undergo an energy-producing fusion reaction that can sustain the [[hydrostatic equilibrium]] of a star.&lt;ref name=&quot;raymond&quot;/&gt;

===Electron cloud===
{{Main|Atomic orbital|Electron configuration}}

[[File:Potential energy well.svg|right|thumb|A potential well, showing, according to [[classical mechanics]], the minimum energy ''V''(''x'') needed to reach each position ''x''. Classically, a particle with energy ''E'' is constrained to a range of positions between ''x''&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; and ''x''&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;.]]
The electrons in an atom are attracted to the protons in the nucleus by the [[electromagnetic force]]. This force binds the electrons inside an [[electrostatic]] [[potential well]] surrounding the smaller nucleus, which means that an external source of energy is needed for the electron to escape. The closer an electron is to the nucleus, the greater the attractive force. Hence electrons bound near the center of the potential well require more energy to escape than those at greater separations.

Electrons, like other particles, have properties of both a [[Wave–particle duality|particle and a wave]]. The electron cloud is a region inside the potential well where each electron forms a type of three-dimensional [[standing wave]]—a wave form that does not move relative to the nucleus. This behavior is defined by an [[atomic orbital]], a mathematical function that characterises the probability that an electron appears to be at a particular location when its position is measured.&lt;ref name=science157_3784_13/&gt; Only a discrete (or [[wikt:quantize|quantized]]) set of these orbitals exist around the nucleus, as other possible wave patterns rapidly decay into a more stable form.&lt;ref name=Brucat2008/&gt; Orbitals can have one or more ring or node structures, and differ from each other in size, shape and orientation.&lt;ref name=manthey2001/&gt;

[[File:Oganesson Subshells and Orbitals.tif|right|thumb| [[Oganesson]]. An illustration of all the Subshells/orbitals of the [[Oganesson]] atom. Blue is for the S-subshell, pink is for the P-subshell, red is for the D-subshell, and green is for the F-subshell.]]
[[File:S-p-Orbitals.svg|left|thumb|Wave functions of the first five atomic orbitals. The three 2p orbitals each display a single angular [[Node (physics)|node]] that has an orientation and a minimum at the center.]]
[[File:Atomic orbitals and periodic table construction.ogv|left|thumb|How atoms are constructed from electron orbitals and link to the periodic table.]]

Each atomic orbital corresponds to a particular [[energy level]] of the electron. The electron can change its state to a higher energy level by absorbing a [[photon]] with sufficient energy to boost it into the new quantum state. Likewise, through [[spontaneous emission]], an electron in a higher energy state can drop to a lower energy state while radiating the excess energy as a photon. These characteristic energy values, defined by the differences in the energies of the quantum states, are responsible for [[atomic spectral line]]s.&lt;ref name=Brucat2008/&gt;

The amount of energy needed to remove or add an electron—the [[electron binding energy]]—is far less than the [[binding energy|binding energy of nucleons]]. For example, it requires only 13.6&amp;nbsp;eV to strip a [[Stationary state|ground-state]] electron from a hydrogen atom,&lt;ref name=herter_8/&gt; compared to 2.23&amp;nbsp;''million'' eV for splitting a [[deuterium]] nucleus.&lt;ref name=pr79_2_282/&gt; Atoms are [[electric charge|electrically]] neutral if they have an equal number of protons and electrons. Atoms that have either a deficit or a surplus of electrons are called [[ion]]s. Electrons that are farthest from the nucleus may be transferred to other nearby atoms or shared between atoms. By this mechanism, atoms are able to [[chemical bond|bond]] into [[molecule]]s and other types of [[chemical compound]]s like [[Ionic crystal|ionic]] and [[Covalent bond|covalent]] network [[Crystallization|crystals]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Smirnov|first=Boris M.|year=2003|title=Physics of Atoms and Ions|publisher=Springer|isbn=978-0-387-95550-6|pages=249–272}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Properties==
===Nuclear properties===
{{Main|Isotope|Stable isotope|List of nuclides|List of elements by stability of isotopes}}

By definition, any two atoms with an identical number of ''protons'' in their nuclei belong to the same [[chemical element]]. Atoms with equal numbers of protons but a different number of ''neutrons'' are different isotopes of the same element. For example, all hydrogen atoms admit exactly one proton, but isotopes exist with no neutrons ([[hydrogen-1]], by far the most common form,&lt;ref name=matis2000/&gt; also called protium), one neutron ([[deuterium]]), two neutrons ([[tritium]]) and [[isotopes of hydrogen|more than two neutrons]]. The known elements form a set of atomic numbers, from the single proton element [[hydrogen]] up to the 118-proton element [[oganesson]].&lt;ref name=weiss20061017/&gt; All known isotopes of elements with atomic numbers greater than 82 are radioactive, although the radioactivity of element 83 ([[bismuth]]) is so slight as to be practically negligible.&lt;ref name=s131&gt;{{cite book|last=Sills|first=Alan D.|year=2003|title=Earth Science the Easy Way|publisher=Barron's Educational Series|isbn=978-0-7641-2146-3|oclc=51543743|pages=[https://archive.org/details/earthscienceeasy00alan/page/131 131–134]|url=https://archive.org/details/earthscienceeasy00alan/page/131}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=dume20030423/&gt;

About 339 nuclides occur naturally on [[Earth]],&lt;ref name=lidsay20000730/&gt; of which 254 (about 75%) have not been observed to decay, and are referred to as &quot;[[stable isotope]]s&quot;. However, only 90 of these nuclides are stable to all decay, even [[list of nuclides|in theory]]. Another 164 (bringing the total to 254) have not been observed to decay, even though in theory it is energetically possible. These are also formally classified as &quot;stable&quot;. An additional 34 radioactive nuclides have half-lives longer than 80 million years, and are long-lived enough to be present from the birth of the [[solar system]]. This collection of 288 nuclides are known as [[primordial nuclide]]s. Finally, an additional 51 short-lived nuclides are known to occur naturally, as daughter products of primordial nuclide decay (such as [[radium]] from [[uranium]]), or else as products of natural energetic processes on Earth, such as cosmic ray bombardment (for example, carbon-14).&lt;ref name=tuli2005/&gt;&lt;ref group=note&gt;For more recent updates see [http://www.nndc.bnl.gov/chart Interactive Chart of Nuclides (Brookhaven National Laboratory)] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090825001001/http://www.nndc.bnl.gov/chart/ |date=25 August 2009 }}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- See article [[list of nuclides]]. The numbers are derived by [[WP:CALC]] (counting the table), which is not [[WP:OR]]--&gt;

For 80 of the chemical elements, at least one [[stable isotope]] exists. As a rule, there is only a handful of stable isotopes for each of these elements, the average being 3.2 stable isotopes per element. Twenty-six elements have only a single stable isotope, while the largest number of stable isotopes observed for any element is ten, for the element [[tin]]. Elements [[technetium|43]], [[promethium|61]], and all elements numbered [[bismuth|83]] or higher have no stable isotopes.&lt;ref name=CRC&gt;CRC Handbook (2002).&lt;/ref&gt;{{Page needed|date=April 2011}}

Stability of isotopes is affected by the ratio of protons to neutrons, and also by the presence of certain &quot;magic numbers&quot; of neutrons or protons that represent closed and filled quantum shells. These quantum shells correspond to a set of energy levels within the [[Nuclear shell model|shell model]] of the nucleus; filled shells, such as the filled shell of 50 protons for tin, confers unusual stability on the nuclide. Of the 254 known stable nuclides, only four have both an odd number of protons ''and'' odd number of neutrons: [[hydrogen-2]] ([[deuterium]]), [[lithium-6]], [[boron-10]] and [[nitrogen-14]]. Also, only four naturally occurring, radioactive odd–odd nuclides have a half-life over a billion years: [[potassium-40]], [[vanadium-50]], [[lanthanum-138]] and [[tantalum-180m]]. Most odd–odd nuclei are highly unstable with respect to [[beta decay]], because the decay products are even–even, and are therefore more strongly bound, due to [[Semi-empirical mass formula#Pairing term|nuclear pairing effects]].&lt;ref name=CRC/&gt;{{Page needed|date=April 2011}}

===Mass===
{{Main|Atomic mass|mass number}}

The large majority of an atom's mass comes from the protons and neutrons that make it up. The total number of these particles (called &quot;nucleons&quot;) in a given atom is called the [[mass number]]. It is a positive integer and dimensionless (instead of having dimension of mass), because it expresses a count. An example of use of a mass number is &quot;carbon-12,&quot; which has 12 nucleons (six protons and six neutrons).

The actual [[Invariant mass|mass of an atom at rest]] is often expressed in [[dalton (unit)|dalton]]s (Da), also called the unified atomic mass unit (u). This unit is defined as a twelfth of the mass of a free neutral atom of [[carbon-12]], which is approximately {{val|1.66|e=-27|u=kg}}.&lt;ref name=iupac/&gt; [[hydrogen atom|Hydrogen-1]] (the lightest isotope of hydrogen which is also the nuclide with the lowest mass) has an atomic weight of 1.007825&amp;nbsp;Da.&lt;ref name=chieh2001/&gt; The value of this number is called the [[atomic mass]]. A given atom has an atomic mass approximately equal (within 1%) to its mass number times the atomic mass unit (for example the mass of a nitrogen-14 is roughly 14&amp;nbsp;Da). However, this number will not be exactly an integer except in the case of carbon-12 (see below).&lt;ref name=nist_wc/&gt; The heaviest [[stable atom]] is lead-208,&lt;ref name=s131/&gt; with a mass of {{val|207.9766521|u=Da}}.&lt;ref name=audi2003/&gt;

As even the most massive atoms are far too light to work with directly, chemists instead use the unit of [[Mole (unit)|moles]]. One mole of atoms of any element always has the same number of atoms (about [[Avogadro constant|{{val|6.022|e=23}}]]). This number was chosen so that if an element has an atomic mass of 1&amp;nbsp;u, a mole of atoms of that element has a mass close to one gram. Because of the definition of the [[Atomic mass unit|unified atomic mass unit]], each carbon-12 atom has an atomic mass of exactly 12&amp;nbsp;Da, and so a mole of carbon-12 atoms weighs exactly 0.012&amp;nbsp;kg.&lt;ref name=iupac&gt;{{cite book
|last=Mills
|first=Ian
|author2=Cvitaš, Tomislav
|author3=Homann, Klaus
|author4=Kallay, Nikola
|author5=Kuchitsu, Kozo
|title=Quantities, Units and Symbols in Physical Chemistry
|publisher=[[International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry]], Commission on Physiochemical Symbols Terminology and Units, Blackwell Scientific Publications
|location=Oxford
|edition=2nd
|year=1993
|isbn=978-0-632-03583-0
|oclc=27011505
|url=https://archive.org/details/quantitiesunitss0000unse/page/70
|page=[https://archive.org/details/quantitiesunitss0000unse/page/70 70]
|access-date=10 December 2011
|url-status=live
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Shape and size===
{{Main|Atomic radius}}
Atoms lack a well-defined outer boundary, so their dimensions are usually described in terms of an [[atomic radius]]. This is a measure of the distance out to which the electron cloud extends from the nucleus.&lt;ref name=Ghosh02&gt;{{cite journal | author = Ghosh, D.C. |author2= Biswas, R. | title = Theoretical calculation of Absolute Radii of Atoms and Ions. Part 1. The Atomic Radii | journal = Int. J. Mol. Sci. | volume = 3 |issue= 11 | pages = 87–113 | year = 2002 | doi=10.3390/i3020087| doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, this assumes the atom to exhibit a spherical shape, which is only obeyed for atoms in vacuum or free space. Atomic radii may be derived from the distances between two nuclei when the two atoms are joined in a [[chemical bond]]. The radius varies with the location of an atom on the atomic chart, the type of chemical bond, the number of neighboring atoms ([[coordination number]]) and a [[quantum mechanics|quantum mechanical]] property known as [[Spin (physics)|spin]].&lt;ref name=aca32_5_751/&gt; On the [[periodic table]] of the elements, atom size tends to increase when moving down columns, but decrease when moving across rows (left to right).&lt;ref name=dong1998/&gt; Consequently, the smallest atom is helium with a radius of 32&amp;nbsp;[[Picometre|pm]], while one of the largest is [[caesium]] at 225&amp;nbsp;pm.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|last=Zumdahl|first=Steven S.|year=2002
|title=Introductory Chemistry: A Foundation
|edition=5th|publisher=Houghton Mifflin
|url=http://college.hmco.com/chemistry/intro/zumdahl/intro_chemistry/5e/students/protected/periodictables/pt/pt/pt_ar5.html
|accessdate=5 February 2008|isbn=978-0-618-34342-3
|oclc=173081482| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080304155935/http://college.hmco.com/chemistry/intro/zumdahl/intro_chemistry/5e/students/protected/periodictables/pt/pt/pt_ar5.html| archivedate= 4 March 2008 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When subjected to external forces, like [[electrical field]]s, the shape of an atom may deviate from [[spherical symmetry]]. The deformation depends on the field magnitude and the orbital type of outer shell electrons, as shown by [[group theory|group-theoretical]] considerations. Aspherical deviations might be elicited for instance in [[crystal]]s, where large crystal-electrical fields may occur at [[crystal symmetry|low-symmetry]] lattice sites.&lt;ref name= Bethe1929&gt;{{cite journal|author = Bethe, Hans|title = Termaufspaltung in Kristallen|journal = Annalen der Physik|volume = 3|issue = 2|pages = 133–208|year = 1929|doi = 10.1002/andp.19293950202|bibcode = 1929AnP...395..133B }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= ZPB1995a&gt;{{cite journal | author = Birkholz, Mario | title = Crystal-field induced dipoles in heteropolar crystals – I. concept | journal = Z. Phys. B | volume = 96 | issue = 3 | pages = 325–332 | year = 1995 | doi = 10.1007/BF01313054 |bibcode = 1995ZPhyB..96..325B | url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/227050494| citeseerx = 10.1.1.424.5632 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Significant [[ellipsoid]]al deformations have been shown to occur for sulfur ions&lt;ref name=pssb2008&gt;{{cite journal | author = Birkholz, M. |author2= Rudert, R. | title = Interatomic distances in pyrite-structure disulfides – a case for ellipsoidal modeling of sulfur ions] | journal = Physica Status Solidi B | volume = 245 |issue= 9 | pages = 1858–1864 | year = 2008 | doi = 10.1002/pssb.200879532 | bibcode=2008PSSBR.245.1858B}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[chalcogen]] ions&lt;ref name=mdpi2014&gt;{{cite journal | author = Birkholz, M. | title = Modeling the Shape of Ions in Pyrite-Type Crystals| journal = Crystals | volume = 4 | issue = 3| pages = 390–403 | year = 2014 | doi = 10.3390/cryst4030390| doi-access = free}}&lt;/ref&gt; in [[pyrite]]-type compounds.

Atomic dimensions are thousands of times smaller than the wavelengths of [[light]] (400–700&amp;nbsp;[[nanometre|nm]]) so they cannot be viewed using an [[optical microscope]]. However, individual atoms can be observed using a [[scanning tunneling microscope]]. To visualize the minuteness of the atom, consider that a typical human hair is about 1&amp;nbsp;million carbon atoms in width.&lt;ref name=osu2007/&gt; A single drop of water contains about 2&amp;nbsp;[[sextillion]] ({{val|2|e=21}}) atoms of oxygen, and twice the number of hydrogen atoms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|last=Padilla|first=Michael J.
|author2=Miaoulis, Ioannis|author3= Cyr, Martha|year = 2002
|title = Prentice Hall Science Explorer: Chemical Building Blocks
|publisher = Prentice-Hall, Inc.
|location = Upper Saddle River, New Jersey
|isbn = 978-0-13-054091-1
|oclc=47925884|page=32
|quote=There are 2,000,000,000,000,000,000,000 (that's 2&amp;nbsp;sextillion) atoms of oxygen in one drop of water—and twice as many atoms of hydrogen.}}&lt;/ref&gt; A single [[Carat (unit)|carat]] [[diamond]] with a mass of {{val|2|e=-4|u=kg}} contains about 10&amp;nbsp;sextillion (10&lt;sup&gt;22&lt;/sup&gt;) atoms of [[carbon]].&lt;ref group=note&gt;A carat is 200&amp;nbsp;milligrams. [[Atomic mass unit|By definition]], carbon-12 has 0.012&amp;nbsp;kg per mole. The [[Avogadro constant]] defines {{val|6|e=23}} atoms per mole.&lt;/ref&gt; If an apple were magnified to the size of the Earth, then the atoms in the apple would be approximately the size of the original apple.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|last=Feynman|first=Richard|year=1995|authorlink=Richard Feynman
|title=Six Easy Pieces|publisher=The Penguin Group
|isbn=978-0-14-027666-4
|oclc=40499574|page=5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Radioactive decay===
{{Main|Radioactive decay}}

[[File:Isotopes and half-life.svg|right|thumb|This diagram shows the [[half-life]] (T&lt;sub&gt;½&lt;/sub&gt;) of various isotopes with Z protons and N neutrons.]]

Every element has one or more isotopes that have unstable nuclei that are subject to radioactive decay, causing the nucleus to emit particles or electromagnetic radiation. Radioactivity can occur when the radius of a nucleus is large compared with the radius of the strong force, which only acts over distances on the order of 1&amp;nbsp;fm.&lt;ref name=splung/&gt;

The most common forms of radioactive decay are:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|last=L'Annunziata&lt;!-- Note: the single quote mark before the name is correct. --&gt;
|first=Michael F.
|year=2003|title=Handbook of Radioactivity Analysis
|publisher=Academic Press|isbn=978-0-12-436603-9
|oclc=16212955|pages=3–56}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=firestone20000522/&gt;
* [[Alpha decay]]: this process is caused when the nucleus emits an alpha particle, which is a helium nucleus consisting of two protons and two neutrons. The result of the emission is a new element with a lower [[atomic number]].
* [[Beta decay]] (and [[electron capture]]): these processes are regulated by the [[weak force]], and result from a transformation of a neutron into a proton, or a proton into a neutron. The neutron to proton transition is accompanied by the emission of an electron and an [[antineutrino]], while proton to neutron transition (except in electron capture) causes the emission of a [[positron]] and a [[neutrino]]. The electron or positron emissions are called beta particles. Beta decay either increases or decreases the atomic number of the nucleus by one. Electron capture is more common than positron emission, because it requires less energy. In this type of decay, an electron is absorbed by the nucleus, rather than a positron emitted from the nucleus. A neutrino is still emitted in this process, and a proton changes to a neutron.
* [[Gamma decay]]: this process results from a change in the energy level of the nucleus to a lower state, resulting in the emission of electromagnetic radiation. The excited state of a nucleus which results in gamma emission usually occurs following the emission of an alpha or a beta particle. Thus, gamma decay usually follows alpha or beta decay.

Other more rare types of [[radioactive decay]] include ejection of neutrons or protons or clusters of [[nucleon]]s from a nucleus, or more than one [[beta particle]]. An analog of gamma emission which allows excited nuclei to lose energy in a different way, is [[internal conversion]]—a process that produces high-speed electrons that are not beta rays, followed by production of high-energy photons that are not gamma rays. A few large nuclei explode into two or more charged fragments of varying masses plus several neutrons, in a decay called spontaneous [[nuclear fission]].

Each [[radioactive isotope]] has a characteristic decay time period—the [[half-life]]—that is determined by the amount of time needed for half of a sample to decay. This is an [[exponential decay]] process that steadily decreases the proportion of the remaining isotope by 50% every half-life. Hence after two half-lives have passed only 25% of the isotope is present, and so forth.&lt;ref name=splung/&gt;

===Magnetic moment===
{{Main|Electron magnetic moment|Nuclear magnetic moment}}

Elementary particles possess an intrinsic quantum mechanical property known as [[Spin (physics)|spin]]. This is analogous to the [[angular momentum]] of an object that is spinning around its [[center of mass]], although strictly speaking these particles are believed to be point-like and cannot be said to be rotating. Spin is measured in units of the reduced [[Planck constant]] (ħ), with electrons, protons and neutrons all having spin ½&amp;nbsp;ħ, or &quot;spin-½&quot;. In an atom, electrons in motion around the [[Atomic nucleus|nucleus]] possess orbital [[angular momentum]] in addition to their spin, while the nucleus itself possesses angular momentum due to its nuclear spin.&lt;ref name=hornak2006/&gt;

The [[magnetic field]] produced by an atom—its [[magnetic moment]]—is determined by these various forms of angular momentum, just as a rotating charged object classically produces a magnetic field. However, the most dominant contribution comes from electron spin. Due to the nature of electrons to obey the [[Pauli exclusion principle]], in which no two electrons may be found in the same [[quantum state]], bound electrons pair up with each other, with one member of each pair in a spin up state and the other in the opposite, spin down state. Thus these spins cancel each other out, reducing the total magnetic dipole moment to zero in some atoms with even number of electrons.&lt;ref name=schroeder2/&gt;

In [[Ferromagnetism|ferromagnetic]] elements such as iron, cobalt and nickel, an odd number of electrons leads to an unpaired electron and a net overall magnetic moment. The orbitals of neighboring atoms overlap and a lower energy state is achieved when the spins of unpaired electrons are aligned with each other, a spontaneous process known as an [[exchange interaction]]. When the magnetic moments of ferromagnetic atoms are lined up, the material can produce a measurable macroscopic field. [[Paramagnetism|Paramagnetic materials]] have atoms with magnetic moments that line up in random directions when no magnetic field is present, but the magnetic moments of the individual atoms line up in the presence of a field.&lt;ref name=schroeder2/&gt;&lt;ref name=goebel20070901/&gt;

The nucleus of an atom will have no spin when it has even numbers of both neutrons and protons, but for other cases of odd numbers, the nucleus may have a spin. Normally nuclei with spin are aligned in random directions because of [[thermal equilibrium]]. However, for certain elements (such as [[xenon|xenon-129]]) it is possible to [[spin polarization|polarize]] a significant proportion of the nuclear spin states so that they are aligned in the same direction—a condition called [[hyperpolarization (physics)|hyperpolarization]]. This has important applications in [[magnetic resonance imaging]].&lt;ref name=yarris1997/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|last1=Liang|first1=Z.-P.|last2=Haacke|first2=E.M.
|editor=Webster, J.G.|year=1999
|volume=vol. 2
|title=Encyclopedia of Electrical and Electronics Engineering: Magnetic Resonance Imaging
|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons
|isbn=978-0-471-13946-1|pages=412–426}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Energy levels===
[[Image:Atomic orbital energy levels.svg|thumb|right|These electron's energy levels (not to scale) are sufficient for ground states of atoms up to [[cadmium]] (5s&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; 4d&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;) inclusively. Do not forget that even the top of the diagram is lower than an unbound electron state.]]
The [[potential energy]] of an electron in an atom is [[negative number|negative]], its dependence of its [[position (vector)|position]] reaches the [[minimum]] (the most [[absolute value]]) inside the nucleus, and vanishes when the [[distance]] from the nucleus [[limit at infinity|goes to infinity]], roughly in an [[inverse proportion]] to the distance. In the quantum-mechanical model, a bound electron can only occupy a set of [[quantum state|states]] centered on the nucleus, and each state corresponds to a specific [[energy level]]; see [[time-independent Schrödinger equation]] for theoretical explanation. An energy level can be measured by the [[ionization potential|amount of energy needed to unbind]] the electron from the atom, and is usually given in units of [[electronvolt]]s (eV). The lowest energy state of a bound electron is called the ground state, i.e. [[stationary state]], while an electron transition to a higher level results in an excited state.&lt;ref name=zeghbroeck1998/&gt; The electron's energy raises when ''[[principal quantum number|n]]'' increases because the (average) distance to the nucleus increases. Dependence of the energy on [[azimuthal quantum number|{{ell}}]] is caused not by [[electrostatic potential]] of the nucleus, but by interaction between electrons.

For an electron to [[atomic electron transition|transition between two different states]], e.g. [[ground state]] to first [[excited state]], it must absorb or emit a [[photon]] at an energy matching the difference in the potential energy of those levels, according to the [[Niels Bohr]] model, what can be precisely calculated by the [[Schrödinger equation]].
Electrons jump between orbitals in a particle-like fashion. For example, if a single photon strikes the electrons, only a single electron changes states in response to the photon; see [[Atomic orbital|Electron properties]].

The energy of an emitted photon is proportional to its [[frequency]], so these specific energy levels appear as distinct bands in the [[electromagnetic spectrum]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|last=Fowles|first=Grant R.|year=1989
|title=Introduction to Modern Optics
|publisher=Courier Dover Publications
|isbn=978-0-486-65957-2
|oclc=18834711|pages=227–233}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Each element has a characteristic spectrum that can depend on the nuclear charge, subshells filled by electrons, the electromagnetic interactions between the electrons and other factors.&lt;ref name=martin2007/&gt;

[[File:Fraunhofer lines.svg|right|thumb|upright=1.5|An example of absorption lines in a spectrum]]

When a continuous [[electromagnetic spectrum|spectrum of energy]] is passed through a gas or plasma, some of the photons are absorbed by atoms, causing electrons to change their energy level. Those excited electrons that remain bound to their atom spontaneously emit this energy as a photon, traveling in a random direction, and so drop back to lower energy levels. Thus the atoms behave like a filter that forms a series of dark [[absorption band]]s in the energy output. (An observer viewing the atoms from a view that does not include the continuous spectrum in the background, instead sees a series of [[emission line]]s from the photons emitted by the atoms.) [[Spectroscopy|Spectroscopic]] measurements of the strength and width of [[atomic spectral line]]s allow the composition and physical properties of a substance to be determined.&lt;ref name=avogadro/&gt;

Close examination of the spectral lines reveals that some display a [[fine structure]] splitting. This occurs because of [[spin–orbit coupling]], which is an interaction between the spin and motion of the outermost electron.&lt;ref name=fitzpatrick20070216/&gt; When an atom is in an external magnetic field, spectral lines become split into three or more components; a phenomenon called the [[Zeeman effect]]. This is caused by the interaction of the magnetic field with the magnetic moment of the atom and its electrons. Some atoms can have multiple [[electron configuration]]s with the same energy level, which thus appear as a single spectral line. The interaction of the magnetic field with the atom shifts these electron configurations to slightly different energy levels, resulting in multiple spectral lines.&lt;ref name=weiss2001/&gt; The presence of an external [[electric field]] can cause a comparable splitting and shifting of spectral lines by modifying the electron energy levels, a phenomenon called the [[Stark effect]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|last=Beyer|first=H.F.
|last2=Shevelko|first2=V.P.
|year=2003
|title=Introduction to the Physics of Highly Charged Ions
|publisher=CRC Press|isbn=978-0-7503-0481-8
|oclc=47150433|pages=232–236}}&lt;/ref&gt;

If a bound electron is in an excited state, an interacting photon with the proper energy can cause [[stimulated emission]] of a photon with a matching energy level. For this to occur, the electron must drop to a lower energy state that has an energy difference matching the energy of the interacting photon. The emitted photon and the interacting photon then move off in parallel and with matching phases. That is, the wave patterns of the two photons are synchronized. This physical property is used to make [[laser]]s, which can emit a coherent beam of light energy in a narrow frequency band.&lt;ref name=watkins_sjsu/&gt;

===Valence and bonding behavior===
{{Main|Valence (chemistry)|Chemical bond}}

Valency is the combining power of an element. It is equal to number of hydrogen atoms that atom can combine or displace in forming compounds.&lt;ref&gt;oxford dictionary – valency&lt;/ref&gt; The outermost electron shell of an atom in its uncombined state is known as the [[valence shell]], and the electrons in
that shell are called [[valence electron]]s. The number of valence electrons determines the [[chemical bond|bonding]]
behavior with other atoms. Atoms tend to [[Chemical reaction|chemically react]] with each other in a manner that fills (or empties) their outer valence shells.&lt;ref name=reusch20070716/&gt; For example, a transfer of a single electron between atoms is a useful approximation for bonds that form between atoms with one-electron more than a filled shell, and others that are one-electron short of a full shell, such as occurs in the compound [[sodium chloride]] and other chemical ionic salts. However, many elements display multiple valences, or tendencies to share differing numbers of electrons in different compounds. Thus, [[chemical bond]]ing between these elements takes many forms of electron-sharing that are more than simple electron transfers. Examples include the element carbon and the [[organic compounds]].&lt;ref name=chemguide/&gt;

The [[chemical element]]s are often displayed in a [[periodic table]] that is laid out to display recurring chemical properties, and elements with the same number of valence electrons form a group that is aligned in the same column of the table. (The horizontal rows correspond to the filling of a quantum shell of electrons.) The elements at the far right of the table have their outer shell completely filled with electrons, which results in chemically inert elements known as the [[noble gas]]es.&lt;ref name=husted20031211/&gt;&lt;ref name=baum2003/&gt;

===States===
{{Main|State of matter|Phase (matter)}}

[[File:Bose Einstein condensate.png|right|thumb|Graphic illustrating the formation of a [[Bose–Einstein condensate]]]]
Quantities of atoms are found in different states of matter that depend on the physical conditions, such as [[temperature]] and [[pressure]]. By varying the conditions, materials can transition between [[solid]]s, [[liquid]]s, [[gas]]es and [[plasma (physics)|plasmas]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|last=Goodstein|first=David L.|year=2002
|title=States of Matter|publisher=Courier Dover Publications
|isbn=978-0-13-843557-8|pages=436–438}}&lt;/ref&gt; Within a state, a material can also exist in different [[allotropes]]. An example of this is solid carbon, which can exist as [[graphite]] or [[diamond]].&lt;ref name=pu49_7_719/&gt; Gaseous allotropes exist as well, such as [[dioxygen]] and [[ozone]].

At temperatures close to [[absolute zero]], atoms can form a [[Bose–Einstein condensate]], at which point quantum mechanical effects, which are normally only observed at the atomic scale, become apparent on a macroscopic scale.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|last=Myers|first=Richard|year=2003
|title=The Basics of Chemistry|publisher=Greenwood Press
|isbn=978-0-313-31664-7
|oclc=50164580|page=85}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=nist_bec/&gt; This super-cooled collection of atoms
then behaves as a single [[super atom]], which may allow fundamental checks of quantum mechanical behavior.&lt;ref name=colton_fyffe1999/&gt;
{{Clear}}

==Identification==
[[File:Atomic resolution Au100.JPG|right|thumb|[[Scanning tunneling microscope]] image showing the individual atoms making up this [[gold]] ([[Miller index|100]]) surface. The surface atoms deviate from the bulk [[crystal structure]] and arrange in columns several atoms wide with pits between them (See [[surface reconstruction]]).]]
The [[scanning tunneling microscope]] is a device for viewing surfaces at the atomic level. It uses the [[quantum tunneling]] phenomenon, which allows particles to pass through a barrier that would normally be insurmountable. Electrons tunnel through the vacuum between two planar metal electrodes, on each of which is an [[adsorb]]ed atom, providing a tunneling-current density that can be measured. Scanning one atom (taken as the tip) as it moves past the other (the sample) permits plotting of tip displacement versus lateral separation for a constant current. The calculation shows the extent to which scanning-tunneling-microscope images of an individual atom are visible. It confirms that for low bias, the microscope images the space-averaged dimensions of the electron orbitals across closely packed energy levels—the [[Fermi level]] [[local density of states]].&lt;ref name=jacox1997/&gt;&lt;ref name=nf_physics1986/&gt;

An atom can be [[ion]]ized by removing one of its electrons. The [[electric charge]] causes the trajectory of an atom to bend when it passes through a [[magnetic field]]. The radius by which the trajectory of a moving ion is turned by the magnetic field is determined by the mass of the atom. The [[Mass spectrometry|mass spectrometer]] uses this principle to measure the [[mass-to-charge ratio]] of ions. If a sample contains multiple isotopes, the mass spectrometer can determine the proportion of each isotope in the sample by measuring the intensity of the different beams of ions. Techniques to vaporize atoms include [[inductively coupled plasma atomic emission spectroscopy]] and [[inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry]], both of which use a plasma to vaporize samples for analysis.&lt;ref name=sab53_13_1739/&gt;

A more area-selective method is [[electron energy loss spectroscopy]], which measures the energy loss of an [[electron beam]] within a [[transmission electron microscope]] when it interacts with a portion of a sample. The [[atom probe|atom-probe tomograph]] has sub-nanometer resolution in 3-D and can chemically identify individual atoms using time-of-flight mass spectrometry.&lt;ref name=rsi39_1_83/&gt;

Spectra of [[excited state]]s can be used to analyze the atomic composition of distant [[star]]s. Specific light [[wavelength]]s contained in the observed light from stars can be separated out and related to the quantized transitions in free gas atoms. These colors can be replicated using a [[gas-discharge lamp]] containing the same element.&lt;ref name=lochner2007/&gt; [[Helium]] was discovered in this way in the spectrum of the Sun 23&amp;nbsp;years before it was found on Earth.&lt;ref name=winter2007/&gt;

==Origin and current state==
[[Baryonic matter]] forms about 4% of the total energy density of the [[observable Universe]], with an average density of about 0.25&amp;nbsp;particles/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; (mostly [[proton]]s and electrons).&lt;ref name=hinshaw20060210/&gt; Within a galaxy such as the [[Milky Way]], particles have a much higher concentration, with the density of matter in the [[interstellar medium]] (ISM) ranging from 10&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; to 10&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt; atoms/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|last=Choppin|first=Gregory R.
|last2=Liljenzin|first2=Jan-Olov|last3=Rydberg|first3=Jan
|year=2001|title=Radiochemistry and Nuclear Chemistry
|publisher=Elsevier|isbn=978-0-7506-7463-8
|oclc=162592180|page=441}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Sun is believed to be inside the [[Local Bubble]], so the density in the solar neighborhood is only about 10&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; atoms/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;ref name=science259_5093_327/&gt; Stars form from dense clouds in the ISM, and the evolutionary processes of stars result in the steady enrichment of the ISM with elements more massive than hydrogen and helium.

Up to 95% of the Milky Way's baryonic matter are concentrated inside stars, where conditions are unfavorable for atomic matter. The total baryonic mass is about 10% of the mass of the galaxy;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|last=Lequeux|first=James|year=2005
|title=The Interstellar Medium
|publisher=Springer|isbn=978-3-540-21326-0
|oclc=133157789|page=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; the remainder of the mass is an unknown [[dark matter]].&lt;ref name=nigel2000/&gt; High [[temperature]] inside stars makes most &quot;atoms&quot; fully ionized, that is, separates ''all'' electrons from the nuclei. In [[stellar remnant]]s—with exception of their surface layers—an immense [[pressure]] make electron shells impossible.

===Formation===
{{main|Nucleosynthesis}}
[[File:Nucleosynthesis periodic table.svg|thumb|600px|Periodic table showing the origin of each element. Elements from carbon up to sulfur may be made in small stars by the [[alpha process]]. Elements beyond iron are made in large stars with slow neutron capture ([[s-process]]). Elements heavier than iron may be made in neutron star mergers or supernovae after the [[r-process]].]]

Electrons are thought to exist in the Universe since early stages of the [[Big Bang]]. Atomic nuclei forms in [[nucleosynthesis]] reactions. In about three minutes [[Big Bang nucleosynthesis]] produced most of the [[helium]], [[lithium]], and [[deuterium]] in the Universe, and perhaps some of the [[beryllium]] and [[boron]].&lt;ref name=ns1794_42/&gt;&lt;ref name=science267_5195_192/&gt;&lt;ref name=hinshaw20051215/&gt;

Ubiquitousness and stability of atoms relies on their [[binding energy]], which means that an atom has a lower energy than an unbound system of the nucleus and electrons. Where the [[temperature]] is much higher than [[ionization potential]], the matter exists in the form of [[plasma (physics)|plasma]]—a gas of positively charged ions (possibly, bare nuclei) and electrons. When the temperature drops below the ionization potential, atoms become [[statistical physics|statistically]] favorable. Atoms (complete with bound electrons) became to dominate over [[electric charge|charged]] [[particle]]s 380,000&amp;nbsp;years after the Big Bang—an epoch called [[recombination (cosmology)|recombination]], when the expanding Universe cooled enough to allow electrons to become attached to nuclei.&lt;ref name=abbott20070530/&gt;

Since the Big Bang, which produced no [[carbon]] or [[atomic number|heavier elements]], atomic nuclei have been combined in [[star]]s through the process of [[nuclear fusion]] to produce more of the element [[helium]], and (via the [[triple alpha process]]) the sequence of elements from carbon up to [[iron]];&lt;ref name=mnras106_343/&gt; see [[stellar nucleosynthesis]] for details.

Isotopes such as lithium-6, as well as some beryllium and boron are generated in space through [[cosmic ray spallation]].&lt;ref name=nature405_656/&gt; This occurs when a high-energy proton strikes an atomic nucleus, causing large numbers of nucleons to be ejected.

Elements heavier than iron were produced in [[supernova]]e and colliding [[neutron star]]s through the [[r-process]], and in [[Asymptotic giant branch|AGB stars]] through the [[s-process]], both of which involve the capture of neutrons by atomic nuclei.&lt;ref name=mashnik2000/&gt; Elements such as [[lead]] formed largely through the radioactive decay of heavier elements.&lt;ref name=kgs20050504/&gt;

===Earth===
Most of the atoms that make up the [[Earth]] and its inhabitants were present in their current form in the [[nebula]] that collapsed out of a [[molecular cloud]] to form the [[Solar System]]. The rest are the result of radioactive decay, and their relative proportion can be used to determine the [[age of the Earth]] through [[radiometric dating]].{{sfn|Manuel|2001|pp=407–430, 511–519}}&lt;ref name=gs190_1_205/&gt; Most of the [[helium]] in the crust of the Earth (about 99% of the helium from gas wells, as shown by its lower abundance of [[helium-3]]) is a product of [[alpha decay]].&lt;ref name=anderson_foulger_meibom2006/&gt;

There are a few trace atoms on Earth that were not present at the beginning (i.e., not &quot;primordial&quot;), nor are results of radioactive decay. [[Carbon-14]] is continuously generated by cosmic rays in the atmosphere.&lt;ref name=pennicott2001/&gt; Some atoms on Earth have been artificially generated either deliberately or as by-products of nuclear reactors or explosions.&lt;ref name=yarris2001/&gt;&lt;ref name=pr119_6_2000/&gt; Of the [[Transuranium element|transuranic elements]]—those with atomic numbers greater than 92—only [[plutonium]] and [[neptunium]] occur naturally on Earth.&lt;ref name=poston1998/&gt;&lt;ref name=cz97_10_522/&gt; Transuranic elements have radioactive lifetimes shorter than the current age of the Earth&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|last1=Zaider|first1=Marco|last2=Rossi|first2=Harald H.|year=2001
|title=Radiation Science for Physicians and Public Health Workers
|publisher=Springer|isbn=978-0-306-46403-4
|oclc=44110319|page=17}}&lt;/ref&gt; and thus identifiable quantities of these elements have long since decayed, with the exception of traces of [[plutonium-244]] possibly deposited by cosmic dust.{{sfn|Manuel|2001|pp=407–430, 511–519}} Natural deposits of plutonium and neptunium are produced by [[neutron capture]] in uranium ore.&lt;ref name=ofr_cut/&gt;

The Earth contains approximately {{val|1.33|e=50}} atoms.&lt;ref name=weisenberger/&gt; Although small numbers of independent atoms of [[noble gas]]es exist, such as [[argon]], [[neon]], and [[helium]]&lt;!-- note that noble gases exist not only in the atmosphere --&gt;, 99% of [[Earth's atmosphere|the atmosphere]] is bound in the form of molecules, including [[carbon dioxide]] and [[Diatomic molecule|diatomic]] [[oxygen]] and [[nitrogen]]. At the surface of the Earth, an overwhelming majority of atoms combine to form various compounds, including [[water]], [[salt]], [[silicate]]s and [[oxide]]s. Atoms can also combine to create materials that do not consist of discrete molecules, including [[crystal]]s and liquid or solid [[metal]]s.&lt;ref name=pidwirnyf/&gt;&lt;ref name=pnas99_22_13966/&gt; This atomic matter forms networked arrangements that lack the particular type of small-scale interrupted order associated with molecular matter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|last=Pauling|first=Linus|year=1960
|title=The Nature of the Chemical Bond
|publisher=Cornell University Press
|isbn=978-0-8014-0333-0
|oclc=17518275|pages=5–10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rare and theoretical forms===

====Superheavy elements====
{{Main|Transactinide element}}

While isotopes with atomic numbers higher than [[lead]] (82) are known to be radioactive, an &quot;[[island of stability]]&quot; has been proposed for some elements with atomic numbers above 103. These [[superheavy element]]s may have a nucleus that is relatively stable against radioactive decay.&lt;ref name=cern28509/&gt; The most likely candidate for a stable superheavy atom, [[unbihexium]], has 126&amp;nbsp;protons and 184&amp;nbsp;neutrons.&lt;ref name=cen84_10_19/&gt;

====Exotic matter====
{{Main|1=Exotic matter}}

Each particle of matter has a corresponding [[antimatter]] particle with the opposite electrical charge. Thus, the [[positron]] is a positively charged [[antielectron]] and the [[antiproton]] is a negatively charged equivalent of a [[proton]]. When a matter and corresponding antimatter particle meet, they annihilate each other. Because of this, along with an imbalance between the number of matter and antimatter particles, the latter are rare in the universe. The first causes of this imbalance are not yet fully understood, although theories of [[baryogenesis]] may offer an explanation. As a result, no antimatter atoms have been discovered in nature.&lt;ref name=koppes1999/&gt;&lt;ref name=cromie20010816/&gt; However, in 1996 the antimatter counterpart of the hydrogen atom ([[antihydrogen]]) was synthesized at the [[CERN]] laboratory in [[Geneva]].&lt;ref name=nature419_6906_439/&gt;&lt;ref name=BBC20021030/&gt;

Other [[exotic atom]]s have been created by replacing one of the protons, neutrons or electrons with other particles that have the same charge. For example, an electron can be replaced by a more massive [[muon]], forming a [[muonic atom]]. These types of atoms can be used to test the fundamental predictions of physics.&lt;ref name=ns1728_77/&gt;&lt;ref name=psT112_1_20/&gt;&lt;ref name=ripin1998/&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Physics|Chemistry}}
{{cmn|colwidth=21em|
* [[History of quantum mechanics]]
* [[Infinite divisibility]]
* [[List of basic chemistry topics]]
* [[Motion]]
* [[Timeline of atomic and subatomic physics]]
* [[Vector model of the atom]]
* [[Nuclear model]]
* [[Radioactive isotope]]
}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=&quot;note&quot;}}

==References==
&lt;!-- this 'empty' section displays references defined elsewhere --&gt;
{{reflist|30em|refs=
&lt;!--Unused ref&lt;ref name=leigh1990&gt;{{cite book|editor=Leigh, G.J.|year=1990|title=International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry, Commission on the Nomenclature of Inorganic Chemistry, [[Nomenclature of Organic Chemistry]] – Recommendations 1990|publisher=Blackwell Scientific Publications|isbn=0-08-022369-9|page=35|location=Oxford|quote=An atom is the smallest unit quantity of an element that is capable of existence whether alone or in chemical combination with other atoms of the same or other elements.}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;!--ref name=slac_20090615&gt;{{cite web|date=15 June 2009|title=Radioactive Decays|url=http://www2.slac.stanford.edu/vvc/theory/nuclearstability.html|publisher=[[Stanford Linear Accelerator Center]]|accessdate=4 July 2009| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20090607115741/http://www2.slac.stanford.edu/vvc/theory/nuclearstability.html| archivedate= 7 June 2009 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref--&gt;

&lt;ref name=adp322_8_549&gt;{{cite journal|last=Einstein|first=Albert|year=1905|title=Über die von der molekularkinetischen Theorie der Wärme geforderte Bewegung von in ruhenden Flüssigkeiten suspendierten Teilchen|journal=[[Annalen der Physik]]|volume=322|issue=8|pages=549–560|language=German|url=http://www.zbp.univie.ac.at/dokumente/einstein2.pdf|doi=10.1002/andp.19053220806|accessdate=4 February 2007|bibcode=1905AnP...322..549E|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070718202731/http://www.zbp.univie.ac.at/dokumente/einstein2.pdf|archive-date=18 July 2007|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=lee_hoon1995&gt;{{cite web|last=Lee|first=Y.K.|year=1995|author2=Hoon, K.|title=Brownian Motion|url=http://www.doc.ic.ac.uk/~nd/surprise_95/journal/vol4/ykl/report.html|publisher=[[Imperial College]]|accessdate=18 December 2007|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071218061408/http://www.doc.ic.ac.uk/~nd/surprise_95/journal/vol4/ykl/report.html|archivedate=18 December 2007|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=e31_2_50&gt;{{cite journal|last=Patterson|first=G.|year=2007 |title=Jean Perrin and the triumph of the atomic doctrine|journal=[[Endeavour (journal)|Endeavour]]|volume=31|issue=2|pages=50–53|doi=10.1016/j.endeavour.2007.05.003|pmid=17602746}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=nobel1096&gt;{{cite web|year=1906|title=J.J. Thomson|url=http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/physics/laureates/1906/thomson-bio.html|publisher=[[Nobel Foundation]]|accessdate=20 December 2007|archive-url=https://www.webcitation.org/6GYgrNSic?url=http://www.nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/physics/laureates/1906/thomson-bio.html|archive-date=12 May 2013|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=pm21_669&gt;{{cite journal|last=Rutherford|first=E.|title=The Scattering of α and β Particles by Matter and the Structure of the Atom|url=http://users.uoa.gr/~pjioannou/mech1/READING/structureatom.pdf|journal=[[Philosophical Magazine]]|year=1911|volume=21|pages=669–688|doi=10.1080/14786440508637080|issue=125|access-date=29 April 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160531232258/http://users.uoa.gr/~pjioannou/mech1/READING/structureatom.pdf|archive-date=31 May 2016|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=npc1921&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/chemistry/laureates/1921/soddy-bio.html|title=Frederick Soddy, The Nobel Prize in Chemistry 1921|publisher=[[Nobel Foundation]]|accessdate=18 January 2008|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080409210519/http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/chemistry/laureates/1921/soddy-bio.html|archive-date=9 April 2008|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=prsA_89_1_1913&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1098/rspa.1913.0057|last=Thomson|first=Joseph John|title=Rays of positive electricity|url=http://web.lemoyne.edu/~giunta/canal.html|series=A|journal=[[Proceedings of the Royal Society]]|year=1913|volume=89|issue=607|pages=1–20|bibcode=1913RSPSA..89....1T|doi-access=free|access-date=12 February 2008|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161104174348/http://web.lemoyne.edu/~giunta/canal.html|archive-date=4 November 2016|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=stern20050516&gt;{{cite web|last=Stern|first=David P.|date=16 May 2005|title=The Atomic Nucleus and Bohr's Early Model of the Atom|url=http://www-spof.gsfc.nasa.gov/stargaze/Q5.htm|publisher=[[NASA]]/[[Goddard Space Flight Center]]|accessdate=20 December 2007|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070820084047/http://www-spof.gsfc.nasa.gov/stargaze/Q5.htm|archive-date=20 August 2007|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=bohr19221211&gt;{{cite web|last=Bohr|first=Niels|date=11 December 1922|title=Niels Bohr, The Nobel Prize in Physics 1922, Nobel Lecture|url=http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/physics/laureates/1922/bohr-lecture.html|publisher=[[Nobel Foundation]]|accessdate=16 February 2008|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080415183736/http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/physics/laureates/1922/bohr-lecture.html|archive-date=15 April 2008|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=jacs38_4_762&gt;{{cite journal|last=Lewis|first=Gilbert N.|year=1916|title=The Atom and the Molecule|journal=[[Journal of the American Chemical Society]]|volume=38|issue=4|pages=762–786|doi=10.1021/ja02261a002|url=https://zenodo.org/record/1429068|access-date=25 August 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190825132554/https://zenodo.org/record/1429068/files/article.pdf|archive-date=25 August 2019|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=jacs41_6_868&gt;{{cite journal|last=Langmuir|first=Irving|year=1919|title=The Arrangement of Electrons in Atoms and Molecules|journal=[[Journal of the American Chemical Society]]|volume=41|issue=6|pages=868–934|doi=10.1021/ja02227a002|url=https://zenodo.org/record/1429026|access-date=27 June 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190621192330/https://zenodo.org/record/1429026|archive-date=21 June 2019|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=fop17_6_575&gt;{{cite journal|last=Scully|first=Marlan O. |author2=Lamb, Willis E.|author3= Barut, Asim|year=1987|title=On the theory of the Stern-Gerlach apparatus|journal=[[Foundations of Physics]]|volume=17|issue=6|pages=575–583|doi=10.1007/BF01882788|bibcode = 1987FoPh...17..575S }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=brown2007&gt;{{cite web|last=Brown|first=Kevin|year=2007|url=http://www.mathpages.com/home/kmath538/kmath538.htm|title=The Hydrogen Atom|publisher=MathPages|accessdate=21 December 2007|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080513082947/http://www.mathpages.com/home/kmath538/kmath538.htm|archive-date=13 May 2008|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=harrison2000&gt;{{cite web|last=Harrison|first=David M.|year=2000|title=The Development of Quantum Mechanics|url=http://www.upscale.utoronto.ca/GeneralInterest/Harrison/DevelQM/DevelQM.html|publisher=[[University of Toronto]]|accessdate=21 December 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20071225095938/http://www.upscale.utoronto.ca/GeneralInterest/Harrison/DevelQM/DevelQM.html| archivedate= 25 December 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=pm39_6_449&gt;{{cite journal|last=Aston|first=Francis W.|year=1920|title=The constitution of atmospheric neon|journal=[[Philosophical Magazine]]|volume=39|issue=6|pages=449–455|doi=10.1080/14786440408636058}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=chadwick1935&gt;{{cite web|last=Chadwick|first=James|date=12 December 1935|title=Nobel Lecture: The Neutron and Its Properties|url=http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/physics/laureates/1935/chadwick-lecture.html|publisher=[[Nobel Foundation]]|accessdate=21 December 2007|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071012100351/http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/physics/laureates/1935/chadwick-lecture.html|archive-date=12 October 2007|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;CHF&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Otto Hahn, Lise Meitner, and Fritz Strassmann|url=https://www.sciencehistory.org/historical-profile/otto-hahn-lise-meitner-and-fritz-strassmann|website=Science History Institute|accessdate=20 March 2018|date=June 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180321130950/https://www.sciencehistory.org/historical-profile/otto-hahn-lise-meitner-and-fritz-strassmann|archive-date=21 March 2018|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Bowden&gt;{{cite book|last1=Bowden|first1=Mary Ellen|title=Chemical achievers : the human face of the chemical sciences|date=1997|publisher=Chemical Heritage Foundation|location=Philadelphia, PA|isbn=978-0-941901-12-3|chapter=Otto Hahn, Lise Meitner, and Fritz Strassmann|pages=[https://archive.org/details/chemicalachiever0000bowd/page/76 76–80, 125]|chapter-url=https://archive.org/details/chemicalachiever0000bowd/page/76}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=nature143_3615_239&gt;{{cite journal |last=Meitner|first=Lise|last2=Frisch|first2=Otto Robert|year=1939|title=Disintegration of uranium by neutrons: a new type of nuclear reaction|journal=[[Nature (journal)|Nature]]|volume=143 |issue=3615 |pages=239–240 |doi=10.1038/143239a0 |bibcode = 1939Natur.143..239M }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=schroeder&gt;{{cite web|last=Schroeder|first=M.|title=Lise Meitner – Zur 125. Wiederkehr Ihres Geburtstages|url=http://www.physik3.gwdg.de/~mrs/Vortraege/Lise_Meitner-Vortrag-20031106/|language=German|accessdate=4 June 2009|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110719034227/http://www.physik3.gwdg.de/~mrs/Vortraege/Lise_Meitner-Vortrag-20031106/|archivedate=19 July 2011|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=schroeder2&gt;{{cite web |last=Schroeder|first=Paul A.
|date=25 February 2000 |url=http://www.gly.uga.edu/schroeder/geol3010/magnetics.html |title=Magnetic Properties |publisher=University of Georgia |accessdate=7 January 2007 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070429150216/http://www.gly.uga.edu/schroeder/geol3010/magnetics.html |archivedate = 29 April 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=pt50_9_26&gt;{{cite journal|last=Crawford |first=E.| year=1997|title=A Nobel tale of postwar injustice|url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/260861491|journal=[[Physics Today]]|volume=50|issue=9|pages=26–32|doi=10.1063/1.881933|last2=Sime|first2=Ruth Lewin|authorlink2=Ruth Lewin Sime|last3=Walker|first3=Mark |bibcode = 1997PhT....50i..26C }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=kullander2001&gt;{{cite web|last=Kullander|first=Sven|date=28 August 2001|title=Accelerators and Nobel Laureates|url=http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/physics/articles/kullander/|publisher=[[Nobel Foundation]]|accessdate=31 January 2008|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080413064924/http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/physics/articles/kullander/|archive-date=13 April 2008|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=npp1990&gt;{{cite web|date=17 October 1990|title=The Nobel Prize in Physics 1990|url=http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/physics/laureates/1990/press.html|publisher=[[Nobel Foundation]]|accessdate=31 January 2008|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080514100040/http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/physics/laureates/1990/press.html|archive-date=14 May 2008|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=pdg2002&gt;{{cite web|author=Particle Data Group|year=2002|url=http://www.particleadventure.org/|title=The Particle Adventure|publisher=Lawrence Berkeley Laboratory|accessdate=3 January 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070104075936/http://www.particleadventure.org/| archivedate= 4 January 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=schombert2006&gt;{{cite web|first=James|last=Schombert|date=18 April 2006|url=http://abyss.uoregon.edu/~js/ast123/lectures/lec07.html|title=Elementary Particles|publisher=University of Oregon|accessdate=3 January 2007|archive-url=https://www.webcitation.org/616PzI2QM?url=http://abyss.uoregon.edu/~js/ast123/lectures/lec07.html|archive-date=21 August 2011|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=wenner2007&gt;{{cite web|last=Wenner|first=Jennifer M.|date=10 October 2007|url=http://serc.carleton.edu/quantskills/methods/quantlit/RadDecay.html|title=How Does Radioactive Decay Work?|publisher=Carleton College|accessdate=9 January 2008|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080511173156/http://serc.carleton.edu/quantskills/methods/quantlit/RadDecay.html|archive-date=11 May 2008|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=mihos2002&gt;{{cite web|last=Mihos|first=Chris|date=23 July 2002|url=http://burro.cwru.edu/Academics/Astr221/StarPhys/coulomb.html|title=Overcoming the Coulomb Barrier|publisher=Case Western Reserve University|accessdate=13 February 2008|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060912013620/http://burro.cwru.edu/Academics/Astr221/StarPhys/coulomb.html|archive-date=12 September 2006|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=lbnl20070330&gt;{{cite web|author=Staff|date=30 March 2007|url=http://www.lbl.gov/abc/Basic.html|title=ABC's of Nuclear Science|publisher=Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory|accessdate=3 January 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20061205215708/http://www.lbl.gov/abc/Basic.html| archivedate= 5 December 2006 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=makhijani_saleska2001&gt;{{cite web|first=Arjun|last=Makhijani|author2=Saleska, Scott|date=2 March 2001|url=http://www.ieer.org/reports/n-basics.html|title=Basics of Nuclear Physics and Fission|publisher=Institute for Energy and Environmental Research |accessdate=3 January 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070116045217/http://www.ieer.org/reports/n-basics.html| archivedate= 16 January 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=ajp63_7_653&gt;{{cite journal|last=Fewell|first=M.P.|title=The atomic nuclide with the highest mean binding energy|journal=[[American Journal of Physics]]|year=1995|volume=63|issue=7|pages=653–658|bibcode=1995AmJPh..63..653F|doi=10.1119/1.17828}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;raymond&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Raymond |first=David |date=7 April 2006 |url=http://physics.nmt.edu/~raymond/classes/ph13xbook/node216.html |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20021201030437/http://physics.nmt.edu/~raymond/classes/ph13xbook/node216.html |url-status=dead |archive-date=1 December 2002 |title=Nuclear Binding Energies |publisher=New Mexico Tech |accessdate=3 January 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=science157_3784_13&gt;{{cite journal|last=Mulliken|first=Robert S.|title=Spectroscopy, Molecular Orbitals, and Chemical Bonding|journal=[[Science (journal)|Science]] |year=1967|volume=157|issue=3784|pages=13–24|doi=10.1126/science.157.3784.13|pmid=5338306|bibcode = 1967Sci...157...13M }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Brucat2008&gt;{{cite web|last=Brucat |first=Philip J. |year=2008 |url=http://www.chem.ufl.edu/~itl/2045/lectures/lec_10.html |title=The Quantum Atom |publisher=University of Florida |accessdate=4 January 2007 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20061207032136/http://www.chem.ufl.edu/~itl/2045/lectures/lec_10.html |archivedate=7 December 2006 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=herter_8&gt;{{cite web|last=Herter |first=Terry |year=2006 |url=http://astrosun2.astro.cornell.edu/academics/courses/astro101/herter/lectures/lec08.htm |title=Lecture 8: The Hydrogen Atom |publisher=Cornell University |accessdate=14 February 2008 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120222062433/http://astrosun2.astro.cornell.edu/academics/courses/astro101/herter/lectures/lec08.htm |archivedate=22 February 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=pr79_2_282&gt;{{cite journal|last=Bell|first=R.E.|title=Gamma-Rays from the Reaction H&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;(n,γ)D&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; and the Binding Energy of the Deuteron|journal=[[Physical Review]]|year=1950|volume=79|issue=2|pages=282–285|doi=10.1103/PhysRev.79.282|last2=Elliott|first2=L.G.|bibcode = 1950PhRv...79..282B }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=matis2000&gt;{{cite web|last=Matis|first=Howard S.|date=9 August 2000|url=http://www.lbl.gov/abc/wallchart/chapters/02/3.html|title=The Isotopes of Hydrogen|website=Guide to the Nuclear Wall Chart|publisher=Lawrence Berkeley National Lab|accessdate=21 December 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20071218153548/http://www.lbl.gov/abc/wallchart/chapters/02/3.html| archivedate= 18 December 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=weiss20061017&gt;{{cite news|last=Weiss|first=Rick|date=17 October 2006|title=Scientists Announce Creation of Atomic Element, the Heaviest Yet|newspaper=Washington Post|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/10/16/AR2006101601083.html|accessdate=21 December 2007|archive-url=https://www.webcitation.org/616Q0bWla?url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/10/16/AR2006101601083.html|archive-date=21 August 2011|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=dume20030423&gt;{{cite news|last=Dumé|first=Belle|date=23 April 2003|title=Bismuth breaks half-life record for alpha decay|publisher=Physics World|url=http://physicsworld.com/cws/article/news/17319|accessdate=21 December 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20071214151450/http://physicsworld.com/cws/article/news/17319| archivedate= 14 December 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=lidsay20000730&gt;{{cite web|last=Lindsay|first=Don|date=30 July 2000|url=http://www.don-lindsay-archive.org/creation/isotope_list.html|title=Radioactives Missing From The Earth|publisher=Don Lindsay Archive|accessdate=23 May 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070428225550/http://www.don-lindsay-archive.org/creation/isotope_list.html| archivedate= 28 April 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=manthey2001&gt;{{cite web|last=Manthey|first=David|year=2001|url=http://www.orbitals.com/orb/|title=Atomic Orbitals|publisher=Orbital Central|accessdate=21 January 2008| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080110102801/http://www.orbitals.com/orb/| archivedate= 10 January 2008 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=tuli2005&gt;{{cite web|first=Jagdish K.|last=Tuli|date=April 2005|title=Nuclear Wallet Cards|publisher=National Nuclear Data Center, Brookhaven National Laboratory|url=http://nucleus.iaea.org/CIR/CIR/NuclearWalletCards.html|accessdate=16 April 2011|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111003185243/http://nucleus.iaea.org/CIR/CIR/NuclearWalletCards.html|archive-date=3 October 2011|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=chieh2001&gt;{{cite web|last=Chieh|first=Chung|date=22 January 2001|url=http://www.science.uwaterloo.ca/~cchieh/cact/nuctek/nuclideunstable.html|title=Nuclide Stability|publisher=University of Waterloo|accessdate=4 January 2007|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070830110015/http://www.science.uwaterloo.ca/~cchieh/cact/nuctek/nuclideunstable.html|archive-date=30 August 2007|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=nist_wc&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://physics.nist.gov/cgi-bin/Compositions/stand_alone.pl?ele=&amp;ascii=html&amp;isotype=some
|title=Atomic Weights and Isotopic Compositions for All Elements
|publisher=National Institute of Standards and Technology
|accessdate=4 January 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20061231212733/http://physics.nist.gov/cgi-bin/Compositions/stand_alone.pl?ele=&amp;ascii=html&amp;isotype=some| archivedate= 31 December 2006 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=audi2003&gt;{{cite journal |last=Audi |first=G. |title=The Ame2003 atomic mass evaluation (II) |journal=[[Nuclear Physics A]] |year=2003 |volume=729 |issue=1 |pages=337–676 |url=http://amdc.in2p3.fr/masstables/Ame2003/Ame2003b.pdf |doi=10.1016/j.nuclphysa.2003.11.003 |bibcode=2003NuPhA.729..337A |last2=Wapstra |first2=A.H. |last3=Thibault |first3=C. |access-date=1 May 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20051016185841/http://amdc.in2p3.fr/masstables/Ame2003/Ame2003b.pdf |archive-date=16 October 2005 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=aca32_5_751&gt;{{cite journal|last = Shannon|first = R.D. |title=Revised effective ionic radii and systematic studies of interatomic distances in halides and chalcogenides|journal=[[Acta Crystallographica A]]|year=1976|volume=32 |issue = 5 |pages=751–767|doi=10.1107/S0567739476001551|bibcode = 1976AcCrA..32..751S |url=http://journals.iucr.org/a/issues/1976/05/00/a12967/a12967.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=dong1998&gt;{{cite web|last=Dong|first=Judy|year=1998 |url=http://hypertextbook.com/facts/MichaelPhillip.shtml|title=Diameter of an Atom|publisher=The Physics Factbook|accessdate=19 November 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20071104160920/http://hypertextbook.com/facts/MichaelPhillip.shtml| archivedate= 4 November 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--ref name=adp5f_3_133&gt;{{cite journal|last = [[Bethe]]|first = H.|title=Termaufspaltung in Kristallen|journal=[[Annalen der Physik]] |year=1929|volume=395 |issue = 2 |pages=133–208|bibcode = 1929AnP...395..133B|doi = 10.1002/andp.19293950202}}&lt;/ref--&gt;

&lt;!--ref name=pssb245_9_1858&gt;{{cite journal
|last = Birkholz|first = M.|author2=Rudert, R.
|title=Interatomic distances in pyrite-structure disulfides – a case for ellipsoidal modeling of sulfur ions
|journal=Physica Status Solidi B
|year=2008|volume=245
|issue=9|pages=1858–1864
|url=http://www.mariobirkholz.de/pssb2008.pdf
|doi=10.1002/pssb.200879532|bibcode = 2008PSSBR.245.1858B }}&lt;/ref--&gt;

&lt;ref name=osu2007&gt;{{cite web
|author=Staff
|year=2007
|url=http://oregonstate.edu/terra/2007/02/small-miracles/
|title=Small Miracles: Harnessing nanotechnology
|publisher=Oregon State University
|accessdate=7 January 2007
|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110521145107/http://oregonstate.edu/terra/2007/02/small-miracles/
|archive-date=21 May 2011
|url-status=live
}} – describes the width of a human hair as {{val|e=5|u=nm}} and 10 carbon atoms as spanning 1&amp;nbsp;nm.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=splung&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.splung.com/content/sid/5/page/radioactivity |title=Radioactivity |publisher=Splung.com |accessdate=19 December 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20071204135150/http://www.splung.com/content/sid/5/page/radioactivity| archivedate= 4 December 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=firestone20000522&gt;{{cite web|last=Firestone |first=Richard B. |date=22 May 2000 |url=http://isotopes.lbl.gov/education/decmode.html |title=Radioactive Decay Modes |publisher=Berkeley Laboratory |accessdate=7 January 2007 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060929111801/http://isotopes.lbl.gov/education/decmode.html |archivedate=29 September 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=hornak2006&gt;{{cite web |last=Hornak|first=J.P.|year=2006 |url=http://www.cis.rit.edu/htbooks/nmr/chap-3/chap-3.htm |title=Chapter 3: Spin Physics|website=The Basics of NMR |publisher=Rochester Institute of Technology |accessdate=7 January 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070203044312/http://www.cis.rit.edu/htbooks/nmr/chap-3/chap-3.htm| archivedate= 3 February 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=goebel20070901&gt;{{cite web |last=Goebel |first=Greg |date=1 September 2007 |url=http://www.vectorsite.net/tpqm_04.html |title=&lt;nowiki&gt;[4.3]&lt;/nowiki&gt; Magnetic Properties of the Atom |website=Elementary Quantum Physics |publisher=In The Public Domain website |accessdate=7 January 2007 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110629143026/http://www.vectorsite.net/tpqm_04.html |archive-date=29 June 2011 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=yarris1997&gt;{{cite journal |last=Yarris|first=Lynn|title=Talking Pictures |journal=Berkeley Lab Research Review |date=Spring 1997 |url=http://www.lbl.gov/Science-Articles/Research-Review/Magazine/1997/story1.html |accessdate=9 January 2008 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080113104939/http://www.lbl.gov/Science-Articles/Research-Review/Magazine/1997/story1.html| archivedate= 13 January 2008 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=zeghbroeck1998&gt;{{cite web
 |last=Zeghbroeck
 |first=Bart J. Van
 |year=1998
 |url=http://physics.ship.edu/~mrc/pfs/308/semicon_book/eband2.htm
 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20050115030639/http://physics.ship.edu/~mrc/pfs/308/semicon_book/eband2.htm
 |url-status=dead
 |archive-date=15 January 2005
 |title=Energy levels
 |publisher=Shippensburg University
 |accessdate=23 December 2007
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=martin2007&gt;{{cite web |last=Martin|first=W.C. |author2=Wiese, W.L.|date=May 2007 |url=http://physics.nist.gov/Pubs/AtSpec/ |title=Atomic Spectroscopy: A Compendium of Basic Ideas, Notation, Data, and Formulas |publisher=National Institute of Standards and Technology |accessdate=8 January 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070208113156/http://physics.nist.gov/Pubs/AtSpec/| archivedate= 8 February 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=avogadro&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.avogadro.co.uk/light/bohr/spectra.htm |title=Atomic Emission Spectra – Origin of Spectral Lines |publisher=Avogadro Web Site |accessdate=10 August 2006 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060228231025/http://www.avogadro.co.uk/light/bohr/spectra.htm |archivedate=28 February 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=fitzpatrick20070216&gt;{{cite web |last=Fitzpatrick |first=Richard |date=16 February 2007 |url=http://farside.ph.utexas.edu/teaching/qm/lectures/node55.html |title=Fine structure |publisher=University of Texas at Austin |accessdate=14 February 2008 |archive-url=https://www.webcitation.org/616Q9bw2M?url=http://farside.ph.utexas.edu/teaching/qm/lectures/node55.html |archive-date=21 August 2011 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=weiss2001&gt;{{cite web |last=Weiss|first=Michael|year=2001 |url=http://math.ucr.edu/home/baez/spin/node8.html |title=The Zeeman Effect |publisher=University of California-Riverside |accessdate=6 February 2008 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080202143147/http://math.ucr.edu/home/baez/spin/node8.html| archivedate= 2 February 2008 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=watkins_sjsu&gt;{{cite web |last=Watkins |first=Thayer |url=http://www.sjsu.edu/faculty/watkins/stimem.htm |title=Coherence in Stimulated Emission |publisher=San José State University |accessdate=23 December 2007 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080112234014/http://www.sjsu.edu/faculty/watkins/stimem.htm| archivedate= 12 January 2008 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=reusch20070716&gt;{{cite web|last=Reusch |first=William |date=16 July 2007 |url=http://www.cem.msu.edu/~reusch/VirtualText/intro1.htm |title=Virtual Textbook of Organic Chemistry |publisher=Michigan State University |accessdate=11 January 2008 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071029211245/http://www.cem.msu.edu/~reusch/VirtualText/intro1.htm |archivedate=29 October 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=chemguide&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.chemguide.co.uk/atoms/bonding/covalent.html |title=Covalent bonding – Single bonds |publisher=chemguide |year=2000 |access-date=20 November 2008 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081101203444/http://www.chemguide.co.uk/atoms/bonding/covalent.html |archive-date=1 November 2008 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=husted20031211&gt;{{cite web |last=Husted | first=Robert |date=11 December 2003 |url=http://periodic.lanl.gov/default.htm |title=Periodic Table of the Elements |publisher=Los Alamos National Laboratory |accessdate=11 January 2008 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080110103232/http://periodic.lanl.gov/default.htm| archivedate= 10 January 2008 | url-status= live|display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=baum2003&gt;{{cite magazine |first=Rudy |last=Baum |year=2003 |url=http://pubs.acs.org/cen/80th/elements.html |title=It's Elemental: The Periodic Table |magazine=Chemical &amp; Engineering News |accessdate=11 January 2008 |archive-url=https://www.webcitation.org/616QCRYK8?url=http://pubs.acs.org/cen/80th/elements.html |archive-date=21 August 2011 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=pu49_7_719&gt;{{cite journal |last=Brazhkin|first=Vadim V. |title=Metastable phases, phase transformations, and phase diagrams in physics and chemistry |journal=Physics-Uspekhi |year=2006|volume=49 |issue=7|pages=719–724 |doi=10.1070/PU2006v049n07ABEH006013 |bibcode = 2006PhyU...49..719B }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=nist_bec&gt;{{cite news |author=Staff|date=9 October 2001 |title=Bose-Einstein Condensate: A New Form of Matter |publisher=National Institute of Standards and Technology |url=https://www.nist.gov/public_affairs/releases/bec_background.cfm |accessdate=16 January 2008| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080103192918/https://www.nist.gov/public_affairs/releases/BEC_background.htm| archivedate= 3 January 2008 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=colton_fyffe1999&gt;{{cite web |last=Colton|first=Imogen|author2=Fyffe, Jeanette
|date=3 February 1999 |url=http://www.ph.unimelb.edu.au/~ywong/poster/articles/bec.html |title=Super Atoms from Bose-Einstein Condensation |publisher=The University of Melbourne |accessdate=6 February 2008| archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070829200820/http://www.ph.unimelb.edu.au/~ywong/poster/articles/bec.html| archivedate = 29 August 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=jacox1997&gt;{{cite web |last=Jacox|first=Marilyn|author2=Gadzuk, J. William |url=http://physics.nist.gov/GenInt/STM/stm.html |title=Scanning Tunneling Microscope |publisher=National Institute of Standards and Technology |date=November 1997|accessdate=11 January 2008 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080107133132/http://physics.nist.gov/GenInt/STM/stm.html| archivedate= 7 January 2008 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=nf_physics1986&gt;{{cite web |url=http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/physics/laureates/1986/index.html |title=The Nobel Prize in Physics 1986 |publisher=The Nobel Foundation |accessdate=11 January 2008 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080917103215/http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/physics/laureates/1986/index.html |archive-date=17 September 2008 |url-status=live }} – in particular, see the Nobel lecture by G. Binnig and H. Rohrer.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=sab53_13_1739&gt;{{cite journal |first=N.|last=Jakubowski |title = Sector field mass spectrometers in ICP-MS |journal = Spectrochimica Acta Part B: Atomic Spectroscopy |volume = 53|issue = 13|year = 1998 |doi=10.1016/S0584-8547(98)00222-5|pages = 1739–1763|bibcode = 1998AcSpe..53.1739J |last2=Moens |first2=Luc |last3=Vanhaecke |first3=Frank }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=rsi39_1_83&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Müller |first1=Erwin W. |authorlink1=Erwin Wilhelm Müller |last2=Panitz |first2=John A. |authorlink2=J.A. Panitz |last3=McLane |first3=S. Brooks |authorlink3=S. Brooks McLane |year=1968 |title=The Atom-Probe Field Ion Microscope |journal=[[Review of Scientific Instruments]] |volume=39 |issue=1 |pages=83–86 |doi=10.1063/1.1683116
|bibcode = 1968RScI...39...83M }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=lochner2007&gt;{{cite web |last=Lochner|first=Jim |author2=Gibb, Meredith|author3= Newman, Phil |date=30 April 2007 |url=http://imagine.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/science/how_l1/spectral_what.html |title=What Do Spectra Tell Us? |publisher=NASA/Goddard Space Flight Center |accessdate=3 January 2008| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080116035542/http://imagine.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/science/how_l1/spectral_what.html| archivedate= 16 January 2008 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=winter2007&gt;{{cite web |last=Winter|first=Mark|year=2007 |url=http://www.webelements.com/webelements/elements/text/He/hist.html |title=Helium|publisher=WebElements |accessdate=3 January 2008| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20071230182148/http://www.webelements.com/webelements/elements/text/He/hist.html| archivedate= 30 December 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=hinshaw20060210&gt;{{cite web |last=Hinshaw|first=Gary |date=10 February 2006 |url=http://map.gsfc.nasa.gov/m_uni/uni_101matter.html |title=What is the Universe Made Of? |publisher=NASA/WMAP|accessdate=7 January 2008| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20071231143948/http://map.gsfc.nasa.gov/m_uni/uni_101matter.html| archivedate= 31 December 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=science259_5093_327&gt;{{cite journal |last=Davidsen|first=Arthur F. |title=Far-Ultraviolet Astronomy on the Astro-1 Space Shuttle Mission |journal=[[Science (journal)|Science]] |year=1993|volume=259 |issue=5093|pages=327–334 |doi=10.1126/science.259.5093.327 |pmid=17832344|bibcode = 1993Sci...259..327D }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=nigel2000&gt;{{cite web |first=Nigel|last=Smith|date=6 January 2000 |url=http://physicsworld.com/cws/article/print/809 |title=The search for dark matter |publisher=Physics World|accessdate = 14 February 2008| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080216185952/http://physicsworld.com/cws/article/print/809| archivedate= 16 February 2008 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=ns1794_42&gt;{{cite journal|last=Croswell |first=Ken |title=Boron, bumps and the Big Bang: Was matter spread evenly when the Universe began? Perhaps not; the clues lie in the creation of the lighter elements such as boron and beryllium |journal=New Scientist |year=1991 |issue=1794 |page=42 |url=https://www.newscientist.com/article/mg13217944.700-boron-bumps-and-the-big-bang-was-matter-spread-evenly-whenthe-universe-began-perhaps-not-the-clues-lie-in-the-creation-of-thelighter-elements-such-as-boron-and-beryllium.html |accessdate=14 January 2008 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080207065342/http://space.newscientist.com/article/mg13217944.700-boron-bumps-and-the-big-bang-was-matter-spread-evenly-whenthe-universe-began-perhaps-not-the-clues-lie-in-the-creation-of-thelighter-elements-such-as-boron-and-beryllium.html |archivedate=7 February 2008 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=science267_5195_192&gt;{{cite journal |last=Copi |first=Craig J. |last2=Schramm |first2=DN |last3=Turner |first3=MS |year=1995 |title=Big-Bang Nucleosynthesis and the Baryon Density of the Universe |journal=[[Science (journal)|Science]] |volume=267 |issue=5195 |pages=192–199 |doi=10.1126/science.7809624 |pmid=7809624 |arxiv=astro-ph/9407006 |bibcode=1995Sci...267..192C |url=http://cds.cern.ch/record/265576 |type=Submitted manuscript |access-date=27 July 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190814070006/http://cds.cern.ch/record/265576 |archive-date=14 August 2019 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=hinshaw20051215&gt;{{cite web |last=Hinshaw|first=Gary|date=15 December 2005 |url=http://map.gsfc.nasa.gov/m_uni/uni_101bbtest2.html |title=Tests of the Big Bang: The Light Elements |publisher=NASA/WMAP|accessdate=13 January 2008 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080117021252/http://map.gsfc.nasa.gov/m_uni/uni_101bbtest2.html| archivedate= 17 January 2008 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=abbott20070530&gt;{{cite web|last=Abbott |first=Brian |date=30 May 2007 |url=http://www.haydenplanetarium.org/universe/duguide/exgg_wmap.php |title=Microwave (WMAP) All-Sky Survey |publisher=Hayden Planetarium |accessdate=13 January 2008 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130213023246/http://www.haydenplanetarium.org/universe/duguide/exgg_wmap.php |archivedate=13 February 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=mnras106_343&gt;{{cite journal |title=The synthesis of the elements from hydrogen |first=F. |last=Hoyle |journal=[[Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society]] |volume=106|issue=5 |pages=343–383|year=1946 |bibcode=1946MNRAS.106..343H |doi=10.1093/mnras/106.5.343}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=nature405_656&gt;{{cite journal |last=Knauth|first=D.C. |title=Newly synthesized lithium in the interstellar medium |journal=[[Nature (journal)|Nature]] |year=2000|volume=405|pages=656–658 |doi=10.1038/35015028 |last2=Knauth|first2=D.C. |last3=Lambert|first3=David L. |last4=Crane|first4=P. |pmid=10864316 |issue=6787|bibcode = 2000Natur.405..656K }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=mashnik2000&gt;{{cite arXiv |last=Mashnik|first=Stepan G. |title=On Solar System and Cosmic Rays Nucleosynthesis and Spallation Processes |eprint=astro-ph/0008382 |year=2000 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=kgs20050504&gt;{{cite web |author=Kansas Geological Survey |date=4 May 2005 |title=Age of the Earth |url=http://www.kgs.ku.edu/Extension/geotopics/earth_age.html |publisher=University of Kansas |accessdate=14 January 2008 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080705052359/http://www.kgs.ku.edu/Extension/geotopics/earth_age.html |archive-date=5 July 2008 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=gs190_1_205&gt;{{cite journal |last=Dalrymple |first=G. Brent |title=The age of the Earth in the twentieth century: a problem (mostly) solved |journal=Geological Society, London, Special Publications |year=2001 |volume=190 |issue=1 |pages=205–221 |doi=10.1144/GSL.SP.2001.190.01.14 |url=http://sp.lyellcollection.org/cgi/content/abstract/190/1/205 |accessdate=14 January 2008 |bibcode=2001GSLSP.190..205D |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071111141237/http://sp.lyellcollection.org/cgi/content/abstract/190/1/205 |archive-date=11 November 2007 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=anderson_foulger_meibom2006&gt;{{cite web |last=Anderson|first=Don L. |authorlink=Don L. Anderson |author2=Foulger, G.R.|author3= Meibom, Anders |date=2 September 2006 |url=http://www.mantleplumes.org/HeliumFundamentals.html |title=Helium: Fundamental models |publisher=MantlePlumes.org|accessdate=14 January 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070208194933/http://www.mantleplumes.org/HeliumFundamentals.html| archivedate= 8 February 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=pennicott2001&gt;{{cite news |last=Pennicott|first=Katie|date=10 May 2001 |title=Carbon clock could show the wrong time |publisher=PhysicsWeb |url=http://physicsworld.com/cws/article/news/2676 |accessdate=14 January 2008| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20071215103132/http://physicsworld.com/cws/article/news/2676| archivedate= 15 December 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=yarris2001&gt;{{cite news |last=Yarris |first=Lynn |date=27 July 2001 |title=New Superheavy Elements 118 and 116 Discovered at Berkeley Lab |publisher=Berkeley Lab |url=http://enews.lbl.gov/Science-Articles/Archive/elements-116-118.html |accessdate=14 January 2008 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080109103538/http://enews.lbl.gov/Science-Articles/Archive/elements-116-118.html |archivedate=9 January 2008 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=pr119_6_2000&gt;{{cite journal |author=Diamond, H |year=1960 |title=Heavy Isotope Abundances in Mike Thermonuclear Device |journal=[[Physical Review]] |volume=119 |issue=6 |pages=2000–2004 |doi=10.1103/PhysRev.119.2000 |bibcode = 1960PhRv..119.2000D |display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=poston1998&gt;{{cite magazine |author1=Poston Sr. |author2=John W. |date=23 March 1998 |title=Do transuranic elements such as plutonium ever occur naturally? |magazine=Scientific American |url=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/do-transuranic-elements-s/ |access-date=1 May 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150327001605/http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/do-transuranic-elements-s/ |archive-date=27 March 2015 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=cz97_10_522&gt;{{cite journal |last=Keller|first=C. |title=Natural occurrence of lanthanides, actinides, and superheavy elements |journal=Chemiker Zeitung |year=1973|volume=97|issue=10|pages=522–530 |osti=4353086 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=ofr_cut&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oklo.curtin.edu.au/index.cfm |title=Oklo Fossil Reactors |publisher=Curtin University of Technology |accessdate=15 January 2008 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071218194159/http://www.oklo.curtin.edu.au/index.cfm |archivedate=18 December 2007 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=weisenberger&gt;{{cite web |last=Weisenberger |first=Drew |url=http://education.jlab.org/qa/mathatom_05.html |title=How many atoms are there in the world? |publisher=Jefferson Lab |accessdate=16 January 2008 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071022185850/http://education.jlab.org/qa/mathatom_05.html |archive-date=22 October 2007 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=pidwirnyf&gt;{{cite web |last=Pidwirny|first=Michael |url=http://www.physicalgeography.net/fundamentals/contents.html |title=Fundamentals of Physical Geography |publisher=University of British Columbia Okanagan |accessdate=16 January 2008 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080121080709/http://www.physicalgeography.net/fundamentals/contents.html| archivedate= 21 January 2008 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=pnas99_22_13966&gt;{{cite journal |last=Anderson|first=Don L. |title=The inner inner core of Earth |journal=[[Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences]] |year=2002|volume=99|issue=22|pages=13966–13968 |doi=10.1073/pnas.232565899 |pmid=12391308 |pmc=137819|bibcode = 2002PNAS...9913966A }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=cern28509&gt;{{cite journal |title=Second postcard from the island of stability |author=Anonymous|journal=CERN Courier |date=2 October 2001 |url=http://cerncourier.com/cws/article/cern/28509 |accessdate=14 January 2008| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080203031237/http://cerncourier.com/cws/article/cern/28509| archivedate= 3 February 2008 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=cen84_10_19&gt;{{cite journal |last=Jacoby|first=Mitch |title=As-yet-unsynthesized superheavy atom should form a stable diatomic molecule with fluorine |journal=[[Chemical &amp; Engineering News]] |year=2006|volume=84|issue=10|page=19 |doi=10.1021/cen-v084n010.p019a }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=koppes1999&gt;{{cite news |last=Koppes |first=Steve |date=1 March 1999 |title=Fermilab Physicists Find New Matter-Antimatter Asymmetry |publisher=University of Chicago |url=http://www-news.uchicago.edu/releases/99/990301.ktev.shtml |accessdate=14 January 2008 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080719211849/http://www-news.uchicago.edu/releases/99/990301.ktev.shtml |archive-date=19 July 2008 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=cromie20010816&gt;{{cite web |last=Cromie |first=William J. |date=16 August 2001 |title=A lifetime of trillionths of a second: Scientists explore antimatter |website=Harvard University Gazette |url=http://news.harvard.edu/gazette/2001/08.16/antimatter.html |accessdate=14 January 2008 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060903172020/http://www.news.harvard.edu/gazette/2001/08.16/antimatter.html |archive-date=3 September 2006 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=nature419_6906_439&gt;{{cite journal |last=Hijmans|first=Tom W. |title=Particle physics: Cold antihydrogen |journal=[[Nature (journal)|Nature]] |year=2002|volume=419 |pages=439–440|doi=10.1038/419439a
|pmid=12368837 |issue=6906 |bibcode = 2002Natur.419..439H |doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=BBC20021030&gt;{{cite news|author=Staff|date=30 October 2002|title=Researchers 'look inside' antimatter|work=BBC News|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/science/nature/2375717.stm|accessdate=14 January 2008|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070222204339/http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/science/nature/2375717.stm|archive-date=22 February 2007|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=ns1728_77&gt;{{cite journal|last=Barrett |first=Roger |title=The Strange World of the Exotic Atom |journal=New Scientist |year=1990 |issue=1728 |pages=77–115 |url=http://media.newscientist.com/article/mg12717284.600-the-strange-world-of-the-exotic-atom-physicists-can-nowmake-atoms-and-molecules-containing-negative-particles-other-than-electronsand-use-them-not-just-to-test-theories-but-also-to-fight-cancer-.html |accessdate=4 January 2008 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071221164440/http://media.newscientist.com/article/mg12717284.600-the-strange-world-of-the-exotic-atom-physicists-can-nowmake-atoms-and-molecules-containing-negative-particles-other-than-electronsand-use-them-not-just-to-test-theories-but-also-to-fight-cancer-.html |archivedate=21 December 2007 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=psT112_1_20&gt;{{cite journal|last=Indelicato|first=Paul|title=Exotic Atoms|journal=[[Physica Scripta]]|year=2004|volume=T112|issue=1|pages=20–26|doi=10.1238/Physica.Topical.112a00020|arxiv=physics/0409058|bibcode=2004PhST..112...20I|url=https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00002825|access-date=4 November 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181104170051/https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00002825|archive-date=4 November 2018|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=ripin1998&gt;{{cite web |last=Ripin|first=Barrett H.|date=July 1998 |url=http://www.aps.org/publications/apsnews/199807/experiment.cfm.html |archive-url=https://archive.today/20120723135110/http://www.aps.org/publications/apsnews/199807/experiment.cfm.html |url-status=dead |archive-date=2012-07-23 |title=Recent Experiments on Exotic Atoms |publisher=American Physical Society |accessdate=15 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

==Bibliography==
*{{cite book
|last=Manuel|first=Oliver|year=2001
|title=Origin of Elements in the Solar System: Implications of Post-1957 Observations
|publisher=Springer|isbn=978-0-306-46562-8
|oclc=228374906|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |author=Andrew G. van Melsen |translator=Henry J. Koren |year=1960 |orig-year=First published 1952 |title=From Atomos to Atom: The History of the Concept Atom |publisher=Dover Publications |isbn=0-486-49584-1 |ref=refMelsen1952}}
*{{cite book |author=J. P. Millington |year=1906 |title=John Dalton |publisher=J. M. Dent &amp; Co. (London); E. P. Dutton &amp; Co. (New York) |url=https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.30924/ |ref=refMillington1906}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book
|last=Dalton|first=J. |authorlink=John Dalton|year=1808
|title=A New System of Chemical Philosophy, Part 1
|publisher=S. Russell
|location=London and Manchester}}
* {{cite book
|last=Gangopadhyaya|first=Mrinalkanti
|title=Indian Atomism: History and Sources
|publisher=Humanities Press|year=1981
|location=Atlantic Highlands, New Jersey
|isbn=978-0-391-02177-8
|oclc=10916778}}
* {{cite book
|last=Harrison|first=Edward Robert|year=2003
|title=Masks of the Universe: Changing Ideas on the Nature of the Cosmos
|publisher=Cambridge University Press
|isbn=978-0-521-77351-5
|oclc=50441595}}
* {{cite book
|last=Iannone|first=A. Pablo|year=2001
|title=Dictionary of World Philosophy
|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0-415-17995-9
|oclc=44541769}}
* {{cite book
|last=King|first=Richard|year=1999
|title=Indian philosophy: an introduction to Hindu and Buddhist thought
|publisher=Edinburgh University Press
|isbn=978-0-7486-0954-3}}
* {{cite book
|last=Levere|first=Trevor, H.|year=2001
|title=Transforming Matter – A History of Chemistry for Alchemy to the Buckyball
|publisher=The Johns Hopkins University Press
|isbn=978-0-8018-6610-4}}
* &lt;!--&lt;ref name=liddell_scott_to_cut&gt;--&gt;{{cite web|author1=Liddell, Henry George |author2=Scott, Robert |title=A Greek-English Lexicon|publisher=Perseus Digital Library|url=http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0057%3Aentry%3Dte%2Fmnw1}}&lt;!--&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;
* &lt;!--&lt;ref name=liddell_scott_uncuttable&gt;--&gt;{{cite web|author1=Liddell, Henry George |author2=Scott, Robert |title=ἄτομος|website=A Greek-English Lexicon|publisher=Perseus Digital Library|url=http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0057%3Aentry%3Da%29%2Ftomos|accessdate=21 June 2010}}&lt;!--&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;
* {{cite book
|last=McEvilley|first=Thomas
|title=The shape of ancient thought: comparative studies in Greek and Indian philosophies
|publisher=Allworth Press|year=2002
|isbn=978-1-58115-203-6}}
* {{cite book
|last=Moran|first=Bruce T.|year=2005
|title=Distilling Knowledge: Alchemy, Chemistry, and the Scientific Revolution
|publisher=[[Harvard University Press]]
|isbn=978-0-674-01495-4}}
* {{cite book
|last=Ponomarev|first=Leonid Ivanovich|year=1993
|title=The Quantum Dice|publisher=CRC Press
|isbn=978-0-7503-0251-7
|oclc=26853108}}
* {{cite book
|last=Roscoe|first=Henry Enfield|year=1895
|authorlink=Henry Enfield Roscoe
|title=John Dalton and the Rise of Modern Chemistry
|series=Century science series
|url=https://archive.org/details/bub_gb_FJMEAAAAYAAJ
|accessdate=3 April 2011|publisher=Macmillan
|location=New York}}
* {{cite book
|last=Siegfried|first=Robert|year=2002
|title=From Elements to Atoms: A History of Chemical Composition
|publisher=DIANE|isbn=978-0-87169-924-4
|oclc=186607849}}
* {{cite book
|last=Teresi|first=Dick|publisher = Simon &amp; Schuster
|title=Lost Discoveries: The Ancient Roots of Modern Science
|year=2003|isbn=978-0-7432-4379-7
|url=https://books.google.com/?id=pheL_ubbXD0C&amp;dq
|pages=213–214}}
* {{cite book
|author=Various|editor=Lide, David R.|year=2002
|title=Handbook of Chemistry &amp; Physics
|edition=88th|publisher=CRC
|url=http://www.hbcpnetbase.com/
|accessdate=23 May 2008|isbn=978-0-8493-0486-6
|oclc=179976746
| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080523110822/http://www.hbcpnetbase.com/| archivedate= 23 May 2008 | url-status= live}}
* {{cite book
|last=Wurtz|first=Charles Adolphe|year=1881
|title=The Atomic Theory
|publisher=D. Appleton and company
|location=New York
|isbn=978-0-559-43636-9}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Sister project links|voy=no|wikt=atom|v=The Atom|n=no|q=Atom|s=The New Student's Reference Work}}
* {{Cite web|url=https://history.aip.org/exhibits/electron/jjhome.htm|title=A Look Inside the Atom|publisher=American Institute of Physics|access-date=2018-04-13|date=2018}}
* {{cite web|first=Tim|last=Sharp|title=What is an Atom?|url=https://www.livescience.com/37206-atom-definition.html|publisher=Live Science|accessdate=13 April 2018|date=8 August 2017}}
* {{cite web
|author=Anonymous|date=3 January 2006
|title=Hitchhikers Guide to the Universe, Atoms and Atomic Structure|website=[[h2g2]]|publisher=BBC| url = https://h2g2.com/edited_entry/A6672963|access-date=13 April 2018}}
* {{cite web
|author=Various|date=3 January 2006|url=http://www.colorado.edu/physics/2000/index.pl?Type=TOC
|title=Physics 2000, Table of Contents
|publisher=University of Colorado|accessdate=11 January 2008| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080114002007/http://www.colorado.edu/physics/2000/index.pl?Type=TOC| archivedate= 14 January 2008 | url-status= live}}
* {{cite web
|author=Various|date=3 February 2006|url=http://www.hydrogenlab.de/elektronium/HTML/einleitung_hauptseite_uk.html
|title=What does an atom look like?
|publisher=University of Karlsruhe|accessdate=12 May 2008}}


{{particles}}
{{composition}}
{{Branches of chemistry}}
{{biological organisation}}
{{featured article}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Atoms| ]]
[[Category:Chemistry]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]</text>
      <sha1>rgez9th9stka5lkfnnkd4ypeibyugjo</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
