  <page>
    <title>Anxiety</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>922</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941802978</id>
      <parentid>941801837</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-20T19:51:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Slywriter</username>
        <id>14494991</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Vandalism. Undid revision 941801837 by [[Special:Contributions/66.146.221.93|66.146.221.93]] ([[User talk:66.146.221.93|talk]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{Redirect|Misgiving|the band|Misgiving (band)}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=February 2020}}{{Emotion}}
'''Anxiety''' is an [[emotion]] characterized by an unpleasant state of inner [[wikt:turmoil|turmoil]], often accompanied by nervous behaviour such as pacing back and forth, [[Somatic anxiety|somatic complaints]], and [[Rumination (psychology)|rumination]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Seligman&quot;&gt;{{cite book | vauthors = Seligman ME, Walker EF, Rosenhan DL |author3-link= David Rosenhan |author1-link= Martin Seligman |title= Abnormal psychology |edition= 4th |location= New York |publisher= W.W. Norton &amp; Company}}{{Page needed|date= May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is the subjectively unpleasant feelings of dread over [[Anticipation|anticipated]] events.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Abnormal Psychology|last=Davison|first=Gerald C.|publisher=Veronica Visentin|year=2008|isbn=978-0-470-84072-6|location=Toronto|page=154|name-list-format=vanc}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{qn|date=November 2018}}

Anxiety is a feeling of uneasiness and [[worry]], usually generalized and unfocused as an [[overreaction]] to a situation that is only subjectively seen as menacing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=E_9Rlqs4T7oC|title=Psychiatric and Behavioral Disorders in Intellectual and Developmental Disabilities|vauthors=Bouras N, Holt G|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2007|isbn=9781139461306|edition=2nd}}{{Page needed|date=May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is often accompanied by muscular tension,&lt;ref name=&quot;DSM-5 189&quot; /&gt; restlessness, [[Fatigue (medical)|fatigue]] and problems in concentration. Normally considered to be appropriate, when anxiety is experienced regularly the individual may suffer from an [[anxiety disorder]].&lt;ref name=&quot;DSM-5 189&quot; /&gt; Anxiety is closely related to [[fear]], which is a response to a real or perceived immediate [[threat]]; anxiety involves the expectation of future threat.&lt;ref name=&quot;DSM-5 189&quot;&gt;{{Cite book | last= American Psychiatric Association | year= 2013 | title= Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders | edition =Fifth | publisher= American Psychiatric Publishing | location= Arlington, VA | page= 189 | isbn = 978-0-89042-555-8 }}&lt;/ref&gt; People facing anxiety may withdraw from situations which have provoked anxiety in the past.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker, P. 2003&quot;&gt;{{cite book | vauthors = Barker P |year= 2003 |title= Psychiatric and Mental Health Nursing: The Craft of Caring |publisher= Edward Arnold |location= London 0|isbn= 978-0-340-81026-2}}{{Page needed|date= May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Anxiety vs. fear==
[[File:Los Angeles, California. Lockheed Employment. A worried applicant waiting to be interviewed - NARA - 532210.tif|thumb|right|A job applicant with a worried facial expression]]
Anxiety is distinguished from [[fear]], which is an appropriate cognitive and emotional response to a perceived threat.&lt;ref&gt;[[Andreas Dorschel]], ''Furcht und Angst.'' In: Dietmar Goltschnigg (ed.), ''Angst. Lähmender Stillstand und Motor des Fortschritts.'' Stauffenburg, Tübingen 2012, pp. 49–54&lt;/ref&gt; Anxiety is related to the specific behaviors of [[fight-or-flight response]]s, defensive behavior or escape. It occurs in situations only perceived as uncontrollable or unavoidable, but not realistically so.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Handbook of emotions|last=Öhman|first=Arne|publisher=The Guilford Press|year=2000|isbn=978-1-57230-529-8|editor1-last=Lewis|editor1-first=Michael|location=New York|pages=[https://archive.org/details/handbookofemotio0000unse/page/573 573–93]|chapter=Fear and anxiety: Evolutionary, cognitive, and clinical perspectives|name-list-format=vanc|editor2-last=Haviland-Jones|editor2-first=Jeannette M.|chapter-url=https://archive.org/details/handbookofemotio0000unse/page/573}}&lt;/ref&gt; David Barlow defines anxiety as &quot;a future-oriented mood state in which one is not ready or prepared to attempt to [[Coping (psychology)|cope]] with upcoming negative events,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Barlow DH|date=November 2000|title=Unraveling the mysteries of anxiety and its disorders from the perspective of emotion theory|journal=The American Psychologist|volume=55|issue=11|pages=1247–63|doi=10.1037/0003-066X.55.11.1247|pmid=11280938}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that it is a distinction between future and present dangers which divides anxiety and fear. Another description of anxiety is agony, dread, terror, or even apprehension.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Iacovou |first1=Susan |year=2011 |title=What is the difference between existential anxiety and so called neurotic anxiety? 'The sine qua non of true vitality' an examination of the difference between existential anxiety and neurotic anxiety |journal=Existential Analysis |volume=22 |issue=2 |id={{Gale|A288874227}} }}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[positive psychology]], anxiety is described as the mental state that results from a difficult challenge for which the subject has insufficient [[Coping (psychology)|coping]] skills.&lt;ref name=&quot;Finding Flow&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Finding Flow|url=https://archive.org/details/findingflowpsych00csik|url-access=registration|last=Csíkszentmihályi|first=Mihály|year=1997|name-list-format=vanc|authorlink=Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi}}{{Page needed|date=May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Fear and anxiety can be differentiated in four domains: (1) duration of emotional experience, (2) temporal focus, (3) specificity of the threat, and (4) motivated direction. Fear is short lived, present focused, geared towards a specific threat, and facilitating escape from threat; anxiety, on the other hand, is long-acting, future focused, broadly focused towards a diffuse threat, and promoting excessive caution while approaching a potential threat and interferes with constructive coping.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Sylvers P, Lilienfeld SO, LaPrairie JL|date=February 2011|title=Differences between trait fear and trait anxiety: implications for psychopathology|journal=Clinical Psychology Review|volume=31|issue=1|pages=122–37|doi=10.1016/j.cpr.2010.08.004|pmid=20817337}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Joseph E. LeDoux]] and [[Lisa Feldman Barrett]] have both sought to separate automatic threat responses from additional associated cognitive activity within anxiety.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://brainworldmagazine.com/on-fear-emotions-and-memory-an-interview-with-dr-joseph-ledoux/|title=On Fear, Emotions, and Memory: An Interview with Dr. Joseph LeDoux |last=Emory|first=Margaret|date=June 7, 2018|website=Brain World|language=en-US|access-date=September 11, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Barrett |first1=Lisa Feldman |title=The theory of constructed emotion: an active inference account of interoception and categorization |journal=Social Cognitive and Affective Neuroscience |volume=12 |issue=1 |date=October 19, 2016 |pages=1–23 |doi=10.1093/scan/nsw154 |pmid=27798257 |pmc=5390700 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Symptoms==
Anxiety can be experienced with long, drawn out daily symptoms that reduce quality of life, known as chronic (or generalized) anxiety, or it can be experienced in short spurts with sporadic, stressful [[panic attack]]s, known as acute anxiety.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Rynn MA, Brawman-Mintzer O | title = Generalized anxiety disorder: acute and chronic treatment | journal = CNS Spectrums | volume = 9 | issue = 10 | pages = 716–23 | date = October 2004 | pmid = 15448583 | doi = 10.1017/S1092852900022367 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Symptoms of anxiety can range in number, intensity, and frequency, depending on the person. While almost everyone has experienced anxiety at some point in their lives, most do not develop long-term problems with anxiety.

Anxiety may cause psychiatric and physiological symptoms.&lt;ref name=&quot;WHO2009&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TestaGiannuzzi2013partI&quot; /&gt;

The risk of anxiety leading to depression could possibly even lead to an individual harming themselves, which is why there are many 24-hour suicide prevention hotlines.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.psychguides.com/guides/depression-hotline/|title=Depression Hotline {{!}} Call Our Free, 24 Hour Depression Helpline|work=PsychGuides.com|access-date=October 11, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The behavioral effects of anxiety may include withdrawal from situations which have provoked anxiety or negative feelings in the past.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker, P. 2003&quot; /&gt; Other effects may include changes in sleeping patterns, changes in habits, increase or decrease in food intake, and increased motor tension (such as foot tapping).&lt;ref name=&quot;Barker, P. 2003&quot; /&gt;

The emotional effects of anxiety may include &quot;feelings of apprehension or dread, trouble concentrating, feeling tense or jumpy, anticipating the worst, irritability, restlessness, watching (and waiting) for signs (and occurrences) of danger, and, feeling like your mind's gone blank&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Smith, Melinda (June 2008). Anxiety attacks and disorders: Guide to the signs, symptoms, and treatment options. Retrieved March 3, 2009, from Helpguide Web site: {{cite web|url=http://www.helpguide.org/mental/anxiety_types_symptoms_treatment.htm |title=HelpGuide.org |access-date=March 4, 2009 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090307161028/http://www.helpguide.org/mental/anxiety_types_symptoms_treatment.htm |archive-date=March 7, 2009  }}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as &quot;nightmares/bad dreams, obsessions about sensations, [[déjà vu]], a trapped-in-your-mind feeling, and feeling like everything is scary.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;(1987–2008). Anxiety Symptoms, Anxiety Attack Symptoms (Panic Attack Symptoms), Symptoms of Anxiety. Retrieved March 3, 2009, from Anxiety Centre Website: {{cite web |url=http://www.anxietycentre.com/anxiety-symptoms.shtml |title=Anxiety Symptoms and Signs – over 100 listed |access-date=March 4, 2009 |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090307132218/http://www.anxietycentre.com/anxiety-symptoms.shtml |archive-date=March 7, 2009  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The cognitive effects of anxiety may include thoughts about suspected dangers, such as fear of dying. &quot;You may&amp;nbsp;... fear that the chest pains are a deadly heart attack or that the shooting pains in your head are the result of a tumor or an aneurysm. You feel an intense fear when you think of dying, or you may think of it more often than normal, or can't get it out of your mind.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;(1987–2008). Anxiety symptoms – Fear of dying. Retrieved March 3, 2009, from Anxiety Centre Website: {{cite web |url=http://www.anxietycentre.com/anxiety-symptoms/fear-of-dying.shtml |title=Fear of dying anxiety symptom |access-date=March 4, 2009 |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090305104407/http://www.anxietycentre.com/anxiety-symptoms/fear-of-dying.shtml |archive-date=March 5, 2009  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The physiological symptoms of anxiety may include:&lt;ref name=&quot;WHO2009&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TestaGiannuzzi2013partI&quot; /&gt;

*Neurological, as [[headache]], [[paresthesia]]s, [[fasciculation]]s, [[vertigo]], or [[presyncope]].
*Digestive, as abdominal pain, [[nausea]], [[diarrhea]], [[indigestion]], [[xerostomia|dry mouth]], or [[bolus (digestion)|bolus]].
*Respiratory, as [[shortness of breath]] or sighing breathing.
*Cardiac, as [[palpitations]], [[tachycardia]], or [[chest pain]].
*Muscular, as [[fatigue (medical)|fatigue]], [[tremor]]s, or [[tetany]].
*Cutaneous, as [[perspiration]], or [[itch]]y skin.
*Uro-genital, as [[frequent urination]], [[urinary urgency]], [[dyspareunia]], or [[erectile dysfunction|impotence]], [[chronic pelvic pain syndrome]]. Stress hormones released in an anxious state have an impact on bowel function and can manifest physical symptoms that may contribute to or [[Loss of significance|exacerbate]] [[Irritable bowel syndrome|IBS]].

==Types==
[[File:Edvard Munch - Anxiety - Google Art Project.jpg|thumb|upright|Painting entitled ''[[Anxiety (painting)|Anxiety]]'', 1894, by [[Edvard Munch]]]]

There are various types of anxiety. [[Existential]] anxiety can occur when a person faces [[angst]], an [[existential crisis]], or [[Nihilism|nihilistic]] feelings. People can also face [[mathematical anxiety]], [[somatic anxiety]], [[stage fright]], or [[test anxiety]]. [[Social anxiety]] and [[stranger anxiety]] are caused when people are apprehensive around strangers or other people in general.{{fact|date=December 2019}}

===Existential===
{{Further|Angst|Existential crisis|Nihilism}}

The philosopher [[Søren Kierkegaard]], in ''[[The Concept of Anxiety]]'' (1844), described anxiety or dread associated with the &quot;dizziness of freedom&quot; and suggested the possibility for positive resolution of anxiety through the self-conscious exercise of responsibility and choosing. In ''Art and Artist'' (1932), the psychologist [[Otto Rank]] wrote that the [[psychological trauma]] of birth was the pre-eminent human symbol of existential anxiety and encompasses the creative person's simultaneous fear of – and desire for – separation, individuation, and differentiation.{{fact|date=December 2019}}

The [[theology|theologian]] [[Paul Tillich]] characterized existential anxiety&lt;ref name=&quot;Tillich&quot;&gt;{{cite book |authorlink=Paul Tillich |last=Tillich |first=Paul | name-list-format = vanc |year=1952 |title=The Courage To Be |location=New Haven |publisher=Yale University Press |isbn=978-0-300-08471-9|page=76}}&lt;/ref&gt; as &quot;the state in which a [[being]] is aware of its possible nonbeing&quot; and he listed three categories for the nonbeing and resulting anxiety: ontic (fate and death), [[Morality|moral]] ([[guilt (emotion)|guilt]] and condemnation), and [[Spirituality|spiritual]] (emptiness and [[Meaning (existential)|meaninglessness]]). According to Tillich, the last of these three types of existential anxiety, i.e. spiritual anxiety, is predominant in modern times while the others were predominant in earlier periods. Tillich argues that this anxiety can be [[Acceptance#Self acceptance|accepted]] as part of the [[human condition]] or it can be resisted but with negative consequences. In its pathological form, spiritual anxiety may tend to &quot;drive the person toward the creation of certitude in systems of meaning which are supported by [[tradition]] and [[authority]]&quot; even though such &quot;undoubted certitude is not built on the rock of [[reality]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tillich&quot; /&gt;

According to [[Viktor Frankl]], the author of ''[[Man's Search for Meaning]]'', when a person is faced with extreme mortal dangers, the most basic of all human wishes is to find a [[meaning of life]] to combat the &quot;trauma of nonbeing&quot; as death is near.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Abulof|first1=Uriel | name-list-format = vanc |title=The Mortality and Morality of Nations|date=2015|location=New York|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-1-107-09707-0|page=26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Depending on the source of the threat, psychoanalytic theory distinguishes the following types of anxiety:

* realistic
* neurotic
* moral&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Hjelle |first=Larry |last2=Ziegler |first2=Daniel |date= 1981 |title= Personality Theories: Basic Assumptions, Research, and Applications|url= |location= |publisher=McGraw-Hill |page=494 |isbn= 9780070290631 |author-link= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Test and performance===
&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Educational psychology]] --&gt;
{{Main|Test anxiety|Mathematical anxiety|Stage fright|Somatic anxiety}}
According to [[Yerkes-Dodson law]], an optimal level of arousal is necessary to best complete a task such as an exam, performance, or competitive event. However, when the anxiety or level of arousal exceeds that optimum, the result is a decline in performance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Teigen&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1177/0959354394044004 |title=Yerkes-Dodson: A Law for all Seasons |journal=Theory &amp; Psychology |volume=4 |issue=4 |pages=525–547 |year=1994 |last1=Teigen |first1=Karl Halvor | name-list-format = vanc }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Test anxiety is the uneasiness, apprehension, or nervousness felt by students who have a fear of failing an [[Test (student assessment)|exam]]. Students who have test anxiety may experience any of the following: the association of [[Grade (education)|grades]] with [[Self-esteem|personal worth]]; fear of embarrassment by a teacher; fear of [[Social alienation|alienation]] from parents or friends; time pressures; or feeling a loss of control. Sweating, dizziness, headaches, racing heartbeats, nausea, fidgeting, uncontrollable crying or laughing and drumming on a desk are all common. Because test anxiety hinges on [[fear of negative evaluation]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Liebert&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Liebert RM, Morris LW | title = Cognitive and emotional components of test anxiety: a distinction and some initial data | journal = Psychological Reports | volume = 20 | issue = 3 | pages = 975–8 | date = June 1967 | pmid = 6042522 | doi = 10.2466/pr0.1967.20.3.975 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; debate exists as to whether test anxiety is itself a unique anxiety disorder or whether it is a specific type of social [[phobia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Beidel&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Beidel DC, Turner SM | title = Comorbidity of test anxiety and other anxiety disorders in children | journal = Journal of Abnormal Child Psychology | volume = 16 | issue = 3 | pages = 275–87 | date = June 1988 | pmid = 3403811 | doi = 10.1007/BF00913800 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The DSM-IV classifies test anxiety as a type of social phobia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rapee&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Rapee RM, Heimberg RG | title = A cognitive-behavioral model of anxiety in social phobia | journal = Behaviour Research and Therapy | volume = 35 | issue = 8 | pages = 741–56 | date = August 1997 | pmid = 9256517 | doi = 10.1016/S0005-7967(97)00022-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

While the term &quot;test anxiety&quot; refers specifically to students,&lt;ref name=&quot;Mathur&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |citeseerx=10.1.1.1027.7497 |url=http://medind.nic.in/daa/t11/i2/daat11i2p337.pdf |title=Impact of Hypnotherapy on Examination Anxiety and Scholastic Performance among School |journal=Delhi Psychiatry Journal |year=2011 |volume=14 |issue=2 |pages=337–42 |first1=Shachi |last1=Mathur |first2=Waheeda |last2=Khan | name-list-format = vanc }}&lt;/ref&gt; many workers share the same experience with regard to their career or profession. The fear of failing at a task and being negatively evaluated for failure can have a similarly negative effect on the adult.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Hall-Flavin|first1=Daniel K.| name-list-format = vanc |title=Is it possible to overcome test anxiety?|url=http://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/generalized-anxiety-disorder/expert-answers/test-anxiety/faq-20058195|website=Mayo Clinic|publisher=Mayo Foundation for Medical Education and Research|access-date=August 11, 2015|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150905063635/http://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/generalized-anxiety-disorder/expert-answers/test-anxiety/faq-20058195|archive-date=September 5, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Management of test anxiety focuses on achieving relaxation and developing mechanisms to manage anxiety.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mathur&quot; /&gt;

===Stranger, social, and intergroup anxiety===
{{Main|Stranger anxiety|Social anxiety}}

Humans generally require social acceptance and thus sometimes dread the disapproval of others. Apprehension of being judged by others may cause anxiety in social environments.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |doi=10.1016/B978-0-12-375096-9.00028-6 |chapter=Introduction: Toward an Understanding of Social Anxiety Disorder |title=Social Anxiety |pages=xix–xxvi |year=2010 |last1=Hofmann |first1=Stefan G. |last2=Dibartolo |first2=Patricia M. | name-list-format = vanc |isbn=978-0-12-375096-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Anxiety during social interactions, particularly between strangers, is common among young people. It may persist into adulthood and become social anxiety or social phobia. &quot;[[Stranger anxiety]]&quot; in small children is not considered a phobia. In adults, an excessive fear of other people is not a developmentally common stage; it is called [[social anxiety]]. According to Cutting,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |editor1-first=Ben |editor1-last=Thomas |editor2-first=Sally |editor2-last=Hardy |editor3-first=Penny |editor3-last=Cutting | name-list-format = vanc |year=1997 |title=Mental Health Nursing: Principles and Practice |publisher=Mosby |location=London |isbn=978-0-7234-2590-8}}{{Page needed|date=May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; social phobics do not fear the crowd but the fact that they may be judged negatively.

[[Social anxiety]] varies in degree and severity. For some people, it is characterized by experiencing discomfort or awkwardness during physical social contact (e.g. embracing, shaking hands, etc.), while in other cases it can lead to a fear of interacting with unfamiliar people altogether. Those suffering from this condition may restrict their lifestyles to accommodate the anxiety, minimizing social interaction whenever possible. Social anxiety also forms a core aspect of certain personality disorders, including [[avoidant personality disorder]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Settipani CA, Kendall PC | title = Social functioning in youth with anxiety disorders: association with anxiety severity and outcomes from cognitive-behavioral therapy | journal = Child Psychiatry and Human Development | volume = 44 | issue = 1 | pages = 1–18 | date = February 2013 | pmid = 22581270 | doi = 10.1007/s10578-012-0307-0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

To the extent that a person is fearful of social encounters with unfamiliar others, some people may experience anxiety particularly during interactions with outgroup members, or people who share different group memberships (i.e., by race, ethnicity, class, gender, etc.). Depending on the nature of the antecedent relations, cognitions, and situational factors, intergroup contact may be stressful and lead to feelings of anxiety. This apprehension or fear of contact with outgroup members is often called interracial or intergroup anxiety.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1111/j.1540-4560.1985.tb01134.x |title=Intergroup Anxiety |journal=Journal of Social Issues |volume=41 |issue=3 |pages=157–175 |year=1985 |last1=Stephan |first1=Walter G. |last2=Stephan |first2=Cookie White | name-list-format = vanc }}&lt;/ref&gt;

As is the case the more generalized forms of [[social anxiety]], intergroup anxiety has behavioral, cognitive, and affective effects. For instance, increases in schematic processing and simplified information processing can occur when anxiety is high. Indeed, such is consistent with related work on attentional bias in implicit memory.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Richeson JA, Trawalter S | title = The threat of appearing prejudiced and race-based attentional biases | journal = Psychological Science | volume = 19 | issue = 2 | pages = 98–102 | date = February 2008 | pmid = 18271854 | doi = 10.1111/j.1467-9280.2008.02052.x | url = https://semanticscholar.org/paper/275be33aed596bf8d126796713b77f02be79075e }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Mathews A, Mogg K, May J, Eysenck M | title = Implicit and explicit memory bias in anxiety | journal = Journal of Abnormal Psychology | volume = 98 | issue = 3 | pages = 236–40 | date = August 1989 | pmid = 2768658 | doi = 10.1037/0021-843x.98.3.236 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1016/0191-8869(91)90096-t |title=Effects of encoding and anxiety on implicit and explicit memory performance |journal=Personality and Individual Differences |volume=12 |issue=2 |pages=131–139 |year=1991 |last1=Richards |first1=Anne |last2=French |first2=Christopher C. | name-list-format = vanc }}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally recent research has found that implicit racial evaluations (i.e. automatic prejudiced attitudes) can be amplified during intergroup interaction.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Amodio DM, Hamilton HK | title = Intergroup anxiety effects on implicit racial evaluation and stereotyping | journal = Emotion | volume = 12 | issue = 6 | pages = 1273–80 | date = December 2012 | pmid = 22775128 | doi = 10.1037/a0029016 | citeseerx = 10.1.1.659.5717 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Negative experiences have been illustrated in producing not only negative expectations, but also avoidant, or antagonistic, behavior such as hostility.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Plant EA, Devine PG | title = The antecedents and implications of interracial anxiety | journal = Personality &amp; Social Psychology Bulletin | volume = 29 | issue = 6 | pages = 790–801 | date = June 2003 | pmid = 15189634 | doi = 10.1177/0146167203029006011 | url = https://semanticscholar.org/paper/5ee3912b513201af87160af846871cdff0542ef9 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, when compared to anxiety levels and cognitive effort (e.g., impression management and self-presentation) in intragroup contexts, levels and depletion of resources may be exacerbated in the intergroup situation.

===Trait===
Anxiety can be either a short-term 'state' or a long-term personality &quot;trait&quot;. Trait anxiety reflects a stable tendency across the lifespan of responding with acute, state anxiety in the anticipation of threatening situations (whether they are actually deemed threatening or not).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Anxiety |url=https://macses.ucsf.edu/research/psychosocial/anxiety.php |website=MacArthur SES &amp; Health Network }}&lt;/ref&gt; A meta-analysis showed that a high level of [[neuroticism]] is a risk factor for development of anxiety symptoms and disorders.&lt;ref name=&quot;NeuroticismMA&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Jeronimus BF, Kotov R, Riese H, Ormel J | title = Neuroticism's prospective association with mental disorders halves after adjustment for baseline symptoms and psychiatric history, but the adjusted association hardly decays with time: a meta-analysis on 59 longitudinal/prospective studies with 443 313 participants | journal = Psychological Medicine | volume = 46 | issue = 14 | pages = 2883–2906 | date = October 2016 | pmid = 27523506 | doi = 10.1017/S0033291716001653 | url = https://zenodo.org/record/895885 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Such anxiety may be conscious or unconscious.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | vauthors = Giddey M, Wright H |title=Mental Health Nursing: From first principles to professional practice |publisher=Stanley Thornes}}{{Page needed|date=May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Personality can also be a trait leading towards anxiety and depression. Through experience many find it difficult to collect themselves due to their own personal nature.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.gulfbend.org/poc/view_doc.php?type=doc&amp;id=8948|title=Gulf Bend MHMR Center|access-date=October 11, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Choice or decision ===
Anxiety induced by the need to choose between similar options is increasingly being recognized as a problem for individuals and for organizations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.thesundaytimes.co.uk/sto/style/fashion/trends/article85734.ece |work=The Times |location=London |title=Premium choice anxiety |date=April 27, 2008 |access-date=April 25, 2010 |first1=Jonathan |last1=Downey | name-list-format = vanc |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140203132027/http://www.thesundaytimes.co.uk/sto/style/fashion/trends/article85734.ece |archive-date=February 3, 2014  }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, [[Capgemini]] wrote: &quot;Today we're all faced with greater choice, more competition and less time to consider our options or seek out the right advice.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.uk.capgemini.com/news/pr1487 Is choice anxiety costing british 'blue chip' business?] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151222143245/https://www.uk.capgemini.com/news/pr1487 |date=December 22, 2015 }}, [[Capgemini]], August 16, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

In a decision context, unpredictability or uncertainty may trigger emotional responses in anxious individuals that systematically alter decision-making.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hartley&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hartley CA, Phelps EA | title = Anxiety and decision-making | journal = Biological Psychiatry | volume = 72 | issue = 2 | pages = 113–8 | date = July 2012 | pmid = 22325982 | pmc = 3864559 | doi = 10.1016/j.biopsych.2011.12.027 }}&lt;/ref&gt; There are primarily two forms of this anxiety type. The first form refers to a choice in which there are multiple potential outcomes with known or calculable probabilities. The second form refers to the uncertainty and ambiguity related to a decision context in which there are multiple possible outcomes with unknown probabilities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hartley&quot; /&gt;

===Panic Disorder===
Panic disorder may share symptoms of stress and anxiety, but it is actually very different.  Panic disorder is an anxiety disorder that occurs without any triggers.  According to the U.S Department of Health and Human Services, this disorder can be distinguished by unexpected and repeated episodes of intense fear.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://www.hhs.gov/answers/mental-health-and-substance-abuse/what-are-the-five-major-types-of-anxiety-disorders/index.html |title = What are the five major types of anxiety disorders?|date = June 8, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Someone who suffers from panic disorder will eventually develop constant fear of another attack and as this progresses it will begin to affect daily functioning and an individual's general quality of life.  It is reported by the Cleveland Clinic that panic disorder affects 2 to 3 percent of adult Americans and can begin around the time of the teenage and early adult years.  Some symptoms include: difficulty breathing, chest pain, dizziness, trembling or shaking, feeling faint, nausea, fear that you are losing control or are about to die.  Even though they suffer from these symptoms during an attack, the main symptom is the persistent fear of having future panic attacks.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/diseases/4451-panic-disorder |title = Panic Disorder &amp; Panic Attacks}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Anxiety disorders===
{{Main|Anxiety disorder}}
&lt;!-- Do not add new content here.  Add to body of Anxiety disorder article, and only if it rises to the importance of the lead there, update the lead there, then update this. Per [[WP:SYNC]] --&gt;
Anxiety disorders are a group of [[mental disorder]]s characterized by exaggerated feelings of [[anxiety (mood)|anxiety]] and [[fear]] responses.&lt;ref name=&quot;DSM5&quot; /&gt; Anxiety is a worry about future events and fear is a reaction to current events.&lt;!-- &lt;ref name= DSM5/&gt; --&gt; These feelings may cause physical symptoms, such as a [[tachycardia|fast heart rate]] and shakiness.&lt;!-- &lt;ref name= DSM5/&gt; --&gt; There are a number of anxiety disorders: including [[generalized anxiety disorder]], [[phobia|specific phobia]], [[social anxiety disorder]], [[separation anxiety disorder]], [[agoraphobia]], [[panic disorder]], and [[selective mutism]].&lt;!-- &lt;ref name= DSM5/&gt; --&gt; The disorder differs by what results in the symptoms.&lt;!-- &lt;ref name= DSM5/&gt; --&gt; People often have more than one anxiety disorder.&lt;ref name=&quot;DSM5&quot; /&gt;

&lt;!-- Causes and diagnosis --&gt;
Anxiety disorders are caused by a complex combination of [[Heredity|genetic]] and environmental factors.{{fact|date=December 2019}} To be diagnosed, symptoms typically need to be present for at least six months, be more than would be expected for the situation, and decrease a person's ability to function in their daily lives.{{fact|date=December 2019}} Other problems that may result in similar symptoms include [[hyperthyroidism]], [[heart disease]], [[caffeine]], [[alcohol (drug)|alcohol]], or [[Cannabis (drug)|cannabis]] use, and withdrawal from certain drugs, among others.{{fact|date=December 2019}}

&lt;!-- Management  --&gt;
Without treatment, anxiety disorders tend to remain.&lt;ref name=&quot;DSM5&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NIH2016&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nimh.nih.gov/health/topics/anxiety-disorders/index.shtml#pub2|title=Anxiety Disorders|date=March 2016|website=NIMH|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160727230427/http://www.nimh.nih.gov/health/topics/anxiety-disorders/index.shtml#pub2|archive-date=July 27, 2016|url-status=live|access-date=August 14, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Treatment may include lifestyle changes, [[psychotherapy|counselling]], and medications.&lt;!-- &lt;ref name=Lancet2016/&gt; --&gt; Counselling is typically with a type of [[cognitive behavioural therapy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Lancet2016&quot; /&gt; Medications, such as [[antidepressants]] or [[beta blockers]], may improve symptoms.&lt;ref name=&quot;NIH2016&quot; /&gt;

&lt;!-- Epidemiology --&gt;
About 12% of people are affected by an anxiety disorder in a given year and between 5–30% are affected at some point in their life.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lancet2016&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kess2007&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Kessler RC, Angermeyer M, Anthony JC, DE Graaf R, Demyttenaere K, Gasquet I, DE Girolamo G, Gluzman S, Gureje O, Haro JM, Kawakami N, Karam A, Levinson D, Medina Mora ME, Oakley Browne MA, Posada-Villa J, Stein DJ, Adley Tsang CH, Aguilar-Gaxiola S, Alonso J, Lee S, Heeringa S, Pennell BE, Berglund P, Gruber MJ, Petukhova M, Chatterji S, Ustün TB | display-authors = 6 | title = Lifetime prevalence and age-of-onset distributions of mental disorders in the World Health Organization's World Mental Health Survey Initiative | journal = World Psychiatry | volume = 6 | issue = 3 | pages = 168–76 | date = October 2007 | pmid = 18188442 | pmc = 2174588 }}&lt;/ref&gt; They occur about twice as often in women than they do in men, and generally begin before the age of 25.&lt;ref name=&quot;DSM5&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lancet2016&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Craske MG, Stein MB | title = Anxiety | journal = Lancet | volume = 388 | issue = 10063 | pages = 3048–3059 | date = December 2016 | pmid = 27349358 | doi = 10.1016/S0140-6736(16)30381-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The most common are specific phobia which affects nearly 12% and social anxiety disorder which affects 10% at some point in their life.&lt;!-- &lt;ref name=Lancet2016/&gt; --&gt; They affect those between the ages of 15 and 35 the most and become less common after the age of 55.&lt;!-- &lt;ref name=Lancet2016/&gt; --&gt; Rates appear to be higher in the United States and Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lancet2016&quot; /&gt;

===Short- and long-term anxiety===
Anxiety can be either a short-term &quot;state&quot; or a long-term &quot;[[Trait theory|trait]]&quot;. Whereas trait anxiety represents worrying about future events, anxiety disorders are a group of [[mental disorder]]s characterized by feelings of anxiety and fear.&lt;ref name=&quot;DSM5&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-JivBAAAQBAJ|title=Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders|author1=American Psychiatric Association|publisher=American Psychiatric Publishing|year=2013|isbn=978-0-89042-555-8|edition=5th|location=Arlington|pages=189–195}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Co-morbidity==
Anxiety disorders often occur with other mental health disorders, particularly [[major depressive disorder]], [[bipolar disorder]], [[eating disorder]]s, or certain [[personality disorder]]s. It also commonly occurs with personality traits such as neuroticism. This observed co-occurrence is partly due to genetic and environmental influences shared between these traits and anxiety.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Smoller |first1=Jordan W. |last2=Andreassen |first2=Ole A. |last3=Edenberg |first3=Howard J. |last4=Faraone |first4=Stephen V. |last5=Glatt |first5=Stephen J. |last6=Kendler |first6=Kenneth S. |title=Correction to: Psychiatric genetics and the structure of psychopathology |journal=Molecular Psychiatry |date=March 14, 2018 |volume=24 |issue=3 |pages=471 |doi=10.1038/s41380-018-0026-4 |pmid=29540840 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Kendler |first1=Kenneth S. |title=Major Depression and Generalised Anxiety Disorder |journal=FOCUS |date=July 2004 |volume=2 |issue=3 |pages=416–425 |doi=10.1176/foc.2.3.416 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Anxiety is often experienced by those with [[obsessive–compulsive disorder]] and is an acute presence in [[panic disorder]].

==Risk factors==
[[File:Emperor Traianus Decius (Mary Harrsch).jpg|thumb|upright|A marble bust of the Roman Emperor [[Decius]] from the [[Capitoline Museum]]. This portrait &quot;conveys an impression of anxiety and weariness, as of a man shouldering heavy [state] responsibilities&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first1=Chris |last1=Scarre | name-list-format = vanc |title=Chronicle of the Roman Emperors |publisher=Thames &amp; Hudson |year=1995 |pages=168–9 |isbn=978-5-00-050775-9}}{{page needed|date=October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

Anxiety disorders are partly genetic, with twin studies suggesting 30-40% genetic influence on individual differences in anxiety.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Reynolds |first1=Chandra A. |title=Robert Plomin, John C. DeFries, Valerie S. Knopik, Jenae M. Neiderhiser, Behavioral Genetics (6th Edition) |journal=Behavior Genetics |date=June 16, 2013 |volume=43 |issue=4 |pages=360–361 |doi=10.1007/s10519-013-9598-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Environmental factors are also important. Twin studies show that individual-specific environments have a large influence on anxiety, whereas shared environmental influences (environments that affect twins in the same way) operate during childhood but decline through adolescence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Smoller |first1=Jordan W. |last2=Block |first2=Stefanie R. |last3=Young |first3=Mirella M. |title=Genetics of anxiety disorders: the complex road from DSM to DNA |journal=Depression and Anxiety |date=November 2009 |volume=26 |issue=11 |pages=965–975 |doi=10.1002/da.20623 |pmid=19885930 |url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/12ca9bddcc942bc9cae986eb5c597b95b0df5530 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Specific measured ‘environments’ that have been associated with anxiety include [[child abuse]], family history of mental health disorders, and [[poverty]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Craske |first1=Michelle G. |last2=Stein |first2=Murray B. |last3=Eley |first3=Thalia C. |last4=Milad |first4=Mohammed R. |last5=Holmes |first5=Andrew |last6=Rapee |first6=Ronald M. |last7=Wittchen |first7=Hans-Ulrich |title=Anxiety disorders |journal=Nature Reviews Disease Primers |date=May 4, 2017 |volume=3 |issue=1 |pages=17024 |doi=10.1038/nrdp.2017.24 |pmid=28470168 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Anxiety is also associated with [[Mood disorder#Substance-induced|drug use]], including [[alcohol (drug)|alcohol]], [[caffeine]], and [[benzodiazepines]] (which are often prescribed to treat anxiety).

===Neuroanatomy===
Neural circuitry involving the [[amygdala]] (which regulates emotions like anxiety and fear, stimulating the [[Hypothalamic–pituitary–adrenal axis|HPA Axis]] and [[sympathetic nervous system]]) and [[hippocampus]] (which is implicated in emotional memory along with the amygdala) is thought to underlie anxiety.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rosen&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Rosen JB, Schulkin J | title = From normal fear to pathological anxiety | journal = Psychological Review | volume = 105 | issue = 2 | pages = 325–50 | date = April 1998 | pmid = 9577241 | doi = 10.1037/0033-295X.105.2.325 }}&lt;/ref&gt; People who have anxiety tend to show high activity in response to emotional stimuli in the amygdala.&lt;ref&gt;Nolen-Hoeksema, S. (2013). (Ab)normal Psychology (6th edition). McGraw Hill.{{page needed|date=October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some writers believe that excessive anxiety can lead to an overpotentiation of the limbic system (which includes the amygdala and nucleus accumbens), giving increased future anxiety, but this does not appear to have been proven.&lt;ref name=&quot;google&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Compassion and Healing in Medicine and Society: On the Nature and Use of Attachment Solutions to Separation Challenges | vauthors =Fricchione G |date=2011 |publisher=Johns Hopkins University Press |isbn=978-1-4214-0220-8 |page=172 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;google2&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=How the Brain Talks to Itself: A Clinical Primer of Psychotherapeutic Neuroscience | vauthors = Harris J |date=1998 |publisher=Haworth |isbn=978-0-7890-0408-6 |page=284 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Research upon adolescents who as infants had been highly apprehensive, vigilant, and fearful finds that their [[nucleus accumbens]] is more sensitive than that in other people when deciding to make an action that determined whether they received a reward.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bar-Haim&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Bar-Haim Y, Fox NA, Benson B, Guyer AE, Williams A, Nelson EE, Perez-Edgar K, Pine DS, Ernst M | display-authors = 6 | title = Neural correlates of reward processing in adolescents with a history of inhibited temperament | journal = Psychological Science | volume = 20 | issue = 8 | pages = 1009–18 | date = August 2009 | pmid = 19594857 | pmc = 2785902 | doi = 10.1111/j.1467-9280.2009.02401.x }}&lt;/ref&gt; This suggests a link between circuits responsible for fear and also reward in anxious people. As researchers note, &quot;a sense of 'responsibility', or self-agency, in a context of uncertainty (probabilistic outcomes) drives the neural system underlying appetitive motivation (i.e., nucleus accumbens) more strongly in temperamentally inhibited than noninhibited adolescents&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bar-Haim&quot; /&gt;

==== The gut-brain axis ====
The microbes of the gut can connect with the brain to affect anxiety. There are various pathways along which this communication can take place. One is through the major neurotransmitters.&lt;ref name=pmid27392632&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Kennedy |first1=P.J. |last2=Cryan |first2=J.F. |last3=Dinan |first3=T.G. |last4=Clarke |first4=G. |title=Kynurenine pathway metabolism and the microbiota-gut-brain axis |journal=Neuropharmacology |date=January 2017 |volume=112 |issue=Pt B |pages=399–412 |doi=10.1016/j.neuropharm.2016.07.002 |pmid=27392632 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The gut microbes such as ''Bifidobacterium'' and ''Bacillus'' produce the neurotransmitters GABA and dopamine, respectively.&lt;ref name=pmid25772005&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Dinan |first1=Timothy G. |last2=Stilling |first2=Roman M. |last3=Stanton |first3=Catherine |last4=Cryan |first4=John F. |title=Collective unconscious: How gut microbes shape human behavior |journal=Journal of Psychiatric Research |date=April 2015 |volume=63 |pages=1–9 |doi=10.1016/j.jpsychires.2015.02.021 |pmid=25772005 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The neurotransmitters signal to the nervous system of the gastrointestinal tract, and those signals will be carried to the brain through the vagus nerve or the spinal system.&lt;ref name=pmid27392632/&gt;&lt;ref name=pmid25772005/&gt;&lt;ref name=pmid28918360&gt;{{cite journal |last1=de Weerth |first1=Carolina |title=Do bacteria shape our development? Crosstalk between intestinal microbiota and HPA axis |journal=Neuroscience &amp; Biobehavioral Reviews |date=December 2017 |volume=83 |pages=458–471 |doi=10.1016/j.neubiorev.2017.09.016 |pmid=28918360 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This is demonstrated by the fact that altering the microbiome has shown anxiety- and depression-reducing effects in mice, but not in subjects without vagus nerves.&lt;ref name=pmid21876150&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Bravo |first1=J. A. |last2=Forsythe |first2=P. |last3=Chew |first3=M. V. |last4=Escaravage |first4=E. |last5=Savignac |first5=H. M. |last6=Dinan |first6=T. G. |last7=Bienenstock |first7=J. |last8=Cryan |first8=J. F. |title=Ingestion of Lactobacillus strain regulates emotional behavior and central GABA receptor expression in a mouse via the vagus nerve |journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences |date=August 29, 2011 |volume=108 |issue=38 |pages=16050–16055 |doi=10.1073/pnas.1102999108 |pmid=21876150 |pmc=3179073 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another key pathway is the HPA axis, as mentioned above.&lt;ref name=pmid28918360/&gt; The microbes can control the levels of cytokines in the body, and altering cytokine levels creates direct effects on areas of the brain such as the hypothalmus, the area that triggers HPA axis activity. The HPA axis regulates production of cortisol, a hormone that takes part in the body's stress response.&lt;ref name=pmid28918360/&gt; When HPA activity spikes, cortisol levels increase, processing and reducing anxiety in stressful situations. These pathways, as well as the specific effects of individual taxa of microbes, are not yet completely clear, but the communication between the gut microbiome and the brain is undeniable, as is the ability of these pathways to alter anxiety levels.

With this communication comes the potential to treat anxiety. Prebiotics and probiotics have been shown to reduced anxiety. For example, experiments in which mice were given fructo- and galacto-oligosaccharide prebiotics&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Burokas |first1=Aurelijus |last2=Arboleya |first2=Silvia |last3=Moloney |first3=Rachel D. |last4=Peterson |first4=Veronica L. |last5=Murphy |first5=Kiera |last6=Clarke |first6=Gerard |last7=Stanton |first7=Catherine |last8=Dinan |first8=Timothy G. |last9=Cryan |first9=John F. |title=Targeting the Microbiota-Gut-Brain Axis: Prebiotics Have Anxiolytic and Antidepressant-like Effects and Reverse the Impact of Chronic Stress in Mice |journal=Biological Psychiatry |date=October 2017 |volume=82 |issue=7 |pages=472–487 |doi=10.1016/j.biopsych.2016.12.031 |pmid=28242013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''Lactobacillus'' probiotics&lt;ref name=pmid21876150/&gt; have both demonstrated a capability to reduce anxiety. In humans, results are not as concrete, but promising.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Benton |first1=D |last2=Williams |first2=C |last3=Brown |first3=A |title=Impact of consuming a milk drink containing a probiotic on mood and cognition |journal=European Journal of Clinical Nutrition |date=December 6, 2006 |volume=61 |issue=3 |pages=355–361 |doi=10.1038/sj.ejcn.1602546 |pmid=17151594 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Schmidt |first1=Kristin |last2=Cowen |first2=Philip J. |last3=Harmer |first3=Catherine J. |last4=Tzortzis |first4=George |last5=Errington |first5=Steven |last6=Burnet |first6=Philip W. J. |title=Prebiotic intake reduces the waking cortisol response and alters emotional bias in healthy volunteers |journal=Psychopharmacology |date=December 3, 2014 |volume=232 |issue=10 |pages=1793–1801 |doi=10.1007/s00213-014-3810-0 |pmid=25449699 |pmc=4410136 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Genetics===
Genetics and family history (e.g. parental anxiety) may put an individual at increased risk of an anxiety disorder, but generally external stimuli will trigger its onset or exacerbation.&lt;sup&gt;[[Anxiety#cite note-%3A0-57|[57]]]&lt;/sup&gt; Estimates of genetic influence on anxiety, based on studies of twins, range from 25–40% depending on the specific type and age-group under study. For example, genetic differences account for about 43% of variance in panic disorder and 28% in generalized anxiety disorder.{{fact|date=December 2019}} Longitudinal twin studies have shown the moderate stability of anxiety from childhood through to adulthood is mainly influenced by stability in genetic influence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Waszczuk |first1=Monika A. |last2=Zavos |first2=Helena M. S. |last3=Gregory |first3=Alice M. |last4=Eley |first4=Thalia C. |title=The Phenotypic and Genetic Structure of Depression and Anxiety Disorder Symptoms in Childhood, Adolescence, and Young Adulthood |journal=JAMA Psychiatry |date=August 1, 2014 |volume=71 |issue=8 |pages=905–16 |doi=10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2014.655 |pmid=24920372 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Nivard |first1=M. G. |last2=Dolan |first2=C. V. |last3=Kendler |first3=K. S. |last4=Kan |first4=K.-J. |last5=Willemsen |first5=G. |last6=van Beijsterveldt |first6=C. E. M. |last7=Lindauer |first7=R. J. L. |last8=van Beek |first8=J. H. D. A. |last9=Geels |first9=L. M. |last10=Bartels |first10=M. |last11=Middeldorp |first11=C. M. |last12=Boomsma |first12=D. I. |title=Stability in symptoms of anxiety and depression as a function of genotype and environment: a longitudinal twin study from ages 3 to 63 years |journal=Psychological Medicine |date=September 4, 2014 |volume=45 |issue=5 |pages=1039–1049 |doi=10.1017/S003329171400213X |pmid=25187475 }}&lt;/ref&gt; When investigating how anxiety is passed on from parents to children, it is important to account for sharing of genes as well as environments, for example using the intergenerational children-of-twins design.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Eley |first1=Thalia C. |last2=McAdams |first2=Tom A. |last3=Rijsdijk |first3=Fruhling V. |last4=Lichtenstein |first4=Paul |last5=Narusyte |first5=Jurgita |last6=Reiss |first6=David |last7=Spotts |first7=Erica L. |last8=Ganiban |first8=Jody M. |last9=Neiderhiser |first9=Jenae M. |title=The Intergenerational Transmission of Anxiety: A Children-of-Twins Study |journal=American Journal of Psychiatry |date=July 2015 |volume=172 |issue=7 |pages=630–637 |doi=10.1176/appi.ajp.2015.14070818 |pmid=25906669 |url=https://kclpure.kcl.ac.uk/portal/en/publications/the-intergenerational-transmission-of-anxiety(c58a9809-2518-433d-bc1b-45a84f548af5).html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many studies in the past used a candidate gene approach to test whether single genes were associated with anxiety. These investigations were based on hypotheses about how certain known genes influence neurotransmitters (such as serotonin and norepinephrine) and hormones (such as cortisol) that are implicated in anxiety. None of these findings are well replicated,{{fact|date=December 2019}} with the possible exception of TMEM132D, COMT and MAO-A.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Howe |first1=A S |last2=Buttenschøn |first2=H N |last3=Bani-Fatemi |first3=A |last4=Maron |first4=E |last5=Otowa |first5=T |last6=Erhardt |first6=A |last7=Binder |first7=E B |last8=Gregersen |first8=N O |last9=Mors |first9=O |last10=Woldbye |first10=D P |last11=Domschke |first11=K |last12=Reif |first12=A |last13=Shlik |first13=J |last14=Kõks |first14=S |last15=Kawamura |first15=Y |last16=Miyashita |first16=A |last17=Kuwano |first17=R |last18=Tokunaga |first18=K |last19=Tanii |first19=H |last20=Smoller |first20=J W |last21=Sasaki |first21=T |last22=Koszycki |first22=D |last23=De Luca |first23=V |title=Candidate genes in panic disorder: meta-analyses of 23 common variants in major anxiogenic pathways |journal=Molecular Psychiatry |date=September 22, 2015 |volume=21 |issue=5 |pages=665–679 |doi=10.1038/mp.2015.138 |pmid=26390831 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The epigenetic signature of ''BDNF'', a gene that codes for a protein called ''brain derived neurotrophic factor'' that is found in the brain, has also been associated with anxiety and specific patterns of neural activity.{{fact|date=December 2019}} and a receptor gene for ''BDNF'' called ''NTRK2'' was associated with anxiety in a large genome-wide investigation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Purves&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Purves |first1=Kirstin L. |last2=Coleman |first2=Jonathan R. I. |last3=Meier |first3=Sandra M. |last4=Rayner |first4=Christopher |last5=Davis |first5=Katrina A. S. |last6=Cheesman |first6=Rosa |last7=Bækvad-Hansen |first7=Marie |last8=Børglum |first8=Anders D. |last9=Wan Cho |first9=Shing |last10=Jürgen Deckert |first10=J. |last11=Gaspar |first11=Héléna A. |last12=Bybjerg-Grauholm |first12=Jonas |last13=Hettema |first13=John M. |last14=Hotopf |first14=Matthew |last15=Hougaard |first15=David |last16=Hübel |first16=Christopher |last17=Kan |first17=Carol |last18=McIntosh |first18=Andrew M. |last19=Mors |first19=Ole |last20=Bo Mortensen |first20=Preben |last21=Nordentoft |first21=Merete |last22=Werge |first22=Thomas |last23=Nicodemus |first23=Kristin K. |last24=Mattheisen |first24=Manuel |last25=Breen |first25=Gerome |last26=Eley |first26=Thalia C. |title=A major role for common genetic variation in anxiety disorders |journal=Molecular Psychiatry |date=November 20, 2019 |doi=10.1038/s41380-019-0559-1 |pmid=31748690 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The reason that most candidate gene findings have not replicated is that anxiety is a complex trait that is influenced by many genomic variants, each of which has a small effect on its own. Increasingly, studies of anxiety are using a hypothesis-free approach to look for parts of the genome that are implicated in anxiety using big enough samples to find associations with variants that have small effects. The largest explorations of the common genetic architecture of anxiety have been facilitated by the UK Biobank, the ANGST consortium and the [https://www.crchealth.com/disorders/anxiety-disorder-panic-treatment/ CRC Fear, Anxiety and Anxiety Disorders].&lt;ref name=&quot;Purves&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Martin|first=Nick|last2=Otowa|first2=Takeshi|last3=Lee|first3=Minyoung|last4=Hartman|first4=Catharina|last5=Oldehinkel|first5=Albertine|last6=Preisig|first6=Martin|last7=Jörgen Grabe|first7=Hans|last8=Middeldorp|first8=Christel|last9=Penninx|first9=Brenda|date=2017|title=Meta-Analysis of Genome-Wide Association Studies of Anxiety Disorders|journal=European Neuropsychopharmacology|volume=27|issue=10|pages=1391–1399|doi=10.1016/j.euroneuro.2016.09.604|pmid=26754954|pmc=4940340}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Deckert |first1=Jurgen |last2=Weber |first2=Heike |last3=Pauli |first3=Paul |last4=Reif |first4=Andreas |title=Glrb Allelic Variation Associated with Agoraphobic Cognitions, Increased Startle Response and Fear Network Activation |journal=European Neuropsychopharmacology |date=2017 |volume=27 |pages=S503 |doi=10.1016/j.euroneuro.2016.09.607 |pmid=28167838 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Medical conditions===
Many medical conditions can cause anxiety. This includes conditions that affect the ability to breathe, like [[COPD]] and [[asthma]], and the difficulty in breathing that often occurs near death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Baldwin J, Cox J | title = Treating Dyspnea: Is Oxygen Therapy the Best Option for All Patients? | journal = The Medical Clinics of North America | volume = 100 | issue = 5 | pages = 1123–30 | date = September 2016 | pmid = 27542431 | doi = 10.1016/j.mcna.2016.04.018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Vanfleteren LE, Spruit MA, Wouters EF, Franssen FM | title = Management of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease beyond the lungs | journal = The Lancet. Respiratory Medicine | volume = 4 | issue = 11 | pages = 911–924 | date = November 2016 | pmid = 27264777 | doi = 10.1016/S2213-2600(16)00097-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TselebisPachi2016&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Tselebis A, Pachi A, Ilias I, Kosmas E, Bratis D, Moussas G, Tzanakis N | title = Strategies to improve anxiety and depression in patients with COPD: a mental health perspective | journal = Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment | volume = 12 | pages = 297–328 | year = 2016 | pmid = 26929625 | pmc = 4755471 | doi = 10.2147/NDT.S79354 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Conditions that cause abdominal pain or chest pain can cause anxiety and may in some cases be a [[somatization]] of anxiety;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Muscatello MR, Bruno A, Mento C, Pandolfo G, Zoccali RA | title = Personality traits and emotional patterns in irritable bowel syndrome | journal = World Journal of Gastroenterology | volume = 22 | issue = 28 | pages = 6402–15 | date = July 2016 | pmid = 27605876 | pmc = 4968122 | doi = 10.3748/wjg.v22.i28.6402 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Remes-Troche JM | title = How to Diagnose and Treat Functional Chest Pain | journal = Current Treatment Options in Gastroenterology | volume = 14 | issue = 4 | pages = 429–443 | date = December 2016 | pmid = 27709331 | doi = 10.1007/s11938-016-0106-y }}&lt;/ref&gt; the same is true for some sexual dysfunctions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Brotto L, Atallah S, Johnson-Agbakwu C, Rosenbaum T, Abdo C, Byers ES, Graham C, Nobre P, Wylie K | display-authors = 6 | title = Psychological and Interpersonal Dimensions of Sexual Function and Dysfunction | journal = The Journal of Sexual Medicine | volume = 13 | issue = 4 | pages = 538–71 | date = April 2016 | pmid = 27045257 | doi = 10.1016/j.jsxm.2016.01.019 | url = https://eprints.soton.ac.uk/390453/1/Final%2520-%2520JSM%2520chapter%2520on%2520psych%2520factors%2520-%2520part%25201%2520-%2520ACCEPTED.doc }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = McMahon CG, Jannini EA, Serefoglu EC, Hellstrom WJ | title = The pathophysiology of acquired premature ejaculation | journal = Translational Andrology and Urology | volume = 5 | issue = 4 | pages = 434–49 | date = August 2016 | pmid = 27652216 | pmc = 5001985 | doi = 10.21037/tau.2016.07.06 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Conditions that affect the face or the skin can cause social anxiety especially among adolescents,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Nguyen CM, Beroukhim K, Danesh MJ, Babikian A, Koo J, Leon A | title = The psychosocial impact of acne, vitiligo, and psoriasis: a review | journal = Clinical, Cosmetic and Investigational Dermatology | volume = 9 | pages = 383–392 | year = 2016 | pmid = 27799808 | pmc = 5076546 | doi = 10.2147/CCID.S76088 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and developmental disabilities often lead to social anxiety for children as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Caçola P | title = Physical and Mental Health of Children with Developmental Coordination Disorder | journal = Frontiers in Public Health | volume = 4 | pages = 224 | year = 2016 | pmid = 27822464 | pmc = 5075567 | doi = 10.3389/fpubh.2016.00224 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Life-threatening conditions like cancer also cause anxiety.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Mosher CE, Winger JG, Given BA, Helft PR, O'Neil BH | title = Mental health outcomes during colorectal cancer survivorship: a review of the literature | journal = Psycho-Oncology | volume = 25 | issue = 11 | pages = 1261–1270 | date = November 2016 | pmid = 26315692 | pmc = 4894828 | doi = 10.1002/pon.3954 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Furthermore, certain organic diseases may present with anxiety or symptoms that mimic anxiety.&lt;ref name=&quot;WHO2009&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TestaGiannuzzi2013partIII&quot; /&gt; These disorders include certain endocrine diseases ([[Hypothyroidism|hypo-]] and [[hyperthyroidism]], [[hyperprolactinemia]]),&lt;ref name=&quot;TestaGiannuzzi2013partIII&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Samuels2008&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Samuels MH | title = Cognitive function in untreated hypothyroidism and hyperthyroidism | journal = Current Opinion in Endocrinology, Diabetes and Obesity | volume = 15 | issue = 5 | pages = 429–33 | date = October 2008 | pmid = 18769215 | doi = 10.1097/MED.0b013e32830eb84c }}&lt;/ref&gt; metabolic disorders ([[diabetes mellitus|diabetes]]),&lt;ref name=&quot;TestaGiannuzzi2013partIII&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BuchbergerHuppertz2016&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Buchberger B, Huppertz H, Krabbe L, Lux B, Mattivi JT, Siafarikas A | title = Symptoms of depression and anxiety in youth with type 1 diabetes: A systematic review and meta-analysis | journal = Psychoneuroendocrinology | volume = 70 | pages = 70–84 | date = August 2016 | pmid = 27179232 | doi = 10.1016/j.psyneuen.2016.04.019 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GrigsbyAnderson2002&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Grigsby AB, Anderson RJ, Freedland KE, Clouse RE, Lustman PJ | title = Prevalence of anxiety in adults with diabetes: a systematic review | journal = Journal of Psychosomatic Research | volume = 53 | issue = 6 | pages = 1053–60 | date = December 2002 | pmid = 12479986 | doi = 10.1016/S0022-3999(02)00417-8 }}&lt;/ref&gt; deficiency states (low levels of [[vitamin D]], [[Riboflavin|B2]], [[vitamin B12|B12]], [[folic acid]]),&lt;ref name=&quot;TestaGiannuzzi2013partIII&quot; /&gt; gastrointestinal diseases ([[celiac disease]], [[non-celiac gluten sensitivity]], [[inflammatory bowel disease]]),&lt;ref name=&quot;ZingoneSwift2015&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zingone F, Swift GL, Card TR, Sanders DS, Ludvigsson JF, Bai JC | title = Psychological morbidity of celiac disease: A review of the literature | journal = United European Gastroenterology Journal | volume = 3 | issue = 2 | pages = 136–45 | date = April 2015 | pmid = 25922673 | pmc = 4406898 | doi = 10.1177/2050640614560786 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MolinaInfanteSantolaria2015SystematicReview&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Molina-Infante J, Santolaria S, Sanders DS, Fernández-Bañares F | title = Systematic review: noncoeliac gluten sensitivity | journal = Alimentary Pharmacology &amp; Therapeutics | volume = 41 | issue = 9 | pages = 807–20 | date = May 2015 | pmid = 25753138 | doi = 10.1111/apt.13155 | url = https://semanticscholar.org/paper/075d25ae039bb1991a847802774bca2e6d53db7e }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NeuendorfHarding2016&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Neuendorf R, Harding A, Stello N, Hanes D, Wahbeh H | title = Depression and anxiety in patients with Inflammatory Bowel Disease: A systematic review | journal = Journal of Psychosomatic Research | volume = 87 | pages = 70–80 | date = August 2016 | pmid = 27411754 | doi = 10.1016/j.jpsychores.2016.06.001 }}&lt;/ref&gt; heart diseases, blood diseases ([[anemia]]),&lt;ref name=&quot;TestaGiannuzzi2013partIII&quot; /&gt; cerebral vascular accidents ([[transient ischemic attack]], [[stroke]]),&lt;ref name=&quot;TestaGiannuzzi2013partIII&quot; /&gt; and brain degenerative diseases ([[Parkinson's disease]], [[dementia]], [[multiple sclerosis]], [[Huntington's disease]]), among others.&lt;ref name=&quot;TestaGiannuzzi2013partIII&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ZhaoTan2016&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zhao QF, Tan L, Wang HF, Jiang T, Tan MS, Tan L, Xu W, Li JQ, Wang J, Lai TJ, Yu JT | display-authors = 6 | title = The prevalence of neuropsychiatric symptoms in Alzheimer's disease: Systematic review and meta-analysis | journal = Journal of Affective Disorders | volume = 190 | pages = 264–271 | date = January 2016 | pmid = 26540080 | doi = 10.1016/j.jad.2015.09.069 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;WenChan2016&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Wen MC, Chan LL, Tan LC, Tan EK | title = Depression, anxiety, and apathy in Parkinson's disease: insights from neuroimaging studies | journal = European Journal of Neurology | volume = 23 | issue = 6 | pages = 1001–19 | date = June 2016 | pmid = 27141858 | pmc = 5084819 | doi = 10.1111/ene.13002 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MarrieReingold2015&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Marrie RA, Reingold S, Cohen J, Stuve O, Trojano M, Sorensen PS, Cutter G, Reider N | display-authors = 6 | title = The incidence and prevalence of psychiatric disorders in multiple sclerosis: a systematic review | journal = Multiple Sclerosis | volume = 21 | issue = 3 | pages = 305–17 | date = March 2015 | pmid = 25583845 | pmc = 4429164 | doi = 10.1177/1352458514564487 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Substance-induced===
Several drugs can cause or worsen anxiety, whether in intoxication, withdrawal or as side effect. These include [[alcohol (drug)|alcohol]], [[tobacco]], [[cannabis]], [[sedative]]s (including prescription [[benzodiazepine]]s), [[opioid]]s (including prescription pain killers and illicit drugs like heroin), [[stimulant]]s (such as [[caffeine]], [[cocaine]] and amphetamines), [[hallucinogen]]s, and [[inhalants]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders|last=American Psychiatric Association|publisher=American Psychiatric Association|year=2013|isbn=|edition=5th|location=Arlington, VA|pages=}}{{page needed|date=October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; While many often report self-medicating anxiety with these substances, improvements in anxiety from drugs are usually short-lived (with worsening of anxiety in the long term, sometimes with acute anxiety as soon as the drug effects wear off) and tend to be exaggerated. Acute exposure to toxic levels of [[benzene]] may cause euphoria, anxiety, and irritability lasting up to 2 weeks after the exposure.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = CDC – The Emergency Response Safety and Health Database: Systemic Agent: BENZENE – NIOSH|url = https://www.cdc.gov/niosh/ershdb/emergencyresponsecard_29750032.html|website = www.cdc.gov|access-date = January 27, 2016|url-status = live|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20160117001341/http://www.cdc.gov/niosh/ershdb/emergencyresponsecard_29750032.html|archive-date = January 17, 2016|df = mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Psychological===
Poor [[Coping (psychology)|coping skills]] (e.g., rigidity/inflexible problem solving, denial, avoidance, impulsivity, extreme self-expectation, negative thoughts, affective instability, and inability to focus on problems) are associated with anxiety. Anxiety is also linked and perpetuated by the person's own pessimistic outcome expectancy and how they cope with feedback negativity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Gu R, Huang YX, Luo YJ | title = Anxiety and feedback negativity | journal = Psychophysiology | volume = 47 | issue = 5 | pages = 961–7 | date = September 2010 | pmid = 20374540 | doi = 10.1111/j.1469-8986.2010.00997.x }}{{primary source inline|date=May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Temperament (e.g., [[neuroticism]])&lt;ref name=&quot;NeuroticismMA&quot; /&gt; and attitudes (e.g. pessimism) have been found to be risk factors for anxiety.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bienvenu Ginsburg 2007&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Bienvenu OJ, Ginsburg GS | title = Prevention of anxiety disorders | journal = International Review of Psychiatry | volume = 19 | issue = 6 | pages = 647–54 | date = December 2007 | pmid = 18092242 | doi = 10.1080/09540260701797837 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Cognitive distortion]]s such as overgeneralizing, catastrophizing, mind reading, [[emotional reasoning]], binocular trick, and mental filter can result in anxiety. For example, an overgeneralized belief that something bad &quot;always&quot; happens may lead someone to have excessive fears of even minimally risky situations and to avoid benign social situations due to anticipatory anxiety of [[embarrassment]]. In addition, those who have high anxiety can also create future stressful life events.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Phillips AC, Carroll D, Der G | title = Negative life events and symptoms of depression and anxiety: stress causation and/or stress generation | journal = Anxiety, Stress, and Coping | volume = 28 | issue = 4 | pages = 357–71 | year = 2015 | pmid = 25572915 | pmc = 4772121 | doi = 10.1080/10615806.2015.1005078 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Together, these findings suggest that anxious thoughts can lead to anticipatory anxiety as well stressful events, which in turn cause more anxiety. Such unhealthy thoughts can be targets for successful treatment with [[cognitive therapy]].

[[Psychodynamics|Psychodynamic]] theory posits that anxiety is often the result of opposing [[Unconscious mind|unconscious]] wishes or fears that manifest via maladaptive [[Defence mechanisms|defense mechanisms]] (such as suppression, repression, anticipation, regression, somatization, passive aggression, dissociation) that develop to [[Ego psychology|adapt]] to problems with early [[Object relations theory|objects]] (e.g., caregivers) and [[Self psychology|empathic failures]] in childhood. For example, persistent parental discouragement of anger may result in repression/suppression of angry feelings which manifests as gastrointestinal distress (somatization) when provoked by another while the anger remains unconscious and outside the individual's awareness. Such conflicts can be targets for successful treatment with [[Psychodynamic psychotherapy|psychodynamic therapy]]. While psychodynamic therapy tends to explore the underlying roots of anxiety, cognitive behavioral therapy has also been shown to be a successful treatment for anxiety by altering irrational thoughts and unwanted behaviors.

====Evolutionary psychology====
An [[evolutionary psychology]] explanation is that increased anxiety serves the purpose of increased [[vigilance (psychology)|vigilance]] regarding potential threats in the environment as well as increased tendency to take proactive actions regarding such possible threats. This may cause [[false positive]] reactions but an individual suffering from anxiety may also avoid real threats. This may explain why anxious people are less likely to die due to accidents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Andrews PW, Thomson JA | title = The bright side of being blue: depression as an adaptation for analyzing complex problems | journal = Psychological Review | volume = 116 | issue = 3 | pages = 620–54 | date = July 2009 | pmid = 19618990 | pmc = 2734449 | doi = 10.1037/a0016242 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

When people are confronted with unpleasant and potentially harmful stimuli such as foul odors or tastes, [[Positron emission tomography|PET-scans]] show increased blood flow in the [[amygdala]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zald DH, Pardo JV | title = Emotion, olfaction, and the human amygdala: amygdala activation during aversive olfactory stimulation | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 94 | issue = 8 | pages = 4119–24 | date = April 1997 | pmid = 9108115 | pmc = 20578 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.94.8.4119 | bibcode = 1997PNAS...94.4119Z }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zald DH, Hagen MC, Pardo JV | title = Neural correlates of tasting concentrated quinine and sugar solutions | journal = Journal of Neurophysiology | volume = 87 | issue = 2 | pages = 1068–75 | date = February 2002 | pmid = 11826070 | doi = 10.1152/jn.00358.2001 | url = https://semanticscholar.org/paper/27c4d5c2ce3f757943fa05db1d6b154d7eccdbb4 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In these studies, the participants also reported moderate anxiety. This might indicate that anxiety is a protective mechanism designed to prevent the organism from engaging in potentially harmful behaviors.

===Social===
Social risk factors for anxiety include a history of trauma (e.g., physical, sexual or emotional abuse or assault), early life experiences and parenting factors (e.g., rejection, lack of warmth, high hostility, harsh discipline, high parental [[Negative affectivity|negative affect]], anxious childrearing, modelling of dysfunctional and drug-abusing behaviour, discouragement of emotions, poor socialization, poor attachment, and child abuse and neglect), cultural factors (e.g., stoic families/cultures, persecuted minorities including the disabled), and socioeconomics (e.g., uneducated, unemployed, impoverished although developed countries have higher rates of anxiety disorders than developing countries).&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |chapter-url=http://books.nap.edu/openbook.php?record_id=12480&amp;page=530 |chapter=Table E-4 Risk Factors for Anxiety |page=530 |veditors=O'Connell ME, Boat T, Warner KE |publisher=National Academies Press |title=Prevention of Mental Disorders, Substance Abuse, and Problem Behaviors: A Developmental Perspective |year=2009 |isbn=978-0-309-12674-8  |doi=10.17226/12480 |pmid=20662125 |vauthors=((National Research Council (Us) Institute Of Medicine (Us) Committee On The Prevention Of Mental Disorders Substance Abuse Among Children, Youth, and Young Adults))|url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/a83d9124d2e53dafd330910fdfa9dfe854440f17 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 
A 2019 comprehensive systematic review of over 50 studies showed that food insecurity in the United States is strongly associated with depression, anxiety, and sleep disorders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Arenas |first1=Daniel J. |last2=Thomas |first2=Arthur |last3=Wang |first3=JiCi |last4=DeLisser |first4=Horace M. |title=A Systematic Review and Meta-analysis of Depression, Anxiety, and Sleep Disorders in US Adults with Food Insecurity |journal=Journal of General Internal Medicine |date=August 5, 2019 |volume=34 |issue=12 |pages=2874–2882 |doi=10.1007/s11606-019-05202-4 |pmid=31385212 |pmc=6854208 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Food-insecure individuals had an almost 3 fold risk increase of testing positive for anxiety when compared to food-secure individuals.

====Gender socialization====
Contextual factors that are thought to contribute to anxiety include gender socialization and learning experiences. In particular, learning mastery (the degree to which people perceive their lives to be under their own control) and instrumentality, which includes such traits as self-confidence, [[self-efficacy]], independence, and competitiveness fully mediate the relation between gender and anxiety. That is, though gender differences in anxiety exist, with higher levels of anxiety in women compared to men, gender socialization and learning mastery explain these gender differences.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1080/03634520009379205 |title=Anticipatory anxiety patterns for male and female public speakers |journal=Communication Education |volume=49 |issue=2 |pages=187–195 |year=2000 |last1=Behnke |first1=Ralph R. |last2=Sawyer |first2=Chris R. | name-list-format = vanc }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{mcn|date=June 2015}}

==Treatment==
{{See also|Fear#Management}}
The first step in the management of a person with anxiety symptoms involves evaluating the possible presence of an underlying medical cause, whose recognition is essential in order to decide the correct treatment.&lt;ref name=&quot;WHO2009&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author= World Health Organization |date= 2009 |title= Pharmacological Treatment of Mental Disorders in Primary Health Care |url= http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/44095/1/9789241547697_eng.pdf |location= Geneva |isbn= 978-92-4-154769-7 |url-status= live |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20161120132530/http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/44095/1/9789241547697_eng.pdf |archive-date= November 20, 2016 |df= mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TestaGiannuzzi2013partIII&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Testa A, Giannuzzi R, Daini S, Bernardini L, Petrongolo L, Gentiloni Silveri N | title = Psychiatric emergencies (part III): psychiatric symptoms resulting from organic diseases | journal = European Review for Medical and Pharmacological Sciences | volume = 17 Suppl 1 | pages = 86–99 | date = February 2013 | pmid = 23436670 | url = http://www.europeanreview.org/article/3087 }}{{open access}}&lt;/ref&gt; Anxiety symptoms may mask an [[Disease|organic disease]], or appear associated with or as a result of a medical disorder.&lt;ref name=&quot;WHO2009&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TestaGiannuzzi2013partIII&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TestaGiannuzzi2013partII&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Testa A, Giannuzzi R, Sollazzo F, Petrongolo L, Bernardini L, Dain S | title = Psychiatric emergencies (part II): psychiatric disorders coexisting with organic diseases | journal = European Review for Medical and Pharmacological Sciences | volume = 17 Suppl 1 | pages = 65–85 | date = February 2013 | pmid = 23436669 | url = http://www.europeanreview.org/article/3085 }}{{open access}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TestaGiannuzzi2013partI&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Testa A, Giannuzzi R, Sollazzo F, Petrongolo L, Bernardini L, Daini S | title = Psychiatric emergencies (part I): psychiatric disorders causing organic symptoms | journal = European Review for Medical and Pharmacological Sciences | volume = 17 Suppl 1 | pages = 55–64 | date = February 2013 | pmid = 23436668 | url = http://www.europeanreview.org/article/3083 }}{{open access}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Cognitive behavioral therapy]] (CBT) is effective for anxiety disorders and is a first line treatment.&lt;ref name=&quot;NEJM2015&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Stein|first1=MB|last2=Sareen|first2=J|date=November 19, 2015|title=Clinical Practice: Generalized Anxiety Disorder.|journal=The New England Journal of Medicine|volume=373|issue=21|pages=2059–68|doi=10.1056/nejmcp1502514|pmid=26580998}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Cuijpers|first=P|author2=Sijbrandij, M|author3=Koole, S|author4=Huibers, M|author5=Berking, M|author6=Andersson, G|date=Mar 2014|title=Psychological treatment of generalized anxiety disorder: A meta-analysis.|journal=Clinical Psychology Review|volume=34|issue=2|pages=130–140|doi=10.1016/j.cpr.2014.01.002|pmid=24487344}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Otte|first=C|year=2011|title=Cognitive behavioral therapy in anxiety disorders: current state of the evidence.|journal=Dialogues in Clinical Neuroscience|volume=13|issue=4|pages=413–21|pmc=3263389|pmid=22275847}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Pompoli|first1=A|last2=Furukawa|first2=TA|last3=Imai|first3=H|last4=Tajika|first4=A|last5=Efthimiou|first5=O|last6=Salanti|first6=G|date=April 13, 2016|title=Psychological therapies for panic disorder with or without agoraphobia in adults: a network meta-analysis.|url=https://boris.unibe.ch/81165/1/Pompoli%20CochraneDatabaseSystRev%202016.pdf|journal=The Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews|volume=4|pages=CD011004|doi=10.1002/14651858.CD011004.pub2|pmid=27071857}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ol2016&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Olthuis|first1=JV|last2=Watt|first2=MC|last3=Bailey|first3=K|last4=Hayden|first4=JA|last5=Stewart|first5=SH|date=March 12, 2016|title=Therapist-supported Internet cognitive behavioural therapy for anxiety disorders in adults.|journal=The Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews|volume=3|pages=CD011565|doi=10.1002/14651858.cd011565.pub2|pmid=26968204}}&lt;/ref&gt; CBT appears to be equally effective when carried out via the internet.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ol2016&quot; /&gt; While evidence for mental health apps is promising, it is preliminary.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Donker|first1=T|last2=Petrie|first2=K|last3=Proudfoot|first3=J|last4=Clarke|first4=J|last5=Birch|first5=MR|last6=Christensen|first6=H|date=November 15, 2013|title=Smartphones for smarter delivery of mental health programs: a systematic review.|journal=Journal of Medical Internet Research|volume=15|issue=11|pages=e247|doi=10.2196/jmir.2791|pmc=3841358|pmid=24240579}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prevention==
The above risk factors give natural avenues for prevention. A 2017 review found that psychological and/or educational interventions have a small yet statistically significant benefit for the prevention of anxiety in varied population types.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Moreno-Peral |first1=Patricia |last2=Conejo-Cerón |first2=Sonia |last3=Rubio-Valera |first3=Maria |last4=Fernández |first4=Anna |last5=Navas-Campaña |first5=Desirée |last6=Rodríguez-Morejón |first6=Alberto |last7=Motrico |first7=Emma |last8=Rigabert |first8=Alina |last9=Luna |first9=Juan de Dios |last10=Martín-Pérez |first10=Carlos |last11=Rodríguez-Bayón |first11=Antonina |last12=Ballesta-Rodríguez |first12=María Isabel |last13=Luciano |first13=Juan Vicente |last14=Bellón |first14=Juan Ángel |title=Effectiveness of Psychological and/or Educational Interventions in the Prevention of Anxiety |journal=JAMA Psychiatry |date=October 1, 2017 |volume=74 |issue=10 |pages=1021–1029 |doi=10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2017.2509 |pmid=28877316 |pmc=5710546 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.nationalelfservice.net/mental-health/anxiety/preventing-anxiety-with-psychological-and-educational-interventions/ |title=Preventing anxiety with psychological and educational interventions |first1=Inês |last1=Pote |website=National Elf Service |date=February 19, 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |doi=10.1016/B978-0-12-813495-5.00008-5 |chapter=Targeting anxiety sensitivity as a prevention strategy |title=The Clinician's Guide to Anxiety Sensitivity Treatment and Assessment |pages=145–178 |year=2019 |last1=Schmidt |first1=Norman B. |last2=Allan |first2=Nicholas P. |last3=Knapp |first3=Ashley A. |last4=Capron |first4=Dan |isbn=978-0-12-813495-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Pathophysiology==
{{Unreferenced section|date=October 2018}}
Anxiety disorder appears to be a genetically inherited neurochemical dysfunction that may involve autonomic imbalance; decreased GABA-ergic tone; allelic polymorphism of the catechol-O-methyltransferase (COMT) gene; increased adenosine receptor function; increased cortisol.&lt;ref&gt;{{EMedicine|article|286227|Anxiety Disorders}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[central nervous system]] (CNS), the major mediators of the symptoms of anxiety disorders appear to be norepinephrine, serotonin, dopamine, and gamma-aminobutyric acid (GABA). Other neurotransmitters and peptides, such as corticotropin-releasing factor, may be involved. Peripherally, the [[autonomic nervous system]], especially the sympathetic nervous system, mediates many of the symptoms. Increased flow in the right parahippocampal region and reduced serotonin type 1A receptor binding in the anterior and posterior cingulate and raphe of patients are the diagnostic factors for prevalence of anxiety disorder.

The amygdala is central to the processing of fear and anxiety, and its function may be disrupted in anxiety disorders. Anxiety processing in the basolateral amygdala has been implicated with dendritic arborization of the amygdaloid neurons. SK2 potassium channels mediate inhibitory influence on action potentials and reduce arborization.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Shelton |first1=Charles I. |title=Diagnosis and Management of Anxiety Disorders |journal=The Journal of the American Osteopathic Association |date=March 1, 2004 |volume=104 |issue=3 Suppl 1 |pages=S2–S5 |url=https://jaoa.org/article.aspx?articleid=2092999 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
*[[Angst]]
*[[Fear]]
*[[Tripartite Model of Anxiety and Depression]]
* [[Uncanny]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Medical resources
| ICD10 = {{ICD10|F06.4}}, {{ICD10|F40}}, {{ICD10|F41}}, {{ICD10|F93.0}}
| ICD10CM = {{ICD10CM|F06.4}}, {{ICD10CM|F40}}, {{ICD10CM|F41}}, {{ICD10CM|F43.22}}, {{ICD10CM|F43.23}}, {{ICD10CM|F93.0}}
| eMedicineTopic =
| MeshID = D001007
| MedlinePlus = 003211
| MedlinePlus_mult = {{MedlinePlus2|000917}}
|OMIM=607834
}}
{{Library resources box|by=no|onlinebooks=no|about=yes|wikititle=anxiety}}
{{Sister project links |commons=no |n=no |s=no |b=no |voy=no |v=no |d=no |species=no |species_author=no |m=no |mw=no }}
* {{Commons category-inline}}
* {{curlie|Health/Mental_Health/Disorders/Anxiety/Support_Groups}}
{{Emotion-footer}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Anxiety| ]]
[[Category:Emotions]]
[[Category:Mental states in Csikszentmihalyi's flow model]]</text>
      <sha1>1jmxoy1jz974v8smubs9g8v690r5ibd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
