  <page>
    <title>Albert Camus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>983</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943074961</id>
      <parentid>943068007</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T17:46:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cinadon36</username>
        <id>29281028</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>As stated earlier, there is no need to insert newspaper sources when text is already sourced by several RS. Also, Albert Camus society is not a RS. Please take it to Talk page if you insist on using newspapers.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|French author and journalist}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2019}}
{{use British English|date=June 2019}}
{{Infobox philosopher
| image = Albert Camus, gagnant de prix Nobel, portrait en buste, posé au bureau, faisant face à gauche, cigarette de tabagisme.jpg
| caption = Portrait from ''[[New York World-Telegram]] and Sun Photograph Collection'', 1957
| region = [[Western philosophy]]
| era = [[20th-century philosophy]]
| birth_date = {{birth date|1913|11|7|df=yes}}
| birth_place = Mondovi (present-day [[Dréan]]), [[French Algeria]]
| death_date = {{death date and age|df=yes|1960|1|4|1913|11|7}}
| death_place = [[Villeblevin]], France
| death_cause = [[Car accident]]
| alma_mater       = [[University of Algiers]]
| notable_works    = ''[[The Stranger (Camus novel)|The Stranger]]'' / ''The Outsider''&lt;br/&gt;''[[The Myth of Sisyphus]]''&lt;br/&gt;''[[The Rebel (book)|The Rebel]]''&lt;br/&gt;''[[The Plague]]''
| signature = Albert Camus signature.svg
| signature_size = 150px
| signature_alt = Albert Camus signature
| school_tradition = [[Continental philosophy]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Absurdism]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Existentialism]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Anarchism]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Syndicalism]]
| main_interests = [[Ethics]], [[Human nature|humanity]], [[justice]], [[politics]], [[suicide]]
| influences = [[Sartre]], [[Georges Sorel]], [[Emma Goldman]], [[Mikhail Bakunin]], [[Peter Kropotkin]], [[Augustine]], [[Homer]], [[Lev Shestov|Shestov]], [[Karl Marx|Marx]], [[Nietzsche]], [[Dostoevsky]], [[Kierkegaard]], [[Jean Grenier|Grenier]], [[Samuel Beckett]], [[Max Stirner]]
| influenced = [[Michel Onfray]] [[Alan Watts]]
| notable_ideas = [[Absurdism]]
| module=
{{infobox person
| embed = yes
| partner = [[Francine Faure]]
| children = [[Catherine Camus|Catherine]], and a son}}
}}

'''Albert Camus''' ({{IPAc-en|k|æ|ˈ|m|uː}} {{IPAc-en|also|US|k|ə|ˈ|m|uː}}; {{IPA-fr|albɛʁ kamy|lang|Fr-Albert Camus.oga}}; 7 November 1913 – 4 January 1960) was a [[France|French]] philosopher, author, and journalist. He won the [[Nobel Prize in Literature]] at the age of 44 in 1957, the second-youngest recipient in history.

Camus was [[pied-noir|born in Algeria]] to French parents. He spent his childhood in a poor neighbourhood and later studied philosophy at the [[University of Algiers]]. He was in Paris when the [[Battle of France|Germans invaded France]] during [[World War II]]. Camus tried to flee but finally joined the [[French Resistance]] where he served as editor-in-chief at ''[[Combat (newspaper)|Combat]]'', an outlawed newspaper. After the war, he was a celebrity figure and gave many lectures around the world. He married twice but had many extramarital affairs. Camus was politically active. He was part of the [[Left-wing politics|Left]] that opposed the [[Soviet Union]] because of its [[totalitarianism]]. Camus was a [[Moralism|moralist]] and leaned towards [[anarcho-syndicalism]]. He was part of many organisations seeking European integration. During the [[Algerian War]], he kept a neutral stance, advocating for a multicultural and pluralistic Algeria, a position that caused controversy and was rejected by most parties.

Philosophically, Camus's views contributed to the rise of the philosophy known as [[absurdism]]. He is also considered to be an [[existentialist]], even though he firmly rejected the term throughout his lifetime.

==Life==

===Early years and education===

[[File:Algiers The University (GRI).jpg|thumb|alt=A postcard showing the University of Algiers|A 20th-century postcard of the University of Algiers]]
Albert Camus was born on 7 November 1913 in a working-class neighbourhood in Mondovi (present-day [[Dréan]]), in [[French Algeria]]. His mother, Catherine Hélène Sintès Camus, was of [[Spaniards|Spanish]]-([[Balearic Islands|Balearic]]) descent. His father, Lucien Camus, a poor French-Algerian agricultural worker, died in the [[First Battle of the Marne|Battle of the Marne]] in 1914 during [[World War I]]. Camus never knew him. Camus, his mother and other relatives lived without many basic material possessions during his childhood in the Belcourt section of [[Algiers]]. He was a second-generation French immigrant to Algeria. His paternal grandfather, along with many others of his generation, had moved to Africa for a better life during the first decades of the 19th century. Hence, he was called {{lang-fr|[[pied-noir]]|label=none|lit='black foot'}}—a slang term for French who were born in Algeria—and his binational identity and his poor background had a substantial effect on his later life.{{sfnm|1a1=Sherman|1y=2009|1p=10|2a1=Hayden|2y=2016|2p=7|3a1=Lottman|3y=1979|3p=11|4a1=Carroll|4y=2007|4pp=2–3}} Nevertheless, Camus was a French citizen, in contrast to the [[Arab]] or [[Berbers|Berberic]] inhabitants of Algeria who were denied the associated privileges this brought.{{sfn|Carroll|2007|pp=2–3}} During his childhood, Camus developed a love for soccer and swimming.{{sfn|Sherman|2009|p=11}}

Under the influence of his teacher Louis Germain, Camus gained a scholarship in 1924 to continue his studies at a prestigious [[lyceum]] (secondary school) near Algiers.{{sfn|Hayden|2016|p=8}} In 1930, he was diagnosed with [[tuberculosis]].{{sfn|Sherman|2009|p=11}} Because it is a transmitted disease, he moved out of his home and stayed with his uncle Gustave Acault, a butcher, who influenced the young Camus. It was at that time that Camus turned to philosophy, with the mentoring of his philosophy teacher [[Jean Grenier]]. He was impressed by [[ancient Greek philosopher]]s and [[Friedrich Nietzsche]].{{sfn|Sherman|2009|p=11}} During that time, he was only able to study part-time. To earn money, he took odd jobs: as a private tutor, car parts clerk, and assistant at the Meteorological Institute.{{sfn|Hayden|2016|p=9}}

In 1933, Camus enrolled at the [[University of Algiers]] and completed his ''[[Licentiate (degree)|licence de philosophie]]'' ([[Bachelor of Arts|BA]]) in 1936; after presenting his thesis on [[Plotinus]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Sherman|2009|p=11|ps=: Camus' thesis was titled &quot;Rapports de l'hellénisme et du christianisme à travers les oeuvres de Plotin et de saint Augustin&quot; (&quot;Relationship of Greek and Christian Thought in Plotinus and St. Augustine&quot;) for his ''diplôme d'études supérieures'' (roughly equivalent to an [[Master of Arts|MA]] thesis).}}&lt;/ref&gt; Camus developed an interest in early Christian philosophers, but Nietzsche and [[Arthur Schopenhauer]] had paved the way towards pessimism and atheism. Camus also studied novelist-philosophers such as [[Stendhal]], [[Herman Melville]], [[Fyodor Dostoyevsky]], and [[Franz Kafka]].{{sfn|Simpson|2019|loc=Background and Influences}} In 1933, he also met Simone Hié, who would become his first wife.{{sfn|Hayden|2016|p=9}}

Camus played [[Goalkeeper (association football)|goalkeeper]] for the [[Racing Universitaire d'Alger]] junior team from 1928 to 1930.{{sfn|Clarke|2009|p=488}} The sense of team spirit, fraternity, and common purpose appealed to Camus enormously.{{sfn|Lattal|1995}} In match reports, he was often praised for playing with passion and courage. Any football ambitions disappeared when he contracted tuberculosis at the age of 17.{{sfn|Clarke|2009|p=488}} Camus drew parallels among football, human existence, morality, and personal identity. For him, the simplistic morality of football contradicted the complicated morality imposed by authorities such as the state and Church.{{sfn|Clarke|2009|p=488}}

===Young Camus===
In 1934, aged 20, Camus was in a relationship with Simone Hié.{{sfnm|1a1=Cohn|1y=1986|1p=30|2a1=Hayden|2y=2016|p=9}} Simone suffered from an addiction to [[morphine]], a drug she used to ease her menstrual pains. His uncle Gustave did not approve of the relationship, but Camus married Hié to help her fight her addiction. He subsequently discovered she was in a relationship with her doctor at the same time and the couple later divorced.{{sfn|Hayden|2016|p=9}} Camus was a womanizer throughout his life.{{sfnm|1a1=Sherman|1y=2009|2a1=Hayden|2y=2016|2p=13}}

Camus joined the [[French Communist Party]] (PCF) in early 1935. He saw it as a way to &quot;fight inequalities between Europeans and 'natives' in Algeria,&quot; even though he was not a [[Marxist]] and had not read ''[[Das Kapital]]'' (''Capital''). He explained: &quot;We might see communism as a springboard and asceticism that prepares the ground for more spiritual activities.&quot; Camus left the PCF a year later.{{sfnm|1a1=Todd|1y=2000|1pp=249–250|2a1=Sherman|2y=2009|2p=12}} In 1936, the independence-minded [[Algerian Communist Party]] (PCA) was founded, and Camus joined it after his mentor Grenier advised him to do so. Camus's main role within the PCA was to organise the ''Théâtre du Travail'' (&quot;Workers' Theatre&quot;). Camus was also close to the Parti du Peuple Algérien ([[Algerian People's Party]] (PPA)), which was a moderate anti-colonialist/nationalist party. As tensions in the [[interwar period]] escalated, the [[Stalinism|Stalinist]] PCA and PPA broke ties. Camus was expelled from the PCA for refusing to toe the party line. This series of events sharpened his belief in human dignity. Camus's mistrust of bureaucracies that aimed for efficiency instead of justice grew. He continued his involvement with theatre and renamed his group Théâtre de l'Equipe (&quot;Theatre of the Team&quot;). Some of his scripts were the basis for his later novels.{{sfn|Hayden|2016|pp=10–11}}

In 1938, Camus began working for the leftist newspaper ''[[Alger républicain]]'' (founded by [[Pascal Pia]]) as he had strong anti-fascist feelings, and the rise of fascist regimes in Europe was worrying him. By then, Camus had developed strong feelings against authoritative [[colonialism]] as he witnessed the harsh treatment of the [[Arab-Berber|Arabs]] and Berbers by French authorities. ''Alger républicain'' was banned in 1940 and Camus flew to Paris to take a new job at ''[[Paris-Soir]]'' as editor-in-chief. In Paris, he almost completed his &quot;first cycle&quot; of works dealing with the absurd and the meaningless—the novel ''L'Étranger'' (''The Outsider'' (UK), or [[The Stranger (Camus novel)|''The Stranger'']] (US)), the philosophical essay ''Le Mythe de Sisyphe'' (''[[The Myth of Sisyphus]]'') and the play ''[[Caligula (play)|Caligula]]''. Each cycle consisted of a novel, an essay and a theatrical play.{{sfnm|1a1=Hayden|1y=2016|1p=12|2a1=Sherman|2y=2009|2pp=12–13}}

===World War II, Resistance and ''Combat''===

Soon after Camus moved to Paris, the outbreak of [[World War II]] began to affect France. Camus volunteered to join the army but was not accepted because he had suffered from tuberculosis. As the Germans were marching towards Paris, Camus fled. He was laid off from ''Paris-Soir'' and ended up in [[Lyon]], where he married pianist and mathematician [[Francine Faure]] on 3 December 1940.{{sfn|Hayden|2016|pp=13–14}} Camus and Faure moved back to Algeria ([[Oran]]) where he taught in primary schools.{{sfn|Sherman|2009|p=13}} Because of his tuberculosis, he was forced to move to the French Alps. There he began writing his second cycle of works, this time dealing with revolt—a novel ''La Peste'' (''[[The Plague]]'') and a play ''Le Malentendu'' (''[[The Misunderstanding]]''). By 1943 he was known because of his earlier work. He returned to Paris where he met and became friends with [[Jean-Paul Sartre]]. He also became part of a circle of intellectuals including [[Simone de Beauvoir]], [[André Breton]], and others. Among them was the actress [[María Casares]], who would later have an affair with Camus.{{sfnm|1a1=Hayden|1y=2016|2a1=Sherman|2y=2009|2p=13}}

Camus took an active role in the underground resistance movement against the Germans during the [[Occupation of France|French Occupation]]. Upon his arrival in Paris, he started working as a journalist and editor of the banned newspaper ''[[Combat (newspaper)|Combat]]''. He continued writing for the paper after the liberation of France.{{sfnm|1a1=Hayden|1y=2016|2a1=Sherman|2y=2009|2p=13}} Camus used a pseudonym for his ''Combat'' articles and used false ID cards to avoid being captured. During that period he composed four ''[[Resistance, Rebellion, and Death|Lettres à un ami allemand]]'' (''Letters to a German Friend''), explaining why resistance was necessary.{{sfn|Hayden|2016|p=15}}

===Post-World War II===
[[File:Albert Camus2.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Photo of Albert Camus in the 1950s|Albert Camus in the 1950s]]
{{external media| float = right| width = 230px | video1 = [https://www.c-span.org/video/?97122-1/albert-camus-life Presentation by Olivier Todd on ''Albert Camus: A Life'', December 15, 1997], [[C-SPAN]]}}

After the War, Camus lived in Paris with Faure, who gave birth to twins, Catherine and Jean in 1945.{{sfn|Willsher|2011}} Camus was now a celebrated writer known for his role in the Resistance. He gave lectures at various universities in the United States and Latin America during two separate trips. He also visited Algeria once more, only to leave disappointed by the continued oppressive colonial policies, which he had warned about many times. During this period he completed the second cycle of his work, with the novel ''L'Homme révolté'' (''[[The Rebel (book)|The Rebel]]''). Camus attacked [[totalitarian]] [[communism]] while advocating [[libertarian]] [[socialism]] and [[anarcho-syndicalism]].{{sfn|Hayden|2016|p=17}} Upsetting many of his colleagues and contemporaries in France with his rejection of communism, the book brought about the final split with Sartre. His relations with the Marxist Left deteriorated further during the [[Algerian War]].{{sfn|Hayden|2016|pp=16–17}}

Camus was a strong supporter of European integration in various marginal organisations working towards that end.{{sfn|Hayden|2016|p=18}} In 1944, he founded the Comité français pour la féderation européenne—(CFFE (French Committee for the European Federation))—declaring that Europe &quot;can only evolve along the path of economic progress, democracy, and peace if the nation states become a federation.&quot;{{sfn|Hayden|2016|p=18}} In 1947–48, he founded the Groupes de liaison internationale (GLI){{sfnm|1a1=Todd|1y=2000|1pp=249–250|2a1=Schaffner|2y=2006|2p=107}} a trade union movement in the context of revolutionary [[syndicalism]] (&quot;syndicalisme révolutionnaire&quot;). According to Olivier Todd's biography ''Albert Camus, une vie'', (''Albert Camus: A Life'') it was a group opposed to some tendencies of the [[Surrealist Manifesto|Surrealist movement]] of André Breton. His colleagues were [[Nicolas Lazarévitch]], [[Louis Mercier]], Roger Lapeyre, Paul Chauvet, Auguste Largentier, and [[Jean de Boë]].{{sfn|Boulouque|2000}} His main aim was to express the positive side of [[surrealism]] and existentialism, rejecting the negativity and the [[nihilism]] of André Breton. Camus also raised his voice against the [[Hungary–Soviet Union relations|Soviet intervention in Hungary]] and the totalitarian tendencies of [[Francisco Franco|Franco]]'s regime in Spain.{{sfn|Hayden|2016|p=18}}

Camus had numerous affairs, particularly an irregular and eventually public affair with the Spanish-born actress María Casares, with whom he had an extensive correspondence.{{sfnm|1a1=Sherman|1y=2009|1pp=14–17|2a1=Zaretsky|2y=2018}} Faure did not take this affair lightly. She had a mental breakdown and needed hospitalisation in the early 1950s. Camus, who felt guilty, withdrew from public life and was slightly depressed for some time.{{sfn|Sherman|2009|p=17}}

In 1957, Camus received the news that he was to be awarded the [[Nobel Prize in Literature]]. This came as a shock to him. He was anticipating [[André Malraux]] would win the prestigious award. At age 44, he was the second-youngest recipient of the prize, after [[Rudyard Kipling]], who was 42. After this he began working on his autobiography ''[[The First Man|Le Premier Homme]]'' (''The First Man'') in an attempt to examine &quot;moral learning&quot;. He also turned to the theatre once more. {{sfn|Hayden|2016|p=19}} Financed by the money he received with his Nobel Prize, he adapted and directed for the stage [[Dostoyevsky]]'s novel ''[[Demons (Dostoyevsky novel)|Demons]]''. The play opened in January 1959 at the [[Théâtre Antoine-Simone Berriau|Antoine Theatre]] in Paris and was a critical success.{{sfn|Sherman|2009|p=18}}

===Camus' death ===
[[File:20041113-002 Lourmarin Tombstone Albert Camus.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Photograph of Camus's gravestone| Albert Camus's gravestone]] [[File:Camus Monument in Villeblevin France 17-august-2003.4.JPG|thumb|The bronze plaque on the monument to Camus in the town of [[Villeblevin]], France. It reads: &quot;From the General Council of the Yonne Department, in homage to the writer Albert Camus whose remains lay in vigil at the Villeblevin town hall on the night of 4 to 5 January 1960&quot;]] [[File:Camus Monument in Villeblevin France 17-august-2003.1.JPG|thumb|alt=A photograph of the monument to Camus built in Villeblevin.|The monument to Camus built in [[Villeblevin]], where he died in a car crash on 4 January 1960]]

Camus died on 4 January 1960 at the age of 46, in a [[Traffic collision|car accident]] near [[Sens]], in Le Grand Fossard in the small town of [[Villeblevin]]. He had spent the New Year's holiday of 1960 at his house in [[Lourmarin]], [[Vaucluse]] with his family, and his publisher [[Michel Gallimard]] of [[Éditions Gallimard]], along with his wife, Janine, and daughter. Camus's wife and children went back to Paris by train on 2 January, but Camus decided to return in Gallimard's luxurious [[Facel Vega FVS|Facel Vega HK500]]. The car crashed into a [[Platanus|plane tree]] on a long straight stretch of the Route nationale 5 (now the [[Route nationale 6|RN 6]]). Camus, who was in the passenger seat and not wearing a safety belt, died instantly.{{sfnm|1a1=Sherman|1y=2009|1p=19|2a1=Simpson|2y=2019|2loc=Life}} Gallimard died a few days later, although his wife and daughter were unharmed. There has been speculation that Camus was assassinated by the [[KGB]] because of his criticism of Soviet abuses.{{sfn|Catelli|2019}}{{sfn|Flood|2019}}

144 pages of a handwritten manuscript entitled ''Le premier homme'' (''The First Man'') were found in the wreckage. Camus had predicted that this unfinished novel based on his childhood in Algeria would be his finest work.{{sfn|Willsher|2011}} Camus was buried in the Lourmarin Cemetery, Vaucluse, France, where he had lived. {{sfn|Bloom|2009|p=52}} His friend Sartre read a eulogy, paying tribute to Camus's heroic &quot;stubborn humanism&quot;.{{sfn|Simpson|2019|loc= Life}}

==Literary career==

[[File:Lucia 1957.jpg|thumb|right|alt=Camus crowning Stockholm's Lucia after accepting the Nobel Prize in Literature.|Camus crowning Stockholm's [[St Lucy's Day#In the Nordic countries|Lucia]] on 13 December 1957, three days after accepting the [[Nobel Prize in Literature]]]]

Camus's first publication was a play called ''[[Révolte dans les Asturies]]'' (''Revolt in the Asturias'') written with three friends in May 1936. The subject was the 1934 revolt by Spanish miners that was brutally suppressed by the Spanish government resulting in 1,500 to 2,000 deaths. In May 1937 he wrote his first book, ''L'Envers et l'Endroit'' (''[[Betwixt and Between]]'', also translated as ''The Wrong Side and the Right Side''). Both were published by [[Edmond Charlot]]'s small publishing house.{{sfn|Hayden|2016|p=11}}
 
Camus separated his work into three cycles. Each cycle consisted of a novel, an essay, and a play. The first was the cycle of the absurd consisting of ''L'Étranger'', ''Le Mythe de Sysiphe'', and ''Caligula''. The second was the cycle of the revolt which included ''La Peste'' (''The Plague''), ''L'Homme révolté'' (''The Rebel''), and ''Les Justes'' (''The Just Assassins''). The third, the cycle of the love, consisted of ''Nemesis''. Each cycle was an examination of a theme with the use of a pagan myth and including biblical motifs. {{sfn|Sharpe|2015|pp=41–44}}

The books in the first cycle were published between 1942 and 1944, but the theme was conceived earlier, at least as far back as 1936.{{sfn|Hayden|2016|p=23}} With this cycle, Camus aims to pose a question on the [[human condition]], discuss the world as an absurd place, and warn humanity of the consequences of totalitarianism.{{sfn|Hayden|2016|p=41}}

Camus began his work on the second cycle while he was in [[Algeria]], in the last months of 1942, just as the Germans were reaching North Africa.{{sfn|Hayden|2016|p=14}} In the second cycle, Camus used [[Prometheus]], who is depicted as a revolutionary humanist, to highlight the nuances between revolution and rebellion. He analyses various aspects of rebellion, its metaphysics, its connection to politics, and examines it under the lens of modernity, of [[historicity]] and the absence of a God.{{sfn|Hayden|2016|pp=45–47}}

After receiving the Nobel Prize, Camus gathered, clarified, and published his pacifist leaning views at ''Actuelles III: Chronique algérienne 1939–1958'' (''Algerian Chronicles''). He then decided to distance himself from the Algerian War as he found the mental burden too heavy. He turned to theatre and the third cycle which was about love and the goddess [[Nemesis]].{{sfn|Hayden|2016|p=19}}

Two of Camus's works were published posthumously. The first entitled ''La mort heureuse'' (''[[A Happy Death]]'') (1970), features a character named Patrice Mersault, comparable to ''The Stranger''{{'}}s Meursault. There is scholarly debate about the relationship between the two books. The second was an unfinished novel, ''Le Premier homme'' (''The First Man'') (1995), which Camus was writing before he died. It was an autobiographical work about his childhood in Algeria.

The publication of this book in 1994 has sparked a widespread reconsideration of Camus's allegedly unrepentant colonialism.{{sfn|Carroll|2007}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+Works of Camus by genre and cycle, &lt;small&gt;according to Matthew Sharpe{{sfn|Sharpe|2015|p=44}}&lt;/small&gt;
|-
! Years 
! Pagan myth 
! Biblical motif 
! Novel 
! Plays
|-
| 1937–42|| Sisyphus|| Alienation, exile|| ''[[The Stranger (Camus novel)|The Stranger]]'' (''L'Étranger'')||''[[Caligula (play)|Caligula]]'',&lt;br/&gt;''[[The Misunderstanding]]'' (''Le Malentendu'')
|-
| 1943–52|| Prometheus|| Rebellion || ''[[The Plague]]'' (''La Peste'')|| ''[[The State of Siege]]'' (''L'État de siège'')&lt;br/&gt; ''[[The Just Assassins|The Just]]'' (''Les Justes'')
|-
| 1952–58|| || Guilt, the fall; exile &amp; the kingdom; &lt;br/&gt;John the Baptist, Christ || ''[[The Fall (Camus novel)|The Fall]]'' (''La Chute'') || Adaptations of ''The Possessed'' (Dostoevsky); &lt;br/&gt; Faulkner's ''Requiem for a Nun''
|-
| 1958– || Nemesis|| The Kingdom|| ''[[The First Man]]'' (''Le Premier Homme'')|| 
|}

==Political stance==

Camus was a moralist; he claimed morality should guide politics. While he did not deny that morals change over time, he rejected the classical [[Marxist doctrine]] that history defines morality.

Camus was also strongly critical of authoritarian communism, especially in the case of the Soviet regime, which he considered [[totalitarianism|totalitarian]]. Camus rebuked Soviet apologists and their &quot;decision to call total servitude freedom&quot;.{{sfn|Foley|2008|pp=75–76}} As a proponent of [[libertarian socialism]], he claimed the USSR was not socialist, and the United States was not liberal.{{sfn|Sherman|2009|pp=185–87}} His fierce critique of the USSR caused him to clash with others on the political left, most notably with his friend Jean-Paul Sartre.

Active in the [[French Resistance]] to the German occupation of France during World War II, Camus wrote for and edited the famous Resistance journal ''Combat''. Of the [[Collaboration with the Axis Powers#France|French collaboration]] with the German occupiers, he wrote: &quot;Now the only moral value is courage, which is useful here for judging the puppets and chatterboxes who pretend to speak in the name of the people.&quot;{{sfn|Bernstein|1997}} After France's liberation, Camus remarked, &quot;This country does not need a [[Talleyrand]], but a [[Louis Antoine de Saint-Just|Saint-Just]].&quot;{{sfn|Bronner|2009|p=74}} The reality of the bloody [[Épuration légale|postwar tribunals]] soon changed his mind: Camus publicly reversed himself and became a lifelong opponent of [[capital punishment]].{{sfn|Bronner|2009|p=74}}

Camus leaned towards anarchism, a tendency that intensified in the 1950s, when he came to believe that the Soviet model was morally bankrupt.{{sfnm|1a1=Dunwoodie|1y=1993|1p=86|2a1=Marshall|2y=1993|2p=445}} Camus was firmly against any kind of exploitation, authority and property, bosses, the State and centralisation.{{sfn|Dunwoodie|1993|p=87}} Philosophy professor David Sherman considers Camus an [[anarcho-syndicalist]].{{sfn|Sherman|2009|p=185}} [[Graeme Nicholson]] considers Camus an [[Existentialist anarchism|existentialist anarchist]].{{sfn|Nicholson|1971|p=14}}

The anarchist [[André Prudhommeaux]] first introduced him at a meeting of the Cercle des Étudiants Anarchistes (&quot;Anarchist Student Circle&quot;) in 1948 as a sympathiser familiar with anarchist thought. Camus wrote for anarchist publications such as ''[[Le Libertaire]]'', ''[[La Révolution prolétarienne]]'', and ''[[Solidaridad Obrera (periodical)|Solidaridad Obrera]]'' (&quot;Workers' Solidarity&quot;), the organ of the anarcho-syndicalist [[Confederación Nacional del Trabajo]] (CNT) (&quot;National Confederation of Labor&quot;).{{sfnm|1a1=Dunwoodie|1y=1993|1pp=87-87|1ps=: See also appendix p 97|2a1=Hayden|2y=2016|2p=18}}

Camus kept a neutral stance during the [[Algerian Revolution]] (1954–62). While he was against the violence of the [[National Liberation Front (Algeria)|National Liberation Front]] (FLN) he acknowledged the injustice and brutalities imposed by colonialist France. He was supportive of [[Pierre Mendès France|Pierre Mendès]]' [[Unified Socialist Party (France)|Unified Socialist Party]] (PSU) and its approach to the crisis;· Mendes advocated reconciliation. Camus also supported a like-minded Algerian militant, [[Aziz Kessous]]. Camus travelled to Algeria to negotiate a truce between the two belligerents but was met with distrust by all parties.{{sfnm|1a1=Sherman|1y=2009|1pp=17–18 &amp; 188|2a1=Cohn|2y=1986|2pp=30 &amp; 38}} His confrontation with an Algerian nationalist during his acceptance speech for the Nobel Prize caused a sensation. When confronted with the dilemma of choosing between his mother and justice, his response was: &quot;I have always condemned [[terrorism]], and I must condemn a terrorism that works blindly in the streets of Algiers and one day might strike at my mother and family. I believe in justice, but I will defend my mother before justice.&quot;{{sfn|Sherman|2009|p=191}} Camus' critics called it reactionary and a result of a colonialist attitude.{{sfnm|1a1=Sherman|1y=2009|1p=19|2a1=Simpson|2y=2019|3a1=Marshall|3y=1993|3p=584}} According to David Sherman, though, Camus tried to highlight the false dichotomy of the two choices as the use of terrorism and indiscriminate violence could not bring justice under any circumstances.{{sfn|Sherman|2009|p=191}}

He was sharply critical of the [[Nuclear proliferation|proliferation of nuclear weapons]] and the [[Atomic bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki|bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki]].{{sfn|Hayden|2016|p=87}} In the 1950s, Camus devoted his efforts to [[human rights]]. In 1952, he resigned from his work for [[UNESCO]] when the UN accepted Spain, under the leadership of the [[caudillo]] General Francisco Franco, as a member.{{sfn|Sherman|2009|p=17}} Camus maintained his pacifism and resisted capital punishment anywhere in the world. He wrote an essay against capital punishment in collaboration with [[Arthur Koestler]], the writer, intellectual, and founder of the League Against Capital Punishment entitled ''[[Réflexions sur la peine capitale]]'', published by [[Calmann-Levy]] in 1957.{{sfn|Hayden|2016|p=73 &amp; 85}}

==Algeria==
[[File:Départements français d'Algérie 1934-1955 map-fr.svg|thumb|alt=Map of French Algeria showing its administrative organisation between 1905 and 1955 |Administrative organisation of French Algeria between 1905 and 1955]]

Born in Algeria to French parents, Camus was familiar with the [[institutional racism]] of France against Arabs, but he was not part of a rich elite. He lived in very poor conditions as a child but was a citizen of France and as such was entitled to citizens' rights; the Arab and [[Berbers|Berber]] majority of the country were not.{{sfn|Carroll|2007|pp=3–4}}

Camus was a vocal advocate of the &quot;new Mediterranean Culture&quot;. This was a term he used to describe his vision of embracing the multi-ethnicity of the Algerian people, in opposition to &quot;Latiny&quot;, a popular pro-fascist and antisemitic ideology among other ''[[Pieds-Noirs]]''—or French or Europeans born in Algeria. For Camus, this vision encapsulated the Hellenic humanism which survived among ordinary people around the Mediterranean Sea.{{sfn|Hayden|2016|p=141-143}} His 1938 address on &quot;The New Mediterranean Culture&quot; represents Camus's most systematic statement of his views at this time. Camus also supported the [[Blum–Viollette proposal]] to grant Algerians full French citizenship in a manifesto with arguments defending this assimilative proposal on radical egalitarian grounds. {{sfn|Hayden|2016|p=145}} In 1939, Camus wrote a stinging series of articles for the ''[[Alger républicain]]'' on the atrocious living conditions of the inhabitants of the [[Kabylie]] highlands. He advocated for economic, educational and political reforms as a matter of emergency.{{sfn|Sharpe|2015|p=356}}

In 1945, following the [[Sétif and Guelma massacre]] after Arab revolts against French mistreatment, Camus was one of only a few mainland journalists to visit the colony. He wrote a series of articles reporting on conditions, and advocating for French reforms and concessions to the demands of the Algerian people.{{sfn|Foley|2008|pp=150–151}}

When the Algerian War began in 1954, Camus was confronted with a moral dilemma. He identified with the ''Pieds-Noirs'' such as his own parents and defended the French government's actions against the revolt. He argued the Algerian uprising was an integral part of the &quot;new [[Arab imperialism]]&quot; led by Egypt, and an &quot;anti-Western&quot; offensive orchestrated by Russia to &quot;encircle Europe&quot; and &quot;isolate the United States&quot;.{{sfn|Sharpe|2015|p=322}} Although favouring greater Algerian [[self-governance|autonomy]] or even federation, though not full-scale independence, he believed the ''Pieds-Noirs'' and Arabs could co-exist. During the war, he advocated a civil truce that would spare the civilians. It was rejected by both sides who regarded it as foolish. Behind the scenes, he began working for imprisoned Algerians who faced the death penalty.{{sfn|Foley|2008|p=161}} His position drew much criticism from the left who considered colonialism unacceptable. In their eyes, Camus was no longer the defender of the oppressed.{{sfn|Carroll|2007|pp=7–8}}

Camus once confided that the troubles in Algeria &quot;affected him as others feel pain in their lungs.&quot;{{sfn|Sharpe|2015|p=9}}

==Philosophy==
===Existentialism===

Even though Camus is mostly connected to [[Absurdism]],{{sfn|Sherman|2009|p=3}} he is routinely categorized as an [[Existentialist]], a term he rejected on several occasions.{{sfn|Sharpe|2015|p=3}}

Camus himself said his philosophical origins lay in ancient Greek philosophy, [[Nietzsche]], and 17th-century moralists whereas existentialism arises from 19th- and early 20th-century philosophy such as [[Kierkegaard]], [[Karl Jaspers]], and [[Heidegger]].{{sfnm|1a1=Foley|1y=2008|1pp=1–2|2a1=Sharpe|2y=2015|2p=29}} He also said his work, ''The Myth of Sisyphus'', was a criticism of various aspects of existentialism.{{sfn|Foley|2008|pp=2}} Camus was rejecting existentialism as a philosophy, but his critique was mostly focused on [[Sartre]]an existentialism, and to a lesser extent on religious existentialism. He thought that the importance of history held by Marx and Sartre was incompatible with his belief in human freedom.{{sfnm|1a1=Foley|1y=2008|1p=3|2a1=Sherman|2y=2009|2p=3}} David Sherman and others also suggest the rivalry between Sartre and Camus also played a part in his rejection of existentialism.{{sfnm|1a1=Sherman|1y=2009|1p=4|2a1=Simpson|2y=2019|2loc= Existentialism}} David Simpson argues further that his humanism and belief in human nature set him apart from the existentialist doctrine that [[existence precedes essence]].{{sfn|Simpson|2019|loc= Existentialism}}

On the other hand, Camus focused most of his philosophy around existential questions. The absurdity of life, the inevitable ending (death) is highlighted in his acts. His belief that the absurd—life being void of meaning, or man's inability to know that meaning if it were to exist—was something that man should embrace. His anti-Christianity, his commitment to individual moral freedom and responsibility are only a few of the similarities with other existential writers.{{sfnm|1a1=Sharpe|1y=2015|1pp=5–6|2a1=Simpson|2y=2019|2loc= Existentialism}} More importantly, Camus addressed one of the fundamental questions of existentialism: the problem of [[suicide]]. He wrote: &quot;There is only one really serious philosophical question, and that is suicide.&quot; Camus viewed the question of suicide as arising naturally as a solution to the absurdity of life.{{sfn|Aronson|2017|loc=Introduction}}

===Absurdism===
Many existentialist writers have addressed the Absurd, each with their own interpretation of what it is and what makes it important. [[Søren Kierkegaard|Kierkegaard]] explains that the absurdity of religious truths prevents us from reaching God rationally.{{sfn|Foley|2008|pp=5–6}} Sartre recognizes the absurdity of individual experience. Camus's thoughts on the Absurd begins with his first cycle of books and the literary essay ''The Myth of Sisyphus'', (''Le Mythe de Sisyphe''), his major work on the subject. In 1942 he published the story of a man living an absurd life in ''L'Étranger''. He also wrote a play about the Roman emperor [[Caligula]], pursuing an absurd logic, which was not performed until 1945. His early thoughts appeared in his first collection of essays, ''L'Envers et l'endroit'' (''Betwixt and Between'') in 1937. Absurd themes were expressed with more sophistication in his second collection of essays, ''Noces'' (''[[Nuptials (Camus)|Nuptials]]''), in 1938 and ''Betwixt and Between''. In these essays, Camus reflects on the experience of the Absurd.{{sfn|Sherman|2009|p=23}} Aspects of the notion of the Absurd can be found in ''The Plague''.{{sfn|Sherman|2009|p=8}}

Camus follows Sartre's definition of the Absurd: &quot;That which is meaningless. Thus man's existence is absurd because his contingency finds no external justification&quot;.{{sfn|Foley|2008|pp=5–6}} The Absurd is created because man, who is placed in an unintelligent universe, realises that human values are not founded on a solid external component; or as Camus himself explains, the Absurd is the result of the &quot;confrontation between human need and the unreasonable silence of the world.&quot;{{sfn|Foley|2008|p=6}} Even though absurdity is inescapable, Camus does not drift towards nihilism. But the realization of absurdity leads to the question: Why should someone continue to live? Suicide is an option that Camus firmly dismisses as the renunciation of human values and freedom. Rather, he proposes we accept that absurdity is a part of our lives and live with it.{{sfn|Foley|2008|p=7-10}}

The turning point in Camus's attitude to the Absurd occurs in a collection of four letters to an anonymous German friend, written between July 1943 and July 1944. The first was published in the ''Revue Libre'' in 1943, the second in the ''Cahiers de Libération'' in 1944, and the third in the newspaper ''Libertés'', in 1945. The four letters were published as ''Lettres à un ami allemand'' (''Letters to a German Friend'') in 1945, and were included in the collection ''Resistance, Rebellion, and Death''.

Camus regretted the continued reference to himself as a &quot;philosopher of the absurd&quot;. He showed less interest in the Absurd shortly after publishing ''Le Mythe de Sisyphe''. To distinguish his ideas, scholars sometimes refer to the Paradox of the Absurd, when referring to &quot;Camus's Absurd&quot;.{{sfn|Curtis|1972|p=335-348}}

===Revolt===

Camus is known for articulating the case for revolting against any kind of oppression, injustice, or whatever disrespects the human condition. He is cautious enough, however, to set the limits on the rebellion.{{sfnm|1a1=Sharpe|1y=2015|1p=18|2a1=Simpson|2y=2019|2loc=Revolt}} ''L'Homme révolté'' (''The Rebel'') explains in detail his thoughts on the issue. There, he builds upon the absurd (described in ''The Myth of Sisyphus'') but goes further. In the introduction, where he examines the metaphysics of rebellion, he concludes with the phrase &quot;I revolt, therefore we exist&quot; implying the recognition of a common human condition.{{sfn|Foley|2008|pp=55–56}} Camus also delineates the difference between revolution and rebellion and notices that history has shown that the rebel's revolution might easily end up as an oppressive regime. So he places importance on the morals accompanying the revolution.{{sfn|Foley|2008|pp=56–58}} Camus poses a crucial question: Is it possible for humans to act in an ethical and meaningful manner, in a silent universe? According to him the answer is yes, as the experience and awareness of the Absurd creates the moral values and also sets the limits of our actions.{{sfn|Hayden|2016|pp=43–44}} Camus separates the modern form of rebellion into two modes. First, there is the metaphysical rebellion, which is &quot;the movement by which man protests against his condition and against the whole of creation.&quot; The other mode, historical rebellion, is the attempt to materialize the abstract spirit of metaphysical rebellion and change the world. In this attempt, the rebel must balance between the evil of the world and the intrinsic evil which every revolt carries, and not cause any unjustifiable suffering.{{sfn|Hayden|2016|pp=50–55}}

==Legacy==
Camus's novels and philosophical essays are still influential. After his death, interest in Camus followed the rise (and diminution) of the [[New Left]]. Following the [[collapse of Soviet Union]], interest in his alternative road to communism resurfaced.{{sfn|Sherman|2009|pp=207–208}} He is remembered for his skeptical humanism and his support for political tolerance, dialogue, and civil rights.{{sfn|Sharpe|2015|pp= 241–242}}

Although Camus has been linked to anti-Soviet communism, reaching as far as anarcho-syndicalism, some neo-liberals have tried to associate him with their policies, e.g. when the French President [[Nicolas Sarkozy]] suggested that his remains to be moved to the [[Panthéon]], an idea that angered many on the [[Left-wing politics|Left]].{{sfnm|1a1=Zaretsky|1y=2013|1pp=3–4|2a1=Sherman|2y=2009|2p=208}}

==Works==

===Novels===
* ''[[The Stranger (Camus novel)|The Stranger]]'' (''L'Étranger'', often translated as ''The Outsider''. An alternate meaning of &quot;l'étranger&quot; is &quot;foreigner&quot; ) (1942)
* ''[[The Plague]]'' (''La Peste'') (1947)
* ''[[The Fall (Camus novel)|The Fall]]'' (''La Chute'') (1956)
* ''[[A Happy Death]]'' (''La Mort heureuse'') (written 1936–38, published posthumously 1971)
* ''[[The First Man]]'' (''Le premier homme'') (incomplete, published posthumously 1995)

===Short stories===
* ''[[Exile and the Kingdom]]'' (''L'exil et le royaume'') (collection, 1957), containing the following short stories:
** &quot;[[The Adulterous Woman]]&quot; (''La Femme adultère'')
** &quot;[[The Renegade (short story)|The Renegade or a Confused Spirit]]&quot; (''Le Renégat ou un esprit confus'')
** &quot;[[The Silent Men]]&quot; (''Les Muets'')
** &quot;[[The Guest (short story)|The Guest]]&quot; (''L'Hôte'')
** &quot;[[the Artist at Work|Jonas, or the Artist at Work]]&quot; (''Jonas, ou l'artiste au travail'')
** &quot;[[The Growing Stone]]&quot; (''La Pierre qui pousse'')

===Non-fiction books===
* ''[[Christian Metaphysics and Neoplatonism]]'' (1935)
* ''[[Betwixt and Between]]'' (''L'envers et l'endroit'', also translated as ''The Wrong Side and the Right Side'') (collection, 1937)
* ''[[Nuptials (Camus)|Nuptials]]'' (''Noces'') (1938)
* ''[[The Myth of Sisyphus]]'' (''Le Mythe de Sisyphe'') (1942)
* ''[[The Rebel (book)|The Rebel]]'' (''L'Homme révolté'') (1951)
* ''[[Notebooks 1935–1942]]'' (''Carnets, mai 1935&amp;nbsp;— fevrier 1942'') (1962)
* ''[[Notebooks 1942–1951]]'' (1965)
* ''[[American Journals]]'' (1978)
* ''[[Notebooks 1951–1959]]'' (2008). Published as ''Carnets Tome III: Mars 1951 – December 1959'' (1989)
* ''[[Algerian Chronicles]]'' (2013) (originally published in 1958 as ''Chroniques algériennes'')
* ''[[Correspondance (1944-1959)]]'' The correspondance of Albert Camus and [[María Casares]]. Preface by his daughter, Catherine Camus (2017).

===Plays===
* ''[[Caligula (play)|Caligula]]'' (performed 1945, written 1938)
* ''[[The Misunderstanding]]'' (''Le Malentendu'') (1944)
* ''[[The State of Siege]]'' (''L'État de Siège'') (1948)
* ''[[The Just Assassins]]'' (''Les Justes'') (1949)
* ''[[Requiem for a Nun (play)|Requiem for a Nun]]'' (''Requiem pour une nonne'', adapted from [[William Faulkner]]'s [[Requiem for a Nun|novel by the same name]]) (1956)
* ''[[The Possessed (play)|The Possessed]]'' (''Les Possédés'', adapted from [[Fyodor Dostoyevsky]]'s novel ''[[Demons (Dostoevsky novel)|Demons]]'') (1959)

===Essays===
* ''[[The Crisis of Man]]'' (''Lecture at Columbia University'') (28 March 1946)
* ''[[Neither Victims nor Executioners]]'' (Series of essays in ''Combat'') (1946)
* ''Why Spain?'' (Essay for the theatrical play ''L'Etat de Siège'') (1948)
* ''Summer'' (''L'Été'') (1954)
* ''The Ancient Greek Tragedy'' (''Parnassos lecture in Greece'') (1956)
* ''[[Reflections on the Guillotine]]'' (''Réflexions sur la guillotine'') (Extended essay, 1957)
* ''Create Dangerously'' (''Essay on Realism and Artistic Creation'', lecture at the University of Uppsala in Sweden) (1957)

===Collected essays===
* ''[[Resistance, Rebellion, and Death]]'' (1961)&amp;nbsp;– a collection of essays selected by the author, including the 1945 ''Lettres à un ami allemand'' (''Letters to a German Friend'') and ''A Defense of Intelligence'', a 1945 speech given at a meeting organized by Amitié Française.{{sfn|Orme|2007}} Also includes ''Why Spain?'', ''[[Reflections on the Guillotine]]'', and ''Create Dangerously''
* ''Lyrical and Critical Essays'' (1970) – essays which include ''L'envers et l'endroit,'' ''Noces'', and ''L'Eté''
* ''Youthful Writings'' (1976)
* ''Between Hell and Reason: Essays from the Resistance Newspaper &quot;Combat&quot;, 1944–1947'' (1991)
* ''Camus at &quot;Combat&quot;: Writing 1944–1947'' (2005)
* ''Albert Camus Contre la Peine de Mort'' (2011)

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Sources==
* {{cite encyclopedia|last=Aronson|first=Ronald|title=Albert Camus|encyclopedia= [[The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]|editor= [[Edward N. Zalta]]|url=https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/sum2017/entries/camus/|year= 2017|ref=harv}}
* {{cite news|last1=Bernstein |first1=Richard |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1997/12/19/books/books-of-the-times-camus-as-a-principled-rebel-among-poseurs.html |title=In Camus's notebooks and letters, as quoted in, 'Albert Camus: A Life', By Olivier Todd |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |accessdate=17 October 2009 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060510104040/http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EED9113FF93AA25751C1A961958260 |archivedate=10 May 2006  |date=19 December 1997|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Bloom|first=Harold |authorlink=Harold Bloom|title=Albert Camus|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ihqHSbg41TUC|year=2009|publisher=[[Infobase Publishing]]|isbn=978-1-4381-1515-3|ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal|last= Boulouque|first=Sylvain |title=Nicolas Lazarévitch, Itinéraire d'un syndicaliste révolutionnaire|journal= [[Communisme]]|year= 2000|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last= Bronner |first=Stephen Eric|authorlink=Stephen Bronner|title=Camus: Portrait of a Moralist|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=TyOjcCm8XDMC&amp;pg=PA74|accessdate=3 September 2011|date=15 September 2009|publisher=[[University of Chicago Press]]|isbn=978-0-226-07567-9|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=11dwG9mnVXsC|title=Albert Camus the Algerian: Colonialism, Terrorism, Justice|last=Carroll|first=David|date=4 May 2007|publisher=[[Columbia University Press]]|isbn=9780231511766|language=en|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Catelli|first=Giovanni |title=La mort de Camus|year=2019|publisher=Balland|isbn=978-2940632015|ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal|last=Clarke|first= Liam |title=Football as a metaphor: learning to cope with life, manage emotional illness and maintain health through to recovery | journal=[[Journal of Psychiatric and Mental Health Nursing]] | publisher=[[Wiley (publisher)|Wiley]] | volume=16 | issue=5 | year=2009 | issn=1351-0126 | doi=10.1111/j.1365-2850.2009.01403.x |pmid= 19538606 | pages=488–492 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal|last=Cohn|first=Robert Greer|title=The True Camus|journal=[[The French Review]]|volume=60|issue=1|pages=30–38|year=1986|ref=harv|jstor=393607}}
* {{Cite journal|last=Curtis|first=Jerry L.|date=1 August 1972|title=The absurdity of rebellion|journal=[[Man and World]]|language=en|volume=5|issue=3|pages=335–348|doi=10.1007/bf01248640|issn=0025-1534|ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal|last=Dunwoodie | first=Peter | title=Albert Camus and the Anarchist Alternative | journal=Australian Journal of French Studies | publisher=Liverpool University Press | volume=30 | issue=1 | year=1993 | issn=0004-9468 | doi=10.3828/ajfs.30.1.84 | pages=84–104 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite news|last1=Flood |first1=Alison |url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2019/dec/05/albert-camus-murdered-by-the-kgb-giovanni-catelli |title=New book claims Albert Camus was murdered by the KGB  |newspaper=[[The Guardian]] |accessdate=5 December 2019 |url-status=live |date=5 December 2019|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Foley|first=John|title=Albert Camus: From the Absurd to Revolt|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=fcO9NwAACAAJ|year=2008|publisher=[[McGill-Queen's University Press]]|isbn=978-0-7735-3467-4|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Hayden|first=Patrick|title=Camus and the Challenge of Political Thought: Between Despair and Hope|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZYeRCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT26|date=9 February 2016|publisher=[[Springer Publishing|Springer]]|isbn=978-1-137-52583-3|ref=harv}}
* {{cite web |last=Lattal|first=Ashley|year=1995|url=http://www.users.muohio.edu/shermalw/honors_2001_fall/honors_papers_2000/lattal.html |title=Albert Camus |publisher=Users.muohio.edu |accessdate=17 October 2009|ref=harv}} 
* {{cite book|last=Lottman|first=Herbert |authorlink=Herbert Lottman|title=Albert Camus: A Biography|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=UJY8PgAACAAJ|year=1979|publisher=Axis|isbn=978-1-870845-12-0|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last = Marshall|first=Peter H.|author-link=Peter Marshall (author)|title=Demanding the Impossible: A History of Anarchism|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=yPl0QgAACAAJ|year=1993|publisher=[[HarperCollins|Fontana]]|isbn=978-0-00-686245-1|ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal|last=Nicholson|first= Graeme|authorlink = Graeme Nicholson|title =Camus and Heidegger: Anarchists| journal =[[University of Toronto Quarterly]]| volume= 41 |year = 1971|pages= 14–23|url= https://www.muse.jhu.edu/article/559809|ref=harv|doi= 10.3138/utq.41.1.14}}
* {{cite book|last=Orme|first=Mark |title=The Development of Albert Camus's Concern for Social and Political Justice: &quot;justice Pour Un Juste&quot;|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VGBSVdHwmUYC&amp;pg=PA139|year=2007|publisher=[[Fairleigh Dickinson Univ Press]]|isbn=978-0-8386-4110-1|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Schaffner|first=Alain |title=Albert Camus: l'exigence morale : hommage à Jacqueline Lévi-Valensi (L'esprit des lettres)|editor=Agnès Spiquel  |publisher=Editions Le Manuscrit|year=2006 |isbn=2748171012|via=Google Books |url=https://books.google.ca/books?id=peseTi-X8FoC|language=French|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Sharpe|first=Matthew |authorlink=Matthew Sharpe|title=Camus, Philosophe: To Return to our Beginnings|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=pdZ0CgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA9|date=3 September 2015|publisher=[[Brill Publishers|BRILL]]|isbn=978-90-04-30234-1|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Sherman|first=David |title=Camus|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=X2zuGq1BCBYC|date=30 January 2009|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|isbn=978-1-4443-0328-5|ref=harv}} 
* {{cite encyclopedia|last=Simpson|first=David|title=Albert Camus (1913–1960)|encyclopedia= [[The Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]|year=2019 |url= https://www.iep.utm.edu/camus/|issn=2161-0002 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book|last=Todd|first=Olivier |authorlink=Oliver Todd|title=Albert Camus: A Life |publisher=[[Carroll &amp; Graf]] |year=2000 |isbn=978-0-7867-0739-3|ref=harv}} 
* {{Cite news |last=Willsher |first=Kim |url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2011/aug/07/albert-camus-killed-by-kgb |title=Albert Camus might have been killed by the KGB for criticising the Soviet Union, claims newspaper |date=7 August 2011 |work=The Guardian |access-date=13 June 2019|ref=harv}}
* {{cite magazine|last=Zaretsky|first=Robert|url=https://lareviewofbooks.org/article/no-longer-the-person-i-was-the-dazzling-correspondence-of-albert-camus-and-maria-casares/#!|title='No Longer the Person I Was': The Dazzling Correspondence of Albert Camus and Maria Casarès|magazine=[[Los Angeles Review of Books]]|year=2018|accessdate=13 April 2018|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Zaretsky|first=Robert |title=A Life Worth Living|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=PQjeAAAAQBAJ|date=7 November 2013|publisher=[[Harvard University Press]]|isbn=978-0-674-72837-0|ref=harv}}

==Further reading==
===Selected biographies===
&lt;!--extensive 'further reading' removed 2015-09-20, see history - largely non-English--&gt;
* {{cite book|last=Thody|first=Philip Malcolm Waller|author-link=Philip Thody|title=Albert Camus: A Study of His Work|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NmAzAAAAMAAJ|year=1957|publisher=[[Hamish Hamilton]]}}
* {{cite book|last=Brisville|first=Jean-Claude|authorlink=Jean-Claude Brisville|title=Camus|url=https://archive.org/details/camus0000bris|url-access=registration|year=1959|publisher=[[Gallimard]]}}
* {{cite book|last=Parker|first=Emmett |title=Albert Camus: The Artist in the Arena|url=https://archive.org/details/albertcamusartis00park|url-access=registration|year=1965|publisher=[[Univ of Wisconsin Press]]|isbn=978-0-299-03554-9}}
* {{cite book|last=King|first=Adele |authorlink=Adele King|title=Albert Camus|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CmQoAQAAIAAJ|year=1964|publisher=[[Grove Press]]}}
* {{cite book|last=McCarthy|first=Patrick |title=Camus: A Critical Study of His Life and Work|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VJNcAAAAMAAJ|year=1982|publisher=Hamish Hamilton|isbn=978-0-241-10603-7}}
* {{cite book|last=Sprintzen|first=David |title=Camus: A Critical Examination|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ugWANQAACAAJ|date=February 1991|publisher=[[Temple University Press]]|isbn=978-0-87722-827-1}}
* {{cite book|last=King|first=Adele |authorlink=Adele King|title=Camus's L'Etranger: Fifty Years on|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=FQexCwAAQBAJ|date=12 June 1992|publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]] UK|isbn=978-1-349-22003-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Bloom|first=Harold |authorlink=Harold Bloom|title=Albert Camus|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ihqHSbg41TUC|year=2009|publisher=[[Infobase Publishing]]|isbn=978-1-4381-1515-3}}
* {{cite book|author=Pierre Louis Rey|title=Camus: l'homme révolté|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=nFRlAAAAMAAJ|year=2006|publisher=Gallimard|isbn=978-2-07-031828-5}}
* {{cite book|last=Hawes|first=Elizabeth |authorlink=Elizabeth Hawes|title=Camus, a Romance|url=https://archive.org/details/camusromance00hawe|url-access=registration|year=2009|publisher=[[Grove Press]]|isbn=978-0-8021-1889-9}}
* {{cite book|last=Carroll|first=Sean B. |authorlink=Sean B. Carroll|title=Brave Genius: A Scientist, a Philosopher, and Their Daring Adventures from the French Resistance to the Nobel Prize|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=XchvDwAAQBAJ|year=2013|publisher=[[Crown Publishers]]|isbn=978-0-307-95234-9}}

==External links==
*[http://camusbibliography.boisestate.edu/ Albert Camus. Selective and Cumulative Bibliography]
*[http://www.uflib.ufl.edu/spec/camus/&lt;nowiki/&gt;Raymond Gay-Crosier Camus collection] at University of Florida Library
*[http://www.camus-society.com/ Albert Camus Society UK]

{{Camus}}
{{Navboxes
|title=Articles related to Albert Camus
|list=
{{The Stranger (Camus novel)}}
{{Nobel Prize in Literature Laureates 1951-1975}}
{{Continental philosophy}}
{{Existentialism}}
{{Social and political philosophy}}
{{Anarchism}}
}}
{{Portal bar|France|Biography}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Camus, Albert}}
[[Category:Albert Camus| ]]
[[Category:1913 births]]
[[Category:1960 deaths]]
[[Category:20th-century atheists]]
[[Category:20th-century essayists]]
[[Category:20th-century French dramatists and playwrights]]
[[Category:20th-century French male writers]]
[[Category:20th-century French novelists]]
[[Category:20th-century French philosophers]]
[[Category:20th-century short story writers]]
[[Category:Anarcho-communists]]
[[Category:Anarcho-pacifists]]
[[Category:Anarcho-syndicalists]]
[[Category:Anti-capitalists]]
[[Category:Anti-fascists]]
[[Category:Anti-Stalinist left]]
[[Category:Communist members of the French Resistance]]
[[Category:Continental philosophers]]
[[Category:French anarchists]]
[[Category:French anti–death penalty activists]]
[[Category:French atheists]]
[[Category:French Communist Party members]]
[[Category:French communists]]
[[Category:French essayists]]
[[Category:French expatriates in Algeria]]
[[Category:French humanists]]
[[Category:French journalists]]
[[Category:French Marxists]]
[[Category:French Nobel laureates]]
[[Category:French pacifists]]
[[Category:French people of Spanish descent]]
[[Category:French Resistance members]]
[[Category:French socialists]]
[[Category:Left-libertarians]]
[[Category:Libertarian socialists]]
[[Category:Légion d'honneur refusals]]
[[Category:Male essayists]]
[[Category:Modernist writers]]
[[Category:Nobel laureates in Literature]]
[[Category:People from Dréan]]
[[Category:Pieds-Noirs]]
[[Category:Road incident deaths in France]]
[[Category:University of Algiers alumni]]</text>
      <sha1>pxps2dustmj7t7uzmsd4gybwzdm7x9l</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
