  <page>
    <title>Applied ethics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>988</id>
    <revision>
      <id>934483412</id>
      <parentid>920731771</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-06T20:00:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wbm1058</username>
        <id>14383484</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>+ hatnote</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Practical ethics|the book|Practical Ethics}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2013}}
{{more footnotes|date=September 2011}}
'''Applied ethics''' refers to the practical application of moral considerations. It is [[ethics]] with respect to real-world actions and their moral considerations in the areas of private and public life, the professions, health, technology, law, and leadership.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oxfordbibliographies.com/view/document/obo-9780195396577/obo-9780195396577-0006.xml &quot;Applied Ethics&quot;] Oxford Bibliographies.
 Retrieved June 25, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; For example, the [[bioethics]] community is concerned with identifying the correct approach to moral issues in the life sciences, such as [[euthanasia]], the allocation of scarce health resources, or the use of human embryos in research.&lt;ref&gt;[https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/disability-care-rationing/ &quot;Disability and Health Care Rationing&quot;] Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy. Retrieved June 25, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/euthanasia-voluntary/ &quot;Voluntary Euthanasia&quot;] Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy. Retrieved June 25, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/stem-cells/ &quot;Ethics of Stem Cell Research&quot;] Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy. Retrieved June 25, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Environmental ethics]] is concerned with ecological issues such as the responsibility of government and corporations to clean up pollution.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iep.utm.edu/envi-eth/ &quot;Environmental Ethics&quot;] Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy. Retrieved June 25, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Business ethics]] includes questions regarding the duties or duty of 'whistleblowers' to the general public or their loyalty to their employers.&lt;ref&gt;[https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/ethics-business/ &quot;Business Ethics&quot;] Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy. Retrieved June 25, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Applied ethics has expanded the study of ethics beyond the realms of academic philosophical discourse.&lt;ref&gt;Bayertz, K. (2002) Self-enlightenment of Applied Ethics, in: Chadwick, R and Schroeder, D. (eds.) Applied Ethics, Vol1. 36-51, London: Routledge&lt;/ref&gt; The field of applied ethics, as it appears today, emerged from debate surrounding rapid medical and technological advances in the early 1970s and is now established as a subdiscipline of moral philosophy. However, applied ethics is, by its very nature, a multi-professional subject because it requires specialist understanding of the potential ethical issues in fields like medicine, business or information technology. Nowadays, [[ethical codes]] of conduct exist in almost every profession.&lt;ref&gt;Giorgini, V., Mecca, J. T., Gibson, C., Medeiros, K., Mumford, M. D., Connelly, S., &amp; Devenport, L. D. (2015). Researcher perceptions of ethical guidelines and codes of conduct. Accountability in research, 22(3), 123-138.&lt;/ref&gt;

An applied ethics approach to the examination of moral dilemmas can take many different forms but one of the most influential and most widely utilised approaches in bioethics and health care ethics is the four-principle approach developed by Tom Beauchamp and James Childress.&lt;ref&gt;Beauchamp, T. L. and Childress, J. F. (1994) Principles of medical ethics, New York: Oxford University Press.
&lt;/ref&gt; The four-principle approach, commonly termed [[principlism]], entails consideration and application of four prima facie ethical principles: autonomy, non-maleficence, beneficence, and justice. 


==Underpinning theory==
Applied ethics is distinguished from [[normative ethics]], which concerns standards for right and wrong behavior, and from [[meta-ethics]], which concerns the nature of ethical properties, statements, attitudes, and judgments.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iep.utm.edu/ap-ethic/#H7 &quot;Applied Ethics&quot;] Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy. Retrieved June 25, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;

Whilst these three areas of ethics appear to be distinct they are also interrelated. The use of an applied ethics approach often draws upon certain normative ethical theories like the following:

# [[Utilitarianism]], where the practical consequences of various policies are evaluated on the assumption that the right policy will be the one which results in the greatest happiness. This theory's main developments came from [[Jeremy Bentham]] and [[John Stuart Mill]] who distinguished between an act and rule utilitarianist morality. Later developments have also adjusted the theory, most notably [[Henry Sidgwick]] who introduced the idea of [[motive (law)|motive]] or [[intent]] in morality, and [[Peter Singer]] who introduced the idea of [[preference]] in moral decision making. 
# [[Deontological ethics]], notions based on 'rules' i.e. that there is an obligation to perform the 'right' action, regardless of actual consequences (epitomized by [[Immanuel Kant]]'s notion of the [[Categorical Imperative]] which was the centre to Kant's ethical theory based on [[duty]]). Another key deontological theory is [[Natural Law]], which was heavily developed by [[Thomas Aquinas]] and is an important part of the [[Catholic Church]]'s teaching on Morals. 
# [[Virtue ethics]], derived from Aristotle's and Confucius's notions, which asserts that the right action will be that chosen by a suitably 'virtuous' agent.

Sometimes, these normative ethical theories clash which poses challenges when trying to resolve real-world ethical dilemmas. One approach which attempts to overcome the seemingly impossible divide between deontology and utilitarianism (of which the divide is caused by the opposite takings of an [[absolute morality|absolute]] and [[Moral relativism|relativist]] moral view) is [[case-based reasoning]], also known as [[casuistry]]. Casuistry does not begin with theory, rather it starts with the immediate facts of a real and concrete case. While casuistry makes use of ethical theory, it does not view ethical theory as the most important feature of moral reasoning. Casuists, like Albert Jonsen and [[Stephen Toulmin]] (''The Abuse of Casuistry'' 1988), challenge the traditional [[paradigm]] of applied ethics. Instead of starting from theory and applying theory to a particular case, casuists start with the particular case itself and then ask what morally significant features (including both theory and practical considerations) ought to be considered for that particular case. In their observations of medical ethics committees, Jonsen and Toulmin note that a consensus on particularly problematic moral cases often emerges when participants focus on the facts of the case, rather than on [[ideology]] or [[theory]]. Thus, a Rabbi, a Catholic priest, and an agnostic might agree that, in this particular case, the best approach is to withhold extraordinary medical care, while disagreeing on the reasons that support their individual positions. By focusing on cases and not on theory, those engaged in moral debate increase the possibility of agreement.

==See also==
{{col div|colwidth=30em}}
*[[Bioethics]]
*[[Business ethics]]
*[[Effective altruism]]
*[[Ethical code]]s
*[[Ethics]]
*[[Medical ethics]]
*[[Outline of ethics]]
*[[Philosophy]]
*[[Precautionary principle]]
{{colend}}

==Bibliography==
&lt;references/&gt;
* {{Cite book| first=R.F. | last=Chadwick | year=1997 | title=Encyclopedia of Applied Ethics | chapter= | editor= | others= | pages= | location=London | publisher=Academic Press | isbn=0-12-227065-7  | url= | authorlink= }}
* {{Cite book| first=Peter | last=Singer | year=1993 | title=[[Practical Ethics]] | chapter= | editor= | others= | pages= | publisher=Cambridge University Press| isbn=0-521-43971-X | url= | authorlink= }} (monograph)
* {{Cite book| first=Andrew I. | last=Cohen | year=2005 | title=Contemporary Debates in Applied Ethics | chapter= | editor= | others= | pages= | publisher=Wiley-Blackwell | isbn=978-1-4051-1548-3 | url= | authorlink= }}
* {{Cite book| first=Hugh | last=LaFollette | year=2002 | title=Ethics in Practice (2nd Edition) | chapter= | editor= | others= | pages= | publisher=Blackwell Publishing| isbn=0-631-22834-9 | url= | authorlink= }}
* {{Cite book| first=Peter | last=Singer | year=1986 | title=Applied Ethics | chapter= | editor= | others= | pages= | publisher=Oxford University Press| isbn=0-19-875067-6 | url= | authorlink= }}
* {{Cite book| first=R.G. | last=Frey | year=2004 | title=A Companion to Applied Ethics | chapter= | editor= | others= | pages= | publisher=Blackwell | isbn=1-4051-3345-7 | url= | authorlink= }}

==External links==
{{Library resources box}}
* Standard Bibliography PhilPapers [https://philpapers.org/browse/applied-ethics Applied Ethics - Bibliography - PhilPapers]
* Chris Young, [http://www.chrisyoung.net/writings/how-to-teach-intro-to-applied-ethics.html How to teach an introduction to applied ethics]
* [http://www.arts.unsw.edu.au/aapae/ Australian Association for Professional and Applied Ethics]
* [http://www.bioethicsinstitute.org Berman Institute of Bioethics, Johns Hopkins Institute]
* [http://www.ccepa.ca/ Canadian Centre for Ethics in Public Affairs]
* [http://www.etica-aplicata.ro Centre for Advanced Research in Management and Applied Ethics]
* [https://www.practicalbioethics.org Center for Practical Bioethics]
* [http://www.crb.uu.se/ Centre for Research Ethics and Bioethics]
* [http://macleanethics.uchicago.edu MacLean Center for Clinical Medical Ethics]
* [http://www.scu.edu/ethics Markkula Center for Applied Ethics at Santa Clara University]
* [http://www.ethics.ubc.ca W. Maurice Young Centre for Applied Ethics at the University of British Columbia]
* [http://nuffieldbioethics.org Nuffield Council on Bioethics]

{{Ethics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Applied Ethics}}
[[Category:Applied ethics|*]]
[[Category:Ethics]]</text>
      <sha1>i2cutirjzo80ov7dl1utpzjga78viez</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
