  <page>
    <title>Agatha Christie</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>984</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942451237</id>
      <parentid>942451163</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-24T19:27:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>188.27.148.22</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|English mystery and detective writer (1890–1976)}}
{{Use British English|date=March 2012}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2020}}
{{Infobox writer &lt;!-- for more information see [[:Template:Infobox writer/doc]] --&gt;
| honorific_prefix = '''Dame'''
| name = Agatha Christie&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;Lady Mallowan&lt;/small&gt;
| honorific_suffix = {{Post-nominals|country=GBR|size=100|DBE}}
| image = Agatha Christie in 1925.jpg
| caption = Agatha Christie in 1925
| pseudonym = Mary Westmacott
| birth_name = Agatha Mary Clarissa Miller
| birth_date = {{Birth date|df=y|1890|9|15}}
| birth_place = [[Torquay]], Devon, England
| death_date = {{Death date and age|df=y|1976|1|12|1890|9|15}}
| death_place = Winterbrook House, [[Winterbrook]], Oxfordshire, England&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;
| resting_place = Church of St Mary, [[Cholsey]], Oxfordshire, England
| occupation = Novelist, short story writer, playwright, poet, memoirist
| genre = Murder mystery, thriller, crime fiction, detective, romance
| movement = [[Golden Age of Detective Fiction]]
| notableworks = Creation of characters [[Hercule Poirot]] and [[Miss Marple]], ''[[Murder on the Orient Express]]'', ''[[The Murder of Roger Ackroyd]]'', ''[[Death on the Nile]]'', ''[[The Murder at the Vicarage]]'', ''[[Partners in Crime (short story collection)|Partners in Crime]]'', ''[[The A.B.C. Murders]]'', ''[[And Then There Were None]]'', ''[[The Mousetrap]]''
| signature = Agatha Christie's signature.png
| spouses = {{unbulleted list | {{marriage|[[Archie Christie|Archibald Christie]]|1914|1928|end=div}} {{marriage|[[Max Mallowan|Sir Max Mallowan]]|1930}}}}
| children = 1
| relatives = [[James Watts (British politician)|James Watts]] (nephew)
| website = {{URL|agathachristie.com}}
| alt = Christie in 1925
}}
'''Dame Agatha Mary Clarissa Christie, Lady Mallowan''', {{Post-nominals|country=GBR|size=100%|DBE}} (née '''Miller'''; 15 September 1890&amp;nbsp;– 12 January 1976) was an English writer known for her 66 detective novels and 14 short story collections, particularly those revolving around fictional detectives [[Hercule Poirot]] and [[Miss Marple]]. She also wrote the world's longest-running play ''[[The Mousetrap]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;Mousetrap&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Agatha Christie's: The Mousetrap|url=https://www.the-mousetrap.co.uk/online/default.asp|publisher=St. Martin's Theatre|accessdate=8 March 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120626071333/https://www.the-mousetrap.co.uk/Online/default.asp|archive-date=26 June 2012|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; and six romances under the pen name '''Mary Westmacott'''. In 1971, she was appointed a [[Dame Commander of the Order of the British Empire]] (DBE) for her contribution to literature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=David Scott|last=Kastan|year=2006|title=The Oxford Encyclopedia of British Literature|volume=1|page=467|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-516921-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.oxfordreference.com/view/10.1093/acref/9780195169218.001.0001/acref-9780195169218-e-0098 Reitz, C. (2006). Christie, Agatha. In The Oxford Encyclopedia of British Literature. : Oxford University Press. Retrieved 24 Oct. 2019]&lt;/ref&gt;

Christie was born into a wealthy upper-middle-class family in [[Torquay]], Devon. She served in a Devon hospital during the [[First World War]], tending to troops coming back from the trenches. She was initially an unsuccessful writer with six consecutive rejections,&lt;ref name=&quot;curran&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Curran|first1=John|title=75 facts about Christie|url=http://www.agathachristie.com/about-christie/christie-experts/john-curran-75-facts-about-christie|website=agathachristie.com|publisher=Agatha Christie Limited|accessdate=21 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; but this changed when ''[[The Mysterious Affair at Styles]]'' was published in 1920 featuring Hercule Poirot.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Fitzgibbon|first1=Russell H.|title=The Agatha Christie Companion|url=https://archive.org/details/agathachristieco00fitz|url-access=registration|date=1980|publisher=Popular Press|page=[https://archive.org/details/agathachristieco00fitz/page/18 18]}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the Second World War, she worked as a pharmacy assistant at University College Hospital, London, acquiring a good knowledge of poisons which feature in many of her novels.

''[[Guinness World Records]]'' lists Christie as the best-selling novelist of all time. Her novels have sold roughly 2 billion copies, and her estate claims that her works come third in the rankings of the world's most-widely published books,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Independent 2015&quot;/&gt; behind only [[William Shakespeare|Shakespeare's]] works and the Bible. According to [[Index Translationum]], she remains the [[list of most-translated individual authors|most-translated individual author]], having been translated into at least 103 languages.&lt;ref name=McWhirter/&gt; ''[[And Then There Were None]]'' is Christie's best-selling novel, with 100 million sales to date, making it the world's best-selling mystery ever and one of the best-selling books of all time.&lt;ref name=BestSeller/&gt; Christie's stage play ''The Mousetrap'' holds the world record for longest initial run. It opened at the [[Ambassadors Theatre (London)|Ambassadors Theatre]] in the [[West End theatre|West End]] on 25 November 1952, and {{as of|April 2019|lc=y}} was still running after more than 27,000 performances.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.the-mousetrap.co.uk/Online ''The Mousetrap'' website] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150623162102/https://www.the-mousetrap.co.uk/Online/ |date=23 June 2015 }}, the-mousetrap.co.uk. Retrieved 2 June 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://artsbeat.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/01/26/london-theater-journal-comfortably-mousetrapped/|title=London Theater Journal: Comfortably Mousetrapped|work=The New York Times|date=26 January 2012|accessdate=26 January 2012|first=Ben|last=Brantley}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1955, Christie was the first recipient of the [[Mystery Writers of America]]'s [[MWA Grand Master Award|Grand Master Award]]. Later the year, ''[[Witness for the Prosecution (play)|Witness for the Prosecution]]'' received an [[Edgar Award]] from the MWA for best play.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://theedgars.com/awards/|title=Edgars Database – Search the Edgars Database|website=theedgars.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In 2013, ''[[The Murder of Roger Ackroyd]]'' was voted the best crime novel ever by 600 writers of the [[Crime Writers' Association]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/books/news/agatha-christies-the-murder-of-roger-ackroyd-voted-best-crime-novel-ever-8923395.html|title=Agatha Christie's ''The Murder of Roger Ackroyd'' voted best crime novel ever|work=The Independent|accessdate=19 February 2014|first=Jonathan|last=Brown|date=5 November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 15 September 2015, coinciding with her 125th birthday, ''[[And Then There Were None]]'' was named the &quot;World's Favourite Christie&quot; in a vote sponsored by the author's estate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2015/sep/01/and-then-there-were-none-declared-worlds-favourite-agatha-christie-novel|title=And Then There Were None declared world's favourite Agatha Christie novel|first=Alison|last=Flood|date=1 September 2015|website=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most of her books and short stories have been adapted for television, radio, video games, and comics, and more than 30 feature films have been based on her work.

==Life and career==
===Childhood and adolescence: 1890–1910===
Agatha Mary Clarissa Miller&lt;!-- Christie comes from her first marriage. --&gt; was born on 15 September 1890 into a wealthy [[upper-middle-class]] family in Torquay, Devon. She was the youngest of three children born to Frederick Alvah (&quot;Fred&quot;) Miller, &quot;a [[gentleman]] of substance&quot;, and his wife Clarissa Margaret (&quot;Clara&quot;) Miller née Boehmer.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books/about/Agatha_Christie.html?id=w4paAAAAMAAJ|title=Agatha Christie: A Biography|last=Morgan|first=Janet P.|date=1984|publisher=HarperCollins|year=|isbn=978-0-00-216330-9|location=London, UK|page=|pages=|access-date=8 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|1–4}}&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;''Marriage Register''. St Peter's Church, Bayswater [Notting Hill], Middlesex, 1878, No. 399, p. 200.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Birth Certificate''. General Register Office (England &amp; Wales), 1890 September Quarter, NEWTON ABBOT, volume 5b, page 151. [Christie's forenames were not registered.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;''Baptism Register''. Parish of Tormohun, Devon, 1890, No. 267, [n.p.].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:5&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|title=OBITUARY Dame Agatha Christie|date=13 January 1976|work=The Times|page=16}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Rp|16|quote=&quot;My father&quot;, she [Christie] recalled, &quot;was a gentleman of substance, and never did a handsturn in his life, and he was a most agreeable man&quot;.}}

Christie's mother Clara was born in [[Dublin]] in 1854{{Refn|Most biographers give Christie's mother's place of birth as Belfast but do not provide sources. Current primary evidence, including various census entries (place of birth Dublin), her baptism record (March 1854, garrison chapel Dublin), and her father's service record and Regimental histories (for when her father was in Dublin), indicates she was almost certainly born in Dublin in the first Quarter of 1854.|group=lower-alpha}}&lt;ref&gt;''1871 England Census.'' Class: RG10; Piece: 3685; Folio: 134; Page: 44&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://discovery.nationalarchives.gov.uk/details/r/C178476 Statement of Services]: Frederick Boehmer, 91st Foot. The National Archives, Kew. WO 76/456, page 57. [Also states his daughter Clarissa Margaret was baptised in Dublin.]&lt;/ref&gt; to Lieutenant (later Captain) Frederick Boehmer ([[91st (Argyllshire Highlanders) Regiment of Foot|91st Regiment of Foot]])&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/historicalrecord00goffuoft/page/218|title=Historical records of the 91st Argyllshire Highlanders, now the 1st Battalion Princess Louise's Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders, containing an account of the Regiment in 1794, and of its subsequent services to 1881|last=Goff|first=Gerald Lionel Joseph|publisher=R. Bentley|year=1891|isbn=|location=|pages=218–219, 322}}&lt;/ref&gt; and his second wife Mary Ann Boehmer née West. Boehmer died aged 49 of bronchitis (although biographers often claim he was killed in a riding accident) in [[Jersey]] in April 1863, leaving his widow to raise Clara and her three brothers alone on a meagre income.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Burials in the Parish of St Helier, in the Island of Jersey.|last=|first=|publisher=|year=1863|isbn=|location=|pages=303}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two weeks after Boehmer's death, Mary's sister Margaret West married widowed dry goods merchant Nathaniel Frary Miller, a U.S. citizen.&lt;ref&gt;''[https://www.familysearch.org/ark:/61903/3:1:S3HY-6LM7-W15?i=299 Marriage Register]''. Parish of Westbourne, Sussex, 1863, No. 318, p. 159.&lt;/ref&gt; To assist Mary financially, the newlyweds agreed to foster nine-year old Clara. The family settled in [[Timperley]], Cheshire.&lt;ref&gt;[https://discovery.nationalarchives.gov.uk/details/r/C7314015 Naturalisation Papers]: Miller, Nathaniel Frary, from the United States. Certificate 4798 issued 25 August 1865. The National Archives, Kew. HO 1/123/4798.&lt;/ref&gt; Margaret and Nathaniel had no children together, but Nathaniel had a seventeen-year-old son, Fred Miller, from his previous marriage. Fred was born in New York City and travelled extensively after leaving his Swiss boarding school. He and Clara eventually formed a romantic attachment and were married in [[St Peter's, Notting Hill|St Peter's Church]], [[Notting Hill]], in April 1878.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;/&gt;{{rp|2–5}}&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;

Fred and Clara's first child, Margaret Frary (&quot;Madge&quot;), was born in Torquay in 1879,&lt;ref&gt;''Birth Certificate''. General Register Office (England &amp; Wales), 1879 March Quarter, NEWTON ABBOT, volume 5b, page 162.&lt;/ref&gt; where the couple were renting lodgings. Their second child, Louis Montant (&quot;Monty&quot;), was born in [[Morristown, New Jersey|Morristown]], [[Morristown, New Jersey|New Jersey]], in 1880&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Births|date=26 June 1880|work=London Evening Standard|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; while they were making an extended visit to the United States. When Fred's father died in 1869,&lt;ref&gt;''Death Certificate''. General Register Office (England &amp; Wales), 1869 June Quarter, WESTBOURNE, volume 02B, page 230.&lt;/ref&gt; he left Clara £2000; they used this money to purchase the leasehold of a villa in Torquay named [[Ashfield, Torquay|Ashfield]] in which to raise their family. It was here that their third and final child, Agatha, was born in 1890.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;/&gt;{{rp|6–7}}&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Agatha Christie as a child No 1.jpg|thumb|150px|Christie as a girl, date unknown|alt=]]
Christie described her childhood as &quot;very happy&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Auto1993&quot; /&gt;{{rp|3}} She was surrounded by a series of strong and independent women from an early age.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;/&gt;{{rp|14}} She lived primarily in Devon, but made occasional visits to the homes of her step-grandmother/great-aunt Margaret Miller in [[Ealing]] and maternal grandmother Mary Boehmer in [[Bayswater]]. One year of her childhood was spent abroad with her family, in the [[Pyrenees|French Pyrenees]], Paris, [[Dinard]], and [[Guernsey]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;/&gt;{{rp|15, 24–25}}

Christie was raised in a household with various [[esotericism|esoteric]] beliefs and, like her siblings, believed that her mother Clara was a psychic with the ability of [[second sight]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;/&gt;{{rp|13}} Christie's sister Madge had been sent to [[Roedean School]] in Sussex for her education, but their mother insisted that Christie receive a [[home education]]. As a result, her parents were responsible for teaching her to read and write and to master basic arithmetic, a subject she particularly enjoyed. They also taught her music, and she learned to play both the piano and the mandolin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;/&gt;{{rp|20–21}} According to one biographer, Clara believed that Christie should not learn to read until she was eight. However, thanks to her own curiosity, Christie taught herself to read much earlier.&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|18}} One of the earliest known photographs of Christie depicts her as a little girl with her first dog, named George Washington by her patriotic father but which she called Tony.&lt;ref name=&quot;Auto1993&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|20–21, 42}}

Christie was a voracious reader from an early age. Among her earliest memories were those of reading the children's books written by [[Mary Louisa Molesworth|Mrs Molesworth]], including ''The Adventures of Herr Baby'' (1881), ''Christmas Tree Land'' (1897), and ''The Magic Nuts'' (1898). She also read the work of [[Edith Nesbit]], including ''[[The Story of the Treasure Seekers]]'' (1899), ''[[The Phoenix and the Carpet]]'' (1903), and ''[[The Railway Children]]'' (1906). When a little older, she moved on to reading the surreal verse of [[Edward Lear]] and [[Lewis Carroll]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;/&gt;{{rp|18–19}} In April 1901, at age 10, she wrote her first poem, &quot;The cowslip&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;film&quot;&gt;{{cite av media|title=The Mystery of Agatha Christie&amp;nbsp;– A Trip With David Suchet (Directed by Claire Lewins)|publisher=Testimony films (for ITV)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although she devoted much time to her pets, Christie spent much of her childhood apart from other children. She eventually made friends with a group of other girls in Torquay, noting that &quot;one of the highlights of my existence&quot; was her appearance with them in a youth production of [[Gilbert and Sullivan]]'s ''[[The Yeomen of the Guard]]'', in which she played the hero, Colonel Fairfax.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;/&gt;{{rp|23–27}} This was her last operatic role for, as she later wrote, &quot;an experience that you really enjoyed should never be repeated.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Auto1993&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Agatha Christie: An Autobiography|url=https://archive.org/details/agathachristieau00chri|url-access=registration|last=Christie|first=Agatha|date=|publisher=Dodd, Mead &amp; Company|year=1977|isbn=0-396-07516-9|location=New York City|page=|pages=|orig-year=1977}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|114}}

By 1901, Christie's father's health had deteriorated, due to what he believed were heart problems.&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|33}} Fred died in November 1901 from pneumonia and chronic kidney disease.&lt;ref&gt;''Death Certificate''. General Register Office (England &amp; Wales), 1901 December Quarter, BRENTFORD, volume 3A, page 71. (&quot;Cause of Death. Bright's disease, chronic. Pneumonia. Coma and heart failure.&quot;)&lt;/ref&gt; The family's financial situation had by this time declined significantly. Christie and her mother Clara continued to live in their Torquay home. Christie's sister Madge married the year after their father's death and moved to [[Cheadle, Greater Manchester|Cheadle]], ([[Historic counties of England|historic county]] of) Cheshire. Christie's brother Monty was overseas, serving in a British regiment. Christie later claimed that her father's death, occurring when she was 11 years old, marked the end of her childhood.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;/&gt;{{rp|32–34}}

In 1902, Christie began attending Miss Guyer's Girls' School in Torquay but found it difficult to adjust to the disciplined atmosphere. In 1905, she was sent to Paris where she was educated in three ''[[Pension (lodging)|pensions]]''&amp;nbsp;– Mademoiselle Cabernet's, Les Marroniers, and then Miss Dryden's&amp;nbsp;– the last of which served primarily as a finishing school.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot; /&gt;{{rp|22–23, 37}}

===Early literary attempts and the First World War: 1910–1919===
After completing her education, Christie returned to England and found her mother ailing. They decided to spend time together in the warmer climate of [[Cairo]], then a regular tourist destination for wealthy Britons. They stayed for three months at the [[Gezirah Palace]] Hotel. Christie attended many social functions and particularly enjoyed watching polo. She visited ancient Egyptian monuments such as the [[Great Pyramid of Giza]], but did not exhibit the great interest in [[archaeology]] and [[Egyptology]] that became prominent in her later years.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;/&gt;{{rp|40–41}} Returning to [[Britain (place name)|Britain]], she continued her social activities, writing and performing in amateur theatricals. She also helped put on a play called ''The Blue Beard of Unhappiness'' with female friends. Her writing extended to both poetry and music. Some early works saw publication, but she decided against focusing on writing or music as future professions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;/&gt;{{rp|45–47}}

Christie wrote her first short story, ''The House of Beauty'' (an early version of her later-published story ''[[While the Light Lasts and Other Stories|The House of Dreams]]'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agathachristie.com/christies-work/stories/the-house-of-dreams/377 ''The House of Dreams'': Details], agathachristie.com. Retrieved 7 August 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;) while recovering in bed from an undisclosed illness. This was about 6,000 words on the topic of &quot;madness and dreams&quot;, a subject of fascination for her. One of her biographers has commented that, despite &quot;infelicities of style&quot;, the story was nevertheless &quot;compelling&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;/&gt;{{rp|48–49}} Other stories followed, most of them illustrating her interest in spiritualism and the paranormal. These included &quot;[[The Hound of Death#The Call of Wings|The Call of Wings]]&quot; and &quot;[[While the Light Lasts and Other Stories|The Little Lonely God]]&quot;. Magazines rejected all her early submissions, made under pseudonyms (including Mac Miller, Nathaniel Miller, and Sydney West), although some submissions were revised and published later, often with new titles.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;/&gt;{{rp|49–50}}

Christie then set her first novel, ''Snow Upon the Desert'', in [[Cairo]] and drew from her recent experiences in that city, writing under the pseudonym Monosyllaba. She was disappointed when the various publishers she contacted all declined.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;/&gt;{{rp|50–51}} Clara suggested that her daughter ask for advice from a family friend and neighbour, the writer [[Eden Philpotts]], who obliged her enquiry, encouraged her writing, and sent her an introduction to his own literary agent, Hughes Massie, who rejected ''Snow Upon the Desert'' and suggested a second novel.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;/&gt;{{rp|51–52}} Meanwhile, her social activities expanded. She entered into short-lived relationships with four separate men and an engagement with another.&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|64–67}} She then met [[Archie Christie|Archibald Christie]] at a dance given by [[Baron Clifford of Chudleigh|Lord and Lady Clifford]] at [[Ugbrooke]], about {{convert|12|mi|0|abbr=off}} from Torquay. Archie was born in [[British India|India]], the son of a [[barrister]] in the [[Indian Civil Service]]. He was an army officer who was seconded to the [[Royal Flying Corps]] in April 1913. The couple quickly fell in love. Upon learning that he would be stationed in [[Farnborough Airfield|Farnborough]], Archie proposed marriage, and Agatha accepted.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;/&gt;{{rp|54–63}}

With the outbreak of the [[First World War]] in August 1914, Archie was sent to France to fight the [[German Army (German Empire)|German forces]]. They married on the afternoon of Christmas Eve 1914 at Emmanuel Church, [[Clifton, Bristol|Clifton]], Bristol, which was close to the home of his mother and stepfather, while Archie was on home leave.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Curtis|first1=Fay|date=24 December 2014|title=Desert Island Doc: Agatha Christie's wartime wedding|url=http://www.bristolmuseums.org.uk/blog/desert-island-doc-agatha-christies-wartime-wedding|publisher=Bristol Museums, Galleries &amp; Archives|accessdate=30 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Marriage Register''. Parish of Emmanuel, Clifton, 1914, No. 305, p. 153.&lt;/ref&gt; Rising through the ranks, he was eventually stationed back to Britain in September 1918 as a colonel in the [[Air Ministry]]. Christie involved herself in the war effort as a member of the [[Voluntary Aid Detachment]] of the [[Red Cross]]. From October 1914 to May 1915, then from June 1916 to September 1918, she worked a total of 3400 hours in the Town Hall Red Cross Hospital, Torquay, first as a nurse (unpaid) then as a dispenser (at £16 a year from 1917) after qualifying as an apothecaries' assistant.&lt;ref name=&quot;BRC&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://vad.redcross.org.uk/Agatha-Christie|title=Agatha Christie {{!}} British Red Cross|website=|publisher=British Red Cross|url-status=live|accessdate=26 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|69}} Her war service ended when Archie was reassigned to London, and they rented a flat in [[St. John's Wood]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;/&gt;{{rp|73–74}}

===First novels and Poirot: 1919–1926===
Christie had long been a fan of detective novels, having enjoyed  [[Wilkie Collins]]'s ''[[The Woman in White (novel)|The Woman in White]]'' and ''[[The Moonstone]]'', as well as [[Sir Arthur Conan Doyle]]'s early [[Sherlock Holmes]] stories. She wrote her own detective novel, ''[[The Mysterious Affair at Styles]]'', featuring [[Hercule Poirot]], a former [[Belgians|Belgian]] police officer noted for his twirly large &quot;magnificent moustaches&quot; and egg-shaped head. Poirot had taken refuge in Britain after Germany invaded [[Belgium]]. Christie's inspiration for the character stemmed from real Belgian refugees who were living in Torquay and the Belgian soldiers whom she helped to treat as a volunteer nurse in Torquay during the First World War.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;/&gt;{{rp|75–79}} She began working on ''The Mysterious Affair at Styles'' in 1916, writing much of it on [[Dartmoor]].&lt;ref name=&quot;film&quot;/&gt; Her original manuscript was rejected by such publishing companies as [[Hodder and Stoughton]] and [[Methuen Publishing|Methuen]]. After keeping the submission for several months, [[John Lane (publisher)|John Lane]] at [[The Bodley Head]] offered to accept it, provided that Christie change the ending. She did so, and signed a contract which she later felt was exploitative.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;/&gt;{{rp|79, 81–82}} It was finally published in 1920.&lt;ref name=&quot;film&quot;/&gt;

Christie, meanwhile, settled into married life, giving birth to her only child, Rosalind Margaret Clarissa, in August 1919 at [[Ashfield, Torquay|Ashfield]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;/&gt;{{rp|79}}&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|340,349,422}} [[Archie Christie|Archie]] left the Air Force at the end of the war and started working in [[The City of London|the City]] financial sector at a relatively low salary, though they still employed a maid.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;/&gt;{{rp|80–81}} Her second novel, ''[[The Secret Adversary]]'' (1922), featured a new detective couple [[Tommy and Tuppence]], again published by The Bodley Head. It earned her £50. A third novel again featured Poirot, ''[[Murder on the Links]]'' (1923), as did short stories commissioned by Bruce Ingram, editor of ''[[The Sketch]]'' magazine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;/&gt;{{rp|83}}

In 1922, the Christies joined an around-the-world promotional tour for the [[British Empire Exhibition]], led by Major [[Ernest Belcher]]. Leaving their daughter with Agatha's mother and sister, in ten months they travelled to South Africa, Australia, New Zealand, Hawaii, and Canada.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot; /&gt;{{rp|86–103}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Grand Tour: Around The World With The Queen Of Mystery|last=Prichard|first=Mathew|publisher=HarperCollins Publishers|year=2012|isbn=978-0-06-219122-9|location=New York City|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; They learned to surf prone in South Africa; then, in [[Waikiki]], they were among the first Britons to [[Surfing|surf]] standing up.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2011/jul/29/agatha-christie-hercule-poirot-surfing-secret|title=Agatha Christie's Surfing Secret Revealed|newspaper=The Guardian|date=29 July 2011|accessdate=30 July 2011|first=Sam|last=Jones}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/books/8670354/Agatha-Christie-one-of-Britains-first-stand-up-surfers.html|title=Agatha Christie 'one of Britain's first stand-up surfers'|work=The Daily Telegraph|date=29 July 2011|accessdate=30 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following their return to England, Archie resumed work in [[City of London|the City]], while Christie continued to work hard at her writing. After a series of apartments in London, they moved to the country, eventually purchasing a house in [[Sunningdale]], Berkshire, which they renamed Styles after the mansion in Christie's first detective novel.&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|154–155}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|124–125}}

Christie's mother died in April 1926. They had been exceptionally close, and the loss sent Christie into a deep depression.&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|168–172}}

===Disappearance: 1926===
[[File:Christie at Hydro.jpg|thumb|right|''[[Daily Herald (UK newspaper)|Daily Herald]]'', 15 December 1926, announcing that Christie had been found]]
In August 1926, Archie asked Christie for a divorce. He had fallen in love with Nancy Neele, who had been a friend of Major Belcher. On 3 December 1926, the pair quarrelled after Archie announced his plan to spend the weekend with friends, unaccompanied by his wife. Late that evening, Christie disappeared from her home. Her [[Morris Cowley]] car was found at [[Newlands Corner]], perched above a chalk quarry with an expired driving licence and clothes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|135}}&lt;ref name=hpcentral2&gt;{{cite web |title=Agatha's Disappearance|url=http://www.poirot.us/disappear.php|publisher=Hercule Poirot Central|last1=Hobbs|first1=James|accessdate=21 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ChristieLife&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.agathachristie.com/about-christie#christies-life |title=Christie's Life: 1925–1928 A Difficult Start |access-date=12 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The disappearance caused a public outcry. Home secretary [[William Joynson-Hicks]] pressured police, and a newspaper offered a £100 reward. Over a thousand police officers, 15,000 volunteers, and several aeroplanes scoured the rural landscape. [[Sir Arthur Conan Doyle]] gave a spirit medium one of Christie's gloves to find her.{{Refn|Crime novelist [[Dorothy L. Sayers]] visited the &quot;scene of the disappearance&quot; and used the scenario in her book ''[[Unnatural Death (novel)|Unnatural Death]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;thorpe&quot;/&gt;|group=lower-alpha}} Christie's disappearance was featured on the front page of ''[[The New York Times]]''. Despite the extensive manhunt, she was not found for 10 days.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Mrs Christie Found in a Yorkshire Spa|newspaper=The New York Times|date=15 December 1926|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1926/12/15/archives/mrs-christie-found-in-a-yorkshire-spa-missing-novelist-under-an.html|accessdate=16 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;thorpe&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2006/oct/15/books.booksnews|title=Christie's most famous mystery solved at last|last=Thorpe|first=Vanessa|date=15 October 2006|newspaper=The Guardian|accessdate=21 May 2013|location=London, UK}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Harrogate&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|title=Agatha Christie's Harrogate mystery|publisher=BBC News|date=3 December 2009|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/local/york/hi/people_and_places/history/newsid_8393000/8393552.stm|accessdate=17 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 14 December 1926, she was found at the [[Old Swan Hotel|Swan Hydropathic Hotel]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.classiclodges.co.uk/the-old-swan/agatha-christie/|title=THE DETAILS OF THIS STRANGE CASE…|year=2019|website=|url-status=live|access-date=27 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Harrogate]], Yorkshire, registered as Mrs Tressa{{Refn|The notice placed by Christie in ''[[The Times]]'' (11 December 1926, p.1) gives the first name as Teresa, but her hotel register signature more naturally reads Tressa and newspapers also reported that Christie used Tressa on other occasions during her disappearance.|group=lower-alpha}} Neele (the surname of her husband's lover) from &quot;Capetown S.A.&quot; (South Africa). The next day, Christie left for her sister's residence at [[Abney Hall]], Cheadle, where she was sequestered &quot;in guarded hall, gates locked, telephone cut off, and callers turned away.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=WHAT WE WANT TO KNOW ABOUT MRS. CHRISTIE..|date=16 December 1926|work=The Leeds Mercury}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Rp|1,4,9}}&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|title=WHAT WE WANT TO KNOW ABOUT MRS. CHRISTIE..|date=17 December 1926|work=The Leeds Mercury}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Rp|1}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|146}}&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|196}}

Christie's autobiography makes no reference to the disappearance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Auto1993&quot;/&gt; Two doctors diagnosed her as suffering from &quot;an unquestionable genuine loss of memory&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|1}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Western Daily Press|date=17 December 1926|work=Western Daily Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Rp|12}} yet opinion remains divided over the reason for her disappearance. Some believe that she disappeared during a [[fugue state]], including her biographer Janet Morgan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|154–159}}&lt;ref name=&quot;thorpe&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;disfugue&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|title=Dissociative Fugue|newspaper=Psychology Today|date=17 March 2012|url=http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/hide-and-seek/201203/dissociative-fugue-the-mystery-agatha-christie|accessdate=17 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast, Jared Cade's research led him to conclude that Christie deliberately planned the event to embarrass her husband, but did not anticipate the public melodrama that resulted.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Cade|first=Jared|title=Agatha Christie and the Missing Eleven Days|year=1997|publisher=Peter Owen|isbn=0-7206-1112-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Rp|121}} Laura Thompson provides the alternative view that Christie disappeared during a nervous breakdown, conscious of her actions but not in emotional control of herself.&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|220–221}} Public reaction at the time was largely negative, supposing a publicity stunt or an attempt to frame her husband for murder.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Adams|first=Cecil|title=Why did mystery writer Agatha Christie mysteriously disappear?|newspaper=The Chicago Reader|date=2 April 1982|url=http://www.straightdope.com/columns/read/361/why-did-mystery-writer-agatha-christie-mysteriously-disappear|accessdate=19 May 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Refn|group=lower-alpha|Christie herself hinted at a nervous breakdown, saying to a woman with similar symptoms, &quot;I think you had better be very careful; it is probably the beginning of a nervous breakdown.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Auto1993&quot;/&gt;{{rp|337}}}}

=== Second marriage and later life: 1927–1976 ===
[[File:Hotel Pera Palace - Istanbul.jpg|thumb|Christie's room at the [[Pera Palace Hotel]] in Istanbul, where she wrote ''[[Murder on the Orient Express]]''|alt=]]
In January 1927, Christie, looking &quot;very pale&quot;, sailed with her daughter and secretary to [[Las Palmas]], Canary Islands, to &quot;complete her convalescence&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=MRS. CHRISTIE LEAVES|date=24 January 1927|work=Daily Herald|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; returning three months later.&lt;ref&gt;[https://discovery.nationalarchives.gov.uk/details/r/C9438379 Inwards Passenger Lists]. The National Archives, Kew. Board of Trade: Commercial and Statistical Department and successors, BT26/837/112.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Refn|Christie's authorised biographer includes an account of specialist psychiatric treatment following Christie's disappearance, but the information was obtained at second- or third-hand after her death.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot;/&gt;{{rp|148–149,159}}|group=lower-alpha}} Christie petitioned for divorce and was granted a [[decree nisi]] against her husband in April 1928 which was made [[Decree nisi|absolute]] in October 1928. Archie married Nancy Neele a week later.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Col. Christie Married.|date=6 November 1928|work=Gloucestershire Echo|page=5.  [Includes divorce details]|note=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Christie retained custody of their daughter Rosalind and the Christie surname for her writing. During their marriage, she published six novels, a collection of short stories, and a number of short stories in magazines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Agatha (Mary Clarissa) Christie |url=http://go.galegroup.com/ps/i.do?id=GALE%7CH1000017972&amp;v=2.1&amp;u=wes_ttda&amp;it=r&amp;p=CA&amp;sw=w&amp;asid=15652a6a75609ed59f3445558f6dfcc7 |website=Gale |publisher=Gale |accessdate=22 January 2019|archivedate=11 September 2015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150911122117/http://go.galegroup.com/ps/i.do?id=GALE%7CH1000017972&amp;v=2.1&amp;u=wes_ttda&amp;it=r&amp;p=CA&amp;sw=w&amp;asid=15652a6a75609ed59f3445558f6dfcc7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some years later, reflecting on the whole period, Christie said, &quot;So, after illness, came sorrow, despair and heartbreak. There is no need to dwell on it.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Auto1993&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|340}}

In autumn 1928, Christie left England and took the [[Orient Express|(Simplon) Orient Express]] to [[Istanbul]]; she subsequently went on to [[Baghdad]]. In [[Iraq]], she became friends with archaeologist [[Leonard Woolley]] and his wife, who invited her to return to their dig in February 1930. On that second trip, she met a young archaeologist 13 years her junior,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.freebmd.org.uk/cgi/information.pl?cite=X/BgKHlbCh8EpgSzBDoLGQ&amp;scan=1|title=FreeBMD Entry Info|website=freebmd.org.uk|accessdate=11 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Max Mallowan]]. In a 1977 interview, Mallowan recounted his first meeting with Christie, when he took her and a group of tourists on a tour of his expedition site in Iraq.&lt;ref name=&quot;max&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Interview with Max Mallowan|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/archive/agatha_christie/12508.shtml|publisher=BBC|accessdate=21 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Christie and Mallowan married in September 1930.&lt;ref&gt;''Marriage Certificate''. Scotland – Statutory Register of Marriages, 685/04 0938, 11 September 1930, District of St Giles, Edinburgh.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|284–285}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|178–179}} Their marriage was happy and lasted until Christie's death in 1976.&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson&quot;&gt;{{Citation|last=Thompson|first=Laura|title=Agatha Christie: An English Mystery|place=London, UK|publisher=Headline Review|year=2008|isbn=978-0-7553-1488-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[File:Agatha Christie with Max Mallowan in Tell Halaf 1930s.jpg|thumb|Christie with Max Mallowan in [[Tell Halaf]], 1930s|alt=]]
Christie frequently used settings that were familiar to her for her stories. She often accompanied Mallowan on his archaeological expeditions, and her travels with him contributed background to several of her novels set in the Middle East.&lt;ref name=&quot;max&quot;/&gt; Other novels (such as ''And Then There Were None'') were set in and around Torquay, where she was raised. Christie's 1934 novel ''[[Murder on the Orient Express]]'' was written in the [[Pera Palace Hotel]] in Istanbul, Turkey, the southern terminus of the railway. The hotel maintains Christie's room as a memorial to the author.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|publisher=Virtual globe trotting|first=J.|last=Bottero|title=Agatha Christie's Hotel Pera Palace|url=http://virtualglobetrotting.com/map/51232|date=5 June 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Greenway Estate]] in Devon, acquired by the couple as a summer residence in 1938, is now in the care of the [[National Trust for Places of Historic Interest or Natural Beauty|National Trust]]. Christie often stayed at Abney Hall, Cheshire, owned by her brother-in-law, James Watts, basing at least two stories there: a short story &quot;[[The Adventure of the Christmas Pudding]]&quot; in the story collection of the same name, and the novel ''[[After the Funeral]]''. &quot;Abney became Agatha's greatest inspiration for country-house life, with all its servants and grandeur being woven into her plots. The descriptions of the fictional Chimneys, Stoneygates, and other houses in her stories are mostly Abney Hall in various forms.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=Agatha Christie: A Reader's Companion|first1=Vanessa|last1=Wagstaff|first2=Stephen|last2=Poole|publisher=Aurum Press|year=2004|page=[https://archive.org/details/agathachristiere00wags/page/14 14]|isbn=1-84513-015-4|url=https://archive.org/details/agathachristiere00wags/page/14}}&lt;/ref&gt;[[File:Cresswell Place.jpg|thumb|left|Cresswell Place]]During the [[Second World War]], Christie worked in the pharmacy at [[University College Hospital]], London, where she acquired a knowledge of poisons that she put to good use in her post-war crime novels. For example, the use of [[thallium]] as a poison was suggested to her by UCH Chief Pharmacist Harold Davis (later appointed Chief Pharmacist at the UK Ministry of Health), and in ''[[The Pale Horse]]'', published in 1961, she employed it to dispatch a series of victims, the first clue to the murder method coming from the victims' loss of hair. So accurate was her description of thallium poisoning that on at least one occasion it helped solve a case that was baffling doctors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Thallium poisoning in fact and in fiction |journal=[[The Pharmaceutical Journal]] |date=25 November 2006 |volume=277 |page=648 |url=https://www.pharmaceutical-journal.com/opinion/column/thallium-poisoning-in-fact-and-in-fiction-/-vexed-question-of-the-geographical-origins-of-the-meat-filled-pasty-/-how-illegal-ch/10002699.article |accessdate=6 September 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;John Emsley, [https://www.independent.co.uk/news/science/the-poison-prescribed-by-agatha-christie-thanks-to-the-mystery-writer-the-deadly-properties-of-thallium-sulphate-have-become-common-knowledge-corrected-1534450.html &quot;The poison prescribed by Agatha Christie&quot;], ''The Independent'', 20 July 1992.&lt;/ref&gt;
Christie lived in [[Chelsea, London|Chelsea]], first in Cresswell Place and later in Sheffield Terrace. Both properties are now marked by [[blue plaque]]s. In 1934, she and Max Mallowan purchased Winterbrook House in [[Winterbrook]], a hamlet adjoining the small market town of [[Wallingford, Oxfordshire|Wallingford]], then within the bounds of [[Cholsey]] and in [[Berkshire]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oxfordshireblueplaques.org.uk/plaques/christie.html Oxfordshire Blue Plaques], oxfordshireblueplaques.org.uk. Retrieved 21 September 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;[[File:Agatha Christie 58 Sheffield Terrace blue plaque.jpg|thumb|Blue plaque, 58 Sheffield Terrace, [[Holland Park]], London]]This was their main residence for the rest of their lives and the place where Christie did much of her writing.&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|365}} This house, too, bears a blue plaque. Christie led a quiet life despite being known in the town of Wallingford,&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/january/12/newsid_4440000/4440120.stm|title=1976: Crime writer Agatha Christie dies|date=12 January 1976|work=BBC ON THIS DAY|access-date=30 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; where she was for many years President of the local [[amateur dramatic society]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.sinodunplayers.org.uk/w2011/heritage|title=Sinodun Players|website=sinodunplayers.org.uk|access-date=9 February 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Agatha Christie in Nederland (detectiveschrijfster), bij aankomst op Schiphol me, Bestanddeelnr 916-8898 (cropped).jpg|thumb|Christie at [[Amsterdam Airport Schiphol|Schiphol]], 17 September 1964]]
Around 1941–42, the British intelligence agency [[MI5]] investigated Christie after a character called Major Bletchley appeared in her 1941 thriller ''[[N or M?]]'', which was about a hunt for a pair of deadly [[fifth column]]ists in wartime England.&lt;ref name=&quot;Richard Norton-Taylor&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Agatha Christie was investigated by MI5 over Bletchley Park mystery|author=Richard Norton-Taylor|url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2013/feb/04/agatha-christie-mi5-bletchley|newspaper=The Guardian|date=4 February 2013|accessdate=29 March 2013|location=London, UK}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[MI5]] was afraid that Christie had a spy in Britain's top-secret codebreaking centre, [[Bletchley Park]]. The agency's fears were allayed when Christie told her friend, the codebreaker [[Dilly Knox]], &quot;I was stuck there on my way by train from Oxford to London and took revenge by giving the name to one of my least lovable characters.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Richard Norton-Taylor&quot;/&gt; In honour of her many literary works, she was appointed [[Commander of the Order of the British Empire]] (CBE) in the [[1956 New Year Honours]].&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=40669|supp=y|page=11|date=30 December 1955}}&lt;/ref&gt; The next year, she became the President of the [[Detection Club]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=Authors|contribution=Biography: Agatha Christie|accessdate=22 February 2009|publisher=Illiterarty|url=http://www.illiterarty.com/authors/biography-agatha-christie}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[1971 New Year Honours]], she was promoted to [[Dame Commander of the Order of the British Empire]] (DBE),&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=45262|supp=y|page=7|date=31 December 1970}}&lt;/ref&gt; three years after her husband had been [[Knight Bachelor|knighted]] for his archaeological work in 1968.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=44600|supp=y|page=6300|date=31 May 1968}}&lt;/ref&gt; They were one of the few married couples where both partners were honoured in their own right. From 1968, owing to her husband's knighthood, Christie could also be [[Style (manner of address)|styled]] Lady Mallowan.

From 1971 to 1974, Christie's health began to fail, although she continued to write. Recently, using experimental tools of textual analysis, Canadian researchers have suggested that Christie may have begun to suffer from Alzheimer's disease or other dementia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Kingston|first=Anne|url=http://www2.macleans.ca/2009/04/02/the-ultimate-whodunit|title=The ultimate whodunit|newspaper=Maclean's|date=2 April 2009|accessdate=28 August 2009|place=Canada}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Boswell|first=Randy|url=https://ottawacitizen.com/health/Study+finds+possible+dementia+Agatha+Christie/1470424/story.html|title=Study finds possible dementia for Agatha Christie|newspaper=[[Ottawa Citizen]]|date=6 April 2009|accessdate=28 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/health/healthnews/5101619/Agatha-Christie-had-Alzheimers-disease-when-she-wrote-final-novels.html|accessdate=28 August 2009|location=London, UK|work=The Daily Telegraph|title=Agatha Christie 'had Alzheimer's disease when she wrote final novels'|first=Kate|last=Devlin|date=4 April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2009/apr/03/agatha-christie-alzheimers-research|accessdate=28 August 2009|location=London, UK|work=The Guardian|title=Study claims Agatha Christie had Alzheimer's|first=Alison|last=Flood|date=3 April 2009|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090801003533/http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2009/apr/03/agatha-christie-alzheimers-research|archivedate=1 August 2009|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Personal qualities===
In 1946, Christie said of herself: &quot;My chief dislikes are crowds, loud noises, gramophones and cinemas. I dislike the taste of alcohol and do not like smoking. I DO like sun, sea, flowers, travelling, strange foods, sports, concerts, theatres, pianos, and doing embroidery.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://trove.nla.gov.au/newspaper/article/17978243|title=The Real AGATHA CHRISTIE|date=30 April 1946|work=The Sydney Morning Herald|access-date=9 November 2019|page=6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Agatha Christie Trust For Children commenced in 1969&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://beta.charitycommission.gov.uk/charity-details/?subid=0&amp;regid=260295|title=Data for financial year ending 05 April 2018 – The Agatha Christie Trust For Children|website=Registered charities in England and Wales|url-status=live|access-date=7 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; and shortly after Christie's death a charitable memorial fund was set up to &quot;help two causes that she favoured: old people and young children.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Agatha Christie memorial fund|date=27 April 1976|work=The Times|page=16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Christie's obituary in ''[[The Times]]'' notes that &quot;she never cared much for the cinema, or for wireless and television&quot;. Further,&lt;blockquote&gt;Dame Agatha's private pleasures were gardening – she won local prizes for horticulture – and buying furniture for her various houses. She was a shy person: she disliked public appearances: but she was friendly and sharp-witted to meet. By inclination as well as breeding she belonged to the English upper middle-class. She wrote about, and for, people like herself. That was an essential part of her charm.&lt;ref name=&quot;:5&quot; /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Death==
[[File:Agatha christie's grave.jpg|thumb|Christie's gravestone at St. Mary's church, [[Cholsey]], Oxfordshire|alt=]]
[[File:Winterbrook House-geograph-1848557-by-Bill-Nicholls.jpg|left|thumb|Winterbrook House]]

===Christie's death and burial===
Christie died peacefully on 12 January 1976 at age 85 from natural causes at her home Winterbrook House which was located in [[Winterbrook]], [[Wallingford, Oxfordshire]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Deaths|date=14 January 1976|work=The Times|page=26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; At the time of her death Winterbrook was still a part of the parish of [[Cholsey]]. She is buried in the nearby churchyard of St Mary's, Cholsey, having chosen the plot for their final resting place with her husband Sir Max some ten years before she died. The simple funeral service was attended by about 20 newspaper and TV reporters, some having travelled from as far away as South America. Thirty wreaths adorned Christie's grave, including one from the cast of her long-running play ''The Mousetrap'' and one sent 'on behalf of the multitude of grateful readers' by the Ulverscroft Large Print Book Publishers.&lt;ref&gt;Marilyn Yurdan&amp;nbsp;– Oxfordshire Graves and Gravestones. The History Press 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

She was survived by her second husband, Sir Max Mallowan; by her only child, Rosalind Hicks (formerly Prichard, née Christie);&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|340,349,422}} and by her only grandchild, Mathew T. Prichard. Mallowan, who remarried in 1977, died in 1978 at age 74. He was interred next to Christie.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.stmaryscholsey.org/history/agatha-christie/|title=St. Mary's Church, Cholsey|website=|access-date=18 February 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{anchor|Christie Estate}} Christie's estate and subsequent ownership of works===
Although Christie was rather unhappy about becoming &quot;an employed wage slave&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|428}} to avoid future adverse tax implications she set up a [[private limited company|private company]], Agatha Christie Limited, in 1955 to hold the rights to her works, and in about 1959 transferred her 278-acre home, [[Greenway Estate]], to her daughter Rosalind.&lt;ref name=&quot;rosalind_obit_telegraph&quot;&gt;[https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/obituaries/1476488/Rosalind-Hicks.html Obituary: Rosalind Hicks], ''The Daily Telegraph'', 13 November 2004. Retrieved 25 January 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/january/12/newsid_4440000/4440120.stm|title=1976: Crime writer Agatha Christie dies|date=12 January 1976|website=BBC ON THIS DAY|url-status=live|access-date=30 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1968, when Christie was almost 80 years old, she sold a 51% stake in Agatha Christie Limited (and therefore the works it owned) to Booker Books (better known as [[Booker Group#Booker Author's Division|Booker Author's Division]]), a subsidiary of the [[:Category:Companies of the United Kingdom|British]] food and transport [[Conglomerate (company)|conglomerate]] Booker-McConnell (now [[Booker Group]]), the founder of the [[Man Booker Prize|Booker Prize]] for literature, which by 1977 had increased its stake to 64%.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|355|quote=In the summer of 1968 a subsidiary [of Booker McConnel], Bookers Books, acquired a fifty-one percent holding in Agatha Christie Ltd (subsequently increased to sixty-four percent).}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Booker is ready for more|date=16 September 1977|work=The Newcastle Journal|page=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Agatha Christie Limited remains the owner of the worldwide rights for over 80 of Christie's novels and short stories, 19 plays, and nearly 40 TV films.&lt;ref name=&quot;guardianchorion&quot;/&gt;

In the late 1950s, Christie had reputedly been earning around ₤100,000 per year but, as a result of her tax planning, her will left only ₤106,683 net which went mostly to her husband and daughter along with some smaller bequests.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=£106,000 will of Dame Agatha Christie|date=1 May 1976|work=The Times|page=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; Her remaining 36% share of Agatha Christie Limited was inherited by her daughter, Rosalind Hicks, who passionately preserved her mother's works, image, and legacy until her own death 28 years later.&lt;ref name=&quot;rosalind_obit_telegraph&quot;/&gt; The family's share of the company allowed them to appoint 50% of the board and the chairman, and thereby to retain a veto over new treatments, updated versions, and republications of her works.&lt;ref name=&quot;rosalind_obit_telegraph&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;birminghampost&quot;&gt;[http://www.thefreelibrary.com/Agatha+Christie+begins+new+chapter+after+pounds+10m+selff.-a060775079 Agatha Christie begins new chapter after £10m selloff], TheFreeLibrary.com, 4 June 1998.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1993, Hicks founded the Agatha Christie Society and became its first president.&lt;ref name=&quot;rosalind_obit_telegraph&quot;/&gt; In 2004 her [[obituary]] in ''[[The Daily Telegraph|The Telegraph]]'' commented that Hicks had been &quot;determined to remain true to her mother's vision and to protect the integrity of her creations&quot; and disapproved of &quot;[[merchandising]]&quot; activities.&lt;ref name=&quot;rosalind_obit_telegraph&quot;/&gt; Upon Hicks's death on 28 October 2004, both the Society and the Greenway Estate passed to Christie's grandson, Mathew Prichard.  After his parents' deaths, Prichard donated Greenway and its contents to the [[National Trust]].&lt;ref name=&quot;rosalind_obit_telegraph&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/books/features/the-big-question-how-big-is-the-agatha-christie-industry-and-what-explains-her-enduring-appeal-1631296.html|title=The Big Question: How big is the Agatha Christie industry, and what explains her enduring appeal?|work=The Independent|accessdate=6 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Society is now chaired and managed by Christie's great-grandson James Prichard.&lt;ref&gt;The Agatha Christie Society. Online. Access 22 October 2017. [http://agathachristiesociety.com/ web site].&lt;/ref&gt;

Christie's family and [[Trust (law)|family trusts]], including James Prichard, continue to own the remaining 36% stake in Agatha Christie Limited,&lt;ref name=&quot;guardianchorion&quot;&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/media/2012/feb/29/acorn-media-bys-stake-agatha-christie Acorn Media buys stake in Agatha Christie estate], ''The Guardian'', 29 December 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; and remain associated with the company. James Prichard became the company's chairman in October 2015.&lt;ref&gt;James Prichard, LinkedIn [https://uk.linkedin.com/in/james-prichard-b33b707 web site]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.agathachristie.com/about-agatha-christie-limited|title=About Agatha Christie Limited|website=The Home of Agatha Christie|url-status=live|access-date=7 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The development of Christie's work continues apace.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/long_reads/agatha-christie-cosy-crime-novels-murder-mystery-writer-why-we-love-a7942901.html|title=Why do we still love the 'cosy crime' of Agatha Christie?|date=14 September 2017|website=The Independent|accessdate=16 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mathew Prichard in his own right holds the copyright to some of his grandmother's later literary works (including ''[[The Mousetrap]]'').&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|427}}

In 1998, Booker sold a number of its non-food assets to focus on its core business.&lt;ref name=&quot;birminghampost&quot;/&gt; As part of that, its shares in Agatha Christie Limited (at the time earning £2.1m annual revenue&lt;ref name=&quot;birminghampost&quot;/&gt;) were sold for £10m to [[Chorion (company)|Chorion]],&lt;ref name=&quot;birminghampost&quot;/&gt; a major international media company whose portfolio of well-known authors' works also included the literary estates of [[Enid Blyton]] and [[Dennis Wheatley]]. In February 2012, some years after a [[management buyout]], Chorion found itself in financial difficulties, and began to sell off its literary assets on the market.&lt;ref name=&quot;guardianchorion&quot;/&gt; The process included the sale of Chorion's 64% stake in Agatha Christie Limited to Acorn Media U.K.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Sweney|first=Mark|url=https://www.theguardian.com/media/2012/feb/29/acorn-media-bys-stake-agatha-christie|title=Acorn Media buys stake in Agatha Christie estate|newspaper=The Guardian|date=29 February 2012|accessdate=16 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2014, [[RLJ Companies|RLJ Entertainment Inc.]] acquired Acorn Media U.K., renamed it [[Acorn DVD|Acorn Media Enterprises]], and incorporated it as the RLJE UK development arm.&lt;ref&gt;RLJ Entertainment Inc. web site [http://www.rljentertainment.com/ RLJE web site]&lt;/ref&gt; RLJ Entertainment Inc. was founded by American entrepreneur [[Robert L. Johnson]].
 
In late February 2014, media reports stated that the [[BBC]] had acquired exclusive TV rights to Christie's works in the UK (previously associated with [[ITV (TV network)|ITV]]) and made plans with Acorn's co-operation to air new productions for the 125th anniversary of Christie's birth in 2015.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.radiotimes.com/news/2014-02-28/david-walliams-heralds-new-era-for-bbc-as-the-new-home-of-agatha-christie-adaptations &quot;New era for BBC as the new home of Agatha Christie adaptations&quot;], ''Radio Times'', 28 February 2014. Retrieved 25 January 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; As part of that deal, the BBC broadcast ''[[Partners in Crime (UK TV series)|Partners in Crime]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/p02vf6rn/episodes/guide|title=BBC One&amp;nbsp;– Partners in Crime&amp;nbsp;– Episode Guide|publisher=BBC|date=1 January 1970|accessdate=16 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[And Then There Were None (miniseries)|And Then There Were None]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Staff|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b06v2v52|title=BBC One&amp;nbsp;– And Then There Were None|publisher=BBC|date=28 December 2015|accessdate=16 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; both in 2015. Subsequent productions have included ''[[The Witness for the Prosecution (miniseries)|The Witness for the Prosecution]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b086z959|title=The Witness for the Prosecution – BBC One|publisher=BBC}}&lt;/ref&gt; but plans to televise ''[[Ordeal by Innocence (TV series)|Ordeal by Innocence]]'' at Christmas 2017 were delayed due to controversy surrounding one of the cast members.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/entertainment-arts-42577505|title=Ed Westwick removed from BBC Agatha Christie drama Ordeal By Innocence|publisher=BBC News|accessdate=23 January 2018|date=5 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The three-part adaptation aired in April 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b09ytrgg|title=BBC One – Ordeal by Innocence|publisher=BBC|accessdate=11 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; A three-part adaptation of ''[[The A.B.C. Murders]]'' starring [[John Malkovich]] and [[Rupert Grint]] began filming in June 2018 for later broadcast.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=All-star cast announced for new BBC One Agatha Christie thriller The ABC Murders | publisher=BBC | date=24 May 2018 | url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/mediacentre/latestnews/2018/abc-murders | access-date=11 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Writings==
{{Main|Agatha Christie bibliography|Adaptations of Agatha Christie}}

===Works of fiction===
====Hercule Poirot and Miss Marple====
[[File:Agatha Christie Memorial (cropped).jpg|thumb|right|Memorial to Christie in central London]]
Christie's first book, ''[[The Mysterious Affair at Styles]]'', was published in 1920 and introduced the detective [[Hercule Poirot]], who became a long-running character in Christie's works, appearing in 33 novels and 54 short stories.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Hercule Poirot Reading List|url=http://agatha-christie-cms-production.s3.amazonaws.com/archive/pdfs/poirot-reading-list.pdf|website=AgathaChristie.com|publisher=Agatha Christie Limited|accessdate=19 January 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160328003939/http://agatha-christie-cms-production.s3.amazonaws.com/archive/pdfs/poirot-reading-list.pdf|archive-date=28 March 2016|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Miss Marple|Miss Jane Marple]] was introduced in the short-story collection ''[[The Thirteen Problems]]'' in 1927. Although Christie states that, &quot;Miss Marple was not in any way a picture of my grandmother; she was far more fussy and spinsterish than my grandmother ever was&quot;, her autobiography does establish a firm connection between the fictional character and Christie's maternal great-aunt Margaret Miller (&quot;Auntie-Grannie&quot;){{Refn|Christie's familial relationship to Margaret Miller née West was complex. From the information provided earlier in the article it can be seen that as well as Christie's maternal great-aunt, Miller was Christie's father's step-mother as well as Christie's mother's foster mother and step-mother-in-law – hence the appellation &quot;Auntie-Grannie&quot;.|group=lower-alpha}} and her &quot;Ealing cronies&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Auto1993&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|422–423}}&lt;ref name =BBCdustyClues&gt;{{cite news|last=Mills|first=Selina|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/today/hi/today/newsid_7612000/7612534.stm|title=Dusty clues to Christie unearthed|publisher=BBC News|date=15 September 2008|accessdate=9 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both Marple and Miller &quot;always expected the worst of everyone and everything, and were, with almost frightening accuracy, usually proved right.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Auto1993&quot; /&gt;{{rp|422}} Marple appeared in 12 novels and 20 stories.

During the Second World War, Christie wrote two novels, ''[[Curtain (novel)|Curtain]]'' and ''[[Sleeping Murder]]'', intended as the last cases of these two great detectives, Hercule Poirot and Miss Marple. Both books were sealed in a [[bank vault]] for over thirty years and were released for publication by Christie only at the end of her life, when she realised that she could not write any more novels. These publications came on the heels of the success of the [[Murder on the Orient Express (1974 film)|film version]] of ''Murder on the Orient Express'' in 1974.&lt;ref name=&quot;Auto1993&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|497}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://mainecrimewriters.com/2018/01/25/dame-agatha-and-her-orient-express/|title=Dame Agatha and Her Orient Express|last=susanvaughan|date=25 January 2018|website=Maine Crime Writers|access-date=20 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Christie became increasingly tired of Poirot, much as Sir [[Arthur Conan Doyle]] had grown weary of his character [[Sherlock Holmes]]. By the end of the 1930s, Christie wrote in her diary that she was finding Poirot &quot;insufferable&quot;, and by the 1960s she felt that he was &quot;an egocentric creep&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Gross |first= John |title= The New Oxford Book of Literary Anecdotes |publisher= Oxford University Press |page=267 |year= 2006 |isbn= 978-0199543410}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, unlike Conan Doyle, Christie resisted the temptation to kill her detective off while he was still popular. She saw herself as an entertainer whose job was to produce what the public liked, and the public liked Poirot.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=The Christie Mystery|title=Agatha Christie&amp;nbsp;– Her Detectives &amp; Other Characters|date=22 February 2009|url=http://www.christiemystery.co.uk/detectives.html|accessdate=25 January 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110906011416/http://www.christiemystery.co.uk/detectives.html|archive-date=6 September 2011|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; She did marry off Poirot's companion [[Arthur Hastings|Captain Hastings]] in an attempt to trim her cast commitments.&lt;ref name=&quot;Auto1993&quot; /&gt;{{rp|268}}

In contrast, Christie was fond of Miss Marple. However, the Belgian detective's titles outnumber the Marple titles more than two to one. This is largely because Christie wrote numerous Poirot novels early in her career, while ''[[The Murder at the Vicarage]]'' remained the sole Marple novel until the 1940s. Christie never wrote a novel or short story featuring both Poirot and Miss Marple. In a recording discovered and released in 2008, Christie revealed the reason for this: &quot;Hercule Poirot, a complete egoist, would not like being taught his business or having suggestions made to him by an elderly spinster lady. Hercule Poirot – a professional sleuth – would not be at home at all in Miss Marple's world.&quot;.&lt;ref name=BBCdustyClues/&gt;  However, ''[[Three Act Tragedy]]'' does feature both Hercule Poirot and the elderly bachelor Mr. Satterthwaite (confederate of Harley Quin).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://worldcat.org/oclc/1027804732|title=THREE ACT TRAGEDY.|last=CHRISTIE, AGATHA.|date=2018|publisher=HARPERCOLLINS PUBLISHERS|isbn=0008255784|oclc=1027804732}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Poirot is the only fictional character to date to be given an obituary in ''The New York Times'', following the publication of ''Curtain''. It appeared on the front page of the paper on 6 August 1975.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=JD|last=Hobbs|place=USA|url=http://www.poirot.us/obituary.php|title=Poirot's Obituary|publisher=Poirot|date=6 August 1975|accessdate=30 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the great success of ''Curtain'', Christie gave permission for the release of ''Sleeping Murder'' sometime in 1976 but died in January 1976 before the book could be released. This may explain some of the inconsistencies compared to the rest of the Marple series—for example, Colonel Arthur Bantry, husband of Miss Marple's friend Dolly, is still alive and well in ''Sleeping Murder'' although he is noted as having died in books published earlier. It may be that Christie simply did not have time to revise the manuscript before she died.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mtv.com/artists/agatha-christie/biography|title=About Agatha Christie|work=Artists|publisher=MTV|accessdate=16 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2013, the Christie family gave their &quot;full backing&quot; to the release of a new Poirot story, ''[[The Monogram murders]]'', which was written by British author [[Sophie Hannah]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.agathachristie.com/the-monogram-murders|title=The Monogram Murders|publisher=Agatha Christie.com|accessdate=11 April 2015|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150403183934/http://www.agathachristie.com/the-monogram-murders/|archivedate=3 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hannah later released a second Poirot mystery, ''[[Closed Casket (novel)|Closed Casket]]'', in 2016&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.agathachristie.com/news/2016/an-interview-with-sophie-hannah|title=An interview with Sophie Hannah|accessdate=10 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Agatha Christie#Writings|''The Mystery of the Three-Quarters'']] in 2018.

====Formula and plot devices====
{{more citations needed section|date=April 2016}}
Christie's reputation as &quot;The Queen of Crime&quot; was built upon the large number of classic [[Motif (literature)|motifs]] that she introduced, or for which she provided the most famous example. Christie built these tropes into what is now considered classic mystery structure: a murder is committed, there are multiple suspects who are all concealing secrets, and the detective gradually uncovers these secrets over the course of the story, discovering the most shocking twists towards the end. Culprits in Christie's mysteries have included children, policemen, narrators, already deceased individuals, and sometimes comprise no known suspects (''[[And Then There Were None]]'') or all of the suspects (''[[Murder on the Orient Express]]'').

At the end, in a Christie hallmark, the detective usually gathers the surviving suspects into one room, explains the course of their deductive reasoning, and reveals the guilty party, although there are exceptions in which it is left to the guilty party to explain all (such as ''[[And Then There Were None]]'' and ''[[Endless Night (novel)|Endless Night]]'').&lt;ref name=me&gt;Mezei, Kathy. [https://www.jstor.org/stable/4619330 &quot;Spinsters, Surveillance, and Speech: The Case of Miss Marple, Miss Mole, and Miss Jekyll&quot;], ''The Journal of Modern Literature'' 30.2 (2007): 103–120&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=be&gt;Beehler, Sharon A. [https://www.jstor.org/stable/818612 &quot;Close vs. Closed Reading: Interpreting the Clues&quot;], ''The English Journal'' 77.6 (1998): 39–43&lt;/ref&gt;

Christie allows some culprits to escape earthly justice for a variety of reasons, such as the passage of time (retrospective cases), in which the most important characters have already died, or by active prescription. Such cases include ''[[The Witness for the Prosecution]]'', ''[[Murder on the Orient Express]]'', ''[[The Man in the Brown Suit]]'', ''[[Elephants Can Remember]]'', and ''[[The Unexpected Guest (play)|The Unexpected Guest]]''. There are instances in which a killer is not brought to justice in the legal sense but does die as a direct result of their plot, sometimes by their own hand at the direction or with the collusion of the detective (usually Hercule Poirot). This occurs in ''[[The Murder of Roger Ackroyd]]'', ''[[Death on the Nile]]'', ''[[Dumb Witness]]'', ''[[Crooked House]]'', ''[[The Hollow]]'', ''[[The Mirror Crack'd from Side to Side]]'', ''[[Cat Among the Pigeons]]'', ''[[Peril at End House]]'', ''[[Nemesis (Agatha Christie novel)|Nemesis]]'', ''[[Appointment with Death]]'', ''[[The Secret Adversary]]'', and ''[[Curtain (novel)|Curtain]]''. In the last of these (''Curtain''), no fewer than three culprits die during the course of the story.

In ''[[The A.B.C. Murders]]'', the murderer has killed four innocent people and attempted to frame an unstable man for the crimes. Hercule Poirot, however, prevents this easy way out, ensuring a trial and hanging. In ''[[And Then There Were None]]'', the killer's own death is intrinsic to the plot; the [[red herring]] is when and how the killer actually died. However, stage, film, and television productions of some of these mysteries were traditionally sanitized with the culprits not evading some form of justice, for a variety of reasons&amp;nbsp;– e.g., censors, plot clarity, and Christie's own changing tastes. (When Christie adapted ''[[The Witness for the Prosecution|Witness for the Prosecution]]'' into a stage play, she lengthened the ending so that the murderer was also killed; this format was followed in screen versions, including the [[Billy Wilder]] film from 1957.) In ''[[Death Comes as the End]]'', set in ancient [[Egypt]], the culprit is killed by one of the few surviving characters before he can claim another victim.

In some stories, the question remains unresolved of whether formal justice will ever be delivered, such as ''[[Five Little Pigs]]'' and ''[[Endless Night (novel)|Endless Night]]''. According to [[P. D. James]], Christie often, but not always, made the unlikeliest character the guilty party. Savvy readers could sometimes identify the culprit by simply identifying the least likely suspect.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=James|first=P.D.|title=Talking About Detective Fiction|year=2009|publisher=[[Random House]]|isbn=0-307-39882-X|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=fcGke2wlt0UC&amp;pg=PT26|accessdate=31 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On an edition of ''[[Desert Island Discs]]'' in 2007, [[Brian Aldiss]] claimed that Christie had told him that she wrote her books up to the last chapter, then decided who the most unlikely suspect was, after which she would go back and make the necessary changes to &quot;frame&quot; that person.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brian Aldiss claims Agatha tells method&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/factual/desertislanddiscs_20070128.shtml|title=BBC Radio 4&amp;nbsp;–Factual&amp;nbsp;–Desert Island Discs|last=Aldiss|first=Brian|publisher=BBC|accessdate=22 February 2009|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090211235326/http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/factual/desertislanddiscs_20070128.shtml |archivedate=11 February 2009|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, John Curran describes different working methods for every book in Christie's bibliography, contradicting the claim by Aldiss.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Agatha Christie's Secret Notebooks: Fifty Years of Mysteries in the Making|last=Curran|first=John|publisher=Harper-Collins|year=2009|isbn=978-0-06-200652-3|location=London, UK|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Titles ====
Christie's mature novels, from 1940 onwards, often have titles drawn from literature.

Four are from [[Shakespeare]]: 
* ''[[Sad Cypress]]'' from a song in ''[[Twelfth Night]]'': &quot;Come away, come away, death / And in sad cypress let me be laid&quot;.
* ''[[By the Pricking of My Thumbs]]'' from Act 4, Scene 1 of ''[[Macbeth]]'' : &quot;By the pricking of my thumbs / Something wicked this way comes&quot;.
* ''[[Taken at the Flood|There is a Tide...]]'' (later ''[[Taken at the Flood]]'') from Brutus' speech in ''[[Julius Caesar (play)|Julius Caesar]]'': &quot;There is a tide in the affairs of men / Which, taken at the flood, leads on to fortune&quot;.
* ''[[Absent in the Spring]]'' from Sonnet 98: &quot;From you have I been absent in the spring&amp;nbsp;...&quot;

Three are from the Bible: 
* ''[[Evil Under the Sun]]'' from [[Ecclesiastes]] 5:13 (and restated in 6:1): &quot;There is a sore evil which I have seen under the sun, namely, riches kept for the owners thereof to their hurt&quot;.
* ''[[The Burden]]'' from Jesus' words: &quot;Take my yoke upon you, and learn of me&amp;nbsp;... For my yoke is easy, and my burden is light.&quot; (Matthew: 11: 29–30).
* ''[[The Pale Horse]]'' from the [[Book of Revelation|Revelation of St John]] (6:8): &quot;I looked, and there before me was a pale horse! Its rider was named Death &amp;nbsp;...&quot;.

Another six are from other works of literature:
* ''[[The Mirror Crack'd from Side to Side]]'' from [[Tennyson]]'s &quot;[[The Lady of Shalott]]&quot;: &quot;Out flew the web, and floated wide/The mirror cracked from side to side/'The curse is come upon me,&quot; cried/The Lady of Shalott&quot;
* ''[[The Moving Finger]]'' from verse 51 of [[Edward FitzGerald (poet)|Edward FitzGerald]]'s translation of the ''[[Rubáiyát of Omar Khayyám]]'': &quot;The Moving Finger writes; and, having writ/Moves on&amp;nbsp;...&quot; This, in turn, refers to the Biblical account of Belshazzar's feast (Daniel, chapter 5), which is the origin of the expression &quot;the writing on the wall&quot;.
* ''[[The Rose and the Yew Tree]]'' from Section V of &quot;[[Little Gidding (poem)|Little Gidding]]&quot; from [[T. S. Eliot]]'s ''[[Four Quartets]]'': &quot;The moment of the rose and the moment of the yew-tree/Are of equal duration&quot;.
* ''[[Postern of Fate]]'' from the poem &quot;Gates of Damascus&quot; by [[James Elroy Flecker]]: &quot;Postern of Fate, the Desert Gate, Disaster's Cavern, Fort of Fear/The Portal of Bagdad am I&amp;nbsp;...&quot;
* ''[[Endless Night (novel)|Endless Night]]'' from [[William Blake]]'s [[Auguries of Innocence]]: &quot;Some are born to sweet delight / Some are born to endless night&quot;.
* ''[[N or M?]]'' from the [[Catechism]] in the [[Book of Common Prayer]] which asks, &quot;What is your Christian name? Answer N. or M.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.stlukesrec.org/bcp1963/catechism63.pdf|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081014121458/http://www.stlukesrec.org/bcp1963/catechism63.pdf|url-status=dead|title=A Catechism from the Book of Common Prayer, 1549, enlarged, 1637, revised in the Bishop White Book, 1785, now again revised and enlarged|archivedate=14 October 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The &quot;N. or M.&quot; stands for the Latin, &quot;nomen vel nomina&quot;, meaning &quot;name or names&quot;. It is an accident of typography that &quot;nomina&quot; came to be represented by &quot;m&quot;.

In such cases, the original context of the title is usually printed as an [[epigraph (literature)|epigraph]].&lt;ref&gt;Hopkins, Lisa. 2016. Who Owns the Wood? Appropriating A Midsummer Night's Dream. In Shakespearean Allusion in Crime Fiction, ed. L. Hopkins, pp. 63–103. Cham, Switzerland: Springer.
&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, the title of Christie's autobiographical travel book ''[[Come, Tell Me How You Live]]'' is a quote from verse three of the [[White Knight (Through the Looking-Glass)|White Knight]]'s poem, &quot;[[Haddocks' Eyes]]&quot; from chapter eight of ''[[Through the Looking-Glass]]'' by [[Lewis Carroll]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.mit.edu/people/dpolicar/writing/poetry/poems/whiteKnightSong.html|title=The White Knight's Song |publisher=Mit.edu|accessdate=16 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is a play on the word &quot;[[Tell (archaeology)|tell]]&quot;, an archaeological mound.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rushthatspeaks.livejournal.com/425313.html|title=Come, Tell Me How You Live, Agatha Christie Mallowan (365 Books, Day 271): rushthatspeaks|publisher=Rushthatspeaks.livejournal.com|date=28 May 2011|accessdate=16 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The title of ''[[The Mousetrap]]'' is purportedly an allusion to [[Shakespeare]]'s play ''[[Hamlet]]'', in which &quot;The Mousetrap&quot; is Hamlet's answer to Claudius's inquiry about the name of the play whose prologue and first scene he and his court have just watched (III, ii).&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|511–512}}

Seven stories are built around words from well known children's [[nursery rhyme]]s: ''[[And Then There Were None]]'' (from &quot;[[Ten Little Indians]]&quot;), ''[[One, Two, Buckle My Shoe (novel)|One, Two, Buckle My Shoe]]'' (from &quot;[[One, Two, Buckle My Shoe]]&quot;), ''[[Five Little Pigs]]'' (from &quot;[[This Little Piggy]]&quot;), ''[[Crooked House]]'' (from &quot;[[There Was a Crooked Man]]&quot;), ''[[A Pocket Full of Rye]]'' (from &quot;[[Sing a Song of Sixpence]]&quot;), ''[[Hickory Dickory Dock (novel)|Hickory Dickory Dock]]'' (from &quot;[[Hickory Dickory Dock]]&quot;), and ''[[Three Blind Mice and Other Stories|Three Blind Mice]]'' (from &quot;[[Three Blind Mice]]&quot;). Similarly, the novel ''[[Mrs McGinty's Dead]]'' is named after a children's game that is explained in the course of the novel.

====Character stereotypes====
Christie occasionally inserted stereotyped descriptions of characters into her work, particularly before the end of the Second World War (when such attitudes were more commonly expressed publicly), and particularly in regard to Italians, Jews, non-Europeans, and sometimes Americans.  For example, she described &quot;Hebraic men with hook-noses wearing rather flamboyant jewellery&quot; in the first editions of the collection ''[[The Mysterious Mr Quin]]'' (1930), in the short story &quot;The Soul of the Croupier&quot;; in later editions, the passage was edited to describe &quot;sallow men&quot; wearing same.

In ''[[The Hollow]]'', published as late as 1946, one of the more unsympathetic characters is &quot;a Whitechapel Jewess with dyed hair and a voice like a [[corncrake]]&amp;nbsp;... a small woman with a thick nose, henna red and a disagreeable voice&quot;. To contrast with the more stereotyped descriptions, Christie sometimes showed &quot;foreigners&quot; as victims or potential victims at the hands of English malefactors, such as, respectively, Olga Seminoff (''[[Hallowe'en Party]]'') and Katrina Reiger (in the short story &quot;How Does Your Garden Grow?&quot;). Jewish characters are often seen as un-English (such as Oliver Manders in ''[[Three Act Tragedy]]''), but they are rarely the culprits.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Pendergast|first=Bruce|title=Everyman's Guide to the Mysteries of Agatha Christie|publisher=Trafford|year=2004|location=Victoria, BC, Canada|page=399|isbn=1-4120-2304-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, many American characters are positive characters living in the UK, and are frequently misunderstood by their British associates. The [[Fulbright scholar]] Sally Finch (''Hickory Dickory'' ''Death'', also published as ''Hickory Dickory Dock'') is intelligent, attractive and innocent, even though Mrs. Nicoletis automatically assumes she will object to sharing house with students of other races. Another (foreign) student falsely labels Sally as being a fanatical anti-Communist simply because she is American (the book was written just after the McCarthy period, in 1955).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://worldcat.org/oclc/999441027|title=Hickory Dickory Dock|last=Christie |first=Agatha|date=2017|publisher=HarperCollins Publishers|isbn=0008255539|oclc=999441027}}&lt;/ref&gt; Anthony Browne (in ''Sparkling Cyanide'', also titled ''Remembered Death''), whom the book depicts as probably American, is suspected of being a spy. However, he is actually in counter-intelligence, and deduces correctly who the murderer is.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/sparklingcyanide00agat|title=Remembered death|last=Christie, Agatha, 1890–1976.|date=2001|publisher=St Martins Pr (Mm)|isbn=0312981295|oclc=655449571}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''They Do it With Mirrors'', Walter Hudd, though outwardly negative, appears so because he is unhappy with life on his in-laws’ estate and his wife's flirtations with other men.  His wife's aunt, Mildred, assumes he committed the murder, with the phrase &quot;He's probably one of those dreadful American gangsters&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://worldcat.org/oclc/1027865465|title=THEY DO IT WITH MIRRORS.|last=CHRISTIE, AGATHA.|date=2018|publisher=HARPERCOLLINS PUBLISHERS|isbn=0008255903|oclc=1027865465}}&lt;/ref&gt; She is probably judging him by what a British character would have read in newspapers about American crime. Christie's father was American.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan1984&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|1}}

Often, she is affectionate or teasing with her prejudices. After four years of war-torn London, Christie hoped to return some day to Syria, which she described as &quot;gentle fertile country and its simple people, who know how to laugh and how to enjoy life; who are idle and gay, and who have dignity, good manners, and a great sense of humour, and to whom death is not terrible.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;mallowan&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Come, Tell Me How You Live|last=Christie Mallowan|first=Agatha|date=1990|publisher=Fontana Books|year=|isbn=0-00-637594-4|location=London, UK|page=|pages=|orig-year=1946}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|167}}

She had trouble with an incompetent Swiss French nursery helper (Marcelle) for toddler Rosalind, and as a result she decided, &quot;Scottish preferred&amp;nbsp;... good with the young. The French were hopeless disciplinarians&amp;nbsp;... Germans good and methodical, but it was not German that I really wanted Rosalind to learn. The Irish were gay but made trouble in the house; the English were of all kinds.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Auto1993&quot; /&gt;{{rp|327}}

===Non-fiction writings===
Christie published relatively few non-fiction works:
*''Come, Tell Me How You Live'', about working on an archaeological dig, drawn from her life with second husband Max Mallowan
*''The Grand Tour: Around the World with the Queen of Mystery'', a collection of correspondence from her 1922 Grand Tour of the British empire, including South Africa, Australia, New Zealand, and Canada
*''[[Agatha Christie: An Autobiography]]'', published posthumously in 1977

===Critical reception and legacy===
Often referred to as the &quot;Queen of Crime&quot; or &quot;Queen of Mystery&quot;, Christie is the world's best-selling mystery writer and is considered a master of suspense, plotting, and characterisation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|first1=Dick|last1=Riley|first2=Pam|last2=McAllister|first3=Julian|last3=Symons|title=The Bedside, Bathtub &amp; Armchair Companion to Agatha Christie|page=240|work=Continuum|year=2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|first=Cindy|last=Härcher|year=2011|title=The Development of Crime Fiction|page=7|publisher=Grin}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|first=Sandra|last=Engelhardt|title=The Investigators of Crime in Literature|page=83|publisher=Tectum|year=2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some critics, however, have regarded Christie's plotting as superior to her skill with other literary elements. Novelist [[Raymond Chandler]] criticised her in his essay &quot;[[The Simple Art of Murder]]&quot;, and American literary critic [[Edmund Wilson]] was dismissive of Christie and the detective fiction genre generally in his ''[[The New Yorker|New Yorker]]'' essay, &quot;Who Cares Who Killed Roger Ackroyd?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite magazine|last=Wilson|first=Edmund|title=Who Cares Who Killed Roger Ackroyd?|url=http://archives.newyorker.com/?iid=18408&amp;startpage=page0000061#folio=058 | url-access=subscription | magazine=The New Yorker|date=20 January 1945}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In honour of the 125th anniversary of her birth, 25 contemporary mystery writers and one publisher revealed their views on Christie's works. Many of the authors read Christie's novels first, before other [[Mystery fiction|mystery writers]], in English or in their native language, influencing their own writing, and nearly all still view her as the &quot;Queen of Crime&quot;, and creator of the [[plot twist]]s used by mystery authors. Nearly all had one or more favourites among Christie's mysteries, and find her books good to read now, nearly 100 years after her first novel was published. Several of the authors would be very pleased to have their own novels in print in 100 years. Just one of the 25 authors held with Edmund Wilson's views.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.irishtimes.com/culture/books/agatha-christie-genius-or-hack-crime-writers-pass-judgment-and-pick-favourites-1.2351699|title=Agatha Christie: genius or hack? Crime writers pass judgment and pick favourites|date=15 September 2015|author=Doyle, Martin|newspaper=The Irish Times|accessdate=7 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Harper Collins also published a souvenir magazine ''Shocking Real Murders: Behind Her Classic Mysteries''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vowelor.com/book/shocking-real-murders-agatha-christie-review/ &quot;Shocking Real Murders&quot;] by Agatha Christie, ''Harper Collins''&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''[[Guinness World Records|Guinness Book of World Records]]'' lists Christie as the best-selling novelist of all time. Her novels have sold roughly 2 [[1,000,000,000 (number)|billion]] copies, and her [[Estate (law)|estate]] claims that her works come third in the rankings of the world's most-widely published books,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Independent 2015&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Has Agatha Christie's most enduring mystery been solved?|website=The Independent|date=14 September 2015|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/books/news/agatha-christie-mystery-of-crime-writers-disappearance-tackled-in-kate-mosse-story-10500837.html |accessdate=23 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; behind only [[William Shakespeare|Shakespeare's]] works and the Bible. Half of the sales are of English language editions, and the other half in translation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.agathachristie.com/about-christie|title=About Agatha Christie|quote=Her books have sold over a billion copies in the English language and a billion in 44 foreign languages.|publisher=Agatha Christie Ltd|accessdate=7 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Index Translationum]], she remains the most-translated individual author&amp;nbsp;– having been translated into at least 103 languages.&lt;ref name=McWhirter&gt;{{cite book|last1=McWhirter|first1=Norris|last2=McWhirter|first2=Ross|date=1976|title=Guinness Book of World Records, 11th U.S. Edition|publisher=Bantam Books|page=704}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[And Then There Were None]]'' is Christie's best-selling novel, with 100 million sales to date, making it the world's best-selling mystery ever, and one of the [[List of best-selling books|best-selling books]] of all time.&lt;ref name=BestSeller&gt;{{cite web|url=http://entertainment.howstuffworks.com/arts/literature/21-best-sellers14.htm#page=6|title=21 Best-Selling Books of All Time|last1=Davies|first1=Helen|first2=Marjorie|last2=Dorfman|first3=Mary|last3=Fons|first4=Deborah|last4=Hawkins|first5=Martin|last5=Hintz|first6=Linnea|last6=Lundgren|first7=David|last7=Priess|first8=Julia Clark|last8=Robinson|first9=Paul|last9=Seaburn|date=14 September 2007|publisher=Editors of Publications International|accessdate=25 March 2009|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090407002704/http://entertainment.howstuffworks.com/21-best-selling-books-of-all-time.htm |archivedate=7 April 2009|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2012, Christie was among the [[Culture of the United Kingdom|British cultural icons]] selected by artist Sir [[Peter Blake (artist)|Peter Blake]] to appear in a new version of his most famous artwork&amp;nbsp;– the Beatles' ''[[Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band]]'' album cover&amp;nbsp;– to celebrate the British cultural figures of his life that he most admires.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=New faces on Sgt Pepper album cover for artist Peter Blake's 80th birthday|url= https://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/2012/apr/02/peter-blake-sgt-pepper-cover-revisited|work=The Guardian|date=13 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Sir Peter Blake's new Beatles' Sgt Pepper's album cover|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-17583026|publisher=BBC|date=13 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Interests and influences==

===Archaeology===
{{quote box
| align = right
| width = 30%|
| source =&lt;ref name=&quot;Auto1993&quot;/&gt;{{rp|364}}
| quote = The lure of the past came up to grab me. To see a dagger slowly appearing, with its gold glint, through the sand was romantic. The carefulness of lifting pots and objects from the soil filled me with a longing to be an archaeologist myself.
}}

Christie had a lifelong interest in archaeology. She met her second husband, [[Max Mallowan|Sir Max Mallowan]], a distinguished archaeologist, on a trip to the excavation site at [[Ur]] in 1930. But her fame as an author far surpassed his fame in archaeology.{{sfn|Dever|2004|p=162}} Prior to meeting Mallowan, Christie had not had any extensive brushes with archaeology, but once the two married, they made sure to only go to sites where they could work together. Christie accompanied Mallowan on countless archaeological trips, spending 3–4 months at a time in [[Syria]] and [[Iraq]] at excavation sites at Ur, [[Nineveh]], [[Tell Arpachiyah]], [[Chagar Bazar]], [[Tell Brak]], and [[Nimrud]]. She wrote novels and short stories, but also contributed work to the archaeological sites, more specifically to the archaeological restoration and labelling of ancient exhibits, including tasks such as cleaning and conserving delicate ivory pieces, reconstructing pottery, developing photos from early excavations which later led to taking photographs of the site and its findings, and taking field notes.&lt;ref name=&quot;britishmuseum&quot;&gt;{{cite web|publisher=Trustees of the British Museum|url=https://www.britishmuseum.org/explore/online_tours/middle_east/agatha_christie__archaeology/agatha_christie__archaeology.aspx|title=Agatha Christie: Archaeology|accessdate=25 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Christie would always pay for her own board and lodging and her travel expenses so as to not influence the funding of the archaeological excavations, and she also supported excavations as an anonymous sponsor.&lt;ref name=&quot;britishmuseum&quot;/&gt; During their time in the Middle East, there was also a large amount of time spent travelling to and from Mallowan's sites. Their extensive travelling had a strong influence on her writing, as some type of transportation often plays a part in her murderer's schemes. The large amount of travel was reused in novels such as ''[[Murder on the Orient Express]]'', as well as suggesting the idea of archaeology as an adventure itself.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.comhem.se/cornelius/brand.html|title=Archaeology is a brand!|publisher=Comhem|accessdate=30 November 2012|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120505140439/http://web.comhem.se/cornelius/brand.html|archivedate=5 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the Second World War, she chronicled her time in Syria with fondness in ''Come Tell Me How You Live''. Anecdotes, memories, funny episodes are strung in a rough timeline, with more emphasis on eccentric characters and lovely scenery than on factual accuracy.&lt;ref name=&quot;mallowan&quot;/&gt; From 8 November 2001 to 24 March 2002, [[British Museum|The British Museum]] had an exhibit named ''Agatha Christie and Archaeology: Mystery in Mesopotamia'', which presented the life of Christie and the influences of archaeology in her life and works.&lt;ref name=&quot;britishmuseum&quot;/&gt;

===Use of archaeology in her writing===
Many of the settings for Christie's books were directly inspired by the many archaeological field seasons spent in the Middle East on the sites managed by her husband Max. The extent of her time spent at the many locations featured in her books is apparent from the extreme detail in which she describes them. One such site featured in her work is the temple site of [[Abu Simbel temples|Abu Simbel]], depicted in ''[[Death on the Nile]]''. Also there is the great detail in which she describes life at the dig site in ''[[Murder in Mesopotamia]]''. Among the characters in her books, Christie has often given prominence to the archaeologists and experts in Middle Eastern cultures and artefacts. Most notable are the characters of Dr. Eric Leidner in ''Murder in Mesopotamia'' and Signor Richetti in ''Death on the Nile'', while many minor characters were archaeologists in ''They Came to Baghdad''.

Some of Christie's best known novels with heavy archaeological influences are:
* ''[[Murder in Mesopotamia]]'' (1936)&amp;nbsp;– the most archaeologically influenced of all her novels, as it is set in the Middle East at an archaeological dig site and associated expedition house. The main characters include archaeologist Dr. Eric Leidner, his wife, many specialists and assistants, and the men working on the site. The novel is noted most for its careful description of the dig site and house, which showed that the author had spent much of her time in very similar situations. The characters in this book in particular are also based on archaeologists whom Christie knew from her personal experiences on excavation sites.
* ''[[Death on the Nile]]'' (1937)&amp;nbsp;– takes place on a tour boat on the Nile. Many archaeological sites are visited along the way and one of the main characters, Signor Richetti, is an archaeologist.
* ''[[Appointment with Death]]'' (1938)&amp;nbsp;– set in [[Jerusalem]] and its surrounding area. The death itself occurs at an old cave site in [[Petra]] and offers some very descriptive details of sites which Christie herself could have visited to write the book.
* ''[[They Came to Baghdad]]'' (1951)&amp;nbsp;– inspired by Christie's own trips to [[Baghdad]] with Mallowan, and involves an archaeologist as the heroine's love interest.

==Portrayals in fiction==
Christie has been portrayed on a number of occasions in film and television. Several biographical programmes have been made, such as [[BBC television]]'s ''[[Agatha Christie: A Life in Pictures]]'' (2004; in which she was portrayed by [[Olivia Williams]], [[Anna Massey]], and [[Bonnie Wright]], at different stages in her life), and in Season 3, Episode 1 of ''[[ITV (TV channel)|ITV Perspectives]]'': &quot;The Mystery of Agatha Christie&quot; (2013), hosted by [[David Suchet]], who plays Hercule Poirot on television.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|work=Perspectives|publisher=ITV|title=The Mystery of Agatha Christie with David Suchet|year=2013|author=Suchet, David|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VUmbf2fMF5M}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Christie has also been portrayed fictionally. Some of these portrayals have explored and offered accounts of Christie's disappearance in 1926, including:

* the film ''[[Agatha (film)|Agatha]]'' (1979) with [[Vanessa Redgrave]], in which she sneaks away to plan revenge against her husband (Christie's heirs sued unsuccessfully to prevent the film's distribution&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tcm.com/this-month/article/1083600%7C0/Agatha.html|title=Agatha|author=Axmaker, Sean|work=Turner Classic Movies|accessdate=17 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;);
* the ''[[Doctor Who]]'' episode &quot;[[The Unicorn and the Wasp]]&quot; (17 May 2008), with [[Fenella Woolgar]], in which her disappearance is the result of her suffering a temporary breakdown owing to a brief psychic link being formed between her and an alien wasp called the [[Vespiform]]; and
* ''[[Agatha and the Truth of Murder]]'', in which she goes under cover to solve the murder of [[Florence Nightingale]]'s [[goddaughter]], Florence Nightingale Shore.

A fictionalised account of Christie's disappearance is also the central theme of a Korean musical, ''Agatha''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Musical Agatha|url=http://www.visitseoul.net/en/article/article.do?_method=view&amp;m=0004009001001&amp;p=06&amp;art_id=78125&amp;lang=en|website=VisitSeoul.com|publisher=Seoul Metropolitan Government|accessdate=10 April 2015|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150416100240/http://www.visitseoul.net/en/article/article.do?_method=view&amp;m=0004009001001&amp;p=06&amp;art_id=78125&amp;lang=en|archivedate=16 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other portrayals, such as Hungarian film, ''Kojak Budapesten'' (1980; not to be confused with the 1986 comedy of the same name) create their own scenarios involving Christie's criminal skill. In the TV play, ''Murder by the Book'' (1986), Christie herself (Dame [[Peggy Ashcroft]]) murdered one of her fictional-turned-real characters, Poirot. The heroine of Liar-Soft's [[visual novel]] ''[[Shikkoku no Sharnoth: What a Beautiful Tomorrow]]'' (2008), Mary Clarissa Christie, is based on the real-life Christie. Christie features as a character in Gaylord Larsen's ''Dorothy and Agatha'' and ''The London Blitz Murders'' by Max Allan Collins.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Gaylord|last=Larsen|publisher=Amazon|url=https://archive.org/details/dorothyagatha00lars|title=Dorothy and Agatha: A Mystery Novel|isbn=978-0-525-24865-1|accessdate=30 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Max Allan|last=Collins|url=https://www.amazon.com/London-Blitz-Murders-Allan-Collins/dp/0425198057|title=The London Blitz Murders|isbn=978-0-425-19805-6|year=2004|publisher=Amazon|accessdate=30 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; A young Agatha is depicted in the Spanish historical television series ''[[Gran Hotel (TV series)|Gran Hotel]]'' (2011). Aiding the local detectives, Agatha finds inspiration to write her new novel.

==See also==
{{Wikipedia books|Agatha Christie}}
* ''[[Agatha Christie: A Life in Pictures]]'' (her life story in a 2004 BBC drama)
* [[Abney Hall]] (home to her brother-in-law; several books use Abney as their setting)
* [[Greenway Estate]] (Christie's former home in Devon. The house and grounds are now in the possession of the [[National Trust for Places of Historic Interest or Natural Beauty|National Trust]] and open to the public)
* [[Agatha Christie indult]] (an oecumenical request to which Christie was signatory seeking permission for the occasional use of the Tridentine (Latin) mass in England and Wales)
* [[Agatha Award]]
* [[Agatha Christie Award (Japan)]]
* [[Agatha Christie (video game series)]]
* [[List of solved missing persons cases]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group=lower-alpha}}

==References==
{{Reflist|32em}}

==Sources==
*{{Citation|author-link=Amanda Adams| last=Adams| first=Amanda|year=2010| title=Ladies of the Field: Early Women Archaeologists and Their Search for Adventure|publisher=Douglas &amp; McIntyre| isbn=978-1-55365-433-9}}
*{{Citation | title= [[Agatha Christie: An Autobiography]] |last= Mallowan | first= Agatha Christie |year= 1977 | publisher = [[Dodd, Mead &amp; Company|Dodd, Mead &amp; Co]] |location=New York |isbn=0-396-07516-9}}
*{{Citation | isbn = 0-553-35049-8 | title = Come, Tell Me How You Live | first = Agatha Christie | last = Mallowan | place = Toronto, New York | publisher = Bantam Books | year = 1985 | url = https://archive.org/details/cometellmehowyou0000mall }}.
*{{Citation | isbn = 0-553-35081-1 | title = An Autobiography | first = Agatha Christie | last = Mallowan | origyear = 1977 | year = 1990 | place = New York, NY, US | publisher = Bantam}}.
*{{cite web| title= Travel and Archaeology| url= http://agathachristie.com/about-christie/travel-and-archeology/| publisher= Agatha Christie Limited| accessdate= 29 February 2012| url-status=dead| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20081009185216/http://www.agathachristie.com/about-christie/travel-and-archeology/| archivedate= 9 October 2008| df= dmy-all}}
*{{cite web | title=Agatha Christie – the explorer &amp; archaeologist | format=PDF | url=http://agathachristie.com/cms-media/assets/PR_-_Agatha_Christie_-_the_Explorer.pdf | publisher=Agatha Christie Limited | accessdate=1 March 2012 | url-status=dead | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091007221242/http://www.agathachristie.com/cms-media/assets/PR_-_Agatha_Christie_-_the_Explorer.pdf | archivedate=7 October 2009 | df=dmy-all }}
*{{Citation | last = Dever | first = Norma | year = 2004 | title = They Also Dug!  Archaeologist's Wives and Their Stories | journal = Near Eastern Archaeology | place = Boston | publisher = The American Schools of Oriental Research | volume = 67 | pages = 162–73 | issue = 3 | doi = 10.2307/4132378}}.
*{{Citation | last = Holtorf | first = Cornelius | year = 2007 | title = Archaeology is a Brand!  The meaning of archaeology in contemporary popular culture | place = Oxford, England | publisher = Archaeopress}}.
*{{Cite magazine | last=Lubelski|first= Amy|title= Museums: In the Field with Agatha Christie| magazine = Archaeology |date=March–April 2002|volume=55|issue=2|url= http://www.archaeology.org/0203/reviews/christie.html |accessdate=28 February 2012}}
*{{Cite journal | last1 = Roaf | first1 = Michael | first2 = Robert | last2 = Killick | year = 1987 | title = A Mysterious Affair of Styles: The Ninevite 5 Pottery of Northern Mesopotamia | journal = Iraq | volume = 49 | pages = 199–230 | doi = 10.2307/4200273}}.
*{{Citation | last = Thomas | first = WG | title = Murder in Mesopotamia: Agatha Christie and Archaeology | url = http://www.gwthomas.org/murderinmeso.htm | url-status=dead | archiveurl = https://archive.today/20130414235457/http://www.gwthomas.org/murderinmeso.htm | archivedate = 14 April 2013 | df = dmy-all }}.
*{{Citation | publisher = Trustees of the British Museum | year = 2012 | title = The British Museum | contribution = Pottery palace ware jar | url = https://www.britishmuseum.org/explore/online_tours/middle_east/agatha_christie__archaeology/pottery_palace_ware_jar.aspx}}.

==External links==
{{Library resources box
| onlinebooksby = yes
| by          = yes
| viaf        = 71388952
| label       = Agatha Christie}}
{{Sister project links | wikt = no | c = :Category:Agatha Christie | n = no | q = Agatha Christie | s = Author:Agatha Mary Clarissa Christie | author = no | b = no | v = no}}
* {{Official website}}
* {{IMDb name|2005}}
* {{Gutenberg author |id=Agatha+Christie}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Agatha Christie}}
* {{OL author}}
* [http://www.oxfordshireblueplaques.org.uk/plaques/christie.html Agatha Christie/Sir Max Mallowan's] [[blue plaque]] at Cholsey
* [https://www.theguardian.com/books/2008/jun/10/agathachristie Profile and related articles] in ''The Guardian''
* [https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/mystery/marple/christie.html Profile on PBS.org]
* [http://www.famousauthors.org/agatha-christie Profile on FamousAuthors.org]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090325002626/http://www.christiemystery.co.uk/ &quot;The Christie Mystery&quot;], a fan site
* [http://www.iwm.org.uk/collections/item/object/80000490 Oral history] at the [[Imperial War Museum]]
* [http://lib-archives.ex.ac.uk/Record.aspx?&amp;id=EUL+MS+99 Agatha Christie business papers at the University of Exeter]

{{Agatha Christie}}
{{Hercule Poirot}}
{{Miss Marple}}
{{And Then There Were None}}
{{The Unexpected Guest}}
{{Agatha Christie video games}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Christie, Agatha}}
[[Category:Agatha Christie| ]]
[[Category:1890 births]]
[[Category:1976 deaths]]
[[Category:20th-century English novelists]]
[[Category:20th-century English writers]]
[[Category:20th-century British dramatists and playwrights]]
[[Category:20th-century British women writers]]
[[Category:20th-century British short story writers]]
[[Category:Anthony Award winners]]
[[Category:Booker authors' division]]
[[Category:British autobiographers]]
[[Category:British detective writers]]
[[Category:British women in World War I]]
[[Category:British women short story writers]]
[[Category:Burials in Oxfordshire]]
[[Category:Dames Commander of the Order of the British Empire]]
[[Category:Edgar Award winners]]
[[Category:English people of American descent]]
[[Category:English crime fiction writers]]
[[Category:English dramatists and playwrights]]
[[Category:English mystery writers]]
[[Category:English short story writers]]
[[Category:English women dramatists and playwrights]]
[[Category:English women novelists]]
[[Category:Fellows of the Royal Society of Literature]]
[[Category:Female nurses in World War I]]
[[Category:Female wartime nurses]]
[[Category:Formerly missing people]]
[[Category:Members of the Detection Club]]
[[Category:Missing person cases in England]]
[[Category:People from Cholsey]]
[[Category:People from Sunningdale]]
[[Category:People from Torquay]]
[[Category:Temporary disappearances]]
[[Category:Wives of knights]]
[[Category:Women mystery writers]]
[[Category:Women archaeologists]]
[[Category:Women autobiographers]]
[[Category:Women historical novelists]]
[[Category:Writers of historical mysteries]]</text>
      <sha1>mqz4tepfftmwd3yvjq6bwh0zf9ykws3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
