  <page>
    <title>A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3032</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942426323</id>
      <parentid>942077540</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-24T16:25:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>12.231.109.141</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>fix link to Miles Gloriosus</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about|the musical|the film|A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum (film)}}
{{Infobox musical
|name=A Funny Thing Happened&lt;br&gt; on the Way to the Forum
|image=AFTHWF original Playbill.jpg
|image_size=225px
|caption=[[Playbill]] from the original Broadway production
|music=[[Stephen Sondheim]]
|lyrics=Stephen Sondheim
|book=[[Burt Shevelove]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Larry Gelbart]]
|productions=1962 [[Broadway theatre|Broadway]]&lt;br /&gt;1963 [[West End theatre|West End]]&lt;br /&gt;1966 [[A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum (film)|film]]&lt;br /&gt;1972 Broadway&lt;br /&gt;1986 West End&lt;br /&gt;1996 Broadway&lt;br /&gt;2004 [[Royal National Theatre]]&lt;br /&gt;2009 [[Kwai Tsing Theatre|Hong Kong]]&lt;br /&gt;2009 [[Stratford Shakespeare Festival]]&lt;br /&gt;2012 [[Her Majesty's Theatre|Melbourne]]
|awards=[[Tony Award for Best Musical]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Tony Award for Best Book of a Musical|Tony Award for Best Author (Musical)]]
}}

'''''A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum''''' is a [[Musical theatre|musical]] with music and lyrics by [[Stephen Sondheim]] and book by [[Burt Shevelove]] and [[Larry Gelbart]].

Inspired by the [[farce]]s of the [[Ancient Rome|ancient Roman]] playwright [[Plautus]] (251&amp;ndash;183 BC), specifically ''[[Pseudolus]]'', ''[[Miles Gloriosus (play)|Miles Gloriosus]]'', and ''[[Mostellaria]]'', the musical tells the bawdy story of a [[slavery|slave]] named Pseudolus and his attempts to win his freedom by helping his young master woo the girl next door. The plot displays many classic elements of [[farce]], including puns, the slamming of doors, cases of [[mistaken identity]] (frequently involving characters disguising themselves as one another), and satirical comments on social class. The title derives from a line often used by [[vaudeville]] comedians to begin a story: &quot;A funny thing happened on the way to the theater&quot;.

The musical's original 1962 [[Broadway theatre|Broadway]] run won several [[Tony Award]]s, including Best Musical and Best Author (Musical). ''A Funny Thing'' has enjoyed several Broadway and [[West End theatre|West End]] revivals and was made into a successful [[A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum (film)|film]] starring the original lead of the stage musical, [[Zero Mostel]].

==Productions==

===Original Broadway===
''A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum'' opened on [[Broadway theatre|Broadway]] on May 8, 1962, at the [[Neil Simon Theatre|Alvin Theatre]], and then transferred to the [[Mark Hellinger Theatre]] and the [[Majestic Theatre (Broadway)|Majestic Theatre]], where the show closed on August 29, 1964, after 964 performances and 8 previews.

The show's creators originally wanted [[Phil Silvers]] in the lead role of [[Pseudolus]], but he turned them down, allegedly because he would have to perform onstage without his glasses, and his vision was so poor that he feared tripping into the orchestra pit. He is also quoted as turning down the role for being &quot;[[The Phil Silvers Show|Sgt. Bilko]] in a toga&quot;. (Silvers eventually played the role — wearing his glasses — in a 1972 revival. In the film, he played Marcus Lycus.) [[Milton Berle]] also passed on the role. Eventually, Zero Mostel was cast.&lt;ref name=green&gt;Green, Stanley and Green, Kay.[https://books.google.com/books?id=KDKFHniTy1YC&amp;lpg=PA198 &quot;A Funny Thing Happened on the Way To the Forum&quot;] ''Broadway Musicals, Show By Show'' (1996),  Hal Leonard Corporation, {{ISBN|0-7935-7750-0}}, p. 198&lt;/ref&gt;

During the out of town pre-Broadway tryouts the show was attracting little business and not playing well. [[Jerome Robbins]] was called in to give advice and make changes. The biggest change Robbins made was a new opening number to replace &quot;Love Is in the Air&quot; and introduce the show as a bawdy, wild comedy. Stephen Sondheim wrote the song &quot;Comedy Tonight&quot; for this new opening.&lt;ref name=green /&gt; From that point on, the show was a success.

It was directed by [[George Abbott]] and produced by [[Hal Prince]], with choreography by [[Jack Cole (choreographer)|Jack Cole]] and uncredited staging and choreography by Robbins. The scenic and costume design was by [[Tony Walton]]. This wardrobe is on display at the Costume World Broadway Collection in Pompano Beach, Florida. The lighting design was by [[Jean Rosenthal]]. Along with Mostel, the musical featured a cast of seasoned performers, including [[Jack Gilford]] (Mostel's friend and fellow blacklist member), [[David Burns (actor)|David Burns]], [[John Carradine]], [[Ruth Kobart]], and [[Raymond Walburn]]. The young lovers were played by Brian Davies and Preshy Marker. [[Karen Black]], originally cast as the ingenue, was replaced out of town.

The show won several [[Tony Award]]s: Best Musical, Best Actor, Best Supporting Actor (Burns), Best Book, and Best Director. The score, however, was coolly received; it was Sondheim's first musical on Broadway in which he wrote both the music and lyrics, and did not earn a nomination for Best Original Score.

===London===
The show was presented twice in London's [[West End theatre|West End]]. The 1963 production and its 1986 revival were staged at the [[Novello Theatre|Strand Theatre]] and the [[Piccadilly Theatre]] respectively,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guidetomusicaltheatre.com/london_shows_chronology/1963.htm &quot;Listing, 1963 production&quot;] Guidetomusicaltheatre.com, retrieved December 9, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thisistheatre.com/shows/piccadilly111.html &quot;Listing, 1986 production&quot;] Thisistheatre.com, retrieved December 9, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; and starred [[Frankie Howerd]] as Pseudolus and [[Leon Greene]] as Miles Gloriosus in both. In the 1963 production, [[Kenneth Connor]] appeared as Hysterium, [['Monsewer' Eddie Gray]] as [[Senex]], [[Jon Pertwee]] as Marcus Lycus, and [[Leon Greene]] as Miles Gloriosus. In the 1986 revival, [[Patrick Cargill]] was Senex with [[Ronnie Stevens (actor)|Ronnie Stevens]] as Hysterium and [[Derek Royle]] as Erronius.

In 2004 there was a limited-run revival at the [[Royal National Theatre]], starring [[Desmond Barrit]] as Pseudolus, [[Philip Quast]] as Miles Gloriosus, [[Hamish McColl]] as Hysterium and [[Isla Blair]] as Domina (who had previously played Philia in the 1963 production).&lt;ref&gt;Inverne, James. [http://www.playbill.com/article/thoroughly-modern-millie-closes-in-london-as-new-musicals-prepare-to-open-com-120179# &quot;Thoroughly Modern Millie Closes in London as New Musicals Prepare to Open&quot;]. ''Playbill'', June 7, 2004, accessed December 25, 2016&lt;/ref&gt; This production was nominated for the 2005 [[Olivier Award]], Outstanding Musical Production.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.olivierawards.com/winners/view/item98372/olivier-winners-2005/ &quot;Olivier Winners, 2005&quot;.] olivierawards.com, accessed December 27, 2016&lt;/ref&gt;

===Motion picture adaptation===
{{main article|A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum (film)}}
''A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum'' was made into a [[musical film]] in 1966, directed by [[Richard Lester]], with Mostel and Gilford re-creating their Broadway stage roles, [[Leon Greene]] reprising his West End stage role, and Phil Silvers in an expanded role as &quot;Marcus Lycus&quot;. [[David Burns (actor)|David Burns]] did not return for the film role of Senex, which was played in the film by [[Michael Hordern]]. [[Buster Keaton]] made his final film appearance in the role of Erronius. Jon Pertwee, who played Lycus in the London production, appears in a cameo role.

===Broadway revivals===
A [[Revival (theatre)|revival]] opened on Broadway at the [[Lunt-Fontanne Theatre]] on April 4, 1972 and closed on August 12, 1972 after 156 performances. Directed by co-author [[Burt Shevelove]] the cast starred Phil Silvers as Pseudolus (later replaced by [[Tom Poston]]), [[Lew Parker]] as Senex, [[Carl Ballantine]] as Lycus and [[Reginald Owen]] as Erronius. [[Larry Blyden]], who played Hysterium, the role created by Jack Gilford, also co-produced.&lt;ref name=phil&gt;[http://www.sondheimguide.com/forum.html#72BR &quot; 'A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum' 1972&quot;] sondheimguide.com, accessed December 25, 2016&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Pretty Little Picture&quot; and &quot;That'll Show Him&quot; were dropped from the show, and were replaced with &quot;Echo Song&quot; (sung by Hero and Philia), and &quot;Farewell&quot; (added for [[Nancy Walker]] as Domina, as she and Senex depart for the country). &quot;Echo Song&quot; and &quot;Farewell&quot; had been added to a production staged in Los Angeles the previous year and were composed by Sondheim. They had to close soon after Phil Silvers suffered a stroke. The show won two Tony Awards, Best Leading Actor in a Musical for Silvers, and Best Featured Actor in a Musical for Blyden.&lt;ref name=phil/&gt;

The musical was revived again with great success in 1996, opening at the [[St. James Theatre]] on April 18, 1996 and closing on January 4, 1998 after 715 performances. The cast starred [[Nathan Lane]] as Pseudolus (replaced by [[Whoopi Goldberg]] and later by [[David Alan Grier]]), [[Mark Linn-Baker]] as Hysterium, [[Ernie Sabella]] as Lycus, [[Jim Stanek]] as Hero, [[Lewis J. Stadlen]] as Senex, and Cris Groenendaal as Miles Gloriosus. The production was directed by [[Jerry Zaks]], with choreography by [[Rob Marshall]]. Lane won the 1996 Tony Award for Best Leading Actor and the Drama Desk Award, Outstanding Actor in a Musical; the production was nominated for the 1996 Tony Award and Drama Desk Award, Revival of a Musical.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.playbill.com/production/a-funny-thing-happened-on-the-way-to-the-forum-st-james-theatre-vault-0000004175# &quot; 'A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum' Broadway 1996&quot;,]. ''Playbill'' (vault), accessed December 26, 2016&lt;/ref&gt;

Every actor who has opened in the role of Pseudolus on Broadway (Zero Mostel, Phil Silvers, and Nathan Lane) has won a Best Leading Actor Tony Award for his performance. In addition, [[Jason Alexander]], who performed as Pseudolus in one scene in ''[[Jerome Robbins' Broadway]]'', also won a Tony for Best Actor in a Musical.

===Other productions===
The original Australian production with American actor [[Jack Collins (actor)|Jack Collins]] as Pseudolus opened at the [[Theatre Royal, Sydney|Theatre Royal]] in Sydney in July 1964, and toured other Australian cities through 1965.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.ausstage.edu.au/pages/event/13525|title=AusStage - A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum|website=www.ausstage.edu.au|access-date=2017-09-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1998, [[Jon English]] starred as Pseudolus in [[Essgee Entertainment]]'s production that opened New Year's Day at the State Theatre, Melbourne and toured Australia and New Zealand, closing September 1999.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://showstoppers.com.au/html/ForumPage.html |title = A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Stephen Sondheim Center for the Performing Arts]] produced a limited-run revival of the musical from January 11 to 27, 2008. The production was directed by Randal K. West, with Justin Hill as musical director and Adam Cates as choreographer. The cast featured [[Richard Kind]] as Pseudolus, Joel Blum as Senex, [[Stephen DeRosa]] as Marcus Lycus, Sean McCall as Hysterium, and Steve Wilson as Miles Gloriosus. It also featured Diana Upton-Hill, Ryan Gaffney, Stephen Mark Crisp, Jack Kloppenborg, and Margret Clair.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gazetteonline.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080117/FEATURES/660746609/1006/NEWS &quot;News&quot;] gazettonline, January 14, 2008]  {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150123130615/http://www.gazetteonline.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=%2F20080117%2FFEATURES%2F660746609%2F1006%2FNEWS |date=January 23, 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lipton, Brian Scott.[http://www.theatermania.com/content/news.cfm/story/12431 &quot;Richard Kind to Star in Fairfield Center's 'Forum'&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080302020119/http://www.theatermania.com/content/news.cfm/story/12431 |date=2008-03-02 }} Theatermania.com, January 4, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gans, Andrew.[http://www.playbill.com/news/article/114148.html &quot;Tragedy Tomorrow, Comedy Tonight: 'Forum' Begins Run at Sondheim Center&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081211112410/http://www.playbill.com/news/article/114148.html |date=December 11, 2008 }} Playbill.com, January 11, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

The Chung Ying Theatre Company in Hong Kong staged a Cantonese version of the musical at [[Kwai Tsing Theatre]], to celebrate the company's 30th anniversary. It was directed by [[Chung King Fai]] and Ko Tin Lung and ran from 14 to 21 March 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chungying.com/09funnything/about.html &quot;Funny Thing&quot;] chungying.com {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090621154358/http://www.chungying.com/09funnything/about.html |date=June 21, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Stratford Shakespeare Festival]] in [[Stratford, Ontario|Stratford]], Ontario, Canada production ran from June 11 to November 7, 2009, with [[Des McAnuff]] directing and [[Wayne Cilento]] as choreographer.&lt;ref&gt;(no author).[http://www.stratfordfestival.ca/about/history.aspx?id=1178 &quot;Stratford Production History&quot;] Stratfordfestival.ca, accessed August 16, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bruce Dow]] originally performed the role of Pseudolus, but was forced to withdraw from the entire 2009 season due to an injury, and the role was then performed by [[Seán Cullen]] as of September 5, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;Bacalzo, Dan.[http://www.theatermania.com/canada/news/08-2009/sean-cullen-to-replace-injured-bruce-dow-in-stratf_20718.html &quot;Sean Cullen to Replace Injured Bruce Dow in Stratford 'Forum' &quot;] Theatermania.com, August 17, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; [[Stephen Ouimette]] played Hysterium. [[Mirvish Productions]] presented the earlier Stratford production at the Canon Theatre, [[Toronto]], in December 2010 through January 2011. Bruce Dow and Sean Cullen were alternates in the lead role.&lt;ref&gt;Nestruck, J. Kelly.[https://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/arts/theatre/a-funny-thing-happened-on-the-way-to-the-forum-still-brings-the-funny-but-not-as-much/article1844917/ &quot;Theatre Review. 'A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum' still brings the funny, but not as much&quot;] ''The Globe and Mail'', December 20, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2012 the play opened at [[Her Majesty's Theatre, Melbourne]], Australia, with [[Geoffrey Rush]] as Pseudolus, [[Magda Szubanski]] as Domina and [[Shane Bourne]] as Senex.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.funnything.com.au/ &quot;A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121028000322/http://www.funnything.com.au/ |date=October 28, 2012 }}, Australian website&lt;/ref&gt; Stephen Sondheim came to Melbourne specifically to watch the show.

''A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum'' was produced at Two River Theater in Red Bank, New Jersey from November 14, 2015 to December 13, 2015. The production was performed by an all-male cast (Paul Castree, Eddie Cooper, Kevin Isola, David Josefsberg, Max Kumangai, Graham Rowat, Manny Stark, Bobby Conte Thornton, David Turner, [[Michael Urie]], [[Tom Deckman]], and [[Christopher Fitzgerald (actor)|Christopher Fitzgerald]]).&lt;ref&gt;Kennedy, Marina. [http://www.broadwayworld.com/new-jersey/article/BWW-Review-A-FUNNY-THING-HAPPENED-ON-THE-WAY-TO-THE-FORUM-at-TRT-Musical-Comedy-at-its-Very-Best-20151124&quot;BWW Review: 'A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum' at TRT-Musical Comedy at its Very Best&quot;] broadwayworld.com, November 24, 2015&lt;/ref&gt;

==Plot==
[[File:Forum LP cover.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Graphic from the original Broadway cast album]]
In ancient Rome, some neighbors live in three adjacent houses. In the center is the house of Senex, who lives there with wife Domina, son Hero, and several slaves, including head slave Hysterium and the musical's main character Pseudolus. A slave belonging to Hero, Pseudolus wishes to buy, win, or steal his freedom. One of the neighboring houses is owned by Marcus Lycus, who is a buyer and seller of beautiful women; the other belongs to the ancient Erronius, who is abroad searching for his long-lost children (stolen in infancy by pirates).

One day, Senex and Domina depart on a visit to Domina's mother and leave Pseudolus in charge of Hero. Hero confides in Pseudolus that he is in love with the lovely Philia, one of the courtesans in the House of Lycus (albeit still a virgin). Pseudolus promises to help him win Philia's love in exchange for his own freedom. Unfortunately (as the two find out when they pay a visit on Lycus), Philia has been sold to the renowned warrior [[Miles Gloriosus]], who is expected to claim her very soon.  Pseudolus, an excellent liar, uses Philia's cheery disposition to convince Lycus that she has picked up a [[Yersinia pestis|plague]] from [[Crete]], which causes its victims to smile endlessly in its terminal stages. By offering to isolate her in Senex's house, he is able to give Philia and Hero some time alone together, and the two fall in love. But Philia insists that, even though she is in love with Hero, she must honor her contract with the Captain, for &quot;that is the way of a courtesan.&quot; To appease her, he tells her to wait (&quot;that's what virgins do best, isn't it?&quot;) inside, and that he will have the captain knock three times when he arrives. Pseudolus comes up with a plan to slip Philia a sleeping potion that will render her unconscious. He will then tell Lycus that she has died of the Cretan plague, and will offer to remove the body. Hero will come along, and they will stow away on a ship headed for Greece. Satisfied with his plan, Pseudolus steals Hysterium's book of potions and has Hero read him the recipe for the sleeping potion; the only ingredient he lacks is &quot;mare's sweat&quot;, and Pseudolus goes off in search of some.

Unexpectedly, Senex returns home early from his trip, and knocks three times on his own door. Philia comes out of the house, and, thinking that Senex is the Captain, offers herself up to him. Surprised but game, Senex instructs Philia to wait in the house for him, and she does. Hysterium arrives to this confusion, and tells Senex that Philia is the new maid that he has hired. Pseudolus returns, having procured the necessary mare's sweat; seeing that Senex has returned unexpectedly and grasping the need to keep him out of the way, Pseudolus discreetly sprinkles some of the horse-sweat onto him, then suggests that the road trip has left Senex in dire need of a bath. Taking the bait, Senex instructs Hysterium to draw him a bath in the long-abandoned house of Erronius. But while this is happening, Erronius returns home, finally having given up the search for his long-lost children. Hysterium, desperate to keep him out of the house where his master is bathing, tells the old man that his house has become haunted – a story seemingly confirmed by the sound of Senex singing in his bath. Erronius immediately determines to have a soothsayer come and banish the spirit from his house, and Pseudolus obligingly poses as one, telling Erronius that, in order to banish the spirit, he must travel seven times around the seven hills of Rome (thus keeping the old man occupied and out of the way for quite a while).

When Miles Gloriosus arrives to claim his courtesan-bride, Pseudolus hides Philia on the roof of Senex's house; told that she has &quot;escaped,&quot; Lycus is terrified to face the Captain's wrath. Pseudolus offers to impersonate Lycus and talk his way out of the mess but, his ingenuity flagging, he ends up merely telling the Captain that Philia has disappeared, and that he, &quot;Lycus&quot;, will search for her. Displeased and suspicious, Miles insists that his soldiers accompany Pseudolus, but the wily slave loses them in Rome's winding streets.

Complicating matters further, Domina returns from her trip early, suspicious that her husband Senex is &quot;up to something low.&quot; She disguises herself in virginal white robes and a veil (much like Philia's) to try to catch Senex being unfaithful. Pseudolus convinces Hysterium to help him by dressing in [[Drag (clothing)|drag]] and pretending to be Philia, &quot;dead&quot; from the plague. Unfortunately, it turns out that Miles Gloriosus has just returned from Crete, where there is of course no actual plague. With the ruse thus revealed, the main characters run for their lives, resulting in a madcap chase across the stage with both Miles and Senex pursuing all three &quot;Philia&quot;s (Domina, Hysterium, and the actual Philia – all wearing identical white robes and veils). Meanwhile, the courtesans from the house of Marcus Lycus &amp;ndash; who had been recruited as mourners at &quot;Philia&quot;'s ersatz funeral &amp;ndash; have escaped, and Lycus sends his [[Eunuch (court official)|eunuch]]s out to bring them all back, adding to the general pandemonium.

Finally, the Captain's troops are able to round everyone up. His plot thoroughly unraveled, Pseudolus appears to be in deep trouble – but Erronius, completing his third circuit of the Roman hills, shows up fortuitously to discover that Miles Gloriosus and Philia are wearing matching rings which mark them as his long-lost children. Philia's betrothal to the Captain is nullified by the unexpected revelation that he's her brother, and, as the daughter of a free-born citizen, she's freed from Marcus Lycus. Philia weds Hero; Pseudolus gets his freedom and the lovely courtesan Gymnasia; Gloriosus receives twin courtesans to replace Philia; and Erronius is reunited with his children. A happy ending prevails for all – except for poor Senex, stuck with his shrewish wife Domina.

==Characters==
*'''[[Pseudolus]]''': A Roman slave, owned by Hero, who seeks to win freedom by helping Hero win the heart of Philia.  The name ''Pseudolus''  means &quot;Faker&quot;. While originally written as a male role, it has been performed by female actors as well.
*'''Hero''': Young son of Senex who falls in love with the virgin, Philia.
*'''Philia''': (Greek for &quot;love&quot;) A virgin in the house of Marcus Lycus, and Hero's love interest. Her name is also a homophone of the Latin word &quot;Filia,&quot; which means daughter. This foreshadows her status as the daughter of Erronius.
* '''Hysterium''': (Latin for &quot;Hysterical&quot;, or &quot;Anxious&quot;, the suffix &quot;-um&quot; makes the name neuter, and the character's gender is often mistaken throughout the piece) The chief slave in the house of Senex.
*'''[[Senex]]''': (Latin for &quot;old man&quot;) A henpecked, sardonic [[Senate of the Roman Republic|Roman senator]] living in a less fashionable suburb of Rome.
*'''Domina''': (Latin for &quot;mistress&quot;) The wife of Senex. A manipulative, shrewish woman loathed by her husband.
*'''Marcus Lycus''': A purveyor of courtesans, who operates from the house to the left of Senex. (Name based on Lycus, the prostitute in [[Plautus]]'s ''Poenulus''.)
*'''[[Miles Gloriosus]]''': (Latin for &quot;boastful soldier,&quot; the archetype of the braggart soldier in Roman comedies) A captain in the Roman army to whom Marcus Lycus has promised Philia.
*'''Erronius''': (Latin for &quot;wandering&quot;) Senex's elderly neighbor in the house to the right. He has spent the past twenty years searching for his two children, kidnapped in infancy by pirates.
*'''Gymnasia''': (Greek for &quot;Athletic&quot;, with the connotation of nakedness) A courtesan from the house of Lycus with whom Pseudolus falls in love.
*'''Tintinabula''': (Latin for &quot;Bells&quot;) A jingling, bell-wearing courtesan in the house of Lycus.
*'''Vibrata''': (Latin for &quot;Vibrant&quot;) A wild, vibrant courtesan in the house of Lycus.
*'''Geminae''': (Latin for &quot;Twins&quot;) Twin courtesans in the house of Lycus.
*'''Panacea''': (Greek for &quot;Cure All&quot;) A courtesan in the house of Lycus.
*'''Proteans''': Choristers who play multiple roles (slaves, citizens, soldiers, and eunuchs). They accompany Pseudolus in &quot;Comedy Tonight&quot;. On Broadway, three people played all of these roles.

==Cast==
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;&quot;
|-
! Role
!Original Broadway
!Original London
!1966 [[A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum (film)|film]]
!1972 Broadway Revival
!1996 Broadway Revival
!2004 London Revival
|-
!Prologus/Pseudolus
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Zero Mostel]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Frankie Howerd]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Zero Mostel]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Phil Silvers]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Nathan Lane]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Desmond Barrit]]
|-
!Hero
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | Brian Davies
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | John Rye
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Michael Crawford]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | John Hansen&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.ibdb.com/broadway-production/a-funny-thing-happened-on-the-way-to-the-forum-3525 |title=A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum – Broadway Musical – 1972 Revival {{!}} IBDB}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Jim Stanek]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | Vince Leigh
|-
!Philia
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | Preshy Marker
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Isla Blair]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Annette Andre]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | Pamela Hall
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Jessica Boevers]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Caroline Sheen]]
|-
!Hysterium
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Jack Gilford]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Kenneth Connor]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Jack Gilford]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Larry Blyden]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Mark Linn-Baker]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Hamish McColl]]
|-
!Senex
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[David Burns (actor)|David Burns]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [['Monsewer' Eddie Gray|Eddie Gray]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Michael Hordern]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Lew Parker]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Lewis J. Stadlen]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Sam Kelly]]
|-
!Domina
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Ruth Kobart]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | Linda Gray 
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Patricia Jessel]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | Lizabeth Pritchett
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Mary Testa]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Isla Blair]]
|-
!Marcus Lycus
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[John Carradine]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Jon Pertwee]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Phil Silvers]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Carl Ballantine]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Ernie Sabella]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[David Schneider (actor)|David Schneider]]
|-
! Miles Gloriosus
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Ronald Holgate]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Leon Greene]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Leon Greene]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Carl Lindstrom]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Cris Groenendaal]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Philip Quast]]
|-
! Erronius
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Raymond Walburn]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Robertson Hare]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Buster Keaton]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Reginald Owen]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[William Duell]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Harry Towb]]
|}

==Songs==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
'''Act I'''
* &quot;Comedy Tonight&quot; – Pseudolus and Company
* &quot;Love, I Hear&quot; – Hero
* &quot;Free&quot; – Pseudolus and Hero
* &quot;The House of Marcus Lycus&quot; – Lycus and Pseudolus
* &quot;Lovely&quot; – Philia and Hero
* &quot;Pretty Little Picture&quot; – Pseudolus, Hero, and Philia
* &quot;Everybody Ought to Have a Maid&quot; – Senex, Pseudolus, Hysterium and Lycus
* &quot;I'm Calm&quot; – Hysterium
* &quot;Impossible&quot; – Senex and Hero
* &quot;Bring Me My Bride&quot; – Miles Gloriosus and Company
{{col-2}}
'''Act II'''
* &quot;That Dirty Old Man&quot; – Domina
* &quot;That'll Show Him&quot; – Philia
* &quot;Lovely&quot; (reprise) – Pseudolus and Hysterium
* &quot;Funeral Sequence&quot; – Pseudolus, Miles Gloriosus and Company
* &quot;Finale&quot; – Company
{{col-end}}

'''Notes:''' 
*The song &quot;Love Is in the Air&quot; was originally intended as the opening number. The song was cut from the show and replaced with &quot;Comedy Tonight&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;(no author).[http://www.sondheim.com/shows/a_funny_thing_happened/#cut_songs &quot;Cut songs, 'A Funny Thing Happened'&quot;] Sondheim.com, accessed August 16, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; The song was later featured in the film ''[[The Birdcage]]'' (1996) and performed by [[Robin Williams]] and [[Christine Baranski]]. Another draft of the opening number, &quot;Invocation and Instructions to the Audience,&quot; has been used in subsequent revues of Sondheim songs and was sung by Nathan Lane in the musical ''[[The Frogs (musical)|The Frogs]]''. &quot;Pretty Little Picture&quot; is frequently dropped from productions of the show, and one verse of &quot;I'm Calm&quot; is also frequently trimmed. Other cut songs include &quot;Love Story (Your Eyes Are Blue)&quot; and &quot;The Echo Song&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sondheim.com/works/a_funny_thing_happened/ &quot; 'A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum' &quot;]. ''sondheim.com''. Retrieved on December 25, 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; The song &quot;Farewell&quot; was added to the 1972 Broadway revival.

==Awards and honors==

===Original Broadway production===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; width=&quot;95%&quot;
|-
! width=&quot;5%&quot;| Year
! width=&quot;25%&quot;| Award ceremony
! width=&quot;40%&quot;| Category
! width=&quot;20%&quot;| Nominee
! width=&quot;10%&quot;| Result
|-
| 1962
| [[Outer Critics Circle Award]]
| Special Award
| [[George Abbott]]
| {{won}}
|-
| rowspan=&quot;8&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;| 1963
| rowspan=&quot;8&quot;| [[Tony Award]]
| colspan=&quot;2&quot;| [[Tony Award for Best Musical|Best Musical]]
| {{won}}
|-
| Best Producer of a Musical
| [[Harold Prince]]
| {{won}}
|-
| [[Tony Award for Best Author|Best Author]]
| [[Burt Shevelove]] and [[Larry Gelbart]]
| {{won}}
|-
| [[Tony Award for Best Performance by a Leading Actor in a Musical|Best Performance by a Leading Actor in a Musical]]
| [[Zero Mostel]]
| {{won}}
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| [[Tony Award for Best Performance by a Featured Actor in a Musical|Best Performance by a Featured Actor in a Musical]]
| [[David Burns (actor)|David Burns]]
| {{won}}
|-
| [[Jack Gilford]]
| {{nom}}
|-
| [[Tony Award for Best Performance by a Featured Actress in a Musical|Best Performance by a Featured Actress in a Musical]]
| [[Ruth Kobart]]
| {{nom}}
|-
| [[Tony Award for Best Direction of a Musical|Best Direction of a Musical]]
| [[George Abbott]]
| {{won}}
|}

===1972 Broadway revival===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:95%;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:5%;&quot;| Year
! style=&quot;width:20%;&quot;| Award
! style=&quot;width:45%;&quot;| Category
! style=&quot;width:20%;&quot;| Nominee
! style=&quot;width:10%;&quot;| Result
|-
| rowspan=3|1972
| rowspan=3|[[Tony Award]]
| [[Tony Award for Best Actor in a Musical|Best Performance by a Leading Actor in a Musical]]
| [[Phil Silvers]]
| {{won}}
|-
| [[Tony Award for Best Featured Actor in a Musical|Best Performance by a Featured Actor in a Musical]]
| [[Larry Blyden]]
| {{won}}
|-
| [[Tony Award for Best Direction of a Musical|Best Direction of a Musical]]
| [[Burt Shevelove]]
| {{nom}}
|}

===1995 Broadway revival===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:95%;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:5%;&quot;| Year
! style=&quot;width:20%;&quot;| Award
! style=&quot;width:45%;&quot;| Category
! style=&quot;width:20%;&quot;| Nominee
! style=&quot;width:10%;&quot;| Result
|-
| rowspan=9|1996
| rowspan=4|[[Tony Award]]
| colspan=2|[[Tony Award for Best Revival of a Musical|Best Revival of a Musical]]
| {{nom}}
|-
| [[Tony Award for Best Performance by a Leading Actor in a Musical|Best Performance by a Leading Actor in a Musical]]
| [[Nathan Lane]]
| {{won}}
|-
| [[Tony Award for Best Performance by a Featured Actor in a Musical|Best Performance by a Featured Actor in a Musical]]
| [[Lewis J. Stadlen]]
| {{nom}}
|-
| [[Tony Award for Best Direction of a Musical|Best Direction of a Musical]]
| [[Jerry Zaks]]
| {{nom}}
|-
| rowspan=2|[[Drama Desk Award]]
| colspan=2|[[Drama Desk Award for Outstanding Revival of a Musical|Outstanding Revival of a Musical]]
| {{nom}}
|-
| [[Drama Desk Award for Outstanding Actor in a Musical|Outstanding Actor in a Musical]]
| [[Nathan Lane]]
| {{won}}
|-
| rowspan=2|[[Outer Critics Circle Award]]
| Outstanding Actor in a Musical
| [[Nathan Lane]]
| {{won}}
|-
| Outstanding Director of a Musical
| [[Jerry Zaks]]
| {{won}}
|-
| [[Drama League Award]]
| colspan=2|Distinguished Production of a Revival
| {{nom}}
|}

==In popular culture==
* In the second season of the AMC series ''[[Mad Men]],'' which takes place in 1962, several characters refer to the musical. For example, [[Don Draper]] runs into his former mistress, Rachel Menken, at [[Sardi's]]. Rachel and her new husband are on their way to see the show on Broadway.
* The musical was referenced in an episode of ''[[Glee (TV series)|Glee]]''; [[Shannon Beiste]] claims she has musical experience and states that she played ''The Forum'' in a production.
* In the ''[[South Park]]'' episode &quot;[[Cherokee Hair Tampons]]&quot;, Cartman sings the word &quot;No&quot; to the tune of &quot;Comedy Tonight&quot;.

==References==
'''Notes'''
{{reflist}}

'''Bibliography'''
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20071023093217/http://libretto.musicals.ru/text.php?textid=6&amp;language=1 &quot;'A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum' plot summary &amp; character descriptions&quot;] from [http://www.stageagent.com StageAgent.com]
*[http://www.guidetomusicaltheatre.com/shows_f/forum.htm &quot;Plot and production information&quot;, guidetomusicaltheatre.com]

==External links==
{{Commons category|A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20071023093217/http://libretto.musicals.ru/text.php?textid=6&amp;language=1 ''A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum'' at the Internet Broadway Database]
* [http://www.sondheimguide.com/forum.html ''''A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum'' Sondheim Guide]
* {{Cite web |url=http://libretto.musicals.ru/text.php?textid=6&amp;language=1 |title=Libretto for the Broadway play |access-date=April 20, 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071023093217/http://libretto.musicals.ru/text.php?textid=6&amp;language=1 |archive-date=October 23, 2007 |url-status=dead |df=mdy-all }}
* [http://www.mtishows.com/show_detail.asp?showid=000038 ''A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum''] at the Music Theatre International website

{{Stephen Sondheim}}
{{TonyAwardBestMusical 1947–1975}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Funny Thing Happened On The Way To The Forum, A}}
[[Category:1962 musicals]]
[[Category:Broadway musicals]]
[[Category:West End musicals]]
[[Category:Musicals based on plays]]
[[Category:Plays set in ancient Rome]]
[[Category:Musicals by Stephen Sondheim]]
[[Category:American plays adapted into films]]
[[Category:Plays based on Greek and Roman plays]]
[[Category:Musicals choreographed by Jerome Robbins]]
[[Category:Tony Award for Best Musical]]
[[Category:Musicals by Larry Gelbart]]
[[Category:Tony Award-winning musicals]]
[[Category:Adaptations of works by Plautus]]</text>
      <sha1>r2ms0ebkj1ul2zsev2liy60o3o5777j</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
