  <page>
    <title>Alcobaça, Portugal</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3043</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941808493</id>
      <parentid>941653484</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-20T20:27:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rodw</username>
        <id>125972</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Disambiguating links to [[The Gift]] (link changed to [[The Gift (band)]]) using [[User:Qwertyytrewqqwerty/DisamAssist|DisamAssist]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Portuguese subdivision
| official_name           = Alcobaça
| type            = municipality
| image_skyline           = Mosteiro_de_Alcoba%C3%A7a_(Portugal).jpg
| image_caption           = 
| image_flag              = Pt-acb3.png
| image_shield            = ACB1.png
| image_map               = LocalAlcobaca.svg
|coordinates             = {{coord|39|33|10|N|8|58|40|W|type:adm1st_region:PT_dim:100000|display=inline,title}}
|region             = [[Centro Region, Portugal|Centro]]
|CIM                = [[Oeste (intermunicipal community)|Oeste]]
|district           = [[Leiria District|Leiria]]
| leader_party            = [[Social Democratic Party (Portugal)|PSD]]
| leader_name             = [[Paulo Inácio]]
| area_total_km2          = 408.14
| elevation_m             = 42
|population_total        = 56693
|population_as_of        = 2011
| postal_code             = 2460, 2461, 2475
| area_code               = 
| parishes         = [[#Parishes|13]]
| patron           = [[Bernard of Clairvaux|Saint Bernard]] 
| holiday          = 20 August
| website                 = http://www.cm-alcobaca.pt/
}}

[[File:Alcobaca - Front.jpg|thumb|250px|Façade of the Alcobaça Monastery.]]
[[File:Alcobaca fountain hires.jpg|thumb|250px|Gothic fountain house and renaissance water basin in the cloister of the Alcobaça Monastery.]]
[[File:Alcobaça Praça da República.jpg|thumb|250px|Square in Alcobaça.]]

'''Alcobaça''' ({{IPA-pt|alkuˈβasɐ|-|Pt-pt Alcobaça FF.ogg}}) is a city and a municipality in [[Oeste Subregion]], region [[Centro Region, Portugal|Centro]] in Portugal, formerly included in the [[Estremadura Province (1936-1976)|Estremadura Province]]. The city grew along the valleys of the rivers Alcoa and Baça, from which it derives its name. The municipality population in 2011 was 56,693,&lt;ref name=ine&gt;[http://www.ine.pt/xportal/xmain?xlang=en&amp;xpid=INE&amp;xpgid=ine_indicadores&amp;indOcorrCod=0005889&amp;contexto=pi&amp;selTab=tab0 Instituto Nacional de Estatística]&lt;/ref&gt; in an area of 408.14&amp;nbsp;km².&lt;ref name=dgt&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.dgterritorio.pt/cartografia_e_geodesia/cartografia/carta_administrativa_oficial_de_portugal_caop_/caop__download_/carta_administrativa_oficial_de_portugal___versao_2017__em_vigor_/ |title=Áreas das freguesias, concelhos, distritos e país |access-date=2018-11-05 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181105172426/http://www.dgterritorio.pt/cartografia_e_geodesia/cartografia/carta_administrativa_oficial_de_portugal_caop_/caop__download_/carta_administrativa_oficial_de_portugal___versao_2017__em_vigor_/ |archive-date=2018-11-05 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; The city proper has a population of 15,800 inhabitants.&lt;ref&gt;[http://codigopostal.ciberforma.pt/cidades/cidade.asp?cid=6 Mail post reference of Portugal]&lt;/ref&gt;

The city of Alcobaça became notable after the [[List of Portuguese monarchs|first king]] of Portugal, [[Afonso Henriques]], decided to build a church to commemorate the [[Conquest of Santarém]] from the Moors in 1147. The church later evolved into the [[Monastery of Alcobaça]], one of the most magnificent [[gothic architecture|gothic]] monuments in the country. In the [[Church (building)|church]] are the tombs of [[Pedro I of Portugal]] and his murdered mistress [[Inês de Castro]]. Over the centuries this monastery played an important role in shaping [[Portuguese culture]].

A few kilometers to the north of Alcobaça is the [[Monastery of Batalha]], another gothic building constructed in memory of a different important battle, that of [[Battle of Aljubarrota|Aljubarrota]]. To the west of Alcobaça is the fishing village of [[Nazaré, Portugal|Nazaré]], now a popular resort town. To the south is the city of [[Caldas da Rainha]] and the medieval town of [[Óbidos, Portugal|Óbidos]]. Also to the northeast is the town of [[Porto de Mós]] with its rebuilt castle.

== History ==
A town that only became notable in the 12th century when it was chosen as the future site of Portugal's largest church. In March 1147, the fledgling King Dom [[Afonso Henriques]], defeated the Moors by capturing the city of [[Santarém, Portugal|Santarém]]. As a tribute to his victory he vowed to build a magnificent home for the [[Cistercian|Order of Cistercians]]. It took another 76 years before this task was completed. The [[monarchy]] continued to carry out further construction and 60 years later [[Dinis I of Portugal|King Dinis]] built the main cloister. The [[Monastery]] was consecrated in 1262.

The church contains the tombs of [[Pedro I of Portugal]] and his murdered mistress [[Inês de Castro]] and with it the story of the tragic liaison between Pedro and Inês. Forced at an early age as a royal duty, he was to marry Constanza, the ''[[Infanta]]'' (Princess) of [[Crown of Castile|Castile]], but died shortly after the marriage. Dom Pedro escape with his true love and later lived in the city of [[Coimbra]]. His father, [[Afonso IV of Portugal|King Afonso IV]], believing that the family of Inês was a threat to his own kingdom had her murdered. Shortly after the death of his father Dom Pedro declared that he had married Inês in a prior secret ceremony in [[Bragança, Portugal|Bragança]], and promptly took a gruesome revenge on the  killers and exhumed her body. He presented the embalmed corpse at the court with a crown on her head and demanded that all his courtiers kneel and individually pay homage to her decomposed hand. Today, their ornate tombs face each other so that on [[Judgment Day]] his first sight would be of his beloved Inês.

During the following centuries the monks from this monastery had a major influence on the development of Portuguese culture. Notably, in 1269 they were the first to give public lessons to their flock, and later they produced the first authoritative history on Portugal in a series of books. In 1810 the invading [[France|French]] pillaged the Abbey taking with them most of its most important treasures, including the noteworthy library. The items that remained were later stolen in 1834 during an anti-clerical riot and the banning of the religious Orders in Portugal.

==Parishes==
Administratively, the municipality is divided into 13 civil parishes (''[[freguesia (Portugal)|freguesias]]''):&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Law nr. 11-A/2013, page 552 7|url=http://dre.pt/pdf1sdip/2013/01/01901/0000200147.pdf |accessdate=16 July 2014|author=''[[Diário da República]]''|language=Portuguese|format=pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Vestiaria, Portugal|Alcobaça e Vestiaria]]
* [[Alfeizerão]]
* [[Aljubarrota]]
* [[Bárrio (Alcobaça)|Bárrio]]
* [[Benedita (Alcobaça)|Benedita]]
* [[Cela, Alcobaça|Cela]]
* [[Coz, Alpedriz e Montes]]
* [[Évora de Alcobaça]]
* [[Maiorga]]
* [[Pataias e Martingança]]
* [[São Martinho do Porto]]
* [[Turquel]]
* [[Vimeiro (Alcobaça)|Vimeiro]]

== City information==
The main feature of the city is essentially the monastery that proudly presents a long and sombre façade with 18th-century embellishments. This austerity is further emphasized in the cloisters with its apt name of &quot;Cloister of Silence&quot;. In contrast within the Abbey is the massive kitchen with a running stream specially diverted to pass through as a supply of fresh water. The open area of the kitchen chimney is large enough to take a whole ox for roasting. The surround to the sacristy doorway is an outstanding example of [[Manueline]] decoration. In 1794, [[William Thomas Beckford|Lord Beckford]] visited the Abbey and commented that he found some 300 monks &quot;living in a very splendid manner&quot;!

== Nearby locations ==
A few kilometers to the north of Alcobaça is another wondrous building constructed in memory of a different important battle, that of [[Battle of Aljubarrota|Aljubarrota]] in 1385, when King [[John I of Portugal]] defeated the Castilians and ensuring two hundred years of independence from the Castilian invaders. The construction of the Abbey at [[Batalha, Portugal|Batalha]] commenced in 1388 and was added to by various Portuguese Kings over these next two centuries. To the east of Batalha is the world-famous location of [[Fátima, Portugal|Fátima]] and a point of pilgrimage for the Roman Catholic religion due to the [[Our Lady of Fátima|vision of the Virgin Mary]] in 1917 by three young children whilst tending their flock. To the west of Alcobaça is the well-known fishing village of [[Nazaré, Portugal|Nazaré]]. Today, the village is now a small town and a popular holiday resort with most of its past and traditions having rapidly evaporated in the course of time. A very successful Portuguese feature film was made in the early 20th century that dramatically captured the primitive and dangerous life of these fishermen. Stoutly Catholic, the inhabitants have retained some of their past as can be still seen in their own particular style of costume. To the south is [[Caldas da Rainha]] and the quaint medieval town of [[Óbidos, Portugal|Óbidos]] that is an attraction for any tourists that enjoys a true glimpse of the past. Also to the south is the town of [[Porto de Mós]] with its fanciful rebuilt castle. This town borders the Nature Reserve [[Parque Natural das Serras de Aire e Candeeiros]]. These 390 square kilometres of limestone-covered landscape is also known for its caverns. The best known being the [[Gruta de Moinhos Velhos|Grutas de Mira de Aire]] can be visited and consists of tunnels, caverns with stalactites, stalagmites, lakes, and a music and light finale.

== Major events ==
* Market days – Every Monday
* [[Carnival|Carnaval]] de Alcobaça – February/March
* [[Cistermúsica]] – classical music festival – June / July&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cistermusica.com/&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Bernard of Clairvaux|Saint Bernard]]'s fair – August 20
* Municipal holiday – August 20
* ''Marionetas na Cidade'' – [[puppetry]] festival – mid-October&lt;ref&gt;http://www.samarionetas.com/#!marionetas-na-cidade/c1l7k&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Simon the Zealot|Saint Simon]]'s fair – 4th week of October
* International display of Sweets and Conventual Liqueurs – November

Notable people from Alcobaça include:
* [[Virgínia Vitorino]] - Poet
* [[Joaquim Vieira de Natividade]] - Engineer
* [[José Aurélio]] - Sculptor
* [[The Gift (band)|The Gift]] - alternative rock band, 1994–present
* [[Spartak!]] – music collective, 2006–2008
* [[Daniel Bernardes]] - Pianist

==International relations==
{{See also|List of twin towns and sister cities in Portugal}}

Alcobaça is [[Twin towns and sister cities|twinned]] with:
*{{flagicon|POL}} [[Bełchatów]], [[Poland]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Bełchatów twinnings&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.belchatow.pl/portal.php?aid=1158607934450ef43e80428|title=Portal Bełchatów|work=Miasto Bełchatów [Bełchatów town council] belchatow.pl|year=2010|accessdate=22 June 2011|language=Polish|trans-title=Bełchatów - Partnership Cities|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110613131345/http://www.belchatow.pl/portal.php?aid=1158607934450ef43e80428 |archivedate=13 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{flagicon|ANG}} [[Cacuaco]], [[Angola]]
*{{flagicon|FRA}} [[Aubergenville]], [[France]]
*{{flagicon|USA}} [[Chicopee, Massachusetts|Chicopee]], [[United States]]

==See also==
{{portal|Portugal}}
*[[Alcobaça IPR]]
*[[Alcobaça Monastery|Monastery of Alcobaça]]
*[[Monastery of Batalha]]
*[[Nazaré, Portugal|Nazaré]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Wikivoyage|Alcobaça}}
{{Commons category|Alcobaça (Portugal)}}
*[http://www.cm-alcobaca.pt/ Municipality official website]

{{Comunidade Intermunicipal do Oeste}}
{{Municipalities of Leiria}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Alcobaca}}
[[Category:Municipalities of Portugal]]
[[Category:Populated places in Leiria District]]
[[Category:Cities in Portugal]]
[[Category:Centro Region, Portugal|Centro Region]]
[[Category:Alcobaça, Portugal| ]]
[[Category:Municipalities of Leiria District]]</text>
      <sha1>57tdoo4oo6uhgkgajp1wsqsd4p9ytgc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
