  <page>
    <title>Durrani Empire</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3070</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941123776</id>
      <parentid>941122960</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-16T19:02:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Vif12vf</username>
        <id>20306027</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted to revision 940809389 by [[Special:Contributions/Vif12vf|Vif12vf]] ([[User talk:Vif12vf|talk]]) ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|the &quot;Durrani Empire&quot;|the Durrani dynasty|Durrani dynasty|people with the surname Durrani|Durrani (disambiguation)}}
{{more citations needed|date=September 2012}}
{{Infobox country
| native_name                = {{lang|ps|د درانیانو ټولواکمني}} ([[Pashto]])
| conventional_long_name                = Durrani Empire
| common_name                = Durrani Empire
| era                = [[Early modern period]]
| year_start                = October 1747
| year_end                = 1826
| p1                = Afsharid dynasty
| flag_p1                = Afsharid Imperial Standard (3 Stripes).svg
| border_p1                = no
| p2                = Mughal Empire
| flag_p2                = Alam of the Mughal Empire.svg
| border_p2                = no
| p3                = Maratha Empire
| flag_p3                = Flag of the Maratha Empire.svg
| border_p3                = no
| p4                = Khanate of Bukhara
| flag_p4                = War flag of Khanate of Bukhara.svg
| border_p4                = no
| s1                = Emirate of Afghanistan
| flag_s1                = Flag of Afghanistan (1919–1921).svg
| s2                = Sikh Empire
| flag_s2                = Nishan_Sahib.svg
| s3                = 
| flag_s3                = Flag of the Maratha Empire.svg
| border_s3                = no
| date_start                = 
| date_end                = 
| event_start                = 
| event_end                = 
| life_span                = 1747–1826
| image_coat                = 
| image_map                = Durrani_Empire_1747_1862_AD.png
| image_map_caption                = The Durrani Empire at its maximum extent under Ahmad Shah Durrani.&lt;ref&gt;Jonathan L. Lee &quot;Afghanistan: A History from 1260 to the Present&quot;, page 132 
&lt;/ref&gt;
| national_motto                = 
| national_anthem                = 
| capital                = [[Kandahar]] &lt;small&gt;(1747–1776)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br/&gt;[[Kabul]] &lt;small&gt;(1776–1823, 1839–1842)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br/&gt;[[Peshawar]] &lt;small&gt;(1776–1818; winter capital)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stanford&quot;&gt;Hanifi, Shah Mahmoud. ''&quot;Timur Shah transferred the Durrani capital from Qandahar in 1775-76. Kabul and Peshawar then shared time as the dual Durrani capital cities, the former during the summer and the latter during the winter season.&quot;'' p. 185. [https://books.google.com/books?id=kh1hpPLSpcEC ''Connecting Histories in Afghanistan: Market Relations and State Formation on a Colonial Frontier'']. [[Stanford University Press]], 2011. Retrieved 2012-08-04.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Singh&quot;&gt;Singh, Sarina (2008). ''&quot;Like the [[Kushan Empire|Kushans]], the Afghan kings favoured Peshawar as a winter residence, and were aggrieved when the upstart Sikh kingdom snatched it in 1818 and levelled its buildings.&quot;'' p. 191. [https://books.google.com/books?id=zn8I4qEew9oC ''Pakistan and the Karakoram Highway'']. Retrieved 2012-08-10.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br/&gt;[[Herat]] &lt;small&gt;(1818–1826)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=L. Lee |first=Jonathan |title=The Ancient Supremacy: Bukhara, Afghanistan and the Battle for Balkh, 1731-1901 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=nYaamE_3kD4C&amp;pg=PA116 |accessdate=March 8, 2013 |year=1996 |publisher=BRILL |edition=illustrated |isbn=9004103996 |page=116 |quote=[The Sadozai kingdom] continued to exist in Herat until the city finally fell to Dost Muhammad Khan in 1862.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| common_languages                = [[Pashto language|Pashto]] (official and court language),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Schimmel|first1=Annemarie|title=Pain and Grace: A Study of Two Mystical Writers of Eighteenth-Century Muslim India|date=1976|publisher=BRILL|isbn=978-9004047716|page=12}}&lt;/ref&gt;[[Persian language|Persian]]
| religion                = [[Islam]]
| government_type                = Monarchy
| title_leader                = [[List of monarchs of Afghanistan|Shah]]
| leader1                = [[Ahmad Shah Durrani]] &lt;small&gt;(first)&lt;/small&gt;
| year_leader1                = 1747–1772
| leader2                = [[Shuja Shah Durrani]] &lt;small&gt;(last)&lt;/small&gt;
| year_leader2                = 1839–1842
| stat_year1                = 
| stat_area1                = 
| stat_pop1                = 
| currency                = 
| demonym                = 
| area_km2                = 
| area_rank                = 
| GDP_PPP                = 
| GDP_PPP_year                = 
| HDI                = 
| HDI_year                = 
| today                = 
}}

The '''Durrani Empire''' ({{lang-ps|د دورانیانو امپراتوري}}), also called the '''Sadozai Kingdom''' ({{lang|ps|د افغانانو واکمني}}),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=nYaamE_3kD4C&amp;pg=PA116&amp;dq=sadozai+kingdom&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiMrduv577hAhXQEVAKHXV2ALsQ6AEIHTAA#v=onepage&amp;q=sadozai%20kingdom&amp;f=false|title=The &quot;Ancient Supremacy&quot;: Bukhara, Afghanistan and the Battle for Balkh, 1731-1901|last=Lee|first=Jonathan L.|date=1996-01-01|publisher=BRILL|isbn=9789004103993|language=en|page=116}}&lt;/ref&gt; and '''Afghan Empire''' ({{lang|ps|د افغانانو واکمني}}),&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/7798/Afghanistan/21392/Last-Afghan-empire |title=Last Afghan empire |accessdate=2010-08-25 |work=[[Louis Dupree (professor)|Louis Dupree]], [[Nancy Hatch Dupree]] and others |publisher=[[Encyclopædia Britannica]] |year=2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; was founded and built by [[Ahmad Shah Durrani]]. At its maximum extent, the empire ruled over what are now the modern-day countries of [[Afghanistan]] and [[Pakistan]], as well as some parts of northeastern [[Iran]], eastern [[Turkmenistan]], and northwestern [[India]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.khyber.org/books/pdf/ahmad-shah-baba.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2013-02-07 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130207183925/http://www.khyber.org/books/pdf/ahmad-shah-baba.pdf |archivedate=2013-02-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the death of [[Nader Shah]] in 1747, the region of [[Kandahar]] was claimed by Ahmad Shah Durrani. From there he began conquering [[Ghazni]] followed by [[Kabul]]. In 1749 the [[Mughal Empire|Mughal]] ruler had ceded sovereignty over much of north-west India to the Afghans. Ahmad Shah then set out westward to take possession of [[Herat]], which was ruled by [[Shahrokh Shah]]. He next sent an army to subdue the areas north of the [[Hindu Kush]] and in short order all the different tribes began joining his cause. Ahmad Shah and his forces invaded India four times, taking control of Kashmir and the [[Punjab region]]. Early in 1757, he sacked [[Delhi]], but permitted the Mughal dynasty to remain in nominal control as long as the ruler acknowledged Ahmad Shah's suzerainty over the Punjab, Sindh, and Kashmir.

After the death of Ahmad Shah in about 1772, his son [[Timur Shah Durrani|Timur Shah]] became the next ruler of the [[Durrani dynasty]] who decided to make [[Kabul]] the new [[capital (political)|capital]] of the empire, and used [[Peshawar]] as the winter capital. The Durrani Empire is considered the foundation of the modern [[Nation state|state]] of Afghanistan, with Ahmad Shah Durrani being credited as &quot;[[Father of the Nation]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/af.html |title=Afghanistan |accessdate=2010-08-25 |work=[[CIA]] |publisher=[[The World Factbook]] |date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reign of Ahmad Shah Durrani (1747–1772)==
{{Campaignbox
| title = [[Campaigns of Ahmad Shah Durrani]]
| name = Campaignbox
| listclass = hlist
| battles =
* [[Battle of Manupur (1748)]] 
* [[Battle of Lahore (1752)]]
* [[Battle of Sabzavar (1755)]]
* [[Durrani occupation of Delhi (1757)]]
* [[Battle of Gohalwar (1757)]]
* [[Battle of Lahore (1759)]]
* [[Battle of Barari Ghat (1760)]] 
* [[Second Battle of Sikandarabad (1760)]]
* [[Siege of Kunjpura (1760)]]
* [[Third Battle of Panipat]]
* [[Battle of Gujranwala (1761)]]
* [[Battle of Sialkot (1761)]]
* [[Battle of Kup (1762)]]
* [[Battle of Sialkot (1763)]]
}}

In 1709 [[Mir Wais Hotak]], chief of the [[Ghilji]] tribe of [[Kandahar Province]], gained independence from the [[Safavid dynasty|Safavid]] Persians. From 1722 to 1725, his son [[Mahmud Hotak]] briefly ruled large parts of [[Iran]] and declared himself as ''Shah of Persia''. However, the [[Hotak dynasty]] came to a complete end in 1738 after being toppled and banished by the [[Afsharid dynasty|Afsharids]] who were led by [[Nader Shah Afshar]] of [[Persia]].

The year 1747 marks the definitive appearance of an Afghan political entity independent of both the Persian and [[Mughal Empire|Mughal]] empires.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |url=http://iranicaonline.org/articles/afghanistan-x-political-history |title=Afghanistan x. Political History |encyclopedia=[[Encyclopædia Iranica]] |author=D. Balland |date=December 15, 1983|accessdate=2012-08-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; In October 1747 a [[loya jirga]] (grand council) concluded near the city of Kandahar with [[Ahmad Shah Durrani]] being selected as the new leader of the Afghans, thus the Durrani dynasty was founded. Despite being younger than the other contenders, Ahmad Shah had several overriding factors in his favor. He belonged to a respectable family of political background, especially since his father served as [[list of governors of Herat|Governor of Herat]] who died in a battle defending the Afghans.

===Early victories===
[[File:Kandahar City during 1839-42.jpg|thumb|City of [[Kandahar]], its principal bazaar and citadel, taken from the Nakkara Khauna]]

One of Ahmad Shah's first military actions was to capture [[Ghazni]] from the Ghiljis, and then wrest Kabul from the local ruler. In 1749, the Mughal ruler was induced to cede [[Sindh Province|Sindh]], the [[Punjab region]] and the important trans [[Indus River]] to Ahmad Shah in order to save his capital from Afghan attack.&lt;ref&gt;Meredith L. Runion [https://books.google.com/books?id=aZk9XzqCFGUC&amp;pg=PA69&amp;dq=ahmad+shah+durrani+1749+sindh+and+punjab&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=bQxIVcbHCovkUp_7gIgI&amp;ved=0CCAQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=ahmad%20shah%20durrani%201749%20sindh%20and%20punjab&amp;f=false ''The History of Afghanistan''] pp 69 Greenwood Publishing Group, 2007 {{ISBN|0313337985}}&lt;/ref&gt; Having thus gained substantial territories to the east without a fight, Ahmad Shah turned westward to take possession of [[Herat Province|Herat]], which was ruled by Nader Shah Afshar's grandson, [[Shahrukh Afshar]]. Ahmad Shah next sent an army to subdue the areas north of the [[Hindu Kush]] mountains. In short order, the powerful army brought under its control the [[Tajik people|Tajik]], [[Hazara people|Hazara]], [[Uzbeks|Uzbek]], [[Turkmen people|Turkmen]], and other tribes of northern Afghanistan. Ahmad Shah invaded the remnants of the Mughal Empire a third time, and then a fourth, consolidating control over the Kashmir and Punjab regions, with [[Lahore]] being governed by Afghans. He sacked Delhi in 1757 but permitted the Mughal dynasty to remain in nominal control of the city as long as the ruler acknowledged Ahmad Shah's suzerainty over Punjab, Sindh, and Kashmir. Leaving his second son [[Timur Shah Durrani|Timur Shah]] to safeguard his interests, Ahmad Shah left India to return to Afghanistan.

===Relations with China===
Alarmed by the expansion of China's [[Qing Dynasty]] up to the eastern border of Kazakhstan, Ahmad Shah attempted to rally neighboring Muslim khanates and the Kazakhs to unite and attack China, ostensibly to liberate its western Muslim subjects.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title= Holy war in China: the Muslim rebellion and state in Chinese Central Asia, 1864-1877 |last1=Kim |first1=Ho-dong |authorlink=|volume=|year=2004|publisher=Stanford University Press |location=|isbn=978-0-8047-4884-1 |page=20|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9kfJ6MlMsJQC|accessdate=2010-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ahmad Shah halted trade with Qing China and dispatched troops to [[Kokand]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Empire and the Khanate: a political history of Qing relations with Khoqand c. 1760-1860 |last1=Newby |first1=Laura J. |authorlink=|volume=|year=2005|publisher=BRILL |location=|isbn=978-90-04-14550-4 |page=34|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=KTmO416hNQ8C|accessdate=2010-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, with his campaigns in India exhausting the state treasury, and with his troops stretched thin throughout Central Asia, Ahmad Shah lacked sufficient resources to do anything except to send envoys to [[Beijing]] for unsuccessful talks.

===Third Battle of Panipat===
{{Main|Third Battle of Panipat}}
[[File:The Third battle of Panipat 13 January 1761.jpg|thumb|[[Ahmad Shah Durrani]] and his coalition decisively defeat the [[Maratha Confederacy]], during the [[Third Battle of Panipat]] and restored the [[Mughal Empire]] to [[Shah Alam II]].&lt;ref&gt;[[S. M. Ikram]] (1964). &quot;XIX. A Century of Political Decline: 1707–1803&quot;. In [[Ainslie Embree|Ainslie T. Embree]]. Muslim Civilization in India. New York: Columbia University Press. Retrieved 5 November 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The [[Mughal power]] in northern India had been declining after the death of Emperor [[Aurangzeb]], who died in 1707. In 1751-52, ''Ahamdiya'' treaty was signed between the [[Maratha Empire|Marathas]] and [[Mughals]], when [[Balaji Bajirao]] was the [[Peshwa]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Panipat&quot;&gt;Patil, Vishwas. ''Panipat''.&lt;/ref&gt; Through this treaty, the Marathas controlled virtually the whole of India from their capital at [[Pune]] and the Mughal rule was restricted only to Delhi (the Mughals remained the nominal heads of Delhi). Marathas were now straining to expand their area of control towards the Northwest of India. Ahmad Shah sacked the Mughal capital and withdrew with the booty he coveted. To counter the Afghans, Peshwa Balaji Bajirao sent [[Raghunathrao]]. He defeated the Rohillas and Afghan garrisons in Punjab and succeeded in ousting Timur Shah and his court from India and brought Lahore, Multan, Kashmir and other subahs on the Indian side of Attock under Maratha rule.&lt;ref name=K.RoyIHB&gt;{{cite book | last=Roy |first=Kaushik |title=India's Historic Battles: From Alexander the Great to Kargil |publisher=Permanent Black, India |pages=80–1 |isbn=978-81-7824-109-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, upon his return to Kandahar in 1757, Ahmad was forced to return to India and face the formidable attacks of the Maratha Confederacy.

Ahmad Shah declared a [[jihad]] (or [[Islam]]ic holy war) against the [[Maratha Empire|Marathas]], and warriors from various Afghan tribes joined his army, including the [[Baloch people]] under the command of [[Khan of Kalat]] Mir [[Nasir I of Kalat]]. Suba Khan Tanoli  (Zabardast Khan) was selected as army chief of all military forces. Early skirmishes were followed by victory for the Afghans against the much larger Maratha garrisons in Northwest India and by 1759 Ahmad Shah and his army had reached Lahore and were poised to confront the Marathas. Ahmad Shah Durrani was famous for winning wars much larger than his army. By 1760, the Maratha groups had coalesced into a big enough army under the command of Sadashivrao Bhau. Once again, [[Panipat]] was the scene of a confrontation between two warring contenders for control of northern India. The Third Battle of Panipat (14 January 1761), fought between largely Muslim and largely Hindu armies was waged along a twelve-kilometer front. Despite decisively defeating the Marathas, what might have been Ahmad Shah's peaceful control of his domains was disrupted by many challenges. As far as losses are concerned, Afghans too suffered heavily in the Third Battle of Panipat. This weakened his grasp over Punjab which fell to the rising [[Sikh]] [[misls]]. There were rebellions in the north in the region of [[Bukhara]]. The Durranis decisively defeated the Marathas in the [[Third Battle of Panipat]] on 14 January 1761.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jpXijlqeRpIC&amp;pg=PA84 |title=India's Historic Battles: From Alexander the Great to Kargil |author=Kaushik Roy |publisher=Orient Blackswan |year=2004 |pages=84–94}}&lt;/ref&gt; The defeat at Panipat resulted in heavy losses for the Marathas, and was a huge setback for Peshwa Balaji Rao. He received the news of the defeat of Panipat on 24 January 1761 at [[Bhilsa]], while leading a reinforcement force. Besides several important generals, he had lost his own son [[Vishwasrao]] in the Battle of Panipat. He died on 23 June 1761, and was succeeded by his younger son [[Madhavrao I|Madhav Rao I]].&lt;ref name=&quot;GSC_2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=G.S.Chhabra |title=Advance Study in the History of Modern India (Volume-1: 1707-1803) |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=UkDi6rVbckoC&amp;pg=PA19 |date=1 January 2005 |publisher=Lotus Press |isbn=978-81-89093-06-8 |pages=29–47 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Decline===
[[File:Bala_Hisar_Fort.jpg|thumb|The [[Bala Hissar, Peshawar|Bala Hissar]] fort in [[Peshawar]] was one of the royal residences of the Durrani kings.]]

The victory at Panipat was the high point of Ahmad Shah's—and Afghan—power. However, even prior to his death, the empire began to unravel. In 1762, Ahmad Shah crossed the passes from Afghanistan for the sixth time to subdue the [[Sikh Empire|Sikhs]]. From this time and on, the domination and control of the Empire began to loosen, and by the time of Durrani's death he had completely lost Punjab to the Sikhs, as well as earlier losses of northern territories to the Uzbeks, necessitating a compromise with them.&lt;ref&gt;Meredith L. Runion [https://books.google.com/books?id=aZk9XzqCFGUC&amp;pg=PA69&amp;dq=ahmad+shah+durrani+1749+sindh+and+punjab&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=bQxIVcbHCovkUp_7gIgI&amp;ved=0CCAQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=ahmad%20shah%20durrani%201749%20sindh%20and%20punjab&amp;f=false ''The History of Afghanistan''] pp 71 Greenwood Publishing Group, 2007 {{ISBN|0313337985}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He assaulted Lahore and, after taking their holy city of [[Amritsar]], massacred thousands of [[Sikh]] inhabitants, destroying their revered [[Harmandir Sahib|Golden Temple]].&lt;ref&gt;Purnima Dhavan, ''When Sparrows Became Hawks: The Making of the Sikh Warrior Tradition, 1699'', (Oxford University Press, 2011), 112.&lt;/ref&gt; Within two years, the Sikhs rebelled again and rebuilt their holy city of Amritsar. Ahmad Shah tried several more times to subjugate the Sikhs permanently, but failed. Durrani's forces instigated the [[Vaḍḍā Ghallūghārā]] when they killed thousands of Sikhs in the [[Punjab region|Punjab]] in 1762.&lt;ref&gt;^ Khushwant Singh, A History of the Sikhs, Volume I: 1469-1839, Delhi, Oxford University Press, 1978, pp. 144-45.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;^ According to the Punjabi-English Dictionary, eds. S.S. Joshi, Mukhtiar Singh Gill, (Patiala, India: Punjabi University Publication Bureau, 1994) the definitions of &quot;Ghalughara&quot; are as follows: &quot;holcaust, massacre, great destruction, deluge, genocide, slaughter, (historically) the great loss of life suffered by Sikhs at the hands of their rulers, particularly on 1 May 1746 and 5 February 1762&quot; (p. 293).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Syad Muhammad Latif, The History of Punjab from the Remotest Antiquity to the Present Time, New Delhi, Eurasia Publishing House (Pvt.) Ltd., 1964, p. 283; Khushwant Singh, A History of the Sikhs, Volume I: 1469-1839, Delhi, Oxford University Press, 1978, p. 154.&lt;/ref&gt; Ahmad Shah also faced other 
rebellions in the north, and eventually he and the Uzbek Emir of [[Emirate of Bukhara|Bukhara]] agreed that the Amu Darya would mark the division of their lands.. Ahmad Shah retired to his home in the mountains east of Kandahar, where he died on April 14, 1773.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Inside Afghanistan: end of the Taliban era? |last1=Reddy |first1=L. R |authorlink=|volume=|year=2002|publisher=APH Publishing |location=|isbn=978-81-7648-319-3 |page=65|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NubtDf2T3cAC|accessdate=2010-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; He had succeeded to a remarkable degree in balancing tribal alliances and hostilities, and in directing tribal energies away from rebellion. He earned recognition as Ahmad Shah Baba, or &quot;Father&quot; of Afghanistan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Singh&quot;/&gt;

==Other Durrani rulers (1772–1826)==
{{History of Afghanistan}}
[[Ahmed Shah Abdali|Ahmad Shah]]'s successors governed so ineptly during a period of profound unrest that within fifty years of his death, the Durrani empire ''per se'' was at an end, and Afghanistan was embroiled in civil war. Much of the territory conquered by Ahmad Shah fell to others in this half century. By 1818, the [[Sadozai (Pastun tribe)|Sadozai]] rulers who succeeded Ahmad Shah controlled little more than Kabul and the surrounding territory within a 160-kilometer radius. They not only lost the outlying territories but also alienated other tribes and lineages among the Durrani Pashtuns.

===Timur Shah (1772–1793)===
{{main|Timur Shah Durrani}}

Ahmad Shah was succeeded by his son, Timur Shah, who had been deputed to administer his father's conquests in Northern India, but had been driven out by the Marathas. Upon Ahmad Shah's death, the Durrani chieftains only reluctantly accepted Timur's accession. Most of his reign was spent fighting a civil war and resisting rebellion; Timur was even forced to move his capital from Kandahar to Kabul due to the insurgency. Timur Shah proved an ineffectual ruler, during whose reign the Durrani empire began to crumble. He is notable for having had 24 sons, several of whom became rulers of the Durrani territories. Timur died in 1793 and was then succeeded by his fifth son Zaman Shah

===Zaman Shah (1793–1801)===
{{Main|Zaman Shah Durrani}}
{{Pashtuns}}
[[File:The main street in the bazaar at Caubul.jpg|thumb|The main street in the bazaar at [[Kabul]]]]

After the death of Timur Shah, three of his sons, the governors of Kandahar, Herat and Kabul, contended for the succession. [[Zaman Shah]], governor of Kabul, held the field by virtue of being in control of the capital, and became shah at the age of twenty-three. Many of his half-brothers were imprisoned on their arrival in the capital for the purpose, ironically, of electing a new shah. The quarrels among Timur's descendants that threw Afghanistan into turmoil also provided the pretext for the interventions of outside forces.

The efforts of the Sadozai heirs of Timur to impose a true monarchy on the truculent Pashtun tribes, and their efforts to rule absolutely and without the advice of the other major Pashtun tribal leaders, were ultimately unsuccessful. The [[Sikhs]] started to rise under the command of Sikh chief, [[Ranjit Singh]], who succeeded in wresting power from Zaman's forces. Later when Zaman was blinded by his brother, Ranjit Singh who gave him asylum in Punjab.

Zaman's downfall was triggered by his attempts to consolidate power. Although it had been through the support of the Barakzai chief, Painda Khan Barakzai, that he had come to the throne, Zaman soon began to remove prominent Barakzai leaders from positions of power and replace them with men of his own lineage, the Sadozai. This upset the delicate balance of Durrani tribal politics that Ahmad Shah had established and may have prompted Painda Khan and other Durrani chiefs to plot against the shah. Painda Khan and the chiefs of the [[Nurzai]] and the [[Alizai tribe|Alizai]] Durrani clans were executed, as was the chief of the [[Qizilbash]] clan. Painda Khan's son fled to Iran and pledged the substantial support of his Barakzai followers to a rival claimant to the throne, Zaman's younger brother, [[Mahmud Shah Durrani|Mahmud Shah]]. The clans of the chiefs Zaman had executed joined forces with the rebels, and they took Kandahar without bloodshed.

===Mahmud Shah (first reign, 1801–1803)===
{{main|Mahmud Shah Durrani}}
Zeman Shah's overthrow in 1801 was not the end of civil strife in Afghanistan, but the beginning of even greater violence. Mahmud Shah's first reign lasted for only two years before he was replaced by [[Shuja Shah Durrani|Shuja Shah]].

===Shuja Shah (1803–1809 and 1839–1842)===
{{Main|Shuja Shah Durrani}}
Yet another of Timur Shah's sons, Shuja Shah (or Shah Shuja), ruled for only six years. On June 7, 1809, Shuja Shah signed a treaty with the [[British East India Company|British]], which included a clause stating that he would oppose the passage of foreign troops through his territories. This agreement, the first Afghan pact with a [[Europe]]an power, stipulated joint action in case of [[France|Franco]]-Persian aggression against Afghan or British dominions. Only a few weeks after signing the agreement, Shuja was deposed by his predecessor, Mahmud. Much later, he was reinstated by the British, ruling during 1839–1842. Two of his sons also ruled for a brief period in 1842.

===Mahmud Shah (second reign, 1809–1818)===
{{main|Mahmud Shah Durrani}}

Mahmud's second reign lasted nine years. Mahmud alienated the Barakzai, especially Fateh Khan, the son of Painda Khan, who was eventually seized and blinded. Revenge would later be sought and obtained by Fateh Khan's youngest brother, [[Dost Mohammad Khan]].

===Sultan Ali Shah (1818–1819)===
{{Main|Ali Shah Durrani}}
Ali Shah was another son of [[Timur Shah Durrani|Timur Shah]]. He seized power for a brief period in 1818–1819.

===Ayub Shah (1819–1823)===
{{Main|Ayub Shah Durrani}}
Ayub Shah was another son of Timur Shah, who deposed Sultan Ali Shah. He was himself later deposed, and presumably killed in 1823. The loss of Kashmir during his reign opened a new chapter in South Asian history.

== See also ==
* [[Indian Campaign of Ahmad Shah Durrani]]
* [[List of Pashtun empires and dynasties]]
* [[Deoni]]

==Notes==
&lt;!--&lt;nowiki&gt;
See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes for an explanation of how to generate footnotes using the &lt;ref&gt; and &lt;/ref&gt; tags.
&lt;/nowiki&gt;--&gt;
{{Reflist|20em}}

==References==
*Malleson, George Bruce (1879) ''History of Afghanistan, from the Earliest Period to the Outbreak of the War of 1878'' W.H. Allen &amp; Co., London, {{OCLC|4219393}}, limited view at [https://www.google.com/books?id=pqNGBEmHUd4C Google Books]
*Singh, Ganda (1959) ''Ahmad Shah Durrani: Father of Modern Afghanistan'' Asia Publishing House, London, {{OCLC|4341271}}
*Fraser-Tytler, William Kerr (1953) ''Afghanistan: A Study of Political Developments in Central and Southern Asia'' Oxford University Press, London, {{OCLC|409453}}
*Tanner, Stephen (2002) ''Afghanistan : a military history from Alexander the Great to the fall of the Taliban'' Da Capo Press, New York, {{ISBN|0-306-81164-2}}, also available from [http://www.netlibrary.com/ NetLibrary]
*Elphinstone, Mountstuart 1779-1859 ''An account of the kingdom of Caubul, and its dependencies in Persia, Tartary and India : comprising a view of the Afghaun nation and a history of the Dooraunee monarchy.''London : Printed for Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme, and Brown, 1815. Available in digital formats from the Internet Archive Digital Library [https://archive.org/details/anaccountkingdo00unkngoog] [https://archive.org/details/anaccountkingdo00elphgoog]

==External links==
{{commons category|Durrani Empire}}
*[http://www.bl.uk/reshelp/findhelpregion/asia/afghanistan/afghanistancollection/1747to1809/sources1747to1809.html Afghanistan 1747–1809: Sources in the India Office Records]
*[http://www.chiefacoins.com/Database/Countries/Afghanistan.htm#Durrani Some details and images of Durrani coins]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20100812115521/http://www.afghan-web.com/bios/yest/abdali.html Biography of Ahmad Shah Abdali (Durrani)]
*[http://www.afghanland.com/history/ahmadshah.html Ahmad Shah Baba]
*[http://www.khyber.org/pashtotribes/a/abdali.shtml History of Abdali tribe]
*[http://www.bijanomrani.com/?p=afgan_search_unit Afghanistan and the Search for Unity] Article on Durrani methods of government, published in ''Asian Affairs'', Volume 38, Issue 2, 2007, pp.&amp;nbsp;145–157.
*[http://rgssamachupicchu.blogspot.com.au/2013/05/afghanistan-british-raj-1.html Afghanistan &amp; the British Raj] From the [http://www.rgssa.org.au/ Royal Geographical Society of South Australia] blog entry with information on the Durrani Empire of Ahmad Shah, &quot;Pearl of the Pearls&quot;. From an extensive collection of 19th century British reference works on travel and exploration in Afghanistan.

{{Durrani dynasty}}
{{Pashtun}}
&lt;!--{{Islam in South Asia}}--&gt;
{{coord missing|Asia}}

[[Category:Durrani Empire| ]]
[[Category:Durrani dynasty|.]]
[[Category:Empires and kingdoms of Afghanistan]]
[[Category:Empires and kingdoms of Pakistan]]
[[Category:Former empires in Asia]]
[[Category:Muslim empires]]
[[Category:Islamic rule in the Indian subcontinent]]
[[Category:Modern history of Afghanistan]]
[[Category:History of Pakistan]]
[[Category:History of Khyber Pakhtunkhwa]]
[[Category:States and territories established in 1747]]
[[Category:States and territories disestablished in 1826]]
[[Category:1747 establishments in Asia]]
[[Category:1826 disestablishments in Asia]]
[[Category:18th century in Afghanistan]]
[[Category:19th century in Afghanistan]]
[[Category:18th century in the Mughal Empire]]</text>
      <sha1>kxy8mkgi2lxihrvoobzkef3qln614fn</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
