  <page>
    <title>Apollinarism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3037</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942598840</id>
      <parentid>942598633</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-25T17:37:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Materialscientist</username>
        <id>7852030</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/68.185.54.182|68.185.54.182]] identified as test/vandalism using [[WP:STiki|STiki]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Apollinarism''' or '''Apollinarianism''' is a [[Christological]] concept proposed by [[Apollinaris of Laodicea]] (died 390) that argues that [[Jesus]] had a normal human body but a [[divine]] mind instead of a regular human [[soul]]. It was deemed [[Christian heresy|heretical]] in 381 and virtually died out within the following decades.&lt;ref name=Sollier&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/01615b.htm  Sollier, Joseph. &quot;Apollinarianism.&quot; The Catholic Encyclopedia] Vol. 1. New York: Robert Appleton Company, 1907. 8 February 2019&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
The [[Trinity]] had been recognized at the Council of Nicea in 325, but debate about exactly what it meant continued. A rival to the more common belief that Jesus Christ had two natures was [[monophysitism]] (&quot;one nature&quot;), the doctrine that Christ had only one nature. Apollinarism and [[Eutychianism]] were two forms of monophysitism. Apollinaris' rejection that Christ had a human mind was considered an over-reaction to [[Arianism]] and its teaching that Christ was not divine.&lt;ref&gt;McGrath, Alister. 1998. ''Historical Theology, An Introduction to the History of Christian Thought.'' Oxford: Blackwell Publishers. Chapter 1.&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Theodoret]] charged Apollinaris with confounding the persons of the [[Godhead (Christianity)|Godhead]] and with giving in to the heretical ways of [[Sabellius]]. [[Basil of Caesarea]] accused him of abandoning the literal sense of the scripture, and taking up wholly with the allegorical sense. His views were condemned in a [[Synod]] at [[Alexandria]], under [[Athanasius of Alexandria]], in 362, and later subdivided into several different heresies, the main ones of which were the Polemians and the [[Antidicomarianite]]s.

Apollinaris, considering the rational soul or spirit as essentially liable to sin and capable, at its best, of only precarious efforts, saw no way of saving Christ's impeccability and the infinite value of Redemption, except by the elimination of the human spirit from Jesus' humanity, and the substitution of the Divine Logos in its stead. Apollinarism was declared to be a [[Christian heresy|heresy]] in 381 by the [[First Council of Constantinople]].&lt;ref name=Sollier/&gt;

Christian philosopher [[William Lane Craig]] has proposed a neo-Apollinarian Christology in which the divine Logos completes the human nature of Christ. Craig says his proposal is tentative and he welcomes critique and interaction from other scholars.&lt;ref&gt;William Lane Craig and J.P. Moreland. 2003. ''Philosophical Foundations for a Christian Worldview.'' InterVarsity Press. 608.&lt;/ref&gt;

Craig also clarifies his proposed neo-Apollinarian Christology with this statement.  &quot;Against Apollinarius, I want to say that Christ did have a '''complete human nature'''. He was truly God and truly man. Therefore his death on our behalf as our representative before God was efficacious.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;https://www.reasonablefaith.org/media/reasonable-faith-podcast/does-dr.-craig-have-an-orthodox-christology/&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}
{{catholic|title=Apollinarianism}}

==Sources==
*{{1728}}
*Artemi, E., «Mia physis of God Logos sesarkomeni» a)The analysis of this phrase according to  Cyril of Alexandria b)The analysis of this phrase according to Apollinaris of Laodicea»,Ecclesiastic Faros t. ΟΔ (2003), 293 – 304.
*[[Alister McGrath|McGrath, Alister]]. 1998. ''Historical Theology, An Introduction to the History of Christian Thought.'' Oxford: Blackwell Publishers. Chapter 1.
* {{Cite book|ref=harv|last=Edwards|first=Mark|year=2009|title=Catholicity and Heresy in the Early Church|publisher=Ashgate|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=z9acTl-jAkAC}}

{{Heresies condemned by the Catholic Church|state=collapsed}}
{{Subject bar |portal1= Catholicism |portal2= Christianity}}
[[Category:Christology]]
[[Category:4th-century Christianity]]
[[Category:Christian terminology]]
[[Category:Heresy in ancient Christianity]]</text>
      <sha1>j07ktfe85khxph7bdlsaw91qgr5anqd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
