  <page>
    <title>Adoptionism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3036</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939025102</id>
      <parentid>939023934</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-03T21:45:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Orphan Wiki</username>
        <id>11316070</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/76.191.116.130|76.191.116.130]] identified as test/vandalism using [[WP:STiki|STiki]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{distinguish|Adoption (theology)}}

[[File:Baptism-of-Christ-xx-Francesco-Alban.JPG|thumb|300px|[[Francesco Albani]]'s  ''The Baptism of Christ,''  when Jesus became one with God according to Adoptionism ]]

'''Adoptionism''', also called [[monarchianism|dynamic monarchianism]], is a [[Christianity|Christian]] [[nontrinitarian]] [[Christian theology|theological doctrine]] which holds that [[Jesus in Christianity|Jesus]] was adopted as the [[Son of God (Christianity)|Son of God]] at his [[Baptism of Jesus|baptism]], his [[resurrection of Jesus|resurrection]], or his [[ascension of Jesus|ascension]]. 

==Definition==
Adoptionism is one of two main forms of [[monarchianism]] (the other is [[modalism]], which regards &quot;Father&quot; and &quot;Son&quot; as two historical or [[soteriology|soteriological]] roles of a single divine Person). Adoptionism denies the eternal [[pre-existence of Christ]], and although it explicitly affirms his deity subsequent to events in his life, many classical [[Trinity|trinitarians]] claim that the doctrine implicitly denies it by denying the constant [[hypostatic union]] of the eternal [[Logos]] to the human nature of Jesus.&lt;ref&gt;Justo L. González, ''Essential Theological Terms'', page 139 (Westminster John Knox Press, 2005). {{ISBN|978-0-664-22810-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Under adoptionism Jesus is currently divine and has been since his adoption, although he is not equal to the Father, per &quot;my Father is greater than I&quot; ({{bibleverse||John|14:28}}).&lt;ref&gt;Ed Hindson, Ergun Caner (editors), ''The Popular Encyclopedia of Apologetics: Surveying the Evidence for the Truth of Christianity'', page 16 (Harvest House Publishers, 2008). {{ISBN|978-0-7369-2084-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; and as such is a kind of [[subordinationism]]. Adoptionism is sometimes, but not always, related to [[denial of the virgin birth of Jesus]].

== History ==

===Early Christianity===

====Adoptionism and High Christology====
{{See also|Early High Christology}}

The New Testament writings contain two different Christologies, namely a &quot;low&quot; or adoptionist Christology, and a &quot;high&quot; or &quot;incarnation Christology.&quot;{{sfn|Ehrman|2014|p=125}} The &quot;low Christology&quot; or &quot;adoptionist Christology&quot; is the belief &quot;that God exalted Jesus to be his Son by raising him from the dead,&quot;{{sfn|Ehrman|2014|p=120; 122}} thereby raising him to &quot;divine status.&quot;&lt;ref group=web name=BE_2013.02.14&gt;{{cite web|last1=Ehrman|first1=Bart D.|authorlink1=Bart D. Ehrman|title=Incarnation Christology, Angels, and Paul |url=https://ehrmanblog.org/incarnation-christology-angels-and-paul-for-members/|website=The Bart Ehrman Blog|accessdate=May 2, 2018|date=February 14, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The other early Christology is &quot;high Christology,&quot; which is &quot;the view that Jesus was a pre-existent divine being who became a human, did the Father’s will on earth, and then was taken back up into heaven whence he had originally come,&quot;&lt;ref group=web name=BE_2013.02.14/&gt;{{sfn|Ehrman|2014|p=122}} and from where he [[Christophany|appeared on earth]]. The chronology of the development of these early Christologies is a matter of debate within contemporary scholarship.{{sfn|Loke|2017}}{{sfn|Ehrman|2014}}{{sfn|Talbert|2011|p=3-6}}&lt;ref group=web name=&quot;Hurtado.2017&quot;&gt;Larry Hurtado, [https://larryhurtado.wordpress.com/2017/10/09/the-origin-of-divine-christology/ ''The Origin of “Divine Christology”?'']&lt;/ref&gt; 

According to the &quot;evolutionary model&quot;{{sfn|Netland|2001|p=175}} c.q. &quot;evolutionary theories,&quot;{{sfn|Loke|2017|p=3}} as proposed by Bousset, followed by Brown, the Christological understanding of Christ developed over time, from a low Christology to a high Christology,{{sfn|Mack|1995}}{{sfn|Ehrman|2003}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Ehrman_HJBG_CG&quot;&gt;Bart Ehrman, ''How Jesus became God'', Course Guide&lt;/ref&gt; as witnessed in the Gospels.{{sfn|Ehrman|2014}} According to the evolutionary model, the earliest Christians believed that Jesus was a human who was exalted, c.q. adopted as God's Son,{{sfn|Loke|2017|p=3-4}}{{sfn|Talbert|2011|p=3}}{{sfn|Brown|2008|p=unpaginated}} when he was resurrected,&lt;ref name=&quot;Ehrman_HJBG_CG&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Geza Vermez (2008), ''The Resurrection'', p.138-139&lt;/ref&gt; signaling the nearness of the [[Kingdom of God]], when all dead would be resurrected and the righteous exalted.{{sfn|Fredriksen|2008|p=unpaginated}} Adoptionist concepts can be found in the [[Gospel of Mark]],{{sfn|Ehrman|1996|p=48–49}}{{sfn|Boyarin|2012|p=56}}{{refn|group=note|Boyarin: &quot;[W]e can still observe within the Gospel (especially in Mark, which has no miraculous birth story, and also even in Paul) the remnants of a version of Christology in which Jesus was born a man but became God at his baptism. This idea, later named the heresy of adoptionism (God adopting Jesus as his Son), was not quite stamped out until the Middle Ages.{{sfn|Boyarin|2012|p=56}}}} in which the birth of Jesus and the epithet &quot;Son of God&quot; are absent in some early manuscripts, suggesting that the concept of the [[Virgin Birth of Jesus]] had not been developed or elucidated at the time Mark was written.{{sfn|Witherington|2006|p=7}} Later beliefs shifted the exaltation to his baptism, birth, and subsequently to the idea of his eternal existence, as witnessed in the Gospel of John.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ehrman_HJBG_CG&quot;/&gt; Mark shifted the moment of when Jesus became the son to the [[baptism of Jesus]], and later still Matthew and Luke shifted it to the moment of the [[Virgin birth of Jesus|divine conception]], and finally John declared that Jesus had been with God from the beginning: &quot;In the beginning was the Word&quot;.{{sfn|Brown|2008|p=unpaginated}}{{sfn|Ehrman|1996|p=74–75}}

Since the 1970s, the late datings for the development of a &quot;high Christology&quot; have been contested,{{sfn|Loke|2017|p=5}} and a majority of scholars argue that this &quot;High Christology&quot; existed already before the writings of Paul.{{sfn|Ehrman|2014|p=125}} This &quot;incarnation Christology&quot; or &quot;high Christology&quot; did not evolve over a longer time, but was a &quot;big bang&quot; of ideas which were already present at the start of Christianity, and took further shape in the first few decades of the church, as witnessed in the writings of Paul.{{sfn|Loke|2017|p=5}}&lt;ref group=web name=&quot;Bouma.2014&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Bouma|first=Jeremy|title=The Early High Christology Club and Bart Ehrman — An Excerpt from &quot;How God Became Jesus&quot;|url=https://zondervanacademic.com/blog/how-god-became-jesus-bart-ehrman-high-christology-excerpt/|website=Zondervan Academic Blog|publisher=[[HarperCollins]] Christian Publishing|accessdate=May 2, 2018|date=March 27, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=web name=BE_2013.02.14/&gt;&lt;ref group=web&gt;Larry Hurtado (July 10, 2015 ), [https://larryhurtado.wordpress.com/2015/07/10/early-high-christology-a-paradigm-shift-new-perspective/ ''&quot;Early High Christology&quot;: A &quot;Paradigm Shift&quot;? &quot;New Perspective&quot;?'']&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Ehrman, these two Christologies existed alongside each other, calling the &quot;low Christology&quot; an &quot;adoptionist Christology, and &quot;the &quot;high Christology&quot; an &quot;incarnation Christology.&quot;{{sfn|Ehrman|2014|p=125}}

====New Testamental epistles====
Adoptionist theology may also be reflected in canonical [[epistle]]s, the earliest of which pre-date the writing of the gospels. The letters of [[Paul the Apostle]], for example, do not mention a [[virgin birth of Christ]]. Paul describes Jesus as &quot;born of a woman, born under the [[Law of Moses|law]]&quot; and &quot;as to his [[human nature]] was a descendant of David&quot; in the [[Epistle to the Galatians]] and the [[Epistle to the Romans]]. Many interpreters, however, take his statements in [[Philippians 2]] to imply that Paul believed Jesus to have existed as equal to God before his [[Incarnation (Christianity)|incarnation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|last=Hurtado|first=L. W.|editor-last=Hawthorne|editor-first=Gerald F.|title=Pre-existence|encyclopedia=Dictionary of Paul and His Letters|pages=743–746|publisher=InterVarsity Press|location=Downers Grove, IL|date=1993}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The [[Book of Hebrews]], a contemporary sermon by an unknown author,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Dunn|first=James D. G.|authorlink=James Dunn (theologian)|title=Christology in the Making: A New Testament Inquiry Into the Origins of the Doctrine of the Incarnation|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=xArawykZRXUC&amp;pg=PA52|year=1996|publisher=Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing|isbn=978-0-8028-4257-2|page=52|quote=Hebrews describes Christ as God’s Son in language which seems to denote pre-existence more clearly than anything we have met so far [...] At the same time, there is more ‘adoptionist’ language in Hebrews than in any other NT document.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://www.cliffsnotes.com/literature/n/new-testament-of-the-bible/summary-and-analysis/the-letter-to-the-hebrews&lt;/ref&gt; describes God as saying &quot;You are my son; today I have begotten you.&quot; ({{bibleverse || Hebrews|1:5|nrsv}}) The latter phrase, a quote of {{bibleverse||Psalm|2:7|nrsv}}, could reflect an early Adoptionist view.

====Shepherd of Hermas====
The 2nd-century work [[Shepherd of Hermas]] may also have taught that Jesus was a virtuous man filled with the Holy Spirit and adopted as the Son.{{refn|group=note|&quot;The Holy Pre-existent Spirit. Which created the whole creation, God made to dwell in flesh that he desired. This flesh, therefore, in which the Holy Spirit dwelt, was subject unto the Spirit, walking honorably in holiness and purity, without in any way defiling the Spirit. When then it had lived honorably in chastity, and had labored with the Spirit, and had cooperated with it in everything, behaving itself boldly and bravely, he chose it as a partner with the Holy Spirit; for the career of this flesh pleased [the Lord], seeing that, as possessing the Holy Spirit, it was not defiled upon the earth. He therefore took the son as adviser and the glorious angels also, that this flesh too, having served the Spirit unblamably, might have some place of sojourn, and might not seem to have lost the reward for its service; for all flesh, which is found undefiled and unspotted, wherein the Holy Spirit dwelt, shall receive a reward.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.earlychristianwritings.com/text/shepherd-lightfoot.html ''The Shepherd of Hermas'']&lt;/ref&gt;}}&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Hermas never mentions Jesus Christ, or the Word, but only the Son of God, who is the highest angel. As holy spirit the Son dwells in the flesh; this human nature is God's adopted son&quot; in, Patrick W. Carey, Joseph T. Lienhard (editors), ''Biographical Dictionary of Christian Theologians'', page 241 (Greenwood Press, 2008). {{ISBN|0-313-29649-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Papandrea2016&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Papandrea|first=James L.|title=The Earliest Christologies: Five Images of Christ in the Postapostolic Age|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=x_akCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA29|date=24 April 2016|publisher=InterVarsity Press|isbn=978-0-8308-5127-0|page=29|quote=The most prominent example of Angel Adoptionism from the early Church would have to be the document known as ''The Shepherd'' of Hermass. In ''The Shepherd,'' the savior is an angel called the “angel of justification,” who seems to be identified with the archangel Michael. Although the angel is often understood to be Jesus, he is never named as Jesus.}}&lt;/ref&gt; While the Shepherd of Hermas was popular and sometimes bound with the canonical scriptures, it didn't retain canonical status, if it ever had it.

====Theodotus of Byzantium====
[[Theodotus of Byzantium]] (fl. late 2nd century), a [[Valentinianism|Valentinian]] [[Gnosticism|Gnostic]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Boukema&quot;/&gt; was the most prominent exponent of adoptionsim.&lt;ref&gt;CARM, [https://carm.org/adoptionism ''Adoptionism'']&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Hippolytus of Rome]] (''[[Philosophumena]]'', VII, xxiii) Theodotus taught that Jesus was a man born of a virgin, according to the Council of Jerusalem, that he lived like other men, and was most pious. At his baptism in the Jordan the &quot;Christ&quot; came down upon the man Jesus, in the likeness of a dove (''[[Philosophumena]]'', VII, xxiii), but Jesus was not himself [[God]] until after his [[resurrection]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Boukema&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Roukema|first=Riemer|title=Jesus, Gnosis and Dogma|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=AfcRBwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA53|date=18 February 2010|publisher=Bloomsbury Publishing|isbn=978-0-567-61585-5|page=53|chapter=Jesus′ Origin and Identity - Theodotus &amp;#91;of Byzantium&amp;#93;|quote=The Saviour, jesus Christ, who from the fullness (the ''pleroma'') of the Father descended on earth, is identified with the Logos, but initially not entirely with the Only Begotten Son. In john 1:14 is written, after all, that his glory was ''as'' of the Only Begotten, from which is concluded that his glory must be distinguished from this (7, 3b). When the Logos or Saviour descended, Sophia, according to Theodotus, provided a piece of flesh (''sarkion''), namely a carnal body, also called ‘spiritual seed’ (1, 1).}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Dirks|first=Jerald F.|editor=F. Kamal|title=Easily Understand Islam: Finally I Get It! : a Collection of Articles|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=C48FMQAACAAJ|year=2006|publisher=Desert Well Network LLC|isbn=978-1-59236-011-6|page=219f|chapter= Jesus: Man and God?|quote=[Per Jesus and Adoptionism] how does one understand the title “Son of God” when it is applied to Jesus? The answer is to be found in the Adoptionist movement within early Christianity. The Adoptionist trajectory in early Christianity begins with the baptism of Jesus by John the Baptist. According to the usual Adoptionist formulations, it was at his moment of baptism that Jesus moved into this special relationship or metaphorical “sonship” with God – not at his conception or virgin birth. [...] the oldest Greek manuscripts of and quotations from ''Luke'' render the key verse in question as follows. &quot;Now when all the people were baptized, and when Jesus also had been baptized and was praying, the heaven was opened, and the Holy Spirit descended upon him in bodily form like a dove. And a voice came from heaven, “You are my son; today I have begotten you” (''Luke'' 3:21-22).&quot; [...] the wording regarding the baptism of Jesus is also to be found in Hebrews 1:5a, Hebrews 5:5, and Acts 13:33. This same wording is also found in Psalms 2:7 in reference to David and in the apocryphal Gospel of the Ebionites in reference to Jesus’ baptism.}}{{Bulleted list|{{cite book|last=Steyn|first=Gert Jacobus|title=A Quest for the Assumed LXX Vorlage of the Explicit Quotations in Hebrews|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=QGk5oSoKJDYC&amp;pg=PA38|year=2011|publisher=Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht|isbn=978-3-525-53099-3|page=38|quote=Ps 2:7-8 is also quoted in 1 ''Clem'' 36:4 and in Just. ''Dial''. 122:6, whilst only verse seven of Ps 2 is found in the Ebionite Gospel (fr. 4) and in Just. ''Dial''. 88:8, 103:6. The quotation from Ps 2:7 that occurs in Heb 1:5 and 5:5 found its way into Hebrews via the early Jewish and early Christian traditions.}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Adoptionism was declared [[Heresy in Christianity|heresy]] at the end of the 2nd century and was rejected by the [[Synods of Antioch]] and the [[First Council of Nicaea]], which defined the [[Orthodoxy|orthodox doctrine]] of the [[Trinity]] and identified the man Jesus with the eternally begotten Son or [[Logos (Christianity)|Word of God]] in the [[Nicene Creed]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Harnack|first=Adolf Von|title=History of Dogma|year=1889|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/harnack/dogma1.II.III.III.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=iAvGNlIWg9IC&amp;pg=PA23&amp;dq=adoptionism+heresy&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=VlRfU8KgM6LjsASg74D4BA&amp;ved=0CEkQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=adoptionism%20heresy&amp;f=false |title= The Popular Encyclopedia of Church History: The People, Places, and Events That Shaped Christianity |authors= Edward E. Hindson, Daniel R. Mitchell | page=23|publisher= Harvest House Publishers|year= 2013 |accessdate=29 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The belief was also declared heretical by [[Pope Victor I]].

====Ebionites====
{{Main|Ebionites}}

Adoptionism was also adhered to by the [[Jewish Christians]] known as [[Ebionites]], who, according to [[Epiphanius of Salamis|Epiphanius]] in the 4th century, believed that Jesus was chosen on account of his [[sinless]] devotion to the [[will of God]].&lt;ref&gt;Epiphanius of Salamis (403 CE). pp. 30:3 &amp; 30:13.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Ebionites were a [[Jewish Christian]] movement that existed during the early centuries of the Christian Era.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | editor1-last = Cross | editor1-first = EA | title = The Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church | publisher = Oxford University Press | year = 1989 | contribution = Ebionites | editor2-last = Livingston | editor2-first = FL}}&lt;/ref&gt; They show strong similarities with the earliest form of Jewish Christianity, and their specific theology may have been a &quot;reaction to the [[Paul and Judaism|law-free Gentile mission]].&quot;{{sfn|Dunn|2006|p=282}} They regarded Jesus as the Messiah while rejecting his [[divinity]] and his [[Virgin birth of Jesus|virgin birth]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia | url = http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/177608/Ebionites | encyclopedia = Encyclopædia Britannica | title = Ebionites}}&lt;/ref&gt; and insisted on the necessity of following [[Halakha|Jewish law and rites]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | first = Kaufmann | last = Kohler | chapter-url = http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=22&amp;letter=E | contribution = Ebionites | editor1-first = Isidore | editor1-last = Singer | editor2-first = Cyrus | editor2-last = Alder | title = Jewish Encyclopedia | year = 1901{{ndash}}1906}}&lt;/ref&gt; They used the [[Gospel of the Ebionites]], one of the [[Jewish–Christian gospels]]; the Hebrew Book of Matthew starting at chapter 3; revered [[James, brother of Jesus|James the brother of Jesus]] (James the Just); and rejected [[Paul the Apostle]] as an [[Antinomianism#Supporting Pauline passages|apostate from the Law]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Maccoby 1987&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| author = [[Hyam Maccoby]]| title = The Mythmaker: Paul and the Invention of Christianity| pages = 172–183.| publisher = HarperCollins | year = 1987 | isbn = 0-06-250585-8}}, [http://ebionite.tripod.com/mac15.htm an abridgement]&lt;/ref&gt; Their name ({{lang-grc-gre|Ἐβιωναῖοι}} ''Ebionaioi'', derived from [[Hebrew]] {{Hebrew|אביונים}} ''ebyonim'', ''ebionim'', meaning &quot;the poor&quot; or &quot;poor ones&quot;) suggests that they placed a special value on [[Vow of poverty|voluntary poverty]].

Distinctive features of the ''Gospel of the Ebionites'' include the absence of the [[virgin birth of Jesus|virgin birth]] and of the [[genealogy of Jesus]]; an [[Adoptionist]] [[Christology]],{{refn|group=note|{{harvnb|Kloppenborg|1994|pp=435–9}}; p.&amp;nbsp;435&amp;nbsp;– &quot;This belief, known as &quot;adoptionism&quot;, held that Jesus was not divine by nature or by birth, but that God chose him to become his son, i.e., adopted him.&quot;}} in which Jesus is chosen to be [[Son of God|God's Son]] at the time of his [[Baptism of Jesus|Baptism]]; the abolition of the [[Korban|Jewish sacrifices]] by Jesus; and an advocacy of [[vegetarianism]].{{refn|group=note|{{harvnb|Vielhauer|Strecker|1991|pp=166–71}}; p.&amp;nbsp;168&amp;nbsp;– &quot;Jesus' task is to do away with the 'sacrifices'. In this saying (16.4–5), the hostility of the Ebionites against the Temple cult is documented.&quot;}}

=== Spanish Adoptionism ===
{{main|Spanish Adoptionism}}
Spanish Adoptionism was a theological position which was articulated in [[Caliphate of Córdoba|Umayyad]] and [[Kingdom of Asturias|Christian]]-held regions of the [[Iberian peninsula]] in the 8th and 9th centuries. The issue seems to have begun with the claim of archbishop [[Elipandus of Toledo]] that – in respect to his human nature – Christ was ''adoptive'' [[Son of God]]. Another leading advocate of this Christology was [[Felix of Urgel]]. In Spain, adoptionism was opposed by [[Beatus of Liebana]], and in the [[Carolingian]] territories, the Adoptionist position was condemned by [[Pope Hadrian I]], [[Alcuin of York]], [[Agobard]], and officially in Carolingian territory by the Council of Frankfurt (794).

Despite the shared name of &quot;adoptionism&quot; the Spanish Adoptionist Christology appears to have differed sharply from the adoptionism of early Christianity. Spanish advocates predicated the term ''adoptivus'' of Christ only in respect to his humanity; once the divine Son &quot;emptied himself&quot; of divinity and &quot;took the form of a servant&quot; (Philippians 2:7), Christ's human nature was &quot;adopted&quot; as divine.&lt;ref&gt;James Ginther, ''Westminster Handbook to Medieval Theology'', (Louisville, KY: Westminster John Knox Press, 2009), 3.&lt;/ref&gt;

Historically, many scholars have followed the Adoptionists' Carolingian opponents in labeling Spanish Adoptionism as a minor revival of “[[Nestorianism|Nestorian]]” Christology.&lt;ref&gt;For an example of this characterization, see Adolph Harnack, ‘’History of Dogma’’, vol. 5, trans. Neil Buchanan, (New York: Dover, 1961), 280.&lt;/ref&gt; John C. Cavadini has challenged this notion by attempting to take the Spanish Christology in its own Spanish/North African context in his study, ''The Last Christology of the West: Adoptionism in Spain and Gaul, 785–820''.&lt;ref&gt;John C. Cavadini, ‘’The Last Christology of the West: Adoptionism in Spain and Gaul, 785–820’’, (Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1993), 4–5.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Scholastic Neo-adoptionism ===
A third wave was the revived form (&quot;Neo-adoptionism&quot;) of [[Peter Abelard]] in the 12th century. Later, various modified and qualified Adoptionist tenets emerged from some theologians in the 14th century. [[Duns Scotus]] (1300) and [[Durandus of Saint-Pourçain]] (1320) admit the term ''Filius adoptivus'' in a qualified sense. In more recent times the Jesuit [[Gabriel Vásquez]], and the Lutheran divines [[Georgius Calixtus]] and [[Johann Ernst Immanuel Walch]], have defended adoptionism as essentially orthodox.

=== Modern adoptionist groups ===
A form of adoptionism surfaced in [[Unitarianism]] during the 18th century as [[denial of the virgin birth of Jesus|denial of the virgin birth]] became increasingly common, led by the views of [[Joseph Priestley]] and others. 

A similar form of adoptionism was expressed in the writings of [[James Strang]], a [[Latter Day Saint movement|Latter Day Saint]] leader who founded the [[Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints (Strangite)]] after the [[death of Joseph Smith]] in 1844.  In his [[Book of the Law of the Lord]], a purported work of ancient scripture found and translated by Strang, he offers an essay entitled &quot;Note on the Sacrifice of Christ&quot; in which he explains his unique (for Mormonism as a whole) doctrines on the subject.  Jesus Christ, said Strang, was the natural-born son of [[Mary (mother of Jesus)|Mary]] and [[Saint Joseph|Joseph]], who was chosen from before all time to be the Savior of mankind, but who had to be born as an ordinary mortal of two human parents (rather than being begotten by the Father or the [[Holy Spirit]]) to be able to truly fulfill his Messianic role.&lt;ref&gt;Book of the Law, pp. 157-58, note 9.&lt;/ref&gt;  Strang claimed that the earthly Christ was in essence &quot;adopted&quot; as God's son at birth, and fully revealed as such during the [[Transfiguration of Jesus|Transfiguration]].&lt;ref&gt;Book of the Law, pp. 165-66.&lt;/ref&gt;  After proving himself to God by living a perfectly sinless life, he was enabled to provide an acceptable sacrifice for the sins of men, prior to his [[Resurrection appearances of Jesus|resurrection]] and [[Ascension of Jesus Christ|ascension]].&lt;ref&gt;Book of the law, pp. 155-58.&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Adoptivi]]
* [[Arianism]]
* [[Binitarianism]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist|group=note|2}}

==References==
{{reflist|35em}}

== Sources ==
;Printed sources
{{refbegin}}
&lt;!-- B --&gt;
* {{Citation | last =Boyarin | first =Daniel | year =2012 | authorlink =Daniel Boyarin | title =The Jewish Gospels | publisher =New Press | isbn =978-1-59558-711-4 | url =https://books.google.com/books?id=Rd48nOco0-wC&amp;pg=PT56}}
* {{Citation | last =Brown | first = R.E. | year =1973 | title =The Virginal Conception and Bodily Resurrection of Jesus | publisher =Paulist Press | url =https://books.google.com/books?id=a0Ik5DuD01cC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}
&lt;!-- D --&gt;
* {{Citation | last =Dunn | first =James D.G. | year =2006 | title =Unity and Diversity in the New Testament | edition =3rd | publisher =scm press}}
&lt;!-- E --&gt;
* {{Citation | last =Ehrman | first =Bart | year =1996 | title =The Orthodox Corruption of the Scripture | publisher =Oxford University Press | location =New York}}
* {{Citation | last =Ehrman | first =Bart D. | year =2003| authorlink=Bart D. Ehrman | title =Lost Christianities: The Battles for Scripture and the Faiths We Never Knew | publisher=Oxford University Press | isbn =978-0-19-972712-4|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vDzRCwAAQBAJ}}
* {{Citation | last =Ehrman | first =Bart | year =2014 | title =How Jesus Became God. The Exaltation of a Jewish Preacher from Galilea | publisher =Harperone}}
&lt;!-- L --&gt;
* {{Citation | last =Loke | first =Andrew Ter Ern | year =2017 | title =The Origin of Divine Christology | volume =169 | publisher =Cambridge University Press | isbn =978-1-108-19142-5 | url =https://books.google.com/books?id=Et0qDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA5}}
&lt;!-- M --&gt;
* {{Citation | last =Mack | first =Burton L. | year =1995 | orig-year =1995 | title =Who Wrote the New Testament? The Making of the Christian Myth}}
* {{Citation | last =Mack | first =Burton L. | year =1997 | orig-year =1995 | title =Wie schreven het Nieuwe Testament werkelijk? Feiten, mythen en motieven. (Who Wrote the New Testament? The Making of the Christian Myth) | publisher =Uitgeverij Ankh-Hermes bv}}
&lt;!-- S --&gt;
* [[Philip Schaff]] ''History of the Christian Church'', Volume IV, 1882
&lt;!-- T --&gt;
* {{Citation | last =Talbert | first =Charles H. | year =2011 | title =The Development of Christology during the First Hundred Years: and Other Essays on Early Christian Christology. Supplements to Novum Testamentum 140. | publisher =BRILL}}
&lt;!-- E --&gt;
* {{Citation | last =Witherington | first =Ben | year =2006 | title =What Have They Done With Jesus? | publisher =Harper Collins | location =San Francisco}}
{{refend}}

;Web-sources
{{reflist|group=web}}

== External links ==
{{EB1911 poster|Adoptianism}}
* [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/01150a.htm Adoptionism] in ''Catholic Encyclopedia''
* [http://www.lcms.org/ca/www/cyclopedia/02/display.asp?t1=a&amp;word=ADOPTIONISM Adoptionism] in ''Christian Cyclopedia''
* [http://www.ccel.org/s/schaff/history/4_ch11.htm Chapter XI. Doctrinal Controversies], from [[Philip Schaff]]'s History of the Christian Church

{{Heresies condemned by the Catholic Church}}
[[Category:Nontrinitarianism]]
[[Category:Christian terminology]]
[[Category:Christology]]
[[Category:Heresy in ancient Christianity]]</text>
      <sha1>5ro01tex0el13rc0o2u2pkclaxxyso7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
