  <page>
    <title>Autumn</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3049</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943371394</id>
      <parentid>943367848</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T14:33:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Needforsuv</username>
        <id>14394651</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>fix spaceing</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{redirect|Fall||Fall (disambiguation)}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{EngvarB|date=April 2017}}
{{multiple image|perrow=2|total_width=272
| image1 = New_hampshire_in_autumn.jpg
| image4 = Cincinnati – Spring Grove Cemetery &amp; Arboretum &quot;Autumn Reflection&quot; (15630100199).jpg
| image3 = Paris raining autumn cityscape (8252181936).jpg
| image2 = Autumn_colors_along_the_road.jpg
| image5 = Tuolumne_Meadows_with_Meandering_River_in_Autumn.jpg
| image6 = Victoria Avenue - Canterbury.jpg
}}
{{Weather}}
'''Autumn''', also known as '''fall''' in [[North American English]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.lexico.com/en/definition/fall |title =Oxford Dictionary on the North American usage of Fall |website=oxforddictionaries.com }}&lt;/ref&gt; is one of the four [[temperate]] [[season]]s. Autumn marks the transition from [[summer]] to [[winter]], in September ([[Northern Hemisphere]]) or March ([[Southern Hemisphere]]), when the duration of [[daylight]] becomes noticeably shorter and the temperature cools considerably. One of its main features in [[temperate climates]] is the [[leaf#Seasonal leaf loss|shedding of leaves]] from [[deciduous trees]].

Some cultures regard the autumnal [[equinox]] as &quot;mid-autumn&quot;, while others with a longer [[Seasonal lag|temperature lag]] treat it as the start of autumn.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.crh.noaa.gov/glossary.php?word=autumn |title=NOAA's National Weather Service - Glossary |publisher=Crh.noaa.gov |accessdate=2010-08-06 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120111152359/http://www.crh.noaa.gov/glossary.php?word=autumn |archive-date=2012-01-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Meteorologists (and most of the [[temperate countries]] in the southern hemisphere)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tourism.net.nz/new-zealand/about-new-zealand/weather-and-climate.html |title=New Zealand Weather and Climate, New Zealand Weather, Temperatures and Climate in New Zealand |publisher=Tourism.net.nz |accessdate=2010-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; use a definition based on Gregorian calendar months, with autumn being September, October, and November in the northern hemisphere,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/weather/features/understanding/autumn_forecasting.shtml |title=Weather Centre - Features - Understanding Weather - Autumn Forecasting |publisher=BBC |accessdate=2010-08-06| archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100904052411/http://www.bbc.co.uk/weather/features/understanding/autumn_forecasting.shtml| archivedate= 4 September 2010 |url-status = live}}&lt;/ref&gt; and March, April, and May in the southern hemisphere. Persians celebrate the beginning of the autumn as Mehregan to honor Mithra (Mehr). 

In [[North America]], autumn traditionally starts with the [[September equinox]] (21 to 24 September)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2010/09/22/first-day-of-fall-2010-au_n_734692.html |title=First Day Of Fall 2010: Autumn Equinox Photos |work=The Huffington Post |date= 22 September 2010|accessdate=2010-09-22 |first=Craig |last=Kanalley| archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100924195451/http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2010/09/22/first-day-of-fall-2010-au_n_734692.html| archivedate= 24 September 2010 |url-status = live}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ends with the [[winter solstice]] (21 or 22 December).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.almanac.com/content/first-day-winter-winter-solstice|title=The First Day of Winter: Winter Solstice 2018|website=Old Farmer's Almanac}}&lt;/ref&gt; Popular culture in the United States associates [[Labor Day]], the first Monday in September, as the end of summer and the start of autumn; certain summer traditions, such as wearing white, are discouraged after that date.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=https://time.com/5658699/white-after-labor-day/ |title=Why We Can't Wear White After Labor Day |author=Laura FitzPatrick |date=September 8, 2009 |work=Time |accessdate=February 25, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; As daytime and nighttime temperatures decrease, trees [[autumn leaf color|change color]] and then shed their leaves.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = https://www.telegraph.co.uk/travel/destinations/northamerica/8050370/Fall-in-North-America-autumn-colour-in-New-England-and-beyond.html|title = Travel|date = 11 October 2010|accessdate = 15 October 2015|website = Fall in North America: autumn colour in New England and beyond|last = Arnold|first = Kathy}}&lt;/ref&gt; In traditional East Asian [[solar term]], autumn starts on or around 8 August and ends on or about 7 November. In [[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]], the autumn months according to the national meteorological service, [[Met Éireann]], are September, October and November.&lt;ref name=&quot;met.ie&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.met.ie/climate/monthly_summarys/autumn07.pdf |title=The Weather of Autumn 2007 (September, October &amp; November summary) |format=PDF |work=Met Éireann - The Irish Meteorological Service Online |date=3 December 2007 |accessdate=10 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, according to the [[Irish Calendar]], which is based on ancient [[Gaelic Ireland|Gaelic]] traditions, autumn lasts throughout the months of August, September and October, or possibly a few days later, depending on tradition. In the [[Irish language]], September is known as ''Meán Fómhair'' (&quot;middle of autumn&quot;) and October as ''Deireadh Fómhair'' (&quot;end of autumn&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.dailyedge.ie/summer-its-literally-not-what-it-used-to-be-164328-Jun2011/|title=Summer, it's literally not what it used to be|first=Hugh|last=O'Connell|website=The Daily Edge}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://everestlanguageschool.com/autumn-in-ireland/|title=Autumn in Ireland - Everest Language School|date=10 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[southern hemisphere]] countries such as [[Australia]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bom.gov.au/climate/glossary/seasons.shtml|title=Climate Glossary - Seasons|website=www.bom.gov.au}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[New Zealand]], which tend to base their seasonal calendars meteorologically rather than astronomically,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://media.bom.gov.au/social/blog/1762/solstices-and-equinoxes-the-reasons-for-the-seasons/ |title=Solstices and equinoxes: the reasons for the seasons |work=[[Bureau of Meteorology]] |date=21 June 2018 |accessdate=16 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; autumn officially begins on 1 March and ends on 31 May.

==Etymology==
[[File:Dülmen, Wildpark -- 2014 -- 3808 color balanced.jpg|thumb|200px|Autumnal scene with yellow, orange and red leaves on trees and fallen on the ground]]
The word ''autumn'' {{IPAc-en|ˈ|ɔː|t|ə|m}} is derived from Latin ''autumnus'', archaic ''auctumnus'', possibly from the ancient [[Etruscan language|Etruscan]] root ''autu-'' and has within it connotations of the passing of the year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Breyer|first=Gertraud|title=Etruskisches Sprachgut im Lateinischen unter Ausschluss des spezifisch onomastischen Bereiches|year=1993|publisher=Peeters Publishers|isbn=9068313355|pages=412–413|language=German}}&lt;/ref&gt; Alternative etymologies include [[Proto-Indo-European language|Proto-Indo-European]] *''h₃ewǵ''- (“cold”) or *''h₂sows''- (“dry”).&lt;ref&gt;Tucker, T.G., Etymological Dictionary of Latin, Ares Publishers, 1976 (reprint of 1931 edition).&lt;/ref&gt;

After the Roman era, the word continued to be used as the [[Old French]] word ''{{lang|fro|autompne}}'' (''{{lang|fr|automne}}'' in [[modern French]]) or ''{{lang|enm|autumpne}}'' in Middle English,&lt;ref&gt;Oxford English Dictionary, 2nd Edition, entry at ''automn''.&lt;/ref&gt; and was later normalised to the original Latin. In the [[Medieval]] period, there are rare examples of its use as early as the 12th century, but by the 16th century, it was in common use.

Before the 16th century, ''[[harvest]]'' was the term usually used to refer to the season, as it is common in other [[West Germanic languages]] to this day ([[cf.]] Dutch ''{{lang|nl|herfst}}'', German ''{{lang|de|Herbst}}'' and Scots ''{{lang|sco|hairst}}''). However, as more people gradually moved from working the land to living in towns, the word ''harvest'' lost its reference to the time of year and came to refer only to the actual activity of reaping, and ''autumn'', as well as ''fall'', began to replace it as a reference to the season.&lt;ref&gt;{{OEtymD|harvest}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{OEtymD|autumn}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The alternative word ''fall'' for the season traces its origins to old [[Germanic languages]]. The exact derivation is unclear, with the [[Old English language|Old English]] ''{{lang|ang|fiæll}}'' or ''{{lang|ang|feallan}}'' and the [[Old Norse language|Old Norse]] ''{{lang|non|fall}}'' all being possible candidates. However, these words all have the meaning &quot;to fall from a height&quot; and are clearly derived either from a common root or from each other. The term came to denote the season in [[16th-century England]], a contraction of [[Middle English]] expressions like &quot;[[Abscission|fall of the leaf]]&quot; and &quot;fall of the year&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{OEtymD|fall}}&lt;/ref&gt; Compare the origin of ''[[spring (season)|spring]]'' from &quot;spring of the leaf&quot; and &quot;spring of the year&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{OEtymD|spring}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 17th century, [[British colonization of the Americas|English emigration to the British colonies]] in North America was at its peak, and the new settlers took the English language with them. While the term ''fall'' gradually became nearly obsolete in Britain, it became the more common term in North America.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Is It 'Autumn' or 'Fall'? |url=https://www.merriam-webster.com/words-at-play/autumn-vs-fall |website=Merriam Webster |accessdate=23 September 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The name ''backend'', a once common name for the season in [[Northern England]], has today been largely replaced by the name ''autumn''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Revealed: How London accents have killed off local dialects across England|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/technology/2016/05/26/revealed-how-london-accents-have-killed-off-local-dialects-acros/|accessdate=27 May 2016|work=The Telegraph}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Associations==

===Harvest===
[[File:Harvest Straw Bales in Schleswig-Holstein.jpg|thumb|200px|left|[[Harvest]] straw bales in a field of [[Schleswig-Holstein]], [[Germany]]]]
Association with the transition from warm to cold weather, and its related status as the season of the primary [[harvest]], has dominated its themes and popular images. In Western cultures, personifications of autumn are usually pretty, well-fed females adorned with fruits, vegetables and grains that ripen at this time. Many cultures feature autumnal [[harvest festival]]s, often the most important on their calendars. Still extant echoes of these celebrations are found in the autumn [[Thanksgiving]] holiday of the United States and Canada, and the Jewish [[Sukkot]] holiday with its roots as a full-moon harvest festival of &quot;tabernacles&quot; (living in outdoor huts around the time of harvest). There are also the many North American Indian festivals tied to harvest of ripe foods gathered in the wild, the Chinese Mid-Autumn or [[Moon festival]], and many others. The predominant mood of these autumnal celebrations is a gladness for the fruits of the earth mixed with a certain melancholy linked to the imminent arrival of harsh weather.

This view is presented in English poet [[John Keats]]' poem ''[[To Autumn]]'', where he describes the season as a time of bounteous fecundity, a time of 'mellow fruitfulness'.

In North America, while most foods are harvested during the autumn, foods particularly associated with the season include [[pumpkin]]s (which are integral parts of both Thanksgiving and [[Halloween]]) and [[apple]]s, which are used to make the seasonal beverage [[apple cider]].

===Melancholia===
Autumn, especially in poetry, has often been associated with [[melancholia]]. The possibilities and opportunities of summer are gone, and the chill of winter is on the horizon. Skies turn grey, the amount of usable daylight drops rapidly, and many people turn inward, both physically and mentally.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.symbolism.org/writing/books/sp/4/page2.html Cyclical Regenerative Time - (c) Autumn] (from 'Symbolism of Place', symbolism.org website)&lt;/ref&gt; It has been referred to as an unhealthy season.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/text-idx?c=did;cc=did;rgn=main;view=text;idno=did2222.0002.576|title = Autumn|year = 2013|accessdate = 31 March 2015|website = The Encyclopedia of Diderot &amp; d'Alembert Collaborative Translation Project|publisher = Michigan Publishing|last = D'Alembert|first = Jean Le Rond|editor-last = Holtrop|editor-first = Ellen|orig-year = 1751}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Similar examples may be found in Irish poet [[William Butler Yeats]]' poem ''[[The Wild Swans at Coole (poem)|The Wild Swans at Coole]]'' where the maturing season that the poet observes symbolically represents his own ageing self. Like the natural world that he observes, he too has reached his prime and now must look forward to the inevitability of old age and death. French poet [[Paul Verlaine]]'s &quot;''[[Chanson d'automne]]''&quot; (&quot;Autumn Song&quot;) is likewise characterised by strong, painful feelings of sorrow. [[John Keats|Keats]]' ''[[To Autumn]]'', written in September 1819, echoes this sense of melancholic reflection, but also emphasises the lush abundance of the season. The song &quot;[[Autumn Leaves (1945 song)|Autumn Leaves]]&quot;, based on the French song &quot;Les Feuilles mortes&quot;, uses the melancholic atmosphere of the season and the end of summer as a metaphor for the mood of being separated from a loved one.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blogs.kcrw.com/music/2017/09/the-original-autumn-leaves/|accessdate=8 September 2018|title=The Original &quot;Autumn Leaves&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Halloween===
[[File:Pumpkins-2009.jpg|left|thumb|[[Halloween]] [[pumpkin]]s]]
[[File:Halloween pumpkins.jpg|thumb|Halloween pumpkins]]
Autumn is associated with [[Halloween]] (influenced by [[Samhain]], a Celtic autumn festival),&lt;ref name=&quot;ENC&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761572079/Halloween.html |title=Halloween |work=[[Microsoft Encarta|Encarta]] |publisher=Microsoft |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091028170821/http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761572079/Halloween.html |archivedate=28 October 2009 |url-status=dead |df=dmy |access-date=20 June 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and with it a widespread marketing campaign that promotes it. Halloween, October 31,  is in autumn in the northern hemisphere. The television, film, book, costume, home decoration, and confectionery industries use this time of year to promote products closely associated with such a holiday, with promotions going from late August or early September to 31 October, since their themes rapidly lose strength once the holiday ends, and advertising starts concentrating on Christmas.

===Other associations===
[[File:Pumpkin-Pie-Whole-Slice.jpg|thumb|right|[[Pumpkin pie]] is commonly served on and around [[Thanksgiving]] in North America]]
[[File:01259 All Saints Day Sanok, 2011.jpg|thumb|left|[[All Saints' Day]] at a cemetery in [[Sanok]] – flowers and lit candles are placed to honor the memory of deceased relatives. Poland, 1 November 2011]]
In some parts of the northern hemisphere, autumn has a strong association with the end of [[summer vacation|summer holiday]] and the [[first day of school|start of a new school year]], particularly for children in primary and secondary education. &quot;[[Back to school (marketing)|Back to School]]&quot; advertising and preparations usually occurs in the weeks leading to the beginning of autumn.

[[Easter]] falls in autumn in the southern hemisphere.

[[Thanksgiving Day]] is a national holiday celebrated in Canada, in the United States, in some of the [[Caribbean|Caribbean islands]] and in [[Liberia]]. Thanksgiving is celebrated on the [[Thanksgiving (Canada)|second Monday of October]] in Canada and on the [[Thanksgiving (United States)|fourth Thursday of November]] in the United States, and around the same part of the year in other places. Similarly named festival holidays occur in [[Germany]] and [[Japan]].

Television stations and networks, particularly in North America, traditionally begin their regular seasons in their autumn, with new series and new episodes of existing series debuting mostly during late September or early October (series that debut outside the fall season are usually known as [[mid-season replacement]]s). A sweeps period takes place in November to measure [[Nielsen Ratings]].

[[American football]] is played almost exclusively in the autumn months; at the [[high school football|high school level]], seasons run from late August through early November, with some playoff games and [[American football on Thanksgiving|holiday rivalry contests]] being played as late as Thanksgiving.  In many American states, the championship games take place in early December. [[College football]]'s regular season runs from September through November, while the main [[professional football (gridiron)|professional]] circuit, the [[National Football League]], plays from September through to early January. Summer sports, such as [[stock car racing]], [[Canadian football]], [[Major League Soccer]], and [[Major League Baseball]], wrap up their seasons in early to late autumn; MLB's championship [[World Series]] is known popularly as the &quot;Fall Classic&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/fallclassicdefin0000ende|url-access=registration|title=The Fall Classic: The Definitive History of the World Series|first=Eric|last= Enders|publisher=Sterling Publishing Company|year=2007|isbn=9781402747700}}, ''et al.''&lt;/ref&gt; (Amateur baseball is usually finished by August.) Likewise, professional winter sports, such as [[ice hockey]], [[basketball]], and most leagues of [[association football]] in Europe, are in the early stages of their seasons during autumn; American [[college basketball]] and [[college ice hockey]] play teams outside their [[athletic conference]]s during the late autumn before their in-conference schedules begin in winter.

The [[Christianity|Christian]] religious holidays of [[All Saints' Day]] and [[All Souls' Day]] are observed in autumn in the Northern hemisphere.

Since 1997, [[Autumn (given name)|Autumn]] has been one of the top 100 names for girls in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ssa.gov/OACT/babynames/ Popular Baby Names], Social Security Online.&lt;/ref&gt;

In Indian mythology, autumn is considered to be the preferred season for the goddess of learning [[Saraswati]], who is also known by the name of &quot;goddess of autumn&quot; (Sharada).

In Asian mysticism, Autumn is associated with the [[Wu Xing|element]] of [[Metal (Wu Xing)|metal]], and subsequently with the colour [[white]], the [[Bai Hu|White Tiger of the West]], and death and mourning.

==Tourism==
[[File:Maple Trees by Creek.jpg|thumb|Maple leaves changing colour by a creek.]]
{{See also|Leaf peeping}}Although [[Autumn leaf color|colour change in leaves]] occurs wherever [[deciduous]] trees are found, coloured autumn [[foliage]] is noted in various regions of the world: most of [[North America]], [[Eastern Asia]] (including China, [[Korea]], and Japan), [[Europe]], the forest of [[Patagonia]], eastern [[Australia]] and [[New Zealand]]'s [[South Island]].

Eastern [[Canada]] and [[New England]] are famous for their autumnal foliage,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gov.ns.ca/news/details.asp?id=19990921001 |title=Nova Scotia Capitalizes on Fall Tourism &amp;#124; Government of Nova Scotia |publisher=Gov.ns.ca |date=21 September 1999 |accessdate=2010-03-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/travel/news-and-advice/the-complete-guide-to-leafpeeping-612904.html |title=The Complete Guide to Leaf-Peeping  &amp; Advice, Travel |work=The Independent |date=14 September 2002 |accessdate=2010-03-06 | location=London | first=Ben | last=Ross}}&lt;/ref&gt; and this attracts major tourism (worth billions of US dollars) for the regions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Shir Haberman |url=http://www.seacoastonline.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20071009/NEWS/710090335 |title=Leaf peepers storm N.H., Maine |publisher=SeacoastOnline.com |accessdate=2010-03-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=10000103&amp;sid=a3vkUrgIabaA&amp;refer=us |title=Record New England Rains Make Foliage `a Dud,' Hurt Tourism |publisher=Bloomberg L.P. |date=4 November 2005 |accessdate=2010-03-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Allegories of autumn in art==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Allegory_of_Autumn_-_sala_di_Prometeo.jpg|''Autumn'', by [[Giuseppe Collignon]]
File:Autumn_Legros_Louvre_MR1981.jpg|''Autumn'', by [[Pierre Le Gros the Elder]]
File:Giuseppe Arcimboldo - Autumn, 1573.jpg|''Autumn'' (1573), by [[Giuseppe Arcimboldo]]
File:Alfons_Mucha_-_1896_-_Autumn.jpg|''Autumn'' (1896), by [[Art Nouveau]] artist [[Alphonse Mucha]]
File:Autumn_LCCN90708855.jpg|''Autumn'' (1871), by Currier &amp; Ives
File:Maxfield_Parrish_-_Autumn_(1905).jpg|This 1905 print by [[Maxfield Frederick Parrish]] illustrated [[John Keats]]' poem ''Autumn''
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Autumn in New England]]
* [[Diwali]]

==References==
:{{Cyclopaedia 1728|title=|volume}}
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Wiktionary|autumn|fall}}
* {{commons-inline}}
* {{Britannica|45215|Autumn}}
{{Authority control}}
{{Seasons}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2014}}
{{Subject bar|commons=y}}

[[Category:Etymologies]]
[[Category:Autumn| ]]</text>
      <sha1>75ub8tjafx9zfugt4bum05876pflent</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
