  <page>
    <title>Amathus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1687</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943136276</id>
      <parentid>896791786</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T02:05:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelink 1 book for [[Wikipedia:Verifiability|verifiability]]. [goog]) #IABot (v2.0) ([[User:GreenC bot|GreenC bot]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{distinguish|Amathus, Transjordan}}
{{for|the town of ancient Laconia, Greece|Amathus (Laconia)}}
{{Expand German|Amathous (Zypern)|date=May 2017}}
{{Infobox ancient site
  |name = Amathus, Amathous
  |native_name = [[wikt:Ἀμαθοῦς|Ἀμαθοῦς]]
  |alternate_name = 
  |image = Limestone sarcophagus- the Amathus sarcophagus MET DT257.jpg
  |alt = 
  |caption = 5th century BC [[Amathus sarcophagus]] found in Amathus integrates Greek, Cypriot, and Oriental features
  |map_type = Cyprus
  |map_alt = 
  |map_size = 250
  |location = [[Cyprus]]
  |region = [[Limassol District]]
  |coordinates = {{coord|34|42|45|N|33|08|30|E|type:city_region:CY|display=inline,title}}
  |type = 
  |part_of = 
  |length = 
  |width = 
  |area = 
  |height = 
  |builder = 
  |material = 
  |built = 
  |abandoned = 
  |epochs = 
  |cultures = 
  |dependency_of = 
  |occupants = 
  |event = 
  |excavations = 
  |archaeologists = 
  |condition = 
  |ownership = 
  |management = 
  |public_access = 
  |website = 
  |notes = 
}}

'''Amathus''' or '''Amathous''' ({{lang-grc|[[wikt:Ἀμαθοῦς|Ἀμαθοῦς]]}}) was an ancient city and one of the ancient royal cities of [[Cyprus]] until about 300 BC. Some of its impressive remains can be seen today on the southern coast in front of [[Agios Tychonas]], about {{convert|24|mi|km}} west of [[Larnaca]] and {{convert|6|mi|km}} east of [[Limassol]]. Its ancient cult sanctuary of [[Aphrodite]] was the second most important in Cyprus, her homeland, after [[Paphos]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Walter Burkert]], ''Greek Religion'' 1985, p. 153; John Karageorghis, ''La grande déesse de Chypre et son culte'', 1977.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;OCD&quot;&gt;{{Cite book  | last = Catling | first = Hector William  | contribution = Amathus  | year = 1996  | title = [[Oxford Classical Dictionary]]  | editor1-last = Hornblower  | editor1-first = Simon  | editor1-link =Simon Hornblower  | editor2-last = Spawforth  | editor2-first = Anthony  | editor2-link =Anthony Spawforth  | edition = 3rd  | place = Oxford  | publisher = [[Oxford University Press]]  | isbn = 0-19-521693-8  | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Archaeological work has recently been continued at the site and many finds are exhibited in the Limassol Museum.

==History==
===Pre-history and ancient era===
[[File:Ancient kingdoms of Cyprus en.svg|thumb|Ancient kingdoms of Cyprus]]
The pre-history of Amathus mixes myth and [[archaeology]].&lt;ref&gt;T. Petit, &quot;Eteocypriot myth and Amathousian reality,&quot; ''JMA'' '''12''' (1999:108-20)&lt;/ref&gt; Archaeology has detected human activity from the earliest [[Iron Age]], {{circa|1100}} BC.&lt;ref name=&quot;OCD&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Amathus during the First Iron Age|journal=Bulletin of the American Schools of Oriental Research|date=November 1997|first=Pierre|last=Aupert|volume=308|issue=308|pages=19–25|id= |format=|doi=10.2307/1357406|jstor=1357406 }}; M. Iacovou, &quot;Amathous, an early Iron Age polity in Cyprus: the chronology of its foundation&quot;, ''Report of the Department of Antiquities of Cyprus'' (2002) pp 101-22.&lt;/ref&gt; 
The city's legendary founder was [[Cinyras]], linked with the birth of [[Adonis]], who called the city after his mother Amathous. According to a version of the [[Ariadne]] legend noted by [[Plutarch]],&lt;ref&gt;Plutarch, ''[[Biography|vita]]'' of Theseus (20.3-.5), citing the lost text of an obscure Amathusan mythographer, [[Paeon of Amathus|Paeon]].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Theseus]] abandoned Ariadne at Amathousa, where she died giving birth to her child and was buried in a sacred tomb. According to Plutarch's source, Amathousians called the [[sacred grove]] where her shrine was situated the Wood of Aphrodite Ariadne. More purely Hellenic myth would have Amathus settled instead by one of the sons of [[Heracles]], thus accounting for the fact that he was worshiped there.
 
It was said in antiquity that the people of Amathus were [[Autochthon (ancient Greece)|autochthonous]], or &quot;[[Pelasgian]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;OCD&quot;/&gt; Their non-Greek language is confirmed on the site by [[Eteocypriot]] inscriptions in the [[Cypriot syllabary]] which alone in the Aegean world survived the [[Bronze Age collapse]] and continued to be used down to the 4th century BC.
 
Amathus was built on the coastal cliffs with a natural harbour and flourished at an early date, soon requiring several cemeteries. Greeks from [[Euboea]] left their pottery at Amathus from the 10th century BC. During the post-Phoenician era of the 8th century BC, a [[palace]] was erected and a port was also constructed, which served the trade with the [[Greeks]] and the [[Levant]]ines. A special burial ground for infants, a ''[[tophet]]''&lt;ref&gt;Agelarakis A., Kanta A., and N. Ch. Stampolidis, “The Osseous Record in the Western Necropolis of Amathous: an Archaeo-Anthropological Investigation”,  Eastern Mediterranean, Cyprus-Dodecanese-Crete 16th-6th c. B.C., Proceedings of the International Symposium: The Eastern Mediterranean, Cyprus-Dodecanese-Crete 16th-6th c. B.C., Rethymnon, Crete, 1998: 217-232&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Agelarakis A., “The Amathous (tophet) cremations in Cyprus”, In D. Christou on “Human Cremations at the Western Necropolis of Amathous”  &lt;Cremations in Bronze and Early Iron Age&gt;, Proceedings of Int. Symposium.  Ministries of the Aegean and of Culture,  Greece, 2001:  201-204&lt;/ref&gt; served the culture of the [[Phoenicia]]ns. For the Hellenes, high on the cliff a temple was built, which became a worship site devoted to [[Aphrodite]], in her particular local presence as ''[[Amathusia|Aphrodite Amathusia]]'' along with a bearded male Aphrodite called ''[[Aphroditos]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Macrobius, ''Saturnalia'' III, 8. Hesychius ''s.v'' Ἀφρόδιτος. Catullus 68, 51, calling the Amathusian Aphrodite ''duplex'', confirms the attribution to Amathus.&lt;/ref&gt; The excavators discovered the final stage of the Temple of Aphrodite, also known as [[Aphrodisias]], which dates approximately to the 1st century BC. According to the legend, it was where festive [[Adonia]] took place, in which athletes competed in hunting wild boars during sport competitions; they also competed in dancing and singing, all to the honour of Adonis.
[[File:Poisson polychrome terre cuite chypre amathonte Louvre AM 976.jpg|thumb|Fish, polychromic terracotta, 5th century BCE, found in Amathus]]
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Apollo Amathus.jpg|thumb|portrait|left|Apollo Temple at Amathus-[[Limassol]]]] --&gt;
The earliest remains hitherto found on the site are tombs of the early [[Iron Age]] period of Graeco-[[Phoenicia]]n influences (1000-600 BC). Amathus is identified&lt;ref&gt;For example by E. Oberhummer, ''Die Insel Cypern'', i., 1902, pp. 13-14.&lt;/ref&gt; with ''Kartihadasti'' (Phoenician &quot;New-Town&quot;) in the Cypriote tribute-list of [[Esarhaddon]] of [[Assyria]] (668 BC).&lt;ref&gt;But see [[Citium]].&lt;/ref&gt;  It certainly maintained strong [[Phoenicia]]n sympathies, for it was its refusal to join the philhellene league of [[Onesilus|Onesilos]] of [[Salamis, Cyprus|Salamis]] which provoked the revolt of Cyprus from [[Achaemenid Empire|Achaemenid Persia]] in 500-494 BC,&lt;ref&gt;[[Herodotus]], v. 105&lt;/ref&gt; when Amathus was besieged unsuccessfully and avenged itself by the capture and execution of Onesilos.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;&gt;{{EB1911|inline=y|wstitle=Amathus|volume=1|page=783|first=John Linton|last=Myres|authorlink=John Myres}}&lt;/ref&gt; Herodotus reports
:&quot;Because he had besieged them, the Amathusians cut off Onesilos’ head and brought it to Amathous, where they hung it above the gates. As it hung there empty, a swarm of bees entered it and filled it with honeycomb.&lt;ref&gt;The [[mytheme]] of bees in the carcase, familiar from the legend of [[Samson]] ( Judges 14:8, a lion's carcase) and the Greek myth of [[Aristaeus]] (a bullock carcase), and in [[Virgil]]'s ''[[Georgics]]'', is examined by Othniel Margalith, &quot;Samson's Riddle and Samson's Magic Locks&quot; ''[[Vetus Testamentum]]'', '''36'''.2 (1986:.&lt;/ref&gt; When they sought advice about this event, an oracle told them to take the head down and bury it, and to make annual sacrifice to Onesilos as a hero, saying that it would be better for them if they did this. The Amathusians did as they were told and still perform these rites in my day.&quot; (''Histories'' 5.114)

Amathus was a rich and densely populated kingdom with a flourishing agriculture (grain&lt;ref&gt;[[Strabo]] 340, quoting the mid-6th century writer [[Hipponax]].&lt;/ref&gt; and sheep) and copper mines situated very close to the northeast [[Tenta, Cyprus|Kalavasos]].&lt;ref&gt;See [[Ovid]], ''Metamorphoses'' x. 220, 227. 531.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;G. Mariti, i. 187; L. Ross, ''Inselreise,'' iv. 195; W. H. Engel, ''Kypros,'' i. 111 ff.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hellenistic Era===
About 385-380 BC, the philhellene [[Evagoras I|Evagoras]] of Salamis was similarly opposed by Amathus, allied with [[Citium]] and [[Soli, Cyprus|Soli]];&lt;ref&gt;[[Diodorus Siculus]] xiv. 98.&lt;/ref&gt; and even after [[Alexander the Great|Alexander]] the city resisted annexation, and was bound over to give hostages to [[Seleucus I Nicator|Seleucus]].&lt;ref&gt;Diodorus Siculus xix. 62.&lt;/ref&gt; Its political importance was now ended but its temple of [[Adonis]] and [[Amathusia|Aphrodite Amathusia]] remained famous in [[Roman Empire|Roman times]]. The epithet ''Amathusia'' in Roman poetry often means little more than &quot;Cypriote,&quot; but attesting to the fame of the city.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

From the 4th century BC the pedestals of two sculptures donated by the last Basileus of Amathous, Androkles, representing his two sons, Orestheus and Andragoras, have survived. Their inscriptions are in both Eteozypric and Greek languages.

The decline of Amathous is often measured by the Ptolemaic gifts to [[Argos]], where Amathous donated only 40 drachmas in 170-160 BC, but Kition and Salamis gave 208, Kourion 172, and Paphos 100. However, this figure contradicts the archaeologic evidence of new buildings in this period including a balneion, a bath, a gymnasium, as well as fortifications of the Acropolis, including a new tower. However, the port of Paphos lost traffic compared to Amathous in the Ptolemaic period, an indication that Paphos as the capital of the island perhaps offered fewer drachmas than the other cities for different reasons, like Amathous.&lt;ref&gt;Giorgos Papantoniou: Religion and Social Transformations in Cyprus. From the Cypriot Basileis to the Hellenistic Strategos, Brill, 2012, S. 221.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Roman Era===

In the Roman era Amathus became the capital of one of the four administrative regions of Cyprus.

A Roman temple was built in the 1st century AD on top of the Hellenistic predecessor. The temple facilities remained so important in Roman times that 'Amathusia' was used as a synonym for 'Cypriot'.

===Late Antiquity and the Middle Ages===
Later, in the 4th century AD, Amasus became the see of a Christian bishop and continued to flourish until the [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine]] period. Of its bishops, Heliodorus was at the [[Council of Chalcedon]] in 451 and Alexander at the [[Second Council of Nicaea]] in 787. In the late 6th century, Saint Ioannis Eleimonas (John the Charitable), protector of the [[Knights of St. John]], was born in Amathus and after 614 sent Theodorus, bishop of Amathus, to Jerusalem to ransom some slaves.&lt;ref&gt;Michel Lequien, [https://archive.org/details/bub_gb_86weAemI-e4C ''Oriens christianus in quatuor Patriarchatus digestus''], Paris 1740, Vol. II, coll. 1063-1066&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Siméon Vailhé, v. ''1. Amathus'', in [http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k6561037d/f515.image ''Dictionnaire d'Histoire et de Géographie ecclésiastiques''], vol. II, Paris 1914, coll. 982-983&lt;/ref&gt;

Today, Amathus is a see of the [[Church of Cyprus]] and is also listed (under the name &quot;Amathus in Cypro&quot;, to distinguish it from &quot;[[Amathus, Transjordan|Amathus in Transjordan]]&quot;) as a [[titular see]] by the Catholic Church, which however, in line with the practice adopted after the [[Second Vatican Council]], has made no appointments to the bishopric since the death of the last [[Latin Church|Latin]] [[titular bishop]] in 1984.&lt;ref&gt;''Annuario Pontificio 2013'' (Libreria Editrice Vaticana 2013 {{ISBN|978-88-209-9070-1}}), p. 830&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Anastasius Sinaita]], the famous 7th-century prolific monk of [[Saint Catherine's Monastery]], was born here. It is thought that he left Cyprus after the 649 Arab conquest of the island, setting out for the Holy Land, and eventually becoming a monk on Sinai.&lt;ref&gt;A. Binggeli, 'Anastasius of Sinai' in D. Thomas (ed.) et al., Christian-Muslim Relations. A Bibliographical History. Volume 1 (600-900). Brill 2009, pp. 193-202; K.H. Uthemann, 'Anastasius the Sinaite' in A. Di Berardino, Patrology: the Eastern fathers from the Council of Chalcedon (451) to John of Damascus (+750). Cambridge 2006, 313-331&lt;/ref&gt;

Amathus declined and was already almost deserted when [[Richard I of England|Richard Plantagenet]] won Cyprus by a victory there over [[Isaac Comnenus of Cyprus|Isaac Comnenus]] in 1191.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; The tombs were plundered and the stones from the beautiful edifices were brought to [[Limassol]] to be used for new constructions. Much later, in 1869, a great number of blocks of stone from Amathus were used for the construction of the [[Suez Canal]]. A ruined [[Byzantian Empire|Byzantine]] church marks its site.

===In modern times===
A new settlement close to Amathus but further inland, Agios Tychonas, is named after the bishop Saint [[Tychon of Amathus]]. The site of the ruins is within the borders of this village, though the expansion of the Limassol tourist area has threatened the ruins: it is speculated that some of the hotels are on top of the Amathus necropolis.

==The Site and Archaeology==

The city had vanished, except for fragments of wall and of a great stone urn on the acropolis,&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; dating from the 6th century BC of which a similar vessel was taken to the [[Musée du Louvre]] in 1867. It is {{convert|1.85|m|0|abbr=on}} tall and weighs 14 tons. It was made from a single piece of stone and has four curved handles carved with bulls. In the 1870s, [[Luigi Palma di Cesnola]] excavated the [[necropolis]] of Amathus, as elsewhere in Cyprus, enriching the early collections of the [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]]; some objects went to the [[British Museum]]. More modern archaeological joint Cypriote-French excavations started in 1980 and still continue. The Acropolis, the Temple of Aphrodite, the agora, the city's walls, the [[basilica]] and the port have all been excavated.

Further archaeological objects found during the excavations are preserved at both the Cyprus Museum in Nicosia and the Limassol District Archaeological Museum.
 
In the agora there are marble columns decorated with spirals and a huge paved squares. On the coastal side of the city there is an Early Christian basilica with mosaic floors decorated with semi-precious stones. Further, near the terraced road leading to the Temple, situated on the top of the cliff, several houses built in a row dating to the Hellenistic period have been discovered. At the east and west extremes of the city the two acropoleis are situated where a number of tombs have been found, many of which are intact.

Two small sanctuaries, with terracotta votive offerings of Graeco-Phoenician age, lie not far off, but the location of the great shrines of Adonis and Aphrodite have not been identified (M. Ohnefalsch-Richter, ''Kypros,'' i. ch.1).&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Amphora from Amathus at the British Museum.jpg|Amphora from tomb 52, Amathus, 6th century BC, British Museum
File:Αρχαιότητες της Αμαθούντας 2.jpg|in-situ copy of massive stone vase (original in the [[Louvre]])
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
*[http://icarus.umkc.edu/sandbox/perseus/pecs/page.232.a.php Richard Stillwell, ed. ''Princeton Encyclopaedia of Classical Sites'', 1976:] &quot;Amathous, Cyprus&quot;
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20060109034549/http://www.limassolmunicipal.com.cy/amathus/index.html Municipality of Limassol]

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Amathus}}
* http://www.mcw.gov.cy/mcw/DA/DA.nsf/0/D20ED526826AB796C225719B00374A92?OpenDocument
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20070405060415/http://www.agiostychonas.com/english/archaeology.shtml Agias Tychonas: Amathus] (English)
* http://www.anastasiosofsinai.org/index.html (English)

{{Ancient Cities of Cyprus}}

[[Category:Cities in ancient Cyprus]]
[[Category:Archaeological sites in Cyprus]]
[[Category:Former populated places in Cyprus]]</text>
      <sha1>c4p1erfg32c3hvf7hm3j9u67wi7tr2o</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
