  <page>
    <title>Afonso V of Portugal</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1661</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942983898</id>
      <parentid>926451033</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T03:07:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelink 1 book for [[Wikipedia:Verifiability|verifiability]]. [goog]) #IABot (v2.0) ([[User:GreenC bot|GreenC bot]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox royalty
|name         = Afonso V
|image        = File:Domafonsov.jpg
|caption      = Contemporary portrait in the ''Itinerarium'' of Georg von Ehingen, c. 1470
|succession   = [[King of Portugal]]
|reign        = 13 September 1438 – {{nowrap|28 August 1481}}{{efn|name=note 1|Afonso V abdicated on 11 November 1477, but was reinstated by request of his son 4 days later, on 15 November.}}
|cor-type     = Acclamation
|coronation   = 15 January 1446
|predecessor  = [[Edward, King of Portugal|Edward]]
|successor    = [[John II of Portugal|John II]]
|reg-type     = Regents
|regent       = {{list collapsed|title=''See list''|1= {{ubl |[[Eleanor of Aragon, Queen of Portugal|Eleanor of Aragon]] (1438–1439) | [[Peter, Duke of Coimbra]] (1439–1448)}} }}
|birth_date   = 15 January 1432
|birth_place  = [[Sintra National Palace|Sintra Palace]], [[Kingdom of Portugal|Portugal]]
|death_date   = {{Death date and age|1481|8|28|1432|1|15|df=y}}
|death_place  = [[Lisbon]], Portugal
|burial_place = [[Batalha Monastery]]
|spouse-type  = Consorts
|spouse       = {{ubl| [[Isabel of Coimbra]]&lt;br /&gt;(m. 1450; d. 1455) | [[Joanna la Beltraneja]]&lt;br /&gt;(m. 1475) }}
|issue        = {{ubl |[[John, Prince of Portugal (1451)|John, Prince of Portugal]] | [[Joanna, Princess of Portugal]] | [[John II of Portugal]] }}
|issue-pipe   = #Marriages and descendants
|house        = [[House of Aviz|Aviz]]
|father       = [[Edward, King of Portugal]]
|mother       = [[Eleanor of Aragon, Queen of Portugal|Eleanor of Aragon]]
|religion     = [[Roman Catholicism]]
|signature    = Assinatura D. Afonso V.svg
}}
'''Afonso V'''&lt;ref&gt;Rendered as Affonso in Archaic Portuguese&lt;/ref&gt; ({{IPA-pt|ɐˈfõsu}}) (15 January 1432 &amp;ndash; 28 August 1481), known by the [[sobriquet]] '''the African''' ({{Lang-pt|o Africano}}), was [[King of Portugal]]. His sobriquet refers to his conquests in [[Northern Africa]].

As of 1471, Afonso V was the first king of Portugal to claim dominion over a plural &quot;Kingdom of the Algarves&quot;, instead of the singular &quot;Kingdom of the Algarve&quot;. Territories added to the Portuguese crown lands in North Africa during the 15th century came to be referred to as possessions of the Kingdom of the Algarve (now a region of southern Portugal), not the Kingdom of Portugal. The &quot;Algarves&quot; then were considered to be the southern Portuguese territories on both sides of the [[Strait of Gibraltar]].

==Early life==
[[File:Cruzade d'Alphonse V dit l'africain.jpg|thumb|Afonso V of Portugal]]
Afonso was born in [[Sintra]], the second son of King [[Edward of Portugal]] by his wife [[Leonor of Aragon (1402-1445)|Eleanor of Aragon]]. Following the death of his older brother, Infante João (1429-1433), Afonso acceded to the position of heir apparent and was made the first [[Prince of Portugal]] by his father, who sought to emulate the English Court's custom of a dynastic title that distinguished the heir apparent from the other children of the monarch. He was only six years old when he succeeded his father in 1438.&lt;ref name=Gerli&gt;Livermore, H.V., &quot;Afonso V&quot;, ''Medieval Iberia'', E. Michael Gerli, and Samuel G. Armistead ed., Taylor &amp; Francis, 2003. [https://books.google.com/books?id=ra9BtjLRNMsC&amp;pg=PA37 p 37] {{ISBN|9780415939188}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During his minority, Afonso V was placed under the regency of his mother&lt;ref name=EB1911&gt;{{cite EB1911|wstitle=Alphonso}}&lt;/ref&gt; in accordance with a will of his late father. As both a foreigner and a woman, the queen was not a popular choice for regent. Opposition rose and without any important ally among the Portuguese aristocracy other than [[Afonso, Duke of Braganza|Afonso, Count of Barcelos]], the illegitimate half brother of King Edward, the queen's position was untenable. In 1439, the [[Portuguese Cortes]] (assembly of the kingdom) decided to replace the queen with [[Peter, Duke of Coimbra]] (Dom Pedro),&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; the young king's oldest uncle.&lt;ref name=Gerli/&gt;

Peter's main policies were concerned with restricting the political power of the great noble houses and expanding the powers of the crown. The country prospered under his rule, but not peacefully, as his laws interfered with the ambition of powerful nobles. The count of Barcelos, a personal enemy of the Duke of Coimbra (despite being half-brothers) eventually became the king's favourite uncle and began a constant struggle for power. In 1442, the king made Afonso the first [[Duke of Braganza]]. With this title and its lands, he became the most powerful man in Portugal and one of the richest men in Europe. To secure his position as regent, Peter had Afonso marry his daughter, [[Isabella of Coimbra]], in 1445.&lt;ref name=Gerli/&gt;

But on 9 June 1448, when the king came of age, Peter had to surrender his power to Afonso V.  The years of conspiracy by the Duke of Braganza finally came to a head. On 15 September of the same year, Afonso V nullified all the laws and edicts approved under the regency. In the following year, led by what were later discovered to be false accusations, Afonso declared Peter a rebel and defeated his army in the [[Battle of Alfarrobeira]], in which his uncle (and father-in-law) was killed.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; After this battle and the loss of one of Portugal's most remarkable infantes, the Duke of Braganza became the ''de facto'' ruler of the country.

==Invasion of Morocco==
{{further information|Morocco-Portugal relations}}
[[File:Landing at Asilah.jpg|thumb|300px|[[Conquest of Asilah|Conquest of Arzila]] in 1471]]
Afonso V then turned his attentions to North Africa. In the reign of his grandfather [[John I of Portugal|John I]], [[Ceuta]] had been conquered from the king of [[Morocco]], and now the new king wanted to expand the conquests. The king's army conquered [[Alcácer Ceguer]] in 1458 and [[Conquest of Arzila|Arzila]] in 1471. [[Tangiers]], on the other hand, was won and lost several times between 1460 and 1464. These achievements granted the king the nickname of ''the African'' or ''Africano''.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt; The king also supported the exploration of the [[Atlantic Ocean]] led by prince [[Henry the Navigator]] but after Henry's death in 1460, he did nothing to continue Henry's work. Administratively, Afonso V was a passive king. He chose not to pursue the revision of laws or development of commerce, preferring instead to preserve the legacy of his father Edward and grandfather [[John I of Portugal|John I]].

In 1452, [[Pope Nicholas V]] issued the [[papal bull]] ''[[Dum Diversas]]'', which granted Afonso V the right to reduce &quot;Saracens, pagans and any other unbelievers&quot; to hereditary slavery. This was reaffirmed and extended in the [[Romanus Pontifex]] bull of 1455 (also by Nicholas V). These papal bulls came to be seen by some as a justification for the subsequent era of slave trade and European colonialism.

[[File:FraMauroDetailedMapInverted.jpg|thumb|left|A copy of the [[Fra Mauro map]] was made under a commission by Afonso V in 1457. Finished on April 24, 1459, it was sent to Portugal with a letter to [[Prince Henry the Navigator]], Afonso's uncle, encouraging further funding of exploration trips. Although the copy has been lost, the [[Andrea Bianco]] original is preserved at the [[Biblioteca Marciana]] (Venice).]]

==Castile==
When the campaigns in Africa were over, Afonso V found new grounds for battle in neighboring [[Crown of Castile|Castile]]. On December 11, 1474 King [[Henry IV of Castile]] died without a male heir, leaving just one daughter, [[Joanna la Beltraneja]]. However, her paternity was questioned; it was rumored that his wife, Queen [[Joan of Portugal]] had an affair with a nobleman named [[Beltrán de La Cueva]]. The death of Henry ignited a [[War of the Castilian Succession|war of succession]] with one faction supporting Joanna and the other supporting [[Isabella I of Castile|Isabella]], Henry's half-sister. Afonso V was persuaded to intervene on behalf of Joanna, his niece. He betrothed himself to her, proclaimed himself king of Castile and led troops into the kingdom. Because of their close blood-relationship, a formal marriage had to wait for papal dispensation.&lt;ref name=Rubin&gt;{{cite book |last1=Rubin |first1=Nancy |title=Isabella of Castile: The First Renaissance Queen |date=1991 |publisher=St. Martin's Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 12, 1475, Afonso entered Castile with an army of 5,600 cavalry and 14,000 foot soldiers. In March, 1476, after several skirmishes and much maneuvering, the 8, 000 men of Afonso and [[John II of Portugal|Prince João]], faced a Castilian force of similar size in the [[battle of Toro]]. The Castilians were led by Isabella's husband, Prince [[Ferdinand II of Aragon]], [[Pedro González de Mendoza|Cardinal Mendoza]] and the [[García Álvarez de Toledo, 1st Duke of Alba|Duke of Alba]]. The fight was fierce and confusing but the result was a stalemate:&lt;ref name= &quot;The two sides&quot;&gt;''“The two sides finally and climactically clashed, in the major confrontation known as the [[Battle of Toro]], on March 1, 1476. he Portuguese army, led by King Afonso, his twenty-one-year-old son Prince João, and the rebellious Archbishop Carrillo of Toledo opposed Ferdinand, the Duke of Alba, Cardinal Mendoza, and other Castilian nobles leading the Isabelline forces. Foggy and rainy, it was bloody chaos on the battlefield. (...) Hundreds of people -perhaps as many as one thousand- died that day. (...). Troops led by [[John II of Portugal|Prince João]] won in their part of the battle; some troops led by [[Ferdinand II of Aragon|King Ferdinand]] won in another part. But the most telling fact was that King Afonso had fled the battlefield with his troops in disarray; the Castilians seized his battle flag, the royal standard of Portugal, despite the valiant efforts of a Portuguese soldier, [[:pt:Duarte de Almeida|Duarte de Almeida]], to retain it. (...). The Portuguese, however, later managed to recover the banner. The battle ended in an inconclusive outcome, but Isabella employed a masterstroke of political theater by recasting events as a stupendous victory for Castile. Each side had won some skirmishes and lost others, but Ferdinand was presented in Castile as the winner and Afonso as a craven failure. (...)..”''  In Downey, Kirstin- [https://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;q=%22troops+led+by+Prince+Joao+won%22  &quot;Isabella: the Warrior Queen&quot;], Anchor Books, New York, 2014, [https://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;q=%22the+battle+ended+in+an+inconclusive+outcome%22  p. 145]&lt;/ref&gt; While the forces of [[Pedro González de Mendoza|Cardinal Mendoza]] and the [[García Álvarez de Toledo, 1st Duke of Alba|Duke of Alba]] won over their opponents led by the Portuguese King –who left the battlefield to take refuge in [[Castronuño]], the troops commanded by [[John II of Portugal|Prince Joao]] defeated and persecuted the troops of the Castilian right wing, recovered the Portuguese royal standard, remaining ordered in the battlefield where they collected the fugitives of Afonso.&lt;ref name= &quot;The two sides&quot;/&gt;  Both sides claimed victory but Afonso's prospects for obtaining the [[Crown of Castile|Castilian crown]] were severely damaged.&lt;ref name=Rubin /&gt;

{{quote|''“It was March 1, 1476. Eight thousand men for each side, the chronicles tell. With Afonso of Portugal were his son João and the bishops of Evora and Toledo. With [[Ferdinand II of Aragon|Fernando of Aragón]], Cardinal Mendoza and the Duke of Alba, as well as the militias of [[Zamora, Spain|Zamora]], [[Ciudad Rodrigo]] and [[Valladolid]]. The battle was long, but not especially bloody: it is estimated that the casualties of each side did not reach a thousand. Who won? In reality, no one: Alfonso's wing of Portugal fell under the thrust of Fernando, but [[John II of Portugal|Prince Juan]]'s troops crushed their Castilian rivals. However, victory in this battle was not going to be military, but ... political. In fact, Ferdinand of Aragon, seeing that the clash concluded without winners or losers, hastened to give his own version of the facts. He sent letters to all the cities of Castile and Aragon and to several European courts.”'' &lt;ref name= &quot;Esparza, José J.&quot;&gt;Esparza, José J. (Spanish)-  [https://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;q=%22Quien+gan%C3%B3%3F+en+realidad+nadie%22  ''¡Santiago y cierra, España!''], La Esfera de los Libros, 2013 ([https://books.google.com/books?id=GaoPAQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT440&amp;dq=%22Quien+gan%C3%B3?+en+realidad+nadie%22&amp;hl=pt-PT&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiT_5KJlMPfAhX9SBUIHf5gAtkQ6AEIKTAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Quien%20gan%C3%B3%3F%20en%20realidad%20nadie%22&amp;f=false  electronic version] without page numbering).&lt;/ref&gt;|In  ''¡Santiago y cierra, España! '', José Esparza}}

After the battle, Afonso sailed to France hoping to obtain the assistance of King [[Louis XI of France|Louis XI]] in his fight against Castile.  But finding himself deceived by the French monarch, he returned to Portugal in 1477. Disillusioned, he abdicated for a few days in November 1477 in favor of his son [[John II of Portugal|John II]], then after returning to the throne, he retired to a monastery in Sintra, where he died in 1481.&lt;ref name=EB1911/&gt;

==Marriages and descendants==
Afonso married firstly, in 1447, [[Isabella of Coimbra]], with whom he had three children:

*[[John, Prince of Portugal (1451)|John, Prince of Portugal]] (29 January 1451).
*[[Joan of Portugal (nun)|Joan, Princess of Portugal]] (6 February 1452 – 12 May 1490): Known as Saint Joan of Portugal or Saint Joan Princess. 
*[[John II of Portugal]] (3 March 1455 – 25 October 1495): Succeeded his father as 13th King of Portugal.

Afonso married secondly, in 1475, his niece [[Joanna la Beltraneja|Joanna of Castile]], known as &quot;La Beltraneja&quot;.

==Ancestry==
{{ahnentafel
|collapsed=yes |align=center
|boxstyle_1=background-color: #fcc;
|boxstyle_2=background-color: #fb9;
|boxstyle_3=background-color: #ffc;
|boxstyle_4=background-color: #bfc;
|boxstyle_5=background-color: #9fe;
|1= 1. '''Afonso V of Portugal'''
|2= 2. [[Edward, King of Portugal|Edward I of Portugal]]
|3= 3. [[Eleanor of Aragon, Queen of Portugal|Eleanor of Aragon]]
|4= 4. [[John I of Portugal]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephens1903&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Stephens|first=Henry Morse|title=The Story of Portugal|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jwMqAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA139|accessdate=17 September 2018|year=1903|publisher=G.P. Putnam's Sons|page=139}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|5= 5. [[Philippa of Lancaster]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephens1903&quot;/&gt;
|6= 6. [[Ferdinand I of Aragon]]&lt;ref name=&quot;DeSousa2&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://archive.org/stream/historiagenealog02sous#page/496/mode/2up |title=Historia genealogica da casa real portugueza |trans-title=Genealogical History of the Royal House of Portugal |volume=2 |language=pt |last=de Sousa |first=Antonio Caetano |publisher=Lisboa Occidental |year=1735 |page=497}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
|7= 7. [[Eleanor of Alburquerque]]&lt;ref name=&quot;DeSousa2&quot;/&gt;
|8= 8. [[Peter I of Portugal]]&lt;ref name=&quot;EB-John I&quot;&gt;{{Britannica|304662|John I, King of Portugal}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|9= 9. [[Teresa Lourenço]]&lt;ref name=&quot;EB-John I&quot;/&gt;
|10= 10. [[John of Gaunt|John of Gaunt, 1st Duke of Lancaster]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Armitage-Smith&quot;&gt;{{cite book| last=Armitage-Smith |first=Sydney |title=John of Gaunt: King of Castile and Leon, Duke of Aquitaine and Lancaster, Earl of Derby, Lincoln, and Leicester, Seneschal of England |url=https://archive.org/details/johngauntkingca01armigoog |accessdate=17 July 2018 |year=1905 |publisher=Charles Scribner's Sons |page=[https://archive.org/details/johngauntkingca01armigoog/page/n22 21]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|11= 11. [[Blanche of Lancaster]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Armitage-Smith&quot;/&gt;
|12= 12. [[John I of Castile]]&lt;ref name=&quot;DeSousa2&quot;/&gt;
|13= 13. [[Eleanor of Aragon, Queen of Castile|Eleanor of Aragon]]&lt;ref name=&quot;DeSousa2&quot;/&gt;
|14= 14. [[Sancho Alfonso, 1st Count of Alburquerque]]&lt;ref name=&quot;DeSousa2&quot;/&gt;
|15= 15. [[Beatrice, Countess of Alburquerque|Beatrice of Portugal]]&lt;ref name=&quot;DeSousa2&quot;/&gt;
}}

==Notes==
{{notelist}}
&lt;references/&gt;

== Bibliography ==

'''Articles'''
* {{cite publication |last=López Poza |first=Sagrario |title=&quot;La divisa de Alfonso V el Africano, rey de Portugal: nueva lectura e interpretación|year=2019 |journal=Janus. Estudios sobre el Siglo de Oro |number=8 |pages=47-74 |issn=2254-7290 |url=https://www.janusdigital.es/articulo.htm?id=122}}
* MILLER, Townsend- [http://www.google.com/search?q=%22the+outcome+of+Toro%2C+militarily%2C+is+debatable%2C+there+is+no+doubt+whatsoever+as%22&amp;tbm=bks&amp;tbo=1&amp;hl=pt-PT  ''The battle of Toro, 1476''], in [[History Today]], volume 14, 1964.
'''Books'''
*DOWNEY, Kirstin- [https://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;q=%22the+battle+ended+in+an+inconclusive+outcome%22  ''Isabella: the Warrior Queen''], Anchor Books, New York, 2014
* SAUL, António- [https://books.google.com/books?id=7U8sAQAAIAAJ&amp;q=%22Afonso+V+Saul%22&amp;dq=%22Afonso+V+Saul%22&amp;hl=pt-PT&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=Z7IVUfi4M9KGhQf2k4CQBQ&amp;redir_esc=y  Dom Afonso V], vol. 12 of Reis de Portugal, 2009, Temas e Debates-Actividades Editoriais, {{ISBN|978-97-2759-975-2}}

{{S-start}}
{{S-hou|[[House of Aviz]]|15 January|1432|28 August|1481|[[Portuguese House of Burgundy|House of Burgundy]]}}
{{S-reg}}
{{S-bef|before=[[Edward of Portugal|Edward]]}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[King of Portugal]]|years=1438–1477}}
{{S-aft|rows=2|after=[[John II of Portugal|John II]]}}
{{S-bef|before=[[John II of Portugal|John II]]}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[King of Portugal]]|years=1477–1481}}
{{S-roy|pt}}
{{S-new|reason=}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[Prince of Portugal]]|years=1433–1438}}
{{S-aft|after=[[Infante Ferdinand, Duke of Viseu|Infante Ferdinand]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{Monarchs of Portugal}}
{{Portuguese infantes}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Afonso 05 Of Portugal}}
[[Category:Portuguese monarchs]]
[[Category:Princes of Portugal]]
[[Category:Portuguese infantes]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic monarchs]]
[[Category:House of Aviz]]
[[Category:Knights of the Garter]]
[[Category:Medieval child rulers]]
[[Category:1432 births]]
[[Category:1481 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Sintra]]
[[Category:15th-century Portuguese monarchs]]
[[Category:Portuguese exploration in the Age of Discovery]]</text>
      <sha1>g53kpn8bv0syxhgt4czpdry24bwam9m</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
