  <page>
    <title>Afonso I of Portugal</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1657</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940986956</id>
      <parentid>935245234</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-15T22:31:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>IznoRepeat</username>
        <id>12897086</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>replace soft-deprecated editors parameter, gen fixes, misc cite cleaning</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Afonso I|the African ruler|Afonso I of Kongo}}
{{short description|12th-century King of Portugal}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2019}}
{{Infobox royalty
| name            = Afonso I
| image           = D. Afonso Henriques - Compendio de crónicas de reyes (Biblioteca Nacional de España).png
| caption         = Portrait in ''Compendium of Chronicles of Kings'' (c. 1312–25)
| succession      = [[King of Portugal]]
| reign           = {{nowrap|26 July 1139{{snd}}6 December 1185}}
| coronation      = 26 July 1139
| cor-type        = Acclamation
| successor       = [[Sancho I of Portugal|Sancho I]]
| birth_date      = Disputed: 1106, 1109 or 1111
| birth_place     = Disputed: [[Coimbra]], [[Guimarães]] or [[Viseu]], [[County of Portugal|Portugal]]; [[Tierra de Campos]] or [[Sahagún]], [[Kingdom of León|León]]
| death_date      = 6 December 1185 (aged 73–79)
| death_place     = [[Coimbra]], [[Portugal in the Middle Ages|Portugal]]
| spouse          = [[Matilda of Savoy, Queen of Portugal|Mafalda of Savoy]]
| issue           = (illeg.) [[Fernando Afonso of Portugal|Fernando Afonso]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Urraca of Portugal|Urraca, Queen of León]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Theresa of Portugal, Countess of Flanders|Teresa of Flanders]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mafalda of Portugal (daughter of Afonso Henriques)|Mafalda]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sancho I of Portugal|Sancho I]]
| issue-link      = #Descendants
| issue-pipe      = among others ...
| house           = [[Portuguese House of Burgundy]]
| father          = [[Henry, Count of Portugal]]
| mother          = [[Teresa, Countess of Portugal]]
| religion        = [[Catholic Church|Catholic]]
| succession1     = [[Count of Portugal]]
| reign1          = 24 June 1128{{snd}}25 July 1139
| predecessor1    = [[Teresa of León, Countess of Portugal|Teresa]]
| regent1         = 
| place of burial = [[Santa Cruz Monastery]], [[Coimbra]], Portugal
}}
'''Afonso I'''&lt;ref group=&quot;lower-alpha&quot;&gt;Or also ''Affonso'' (Archaic [[Portuguese-Galician]]) or ''Alphonso'' ([[Portuguese-Galician languages|Portuguese-Galician]]) or ''Alphonsus'' ([[Latin]] version), sometimes rendered in English as ''Alphonzo'' or ''Alphonse'', depending on the Spanish or French influence.&lt;/ref&gt; ({{IPA-pt|ɐˈfõsu|eu}}; 1106 / 25 July 1109 / August 1109 / 1111{{snd}}6 December 1185), nicknamed '''the Conqueror''' ({{lang-pt|O Conquistador}}), '''the Founder''' ({{lang|pt|O Fundador}}) or '''the Great''' ({{lang|pt|O Grande}}) by the [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]], and '''''El-Bortukali''''' ([in Arabic {{lang|ar|البرتقالي}}] &quot;the Portuguese&quot;) and ''Ibn-Arrink'' or ''Ibn Arrinq'' ([in Arabic {{lang|ar|ابن الرَّنك}} or {{lang|ar|ابن الرَنْق}}] &quot;son of Henry&quot;, &quot;Henriques&quot;) by the [[Moors]] whom he fought, was the first [[King of Portugal]]. He achieved the independence of the County of Portugal, establishing a new kingdom and doubling its area with the ''[[Reconquista]]'', an objective that he pursued until his death.

Afonso was the son of [[Henry, Count of Portugal|Henry of Burgundy]] and [[Theresa, Countess of Portugal|Theresa of León]], co-rulers of the County of Portugal. Henry died in 1112, leaving Theresa as the sole ruler. Unhappy with Theresa's alliance with [[Kingdom of Galicia|Galicia]], the Portuguese nobility rallied around Afonso, who revolted and defeated his mother at the [[Battle of São Mamede]] in 1128 and became Count of Portugal soon afterwards. In 1139, Afonso renounced the [[suzerainty]] of the [[Kingdom of León]] and established the independent [[Kingdom of Portugal]].

Afonso actively campaigned against the Moors in the south. In 1139 he won a decisive victory at the [[Battle of Ourique]], and in 1147 he conquered [[Conquest of Santarém|Santarém]] and [[Siege of Lisbon|Lisbon]] from the Moors. He secured the independence of Portugal following a victory over León at [[Battle of Valdevez|Valdevez]] and received papal approval through ''[[Manifestis Probatum]]''. Afonso died in 1185 and was suceeded by his son, [[Sancho I of Portugal|Sancho I]].

==Youth==
Afonso was the son of [[Henry, Count of Portugal|Henry of Burgundy]] and [[Teresa of León, Countess of Portugal|Teresa]], the [[illegitimate]] daughter of King [[Alfonso VI of León and Castile]]. According to [[Fernão Lopes]]' ''Crónica de Portugal de 1419,'' the future Portuguese king was born in [[Guimarães]], which was at the time the most important political center of his parents. This was accepted by most Portuguese scholarship until in 1990 Torquato de Sousa Soares proposed Coimbra, the center of the county of Coimbra and another political center of Afonso's progenitors, as his birthplace, which caused outrage in Guimarães and a polemic between this historian and [[José Hermano Saraiva]]. Almeida Fernandes later proposed [[Viseu]] as the birthplace of Afonso basing himself on the ''[[Chronica Gothorum]]'', which states Afonso was born in 1109, a position followed by [[José Mattoso]] in his biography of the king.{{Sfn|Mattoso|2014|pp=26–27
}}  Abel Estefânio has suggested a different date and thesis, proposing 1106 as the birth date and the region of [[Tierra de Campos]] or even [[Sahagún]] as likely birth places based on the known itineraries of counts Henry and Teresa.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Estefânio|first=Abel|date=July 2010|title=A data de nascimento de Afonso I|url=http://www2.fcsh.unl.pt/iem/medievalista/MEDIEVALISTA8/estefanio8002.html|journal=Medievalista|volume= 8|language=PT|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Estefânio|first=Abel|date=January 2016|title=De novo a data e o local de nascimento de Afonso I|url=http://www2.fcsh.unl.pt/iem/medievalista/MEDIEVALISTA19/estefanio1906.html|journal=Medievalista|volume= 19|language=PT|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Henry and Teresa reigned jointly as count and countess of Portugal until his death on 22 May 1112 during the siege of [[Astorga, Spain|Astorga]],{{Sfn|Mattoso|2014|p=34}} after which Teresa ruled Portugal alone.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gerli&quot;&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=QlpKAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA676&amp;lpg=PA676&amp;dq=afonso+i+of+portugal&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=sWxOTr0U1v&amp;sig=HbyK45MU-hykot9JlUwI7jRwtTU&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAzgeahUKEwi_xp_5zPvGAhUFWz4KHWWAAh8#v=onepage&amp;q=afonso%20i%20of%20portugal&amp;f=false Gerli, E. Michael. ''Medieval Iberia'', Routledge, 2013] {{ISBN|9781136771613}}&lt;/ref&gt; She would proclaim herself queen (a claim recognised by [[Pope Paschal II]] in 1116) but was captured and forced to reaffirm her vassalage to her half-sister, [[Urraca of León]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Gerli&quot;/&gt;

It is not known who was the tutor of Afonso. Later traditions, probably started with João Soares Coelho (a bastard descendant of Egas Moniz through a female line) in the mid-13th century and ampliated by later chronicles such as the ''Crónica de Portugal de 1419'', asserted he had been [[Egas Moniz o Aio|Egas Moniz de Ribadouro]], possibly with the help of oral memories that associated the tutor to the house of Ribadouro. Yet, contemporary documents, namely from the chancery of Afonso in his early years as count of Portucale, indicate according to the [[historian]] [[José Mattoso]] that the most likely tutor of Afonso Henriques was Egas Moniz's oldest brother, [[Ermígio Moniz]], who, besides being the senior brother within the family of Ribadouro, became the &quot;dapifer&quot; and &quot;[[Mayor of the Palace|majordomus]]&quot; of Afonso I from 1128 until his death in 1135, which indicates his closer proximity to the prince.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=João Soares Coelho e a gesta de Egas Moniz. In Portugal Medieval: Novas Interpretações|last=Mattoso|first=José|publisher=Imprensa Nacional – Casa da Moeda|year=1985|isbn=|location=Lisboa|pages=409–435}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=D. Afonso Henriques|last=Mattoso|first=José|publisher=Temas e Debates|year=2007|isbn=978-972-759-911-0|location=Lisboa|pages=35–38}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In an effort to pursue a larger share in the Leonese inheritance, his mother Teresa joined forces with [[Fernando Pérez de Trava]], the most powerful count in [[kingdom of Galicia|Galicia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Gerli&quot; /&gt; The Portuguese nobility disliked the alliance between Galicia and Portugal and rallied around Afonso.  The [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Braga|Archbishop of Braga]] was also concerned with the dominance of Galicia, apprehensive of the ecclesiastical pretensions of his new rival the Galician [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Santiago de Compostela|Archbishop of Santiago de Compostela]], [[Diego Gelmírez]], who had claimed an alleged discovery of relics of [[James, son of Zebedee|Saint James]] in his town, as a way to gain power and riches over the other cathedrals in the Iberian Peninsula. In 1122, Afonso turned fourteen, the adult age in the 12th century. In symmetry with his [[Alfonso VII of León and Castile|cousin]] he made himself a [[knight]] on his own account in the [[Cathedral of Zamora]] in 1125, with the permission of his mother.  After the military campaign of Alfonso VII against his mother in 1127, Afonso revolted against her and proceeded to take control of the county from its queen.

== Sole count ==
In 1128, near [[Guimarães]] at the [[Battle of São Mamede]], Afonso and his supporters overcame troops under both his mother and her lover, Count [[Fernando Peres de Trava]] of [[Kingdom of Galicia|Galicia]]. Afonso exiled his mother to Galicia, and took over rule of the County of Portucale.&lt;ref name=Gerli/&gt; Thus the possibility of re-incorporating Portucale into a Kingdom of Portugal and Galicia as before was eliminated and Afonso became sole ruler following demands for greater independence from the county's church and nobles. The battle was mostly ignored by the Leonese [[suzerain]] who was occupied at the time with a revolt in Castille. He was also, most likely, waiting for the reaction of the Galician families. After Teresa's death in 1131, [[Alfonso VII of León and Castile|Afonso VII of León and Castille]] proceeded to demand vassalage from his cousin.  On 6 April 1129, Afonso Henriques dictated the [[writ]] in which he proclaimed himself Prince of Portugal or Prince of the Portuguese, an act informally allowed by Afonso VII, as it was thought to be Afonso Henriques's right by blood, as one of two grandsons of the [[Alfonso VI of León and Castile|Emperor of Hispania]].

Afonso then turned his arms against the persistent problem of the Moors in the south. His campaigns were successful and, on 25 July 1139, he obtained an overwhelming victory in the [[Battle of Ourique]], and straight after was (possibly unanimously) proclaimed King of the Portuguese by his soldiers, establishing his equality in rank to the other realms of the Peninsula, although the first reference to his royal title dates from 1140. The first assembly of the [[Portuguese Cortes]] convened at [[Lamego]] (wherein he would have been given the crown from the Archbishop of Braga, to confirm his independence) is a 17th-century embellishment of Portuguese history.{{clarify|reason=uninterpretable grammar|date=October 2019}}

== Kingship ==
[[File:D. Afonso Henriques (Quinta da Regaleira).png|left|thumb|287x287px|19th-century depiction of King Afonso I Henriques of Portugal, on the ceiling of the Kings' Room, [[Quinta da Regaleira]], [[Sintra]], Portugal.]]
Complete independence from Alfonso VII of León's [[suzerainty]], however, was not a thing he just could achieve militarily. The County of Portugal still had to be acknowledged diplomatically by the neighboring lands as a kingdom and, most importantly, by the [[Catholic Church]] and the [[Pope]]. Afonso wed [[Mafalda of Savoy, Queen of Portugal|Mafalda of Savoy]], daughter of [[Amadeus III, Count of Savoy]], and sent ambassadors to Rome to negotiate with the Pope. He succeeded in renouncing the suzerainty of his cousin, Alfonso VII of León, becoming instead a vassal of the papacy, as the kings of Sicily and Aragon had done before him. 
[[Image:Siege of Lisbon - Muslim surrender.jpg|thumb|339x339px|King Afonso I at the [[Siege of Lisbon]] (Oil on Canvas by Joaquim Rodrigues Braga)]]
In Portugal he built several monasteries and convents and bestowed important privileges to religious orders. He is notably the builder of [[Alcobaça Monastery]], to which he called the [[Cistercians|Cistercian Order]] of his uncle [[Bernard of Clairvaux]] of [[Burgundy (region)|Burgundy]]. In 1143, he wrote to [[Pope Innocent II]] to declare himself and the kingdom servants of the church, swearing to pursue driving the Moors out of the Iberian Peninsula. Bypassing any king of León, Afonso declared himself the direct [[wikt:liege|liege man]] of the papacy. Afonso continued to distinguish himself by his exploits against the Moors, from whom he wrested [[Santarém, Portugal|Santarém]] (see [[Conquest of Santarém]]) and [[Lisbon]] in 1147 (see [[Siege of Lisbon]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;&gt;{{EB1911|inline=1|wstitle=Alphonso|display=Alphonso s.v. Alphonso I.|first=David|last=Hannay|authorlink=David Hannay (historian)|volume=1|page=733}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also conquered an important part of the land south of the [[Tagus]] River, although this was lost again to the Moors in the following years.

Meanwhile, King Alfonso VII of León (Afonso's cousin) regarded the independent ruler of Portugal as nothing but a rebel. Conflict between the two was constant and bitter in the following years. Afonso became involved in a war, taking the side of the Aragonese king, an enemy of Castile. To ensure the alliance, his son [[Sancho I of Portugal|Sancho]] was engaged to [[Dulce of Aragon|Dulce]], sister of the [[Count of Barcelona]] and Infanta of Aragon. Finally after winning the [[Battle of Valdevez]], the [[Treaty of Zamora (1143)]] established peace between the cousins and the recognition by the Kingdom of León that Portugal was a fully independent kingdom.

In 1169 the now old Dom Afonso was possibly disabled in an engagement near [[Badajoz]], by a fall from his horse and slamming against the castles gate, and made prisoner by the soldiers of the king of León [[Ferdinand II of León|Fernando II]] also his son-in-law. He spent months at the [[São Pedro do Sul, Portugal|hot springs of São Pedro do Sul]], but never recovered and from this time onward the Portuguese king never rode a horse again. However, it is not certain if this was because of the disability: according to the later Portuguese chronistic tradition, this happened because Afonso would have to surrender himself again to Fernando II of León or risk war between the two kingdoms if he ever rode a horse again. Portugal was obliged to surrender as his ransom almost all the conquests Afonso had made in Galicia (north of the [[Minho River]]) in the previous years.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; This event became known in portuguese history as the Disaster of Badajoz (''o Desastre de Badajoz''). 
[[Image:BatalhaOurique.jpg|thumb|left|341x341px|Afonso at the [[Battle of Ourique]] witnessing the Miracle of the Cross (dated 1793 by Domigos Sequeira)]]

In 1179 the privileges and favours given to the [[Catholic Church]] were compensated. With consistent effort by several parties, such as the [[Primate (bishop)|Primate]] [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Braga|Archpishop of Braga]] [[Paio Mendes]], in the papal court, the [[papal bull]] ''[[Manifestis Probatum]]'' was promulgated accepting the new king as vassal to the pope exclusively. In it [[Pope Alexander III]] also acknowledged Afonso as King and Portugal as an independent crown with the right to conquer lands from the Moors. With this papal blessing, Portugal was at last secured as a kingdom.

In 1184, the Almohad caliph [[Abu Yaqub Yusuf]] rallied a great [[Almohad Caliphate|Almohad]] force to retaliate against the Portuguese raids done since the end of a five-year truce in 1178 and besieged [[Santarém, Portugal|Santarém]], which was defended by the heir [[Sancho I of Portugal|Sancho]]. The Almohad siege failed when news arrived the [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Santiago de Compostela|archbishop of Compostela]] had come to the defense of the city and Fernando II of León himself with his army. The Almohads ended the siege and their retreat turned into a rout due to panic in their camp, with the Almohad caliph being injured in the process (according to one version, because of a [[crossbow]] bolt) and dying on the way back to [[Seville]]. Afonso died shortly after, probably out of a sudden cause of death, on 6 December 1185. The Portuguese revere him as a hero, both on account of his personal character and as the founder of their nation.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; There are mythical stories that it took 10 men to carry his sword, and that Afonso wanted to engage other monarchs in personal combat, but no one would dare accept his challenge. It is also told, despite his honourable character, that he had a temper. Several chronicles give the example of a papal legate that brought a message from the [[Pope Paschal II]] refusing to acknowledge Afonso's claim as King: either after committing or saying a small offense against him or after being simply read the letter, Afonso almost killed, in his rage, the papal representative, taking several portucalense nobles and soldiers to physically restrain the young would-be king.

==Scientific research==
[[Image:AfonsoHenriques-Tomb.jpg|thumb|right|Tomb of Afonso Henriques in the [[Monastery of Santa Cruz (Coimbra)|Santa Cruz Monastery]] in [[Coimbra]].]]
In July 2006, the tomb of the king (which is located in the [[Monastery of Santa Cruz (Coimbra)|Santa Cruz Monastery]] in [[Coimbra]]) was to be opened for scientific purposes by researchers from the [[University of Coimbra]] (Portugal) and the [[University of Granada]] (Spain). The opening of the tomb provoked considerable concern among some sectors of Portuguese society and Portuguese State Agency for Architectural Patrimony (''Instituto Português do Património Arquitectónico'' – [[IPPAR]]) halted the opening, requesting more protocols from the scientific team because of the importance of the king in the nation's heart and public thought.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dossiers.publico.pt/shownews.asp?id=1263265&amp;idCanal=1806 ''IPPAR: direcção nacional diz que não foi consultada sobre abertura do túmulo de D. Afonso Henriques''] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070610200658/http://dossiers.publico.pt/shownews.asp?id=1263265&amp;idCanal=1806 |date=10 June 2007 }}, [[Público (Portugal)|Público]], 6 July 2006. Retrieved December 2006 (in Portuguese)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[n:Portuguese Culture Ministry suspends opening of Afonso I's tomb]]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Descendants==
In 1146,{{efn|Although the ''Annales D. Alfonsi Portugallensium Regis'', record that the wedding of Alfonso and Mafalda was celebrated in 1145, it was not until a year later, in May 1146, when they both appear in royal charters. Historian José Mattoso refers to another source, ''Noticia sobre a Conquista de Santarém'' (News on the [[Conquest of Santarém]]), which states that the city was taken on 15 May 1147, less than a year after their marriage. Since at that time no wedding ceremony could be performed during [[Lent]], Mattoso suggests that the marriage could have taken place in March or April 1146, possibly on Easter Sunday which fell on 31 March of that year.{{Sfn|Mattoso|2014|p=220}}}} Afonso married [[Matilda of Savoy, Queen of Portugal|Mafalda]], daughter of [[Amadeus III, Count of Savoy]] and [[Mahaut of Albon]], both appearing together for the first time in May of that year confirming royal charters.{{Sfn|Mattoso|2014|p=220}} They had the following issue:{{Sfn|Mattoso|2014|pp=226–227}}

* Henry (5 March 1147 – 1155{{Sfn|Caetano de Souza|1735|p=60}}{{Sfn|Rodrigues Oliveira|2010|p=71}} named after his paternal grandfather, [[Henry, Count of Portugal]], he died when he was only eight years old.  Despite being just a child he represented his father at a council in [[Toledo, Spain|Toledo]] at the age of three;{{Sfn|Mattoso|2014|p=226}}
* [[Urraca of Portugal|Urraca]] (1148–1211{{Sfn|Mattoso|2014|p=226}}{{Sfn|Rodrigues Oliveira|2010|p=79}}), married King [[Ferdinand II of León]] and was the mother of King [[Alfonso IX of León|Alfonso IX]]. The marriage was subsequently annulled in 1171 or 1172 and she retired in [[Zamora, Spain|Zamora]], one of the villas that she had received as part of her [[Las arras#Origins and representation|''arras'']], and later at the Monastery of Santa María in [[Wamba, Valladolid]] where she was buried.;{{Sfn|Arco y Garay|1954|p=168}}
* [[Theresa of Portugal, Countess of Flanders|Teresa]] (1151–1218{{Sfn|Mattoso|2014|p=226}}{{Sfn|Rodrigues Oliveira|2010|p=80}}), [[Countess of Flanders|Countess consort of Flanders]] due to her marriage to [[Philip I, Count of Flanders|Philip I]]{{Sfn|Mattoso|2014|pp=372–373}} and [[List of Burgundian consorts|Duchess consort of Burgundy]] through her second marriage to [[Odo III, Duke of Burgundy|Odo III]];{{Sfn|Rodrigues Oliveira|2010|p=79}}
* [[Mafalda of Portugal (daughter of Afonso Henriques)|Mafalda]] (1153{{Sfn|Mattoso|2014|p=226}}{{Sfn|Rodrigues Oliveira|2010|p=71}}{{snd}}after 1162). In January 1160, her father and [[Ramón Berenguer IV, Count of Barcelona]], negotiated the marriage of Mafalda to Alfonso, future King [[Alfonso II of Aragon]]{{Sfn|Caetano de Souza|1735|p=60}}{{Sfn|Rodrigues Oliveira|2010|p=78}} who at that time was three or four years old. After the death of Ramón Berenguer IV in the summer of 1162, King Ferdinand II of León convinced his widow, Queen [[Petronilla of Aragón|Petronilla]], to cancel the infante's wedding plans with Mafalda and for Alfonso to marry instead [[Sancha of Castile, Queen of Aragon|Sancha,]] daughter of [[Alfonso VII of León]] and his second wife Queen [[Richeza of Poland, Queen of Castile|Richeza of Poland]].{{Sfn|Mattoso|2014|pp=287–288, 290}} Mafalda died in her childhood at an unrecorded date.
* Sancho, the future King [[Sancho I of Portugal]] (11 November 1154{{Sfn|Rodrigues Oliveira|2010|p=71}}{{snd}}26 March 1211). He was baptised with the name of Martin for having been born on the [[Martin of Tours|saint's]] feast day.;{{Sfn|Mattoso|2014|p=226}}
* John (1156–25 August 1164);{{Sfn|Mattoso|2014|p=227}} and
* Sancha (1157–14 February 1166/67), born ten days before the death of her mother, Sancha died before reaching the age of ten{{Sfn|Mattoso|2014|pp =227, 383}}{{Sfn|Rodrigues Oliveira|2010|p=71}} on 14 February according to the death registry at the Monastery of Santa Cruz (Coimbra) where she was buried.{{Sfn|Caetano de Souza|1735|p=60}}

Before his marriage to Mafalda, King Afonso fathered his first son with Chamoa Gómez,{{Sfn|Rodrigues Oliveira|2010|p=71}} daughter of Count [[Gómez Núñez]] and Elvira Pérez, sister of [[Fernando Pérez de Traba|Fernando]] and [[Bermudo Pérez de Traba]]:{{Sfn|Calderón Medina|2008|p=42, n. 11}}{{Sfn|Mattoso|2014|pp=98, 228, 320}}

* [[Fernando Afonso of Portugal|Afonso]] (1140–1207). Born around 1140,{{Sfn|Mattoso|2014|p=228}} according to recent investigations, he is the same person as the one often called '''Fernando Afonso''' who was the [[Alférez|''alferes-mor'']] of the king and later Grand Master of the [[Knights Hospitaller]]. His presence in the court is first recorded in 1159. In 1169 he succeeded as alferes-mor his half-brother, Pedro Pais da Maia, the legitimate son of his mother and Paio Soares da Maia.{{Sfn|Mattoso|2014|pp=227–229}}{{Sfn|Calderón Medina|2008|pp=42–43, and notes}}

The extramarital offspring by Elvira Gálter were:
* [[Urraca Afonso, Lady of Aveiro|Urraca Afonso]].{{Sfn|Caetano de Souza|1735|pp=28, 64}} In 1185, her father gave her [[Avô]], stipulating that this villa was to be inherited only by the children that she had with her husband Pedro Afonso de Ribadouro (also known as Pedro Afonso Viegas), grandson of [[Egas Moniz, Aio|Egas Moniz]],{{Sfn|Caetano de Souza|1735|p=64}} which could indicate another previous or subsequent marriage. In 1187, she exchanged with her half-brother, King Sancho, this villa for [[Aveiro, Portugal|Aveiro]]. She died after 1216, the year she made a donation to the Monastery of Tarouca. {{Sfn|Sotto Mayor Pizarro|1997|p=457, n. 9 and 10, Vol. I}}
* Teresa Afonso. In some genealogies she appears as the daughter of Elvira Gálter,{{Sfn|Caetano de Souza|1735|pp=28, 63}} and in others as the daughter of Chamoa Gómez. Her first marriage was with Sancho Nunes de Barbosa with whom she had a daughter, Urraca Sanches, who married Gonçalo Mendes de Sousa, the father of Mendo Gonçalves de Sousa known as &quot;Sousão&quot;.{{Sfn|Caetano de Souza|1735|p=63}} Her second husband was Fernando Martins Bravo, Lord of [[Bragança, Portugal|Bragança]] and [[Chaves, Portugal|Chaves]], with no issue from this marriage.{{Sfn|Caetano de Souza|1735|p=63}}

King Afonso was also the father of:
* [[Pedro Afonso, Master of Aviz|Pedro Afonso]] (died after 1183), Lord of [[Arega]] and Pedrógão, mayor of [[Abrantes]] in 1179, ''alferes'' of King Afonso I between 1181 and 1183, and Master of the [[Order of Aviz]].{{Sfn|Mattoso|2014|pp=103, 229, 388}}{{Sfn|Caetano de Souza|1735|p=28}}

==Ancestry==
{{ahnentafel
|collapsed=yes |align=center
|boxstyle_1=background-color: #fcc;
|boxstyle_2=background-color: #fb9;
|boxstyle_3=background-color: #ffc;
|boxstyle_4=background-color: #bfc;
|boxstyle_5=background-color: #9fe;
|1= 1. '''Afonso I of Portugal'''
|2= 2. [[Henry, Count of Portugal]]
|3= 3. [[Theresa, Countess of Portugal]]
|4= 4. [[Henry, son of Robert I of Burgundy|Henry of Burgundy]]
|5= 5. Clémence (disputed)
|6= 6. [[Alfonso VI of León and Castile]]
|7= 7. [[Jimena Muñoz]]
|8= 8. [[Robert I, Duke of Burgundy]]
|9= 9. Helie of Semur
|10=
|11= 
|12= 12. [[Ferdinand I of León]]
|13= 13. [[Sancha of León]]
|14=
|15=
}}

==See also==
{{Commons|Afonso Henriques}}
*[[Gallaecia]]
*[[Galicia (Spain)|Galicia]]
*[[History of Portugal]]
*[[Timeline of Portuguese history]]

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Bibliography==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book|title = Sepulcros de la Casa Real de Castilla|last =Arco y Garay|first= Ricardo del|publisher =  Instituto Jerónimo Zurita. Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Científicas|year = 1954|location = Madrid|language=ES|oclc = 11366237|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|title = Astúrias e Portugal. Relações históricas e culturais. Actas do Colóquio 5 a 7 de Dezembro de 2005|last=Baquero Moreno|first= Humberto|publisher= Academia Portuguesa da História|year =2006|isbn= 972-624-164-2|location= Lisbon|pages= 115–141|language=pt|chapter = Portugal e o reino das Astúrias no período de formação|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|url = http://purl.pt/776/4/hg-2593-v/hg-2593-v_item4/hg-2593-v_PDF/hg-2593-v_PDF_24-C-R0150/hg-2593-v_0000_1-800_t24-C-R0150.pdf|title=Historia Genealógica de la Real Casa Portuguesa|last= Caetano de Souza|first=Antonio|publisher= Lisboa Occidental, na oficina de Joseph Antonio da Sylva|year= 1735|isbn= 978-84-8109-908-9|volume = Vol. I|location=Lisbon|language=pt|ref = harv}}
*{{Cite book|url=http://jovenesmedievalistas.net/archivo/lorca2008/IVSIMPOSIO.pdf|title = Actas IV Simposio Internacional de Jóvenes Medievalistas, Lorca 2008|last = Calderón Medina|first = Inés|publisher= Universidad de Murcia, Sociedad Española de Estudios Medievales, Ayuntamiento de Lorca, et al|year= 2004|isbn= 978-84-8371-801-8|pages = 39–50|language= es|chapter = La nobleza portuguesa al servicio del rey de León 1157–1187. Pero Pais de Maia y Vasco Fernandes de Soverosa|ref = harv}}
* {{cite book|title = D. Afonso Henriques|last=Freitas do Amaral|first =Diogo|publisher = Bertrand|year = 2000|isbn=972-25-1157-2|location=Lisbon|language =pt|ref=harv|authorlink =Diogo de Freitas do Amaral}}
* {{cite book|title = D. Afonso Henriques|last=Mattoso|first = José|publisher = Temas e Debates|year = 2014|isbn= 978-972-759-911-0|location=Lisbon|language =pt|ref=harv|orig-year=2007|authorlink =José Mattoso}}
* {{cite book|title=The Early History of the House of Savoy: 1000–1233|url=https://archive.org/details/earlyhistoryofho00prevuoft|last=Previte-Orton|first=C.W.|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=1912|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|title= Rainhas medievais de Portugal. Dezassete mulheres, duas dinastias, quatro séculos de História|last=Rodrigues Oliveira|first= Ana|publisher= A esfera dos livros|year= 2010|isbn= 978-989-626-261-7|location = Lisbon|language= PT|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|title = Castilla y León en el siglo XI, estudio del reinado de Fernando I|last = Sánchez Candeira|first = Alfonso|publisher = Real Academia de la Historia|year = 1999|isbn =978-84-8951241-2|editor= Rosa Montero Tejada |location = Madrid|language=ES|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|url=http://hdl.handle.net/10216/18023|title = Linhagens Medievais Portuguesas: Genealogias e Estratégias (1279–1325)|last = Sotto Mayor Pizarro|first = José Augusto|publisher=Doctorate thesis, author's edition|year= 1997|volume= Vol. I|location =Oporto|language = pt|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|title = Linajes nobiliarios de León y Castilla: Siglos IX–XIII|last = Torres Sevilla-Quiñones de León|first=Margarita Cecilia|publisher = Junta de Castilla y León, Consejería de educación y cultura|year = 1999|isbn =  84-7846-781-5|location= Salamanca|language=es|ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou|[[Portuguese House of Burgundy|House of Burgundy]]||1106, 1109 or 1111|6 December|1185|[[House of Capet]]}}
{{s-reg}}
{{s-new|reason=Independence from [[Kingdom of León|León]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[King of Portugal]]|years=1139–1185}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Sancho I of Portugal|Sancho I]]}}
{{s-reg|other}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Henry, Count of Portugal|Henry]] and [[Theresa, Countess of Portugal|Teresa]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Count of Portugal]]|years=1112–1139|regent1=[[Theresa, Countess of Portugal|Teresa]] |years1=1112–1126}}
{{s-non|reason=Independence}}
{{s-end}}

{{Portal bar|Biography|Portugal|Monarchy|Middle Ages|Christianity|War}}
{{Authority control}}
{{Counts of Portugal}}
{{Monarchs of Portugal}}
{{House of Burgundy-Portugal}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Afonso 01 Of Portugal}}
[[Category:Portuguese Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic monarchs]]
[[Category:Portuguese monarchs]]
[[Category:Portuguese people of French descent]]
[[Category:House of Burgundy-Portugal]]
[[Category:People of the Reconquista]]
[[Category:Date of birth unknown]]
[[Category:1106 births]]
[[Category:1109 births]]
[[Category:1111 births]]
[[Category:1185 deaths]]
[[Category:12th-century Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Christians of the Second Crusade]]
[[Category:Counts of Portugal (Asturias-León)]]
[[Category:County of Portugal]]
[[Category:12th-century Portuguese monarchs]]
[[Category:Portuguese revolutionaries]]
[[Category:Founding monarchs]]
[[Category:People from Guimarães]]</text>
      <sha1>65r37mljgmbfk2piqceyv0h22kezzgj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
