  <page>
    <title>Amalasuntha</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1655</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939589528</id>
      <parentid>939589454</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-07T12:13:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mnemosientje</username>
        <id>13563091</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Personal life */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Ostrogoth queen}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2019}}
{{Infobox royalty
|birth_date={{circa|lk=no|495}}
|death_date={{death year and age|535|495}}
|father=[[Theoderic the Great]]
|mother=[[Audofleda]]
|spouse=Traguilla&lt;br /&gt;[[Eutharic]]
|issue=[[Athalaric]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Matasuntha]]
|dynasty=[[Amali dynasty|Amali]]
}}

'''Amalasuntha'''&lt;ref&gt;The name is also spelled '''Amalasuentha''', '''Amalaswintha''', '''Amalasuintha''', '''Amalswinthe''', '''Amalasontha''' and '''Amalsenta'''.&lt;/ref&gt; ({{circa|495}}{{snd}}30 April 534/535) ruled the [[Ostrogoths]] as [[regent]] during the minority of her son from 526 to 534 and then as [[queen regnant]] from 534 to 535. She was the youngest daughter of [[Theoderic the Great]],&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Amalasuntha|url=http://www.oxfordreference.com/view/10.1093/acref/9780195046526.001.0001/acref-9780195046526-e-0199|isbn=978-0-19-518792-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and firmly believed in the upholding of Roman virtues and values. She is best known for her diplomatic relationship with [[Justinian I]], who invaded Italy in response to her assassination.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt;

== Personal life ==
[[File:Ritratto femminile di tipo ariadne-amalasunta, 480-525 dc ca, da s.m. ai monti (musei capitolini).jpg|upright|thumb|Bust at the [[Capitoline Museums]] assumed to depict either Queen Amalasuntha or [[Empress Ariadne]]]]
In 515, Amalasuntha married [[Eutharic]] ({{circa|lk=no|480}}{{snd}}522), an Ostrogoth noble of the old [[Amali dynasty]] who had been previously living in the [[Visigothic Kingdom#Arian Kingdom of Hispania|Arian Kingdom of Hispania]]. Her husband was the son of Widerich (born {{circa|lk=no|450}}), grandson of Berismund (born {{circa|lk=no|410}}), and great-grandson of [[Thorismund]] (died after 400), [[Ostrogoths#Ostrogothic rulers|king of the Ostrogoths]] {{circa|lk=no|400}}. It was important to Amalasuntha's father, [[Theoderic the Great]], that she marry into a legitimate royal family, lest her own family's legitimacy be questioned.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;

She was very much an intellectual, and was well known for her extensive knowledge and reading, which included fluency in Latin, Greek and [[Gothic language|Gothic]]. In addition, she was a student of philosophy and was said to possess the wisdom of [[Solomon]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Vitiello|first=Massimiliano|date=2006|title=&quot;Nourished at the Breast of Rome&quot;: The Queens of Ostrogothic Italy and the Education of the Roman Elite|url=http://www.rhm.uni-koeln.de/149/Vitiello.pdf|journal=Rheinisches Museum für Philologie |volume=149|doi=|pmid=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Amalasuntha was also described in her day as possessing all of the central [[Virtue#Roman_virtues|Roman virtues]] expected of a noble woman: happiness, fertility, and patience, although more emphasis was placed on her virtues within the political realm versus the feminine, something that separates her from other Ostrogoth princesses.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt; Like most Ostrogoths, Amalasuntha was an [[Arian Christian]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.thoughtco.com/amalasuntha-3525248|title=Amalasuntha, Queen of the Ostrogoths|website=ThoughtCo}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rule==
[[File:Diptych Rufus Gennadius Probus Orestes VandA 139-1866.jpg|thumb|[[Consular diptych]] of Rufius Gennadius Probus Orestes, [[Victoria and Albert museum]]. Portraits of Amalasuntha and her son Athalaric are above the inscription, flanking the cross.]]
Eutharic died, apparently in the early years of his marriage to Amalasuntha, leaving her with two children, [[Athalaric]] and [[Matasuntha]] ({{circa|lk=no|517}}{{snd}}after 550). On the death of her father on 30 August 526,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=_7EwDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA225 | last=Wolfram | first=Herwig | year=1988 | title=History of the Goths | place=Berkeley and Los Angeles| publisher=University of California Press | isbn= 0-520-05259-5|p=225}}&lt;/ref&gt; her son succeeded him at the age of ten,&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Grierson|first=P.|date=1941|title=Election and Inheritance in Early Germanic Kingship|jstor=3020840|journal=The Cambridge Historical Journal |volume=7 |issue=1|doi=|pmid=}}&lt;/ref&gt; but she held the power as [[regent]] for her son. Her tremendous influence in her position as regent can be seen in a [[diptych]] of [[Rufius Gennadius Probus Orestes]] she appears in alongside her son, Athalaric, in 530.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; Deeply imbued with the old Roman culture, she gave to that son's education a more refined and literary turn than suited the ideas of her Gothic subjects. Conscious of her unpopularity she banished &amp;mdash; and afterwards put to death &amp;mdash; three Gothic nobles whom she suspected of conspiring against her rule. At the same time, she opened negotiations with the [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine emperor]] [[Justinian I]] with the view of removing herself and the Gothic treasure to [[Constantinople]]. Her son's death on 2 October 534 initially made little apparent change in the state of affairs.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;&gt;{{EB1911|inline=y|wstitle=Amalasuntha|volume=1|page=777}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After Athalaric's death, Amalasuntha became queen, ruling alone only for a short while before making her cousin [[Theodahad]] co-ruler (not, as sometimes stated, her husband, for his wife was still living),&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; with the intent of strengthening her position. Theodahad was a prominent leader of the Gothic military aristocracy, the very group that so opposed her pro-Roman stances. Amalasuntha believed this pairing would help to make supporters out of her harshest critics.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; The choice was unfortunate, for Theodahad fostered the disaffection of the Goths, and either by his orders or with his permission, Amalasuntha was imprisoned on the island of Martana, located in [[Lake Bolsena|lake of Bolsena]] in northern Lazio, where on 30 April in the spring of 534/535 she was murdered in her bath.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

==Death==
{{seealso|Gothic War (535–554)}}
The death of Amalasuntha gave [[Justinian I]] a reason to go to war with the Ostrogoths and attempt to take Italy. According to the Eastern Roman historian [[Procopius]], it is believed that Amalasuntha and Justinian I had a very close diplomatic relationship. More specifically, Procopius believed that Amalasuntha was thinking about handing over Italy to Justinian around the time of her death.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Sarantis|first=Alexander|date=2009|title=War and Diplomacy in Pannonia and the Northwest Balkans during the Reign of Justinian: The Gepid Threat and Imperial Responses|jstor=41219761|journal=Dumbarton Oaks Papers |volume=63|doi=|pmid=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly after Amalasuntha's murder, Theodahad was replaced by [[Vitiges|Witigis]], Amalasuntha's son-in-law. With the people's support, Witigis had Theodahad put to death.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;

== Sources ==
The letters of [[Cassiodorus]], chief minister and literary adviser of Amalasuntha, and the histories of [[Procopius]] and [[Jordanes]], give us our chief information as to the character of Amalasuntha.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; Cassiodorus was a part of a greater pro-Roman party that desired to Romanize the traditional Ostrogothic kingship, further evidence of the pro-Roman circle that Amalasuntha surrounded herself with.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Foote|first=David|date=2009|title=Reviewed Work: Il principe, il filosofo, il guerriero: Lineamenti di pensiero politico nell'Italia ostrogota by Massimiliano Vitiell|jstor=42586872|journal=Mediaevistik |volume=22|doi=|pmid=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
[[File:Nuremberg chronicles f 143r 3.jpg|thumb|upright|''Amalasiuntha regina'' – woodcut from the [[Nuremberg Chronicle]] (1493)]]
The life of Amalasuntha was made the subject of a [[tragedy]], the first play written by the young [[Carlo Goldoni]] and presented at [[Milan]] in 1733.

[[Romania|Romanian]] [[poet]] [[George Coșbuc]] wrote a poem entitled ''The Queen Of The Ostrogoths'' in which Amalasuntha speaks to Theodahad (named Teodat in the poem) shortly before he kills her.

[[Asteroid]] [[650 Amalasuntha]] is named in her honour.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmadel2012&quot;&gt;{{Citation | first1    = Lutz D. | last1     = Schmadel| title     = Dictionary of Minor Planet Names| publisher = Springer| page      = 63| year      = 2012| isbn      = 3642297188| url       = https://books.google.com/books?id=aeAg1X7afOoC&amp;pg=PA63| postscript= .}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}
{{s-start}}
{{s-reg}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Athalaric]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Queen of the Ostrogoths]]|years=534-535}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Theodahad ]]}}
{{s-end}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Year of birth unknown]]
[[Category:535 deaths]]
[[Category:6th-century women rulers]]
[[Category:Ostrogothic women]]
[[Category:Ostrogothic kings]]
[[Category:Amali dynasty]]
[[Category:6th-century monarchs in Europe]]
[[Category:6th-century murdered monarchs]]
[[Category:6th-century Ostrogothic people]]
[[Category:6th-century Italian women]]
[[Category:Christians of Late Antiquity]] 
[[Category:Christians of the Middle Ages]] 
[[Category:6th-century Christians]] 
[[Category:6th-century scholars]] 
[[Category:Women scholars and academics]]
[[Category:Scholars of Latin literature]]
[[Category:Scholars of Greek language]]
[[Category:Queens regnant]]</text>
      <sha1>6y395zgcwxfsivato3ijt70pscq7zo5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
