  <page>
    <title>Age of consent</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1653</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942200741</id>
      <parentid>942078632</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-23T06:49:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Crossroads</username>
        <id>34413366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Undid revision 942078632 by [[Special:Contributions/2001:8003:2601:3300:548:6B82:5088:A1A7|2001:8003:2601:3300:548:6B82:5088:A1A7]] ([[User talk:2001:8003:2601:3300:548:6B82:5088:A1A7|talk]]) unexplained formatting change</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Minimum age considered to be legally competent for sexual activities}}
{{distinguish-otheruses2|Marriageable age|Age of consent}}
{{pp-move-indef|small=yes}}
&lt;!--I shall te This page has been automatically assigned the correct protection templates by [[User:Lowercase sigmabot]]. If the protection templates are wrong, please fix them. Thanks. --&gt;
{{Sex and the Law}}
{{Youth rights sidebar}}
The '''age of consent''' is the age at which a person is considered to be [[legally competent]] to [[consent]] to [[Human sexual activity|sexual acts]]. Consequently, an adult who engages in sexual activity with a person younger than the age of consent cannot claim that the sexual activity was [[Consent|consensual]], and such sexual activity may be considered [[child sexual abuse]] or [[statutory rape]]. The person below the minimum age is regarded as the victim and their sex partner is regarded as the offender, unless both are underage. The purpose of setting an age of consent is to protect an underage person from sexual advances.

The term ''age of consent'' rarely appears in legal [[statute]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;waites&quot;&gt;{{cite book| last=Waites| first=Matthew| title=The Age of Consent: Young People, Sexuality and Citizenship| publisher=Palgrave Macmillan| year=2005| isbn=1-4039-2173-3| oclc=238887395}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=August 2017}} Generally, a law will instead establish the age below which it is illegal to engage in sexual activity with that person. It has sometimes been used with other meanings, such as the age at which a person becomes competent to consent to [[marriageable age|marriage]],&lt;ref&gt;''Oxford English Dictionary'', entry for &quot;age of consent&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; but the meaning given above is the one now generally understood. It should not be confused with other laws regarding age minimums including, but not limited to, the [[age of majority]], [[defense of infancy|age of criminal responsibility]], [[voting age]], [[Legal drinking age|drinking age]], and [[List of countries by minimum driving age|driving age]].

Age of consent laws vary widely from jurisdiction to jurisdiction,&lt;ref name=&quot;waites&quot; /&gt; though most jurisdictions set the age of consent in the range 14 to 18. The laws may also vary by the type of sexual act, the gender of the participants or other considerations, such as involving a [[position of trust]]; some jurisdictions may also make allowances for minors engaged in sexual acts with each other, rather than a single age. Charges and penalties resulting from a breach of these laws may range from a [[misdemeanor]], such as ''corruption of a minor'', to what is popularly called ''statutory rape''.

There are many &quot;grey areas&quot; in this area of law, some regarding unspecific and untried legislation, others brought about by debates regarding changing societal attitudes, and others due to conflicts between [[federal law|federal]] and [[state law|state]] laws. These factors all make age of consent an often confusing subject, and a topic of highly charged debates.&lt;ref name=&quot;waites&quot; /&gt;

== Age of consent by continent ==
{{main|List of countries by age of consent}}
[[File:Age of Consent - Global.svg|alt=|thumb|Age of consent for heterosexual sex in various countries
CN=#ff7f00 | JP=#1f78b4 | DE=#33a02c | GB=#e31a1c | FR=#fdbf6f | IN=#33a02c | IT=#e31a1c | BR=#ff7f00 | CA=#33a02c | KR=#cab2d6 | RU=#e31a1c | ES=#e31a1c | ID=#33a02c | NL=#e31a1c | TR=#33a02c | CH=#e31a1c | SA=#fdbf6f | SE=#fdbf6f | NG=#33a02c | PL=#fdbf6f | AR=#33a02c | BE=#e31a1c | VE=#e31a1c | NO=#e31a1c | AT=#e31a1c | IR=#fdbf6f | TH=#33a02c | AE=#33a02c | CO=#ff7f00 | ZA=#e31a1c | DK=#fdbf6f | MY=#e31a1c | SG=#e31a1c | IL=#e31a1c | PH=#33a02c | EG=#33a02c | HK=#a6cee3 | FI=#e31a1c | CL=#33a02c | PK=#e31a1c | IE=#fb9a99 | GR=#fdbf6f | PT=#ff7f00 | IQ=#33a02c | KZ=#e31a1c | DZ=#e31a1c | QA=#e31a1c | CZ=#fdbf6f | PE=#33a02c | RO=#fdbf6f | NZ=#e31a1c | VN=#e31a1c | BD=#ff7f00 | KW=#fdbf6f | AO=#e31a1c | HU=#ff7f00 | UA=#e31a1c | MA=#33a02c | PR=#e31a1c | EC=#ff7f00 | SK=#fdbf6f | CU=#e31a1c | SD=#6a3d9a | OM=#33a02c | BY=#e31a1c | AZ=#e31a1c | LK=#e31a1c | MM=#ff7f00 | LU=#e31a1c | DO=#33a02c | UZ=#e31a1c | KE=#33a02c | GT=#33a02c | UY=#33a02c | HR=#fdbf6f | BG=#ff7f00 | MO=#ff7f00 | ET=#33a02c | LB=#33a02c | CR=#33a02c | SI=#fdbf6f | PA=#33a02c | LT=#e31a1c | TZ=#33a02c | TM=#e31a1c | TN=#33a02c | RS=#ff7f00 | LY=#e31a1c | GH=#e31a1c | YE=#FEEBE2 | CD=#33a02c | JO=#e31a1c | CI=#33a02c | BH=#a6cee3 | BO=#33a02c | CM=#a6cee3 | LV=#e31a1c | PY=#ff7f00 | TT=#33a02c | UG=#33a02c | ZM=#e31a1c | EE=#ff7f00 | SV=#33a02c | CY=#fb9a99 | AF=#e31a1c | HN=#ff7f00 | NP=#e31a1c | BA=#ff7f00 | GA=#33a02c | KP=#fdbf6f | BN=#e31a1c | MZ=#e31a1c | IS=#fdbf6f | KH=#fdbf6f | GQ=#33a02c | PG=#fb9a99 | GE=#e31a1c | BW=#33a02c | SN=#e31a1c | ZW=#e31a1c | CG=#33a02c | JM=#e31a1c | NA=#e31a1c | AL=#ff7f00 | TD=#e31a1c | BF=#33a02c | MU=#e31a1c | MN=#e31a1c | ML=#fdbf6f | NI=#33a02c | LA=#fdbf6f | MK=#ff7f00 | SS=#33a02c | AM=#e31a1c | MG=#ff7f00 | MT=#e31a1c | BJ=#e31a1c | TJ=#e31a1c | HT=#33a02c | BS=#e31a1c | NE=#a6cee3 | MD=#e31a1c | RW=#33a02c | KG=#e31a1c | KOSOVO=#e31a1c | MC=#fdbf6f | GN=#fdbf6f | LI=#e31a1c | MW=#e31a1c | BM=#e31a1c | SR=#e31a1c | MR=#33a02c | TL=#ff7f00 | SL=#33a02c | ME=#ff7f00 | TG=#fdbf6f | FJ=#e31a1c | SZ=#33a02c | BB=#e31a1c | ER=#33a02c | AD=#ff7f00 | CW=#fdbf6f | GY=#e31a1c | MV=#FEEBE2 | BI=#33a02c | AW=#fdbf6f | LR=#33a02c | LS=#ff7f00 | BT=#33a02c | CV=#e31a1c | SM=#33a02c | CF=#33a02c | BZ=#e31a1c | DJ=#33a02c | SC=#fdbf6f | LC=#e31a1c | SO=#33a02c | AG=#e31a1c | GW=#e31a1c | GM=#33a02c | WS=#e31a1c | VU=#33a02c | KM=#fdbf6f | DM=#e31a1c | ST=#e31a1c | KI=#33a02c | TV=#33a02c | SY=#fdbf6f | TW=#e31a1c | VA=#33a02c |
{{legend|#FEF592|12}}
{{legend|#7FFFD4|13}}
{{legend|#00CED1|14}}
{{legend|#1E90FF|15}}
{{legend|#0000CD|16}}
{{legend|#808000|17}}
{{legend|#32CD32|18}}
{{legend|#006400|19}}
{{legend|#EE82EE|20 (void at present)}}
{{legend|#9400D3|21 (void at present)}}
{{legend|#DAA520|varies by state/province/region/territory (void at present)}}
{{legend|#FF1493|must be married}}
{{legend|#808080|no law (void at present)}}
{{legend|#D3D3D3|no data available / other}}]]

===Africa===
* [[Ages of consent in Africa]]

===Americas===
* [[Ages of consent in North America]]
** [[Ages of consent in the United States]]
* [[Ages of consent in South America]]

===Asia===
* [[Ages of consent in Asia]]

===Europe===
* [[Ages of consent in Europe]]

===Oceania===
* [[Ages of consent in Oceania]]

==History and social attitudes==

===Traditional attitudes===
In traditional societies, the age of consent for a sexual union was a matter for the family to decide, or a tribal custom. In most cases, this coincided with signs of [[puberty]], [[menstruation]] for a woman, and pubic hair for a man.&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedia of Children and Childhood in History and Society, A-Ar, Age of Consent&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.faqs.org/childhood/A-Ar/Age-of-Consent.html |title= Encyclopedia of Children and Childhood in History and Society |website=faqs.org |publisher = Internet FAQ Archives |access-date = 25 August 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080928120836/http://www.faqs.org/childhood/A-Ar/Age-of-Consent.html |archive-date=28 September 2008 |first=Vern |last=Bullough}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ancient Greek poet [[Hesiod]] in ''[[Works and Days]]'' (c. 700&amp;nbsp;BC) suggests that a man should marry around the age of thirty, and that he should take a wife who is five years past puberty.

Reliable data for ages at marriage is scarce. In England, for example, the only reliable data in the early modern period comes from property records made after death. Not only were the records relatively rare, but not all bothered to record the participants' ages, and it seems that the more complete the records are, the more likely they are to reveal young marriages. Modern historians have sometimes shown reluctance to accept evidence of young ages of marriage, dismissing it as a 'misreading' by a later copier of the records.&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedia of Children and Childhood in History and Society, A-Ar, Age of Consent&quot;/&gt;

In the 12th century, [[Gratian (jurist)|Gratian]], the influential founder of [[canon law]] in [[medieval]] Europe, accepted the age of puberty for marriage to be around twelve for girls and around fourteen for boys but acknowledged consent to be meaningful if both children were older than seven years of age.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://faculty.cua.edu/Pennington/Canon%20Law/marriagelaw.htm |first=John |last=Noonan |date=1967 |website=CUA.edu |title=MARRIAGE CANONS from THE DECRETUM OF GRATIAN—BOOK FOUR—TITLE I—Betrothals and Marriages—C3 |quote=If one over the age of seven takes a prepubescent wife of less than seven and transfers her to his house, such a contract gives rise to the impediment of public propriety. |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160117042750/http://faculty.cua.edu/pennington/Canon%20Law/marriagelaw.htm |archive-date=17 January 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; There were authorities that said that consent could take place earlier. Marriage would then be valid as long as neither of the two parties annulled the marital agreement before reaching puberty, or if they had already consummated the marriage. Judges sometimes honored marriages based on mutual consent at ages younger than&amp;nbsp;seven: in contrast to established canon, there are recorded marriages of two- and three-year-olds.&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedia of Children and Childhood in History and Society, A-Ar, Age of Consent&quot;/&gt;

The first ''recorded'' age-of-consent law dates from 1275 in England; as part of its provisions on rape, the [[Statute of Westminster 1275]] made it a misdemeanor to &quot;ravish&quot; a &quot;maiden within age,&quot; whether with or without her consent. The phrase &quot;within age&quot; was later interpreted by jurist Sir [[Edward Coke]] (England, 17th century) as meaning the age of marriage, which at the time was twelve years of age.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephen Robertson, University of Sydney, Australia&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Robertson|first=Stephen|publisher=University of Sydney, Australia|url=http://chnm.gmu.edu/cyh/teaching-modules/230|title=Children and Youth in History &amp;#124; Age of Consent Laws|website=Chnm.gmu.edu|access-date=30 June 2010|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100627095601/http://chnm.gmu.edu/cyh/teaching-modules/230|archive-date=27 June 2010|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The American colonies followed the English tradition, and the law was more of a guide. For example, Mary Hathaway (Virginia, 1689) was only nine when she was married to William Williams.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/958061287|title=By birth or consent: children, law, and the Anglo-American revolution in authority.|last=Brewer|first=Holly|publisher=University of North Carolina Press|year=2012|isbn=0807829501|location=Chapel Hill, NC|pages=288}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sir Edward Coke &quot;made it clear that the marriage of girls under 12 was normal, and the age at which a girl who was a wife was eligible for a [[dower]] from her husband's estate was 9 even though her husband be only four years old.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedia of Children and Childhood in History and Society, A-Ar, Age of Consent&quot;/&gt;

In the 16th century, a small number of Italian and German states set the minimum age for sexual intercourse for girls, setting it at twelve years. Towards the end of the 18th century, other European countries also began to enact similar laws. The first French Constitution of 1791 established the minimum age at eleven years. Portugal, Spain, Denmark and the Swiss cantons initially set the minimum age at ten to twelve years.&lt;ref name=&quot;chnm.gmu.edu&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://chnm.gmu.edu/cyh/teaching-modules/230|title = Children and Youth in History—Age of Consent Laws|publisher = George Mason University|access-date = 29 June 2015|last = Robertson|first = Stephen}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Age of consent laws were, historically, difficult to follow and enforce: legal norms based on ''age'' were not, in general, common until the 19th century, because clear proof of exact age and precise date of birth were often unavailable.&lt;ref name=&quot;chnm.gmu.edu&quot;/&gt;

In [[Christianity|Christian]] societies, [[fornication|sex outside marriage]] was forbidden. Older children were themselves often punished for being complicit in sexual interaction with an adult.{{citation needed|date=July 2016}} Western Christianity also deemed that children were born into the [[original sin]], and, as such, were perceived as inherently immoral.&lt;ref name=&quot;aic&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aic.gov.au/media_library/publications/special/007/Historical-review-sexual-offence-child-sexual-abuse.pdf|title=Historical review of sexual offence and child sexual abuse legislation in Australia: 1788–2013|publisher=Australian Institute of Criminology|last1=Boxall|first1=Hayley|last2=Tomison|first2=Adam M.|last3=Hulme|first3=Shann|date=2014|access-date=25 August 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150412095850/http://aic.gov.au/media_library/publications/special/007/Historical-review-sexual-offence-child-sexual-abuse.pdf|archive-date=12 April 2015|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Children had very few rights and were considered the [[wikt:chattel|chattel]] of the father.&lt;ref name=&quot;aic&quot;/&gt; From the late 18th century, and especially in the 19th century, attitudes started to change. By the mid-19th century there was increased concern over child sexual abuse.&lt;ref name=&quot;aic&quot;/&gt;

===Reforms in the 19th and 20th century===
A general shift in social and legal attitudes toward issues of sex occurred during the modern era. Attitudes on the appropriate age of permission for females to engage in sexual activity drifted toward adulthood. While ages from ten to thirteen years were typically regarded as acceptable ages for sexual consent in [[western world|Western countries]] during the mid-19th century,&lt;ref name=&quot;waites&quot; /&gt; by the end of the 19th century changing attitudes towards sexuality and childhood resulted in the raising of the age of consent.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephen Robertson, University of Sydney, Australia&quot;/&gt;

[[File:William Thomas Stead.jpg|thumb|200 px|Several articles written by investigative journalist [[William Thomas Stead]] in the late 19th century on the issue of [[child prostitution]] in London led to public outrage and ultimately to the raising of the age of consent to sixteen.]]

English [[common law]] had traditionally set the age of consent within the range of ten to twelve years old, but the [[Offences Against the Person Act 1875]] raised this to thirteen in Great Britain and Ireland. Early feminists of the [[Social Purity movement]], such as [[Josephine Butler]] and others, instrumental in securing the repeal of the [[Contagious Diseases Acts]], began to turn towards the problem of [[child prostitution]] by the end of the 1870s. Sensational media revelations about the scourge of child prostitution in London in the 1880s then caused outrage among the respectable middle-classes, leading to pressure for the age of consent to be raised again.

The investigative journalist [[William Thomas Stead]] of the ''[[Pall Mall Gazette]]'' was pivotal in exposing the problem of child prostitution in the London underworld through a publicity stunt. In 1885 he &quot;purchased&quot; one victim, [[The Eliza Armstrong Case|Eliza Armstrong]], the thirteen-year-old daughter of a [[chimney sweep]], for five pounds and took her to a brothel where she was drugged. He then published a series of four exposés entitled ''[[The Maiden Tribute of Modern Babylon]]'', which shocked its readers with tales of child prostitution and the abduction, procurement, and sale of young English virgins to Continental &quot;pleasure palaces&quot;. The &quot;Maiden Tribute&quot; was an instant sensation with the reading public, and Victorian society was thrown into an uproar about prostitution. Fearing riots on a national scale, the [[Home Secretary]], [[William Vernon Harcourt (politician)|Sir William Harcourt]], pleaded in vain with Stead to cease publication of the articles. A wide variety of reform groups held protest meetings and marched together to [[Hyde Park, London|Hyde Park]] demanding that the age of consent be raised. The government was forced to propose the [[Criminal Law Amendment Act 1885]], which raised the age of consent from thirteen to sixteen and clamped down on prostitution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/0/20097046|title = Child prostitutes: How the age of consent was raised to 16|url-status = dead|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20140727184445/http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/0/20097046|archive-date = 27 July 2014|last = Hogenbloom|first = Melissa|date = 1 November 2012|publisher = BBC History}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States, as late as the 1880s most states set the minimum age at ten to twelve (in Delaware, it was seven in 1895).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=The New York Times|date=October 15, 1895|title=[[:s:The New York Times/1895/10/15/Purity Congress Meets|PURITY CONGRESS MEETS; A Great Gathering for Moral Work in the City of Baltimore. AIMS AND OBJECTS OF THE MOVEMENT Determined to Prevent State Regulation of Vice and to Rescue Fallen Men and Fallen Women.]]|location=BALTIMORE, Oct. 14.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Inspired by the &quot;Maiden Tribute&quot; articles, female reformers in the U.S. initiated their own campaign,&lt;ref&gt;''Delinquent Daughters: Policing and Protecting Adolescent Female Sexuality in the United States, 1885–1920.'' by Mary Odem. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1995. {{ISBN|978-0807863671}}.&lt;/ref&gt; which petitioned legislators to raise the legal minimum age to at least sixteen, with the ultimate goal to raise the age to eighteen. The campaign was successful, with almost all states raising the minimum age to sixteen to eighteen years by 1920.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephen Robertson, University of Sydney, Australia&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://womhist.alexanderstreet.com/teacher/aoc.htm |title=Campaign to Raise the Legal Age of Consent, 1885–1914, Lesson Plan |publisher=Womhist.alexanderstreet.com |access-date=30 June 2010| archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20100617063339/http://womhist.alexanderstreet.com/teacher/aoc.htm| archive-date= 17 June 2010 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[France]], Portugal, Denmark, the [[Swiss canton]]s and other countries, the minimum age was raised to between thirteen and sixteen years in the following decades.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephen Robertson, University of Sydney, Australia&quot;/&gt; Though the original arguments for raising the age of consent were based on morality, since then the ''raison d'être'' of the laws has changed to [[child welfare]] and a so-called right to childhood or innocence.&lt;ref&gt;''The Emergence of a New Taboo: The Desexualization of Youth in Western Societies Since 1800.'' by Martin Killias. European Journal on Criminal Policy and Research Vol.8 (2000). {{ISSN|0928-1371}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

In France, under the [[Napoleonic Code]], the age of consent was set in 1832 at eleven,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichTexte.do?cidTexte=JORFTEXT000000515393|title=Loi du 28 avril 1832 CONTENANT DES MODIFICATIONS AU CODE PENAL ET AU CODE D'INSTRUCTION CRIMINELLE—Legifrance|publisher=|access-date=29 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was raised to thirteen in 1863.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichTexte.do?cidTexte=JORFTEXT000000882642|title=Loi du 13 mai 1863 PORTANT MODIFICATION DE PLUSIEURS ARTICLES DU CODE PENAL—Legifrance|publisher=|access-date=29 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was increased to fifteen in 1945.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichTexte.do?cidTexte=JORFTEXT000000516232|title=Ordonnance n°45-1456 du 2 juillet 1945 ABROGE ET REMPLACE L'ART. 331 (AL. 1 ET 2) DU CODE PENAL, MODIFIE PAR LA LOI DU 13-05-1863 (ATTENTAT A LA PUDEUR CONTRE UN ENFANT DE MOINS DE 15 ANS OU NON EMANCIPE PAR LE MARIAGE POUR LES PLUS DE 15 ANS, PUNI DE RECLUSION)—Legifrance|publisher=|access-date=29 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Spain]], it was set in 1822 at &quot;puberty age&quot;, and changed to twelve in 1870,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://sirio.ua.es/libros/BDerecho/codigo_penal/ima0119.htm|title = Código penal reformado|publisher = |access-date = 29 June 2015|date = 17 June 1870|website = sirio.ua.es}}&lt;/ref&gt; which was kept until 1999, when it became 13;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.boe.es/buscar/doc.php?id=BOE-A-1973-1715|title=BOE.es—Documento BOE-A-1973-1715|author =|date=|work=boe.es|access-date=23 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://noticias.juridicas.com/base_datos/Penal/lo11-1999.html#a2|title=Ley Orgánica 11/1999, de 30 de abril, de modificación del Título VIII del Libro II del Código Penal, aprobado por Ley Orgánica 10/1995, de 23 de noviembre.|work=Noticias Jurídicas|access-date=29 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in 2015 it was raised to 16.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boe.es/boe/dias/2015/03/31/pdfs/BOE-A-2015-3439.pdf|title=Disposición 3439 del BOE núm|date=31 March 2015|access-date=25 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.radiointereconomia.com/2015/07/01/las-20-claves-del-nuevo-codigo-penal/|title=Las 20 claves del nuevo Código Penal|work=radiointereconomia.com|access-date=23 August 2015|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150924084242/http://www.radiointereconomia.com/2015/07/01/las-20-claves-del-nuevo-codigo-penal/|archive-date=24 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.abc.es/videos-espana/20150630/entra-vigor-llamada-mordaza-4330498762001.html|title=Entra en vigor la llamada ley mordaza|author =|date=|work=ABC|access-date=23 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===21st century and present day situation===
In the 21st century, concerns about [[child sex tourism]] and [[commercial sexual exploitation]] of children gained international prominence, and have resulted in legislative changes in several jurisdictions, as well as in the adoption of several international instruments.

The [[Council of Europe]] [[Convention on the Protection of Children against Sexual Exploitation and Sexual Abuse]] ([[Lanzarote]], 25 October 2007), and the [[European Union]]'s ''Directive 2011/92/EU of the European Parliament and of the Council'' of 13 December 2011 on combating the sexual abuse and sexual exploitation of children and child pornography&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2011:335:0001:0014:EN:PDF|title=DIRECTIVE 2011/92/EU OF THE EUROPEAN PARLIAMENT AND OF THE COUNCIL of 13 December 2011 on combating the sexual abuse and sexual exploitation of children and child pornography, and replacing Council Framework Decision 2004/68/JHA|publisher=Official Journal of the European Union|date=13 December 2011|access-date=25 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; were adopted.

The [[Optional Protocol on the Sale of Children, Child Prostitution and Child Pornography]] came into force in 2002.

The [[Protocol to Prevent, Suppress and Punish Trafficking in Persons, especially Women and Children]], which came into force in 2003, prohibits commercial sexual exploitation of children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ohchr.org/EN/ProfessionalInterest/Pages/ProtocolTraffickingInPersons.aspx|title=Protocol to Prevent, Suppress and Punish Trafficking in Persons Especially Women and Children, supplementing the United Nations Convention against Transnational Organized Crime|publisher=[[OHCHR]]|date=15 November 2000|access-date=25 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Council of Europe Convention on Action against Trafficking in Human Beings]] (which came into force in 2008) also deals with commercial sexual exploitation of children.

Several Western countries have raised their ages of consent recently. These include [[Ages of consent in Canada|Canada]] (in 2008—from 14 to 16); and in Europe, [[Ages of consent in Europe#Iceland|Iceland]] (in 2007—from 14 to 15), [[Ages of consent in Europe#Lithuania|Lithuania]] (in 2010—from 14 to 16), [[Ages of consent in Europe#Croatia|Croatia]] (in 2013—from 14 to 15), and [[Ages of consent in Europe#Spain|Spain]] (in 2015—from 13 to 16).

The International Criminal Court Statute does not provide a specific age of consent in its rape/sexual violence statute, but makes reference to sexual acts committed against persons &quot;''incapable of giving genuine consent''&quot;; and the explicative footnote states, &quot;It is understood that a person may be incapable of giving genuine consent if affected by natural, induced or ''age-related incapacity''.&quot; (see note 51)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.icc-cpi.int/NR/rdonlyres/336923D8-A6AD-40EC-AD7B-45BF9DE73D56/0/ElementsOfCrimesEng.pdf|title=Elements of Crimes|publisher=[[International Criminal Court]]|date=2011|access-date=25 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Law===
Sexual relations with a person under the age of consent is a crime in most countries; exceptions to this include Yemen, and Saudi Arabia. Jurisdictions use a variety of terms for the offense, including ''[[child sexual abuse]]'', ''[[statutory rape]]'', ''illegal [[carnal knowledge]]'', ''corruption of a minor'',&lt;ref name=&quot;waites&quot; /&gt; besides others.

The enforcement practices of age-of-consent laws vary depending on the social sensibilities of the particular culture (see above). Often, enforcement is not exercised to the letter of the law, with legal action being taken only when a sufficiently socially-unacceptable age gap exists between the two individuals, or if the perpetrator is in a position of power over the minor (e.g. a teacher, minister, or doctor). The [[sex]] of each participant can also influence perceptions of an individual's guilt and therefore enforcement.&lt;ref name=&quot;waites&quot; /&gt;

===Age===
The threshold age for engaging in sexual activity varies between jurisdictions. Most jurisdictions have set a fixed age of consent.&lt;ref name=&quot;SOA2003&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts2003/pdf/ukpga_20030042_en.pdf|title=Sexual Offences Act 2003 (See Sections 9 to 12)|publisher=Published by the Government of the United Kingdom, (Office of Public Sector Information)|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, some jurisdictions permit sex with a person after the onset of their [[puberty]], such as [[Ages of consent in Asia#Yemen|Yemen]], but only in marriage. Ages can also vary based on the type of calendar used, such as the [[Lunar calendar]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ukm.my/ijwas/images/koleksi_jurnal_pdf/vol4_n1_2012a/3_Pesalah_KanakKanak_Article.pdf|title=Child offenders in Iran: Legal Analysis on the Age of Criminal Responsibility|publisher=Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia|last1=Mousavi|first1=Shohreh|last2=Shapiee|first2=Rohimi|last3=Nordin|first3=Rohaida|date=30 June 2012|access-date=25 August 2015|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304193702/http://www.ukm.my/ijwas/images/koleksi_jurnal_pdf/vol4_n1_2012a/3_Pesalah_KanakKanak_Article.pdf|archive-date=4 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; how [[February 29#Births|birth dates]] in [[leap year]]s are handled, or even the method by which birth date is calculated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
| url        = http://www.ilpa.org.uk/data/resources/13266/ILPA-Age-Dispute-Report.pdf
| title      = When is a child not a child? Asylum, age disputes and the process of age assessment
| last       = Crawley
| first      = Heaven
| date       = May 2007
| website    = ILPA
| publisher  = Immigration Law Practitioners' Association
| access-date = 8 June 2014
| page       = 45
| isbn       = 1901833135
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Defenses and exceptions===
The age of consent is a legal barrier to the minor's ability to consent and therefore obtaining consent is not in general a defense to having sexual relations with a person under the prescribed age, for example:
; Reasonable belief that the victim is over the age of consent: In some jurisdictions it is a defense if the accused can show that he or she reasonably believed the victim was over the age of consent. However, where such a defense is provided, it normally applies only when the victim is close to the age of consent or the accused can show [[due diligence]] in determining the age of the victim (e.g. an underage person who used a fake identification document claiming to be of legal age).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author =Larry W. Myers | title=Reasonable Mistake of Age: A Needed defense to Statutory Rape| journal= Michigan Law Review| volume= 64| issue=1|year=1965|pages=105–136 | doi=10.2307/1287118|publisher=The Michigan Law Review Association|jstor=1287118}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; Marriage: In various jurisdictions, age of consent laws do not apply if the parties are legally married to each other.
; {{visible anchor|Close-in-age exemptions}}: Some jurisdictions have laws explicitly allowing sexual acts with minors under the age of consent if their partner is close in age to them. For instance, in [[Canada]], the age of consent is 16, but there are two close-in-age exemptions: sex with minors aged 14–15 is permitted if the partner is less than five years older, and sex with minors aged 12–13 is permitted if the partner is less than two years older.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/canada-s-age-of-consent-raised-by-2-years-1.754941|title=Canada's age of consent raised by 2 years|publisher=CBC News|date=2008-05-01|access-date=22 March 2009| archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20090320002644/http://www.cbc.ca/canada/story/2008/05/01/crime-bill.html| archive-date= 20 March 2009 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other countries state that the sexual conduct with the minor is not to be punished if the partners are of a similar age and development: for instance, the age of consent in [[Finland]] is 16, but the law states that the act will not be punished if &quot;there is no great difference in the ages or the mental and physical maturity of the persons involved&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.finlex.fi/en/laki/kaannokset/1889/en18890039 |title=FINLEX ®—Translations of Finnish acts and decrees: 39/1889 English |publisher=Finlex.fi |date=2009-05-29 |access-date=14 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another approach takes the form of a stipulation that sexual intercourse between a minor and an adult is legal under the condition that the latter does not exceed a certain age. For example, the age of consent in the US state of [[Delaware]] is 18, but it is allowed for teenagers aged 16 and 17 to engage in sexual intercourse as long as the older partner is younger than 30.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | work = Delaware Code | title = TITLE 11, Crimes and Criminal Procedure, Delaware Criminal Code, CHAPTER 5. SPECIFIC OFFENSES, Subchapter II. Offenses Against the Person, Subpart A. Assaults and Related Offenses (see § 768 and § 770) | url = http://delcode.delaware.gov/title11/c005/sc02/index.shtml#768}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Slovenia]], the age of consent is 15, but the law requires that there be &quot;a marked discrepancy between the maturity of the perpetrator and that of the victim&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dtxtq4w60xqpw.cloudfront.net/sites/all/files/docpdf/slovenia.pdf |title=Republic of Slovenia—Legislation against child sex tourism |publisher=[[WTO]] |access-date=25 August 2015 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304043215/http://dtxtq4w60xqpw.cloudfront.net/sites/all/files/docpdf/slovenia.pdf |archive-date=4 March 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
; Homosexual and heterosexual age discrepancies: Some jurisdictions, such as [[the Bahamas]], UK overseas territory of the [[Cayman Islands]], [[Chile]], [[Paraguay]] and [[Suriname]] have a higher age of consent for [[Homosexuality|same-sex]] sexual activity. However, such discrepancies are increasingly being challenged. Within [[Bermuda]] for example (since 1 November, 2019 under section 177 of the Criminal Code Act 1907) the age of consent for vaginal and oral sex is 16, but for anal sex it is 18. In Canada, the United Kingdom and Western Australia, for example, the age of consent was originally 21 for same-sex sexual activity between males (with no laws regarding [[lesbian]] sexual activities), while it was 16 for [[Heterosexuality|heterosexual]] sexual activity; this is no longer the case and the age of consent for all sexual activity is 16.&lt;ref&gt;''The Causes and Cures of Criminality'' Eysenck, Hans 1989 Plenum Press New York page 229&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2019, the Canadian Government repealed the section of the Criminal Code that set a higher age of consent for anal intercourse.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite act |type=bill |date=21 June 2019 |legislature=Parliament of Canada |title=Bill C-75 |url=https://www.parl.ca/DocumentViewer/en/42-1/bill/C-75/royal-assent}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; Gender-age differentials: In some jurisdictions (such as [[Indonesia]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Indonesia&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.interpol.int/Public/Children/SexualAbuse/NationalLaws/csaIndonesia.asp |archive-url=http://arquivo.pt/wayback/20080229151529/http://www.interpol.int/Public/Children/SexualAbuse/NationalLaws/csaIndonesia.asp |url-status=dead |archive-date=29 February 2008 |title=Sexual Offences Laws – Indonesia |publisher=Interpol |access-date=5 September 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;), there are different ages of consent for heterosexual sexual activity that are based on the gender of each person. In countries where there are gender-age differentials, the age of consent may be higher for girls—for example in [[Papua New Guinea]], where the age of consent for heterosexual sex is 16 for girls and 14 for boys,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.paclii.org/pg/LRC/WP_1.htm |title=Law, Ethics and HIV/AIDS: Existing Law of Papua New Guinea |publisher=Paclii.org |access-date=14 January 2013 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120419132305/http://www.paclii.org/pg/LRC/WP_1.htm |archive-date=19 April 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; or they may be higher for males, such as in Indonesia, where males must be 19 years old and females must be 16 years old.&lt;ref name=&quot;Indonesia&quot; /&gt; There are also numerous jurisdictions—such as Kuwait&lt;ref name=&quot;Kuwait&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.unhchr.ch/tbs/doc.nsf/0/2f5665ae20b956cb8025675a0033cafb?Opendocument |title=Summary record of the 488th meeting : Kuwait |publisher=Committee on the Rights of the Child |access-date=5 September 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Palestinian National Authority|the Palestinian Territories]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Palestine&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.law.emory.edu/ifl/legal/palestine.htm |title=Palestinian Territories of West Bank and Gaza Strip – Marriage Age |publisher=Emory Law |access-date=5 September 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;—in which [[Islamic marital jurisprudence|marriage laws]] govern the gender-age differential. In these jurisdictions, it is illegal to have sexual intercourse outside of marriage, so the ''de facto'' age of consent is the marriageable age. In Kuwait, this means that boys must be at least 17 and girls at least 15 years old.
; Position of authority/trust: In most jurisdictions where the age of consent is below 18 (such as England and Wales),&lt;ref name=SOA2003_a&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts2003/pdf/ukpga_20030042_en.pdf |format=PDF|title=Sexual Offences Act 2003 (See Sections 16 to&amp;nbsp;24) |publisher=Published by the Government of the United Kingdom, (Office of Public Sector Information)}}&lt;/ref&gt; in cases where a person aged 18 or older is in a position of trust over a person under 18, the age of consent usually rises to 18 or higher. Examples of such positions of trust include relationships between teachers and students. For example, in England and Wales the age of consent is 16, but if the person is a student of the older person it becomes&amp;nbsp;18.

; Circumstances of the relationship: In several jurisdictions, it is illegal to engage in sexual activity with a person under a certain age under certain circumstances regarding the relationship in question, such as if it involves taking advantage of or corrupting the morals of the young person. For example, while the age of consent is 14 in Germany and 16 in Canada, it is illegal in both countries to engage in sexual activity with a person under 18 if the activity exploits the younger person. Another example is in Mexico, where there is a crime called &quot;estupro&quot; defined as sexual activity with a person over the age of consent but under a certain age limit (generally 18) in which consent of the younger person was obtained through seduction and/or deceit. In Pennsylvania, the age of consent is officially 16, but if the older partner is 18 or older, he/she may still be prosecuted for corruption of minors if he/she corrupts or tends to corrupt the morals of the younger person.

===Extraterritoriality===
{{see also|Child sex tourism#Extraterritorial jurisdiction}}
A growing number of countries have specific [[Extraterritorial jurisdiction|extraterritorial legislation]] that prosecutes their citizens in their homeland should they engage in illicit sexual conduct in a foreign country with children. In 2008, [[ECPAT]] reported that 44 countries had extraterritorial child sex legislation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=What is Child Sex Tourism? - ECPAT International|url=http://www.ecpat.org/wp-content/uploads/legacy/cst_faq_eng.pdf|page=35|publisher=[[ECPAT]]|access-date=12 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, [[PROTECT Act of 2003]], a federal United States law bans sexual activity by its citizens with foreigners or with U.S. citizens from another state, if the partner is under 18 and the activity is illegal under the federal, state, or local law. This applies in cases where any of the partners travels into or out of the United States, or from one state into another, for the purpose of an illegal sexual encounter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/18/2423|title=18 U.S. Code § 2423—Transportation of minors|publisher=Legal Information Institute|access-date=29 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SOLR&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.solresearch.org/~SOLR/rprt/USnatlAoC.asp |title=Research on sex offender laws and their effects on people and society |year=2009 |publisher=SOL Research.org |access-date=23 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other issues==

===Gender of participants===
There is debate as to whether the gender of those involved should lead to different treatment of the sexual encounter, in law or in practice. Traditionally, age of consent laws regarding vaginal intercourse were often meant to protect the chastity of unmarried girls.&lt;ref name=&quot;chnm.gmu.edu&quot;/&gt; Many feminists and social campaigners in the 1970s have objected to the social importance of virginity, and have also attempted to change the stereotypes of female passivity and male aggression; demanding that the law protect children from exploitation regardless of their gender, rather than dealing with concerns of chastity. This has led to gender-neutral laws in many jurisdictions.&lt;ref name=&quot;chnm.gmu.edu&quot;/&gt; On the other hand, there is an opposing view which argues that the act of vaginal intercourse is an &quot;unequal act&quot; for males and females, due to issues such as pregnancy, increased risk of STDs,&lt;ref&gt;UNFPA writes that &quot;Biologically, women's risk of acquiring sexually transmitted infections during unprotected sexual relations is two to four times that of men.&quot;[http://www.unfpa.org/resources/giving-special-attention-girls-and-adolescents]&lt;/ref&gt; and risk of physical injury if the girl is too young and not physically ready. In the US, in ''[[Michael M. v. Superior Court of Sonoma County|Michael M. v. Superior Ct.450 U.S. 464 (1981)]]'' it was ruled that the double standard of offering more legal protection to girls is valid because &quot;the Equal Protection Clause does not mean that the physiological differences between men and women must be disregarded&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/450/464/case.html|title=Michael M. v. Superior Ct. :: 450 U.S. 464 (1981) :: Justia U.S. Supreme Court Center|work=Justia Law|access-date=29 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Traditionally, many age of consent laws dealt primarily with men engaging in sexual acts with underage girls and boys (the latter acts often falling under [[sodomy]] and [[buggery]] laws). This means that in some legal systems, issues of women having sexual contact with underage partners were rarely acknowledged. For example, until 2000, in the UK, before the [[Sexual Offences (Amendment) Act 2000]], there was no statutory age of consent for [[lesbian]] sex.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/1045383.stm|title=BBC News—UK—Q and A: The age of consent|work=BBC News|date=29 November 2000|access-date=29 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[New Zealand]], before 2005, there were no age of consent laws dealing with women having sex with underage boys.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;In respect of sexual conduct with a young person aged under 16, the bill [Crimes Amendment Bill (No 2) which became law in 2005 [http://www.parliament.nz/en-nz/pb/legislation/bills/00DBHOH_BILL5923_1/crimes-amendment-bill-no-2] significantly toughens the law. The loophole protecting women against being charged with sexual offending against children is removed&quot;.{{cite web|url=http://www.parliament.nz/en-nz/pb/debates/debates/47HansD_20050414_00000206/crimes-amendment-bill-no-2-%E2%80%94-second-reading-instruction|title=Crimes Amendment Bill (No 2) — Second Reading, Instruction to Committee, In Committee|date=12 April 2005|website=parliament.nz|access-date=8 June 2015|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150609123151/https://www.parliament.nz/en-nz/pb/debates/debates/47HansD_20050414_00000206/crimes-amendment-bill-no-2-%E2%80%94-second-reading-instruction|archive-date=9 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Previously, in Fiji, male offenders of child sexual abuse could receive up to life imprisonment, whilst female offenders would receive up to seven years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/304495447_Child_Sexual_Abuse_in_Fiji_Authority_Risk_Factors_and_Responses|title=Whitehead, John and Roffee, James. Child sexual abuse in Fiji: Authority, risk factors and responses [online]. Current Issues in Criminal Justice, Vol. 27, No. 3, Mar 2016: [323]-334}}&lt;/ref&gt; Situations like these have been attributed to societal views on traditional [[gender roles]], and to constructs of [[male sexuality]] and [[female sexuality]]; according to E Martellozzo, &quot;[V]iewing females as perpetrators of sexual abuse goes against every stereotype that society has of women: women as mothers and caregivers and not as people who abuse and harm&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cybercrimejournal.com/elenaetal2010ijcc.pdf|title=Online child sexual abuse by female offenders: An Exploratory study|publisher=International Journal of Cyber Criminology|last1=Martellozzo|first1=Elena|last2=Nehring|first2=Daniel|last3=Taylor|first3=Helen|date=2010|access-date=25 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Alissa Nutting]] argues that women are not acknowledged as perpetrators of sex crimes because society does not accept that women have an autonomous sexuality of their own.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cultmagazine.com.au/2014/08/festival-dangerous-ideas-top-10/ |title=CULT Magazine FESTIVAL OF DANGEROUS IDEAS TOP 10—CULT Magazine |work=CULT Magazine |access-date=29 June 2015 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150609123104/http://cultmagazine.com.au/2014/08/festival-dangerous-ideas-top-10/ |archive-date=9 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Marriage and the age of consent===
{{Main article|Marriageable age|Child marriage}}&lt;!-- Please note that this section is a summary of another article and should reflect that article's current state. Do not add any extra information here, rather edit the alternate article and then summarize that article here. --&gt;
The age at which a person can be legally married can differ from the age of consent. In jurisdictions where the marriageable age is lower than the age of consent, those laws usually override the age of consent laws in the case of a married couple where one or both partners are below the age of consent. Some jurisdictions prohibit all sex outside of marriage irrespective of age, as in the case of [[Yemen]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Power |first=Carla |title=Nujood Ali &amp; Shada Nasser win &quot;Women of the Year Fund 2008 Glamour Award&quot; |publisher=Yemen Times |date=12 August 2009 |url=http://www.yementimes.com/DefaultDET.aspx?i=1207&amp;p=report&amp;a=1 |access-date=6 February 2017 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110405190616/http://www.yementimes.com/DefaultDET.aspx?i=1207&amp;p=report&amp;a=1 |archive-date=5 April 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|author =Human Rights Watch| title= World Report 2001|chapter= Yemen: Human Rights Developments | publisher= Human Rights Watch | year=2001 | url= https://www.hrw.org/wr2k1/mideast/yemen.html | access-date=8 April 2010| archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20100615214816/http://www.hrw.org/wr2k1/mideast/yemen.html| archive-date=15 June 2010| url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Prostitution===
{{Main article|Prostitution of children}}&lt;!-- Please note that this section is a summary of another article and should reflect that article's current state. Do not add any extra information here, rather edit the alternate article and then summarize that article here. --&gt;
In many countries, there are specific laws dealing with child prostitution.{{citation needed|date=August 2015}}

===Pornography and 'jailbait' images===
{{Main article|Child pornography|Jailbait images}}&lt;!-- Please note that this section is a summary of another article and should reflect that article's current state. Do not add any extra information here, rather edit the alternate article and then summarize that article here. --&gt;

In some countries, states, or other jurisdictions, the age of consent may be lower than the age at which a person can appear in [[pornography|pornographic]] images and films. In many jurisdictions, the minimum age for participation and even viewing such material is 18. As such, in some jurisdictions, films and images showing individuals under the age of 18, but above the age of consent, that meet the legal definition of [[child pornography]] are prohibited despite the fact that the sexual acts depicted are legal to engage in otherwise under that jurisdiction's age of consent laws. In those cases, it is only the filming of the sex act that is the crime as the act itself would not be considered a sex crime. For example, in the United States under federal law it is a crime to film minors below 18 in sexual acts, even in states where the age of consent is below 18.&lt;ref name=&quot;SOLR&quot; /&gt; In those states, charges such as child pornography can be used to prosecute someone having sex with a minor, who could not otherwise be prosecuted for statutory rape, provided they filmed or photographed the act.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Brilliant |first=Jeremy |title=New Castle detective resigns over child porn charges |url=http://www.wthr.com/Global/story.asp?S=10854092&amp;nav=9Tai |access-date=25 May 2012 |newspaper=wthr.com Eyewitness News |date=August 5, 2009 |location=Henry County |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130524173904/http://www.wthr.com/Global/story.asp?S=10854092&amp;nav=9Tai |archive-date=24 May 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Jailbait images]] can be differentiated from [[child pornography]], as they do not feature minors before the onset of puberty, nor do they contain nudity.&lt;ref name=boost&gt;{{cite news|last=Morris |first=Kevin |title=Anderson Cooper boosts visibility of teen-girl pics |url=http://www.dailydot.com/society/anderson-cooper-reddit-jailbait-traffic/ |access-date=12 June 2014 |newspaper=[[The Daily Dot]] |date=3 October 2011 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304195251/http://www.dailydot.com/society/anderson-cooper-reddit-jailbait-traffic/ |archive-date=4 March 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=AlfonsoIII&gt;{{cite news|last=Alfonso III|first=Fernando|title=A free-speech haven wrestles with violent images|url=http://www.dailydot.com/society/reddit-beatingwomen-misogyny-images/|access-date=12 June 2014|newspaper=[[The Daily Dot]]|date=11 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The images are, however, usually sexualized,&lt;ref name=boost /&gt; often featuring [[Tween (demographic)|tween]] or young teenagers in bikinis, skirts,&lt;ref name=gawk&gt;{{cite news|last=Chen |first=Adrian |title=Unmasking Reddit's Violentacrez, The Biggest Troll on the Web |url=http://gawker.com/5950981/unmasking-reddits-violentacrez-the-biggest-troll-on-the-web |access-date=12 June 2014 |newspaper=[[Gawker]] |date=12 October 2012 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121012213707/http://gawker.com/5950981/unmasking-reddits-violentacrez-the-biggest-troll-on-the-web |archive-date=12 October 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; underwear or lingerie.&lt;ref name=pcmag&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2391317,00.asp |title=Reddit Closes 'Jailbait' Pic Site, Allows Others to Remain |last1=Hachman |first1=Mark |date=August 10, 2011 |work=[[PC Magazine]] |publisher= |access-date=12 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Whether or not these images are legal is debated. When questioned regarding their legality legal analyst [[Jeffrey Toobin]] stated he thought it was not illegal, though legal expert [[Sunny Hostin]] was more skeptical, describing jailbait images as &quot;borderline&quot; child pornography which may be illegal.&lt;ref name=mediaite&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mediaite.com/tv/anderson-cooper-excoriates-reddit-for-creepy-jailbait-section/ |title=Anderson Cooper Excoriates Reddit For 'Creepy' Jailbait Section |last1=Crugnale |first1=James |date=September 30, 2011 |work=[[Mediaite]] |publisher= |access-date=12 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://edition.cnn.com/2012/10/18/us/internet-troll-apology/ |title=Man behind 'Jailbait' posts exposed, loses job |last1=Fitzpatrick |first1=David |last2=Griffin |first2=Drew |date=October 19, 2012 |work=[[CNN]] |publisher= |access-date=12 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Health===
{{See also|Sexual intercourse#Health effects}}
The human [[immune system]] continues to develop after puberty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/524225_4|title=Medscape: Medscape Access|publisher=|access-date=29 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The age of exposure has an influence upon if the immune system can fend off infections in general, and this is also true in the case of some [[Sexually transmitted infection|sexually transmitted diseases]]. For example, a risk factor for [[HPV]] strains causing [[genital wart]]s is sexual debut at a young age;&lt;ref name=&quot;ncbi.nlm.nih.gov&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|pmc=4018629 |title=Men's beliefs about HPV-related disease|journal=Journal of Behavioral Medicine|volume=33|issue=4|pages=274–281|year=2010|author1=Brewer|first1=N. T.|last2=Ng|first2=T. W.|last3=McRee|first3=A. L.|last4=Reiter|first4=P. L.|doi=10.1007/s10865-010-9251-2|pmid=20162346}}&lt;/ref&gt; if this extends to the cancer causing strains, then sexual debut at a young age would potentially also increase risk of persistence of HPV infections that cause the very [[Human papillomavirus#Cancer|HPV induced cancers]] that are being diagnosed in spiking numbers of relatively young people.&lt;ref name=&quot;ncbi.nlm.nih.gov&quot;/&gt;

==Initiatives to change the age of consent==
{{Main article|Age of consent reform}}
Age-of-consent reform refers to the efforts of some individuals or groups, for different reasons, to alter or abolish age-of-consent laws. These efforts advocate positions such as:
* Introductions of close-in-age exceptions.
* Reducing the age-of-consent for homosexual activity to that of heterosexual activity.
* A change in the way that age-of-consent laws are examined in court.
* Either increases in the ages of consent or more severe penalties or both.
* Either decreases in the ages of consent or less severe penalties or both.
* Abolition of the age-of-consent laws either permanently or as a temporary, practical expedient.

==See also==
{{Portal|Human sexuality|Law}}
{{Div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [[Adult film industry regulations]]
* [[Age disparity in sexual relationships]]
* [[Age of accountability]]
* [[Age of candidacy]]
* [[Age of Consent Act, 1891]] (British India)
* [[Age of consent reform (UK)]]
* [[Age of majority]]
* [[Age of reason (canon law)]]
* [[Child sexual abuse]]
* [[Comprehensive sex education]]
* [[Convention on the Rights of the Child]]
* [[Emancipation of minors]]
* [[Fitness to plead]], ''law of England and Wales''
* [[French petition against age of consent laws]]
* [[Legal age]]
* [[Mature minor doctrine]]
* [[Minors and abortion]]
* [[Sexual Morality and the Law]]
* [[Sex-positive movement]]
* [[Sodomy law]]
* ''[[The Maiden Tribute of Modern Babylon]]''
* [[Youth]]
* [[Youth suffrage]]
* [[Youth rights]]
{{Div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* Brewer, Holly. [http://uncpress.unc.edu/browse/book_detail?title_id=833 ''By Birth or Consent: Children, Law, &amp; the Anglo-American Revolution in Authority'']; Univ. of North Carolina Press (Chapel Hill, 2005) {{ISBN|978-0-8078-5832-5}}
* Robertson, Stephen ([[University of Sydney]]). &quot;[http://chnm.gmu.edu/cyh/case-studies/230 Age of Consent Laws].&quot; In: ''Children &amp; Youth in History'', Roy Rosenzweig Center for History and New Media (CHNM) at [[George Mason University]] and the [[University of Missouri–Kansas City]].—Includes links to primary sources.
* Waites, Matthew (2005). ''The Age of Consent: Young People, Sexuality and Citizenship'', (New York [United States] and Houndmills, Basingstoke [United Kingdom]: Palgrave Macmillan) {{ISBN|1-4039-2173-3}}
* {{cite journal|last=Schaffner|first=Laurie|year=2002|title=An Age of Reason: Paradoxes in Legal Constructions of Adulthood|url=|journal=[[International Journal of Children's Rights]]|volume=10|issue=3|pages=201–232|doi=10.1163/157181802761586699}}

==External links==
* {{Cite web|url=http://www.interpol.int/public/children/sexualabuse/nationallaws/default.asp|title=Legislation of Interpol member states on sexual offenses against children|access-date=2017-04-03|archive-url=http://webarchive.loc.gov/all/20010925002953/http://www.interpol.int/public/children/sexualabuse/nationallaws/default.asp|archive-date=2001-09-25|url-status=dead}} (Some information may be out of date)
* {{Cite web|url=http://moraloutrage.net/state-laws/|title=Links to the relevant state laws for all 50 States and Washington DC|access-date=2010-08-27|archive-url=https://archive.is/20100831060017/http://moraloutrage.net/state-laws/|archive-date=2010-08-31|url-status=usurped}}
* [http://www.avert.org/age-of-consent.htm Avert.org list]

{{Sex}}
{{Human sexuality}}
{{Sexual ethics}}
{{Law country lists}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Age Of Consent}}
[[Category:Age of consent| ]]
[[Category:Adolescent sexuality]]
[[Category:Age and society]]
[[Category:Minimum ages]]
[[Category:Sex laws]]
[[Category:Sexuality and age]]
[[Category:Statutory law]]</text>
      <sha1>glvh3w1qtthttbdfj69z9b5qjlic181</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
