  <page>
    <title>Alexios III Angelos</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1616</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940840829</id>
      <parentid>934663837</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-14T23:55:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>71.236.163.199</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Corrected reign end date.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{More footnotes|date=December 2008}}

{{Infobox monarch
|name        =Alexios III Angelos
|image= Alexios_III.jpg
|succession  = [[Byzantine Emperor|Emperor]] of the [[Byzantine Empire]]
|reign       = 8 April 1195 {{ndash}} 18 July 1203
|predecessor =[[Isaac II Angelos]]
|successor   =[[Isaac II Angelos]]  and [[Alexios IV Angelos]]
|spouse      =[[Euphrosyne Doukaina Kamatera]]
|issue       =Eirine Angelina&lt;br /&gt;[[Anna Komnene Angelina]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Eudokia Angelina]]
|dynasty     =[[Angelos|Angelos dynasty]]
|father      =[[Andronikos Doukas Angelos]]
|mother      =[[Euphrosyne Kastamonitissa]]
|birth_date  = {{birth-date|c. 1153}}
|death_date  = {{death-date|1211}}
|title=[[List of Byzantine Emperors|Emperor and Autocrat of the Romans]]}}

'''Alexios III Angelos''' ({{lang-gkm|Ἀλέξιος Γ′ Ἄγγελος}}) ({{circa|1153}}{{snd}}1211) was [[Byzantine Emperors|Byzantine Emperor]] from March 1195 to July 17/18, 1203.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agiasofia.com/emperors/fall1204.html http://www.agiasofia.com/emperors/fall1204.html]&lt;/ref&gt;  A member of the extended imperial family, Alexios came to throne after deposing, blinding, and imprisoning his younger brother [[Isaac II Angelos]].  The most significant event of his reign was the attack of the [[Fourth Crusade]] on [[Constantinople]] in 1203, on behalf of [[Alexios IV Angelos]].  Alexios III took over the defense of the city, which he mismanaged, then fled the city at night with one of his three daughters. From [[Adrianople]], and then [[Mosynopolis]], he unsuccessfully attempted to rally his supporters, only to end up a captive of Marquis [[Boniface of Montferrat]]. He was ransomed, sent to Asia Minor where he plotted against his son-in-law [[Theodore I Laskaris|Theodore Laskaris]], but was eventually arrested and spent his last days confined to the Monastery of Hyakinthos in [[Nicaea]], where he died.

==Early life==
Alexios III Angelos was the second son of [[Andronikos Doukas Angelos]] and [[Euphrosyne Kastamonitissa]]. Andronikos was himself a son of [[Theodora Komnene (daughter of Alexios I)|Theodora Komnene]], the youngest daughter of Emperor [[Alexios I Komnenos]] and [[Irene Doukaina]]. Thus Alexios Angelos was a member of the extended imperial family. Together with his father and brothers, Alexios had conspired against Emperor [[Andronikos I Komnenos]] ({{circa|lk=no|1183}}), and thus he spent several years in exile in Muslim courts, including that of [[Saladin]].

His younger brother [[Isaac II Angelos|Isaac]] was threatened with execution under orders of Andronikos I, their first-cousin once-removed, on September 11, 1185. Isaac made a desperate attack on the imperial agents and soon killed their leader [[Stephen Hagiochristophorites]]. He then took refuge in the church of [[Hagia Sophia]] and from there appealed to the populace. His actions provoked a riot, which resulted in the deposition of Andronikos I and the proclamation of Isaac as Emperor. Alexios was now closer to the imperial throne than ever before.

==Reign==
[[File:Alexios III -Angelos.jpg|thumb|Alexios III from ''Promptuarii Iconum Insigniorum'']]
By 1190 Alexios had returned to the court of his younger brother, from whom he received the elevated title of ''[[sebastokrator|sebastokratōr]]''.  In March 1195 while Isaac II was away hunting in [[Thrace]], Alexios was acclaimed as emperor by the troops with the covert support of Alexios' wife [[Euphrosyne Doukaina Kamatera]]. Alexios captured Isaac at [[Stagira]] in [[Macedonia (region)|Macedonia]], [[political mutilation in Byzantine culture|put out his eyes]], and thenceforth kept him a close prisoner, despite having previously been redeemed by Alexios from captivity at [[Antioch]] and showered with honours.{{sfn|Bury|1911}}

To compensate for this crime and to solidify his position as emperor, Alexios had to scatter money so lavishly as to empty his treasury, and to allow such licence to the officers of the army as to leave the Empire practically defenceless. These actions inevitably led to the financial ruin of the state. At Christmas 1196, Holy Roman Emperor [[Henry VI, Holy Roman Emperor|Henry VI]] attempted to force Alexios to pay him a tribute of 5,000 pounds (later negotiated down to 1,600 pounds) of gold or face invasion. Alexios gathered the money by plundering imperial tombs at the church of the Holy Apostles and [[Alamanikon|taxing the people heavily]], though Henry's death in September 1197 meant the gold was never dispatched. The able and forceful empress Euphrosyne tried in vain to sustain his credit and his court; Vatatzes, the favourite instrument in her attempts at reform, was [[assassination|assassinated]] by the emperor's orders.{{sfn|Bury|1911}}

In the east the Empire was overrun by the [[Seljuk Turks]]; from the north, the [[Kingdom of Hungary]] and the rebellious [[Bulgarians]] and [[Vlachs]] descended unchecked to ravage the Balkan provinces of the Empire, sometimes penetrating as far as Greece, while Alexios squandered the public treasure on his palaces and gardens and attempted to deal with the crisis through diplomatic means. The Emperor's attempts to bolster the empire's defences by special concessions to [[pronoia]]rs (notables) in the frontier zone backfired, as the latter increased their regional autonomy. Byzantine authority survived, but in a much weakened state. In 1197, local lord [[Dobromir Chrysos]] established himself in region of [[Vardar Macedonia]], defying the imperial power for several years.{{sfn|Fine|1994|p=29-30}}

During first years of Alexios reign, relations between Byzantium and [[Grand Principality of Serbia|Serbia]] were good, since his daughter [[Eudokia Angelina]] was married to Serbian Grand Prince [[Stefan Nemanjić]], who was granted the title of ''[[sebastokrator]]''. But in 1200, those relations deteriorated. Marriage between Stefan and Eudokia was dissolved, and alliance between Serbia and Byzantium ended, leaving Byzantium without a single ally in Southeastern Europe.{{sfn|Fine|1994|p=46}}{{sfn|Ćirković|2004|p=34-35}}

==Fourth Crusade==
Soon Alexios was threatened by a new and more formidable danger. In 1202, soldiers assembled at [[Venice]] to launch the [[Fourth Crusade]]. [[Alexios IV Angelos]], the son of the deposed Isaac II, had recently escaped from [[Constantinople]] and now appealed for support to the crusaders, promising to end the [[East-West Schism|schism]] of [[Eastern Orthodoxy|East]] and [[Roman Catholicism|West]], to pay for their transport, and to provide military support if they would help him depose his uncle and ascend to his father's throne.{{sfn|Bury|1911}}

The crusaders, whose objective had been [[Egypt]], were persuaded to set their course for Constantinople, arriving there in June 1203, proclaiming Alexios IV as Emperor, and inviting the populace of the capital to depose his uncle. Alexios III took no effective measures to resist, and his attempts to bribe the crusaders failed. His son-in-law, [[Theodore I Laskaris|Theodore Laskaris]], who was the only one to attempt anything significant, was defeated at [[Üsküdar|Scutari]], and the siege of Constantinople began. Unfortunately for the city, misgovernment by Alexios III had left the Byzantine navy with only 20 worm-eaten hulks by the time the crusaders arrived.

In July, the crusaders, led by the aged [[Doge of Venice|Doge]] [[Enrico Dandolo]], scaled the walls and took control of a major section of the city. In the ensuing fighting, the crusaders set the city on fire, ultimately leaving 20,000 people homeless.  On 17 July Alexios III finally took action and led 17 divisions from the [[Gate of St. Romanus|St. Romanus Gate]], vastly outnumbering the crusaders. His courage failed, however, and the Byzantine army returned to the city without a fight. His courtiers demanded action, and Alexios III promised to fight. Instead, that night (July 17/18), Alexios III hid in the palace, and finally, with one of his daughters, Eirene, and as much treasure (1,000 pounds of gold) as he could collect, got into a boat and escaped to [[Debeltos]] in Thrace, leaving his wife and his other daughters behind. Isaac II, drawn from his prison and robed once more in the imperial purple, received his son, Alexios IV, in state.

==Life in exile==
Alexios III attempted to organize resistance to the new regime from [[Adrianople]] and then [[Mosynopolis]], where he was joined by the later usurper [[Alexios V Doukas|Alexios V Doukas ''Mourtzouphlos'']] in April 1204, after the definitive fall of Constantinople to the crusaders and the establishment of the [[Latin Empire]]. At first Alexios III received Alexios V well, even allowing him to marry his daughter [[Eudokia Angelina]]. Later Alexios V was blinded and deserted by his father-in-law, who fled from the crusaders into [[Thessaly]]. Here Alexios III eventually surrendered, with Euphrosyne, to Marquis [[Boniface of Montferrat]], who was establishing himself as ruler of the [[Kingdom of Thessalonica]].

Alexios III attempted to escape Boniface's &quot;protection&quot; in 1205, seeking shelter with [[Michael I Komnenos Doukas]], the ruler of [[Despotate of Epirus|Epirus]]. Captured by Boniface, Alexios and his retinue were sent to [[Montferrat]] before being brought back to [[Thessalonica]] in {{circa|1209}}. At that point the deposed emperor was ransomed by Michael I, who sent him to [[Asia Minor]], where Alexios' son-in-law Theodore Laskaris - now [[Empire of Nicaea|emperor of Nicaea]] - was holding his own against the Latins. Here Alexios conspired against his son-in-law after the latter refused to recognize Alexios' authority, receiving the support of [[Kaykhusraw I]], the [[Sultanate of Rum|sultan of Rûm]]. In the [[Battle of Antioch on the Meander]] in 1211, the sultan was defeated and killed, and Alexios was captured by Theodore Laskaris. Alexios was then confined to a [[monastery]] at [[İznik|Nicaea]],{{sfn|Treadgold|1997|p=717}} where he died later in 1211.

==Family==
By his marriage to [[Euphrosyne Doukaina Kamatera]], Alexios had three daughters:
* Eirene Angelina, who married (1) Andronikos Kontostephanos, and (2) [[Alexios Palaiologos (despot)|Alexios Palaiologos]], by whom she was the grandmother of Emperor [[Michael VIII Palaiologos]].
* [[Anna Angelina]], who married (1) the ''sebastokratōr'' Isaac Komnenos, great-nephew of emperor [[Manuel I Komnenos]], and (2) [[Theodore I Laskaris|Theodore Laskaris]], emperor of Nicaea.
* [[Eudokia Angelina]], who married (1) Serbian King [[Stefan the First-Crowned|Stefan Nemanjić]], then (2) Emperor [[Alexios V Doukas]], and (3) [[Leo Sgouros]], ruler of [[Corinth]].{{sfn|Finley, Jr.|1932|p=484}}

==See also==
{{portal|Byzantine Empire}}
* [[List of Byzantine emperors]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
* [[Michael Angold]], ''The Byzantine Empire, 1025–1204: A Political History'', second edition (London and New York, 1997)
* {{EB1911|wstitle=Alexius III.|volume=1|pages=577-578|first=John Bagnell|last=Bury|authorlink=J. B. Bury}}
* {{Byzantium Confronts the West}}
* {{Cite book|ref=harv|last=Ćirković|first=Sima|authorlink=Sima Ćirković|year=2004|title=The Serbs|location=Malden|publisher=Blackwell Publishing|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2Wc-DWRzoeIC}}
* {{The Late Medieval Balkans}}
*{{cite journal |title=Corinth in the Middle Ages|first=John H. |last=Finley, Jr. |journal=Speculum |volume= 7 |number=No. 4 |year=1932 |ref=harv}}
* Jonathan Harris, ''Byzantium and the Crusades'', (2nd ed. London and New York, 2014). {{ISBN|978-1-78093-767-0}}
* Jonathan Harris, ''Constantinople: Capital of Byzantium'' (London and New York, 2007)
* {{Oxford Dictionary of Byzantium}}
* {{cite web|url=https://www.academia.edu/31064036/ |first=David |last=Savignac|title=The Medieval Russian Account of the Fourth Crusade - A New Annotated Translation}}
* {{Η Γενεαλογία των Κομνηνών | volume = B}}
* {{cite encyclopedia | last = Plate | first = William | authorlink = | title = Alexios III Angelos | editor = [[William Smith (lexicographer)|William Smith]] | encyclopedia = [[Dictionary of Greek and Roman Biography and Mythology]] | volume = 1 | pages = 130 | publisher = [[Little, Brown and Company]] | location = Boston | year = 1867 | url = http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=moa;cc=moa;idno=acl3129.0001.001;q1=demosthenes;size=l;frm=frameset;seq=145;page=root;view=image}}
* {{A History of the Byzantine State and Society}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou|[[Angelus (dynasty)|Angelid]] dynasty||1153||1211}}
{{s-reg}}
{{s-bef|rows=2|before=[[Isaac II Angelos]]}}
{{s-ttl|rows=2|title=[[List of Byzantine Emperors|Byzantine Emperor]]|years=1195–1203}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Isaac II Angelos]]}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Alexios IV Angelos]]}}
{{s-end}}
{{Roman Emperors}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Alexios 03 Angelos,}}
[[Category:Angelid dynasty]]
[[Category:12th-century Byzantine emperors]]
[[Category:13th-century Byzantine emperors]]
[[Category:Christians of the Crusade of 1197]]
[[Category:Christians of the Fourth Crusade]]
[[Category:1153 births|Alexios Angelos]]
[[Category:1211 deaths|Alexios Angelos]]
[[Category:Eastern Orthodox monarchs]]
[[Category:Monarchs imprisoned and detained during war]]
[[Category:Sebastokrators]]</text>
      <sha1>mtkniqru8xawbq62mr1u448v5uj1kqr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
