  <page>
    <title>Severus Alexander</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1600</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942168473</id>
      <parentid>936221358</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-23T01:04:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>183.83.137.243</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Germanic War */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{distinguish|Septimius Severus|Valerius Severus|Libius Severus|Alexander (Byzantine emperor)}}
{{Infobox Roman emperor
| name            = Severus Alexander
| full name       = Marcus Julius Gessius Bassianus Alexianus &lt;br /&gt;(from birth to adoption);&lt;br /&gt; Caesar Marcus Aurelius Alexander (from adoption to accession)
| regnal name     = Imperator Caesar Marcus Aurelius Severus Alexander Augustus
| image           = Alexander Severus Musei Capitolini MC471.jpg
| caption         = Bust of Severus Alexander, [[Musei Capitolini]]
| title           = [[Augustus (honorific)|Augustus]]
| succession      = [[Roman Emperor|Emperor of the Roman Empire]]
| reign           = 11 March 222{{snd}}18/19 March 235
| predecessor     = [[Elagabalus]]
| successor       = [[Maximinus Thrax]]
| spouse          = [[Sallustia Orbiana]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sulpicia Memmia]]
| issue           =
| royal house     = [[Severan dynasty|Severan]]
| house-type      = Imperial Dynasty
| father          = [[Marcus Julius Gessius Marcianus]]
| mother          = [[Julia Avita Mamaea]]
| birth_date      = c. 208
| birth_place     = [[Arqa|Arca Caesarea]], [[Phoenicia|Syria Phoenicia Province]] (modern [[Akkar District|Akkar]], [[Lebanon]])
| death_date      = 19 March 235 (aged around 27)
| death_place     = [[Mainz|Moguntiacum]], [[Germania Superior]]
| place of burial =
| religion        = [[Syncretism]] of [[Ancient Greek religion|Pagan]], [[Orphism (religion)|Orphic]] and [[Christianity|Christian]] beliefs
}}
{{Severan dynasty
| image   = [[File:Julia mammea01 pushkin.jpg|200px]]
| caption = Bust of Julia Mamaea
}}
'''Severus Alexander''' ({{IPAc-en|s|ə|ˈ|v|ɪər|ə|s}}; {{lang-la|Marcus Aurelius Severus Alexander Augustus}};&lt;ref&gt;In [[Classical Latin]], Alexander's name would be inscribed as MARCVS AVRELIVS SEVERVS ALEXANDER AVGVSTVS.&lt;/ref&gt; c. 208 – 19 March 235) was [[Roman Emperor]] from 222 to 235 and the last emperor of the [[Severan dynasty]]. He succeeded his cousin [[Elagabalus]] upon the latter's [[assassination]] in 222. His own assassination marked the [[epoch event]] for the [[Crisis of the Third Century]]—nearly 50 years of civil wars, foreign invasion, and collapse of the monetary economy.

Alexander was the heir to his cousin, the 18-year-old Emperor who had been murdered along with his mother [[Julia Soaemias]], by his own guards, who, as a mark of contempt, had their remains cast into the [[Tiber river]].&lt;ref&gt;Dio, 60:20:2&lt;/ref&gt; He and his cousin were both grandsons of the influential and powerful [[Julia Maesa]], who had arranged for Elagabalus' acclamation as emperor by the famous [[Legio III Gallica|Third Gallic Legion]]. It was the rumor of Alexander's death that triggered the assassination of Elagabalus and his mother.&lt;ref&gt;Herodian, 5:8:5&lt;/ref&gt; His 13-year reign was the longest reign of a ''sole'' emperor since [[Antoninus Pius]].&lt;ref&gt;A handful of emperors since Antoninus Pius reigned for longer than 13 years, but for some or most of their reign they were co-emperors with others and therefore they were sole emperor for less than 13 years.&lt;/ref&gt; He was also the second-youngest ever sole legal Roman Emperor during the existence of the united empire, the youngest being [[Gordian III]].

As emperor, Alexander's peacetime reign was prosperous. However, Rome was militarily confronted with the rising [[Sassanid Empire]] and growing incursions from the tribes of [[Germania]]. He managed to check the threat of the Sassanids. But when campaigning against [[Germanic peoples|Germanic tribes]], Alexander attempted to bring peace by engaging in diplomacy and bribery. This alienated many in the [[Roman Army]] and led to a conspiracy to assassinate and replace him.

==Early reign==
Born between around 207 or 208,&lt;ref&gt;''The life of Severus Alexander'': &quot;The presumption therefore is that he was born in 207 or 208&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Severus Alexander became emperor when he was around 14 years old, making him the youngest emperor in [[Roman Empire|Rome]]'s history, until the ascension of [[Gordian III]]. Alexander's grandmother believed that he had more potential to rule than her other grandson, the increasingly unpopular emperor [[Elagabalus]].{{citation needed|date=August 2018}} Thus, to preserve her own position, she had Elagabalus adopt the young Alexander and then arranged for Elagabalus' assassination, securing the throne for Alexander.&lt;ref&gt;Wells, pg. 266&lt;/ref&gt; The Roman army hailed Alexander as emperor on 13 March 222, immediately conferring on him the titles of Augustus, ''pater patriae'' and ''pontifex maximus''.{{citation needed|date=March 2018}}

Throughout his life, Alexander relied heavily on guidance from his grandmother, Maesa, and mother, [[Julia Avita Mamaea|Julia Mamaea]]. Maesa died in 223, leaving Mamaea as the sole influence upon Alexander's actions.{{citation needed|date=March 2018}} As a young, immature, and inexperienced adolescent, Alexander knew little about government, warcraft, or the role of ruling over an empire. Because of this, throughout his entire reign he was a puppet of his mother's advice and entirely under her jurisdiction, a state of affairs that was not popular with the soldiers.{{citation needed|date=August 2018}}

==Domestic achievements==
[[File:Bust Alexander Severus Louvre Ma1051 n1.jpg|thumb|Bust of Alexander Severus, [[Louvre]].]]
Under the influence of his mother, Alexander did much to improve the morals and condition of the people, and to enhance the dignity of the state.&lt;ref name=&quot;Benario, Alexander Severus&quot;/&gt; He employed noted [[jurist]]s to oversee the administration of justice, such as the famous jurist [[Ulpian]].{{citation needed|date=August 2018}} His advisers were men like the [[Roman Senate|senator]] and historian [[Cassius Dio]], and it is claimed that he created a select board of 16 senators,&lt;ref name=&quot;Southern, pg. 60&quot;&gt;Southern, p. 60&lt;/ref&gt; although this claim is disputed.&lt;ref&gt;from the chapter entitled Administrative Strategies of the Emperor Severus Alexander and his Advisers, written by Lukas de Blois in the book Herrschaftsstrukturen und Herrschaftspraxis, chapter by&lt;/ref&gt; He also created a municipal council of 14 who assisted the [[urban prefect]] in administering the affairs of the 14 districts of Rome.&lt;ref&gt;Historia Augusta, ''Life of Severus Alexander'', 33:1&lt;/ref&gt; Excessive luxury and extravagance at the imperial court were diminished,&lt;ref&gt;Historia Augusta, ''Life of Severus Alexander'', 15:1&lt;/ref&gt; and he restored the [[Baths of Nero]] in 227 or 229; consequently, they are sometimes also known as the Baths of Alexander after him.

Upon his accession he reduced the silver purity of the [[denarius]] from 46.5% to 43%—the actual silver weight dropped from 1.41&amp;nbsp;grams to 1.30&amp;nbsp;grams; however, in 229 he revalued the denarius, increasing the silver purity and weight to 45% and 1.46&amp;nbsp;grams. The following year he decreased the amount of base metal in the denarius while adding more silver, raising the silver purity and weight again to 50.5% and 1.50&amp;nbsp;grams.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tulane.edu/~august/handouts/601cprin.htm Tulane University &quot;Roman Currency of the Principate&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, during his reign taxes were lightened; literature, art and science were encouraged;&lt;ref&gt;Historia Augusta, ''Life of Severus Alexander'', 21:6&lt;/ref&gt; and, for the convenience of the people, loan offices were instituted for lending money at a moderate rate of interest.&lt;ref&gt;Historia Augusta, ''Life of Severus Alexander'', 21:2&lt;/ref&gt;

In religious matters, Alexander preserved an open mind. According to the ''Historia Augusta'', he wished to erect a temple to [[Jesus]] but was dissuaded by the [[Paganism|pagan]] priests; however, much of this book is full of falsifications and modern scholars deem it almost completely untrustworthy.&lt;ref&gt;Historia Augusta, ''Life of Severus Alexander'', 43:6–7&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.livius.org/sources/about/historia-augusta/ livius]&lt;/ref&gt; He allowed a [[synagogue]] to be built in Rome, and he gave as a gift to this synagogue a scroll of the [[Torah]] known as the [[Severus Scroll]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?letter=A&amp;artid=1153 1901–1906 Jewish Encyclopedia article &quot;Alexander Severus&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In legal matters, Alexander did much to aid [[Military justice|the rights of his soldiers]]. He confirmed that soldiers could name anyone as heirs in their [[Will and testament|will]], whereas civilians had strict restrictions over who could become heirs or receive a legacy.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, p. 221&lt;/ref&gt; He also confirmed that soldiers could free their slaves in their wills,&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, p. 224&lt;/ref&gt; protected the rights of soldiers to their property when they were on campaign,&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, p. 239&lt;/ref&gt; and reasserted that a soldier's property acquired in or because of military service (his ''castrense peculium'') could be claimed by no-one else, not even the soldier's father.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, p. 234&lt;/ref&gt;

==Persian War==
On the whole, Alexander's reign was prosperous until the rise, in the east, of the [[Sassanid Empire|Sassanids]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Southern, pg. 61&quot;&gt;Southern, p. 61&lt;/ref&gt; under [[Ardashir I]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Severus Alexander |publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica Online Academic Edition. Encyclopædia Britannica Inc., 2014|accessdate=2 May 2014|url= http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/536782/Severus-Alexander}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 231 AD, Ardeshir invaded the Roman provinces of the east, overrunning Mesopotamia and penetrating possibly as far as Syria and Cappadocia, forcing from the young Alexander a vigorous response.&lt;ref&gt;Arthur E.R. Boak, ''A History Of Rome To 565 A.D.'', (The Macmillan Company, 1921, New York), chap. XVIII., p. 258&lt;/ref&gt; Of the war that followed there are various accounts. According to the most detailed authority, [[Herodian]], the Roman armies suffered a number of humiliating setbacks and defeats,&lt;ref&gt;Herodian, 6:5–6:6&lt;/ref&gt; while according to the [[Historia Augusta]]&lt;ref&gt;Historia Augusta, ''Life of Severus Alexander'', 55:1–3&lt;/ref&gt; as well as Alexander's own dispatch to the [[Roman Senate]], he gained great victories.&lt;ref name=&quot;Southern, pg. 62&quot;&gt;Southern, p. 62&lt;/ref&gt; Making [[Antioch]] his base, he organized in 233 a three-fold invasion of the [[Sassanian Empire]]; at the head of the main body he himself advanced to recapture northern [[Mesopotamia]], while another army invaded [[Media (region)|Media]] through the mountains of Armenia, and a third advanced from the south in the direction of [[Babylon]]. The northernmost army gained some success, fighting in mountainous territory favorable to the Roman infantry, but the southern army was surrounded and destroyed by Ardashir's skilful horse-archers, and Alexander himself retreated after an indecisive campaign, his army wracked by indiscipline and disease.&lt;ref&gt;[[Edward Gibbon]], ''The Decline And Fall Of The Roman Empire'', (The Modern Library, 1932), chap. VIII., p. 182&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Herodian, 6:5:10&lt;/ref&gt; Further losses were incurred by the retreating northern army in the inclement cold of [[Roman Armenia|Armenia]] as it retired into winter quarters, due to an incompetent failure to establish adequate supply lines.&lt;ref&gt;Herodian, 6:6:3&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gibbon, Ibid.&lt;/ref&gt; Still, Mesopotamia was retaken, and Ardashir was not thereafter able to extend his conquests, though his son, Shapur, would obtain some success later in the century.&lt;ref&gt;Gibbon, Ibid.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the Sassanids were checked for the time,&lt;ref name=&quot;Southern, pg. 62&quot;&gt;Southern, p. 62&lt;/ref&gt; the conduct of the [[Imperial Roman army|Roman army]] showed an extraordinary lack of discipline. In 232, there was a mutiny in the Syrian legion, which proclaimed [[Taurinus]] emperor.&lt;ref&gt;Victor, 24:2&lt;/ref&gt; Alexander managed to suppress the uprising, and Taurinus drowned while attempting to flee across the [[Euphrates]].{{citation needed|date=August 2018}} The emperor returned to Rome and celebrated a triumph in 233.&lt;ref name=&quot;Southern, pg. 62&quot;&gt;Southern, p. 62&lt;/ref&gt;

==Military discipline==
{{multiple image
|align  = left
|image1 = Severus alexander.jpg
|caption1 = IMP. ALEXANDER PIVS AVG.
|width1 = 170
|image2 = Denarius of Severus Alexander (YORYM 2001 200) obverse.jpg
|caption2 = IMP. ALEXANDER PIVS AVG.
|width2 = 170
|footer = &lt;center&gt;''[[Denarii]]'' of Severus Alexander&lt;/center&gt;
}}
Alexander's reign was also characterized by a significant breakdown of military discipline.&lt;ref name=&quot;Campbell, pg. 196&quot;&gt;Campbell, p. 196&lt;/ref&gt; In 223, the [[Praetorian Guard]] murdered their [[Praetorian prefect|prefect]], Ulpian,&lt;ref name=&quot;Campbell, pg. 196&quot; /&gt; in Alexander's presence. Alexander could not openly punish the ringleader of the riot, and instead removed him to nominal post of honor in [[Egypt]] and then [[Crete]], where he was &quot;quietly put out of the way&quot; sometime after the excitement had abated.&lt;ref name=&quot;ledlie-ulpian&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Ledlie |first1=James Crawford |title=Ulpian |journal=Journal of the Society of Comparative Legislation |date=1903 |volume=5 |issue=1 |page=19 |jstor=751768 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The soldiers then fought a three-day battle against the populace of Rome, and this battle ended after several parts of the city were set on fire.&lt;ref name=&quot;Campbell, pg. 197&quot;&gt;Campbell, p. 197&lt;/ref&gt;

Dio was among those who gave a highly critical account of military discipline during the time, saying that the soldiers would rather just surrender to the enemy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Campbell, pg. 197&quot; /&gt; Different reasons are given for this issue; Campbell points to &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;...the decline in the prestige of the Severan dynasty, the feeble nature of Alexander himself, who appeared to be no soldier and to be completely dominated by his mother's advice, and lack of real military success at a time during which the empire was coming under increasing pressure.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Campbell, pg. 197&quot; /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Herodian, on the other hand, was convinced that &quot;the emperor's miserliness (partly the result of his mother's greed) and slowness to bestow donatives&quot; were instrumental in the fall of military discipline under Alexander.&lt;ref name=&quot;Campbell, pg. 197&quot; /&gt;

==Germanic War==
After the Persian war, Alexander returned to Antioch with the famous [[Origen]], one of the greatest Fathers of the Christian Church. Alexander's mother, Julia Mamaea, asked for Origen to tutor Alexander in [[Christianity]].{{citation needed|date=March 2018}}

While Alexander was being educated in the Christian doctrines, the northern portion of his empire was being invaded by Germanic and Sarmatian tribes. A new and menacing enemy started to emerge directly after Alexander's success in the Persian war. In 234, the barbarians crossed the Rhine and Danube in hordes that caused alarm as far as Rome. The soldiers serving under Alexander, already demoralized after their costly war against the Persians, were further discontented with their emperor when their homes were destroyed by the barbarian invaders.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, 54&lt;/ref&gt;

As word of the invasion spread, the Emperor took the front line and went to battle against the Germanic invaders. The Romans prepared heavily for the war, building a fleet to carry the entire army across. However, at this point in Alexander's career, he still knew little about being a general. Because of this, he hoped the mere threat of his armies would be sufficient to persuade the hostile tribes to surrender.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Alexander Severus|url=http://www.roman-empire.net/decline/alex-severus-index.html|publisher=Capitoline Museums}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Severus enforced a strict military discipline in his men that sparked a rebellion among his legions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Western Press Association&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Library of World History: Containing a Record of the Human Race from the Earliest Historical Period to the Present Time; Embracing a General Survey of the Progress of Mankind in National and Social Life, Civil Government, Religion, Literature, Science and Art, Volume 3|publisher=Western Press Association|location=New York Public Library|page=1442}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to incurring heavy losses against the Persians, and on the advice of his mother, Alexander attempted to buy the Germanic tribes off, so as to gain time.&lt;ref&gt;Herodian, &lt;I&gt;Roman history, book 6, chapter 7&lt;/I&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

It was this decision that resulted in the [[Legionary|legionaries]] looking down upon Alexander. They considered him dishonorable and feared he was unfit to be Emperor. Under these circumstances the army swiftly looked to replace Alexander.&lt;ref&gt;Herodian, &lt;I&gt;Roman history, book 6, chapter 8&lt;/I&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Maximinus Thrax|Gaius Iulius Verus Maximinus]] was the next best option. He was a soldier from Thrace who had a golden reputation and was working hard to increase his military status.&lt;ref name=&quot;Western Press Association&quot;/&gt; He was also a man with superior personal strength, who rose to his present position from a peasant background. With the Thracian's hailing came the end of the Severan Dynasty,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Saylor Foundation&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Severus Alexander (222–235 AD): The Calm before the Storm|url=http://www.saylor.org/site/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/HIST301-7.2-SeverusAlexander-FINAL.pdf|publisher=The Saylor Foundation}}&lt;/ref&gt; and, with the growing animosity of Severus' army towards him, the path for his assassination was paved.

== Death ==
Alexander was forced to face his German enemies in the early months of 235. By the time he and his mother arrived, the situation had settled, and so his mother convinced him that to avoid violence, trying to bribe the German army to surrender was the more sensible course of action.{{citation needed|date=August 2018}} According to historians, it was this tactic combined with insubordination from his own men that destroyed his reputation and popularity. Pusillanimity was responsible for the revolt of Alexander's army, resulting in Severus falling victim to the swords of his own men,&lt;ref name=&quot;Valentine Nind Hopkins 240&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Valentine Nind Hopkins|first=Sir Richard|title=The Life of Alexander Severus|publisher=The University Press|location=Princeton University|pages=240}}&lt;/ref&gt; following the nomination of Maximinus as emperor.

Alexander was assassinated on 19 March 235, together with his mother, in a mutiny of the [[Legio XXII Primigenia|Legio XXII ''Primigenia'']] at [[Mainz|Moguntiacum (Mainz)]] while at a meeting with his generals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Southern, pg. 63&quot;&gt;Southern, p. 63&lt;/ref&gt; These assassinations secured the throne for Maximinus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Benario, Alexander Severus&quot;&gt;Benario, ''Alexander Severus''&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Aelius Lampridius|Lampridius]] documents two theories that elaborate on Severus's assassination. The first claims that the disaffection of Mamaea was the main motive behind the homicide. However, Lampridius makes it clear that he is more supportive of an alternative theory, that Alexander was murdered in Sicilia (located in Britain).&lt;ref&gt;Historia Augusta, ''Life of Severus Alexander'', 59:6&lt;/ref&gt;

This theory has it that, in an open tent after his lunch, Alexander was consulting with his insubordinate troops, who compared him to his cousin [[Elagabalus]], the divisive and unpopular Emperor whose own assassination paved the way for Alexander's reign. A German servant entered the tent and initiated the call for Alexander's assassination, at which point many of the troops joined in the attack. Alexander's attendants fought against the other troops but could not hold off the combined might of those seeking the Emperor's assassination. Within minutes, Alexander was dead. His mother Julia Mamaea was in the same tent with Alexander and soon fell victim to the same group of assassins.&lt;ref name=&quot;Valentine Nind Hopkins 240&quot;/&gt;

==Legacy==
[[File:Medaglione con effigie di alessandro severo, 1490 ca.JPG|thumb|15th century depiction of Severus Alexander]]
Alexander's death marked the end of the [[Severan dynasty]]. He was the last of the Syrian emperors and the first emperor to be overthrown by military discontent on a wide scale.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, p. 55&lt;/ref&gt; After his death his economic policies were completely discarded, and the Roman currency was devalued; this signaled the beginning of the chaotic period known as the [[Crisis of the Third Century]], which brought the empire to the brink of collapse.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Saylor Foundation&quot;/&gt;

Alexander's death at the hands of his troops can also be seen as the heralding of a new role for Roman emperors. Though they were not yet expected to personally fight in battle during Alexander's time, emperors were increasingly expected to display general competence in military affairs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Campbell, pg. 69&quot;&gt;Campbell, p. 69&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, Alexander's taking of his mother's advice to not get involved in battle, his dishonorable and unsoldierly methods of dealing with the Germanic threat, and the relative failure of his military campaign against the Persians were all deemed highly unacceptable by the soldiers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Campbell, pg. 69&quot;&gt;Campbell, p. 69&lt;/ref&gt; Indeed, Maximinus was able to overthrow Alexander by &quot;harping on his own military excellence in contrast to that feeble coward&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Campbell, pg. 69&quot;&gt;Campbell, p. 69&lt;/ref&gt; Yet by arrogating the power to dethrone their emperor, the legions paved the way for a half-century of widespread chaos and instability.

Although the Senate declared the emperor and his rule damned upon the report of his death and the ascension of a replacement emperor, Alexander was [[Apotheosis|deified]] after the death of Maximinus in 238.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Severus Alexander|publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica Online Academic Edition. Encyclopædia Britannica Inc., 2014 |accessdate=2 May 2014 |url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/536782/Severus-Alexander}}&lt;/ref&gt; His ''[[damnatio memoriae]]'' was also reversed after Maximinus's death.

Perhaps his most tangible legacy was the emergence in the 16th Century of the 'Barberini vase'. This was allegedly found at the mausoleum of the Roman Emperor Alexander Severus and his family at [[:it:Monte_del_Grano|Monte Del Grano]]. The discovery of the vase is described by [[Pietro Santi Bartoli]] and referenced on page 28 of a book on The Portland Vase&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Portland Vase : the extraordinary odyssey of a mysterious Roman treasure|last=Brooks, Robin (Robin Jeremy)|date=2004|publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=0-06-051099-4|edition=1st|location=New York, NY|oclc=54960357}}&lt;/ref&gt;. Pietro Bartoli indicates that the vase contained the ashes of Severus Alexander. However, this together with the interpretations of the scenes depicted are the source of countless theories and disputed 'facts'. The vase passed through the hands of [[William Hamilton (diplomat)|Sir William Hamilton]] Ambassador to the Royal Court in Naples and was later sold to the [[William Cavendish-Bentinck, 3rd Duke of Portland|Duke and Duchess of Portland]], and has subsequently been known as the [[Portland Vase]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://research.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=466190&amp;partId=1&amp;searchText=portland+vase&amp;page=1|title=The Portland Vase|website=British Museum|language=en-GB|access-date=2020-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;. Following catastrophic damage, this vase (1-25BC) has been reconstructed three times and resides in the [[British Museum]]. The [[Portland Vase|Portland vase]] itself was borrowed and near copied by [[Josiah Wedgwood|Josiah Wedgewood]] who appears to have added modesty drapery. The vase formed the basis of [[Jasperware]].
[[File:Portland Vase BM Gem4036 n1 resized white-balanced white bg.png|thumb|Portland Vase]]

==Personal life==
[[File:Orbiana Denarius.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Denarius of Sallustia Orbiana. Inscription: SALL. BARBIA ORBIANA AVG.]]
Alexander was married three times. His most famous wife was [[Sallustia Orbiana]], ''[[Augusta (honorific)|Augusta]]'', whom he married in 225 when she was 16 years old. Their marriage was arranged by Alexander's mother, Mamaea. However, as soon as Orbiana received the title of ''Augusta'', Mamaea became increasingly jealous and resentful of Alexander's wife due to Mamaea's excessive desire of all regal female titles.&lt;ref name=&quot;Benario, Alexander Severus&quot;/&gt; Alexander divorced and exiled Orbiana in 227, after her father, [[Seius Sallustius]], was executed after being accused of treason.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Davenport|first=Caillan|date=2011|title=Iterated Consulships and the Government of Severus Alexander.|journal=Zeitschrift für Papyrologie und Epigraphik|volume=177|pages=281–288|jstor=41291183}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Alexander's second wife was Sulpicia Memmia, a member of one of the most ancient Patrician families in Rome. Her father was a man of consular rank; her grandfather's name was ''Catulus''.&lt;ref&gt;Historia Augusta, ''Life of Severus Alexander'', 20:3&lt;/ref&gt;

The identity of Alexander's third wife is unknown. Alexander did not father children with any of his wives.

According to the [[Augustan History]], a late Roman work containing biographies of emperors and others, and considered by scholars to be a work of very dubious historical reliability,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Browning|first1=Robert|title=The Cambridge History of Classical Literature: Volume 2, Latin Literature, Part 5, The Later Principat|date=1983|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-27371-8|pages=[https://archive.org/details/latinliterature0000unse/page/41 41–50]|url=https://archive.org/details/latinliterature0000unse/page/41}}&lt;/ref&gt; Alexander prayed every morning in his private chapel. He was extremely tolerant of [[Jews]] and Christians alike. He continued all privileges towards Jews during his reign,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|title=Alexander Severus|url=http://jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/1153-alexander-severus|encyclopedia=Jewish Encyclopedia}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Grant|first1=Michael|title=Jews In The Roman World|date=1973|publisher=Macmillan Publishing Company|isbn=978-0684133409}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Augustan History relates that Alexander placed images of Abraham and Jesus in his oratory, along with other Roman deities and classical figures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Alexander Severus|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/13743a.htm|publisher=Catholic Encyclopedia}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Novak|first1=Ralph Martin|title=Christianity and the Roman Empire: Background Texts|date=2001|publisher=Bloomsbury T&amp;T Clark;|isbn=978-1563383472}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Also according to the ''Historia Augusta'', Alexander's &quot;chief amusement consisted in having young dogs play with little pigs.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Historia Augusta, ''Life of Severus Alexander'', 41:5&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ancestry==
{{ahnentafel
|collapsed=yes |align=center
|boxstyle_1=background-color: #fcc;
|boxstyle_2=background-color: #fb9;
|boxstyle_3=background-color: #ffc;
|boxstyle_4=background-color: #bfc;
|boxstyle_5=background-color: #9fe;
|1= 1. '''Severus Alexander'''
|2= 2. [[Marcus Julius Gessius Marcianus]]
|3= 3. [[Julia Avita Mamaea]]
|6= 6. [[Julius Avitus|Julius Avitus Alexianus]]{{citation needed|date=March 2019}}
|7= 7. [[Julia Maesa]]{{citation needed|date=March 2019}}
|14= 14. [[Julius Bassianus]]{{citation needed|date=March 2019}}
}}

==See also==
* [[Severan dynasty family tree]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

== Bibliography ==

===Primary===
* [[Cassius Dio]], [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Cassius_Dio/80*.html ''Roman History, Book 80'']
* [[Herodian]], [https://www.livius.org/sources/content/herodian-s-roman-history/ ''Roman History, Book 6'']
* [[Historia Augusta]], [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Historia_Augusta/Severus_Alexander/1*.html ''Life of Severus Alexander'']
* [[Aurelius Victor]], [http://www.roman-emperors.org/epitome.htm ''Epitome de Caesaribus'']
* [[Joannes Zonaras]], Compendium of History [https://web.archive.org/web/20080521191250/http://www.ancientsites.com/aw/Post/1049415 extract: ''Zonaras: Alexander Severus to Diocletian: 222–284'']
* [[Zosimus]], [http://www.tertullian.org/fathers/zosimus01_book1.htm ''Historia Nova'']

===Secondary===
* Birley, A.R., ''Septimius Severus: The African Emperor'', Routledge, 2002
* Southern, Pat. ''The Roman Empire from Severus to Constantine'', Routledge, 2001
* [http://www.roman-emperors.org/alexsev.htm Benario, Herbert W., ''Alexander Severus (A.D. 222–235)'', ''De Imperatoribus Romanis''] (2001)
* Gibbon. Edward ''Decline &amp; Fall of the Roman Empire'' (1888)
* Campbell, J.B., ''The Emperor and the Roman Army 31 BC{{snd}}AD 235'', Clarenden, 1984
* Wells, Colin, ''The Roman Empire'', Harvard University Press, 1997
* {{EB1911|wstitle=Alexander Severus |volume=1|page=567}} Although a few phrases appear to be copied from this encyclopedia, all of them are attributed here to primary sources.

==External links==
{{wikisource author}}
{{Commons-inline|Severus Alexander}}
* {{Cite CE1913|wstitle=Alexander Severus |short=x}}
* [http://www.forumancientcoins.com/numiswiki/view.asp?key=Severus%20Alexander Severus Alexander on NumisWiki]
* [http://www.forumancientcoins.com/Roman-Coins.asp?e=Severus_Alexander&amp;par=578&amp;pos=1&amp;target=55 Coins of Severus Alexander]

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou|[[Severan Dynasty]]||{{circa|208}}|19 March|235}}
{{S-reg}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Elagabalus]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Roman Emperor]]|years=222–235}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Maximinus I (Thrax)]]}}
{{s-off}}
{{s-bef | before= [[Gaius Vettius Gratus Sabinianus]],&lt;br /&gt; [[Seleucus (Roman usurper)|Marcus Flavius Vitellius Seleucus]]}}
{{s-ttl | title=[[List of late imperial Roman consuls|Consul]] of the [[Roman Empire]]|years=222|regent1= [[Elagabalus]]}}
{{s-aft | after=[[Marius Maximus]], &lt;br /&gt;[[Luscius Roscius Aelianus Paculus Salvius Julianus]]}}
{{s-bef | before= [[Tiberius Manilius Fuscus]],&lt;br /&gt; [[Servius Calpurnius Domitius Dexter]]}}
{{s-ttl | title=[[List of late imperial Roman consuls|Consul]] of the [[Roman Empire]]|years=226|regent1= [[Gaius Aufidius Marcellus]]}}
{{s-aft | after=[[Marcus Nummius Senecio Albinus]], &lt;br /&gt;[[Marcus Laelius Fulvius Maximus Aemilianus]]}}
{{s-bef | before= [[Quintus Aiacius Modestus Crescentianus]],&lt;br /&gt; [[Marcus Pomponius Maecius Probus]]}}
{{s-ttl | title=[[List of late imperial Roman consuls|Consul]] of the [[Roman Empire]]|years=229|regent1= [[Cassius Dio]]}}
{{s-aft | after=[[Lucius Virius Agricola]], &lt;br /&gt;[[Sextus Catius Clementinus Priscillianus]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{Roman Emperors}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Severus, Alexander}}
[[Category:208 births]]
[[Category:235 deaths]]
[[Category:3rd-century Roman emperors]]
[[Category:3rd-century murdered monarchs]]
[[Category:Imperial Roman consuls]]
[[Category:Severan dynasty]]
[[Category:Crisis of the Third Century]]
[[Category:Murdered Roman emperors]]
[[Category:Deified Roman emperors]]
[[Category:Ancient child rulers]]
[[Category:People from Homs]]
[[Category:Royal Family of Emesa]]
[[Category:Julii|Severus Alexander]]
[[Category:Aurelii]]
[[Category:People of Roman Syria]]
[[Category:Severus Alexander]]
[[Category:Ancient Roman adoptees]]
[[Category:Adoptees adopted by relations]]</text>
      <sha1>r0dabuaz4ag9cdwe2y2p6etju6o3p6k</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
