  <page>
    <title>Algiers</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1644</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942865011</id>
      <parentid>942133058</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T09:55:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JzG</username>
        <id>760284</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] rule */Addind &quot;self-published source&quot; inside ref tags where tagged inline only</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Capital of Algeria}}
{{About|the capital of Algeria}}
{{Redirect|Algerine}}
{{Infobox settlement
| name                            = Algiers
| native_name                     = {{lang|ar|الجزائر}}
| other_name                      = Alger
| official_name                   =
| nickname                        = Algiers the White; Algiers the Dazzling
| settlement_type                 = [[Capital city|Capital City]]
| imagesize                       = 275px
| image_skyline                   = Algiers Montage.png
| image_caption                   = Clockwise: Buildings along the [[Mediterranean Sea|Mediterranean]] coast of Algiers, [[Martyrs' Memorial, Algiers|Martyrs Memorial]], [[Notre-Dame d'Afrique]], [[Ketchaoua Mosque]], [[Casbah of Algiers|Casbah]], the Grand Post Office and the [[Ministry of Finance (Algeria)|Ministry of Finance of Algeria]]
| image_flag                      = 
| image_shield                    = Armoiries d'Alger.svg
| pushpin_map                     = Algeria#Africa
| pushpin_relief                  = yes
| pushpin_mapsize                 = 275
| pushpin_map_caption             = Location in [[Algeria]] and [[Africa]]
| subdivision_type                = [[List of sovereign states|Country]]
| subdivision_type1               = [[Provinces of Algeria|Province]]
| subdivision_name1               = [[Algiers Province]]
| subdivision_type2               = [[Districts of Algeria|District]]
| subdivision_name2               = [[Sidi M'Hamed District]]
| subdivision_name                = {{flag|Algeria}}
| leader_title                    = [[Wali]] ([[Governor]])
| leader_name                     = Abdelkader Zoukh (since 2013)
| established_title               = Re-founded
| established_date                = 
| area_magnitude                  = 
| area_total_km2                  = 363
| area_metro_km2                  = 1190
| population_as_of                = 2011
| population_footnotes            = &lt;ref name=citypop&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://citypopulation.de/Algeria.html
 |title=Population of the city proper according to the 2008 census|publisher=Citypopulation.de 
 |accessdate=2010-06-27| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20100615060640/http://www.citypopulation.de/Algeria.html| archivedate= 15 June 2010 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=wup&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://esa.un.org/unup/index.asp?panel=2 |title=UN World Urbanization Prospects
 |publisher=Esa.un.org |accessdate=2010-06-27 |url-status=dead
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091223005931/http://esa.un.org/unup/index.asp?panel=2
 |archivedate=2009-12-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| population_total                = 3,415,811
| population_metro                = 7,796,923
| population_density_km2          = auto
| population_density_metro_km2    = auto
| timezone                        = [[Central European Time|CET]]
| utc_offset                      = +01:00
| coordinates                     = {{coord|36|45|14|N|3|3|32|E|region:DZ_type:city|display=inline,title}}
| elevation_min_m                 = 2
| elevation_max_m                 = 424
| postal_code_type                = Postal codes
| postal_code                     = 16000–16132
| area_code                       = (+213) 021
| blank_name                      = [[Köppen climate classification|Climate]]
| blank_info                      = [[Mediterranean climate|Csa]]
| website                         = 
| footnotes                       = 
}}

'''Algiers''' ({{IPAc-en|æ|l|ˈ|dʒ|ɪər|z}} {{respell|al|JEERZ}}; {{lang-ar|{{linktext|الجزائر}}|Al-Jazāʾir}}; {{lang-fr|Alger}}) is the [[Capital city|capital]] and largest city of [[Algeria]]. The city's population at the 2008 Census was 2,988,145&lt;ref&gt;Census 14 April 2008: Office National des Statistiques de l'Algérie (web).&lt;/ref&gt; and in 2011 was estimated to be around 3,500,000. An estimate puts the population of the larger metropolitan city to be around 5,000,000. Algiers is located on the [[Mediterranean Sea]] and in the north-central portion of Algeria.&lt;ref name=wup/&gt;

Algiers is situated on the west side of a bay of the [[Mediterranean Sea]]. The modern part of the city is built on the level ground by the seashore; the old part, the ancient city of the [[dey]]s, climbs the steep hill behind the modern town and is crowned by the [[Kasbah|casbah]] or citadel, {{convert|122|m|0}} above the sea. The casbah and the two quays form a triangle.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=653}}

{{anchor|Etymology|Toponymy|Name}}&lt;!--linked name--&gt;

==Names==
The city's name is derived via [[French language|French]] and [[Catalan language|Catalan]] {{lang|ca|Alger}}&lt;ref name=leschi&gt;''Origins of Algiers'' by [[Louis Leschi]], speech delivered June 16, 1941, published in ''El Djezair Sheets'', July 1941 [http://alger-roi.fr/Alger/alger_son_histoire/textes/3_origines_alger_1941_feuillets.htm History of Algeria] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130116134513/http://alger-roi.fr/Alger/alger_son_histoire/textes/3_origines_alger_1941_feuillets.htm |date=2013-01-16 }} {{in lang|fr}}.&lt;/ref&gt; from the Arabic name ''al-Jazāʾir'' ({{lang|ar|الجزائر}}), &quot;The Islands&quot;. This name refers to the four former islands which lay off the city's coast before becoming part of the mainland in 1525. ''Al-Jazāʾir'' is itself a truncated form of the city's older name ''Jazaʾir Banī Mazghanna'' ({{lang|ar|جزائر بني مزغانة}}), &quot;The Islands of the [[Banu Mazghanna|Sons of Mazghana]]&quot;, used by early medieval geographers such as [[al-Idrisi]] and [[Yaqut al-Hamawi]].

In [[classical antiquity|antiquity]], the [[ancient Greek geography|Greeks]] knew the town as ''Ikósion'' ({{lang-grc|Ἰκόσιον}}), which was [[latinization of names|Latinized]] as [[Icosium]] under [[Roman Republic|Roman rule]]. The Greeks [[folk etymology|explained the name]] as coming from their word for &quot;twenty&quot; ({{lang|grc|εἴκοσι}}, ''eíkosi''), supposedly because it had been founded by 20 companions of [[Hercules]] when he visited the [[Atlas Mountains]] during [[Labors of Hercules|his labors]].&lt;ref name=backtalk&gt;{{harvp|Lipiński|2004|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=SLSzNfdcqfoC&amp;pg=PA403 403]}}.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Algiers is also known as ''el-Behdja'' ({{lang|ar|البهجة}}, &quot;The Joyous&quot;) or &quot;Algiers the White&quot; ({{lang-fr|Alger la Blanche|links=no}}) for its whitewashed buildings, seen rising from the sea.

==History==
{{see also|Timeline of Algiers}}

===Early history===
{{main|Icosium}}
A small [[Phoenicians|Phoenician]] [[Phoenician colonies|colony]] on Algiers's former islands was established and taken over by the [[Carthaginian Empire|Carthaginians]] sometime before the 3rd century{{nbsp}}{{sc|bc}}. After the [[Punic Wars]], the [[Roman Republic|Romans]] eventually took over administration of the town, which they called [[Icosium]]. Its ruins now form part of the modern city's marine quarter, with the Rue de la Marine following a former [[Roman road]]. Roman cemeteries existed near ''[[Bab-el-Oued]]'' and ''[[Bab Azoun]]''. The city was given [[Latin citizenship|Latin rights]] by the emperor [[Vespasian]]. The [[bishop]]s of Icosium are mentioned as late as the 5th century,{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=655}} but the ancient town fell into obscurity during the [[Muslim conquest of the Maghreb|Muslim conquest of North Africa]].

The present city was founded in 944 by [[Bologhine ibn Ziri]], the founder of the [[Berber people|Berber]] [[Zirid]]–[[Sanhaja]] dynasty.  He had earlier (935) built his own house and a [[Sanhaja]] center at Ashir, just south of Algiers.  Although his Zirid dynasty was overthrown by [[Roger II of Sicily]] in 1148, the Zirids had already lost control of Algiers to their cousins the [[Hammadid]]s in 1014.&lt;ref&gt;Ruedy, John Douglas (2005) ''Modern Algeria: The origins and development of a nation'' Indiana University Press, Bloomington, Indiana [https://books.google.com/books?id=WIRWgrbE_fEC&amp;pg=PA13 page 13] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160517220646/https://books.google.com/books?id=WIRWgrbE_fEC&amp;pg=PA13 |date=2016-05-17 }}, {{ISBN|978-0-253-21782-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; The city was wrested from the Hammadids by the [[Almohads]] in 1159, and in the 13th century came under the dominion of the [[Ziyanid]] sultans of [[Kingdom of Tlemcen|Tlemcen]]. Nominally part of the sultanate of Tlemcen, Algiers had a large measure of independence under [[amir]]s of its own due to [[Oran]] being the chief seaport of the Ziyanids.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=655}}

The [[Peñón of Algiers]], an islet in front of Algiers harbour had been occupied by the Spaniards as early as 1302. Thereafter, a considerable amount of trade began to flow between Algiers and [[Spain]]. However, Algiers continued to be of comparatively little importance until after the [[Reconquista#Conversions and expulsions|expulsion of the Moors]] from Spain, many of whom sought asylum in the city. In 1510, following their occupation of Oran and other towns on the coast of Africa, the Spaniards fortified the islet of Peñon{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=655}} and imposed a levy intended to suppress [[Barbary corsairs|corsair]] activity.&lt;ref&gt;Celik, Zeynep, ''Urban Forms and Colonial Confrontations: Algiers Under French Rule'', University of California Press, 1997, p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;

===[[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] rule===
[[File:Duquesne fait liberer des captifs chretiens apres le bombardement d Alger en 1683.jpg|thumb|[[Abraham Duquesne]] delivering Christian captives in Algiers after the bombing in 1683.]]
In 1516, the amir of Algiers, Selim b. Teumi, invited the corsair brothers [[Aruj]] and [[Barbarossa (Ottoman admiral)|Hayreddin ''Barbarossa'']] to expel the Spaniards. Aruj came to Algiers, ordered the assassination of Selim, and seized the town and ousted the Spanish in the [[Capture of Algiers (1516)]]. Hayreddin, succeeding Aruj after the latter was killed in battle against the Spaniards in the [[Fall of Tlemcen (1517)]], was the founder of the ''[[pashaluk]]'', which subsequently became the ''[[bey]]lik'', of Algeria. Barbarossa lost Algiers in 1524 but regained it with the [[Capture of Algiers (1529)]], and then formally invited the Sultan [[Suleiman the Magnificent]] to accept sovereignty over the territory and to annex Algiers to the [[Ottoman Empire]].

[[File:Algiers and Bejaia by Piri Reis.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Historic map of Algiers by [[Piri Reis]]]]
{{Anchor|Algerine}}&lt;!-- common name for inhabitants of the area at this time &quot;Algerine&quot; redirect here do not remove--&gt;
Algiers from this time became the chief seat of the [[Barbary pirates]]. In October 1541 in the [[Algiers expedition (1541)|Algiers expedition]], the King of Spain and Holy Roman Emperor [[Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor|Charles V]] sought to capture the city, but a storm destroyed a great number of his ships, and his army of some 30,000, chiefly made up of Spaniards, was defeated by the Algerians under their [[Pasha]], Hassan.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=655}}
[[File:Sm Bombardment of Algiers, August 1816-Luny.jpg|thumb|left|The bombardment of Algiers by Lord Exmouth, August 1816, painted by Thomas Luny]]
[[File:Ottoman cannon end of 16th century length 385cm cal 178mm weight 2910 stone projectile founded 8 October 1581 Alger seized 1830.jpg|right|thumb|Ornate [[Ottoman weapons|Ottoman cannon]] found in Algiers on 8 October 1581 by Ca'fer el-Mu'allim. Length: 385&amp;nbsp;cm, cal:178&amp;nbsp;mm, weight: 2910&amp;nbsp;kg, stone projectile. Seized by France during the [[invasion of Algiers in 1830]]. [[Musée de l'Armée]], [[Paris]].]]

Formally part of the Ottoman Empire but essentially free from Ottoman control, starting in the 16th century Algiers turned to piracy and ransoming. Due to its location on the periphery of both the Ottoman and European economic spheres, and depending for its existence on a Mediterranean that was increasingly controlled by European shipping, backed by European navies, piracy became the primary economic activity. Repeated attempts were made by various nations to subdue the pirates that disturbed shipping in the western Mediterranean and engaged in slave raids as far north as Iceland.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.heimaslod.is/index.php/Tyrkjar%C3%A1ni%C3%B0 |title=Tyrkjaránið – Heimaslóð |language=is |publisher=Heimaslod.is |accessdate=2010-06-27 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110527072348/http://www.heimaslod.is/index.php/Tyrkjar%C3%A1ni%C3%B0 |archive-date=2011-05-27 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[United States]] fought two wars (the [[First Barbary War|First]] and [[Second Barbary War]]s) over Algiers' attacks on shipping.

Among the notable people held for ransom was the future Spanish novelist [[Miguel de Cervantes]], who was captive in Algiers almost five years, and who wrote two plays set in Algiers of the period. The primary source for knowledge of Algiers of this period, since there are no contemporary local sources, is the ''Topografía e historia general de Argel'' (1612, but written earlier), published by Diego de Haedo, but whose authorship is disputed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite article
|first=Daniel
|last=Eisenberg
|author-link=:es:Daniel Eisenberg
|title=Cervantes, autor de la ''Topografía e historia general de Argel'' publicada por Diego de Haedo
|journal=Cervantes: Bulletin of the Cervantes Society of America
|volume=16
|number=1
|year=1996
|pages=32–53
|url=http://www.h-net.org/~cervantes/csa/artics96/topograf.htm |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150318061159/http://www.h-net.org/~cervantes/csa/artics96/topograf.htm |archive-date=2015-03-18}} Others have disputed Eisenberg's attribution of the work to Cervantes.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|author-link=:es:Daniel Eisenberg
|first=Daniel
|last=Eisenberg
|contribution=¿Por qué volvió Cervantes de Argel?&quot; (&quot;Why Did Cervantes return from Algiers?
|title=''Ingeniosa invención'': Essays on Golden Age Spanish Literature for Geoffrey L. Stagg in Honor of his Eighty-Fifth Birthday
|location=[[Newark, Delaware]]
|publisher=Juan de la Cuesta
|year=1999
|ISBN=0936388838
|pages=241–253
|url=http://users.ipfw.edu/jehle/deisenbe/cervantes/argel.pdf |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304045937/http://users.ipfw.edu/jehle/deisenbe/cervantes/argel.pdf
|archive-date=2016-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; This work describes in detail the city, the behavior of its inhabitants, and its military defenses, with the unsuccessful hope of facilitating an attack by Spain so as to end the piracy.

A significant number of renegades lived in Algiers at the time, Christians converted voluntarily to [[Islam]], many fleeing the law or other problems at home. Once converted to Islam, they were safe in Algiers. Many occupied positions of authority, such as [[Samson Rowlie]], an Englishman who became Treasurer of Algiers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-35843991|title=The First Muslims in England|website=BBC News|language=en-GB|access-date=2016-03-21|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160321043520/http://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-35843991|archive-date=2016-03-21|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The city under Ottoman control was enclosed by a wall on all sides, including along the seafront. In this wall, five gates allowed access to the city, with five roads from each gate dividing the city and meeting in front of the Ketchaoua Mosque. In 1556, a citadel was constructed at the highest point in the wall. A major road running north to south divided the city in two: The upper city (al-Gabal, or 'the mountain') which consisted of about fifty small quarters of [[Andalusian people|Andalusian]], [[Jew]]ish, [[Moors|Moorish]] and [[Kabyle people|Kabyle]] communities, and the lower city (al-Wata, or 'the plains') which was the administrative, military and commercial centre of the city, mostly inhabited by Turkish dignitaries and other upper-class families.&lt;ref&gt;Celik, Zeynep, ''Urban Forms and Colonial Confrontations: Algiers Under French Rule'', University of California Press, 1997, pp. 13–14.&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 1816, the city was bombarded by a British squadron under [[Edward Pellew, 1st Viscount Exmouth|Lord Exmouth]] (a descendant of Thomas Pellew, taken in an Algerian slave raid in 1715&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/946180025|title=Africa (a-z).|last=Godfrey.|first=Mugoti,|date=2009|publisher=Lulu Com|isbn=1435728904|location=[Place of publication not identified]|oclc=946180025}}{{self-published source|date=February 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{self-published inline|date=February 2020}}), assisted by [[Netherlands|Dutch]] men-of-war, destroying the corsair fleet harboured in Algiers.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=655}}

===French rule===
[[File:Algiers - depot and station grounds of Algerian Railway LCCN2004707260.tif|thumb|Algiers depot and station grounds of Algerian Railway, 1894]]
The history of Algiers from 1830 to 1962 is bound to the larger history of [[Algeria]] and its relationship to [[France]]. On July 4, 1830, under the pretext of an affront to the French consul—whom the [[dey]] had hit with a [[fly-whisk]] when the consul said the French government was not prepared to pay its large outstanding debts to two Algerian merchants—a French army under [[Louis-Auguste-Victor, Count de Ghaisnes de Bourmont|General de Bourmont]] attacked the city in the [[invasion of Algiers in 1830|1830 invasion of Algiers]]. The city capitulated the following day. Algiers became the capital of [[French Algeria]].

Many Europeans settled in Algiers, and by the early 20th century they formed a majority of the city's population.&lt;ref&gt;Albert Habib Hourani, Malise Ruthven (2002). &quot;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=egbOb0mewz4C&amp;pg=PA323&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false A history of the Arab peoples] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150906022938/https://books.google.com/books?id=egbOb0mewz4C&amp;pg=PA323&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false |date=2015-09-06 }}''&quot;. Harvard University Press. p.323. {{ISBN|0-674-01017-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the 1930s, the architect [[Le Corbusier]] drew up plans for a complete redesign of the colonial city. Le Corbusier was highly critical of the urban style of Algiers, describing the European district as &quot;nothing but crumbling walls and devastated nature, the whole a sullied blot&quot;. He also criticised the difference in living standards he perceived between the European and African residents of the city, describing a situation in which &quot;the 'civilised' live like rats in holes&quot; whereas &quot;the 'barbarians' live in solitude, in well-being&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Celik, Zeynep, ''Urban Forms and Colonial Confrontations: Algiers Under French Rule'', University of California Press, 1997, p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt; However, these plans were ultimately ignored by the French administration.

During [[World War II]], Algiers was the first city to be seized from the Germans by the Allies during [[Operation Torch]].
[[File:Algiers CNE-v1-p58-J.jpg|thumb|left|City and harbour of Algiers, {{circa|1921}}]]

In 1962, after a bloody independence struggle in which hundreds of thousands (estimates range between 350,000 and 1,500,000) died (mostly Algerians but also French and [[Pied-Noir|Pieds-Noirs]]) during fighting between the [[French Army]] and the Algerian [[National Liberation Front (Algeria)|Front de Libération Nationale]], Algeria gained its independence, with Algiers as its capital. Since then, despite losing its entire ''[[pied-noir]]'' population, the city has expanded massively. It now has about five million inhabitants, or 10 percent of Algeria's population—and its suburbs now cover most of the surrounding [[Geography of Algeria|Mitidja]] plain.

===Algerian War===
[[File:1962-03-22 Algeria tense cease fire.ogv|thumb|right|The &quot;tense truce&quot; between Algerian rebels, French army and the OAS in 1962]]
Algiers also played a pivotal role in the [[Algerian War]] (1954–1962), particularly during the [[Algerian War#Battle of Algiers|Battle of Algiers]] when the 10th Parachute Division of the French Army, starting on January 7, 1957, and on the orders of the French Minister of Justice [[François Mitterrand]] (who authorized any means &quot;to eliminate the insurrectionists&quot;{{Citation needed|date=June 2008}}), led attacks against the Algerian fighters for independence. Algiers remains marked by this battle, which was characterized by merciless fighting between FLN forces which carried out a guerrilla campaign against the French military and police and pro-French Algerian soldiers, and the French Army which responded with a bloody repression, torture and blanket terrorism against the native population. The demonstrations of May 13 during the crisis of 1958 provoked the fall of the [[French Fourth Republic|Fourth Republic]] in France, as well as the return of General [[Charles de Gaulle|de Gaulle]] to power.

===Independence===
Algeria achieved [[independence]] on July 5, 1962. Run by the FLN that had secured independence, Algiers became a member of [[Non-Aligned Movement]] during the [[Cold War]]. In October 1988, one year before the fall of the [[Berlin Wall]], Algiers was the site of demonstrations demanding the end of the single-party system and the creation of a ''real'' [[democracy]] baptized the &quot;Spring of Algier&quot;. The demonstrators were repressed by the authorities (more than 300 dead), but the movement constituted a turning point in the political history of modern Algeria. In 1989, a new constitution was adopted that put an end to the one-party rule and saw the creation of more than fifty political parties, as well as official freedom of the press.

===Crisis of the 1990s===
The city became the theatre of many political demonstrations of all descriptions until 1993. In 1991, a political entity dominated by religious conservatives called the [[Islamic Salvation Front]] engaged in a political test of wills with the authorities. In the 1992 elections for the Algerian National Assembly, the Islamists garnered a large amount of support in the first round, helped by a massive abstention from disillusioned Algerian voters by the turn of events. Fearing an eventual win by the Islamists, the army canceled the election process, setting off a [[Algerian Civil War|civil war]] between the State and armed religious conservatives which would last for a decade.

On December 11, 2007, two car [[11 December 2007 Algiers bombings|bombs exploded in Algiers]]. One bomb targeted two United Nations buildings and the other targeted a government building housing the Supreme Court. The death toll was at least 62, with over two hundred injured in the attacks.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Les autorités accusent al-Qaïda|publisher=RFI|url=http://www.rfi.fr/actufr/articles/096/article_60149.asp|accessdate=2007-12-11| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20071213023440/http://www.rfi.fr/actufr/articles/096/article_60149.asp| archivedate= 13 December 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, only 26 remained hospitalized the following day.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Toll in Algiers bombings rises to 31 |agency=Associated Press |url=https://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20071212/ap_on_re_af/algeria_explosion |accessdate=2007-12-12 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071214021257/http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20071212/ap_on_re_af/algeria_explosion |archivedate=2007-12-14 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; {{as of|2008}}, it is speculated that the attack was carried out by the Al Qaida cell within the city.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Al Qaeda blamed for Algeria bombs|publisher=CNN|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2007/WORLD/africa/12/11/algeria.blast/index.html|accessdate=2007-12-11 | date=2007-12-12| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20071212153122/http://edition.cnn.com/2007/WORLD/africa/12/11/algeria.blast/index.html| archivedate= 12 December 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Indigenous terrorist groups have been actively [[Islamic insurgency in Algeria (2002–present)#2007|operating in Algeria since around 2002]].

==Geography==

===Districts of Algiers===
[[File:NOTRE DAME D'AFRIQUE.ALGER.jpg|thumb|[[Notre Dame d'Afrique]], built by European settlers in 1872&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.wdl.org/en/item/8766/ |title = Notre Dame d’Afrique and Carmelite Convent, Algiers, Algeria |website = [[World Digital Library]] |year = 1899 |accessdate = 2013-09-25 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20130927125818/http://www.wdl.org/en/item/8766/ |archive-date = 2013-09-27 |url-status = live }}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
* '''[[Casbah of Algiers|The Casbah]]''' (of '' Al Qasbah'', “the Citadel”), Ier District of Algiers: called '' Al-Djazaïr Al Mahroussa '' (“Well Kept Algiers”), it is founded on the ruins of old Icosium. It is a small city which, built on a hill, goes down towards the sea, divided in two: the High city and the Low city. One finds there masonries and mosques of the 17th century; Ketchaoua mosque (built in 1794 by the Dey Baba Hassan) flanked by two minarets, mosque el Djedid (built in 1660, at the time of Turkish regency) with its large finished ovoid cupola points some and its four coupolettes, mosque El Kébir (oldest of the mosques, it was built by [[Almoravid]] [[Youssef Ibn Tachfin]] and rebuilt later in 1794), mosque Ali Betchnin (Raïs, 1623), Dar Aziza, palate of Jénina. In the Kasbah, there are also labyrinths of lanes and houses that are very picturesque, and if one gets lost there, it is enough to go down again towards the sea to reposition oneself.
* ''' [[Bab El Oued]]''': Literally ''the River's Gate'', the popular district which extends from the Casbah beyond &quot;the gate of the river&quot;. It is the capital's darling and best liked borough. Famous for its square with “the three clocks” and for its “market Triplet”, it is also a district of workshops and manufacturing plants.
* ''' [[Edge of sea]]''': from 1840, the architects Pierre-August Guiauchain and [[Charles Frédéric Chassériau]] designed new buildings apart from the Casbah, town hall, law courts, buildings, theatre, palace of the Governor, and casino, to form an elegant walk bordered by arcades which is today the boulevard [[Che Guevara]] (formerly the Boulevard of the [[Republic]]).
* ''' [[Kouba, Algeria|Kouba]]''' ([[will daira]] of [[Hussein-dey]]): Kouba is an old village which was absorbed by the expansion of the town of Algiers. Kouba quickly developed under the French colonial era then continued growing due to formidable demographic expansion that Algiers saw after the independence of Algeria in 1962. It is today a district of Algiers which is largely made up of houses, villas and buildings not exceeding five stories.
* [[El Harrach]], a suburb of Algiers, is located about {{convert|10|km|0|abbr=off}} to the east of the city.
* The communes of [[Hydra (Algiers) will|Hydra]], [[Ben Aknoun]], [[El-Biar]] and [[Bouzareah]] form what the inhabitants of Algiers call the &quot;Heights of Algiers&quot;. These communes shelter the majority of the foreign embassies of Algiers, of many ministries and university centers, which makes it one of the administrative and policy centers of the country.
* The  '''Didouche Mourad street''' is located in the 3rd district Of Algiers. It extends from the '''Grande Post office''' to the Heights of Algiers. It crosses in particular the '''place Audin''', '''the Faculty of Algiers''', '''The Crowned Heart''' and '''the park of Galland'''. It is bordered by smart stores and restaurants along most of its length. It is regarded as the heart of the capital.
[[File:Algiers, Algeria.jpg|thumb|Astronautical view of Algiers]]

===Climate===
Algiers has a [[Mediterranean climate]] ([[Köppen climate classification]] ''Csa''). Its proximity to the [[Mediterranean Sea]] aids in moderating the city's temperatures. As a result, Algiers usually does not see the extreme temperatures that are experienced in the adjacent interior. Algiers on average receives roughly {{convert|600|mm|in|0}} of rain per year, the bulk of which is seen between October and April. The precipitation is higher than in most of coastal Mediterranean [[Spain]], and similar to most of coastal Mediterranean [[France]], as opposed to the interior North African semi-arid or arid climate.

Snow is very rare; in 2012, the city received {{convert|100|mm|in|0}}, its first snowfall in eight years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=European Chill Moves West, 122 Die in Ukraine |first=Richard |last=Balmforth |date=4 February 2012 |work=Reuters |url=https://www.reuters.com/article/2012/02/04/us-europe-weather-idUSTRE8130NK20120204 |access-date=30 June 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140914142912/http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/02/04/us-europe-weather-idUSTRE8130NK20120204 |archive-date=14 September 2014 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Weather box
|location = Algiers (Dar El Beïda international airport) 1976–2005 averages, extremes 1838–present
|metric first = yes
|single line = yes
|Jan record high C = 27.6
|Feb record high C = 31.4
|Mar record high C = 36.3
|Apr record high C = 36.5
|May record high C = 41.1
|Jun record high C = 44.6
|Jul record high C = 45.2
|Aug record high C = 47.5
|Sep record high C = 44.4
|Oct record high C = 39.5
|Nov record high C = 34.4
|Dec record high C = 30.4
|year record high C = 47.5
|Jan high C = 16.7
|Feb high C = 17.4
|Mar high C = 19.3
|Apr high C = 20.9
|May high C = 23.9
|Jun high C = 28.2
|Jul high C = 31.2
|Aug high C = 32.2
|Sep high C = 29.6
|Oct high C = 25.9
|Nov high C = 20.8
|Dec high C = 17.9
|year high C = 23.7
|Jan mean C = 11.1
|Feb mean C = 11.7
|Mar mean C = 13.2
|Apr mean C = 14.9
|May mean C = 18.1
|Jun mean C = 22.2
|Jul mean C = 25.1
|Aug mean C = 26.0
|Sep mean C = 23.6
|Oct mean C = 20.1
|Nov mean C = 15.3
|Dec mean C = 12.6
|year mean C = 17.8
|Jan low C = 5.5
|Feb low C = 5.9
|Mar low C = 7.1
|Apr low C = 8.8
|May low C = 12.3
|Jun low C = 16.1
|Jul low C = 18.9
|Aug low C = 19.8
|Sep low C = 17.6
|Oct low C = 14.2
|Nov low C = 9.8
|Dec low C = 7.2
|year low C = 11.9
|Jan record low C = -3.3
|Feb record low C = -1.9
|Mar record low C = -1.0
|Apr record low C = -0.8
|May record low C = 2.6
|Jun record low C = 5.5
|Jul record low C = 9.0
|Aug record low C = 9.5
|Sep record low C = 8.2
|Oct record low C = 4.1
|Nov record low C = -0.1
|Dec record low C = -2.3
|year record low C = -3.3
|precipitation colour = green
|Jan precipitation mm = 81.4
|Feb precipitation mm = 72.7
|Mar precipitation mm = 55.0
|Apr precipitation mm = 58.4
|May precipitation mm = 41.9
|Jun precipitation mm = 8.5
|Jul precipitation mm = 4.5
|Aug precipitation mm = 8.2
|Sep precipitation mm = 28.3
|Oct precipitation mm = 58.8
|Nov precipitation mm = 89.6
|Dec precipitation mm = 91.0
|year precipitation mm = 598.3
|unit precipitation days = 0.1 mm
|Jan precipitation days = 11.4
|Feb precipitation days = 10.6
|Mar precipitation days = 9.7
|Apr precipitation days = 9.1
|May precipitation days = 7.3
|Jun precipitation days = 2.5
|Jul precipitation days = 1.5
|Aug precipitation days = 2.5
|Sep precipitation days = 5.3
|Oct precipitation days = 8.6
|Nov precipitation days = 11.1
|Dec precipitation days = 12.1
|year precipitation days = 91.7
|Jan humidity = 71
|Feb humidity = 66
|Mar humidity = 65
|Apr humidity = 62
|May humidity = 66
|Jun humidity = 66
|Jul humidity = 67
|Aug humidity = 65
|Sep humidity = 68
|Oct humidity = 66
|Nov humidity = 68
|Dec humidity = 68
|year humidity = 67
|Jan sun = 139.5
|Feb sun = 158.2
|Mar sun = 207.7
|Apr sun = 228.0
|May sun = 300.7
|Jun sun = 300.0
|Jul sun = 353.4
|Aug sun = 325.5
|Sep sun = 267.0
|Oct sun = 198.4
|Nov sun = 153.0
|Dec sun = 145.7
|year sun = 2777.1
|Jand sun = 4.5
|Febd sun = 5.6
|Mard sun = 6.7
|Aprd sun = 7.6
|Mayd sun = 9.7
|Jund sun = 10.0
|Juld sun = 11.4
|Augd sun = 10.5
|Sepd sun = 8.9
|Octd sun = 6.4
|Novd sun = 5.1
|Decd sun = 4.7
|yeard sun = 7.6
|source 1 = [[World Meteorological Organization]] (average temperatures and precipitation, 1976–2005)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://worldweather.wmo.int/en/city.html?cityId=242
| title = World Weather Information Service–Algiers
| publisher = World Meteorological Organization
| accessdate = 16 October 2016
| archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20161018205356/http://worldweather.wmo.int/en/city.html?cityId=242
| archive-date = 18 October 2016
| url-status = live
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|source 2 = Arab Meteorology Book (humidity and sun),&lt;ref name=climate&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://extras.springer.com/2007/978-1-4020-4577-6/Book_Shahin_ISBN_9781402045776_Appendix.pdf
| title = Appendix I: Meteorological Data
| publisher = Springer
| accessdate = 16 October 2016
| archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20160304072830/http://extras.springer.com/2007/978-1-4020-4577-6/Book_Shahin_ISBN_9781402045776_Appendix.pdf
| archive-date = 4 March 2016
| url-status = live
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Meteo Climat (record highs and lows)&lt;ref name = meteoclimat&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://meteo-climat-bzh.dyndns.org/index.php?page=stati&amp;id=15
| title = Station Alger
| publisher = Meteo Climat
|language = French
| accessdate = 16 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|date=January 2011}}

==Government==
:''See also: Algiers politics and administration ([[:fr:Alger#Administration et politique|fr]]) and [[List of mayors of Algiers]]''
The city (and province) of Algiers is composed of 13 administrative districts, sub-divided into 57 ''communes'' listed below with their populations at the 1998 and 2008 Censuses:

{|  class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; 
! '''Name'''
! '''Name in &lt;br&gt; Arabic '''
! '''Population&lt;br&gt;(1998)'''&lt;ref&gt;Census of 25 June 1998: Office National des Statistiques de l'Algérie (web).&lt;/ref&gt;
! '''Population&lt;br&gt;(2008)'''&lt;ref&gt;Census 14 April 2008: Office National des Statistiques de l'Algérie (web).&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Bab El Oued]]
| باب الوادي	
| align=right | 87,557
| align=right | 64,732
|-
| [[Bologhine]]
| بولوغين	
| align=right | 43,283
| align=right | 43,835
|-
| [[Casbah of Algiers|Casbah]]
| القصبة	
| align=right | 50,453
| align=right | 36,762
|-
| [[Oued Koriche]]
| وادي قريش	
| align=right | 53,378
| align=right | 46,182
|-
| [[Raïs Hamidou, Algeria|Raïs Hamidou]]
| الرايس حميدو	
| align=right | 21,518
| align=right | 28,451
|-
| '''''[[Bab El Oued District]]'''''
| 	
| align=right | 256,189
| align=right | 219,962
|-
| [[Baraki, Algiers|Baraki]]
| براقي	
| align=right | 95,247
| align=right | 116,375
|-
| [[Les Eucalyptus]]
| الكليتوس	
| align=right | 96,310
| align=right | 116,107
|-
| [[Sidi Moussa, Algeria|Sidi Moussa]]
| سيدي موسى	
| align=right | 27,888
| align=right | 40,750
|-
| '''''[[Baraki District]]'''''
|
| align=right | 219,445
| align=right | 273,232
|-
| [[Bir Mourad Raïs]]
| بئر مراد رايس	
| align=right | 43,254
| align=right | 45,345
|-
| [[Birkhadem]]
| بئر خادم	
| align=right | 55,084
| align=right | 77,749
|-
| [[Djasr Kasentina]]
| جسر قسنطينة	
| align=right | 82,729
| align=right | 133,247
|-
| [[Hydra (Algiers) will|Hydra]]
| حيدرة	
| align=right | 35,727
| align=right | 31,133
|-
| [[Saoula]]
| سحاولة	
| align=right | 31,388
| align=right | 41,690
|-
| '''''[[Bir Mourad Raïs District]]'''''
| 	
| align=right | 248,182
| align=right | 329,164
|-
| [[Birtouta]]
| بئر توتة	
| align=right | 21,808
| align=right | 30,575
|-
| [[Ouled Chebel]]
| أولاد الشبل	
| align=right | 16,335
| align=right | 20,006
|-
| [[Tessala El Merdja]]
| تسالة المرجى	
| align=right | 10,792
| align=right | 15,847
|-
| '''''[[Birtouta District]]'''''
| 
| align=right | 48,935
| align=right | 66,428
|-
| [[Ben Aknoun]]
| بن عكنون	
| align=right | 19,404
| align=right | 18,838
|-
| [[Beni Messous]]
| بني مسوس	
| align=right | 17,490
| align=right | 36,191
|-
| [[Bouzareah]]
| بوزريعة	
| align=right | 69,153
| align=right | 83,797
|-
| [[El-Biar|El Biar]]
| الأبيار	
| align=right | 52,582
| align=right | 47,332
|-
| '''''[[Bouzareah District]]'''''
| 
| align=right | 158,629
| align=right | 186,158
|-
| [[Aïn Bénian, Algiers|Aïn Bénian]]
| عين البنيان
| align=right | 52,343
| align=right | 68,354
|-
| [[Chéraga]]
| الشراقة	
| align=right | 60,374
| align=right | 80,824
|-
| [[Dely Ibrahim]]
| دالي إبرهيم	
| align=right | 30,576
| align=right | 35,230
|-
| [[El Hammamet]]
| الحمامات الرومانية	
| align=right | 19,651
| align=right | 23,990
|-
| [[Ouled Fayet]]
| أولاد فايت	
| align=right | 15,209
| align=right | 27,593
|-
| '''''[[Chéraga District]]'''''
| 
| align=right | 178,153
| align=right | 235,991
|-
| [[Aïn Taya]]
| عين طاية
| align=right | 29,515
| align=right | 34,501
|-
| [[Bab Ezzouar]]
| باب الزوار	
| align=right | 92,157
| align=right | 96,597
|-
| [[Bordj El Bahri]]
| برج البحري	
| align=right | 27,905
| align=right | 52,816
|-
| [[Bordj El Kiffan]]
| برج الكيفان	
| align=right | 103,690
| align=right | 151,950
|-
| [[Dar El Beïda]]
| الدار البيضاء	
| align=right | 44,753
| align=right | 80,033
|-
| [[El Marsa, Algiers|El Marsa]]
| المرسى	
| align=right | 8,784
| align=right | 12,100
|-
| [[Mohammedia, Algiers|Mohammedia]]
| المحمدية 	
| align=right | 42,079
| align=right | 62,543
|-
| '''''[[Dar El Beïda District]]'''''
| 
| align=right | 348,883
| align=right | 490,540
|-
| [[Baba Hassen]]
| بابا حسن	
| align=right | 13,827
| align=right | 23,756
|-
| [[Douera]]
| دويرة	
| align=right | 41,804
| align=right | 56,998
|-
| [[Draria]]
| درارية	
| align=right | 23,050
| align=right | 44,141
|-
| [[El Achour]]
| العاشور	
| align=right | 19,524
| align=right | 41,070
|-
| [[Khraicia]]
| خراسية	
| align=right | 17,690
| align=right | 27,910
|-
| '''''[[Draria District]]'''''
| 
| align=right | 115,895
| align=right | 193,875
|-
| [[Bachdjerrah]]
| باش جراح	
| align=right | 90,073
| align=right | 93,289
|-
| [[Bourouba]]
| بوروبة	
| align=right | 77,498
| align=right | 71,661
|-
| [[El Harrach]]
| الحراش	
| align=right | 48,167
| align=right | 48,869
|-
| [[Oued Smar]]
| وادي سمار	
| align=right | 21,397
| align=right | 32,062
|-
| '''''[[El Harrach District]]'''''
| 	
| align=right | 237,135
| align=right | 245,881
|-
| [[El Magharia]]
| المغارية	
| align=right | 30,457
| align=right | 31,453
|-
| [[Hussein Dey (commune)|Hussein Dey]]
| حسين داي	
| align=right | 49,921
| align=right | 40,698
|-
| [[Kouba, Algeria|Kouba]]
| القبة	
| align=right | 105,253
| align=right | 104,708
|-
| [[Mohamed Belouizdad]] &lt;br&gt;(Hamma Annassers)
| الحامة العناصر	
| align=right | 59,248
| align=right | 44,050
|-
| '''''[[Hussein Dey District]]'''''
| 
| align=right | 244,879
| align=right | 220,909
|-
| [[Haraoua]]
| الهراوة	
| align=right | 18,167
| align=right | 27,565
|-
| [[Reghaïa]]
| رغاية	
| align=right | 66,215
| align=right | 85,452
|-
| [[Rouïba]]
| الرويبة	
| align=right | 49,881
| align=right | 61,984
|-
| '''''[[Rouïba District]]'''''
| 	
| align=right | 134,263
| align=right | 175,001
|-
| [[El Djazaïr|Alger Centre]]
| الجزائرالوسطى	
| align=right | 96,329
| align=right | 75,541
|-
| [[El Madania]]
| المدنية	
| align=right | 51,404
| align=right | 40,301
|-
| [[El Mouradia]]
| المرادية	
| align=right | 29,503
| align=right | 22,813
|-
| [[Sidi M'Hamed]]
| سيدي امحمد	
| align=right | 90,455
| align=right | 67,873
|-
| '''''[[Sidi M'Hamed District]]'''''
| 
| align=right | 267,691
| align=right | 206,528
|-
| [[Mahelma]]
| محالمة	
| align=right | 14,810
| align=right | 20,758
|-
| [[Rahmania]]
| الرحمانية	
| align=right | 5,759
| align=right | 7,396
|-
| [[Souidania]]
| سويدانية	
| align=right | 11,620
| align=right | 17,105
|-
| [[Staoueli]]
| سطاوالي	
| align=right | 38,915
| align=right | 47,664
|-
| [[Zéralda]]
| زرالدة	
| align=right | 33,047
| align=right | 51,552
|-
| '''''[[Zéralda District]]'''''
| 	
| align=right | 104,151
| align=right | 144,475
|-
| '''''Totals'''''
| الجزائر	
| align=right | 2,562,428
| align=right | 2,988,145
|-
|}

==Local architecture==
[[File:Alger front de mer.jpg|thumb|upright=1.65|Algiers waterfront]]
[[File:Algeri04.jpg|thumb|Cosmopolitan Algiers]]

There are many public buildings of interest, including the whole [[Kasbah]] quarter, Martyrs Square (''Sahat ech-Chouhada'' ساحة الشهداء), the government offices (formerly the [[United Kingdom|British]] consulate), the &quot;Grand&quot;, &quot;New&quot;, and Ketchaoua [[Mosque]]s, the [[Roman Catholic]] cathedral of [[Notre Dame d'Afrique]], the [[Bardo National Museum of Prehistory and Ethnography|Bardo Museum]] (a former Turkish mansion), the old ''Bibliothèque Nationale d'Alger''—a [[Turkey|Turkish]] palace built in 1799–1800{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=654}}—and the new [[National Library of Algeria|National Library]], built in a style reminiscent of the [[British Library]].

The main building in the Kasbah was begun in 1516 on the site of an older building, and served as the palace of the deys until the French conquest. A road has been cut through the centre of the building, the mosque turned into [[barracks]], and the hall of audience allowed to fall into ruin. There still remain a [[minaret]] and some marble arches and columns. Traces exist of the vaults in which were stored the treasures of the dey.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=654}}

[[Djamaa el Kebir]] (''Jamaa-el-Kebir'' الجامع الكبير) is the oldest mosque in Algiers. It was first built by [[Yusuf ibn Tashfin]], but reconstructed many times. The pulpit (''[[minbar]]'' منبر) bears an inscription showing that the building existed in 1097. The minaret was built by the sultan of [[Tlemcen]], in 1324.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.wdl.org/en/item/8764/ |title = Fountain in Mosque of El Kebir, Algiers, Algeria |website = [[World Digital Library]] |year = 1899 |accessdate = 2013-09-24 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20130927125712/http://www.wdl.org/en/item/8764/ |archive-date = 2013-09-27 |url-status = live }}&lt;/ref&gt; The interior of the mosque is square and is divided into aisles by columns joined by [[Moors|Moorish]] arches.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=654}}

The New Mosque (''Jamaa-el-Jedid'' الجامع الجديد), dating from the 17th century, is in the form of a [[Greek cross]], surmounted by a large white cupola, with four small cupolas at the corners. The minaret is {{convert|27|m|0}} high. The interior resembles that of the Grand Mosque.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=654}}

The church of the Holy Trinity (built in 1870) stands at the southern end of the ''rue d'Isly'' near the site of the demolished Fort Bab Azoun باب عزون. The interior is richly decorated with various coloured marbles. Many of these marbles contain memorial inscriptions relating to the British residents (voluntary and involuntary) of Algiers from the time of John Tipton, the first English consul, in 1580 (NB Some sources give 1585). One tablet records that in 1631 two Algerine pirate crews landed in [[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]], sacked [[Baltimore, County Cork|Baltimore]], and enslaved its inhabitants.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=654}}

[[File:Mosquée Ketchaoua.jpg|thumb|left|upright|The Ketchaoua Mosque]]

The Ketchaoua mosque (''Djamaa Ketchaoua'' جامع كتشاوة), at the foot of the Casbah, was before independence in 1962 the cathedral of St Philippe, itself made in 1845 from a mosque dating from 1612. The principal entrance, reached by a flight of 23 steps, is ornamented with a [[portico]] supported by four black-veined marble columns. The roof of the nave is of [[Moorish Empire|Moorish]] [[plaster]] work. It rests on a series of arcades supported by white marble columns. Several of these columns belonged to the original mosque. In one of the chapels was a tomb containing the bones of [[San Geronimo]].{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=654}} The building seems a curious blend of Moorish and [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine]] styles.

Algiers possesses a college with schools of law, medicine, science and letters. The college buildings are large and handsome. The [[Bardo National Museum|Bardo Museum]] in [[Tunisia]] holds some of the ancient sculptures and mosaics discovered in Algeria, together with medals and Algerian money.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=654}}

The port of Algiers is sheltered from all winds. There are two harbours, both artificial—the old or northern harbour and the southern or Agha harbour. The northern harbour covers an area of {{convert|95|ha|acre|0}}. An opening in the south [[jetty]] affords an entrance into Agha harbour, constructed in Agha Bay. Agha harbour has also an independent entrance on its southern side. The inner harbour was begun in 1518 by [[Khair-ad-Din Barbarossa]] (see History, below), who, to accommodated his pirate vessels, caused the island on which was Fort Penon to be connected with the mainland by a [[mole (architecture)|mole]]. The lighthouse which occupies the site of [[Fort Penon]] was built in 1544.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=654}}

Algiers was a walled city from the time of the deys until the close of the 19th century. The French, after their occupation of the city (1830), built a [[Defensive wall|rampart]], [[parapet]] and [[ditch (fortification)|ditch]], with two terminal forts, [[Bab Azoun]] باب عزون to the south and [[Bab-el-Oued]] اد to the north. The forts and part of the ramparts were demolished at the beginning of the 20th century, when a line of forts occupying the heights of [[Bouzareah]] بوزريعة (at an elevation of {{convert|396|m|0}} above the sea) took their place.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=654}}

[[Notre Dame d'Afrique]], a church built (1858–1872) in a mixture of the [[Roman Empire|Roman]] and [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine]] styles, is conspicuously situated overlooking the sea, on the shoulder of the [[Bouzareah]] hills, {{convert|3|km|0|abbr=on}}
to the north of the city. Above the altar is a statue of the [[Mary, the mother of Jesus|Virgin]] depicted as a black woman. The church also contains a solid silver statue of the [[archangel Michael]], belonging to the confraternity of [[Naples|Neapolitan]] fishermen.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911|p=655}}

[[Villa Abd-el-Tif]], former residence of the [[dey]], was used during the French period, to accommodate French artists, chiefly painters, and winners of the [[Abd-el-Tif prize]], among whom [[Maurice Boitel]], for a while of two years. Nowadays, Algerian artists are back in the villa's studios.

==Monuments==
[[File:Makamelchahid.JPG|thumb|right|The Monument of the Martyrs (Maquam E’chahid)]]
[[File:Alger - Grande Poste.jpg|thumb|right|Grand Post Office]]
* [[Notre Dame d'Afrique]], accessible by one [[Aerial tramway|cable car]], is one of the city's most outstanding monuments: located in the district of Z' will ghara, the basilica was built around 1858.
* [[Monument des Martyrs]] (''Marquand E' chahid''): an iconic concrete monument commemorating the [[Algerian War|Algerian war for independence]]. The monument was opened in 1982 on the 20th anniversary of Algeria's independence. It is fashioned in the shape of three standing palm leaves which shelter the &quot;Eternal Flame&quot; beneath. At the edge of each palm leaf stands a statue of a soldier, each representing a stage of Algeria's struggle.
[[File:Algiers mosque.jpg|thumb|left|upright|The El Jedid mosque at the Place des Martyrs]]
* The El Jedid mosque at the Place des Martyrs near the port.
* Place of the Emir Abdelkader (formerly [[Thomas-Robert Bugeaud|Bugeaud]]): in memory of the famous emir [[Abd al-Qadir al-Jaza'iri|Abd El-Kader]], resistant during [[French conquest of Algeria]].
* Grand Post Office (1910, by [[Voinot]] and [[Tondoire]]): construction of the neo-Moorish type which is in full centre town of Algiers.
* The Jardin d'essai (''Garden of Test''; ''El-Hamma''): situated in the east of Algiers, it extends over {{convert|80|ha|acre|0}} and contains exotic plants and gardens. It was created in 1832 by A. Hardy.
* Villa Abd-el-Hair, with the top of the Garden of test, one of the old residences of the dey, where until 1962, were placed the artists prizes winner of [[Price Abd-el-Hair]], and in particular [[Maurice Boitel]] and [[Andre Hamburg]].
* Citadel.
* Riadh El-Feth (shopping centre and art gallery).
* [[Ketchaoua Mosque]] (This mosque became the Saint-Philippe cathedral during colonization before becoming again a mosque).
* [[National Library of Algeria|National Library]], is in the district of El HAMMA and was built in the 1990s.
* [[Djamaa el Kebir]] at the [[Rue de la Marine]]. It is the oldest mosque of Algiers and was built during the reign of the [[Almoravid]] sultan [[Yusuf ibn Tashfin]].
* [[Palais des Rais|Le Bastion 23 – Palais des Rais]], built in 1576 by Dey Ramdhan Pacha and located in the lower Casbah in the Bab El Oued neighborhood.

==Demographics==
{| style=&quot;float: right;&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; |-
! style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot; | Year
! style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot; | Population
|-
| 1977 (Census) || style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;| 1,523,000&lt;ref name=&quot;citypopulation.de&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://citypopulation.de/Algeria-Cities.html |title=Archived copy |access-date=2019-03-28 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111001025954/http://citypopulation.de/Algeria-Cities.html |archive-date=2011-10-01 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 1987 (Census) || style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;| 1,507,241&lt;ref name=&quot;citypopulation.de&quot;/&gt;
|-
| 1998 (Census) || style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;| 2,086,212&lt;ref name=&quot;citypopulation.de&quot;/&gt;
|-
| 2008 (Census) || style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;| 2,364,230&lt;ref name=&quot;citypopulation.de&quot;/&gt;
|}

Algiers has a population of about 3,335,418 (2012 estimate).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.world-gazetteer.com/wg.php?x=&amp;men=gadm&amp;lng=en&amp;dat=32&amp;geo=-66&amp;srt=npan&amp;col=aohdq |title=Algiers in the World Gazetteer |publisher=World-gazetteer.com |accessdate=2010-06-27 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070930225838/http://www.world-gazetteer.com/wg.php?x=&amp;men=gadm&amp;lng=en&amp;dat=32&amp;geo=-66&amp;srt=npan&amp;col=aohdq |archive-date=2007-09-30 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ethnic distribution is 53% from an Arabic-speaking background, 44% from a Berber-speaking background and 3% foreign-born.
* 1940 – 300,000 people lived in Algiers.
* 1960 – 900,000 people lived in Algiers.
* 1963 – 600,000 people lived in Algiers.

==Economy==
[[File:El Quds Mall - Cheraga.jpg|thumb|&quot;[[Centre Commercial Al Qods]]&quot; in Algiers]]
[[File:Ministerefinacealger.jpg|thumb|Ministry of Finance of Algeria]]
Algiers is an important economic, commercial and financial center, with in particular a stock exchange with a capitalisation of 60 million euros. The city has the highest cost of living of any city in [[North Africa]], as well as the 50th highest worldwide, as of March 2007, having gained one position compared to the previous year.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.mercerhr.com/costofliving |title=MERCER Human Resources Consulting – Moscow tops Mercer's cost of living list; London is close behind |publisher=Mercerhr.com |accessdate=2010-06-27| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20100701021708/http://www.mercerhr.com/costofliving| archivedate= 1 July 2010 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Mohamed Ben Ali El Abbar, president of the Council of Administration of the Emirate Group EMAAR, presented five &quot;megaprojects&quot; to Algerian President Abdelaziz Bouteflika, during a ceremony which took place Saturday, July 15, within the Palace of the People of Algiers. These projects will transform the city of Algiers and its surroundings by equipping them with a retail area and restoration and leisure facilities.

The first project will concentrate on the reorganization and the development of the infrastructures of the railway station &quot;Aga&quot; located in the downtown area. The ultramodern station intended to accommodate more than 80.000 passengers per day, will become a center of circulation in the heart of the grid system, surrounded by commercial offices and buildings and hotels intended for travelers in transit. A shopping centre and three high-rise office buildings rising with the top of the commercial zone will accompany the project.

The second project will not relate to the bay of Algiers and aims to revitalize the sea front. The development of the {{convert|44|km|mi|0|abbr=on}} sea front will include marinas, channels, luxury hotels, offices, apartments of great standing, luxury stores and leisure amenities. A crescent-shaped peninsula will be set up on the open sea. The project of the bay of Algiers will also comprise six small islands, of which four of round form, connected to each other by bridges and marinas and will include tourist and residential complexes.
[[File:Alger Tunnel-des-Facultes - Place-Maurice-Audin IMG 0236.JPG|thumb|left|[[Air Algérie]] head office in Place [[Maurice Audin|Audin]] near the [[University of Algiers]], in Alger-Centre]]
The third project will relate to restructuring an area of Algiers, qualified by the originators of the project of &quot;city of wellness&quot;. El Abbar indicated to the journalists that the complex would be &quot;agreeable for all those which will want to combine tourism and well-being or tourism and relaxation&quot;. The complex will include a university, a research center and a medical centre. It should also include a hospital complex, a care centre, a hotel zone, an urban centre and a thermal spa with villas and apartments. The university will include a medical school and a school for care male nurses which will be able to accommodate 500 students. The university campus will have the possibility of seeing setting up broad ranges of buildings of research laboratories and residences.

Another project relates to technological implantation of a campus in Sidi Abdellah, {{convert|25|km|mi|0|abbr=on}} south-east from Algiers. This {{convert|90|ha|acre|0|}} site will include shopping centres, residential zones with high standard apartments and a golf course surrounded by villas and hotels. Two other residential zones, including 1.800 apartments and 40 high standard villas, will be built on the surrounding hills.

The fifth project is that of the tourist complex Colonel Abbès, which will be located {{convert|25|km|mi|0|abbr=on}} west from Algiers. This complex will include several retail zones, meeting places, and residential zones composed of apartments and villas with views of the sea.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The report 2008 : Algeria. |publisher=Oxford Business Group |isbn=978-1-902339-09-2 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=zPz9FHXJVLUC&amp;pg=PA32&amp;lpg=PA32&amp;dq=Colonel+Abbes++tourist+complex&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=DBi-VlobAz&amp;sig=ACfU3U3dEgbLlSvkxbTmj3fZejMoGJGoIA&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwjq8d3grabnAhU8mHIEHTPMANMQ6AEwAHoECAkQAQ&amp;safe=active&amp;surl=1#v=onepage&amp;q=Colonel%20Abbes%20%20tourist%20complex&amp;f=false |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Currently there is another project under construction, by the name of Algiers Medina. The first step of the project is nearly complete.

A [[Hewlett Packard]] office for French-speaking countries in Africa is in Algiers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://welcome.hp.com/gms/emea_africa/en/contact/office_locs.html |title=HP Office locations |publisher=Welcome.hp.com |accessdate=2010-06-27 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090928005628/http://welcome.hp.com/gms/emea_africa/en/contact/office_locs.html |archive-date=2009-09-28 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Tourist installations==
[[File:Algeri08.jpg|thumb|Panorama of the city as seen from [[Bologhine]] district]]

Some {{convert|20|km|mi|0|abbr=on}} to the west of Algiers are such seaside resorts as [[Sidi-Ferruch|Sidi Fredj]] (ex-Sidi Ferruch), [[Palm Beach (Algeria)|Palm Beach]], [[Douaouda]], [[Zéralda]], and the '' Club of the Pines '' (residence of State); there are tourist complexes, Algerian and other restaurants, souvenir shops, supervised beaches, and other amenities. The city is also equipped with important hotel complexes such as the hotel Hilton, El-Aurassi or El Djazair. Algiers also has the first [[water park]] in the country. The [[tourism]] of Algiers is growing but is not as developed as that of the larger cities in [[Morocco]] or [[Tunisia]].

==Education==
{{expand section|date=January 2017}}

International schools for foreign residents include:
* [[Lycée International Alexandre Dumas]] (French school)
* [[Roma Italian School of Algiers]]
* [[Russian Embassy School in Algiers]]
* [[El Kalimat School]] (English-language school)

There was formerly the École japonaise d'Alger (アルジェ日本人学校 ''Aruje Nihonjin Gakkō''), a [[Nihonjin gakko|school for Japanese children]].&lt;ref&gt;Kobori, Iwao (Conseiller aupres del'Universite des Nations Unies). &quot;[http://www.japan-algeria-center.jp/andalg/fr/andalg20010705f.html L'Algerie et moi]&quot; ( {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150116182909/http://www.japan-algeria-center.jp/andalg/fr/andalg20010705f.html |date=2015-01-16 }}). Japan-Algeria Center. Retrieved on 16 January 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.mext.go.jp/a_menu/shotou/clarinet/002/1338806.htm 過去に指定・認定していた在外教育施設]&quot; ( {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150115030344/http://www.mext.go.jp/a_menu/shotou/clarinet/002/1338806.htm |date=2015-01-15 }}). [[Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology]]. Retrieved on January 15, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Public transport==
[[File:Metro, suburban train and tramway map of Algiers.png|thumb|Public transport of Algiers]]
* [[ETUSA]] (urban and suburban bus transportation for Algiers) operates bus service in Algiers and the surrounding suburbs. 54 lines are currently operating, with service from 5:30&amp;nbsp;a.m. to 12:45&amp;nbsp;a.m.
* [[SNTF]] (national railroad company) operates commuter-rail lines connecting the capital to the surrounding suburbs.
* [[Algiers Metro]], opened November 1, 2011.
* [[Algiers tramway]], opened on May 8, 2011.
* [[Houari Boumediene Airport]] is located {{convert|20|km|mi|0|abbr=on}} from the city. The airport serves domestics, many European cities, [[West Africa]], the [[Middle East]], [[Asia]] and [[North America]]. On July 5, 2006, a new international air terminal was opened for service. The terminal is managed by [[Aéroports de Paris]].

4 urban beltways:
* El Madania – Belouizdad
* Notre Dame d’Afrique – Bologhine
* Memorial des Martyres/Riad el Feth – Jardin d’essais
* Palais de la culture – Oued Kniss

==Sports==
Algiers is the sporting centre of [[Algeria]]. The city has a number of professional clubs in the variety of sports, which have won national and international titles. Among the sports facilities within the city, there is an enormous sporting complex – Complex of OCO – [[Mohamed Boudiaf]]. This includes the [[Stade 5 Juillet 1962]] (capacity {{Formatnum: 64,000}}), a venue for [[Athletics (sport)|athletics]], an Olympic [[swimming pool]], a multisports room (the Cupola), an 18-hole golf course, and several tennis courts.

The following major sporting events have been held in Algiers (not-exhaustive list):
{{div col|content=
* [[Mediterranean Games]] 1975.
* [[All-Africa Games]] 1978, 2007.
* [[African Cup of Nations]] [[1990 African Cup of Nations|1990]].
* [[African Handball Nations Championship]] 1989, 2001.
* [[Pan Arab Games]] 2004.
* [[FIBA Africa Championship]] 2005.
* [[Boys' U19 Volleyball World Championship|Men's U19 World Championship]] 2005.
}}

===Football clubs===
Major [[association football]] club based in Algiers include:
{{div col|content=
* [[MC Alger]]
* [[USM Alger]]
* [[CR Belouizdad]]
* [[NA Hussein Dey]]
* [[Paradou AC]]
* [[USM El Harrach]]
* [[RC Kouba]]
* [[OMR El Annasser]]
* [[JH Djazaïr]] (now defunct)
}}

==International relations==
{{More citations needed section|date=June 2015}}
{{See also|List of twin towns and sister cities in Africa#Algeria|l1=List of twin towns and sister cities in Algeria}}

===Twin towns – Sister cities===
Algiers is [[Twin towns and sister cities|twinned]] with:
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|
*{{flagicon|JOR}} [[Amman]], [[Jordan]]
*{{flagicon|PRC}} [[Beijing]], [[China]]
*{{flagicon|GER}} [[Berlin]], [[Germany]]
*{{flagicon|TUN}} [[Tunis]], [[Tunisia]]
*{{flagicon|PRK}} [[Pyongyang]], [[North Korea]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20010919131236/http://www.kcna.co.jp/item/2000/200001/news01/06.htm#3|archive-date=2001-09-19|url=http://kcna.co.jp/item/2000/200001/news01/06.htm#3|date=6 January 2000|publisher=KCNA|title=Anniversary of sister-city relations|access-date=2017-12-03|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
||
*{{flagicon|CAN}} [[Montreal|Montreal, Quebec]], [[Canada]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www11.ville.montreal.qc.ca/sherlock2/servlet/template/sherlock%2CAfficherDocumentInternet.vm/nodocument/20146;jsessionid=24C10045060CDD0AA23BD919B260FD0F |title=Sherlock, banque d'information de la Ville de Montréal |publisher=1.ville.montreal.qc.ca |accessdate=2010-06-27 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090223231510/http://www11.ville.montreal.qc.ca/sherlock2/servlet/template/sherlock%2CAfficherDocumentInternet.vm/nodocument/20146%3Bjsessionid%3D24C10045060CDD0AA23BD919B260FD0F |archivedate=2009-02-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{flagicon|UK}} [[London]], [[United Kingdom]]
*{{flagicon|RUS}} [[Moscow]], [[Russia]]
*{{flagicon|LIB}} [[Tyre, Lebanon]]
*{{flagicon|BUL}} [[Sofia]], [[Bulgaria]]
*{{flagicon|ITA}} [[Rome]], [[Italy]]
||

*{{flagicon|NED}} [[Amsterdam]], [[Netherlands]]
*{{flagicon|BRA}} [[São Paulo]], [[Brazil]]
*{{flagicon|PRC}} [[Shanghai]], [[China]]
*{{flagicon|LBY}} [[Tripoli]], [[Libya]]
*{{flagicon|IDN}} [[Surakarta]], [[Indonesia]] (Since 2011)
*{{flagicon|SGP}} [[Singapore]], [[Singapore]]
|}

===Cooperation agreements===
Algiers has cooperation agreements with:
*{{flagicon|POR}} [[Lisbon]], Portugal&lt;ref name=&quot;Lisbon twinnings&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.anmp.pt/anmp/pro/mun1/gem101l0.php?cod_ent=M1100|title=Lisboa – Geminações de Cidades e Vilas|accessdate=2013-08-23|work=Associação Nacional de Municípios Portugueses [National Association of Portuguese Municipalities]|language=Portuguese|trans-title=Lisbon – Twinning of Cities and Towns|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150201175323/http://www.anmp.pt/anmp/pro/mun1/gem101l0.php?cod_ent=M1100|archive-date=2015-02-01|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lisbon twinnings 2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cm-lisboa.pt/municipio/relacoes-internacionais |title=Acordos de Geminação, de Cooperação e/ou Amizade da Cidade de Lisboa |accessdate=2013-08-23 |work=Camara Municipal de Lisboa |language=Portuguese |trans-title=Lisbon – Twinning Agreements, Cooperation and Friendship |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131031202617/http://www.cm-lisboa.pt/municipio/relacoes-internacionais |archivedate=2013-10-31 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{flagicon|FRA}} [[Paris]], [[France]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://next.paris.fr/english/paris-a-city-with-an-international-profile/international-action-cooperation/friendship-and-cooperation-agreements/rub_8139_stand_29940_port_18784 |title=Friendship and cooperation agreements |publisher=Marie de Paris |location=Paris |accessdate=2016-09-10 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160701024003/http://next.paris.fr/english/paris-a-city-with-an-international-profile/international-action-cooperation/friendship-and-cooperation-agreements/rub_8139_stand_29940_port_18784 |archivedate=2016-07-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

''In addition, many of the wards and cities within Algiers maintain sister-city relationships with other foreign cities.''

==Films about Algiers==
[[File:La battaglia di Algeri screen.png|thumb|275px|''[[The Battle of Algiers]]'' (1966), Italian-Algerian movie by [[Gillo Pontecorvo]].]]
* ''[[Algiers (film)|Algiers]]'', 1938, starring Charles Boyer and Hedy Lamarr, and directed by [[John Cromwell (director)|John Cromwell]];
* ''[[The Battle of Algiers (film)|The Battle of Algiers]]'', 1966, directed by [[Gillo Pontecorvo]];
* ''Tahya ya Didou, Alger Insolite'', 1970, Mohammed Zinet;
* ''[[Bab El-Oued City]]'', 1994, directed by [[Merzak Allouache]];
* ''Viva Laldjérie'', 2003, directed by Nadir Moknèche, with [[Biyouna]] and [[Lubna Azabal]];
* ''Bab el Web'', 2004, directed by Merzak Allouache, with [[Samy Naceri]], [[Julie Gayet]], [[Faudel]];
* ''Once upon a time in the Oued'', 2005, directed by Djamel Bensalah;
* ''Beur, White, Red'', 2005, directed by Mahmoud Zemmouri.
* ''[[Delice Paloma]]'', 2007, directed by Nadir Moknèche, with [[Biyouna]] and Nadia Kaci.
* ''[[Abbott and Costello in the Foreign Legion]]'', 1950, starring Bud Abbott and Lou Costello.

==See also==
* [[Barbary pirates]]
* [[Botanical Garden Hamma]]
* [[List of Ottoman governors of Algiers]]

==References==
{{hatnote|This article was originally based on a translation of the [[French Wikipedia]]'s [[:fr:Alger|article &quot;Alger&quot;]].}}

===Citations===
{{Reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
{{See also|Timeline of Algiers#Bibliography|l1=Bibliography of the history of Algiers}}
* {{EB1911|wstitle=Algiers|volume=1|pages=653–655}}
* Emerson, Charles. ''1913: In Search of the World Before the Great War'' (2013) compares Algiers to 20 major world cities; pp 267–79.
* {{citation |first=Nacéra |last=Benseddik |contribution=Chronique d’une Cité Antique |title=Alger: Lumières sur la Ville |series=''Actes du Colloque de l'EPAU 4–6 May 2001'' |location=Algiers |date=2004 |p=29–34 }}. {{in lang|fr}}
* {{citation |last=Ghaki |first=Mansour |contribution=Toponymie et Onomastique Libyques: L'Apport de l'Écriture Punique/Néopunique |contribution-url=https://s3.amazonaws.com/academia.edu.documents/50105050/Toponymie_et_onomastique_Lapport_de_lecriture_punique_neopunique.pdf |pp=65–71 |date=2015 |location=Naples |publisher=Unior |editor=Anna Maria di Tolla |display-editors=0 |title=La Lingua nella Vita e la Vita della Lingua: Itinerari e Percorsi degli Studi Berberi |series=''Studi Africanistici: Quaderni di Studi Berberi e Libico-Berberi'' |volume=No. 4 |isbn=978-88-6719-125-3 |issn=2283-5636 }}. {{in lang|fr}} 
* {{citation |last=Lipiński |first=Edward |author-link=Edward Lipinski (orientalist) |title=Itineraria Phoenicia |series=''Orientalia Lovaniensia Analecta'', No.{{nbsp}}127, ''Studia Phoenicia'', Vol.{{nbsp}}XVIII |publisher=Uitgeverij Peeters |location=Leuven |date=2004 |url=https://books.google.co.kr/books?id=SLSzNfdcqfoC&amp;printsec=frontcover }}.

{{wikivoyage|Algiers}}
{{Commons category|Algiers}}
{{Algiers}}
{{Algiers Province}}
{{Province seats of Algeria}}
{{Phoenician cities and colonies navbox|state=collapsed}}
{{Capitals of Arab countries}}
{{List of African capitals}}
{{All-Africa Games Host Cities}}
{{Arab Capital of Culture}}
{{Mediterranean Games}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Algiers| ]]
[[Category:944 establishments]]
[[Category:Barbary Wars]]
[[Category:Capitals in Africa]]
[[Category:Former Spanish colonies]]
[[Category:Mediterranean port cities and towns in Algeria]]
[[Category:Populated coastal places in Algeria]]
[[Category:World Heritage Sites in Algeria]]
[[Category:Coastal cities in Algeria]]
[[Category:Populated places in Algiers Province]]
[[Category:Province seats of Algeria]]
[[Category:Populated places established in the 10th century]]
[[Category:10th-century establishments in Africa]]</text>
      <sha1>0ag9h1wdckfivztm4j7bqnztrp8kkeb</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
