  <page>
    <title>Alfonso V of Aragon</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1686</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942084508</id>
      <parentid>933834606</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-22T14:14:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>49.184.28.197</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Removed error.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{for|the Portuguese king with the same name|Afonso V}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2013}}
{{refimprove|date=January 2014}}

{{Infobox royalty
| type         = monarch
| name         = Alfonso the Magnanimous
| image        = Alfonso V de Aragón (Juan de Juanes, 1557).jpg
| caption      = Portrait of Alfonso V of Aragon, by 16th century painter [[Vicente Juan Masip]]
| spouse       = [[Maria of Castile]]
| succession   = [[Crown of Aragon|King of Aragon]]
| reign        = 2 April 1416 – 27 June 1458
| predecessor  = [[Ferdinand I of Aragon|Ferdinand I]]
| successor    = [[John II of Aragon|John II]]
| succession1  = [[List of monarchs of Naples|King of Naples]]
| reign1       = 2 June 1442 – 27 June 1458
| predecessor1 = [[René of Anjou|René]]
| successor1   = [[Ferdinand I of Naples|Ferdinand I]]
| issue        = [[Ferdinand I of Naples]] &lt;small&gt;)&lt;/small&gt;
| issue-link   = #Family
| issue-pipe   = among others...
| house        = [[House of Trastámara|Trastámara]]
| father       = [[Ferdinand I of Aragon]]
| mother       = [[Eleanor of Alburquerque]]
| birth_date   = 1396
| birth_place  = [[Medina del Campo]], [[Kingdom of Castile]]
| death_date   = 27 June {{death year and age|1458|1396}}
| death_place  = [[Castel dell'Ovo]], [[Naples]], [[Kingdom of Naples]]
| burial_date  =
| burial_place = [[Poblet Monastery]]
| religion     = [[Catholic Church|Roman Catholicism]]
}}

[[File:Pisanello - Codex Vallardi 2481.jpg|thumb|200px|right|Drawing of Alfonso by [[Pisanello]]]]

'''Alfonso the Magnanimous''' {{post-nominals|country=GBR|KG}} (also '''Alphonso'''; {{lang-ca|'''Alfons'''}}; 1396 – 27 June 1458) was the [[King of Aragon]] (as '''Alfonso V'''), [[King of Valencia|Valencia]] (as '''Alfonso III'''), [[Kingdom of Majorca|Majorca]], [[Kingdom of Sardinia|Sardinia and Corsica]] (as '''Alfonso II'''), [[Kingdom of Sicily|Sicily]] (as '''Alfonso I''') and [[Count of Barcelona]] (as '''Alfonso IV''') from 1416, and [[King of Naples]] (as '''Alfonso I''') from 1442 until his death. He was one of the most prominent figures of the early [[Renaissance]]&lt;ref&gt;On This Day: [http://www.onthisday.com/people/alfons-v-of-aragon/ Alfonso V of Aragon]&lt;/ref&gt; and a knight of the [[Order of the Dragon]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2019}}

==Biography==
Born at [[Medina del Campo]], he was the son of [[Ferdinand I of Aragon]] and [[Eleanor of Alburquerque]]. He represented the old line of the counts of [[Barcelona]] through the female line, and was on his father's side descended from the [[House of Trastamara]], the reigning House of [[Castile (historical region)|Castile]]. By hereditary right he was king of [[Sicily]] and claimed the island of [[Sardinia]] for himself, though it was then in the possession of [[Genoa]]. Alfonso was also in possession of much of [[Corsica]] by the 1420s.{{Citation needed|date=February 2019}}

[[File:Escudo armas Alfonso V de Aragón en Satyrarum hecatostichon cropped.jpg|thumb|Coat of Arms of Alphonse V of Aragon in ''Satyrarum hecatostichon'' by [[Francesco Filelfo]] (1449).]]
In 1421 the childless Queen [[Joanna II of Naples]] adopted and named him as heir to the [[Kingdom of Naples]], and Alfonso went to [[Naples]].{{sfn|Armstrong|1964|p=164}} Here he hired the [[condottiero]] [[Braccio da Montone]] with the task of reducing the resistance of his rival claimant, [[Louis III of Anjou]], and his forces led by [[Muzio Attendolo]] [[Sforza]]. With Pope [[Martin V]] supporting Sforza, Alfonso switched his religious allegiance to the Aragonese [[antipope Benedict XIII]]. When Sforza abandoned Louis' cause, Alfonso seemed to have all his problems solved; however, his relationship with Joanna suddenly worsened, and in May 1423 he had her lover, [[Gianni Caracciolo]], a powerful figure in the Neapolitan court, arrested.{{sfn|Armstrong|1964|p=164}}

After an attempt to arrest the queen herself had failed, Joan called on Sforza who defeated the Aragonese militias near [[Castel Capuano]] in Naples. Alfonso fled to [[Castel Nuovo]], but the help of a fleet of 22 galleys led by [[Giovanni da Cardona]] improved his situation.{{sfn|Armstrong|1964|p=165}} Sforza and Joanna ransomed Caracciolo and retreated to the fortress of [[Aversa]].{{sfn|Armstrong|1964|p=165}} Here she repudiated her earlier adoption of Alfonso and, with the backing of Martin V, named Louis III as her heir instead.{{sfn|Grierson|Travaini|1998|p=245}}

The Duke of Milan, [[Filippo Maria Visconti]], joined the anti-Aragonese coalition. Alfonso requested support from Braccio da Montone, who was besieging Joanna's troops in [[L'Aquila]], but had to set sail for Spain, where a war had broken out between his brothers and the [[Kingdom of Castile]]. On his way towards Barcelona, Alfonso sacked [[Marseille]], a possession of Louis III.{{sfn|Armstrong|1964|p=165}}

[[File:King-alfonsoVaragon2.jpg|left|thumb|Manuscript detail of Alfonso V of Aragon.]]

In late 1423 the Genoese fleet of Filippo Maria Visconti moved in the southern [[Tyrrhenian Sea]], rapidly conquering [[Gaeta]], [[Procida]], [[Castellammare di Stabia|Castellammare]] and [[Sorrento]]. Naples, which was held by Alfonso's brother, Pedro de Aragon,{{sfn|Armstrong|1964|p=165}} was besieged in 1424 by the Genoese ships and Joanna's troops, now led by [[Francesco Sforza]], the son of Muzio Sforza (who had met his death at L'Aquila). The city fell in April 1424. Pedro, after a short resistance in Castel Nuovo, fled to [[Sicily]] in August. Joanna II and Louis III again took possession of the realm, although the true power was in the hands of [[Gianni Caracciolo]].{{sfn|Armstrong|1964|p=165}}

An opportunity for Alfonso to reconquer Naples occurred in 1432, when Caracciolo was killed in a conspiracy.{{sfn|Armstrong|1964|p=165}} Alfonso tried to regain the favour of the queen, but failed, and had to wait for the death of both Louis (at Cosenza in 1434) and Joanna herself (February 1435). In her will, she bequeathed her realm to [[René I of Naples|René of Anjou]], Louis III's younger brother. This solution was opposed by the new pope, [[Eugene IV]], who nominally was the feudal lord of the King of Naples. The Neapolitans having called in the French, Alfonso decided to intervene and, with the support of several barons of the kingdom, captured [[Capua]] and besieged the important sea fortress of Gaeta. His fleet of 25 galleys was met by the Genoese ships sent by Visconti, led by [[Biagio Assereto]]. In the [[Battle of Ponza (1435)|battle of Ponza]] that ensued, Alfonso was defeated and taken prisoner.{{sfn|Bisson|1991|p=144}}

In Milan, however, he impressed his captor with his cultured demeanor and persuaded him to let him go by making it plain that it was not in Milan's interest to prevent the victory of the Aragonese party in Naples.{{sfn|Bisson|1991|p=144}} Helped by a Sicilian fleet, Alfonso recaptured Capua and set his base in Gaeta in February 1436. Meanwhile, papal troops had invaded the Neapolitan kingdom, but Alfonso bribed their commander, Cardinal [[Giovanni Vitelleschi]], and their successes waned.{{Citation needed|date=February 2019}}

{{Aragonese House of Trastámara}}

In the meantime, René had managed to reach Naples on 19 May 1438. Alfonso tried to besiege the city in the following September, but failed.{{sfn|Bisson|1991|p=144}} His brother Pedro was killed during the battle. Castel Nuovo, where an Aragonese garrison resisted, fell to the Angevine mercenaries in August 1439. After the death of his condottiero [[Jacopo Caldora]], however, René's fortune started to decline: Alfonso could easily capture [[Aversa]], [[Salerno]], [[Benevento]], [[Manfredonia]] and [[Bitonto]]. René, whose possession included now only part of the [[Abruzzi]] and Naples, obtained 10,000 men from the pope, but the cardinal leading them signed a truce with Alfonso. Giovanni Sforza came with a reduced corps, as troops sent by Eugene IV had halted his father Francesco in the [[Marche]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2019}}

Alfonso, provided with the most impressive artillery of the times, again besieged Naples. The siege began on 10 November 1441, ending on 2 June the following year.  After the return of René to Provence, Alfonso easily reduced the remaining resistance and made his triumphal entrance in Naples on 26 February 1443, as the monarch of a pacified kingdom.{{sfn|Bisson|1991|p=144}} In 1446 he also conquered Sardinia.{{Citation needed|date=February 2019}}

Alfonso, by formally submitting his reign to the Papacy, obtained the consent of Pope [[Eugene IV]] that the Kingdom of Naples would go to his illegitimate son [[Ferdinand I of Naples|Ferdinand]]. He died in [[Castel dell'Ovo]] in 1458, while he was planning the conquest of [[Genoa]]. At the time, Alfonso was at odds with [[Pope Callixtus III|Callixtus III]], who died shortly afterwards.{{Citation needed|date=February 2019}}

His Spanish possessions were ruled for him by his brother John, later king [[John II of Aragon]].{{sfn|Bisson|1991|p=147}}  Sicily and [[Sardinia]] were also inherited by his brother.

Alfonso was also a powerful and faithful supporter of [[Skanderbeg]], whom he decided to take under his protection as a vassal in 1451, shortly after the latter had scored his second victory against [[Murad II]]. In addition to financial assistance, he supplied the [[Albania]]n leader with troops, military equipment, and sanctuary for himself and his family if such a need should arise.  This was because in 1448, while Skanderbeg was victoriously fighting off the Turkish invasions, three military columns, commanded by [[Demetrio Reres]] along with his sons Giorgio and Basilio, had been dispatched to help Alfonso V defeat the barons of Naples who had rebelled against him.{{Citation needed|date=February 2019}}

==Family==

Alfonso had been betrothed to [[Maria of Castile]] (1401–1458; sister of [[John II of Castile]]) in [[Valladolid]] in 1408; the marriage was celebrated in [[Valencia (city in Spain)|Valencia]] on 12 June 1415. They failed to produce children.  Alfonso had been in love with a woman of noble family named [[Lucrezia d'Alagno]], who served as a ''de facto'' queen at the Neapolitan court as well as an inspiring [[muse]].

Genealogical records in the [[Occitan language|Old Occitan]] [[Chronique romane|Chronicle of Montpellier]] in ''Le petit Thalamus de Montpellier'' indicate that Alphonso's relationship with his mistress, [[Giraldona Carlino]], produced three children:{{sfn|Widmayer|2006|p=231}}

* His successor in Naples, King [[Ferdinand I of Naples]], (b. 1423; reigned 1458–1494).
* Maria d'Aragon (died 1449, aged around 15 or 16). She had married in 1444 [[Leonello d'Este, margrave of Ferrara|Leonello d'Este]], deceased 1450.
* [[Leonora d'Aragona]], who married circa 1443, Mariano Marzano, Duke of Squillace, Prince of Rossano. Her daughter Francesca married [[Leonardo III Tocco]].

Giraldona was the daughter of Enrique Carlino and his wife, Isabel.

==Art and administration==
Like many Renaissance rulers, Alfonso V was a patron of the arts. He founded the Academy of [[Naples]] under [[Giovanni Pontano]], and for his entrance into the city in 1443 had a magnificent triumphal arch added to the main gate of [[Castel Nuovo]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.britannica.com/place/Naples-Italy|title=Naples {{!}} History &amp; Points of Interest|website=Encyclopedia Britannica|language=en|access-date=2019-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Alfonso V supplied the theme of Renaissance sculptures over the west entrance.
[[File:NapoliMaschioAngioinoIngresso.jpg|thumb|left|The triumphal arch entrance of Castel Nuovo.]]

Alfonso was particularly attracted to [[classical literature]]. He reportedly brought copies of the works of [[Livy]] and [[Julius Caesar]] on his campaigns; the poet [[Antonio Beccadelli (poet)|Antonio Beccadelli]] even claimed that Alfonso was cured of a disease by the reading of a few pages from [[Quintus Curtius Rufus]]' history of [[Alexander the Great]]. Although this reputed erudition attracted scholars to his court, Alfonso apparently enjoyed pitting them against each other in spectacles of bawdy Latin rhetoric.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Hugh Chrisholm|title=The Encyclopædia Britannica: A Dictionary of Arts, Sciences, Literature and General Information|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Fs09AQAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA736|year=1911|publisher=At the University Press|page=736}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After his conquest of Naples in 1442, Alfonso ruled primarily through his mercenaries and political lackeys. In his Italian kingdom, he maintained the former political and administrative institutions. His holdings in Spain were governed by his brother John.{{sfn|Bisson|1991|p=147}}

A unified General Chancellorship for the whole Aragonese realm was set up in Naples, although the main functionaries were of Aragonese nationality. Apart from financial, administrative and artistic improvements, his other accomplishments in the Sicilian kingdom include the restoration of the aqueducts, the drainage of marshy areas, and the paving of streets.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.encyclopedia.com/arts/arts-construction-medicine-science-and-technology-magazines/alfonso-v-aragon-magnanimous-1396-1458|title=Alfonso V of Aragon (the Magnanimous) (1396–1458) - Dictionary definition of Alfonso V of Aragon (the Magnanimous) (1396–1458) {{!}} Encyclopedia.com: FREE online dictionary|website=www.encyclopedia.com|language=en|access-date=2017-01-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Connection with Ethiopia==
Alfonso was the object of diplomatic contacts from the empire of [[Ethiopia]]. In 1428, he received a letter from [[Yeshaq I of Ethiopia]], borne by two dignitaries, which proposed an alliance against the [[Muslim]]s and would be sealed by a dual marriage that would require the [[Peter of Aragon, Count of Alburquerque|Infante Peter]] to bring a group of artisans to Ethiopia where he would marry Yeshaq's daughter.{{Citation needed|date=February 2019}}

In return, Alfonso sent a party of 13 craftsmen, all of whom perished on the way to Ethiopia.&lt;ref&gt;Girma Beshah and Merid Wolde Aregay, ''The Question of the Union of the Churches in Luso-Ethiopian Relations (1500–1632)'' (Lisbon: Junta de Investigações do Ultramar and Centro de Estudos Históricos Ultramarinos, 1964), pp.13–4.&lt;/ref&gt; He later sent a letter to Yeshaq's successor [[Zara Yaqob]] in 1450, in which he wrote that he would be happy to send artisans to Ethiopia if their safe arrival could be guaranteed, but it probably never reached the Emperor.&lt;ref&gt;Girma Beshah and Merid Wolde Aregay, ''The Question of the Union of the Churches'', pp.14.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[O. G. S. Crawford]] (editor), ''Ethiopian Itineraries, circa 1400 – 1524'' (Cambridge: the Hakluyt Society, 1958), pp. 12f.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ancestors==
{{ahnentafel
|collapsed=yes |align=center |ref=&lt;ref name=&quot;DeSousa2&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://archive.org/stream/historiagenealog02sous#page/496/mode/2up |title=Historia genealogica da casa real portugueza |trans-title=Genealogical History of the Royal House of Portugal |volume=2 |language=pt |last=de Sousa |first=Antonio Caetano |publisher=Lisboa Occidental |year=1735 |page=497}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|boxstyle_1=background-color: #fcc;
|boxstyle_2=background-color: #fb9;
|boxstyle_3=background-color: #ffc;
|boxstyle_4=background-color: #bfc;
|boxstyle_5=background-color: #9fe;
|1= 1. '''Alfonso V of Aragon'''
|2= 2. [[Ferdinand I of Aragon]]
|3= 3. [[Eleanor of Alburquerque]]
|4= 4. [[John I of Castile]]
|5= 5. [[Eleanor of Aragon, Queen of Castile|Eleanor of Aragon]]
|6= 6. [[Sancho Alfonso, 1st Count of Alburquerque]]
|7= 7. [[Beatrice, Countess of Alburquerque|Beatrice of Portugal]]
|8= 8. [[Henry II of Castile]]
|9= 9. [[Juana Manuel]]
|10= 10. [[Peter IV of Aragon]]
|11= 11. [[Eleanor of Sicily]]
|12= 12. [[Alfonso XI of Castile]]
|13= 13. [[Eleanor de Guzmán|Leonor de Guzmán]]
|14= 14. [[Peter I of Portugal]]
|15= 15. [[Inês de Castro]]
|16= 16. [[Alfonso XI of Castile]] (= 12)
|17= 17. [[Eleanor de Guzmán|Leonor de Guzmán]] (= 13)
|18= 18. [[Juan Manuel, Prince of Villena]] 
|19= 19. [[Blanca de La Cerda y Lara|Blanca de La Cerda]]
|20= 20. [[Alfonso IV of Aragon]]
|21= 21. Teresa d'Entença
|22= 22. [[Peter II of Sicily]]
|23= 23. [[Elizabeth of Carinthia, Queen of Sicily|Elisabeth of Carinthia]]
|24= 24. [[Ferdinand IV of Castile]]
|25= 25. [[Constance of Portugal]]
|26= 26. Pedro Núñez de Guzmán
|27= 27. Beatriz Ponce de León
|28= 28. [[Afonso IV of Portugal]]
|29= 29. [[Beatrice of Castile (1293–1359)|Beatrice of Castile]]
|30= 30. [[Pedro Fernández de Castro]]
|31= 31. Aldonça Lourenço de Valadares
}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Sources==
*{{cite book |title=The Cambridge Medieval History: The Close of the Middle Ages |volume=VIII |chapter=The Papacy and Naples in the Fifteenth Century |first=Edward |last=Armstrong |editor-first1=C.W. |editor-last1=Previte-Orton |editor-first2=Z.N. |editor-last2=Brooke |publisher=Cambridge at the University Press |year=1964 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |title=The Medieval Crown of Aragon |first=T.N. |last=Bisson |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=1991 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |title=Medieval European Coinage: Volume 14, South Italy, Sicily, Sardinia |first1=Philip |last1=Grierson |first2=Lucia |last2=Travaini |publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=1998 |ref=harv}} 
*{{cite book|first=Jeffrey S. |last=Widmayer|editor-first=Erik |editor-last=Kooper|title=The Medieval Chronicle IV|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=aLUGdr4-0j4C|accessdate=5 February 2013 |year=2006 |publisher=Rodopi|isbn=978-90-420-2088-7 |chapter=The Chronicle of Montpellier H119: Text, Translation and Commentary |ref=harv}}

{{S-start}}
{{S-hou|[[House of Trastámara]]||1396|27 June|1458}}
{{S-reg}}
{{s-bef | rows=1| before=[[Ferdinand I of Aragon|Ferdinand the Just]]}}
{{s-ttl | title= [[King of Aragon]], [[King of Valencia|Valencia]], [[King of Majorca|Majorca]],&lt;br&gt;[[King of Sicily|Sicily]], [[King of Sardinia and Corsica|Sardinia and Corsica]];&lt;br&gt;[[Count of Barcelona]], [[Count of Roussillon|Roussillon]] and [[Count of Cerdagne|Cerdagne]]| years=1416–1458}}
{{s-aft | rows=1 | after=[[John II of Aragon|John the Great]]}}
{{s-break}}
{{s-bef | before=[[René of Anjou]]}}
{{s-ttl | title= [[King of Naples]] | years=1442–1458}}
{{s-aft | after=[[Ferdinand I of Naples|Ferdinand I]]}}
{{s-break}}
{{s-roy|es}}
{{S-break}}
{{S-vac|rows=2|last=[[Infante Peter, Duke of Girona|Infante Peter]]}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[Duke of Girona]]|years=1414–1416}}
{{S-non|reason=Elevation to a Principality}}
{{s-break}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Count of Cervera]]|years=1414–1416}}
{{S-aft|rows=2|after=[[Charles, Prince of Viana|Prince Charles]]}}
{{S-break}}
{{S-new}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[Prince of Girona]]|years=1416}}
{{s-end}}
{{Infantes of Aragon}}
{{Princes of Girona}}
{{Aragonese monarchs}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Alfonso 05 Of Aragon}}
[[Category:1396 births]]
[[Category:1458 deaths]]
[[Category:15th-century Aragonese monarchs]]
[[Category:15th-century Kings of Sicily]]
[[Category:People from Medina del Campo]]
[[Category:House of Trastámara]]
[[Category:Aragonese infantes]]
[[Category:Monarchs of Naples]]
[[Category:Monarchs of Majorca]]
[[Category:Valencian monarchs]]
[[Category:Kings of Sicily]]
[[Category:Patrons of literature]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic monarchs]]
[[Category:Knights of the Golden Fleece]]
[[Category:Counts of Barcelona]]
[[Category:Extra Knights Companion of the Garter]]
[[Category:15th-century monarchs in Europe]]
[[Category:Knights of the Dragon]]
[[Category:Burials at the Poblet Monastery]]
[[Category:Patrons of art]]</text>
      <sha1>1x4cxpverv8zn0pfqbnkx231d2f4mfk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
