  <page>
    <title>Breast reconstruction</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4419</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941372983</id>
      <parentid>937950950</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-18T05:14:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Chris the speller</username>
        <id>525927</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>replaced: well-tolerated → well tolerated, [[WP:AWB/T|typo(s) fixed]]: Often times → Oftentimes</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox medical intervention
| name         = Breast reconstruction
| synonym      =
| image        = File:Breast reconstruction 2.jpg|thumb|
| caption      = Result of breast reconstruction after mastectomy. Nipple missing, and cicatrix (scar) is prominent.
| alt          = 
| pronounce    = 
| specialty    = plastic surgeon
| synonyms     = 
| ICD10        = 
| ICD9         = 
| ICD9unlinked = 
| CPT          = 
| MeshID       = 
| LOINC        = 
| other_codes  = 
| MedlinePlus  = 
| eMedicine    = 
}}

'''Breast reconstruction''' is the surgical process of rebuilding the shape and look of a [[breast]], most commonly in [[woman|women]] who have had surgery to treat breast cancer. It involves using [[autologous]] tissue, [[prosthesis|prosthetic]] implants, or a combination of both with the goal of reconstructing a natural-looking breast.  This process often also includes the rebuilding of the nipple and areola, known as nipple-areola complex (NAC) reconstruction, as one of the final stages.

Generally, the aesthetic appearance is acceptable to the woman, but the reconstructed area is commonly completely numb afterwards, which results in loss of sexual function as well as the ability to perceive [[pain]] caused by [[burn]]s and other injuries.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2017/01/29/well/live/after-mastectomies-an-unexpected-blow-numb-new-breasts.html|title=After Mastectomies, an Unexpected Blow: Numb New Breasts|last=Rabin|first=Roni Caryn|date=2017-01-29|work=The New York Times|access-date=2017-03-31|issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Timing ==
Breast reconstruction can be performed either immediately following the mastectomy or as a separate procedure at a later date, known as immediate reconstruction and delayed reconstruction, respectively. The decision of when breast reconstruction will take place is patient-specific and based on many different factors. Breast reconstruction is a large undertaking that usually requires multiple operations.  These subsequent surgeries may be spread out over weeks or months. 

=== Immediate reconstruction ===
Breast reconstruction is termed &quot;immediate&quot; when it takes place during the same procedure as the mastectomy. Within the United States, approximately 35% of women who have undergone a total mastectomy for breast cancer will choose to pursue immediate breast reconstruction.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Plastic surgery.|others=Neligan, Peter,, Warren, Richard J.,, Van Beek, Allen|isbn=978-0-323-35695-4|edition=4th|location=London|oclc=1006385273|date = 2017-08-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;  One of the inherent advantages of immediate reconstruction is the potential for a single-stage procedure. This also means that the cost of immediate reconstruction is often far less to the patient.  It can also reduce hospital costs by having fewer procedures and requiring a shorter length of the stay as an inpatient.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt;  Additionally, immediate reconstruction often has a better cosmetic result because of the preservation of anatomic landmarks and skin.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt; With regards to psychosocial outcomes, opinions on timing have shifted in favor of immediate reconstruction. Originally, delayed reconstruction was believed to provide patients with time to psychologically adjust to the mastectomy and its effects on body image. However, this opinion is no longer widely held.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt; Compared to delayed procedures, immediate reconstruction can have a more positive psychological impact on patients and their self-esteem, most likely due to the post-operative breast more closely resembling the natural breast compared to the defect left by mastectomy alone.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt;

=== Delayed reconstruction ===
Delayed breast reconstruction is considered more challenging than immediate reconstruction. Frequently not just breast volume, but also skin surface area needs to be restored. Many patients undergoing delayed breast reconstruction have been previously treated with radiation or have had a reconstruction failure with immediate breast reconstruction. In nearly all cases of delayed breast reconstruction tissue must be borrowed from another part of the body to make the new breast.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.drdec.com/#!immediate-or-delayed/c1blj|title=Breast Reconstruction: Immediate or Delayed}}&lt;/ref&gt; Patients expected to receive [[radiation therapy]] as part of their adjuvant treatment are also commonly considered for delayed autologous reconstruction due to significantly higher complication rates with tissue expander-implant techniques in those patients.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt;  While waiting to begin breast reconstruction until several months after radiation therapy may decrease the risk of complications, this risk will always be higher in patients who have received radiation therapy.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt; As with many other surgeries, patients with significant medical comorbidities (e.g., [[high blood pressure]], [[obesity]], [[diabetes]]) and [[Tobacco smoking|smokers]] are higher-risk candidates.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt;  Surgeons may choose to perform delayed reconstruction to decrease this risk.

==Techniques==
There are several techniques for breast reconstruction.  These options are broadly categorized into two different groups:[[File:Blausen 0138 BreastReconstruction Expander.png|thumb|Breast reconstruction using a tissue expander, which is later replaced by a permanent prosthetic implant.]]
=== Implant-based reconstruction ===
This is the most common technique used worldwide.  Implant-based reconstruction is an option for patients who have sufficient skin after mastectomy to cover a prosthetic implant and allow for a natural shape.  For women undergoing bilateral mastectomies, implants provide the greatest opportunity for symmetrical shape and lift.  Additionally, these procedures are generally much faster than flap-based reconstruction since tissue does not have to be taken from another part of the patient's body.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Sabiston textbook of surgery : the biological basis of modern surgical practice|publisher=|others=Townsend, Courtney M., Jr.,, Beauchamp, R. Daniel,, Evers, B. Mark, 1957–, Mattox, Kenneth L., 1938–|year=2017|isbn=978-0-323-29987-9|edition=20th|location=Philadelphia, PA|pages=865–877|oclc=921338900}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Typically, at the time of the mastectomy, the surgeon will insert a [[tissue expansion|tissue expander]] underneath the pectoralis major muscle of the chest wall.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1111/ans.12603 |pmid=24754896 |title=Sentinel lymph node biopsy before mastectomy and immediate breast reconstruction does not significantly delay surgery in early breast cancer |journal=ANZ Journal of Surgery |volume=85 |issue=6 |pages=438–43 |year=2015 |last1=Mannu |first1=Gurdeep S. |last2=Navi |first2=Ali |last3=Hussien |first3=Maged }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1016/j.ijsu.2012.04.010 |pmid=22525383 |title=Sentinel lymph node biopsy before mastectomy and immediate breast reconstruction may predict post-mastectomy radiotherapy, reduce delayed complications and improve the choice of reconstruction |journal=International Journal of Surgery |volume=10 |issue=5 |pages=259–64 |year=2012 |last1=Mannu |first1=G.S. |last2=Navi |first2=A. |last3=Morgan |first3=A. |last4=Mirza |first4=S.M. |last5=Down |first5=S.K. |last6=Farooq |first6=N. |last7=Burger |first7=A. |last8=Hussien |first8=M.I. }}&lt;/ref&gt;  This temporary [[silastic]] implant is used to hold tension on the mastectomy flaps.  In doing so, the tissue expander prevents the breast tissue from contracting and allows for use of a larger implant later on compared to what would be safe at the time of the mastectomy.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;  Following this initial procedure, the patient must return to the clinic on multiple occasions for saline to be injected into a tube inside the tissue expander.  By doing this slowly over the course of several weeks, the space beneath the pectoralis major muscle is safely expanded to an appropriate size without causing too much stress on the breast tissue.  A second procedure is then necessary to remove the tissue expander and replace it with the final, permanent prosthetic implant.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/breast_center/treatments_services/reconstructive_breast_surgery/tissue_expanders.html|title=Tissue Expanders|last=|first=|date=|website=hopkinsmedicine.org|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;[[File:Blausen 0139 BreastReconstruction Prosthesis.png|thumb|A permanent prosthetic implant eventually replaces the tissue expander.]]Although in the past, prosthetic implants were placed directly under the skin, this method has fallen out of favor because of the greater risk of complications, including visible rippling of the implant and capsular contracture.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;  The sub-pectoral technique described above is now preferred because it provides an additional muscular layer between the skin and the implant, decreasing the risk of visible deformity.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;  Oftentimes, however, the pectoralis major muscle is not sufficiently large enough to cover the inferior portion of the prosthetic implant.  If this is the case, one option is to use an acellular dermal matrix to cover the exposed portion of the prosthetic implant, improving both functional and aesthetic outcomes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Breuing|first1=Karl H.|last2=Warren|first2=Stephen M.|year=2005|title=Immediate Bilateral Breast Reconstruction with Implants and Inferolateral AlloDerm Slings|journal=Annals of Plastic Surgery|volume=55|issue=3|pages=232–9|doi=10.1097/01.sap.0000168527.52472.3c|pmid=16106158}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Salzberg|first1=C Andrew|year=2006|title=Nonexpansive Immediate Breast Reconstruction Using Human Acellular Tissue Matrix Graft (AlloDerm)|journal=Annals of Plastic Surgery|volume=57|issue=1|pages=1–5|doi=10.1097/01.sap.0000214873.13102.9f|pmid=16799299}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Of note, a [[Cochrane review]] published in 2016 concluded that implants for use in breast reconstructive surgery have not been adequately studied in good quality clinical trials. &quot;These days - even after a few million women have had breasts reconstructed – surgeons cannot inform women about the risks and complications of different implant-based breast reconstructive options on the basis of results derived from [[Randomized Controlled Trial]]s.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Rocco|first1=Nicola|last2=Rispoli|first2=Corrado|last3=Moja|first3=Lorenzo|last4=Amato|first4=Bruno|last5=Iannone|first5=Loredana|last6=Testa|first6=Serena|last7=Spano|first7=Andrea|last8=Catanuto|first8=Giuseppe|last9=Accurso|first9=Antonello|last10=Nava|first10=Maurizio B|year=2016|title=Different types of implants for reconstructive breast surgery|journal=Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews|volume=2016|issue=5|pages=CD010895|doi=10.1002/14651858.CD010895.pub2|pmid=27182693|hdl=2434/442804}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Potter|first=Shelley|last2=Conroy|first2=Elizabeth J.|last3=Williamson|first3=Paula R.|last4=Thrush|first4=Steven|last5=Whisker|first5=Lisa J.|last6=Skillman|first6=Joanna M|last7=Barnes|first7=Nicola L. P.|last8=Cutress|first8=Ramsey I.|last9=Teasdale|first9=Elizabeth M.|last10=Mills|first10=Nicola|last11=Mylvaganam|first11=Senthurun|date=2016-08-04|title=The iBRA (implant breast reconstruction evaluation) study: protocol for a prospective multi-centre cohort study to inform the feasibility, design and conduct of a pragmatic randomised clinical trial comparing new techniques of implant-based breast reconstruction|url=https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5154059/|journal=Pilot and Feasibility Studies|volume=2|doi=10.1186/s40814-016-0085-8|issn=2055-5784|pmc=5154059|pmid=27965859}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Flap-based reconstruction ===
Flap-based reconstruction uses tissue from other parts of the patient's body (i.e., autologous tissue) such as the [[human back|back]], [[buttocks]], [[thigh]] or [[human abdomen|abdomen]]. In surgery, a &quot;flap&quot; is any type of tissue that is lifted from a donor site and moved to a recipient site using its own blood supply.  Flap-based reconstruction may be performed either by leaving the donor tissue connected to the original site to retain its blood supply (where the vessels are tunneled beneath the skin surface to the new site) or by cutting the donor tissue's vessels and surgically reconnecting them to a new blood supply at the recipient site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Breast cancer {{!}} Breast reconstruction using body tissue {{!}} Cancer Research UK|url=http://www.cancerresearchuk.org/about-cancer/breast-cancer/treatment/surgery/breast-reconstruction/using-body-tissue#collapseListRefeferences|website=www.cancerresearchuk.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;[[File:Blausen 0140 BreastReconstruction TRAM.png|thumb|Transverse Rectus Abdominis Myocutaneous flap (TRAM).]]One option for breast reconstruction involves using the [[latissimus dorsi muscle]] as the donor tissue.  As a back muscle, the latissimus dorsi is large and flat and can be used without significant loss of function.  It can be moved into the breast defect while still attached to its blood supply under the arm pit (axilla). A latissimus flap is often used to recruit soft-tissue coverage over an underlying implant; however, if the latissimus flap can provide enough volume, then occasionally it is used to reconstruct small breasts without the need for an implant.  The latissimus dorsi flap has a number of advantages, but despite the advances in surgical techniques, it has remained vulnerable to skin dehiscence or necrosis at the donor site (on the back).&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt; The Mannu flap is a form of latissimus dorsi flap which avoids this complication by preserving a generous subcutaneous fat layer at the donor site and has been shown to be a safe, simple and effective way of avoiding wound dehiscence at the donor site after extended latissimus dorsi flap reconstruction.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Mannu|first1=Gurdeep S.|last2=Farooq|first2=Naheed|last3=Down|first3=Sue|last4=Burger|first4=Amy|last5=Hussien|first5=Maged I.|year=2013|title=Avoiding back wound dehiscence in extended latissimus dorsi flap reconstruction|journal=ANZ Journal of Surgery|volume=83|issue=5|pages=359–64|doi=10.1111/j.1445-2197.2012.06292.x|pmid=23088555}}&lt;/ref&gt;[[File:Blausen 0141 BreastReconstruction TRAM PostOp.png|thumb|Post-operative state after Transverse Rectus Abdominis Myocutaneous flap(TRAM).]]Another possible donor site for breast reconstruction is the abdomen.  The TRAM (transverse rectus abdominis myocutaneous) flap or its technically distinct variants of microvascular &quot;perforator flaps&quot; like the DIEP/SIEA flaps are all commonly used.  In a TRAM procedure, a portion of the abdominal tissue, which includes skin, subcutaneous fat, minor muscles, and connective tissues, is taken from the patient's abdomen and transplanted to the breast site.  Both TRAM and DIEP/SIEA use the abdominal tissue between the umbilicus (or &quot;belly button&quot;) and the pubis. The [[DIEP flap]] and free-TRAM flap require advanced microsurgical technique and are less common as a result. Both can provide enough tissue to reconstruct large breasts and are a good option for patients who would prefer to maintain their pre-operative breast volume. These procedures are preferred by some breast cancer patients because removal of the donor site tissue results in an [[abdominoplasty]] (tummy tuck) and allow the breast to be reconstructed with one's own tissues instead of a prosthetic implant that uses foreign material.  That said, TRAM flap procedures can potentially weaken the abdominal wall and torso strength, but they are generally well tolerated by most patients.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;  Perforator techniques such as the DIEP (deep inferior epigastric perforator) flap and SIEA (superficial inferior epigastric artery) flap require precise dissection of small perforating vessels through the rectus muscle and, thus, do not require removal of abdominal muscle.  Because of this, these flaps have the advantage of maintaining the majority of abdominal wall strength.

Other donor sites for autologous breast reconstruction include the buttocks, which provides tissue for the SGAP and IGAP (superior and inferior gluteal artery perforator, respectively) flaps. The purpose of perforator flaps (DIEP, SIEA, SGAP, IGAP) is to provide sufficient skin and fat for an aesthetic reconstruction while minimizing post-operative complications from harvesting the underlying muscles. DIEP reconstruction generally produces the best outcome for most women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Erić|first=M.|last2=Mihić|first2=N.|last3=Krivokuća|first3=D.|date=2009-03-01|title=Breast reconstruction following mastectomy; patient's satisfaction|journal=Acta Chirurgica Belgica|volume=109|issue=2|pages=159–166|doi=10.1080/00015458.2009.11680398|issn=0001-5458|pmid=19499674}}&lt;/ref&gt;  See [[free flap breast reconstruction]] for more information.

Mold-assisted reconstruction is a potential adjunctive process to help in flap-based reconstruction.  By using a laser and 3D printer, a patient-specific silicone mold can be used as an aid during surgery, used as a guide for orienting and shaping the flap to improve accuracy and symmetry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Melchels|first1=Ferry|last2=Wiggenhauser|first2=Paul Severin|last3=Warne|first3=David|last4=Barry|first4=Mark|last5=Ong|first5=Fook Rhu|last6=Chong|first6=Woon Shin|last7=Hutmacher|first7=Dietmar Werner|last8=Schantz|first8=Jan-Thorsten|year=2011|title=CAD/CAM-assisted breast reconstruction|url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/efaa382db73ff5d9cc7fb9fd15f720c532e940f7|journal=Biofabrication|volume=3|issue=3|pages=034114|bibcode=2011BioFa...3c4114M|doi=10.1088/1758-5082/3/3/034114|pmid=21900731}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Adjunctive procedures==
To restore the appearance of the pre-operative breast, there are a few options regarding the nipple-areolar complex (NAC):
*A [[nipple prosthesis]] can be used to restore the appearance of the reconstructed breast. Impressions can be made and photographs can be used to accurately replace the nipple lost with some types of mastectomies. This can be instrumental in restoring the psychological well-being of the breast cancer survivor. The same process can be used to replicate the remaining nipple in cases of a single mastectomy. Ideally, a prosthesis is made around the time of the mastectomy and it can be used just weeks after the surgery.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Ward|first=Christopher M.|date=1985|title=The uses of external nipple-areola prostheses following reconstruction of a breast mound after mastectomy|journal=British Journal of Plastic Surgery|language=en|volume=38|issue=1|pages=51–54|doi=10.1016/0007-1226(85)90087-6|pmid=3967113}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Nipple-areolar complex reconstruction can also be performed surgically.  Within the first year following breast reconstruction, flaps can undergo contraction and decrease in size by up to 50%.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;  Although flaps are made larger initially for this reason, it is hard to accurately predict the final breast volume.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;  Because of this, NAC reconstruction is considered the very last stage of breast reconstruction, delayed until after breast mound reconstruction is completed (including additional procedures such as fat grafting or excess tissue removal) so that the positioning of the NAC can be planned precisely.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;  There are several methods of reconstructing the nipple-areolar complex:
**'''Nipple Grafting (aka, &quot;Nipple Sharing&quot;):''' If a patient undergoes a single mastectomy with reconstruction and the opposite breast is preserved, then one option is to remove part of the preserved nipple and transfer it to the reconstructed breast.  This also requires that the patient has sufficient nipple-areolar tissue to be removed as nipple grafting will decrease the native nipple's projection by about 50%.&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Sisti|first=A.|last2=Grimaldi|first2=L.|last3=Tassinari|first3=J.|last4=Cuomo|first4=R.|last5=Fortezza|first5=L.|last6=Bocchiotti|first6=M.A.|last7=Roviello|first7=F.|last8=D'Aniello|first8=C.|last9=Nisi|first9=G.|title=Nipple-areola complex reconstruction techniques: A literature review|journal=European Journal of Surgical Oncology (EJSO)|language=en|volume=42|issue=4|pages=441–465|doi=10.1016/j.ejso.2016.01.003|pmid=26868167|year=2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;  One of the benefits of this procedure is that the color and texture of the NAC is identical to that of the opposite breast.&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot; /&gt;
**'''Local Tissue Flaps:''' For patients who have undergone bilateral mastectomies (as well as patients receiving a unilateral mastectomy who do not want to pursue nipple grafting), a nipple can be created by raising a small, local flap in the target area and producing a raised mound of skin very similar in shape to a nipple.  To create an areola, a circular incision may be made around the new nipple and sutured back again.  While this option does produce the shape and outline of the NAC, it does not affect the skin color.  To make it appear more natural, the nipple and areolar region may then be tattooed to produce a darker skin color more similar to a natural nipple and areola.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt;
**'''Local Tissue Flaps With Use of AlloDerm:''' As above, a nipple may be created by raising a small flap in the target area and producing a raised mound of skin. AlloDerm (cadaveric dermis) can then be inserted into the core of the new nipple acting like a &quot;strut&quot; which may help maintain the projection of the nipple for a longer period of time. The nipple and areolar region may then be tattooed later.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1097/01.prs.0000258831.38615.80 |pmid=17440338 |title=Use of AlloDerm in Primary Nipple Reconstruction to Improve Long-Term Nipple Projection |journal=Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery |volume=119 |issue=6 |pages=1663–8 |year=2007 |last1=Garramone |first1=Charles E. |last2=Lam |first2=Benjamin |url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/ab9fa5dba116b06474740f52a4bb974a8265b5d5 }}&lt;/ref&gt; There are, however, some important issues in relation to NAC tattooing that should be considered prior to opting for tattooing, such as the choice of pigments and equipment used for the procedure.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cosmetictattoo.org/article/3d-nipple-tattooing-a-new-service.html A. Darby. 3D Nipple Tattooing a New Service? (inc revisions). CosmeticTattoo.org Educational Articles 24/10/2013]&lt;/ref&gt;

When looking at the entire process of breast reconstruction, patients typically report that NAC reconstruction is the least satisfying step.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;  Compared to a normal nipple, the reconstructed nipple often has less projection (how far the nipple extends beyond the breast mound) and lacks sensation.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;  In women who have undergone a single mastectomy with reconstruction, another challenge in aesthetically matching the reconstructed NAC to the native breast.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;

==Outcomes==
The typical outcome of breast reconstruction surgery is a breast mound with a pleasing aesthetic shape, with a texture similar to a natural breast, but which feels completely or mostly numb for the woman herself.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;  This loss of sensation, called ''[[somatosensory loss]]'' or the inability to perceive touch, heat, cold, and pain, sometimes results in women burning themselves or injuring themselves without noticing, or not noticing that their clothing has shifted to expose their breasts.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;  &quot;I can't even feel it when my kids hug me,&quot; said one mother, who had nipple-sparing breast reconstruction after a bilateral mastectomy.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;  The loss of sensation has long-term medical consequences, because it makes the affected women unable to feel itchy rashes, infected sores, cuts, bruises, or situations that risk sunburns or frostbite on the affected areas.

More than half of women treated for breast cancer develop [[upper quarter dysfunction]], including limits on how well they can move, pain in the breast, shoulder or arm, [[lymphedema]], loss of sensation, and impaired strength.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=McNeely|first=Margaret L.|last2=Binkley|first2=Jill M.|last3=Pusic|first3=Andrea L.|last4=Campbell|first4=Kristin L.|last5=Gabram|first5=Sheryl|last6=Soballe|first6=Peter W.|date=2012-04-15|title=A prospective model of care for breast cancer rehabilitation: postoperative and postreconstructive issues|journal=Cancer|volume=118|issue=8 Suppl|pages=2226–2236|doi=10.1002/cncr.27468|issn=1097-0142|pmid=22488697|url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/b510da7391be8bd20d9e16ef5ee220f9c289d7d1}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The risk of dysfunction is higher among women who have breast reconstruction surgery.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt; One in three have complications, one in five need further surgery and the procedure fails in 5%.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2018/06/20/well/one-in-three-women-undergoing-breast-reconstruction-have-complications.html?module=WatchingPortal&amp;region=c-column-middle-span-region&amp;pgType=Homepage&amp;action=click&amp;mediaId=thumb_square&amp;state=standard&amp;contentPlacement=11&amp;version=internal&amp;contentCollection=www.nytimes.com&amp;contentId=https://www.nytimes.com/2018/06/20/well/one-in-three-women-undergoing-breast-reconstruction-have-complications.html&amp;eventName=Watching-article-click|title=One in Three Women Undergoing Breast Reconstruction Have Complications|access-date=2018-06-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some methods have specific side effects.  The [[Free flap breast reconstruction#TRAM flap — Transverse Rectus Abdominis Myocutaneous free flap|transverse rectus abdominis myocutaneous]] (TRAM) flap method results in weakness and loss of flexibility in the abdominal wall.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Atisha|first=Dunya|last2=Alderman|first2=Amy K.|date=2009-08-01|title=A systematic review of abdominal wall function following abdominal flaps for postmastectomy breast reconstruction|journal=Annals of Plastic Surgery|volume=63|issue=2|pages=222–230|doi=10.1097/SAP.0b013e31818c4a9e|issn=1536-3708|pmid=19593108|url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/a5e133f691d47c632a6c369e17faebbce0f9c6a7}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Reconstruction with implants have a higher risk of long-term pain.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;

Outcomes-based research on quality of life improvements and psychosocial benefits associated with breast reconstruction &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last2=Rumsey|first2=Nichola J.|last3=Ambler|first3=Nicholas R.|last4=Cawthorn|first4=Simon J.|last5=Reid|first5=Clive D.|last6=Maddox|first6=Paul R.|last7=Kenealy|first7=John M.|last8=Rainsbury|first8=Richard M.|last9=Umpleby|first9=Harry C.|year=2003|title=The Psychological Effect of Mastectomy with or without Breast Reconstruction: A Prospective, Multicenter Study|journal=Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery|volume=111|issue=3|pages=1060–8|doi=10.1097/01.PRS.0000046249.33122.76|pmid=12621175|last1=Harcourt|first1=Diana M.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last2=Malm|first2=Maj|last3=Blomqvist|first3=Lennart|year=2000|title=A Prospective and Randomized Study, 'SVEA,' Comparing Effects of Three Methods for Delayed Breast Reconstruction on Quality of Life, Patient-Defined Problem Areas of Life, and Cosmetic Result|journal=Plastic &amp; Reconstructive Surgery|volume=105|issue=1|pages=66–74; discussion 75–6|doi=10.1097/00006534-200001000-00011|pmid=10626972|last1=Brandberg|first1=Yvonne}}&lt;/ref&gt; served as the stimulus in the United States for the 1998 [[Women's Health and Cancer Rights Act]], which mandated that health care payer cover breast and nipple reconstruction, contralateral procedures to achieve symmetry, and treatment for the sequelae of mastectomy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dol.gov/ebsa/publications/whcra.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090116025044/https://www.dol.gov/ebsa/publications/whcra.html |archivedate=2009-01-16 |date=January 15, 2009 |title=Your Rights After A Mastectomy... Women's Health &amp; Cancer Rights Act of 1998 |publisher=U.S. Department of Labor }}&lt;/ref&gt; This was followed in 2001 by additional legislation imposing penalties on noncompliant insurers. Similar provisions for coverage exist in most countries worldwide through national health care programs.

==See also==
* [[Breast implant]]
* [[Breast lift]]
* [[Breast reduction plasty]]
* [[Free flap breast reconstruction]]
* [[Nipple prosthesis]]
* [[Titoo]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.plasticsurgery.org/public_education/procedures/BreastReconstruction.cfm ''Breast Reconstruction Following Breast Removal''] from the American Society of Plastic Surgeons
* [http://www.cancer.gov/cancertopics/types/breast National Cancer Institute breast cancer page]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20150330022609/http://www.dol.gov/ebsa/Publications/whcra.html US Dept. of Labor – Women's Health &amp; Cancer Rights Act of 1998]
* [https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB898729966633093500?mod=googlewsj Plastic Surgery Stirs a Debate]

{{Operations and other procedures of the integumentary system}}
{{Commons category|Breast reconstruction}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Breast Reconstruction}}
[[Category:Breast surgery]]</text>
      <sha1>pfne70p2f9tgd0lo6er2rf0hzgc85wy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
