  <page>
    <title>Breast</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4489</id>
    <revision>
      <id>935018294</id>
      <parentid>934816171</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-09T23:31:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Clayoquot</username>
        <id>1256755</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Puberty */ Replacing image with more detailed one</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Region of the torso of a primate containing the mammary gland}}
{{Other uses}}
{{Pp-protected|small=yes}}
{{Pp-move-indef}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2020}}
{{Use American English|date=September 2017}}
{{Infobox anatomy
| Name        = Breast
| Latin       = [[wikt:en:mamma#Latin|mamma]] (mammalis &quot;of the breast&quot;)&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web |url = http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/mammal |title = mammal – Definitions from Dictionary.com |publisher = Dictionary.reference.com |accessdate = 31 October 2011 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20111114204020/http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/mammal |archive-date = 14 November 2011 |url-status = live |df = dmy-all }}
&lt;/ref&gt;
| Image       = Weibliche brust en.jpg
| Caption     = Morphology of human breasts with the [[areola]], [[nipple]], and [[inframammary fold]]
| Width       =
| Image2      =
| Caption2    =
| Precursor   =
| System      =
| Artery      = [[internal thoracic artery]]
| Vein        = [[internal thoracic vein]]
| Nerve       =
| Lymph       =
}}

The '''breast''' is one of two prominences located on the upper [[ventral]] region of the [[torso]] of [[primate]]s. In females, it serves as the [[mammary gland]], which produces and secretes milk to feed [[infant]]s.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web |url = http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/breast |title = Breast – Definition of breast by Merriam-Webster |work = merriam-webster.com |accessdate = 21 October 2015 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20150906013636/http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/breast |archive-date = 6 September 2015 |url-status = live |df = dmy-all }}
&lt;/ref&gt; Both females and males develop breasts from the same [[embryology|embryological]] tissues. At [[puberty]], [[estrogen]]s, in conjunction with [[growth hormone]], cause [[breast development]] in female humans and to a much lesser extent in other primates.  Breast development in other primate females generally only occurs with pregnancy.

[[Subcutaneous fat]] covers and envelops a network of [[lactiferous duct|ducts]] that converge on the [[nipple]], and these [[tissue (biology)|tissues]] give the breast its size and shape. At the ends of the ducts are [[mammary lobule|lobules]], or clusters of [[mammary alveolus|alveoli]], where milk is produced and stored in response to [[hormone|hormonal signals]].&lt;ref name=SEER&gt;
{{cite web |title = SEER Training: Breast Anatomy |url = http://training.seer.cancer.gov/breast/anatomy/ |publisher = National Cancer Institute |accessdate = 9 May 2012 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20120502155537/http://training.seer.cancer.gov/breast/anatomy/ |archive-date = 2 May 2012 |url-status = live |df = dmy-all }}
&lt;/ref&gt; During pregnancy, the breast responds to a complex interaction of hormones, including [[estrogen]]s, [[progesterone]], and [[prolactin]], that mediate the completion of its development, namely [[lobuloalveolar]] maturation, in preparation of [[lactation]] and [[breastfeeding]].

Along with their major function in providing nutrition for infants, female breasts have social and sexual characteristics. Breasts have been featured in notable ancient and modern sculpture, art, and photography. They can figure prominently in the perception of a woman's body and [[Sexual attraction|sexual attractiveness]]. A number of [[culture]]s associate breasts with [[sexuality]] and tend to regard bare breasts in public as immodest or indecent. Breasts, especially the nipples, are an [[erogenous zone]].

==Etymology and terminology==
The English word ''breast'' derives from the [[Old English]] word ''brēost'' (breast, bosom) from [[Proto-Germanic]] ''breustam'' (breast), from the Proto-Indo-European base '''bhreus–''' (to swell, to sprout).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.utexas.edu/cola/centers/lrc/ielex/PokornyMaster-X.html |title = Early Indo-European Online: Introduction to the Language Lessons |website = www.utexas.edu |url-status = dead |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20160420225029/http://www.utexas.edu/cola/centers/lrc/ielex/PokornyMaster-X.html |archivedate = 20 April 2016 |df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''breast'' spelling conforms to the Scottish and North English dialectal pronunciations.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web |url = http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=breast |title = Online Etymology Dictionary |website = www.etymonline.com |access-date = 7 March 2011 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20120202185418/http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=breast |archive-date = 2 February 2012 |url-status = live |df = dmy-all }}
&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Merriam-Webster Dictionary'' states that &quot;Middle English brest, [comes] from Old English brēost; akin to Old High German brust..., Old Irish brú [belly], [and] Russian bryukho&quot;; the first known usage of the term was before the 12th century.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web |url = https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/breast |title = Definition of BREAST |website = www.merriam-webster.com |access-date = 10 December 2016 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20161220084629/https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/breast |archive-date = 20 December 2016 |url-status = live |df = dmy-all }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

A large number of colloquial terms for breasts are used in English, ranging from fairly polite terms to vulgar or slang. Some vulgar slang expressions may be considered to be derogatory or sexist to women.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web |url = http://www.timeslive.co.za/sundaytimes/lifestyle/opinion/article1754258.ece |title = Is there a respectful slang word for breasts? |first = SUE DE |last = GROOT |website = Sunday Times |access-date = 11 December 2016 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20161211114217/http://www.timeslive.co.za/sundaytimes/lifestyle/opinion/article1754258.ece |archive-date = 11 December 2016 |url-status = live |df = dmy-all }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

==Anatomy==
[[File:Breast anatomy normal scheme.png|thumb|upright=1.36|The breast: cross-section scheme of the [[mammary gland]]. {{ordered list |[[Chest wall]] |[[Pectoralis muscle]]s |[[Lobules]] |[[Nipple]] |[[Areola]] |[[Lactiferous duct|Milk duct]] |[[Adipose tissue|Fatty tissue]] |[[Skin]]}}]]

In women, the breasts overlie the [[pectoralis major muscle]]s and usually extend from the level of the second rib to the level of the sixth rib in the front of the [[human rib cage]]; thus, the breasts cover much of the chest area and the chest walls. At the front of the chest, the breast tissue can extend from the [[clavicle]] (collarbone) to the middle of the [[sternum]] (breastbone). At the sides of the chest, the breast tissue can extend into the [[axilla]] (armpit), and can reach as far to the back as the [[latissimus dorsi muscle]], extending from the lower back to the [[humerus]] bone (the bone of the upper arm). As a [[mammary gland]], the breast is composed of differing layers of [[Histology|tissue]], predominantly two types: [[adipose tissue]]; and [[Lactiferous duct|glandular tissue]], which affects the lactation functions of the breasts.
&lt;ref name=GRAYS2005&gt;{{cite book |last = Drake |first = Richard L. |title = Gray's anatomy for students |year = 2005 |publisher = Elsevier/Churchill Livingstone |location = Philadelphia |isbn = 978-0-8089-2306-0 |author2 = Vogl, Wayne |author3 = Tibbitts, Adam W.M. Mitchell |others = illustrations by Richard Richardson, Paul }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|115}}

[[Morphology (biology)|Morphologically]] the breast is tear-shaped.&lt;ref name=&quot;love_c1&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Love|first1=Susan M.|title=Dr. Susan Love's Breast Book|date=2015|publisher=Da Capo Press|location=U.S.A.|isbn=978-07382-1821-2|edition=6|chapter=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; The superficial tissue layer ([[superficial fascia]]) is separated from the skin by 0.5–2.5&amp;nbsp;cm of subcutaneous fat (adipose tissue). The [[Cooper's ligaments|suspensory Cooper's ligaments]] are fibrous-tissue prolongations that radiate from the superficial fascia to the skin envelope. The female adult breast contains 14–18 irregular lactiferous lobes that converge at the nipple. The 2.0–4.5&amp;nbsp;mm milk ducts are immediately surrounded with dense connective tissue that support the glands. Milk exits the breast through the nipple, which is surrounded by a pigmented area of skin called the areola. The size of the areola can vary widely among women. The areola contains modified [[sebaceous gland|sweat glands]] known as [[Areolar gland|Montgomery's glands]]. These glands secrete oily fluid that lubricate and protect the nipple during breastfeeding.&lt;ref name=stoppler&gt;{{cite web |last1 = Stöppler |first1 = Melissa Conrad |title = Breast Anatomy |url = http://www.medicinenet.com/breast_anatomy/article.htm |accessdate = 28 June 2015 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20150627065040/http://www.medicinenet.com/breast_anatomy/article.htm |archive-date = 27 June 2015 |url-status = live |df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Volatile compounds in these secretions may also serve as an olfactory stimulus for the newborn's appetite.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi = 10.1371/journal.pone.0007579 |ref = harv |title = The Secretion of Areolar (Montgomery's) Glands from Lactating Women Elicits Selective, Unconditional Responses in Neonates |year = 2009 |editor1-last = Hausberger |editor1-first = Martine |last1 = Doucet |first1 = Sébastien |last2 = Soussignan |first2 = Robert |last3 = Sagot |first3 = Paul |last4 = Schaal |first4 = Benoist |journal = PLoS ONE |volume = 4 |issue = 10 |pages = e7579 |pmid = 19851461 |pmc = 2761488 |bibcode = 2009PLoSO...4.7579D }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The dimensions and weight of the breast vary widely among women. A small-to-medium-sized breast weighs 500&amp;nbsp;grams (1.1 pounds) or less, and a large breast can weigh approximately 750 to 1,000 grams (1.7 to 2.2 pounds) or more. The tissue composition ratios of the breast also vary among women. Some women's breasts have varying proportions of glandular tissue than of adipose or [[connective tissue|connective]] tissues. The fat-to-connective-tissue ratio determines the density or firmness of the breast. During a woman's life, her breasts change size, shape, and weight due to hormonal changes during [[thelarche|puberty]], the [[menstruation|menstrual cycle]], pregnancy, breastfeeding, and menopause.&lt;ref&gt;Pamplona DC, de Abreu Alvim C. Breast Reconstruction with Expanders and Implants: a Numerical Analysis. Artificial Organs 8 (2004), pp. 353–356.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1 = Grassley |first1 = JS |year = 2002 |title = Breast Reduction Surgery: What every Woman Needs to Know |journal = Lifelines |volume = 6 |issue = 3 |pages = 244–249 |doi = 10.1111/j.1552-6356.2002.tb00088.x |pmid = 12078570 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Glandular structure===
The breast is an [[apocrine]] gland that produces the [[Breast milk|milk]] used to feed an infant. The [[nipple]] of the breast is surrounded by the [[areola]] (nipple-areola complex). The areola has many sebaceous glands, and the skin color varies from pink to dark brown. The basic units of the breast are the terminal duct lobular units (TDLUs), which produce the fatty breast milk. They give the breast its offspring-feeding functions as a mammary gland. They are distributed throughout the body of the breast. Approximately two-thirds of the lactiferous tissue is within 30&amp;nbsp;mm of the base of the nipple. The terminal lactiferous ducts drain the milk from TDLUs into 4–18 lactiferous ducts, which drain to the nipple. The milk-glands-to-fat ratio is 2:1 in a lactating woman, and 1:1 in a non-lactating woman. In addition to the milk glands, the breast is also composed of connective tissues ([[collagen]], [[elastin]]), white fat, and the suspensory Cooper's ligaments. Sensation in the breast is provided by the [[peripheral nervous system]] innervation by means of the front (anterior) and side (lateral) cutaneous branches of the fourth-, fifth-, and sixth [[intercostal nerves]]. The T-4 nerve ([[Thoracic spinal nerve 4]]), which innervates the [[dermatomic area]], supplies sensation to the nipple-areola complex.&lt;ref name=grabowski&gt;{{cite book |first1 = Gerard J. |last1 = Tortora |first2 = Sandra Reynolds |last2 = Grabowski |title = Introduction to the Human Body: the Essentials of Anatomy and Physiology |date = 2001 |publisher = J. Wiley |location = New York; Toronto |isbn = 978-0-471-36777-2 |edition = Fifth. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lymphatic drainage===
Approximately 75% of the [[lymph]] from the breast travels to the axillary [[lymph node]]s on the same side of the body, whilst 25% of the lymph travels to the parasternal nodes (beside the sternum bone).&lt;ref name=GRAYS2005 /&gt;{{rp|116}} A small amount of remaining lymph travels to the other breast and to the abdominal lymph nodes. The [[axillary lymph node]]s include the pectoral (chest), subscapular (under the scapula), and humeral (humerus-bone area) lymph-node groups, which drain to the central [[axillary lymph nodes]] and to the apical axillary lymph nodes. The lymphatic drainage of the breasts is especially relevant to [[oncology]] because breast cancer is common to the mammary gland, and cancer cells can [[Metastasis|metastasize]] (break away) from a [[tumour]] and be dispersed to other parts of the body by means of the lymphatic system.

===Shape, texture, and support===
The morphologic variations in the size, shape, volume, tissue density, pectoral locale, and spacing of the breasts determine their natural shape, appearance, and position on a woman's chest. Breast size and other characteristics do not predict the fat-to-milk-gland ratio or the potential for the woman to nurse an infant. The size and the shape of the breasts are influenced by normal-life hormonal changes (thelarche, menstruation, pregnancy, menopause) and medical conditions (e.g. [[virginal breast hypertrophy]]).&lt;ref name=wood&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors = Wood K, Cameron M, Fitzgerald K |title = Breast Size, Bra Fit and Thoracic Pain in Young Women: A Correlational Study |journal = Chiropractic &amp; Osteopathy |volume = 16 |page = 1 |year = 2008 |pmid = 18339205 |pmc = 2275741 |doi = 10.1186/1746-1340-16-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The shape of the breasts is naturally determined by the support of the suspensory Cooper's ligaments, the underlying muscle and bone structures of the chest, and by the skin envelope. The suspensory ligaments sustain the breast from the clavicle (collarbone) and the clavico-pectoral fascia (collarbone and chest) by traversing and encompassing the fat and milk-gland tissues. The breast is positioned, affixed to, and supported upon the chest wall, while its shape is established and maintained by the skin envelope.{{citation needed|date=June 2015}} In most women, one breast is slightly larger than the other.&lt;ref name=love_c1/&gt; More obvious and persistent asymmetry in breast size occurs in up to 25% of women.&lt;ref name=mgh2010&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.mgh.harvard.edu/children/adolescenthealth/articles/aa_breast_development.aspx |title = Breast Development |publisher = Massachusetts Hospital for Children |accessdate = 2 June 2010 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20101225165742/http://www.mgh.harvard.edu/children/adolescenthealth/articles/aa_breast_development.aspx |archivedate = 25 December 2010 |url-status = dead |df = dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

While it has been a common belief that breastfeeding causes breasts to sag,&lt;ref name=lauersen&gt;{{cite book |last = Lauersen |first = Niels H. |title = The Complete Book of Breast Care |year = 1998 |publisher = Fawcett Columbine/Ballantine |location = New York |isbn = 978-0-449-91241-6 |edition = 1st Trade Paperback |author2 = Stukane, Eileen |quote = ...there is no medical reason to wear a bra, so the decision is yours, based on your own personal comfort and aesthetics. Whether you have always worn a bra or always gone braless, age and breastfeeding will naturally fcause your breasts to sag. |url = https://archive.org/details/completebookofbr00laue_0 }}&lt;/ref&gt; researchers have found that a woman's breasts [[ptosis (breasts)|sag]] due to four key factors: cigarette smoking, [[gravidity|number of pregnancies]], [[gravity]], and weight loss or gain.&lt;ref name=thompson&gt;{{cite journal |doi = 10.1016/j.asj.2008.07.004 |lay-url = http://www.livescience.com/1998-breastfeeding-breasts-sag-study-suggests.html |laysource = LiveScience |laydate = 2 November 2007 |title = The Effect of Breastfeeding on Breast Aesthetics |year = 2008 |last1 = Rinker |first1 = B |last2 = Veneracion |first2 = M |last3 = Walsh |first3 = C |journal = Aesthetic Surgery Journal |volume = 28 |issue = 5 |pages = 534–7 |pmid = 19083576 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The base of each breast is attached to the chest by the deep fascia over the pectoralis major muscles. The space between the breast and the pectoralis major muscle, called [[retromammary space]], gives mobility to the breast. 
The chest ([[thoracic cavity]]) progressively slopes outwards from the thoracic inlet (atop the [[Human breastbone|breastbone]]) and above to the lowest ribs that support the breasts. The inframammary fold, where the lower portion of the breast meets the chest, is an anatomic feature created by the adherence of the breast skin and the underlying connective tissues of the chest; the IMF is the lower-most extent of the anatomic breast. Normal breast tissue typically has a texture that feels nodular or granular, to an extent that varies considerably from woman to woman.&lt;ref name=love_c1/&gt;
 
The study ''The Evolution of the Human Breast'' (2001) proposed that the rounded shape of a woman's breast evolved to prevent the sucking infant offspring from suffocating while feeding at the teat; that is, because of the human infant's small jaw, which did not project from the face to reach the nipple, he or she might block the [[Nose|nostrils]] against the mother's breast if it were of a flatter form (cf. [[common chimpanzee]]). Theoretically, as the human jaw receded into the face, the woman's body compensated with round breasts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bentley&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last = Bentley |first = Gillian R. |year = 2001 |title = The Evolution of the Human Breast |journal = American Journal of Physical Anthropology |volume = 32 |issue = 38 |doi = 10.1002/ajpa.1033 |pages = 30–50 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Development==
{{Main|Breast development}}
The breasts are principally composed of adipose, [[glandular tissue|glandular]], and [[w:connective tissue|connective]] tissues.&lt;ref name=&quot;yen&quot;&gt;{{citation |title = Yen &amp; Jaffe's Reproductive Endocrinology |url = https://www.elsevier.com/books/yen-and-jaffes-reproductive-endocrinology/strauss/978-1-4160-4907-4 |author = Robert L. Barbieri |doi = 10.1016/B978-1-4160-4907-4.00010-3 |edition = 6th |publisher = Elsevier |date = 2009 |journal = Yen |pages = 235–248 |isbn = 978-1-4160-4907-4 |access-date = 6 March 2018 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20180306142739/https://www.elsevier.com/books/yen-and-jaffes-reproductive-endocrinology/strauss/978-1-4160-4907-4 |archive-date = 6 March 2018 |url-status = live |df = dmy-all }}
&lt;/ref&gt; Because these tissues have hormone receptors,&lt;ref name=&quot;yen&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;gland activation&quot;&gt;{{citation |title = Hormone Action in the Mammary Gland |author1 = Brisken |author2 = Malley |doi = 10.1101/cshperspect.a003178 |date = 2 December 2010 |pmid = 20739412 |pmc = 2982168 |volume = 2 |issue = 12 |journal = Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol |pages = a003178 }}&lt;/ref&gt; their sizes and volumes fluctuate according to the hormonal changes particular to thelarche (sprouting of breasts), menstruation (egg production), pregnancy (reproduction), lactation (feeding of offspring), and menopause (end of menstruation).

===Puberty===
[[File:Breast Tanner Stages.tif|thumb|Breast development in puberty is measured with the five-stage Tanner Scale]]

The morphological structure of the human breast is identical in males and females until [[puberty]]. For pubescent girls in thelarche (the breast-development stage), the female [[sex hormone]]s (principally estrogens) in conjunction with [[growth hormone]] promote the sprouting, growth, and development of the breasts. During this time, the mammary glands grow in size and volume and begin resting on the chest. These development stages of [[secondary sex characteristic]]s (breasts, pubic hair, etc.) are illustrated in the five-stage [[Tanner stage|Tanner Scale]].&lt;ref name=&quot;A.R.Greenbaum&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors = Greenbaum AR, Heslop T, Morris J, Dunn KW |title = An Investigation of the Suitability of Bra fit in Women Referred for Reduction Mammaplasty |journal = British Journal of Plastic Surgery |volume = 56 |issue = 3 |pages = 230–6 |date = April 2003 |pmid = 12859918 |doi = 10.1016/S0007-1226(03)00122-X }}&lt;/ref&gt;

During [[thelarche]] the developing breasts are sometimes of unequal size, and usually the left breast is slightly larger. This condition of asymmetry is transitory and statistically normal in female physical and sexual development.&lt;ref name=&quot;asymmetry&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author = Loughry CW |title = Breast Volume Measurement of 598 Women using Biostereometric Analysis |journal = Annals of Plastic Surgery |year = 1989 |volume = 22 |issue = 5 |pages = 380–385 |doi = 10.1097/00000637-198905000-00002 |pmid = 2729845 |display-authors = 1 |last2 = Sheffer |first2 = Daniel B. |last3 = Price |first3 = Thomas E. |last4 = Einsporn |first4 = Richard L. |last5 = Bartfai |first5 = Ronald G. |last6 = Morek |first6 = Wayne M. |last7 = Meli |first7 = Nancy M. }}&lt;/ref&gt; Medical conditions can cause overdevelopment (e.g., virginal breast hypertrophy, [[macromastia]]) or underdevelopment (e.g., [[tuberous breast deformity]], [[micromastia]]) in girls and women.

Approximately two years after the onset of puberty (a girl's first [[menstrual cycle]]), estrogen and growth hormone stimulate the development and growth of the glandular fat and suspensory tissues that compose the breast. This continues for approximately four years until the final shape of the breast (size, volume, density) is established at about the age of 21. [[Mammoplasia]] (breast enlargement) in girls begins at puberty, unlike all other primates in which breasts enlarge only during lactation.&lt;ref name=&quot;stoppler&quot; /&gt;
[[File:Stretch marks on female breast.jpg|thumb|right|Breast with visible [[stretch marks]]]]

===Changes during the menstrual cycle===
During the menstrual cycle, the breasts are enlarged by [[premenstrual water retention]] and temporary growth.&lt;ref name=&quot;mlpswelling&quot;&gt;{{citation |title = Breast – premenstrual tenderness and swelling |url = https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003153.htm |publisher = A.D.A.M. |date = May 2012 |access-date = 21 March 2018 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20160705060104/https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003153.htm |archive-date = 5 July 2016 |url-status = live |df = dmy-all }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Pregnancy and breastfeeding===
The breasts reach full maturity only when a woman's first pregnancy occurs.{{sfn | Lawrence | 2016 | p=34}}  Changes to the breasts are among the very first signs of pregnancy. The breasts become larger, the nipple-areola complex becomes larger and darker, the [[Montgomery's glands]] enlarge, and veins sometimes become more visible. Breast tenderness during pregnancy is common, especially during the first trimester. By mid-pregnancy, the breast is physiologically capable of lactation and some women can express [[colostrum]], a form of breast milk.{{sfn | Lawrence | 2016 | p=58}}

Pregnancy causes elevated levels of the hormone [[prolactin]], which has a key role in the production of milk. However, milk production is blocked by the hormones [[progesterone]] and [[estrogen]] until after delivery, when progesterone and estrogen levels plummet.&lt;ref name=&quot;NCBI Bookshelf 2008&quot;/&gt;

===Menopause===

At menopause, breast atrophy occurs. The breasts can decrease in size when the levels of circulating estrogen decline. The adipose tissue and milk glands also begin to wither. The breasts can also become enlarged from [[Adverse effect|adverse side effect]]&lt;nowiki/&gt;s of [[combined oral contraceptive pill]]s. The size of the breasts can also increase and decrease in response to [[body weight|weight]] fluctuations. Physical changes to the breasts are often recorded in the [[stretch marks]] of the skin envelope; they can serve as historical indicators of the increments and the decrements of the size and volume of a woman's breasts throughout the course of her life.{{citation needed|date=June 2015}}

==Breastfeeding==
{{Main|Breastfeeding}}

The primary function of the breasts, as mammary glands, is the nourishing of an infant with [[breast milk]]. Milk is produced in milk-secreting cells in the alveoli. When the breasts are stimulated by the suckling of her baby, the mother's brain secretes [[oxytocin]]. High levels of oxytocin trigger the contraction of muscle cells surrounding the alveoli, causing milk to flow along the ducts that connect the alveoli to the nipple.&lt;ref name=&quot;NCBI Bookshelf 2008&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=The physiological basis of breastfeeding | website=NCBI Bookshelf | date=5 November 2008 | url=https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK148970/ | access-date=13 February 2018 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180119051121/https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK148970/ | archive-date=19 January 2018 | url-status=live | df=dmy-all }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

Full-term newborns have an instinct and a need to suck on a nipple, and breastfed babies nurse for both nutrition and for comfort.{{sfn|Lawrence|2016|p=201}}  Breast milk provides all necessary nutrients for the first six months of life, and then remains an important source of nutrition, alongside solid foods, until at least one or two years of age.

==Clinical significance==
{{Main|Breast disease}}

The breast is susceptible to numerous benign and malignant conditions. The most frequent benign conditions are [[puerperal mastitis]], [[fibrocystic breast changes]] and [[mastalgia]].

[[Lactation]] unrelated to pregnancy is known as [[galactorrhea]]. It can be caused by certain drugs (such as [[antipsychotic]] medications), extreme physical stress, or [[endocrine]] disorders. Lactation in newborns is caused by hormones from the mother that crossed into the baby's bloodstream during pregnancy.

===Breast cancer===
{{Main|Breast cancer}}
Breast cancer is the most common cause of cancer death among women&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web |author = World Health Organization |date = February 2006 |title = Fact sheet No. 297: Cancer |url = http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs297/en/index.html |accessdate = 26 April 2007 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20140213212322/http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs297/en/index.html |archive-date = 13 February 2014 |url-status = live |df = dmy-all |author-link = World Health Organization }}
&lt;/ref&gt; and it is one of the leading causes of death among women. Factors that appear to be implicated in decreasing the risk of breast cancer are regular breast examinations by health care professionals, regular [[mammograms]], [[Breast self-examination|self-examination of breasts]], healthy diet, and exercise to decrease excess body fat,&lt;ref&gt;
[http://hms.harvard.edu/public/disease/breast_cancer/7things.html Seven things you should know about breast cancer risk] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100704055600/http://hms.harvard.edu/public/disease/breast_cancer/7things.html |date=4 July 2010 }} Harvard College. Last updated June 2008
&lt;/ref&gt; and [[breastfeeding]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://cebp.aacrjournals.org/content/26/5_Supplement/IA23|website=American Association for Cancer Research|title=Reducing cancer risk by enabling women to breastfeed}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Male breasts===
Both females and males develop breasts from the same [[embryology|embryological]] tissues. Normally, males produce lower levels of estrogens and higher levels of [[androgen]]s, namely [[testosterone]], which suppress the effects of estrogens in developing excessive breast tissue.
In boys and men, abnormal breast development is manifested as [[gynecomastia]], the consequence of a biochemical imbalance between the normal levels of estrogen and testosterone in the male body.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author = Olson, James Stuart |title = Bathsheba's Breast: Women, Cancer and History |publisher = The Johns Hopkins University Press |location = Baltimore |year = 2002 |page = [https://archive.org/details/bathshebasbreast00olso/page/109 109] |oclc = 186453370 |isbn = 978-0-8018-6936-5 |url = https://archive.org/details/bathshebasbreast00olso/page/109 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Around 70% of boys temporarily develop breast tissue during adolescence.&lt;ref name=mgh2010/&gt;
The condition usually resolves by itself within two years.&lt;ref name=mgh2010/&gt; When [[male lactation]] occurs, it is considered a symptom of a disorder of the [[pituitary gland]].

===Plastic surgery===
[[File:Mastectomy Procedures.jpg|thumb|Conventional mastectomy ''(top)''; skin sparing mastectomy and [[latissimus dorsi]] myocutaneous flap reconstruction, prior to nipple reconstruction and tattooing ''(bottom)''.]]

Plastic surgery can be performed to [[Breast augmentation|augment]] or [[Breast reduction|reduce]] the size of breasts, or [[reconstructive surgery|reconstruct]] the breast in cases of deformative disease, such as breast cancer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.sexarchive.info/ATLAS_EN/html/secondary_characteristics.html |title = Secondary sex characteristics |publisher = .hu-berlin.de |accessdate = 31 October 2011 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20130622035035/http://www.sexarchive.info/ATLAS_EN/html/secondary_characteristics.html |archive-date = 22 June 2013 |url-status = live |df = dmy-all }}
&lt;/ref&gt; Breast augmentation and breast lift ([[mastopexy]]) procedures are done only for cosmetic reasons, whereas breast reduction is sometimes medically indicated.&lt;ref name=love_c1/&gt;
In cases where a woman's breasts are severely asymmetrical, surgery can be performed to either enlarge the smaller breast, reduce the size of the larger breast, or both.&lt;ref name=love_c1/&gt;

Breast augmentation surgery generally does not interfere with future ability to breastfeed.{{sfn | Lawrence | 2016 | pp= 613–616}} Breast reduction surgery more frequently leads to decreased sensation in the nipple-areola complex, and to low milk supply in women who choose to breastfeed.{{sfn | Lawrence | 2016 | pp= 613–616}} Implants can interfere with [[mammography]] (breast x-rays images).

==Society and culture==

===General===
In [[Saint symbology|Christian iconography]], some works of art depict women with their breasts in their hands or on a platter, signifying that they died as a martyr by having their breasts severed; one example of this is [[Agatha of Sicily|Saint Agatha of Sicily]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title = St Agatha |url = http://www.catholic.org/saints/saint.php?saint_id=14 |publisher = Catholic Online |accessdate = 27 December 2015 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20160304000129/http://www.catholic.org/saints/saint.php?saint_id=14 |archive-date = 4 March 2016 |url-status = live |df = dmy-all }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bare breasts are our weapons crop.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Femen]] member participating in a protest]]

[[Femen]] is a [[feminism|feminist]] activist group which uses [[topless protest]]s as part of their campaigns against [[sex tourism]]&lt;ref name=FEMEN&gt;[http://www.kyivpost.com/news/politics/detail/65379/ Femen wants to move from public exposure to political power] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101207042451/http://www.kyivpost.com/news/politics/detail/65379 |date=7 December 2010 }}, ''[[Kyiv Post]]'' (28 April 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;movements1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.movements.org/case-study/entry/ukraines-ladies-of-femen/ |title = Ukraine's Ladies of Femen |publisher = Movements.org |date = 16 August 2011 |accessdate = 22 April 2013 |url-status = dead |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20120414005441/http://www.movements.org/case-study/entry/ukraines-ladies-of-femen |archivedate = 14 April 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; religious institutions,&lt;ref name=BBCobservOct12&gt;
[https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-20028797 Ukraine's Femen:Topless protests 'help feminist cause'] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180412230110/http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-20028797 |date=12 April 2018 }}, [[BBC News]] (23 October 2012)&lt;/ref&gt; [[sexism]], [[homophobia]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url = http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/04/24/topless-femen-protest-andre-jozef-leonard_n_3146609.html |title = Topless FEMEN Protesters Drench Belgian Archbishop André-Jozef Léonard, Protest Homophobia in Catholic Church (PHOTOS) |work = The Huffington Post |accessdate = 23 March 2015 |date = 24 April 2013 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20150416042913/http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/04/24/topless-femen-protest-andre-jozef-leonard_n_3146609.html |archive-date = 16 April 2015 |url-status = live |df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; and to &quot;defend [women's] right to abortion&quot;.&lt;ref name=RussiaTimes&gt;{{cite news |url = http://rt.com/news/femen-protest-abortion-ukraine-705/ |title = FEMEN rings the bell: Naked activists defend right to abortion |publisher = Russia Today |date = 10 April 2012 |access-date = 11 December 2016 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20170201214225/https://www.rt.com/news/femen-protest-abortion-ukraine-705/ |archive-date = 1 February 2017 |url-status = live |df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Femen activists have been regularly detained by police in response to their protests.&lt;ref name=BBCTunis&gt;[https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-22881163 Femen activists jailed in Tunisia for topless protest] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180827210121/https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-22881163 |date=27 August 2018 }}, [[BBC News]] (12 June 2013)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RussiaTimes&quot; /&gt;

There is a long history of female breasts being used by comedians as a subject for comedy fodder (e.g., British comic [[Benny Hill|Benny Hill's]] burlesque/slapstick routines).&lt;ref name=&quot;thedailybeast.com&quot; /&gt;

===Art history===
In European pre-historic societies, sculptures of female figures with pronounced or highly exaggerated breasts were common. A typical example is the so-called [[Venus of Willendorf]], one of many [[Paleolithic]] [[Venus figurines]] with ample hips and bosom. Artifacts such as bowls, rock carvings and sacred statues with breasts have been recorded from 15,000&amp;nbsp;BC up to late antiquity all across Europe, North Africa and the Middle East.

Many female deities representing love and fertility were associated with breasts and breast milk. Figures of the Phoenician goddess [[Astarte]] were represented as pillars studded with breasts. [[Isis]], an Egyptian goddess who represented, among many other things, ideal motherhood, was often portrayed as suckling [[pharaohs]], thereby confirming their divine status as rulers. Even certain male deities representing regeneration and fertility were occasionally depicted with breast-like appendices, such as the river god [[Hapy]] who was considered to be responsible for the annual overflowing of the [[Nile]].

Female breasts were also prominent in the [[Minoan civilization]] in the form of the famous [[Snake Goddess]] statuettes. In [[Ancient Greece]] there were several cults worshipping the &quot;Kourotrophos&quot;, the suckling mother, represented by goddesses such as [[Gaia (mythology)|Gaia]], [[Hera]] and [[Artemis]]. The worship of deities symbolized by the female breast in Greece became less common during the first millennium. The popular adoration of female goddesses decreased significantly during the rise of the Greek city states, a legacy which was passed on to the later [[Roman Empire]].&lt;ref&gt;Yalom (1998) pp. 9–16; see Eva Keuls (1993), ''Reign of the Phallus: Sexual Politics in Ancient Athens'' for a detailed study of male-dominant rule in ancient Greece.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the middle of the first millennium BC, Greek culture experienced a gradual change in the perception of female breasts. Women in art were covered in clothing from the neck down, including female goddesses like [[Athena]], the patron of Athens who represented heroic endeavor. There were exceptions: [[Aphrodite]], the goddess of love, was more frequently portrayed fully nude, though in postures that were intended to portray shyness or modesty, a portrayal that has been compared to modern [[Pin-up|pin ups]] by historian [[Marilyn Yalom]].&lt;ref&gt;Yalom (1998), p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; Although nude men were depicted standing upright, most depictions of female nudity in Greek art occurred &quot;usually with drapery near at hand and with a forward-bending, self-protecting posture&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Hollander (1993), p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; A popular legend at the time was of the [[Amazons]], a tribe of fierce female warriors who socialized with men only for procreation and even removed one breast to become better warriors (the idea being that the right breast would interfere with the operation of a bow and arrow). The legend was a popular motif in art during Greek and Roman antiquity and served as an antithetical cautionary tale.

&lt;gallery widths=&quot;200px&quot; heights=&quot;200px&quot;&gt;
File:Θεά των Όφεων 6393.JPG|A [[Minoan snake goddess figurines|Cretan snake goddess]] from the [[Minoan civilization]], {{circa|1600}}&amp;nbsp;BC
File:Robert Dampier's oil on canvas painting 'Tetuppa, a Native Female of the Sandwich Islands', 1825.jpg|1825 oil painting entitled ''Tetuppa, a Native Female of the Sandwich Islands'', by [[Robert Dampier]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

===Body image===
Many women regard their breasts as important to their [[sexual attractiveness]], as a sign of [[femininity]] that is important to their [[Self-concept|sense of self]].

===Clothing===
{{See also|Brassiere|Cleavage (breasts)|Toplessness|Modesty|Naturism|Exhibitionism}}
[[File:Namibie Himba 0716a.jpg|thumb|upright|As is customary in her culture, a bare-breasted [[Himba people|Himba]] woman of northern Namibia wears a traditional headdress and skirt]]

Because breasts are mostly fatty tissue, their shape can -within limits- be molded by clothing, such as [[foundation garment]]s. [[brassiere|Bras]] are commonly worn by about 90% of Western women,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.1stbras.com/bra-cup-sizes.php |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20160308210937/http://www.1stbras.com/bra-cup-sizes.php |url-status = dead |archive-date = 8 March 2016 |title = Bra Cup Sizes—getting fitted with the right size |publisher = 1stbras.com |accessdate = 11 May 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.liv.com/right_bra.php |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20090328083521/http://www.liv.com/right_bra.php |url-status = dead |archive-date = 28 March 2009 |title = The Right Bra |publisher = Liv.com |accessdate = 11 May 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news |url = https://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/this-britain/breast-supporting-act-a-century-of-the-bra-5334510.html |title = Breast supporting act: a century of the bra |date = 15 August 2007 |publisher = The Independent UK |accessdate = 11 May 2010 |location = London |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20160305101134/http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/this-britain/breast-supporting-act-a-century-of-the-bra-5334510.html |archive-date = 5 March 2016 |url-status = live |df = dmy-all }}
&lt;/ref&gt; and are often worn for support.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |pmc = 2275741 |pmid = 18339205 |doi = 10.1186/1746-1340-16-1 |volume = 16 |title = Breast size, bra fit and thoracic pain in young women: a correlational study |year = 2008 |journal = Chiropr Osteopat |pages = 1 |last1 = Wood |first1 = K |last2 = Cameron |first2 = M |last3 = Fitzgerald |first3 = K }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[social norm]] in most [[Western culture]]s is to cover breasts in public, though the extent of coverage varies depending on the social context. Some religions ascribe a special status to the female breast, either in formal teachings or through symbolism.{{citation needed|date=April 2013}} [[Islam]] forbids women from exposing their breasts in public.

Many cultures, including Western cultures in North America, associate breasts with sexuality and tend to regard bare breasts as [[modesty|immodest]] or [[decency|indecent]]. In some cultures, like the [[Himba people|Himba]] in northern [[Namibia]], bare-breasted women are normal. In some African cultures, for example, the thigh is regarded as highly sexualised and never exposed in public, but breast exposure is not taboo. In a few [[Western world|Western countries]] and regions female [[toplessness]] at a beach is acceptable, although it may not be acceptable in the town center.{{citation needed|date=January 2018}}

Social attitudes and laws regarding [[breastfeeding in public]] vary widely. In many countries, breastfeeding in public is common, legally protected, and generally not regarded as an issue. However, even though the practice may be legal or socially accepted, some mothers may nevertheless be reluctant to expose a breast in public to breastfeed&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1186/1746-4358-3-11|title=Got milk? Not in public!|pmid=18680578|year=2008|last1=Wolf|first1=J.H.|volume=3|issue=1|page=11|pmc=2518137|journal=International Breastfeeding Journal}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Vance_2005&gt;{{cite journal | last = Vance | first = Melissa R. | title = Breastfeeding Legislation in the United States: A General Overview and Implications for Helping Mothers | journal = LEAVEN | volume = 41 | issue = 3 | pages = 51–54 | date = June–July 2005 | url = http://www.llli.org/llleaderweb/LV/LVJunJul05p51.html | ref = harv | url-status = dead | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070331220518/http://www.llli.org/llleaderweb/LV/LVJunJul05p51.html | archivedate = 31 March 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; due to actual or potential objections by other people, negative comments, or harassment.&lt;ref name=Jordan_2002&gt;{{cite book |editor-last=Jordan |editor-first=Tim |editor-last2=Pile |editor-first2=Steve |title=Social Change|page=233|publisher=Blackwell|year=2002|isbn=9780631233114}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is estimated that around 63% of mothers across the world have publicly breast-fed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Breast Feeding With Confidence|last = Cox|first = Sue|publisher = Meadowbrook Press|year = 2002|isbn = 0684040050|location = United States|url-access = registration|url = https://archive.org/details/breastfeedingwit00suec}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bare-breasted women are legal and culturally acceptable at public beaches in Australia and much of Europe.{{citation needed|date=June 2015}} Filmmaker [[Lina Esco]] made a film entitled ''[[Free the Nipple]]'', which is about &quot;...laws against female toplessness or restrictions on images of female, but not male, nipples&quot;, which Esco states is an example of [[sexism]] in society.&lt;ref name=&quot;thedailybeast.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url = http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2014/09/09/women-it-s-time-to-reclaim-our-breasts.html |title = Women, It's Time to Reclaim Our Breasts |first = Emily |last = Shire |date = 9 September 2014 |newspaper = The Daily Beast |access-date = 11 December 2016 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20161101085547/http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2014/09/09/women-it-s-time-to-reclaim-our-breasts.html |archive-date = 1 November 2016 |url-status = live |df = dmy-all }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sexual characteristic===
{{See also|Mammary intercourse|Breast fetishism|Stimulation of nipples}}

In some cultures, breasts play a role in [[human sexual activity]]. In Western culture, breasts have a &quot;...hallowed sexual status, arguably more fetishized than either sex’s genitalia&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;thedailybeast.com&quot; /&gt; Breasts and especially the nipples are among the various human [[erogenous zone]]s. They are sensitive to the touch as they have many nerve endings; and it is common to press or [[massage]] them with hands or [[stimulation of nipples|orally]] before or during sexual activity. During [[sexual arousal]], breast size increases, [[vein|venous]] patterns across the breasts become more visible, and nipples harden. Compared to other primates, human breasts are proportionately large throughout adult females' lives. Some writers have suggested that they may have evolved as a visual signal of sexual maturity and fertility.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author = Anders Pape Møller |title = Breast asymmetry, sexual selection, and human reproductive success |journal = Ethology and Sociobiology |year = 1995 |volume = 16 |issue = 3 |pages = 207–219 |doi = 10.1016/0162-3095(95)00002-3 |display-authors = 1 |last2 = Soler |first2 = M |last3 = Thornhill |first3 = R }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many people regard bare female breasts to be [[aesthetics|aesthetically]] pleasing or [[erotic]], and they can elicit heightened [[sexual desire]]s in men in many cultures. In the [[History of India|ancient Indian]] work the ''[[Kama Sutra]]'', light scratching of the breasts with nails and biting with teeth are considered erotic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.sacred-texts.com/sex/kama/index.htm |title = Sir Richard Burton's English translation of Kama Sutra |publisher = Sacred-texts.com |accessdate = 31 October 2011 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20100102051149/http://sacred-texts.com/sex/kama/index.htm |archivedate = 2 January 2010 |url-status = live |df = dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; Some people show a [[sexual interest]] in female breasts distinct from that of the person, which may be regarded as a [[breast fetish]].&lt;ref&gt;Hickey, Eric W. (2003). Encyclopaedia of Murder and Violent Crime. Sage Publications Inc. {{ISBN|978-0-7619-2437-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; A number of Western fashions include clothing which accentuate the breasts, such as the use of [[push-up bra]]s and [[decollete]] (plunging neckline) gowns and blouses which show [[cleavage (breasts)|cleavage]]. While U.S. culture prefers breasts that are youthful and upright, some cultures venerate women with drooping breasts, indicating mothering and the wisdom of experience.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last = Burns-Ardolino |first = Wendy |title = Jiggle: (Re)shaping American women |year = 2007 |publisher = Lexington Books |location = Lanham, MD |isbn = 978-0-7391-1299-1 |page = 31 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Research conducted at the [[Victoria University of Wellington]] showed that breasts are often the first thing men look at, and for a longer time than other body parts.&lt;ref name=ASB&gt;{{cite journal |last = Dixson |first = BJ |last2 = Grimshaw |first2 = GM |author-link2 =  |last3 = Linklater |first3 = WL |author-link3 =  |last4 = Dixson |first4 = AF |author-link4 =  |title = Eye-tracking of men's preferences for waist-to-hip ratio and breast size of women |journal = [[Archives of Sexual Behavior]] |volume = 40 |issue = 1 |pages = 43–50 |publisher = [[International Academy of Sex Research]] |date = February 2011 |doi = 10.1007/s10508-009-9523-5 |pmid = 19688590 |access-date = }}&lt;/ref&gt; The writers of the study had initially speculated that the reason for this is due to [[endocrinology]] with larger breasts indicating higher levels of estrogen and a sign of greater fertility,&lt;ref name=ASB /&gt;&lt;ref name=BBC&gt;{{cite news |url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/3682657.stm |title = Hourglass figure fertility link |work = BBC News |date = 4 May 2004 |accessdate = 31 October 2011 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20111011122830/http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/3682657.stm |archive-date = 11 October 2011 |url-status = live |df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; but the researchers said that &quot;Men may be looking more often at the breasts because they are simply aesthetically pleasing, regardless of the size.&quot;&lt;ref name=ASB /&gt;

Some women report achieving an [[orgasm]] from nipple stimulation, but this is rare.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kinsey&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author1 = Alfred C. Kinsey |author2 = Wardell B. Pomeroy |author3 = Clyde E. Martin |author4 = Paul H. Gebhard |title = Sexual Behavior in the Human Female |publisher = [[Indiana University Press]] |isbn = 0-253-01924-9 |page = 587 |date = 1998 |accessdate = 12 August 2017 |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=JHWHCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA587 |quote = There are some females who appear to find no erotic satisfaction in having their breasts manipulated; perhaps half of them derive some distinct satisfaction, but not more than a very small percentage ever respond intensely enough to reach orgasm as a result of such stimulation (Chapter 5). [...] Records of females reaching orgasm from breast stimulation alone are rare. }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Boston&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author = Boston Women's Health Book Collective |title = The New Our Bodies, Ourselves: A Book by and for Women |publisher = [[Simon &amp; Schuster]] |isbn = 0-684-82352-7 |page = 575 |date = 1996 |accessdate = 12 August 2017 |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=JFI4AQAAIAAJ&amp;q |quote = A few women can even experience orgasm from breast stimulation alone. }}&lt;/ref&gt; Research suggests that the orgasms are genital orgasms, and may also be directly linked to &quot;the genital area of the brain&quot;. In these cases, it seems that sensation from the nipples travels to the same part of the brain as sensations from the vagina, clitoris and cervix. Nipple stimulation may trigger uterine contractions, which then produce a sensation in the genital area of the brain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author = Merril D. Smith |title = Cultural Encyclopedia of the Breast |publisher = [[Rowman &amp; Littlefield]] |isbn = 978-0-7591-2332-8 |page = 71 |date = 2014 |accessdate = 12 August 2017 |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=qrCCBAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA71 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lehmiller&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author = Justin J. Lehmiller |title = The Psychology of Human Sexuality |publisher = [[John Wiley &amp; Sons]] |isbn = 978-1-118-35132-1 |page = 120 |date = 2013 |accessdate = 12 August 2017 |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=pQRgAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT120 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Komisaruk&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |author1 = Komisaruk, B. R. |author2 = Wise, N. |author3 = Frangos, E. |author4 = Liu, W.C. |author5 = Allen, K. |author6 = Brody, S. |title = Women's Clitoris, Vagina, and Cervix Mapped on the Sensory Cortex: fMRI Evidence, Surprise finding in response to nipple stimulation |journal = [[The Journal of Sexual Medicine]] |year = 2011 |doi = 10.1111/j.1743-6109.2011.02388.x |lay-url = http://www.cbsnews.com/news/surprise-finding-in-response-to-nipple-stimulation/ |laysource = [[CBS]]news.com |laydate = 5 August 2011 |volume = 8 |issue = 10 |pages = 2822–30 |pmid = 21797981 |pmc = 3186818 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Anthropomorphic geography===
{{Main|Breast-shaped hill}}

There are many mountains named after the breast because they resemble it in appearance and so are objects of religious and ancestral veneration as a fertility symbol and of well-being. In Asia, there was &quot;Breast Mountain&quot;, which had a cave where the [[Buddhist monk]] [[Bodhidharma]] (Da Mo) spent much time in [[meditation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.usashaolintemple.org/chanbuddhism-history/ |title = The Story of Bodhidharma |publisher = Usashaolintemple.org |accessdate = 31 October 2011 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20111130054841/http://www.usashaolintemple.org/chanbuddhism-history/ |archive-date = 30 November 2011 |url-status = live |df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Other such breast mountains are [[Mount Elgon]] on the [[Uganda]]-[[Kenya]] border, [[Lochnagar|Beinn Chìochan]] and the [[Maiden Paps, Caithness|Maiden Paps]] in Scotland, the &quot;Bundok ng Susong Dalaga&quot; (Maiden's breast mountains) in [[Talim Island]], Philippines, the twin hills known as the [[Paps of Anu]] (''Dá Chích Anann'' or &quot;the breasts of [[Anu (goddess)|Anu]]&quot;), near [[Killarney]] in Ireland, the 2,086&amp;nbsp;m high ''Tetica de Bacares'' or &quot;La Tetica&quot; in the [[Sierra de Los Filabres]], Spain, and [[Khao Nom Sao]] in Thailand, [[Cerro Las Tetas]] in [[Puerto Rico]] and the Breasts of Aphrodite in Mykonos, among many others. In the United States, the [[Teton Range]] is named after the French word for &quot;breast&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.nps.gov/parkhistory/online_books/grte/grte_geology/sec1.htm |title = Creation of the Teton Landscape: The Geologic Story of Grand Teton National Park (The Story Begins) |publisher = U.S. National Park Service |date = 19 January 2007 |accessdate = 23 September 2011 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20150419054617/http://www.nps.gov/parkhistory/online_books/grte/grte_geology/sec1.htm |archive-date = 19 April 2015 |url-status = live |df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* {{Portal-inline|Medicine}}
* {{Portal-inline|Human sexuality}}

==References==
=== Citations ===
{{Reflist}}

=== Bibliography ===
* {{cite book |last = Hollander |first = Anne |title = Seeing through clothes |publisher = University of California Press |location = Berkeley |year = 1993 |isbn = 978-0-520-08231-1 }}
* [[Desmond Morris|Morris, Desmond]] ''The Naked Ape: a zoologist's study of the human animal'' Bantam Books, Canada. 1967
* {{cite book |last = Yalom |first = Marilyn |title = A history of the breast |publisher = Pandora |location = London |year = 1998 |isbn = 978-0-86358-400-8 }}
* {{cite book |last = Venes |first = Donald |title = Taber's cyclopedic medical dictionary |publisher = F.A. Davis |location = Philadelphia |year = 2013 |isbn = 978-0-8036-2977-6 }}
* {{cite book | last=Lawrence | first=Ruth | title=Breastfeeding : a guide for the medical profession, 8th edition | publisher=Elsevier | location=Philadelphia, PA | year=2016 | isbn=978-0-323-35776-0 | ref=harv}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|breasts}}
{{Commons category|Breasts}}
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Wikibooks|Radiation Oncology/Breast}}
{{Wikisource|1911 Encyclopædia Britannica/Breast}}
* {{cite web |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20111202170751/http://www.nyu.edu/fas/ihpk/CultureMatters/Mascia-Lees.htm |title = Are Women Evolutionary Sex Objects?: Why Women Have Breasts |archivedate = 2 December 2011 |url = http://www.nyu.edu/fas/ihpk/CultureMatters/Mascia-Lees.htm }}

{{Breast anatomy}}
{{Disorders of the breast}}
{{Sex}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Breast| ]]
[[Category:Breastfeeding]]
[[Category:Human sexuality]]</text>
      <sha1>3mbal2dq6zg9bzwvrul0j6sqkkosbfi</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
