  <page>
    <title>Book of Nahum</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4453</id>
    <revision>
      <id>934871485</id>
      <parentid>932597370</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-09T00:05:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Alephb</username>
        <id>5105042</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Background */ spacing</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Tanakh OT|Nevi'im|prophetic}}
The '''Book of Nahum''' is the seventh book of the 12 [[minor prophets]] of the [[Hebrew Bible]]. It is attributed to the prophet [[Nahum]], and was probably written in [[Jerusalem]] in the 7th century BC.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;There is no explicit date in the book of Nahum, but internal evidence suggests a date in the mid-seventh century.&quot; {{cite book |last=Baker |first=David W. |date=1988 |title=Nahum, Habakkuk and Zephaniah |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=zdu2CwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA18&amp;dq=nahum+date+seventh+century&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjqiaXav7HRAhUn0YMKHRdRD1MQ6AEIKDAC#v=onepage&amp;q=nahum%20date%20seventh%20century&amp;f=false |location=Downers Grove, IL |publisher=InterVarsity Press |page=18 |isbn=978-0-8308-9482-6 |author-link= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
[[Josephus]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://archive.org/details/L326JosephusJewishAntiquitiesVIII1213|title=Vol. VI: Jewish Antiquities, Books IX–XI|last=Josephus|first=Flavius|publisher=William Heinemann|year=1958|isbn=|series=Loeb Classical Library|volume=326|location=London|pages=125–129, XI.xi.2–3|translator-last=Marcus|translator-first=William}}&lt;/ref&gt; places [[Nahum]] during the reign of [[Jotham of Judah|Jotham]], while others place him in the beginning of the reign of [[Ahaz]], Judah's next king, or even the latter half of the reign of [[Hezekiah]], Ahaz's son;{{citation needed|date=August 2016}} all three accounts date the book to the 8th century&amp;nbsp;BC. The book would then have been written in [[Jerusalem]], where Nahum would have witnessed the invasion of [[Sennacherib]] and the destruction of his host ([[Books of Kings|2 Kings]] 19:35).

The scholarly consensus is that the &quot;book of vision&quot; was written at the time of the fall of [[Nineveh]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Kent H. Richards 2006&quot; /&gt; at the hands of the [[Medes]] and [[Babylon]]ians in 612 BC&lt;ref name=&quot;Coogan 2009&quot;&gt;Michael D. Coogan, ''A Brief Introduction to the Old Testament'', (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2009) 297–298&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Pinker|first=Aron|date=April–June 2005|title=Nahum – The Prophet and His Message|url=http://www.jbq.jewishbible.org/assets/Uploads/332/332_Nahump_4.pdf|journal=Jewish Bible Quarterly|volume=33|issue=2|pages=6|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;. This theory is demonstrated by the fact that the oracles must be dated after [[Sack of Thebes|the Assyrian destruction]] of [[Thebes, Egypt]] in 663&amp;nbsp;BC, as this event is mentioned in [[Nahum 3:8]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Kent H. Richards 2006&quot;&gt;Kent H. Richards, ''Nahum Introduction: The Harper Collins Study Bible'', (New York: Harper Collins, 2006) 1250&lt;/ref&gt;

===Author===
{{main|Nahum}}
Little is known about Nahum's personal history. His name means &quot;comforter&quot;, and he was from the town of ''Elkosh'' or ''Alqosh'' ([[Nahum 1:1]]), which scholars have attempted to identify with several cities, including the modern [[Alqosh|`Alqush]] of [[Assyria]] and [[Capernaum|Capharnaum]] of northern [[Galilee]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/10670a.htm|title=CATHOLIC ENCYCLOPEDIA: Nahum|publisher=newadvent.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was a very nationalistic Hebrew, and lived amongst the Elkoshites in peace. His writings were likely written in about 615 BC, before the downfall of Assyria.&lt;ref name=&quot;Heaton, E. W. p. 35&quot;&gt;Heaton, E. W., ''A Short Introduction to the Old Testament Prophets'', p. 35, Oneworld Publications, P.O. Box 830, 21 Broadway, Rockport, NA 01966, {{ISBN|1-85168-114-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;abp&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aboutbibleprophecy.com/p52.htm|title=Nahum|work=aboutbibleprophecy.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Historical context===
[[File:Nineveh map city walls &amp; gates.JPG|thumb|Simplified plan of ancient [[Nineveh]], showing city wall and location of gateways.]]
The subject of Nahum's prophecy is the approaching complete and final destruction of [[Nineveh]], the capital of the great and at that time flourishing [[Assyria|Assyrian empire]]. [[Ashurbanipal]] was at the height of his glory. Nineveh was a city of vast extent, and was then the center of the civilization and commerce of the world, according to Nahum a &quot;bloody city all full of lies and robbery&quot; ({{bibleverse|Nahum|3:1|KJV}}), a reference to the Neo-Assyrian Empire's military campaigns and demand of tribute and plunder from conquered cities.

[[Jonah]] had already uttered his message of warning, and Nahum was followed by [[Zephaniah]], who also predicted ([[Book of Zephaniah|Zephaniah]] {{bibleverse-nb|Zephaniah|2:4–15|NKJV}}) the destruction of the city.

Nineveh was destroyed apparently by fire around 625 BC, and the Assyrian empire came to an end, an event which changed the face of Asia.
Archaeological digs have uncovered the splendor of Nineveh in its zenith under [[Sennacherib]] (705–681 BC), [[Esarhaddon]] (681–669 BC), and [[Ashurbanipal]] (669–633 BC). Massive walls were eight miles in circumference.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://members.bib-arch.org/publication.asp?PubID=BSBA&amp;Volume=10&amp;Issue=2&amp;ArticleID=7|title=Destruction of Judean Fortress Portrayed in Dramatic Eighth-Century B.C. Pictures - The BAS Library|first=The Biblical Archaeology|last=Society|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; It had a water [[aqueduct (watercourse)|aqueduct]], palaces and a library with 20,000 clay tablets, including accounts of a creation in [[Enuma Elish]] and a flood in the [[Epic of Gilgamesh]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.saudiaramcoworld.com/issue/196202/nineveh.htm|title=Saudi Aramco World : Nineveh|publisher=saudiaramcoworld.com|access-date=2011-11-13|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110708132641/http://www.saudiaramcoworld.com/issue/196202/nineveh.htm#|archive-date=2011-07-08|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://darkwing.uoregon.edu/~dfalk/courses/bible/creation%20myths.htm|title=CREATION MYTHS IN THE ANCIENT NEAR EAST|publisher=uoregon.edu|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111127035404/http://darkwing.uoregon.edu/~dfalk/courses/bible/creation%20myths.htm|archivedate=2011-11-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Babylonian chronicle of the fall of Nineveh tells the story of the end of Nineveh. [[Nabopolassar|Nabopolassar of Babylon]] joined forces with Cyaxares, king of the Medes, and laid siege for three months.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.livius.org/ne-nn/nineveh/nineveh02.html|title=The fall of Nineveh Chronicle (ABC 3)|publisher=livius.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Assyria lasted a few more years after the loss of its fortress, but attempts by [[Ancient Egypt|Egyptian]] [[Pharaoh]] [[Neco II]] to rally the Assyrians failed due to opposition from king [[Josiah]] of [[kingdom of Judah|Judah]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theology.edu/lec21.htm|title=ANE History: The End of Judah|publisher=theology.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; and it seemed to be all over by 609 BC.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/hd/assy/hd_assy.htm|title=Assyria, 1365609 B.C.|publisher=metmuseum.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Overview ==
The Book of Nahum consists of two parts:&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark 1994&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last1=Clark | first1=David J. | last2=Hatton | first2=Howard A. | year=1994 | title=The Books of Nahum, Habakkuk, and Zephaniah | location=New York | publisher=United Bible Societies | isbn=0-8267-0130-2 | page=1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Chapters two and three describe the fall of Nineveh, which later took place in 612&amp;nbsp;BC. Nineveh is compared to [[Thebes (Egypt)|Thebes]], the Egyptian city that Assyria itself [[Sack of Thebes|had destroyed]] in 663&amp;nbsp;BC.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kent H. Richards 2006&quot;/&gt; Nahum describes the siege and frenzied activity of Nineveh's troops as they try in vain to halt the invaders. Poetically, he becomes a participant in the battle, and with subtle irony, barks battle commands to the defenders. Nahum uses numerous similes and [[metaphor]]s {{citation needed|date=September 2015}}. Nineveh is ironically compared with a lion, in reference to the lion as an Assyrian symbol of power; Nineveh is the lion of strength that has a den full of dead prey but will become weak like the lion hiding in its den. It comes to conclusion with a taunt song and funeral dirge of the impending destruction of Nineveh and the &quot;sleep&quot; or death of the Assyrian people and demise of the once great Assyrian conqueror-rulers .

== Themes ==

===The fall of Nineveh===
[[File:Naum e Nínive destruída (Biblioteca Nacional de Portugal ALC.455, fl.300).png|thumb|left|[[Nahum]] and the destruction of [[Nineveh]]; Illuminated Bible from the 1220s, [[Biblioteca Nacional de Portugal|National Library of Portugal]]]]
Nahum's prophecy carries a particular warning to the Ninevites of coming events, although he is partly in favor of the destruction.&lt;ref name=&quot;abp&quot; /&gt; One might even say that the book of Nahum is &quot;a celebration of the fall of Assyria.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coogan 2009&quot; /&gt; And this is not just a warning or speaking positively of the destruction of Nineveh, it is also a positive encouragement and &quot;message of comfort for Israel, Judah, and others who had experienced the &quot;endless cruelty&quot; ([[Nahum 3:19]]) of the Assyrians.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coogan 2009&quot; /&gt; The prophet [[Jonah]] shows us where God shows concern for the people of Nineveh, while Nahum's writing testifies to his belief in the righteousness/justice of God&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.earlyjewishwritings.com/nahum.html|title=Nahum|publisher=earlyjewishwritings.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; and how God dealt with those Assyrians in punishment according to &quot;their cruelty&quot; ([[Nahum 3:19]]). The Assyrians had been used as God's &quot;rod of […] anger, and the staff in their hand [as] indignation.&quot; (Isaiah 10:5)

===The nature of God===
From its opening, Nahum shows God to be slow to anger, but that God will by no means ignore the guilty; God will bring his vengeance and wrath to pass. God is presented as a God who will punish evil, but will protect those who trust in Him. The opening passage ({{bibleref2|Nahum|1:2–3|KJV}}) states: &quot;God is jealous, and the L&lt;small&gt;ORD&lt;/small&gt; revengeth; the L&lt;small&gt;ORD&lt;/small&gt; revengeth, and is furious; the L&lt;small&gt;ORD&lt;/small&gt; will take vengeance on his adversaries, and he reserveth wrath for his enemies. The L&lt;small&gt;ORD&lt;/small&gt; is slow to anger, and great in power, and will not at all acquit the wicked&quot;. God is strong and will use means, but a mighty God doesn't need anyone else to carry out vengeance and wrath for him.

{{bibleref2|Nahum|1:3|NIV}} (NIV) ''The L&lt;small&gt;ORD&lt;/small&gt; is slow to anger and Quick to love; the L&lt;small&gt;ORD&lt;/small&gt; will not leave the guilty unpunished.''

{{bibleref2|Nahum|1:7|NIV}} (NIV) ''The L&lt;small&gt;ORD&lt;/small&gt; is good, a refuge in times of trouble. He cares for those who trust in him''

== Importance ==
God's judgement on Nineveh is &quot;all because of the wanton lust of a harlot, alluring, the mistress of sorceries, who enslaved nations by her prostitution and peoples by her witchcraft&quot; ({{bibleref2|Nahum|3:4|NIV}} NIV). Infidelity, according to the prophets, related to spiritual unfaithfulness.&lt;ref&gt;Centre Column Reference Bible, (Nashville: Thomas Nelson Publishers, 1994) 1262&lt;/ref&gt; For example: &quot;the land is guilty of the vilest adultery in departing from the L&lt;small&gt;ORD&lt;/small&gt;&quot; ({{bibleref2|Hosea|1:2|NIV}} NIV). The apostle [[John the Apostle#Book of Revelation|John]] used a similar analogy in [[Revelation 17|Revelation chapter 17]].

The prophecy of Nahum was referenced in the deuterocanonical [[Book of Tobit]]. In Tobit 14:4 (NRSV) a dying Tobit says to his son Tobias and Tobias' sons:&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleref2|Tobit|14:4|NRSV}} NRSV&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
[My son] hurry off to Media, for I believe the word of God that Nahum spoke about Nineveh, that all these things will take place and overtake Assyria and Nineveh. Indeed, everything that was spoken by the prophets of Israel, whom God sent, will occur. &lt;/blockquote&gt;
However, some versions, such as the King James Version, refer to the prophet [[Jonah]] instead.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/Tobit-14-4/ Tobit 14:4 KJV]. Quote: ''&quot;Go into Media my son, for I surely believe those things which '''Jonas''' the prophet spake of Nineve, that it shall be overthrown; and that for a time peace shall rather be in Media; and that our brethren shall lie scattered in the earth from that good land: and Jerusalem shall be desolate, and the house of God in it shall be burned, and shall be desolate for a time;&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

== Discourse ==
The book was introduced in [[John Calvin|Calvin]]'s Commentary &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Commentaries on Twelve Minor Prophets | url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/calvin/calcom28.titlepage.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; as a complete and finished poem:
{{Quote|No one of the minor Prophets seems to equal the sublimity, the vehemence and the boldness of Nahum: besides, his Prophecy is a complete and finished poem; his exordium is magnificent, and indeed majestic; the preparation for the destruction of Nineveh, and the description of its ruin, and its greatness, are expressed in most vivid colors, and possess admirable perspicuity and fulness.|Rev. John Owen, translator|Calvin's Commentary on Jonah, Micah, Nahum}}

Nahum, taking words from Moses himself, have shown in a general way what sort of &quot;Being God is&quot;. The Reformation theologian Calvin argued, Nahum painted God by which His nature must be seen, and &quot;it is from that most memorable vision, when God appeared to Moses after the breaking of the tables.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.is/20121130075010/http://onetenthblog.wordpress.com/readings/780-2/ Source deleted by authors] as at 24 August 2016&lt;/ref&gt;

The book could be seen as an allusion to the history as described by Moses; for the minor Prophets, in promising God's assistance to his people, must often remind how God in a miraculous manner brought up the Jews from Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;Calvin's Commentary on Jonah, Micah, Nahum; Rev. John Owen, translator&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Wikisource|Nahum (Bible)|Nahum}}
{{Commons category|Book of Nahum}}
* [http://www.babylonjews.com/prophet-pictures/the-prophet-nahum/ Unique Pictures Of Nahum Tomb By Kobi Arami]
* [[Judaism|Jewish]] translations:
** [http://www.chabad.org/library/archive/LibraryArchive2.asp?AID=15764 Nachum – Nahum (Judaica Press)] translation [with [[Rashi]]'s commentary] at Chabad.org
* [[Christianity|Christian]] translations:
** [http://www.gospelhall.org/bible/bible.php?passage=Nahum+1 ''Online Bible'' at GospelHall.org] (ESV, KJV, Darby, American Standard Version, Bible in Basic English)
** [http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=nahum;&amp;version=31; BibleGateway]
** [https://www.kingjamesbibleonline.org/Nahum-Chapter-1/ Nahum – King James Version]
* {{librivox book | title=Nahum}} Various versions

;Commentary
*{{Cite EB1911|wstitle=Nahum}} This article also contains a section on the Book of Nahum.

{{eastons|Nahum}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou | [[Minor prophet]]s|||}}
{{s-bef | before= [[Book of Micah|Micah]] | rows = 2 }}
{{s-ttl | title  = [[Tanakh|Hebrew Bible]] }}
{{s-aft | after= [[Book of Habakkuk|Habakkuk]] | rows = 2 }}
{{s-ttl | title = [[Christianity|Christian]]&lt;br&gt;[[Old Testament]] }}
{{s-end}}
{{Book of Nahum}}
{{Books of the Bible}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Nahum}}
[[Category:7th-century BC books]]
[[Category:Twelve Minor Prophets]]
[[Category:Book of Nahum| ]]</text>
      <sha1>580hibi2wxfco24wibhfio5nwvt3xhg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
