  <page>
    <title>Beauty</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4431</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942982791</id>
      <parentid>942955890</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T02:56:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ewulp</username>
        <id>998182</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rv, no improvement</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi-protected|small=yes}}

{{Use mdy dates|date=June 2012}}
[[File:Rozeta Paryż notre-dame chalger.jpg|thumb|260px|[[Rayonnant]] [[rose window]] in [[Notre Dame de Paris]]. In [[Gothic architecture]], [[light]] was considered the most beautiful revelation of [[God]], which was heralded in its design.]]

'''Beauty'''  is the ascription of a property or characteristic to an [[animal]], [[idea]], [[Object (philosophy)|object]], person or [[Location (geography)|place]] that provides a [[perception|perceptual]] experience of [[pleasure]] or [[Contentment|satisfaction]]. Beauty is studied as part of [[aesthetics]], [[culture]], [[social psychology]] and [[sociology]]. An &quot;ideal beauty&quot; is an entity which is admired, or possesses features widely attributed to beauty in a particular culture, for perfection. [[Unattractiveness|Ugliness]] is the opposite of beauty.

The experience of &quot;beauty&quot; often involves an interpretation of some entity as being in balance and [[harmony]] with [[nature]], which may lead to feelings of [[sexual attraction|attraction]] and [[emotional well-being]]. Because this can be a [[Subjectivity|subjective]] experience, it is often said that &quot;beauty is in the eye of the beholder.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;phrase&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.phrases.org.uk/meanings/59100.html|title=Beauty is in the eye of the beholder|accessdate=December 4, 2007|publisher=The Phrase Finder|year=2007|author=Gary Martin| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20071130023507/http://www.phrases.org.uk/meanings/59100.html| archivedate= November 30, 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Often, given the observation that empirical observations of things that are considered beautiful often align among groups in consensus, beauty has been stated to have levels of [[objectivity (philosophy)|objectivity]] and partial subjectivity which are not fully subjective in their aesthetic judgement.

==Ancient Greek==
The classical Greek noun that best translates to the English-language words &quot;beauty&quot; or &quot;beautiful&quot; was [[wikt:κάλλος|κάλλος]], ''kallos'', and the adjective was καλός, ''kalos''. However, ''kalos'' may and is also translated as ″good″ or ″of fine quality″ and thus has a broader meaning than mere physical or material beauty. Similarly, ''kallos'' was used differently from the English word beauty in that it first and foremost applied to humans and bears an erotic connotation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Konstan|first1=David|title=Beauty - The Fortunes of an Ancient Greek Idea|date=2014|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=New York|isbn=978-0-19-992726-5|pages=30–35}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Koine Greek]] word for beautiful was ὡραῖος, ''hōraios'',&lt;ref&gt;Matthew 23:27, Acts 3:10, Flavius Josephus, 12.65&lt;/ref&gt; an adjective etymologically coming from the word ὥρα, ''hōra'', meaning &quot;hour&quot;. In Koine Greek, beauty was thus associated with &quot;being of one's hour&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Euripides, Alcestis 515&quot;&gt;Euripides, ''Alcestis'' 515.&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, a ripe fruit (of its time) was considered beautiful, whereas a young woman trying to appear older or an older woman trying to appear younger would not be considered beautiful. In Attic Greek, ''hōraios'' had many meanings, including &quot;youthful&quot; and &quot;ripe old age&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Euripides, Alcestis 515&quot;/&gt;

The [[Beauty (ancient thought)|earliest Western theory of beauty]] can be found in the works of early Greek philosophers from the [[pre-Socratic]] period, such as [[Pythagoras]]. The Pythagorean school saw a strong connection between [[mathematics]] and beauty. In particular, they noted that objects proportioned according to the [[golden ratio]] seemed more attractive.&lt;ref&gt;Seife, Charles (2000). ''[[Zero: The Biography of a Dangerous Idea]]''. Penguin. {{ISBN|0-14-029647-6}}. p. 32&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ancient Greek architecture]] is based on this view of symmetry and [[ratio|proportion]].

Plato considered beauty to be the Idea (Form) above all other Ideas.&lt;ref&gt;Phaedrus&lt;/ref&gt; Aristotle saw a relationship between the beautiful (''to kalon'') and virtue, arguing that &quot;Virtue aims at the beautiful.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Nicomachean Ethics&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Classical philosophy]] and sculptures of men and women produced according to the [[Ancient Greek philosophy|Greek philosophers]]' tenets of ideal human beauty were rediscovered in [[Renaissance]] Europe, leading to a re-adoption of what became known as a &quot;classical ideal&quot;. In terms of female human beauty, a woman whose [[human physical appearance|appearance]] conforms to these tenets is still called a &quot;classical beauty&quot; or said to possess a &quot;classical beauty&quot;, whilst the foundations laid by Greek and Roman artists have also supplied the standard for male beauty and female beauty in western civilization as seen, for example, in  the ''[[Winged Victory of Samothrace]]''. During the Gothic era, the classical aesthetical canon of beauty was rejected as sinful. Later, [[Renaissance]] and [[Humanism|Humanist]] thinkers rejected this view, and considered beauty to be the product of rational order and harmonious proportions. Renaissance artists and architects (such as [[Giorgio Vasari]] in his &quot;Lives of Artists&quot;) criticised the Gothic period as irrational and barbarian. This point of view of [[Gothic art]] lasted until Romanticism, in the 19th century.

==Middle Ages==
In the [[Middle Ages]], [[Catholic philosopher]]s like [[Thomas Aquinas]] included beauty among the [[Transcendentals|transcendental]] attributes of [[being]].  In his [[Summa Theologica]], Aquinas described the three conditions of beauty as: integritas (Wholeness), consonantia (harmony), claritas (radiance of form)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/summa/1039.htm#article8 Summa Theologica, Part 1, Question 39, Article 8]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Gothic Architecture of the [[High Middle Ages|High]] and [[Late Middle Ages|Late]] [[Middle Ages]], light was considered the most beautiful revelation of [[God]], which was heralded in design.  Examples are the [[Stained glass#Medieval glass in Europe|stained glass]] of Gothic [[Cathedral]]s including [[Notre-Dame de Paris]] and [[Chartes Cathedral]].

==The Age of Reason==
[[File:Sandro Botticelli - La nascita di Venere - Google Art Project - edited.jpg|thumb|upright=1.2|left|''[[The Birth of Venus (Botticelli)|The Birth of Venus]]'', by [[Sandro Botticelli]]. The goddess Venus is the classical personification of beauty.]]

The [[Age of Enlightenment|Age of Reason]] saw a rise in an interest in beauty as a philosophical subject. For example, Scottish philosopher [[Francis Hutcheson (philosopher)|Francis Hutcheson]] argued that beauty is &quot;unity in variety and variety in unity&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;An Inquiry Into the Original of Our Ideas of Beauty and Virtue; In Two Treatises&lt;/ref&gt; The Romantic poets, too, became highly concerned with the [[nature (philosophy)|nature]] of beauty, with [[John Keats]] arguing in ''Ode on a Grecian Urn'' that:

:  Beauty is truth, truth beauty, —that is all
:  Ye know on earth, and all ye need to know.

==The Romantic period==
In the Romantic period, [[Edmund Burke]] postulated a difference between beauty in its classical meaning and the [[Sublime (philosophy)|sublime]]. The concept of the sublime, as explicated by Burke and [[Immanuel Kant|Kant]], suggested viewing Gothic art and architecture, though not in accordance with the classical standard of beauty, as sublime.{{citation needed|date=December 2012}}

==The 20th century and after==
The 20th century saw an increasing rejection of beauty by artists and philosophers alike, culminating in [[postmodernism]]'s anti-aesthetics.&lt;ref&gt;The Anti-Aesthetic: Essays on Postmodern Culture by Hal Foster&lt;/ref&gt; This is despite beauty being a central concern of one of postmodernism's main influences, [[Friedrich Nietzsche]], who argued that the Will to Power was the Will to Beauty.&lt;ref&gt;The Will to Power&lt;/ref&gt;

In the aftermath of postmodernism's rejection of beauty, thinkers have returned to beauty as an important value. American analytic philosopher [[Guy Sircello]] proposed his New Theory of Beauty as an effort to reaffirm the status of beauty as an important philosophical concept.&lt;ref&gt;A New Theory of Beauty. Princeton Essays on the Arts, 1. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1975.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Love and Beauty. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1989.&lt;/ref&gt; Elaine Scarry also argues that beauty is related to justice.&lt;ref&gt;On Beauty and Being Just&lt;/ref&gt;

Beauty is also studied by psychologists and neuroscientists in the field of [[experimental aesthetics]] and [[neuroesthetics]] respectively. Psychological theories see beauty as a form of [[pleasure]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Reber|first=Rolf|last2=Schwarz|first2=Norbert|last3=Winkielman|first3=Piotr|date=2004|title=Processing fluency and aesthetic pleasure: is beauty in the perceiver's processing experience?|journal=Personality and Social Psychology Review|volume=8|issue=4|pages=364–382|doi=10.1207/s15327957pspr0804_3|issn=1088-8683|pmid=15582859|hdl=1956/594}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Armstrong|first=Thomas|last2=Detweiler-Bedell|first2=Brian|date=December 2008|title=Beauty as an emotion: The exhilarating prospect of mastering a challenging world.|url=http://psycnet.apa.org/journals/gpr/12/4/305/|journal=Review of General Psychology|language=English|volume=12|issue=4|pages=305–329|doi=10.1037/a0012558|issn=1939-1552|citeseerx=10.1.1.406.1825}}&lt;/ref&gt; Correlational findings support the view that more beautiful objects are also more pleasing.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Vartanian|first=Oshin|last2=Navarrete|first2=Gorka|last3=Chatterjee|first3=Anjan|last4=Fich|first4=Lars Brorson|last5=Leder|first5=Helmut|last6=Modroño|first6=Cristián|last7=Nadal|first7=Marcos|last8=Rostrup|first8=Nicolai|last9=Skov|first9=Martin|date=2013-06-18|title=Impact of contour on aesthetic judgments and approach-avoidance decisions in architecture|journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences|language=en|volume=110|issue=Supplement 2|pages=10446–10453|doi=10.1073/pnas.1301227110|issn=0027-8424|pmc=3690611|pmid=23754408|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Marin|first=Manuela M.|last2=Lampatz|first2=Allegra|last3=Wandl|first3=Michaela|last4=Leder|first4=Helmut|date=2016-11-04|title=Berlyne Revisited: Evidence for the Multifaceted Nature of Hedonic Tone in the Appreciation of Paintings and Music|journal=Frontiers in Human Neuroscience|volume=10|pages=536|doi=10.3389/fnhum.2016.00536|issn=1662-5161|pmc=5095118|pmid=27867350}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Brielmann|first=Aenne A.|last2=Pelli|first2=Denis G.|date=2017-05-22|title=Beauty Requires Thought|url=http://www.cell.com/current-biology/abstract/S0960-9822(17)30427-X|journal=Current Biology|language=English|volume=27|issue=10|pages=1506–1513.e3|doi=10.1016/j.cub.2017.04.018|issn=0960-9822|pmid=28502660|pmc=6778408}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some studies suggest that higher experienced beauty is associated with activity in the medial [[orbitofrontal cortex]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Kawabata|first=Hideaki|last2=Zeki|first2=Semir|date=April 2004|title=Neural correlates of beauty|journal=Journal of Neurophysiology|volume=91|issue=4|pages=1699–1705|doi=10.1152/jn.00696.2003|issn=0022-3077|pmid=15010496}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Ishizu|first=Tomohiro|last2=Zeki|first2=Semir|date=2011-07-06|title=Toward A Brain-Based Theory of Beauty|journal=PLOS ONE|volume=6|issue=7|pages=e21852|doi=10.1371/journal.pone.0021852|issn=1932-6203|pmc=3130765|pmid=21755004|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; This approach of localizing the processing of beauty in one brain region has received criticism within the field.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Conway|first=Bevil R.|last2=Rehding|first2=Alexander|date=2013-03-19|title=Neuroaesthetics and the Trouble with Beauty|journal=PLOS Biology|volume=11|issue=3|pages=e1001504|doi=10.1371/journal.pbio.1001504|issn=1545-7885|pmc=3601993|pmid=23526878|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Human beauty==
{{Main|Physical attractiveness}}
[[File:Herkulaneischer Meister 002.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Fresco of a Roman woman from [[Pompeii]], c. 50 AD]]
The characterization of a person as “beautiful”, whether on an individual basis or by community consensus, is often based on some combination of ''inner beauty'', which includes psychological factors such as [[Personality type|personality]], [[intelligence]], [[wiktionary:grace|grace]], [[politeness]], [[charisma]], [[integrity]], [[wikt:congruence|congruence]] and [[elegance]], and ''outer beauty'' (i.e. [[physical attractiveness]]) which includes physical attributes which are valued on an aesthetic basis.

Standards of beauty have changed over time, based on changing cultural values. Historically, paintings show a wide range of different standards for beauty. However, humans who are relatively young, with smooth skin, well-proportioned bodies, and regular features, have traditionally been considered the most beautiful throughout history.

A strong indicator of physical beauty is &quot;[[averageness]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Langlois &amp; Roggman, 1990&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |doi = 10.1111/j.1467-9280.1990.tb00079.x|title = Attractive Faces Are Only Average|journal = Psychological Science|volume = 1|issue = 2|pages = 115–121|year = 1990|last1 = Langlois|first1 = Judith H.|last2 = Roggman|first2 = Lori A.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Straus, 1979&quot;&gt;Strauss, M.S. (1979). &quot;Abstraction of prototypical information by adults and 10-month-old infants.&quot; ''J. Exp. Psychol.: Human Learn. Mem.'' '''5''', 618–632.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rhodes &amp; Tremewan, 1997&quot;&gt;Rhodes, G., Tremewan, T. (1997) Averageness, exaggeration, and facial attractiveness. ''Psychol. Sci. '' '''7''', 105–110.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Valentine, 2004&quot;&gt;Valentine, T., Darling, S., Donnelly, M. (2004). Why are average faces attractive? The effect of view and averageness on the attractiveness of the attractiveness of female faces. ''Psychon. Bull. Rev.'' '''11''', 482–487&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://homepage.psy.utexas.edu/HomePage/Group/LangloisLAB/averagenessbeauty.html|title=Langlois Social Development Lab – The University of Texas at Austin|website=homepage.psy.utexas.edu|accessdate=May 1, 2018|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150204053616/http://homepage.psy.utexas.edu/homepage/group/langloislab/averagenessbeauty.html|archivedate=February 4, 2015|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; When images of human faces are averaged together to form a composite image, they become progressively closer to the &quot;ideal&quot; image and are perceived as more attractive. This was first noticed in 1883, when [[Francis Galton]] overlaid photographic composite images of the faces of vegetarians and criminals to see if there was a typical facial appearance for each. When doing this, he noticed that the composite images were more attractive compared to any of the individual images.&lt;ref name=&quot;Galton, 1878&quot;&gt;Galton, F. (1878). Composite portraits, made by combining those of many different persons in a single resultant figure. '' J. Anthropol. Inst. '' '''8''', 132–144.&lt;/ref&gt; Researchers have replicated the result under more controlled conditions and found that the computer-generated, mathematical average of a series of faces is rated more favorably than individual faces.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | doi = 10.1111/j.1467-9280.1994.tb00503.x | authors = Langlois, J. H., Roggman, L. A., &amp; Musselman, L. | year = 1994 | title = What is average and what is not average about attractive faces? | url = | journal = Psychological Science | volume = 5 | issue = 4 | pages = 214–220 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It is argued that it is evolutionarily advantageous that sexual creatures are attracted to mates who possess predominantly common or average features, because it suggests the [[Koinophilia|absence of genetic or acquired defects]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Langlois &amp; Roggman, 1990&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Koeslag, 1990&quot;&gt;Koeslag, J.H. (1990). &quot;Koinophilia groups sexual creatures into species, promotes stasis, and stabilizes social behaviour.&quot; ''J. theor. Biol.'' '''144''', 15–35&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=symons&gt;Symons, D. (1979) ''The Evolution of Human Sexuality''. Oxford: Oxford University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/science/science-news/3341719/Why-beauty-is-an-advert-for-good-genes.html |last=Highfield |first=Roger |author-link=Roger Highfield |title=Why beauty is an advert for good genes |newspaper=[[The Daily Telegraph]] |access-date=13 February 2012 |date=7 May 2008 |publisher=[[Telegraph Media Group Limited]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is also evidence that a preference for beautiful faces emerges early in infancy, and is probably innate,&lt;ref name=&quot;Slater, 1998&quot;&gt;Slater, A.M., Von Der Schulenburg, C., Brown, E., et al. (1998). &quot;Newborn infants prefer attractive faces.&quot; ''Infant Behav. Dev.'' ''' 21''', 345–354.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kramer, 1995&quot;&gt;Kramer, S., Zebrowitz, L.A., San Giovanni, J.P., Sherak, B. (1995). &quot;Infants' preferences for attractiveness and babyfaceness.&quot; In Bardy, B.G., Bootsma, R.J., Guiard, Y. (Eds.) ''Studies in perception and action III''. pp. 389–392. Hillsdale, N.J.: Erlbaum Associates.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Straus, 1979&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rubenstein, 1999&quot;&gt;Rubenstein, A.J, Kalakanis, L., Langlois, J.H. (1999). Infant preferences for attractive faces: a cognitive explanation. ''Dev. Psychol.'' '''35''', 848–855.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Langlois, 1991&quot;&gt;Langlois, J.H., Ritter, J.M., Roggman, L.A., Vaughn, L.S. (1991). &quot;Facial diversity and infant preferences for attractive faces.&quot; ''Dev. Psychol.'' '''27''', 79–84.&lt;/ref&gt;
and that the rules by which attractiveness is established are similar across different genders and cultures.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apicella, 2007&quot;&gt;Apicella, C.L., Little, A.C., Marlowe, F.W. (2007). &quot;Facial averageness and attractiveness in an isolated population of hunter-gatherers.&quot; ''Perception'' '''36''', 1813–1820.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rhodes, G. 2006 199–226&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|authors=Rhodes, G.|year=2006|title=The evolutionary psychology of facial beauty|url=|journal=Annual Review of Psychology|volume=57|pages=199–226|doi=10.1146/annurev.psych.57.102904.190208|pmid=16318594}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Indian girl in traditional attire.jpg|thumb|An Indian girl in her traditional attire]]

A feature of beautiful women that has been explored by researchers is a [[waist–hip ratio]] of approximately 0.70. Physiologists have shown that women with [[Female body shape|hourglass figures]] are more fertile than other women due to higher levels of certain female hormones, a fact that may subconsciously condition males choosing mates.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/3682657.stm|title=Hourglass figure fertility link|last=|first=|date=4 May 2004|work=BBC News|access-date=1 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.newscientist.com/article/dn4953-barbie-shaped-women-more-fertile/|title=Barbie-shaped women more fertile|last=Bhattacharya|first=Shaoni|date=5 May 2004|website=New Scientist|access-date=1 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, other commentators have suggested that this preference may not be universal. For instance,  in some non-Western cultures in which women have to do work such as finding food, men tend to have preferences for higher waist-hip ratios.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.livescience.com/3098-female-figure-hourglass.html|title=Best Female Figure Not an Hourglass|date=December 3, 2008|website=Live Science|access-date=1 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.vox.com/2014/6/22/5832826/did-evolution-really-make-men-prefer-women-with-hourglass-figures|title=Did evolution really make men prefer women with hourglass figures?|last=Locke|first=Susannah|date=June 22, 2014|work=Vox|access-date=1 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.sharonlbegley.com/hourglass-figures-we-take-it-all-back|title=Hourglass Figures: We Take It All Back|last=Begley|first=Sharon|website=Sharon Begley|access-date=1 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Beauty standards are rooted in cultural norms crafted by societies and media over centuries. Globally, it is argued that the predominance of white women featured in movies and advertising leads to a [[Eurocentrism|Eurocentric]] concept of beauty, breeding cultures that assign inferiority to women of color.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Harper|first=Kathryn|last2=Choma|first2=Becky L.|date=2018-10-05|title=Internalised White Ideal, Skin Tone Surveillance, and Hair Surveillance Predict Skin and Hair Dissatisfaction and Skin Bleaching among African American and Indian Women|journal=Sex Roles|volume=80|issue=11–12|pages=735–744|doi=10.1007/s11199-018-0966-9|issn=0360-0025}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, societies and cultures across the globe struggle to diminish the longstanding [[internalized racism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Weedon|first=Chris|date=December 6, 2007|title=Key Issues in Postcolonial Feminism: A Western Perspective|url=|journal=Gender Forum Electronic Journal|volume=|pages=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[black is beautiful]] &lt;nowiki/&gt;cultural movement sought to dispel this notion in the 1960s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=DoCarmo|date=December 20, 2007|title=Dr. DoCarmo's Notes on the Black Cultural Movement|url=|journal=|publisher=Bucks County Community College|volume=|pages=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Exposure to the thin ideal in mass media, such as fashion magazines, directly correlates with body dissatisfaction, low self-esteem, and the development of eating disorders among female viewers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nationaleatingdisorders.org/media-eating-disorders|title=Media &amp; Eating Disorders|date=2017-10-05|work=National Eating Disorders Association|access-date=2018-11-27|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/769290.stm|title=Model's link to teenage anorexia|date=May 30, 2000|website=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt; Further, the widening gap between individual body sizes and societal ideals continues to breed anxiety among young girls as they grow, highlighting the dangerous nature of beauty standards in society.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://eating-disorders.org.uk/information/the-media-eating-disorders/|title=National Centre for Eating Disorders - The Media &amp; Eating Disorders|last=Jade|first=Deanne|date=|work=National Centre for Eating Disorders|access-date=2018-11-27|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The concept of beauty in men is known as '[[bishōnen]]' in Japan. Bishōnen refers to males with distinctly [[Femininity|feminine]] features, physical characteristics establishing the standard of beauty in Japan and typically exhibited in their [[popular culture|pop culture]] [[Japanese idol|idols]]. A multibillion-dollar industry of [[Japanese Aesthetic Salons]] exists for this reason. However, different nations have varying male beauty ideals; Eurocentric standards for men include tallness, leanness, and muscularity; thus, these features are idolized through American media, such as in [[Cinema of the United States|Hollywood]] films and magazine covers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.doctornerdlove.com/new-impossible-standards-male-beauty/|title=The New (And Impossible) Standards of Male Beauty|last=|first=|date=2015-01-26|work=Paging Dr. NerdLove|access-date=2018-11-27|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Eurocentrism and beauty ===
The prevailing eurocentric concept of beauty has varying effects on different cultures. Primarily, adherence to this standard among African American women has bred a lack of positive reification of African beauty, and philosopher [[Cornel West]] elaborates that, &quot;much of black self-hatred and self-contempt has to do with the refusal of many black Americans to love their own black bodies-especially their black noses, hips, lips, and hair.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Race Matters|last=West|first=Cornel|publisher=Vintage|year=1994|isbn=|location=|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; These insecurities can be traced back to global idealization of women with light skin, green or blue eyes, and long straight or wavy hair in magazines and media that starkly contrast with the natural features of African women.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;https://search.proquest.com/docview/233235409/&lt;/ref&gt;

In East Asian cultures, familial pressures and cultural norms shape beauty ideals; professor and scholar Stephanie Wong's experimental study concluded that expecting that men in Asian culture didn't like women who look “fragile” impacted the lifestyle, eating, and appearance choices made by Asian American women.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Wong|first=Stephanie N.|last2=Keum|first2=Brian TaeHyuk|last3=Caffarel|first3=Daniel|last4=Srinivasan|first4=Ranjana|last5=Morshedian|first5=Negar|last6=Capodilupo|first6=Christina M.|last7=Brewster|first7=Melanie E.|date=December 2017|title=Exploring the conceptualization of body image for Asian American women.|journal=Asian American Journal of Psychology|language=en|volume=8|issue=4|pages=296–307|doi=10.1037/aap0000077|issn=1948-1993}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://thesocietypages.org/papers/homoegenization-of-asian-beauty/|title=The Homogenization of Asian Beauty - The Society Pages|last=Le|first=C.N|date=June 4, 2014|website=thesocietypages.org|language=en|access-date=2018-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to the male gaze, media portrayals of Asian women as petite and the portrayal of beautiful women in American media as fair complexioned and slim-figured induce anxiety and depressive symptoms among Asian American women who don't fit either of these beauty ideals.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt; Further, the high status associated with fairer skin can be attributed to Asian societal history; upper-class people hired workers to perform outdoor, manual labor, cultivating a visual divide over time between lighter complexioned, wealthier families and sun tanned, darker laborers.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt; This along with the Eurocentric beauty ideals embedded in Asian culture has made skin lightening creams, [[rhinoplasty]], and [[blepharoplasty]] (an eyelid surgery meant to give Asians a more European, &quot;double-eyelid&quot; appearance) commonplace among Asian women, illuminating the insecurity that results from cultural beauty standards.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;

===Western ideals in beauty and body type===
Much criticism has been directed at models of beauty which depend solely upon Western ideals of beauty as seen for example in the [[Barbie]] model franchise. Criticisms of Barbie are often centered around concerns that children consider Barbie a role model of beauty and will attempt to emulate her. One of the most common criticisms of Barbie is that she promotes an unrealistic idea of body image for a young woman, leading to a risk that girls who attempt to emulate her will become [[anorexia nervosa|anorexic]].&lt;ref&gt;Helga Dittmar, Emma Halliwell, and Suzanne Ive, &quot;Does Barbie make girls want to be thin? The effect of experimental exposure to images of dolls on the body image of 5-to 8-year-old girls.&quot; ''Developmental psychology'' 42#2 (2006): 283.&lt;/ref&gt;

These criticisms have led to a constructive dialogue to enhance the presence of non-exclusive models of Western ideals in body type and beauty. Complaints also point to a lack of diversity in such franchises as the [[Barbie]] model of beauty in Western culture.&lt;ref&gt;Marco Tosa, ''Barbie: Four decades of fashion, fantasy, and fun'' (1998).&lt;/ref&gt; Mattel responded to these criticisms. Starting in 1980, it produced Hispanic dolls, and later came models from across the globe. For example, in 2007, it introduced &quot;Cinco de Mayo Barbie&quot; wearing a ruffled red, white, and green dress (echoing the Mexican flag). ''Hispanic'' magazine reports that:
{{quote|[O]ne of the most dramatic developments in Barbie's history came when she embraced multi-culturalism and was released in a wide variety of native costumes, hair colors and skin tones to more closely resemble the girls who idolized her. Among these were Cinco De Mayo Barbie, Spanish Barbie, Peruvian Barbie, Mexican Barbie and Puerto Rican Barbie. She also has had close Hispanic friends, such as Teresa.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;A Barbie for Everyone&quot; ''Hispanic'' (February–March 2009), Vol. 22, Issue 1&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Effects on society==
Researchers have found that good-looking students get higher grades from their teachers than students with an ordinary appearance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Sharon Begley|url=http://www.newsweek.com/id/206597 |title=The Link Between Beauty and Grades |work=Newsweek |date=14 July 2009 |accessdate=2010-05-31| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20100420004627/http://www.newsweek.com/id/206597| archivedate=April 20, 2010| url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some studies using mock criminal trials have shown that physically attractive &quot;defendants&quot; are less likely to be convicted—and if convicted are likely to receive lighter sentences—than less attractive ones (although the opposite effect was observed when the alleged crime was swindling, perhaps because jurors perceived the defendant's attractiveness as facilitating the crime).&lt;ref&gt;Amina A Memon, Aldert Vrij, Ray Bull (2003). ''Psychology and Law: Truthfulness, Accuracy and Credibility''. John Wiley &amp; Sons. pp. 46–47. {{ISBN|047086835X}}&lt;/ref&gt; Studies among teens and young adults, such as those of psychiatrist and self-help author [[Eva Ritvo]] show that skin conditions have a profound effect on social behavior and opportunity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://multivu.prnewswire.com/mnr/galderma/38432 |title=Image survey reveals &quot;perception is reality&quot; when it comes to teenagers |publisher=multivu.prnewswire.com |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://archive.is/20120710073856/http://multivu.prnewswire.com/mnr/galderma/38432 |archivedate=July 10, 2012 |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

How much money a person earns may also be influenced by physical beauty. One study found that people low in physical attractiveness earn 5 to 10 percent less than ordinary-looking people, who in turn earn 3 to 8 percent less than those who are considered good-looking.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Lorenz |first=K. |year=2005 |url=http://www.cnn.com/2005/US/Careers/07/08/looks/ |title=Do pretty people earn more? |work=[[CNN News]] |publisher=[[Time Warner]] |agency=[[Cable News Network]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the market for loans, the least attractive people are less likely to get approvals, although they are less likely to default. In the marriage market, women's looks are at a premium, but men's looks do not matter much.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author1=Daniel Hamermesh |author2=Stephen J. Dubner |url=http://freakonomics.com/2014/01/30/reasons-to-not-be-ugly-full-transcript/ |title=Reasons to not be ugly: full transcript |work=Freakonomics |date=30 January 2014 |accessdate=2014-03-04 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140301230021/http://freakonomics.com/2014/01/30/reasons-to-not-be-ugly-full-transcript/ |archivedate=March 1, 2014 |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Conversely, being very unattractive increases the individual's propensity for criminal activity for a number of crimes ranging from burglary to theft to selling illicit drugs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author1=Erdal Tekin |author2=Stephen J. Dubner |url=http://freakonomics.com/2014/01/30/reasons-to-not-be-ugly-full-transcript/ |title=Reasons to not be ugly: full transcript |work=Freakonomics |date=30 January 2014 |accessdate=2014-03-04 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140301230021/http://freakonomics.com/2014/01/30/reasons-to-not-be-ugly-full-transcript/ |archivedate=March 1, 2014 |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Discrimination against others based on their appearance is known as [[lookism]].&lt;ref&gt;Gough, L. (2011). C. Northcote Parkinson's Parkinson's law. Oxford, U.K: Infinite Ideas Ltd. p. 36. {{ISBN|1283147378}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Writers' definitions ==
[[Augustine of Hippo|St. Augustine]] said of beauty &quot;Beauty is indeed a good gift of God; but that the good may not think it a great good, God dispenses it even to the wicked.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf102.iv.XV.22.html|title=NPNF1-02. St. Augustine's City of God and Christian Doctrine - Christian Classics Ethereal Library|website=www.ccel.org|accessdate=May 1, 2018|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170701195246/http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf102.iv.XV.22.html|archivedate=July 1, 2017|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Philosopher and novelist [[Umberto Eco]] wrote ''[[On Beauty: A History of a Western Idea]]'' (2004)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=On Beauty: A historyof a western idea|last=Eco|first=Umberto|publisher=Secker &amp; Warburg|year=2004|isbn=978-0436205170|location=London|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[On Ugliness]]'' (2007).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=On Ugliness|last=Eco|first=Umberto|publisher=Harvill Secker|year=2007|isbn=9781846551222|location=London|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; A character in his novel ''[[The Name of the Rose]]'' declares: &quot;three things concur in creating beauty: first of all integrity or perfection, and for this reason we consider ugly all incomplete things; then proper proportion or consonance; and finally clarity and light&quot;, before going on to say &quot;the sight of the beautiful implies peace&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Name of the Rose|last=Eco|first=Umberto|publisher=Vintage|year=1980|isbn=9780099466031|location=London|pages=65}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Adornment]]
* [[Beauty pageant]]
* [[Body modification]]
* [[Glamour (presentation)]]
* [[Processing fluency theory of aesthetic pleasure]]
* [[Unattractiveness]]

==References==
{{Reflist|35em}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Beauty}}
{{Wikiquote|Beauty}}
{{Wiktionary|beauty|pretty}}
* {{cite SEP |url-id=beauty |title=Beauty |last=Sartwell |first=Crispin}}
* {{InPho|idea|1998}}
* [http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/history/inourtime/inourtime_20050519.shtml BBC Radio 4's In Our Time programme on Beauty] (requires [[RealAudio]])
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20050305091132/http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/cgi-local/DHI/dhi.cgi?id=dv1-28 ''Dictionary of the History of Ideas'':] Theories of Beauty to the Mid-Nineteenth Century
* [http://www.uni-regensburg.de/Fakultaeten/phil_Fak_II/Psychologie/Psy_II/beautycheck/english/prototypen/prototypen.htm beautycheck.de/english] Regensburg University – Characteristics of beautiful faces
* [http://www.terraingallery.org/IsBeauty.html Eli Siegel's &quot;Is Beauty the Making One of Opposites?&quot;]
* [http://libmma.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/ref/collection/p15324coll10/id/53033 ''Art and love in Renaissance Italy ''], Issued in connection with an exhibition held Nov. 11, 2008-Feb. 16, 2009, Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York (see Belle: Picturing Beautiful Women; pages 246-254).

{{aesthetics}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Beauty| ]]
[[Category:Physical attractiveness]]
[[Category:Aesthetic beauty]]
[[Category:Concepts in aesthetics]]
[[Category:Fashion]]</text>
      <sha1>du9jbxco6j8vnngdraushi0ds62rsqu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
