  <page>
    <title>Buddy Holly</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4408</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942536825</id>
      <parentid>942029466</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-25T08:13:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>85.145.164.173</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Influence */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{For|the Weezer song|Buddy Holly (song)}}
{{redirect|Buddy Holly and the Crickets|the band|The Crickets}}
{{redirect|Charles Holly|the Colorado judge|Charles Frederick Holly}}
{{short description|20th-century American singer-songwriter}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2019}}
{{Infobox person
| name             = Buddy Holly
| image            = Buddy Holly cropped.JPG
| caption          = Holly in 1958
| birth_name       = Charles Hardin Holley
| birth_date       = {{Birth date|mf=yes|1936|09|07}}
| birth_place      = [[Lubbock, Texas]], U.S.
| death_date       = {{Death date and age|mf=yes|1959|02|03|1936|09|07}}
| death_place      = [[Clear Lake, Iowa]], U.S.
| spouse           = {{marriage|[[Maria Elena Santiago]]|August 15, 1958}}
| module           = {{Infobox musical artist|embed=yes
| background       = solo_singer
| Instrument       = Vocals, guitar&lt;!-- If you think an instrument should be listed, a discussion to reach consensus is needed first per: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Infobox_musical_artist#instrument --&gt;
| genre            = {{flatlist|
*[[Rock and roll]]
*[[rockabilly]]
*[[pop music|pop]]
*[[country music|country]]
}}
| occupation       = Singer-songwriter, musician
| years_active     = 1952–1959
| label            = [[Decca Records|Decca]], [[Brunswick Records|Brunswick]], [[Coral Records|Coral]]
| associated_acts  = Buddy and Bob, [[The Crickets]], [[The Picks]], [[Waylon Jennings]]
}}
}}

'''Charles Hardin Holley''' (September 7, 1936&amp;nbsp;– February 3, 1959), known professionally as '''Buddy Holly''', was an American musician and singer-songwriter who was a central and pioneering figure of mid-1950s [[rock and roll]]. He was born in [[Lubbock, Texas]], to a musical family during the [[Great Depression]], and learned to play guitar and sing alongside his siblings. His style was influenced by [[gospel music]], [[country music]], and [[rhythm and blues]] acts, which he performed in Lubbock with his friends from high school.

He made his first appearance on local television in 1952, and the following year he formed the group &quot;Buddy and Bob&quot; with his friend [[Bob Montgomery (songwriter)|Bob Montgomery]]. In 1955, after [[opening act|opening]] for [[Elvis Presley]], he decided to pursue a career in music. He opened for Presley three times that year; his band's style shifted from country and western to entirely rock and roll. In October that year, when he opened for [[Bill Haley &amp; His Comets]], he was spotted by [[Nashville, Tennessee|Nashville]] scout Eddie Crandall, who helped him get a contract with [[Decca Records]].

Holly's recording sessions at Decca were produced by [[Owen Bradley]], who had become famous for producing orchestrated country hits for stars like [[Patsy Cline]]. Unhappy with Bradley's musical style and control in the studio, Holly went to producer [[Norman Petty]] in [[Clovis, New Mexico]], and recorded a demo of &quot;[[That'll Be the Day]]&quot;, among other songs. Petty became the band's manager and sent the demo to [[Brunswick Records]], which released it as a single credited to &quot;[[The Crickets]]&quot;, which became the name of Holly's band. In September 1957, as the band toured, &quot;That'll Be the Day&quot; topped the [[List of Billboard number-one singles of 1957|US]] and [[UK Singles Chart|UK]] singles charts. Its success was followed in October by another major hit, &quot;[[Peggy Sue]]&quot;.

The album ''[[The &quot;Chirping&quot; Crickets|Chirping Crickets]]'', released in November 1957, reached number five on the [[UK Albums Chart]]. Holly made his second appearance on ''[[The Ed Sullivan Show]]'' in January 1958 and soon after, toured Australia and then the UK. In early 1959, he assembled a new band, consisting of future country music star [[Waylon Jennings]] (bass), famed session musician [[Tommy Allsup]] (guitar), and [[Carl Bunch]] (drums), and embarked on a tour of the midwestern U.S. After a show in [[Clear Lake, Iowa]], he chartered an airplane to travel to his next show, in [[Moorhead, Minnesota]]. Soon after takeoff, the plane crashed, killing Holly, [[Ritchie Valens]], [[The Big Bopper]], and pilot Roger Peterson in a tragedy later referred to by [[Don McLean]] as &quot;[[The Day the Music Died]]&quot;.

During his short career, Holly wrote and recorded several songs. He is often regarded as the artist who defined the traditional rock-and-roll lineup of two guitars, bass, and drums. He was a major influence on later [[popular music]] artists, including [[Elvis Presley]], [[Bob Dylan]], [[The Beatles]], [[The Rolling Stones]], [[Eric Clapton]], [[Elvis Costello]], [[Marshall Crenshaw]] (who later played Holly), and [[Elton John]]. He was among the first artists inducted into the [[Rock and Roll Hall of Fame]], in 1986. ''[[Rolling Stone]]'' magazine ranked him number 13 in its list of &quot;100 Greatest Artists&quot;.

==Life and career==
===Early life and career (1936–1955)===
Holly was born Charles Hardin Holley on September 7, 1936, in [[Lubbock, Texas]], the fourth child of Lawrence Odell &quot;L.O.&quot; Holley (1901–1985) and Ella Pauline Drake (1902–1990). His elder siblings were Larry (born in 1925), Travis (1927–2016),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://lubbockonline.com/interact/blog-post/william-kerns/2016-12-02/travis-holley-one-buddys-brothers-passes-away-thursday|title=Travis Holley, one of Buddy's brothers, dies Thursday (Playbill by Kerns blog) – Lubbock Online – Lubbock Avalanche-Journal|website=lubbockonline.com|access-date=December 30, 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170806180712/http://lubbockonline.com/interact/blog-post/william-kerns/2016-12-02/travis-holley-one-buddys-brothers-passes-away-thursday#|archive-date=August 6, 2017|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Patricia Lou (1929–2008).  Buddy Holly was of mostly English and Welsh descent but had small amounts of Native American ancestry as well.&lt;ref&gt;Buddy Holly: A Biography By Ellis Amburn pg. 10&lt;/ref&gt; From early childhood, he was nicknamed &quot;Buddy&quot;.{{sfn|Gribbin, John|2012|p=12}} During the Great Depression, the Holleys frequently moved residence within Lubbock; L.O. changed jobs several times. Buddy Holly was baptized a [[Baptist]], and the family were members of the Tabernacle Baptist Church.{{sfn|Gribbin, John|2012|p=12}}

The Holleys had an interest in music; all the family members except L.O. were able to play an instrument or sing. The elder Holley brothers performed in local talent shows; on one occasion, Buddy joined them on violin. Since he could not play it, his brother Larry greased the strings so it would not make any sound. The brothers won the contest.{{sfn|Gribbin, John|2012|p=13}} During [[World War II]], Larry and Travis were called to military service. Upon his return, Larry brought with him a guitar he had bought from a shipmate while serving in the Pacific. At age 11, Buddy took piano lessons but abandoned them after nine months. He switched to the guitar after he saw a classmate playing and singing on the school bus. Buddy's parents initially bought him a [[steel guitar]], but he insisted that he wanted a guitar like his brother's. His parents bought the guitar from a pawnshop, and Travis taught him to play it.{{sfn|Gribbin, John|2012|p=14}}

During his early childhood, Holley was influenced by the music of [[Hank Williams]], [[Jimmie Rodgers (country singer)|Jimmie Rodgers]], [[Hank Snow]], [[Bob Wills]], and the [[Carter Family]]. At Roscoe Wilson Elementary, he became friends with [[Bob Montgomery (songwriter)|Bob Montgomery]], and the two played together, practicing with songs by the [[Louvin Brothers]] and [[Johnnie &amp; Jack]].{{sfn|Norman, Philip|2011|p=34}} They both listened to the radio programs ''[[Grand Ole Opry]]'' on [[WSM (AM)|WSM]], ''[[Louisiana Hayride]]'' on [[KWKH]], and ''[[Big D Jamboree]]''. At the same time, Holley played with other musicians he met in high school, including [[Sonny Curtis]] and [[Jerry Allison]].{{sfn|Scott Schinder, Andy Schwartz|p=80|2007}} In 1952 Holley and Jack Neal participated as a duo billed as &quot;Buddy and Jack&quot; in a talent contest on a local television show. After Neal left, he was replaced by Bob Montgomery and they were billed as &quot;Buddy and Bob&quot;. The two soon started performing on the ''Sunday Party'' show on [[KDAV]] in 1953 and performed live gigs in Lubbock.{{sfn|Lehmer, Larry|p=6|2003}} At that time, Holley was influenced by late-night radio stations that played [[blues]] and [[rhythm and blues]] (R&amp;B). Holley would sit in his car with Curtis and tune to distant radio stations that could only be received at night, when local transmissions ceased.{{sfn|Lehmer, Larry|p=7|2003}} Holley then modified his music by blending his earlier country and western (C&amp;W) influence with R &amp; B.{{sfn|Wishart, David|p=540|2004}}

By 1955, after graduating from Lubbock High School, Holley decided to pursue a full-time career in music. He was further encouraged after seeing Elvis Presley performing live in Lubbock, whose act was booked by Pappy Dave Stone of KDAV. In February, Holley opened for Presley at the Fair Park Coliseum, in April at the Cotton Club, and again in June at the Coliseum. By that time, he had incorporated into his band Larry Welborn on the stand-up bass and Allison on drums, as his style shifted from C&amp;W to [[rock and roll]] due to seeing Presley's performances and hearing his music.{{sfn|Lehmer, Larry|p=7|2003}} In October, Stone booked Bill Haley &amp; His Comets and placed Holley as the opening act to be seen by [[Nashville, Tennessee|Nashville]] scout Eddie Crandall. Impressed, Crandall persuaded Grand Ole Opry manager Jim Denny to seek a recording contract for Holley. Stone sent a demo tape, which Denny forwarded to [[Paul Cohen (record producer)|Paul Cohen]], who signed the band to [[Decca Records]] in February 1956.{{sfn|Carr, Joseph|Munde, Alan|p=130|1997}} In the contract, Decca misspelled Holley's surname as &quot;Holly&quot;, and from then on he was known as &quot;Buddy Holly&quot;.{{sfn|MacDonald, Les|p=17|2010}}

On January 26, 1956, Holly attended his first formal recording session, which was produced by [[Owen Bradley]].{{sfn|Scott Schinder, Andy Schwartz|2007|p=97}} He attended two more sessions in Nashville, but with the producer selecting the session musicians and arrangements, Holly became increasingly frustrated by his lack of creative control.{{sfn|Carr, Joseph|Munde, Alan|1997|p=130}} In April 1956, Decca released &quot;[[Blue Days, Black Nights]]&quot; as a single, with &quot;Love Me&quot; on the B-side. Denny included Holly on a tour as the opening act for [[Faron Young]]. During the tour, they were promoted as &quot;Buddy Holly and the Two Tones&quot;, while later Decca called them &quot;Buddy Holly and the Three Tunes&quot;.{{sfn|Carr, Joseph|Munde, Alan|1997|p=130}} The label later released Holly's second single &quot;Modern Don Juan&quot;, backed with &quot;You Are My One Desire&quot;. Neither single made an impression. On January 22, 1957, Decca informed Holly his contract would not be renewed, but insisted he could not record the same songs for anyone else for five years.{{sfn|Uslan, Michael|Solomon, Bruce|1981|p=49}}

===The Crickets (1956–1957) ===
[[File:Buddy Holly &amp; The Crickets publicity portrait - cropped.jpg|Buddy Holly and the Crickets in 1957 (top to bottom: Allison, Holly and Mauldin)|thumb]]
Holly was unhappy with the results of his time with Decca; he was inspired by the success of [[Buddy Knox]]'s &quot;[[Party Doll]]&quot; and [[Jimmy Bowen]]'s &quot;[[I'm Stickin' with You]]&quot;, and visited [[Norman Petty]], who had produced and promoted both records. Together with Allison, bassist [[Joe B. Mauldin]], and rhythm guitarist [[Niki Sullivan]], he went to Petty's studio in [[Clovis, New Mexico]]. The group recorded a demo of &quot;[[That'll Be the Day]]&quot;, a song they had previously recorded in Nashville. Now playing lead guitar, Holly achieved the sound he desired. Petty became his manager and sent the record to [[Brunswick Records]] in New York City. Holly, still under contract with Decca, could not release the record under his name, so a band name was used; Allison proposed the name &quot;Crickets&quot;. Brunswick gave Holly a basic agreement to release &quot;That'll Be the Day&quot;, leaving him with both artistic control and financial responsibility for future recordings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3EAGAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT101|page=101|title=Buddy Holly: A Biography|first =Ellis|last =Amburn|publisher=St. Martin's Griffin|date=April 22, 2014|isbn=9781466868564}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Impressed with the demo, the label's executives released it without recording a new version. &quot;I'm Looking for Someone to Love&quot; was the B-side; the single was credited to the [[The Crickets|Crickets]]. Petty and Holly later learned that Brunswick was a subsidiary of Decca, which legally cleared future recordings under the name Buddy Holly. Recordings credited to the Crickets would be released on Brunswick, while the recordings under Holly's name were released on another subsidiary label, [[Coral Records]]. Holly concurrently held a recording contract with both labels.{{sfn|Carr, Joseph|Munde, Alan|1997|p=131}}

&quot;That'll Be the Day&quot; was released on May 27, 1957. Petty booked Holly and the Crickets for a tour with [[Irvin Feld]], who had noticed the band after &quot;That'll Be the Day&quot; appeared on the R&amp;B chart. He booked them for appearances in Washington, D.C., [[Baltimore]], and New York City.{{sfn|Lehmer, Larry|2003|p=16}} The band was booked to play at New York's [[Apollo Theater]] on August 16–22. During the opening performances, the group did not impress the audience, but they were accepted after they included &quot;[[Bo Diddley (Bo Diddley song)|Bo Diddley]].&quot; By the end of their run at the Apollo, &quot;That'll Be the Day&quot; was climbing the charts. Encouraged by the single's success, Petty started to prepare two album releases; a solo album for Holly and another for the Crickets.{{sfn|Lehmer, Larry|2003|p=17}} Holly appeared on ''[[American Bandstand]]'', hosted by [[Dick Clark]] on [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]], on August 26. Before leaving New York, the band befriended the [[Everly Brothers]].{{sfn|Lehmer, Larry|2003|p=18}}

&quot;That'll Be the Day&quot; topped the [[Number-one hits of 1957 (United States)|US &quot;Best Sellers in Stores&quot;]] chart on September 23 and was number one on the UK Singles Chart for three weeks in November.{{sfn|Lehmer, Larry|2003|p=19}} On September 20, Coral released &quot;[[Peggy Sue]]&quot;, backed with &quot;[[Everyday (Buddy Holly song)|Everyday]]&quot;, with Holly credited as the performer. By October, &quot;Peggy Sue&quot; had reached number three on ''Billboard'''s pop chart and number two on the R&amp;B chart; it peaked at number six on the UK Singles chart. As the success of the song grew, it brought more attention to Holly, with the band at the time being billed as &quot;Buddy Holly and the Crickets&quot;.{{sfn|Gribbin, John|2012|p=57}}

In the last week of September the band members flew to Lubbock to visit their families.{{sfn|Gribbin, John|2012|p=58}} Holly's high school girlfriend, Echo McGuire, had left him for a fellow student.{{sfn|Norman, Phillip|p=156|1996}} Aside from McGuire, Holly had a relationship with Lubbock fan June Clark.{{sfn|Norman, Phillip|p=127|1996}} After Clark ended their relationship, Holly realized the importance of his relationship with McGuire and considered his with Clark a temporary one.{{sfn|Norman, Phillip|p=156|1996}} Meanwhile, for their return to recording, Petty arranged a session in [[Oklahoma City]], where he was performing with his own band. While the band drove to the location, the producer set up a makeshift studio. The rest of the songs needed for an album and singles were recorded; Petty later dubbed the material in Clovis.{{sfn|Gribbin, John|2012|p=58}} The resulting album, ''[[The &quot;Chirping&quot; Crickets]]'', was released on November 27, 1957. It reached number five on the UK Albums Chart. In October, Brunswick released the second single by the Crickets, &quot;[[Oh, Boy! (The Crickets song)|Oh, Boy!]]&quot;, with &quot;[[Not Fade Away (song)|Not Fade Away]]&quot; on the B-side. The single reached number 10 on the pop chart and 13 on the R&amp;B chart.{{sfn|Gribbin, John|2012|p=57}} Holly and the Crickets performed &quot;That'll Be the Day&quot; and &quot;Peggy Sue&quot; on ''The Ed Sullivan Show'' on December 1, 1957. Following the appearance, Niki Sullivan left the group because of the intensive touring. On December 29 Holly and the Crickets performed &quot;Peggy Sue&quot; on ''[[The Arthur Murray Party]]''.{{sfn|Moore, Gary|2011|p=127}}

===International tours and breakaway (1958)===
On January 8, 1958, Holly and the Crickets joined ''America's Greatest Teenage Recording Stars'' tour.{{sfn|Moore, Gary|2011|p=128}} On January 25, Holly recorded &quot;[[Rave On]]&quot;; the next day, he made his second appearance on ''The Ed Sullivan Show'', singing &quot;Oh, Boy!&quot;{{sfn|Moore, Gary|2011|p=128}} He departed to perform in [[Honolulu, Hawaii]], on January 27, and then started a week-long tour of Australia.{{sfn|Norman, Philip|2011|p=189}} In March, the band toured the United Kingdom, playing 50 shows in 25 days.&lt;ref name=&quot;Buddy Holly UK Tour&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=americanrocknrolluktours.co.uk|url= http://www.americanrocknrolluktours.co.uk/tour/buddy-holly-and-the-crickets-march-1958/}}&lt;/ref&gt; The same month, his debut solo album, ''[[Buddy Holly (album)|Buddy Holly]]'', was released. Upon their return to the United States, Holly and the Crickets joined Alan Freed's ''Big Beat Show'' tour for 41 dates. In April, Decca released ''[[That'll Be the Day (album)|That'll Be the Day]]'', featuring the songs recorded with Bradley during his early Nashville sessions.{{sfn|Scott Schinder, Andy Schwartz|2007|p=90}}

A new recording session in Clovis was arranged in May; Holly hired [[Tommy Allsup]] to play lead guitar. The session produced the recordings of &quot;[[It's So Easy! (The Crickets song)|It's So Easy]]&quot; and &quot;[[Heartbeat (Buddy Holly song)|Heartbeat]]&quot;. Holly was impressed by Allsup and invited him to join the Crickets. In June, Holly traveled alone to New York for a solo recording session. Without the Crickets, he chose to be backed by a jazz and R&amp;B band, recording &quot;Now We're One&quot; and [[Bobby Darin]]'s &quot;[[Early in the Morning (Bobby Darin song)|Early in the Morning]]&quot;.{{sfn|Scott Schinder, Andy Schwartz|2007|p=91}}

During a visit to the offices of [[Peermusic|Peer-South]], Holly met [[María Elena Santiago]]. He asked her out on their first meeting and proposed marriage to her on their first date. The wedding took place on August 15. Petty disapproved of the marriage and advised Holly to keep it secret to avoid upsetting Holly's female fans. Petty's reaction created friction with Holly, who had also started to question Petty's bookkeeping. The Crickets, frustrated because he controlled all of the proceeds from the band, were also in conflict with Petty.{{sfn|Scott Schinder, Andy Schwartz|2007|p=92}}

Holly and Santiago frequented many of New York's music venues, including the [[The Village Gate|Village Gate]], Blue Note, [[Village Vanguard]], and Johnny Johnson's. Santiago later said that Holly was keen to learn fingerstyle flamenco guitar and that he would often visit her aunt's home to play the piano there. Holly planned collaborations between soul singers and rock and roll. He wanted to make an album with [[Ray Charles]] and [[Mahalia Jackson]]. He also had ambitions to work in film and registered for acting classes with Lee Strasberg's [[Actors Studio]].{{sfn|Norman, Philip|2011|p=281}}

Santiago accompanied Holly on tours. To hide her marriage to Holly, she was presented as the Crickets' secretary. She took care of the laundry and equipment set-up and collected the concert revenues. Santiago kept the money for the band instead of their habitual transfer to Petty in New Mexico.{{sfn|Norman, Philip|2011|p=274}} She and her aunt Provi Garcia, executive of the Latin American music department at [[Peer-Southern]], convinced Holly that Petty was paying the band's royalties from Coral-Brunswick into his own company's account. Holly planned to retrieve his royalties from Petty and to later fire him as manager and producer. At the recommendation of the Everly Brothers, Holly hired lawyer Harold Orenstein to negotiate his royalties.{{sfn|Norman, Philip|2011|p=280}} The problems with Petty were triggered after he was unable to pay Holly. At the time, New York promoter Manny Greenfield reclaimed a large part of Holly's earnings; Greenfield had booked Holly for shows during previous tours. The two had a verbal agreement; Greenfield would obtain 5% of the booking earnings. Greenfield later felt he was also acting as Holly's manager and deserved a higher payment, which Holly refused. Greenfield then sued Holly. Under New York law, because Holly's royalties originated in New York and were directed out of the state, the payments were frozen until the dispute was settled. Petty then could not complete the transfers to Holly, who considered him responsible for the missing profit.{{sfn|Laing, Dave|p=153|2010}}

In September, Holly returned to Clovis for a new recording session, which yielded &quot;Reminiscing&quot; and &quot;Come Back Baby&quot;. During the session, he ventured into producing by recording Lubbock DJ [[Waylon Jennings]]. Holly produced the single &quot;Jole Blon&quot; and &quot;When Sin Stops (Love Begins)&quot; for Jennings.{{sfn|Carr, Joseph|Munde, Alan|1997|p=155}} Holly became increasingly interested in the New York music, recording, and publishing scene. Santiago and he settled in Apartment 4H of the Brevoort Apartments, at 11 Fifth Avenue in [[Greenwich Village]], where he recorded a series of acoustic songs, including &quot;[[Crying, Waiting, Hoping]]&quot; and &quot;What to Do&quot;.{{sfn|Norman, Philip|2011|p=274–278}} The inspiration to record the songs is sometimes attributed to the ending of his relationship with McGuire.{{sfn|Lloyd Webber, Julian|2015}} In October, Holly recorded tracks for Coral; these were backed by saxophonist [[Boomie Richman]] and an 18-piece orchestra composed of former members of the [[NBC Symphony Orchestra]]. The three-and-a-half-hour session produced &quot;[[It Doesn't Matter Anymore]]&quot;, &quot;[[Raining in My Heart]]&quot;, &quot;[[Moondreams (Norman Petty song)|Moondreams]]&quot; (written by Petty), and &quot;[[True Love Ways]]&quot;.{{sfn|Norman, Philip|2011|p=276–278}}

Holly ended his association with Petty in December 1958. His band members kept Petty as their manager, and Holly also split from the Crickets. Petty was still holding the money from the royalties, forcing Holly to form a new band and return to touring.{{sfn|Norman, Philip|2011|p=284–285}}

===Winter Dance Party tour and death (1959)===
{{Main|The Day the Music Died}}
[[File:GlassesSign.jpg|thumb|right|Signpost near the Clear Lake crash site]]
[[File:HollyMonument.jpg|thumb|left|Monument at crash site in 2003]]
Holly vacationed with his wife in Lubbock and visited Jennings's radio station in December 1958.{{sfn|Jennings, Waylon|Kaye, Lenny|1996|p = 51}} For the start of the [[Winter Dance Party]] tour, he assembled a band consisting of [[Waylon Jennings]] (electric bass), Tommy Allsup (guitar), and [[Carl Bunch]] (drums).{{sfn|Corbin, Sky|2014}} Holly and Jennings left for New York City, arriving on January 15, 1959. Jennings stayed at Holly's apartment by [[Washington Square Park]] on the days prior to a meeting scheduled at the headquarters of the [[General Amusement Corporation|General Artists Corporation]], which organized the tour.{{sfn|Jennings, Waylon|Kaye, Lenny|1996|p = 58, 59}} They then traveled by train to Chicago to join the rest of the band.{{sfn|Jennings, Waylon|Kaye, Lenny|1996|p = 62}}

[[File:Surf Ballroom Monument.jpg|thumb|Monument in front of Surf Ballroom in Clear Lake, Iowa]]
The Winter Dance Party tour began in [[Milwaukee, Wisconsin]], on January 23, 1959. The amount of travel involved created logistical problems, as the distance between venues had not been considered when scheduling performances. Adding to the problem, the unheated tour buses twice broke down in freezing weather, with dire consequences. Holly's drummer Carl Bunch was hospitalized for [[frostbite]] to his toes (suffered while aboard the bus), so Holly decided to seek other transportation.{{sfn|Everitt|2004|p = [https://books.google.com/books?id=H4TSH_b7IHYC&amp;pg=PA13 13]}} On February 2, before their appearance in [[Clear Lake, Iowa]], Holly chartered a four-seat [[Beechcraft Bonanza]] airplane for Jennings, Allsup, and himself, from Dwyer Flying Service in [[Mason City, Iowa]]. Holly's idea was to depart following the show at the [[Surf Ballroom]] in Clear Lake and fly to their next venue, in [[Moorhead, Minnesota]], via [[Fargo, North Dakota]], allowing them time to rest and launder their clothes and avoid a rigorous bus journey. Immediately after the Clear Lake show (which ended just before midnight), Allsup agreed to flip a coin for the seat with Valens. Valens called heads; when he won, he reportedly said, &quot;That's the first time I've ever won anything in my life,&quot; Allsup later opened a restaurant in [[Fort Worth, Texas]] called Heads Up.&lt;ref&gt;Galloway, P. (June 24, 1988). Hit parade. Chicago Tribune (1963–Current File) Retrieved from http://search.proquest.com/docview/882608515&lt;/ref&gt; Waylon Jennings voluntarily gave up his seat to [[The Big Bopper|J. P. Richardson (the Big Bopper)]], who had influenza and complained that the tour bus was too cold and uncomfortable for a man of his size.&lt;ref&gt;Texas Monthly, January 1988; [https://books.google.com/books?id=AyoEAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA103 p.108]&lt;/ref&gt;

The pilot, [[Roger Peterson (pilot)|Roger Peterson]], took off in inclement weather&lt;!-- The meteorological conditions at the time of the aircraft's takeoff were not &quot;a snowstorm&quot; as previously stated here, but &quot;Precipitation ceiling 3,000 feet (1,800 feet AGL), sky obscured; visibility 6 miles; scattered light snow; temperature {{convert|18|°F|°C|abbr=on}}; winds south 20 knots, gusts to 30 knots; altimeter setting 29.85 inches&quot;. Snow level on the ground the morning after was 4 inches. See [[http://www.fiftiesweb.com/cab.htm]] for the Civil Aeronautics Board investigation report. --&gt;, although he was not certified to fly by [[instrument flight rules|instruments only]]. Shortly after 12:55&amp;nbsp;am on February 3, 1959, Holly, Valens, Richardson, and Peterson were killed instantly when the aircraft crashed into a frozen cornfield five miles northwest of Mason City, Iowa, airport shortly after takeoff. The three musicians, who were ejected from the fuselage upon impact, suffered severe head and chest injuries.{{sfn|Associated Press staff|1959}}

[[File:Buddy holley headstone.jpg|thumb|left|Holly's headstone in the City of Lubbock Cemetery]]
Holly's funeral was held on February 7, 1959, at the Tabernacle Baptist Church in Lubbock. The service was officiated by Ben D. Johnson, who had presided at the Hollys' wedding just months earlier. The pallbearers were Jerry Allison, Joe B. Mauldin, Niki Sullivan, Bob Montgomery, and [[Sonny Curtis]]. Some sources say that Phil Everly, the one half of [[The Everly Brothers]], was also the pallbearer, but he said at one time that he attended the funeral but was not a pallbearer.{{sfn|Amburn, Ellis|p=347|2014}} Waylon Jennings was unable to attend, because of his commitment to the still-touring Winter Dance Party. Holly's body was interred in the City of Lubbock Cemetery, in the eastern part of the city. His headstone carries the correct spelling of his surname (Holley) and a carving of his [[Fender Stratocaster]] guitar.{{sfn|Amburn, Ellis|p=348–52|2014}}

María Elena watched the first reports of Holly's death on television. The following day, she claimed, she suffered a miscarriage, although there is no independent source for this. Holly's mother, who heard the news on the radio in Lubbock, Texas, screamed and collapsed. Because of Elena's miscarriage, in the months following the accident, the authorities implemented a policy against announcing victims' names until after families are informed.{{sfn|Suddath, Claire|2009}} Santiago did not attend the funeral and has never visited the grave site. She later told the ''Avalanche-Journal'', &quot;In a way, I blame myself. I was not feeling well when he left. I was two weeks pregnant, and I wanted Buddy to stay with me, but he had scheduled that tour. It was the only time I wasn't with him. And I blame myself because I know that, if only I had gone along, Buddy never would have gotten into that airplane.&quot;{{sfn|Kerns, William|2008}}

==Image and style==
Holly's singing style was characterized by his vocal hiccups and his alternation between his [[Modal voice|regular voice]] and [[falsetto]].{{sfn|Rolling Stone staff|2001}} His &quot;stuttering vocals&quot; were complemented by his [[Percussive fingerstyle|percussive guitar playing]], solos, [[Double stop|stops]], [[bent note]]s, and rhythm and blues [[chord progression]]s.{{sfn|Henderson, Lol|Stacey, Lee|p=296|2014}} He often strummed [[Downpicking|downstrokes]] that were accompanied by Allison's &quot;driving&quot; percussion.{{sfn|Wishart, David|p=540|2004}}

Holly bought his first Fender Stratocaster, which became his signature guitar, at Harrod Music in Lubbock for US$249.50. Fender Stratocasters were popular with country musicians; Holly chose it for its loud sound.{{sfn|Amburn, Ellis|2014|p=59}} His &quot;innovative&quot; playing style was characterized by its blending of &quot;chunky rhythm&quot; and &quot;high string lead work&quot;. He played his first Stratocaster, a 1954 model, until it was stolen during a tour stop in [[Michigan]] in 1957. To replace it, he purchased a 1957 model before a show in Detroit. Holly owned four or five Stratocasters during his career.{{sfn|Hunter, Dave|p=87|2013}}

At the beginning of their music careers, Holly and his band wore business suits. When they met the Everly Brothers, Don Everly took the band to Phil's men's shop in New York City and introduced them to [[Ivy League (clothes)|Ivy League clothes]]. The brothers advised Holly to replace his old-fashioned glasses with [[horn-rimmed glasses]], which had been popularized by [[Steve Allen]].{{sfn|Norman, Phillip|1996|p=144}} Holly bought a pair of glasses made in Mexico from Lubbock optometrist Dr. J. Davis Armistead. Teenagers in the United States started to request this style of glasses, which were later popularly known as &quot;Buddy Holly glasses&quot;.{{sfn|Jones, Steve|p=175|2014}}

When the plane crashed, the wreckage was strewn across many yards of snow-covered ground. While his other belongings were recovered immediately, there was no record of his signature glasses being found. They were presumed lost until, in March 1980, they were discovered in a Cerro Gordo County courthouse storage area by Sheriff Gerald Allen. They had been found in the spring of 1959, after the snow had melted, and had been given to the sheriff's office. They were placed in an envelope dated April 7, 1959, along with the Big Bopper's watch, a lighter, two pairs of dice and part of another watch, and misplaced when the county moved courthouses. The glasses, missing their lenses, were returned to Maria Elena a year later, after a legal contest over them with his parents. They are now on display at the Buddy Holly Center in Lubbock, Texas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=2002&amp;dat=19800312&amp;id=UfsqAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=3dkFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4079,2430645|title=Holly's glasses returned to family |newspaper=The Beaver County Times |date=March 12, 1980 |accessdate=December 19, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=886&amp;dat=19810322&amp;id=oZ5OAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=o0wDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6240,5970296|title=Eyeglasses returned |newspaper=The Prescott Courier |date=March 22, 1981 |accessdate=December 19, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
Buddy Holly left behind dozens of unfinished recordings&amp;nbsp;— solo transcriptions of his new compositions, informal jam sessions with bandmates, or tapes demonstrating songs intended for other artists. The most recent recordings, made in Holly's apartment in late 1958, were his last six original songs. In June 1959, Coral Records overdubbed two of them with backing vocals by the [[Ray Charles Singers]] and studio musicians in an attempt to simulate the established Crickets sound. The finished tracks became the first posthumous Holly single, &quot;[[Peggy Sue Got Married (song)|Peggy Sue Got Married]]&quot;/&quot;[[Crying, Waiting, Hoping]]&quot;. The new release was successful enough to warrant an album drawing upon the other Holly demos, using the same studio personnel, in January 1960.&lt;ref&gt;Goldrosen, John (1979). The Buddy Holly Story. Quick Fox. {{ISBN|978-0-825-63936-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; All six songs were included in &quot;The Buddy Holly Story, Vol. 2&quot; (1960).

The demand for Holly records was so great, and Holly had recorded so prolifically, that his record label was able to release new Holly albums and singles for the next 10 years. Norman Petty produced most of these new editions, drawing upon unreleased studio masters, alternative takes, audition tapes, and even amateur recordings (some dating back to 1954 with low-fidelity vocals). The final &quot;new&quot; Buddy Holly album, &quot;Giant&quot;, was released in 1969; the single chosen from the album was &quot;[[Love Is Strange]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.discogs.com/Buddy-Holly-Giant/master/490135|title=Buddy Holly- Giant|last=|first=|date=|website=Discogs|archive-url=|archive-date=|url-status=|access-date=February 24, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
''[[Encyclopædia Britannica]]'' stated that Holly &quot;produced some of the most distinctive and influential work in rock music&quot;.{{sfn|Crenshaw, Marshall|2015}} [[AllMusic]] defined him as &quot;the single most influential creative force in early rock and roll&quot;.{{sfn|Eder, Bruce|2015}} ''[[Rolling Stone (magazine)|Rolling Stone]]'' ranked him number 13 on its list of &quot;100 Greatest Artists&quot;.{{sfn|Mellecamp, John|2011}} The ''[[The Daily Telegraph|Telegraph]]'' called him a &quot;pioneer and a revolutionary [...] a multidimensional talent [...] (who) co-wrote and performed (songs that) remain as fresh and potent today&quot;.{{sfn|Norman, Phillip|2015}}

The Rock and Roll Hall of Fame included Holly among its first class in 1986. On its entry, the Hall of Fame remarked upon the large quantity of material he produced during his short musical career, and said it &quot;made a major and lasting impact on popular music&quot;. It called him an &quot;innovator&quot; for writing his own material, his experimentation with [[double tracking]] and the use of [[orchestration]]; he is also said to have &quot;pioneered and popularized the now-standard&quot; use of two guitars, bass, and drums by rock bands.{{sfn|Rock and Roll Hall of Fame staff|2015}} [[The Songwriters Hall of Fame]] also inducted Holly in 1986, and said his contributions &quot;changed the face of Rock 'n' Roll&quot;.{{sfn|Songwriters hall of Fame staff|2002}} Holly developed in collaboration with Petty techniques of [[overdubbing]] and [[reverberation]], while he used innovative instrumentation later implemented by other artists.{{sfn|Wishart, David|p=540|2004}} Holly became &quot;one of the most influential pioneers of rock and roll&quot; who had a &quot;lasting influence&quot; on genre performers of the 1960s.{{sfn|Henderson, Lol|Stacey, Lee|p=296|2014}}

[[File:Buddy Holly Center in Lubbock, TX IMG 0078.JPG|thumb|The [[Buddy Holly Center]], a museum in Lubbock, Texas]]
In 1980, [[Grant Speed]] sculpted a statue of Holly playing his Fender guitar. This statue is the centerpiece of Lubbock's Walk of Fame, which honors notable people who contributed to Lubbock's musical history. Other memorials to Buddy Holly include a street named in his honor and the [[Buddy Holly Center]], which contains a museum of Holly memorabilia and fine arts gallery. The Center is located on Crickets Avenue, one street east of Buddy Holly Avenue, in a building that previously housed the Fort Worth and Denver South Plains Railway Depot.{{sfn|Buddy Holly Center staff|2014}}

In 1997, the [[National Academy of Recording Arts and Sciences]] gave Holly the [[Grammy Lifetime Achievement Award|Lifetime Achievement Award]].{{sfn|Hollywood Reporter Staff|1997}} Holly was inducted into the [[Iowa Rock 'n' Roll Hall of Fame]] in 2000. In 2010, Grant Speed's statue was taken down for refurbishment and construction of a new Walk of Fame began. On May 9, 2011, the City of Lubbock held a ribbon-cutting ceremony for the Buddy and Maria Elena Holly Plaza, the new home of the statue and the Walk of Fame.{{sfn|Kerns, William|2011}} The same year, a star bearing Holly's name was placed on the [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]], commemorating his 75th birthday.{{sfn|Duke, Alan|2011}}

Groundbreaking was held on April 20, 2017, for the construction of a new performing arts center in Lubbock, the [[Buddy Holly Hall of Performing Arts and Sciences]], a downtown $153 million project expected to be completed in 2020.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.constructionequipmentguide.com/lubbocks-153m-buddy-holly-hall-due-to-open-in-2020/38691|title=Lubbock's $153M Buddy Holly Hall Due to Open in 2020|website=www.constructionequipmentguide.com|language=en|access-date=August 7, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus far, the private group, the Lubbock Entertainment and Performing Arts Association, has raised or received pledges in the amount of $93 million to underwrite the project.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://lubbockonline.com/entertainment/news/2017-04-01/restaurant-partnership-groundbreaking-date-announced-buddy-holly-hall|title=Restaurant partnership, groundbreaking date announced for Buddy Holly Hall|author=William Kerns|newspaper=Lubbock Avalanche-Journal|accessdate=April 1, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to a June 2019 article in ''[[The New York Times Magazine]]'', &quot;virtually all of Holly's masters were lost&quot; in the [[2008 Universal fire]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT-20190611&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Rosen |first=Jody |title=The Day the Music Burned: It was the biggest disaster in the history of the music business — and almost nobody knew |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2019/06/11/magazine/universal-fire-master-recordings.html |date=June 11, 2019 |work=[[The New York Times Magazine]] |accessdate=June 11, 2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This is disputed by Chad Kassem of Analogue Productions, who claims to have used the master tapes of Holly's first two albums in Analogue Productions reissues of these albums on LP and SACD in 2017.{{citation needed|date=June 2019}}

===Influence===
[[John Lennon]] and [[Paul McCartney]] saw Holly for the first time when he appeared on ''[[Sunday Night at the London Palladium]]''.{{sfn|Humphries, Patrick|p=73|2003}} The two had recently met and begun their musical association. They studied Holly's records, learned his performance style and lyricism, and based their act around his persona. Inspired by Holly's insect-themed Crickets, they chose to name their band &quot;[[The Beatles]]&quot;. Lennon and McCartney later cited Holly as one of their main influences.{{sfn|Riley, Tim|p=67–70|2011}}

Lennon's band [[the Quarrymen]] covered &quot;That'll Be the Day&quot; in their first recording session, in 1958.{{sfn|Gaar, Gillian|p=238|2013}} During breaks in the Beatles' first appearance on ''The Ed Sullivan Show'', on February 9, 1964, Lennon asked [[CBS]] coordinator Vic Calandra about Holly's performances; Calandra said Lennon and McCartney repeatedly expressed their appreciation of Holly.{{sfn|Harris, Michael|p=192–193|2014}} The Beatles recorded a close cover of Holly's version of &quot;[[Words of Love]]&quot;, which was released on their 1964 album ''[[Beatles for Sale]]'' (in the U.S., in June 1965 on ''[[Beatles VI]]''). During the January 1969 recording sessions for their album ''[[Let It Be (The Beatles album)|Let It Be]]'', the Beatles played a slow, impromptu version of &quot;Mailman, Bring Me No More Blues&quot; – which Holly popularized but did not write – with Lennon mimicking Holly's vocal style.{{sfn|Margotin, Phillipe|Guesdon, Jean-Michael|2014|p=186}} Lennon recorded a cover version of &quot;Peggy Sue&quot; on his 1975 album ''[[Rock 'n' Roll (John Lennon album)|Rock 'n' Roll]]''.{{sfn|Blaney, John|p=163|2005}} McCartney owns the [[Music publisher (popular music)|publishing rights]] to Holly's song catalogue.{{sfn|BBC News staff|2003}}

On January 31, 1959, two nights before Holly's death, 17-year-old [[Bob Dylan]] attended Holly's performance in Duluth. Dylan referred to this in his acceptance speech when he received the [[Grammy Award for Album of the Year]] for ''[[Time Out of Mind (Bob Dylan album)|Time Out of Mind]]'' in 1998: &quot;...&amp;nbsp;when I was sixteen or seventeen years old, I went to see Buddy Holly play at [[Duluth National Guard Armory]] and I was three feet away from him&amp;nbsp;... and he looked at me. And I just have some sort of feeling that he was&amp;nbsp;... with us all the time we were making this record in some kind of way&quot;.{{sfn|Shelton, Robert|p=37|2011}}

[[Mick Jagger]] saw Holly performing live in [[Woolwich]], London, during a tour of England; Jagger particularly remembered Holly's performance of &quot;[[Not Fade Away (song)|Not Fade Away]]&quot; – a song that also inspired [[Keith Richards]], who modeled his early guitar playing on the track. The Rolling Stones had a hit version of the song in 1964.{{sfn|Norman, Philip|p=12|2011}} Richards later said, &quot;[Holly] passed it on via the Beatles and via [the Rolling Stones]&amp;nbsp;...&amp;nbsp;He's in everybody&quot;.{{sfn|Amburn, Ellis|2014|p=274}}

[[Don McLean]]'s popular 1971 [[ballad (music)|ballad]] &quot;[[American Pie (song)|American Pie]]&quot; was inspired by Holly's death and the day of the plane crash. The song's lyric, which calls the incident &quot;The Day the Music Died&quot;, became popularly associated with the crash. McLean's album ''[[American Pie (Don McLean album)|American Pie]]'' is dedicated to Holly.{{sfn|Crouse, Richard|p=86|2012}} In 2015, McLean wrote, &quot;Buddy Holly would have the same stature musically whether he would have lived or died, because of his accomplishments&amp;nbsp;...&amp;nbsp;By the time he was 22 years old, he had recorded some 50 tracks, most of which he had written himself&amp;nbsp;...&amp;nbsp;in my view and the view of many others, a hit&amp;nbsp;...&amp;nbsp;Buddy Holly and the Crickets were the template for all the rock bands that followed&quot;.{{sfn|McLean, Don|2015}}

[[Elton John]] was musically influenced by Holly. At age 13, although he did not require them, John started wearing horn-rimmed glasses to imitate Holly.{{sfn|Goldrosen, John|1979|p=8}} [[The Clash]] were also influenced by Holly, and referenced him in their song &quot;Corner Soul&quot; from the ''[[Sandinista!]]'' album.{{sfn|Fletcher, Tony|p=174|2012}} ''The Chirping Crickets'' was the first album [[Eric Clapton]] ever bought; he later saw Holly on ''Sunday Night at the London Palladium''. In his autobiography, Clapton recounted the first time he saw Holly and his Fender, saying, &quot;I thought I'd died and gone to heaven&amp;nbsp;...&amp;nbsp;it was like seeing an instrument from outer space and I said to myself: 'That's the future – that's what I want'&quot;.{{sfn|Clapton, Eric|p=19|2010}}

The launch of [[Bobby Vee]]'s successful musical career resulted from Holly's death; Vee was selected to replace Holly on the tour that continued after the plane crash. Holly's profound influence on Vee's singing style can be heard in the songs &quot;[[Rubber Ball]]&quot; – the B-side of which was a cover of Holly's &quot;Everyday&quot; – and &quot;Run to Him.&quot;{{sfn|Dean, Maury|2003|p=73}} The name of the British rock band [[the Hollies]] is often claimed as a tribute to Holly; according to the band, they admired Holly, but their name was mainly inspired by sprigs of holly in evidence around Christmas 1962.{{sfn|Eder, Bruce|1996}} In an August 24, 1978, interview with ''Rolling Stone'', [[Bruce Springsteen]] told [[Dave Marsh]], &quot;I play Buddy Holly every night before I go on; that keeps me honest&quot;.{{sfn|Deardorff II, Donald|p=16|2013}} The [[Grateful Dead]] performed the song &quot;Not Fade Away&quot; in concerts.{{sfn|Meriwether, Nicholas|p=134|2013}}

In 2016, [[Richard Barone]] released his album ''Sorrows &amp; Promises: Greenwich Village in the 1960s'', paying tribute to the new wave of singer-songwriters in the Village during that pivotal, post-Holly era. The album opens with Barone's version of &quot;Learning the Game&quot;, one of the final songs written and recorded by Holly at his home in Greenwich Village, a week before his death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Richard Barone Breathes New Life Into the Golden Age of Village Folk|url=http://observer.com/2016/08/richard-barone-breathes-new-life-into-the-golden-age-of-village-folk/|newspaper=Observer|date=April 12, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Terry Pratchett]]'s main charachter in his book [[Soul Music (novel)]] was named Imp Y Celyn, a young lad from Llamedos who sings and plays the guitar. His name is Welsh and means &quot;Bud of the holly&quot;. Later on he uses the name &quot;Buddy&quot;.

===Film and musical depictions===
Holly's life story inspired a Hollywood [[biographical film]], ''[[The Buddy Holly Story]]'' (1978); its lead actor [[Gary Busey]] received a nomination for the [[Academy Award for Best Actor]] for his portrayal of Holly. The film was widely criticized by the rock press, and by Holly's friends and family, for its inaccuracies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Flippo |first=Chet |url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/features/the-buddy-holly-story-19780921 |title=The Truth Behind 'The Buddy Holly Story' |work=Rolling Stone |date=September 21, 1978 |accessdate=December 19, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; This led Paul McCartney (whose MPL Communications by then controlled the publishing rights to Buddy Holly's song catalog) to produce and host his own documentary about Holly in 1985, titled ''The Real Buddy Holly Story''. This video includes interviews with Keith Richards, Phil and Don Everly, Sonny Curtis, Jerry Allison, Holly's family, and McCartney, among others.{{sfn|Lehmer, Larry|2003|p=174–176}}

In 1987, musician [[Marshall Crenshaw]] portrayed Buddy Holly in the movie ''[[La Bamba (film)|La Bamba]]'', which depicts him performing at the Surf Ballroom and boarding the fatal airplane with Ritchie Valens and the Big Bopper. Crenshaw's version of &quot;Crying, Waiting, Hoping&quot; is featured on the ''La Bamba'' original motion picture soundtrack.{{sfn|Green, Stanley|p=267|1999}} ''[[Buddy – The Buddy Holly Story]]'', a [[jukebox musical]] depicting Holly's life, is credited for being the first of its kind. It spawned the genre that later included ''[[Mamma Mia!]]'' and ''[[We Will Rock You (musical)|We Will Rock You]]''. The musical opened in the late 1980s and its most recent UK tour occurred in 2019.

[[Steve Buscemi]] appeared as Holly in a brief cameo as a 1950s-themed restaurant employee in [[Quentin Tarantino]]'s 1994 film ''[[Pulp Fiction]]'', in which he takes Mia Wallace and Vincent Vega's orders (portrayed respectively by [[Uma Thurman]] and [[John Travolta]]).

Holly was depicted in an episode of the science-fiction television program ''[[Quantum Leap]]'' titled &quot;How the Tess Was Won&quot;; Holly's identity is only revealed at the end of the episode. Dr. [[Sam Beckett]] ([[Scott Bakula]]) influences Buddy Holly to change his lyrics from &quot;piggy, suey&quot; to &quot;Peggy Sue&quot;, setting up Holly's future hit song.{{sfn|Phillips, Mark|Garcia, Frank|1996|p=358}} Holly's follow up to that hit song is featured in the 1986 [[Francis Ford Coppola]] film ''[[Peggy Sue Got Married]]'', in which a 43-year-old mother and housewife facing divorce played by [[Kathleen Turner]] is thrust back in time and given the chance to change the course of her life.

In 1961 Mike Berry recorded &quot;Tribute to Buddy Holly&quot;.

[[Weezer|Weezer's]] first top 40 single in the US was titled [[Buddy Holly (song)|''Buddy Holly'']].

In 2006, country band, the [[Dixie Chicks]] mention Buddy Holly in their song [[Lubbock or Leave It]]. Lead singer, [[Natalie Maines]], and Holly share a hometown, [[Lubbock, Texas]].

Musician [[Richard Barone]] recorded one of Buddy Holly's Greenwich Village demos, &quot;Learning the Game&quot; on his 2016 album ''Sorrows &amp; Promises''. In concert, Barone speaks of the importance of Holly's presence in the Village at the end of 1950s, speculating that had he lived, Holly would have expedited the [[folk rock]] and [[singer-songwriter]] movements that emerged in the mid-1960s.&lt;ref&gt;http://popdose.com/album-review-richard-barone-sorrows-promises-greenwich-village-in-the-1960s/&lt;/ref&gt;

==Discography==
{{Main|Buddy Holly discography}}

===The Crickets===
* ''[[The &quot;Chirping&quot; Crickets]]'' (1957)

===Solo===
* ''[[Buddy Holly (album)|Buddy Holly]]'' (1958)
* ''[[That'll Be the Day (album)|That'll Be the Day]]'' (1958)

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

===Sources===
{{refbegin|30em}}
* {{cite book|author=Amburn, Ellis|year=2014|title=Buddy Holly: A Biography|publisher=St. Martin's Press|isbn=978-0-312-14557-6|ref=harv}}
* {{cite news|author=Associated Press staff|year=1959|title=Iowa Crash Kills 3 Singers; Rock 'n' Roll Stars and Pilot Die as Chartered Craft Falls After Its Take-Off |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1959/02/04/archives/iowa-air-crash-kills-3-singers-rock-n-roll-stars-and-pilot-die-as.html |agency=Associated Press|newspaper=New York Times|page=1|accessdate=November 13, 2010|ref=harv}}
* {{cite news|author=BBC News staff|year=2003|title = Sir Paul's fortune boosted|publisher=BBC|work=BBC News|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/showbiz/2974853.stm| accessdate=January 2, 2010|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|author=Blaney, John|year=2005|title=John Lennon: Listen to This Book|publisher=John Blaney|isbn=978-0-954-45281-0|ref=harv}}
* {{cite web|author=Buddy Holly Center staff|year=2014|url=http://www.mylubbock.us/departmental-websites/departments/buddy-holly-center/history|title=The Buddy Holly Center – History|work=The Buddy Holly Center|publisher=The City of Lubbock|accessdate=March 25, 2015|ref=harv|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150325191616/http://www.mylubbock.us/departmental-websites/departments/buddy-holly-center/history|archive-date=March 25, 2015|url-status=dead}}
* {{cite book|author1=Carr, Joseph |author2=Munde, Alan |title=Prairie Nights to Neon Lights: The Story of Country Music in West Texas|publisher=Texas Tech University Press|year=1997|isbn=978-0-89672-365-8 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|author=Clapton, Eric|year=2010|title=Eric Clapton: The Autobiography|publisher=Random House|isbn=978-1-409-06039-0|ref=harv}}
* {{cite news|author=Corbin, Sky|url=http://www.klll.com/pages/18144181.php?pid=395032|title=The Waylon Jennings Years at KLLL (Part Five)|work=KLLL|publisher=KLLL Lubbock|year=2014|ref=harv|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140714155659/http://www.klll.com/pages/18144181.php?pid=395032|archivedate=July 14, 2014}}
* {{cite web|author=Crenshaw, Marshall|year=2015|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/269448/Buddy-Holly|title=Buddy Holly (American Musician)|encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Britannica|publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.|accessdate=March 24, 2015|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|author=Crouse, Richard|title=Who Wrote The Book of Love?|publisher=Random House Digital|year=2012|isbn=978-0-385-67442-3|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|author=Dean, Maury|year=2003|title=Rock and Roll: Gold Rush|isbn= 978-0-875-86227-9|publisher=Algora Publishing|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|author=Deardorff II, Donald|year=2013|title=Bruce Springsteen: American Poet and Prophet|publisher=Scarecrow Press|isbn=978-0-810-88427-4|ref=harv|url=https://archive.org/details/brucespringsteen0000dear}}
* {{cite news|author=Duke, Alan|year=2011|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2011/SHOWBIZ/celebrity.news.gossip/09/08/buddy.holly.star/|title=Buddy Holly's Officially a Hollywood Star|work=CNN|publisher=Turner Broadcasting System, Inc|accessdate=March 24, 2015|ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal|author=Eder, Bruce|year=1996|journal=Goldmine|volume=22|number=14|title=Just One More Look at The Hollies|ref=harv}}
* {{cite web|author=Eder, Bruce|year=2015|url=http://www.allmusic.com/artist/buddy-holly-mn0000538677/biography|title=Buddy Holly – Biography|work=Allmusic|publisher=Rovi Corporation|accessdate=March 24, 2015|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|author=Eiss, Harry|year=2013|title=The Mythology of Dance|publisher=Cambridge Scholars Publishing|isbn=978-1-443-85288-3|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Everitt |first= Rich|title=Falling Stars: Air Crashes That Filled Rock and Roll Heaven|publisher=Harbor House|year=2004|isbn=978-1-891799-04-4|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|author=Fletcher, Tony|year=2012|title=The Clash: The Music That Matters|publisher=Music Sales Group|isbn=978-0-857-12749-5|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|author=Gaar, Gillian|year=2013|title=100 Things Beatles Fans Should Know &amp; Do Before They Die|publisher=Triunph Books|isbn=978-1-623-68202-6|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|author=Goldrosen, John|year=1979|title=The Buddy Holly Story|publisher=Quick Fox|isbn=978-0-825-63936-4|ref=harv|url=https://archive.org/details/buddyhollystoryj00gold}}
* {{cite book|author=Green, Stanley|year=1999|title=Hollywood Musicals Year by Year|publisher=Hal Leonard Corporation|isbn=978-0-634-00765-1|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|author=Gribbin, John|year=2012|title=Not Fade Away: The Life and Music of Buddy Holly|publisher=Icon Books|isbn=978-1-848-31384-2|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|author=Harris, Michael|year=2014|title=Always on Sunday: An Inside View of Ed Sullivan, the Beatles, Elvis, Sinatra &amp; Ed's Other Guests|publisher=Word International|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|author1=Henderson, Lol |author2=Stacey, Lee |year=2014|title=Encyclopedia of Music in the 20th Century|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-1-135-92946-6|ref=harv}}
* {{cite news|author=Hollywood Reporter Staff|year=1997|title=Highest Honor|url=https://www.newspapers.com/clip/2058669/|work=Hollywood News Reporter|publisher=The Index-Journal|via=Newspapers.com|accessdate=March 24, 2015|ref=harv}}{{open access}}
* {{cite book|author=Humphries, Patrick|year=2003|title=Elvis The #1 Hits: The Secret History of the Classics|publisher=Andrews McMeel Publishing|isbn=978-0-740-73803-6|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|author=Hunter, Dave|year=2013|title=The Fender Stratocaster: The Life &amp; Times of the World's Greatest Guitar &amp; Its Players|publisher=Voyageur Press|isbn=978-0-760-34484-2|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|author1=Jennings, Waylon|author2=Kaye, Lenny|title=Waylon: An Autobiography|publisher=Warner Books|year=1996|isbn=978-0-446-51865-9|ref=harv|url=https://archive.org/details/waylonautobiogra00jenn}}
* {{cite book|author=Jones, Steve|year=2014|title=Start You Up: Rock Star Secrets to Unleash Your Personal Brand and Set Your Career on Fire|publisher=Greenleaf Book Group|isbn=978-1-626-34070-1|ref=harv}}
* {{cite news|author=Kerns, William|year=2008|url=http://www.lubbockonline.com/stories/081508/loc_318846994.shtml|title=Buddy and Maria Elena Holly married 50 years ago|work=LubbockOnline.com|publisher=Lubbock Avalanche-Journal|ref=harv|accessdate=March 25, 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160323234441/http://lubbockonline.com/stories/081508/loc_318846994.shtml|archive-date=March 23, 2016|url-status=dead}}
* {{cite news|author=Kerns, William|year=2011|url=http://lubbockonline.com/entertainment/2011-05-09/buddy-and-maria-holly-plaza-dedication-attracts-large-turnoutn|title=Buddy and Maria Holly Plaza dedication attracts large turnout|work=Lubbock-Online.com|publisher=Lubbock Avalanche-Journal|accessdate=March 25, 2015|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|author=Laing, Dave|year=2010|title=Buddy Holly|publisher=Indiana University Press|isbn=978-0-253-22168-1|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|author=Lehmer, Larry|year=2003|title=The Day the Music Died: The Last Tour of Buddy Holly, the Big Bopper and Ritchie Valens|publisher=Music Sales Group|isbn= 978-0-825-67287-3|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|author1=Margotin, Phillipe |author2=Guesdon, Jean-Michael |year=2014|title=All The Songs: The Story Behind Every Beatles Release|publisher=Black Dog, Leventhal|isbn=978-1-603-76371-4|ref=harv}}
*{{cite news|author=McLean, Don|year=2015|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2015/03/05/opinions/mclean-buddy-holly-ntsb/|title=Don McLean: Buddy Holly, rest in peace|work=CNN|publisher=Turner, Inc|accessdate=March 26, 2015|ref=harv}}
*{{cite web|author=Mellecamp, John|year=2011|url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/lists/100-greatest-artists-of-all-time-19691231/buddy-holly-20110420|title=100 Greatest Artists|work=Rolling Stone|publisher=Wenner Media, LLC|accessdate=March 24, 2015|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|author=Meriwether, Nicholas|year=2013|title=Studying the Dead: The Grateful Dead Scholars Caucus, An Informal History|publisher=Scarecrow Press|isbn=978-0-810-89125-8|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|author=Moore, Gary|year=2011|title=Hey Buddy: In Pursuit of Buddy Holly, My New Buddy John, and My Lost Decade of Music|publisher=Savas Beatie|isbn=978-1-932-71497-5|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|author=Norman, Phillip|year=1996|title=Rave on: The Biography of Buddy Holly|publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster|isbn=978-0-684-80082-0|ref=harv|url=https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780684800820}}
*{{cite book|author=Norman, Philip|year=2011|title=Buddy: The Definitive Biography of Buddy Holly |publisher=Pan MacMillan|isbn=978-1-447-20340-7|ref=harv}}
*{{cite news|author=Norman, Phillip|title=Why Buddy Holly will never fade away|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/music/rockandjazzmusic/4402149/Why-Buddy-Holly-will-never-fade-away.html|date=February 3, 2015|accessdate=August 27, 2015|work=The Telegraph|publisher=Telegraph Media Group Limited|ref={{sfnref|Norman, Phillip|2015}}}}
*{{cite book|author1=Phillips, Mark |author2=Garcia, Frank |year=1996|title=Science Fiction Television Series: Episode Guides, Histories, and Casts and Credits for 62 Prime-Time Shows, 1959 through 1989|publisher=McFarland|isbn=978-1-476-61030-6|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|author=Riley, Tim|year=2011|title=Lennon: The Man, the Myth, the Music|publisher=Random House|isbn=978-1-448-11319-4|ref=harv}}
*{{cite web|author=Rock and Roll Hall of Fame staff|url=http://www.rockhall.com/inductees/buddy-holly/bio/|title=Buddy Holly Biography|work=Rock and Roll Hall of Fame|publisher=The Rock and Roll Hall of Fame and Museum, Inc|year=2015|accessdate=March 24, 2015|ref=harv}}
*{{cite web|author=Rolling Stone staff|year=2001|url=https://www.rollingstone.com/music/artists/buddy-holly/biography|title=Buddy Holly Biography|work=Rolling Stone|publisher=Wenner Media, LLC|accessdate=March 24, 2015|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|author=Scott Schinder, Andy Schwartz|year=2007|title=Icons of Rock: An Encyclopedia of the Legends Who Changed Music Forever|volume=1|publisher=Greenwood|isbn=978-0-313-33845-8|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|author=Shelton, Robert|year=2011|title=No Direction Home – The Life And Music of Bob Dylan|publisher=Omnibus Press|isbn=978-0-857-12616-0|ref=harv}}
*{{cite web|author=Songwriters hall of Fame staff|year=2002|url=http://www.songwritershalloffame.org/index.php/exhibits/bio/C118|title=Buddy Holly|work=Songwriters Hall of Fame|publisher=American National Academy of Popular Music|accessdate=March 24, 2015|ref=harv|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150402164041/http://www.songwritershalloffame.org/index.php/exhibits/bio/C118|archive-date=April 2, 2015|url-status=dead}}
*{{cite news|author=Suddath, Claire|year=2009|title=The Day the Music Died|url=http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1876542,00.html|work=TIME magazine|publisher=Time Inc.|accessdate=February 23, 2011|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|author1=Uslan, Michael|author2=Solomon, Bruce|year=1981|title=Dick Clark's the First 25 Years of Rock &amp; Roll|publisher=Dell Publishing Company|isbn=978-0-440-51763-4|ref=harv|url=https://archive.org/details/dickclarksfirst200usla}}
*{{cite news|author=Lloyd Webber, Julian|year=2015|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/music/rockandjazzmusic/4433239/Buddy-Hollys-heartbreak-songs.html|title=Buddy Holly's heartbreak songs|accessdate=May 11, 2015|work=The Telegraph|publisher=Telegraph Media Group Limited|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|author=Wishart, David|year=2004|title=Encyclopedia of the Great Plains|publisher=University of Nebraska Press|isbn=978-0-80-324787-1|ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* Bustard, Anne (2005). ''Buddy: The Story of Buddy Holly''. Simon &amp; Schuster. {{ISBN|978-1-4223-9302-4}}.
* Comentale, Edward P. (2013). Chapter Five. ''Sweet Air: Modernism, Regionalism, and American Popular Song''. University of Illinois Press. {{ISBN|978-0-252-07892-7}}.
* Dawson, Jim; Leigh, Spencer (1996). ''Memories of Buddy Holly''. Big Nickel Publications. {{ISBN|978-0-936433-20-2}}.
* Gerron, Peggy Sue (2008). ''Whatever Happened to Peggy Sue?''. Togi Entertainment. {{ISBN|978-0-9800085-0-0}}.
* Goldrosen, John; Beecher, John (1996). ''Remembering Buddy: The Definitive Biography''. New York: Da Capo Press. {{ISBN|0-306-80715-7}}.
* Goldrosen, John (1975). ''Buddy Holly: His Life and Music''. Popular Press. {{ISBN|0-85947-018-0}}
* Laing, Dave (1971–2010). ''Buddy Holly (Icons of Pop Music)''. Indiana University Press. {{ISBN|0-253-22168-4}}.
* Mann, Alan (1996). ''The A-Z of Buddy Holly''. Aurum Press (2nd edition). {{ISBN|1-85410-433-0}} or 978-1854104335.
* McFadden, Hugh (2005). ''Elegy for Charles Hardin Holley'', in ''Elegies &amp; Epiphanies''. Belfast: Lagan Press.
* Peer, Elizabeth and Ralph II (1972). ''Buddy Holly: A Biography in Words, Photographs and Music'' Australia: Peer International. ASIN B000W24DZO.
* Peters, Richard (1990). ''The Legend That Is Buddy Holly''. Barnes &amp; Noble Books. {{ISBN|0-285-63005-9}} or 978-0285630055.
* Rabin, Stanton (2009). ''OH BOY! The Life and Music of Rock 'n' Roll Pioneer Buddy Holly''. Van Winkle Publishing (Kindle). ASIN B0010QBLLG.
* Tobler, John (1979). ''The Buddy Holly Story''. Beaufort Books.
* VH1's Behind the Music &quot;The Day the Music Died&quot; interview with Waylon Jennings
{{refend}}

== External links ==
{{Wikiquote}}{{Wikipedia books|Buddy Holly}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20011019201015/http://www.buddyhollyarchives.com/ Buddy Holly news archives at the Lubbock Avalanche-Journal]
* {{IMDb name|0391398}}
* {{MusicBrainz artist|id=d352f5dd-3023-4565-a7bb-52396bf8821d|name=Buddy Holly}}
* [http://www.hankwilliamslistings.com/ind-bud.htm?= Buddy Holly – sessions and cover songs]

{{Buddy Holly}}
{{The Crickets}}
{{1986 Rock and Roll Hall of Fame}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Holly, Buddy}}
[[Category:Buddy Holly| ]]
[[Category:1936 births]]
[[Category:1959 deaths]]
[[Category:20th-century American singers]]
[[Category:Accidental deaths in Iowa]]
[[Category:American rock guitarists]]
[[Category:American rock singers]]
[[Category:American rockabilly musicians]]
[[Category:American people of Cherokee descent]]
[[Category:American people of English descent]]
[[Category:American people of Native American descent]]
[[Category:American people of Welsh descent]]
[[Category:Baptists from Texas]]
[[Category:Brunswick Records artists]]
[[Category:Coral Records artists]]
[[Category:Decca Records artists]]
[[Category:Grammy Lifetime Achievement Award winners]]
[[Category:Lubbock High School alumni]]
[[Category:People from Lubbock, Texas]]
[[Category:Rock and roll musicians]]
[[Category:Singers from Texas]]
[[Category:The Crickets members]]
[[Category:Victims of aviation accidents or incidents in the United States]]
[[Category:Lead guitarists]]
[[Category:American rockabilly guitarists]]
[[Category:American male guitarists]]
[[Category:American country rock singers]]
[[Category:American male singer-songwriters]]
[[Category:American country singer-songwriters]]
[[Category:Songwriters from Texas]]
[[Category:Guitarists from Texas]]
[[Category:20th-century American guitarists]]
[[Category:Victims of aviation accidents or incidents in 1959]]</text>
      <sha1>41xpsagddnkxc7vrif06kdwz217kwln</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
