  <page>
    <title>Book of Micah</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4452</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941182131</id>
      <parentid>941182084</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-17T02:23:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bruce Lee's Relative Chin</username>
        <id>32582020</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/203.144.22.65|203.144.22.65]] ([[User talk:203.144.22.65|talk]]) ([[WP:HG|HG]]) (3.4.9)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Tanakh OT|Nevi'im|prophetic}}

The '''Book of Micah''' is the sixth of the [[Twelve Minor Prophets|twelve minor prophets]] in the [[Hebrew Bible]]{{\}}[[Old Testament]].&lt;ref&gt;Ben Zvi (2000), p.4&lt;/ref&gt; Ostensibly, it records the sayings of [[Micah (prophet)|Micah]], whose name is ''Mikayahu'' ({{lang-he-n|מִיכָיָ֫הוּ}}), meaning &quot;Who is like Yahweh?&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Mays (1976), p.1&lt;/ref&gt; an 8th-century BC prophet from the village of [[Moresheth-Gath|Moresheth]] in [[kingdom of Judah|Judah]] (Hebrew name from the opening verse: מיכה המרשתי).&lt;ref&gt;Limburg (1988), p.160&lt;/ref&gt;

The book has three major divisions, chapters 1–2, 3–5 and 6–7, each introduced by the word &quot;Hear,&quot; with a pattern of alternating announcements of doom and expressions of hope within each division.&lt;ref&gt;Limburg (1988), p.159&lt;/ref&gt; Micah reproaches unjust leaders, defends the rights of the poor against the [[plutocracy|rich and powerful]];&lt;ref&gt;King (1988), pp.27–28&lt;/ref&gt; while looking forward to a world at peace centered on [[Zion]] under the leadership of a new [[David]]ic monarch.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sweeney 2000, pp.341-342&quot;&gt;Sweeney (2000), pp.341–342&lt;/ref&gt;

While the book is relatively short, it includes [[lament]] (1.8–16; 7.8–10), [[theophany]] (1.3–4), hymnic prayer of petition and confidence (7.14–20),&lt;ref&gt;Coogan (2009), p.284&lt;/ref&gt; and the &quot;covenant lawsuit&quot; (6.1–8), a distinct genre in which [[Yahweh]] (God) sues Israel for breach of contract of the [[Mosaic covenant]].&lt;ref&gt;Coogan (2009), p.265&lt;/ref&gt;

==Setting==
[[File:Sennacherib sling.jpg|thumb|right|250px|[[Assyrian people|Assyrian]] warriors armed with slings from the palace of Sennacherib, 7th century BCE]]
{{See also|Nevi'im|Prophets in Judaism}}
Chapter 1:1&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleref2|Micah|1:1}}&lt;/ref&gt; identifies the prophet as &quot;Micah of Moresheth&quot; (a town in southern Judah), and states that he lived during the reigns of [[Jotham of Judah|Yehotam]], [[Ahaz]] and [[Hezekiah]], roughly 750–700&amp;nbsp;BC.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rogerson 2003, p.703&quot;/&gt;

This corresponds to the period when, after a long period of peace, Israel, Judah, and the other nations of the region came under increasing pressure from the aggressive and rapidly expanding [[Neo-Assyrian empire]]. Between 734 and 727 [[Tiglath-Pileser III]] of Assyria conducted almost annual campaigns in [[Palestine (region)|Palestine]], reducing the [[Kingdom of Israel (Samaria)|Kingdom of Israel]], the [[Kingdom of Judah]] and the [[Philistines|Philistine]] cities to [[vassal]]age, receiving [[tribute]] from [[Ammon]], [[Moab]] and [[Edom]], and absorbing Damascus (the Kingdom of [[Aram-Damascus|Aram]]) into the Empire.&lt;ref&gt;King (1988), pp.31–33&lt;/ref&gt; On Tiglath-Pileser's death Israel rebelled, resulting in an Assyrian counter-attack and the [[Kingdom of Israel (Samaria)#Destruction of the_kingdom|destruction of the capital]], [[Samaria (ancient city)|Samaria]], in 721 after a three-year siege.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rogerson 2003, p.703&quot;/&gt; Micah 1:2–7 draws on this event: Samaria, says the prophet, has been destroyed by God because of its crimes of idolatry, oppression of the poor, and misuse of power.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rogerson 2003, p.703&quot;/&gt; The Assyrian attacks on Israel (the northern kingdom) led to an influx of refugees into Judah, which would have increased social stresses, while at the same time the authorities in Jerusalem had to invest huge amounts in tribute and defense.&lt;ref name=&quot;King 1988, p.27&quot;/&gt;

When the Assyrians attacked Judah in 701 they did so via the Philistine coast and the [[Shfela|Shephelah]], the border region which included Micah's village of Moresheth, as well as [[Lachish]], Judah's second largest city. This in turn forms the background to verses 1:8–16, in which Micah warns the towns of the coming disaster (Lachish is singled out for special mention, accused of the corrupt practices of both Samaria and Jerusalem). In verses 2:1–5 he denounces the appropriation of land and houses, which might simply be the greed of the wealthy and powerful, or possibly the result of the militarising of the area in preparation for the Assyrian attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rogerson704&quot;/&gt;

==Composition==
{{See|Babylonian captivity|Postdiction}}
Some, but not all, scholars accept that only chapters 1–3 contain material from the late 8th century prophet Micah.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rogerson 2003, p.703&quot;/&gt; The latest material comes from the [[Second Temple period|post-Exilic period]] after the [[Second Temple|Temple]] was rebuilt in 515&amp;nbsp;BC, so that the early 5th century BC seems to be the period when the book was completed.&lt;ref&gt;Mays (1976), p.21&lt;/ref&gt; The first stage was the collection and arrangement of some spoken sayings of the historical Micah (the material in chapters 1–3), in which the prophet attacks those who build estates through oppression and depicts the Assyrian invasion of Judah as Yahweh's punishment on the kingdom's corrupt rulers, including a prophecy that the Temple will be destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;Mays (1976), p.23&lt;/ref&gt;

The prophecy was not fulfilled in Micah's time, but a hundred years later when Judah was facing a similar crisis with the [[Neo-Babylonian Empire]], Micah's prophecies were reworked and expanded to reflect the new situation.&lt;ref&gt;Mays (1976), pp.24–25&lt;/ref&gt; Still later, after Jerusalem did [[Siege of Jerusalem (587 BC)|fall to the Neo-Babylonian Empire]], the book was revised and expanded further to reflect the circumstances of the late exilic and post-exilic community.&lt;ref&gt;Mays (1976), p.30&lt;/ref&gt;

== Content ==
[[File:JudeanImpalement Roaf185.jpg|thumb|250px|Impalement of [[Judea]]ns by Assyrian soldiers ([[Assyria|Neo-Assyrian]] relief)]]

===Structure===
At the broadest level, Micah can be divided into three roughly equal parts:&lt;ref name=&quot;King 1988, p.27&quot;&gt;King (1988), p.27&lt;/ref&gt;
* Judgment against the nations and their leaders 
* Restoration of Zion (chapters 4–5, probably exilic and post-exilic, together with the next section);&lt;ref name=&quot;Rogerson 2003, p.703&quot;&gt;Rogerson (2003), p.703&lt;/ref&gt;
* God's lawsuit against Israel and expression of hope (chapters 6–7).

Within this broad three-part structure are a series of alternating oracles of judgment and promises of restoration:&lt;ref&gt;Coogan (2009)&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1.1 Superscription
* 1.2–2.11 Oracles of judgment
* 2.12–13 Oracles of restoration
* 3.1–12 Oracles of judgment
* 4.1–5.15 Oracles of restoration
* 6.1–7.6 Oracles of judgment
* 7.7–20 Oracles of restoration

===Subsections===
* '''The Heading ([[Isaiah 1#Verse 1|1:1]])''': As is typical of prophetic books, an anonymous editor has supplied the name of the prophet, an indication of his time of activity, and an identification of his speech as the &quot;word of Yahweh&quot;, a generic term carrying a claim to prophetic legitimacy and authority.&lt;ref&gt;Ben Zvi (2000), p.13&lt;/ref&gt; Samaria and Jerusalem are given prominence as the foci of the prophet's attention.&lt;ref&gt;Sweeney (2000), p.343&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Judgment against Samaria (1:2–7):''' Drawing upon ancient traditions for depicting a theophany, the prophet depicts the coming of Yahweh to punish the city, whose sins are idolatry and the abuse of the poor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rogerson 2003, p.703&quot; /&gt;
* '''Warnings to the cities of Judah (1:8–16):''' Samaria has fallen, Judah is next. Micah describes the destruction of the lesser towns of Judah (referring to the invasion of Judah by Sennacherib, 701&amp;nbsp;BC). For these passages of doom on the various cities, [[Pun|paronomasia]] is used. Paronomasia is a [[List of narrative techniques|literary device]] which 'plays' on the sound of each word for literary effect. For example, the inhabitants of Beth-le-aphrah (&quot;house of dust&quot;) are told to &quot;roll yourselves in the dust.&quot; 1:14. Though most of the Paronomasia is lost in translation, it is the equivalent of 'Ashdod shall be but ashes,' where the fate of the city matches its name.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rogerson704&quot;/&gt;
* '''Misuse of power denounced (2:1–5)''': Denounces those who appropriate the land and houses of others. The context may be simply the amassing wealth for its own sake, or could be connected with the militarisation of the region for the expected Assyrian attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rogerson704&quot;&gt;Rogerson (2003), p.704&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Threats against the prophet (2:6–11)''': The prophet is warned not to prophesy. He answers that the rulers are harming God's people, and want to listen only to those who advocate the virtues of wine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rogerson704&quot;/&gt;
* '''A later promise (2:12–13):''' These verses assume that judgement has already fallen and Israel is already scattered abroad.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rogerson704&quot;/&gt;
* '''Judgment on wicked Zion (3:1–4):''' Israel's rulers are accused of gaining more wealth at the expense of the poor, by any means. The metaphor of flesh being torn illustrates the length to which the ruling classes and socialites would go to further increase their wealth. Prophets are corrupt, seeking personal gain. Jerusalem's rulers believe that God will always be with them, but God will be with his people, and Jerusalem will be destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;Rogerson (2003), pp.704–705&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Zion's future hope (4:1–5)''' This is a later passage, almost identical with Isaiah 2:2–4. Zion (meaning the Temple) will be rebuilt, but by God, and based not on violence and [[corruption]] but on the desire to learn God's laws, [[swords to ploughshares#Biblical references|beat swords to ploughshares]] and live in peace.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rogerson705&quot;&gt;Rogerson (2003), p.705&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Further promises to Zion (4:6–7)''' This is another later passage, promising Zion that she will once more enjoy her former independence and power.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rogerson705&quot;/&gt;
* '''Deliverance from Distress in Babylon (4:9–5:1)''' The similarities to Isaiah 41:15–16 and the references to Babylon suggest the period of this material, although it is unclear whether a period during or after the siege of 586 is meant. Despite their trials, God will not desert his people.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rogerson705&quot;/&gt;
* '''The promised ruler from Bethlehem (5:1–14):''' This passage is usually dated to the exile.&lt;ref&gt;Rogerson (2003), pp.705–706&lt;/ref&gt; Although chapters 4:9–10 have said that there is &quot;no king in Zion&quot;, these chapters predict the coming Messiah will emerge from Bethlehem, the traditional home of the Davidic monarchy, to restore Israel. Assyria will be stricken, and Israel's punishment will lead to the punishment of the nations.&lt;ref&gt;Sweeney (2000), p.387&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''A Covenant lawsuit (6:1–5):''' Yahweh accuses Israel (the people of Judah) of breaking the covenant through their lack of justice and honesty, after the pattern of the kings of Israel (northern kingdom).&lt;ref&gt;Sweeney (2000), p.395&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Torah Liturgy (6:6–8):''' Micah speaks on behalf of the community asking what they should do in order to get back on God's good side. Micah then responds by saying that God requires only &quot;to do justice, and to love [[mercy]], and to walk humbly with your God.&quot; Thus declaring that the burnt offering of both animals and humans (which may have been practiced in Judah under Kings [[Ahaziah of Judah|Ahaz]] and [[Manasseh of Judah|Manasseh]]) is not necessary for God.&lt;ref&gt;King (2006), pp.1246–1247&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''The City as a Cheat (6:9–16):''' The city is reprimanded for its dishonest trade practices.
* '''Lament (7:1–7):''' The first passage in the book in the first person: whether it comes from Micah himself is disputed. Honesty and decency have vanished, families are filled with strife.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rogerson707&quot;&gt;Rogerson (2003), p.707&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''A song of fallen Jerusalem (7:8–10):''' The first person voice continues, but now it is the city who speaks. She recognises that her destruction is deserved punishment from God. The recognition gives grounds for hope that God is still with her.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rogerson707&quot;/&gt;
* '''A prophecy of restoration (7:11–13):''' Fallen Jerusalem is promised that she will be rebuilt and that her power will be greater than ever (a contrast with the vision of peace in 4:1–5).&lt;ref name=&quot;Rogerson707&quot;/&gt;
* '''A prayer for future prosperity (7:14–17):''' The mood switches from a request for power to grateful astonishment at God's mercy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rogerson707&quot;/&gt;

== Themes ==
Micah addresses the future of Judah/Israel after the Babylonian exile. Like [[book of Isaiah|Isaiah]], the book has a vision of the punishment of Israel and creation of a &quot;[[Remnant (Bible)#Hebrew Bible|remnant]]&quot;, followed by world peace centered on Zion under the leadership of a new Davidic monarch; the people should do justice, turn to Yahweh, and await the end of their punishment. However, whereas Isaiah sees Jacob/Israel joining &quot;the nations&quot; under Yahweh's rule, Micah looks forward to Israel ruling over the nations. Insofar as Micah appears to draw on and rework parts of Isaiah, it seems designed at least partly to provide a counterpoint to that book.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sweeney 2000, pp.341-342&quot;/&gt;

==Quotations in the New Testament==
In the [[New Testament]], the [[Book of Matthew]] quotes from the Book of Micah in relation to Jesus being born in [[Bethlehem]]:
{{quote|And they said unto him, In Bethlehem of Judæa: for thus it is written by the prophet, And thou Bethlehem, in the land of Juda, art not the least among the princes of Juda: for out of thee shall come a Governor, that shall rule my people Israel.|{{bibleverse||Matthew|2:5-6|KJV}}}}

:{{quote|But thou, Bethlehem Ephratah, though thou be little among the thousands of Judah, yet out of thee shall he come forth unto me that is to be ruler in Israel; whose goings forth have been from of old, from everlasting.|{{bibleverse||Micah|5:2|KJV}}}}

Jesus quotes Micah when he warns that families will be divided by the gospel:
{{quote|A man’s enemies will be those of his own household.|{{bibleverse||Matthew|10:36|KJV}}}}

:{{quote|For the son dishonoureth the father, the daughter riseth up against her mother, the daughter in law against her mother in law; a man's enemies are the men of his own house.|{{bibleverse||Micah|7:6|KJV}}}}

== See also ==
* [[Zion]]

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== Bibliography ==
* {{Cite book|last=Allen|first=Leslie C|title=The Books of Joel, Obadiah, Jonah, and Micah|publisher=Eerdmans|year=1976|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wwTKrlvr3c0C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Micah#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|isbn=9780802825315}}
* {{Cite book|last= Ben Zvi|first=Ehud|title=Micah|publisher=Eerdmans|year=2000|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=PlO0kMRUuB0C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Micah#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|isbn= 9780802845993}}
* {{Cite book|last=Coogan|first=Michael|title=A Brief Introduction to the Old Testament|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2009}}
* {{Cite book|last=Grigg|first=Donald L|title=The Bible from Scratch: The Old Testament for Beginners|publisher=Eerdmans|year=2006|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=TUAykz2hS10C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=The+Bible+from+Scratch:+The+Old+Testament+for+Beginners#v=onepage&amp;q=The%20Bible%20from%20Scratch%3A%20The%20Old%20Testament%20for%20Beginners&amp;f=false|isbn=9780664225773}}
* {{Cite book|last=King|first=Phillip J|title=HarperCollins Study Bible: Micah|publisher=Harper Collins Publishers|year=2006}}
* {{Cite book|last=King|first=Philip J|title=Amos, Hosea, Micah: an archaeological commentary|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|year=1988|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=HS5Z4k7RiUkC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Micah#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|isbn=9780664240776}}
* {{Cite book|last=Limburg|first=James|title=Hosea-Micah|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|year=1988|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DAbUFlJdSgEC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Micah#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|isbn=9780664237578}}
* {{Cite book|last=Mays|first=James L|author-link=James Luther Mays|title=Micah|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|year=1976|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=1iDaeovh1IoC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Micah#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|isbn=9780664208172}}
* {{Cite book|last=Rogerson|first=John W|chapter=Micah|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2Vo-11umIZQC&amp;pg=PA703&amp;dq=Micah+John+W.+Rogerson#v=onepage&amp;q=Micah%20John%20W.%20Rogerson&amp;f=false|editor=James D. G. Dunn, John William Rogerson|title=Eerdmans Bible Commentary|publisher=Eerdmans|year=2003|isbn=9780802837110}}
* {{Cite book|last=Sweeney|first=Marvin A|title=The Twelve Prophets|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=R7HaijsNACAC&amp;pg=PA339&amp;dq=Micah+overview+micah+is+the+sixth+book#v=onepage&amp;q=Micah%20overview%20micah%20is%20the%20sixth%20book&amp;f=false|publisher=Liturgical Press|year=2000|isbn=9780814650912}}

== Further reading ==
* &quot;Book of Micah.&quot; The Anchor Bible Dictionary. Vol. 4, Editor-in-Chief: Freedman, David N. Doubleday; New York, NY. 1992.
* &quot;Book of Micah.&quot; International Standard Bible Encyclopedia. General Editor: Bromley, G.W. William B. Erdmans Publishing Co.; Grand Rapids, MI. 1986.
* [http://www.vts.edu/ftpimages/95/download/download_group10629_id317189.pdf “ Book of Micah”] Forward Movement Publications, Cincinnati, Ohio, 2007
* Holy Bible: The New Oxford Annotated Bible. Coogan; Oxford University Press, 2007.
* LaSor, William Sanford et al. ''Old Testament Survey: the Message, Form, and Background of the Old Testament''. Grand Rapids: William B. Eerdmans, 1996.
* Hailey, Homer. (1973). A Commentary on the Minor Prophets. Grand Rapids: Baker Book House.
* Maxey, Al. THE MINOR PROPHETS: Micah. (n.d.). 20 Paragraphs. Retrieved October 4, 2005, from http://www.zianet.com/maxey/Proph11.htm
* McKeating, Henry Engel. (1971). The Books of AMOS, HOSEA, AND MICAH. New York: the Syndics of the Cambridge University Press.
* Pusey, E. B. (1963). The Minor Prophets: A Commentary (Vol. II). Grand Rapids: Baker Book House.
* Wood, Joyce Rilett. (2000). Speech and action in Micah's prophecy. [[Catholic Biblical Quarterly]], no. 4(62), 49 paragraphs. Retrieved September 30, 2005, from OCLC (FirstSearch) database http://newfirstsearch.oclc.org

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Book of Micah}}
{{Wikisource|Micah (Bible)|Micah}}
{{wikiquote}}
* Jewish translations:
** [http://www.chabad.org/library/archive/LibraryArchive2.asp?AID=15763 Michah – Micah (Judaica Press)] translation [with [[Rashi]]'s commentary] at Chabad.org
* Christian translations:
** [http://www.gospelhall.org/bible/bible.php?passage=Micah+1 ''Online Bible'' at GospelHall.org] (ESV, KJV, Darby, American Standard Version, Bible in Basic English)
** [http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?book_id=40&amp;version=31 BibleGateway.com] (New International Version)
** [https://web.archive.org/web/20050204033155/http://www.anova.org/sev/htm/hb/33_micah.htm Micah at The Great Books] (New Revised Standard Version)
* {{librivox book | title=Micah}} Various versions

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou | [[Minor prophet]]s|||}}
{{S-bef| before= [[Book of Jonah|Jonah]] | rows = 2 }}
{{S-ttl| title  = [[Tanakh|Hebrew Bible]] }}
{{s-aft | after= [[Book of Nahum|Nahum]] | rows = 2 }}
{{s-ttl | title = [[Christianity|Christian]]&lt;br&gt;[[Old Testament]] }}
{{s-end}}

{{Book of Micah}}
{{Books of the Bible}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Micah}}
[[Category:Book of Micah| ]]
[[Category:8th-century BC books]]
[[Category:5th-century BC books]]
[[Category:Twelve Minor Prophets]]</text>
      <sha1>r8eesgjyxfxo0jl5p1oath0txa4tgh1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
