  <page>
    <title>Book of Haggai</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4454</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942797405</id>
      <parentid>942687153</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-26T22:12:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JohnThorne</username>
        <id>15160288</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/65.129.9.94|65.129.9.94]] ([[User talk:65.129.9.94|talk]]): Unsourced change ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{redirect |Hag.|rabbinic text Ḥag.|Hagigah}}
{{Tanakh OT|Nevi'im|prophetic}}

The '''Book of Haggai''', also known as the '''Book of Aggeus''', is a book of the [[Hebrew Bible]] or [[Tanakh]], and has its place as the third-to-last of the [[Twelve Minor Prophets|Minor Prophets]]. It is a short book, consisting of only two chapters. The historical setting dates around 520&amp;nbsp;BCE before the Temple has been rebuilt.&lt;ref&gt;Coogan, Michael D. &quot;A Brief Introduction to the Old Testament.&quot; Oxford University Press, 2009. o. 346.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Authorship ==

The Book of Haggai is named after its presumed author, the prophet [[Haggai]]. There is no biographical information given about the prophet in the Book of Haggai.  Haggai's name is derived from the Hebrew verbal root ''hgg'', which means &quot;to make a pilgrimage.&quot;  W. Sibley Towner suggests that Haggai's name might come &quot;from his single-minded effort to bring about the reconstruction of that destination of ancient Judean pilgrims, the [[Temple in Jerusalem]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Towner, W. Sibley. ''The Harper Collins Study Bible''. HarperCollins Publishers. 2006. p. 1265.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Date ==

The ''Book of Haggai'' was written in 520&amp;nbsp;BCE, some 18 years after [[Cyrus the Great|Cyrus]] had conquered [[Babylon]] and issued a decree in 538&amp;nbsp;BCE, allowing the captive Jews to return to Judea. Cyrus saw the restoration of the temple as necessary for the restoration of the religious practices, and a sense of peoplehood, after a long exile.{{citation needed|date=May 2014}}

== Synopsis ==

Haggai's message is filled with an urgency for the people to proceed with the rebuilding of the [[Second Temple|second Jerusalem temple]]. Haggai attributes a recent drought to the people's refusal to rebuild the temple, which he sees as key to [[Jerusalem]]’s glory.  The book ends with the prediction of the downfall of kingdoms, with one [[Zerubbabel]], governor of [[Kingdom of Judah|Judah]], as the Lord’s chosen leader. The language here is not as finely wrought as in some other books of the [[minor prophets]],{{citation needed|date=May 2014}} yet the intent seems straightforward.

The first chapter contains the first address (2–11) and its effects (12–15).

The second chapter contains:
#The second prophecy (1–9), which was delivered a month after the first
#The third prophecy (10–19), delivered two months and three days after the second; and
#The fourth prophecy (20–23), delivered on the same day as the third

These discourses are referred to in [[Book of Ezra|Ezra]] 5:1 and 6:14. (Compare Haggai 2:7, 8 and 22)

Haggai reports that three weeks after his first prophecy, the rebuilding of the Temple began on September 7 521&amp;nbsp;BCE. &quot;They came and began to work on the house of the LORD Almighty, their God, on the twenty-fourth day of the sixth month in the second year of Darius the King.(Haggai 1:14–15) and the Book of Ezra indicates that it was finished on February 25 516&amp;nbsp;BCE &quot;The Temple was completed on the third day of the month Adar, in the sixth year of the reign of King Darius.&quot; (Ezra 6:15)

== Outline ==
[[File:CodexGigas 116 MinorProphets.jpg|thumb|First page of the Book of Haggai, [[Codex Gigas]] ([[Latin]] translation, early 13th century)]]
#Divine Announcement: The Command to Rebuild the Temple  ({{Bibleref2-nb|Haggai|1.1–15}} )
##Introduction: Reluctant Rebuilders  ({{Bibleref2-nb|Haggai|1.1–2}} )
##Consider your ways: fruitless prosperity ({{Bibleref2-nb|Haggai|1.3–12}} )
##Promise and Progress  ({{Bibleref2-nb|Haggai|1.13–15}} )
#Divine Announcement: The Coming Glory of the Temple  ({{Bibleref2-nb|Haggai|2.1–2.9}} )
##God will fulfill his promise ({{Bibleref2-nb|Haggai|2:1–5}} ) &lt;ref name=&quot;Achtemeier, Paul J. 1996&quot;&gt;Achtemeier, Paul J., and Roger S. Boraas. The HarperCollins Bible Dictionary. San Francisco, CA: HarperSanFrancisco, 1996. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;
##Future Splendor of the temple ({{Bibleref2-nb|Haggai|2:6–9}} )&lt;ref name=&quot;Achtemeier, Paul J. 1996&quot;/&gt;
#Divine Announcement: Blessings for a Defiled People  ({{Bibleref2-nb|Haggai|2.10–19}} )
##Former Misery ({{Bibleref2-nb|Haggai|2.10–17}} )&lt;ref name=&quot;Achtemeier, Paul J. 1996&quot;/&gt;
##Future Blessing ({{Bibleref2-nb|Haggai|2.18–19}} )&lt;ref name=&quot;Achtemeier, Paul J. 1996&quot;/&gt;
#Divine Announcement: Zerubbabel Chosen as a Signet  ({{Bibleref2-nb|Haggai|2.20–23}} )

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Wikisource|Haggai (Bible)|Haggai}}
*[[Judaism|Jewish]] translations:
** [http://www.chabad.org/article.asp?AID=15767 Chaggai – Haggai (Judaica Press)] translation with [[Rashi]]'s commentary at [[Chabad.org]]
*[[Christianity|Christian]] translations:
**[http://www.gospelhall.org/bible/bible.php?passage=Haggai+1 ''Online Bible'' at GospelHall.org] (ESV, KJV, Darby, American Standard Version, Bible in Basic English)
* {{librivox book | title=Haggai}} Various versions

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou | [[Minor prophet]]s|||}}
{{s-bef | before= [[Book of Zephaniah|Zephaniah]] | rows = 2 }}
{{s-ttl | title  = [[Tanakh|Hebrew Bible]] }}
{{s-aft | after= [[Book of Zechariah|Zechariah]] | rows = 2 }}
{{s-ttl | title = [[Christianity|Christian]]&lt;br&gt;[[Old Testament]] }}
{{s-end}}
{{Book of Haggai}}
{{Books of the Bible}}
{{Authority control}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Haggai}}
[[Category:6th-century BC books]]
[[Category:Twelve Minor Prophets]]
[[Category:Book of Haggai| ]]</text>
      <sha1>5065a1rapmaecoue74zmzbrzrqfyukd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
