  <page>
    <title>Backward compatibility</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4459</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939263209</id>
      <parentid>939262457</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-05T10:42:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tea2min</username>
        <id>36029</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 939262457 by [[Special:Contributions/89.242.11.4|89.242.11.4]] ([[User talk:89.242.11.4|talk]]): While &quot;backwards compatibility&quot; is common, too (and [[backwards compatibility]] is a redirect here to [[backward compatibility]]), this article consistently uses &quot;backward compatibility&quot;.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[File:Wii-gamecube-compatibility.jpg|thumb|The original model of the [[Wii]] video game console, which usually uses wireless controllers, is also backwardly compatible with [[GameCube controller|those from Nintendo's earlier GameCube console]], along with said system's games.]]

'''Backward compatibility''' is a property of a system, product, or technology that allows for [[interoperability]] with an older [[legacy system]], or with [[Input/output|input]] designed for such a system, especially in [[telecommunications]] and [[computing]]. Backward compatibility is sometimes also called '''downward compatibility'''.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=The Telecommunications Illustrated Dictionary|author=J.K. Petersen|date=2002|edition=Second|publisher=CRC Press|isbn=9781420040678}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Modifying a system in a way that does not allow backward compatibility is sometimes called &quot;[[wikt:breaking change|breaking]]&quot; backward compatibility.&lt;ref name=&quot;Belleflamme&quot;&gt;{{citation|title=Industrial Organization: Markets and Strategies|author1=Paul Belleflamme|author2=Martin Peitz|date=2010|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=9780521862998|chapter=Strategies in standard wars}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A complementary concept is [[forward compatibility]]. A design that is forward-compatible usually has a [[Technology roadmap|roadmap]] for compatibility with future standards and products.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zeldman&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Designing with Web Standards|author=Jeffrey Zeldman|year=2006|publisher=Peachpit Press|isbn=0-321-38555-1|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZCPWYFoWaMIC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=compatibility&amp;hl=sv|pp=15–16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Computer programming|programming]] jargon, the concept is sometimes referred to as '''hysterical reasons''' or '''hysterical raisins''', homophones for &quot;historical reasons&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://foldoc.org/hysterical+reasons|title=hysterical reasons|last=|first=|date=|publisher=[[FOLDOC]]|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2019-06-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://catb.org/jargon/html/H/hysterical-reasons.html|title=hysterical reasons|last=Raymond|first=Eric  S.|authorlink=Eric S. Raymond|date=29 Dec 2003|website=catb.org|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2019-06-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc8279/ballot/|title=RFC 8279: Multicast Using Bit Index Explicit Replication|last=Kumari|first=Warren|date=2017-07-05|website=datatracker.ietf.org|publisher=[[IETF]]|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2019-06-25|quote=Warren Kumari (Google): &quot;discuss comment below for hysterical raisins&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Benefits==
There are several incentives for a company to implement backward compatibility. Backward compatibility can be used to preserve older software that would have otherwise been lost when a manufacturer decides to stop supporting older hardware. Classic video games are a common example used when discussing the value of supporting older software. The cultural impact of video games is a large part of their continued success, and some believe ignoring backward compatibility would cause these titles to disappear.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.popmatters.com/192068-backwards-compatibility-is-the-only-way-forward-2495543836.html|title=Backwards Compatibility is the Only Way Forward|date=2015-04-10|website=PopMatters|language=en|access-date=2019-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Backward compatibility also acts as an additional selling point for new hardware, as an existing player base can more affordably [[upgrade]] to subsequent generations of a console. This also helps to make up for a lack of content in the early launch of new systems, as users can pull from the previous console's large library of games while developers slowly transition to the new hardware.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://techconnectmagazine.com/what-is-backwards-compatibility/|title=Understanding backwards compatibility and how it benefits gamers|date=2018-08-14|website=Tech Magazine|language=en-US|access-date=2019-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

One example of this is the Sony [[PlayStation 2]] (PS2) which was backward compatible with games for its predecessor [[PlayStation (console)|PlayStation]] (PS1). While the selection of PS2 games available at launch was small, sales of the console were nonetheless strong in 2000-2001 thanks to the large library of games for the preceding PS1. This bought time for the PS2 to grow a large installed base and developers to release more quality PS2 games for the crucial 2001 holiday season.{{Citation needed|date=March 2018}}

Additionally, and despite not being included at launch, Microsoft slowly incorporated backward compatibility for select titles on the Xbox One several years into its product life cycle.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.androidcentral.com/playstation-5-set-be-backward-compatible-remasters-wont-be-necessary|title=Remasters aren't needed if the PS5 is completely backward compatible|date=2019-09-24|website=Android Central|language=en|access-date=2019-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Players have racked up over a billion hours with backward compatible games, and it is rumored that next generation console like the PlayStation 5 will also support this feature.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt; A large part of the success and implementation of this feature is that the hardware within newer generation consoles is both powerful and similar enough to legacy systems that older titles can be broken down and re-configured to run on the Xbox One.&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.eurogamer.net/articles/digitalfoundry-2017-xbox-one-x-back-compat-how-does-it-actually-work|title=Xbox One backwards compatibility: how does it actually work?|last=Leadbetter|first=Richard|date=2017-12-09|website=Eurogamer|language=en|access-date=2019-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; The backward compatibility program not only supports the previous generation Xbox 360, but also titles from the original Xbox system.&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot; /&gt; Some titles are even given slight visual improvements and additional levels at no cost to the user. This program has proven incredibly popular with Xbox players and goes against the recent trend of studio made remasters of classic titles, creating what some believe to be an important shift in console maker's strategies.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt;

==Costs==
{{More citations needed section|date=January 2019}}
The literal costs of supporting old software is considered a large drawback to the usage of backward compatibility.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt; The associated costs of backward compatibility are a higher [[bill of materials]] if hardware is required to support the legacy systems; increased complexity of the product that may lead to longer [[time to market]], technological hindrances, and slowing innovation; and increased expectations from users in terms of compatibility.&lt;ref name=&quot;Belleflamme&quot; /&gt; Because of this, several gaming consoles chose to phase out backward compatibility toward the end of the console generation in order to reduce cost and briefly re-invigorate sales before the arrival of newer hardware.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.cnet.com/news/game-consoles-and-the-death-of-backward-compatibility-why-we-dont-care/|title=Game consoles and the death of backward-compatibility: Why we don't care|last=Stein|first=Scott|website=CNET|language=en|access-date=2019-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

A notable example is the Sony [[PlayStation 3]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.theregister.co.uk/2006/11/16/isuppli_prices_up_ps3/|title=Sony PS3 'costs at least $805-840' to make|last=tweet_btn()|first=Tony Smith 16 Nov 2006 at 12:00|website=www.theregister.co.uk|language=en|access-date=2019-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; as the first PS3 iteration was expensive to manufacture in part due to including the [[Emotion Engine]] from the preceding PS2 in order to run PS2 games,&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.wired.com/2007/02/sony-confirms-b/|title=Sony Confirms Backwards Compatibility Dumped to Lower Costs|last=Arendt|first=Susan|date=2007-02-26|work=Wired|access-date=2019-03-08|issn=1059-1028}}&lt;/ref&gt; since the PS3 architecture was completely different from the PS2. Subsequent PS3 hardware revisions have eliminated the Emotion Engine as it saved production costs while removing the ability to run PS2 titles,&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; as Sony found out that backward compatibility was not a major selling point for the PS3 in contrast to the PS2.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; The PS3's chief competitor, the Microsoft [[Xbox 360]], took a different approach to backward compatibility by using software emulation in order to run games from the first [[Xbox (console)|Xbox]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130401060443/http://news.teamxbox.com/xbox/8357/MS-Engineer-Speaks-on-Xbox-360-Backward-Compatibility/|title=MS Engineer Speaks on Xbox 360 Backward Compatibility - Xbox|date=2013-04-01|website=web.archive.org|access-date=2019-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; rather than including legacy hardware from the original Xbox which was quite different from the Xbox 360, however Microsoft stopped releasing emulation profiles after 2007.{{Citation needed|date=April 2018}}

However, with the current decline in physical game sales and the rise of digital storefronts and downloads, some believe backwards compatibility will soon be as obsolete as the phased-out consoles it supports.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt; Many game studios are re-mastering and re-releasing their most popular titles by improving the quality of graphics and adding new content. These remasters have found success by appealing both to nostalgic players who remember enjoying the original versions when they were younger, and to newcomers who may not have had the original system it was released on. For most consumers, digital remasters are more appealing than hanging on to bulky cartridges and obsolete hardware. For the manufacturers of consoles, digital re-releases of classic titles are a large benefit. It not only removes the financial drawbacks of supporting older hardware, but also shifts all of the costs of updating software to the developers. The manufacturer gets a new addition to their system with strong name recognition, and the studio does not have to completely develop a game from the ground up.

==Hardware==
A simple example of both backward and forward compatibility is the introduction of [[FM broadcasting|FM radio]] in [[stereophonic sound|stereo]]. FM radio was initially [[monaural|mono]], with only one audio channel represented by one [[signal (electrical engineering)|signal]]. With the introduction of two-channel stereo FM radio, many listeners had only mono FM receivers. Forward compatibility for mono receivers with stereo signals was achieved through sending the sum of both left and right audio channels in one signal and the difference in another signal. That allows mono FM receivers to receive and decode the sum signal while ignoring the difference signal, which is necessary only for separating the audio channels. Stereo FM receivers can receive a mono signal and decode it without the need for a second signal, and they can separate a sum signal to left and right channels if both sum and difference signals are received. Without the requirement for backward compatibility, a simpler method could have been chosen.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Newnes Radio and RF Engineering Pocket Book|first1=Steve|last1=Winder|first2=Joseph|last2=Carr|edition=3|date=2002|publisher=Newnes|isbn=9780080497471|pp=121–123}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Full backward compatibility is particularly important in computer [[instruction set]] architectures, one of the most successful being the [[x86]] family of [[microprocessor]]s. Their full backward compatibility spans back to the 16-bit [[Intel 8086]]/[[Intel 8088|8088]] processors introduced in 1978. (The 8086/8088, in turn, were designed with easy machine-translatability of programs written for its predecessor in mind, although they were not instruction-set compatible with the 8-bit [[Intel 8080]] processor as of 1974. The [[Zilog Z80]], however, was fully backwards compatible with the Intel 8080.)
Fully backwards compatible processors can process the same [[executable|binary executable software instructions]] as their predecessors, allowing the use of a newer processor without having to acquire new [[application software|applications]] or [[operating system]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Computer System Organization|author=Naresh Jotwani|publisher=Tata McGraw-Hill Education|date=2009|pp=320&amp;ndash;324|isbn=9781259081217}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, the success of the [[Wi-Fi]] digital communication standard is attributed to its broad forward and backward compatibility; it became more popular than other standards that were not backward compatible.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Next Generation Wireless LANs: 802.11n and 802.11ac|first1=Eldad|last1=Perahia|first2=Robert|last2=Stacey|date=2013|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=9781107016767|chapter=Foreword}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Software ==
[[Compiler]] backward compatibility may refer to the ability of a compiler of a newer version of the language to accept programs or data that worked under the previous version.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Vzy8ap4YYW8C&amp;pg=PA123&amp;dq=forward+compatibility&amp;lr=&amp;hl=sv|first=Michael|last=Kay|title=XSLT 2.0 Programmer's Reference|publisher=Wiley|date=2004|isbn=0-7645-6909-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=July 2016}}

A data format is said to be backward compatible with its predecessor if every message or file that is valid under the old format is still valid, retaining its meaning under the new format.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=What is a Good Standard?|chapter-url=http://www.w3.org/People/Bos/DesignGuide/compatibility.html|chapter=Backwards Compatibility|first=Bert|last=Bos|date=2003|accessdate=July 12, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{columns-list|colwidth=20em|
* [[Bug compatibility]], backward compatibility that maintains known flaws
* [[Compatibility mode]]
* [[Computer compatibility]]
* [[Deprecation]]
* [[Downgrade attack]]
* [[Emulator]]
* [[Flag day (computing)]]
* [[Legacy mode]]
* [[List of backward compatible games for Xbox One]]
* [[List of Xbox games compatible with Xbox 360]]
* [[Shim (computing)]]
* [[Software regression]]
* [[Vendor lock-in]]
}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Backward Compatibility}}
[[Category:Backward compatibility| ]]
[[Category:Interoperability]]</text>
      <sha1>9w9lg3djp0vpvzych36fhgdc32n97rv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
