  <page>
    <title>Espagnole sauce</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9929</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939048123</id>
      <parentid>939034956</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-04T01:12:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Dating maintenance tags: {{Fact}}</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[File:Sauce Spagnole-09.JPG|thumb|Beef with espagnole sauce and French fries]]
'''Espagnole sauce''' ({{IPA-fr|ɛspaɲɔl}}) is a basic [[Brown sauce (meat stock based)|brown sauce]], and is one of [[Auguste Escoffier]]'s five [[mother sauce]]s of classic [[French cuisine|French cooking]]. Escoffier popularized the recipe, which is still followed today.&lt;ref name=guide&gt;Escoffier (1903), ''[[Le Guide culinaire]]'', Editions Flammarion&lt;/ref&gt;

Espagnole has a strong taste, and is rarely used directly on food. As a mother sauce, it serves as the starting point for many derivatives, such as [[sauce Africaine|sauce africaine]], sauce [[Bitter orange|bigarade]], [[sauce Bourguignonne|sauce bourguignonne]], sauce aux [[Agaricus bisporus|champignons]], [[sauce charcutière]], [[Chasseur (sauce)|sauce chasseur]], sauce chevreuil, and [[demi-glace]]. Hundreds of other derivatives are in the classical French repertoire.

Escoffier included a recipe for a [[Lent]]en espagnole sauce, using fish stock and mushrooms, in ''[[Le Guide culinaire]]'', but doubted its necessity.

==Preparation==

The basic method of making espagnole is to prepare a very dark brown [[roux]], to which [[veal]] [[stock (food)|stock]] or water is added, along with  browned bones, pieces of [[beef]], [[vegetable]]s, [[brown sugar]] and various [[seasoning]]s.  This blend is allowed to slowly reduce while being frequently skimmed. The classic recipe calls for additional veal stock to be added as the liquid gradually reduces, but today, water is generally used instead. [[Tomato paste]] or pureed tomatoes are added towards the end of the process, and the sauce is further reduced.&lt;ref name=guide/&gt;

==Etymology==
''Espagnole'' is the French word for &quot;Spanish&quot;, but the sauce's origin story is argued by French cooks.  According to [[Louis Diat]], the creator of ''[[vichyssoise]]'' and the author of the classic ''Gourmet's Basic French Cookbook'':&lt;blockquote&gt; &quot;There is a story that explains why the most important basic brown sauce in French cuisine is called ''sauce espagnole'', or Spanish sauce.  According to the story, the Spanish cooks of [[Louis XIII of France|Louis XIII]]'s bride, Anne, helped to prepare their wedding feast, and insisted upon improving the rich brown sauce of France with Spanish [[tomato]]es.  This new sauce was an instant success, and was gratefully named in honor of its creators.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Waters | first = Mrs. W.G. | year = 1920 | title = The Cook's Decameron: A Study In Taste | publisher = IndyPublish.com | isbn = 1-4043-4580-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In ''Kettner's Book of the Table'', published in 1877, an entirely different explanation is given:

{{quote|When the [[House of Bourbon|Bourbons]] made their way to the [[Philip V of Spain|Spanish throne]] under [[Louis XV]], and when Spanish fashions came back to Paris, the French cooks took a hint from the Spanish ''[[pot-au-feu]]''—the ''[[olla podrida]]''—and produced a variation of their brown sauce which they called &quot;Spanish&quot;. The essential principle of the French ''pot-au-feu'' was beef; the essential principle of the Spanish was [[bacon]], [[ham]], the red Estremadura [[sausage]]—all well smoked... The [[Louis de Rouvroy, duc de Saint-Simon|Duc de St. Simon]] sent home marvellous accounts of the hams of [[Montánchez|Montanches]]; there grew up a rage for [[Jamón ibérico|Spanish hams]]; and the French were not to blame, for they have no hams of their own which have any reputation. Great as they are in pig's flesh, they are poor hands at bacon and ham; and the treasures of Montanches were a revelation to them. They ran wild after ham... And so, by introducing the flavour of the [[Extremadura|Estremadura]] bacon and ham into the old brown sauce of the French, there came into being the Spanish sauce... The hams of Montanches are not too plentiful in this world of sorrow, and the cooks came to be satisfied with any ham—even with French ham, which is little better than salted pork. So the meaning of the prescription was lost; the peculiarity of the Spanish sauce passed away, and its name became a puzzle.&lt;ref&gt;E.S.Dallas (1877), ''Kettner's Book of the Table'', Dullau and Co., London, digitized by Google, retrieved 2008&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The name &quot;Kettner&quot; in the title refers to Auguste Kettner, former chef to [[Napoleon III]], who emigrated to England and in 1867 opened a restaurant in [[Soho]], Kettner's, one of the oldest restaurants in London.{{fact|date=February 2020}}

==See also==
*[[Brown sauce (meat stock based)|Brown sauce]]
*[[Demi-glace]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Cookbook}}
* [http://onlinebooks.library.upenn.edu/webbin/gutbook/lookup?num=930 ''The Cook's Decameron'' from Project Gutenberg]
* [https://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:djCrQlrQtwgJ:https://www.emerils.com/120804/espagnole-sauce+&amp;cd=3&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=us Emeril Lagasse's recipe at emerils.com]

{{Brown sauces}}

{{portal bar|Food}}

[[Category:Brown sauces]]
[[Category:French sauces]]
[[Category:Mother sauces]]

[[de:Grundsauce#Braune Grundsaucen]]</text>
      <sha1>8rs84pkdlac06yqsqqazac5v81epg7h</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
