  <page>
    <title>Eden Project</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9971</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943140883</id>
      <parentid>940630909</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T02:50:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Buttons0603</username>
        <id>8735322</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Eden Sessions */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Visitor attraction in Cornwall in the United Kingdom}}
{{redirect|The Eden Project|the musician|Eden (musician)}}
{{EngvarB|date=September 2013}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2013}}
{{Infobox building
|name                = Eden Project
|image               = Eden project.JPG
|building_type       = Multiple Greenhouse Complex
|architectural_style = Inspired by [[James T. Baldwin]]'s Pillow Dome&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last= Baldwin |first= James T. |authorlink= James T. Baldwin |title= The Pillow Dome |url= http://www.thegreencenter.net/pdf/dome1985.pdf |format=[[PDF]] |publisher=[[The Buckminster Fuller Institute]] |accessdate= 9 February 2014 |url-status= dead |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20120617025855/http://www.thegreencenter.net/pdf/dome1985.pdf |archivedate= 17 June 2012 |df= dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|structural_system   = Steel frame and thermoplastic
|location            = [[St Blazey]], Cornwall, UK
|completion_date     = May 2000
|opened              = 17 March 2001
|main_contractors    =
|architect           = [[Nicholas Grimshaw]]
|structural_engineer = Anthony Hunt and Associates
|services_engineer   = [[Arup Group Limited|Arup]]
|coordinates         = {{Coord|50|21|43|N|4|44|41|W|region:GB_type:landmark|display=inline,title}}
}}
The '''Eden Project''' ({{lang-kw|Edenva}}) is a popular visitor attraction in [[Cornwall]], England, UK. Inside the two biomes are plants that are collected from many diverse climates and environments. The project is located in a reclaimed [[china clay]] [[clay pit|pit]], located {{convert|2|km|abbr=on}} from the town of [[St Blazey]] and {{convert|5|km|mi|0|abbr=on}} from the larger town of [[St Austell]].&lt;ref name=&quot;osexp1&quot;&gt;Ordnance Survey (2005). ''OS Explorer Map 107 – Fowey, Looe &amp; Lostwithiel''. {{ISBN|0-319-23708-7}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The complex is dominated by two huge enclosures consisting of adjoining domes that house thousands of plant [[species]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.edenproject.com/come-and-visit/whats-here/rainforest-biome/index.php | title = Rainforest Biome | publisher = Eden project | accessdate = 11 October 2011 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20111024185941/http://www.edenproject.com/come-and-visit/whats-here/rainforest-biome/index.php | archive-date = 24 October 2011 | url-status = dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; and each enclosure emulates a natural [[biome]]. The biomes consist of hundreds of [[hexagon]]al and [[pentagon]]al, inflated, plastic cells supported by steel frames. The largest of the two biomes simulates a [[rainforest]] environment and the second, a [[Mediterranean climate|Mediterranean environment]]. The attraction also has an outside [[botanical garden]] which is home to many plants and wildlife native to Cornwall and the UK in general; it also has many plants that provide an important and interesting backstory, for example, those with a prehistoric heritage.

There are plans to build an Eden Project North in the seaside town of [[Morecambe]], Lancashire, with a focus on the marine environment.

== History ==
[[File:Equus eden.jpg|thumb|Driftwood sculpture of a horse by Heather Jansch,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first= Heather |last= Jansch |url= http://www.heatherjansch.com/index.php |title= Heather Jansch Sculptor Bronze &amp; Driftwood Horse |publisher= Heather Jansch }}&lt;/ref&gt; from the main entrance]]
[[File:Eden Project sculpture Made from the detritus of modern living - the teeth are computer mouses.JPG|thumb|Eden Project sculpture Made from the detritus of modern living—the teeth are computer mice]]
[[File:Grasswoman eden.jpg|thumb|''Eve'', by Sue and Pete Hill, shaped from the soil]]
The clay pit in which the project is sited was in use for over 160 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.edenproject.com/whats-it-all-about/behind-the-scenes/about-us/our-story |title= Our Story |publisher= Eden Project |url-status=dead |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20120712023922/http://www.edenproject.com/whats-it-all-about/behind-the-scenes/about-us/our-story |archivedate= 12 July 2012 |df= dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1981, the pit was used by the [[BBC]] as the planet surface of Magrathea in the 1981 TV series of ''[[The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy (TV series)|the Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= https://www.theguardian.com/books/2009/oct/03/hitchhikers-guide-galaxy-douglas-adams |location= London |work=[[The Guardian]] |first= Jenny |last= Turner |title= Does the Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy still answer the ultimate question? |date= 3 October 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; By the mid-1990s the pit was all but exhausted.&lt;ref name=&quot;edenproject.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.edenproject.com/whats-it-all-about/behind-the-scenes/10th-birthday/10th-birthday-timeline |title= Eden story, educational charity – Eden Project, Cornwall |publisher= Eden Project }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The initial idea for the project dates back to 1996, with construction beginning in 1998. The work was hampered by torrential rain in the first few months of the project, and parts of the pit flooded as it sits {{convert|15|m|ft|abbr=on}} below the water table.&lt;ref name=&quot;edenproject.com&quot; /&gt;

The first part of the Eden Project, the visitor centre, opened to the public in May 2000. The first plants began arriving in September of that year,&lt;ref name=&quot;edenproject.com&quot; /&gt; and the full site opened on 17 March 2001.

The Eden Project was used as a filming location for the 2002 [[James Bond]] film, ''[[Die Another Day]]''. On 2 July 2005 The Eden Project hosted the [[Live 8 concert, Eden Project|&quot;Africa Calling&quot; concert]] of the [[Live 8]] concert series.  It has also provided some plants for the [[British Museum]]'s Africa garden.

In 2005, the Project launched &quot;A Time of Gifts&quot; for the winter months, November to February. This features an ice rink covering the lake, with a small café/bar attached, as well as a Christmas market. Cornish choirs regularly perform in the biomes.

In 2007, the Eden Project campaigned unsuccessfully for £50&amp;nbsp;million in [[Big Lottery Fund]] money for a proposed [[desert]] biome.&lt;ref name=BigLottery&gt;{{cite web |url= https://www.biglotteryfund.org.uk/global-content/press-releases/england/south-west/eden-edges-closer-to-winning-lottery-millions |title= Eden edges closer to winning Lottery millions: Big Lottery Fund |accessdate= 16 May 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/7140621.stm |work=[[BBC News]] |date= 12 December 2007 |title= Routes scheme tops lottery vote |accessdate= 3 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; It received just 12.07% of the votes, the lowest for the four projects being considered.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.biglotteryfund.org.uk/prog_the_peoples_50_million.htm |publisher= [[The Big Lottery Fund]] |title= The People's 50 Million – Sustrans' Connect2 wins £50 million prize |accessdate= 3 February 2008 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20080119020032/http://www.biglotteryfund.org.uk/prog_the_peoples_50_million.htm |archive-date= 19 January 2008 |url-status= dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; As part of the campaign, the Eden Project invited people all over Cornwall to try to break the [[world record]] for the biggest ever [[pub quiz]] as part of its campaign to bring £50&amp;nbsp;million of [[lottery]] funds to Cornwall.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.edenproject.com/about/3200.html |title= About |publisher= Eden Project |url-status= dead |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20071226181304/http://www.edenproject.com/about/3200.html |archivedate= 26 December 2007 |df= dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 2009, much of the project, including both greenhouses, became available to navigate through [[Google Street View]].

The Eden Trust revealed a trading loss of £1.3&amp;nbsp;million for 2012-13, on a turnover of £25.4&amp;nbsp;million. The Eden Project had posted a surplus of £136,000 for the previous year. In 2014 Eden accounts showed a surplus of £2&amp;nbsp;million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.cornishguardian.co.uk/St-Austell-8217-s-Eden-Project-black/story-21239280-detail/story.html#ixzz3df3N6sV2 |title= St Austell’s Eden Project |date= 15 June 2014 |publisher=[[Cornish Guardian]] |url-status= dead |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20150923210710/http://www.cornishguardian.co.uk/St-Austell-8217-s-Eden-Project-black/story-21239280-detail/story.html#ixzz3df3N6sV2 |archivedate= 23 September 2015 |df= dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[World Pasty Championships]] have been held at the Eden Project since 2012, an international competition to find the best [[Cornish pasties]] and other pasty-type savoury snacks.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |ref= {{harvid|World Pasty Championships winners chosen}} |title= World Pasty Championships winners chosen |date= 4 March 2012 |journal=[[BBC News]] |url= https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-england-cornwall-17249619 |accessdate= 2016-08-13 |df= dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |journal=[[The Herald (Plymouth)]] |first= Neil |last= Shaw |date= 5 March 2016 |title= Pictures as World Pasty Championships are held at Eden Project on St Piran's Day 2016 |url= http://www.plymouthherald.co.uk/pictures-world-pasty-championships-held-eden/story-28865929-detail/story.html |accessdate= 2016-08-13 |df= dmy-all }}{{dead link|date=March 2018 |bot=Darkmorpher |fix-attempted=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{dead link|date=March 2018 |bot=Darkmorpher |fix-attempted=yes}}

The Eden Project is said to have contributed over £1&amp;nbsp;billion to the Cornish economy.&lt;ref name=personally&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.personallyspeakingbureau.com/speaker/tim-smit-kbe-sir/ |title= Tim Smit KBE, Sir – Personally Speaking Bureau |accessdate= 16 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2016, Eden became home to Europe's only Redwood forest when forty saplings of coast redwoods (Sequoia sempervirens), which could live for 4,000 years and reach 115 metres in height, were planted there.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.edenproject.com/eden-story/our-ethos/redwood-conservation-project|title=Redwood conservation project|date=March 2016|website=Eden Project}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Eden Project received 1,006,928 visitors in 2018.&lt;ref name=&quot;ALVA 2018 visitor numbers&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=ALVA - Association of Leading Visitor Attractions |url=http://www.alva.org.uk/details.cfm?p=423 |website=www.alva.org.uk |accessdate=27 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Design and construction ==
The project was conceived by [[Tim Smit]] and designed by architect [[Nicholas Grimshaw]] and engineering firm Anthony Hunt and Associates (now part of [[Sinclair Knight Merz]]). [[Davis Langdon]] carried out the project management, [[Sir Robert McAlpine]] and [[Alfred McAlpine]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.edenproject.com/whats-it-all-about/behind-the-scenes/our-history/index.php |title= Our history |publisher= Eden project |accessdate= 27 September 2010 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20100611003612/http://www.edenproject.com/whats-it-all-about/behind-the-scenes/our-history/index.php |archive-date= 11 June 2010 |url-status= dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; did the construction, [[Mero-Schmidlin|MERO]] designed and built the biomes, and [[Arup Group Limited|Arup]] was the services engineer, economic consultant, environmental engineer and transportation engineer. [https://landuse.co.uk/what-we-do Land Use Consultants] led the masterplan and landscape design. The project took 2½ years to construct and opened to the public on 17 March 2001.

== Site ==
[[File:Eden Project geodesic domes panorama.jpg|thumb|center|upright=3|Panoramic view of the geodesic biome domes at the Eden Project]]

=== Layout ===
[[File:The Bee (Eden Project).JPG|thumb|''The Bee'']]
Once into the attraction, there is a meandering path with views of the two biomes, planted landscapes, including vegetable gardens, and sculptures that include a giant [[bee]] and previously The [[WEEE]] Man (removed in 2016), a towering figure made from old electrical appliances and was meant to represent the average electrical waste used by one person in a lifetime.

=== Biomes ===
At the bottom of the pit are two covered [[biome]]s:

The Tropical Biome, covers {{convert|1.56|ha|acre|1|abbr=on}} and measures {{convert|55|m|ft|0|abbr=on}} high, {{convert|100|m|ft|0|abbr=on}} wide, and {{convert|200|m|ft|0|abbr=on}} long. It is used for tropical plants, such as fruiting [[banana]] plants, [[coffee]], rubber and giant [[bamboo]], and is kept at a tropical temperature and moisture level.
[[File:The Tropical Biome.jpg|thumb|The Tropical Biome]]

The [[Mediterranean climate|Mediterranean]] Biome covers {{convert|0.654|ha|acre|1|abbr=on}} and measures {{convert|35|m|ft|0|abbr=on}} high, {{convert|65|m|ft|0|abbr=on}} wide, and {{convert|135|m|ft|0|abbr=on}} long. It houses familiar warm [[temperate]] and [[arid]] plants such as [[olive]]s and grape [[vine]]s and various sculptures.

The Outdoor Gardens represent the temperate regions of the world with plants such as [[tea]], [[lavender]], [[hops]], [[hemp]], and [[sunflower]]s, as well as local plant species.

The covered biomes are constructed from a tubular steel (hex-tri-hex) with mostly hexagonal external cladding panels made from the thermoplastic [[ETFE]]. Glass was avoided due to its weight and potential dangers. The cladding panels themselves are created from several layers of thin [[ultraviolet|UV]]-transparent ETFE [[tensile structure|film]], which are sealed around their [[perimeter]] and inflated to create a large cushion. The resulting cushion acts as a thermal blanket to the structure. The ETFE material is resistant to most stains, which simply wash off in the rain. If required, cleaning can be performed by [[abseil]]ers. Although the ETFE is susceptible to punctures, these can be easily fixed with ETFE tape. The structure is completely self-supporting, with no internal supports, and takes the form of a [[geodesic dome|geodesic]] structure. The panels vary in size up to {{convert|9|m|ft|1|abbr=on}} across, with the largest at the top of the structure.

The ETFE technology was supplied and installed by the firm [[Vector Foiltec]], which is also responsible for ongoing maintenance of the cladding. The steel spaceframe and cladding package (with Vector Foiltec as ETFE subcontractor) was designed, supplied and installed by MERO (UK) PLC, who also jointly developed the overall scheme geometry with the architect, Nicholas Grimshaw &amp; Partners.

The entire build project was managed by McAlpine Joint Venture.
&lt;gallery widths=&quot;200px&quot; heights=&quot;150px&quot;&gt;
File:Eden Project Winter 2008 showing Bruce Munro field of Light.JPG|The Biomes and Link building showing [[Field of Light]] installation by [[Bruce Munro]]
File:Eden Project - tropical canopy.jpg|Inside the tropical Biome
File:The Eden Project, Cornwall.JPG|The Biomes (or eco domes) at The Eden Project in Cornwall
File:EdenProjectRoof.jpg|The hexagonal structure looking from the inside
&lt;/gallery&gt;

=== The Core ===
[[File:The Core, Eden Project.JPG|thumb|The Core]]
The Core is the latest addition to the site and opened in September 2005. It provides the Eden Project with an education facility, incorporating classrooms and exhibition spaces designed to help communicate Eden's central message about the relationship between people and plants. Accordingly, the building has taken its inspiration from plants, most noticeable in the form of the soaring timber roof, which gives the building its distinctive shape.

Grimshaw developed the geometry of the copper-clad roof in collaboration with a sculptor, Peter Randall-Page, and Mike Purvis of structural engineers [[Sinclair Knight Merz|SKM Anthony Hunts]]. It is derived from [[phyllotaxis]], which is the mathematical basis for nearly all plant growth; the &quot;opposing spirals&quot; found in many plants such as the seeds in a sunflower's head, [[pine cone]]s and [[pineapple]]s. The copper was obtained from traceable sources, and the Eden Project is working with [[Rio Tinto Group]] to explore the possibility of encouraging further traceable supply routes for metals, which would enable users to avoid metals mined unethically. The services and [[acoustics|acoustic]], mechanical, and electrical engineering design was carried out by [[Buro Happold]].

==== Art at The Core ====
[[File:The Seed at Eden Project.jpg|thumbnail|right|upright=0.6|''Seed'' by [[Peter Randall-Page]]]]
The Core is also home to art exhibitions throughout the year. A permanent installation entitled ''Seed'', by [[Peter Randall-Page]], occupies the anteroom. ''Seed'' is a large, 70 tonne egg-shaped stone installation standing some {{convert|13|ft}} tall and displaying a complex pattern of protrusions that are based upon the [[Fibonacci number#In nature|geometric and mathematical principles that underlie plant growth]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Granite seed is 'planted' at Eden |work=[[BBC News Online]] |date= 2007-06-11 |url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/cornwall/6738783.stm |access-date= 2018-02-25 |df= dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.edenproject.com/visit/whats-here/seed-sculpture |title= Seed sculpture by Peter Randall-Page |publisher= Eden Project |access-date= 2018-02-25 |quote= Made out of a single piece of granite, its surface has been carved with 1,800 nodes in the pattern of a Fibonacci spiral – the growth pattern found across the natural world in things like sunflowers, pine cones and ammonites |df= dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Environmental aspects ==
[[File:Cornwall, eden project tropical.jpg|thumb|left|Inside the tropical Biome]]
The biomes provide diverse growing conditions, and many plants are on display.

The Eden Project includes [[environmental education]] focusing on the interdependence of plants and people; plants are labelled with their medicinal uses. The massive amounts of water required to create the humid conditions of the Tropical Biome, and to serve the toilet facilities, are all sanitised rain water that would otherwise collect at the bottom of the quarry. The only [[Public utility|mains]] water used is for hand washing and for cooking. The complex also uses Green Tariff Electricity – the energy comes from one of the many [[wind turbine]]s in Cornwall, which were among the first in Europe.

In December 2010 the Eden Project received permission to build a [[geothermal electricity]] plant which will generate approx 4MWe, enough to supply Eden and about 5000 households.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC Geotherm&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-cornwall-12026753|title=BBC News – Eden Project geothermal plant plans to go ahead |work=[[BBC News]]|accessdate=18 December 2010|date=18 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The project will involve [[geothermal heating]] as well as geothermal electricity.  [[Cornwall Council]] and the [[European Union]] came up with the greater part of £16.8m required to start the project.  First a well will be sunk nearly 3 miles (4.5km) into the granite crust underneath Eden.  Funding has been secured and drilling is set to begin in summer 2020.  Eden co-founder, Sir [[Tim Smit]] said, “Since we began, Eden has had a dream that the world should be powered by renewable energy. The sun can provide massive solar power and the wind has been harnessed by humankind for thousands of years, but because both are intermittent and battery technology cannot yet store all we need there is a gap.  We believe the answer lies beneath our feet in the heat underground that can be accessed by drilling technology that pumps water towards the centre of the Earth and brings it back up superheated to provide us with heat and electricity.”&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2019/oct/14/eden-project-drilling-clean-geothermal-energy Eden Project to begin drilling for clean geothermal energy] ''[[The Guardian]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

== Eden Project North==
In 2018, the Eden Project revealed its design for a new version of the project, located on the seafront in [[Morecambe]], [[Lancashire]]. There will be biomes shaped like mussels and a focus on the marine environment. There will also be reimagined lidos, gardens, performance spaces, immersive experiences and observatories.&lt;ref name=edenprojectnorth&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.edenproject.com/media/2018/11/new-vision-morecambes-eden-project-revealed|title=New vision for Morecambe's Eden Project revealed|website=Edenproject.com|accessdate=21 December 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=indynorth&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/home-news/morecambe-eden-project-morecambe-bay-mussl-david-harland-cornwall-a8537126.html|title=Morecambe Eden Project will be shaped like a giant mussel|date=24 November 2018|newspaper=[[The Independent]]|accessdate=21 December 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Grimshaw Architects|Grimshaw]] are the architects for the project, which is expected to cost £80 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.manchestereveningnews.co.uk/news/greater-manchester-news/plans-80m-eden-project-north-15458954|title=Plans for £80m Eden Project North are unveiled|first=Damon|last=Wilkinson|date=23 November 2018|website=Manchestereveingnews.comm|accessdate=21 December 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The project is a partnership with the Lancashire Enterprise Partnership, Lancaster University, Lancashire County Council and Lancaster City Council.&lt;ref name=edenprojectnorth/&gt;&lt;ref name=indynorth/&gt; In December 2018, the four local partners agreed to provide £1 million to develop the idea, which will allow the development of an outline planning application for the project.&lt;ref name=placenorthwest&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.placenorthwest.co.uk/news/eden-project-north-secures-council-cash/|title=Place North West - Eden Project North secures council cash|date=19 December 2018|website=Placenorthwest.co.uk|accessdate=21 December 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is expected that there will be 500 jobs created and 8,000 visitors a day to the site.&lt;ref name=placenorthwest/&gt;

== Eden Sessions ==
Since 2002, the Project has hosted a series of musical performances, called the Eden Sessions. Artists have included [[Amy Winehouse]], [[James Morrison (singer)|James Morrison]], [[Muse (band)|Muse]], [[Lily Allen]], [[Snow Patrol]], [[Pulp (band)|Pulp]], [[Brian Wilson]], and [[The Magic Numbers]]. 2008's summer headliners were: [[The Verve]], [[Kaiser Chiefs]], and [[KT Tunstall]]. [[Oasis (band)|Oasis]] were also set to play in the summer of 2008, but the concert was postponed because [[Noel Gallagher]] was unable to perform after breaking three ribs in a stage invasion incident several weeks before. The concert was instead played in the summer of 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.edenproject.com/media/archive/2008/oasisrescheduled.php |title= Media relations |publisher= Eden Project }}&lt;/ref&gt; 2010 saw performances from artists including [[Mika (singer)|Mika]], [[Jack Johnson (musician)|Jack Johnson]], [[Mojave 3]], [[Doves (band)|Doves]], [[Paolo Nutini]], [[Mumford &amp; Sons]], and [[Martha Wainwright]].

The 2011 sessions were headlined by [[The Flaming Lips]], [[Primal Scream]], [[Pendulum (drum and bass band)|Pendulum]], [[Fleet Foxes]], and [[Brandon Flowers]] with support from [[The Horrors]], [[The Go! Team]], [[OK Go]], [[Villagers (band)|Villagers]], and [[The Bees (UK band)|The Bees]].&lt;ref name=lineup&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.edensessions.com/line-up/previous-line-ups|title=Previous line-ups – Eden Sessions concerts, Eden Project, Cornwall|publisher=Eden Sessions|access-date=16 March 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140317003945/http://www.edensessions.com/line-up/previous-line-ups/|archive-date=17 March 2014|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2012 Eden sessions were headlined by: [[Tim Minchin]], [[Example (musician)|Example]], [[Frank Turner]], [[Chase &amp; Status]], [[Plan B (musician)|Plan B]], [[Blink-182]], [[Noah and the Whale]], and [[The Vaccines]].&lt;ref name=&quot;lineup&quot; /&gt;

The 2013 Eden Sessions were headlined by: [[Kaiser Chiefs]], [[Jessie J]], [[Eddie Izzard]], [[Sigur Rós]], and [[The xx]].&lt;ref name=&quot;lineup&quot; /&gt;

The 2014 Eden Sessions were headlined by: [[Dizzee Rascal]], [[Skrillex]], [[Pixar]] in Concert, [[Ellie Goulding]], and [[Elbow (band)|Elbow]].&lt;ref name=&quot;lineup&quot; /&gt;

The 2015 Eden Sessions were headlined by: [[Paolo Nutini]], [[Elton John]], [[Paloma Faith]], [[Motörhead]], [[The Stranglers]], [[Spandau Ballet]], and [[Ben Howard]].&lt;ref name=&quot;lineup&quot; /&gt;

The 2016 Eden Sessions were headlined by: [[Lionel Richie]], [[Tom Jones (singer)|Tom Jones]], [[PJ Harvey]], [[Manic Street Preachers]], and [[Jess Glynne]].&lt;ref name=&quot;lineup&quot; /&gt;

The 2017 Eden Sessions were headlined by: [[Bastille (band)|Bastille]], [[Madness (band)|Madness]], [[Royal Blood (band)|Royal Blood]], [[Blondie (band)|Blondie]], [[Van Morrison]], [[Bryan Adams]], and [[Foals (band)|Foals]].&lt;ref name=&quot;lineup&quot; /&gt;

The 2018 Eden Sessions were headlined by: [[Gary Barlow]], [[Massive Attack]], A Beautiful Day Out, [[Ben Howard]], [[Queens of the Stone Age]], [[Jack Johnson (musician)|Jack Johnson]], [[Björk]].&lt;ref name=&quot;lineup&quot; /&gt;

The 2019 Eden Sessions are headlined by: [[Stereophonics]], [[Nile Rodgers|Nile Rogers]] &amp; Chic, The 100th session, [[Liam Gallagher]], [[The Chemical Brothers]], [[Snow Patrol]],  [[Kylie Minogue]].&lt;ref name=&quot;lineup&quot; /&gt;

[[My Chemical Romance]] will play the 2020 Eden Sessions in their first UK shows after a six-year hiatus, as part of their [[My Chemical Romance reunion tour|reunion tour]].

== In the media ==
* Robin Kewell (Ed.): ''Eden: The Inside Story''. St Austell n.d.: The Eden Project. DVD.
* ''The Eden Radio Project''. Every Thursday between 5:30 and 7 p.m. on [[Radio St Austell Bay]].
* ''[[Die Another Day]]'': Graves' diamond mine
* ''[[Trees A Crowd]] Podcast'': An Interview between the Project’s head of interpretation, Dr Jo Elworthy, and [[David Oakes]] was released on the 18th of November.

== See also ==
{{Portal|Cornwall|Ecology|Gardening|Gardens}}
{{div col|colwidth=35em}}
* [[BIOS-3]]
* [[Biosphere 2]]
* [[Closed ecological system]]
* [[Montreal Biodome]]
* [[Montreal Biosphère]]
* [[Mitchell Park Horticultural Conservatory]] (&quot;The Domes&quot; of Milwaukee)
* [[Ecosystem]]
* [[Vivarium]]
* The [[Lost Gardens of Heligan]]
* [[List of topics related to Cornwall]]
* [[Earthpark]]
* [[Richard Carew Pole|Sir Richard Carew Pole]]
* [[Thin-shell structure]]
* [[List of thin shell structures]]
{{div col end}}
{{-}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Further reading ==
* Philip McMillan Browse, Louise Frost, Alistair Griffiths: ''Plants of Eden (Eden Project)''. Penzance 2001: Alison Hodge.
* [[Richard Mabey]]: ''Fencing Paradise: Exploring the Gardens of Eden'' London 2005: Eden Project Books. {{ISBN|1-903919-31-2}}
* Hugh Pearman, Andrew Whalley: ''The Architecture of Eden''. With a foreword by Sir Nicholas Grimshaw. London 2003: Eden Project Books. {{ISBN|1-903919-15-0}}
* Eden Team (Ed.): ''Eden Project: The Guide 2008/9.'' London 2008: Eden Project Books.
* Tim Smit: ''Eden''. London 2001: Bantam Press.
* Paul Spooner: ''The Revenge of the Green Planet: The Eden Project Book of Amazing Facts About Plants''. London 2003: Eden Project Books.
* [[Alan Titchmarsh]]: ''The Eden Project''. United Kingdom: Acorn Media, 2006. {{OCLC|225403941}}.

== External links ==
&lt;!--Please note – All links that are of dubious quality WILL be removed within days. Please remember that any one can just type into Google Image Search the Eden Project if they want to see pictures. Also this not the place for advertising--&gt;
{{Commons category}}
* {{Official site|http://www.edenproject.com/}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080606144820/http://sessions.edenproject.com/ Eden Sessions Website]—Official site for live gigs
* [https://www.bbc.co.uk/cornwall/content/webcams/eden_webcam.shtml Webcam of the Eden Project]—BBC

[[Category:Buildings and structures completed in 2000]]
[[Category:Nicholas Grimshaw buildings]]
[[Category:High-tech architecture]]
[[Category:Botanical gardens in Cornwall]]
[[Category:Building engineering]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Cornwall]]
[[Category:Ecological experiments]]
[[Category:Environmental design]]
[[Category:Geodesic domes]]
[[Category:Greenhouses in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Tourist attractions in Cornwall]]
[[Category:2000 establishments in England]]
[[Category:St Blazey]]</text>
      <sha1>3fd7jhck6fj9b935ed1gp7d4e3jy8j1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
