  <page>
    <title>Epistle to the Romans</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9961</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940934563</id>
      <parentid>940779951</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-15T15:41:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Grammarian79</username>
        <id>20258846</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* General presentation */ Fixed grammar</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about|the book of the New Testament|[[Ignatius of Antioch|Ignatius]]' letter to the Romans|Epistle of Ignatius to the Romans}}
{{Paul}}{{Books of the New Testament}}

The '''Epistle to the Romans''' or '''Letter to the Romans''', often shortened to '''Romans''', is the sixth book in the [[New Testament]]. Biblical scholars agree that it was composed by the [[Apostle Paul]] to explain that [[Salvation (Christianity)|salvation]] is offered through [[the gospel]] of [[Jesus in Christianity|Jesus Christ]]. It is the longest of the [[Pauline epistles]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Felix Just, S.J. |url=http://catholic-resources.org/Bible/NT-Statistics-Greek.htm |title=New Testament Statistics: Number of Chapters, Verses, and Words in the Greek NT |publisher=Catholic-resources.org |date=2 September 2005 |accessdate=18 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== General presentation ==
In the opinion of [[Society of Jesus|Jesuit]] scholar [[Joseph Fitzmyer]], the book &quot;overwhelms the reader by the density and sublimity of the topic with which it deals, the gospel of the justification and salvation of Jew and Greek alike by the grace of God through faith in Jesus Christ, revealing the uprightness and love of [[God the Father]].&quot;{{sfn|Fitzmyer|1993|p=xiii}}

[[N. T. Wright]] notes that Romans is
{{quote
|neither a systematic theology nor a summary of Paul's lifework, but it is by common consent his masterpiece. It dwarfs most of his other writings, an Alpine peak towering over hills and villages. Not all onlookers have viewed it in the same light or from the same angle, and their snapshots and paintings of it are sometimes remarkably unalike. Not all climbers have taken the same route up its sheer sides, and there is frequent disagreement on the best approach. What nobody doubts is that we are here dealing with a work of massive substance, presenting a formidable intellectual challenge while offering a breathtaking theological and spiritual vision.&lt;ref&gt;Leander E. Keck and others, eds., ''The New Interpreter's Bible: A Commentary in Twelve Volumes'' (Nashville: Abingdon Press, 2002) 395&lt;/ref&gt;}}

== Authorship and dating ==
{{Main|Authorship of the Pauline epistles}}

The scholarly consensus is that Paul wrote the Epistle to the Romans.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Finally, there are seven letters that virtually all scholars agree were written by Paul himself: Romans, 1 and 2 Corinthians, Galatians, Philippians, 1 Thessalonians, and Philemon. These 'undisputed' epistles are similar in terms of writing style, vocabulary, and theology. In addition, the issues that they address can plausibly be situated in the early Christian movement of the 40s and 50s of the Common Era, when Paul was active as an apostle and missionary.&quot; Bart Ehrman (2000, 2nd ed.). ''The New Testament: A Historical Introduction to the Early Christian Writings.''&lt;/ref&gt; [[C. E. B. Cranfield]], in the introduction to his commentary on Romans, says:
&lt;blockquote&gt;The denial of Paul's authorship of Romans by such critics ... is now rightly relegated to a place among the curiosities of NT scholarship. Today no responsible criticism disputes its Pauline origin. The evidence of its use in the Apostolic Fathers is clear, and before the end of the second century it is listed and cited as Paul's. Every extant early list of NT books includes it among his letters. The external evidence of authenticity could indeed hardly be stronger; and it is altogether borne out by the internal evidence, linguistic, stylistic, literary, historical and theological.&lt;ref&gt;Cranfield, C. E. B. The Epistle to the Romans 1–8 (Vol. 1), International Critical Commentary Series. King's Lynn: T&amp;T Clark Ltd, 2004, pp. 1–2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[File:PaulT.jpg|thumb|right|A 17th-century depiction of Paul writing his epistles. Romans 16:22 indicates that Tertius acted as his [[amanuensis]]. ]]

The letter was most probably written while Paul was in [[Ancient Corinth|Corinth]], probably while he was staying in the house of [[Gaius (biblical figure)|Gaius]], and transcribed by [[Tertius of Iconium|Tertius]], his [[amanuensis]].&lt;ref&gt;Dunn, xliv; Stuhlmacher, 5; {{Bibleref2|Romans|16:22|31}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are a number of reasons why Corinth is considered most plausible. Paul was about to travel to [[Early centers of Christianity#Jerusalem|Jerusalem]] on writing the letter, which matches Acts{{Bibleref2c|Acts|20:3|KJV}} where it is reported that Paul stayed for three months in [[Early centers of Christianity#Greece|Greece]]. This probably implies Corinth as it was the location of Paul's greatest missionary success in Greece.&lt;ref name=Dunn&gt;Dunn, xliv&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, [[Phoebe (Christian woman)|Phoebe]] was a deacon of the church in [[Kechries|Cenchreae]], a port to the east of Corinth, and would have been able to convey the letter to [[Early centers of Christianity#Rome|Rome]] after passing through Corinth and taking a ship from Corinth's west port.&lt;ref name=Dunn/&gt; [[Erastus of Corinth|Erastus]], mentioned in {{Bibleref2|Romans|16:23|31}}, also lived in Corinth, being the city's commissioner for public works and city treasurer at various times, again indicating that the letter was written in Corinth.&lt;ref&gt;Bruce, 280–281; Dunn, xliv&lt;/ref&gt;

The precise time at which it was written is not mentioned in the epistle, but it was obviously written when the collection for Jerusalem had been assembled and Paul was about to &quot;go unto Jerusalem to minister unto the saints&quot;, that is, at the close of his second visit to Greece, during the winter preceding his last visit to that city.&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleref2|Rom|15:25|KJV}}; cf. {{Bibleref2|Acts|19:21|KJV}}; {{Bibleref2|Acts|20:2–3|KJV}}, {{Bibleref2-nb|Acts|20:16|KJV}}; {{bibleref2|1Cor|16:1–4|KJV|1 Cor 16:1–4}}&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of scholars writing on Romans propose the letter was written in late 55/early 56 or late 56/early 57.&lt;ref&gt;Bruce, 12; Dunn, xliii&lt;/ref&gt; Early 55 and early 58 both have some support, while German New Testament scholar [[Gerd Lüdemann]] argues for a date as early as 51/52 (or 54/55), following on from Knox, who proposed 53/54. Lüdemann is the only serious challenge to the consensus of mid to late 50s.&lt;ref&gt;Dunn, xliii–xliv&lt;/ref&gt;

== Textual variants ==
=== Fourteen-chapter form ===
There is strong, albeit indirect, evidence that a [[recension]] of Romans that lacked Chapters 15 and 16 was widely used in the western half of the Roman Empire until the mid-4th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;beduhn&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=BeDuhn |first=Jason |author-link=Jason BeDuhn |title=The First New Testament: Marcion's Scriptural Canon |page=305 |year=2013 |publisher=Polebridge Press |isbn=9781598151312 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;longenecker&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Longenecker |first=Richard N. |author-link=Richard Longenecker |title=Introducing Romans: Critical Issues in Paul's Most Famous Letter |year=2011 |publisher=Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing |location=Grand Rapids, MI |isbn=978-0-8028-6619-6 |pages=20ff }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;gamble&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last = Gamble |first = Harry Y. |title = The Textual History of the Letter to the Romans |pages=16ff |year=1977 |publisher = Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing Co. |location = Grand Rapids, MI |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=HEauJ3nNnQcC |isbn = 0-8028-1670-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This conclusion is partially based on the fact that a variety of [[Church Fathers]], such as [[Origen]] and [[Tertullian]], refer to a fourteen-chapter edition of Romans, either directly or indirectly. The fact that Paul's [[doxology]] is placed in various different places in different [[Manuscript|manuscripts]] of Romans only strengthens the case for an early fourteen-chapter recension. While there is some uncertainty, Harry Gamble concludes that the canonical sixteen-chapter recension is likely the earlier version of the text.&lt;ref name=&quot;gamble&quot; /&gt;{{rp|19ff}}

The [[Codex Boernerianus]] lacks the explicit references to the Roman church as the audience of the epistle found in Romans 1:7 and 1:15. There is evidence from [[Church Fathers|patristic]] commentaries indicating that Boernarianus is not unique in this regard; many early, no longer extant manuscripts also lacked an explicit Roman addressee in Chapter 1.&lt;ref name=&quot;longenecker&quot;/&gt;{{rp|31}} It is notable that, when this textual variant is combined with the omission of Chapters 15 and 16, there is no longer any clear reference to the Roman church throughout the entire epistle. Harry Gamble speculates that 1:7, 1:15, and Chapters 15 and 16 may have been removed by a scribe in order to make the epistle more suitable for a &quot;general&quot; audience.&lt;ref name=&quot;gamble&quot;/&gt;{{rp|29ff}}

=== Fifteen-chapter form ===
It is quite possible that a fifteen-chapter form of Romans, omitting Chapter 16, may have existed at an early date. Several scholars have argued, largely on the basis of internal evidence, that Chapter 16 represents a separate letter of Paul— possibly addressed to [[Ephesus]]— that was later appended to Romans.&lt;ref name=&quot;longenecker&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;gamble&quot;/&gt;

There are a few different arguments for this conclusion. First of all, there is a concluding peace benediction at 15:33, which reads like the other Pauline benedictions that conclude their respective letters. Secondly, Paul greets a large number of people and families in Chapter 16, in a way that suggests he was already familiar with them, whereas the material of Chapters 1-15 presupposes that Paul has never met anyone from the Roman church. The fact that [[Papyrus 46]] places Paul's doxology at the end of Chapter 15 can also be interpreted as evidence for the existence of a fifteen-chapter recension of the epistle.&lt;ref name=&quot;longenecker&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;gamble&quot;/&gt;

=== Subscript ===
Some manuscripts have a subscript at the end of the Epistle:
* προς Ρωμαιους (&quot;to the Romans&quot;) is found in these manuscripts: [[Codex Sinaiticus]], [[Codex Alexandrinus]], [[Codex Vaticanus]], [[Codex Ephraemi Rescriptus]], [[Codex Claromontanus]];
* προς Ρωμαιους εγραφη απο Κορινθου (&quot;to the Romans it was written from Corinth&quot;): B&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, D&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; ([[Codex Porphyrianus|P]]);
* προς Ρωμαιους εγραφη απο Κορινθου δια Φοιβης της διακονου (&quot;to the Romans it was written from Corinth by Phoebus the deacon&quot;): [[Minuscule 42|42]], [[Minuscule 90|90]], [[Minuscule 216|216]], [[Minuscule 339|339]], [[Minuscule 462|462]], [[Minuscule 466|466*]], [[Minuscule 642|642]];
* εγραφη η προς Ρωμαιους επιστολη δια Τερτιου επεμφτη δε δια Φοιβης απο Κορινθιων της εν Κεγχρεαις εκκλησιας (&quot;the epistle to the Romans was written by Tertius and was sent by Phoebus from the Corinthians of the church in [[Kechries|Cenchreae]]&quot;): only in [[Minuscule 337|337]];
* προς Ρωμαιους εγραφη απο Κορινθου δια Φοιβης της διακονου της εν Κεγχρεαις εκκλησιας (&quot;to the Romans it was written from Corinth by Phoebus the deacon of the church in Cenchreae&quot;): [[Minuscule 101|101]], [[Minuscule 241|241]], [[Minuscule 460|460]], [[Minuscule 466|466]], [[Minuscule 469|469]], [[Minuscule 602|602]], [[Minuscule 603|603]], [[Minuscule 605|605]], [[Minuscule 618|618]], 1923, 1924, 1927, 1932, followed by [[Textus Receptus]].&lt;ref&gt;Bruce M. Metzger, ''A Textual Commentary on the Greek New Testament'' (2001), p. 477.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Paul's life in relation to his epistle ==
[[File:Paul arrested.jpg|thumb|right|Saint Paul arrested by the Romans]]
For ten years before writing the letter (approx. 47–57), Paul had traveled around the territories bordering the [[Aegean Sea]] evangelizing. Churches had been planted in the Roman provinces of [[Galatia]], [[Macedonia (Roman province)|Macedonia]], [[Achaea (Roman province)|Achaia]] and [[Asia (Roman province)|Asia]]. Paul, considering his task complete, wanted to preach the gospel in [[Early centers of Christianity#Seville|Spain]], where he would not &quot;build upon another man’s foundation&quot;.{{Bibleref2c|Rom|15:20|31}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Bruce, 11-12&quot;&gt;Bruce, 11–12&lt;/ref&gt; This allowed him to visit Rome on the way, a long-time ambition of his. The letter to the Romans, in part, prepares them and gives reasons for his visit.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bruce, 11-12&quot;/&gt;

In addition to Paul's geographic location, his religious views are important. First, Paul was a [[Hellenistic Jew]] with a [[Pharisaic]] background (see [[Gamaliel]]), integral to his identity: see [[Paul the Apostle and Judaism]] for details. His concern for his people is one part of the dialogue and runs throughout the letter. Second, the other side of the dialogue is [[Road to Damascus|Paul's conversion]] and calling to follow Christ in the early 30s.

== The churches in Rome ==
{{see also|Early centers of Christianity#Rome}}
[[File:Papyrus 26 - Papyrus Oxyrhynchus 1354 - Bridwell Papyrus 1 - Epistle to the Romans 1,1-16 - verso.jpg|thumb|[[Papyrus]], [[Oxyrhynchus]], Egypt: 6th century – Epistle to the Romans 1: 1–16]]

The most probable ancient account of the beginning of Christianity in Rome is given by a 4th-century writer known as [[Ambrosiaster]]:&lt;ref&gt;TIB IX 1955 p. 367&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|It is established that there were [[Roman Jews|Jews living in Rome]] in the [[Apostolic Age|times of the Apostles]], and that those Jews who had believed [in Christ] passed on to the Romans the tradition that they ought to profess Christ but keep the law [Torah] ... One ought not to condemn the Romans, but to praise their faith, because without seeing any signs or miracles and without seeing any of the apostles, they nevertheless accepted faith in Christ, although [[Judaizers|according to a Jewish rite]].&lt;ref&gt;Ambrosius, ''Works'', iii 373.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

From Adam Clarke:
{{quote|The occasion of writing the epistle: ... Paul had made acquaintance with all circumstances of the Christians at Rome ... and finding that it was ... partly of heathens converted to Christianity, and partly of [[Jewish Christians|Jews]], who had, with many [[Judaizers|remaining prejudices]], believed in Jesus as the true Messiah, and that many contentions arose from the claims of the Gentiles to equal privileges with the Jews, and from absolute refusal of the Jews to admit these claims, unless the Gentile converts become [[Circumcision controversy in early Christianity|circumcised]]; he wrote this epistle to adjust and settle these differences.&lt;ref&gt;A.C. 1831 VI p. 3&lt;/ref&gt;}}

At this time, the [[Jew]]s made up a substantial number in Rome, and their [[synagogue]]s, frequented by many, enabled the [[Gentile]]s to become acquainted with the story of [[Jesus|Jesus of Nazareth]]. Consequently, churches composed of both Jews and Gentiles were formed at Rome. According to [[Irenaeus]], a 2nd-century [[Church Father]], the church at Rome was founded directly by the apostles [[St. Peter|Peter]] and [[Paul the Apostle|Paul]].&lt;ref&gt;Irenaeus, [http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/0103303.htm ''Against Heresies'', Book III,3,2]&lt;/ref&gt; However, many modern scholars disagree with Irenaeus, holding that while little is known of the circumstances of the church's founding, it was not founded by Paul:&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Expositor's Bible Commentary&quot;, (Ed. F.E.Gaebelein, Zondervan, 1976–92) Commentary on Romans (Introduction)&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|1=Many of the brethren went out to meet Paul on his approach to Rome. There is evidence that Christians were then in Rome in considerable numbers and probably had more than one place of meeting.|2=Easton's Bible Dictionary&lt;ref&gt;{{cite EBD|wstitle=Romans, Epistle to the}}&lt;br&gt;{{Bibleref2|Acts|28:13–15|KJV}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Note the large number of names in {{Bibleref2|Romans|16:3–15|KJV}} of those then in Rome, and verses 5, 15 and 16 indicate there was more than one church assembly or company of believers in Rome. Verse 5 mentions a church that met in the house of [[Aquila and Priscilla]]. Verses 14 and 15 each mention groupings of believers and saints.&lt;ref&gt;
[http://biblehub.com/commentaries/gsb/romans/16.htm Geneva Study Bible] on Romans 16:5, regarding the &quot;church&quot; (translated as &quot;company&quot; or congregation in some 16th-century translations) says: (b) The company of the faithful, for in so great a city as that was, there were different companies.
* [http://biblehub.com/commentaries/vws/romans/16.htm Vincent's Word Studies] (1886) on Romans 16:5 says: The phrase ''church that is in their'' (or his) ''house'' occurs 1 Corinthians 16:19, of Aquila and Priscilla; Colossians 4:15, of Nymphas; Plm 1:2, of Philemon. A similar gathering may be implied in Romans 16:14, Romans 16:15. Bishop Lightfoot says there is no clear example of a separate building set apart for christian worship within the limits of the Roman Empire before the third century.
* [http://biblehub.com/commentaries/pnt/romans/16.htm People's New Testament] (PNT 1891) on Romans 16:5 says: . As the early Christians had no houses of worship, they met in the homes of prominent brethren. In the large cities there would be several such groups. One of these in Rome met in the house of Priscilla and Aquila.
* and PNT on verse 16:15 says: ''And all the saints which are with them''. Probably another household church, which met with those just named.
&lt;/ref&gt;

Jews were expelled from Rome because of disturbances around AD 49 by the [[edict]] of [[Claudius]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleref2|Acts|18:1–2|9|Acts 18:1–2}} &quot;After these things Paul departed from Athens, and came to Corinth; &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; And found a certain Jew named Aquila, born in Pontus, lately come from Italy, with his wife Priscilla; (because that Claudius had commanded all Jews to depart from Rome:) and came unto them.&quot;
* [[Suetonius]]' ''[[Lives of the Twelve Caesars]]'', [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Suetonius/12Caesars/Claudius*.html#25.4 Claudius XXV.4] &quot;4 Since the Jews constantly made disturbances at the instigation of Chrestus,&lt;sup&gt;75&lt;/sup&gt; he expelled them from Rome.&quot;
* [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Suetonius/12Caesars/Claudius*.html#note75 Note-75]
* see also [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Tacitus/Annals/15B*.html#44 Tacitus, Annals — Book XV Chapters 44 concerning Christus]
&lt;/ref&gt; Fitzmyer claims that both Jews and Jewish Christians were expelled as a result of their infighting.{{sfn|Fitzmyer|1993|p=77}} [[Claudius]] died around the year AD 54, and his successor, [[Emperor Nero]], allowed the Jews back into Rome, but then, after the [[Great Fire of Rome]] of 64, Christians were persecuted.  Fitzmyer argues that with the return of the Jews to Rome in 54 new conflict arose between the Gentile Christians and the Jewish Christians who had formerly been expelled.&lt;ref&gt;Fitzmyer 1993, p. 77 also argues that this may be what Paul is referring to when he talks about the &quot;strong&quot; and the &quot;weak&quot; in {{Bibleref2|Romans|15}}; this theory was originally put forth by W. Marxsen, ''Introduction to the New Testament: An Approach to its problems'' (Philadelphia: Fortress, 1968) but is critiqued and modified by Fitzmyer. Fitzmyer's main contention is that Paul seems to be purposefully vague. Paul could have been more specific if he wanted to address this problem specifically.&lt;/ref&gt; Keck thinks Gentile Christians may have developed a dislike of or looked down on Jews (see also [[Antisemitism]] and [[Responsibility for the death of Jesus]]), because they [[Supersessionism|theologically rationalized]] that Jews were no longer God's people.&lt;ref&gt;Leander E. Keck, ''The New Interpreter's Bible'', 407&lt;/ref&gt;

== Style ==
Scholars often have difficulty assessing whether Romans is a [[Letter (message)|letter]] or an [[epistle]], a relevant distinction in [[Form criticism|form-critical]] analysis:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
A letter is something non-literary, a means of communication between persons who are separated from each other. Confidential and personal in nature, it is intended only for the person or persons to whom it is addressed, and not at all for the public or any kind of publicity...An Epistle is an artistic literary form, just like the dialogue, the oration, or the drama. It has nothing in common with the letter except its form: apart from that one might venture the paradox that the epistle is the opposite of a real letter. The contents of the epistle are intended for publicity—they aim at interesting &quot;the public.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[A. Deissmann]], ''Light from the Ancient East, 2nd ed'' (London: Hodder &amp; Stoughton, 1927), 218, 220&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Joseph Fitzmyer argues, from evidence put forth by Stirewalt, that the style of Romans is an &quot;essay-letter.&quot;{{sfn|Fitzmyer|1993|p=69}} [[Philip Melanchthon]], a writer during the [[Protestant Reformation|Reformation]], suggested that Romans was ''caput et summa universae doctrinae christianae'' (&quot;a summary of all Christian doctrine&quot;).{{sfn|Fitzmyer|1993|p=74}} While some scholars{{who|date= November 2018}} suggest, like Melanchthon, that it is a type of theological treatise, this view largely ignores chapters 14 and 15 of Romans. There are also many &quot;noteworthy elements&quot; missing from Romans that are included in other areas of the Pauline corpus.&lt;ref&gt;Fitzmyer 1993, p. 74, who notes that the Ekklesia, Eucharist and eschatology (especially the parousia) are not present in Romans&lt;/ref&gt; The breakdown of Romans as a treatise began with [[F.C. Baur]] in 1836 when he suggested &quot;this letter had to be interpreted according to the historical circumstances in which Paul wrote it.&quot;{{sfn|Fitzmyer|1993|p=74}}

Paul sometimes uses a style of writing common in his time called a &quot;diatribe&quot;. He appears to be responding to a &quot;heckler&quot; (probably an imaginary one based on Paul's encounters with real objections in his previous preaching), and the letter is structured as a series of arguments. In the flow of the letter, Paul shifts his arguments, sometimes addressing the Jewish members of the church, sometimes the Gentile membership and sometimes the church as a whole.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The church epistles: Romans to Thessalonians|last=Bullinger|first=E. W.|publisher=Eyre &amp; Spottiswoode.|year=1905|isbn=|location=London|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Purposes of writing ==
To review the current scholarly viewpoints on the purpose of Romans, along with a bibliography, see ''Dictionary of Paul and His Letters''.&lt;ref&gt;s.v. &quot;Romans, Letter to the&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; For a 16th-century &quot;Lollard&quot; reformer view, see the work of [[William Tyndale]]. In his prologue to his translation of the book of Romans, which was largely taken from the prologue of German Reformer [[Martin Luther]], Tyndale writes that:
&lt;blockquote&gt;... this epistle is the principal and most excellent part of the new testament, and most pure evangelion, that is to say glad tidings and what we call the gospel, and also a light and a way in unto the whole scripture ... The sum and whole cause of the writings of this epistle, is, to prove that a man is justified by faith only: which proposition whoso denieth, to him is not only this epistle and all that Paul writeth, but also the whole scripture, so locked up that he shall never understand it to his soul's health. And to bring a man to the understanding and feeling that faith only justifieth, Paul proveth that the whole nature of man is so poisoned and so corrupt, yea and so dead concerning godly living or godly thinking, that it is impossible for her to keep the law in the sight of God.&lt;ref&gt;Tyndale's New Testament, edited by David Daniel (Yale University Press, London and New Haven, 1989), 223&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

== Contents ==
[[File:Codex Alexandrinus 088a - Ro 1,1 ff.jpg|thumb|The beginning of the Epistle in [[Codex Alexandrinus]]]]This essay-letter composed by Paul was written to a specific audience at a specific time; to understand it, the situations of both Paul and the recipients must be understood.

=== Prologue ([[Romans 1|1:1–15]]) ===

====Greeting ([[Romans 1|1:1–7]])====
The introduction{{Bibleref2c|Rom|1:1–16}} provides some general notes about Paul. He introduces [[Apostle (Christian)#The Apostle of the Gentiles: Paul the Apostle|his apostleship]] here and introductory notes about the gospel he wishes to preach to the church at Rome. Jesus' human line stems from [[David]].{{Bibleref2c-nb|Rom|1:3}} Paul, however, does not limit his ministry to Jews. Paul's goal is that the [[Gentiles]] would also hear the [[gospel]].{{Bibleref2c-nb|Ro|1:5}}

====Prayer of Thanksgiving ([[Romans 1|1:8–15]])====
He commends the Romans for  [[faith]].{{Bibleref2c-nb|Rom|1:8}} Paul also speaks of the past obstacles that have blocked his coming to Rome earlier.{{Bibleref2c-nb|Ro|1:11–13}}

=== Salvation in the Christ ([[Romans 1|1:16]] [[Romans 8|–8:39]]) ===

====Righteousness of God ([[Romans 1|1:16–17]])====
Paul's announcement that he is not &quot;ashamed&quot; (''epaiscúnomai'') of his gospel because it holds power (''dúnamis''). These two verses form a backdrop for the rest of the book. First, we note that Paul is unashamed of his love for this gospel that he preaches about Jesus Christ. He also notes that he is speaking to the &quot;Jew first.&quot;{{Bibleref2c-nb|Ro|1:16}} There is significance to this, but much of it is scholarly conjecture as the relationship of [[Paul the Apostle and Judaism]] is still debated. We are hard-pressed to find an answer to such a question without knowing more about the audience in question. Wayne Brindle argues, based on Paul's former writings against the [[Judaizers]] in [[Epistle to the Galatians|Galatians]] and [[2&amp;nbsp;Corinthians]], that rumors had probably spread about Paul totally negating the Jewish existence in a Christian world (see also [[Antinomianism#Antinomianism in the New Testament|Antinomianism in the New Testament]] and [[Supersessionism]]). Paul may have used the &quot;Jew first&quot; approach to counter such a view.&lt;ref&gt;W.A. Brindle, &quot;To The Jew First: Rhetoric, Strategy, History, or Theology?&quot; ''Bibliotheca Sacra'' 159 (2002): 221&lt;/ref&gt;

====Condemnation: The Universal corruption of Gentiles and Jews ([[Romans 1|1:18]] [[Romans 3|–3:20]])====

===== The judgment of God ([[Romans 1|1:18–32]]) =====
Paul begins with a summary of Hellenistic Jewish apologist discourse.&lt;ref&gt;J. C. O'Neill, ''Paul's Letter to the Romans'' (Penguin, 1975); E. P. Sanders, ''Paul, the Law, and Jewish People'' (Fortress, 1983); Calvin Porter, 'Romans 1.18-32: Its Role in Developing the Argument (New Testament Studies, Cambridge University Press, 1994); Scot McKnight, ''Reading Romans Backwards: A Gospel of Peace in the Midst of Empire'' (Baylor, 2019)&lt;/ref&gt; His summary begins by suggesting that humans have taken up ungodliness and wickedness for which there already is [[Divine retribution|wrath from God]].{{Bibleref2c-nb|Ro|1:18}} People have taken God's invisible image and made him into an [[Idolatry and Christianity|idol]]. Paul draws heavily here from the [[Wisdom of Solomon]].&lt;ref&gt;for all of these comparisons see Ben Witherington's commentary on Romans, p. 63 which is available on a limited preview basis from Google books.&lt;/ref&gt; This summary condemns [[Non-traditional sexual relationships|&quot;unnatural sexual behavior&quot;]] and warns that such behavior has already resulted in a depraved body and mind (&quot;reprobate mind&quot; in the King James Version) {{Bibleref2c-nb|Ro|1:26–27}} and says that people who do such things (including murder and wickedness {{Bibleref2c-nb|Ro|1:29}}) are worthy of death.{{Bibleref2c-nb|Ro|1:32}} Paul stands firmly against the [[Imperial cult (ancient Rome)|idol worship system which was common in Rome]]. Several scholars believe the passage is a non-Pauline [[Interpolation (manuscripts)|interpolation]].&lt;ref&gt;Percy Neale Harrison, ''Paulines and Pastorals'' (London: Villiers Publications, 1964), 80–85; Robert Martyr Hawkins, ''The Recovery of the Historical Paul'' (Nashville, TN: Vanderbilt University Press, 1943), 79–86; Alfred Firmin Loisy, ''The Origins of the New Testament'' (New Hyde Park, NY: University Books, 1962), 250; ibid., ''The Birth of the Christian Religion'' (New Hyde Park, NY: University Books, 1962), 363 n. 21; Winsome Munro, ''Authority in Paul and Peter: The Identification of a Pastoral Stratum in the Pauline Corpus and 1 Peter'', SNTSMS 45 (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1983), 113; John C. O'Neill, ''Paul's Letter to the Romans'' (Harmondsworth: Penguin Books, 1975), 40–56; William O. Walker, Jr., &quot;Romans 1.18–2.29: A Non-Pauline Interpolation?&quot; ''New Testament Studies'' 45, no. 4 (1999): 533–52.&lt;/ref&gt;

===== Paul's warning of hypocrites ([[Romans 2|2:1–4]]) =====

On the traditional [[Protestant]] interpretation, Paul here calls out Jews who are condemning others for not following the law when they themselves are also not following the law. Stanley Stowers, however, has argued on rhetorical grounds that Paul is in these verses not addressing a Jew at all but rather an easily recognizable caricature of the typical boastful person (ὁ ἀλαζων). Stowers writes, &quot;There is absolutely no justification for reading {{Bibleref2-nb|Ro|2:1–5}} as Paul's attack on 'the hypocrisy of the Jew.' No one in the [[Christianity in the 1st century|first century]] would have identified ''ho alazon'' with Judaism. That popular interpretation depends upon anachronistically reading later Christian characterizations of Jews as 'hypocritical [[Pharisees]]'&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Stowers, ''A Rereading of Romans''. Yale Press, 1994, p. 101&lt;/ref&gt; See also [[Anti-Judaism]].

==== Justification: The Gift of Grace and Forgiveness through Faith ([[Romans 3|3:21]] [[Romans 5|–5:11]]) ====

Paul says that a righteousness from God has made itself known apart from the law, to which the [[Torah|law]] and [[Neviim|prophets]] testify, and this righteousness from God comes through faith in Jesus to all who believe.{{Bibleref2c-nb|Ro|3:21–22}} He describes [[Justification (theology)|justification]] – legally clearing the believer of the guilt and penalty of sin – as a gift of God,{{Bibleref2c-nb|Ro|3:24}} and not the work of man (lest he might boast), but by faith.{{Bibleref2c-nb|Ro|3:28}}

==== Assurance of salvation ([[Romans 5|5]] [[Romans 11|–11]]) ====

In chapters five through eight, Paul argues that believers can be [[Assurance (theology)|assured]] of their [[hope]] in [[salvation]], having been freed from the bondage of sin. Paul teaches that through [[faith]],{{Bibleref2c-nb|Rom|3:28|KJV}} {{Bibleref2c-nb|Rom|4:3|KJV}} the faithful have been joined with [[Jesus]]{{Bibleref2c-nb|Rom|5:1|KJV}} and freed from sin.{{Bibleref2c-nb|Rom|6:1–2|KJV}} {{Bibleref2c-nb|Rom|6:18|KJV}} Believers should celebrate in the assurance of salvation{{Bibleref2c-nb|Rom|12:12|KJV}} and be certain that no external force or party can take their salvation away from them.{{Bibleref2c-nb|Rom|8:38-39|KJV}}&lt;ref&gt;These verses are commonly quoted to provide evidence of [[eternal security]]; however, groups who oppose eternal security state that this does not take into account the individual believer choosing voluntarily to leave Christianity.&lt;/ref&gt;  This promise is open to everyone since everyone has sinned,{{Bibleref2c-nb|Rom|3:23|KJV}} save the one who paid for all of them.{{Bibleref2c-nb|Rom|3:24|KJV}}

In {{Bibleref2|Romans|9–11||chapters 9–11}} Paul addresses the faithfulness of [[God]] to the [[Israelites]], where he says that God has been faithful to his promise. Paul hopes that all Israelites will come to realize the truth{{Bibleref2c-nb|Rom|9:1–5|KJV}} since he himself is also an Israelite,{{Bibleref2c-nb|Rom|11:1|KJV}} and had in the past been a persecutor of [[Early Christians]]. In {{Bibleref2|Romans|9–11}} Paul talks about how the nation of Israel has been cast away, and the conditions under which Israel will be God's chosen nation again: when Israel returns to its faith, sets aside its unbelief.{{Bibleref2c-nb|Rom|11:19–24|KJV}}

In {{Bibleref2|Romans|7:1|KJV}}, Paul says that humans are under the law while we live: &quot;Know ye not...that the law hath dominion over a man as long as he liveth?&quot; However, Jesus' death on the cross makes believers dead to the law ({{Bibleref2-nb|Rom|7:4|KJV}}, &quot;Wherefore, my brethren, ye are also become dead to the law by the [[body of Christ]]&quot;), according to [[Antinomianism#Pauline passages supporting antinomianism|an antinomistic interpretation]].

===Transformation of believers ([[Romans 12|12]] [[Romans 15|–15:13]])===
From chapter 12 through the first part of chapter 15, Paul outlines how the [[Gospel]] transforms believers and the behaviour that results from such a transformation. This transformation is described as a &quot;renewing of your mind&quot; (12:2),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blueletterbible.org/Bible.cfm?b=Rom&amp;c=12&amp;t=NASB#s=t_conc_1058002|title=Blue Letter Bible|work=Blue Letter Bible}}&lt;/ref&gt; a transformation that [[Douglas J. Moo]] characterizes as “the heart of the matter.”&lt;ref&gt;Douglas J. Moo, ''The Epistle to the Romans (Eerdmans'', 1996), 748.&lt;/ref&gt; It is a transformation so radical that it amounts to “a transfiguration of your brain,” a &quot;[[Metanoia (theology)|metanoia]]&quot;, a “mental revolution.”&lt;ref&gt;Edward J Anton, ''Repentance: A Cosmic Shift of Mind and Heart'' (Discipleship Publications, 2005) 30.&lt;/ref&gt;

Paul goes on to describe how believers should live. Christians are no longer under the law, that is, no longer bound by the law of Moses,&lt;ref&gt;[[Douglas J. Moo]], ''Romans: The NIV Application Commentary: From Biblical Text to Contemporary Life'' (Zondervan, 2000), 399.&lt;/ref&gt; but under the grace of God, see [[Law and grace]]. We do not need to live under the law because to the extent our minds have been renewed, we will know &quot;almost instinctively&quot; what God wants of us. The law then provides an &quot;objective standard&quot; for judging progress in the &quot;lifelong process&quot; of our mind's renewal.&lt;ref&gt;Douglas J. Moo, ''The Epistle to the Romans'' (Eerdmans, 1996), 756–758.&lt;/ref&gt;

To the extent they have been set free from [[sin]] by renewed minds (Romans 6:18),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blueletterbible.org/Bible.cfm?b=Rom&amp;c=6&amp;t=NASB&amp;ss=1#s=t_conc_1052018|title=Blue Letter Bible|work=Blue Letter Bible}}&lt;/ref&gt; believers are no longer bound to sin. Believers are free to live in obedience to God and love everybody. As Paul says in Romans 13:10, &quot;love (ἀγάπη) worketh no ill to his neighbor: therefore love is the fulfilling of law&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blueletterbible.org/Bible.cfm?b=Rom&amp;c=13&amp;t=KJV&amp;ss=1#s=1059010|title=Blue Letter Bible|work=Blue Letter Bible}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Obedience to earthly powers ([[Romans 13|13:1–7]]) ====
The fragment in Romans 13:1–7 dealing with obedience to earthly powers is considered by some, for example [[James Kallas]],&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20140424030124/http://www.swordandploughshare.com/main-blog/2010/9/30/romans-131-7-an-interpolation.html The Sword and the Ploughshare ''Romans 13:1–7 an Interpolation?'']&lt;/ref&gt; to be an [[Interpolation (manuscripts)|interpolation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://hodos.org/romans/Paul%20and%20Empire%20-%20book%20report.htm |title=Review of the book ''Paul and Empire – Religion and Power in Roman Imperial Society'' (Edited by Richard A. Horsley) |access-date=2012-11-01 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130420174100/http://hodos.org/romans/Paul%20and%20Empire%20-%20book%20report.htm |archive-date=2013-04-20 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; (See also the [[Great Commandment]] and [[Christianity and politics]]). [[Paul Tillich]] accepts the historical authenticity of Romans 13:1–7, but claims it has been misinterpreted by churches with an anti-revolutionary bias:
&lt;blockquote&gt;One of the many politico-theological abuses of biblical statements is the understanding of Paul’s words [Romans 13:1–7] as justifying the anti-revolutionary bias of some churches, particularly the Lutheran. But neither these words nor any other New Testament statement deals with the methods of gaining political power. In Romans, Paul is addressing eschatological enthusiasts, not a revolutionary political movement.&lt;ref&gt;[[Paul Tillich]], ''Systematic Theology'', volume 3 ([[University of Chicago Press]]: 1963), p. 389.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Epilogue ([[Romans 15|15:1]] [[Romans 16|–16:23]])===
* Admonition ([[Romans 15|15:1–7]])
* Summary of the Epistle ([[Romans 15|15:8]])

====Paul's ministry and travel plans ([[Romans 16|16:14–27]])====

The concluding verses contain a description of his travel plans, personal greetings and salutations. One-third of the twenty-one Christians identified in the greetings are [[Paul the Apostle and women|women]]. Additionally, none of these Christians answer to the name [[Saint Peter|Peter]], although according to the [[History of the Catholic Church|Catholic tradition]], he had been ruling as [[Pope]] in Rome for about 25 years. Possibly related was the [[Incident at Antioch]] between Paul and Cephas.{{citation needed|date= November 2018}}
* Personal greetings ([[Romans 16|16:1–23]] [24])
* Closing [[doxology]] ([[Romans 16|16:25–27]])

== Hermeneutics ==
{{Main|Biblical hermeneutics}}

=== Catholic interpretation ===
{{Main|Sola gratia}}

Roman Catholics accept the necessity of faith for salvation but point to {{Bibleref2|Romans|2:5–11|KJV}} for the necessity of living a [[Good works|virtuous life]] as well:&lt;ref&gt;For an authoritative discussion of the Catholic viewpoint, see ''[[Catholic Encyclopedia]]'', s.v. [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/13156a.htm &quot;Epistle to the Romans&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
But by your hard and impenitent heart you are storing up wrath for yourself on the day of wrath when God's righteous judgment will be revealed. For he will render to every man according to his works: to those who by patience in well-doing seek for glory and honor and immortality, he will give eternal life; but for those who are factious and do not obey the truth, but obey wickedness, there will be wrath and fury. There will be tribulation and distress for every human being who does evil, the Jew first and also the Greek, but glory and honor and peace for every one who does good, the Jew first and also the Greek. For God shows no partiality.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Throughout his writings, St. Augustine strongly affirms the Catholic understanding of this and other such Scriptural admonitions. In his sermons to his Catholic congregations, he is especially careful to warn them against an inordinate desire for a complete assurance of salvation. In his ''Exposition of Psalm 147'' for example, he states:&lt;ref&gt;''Works, Expositions of the Psalms (121–150)'', 2004, New City Press, {{ISBN|1-56548-210-7}} {{ISBN|9781565482104}}, Part 3, volume, 20, p. 446.[https://books.google.com/books?id=pcwHg1EszuQC&amp;pg=PA446&amp;dq=%22ought+to+be+secure+only+when+they+have+dominated+this+world%E2%80%99s+lusts%22&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q=%22ought%20to%20be%20secure%20only%20when%20they%20have%20dominated%20this%20world%E2%80%99s%20lusts%22&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The gospel warned us, &quot;Be on the watch for the last day, the day when the Son of Man will come,&quot; because it will spell disaster for those it finds secure as they are now – secure for the wrong reasons, I mean, secure in the pleasures of this world, when they ought to be secure only when they have ''dominated this world's lusts''. The apostle certainly prepares us for that future life in words of which I also reminded you on that occasion.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Again, in his ''Exposition of Psalm 85'' ([[Psalm 85]] or [[Psalm 86]]), Augustine is perhaps even more specific:&lt;ref&gt;''Works, Expositions of the Psalms (73–98)'', 2002 John E. Rotelle, ed., {{ISBN|1-56548-167-4}}, {{ISBN|978-1-56548-167-1}}, part 3, vol. 18, p. 236. [https://books.google.com/books?id=W6UsLdKZsKgC&amp;pg=PA236&amp;dq=%22Let+us+not+expect+security+while+we+are+on+pilgrimage%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=4rMbTfOQCYGs8Aak3fS1Dg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCMQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Let%20us%20not%20expect%20security%20while%20we%20are%20on%20pilgrimage%22&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Let us not expect security while we are on pilgrimage. When we do find ourselves wanting it, what we are looking for is bodily sluggishness rather than personal security.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Catholics would also look to the passage in Romans 8:13 for evidence that justification by faith is only valid so long as it is combined with obedient cooperation with The Holy Spirit, and the passage in Romans 11:22 to show that the Christian can lose their justification if they turn away from cooperating with The Holy Spirit and reject Christ through mortal sin.

=== Protestant interpretation ===
{{Main|Sola fide}}

In the Protestant interpretation, the New Testament epistles (including Romans), describes salvation as coming from faith and not from righteous actions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Concerning_Christian_Liberty|title=Concerning Christian Liberty|last=Luther|first=Martin}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, Romans {{Bibleref2-nb|Romans|4:2–5|9}} (underlining added):

: 2 For if Abraham were justified by works, he hath ''whereof''&lt;!--italics in source--&gt; to glory; but &lt;u&gt;not before God&lt;/u&gt;. 3 For what saith the scripture? Abraham &lt;u&gt;believed&lt;/u&gt; God, and it was counted unto him for righteousness. 4 Now to him that worketh is the reward not reckoned of grace, but of debt. 5 But to him that &lt;u&gt;worketh not, but believeth&lt;/u&gt; on him that justifieth the ungodly, his faith is counted unto him for righteousness.

They also point out{{Citation needed|date=June 2018}} that in Romans &lt;span class=plainlinks&gt;{{Bibleref2|Romans|2|9|chapter 2:9}}&lt;/span&gt;, Paul says that God will reward those who follow the law and then goes on to say that ''no one'' follows the law perfectly (see also [[Sermon on the Mount#Interpretations|Sermon on the Mount: Interpretation]]) Romans {{Bibleref2-nb|Rom|2:21–25|9}}:

:21 Thou therefore which teachest another, teachest thou not thyself? thou that preachest a man should not steal, dost thou steal? 22 Thou that sayest a man should not commit adultery, dost thou commit adultery? thou that abhorrest idols, dost thou commit sacrilege? 23 Thou that makest thy boast of the law, through breaking the law dishonourest thou God? 24 For the name of God is blasphemed among the Gentiles through you, as it is written. 25 For circumcision verily profiteth, if thou keep the law: but if thou be a breaker of the law, thy circumcision is made uncircumcision.

[[Martin Luther]] described Paul's letter to the Romans as &quot;the most important piece in the New Testament. It is purest Gospel. It is well worth a Christian's while not only to memorize it word for word but also to occupy himself with it daily, as though it were the daily bread of the soul&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/l/luther/romans/pref_romans.html Martin Luther's Preface to the Letter of St. Paul to the Romans] cf. Luther's comments in his treatise on ''The Adoration of the Sacrament'' (1523) in which he refers to the [[Words of Institution|words of institution]] of the [[Eucharist]] as being &quot;the sum and substance of the whole gospel&quot;. ''Luther's Works'', American Edition, St. Louis and Philadelphia: [[Concordia Publishing House]] and Fortress (Muhlenberg) Press, [https://archive.org/details/luthersworksvolu008249mbp vol. 36 (Word and Sacrament II (1959))], [https://books.google.com/books?id=FQHx9n3qBu8C&amp;pg=PA277&amp;ots=g5iYjZ6Hny&amp;dq=%22the+sum+and+substance+of+the+whole+gospel%22&amp;sig=YFKDJjhyuXrRdII_T0jrpZoA2Oo], p. 277.&lt;/ref&gt;

Luther controversially added the word &quot;alone&quot; (''allein'' in German) to Romans {{Bibleref2-nb|Romans|3:28|9;10}}&lt;!-- added Luther Bibel 1545 --&gt; so that it read: &quot;thus, we hold, then, that man is justified without doing the works of the law, ''alone'' through faith&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;The 1522 &quot;Testament&quot; reads at Romans 3:28: &quot;So halten wyrs nu, das der mensch gerechtfertiget werde, on zu thun der werck des gesetzs, ''alleyn'' durch den glawben&quot; (emphasis added to the German word for &quot;alone&quot;). [http://de.wikisource.org/wiki/Lutherbibel/R%C3%B6mer_%281522%29#Das_Dritte_Capitel]&lt;/ref&gt; The word &quot;alone&quot; does not appear in the original Greek [[Biblical manuscript|text]],&lt;ref&gt;The Greek text reads: λογιζόμεθα γάρ δικαιоῦσθαι πίστει ἄνθρωπον χωρὶς ἔργων νόμου (&quot;for we reckon a man to be justified by faith without deeds of law&quot;)[http://www-users.cs.york.ac.uk/~fisher/cgi-bin/gnt?id=0603]&lt;/ref&gt; but Luther defended his translation by maintaining that the adverb &quot;alone&quot; was required both by idiomatic German and Paul's intended meaning. This is a ''&quot;literalist view&quot;'' rather than a [[Literal translation|literal view]] of the Bible.&lt;ref&gt;Martin Luther, ''On Translating: An Open Letter'' (1530), Luther's Works, 55 vols., (St. Louis and Philadelphia: Concordia Publishing House and Fortress Press), 35:187–189, 195; cf. also Heinz Bluhm, ''Martin Luther Creative Translator'', (St. Louis: Concordia Publishing House, 1965), 125–137.&lt;/ref&gt;

Apologist James Swan lists numerous Catholic sources that also translated [[Romans 3#Verse 28|Romans 3:28]] with the word &quot;alone,&quot; or testified to others doing so before Luther.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last=Swan|first=James|title=Luther Added The Word &quot;Alone&quot; to Romans 3:28?|url= http://beggarsallreformation.blogspot.com/2006/02/luther-added-word-alone-to-romans-328.html |work=February 05, 2006|accessdate=29 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; A Bible commentary published in 1864 reports that:

{{quote|Catholic translators before the time of Luther had given the same translation. So in the Nuremberg Bible, 1483, &quot;Nur durch den glauben.&quot; And the Italian Bibles of Geneva, 1476, and of Venice, 1538, ''per sola fede''. The Fathers also often use the expression, &quot;man is justified by faith alone;&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Hodge, Charles, ''Commentary on the Epistle to the Romans'' (New Edition), 1864, p. 100&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The ''Romans Road'' (or ''Roman Road'') refers to a set of scriptures from Romans that Christian evangelists use to present a clear and simple case for personal salvation to each person, as all the verses are contained in one single book, making it easier for evangelism without going back and forth through the entire New Testament. The core verses used by nearly all groups using ''Romans Road'' are: Romans {{bibleref2-nb|Romans|3:23|9}}, {{bibleref2-nb|Romans|6:23|9}}, {{bibleref2-nb|Romans|5:8|9}}, {{bibleref2-nb|Romans|10:9|9}}, and {{bibleref2-nb|Romans|10:13|9}}.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.gotquestions.org/Romans-road-salvation.html What is the Romans Road to salvation?], from Got Questions?&lt;/ref&gt;

Romans has been at the forefront of several major movements in Protestantism. [[Martin Luther]]'s lectures on Romans in 1515–1516 probably coincided&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
| last       = Wiersma
| first      = Hans
| date       = 9 September 2019
| title      = Martin Luther's Lectures On Romans (1515-1516): Their Rediscovery And Legacy | url        = http://wordandworld.luthersem.edu/issues.aspx?article_id=4123
| journal    = Word &amp; World: Theology for Christian Ministry
| volume     = Vol. 39
| issue      = Romans
| access-date = 14 February 2020
}} &lt;/ref&gt; with the development of his criticism of [[Roman Catholic Church|Roman Catholicism]] which led to the [[95 Theses]] of 1517. In 1738, while hearing Luther's Preface to the Epistle to the Romans read at [[St. Botolph]] Church on [[Aldersgate Street]] in London, [[John Wesley]] famously felt his heart &quot;strangely warmed&quot;, a conversion experience which is often seen{{Citation needed|date=June 2018}} as the beginning of [[Methodism]]. In 1919 [[Karl Barth]]'s commentary on Romans, ''[[The Epistle to the Romans (Barth)|The Epistle to the Romans]]'', was the publication which is widely seen as the beginning of [[neo-orthodoxy]].{{Citation needed|reason=Your explanation here|date=October 2016}}

== See also ==
* [[The Epistle to the Romans (Barth)|''The Epistle to the Romans'' (Barth)]]
* [[Loci Communes]]
* [[New Perspective on Paul]]
* [[Paul the Apostle and Judaism]]
* Rudyard Kipling 1919 poem &quot;[[The Gods of the Copybook Headings]]&quot; &quot;The Wages of Sin is Death.&quot; Romans 6:23
* [[The Justice of God in the Damnation of Sinners]], sermon on Romans 3:19
* [[Textual variants in the New Testament#Epistle to the Romans|Textual variants in the Epistle to the Romans]]

== Notes ==
{{Reflist}}

== References ==
* {{cite book | author = Bruce, F. F. |authorlink= F. F. Bruce | year = 1983 | title = The Epistle of Paul to the Romans: An Introduction and Commentary |series= [[Tyndale New Testament Commentaries]] | publisher = Inter-Varsity Press |location= Leicester, England | isbn = 0851118550 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | author = Dunn, J. D. G. |authorlink= James Dunn (theologian) | year = 1988a | title = Romans 1–8 |series= Word Bible Commentary | publisher = Word Books, Publisher |location= Dallas, Texas | isbn = | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | author = Dunn, J. D. G. | year = 1988b | title = Romans 9–16 |series= Word Bible Commentary | publisher = Word Books, Publisher |location= Dallas, Texas |isbn = | ref = harv}}
* {{eastons|Romans, Epistle to the}}
* {{cite book |last= Fitzmyer |first= Joseph A. |authorlink= Joseph Fitzmyer |title= Romans: A New Translation with Introduction and Commentary |series= Anchor Bible |year= 1993 |publisher= Doubleday |location= New York |isbn= | ref = harv}}
* Rutherford, Graeme (1993). ''The Heart of Christianity: Romans [chapters] 1 to 8''. Second ed. Oxford, Eng.: Bible Reading Fellowship. 248 p. {{ISBN|0-7459-2810-2}}
* {{cite book | author = Stuhlmacher, Peter | year = 1994 | title = Paul's Letter to the Romans: A Commentary | publisher = John Knox Press |location= Westminster | isbn = 0-664-25287-7| ref = harv}}

== External links ==
{{wikiquote}}
{{wiktionary|πίστις}}
{{Wikisource|Romans (Bible)|Romans}}

''Translations''
* [http://www.biblegateway.com &quot;Bible Gateway 35 languages/50 versions&quot;]
* [http://www.earlychristianwritings.com/romans.html &quot;Epistle to the Romans&quot; – Early Christian Writings]
* [http://www.gospelhall.org/bible/bible.php?passage=Romans+1 &quot;Online Bible&quot; – gospelhall.org]
* [http://www.christnotes.org/bible.php?q=Romans &quot;Romans, Online Bible&quot; – ChristNotes.org]
* [http://unbound.biola.edu &quot;Unbound Bible 100 + languages/versions&quot; – Biola University]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120801161444/http://xn-----7kcagabcx1bboelivelc9a1ae5h2keg.xn--p1ai/63_poslanie_k_rimlyanam_svyatogo_apostola_pavla.docs.htm Epistle to the Romans]
* {{librivox book | dtitle=Bible: Romans| stitle=NT 06: Romans}} Various versions

''Other''
* [http://www.vts.edu/ftpimages/95/download/download_group10628_id314975.pdf A Brief Introduction to Romans]
* [http://www.christians.eu/understanding-romans-7/ Understanding Romans 7 – www.christians.eu]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20050526100114/http://wesley.nnu.edu/wesleyan_theology/theojrnl/16-20/16-04.htm A Wesleyan Interpretation of Romans 5–8 – Jerry McCant]
* [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/13156a.htm Epistle to the Romans – Catholic Encyclopedia]
* [http://www.ccel.org/ccel/calvin/calcom38.toc.html John Calvin on Romans]
* [http://www.biblestudytools.com/dictionaries/eastons-bible-dictionary/the-romans-epistle-to.html Easton's Bible Dictionary on Romans, Epistle to the] on BibleStudyTools.com
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080730000329/http://www.ccel.org/ccel/henry/mhc6.vi_1.i.html Matthew Henry on Romans]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080626081628/http://www.chbcaudio.org/1999/09/19/justification-the-message-of-romans/ Romans Overview, by Mark Dever]
* [http://www.smashwords.com/books/view/349879 Reading Through Romans, by Michael Morrison]
* [http://www.desiringgod.org/ResourceLibrary/Sermons/BySeries/2/ Romans the Greatest Letter Ever Written: John Piper]
* [http://www.whataboutjesus.com/new-testament/romans Book by Book: Romans], by [[Wisconsin Evangelical Lutheran Synod|WELS]]-WhatAboutJesus.com

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou|[[Pauline epistles|Pauline]] [[Epistles|Epistle]]|||}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Acts of the Apostles|Acts]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=&lt;small&gt;[[New Testament]]&lt;/small&gt;
[[Books of the Bible]]}}
{{s-aft|after=[[First Epistle to the Corinthians|1 Corinthians]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{Epistle to the Romans}}
{{Books of the Bible}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Epistle To The Romans}}
[[Category:50s]]
[[Category:1st-century Christian texts]]
[[Category:Canonical epistles|Romans]]
[[Category:Epistle to the Romans| ]]
[[Category:New Testament books|Romans]]
[[Category:Pauline epistles]]</text>
      <sha1>qw4w662btzp3umeymwvd8j7aix1c7ff</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
