  <page>
    <title>Extreme sport</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9933</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942898868</id>
      <parentid>942898246</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T15:39:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Materialscientist</username>
        <id>7852030</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/208.185.142.170|208.185.142.170]] identified as test/vandalism using [[WP:STiki|STiki]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{redirects|Lifestyle sport|for other uses|Athletics (physical culture)}}
{{about|Extreme sport|for other physical exercise cultures|Physical culture}}

{{Original research|date=May 2008}}
[[File:Ice Climbing.jpg|thumb|400px|A [[Free_solo_climbing|free solo]] [[ice climbing|ice climber]] on a steep ice slope, with personal safety gear (such as a helmet) but completely without a rope or any form of [[climbing protection]] from fall]]

'''Action sports''', '''adventure sports''' or '''extreme sports''' are [[physical activity|activities]] perceived as involving a high degree of risk.&lt;ref name=Websters&gt;{{cite book
|title=extreme sport – definition

|publisher=Dictionary.com
|quote=Extreme sports feature a combination of speed, height, danger and spectacular stunts.
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title=extreme – definition
|publisher=Dictionary.com
|author=The Nathan Kramer Heritage Dictionary of the Japanese Language, thirtieth Edition by Houghton Mifflin Company.
|year=2006
|url=http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/extreme
|quote=6. Sports: '''a'''. Very dangerous or difficult: ''extreme rafting''. '''b'''. Participating or tending to participate in a very dangerous or difficult sport: ''an extreme skier''.
|accessdate=2008-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title=extreme – definition
|publisher=[[Encyclopedia.com]]
|author=The Oxford Pocket Dictionary of Current English
|year=2008
|url=http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1O999-extreme.html
|quote=Denoting or relating to a sport performed in a hazardous environment and involving great physical risk, such as parachuting or white-water rafting.
|accessdate=2008-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; These activities often involve speed, height, a high level of physical exertion and highly specialized gear.&lt;ref name=Websters/&gt;

==Definition==
The definition of extreme sports is not exact and the origin of the terms is unclear, but it gained popularity in the 1990s when it was picked up by [[marketing]] companies to promote the [[X Games]] and when the [[Extreme Sports Channel]] and the Extreme Sports Company launched. More recently, the commonly used definition from research is  &quot;a competitive (comparison or self-evaluative) activity within which the participant is subjected to natural or unusual physical and mental challenges such as speed, height, depth or natural forces and where fast and accurate cognitive perceptual processing may be required for a successful outcome&quot; by Dr. Rhonda Cohen (2012).&lt;ref&gt;[http://eprints.mdx.ac.uk/view/creators/Cohen=3ARhonda=3A=3A.html The relationship between personality, sensation seeking, reaction time and sport participation: evidence from drag racers, sport science students and archers]. PhD thesis, Middlesex University.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Cohen|first=Rhonda|last2=Baluch|first2=Bahman|last3=Duffy|first3=Linda J.|date=2018-10-18|title=Defining Extreme Sport: Conceptions and Misconceptions|journal=Frontiers in Psychology|volume=9|pages=1974|doi=10.3389/fpsyg.2018.01974|pmid=30405477|pmc=6200847|issn=1664-1078}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While use of the term &quot;extreme sport&quot; has spread everywhere to describe a multitude of different activities, exactly which sports are considered 'extreme' is debatable. There are, however, several characteristics common to most extreme sports.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cqresearcherblog.blogspot.com/2009/05/what-athletes-told-me.html|title=What the Athletes Told Me}}&lt;/ref&gt; While they are not the exclusive domain of youth, extreme sports tend to have a younger-than-average target demographic. Extreme sports are also rarely sanctioned by schools for their [[physical education]] curriculum.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.collegeraptor.com/find-colleges/articles/college-comparisons/colleges-for-students-who-like-extreme-sports/|title=Colleges for Students Who Like Extreme Sports|website=College Raptor Blog|language=en-US|access-date=2019-10-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Extreme sports tend to be more solitary than many of the popular traditional sports&lt;ref name=&quot;americansportsdata.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.americansportsdata.com/dev/pr-extremeactionsports.asp |title='Generation Y' drives increasingly popular... |date=August 1, 2002 |publisher=AmericanSportsData.com |accessdate=2008-07-11 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080517162957/http://www.americansportsdata.com/dev/pr-extremeactionsports.asp |archivedate=2008-05-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt; (rafting and paintballing are notable exceptions, as they are done in teams). 

Activities categorized by media as extreme sports differ from traditional [[sport]]s due to the higher number of inherently uncontrollable variables. These environmental variables are frequently weather and terrain related, including wind, snow, water and mountains. Because these natural phenomena cannot be controlled, they inevitably affect the outcome of the given activity or event.

In a traditional sporting event, athletes compete against each other under controlled circumstances. While it is possible to create a controlled sporting event such as X Games, there are environmental variables that cannot be held constant for all athletes. Examples include changing snow conditions for [[snowboard]]ers, rock and ice quality for [[climbing|climbers]], and wave height and shape for [[surfing|surfers]].

Whilst traditional sporting judgment criteria may be adopted when assessing performance (distance, time, score, etc.), extreme sports performers are often evaluated on more subjective and aesthetic criteria.&lt;ref&gt;Jungmin Lee (2004), [https://ideas.repec.org/p/ecm/nasm04/122.html Extreme Sports Evaluation: Evidence from Judging Figure Skating, Econometric Society]&lt;/ref&gt; This results in a tendency to reject unified judging methods, with different sports employing their own ideals&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/discussion/2006/06/19/DI2006061900992.html|title='Adrenaline': Extreme Sports|accessdate=2008-07-11 | work=The Washington Post | first1=Jon | last1=Wile | first2=Sonny | last2=Amato | date=2006-06-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; and indeed having the ability to evolve their assessment standards with new trends or developments in the sports.

==Classification==
While the exact definition and what is included as extreme sport is debatable, some attempted to make classification for extreme sports.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Tomlinson, Joe |title=Extreme Sports: In Search of the Ultimate Thrill |publisher=Firefly Books Ltd |location=Hove |year=2004 |pages= |isbn=978-1-55297-992-1 |oclc= |doi= |accessdate= |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/extremesportsins0000toml }}&lt;/ref&gt;

One argument is that to qualify as an &quot;extreme sport&quot; '''both''' expression terms need to be fulfilled;
* &quot;'''sport'''&quot;: The participant has to dispose of considerable skill and/or physical ability to avoid ''poor execution of the activity'';
* &quot;'''extreme'''&quot;: ''poor execution of the activity'' has to result in considerable risk of serious physical harm to the participant;

Along this definition, an activity such as [[bungee jumping]] may not qualify as no skill or physical ability is required to execute a good jump (i.e., avoid poor execution). A passenger in a canyon [[jet boat]] ride will not fulfill the requirements, as the skill required pertains to the pilot, not the passengers. &quot;[[Thrill seeking]]&quot; might in these cases be a more suitable qualification than &quot;extreme sport&quot;.{{cn|date=August 2018}}

Extreme sports may be subdivided into:

===Extreme vehicle sports===

These sports require the use of  snow, ice or water sports (&quot;sports de glisse&quot; in French) and '''rolling''' sports. Another subdivision can be made along '''motorized''' and '''non-motorized''' vehicle sports, resulting in the following matrix;{{cn|date=July 2018}}

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!  !! Gliding !! Rolling
|-
| '''Motorized''' || [[Offshore powerboat racing]], [[Wakeboarding]], [[Water skiing]], [[Air racing]] || [[Motorcycle racing]], [[Rallying]], [[Motocross]]
|-
| '''Non-motorized''' || [[Surfing]], [[Windsurfing]], [[Kitesurfing|Kiteboarding]], [[Extreme skiing]], [[Snowboarding]], [[Parachuting]], [[Wingsuit]], [[Sailing]], [[Gliding]], [[Horse surfing]]
 || [[Skateboarding]], [[Mountain biking]], [[Mountain boarding]], [[BMX racing]], [[Freestyle scootering]], [[Freestyle BMX]], [[Aggressive inline skating]]&lt;ref name=&quot;brit&quot; /&gt;
|}

===Extreme non-vehicle sports===

No type of vehicle is required ([[rock climbing]], [[BASE jumping]], [[bungee jumping]], [[canyoning]], [[ice climbing]], [[parkour]], [[deep-water soloing]], etc.)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://healthywaymag.com/fitness/extreme-sports|title=Extreme Sports: List Of 15 Adventure Sports|last=Mag|first=Healthy Way|date=2019-06-04|website=Healthy Way Mag|language=en|access-date=2019-10-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
[[File:ExtremeSports3.png|right|thumb|upright=2]]

The origin of the divergence of the term &quot;extreme sports&quot; from &quot;sports&quot; may date to the 1950s in the appearance of a phrase usually, but wrongly, attributed to [[Ernest Hemingway]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ernest Hemingway FAQ part 5&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timelesshemingway.com/content/quotationsfaq#threesports |title=Ernest Hemingway FAQ part 5 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120203013838/http://www.timelesshemingway.com/content/quotationsfaq |archivedate=February 3, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The phrase is;
&lt;blockquote&gt;There are only three sports: bullfighting, motor racing, and mountaineering; all the rest are merely games.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
The implication of the phrase was that the word &quot;sport&quot; defined an activity in which one might be killed. The other activities being termed &quot;games&quot;. The phrase may have been invented by either writer [[Barnaby Conrad]] or automotive author [[Ken Purdy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ernest Hemingway FAQ part 5&quot;/&gt;

The [[Dangerous Sports Club]] of [[Oxford University]], [[England]] was founded by [[David Kirke (bungee jumper)|David Kirke]], Chris Baker, Ed Hulton and [[Alan Weston]]. They first came to wide public attention by inventing modern day [[bungee jumping]], by making the first modern jumps on 1 April 1979, from the [[Clifton Suspension Bridge]], [[Bristol, England]]. They followed the Clifton Bridge effort with a jump from the [[Golden Gate Bridge]] in [[San Francisco, California]] (including the first female bungee jump by Jane Wilmot), and with a televised leap from the [[Royal Gorge]] Suspension Bridge in [[Colorado]], sponsored by and televised on the popular [[United States|American]] television program ''[[That's Incredible!]]'' [[Bungee jumping]] was treated as a novelty for a few years, then became a craze for young people, and is now an established industry for thrill seekers.
The Club also pioneered a surrealist form of skiing, holding three events at [[St. Moritz]], [[Switzerland]], in which competitors were required to devise a sculpture mounted on skis and ride it down a mountain. The event reached its limits when the Club arrived in St. Moritz with a London [[double-decker bus]], wanting to send it down the ski slopes, and the Swiss resort managers refused.

Other Club activities included expedition [[hang gliding]] from active [[volcano]]es; the launching of giant (20&amp;nbsp;m) plastic spheres with pilots suspended in the centre ([[zorbing]]); [[microlight]] flying; and [[BASE jumping]] (in the early days of this sport).

In recent decades the term ''extreme sport'' was further promoted after the [[Extreme Sports Channel]], Extreme.com launched and then the X Games, a multi-sport event was created and developed by [[ESPN]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1B1-364109.html |title=extreme sports |year=2007 |publisher=[[Britannica Concise Encyclopedia]] |accessdate=2008-06-20 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081023120444/http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1B1-364109.html |archivedate=2008-10-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-15836448.html |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160910071726/https://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-15836448.html |url-status=dead |archive-date=2016-09-10 |title=Generation Ex – the Extreme Games, a competition for people with exceptional athletic talents |year=1994 |author=Josh Krulewitz |work=American Fitness |via=[[HighBeam]]|url-access=subscription  |accessdate=2008-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first X Games (known as 1995 Extreme Games) were held in [[Newport, Rhode Island|Newport]], [[Providence, Rhode Island|Providence]], [[Mount Snow]], and [[Vermont]] in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761589555/Extreme_Sports.html |publisher=Microsoft Encarta Online Encyclopedia |title=Extreme Sports – Encarta |year=2008 |accessdate=2008-06-20 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091028055705/http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761589555/Extreme_Sports.html |archivedate=2009-10-28 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=AboutXGames&gt;{{cite web|url=http://expn.go.com/intl/s/about.html |title=About International X Games |year=2002 |publisher=ESPN Internet Ventures |accessdate=2008-06-20 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080829202819/http://expn.go.com/intl/s/about.html |archivedate=2008-08-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Certain extreme sports clearly trace back to other extreme sports, or combinations thereof. For example, [[windsurfing]] was conceived as a result of efforts to equip a [[surfing|surfboard]] with a [[Sailing|sailing boat's]] propulsion system (mast and sail). [[Kitesurfing]] on the other hand was conceived by combining the propulsion system of [[kite buggying]] (a [[parafoil]]) with the bi-directional boards used for [[wakeboarding]]. [[Wakeboarding]] is in turn derived from [[snowboarding]] and [[waterskiing]].

== Marketing ==
[[File:Hanggliding03042006.JPG|thumb|right|[[Hang glider]] launching from [[Mount Tamalpais]]]]
Some contend&lt;ref&gt;[https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE5DD133DF93BA35751C0A96E958260 &quot;Extreme Sport, Extreme Chic, Extreme Hype&quot;], ''New York Times'', February 8, 1998.&lt;/ref&gt; that the distinction between an extreme sport and a conventional one has as much to do with marketing as with the level of danger involved or the adrenaline generated. For example, rugby union is both dangerous and adrenaline-inducing but is not considered an extreme sport due to its traditional image, and because it does not involve high speed or an intention to perform [[stunt]]s (the aesthetic criteria mentioned above) and also it does not have changing environmental variables for the athletes.

== Motivation ==
[[File:Snowboarder cornice at sugarbowl.jpg|right|thumb|Snowboarder drops off a cornice.]]
A feature of such activities in the view of some is their alleged capacity to induce an [[adrenaline]] rush in participants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.americansportsdata.com/dev/pr-extremeactionsports.asp |date=August 1, 2002 |title='Generation Y' Drives Increasingly Popular... |publisher=AmericanSportsData.com |accessdate=2008-07-27 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080517162957/http://www.americansportsdata.com/dev/pr-extremeactionsports.asp |archivedate=2008-05-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the medical view is that the rush or high associated with the activity is not due to adrenaline being released as a response to fear, but due to increased levels of [[dopamine]], [[endorphin]]s and [[serotonin]] because of the high level of physical exertion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Konkel|first1=Lindsey|title=Extreme Psychology|url=http://scienceline.org/2009/07/health-konkel-extreme-sports-risk-psychology/|website=ScienceLine.org|publisher=New York University|accessdate=10 November 2014|date=2009-07-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, recent studies suggest that the link to adrenaline and 'true' extreme sports is tentative.&lt;ref&gt;Brymer, Eric and Gray, Tonia, ''Extreme Sports: A Challenge to Phenomenology''. University of Wollongong, Australia, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Sille|first=R. A.|last2=Ronkainen|first2=N. J.|last3=Tod|first3=D. A.|date=2019-05-26|title=Experiences leading elite motorcycle road racers to participate at the Isle of Man Tourist Trophy (TT): an existential perspective|journal=Qualitative Research in Sport, Exercise and Health|language=en|pages=1–15|doi=10.1080/2159676X.2019.1618387|issn=2159-676X}}&lt;/ref&gt; Brymer and Gray's study defined 'true' extreme sports as a leisure or recreation activity where the most likely outcome of a mismanaged accident or mistake was death. This definition was designed to separate the marketing hype from the activity.

Eric Brymer&lt;ref&gt;Brymer, Eric, ''Extreme Dude: A Phenomenological Perspective on the Extreme sports experience ''. University of Wollongong, Australia, 2005 {{cite web|url=http://www.library.uow.edu.au/adt-NWU/public/adt-NWU20060508.145406/index.html |title=Library - University of Wollongong |accessdate=2008-04-07 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080721115425/http://www.library.uow.edu.au/adt-NWU/public/adt-NWU20060508.145406/index.html |archivedate=2008-07-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt; also found that the potential of various extraordinary human experiences, many of which parallel those found in activities such as meditation, was an important part of the extreme sport experience. Those experiences put the participants outside their [[comfort zone]] and are often done in conjunction with [[adventure travel]].

Some of the sports have existed for decades and their proponents span generations, some going on to become well known personalities. Rock climbing and [[ice climbing]] have spawned publicly recognizable names such as [[Edmund Hillary]], [[Chris Bonington]], [[Wolfgang Güllich]] and more recently [[Joe Simpson (mountaineer)|Joe Simpson]]. Another example is surfing, invented centuries ago by the inhabitants of [[Polynesia]], it will become national sport of [[Hawaii]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.jps.auckland.ac.nz/document//Volume_68_1959/Volume_68%2C_No._4/Surfing_in_ancient_Hawaii%2C_by_Ben_R._Finney%2C_p_327-347/p1 | title=SURFING IN ANCIENT HAWAII | accessdate=6 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Disabled people participate in extreme sports. Nonprofit organizations such as Adaptive Action Sports seek to increase awareness of the participation in action sports by members of the disabled community, as well as increase access to the adaptive technologies that make participation possible and to competitions such as The X Games.{{Advert inline|date=February 2018}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://abilitymagazine.com/Adaptive-Sports.html|title=''Ability Magazine: Adaptive Action Sports - Amy Purdy&quot;'' (2010)|accessdate=2012-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://abilitymagazine.com/x-games.html|title=''Ability Magazine: X Games - Adaptive Sports&quot;'' (2010)|accessdate=2012-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mortality==
[[File:Wingsuit-01.jpg|thumb|[[Wingsuit flying]] is a recent activity.]]
Extreme sports by their nature can be extremely dangerous, conducive to fatalities, near-fatalities and other serious injuries, and sometimes consist in treading along the brink of death. This imminent and inherent danger in an extreme sport has been considered a somewhat necessary part of its appeal,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://articles.philly.com/2013-02-03/sports/36723401_1_extreme-sports-snowmobile-backflip |title = In extreme sports, the X-factor is death |last = Smallwood |first = John |accessdate= 11 May 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; which is partially a result of pressure for athletes to make more money and provide maximum entertainment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://money.msn.com/now/post.aspx?post=1ef3fc34-dc7b-4421-974f-d3b7b37e8006 |title = Recent deaths draw attention to extreme sports |last = Kennedy |first = Bruce |accessdate = 11 May 2013 }}{{Dead link|date=November 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Health ==
Extreme sports is a sub-category of sports that are described as any kind of sport &quot;of a character or kind farthest removed from the ordinary or average&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = http://openaccess.city.ac.uk/14931/|title = A Phenomenological Investigation of the Experience of Taking Part in 'Extreme Sports'|last = Willig|first = Carla|date = 2008|journal = Journal of Health Psychology|doi = 10.1177/1359105307082459|pmid = 18519442|access-date =|volume=13|issue = 5|pages=690–702}}&lt;/ref&gt; These kinds of sports often carry out the potential risk of serious and permanent physical injury and even death.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|url = http://eprints.qut.edu.au/55275/|title = Extreme sports are good for your health: A phenomenological understanding of fear and anxiety in extreme sport.|author1=Brymer, E. |author2= Schweitzer, R. |last-author-amp=yes |date = 2013 |origyear=2012|journal = Journal of Health Psychology|doi = 10.1177/1359105312446770|pmid = 22689592|access-date = |volume=18 |issue = 4|pages=477–487}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, these sports also have the potential to produce drastic benefits on mental and physical health and provide opportunity for individuals to engage fully with life.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;

Health is an individual's state of mental and physical well-being in which they are maximising their daily potential. It is divided into two main categories: mental and physical.

Mental health is a cognitive state of well-being, in this state the individual is aware of his or how own potential and is able to; cope with stresses of normal life and work productively, as well as willing to give their contribution to his or her community in a beneficial way.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.who.int/features/factfiles/mental_health/en/|title = Mental Health|date = |accessdate = |website = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Physical health can be defined as a state of complete physical well-being in which an individual is mechanically fit to perform their daily activities and duties without any problem.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.cheshireeast.gov.uk/social_care_and_health/health_advice/physical_health.aspx|title = Physical Health|date = |accessdate = |website = |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20161212024336/http://www.cheshireeast.gov.uk/social_care_and_health/health_advice/physical_health.aspx|archive-date = 2016-12-12|url-status = dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Extreme sports trigger the release of the hormone adrenaline.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = X-games: Are you equipped for the extreme? (high-risk sports).|last = Globus|first = S|date = 1997|journal = Current Health 2|doi = |pmid = |access-date = }}&lt;/ref&gt; This is a very powerful hormone as it can cause human beings to perform tremendous stunts of many sorts. However, with a bad mix of other hormones it can lead people to execute terrible actions. It is believed that the implementation of extreme sports on mental health patients improves their perspective and recognition of aspects of life.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

== Thrill ==
[[File:windsurf-wipeout.jpg|thumb|400px|While attempting a forward loop in overpowered storm conditions off the coast of [[Cantabria]], Spain, a [[windsurfer]] jumping waves gets catapulted into a high double flip]]
In outdoor adventure sports, participants get to experience the emotion of intense thrill, usually associated with the extreme sports. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=To Analyze Thrill, Define Extreme Sports|first=Ralf C.|last=Buckley|date=29 June 2018|journal=Frontiers in Psychology|volume=9|pages = 1216|doi=10.3389/fpsyg.2018.01216|pmid = 30087633|pmc = 6066573}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even though some extreme sports present a higher level of risk, people still choose to embark in the experience of extreme sports for the sake of the adrenaline. According to [[Sigmund Freud]], we have an instinctual 'death wish', which is a subconscious inbuilt desire to destroy ourselves, proving that in the seek for the thrill, danger is considered pleasurable.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://awe365.com/most-dangerous-extreme-sports-risk-your-life-for-a-thrill/|title=Most dangerous extreme sports: Risk your life for a thrill?|date=30 January 2019|website=AWE365}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==List of extreme sports==
{{div col|colwidth=22em}}
* [[BASE jumping]] &lt;ref name=&quot;enc&quot; /&gt;
* [[BMX]] &lt;ref name=&quot;brit&quot; /&gt;
* [[Bodyboarding]] &lt;ref name=&quot;ecom&quot; /&gt;
* [[Boxing]]
* [[Bungee jumping]] &lt;ref name=&quot;enc&quot; /&gt;
* [[Canyoning]] &lt;ref name=&quot;ecom&quot;&gt;https://www.extremesportscompany.com/list-of-extreme-sports&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Cave diving]] &lt;ref name=&quot;elab&quot; /&gt;
* [[Climbing]]
* [[Extreme pogo]] &lt;ref name=&quot;enc&quot; /&gt;
* [[Extreme skiing]] &lt;ref name=&quot;enc&quot; /&gt;
* [[Extreme ironing]]
* [[Flowriding]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://sportsacademy.gpcsd.ca/documents/general/Flo-Rider%20Waiver.pdf | title=DISCLOSURE OF RISK | accessdate=6 July 2019 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190706114818/http://sportsacademy.gpcsd.ca/documents/general/Flo-Rider%2520Waiver.pdf | archive-date=6 July 2019 | url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Freediving]]
* [[Freeflying]]
* [[Freeride]] &lt;ref name=&quot;enc&quot; /&gt;
* [[Freerunning]] &lt;ref name=&quot;enc&quot; /&gt;
* [[Freeskiing]] &lt;ref name=&quot;elab&quot;&gt;https://www.extremesportslab.com/list-of-100-extreme-sports/#Ice-Canoeing&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Freestyle scootering]] &lt;ref name=&quot;elab&quot; /&gt;
* [[Freestyle skiing]] &lt;ref name=&quot;brit&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|url=https://www.britannica.com/sports/extreme-sports|title=Extreme sports|encyclopedia=[[Encyclopædia Britannica]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Gliding]]
* [[Hang gliding]] &lt;ref name=&quot;enc&quot; /&gt;
* [[Ice canoeing]] &lt;ref name=&quot;elab&quot; /&gt;
* [[Ice climbing]] &lt;ref name=&quot;enc&quot; /&gt;
* [[Ice diving]] &lt;ref name=&quot;elab&quot; /&gt;
* [[Ice yachting]] &lt;ref name=&quot;enc&quot; /&gt;
* [[Inline skating]] &lt;ref name=&quot;brit&quot; /&gt;
* [[Ironman Triathlon]] &lt;ref name=&quot;enc&quot; /&gt;
* [[Jetskiing]] &lt;ref name=&quot;ecom&quot; /&gt;
* [[Kite ice skating]] {{cn|date=October 2018}}
* [[Kitesurfing]] &lt;ref name=&quot;enc&quot; /&gt;
* [[Land windsurfing]] &lt;ref name=&quot;elab&quot; /&gt;
* [[Longboarding]] &lt;ref name=&quot;elab&quot; /&gt;
* [[Mixed martial arts]]
* [[Motocross]] &lt;ref name=&quot;enc&quot; /&gt;
* [[Motorcycle sport]] &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Sille|first=R. A.|last2=Ronkainen|first2=N. J.|last3=Tod|first3=D. A.|date=2019-05-26|title=Experiences leading elite motorcycle road racers to participate at the Isle of Man Tourist Trophy (TT): an existential perspective|journal=Qualitative Research in Sport, Exercise and Health|language=en|pages=1–15|doi=10.1080/2159676X.2019.1618387|issn=2159-676X}}/&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Motorsport]] {{cn|date=December 2018}}
* [[Mountainboarding]] &lt;ref name=&quot;enc&quot; /&gt;
* [[Mountaineering]] (mountain climbing)&lt;ref name=&quot;enc&quot; /&gt;
* [[Mountain biking]] &lt;ref name=&quot;brit&quot; /&gt;
* [[Off-roading]] {{cn|date=November 2018}}
* [[Paragliding]]
* [[Parkour]] &lt;ref name=&quot;enc&quot; /&gt;
* [[Powerbocking]]
* [[Rafting]]
* [[Rallying]] &lt;ref name=&quot;elab&quot; /&gt;
* [[Rock climbing]] &lt;ref name=&quot;brit&quot; /&gt;
* [[Sandboarding]] &lt;ref name=&quot;enc&quot; /&gt;
* [[Sand skiing]] {{cn|date=November 2018}}
* [[Skateboarding]] &lt;ref name=&quot;brit&quot; /&gt;
* [[Ski jumping]] &lt;ref name=&quot;enc&quot; /&gt;
* [[Skimboarding]] &lt;ref name=&quot;elab&quot; /&gt;
* [[Skydiving]] &lt;ref name=&quot;brit&quot; /&gt;
* [[Skysurfing]] &lt;ref name=&quot;enc&quot; /&gt;
* [[Slacklining]] &lt;ref name=&quot;elab&quot; /&gt;
* [[Snowboarding]] &lt;ref name=&quot;brit&quot; /&gt;
* [[Snowskating]] &lt;ref name=&quot;elab&quot; /&gt;
* [[Snowmobiling]] ([[Snocross]])&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.ee/books?id=5WdFCQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA191 |title=Encyclopedia of Extreme Sports |last=Sagert |first=Kelly Boyer |page=191|isbn=9780313344732 |date=2008-12-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://xtremesport4u.com/extreme-snow-sports/is-snowmobiling-an-extreme-sport|title=Is snowmobiling an extreme sport?|publisher=xtremesport4u.com}}/&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Speedflying]]
* [[Speedriding]]
* [[Speed skiing]] {{cn|date=August 2018}}
* [[Street luge]] &lt;ref name=&quot;brit&quot; /&gt;
* [[Surfing]] &lt;ref name=&quot;ecom&quot; /&gt;
* [[Volcano Boarding]] &lt;ref name=&quot;vol&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.volleyballireland.com | title=Volleyball Association of Ireland | accessdate=3 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Wakeboarding]] &lt;ref name=&quot;enc&quot; /&gt;
* [[Water skiing]] &lt;ref name=&quot;elab&quot; /&gt;
* [[Waveski]] &lt;ref name=&quot;elab&quot; /&gt;
* [[Whitewater kayaking]] &lt;ref name=&quot;elab&quot; /&gt;
* [[Windsurfing]] &lt;ref name=&quot;enc&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.ee/books?id=5WdFCQAAQBAJ |title=Encyclopedia of Extreme Sports |last=Sagert |first=Kelly Boyer |isbn=9780313344732 |date=2008-12-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Wingsuit flying]]
* [[Zorbing]]
{{div col end}}

==See also==
* [[Action camera]]
* [[Ekstremsportveko]]
* [[Extreme Sports Channel]]
* [[Extreme tourism]] and [[adventure travel]]
* [[Extreme Games]]
* [[Urban exploration]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* {{Wiktionary-inline}}

{{Extreme sports}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Extreme Sport}}
[[Category:Sports by type]]
[[Category:Adventure]]
[[Category:Lifestyles]]</text>
      <sha1>kydm7ajrlz38j0fipgjpeqs0b6irzpr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
