  <page>
    <title>Élisabeth Vigée Le Brun</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9948</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943063814</id>
      <parentid>943063633</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T16:14:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>KylieTastic</username>
        <id>2790592</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 2 edits by [[Special:Contributions/216.213.199.89|216.213.199.89]] ([[User talk:216.213.199.89|talk]]) to last revision by Kelisi ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|18th and 19th-century French painter}}
{{Infobox artist
| name        = Élisabeth Louise Vigée Le Brun
| image       = Self-portrait in a Straw Hat by Elisabeth-Louise Vigée-Lebrun.jpg
| caption     = ''Self-Portrait with Straw Hat'', 1782
| birth_name   = Élisabeth Louise Vigée
| birth_date   = {{birth date|1755|4|16|df=y}}
| birth_place = [[Paris]], France
| death_date   = {{death date and age|1842|3|30|1755|4|16|df=y}}
| death_place  = Paris, France
| nationality = French
| field       = [[Painting]]
| training    = 
| movement    = [[Rococo]], [[Neoclassicism]]
| works       = &lt;!-- which ones are important? --&gt;
}}

'''Élisabeth Louise Vigée Le Brun''' ({{IPA-fr|e.liz.a.bɛt lwiz vi.ʒe lə.bʁœ̃|lang}}; 16 April 1755 – 30 March 1842),&lt;ref name=ExhCat&gt;{{cite book|title=Élisabeth Louise Vigée Le Brun|editor1-last=Baillio|editor1-first=Joseph|editor2-last=Salmon|editor2-first=Xavier|publisher=Éditions de la Réunion des musées nationaux—Grand Palais|location=Paris|date=2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; also known as '''Madame Lebrun''' or '''Madame Le Brun''', was a prominent French [[portrait]] [[Painting|painter]] of the late 18th century.

Her artistic style is generally considered part of the aftermath of [[Rococo]] with elements of an adopted [[Neoclassicism|Neoclassical]] style.&lt;ref name=Gardner&gt;{{cite book|title=Gardner's Art through the Ages: The Western Perspective|volume=2|editor-last=Kleiner|editor-first=Fred S.|date=2015|publisher=Cengage Learning|isbn=9781305645059|edition=15th|location=Boston|page=656}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her subject matter and color palette can be classified as Rococo, but her style is aligned with the emergence of Neoclassicism. Vigée Le Brun created a name for herself in [[Ancien Régime]] society by serving as the portrait painter to [[Marie Antoinette]]. She enjoyed the patronage of European aristocrats, actors, and writers, and was elected to art academies in ten cities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=National Museum of Women in the Arts|url=https://nmwa.org/explore/artist-profiles/%c3%a9lisabeth-louise-vig%c3%a9e-lebrun|accessdate=26 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Vigée Le Brun created some 660 portraits and 200 landscapes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/195744889|title=50 Women Artists You Should Know|author1-last=Christiane|author1-first=Weidemann|author2-last=Larass|author2-first=Petra|author3-last=Klier|author3-first=Melanie|date=2008|publisher=Prestel|location=Munich}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to many works in private collections, her paintings are owned by major museums, such as the [[Louvre]], [[Hermitage Museum]], [[National Gallery]] in London, [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]] in New York, and many other collections in continental Europe and the United States.

== Biography ==
[[File:Madame Vigee-Lebrun and her daughter, Jeanne Lucia (Julie).jpg|thumb|left|upright|''Self-Portrait with Her Daughter Julie'', 1786]]

===Early life===
Born in Paris on 16 April 1755, Élisabeth Louise Vigée was the daughter of Jeanne (née Maissin) (1728–1800), a hairdresser,&lt;ref name=&quot;ExhCat&quot; /&gt; and portraitist and fan painter, [[Louis Vigée]], from whom she received her first instruction.&lt;ref name=ExhCat/&gt; In 1760, at the age of five, she entered a convent, where she remained until 1766.&lt;ref name=ExhCat/&gt; Her father died when she was 12 years old. In 1768, her mother married a wealthy jeweller, Jacques-François Le Sèvre, and shortly after, the family moved to the [[Rue Saint-Honoré]], close to the [[Palais Royal]].&lt;ref name=Goodden&gt;{{cite book|title=The Sweetness of Life: A Biography of Elisabeth Louise Vigée Le Brun|last=Goodden|first=Angelica|publisher=André Deutsch Limited|location=London|date=1997}}&lt;/ref&gt; In her [[memoir]], Vigée Le Brun directly stated her feelings about her step-father: &quot;I hated this man; even more so since he made use of my father's personal possessions. He wore his clothes, just as they were, without altering them to fit his figure.&quot;&lt;ref name=Memoirs/&gt; During this period, Élisabeth benefited from the advice of [[Gabriel François Doyen]], [[Jean-Baptiste Greuze]], and [[Joseph Vernet]], whose influence is evident in her portrait of her younger brother, [[Étienne Vigée]] (1773).&lt;ref name=Goodden/&gt;

By the time she was in her early teens, Élisabeth was painting portraits professionally.&lt;ref name=OxfordArt&gt;{{cite web|last1=Nicholson|first1=Kathleen|title=Vigée Le Brun, Elisabeth-Louise|url=http://www.oxfordartonline.com/subscriber/article/grove/art/T089458|website=Grove Art Online. Oxford Art Online.|publisher=Oxford University Press|accessdate=21 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; After her studio was seized for her practicing without a license, she applied to the [[Académie de Saint-Luc]], which unwittingly exhibited her works in their Salon. In 1774, she was made a member of the Académie.&lt;ref name=OxfordArt/&gt; On 11 January 1776 she married Jean-Baptiste-Pierre Le Brun, a painter and art dealer. Vigée Le Brun began exhibiting her work at their home in Paris, the Hôtel de Lubert, and the Salons she held here supplied her with many new and important contacts.&lt;ref name=OxfordArt/&gt; Her husband's great-great-uncle was [[Charles Le Brun]], the first director of the French Academy under Louis XIV. Vigée Le Brun painted portraits of many of the nobility.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Karvouni|first=Evangelia|date=2014|title=Elisabeth Louise Vigee Le Brun: A Historical Survey of a Woman Artist in the Eighteenth Century|url=https://vc.bridgew.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1765&amp;context=jiws|journal=Journal of International Women's Studies|volume=15|issue=2|pages=268–285|issn=1539-8706|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 12 February 1780, Vigée-Le Brun gave birth to a daughter, [[Julie Le Brun|Jeanne Lucie Louise]], whom she called Julie and nicknamed &quot;Brunette.&quot;&lt;ref name=Memoirs/&gt;

[[File:Elisabeth_Vig%C3%A9e-Lebrun_-_Madame_Perregaux_-_WGA25078.jpg|thumb|upright|''Madame Perregaux'', 1789]]

In 1781 she and her husband toured [[Flanders]] and the [[Netherlands]], where seeing the works of the Flemish masters inspired her to try new techniques. Her ''Self-Portrait with Straw Hat'' (1782) was a &quot;free imitation&quot; of [[Peter Paul Rubens]]' ''[[Portrait of Susanna Lunden|La Chapeau de Paille]]'' (ca. 1622–25).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The National Gallery Companion Guide|edition=rev.|last=Langmuir|first=Erika|publisher=National Gallery Publications Ltd.|location=London|date=1997|pages=328–329}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nationalgallery.org.uk/paintings/elisabeth-louise-vigee-le-brun-self-portrait-in-a-straw-hat|title=Self-Portrait in a Straw Hat|website=National Gallery|accessdate=10 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dutch and Flemish influences have also been noted in ''The Comte d'Espagnac'' (1786) and ''Madame Perregaux'' (1789).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Wallace Collection's Pictures: A Complete Catalogue|author1-last=Duffy|author1-first=Stephen|author2-last=Hedley|author2-first=Jo|publisher=Unicorn Press and Lindsay Fine Art Ltd|location=London|date=2004|pages=460–462}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1787, she caused a minor public scandal when her ''Self-Portrait with Her Daughter Julie'' (1787) was exhibited at the [[Salon (Paris)|Salon of 1787]] showing her smiling and open-mouthed, which was in direct contravention of traditional painting conventions going back to antiquity. The court gossip-sheet ''[[Mémoires secrets]]'' commented: &quot;An affectation which artists, art-lovers and persons of taste have been united in condemning, and which finds no precedent among the Ancients, is that in smiling, [Madame Vigée LeBrun] shows her teeth.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Great Nation: France from Louis XIV to Napoleon|last=Jones|first=Colin|publisher=Penguin Books|location=London|date=2003|page=364|ISBN=9780140130935}}&lt;/ref&gt; In light of this and her other ''Self-Portrait with Her Daughter Julie'' (1789), [[Simone de Beauvoir]] dismissed Vigée Le Brun as narcissistic in ''[[The Second Sex]]'' (1949): &quot;Madame Vigée-Lebrun never wearied of putting her smiling maternity on her canvases.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Extracts from The Second Sex|last=Beauvoir|first=Simone de|translator=Constance Borde and Sheila Malovany-Chevallier|publisher=Vintage|date=2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Marie Antoinette and her Children by Élisabeth Vigée-Lebrun.jpg|thumb|upright|''Marie Antoinette and her Children'', 1787]]

===Marie Antoinette===
As her career blossomed, Vigée Le Brun was granted patronage by [[Marie Antoinette]].&lt;ref name=OxfordArt/&gt; She painted more than 30 portraits of the queen and her family,&lt;ref name=OxfordArt/&gt; leading to the common perception that she was the official portraitist of Marie Antoinette. At the Salon of 1783, Vigée Le Brun exhibited ''Marie-Antoinette in a Muslin Dress'' (1783), sometimes called ''Marie-Antoinette en gaulle'', in which the queen chose to be shown in a simple, informal white cotton garment.&lt;ref name=Larkin&gt;{{cite journal|title='Je ne suis plus la Reine, je suis moi': Marie-Antoinette at the Salon of 1783|last=Larkin|first=T. Lawrence|journal=Aurora: The Journal of the History of Art|volume=4|date=2003|pages=109–134}}&lt;/ref&gt; The resulting scandal was prompted by both the informality and the queen's decision to be shown in that way.&lt;ref name=Larkin/&gt; Vigée Le Brun's later ''Marie-Antoinette and her Children'' (1787) was evidently an attempt to improve the queen's image by making her more relatable to the public, in the hopes of countering the bad press and negative judgments that the queen had recently received.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Le dossier d'une oeuvre d'actualité politique: Marie-Antoinette et ses enfants par Mme Vigée Le Brun (2e partie)|last=Baillio|first=Joseph|journal=L'Oeil|number=310|date=May 1981|pages=53–60, 90–91}}&lt;/ref&gt; The portrait shows the queen at home in the [[Palace of Versailles]], engaged in her official function as the mother of the king's children, but also suggests Marie-Antoinette's uneasy identity as a foreign-born queen whose maternal role was her only true function under [[Salic law]].&lt;ref name=HydeMilam&gt;{{cite book|title=Women, Art and the Politics of Identity in Eighteenth-Century Europe|editor1-last=Hyde|editor1-first=Melissa|editor2-last=Milam|editor2-first=Jennifer|chapter=The Cradle is Empty: Elisabeth Vigée-Lebrun, Marie-Antoinette, and the Problem of Invention|author1-last=Sheriff|author1-first=Mary D.|publisher=Ashgate Publishing Company|location=Burlington, VT|date=2003|pages=164–187}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:%C3%89lisabeth_Vig%C3%A9e_Le_Brun._La_paix_ramenant_l%27abondance.jpg|thumb|left|upright|''Peace Bringing Back Abundance'', 1783]]

===Académie royale de peinture et de sculpture===
On 31 May 1783, Vigée Le Brun was received as a member of the [[Académie royale de peinture et de sculpture]].&lt;ref name=Fidière&gt;{{cite book|title=Les Femmes artistes à l'Académie royale de peinture et de sculpture|url=https://archive.org/details/lesfemmesartist00fidigoog|last=Fidière|first=Octave|publisher=Charavay Frères|location=Paris|year=1885}}&lt;/ref&gt; She was one of only 15 women to be granted full membership in the Académie between 1648 and 1793.&lt;ref name=Fidière/&gt; Her rival, [[Adélaïde Labille-Guiard]], was admitted on the same day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Auricchio|first=Laura|title=Adélaïde Labille-Guiard: Artist in the Age of Revolution|publisher=J. Paul Getty Museum|location=Los Angeles|date=2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Vigée Le Brun was initially refused on the grounds that her husband was an art dealer, but eventually the Académie was overruled by an order from [[Louis XVI of France|Louis XVI]] because Marie Antoinette put considerable pressure on her husband on behalf of her portraitist.&lt;ref name=Sheriff&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Exceptional Woman: Elisabeth Vigée-Lebrun and the Cultural Politics of Art|last=Sheriff|first=Mary D.|publisher=University of Chicago|location=Chicago|year=1996}}&lt;/ref&gt; As her [[reception piece]], Vigée Le Brun submitted an allegorical painting, ''Peace Bringing Back Abundance'' (''La Paix ramenant l'Abondance''), instead of a portrait.&lt;ref name=Sheriff/&gt; As a consequence, the Académie did not place her work within a standard [[hierarchy of genres|category of painting]]—either [[history painting|history]] or portraiture.&lt;ref name=Sheriff/&gt; Vigée Le Brun's membership in the Académie dissolved after the French Revolution because female academicians were abolished.&lt;ref name=Gardner/&gt;

=== Exile ===
In October 1789, after the arrest of the royal family during the [[French Revolution]], Vigée Le Brun fled France with her young daughter, Julie.&lt;ref name=GitaMay&gt;{{cite book|last=May|first=Gita|title=Elisabeth Vigée Le Brun: The Odyssey of an Artist in an Age of Revolution|publisher=Yale University Press|location=New Haven|year=2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her husband, who remained in Paris, claimed that Vigée Le Brun went to Italy &quot;to instruct and improve herself&quot;,&lt;ref name=Sheriff/&gt; but she certainly feared for her own safety.&lt;ref name=Memoirs&gt;{{cite book|title=The Memoirs of Elisabeth Vigée-Le Brun|translator=Siân Evans|publisher=Camden Press|location=London|year=1989}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=GitaMay/&gt;&lt;ref name=Baillio&gt;{{cite book|title=Elisabeth Louise Vigée Le Brun|last=Baillio|first=Joseph|publisher=Kimbell Art Museum|location=Fort Worth|year=1982}}&lt;/ref&gt; In her 12-year absence from France, she lived and worked in Italy (1789–92), Austria (1792–95), Russia (1795–1801), and Germany (1801).&lt;ref name=Baillio/&gt;

[[File:Elisabeth_Vig%C3%A9e-Lebrun_-_Lady_Hamilton_as_the_Persian_Sibyl.jpg|thumb|upright|''Head of Emma Hamilton as the Cumaean Sibyl'', 1792]]

====Italy====
While in Italy, Vigée Le Brun was elected to the Academy in [[Parma]] (1789) and the [[Accademia di San Luca]] in Rome (1790).&lt;ref name=Baillio/&gt; In [[Naples]], she painted portraits of [[Maria Carolina of Austria]] (sister of Marie Antoinette) and her eldest four living children: [[Maria Theresa of Naples and Sicily|Maria Teresa]], [[Francis I of the Two Sicilies|Francesco]], [[Princess Luisa of Naples and Sicily|Luisa]], and [[Maria Cristina of Naples and Sicily|Maria Cristina]].&lt;ref name=Baillio/&gt; She later recalled that Luisa &quot;was extremely ugly, and pulled such faces that I was most reluctant to finish her portrait.&quot;&lt;ref name=Memoirs/&gt; Vigée Le Brun also painted [[Allegory|allegorical]] portraits of the notorious [[Emma, Lady Hamilton|Emma Hamilton]] as [[Ariadne]] (1790) and as a [[Maenad|Bacchante]] (ca. 1792). Lady Hamilton was similarly the model for Vigée Le Brun's ''Sibyl'' (1792), which was inspired by the painted [[sibyl]]s of [[Domenichino]].&lt;ref name=Sheriff/&gt;&lt;ref name=Baillio2&gt;{{cite book|title=The Arts of France from François Ier to Napoléon Ier|editor-last=Baillio|editor-first=Joseph|publisher=Wildenstein|location=New York|year=2005|pages=325–329}}&lt;/ref&gt; The painting represents the [[Cumaean Sibyl]], as indicated by the Greek inscription on the figure's scroll, which is taken from [[Virgil]]'s fourth [[Eclogues|Eclogue]].&lt;ref name=Hottle&gt;{{cite journal|title=More Than 'a preposterous neo-classic rehash': Élisabeth Vigée Le Brun's ''Sibyl'' and its Virgilian Connotations|last=Hottle|first=Andrew D.|journal=Aurora: The Journal of the History of Art|volume=11|year=2010|pages=120–146}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Sibyl'' was Vigée Le Brun's favorite painting.&lt;ref name=Baillio/&gt; It is mentioned in her [[memoir]] more than any other work.&lt;ref name=Sheriff/&gt;&lt;ref name=Baillio/&gt; She displayed it while in [[Venice]] (1792), [[Vienna]] (1792), [[Dresden]] (1794), and [[Saint Petersburg]] (1795); she also sent it to be shown at the [[Salon (Paris)|Salon]] of 1798.&lt;ref name=Memoirs/&gt;&lt;ref name=Baillio2/&gt; Like her reception piece, ''Peace Bringing Back Abundance'' (1783), Vigée Le Brun regarded her ''Sibyl'' as a [[history painting]], the most elevated category in the Académie's hierarchy.&lt;ref name=Hottle/&gt;

[[File:Portrait_of_Princess_Maria_Josefa_Hermenegilde_von_Esterhazy_(1793)_Le_Brun.jpg|thumb|left|upright|''Princess von Esterhazy as Ariadne'', 1793]]

====Austria====
While in Vienna, Vigée Le Brun was commissioned to paint ''Princess Maria Josefa Hermengilde von Esterhazy as Ariadne'' (1793) and its [[Pendant painting|pendant]] ''Princess Karoline von Liechtenstein as Iris'' (1793).&lt;ref name=Baumstark&gt;{{cite book|title=Masterpieces from the Collection of the Princes of Liechtenstein|last=Baumstark|first=Reinhold|translator=Robert Erich Wolfe|publisher=Artemis Verlag|location=Zürich|date=1981|pages=312–313}}&lt;/ref&gt; The portraits depict the Liechtenstein sisters-in-law in unornamented Roman-inspired garments that show the influence of [[Neoclassicism]], and which may have been a reference to the virtuous republican Roman matron [[Cornelia Africana|Cornelia, mother of the Gracchi]].&lt;ref name=Baumstark/&gt;

====Russia====
[[File:Alexandra and Elena Pavlovna of Russia by E.Vigee-Lebrun (1796, Hermitage).jpg|thumb|upright|''[[Paul I of Russia#Issue|Alexandra and Elena Pavlovna]]'', 1795–97]]

In Russia, where she stayed from 1795 until 1801, she was received by the nobility and painted numerous aristocrats, including the former king of Poland, [[Stanisław August Poniatowski]], and members of the family of [[Catherine II of Russia|Catherine the Great]].&lt;ref name=Nikolenko&gt;{{cite journal|title=The Russian Portraits of Madame Vigée-Lebrun|last=Nikolenko|first=Lada|journal=Gazette des Beaux-Arts|volume=70|date=1967|pages=93–120}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the French aesthetic was widely admired in Russia,&lt;ref name=Francophiles&gt;{{cite journal|title=Russian Francophiles of the ''Dix-huitième''|journal=Apollo|number=160|date=June 1975|pages=420–451}}&lt;/ref&gt; there remained various cultural differences as to what was deemed acceptable. Catherine was not initially happy with Vigée Le Brun's portrait of her granddaughters, Elena and Alexandra Pavlovna, due to the amount of bare skin the short-sleeved gowns revealed.&lt;ref name=Memoirs/&gt; In order to please the Empress, Vigée Le Brun added sleeves. This tactic seemed effective in pleasing Catherine, as she agreed to sit herself for Vigée Le Brun (although Catherine died of a stroke before this work was due to begin).&lt;ref name=GitaMay/&gt; While in Russia, Vigée Le Brun was made a member of the Academy of Fine Arts of Saint Petersburg.&lt;ref name=OxfordArt/&gt; Much to Vigée Le Brun's dismay, her daughter Julie married Gaétan Bernard Nigris, secretary to the Director of the Imperial Theaters of Saint Petersburg.&lt;ref name=Baillio/&gt;

[[File:Marie_Louise_Elisabeth_Vig%C3%A9e-Lebrun_001.jpg|thumb|upright|''[[Madame de Staël]] as Corinne at Cape Miseno'', 1807–09]]

===Return to France and later life===
After a sustained campaign by her ex-husband and other family members to have her name removed from the list of counter-revolutionary émigrés, Vigée Le Brun was finally able to return to France in January 1802.&lt;ref name=ExhCat/&gt; She travelled to London in 1803, to Switzerland in 1807, and to Switzerland again in 1808.&lt;ref name=ExhCat/&gt; In Geneva, she was made an honorary member of the Société pour l'Avancement des Beaux-Arts. She stayed at [[Coppet]] with [[Germaine de Staël|Madame de Staël]], who appears as the title character in ''Corinne, ou l'Italie'' (1807).&lt;ref name=Goodden/&gt;

In her later years, Vigée Le Brun purchased a house in [[Louveciennes]], [[Île-de-France (region)|Île-de-France]], and divided her time between Louveciennes and Paris. She died in Paris on 30 March 1842, aged 86. She was buried at the [[Cimetière de Louveciennes]] near her old home. Her tombstone [[epitaph]] says &quot;''Ici, enfin, je repose...''&quot; (Here, at last, I rest...).{{citation needed|date=March 2019}}

Between 1835 and 1837, when Vigée Le Brun was in her 80s, she published her memoirs in three volumes (''Souvenirs'').&lt;ref name=Memoirs/&gt;

==Exhibitions==
During her lifetime, Vigée Le Brun's work was publicly exhibited in Paris at the [[Académie de Saint-Luc]] (1774), Salon de la Correspondance (1779, 1781, 1782, 1783), and [[Salon (Paris)|Salon of the Académie in Paris]] (1783, 1785, 1787, 1789, 1791, 1798, 1802, 1817, 1824).&lt;ref name=Baillio/&gt;

The first [[retrospective]] exhibition of Vigée Le Brun's work was held in 1982 at the [[Kimbell Art Museum]] in [[Fort Worth, Texas]]. The first major international retrospective exhibition of her art premiered at the [[Galeries nationales du Grand Palais]] in Paris (2015—2016) and was subsequently shown at the [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]] in [[New York City]] (2016) and the [[National Gallery of Canada]] in [[Ottawa]] (2016).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.metmuseum.org/exhibitions/listings/2016/vigee-le-brun|title=Élisabeth Vigée Le Brun: Woman Artist in Revolutionary France|website=Metropolitan Museum of Art|accessdate=10 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.gallery.ca/for-professionals/media/press-releases/elisabeth-louise-vigee-le-brun-1755-1842|title=Elisabeth Louise Vigée Le Brun (1755–1842)|website=National Gallery of Canada|accessdate=10 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Portrayal in popular culture==
In the episode &quot;The Portrait&quot; from the BBC series ''[[Let Them Eat Cake (TV series)|Let Them Eat Cake]]'' (1999), written by Peter Learmouth and starring [[Dawn French]] and [[Jennifer Saunders]], Madame Vigée Le Brun ([[Maggie Steed]]) paints a portrait of the Comtesse de Vache (Jennifer Saunders) weeping over a dead canary.{{citation needed|date=March 2019}}

Vigée Le Brun is one of only three characters in Joel Gross's ''Marie Antoinette: The Color of Flesh'' (premiered in 2007), a fictionalized historical drama about a love triangle set against the backdrop of the French Revolution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite newspaper|title=How a Queen Lost Her Heart Before She Lost Her Head|last=Genzlinger|first=Neil|newspaper=New York Times|date=11 April 2007|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/theater/reviews/11fles.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the album ''[[Nobody's Daughter]]'' is featured the cropped portrait of Marie Antoinette.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Hole Reveal New Album Art and Tracklist |url=https://www.spin.com/2010/03/hole-reveal-new-album-art-and-tracklist/ |accessdate=1 November 2019 |work=Spin |date=25 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery widths=&quot;175px&quot; heights=&quot;160px&quot; perrow=&quot;&quot; mode=&quot;packed&quot; caption=&quot;Portraits painted in France&quot;&gt;
File:Portrait Of The Artists Brother by Élisabeth Vigée-Lebrun.jpg|''Étienne Vigée'', 1773
File:Vigée-Lebrun Marie Antoinette 1783.jpg|''Portrait of Marie Antoinette'', 1783
File:Madame Grand (Noël Catherine Vorlée, 1761–1835) MET DP320094.jpg|''[[Madame Grand (Louise Élisabeth Vigée Le Brun)|Madame Grand]]'', 1783
File:Elisabeth-Louise Vigée Le Brun - Portrait of Marie Gabrielle de Gramont, Duchesse de Caderousse - Google Art Project.jpg|''Marie-Gabrielle de Gramont, Duchesse de Caderousse '', 1784
File:Vigée-Lebrun, Elisabeth-Louise - Charles-Alexandre de Calonne (1734-1802) - Google Art Project.jpg|''[[Charles-Alexandre de Calonne]]'', 1784
File:Vigée Le Brun Baronne de Crussol (RO 307).jpg|''Baronne de Crussol'', 1785
File:Elizabeth Vigee Lebrun - Portrait of Mohammed Dervish Khan 366N10007 B3Y2Q.jpg|[[Portrait of Muhammad Dervish Khan|''Muhammad Dervish Khan'']], 1788
File:Comtesse de la Châtre (Marie Charlotte Louise Perrette Aglaé Bontemps, 1762–1848) MET DP320086.jpg|''Comtesse de La Châtre'', 1789
File:Self-portrait with Her Daughter by Elisabeth-Louise Vigée Le Brun.jpg|''Self-Portrait with Her Daughter'', 1789
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;gallery widths=&quot;175px&quot; heights=&quot;160px&quot; perrow=&quot;&quot; mode=&quot;packed&quot; caption=&quot;Portraits painted in Italy&quot;&gt;
File:Francesco I von Neapel Sizilien.jpg|''Francesco di Borbone'', 1790
File:Luisa Maria Amelia Teresa di Borbone-Due Sicilie V2.jpg|''Luisa Maria Amelia di Borbone'', 1790
File:Maria Cristina by Élisabeth Vigée.jpg|''[[Portrait of Princess Maria Cristina|Maria Cristina of Bourbon]]'', 1790
File:Elisabeth Vigée-Lebrun - Portrait of Anna Pitt as Hebe - WGA25079.jpg|''[[Anne Pitt]] as Hebe'', 1792
File:LadyHamilton.jpg|[[Emma, Lady Hamilton|Emma Hamilton as a Bacchante]], ca. 1792
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;gallery widths=&quot;175&quot; heights=&quot;160&quot; mode=&quot;packed&quot; caption=&quot;Portraits painted in Austria&quot;&gt;
File:Marie Louise Elisabeth Vigée-Le Brun - Portrait de la comtesse Maria Theresia Bucquoi.jpg|''Portrait de la comtesse Maria Theresia Bucquoi'', 1793
File:Theresa, Countess Kinsky by Marie-Louise-Elisabeth Vigee-Lebrun.jpg|''Theresa, Countess Kinsky'', 1793
File:Portrait of Princess Karoline of Liechtenstein (1793) LeBrun.jpg|''Princess Karoline of Liechtenstein'', 1793
File:Countess Siemontkowsky Bystry by Vigee le Brun.jpg|''Countess Siemontkowsky-Bystry'', 1793
File:Lebrun Pelagie Sapiezyna.jpg|''Portrait of Pélagie Sapieżyna-Potocka, (1794) [[Royal Castle, Warsaw]]''
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;gallery widths=&quot;175px&quot; heights=&quot;160px&quot; perrow=&quot;&quot; mode=&quot;packed&quot; caption=&quot;Portraits painted in Russia&quot;&gt;
File:Louise Élisabeth Vigée Le Brun. The portrait of princess Ekaterina Nikolaevna Menshikova.jpg|''Princess Ekaterina Nikolaevna Menshikova'', 1795
File:Anna tolstoy Vigée-Lebrun.jpg|[[Anna Ivanovna Baryatinskaya Tolstoy]], 1796
File:Ekaterina Dolgorukaya (Baryatinsky).jpg|''[[Ekaterina Feodorovna Baryatinskaya-Dolgorukova]]'', 1796
File:Anna Alexandrovna Galitzin, nee Gruzinsky.jpg|Princess [[Ana Gruzinsky Galitzine]], 1797
File:The Barber Institute of Fine Arts - Elisabeth Vigée-Lebrun - Portrait of Countess Golovina.jpg|''[[Varvara Golovina]]'', ca. 1797–1800
File:Anna Beloselskaya-Belozerskaya by Vigée-Lebrun.jpg|''Anna Beloselskaya-Belozerskaya'', 1798
File:Vigee-Lebrun–Julie-Lebrun-as-Flora.jpg|''Julie Le Brun as Flora'', 1799
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
* [[Marie-Victoire Lemoine]]
*''[[Nobody's Daughter]]''
* [[Women artists]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Elisabeth Vigée-Lebrun}}
* [http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/author/25622 ''The Memoirs of Madame Vigée Lebrun'' at Project Gutenberg]
* [http://www.artcyclopedia.com/artists/vigee-lebrun_marie_louise_elisabeth.html Artcyclopedia entry]
* [http://www.pastellists.com Neil Jeffares, ''Dictionary of Pastellists before 1800'', Online Edition]
* [https://artuk.org/discover/artists/vigee-lebrun-elisabeth-louise-17551842 Art UK: Works of art by Vigée Le Brun in British Collections]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/19981205170835/http://www.batguano.com/vigee.html Gallery of works by Vigée Le Brun, articles, her memoirs, and biographical information]
* [http://www.metmuseum.org/exhibitions/listings/2016/vigee-le-brun ''Vigée Le Brun: Woman Artist in Revolutionary France'' at the Metropolitan Museum of Art]
* {{librivox author | id=13345}}
* [https://manpodcast.com/portfolio/no-228-katharine-baetjer-nancy-princenthal/ Katherine Baetjer: &quot;Vigée Le Brun: Woman Artist in Revolutionary France.&quot;], ''Modern Arts Notes Podcast''

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Vigee Le Brun, Elisabeth Louise}}
[[Category:1755 births]]
[[Category:1842 deaths]]
[[Category:18th-century French painters]]
[[Category:18th-century women artists]]
[[Category:19th-century French painters]]
[[Category:19th-century French women artists]]
[[Category:Artists from Paris]]
[[Category:French memoirists]]
[[Category:French neoclassical painters]]
[[Category:French portrait painters]]
[[Category:French women painters]]
[[Category:French women writers]]
[[Category:Rococo painters]]
[[Category:Women memoirists]]
[[Category:Le Brun family|Elisabeth]]
[[Category:Vigée family|Elisabeth]]
[[Category:Pastel artists]]</text>
      <sha1>ihh7bfcr8o9ddqsh1jke4nmu128v9te</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
