  <page>
    <title>Eyes Wide Shut</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9979</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943103863</id>
      <parentid>942954757</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T21:21:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>35.138.51.93</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Cast */Added content</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2019}}
{{short description|1999 British-American drama film directed by Stanley Kubrick}}
{{other uses}}

{{Infobox film
| name                 = Eyes Wide Shut
| image                = Eyes Wide Shut (1999).png
| alt                  = A framed image of a nude couple kissing – she with her eye open – against a purple background. Below the picture frame are the film's credits.
| caption              = Theatrical release poster
| director             = [[Stanley Kubrick]]
| producer             = Stanley Kubrick
| screenplay           = {{ubl|Stanley Kubrick|[[Frederic Raphael]]}}
| based on             = {{Based on|''[[Traumnovelle]]''&lt;!--- Credited in the film as &quot;Traumnovelle&quot; ---&gt;|[[Arthur Schnitzler]]}}
| starring             = {{Plain list|
* [[Tom Cruise]]
* [[Nicole Kidman]]
* [[Sydney Pollack]]
* [[Marie Richardson]]
}}
| music                = [[Jocelyn Pook]]
| cinematography       = [[Larry Smith (cinematographer)|Larry Smith]]
| editing              = Nigel Galt
| studio               = {{ubl|[[Hawk Films|Stanley Kubrick Productions]]|Pole Star|Hobby Films}}
| distributor          = [[Warner Bros. Pictures]]
| released             = {{Film date|1999|07|16|United States|1999|09|10|United Kingdom}}
| runtime              = 159 minutes&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=EYES WIDE SHUT |url=http://www.bbfc.co.uk/releases/eyes-wide-shut-1970-5 |publisher=[[British Board of Film Classification]] |accessdate=September 29, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| country              = {{ubl|United Kingdom|United States&lt;ref name =&quot;BFI&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Eyes Wide Shut (1999) |url=http://explore.bfi.org.uk/4ce2b7f5aa12a |publisher=[[British Film Institute]] |accessdate=December 2, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
| language             = English
| budget               = $65 million&lt;ref name=&quot;Mojo&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Eyes Wide Shut (1999) |url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=eyeswideshut.htm |website=[[Box Office Mojo]] |accessdate=December 24, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| gross                = $162.1 million&lt;ref name=&quot;Mojo&quot; /&gt;
}}
'''''Eyes Wide Shut''''' is a 1999 [[Sex in film|erotic]] [[mystery film|mystery]] [[psychological]] [[Drama (film and television)|drama film]]&lt;!-- Before changing to &quot;erotic thriller&quot; with citation, address issues in new article section Genre and Marketing below. See also WP policy [[WP:UNDUE]]--&gt; directed, produced and co-written by [[Stanley Kubrick]]. Based on the 1926 [[novella]] ''[[Dream Story|Traumnovelle]]'' (''Dream Story'') by [[Arthur Schnitzler]], the story is transferred from early 20th-century Vienna to 1990s [[New York City]]. The film follows the sexually charged adventures of Dr. Bill Harford, who is shocked when his wife, Alice, reveals that she had contemplated having an affair a year earlier. He embarks on a night-long adventure, during which he infiltrates a massive masked [[orgy]] of an unnamed [[secret society]].

Kubrick obtained the filming rights for ''Dream Story'' in the 1960s, considering it a perfect text for a [[film adaptation]] about sexual relations. He revived the project in the 1990s when he hired writer [[Frederic Raphael]] to help him with the adaptation. The film, which was mostly shot in the [[United Kingdom]], apart from some exterior [[establishing shots]], includes a detailed recreation of exterior [[Greenwich Village]] street scenes made at [[Pinewood Studios]]. The film's production, at 400 days, holds the [[Guinness World Record]] for the longest continuous film shoot.

Kubrick died six days after showing his final cut to [[Warner Bros. Pictures]], making this the final film he directed. In order to ensure a theatrical [[Motion Picture Association of America film rating system#Ratings|R rating]] in the United States, Warner Bros. digitally altered several sexually explicit scenes during [[post-production]]. This version was released on July 16, 1999, to moderately positive reactions from film critics. Box office receipts for the film worldwide were about $162 million. The uncut version has since been released in [[DVD]], [[HD DVD]] and [[Blu-ray Disc]] formats.

==Plot==
Dr. Bill and Alice Harford live in New York with their daughter Helena. They attend a Christmas party hosted by wealthy patient, Victor Ziegler, where Bill is reunited with Nick Nightingale, a medical school drop-out who now plays the piano professionally. An older Hungarian guest attempts to seduce Alice, and two young models attempt to seduce Bill. He is interrupted by his host who had been having sex with Mandy, a young woman who has overdosed on a [[Speedball (drug)|speedball]]. Mandy recovers with Bill's aid.

The following evening, while smoking marijuana, Alice and Bill discuss their episodes of unfulfilled temptation. Bill tells Alice he is not jealous of other men's attraction to her because he deems women naturally inclined to fidelity. She then discloses that during their vacation in Cape Cod, she encountered a naval officer and fantasized about him enough to consider leaving Bill and their daughter, Helena. Bill is disturbed by Alice's revelation before being called to the house of a patient who has just died. The patient's distraught daughter unsuccessfully tries to seduce Bill. Upon leaving, he engages a prostitute named Domino. Alice phones when they start kissing, prompting Bill to have a change of heart. He pays Domino for the sexless encounter and meets Nick at a jazz club. Nick describes an engagement where he must play piano blindfolded in events featuring beautiful women. Invitees require a costume, a mask and a password. Bill goes to a costume shop and offers the owner, Milich, a generous amount of money to rent a costume. Inside the shop, Milich is outraged when he catches his teenage daughter with two men.

Bill takes a taxi to the country mansion mentioned by Nick. He gives the password and discovers a sexual ritual is taking place. One of the masked women warns him he is in terrible danger. Bill is ushered to a crowded room and unmasked by the master of ceremonies. The woman who had tried to warn Bill intervenes and insists on redeeming him, at an undisclosed personal cost. Bill is let off with a warning not to tell anyone about what happened.

Bill arrives home guilty and confused. He finds Alice laughing in her sleep and awakens her. She tearfully explains a dream in which she was having sex with the naval officer and many other men, and laughing at the idea of Bill witnessing the scene. The next morning Bill goes to Nick's hotel. The desk clerk explains that a bruised and frightened Nick checked out hours earlier escorted by two dangerous-looking men. Bill returns the costume but seems to have misplaced the mask, and learns Milich is now [[Procuring (prostitution)|procuring]] his daughter to the same men he performed citizen's arrest on the previous night.

Bill reads the news about a beauty queen's death from an overdose, goes to the morgue and identifies her as Mandy. He is then summoned by Ziegler, who reveals he was a guest in the orgy and identified Bill through his connection with Nick. Ziegler claims the secret society's warnings are only intended to scare Bill from speaking about the orgy. However, he implies the society is capable of acting on their threats. Bill asks about Nick's disappearance and Mandy's death, correctly identifying her as the masked orgy participant who sacrificed herself for him. Ziegler insists that Nick is safely back home in Seattle, and the punishment was part of the same charade of intimidation and had nothing to do with Mandy's death. He also says Mandy was a hooker and addict who had died from another accidental drug overdose. Bill does not know whether Ziegler is telling the truth about Nick's whereabouts or Mandy's death.

Upon returning home, Bill finds the rented mask on his pillow next to his sleeping wife. He breaks down in tears and tells Alice the whole truth of the past two days. The next morning, they go Christmas shopping with Helena, who wanders near two older men who had been first seen at Ziegler's party. Unconcerned with their child, Bill apologizes to Alice, and Alice muses that they should be grateful that their marriage and mutual love survived.

==Cast==
{{castlist|
* [[Tom Cruise]] as Dr. William &quot;Bill&quot; Harford
* [[Nicole Kidman]] as Alice Harford
* [[Sydney Pollack]] as Victor Ziegler
* [[Todd Field]] as Nick Nightingale
* [[Marie Richardson]] as Marion Nathanson
* [[Sky du Mont]] as Sandor Szavost
* [[Rade Šerbedžija]] as Mr. Milich
* [[Thomas Gibson]] as Carl
* [[Vinessa Shaw]] as Domino
* [[Fay Masterson]] as Sally
* [[Alan Cumming]] as Hotel Desk Clerk
* [[Leelee Sobieski]] as Milich's daughter
* [[Leon Vitali]] as Red Cloak
* [[Julienne Davis]] as Amanda &quot;Mandy&quot; Curran
* [[Abigail Good]] as Mysterious Woman}}

==Production==
===Development===
''Eyes Wide Shut'' developed after Stanley Kubrick read Arthur Schnitzler's ''Dream Story'' in 1968, when Kubrick was looking for a project to follow ''[[2001: A Space Odyssey (film)|2001: A Space Odyssey]]''. Kubrick was interested in adapting the story, and with the help of journalist [[Jay Cocks]], bought the filming rights to the novel.&lt;ref name=&quot;time&quot;&gt;{{cite magazine|url=http://content.time.com/time/subscriber/article/0,33009,991414-1,00.html|title=All Eyes On Them|author=[[Richard Schickel|Schickel, Richard]]|date=July 5, 1999|magazine=Time|accessdate=February 18, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1970s, Kubrick thought of [[Woody Allen]] as the Jewish protagonist.{{sfn|Rasmussen|2005|p=222}} For the following decade, Kubrick considered making the ''Dream Story'' adaptation a sex comedy &quot;with a wild and somber streak running through it&quot;, starring [[Steve Martin]] in the main role.&lt;ref name=&quot;vf&quot;&gt;[[Michael Herr|Herr, Michael]]. [http://www.vanityfair.com/hollywood/classic/features/kubrick-199908 CLASSIC HOLLYWOOD: Kubrick], ''[[Vanity Fair (magazine)|Vanity Fair]]'' (August 1999)&lt;/ref&gt; The project was revived in 1994 when Kubrick hired Frederic Raphael to work on the script, updating the setting from early 20th century Vienna to late 20th century New York City.&lt;ref name=&quot;S&amp;S&quot;&gt;[[Frederic Raphael|Raphael, Frederic]]. [https://www.bfi.org.uk/news-opinion/sight-sound-magazine/features/frederic-raphael-reflects-writing-eyes-wide-shut-with-stanley-kubrick “This is confidential material. Where did you get it?” Frederic Raphael looks back at Eyes Wide Shut], ''[[Sight &amp; Sound]]'' (November 2019)&lt;/ref&gt; Kubrick invited his friend [[Michael Herr]], who helped write ''[[Full Metal Jacket]]'', to make revisions, but Herr declined for fear he would be underpaid and have to commit to a long production.&lt;ref name=&quot;vf&quot; /&gt;

===Adaptation===
Arthur Schnitzler's 1926 novella ''Dream Story'' is set around Vienna after the turn of the century. The main characters are a couple named Fridolin and Albertina. The couple's home is a typical suburban middle-class home. Like the protagonist of the novel, Schnitzler was Jewish, lived in Vienna, and was a medical doctor, although he left medicine to write.

Kubrick frequently removed references to the Jewishness of characters in the novels he adapted.&lt;ref name=&quot;cocks29&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Cocks|2004|p=29}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''Eyes Wide Shut'', Frederic Raphael, who is Jewish, wanted to keep the Jewish background of the protagonists, but Kubrick disagreed and removed details that would identify characters as Jewish. Kubrick determined Bill should be a &quot;[[Harrison Ford]]-ish [[Gentile|goy]]&quot; and created the surname of Harford as an allusion to the actor.{{sfn|Raphael|2000|p=59}} In the film, Bill is taunted with homophobic slurs. In the novella, the taunters are members of an [[anti-Semitic]] college fraternity.&lt;ref name=&quot;cocks29&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lowenberg, Peter. &quot;Freud, Schnitzler, and Eyes Wide Shut,&quot; in ''[[#Depth|Depth of field: Stanley Kubrick, film, and the uses of history]]'' (2006), pp.&amp;nbsp;255–279.&lt;/ref&gt; In an introduction to a Penguin Classics edition of ''Dream Story'', Raphael wrote that &quot;Fridolin is not declared to be a Jew, but his feelings of cowardice, for failing to challenge his aggressor, echo the uneasiness of Austrian Jews in the face of Gentile provocation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Dream Story |last=Schnitzler |first=Arthur |authorlink= |author2=Fredric Raphael |year=1999 |publisher=Penguin |location= |isbn=978-0-14-118224-7 |page=xiii |url= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The novella is set during the [[Carnival in Germany, Switzerland and Austria|Carnival]], when people often wear masks to parties. The party that both husband and wife attend at the opening of the story is a Carnival [[Masquerade ball]], whereas the film's story begins at Christmas time.&lt;ref name=rs/&gt;

In the novella, the party (which is sparsely attended) uses &quot;Denmark&quot; as the password for entrance; that is significant in that Albertina had her infatuation with her soldier in Denmark; the film's password is &quot;Fidelio&quot;. In early drafts of the screenplay, the password was &quot;Fidelio Rainbow&quot;. Jonathan Rosenbaum noted that both passwords echo elements of one member of the couple's behaviour, though in opposite ways.&lt;ref&gt;Rosenbaum, Jonathan. &quot;In Dreams Begin Responsibilities&quot;; in ''[[#Depth|Depth of field: Stanley Kubrick, film, and the uses of history]]'' (2006), pp.&amp;nbsp;245–254&lt;/ref&gt; The party in the novella consists mostly of nude ballroom dancing.

In the novella, the woman who &quot;redeems&quot; Fridolin at the party, saving him from punishment, is costumed as a nun, and most of the characters at the party are dressed as nuns or monks; Fridolin himself used a monk costume. This aspect was retained in the film's original screenplay,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.godamongdirectors.com/scripts/eyeswshu.htm |title=Eyes Wide Shut original screenplay |publisher=Godamongdirectors.com |date= |accessdate=August 22, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; but was deleted in the filmed version.

The novella makes it clear that Fridolin at this point hates Albertina more than ever, thinking they are now lying together &quot;like mortal enemies&quot;. It has been argued{{who?|date=December 2019}} that the dramatic climax of the novella is actually Albertina's dream, and the film has shifted the focus to Bill's visit to the secret society's orgy, whose content is more shocking in the film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.clas.ufl.edu/ipsa/2003/Greenwich%20conference.html |title=Rainer J. Kaus, ''Notes on Eyes Wide Shut'' |publisher=Clas.ufl.edu |date= |accessdate=August 22, 2014 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140902030345/http://www.clas.ufl.edu/ipsa/2003/Greenwich%20conference.html |archive-date=September 2, 2014 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The adaptation created a character with no counterpart in the novella: Ziegler, who represents both the high wealth and prestige to which Bill Harford aspires, and a connection between Bill's two worlds (his regular life, and the secret society organizing the ball).{{sfn|Chion|2002 |p= 21}} Critic Randy Rasmussen interprets Ziegler as representing Bill's worst self, much as in other Kubrick films; the title character in ''[[Dr. Strangelove]]'' represents the worst of the American national security establishment, Charles Grady represents the worst of [[Jack Torrance]] in ''[[The Shining (film)|The Shining]]'', and Clare Quilty represents the worst of Humbert Humbert in ''[[Lolita (1962 film)|Lolita]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Rasmussen|2005 |p= 332}}&lt;/ref&gt;

More significantly, in the film, Ziegler gives a commentary on the whole story to Bill, including an explanation that the party incident, where Bill is apprehended, threatened, and ultimately redeemed by the woman's sacrifice, was staged. Whether this is to be believed or not, it is an exposition of Ziegler's view of the ways of the world as a member of the power elite.{{sfn|Cocks|2004 |p= 146}}

===Casting===
When Warner Bros. president [[Terry Semel]] approved production, he asked Kubrick to cast a movie star as &quot;you haven't done that since [[Jack Nicholson]] [in ''[[The Shining (film)|The Shining]]'']&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;time&quot; /&gt; Cruise was in England because his wife [[Nicole Kidman]] was there shooting ''[[The Portrait of a Lady (film)|The Portrait of a Lady]]'', and eventually Cruise decided to visit Kubrick's estate with Kidman.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=September 3, 2019|title=Eyes Wide Shut: 20 years on, Stanley Kubrick’s most notorious film is still shrouded in mystery|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/films/features/eyes-wide-shut-stanley-kubrick-tom-cruise-nicole-kidman-marriage-film-plot-a9083926.html|date=September 1, 2019|website=The Independent}}&lt;/ref&gt; After that meeting, the director awarded them the roles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video|title=Interview: Tom Cruise on Stanley Kubrick|location=Eyes Wide Shut Blu-Ray (2007)|date=1999|publisher=Warner Bros Home Entertainment}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kubrick also managed to make both not commit to other projects until ''Eyes Wide Shut'' was completed.&lt;ref name=closing/&gt; [[Jennifer Jason Leigh]] and [[Harvey Keitel]] each were cast and filmed by Kubrick. Due to scheduling conflicts, both had to drop out&lt;ref name=&quot;ew&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20471622_272431,00.html|title=Behind the scenes of ''Eyes Wide Shut''|last=Svetkey|first=Benjamin|date=July 23, 1999|work=[[Entertainment Weekly]]|accessdate=October 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; – first Keitel with ''[[Finding Graceland]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=M-gCAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA11 |title=Keitel's Heartbreak Hotel |date=April 21, 1997 |accessdate=August 22, 2014|magazine=New York Magazine|last1=Landman Keil|first1=Beth|last2=Mitchell|first2=Deborah}}&lt;/ref&gt; then Leigh with ''[[eXistenZ]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.chicagotribune.com/1999-04-27/features/9904270063_1_existenz-allegra-geller-virtual-reality|title=Hyper 'Existenz'|date=April 27, 1999|first=Gary|last=Dretzka|work=[[Chicago Tribune]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; – and they were replaced by Sydney Pollack and Marie Richardson in the final cut.&lt;ref name=&quot;time&quot; /&gt;

In 2019, it was revealed that [[Cate Blanchett]] had provided the voice of the mysterious masked woman at the orgy party. Actress [[Abigail Good]] could not do a convincing American accent, and Cruise and Kidman ended up suggesting Blanchett for the [[Dubbing (filmmaking)|dubbing]], which occurred after Kubrick's death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Cate Blanchett Lent Her ‘Warm and Sensual Voice’ to Eyes Wide Shut |url=https://www.vulture.com/2019/06/cate-blanchett-eyes-wide-shut-cameo.html |publisher=Vulture |accessdate=June 27, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Filming===
[[File:Mentmore Towers from angle.jpg|thumb|[[Mentmore Towers]], one of the settings used by the film|alt=A mansion with four towers.]]
Principal photography began in November 1996. Kubrick's perfectionism led to script pages being rewritten on the set, and most scenes requiring numerous takes. The shoot went much longer than expected; [[Vinessa Shaw]] was initially contracted for two weeks but ended up working two months,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.vanityfair.com/hollywood/2014/07/eyes-wide-shut-tom-cruise-nicole-kidman|title=Eyes Wide Shut at 15: Inside the Epic, Secretive Film Shoot that Pushed Tom Cruise and Nicole Kidman to Their Limits|last=Nicholson|first=Amy|date=July 17, 2014|website=Vanity Fair|access-date=February 18, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; while [[Alan Cumming]], who appears in one scene, auditioned six times before the filming process.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gMdVy-nF6cs|title=Alan Cumming on &quot;Standing Up&quot; to Stanley Kubrick|via=www.youtube.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; The crew got exhausted and reported to have a low morale.&lt;ref name=closing&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20471622_289898,00.html|title=Closing Their 'Eyes Wide Shut'|work=Entertainment Weekly|first=Dave|last=Karger |date=Oct 17, 1997|accessdate=October 27, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Filming finally wrapped in June 1998.&lt;ref name=&quot;ew&quot; /&gt; The ''[[Guinness World Records]]'' recognized ''Eyes Wide Shut'' as the longest constant movie shoot, &quot;for over 15 months, a period that included an unbroken shoot of 46 weeks&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=''Guinness World Records 2001''|page=[https://archive.org/details/guinnessworldrec00enfi/page/93 93]|year=2000|isbn=978-0-85112-102-4|title-link=Guinness World Records}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Given Kubrick's fear of flying, the entire film was shot in England.{{Sfn|Ronson|2013|p=170, 174}} Sound-stage works were done at London's [[Pinewood Studios]], which included a detailed recreation of Greenwich Village. Kubrick's perfectionism went as far as sending workmen to Manhattan to measure street widths and note newspaper vending machine locations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Jacobs|first1=Matthew|title=13 Facts You May Not Know about Stanley Kubrick's 'Eyes Wide Shut'|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/entry/facts-about-eyes-wide-shut_n_5598973|website=huffingtonpost.co.uk |publisher=Huffington Post|accessdate=August 18, 2014|date=July 18, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Real New York footage was also shot to be [[rear projection effect|rear projected]] behind Cruise. Production was followed by a strong campaign of secrecy, helped by Kubrick always working with a short team on set.&lt;ref name=&quot;ew&quot; /&gt; Outdoor locations included [[Hatton Garden]] for a Greenwich Village street,{{sfn|Adams|2000|p=24}} [[Hamleys]] for the toy store from the film's ending,{{sfn|Adams|2000|p=16}} and [[Mentmore Towers]] and [[Elveden Hall]] in Elveden, Suffolk, England for the mansion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|page=[https://archive.org/details/worldwideguideto00reev/page/70 70]|title=The Worldwide Guide to Movie Locations|first=Tony|last=Reeves|publisher=Chicago Review Press|year=2001|isbn=978-1-55652-432-5|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/worldwideguideto00reev/page/70}}&lt;/ref&gt; Larry Smith, who had first served as a [[Gaffer (filmmaking)|gaffer]] on both ''[[Barry Lyndon]]'' and ''The Shining'', was chosen by Kubrick to be the film's cinematographer. When possible, Smith made use of available light sources visible in the shots, such as lamps and Christmas tree lights. When this was not adequate, Smith used Chinese paper ball lamps to softly brighten the scene, and/or other type of film lighting. The color was enhanced by [[push processing]] the film reels, which helped bring out the intensity of the color.&lt;ref name=&quot;asc&quot; /&gt;

Kubrick's perfectionism led him to oversee every visual element that would appear in a given frame, from props and furniture to the color of walls and other objects.&lt;ref name=&quot;asc&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.theasc.com/magazine/oct99/sword/pg1.htm|title=A Sword in the Bed|first=Stephen|last=Pizzella|journal=[[American Cinematographer]]|issue=33|date=October 28, 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt; One such element were the masks used in the orgy, which were inspired by the masked Carnival balls visited by the protagonists of the novel. Costume designer Marit Allen explained that Kubrick felt they fit in that scene for being part of the imaginary world, and ended up &quot;creat[ing] the impression of menace, but without exaggeration&quot;. Many masks as used in the Venetian carnival were sent to London, and Kubrick separated who would wear each piece.{{sfn|Ciment|2003|p. 177}} The paintings of Kubrick's wife Christiane and his daughter Katharina are featured on decoration.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sensesofcinema.com/2002/23/ornament/#b6 ''Eyes Wide Shut''], ''[[Senses of Cinema]]''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|last=James|first=Nick|date=September 1999|title=At Home with the Kubrick's|url=|magazine=[[Sight and Sound]]|volume=9|issue=9|page=12|doi=|pmid=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After shooting completed, Kubrick entered a prolonged post-production process. On March 1, 1999, Kubrick showed a cut to Cruise, Kidman, and the Warner Bros. executives. The director died six days later.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jan Harlan&quot;&gt;Jan Harlan, ''Stanley Kubrick: A Life in Pictures''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Music==
[[Jocelyn Pook]] wrote the original music for ''Eyes Wide Shut'' but, like other Kubrick movies, the film was noted for its use of classical music.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allmusic.com/album/eyes-wide-shut-mw0000242501|title=Eyes Wide Shut|author=Ruhlmann, William|website=[[AllMusic]]|accessdate=October 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The opening title music is [[Dmitri Shostakovich|Shostakovich]]'s Waltz No. 2 from &quot;[[Suite for Variety Orchestra (Shostakovich)|Suite for Variety Stage Orchestra]]&quot;, misidentified as &quot;[[Suite for Jazz Orchestra No. 2 (Shostakovich)|Waltz 2 from Jazz Suite]]&quot;. One recurring piece is the second movement of [[György Ligeti]]'s piano cycle &quot;[[Musica ricercata]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|page=7|title=Changing Tunes: The Use of Pre-Existing Music in Film|last1=Powrie|first1=Phil|last2=Stilwell|first2=Robynn Jeananne|publisher=Ashgate Publishing, Ltd.|year=2006|isbn=978-0-7546-5137-6|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kubrick originally intended to feature &quot;Im Treibhaus&quot; from [[Richard Wagner|Wagner]]'s ''[[Wesendonck Lieder]]'', but the director eventually replaced it with Ligeti's tune feeling Wagner's song was &quot;too beautiful&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Music, Sound and Filmmakers: Sonic Style in Cinema|first=James|last=Wierzbicki|pages=147–148|publisher=Routledge|year=2012|isbn=978-0-415-89894-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[morgue]] scene, [[Franz Liszt]]'s late solo piano piece, &quot;[[Nuages Gris]]&quot; (&quot;Grey Clouds&quot;) (1881), is heard.&lt;ref&gt;Arnold, Ben. [https://books.google.com/books?id=_jZs6zP6R6gC&amp;pg=PA169&amp;lpg=PA169&amp;dq=Eyes+Wide+Shut+nuages+Gris&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=10#v=onepage&amp;q=Eyes%20Wide%20Shut%20nuages%20Gris ''The Liszt Companion''] Greenwood Publishing Group, 2002. Pg. 169&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Rex tremendae&quot; from [[Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart|Mozart]]'s ''[[Requiem (Mozart)|Requiem]]'' plays as Bill walks into the cafe and reads of Mandy's death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pep-web.org/document.php?id=ijp.085.0209a |title=Stanley Kubrick's swan song: Eyes wide shut |publisher=PEP Web |accessdate=July 2, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Pook was hired after choreographer Yolande Snaith rehearsed the masked ball orgy scene using Pook's composition &quot;Backwards Priests&quot; – which features a [[Romanian Orthodox Church|Romanian Orthodox]] [[Divine Liturgy]] recorded in a church in [[Baia Mare]], played backwards – as a reference track. Kubrick then called the composer and asked if she had anything else &quot;weird&quot; like that song, which was reworked for the final cut of the scene, with the title &quot;Masked Ball&quot;. Pook ended up composing and recording four pieces of music, many times based on her previous work, totaling 24 minutes. The composer's work ended up having mostly [[string instrument]]s – including a [[viola]] played by Pook herself – with no [[brass instrument|brass]] or [[woodwind]]s as Pook &quot;just couldn't justify these other textures&quot;, particularly as she wanted the tracks played on dialogue-heavy scenes to be &quot;subliminal&quot; and felt such instruments would be intrusive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1999/10/27/style/27iht-pook.t.html|title=Kubrick's Approval Sets Seal on Classical Crossover Success : Pook's Unique Musical Mix|work=International Herald Tribune|first=Mike |last=Zwerin|date=October 27, 1999|accessdate=November 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pook&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=https://cnmsarchive.wordpress.com/2013/06/23/jocelyn-pook-on-eyes-wide-shut/|title=Jocelyn Pook on EYES WIDE SHUT|first=Rudy|last=Koppl|journal=Soundtrack Magazine|volume=18|number=71|year=1999}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another track in the orgy, &quot;Migrations&quot;, features a [[Tamil language|Tamil]] song sung by [[Manickam Yogeswaran]], a [[Carnatic music|Carnatic]] singer. The original cut featured a [[shloka|scriptural recitation]] from the ''[[Bhagavad Gita]]'', which Pook took from a previous Yogeswaran recording.&lt;ref name=&quot;pook&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120302202837/http://www.themusicmagazine.com/newsnov.html|title=Ears wide open |publisher=The Music Magazine |accessdate=July 2, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of various [[Hindu]] groups protesting against their most sacred [[scripture]] being used in such a context,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160303180126/http://www.hindunet.org/anti_defamation/eyes/|title=AHAD Gives Voice to Hindu Sentiments Against Eyes Wide Shut |publisher=American Hindus Against Defamation|accessdate=November 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Warner Bros. issued a public apology,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cscsarchive.org:8081/MediaArchive/art.nsf/(docid)/BEA4055D27D443E165256940004BD72D|title=Warner Bros apologises to Hindus|author=[[Press Trust of India]]|work=[[The Times of India]]|date=August 9, 1999|accessdate=November 12, 2012|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120322145537/http://www.cscsarchive.org:8081/MediaArchive/art.nsf/%28docid%29/BEA4055D27D443E165256940004BD72D|archivedate=March 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and hired the singer to record a similar track to replace the chant.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.unomaha.edu/jrf/dharma.htm|title=The Dharma Blues|first=Robert|last=Castle|journal=[[Journal of Religion and Film]]|volume=6|number=1|date=April 2002|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160303204051/http://www.unomaha.edu/jrf/dharma.htm|archivedate=March 3, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The party at Ziegler's house features rearrangements of love songs such as &quot;[[When I Fall in Love]]&quot; and &quot;[[It Had to Be You (song)|It Had to Be You]]&quot;, used in increasingly ironic ways considering how Alice and Bill flirt with other people in the scene.&lt;ref&gt;Powrie, Stillwell (2006) p. 17&lt;/ref&gt; As Kidman was nervous about doing nude scenes, Kubrick stated she could bring music to liven up. When Kidman brought a [[Chris Isaak]] CD, Kubrick approved it, and incorporated Isaak's song &quot;[[Baby Did a Bad, Bad Thing]]&quot; to both an early romantic embrace of Bill and Alice and the film's trailer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/1999/jul/26/entertainment/ca-59623|title='Bad Bad Thing' Is Good Indeed for Isaak|work=[[The Los Angeles Times]]|date=July 26, 1999|accessdate=October 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Themes and interpretation==
===Genre===
The film was described by some reviewers, and partially marketed, as an [[erotic thriller]], a categorization disputed by others. It is classified as such in the book ''The Erotic Thriller in Contemporary Cinema'', by [[Linda Ruth Williams]],&lt;ref&gt;p. 397 Book published by Indiana University Press, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; and was described as such in news articles about Cruise and Kidman's lawsuit over assertions they saw a sex therapist during filming.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.vanityfair.com/hollywood/2014/07/eyes-wide-shut-tom-cruise-nicole-kidman|title=15 Years Later, New Details from Kubrick’s Secretive Eyes Wide Shut Set|first=Amy|last=Nicholson|website=Vanity Fair}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/1999/apr/24/ameliagentleman|title=Erotic thriller Hollywood couple sue over sex claims|first=By Amelia|last=Gentleman|date=April 24, 1999|via=www.theguardian.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; The positive review in ''Combustible Celluloid'' describes it as an erotic thriller upon first viewing, but actually a &quot;complex story about marriage and sexuality&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.combustiblecelluloid.com/archive/eyeswide.shtml |title=Combustible Celluloid Review – Eyes Wide Shut (1999) |first=Jeffrey M. |last=Anderson |publisher=Combustiblecelluloid.com |date=July 16, 1999 |accessdate=May 24, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; High-Def Digest also called it an erotic thriller.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bluray.highdefdigest.com/273/eyeswideshut.html |title=Blu-ray Review: Eyes Wide Shut &amp;#124; High-Def Digest |publisher=Bluray.highdefdigest.com |accessdate=July 2, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, reviewing the film at AboutFilm.com, Carlo Cavagna regards this as a misleading classification,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.aboutfilm.com/movies/e/eyeswideshut.htm |title=Eyes Wide Shut (1999) |publisher=AboutFilm.Com |accessdate=July 2, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; as does Leo Goldsmith, writing at notcoming.com,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.notcoming.com/reviews/eyeswideshut |title=Eyes Wide Shut |publisher=notcoming.com |date=March 14, 2010 |accessdate=July 2, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the review on Blu-ray.com.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.blu-ray.com/movies/Eyes-Wide-Shut-Blu-ray/509/#Review |title=Eyes Wide Shut Blu-ray |publisher=Blu-ray.com |accessdate=July 2, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Writing in ''TV Guide'', [[Maitland McDonagh]] writes &quot;No one familiar with the cold precision of Kubrick's work will be surprised that this isn't the steamy erotic thriller a synopsis (or the ads) might suggest.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://movies.tvguide.com/eyes-wide-shut/review/134111 |title=Eyes Wide Shut Review |publisher=Movies.tvguide.com |accessdate=July 2, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Writing in general about the genre of 'erotic thriller' for CineAction in 2001, Douglas Keesey states that &quot;whatever [Eyes Wide Shut's] actual type, [it] was at least marketed as an erotic thriller&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=https://www.questia.com/read/1G1-79981141 |title=They Kill for Love – CineAction |journal=Cineaction |last=Keesey |first=Douglas |date=June 22, 2001 |accessdate=May 26, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Michael Koresky, writing in the 2006 issue of film journal ''Reverse Shot'', writes &quot;this director, who defies expectations at every turn and brings genre to his feet, was&amp;nbsp; ... setting out to make neither the 'erotic thriller' that the press maintained nor an easily identifiable 'Kubrick film'&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reverseshot.com/article/eyes_wide_shut |title=Eyes Wide Shut |first=Michael |last=Koresky |publisher=Reverse Shot |date=May 11, 2006 |accessdate=May 26, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''DVD Talk'' similarly dissociates the film from this genre.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dvdtalk.com/reviews/31748/eyes-wide-shut/ |title=Eyes Wide Shut (Blu-ray) : DVD Talk Review of the Blu-ray |publisher=Dvdtalk.com |accessdate=July 2, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Christmas setting===
In addition to relocating the story from Vienna in the 1900s to New York City in the 1990s, Kubrick changed the time-frame of Schnitzler's story from Mardi Gras to Christmas. Michael Koresky believed Kubrick did this because of the rejuvenating symbolism of Christmas.&lt;ref name=rs&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.reverseshot.com/article/eyes_wide_shut |title=Wake Up Call |author=Michael Koresky |date=Spring 2006 |website= |publisher=Reverse Shot |accessdate=December 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mario Falsetto, on the other hand, notes that Christmas lights allow Kubrick to employ some of his distinct methods of shooting including using source location lighting, as he also did in ''Barry Lyndon''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Stanley Kubrick: a narrative and stylistic analysis |last=Falsetto |first=Mario |authorlink= |year=2001 |publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group |location= |isbn= 978-0-275-96974-5 |page=137 |url= |accessdate=}} See also the section on &quot;Disappearing Film Grain&quot; at {{cite web|url=http://kubrickfilms.tripod.com/id79.html |title=Archived copy |accessdate=December 15, 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120126164713/http://kubrickfilms.tripod.com/id79.html |archivedate=January 26, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''New York Times'' notes that the film &quot;gives an otherworldly radiance and personality to Christmas lights&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1999/07/16/movies/film-review-bedroom-odyssey.html |title=Film Review; Bedroom Odyssey |author=Janet Maslin |year=1999 |accessdate=March 4, 2015|newspaper=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; and critic Randy Rasmussen notes that &quot;colorful Christmas lights&amp;nbsp; ... illuminate almost every location in the film.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Stanley Kubrick: Seven Films Analyzed |last=Rasmussen |first=Randy |authorlink= |year=2005 |publisher=McFarland |location= |isbn= 978-0-7864-2152-7 |page=333 |url= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Harper'''s film critic, Lee Siegel, believes that the film's recurring motif is the Christmas tree, because it symbolizes the way that &quot;Compared with the everyday reality of sex and emotion, our fantasies of gratification are&amp;nbsp; ... pompous and solemn in the extreme&amp;nbsp; ... For desire is like Christmas: it always promises more than it delivers.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.indelibleinc.com/kubrick/films/ews/reviews/harpers.html |title=What the critics failed to see in Kubrick's last film |author=Lee Siegel |website= |publisher=Harper's |accessdate=December 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Author [[Tim Kreider]] notes that the &quot;Satanic&quot; mansion-party at Somerton is the only set in the film without a Christmas tree, stating that &quot;Almost every set is suffused with the dreamlike, hazy glow of colored lights and tinsel.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;krieder&quot;&gt;Krieder, Tim. [http://www.visual-memory.co.uk/amk/doc/0096.html &quot;Introducing Sociology&quot;]; in ''[[#Depth|Depth of Field: Stanley Kubrick, Film, and the Uses of History]]'' (2006, pp. 280–297)&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, he argues that &quot;Eyes Wide Shut, though it was released in summer, was ''the'' Christmas movie of 1999.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;krieder&quot; /&gt; Noting that Kubrick has shown viewers the dark side of Christmas consumerism, Louise Kaplan states that the film illustrates ways in which the &quot;material reality of money&quot; is shown replacing the spiritual values of Christmas, charity and compassion. While virtually every scene has a Christmas tree, there is &quot;no Christmas music or cheery Christmas spirit.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Cultures of fetishism |last=Kaplan |first=Louise |authorlink= |year=2006|publisher=MacMillan |location= |isbn= 978-1-4039-6968-2 |page=61|url= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Critic [[Alonso Duralde]], in his book ''Have Yourself a Movie Little Christmas'', categorized the film as a &quot;Christmas movie for grownups&quot;, arguing that &quot;Christmas weaves its way through the film from start to finish&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Have Yourself a Movie Little Christmas |last=Duralde |first=Alonso |authorlink= |year=2010|publisher=Limelight Editions |location= |isbn= 978-0-275-96974-5 |page=33|url= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Use of Venetian masks===
Historians, travel guide authors, novelists, and merchants of [[Venetian mask]]s have noted that these have a long history of being worn during promiscuous activities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.com/?id=fTIuAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA311&amp;dq=venetian+masks+history&amp;cd=31#v=onepage|title=Sketches from Venetian History|first=Edward|last=Smedley|date=March 13, 2018|publisher=Harper|via=Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Frommer's Portable Venice |first1= Darwin |last1=Porter |first2=Danforth |last2=Prince |url=https://books.google.com/?id=hkuNDff0RscC&amp;pg=PA150&amp;dq=venetian+masks+history&amp;cd=12#v=onepage&amp;q=venetianmaskshistory|isbn= 978-0-470-39904-0 |date=March 16, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=qjpduEh-ajAC&amp;dq=venetian+masks+history |title=Novel ''The Venetian Mask'' by Rosalind Laker |date=March 25, 2008 |accessdate=August 22, 2014|isbn=978-0-307-41018-4 |last1=Laker |first1=Rosalind}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.magicofvenezia.com/servlet/the-template/maskstory/Page |title=Magic of Venezia Mask Story |publisher=Magicofvenezia.com |accessdate=July 2, 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120621223111/http://www.magicofvenezia.com/servlet/the-template/maskstory/Page |archivedate=June 21, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Authors Tim Kreider and Thomas Nelson have linked the film's usage of these to Venice's reputation as a center of both [[eroticism]] and [[mercantilism]]. Nelson notes that the sex ritual combines elements of Venetian Carnival and Catholic rites, in particular, the character of &quot;Red Cloak&quot; who simultaneously serves as Grand Inquisitor and King of Carnival. As such, Nelson argues that the sex ritual is a symbolic mirror of the darker truth behind the façade of Victor Ziegler's earlier Christmas party.{{sfn|Nelson|2000|pp=288–289}} Carolin Ruwe, in her book ''Symbols in Stanley Kubrick's Movie 'Eyes Wide Shut''', argues that the mask is the prime symbol of the film. Its symbolic meaning is represented through its connection to the characters in the film; as Tim Kreider points out, this can be seen through the masks in the prostitute's apartment and her being renamed as &quot;[[Domino mask|Domino]]&quot; in the film, which is a type of Venetian Mask.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=_dfKY3D7cuEC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Eyes+Wide+Shut&amp;cd=14#v=onepage |title=Symbols in Stanley Kubrick's Movie 'Eyes Wide Shut' – Carolin Ruwe – Google Boeken |date=July 30, 2000 |accessdate=July 2, 2012|isbn=978-3-638-84176-4 |last1=Ruwe |first1=Carolin}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unused early poster designs for the film by Kubrick's daughter Katharina used the motif of Venetian masks, but were rejected by the studio because they obscured the faces of the film's two stars.&lt;ref name=&quot;S&amp;S2&quot;&gt;[[Katharina Kubrick|Kubrick, Katharina]]. [https://www.bfi.org.uk/news-opinion/sight-sound-magazine/interviews/katharina-kubrick-eyes-wide-shut “When you hold a mirror to society it rebels”: Katharina Kubrick on Eyes Wide Shut], ''[[Sight &amp; Sound]]'' (November 2019)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Release==
===Marketing===
Warner Bros. heavily promoted ''Eyes Wide Shut'', while following Kubrick's secrecy campaign – to the point that the film's [[press kit]]s contained no production notes, nor even the director's suggestions to Semel regarding the marketing campaign, given one week prior to Kubrick's death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Campbell|first1=Duncan|title=Mouths wide shut for new Kubrick film|url=https://www.theguardian.com/uk/1999/jul/10/duncancampbell|newspaper=The Guardian|accessdate=February 18, 2018|date=July 10, 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first footage was shown to theater owners attending the 1999 [[ShoWest]] convention in Las Vegas. TV spots featured both Isaak and Ligeti's music from the soundtrack, while revealing little about the movie's plot.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Natale|first1=Richard|title=ShoWest to Get Quick Glimpse of Kubrick's 'Eyes Wide Shut'|url=http://articles.latimes.com/1999/mar/09/entertainment/ca-15328|newspaper=Los Angeles Times|date=March 9, 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film also appeared on the cover of ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' magazine, and on show business programs such as ''[[Entertainment Tonight]]'' and ''[[Access Hollywood]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/1999/jul/05/entertainment/ca-53039|title=The Way Kubrick Would Have Wanted|work=The Los Angeles Times|date=July 5, 1999|author=Welkos, Robert W.|accessdate=October 27, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Box office===
''Eyes Wide Shut'' opened on July 16, 1999, in the United States. The film topped the weekend box office, with $21.7 million from 2,411 screens.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/weekend/chart/?yr=1999&amp;wknd=29&amp;p=.htm|title=Weekend Box Office: July 16–18, 1999 Weekend|website=[[Box Office Mojo]]|accessdate=October 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; These numbers surpassed the studio's expectations of $20 million, and became both Cruise's sixth consecutive chart topper and Kubrick's highest opening weekend.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/1999/jul/19/entertainment/ca-57357|title='Eyes' Sees Its Way to Top Spot|date=July 19, 1999|first=Richard|last=Natale|work=[[The Los Angeles Times]]|accessdate=October 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/398234.stm|date=July 19, 1999|title=Eyes Wide Shut opens on top|publisher=BBC|accessdate=October 28, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Eyes Wide Shut'' ended up grossing a total of $55,691,208 in the US. The numbers put it as Kubrick's second highest-grossing film in the country, behind ''2001: A Space Odyssey'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.the-numbers.com/person/80270401-Stanley-Kubrick|title=Stanley Kubrick – Box Office History|publisher=The Numbers|accessdate=November 9, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; but were considered a box office disappointment.&lt;ref name=&quot;genius&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2001/jun/12/entertainment/ca-9258|title=Remembering a Difficult Genius|work=The Los Angeles Times|date=June 12, 2001|author=King, Susan|accessdate=November 9, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Shortly after its screening at the [[Venice Film Festival]], ''Eyes Wide Shut'' had a British premiere on September 3, 1999, at the [[Warner Village Cinemas|Warner Village cinema]] in [[Leicester Square]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/437224.stm|publisher=BBC|date=September 3, 1999|title=Stars flock to Kubrick premiere}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film's wide opening occurred the following weekend, and topped the UK charts with £1,189,672.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/film-box-office-1120316.html|title=FILM: BOX OFFICE|date=September 19, 1999|work=[[The Independent]]|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The international performances for ''Eyes Wide Shut'' were more positive, with Kubrick's long-time assistant and brother-in-law [[Jan Harlan]] stating that &quot;It was badly received in the Anglo-Saxon world, but it was very well received in the Latin world and Japan. In Italy, it was a huge hit.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;genius&quot; /&gt; Overseas earnings of over $105 million led to a $162,091,208 box office run worldwide, turning it into the highest-grossing Kubrick film.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.boxofficemojo.com/name/nm0000040/|title=Stanley Kubrick|website=Box Office Mojo}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Critical reception===
''Eyes Wide Shut'' received positive reviews from critics. It currently has an approval rating of 75% on [[Rotten Tomatoes]], based on 154 reviews with an average rating of 7.48/10. The website's critical consensus states, &quot;Kubrick's intense study of the human psyche yields an impressive cinematic work.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/eyes_wide_shut/|title=Eyes Wide Shut|publisher=[[Fandango Media]]|work=[[Rotten Tomatoes]]|accessdate=April 20, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film also has a score of 68 out of 100 on [[Metacritic]], based on 33 critics, indicating &quot;Generally favorable reviews&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.metacritic.com/movie/eyes-wide-shut|title=Eyes Wide Shut Reviews|publisher=[[CBS Interactive]]|work=[[Metacritic]]|accessdate=November 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Over 50 critics listed the film among the best of 1999.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uk.ign.com/articles/2000/02/10/eyes-wide-shut-dvd-press-release|title='EYES WIDE SHUT' DVD PRESS RELEASE|last=Head|first=Steve|date=February 24, 2000|website=IGN|access-date=February 18, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; French magazine ''[[Cahiers du Cinema]]'' named it the best film of the year in its annual &quot;top ten&quot; list.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://alumnus.caltech.edu/~ejohnson/critics/cahiers.html|title=Cahiers du Cinema: Top Ten Lists 1951–2009|last=Johnson|first=Eric C.|website=alumnus.caltech.edu|language=en-US|access-date=December 17, 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120327102838/http://alumnus.caltech.edu/~ejohnson/critics/cahiers.html|archive-date=March 27, 2012|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the ''[[Chicago Tribune]]'', Michael Wilmington declared the film a masterpiece, lauding it as &quot;provocatively conceived, gorgeously shot and masterfully executed ... Kubrick's brilliantly choreographed one-take scenes create a near-hypnotic atmosphere of commingled desire and dread.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.chicagotribune.com/1999-07-16/entertainment/9907170013_1_cruise-and-kidman-sexual-alice-harford|title=The Sexy, Scary, Stylish `Eyes Wide Shut' Is Stanley Kubrick's Final Masterpiece|last=Wilmington|first=Michael|newspaper=Chicago Tribune|date=July 16, 1999|accessdate=April 7, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nathan Rabin of ''[[The A.V. Club]]'' was also highly positive, arguing that &quot;the film's primal, almost religious intensity and power is primarily derived from its multifaceted realization that disobeying the dictates of society and your conscience can be both terrifying and exhilarating. ... The film's depiction of sexual depravity and amorality could easily venture into the realm of camp in the hands of a lesser filmmaker, but Kubrick depicts primal evil in a way that somehow makes it seem both new and deeply terrifying.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.avclub.com/review/eyes-wide-shut-18794|title=Eyes Wide Shut|last=Rabin|first=Nathan|work=The A.V. Club|publisher=Onion, Inc.|date=July 16, 1999|accessdate=April 7, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Critic [[Roger Ebert]] gave the film a positive 3.5/4 stars, writing, &quot;Kubrick's great achievement in the film is to find and hold an odd, unsettling, sometimes erotic tone for the doctor's strange encounters.&quot; He praised the individual dream-like atmosphere of the separate scenes, and called the choice of Christmas-themed lighting &quot;garish, like an urban sideshow&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rogerebert.com/reviews/eyes-wide-shut-1999|title=Review: Eyes Wide Shut |publisher=rogerebert.com |accessdate=June 23, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Reviewer [[James Berardinelli]] stated that it was arguably one of Kubrick's best films. Along with considering Kidman &quot;consistently excellent&quot;, he wrote that Kubrick &quot;has something to say about the causes and effects of depersonalized sex&quot;, and praised the work as &quot;thought-provoking and unsettling&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://preview.reelviews.net/movies/e/eyes_wide.html |title=Review: Eyes Wide Shut |publisher=Reelviews.net |date=March 7, 1999 |accessdate=September 1, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Writing for ''[[The New York Times]]'', reviewer [[Janet Maslin]] commented, &quot;This is a dead-serious film about sexual yearnings, one that flirts with ridicule yet sustains its fundamental eeriness and gravity throughout. The dreamlike intensity of previous Kubrick visions is in full force here.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.nytimes.com/library/film/071699eyes-film-review.html | work=The New York Times | title='Eyes Wide Shut': Danger and Desire in a Haunting Bedroom Odyssey}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some reviewers were unfavorable. One complaint was that the movie's pacing was too slow; while this may have been intended to convey a dream state, critics objected that it made actions and decisions seem laboured.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Tatara|first1=Paul|title=&quot;Eyes Wide Shut&quot; - All undressed with no place to go|url=http://edition.cnn.com/SHOWBIZ/Movies/9907/15/review.eyeswideshut/|website=edition.cnn.com/SHOWBIZ/Movies/9907/15/review.eyeswideshut|publisher=CNN|date=July 15, 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another complaint was that it did not live up to the expectation of it being a &quot;sexy film&quot; which is what it had been marketed as, thus defying audiences' expectations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Kreider|first1=Tim|jstor=1213735|title=Review|journal=Film Quarterly|date=Spring 2000|volume=53|number=3|pages=41–48}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many critics, such as [[Manohla Dargis]] of ''[[LA Weekly]]'' found the prolific orgy scene to be &quot;banal&quot; and &quot;surprisingly tame&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Dargis|first1=Manohla|title=Peep Show|url=http://www.laweekly.com/film/peep-show-2130925|website=LA Weekly|accessdate=February 18, 2018|date=July 14, 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt; While Kubrick's &quot;pictorial talents&quot; were described as &quot;striking&quot; by [[Rod Dreher]] of the ''[[New York Post]]'', the pivotal scene was deemed by Stephen Hunter, writing for ''[[The Washington Post]]'', as the &quot;dullest orgy [he'd] ever seen&quot;. Hunter elaborates on his criticism, and states that &quot;Kubrick is annoyingly offhand while at the same time grindingly pedantic; plot points are made over and over again, things are explained till the dawn threatens to break in the east, and the movie stumbles along at a glacial pace&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/style/longterm/movies/videos/eyeswideshuthunter.htm|title=Kubrick's Sleepy 'Eyes Wide Shut'|last=Hunter|first=Stephen|newspaper=The Washington Post|date=July 16, 1999|accessdate=April 7, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Owen Gleiberman]] of ''[[Entertainment Weekly]]'' complained about the inauthenticity of the New York setting, claiming that the soundstage used for the film's production didn't have &quot;enough bustle&quot; to capture the reality of New York.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Gleiberman|first1=Owen|title=Eyes Wide Shut|url=http://ew.com/article/1999/07/23/eyes-wide-shut-5/|website=Entertainment Weekly|accessdate=February 18, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Paul Tatara of ''[[CNN]]'' described the film as a &quot;slow-motion morality tale full of hot female bodies and thoroughly uneventful 'mystery'&quot;, while [[Andrew Sarris]] writing for the ''[[New York Observer]]'' criticised the film's &quot;feeble attempts at melodramatic tension and suspense&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Sarris|first1=Andrew|title=Eyes Don't Have It: Kubrick Turgid Finale|url=http://observer.com/1999/07/eyes-dont-have-it-kubricks-turgid-finale/|accessdate=February 18, 2018|date=July 26, 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt; David Edelstein of ''[[Slate (magazine)|Slate]]'' dismissed it as &quot;estranged from any period I recognize. Who are these people played by Cruise and Kidman, who act as if no one has ever made a pass at them and are so deeply traumatized by their newfound knowledge of sexual fantasies—the kind that mainstream culture absorbed at least half a century ago? ... Who are these aristocrats whose limos take them to secret masked orgies in Long Island mansions? Even dream plays need some grounding in the real world.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|url=http://www.slate.com/articles/arts/movies/1999/07/the_naked_and_the_dead.html|title=The Naked and the Dead|last=Edelstein|first=David|magazine=Slate|date=July 16, 1999|accessdate=April 7, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[J. Hoberman]] wrote that the film &quot;feels like a rough draft at best.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.villagevoice.com/film/i-wake-up-dreaming-6421330|title=I Wake Up Dreaming|last=Hoberman|first=J.|newspaper=The Village Voice|date=July 20, 1999|accessdate=April 7, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Lee Siegel (cultural critic)|Lee Siegel]] from ''[[Harper's]]'' felt that most critics responded mainly to the marketing campaign and did not address the film on its own terms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.indelibleinc.com/kubrick/films/ews/reviews/harpers.html |title=EYES WIDE SHUT What the critics failed to see in Kubrick's last film |publisher=Indelibleinc.com |accessdate=July 2, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Others felt that American censorship took an esoteric film and made it even harder to understand.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.moviecitynews.com/festivals/sundance_2006/dp_060125.html |title=For Movie Folks Who Considered Burning Down The Ratings Board When The Adjustment Was Enuf |publisher=Movie City News |date=January 26, 2006 |accessdate=April 15, 2008 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071224055634/http://www.moviecitynews.com/festivals/sundance_2006/dp_060125.html |archivedate=December 24, 2007 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; In his article &quot;Grotesque Caricature&quot;, Stefan Mattesich of [[Loyola Marymount University]] praises the film's nuanced caricatured elements, and states that the film's negation of conventional narrative elements is what resulted in its subsequent negative reception.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Mattessich|first1=Stefan|title=Grotesque Caricature: Stanley Kubrick's Eyes Wide Shut as the Allegory Of Its Own Reception|journal=Postmodern Culture|date=2000|volume=10|issue=2|pages=1–8|url=https://muse.jhu.edu/article/41945|accessdate=February 18, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For the introduction to [[Michel Ciment]]'s ''Kubrick: The Definitive Edition'', Scorsese wrote: &quot;When ''Eyes Wide Shut'' came out a few months after Stanley Kubrick's death in 1999, it was severely misunderstood, which came as no surprise. If you go back and look at the contemporary reactions to any Kubrick picture (except the earliest ones), you'll see that all his films were initially misunderstood. Then, after five or ten years came the realization that ''[[2001: A Space Odyssey (film)|2001]]'' or ''[[Barry Lyndon]]'' or ''[[The Shining (film)|The Shining]]'' was like nothing else before or since.&quot;{{sfn|Ciment|2003|p. viii}} In 2012, ''[[Slant Magazine]]'' ranked the film as the second greatest of the 1990s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.slantmagazine.com/film/feature/the-100-best-films-of-the-1990s/334/page_10 |title=The 100 Best Films of the 1990s |publisher=Slantmagazine.com |date= |accessdate=August 22, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[BBC]] listed it number 61 in its list of the 100 greatest American films of all time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.com/culture/story/20150720-the-100-greatest-american-films|title=The 100 greatest American films|first=July 20|last=2015|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Awards and honors===
{| class=&quot;wikitable plainrowheaders sortable&quot;
|-
! scope=&quot;col&quot;| Award
! scope=&quot;col&quot;| Category
! scope=&quot;col&quot;| Recipient
! scope=&quot;col&quot;| Result
|-
| [[Golden Globe Awards]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.goldenglobes.org/browse/?param=/film/24031|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130606103936/http://www.goldenglobes.org/browse/?param=%2Ffilm%2F24031|url-status=dead|archive-date=June 6, 2013|title=Eyes Wide Shut|work=[[Hollywood Foreign Press Association]]|accessdate=October 14, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| [[Golden Globe Award for Best Original Score|Best Original Score]]
| [[Jocelyn Pook]]
| {{nom}}
|-
| [[French Syndicate of Cinema Critics]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.screendaily.com/eyes-wide-shut-is-french-critics-best-foreign-pic/401306.article|title=Eyes Wide Shut is French critics' best foreign pic|publisher=Screen Daily|date=February 8, 2000 |first=Francoise|last=Meaux Saint Marc|accessdate=November 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| Best Foreign Film 
|rowspan=2|[[Stanley Kubrick]]
| {{won}}
|-
|rowspan=3| [[Chicago Film Critics Association]]&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;
| [[Chicago Film Critics Association Award for Best Director|Best Director]]
| {{nom}}
|-
| [[Chicago Film Critics Association Award for Best Cinematography|Best Cinematography]]
| Stanley Kubrick and [[Larry Smith (cinematographer)|Larry Smith]]
| {{nom}}
|-
| [[Chicago Film Critics Association Award for Best Original Score|Best Original score]]
| Jocelyn Pook 
| {{nom}}
|-
| [[Costume Designers Guild]]{{Sfn|Kagan|2012|p=362}}
| [[Costume Designers Guild Award for Excellence in Contemporary Film|Excellence in Costume Design for Film – Contemporary]] 
| [[Marit Allen]]
| {{nom}}
|-
|rowspan=3| [[Satellite Award]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20000611105334/http://www.pressacademy.com/1999_nominations.html |archivedate=June 11, 2000|url=http://www.pressacademy.com/1999_nominations.html|title=2000 Golden Satellite Award Nominees|publisher=[[International Press Academy]]|accessdate=September 11, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| [[Satellite Award for Best Actress – Motion Picture|Best Actress - Drama]]
| [[Nicole Kidman]]
| {{nom}}
|-
| [[Satellite Award for Best Cinematography|Best Cinematography]]
| Larry Smith 
| {{nom}}
|-
| [[Satellite Award for Best Sound|Best Sound]]
| Paul Conway and Edward Tise 
| {{nom}}
|-
| [[César Award]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.academie-cinema.org/ceremonie/palmares.html?annee=2000#meilleur-film-etranger|title=2000 César|publisher=Académie des arts et techniques du cinéma|language=French|accessdate=September 11, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| [[César Award for Best Foreign Film|Best Foreign Film]] (Meilleur film étranger) 
|rowspan=2| Stanley Kubrick 
| {{nom}}
|-
|rowspan=3| [[Online Film Critics Society]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ofcs.org/awards/1999-awards/ |title=1999 Awards |publisher=Ofcs.org |date=January 21, 2014 |accessdate=August 22, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| [[Online Film Critics Society Award for Best Director|Best Director]]
| {{nom}}
|-
| [[Online Film Critics Society Award for Best Cinematography|Best Cinematography]]
| Larry Smith 
| {{nom}}
|-
| [[Online Film Critics Society Award for Best Original Score|Best Original score]]
| Jocelyn Pook 
| {{nom}}
|-
|}

===Home media===
''Eyes Wide Shut'' was first released in [[VHS]] and [[DVD]] on March 7, 2000.&lt;ref name=&quot;press&quot;&gt;{{cite press release|url=http://kubrickfilms.warnerbros.com/news/press/ews_pressrelease.html|title=&quot;Kubrick's Definitive Film &amp; Haunting Final Masterpiece&quot; and 1999's Most Talked About Film Debuts on VHS and DVD|publisher=Warner Bros. Home Entertainment|date=February 24, 2000|accessdate=November 9, 2012|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130617155937/http://kubrickfilms.warnerbros.com/news/press/ews_pressrelease.html|archive-date=June 17, 2013|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; The original DVD release corrects technical gaffes, including a reflected crew member, and altering a piece of Alice Harford's dialogue. Most home videos remove the verse that was claimed to be cited from the sacred Hindu scripture Bhagavad Gita (although it was Pook's reworking of &quot;Backwards Priests&quot; as stated above.)

On October 23, 2007, [[Warner Home Video]] released ''Eyes Wide Shut'' in a special edition DVD, plus the HD DVD and [[Blu-ray]] Disc formats.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=McCutcheon |first=David |url=http://www.ign.com/articles/2007/08/03/kubrick-overload |title=Kubrick Overload! |website=IGN |date=August 3, 2007 |accessdate=August 22, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is the first home video release that presents the film in anamorphic 1.78:1 (16:9) format (the film was shown theatrically as soft matted 1.66:1 in Europe and 1.85:1 in the US and Japan). The previous DVD release used a 1.33:1 (4:3) aspect ratio. It is also the first American home video release to feature the uncut version. Although the earliest American DVD of the uncut version states on the cover that it includes both the R-rated and unrated editions, in actuality only the unrated edition is on the DVD.

==Controversies==
===Debate over the film's state of completion===
Though Warner Bros. insisted that Kubrick had turned in his final cut before his death, the film was still in the final stages of post-production, which was therefore completed by the studio in collaboration with Kubrick's estate. Some have argued that the work which remained was minor and exclusively technical in nature, allowing the estate to faithfully complete the film based on the director's notes. However, decisions regarding sound mixing, scoring and color-correction would have necessarily been made without Kubrick's input. Furthermore, Kubrick had a history of continuing to edit his films up until the last minute, and in some cases even after initial public screenings, as had been the case with ''2001: A Space Odyssey'' and ''The Shining''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Allman|first=Marshall|title=Kubrick's Final Film Reimagined|url=https://www.eyeswidecut.com/inspiration/|accessdate=August 24, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Writing for ''Vanity Fair'', Kubrick collaborator Michael Herr recalled a phone call from the director regarding the cut that would be screened for the Warner Bros. executives four days before his death:

{{quote|text=... there was looping to be done and the music wasn't finished, lots of small technical fixes on color and sound; would I show work that wasn't finished? He had to show it to Tom and Nicole because they had to sign nudity releases, and to Terry Semel and Bob Daly of Warner Bros., but he hated it that he had to, and I could hear it in his voice that he did.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|last=Herr|first=Michael|title=Kubrick|url=http://www.vanityfair.com/hollywood/classic/features/kubrick-199908|magazine=[[Vanity Fair (magazine)|Vanity Fair]]|accessdate=2012-06-02|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120629212013/http://www.vanityfair.com/hollywood/classic/features/kubrick-199908.print|archivedate=June 29, 2012|url-status=live|date=August 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[Garrett Brown]], inventor of the [[Steadicam]], has expressed that he considers ''Eyes Wide Shut'' to be an unfinished film:

{{quote|text=I think ''Eyes Wide Shut'' was snatched up by the studio when Stanley died and they just grabbed the highest number Avid edit and ran off as if that was the movie. But it was three months before the movie was due to be released. I don't think there's a chance that was the movie he had in mind, or the music track and a lot of other things. It's a great shame because you know it's out there, but it doesn't feel to me as it's really his film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.moviegeeksunited.net/kubrick.htm |title=Movie Geeks United! - The Kubrick Series |publisher=Movie Geeks United! |accessdate=2017-01-06 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170107170417/http://www.moviegeeksunited.net/kubrick.htm |archive-date=2017-01-07 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Nicole Kidman, one of the stars of the film, briefly wrote about the completion of the film and the release of the film being at the same time of [[John F. Kennedy Jr.]]’s death from her perspective:

{{quote|text=There was a lot of interest in ''Eyes Wide Shut'' before it was released. But the weekend it came out, July 16, 1999, was the death of JFK Jr., his wife and her sister – a black, black weekend. And for Stanley to have died [on March 7, 1999, at age 70] before the film opened&amp;nbsp; ... well, it all felt so dark and strange. Stanley had sent over the cut he considered done to us, Tom and I watched it in New York – and then he died.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Ginsburg|first1=Merle|title=Nicole Kidman on Life with Tom Cruise Through Stanley Kubrick's Lens|url=https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/nicole-kidman-stanley-kubricks-lens-382186|website=hollywoodreporter.com |publisher=The Hollywood Reporter|accessdate=24 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Kubrick's opinion===
[[Jan Harlan]], Kubrick's brother-in-law and executive producer, reported that Kubrick was &quot;very happy&quot; with the film and considered it to be his &quot;greatest contribution to the art of cinema&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=DVDTalk.com – news, reviews, bargains, and discussion forum |url=http://www.dvdtalk.com/janharlaninterview.html |title=On Kubrick – A Talk With Kubrick Documentarian Jan Harlan |publisher=Dvdtalk.com |date= |accessdate=August 22, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://timessquare.com/Film/Film_Interviews/Jan_Harlan_Keeps_His_Eyes_Wide_Open_On_New_Ideas/ |title=Jan Harlan Keeps His Eyes Wide Open On New Ideas &amp;#124; Times Square New York City |publisher=Timessquare.com |date=November 7, 2007 |accessdate=July 2, 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120226124101/http://timessquare.com/Film/Film_Interviews/Jan_Harlan_Keeps_His_Eyes_Wide_Open_On_New_Ideas/ |archivedate=February 26, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[R. Lee Ermey]], an actor in Kubrick's film ''[[Full Metal Jacket]]'', stated that Kubrick phoned him two weeks before his death to express his despondency over ''Eyes Wide Shut''. &quot;He told me it was a piece of shit&quot;, Ermey said in ''Radar'' magazine, &quot;and that he was disgusted with it and that the critics were going to 'have him for lunch'. He said Cruise and Kidman had their way with him – exactly the words he used.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://filmdrunk.uproxx.com/2010/03/kubrick-says-cruise-kidman-ruined-eyes-wide-shut|title=''Kubrick says Cruise and Kidman ruined EWS''|date=March 2, 2010|access-date=April 8, 2010|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100419035751/http://filmdrunk.uproxx.com/2010/03/kubrick-says-cruise-kidman-ruined-eyes-wide-shut|archive-date=April 19, 2010|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[Todd Field]], Kubrick's friend and an actor in ''Eyes Wide Shut'', Ermey's claims do not accurately reflect Kubrick's essential attitude. Field's response appeared in an October 18, 2006 interview with Grouch Reviews:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=grouchoreviews.com|url=http://grouchoreviews.com/interviews/187|title=Todd Field – Little Children |publisher=grouchoreviews.com |date= |accessdate=August 10, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The polite thing would be to say 'No comment'. But the truth is that&amp;nbsp; ... let's put it this way, you've never seen two actors more completely subservient and prostrate themselves at the feet of a director. Stanley was absolutely thrilled with the film. He was still working on the film when he died. And he probably died because he finally relaxed. It was one of the happiest weekends of his life, right before he died, after he had shown the first cut to Terry, Tom and Nicole. He would have kept working on it, like he did on all of his films. But I know that from people around him personally, my partner who was his assistant for thirty years. And I thought about [[R. Lee Ermey]] for ''[[In the Bedroom]]''. And I talked to Stanley a lot about that film, and all I can say is Stanley was adamant that I shouldn't work with him for all kinds of reasons that I won't get into because there is no reason to do that to anyone, even if they are saying slanderous things that I know are completely untrue.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In a [[reddit]] &quot;Ask Me Anything&quot; session, Stanley Kubrick's daughter, Katharina Kubrick, claimed that her father was very proud of the film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.reddit.com/r/IAmA/comments/134rvs/stanley_kubricks_daughter_katharina_kubrick_and/c70tgdp |title=littleroom comments on Stanley Kubrick's daughter Katharina Kubrick, and grandson Joe. AMA |publisher=Reddit.com |date=November 13, 2012 |accessdate=August 22, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; She also discredited Ermey's claims, saying to a user who asked about Kubrick's alleged comments, &quot;[not to] believe that for a second.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.reddit.com/r/IAmA/comments/134rvs/stanley_kubricks_daughter_katharina_kubrick_and/c70tkzu |title=seluropnek comments on Stanley Kubrick's daughter Katharina Kubrick, and grandson Joe. AMA |publisher=Reddit.com |date=November 13, 2012 |accessdate=August 22, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Studio censorship and classification===
Citing contractual obligations to deliver an [[Motion Picture Association of America film rating system|R rating]], Warner Bros. digitally altered the orgy for the film's American release by [[censorship|blocking out]] graphic sexuality using additional figures to obscure the view in order to avoid an adults-only [[NC-17]] rating that limited distribution, due to some large American theaters and video store operators banning films with that rating. This alteration antagonized both film critics and cinephiles,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://partners.nytimes.com/library/film/072899eyes-movie.html | work=The New York Times | title=Critics Assail Ratings Board Over 'Eyes Wide Shut'}}&lt;/ref&gt; who argued that Kubrick had never been shy about ratings (''[[A Clockwork Orange (film)|A Clockwork Orange]]'' was originally given an [[X-rated|X-rating]]). The unrated version of ''Eyes Wide Shut'' was released in the United States on October 23, 2007, on [[DVD]], [[HD DVD]] and [[Blu-ray]] formats.

[[Roger Ebert]] heavily criticized the technique of using digital images to mask the action. In his positive review of the film, he said it &quot;should not have been done at all&quot; and it is &quot;symbolic of the moral hypocrisy of the rating system that it would force a great director to compromise his vision, while by the same process making his adult film more accessible to young viewers.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eyes Wide Shut&quot;&gt;Roger Ebert's review of [http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/19990716/REVIEWS/907160302/1023 Eyes Wide Shut]&lt;/ref&gt; Although Ebert has been frequently cited as calling the standard North American R-rated version the &quot;[[Austin Powers (film series)|Austin Powers]]&quot; version of ''Eyes Wide Shut'' – referencing two scenes in ''[[Austin Powers: International Man of Mystery]]'' in which, through camera angles and coincidences, sexual body parts are blocked from view in a comical way&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.reelviews.net/reelviews/eyes-wide-shut Reel Views ''Eyes Wide Shut''], [http://www.metroactive.com/papers/metro/07.15.99/eyeswideshut-9928.html MetroActive ''Eyes Wide Shut''] and [http://www.filmblather.com/review.php?n=eyeswideshut FilmBlather, ''Eyes Wide Shut''] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100923052226/http://filmblather.com/review.php?n=eyeswideshut |date=September 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; – his review stated that this joke referred to an early rough draft of the altered scene, never publicly released.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eyes Wide Shut&quot; /&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book|last=Adams|first=Mark|title=Location London|publisher=Interlink|year=2004|isbn=978-1-84330-478-4 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|title=Eyes wide shut|first=Michel|last=Chion|publisher=[[British Film Institute|BFI Publishing]]|year=2002|isbn=978-0-85170-932-1|ref=harv|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/eyeswideshut0000chio}}
* {{cite book|last=Ciment|first=Michel|year=2003|title=Kubrick: The Definitive Edition|publisher=Faber and Faber|isbn=978-0-571-21108-1|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|title=The Wolf at the Door: Stanley Kubrick, History, &amp; the Holocaust|first=Geoffrey|last=Cocks|publisher=Peter Lang|year=2004|isbn=978-0-8204-7115-0|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|title=Depth of field: Stanley Kubrick, film, and the uses of history|author=Cocks, Geoffrey; Diedrick, James; Perusek, Glen (eds.)|publisher=[[University of Wisconsin Press]]|year=2006|isbn=978-0-299-21614-6}}
* {{cite book|title=Directors Close Up 2: Interviews with Directors Nominated for Best Film by the Directors Guild of America: 2006–2012|last=Kagan|first=Jeremy|publisher=Scarecrow Press|year=2012|isbn=978-0-8108-8391-8|location=United Kingdom|pages=362}}
* {{cite book |first=Thomas Allen | last=Nelson | title=Kubrick: Inside a Film Artist's Maze. New and Expanded Edition | year=2000 | publisher=Indiana University Press | isbn=978-0-253-21390-7}}
* {{cite book|first=Frederic|last=Raphael|title=Eyes Wide Open. A Memoir of Stanley Kubrick and Eyes Wide Shut|publisher=Orion Publishing|year=2000|isbn=978-0-7538-0955-6|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book| last=Rasmussen | first=Randy | title=Stanley Kubrick: Seven Films Analyzed | publisher=McFarland &amp; Company | year=2005 | isbn = 978-0-7864-2152-7}}
* {{cite book|title=Lost at Sea: The Jon Ronson Mysteries|last=Ronson|first=Jon|publisher=Picador|year=2013|isbn=978-1-4472-6471-2|location=London|pages=170, 174}}

==External links==
{{sisterlinks|d=Q209481|c=category:Eyes Wide Shut|n=no|b=no|v=no|voy=no|m=no|mw=no|wikt=no|s=no|species=no|display=''Eyes Wide Shut''}}
* {{IMDb title|0120663}}
* {{tcmdb title|434559}}
* {{mojo title|eyeswideshut}}
* {{rotten-tomatoes|eyes_wide_shut}}
* {{metacritic film|eyes-wide-shut}}

{{Stanley Kubrick}}
{{Arthur Schnitzler}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:1999 films]]
[[Category:1990s erotic films]]
[[Category:1990s mystery films]]
[[Category:1990s thriller drama films]]
[[Category:American Christmas films]]
[[Category:American erotic films]]
[[Category:American films]]
[[Category:American mystery films]]
[[Category:American thriller drama films]]
[[Category:British Christmas films]]
[[Category:British erotic films]]
[[Category:British films]]
[[Category:British mystery films]]
[[Category:British thriller drama films]]
[[Category:Censored films]]
[[Category:English-language films]]
[[Category:Erotic drama films]]
[[Category:Erotic mystery films]]
[[Category:Erotic thriller films]]
[[Category:Films based on Austrian novels]]
[[Category:Films based on works by Arthur Schnitzler]]
[[Category:Films directed by Stanley Kubrick]]
[[Category:Films produced by Stanley Kubrick]]
[[Category:Films set in New York City]]
[[Category:Films shot at Pinewood Studios]]
[[Category:Films shot in Bedfordshire]]
[[Category:Films shot in Hampshire]]
[[Category:Films shot in Hertfordshire]]
[[Category:Films shot in London]]
[[Category:Films shot in New York City]]
[[Category:Films shot in Norfolk]]
[[Category:Films shot in Suffolk]]
[[Category:Hinduism-related controversies]]
[[Category:Obscenity controversies in film]]
[[Category:Films with screenplays by Stanley Kubrick]]
[[Category:Warner Bros. films]]</text>
      <sha1>cakby92v1xkxbl7c5p3kjw87q60xkjx</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
