  <page>
    <title>Epistle to the Philippians</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9950</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941652562</id>
      <parentid>941637166</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-19T22:02:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Dating maintenance tags: {{Contradiction}}</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|eleventh book in the New Testament}}
{{redirect-distinguish|Philippians|Philippines}}
{{Paul}}{{Books of the New Testament}}

The '''Epistle to the Philippians''', commonly referred to as '''Philippians''', is a [[Pauline epistle]] of the [[New Testament]] of the [[Christian Bible]]. The [[epistle]] is attributed to [[Paul the Apostle]] and a co-author named [[Saint Timothy|Timothy]], and is addressed to the Christian church in [[Philippi]].{{Bibleref2c|Phil|1:1}} [[Paul the Apostle|Paul]] and [[Silas]] first visited [[Philippi]] in [[Early centers of Christianity#Greece|Greece]] during Paul's second [[Missionary journeys of Paul|missionary journey]], which occurred between approximately 49 and 51 AD. Philippi was the location of the first [[Early Christian churches|Christian community]] established in Greece.{{citation needed|date=June 2019}}

While there is a general consensus that Philippians consists of authentically Pauline material, the majority of scholars believe that the epistle is a composite of multiple letter fragments from Paul to the church in Philippi.&lt;ref name=&quot;hansen&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Hansen |first=Walter |date=2009 |title=The Letter to the Philippians |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=lX9roIFc_50C |location=Grand Rapids, MI |publisher=William B. Eerdmans Publishing Company |page=15 |isbn=978-1-84474-403-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sellew&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Sellew |first1=Philip |date=January 1994 |title=Laodiceans and the Philippians fragments hypothesis |journal=Harvard Theological Review |volume=87 |issue=1 |pages=17–28 |doi=10.1017/S0017816000031618 |jstor=1509846 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|17}} These letters could have been written from [[Ephesus]] in 52–55 AD or [[Caesarea Maritima]] in 57–59, but the most likely city of provenance is Rome, around 62 AD, or about 10 years after Paul's first visit to Philippi.&lt;ref name =&quot;Harris&quot;&gt;[[Stephen L Harris|Harris, Stephen L.]], Understanding the Bible. Palo Alto: Mayfield. 1985.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Composition ==
Starting in the 1960s, a general consensus emerged among biblical scholars that Philippians was not written as one unified letter, but is rather a compilation of fragments from three separate letters from Paul to the church in Philippi.&lt;ref name=&quot;sellew&quot;/&gt;{{rp|17}} According to Philip Sellew, Philippians contains the following letter fragments:
* '''Letter A''' consists of Philippians 4:10-20. It is a short thank-you note from Paul to the Philippian church, regarding gifts they had sent him.{{Bibleref2c|Phil|4:17}}
* '''Letter B''' consists of Philippians 1:1-3:1, and may also include 4:4-9 and 4:21-23.
* '''Letter C''' consists of Philippians 3:2-4:1, and may also include 4:2-3. It is a testament to Paul's rejection of all worldly things for the sake of the gospel of Jesus.&lt;ref name=&quot;sellew&quot;/&gt;{{rp|19}}
In support of the idea that Philippians is a composite work, scholars point to the abrupt shifts in tone and topic within the text. There also seem to be chronological inconsistencies from one chapter to the next concerning Paul's associate [[Epaphroditus]]:{{quote|Another argument against unity has been found in the swiftly changing fortunes of Epaphroditus: this associate of Paul is at the point of death in chapter two (Phil 2:25-30), where seemingly he has long been bereft of the company of the Philippian Christians; Paul says that he intended to send him back to Philippi after this apparently lengthy, or at least near-fatal separation. Two chapters later, however, at the end of the canonical letter, Paul notes that Epaphroditus had only now just arrived at Paul's side, carrying a gift from Philippi, a reference found toward the close of the &quot;thank-you note&quot; as a formulaic acknowledgement of receipt at Phil 4:18.|Philip Sellew&lt;ref name=&quot;sellew&quot;/&gt;{{rp|18}}}}
These letter fragments likely would have been edited into a single document by the first collector of the Pauline corpus, although there is no clear consensus among scholars regarding who this initial collector may have been, or when the first collection of Pauline epistles may have been published.&lt;ref name=&quot;sellew&quot;/&gt;{{rp|26}}

Today, a majority of scholars believe that Philippians is a composite of multiple letter fragments. According to the [[Theology|theologian]] G. Walter Hansen, &quot;The traditional view that Philippians was composed as one letter in the form presented in the NT ''[New Testament]'' can no longer claim widespread support.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;hansen&quot;/&gt; Nevertheless, a number of scholars continue to argue for the unity of Philippians.

Regardless of the literary unity of the letter, scholars agree that the material that was compiled into the Epistle to the Philippians was originally composed in Greek, some time during the 50s or early 60s AD.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/alexander_a/canon.iv.x.html?highlight=epistle,greek,language,philippians#highlight Section X. Testimonies to the Canonical Authority of the Fourteen Epistles of Paul]. Canon of the Old and New Testaments Ascertained, or The Bible Complete without the Apocrypha and Unwritten Traditions. Alexander, Archibald (1772–1851).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Place of writing===
It is uncertain where Paul was when he wrote the letter(s) that make up Philippians. Internal evidence in the letter itself points clearly to it being composed while Paul was in custody,{{Bibleref2c|Phil|1:7,13}} but it is unclear ''which'' period of imprisonment the letter refers to. If the testimony of the [[Acts of the Apostles]] is [[Historical reliability of the Acts of the Apostles|to be trusted]], candidates would include the Roman imprisonment at the end of Acts,{{Bibleref2c|Acts|28:30-31}} and the earlier [[Caesarea Maritima|Caesarean]] imprisonment (Acts 23–26). Any identification of the place of writing of Philippians is complicated by the fact that scholars generally view Acts as being an unreliable source of information about the early Church.&lt;ref name=Hornik2017&gt;{{cite book |last1=Hornik |first1=Heidi J. |last2=Parsons |first2=Mikeal C. |title=The Acts of the Apostles through the centuries |date=2017 |publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. |isbn=9781118597873 |edition= 1st}} In the words of Hornik and Parsons, &quot;Acts must be carefully sifted and mined for historical information.&quot; (pg. 10)&lt;/ref&gt;

Jim Reiher has suggested that the letters could stem from the second period of Roman imprisonment attested by early church fathers.&lt;ref&gt;[[Clement of Rome]] (late 1st century) makes a reference to the ministry of Paul after the end of Acts. Clement, To the Corinthians, 5. In J. B. Lightfoot (ed), The Apostolic Fathers (Michigan: Baker Book House, 1978) 15. The author of the [[Muratorian Canon]] (late 2nd century) says that Luke recorded mostly that which he himself witnessed and therefore that is why he did not include ‘the journey of Paul, when he went from the city – Rome – to [[Spain]].’ The Muratoriun Canon. 2. The apocryphal [[Acts of Peter]] makes reference to the tradition that Paul reached Spain. Paul is described in prison in Rome, receiving a vision from God that he would go to Spain. Acts of Peter, Verscelli Acts 1 and 3. Eusebius (early 300’s) recorded that Paul did more ministry after his first jail time in Rome. Eusebius, Ecclesiastical History, II, 22, 1–8, in Philip Schaff and Henry Wace (editors), A Select Library of Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers of the Christian Church 2nd series. Vol.1. Eusebius: Church History, Life of Constantine the Great, and Oration in Praise of Constantine (Edinburgh: Eerdmans, 1997) 124–125.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jim Reiher, “Could Philippians have been written from the Second Roman Imprisonment?” [[Evangelical Quarterly]]. Vol. LXXXIV. No. 3 July 2012. pp. 213–233. This article summarises the other theories, and offers examples of different scholars who adhere to different theories, but presents a different option for consideration.&lt;/ref&gt; The main reasons suggested for a later date, include:
# The letter's highly developed [[Ecclesiology]]
# An impending sense of death permeating the letter
# The absence of any mention of [[Luke the Evangelist|Luke]] in a letter to Luke's home church (when the narrative in Acts clearly suggests that Luke was with Paul in his first Roman imprisonment)
# A harsher imprisonment than the [[house arrest|open house arrest]] of his first Roman imprisonment
# A similar unique expression that is shared only with [[2 Timothy]].
# A similar disappointment with co-workers shared only with 2 Timothy.

==Contents==
In Chapters 1 and 2 of Philippians ('''Letter B'''), Paul sends word to the Philippians of his upcoming sentence in Rome and of his optimism in the face of death,{{Bibleref2c|Phil|1:18b–26}} along with exhortations to imitate his capacity to rejoice in the Lord despite one's circumstances.{{Bibleref2c|Phil|2:14–18}} Paul assures the Philippians that his imprisonment is actually helping to spread the Christian message, rather than hindering it.{{Bibleref2c|Phil|1:12–15}} He also expresses gratitude for the devotion and heroism of Epaphroditus, who the Philippian church had sent to visit Paul and bring him gifts.{{Bibleref2c|Phil|2:25–30}} Some time during his visit with Paul, Epaphroditus apparently contracted some life-threatening debilitating illness.{{Bibleref2c|Phil|2:26–27}} But he recovers before being sent back to the Philippians.

In Chapter 3 ('''Letter C'''), Paul warns the Philippians about those Christians who insist that [[circumcision]] is necessary for salvation. He testifies that while he once was a devout [[Pharisees|Pharisee]] and follower of the Jewish law, he now considers these things to be worthless and worldly compared to the gospel of Jesus.{{Bibleref2c|Phil|3:2–10}}

In Chapter 4, Paul urges the Philippians to resolve conflicts within their fellowship.{{Bibleref2c|Phil|4:2–3}} In the latter part of the chapter ('''Letter A'''), Paul expresses his gratitude for the gifts that the Philippians had sent him, and assures them that God will reward them for their generosity.{{Bibleref2c|Phil|4:15–20}}

Throughout the epistle there is a sense of optimism. Paul is hopeful that he will be released, and on this basis he promises to send Timothy to the Philippians for ministry,{{Bibleref2c|Phil|2:19–23}} and expects to also pay them a personal visit.{{Bibleref2c|Phil|2:24}}

==Christ poem==
{{contradiction|date=February 2020}}
Chapter 2 of the epistle contains a famous poem describing the nature of Christ and his act of redemption:
{{quote|Who, though he was in the form of God,&lt;br/&gt;
:Did not regard being equal with God
:Something to be grasped after.
But he emptied himself&lt;br/&gt;
:Taking on the form of a slave,
:And coming in the likeness of humans.
And being found in appearance as a human&lt;br/&gt;
:He humbled himself
:Becoming obedient unto death— even death on a cross.

Therefore God highly exalted him&lt;br/&gt;
:And bestowed on him the name
:That is above every name,
That at the name of Jesus&lt;br/&gt;
:Every knee should bow
:Of those in heaven, and on earth, and under the earth.
And every tongue should confess&lt;br/&gt;
:That Jesus Christ is Lord
:To the glory of God the Father.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;|Philippians 2:5-11, translated by [[Bart D. Ehrman]]&lt;ref name=&quot;ehrman&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Ehrman |first=Bart D. |title=How Jesus Became God: The Exaltation of a Jewish Preacher from Galilee |year=2014 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dmspAgAAQBAJ |publisher=HarperOne |isbn=978-0-0617-7819-3 |chapter=7. Jesus as God on Earth: Early Incarnation Christologies }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
Due to its unique poetic style, scholars{{who?|date=January 2020}} agree that this passage constitutes an early Christian poem that was composed by someone else prior to Paul's writings, as early as the 40s AD. While the passage is often called a &quot;hymn,&quot; some scholars believe this to be an inappropriate name since it does not have a rhythmic or metrical structure in the original Greek.&lt;ref name=&quot;ehrman&quot;/&gt;

=== Incarnation Christology ===
The Christ poem is significant because it strongly suggests that there were very early Christians who understood Jesus to be a pre-existent celestial being, who chose to take on human form, rather than a human who was later exalted to a divine status.&lt;ref name=&quot;martin&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Martin |first=Ralph P. |title=Philippians 2:5-11 in Recent Interpretation &amp; in the Setting of Early Christian Worship |year=1997 |edition=2nd |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Xwvi00xlTCEC |publisher=InterVarsity Press |location=Downers Grove, IL |isbn=0-8308-1894-4 |pages=vii-ix }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ehrman&quot;/&gt;

Importantly, while the author of the poem did believe that Jesus existed in heaven before his physical incarnation, this does not necessarily mean that he was believed to be ''equal'' to [[God the Father]] prior to his death and resurrection. This largely depends on how the Greek word [[wikt: ἁρπάζω|harpagmon]] is translated in verse 6 (&quot;Something to be grasped after / exploited&quot;). If &quot;harpagmon&quot; is rendered as &quot;something to be exploited,&quot; as it is in many Christian Bible translations, then the implication is that Christ was already equal to God prior to his incarnation. But Bart Ehrman and others have argued that the correct translation is in fact &quot;something to be grasped after,&quot; implying that Jesus was ''not'' equal to God before his resurrection. Outside of this passage, &quot;harpagmon&quot; and related words were almost always used to refer to something that a person doesn't yet possess but tries to acquire.&lt;ref name=&quot;ehrman&quot;/&gt;

It is widely agreed by interpreters, however, that the Christ poem depicts Jesus as equal to God ''after'' his resurrection. This is because the last two stanzas quote {{Bibleverse|Isaiah|45:22–23|NRSV}} (&quot;Every knee shall bow, every tongue confess&quot;), which in the original context clearly refers to God the Father.&lt;ref name=&quot;ehrman&quot;/&gt;

== Outline ==
{{Div col}}
:I. Preface (1:1–11)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bible.org/seriespage/philippians-introduction-argument-and-outline|title=11. Philippians: Introduction, Argument, and Outline|work=Bible.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:
::A. Salutation (1:1–2)
::
::B. Thanksgiving for the Philippians’ Participation in the Gospel (1:3–8)
::
::C. Prayer for the Philippians’ Discerning Love to Increase until the Day of Christ (1:9–11)
:
:II. Paul’s Present Circumstances (1:12–26)
:
::A. Paul’s Imprisonment (1:12–13)
::
::B. The Brothers’ Response (1:14–17)
::
::C. Paul’s Attitude (1:18–26)
:
:III. Practical Instructions in Sanctification (1:27–2:30)
:
::A. Living Boldly as Citizens of Heaven (1:27–1:30)
::
::B. Living Humbly as Servants of Christ (2:1–11)
::
:::1. The Motivation to Live Humbly (2:1–4)
:::
:::2. The Model of Living Humbly (2:5–11)
::
::::a. Christ’s Emptying (2:5–8)
::::
::::b. Christ’s Exaltation (2:9–11)
::
::C. Living Obediently as Children of God (2:12–18)
::
:::1. The Energizing of God (2:12–13)
:::
:::2. The Effect on the Saints (2:14–18)
::
::D. Examples of Humble Servants (2:19–30)
::
:::1. The Example of Timothy (2:19–24)
:::
:::2. The Example of Epaphroditus (2:25–30)
::
:IV. Polemical Doctrinal Issues (3:1–4:1)
:
::A. The Judaizers Basis: The Flesh (3:1–6)
::
::B. Paul’s Goal: The Resurrection (3:7–11)
::
::C. Perfection and Humility (3:12–16)
::
::D. Paul as an Example of Conduct and Watchfulness (3:17–4:1)
:
:V. Postlude (4:2–23)
:
::A. Exhortations (4:2–9)
::
:::1. Being United (4:2–3)
:::
:::2. Rejoicing without Anxiety (4:4–7)
:::
:::3. Thinking and Acting Purely (4:8–9)
::
::B. A Note of Thanks (4:10–20)
::
:::1. Paul’s Contentment (4:10–13)
:::
:::2. The Philippians’ Gift (4:14–18)
:::
:::3. God’s Provision (4:19–20)
::
::C. Final Greetings (4:21–23)
{{Div col end}}

==See also==
* [[Textual variants in the New Testament#Epistle to the Philippians|Textual variants in the Epistle to the Philippians]]
* ''[[Cupio dissolvi]]''

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
* {{Eastons}}

==Further reading==
* {{Cite journal |first=Valerie |last=Abrahamsen |authorlink= |date=March 1988 |title=Christianity and the Rock Reliefs at Philippi |journal=Biblical Archaeologist |volume=51 |issue=1 |pages=46–56 |id= |url= |accessdate= |quote= |doi=10.2307/3210038 |jstor=3210038 }}
* Barclay, William. 1975. ''The Letters to the Philippians, Colossians, and Thessalonians''. Rev. ed. Daily Bible Study Series. Louisville, Ky.: Westminster.
* Barnes, Albert. 1949. ''Ephesians, Philippians, and Colossians''. Enlarged type edition. Edited by Robert Frew. Grand Rapids, Mich.: Baker.
* Black, David A. 1995. &quot;The Discourse Structure of Philippians: A Study in Textlinquistics.&quot; ''Novum Testamentum'' 37.1 (Jan.): 16–49
* Blevins, James L. 1980. &quot;Introduction to Philippians.&quot; ''Review and Expositor'' 77 (Sum.): 311–325.
* Brooks, James A. 1980. “Introduction to Philippians.” ''[[Southwestern Journal of Theology]]'' 23.1 (Fall): 7–54.
* Bruce, Frederick F. 1989. ''Philippians''. New International Biblical Commentary. New Testament Series. Edited by W. Ward Gasque. Peabody, Mass.: Hendrickson, 2002.
* Burton, Ernest De Witt. 1896. “The Epistles of the Imprisonment.” ''Biblical World'' 7.1: 46–56.
* Elkins, Garland. 1976. “The Living Message of Philippians.” pp.&amp;nbsp;171–180 in ''The Living Messages of the Books of the New Testament''. Edited by Garland Elkins and Thomas B. Warren. Jonesboro, Ark.: National Christian.
* Garland, David E. 1985. “The Composition and Unity of Philippians: Some Neglected Literary Factors.” ''Novum Testamentum'' 27.2 (April): 141–173.
* Hagelberg, Dave. 2007. ''Philippians: An Ancient Thank You Letter – A Study of Paul and His Ministry Partners’ Relationship''. English ed. Metro Manila: Philippine Challenge.
* Hawthorne, Gerald F. 1983. ''Philippians''. Word Biblical Commentary 43. Edited by Bruce Metzger. Nashville, Tenn.: Nelson.
* Herrick, Greg. [http://bible.org/seriespage/introduction-background-and-outline-philippians “Introduction, Background, and Outline to Philippians.”] ''Bible.org''.
* Jackson, Wayne. 1987. ''The Book of Philippians: A Grammatical and Practical Study''. Abilene, Tex.: Quality.
* Kennedy, H. A. A. 1900. “The Epistle to the Philippians.” ''Expositor’s Greek Testament''. Vol. 3. Edited by W. Robertson Nicoll. New York, NY: Doran.
* Lenski, Richard C. H. 1937. ''The Interpretation of St. Paul’s Epistles to the Galatians, to the Ephesians, and to the Philippians''. Repr. Peabody, Mass.: Hendrickson, 2001.
* Lipscomb, David and J.W. Shepherd. 1968. ''Ephesians, Philippians, and Colossians''. Rev. ed. Edited by J.W. Shepherd. Gospel Advocated Commentary. Nashville, Tenn.: Gospel Advocate.
* Llewelyn, Stephen R. 1995. [https://web.archive.org/web/20081217152148/http://98.131.162.170//tynbul/library/TynBull_1995_46_2_07_Llewelyn_SendingLetters_Philp.pdf “Sending Letters in the Ancient World: Paul and the Philippians.”] ''Tyndale Bulletin'' 46.2: 337–356.
* Mackay, B. S. 1961. “Further Thoughts on Philippians.” ''New Testament Studies'' 7.2 (Jan.): 161–170.
* Martin, Ralph P. 1959. ''The Epistle of Paul to the Philippians''. Tyndale New Testament Commentaries. Ed. By R.V.G. Tasker. Grand Rapids, Mich.: Eerdmans, 1977.
* Martin, Ralph P. 1976. ''Philippians''. New Century Bible Commentary. New Testament. Edited by Matthew Black. Repr. Grand Rapids, Mich.: Eerdmans.
* McAlister, Bryan. 2011. “Introduction to Philippians: Mindful of How We Fill Our Minds.” ''Gospel Advocate'' 153.9 (Sept.): 12–13
* Mule, D. S. M. (1981). The Letter to the Philippians. Cook Book House.
* Müller, Jacobus J. 1955. ''The Epistle of Paul to the Philippians''. New International Commentary on the New Testament. Ed. By Frederick F. Bruce. Grand Rapids, Mich.: Eerdmans, 1991.
* Pelaez, I. N. (1970). Epistle on the Philippians. Angel &amp; Water;reprint, Angels new books, ed. Michael Angelo. (1987). Peabody, MA: Hendrickson.
* ''Dictionary of Paul and His Letters'', s.v. &quot;Philippians, Letter to the&quot;
* Reicke, Bo. 1970. [http://biblicalstudies.org.uk/pdf/ahg/caesarea_reicke.pdf “Caesarea, Rome, and the Captivity Epistles.”] pp.&amp;nbsp;277–286 in ''Apostolic History and the Gospel: Biblical and Historical Essays Presented to F. F. Bruce''. Edited by W. Ward Gasque and Ralph P. Martin. Exeter: Paternoster Press.
* Roper, David. 2003. [http://www.biblecourses.com/English/en_lessons/EN_199307_11.pdf “Philippians: Rejoicing in Christ.”] ''BibleCourses.com''. Accessed: 3 Sept. 2011.
* Russell, Ronald. 1982. [http://www.etsjets.org/files/JETS-PDFs/25/25-3/25-3-pp295-306_JETS.pdf &quot;Pauline Letter Structure in Philippians.&quot;] ''Journal of the Evangelical Theological Society'' 25.3 (Sept.): 295–306.
* Sanders, Ed. 1987. “Philippians.” pp.&amp;nbsp;331–339 in ''New Testament Survey''. Edited by Don Shackelford. Searcy, Ark.: Harding University.
* Sergio Rosell Nebreda, ''Christ Identity: A Social-Scientific Reading of Philippians 2.5–11'' (Göttingen, Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht, 2011) (Forschungen zur Religion und Literatur des Alten und Neuen Testaments, 240).
* Swift, Robert C. 1984. [http://faculty.gordon.edu/hu/bi/Ted_Hildebrandt/NTeSources/NTArticles/BSac-NT/Swift-PhilipStruct-BS.htm &quot;The Theme and Structure of Philippians.&quot;] ''Bibliotheca Sacra'' 141 (July): 234–254.
* Synge, F.C. 1951. ''Philippians and Colossians''. Torch Bible Commentaries. Edited by John Marsh, David M. Paton, and Alan Richardson. London: SCM, 1958.
* Thielman, Frank. 1995. ''Philippians''. NIV Application Commentary. General Editor. Terry Muck. Grand Rapids, Mich.: Zondervan.
* Vincent, Marvin R. 1897. ''The Epistle to the Philippians and to Philemon''. International Critical Commentary. Ed. By Samuel R. Driver, Alfred Plummer, Charles A. Briggs. Edinburgh: Clark, 1902.
* Vincent, Marvin R. ''Vincent’s Word Studies in the New Testament''. 4 vols. Peabody, Mass.: Hendrickson, n.d.
* Wallace, Daniel B. [http://bible.org/seriespage/philippians-introduction-argument-and-outline “Philippians: Introductions, Argument, and Outline.”] ''Bible.org''.
* Walvoord, John F. 1971. ''Philippians: Triumph in Christ''. Everyman's Bible Commentary. Chicago, Ill.: Moody.

== External links ==
{{wikiquote}}
Online translations of the Epistle to the Philippians:
* [http://www.gospelhall.org/bible/bible.php?passage=Philippians+1 ''Online Bible'' at GospelHall.org]
* {{librivox book | dtitle=Bible: Philippians| stitle=Bible NT Philippians}} Various versions
Online Study of Philippians:
* [http://www.tyndale.ca/seminary/mtsmodular/reading-rooms/newt/philippians Letter to the Philippians Online Reading Room]: Commentaries and other resources (Tyndale Seminary)
* [http://biblicalstudies.org.uk/philippians.php Letter to the Philippians Online Reading Room]: Commentaries and other resources (BiblicalStudies.org.uk)
* [http://www.ntgateway.com/paul-the-apostle/philippians/ Letter to the Philippians Online Reading Room]: Commentaries and other resources (NTGateway.com)
* [http://www.textweek.com/pauline/phil.htm Letter to the Philippians Online Reading Room]: Commentaries and other resources (TextWeek.com)

Related articles:
* [http://www.bible.org/page.asp?page_id=1333 Bible.org introduction to Philippians]
* [http://www.new-testament-christian.com/philippians.html Sermons on Philippians]
* {{CathEncy|wstitle=Epistle to the Philippians}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou|[[Pauline epistles|Pauline]] [[Epistles|Epistle]]|||}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Epistle to the Ephesians|Ephesians]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=&lt;small&gt;[[New Testament]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Books of the Bible]]}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Epistle to the Colossians|Colossians]]}}
{{s-end}}
{{Epistle to the Philippians}}
{{Books of the Bible}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Epistle To The Philippians}}
[[Category:1st-century Christian texts]]
[[Category:New Testament books|Philippians]]
[[Category:Pauline epistles]]
[[Category:Prison writings]]
[[Category:Canonical epistles|Philippians]]
[[Category:Christianity in Roman Macedonia|Philippians]]
[[Category:Ancient Philippi]]
[[Category:Epistle to the Philippians| ]]</text>
      <sha1>2jwe3n4jsdy8pzc561djge9gkm82x1e</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
