  <page>
    <title>Colossae</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6846</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941047895</id>
      <parentid>937304693</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-16T08:30:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2A00:23C6:EA04:3900:656D:BA7D:C148:53EE</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues|
{{more citations needed|date=February 2016}}
{{format footnotes|date=February 2016}}
}}

'''Colossae''' ({{IPAc-en|k|ə|ˈ|l|ɒ|s|i}}; [[Ancient Greek|Greek]]: [[wikt:Κολοσσαί|Κολοσσαί]]) was an ancient city of [[Phrygia]] in Asia Minor, and one of the most celebrated cities of southern [[Anatolia]] (modern [[Turkey]]). The [[Epistle to the Colossians]], an early Christian text which identifies its author as [[Paul the Apostle]], is addressed to the church in Colossae.  A significant city from the 5th century BC onwards, it had dwindled in importance by the time of Paul, but was notable for the existence of its local angel cult.  It was part of the Roman – and then Byzantine – province of [[Phrygia Pacatiana]], before being destroyed in 1192/3 and its population relocating to nearby Chonai (modern day [[Honaz]]).

==Location and geography==
Colossae was located in [[Phrygia]], in Asia Minor.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=S5GJaakRvPgC&amp;pg=PA71&amp;lpg=PA71&amp;dq=Colossae+was+located+in+Phrygia,+in+Asia+Minor.&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=qYdJwFpvyO&amp;sig=i7_PSwRcnV-oZvCqDa-xvFBzRyg&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjL4ZukgbvRAhWHWCYKHXt5AEI4ChDoAQgvMAU#v=onepage&amp;q=Colossae%20was%20located%20in%20Phrygia,%20in%20Asia%20Minor.&amp;f=false|title=The Uttermost Part of the Earth: A Guide to Places in the Bible|last=Losch|first=Richard R.|date=2005-01-01|publisher=Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing|isbn=9780802828057|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was located 15&amp;nbsp;km southeast of [[Laodicea on the Lycus|Laodicea]] on the road through the [[Lycus (river of Phrygia)|Lycus]] Valley near the Lycus River at the foot of Mt. Cadmus, the highest mountain in Turkey's western Aegean Region, and between the cities Sardeis and Celaenae, and southeast of the ancient city of [[Hierapolis]].&lt;ref&gt;Trainor, Michael, ''Colossae - Colossal In Name Only?'' [[Biblical Archaeology Review]], March/April 2019, Vol. 45, No. 2, p. 45.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/54952013|title=Brill's New Pauly : encyclopaedia of the ancient world. Antiquity. [CAT-CYP]|last=|first=|date=2002-2010|publisher=Brill|others=Cancik, Hubert., Schneider, Helmuth., Salazar, Christine F., Orton, David E.|year=|isbn=9004122664|location=Leiden|page=579|oclc=54952013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  At Colossae, [[Herodotus]] describes how, &quot;the river Lycos falls into an opening of the earth and disappears from view, and then after an interval of about five furlongs it comes up to view again, and this river also flows into the [[Büyük Menderes River|Maiander.]]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/2456|title=The History of Herodotus — Volume 2 by Herodotus|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Despite a treacherously ambiguous cartography and history, Colossae has been clearly distinguished in modern research from nearby ''Chonai'' (Χῶναι), now called [[Honaz]], with what remains of the buried ruins of Colossae (&quot;the mound&quot;)  lying 3&amp;nbsp;km to the north of Honaz.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author1=Cadwallader, Alan H.  |author2=Trainor, Michael | year = 2011 | title = Colossae in Space and Time: Linking to an Ancient City | chapter = Colossae in Space and Time: Overcoming Dislocation, Dismemberment and Anachronicity | series = Novum Testamentum et Orbis Antiquus/Studien zur Umwelt des Neuen Testaments (NTOA/StUNT), Vol. 94 | editors = Cadwallader, Alan H. &amp; Trainor, Michael | pages = 9–47 | location = Göttingen, GER | publisher = Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht | isbn = 3647533971 | url = https://books.google.com/books?isbn=3525533977 | access-date = 17 February 2016 | quote = }} The case is made exhaustively in this book, over pages 11-37, wherein it states—after dispensing with a further false association of the ancient city with the island of Rhodes  the home of The Colossus of Rhodes, which resulted in its being misplaced for hundreds of years (by &quot;almost 200 kilometers to the south-west,&quot; p. 18ff)—in summary, that: &quot;Colossae's various positions on early maps confirmed the confusion over identity [opening section title]. Cartographers positioned Colossae to the west (rather than south-east) of Laodicea&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt; or, as 'Conos', between Laodicea to the north-west and Hieropolis to the north-east.&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt; [p. 11] … 'Chonos' or some other guesttimation of the spelling of Honaz&lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt; sometimes subsumed Colossae. [p. 13] … The inhabitants of the immediate vicinity of the ancient site [Colossae, which had ceased to exist] were shackled in bureaucratic tabulation for tax purposes to the town of Honaz. [p. 14] … When Frances Arundell's sketch of Honaz appeared in 1834, the town had descended from the mountain heights [it was a mountain fortress, Honazdağ] but it was similarly labelled, albeit after the fashion of Nicetas Choniates: 'Chonas, … anciently Colossae'.&lt;sup&gt;98&lt;/sup&gt; [p. 32] … The question was whether Honaz and Colossae were to be equated or separated and whether the contemporary Honaz was the means to pinpoint the ancient… site. [p. 33] … William Hamilton became the one credited with the separation of Colossae from Chonai with the former's location at the mound three kilometers to the north of Honaz.&lt;sup&gt;108&lt;/sup&gt; [p. 35] … Two photographs of the 'Ruines de Colossae' and 'Chonas' by Henri Carmignac published toward the endif the nineteenth century finally eliminated the concordant visualisation of the places that had been the legacy of Arundell ''(Fig. 11)''.&lt;sup&gt;113&lt;/sup&gt; [p. 37].&quot; For much earlier sources presenting the errant historical opinion, see the next two citations.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = Smith, William | year = 1854 | title = Dictionary of Greek and Roman Geography | chapter = Colossae |  url = http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus:text:1999.04.0064:id=colossae-geo | location =  | publisher =  | access-date =  | quote =  }}{{full citation needed|date=February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = Pétridès, Sophrone  | year = 1908 | title = Catholic Encyclopedia | chapter = Colossae | location = New York, NY | publisher =  | url = http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/04131a.htm  | access-date =  | quote =  }}{{full citation needed|date=February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origin and etymology of place name==

The medieval poet [[Manuel Philes]], incorrectly, imagined that the name &quot;Colossae&quot; was connected to the [[Colossus of Rhodes]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Cad-Train&quot;&gt;Cadwallader, Alan H., and Michael Trainor (2011). &quot;Colossae in Space and Time: Overcoming Dislocation, Dismemberment and Anachronicity&quot;. In Cadwallader and Trainor, eds. ''Colossae in Space and Time: Linding to an Ancient City.'' Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht. pp. 18-19.&lt;/ref&gt; More recently, in an interpretation which ties Colossae to an Indo-European root that happens to be shared with the word ''kolossos'', Jean-Pierre Vernant has connected the name to the idea of setting up a sacred space or shrine.&lt;ref&gt;Vernant, Jean-Pierre (2006) [1965]. ''Myth and Thought Among the Greeks''. Third edition of a translation from the French originally published in 1983, from a French work published in 1965. Zone Books. p. 321.&lt;/ref&gt; Another proposal relates the name to the Greek ''kolazo'', &quot;to punish&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cad-Train&quot; /&gt; Others believe the name derives from the manufacture of its famous dyed wool, or ''colossinus''.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated47&quot;&gt;Trainor, Michael, ''Colossae - Colossal In Name Only?'' [[Biblical Archaeology Review]], March/April 2019, Vol. 45, No. 2, p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
===Before the Pauline period===

{{expand section | a cohesive account of the history of the municipality and its peoples and cultures, as appear in many texts on the subject | small = no |date=February 2016}}

The first mention of the city may be in a 17th-century BC [[Hittite language|Hittite]] inscription, which speaks of a city called Huwalušija, which some archeologists believe refer to early Colossae. The Fifth Century geographer [[Herodotus]] first mentions Colossae by name and as a &quot;great city in Phrygia&quot;, which accommodates the Persian King [[Xerxes I]] while en route to wage war against the Greeks - showing the city had already reached a certain level of wealth and size by this time. &lt;ref&gt;Trainor, Michael, ''Colossae - Colossal In Name Only?'' [[Biblical Archaeology Review]], March/April 2019, Vol. 45, No. 2, p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt; 
Writing in the 5th Century BC, [[Xenophon]] refers to Colossae as &quot;a populous city, wealthy and of considerable magnitude&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/22003|title=The First Four Books of Xenophon's Anabasis|last=Watson|first=J. S.|publisher=Project Gutenberg|year=2007|isbn=|location=|page=6}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It was famous for its wool trade.  [[Strabo]] notes that the city drew great revenue from the flocks, and that the wool of Colossae gave its name to colour ''colossinus''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/44885|title=The Geography of Strabo, Volume 2 (of 3) by Strabo|last=|first=|publisher=|year=|isbn=|location=|page=334|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;   

In 396 BC, Colossae was the site of the execution of the rebellious Persian satrap [[Tissaphernes]] who was lured there and slain by an agent of the party of [[Cyrus the Younger]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Tissaphernes|url=https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/1911_Encyclop%C3%A6dia_Britannica/Tissaphernes|journal=1911 Encyclopædia Britannica|volume= 26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Pauline period===

Although during the [[Hellenistic]] period, the town was of some mercantile importance, by the 1st century it had dwindled greatly in size and significance.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=pAwqB33cr_wC&amp;pg=PA174&amp;lpg=PA174&amp;dq=Colossae+first+century&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=m_8EbgOhQ7&amp;sig=z8PV_iBFxi_69TlgsSM8U4XtlyY&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwim_rmQpdvRAhXFZCYKHVKlBusQ6AEIPzAG#v=onepage&amp;q=Colossae%20first%20century&amp;f=false|title=Colossae in Space and Time: Linking to an Ancient City|last=Cadwallader|first=Alan H.|last2=Trainor|first2=Michael|date=2011-12-07|publisher=Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht|isbn=9783647533971|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Paul the Apostle|Paul']]&lt;nowiki/&gt;s letter to the Colossians point to the existence of an early Christian community.  The town was known for its fusion of religious influences (syncretism), which included [[ancient Judaism|Jewish]], [[Gnosticism|Gnostic]], and pagan influences that in the first century AD were described as an angel-cult.&lt;ref name=&quot;BruceNTH69&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2RyJAAAAMAAJ|title=New Testament History|author=Bruce, F.F. [Frederick Fyvie]|publisher=Galilee/Doubleday|year=1980|isbn=0385025335|location=New York, NY|pages=415f|quote=[Quoting:] Those churches which claimed an apostolic foundation attached great importance to the maintenance of the teaching which they had originally received. There were powerful forces at work in many of them which militated against the maintenance of that teaching; chief among these were those tendencies which in a few decades blossomed forth in the elaborate systems of the various schools of Gnosticism. One form of incipient Gnosticism is the syncretistic angel-cult of nonconformist Jewish foundation and pagan superstructure attacked in the Epistle to the Colossians.|access-date=17 February 2016|orig-year=1969}} A further, less stable online source with access to these pages is available at [https://www.amazon.com/New-Testament-History-F-Bruce/dp/0385025335], accessed same date.&lt;/ref&gt;  This unorthodox cult venerated the [[Michael (archangel)|archangel Michael]] who is said to have caused a curative spring to gush from a fissure in the Earth.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

The canonical biblical text [[Epistle to the Colossians]] is addressed to the Christian community in Colossae. The epistle has traditionally been attributed to [[Paul the Apostle]] due to its autobiographical salutation &amp; style&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=colossians+1&amp;version=NIV Colossians 1:1 Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus by the will of God, and Timothy our brother,  2 To God’s holy people in Colossae, the faithful brothers and sisters in Christ]&lt;/ref&gt;, but some modern critical scholars now believe it to be written by another author some time after Paul's death.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODCC self&quot;&gt;{{Citation | contribution = Colossians, Epistle to the | editor-last = Cross | editor-first = F.L. | title = The Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church | place = New York | publisher = Oxford University Press | year = 2005}}.&lt;/ref&gt; It is believed that one aim of the letter was to address the challenges that the Colossian community faced in its context of the syncretistic Gnostic religions that were developing in Asia Minor.&lt;ref name = BruceNTH69/&gt;

According to the Epistle to the Colossians, [[Epaphras]] seems to have been a person of some importance in the Christian community in Colossae ({{bibleverse||Col.|1:7|NSRV}}; {{bibleverse-nb||Col.|4:12|NSRV}}), and tradition presents him as its first bishop.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = Pétridès, Sophrone  | year = 1908 | title = Catholic Encyclopedia | chapter = Colossae | location = New York, NY | publisher =  | url = http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/04131a.htm  | access-date =  | quote = &quot;Colossæ was the home of...Onesimus and Epaphras, who probably founded the Church of Colossæ.&quot;  }}&lt;/ref&gt;
The epistle also seems to imply that [[Paul the Apostle|Paul]] had never visited the city, because it only speaks of him having &quot;heard&quot; of the Colossians' faith ({{bibleverse||Col.|1:4|NSRV}}), and in the [[Epistle to Philemon]] Paul tells [[Philemon of Colossae|Philemon]] of his hope to visit Colossae upon being freed from prison (see [[Philemon 1:22]]). Tradition also gives Philemon as the second bishop of the see.

The city was decimated by an earthquake in the 60s AD, and was rebuilt independent of the support of Rome.{{citation needed|date=February 2016}}

The Apostolic Constitutions list Philemon as a Bishop of Colossae.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = Translated by James Donaldson. | year = 1886 | title = Apostolic Constitutions. From Ante-Nicene Fathers, Vol. 7. Edited by Alexander Roberts, James Donaldson, and A. Cleveland Coxe. | chapter = (Book VII) Section 4 | location = Buffalo, NY | publisher = Christian Literature Publishing Co. | url = http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/07157.htm | access-date = 2018-12-28 | quote = &quot;Of Colossæ, Philemon.&quot;  }}&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, the Catholic Encyclopedia considers Philemon doubtful. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = Pétridès, Sophrone  | year = 1908 | title = Catholic Encyclopedia | chapter = Colossae | location = New York, NY | publisher =  | url = http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/04131a.htm | access-date = 2018-12-28 | quote = &quot;Besides St. Epaphras... Archippus and Philemon, especially the latter, are very doubtful.&quot;  }} &lt;/ref&gt;

The first historically documented bishop is Epiphanius,{{when|date=February 2016}} who was not personally at the [[Council of Chalcedon]], but whose metropolitan bishop Nunechius of [[Laodicea on the Lycus|Laodicea]], the capital of the [[Roman province]] of [[Phrygia Pacatiana]] signed the acts on his behalf.{{citation needed|date=February 2016}}

===Byzantine period and decline===
{{expand section | with SOURCED material relevant to its destruction by the Saracens and the Turks | small = no|date=February 2016}}
The city's fame and renowned status continued into the Byzantine period, and in 858, it was distinguished as a Metropolitan See. The Byzantines also built the church of St. Michael in the vicinity of Colossae, one of the largest church buildings in the Middle East. Nevertheless, sources suggest that the town may have decreased in size or may even been completely abandoned due to Arab invasions in the seventh and eighth centuries, forcing the population to flee to resettle in the nearby city of Chonai (modern day [[Honaz]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated47&quot;/&gt;

Colossae's famous church was destroyed in 1192/3 during the Byzantine civil wars.  It was a suffragan diocese of Laodicea in Phyrigia Pacatiane but was replaced in the Byzantine period by the Chonae settlement on higher ground&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

===Modern study and archeology===
{{expand section | with SOURCED material relevant to the history of its mapping and historical and literary discussion (see further reading), and on plans for its excavation | small = no|date=February 2016}}
As of 2019, Colossae has never been excavated, as most archeological attention has been focused on nearby Laodicea and Hierapolis,&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated48&quot;&gt;Trainor, Michael, ''Colossae - Colossal In Name Only?'' [[Biblical Archaeology Review]], March/April 2019, Vol. 45, No. 2, p. 48.&lt;/ref&gt; though plans are reported for an Australian-led expedition to the site. The present site exhibits a biconical acropolis almost 100 feet high, and encompasses an area of almost 22 acres. On the eastern slope there sits a theater which probably seated around 5,000 people, suggesting a total population of 25,000 - 30,000 people. The theater was probably built during the Roman period, and may be near an agora that abuts the ''Cardo Maximus'', or the city's main north-south road. Ceramic finds around the theater confirm the city's early occupation in the third and second millennia BC. Northeast of the [[tell (archaeology)|tell]], and most likely outside the city walls, a [[necropolis]] displays Hellenistic tombs with two main styles of burial: one with an antecedent room connected to an inner chamber, and [[tumulus | tumuli]], or underground chambers accessed by stairs leading to the entrance. Outside the tell there are also remains of sections of columns that may have marked a processional way or the ''cardo''. Today, the remains of one column marks the location where locals believe a church once stood, possibly that of St. Michael. &lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated48&quot;/&gt; Near the Lycus River, there is evidence that water channels had been cut out of the rock with a complex of pipes and sluice gates to divert water for bathing and for agricultural and industrial purposes. &lt;ref&gt;Trainor, Michael, ''Colossae - Colossal In Name Only?'' [[Biblical Archaeology Review]], March/April 2019, Vol. 45, No. 2, p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Modern legacy===
The holiness and healing properties associated with the waters of Colossae during the Byzantine Era continue to this day, particularly at a pool fed by the Lycus River at the Göz picnic grounds west of Colossae at the foot of Mt. Cadmus. Locals consider the water to be therapeutic. &lt;ref&gt;Trainor, Michael, ''Colossae - Colossal In Name Only?'' [[Biblical Archaeology Review]], March/April 2019, Vol. 45, No. 2, p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes and references==
{{reflist}}
{{EBD|wstitle=Colossae}}

== Further reading ==
* {{cite book | author = Bruce, F.F. [Frederick Fyvie] | year = 1980 | orig-year =  1969 | title = New Testament History | location = New York, NY | publisher = Galilee/Doubleday | isbn = 0-38502533-5 | url =  https://books.google.com/books?id=2RyJAAAAMAAJ | access-date = 17 February 2016 | pages = 415f}} A further, less stable online source with access to these pages is [https://www.amazon.com/New-Testament-History-F-Bruce/dp/0385025335  Amazon], accessed same date.
* {{EBD|wstitle=Colossae}}{{Update inline|date=February 2016}}
* Bennett, Andrew Lloyd. &quot;Archaeology From Art: Investigating Colossae and the Miracle of the Archangel Michael at Kona.&quot; ''Near East Archaeological Society Bulletin'' 50 (2005):15–26.

==External links==
*[http://holylandphotos.org/browse.asp?s=1,3,7,23,62 Map and pictures of ruins]
*{{cite EB1911|wstitle=Colossae|volume=6|pages=725–726|short=1}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2018}}

{{Ancient settlements in Turkey}}

[[Category:Roman towns and cities in Turkey]]
[[Category:Pauline churches]]
[[Category:New Testament cities]]
[[Category:Former populated places in Turkey]]
[[Category:Populated places in Phrygia]]
[[Category:Populated places of the Byzantine Empire]]
[[Category:Catholic titular sees in Asia]]
[[Category:History of Denizli Province]]</text>
      <sha1>s23ppcsd9ty51o19r22vjdz522ebiq5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
