  <page>
    <title>CDC</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6809</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939139178</id>
      <parentid>938875891</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-04T16:33:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TheGreatSG'rean</username>
        <id>36415105</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Places */Added 'defunct' as CDC is replaced by NCID.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Wiktionary|CDC}}
'''CDC'''  may refer to:
{{TOC right}}

==Organizations==

===Government===
* [[Centers for Disease Control and Prevention]], a United States government public health agency
* [[Centers for Disease Control and Prevention Korea]], a South Korean government public health agency
* [[Centers for Disease Control (Taiwan)]], an agency in Taiwan (the Republic of China) that combats the threat of communicable diseases
* [[Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention]], a public health agency in the People's Republic of China
* [[Civil Defence Corps]], (established in 1949 and stood down in 1968), under the authority of the [[Home Office]] of the [[United Kingdom|UK]]. 
* [[Community Development Council]], Singapore government-led community programs
* [[Community of Democratic Choice]], an intergovernmental organization in Eastern Europe to promote democracy and human rights
* [[Canadian Dairy Commission]], a Canadian government Crown Corporation that oversees dairy production

===Politics===
* [[Congress for Democratic Change]], a Liberian political party
* [[Democratic Convergence of Catalonia]] ({{lang-ca|Convergència Democràtica de Catalunya|links=no}}), a former political party in Catalonia, Spain (1974–2016)
* [[California Democratic Council]], an unofficial umbrella organization of volunteer Democratic Clubs in the United States

===Associations===
* [[Coalition to Diversify Computing]], a joint organization of the Association for Computing Machinery (ACM) and the Computing Research Association (CRA)

===Non-profit===
* [[Community development corporation]], any non-profit organization that promotes and supports a community
* [[Certified Development Company]], a U.S. Small Business Administration program designed to provide financing for the purchase of fixed assets
* Commission for Developing Countries, a Commission of the [[International Mathematical Union]]

===Business===
* ''{{lang|fr|[[Caisse des dépôts et consignations]]}}'' (&quot;Deposits and Consignments Fund&quot;), a financial institution owned by the French government
* [[CDC Group]], formerly the Commonwealth Development Corporation and Colonial Development Corporation, a British development organisation owned by the UK Government
* [[Cameroon Development Corporation]], an agribusiness company located in Limbe, Cameroon
* [[Control Data Corporation]], former supercomputer company
** [[CDC Software]], a computer software company spun off from Control Data Corporation
* [[ComfortDelGro Australia]], a major Australian operator of buses formerly named ComfortDelGro Cabcharge
* [[Construction Data Company]], also known as CDC News and CDC Publishing, a commercial construction reporting service
* [[Loong Air]], by ICAO code

===Other organizations===
* [[Cult of the Dead Cow]] (cDc), a computer hacker and DIY media organization

==Places==
* [[Center Day Camp]], a summer day camp in North Windham, Maine, U.S.
* ''{{lang|fr|[[Centre de documentation collégiale]]}}'', specialized library in  Quebec, Canada
* [[Communicable Disease Centre]], a defunct hospital at Moulmein Road in Novena, Singapore
* [[Cedar City Regional Airport]], by IATA code

==Science==
* [[Cholesterol-dependent cytolysin]], pore forming exotoxins, secreted by Gram positive bacteria
* [[Cell-division cycle]], also cell cycle in biology
** Cell-division cycle protein, e.g. [[Cdc42]]
* [[Complement-dependent cytotoxicity]]
* [[Conventional dendritic cell]] (previously called Myeloid dendritic cell, cDC)
* [[Cross-Dehydrogenative Coupling]], a type of reactions in organic chemistry

==Technology==
* [[Change data capture]], a methodology used in  data warehousing and  databases
* [[Clock domain crossing]], a signal that crosses between different clock domains of a system
* [[Connected Device Configuration]], Java framework for building Java ME applications on embedded devices
* [[Communications daughter card]], an Ethernet, Modem or Bluetooth expansion card for mobiles
* [[Carbide-derived carbon]], a family of carbon structures with tunable properties produced via etching of metal carbides
* [[USB communications device class]], a composite Universal Serial Bus device class

==Other uses==
* Book titles:
** ''[[CDC?]]'', a children's book by William Steig (sequel to ''CDB!'')
** ''CDC'', 20th-century diet book ''[[Calories Don't Count]]''
* [[Combat Direction Center]], the tactical center of an aircraft carrier
* [[Cul de canard]], duck feathers used in fly fishing
* [[Continuous Discharge Certificate]], seafarer's identity document

==See also==
* C.DC., the Swiss botany author abbreviation of Anne [[Casimir de Candolle]]

{{disambiguation}}</text>
      <sha1>03bq8tgkqaqra9sno9ov894pmujr9xt</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
