  <page>
    <title>Base on balls</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3802</id>
    <revision>
      <id>931453982</id>
      <parentid>915495575</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-19T00:20:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelinking 3 books for [[WP:V|verifiability]].) #IABot (v2.1alpha3</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Rashad eldridge draws a walk.jpg|right|thumb|275px|Rashad Eldridge of the [[Oklahoma Redhawks]] walks to [[first base]] after drawing a base on balls.]]
A '''base on balls''' ('''BB'''), also known as a '''walk''', occurs in [[baseball]] when a batter receives four pitches that the umpire calls ''[[strike zone|balls]]'', and is in turn awarded first base without the possibility of being called [[Out (baseball)|out]].  The base on balls is defined in Section 2.00 of baseball's Official Rules,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mlb.mlb.com/mlb/official_info/official_rules/definition_terms_2.jsp|title=Official Rules|author=|date=|website=Major League Baseball}}&lt;/ref&gt; and further detail is given in 6.08(a).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mlb.mlb.com/mlb/official_info/official_rules/batter_6.jsp|title=Official Rules|author=|date=|website=Major League Baseball}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It is, however, considered a faux pas for a [[professional baseball|professional]] player to actually walk to first base; the batter-runner and any advancing runners normally jog on such a play.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://espn.go.com/classic/biography/s/rosepete000824.html|title=Hustle made Rose respected, infamous|author=Bob Carter|publisher=[[ESPN]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://articles.philly.com/2013-04-13/sports/38513466_1_pete-rose-reds-base|title=Pete Rose brought hustle, first hit 50 years ago|author=Joe Kay|date=April 13, 2013|work=[[philly.com]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term &quot;base on balls&quot; distinguishes a walk from the other manners in which a batter can be awarded first base without liability to be put out (e.g., [[hit by pitch]] (HBP), [[catcher's interference]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Office of the Comm'r of Baseball|title=2001 Official Rules of Major League Baseball, 6.08(a)|publisher=Triumph Books|isbn=1-57243-397-3|pages=[https://archive.org/details/officialrulesofm00mlbt/page/93 93 (Rule 6.08(a))]|url=https://archive.org/details/officialrulesofm00mlbt/page/93}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though a base on balls, catcher's interference, or a batter hit by a pitched ball all result in the batter (and possibly runners on base) being awarded a base,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Office of the Comm'r of Baseball|title=2001 Official Rules of Major League Baseball|year=2000|publisher=Triumph Books|isbn=1-57243-397-3|pages=[https://archive.org/details/officialrulesofm00mlbt/page/93 93–94 (Rule 6.08(a)-(c)) (describing (a) bases on balls, (b) hit-by-pitched-ball, and (c) interference)]|url=https://archive.org/details/officialrulesofm00mlbt/page/93}}&lt;/ref&gt;  the term &quot;walk&quot; usually refers only to a base on balls, and not the other methods of reaching base without the bat touching the ball.  An important difference is that for a hit batter or catcher's interference, the ball is dead and no one may advance unless forced; the ball is live after a walk (see below for details).

A batter who draws a base on balls is commonly said to have been &quot;walked&quot; by the pitcher. When the batter is walked, runners advance one base without liability to be put out only if forced to vacate their base to allow the batter to take first base. If a batter draws a walk with the [[bases loaded]], all preceding runners are forced to advance, including the runner on third base who is forced to home plate to score a run; when a run is forced on a walk, the batter is credited with an [[Run batted in|RBI]] per rule 10.04.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mlb.mlb.com/mlb/official_info/official_rules/official_scorer_10.jsp|title=Official Rules|author=|date=|website=Major League Baseball}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Receiving a base on balls does not count as a [[hit (baseball)|hit]] or an [[at bat]] for a batter but does count as a [[times on base|time on base]] and a [[plate appearance]]. Therefore, a base on balls does not affect a player's [[batting average (baseball)|batting average]], but it can increase his [[on-base percentage]].&lt;ref&gt;In [[1887 in baseball|1887]], [[Major League Baseball]] counted bases on balls as [[Hit (baseball)|hits]].  The result was skyrocketed batting averages, including some near .500, and the experiment was abandoned the following season. Current record books do not count walks in 1887 as hits.&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[hit by pitch]] is not counted statistically as a walk, though the effect is mostly the same, with the batter receiving a free pass to first base.  One exception is that on a HBP (hit-by-pitch), the ball is dead.  On a HBP, any runners attempting to steal on the play must return to their original base unless forced to the next base anyway.  When a walk occurs, the ball is still live: any runner not forced to advance may nevertheless attempt to advance at his own risk, which might occur on a [[steal (baseball)|steal]] play, [[passed ball]], or [[wild pitch]].  Also, because a ball is live when a base on balls occurs, runners on base forced to advance one base may attempt to advance beyond one base, at their own risk. The batter-runner himself may attempt to advance beyond first base, at his own risk.  Rule 6.08 addresses this matter as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Office of the Comm'r of Baseball|title=2001 Official Rules of Major League Baseball|year=2000|publisher=Triumph Books|isbn=1-57243-397-3|pages=[https://archive.org/details/officialrulesofm00mlbt/page/93 93–94 (Rule 6.08)]|url=https://archive.org/details/officialrulesofm00mlbt/page/93}}&lt;/ref&gt;   An attempt to advance an additional base beyond the base awarded might occur when ball four is a [[passed ball]] or a [[wild pitch]].

==History==
In 1880, the National League changed the rules so that eight balls instead of nine were required for a walk.  In 1884, the National League changed the rules so that six balls were required for a walk.  In 1886, the American Association changed the rules so that six balls instead of seven were required for a walk; however, the National League changed the rules so that seven balls were required for a walk instead of six.  In 1887, the National League and American Association agreed to abide by some uniform rule changes and decreased the number of balls required for a walk to five.  In 1889, the National League and the American Association decreased the number of balls required for a walk to four.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = | editor = | year = 2001 | title = 2001 Official Major League Baseball Fact Book | publisher = The Sporting News | location = St. Louis, Missouri | id = 0-89204-646-5 | pages = 276–280}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2017, Major League Baseball approved a rule change allowing for a batter to be walked intentionally by having the defending bench signal to the Umpire. The move was met with some controversy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2017/02/23/516878572/major-league-baseball-poised-to-change-intentional-walk-rule|title=Major League Baseball Poised To Change Intentional Walk Rule|author=|date=|website=npr.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Intentional base on balls==
{{main|Intentional base on balls}}
A subset of the base on balls, an '''intentional base on balls''' ('''IBB''') or '''intentional walk''' is when the pitcher deliberately pitches the ball away from the batter in order to issue a base on balls. As with any other walk, an intentional walk entitles the batter to first base without liability to be put out, and entitles any runners to advance if forced. Intentional walks are a strategic defensive maneuver, commonly done to bypass one hitter for one the defensive team believes is less likely to initiate a run-scoring play (e.g., a [[home run]], [[sacrifice fly]], or [[Run batted in|RBI]] [[hit (baseball)|base hit]]).  Teams also commonly use intentional walks to set up a [[double play]] or [[force play|force out]] situation for the next batter.

Intentional walks do carry risks, however.  They carry an obvious, inherent risk: they give the offensive team another runner on base, without any effort on their part, who could potentially score a run.  They may carry additional risks.

[[Image:Escobar IBB.jpg|thumb|right|[[Mark Hendrickson]] of the [[Florida Marlins]] intentionally walking the [[Atlanta Braves]]' [[Yunel Escobar]] in 2008. Note the Florida [[catcher]], [[Mike Rabelo]], in a standing position behind the opposite batter's box to receive the pitch]]

An intentional walk is signaled by the catcher standing and extending one arm to the side away from the batter. The pitcher then pitches the ball to that side several feet outside from home plate, usually outside the reach of the batter. A ball pitched in this manner is called an '''intentional ball''' and counts as a ball in the pitcher's [[pitch count]]. In order to count as an intentional ball, the ball must be legally pitched, i.e., the pitcher's foot must be on the [[baseball field#Pitcher's mound|pitcher's rubber]], the catcher must be in the [[baseball field#Batter's box and catcher's box|catcher's box]], and the batter must be in the [[baseball field#Batter's box and catcher's box|batter's box]] appearing ready to take a pitch at the time the ball is thrown. An intentional walk may be signaled at any time during the batter's turn at the plate; in these cases only enough additional intentional balls need to be thrown to bring the total to four. Only walks issued by the catcher signaling as described above are recorded as intentional walks (see below); walks issued without the catcher signaling – even if the pitches ''are'' intentionally thrown outside of the strike zone – are not recorded as intentional.

Another risk taken by the defensive team in issuing a base on balls is that since intentional balls must be pitched in a legal manner, they can legally become [[wild pitch]]es or [[passed ball]]s. Likewise, a baserunner can attempt to [[stolen base|steal]] a base, or the batter can choose to swing at an intentional ball; however, these rarely occur since taking these risks is rarely more beneficial to the offensive team than allowing the walk. In the Major Leagues, the most recent example of a swing at an intentional ball resulting in a hit occurred during a June 22, 2006 game between the [[Florida Marlins]] and the [[Baltimore Orioles]]. In the top of the 10th inning, with a runner on second base, Baltimore pitcher [[Todd Williams]] was signaled to intentionally walk the Marlins' [[Miguel Cabrera]]. Noticing that the intentional ball came in too close to the plate, Cabrera swung at the ball, resulting in a base hit, and a run scored for Florida.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 |title=Marlins' Cabrera spoils intentional walk in win 
 |url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/13493228/ 
 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070419212858/http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/13493228/ 
 |url-status=dead 
 |archive-date=2007-04-19 
 |publisher=espn.com 
 |date=2006-06-22 
 |accessdate=2007-06-02 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Intentional walks also carry other nuanced risks.  They might give the subsequent batter the strategic advantage of anticipating that the pitcher will avoid walking him.  This subsequent batter might then more aggressively anticipate a pitch in the strike zone.  If this batter guesses correctly, he could achieve more success than he otherwise would.  Moreover, a subsequent batter might perceive an immediately preceding intentional walk as a slight to his abilities; if such a batter performs better when he feels underestimated by his opposition, an intentional walk could provide a spark.

Though intentional walks are recorded as such in the records of the [[official scorer]], they are combined with standard, non-intentional walks when calculating a player's on-base percentage, and have only received a separate column in a player's statistics since [[1955 in baseball|1955]].

Batters, on occasion, have been given intentional walks with the bases loaded (effectively giving the offensive team a risk-free run), although this occurs very infrequently.&lt;ref&gt;Holtzman, Jerome (May 2000). [http://arquivo.pt/wayback/20090628141324/http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0FCI/is_5_59/ai_64150752/ Free Pass—Players who were intentionally walked with bases loaded – Brief Article]. ''[[Baseball Digest]]''. Retrieved on 2009-05-13.&lt;/ref&gt; This is generally done in the 9th inning when the pitching team is ahead by more than one run, and the batter is highly skilled. The free run does not matter to either team, as the pitching team remains ahead, and in theory the pitcher feels more comfortable in his ability to get the following batter out instead.

A common nickname for the intentional walk is '''four-finger salute''', since most [[manager (baseball)|managers]] call for an intentional walk by holding up four fingers. As of 2017, the manager may simply request to the plate umpire to let the batter go to first instead of having the pitcher waste four outside pitches.

[[Barry Bonds]] is the all-time record holder with 688 intentional bases on balls.  The next most is [[Hank Aaron]] with 293.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.baseball-reference.com/leaders/IBB_career.shtml|title=Career Leaders &amp;Records for Intentional Bases on Balls - Baseball-Reference.com|author=|date=|website=Baseball-Reference.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Major League Baseball leaders==

===Career===
{{main|List of Major League Baseball career bases on balls leaders}}

===Single-season===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Rank || Player || Year || Base on balls
|-
| 1 || [[Barry Bonds]] || 2004 || 232
|-
| 2 || [[Barry Bonds]] || 2002 || 198
|-
| 3 || [[Barry Bonds]] || 2001 || 177
|-
| 4 || [[Babe Ruth]] || 1923 || 170
|-
| rowspan=3 | 5 || [[Mark McGwire]] || 1998 || 162
|-
| [[Ted Williams]] || 1947 || 162
|-
| [[Ted Williams]] || 1949 || 162
|-
| 8 || [[Ted Williams]] || 1946 || 156
|-
| rowspan=2 | 9 || [[Barry Bonds]] || 1996 || 151
|-
| [[Eddie Yost]] || 1956 || 151
|}

===Game===

[[Jimmie Foxx]], [[Andre Thornton]], [[Jeff Bagwell]] and [[Bryce Harper]] have each been walked six times during a major league regular season game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.baseball-reference.com/tiny/Yp1x2|title=Batting Game Finder: From 1908 to 2018, (requiring BB&gt;=6), sorted by greatest BB|website=Baseball Reference|accessdate=August 21, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among pitchers, [[Tommy Byrne (baseball)|Tommy Byrne]] and [[Bruno Haas]] both gave up 16 bases on balls in a game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.baseball-reference.com/tiny/T22Mw|title=Pitching Game Finder: From 1908 to 2018, (requiring BB&gt;=14), sorted by greatest BB|website=Baseball Reference|accessdate=August 21, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also related lists==
{{portal|Baseball}}
*[[Baseball statistics]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball career bases on balls leaders]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball career total bases leaders]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball career on-base percentage leaders]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball career OPS leaders]]
*[[3000 strikeout club]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball career strikeout leaders]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
*[https://www.baseball-reference.com/leaders/BB_career.shtml Career walks leaders, Baseball-Reference.com]
*[https://www.baseball-reference.com/leaders/BB_season.shtml Single-season walks leaders, Baseball-Reference.com]

{{Baseball}}
{{Baseball statistics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Base On Balls}}
[[Category:Baseball terminology]]
[[Category:Baseball pitching]]
[[Category:Batting (baseball)]]
[[Category:Pitching statistics]]
[[Category:Batting statistics]]</text>
      <sha1>c0sqviokgllgaj4ywyemhalmispdr90</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
