  <page>
    <title>Bruce Perens</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3869</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943157956</id>
      <parentid>943146853</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-29T05:53:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing orphaned refs (&quot;out at hp&quot; from rev 942982740)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=January 2020}}
{{Infobox person
| name          = Bruce Perens
| image         = 3541705843 f896546bec o crop.jpg
| image_size    = 300px
| caption       = Bruce Perens in 2009
| birth_name    =
| birth_date    = {{Birth date and age|1957|10|24}}
| birth_place   =
| death_date    = &lt;!-- {{Death date and age|YYYY|MM|DD|YYYY|MM|DD}} --&gt;
| death_place   =
| body_discovered =
| death_cause   =
| resting_place =
| resting_place_coordinates = &lt;!-- {{coord|LAT|LONG|display=inline,title}} --&gt;
| residence     =
| nationality   =
| ethnicity     =
| citizenship   =
| other_names   =
| known_for     = [[Open Source Initiative]], [[BusyBox]]
| education     =
| alma_mater    =
| employer      =
| occupation    = [[Venture capital]]ist, [[Programmer|Computer Programmer]]
| years_active  =
| home_town     =
| salary        =
| networth      =
| height        =
| weight        =
| title         =
| term          =
| predecessor   =
| successor     =
| party         =
| opponents     =
| boards        =
| religion      =
| spouse        = Valerie&lt;ref name=&quot;spoke out&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;meet the perens&quot; /&gt;
| partner       =
| children      = Stanley (son)&lt;ref name=&quot;spoke out&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;meet the perens&quot; /&gt;
| parents       =
| relations     =
| callsign      = K6BP
| awards        =
| signature     =
| website       = {{URL|https://perens.com}}
}}
[[File:051118-WSIS.2005-Bruce.Perens.ogv|thumb|Perens at the World Summit on the Information Society 2005 in Tunis speaking on &quot;Is Free/Open Source Software the Answer?&quot;]]

'''Bruce Perens''' (born October 24, 1957) is an American [[venture capital]]ist, [[Programmer|computer programmer]] and advocate in the [[free software movement]]. He created [[The Open Source Definition]] and published the first formal announcement and manifesto of [[Open-source model|open source]].&lt;ref name=&quot;LG&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ldp.dvo.ru/LDP/LGNET/issue26/perens.html |title=The Open Source Definition |publisher=ldp.dvo.ru |accessdate=July 27, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/opensources/book/perens.html |title=Open Sources: Voices from the Open Source Revolution |publisher=Oreilly.com |date=March 29, 1999 |accessdate=July 15, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; He co-founded the [[Open Source Initiative]] (OSI) with [[Eric S. Raymond]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://opensource.org/history |title=History of the OSI &amp;#124; Open Source Initiative |publisher=Opensource.org |accessdate=July 15, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today, he is a partner at [[OSS Capital]].

In 2005, Perens represented Open Source at the [[World Summit on the Information Society|United Nations World Summit on the Information Society]], at the invitation of the [[United Nations Development Programme]]. He has appeared before national legislatures and is often quoted in the press, advocating for open source and the reform of national and international technology policy.

Perens is also an [[Amateur radio|amateur radio operator]], with [[call sign]] K6BP. He promotes open radio communications standards&lt;ref&gt;Interview with Leo Laporte on 'The Tech Guy' radio show, October 16, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; and [[open-source hardware]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://arstechnica.com/uncategorized/2007/02/8911/ TAPR introduces open-source hardware license, OSI skeptical] on [[Ars Technica]] by Ryan Paul ''&quot;Bruce Perens and the Tucson Amateur Packet Radio Organization have submitted an Open hardware license&quot;'' (February 23, 2007)&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2016 Perens, along with Boalt Hall (Berkeley Law) professor Lothar Determann, co-authored &quot;Open Cars&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Determann |first1=Lothar |last2=Perens |first2=Bruce |title=Open Cars |journal=Berkeley Technology Law Journal |date=September 11, 2016 |volume= 32| issue =  2, 2017 |page=50 Pages |url=https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2837598 |accessdate=July 3, 2018 |publisher=Social Science Research Network }}&lt;/ref&gt; which appeared in the Berkeley Technology Law Journal.

In 2018 Perens founded the Open Research Institute (ORI), a non-profit research and development organization to address technologies involving Open Source, Open Hardware, Open Standards, Open Content, and Open Access to Research. ORI facilitate worldwide collaboration in the development of technology that would otherwise be restricted under national laws like ITAR and EAR.

==Companies==
Perens is a partner at [[OSS Capital]], and continues to operate two companies: Algoram is a start-up which is creating a software-defined radio transceiver. Legal Engineering is a legal-technical consultancy which specializes in resolving copyright infringement in relation to open source software.

==Early life==
Perens grew up in [[Long Island]], New York. He was born with [[cerebral palsy]], which caused him to have slurred speech as a child, a condition that led to a misdiagnosis of him as [[Developmental disability|developmentally disabled]] in school and led the school to fail to teach him to read.&lt;ref name=&quot;spoke out&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=The man who spoke out once too often |url= http://www.computing.co.uk/ctg/feature/1860167/the-spoke |publisher=Computing |date=October 2, 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; He developed an interest in technology at an early age: besides his interest in amateur radio, he ran a [[pirate radio]] station in the town of [[Lido Beach, New York|Lido Beach]] and briefly engaged in phone [[phreaking]].&lt;ref name=&quot;out at hp&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=TECHNOLOGY; Champion of Open-Source Is Out at Hewlett-Packard |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/09/business/technology-champion-of-open-source-is-out-at-hewlett-packard.html |first=Steve |last=Lohr |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |date=September 9, 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Career==

===Computer graphics===
Perens worked for seven years at the [[New York Institute of Technology Computer Graphics Lab]]. After that, he worked at [[Pixar]] for 12 years, from 1987 to 1999. He is credited as a studio tools engineer on the Pixar films ''[[A Bug's Life]]'' (1998) and ''[[Toy Story 2]]'' (1999).&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0673302/ Bruce Perens] on IMDb.&lt;/ref&gt;

===No-Code International===
Perens founded No-Code International in 1998 with the goal of ending the Morse Code test then required for an [[amateur radio]] license. His rationale was that amateur radio should be a tool for young people to learn advanced technology and networking, rather than something that preserved antiquity and required new hams to master outmoded technology before they were allowed on the air.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Lindquist|first=Rick|date=August 1999|title=Morse debate makes page 1|journal=QST|publisher=ARRL|pages=68}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Perens lobbied intensively on the Internet, at amateur radio events in the United States, and during visits to other nations.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.eham.net/articles/12727|title=No-Code International Waged 'Battle':|website=eham.net|access-date=November 10, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of his visits was to Iceland, where he had half of that nation's radio amateurs in the room, and their vote in the International Amateur Radio Union was equivalent to that of the entire United States.{{citation needed|date=November 2017}}

===BusyBox===
In 1995, Perens created [[BusyBox]], a package of [[Unix]]-style utilities for operating systems including [[Linux]]-based ones and [[FreeBSD]]. He stopped working on it in 1996, after which it was taken over by other developers.

Starting in 2007, several lawsuits were filed for infringement of BusyBox copyright and licensing. These lawsuits were filed by the [[Software Freedom Law Center]] (SFLC), and some of the later managing developers of BusyBox.

In 2009, Bruce Perens released a statement about the lawsuits and [[plaintiff|those filing them]]. In it, he claims that he maintains a significant or even majority ownership of the software in the litigation, but was not contacted nor represented by the plaintiffs; and that some of the plaintiffs had themselves modified BusyBox and its distribution package in such a way as to violate applicable licensing terms and copyright owned by Perens and additional BusyBox developers. Perens supports enforcement of the GPL license used on Busybox. Because he was denied participation in the Busybox cases on the side of the plaintiffs, Perens started a consulting business to assist the defendants in coming into compliance with the GPL and arriving at an amicable settlement with the Software Freedom Law Center.

===Debian Project Leader===
From April 1996 to December 1997, while still working at Pixar, Perens served as [[Debian#Organization|Debian Project Leader]], the person who coordinates development of the [[Debian]] open source operating system. He replaced [[Ian Murdock]], the creator of Debian, who had been the first project leader.

===Software in the Public Interest===
In 1997, Perens was a co-founder of [[Software in the Public Interest]] (SPI), a nonprofit organization intended to serve as an umbrella organization to aid open-source software and hardware projects. It was originally created to allow the [[Debian|Debian Project]] to accept donations.

===Debian Social Contract===
In 1997,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Perens|first1=Bruce|title=About The Creation of the Open Source Definition|url=http://blog.algoram.com/blog/2014/11/24/about-the-creation-of-the-open-source-definition-and-the-debian-social-contract/|website=Algoram|accessdate=August 24, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Perens carbon-copied an email conversation between Donnie Barnes of Red Hat and Ean Schuessler, who was then working on Debian. Schuessler bemoaned that Red Hat had never stated its social contract with the developer community. Perens took this as inspiration to create a formal social contract for Debian. In a blog posting, Perens claims not to have made use of the Three Freedoms (later the Four Freedoms) published by the Free Software Foundation in composing his document. Perens proposed a draft of the Debian Social Contract to the Debian developers on the debian-private mailing list early in June 1997. Debian developers contributed discussion and changes for the rest of the month while Perens edited, and the completed document was then announced as Debian project policy. Part of the Debian Social Contract was the [[Debian Free Software Guidelines]], a set of 10 guidelines for determining whether a set of software can be described as &quot;free software&quot;, and thus whether it could be included in Debian.

===Open Source Definition and The Open Source Initiative===
On February 3, 1998, a group of people (not including Perens) met at VA Linux Systems to discuss the promotion of Free Software to business in pragmatic terms, rather than the moral terms preferred by [[Richard Stallman]]. Christine Petersen of the nanotechnology organization Foresight Institute, who was present because Foresight took an early interest in Free Software, suggested the term &quot;Open Source&quot;. The next day, Eric S. Raymond recruited Perens to work with him on the formation of Open Source. Perens modified the Debian Free Software Guidelines into the Open Source Definition by removing Debian references and replacing them with &quot;Open Source&quot;.

The original announcement of [[The Open Source Definition]] was made on February 9, 1998 on [[Slashdot]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=98/02/09/213900 |title=Free Software's New Name |publisher=Slashdot |date=February 9, 1998 |accessdate=July 15, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and elsewhere; the definition was given in [[Linux Gazette]] on February 10, 1998.&lt;ref name=&quot;LG&quot;/&gt;

Concurrently, Perens and Raymond established the [[Open Source Initiative]], an organization intended to promote open source software.

Perens left OSI in 1999, a year after co-founding it. In February 1999 in an email to the Debian developers mailing list he explained his decision and stated that, though &quot;most hackers know that Free Software and Open Source are just two words for the same thing&quot;, the success of &quot;open source&quot; as a marketing term had &quot;de-emphasized the importance of the freedoms involved in Free Software&quot;; he added, &quot;It's time for us to fix that.&quot; He stated his regret that OSI co-founder Eric Raymond &quot;seems to be losing his free software focus.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://lists.debian.org/debian-devel/1999/debian-devel-199902/msg01641.html|author=Bruce Perens |title=It's Time to Talk About Free Software Again |publisher=Lists.debian.org |date=February 17, 1999|accessdate=July 15, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; But in the following 2000s he spoke about Open source again.&lt;ref name=&quot;meet the perens&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;10yearsoss&quot;/&gt; Perens presently volunteers as the Open Source Initiative's representative to the European Technical Standards Institute (&quot;ETSI&quot;), and is a frequent participant in review of license texts submitted to OSI for certification as Open Source licenses.

===Linux Capital Group===
In 1999, Perens left Pixar and became the president of Linux Capital Group, a business incubator and [[venture capital]] firm focusing on Linux-based businesses. Their major investment was in [[Progeny Linux Systems]], a company headed by Debian founder Ian Murdock. In 2000, as a result of the economic downturn, Perens shut down Linux Capital Group.&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.is/20131104101155/http://www.ageofpeers.com/resources/transcripts/transcript-bruce-perens-about-marketing-open-source-software Transcript of Bruce Perens about Marketing Open Source Software], ''Age of Peers''&lt;/ref&gt; (Progeny Linux Systems would end operations in 2007.)

===Hewlett-Packard===
From December 2000 to September 2002, Perens served as &quot;Senior Global Strategist for Linux and Open Source&quot; at [[Hewlett-Packard]], internally evangelizing for the use of Linux and other open-source software. He was fired as a result of his anti-[[Microsoft]] statements, which especially became an issue after HP acquired [[Compaq]], a major manufacturer of [[Microsoft Windows]]-based PCs, in 2002.&lt;ref name=&quot;out at hp&quot; /&gt;

===Linux Standard Base===
In 1998, Perens founded, and became the first project leader, of the [[Linux Standard Base]] project, a joint project by several Linux distributions now under the organizational structure of the [[Linux Foundation]] to standardize the Linux software system structure.

===UserLinux===
In 2003 Perens created [[UserLinux]], a Debian-based distribution whose stated goal was, &quot;Provide businesses with freely available, high quality Linux operating systems accompanied by certifications, service, and support options designed to encourage productivity and security while reducing overall costs.&quot; UserLinux was eventually overtaken in popularity by [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]], another Debian-based distribution, which was started in 2004, and UserLinux became unmaintained in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://lwn.net/Articles/150701/ |title=Whither UserLinux? |publisher=lwn.net |date=September 7, 2005 |accessdate=July 27, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===SourceLabs===
Perens was an employee of SourceLabs, a [[Seattle]]-based open source software and services company, from June 2005 until December 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://technocrat.net/d/2007/12/3/31038 |title=On My Own Again |publisher=Technocrat.net |accessdate=July 15, 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090224044617/http://technocrat.net/d/2007/12/3/31038/ |archivedate=February 24, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; He produced a video commercial, ''Impending Security Breach'', for SourceLabs in 2007. (SourceLabs was acquired by EMC in 2009.)

===University faculty===
Between 1981 and 1986, Perens was on the staff of the [[New York Institute of Technology Computer Graphics Lab]] as a Unix kernel programmer.

In 2002, Perens was a remote Senior Scientist for Open Source with the Cyber Security Policy Laboratory of [[George Washington University]] under the direction of Tony Stanco. Stanco was director of the laboratory for a year, while its regular director was on sabbatical.

Between 2006 and 2007, Perens was a visiting lecturer and researcher for the [[University of Agder]] under a three-year grant from the Competence Fund of Southern Norway. During this time he consulted the Norwegian Government and other entities on government policy issues related to computers and software.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=3/6: BRUCE PERENS: INNOVATION GOES PUBLIC|url=http://cyberlaw.stanford.edu/events/36-bruce-perens-innovation-goes-public|publisher=Stanford Law School}}&lt;/ref&gt; After this time Perens worked remotely on Agder programs, mainly concerning the [[European Internet Accessibility Observatory]].

===Other activities===
In 2007, some of Perens's government advisory roles included a meeting with the President of the [[Chamber of Deputies]] (the lower house of parliament) in Italy and testimony to the Culture Committee of the Chamber of Deputies;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://technocrat.net/d/2007/8/17/25151 |title=Visit to Rome |publisher=Technocrat.net |accessdate=July 15, 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090223025543/http://technocrat.net/d/2007/8/17/25151/ |archivedate=February 23, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; a keynote speech at the foundation of Norway's Open Source Center, following Norway's Minister of Governmental Reform (Perens is on the advisory board of the center);&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://technocrat.net/d/2007/8/17/25148 |title=Norway opens Free Software Center |publisher=Technocrat.net |accessdate=July 15, 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080719170110/http://technocrat.net/d/2007/8/17/25148 |archivedate=July 19, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; he provided input on the revision of the [[European Interoperability Framework]];&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://perens.com/works/articles/EIF2/ |title=Bruce Perens – The Confusion of Tongues: EIF 2.0, Standards, and Interoperability |publisher=Perens.com |date=September 13, 2007 |accessdate=July 15, 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090204002109/http://perens.com/works/articles/EIF2/ |archivedate=February 4, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and he was keynote speaker at a European Commission conference on ''Digital Business Ecosystems at the Centre Borschette, Brussels, on November 7''.

In 2009, Perens acted as an [[expert witness]] on open source in the [[Jacobsen v. Katzer]] U.S. Federal lawsuit. His report, which was made publicly available by Jacobsen, presented the culture and impact of [[open-source software development]] to the federal courts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://perens.com/works/testimony/PerensJMRI.pdf |title=Expert Report of Bruce Perens |publisher=Northern California District Court |date=October 20, 2009 |accessdate=March 12, 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100331083827/http://perens.com/works/testimony/PerensJMRI.pdf |archivedate=March 31, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Perens delivered one of the keynote addresses at the 2012 [[linux.conf.au]] conference in [[Ballarat]], Australia. He discussed the need for open source software to market itself better to non-technical users.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.techrepublic.com/blog/opensource/dont-miss-developments-from-linuxconfau-2012/3361 |title=Don't miss developments from Linux.conf.au 2012 |author=Selena Frye |date=January 20, 2012 |work=blog |publisher=Tech Republic |accessdate=July 30, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also discussed some of the latest developments in open-source hardware, such as Papilio and Bus Pirate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gadgetfactory.net/2012/01/bruce-perens-mentions-papilio-and-bus-pirate-in-linux-keynote-speech/ |title=Bruce Perens Mentions Papilio and Bus Pirate in Linux Keynote Speech |author=hoppasaurus |date=January 25, 2012 |work=blog |publisher=Tech Factory |accessdate=July 30, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2013, Perens spoke in South America, as the closing keynote at Latinoware 2013. He was the keynote of CISL – Conferencia Internacional de Software Libre, in Buenos Aires, Argentina, and keynoted a special event along with the Minister of software and innovation of Chubut Province, in Puerto Madrin, Patagonia, Argentina. He keynoted the Festival de Software Libre 2013, in Puerto Vallarta, Mexico.

In 2014–2015, Perens took a break from Open Source conferences, having spoken at them often since 1996. In 2016, he returned to the conference circuit, keynoting the Open Source Insight conference in Seoul, sponsored by the Copyright Commission of South Korea. Perens web site presently advertises his availability to keynote conferences as long as travel and lodging expenses are compensated.

==Views==
Perens poses &quot;Open Source&quot; as a means of marketing the [[free and open-source software]] idea to business people and mainstream who might be more interested in the practical benefits of an open source development model and ecosystem than abstract ethics. He states that open source and free software are only two ways of talking about the same phenomenon, a point of view not shared by Stallman and his [[free software]] movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://technocrat.net/d/2007/8/17/25169 |title=Review: Perens Speaks about Free Software in Copenhagen |publisher=Technocrat.net |date=August 17, 2007 |accessdate=July 15, 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090223025659/http://technocrat.net/d/2007/8/17/25169/ |archivedate=February 23, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://technocrat.net/d/2007/8/17/25149 |title=Review: Perens Speaks about Free Software in Copenhagen |publisher=Technocrat.net |date=August 17, 2007 |accessdate=July 15, 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090223025914/http://technocrat.net/d/2007/8/17/25149/ |archivedate=February 23, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Perens postulated in 2004 an economic theory for business use of Open Source in his paper ''The Emerging Economic Paradigm of Open Source'' and his speech ''Innovation Goes Public''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://mondrian.die.udec.cl/~mmedina/Desvarios/Files/Perens%20-%20The%20Emerging%20Economics%20of%20Open%20Source%20Software.pdf |title=The Emerging Economics of Open Source Software |publisher=Perens.com |date=September 30, 2004 |accessdate=November 24, 2014 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141202093236/http://mondrian.die.udec.cl/~mmedina/Desvarios/Files/Perens%20-%20The%20Emerging%20Economics%20of%20Open%20Source%20Software.pdf |archive-date=December 2, 2014 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; This differs from Raymond's theory in ''[[The Cathedral and the Bazaar]]'', which having been written before there was much business involvement in open source, explains open source as a consequence of programmer motivation and leisure.

In February 2008, for the 10th anniversary of the phrase &quot;open source&quot;, Perens published a message to the community called &quot;State of Open Source Message: A New Decade For Open Source&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;10yearsoss&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://perens.com/works/articles/State8Feb2008.html |title=Bruce Perens – State of Open Source Message: A New Decade For Open Source |publisher=Perens.com |date=February 9, 1998 |accessdate=July 15, 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131104135143/http://perens.com/works/articles/State8Feb2008.html |archivedate=November 4, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Around the same time the ezine RegDeveloper published an interview with Perens where he spoke of the successes of open source, but also warned of dangers, including a proliferation of OSI-approved licenses which had not undergone legal scrutiny. He advocated the use of the [[GNU General Public License#Version 3|GPLv3]] license, especially noting [[Linus Torvalds]]' refusal to switch away from [[GNU General Public License#Version 2|GPLv2]] for the Linux kernel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = https://www.theregister.co.uk/2008/02/11/open_source_at_ten/ | title = Perens: 'Badgeware' threat to open source's next decade | first = Gavin | last = Clarke | date = February 11, 2008 | department = Software | work = The Register | accessdate = July 15, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bruce Perens supported [[Bernie Sanders]] for President&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://perens.com/blog/2016/02/24/im-endorsing-bernie-sanders-because-of-what-ive-learned-from-open-source/ |title=I’m Endorsing Bernie Sanders, Because of What I’ve Learned From Open Source|first=Bruce|last=Perens|accessdate=March 20, 2016 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160329050902/https://perens.com/blog/2016/02/24/im-endorsing-bernie-sanders-because-of-what-ive-learned-from-open-source/ |archivedate=March 29, 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and he claims that his experience with the open source movement influenced that decision. On July 13, 2016, following Sanders's endorsement of [[Hillary Clinton]] for president,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://perens.com/blog/2016/07/14/im-endorsing-hillary/ |title=I’m Endorsing Hillary|first=Bruce|last=Perens|accessdate=July 14, 2016 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160809003210/http://perens.com/blog/2016/07/14/im-endorsing-hillary/ |archivedate=August 9, 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Perens endorsed Clinton.

==Amateur radio and other activities==
Perens is an avid [[amateur radio]] enthusiast ([[call sign]] K6BP&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wireless2.fcc.gov/UlsApp/UlsSearch/license.jsp?licKey=254811 |title=ULS License – Vanity License – K6BP – PERENS, BRUCE J |publisher=Wireless2.fcc.gov |date=September 26, 2006 |accessdate=July 15, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;) and maintained technocrat.net, which he closed in late 2008, because its revenues did not cover its costs.

==Media appearances==
Perens is featured in the 2001 documentary film ''[[Revolution OS]]'' and the 2006 [[BBC]] television documentary ''[[The Code-Breakers]]''.

From 2002 to 2006, Prentice Hall PTR published the [[Bruce Perens' Open Source Series]], a set of 24 books covering various open source software tools, for which Perens served as the series editor. It was the first book series to be published under an open license.&lt;ref name=&quot;meet the perens&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Meet the Perens |url=http://akashsingh.ulitzer.com/node/32606 |first=Joe |last=Barr |publisher=LinuxWorld Magazine |date=January 13, 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
Perens lives in [[Berkeley, California]] with his wife, Valerie, and son, Stanley, born in 2000.&lt;ref name=&quot;spoke out&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;meet the perens&quot; /&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Free and open-source software}}
{{Commons category}}
{{Wikiquote}}
* {{Official website|perens.com}}
* [https://lwn.net/1998/0528/a/lsb.html Project Proposal and Call for Participation: The Linux Standard Base]
* [http://lists.debian.org/debian-devel/1999/02/msg01641.html &quot;It's Time to Talk About Free Software Again&quot;, 1999]
* [http://www.linux-magazin.de/news/video_bruce_perens_ueber_open_source_lizenzen Video with Bruce Perens at Hannover Industry Trade Fair, Germany, May 2008]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070829053313/http://www.spiderlessweb.com/?p=11 A talk about open source recorded in Rome in June 2007]

{{S-start}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Ian Murdock]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Debian Project Leader]]|years=April 1996 – December 1997}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Ian Jackson]]}}
{{S-end}}

{{Linux}}
{{Debian}}
{{Linux people}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Perens, Bruce}}
[[Category:Debian Project leaders]]
[[Category:Amateur radio people]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People with cerebral palsy]]&lt;!--Delete? as he says on talk page &quot;they force me to consider that my own CP diagnosis may have been incorrect.&quot;--&gt;
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Members of the Open Source Initiative board of directors]]
[[Category:People from Lido Beach, New York]]
[[Category:New York Institute of Technology faculty]]
[[Category:Open source advocates]]
[[Category:1950s births]]</text>
      <sha1>0ln2wpeofp7qk708n1f7kxz11vhqs2u</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
