  <page>
    <title>Blazing Saddles</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3837</id>
    <revision>
      <id>936998174</id>
      <parentid>936988599</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-22T09:01:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dimadick</username>
        <id>24198</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Plot */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|1974 film by Mel Brooks}}
{{Use American English|date=January 2020}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2018}}
{{Infobox film
&lt;!--| name           = Blazing Saddles--&gt;
| image          = blazing_saddles_movie_poster.jpg
| alt            =
| caption        = Theatrical release poster by [[John Alvin]]&lt;ref name=&quot;lat&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Jocelyn|last=Stewart|title=John Alvin, 59; created movie posters for such films as 'Blazing Saddles' and 'E.T.'|url=http://www.latimes.com/news/printedition/california/la-me-alvin10feb10,1,5113268.story |newspaper=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=February 10, 2008 |accessdate=February 10, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| director       = [[Mel Brooks]]
| producer       = [[Michael Hertzberg]]
| screenplay     = {{Plainlist|
* [[Andrew Bergman]]
* Mel Brooks
* [[Richard Pryor]]
* Norman Steinberg
* Al Uger
}}
| story = Andrew Bergman
| starring = {{Plainlist|
* [[Cleavon Little]]
* [[Gene Wilder]]
* [[Slim Pickens]]
* [[David Huddleston]]
* [[Jack Starrett|Claude Ennis Starrett Jr.]]
* Mel Brooks
* [[Harvey Korman]]
* [[Madeline Kahn]]
}}
| music          = [[John Morris (composer)|John Morris]]
| cinematography = [[Joseph Biroc]]
| editing        = {{Plainlist|
* [[Danford B. Greene|Danford Greene]]
* [[John C. Howard]]
}}
| distributor    = [[Warner Bros.]]
| released       = {{Film date|1974|2|7}}
| runtime        = 93 minutes&lt;!--Theatrical runtime: 92:37--&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.bbfc.co.uk/releases/blazing-saddles-1970-2 | title=''Blazing Saddles'' (AA) | work=[[British Board of Film Classification]] | date=May 3, 1974 | accessdate=August 31, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| country        = United States
| budget         = $2.6 million
| gross          = $119.6 million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=blazingsaddles.htm|title= Blazing Saddles (1974) |accessdate=January 17, 2012|website=[[Box Office Mojo]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
'''''Blazing Saddles''''' is a 1974 American [[Satire|satirical]] [[black comedy]]-[[Western (genre)|western film]] directed by [[Mel Brooks]]. Starring [[Cleavon Little]] and [[Gene Wilder]], the film was written by Brooks, [[Andrew Bergman]], [[Richard Pryor]], Norman Steinberg and [[Alan Uger]], and was based on Bergman's story and draft.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.getback.com/movie/blazing-saddles/1499232 |title=Director and Leading Actors |publisher=Getback.com |archive-date=October 4, 2008 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081004054717/http://www.getback.com/movie/blazing-saddles/1499232 |accessdate=November 1, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film received generally positive reviews from critics and audiences, was nominated for three [[Academy Awards]] and is ranked No. 6 on the [[American Film Institute]]'s ''[[AFI's 100 Years...100 Laughs|100 Years...100 Laughs]]'' list.

Brooks appears in three supporting roles, Governor William J. Le Petomane, a [[Yiddish]]-speaking Native American chief and &quot;a director&quot; in line to help invade Rock Ridge (a nod to Hitchcock); he also dubs lines for one of Lili von Shtupp's backing troupe. The supporting cast includes [[Slim Pickens]], [[Alex Karras]] and [[David Huddleston]], as well as Brooks regulars [[Dom DeLuise]], [[Madeline Kahn]] and [[Harvey Korman]]. Bandleader [[Count Basie]] has a cameo as himself.

The film satirizes the [[racism]] obscured by myth-making [[Cinema of the United States|Hollywood]] accounts of the [[American frontier|American West]], with the hero being a [[African Americans|black]] [[Sheriffs in the United States|sheriff]] in an all-white town. The film is full of deliberate [[anachronism]]s, from the [[Count Basie Orchestra]] playing &quot;[[April in Paris (song)|April in Paris]]&quot; in the Wild West, to Slim Pickens referring to the ''[[Wide World of Sports (U.S. TV series)|Wide World of Sports]]'', to the [[German Army (1935–1945)|German army]] of [[World War II]].

In 2006, ''Blazing Saddles'' was deemed &quot;culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant&quot; by the [[Library of Congress]] and was selected for preservation in the [[National Film Registry]].&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;/&gt;

==Plot==
On the [[American frontier]] of 1874, a new railroad will soon be rerouted through Rock Ridge, in order to avoid running through [[quicksand]]. Realizing this will make Rock Ridge worth millions, the conniving attorney general Hedley Lamarr (named after [[Hedy Lamarr]]) wants to force Rock Ridge's residents to abandon their town, and sends a gang of thugs, led by his flunky Taggart, to shoot the sheriff and trash the town. The townspeople demand that Governor William J. Le Petomane (named after [[Le Petomane]]) appoint a new sheriff to protect them. Lamarr persuades the dim-witted Le Petomane to appoint Bart, a black railroad worker, who was about to be executed for assaulting Taggart earlier. A black sheriff, he reasons, will offend the townspeople, create chaos, and leave the town at his mercy.

After an initial hostile reception (where Sheriff Bart has to take himself as a hostage to escape), he relies on his quick wits and the assistance of Jim, an alcoholic gunslinger known as the &quot;Waco Kid,&quot; to overcome the townspeople's hostility. He subdues Mongo, an immensely strong, dim-witted, but philosophical henchman sent to kill him, then he beats German seductress-for-hire Lili von Shtüpp at her own game, with Lili falling in love with him. Upon Mongo's release, he vaguely informs Bart of Lamarr's connection to the railroad, so Bart and Jim visit the railroad work site and discover from Charlie, Bart's best friend, that the railway is planned to go through Rock Ridge. Just as Taggart and his men arrive to kill Bart, Jim outshoots the thugs, forcing Taggart to retreat to Lamarr. Lamarr, furious that his schemes have backfired, hatches a larger plan involving a recruited army of thugs, including common criminals, [[Ku Klux Klan]]smen, Nazis, and [[Methodism|Methodists]].

At a distance of {{convert|3|mi|abbr=on}} east of Rock Ridge, Bart introduces the white townspeople to the black, Chinese, and Irish railroad workers, who have agreed to help in exchange for acceptance by the community, and explains his plan to defeat Lamarr's army. They labor all night to build a perfect replica of their town, as a diversion; with no people in it, though, Bart realizes it will not fool the villains. While the townspeople construct replicas of themselves, Bart, Jim, and Mongo buy time by constructing the &quot;[[New York State Thruway|Gov. William J. Le Petomane Thruway]]&quot;, forcing the raiding party to turn back for &quot;a shitload of dimes&quot; to pay the toll. Once through the tollbooth, the raiders attack the fake town populated with dummies, which are booby-trapped with dynamite bombs. After Jim detonates the bombs with his sharpshooting, launching bad guys and horses skyward, the Rock Ridgers storm the villains.

The resulting brawl between townsfolk, railroad workers, and Lamarr's thugs literally breaks the [[fourth wall]] as the fight spills onto a neighboring set, where director Buddy Bizarre is directing a [[Busby Berkeley]]-style top-hat-and-tails musical number; then into the studio commissary for a food fight; and then out of the [[Warner Bros. Studios, Burbank|Warner Bros. film lot]] into the streets of Burbank. Lamarr, realizing he has been beaten, hails a taxi and orders the driver to &quot;drive me off this picture&quot;. He ducks into [[Grauman's Chinese Theatre]], which is playing the premiere of ''Blazing Saddles''. As he settles into his seat, he sees Bart arriving on horseback outside the theatre. Bart blocks Lamarr's escape, and then shoots him in the groin. Bart and Jim then go into Grauman's to watch the end of the film, in which Bart announces to the townspeople that he is moving on because his work in Rock Ridge is done (and he's bored). Riding out of town, he finds Jim, still eating his popcorn, and invites him along to &quot;nowhere special&quot;. The two friends ride off into the sunset—in a chauffeured [[limousine]].

==Cast==
{{cast listing|1=
* [[Cleavon Little]] as Sheriff Bart
* [[Gene Wilder]] as Jim, the &quot;Waco Kid&quot;
* [[Harvey Korman]] as Hedley Lamarr
* [[Madeline Kahn]] as Lili von Shtüpp, the &quot;Teutonic Titwillow&quot;
* [[Slim Pickens]] as Taggart
* [[Dom DeLuise]] as Buddy Bizarre
* [[Mel Brooks]] as Gov. William J. Le Petomane / Indian Chief
* [[Liam Dunn]] as Reverend Johnson
* [[George Furth]] as Van Johnson
* [[Burton Gilliam]] as Lyle
* [[John Hillerman]] as Howard Johnson
* [[David Huddleston]] as Olson Johnson
* Richard Collier as Dr. Samuel Johnson
* [[Alex Karras]] as Mongo
* [[Jack Starrett]] as Gabby Johnson
* [[Robyn Hilton]] as Miss Stein, the governor's secretary
* [[Rodney Allen Rippy]] as Young Bart
* [[Charles McGregor]] as Charlie
* [[Robert Ridgely]] as Boris, the hangman
* [[Carol Arthur]] as Harriet Johnson
* [[Anne Bancroft]] as extra in church congregation
* [[Ralph Manza]] as man in commissary playing [[Adolf Hitler|Hitler]]
}}

[[Count Basie]] and his [[Count Basie Orchestra|orchestra]] make a cameo appearance, playing &quot;[[April in Paris (song)|April in Paris]]&quot; in the middle of the desert as Bart rides toward Rock Ridge to assume the post of sheriff.

Brooks appears in three on-screen roles: Governor Le Petomane, the [[Yiddish]]-speaking Native American chief, and an applicant for Hedley Lamarr's thug army (an aviator wearing sunglasses and a [[flight jacket]]). He also has two off-screen voice roles, as one of Lili's German chorus boys during &quot;I'm Tired&quot;, and as a grouchy moviegoer.&lt;ref name=&quot;crick&quot;&gt;Crick, Robert Alan. [https://books.google.com/books?id=LbtuDkazJfQC&amp;q=aviator ''The Big Screen Comedies of Mel Brooks''] McFarland, 2002. {{ISBN|978-0-7864-4326-0}}. pp. 65–66. Quote:&quot;As for Mel Brooks himself, his aviator and voice-overs as a German dancer and cranky film-goer provide funny cameos...&quot;. The book credits him as playing &quot;William J. LePetomane/Indian Chief/Aviator/Voice of German Dancer/Voice of Moviegoer.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Production==
The idea for the film came from a story outline written by [[Andrew Bergman]] that he originally intended to develop and produce himself. &quot;I wrote a first draft called ''Tex-X''&quot; (a play on [[Malcolm X]]'s name), he said. &quot;[[Alan Arkin]] was hired to direct and [[James Earl Jones]] was going to play the sheriff. That fell apart, as things often do.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;bergman&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://creativescreenwriting.com/andrew-bergman/|title='It’s a Good-Natured Insanity.' Andrew Bergman on Screenwriting|last=Swinson|first=Brock|date=June 24, 2016|newspaper=Creative Screenwriting|accessdate=June 24, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Brooks was taken with the story, which he described as &quot;hip talk—1974 talk and expressions—happening in 1874 in the Old West&quot;, and purchased the film rights from Bergman. Though he had not worked with a writing team since ''[[Your Show of Shows]]'', he hired a group of writers (including Bergman) to expand the outline, and posted a large sign: &quot;Please do not write a polite script.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = https://movies.yahoo.com/blogs/movie-news/mel-brooks-on-blazing-new-comedic-trails-in--blazing-saddles-215405381.html | title = Mel Brooks on Blazing New Comedic Trails in 'Blazing Saddles' | first = Andrew | last = Pockross | date = May 9, 2014 | accessdate = May 9, 2014 | publisher = [[Yahoo! Movies]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Brooks described the writing process as chaotic: &quot;''Blazing Saddles'' was more or less written in the middle of a drunken fistfight. There were five of us all yelling loudly for our ideas to be put into the movie. Not only was I the loudest, but luckily I also had the right as director to decide what was in or out.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://creativescreenwriting.com/mel-brooks-on-screenwriting/|title=Mel Brooks on Screenwriting|last=Swinson|first=Brock|date=January 14, 2016|newspaper=Creative Screenwriting|accessdate=January 21, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bergman remembers the room being just as chaotic, telling ''Creative Screenwriting'', &quot;In the beginning, we had five people. One guy left after a couple of weeks. Then, it was basically me, Mel, [[Richard Pryor|Richie Pryor]] and Norman Steinberg. Richie left after the first draft and then Norman, Mel and I wrote the next three or four drafts. It was a riot. It was a rioter’s room!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;bergman&quot; /&gt;

The original title, ''Tex X'', was rejected, as were ''Black Bart'' and ''Purple Sage''. Brooks said he finally conceived ''Blazing Saddles'' one morning while taking a shower.&lt;ref name=&quot;salon&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archive.salon.com/ent/movies/dvd/review/2001/05/08/blazing/|title=Salon: in-depth news, politics, business, technology &amp; culture|website=Salon|accessdate=November 9, 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090114084925/http://archive.salon.com/ent/movies/dvd/review/2001/05/08/blazing/|archive-date=January 14, 2009|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; For the movie's title song, Brooks advertised in the trade papers for a &quot;[[Frankie Laine]]–type&quot; singer; to his surprise, Laine himself offered his services. &quot;Frankie sang his heart out ... and we didn't have the heart to tell him it was a spoof. He never heard the whip cracks; we put those in later. We got so lucky with his serious interpretation of the song.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;libretto&quot;&gt;From the libretto of the La-LaLand Records soundtrack album&lt;/ref&gt;

Casting was problematic. Richard Pryor was Brooks' original choice to play Sheriff Bart, but the studio, claiming his history of drug arrests made him uninsurable, refused to approve financing with Pryor as the star.&lt;ref name=&quot;salon&quot;/&gt; Cleavon Little was cast in the role, and Pryor remained as a writer. Brooks offered the other leading role, the Waco Kid, to [[John Wayne]]; he declined, deeming the film &quot;too [[pornographic movie|blue]]&quot; for his family-oriented image, but assured Brooks that &quot;he would be the first one in line to see it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Staff (May 20, 2016) [http://www.metro.us/philadelphia/mel-brooks-on-john-wayne-improv-and-the-presidential-race/zsJpes---t1y4luA8q4ho/ &quot;Mel Brooks on John Wayne, Improv and the Presidential Race&quot;] ''Metro Philadelphia''&lt;/ref&gt; [[Gig Young]] was cast, but he collapsed during his first scene from what was later determined to be [[alcohol withdrawal syndrome]], and Gene Wilder was flown in to replace him.&lt;ref name=&quot;donnelly&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Donnelly|first=Paul |title=Fade To Black: A Book of Movie Obituaries|publisher=Omnibus|year=2005|edition=3|page=746|isbn=978-1-84449-430-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Parish|first= James Robert |title=It's Good to Be the King: The Seriously Funny Life of Mel Brooks|publisher=John Wiley and Sons|year=2008|page=9|isbn=978-0-470-22526-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Johnny Carson]] and Wilder both turned down the Hedley Lamarr role before Harvey Korman was cast.&lt;ref&gt;[[Timothy White (editor)|White, Timothy]] (March 22, 1979) &quot;Johnny Carson: The ''Rolling Stone'' Interview&quot; in [[Jann Wenner|Wenner, Jann S.]] ed. (2007) [https://books.google.com/books?id=t2CaFeDa_m0C&amp;pg=PT109&amp;q=Johnny%20Carson:%20The%20Rolling%20Stone%20Interview ''The Rolling Stone Interviews''] New York: Little, Brown. {{ISBN|978-0-316-02313-9}}. Retrieved May 24, 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; Madeline Kahn objected when Brooks asked to see her legs during her audition. &quot;She said, 'So it’s THAT kind of an audition?{{'&quot;}} Brooks recalled. &quot;I explained that I was a happily married man and that I needed someone who could straddle a chair with her legs like [[Marlene Dietrich]] in ''[[Destry Rides Again]].'' So she lifted her skirt and said, 'No touching.{{'&quot;}}&lt;ref name=&quot;nypost&quot;/&gt;

Brooks had numerous conflicts over content with Warner Bros. executives, including frequent use of the word &quot;[[nigger]]&quot;, Lili Von Shtupp's seduction scene, the cacophony of flatulence around the campfire, and Mongo punching out a horse. Brooks, whose contract gave him final content control, declined to make any substantive changes, with the exception of cutting Bart's final line during Lili's seduction: &quot;I hate to disappoint you, ma'am, but you're sucking my arm.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Madison2015&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Madison, William V.|title=Madeline Kahn: Being the Music, A Life|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CvAaBwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT119|date=May 1, 2015|publisher=University Press of Mississippi|isbn=978-1-61703-762-7|pages=119-}}&lt;/ref&gt; When asked later about the many &quot;nigger&quot; references, Brooks said he received consistent support from Pryor and Little. He added, &quot;If they did a remake of ''Blazing Saddles'' today [2012], they would leave out the N-word. And then, you've got no movie.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;DGA-Quarterly-summer2012&quot;&gt;
{{cite journal
| last = Weide
| first= Robert
| date = Summer 2012
| title = Quiet on the Set! Mel Brooks: the DGA Interview
|url=http://www.dga.org/Craft/DGAQ/All-Articles/1203-Summer-2012/DGA-Interview-Mel-Brooks.aspx
| journal = DGA Quarterly
| location = Los Angeles, California
| pages = 30–37
| publisher = Directors Guild of America, Inc.
| oclc=68905662
}} Page 36: '''Q:''' ''Blazing Saddles'' also makes frequent use of the &quot;N-word.&quot; Could you get away with that today? '''A:''' Never. If they did a remake of ''Blazing Saddles'' today, they would leave out the N-word. And then, you've got no movie. And I wouldn't have used it so much if I didn't have Richard Pryor with me on the set as one of my writers. And Cleavon Little [as Sheriff Bart] was great. Even though it was allowed, I kept asking Cleavon, &quot;Is that all right there? Is that too much there? Am I pushing this?&quot; and he'd say, &quot;no, no, no, it's perfect there.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Brooks said he received many letters of complaint after the film's release, &quot; ... but of course, most of them were from white people.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;DVD&quot;/&gt;

The film was almost not released. &quot;When we screened it for executives, there were few laughs&quot;, said Brooks. &quot;The head of distribution said, 'Let’s dump it and take a loss.' But [studio president John] Calley insisted they open it in New York, Los Angeles and Chicago as a test. It became the studio's top moneymaker that summer.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;nypost&quot;&gt;Lumenick, L. (May 3, 2014). Mel Brooks: 10 things you never knew about ''Blazing Saddles''. [https://nypost.com/2014/05/03/mel-brooks-10-things-you-never-knew-about-blazing-saddles/ nypost.com]. Retrieved May 24, 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; The world premiere took place on February 7, 1974, at the Pickwick Drive-In Theater in Burbank; 250 invited guests—including Little and Wilder—watched the film on horseback.&lt;ref&gt;Lozano, C (October 8, 1989). Death of a Drive-In : Pickwick Theater Shuts Down, Ending an Era for Burbank Moviegoers and Film Makers. [http://articles.latimes.com/1989-10-08/local/me-287_1_pickwick-theater LATimes.com]. Retrieved May 31, 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; The film's subtitle on the poster, ''&quot;or never give a saga an even break!'' refers to [[W.C. Fields]]' film (and motto) ''&quot;[[Never Give a Sucker an Even Break]]&quot;''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Film Parody Harries&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Harries |first1=Dan |title=Film Parody |date=2000 |publisher=British Film Institute |location=London |isbn=978-0-85170-802-7 |page=115}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reception==
While the film is now considered a classic comedy, critical reaction was mixed when the film was released. [[Vincent Canby]] wrote:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1974/02/08/archives/screen-blazing-saddles-a-western-in-burlesque.html |title=Screen: 'Blazing Saddles', a Western in Burlesque |first=Vincent |last=Canby |work=The New York Times |date=February 8, 1974}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quote|''Blazing Saddles'' has no dominant personality, and it looks as if it includes every gag thought up in every story conference. Whether good, bad or mild, nothing was thrown out. [[Woody Allen]]'s comedy, though very much a product of our Age of Analysis, recalls the wonder and discipline of people like [[Buster Keaton|Keaton]] and [[Laurel and Hardy]]. Mr. Brooks's sights are lower. His brashness is rare, but his use of anachronism and anarchy recalls not the great film comedies of the past, but the middling ones like the Hope-Crosby [[Road to ...|&quot;Road&quot; pictures]]. With his talent he should do much better than that.}}

[[Roger Ebert]] gave the film four stars and called it a &quot;crazed grabbag of a movie that does everything to keep us laughing except hit us over the head with a [[rubber chicken]]. Mostly, it succeeds. It's an audience picture; it doesn't have a lot of classy polish and its structure is a total mess. But of course! What does that matter while Alex Karras is knocking a horse cold with a right cross to the jaw?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Roger |last=Ebert |url=http://www.rogerebert.com/reviews/blazing-saddles-1974 |title=Blazing Saddles |work=Chicago Sun-Times |date=February 7, 1974}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Gene Siskel]] awarded three stars out of four and called it &quot;bound to rank with the funniest of the year,&quot; adding, &quot;Whenever the laughs begin to run dry, Brooks and his quartet of gagwriters splash about in a pool of obscenities that score bellylaughs if your ears aren't sensitive and if you're hip to western movie conventions being parodied.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Gene Siskel|Siskel, Gene]] (March 1, 1974). &quot;Shootout at 'Cockeyed Corral'&quot;. ''[[Chicago Tribune]]''. Section 2, p. 1.&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'' wrote, &quot;If comedies are measured solely by the number of yocks they generate from audiences, then 'Blazing Saddles' must be counted a success ... Few viewers will have time between laughs to complain that pic is essentially a raunchy, protracted version of a television comedy skit.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Film Reviews: Blazing Saddles&quot;. ''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]''. February 13, 1974. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Charles Champlin]] of the ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' called the film &quot;irreverent, outrageous, improbable, often as blithely tasteless as a stag night at the Friar's Club and almost continuously funny.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Charles Champlin|Champlin, Charles]] (February 7, 1974). &quot;Was the West Ever Like This?&quot; ''[[Los Angeles Times]]''. Part IV, p. 1.&lt;/ref&gt; Gary Arnold of ''[[The Washington Post]]'' was negative, writing that &quot;Mel Brooks squanders a snappy title on a stockpile of stale jokes. To say that this slapdash Western spoof lacks freshness and spontaneity and originality is putting it mildly. 'Blazing Saddles' is at once a messy and antiquated gag machine.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Arnold. Gary (March 7, 1974). &quot;'Blazing Saddles' On a Dead Horse&quot;. ''[[The Washington Post]]''. B15.&lt;/ref&gt; Jan Dawson of ''[[The Monthly Film Bulletin]]'' wrote, &quot;Perhaps it is pedantic to complain that the whole is not up to the sum of its parts when, for the [[curate's egg]] that it is, ''Blazing Saddles'' contains so many good parts and memorable performances.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Dawson |first=Jan |date=June 1974 |title=Blazing Saddles |journal=[[The Monthly Film Bulletin]] |volume=41 |issue=485 |page=120 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[John Simon (critic)|John Simon]] wrote a negative review of ''Blazing Saddles'', saying, &quot;All kinds of gags—chiefly anachronisms, irrelevancies, reverse ethnic jokes, and out and out vulgarities—are thrown together pell-mell, batted about insanely in all directions, and usually beaten into the ground.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Reverse Angle: A Decade of American Film|url=https://archive.org/details/reverseangledeca0000simo/page/145|url-access=registration|last1=Simon|first1=John |publisher=Crown Publishers Inc. |year=1982 |page=[https://archive.org/details/reverseangledeca0000simo/page/145 145]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The film grossed $119.5 million at the box office, becoming only the tenth film up to that time to pass the $100 million mark.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=blazingsaddles.htm |title=Blazing Saddles (1974) |website=Box Office Mojo |date=January 1, 1982 |accessdate=November 1, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the [[film-critic]]s aggregator [[Rotten Tomatoes]], the film has a 91% approval rating based on 54 reviews, with a [[weighted arithmetic mean|weighted average]] of 8.11/10. The site's Critics Consensus reads: &quot;Daring, provocative, and laugh-out-loud funny, ''Blazing Saddles'' is a gleefully vulgar spoof of Westerns that marks a high point in Mel Brooks' storied career.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/blazing_saddles/|title=Blazing Saddles on Rotten Tomatoes|accessdate=July 9, 2019|website=[[Rotten Tomatoes]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During production for the film, longtime film star [[Hedy Lamarr]] sued Warner Bros., charging that the film's running parody of her name infringed on her right to privacy. Brooks said that he was flattered and chose to not fight it in court; the studio settled out of court for a small sum and an apology for “almost using her name.&quot; Brooks said that Lamarr &quot;never got the joke.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;DVD&quot;&gt;Interview: Mel Brooks. ''Blazing Saddles'' (DVD). Burbank, California: Warner Brothers Pictures/Warner Home Video, 2004. {{ISBN|978-0-7907-5735-3}}.&lt;/ref&gt; This lawsuit would be referenced by an in-film joke where Brooks' character, the Governor, tells Hedley Lamarr that, &quot;This is 1874; you'll be able to sue HER.&quot;

==Accolades==
While addressing his group of bad guys, Harvey Korman's character reminds them that, although they are risking their lives, he is &quot;risking an almost certain [[Academy Awards|Academy Award]] nomination for [[Academy Award for Best Supporting Actor|Best Supporting Actor]]!&quot; Korman did not receive an Oscar bid, but the film did get three nominations in [[47th Academy Awards|1974]]: [[Academy Award for Best Supporting Actress|Best Supporting Actress]] (Madeline Kahn, who lost to [[Ingrid Bergman]] in ''[[Murder on the Orient Express (1974 film)]]''), [[Academy Award for Best Film Editing|Best Film Editing]] (losing out to ''[[The Towering Inferno]]''), and [[Academy Award for Best Original Song|Best Music, Original Song]] (the title song, which lost to &quot;We May Never Love Like This Again&quot;, also from ''The Towering Inferno''). The film also earned two [[British Academy Film Awards|BAFTA]] awards nominations, for [[BAFTA Award for Best Newcomer|Best Newcomer]] (Cleavon Little) and [[BAFTA Award for Best Screenplay|Best Screenplay]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://awards.bafta.org/award/1975/film/most-promising-newcomer-to-leading-film-roles &quot;Film | Most Promising Newcomer To Leading Film Roles in 1975&quot;] BAFTA&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://awards.bafta.org/award/1975/film/screenplay &quot;Film | Screenplay in 1975&quot;] BAFTA&lt;/ref&gt;

The film won the [[Writers Guild of America Award]] for &quot;[[Writers Guild of America Award for Best Original Screenplay|Best Comedy Written Directly for the Screen]]&quot; for writers Mel Brooks, Norman Steinberg, Andrew Bergman, Richard Pryor, and Alan Uger.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0071230/awards|title=Blazing Saddles|accessdate=November 9, 2017|publisher=IMDb}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006, ''Blazing Saddles'' was deemed &quot;culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant&quot; by the [[Library of Congress]] and was selected for preservation in the [[National Film Registry]].&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;/&gt;

The film is recognized by [[American Film Institute]] in these lists:
* 2000: [[AFI's 100 Years...100 Laughs]] - #6&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=AFI's 100 Years...100 Laughs |url=http://www.afi.com/Docs/100Years/laughs100.pdf |publisher=[[American Film Institute]] |accessdate=July 17, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
===TV pilot===
{{unreferenced section|date=August 2016}}
A television series titled ''Black Bart'' was produced for CBS based on Bergman's original story. It featured [[Louis Gossett, Jr.]] as Bart and [[Steve Landesberg]] as his drunkard sidekick, a former Confederate officer named &quot;Reb Jordan&quot;. Other cast members included Millie Slavin and [[Noble Willingham]]. Bergman is listed as the sole creator.

CBS aired the pilot once on April 4, 1975. The pilot episode featured guest appearances by [[Gerrit Graham]] and [[Brooke Adams (actress)|Brooke Adams]] and was written by [[Michael Elias]] and Rich Eustis. Elias and Eustis later created and executive produced the [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] sitcom ''[[Head of the Class]]'' (1986–1991).

Interviewed in 1996, Steve Landesberg said ''Black Bart'' &quot;was like a joke. ... We did the pilot, and CBS dumped it at the end of the 1975 season in April or May on a Friday. We thought it was done, then CBS tells us to come back and film six more episodes. And then another six. Six episodes each season, when an order was usually for 24 or 26. I was on ''[[Barney Miller]]'' by that point, and we'd film during the winter break when all other TV shows were on hiatus. And they never aired any of them. It was like a sick joke. If I wasn't under contract I would have walked, but they were paying me so I can't complain.&quot;

In 1989, Louis Gossett, Jr. told ''Entertainment Tonight'', &quot;CBS and Warner Bros. made a deal. ... The deal was that CBS would get to air ''Blazing Saddles'', and any sequels from the movie, in exchange for co-producing a TV show. At the time Warners wanted to make ''Blazing Saddles'' into a comedy series of films, a new one coming out every year or so. They wanted to use the model that the Brits had for the ''[[Carry On (franchise)|Carry On]]'' films. But [Mel] Brooks had a clause in his contract that said Warner had to keep producing ''Blazing Saddles'' stories, in the movies or TV, or they'd lose the rights to make sequels. The TV show was a way to keep the rights. They didn't have to air it, just keep producing it. So for four years I spent my winter on a soundstage being paid to be in a show that would never see the light of day, just so Warners could keep the sequel rights to ''Blazing Saddles''. By 1979 they finally figured out the market had changed and they weren't going to make any sequels, so we were cancelled, if a show that never was supposed to air can be cancelled.&quot;

Mel Brooks addressed the existence of the ''Black Bart'' series in 2005: &quot;My lawyers, bless their souls, came to me and said, 'Warner Bros. is going to try and take away your control of the movie. Let's put in a crazy condition that says they can't do any sequels unless they make it right away or make a TV show out of it within six months.' Which is brilliant. They couldn't make a sequel in six months, and the movie was too vulgar to be a TV show. Now it would air in family hour if that was still a thing. So the lawyers put that in, never thinking they'd make a TV show. ... In 1977, three years later, Warner Bros comes to me and says they want to make another ''Blazing Saddles'', and I say, 'No. You don't have the right to do that.' They say, 'Yes we do, we've been making a TV series and still control the rights.' What TV series? I haven't seen a TV show. They take me onto the lot, into a projection booth, and show me three episodes. My lawyers never thought to put in language that said they had to air the damn thing, only that they had to make it. [[Oy gevalt]]! Well, management changed and they never did ''Blazing Saddles 2'', and as far as I know they're still making that stupid show to this day.&quot;

The pilot episode of ''Black Bart'' was later included as a bonus feature on the ''Blazing Saddles'' 30th Anniversary DVD and the [[Blu-ray]] disc.&lt;ref&gt;{{IMDb title|0121113|Black Bart}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Soundtrack===
The first studio-licensed release of the full music soundtrack to ''Blazing Saddles'' was on La-La Land Records on August 26, 2008. Remastered from original studio vault elements, the limited edition CD (a run of 3000) features the songs from the film as well as composer [[John Morris (composer)|John Morris]]'s score. Instrumental versions of all the songs are bonus tracks on the disc. The disc features exclusive liner notes featuring comments from Mel Brooks and John Morris.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lalalandrecords.com/BlazingSaddles.html |title=''Blazing Saddles'' press release at La-La Land Records |publisher=Lalalandrecords.com |accessdate=November 1, 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121113172746/http://www.lalalandrecords.com/BlazingSaddles.html |archivedate=November 13, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===In popular culture===
The unreleased animated film ''[[Blazing Samurai]]'', starring [[Michael Cera]], [[Samuel L. Jackson]], [[Michelle Yeoh]], and [[Ricky Gervais]], has been characterized by its creators as &quot;equally inspired by and an homage to ''Blazing Saddles''.&quot; Brooks served as an executive producer for the production, and voiced one of the characters.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nov2015D&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last1=Busch|first1=Anita|title=‘Blazing Samurai’ Lands A-List Voice Talent Led By Samuel L. Jackson|url=http://deadline.com/2015/11/blazing-samurai-animated-feature-samuel-l-jackson-mel-brooks-george-takei-1201605395/|accessdate=September 7, 2016|website=[[Deadline Hollywood]]|date=November 3, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Possible stage production===
In September 2017, Mel Brooks indicated his desire to do a stage play version of ''Blazing Saddles'' in the future.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/2017/09/21/stupidly-politically-correct-society-death-comedy-warns-veteran/ |title='Stupidly politically correct society is the death of comedy', warns veteran comedian Mel Brooks |last=Sabur |first=Rozina |date=September 21, 2017 |website=The Daily Telegraph |publisher=Telegraph Media Group Limited |accessdate=September 22, 2017 |quote=The director said he hopes he is able to recreate Blazing Saddles on the stage in the future.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Home media==
The film was first released on VHS and DVD in 1997.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blu-ray.com/dvd/Blazing-Saddles-DVD/30881/ |title=Blazing Saddles DVD |publisher=Blu-ray.com |date=June 25, 1997 |accessdate=September 7, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006, the film was released on DVD and Blu-ray.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blu-ray.com/movies/Blazing-Saddles-Blu-ray/108/ |title=Blazing Saddles Blu-ray |publisher=Blu-ray.com |accessdate=September 7, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 40th Anniversary Blu-Ray set was released in 2014.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blu-ray.com/movies/Blazing-Saddles-Blu-ray/94370/ |title=Blazing Saddles Blu-ray |publisher=Blu-ray.com |accessdate=September 7, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
* {{IMDb title|0071230}}
* {{tcmdb title|69005|Blazing Saddles}}
* {{amg movie|6029}}
* {{AFI film|id=54998|title=Blazing Saddles}}
* {{mojo title|blazingsaddles}}
* {{Rotten Tomatoes|blazing_saddles}}

{{Mel Brooks}}

[[Category:1974 films]]
[[Category:1970s parody films]]
[[Category:1970s Western (genre) comedy films]]
[[Category:American films]]
[[Category:American parody films]]
[[Category:American Western (genre) comedy films]]
[[Category:English-language films]]
[[Category:Films scored by John Morris]]
[[Category:Films about racism]]
[[Category:Films directed by Mel Brooks]]
[[Category:Films shot in California]]
[[Category:Self-reflexive films]]
[[Category:Films with screenplays by Mel Brooks]]
[[Category:Warner Bros. films]]
[[Category:Weird West]]
[[Category:United States National Film Registry films]]
[[Category:Films set in 1856]]
[[Category:Films set in 1874]]
[[Category:American satirical films]]</text>
      <sha1>qo3woyr8upomwzzmjxymjnuox2lk68m</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
