  <page>
    <title>Herman Boerhaave</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3874</id>
    <revision>
      <id>935888477</id>
      <parentid>918273603</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-15T11:05:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ArbieP</username>
        <id>29738728</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */ added * {{cite EB1911|wstitle=Boerhaave, Hermann |volume=4 |short=x}}</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Dutch botanist, chemist, humanist, and physician}}
{{EngvarB|date=July 2017}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2017}}
{{Infobox scientist
|name              = Herman Boerhaave
|image             = Herman Boerhaave by J Champan.jpg
|image_size       = 230px
|caption           = Herman Boerhaave (1668–1738)
|birth_date        = {{birth date|df=yes|1668|12|31}}
|birth_place       = [[Voorhout]], [[Dutch Republic]]
|death_date        = {{death date and age|df=yes|1738|9|23|1668|12|31}}
|death_place       = [[Leiden]], Dutch Republic
|nationality       = Dutch
|field             = Physician
|work_institutions = [[University of Leiden]]
|alma_mater        = [[University of Leiden]]
|doctoral_advisor  = [[Burchard de Volder]]
|doctoral_students = [[Gerard van Swieten]] 
|known_for         = Founder of clinical teaching
|author_abbrev_bot = Boerh.
}}

'''Herman Boerhaave''' ({{IPA-nl|ˈɦɛrmɑn ˈbuːrˌɦaːvə|lang}}, 31 December 1668 – 23 September 1738)&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;Underwood, E. Ashworth. &quot;Boerhaave After Three Hundred Years.&quot; ''The British Medical Journal'' 4, no. 5634 (1968): 820–25. &lt;nowiki&gt;https://www.jstor.org/stable/20395297&lt;/nowiki&gt;.&lt;/ref&gt; was a Dutch [[Botany|botanist]], [[chemist]], [[Christian humanism|Christian humanist]], and [[physician]] of European fame. He is regarded as the founder of clinical teaching and of the modern academic hospital and is sometimes referred to as &quot;the father of physiology,&quot; along with Venetian physician [[Santorio Santorio]] (1561–1636). Boerhaave introduced the quantitative approach into medicine, along with his pupil [[Albrecht von Haller]] (1708–1777) and is best known for demonstrating the relation of symptoms to lesions. He was the first to isolate the chemical [[urea]] from urine. He was the first physician to put thermometer measurements to clinical practice. His motto was ''Simplex sigillum veri'': 'Simplicity is the sign of the truth'. He is often hailed as the &quot;Dutch [[Hippocrates]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

==Biography==
[[File:Oud Poelgeest Oegstgeest.jpg|left|thumb|200x200px|[[Oud Poelgeest]] Castle, Herman Boerhaave's home in [[Oegstgeest]], near Leiden. This was the site of his outdoor botanical garden that was renowned during his lifetime and rivalled [[Hortus Cliffortianus]], the garden of his friend and sponsor to [[Carl Linnaeus|Linnaeus]]. He traveled back and forth to his friend's garden and to the Leiden University by [[trekschuit]].]]
Boerhaave was born at [[Voorhout]] near [[Leiden]]. The son of a [[Protestant]] pastor,&lt;ref&gt;Robert Siegfried (2002). ''From Elements to Atoms: A History of Chemical Composition, Volume 92, Issues 4–6''. American Philosophical Society. p. 128&lt;/ref&gt; in his youth Boerhaave studied for a [[Divinity (academic discipline)|divinity]] degree and wanted to become a preacher.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mendelsohn, p.287&quot;&gt;Mendelsohn, p. 287&lt;/ref&gt; After the death of his father, however, he was offered a scholarship and he entered the [[University of Leiden]], where he took his degree in philosophy in 1689, with a dissertation ''De distinctione mentis a corpore'' (on the difference of the mind from the body).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Herman Boerhaave |url=http://ilorentz.org/history/proefschriften/sources/Boerhaave_1690.pdf |title=De distinctione mentis a corpore |year=1690}}&lt;/ref&gt; There he attacked the doctrines of [[Epicurus]], [[Thomas Hobbes]] and [[Baruch Spinoza|Spinoza]]. He then turned to the study of medicine, in which he graduated in 1693 at [[University of Harderwijk|Harderwijk]] in present-day [[Gelderland]].

In 1701 he was appointed lecturer on the institutes of medicine at Leiden; in his inaugural discourse, ''De commendando [[Hippocrates|Hippocratis]] studio'', he recommended to his pupils that great physician as their model. In 1709 he became professor of [[botany]] and medicine, and in that capacity he did good service, not only to his own university, but also to botanical science, by his improvements and additions to the [[Hortus Botanicus Leiden|botanic garden of Leiden]], and by the publication of numerous works descriptive of new species of plants.

On 14 September 1710, Boerhaave married Maria Drolenvaux, the daughter of the rich merchant, Alderman Abraham Drolenvaux. They had four children, of whom one daughter, Maria Joanna, lived to adulthood.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.whonamedit.com/doctor.cfm/2404.html |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2006-02-07 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060207020803/http://www.whonamedit.com/doctor.cfm/2404.html |archivedate=7 February 2006 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1722, he began to suffer from an extreme case of [[gout]], recovering the next year.

In 1714, when he was appointed rector of the university, he succeeded [[Govert Bidloo]] in the chair of practical medicine, and in this capacity he introduced the modern system of clinical instruction. Four years later he was appointed to the chair of chemistry as well. In 1728 he was elected into the [[French Academy of Sciences]], and two years later into the [[Royal Society]] of London. In 1729 declining health obliged him to resign the chairs of chemistry and botany; and he died, after a lingering and painful illness, at Leiden.

==Legacy==
His reputation so increased the fame of the University of Leiden, especially as a school of medicine, that it became popular with visitors from every part of Europe. All the princes of Europe sent him pupils, who found in this skilful professor not only an indefatigable teacher, but an affectionate guardian. When [[Peter I of Russia|Peter the Great]] went to Holland in 1716 (he was in Holland before in 1697 to instruct himself in maritime affairs), he also took lessons from Boerhaave. [[Voltaire]] travelled to see him, as did [[Carl Linnaeus]], who became a close friend. His reputation was not confined to Europe; a Chinese mandarin sent him a letter addressed to &quot;the illustrious Boerhaave, physician in Europe,&quot; and it reached him in due course.
[[File:ErfgoedLeiden LEI001019039 Herman Boerhaave, bronzen standbeeld van J.Stracke (1817-1891).jpeg|thumb|Bronze statue made by J.Stracke (1817–1891)]]
The operating theatre of the University of Leiden in which he once worked as an anatomist is now at the centre of a museum named after him; the [[Boerhaave Museum]]. [[Asteroid]] [[8175 Boerhaave]] is named after Boerhaave. From 1955 to 1961 Boerhaave's image was printed on Dutch 20-[[guilder]] banknotes. The [[Leiden University Medical Centre]] organises medical trainings called ''Boerhaave-courses''.

He had a prodigious influence on the development of medicine and chemistry in Scotland. British medical schools credit Boerhaave for developing the system of medical education upon which their current institutions are based.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Underwood|first=E. Ashworth|date=1 January 1968|title=Boerhaave After Three Hundred Years|jstor=20395297|journal=The British Medical Journal|volume=4|issue=5634|pages=820–25|pmc=1912963}}&lt;/ref&gt; Every founding member of the [[Edinburgh Medical School]] had studied at Leyden and attended Boerhaave's lectures on chemistry including [[John Rutherford (physician)|John Rutherford]] and [[Francis Home]]. Boerhaave's ''Elementa Chemiae (1732)'' is recognised as the first text on chemistry.&lt;ref&gt;Clow, Archibald &amp; Nan L. Clow ''The Chemical Revolution'', Batchworth Press, London, 1952.&lt;/ref&gt;  
 
Boerhaave first described [[Boerhaave syndrome]], which involves tearing of the oesophagus, usually a consequence of vigorous vomiting.  He notoriously described in 1724 the case of Baron Jan van Wassenaer, a Dutch admiral who died of this condition following a gluttonous feast and subsequent regurgitation.&lt;ref&gt;Boerhaave H. Atrocis, nec descripti prius, morbii historia: secundum medicae artis leges conscripta. Leiden, the Netherlands: Lugduni Batavorum Boutesteniana, 1724&lt;/ref&gt;  This condition was uniformly fatal prior to modern surgical techniques allowing repair of the oesophagus.

Boerhaave was critical of his [[Netherlands (terminology)#Dutch|Dutch]] contemporary, [[Baruch Spinoza]], attacking him in his dissertation in 1689. At the same time, he admired [[Isaac Newton]] and was a devout Christian who often wrote about God in his works.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mendelsohn, p.287&quot;/&gt; A collection of his religious thoughts on medicine, translated from Latin to English, has been compiled by the ''Sir Thomas Browne Instituut Leiden'' under the name ''Boerhaave's Orations'' (meaning &quot;Boerhaave's Prayers&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;Boerhaave, Herman (1983). edited by Elze Kegel-Brinkgreve &amp; Antonie Maria Luyendijk-Elshout. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=y-UUAAAAIAAJ&amp;hl=es&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s Boerhaaveìs Orations]''. Volume 4 of Publications of the Sir Thomas Browne Institute Leiden. Brill Archive. {{ISBN|9004070435| 978-9004070431}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among other things, he considered nature as God's Creation&lt;ref&gt;Principe, Lawrence (2007). ''New Narratives in Eighteenth-Century Chemistry: Contributions from the First Francis Bacon Workshop, 21–23 April 2005, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, California''. Springer, pp. 66–67&lt;/ref&gt; and he used to say that the poor were his best patients because God was their paymaster.&lt;ref&gt;H. Biglow, Orville Luther Holley (1817). ''The American Monthly Magazine and Critical Review, Volume 1''. H. Biglow, p. 192&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hosack, David (1824). ''Essays on various subjects of medical science''. New York Symour. p. 113&lt;/ref&gt;

==Medical contributions==

As a credible chemist and physician of European, the human body was a very inquisitive and compelling component in agreed with other physicians of his time – like Borellis – and thus he devoted a diligent focus towards this subject matter.

Boerhaave's ideas about the human body were heavily influenced by French mathematician and philosopher [[René Descartes]]. Descartes contributed much to iatromechanical theories. Another influencer of Boerhaave's reasoning was [[Giovanni Borelli]]. He was a distinguished astronomer and mathematician in the 1600s and published writings on animal motions mirroring machinery principles. Inspired by this and Cartesianism, Boerhaave proposed that the human body's operations are based on a hydraulic model.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Cook|first1=Harold|title=Matters of Exchange|date=2007|publisher=Commerce, Medicine, and Science in the Dutch Golden Age|location=New Haven|pages=393}}&lt;/ref&gt; In his work, he alluded to simple machines, such as levers and pulleys, as well as other mechanisms to explain parts of the body. Boerhaave described the body as made up of pipe-like structures such as are found in a machine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Lindemann|first1=Mary|title=Medicine and Society in Early Modern Europe|date=2013|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location= Cambridge|isbn=978-0521425926|pages=101–05|edition=second}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, pipes in a machine parallel the physiology of veins in the human body. Boerhaave took this mechanistic notion even further by noting the importance of a proper balance of fluid pressure. Fluids within the body should be able to move around freely, without obstacles.  Similar to a machine, a well-being was self-regulating. The body must maintain these conditions to be a healthy equilibrium state. Boerhaave's view on medicine accepted this apparatus-like body philosophy and thus focused attention on materialistic problems rather than mystical explanations of illness.

Boerhaave stressed the atomically research conceived on sense experiences and scientific experiments. Boerhaave attracted many students to Leiden University, where he taught his perception and philosophy. Boerhaave's notion of the systematic body burgeoned throughout Europe and consequently aiding in the transformation of medical educations in European schools.
Boerhaave's intuition struck up a great deal of interest among other critical medical thinkers – one being [[Friedrich Hoffmann]], who emphasised using physico-mechanical principles to preserve and, if needed, restore health.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Broman|first1=Thomas|title=The Medical Sciences|date=2003|publisher=The Cambridge History of Sciences|location=Cambridge|page=469}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a professor at Leiden, Boerhaave influenced many of his students. Some of his followers conducted experiments to bolster Boerhaave's philosophy, while other physicians rejected and proposed alternative notions about the human body. Boerhaave also contributed a great number of textbooks and writings that circulated Europe. The enrichment extracted from his lectures at Leiden. In 1708, his publication of the Institutes of Medicine was issued in over five languages with approximately ten editions. ''Elementa Chemia'', a world-renowned chemistry textbook, was published in 1732.

Viewing the body as a mechanism deviated from the path that [[Galen]] and [[Aristotle]] previously laid down. Instead of solely relying on past finding, Boerhaave understood the importance of seeking fixed results on his own and experiencing the findings first hand. This new thinking augmented Renaissance anatomy and opened doors of novel reasoning leading up to the medical enlightenment germane to [[iatrochemistry]].

==Publications==
[[Image:Boerhaave - Aphorismi de cognoscendis et curandis morbis, 1728 - 3032194.tif|thumb|''Aphorismi de cognoscendis et curandis morbis'', 1728]]
*''Het Nut der Mechanistische Methode in de Geneeskunde'' (Leiden, 1703)
*''Institutiones medicae'' (Leiden, 1708) (Digital edition from 1746 by the [[University and State Library Düsseldorf]])
*''Aphorismi de cognoscendis et curandis morbis'' (Leiden, 1709), on which his pupil and assistant, [[Gerard van Swieten]] (1700–1772) published a commentary in 5 vols.
*''Institutiones et Experimenta chemiae'' (Paris, 1724) (unauthorised). (Digital edition by the [[University and State Library Düsseldorf]])
*''Elementa chemiae'' (Leiden, 1732).[[File:Elementa Chemiae-Boerhaave.jpg|thumb|Elementa Chemiae-Boerhaave]]
{{Clear}}
{{botanist|Boerh.}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|30em}}

==References==
* Mendelsohn, Everett (2003). ''Transformation and Tradition in the Sciences''. Cambridge University Press. {{ISBN|9780521524858}}
* Rina Knoeff (2002), &quot;Herman Boerhaave (1668–1783): Calvinist chemist and physician.&quot; History of Science and Scholarship in the Netherlands, Volume 3. Royal Netherlands Academy of Arts and Sciences.
* Underwood, E. Ashworth. &quot;Boerhaave After Three Hundred Years.&quot; ''The British Medical Journal'' 4, no. 5634 (1968): 820–25. &lt;nowiki&gt;https://www.jstor.org/stable/20395297&lt;/nowiki&gt;.

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |title=Inventing Chemistry: Herman Boerhaave and the Reform of the Chemical Arts |last=Powers |first=John C. |year=2012 |publisher=University of Chicago Press |location=Chicago, London |isbn=978-0-226-67760-6}}

==External links==
{{Commons}}
{{Wikisource}}
* {{cite EB1911|wstitle=Boerhaave, Hermann |volume=4 |short=x}}
*[[Samuel Johnson]]'s 1739 biography of him online: [http://www.samueljohnson.com/boerhaave.html Life of Herman Boerhaave]
*[http://www.museumboerhaave.nl/ Museum Boerhaave] in Leiden, National Museum of the History of Science and Medicine
*[http://content.nejm.org/cgi/content/extract/344/2/138 A recent discussion of Boerhaave's Syndrome] in the New England Journal of Medicine (subscription required)
* {{Gutenberg author |id=Boerhaave,+Herman | name=Herman Boerhaave}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Herman Boerhaave}}
*[https://openlibrary.org/authors/OL863081A Works] at [https://openlibrary.org Open Library]
* {{MathGenealogy|id=101856}}
*[https://archive.org/details/hermanniboerhaa00boergoog &quot;Aphorismi de Cognoscendis et Curandis Morbis&quot; (1709; “Aphorisms on the Recognition and Treatment of Diseases”)]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20120916115830/http://personal.telefonica.terra.es/web/rotochem/Boer.html &quot;Elementa Chemiae&quot; (1733) (''Elements of Chemistry'')]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20080612173212/http://usuarios.lycos.es/rotedu/Shaw.html &quot;A New Method of Chemistry&quot; (1741 &amp; 1753) (''English Translation of ''&quot;Elementa Chemiae&quot;'' by Peter Shaw'')]
*[http://www.javed-chaudhry.com/zindagi-ka-khoya-howa-sira-by-javed-chaudhry/ Javed Chaudhry Article about Herman Boerhaave]

{{Carl Linnaeus|state=collapsed}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Boerhaave, Herman}}
[[Category:17th-century Dutch physicians]]
[[Category:17th-century Dutch writers]]
[[Category:18th-century Dutch physicians]]
[[Category:18th-century Dutch writers]]
[[Category:1668 births]]
[[Category:1738 deaths]]
[[Category:Burials at Pieterskerk, Leiden]]
[[Category:Dutch anatomists]]
[[Category:Dutch botanists]]
[[Category:Dutch chemists]]
[[Category:Dutch Christians]]
[[Category:Dutch entomologists]]
[[Category:Dutch Renaissance humanists]]
[[Category:Fellows of the Royal Society]]
[[Category:Leiden University alumni]]
[[Category:Leiden University faculty]]
[[Category:Members of the French Academy of Sciences]]
[[Category:People from Leiden]]
[[Category:People from Teylingen]]
[[Category:University of Harderwijk alumni]]</text>
      <sha1>jn7fn8bs12r07b81950km772ity7kfu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
