  <page>
    <title>Ethiopian cuisine</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9686</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942739267</id>
      <parentid>941691149</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-26T15:04:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>196.188.176.226</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Oromo dishes */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Culinary traditions of Ethiopia}}
{{disputed|date=September 2018}}
{{over-coverage|date=September 2018}}
{{Contains Ethiopic text}}
[[File:Alicha 1.jpg|thumb|right|250px|This meal consisting of ''[[injera]]'' and several kinds of ''[[Wat (food)|wat]]'' (stew) is typical of [[Ethiopia]]n cuisine.]]
[[File:LocationEthiopia.svg|thumb|Location of [[Ethiopia]]]]

'''Ethiopian cuisine''' ({{lang-am|የኢትዮጵያ ምግብ}}) characteristically consists of vegetable and often very spicy meat dishes. This is usually in the form of ''[[wat (food)|wat]],'' a thick stew, served atop ''[[injera]]'', a large [[sourdough]] [[flatbread]],&lt;ref name=&quot;gonomad&quot;&gt;Javins, Marie. [http://www.gonomad.com/features/0211/ethiopiafood.html &quot;Eating and Drinking in Ethiopia.&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130131180721/http://www.gonomad.com/features/0211/ethiopiafood.html |date=31 January 2013 }} [http://www.gonomad.com Gonomad.com]. Accessed July 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; which is about {{convert|50|cm|in|abbr=off|sp=us}} in diameter and made out of fermented [[teff]] flour.&lt;ref name=&quot;gonomad&quot;/&gt; [[People of Ethiopia|Ethiopians]] eat most of the time with their right hands, using pieces of ''injera'' to pick up bites of entrées and side dishes.&lt;ref name=&quot;gonomad&quot;/&gt;

The [[Fasting and abstinence in the Ethiopian Orthodox Tewahedo Church|Ethiopian Orthodox Tewahedo Church prescribes a number of fasting periods]] (''tsom'', {{lang-gez|ጾም}} ''ṣōm'') from any kind of animal products (including dairy products and eggs) on Wednesdays, Fridays, and the entire [[Lent]]en season, so Ethiopian cuisine contains many dishes that are [[Vegan cuisine|vegan]].&lt;ref name=Henze&gt;Paul B. Henze, ''Layers of Time: A history of Ethiopia'' (New York: Palgrave, 2000), p. 12 and note&lt;/ref&gt;

==Overview==
[[File:Kita herb bread.jpg|thumb|right|Ethiopian ''kita'' herb bread]]
A typical dish consists of [[injera]] accompanied by a spicy stew, which frequently includes beef, lamb, vegetables and various types of legumes, such as lentils. The cuisines of the [[Southern Nations, Nationalities and People's Region]] and the Sidama people also make use of the false banana plant (''enset'', Ge'ez: እንሰት ''ïnset''), a type of [[ensete]]. The plant is pulverized and fermented to make various foods, including a bread-like food called ''qocho'' or ''[[Kocho (food)|kocho]]'' (Ge'ez: ቆጮ ''ḳōč̣ō''), which is eaten with kitfo.&lt;ref name=aaas&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aaas.org/international/africa/enset/uses.shtml|title=Uses of Enset|accessdate=13 August 2007|year=1997|work=The 'Tree Against Hunger': Enset-Based Agricultural Systems in Ethiopia|publisher=[[American Association for the Advancement of Science]]|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070819143500/http://www.aaas.org/international/africa/enset/uses.shtml|archivedate=19 August 2007|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; The root of this plant may be powdered and prepared as a hot drink called ''bulla'' (Ge'ez: ቡላ ''būlā''), which is often given to those who are tired or ill. Another typical Gurage preparation is coffee with butter (''kebbeh''). ''Kita'' herb bread is also baked.

Due in part to the brief [[Italian East Africa|Italian occupation]], [[pasta]] is popular and frequently available throughout Ethiopia, including rural areas.&lt;ref name=&quot;gonomad&quot;/&gt; Coffee is also a large part of Ethiopian culture and cuisine. After every meal, a [[coffee ceremony]] is enacted and coffee is served.

==Restrictions of certain meats==
Ethiopian Orthodox Christians, [[Ethiopian Jews]] and [[Ethiopian Muslims]] avoid eating [[pork]] or [[shellfish]], for religious reasons. Pork is considered unclean in Ethiopian Orthodox Christianity, [[Judaism]] and [[Islam]]. Many Ethiopians abstain from eating certain meats, and mostly eat vegetarian and vegan foods.

==Traditional ingredients==
[[File:BerbereOtherIngredients.JPG|thumb|[[Trachyspermum ammi|Ajwain]] or [[radhuni]], [[Aframomum corrorima|korarima]], [[Nigella sativa|nigella]] and [[fenugreek]] (clockwise, from top) are used with chilis and salt to make ''[[berbere]]'', a basic ingredient in many Ethiopian dishes.]]
''[[Berbere]]'', a combination of powdered [[chili pepper]] and other spices (somewhat analogous to [[Cuisine of the Southwestern United States|Southwestern American]] [[chili powder]]), is an important ingredient used in many dishes. Also essential is ''[[niter kibbeh]]'', a [[clarified butter]] infused with ginger, garlic, and several spices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Debrawork Abate |title=የባህላዌ መግቦች አዘገጃጀት |trans-title=Traditional Food Preparation |type= |edition=2nd |year=1995([[Ethiopian calendar|EC]]) |origyear=1993([[Ethiopian calendar|EC]])|publisher=Mega Asatame Derjet (Mega Publisher Enterprise) |location=[[Addis Ababa]] |language=Amharic |isbn= |pages=22–23 |trans-chapter= |chapter=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ethnomed&quot;&gt;{{Cite web | first=Alevtina | last=Gall |author2=Zerihun Shenkute | title=Ethiopian Traditional and Herbal Medications and their Interactions with Conventional Drugs  | url=http://ethnomed.org/clinical/pharmacy/ethiopian-herb-drug-interactions | work=EthnoMed |publisher=[[University of Washington]] | date=3 November 2009  | accessdate=27 January 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Mitmita'' ({{lang-am|ሚጥሚጣ}}, {{IPA-am|mitʼmitʼa|IPA}}) is a powdered [[seasoning mix]] used in Ethiopian cuisine. It is orange-red in color and contains ground birdseye chili peppers ([[piri piri]]), [[cardamom]] seed, [[clove]]s and salt.&lt;ref&gt;Mesfin, D.J. ''Exotic Ethiopian Cooking'' (2006): 20.  Falls Church, VA: Ethiopian Cookbooks Enterprises&lt;/ref&gt; It occasionally has other spices including [[cinnamon]], [[cumin]] and [[ginger]].

In their adherence to strict [[Fasting#Oriental Orthodox Churches|fasting]], Ethiopian cooks have developed a rich array of cooking oil sources&amp;mdash;besides [[sesame]] and [[safflower]]&amp;mdash;for use as a substitute for animal fats which are forbidden during fasting periods. Ethiopian cuisine also uses ''[[Guizotia abyssinica|nug]]'' (also spelled ''noog'', also known as &quot;niger seed&quot;).&lt;ref name=Henze/&gt;

==Dishes==
{{See also|List of Ethiopian dishes and foods}}

===Wat===
[[File:Ethiopian food.jpg|thumb|right|A typical serving of [[wat (food)|wat]]]]
''[[Wat (food)|Wat]]'' begins with a large amount of chopped red [[onion]], which is simmered or sauteed in a pot. Once the onions have softened, ''[[niter kebbeh]]'' (or, in the case of vegan dishes, [[vegetable oil]]) is added. Following this, ''berbere'' is added to make a spicy ''keiy wat'' or ''keyyih tsebhi''. [[Turmeric]] is used instead of ''berbere'' for a milder ''[[alicha wat]]'' or both spices are omitted when making vegetable stews, such as atkilt wat. Meat such as [[beef]] (''ሥጋ'',&lt;ref&gt;Selam Soft, [http://www.amharicdictionary.com/index.aspx?word=ሥጋ &quot;ሥጋ&quot;], ''Amharic-English Dictionary', 4/30/13&lt;/ref&gt; ''səga''), [[Chicken (food)|chicken]] (''ዶሮ'',&lt;ref&gt;Selam Soft, [http://www.amharicdictionary.com/index.aspx?word=ዶሮ &quot;ዶሮ&quot;], ''Amharic-English Dictionary', 4/30/13&lt;/ref&gt; ''doro'' or ''derho''), [[Fish (food)|fish]] (''ዓሣ'',&lt;ref&gt;Selam Soft, [http://www.amharicdictionary.com/index.aspx?word=ዓሣ &quot;ዓሣ&quot;], ''Amharic-English Dictionary', 4/30/13&lt;/ref&gt; ''asa''), [[Goat meat|goat]] or [[Lamb and mutton|lamb]] (''በግ'',&lt;ref&gt;Selam Soft, [http://www.amharicdictionary.com/index.aspx?word=በግ &quot;'በግ''], ''Amharic-English Dictionary', 4/30/13&lt;/ref&gt; ''beg'' or ''beggi'') is also added. [[Legume]]s such as [[split pea]]s (''ክክ'',&lt;ref&gt;Selam Soft, [http://www.amharicdictionary.com/index.aspx?word=ክክ &quot;ክክ&quot;], ''Amharic-English Dictionary', 4/30/13&lt;/ref&gt; ''kək''  or ''kikki'') and [[lentil]]s (''ምስር'',&lt;ref&gt;Selam Soft, [http://www.amharicdictionary.com/index.aspx?word=ምስር &quot;ምስር&quot;], ''Amharic-English Dictionary', 4/30/13&lt;/ref&gt; ''məsər'' or ''birsin''); or [[vegetable]]s such as [[potato]]es (''ድንች'',&lt;ref&gt;Selam Soft, [http://www.amharicdictionary.com/index.aspx?word=ድንች &quot;ድንች&quot;], ''Amharic-English Dictionary', 4/30/13&lt;/ref&gt; ''Dənəch''), [[carrot]]s and [[chard]] (ቆስጣ) are also used instead in vegan dishes.

Each variation is named by appending the main ingredient to the type of wat (e.g. ''kek alicha wat''). However, the word ''keiy'' is usually not necessary, as the spicy variety is assumed when it is omitted (e.g. ''doro wat''). The term ''atkilt wat'' is sometimes used to refer to all vegetable dishes, but a more specific name can also be used (as in ''dinich'na caroht wat'', which translates to &quot;potatoes and carrots stew&quot;; but notice the word &quot;atkilt&quot; is usually omitted when using the more specific term).

===Tibs===
{{Redirect|Tibs}}
Meat along with vegetables are [[Sautéing|sautéed]] to make ''tibs'' (also ''tebs'', ''t'ibs'', ''tibbs'', etc., Ge'ez: ጥብስ ''ṭïbs''). Tibs is served in a variety of manners, and can range from hot to mild or contain little to no vegetables. There are many variations of the delicacy, depending on type, size or shape of the cuts of meat used. Beef, mutton, and goat are the most common meats used in the preparation of tibs.
 
The mid-18th century European visitor to Ethiopia {{interlanguage link|Remedius Prutky|cs|Remedius Prutký}} describes ''tibs'' as a portion of grilled meat served &quot;to pay a particular compliment or show especial respect to someone.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;J.H. Arrowsmith-Brown (trans.), ''Prutky's Travels in Ethiopia and other Countries'' with notes by Richard Pankhurst (London: Hakluyt Society, 1991), p. 286&lt;/ref&gt; It may still be seen this way; today the dish is prepared to commemorate special events and holidays.

===Kinche (Qinch'e)===

Kinche (Qinch’e) is a very common Ethiopian breakfast, its equivalent of [[oatmeal]].  It is incredibly simple, inexpensive, and nutritious.  It is made from cracked wheat, Ethiopian oats, barley or a mixture of those. It can be boiled in either milk or water.  The flavor of the Kinche comes from the nit'ir qibe, which is a spiced butter.&lt;ref&gt;slow food foundation for biodiversity&lt;/ref&gt;

===Oromo dishes===

[[File:Tibs in Yod Abyssinia.jpg|thumb|right|A ''tibs'' (''waadii'') dish at a restaurant in Yod Abyssinia, [[Addis Ababa]]]]
*'''Waadii''' – also known as ''tibs''; specially seasoned
*'''Anchotte''' – a common dish in the western part of Oromia (Wallaga)
*'''Baduu''' – also known as ''aybe''
*'''Marqaa''' – also known as ''genfo''
*'''Chechebsa''' – also known as ''kita''
*'''Qoocco''' – although also known as ''kocho'', it is not the Gurage type of kocho but a different kind; a common dish in the western part of Oromia (Wallaga)
*'''Itto''' – also known as ''wat''; comprises all sorts of wat, including vegetables and meat
*'''Chuuco''' – also known as ''besso''; a sweet flavor of whole grain, seasoned with butter and spices
*'''Chororsaa''' – a common dish in western part of Oromia (Wallaga)

===Gurage dishes===

====Kitfo====
[[File:Kitfo.jpg|thumb|right|[[Kitfo]] served rare]]
Another distinctively Ethiopian dish is ''[[kitfo]]'' (frequently spelled ''ketfo''). It consists of raw (or rare) beef mince marinated in ''[[mitmita]]'' (Ge'ez: ሚጥሚጣ ''mīṭmīṭā'' a very spicy chili powder similar to the ''berbere'') and ''niter kibbeh''. ''[[Gored gored]]'' is very similar to ''kitfo'', but uses cubed rather than ground beef.

====Ayibe====
''Ayibe'' is a [[cottage cheese]] that is mild and crumbly. It is much closer in texture to crumbled [[feta]]. Although not quite pressed, the whey has been drained and squeezed out. It is often served as a side dish to soften the effect of very spicy food. It has little to no distinct taste of its own. However, when served separately, ayibe is often mixed with a variety of mild or hot spices typical of Gurage cuisine.

====Gomen kitfo====
''Gomen kitfo'' is another typical Gurage dish. [[Collard greens]] (ጎመን ''gōmen'') are boiled, dried and then finely chopped and served with butter, chili and spices. It is a dish specially prepared for the occasion of [[Meskel]], a very popular holiday marking the discovery of the [[True Cross]]. It is served along with ''ayibe'' or sometimes even ''kitfo'' in this tradition called ''dengesa''.

===Sidama dishes===
====Wassa====
The [[enset]] plant (called ''wesse'' in the [[Sidamo language]]) is central to Sidama cuisine and after grinding and fermenting the root to produce ''wassa'', it is used in the preparation of several foods.

''Amulcho'' is an enset flatbread used similarly to injera to eat wats made from beef, mushrooms, beans, gomen, and pumpkin.

''Borasaame'' is a cooked mixture of wassa and butter sometimes eaten with [[Ethiopian mustard]] greens. It is traditionally eaten by hand using a false banana leaf and is served in a ''shafeta'', a vase-like ceramic vessel. A common variant of borasaame uses [[maize]] flour instead of wassa and is called ''badela borasaame''.
Borasaame is typically paired with a seasoned yogurt drink called wätät. Both are common foods for funerals and the celebration of ''Fichee Chambalaalla'', the Sidama new year.

====Gomen ba siga====
Gomen ba siga (ጎመን በስጋ, Amharic: &quot;cabbage with meat&quot;) is a stewed mixture of beef and Ethiopian mustard served under a layer of amulcho.

====Maize====
A commonly grown crop in Sidama, maize (badela in Sidaamu) is often eaten as a snack with coffee. It can be ground into flour to make bread, roasted on the cob, or the kernels can be picked off to make ''bokolo'', which is served either boiled or roasted.

===Breakfast===
[[File:Kitcha fit fit.png|thumb|[[Fit-fit]], or chechebsa, made with [[kitcha]] (unleavened bread), [[niter kibbeh]] (seasoned clarified butter) and [[berbere]] (spice), is a typical breakfast food.]]
''[[Fit-fit]]'' or ''fir-fir'' is a common breakfast dish. It is made from shredded ''injera'' or ''[[kitcha]]'' stir-fried with spices or [[wat (food)|wat]]. Another popular breakfast food is ''fatira''. The delicacy consists of a large fried pancake made with flour, often with a layer of egg. It is eaten with honey. ''[[Kitcha fit-fit|Chechebsa]]'' (or ''kita firfir'') resembles a [[pancake]] covered with ''berbere'' and ''niter kibbeh'', or other spices, and may be eaten with a spoon. ''Genfo'' is a kind of [[porridge]], which is another common breakfast dish. It is usually served in a large bowl with a dug-out made in the middle of the genfo and filled with spiced ''niter kibbeh''. A variation of ''[[Shahan ful|ful]]'', a fava bean stew with condiments, served with baked rolls instead of ''injera'', is also common for breakfast.

==Snacks==
Typical Ethiopian snacks are [[Dabo Kolo]] (small pieces of baked bread that are similar to [[pretzel]]s) or ''kolo'' (roasted [[barley]] sometimes mixed with other local grains). ''Kolo'' made from roasted and spiced barley, safflower kernels, chickpeas and/or peanuts are often sold by kiosks and street vendors, wrapped in a paper cone. Snacking on [[popcorn]] is also common.&lt;ref name=&quot;gonomad&quot;/&gt;

==Gursha==
A ''gursha'' (var. ''gorsha'', ''goorsha'') is an act of friendship and love. When eating injera, a person uses his or her right hand to strip off a piece, wraps it around some ''wat'' or ''kitfo'', and then puts it into his or her mouth. During a meal with friends or family, it is a common custom to feed others in the group with one's hand by putting the rolled injera or a spoon full of other dishes into another's mouth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ethnomed.org/clinical/nutrition/the-traditional-foods-of-the-central-ethiopian|title=The Traditional Foods of the Central Ethiopian Highlands (research report no. 7)|last=Selinus|first=Ruth|date=1 January 1971|publisher=EthnoMed|accessdate=1 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is called a ''gursha'', and the larger the gursha, the stronger the friendship or bond (only surpassed by the brewing of Tej together). This tradition was featured in &quot;[[The Food Wife]],&quot; an episode of ''[[The Simpsons]]'' that uses Ethiopian cuisine as a plot point.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tadias.com/12/01/2011/the-simpsons-episode-well-received-by-ethiopians-on-social-media-elsewhere/|title=The Simpsons Episode Well-Received by Ethiopians On Social Media|publisher=Tadias Magazine|accessdate=3 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Beverages==

=== Traditional alcoholic beverages ===
There are many different traditional alcoholic drinks which are home made and of natural ingredients.

====Tella====
[[Tella]] is a home-brewed beer served in ''tella bet'' (&quot;tella houses&quot;) which specialize in serving only tella. Tella is the most common beverage made and served in households during holidays.

It is an alcoholic drink which is prepared from bikil (barley) as main ingredient and [[Rhamnus prinoides|gesho]] (''Rhamnus prinoides'') for fermentation purpose.

In [[Oromiffaa]] the drink is called ''farso'' and in Tigrinya ''[[siwa (beer)|siwa]]''.

====Tej (honey wine) ====
[[Tej]] is a potent honey wine.&lt;ref name=&quot;gonomad&quot; /&gt; It is similar to [[mead]], and is frequently served in bars, particularly in a ''tej bet'' or &quot;tej house&quot;.

It is prepared from honey and gesho. It has a sweet taste and the alcoholic content is relatively higher than tella. This drink can be stored for a long time; the longer it is stored, the higher the alcohol content, and the stronger the taste.

====Areki (katikala)====
Areki, also known as katikala, is probably the strongest alcoholic drink of Ethiopia.&lt;ref&gt;[https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/e979/2cd7eab761616d1dd1157c2e4850cdb4d9b0.pdf Areki]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Non-alcoholic beverages ===
Ethiopians have diverse traditional non-alcoholic drinks which include natural and healthy ingredients.

====Kenetto (keribo)====
Kenetto, also known as keribo, is a non-alcoholic traditional drink. It is mostly used as substitute for tella for those who don't drink alcohol.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0956713517305455 Kenetto]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Borde====
Borde is a cereal-based traditional fermented beverage famous in southern Ethiopia.&lt;ref&gt;[https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/e979/2cd7eab761616d1dd1157c2e4850cdb4d9b0.pdf Borde]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Manufactured drinks===
Just like the rest of the world Ethiopians also enjoy several locally manufactured beers, wine and non alcoholic products  like Coca-Cola and other similar products.[[File:Ethiopian Coca Cola bottle.JPG|thumb|right|200px|A [[Coca-Cola]] bottle in Ethiopia, with the distinct logo in the [[Ge'ez script|Ethiopic script]]]]
[[Ambo Mineral Water]] or ''Ambo wuha'' is a bottled carbonated [[mineral water]], sourced from the springs in [[Ambo Senkele]] near the town of [[Ambo, Ethiopia|Ambo]].&lt;ref name=&quot;gonomad&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ambowater.com/aboutus.html|title=About us|publisher=Ambo Mineral Water|access-date=4 January 2013|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121104060506/http://www.ambowater.com/aboutus.html|archive-date=4 November 2012|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Non-alcoholic brews (hot drinks)===

==== Atmet ====
''[[Atmet]]'' is a barley and oat-flour based drink that is cooked with water, sugar and ''kibe'' (Ethiopian clarified butter) until the ingredients have combined to create a consistency slightly thicker than [[Eggnog|egg-nog]]. Though this drink is often given to women who are nursing, the sweetness and smooth texture make it a comfort drink for anyone who enjoys its flavor.

====Coffee====
[[File:Ethcofcerm.jpg|thumb|200px|An Ethiopian woman roasting coffee at a traditional [[coffee ceremony]]]]
According to some sources, drinking of [[coffee]] (''buna'') is likely to have originated in Ethiopia.&lt;ref name=&quot;gonomad&quot;/&gt; A key national beverage, it is an important part of local commerce.&lt;ref name=&quot;cia&quot;&gt;{{Cite web| title=Ethiopia | url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/et.html | work=[[The World Factbook]] | publisher=[[Central Intelligence Agency]] | date=12 January 2011 | accessdate=31 January 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[coffee ceremony]] is the traditional serving of coffee, usually after a big meal. It often involves the use of a ''[[jebena]]'' (ጀበና), a clay coffee pot in which the coffee is boiled. The preparer roasts the coffee beans in front of guests, then walks around wafting the smoke throughout the room so participants may sample the scent of coffee. Then the preparer grinds the coffee beans in a traditional tool called a ''mokecha''. The coffee is put into the jebena, boiled with water, and then served in small cups called ''si'ni''. Coffee is usually served with sugar, but is also served with salt in many parts of Ethiopia. In some parts of the country, ''niter kibbeh'' is added instead of sugar or salt.

Snacks, such as popcorn or toasted barley (or ''[[Dabo Kolo|kolo]]''), are often served with the coffee. In most homes, a dedicated coffee area is surrounded by fresh grass, with special furniture for the coffee maker. A complete ceremony has three rounds of coffee (abol, tona and bereka) and is accompanied by the burning of [[frankincense]].

====Tea (chai)====
[[Tea]] will most likely be served if coffee is declined.

==See also==
* [[List of African cuisines]]
* [[Ethiopian Jewish cuisine]]
{{portalbar|Africa|Food}}

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Cuisine of Ethiopia}}
{{Div col}}
* [http://ethiopianfood.wordpress.com Mesob Across America: Ethiopian Food in the U.S.A.] A book about the history and culture of Ethiopian cuisine
* [https://ethiopianrestaurants.wordpress.com/ Ethiopian Restaurant Guide] A guide to Ethiopian restaurants in the USA. Includes video visits to some restaurants
* [http://ethiopiantej.wordpress.com All About Tej] An extensive website about the Ethiopian honey wine
*[http://www.latimes.com/features/food/la-fo-raw-meat-20110714,0,1810781.story Raw Meat, a Manly Ethiopian Dish] The Los Angeles Times, 14 July 2011
* [http://www.fassica.com Ethiopian Spices]  by Fassica - Authentic Ethiopian Food and Spices{{Div col end}}

{{Ethiopia topics}}
{{African cuisine}}
{{cuisine}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2011}}

[[Category:Ethiopian cuisine|*]]
[[Category:African cuisine]]</text>
      <sha1>5t0hrxtp3rjh1gb7eghsp8ddv6b3v9e</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
