  <page>
    <title>Book of Exodus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9662</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942965898</id>
      <parentid>942965696</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T00:11:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>CLCStudent</username>
        <id>26398660</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/217.213.66.213|217.213.66.213]] ([[User talk:217.213.66.213|talk]]) to last version by Wallyfromdilbert</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Second book of the Bible}}
{{About|the second book of the Bible|other uses|Exodus (disambiguation){{!}}Exodus}}

[[File:The Crossing fo The Red Sea.jpg|thumb|300px|''Crossing of the Red Sea'', [[Nicholas Poussin]]]]
{{Tanakh OT |Torah |Pentateuch}}
The '''Book of Exodus''' is the second book of the [[Bible]] and describes [[the Exodus]], which includes the [[Israelites]]' deliverance from slavery in Egypt through the hand of [[Yahweh]], the revelations at [[biblical Mount Sinai]], and the subsequent &quot;divine indwelling&quot; of God with Israel.{{sfn|Sparks|2010}}

Exodus is traditionally [[Mosaic authorship|ascribed to Moses]], but modern scholars see its initial composition as a product of the [[Babylonian captivity|Babylonian exile]] (6th century BCE), with final revisions in the [[Yehud Medinata|Persian post-exilic period]] (5th century BCE).{{sfn|Johnstone|2003|p=72}}{{sfn|Finkelstein|Silberman|2002|p=68}} [[Carol Meyers]], in her commentary on Exodus, suggests that it is arguably the most important book in the Bible, as it presents the defining features of Israel's identity—memories of a past marked by hardship and escape, a binding covenant with God, who chooses Israel, and the establishment of the life of the community and the guidelines for sustaining it.&lt;ref&gt;Meyers, p. xv.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Name==
[[File:1867 Edward Poynter - Israel in Egypt.jpg|thumb|400px|Children of Israel in Egypt (1867 painting by [[Edward Poynter]])]]
The English name ''Exodus'' comes from the {{lang-grc|ἔξοδος}}, ''éxodos'', meaning &quot;going out&quot;, from ἐξ-&amp;nbsp;(ex,&amp;nbsp;“out”)&amp;nbsp;+&amp;nbsp;ὁδός&amp;nbsp;(hodós,&amp;nbsp;“path, road”). 

In Hebrew the book's title is שְׁמוֹת, ''shemōt'', &quot;Names&quot;, from the [[Incipit|beginning words of the text]]: &quot;These are the names of the sons of Israel&quot; ({{lang-he-n|וְאֵלֶּה שְׁמֹות בְּנֵי יִשְׂרָאֵל}}).{{sfn|Dozeman|2009|p=1}}

== Structure ==
There is no unanimous agreement among scholars on the structure of Exodus. One strong possibility is that it is a [[diptych]] (i.e., divided into two parts), with the division between parts 1 and 2 at the [[crossing of the Red Sea]] or at the beginning of the [[theophany]] (appearance of God) in chapter 19.&lt;ref&gt;Meyers, p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; On this plan, the first part tells of God's rescue of his people from Egypt and their journey under his care to Sinai (chapters 1–19) and the second tells of the covenant between them (chapters 20–40).&lt;ref&gt;Stuart, p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Summary ==
[[File:Dura Europos fresco Moses from river.jpg|thumb|''[[Finding of Moses]]'' in the [[Dura-Europos synagogue]], c. 244]]
[[Jacob]]'s sons and their families join their brother, [[Joseph (Genesis)|Joseph]], in Egypt.  Once there, the Israelites begin to grow in number. Egypt's [[Pharaoh of the Exodus|Pharaoh]], fearful that the [[Israelites]] could be a [[fifth column]], forces the Israelites into slavery and orders the throwing of all newborn boys into the [[Nile]]. A [[Levite]] woman ([[Jochebed]], according to other sources) saves her baby by [[Finding of Moses|setting him adrift]] on the river Nile in an [[ark of bulrushes]]. The [[Bithiah|Pharaoh's daughter]] finds the child, names him [[Moses]], and brings him up as her own. But Moses is aware of his origins, and one day, when grown, he kills an Egyptian overseer who is beating a [[Hebrew]] slave and has to flee into [[Midian]]. There he marries [[Zipporah]], the daughter of Midianite priest [[Jethro (Bible)|Jethro]], and encounters God in a [[burning bush]]. Moses asks God for his name: God replies: &quot;[[I Am that I Am|I AM that I AM]]&quot;, the explanation of the name &quot;Yahweh&quot; as he is thereafter known. God tells Moses to return to Egypt and lead the Hebrews into [[Canaan]], the land promised to [[Abraham]].

Moses returns to Egypt and fails to convince the Pharaoh to release the Israelites.  God smites the Egyptians with 10 terrible plagues ([[Plagues of Egypt]]) including a river of blood, many frogs, and the death of first-born sons.  Moses leads the Israelites out of bondage after a final chase when the Pharaoh reneges on his coerced consent ([[Parting of the Red Sea|Crossing the Red Sea]] and [[Yam Suph]]). The desert proves arduous, and the Israelites complain and long for Egypt, but God provides [[manna]] and miraculous water for them. The Israelites arrive at the mountain of God, where Moses's father-in-law Jethro visits Moses; at his suggestion Moses appoints [[Biblical judges|judges]] over Israel. God asks whether they will agree to be his people. They accept. The people gather at the foot of the mountain, and with thunder and lightning, fire and clouds of smoke, and the sound of trumpets, and the trembling of the mountain, God appears on the peak, and the people see the cloud and hear the voice [or possibly &quot;sound&quot;] of God. God tells Moses to ascend the mountain. God pronounces the [[Ten Commandments]] (the [[Ethical Decalogue]]) in the hearing of all Israel. Moses goes up the mountain into the presence of God, who pronounces the [[Covenant Code]] (a detailed code of ritual and civil law), and promises [[Canaan]] to them if they obey. Moses comes down the mountain and writes down God's words and the people agree to keep them. God calls Moses up the mountain where he remains for 40 days and 40 nights. At the conclusion of the 40 days and 40 nights, Moses returns holding the set of stone [[tablet (religious)|tablets]].

God gives Moses instructions for the construction of the [[tabernacle (Judaism)|tabernacle]] so that God could dwell permanently among his chosen people, as well as instructions for the [[Priestly robe (Judaism)|priestly vestments]], the altar and its appurtenances, the procedure for ordaining the priests, and the daily sacrifice offerings. Aaron becomes the first [[High Priest of Israel|hereditary high priest]]. God gives Moses the two tablets of stone containing the words of the ten commandments, written with the [[Finger of God (Commandments)|&quot;finger of God&quot;]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleref2|Exodus|31:18}}; {{bibleref2|Deuteronomy|9:10|9}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Gerrit de Wet - The Adoration of the Golden Calf - WGA25563.jpg|thumb|''Worship of the Golden Calf'', [[Gerrit de Wet]], 17th century]]

While Moses is with God, Aaron makes a [[golden calf]], which the people worship. God informs Moses of their [[apostasy]] and threatens to kill them all, but relents when Moses pleads for them. Moses comes down from the mountain, smashes the stone tablets in anger, and commands the [[Levites]] to massacre the unfaithful Israelites. God commands Moses to make two new tablets on which He will personally write the words that were on the first tablets. Moses ascends the mountain, God dictates the Ten Commandments (the [[Ritual Decalogue]]), and Moses writes them on the tablets.

Moses descends from the mountain with a transformed face; from that time onwards he has to hide his face with a veil. Moses assembles the Hebrews and repeats to them the commandments he has received from God, which are to keep the [[Sabbath]] and to construct the Tabernacle. &quot;And all the construction of the Tabernacle of the Tent of Meeting was finished, and the children of Israel did according to everything that God had commanded Moses&quot;, and from that time God dwelt in the Tabernacle and ordered the travels of the Hebrews.

== Composition ==
=== Authorship ===
Jewish and Christian tradition viewed [[Mosaic authorship|Moses as the author of Exodus]] and the entire [[Torah]], but by the end of the 19th century the increasing awareness of discrepancies, inconsistencies, repetitions and other features of the Pentateuch had led scholars to abandon this idea.{{sfn|Meyers|2005|p=16}} In approximate round dates, the process which produced Exodus and the Pentateuch probably began around 600 BCE when existing oral and written traditions were brought together to form books recognisable as those we know, reaching their final form as unchangeable sacred texts around 400 BCE.{{sfn|McEntire|2008|p=8}}

=== Genre and sources ===
The story of [[the exodus]] is the [[founding myth]] of the Israelites, telling of their deliverance from slavery by [[Yahweh]] which made them his chosen people according to the [[Mosaic covenant]].{{sfn|Sparks|2010|p=73}}  Fretheim says that it is not a historical narrative in any modern sense, instead its primary concern is theological.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;Fretheim, p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt; It reflects common themes of past communities in exile, including facing foreign captivity and suffering under just judgment because of disloyalty to God.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; In Exodus, everything is presented as the work of God, who appears frequently in person.&lt;ref&gt;Houston, p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although mythical elements are not so prominent in Exodus as in [[Book of Genesis|Genesis]], ancient legends may have an influence on the book's form or content: for example, the story of the infant Moses's salvation from the Nile is argued to be based on an earlier legend of king [[Sargon of Akkad]], while the story of the [[parting of the Red Sea]] may trade on Mesopotamian [[creation myth]]ology.  Similarly, the [[Covenant Code]] (the law code in Exodus 20:22–23:33) has some similarities in both content and structure with the [[Laws of Hammurabi]]. These influences serve to reinforce the conclusion that the Book of Exodus originated in the exiled Jewish community of 6th-century BCE [[Babylon]], but not all the sources are Mesopotamian: the story of Moses's flight to Midian following the murder of the Egyptian overseer may draw on the Egyptian ''[[Story of Sinuhe]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Kugler, Hartin, p. 74.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Themes ==
[[File:David Roberts-IsraelitesLeavingEgypt 1828.jpg|thumb|300px|''Departure of the Israelites'' by [[David Roberts (painter)|David Roberts]], 1829]]

=== Salvation ===
Biblical scholars describe the Bible's theologically-motivated history writing as &quot;[[salvation history]]&quot;, meaning a history of God's saving actions that give identity to Israel – the promise of offspring and land to the ancestors, the exodus from Egypt (in which God saves Israel from slavery), the wilderness wandering, the revelation at Sinai, and the hope for the future life in the [[promised land]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Dozeman&quot;&gt;Dozeman, p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Theophany ===
A [[theophany]] is a manifestation (appearance) of a god – in the Bible, an appearance of the God of Israel, accompanied by storms – the earth trembles, the mountains quake, the heavens pour rain, thunder peals and lightning flashes.&lt;ref&gt;Dozeman, p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt; The theophany in Exodus begins &quot;the third day&quot; from their arrival at Sinai in chapter 19: Yahweh and the people meet at the mountain, God appears in the storm and converses with Moses, giving him the [[Ten Commandments]] while the people listen. The theophany is therefore a public experience of divine law.&lt;ref&gt;Dozeman, p. 427.&lt;/ref&gt;

The second half of Exodus marks the point at which, and describes the process through which, God's theophany becomes a permanent presence for Israel via the [[Tabernacle]]. That so much of the book (chapters 25–31, 35–40) describes the plans of the Tabernacle demonstrates the importance it played in the perception of [[Second Temple Judaism]] at the time of the text's redaction by the Priestly writers: the Tabernacle is the place where God is physically present, where, through the priesthood, Israel could be in direct, literal communion with him.&lt;ref&gt;Dempster, p. 107.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Covenant ===
The heart of Exodus is the [[Mosaic covenant|Sinaitic covenant]].&lt;ref&gt;Wenham, p. 29.&lt;/ref&gt; A covenant is a legal document binding two parties to take on certain obligations towards each other.&lt;ref&gt;Meyers, p. 148.&lt;/ref&gt; There are several covenants in the Bible, and in each case they exhibit at least some of the elements in real-life treaties of the ancient Middle East: a preamble, historical prologue, stipulations, deposition and reading, list of witnesses, blessings and curses, and ratification by animal sacrifice.&lt;ref&gt;Meyers, pp. 149–150.&lt;/ref&gt; Biblical covenants, in contrast to Eastern covenants in general, are between a god, Yahweh, and a people, Israel, instead of between a strong ruler and a weaker vassal.&lt;ref&gt;Meyers, p. 150.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Election of Israel ===
God elects Israel for salvation because the &quot;sons of Israel&quot; are &quot;the firstborn son&quot; of the God of Israel, descended through Shem and Abraham to the chosen line of [[Jacob]] whose name is changed to Israel. The goal of the divine plan in Exodus is a return to humanity's state in [[Garden of Eden|Eden]], so that God can dwell with the Israelites as he had with [[Adam and Eve]] through the Ark and Tabernacle, which together form a model of the universe; in later [[Abrahamic religion]]s Israel becomes the guardian of God's plan for humanity, to bring &quot;God's creation blessing to mankind&quot; begun in Adam.&lt;ref&gt;Dempster, p. 100.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Weekly Torah portions ==
[[File:Rembrandt Harmensz. van Rijn 079.jpg|thumb|right|upright|[[Moses]] with the Ten Commandments, by [[Rembrandt]] (1659)]]
{{main|Weekly Torah portion}}

:*[[Shemot (parsha)|Shemot]], on Exodus 1–5: Affliction in Egypt, discovery of baby Moses, Pharaoh
:*[[Va'eira (parsha)|Va'eira]], on Exodus 6–9: Plagues 1 to 7 of Egypt
:*[[Bo (parsha)|Bo]], on Exodus 10–13: Last plagues of Egypt, first Passover
:*[[Beshalach (parsha)|Beshalach]], on Exodus 13–17: Parting the Sea, water, manna, Amalek
:*[[Yitro (parsha)|Yitro]], on Exodus 18–20: Jethro’s advice, The Ten Commandments
:*[[Mishpatim (parsha)|Mishpatim]], on Exodus 21–24: The Covenant Code
:*[[Terumah (parsha)|Terumah]], on Exodus 25–27: God's instructions on the Tabernacle and furnishings
:*[[Tetzaveh (parsha)|Tetzaveh]], on Exodus 27–30: God's instructions on the first priests
:*[[Ki Tissa]], on Exodus 30–34: Census, anointing oil, golden calf, stone tablets, Moses radiant
:*[[Vayakhel (parsha)|Vayakhel]], on Exodus 35–38: Israelites collect gifts, make the Tabernacle and furnishings
:*[[Pekudei (parsha)|Pekudei]], on Exodus 38–40: Setting up and filling of The Tabernacle

== Historicity ==
{{multiple image | align. = left | width1 = 150	| image1 = Exodus map.jpg | caption1 = 1585 map | width2 = 168	| image2 = Wanderings in the desert map.jpg | caption2 = 1641 map | footer = Historical representations of the [[Stations of the Exodus]]}}
The overwhelming consensus among scholars is that the Exodus story is best understood as a [[myth]] and does not accurately describe historical events.{{sfn|Collins|2005|p=46}}  While archaeology has found traces left by even small bands of hunter-gatherers in the Sinai, there is no evidence at all for the large body of people described in the Exodus story: &quot;The conclusion – that Exodus did not happen at the time and in the manner described in the Bible – seems irrefutable [...] repeated excavations and surveys throughout the entire area have not provided even the slightest evidence&quot; (Finkelstein and Silberman, 2001).{{sfn|Finkelstein|Silberman|2001|p=63}} Instead, modern archaeology suggests continuity between Canaanite and Israelite settlement, indicating a primarily Canaanite origin for Israel.{{sfn|Barmash|2015|p=4}}{{sfn|Shaw|2002|p=313}}

While all but the most conservative scholars reject the biblical account of the Exodus,{{sfn|Collins|2005|p=46}} a majority still believes that the story has some historical basis,{{sfn|Faust|2015|p=476}}{{sfn|Redmount|2001|p=87}} with Kenton Sparks referring to it as &quot;mythologized history.&quot;{{sfn|Sparks|2010|p=73}} Some scholars, associated with the interpretative school of [[Biblical minimalism]],{{sfn|Davies|2004|p=23-24}} show more skepticism towards ascribing any [[historicity]] to the Exodus,{{sfn|Moore|Kelle|2011|p=95}} with some arguing that the myth has its origins in the [[Babylonian exile|exilic]] and post-exilic Jewish community and has little to no historical basis.{{sfn|Russell|2009|pp=11-14}}

== See also ==
{{Portal|Bible}}
* [[List of films based on the Bible#Moses and the 40 years in the desert|Film adaptations of the Book of Exodus]]
* [[History of the Jews in Egypt#Ancient times|History of the Jews in Ancient Egypt]]
* [[Ketef Hinnom]]
* [[Song of the sea]]

== References ==

=== Citations ===
{{reflist|30em}}

=== Bibliography ===
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book
| last           = Barmash
| first          = Pamela
| chapter        = Out of the Mists of History: The Exaltation of the Exodus in the Bible
| editor1-last   = Barmash
| editor1-first  = Pamela
| editor2-last   = Nelson
| editor2-first  = W. David
| title          = Exodus in the Jewish Experience: Echoes and Reverberations
| year           = 2015
| publisher      = Lexington Books
| chapterurl     = https://books.google.com/books?id=jKYlCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA1
| isbn           = 9781498502931
| pages          = 1–22
| ref            = harv
}}
*{{Cite book|last=Childs|first=Brevard S|title=The Book of Exodus|publisher=Eerdmans|year=1979|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Z7sKWo7FRAgC |isbn=9780664229689|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
| last           = Collins
| first          = John J.
| title          = The Bible After Babel: Historical Criticism in a Postmodern Age
| year           = 2005
| publisher      = Eerdmans
| isbn           = 9780802828927
| url            = https://books.google.com/?id=yqClWOhqso0C&amp;pg=PA45&amp;dq=%22collective+memory%22#v=onepage&amp;q=%22collective%20memory%22&amp;f=false
| ref            = harv
}}
*{{cite book
| last           = Davies
| first          = Graham
| editor1-last   = Day
| editor1-first  = John
| title          = In Search of Pre-exilic Israel: Proceedings of the Oxford Old Testament Seminar 
| chapter        = Was There an Exodus?
| year           = 2004
| publisher      = Continuum
| isbn           = 9780567082060
| chapter-url    = https://books.google.com/books?id=yM_X2yzRLx4C&amp;pg=PA23
| ref            = harv
| pages=23–40}}
*{{Cite book|last=Dempster|first=Stephen G|author-link=Stephen Dempster|title=Dominion and Dynasty|publisher=InterVarsity Press|year=2006|url=https://books.google.com/?id=G329hmhyBa8C |isbn=9780830826155|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last=Dozeman|first=Thomas B|title=Commentary on Exodus|publisher=Eerdmans|year=2009|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=fRXjfa6RWPwC |isbn=9780802826176|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book
|last         = Dozeman
|first        = Thomas B
|chapter      = Exodus, Book of
|editor1-first= Freedman 
|editor1-last = David Noel 
|editor2-first= Myers
|editor2-last = Allen C.  
|title        = Eerdmans Dictionary of the Bible
|publisher    = Eerdmans
|year         = 2000
|chapter-url  = https://books.google.com/books?id=qRtUqxkB7wkC
|isbn         = 
|ref          = harv
}}
*{{Cite book 
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CiqF7sVqDQcC&amp;pg=PA73 
|title       = Methods for Exodus 
|last        = Dozeman 
|first       = Thomas B. 
|year        = 2010 
|publisher   = Cambridge University Press 
|isbn        = 9781139487382 
|language    = en
}}
*{{cite book
|last1=Faust
|first1=Avraham
|chapter=The Emergence of Iron Age Israel: On Origins and Habitus 
|title=Israel's Exodus in Transdisciplinary Perspective: Text, Archaeology, Culture, and Geoscience
|editor1=Thomas E. Levy
|editor2=Thomas Schneider
|editor3=William H.C. Propp
|chapter-url=https://www.academia.edu/11906343
|date=2015
|publisher=Springer
|isbn=978-3-319-04768-3
|ref=harv
}}
*{{Cite book
|last1        = Finkelstein
|first1       = Israel
|last2        = Silberman
|first2       = Neil Asher
|title        = The Bible Unearthed
|publisher    = Simon and Schuster
|year         = 2002
|url          = https://books.google.com/?id=lu6ywyJr0CMC
|isbn         = 9780743223386
|ref          = harv
}}
*{{Cite book|last=Fretheim|first=Terence E|title=Exodus|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|year=1991|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=hU546phUN0oC |isbn=9780664237349|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last=Houston|first=Walter J|chapter=Exodus|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3surkLVdw3UC&amp;pg=PA67|editor=John Barton|title=Oxford Bible Commentary|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=1998|isbn=9780198755005|ref=harv|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/oxfordbiblecomme0000unse}}
*{{Cite book|last=Johnstone|first=William D|chapter=Exodus|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2Vo-11umIZQC&amp;pg=PA72 |editor=James D. G. Dunn, John William Rogerson|title=Eerdmans Bible Commentary|publisher=Eerdmans|year=2003|isbn=9780802837110|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last1=Kugler|first1=Robert|last2=Hartin|first2=Patrick|title=An Introduction to the Bible|publisher=Eerdmans|year=2009|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=L8WbXbPjxpoC |isbn=9780802846365|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last=McEntire|first=Mark|title=Struggling with God: An Introduction to the Pentateuch|publisher=Mercer University Press|year=2008|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VwOs9f1FpmsC&amp;pg=PA87 |isbn=9780881461015|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last=Meyers|first=Carol|author-link=Carol Meyers|title=Exodus|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2005|url=https://books.google.com/?id=0QHHITXsyskC |isbn=9780521002912|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|last1         = Moore
|first1        = Megan Bishop
|last2         = Kelle
|first2        = Brad E.
|title         = Biblical History and Israel's Past
|year          = 2011
|publisher     = Eerdmans
|url           = https://books.google.com/books?id=Qjkz_8EMoaUC&amp;pg=PA81
|ref           = harv
|isbn        = 9780802862600
}}
*Newman, Murray L (2000) [http://www.vts.edu/ftpimages/95/download/download_group10629_id314910.pdf  ''Exodus''] Forward Movement Publications
*[[Gunther Plaut|Plaut, Gunther]]. ''The Torah: A Modern Commentary'' (1981), {{ISBN|0-8074-0055-6}}
*{{cite book |last= Redmount| first= Carol A.| title= The Oxford History of the Biblical World| chapter= Bitter Lives: Israel In And Out of Egypt| editor-last  = Coogan | editor-first = Michael D. | year         = 2001 | orig-year    = 1998 | publisher    = OUP| isbn= 9780199881482 | chapter-url= https://books.google.com/?id=4DVHJRFW3mYC&amp;pg=PA59 |pages=58–89| ref = harv
}}
*{{cite book
| last          = Gmirkin
| first         = Russell E.
| title         = Berossus and Genesis, Manetho and Exodus: Hellenistic Histories and The Date of the Pentateuch
| year          = 2006
| publisher     = T &amp; T Clark International
| isbn          = 9780567025920
| url           = https://books.google.com/books?id=noKI6AsqnhMC
| ref           = harv
}}
*{{cite book| last1 = Shaw | first1 = Ian| editor1-last = Shaw    | editor1-first = Ian| editor2-last = Jameson | editor2-first = Robert| title = A Dictionary of Archaeology| chapter = Israel, Israelites| year = 2002| publisher = Wiley Blackwell| isbn =9780631235835|page=313| chapter-url = https://books.google.com/books?id=zmvNogJO2ZgC&amp;pg=PA313| ref = harv}}
*{{cite book
| last           = Sparks
| first          = Kenton L.
| editor1-last   = Dozeman
| editor1-first  = Thomas B.
| title          = Methods for Exodus
| chapter        = Genre Criticism
| year           = 2010
| publisher      = Cambridge University Press
| chapter-url    = https://books.google.com/?id=CiqF7sVqDQcC&amp;pg=PA73
| ref            = harv 
| isbn           = 9781139487382
}}
*{{Cite book|last=Stuart|first=Douglas K|title=Exodus|publisher=B&amp;H Publishing Group|year=2006|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=8H9E00e5PSwC |isbn=9780805401028|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last=Wenham|first=Gordon|title=The Book of Leviticus|publisher=Eerdmans|year=1979|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9SKlbar7-SkC |isbn=9780802825223|ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
{{wikiquote}}
{{Wikisource|Exodus (Bible)}}
{{commons category|Book of Exodus}}
*[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Exodus%201&amp;version=ESV Exodus] at [[BibleGateway.com]]
*[http://www.mechon-mamre.org/e/et/et0201.htm Exodus at Mechon-Mamre] (Jewish Publication Society translation)
*[http://bible.ort.org/books/pentd2.asp?ACTION=displaypage&amp;BOOK=2&amp;CHAPTER=1 Exodus (The Living Torah)] Rabbi [[Aryeh Kaplan]]'s translation and commentary at Ort.org
*[http://www.chabad.org/article.asp?aid=8161 Shemot – Exodus (Judaica Press)] translation [with [[Rashi]]'s commentary] at Chabad.org
*[http://www.mechon-mamre.org/p/pt/pt0201.htm ''Shmot''] (Original [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] – English at Mechon-Mamre.org)
* {{librivox book | title=Exodus}} Various versions

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou | [[Torah|Pentateuch]]|||}}
{{S-bef | before = [[Book of Genesis|Genesis]] | rows = 2 }}
{{S-ttl | title = [[Tanakh|Hebrew Bible]] }}
{{s-aft | after = [[Book of Leviticus|Leviticus]] | rows= 2 }}
{{S-ttl | title = [[Christianity|Christian]]&lt;br&gt;[[Old Testament]] }}
{{s-end}}

{{Books of the Bible}}
{{Ten Commandments}}
{{Book of Exodus}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Book Of Exodus}}
[[Category:Book of Exodus| ]]
[[Category:6th-century BC books]]
[[Category:5th-century BC books]]
[[Category:Books about Egypt]]
[[Category:Mythology books]]
[[Category:Torah books|2]]</text>
      <sha1>03871l7s3kqcwy2rqsgurgr3hyv8b95</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
