  <page>
    <title>Entscheidungsproblem</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9672</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941425318</id>
      <parentid>939527626</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-18T14:52:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>47.208.117.96</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Algorithims don’t necessarily “take” inputs</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Impossible task in computing}}
{{italic title}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
In [[mathematics]] and [[computer science]], the '''''{{lang|de|Entscheidungsproblem}}''''' ({{IPA-de|ɛntˈʃaɪ̯dʊŋspʁoˌbleːm|pron}}, [[German language|German]] for &quot;decision problem&quot;) is a challenge posed by [[David Hilbert]] and [[Wilhelm Ackermann]]  in 1928.&lt;ref&gt;David Hilbert and Wilhlem Ackermann. Grundzüge der Theoretischen Logik. Springer, Berlin, Germany, 1928. English translation: David Hilbert and Wilhelm Ackermann. Principles of Mathematical Logic. AMS Chelsea Publishing, Providence, Rhode Island, USA, 
 1950&lt;/ref&gt; The problem asks for an [[algorithm]] that considers, as input, a statement and answers &quot;Yes&quot; or &quot;No&quot; according to whether the statement is ''universally valid'', i.e., valid in every [[Structure (mathematical logic)|structure]] satisfying the axioms.

==Completeness theorem==
By [[Gödel's completeness theorem|the completeness theorem of first-order logic]], a statement is universally valid if and only if it can be deduced from the axioms, so the ''{{lang|de|Entscheidungsproblem}}'' can also be viewed as asking for an algorithm to decide whether a given statement is provable from the axioms using the [[rules of logic]].

In 1936, [[Alonzo Church]] and [[Alan Turing]] published independent papers&lt;ref&gt;Church's paper was presented to the American Mathematical Society on 19 April 1935 and published on 15 April 1936. Turing, who had made substantial progress in writing up his own results, was disappointed to learn of Church's proof upon its publication (see correspondence between [[Max Newman]] and Church in [http://diglib.princeton.edu/ead/getEad?eadid=C0948&amp;kw= Alonzo Church papers] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100607132453/http://diglib.princeton.edu/ead/getEad?eadid=C0948&amp;kw= |date=7 June 2010 }}). Turing quickly completed his paper and rushed it to publication; it was received by the ''Proceedings of the London Mathematical Society'' on 28 May 1936, read on 12 November 1936, and published in series 2, volume 42 (1936–7); it appeared in two sections: in Part 3 (pages 230–240), issued on Nov 30, 1936 and in Part 4 (pages 241–265), issued on Dec 23, 1936; Turing added corrections in volume 43 (1937), pp. 544–546. See the footnote at the end of Soare: 1996.&lt;/ref&gt; showing that a general solution to the ''{{lang|de|Entscheidungsproblem}}'' is impossible, assuming that the intuitive notion of &quot;[[effectively calculable]]&quot; is captured by the functions computable by a [[Turing machine]] (or equivalently, by those expressible in the [[lambda calculus]]). This assumption is now known as the [[Church–Turing thesis]].

== History of the problem ==
The origin of the ''{{lang|de|Entscheidungsproblem}}'' goes back to [[Gottfried Leibniz]], who in the seventeenth century, after having constructed a successful mechanical [[calculating machine]], dreamt of building a machine that could manipulate symbols in order to determine the [[truth value]]s of mathematical statements.&lt;ref&gt;Davis 2000: pp.&amp;nbsp;3–20&lt;/ref&gt;  He realized that the first step would have to be a clean [[formal language]], and much of his subsequent work was directed towards that goal.  In 1928, [[David Hilbert]] and [[Wilhelm Ackermann]] posed the question in the form outlined above.

In continuation of his &quot;program&quot;, Hilbert posed three questions at an international conference in 1928,  the third of which became known as &quot;Hilbert's ''{{lang|de|Entscheidungsproblem}}''.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Hodges p.&amp;nbsp;91&lt;/ref&gt; In 1929, [[Moses Schönfinkel]] published one paper on special cases of the decision problem, that was prepared by [[Paul Bernays]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Kline&quot;&gt;{{Citation | first=G. L. | last=Kline | title=Review of Foundations of mathematics and mathematical logic by S. A. Yanovskaya | journal=[[Journal of Symbolic Logic]] | volume=16 | pages=46–48 | year=1951 | doi=10.2307/2268665 | jstor=2268665 | issue=1 | last2=Anovskaa | first2=S. A.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As late as 1930, Hilbert believed that there would be no such thing as an unsolvable problem.&lt;ref&gt;Hodges p.&amp;nbsp;92, quoting from Hilbert&lt;/ref&gt;

== Negative answer ==
Before the question could be answered, the notion of &quot;algorithm&quot; had to be formally defined.  This was done by [[Alonzo Church]] in 1935 with the concept of &quot;effective calculability&quot; based on his [[lambda calculus|λ-calculus]] and by Alan Turing the next year with his concept of [[Turing machine]]s.  Turing  immediately recognized that these are equivalent [[model of computation|models of computation]].

The negative answer to the ''{{lang|de|Entscheidungsproblem}}'' was then given by Alonzo Church in 1935–36 and [[multiple discovery|independently]] shortly thereafter by Alan Turing in 1936.  Church proved that there is no [[computable function]] which decides for two given λ-calculus expressions whether they are equivalent or not. He relied heavily on earlier work by [[Stephen Cole Kleene|Stephen Kleene]]. Turing reduced the question of the existence of a 'general method' which decides whether any given Turing Machine halts or not (the [[halting problem]]) to the question of the existence of an 'algorithm' or 'general method' able to solve the ''{{lang|de|Entscheidungsproblem}}''. If 'Algorithm' is understood as being equivalent to a Turing Machine, and with the answer to the latter question negative (in general), the question about the existence of an Algorithm for the ''{{lang|de|Entscheidungsproblem}}'' also must be negative (in general). In his 1936 paper, Turing says: ''&quot;Corresponding to each computing machine 'it' we construct a  formula 'Un(it)' and we show that, if there is a general method for determining whether 'Un(it)' is provable, then there is a general method for determining whether 'it' ever prints 0&quot;''.

The work of both Church and Turing was heavily influenced by [[Kurt Gödel]]'s earlier work on his [[Gödel's incompleteness theorem|incompleteness theorem]], especially by the method of assigning numbers (a [[Gödel numbering]]) to logical formulas in order to reduce logic to arithmetic.

The ''{{lang|de|Entscheidungsproblem}}'' is related to [[Hilbert's tenth problem]], which asks for an [[algorithm]] to decide whether [[Diophantine equation]]s have a solution.  The non-existence of such an algorithm, established by [[Yuri Matiyasevich]] in 1970, also implies a negative answer to the Entscheidungsproblem.

Some first-order theories are algorithmically decidable; examples of this include [[Presburger arithmetic]], [[real closed field]]s and [[Type system#Static typing|static type systems]] of many [[programming language]]s. The general first-order theory of the [[natural number]]s expressed in [[Peano axioms|Peano's axioms]] cannot be decided with an algorithm, however.

==Practical decision procedures==
Having practical decision procedures for classes of logical formulas is of considerable interest for [[program verification]] and circuit verification. Pure Boolean logical formulas are usually decided using [[Boolean satisfiability problem|SAT-solving]] techniques based on the [[DPLL algorithm]]. Conjunctive formulas over linear real or rational arithmetic can be decided using the [[simplex algorithm]], formulas in linear integer arithmetic ([[Presburger arithmetic]]) can be decided using [[Cooper's algorithm]] or [[William Pugh (computer scientist)|William Pugh]]'s [[Omega test]]. Formulas with negations, conjunctions and disjunctions combine the difficulties of satisfiability testing with that of decision of conjunctions; they are generally decided nowadays using [[satisfiability modulo theories|SMT-solving]] techniques, which combine SAT-solving with decision procedures for conjunctions and propagation techniques. Real polynomial arithmetic, also known as the theory of [[real closed field]]s, is decidable; this is the [[Tarski–Seidenberg theorem]], which has been implemented in computers by using the [[cylindrical algebraic decomposition]].

== See also ==
* [[Automated theorem proving]]
* [[Hilbert's second problem]]
* [[Oracle machine]]
* [[Turing's proof]]

== Notes ==
{{Reflist}}

== References ==
* [[David Hilbert]] and [[Wilhelm Ackermann]] (1928). ''Grundzüge der theoretischen Logik'' (''Principles of Mathematical Logic''). Springer-Verlag, {{ISBN|0-8218-2024-9}}.
* [[Alonzo Church]], &quot;An unsolvable problem of [[elementary number theory]]&quot;, American Journal of Mathematics, 58 (1936), pp 345–363
* [[Alonzo Church]], &quot;A note on the Entscheidungsproblem&quot;, Journal of Symbolic Logic, 1 (1936), pp 40–41.
* [[Martin Davis (mathematician)|Martin Davis]], 2000, ''Engines of Logic'', W.W. Norton &amp; Company, London, {{ISBN|0-393-32229-7}} pbk.
* [[Alan Turing]], &quot;[[On Computable Numbers, with an Application to the Entscheidungsproblem]]&quot;, Proceedings of the [[London Mathematical Society]], Series 2, 42 (1936–7), pp 230–265. Online versions: [http://plms.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/reprint/s2-42/1/230 from journal website], [http://www.turingarchive.org/browse.php/B/12 from Turing Digital Archive], [http://www.abelard.org/turpap2/tp2-ie.asp from abelard.org].  Errata appeared in Series 2, 43 (1937), pp 544–546.
* [[Martin Davis (mathematician)|Martin Davis]], &quot;The Undecidable, Basic Papers on Undecidable Propositions, Unsolvable Problems And Computable Functions&quot;, Raven Press, New York, 1965. Turing's paper is #3 in this volume. Papers include those by Gödel, Church, Rosser, Kleene, and Post.
* [[Andrew Hodges]], [[Alan Turing: The Enigma]], [[Simon and Schuster]], New York, 1983. Alan M. Turing's biography. Cf Chapter &quot;The Spirit of Truth&quot; for a history leading to, and a discussion of, his proof.
* [[Robert Soare]], &quot;Computability and recursion&quot;, Bull. Symbolic Logic 2 (1996), no. 3, 284–321. 
* [[Stephen Toulmin]], &quot;Fall of a Genius&quot;, a book review of &quot;[[Alan Turing: The Enigma]] by Andrew Hodges&quot;, in The New York Review of Books, 19 January 1984, p.&amp;nbsp;3ff.
* [[Alfred North Whitehead]] and [[Bertrand Russell]], Principia Mathematica to *56, Cambridge at the University Press, 1962. Re: the problem of paradoxes, the authors discuss the problem of a set not be an object in any of its &quot;determining functions&quot;, in particular &quot;Introduction, Chap. 1 p. 24 &quot;...difficulties which arise in formal logic&quot;, and Chap. 2.I. &quot;The Vicious-Circle Principle&quot; p.&amp;nbsp;37ff, and Chap. 2.VIII. &quot;The Contradictions&quot; p.&amp;nbsp;60 ff.

==External links==
* {{wiktionary-inline}}

{{Mathematical logic}}
{{Metalogic}}

[[Category:Theory of computation]]
[[Category:Computability theory]]
[[Category:Gottfried Leibniz]]
[[Category:Mathematical logic]]
[[Category:Metatheorems]]
[[Category:Undecidable problems]]</text>
      <sha1>41qljrrzxvs66kujxlt10fzcifhm5cc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
