  <page>
    <title>Einhard</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9674</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939143931</id>
      <parentid>939143382</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-04T17:10:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Serols</username>
        <id>9929111</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/173.251.75.215|173.251.75.215]] ([[User talk:173.251.75.215|talk]]) ([[WP:HG|HG]]) (3.4.9)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[File:Éginhard Vita Caroli magni imperatoris-Lettrine V historiée Charlemagne assis.jpg|thumb|Einhard as scribe. Manuscript depiction from 1050]]

'''Einhard''' (also '''Eginhard''' or '''Einhart'''; {{lang-la|E(g)inhardus}}; {{circa}} 775 – March 14, 840) was a [[Franks|Frankish]] scholar and courtier. Einhard was a dedicated servant of [[Charlemagne]] and his son [[Louis the Pious]]; his main work is a biography of Charlemagne, the ''[[Vita Karoli Magni]]'', &quot;one of the most precious literary bequests of the early Middle Ages.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Hodgkin 222.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Public life==
Einhard was from the eastern [[German language|German-speaking]] part of the [[Francia|Frankish Kingdom]]. Born into a family of landowners of some importance, his parents sent him to be educated by the monks of [[Fulda]], one of the most impressive centers of learning in the Frank lands. Perhaps due to his small stature, which restricted his riding and sword-fighting ability, Einhard concentrated his energies on scholarship, especially the mastering of [[Latin]].&lt;ref&gt;Smith 62&lt;/ref&gt; He was accepted into the hugely wealthy court of Charlemagne around 791 or 792. Charlemagne actively sought to amass [[scholar]]ly men around him and established a royal school led by the [[Northumbria]]n scholar [[Alcuin]]. Einhard evidently was a talented builder and [[construction]] manager, because Charlemagne put him in charge of the completion of several [[palace]] complexes including [[Charlemagne's Palace in Aachen|Aachen]] and [[Imperial Palace Ingelheim|Ingelheim]]. Despite the fact that Einhard was on intimate terms with Charlemagne, he never achieved office in his [[reign]]. In 814, on Charlemagne's death, his son [[Louis the Pious]] made Einhard his private [[secretary]]. Einhard retired from [[Noble court|court]] during the time of the disputes between Louis and his sons in the spring of 830.

He died at [[Seligenstadt]] in 840.

==Private life==
Einhard was married to Emma, of whom little is known. There is a possibility that their marriage bore a son, Vussin. Their marriage also appears to have been exceptionally liberal for the period, with Emma being as active as Einhard, if not more so, in the handling of their property.&lt;ref&gt;Smith 58.&lt;/ref&gt; It is said that in the later years of their marriage Emma and Einhard abstained from sexual relations, choosing instead to focus their attentions on their many religious commitments. Though he was undoubtedly devoted to her, Einhard wrote nothing of his wife until after her death on 13 December 835, when he wrote to a friend that he was reminded of her loss in ‘every day, in every action, in every undertaking, in all the administration of the house and household, in everything needing to be decided upon and sorted out in my religious and earthly responsibilities’.&lt;ref&gt;From Einhard’s letter of April 836 to Lupus of Ferrieres. Qtd. in Smith 55.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Denkmal Einhard Eschweiler.jpg|thumb|Einhard memorial in the German city of [[Eschweiler]]]]

==Religious beliefs==
Einhard made numerous references to himself as a &quot;sinner&quot; according to his strong Christian faith.&lt;ref&gt;Smith 60-61.&lt;/ref&gt; He erected churches at both of his estates in Michelstadt and Mulinheim. In Michelstadt, he also saw fit to build a basilica completed in 827 and then sent a servant, Ratleic, to Rome with an end to find relics for the new building. Once in Rome, Ratleic robbed a catacomb of the bones of the Martyrs [[Marcellinus and Peter]] and had them translated to Michelstadt. Once there, the relics made it known they were unhappy with their new tomb and thus had to be moved again to Mulinheim. Once established there, they proved to be miracle workers. Although unsure as to why these saints should choose such a &quot;sinner&quot; as their patron, Einhard nonetheless set about ensuring they continued to receive a resting place fitting of their honour.&lt;ref&gt;Smith 67.&lt;/ref&gt;  Between 831 and 834 he founded a Benedictine Monastery and, after the death of his wife, served as its Abbot until his own death in 840.

==Local lore==
Local lore from Seligenstadt portrays Einhard as the lover of Emma, one of [[Charlemagne]]'s daughters, and has the couple elope from court. Charlemagne found them at Seligenstadt (then called Obermühlheim) and forgave them. This account is used to explain the name &quot;Seligenstadt&quot; by [[folk etymology]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Der hessische Spessart&quot; par. 4.&lt;/ref&gt; Einhard and his wife were originally buried in one sarcophagus in the choir of the church in Seligenstadt, but in 1810 the sarcophagus was presented by the Grand Duke of Hesse to the count of Erbach, who claims descent from Einhard as the husband of Imma, the reputed daughter of Charlemagne. The count put it in the famous chapel of his castle at Erbach in the Odenwald.&lt;ref&gt;Schaff par. 164.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Works==
The most famous of Einhard's works is his [[biography]] of Charlemagne, the ''[[Vita Karoli Magni]]'', &quot;The Life of Charlemagne&quot; (c. 817–836), which provides much direct information about Charlemagne's life and character, written sometime between 817 and 830. In composing this he relied heavily upon the [[Royal Frankish Annals]]. Einhard's literary model was the classical work of the Roman historian [[Suetonius]], the ''[[Lives of the Twelve Caesars|Lives of the Caesars]]'', though it is important to stress that the work is very much Einhard's own, that is to say he adapts the models and sources for his own purposes. His work was written as a praise of Charlemagne, whom he regarded as a foster-father (''nutritor'') and to whom he was a debtor &quot;in life and death&quot;. The work thus contains an understandable degree of bias, Einhard taking care to exculpate Charlemagne in some matters, not mention others, and to gloss over certain issues which would be of embarrassment to Charlemagne, such as the morality of his daughters; by contrast, other issues are curiously not glossed over, like his concubines.

Einhard is also responsible for three other extant works: a collection of letters, ''On the Translations and the Miracles of SS. Marcellinus and Petrus'', and ''On the Adoration of the Cross''.&lt;ref&gt;Thorpe.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Müller 252.&lt;/ref&gt; The latter dates from ca. 830 and was not rediscovered until 1885,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Einhard ca. 770-840&quot; par. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; when [[Ernst Dümmler]] identified a text in a manuscript in [[Vienna]] as the missing ''Libellus de adoranda cruce'',&lt;ref&gt;Dümmler.&lt;/ref&gt; which Einhard had dedicated to his pupil [[Lupus Servatus]].&lt;ref&gt;Levison 271.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stofferahn par. 10.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Royal Frankish Annals]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite news|url=http://www.hr-online.de/website/rubriken/freizeit/index.jsp?rubrik=7480&amp;key=standard_document_914328&amp;seite=1|title=Der hessische Spessart|publisher=HR Online|language=German|accessdate=25 March 2010}}{{Dead link|date=August 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}
* {{cite journal|last=Dümmler|first=Ernst|year=1885|title=Ein Nachtrag zu Einhards Werken|journal=[[Neues Archiv der Gesellschaft für ältere deutsche Geschichtskunde]]|volume=11|pages=231–38|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=QgQOAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA281|accessdate=25 March 2010}}
* {{cite web|url=http://www.enotes.com/classical-medieval-criticism/einhard|title=Einhard c. 770-840|publisher=Enotes|accessdate=25 March 2010}}
* {{cite book | last = Hodgkin | first = T. | authorlink = Thomas Hodgkin (historian) | title = Charles the Great | publisher = Macmillan | year = 1897 | location = London | pages = | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=PivfxsqPousC}}
* {{cite book|last=Levison|first=Wilhelm|author2=Wilhelm Wattenbach |author3=Rudolf Buchner |title=Deutschlands Geschichtsquellen im Mittelalter, Vorzeit und Karolinger: Heft. Die Karolinger vom Anfang des 8. Jahrhunderts bis zum Tode Karis des Grossen|publisher=H. Böhlaus Nachfolger|year=1952|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Yi7TAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=%22Libellus+de+adoranda+cruce%22+1885&amp;dq=%22Libellus+de+adoranda+cruce%22+1885|accessdate=25 March 2010|language=German}}
* {{cite book|last=Müller|first=Bianca|title=Persönlichkeit Karl des Großen nach Einhards Vita Karoli Magni|publisher=GRIN Verlag|year=2009|isbn=978-3-640-47253-6|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=4X1V8S2ajkgC&amp;pg=PA4&amp;lpg=PA4}}
* {{cite book|last=Schaff|first=Philip|title=History of the Christian Church|volume=IV: Mediaeval Christianity. A.D. 590-1073.|chapter=&quot;Einhard&quot;|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/hcc4.i.xiv.xxiii.html|accessdate=25 March 2010}}
* {{cite journal|last=Smith|first=Julia|date=March 2003|title=Einhard|journal=[[Transactions of the Royal Historical Society]]|pages=55–77}}
* {{cite journal|last=Stofferahn|first=Steven A.|year=2010|title=Knowledge for Its Own Sake? A Practical Humanist in the Carolingian Age|journal=[[The Heroic Age (journal)|The Heroic Age]]|volume=13|url=http://www.heroicage.org/|accessdate=25 March 2010}}
* Tischler, Matthias M. (2001) [https://www.amazon.de/Einharts-Vita-Karoli-Entstehung-%C3%9Cberlieferung/dp/377525448X ''Einharts Vita Karoli. Studien zur Entstehung, Überlieferung und Rezeption''] (MGH. Schriften 48, I–II), Hanover: Hahn. {{ISBN|3-7752-5448-X}}.
* {{cite book|last=Thorpe|first=Lewis G.M.|title=Einhard and Notker the Stammerer: two lives of Charlemagne|publisher=Penguin|location=London|year=1969|isbn=978-0-14-044213-7|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=L7Rf2PsyvowC&amp;pg=PP3|accessdate=25 March 2010}}
* {{cite book|last=Noble|first=Thomas F.X.|title=Charlemagne and Louis the Pious: Lives by Einhard, Notker, Ermoldus, Thegan, and the Astronomer|publisher=Penn State Press|location=|year=2009|isbn=978-0-27-103715-8|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=BGY3UiD92YMC&amp;dq=|accessdate=25 July 2012}}
* {{cite book|last=Chiesa|first=Paolo (ed.)|title=Eginardo, Vita Karoli|publisher=Edizioni del Galluzzo|location=Firenze|year=2014|isbn=978-88-8450-537-8}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Einhard}}
{{Wikisource|Author:Einhard|Einhard}}
* {{Gutenberg author|id=45007}}
* [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/05366b.htm Einhard] at the [[Catholic Encyclopedia]]
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Einhard}}
* {{Librivox author |id=4225}}
* [http://www.thelatinlibrary.com/ein.html ''Vita Karoli Magni'']—Einhard's ''Life of Charlemagne,'' Latin text at [[The Latin Library]]
* {{Gutenberg|no=48870 |name=Life of Charlemagne |author = Einhard}}, translated by {{cite book | last = Grant | first = A.J. | authorlink = | title = Early lives of Charlemagne by Eginhard and the Monk of St Gall | publisher = Moring | year = 1905 | location = London |url = https://archive.org/details/earlylivesofchar00einh }}
* [http://www.einhardpreis.de Einhard-Preis] Literature prize awarded by the Einhard-Foundation of Seligenstadt to authors for writing an outstanding biography
* [http://www.documentacatholicaomnia.eu/30_10_0770-0840-_Eginhardus_(Einhardus).html Opera Omnia by Migne Patrologia Latina with analytical indexes]
* {{DNB-Portal|118529560}}
* {{Geschichtsquellen Person|118529560|Einhardus}}
* [http://www.fh-augsburg.de/~harsch/egiv0.html Einhardi vita Karoli Magni] in [[Bibliotheca Augustana]]
* [http://www.geschichte-untermain.de/f_einhardweg.html The Einhard Way from Michelstadt to Seligenstadt]
* [http://www.einhardpreis.de/ Home page of the Einhard Foundation at Seligenstadt]
* [http://www.einhard-gesellschaft-seligenstadt.de/ Home page of the Einhard Society, Seligenstadt]

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:775 births]]
[[Category:840 deaths]]
[[Category:9th-century Latin writers]]
[[Category:Frankish historians]]
[[Category:Charlemagne]]
[[Category:9th-century historians]]
[[Category:Writers of the Carolingian Empire]]
[[Category:9th-century astronomers]]</text>
      <sha1>oln8v48l3ao903w10jntjun01q20ybw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
