  <page>
    <title>Epistle of Jude</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9689</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941510007</id>
      <parentid>941184230</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-19T00:39:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Editor2020</username>
        <id>6046894</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */ alphabetical order</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Book of the Bible}}
{{distinguish|Gospel of Judas}}
{{Books of the New Testament}}
The '''Epistle of Jude''', often shortened to '''Jude''', is the penultimate book of the [[New Testament]] and the [[Bible]] as a whole and is traditionally attributed to [[Jude (brother of Jesus)|Jude]], the servant of Jesus and the brother of [[James the Just]].

== Composition ==
The letter of Jude was one of the disputed books of the [[biblical canon]].&lt;ref&gt;Eusebius, ''Church History'' 2 23&lt;/ref&gt;  The links between the Epistle and [[2 Peter]], its use of the [[biblical apocrypha]], and its brevity raised concern. It is one of the shortest books in the Bible: only [[Chapters and verses of the Bible|1 chapter of 25 verses]] long.
[[File:P078-Jud-1 4-5-POxy2684-III-IV.jpg|thumb|left|150px|[[Papyrus 78]], containing the Epistle of Jude verses 4, 5, 7 and 8. Dated to the 3rd or 4th century.]]
[[File:Colophon Alexandrinus Jude.JPG|thumb|left|150px|Colophon at the Epistle of Jude in the [[Codex Alexandrinus]]]]

===Textual witnesses===
Some early manuscripts containing the text of this epistle are:{{sfn|Robinson|2017|p=12}}
*[[Papyrus 72]] (3rd/4th century)
*[[Papyrus 78]] (3rd/4th century; extant verses 4-5, 7-8)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
 | last = Aland
 | first = Kurt
 | authorlink = Kurt Aland
 | last2 = Aland
 | first2 = Barbara
 | authorlink2 = Barbara Aland
 | others = Erroll F. Rhodes (trans.)
 | title = The Text of the New Testament: An Introduction to the Critical Editions and to the Theory and Practice of Modern Textual Criticism
 | publisher = [[William B. Eerdmans Publishing Company]]
 | year = 1995
 | location = Grand Rapids
 | page = 101
 | url =https://books.google.com/books?id=2pYDsAhUOxAC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false
 | isbn = 978-0-8028-4098-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Codex Vaticanus]] ('''B''' or '''03'''; 325-350)
*[[Codex Sinaiticus]] ('''{{lang|he|א}}''' or '''01'''; 330–360)
*[[Codex Alexandrinus]] ('''A''' or '''02'''; 400–440)
*[[Codex Ephraemi Rescriptus]] ('''C''' or '''04'''; c. 450; extant verses 3–25)&lt;ref&gt;[[Eberhard Nestle]], [[Erwin Nestle]], Barbara Aland and [[Kurt Aland]] (eds), ''[[Novum Testamentum Graece]]'', 26th edition, (Stuttgart: ''[[Deutsche Bibelgesellschaft]]'', 1991), p. 689.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Content ==
Jude urges his readers to defend the deposit of Christ's doctrine that had been closed by the time he wrote his epistle, and to remember the words of the apostles spoken somewhat before. Jude then asks the reader to recall how even after the Lord saved his own people out of the land of Egypt, he did not hesitate to destroy those who fell into unbelief, much as he punished the angels who fell from their original exalted status and Sodom and Gomorrah.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|Jude|1:5-7|9|Jude 5–7}}&lt;/ref&gt; He describes in vivid terms the apostates of his day.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|Jude|1:8-16|9|Jude 8–16}}&lt;/ref&gt; He exhorts believers to remember the words spoken by the Apostles, using language similar to the second epistle of Peter to answer concerns that the Lord seemed to tarry, ''How that they told you there should be mockers in the last time, who should walk after their own ungodly lusts...'',&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|Jude|1:18|9|Jude 18}}&lt;/ref&gt; and to keep themselves in God's love,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|Jude|1:21|9|Jude 21}}&lt;/ref&gt; before delivering a doxology.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|Jude|1:24-25|9|Jude 24–25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Jude quotes directly from the [[Book of Enoch]], part of the scripture of the [[Ethiopian Orthodox Church|Ethiopian]] and [[Eritrean Orthodox Tewahedo Church|Eritrean church]]es but rejected by other churches. He cites Enoch's prophecy that the Lord would come with many thousands of his saints to render judgment on the whole world.  He also paraphrases (verse 9) an incident in a text that has been lost about [[Satan]] and [[Michael (archangel)|Michael the Archangel]] quarreling over the body of Moses.

===Outline===

I. Salutation (1–3)

II. Occasion for the Letter (3–4)&lt;br&gt;
&amp;nbsp; A. The change of Subject (3) &lt;br&gt;
&amp;nbsp; B. The Reason for the Change: The Presence of Godless Apostates (4)

III. Warning against the False Teachers (5–16)&lt;br&gt;
&amp;nbsp; A. Historical Examples of the Judgement of Apostates (5–7) &lt;br&gt;
&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;  1. Unbelieving Israel (5) &lt;br&gt;
&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;  2. Angels who fell (6) &lt;br&gt;
&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;  3. Sodom and Gomorrah (7) &lt;br&gt;
&amp;nbsp; B. Description of the Apostates of Jude's Day (8–16)&lt;br&gt;
&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   1. Their slanderous speech deplored (8–10) &lt;br&gt;
&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   2. Their character graphically portrayed (11–13) &lt;br&gt;
&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;   3. Their destruction prophesied (14–16)

IV. Exhortation to Believers (17–23)

V. Concluding Doxology (24–25)&lt;ref&gt;NIV Bible (Large Print ed.). (2007). London: Hodder &amp; Stoughton Ltd&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Canonical status ===
The Epistle of Jude is held as canonical in the [[Christian Church]]. Conservative scholars date it between 70 and 90. Some scholars consider the letter a [[pseudonym]]ous work written between the end of the 1st century and the first quarter of the 2nd century because of its references to the [[apostles]]&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|Jude|1:17-18|9|Jude 17–18}}&lt;/ref&gt; and to tradition&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|Jude|1:3|9|Jude 3}}&lt;/ref&gt; and because of its competent Greek style.&lt;ref name=&quot;NAB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usccb.org/nab/bible/jude/jude.htm|title=scripture|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Norman Perrin, (1974) ''The New Testament: An Introduction'', p. 260&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bauckham, RJ (1986), [[Word Biblical Commentary]], Vol.50, Word (UK) Ltd. p.16&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;More remarkable is the evidence that by the end of the second century Jude was widely accepted as canonical.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bauckham, RJ (1986), [[Word Biblical Commentary]], Vol.50, Word (UK) Ltd. p.17&lt;/ref&gt; [[Clement of Alexandria]], [[Tertullian]], and the [[Muratorian fragment|Muratorian canon]] considered the letter canonical. The first historical record of doubts as to authorship are found in the writings of [[Origen of Alexandria]], who spoke of the doubts held by some, albeit not him. [[Eusebius of Caesarea|Eusebius]] classified it with the &quot;disputed writings, the ''[[antilegomena]].''&quot; The letter was eventually accepted as part of the Canon by [[Church Fathers]] such as [[Athanasius]]&lt;ref&gt;Lindberg, Carter (2006). ''A Brief History of Christianity''. Blackwell Publishing. p. 15. {{ISBN|1-4051-1078-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Synod of Laodicea|Synods of Laodicea]] (c. 363)&lt;ref&gt;Council of Laodicea at bible-researcher.com. Retrieved 2011-10-05.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Council of Carthage (397)|Carthage (397)]].&lt;ref&gt;B. F. Westcott, ''A General Survey of the History of the Canon of the New Testament'' (5th ed. Edinburgh, 1881), pp. 440, 541–2.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Authorship ===
The epistle title is written as follows: &quot;Jude, a servant of [[Jesus]] Christ and brother of James&quot; ([[New Revised Standard Version|NRSV]]). &quot;James&quot; is generally taken to mean [[James the Just]], a prominent leader in the early church. Not a lot is known of Jude, which would explain the apparent need to identify him by reference to his better-known brother.&lt;ref name=&quot;NAB&quot;/&gt;

As the brother of James the Just, it has traditionally meant Jude was also the brother of Jesus, since James is described as being the brother of Jesus. For instance [[Clement of Alexandria]] (c.&amp;nbsp;150–215 AD) wrote in his work ''&quot;Comments on the Epistle of Jude&quot;'' that Jude, the Epistle of Jude's author, was a son of Joseph and a brother of Jesus (without specifying whether he was a son of Joseph by a previous marriage or of Joseph and Mary).&lt;ref&gt;''&quot;Jude wrote the Catholic Epistle, the brother of the sons of Joseph, and very religious, while knowing the near relationship of the Lord, yet did not say that he himself was His brother. But what said he? &quot;Jude, a servant of Jesus Christ,&quot;— of Him as Lord; but &quot;the brother of James.&quot; For this is true; he was His brother, (the son) of Joseph.&quot;''{{cite book|last1=of Alexandria|first1=Clement|title=Comments on the Epistle of Jude.|website=newadvent.org|url=http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/0211.htm|accessdate=24 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There is also a dispute as to whether &quot;brother&quot; means someone who has the same father and mother, or a half-brother or cousin or more distant familial relationship. This dispute over the true meaning of &quot;brother&quot; grew as the [[Virgin birth of Jesus|doctrine of the Virgin Birth]] evolved.&lt;ref&gt;Jocelyn Rhys, ''Shaken Creeds: The Virgin Birth Doctrine: A Study of Its Origin'', Kessinger Publishing (reprint), 2003 [1922] {{ISBN|0-7661-7988-5}}, pp 3–53&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Chester, A and Martin, RP (1994), 'The Theology of the Letters of James, Peter and Jude', CUP, p.65&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bauckham, R. J. (1986), [[Word Biblical Commentary]], Vol.50, Word (UK) Ltd. p.14&lt;/ref&gt;

Outside the book of Jude, a &quot;Jude&quot; is mentioned five times in the New Testament: three times as [[Jude the Apostle]] (Luke 6:16, Acts 1:13, John 14:22), and twice as [[Jude, brother of Jesus|Jude the brother of Jesus]] (Matthew 13:55, Mark 6:3) (aside from references to [[Judas Iscariot]] and [[Judah (son of Jacob)]]). Debate continues as to whether the author of the epistle is either, both, or neither. Some scholars have argued that since the author of the letter has not identified himself as an apostle and actually refers to the apostles as a third party, he cannot be identified with Jude the Apostle. Others have drawn the opposite conclusion, i.e., that, as an apostle, he would not have made a claim of apostleship on his own behalf.&lt;ref&gt;Bauckham, R. J. (1986), [[Word Biblical Commentary]], Vol.50, Word (UK) Ltd. p.14f&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Style ===
The Epistle of Jude is a brief book of only a single chapter with 25 verses. It was composed as an ''[[encyclical]] letter''—that is, one not directed to the members of one church in particular, but intended rather to be circulated and read in all churches.

The wording and syntax of this epistle in its original Greek demonstrates that the author was capable and fluent. The epistle is addressed to Christians in general,&lt;ref&gt;Jude 1:1&lt;/ref&gt; and it warns them about the doctrine of certain errant teachers to whom they were exposed.

The epistle's style is combative, impassioned, and rushed. Many examples of evildoers and warnings about their fates are given in rapid succession.

The epistle concludes with a [[doxology]], which is considered by [[Peter H. Davids]] to be one of the highest in quality contained in the Bible.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Davids|first1=Peter H.|title=The Pillar New Testament Commentary: The Letters of 2 Peter and Jude|date=2006|publisher=Wm. B. Eardmans Publishing Co.|location=Grand Rapids, Michigan|page=106&lt;!--|accessdate=29 November 2016--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Jude and 2 Peter ==
Part of Jude is very similar to [[2 Peter]] (mainly [[2 Peter 2|2 Peter chapter 2]]), so much so that most scholars agree that there is a dependence between the two, i.e., that either one letter used the other directly, or they both drew on a common source.&lt;ref&gt;''Introduction to 2 Peter'' in ''Expositor's Bible Commentary'', Ed. F. E. Gaebelein, Zondervan 1976–1992&lt;/ref&gt; Comparing the Greek text portions of 2 Peter 2:1–3:3 (426 words) to Jude 4–18 (311 words) results in 80 words in common and 7 words of substituted synonyms.{{sfn|Callan|2004|p=43}}

The shared passages are:{{sfn|Robinson|2017|p=10}}
{|class=wikitable
! 2 Peter !! Jude 
|-
|1:5 || 3
|-
|1:12 || 5
|-
|2:1 || 4
|-
|2:4 || 6
|-
|2:6 || 7
|-
|2:10–11 || 8–9
|-
|2:12 || 10
|-
|2:13–17 || 11–13
|-
|3:2-3 || 17-18
|-
|3:14 || 24
|-
|3:18 || 25
|-
|}

Because this epistle is much shorter than 2 Peter, and due to various stylistic details, some writers consider Jude the source for the similar passages of 2 Peter.&lt;ref&gt;e.g. Callan 2004, pp. 42–64.&lt;/ref&gt; However, other writers, arguing that Jude 18 quotes [[2 Peter 3:3]] as past tense, consider Jude to have come after 2 Peter.&lt;ref&gt;e.g. John MacArthur ''1, 2, 3, John Jude'' 2007 p101 &quot;...closely parallels that of 2 Peter (2:1–3:4), and it is believed that Peter's writing predated Jude for several reasons: (1) Second Peter anticipates the coming of false teachers (2 Peter 2:1–2; 3:3), whereas Jude deals with their arrival (verses 4, 11–12, 17–18); and (2) Jude quotes directly from 2 Peter 3:3 and acknowledges that it is from an apostle (verses 17–18).&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Some scholars who consider Jude to predate 2 Peter note that the latter appears to quote the former but omits the reference to the non-canonical book of Enoch.&lt;ref&gt;[[Dale Martin]] 2009 (lecture). [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XJ9Gt_R5a-k &quot;24. Apocalyptic and Accommodation&quot;]. [[Yale University]]. Accessed July 22, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

== References to other books ==
[[File:Judas9.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Jude 9 on [[Codex Sinaiticus]] (c. 330-360)]]
The Epistle of Jude references at least two other books, with one being non-canonical in all churches and the other non-canonical in most churches.

{{anchor|Moses}}'''Verse 9''' refers to a dispute between [[Michael (archangel)|Michael the Archangel]] and the [[devil]] about the body of [[Moses]]. Some interpreters understand this reference to be an allusion to the events described in {{bibleverse|Zechariah|3:1–2|KJV}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;DavidsMoo2016&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Peter H. Davids|author2=Douglas J. Moo|author3=Robert Yarbrough|title=1 and 2 Peter, Jude, 1, 2, and 3 John|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=opOGCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT240|date=5 April 2016|publisher=Zondervan|isbn=978-0-310-53025-1|page=240}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LucasGreen2014&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=R. C. Lucas|author2=Christopher Green|title=The Message of 2 Peter &amp; Jude|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sbadAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT168|date=2 May 2014|publisher=InterVarsity Press|isbn=978-0-8308-9784-1|pages=168–}}&lt;/ref&gt; The classical theologian [[Origen]] attributes this reference to the non-canonical [[Assumption of Moses]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/anf04.vi.v.iv.iv.html|title=ANF04. Fathers of the Third Century: Tertullian, Part Fourth; Minucius Felix; Commodian; Origen, Parts First and Second|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[James Charlesworth]], there is no evidence the surviving book of this name ever contained any such content.&lt;ref name=&quot;OTP&quot;&gt;James Charlesworth ''Old Testament Pseudepigrapha'', p. 76, [https://books.google.com/books?id=eRQ9AAAAIAAJ&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;dq=James%20Charlesworth&amp;pg=PA76#v=onepage&amp;q=Jude%20Moses&amp;f=false Google books link]&lt;/ref&gt; Others believe it to be in the lost ending of the book.&lt;ref name=&quot;OTP&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Assumption of Moses: a critical edition with commentary By Johannes Tromp. P270&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Verses 14–15''' contain a direct quotation of a prophecy from 1 Enoch 1:9. The title &quot;Enoch, the seventh from Adam&quot; is also sourced from 1 En. 60:1. Most commentators assume that this indicates that Jude accepts the [[antediluvian]] patriarch [[Enoch (ancestor of Noah)|Enoch]] as the author of the [[Book of Enoch]] which contains the same quotation. However, an alternative explanation is that Jude quotes the Book of Enoch aware that verses 14–15 are in fact an expansion of the words of Moses from Deuteronomy 33:2.&lt;ref&gt;Charles R. ''Enoch'' OUP, p. 119&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Nickelsburg G. ''1 Enoch'' Fortress&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cox S. [http://www.christadelphia.org/pamphlet/p_sinned.htm ''Slandering celestial beings'']&lt;/ref&gt; This is supported by Jude's unusual Greek statement that &quot;Enoch the Seventh from Adam prophesied ''to'' the false teachers&quot;, not ''concerning'' them.&lt;ref&gt;AUTOI dative&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Book of Enoch]] is not considered canonical by most churches, although it is by the [[Ethiopian Orthodox]] church.  According to Western scholars, the older sections of the Book of Enoch (mainly in the ''Book of the Watchers'') date from about 300 BC and the latest part (''Book of Parables'') probably was composed at the end of the 1st century BC.&lt;ref&gt;Fahlbusch E., Bromiley G. W. ''The Encyclopedia of Christianity: P-Sh'' page 411, {{ISBN|0-8028-2416-1}} (2004)&lt;/ref&gt; 1 Enoch 1:9, mentioned above, is part of the [[pseudepigrapha]] and is among the Dead Sea Scrolls [4Q Enoch (4Q204[4QENAR]) COL I 16–18].&lt;ref&gt;Clontz, T. E. and J., ''The Comprehensive New Testament with complete textual variant mapping and references for the Dead Sea Scrolls, Philo, Josephus, Nag Hammadi Library, Pseudepigrapha, Apocrypha, Plato, Egyptian Book of the Dead, Talmud, Old Testament, Patristic Writings, Dhammapada, Tacitus, Epic of Gilgamesh'', Cornerstone Publications, 2008, p.711, {{ISBN|978-0-9778737-1-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is generally accepted by scholars that the author of the Epistle of Jude was familiar with the Book of Enoch and was influenced by it in thought and diction.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Apocalyptic Literature&quot; (column 220), ''[[Encyclopedia Biblica]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Oiketerion]] ({{bibleverse||Jude|1:6}})
* [[Textual variants in the New Testament#Epistle of Jude|Textual variants in the Epistle of Jude]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist}}

==Sources==
*{{cite journal|last= Callan |first= Terrance |title= Use of the Letter of Jude by the Second Letter of Peter |journal= Biblica |volume= 85 |year= 2004| pages= 42-64 | url= https://www.bsw.org/biblica/vol-85-2004/use-of-the-letter-of-jude-by-the-second-letter-of-peter/156/ }}
*{{cite book  | last= Robinson  | first= Alexandra |title=Jude on the Attack: A Comparative Analysis of the Epistle of Jude, Jewish Judgement Oracles, and Greco-Roman Invective| series=The Library of New Testament Studies |publisher= Bloomsbury Publishing | year= 2017 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=M_lBDwAAQBAJ |isbn = 978- 0567678799}}

==Further reading==
{{Cite web|url=https://www.academia.edu/34452183/Canonical_Exclusion_or_Embrace_The_Use_of_Enoch_in_the_Epistle_of_Jude|title=Canonical Exclusion or Embrace? The Use of Enoch in the Epistle of Jude|last=Vela|first=Tyler|date=2017|website=Academia.edu|language=en|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}

== External links ==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Wikisource|Jude (Bible)|Jude}}

Online translations of the Epistle of Jude:
* [http://www.usccb.org/nab/bible/jude/jude.htm Jude in New American Bible]
* [http://www.gospelhall.org/bible/bible.php?passage=Jude+1 ''Online Bible'' at GospelHall.org]
* [http://www.biblegateway.com/cgi-bin/bible?language=english&amp;version=NIV&amp;passage=Jude Jude at Bible Gateway] (various versions)
* [http://www.earlychristianwritings.com/jude.html Early Christian writings: ''Epistle of Jude:'' comparable translations and interpretations]
Audiobook Version:
* {{librivox book | dtitle=Jude | stitle=Bible Jude}}

Additional information:
* [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/08542b.htm Catholic Encyclopedia]
* [http://www.watton.org/studies&amp;stories/jude/index.htm Comprehensive study the Epistle of Jude]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070614184904/http://www.wlsessays.net/authors/PQ/QuandtJude/QuandtJude.PDF An Exegesis of Jude by Michael Quandt]
{{s-start}}
{{s-hou|[[General epistles|General]] [[Epistles|Epistle]]|||}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Third Epistle of John|Third John]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=&lt;small&gt;[[New Testament]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Books of the Bible]]}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Book of Revelation|Revelation]]}}
{{s-end}}
{{Books of the Bible}}
{{Authority control}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Epistle Of Jude}}
[[Category:New Testament books|Jude]]
[[Category:Canonical epistles|Jude]]
[[Category:Luther's Antilegomena]]
[[Category:Epistle of Jude| ]]</text>
      <sha1>kgmrxkuilgx0nn8cu5gu42kujxw24mv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
