  <page>
    <title>Entorhinal cortex</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9667</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938794722</id>
      <parentid>930054123</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-02T11:06:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tony1</username>
        <id>332841</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Part of the brain's cerebral cortex}}{{Infobox brain
| Name            = Entorhinal cortex
| Pronunciation = ɛntəɹ'ɪnəl
| Latin           = Cortex entorhinalis
| Image           = Gray-Brodman-Entorhinal Cortex EC .png
| Caption         = Medial surface. (Entorhinal cortex approximately maps to areas 28 and 34, at lower left.)
| Image2          = Medial surface of cerebral cortex - entorhinal cortex.png
| Caption2        = Medial surface of right hemisphere. Entorhinal cortex visible at near bottom.
| Width           = 300
| IsPartOf        = [[Temporal lobe]]
| Components      =
| Artery          = [[Posterior cerebral artery|Posterior cerebral]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Choroid artery|Choroid]]
| Vein            = [[Inferior striate vein|Inferior striate]]
}}
The '''entorhinal cortex''' ('''EC''')  is an area of the [[brain]] located in the [[medial temporal lobe]] and functions as a hub in a widespread network for [[memory]], navigation and the perception of time.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;Integrating time from experience in the lateral entorhinal cortex      Albert Tsao, Jørgen Sugar, Li Lu, Cheng Wang, James J. Knierim, May-Britt Moser &amp; Edvard I. Moser   Naturevolume 561, pages57–62 (2018)&lt;/ref&gt; The EC is the main interface between the [[hippocampus]] and [[neocortex]]. The [[EC-hippocampus system]] plays an important role in declarative (autobiographical/episodic/semantic) memories and in particular [[spatial memory|spatial memories]] including [[memory formation]], [[memory consolidation]], and memory optimization in [[sleep]]. The EC is also responsible for the pre-processing (familiarity) of the input signals in the reflex [[nictitating membrane]] response of classical trace conditioning; the association of impulses from the [[Human eye|eye]] and the [[ear]] occurs in the entorhinal cortex.

==Structure==
In rodents, the EC is located at the [[Caudal (anatomical term)|caudal]] end of the [[temporal lobe]]. In primates it is located at the [[Anatomical terms of location#Cranial and caudal|rostral]] end of the temporal lobe and stretches dorsolaterally. It is usually divided into [[medial (anatomy)|medial]] and [[lateral (anatomy)|lateral]] regions with three bands with distinct properties and connectivity running perpendicular across the whole area. A distinguishing characteristic of the EC is the lack of cell bodies where layer IV should be; this layer is called the ''lamina dissecans''.

===Connections===
[[File:Apoe-cortical-thickness-entorhinal.jpg|thumb|right|300px|View of left entorhinal cortex (red) from beneath the brain, with front of brain at top. Artist’s rendering.]]
The superficial layers – layers II and III – of EC project to the [[dentate gyrus]] and [[hippocampus]]: Layer II projects primarily to [[dentate gyrus]] and hippocampal region CA3; layer III projects primarily to hippocampal region CA1 and the [[subiculum]]. These layers receive input from other cortical areas, especially associational, [[Perirhinal cortex|perirhinal]], and [[Parahippocampal gyrus|parahippocampal]] cortices, as well as [[prefrontal cortex]]. EC as a whole, therefore, receives highly processed input from every sensory modality, as well as input relating to ongoing cognitive processes, though it should be stressed that, within EC, this information remains at least partially segregated.

The deep layers, especially layer V, receive one of the three main outputs of the [[hippocampus]] and, in turn, reciprocate connections from other cortical areas that project to superficial EC.

The rodent entorhinal cortex shows a modular organization, with different properties and connections in different areas.

===Brodmann's areas===
* [[Brodmann area 28]] is known as the &quot;area entorhinalis&quot;
* [[Brodmann area 34]] is known as the &quot;area entorhinalis dorsalis&quot;

==Function==
===Neuron information processing===
In 2005, it was discovered that entorhinal cortex contains a [[connectome|neural map]] of the spatial environment in rats.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hafting&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Hafting T, Fyhn M, Molden S, Moser M, Moser E |title=Microstructure of a spatial map in the entorhinal cortex |journal=Nature |volume=436 |issue=7052 |pages=801–6 |year=2005 |pmid=15965463 | doi = 10.1038/nature03721 |bibcode=2005Natur.436..801H}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2014, John O'Keefe, May-Britt Moser and Edvard Moser received the [[Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine]], partly because of this discovery.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Overview of Nobel Prize laureates in Physiology or Medicine|url=https://www.nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/medicine/laureates/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Neurons in the lateral entorhinal cortex exhibit little spatial selectivity,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Hargreaves E, Rao G, Lee I, Knierim J |title=Major dissociation between medial and lateral entorhinal input to dorsal hippocampus |journal=Science |volume=308 |issue=5729 |pages=1792–4 |year=2005 |pmid=15961670 |doi=10.1126/science.1110449|bibcode = 2005Sci...308.1792H }}&lt;/ref&gt; whereas neurons of the medial entorhinal cortex (MEC), exhibit multiple &quot;place fields&quot; that are arranged in a hexagonal pattern, and are, therefore, called &quot;[[grid cells]]&quot;. These fields and spacing between fields increase from the dorso-lateral MEA to the ventro-medial MEA.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hafting&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Fyhn M, Molden S, Witter M, Moser E, Moser M |title=Spatial representation in the entorhinal cortex |journal=Science |volume=305 |issue=5688 |pages=1258–64 |year=2004 |pmid=15333832 |doi=10.1126/science.1099901 |bibcode=2004Sci...305.1258F}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The same group of researchers have found speed cells in the medial entorhinal cortex of rats. The speed of movement is translated from proprioceptive information and is represented as firing rates in these cells. The cells are known to fire in correlation to future speed of the rodent.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kropff&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Kropff Em |author2=Carmichael J E |author3=Moser M-B |author4=Moser E-I | year = 2015 | title = Speed cells in the medial entorhinal cortex | url = | journal = Nature | volume = 523 |issue=7561 | pages = 419–424 | doi = 10.1038/nature14622 |pmid=26176924 |bibcode = 2015Natur.523..419K |hdl=11336/10493 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Single-unit recording]] of neurons in humans playing [[video game]]s find path cells in the EC, the activity of which indicates whether a person is taking a clockwise or counterclockwise path. Such EC &quot;direction&quot; path cells show this directional activity irrespective of the location of where a person experiences themselves, which contrasts them to place cells in the hippocampus, which are activated by specific locations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jacobs&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Jacobs J, Kahana MJ, Ekstrom AD, Mollison MV, Fried I | year = 2010 | title = A sense of direction in human entorhinal cortex | url = | journal = Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A | volume = 107 | issue = 14| pages = 6487–6492 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0911213107 | pmid = 20308554 | pmc=2851993|bibcode = 2010PNAS..107.6487J }}&lt;/ref&gt;

EC neurons process general information such as directional activity in the environment, which contrasts to that of the hippocampal neurons, which usually encode information about specific places. This suggests that EC encodes general properties about current contexts that are then used by hippocampus to create unique representations from combinations of these properties.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jacobs&quot;/&gt;

Research generally highlights a useful distinction in which the medial entorhinal cortex (MEC) mainly supports processing of space&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Cellular mechanisms of spatial navigation in the medial entorhinal cortex|journal=Nature|volume=16|issue=3|pages=325–331|doi=10.1038/nn.3340|pmid=23396102|year=2013|last1=Schmidt-Hieber|first1=Christoph|last2=Häusser|first2=Michael}}&lt;/ref&gt;, whereas the lateral entorhinal cortex (LEC) mainly supports the processing of time&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;. 

Individual variation in the volume of EC is linked to taste perception. People with a larger EC in the left hemisphere found quinine, the source of bitterness in [[tonic water]], less bitter. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Hwang LD, Strike LT, Couvy-Duchesne B, de Zubicaray GI, McMahon K, Bresline PA, Reed DR, Martin NG, Wright MJ | year = 2019 | title = Associations between brain structure and perceived intensity of sweet and bitter tastes | journal = Behav. Brain Res. | volume = 2 |issue=363 | pages = 103–108 | doi = 10.1016/j.bbr.2019.01.046 |pmid= 30703394 | pmc = 6470356 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Clinical significance==
===Alzheimer's disease===
The entorhinal cortex is the first area of the brain to be affected in [[Alzheimer's disease]]; a recent functional [[magnetic resonance imaging]] study has localised the area to the lateral entorhinal cortex.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Khan UA, Liu L, Provenzano FA, Berman DE, Profaci CP, Sloan R, Mayeux R, Duff KE, Small SA |year=2013|title=Molecular drivers and cortical spread of lateral entorhinal cortex dysfunction in preclinical Alzheimer's disease|journal=[[Nature Neuroscience]]|doi=10.1038/nn.3606|volume=17|issue=2|pages=304–311|pmc=4044925|pmid=24362760}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lopez ''et al.''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Lopez|first1=M. E.|last2=Bruna|first2=R.|last3=Aurtenetxe|first3=S.|last4=Pineda-Pardo|first4=J. A.|last5=Marcos|first5=A.|last6=Arrazola|first6=J.|last7=Reinoso|first7=A. I.|last8=Montejo|first8=P.|last9=Bajo|first9=R.|last10=Maestu|first10=F.|title=Alpha-Band Hypersynchronization in Progressive Mild Cognitive Impairment: A Magnetoencephalography Study|journal=Journal of Neuroscience|date=2014|volume=34|issue=44|pages=14551–14559|doi=10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0964-14.2014|pmid=25355209|pmc=6608420}}&lt;/ref&gt; have shown, in a multimodal study, that there are differences in the volume of the left entorhinal cortex between progressing (to Alzheimer's disease) and stable mild cognitive impairment patients. These authors also found that the volume of the left entorhinal cortex inversely correlates with the level of alpha band phase synchronization between the right anterior cingulate and temporo-occipital regions.

In 2012, neuroscientists at [[UCLA]] conducted an experiment using a virtual taxi video game connected to seven epilepsy patients with electrodes already implanted in their brains, allowing the researchers to monitor neuronal activity whenever memories were being formed. As the researchers stimulated the nerve fibers of each of the patients' entorhinal cortex as they were learning, they were then able to better navigate themselves through various routes and recognize landmarks more quickly. This signified an improvement in the patients' spatial memory.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Suthana|first1=N.|last2=Haneef|first2=Z.|last3=Stern|first3=J.|last4=Mukamel|first4=R.|last5=Behnke|first5=E.|last6=Knowlton|first6=B.|last7=Fried|first7=I.|year=2012|title=Memory Enhancement and Deep-Brain Stimulation of the Entorhinal Area|journal=[[New England Journal of Medicine]]|doi=10.1056/NEJMoa1107212|volume=366|issue=6|pages=502–510|pmc=3447081|pmid=22316444}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Effect of aerobic exercise===
A study finds that regardless of gender, young adults who have greater aerobic fitness also have greater volume of their entorhinal cortex. It suggests that aerobic exercise may have a positive effect on the medial temporal lobe memory system (which includes the entorhinal cortex) in healthy young adults. This also suggests that exercise training, when designed to increase aerobic fitness, might have a positive effect on the brain in healthy young adults&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://m.medicalxpress.com/news/2015-12-highlights-importance-physical-aerobic-healthy.html|title=Study highlights the importance of physical activity and aerobic exercise for healthy brain function|access-date=2017-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Entorhinal cortex}}
* {{BrainMaps|Entorhinal%20cortex|Entorhinal cortex}}
* [https://www.neuinfo.org/mynif/search.php?q=Entorhinal%20Cortex&amp;t=data&amp;s=cover&amp;b=0&amp;r=20 NIF Search - Entorhinal Cortex] via the [[Neuroscience Information Framework]]

{{Cerebral cortex}}
{{Papez circuit}}

For delineating the Entorhinal cortex, see Desikan RS, Ségonne F, Fischl B, Quinn BT, Dickerson BC, Blacker D, Buckner RL, Dale AM, Maguire RP, Hyman BT, Albert MS, Killiany RJ. An automated labeling system for subdividing the human cerebral cortex on MRI scans into gyral based regions of interest. Neuroimage. 2006 Jul 1;31(3):968-80.

{{DEFAULTSORT:Entorhinal Cortex}}
[[Category:Limbic system]]
[[Category:Cerebral cortex]]</text>
      <sha1>n4urgpgnbpmc4046tow06lf2860ey1f</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
