  <page>
    <title>Emanuel Leutze</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9683</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939184639</id>
      <parentid>938899115</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-04T21:51:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Howcheng</username>
        <id>314721</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>ANB link</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|German-American painter}}
{{Infobox artist
| name          = Emanuel Leutze
| image         = Emanuel Leutze.jpg
| imagesize     = 
| caption       = 
| birth_name    = 
| birth_date    = {{birth date |1816|5|24|}}
| birth_place   = [[Schwäbisch Gmünd]], [[Kingdom of Württemberg|Württemberg]], [[German Confederation]]
| death_date    = {{Death date and age |1868|7|18|1816|5|24|}}
| death_place   = Washington, D.C., U.S.
| nationality   = German American
| field         = [[History painting|History painter]]
| training      = [[John Rubens Smith]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Karl Friedrich Lessing]]
| movement      = 
| works         = 
| patrons       = 
| influenced by =
| influenced    =
| awards        = 
| resting_place = [[Glenwood Cemetery (Washington, D.C.)|Glenwood Cemetery]]
}}
[[File:Christophe_Colomb_devant_le_conseil_de_Salamanque_-_Emanuel_Leutze_-_MBA_Lyon_2014.jpg|thumb|''[[Christopher Columbus Before the Council of Salamanca]]'' (1841)]]
'''Emanuel Gottlieb Leutze''' (May 24, 1816{{spaced ndash}}July 18, 1868) was a [[German American]] [[History painting|history painter]] best known for his 1851 painting ''[[Washington Crossing the Delaware (1851 painting)|Washington Crossing the Delaware]]''. He is associated with the [[Düsseldorf school of painting]].

==Biography==

Leutze was born in Schwäbisch Gmünd, [[Württemberg]], [[German Confederation|Germany]], and was brought to the United States as a child.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Marter|first=Joan M.|title=The Grove Encyclopedia of American Art|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sPGdBxzaWj0C&amp;pg=RA2-PA144|year=2011|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-533579-8|page=144}}&lt;/ref&gt; His parents settled first in [[Fredericksburg, Virginia]], and then at [[Philadelphia]].  The first development of his artistic talent occurred while he was attending the sickbed of his father, when he attempted drawing to occupy the long hours of waiting.&lt;ref name=&quot;appletons&quot;&gt;{{Cite Appletons'|wstitle=Leutze, Emanuel|year=1892}}&lt;/ref&gt; His father died in 1831.&lt;ref name=&quot;danforth&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last=Witthoft |first=Brucia |title=American Artists in Düsseldorf: 1840–1865|location=[[Framingham, Massachusetts]]|publisher=Danforth Museum|year=1982|pages=14, 32|url=https://openlibrary.org/books/OL3512328M/American_artists_in_Du%CC%88sseldorf_1840-1865|display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt; At 14, he was painting portraits for $5 apiece.  Through such work, he supported himself after the death of his father.&lt;ref name=&quot;adb&quot;&gt;{{Cite ADB|18|500|502|Leutze, Emanuel|[[Moritz Blanckarts]]|ADB:Leutze, Emanuel}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1834, he received his first instruction in art in classes of [[John Rubens Smith]],&lt;ref name=&quot;anb&quot;&gt;{{Cite ANB |last=Groseclose |first=Barbara |title=Leutze, Emanuel Gottlieb |id=1700519}}&lt;/ref&gt; a portrait painter in Philadelphia.  He soon became skilled, and promoted a plan for publishing, in Washington, portraits of eminent American statesmen; however, he met with but slight encouragement.&lt;ref name=&quot;appletons&quot;/&gt;

===Europe===
In 1840, one of his paintings attracted attention and procured him several orders, which enabled him to go to the [[Kunstakademie Düsseldorf]]. Due to his anti-academic attitude, he studied only one year at the academy (in the class of Director [[Friedrich Wilhelm Schadow|Schadow]]). Mainly Leutze was affected by the painter [[Karl Friedrich Lessing|Lessing]].&lt;ref&gt;Wolfgang Müller von Königswinter: ''Düsseldorfer Künstler aus den letzten fünfundzwanzig Jahren''. 1854, S. 139.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1842 he went to [[Munich]], studying the works of [[Peter von Cornelius|Cornelius]] and Kaulbach, and, while there, finished his ''Columbus before the Queen''. The following year he visited [[Venice]] and Rome, making studies from [[Titian]] and [[Michelangelo]]. His first work, ''[[Columbus before the Council of Salamanca]]'' (1841) was purchased by the Düsseldorf Art Union. A companion picture, ''Columbus in Chains'', procured him the gold medal of the Brussels Art Exhibition, and was subsequently purchased by the Art Union in New York; it was the basis of the 1893 $2 [[Columbian Issue]] stamp. In 1845, after a tour in Italy, he returned to Düsseldorf, marrying Juliane Lottner&lt;ref name=&quot;danforth&quot;/&gt; and making his home there for 14 years.&lt;ref name=&quot;appletons&quot;/&gt;

During his years in Düsseldorf, he was a resource for visiting Americans:  he found them places to live and work, provided introductions, and emotional and even financial support.&lt;ref name=&quot;danforth&quot;/&gt; For many years, he was the president of the Düsseldorf Artists' Association; in 1848, he was an early promoter of the &quot;Malkasten&quot; art association; and in 1857, he led the call for a gathering of artists which led to the founding of the Allgemeine deutsche Kunstgenossenschaft.&lt;ref name=&quot;adb&quot;/&gt;
[[Image:Washington Crossing the Delaware by Emanuel Leutze, MMA-NYC, 1851.jpg|thumb|300px|''[[Washington Crossing the Delaware (1851 painting)|Washington Crossing the Delaware]]'' (1851) {{efn|According to one art critic. minor historical inaccuracies in Leutze's painting include the [[Betsy Ross flag]], which was created about one year after the event; soldiers used a different type of boat for the crossing; and Washington is depicted older than he was at the time of the crossing at age 44. The soldiers' uniforms are accurately depicted, and the painting correctly conveys colonial unity and pride.{{sfn|Parrish|2014}} &amp;nbsp;The official United States flag was adopted by Congress on June 14, 1777.{{sfn|Preble|1880|p=259}}}} ]]
A strong supporter of Europe's [[Revolutions of 1848]], Leutze decided to paint an image that would encourage Europe's liberal reformers with the example of the American Revolution. Using American tourists and art students as models and assistants, Leutze finished a first version of ''[[Washington Crossing the Delaware (1851 painting)|Washington Crossing the Delaware]]'' in 1850.  Just after it was completed, the first version was damaged by fire in his studio, subsequently restored, and acquired by the Kunsthalle Bremen. On September 5, 1942, during World War II, it was destroyed in a bombing raid by the Allied forces. The second painting, a replica of the first, only larger, was ordered 1850 by the Parisian art trader Adolphe Goupil for his New York branch and placed on exhibition on Broadway in October 1851.&lt;ref&gt;[[Barratt, Carrie Rebora]] (2011). [http://www.metmuseum.org/art/metpublications/Washington_Crossing_the_Delaware_Restoring_an_American_Masterpiece ''Washington Crossing the Delaware. Restoring an American Masterpiece'']. MET publications. S. 7. 
&lt;/ref&gt; It is owned by the [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]] in New York.  In 1854, Leutze finished his depiction of the [[Battle of Monmouth]], &quot;Washington rallying the troops at Monmouth,&quot; commissioned by an important Leutze patron, banker [[David Leavitt (banker)|David Leavitt]] of New York City and [[Great Barrington, Massachusetts]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.americanheritage.com/articles/magazine/ah/1965/4/1965_4_14_print.shtml &quot;Washington at Monmouth,&quot; American Heritage Magazine, June 1965, AmericanHeritage.com] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080608192951/http://www.americanheritage.com/articles/magazine/ah/1965/4/1965_4_14_print.shtml |date=2008-06-08 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===New York City and Washington, D.C.===
[[File:Emanuel Leutze grave - Glenwood Cemetery - 2014-09-14.jpg|thumb|left|upright=.8|Grave of Emanuel Leutze at Glenwood Cemetery.]]
In 1859, Leutze returned to the United States and opened a studio in New York City.&lt;ref name=&quot;appletons&quot;/&gt; He divided his time between New York City and Washington, D.C.&lt;ref name=&quot;dab&quot;&gt;{{Cite DAB |last=Downes |first=William Howe |title=Leutze, Emanuel|year=1933}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1859, he painted a portrait of Chief Justice [[Roger Brooke Taney]] which hangs in the [[Harvard Law School]].  In a 1992 opinion, Justice [[Antonin Scalia]] described the portrait of Taney, made two years after Taney's infamous decision in ''[[Dred Scott v. Sandford]]'', as showing Taney &quot;in black, sitting in a shadowed red armchair, left hand resting upon a pad of paper in his lap, right hand hanging limply, almost lifelessly, beside the inner arm of the chair. He sits facing the viewer and staring straight out. There seems to be on his face, and in his deep-set eyes, an expression of profound sadness and disillusionment.&quot;

Leutze also executed other portraits, including one of fellow painter [[William Morris Hunt]]. That portrait was owned by Hunt's brother [[Leavitt Hunt]], a New York attorney and sometime Vermont resident, and was shown at an exhibition devoted to William Morris Hunt's work at the [[Museum of Fine Arts, Boston]] in 1878.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=dYkVAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA60&amp;lpg=PA60&amp;dq=%22william+morris+hunt%22+richard+leavitt+paris&amp;source=web&amp;ots=I8J6FcEbNu&amp;sig=d7qFDpr8SwJIUn8I851W8Tym3hQ&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=7&amp;ct=result#PPA60,M1 Exhibition of the Works of William Morris Hunt, Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, John C. Dalton, Alfred Mudge &amp; Son, Boston, 1879]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1860 Leutze was commissioned by the [[Congress of the United States|U.S. Congress]] to decorate a stairway in the [[United States Capitol|Capitol]] Building in Washington, DC, for which he painted a large composition, ''[[Westward the Course of Empire Takes Its Way]]'', which is also commonly known as ''Westward Ho!''.

Late in life, he became a member of the [[National Academy of Design]]. He was also a member of the [[Union League Club of New York]], which has a number of his paintings. At age 52, he died in Washington, D.C. of heat stroke. He was interred at [[Glenwood Cemetery (Washington, D.C.)|Glenwood Cemetery]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Heiderstadt|first=Dorothy|title=Painters of America|url=https://archive.org/details/paintersofameric00heid|url-access=registration|location=New York|publisher=D. McKay Co.|date=1970|page=[https://archive.org/details/paintersofameric00heid/page/88 88]}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the time of his death, a painting, ''The Emancipation of the Slaves'', was in preparation.&lt;ref name=&quot;anb&quot;/&gt;

Leutze's portraits are known for their artistic quality and their patriotic [[romanticism]].  ''Washington Crossing the Delaware'' firmly ranks among the American national [[iconography]].
{{clear}}

==Gallery of works==
&lt;gallery widths=&quot;200px&quot; heights=&quot;200px&quot; mode=&quot;nolines&quot;&gt;
File:Emanuel Gottlieb Leutze - Columbus Before the Queen.JPG|''Columbus before the Queen'' (1843)
File:Emanuel Leutze - Westward the Course of Empire Takes Its Way - Capitol.jpg|''[[Westward the Course of Empire Takes Its Way]]'' (1860)
File:Mrs. Schuyler Burning Her Wheat Fields on the Approach of the British.jpg|''Mrs. Schuyler Burning Her Wheat Fields on the Approach of the British'' (1852)
Image:BattleofMonmouth.jpg|''Washington Rallying the Troops at [[Battle of Monmouth|Monmouth]]'' (c. 1851-1854)
File:Alaska purchase.jpg|''[[William H. Seward]] and [[Eduard de Stoeckl]] Negotiating the [[Alaska Purchase]]'' (1867)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor1-first=Peter M.|editor1-last=Metcalfe|title=Alaska Blue Book|edition=Tenth|year=1991|publisher=[[Alaska Department of Education &amp; Early Development|Alaska Department of Education]], [[Alaska State Library|Division of State Libraries, Archives and Museums]]|location=[[Juneau]]|page=227|chapter=History, State Designations and Superlatives}}&lt;/ref&gt;
File:Leutze, Emanuel — Storming of the Teocalli by Cortez and His Troops — 1848.jpg|''Storming of the Teocalli by Cortez and his Troops'' (1848)
File:Worthington Whittredge in His Tenth Street Studio.jpeg|''Worthington Whittredge in His Tenth Street Studio'' (1865)
File:Emanuel Leutze William Morris Hunt.jpeg|''Portrait of [[William Morris Hunt]]'' (ca. 1845)
File:General Ambrose Burnside at Antietam by Leutze.jpg|General [[Ambrose Burnside]] at Antietam (1863)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Harrington|first1=Peter|title=Emanuel Leutze's Portrait of General Ambrose Burnside at Antietam|url=http://blogs.brown.edu/bulspecialcollections/2011/02/21/emanuel-leutze%E2%80%99s-portrait-of-general-ambrose-burnside-at-antietam/|website=Brown University Library|accessdate=8 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
File:Nathaniel Hawthorne by Emanuel Gottlieb Leutze.png|''[[Nathaniel Hawthorne]]'' (1862)
File:Emanuel Gottlieb Leutze, Political Cartoon of the American Civil War, c. 1860s, NGA 181018.jpg|''Political Cartoon of the American Civil War'', c. 1860s, [[National Gallery of Art]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Footnotes==
{{notelist}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

Additional References:
* Wierich, Jochen. ''Grand Themes: Emanuel Leutze, &quot;Washington Crossing the Delaware,&quot; and American History Painting'' (Penn State University Press; 2012) 240 pages; Argues that the painting was a touchstone for debates over history painting at a time of intense sectionalism.
*{{cite book |last=Hutton |first=Anne Hawkes |title=Portrait of Patriotism: Washington Crossing the Delaware|publisher=Chilton Book Company|location=Radnor, Pennsylvania|year=1975|isbn=0-8019-6418-0}}
* Irre, Heidrun. ''Emanuel Gottlob Leutze: Von der Rems zum Delaware'', einhorn-Verlag+Druck GmbH, Schwäbisch Gmünd 2016, {{ISBN|978-3-95747-033-1}} https://einhornverlag.de/shop/buecher/von-der-rems-zum-delaware/ 
* [[New International Encyclopedia]]

==External links==
{{EB1911 poster|Leutze, Emanuel}}
{{Commons category}}
* [http://www.museumsyndicate.com/artist.php?artist=514 Leutze Gallery at MuseumSyndicate]
* [https://archive.is/20121209080350/http://wwar.com/masters/l/leutze-emanuel_gottlieb.html Emanuel Leutze]
* {{worldcat id|lccn-n82-96322}}
* [http://blog.oup.com/oupblog/2006/02/washingtons_cro.html Introduction to ''Washington's Crossing''] by David Hackett Fischer at the Oxford University Press blog, discusses Leutze's most famous painting.
* {{Cite NIE|wstitle=Leutze, Emanuel|year=1905 |short=x}}
* {{Cite Collier's|wstitle=Leutze, Emanuel |short=x}}
* [http://www.reynoldahouse.org/index.php Reynolda House Museum of American Art]
*[http://libmma.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/compoundobject/collection/p15324coll10/id/56268/rec/16 ''Art and the empire city: New York, 1825-1861''], an exhibition catalog from The Metropolitan Museum of Art (fully available online as PDF), which contains material on Leutze (see index)

{{Romanticism}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Leutze, Emanuel}}
[[Category:1816 births]]
[[Category:1868 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Schwäbisch Gmünd]]
[[Category:19th-century American painters]]
[[Category:American male painters]]
[[Category:19th-century German painters]]
[[Category:German male painters]]
[[Category:People of the Revolutions of 1848]]
[[Category:German emigrants to the United States]]
[[Category:Burials at Glenwood Cemetery (Washington, D.C.)]]
[[Category:American people of German descent]]
[[Category:19th-century painters of historical subjects]]
[[Category:National Academy of Design members]]
[[Category:American history painters]]
[[Category:Artists of the Boston Public Library]]</text>
      <sha1>79qc0zeijeleauybb3d854xcsjcsaw4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
