  <page>
    <title>Endosymbiont</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9677</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940157456</id>
      <parentid>939827351</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-10T21:42:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ArdenKAberly</username>
        <id>38511365</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Endosymbionts of plants */ Citation Needed</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{more citations needed|date=July 2018}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2020}}
[[File:Endosymbiosis.PNG|thumb|200px|A representation of the [[endosymbiotic theory]]]]

An '''endosymbiont''' or '''endobiont'''&lt;ref name=&quot;KingDom&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Margulis |first1=Lynn |author1link=Lynn Margulis |last2=Chapman |first2=Michael J. | name-list-format = vanc |title=Kingdoms &amp; domains an illustrated guide to the phyla of life on Earth |date=2009 |publisher=Academic Press/Elsevier |location=Amsterdam |isbn=978-0-08-092014-6 |page=493 |edition=4th |url=https://books.google.de/books?id=9IWaqAOGyt4C&amp;pg=PA493}}&lt;/ref&gt; is any [[organism]] that lives within the body or cells of another organism most often, though not always, in a [[mutualism (biology)|mutualistic]] relationship.
(The term '''endosymbiosis''' is from the [[Greek language|Greek]]: ἔνδον ''endon'' &quot;within&quot;, σύν ''syn'' &quot;together&quot; and βίωσις ''biosis'' &quot;living&quot;.) Examples are [[nitrogen-fixing]] [[bacteria]] (called [[rhizobia]]), which live in the [[root nodule]]s of [[legume]]s; single-cell [[algae]] inside [[Coral reef|reef-building]] [[coral]]s, and bacterial endosymbionts that provide essential nutrients to about 10–15% of [[insect]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid29393944&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Mergaert P | title = Role of antimicrobial peptides in controlling symbiotic bacterial populations | journal = Natural Product Reports | volume = 35 | issue = 4 | pages = 336–356 | date = April 2018 | pmid = 29393944 | doi = 10.1039/c7np00056a }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15178799&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Little AF, van Oppen MJ, Willis BL | title = Flexibility in algal endosymbioses shapes growth in reef corals | journal = Science | location = New York, N.Y. | volume = 304 | issue = 5676 | pages = 1492–4 | date = June 2004 | pmid = 15178799 | doi = 10.1126/science.1095733 | bibcode = 2004Sci...304.1491L }}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are two types of symbiont transmissions. In [[horizontal transmission]], each new generation acquires free living symbionts from the environment. An example is the nitrogen-fixing bacteria in certain plant roots. [[Vertical transmission (symbiont)|Vertical transmission]] takes place when the symbiont is transferred directly from parent to offspring. There is also a combination of these types, where symbionts are transferred vertically for some generation before a switch of host occurs and new symbionts are horizontally acquired from the environment{{Citation needed|date=August 2019}}. In vertical transmissions, the symbionts often have a reduced genomes and are no longer able to survive on their own. As a result, the symbiont depends on the host, resulting in a highly intimate co-dependent relationship. For instance, [[Acyrthosiphon pisum|pea aphid]] symbionts have lost genes for essential molecules, now relying on the host to supply them with nutrients. In return, the symbionts synthesize essential amino acids for the aphid host .&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid10993077&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Shigenobu S, Watanabe H, Hattori M, Sakaki Y, Ishikawa H | title = Genome sequence of the endocellular bacterial symbiont of aphids Buchnera sp. APS | journal = Nature | volume = 407 | issue = 6800 | pages = 81–6 | date = September 2000 | pmid = 10993077 | doi = 10.1038/35024074 | bibcode = 2000Natur.407...81S }}&lt;/ref&gt; Other examples include ''[[Wigglesworthia]]'' nutritional symbionts of tse-tse flies, or in sponges.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid20157340&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Bright M, Bulgheresi S | title = A complex journey: transmission of microbial symbionts | journal = Nature Reviews. Microbiology | volume = 8 | issue = 3 | pages = 218–30 | date = March 2010 | pmid = 20157340 | pmc = 2967712 | doi = 10.1038/nrmicro2262 }}&lt;/ref&gt; When a symbiont reaches this stage, it begins to resemble a cellular [[organelle]], similar to [[mitochondria]] or [[chloroplasts]].

Many instances of endosymbiosis are obligate; that is, either the endosymbiont or the host cannot survive without the other, such as the [[Siboglinidae|gutless marine worms]] of the [[genus]] ''[[Riftia]]'', which get nutrition from their endosymbiotic bacteria. The most common examples of obligate endosymbioses are [[mitochondria]] and [[chloroplast]]s. Some human parasites, e.g. ''[[Wuchereria bancrofti]]'' and ''[[Mansonella perstans]]'', thrive in their intermediate insect hosts because of an obligate endosymbiosis with ''[[Wolbachia]] spp''{{Citation needed|date=August 2019}}. They can both be eliminated from said hosts by treatments that target this bacterium{{Citation needed|reason=which bacteria?|date=August 2019}}. However, not all endosymbioses are obligate and some endosymbioses can be [[symbiosis|harmful]] to either of the organisms involved.

Two major types of [[organelle]] in [[Eukaryote|eukaryotic cells]], [[mitochondria]] and [[plastid]]s such as [[chloroplast]]s, are considered to be bacterial endosymbionts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Moore KR, Magnabosco C, Momper L, Gold DA, Bosak T, Fournier GP | title = An Expanded Ribosomal Phylogeny of Cyanobacteria Supports a Deep Placement of Plastids | language = English | journal = Frontiers in Microbiology | volume = 10 | pages = 1612 | date = 2019 | pmid = 31354692 | pmc = 6640209 | doi = 10.3389/fmicb.2019.01612 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This process is commonly referred to as [[symbiogenesis]].

== Symbiogenesis and organelles ==
{{Main|Symbiogenesis}}

[[File:Endosymbiotic theory.svg|thumb|An overview of endosymbiosis.]]
Symbiogenesis explains the origins of [[eukaryote]]s, whose cells contain two major kinds of [[organelle]]: [[mitochondria]] and [[chloroplast]]s. The theory proposes that these organelles evolved from certain types of bacteria that eukaryotic cells engulfed through [[cytosis|phagocytosis]]. These cells and the bacteria trapped inside them entered an endosymbiotic relationship, meaning that the bacteria took up residence and began living exclusively within the eukaryotic cells.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Sagan L | title = On the origin of mitosing cells | journal = Journal of Theoretical Biology | volume = 14 | issue = 3 | pages = 255–74 | date = March 1967 | pmid = 11541392 | doi = 10.1016/0022-5193(67)90079-3 | authorlink = Lynn Margulis }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Numerous insect species have endosymbionts at different stages of symbiogenesis. A common theme of symbiogenesis involves the reduction of the genome to only essential genes for the host and symbiont [[hologenome|collective genome]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid12415315&quot;/&gt; An incredible example of this is the fractionation of the ''[[Hodgkinia]]'' genome of ''[[Magicicada]]'' [[cicadas]]. Because the cicada life cycle takes years underground, [[natural selection]] on endosymbiont populations is relaxed for many bacterial generations. This allows the symbiont genomes to diversify within the host for years with only punctuated periods of selection when the cicadas reproduce. As a result, the ancestral ''[[Hodgkinia]]'' genome has split into three groups of primary endosymbiont, each encoding only a fraction of the essential genes for the symbiosis. The host now requires all three sub-groups of symbiont, each with degraded genomes lacking most essential genes for bacterial viability.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid29129532&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Campbell MA, Łukasik P, Simon C, McCutcheon JP | title = Idiosyncratic Genome Degradation in a Bacterial Endosymbiont of Periodical Cicadas | journal = Current Biology | volume = 27 | issue = 22 | pages = 3568–3575.e3 | date = November 2017 | pmid = 29129532 | doi = 10.1016/j.cub.2017.10.008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Bacterial endosymbionts of invertebrates==

The best-studied examples of endosymbiosis are known from invertebrates. These symbioses affect organisms with global impact, including ''[[symbiodinium]]'' of corals, or ''[[Wolbachia]]'' of insects. Many insect agricultural pests and human disease vectors have intimate relationships with primary endosymbionts.

=== Endosymbionts of insects ===
[[File:Cospeciation (5 processes) - with key.png|thumb|right|Diagram of cospeciation, where parasites or endosymbionts speciate or branch alongside their hosts. This process is more common in hosts with primary endosymbionts.]]
Scientists classify insect endosymbionts in two broad categories, 'Primary' and 'Secondary'. Primary endosymbionts (sometimes referred to as P-endosymbionts) have been associated with their [[insect]] hosts for many millions of years (from 10 to several hundred million years in some cases). They form obligate associations (see below), and display [[cospeciation]] with their insect hosts. Secondary endosymbionts exhibit a more recently developed association, are sometimes horizontally transferred between hosts, live in the [[hemolymph]] of the insects (not specialized bacteriocytes, see below), and are not obligate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | vauthors = Baumann P, Moran NA, Baumann L | chapter = Bacteriocyte-associated endosymbionts of insects | veditors = Dworkin M | title = The prokaryotes | publisher = Springer | location = New York | date = 2000 | chapter-url = http://link.springer.de/link/service/books/10125/ }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Primary endosymbionts ====

Among primary endosymbionts of insects, the best-studied are the pea [[aphid]] (''[[Acyrthosiphon pisum]]'') and its endosymbiont ''[[Buchnera (proteobacteria)|Buchnera]] sp.'' APS,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Douglas AE | title = Nutritional interactions in insect-microbial symbioses: aphids and their symbiotic bacteria Buchnera | journal = Annual Review of Entomology | volume = 43 | pages = 17–37 | year = 1998 | pmid = 15012383 | doi = 10.1146/annurev.ento.43.1.17 | url = https://semanticscholar.org/paper/c83da773023e9412e158ad10bf2f646a88401cd2 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Douglas AE | title = Nutritional interactions in insect-microbial symbioses: aphids and their symbiotic bacteria Buchnera | journal = Annual Review of Entomology | volume = 43 | pages = 17–37 | date = January 1998 | pmid = 15012383 | doi = 10.1146/annurev.ento.43.1.17 | url = https://semanticscholar.org/paper/c83da773023e9412e158ad10bf2f646a88401cd2 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid10993077&quot;/&gt; the [[tsetse fly]] ''Glossina morsitans morsitans'' and its endosymbiont ''[[Wigglesworthia glossinidia brevipalpis]]'' and the endosymbiotic [[protists]] in lower [[termite]]s. As with endosymbiosis in other insects, the symbiosis is obligate in that neither the bacteria nor the insect is viable without the other. Scientists have been unable to cultivate the bacteria in lab conditions outside of the insect. With special nutritionally-enhanced diets, the insects can survive, but are unhealthy, and at best survive only a few generations.

In some insect groups, these endosymbionts live in specialized insect cells called [[bacteriocyte]]s (also called ''mycetocytes''), and are maternally-transmitted, i.e. the mother transmits her endosymbionts to her offspring. In some cases, the bacteria are transmitted in the [[Egg (biology)|egg]], as in ''Buchnera''; in others like ''Wigglesworthia'', they are transmitted via milk to the developing insect embryo. In termites, the endosymbionts reside within the hindguts and are transmitted through [[trophallaxis]] among colony members.

The primary endosymbionts are thought to help the host either by providing nutrients that the host cannot obtain itself or by metabolizing insect waste products into safer forms. For example, the putative primary role of ''Buchnera'' is to synthesize [[essential amino acid]]s that the aphid cannot acquire from its natural diet of plant sap. Likewise, the primary role of ''Wigglesworthia'', it is presumed, is to synthesize [[vitamin]]s that the tsetse fly does not get from the [[blood]] that it eats. In lower termites, the endosymbiotic protists play a major role in the digestion of lignocellulosic materials that constitute a bulk of the termites' diet.

Bacteria benefit from the reduced exposure to [[predator]]s and competition from other bacterial species, the ample supply of nutrients and relative environmental stability inside the host.

Genome sequencing reveals that obligate bacterial endosymbionts of insects have among the smallest of known bacterial genomes and have [[genome reduction|lost many genes]] that are commonly found in closely related bacteria. Several theories have been put forth to explain the loss of genes. It is presumed that some of these genes are not needed in the environment of the host insect cell. A complementary theory suggests that the relatively small numbers of bacteria inside each insect decrease the efficiency of natural selection in 'purging' deleterious mutations and small mutations from the population, resulting in a loss of genes over many millions of years. Research in which a parallel [[phylogeny]] of bacteria and insects was inferred supports the belief that the primary endosymbionts are transferred only vertically (i.e., from the mother), and not horizontally (i.e., by escaping the host and entering a new host).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Wernegreen JJ | title = Endosymbiosis: lessons in conflict resolution | journal = PLOS Biology | volume = 2 | issue = 3 | pages = E68 | date = March 2004 | pmid = 15024418 | pmc = 368163 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pbio.0020068 | df = dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Moran NA | title = Accelerated evolution and Muller's rachet in endosymbiotic bacteria | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 93 | issue = 7 | pages = 2873–8 | date = April 1996 | pmid = 8610134 | pmc = 39726 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.93.7.2873 | bibcode = 1996PNAS...93.2873M }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Attacking obligate bacterial endosymbionts may present a way to control their insect hosts, many of which are pests or carriers of human disease. For example, aphids are crop pests and the tsetse fly carries the organism ''[[Trypanosoma brucei]]'' that causes African [[African trypanosomiasis|sleeping sickness]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Aksoy S, Maudlin I, Dale C, Robinson AS, O'Neill SL | title = Prospects for control of African trypanosomiasis by tsetse vector manipulation | journal = Trends in Parasitology | volume = 17 | issue = 1 | pages = 29–35 | date = January 2001 | pmid = 11137738 | doi = 10.1016/S1471-4922(00)01850-X }}&lt;/ref&gt; Other motivations for their study involve understanding the origins of symbioses in general, as a proxy for understanding e.g. how chloroplasts or mitochondria came to be obligate symbionts of [[eukaryotes]] or plants.

==== Secondary endosymbionts ====
[[File:HEMI Aphididae Aphidius attacking pea aphid.png|thumb|right|Pea aphids are commonly infested by parasitic wasps. Their secondary endosymbionts attack the infesting parasitoid wasp larvae promoting the survival of both the aphid host and its endosymbionts.]]
The pea aphid (''[[Acyrthosiphon pisum]]'') is known to contain at least three secondary endosymbionts, ''[[Hamiltonella defensa]]'', ''[[Regiella insecticola]]'', and ''[[Serratia symbiotica]]''. ''Hamiltonella defensa'' defends its aphid host from parasitoid wasps.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18029301&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Oliver KM, Campos J, Moran NA, Hunter MS | title = Population dynamics of defensive symbionts in aphids | journal = Proceedings. Biological Sciences | volume = 275 | issue = 1632 | pages = 293–9 | date = February 2008 | pmid = 18029301 | pmc = 2593717 | doi = 10.1098/rspb.2007.1192 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This defensive symbiosis improves the survival of aphids, which have lost some elements of the insect immune response.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid20186266&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | title = Genome sequence of the pea aphid Acyrthosiphon pisum | journal = PLOS Biology | volume = 8 | issue = 2 | pages = e1000313 | date = February 2010 | pmid = 20186266 | pmc = 2826372 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pbio.1000313 | author1 = International Aphid Genomics Consortium }}&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the best-understood defensive symbionts is the spiral bacteria ''[[Spiroplasma poulsonii]]''. ''Spiroplasma sp.'' can be reproductive manipulators, but also defensive symbionts of ''[[Drosophila]]'' flies. In ''[[Drosophila neotestacea]]'', ''S. poulsonii'' has spread across North America owing to its ability to defend its fly host against nematode parasites.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Jaenike J, Unckless R, Cockburn SN, Boelio LM, Perlman SJ | title = Adaptation via symbiosis: recent spread of a Drosophila defensive symbiont | journal = Science | volume = 329 | issue = 5988 | pages = 212–5 | date = July 2010 | pmid = 20616278 | doi = 10.1126/science.1188235 | bibcode = 2010Sci...329..212J | url = https://semanticscholar.org/paper/dd035b34099830ee0a85402277d605e37bd53ffd }}&lt;/ref&gt; This defence is mediated by toxins called &quot;ribosome-inactivating proteins&quot; that attack the molecular machinery of invading parasites.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hamilton PT, Peng F, Boulanger MJ, Perlman SJ | title = A ribosome-inactivating protein in a Drosophila defensive symbiont | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 113 | issue = 2 | pages = 350–5 | date = January 2016 | pmid = 26712000 | pmc = 4720295 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.1518648113 | bibcode = 2016PNAS..113..350H }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ballinger MJ, Perlman SJ | title = Generality of toxins in defensive symbiosis: Ribosome-inactivating proteins and defense against parasitic wasps in Drosophila | journal = PLOS Pathogens | volume = 13 | issue = 7 | pages = e1006431 | date = July 2017 | pmid = 28683136 | pmc = 5500355 | doi = 10.1371/journal.ppat.1006431 }}&lt;/ref&gt; These ''Spiroplasma'' toxins represent one of the first examples of a defensive symbiosis with a mechanistic understanding for defensive symbiosis between an insect endosymbiont and its host.

''[[Sodalis glossinidius]]'' is a secondary endosymbiont of tsetse flies that lives inter- and intracellularly in various host tissues, including the midgut and hemolymph. Phylogenetic studies have not indicated a correlation between evolution of ''[[Sodalis]]'' and tsetse.&lt;ref&gt;Aksoy, S., Pourhosseini, A. &amp; Chow, A. 1995. Mycetome endosymbionts of tsetse flies constitute a distinct lineage related to Enterobacteriaceae. Insect Mol Biol. '''4''', 15–22.&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike tsetse's primary symbiont ''Wigglesworthia'', though, ''Sodalis'' has been cultured ''in vitro''.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid3662675&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Welburn SC, Maudlin I, Ellis DS | title = In vitro cultivation of rickettsia-like-organisms from Glossina spp | journal = Annals of Tropical Medicine and Parasitology | volume = 81 | issue = 3 | pages = 331–5 | date = June 1987 | pmid = 3662675 | doi = 10.1080/00034983.1987.11812127 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many other insects have secondary endosymbionts not reviewed here.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15189221&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zchori-Fein E, Perlman SJ | title = Distribution of the bacterial symbiont Cardinium in arthropods | journal = Molecular Ecology | volume = 13 | issue = 7 | pages = 2009–16 | date = July 2004 | pmid = 15189221 | doi = 10.1111/j.1365-294X.2004.02203.x }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid12415315&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Wernegreen JJ | title = Genome evolution in bacterial endosymbionts of insects | journal = Nature Reviews. Genetics | volume = 3 | issue = 11 | pages = 850–61 | date = November 2002 | pmid = 12415315 | doi = 10.1038/nrg931 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Endosymbionts of marine invertebrates===
Extracellular endosymbionts are also represented in all four extant classes of [[Echinodermata]] ([[Crinoidea]], [[Ophiuroidea]], [[Echinoidea]], and [[Holothuroidea]]). Little is known of the nature of the association (mode of infection, transmission, metabolic requirements, etc.) but [[phylogenetic]] analysis indicates that these symbionts belong to the alpha group of the class [[Proteobacteria]], relating them to ''Rhizobium'' and ''Thiobacillus''. Other studies indicate that these [[subcuticular bacteria]] may be both abundant within their hosts and widely distributed among the Echinoderms in general.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Burnett WJ, McKenzie JD | title = Subcuticular bacteria from the brittle star Ophiactis balli (Echinodermata: Ophiuroidea) represent a new lineage of extracellular marine symbionts in the alpha subdivision of the class Proteobacteria | journal = Applied and Environmental Microbiology | volume = 63 | issue = 5 | pages = 1721–4 | date = May 1997 | pmid = 9143108 | pmc = 168468 | doi = 10.1128/AEM.63.5.1721-1724.1997 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some marine [[oligochaeta]] (e.g., ''[[Olavius algarvensis]]'' and ''[[Inanidrillus spp.]]'') have obligate extracellular endosymbionts that fill the entire body of their host. These marine worms are nutritionally dependent on their symbiotic [[chemoautotroph]]ic bacteria lacking any digestive or excretory system (no gut, mouth, or [[nephridia]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Dubilier N, Mülders C, Ferdelman T, de Beer D, Pernthaler A, Klein M, Wagner M, Erséus C, Thiermann F, Krieger J, Giere O, Amann R | title = Endosymbiotic sulphate-reducing and sulphide-oxidizing bacteria in an oligochaete worm | journal = Nature | volume = 411 | issue = 6835 | pages = 298–302 | date = May 2001 | pmid = 11357130 | doi = 10.1038/35077067 | bibcode = 2001Natur.411..298D }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The sea slug ''[[Elysia chlorotica]]'' lives in endosymbiotic relationship with the algae ''[[Vaucheria litorea]]'', and the jellyfish ''[[Mastigias]]'' have a similar relationship with an algae.

==== Dinoflagellate endosymbionts ====

[[Dinoflagellate]] endosymbionts of the genus ''Symbiodinium'', commonly known as [[zooxanthella]]e, are found in [[corals]], [[mollusk]]s (esp. [[giant clam]]s, the ''Tridacna''), [[sea sponge|sponges]], and [[foraminifera]]. These endosymbionts drive the formation of [[coral reefs]] by capturing sunlight and providing their hosts with energy for [[carbonate]] deposition.&lt;ref name=Baker2003&gt;{{cite journal |author=Baker AC |title=FLEXIBILITY AND SPECIFICITY IN CORAL-ALGAL SYMBIOSIS: Diversity, Ecology, and Biogeography of Symbiodinium |journal=Annual Review of Ecology, Evolution, and Systematics |volume=34 |pages=661–89 |date=November 2003 |doi=10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.34.011802.132417 |url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/b3c5931f92fd1a44d15a6ea04ad78b2bb7ed5b39 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Previously thought to be a single species, molecular [[phylogenetic]] evidence over the past couple decades has shown there to be great diversity in ''Symbiodinium''. In some cases, there is specificity between host and ''Symbiodinium'' [[clade]]. More often, however, there is an ecological distribution of ''Symbiodinium'', the symbionts switching between hosts with apparent ease. When reefs become environmentally stressed, this distribution of symbionts is related to the observed pattern of [[coral bleaching]] and recovery. Thus, the distribution of ''Symbiodinium'' on coral reefs and its role in coral bleaching presents one of the most complex and interesting current problems in reef [[ecology]].&lt;ref name=Baker2003/&gt;

===Endosymbionts of phytoplankton===
{{Further|Microbial loop}}

In marine environments, bacterial endosymbionts have more recently been discovered.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Villareal|first=Tracy | name-list-format = vanc |date=1994|title=Widespread occurrence of the Hemiaulus-cyanobacterial symbiosis in the southwest North Atlantic Ocean |journal=Bulletin of Marine Science|volume=54|pages=1–7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal | vauthors = Carpenter EJ, Montoya JP, Burns J, Mulholland MR, Subramaniam A, Capone DG |date=20 August 1999 |title=Extensive bloom of a N2-fixing diatom/cyanobacterial association in the tropical Atlantic Ocean|journal=Marine Ecology Progress Series |volume=185 |pages=273–283 |doi=10.3354/meps185273|bibcode=1999MEPS..185..273C}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal| vauthors = Foster RA, Subramaniam A, Mahaffey C, Carpenter EJ, Capone DG, Zehr JP |date=March 2007 |title=Influence of the Amazon River plume on distributions of free-living and symbiotic cyanobacteria in the western tropical north Atlantic Ocean|journal=Limnology and Oceanography |volume=52|issue=2|pages=517–532|doi=10.4319/lo.2007.52.2.0517|bibcode=2007LimOc..52..517F |url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/c30dd362107f207741147e9ca9d6bdf5134ce5af }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Subramaniam A, Yager PL, Carpenter EJ, Mahaffey C, Björkman K, Cooley S, Kustka AB, Montoya JP, Sañudo-Wilhelmy SA, Shipe R, Capone DG | title = Amazon River enhances diazotrophy and carbon sequestration in the tropical North Atlantic Ocean | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 105 | issue = 30 | pages = 10460–5 | date = July 2008 | pmid = 18647838 | pmc = 2480616 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0710279105 }}&lt;/ref&gt; These endosymbiotic relationships are especially prevalent in [[Trophic state index#|oligotrophic]] or nutrient-poor regions of the ocean like that of the North Atlantic.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Goebel NL, Turk KA, Achilles KM, Paerl R, Hewson I, Morrison AE, Montoya JP, Edwards CA, Zehr JP | title = Abundance and distribution of major groups of diazotrophic cyanobacteria and their potential contribution to N₂ fixation in the tropical Atlantic Ocean | journal = Environmental Microbiology | volume = 12 | issue = 12 | pages = 3272–89 | date = December 2010 | pmid = 20678117 | doi = 10.1111/j.1462-2920.2010.02303.x }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;  In these oligotrophic waters, cell growth of larger phytoplankton like that of [[diatom]]s is limited by low nitrate concentrations.&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Foster RA, Kuypers MM, Vagner T, Paerl RW, Musat N, Zehr JP | title = Nitrogen fixation and transfer in open ocean diatom-cyanobacterial symbioses | journal = The ISME Journal | volume = 5 | issue = 9 | pages = 1484–93 | date = September 2011 | pmid = 21451586 | pmc = 3160684 | doi = 10.1038/ismej.2011.26 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Endosymbiotic bacteria fix nitrogen for their diatom hosts and in turn receive organic carbon from photosynthesis.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt; These symbioses play an important role in global [[carbon cycle|carbon cycling]] in oligotrophic regions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal| vauthors = Scharek R, Tupas LM, Karl DM |date=11 June 1999|title=Diatom fluxes to the deep sea in the oligotrophic North Pacific gyre at Station ALOHA |journal=Marine Ecology Progress Series |volume=182|pages=55–67|doi=10.3354/meps182055|bibcode=1999MEPS..182...55S}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;

One known symbiosis between the diatom ''[[Cyanobiont#Diatoms|Hemialus]]'' spp. and the cyanobacterium ''Richelia intracellularis'' has been found in the North Atlantic, Mediterranean, and Pacific Ocean.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zeev EB, Yogev T, Man-Aharonovich D, Kress N, Herut B, Béjà O, Berman-Frank I | title = Seasonal dynamics of the endosymbiotic, nitrogen-fixing cyanobacterium Richelia intracellularis in the eastern Mediterranean Sea | journal = The ISME Journal | volume = 2 | issue = 9 | pages = 911–23 | date = September 2008 | pmid = 18580972 | doi = 10.1038/ismej.2008.56 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Richelia'' endosymbiont is found within the diatom frustule of ''Hemiaulus'' spp., and has a reduced genome likely losing genes related to pathways the host now provides.&lt;ref name=&quot;:5&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hilton JA, Foster RA, Tripp HJ, Carter BJ, Zehr JP, Villareal TA | title = Genomic deletions disrupt nitrogen metabolism pathways of a cyanobacterial diatom symbiont | journal = Nature Communications | volume = 4 | issue = 1 | pages = 1767 | date = 23 April 2013 | pmid = 23612308 | pmc = 3667715 | doi = 10.1038/ncomms2748 | bibcode = 2013NatCo...4.1767H }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Research by Foster et al. (2011) measured nitrogen fixation by the cyanobacterial host ''Richelia intracellularis'' well above intracellular requirements, and found the cyanobacterium was likely fixing excess nitrogen for Hemiaulus host cells.&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot; /&gt;  Additionally, both host and symbiont cell growth were much greater than free-living ''Richelia intracellularis'' or symbiont-free ''Hemiaulus'' spp.&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot; /&gt;  The ''Hemaiulus''-''Richelia'' symbiosis is not obligatory especially in areas with excess nitrogen (nitrogen replete).&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

''Richelia intracellularis'' is also found in ''Rhizosolenia'' spp., a diatom found in oligotrophic oceans.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt; Compared to the ''Hemaiulus'' host, the endosymbiosis with ''Rhizosolenia'' is much more consistent, and ''Richelia intracellularis'' is generally found in ''Rhizosolenia''.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; There are some asymbiotic (occurs without an endosymbiont) Rhizosolenia, however there appears to be mechanisms limiting growth of these organisms in low nutrient conditions.&lt;ref name=&quot;:6&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Villareal |first=Tracy A. | name-list-format = vanc |date=December 1989 |title=Division cycles in the nitrogen-fixingRhizosolenia(Bacillariophyceae)-Richelia(Nostocaceae) symbiosis |journal=British Phycological Journal |volume=24 |issue=4 |pages=357–365 |doi=10.1080/00071618900650371}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cell division for both the diatom host and cyanobacterial symbiont can be uncoupled and mechanisms for passing bacterial symbionts to daughter cells during cell division are still relatively unknown.&lt;ref name=&quot;:6&quot; /&gt;

Other endosymbiosis with nitrogen fixers in open oceans include Calothrix in Chaetocerous spp. and UNCY-A in prymnesiophyte microalga.&lt;ref name=&quot;:7&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zehr JP | title = EVOLUTION. How single cells work together | journal = Science | volume = 349 | issue = 6253 | pages = 1163–4 | date = September 2015 | pmid = 26359387 | doi = 10.1126/science.aac9752 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Chaetocerous-Calothrix endosymbiosis is hypothesized to be more recent, as the Calothrix genome is generally intact. While other species like that of the UNCY-A symbiont and Richelia have reduced genomes.&lt;ref name=&quot;:5&quot; /&gt;  This reduction in genome size occurs within nitrogen metabolism pathways indicating endosymbiont species are generating nitrogen for their hosts and losing the ability to use this nitrogen independently.&lt;ref name=&quot;:5&quot; /&gt; This endosymbiont reduction in genome size, might be a step that occurred in the evolution of organelles (above).&lt;ref name=&quot;:7&quot; /&gt;

===Endosymbionts of protists===
''[[Mixotricha paradoxa]]'' is a protozoan that lacks mitochondria. However, spherical bacteria live inside the cell and serve the function of the mitochondria. ''Mixotricha'' also has three other species of symbionts that live on the surface of the cell.

''[[Paramecium bursaria]]'', a species of [[ciliate]], has a mutualistic symbiotic relationship with green alga called Zoochlorella. The algae live inside the cell, in the cytoplasm.

''[[Paulinella|Paulinella chromatophora]]'' is a freshwater [[amoeboid]] which has recently (evolutionarily speaking) taken on a [[cyanobacterium]] as an endosymbiont.

Many [[foraminifera]] are hosts to several types of algae, such as [[red algae]], [[diatom]]s, [[dinoflagellate]]s and [[chlorophyta]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Joseph Seckbach|author2=Patrick Kociolek|title=The Diatom World|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Va35Mtn9VGYC&amp;pg=PA439|year=2011|publisher=Springer Science &amp; Business Media|isbn=978-94-007-1327-7|page=439}}&lt;/ref&gt; These endosymbionts can be transmitted vertically to the next generation via asexual reproduction of the host, but because the endosymbionts are larger than the foraminiferal [[gamete]]s, they need to acquire new algae again after sexual reproduction.&lt;ref&gt;[https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/9ad3/49668622d7c53c861868ce82fbaa59bba0c4.pdf Origins and early evolution of photosynthetic eukaryotes – Semantic Scholar]&lt;/ref&gt;

Several species of [[radiolaria]] have photosynthetic symbionts. In some species the host will sometimes digest algae to keep their population at a constant level.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Surindar Paracer|author2=Vernon Ahmadjian|title=Symbiosis: An Introduction to Biological Associations|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Z3Y8DwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA155|year=2000|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-511807-0|page=155}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Hatena arenicola]] is a flagellate protist with a complicated feeding apparaturs that feed on other microbes. But when it engulf a green alga from the genus Nephroselmis, the feeding apparatus disappears and it becomes photosyntethic. During [[mitosis]] the algae is transferred to only one of the two cells, and the cell without the algae needs to start the cycle all over again.

In 1966, biologist Kwang W. Jeon found that a lab strain of [[Amoeba proteus]] had been infected by bacteria that lived inside the cytoplasmic vacuoles. This infection killed all the protists except from a few individuals. After the equivalent of 40 host generations, the two organisms gradually became mutually interdependent. Over many years of study, it has been confirmed that a genetic exchenge between the prokaryotes and protists has occurred.&lt;ref&gt;[https://bcmb.utk.edu/people/emeritus/kwang-w-jeon/ Kwang W. Jeon | Biochemistry &amp; Cellular and Molecular Biology – UTK BCMB]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Luigi Nibali|author2=Brian Henderson|title=The Human Microbiota and Chronic Disease: Dysbiosis as a Cause of Human Pathology|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sQ6lDAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA165|year=2016|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|isbn=978-1-118-98287-7|page=165}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Endosymbionts of vertebrates===
The spotted salamander (''Ambystoma maculatum'') lives in a relationship with the algae ''Oophila amblystomatis'', which grows in the egg cases.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid21464324&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Kerney R, Kim E, Hangarter RP, Heiss AA, Bishop CD, Hall BK | title = Intracellular invasion of green algae in a salamander host | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 108 | issue = 16 | pages = 6497–502 | date = April 2011 | pmid = 21464324 | pmc = 3080989 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.1018259108 | bibcode = 2011PNAS..108.6497K }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Endosymbionts of plants===
Chloroplasts are primary endosymbionts of plants that provide energy to the plant by generating sugars.

Of all the plants, ''[[Azolla]]'' has the most intimate relationship with a symbiont, as its cyanobacterium symbiont ''[[Anabaena]]'' is passed on directly from one generation to the next.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid29967517&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Li FW, Brouwer P, Carretero-Paulet L, Cheng S, de Vries J, Delaux PM, Eily A, Koppers N, Kuo LY, Li Z, Simenc M, Small I, Wafula E, Angarita S, Barker MS, Bräutigam A, dePamphilis C, Gould S, Hosmani PS, Huang YM, Huettel B, Kato Y, Liu X, Maere S, McDowell R, Mueller LA, Nierop KG, Rensing SA, Robison T, Rothfels CJ, Sigel EM, Song Y, Timilsena PR, Van de Peer Y, Wang H, Wilhelmsson PK, Wolf PG, Xu X, Der JP, Schluepmann H, Wong GK, Pryer KM | display-authors = 6 | title = Fern genomes elucidate land plant evolution and cyanobacterial symbioses | journal = Nature Plants | volume = 4 | issue = 7 | pages = 460–472 | date = July 2018 | pmid = 29967517 | pmc = 6786969 | doi = 10.1038/s41477-018-0188-8 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://theazollafoundation.org/azolla/the-azolla-anabaena-symbiosis-2/|title=Why is Azolla unique? {{!}} The Azolla Foundation|website=theazollafoundation.org|access-date=2020-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Virus-host associations==
{{main|Endogenous retrovirus}}

The human genome project found several thousand [[endogenous retrovirus]]es, [[endogenous viral element]]s in the [[genome]] that closely resemble and can be derived from [[retrovirus]]es, organized into 24 families.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Villarreal LP |title=Persisting Viruses Could Play Role in Driving Host Evolution |journal=ASM News |date=October 2001 |url=http://newsarchive.asm.org/oct01/feature1.asp |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090508113235/http://newsarchive.asm.org/oct01/feature1.asp |archive-date=8 May 2009  }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Citation needed|reason=It is unclear why this is in the endosymbiosis article. Not everything that interacts with a host is a symbiont. It can be debated whether viruses are even alive, and many retroviruses are no longer active. A convincing argument should be provided for this entry, or it should be removed from the article.|date=August 2019}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Belshaw R, Pereira V, Katzourakis A, Talbot G, Paces J, Burt A, Tristem M | title = Long-term reinfection of the human genome by endogenous retroviruses | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 101 | issue = 14 | pages = 4894–9 | date = April 2004 | pmid = 15044706 | pmc = 387345 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0307800101 | bibcode = 2004PNAS..101.4894B }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{col div|colwidth=30em}}
* [[Anagenesis]]
* [[Endophyte]]
* [[Ectosymbiosis]]
* [[List of symbiotic organisms]]
* [[List of symbiotic relationships]]
* [[Multigenomic organism]]
* [[Protocell]]
{{colend}}

== References ==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Symbiosis]]
[[Category:Microbial population biology]]
[[Category:Environmental microbiology]]
[[Category:Endosymbiotic events]]</text>
      <sha1>2m2uqshhnx0h0mruk5mkpw0xuhxs8ey</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
