  <page>
    <title>Epistle of James</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9688</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939385254</id>
      <parentid>935039635</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-06T03:46:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MagicatthemovieS</username>
        <id>19507760</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>No sources given</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{distinguish|Gospel of James}}
{{short description|One of the 21 epistles in the New Testament}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2015}}
{{Books of the New Testament}}

The '''Letter of James''' ({{lang-grc|Ἰάκωβος|Iakōbos}}), the '''Epistle of James''', or simply '''James''', is one of the 21 [[epistle]]s ([[didactic]] letters) in the [[New Testament]].

The author identifies himself as &quot;James, a servant of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ&quot; who is writing to &quot;the twelve tribes scattered abroad&quot;. The epistle is traditionally attributed to [[James, brother of Jesus|James the brother of Jesus]] (James the Just),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Davids|first=Peter H|series=New International Greek Testament Commentary|title = The Epistle of James: A Commentary on the Greek Text|year=1982|publisher=Eerdmans|location=Grand Rapids, Mich.|isbn=0802823882|edition=Repr.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Evans|first=Craig A|title=Bible Knowledge Background Commentary: John, Hebrews-Revelation|year=2005|publisher=Victor|location=Colorado Springs, Colo.|isbn=0781442281|editor=Craig A Evans}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the audience is generally considered to be [[Jewish Christian]]s, who were dispersed outside [[Palestine (region)|Palestine]].&lt;ref name=&quot;newadvent&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Camerlynck|first=Achille|title=Epistle of St James|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/08275b.htm|encyclopedia=The Catholic Encyclopedia|date=1910|accessdate=16 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;OCA&quot;&gt;[https://www.oca.org/orthodoxy/the-orthodox-faith/doctrine-scripture/new-testament/letters-of-saint-james &quot;Letters of Saint James.&quot;] ''[[Orthodox Church in America]]'', OCA, (n.d.). Accessed 11 Dec. 2018.&lt;/ref&gt;

Framing his letter within an overall theme of patient perseverance during trials and [[temptation]]s, James writes to encourage his readers to live consistently with what they have learned in Christ. He wants his readers to mature in their [[Faith in Christianity|faith]] in Christ by living what they say they believe. He condemns various [[sins]], including [[pride]], [[hypocrisy]], [[discrimination|favouritism]], and [[Defamation#Slander|slander]]. He encourages and implores believers to humbly live by godly, rather than worldly wisdom and to [[Prayer#Christianity|pray]] in all situations.

== Authorship ==
According to Robert J. Foster, &quot;there is little consensus as to the genre, structure, dating, and authorship of the book of James.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Foster2014&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first=Robert J. |last=Foster|title=The Significance of Exemplars for the Interpretation of the Letter of James|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=T4eFQ5Vq8ncC&amp;pg=PA8|date=23 September 2014|publisher=Mohr Siebeck|isbn=978-3-16-153263-4|page=8}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are four &quot;commonly espoused&quot; views concerning authorship and dating of the Epistle of James:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Dan G. McCartney|title=James|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=raBzBQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA14|date=1 November 2009|publisher=Baker Academic|isbn=978-0-8010-2676-8|pages=14–}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# the letter was written by James before the [[Pauline epistles]],
# the letter was written by James after the Pauline epistles,
# the letter is [[pseudonym]]ous,
# the letter comprises material originally from James but reworked by a later editor.&lt;ref name=&quot;McCartney2009&quot; /&gt;

===James===
{{See also|James, brother of Jesus|l1=James, brother of Jesus (James the Just)|James the Great|l2=James, son of Zebedee (James the Great)|James, son of Alphaeus|l3=James, son of Alphaeus (James the Less)}}
{{Religious text primary|section|date=November 2019}}
The writer refers to himself only as &quot;James, a servant of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ&quot; ({{bibleref2|James|1:1}}). Jesus had two [[apostles]] named James: James, the son of Zebedee and James, the son of Alphaeus, but it is unlikely that either of these wrote the letter. According to the [[Book of Acts]], James, the brother of [[John the Apostle|John]], was killed by [[Herod Agrippa I]] ({{bibleref2|Acts|12:1–2}}). James, the son of Alphaeus is a more viable candidate for authorship, although he is not prominent in the scriptural record, and relatively little is known about him. [[Hippolytus of Rome|Hippolytus]], writing in the early third century, asserted in his work ''On the 12 Apostles'':&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=of Rome|first1=Pseudo-Hippolytus|title=&quot;On the Twelve Apostles&quot; and &quot;On the Seventy Disciples&quot;|publisher=newadvent.org|url=http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/0524.htm|accessdate=10 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
{{quote|And James the son of Alphaeus, when preaching in Jerusalem was stoned to death by the Jews, and was buried there beside the temple.}}

The similarity of his alleged martyrdom to the [[stoning]] of James the Just has led some scholars, such as [[Robert Eisenman]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Eisenman, Robert 2002&quot;&gt;Eisenman, Robert (2002), James, the Brother of Jesus&quot; (Watkins)&lt;/ref&gt; and [[James Tabor]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Tabor 2006&quot;&gt;{{Cite book | author-link = James Tabor | last = Tabor | first = James D | title = The Jesus Dynasty: A New Historical Investigation of Jesus, His Royal Family, and the Birth of Christianity | publisher = Simon &amp; Schuster | year = 2006 | isbn = 0-7432-8723-1 | url-access = registration | url = https://archive.org/details/jesusdynastyhidd00tabo }}&lt;/ref&gt; to assume that these &quot;two Jameses&quot; were one and the same. This identification of James of Alphaeus with James the Just (as well as James the Less) has long been asserted, as evidenced by their conflation in [[Jacobus da Varagine|Jacobus de Voragine]]'s medieval [[hagiography]] the ''[[Golden Legend]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://sourcebooks.fordham.edu/basis/goldenlegend/GoldenLegend-Volume3.asp#James%20the%20Less|title=The Life of S. James the Less|last=de Voragine|first=Jabobus|date=1275|website=Fordham.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some have said the authorship of this epistle points to James, the brother of Jesus, to whom Jesus evidently had made a special appearance after his resurrection described in the New Testament as this James was prominent among the [[Disciple (Christianity)|disciples]].&lt;ref&gt;See {{bibleref2|Matthew|13:55}}; {{bibleref2|Acts|21:15–25}};{{bibleref2|1Cor|15:7|esv|1 Corinthians 15:7}}; and {{bibleref2|Galatians|1:19}}, {{bibleref2-nb|Galatians|2:9}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Moo|first=Douglas J|title=The Letter of James|year=2000|publisher=Wm B Eerdmans Publishing co|location=Grand Rapids|isbn=0802837301|editor=D A Carson}}&lt;/ref&gt; James the brother of Jesus was not a follower of Jesus before Jesus died according to John 7:2-5,&lt;ref name=&quot;BG Jn 7:2-5&quot;&gt;[https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=John+7%3A2-5&amp;version=WEB &quot;John 7:2-5&quot;.] ''[[BibleGateway.com]]''. [[World English Bible]] &lt;!-- public domain --&gt;. Retrieved September 18, 2019.&lt;/ref&gt; which states that during Jesus' life &quot;not even his brothers believed in him&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;BWIII 2004 Brother&quot;&lt;/&gt;{{rp|98}}

From the middle of the 3rd century, [[patristic]] authors cited the epistle as written by James, the brother of Jesus and a leader of the [[Early centers of Christianity#Jerusalem|Jerusalem church]].&lt;ref name=&quot;newadvent&quot; /&gt; Not numbered among the [[Twelve Apostles]] unless he is identified as James the Less,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Bechtel|first=Florentine|title=The Brethren of the Lord|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/02767a.htm|encyclopedia=Catholic Encyclopedia|accessdate=16 May 2012|quote=His identity with James the Less (Mark 15:40) and the Apostle James, the son of Alpheus (Matthew 10:3; Mark 3:18), although contested by many Protestant critics, may also be considered as certain.}}&lt;/ref&gt; James was nonetheless a very important figure: [[Paul the Apostle]] described him as &quot;the brother of the Lord&quot; in [[Epistle to the Galatians|Galatians]] 1:19 and as one of the three &quot;pillars of the Church&quot; in 2:9.

Pseudonymous authorship (3 above) implies that the person named &quot;James&quot; is respected and doubtless well known. Moreover, this James, brother of Jesus, is honored by the epistle written and distributed after the lifetime of James, the brother of Jesus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shillington&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Shillington|first1=V. George|title=James and Paul: The Politics of Identity at the Turn of the Ages|date=2015|publisher=Fortress Press|location=Minneapolis|isbn=978-1-4514-8213-3|pages=65–96}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[John Calvin]] and others suggested that the author was the James, son of Alphaeus, who is referred to as James the Less. The Protestant reformer [[Martin Luther]] denied it was the work of an [[Twelve apostles|apostle]] and termed it an &quot;epistle of straw&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ccel.org/s/schaff/history/7_ch04.htm |title=History of the Christian Church, book 7, chapter 4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Sacred tradition|Holy Tradition]] of the [[Orthodox Church]] teaches that the Book of James was &quot;written not by either of the apostles, but by the 'brother of the Lord' who was the first bishop of the Church in Jerusalem (see {{Bibleverse|Acts|15|KJV}}, {{Bibleverse|Galatians|1:19|KJV}}).&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;OCA&quot;/&gt;

===Pseudegraphical===
[[File:Minuscule 319 (GA) f85r.jpg|thumb|The first page of James in [[Minuscule 319]], a Greek minuscule manuscript of the New Testament. ]]
Many scholars consider the epistle to be [[pseudepigrapha]]:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Epistle of James|url=http://earlychristianwritings.com/james.html|work=Early Christian Writings|accessdate=16 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The author introduces himself merely as &quot;a servant of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ&quot; without invoking any special family relationship to Jesus.
* The cultured Greek language of the Epistle, it is contended, could not have been written by a Jerusalem Jew. Some scholars argue for a primitive version of the letter composed by James and then later polished by another writer.&lt;ref name=&quot;TheOxford2001&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=The Oxford Bible Commentary|year=2001|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford|isbn=0198755007|editor=John Barton and John Muddiman|page=[https://archive.org/details/oxfordbiblecomme0000unse/page/1256 1256]|url=https://archive.org/details/oxfordbiblecomme0000unse/page/1256}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The epistle was only gradually accepted into the [[Development of the New Testament canon|canon of the New Testament]].
* Some see parallels between James and [[1 Peter]], [[1 Clement]], and the [[Shepherd of Hermas]] and take this to reflect the socio-economic situation Christians were dealing with in the late 1st or early 2nd century. It thus could have been written anywhere in the Empire that Christians spoke Greek. There are some scholars who argued for Syria.&lt;ref name=&quot;TheOxford2001&quot; /&gt;

==Dating==
Scholars, such as [[Luke Timothy Johnson]], suggest an early dating for the Epistle of James:
&lt;blockquote&gt;The Letter of James also, according to the majority of scholars who have carefully worked through its text in the past two centuries, is among the earliest of New Testament compositions. It contains no reference to the events in Jesus' life, but it bears striking testimony to Jesus' words. Jesus' sayings are embedded in James' exhortations in a form that is clearly not dependent on the written Gospels.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Johnson|first1=Luke Timothy|title=The Real Jesus|date=1996|publisher=HarperOne|isbn=0060641665|page=121|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jAasE041fJYC&amp;q=%22The%20Letter%20of%20James%20also%22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

If written by James the brother of Jesus, it would have been written sometime before [[AD 69]] (or [[AD 62]]), when he was [[James, brother of Jesus#Death|martyred]].

The earliest extant [[manuscript]]s of James usually date to the mid-to-late 3rd century.&lt;ref name=&quot;McCartney2009&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=McCartney|first=Dan G|title=Baker Exegetical Commentary on the New Testament: James|year=2009|publisher=Baker Academic|location=Grand Rapids|isbn=978-0801026768|editor=Robert W Yarbrough and Robert H Stein}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Genre==
James is considered New Testament [[wisdom literature]]: &quot;like [[Book of Proverbs|Proverbs]] and [[Sirach]], it consists largely of moral exhortations and precepts of a traditional and eclectic nature.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Laws|first=Sophie|title=The HarperCollins Study Bible|year=1993|publisher=HarperCollins Publishers|location=San Francisco|isbn=0060655267|pages=[https://archive.org/details/harpercollinsstu00wayn/page/2052 2052]|url=https://archive.org/details/harpercollinsstu00wayn/page/2052}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The content of James is directly parallel, in many instances, to sayings of Jesus found in the gospels of [[Gospel of Luke|Luke]] and [[Gospel of Matthew|Matthew]], i.e., those attributed to the hypothetical [[Q source]]. Compare, e.g., &quot;Do not swear at all, either by [[Heaven in Christianity|heaven]]...or by the earth....Let your word be 'Yes, Yes' or 'No, No'; anything more than this comes from the [[Devil in Christianity|evil one]]&quot; (Matthew 5:34, 37) and &quot;...do not swear either by heaven or by earth or by any other oath, but let your 'Yes' be yes and your 'No' be no, so that you may not fall under [[Divine judgment#Christian|condemnation]]&quot; (James 5:12). According to [[James Tabor]], the epistle of James contains &quot;no fewer than thirty direct references, echoes, and [[allusion]]s to the teachings of Jesus found in the Q source.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Paul and Jesus: How the Apostle Transformed Christianity|last=Tabor|first=James D.|publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster|year=2012|isbn=978-1-4391-2332-4|location=New York|pages=41|quote=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Structure==
Some view the epistle as having no overarching outline: &quot;James may have simply grouped together small 'thematic essays' without having more linear, Greco-Roman structures in mind.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Blomberg 2008 23&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Blomberg |first=Craig |date=2008 |title=James |url= |location=Grand Rapids |publisher=Zondervan |page=23 |isbn=9780310244028}}&lt;/ref&gt; That view is generally supported by those who believe that the epistle may not be a true piece of correspondence between specific parties but an example of [[wisdom literature]], formulated as a letter for circulation. The ''[[Catholic Encyclopedia]]'' says, &quot;the subjects treated of in the Epistle are many and various; moreover, St. James not infrequently, whilst elucidating a certain point, passes abruptly to another, and presently resumes once more his former argument.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;newadvent&quot;/&gt;

Others view the letter as having only broad topical or thematic structure. They generally organize James under three (Ralph Martin&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Martin |first=Ralph |date=1988 |title=James |url= |location=Waco, TX |publisher=WBC |page=xcviii - civ}}&lt;/ref&gt;) to seven (Luke Johnson&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Johnson |first=Luke |date=2000 |title=The Letter of James |url= |location=Grand Rapids |publisher=Pillar |pages=11–16 |isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt;) general key themes or segments.

A third group believes that James was more purposeful in structuring his letter, linking each paragraph theologically and thematically:
{{Quote|James, like the gospel writers, can be seen as a purposeful theologian, carefully weaving his smaller units together into larger fabrics of thought and using his overall structure to prioritize his key themes. |author=Blomberg and Kamell&lt;ref name=&quot;Blomberg 2008 23&quot;/&gt;}}
The third view of the structuring of James is a historical approach that is supported by scholars who are not content with leaving the book as &quot;New Testament wisdom literature, like a small book of proverbs&quot; or &quot;like a loose collection of random pearls dropped in no particular order onto a piece of string.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Some numerous writers and commentators assume so, like William Barclay, ''The Daily Study Bible'', rev. ed., 17 vols. (Philadelphia: The Westminster Press, 1976), Vol 14, The Letters of James and Peter, p. 28.&lt;/ref&gt;

A fourth group uses modern [[discourse analysis]] or Greco-Roman rhetorical structures to describe the structure of James.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Taylor |first=Mark |date=2006 |title=A Linguistic Investigation into the Discource Structure of James |url= |location=London |publisher=T&amp;T Clark |page= |isbn=9780310244028}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United Bible Societies]]' ''Greek New Testament'' divides the letter into the following sections:
{|
|
| valign|
* ''Salutation'' (1:1)
* ''Faith and Wisdom'' (1:2–8)
* ''Poverty and Riches'' (1:9-11)
* ''Trial and Temptation'' (1:12–18)
* ''Hearing and Doing the Word'' (1:19–27)
* ''Warning against Partiality'' (2:1–13)
* ''Faith and Works'' (2:14–26)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Faith versus Works|url=http://www.estudobiblico.org/detalhe/ver/faith-versus-works-289|access-date=5 July 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150706020640/http://www.estudobiblico.org/detalhe/ver/faith-versus-works-289|archive-date=6 July 2015|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| valign|

* ''The Tongue'' (3:1–12)
* ''The Wisdom from Above'' (3:13–18)
* ''Friendship with the World'' (4:1–10)
* ''Judging a Brother'' (4:11–12)
* ''Warning against Boasting'' (4:13–17)
* ''Warning to the Rich'' (5:1–6)
* ''Patience and Prayer'' (5:7–20)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Greek New Testament With Revised Concise Greek-English Dictionary.|year=2011|publisher=Hendrickson Publishers|isbn=978-1598567205|edition=4th Revised|editor=Eberhard Nestle}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
|}

== Historical context ==
A 2013 article in the ''[[Evangelical Quarterly]]''&lt;ref&gt;Jim Reiher, &quot;Violent Language – a clue to the Historical Occasion of James.&quot; ''Evangelical Quarterly''. Vol. LXXXV No. 3. July 2013&lt;/ref&gt; explores a violent historical background behind the epistle and offers the suggestion that it was indeed written by James, the brother of Jesus, and it was written before AD 62, the year he was killed.&lt;ref&gt;On the death of James, see [[Josephus]] Antiquities, 20.9.1 and [[Eusebius]] II.23.1-18.&lt;/ref&gt; The 50s saw the growth of turmoil and violence in [[Roman Judea]], as Jews became more and more frustrated with corruption, injustice and poverty. It continued into the 60s, four years before James was killed. War broke out with Rome and would lead to the [[Siege of Jerusalem (70 CE)#Destruction of Jerusalem|destruction of Jerusalem]] and the [[Jewish diaspora#Roman destruction of Judea|scattering of the people]]. The epistle is renowned for exhortions on fighting poverty and caring for the poor in practical ways (1:26–27; 2:1-4; 2:14-19; 5:1-6), standing up for the oppressed (2:1-4; 5:1-6) and not being &quot;like the world&quot; in the way one responds to evil in the world (1:26-27; 2:11; 3:13-18; 4:1-10). Worldly wisdom is rejected and people are exhorted to embrace heavenly wisdom, which includes peacemaking and pursuing righteousness and justice (3:13-18).

This approach sees the epistle as a real letter with a real immediate purpose: to encourage Christian Jews not to revert to violence in their response to injustice and poverty but to stay focused on doing good, staying holy and to embrace the wisdom of heaven, not that of the world.&lt;ref&gt;Numerous studies argue for a letter- structure to James. See, for example, Euan Fry, &quot;Commentaries on James, I and 2 Peter, and Jude,&quot; The Bible Translator, 41 (July 1990): 330, and F.O. Francis, &quot;The Form and Function of the Opening and Closing Paragraphs of James and I John,&quot; ZNW 61 (1970):110-126.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Doctrine ==

=== Justification ===
{{Main|Justification (theology)|Joint Declaration on the Doctrine of Justification|Sola fide}}
The epistle contains the following famous passage concerning [[salvation]] and justification:
{{quote|14 What good is it, my brothers, if someone says he has faith but does not have works? Can that faith save him? 15 If a brother or sister is poorly clothed and lacking in daily food, 16 and one of you says to them, “Go in peace, be warmed and filled,” without giving them the things needed for the body, what good is that? 17 So also faith by itself, if it does not have works, is dead.

18 But someone will say, “You have faith and I have works.” Show me your faith apart from your works, and I will show you my faith by my works. 19 You believe that God is one; you do well. Even the demons believe—and shudder! 20 Do you want to be shown, you foolish person, that faith apart from works is useless? 21 Was not Abraham our father justified by works when he offered up his son Isaac on the altar? 22 You see that faith was active along with his works, and faith was completed by his works; 23 and the Scripture was fulfilled that says, “Abraham believed God, and it was counted to him as righteousness”—and he was called a friend of God. 24 You see that a person is justified by works and not by faith alone. 25 And in the same way was not also Rahab the prostitute justified by works when she received the messengers and sent them out by another way? 26 For as the body apart from the spirit is dead, so also faith apart from works is dead.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleref2|James|2:14-26|ESV}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

That passage has been cited in Christian theological debates, especially regarding the doctrine of justification. [[Gaius Marius Victorinus]] (4th century) associated James's teaching on works with the heretical Symmachian sect, followers of [[Symmachus the Ebionite]], and openly questioned whether James' teachings were heretical. This passage has also been contrasted with the teachings of Paul the Apostle on justification. Some scholars even believe that the passage is a response to Paul.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Scot |last=McKnight |title=The Letter of James |publisher=William B. Erdmans |location=Grand Rapids, Michigan |series=The New International Commentary on the New Testament |isbn=978-0-8028-2627-5 |year=2011 |pages=259–263}}&lt;/ref&gt; One issue in the debate is the meaning of the Greek word δικαιόω (dikaiόō) 'render righteous or such as he ought to be',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Dikaioo|url=http://www.studylight.org/lex/grk/view.cgi?number=1344|work=Greek Lexicon|accessdate=16 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; with some among the participants taking the view that James is responding to a misunderstanding of Paul.&lt;ref name=&quot;Martin 2009&quot;&gt;Martin, D. 2009. [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BRWj6j2Dswc New Testament History &amp; Literature: 18. Arguing with Paul]. Yale University.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Roman Catholicism]] and [[Eastern Orthodoxy]] have historically argued that the passage disproves the doctrine of justification by faith alone (''sola fide'').&lt;!--Replace with actual book citation--&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Catechism of the Catholic Church|chapter-url=http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/_P66.HTM|chapter=The Theological Virtues: 1815|quote=The gift of faith remains in one who has not sinned against it. But 'faith apart from works is dead':[Jas 2:26] when it is deprived of hope and love, faith does not fully unite the believer to Christ and does not make him a living member of his Body.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Schaff|first=Philip|title=Creeds of Christendom|year=1877|publisher=Harper &amp; Brothers|chapter-url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/creeds1.v.vii.html|chapter=The Synod of Jerusalem and the Confession of Dositheus, A.D. 1672: Article XIII|quote=Man is justified, not by faith alone, but also by works.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The early (and many modern) Protestants resolve the apparent conflict between James and Paul regarding faith and works in alternate ways from the Catholics and Orthodox:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Calvin|first=John|title=Commentaries on the Catholic Epistles|chapter-url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/calvin/calcom45.vi.iii.vii.html|chapter=James 2:20–26|quote=When, therefore, the Sophists set up James against Paul, they go astray through the ambiguous meaning of a term.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|Paul was dealing with one kind of error while James was dealing with a different error. The errorists Paul was dealing with were people who said that works of the law were needed to be added to faith in order to help earn God's favor. Paul countered this error by pointing out that salvation was by faith alone apart from deeds of the law (Galatians 2:16; Romans 3:21-22). Paul also taught that saving faith is not dead but alive, showing thanks to God in deeds of love (Galatians 5:6 ['...since in Christ Jesus it is not being circumcised or being uncircumcised that can effect anything - only faith working through love.']). James was dealing with errorists who said that if they had faith they didn't need to show love by a life of faith (James 2:14-17). James countered this error by teaching that faith is alive, showing itself to be so by deeds of love (James 2:18,26). James and Paul both teach that salvation is by faith alone and also that faith is never alone but shows itself to be alive by deeds of love that express a believer's thanks to God for the free gift of salvation by faith in Jesus.&lt;ref name=WELS&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wels.net/cgi-bin/site.pl?1518&amp;cuTopic_topicID=19&amp;cuItem_itemID=6343 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131220114120/http://arkiv.lbk.cc/faq/site.pl%401518cutopic_topicid19cuitem_itemid6343.htm |archivedate=20 December 2013 |work=WELS Topical Q&amp;A |title=Faith and Works |publisher=[[Wisconsin Evangelical Lutheran Synod]] |accessdate=30 Sep 2015 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

According to [[Ben Witherington III]], differences exist between the [[Apostle]] Paul and James, but both used the [[law of Moses]], the [[Jesus in Christianity#Teachings, parables and miracles|teachings of Jesus]] and other Jewish and non-Jewish sources, and &quot;Paul was not anti-law any more than James was a [[Legalism (theology)|legalist]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;BWIII 2004 Brother&quot;&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=NnDSKgmm4gEC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;vq=james%20was%20a%20legalist&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q=james%20was%20a%20legalist&amp;f=false Shanks, Hershel and Witherington III, Ben. (2004). ''The Brother of Jesus: The Dramatic Story &amp; Meaning of the First Archaeological Link to Jesus &amp; His Family''.] HarperSanFrancisco, CA. Retrieved September 18, 2019. {{ISBN|978-0060581176}}.&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|157–158}}

=== Anointing of the Sick ===
The epistle is also the chief biblical text for the [[Anointing of the Sick]]. James wrote:
{{quote|&lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;Is anyone among you sick? Let him call for the elders of the church, and let them pray over him, anointing him with oil in the name of the Lord. &lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;And the prayer of faith will save the one who is sick, and the Lord will raise him up. And if he has committed sins, he will be forgiven.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleref2|James|5:14–15}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[G. A. Wells]] suggested that the passage was evidence of late authorship of the epistle, on the grounds that the healing of the sick being done through an official body of [[presbyter]]s ([[elder (Christianity)|elders]]) indicated a considerable development of ecclesiastical organisation &quot;whereas in Paul's day to heal and work miracles pertained to believers indiscriminately (I Corinthians, XII:9).&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wells1971&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Wells|first=George Albert|title=The Jesus of Early Christians|year=1971|publisher=Pemberton|location=London|isbn=0301710147|page=[https://archive.org/details/jesusofearlych00well/page/152 152]|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/jesusofearlych00well/page/152}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Canonicity ==
{{see also|Antilegomena|Biblical canon}}
The Epistle was first explicitly referred to and quoted by [[Origen of Alexandria]]{{Citation needed|reason=Your explanation here|date=August 2019}} , and possibly a bit earlier by [[Irenaeus of Lyons]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Davis|first=Glenn|title=Irenaeus of Lyons|url=http://www.ntcanon.org/Irenaeus.shtml|work=The Development of the Canon of the New Testament|accessdate=16 May 2012|year=2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as [[Clement of Alexandria]] in a lost work according to [[Eusebius]] {{Citation needed|reason=Your explanation here|date=August 2019}}, although it was not mentioned by [[Tertullian]], who was writing at the end of the Second Century.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wells1971&quot; /&gt; It is also absent from the [[Muratorian fragment]], the earliest known list of New Testament books.{{Citation needed|reason=Your explanation here|date=October 2016}}

&quot;The Epistle of James was included among the twenty-seven New Testament books first listed by [[Athanasius of Alexandria]] in his ''Thirty-Ninth Festal Epistle'' (AD 367)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Griggs|first=C Wilfred|title=Early Egyptian Christianity|year=1991|publisher=Brill Academic Publisher|location=Leiden|isbn=9004094075|edition=2nd|page=173}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was confirmed as a canonical epistle of the New Testament by a series of councils in the fourth century. Today, virtually all denominations of Christianity consider this book to be a canonical epistle of the New Testament.&quot;{{citation needed|date=November 2019}}

In the first centuries of the Church the authenticity of the Epistle was doubted by some, including [[Theodore of Mopsuestia|Theodore]], Bishop of [[Mopsuestia]] in [[Cilicia]]. Because of the silence of several of the western churches regarding it, [[Eusebius]] classes it among the [[Antilegomena]] or contested writings (''[[Church History (Eusebius)|Historia ecclesiae]]'', 3.25; 2.23). [[Jerome]] gives a similar appraisal but adds that with time it had been universally admitted.{{citation needed|date=May 2014}} [[Gaius Marius Victorinus]], in his commentary on the Epistle to the Galatians, openly questioned whether the teachings of James were heretical.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Marius Victorinus' &quot;Commentary on Galatians&quot; : introduction, translation, and notes|last=1958-|first=Cooper, Stephen Andrew|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=0198270275|location=|pages=265–266|oclc=878694940|date = 24 March 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Its late recognition in the Church, especially in the West, may be explained by the fact that it was written for or by [[Jewish Christians]], and therefore not widely circulated among the [[Pauline Christianity|Gentile Churches]]. There is some indication that a few groups distrusted the book because of its doctrine. In [[Reformation]] times a few theologians, most notably [[Martin Luther]] in his early career,&lt;ref name=&quot;TLSB&quot;&gt;[[The Lutheran Study Bible]], [[Concordia Publishing House]], 2009, p2132&lt;/ref&gt; argued that this epistle should not be part of the canonical New Testament.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Schaff|first=Philip|title=History of the Reformation|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/hcc7.ii.iv.iv.html|quote=The most important example of dogmatic influence in Luther’s version is the famous interpolation of the word alone in Rom. 3:28 (allein durch den Glauben), by which he intended to emphasize his solifidian doctrine of justification, on the plea that the German idiom required the insertion for the sake of clearness.464 But he thereby brought Paul into direct verbal conflict with James, who says (James 2:24), &quot;by works a man is justified, and not only by faith&quot; (&quot;nicht durch den Glauben allein&quot;). It is well known that Luther deemed it impossible to harmonize the two apostles in this article, and characterized the Epistle of James as an &quot;epistle of straw,&quot; because it had no evangelical character (&quot;keine evangelische Art&quot;).}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Stonehouse|first=Ned B|title=Paul Before the Areopagus|year=1957|pages=186–197}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Martin Luther's description of the Epistle of James varies. In some cases, Luther argues that it was not written by an apostle; but in other cases, he describes James as the work of an apostle.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Luther Bible|Die deutsche Bibel]]'' 41:578-90&lt;/ref&gt; He even cites it as authoritative teaching from God&lt;ref&gt;''[[Luther's Large Catechism]]'', [http://bookofconcord.org/lc-5-ourfather.php#para123 IV 122-24]&lt;/ref&gt; and describes James as &quot;a good book, because it sets up no doctrines of men but ''vigorously promulgates the law of God''.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Luther's Works'' (American Edition) 35:395&lt;/ref&gt; Lutherans hold that the Epistle is rightly part of the New Testament, citing its authority in the [[Book of Concord]];&lt;ref name=&quot;TLSB&quot;/&gt; however, it remains part of the Lutheran [[antilegomena]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cyclopedia.lcms.org/display.asp?t1=a&amp;word=ANTILEGOMENA|title=Lutheran Church - Missouri Synod - Christian Cyclopedia|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{wikiquote}}
* [[Abrogation of Old Covenant laws]]
* [[Gospel of James|Protevangelium of James]]
* [[Jacob (name)]]
* [[Pauline Christianity]]
* [[Textual variants in the New Testament#Epistle of James|Textual variants in the Epistle of James]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* {{librivox book | dtitle=Bible: James| stitle=NT 20: James}} Various versions
* {{wikiquote-inline|Epistle of James|''Epistle of James''}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou|[[General epistles|General]] [[Epistles|Epistle]]|||}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Epistle to the Hebrews|Hebrews]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=&lt;small&gt;[[New Testament]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Books of the Bible]]}}
{{s-aft|after=[[First Epistle of Peter|First Peter]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{Epistle of James}}
{{Books of the Bible}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Epistle Of James}}
[[Category:Epistle of James| ]]
[[Category:Canonical epistles|James]]
[[Category:New Testament books|James]]
[[Category:Luther's Antilegomena]]</text>
      <sha1>8orbb2g8gohzhfykdrqwbd4xq0ckfzm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
