  <page>
    <title>Black Death</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4501</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943325029</id>
      <parentid>943280034</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T06:31:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Metonyme</username>
        <id>312680</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses|Black Death (disambiguation)}}
{{Bots|deny=InternetArchiveBot}}
{{short description|Pandemic in Eurasia in the 1300s}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2020}}
{{Use British English|date=August 2016}}
{{Pp-vandalism|small=yes}}
[[File:1346-1353 spread of the Black Death in Europe map.svg|thumb|upright=1.35|Spread of the Black Death in Europe and the Near East (1346–1353)]]
The '''Black Death''', also known as the '''Pestilence''' ('''Pest''' for short), the '''Great Plague''' or the '''Plague''', or less commonly the '''Black Plague''', was one of the most devastating [[pandemic]]s in [[History of the world|human history]], resulting in the deaths of an estimated {{nowrap|75 to 200 million}} people in [[Eurasia]], peaking in [[Europe]] from 1347 to 1351.&lt;ref name=&quot;ABC/Reuters&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.abc.net.au/science/articles/2008/01/29/2149185.htm |title=Black death 'discriminated' between victims (ABC News in Science)|publisher=Australian Broadcasting Corporation |author=ABC/Reuters |date=29 January 2008 |accessdate=3 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Health: De-coding the Black Death&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/1576875.stm |title=Health: De-coding the Black Death |publisher=BBC |date=3 October 2001|accessdate=3 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Black Death's Gene Code Cracked&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://archive.wired.com/medtech/health/news/2001/10/47288|title=Black Death's Gene Code Cracked |work=Wired |date= 3 October 2001|accessdate=12 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Bacteria|bacterium]] ''[[Yersinia pestis]]'', which results in several forms of [[Plague (disease)|plague]] (septicemic, pneumonic and, the most common, bubonic) is believed to have been the cause.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Plague|url=http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs267/en/|website=World Health Organization|accessdate=8 November 2017|date=October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Black Death was the first major European outbreak of plague and the [[second plague pandemic]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://jmvh.org/article/the-history-of-plague-part-1-the-three-great-pandemics/|title=The History of Plague – Part 1. The Three Great Pandemics|last=Firth|first=John|date=April 2012|website=jmvh.org|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=14 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The plague created a number of religious, social and economic upheavals, with profound effects on the course of [[History of Europe|European history]].

The Black Death may have originated in [[East Asia]], but some sources suggest that it may also have originated in Europe before traveling to East Asia, where foci then developed and hence were assumed to be the origin of the disease.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1931312816302086|title=Historical Y. pestis Genomes Reveal the European Black Death as the Source of Ancient and Modern Plague Pandemics|first=Maria |last=Spyrou|display-authors=etal|journal=Cell Host &amp; Microbe|date=8 June 2016|volume=19|issue=6}}&lt;/ref&gt; from where it travelled along the [[Silk Road]], reaching [[Crimea]] by 1343.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/history/british/middle_ages/blackdisease_01.shtml|title=Black Death |publisher=BBC – History |date=17 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; From there, it was most likely carried by [[Oriental rat flea|fleas]] living on the [[black rat]]s that traveled on [[Republic of Genoa|Genoese]] merchant ships, spreading throughout the [[Mediterranean Basin]], reaching the rest of Europe via the Italian peninsula.

The Black Death is estimated to have killed 30% to 60% of [[Demographics of Europe|Europe's population]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last = Austin Alchon | first = Suzanne | title = A pest in the land: new world epidemics in a global perspective | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=YiHHnV08ebkC&amp;pg=PA21| publisher = University of New Mexico Press | year = 2003 | page = 21 | isbn = 978-0-8263-2871-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In total, the plague may have reduced the [[world population]] from an estimated 475&amp;nbsp;million to 350–375 million in the 14th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.census.gov/data/tables/time-series/demo/international-programs/historical-est-worldpop.html|title=Historical Estimates of World Population |publisher=Census.gov |accessdate=28 April 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; It took 200&amp;nbsp;years for Europe’s population to recover to its previous level&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Jay |first=Peter |url=http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,2050585,00.html |title=A Distant Mirror |journal=TIME Europe |date=17 July 2000 |volume=156 |issue=3 |accessdate=25 January 2018 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20080725005418/http://www.time.com/time/europe/magazine/2000/0717/peter.html |archivedate=25 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and some regions like [[Florence]] only recovered by the 19th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;nauert&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Nauert |first1=Charles G. |title=The A to Z of the Renaissance. |date=2006 |publisher=Scarecrow Press |isbn=9781461718963 |page=106}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;jussilamajoral&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Jussila |first1=Heikki |last2=Majoral |first2=Roser |title=Sustainable Development and Geographical Space: Issues of Population, Environment, Globalization and Education in Marginal Regionsons. |date=2018 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=9781351724814 |page=13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;goldthwaite&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Goldthwaite |first1=Richard A. |title=The economy of Renaissance Florence |date=2009 |publisher=Johns Hopkins University Press |isbn=9780801889820 |page=278}}&lt;/ref&gt; The plague recurred as outbreaks until the early 20th century.

== Chronology ==
=== Origins ===
{{Main|Black Death migration}}
The plague disease, caused by ''Yersinia pestis'', is [[enzootic]] (commonly present) in populations of fleas carried by ground [[rodent]]s, including [[marmot]]s, in various areas, including [[Central Asia]], [[Kurdistan]], [[Western Asia]], [[North India]], and [[Uganda]].{{sfn|Ziegler|1998|p=25}} Due to climate change in Asia, rodents began to flee the dried-out grasslands to more populated areas, spreading the disease.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; [[Nestorianism|Nestorian]] graves dating to 1338–1339 near [[Issyk-Kul]] in [[Kyrgyzstan]] have inscriptions referring to plague and are thought by many [[epidemiology|epidemiologists]] to mark the outbreak of the [[epidemic]], from which it could easily have spread to China and India.{{citation needed|date=November 2019}} In October 2010, [[Medical genetics|medical geneticists]] suggested that all three of the great waves of the plague originated in China.&lt;ref name=china&gt;{{cite news |author=Nicholas Wade |title=Europe's Plagues Came From China, Study Finds |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/01/health/01plague.html |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=31 October 2010 |accessdate=1 November 2010 |author-link=Nicholas Wade }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 13th-century [[Mongol conquest of China]] caused a decline in farming and trading. Economic recovery had been observed at the beginning of the fourteenth&amp;nbsp;century. In the 1330s, many natural disasters and plagues led to widespread famine, starting in 1331, with a deadly plague arriving soon after.&lt;ref&gt;The Cambridge History of China: Alien regimes and border states, 907–1368, p. 585.&lt;/ref&gt; Epidemics that may have included the plague killed an estimated 25&amp;nbsp;million across Asia during the fifteen&amp;nbsp;years before it reached [[Constantinople]] in 1347.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | first = George C. | last = Kohn | title = Encyclopedia of plague and pestilence: from ancient times to the present | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=tzRwRmb09rgC&amp;pg=PA31| publisher = Infobase Publishing | year = 2008 | page = 31 | isbn = 978-0-8160-6935-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Sussman GD | title = Was the black death in India and China? | journal = Bulletin of the History of Medicine | volume = 85 | issue = 3 | pages = 319–55 | year = 2011 | pmid = 22080795 | doi = 10.1353/bhm.2011.0054 | url = http://contagions.wordpress.com/2011/11/26/did-india-and-china-escape-the-black-death/ }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The disease may have travelled along the [[Silk Road]] with [[Mongols|Mongol]] armies and traders or it could have arrived via ship.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/china/8102278/Black-Death-may-have-originated-in-China.html |title=Black Death may have originated in China |journal=The Daily Telegraph |date=1 November 2010 |ref=harv|last1=Moore |first1=Malcolm }}&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of 1346, reports of plague had reached the seaports of Europe: &quot;India was depopulated, [[Tartary]], [[Mesopotamia]], [[Syria]], [[Armenia]] were covered with dead bodies&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hecker|1859|p=21}} cited by Ziegler, p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;

Plague was reportedly first introduced to Europe via [[Republic of Genoa|Genoese]] traders from the port city of [[Feodosia|Kaffa]] in the Crimea in 1347.&lt;ref&gt;Wheelis M. Biological Warfare at the 1346 Siege of Caffa. Emerging Infectious Diseases. 2002;8(9):971–75. {{doi|10.3201/eid0809.010536}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Barras|first1=Vincent|last2=Greub|first2=Gilbert|title=History of biological warfare and bioterrorism|journal=Clinical Microbiology and Infection|date=June 2014|volume=20|issue=6|page=498|doi=10.1111/1469-0691.12706|pmid=24894605|quote=In the Middle Ages, a famous although controversial example is offered by the siege of Caffa (now Feodossia in Ukraine/Crimea), a Genovese outpost on the Black Sea coast, by the Mongols. In 1346, the attacking army experienced an epidemic of bubonic plague. The Italian chronicler Gabriele de’ Mussi, in his ''Istoria de Morbo sive Mortalitate quae fuit Anno Domini 1348'', describes quite plausibly how the plague was transmitted by the Mongols by throwing diseased cadavers with catapults into the besieged city, and how ships transporting Genovese soldiers, fleas and rats fleeing from there brought it to the Mediterranean ports. Given the highly complex epidemiology of plague, this interpretation of the Black Death (which might have killed &gt; 25 million people in the following years throughout Europe) as stemming from a specific and localized origin of the Black Death remains controversial. Similarly, it remains doubtful whether the effect of throwing infected cadavers could have been the sole cause of the outburst of an epidemic in the besieged city.}}&lt;/ref&gt; During a protracted siege of the city by the Mongol army under [[Jani Beg]], whose army was suffering from the disease, the army [[Biological warfare|catapulted infected corpses]] over the [[defensive wall|city walls]] of Kaffa to infect the inhabitants. The Genoese traders fled, taking the plague by ship into [[Sicily]], then the Italian mainland, whence it spread north.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.channel4.com/history/microsites/H/history/a-b/blackdeath.html |title=Channel 4 – History – The Black Death |publisher=Channel 4 |accessdate=3 November 2008 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080625094232/http://www.channel4.com/history/microsites/H/history/a-b/blackdeath.html |archivedate=25 June 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Whether or not this hypothesis is accurate, it is clear that several existing conditions such as war, famine, and weather contributed to the severity of the Black Death. Among many other culprits of plague contagiousness malnutrition even if distantly also had an effect as a contributor to such an immense loss in European population since it lead to weakened immune systems.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Baten|first=Joerg|last2=Koepke|first2=Nikola|date=2005|title=The Biological Standard of Living in Europe during the Last Two Millennia|url=https://academic.oup.com/ereh/issue.|journal=European Review of Economic History|volume=9 (1)|pages=61–95|via=EBSCO}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===European outbreak===
{{quote box
| align = right
| width = 25em
| quote = The seventh year after it began, it came to England and first began in the towns and ports joining on the seacoasts, in Dorsetshire, where, as in other counties, it made the country quite void of inhabitants so that there were almost none left alive.&lt;p&gt;... But at length it came to Gloucester, yea even to Oxford and to London, and finally it spread over all England and so wasted the people that scarce the tenth person of any sort was left alive.&lt;/p&gt;
| source = [[Geoffrey the Baker]], ''Chronicon Angliae''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Galfridi Le Baker de Swinbroke, Chronicon Angliae temporibus Edwardi II et Edwardi III|first=Baker|last=Geoffrey|editor1-first=John Allen|editor1-last=Gilles|url= https://books.google.com/?id=h5kKAAAAYAAJ|archive-url=https://archive.org/details/galfridilebaker00gilegoog/page/n27|archive-date=3 August 2008| location=Londini|publisher=apud Jacobum Bohn| year=1847|orig-year=1350| lccn = 08014593 | ol =6996785M| via=[[Internet Archive]]|language=la, en}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

There appear to have been several introductions into [[Europe]]. The plague reached Sicily in October 1347, carried by twelve Genoese galleys,&lt;ref&gt;Michael of Piazza (Platiensis) ''Bibliotheca scriptorum qui res in Sicilia gestas retulere'' Vol 1, p. 562, cited in Ziegler, 1998, p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt; and rapidly spread all over the island. Galleys from [[Feodosia|Kaffa]] reached Genoa and Venice in January 1348, but it was the outbreak in [[Pisa]] a few weeks later that was the entry point to northern Italy. Towards the end of January, one of the galleys expelled from Italy arrived in [[Marseille]].&lt;ref&gt;De Smet, Vol II, ''Breve Chronicon'', p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;

From Italy, the disease spread northwest across Europe, striking France, Spain (which was hit due to the heat – the epidemic raged in the early weeks of July),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.historytoday.com/archive/black-death-greatest-catastrophe-ever |title=The Black Death: The Greatest Catastrophe Ever |website=English |accessdate=18 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Portugal and England by June 1348, then spread east and north through Germany, Scotland and Scandinavia from 1348 to 1350. It was introduced into Norway in 1349 when a ship landed at [[Askøy]], then spread to Bjørgvin (modern [[Bergen]]) and [[Iceland]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite book|title=Iceland's 1100 years: the history of a marginal society |author=Gunnar Karlsson |year=2000 |publisher=London:C. Hurst |page=111 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=4eRLXJpf2EoC |isbn=978-1-85065-420-9 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Finally, it spread to northwestern Russia in 1351. The plague was somewhat more uncommon in parts of Europe with less developed trade with their neighbours, including the majority of the [[Basque Country (greater region)|Basque Country]], isolated parts of Belgium and the Netherlands, and isolated alpine villages throughout the continent.&lt;ref&gt;Zuchora-Walske, Christine, Poland, North Mankato: ABDO Publishing, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Welford|first=Mark|last2=Bossak|first2=Brian H.|date=4 June 2010|title=Revisiting the Medieval Black Death of 1347–1351: Spatiotemporal Dynamics Suggestive of an Alternate Causation|journal=Geography Compass|language=en|volume=4|issue=6|pages=561–75|doi=10.1111/j.1749-8198.2010.00335.x|issn=1749-8198}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to some epidemiologists, periods of unfavorable weather decimated plague-infected rodent populations and forced their fleas onto alternative hosts,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.pnas.org/content/108/35/14527.short|title=Dynamics of the plague–wildlife–human system in Central Asia are controlled by two epidemiological thresholds|website=English|access-date=1 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; inducing plague outbreaks which often peaked in the hot summers of the Mediterranean,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/medical-history/article/4-epidemiology-of-the-black-death-and-successive-waves-of-plague/6B70B323BC04D13C7EBCDBB991B728CB|title=4 Epidemiology of the Black Death and Successive Waves of Plague|website=English|access-date=1 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as during the cool autumn months of the southern Baltic states.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''[https://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=JcdONPwL2wC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA7&amp;dq(2004)+Städtesystem+und+Urbanisierung+im+Ostseeraum+in+der+frühen+Neuzeit:+Wirtschaft,+Baukultur+und+historische+Informationssysteme:+Beiträge+des+wissenschaftlichen+Kolloquiums+in+Wismar+vom+4.+und+5.+September+2003+(LIT,+Munster,+Germany).+German&amp;ots=LZxtzWCMOs&amp;sig=LoUQxk7KqmBkeqOgfZpC4tmByRE#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false]''&quot;. Stefan Kroll, Kersten Krüger(2004). [[LIT Verlag Berlin]]. {{ISBN|3-8258-8778-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, other researchers do not think that the plague ever became endemic in Europe or its rat population. The disease repeatedly wiped out the rodent carriers, so that the fleas died out until a new outbreak from Central Asia repeated the process. The outbreaks have been shown to occur roughly 15 years after a warmer and wetter period in areas where plague is endemic in other species, such as [[gerbil]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|title=Bubonic plague was a serial visitor in European Middle Ages|url=https://www.sciencenews.org/article/bubonic-plague-was-serial-visitor-european-middle-ages|first= Kate |last=Baggaley|date=24 February 2015|magazine=Science News|accessdate=24 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Schmid|first=Boris V.|year=2015|title=Climate-driven introduction of the Black Death and successive plague reintroductions into Europe|journal=Proc Natl Acad Sci USA|doi=10.1073/pnas.1412887112|url=http://www.pnas.org/content/early/2015/02/20/1412887112|accessdate=24 February 2015|volume=112|issue=10|pages=3020–25|pmid=25713390|pmc=4364181|bibcode=2015PNAS..112.3020S}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Middle Eastern outbreak===
The plague struck various regions in the Middle East during the [[pandemic]], leading to serious depopulation and permanent change in both economic and social structures. It spread from China with the [[Mongols]] to a trading post in Crimea, called Kaffa, controlled by the [[Republic of Genoa]]. As infected rodents infected new rodents, the disease spread across the region, including South Africa&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://journals.openedition.org/afriques/2125|title=Putting Africa on the Black Death map: Narratives from genetics and history|website=English|accessdate=15 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;  entering also from southern Russia. By autumn 1347, the plague reached [[Alexandria]] in Egypt, through the port's trade with [[Constantinople]], and ports on the [[Black Sea]]. During 1347, the disease travelled eastward to [[Gaza City|Gaza]], and north along the eastern coast to cities in modern [[Lebanon]], [[Syria]], [[Israel]] and [[Palestinian territories|Palestine]], including [[Ashkelon]], [[Acre, Israel|Acre]], [[Jerusalem]], [[Sidon]], [[Damascus]], [[Homs]], and [[Aleppo]]. Within two years, the plague had spread throughout the entire Muslim empire from Arabia across North Africa.&lt;ref&gt;{{https://www.harpercollins.com/9780062243218/the-great-mortality/|title=The Great Mortality
An Intimate History of the Black Death, the Most Devastating Plague of All Time|John Kelly(2005). [[Harper Collins Publishers]]. {{ISBN|0060006927}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1348–1349, the disease reached [[Antioch]]. The city's residents fled to the north, but most of them ended up dying during the journey.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.thegreatcourses.com/courses/an-economic-history-of-the-world-since-1400.html|title=An Economic History of the World since 1400|website=English|accessdate=23 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Mecca]] became infected in 1349. During the same year, records show the city of [[Mosul|Mawsil]] (Mosul) suffered a massive epidemic, and the city of [[Baghdad]] experienced a second round of the disease. 

[[Muslim]] religious scholars taught that the plague was a “martyrdom and mercy” from God, assuring the believer’s place in paradise. For non-believers, it was a punishment.&lt;ref&gt;{{https://www.harpercollins.com/9780062243218/the-great-mortality/|title=The Great Mortality: An Intimate History of the Black Death, the Most Devastating Plague of All Time|John Kelly(2005). [[Harper Collins Publishers]]. {{ISBN|0060006927}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some Muslim doctors cautioned against trying to prevent or treat a disease sent by God. Others adopted many of the same preventive measures and treatments for the plague used by the Europeans. These Muslim doctors also depended on the writings of the ancient Greeks.{{cn|date=January 2020}}

== Signs and symptoms ==
[[File:Acral gangrene due to plague.jpg|thumb|A hand showing how [[wikt:acral|acral]] [[gangrene]] of the [[Digit (anatomy)|fingers]] due to [[bubonic plague]] causes the skin and [[Tissue (biology)|flesh]] to [[Necrosis|die]] and turn black]] [[File:Plague bubo.jpg|thumb|An inguinal [[bubo]] on the upper thigh of a person infected with bubonic plague. Swollen [[lymph node]]s (''buboes'') often occur in the neck, armpit and groin (''inguinal'') regions of plague victims.]]
Contemporary accounts of the plague are often varied or imprecise. The most commonly noted symptom was the appearance of [[bubo]]es (or ''gavocciolos'') in the groin, the neck and armpits, which oozed pus and bled when opened.&lt;ref name=Byrne2004pp21-9/&gt; [[Giovanni Boccaccio|Boccaccio]]'s description:

{{Quote | style=font-size:100% | In men and women alike it first betrayed itself by the emergence of certain [[Neoplasm|tumours]] in the groin or armpits, some of which grew as large as a common apple, others as an egg&amp;nbsp;... From the two said parts of the body this deadly ''gavocciolo'' soon began to propagate and spread itself in all directions indifferently; after which the form of the [[Disease|malady]] began to change, black spots or livid making their appearance in many cases on the arm or the thigh or elsewhere, now few and large, now minute and numerous. As the ''gavocciolo'' had been and still was an infallible token of approaching death, such also were these spots on whomsoever they showed themselves.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Giovanni Boccaccio|title=Decameron|year=1351|ref=harv|title-link=The Decameron}}&lt;/ref&gt;|sign=|source=}}

The only medical detail that is questionable in Boccaccio's description is that the gavocciolo was an &quot;infallible token of approaching death&quot;, as, if the bubo discharges, recovery is possible.{{sfn|Ziegler|1998|pages=18–19}}

This was followed by acute [[fever]] and [[Hematemesis|vomiting of blood]]. Most victims died two to seven days after initial infection. Freckle-like spots and rashes,&lt;ref&gt;D. Herlihy, ''The Black Death and the Transformation of the West'' (Harvard University Press: Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1997), p. 29.&lt;/ref&gt; which could have been caused by [[Pulicosis|flea-bites]], were identified as another potential sign of the plague.

Some accounts, like that of [[Lodewijk Heyligen]], whose master the [[Giovanni Colonna (cardinal, 1295–1348)|Cardinal Colonna]] died of the plague in 1348, noted a distinct form of the disease that infected the lungs and led to respiratory problems&lt;ref name=Byrne2004pp21-9/&gt; and is identified with [[pneumonic plague]].

{{Quote | style=font-size:100% | It is said that the plague takes three forms. In the first people suffer an infection of the lungs, which leads to breathing difficulties. Whoever has this corruption or contamination to any extent cannot escape but will die within two days. Another form&amp;nbsp;... in which boils erupt under the armpits,&amp;nbsp;... a third form in which people of both sexes are attacked in the groin.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|first=Rosemary|last=Horrox|year=1994|title=Black Death|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=1O_PX2wVD0sC&amp;pg=PA41|publisher=Manchester University Press|isbn=978-0-7190-3498-5|page=41|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Causes==
{{Multiple image
 | align     = right
 | direction = horizontal
 | image1    = Xenopsylla chepsis (oriental rat flea).jpg
 | width1    = 214
 | caption1  = The [[Oriental rat flea]] (''Xenopsylla cheopis'') engorged with blood. This [[species]] of flea is the primary [[Vector (epidemiology)|vector]] for the transmission of ''[[Yersinia pestis]]'', the organism responsible for spreading bubonic plague in most plague epidemics. Both male and female fleas [[hematophagy|feed on blood]] and can transmit the infection.
 | image2    = Flea infected with yersinia pestis.jpg
 | width2    = 180
 | caption2  = Oriental rat flea (''Xenopsylla cheopis'') infected with the ''[[Yersinia pestis]]'' [[Bacteria|bacterium]] which appears as a dark mass in the gut. The foregut (''proventriculus'') of this flea is blocked by a ''Y. pestis'' [[biofilm]]; when the flea attempts to feed on an uninfected [[Host (biology)|host]] ''Y. pestis'' is regurgitated into the wound, causing infection.
}}
[[File:Yersinia pestis fluorescent.jpeg|thumb|''[[Yersinia pestis]]'' (200× magnification), the bacterium which causes bubonic plague&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.avma.org/public_health/biosecurity/plague_bgnd.asp |title=Plague Backgrounder |publisher=Avma.org |accessdate=3 November 2008 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20080516012329/http://www.avma.org/public_health/biosecurity/plague_bgnd.asp |archivedate = 16 May 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

Medical knowledge had stagnated during the [[Middle Ages]]. The most authoritative account at the time came from the medical faculty in Paris in a report to the [[Philip VI of France|king of France]] that blamed the heavens, in the form of a [[Conjunction (astronomy)|conjunction]] of three planets in 1345 that caused a &quot;great pestilence in the air&quot;.{{sfn|Horrox|1994|p=159}} This report became the first and most widely circulated of a series of plague tracts that sought to give advice to sufferers. That the plague was caused by bad air became the most widely accepted theory at the time, the [[miasma theory]]. The word ''plague'' did not at first refer to a specific illness, and only the recurrence of outbreaks during the Middle Ages gave it the meaning which persists in modern medicine.

The importance of [[hygiene]] was recognised only in the nineteenth century; until then streets were commonly filthy, with live animals of all sorts around and human parasites abounding facilitating the spead of [[Transmission (medicine)|transmissible disease]]. One early medical advance as a result of the Black Death was the establishment of the idea of [[quarantine]] in the city-state of [[Republic of Ragusa|Ragusa]] (modern [[Dubrovnik]], Croatia) in 1377 after continuing outbreaks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Sehdev PS | title = The Origin of Quarantine | journal = Clinical Infectious Diseases | volume = 35 | issue = 9 | pages = 1071–72 | year = 2002 | pmid = 12398064 | doi = 10.1086/344062 | url = http://cid.oxfordjournals.org/content/35/9/1071.full }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Today, the dominant explanation for the Black Death is the ''plague theory'', which attributes the outbreak to ''Yersinia pestis'', also responsible for an epidemic that began in southern China in 1865, eventually spreading to India. The investigation of the pathogen that caused the 19th-century plague was begun by teams of scientists who visited Hong Kong in 1894, among whom was the French-Swiss bacteriologist [[Alexandre Yersin]], after whom the pathogen was named.&lt;ref name=Chritakos2005&gt;{{cite book|first=George |last=Christakos |first2=Ricardo A. |last2=Olea |first3=Marc L. |last3=Serre |first4=Hwa-Lung |last4=Yu |first5=Lin-Lin |last5=Wang |title=Interdisciplinary Public Health Reasoning and Epidemic Modelling: the Case of Black Death |year=2005 |publisher=Springer |isbn=978-3-540-25794-3 |pages=110–14}}&lt;/ref&gt; The mechanism by which ''Y. pestis'' is usually transmitted was established in 1898 by [[Paul-Louis Simond]] and was found to involve the bites of fleas whose [[midgut]]s had become obstructed by replicating ''Y. pestis'' several days after feeding on an infected host. This blockage starves the fleas and drives them to aggressive feeding behaviour and attempts to clear the blockage by [[vomiting|regurgitation]], resulting in thousands of plague bacteria being flushed into the feeding site, infecting the host. The bubonic plague mechanism was also dependent on two populations of rodents: one resistant to the disease, which act as [[Host (biology)|hosts]], keeping the disease [[Endemic (epidemiology)|endemic]], and a second that lack resistance. When the second population dies, the fleas move on to other hosts, including people, thus creating a human [[Epidemic typhus|epidemic]].&lt;ref name=Chritakos2005/&gt;

The historian [[Francis Aidan Gasquet]] wrote about the Great Pestilence in 1893{{sfn|Gasquet|1893}} and suggested that &quot;it would appear to be some form of the ordinary Eastern or bubonic plague&quot;. He was able to adopt the epidemiology of the bubonic plague for the Black Death for the second edition in 1908, implicating rats and fleas in the process, and his interpretation was widely accepted for other ancient and medieval epidemics, such as the [[Plague of Justinian]] that was prevalent in the [[Byzantine Empire|Eastern Roman Empire]] from 541 to 700&amp;nbsp;CE.&lt;ref name=Chritakos2005/&gt;

An estimate of the [[case fatality rate]] for the modern [[bubonic plague]], following the introduction of [[antibiotic]]s, is 11%, although it may be higher in underdeveloped regions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cdc.gov/plague/faq/index.html|author=Centers for Disease Control (CDC)|title= FAQ: Plague|date=24 September 2015|accessdate=24 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Symptoms of the disease include fever of {{convert|38|–|41|°C|°F}}, headaches, [[Arthralgia|painful aching joints]], [[nausea]] and vomiting, and a general feeling of [[malaise]]. Left untreated, of those that contract the bubonic plague, 80 percent die within eight days.&lt;ref&gt;R. Totaro ''Suffering in Paradise: The Bubonic Plague in English Literature from More to Milton'' (Pittsburgh: Duquesne University Press, 2005), p. 26&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pneumonic plague]] has a mortality rate of 90 to 95 percent. Symptoms include fever, cough, and [[Hemoptysis|blood-tinged sputum]]. As the disease progresses, sputum becomes free-flowing and bright red. [[Septicemic plague]] is the least common of the three forms, with a mortality rate near 100%. Symptoms are high fevers and purple skin patches ([[purpura]] due to [[disseminated intravascular coagulation]]). In cases of pneumonic and particularly septicemic plague, the progress of the disease is so rapid that there would often be no time for the development of the enlarged lymph nodes that were noted as buboes.{{sfn|Byrne|2004|p=8}}

A number of alternative theories, implicating other diseases in the Black Death pandemic, have also been proposed by some modern scientists (see below&amp;nbsp;— &quot;[[#Alternative explanations|Alternative explanations]]&quot;).

===DNA evidence===
[[File:Bubonic plague victims-mass grave in Martigues, France 1720-1721.jpg|thumb|Skeletons in a mass grave from 1720–1721 in [[Martigues]], France, yielded molecular evidence of the ''orientalis'' strain of ''Yersinia pestis'', the organism responsible for bubonic plague. The second pandemic of bubonic plague was active in Europe from&amp;nbsp;1347, the beginning of the Black Death, until 1750.]]

In 1998, Drancourt et al. reported the detection of ''Y. pestis'' DNA in human dental pulp from a medieval grave.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Drancourt M, Aboudharam G, Signoli M, Dutour O, Raoult D|year=1998|title=Detection of 400-year-old Yersinia pestis DNA in human dental pulp: an approach to the diagnosis of ancient septicemia|journal=Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A|volume=95|issue=21|pages=12637–40|bibcode=1998PNAS...9512637D|doi=10.1073/pnas.95.21.12637|pmc=22883|pmid=9770538|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;. Another team led by [[Marcus Thomas Pius Gilbert|Tom Gilbert]] cast doubt on this identification&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author1=MTP Gilbert|author2=J Cuccui|author3=W White|author4=N Lynnerup|author5=RW Titball|author6=A Cooper|author7=MB Prentice|title=Absence of Yersinia pestis-specific DNA in human teeth from five European excavations of putative plague victims|journal=Microbiology|year=2004|pages=341-354|doi=10.1099/mic.0.26594-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the techniques employed, stating that this method &quot;does not allow us to confirm the identification of Y. pestis as the aetiological agent of the Black Death and subsequent plagues. In addition, the utility of the published tooth-based ancient DNA technique used to diagnose fatal bacteraemias in historical epidemics still awaits independent corroboration&quot;.

Definitive confirmation of the role of ''Y. pestis'' arrived in 2010 with a publication in [[PLoS Pathogens]] by Haensch et al.&lt;ref name=&quot;Haensch2010&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Haensch S, Bianucci R, Signoli M, Rajerison M, Schultz M, Kacki S, Vermunt M, Weston DA, Hurst D, Achtman M, Carniel E, Bramanti B | title = Distinct Clones of Yersinia pestis Caused the Black Death | journal = PLoS Pathogens | volume = 6 | issue = 10 | pages = e1001134 | year = 2010 | pmid = 20949072 | pmc = 2951374 | doi = 10.1371/journal.ppat.1001134 | editor1-last = Besansky | editor1-first = Nora J }}&lt;/ref&gt; They assessed the presence of [[DNA]]/[[RNA]] with [[polymerase chain reaction]] (PCR) techniques for ''Y. pestis'' from the [[Dental alveolus|tooth sockets]] in human skeletons from mass graves in northern, central and southern Europe that were associated archaeologically with the Black Death and subsequent resurgences. The authors concluded that this new research, together with prior analyses from the south of France and Germany, &quot;ends the debate about the cause of the Black Death, and unambiguously demonstrates that ''Y. pestis'' was the [[Disease causative agent|causative agent]] of the epidemic plague that devastated Europe during the Middle Ages&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Haensch2010&quot;/&gt; In 2011, these results were further confirmed with genetic evidence derived from Black Death victims in the [[East Smithfield]] burial site in England. Schuenemann et al. concluded in 2011 &quot;that the Black Death in medieval Europe was caused by a variant of ''Y. pestis'' that may no longer exist.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author1 = VJ Schuenemann | author2 = K Bos | author3 = S DeWitte | author4 = S Schmedes | author5 = J Jamieson | author6 = A Mittnik | author7 = S Forrest | author8 = BK Coombes | author9 = JW Wood | author10 = DJD Earn | author11 = W White | author12 = J Krause | author13 = H Poinar | year = 2011 | url = http://www.pnas.org/content/early/2011/08/24/1105107108.full.pdf+html | title = Targeted enrichment of ancient pathogens yielding the pPCP1 plasmid of Yersinia pestis from victims of the Black Death | journal = PNAS  | date = 29 August 2011 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.1105107108}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Later in 2011, [[Kirsten Bos|Bos]] et al. reported&lt;ref name=&quot;nature_bos&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Bos KI, Schuenemann VJ, Golding GB, Burbano HA, Waglechner N, Coombes BK, McPhee JB, DeWitte SN, Meyer M, Schmedes S, Wood J, Earn DJ, Herring DA, Bauer P, Poinar HN, Krause J | title = A draft genome of Yersinia pestis from victims of the Black Death | journal = Nature | volume = 478 | issue = 7370 | pages = 506–10 | date = 12 October 2011 | pmid = 21993626 | pmc = 3690193 | doi = 10.1038/nature10549 | ref = harv | bibcode = 2011Natur.478..506B}}&lt;/ref&gt; in ''[[Nature (journal)|Nature]]'' the first draft genome of ''Y. pestis'' from plague victims from the same East Smithfield cemetery and indicated that the strain that caused the Black Death is ancestral to most modern strains of ''Y. pestis''.&lt;ref name=&quot;nature_bos&quot;/&gt;

Since this time, further genomic papers have further confirmed the phylogenetic placement of the ''Y. pestis'' strain responsible for the Black Death as both the ancestor&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last= Spyrou | first= Maria A | author2 = Marcel Keller | author3 = R. I. Tukhbatova | author4 = CL Scheib |author5 = EA Nelson | author6 = A  Andrades Valtueña | author7 = GU Neumann | author8 = D Walker | author9 = A Alterauge A | author10 = N Carty | author11 = C Cessford | author12 = H Fetz | author13 = M  Gourvennec |author14 = R Hartle | author15 = M Henderson | author16 = K von Heyking | author17 = SA Inskip | author18 = S Kacki | author19 = FM Key | author20 = EL Knox | author21 = C Later | author22 = P Maheshwari-Aplin | author23 = J Peters | author24 = JE Robb | author25 = J Schreiber | author26 = T Kivisild | author27 = D Castex | author28 = S Lösch | author29 = M Harbeck M | author30 = A Herbig | author31 = KI Bos | author32 = J Krause | title = Phylogeography of the second plague pandemic revealed through analysis of historical Yersinia pestis genomes | journal = Nature Communications | volume = 10 | issue = 4470 | doi = 10.1038/s41467-019-12154-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; of later plague epidemics including the [[third plague pandemic]] and as the descendant&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Wagner|first=David M |author2=J. Klunk |author3=M. Harbeck |author4=A. Devault |author5=N. Waglechner |author6=J. W. Sahl |author7=J. Enk |author8=D. N. Birdsell |author9=M. Kuch |author10=C. Lumibao |author11=D. Poinar |author12=T. Pearson |author13=M. Fourment |author14=B. Golding |author15=J. M. Riehm |author16=D. J. D. Earn |author17=S. DeWitte |author18=J.-M. Rouillard |author19=G. Grupe |author20=I. Wiechmann |author21=J. B. Bliska |author22=P. S. Keim |author23=H. C. Scholz |author24=E. C. Holmes |author25=H. Poinar |date=28 January 2014|title=Yersinia pestis and the Plague of Justinian 541—543 AD: a genomic analysis|journal=The Lancet Infectious Diseases |volume=14 |issue=4 |pages=319–26 |url=http://www.thelancet.com/journals/laninf/article/PIIS1473-3099(13)70323-2/|doi=10.1016/S1473-3099(13)70323-2|pmid=24480148 }}&lt;/ref&gt; of the strain responsible for the [[Plague of Justinian]].  In addition, plague genomes from significantly earlier in prehistory have been recovered.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | title = Early Divergent Strains of Yersinia pestis in Eurasia 5,000 Years Ago | vauthors = Rasmussen S, Allentoft ME, Nielsen K, Orlando L, Sikora M, Sjögren KG, Pedersen AG, Schubert M, Van Dam A, Kapel CM, Nielsen HB, Brunak S, Avetisyan P, Epimakhov A, Khalyapin MV, Gnuni A, Kriiska A, Lasak I, Metspalu M, Moiseyev V, Gromov A, Pokutta D, Saag L, Varul L, Yepiskoposyan L, Sicheritz-Pontén T, Foley RA, Lahr MM, Nielsen R, Kristiansen K, Willerslev E|journal=Cell|volume=163|issue=3|pages=571-82|doi=10.1016/j.cell.2015.10.009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

DNA taken from 25 skeletons from 14th century London have shown the plague is a strain of ''Y. pestis'' almost identical to that which hit Madagascar in 2013.&lt;ref name=guardian/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-26770334|title=Black Death skeletons unearthed by Crossrail project|last=Morgan|first=James|date=30 March 2014|work=BBC News|access-date=20 August 2017|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Alternative explanations{{Anchor|Alternative explanations}} ===
{{Main|Theories of the Black Death}}
The plague theory implicating ''Y. pestis'' was first significantly challenged by the work of British bacteriologist J. F. D. Shrewsbury in 1970, who noted that the reported rates of mortality in rural areas during the 14th-century pandemic were inconsistent with the modern bubonic plague, leading him to conclude that contemporary accounts were exaggerations.&lt;ref name=Chritakos2005/&gt; In 1984, zoologist Graham Twigg produced the first major work to challenge the bubonic plague theory directly, and his doubts about the identity of the Black Death have been taken up by a number of authors, including Samuel K. Cohn, Jr. (2002 and 2013), [[David Herlihy]] (1997), and Susan Scott and Christopher Duncan (2001).&lt;ref name=Chritakos2005/&gt;

It is recognised that an [[Epidemiology|epidemiological]] account of the plague is as important as an identification of symptoms, but researchers are hampered by the lack of reliable statistics from this period. Most work has been done on the spread of the plague in England, and even estimates of overall population at the start vary by over 100% as no census was undertaken between the time of publication of the [[Domesday Book]] and [[Poll tax (Great Britain)|poll tax]] of the year 1377.{{sfn|Ziegler|1998|p=233}} Estimates of plague victims are usually [[Extrapolation|extrapolated]] from figures for the clergy.

In addition to arguing that the rat population was insufficient to account for a bubonic plague pandemic, sceptics of the bubonic plague theory point out that the symptoms of the Black Death are not unique (and arguably in some accounts may differ from bubonic plague); that transference via fleas in goods was likely to be of marginal significance; and that the DNA results may be flawed and might not have been repeated elsewhere or [[Replication crisis|were not replicable at all]], despite extensive samples from other mass graves.&lt;ref name=Chritakos2005/&gt; Other arguments include the lack of accounts of the death of rats before outbreaks of plague between the 14th and 17th centuries; temperatures that are too cold in northern Europe for the survival of fleas; that, despite primitive transport systems, the spread of the Black Death was much faster than that of modern bubonic plague; that mortality rates of the Black Death appear to be very high; that, while modern bubonic plague is largely endemic as a rural disease, the Black Death indiscriminately struck urban and rural areas; and that the pattern of the Black Death, with major outbreaks in the same areas separated by 5 to 15 years, differs from modern bubonic plague—which often becomes endemic for decades with annual flare-ups.&lt;ref name=Chritakos2005/&gt;

McCormick has suggested that earlier archaeologists were simply not interested in the &quot;laborious&quot; processes needed to discover rat remains.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=McCormick|first=Michael|date=1 July 2003|title=Rats, Communications, and Plague: Toward an Ecological History|journal=Journal of Interdisciplinary History|volume=34|issue=1|page=6|doi=10.1162/002219503322645439|issn=0022-1953|url=http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:HUL.InstRepos:3208221|type=Submitted manuscript}}&lt;/ref&gt; Walløe complains that all of these authors &quot;take it for granted that Simond's infection model, black rat → rat flea → human, which was developed to explain the spread of plague in India, is the only way an epidemic of ''Yersinia pestis'' infection could spread&quot;, whilst pointing to several other possibilities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Medieval and Modern Bubonic Plague: some clinical continuities|first =Lars|last=Walloe|page=69|series=Pestilential Complexities: Understanding Medieval Plague|editor=Vivian Nutton|publisher=Wellcome Trust Centre for the History of Medicine at UCL|year=2008|ref=harv}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, Green has argued that greater attention is needed to the range of (especially non-[[commensalism|commensal]]) animals that might be involved in the transmission of plague.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Green|first=Monica|date=2014|title=Taking &quot;Pandemic&quot; Seriously: Making the Black Death Global|url=http://scholarworks.wmich.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?filename=2&amp;article=1000&amp;context=medieval_globe&amp;type=additional|journal=The Medieval Globe|pages=31ff|doi=|pmid=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Anthrax PHIL 2033.png|thumb|[[Anthrax]] skin lesion]]
A variety of alternatives to ''Y. pestis'' have been put forward. Twigg suggested that the cause was a form of [[anthrax]], and [[Norman Cantor]] thought it may have been a combination of anthrax and other pandemics. Scott and Duncan have argued that the pandemic was a form of infectious disease that they characterise as ''hemorrhagic'' plague similar to [[Ebola virus disease|Ebola]]. Archaeologist Barney Sloane has argued that there is insufficient evidence of the extinction of numerous rats in the archaeological record of the medieval waterfront in London and that the plague spread too quickly to support the thesis that ''Y. pestis'' was spread from fleas on rats; he argues that transmission must have been person to person.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |author=M. Kennedy |title=Black Death study lets rats off the hook |journal=The Guardian |isbn=978-0-7524-2829-1|place=London |url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/aug/17/black-death-rats-off-hook |ref=harv|year=2011 }}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |author=B. Slone |contribution= |title=The Black Death in London |date= 2011|edition= |isbn=978-0-7524-2829-1 |issn= |volume= |pages= |place=London |publisher=The History Press Ltd |url= |accessdate=|ref=harv}}.&lt;/ref&gt; This theory is supported by research in 2018 which suggested transmission was more likely by body lice and human fleas during the [[second plague pandemic]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Dean|first1=Katharine R.|last2=Krauer|first2=Fabienne|last3=Walløe|first3=Lars|last4=Lingjærde|first4=Ole Christian|last5=Bramanti|first5=Barbara|last6=Stenseth|first6=Nils Chr|last7=Schmid|first7=Boris V.|title=Human ectoparasites and the spread of plague in Europe during the Second Pandemic|journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences|volume=115|issue=6|date=10 January 2018|pages=1304–1309|doi=10.1073/pnas.1715640115|pmid=29339508|pmc=5819418|language=en|issn=0027-8424}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, no single alternative solution has achieved widespread acceptance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chritakos2005&quot; /&gt; Many scholars arguing for ''Y. pestis'' as the major agent of the pandemic suggest that its extent and symptoms can be explained by a combination of bubonic plague with other diseases, including [[typhus]], [[smallpox]] and [[Respiratory tract infection|respiratory infections]]. In addition to the bubonic infection, others point to additional septicemic (a type of &quot;blood poisoning&quot;) and pneumonic (an airborne plague that attacks the lungs before the rest of the body) forms of the plague, which lengthen the duration of outbreaks throughout the seasons and help account for its high mortality rate and additional recorded symptoms.&lt;ref name=&quot;Byrne2004pp21-9&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Byrne|2004|pp=21–29}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2014, [[Public Health England]] announced the results of an examination of 25 bodies exhumed in the Clerkenwell area of London, as well as of wills registered in London during the period, which supported the pneumonic hypothesis.&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian&quot; /&gt;

The historian George Hussman claimed that the plague had not occurred in [[East Africa]] until the 1900s. However, other sources suggest that the Second pandemic did indeed reach Sub-Saharan Africa.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://journals.openedition.org/afriques/2125|title=Putting Africa on the Black Death map: Narratives from genetics and history|website=English|accessdate=17 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Consequences ==
{{Main|Consequences of the Black Death}}
=== Death toll ===
[[File:Doutielt3.jpg|thumb|upright=1.3|Citizens of [[Tournai]] bury plague victims]]
There are no exact figures for the [[Infection#Historic pandemics|death toll]]; the rate varied widely by locality. In urban centres, the greater the population before the outbreak, the longer the duration of the period of abnormal mortality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Olea Ricardo A. |author2=Christakos G. | year = 2005 | title = Duration assessment of urban mortality for the 14th century Black Death epidemic | url = | journal = Human Biology | volume = 77 | issue = 3| pages = 291–303 | doi=10.1353/hub.2005.0051|pmid=16392633 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It killed some {{nowrap|75 to 200 million}} people in Eurasia.&lt;ref name=&quot;ABC/Reuters&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Health. De-coding the Black Death&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/1576875.stm |title=Health. De-coding the Black Death |publisher=BBC |date=3 October 2001|accessdate=3 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Black Death's Gene Code Cracked&quot;/&gt; According to medieval historian [[Philip Daileader]] in 2007:

{{Quote | style=font-size:100% | The trend of recent research is pointing to a figure more like 45–50% of the European population dying during a four-year period. There is a fair amount of geographic variation. In Mediterranean Europe, areas such as Italy, the south of France and Spain, where plague ran for about four years consecutively, it was probably closer to 75–80% of the population. In Germany and England&amp;nbsp;... it was probably closer to 20%.&lt;ref&gt;[[Philip Daileader]], ''The Late Middle Ages'', audio/video course produced by [[The Teaching Company]], (2007) {{ISBN|978-1-59803-345-8}}.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

A death rate as high as 60% in Europe has been suggested by Norwegian historian Ole Benedictow:
{{Quote | style=font-size:100% | Detailed study of the mortality data available points to two conspicuous features in relation to the mortality caused by the Black Death: namely the extreme level of mortality caused by the Black Death, and the remarkable similarity or consistency of the level of mortality, from Spain in southern Europe to England in north-western Europe. The data is sufficiently widespread and numerous to make it likely that the Black Death swept away around 60 per cent of Europe's population. It is generally assumed that the size of Europe's population at the time was around 80 million. This implies that around 50 million people died in the Black Death.&lt;ref&gt;Ole J. Benedictow, &quot;The Black Death: The Greatest Catastrophe Ever&quot;, ''History TodayVolume 55 Issue 3 March 2005'' (http://www.historytoday.com/ole-j-benedictow/black-death-greatest-catastrophe-ever). Cf. Benedictow, ''The Black Death 1346–1353: The Complete History'', Boydell Press (7 Dec. 2012), pp. 380ff.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
[[File:Paul Fürst, Der Doctor Schnabel von Rom (coloured version).png|thumb|200px|A [[Plague doctor]] and his typical [[Plague doctor costume|apparel]]]]
Half of Paris's population of 100,000 people died. In Italy, the population of [[Florence]] was reduced from 110,000–120,000 inhabitants in 1338 down to 50,000 in 1351. At least 60% of the population of [[Hamburg]] and [[Bremen]] perished,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Snell |first=Melissa |url=http://historymedren.about.com/od/theblackdeath/a/greatmortality_2.htm |title=The Great Mortality |publisher=Historymedren.about.com |accessdate=19 April 2009 |year=2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and a similar percentage of [[London]]ers may have died from the disease as well.&lt;ref name=guardian&gt;{{cite news |url= https://www.theguardian.com/science/2014/mar/29/black-death-not-spread-rat-fleas-london-plague |title=Black death was not spread by rat fleas, say researchers |last1= Thorpe |first1= Vanessa |date= 29 March 2014 |newspaper= The Guardian |publisher= |access-date= 29 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; In London approximately 62,000 people died between 1346 and 1353.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Worlds Together, Worlds Apart, Volume 1: Beginnings to the 15th Century|last=Tignor, Adelman, Brown, Elman, Liu, Pittman, Shaw|first=Robert, Jeremy, Peter, Benjamin, Xinru, Holly, Brent|publisher=W.W Norton &amp; Company|year=2014|isbn=978-0-393-92208-0|location=New York, London|pages=407}}&lt;/ref&gt; While contemporary reports account of mass burial pits being created in response to the large numbers of dead, recent scientific investigations of a burial pit in Central London found well-preserved individuals to be buried in isolated, evenly spaced graves, suggesting at least some pre-planning and Christian burials at this time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | doi=10.1016/j.jas.2015.04.010 |year=2015 |last1=Dick |first1=HC |last2=Pringle |first2=JK |last3=Sloane |first3=B |last4=Carver |first4=J |last5=Wisneiwski |first5=KD |last6=Haffenden |first6=A |last7=Porter |first7=S |last8=Roberts |first8=D |last9=Cassidy |first9=NJ |title=Detection and characterisation of Black Death burials by multi-proxy geophysical methods |volume=59 |pages=132–41| journal=Journal of Archaeological Science |url=http://eprints.keele.ac.uk/500/1/pringle_may_15.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt; Before 1350, there were about 170,000 settlements in Germany, and this was reduced by nearly 40,000 by 1450.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Peasant Fires: The Drummer of Niklashausen|author=Richard Wunderli|publisher=[[Indiana University Press]]|page=52|isbn=978-0-253-36725-9|year=1992}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1348, the plague spread so rapidly that before any physicians or government authorities had time to reflect upon its origins, about a third of the European population had already perished. In crowded cities, it was not uncommon for as much as 50% of the population to die.&lt;ref name=Chritakos2005/&gt; The disease bypassed some areas, and the most isolated areas were less vulnerable to contagion. Monks, nuns and priests were especially hard-hit since they cared for victims of the Black Death.&lt;ref&gt;J. M. Bennett and C. W. Hollister, ''Medieval Europe: A Short History'' (New York: McGraw-Hill, 2006), p. 329.&lt;/ref&gt;

The most widely accepted estimate for the Middle East, including Iraq, Iran and Syria, during this time, is for a death rate of about a third.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://old.nationalreview.com/interrogatory/kelly200509140843.asp|title=Q&amp;A with John Kelly on The Great Mortality on National Review Online|author=Kathryn Jean Lopez|date=14 September 2005|publisher=Nationalreview.com|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120216075334/http://old.nationalreview.com/interrogatory/kelly200509140843.asp|archive-date=16 February 2012|accessdate=9 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Black Death killed about 40% of Egypt's population.&lt;ref&gt;[http://countrystudies.us/egypt/57.htm Egypt – Major Cities], ''U.S. Library of Congress''&lt;/ref&gt; 

=== Economic ===
With such a large [[population decline]] from the Plague, [[wage]]s soared in response to a labor shortage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last =  Scheidel| first = Walter | author-link =Walter Scheidel| title =The Great Leveler: Violence and the History of Inequality from the Stone Age to the Twenty-First Century | publisher = [[Princeton University Press]]| location =| year =2017  | isbn =978-0691165028|url=http://press.princeton.edu/titles/10921.html|pages=292–93, 304}}&lt;/ref&gt; Landowners were also pushed to substitute monetary rents for labour services in an effort to keep tenants.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.britannica.com/event/Black-Death|title=Black Death &amp;#124; Causes, Facts, and Consequences|last=|first=|date=|website=Encyclopaedia Britannica|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=26 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Environmental ===
Some historians believe the innumerable deaths brought on by the plague cooled the climate by freeing up land and triggering [[reforestation]]. This may have led to the [[Little Ice Age]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/science/nature/4755328.stm |title=Europe's chill linked to disease|date=27 February 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;
=== Persecutions ===
{{See also|Jewish persecutions during the Black Death}}
[[File:Nuremberg chronicles - Dance of Death (CCLXIIIIv).jpg|thumb|Inspired by the Black Death, ''The Dance of Death'', or ''[[Danse Macabre]]'', an [[allegory]] on the universality of death, was a common painting motif in the late medieval period.]]
Renewed religious fervour and [[fanaticism]] bloomed in the wake of the Black Death. Some Europeans targeted &quot;various groups such as [[Jews]], [[friar]]s, foreigners, beggars, [[pilgrim]]s&quot;,&lt;ref name=nirenberg&gt;David Nirenberg, ''Communities of Violence'', 1998, {{ISBN|0-691-05889-X}}.&lt;/ref&gt; lepers,&lt;ref name=nirenberg/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;R.I. Moore ''The Formation of a Persecuting Society'', Oxford, 1987 {{ISBN|0-631-17145-2}}.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Romani people|Romani]], blaming them for the crisis. [[Leprosy|Lepers]], and others with skin diseases such as [[acne]] or [[psoriasis]], were killed throughout Europe.

Because 14th-century healers and governments were at a loss to explain or stop the desease, Europeans turned to [[Astrology|astrological]] forces, earthquakes, and the poisoning of wells by Jews as possible reasons for outbreaks.&lt;ref name=Bennet&amp;Hollister2006/&gt; Many believed the epidemic was a [[Divine retribution|punishment by God]] for their [[Sin|sins]], and could be relieved by winning [[Forgiveness#God's forgiveness|God's forgiveness]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.history.com/topics/black-death|title=Black Death|last=|first=|date=2010|website=history.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There were many attacks against [[History of European Jews in the Middle Ages|Jewish]] communities.&lt;ref name=JewishEncyclopedia&gt;[http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=1114&amp;letter=B Black Death], Jewishencyclopedia.com&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Strasbourg massacre]] of February 1349, about 2,000 Jews were murdered.&lt;ref name=JewishEncyclopedia/&gt; In August 1349, the Jewish communities in [[Mainz]] and [[Cologne]] were annihilated. By 1351, 60 major and 150 smaller Jewish communities had been destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishhistory.org.il/history.php?startyear=1340&amp;endyear=1349 &quot;Jewish History 1340–1349&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt; These massacres eventually died out in Western Europe, only to continue on in Eastern Europe. During this period many Jews relocated to Poland, where they received a warm welcome from King [[Casimir III the Great|Casimir the Great]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Robert S.|last=Gottfried|title=Black Death|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=oK4HTBcdSJsC&amp;pg=PA74|year=2010|publisher=Simon and Schuster|isbn=978-1-4391-1846-7|orig-year=1983|page=74}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Recurrence ===
{{Main|Second plague pandemic}}
[[File:Great plague of london-1665.jpg|thumb|upright|The Great Plague of London, in 1665, killed up to 100,000 people.]]
The plague repeatedly returned to haunt Europe and the Mediterranean throughout the 14th to 17th centuries.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=x2EBkPNnUXEC&amp;pg=PA25 The Great Plague]''&quot;. Stephen Porter (2009). Amberley Publishing. p. 25. {{ISBN|1-84868-087-2}}.&lt;/ref&gt; According to Biraben, the plague was present somewhere in Europe in every year between 1346 and 1671.&lt;ref&gt;J. N. Hays (1998). &quot;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=iMHmn9c38QgC&amp;pg=PA58 The burdens of disease: epidemics and human response in western history.]''&quot;. p. 58. {{ISBN|0-8135-2528-4}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Plague (disease)#Second Pandemic: Black Death|Second Pandemic]] was particularly widespread in the following years: 1360–1363; 1374; 1400; 1438–1439; 1456–1457; 1464–1466; 1481–1485; 1500–1503; 1518–1531; 1544–1548; 1563–1566; 1573–1588; 1596–1599; 1602–1611; 1623–1640; 1644–1654; and 1664–1667. Subsequent outbreaks, though severe, marked the retreat from most of Europe (18th&amp;nbsp;century) and northern Africa (19th&amp;nbsp;century).&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=GyE8Qt-kS1kC&amp;pg=PA46 Epidemics and pandemics: their impacts on human history]''&quot;. J. N. Hays (2005). p. 46. {{ISBN|1-85109-658-2}}.&lt;/ref&gt; According to Geoffrey Parker, &quot;[[Early modern France|France]] alone lost almost a million people to the plague in the epidemic of 1628–31.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Geoffrey Parker (2001). &quot;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=qy8y8rHgucoC&amp;pg=PA7 Europe in crisis, 1598–1648]''&quot;. Wiley-Blackwell. p. 7. {{ISBN|0-631-22028-3}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

In England, in the absence of census figures, historians propose a range of pre-incident population figures from as high as 7&amp;nbsp;million to as low as 4&amp;nbsp;million in 1300,&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20080504134636/http://eh.net/bookreviews/library/1053 ''The Black Death in Egypt and England: A Comparative Study''], Stuart J. Borsch, Austin: University of Texas&lt;/ref&gt; and a post-incident population figure as low as 2&amp;nbsp;million.&lt;ref&gt;Secondary sources such as the ''Cambridge History of Medieval England'' often contain discussions of methodology in reaching these figures that are necessary reading for anyone wishing to understand this controversial episode in more detail.&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of 1350, the Black Death subsided, but there were further outbreaks occurred in 1361–1362, 1369, 1379–1383, 1389–1393, and throughout the first half of the 15th&amp;nbsp;century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/history/british/middle_ages/black_09.shtml |title= Black Death |publisher=BBC – History |accessdate=3 November 2008|page=131}}&lt;/ref&gt; An outbreak in 1471 took as much as 10–15% of the population, while the death rate of the plague of 1479–1480 could have been as high as 20%.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|first=Robert S.|last=Gottfried|title=The Black Death: Natural and Human Disaster in Medieval Europe|edition=|publisher=Hale|location=London|year=1983|isbn=978-0-7090-1299-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; The most general outbreaks in [[House of Tudor|Tudor]] and [[House of Stuart|Stuart]] England seem to have begun in 1498, 1535, 1543, 1563, 1589, 1603, 1625, and 1636, and ended with the [[Great Plague of London]] in 1665.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/history/voices/voices_salisbury.shtml |title=BBC – Radio 4 Voices of the Powerless – 29 August 2002 Plague in Tudor and Stuart Britain |publisher=BBC |accessdate=3 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Chumbunt.png|thumb|left|[[Moscow plague riot of 1771|Plague riot]] in Moscow in 1771: during the course of the [[1770–1772 Russian plague|city's plague]], between 50,000 and 100,000 people died, 17–33% of its population.]]
In 1466, perhaps 40,000&amp;nbsp;people died of the plague in Paris.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite EB1911 |wstitle=Plague |volume=21 |page=694}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the 16th and 17th centuries, the plague was present in Paris around 30 percent of the time.&lt;ref&gt;Vanessa Harding (2002). &quot;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=JCPXfSUlUV8C&amp;pg=PA25 The dead and the living in Paris and London, 1500–1670.]''&quot;. p. 25. {{ISBN|0-521-81126-0}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The Black Death ravaged Europe for three years before it continued on into Russia, where the disease was present somewhere in the country 25 times between 1350 and 1490.{{sfn|Byrne|2004|p=62}} Plague epidemics ravaged London in 1563, 1593, 1603, 1625, 1636, and 1665,&lt;ref&gt;Vanessa Harding (2002). &quot;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=JCPXfSUlUV8C The dead and the living in Paris and London, 1500–1670.]''&quot;. p. 24. {{ISBN|0-521-81126-0}}.&lt;/ref&gt; reducing its population by 10 to 30% during those years.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.history.ac.uk/cmh/epitwig.html Plague in London: spatial and temporal aspects of mortality]&quot;, J. A. I. Champion, ''Epidemic Disease in London'', ''Centre for Metropolitan History Working Papers Series'', No. 1 (1993).&lt;/ref&gt; Over 10% of [[Amsterdam]]'s population died in 1623–1625, and again in 1635–1636, 1655, and 1664.&lt;ref&gt;[http://history.wisc.edu/sommerville/351/351-012.htm Geography, climate, population, economy, society] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100203042756/http://history.wisc.edu/sommerville/351/351-012.htm |date=3 February 2010 }}. J.P. Sommerville.&lt;/ref&gt; Plague occurred in [[Venice]] 22 times between 1361 and 1528.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=2DlGaWQBDQEC&amp;pg=PA151 Crisis and Change in the Venetian Economy in the Sixteenth and Seventeenth Centuries]''&quot;. Brian Pullan. (2006). p. 151. {{ISBN|0-415-37700-5}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The plague of 1576–1577 killed 50,000 in Venice, almost a third of the population.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=fQxAkrbksTEC&amp;pg=PA41 Medicine and society in early modern Europe]''&quot;. Mary Lindemann (1999). [[Cambridge University Press]]. p. 41. {{ISBN|0-521-42354-6}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Late outbreaks in central Europe included the [[1629–1631 Italian plague|Italian Plague of 1629–1631]], which is associated with troop movements during the [[Thirty Years' War]], and the [[Great Plague of Vienna]] in 1679. Over 60% of Norway's population died in 1348–1350.&lt;ref name=&quot;forskning&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.forskning.no/Artikler/2004/juli/1090833676.68 |title=Svartedauden enda verre enn antatt |publisher=Forskning.no |author=Harald Aastorp |date=1 August 2004 |accessdate=3 January 2009 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080331003935/http://www.forskning.no/Artikler/2004/juli/1090833676.68 |archive-date=31 March 2008 |url-status=dead  }}&lt;/ref&gt; The last plague outbreak ravaged [[Oslo]] in 1654.&lt;ref name=&quot;cripkl&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dnms.no/index.php?kat_id=16&amp;art_id=87 |title=DNMS.NO : Michael: 2005 : 03/2005 : Book review: Black Death and hard facts |publisher=Dnms.no |author=Øivind Larsen |accessdate=3 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the first half of the 17th century, a plague claimed some 1.7 million victims in Italy, or about 14% of the population.&lt;ref&gt;Karl Julius Beloch, ''Bevölkerungsgeschichte Italiens'', volume 3, pp. 359–60.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1656, the plague killed about half of [[Naples]]' 300,000 inhabitants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://faculty.ed.umuc.edu/~jmatthew/naples/goldenage.htm |title=Naples in the 1600s |publisher=Faculty.ed.umuc.edu |accessdate=3 November 2008 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081010145720/http://faculty.ed.umuc.edu/~jmatthew/naples/goldenage.htm |archivedate=10 October 2008  }}&lt;/ref&gt; More than 1.25 million deaths resulted from the extreme incidence of plague in 17th-century [[Habsburg Spain|Spain]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://libro.uca.edu/payne1/payne15.htm The Seventeenth-Century Decline], S. G. Payne, ''A History of Spain and Portugal''&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Great Plague of Seville|plague of 1649]] probably reduced the population of [[Seville]] by half.&lt;ref name=&quot;pandemics&quot;/&gt; In 1709–1713, a [[Great Northern War plague outbreak|plague epidemic that followed the Great Northern War]] (1700–1721, [[Swedish Empire|Sweden]] v. Russia and allies)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://depts.washington.edu/baltic/papers/poland.htm|title=Kathy McDonough, Empire of Poland|publisher=Depts.washington.edu|accessdate=3 November 2008|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081011134718/http://depts.washington.edu/baltic/papers/poland.htm|archivedate=11 October 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; killed about 100,000 in Sweden,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=IcljzNyv4EgC&amp;pg=PA21 Bubonic plague in early modern Russia: public health and urban disaster]''&quot;. John T. Alexander (2002). [[Oxford University Press|Oxford University Press US]]. p. 21. {{ISBN|0-19-515818-0}}.&lt;/ref&gt; and 300,000 in [[Prussia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pandemics&quot;&gt;&quot;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=djPWGnvBm08C&amp;pg=PA72 Armies of pestilence: the effects of pandemics on history]''&quot;. James Clarke &amp; Co. (2004). p. 72. {{ISBN|0-227-17240-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; The plague killed two-thirds of the inhabitants of [[Helsinki]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tabblo.com/studio/stories/view/409531/ |title=Ruttopuisto – Plague Park |publisher=Tabblo.com |accessdate=3 November 2008 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080411112934/http://www.tabblo.com/studio/stories/view/409531/ |archivedate=11 April 2008 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; and claimed a third of [[Stockholm]]'s population.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=sB7rtxDpeB4C&amp;pg=PA9 Stockholm: A Cultural History]''&quot;. Tony Griffiths (2009). [[Oxford University Press|Oxford University Press US]]. p. 9. {{ISBN|0-19-538638-8}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Europe's last major epidemic occurred in 1720 in [[Great Plague of Marseille|Marseille]].&lt;ref name=&quot;forskning&quot;/&gt;

[[File:World distribution of plague 1998.PNG|thumb|Worldwide distribution of plague-infected animals, 1998]]
The Black Death ravaged much of the [[Muslim world|Islamic world]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ucalgary.ca/applied_history/tutor/islam/mongols/blackDeath.html |title=The Islamic World to 1600: The Mongol Invasions (The Black Death) |publisher=Ucalgary.ca |accessdate=10 December 2011 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090721033845/http://www.ucalgary.ca/applied_history/tutor/islam/mongols/blackDeath.html |archivedate=21 July 2009  }}&lt;/ref&gt; Plague was present in at least one location in the Islamic world virtually every year between 1500 and 1850.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | first = Joseph Patrick | last = Byrne | title = Encyclopedia of Pestilence, Pandemics, and Plagues: A–M | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=5Pvi-ksuKFIC&amp;pg=PA519| publisher = ABC-CLIO | year = 2008 | page = 519 | isbn = 978-0-313-34102-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Plague repeatedly struck the cities of North Africa. [[Algiers]] lost 30,000–50,000 inhabitants to it in 1620–1621, and again in 1654–1657, 1665, 1691, and 1740–1742.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=5q9zcB3JS40C&amp;pg=PA18 Christian Slaves, Muslim Masters: White Slavery in the Mediterranean, the Barbary Coast and Italy, 1500–1800]''&quot;. Robert Davis (2004). {{ISBN|1-4039-4551-9}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Plague remained a major event in [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] society until the second quarter of the 19th century. Between 1701 and 1750, thirty-seven larger and smaller epidemics were recorded in [[Constantinople]], and an additional thirty-one between 1751 and 1800.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |authors=Université de Strasbourg. Institut de turcologie, Université de Strasbourg. Institut d'études turques, Association pour le développement des études turques.|title=Turcica|publisher=Éditions Klincksieck|year=1998|page=198}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Baghdad]] has suffered severely from visitations of the plague, and sometimes two-thirds of its population has been wiped out.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=F2TGkO7G43oC&amp;pg=PA99 The Fertile Crescent, 1800–1914: a documentary economic history]''&quot;. Charles Philip Issawi (1988). [[Oxford University Press|Oxford University Press US]]. p. 99. {{ISBN|0-19-504951-9}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Third plague pandemic ===
{{Main|Third plague pandemic}}
The third plague pandemic (1855–1859) started in China in the mid-19th century, spreading to all inhabited continents and killing 10 million people in India alone.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/321/5890/773 Infectious Diseases: Plague Through History], sciencemag.org&lt;/ref&gt; Twelve plague outbreaks in Australia between 1900 and 1925 resulted in well over 1,000 deaths, chiefly in Sydney. This led to the establishment of a Public Health Department there which undertook some leading-edge research on plague transmission from rat fleas to humans via the bacillus ''Yersinia pestis''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sydney.edu.au/medicine/museum/mwmuseum/index.php/Bubonic_Plague_comes_to_Sydney_in_1900 Bubonic Plague comes to Sydney in 1900], University of Sydney, Sydney Medical School&lt;/ref&gt;

The first North American plague epidemic was the [[San Francisco plague of 1900–1904]], followed by another outbreak in 1907–1908.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Chase |first=Marilyn |title=The Barbary Plague: The Black Death in Victorian San Francisco |publisher=Random House Digital |year=2004 |isbn=978-0-375-75708-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Echenberg |first=Myron |title=Plague Ports: The Global Urban Impact of Bubonic Plague: 1894–1901 |location=Sacramento |publisher=New York University Press |year=2007 |isbn=978-0-8147-2232-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Kraut |first=Alan M. |title=Silent travelers: germs, genes, and the &quot;immigrant menace&quot; |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=EIqwDj9umzYC |year=1995 |publisher=JHU Press |isbn=978-0-8018-5096-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Modern treatment methods include [[insecticide]]s, the use of [[antibiotic]]s, and a [[Waldemar Haffkine#Anti-plague vaccine|plague vaccine]]. It is feared that the plague bacterium could develop [[drug resistance]] and again become a major health threat. One case of a drug-resistant form of the bacterium was found in [[Madagascar]] in 1995.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scidev.net/en/health/antibiotic-resistance/news/drugresistant-plague-a-major-threat-say-scient.html Drug-resistant plague a 'major threat', say scientists], SciDev.Net.&lt;/ref&gt; A further outbreak in Madagascar was reported in November 2014.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.who.int/csr/don/21-november-2014-plague/en/ |title=Plague – Madagascar |date=21 November 2014 |publisher=World Health Organisation |accessdate=26 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; In October 2017 the [[21st century Madagascar plague outbreaks|deadliest outbreak of the plague]] in modern times hit Madagascar, killing 170 people and infecting thousands.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.wsj.com/articles/madagascar-wrestles-with-worst-outbreak-of-plague-in-half-a-century-1510788541|title=Madagascar Wrestles With Worst Outbreak of Plague in Half a Century|last=Wexler|first=Alexandra|date=16 November 2017|work=Wall Street Journal|access-date=17 November 2017|last2=Antoy|first2=Amir|language=en-US|issn=0099-9660}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Names{{Anchor|Etymology|Name|Naming}} ==
The phrase {{nowrap|&quot;black death&quot;}} (''{{lang|la|mors nigra}}'') was used in 1350 by Simon de Covino or Couvin, a Belgian astronomer, who wrote the poem &quot;On the Judgment of the Sun at a Feast of Saturn&quot; (''{{lang|la|De judicio Solis in convivio Saturni}}''), which attributes the plague to a conjunction of Jupiter and Saturn.&lt;ref&gt;
* On page 22 of the manuscript in [http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b9078277z/f25.image Gallica], Simon mentions the phrase &quot;''mors nigra''&quot; (Black Death): &quot;''Cum rex finisset oracula judiciorum / Mors nigra surrexit, et gentes reddidit illi'';&quot; (When the king ended the oracles of judgment / Black Death arose, and the nations surrendered to him;).
* A more legible copy of the poem appears in: Emile Littré (1841) [http://www.persee.fr/web/revues/home/prescript/article/bec_0373-6237_1841_num_2_1_451584?_Prescripts_Search_tabs1=standard&amp; &quot;Opuscule relatif à la peste de 1348, composé par un contemporain&quot;] (Work concerning the plague of 1348, composed by a contemporary), ''Bibliothèque de l'école des chartes'', '''2''' (2) : 201–243; see especially p. 228.
* See also: Joseph Patrick Byrne, ''The Black Death'' (Westport, Connecticut: Greenwood Press, 2004), [https://books.google.com/books?id=yw3HmjRvVQMC&amp;pg=PA1 p. 1.]
&lt;/ref&gt;
In 1908, Gasquet claimed that use of the name ''{{lang|la|atra mors}}'' for the 14th-century epidemic first appeared in a 1631 book on Danish history by [[Johannes Isacius Pontanus|J.&amp;nbsp;I. Pontanus]]: &quot;Commonly and from its effects, they called it the black death&quot; (''{{lang|la|Vulgo &amp; ab effectu atram mortem vocitabant}}'').&lt;ref&gt;Francis Aidan Gasquet, ''The Black Death of 1348 and 1349'', 2nd ed. (London, England: George Bell and Sons, 1908), [https://books.google.com/books?id=5wMAAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA7 p. 7.]
Johan Isaksson Pontanus, ''Rerum Danicarum Historia'' ... (Amsterdam (Netherlands): Johann Jansson, 1631), [https://books.google.com/books?id=HaExAQAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA476 p. 476.]&lt;/ref&gt; The name spread through Scandinavia and then Germany, gradually becoming attached to the mid 14th-century epidemic as a proper name.&lt;ref&gt;The German physician [[Justus Hecker|Justus Friedrich Karl Hecker]] (1795–1850) cited the phrase in Icelandic (''{{lang|is|Svarti Dauði}}''), Danish (''{{lang|da|den sorte Dod}}''), etc. See: J. F. C. Hecker, ''Der schwarze Tod im vierzehnten Jahrhundert'' [The Black Death in the Fourteenth Century] (Berlin, (Germany): Friedr. Aug. Herbig, 1832), [https://books.google.com/books?id=LhoqAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA3 page 3.]&lt;/ref&gt;
However, ''{{lang|la|atra mors}}'' is used to refer to a pestilential fever (''{{lang|la|febris pestilentialis}}'') already in the 12th-century ''On the Signs and Symptoms of Diseases'' ({{lang-la|De signis et sinthomatibus egritudinum}}) by French physician [[Gilles de Corbeil]].&lt;ref&gt;See: Stephen d'Irsay (May 1926) &quot;Notes to the origin of the expression: atra mors,&quot; ''Isis'', '''8''' (2): 328–332.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=W-JLstM4cU4C|title=Egidii Corboliensis Viaticus: De signis et symptomatibus aegritudium|last=de Corbeil|first=Gilles|date=1907|work=Bibliotheca scriptorum medii aevi Teubneriana|publisher=|isbn=|editor-last=Valentin|editor-first=Rose|location=Harvard University|pages=|language=la|chapter=|orig-year=1200}}&lt;/ref&gt; In English, the term was first used in 1755.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'', 3rd edition, [http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/280254 ''s.v.'']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Pontoppidan |first1=Erich |title=The Natural History of Norway: … |date=1755 |publisher=A. Linde |location=London, England |page=24 |url=https://archive.org/details/naturalhistoryNc2Pont/page/n57}}  From p. 24:  &quot;Norway, indeed, cannot be said to be entirely exempt from pestilential distempers, for the Black-death, known all over Europe by its terrible ravages, from the years 1348 to 50, was felt here as in other parts, and to the great diminution of the number of the inhabitants.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Writers contemporary with the plague described the event as &quot;great plague&quot;&lt;ref name=Bennet&amp;Hollister2006&gt;J. M. Bennett and C. W. Hollister, ''Medieval Europe: A Short History'' (New York: McGraw-Hill, 2006), p. 326.&lt;/ref&gt; or &quot;great pestilence&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;John of Fordun's ''Scotichronicon'' (&quot;there was a great pestilence and mortality of men&quot;) {{Cite book|first=Rosemary|last=Horrox|year=1994|title=Black Death|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=1O_PX2wVD0sC&amp;pg=PA84|isbn=978-0-7190-3498-5|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}

==See also==
{{Div col}}
* [[Plague of Justinian]]
* [[Black Death (film)|''Black Death'' (film)]]
* [[Black Death in England]]
* [[CCR5]], a human gene hypothesised to be associated with the plague
* [[Crisis of the Late Middle Ages]]
* ''[[Cronaca fiorentina di Marchionne di Coppo Stefani|Cronaca fiorentina]]'' (''Chronicle of Florence''); a literary history of the plague, and of Florence up to 1386, by [[Baldassarre Bonaiuti]]
* ''[[Danse Macabre]]''
* [[Death (personification)|Death]]
* [[Doomsday Book (novel)|''Doomsday Book'' (novel)]], a science fiction novel written by Connie Willis
* [[Four thieves vinegar]]; a popular French legend supposed to provide immunity to the plague
* [[Geisslerlieder]]
* [[Globalization and disease]]
* [[Last outbreak of bubonic plague in England]] (1906–1918)
* [[Plague doctor]]
* [[Plague doctor costume]]
* [[Spanish flu]]
* [[Ring a Ring o' Roses]]
* ''[[The Seventh Seal]]'', a film directed by Ingmar Bergman
* [[Timeline of plague]]
{{Div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* {{Cite book |first = Dorsey |last = Armstrong |title = The Black Death: The World's Most Devastating Plague |publisher = The Great Courses |year = 2016 |asin=B01FWOO2G6 | url=http://www.thegreatcourses.com/courses/the-black-death-the-worlds-most-devastating-plague.html |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book| first = Ole Jørgen |last=Benedictow| title = Black Death 1346–1353: The Complete History| year = 2004| isbn = 978-1-84383-214-0|authorlink=Ole Jørgen Benedictow|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZtjwPOB7aMkC |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|first=J. P.|last=Byrne|title=The Black Death|publisher=London: Greenwood Publishing Group|year= 2004|isbn=978-0-313-32492-5|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=yw3HmjRvVQMC|ref=harv}}
* Cantor, Norman F. (2001). ''In the Wake of the Plague: The Black Death and the World It Made'', New York, Free Press.
* Cohn, Samuel K. Jr., (2002). ''The Black Death Transformed: Disease and Culture in Early Renaissance Europe'', London: Arnold.
* {{Cite book |first = Dorothy |last = Crawford |title = Deadly Companions: How Microbes Shaped Our History |publisher = Oxford University Press |year = 2018 |url=https://global.oup.com/academic/product/deadly-companions-9780198815440?cc=us&amp;lang=en&amp; |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|first=Francis Aidan|last=Gasquet|title=The Great Pestilence AD&amp;nbsp;1348 to 1349: Now Commonly Known As the Black Death|year=1893|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CORQjhbgW9QC|isbn=978-1-4179-7113-8|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|last=Hecker|first=J.F.C.|title=Epidemics of the Middle Ages|editor=B.G. Babington (trans)|publisher=London: Trübner|year=1859|url=https://archive.org/stream/epidemicsofmiddl00heck|ref=harv}}
* Herlihy, D., (1997). ''The Black Death and the Transformation of the West'', Cambridge, Massachusetts: Harvard University Press.
* {{Cite book |title=Plagues and Peoples |last=McNeill |first=William H. |year=1976 |publisher=Anchor/Doubleday |isbn=978-0-385-11256-7 |ref=harv}}
* Scott, S., and Duncan, C. J., (2001). ''Biology of Plagues: Evidence from Historical Populations'', Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.
* Shrewsbury, J. F. D., (1970). ''A History of Bubonic Plague in the British Isles'', London: Cambridge University Press.
* Twigg, G., (1984). ''The Black Death: A Biological Reappraisal'', London: Batsford.
* {{Cite book |title=The Black Death |last=Ziegler |first=Philip |year=1998|publisher=Penguin Books |isbn=978-0-14-027524-7 |ref=harv}} 1st editions 1969.

==External links==
{{Commons category|Black Death}}
* {{In Our Time|Black Death|b00bcqt8|Black_Death}}
* [https://www.bbc.co.uk/history/british/middle_ages/black_01.shtml Black Death] at [[BBC]]

{{Black Death}}

[[Category:Black Death| ]]
[[Category:Plague pandemics]]
[[Category:14th-century health disasters]]
[[Category:1340s in Asia]]
[[Category:1340s in Europe]]
[[Category:Eurasian history]]
[[Category:History of medieval medicine]]
[[Category:History of the Middle East]]
[[Category:Medieval health disasters]]
[[Category:Second plague pandemic]]
[[Category:1350s in Europe]]
[[Category:Causes of death]]
[[Category:1350s in Asia]]

[[ja:ペスト#14世紀の大流行]]</text>
      <sha1>1y57b0eg2xcvc1p8zs89drmmb5p29av</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
