  <page>
    <title>Bill Haley</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4528</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941733515</id>
      <parentid>941724984</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-20T09:38:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Materialscientist</username>
        <id>7852030</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/Yeet,69.seee|Yeet,69.seee]] identified as test/vandalism using [[WP:STiki|STiki]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{other people}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=December 2013}}
{{Infobox musical artist
| name             = Bill Haley
| image            = Bill Haley (1974).jpg
| caption          = 
| alt              = Haley smiling
| background       = solo_singer
| birth_name       = William John Clifton Haley
| origin           = [[Boothwyn]], [[Pennsylvania]], US
| birth_date       = {{birth date|1925|7|6|mf=y}}
| birth_place      = [[Highland Park, Michigan|Highland Park]], [[Michigan]], US
| death_cause      = Brain Tumor
| death_date       = {{death date and age|1981|2|9|1925|7|6|mf=y}}
| death_place      = [[Harlingen, Texas|Harlingen]], [[Texas]], US
| genre            = {{hlist|[[Rock and roll]]|[[Country music|country]]|[[rockabilly]]}}
| occupations      = {{hlist|Singer-songwriter|musician|bandleader}}
| instrument       = {{hlist|Vocals|guitar|double bass}}
| years_active     = 1946–1980
| label            = {{hlist|[[Decca Records|Decca]]|[[London Records|London]]|[[Brunswick Records|Brunswick]]|[[Cowboy Records|Cowboy]]|[[Atlantic Records|Atlantic]]|[[Vogue Records|Vogue]]|[[Holiday Records|Holiday]]|[[Essex Records|Essex]]|[[Warner Bros. Records]]|[[Orfeón]]|[[Dimsa Records|Dimsa]]|[[Logo Records|Logo]]|[[Gone Records|Gone]]|[[United Artists Records|United Artists]]|[[Roulette Records|Roulette]]|[[Sonet Records|Sonet]]|[[Buddah Records|Buddah]]}}
| associated_acts  = {{hlist|[[Bill Haley &amp; His Comets]]|The Down Homers}}
}}

'''William John Clifton Haley''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|h|eɪ|l|i}}; July 6, 1925 – February 9, 1981) was a pioneering American [[rock and roll]] musician. He is credited by many with first popularizing this form of music in the early 1950s with his group [[Bill Haley &amp; His Comets]] and million-selling hits such as &quot;[[Rock Around the Clock]]&quot;, &quot;[[See You Later, Alligator]]&quot;, &quot;[[Shake, Rattle and Roll]]&quot;, &quot;[[Rocket 88]]&quot;, &quot;[[Skinny Minnie]]&quot;, and &quot;Razzle Dazzle&quot;, and has sold over 60 million records worldwide.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0006426/bio|title=Bill Haley|website=IMDb|access-date=2018-10-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.rockhall.com/inductees/bill-haley|title=Bill Haley|website=Rock &amp; Roll Hall of Fame|language=en|access-date=2018-10-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biography==

===Early life and career===
Bill Haley was born July 6, 1925 in [[Highland Park, Michigan|Highland Park]], [[Michigan]], Haley was born William John Clifton Haley. In 1929, the four-year-old Haley underwent an inner-ear mastoid operation which accidentally severed an optic nerve, leaving him blind in his left eye for the rest of his life. It is said that he adopted his trademark kiss curl over his right eye to draw attention from his left, but it also became his &quot;gimmick&quot;, and added to his popularity.&lt;ref name=Fuchs&gt;{{cite book|last1=Fuchs|first1=Otto|title=Bill Haley: The Father of Rock &amp; Roll|date=2014|publisher=Wagner|isbn=9783866839014|page=16}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of the effects of the [[Great Depression]] on the [[Detroit, Michigan|Detroit]] area, his father moved the family to [[Bethel Township, Delaware County, Pennsylvania|Bethel]], Pennsylvania, when Bill was seven years old.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Goodley|first1=George Walter|title=Bethel Township Delaware County, Pennsylvania Thru Three Centuries|date=1987|page=97}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Haley's father William Albert Haley was from [[Kentucky]] and played the [[banjo]] and [[mandolin]], and his mother, Maude Green, who was originally from [[Ulverston]] in [[Lancashire]], [[England]], was a technically accomplished [[keyboardist]] with classical training.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.classicbands.com/haley.html|title=Bill Haley and his Comets|publisher=Classic Bands}}&lt;/ref&gt; Haley told the story that when he made a simulated guitar out of cardboard, his parents bought him a real one.&lt;ref&gt;Bill Haley: The Daddy of Rock and Roll. John Swenson. 1982. Stein and Day. pages 15, 17. {{ISBN|0-8128-2909-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One of his first appearances was in 1938 for a Bethel Junior baseball team entertainment event, performing guitar and songs when he was 13 years old.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=McCarrick|first1=Elizabeth|title=Bethel Township, Delaware County|date=2013|publisher=Arcadia Publishing|location=Charleston, South Carolina|isbn=978-0-7385-9818-5|page=105}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The anonymous sleeve notes accompanying the 1956 Decca album ''Rock Around The Clock'' describe Haley's early life and career: &quot;When Bill Haley was fifteen [c. 1940] he left home with his guitar and very little else and set out on the hard road to fame and fortune. The next few years, continuing this story in a fairy-tale manner, were hard and poverty-stricken, but crammed full of useful experience. Apart from learning how to exist on one meal a day and other artistic exercises, he worked at an open-air park show, sang and yodelled with any band that would have him, and worked with a traveling medicine show. Eventually he got a job with a popular group known as the &quot;Down Homers&quot; while they were in [[Hartford, Connecticut|Hartford]], [[Connecticut]]. Soon after this he decided, as all successful people must decide at some time or another, to be his own boss again – and he has been that ever since.' These notes fail to account for his early band, known as the Four Aces of Western Swing. During the 1940s Haley was considered one of the top cowboy yodelers in America as &quot;Silver Yodeling Bill Haley&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hillbilly-music.com/artists/story/index.php?id=13813 |title=Bill Haley and the Saddlemen |publisher=Hillbilly-Music.com |date=February 9, 1981 |accessdate=November 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The sleeve notes conclude: &quot;For six years Bill Haley was a musical director of Radio Station [[WPWA]] in [[Chester, Pennsylvania|Chester]], Pennsylvania, and led his own band all through this period. It was then known as Bill Haley's Saddlemen, indicating their definite leaning toward the tough Western style. They continued playing in clubs as well as over the radio around [[Philadelphia]], and in 1951 made their first recordings on Ed Wilson's Keystone Records in Philadelphia.&quot;  The group subsequently signed with [[Dave Miller (producer)|Dave Miller's]] [[Holiday Records]] and, on June 14, 1951 the Saddlemen recorded a cover of &quot;[[Rocket 88]]&quot;.

===Bill Haley and His Comets===
[[File:Bill Haley, 1974, Liége 1.jpg|thumb|upright|Bill Haley and the Comets performing in 1974]]
{{main|Bill Haley &amp; His Comets}}
During the Labor Day weekend in 1952, the Saddlemen were renamed '''Bill Haley with Haley's Comets''' (inspired by the supposedly official pronunciation of [[Halley's Comet]], a name suggested by WPWA radio station program director, Bob Johnson, where Bill Haley had a live radio program from noon to 1 p.m.), and in 1953, Haley's recording of &quot;[[Crazy Man, Crazy]]&quot; (co-written by him and his bass player, [[Marshall Lytle]], although Lytle would not receive credit until 2001) became the first rock and roll song to hit the American charts, peaking at number 15 on ''Billboard'' and number 11 on ''Cash Box''. Soon after, the band's name was revised to &quot;Bill Haley &amp; His Comets&quot;.

In 1954, Haley recorded &quot;[[Rock Around the Clock]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Dawson 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Initially, it was relatively successful, peaking at number  23 on the ''Billboard'' pop singles chart and staying on the charts for a few weeks.  On re-release, the record reached #1 on July 9, 1955.

Haley soon had another worldwide hit with &quot;[[Shake, Rattle and Roll]]&quot;, which went on to sell a million copies and was the first rock 'n' roll song to enter the British singles charts in December 1954, becoming a gold record. He retained elements of the original (which was slow blues), but sped it up with some country music aspects into the song (specifically, Western swing) and changed up the lyrics. Haley and his band were important in launching the music known as &quot;Rock and Roll&quot; to a wider audience after a period of it being considered an underground genre.

When &quot;Rock Around the Clock&quot; appeared as the theme song of the 1955 film ''[[Blackboard Jungle]]'' starring [[Glenn Ford]], it soared to the top of the American ''[[Billboard (magazine)|Billboard]]'' chart for eight weeks. The single is commonly used as a convenient line of demarcation between the &quot;rock era&quot; and the music industry that preceded it. ''Billboard'' separated its statistical tabulations into 1890–1954 and 1955–present. After the record rose to number one, Haley became widely popular by those who had come to embrace the new style of music. With the song's success, the age of rock music began overnight and ended the dominance of the jazz and pop standards performed by [[Frank Sinatra]], [[Jo Stafford]], [[Perry Como]], [[Bing Crosby]], and others. Nevertheless, in the United Kingdom, Haley was supported by former Dankworth Seven lead vocalist [[Frank Holder (musician)|Frank Holder]] among others.

&quot;Rock Around the Clock&quot; was the first record to sell over one million copies in both [[UK|Britain]] and [[West Germany|Germany]]. Later on in 1957, Haley became the first major American rock singer to tour Europe. Haley continued to score hits throughout the 1950s such as &quot;[[See You Later, Alligator]]&quot; and he starred in the first rock and roll musical films ''[[Rock Around the Clock (film)|Rock Around the Clock]]'' and ''[[Don't Knock the Rock]]'', both in 1956. Haley was already 30 years old, and he was soon eclipsed in the United States by the younger, sexier [[Elvis Presley]], but continued to enjoy great popularity in Latin America, Europe, and Australia during the 1960s.
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Bill Haley Elvis Presley 1955 Cleveland.jpg|left|thumb|Bill Haley and Elvis Presley at the Brooklyn High School Auditorium, Cleveland, Ohio, October 20, 1955{{ffdc|1=Bill Haley Elvis Presley 1955 Cleveland.jpg|log=2018 March 29}}]] --&gt;
Bill Haley and the Comets performed &quot;Rock Around the Clock&quot; on the ''[[Texaco Star Theater]]'' hosted by [[Milton Berle]] on Tuesday, May 31, 1955, on [[NBC]] in an'' a cappella'' and lip-synched version. Berle predicted that the song would go number one: &quot;A group of entertainers who are going right to the top.&quot; Berle also sang and danced to the song which was performed by the entire cast of the show. This was one of the earliest nationally televised performances by a rock and roll band and provided the new musical genre with a much wider audience.

Bill Haley and the Comets were the first rock and roll act to appear on the iconic American musical variety series the ''[[Ed Sullivan Show]]'' on Sunday, August 7, 1955, on [[CBS]] in a broadcast that originated from the Shakespeare Festival Theater in Hartford, Connecticut. They performed a live version of &quot;Rock Around the Clock&quot; with Franny Beecher on lead guitar and Dick Richards on drums. The band made their second appearance on the show on Sunday, April 28, 1957, performing the songs &quot;[[Rudy's Rock]]&quot; and &quot;Forty Cups of Coffee&quot;.

Bill Haley and the Comets appeared on ''[[American Bandstand]]'' hosted by [[Dick Clark]] on [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] twice in 1957, on the prime time show October 28, 1957, and on the regular daytime show on November 27, 1957. The band also appeared on Dick Clark's ''Saturday Night Beechnut Show'', also known as ''[[The Dick Clark Show]]'', a primetime TV series from New York on March 22, 1958, during the first season and on February 20, 1960, performing &quot;Rock Around the Clock&quot;, &quot;Shake, Rattle and Roll&quot;, and &quot;Tamiami&quot;. In 2017 Haley was inducted into the National Rhythm &amp; Blues Hall of Fame.

=== Personal life ===

====Marriages====
Bill Haley was married three times:
* Dorothy Crowe 	(December 11, 1946 – November 14, 1952) (divorced) (two children)
* Barbara Joan Cupchak 	(November 18, 1952 – 1960) (divorced) (five children)
* Martha Velasco 	(1963–February 9, 1981; his death) (three children)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0006426/bio?ref_=nm_ov_bio_sm | title=Bill Haley}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Children====
Bill Haley had at least ten children. John W. Haley, his eldest son, wrote ''Sound and Glory'', a biography of Haley.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rockabillyhall.com/BillHaley.html|title=Bill Haley 1925–1981|publisher=Rockabilly Hall of Fame|accessdate=July 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; His youngest daughter, [[Gina Haley]], is a professional musician based in [[Texas]].&lt;ref&gt;Carman, Tim. [http://www.houstonpress.com/1995-05-18/music/rock-and-roll-royalty/1 &quot;Rock and Roll Royalty&quot;], &quot;[[The Houston Press]]&quot;, Houston, May 18, 1995.&lt;/ref&gt; Scott Haley is an athlete. His youngest son Pedro is also a musician.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bruce Lee Smith&quot;/&gt;

He also had a daughter, Martha Maria, from his last marriage with Martha Velasco.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bruce Lee Smith&quot;/&gt;

Bill Haley Jr., Haley's second son and first with Joan Barbara &quot;Cuppy&quot; Haley-Hahn, publishes a regional business magazine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.422business.com/about_us.html|title=Route 422 Business Advisor – About Us|publisher=Route 422 Business Advisor|accessdate=July 24, 2012|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120512010249/http://www.422business.com/about_us.html|archivedate=May 12, 2012|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; In February, 2011, he formed a tribute band, performing his father's music and telling the stories behind the songs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.montgomerynews.com/articles/2011/11/17/entertainment/doc4ec3cf37e92da127171573.txtl|title=Bill Haley (Jr.) &amp; Comets rock out again!|author=Mike Morsch|publisher=Montgomery News|date=November 17, 2011}}{{dead link|date=July 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Last years==
{{more citations needed|section|date=June 2018}}
{{Undue weight section|date=September 2018}}
An admitted alcoholic,&lt;ref&gt;1974 radio interview for the [[BBC]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.texasmonthly.com/articles/falling-comet/|title=Falling Comet|date=2011-06-01|website=Texas Monthly|language=en|access-date=2020-01-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.ca/books?id=PgGqNrqfrsoC&amp;lpg=PP15&amp;ots=cKDn8n9efC&amp;dq=bill%20haley%20%22alcoholism%22&amp;pg=PP15#v=onepage&amp;q=bill%20haley%20%22alcoholism%22&amp;f=false|title=The Billboard Book of Number One Hits|last=Bronson|first=Fred|date=2003|publisher=Billboard Books|isbn=978-0-8230-7677-2|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Haley fought a battle with alcohol into the 1970s. Nonetheless, he and his band continued to be a popular touring act, benefiting from a 1950s nostalgia movement that began in the late 1960s and the signing of a lucrative record deal with the European [[Sonet Records|Sonet]] label. After performing for [[Elizabeth II|Queen Elizabeth II]] at the [[Royal Variety Performance]] on November 10, 1979, Haley made his final performances in South Africa in May and June 1980. Before the South African tour, he was diagnosed with a [[brain tumor]], and a planned tour of [[Germany]] in the autumn of 1980 was cancelled.

The October 25, 1980 issue of German tabloid ''[[Bild]]'' reported that Haley had a brain tumor, quoting British manager Patrick Malynn as saying that Haley &quot;had taken a fit [and] didn't recognize anyone any more&quot; after being taken to his home in Beverly Hills, in addition to the paper quoting a doctor that the tumor was inoperable.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bill Haley 1982. page 154&quot;&gt;Bill Haley: The Daddy of Rock and Roll. John Swenson. 1982. Stein and Day. page 154. {{ISBN|0-8128-2909-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[Berliner Zeitung]]'' reported a few days later that Haley had collapsed after a performance in Texas and was taken to the hospital in his hometown of [[Harlingen, Texas]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bill Haley 1982. page 154&quot;/&gt;

His drinking problem was getting worse. By this time, Bill and Martha fought all the time and she told him to stop drinking or move out. He then did move out into a room in their pool house. Martha still took care of him and sometimes, he would come in the house to eat, but he ate very little. &quot;There were days we never saw him,&quot; said his daughter Martha Maria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Hall|first1=Michael|title=Falling Comet|url=http://www.texasmonthly.com/articles/falling-comet/|website=Texas Monthly|accessdate=5 February 2017|date=31 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In addition to Haley's drinking problems, he was having serious mental problems, as well. Martha Maria said, &quot;It was like sometimes he was drunk even when he wasn't drinking.&quot; After he'd been jailed by the Harlingen Police, Martha had the judge put Haley in the hospital, where he was seen by a psychiatrist, who said Bill's brain was overproducing a chemical, like adrenaline. The doctor prescribed a medication to stop the overproduction, but said Bill would have to stop drinking. Martha said, &quot;This is pointless.&quot; She took him home, however, fed him and gave him his first dose. As soon as he felt better, he went back out to his room in the pool house, and the downward spiral continued until his passing.&lt;ref&gt;Falling Comet. Michael Hall. 2011. ''Texas Monthly'', June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Haley made a succession of bizarre, mostly monologue late-night phone calls to friends and relatives towards the end of his life in which he was semi-coherent, his first wife has been quoted as saying, &quot;He would call you and ramble, dwelling on the past ...&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;'Bill Haley: The Daddy of Rock and Roll', P.155-159, John Swenson. (1982. Pub. Stein and Day, 1982){{ISBN|0-8128-2909-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Death==
Haley died on 9 February 1981 at the age of 55 at his home in [[Harlingen, Texas|Harlingen]] in [[Texas]].&lt;ref&gt;Obituary for Bill Haley, 'New York Times', 10 February 1981. https://www.nytimes.com/1981/02/10/obituaries/bill-haley-55-dies-singer-band-leader.html&lt;/ref&gt; His body was cremated; the fate of his ashes is publicly unknown.&lt;ref&gt;Entry for Bill Haley in [[Findagrave]] website (2019). https://www.findagrave.com/memorial/6942256/bill-haley&lt;/ref&gt; His death certificate gave 'natural causes, most likely a [[myocardial infarction|heart attack]]' as being the cause.&lt;ref&gt;'Bill Haley: The Daddy of Rock and Roll', P.164, by John Swenson (Pub. Stein and Day 1982).{{ISBN|0-8128-2909-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Tributes and legacy==
Haley was posthumously inducted into the [[Rock and Roll Hall of Fame]] in 1987. His son Pedro represented him at the ceremony.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bruce Lee Smith&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.themonitor.com/articles/harlingen-22920-haley-pioneer.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090822144225/http://www.themonitor.com/articles/harlingen-22920-haley-pioneer.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=August 22, 2009|title=Pioneer Haley almost forgotten in Harlingen|author=Bruce Lee Smith|publisher=AIM Media Texas|date=February 6, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; He received a star on the [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]]&lt;ref&gt;Dawson, Jim and Whitcomb, Ian (2005). ''Rock Around the Clock: The Record that Started the Rock Revolution!'', p. 180. Hal Leonard Corporation. {{ISBN|0-87930-829-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; on February 8, 1960,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.walkoffame.com/bill-haley|title=Bill Haley {{!}} Hollywood Walk of Fame|website=www.walkoffame.com|access-date=2016-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; for his contributions to the music industry at 6350 [[Hollywood Boulevard]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://projects.latimes.com/hollywood/star-walk/bill-haley/|title=Bill Haley|website=latimes.com|access-date=2016-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://rockandrollroadmap.com/places/miscellaneous/los-angeles-area-miscellaneous/hollywood-walk-of-fame/|title=Hollywood Walk of Fame - Our list of Rock stars on the Walk|date=2015-12-19|website=History Of Rock Music|language=en-US|access-date=2016-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Comets were separately inducted into the Hall of Fame as a group in 2012, after a rule change allowed the induction of backing groups.

Songwriters [[Tom Russell]] and [[Dave Alvin]] addressed Haley's demise in musical terms with &quot;Haley's Comet&quot; on Alvin's 1991 album ''Blue Blvd.'' [[Dwight Yoakam]] sang backup on the tribute.

Surviving members of the 1954&amp;ndash;55 contingent of Haley's Comets reunited in the late 1980s and continued to perform for many years around the world. They released a concert DVD in 2004 on Hydra Records, played the [[Viper Room]] in [[West Hollywood]] in 2005, and performed at Dick Clark's American Bandstand Theater in [[Branson, Missouri]], beginning in 2006–07. As of 2014, only two members of this particular contingent are still alive (Joey Ambrose and Dick Richards), but they continue to perform in Branson and in Europe. At least two other groups also continue to perform in North America under the Comets name as of 2014.

In March 2007, the Original Comets opened the Bill Haley Museum in Munich, Germany.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rockithydra.de |title=Rockithydra |language=de |publisher=Rockithydra.de |date= |accessdate=November 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On October 27, 2007, ex-Comets guitar player Bill Turner opened the Bill Haley Museum for the public.

====Asteroid====
{{main|79896 Billhaley}}

In February 2006, the [[International Astronomical Union]] announced the naming of [[asteroid]] 79896 Billhaley to mark the 25th anniversary of Bill Haley's death.

==Published biographies==
* In 2019, Bill Haley Jr. and Peter Benjaminson wrote &quot;Crazy Man, Crazy — The Bill Haley Story&quot; published by Backbeat Books in North America ({{ISBN|978-1-61713-711-2}}) and Omnibus Press (UK and World Rights) ({{ISBN|9781785588327}}). This biography focuses on Bill Haley's professional career and his private personal life, based on exhaustive research and extensive interviews with ex-wives and family members, business associates and fellow musicians.
* In 1980, Haley began working on an autobiography entitled ''The Life and Times of Bill Haley'', but died after completing only 100 pages. The work is registered with the [[U.S. Copyright Office]], but has yet to be released to the public. According to Gina Haley, Bill's youngest daughter, her father managed to complete the book on his career, and the manuscript is in possession of the Bill Haley estate.
* In 1982, John Swenson wrote ''Bill Haley: The Daddy of Rock and Roll'' (published in the UK under the title, ''Bill Haley'').
* In 1990, Haley's eldest son, John W. Haley, along with John von Hoëlle, wrote ''Sound and Glory'', a biography focusing mostly on Haley's early life and peak career years. This book is out of print.
* A German-language biography was published soon after Haley's death, written by Peter Cornelsen and Harald D. Kain.
* A book on the history of Haley's most famous recording, ''Rock Around the Clock: The Record That Started the Rock Revolution'' by [[Jim Dawson]] was published in June 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rockabillyhall.com/Extra.html#clockbook |title=&quot;EXTRA!&quot; Page 1 / Bill Haley and the Comets |publisher=Rockabillyhall.com |date= |accessdate=November 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* A two-volume paperback Bill Haley biography written by Otto Fuchs, proofread by Haley lead guitarist Bill Turner, was published in 2016 on Books On Demand:'' BILL HALEY The Father of Rock ´n´ Roll - The Rise of Bill Haley And Rock ´N´ Roll'' by Otto Fuchs {{ISBN|978-3-7412-4856-6}} &lt;ref&gt;Books On Demand, BILL HALEY The Father of Rock ´n´ Roll - The Rock &amp; Roll Revival Years And Bill Haley´s Legacy By Otto Fuchs {{ISBN|978-3-7412-4874-0}} Books On Demand, published July 6, 2016. (www.billhaley.at)
&lt;/ref&gt;

==Film portrayals==
Unlike his contemporaries, Bill Haley has rarely been portrayed on screen. Following the success of ''[[The Buddy Holly Story]]'' in 1978, Haley expressed interest in having his life story committed to film, but this never came to fruition. In the 1980s and early 1990s, numerous media reports emerged stating that plans were underway to do a biopic based upon Haley's life, with [[Beau Bridges]], [[Jeff Bridges]] and [[John Ritter]] all at one point being mentioned as actors in line to play Haley (according to ''[[Goldmine (magazine)|Goldmine Magazine]]'', Ritter attempted to buy the film rights to ''Sound and Glory'').

Bill Haley has also been portrayed – not always in a positive light – in several &quot;period&quot; films:
* John Paramor in ''[[Shout! The Story of Johnny O'Keefe]]'' (1985)
* Michael Daingerfield in ''Mr. Rock 'n' Roll: The Alan Freed Story'' (1999)
* [[Dicky Barrett]] (of [[The Mighty Mighty Bosstones]]) in ''[[Shake, Rattle and Roll: An American Love Story]]'' (also 1999)

==Discography==
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Bill Haley Comets Ed Sullivan 1957.jpg|thumb|Sunday, April 28, 1957 second appearance on the Ed Sullivan Show rehearsal photograph, CBS{{ffdc|1=Bill Haley Comets Ed Sullivan 1957.jpg|log=2018 March 29}}]] --&gt;
Before the formation of Bill Haley and the Saddlemen, which later became the Comets, Haley released several singles with other groups. Dates are approximate due to lack of documentation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.billhaleycentral.com |title=Bill Haley Database |publisher=Billhaleycentral.com |date= |accessdate=November 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As '''Bill Haley and the Four Aces of Western Swing''':

1948
* ''[[Too Many Parties and Too Many Pals]]'' (vocal by Tex King)/''Four Leaf Clover Blues'' ([[Cowboy Records|Cowboy]] CR1201) August 1948 &lt;ref&gt;Billboard Record Review  Aug 14, 1948 page 121&lt;/ref&gt;
1949
* ''Tennessee Border/[[Candy Kisses (George Morgan song)|Candy Kisses]]'' (Cowboy CR1202)  March 1949 &lt;ref&gt;Billboard Advance Folk Record Releases Mar 19, 1949 page 38&lt;/ref&gt;

As '''Johnny Clifton and His String Band''':

1950
* ''Stand Up and Be Counted/Loveless Blues'' ([[Center Records|Center]] C102)

Many Haley discographies list two 1946 recordings by the Down Homers released on the [[Vogue Records]] label as featuring Haley. Haley historian Chris Gardner, as well as surviving members of the group, have confirmed that the two singles: &quot;Out Where the West Winds Blow&quot;/&quot;Who's Gonna Kiss You When I'm Gone&quot; (Vogue R736) and &quot;Boogie Woogie Yodel&quot;/&quot;Baby I Found Out All About You&quot; (Vogue R786) do not feature Haley.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://thegardnerfamily.org/haley/discography/recordings.html |title=Thegardnerfamily.org |access-date=April 1, 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120205001942/http://thegardnerfamily.org/haley/discography/recordings.html |archive-date=February 5, 2012 |url-status=dead |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the tracks were nonetheless included in the compilation box set ''Rock 'n' Roll Arrives'' released by [[Bear Family Records]] in 2006.

:''See the [[Bill Haley &amp; His Comets discography|discography of Bill Haley &amp; His Comets]] for a list of the singles and albums released by Haley with the Saddlemen and the Comets from 1950 onwards.''

===Unreleased recordings===
Bill Haley recorded prolifically during the 1940s, often at the radio stations where he worked, or in formal studio settings. Virtually none of these recordings were ever released. Liner notes for a 2003 CD release by [[Hydra Records]] entitled ''Bill Haley and Friends Vol. 2: The Legendary Cowboy Recordings'' reveal that several additional Cowboy label single releases were planned for the Four Aces, but this never occurred.

A number of previously unreleased Haley country-western recordings from the 1946–1950 period began to emerge near the end of Haley's life, some of which were released by the [[Arzee Records|Arzee]] label, with titles such as &quot;Yodel Your Blues Away&quot; and &quot;Rose of My Heart.&quot; Still more demos, alternate takes, and wholly unheard-before recordings have been released since Haley's death. Notable examples of such releases include the albums ''Golden Country Origins'' by [[Grassroots Records]] of Australia and ''Hillbilly Haley'' by the British label, [[Rollercoaster Records|Rollercoaster]], as well as the aforementioned German release by Hydra Records. In 2006, [[Bear Family Records]] of Germany released what is considered to be the most comprehensive (yet still incomplete) collection of Haley's 1946–1950 recordings as part of its Haley box set ''Rock n' Roll Arrives''.

==Compositions==

Bill Haley's compositions included &quot;Four Leaf Clover Blues&quot; in 1948, &quot;Rose of My Heart&quot;, &quot;Yodel Your Blues Away&quot;, &quot;[[Crazy Man, Crazy]]&quot;, &quot;What'Cha Gonna Do&quot;, &quot;[[Fractured (Bill Haley song)|Fractured]]&quot;, &quot;[[Live It Up (Bill Haley song)|Live It Up]]&quot;, &quot;Farewell, So Long, Goodbye&quot;, &quot;[[Real Rock Drive]]&quot;, &quot;Rocking Chair on the Moon&quot;, &quot;Sundown Boogie&quot;, &quot;Green Tree Boogie&quot;, &quot;Tearstains on My Heart&quot;, &quot;Down Deep in My Heart&quot;, &quot;Straight Jacket&quot;, &quot;[[Birth of the Boogie]]&quot;, &quot;[[Two Hound Dogs]]&quot;, &quot;[[Rock-A-Beatin' Boogie]]&quot;, &quot;[[Hot Dog Buddy Buddy]]&quot;, &quot;[[R-O-C-K]]&quot;, &quot;[[Rudy's Rock]]&quot;, &quot;Calling All Comets&quot;, &quot;Tonight's the Night&quot;, &quot;Hook, Line and Sinker&quot;, &quot;Sway with Me&quot;, &quot;Paper Boy (On Main Street U.S.A.)&quot;, &quot;[[Skinny Minnie]]&quot;, &quot;B.B. Betty&quot;, &quot;Eloise&quot;, &quot;Whoa Mabel!&quot;, &quot;Vive le Rock and Roll&quot;, &quot;I've Got News For You&quot;, &quot;So Right Tonight&quot;, &quot;Jamaica D.J.&quot;, &quot;Ana Maria&quot;, &quot;Yucatán Twist&quot;, &quot;Football Rock and Roll&quot;, &quot;Let the Good Times Roll Again&quot; in 1979, and &quot;Chick Safari&quot; in 1960.&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.org/stream/catalogofcopyrig3145lib#page/60/mode/2up. &quot;Chick Safari&quot;. Catalog of Copyright Entries: 1960.]&lt;/ref&gt;

He also wrote or co-wrote songs for other artists such as &quot;I've Got News for You&quot; for Penny Smith in 1955 on Kahill, &quot;Calypso Rock&quot; for Dave Day and The Red Coats on Kapp in 1956, &quot;Half Your Heart&quot; with Robert J. Hayes for Kitty Nation in 1956 on Wing, &quot;I Oughta&quot; and &quot;Everything But You&quot; for Dotti Malone in 1956 also on Wing,&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=Qh8EAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=RA1-PA22&amp;lpg=RA1-PA22&amp;dq=half+your+heart+kitty+nation+haley&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=4EEIziLNf7&amp;sig=IruSKzEkmaGPLOcdJwek9Yo8c8Q&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjJgNSIjp7ZAhUCS60KHbzNB_sQ6AEIQDAH#v=onepage&amp;q=half%20your%20heart%20kitty%20nation%20haley&amp;f=false ''Billboard'', &quot;Music As Written&quot;, March 24, 1956, p. 22.]&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;A.B.C. Rock&quot; and &quot;Rocky the Rockin' Rabbit&quot; for [[Sally Starr (TV hostess)|Sally Starr]] on Arcade, &quot;A Sweet Bunch of Roses&quot; for Country and Western singer Lou Graham, &quot;Toodle-Oo-Bamboo&quot; for Ray Coleman and His Skyrockets on Skyrocket Records in 1959, &quot;Always Together&quot; for the Cook Brothers on Arcade in 1960, &quot;Crazy Street&quot; for [[The Matys Brothers]] on [[Coral Records]], &quot;The Cat&quot; for Cappy Bianco, and &quot;(Ya Gotta) Sing For the Ladies&quot; and &quot;Butterfly Love&quot; for Ginger Shannon and Johnny Montana in 1960 on Arcade as well as the unissued &quot;I'm Shook&quot; in 1958.

==Quotations==
{{quotation|Frankly, our market is the teenagers. They are the ones we constantly try to please. We keep very close to them, listening for their new expressions and asking what they want in the way of music.}}
''[[NME]]'' – October 1955&lt;ref name=&quot;NME Rock 'N' Roll Years&quot;&gt;{{cite book
| first= John
| last= Tobler
| year= 1992
| title= NME Rock 'N' Roll Years
| edition= 1st
| publisher= Reed International Books Ltd 
| location= London
| page= 19
| id= CN 5585}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quotation|There has to be a Cadillac music and a Ford music. Tchaikovsky and Bach is Cadillac music, while we play more down-to-earth Ford music. It's got a good solid beat that can't be missed... definitely designed for teenage kids to dance to.}}
''[[NME]]'' – January 1957&lt;ref name=&quot;NME Rock 'N' Roll Years 2&quot;&gt;{{cite book
| first= John
| last= Tobler
| year= 1992
| title= NME Rock 'N' Roll Years
| edition= 1st
| publisher= Reed International Books Ltd 
| location= London
| page= 36
| id= CN 5585}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards==
In 1982, Haley's &quot;Rock Around the Clock&quot; was inducted into the [[Grammy Hall of Fame]], a special Grammy award established in 1973 to honor recordings at least 25 years old and with &quot;qualitative or historical significance&quot;.

In December 2017, Haley was inducted into the [[Rhythm and Blues Music Hall of Fame|Rhythm and Blues Hall Of Fame]].

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Other sources==
* Jim Dawson, ''Rock Around the Clock: The Record That Started the Rock Revolution!'' (San Francisco: Backbeat Books, 2005)
* John W. Haley and John von Hoëlle, ''Sound and Glory'' (Wilmington, DE: Dyne-American, 1990)
* John Swenson, ''Bill Haley'' (London: W.H. Allen, 1982)

==External links==
* [http://www.bill-haley.com/ Bill Haley's new Comets web site]
* [https://archive.today/20091025075400/http://www.geocities.com/buddycruiser/bio4.html?1054745371300  Melody Manor (Bill Haley's house)] [https://maps.google.com/maps?li=rwp&amp;q=3190+FOULK+RD,+MARCUS+HOOK,+PA+19061&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;t=h&amp;om=1&amp;z=16&amp;ll=39.850902,-75.484078&amp;spn=0.007215,0.021458&amp;iwloc=A Google Map]
*{{IMDb name|id=0006426|name=Bill Haley}}
* [http://www.billhaleyjrandthecomets.com/ Bill Haley Jr. and the Comets site]
{{Bill Haley &amp; His Comets}}
{{1987 Rock and Roll Hall of Fame}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Haley, Bill}}
[[Category:Bill Haley| ]]
[[Category:1925 births]]
[[Category:1981 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Highland Park, Michigan]]
[[Category:Bill Haley &amp; His Comets members]]
[[Category:American people of English descent]]
[[Category:American radio personalities]]
[[Category:American rock singers]]
[[Category:American rockabilly guitarists]]
[[Category:American male guitarists]]
[[Category:People from Delaware County, Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:People from Harlingen, Texas]]
[[Category:Rock and roll musicians]]
[[Category:American bandleaders]]
[[Category:Decca Records artists]]
[[Category:Songwriters from Michigan]]
[[Category:Yodelers]]
[[Category:20th-century American singers]]
[[Category:American rock guitarists]]
[[Category:American male singers]]
[[Category:Singers from Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Guitarists from Michigan]]
[[Category:Guitarists from Philadelphia]]
[[Category:20th-century American guitarists]]</text>
      <sha1>o79x5tru4mwsokhd73ep3rbz2rbqb24</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
