  <page>
    <title>Wireless broadband</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4595</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940523258</id>
      <parentid>940407211</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-13T01:31:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Apparition11</username>
        <id>6046731</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/Jacob Worton|Jacob Worton]] ([[User talk:Jacob Worton|talk]]): Spam using [[WP:TWINKLE|TW]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about|wireless networking in general|local area network technologies|Wireless LAN}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=March 2011}}

[[File:Dishes ft worth2.JPG|thumb |right |upright=1.3 |Three [[fixed wireless]] dishes with protective covers on top of 307 W. 7th Street, [[Fort Worth, Texas]] around 2001]]

'''Wireless broadband''' is telecommunications technology that provides high-speed [[wireless]] [[Internet access]] or [[computer network]]ing access over a wide area. The term comprises both [[Fixed wireless|fixed]] and [[Mobile broadband|mobile]] broadband.

==The term broadband==
Originally the word &quot;[[broadband]]&quot; had a technical meaning, but became a marketing term for any kind of relatively high-speed computer network or Internet access technology.
According to the [[IEEE 802.16|802.16-2004]] standard, broadband means &quot;having instantaneous [[Bandwidth (signal processing)|bandwidths]] greater than 1 [[MHz]] and supporting [[bit rate|data rates]] greater than about 1.5 [[Megabit|Mbit]]/s.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://standards.ieee.org/about/get/802/802.16.html Coexistence of Fixed Broadband Wireless Access Systems]&lt;/ref&gt;
The Federal Communications Commission (FCC) recently re-defined the definition to mean download speeds of at least 25 [[Megabit|Mbit]]/s and upload speeds of at least 3 [[Megabit|Mbit]]/s.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.theverge.com/2015/1/29/7932653/fcc-changed-definition-broadband-25mbps&lt;/ref&gt;

==Technology and speeds==

[[File:WISP CPE installed on a residence.JPG|thumb|right |A typical WISP Customer Premises Equipment (CPE) installed on a residence]]&lt;!-- not descriptive file name --&gt;

Wireless networks can feature  data rates roughly equivalent to some wired networks, such as that of [[asymmetric digital subscriber line]] (ADSL) or a [[cable modem]].  Wireless  networks can also be symmetrical, meaning the same rate in both directions ([[downstream (networking)|downstream]] and [[upstream (networking)|upstream]]), which is most commonly associated with [[fixed wireless]] networks. A fixed wireless network link is a stationary terrestrial wireless connection, which can support higher data rates for the same power as mobile or satellite systems.

Few [[wireless Internet service provider]]s (WISPs) provide download speeds of over 100 Mbit/s; most broadband wireless access (BWA) services are estimated to have a range of {{convert|50|km|mi|abbr=on}} from a tower.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=WiMAX: Broadband Wireless Access|url=http://www.wi-fiplanet.com/tutorials/article.php/3412391|publisher=wi-fiplanet.com|accessdate=March 17, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Technologies used include [[Local Multipoint Distribution Service]] (LMDS) and [[Multichannel Multipoint Distribution Service]] (MMDS), as well as heavy use of the [[ISM band|industrial, scientific and medical (ISM) radio bands]] and one particular access technology was standardized by [[IEEE 802.16]], with products known as [[WiMAX]].&lt;ref name=&quot;hraunfoss.fcc.gov&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=REPORT AND ORDER – Released: March&amp;nbsp;16, 2005|url=http://hraunfoss.fcc.gov/edocs_public/attachmatch/FCC-05-56A1.pdf|format=PDF|publisher=[[Federal Communications Commission]]|accessdate=March 17, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

WiMAX is highly popular in Europe but has not met full acceptance in the United States because cost of deployment does not meet [[return on investment]] figures. In 2005 the [[Federal Communications Commission]] adopted a [[Report and Order]] that revised the FCC’s rules to open the 3650&amp;nbsp;MHz band for terrestrial wireless broadband operations.&lt;ref name=&quot;hraunfoss.fcc.gov&quot;/&gt;

==Development of Wireless Broadband in the United States==

On November 14, 2007 the Commission released Public Notice DA 07-4605 in which the Wireless Telecommunications Bureau announced the start date for licensing and registration process for the [[IEEE 802.11y-2008|3650–3700 MHz]] band.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=PUBLIC NOTICE – Released: November&amp;nbsp;14, 2007|url=http://hraunfoss.fcc.gov/edocs_public/attachmatch/DA-07-4605A1.pdf|format=PDF|publisher=[[Federal Communications Commission]]|accessdate=March 17, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In 2010 the FCC adopted the TV White Space Rules (TVWS) and allowed some of the better no line of sight frequency (700&amp;nbsp;MHz) into the FCC Part-15 Rules.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= The FCC Decision and the Use of White Spaces |author= Alex Goldman |publisher= Wireless Internet Service Providers Association |url= http://www.wispa.org/?p=3146 |accessdate= July 16, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Wireless Internet Service Providers Association, a national association of WISPs, petitioned the FCC and won.{{citation needed |date= July 2011}}

Initially, WISPs were only found in rural areas not covered by [[Cable Internet access|cable]] or [[DSL]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=A WISP with Vision|url=http://www.wi-fiplanet.com/columns/article.php/3652986|publisher=wi-fiplanet.com|accessdate=March 17, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; These early WISPs would employ a high-capacity [[T-carrier]], such as a [[Digital Signal 1|T1]] or [[Digital Signal 3|DS3]] connection, and then broadcast the signal from a high elevation, such as at the top of a [[water tower]]. To receive this type of Internet connection, consumers mount a small [[Parabolic antenna|dish]] to the roof of their home or office and point it to the transmitter. [[Line-of-sight propagation|Line of sight]] is usually necessary for WISPs operating in the [[IEEE 802.11|2.4 and 5 GHz]] bands with 900&amp;nbsp;MHz offering better [[NLOS]] (non-line-of-sight) performance.

===Residential Wireless Internet===
Providers of fixed wireless broadband services typically provide equipment to customers and install a small antenna or dish somewhere on the roof. This equipment is usually deployed as a service and maintained by the company providing that service. Fixed wireless services have become particularly popular in many rural areas where cable, DSL or other typical home internet services are not available.

===Business Wireless Internet===
Many companies in the US and worldwide have started using wireless alternatives to incumbent and local providers for internet and voice service. These providers tend to offer competitive services and options in areas where there is a difficulty getting affordable Ethernet connections from terrestrial providers such as ATT, Comcast, Verizon and others. Also, companies looking for full diversity between carriers for critical uptime requirements may seek wireless alternatives to local options.

===Demand for spectrum===
{{Main|Spectrum reallocation}}
To cope with increased demand for wireless broadband, increased [[Radio spectrum|spectrum]] would be needed. Studies began in 2009, and while some unused spectrum was available, it appeared broadcasters would have to give up at least some spectrum. This led to strong objections from the broadcasting community. In 2013, auctions were planned, and for now any action by broadcasters is voluntary.

==Mobile wireless broadband==
Called [[mobile broadband]], wireless broadband technologies include services from [[mobile phone]] service providers such as [[Verizon Wireless]], [[Sprint Corporation]], and [[AT&amp;T Mobility]], and T-Mobile  which allow a more mobile version of Internet access. Consumers can purchase a [[PC card]], laptop card, or [[USB]] equipment to connect their PC or laptop to the Internet via [[cell phone tower]]s. This type of connection would be stable in almost any area that could also receive a strong cell phone connection. These connections can cost more for portable convenience as well as having speed limitations in all but urban environments.{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}}

On June 2, 2010, after months of discussion,  AT&amp;T became the first wireless Internet provider in the USA to announce plans to charge according to usage. As the only [[iPhone]] service in the United States, AT&amp;T experienced the problem of heavy Internet use more than other providers. About 3 percent of AT&amp;T [[Smartphone|smart phone]] customers account for 40 percent of the technology's use. 98 percent of the company's customers use less than 2 [[gigabyte]]s (4000 page views, 10,000 emails or 200 minutes of [[Streaming media|streaming video]]), the limit under the $25 monthly plan, and 65 percent use less than 200 [[megabyte]]s, the limit for the $15 plan. For each gigabyte in excess of the limit, customers would be charged $10 a month starting June 7, 2010, though existing customers would not be required to change from the $30 a month unlimited service plan. The new plan would become a requirement for those upgrading to the new iPhone technology later in the summer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.thesunnews.com/2010/06/03/1509693/att-first-carrier-to-end-unlimited.html |title=AT&amp;T first carrier to end unlimited data plans |last=Bartash |first=Jeffrey|work=[[MarketWatch]]|date=June 3, 2010|accessdate=2010-06-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Licensing==

A wireless connection can be either licensed or unlicensed. In the [[United States|U.S.]], licensed connections use a private [[Electromagnetic spectrum|spectrum]] the user has secured rights to from the [[Federal Communications Commission]] (FCC). In other countries, spectrum is licensed from the country's national radio communications authority (such as the [[Australian Communications and Media Authority|ACMA]] in [[Australia]] or [[Nigerian Communications Commission]] in [[Nigeria]] (NCC)). Licensing is usually expensive and often reserved for large companies who wish to guarantee private access to spectrum for use in point to point communication. Because of this, most wireless ISP's use [[unlicensed spectrum]] which is publicly shared.

==See also==
* [[Clearwire]]
* [[CorDECT]]
* [[HIPERMAN]]
* [[Skyriver]], provider in California
* [[WiBro]], provider in South Korea
* [[iBurst]]
* [[802.20]]
* [[Connect card]]
* [[Policies promoting wireless broadband]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
&lt;!-- Don't even think of adding your promotional links here. --&gt;
&lt;!-- This is not a search engine optimization opportunity. --&gt;
&lt;!-- Spammers are publicly blacklisted.--&gt; 
&lt;!-- Search engines crawl our blacklist.--&gt;
* [http://www.wispa.org/ Wireless Internet Service Provider Association]
* [https://www.wavedirect.net/ Wireless Internet Service Provider Ontario]
{{Internet access}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wireless Broadband}}
[[Category:Wireless networking]]
[[Category:Broadband]]</text>
      <sha1>ejs26hjv1abgzc0qccmywnkeyweiks7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
