  <page>
    <title>Burt Lancaster</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4537</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943292231</id>
      <parentid>943076222</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T01:31:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yoninah</username>
        <id>317119</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Political Activism */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|American actor}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2019}}
{{Infobox person
| name             = Burt Lancaster
| image            = Burt Lancaster - publicity 1947.JPG
| imagesize        =
| caption          = Lancaster in ''[[Desert Fury]]'' (1947)
| birth_name       = Burton Stephen Lancaster
| birth_date       = {{birth date|1913|11|2}}
| birth_place      = [[Manhattan]], [[New York (state)|New York]], [[United States|U.S.]]
| death_date       = {{death date and age|1994|10|20|1913|11|2}}
| death_place      = [[Century City, California]], U.S.
| years_active     = 1935–1991
| occupation       = Actor, producer
| spouse           = June Ernst&lt;br&gt;({{abbr|m.|married}} 1935; {{abbr|div.|divorced}} 1946)&lt;br/&gt;{{marriage|Norma Anderson&lt;br&gt;|1946|1969|end=divorced}}&lt;br/&gt;{{marriage|Susan Martin&lt;br&gt;|1990}}
| children         = 5, including [[Bill Lancaster]]
| party        = [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic]]
}}

'''Burton Stephen Lancaster''' (November 2, 1913 – October 20, 1994) was an American actor and producer. Initially known for playing &quot;tough guys&quot; with a tender streak, he went on to achieve success with more complex and challenging roles over a 45-year career in film and, later, television. He was a four-time nominee for the [[Academy Award for Best Actor]] (winning once), and also winning two [[BAFTA]] Awards and one [[Golden Globe Award]] for Best Lead Actor.

Lancaster performed as a circus acrobat in the 1930s. After serving in [[World War II]], the 32-year-old Lancaster landed a role in a Broadway play and drew the attention of a Hollywood agent. His breakthrough role was the film noir ''[[The Killers (1946 film)|The Killers]]'' in 1946 alongside [[Ava Gardner]]. A critical success, it launched both of their careers.

In 1953, Lancaster played the illicit lover of [[Deborah Kerr]] in the military drama ''[[From Here to Eternity]]''. A box office smash, it won eight Academy Awards, including Best Picture, and landed a Best Actor nomination for Lancaster. In 1956, he starred in ''[[The Rainmaker (1956 film)|The Rainmaker]]'', with [[Katharine Hepburn]], earning a Best Actor Golden Globe nomination, and in ''[[Gunfight at the O.K. Corral (film)|Gunfight at the O.K. Corral]]'' in 1957, with frequent co-star Kirk Douglas. During the 1950s, his production company, [[Hecht-Hill-Lancaster]], was highly successful, with Lancaster acting in films such as: ''[[Trapeze (film)|Trapeze]]'' in 1956, a box office smash in which he used his acrobatic skills; ''[[Sweet Smell of Success]]'' (1957), a dark drama today considered a classic; ''[[Run Silent, Run Deep (1958 film)|Run Silent, Run Deep]]'' (1958), a WWII submarine drama with [[Clark Gable]]; and ''[[Separate Tables (film)|Separate Tables]]'' (1958), a hotel-set drama which received seven Oscar nominations.

In the early 1960s, Lancaster starred in a string of critically successful films, each in very disparate roles. Playing a charismatic biblical con-man in ''[[Elmer Gantry (film)|Elmer Gantry]]'' in 1960 won him the Academy Award and the Golden Globe for Best Actor. He played a Nazi war criminal in 1961 in the all-star, war-crime-trial film, ''[[Judgment at Nuremberg]]''. Playing a bird expert prisoner in ''[[Birdman of Alcatraz (film)|Birdman of Alcatraz]]'' in 1962, he earned the BAFTA Award for Best Foreign Actor and his third Oscar nomination. In 1963, Lancaster traveled to Italy to star as an Italian prince in the epic period drama ''[[The Leopard (1963 film)|The Leopard]]''. In 1964, he played a US Air Force General who, opposed by a Colonel played by Kirk Douglas, tries to overthrow the President in ''[[Seven Days in May]]''. Then, in 1966, he played an explosives expert in the western ''[[The Professionals (1966 film)|The Professionals]]''.

In 1970, Lancaster starred in the box-office hit, air-disaster drama ''[[Airport (1970 film)|Airport]]''. He experienced a career resurgence in 1980 with the crime-romance ''[[Atlantic City (1980 film)|Atlantic City]]'', winning the BAFTA for Best Actor and landing his fourth Oscar nomination. Starting in the late 1970s, he also appeared in television mini-series, including the award-winning [[Separate but Equal (film)|''Separate but Equal'']] with [[Sidney Poitier]]. He continued acting into his late 70s, until a stroke in 1990 forced him to retire; four years later he died from a heart attack. His final film role was in the Oscar-nominated ''[[Field of Dreams]]''.

The [[American Film Institute]] ranks Lancaster as #19 of the [[AFI's 100 Years...100 Stars|greatest male stars]] of classic Hollywood cinema.&lt;ref&gt;[http://afi.com/100years/stars.aspx &quot;AFI's 50 GREATEST AMERICAN SCREEN LEGENDS&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190222091649/http://www.afi.com/100Years/stars.aspx |date=February 22, 2019 }} ''[[American Film Institute]].'' Retrieved: December 7, 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==

Lancaster was born on November 2, 1913, in [[Manhattan]], [[New York (state)|New York]], at his parents' home at 209 East 106th Street, the son of Elizabeth (''née'' Roberts) and mailman James Lancaster.&lt;ref name=&quot;buford p. 12&quot;&gt;Buford 2008, p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt; Both of his parents were [[Protestants]] of working-class origin. All four of his grandparents were Scots-Irish immigrants to the United States, from the province of [[Ulster]]; his maternal grandparents were from [[Belfast]] and were descendants of [[English people|English]] immigrants to Ireland.&lt;ref name=&quot;buford p. 12&quot;/&gt;

Lancaster grew up in [[East Harlem]] and spent much of his time on the streets. He developed a great interest and skill in gymnastics while attending [[DeWitt Clinton High School]], where he was a [[basketball]] star. Before he graduated from DeWitt Clinton, his mother died of a [[cerebral hemorrhage]]. Lancaster was accepted by [[New York University]] with an athletic scholarship, but subsequently dropped out.&lt;ref&gt;Buford 2008, p. 28.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Circus career==
 {{multiple image
&lt;!-- Essential parameters --&gt;
| align     = right
| direction = vertical
| width     = 220
&lt;!-- Image 1 --&gt;
| image1    = Circus-Lancaster-Cravat.jpg
| alt1      =
| caption1  = Lancaster and [[Nick Cravat]], performing with the [[Federal Theatre Project]] Circus (1935–38)
&lt;!-- Image 2 --&gt;
| image2    = Circus-Lancaster.jpg
| alt2      =
| caption2  = Cravat and Lancaster performing on the horizontal bars
}}

At the age of 9, Lancaster met [[Nick Cravat]] with whom he developed a lifelong partnership.&lt;ref name=Andreychukp3&gt;Andreychuk 2005, p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; Together, they learned to act in local theatre productions and circus arts at [[Union Settlement Association|Union Settlement]], one of the city's oldest settlement houses.&lt;ref name=Andreychukp3/&gt; In the 1930s, they formed the acrobat duo Lang and Cravat and soon joined the Kay Brothers circus. However, in 1939, an injury forced Lancaster to give up the profession, with great regret. He then found temporary work, first as a salesman for [[Marshall Fields]] and then as a singing waiter in various restaurants.&lt;ref&gt;Andreychuk 2005, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt;

==World War II service==

With the United States having entered [[World War II]], Lancaster joined the [[United States Army]] in 1942 and performed with the Army's 21st [[Special Services (entertainment)|Special Services]] Division, one of the military groups organized to follow the troops on the ground and provide [[USO]] entertainment to keep up morale. He served with General [[Mark W. Clark|Mark Clark]]'s [[United States Army North|Fifth Army]] in Italy from 1943 to 1945.&lt;ref&gt;Andreychuk 2005, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Acting career==
===Broadway===
[[File:Killers001.jpg|left|thumb|With [[Ava Gardner]] in ''[[The Killers (1946 film)|The Killers]]'' (1946)]]
Lancaster returned to New York after his Army service. Although initially unenthusiastic about acting, Lancaster was encouraged to audition for a Broadway play by a producer who saw him in an elevator while he was visiting his then-girlfriend at work.&lt;ref name=&quot;Film and Bio&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Andreychuk|first=Ed|title=
Burt Lancaster: A Filmography and Biography|page=7 |quote=&quot;[Norma] was then working for radio producer Ray Knight at the RCA Building in New York City. Going up in an elevator there, Burt noticed he was being stared at by a smaller man. ...His name was Jack Mahlor and as an associate of Irving Jacobs he was looking for a big-framed actor ... to read for the role of the tough-minded sergeant.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; The audition was successful and Lancaster was cast in [[Harry Brown (writer)|Harry Brown]]'s ''[[Eight Iron Men|A Sound of Hunting]]'' (1945). The show only ran three weeks, but his performance attracted the interest of a Hollywood agent, [[Harold Hecht]]. Lancaster had other offers but Hecht promised him the opportunity to produce their own movies within five years of hitting Hollywood.

Through Hecht, Lancaster was brought to the attention of producer [[Hal B. Wallis]], who signed him to a non-exclusive eight-movie contract.

===Hal Wallis===

Lancaster's first filmed movie was ''[[Desert Fury]]'' for Wallis in 1947, where Lancaster was billed after [[John Hodiak]] and [[Lizabeth Scott]]. It was directed by [[Lewis Allen (director)|Lewis Allen]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Grossers1947&quot;&gt;{{Cite magazine | url = http://archive.org/details/variety169-1948-01 | title = Top Grossers of 1947 | magazine = [[Variety (magazine)|Variety]] | date = January 7, 1948 | publisher = New York, NY: Variety Publishing Company | via = Internet Archive | page = 63}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://catalog.afi.com/Catalog/moviedetails/25137 |title=Desert Fury (1947) |website=AFI Catalog |access-date=2019-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Then producer [[Mark Hellinger]] approached him to star in 1946's ''[[The Killers (1946 film)|The Killers]]'', which was completed and released prior to ''Desert Fury''. Directed by [[Robert Siodmak]], it was a great commercial and critical success&lt;ref name=&quot;August 1946&quot;&gt;{{Cite magazine |url = https://archive.org/details/variety163-1946-08/page/n13 |title = Film reviews |magazine = [[Variety (magazine)|Variety]] |date= August 7, 1946 |publisher = New York, NY: Variety Publishing Company | via = Internet Archive |page = 13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite magazine |url = http://archive.org/details/variety165-1947-01 | title = 60 Top Grossers of 1946 | magazine = [[Variety (magazine)|Variety]] | date = January 1, 1947 | publisher = New York, NY: Variety Publishing Company | via = Internet Archive | page = 55}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{fv|date=October 2019|reason=Killers is listed as #50 on a list of 60 top grossers, which may not substantiate the claim of it being a &quot;critical success&quot;.}} and launched Lancaster and his co-star [[Ava Gardner]] to stardom. It has since come to be regarded as a classic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.criterion.com/films/724-the-killers |title=The Killers |website=Criterion.com |access-date=2019-10-30 |quote=&quot;Its first screen incarnation came in 1946, when director Robert Siodmak unleashed The Killers, helping to define the film noir style and launching the careers of Burt Lancaster and Ava Gardner in this archetypal masterpiece&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.britannica.com/topic/The-Killers-film-1946 |title=The Killers (1946) |website=britannica.com |access-date=2019-10-30 |quote=&quot;The film established Lancaster as a major talent, and it helped launch Gardner as one of the screen’s legendary sex symbols. ...The film is regarded as one of the top crime sagas of 1940s cinema&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Hellinger used Lancaster again on ''[[Brute Force (1947 film)|Brute Force]]'' in 1947, a prison drama written by [[Richard Brooks]] and directed by [[Jules Dassin]]. It was also well received.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grossers1947&quot;/&gt; Wallis released his films through Paramount, and so Lancaster and other Wallis contractees made cameos in ''[[Variety Girl]]'' in 1947.

Lancaster's next film was a thriller for Wallis in 1947, ''[[I Walk Alone]]'', co-starring Scott and a young [[Kirk Douglas]], who was also under contract to Wallis. ''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'' listed it as one of the top grossers of the year, taking in more than 2 million dollars.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grossers1948&quot;&gt;{{Cite magazine | url = https://archive.org/details/variety173-1949-01/page/n45 | title = Top Grossers of 1948 | magazine = [[Variety (magazine)|Variety]] | date = January 5, 1949 | publisher = New York, NY: Variety Publishing Company | via = Internet Archive | page = 46}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1948, Lancaster had a change of pace with the film adaptation of [[Arthur Miller]]'s ''[[All My Sons (film)|All My Sons]]'', made at [[Universal Pictures]] with [[Edward G. Robinson]]. His third film for Wallis was an adaptation of ''[[Sorry, Wrong Number (film)|Sorry, Wrong Number]]'' in 1948, with [[Barbara Stanwyck]].

===Norma Productions===

Hecht kept to his promise to Lancaster to turn producer. The two of them formed a company, Norma Productions, and did a deal with Universal to make a thriller in England, ''[[Kiss the Blood Off My Hands]]'' in 1948, with [[Joan Fontaine]] and directed by Norman Foster. It made a profit of only $50,000, but was critically acclaimed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grossers1948&quot;/&gt;

Back in Hollywood, Lancaster did another film noir with Siodmak, ''[[Criss Cross (film)|Criss Cross]]'', in 1949. It was originally going to be produced by Hellinger and when Hellinger died, another took over. [[Tony Curtis]] made an early appearance.

Lancaster did a fourth picture for Wallis, ''[[Rope of Sand]]'', in 1949.

Norma Productions signed a three-picture deal with [[Warner Bros.]] The first was 1950's ''[[The Flame and the Arrow]]'', a swashbuckler movie, in which Lancaster drew on his circus skills. Nick Cravat had a supporting role and the film was a huge commercial success, making $6 million. It was Warners' most popular film of the year and established an entirely new image for Lancaster.&lt;ref name=&quot;warners&quot;&gt;Warner Bros financial information in The William Shaefer Ledger. See Appendix 1, Historical Journal of Film, Radio and Television, (1995) 15:sup1, 1-31 p 30 {{DOI|10.1080/01439689508604551}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lancaster was borrowed by [[20th Century Fox]] for ''[[Mister 880]]'' in 1950, a comedy with [[Edmund Gwenn]]. MGM put him in a popular Western, ''[[Vengeance Valley]]'' in 1951,&lt;ref name=&quot;Mannix&quot;&gt;{{Citation | title = The Eddie Mannix Ledger | publisher = Margaret Herrick Library, Center for Motion Picture Study | place = Los Angeles}}&lt;/ref&gt; then he went to Warners to play the title role in the biopic ''[[Jim Thorpe – All-American]]'', also in 1951.

===Halburt===

Norma signed a deal with [[Columbia Pictures]] to make two films through a Norma subsidiary, Halburt. The first film was 1951's ''[[Ten Tall Men]]'', where Lancaster was a member of the [[French Foreign Legion]]. [[Robert Aldrich]] worked on the movie as a production manager.

The second was 1952's ''[[The First Time (1952 film)|The First Time]]'', a comedy which was the directorial debut of [[Frank Tashlin]]. It was meant to star Lancaster but he wound up not appearing in the film—the first of their productions in which he did not act.&lt;ref&gt;FILM ACTORS' UNION EXTENDS CONTRACT: Screen Guild Eases Pressure on Producers by Negotiating 6-Month Addition to Pact
By THOMAS F. BRADY Special to THE NEW YORK TIMES 14 Dec 1950: 51.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hecht-Lancaster Productions===

In 1951, the actor/producer duo changed the company's name to Hecht-Lancaster Productions. The first film under the new name was another swashbuckler: 1952's ''[[The Crimson Pirate]]'', directed by Siodmak. Co-starring Cravat, it was extremely popular.

Lancaster changed pace once more by doing a straight dramatic part in 1952's ''[[Come Back, Little Sheba (1952 film)|Come Back, Little Sheba]]'', based on a Broadway hit, with [[Shirley Booth]], produced by Wallis and directed by [[Daniel Mann]].

Alternating with adventure films, he went into ''[[South Sea Woman]]'' in 1952 at Warners. Part of the Norma-Warners contract was that Lancaster had to appear in some non-Norma films, of which this was one.&lt;ref&gt;Burt Breaks Mold When Typed: Burt Balks at Typed Film Roles – Scheuer, Philip K. Los Angeles Times December 14, 1952: D1.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Burt Lancaster and Deborah Kerr in From Here to Eternity trailer.jpg|thumb|right|With [[Deborah Kerr]] in ''[[From Here to Eternity]]'' (1953)]]

In 1954, for his own company, Lancaster produced and starred in ''[[His Majesty O'Keefe]]'', a South Sea island tale shot in Fiji. It was co-written by James Hill, who would soon become a part of the Hecht-Lancaster partnership.&lt;ref&gt;LANCASTER TO STAR IN SHIPWRECK TALE: Norma Productions Buys 'His Majesty O'Keefe' for the Actor's First '52 Role By THOMAS F. BRADY ''The New York Times'' January 1, 1951: 14.&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Artists===

Hecht and Lancaster left Warners for [[United Artists]], for what began as a two-picture deal, the first of which was to be 1954's ''[[Apache (film)|Apache]]'', starring Lancaster as a Native American.&lt;ref&gt;BURT LANCASTER MAKES U. A. DEAL: Movie Star and His Partner, Harold Hecht, Find a New Outlet for Productions By THOMAS M. PRYOR New York Times June 24, 1953: 30.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Looking at Hollywood: Lancaster Gets Indian Role in 'Bronco Apache' Hopper, Hedda. Chicago Daily Tribune2 Dec 1952: a5.&lt;/ref&gt;

They followed it with another Western in 1954, ''[[Vera Cruz (film)|Vera Cruz]]'', co-starring [[Gary Cooper]] and produced by Hill. Both films were directed by [[Robert Aldrich]] and were hugely popular.

United Artists signed Hecht-Lancaster to a multi-picture contract, to make seven films over two years.&lt;ref&gt;HOLLYWOOD SURPRISE by THOMAS M. PRYOR. ''The New York Times'' February 14, 1954: X5.&lt;/ref&gt; These included films which Lancaster did not act in. Their first was ''[[Marty (film)|Marty]]'' in 1955, based on [[Paddy Chayefsky]]'s TV play starring [[Ernest Borgnine]] and directed by [[Delbert Mann]]. It won both the [[Academy Award for Best Picture|Best Picture Oscar]] and the [[Palme d'Or]] award at [[Cannes Film Festival|Cannes]]. It also earned $2 million on a budget of $350,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;times&quot;&gt;HOLLYWOOD DOSSIER: 'MARTY' HITS JACKPOT – TEAM – ON THE SET By OSCAR GODBOUT HOLLYWOOD.. ''The New York Times'' September 11, 1955: X7.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Vera Cruz'' had been a huge success, but ''Marty'' secured Hecht-Lancaster as one of the most successful independent production companies in Hollywood at the time.&lt;ref name=&quot;tino&quot;&gt;Tino Balio, ''United Artists: The Company That Changed the Film Industry'', University of Wisconsin Press, 1987 p. 82&lt;/ref&gt; ''Marty'' star [[Ernest Borgnine]] was under contract to Hecht-Lancaster and was unhappy about his lack of upcoming roles, especially after only receiving some seven lines in 1957's ''Sweet Smell of Success'' and half of his pay for ''Marty''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url = https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/race/ernest-borgnine-1917-2012-interview-346400 | title = Ernest Borgnine (1917-2012): A Personal Remembrance and An Unforgettable Interview | website = The Hollywood Reporter | language = en|access-date=September 25, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; He eventually sued for breach of contract to gain back some of this money in 1957.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | url = https://books.google.com/?id=ooqACgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA14&amp;lpg=PA14&amp;dq=burt+lancaster+ernest+borgnine+contract#v=onepage&amp;q=burt%20lancaster%20ernest%20borgnine%20contract&amp;f=false | title = Burt Lancaster: A Filmography and Biography | last = Andreychuk | first = Ed | date = September 1, 2015 | publisher = McFarland | isbn = 9781476606491 | language = en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Without Hill, Hecht and Lancaster produced ''[[The Kentuckian (1955 film)|The Kentuckian]]'' in 1955; it was directed by Lancaster in his [[directorial debut]], and he also played a lead role. Lancaster disliked directing and only did it once more, in the 1970s.&lt;ref&gt;' The Top Box-Office Hits of 1955', ''Variety Weekly'', January 25, 1956&lt;/ref&gt;

Lancaster still had commitments with Wallis, and made ''[[The Rose Tattoo (film)|The Rose Tattoo]]'' for him in 1955, starring with [[Anna Magnani]] and [[Daniel Mann]] directing. It was very popular at the box office and critically acclaimed, winning Magnani an Oscar.&lt;ref&gt;' The Top Box-Office Hits of 1956', ''Variety Weekly'', January 2, 1957&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hecht-Hill-Lancaster===

In 1955, Hill was made an equal partner in the production company, with his name added to the company name, [[Hecht-Hill-Lancaster]] (HHL), releasing their first film in 1956, ''[[Trapeze (film)|Trapeze]]'', in which Lancaster performed many of his own stunts. ''Trapeze'', co-starring [[Tony Curtis]] and [[Gina Lollobrigida]], went on to become the production company's top box office success, and United Artists expanded its deal with HHL.&lt;ref&gt;Pryor, Thomas M. (1956). &quot;Hecht-Lancaster Plans New Films: Producing Unit Signs Deal with United Artists—5 Features Are Listed Lancaster to Act&quot;. ''The New York Times'', April 13, 1956. p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1956, Lancaster and Hecht entered the music industry with the companies [[Hecht-Lancaster &amp; Buzzell Music]] and [[Calyork Music]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url = http://www.americanradiohistory.com/Archive-Billboard/50s/1957/Billboard%201957-03-16.pdf | title = Buzzell Ties with Hecht &amp; Lancaster | magazine = [[Billboard (magazine)|Billboard]] | date = March 16, 1957 | page = 8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The HHL team impressed Hollywood with its success; as [[Life (magazine)|''Life'']] wrote in 1957, &quot;[a]fter the independent production of a baker's [[dozen]] of pictures, it has yet to have its first flop ... (They were also good pictures.).&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;hodgins19570610&quot;&gt;Hodgins, Eric. [https://books.google.com/books?id=Nz8EAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA146  &quot;Amid Ruins of an Empire a New Hollywood Arises.&quot;] ''Life,'' June 10, 1957, p. 146. Retrieved: April 22, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; In late 1957, they announced they would make ten films worth $14 million in 1958.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Hecht-Hill-Lancaster Planning Record Year: Group Will Produce $14,000,000 Worth of Motion Pictures in 1958&quot;. ''Los Angeles Times'', December 16, 1957. p. B9.&lt;/ref&gt;

Lancaster did two films for Wallis, to complete his eight film commitment for that contract: ''[[The Rainmaker (1956 film)|The Rainmaker]]'' in 1956, with [[Katharine Hepburn]], which earned Lancaster a Golden Globe nomination for Best Actor; and ''[[Gunfight at the O.K. Corral (film)|Gunfight at the O.K. Corral]]'' in 1957,  with Kirk Douglas, directed by [[John Sturges]], which was a huge commercial hit.

Lancaster worked with [[Tony Curtis]] again on ''[[Sweet Smell of Success]]'' (1957), a co-production between Hecht-Hill-Lancaster and Curtis' own company Curtleigh Productions (co-owned with his wife, [[Janet Leigh]]). The movie, directed by [[Alexander Mackendrick]], was a critical success but a commercial disappointment. Over the years it has come to be regarded as one of Lancaster's greatest films.&lt;ref&gt;Kate Buford, ''Burt Lancaster: An American Life'', Da Capo 2000 p 183&lt;/ref&gt;

Hecht-Hill-Lancaster produced seven additional films in the late 1950s. Four starred Lancaster: ''[[Run Silent, Run Deep (1958 film)|Run Silent, Run Deep]]'' (1958), a war film with [[Clark Gable]], directed by [[Robert Wise]], which was mildly popular; ''[[Separate Tables (film)|Separate Tables]]'' (1958), a hotel-set drama with Kerr and [[Rita Hayworth]] (who married James Hill), based on a play by [[Terence Rattigan]] which received an Oscar nomination for Best Picture and Oscar awards for lead actor for [[David Niven]] and supporting actress [[Wendy Hiller]], and was both a critical and commercial success; ''[[The Devil's Disciple (1959 film)|The Devil's Disciple]]'' (1959), with Douglas and [[Laurence Olivier]], which lost money (and saw Lancaster fire Mackendirck during shooting);&lt;ref&gt;&quot;1959: Probable Domestic Take&quot;, ''Variety'', January 6, 1960 p 34&lt;/ref&gt; and the western ''[[The Unforgiven (1960 film)|The Unforgiven]]'' (1960), with [[Audrey Hepburn]], which was a critical and commercial disappointment.&lt;ref&gt;pp. 151–152 Larkins, Bob &amp;  Magers, Boyd ''The Films of Audie Murphy'' McFarland, August 19, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

Three were made without Lancaster, all of which lost money: ''[[The Bachelor Party]]'' (1957), from another TV play by Chayefsky, and directed by Delbert Mann; ''[[Take a Giant Step]]'' (1959), about a black student; and ''[[Summer of the Seventeenth Doll (1959 film)|Summer of the Seventeenth Doll]]'' (1960), from an Australian play, shot in Australia and Britain.

Additionally, Hecht-Hill-Lancaster served as the production company for the 1960–61 TV series ''[[Whiplash (TV series)|Whiplash]]''.

The Hecht-Hill-Lancaster Productions company dissolved in 1960 after Hill ruptured his relationship with both Hecht and Lancaster.&lt;ref&gt;Hill went on to produce a single additional film, ''[[The Happy Thieves]]'', in a new production company, Hillworth Productions, co-owned with his wife [[Rita Hayworth]].&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hecht and Lancaster===
[[File:Burt Lancaster 1960.jpg|thumb|left|Drawing of Lancaster after he won an Oscar for ''Elmer Gantry'' (1960). Artist: [[Nicholas Volpe]]]]
Lancaster played the title role in ''[[Elmer Gantry (film)|Elmer Gantry]]'' (1960), written and directed by Richard Brooks for United Artists. The film received five Academy Award nominations, including Best Picture and Best Actor. Lancaster won the [[33rd Academy Awards|1960 Academy Award]] for Best Actor, a Golden Globe Award, and the [[New York Film Critics Award]] for his performance.

Hecht and Lancaster worked together on ''[[The Young Savages]]'' (1961), directed by [[John Frankenheimer]] and produced by Hecht. [[Sydney Pollack]] worked as a dialogue coach.

Lancaster starred in ''[[Judgment at Nuremberg]]'' (1961) for [[Stanley Kramer]], alongside [[Spencer Tracy]], [[Richard Widmark]] and a number of other iconic stars. The film was both a commercial and critical success, receiving 11 Oscar nominations, including Best Picture.

He then did another film with Hecht and Frankenheimer (replacing [[Charles Crichton]]), ''[[Birdman of Alcatraz (film)|Birdman of Alcatraz]]'' (1962), a largely fictionalized biography. In it he plays [[Robert Stroud]], a federal prisoner incarcerated for life for two murders, who begins to collect birds and over time becomes an expert in bird diseases even publishing a book. The film shows Stroud transferred to the maximum security Alcatraz prison where he is not allowed to keep birds and as he ages he gets married, markets bird remedies, helps stop a prison rebellion, and writes a book on the history of the U.S. penal system, but never gets paroled. The sympathetic performance earned Lancaster a Best Actor Oscar nomination, a BAFTA Award for Best Actor, and a Golden Globe nomination for Best Actor in a Dramatic Role. Hecht went on to produce five films without Lancaster's assistance, through his company Harold Hecht Films Productions between 1961 and 1967, including another Academy Award winner, ''[[Cat Ballou]]'', starring [[Lee Marvin]] and [[Jane Fonda]].

===Collaborations with younger filmmakers===
Lancaster made ''[[A Child Is Waiting]]'' (1963) with [[Judy Garland]]. It was produced by Kramer and directed by [[John Cassavetes]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | first = Tino | last = Balio | title = United Artists: The Company That Changed the Film Industry | url = https://archive.org/details/unitedartistscom00bali | url-access = registration | publisher = University of Wisconsin Press | date = 1987 | page = [https://archive.org/details/unitedartistscom00bali/page/145 145]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He went to Italy to star in ''[[The Leopard (1963 film)|The Leopard]]'' (1963) for [[Luchino Visconti]], co-starring [[Alain Delon]] and [[Claudia Cardinale]]. It was one of Lancaster's favourite films and was a big hit in France but failed in the US (though the version released was much truncated.)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Buford | first = Kate | title = Burt Lancaster: An American Life | year = 2000 | publisher = Aurum | location = London | isbn = 1-85410-740-2 | pages = 222–227}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He had a small role in ''[[The List of Adrian Messenger]]'' (1963) for producer/star Kirk Douglas, and then did two for Frankenheimer: ''[[Seven Days in May]]'' (1964), a political thriller with Douglas, and ''[[The Train (1964 film)|The Train]]'' (1964), a World War Two action film (Lancaster had Frankenheimer replace [[Arthur Penn]] several days into filming).

Lancaster starred in ''[[The Hallelujah Trail]]'' (1965), a comic Western produced and directed by [[John Sturges]] which failed to recoup its large cost.&lt;ref name=&quot;sturges&quot;&gt;Glenn Lovell, ''Escape Artist: The Life and Films of John Sturges'', University of Wisconsin Press, 2008 p250&lt;/ref&gt;

He had a big hit with ''[[The Professionals (1966 film)|The Professionals]]'' (1966), a Western directed by Brooks and also starring [[Lee Marvin]].

In 1966, at the age of 52, Lancaster appeared nude in director [[Frank Perry]]'s film ''[[The Swimmer (1968 film)|The Swimmer]]'' (1968), in what the critic [[Roger Ebert]] called &quot;his finest performance&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ebert&quot;&gt;{{cite news | first = Roger | last = Ebert | authorlink = Roger Ebert | url = http://www.rogerebert.com/reviews/the-swimmer-1968 | title = Review: &quot;The Swimmer&quot; | newspaper = [[Chicago Sun-Times]] | publisher = [[Sun-Times Media Group]] | location = Chicago, Illinois | date = July 2, 1968 | accessdate = October 24, 2018 | via = RogerEbert.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to working on ''The Swimmer'', Lancaster was terrified of the water because he did not know how to swim. In preparation for the film, he took swimming lessons from [[UCLA]] swim coach Bob Horn.&lt;ref name=&quot;StoryOftheSwimmer&quot;&gt;{{cite AV media | people = [[Chris Innis|Innis, Chris]] | url = http://grindhousereleasing.com/?tag=story-of-the-swimmer | chapter = The Story of The Swimmer | title = The Swimmer | publisher = [[Grindhouse Releasing]] | location = Los Angeles, California | edition = 2014 | format = Blu-ray/DVD}}&lt;/ref&gt; Filming was difficult and clashes between Lancaster and Perry led to [[Sydney Pollack]] coming in to do some filming.&lt;ref name=tcmart&gt;Stafford, Jeff [http://www.tcm.com/tcmdb/title/12842/The-Swimmer/articles.html &quot;The Swimmer&quot; (article)] on [[TCM.com]]&lt;/ref&gt; The film was not released until 1968, when it proved to be a commercial failure, though Lancaster remained proud of the movie and his performance.

===Norlan Productions===
[[File:Burt Lancaster - Audrey Hepburn - 1960.JPG|thumb|right|With [[Audrey Hepburn]] in ''[[The Unforgiven (1960 film)|The Unforgiven]]'' (1960)]]
In 1967, Lancaster formed a new partnership with [[Roland Kibbee]], who had already worked as a writer on five Lancaster projects:
* ''Ten Tall Men''
* ''The Crimson Pirate''*
* ''[[Three Sailors and a Girl]]'' (in which Lancaster made a cameo appearance)
* ''Vera Cruz''
* ''The Devil's Disciple''

Through Norlan Productions, Lancaster and Kibbee produced ''[[The Scalphunters]]'' in 1968, directed by Sydney Pollack.

Lancaster followed it with another film from Pollack, ''[[Castle Keep]]'' in 1969, which was a big flop. So was ''[[The Gypsy Moths]]'', for Frankenheimer, also in 1969.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Big Rental Films of 1969&quot;, ''Variety'', January 7, 1970 p 15&lt;/ref&gt;

===1970s===

Lancaster had one of the biggest successes of his career with ''[[Airport (1970 film)|Airport]]'', in 1970, starring alongside [[Dean Martin]], [[Jean Seberg]] and [[Jacqueline Bisset]]. The film received nine Academy Award nominations, including one for Best Picture. It became one of the biggest box-office hits of 1970 and, at that time, reportedly the highest-grossing film in the history of [[Universal Pictures]].

He then went into a series of Westerns: ''[[Lawman (film)|Lawman]]'' in 1971, directed by [[Michael Winner]]; ''[[Valdez Is Coming]]'' in 1971, for Norlan; and ''[[Ulzana's Raid]]'' in 1972, directed by Aldrich and produced by himself and Hecht. None were particularly popular but ''Ulzana's Raid'' has become a cult film.&lt;ref name=&quot;aldrich&quot;&gt;&quot;I CAN'T GET JIMMY CARTER TO SEE MY MOVIE!&quot;
Aldrich, Robert. Film Comment; New York Vol. 13, Iss. 2,  (Mar/Apr 1977): 46-52.&lt;/ref&gt;

Lancaster did two thrillers, both 1973: ''[[Scorpio (1973 film)|Scorpio]]'' with Winner and ''[[Executive Action (film)|Executive Action]]''.

Lancaster returned to directing in 1974 with ''[[The Midnight Man (1974 film)|The Midnight Man]]'', which he also wrote and produced with Kibee.

He made a second film with Visconti, ''[[Conversation Piece (film)|Conversation Piece]]'' in 1974 and played the title role in the TV series ''[[Moses the Lawgiver]]'', also in 1974.

Lancaster was one of many names in 1975's ''[[1900 (film)|1900]]'', directed by [[Bernardo Bertolucci]], and he had a cameo in 1976's ''[[Buffalo Bill and the Indians, or Sitting Bull's History Lesson]]'' for [[Robert Altman]].

He played [[Shimon Peres]] in the TV movie ''[[Victory at Entebbe]]'' in 1977 and had a supporting role in ''[[The Cassandra Crossing]]'' in 1976. He made a fourth and final film with Aldrich, ''[[Twilight's Last Gleaming]]'' in 1977, and had the title role in 1977's ''[[The Island of Dr. Moreau (1977 film)|The Island of Dr. Moreau]]''.&lt;ref&gt;A Bittersweet Burt Lancaster, Looking Back-and Forward--at 62: A Bittersweet Burt Lancaster By Kenneth Turan. The Washington Post May 23, 1976: 165.&lt;/ref&gt;

Lancaster was top-billed in ''[[Go Tell the Spartans]]'' in 1978, a [[Vietnam War]] film; Lancaster admired the script so much that he took a reduced fee and donated money to help the movie to be completed. He was in ''[[Zulu Dawn]]'' in 1979.&lt;ref&gt;Kate Buford, ''Burt Lancaster'' (Da Capo Press, 2000) {{ISBN|0-306-81019-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1980s===
Lancaster began the 1980s with a highly acclaimed performance in ''[[Atlantic City (1980 film)|Atlantic City]]'' in 1980, directed by [[Louis Malle]]. The film received 5 Oscar nominations, including Best Picture and a Best Actor nomination for Lancaster.

He had key roles in ''[[Cattle Annie and Little Britches]]'' in 1981, ''[[The Skin]]'' in 1982 with Cardinale, ''[[Marco Polo (mini-series)|Marco Polo]]'', also in 1982, and ''[[Local Hero (film)|Local Hero]]'' in 1983.

By now, Lancaster was mostly a character actor in features, as in ''[[The Osterman Weekend (film)|The Osterman Weekend]]'' in 1983, but he was the lead in the TV movie ''[[Scandal Sheet (1985 film)|Scandal Sheet]]'' in 1985.

He was in ''[[Little Treasure]]'' in 1985, directed by [[Alan Sharp]], who had written ''Ulzana's Raid''; ''[[On Wings of Eagles (miniseries)|On Wings of Eagles]]'' in 1986, for TV, as [[Bull Simons]]; 1986's ''[[Barnum (TV movie)|Barnum]]'', made for TV, in the title role; ''[[Tough Guys (film)|Tough Guys]]'', in 1986, with Douglas, ''[[Fathers and Sons: A German Tragedy]]'', in 1986, for German TV, 1987's ''[[Control (1987 film)|Control]]'', in Italy, ''[[Rocket Gibraltar]]'', in 1988, and ''[[La bottega dell'orefice|The Jeweller's Shop]]'', in 1989.

His first big hit in a while was ''[[Field of Dreams]]'' in 1989, in which he played a supporting role as [[Moonlight Graham]]. He was also in the miniseries ''[[The Betrothed (miniseries)|The Betrothed]]'' in 1989.

===Final years===
Lancaster's final performances included TV mini series ''[[The Phantom of the Opera (1990 film)|The Phantom of the Opera]]'' (1990); ''[[Voyage of Terror: The Achille Lauro Affair]]'' (1990) as [[Leon Klinghoffer]]; and ''[[Separate But Equal (film)|Separate But Equal]]'' (1991) with [[Sidney Poitier]].

===Frequent collaborators===
[[File:Judgment at Nuremberg-Burt Lancaster 2.jpg|thumb|In ''[[Judgment at Nuremberg]]'' (1961)]]
Lancaster appeared in a total of 17 films produced by his agent, [[Harold Hecht]]. Eight of these were co-produced by [[James Hill (producer)|James Hill]]. He also appeared in eight films produced by [[Hal B. Wallis]] and two with producer [[Mark Hellinger]]. Although Lancaster's work alongside Kirk Douglas was mostly known as a successful pair of actors, Douglas, in fact, produced four films for the pair, through his production companies Bryna Productions and Joel Productions. Roland Kibbee also produced three Lancaster films, and Lancaster was also cast in two [[Stanley Kramer]] productions.

[[John Frankenheimer]] directed five films with Lancaster:
* 1961's ''[[The Young Savages]]'' (1961)
* 1962's ''Birdman of Alcatraz'' (1962)
* 1964's ''[[Seven Days in May]]''
* 1964's ''[[The Train (1964 film)|The Train]]''
* 1969's ''[[The Gypsy Moths]]''

He was directed four times by [[Robert Aldrich]], three times each by [[Robert Siodmak]] and [[Sydney Pollack]], and twice each by [[Byron Haskin]], [[Daniel Mann]], [[John Sturges]], [[John Huston]], [[Richard Brooks]], [[Alexander Mackendrick]], [[Luchino Visconti]], and [[Michael Winner]].

[[Roland Kibbee]] wrote for seven Lancaster films. Lancaster used makeup veteran Robert Schiffer in 20 credited films, hiring Schiffer on nearly all of the films he produced.

==Political activism==
Lancaster was a vocal supporter of progressive and [[liberalism|liberal]] political causes and an opponent of [[right-wing]] political movements such as [[McCarthyism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | first = Peter | last = Stanfield | first2 = Frank | last2 = Krutnik | first3 = Brian | last3 = Neve | first4 = Steve | last4 = Neale | title = 'Un-American' Hollywood: Politics and Film in the Blacklist Era | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=ItXpEDXFrncC&amp;pg=PA212 | publisher = [[Rutgers University Press]] | location = New Brunswick, New Jersey | date = December 27, 2007 | page = 212 | isbn = 9780813543970}}&lt;/ref&gt; He frequently spoke out in support of racial and other minorities. As a result, he was often a target of FBI investigations.&lt;ref name=&quot;ACLU HQ Serial&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Marquette Archives&quot;&gt;{{cite archive |first= |last= |item=Series 70 |type=manuscript |item-id=810-1032 |series = |file=61-10149 |box=1 |collection=1 |collection-url =https://www.marquette.edu/library/archives/Mss/FBI/FBI-sc.php |repository = |institution=Marquette Archives |location=Marquette University |quote=Actor Burt Lancaster was investigated by the FBI for affiliation with the Communist Party of America in the 1940s, for alleged homosexual behavior in the 1950s, and participating in the activities of the Civil Rights Congress in the 1960s.}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was named in President [[Richard Nixon]]'s 1973 &quot;Enemies List&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.enemieslist.info/list2sc.php&lt;/ref&gt;

A vocal opponent of the [[Vietnam War]], he helped pay for the successful defense of a soldier accused of &quot;[[fragging]]&quot;, i.e. (murdering) another soldier during war-time.&lt;ref&gt;Buford 2008, p. 266.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1968, Lancaster actively supported the presidential candidacy of [[anti-war]] Senator [[Eugene McCarthy]] of [[Minnesota]], and frequently spoke on his behalf during the [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic]] primaries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Wheeler | first = Mark | title = Celebrity Politics | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=Yu-U5tfCaqoC&amp;pg=PA48 | publisher = [[Polity (publisher)|Polity]] | location = Cambridge, England | date = August 5, 2013 | page = 48 | isbn = 9780745652498}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He campaigned heavily for [[George McGovern]] in the [[1972 United States presidential election]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = The Daily News from Port Angeles, Washington | url = https://www.newspapers.com/newspage/25642163/ | page = 4 | date = July 20, 1976 |access-date=August 1, 2018 | newspaper = [[Peninsula Daily News]] | publisher = [[Black Press Ltd.]] | location = Port Angeles, Washington | via = [[Newspapers.com]]|url-access=subscription}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1985, Lancaster joined the fight against [[AIDS]] after fellow movie star, [[Rock Hudson]], contracted the disease.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first = Mary T. | last = Schmich | first2 = Gene | last2 = Siskel |author2-link=Gene Siskel | url = http://articles.chicagotribune.com/1985-10-03/news/8503070295_1_actor-rock-hudson-aids-benefit-aids-research | title = Actor Rock Hudson, 59, Victim Of Aids | newspaper = [[Chicago Tribune]] | publisher = [[Tronc]] | location = Chicago, Illinois | date = October 3, 1985 |access-date=August 1, 2018 | page = 2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lancaster delivered the bed-ridden Hudson's last words at the Commitment to Life fundraiser at a time when the stigma surrounding AIDS was at its height. He was the only major male star who attended.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = https://www.nytimes.com/1985/09/20/us/hollywood-turns-out-for-aids-benefit.html | title = Hollywood Turns Out for AIDS Benefit |access-date=October 23, 2019 | newspaper = [[The New York Times]] | date = September 20, 1985 | last1 = Harmetz | first1 = Aljean |author1-link=Aljean Harmetz}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Buford&quot;/&gt;

Of his political opinions, frequent co-star [[Tony Curtis]] said: &quot;Here's this great big aggressive guy that looks like a ding-dong athlete playing these big tough guys and he has the soul of—who were those first philosophers of equality?—[[Socrates]], [[Plato]]. He was a Greek philosopher with a sense that everybody was equal.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Buford&quot;/&gt;

Actor and [[Screen Actors Guild|SAG]] president [[Ed Asner]] said he showed everybody in Hollywood &quot;how to be a liberal with balls&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Buford&quot;/&gt;

===Hollywood Ten===
Early in his career, Lancaster reportedly signed a statement release by the [[National Council of the Arts, Sciences and Professions]] (NCASP) asking Congress to abolish the [[House Un-American Activities Committee]]&lt;ref name=&quot;ACLU HQ Serial&quot;/&gt;. He was also a member of the short-lived [[Committee for the First Amendment]], formed in support of the [[Hollywood Ten]]. He was one of 26 movie stars who flew to Washington in October 1947 to protest against the HUAC hearings.&lt;ref name=&quot;ACLU HQ Serial&quot;/&gt; The committee's ''Hollywood Fights Back'' broadcasts on [[ABC Radio Network]] were two 30-minute programs that took place October 27 and November 2, 1947, during which committee members voiced their opposition to the HUAC hearings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | ref = harv | last = Smith | first = Ronald L | title = Horror Stars on Radio: The Broadcast Histories of 29 Chilling Hollywood Voices | year = 2010 | page = 168 | publisher = McFarland &amp; Co | location = Jefferson, NC | isbn = 978-0-7864-5729-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url = https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i6HpeyPjYxI | title = Hollywood Fights Back - 10/26/1947 (1 of 2) | via = www.youtube.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many members faced black-listing and backlash due to their involvement in the committee. Lancaster was listed in anti-communist literature as a [[fellow traveler]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Red Stars In Hollywood&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Fagan |first=Myron |date=1948 |title=Red Stars In Hollywood |url=https://archive.org/details/1948RedStarsInHollywoodMyronCourevalFagan/page/n5 |page=6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Civil Rights Movement===
He and his second wife, Norma, hosted a fundraiser for [[Martin Luther King Jr.]] and the [[Student Diversity Leadership Conference|SDLC]], ahead of the historic [[March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom|March on Washington]] in 1963.&lt;ref name=&quot;Buford&quot;/&gt; He attended the [[March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom|March]], where he was one of the speakers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | url = https://variety.com/2015/biz/columns/1963-march-on-washington-hollywood-bob-dylan-sidney-poitier-1201580118/ | title = Hollywood Turned Out for Historic 'I Have a Dream' Speech | last = Gray | first = Tim | date = August 28, 2015 |access-date=August 1, 2018 | journal = [[Variety (magazine)|Variety]] | publisher = [[Penske Business Media, LLC.]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = https://edition.cnn.com/2013/08/28/politics/march-on-washington-kennedy-jitters/index.html | title = Kennedy White House had jitters ahead of 1963 March on Washington | last = Matthews | first = David | date = August 28, 2013 |access-date=August 1, 2018 | work = [[CNN Entertainment]] | publisher = [[Turner Broadcasting System, Inc.]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; He flew in from France for the event, where he was shooting [[The Train (1964 film)|''The Train'']], and flew back again the next day, despite a reported [[fear of flying]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Buford&quot;&gt;{{Cite web | url = http://www.thefreelibrary.com/Burt+Lancaster:+An+American+Life.-a067051657 | title = Burt Lancaster: An American Life}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = https://www.youtube.com/watch/?v=U54KWuN0lIE | title = Burt Lancaster speaks at the &quot;March on Washington&quot; |access-date=October 23, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===ACLU===
In 1968, Lancaster was elected to serve as chairman of the [[Roger Baldwin Foundation]], a newly formed fund-raising arm of the [[American Civil Liberties Union of Southern California]]. His co-chairs were [[Frank Sinatra]] and [[Irving L. Lichtenstein]]. In October 1968, he hosted a party at his home to raise money for the [[ACLU]] to use for the defense of the more than four hundred people at the [[1968 Democratic National Convention]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Buford&quot;/&gt; Throughout the years, he remained an ardent supporter and a fundraiser for the organization.

While serving as a member of the five-person ACLU Foundation executive committee, he cast the key vote to retain [[Ramona Ripston]] as executive director of the Southern California affiliate, a position she would build into a powerful advocacy force in Los Angeles politics. Ripston later recalled: &quot;There was a feeling that a woman couldn't run the ACLU foundation, nor have access to the books. The vote finally came down to two 'yes' and two 'no.' Who had the deciding vote? Burt. He had a scotch or two and finally he said, 'I think she should be executive director.' I always loved him for that.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Buford&quot;/&gt;

When President [[George H. W. Bush]] derided Democratic candidate [[Michael Dukakis]] as a “card-carrying member of the ACLU”, Lancaster was one of the supporters featured in the organization's first television advertising campaign stating: &quot;I'm a card-carrying member of the ACLU&quot; and &quot;No one agrees with every single thing they've done. But no one can disagree with the guiding principle—with liberty and justice for all.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nwAVj-L0lck | title = ACLU PSA with Burt Lancaster |access-date=October 23, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also campaigned for [[Michael Dukakis]] in the [[1988 United States presidential election]].

==Personal life==
[[File:Bill Lancaster 1967.JPG|thumb|left|Lancaster's son [[Bill Lancaster|Bill]] in ''[[The Big Valley]]'' (1967)]]

===Marriages and relationships===
Lancaster guarded his private life and attempted to keep it private despite his stardom. He was married three times and had 5 children.

====June Ernst====
His first marriage was to June Ernst, a trapeze acrobat. Ernst was the daughter of a renowned female aerialist and an accomplished acrobat herself. After they were married, he performed with her and her family until their separation in the late 1930s. It is not clear when they divorced. Contemporary reports listed 1940, but subsequent biographers have suggested dates as late as 1946, thus delaying his marriage to his second wife.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;Buford 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Norma Anderson====
He met Norma Anderson (1917–1988) when she substituted for an ill actress in a USO production for the troops in Italy. She had been working as a stenographer. Reportedly, on seeing Lancaster in the crowd on her way to town from the airport, she turned to an officer and asked, &quot;Who is that good-looking officer and is he married?&quot; The officer set up a blind date between the two for that evening.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;/&gt;

Norma Lancaster was active in political causes. An entire room in their Bel Air home was devoted to her major interest, the League of Woman Voters, crammed with printing presses and all the necessary supplies for mass mailings.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;/&gt; She was a life-long member of the [[NAACP]]. The couple held a fundraiser for [[Martin Luther King Jr.]] and the [[Southern Christian Leadership Conference|SDLC]] ahead of the 1963 [[March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom|March on Washington]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | url = https://books.google.com/?id=3QDbDgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT75&amp;lpg=PT75&amp;dq=nomra+lancaster+nAACP#v=onepage&amp;q=norma%20lancaster%20nAACP&amp;f=false | title = Nothing but Love in God's Water: Volume 2: Black Sacred Music from Sit-Ins to Resurrection City | isbn = 9780271080123 | last1 = Darden | first1 = Robert | date = September 23, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

All five of his children were with Anderson: [[Bill Lancaster|Bill]] (who became an actor and screenwriter), James, Susan, Joanna (who worked as a film producer), and Sighle (pronounced &quot;Sheila&quot;). However, it was a troubled marriage. The pair separated in 1966, and finally divorced in 1969.

====Jackie Bone====
In 1966, Lancaster began what would be a long-term relationship with the recently widowed Jackie Bone, who worked as a hairdresser on [[The Professionals (1966 film)|''The Professionals'']]. It was a tumultuous relationship with Bone once smashing a wine bottle over Lancaster's head at a dinner with [[Sydney Pollack]] and [[Peter Falk]]. Reportedly, they eventually split up after her religious conversion, which Lancaster believed he couldn't share with her.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;/&gt;

====Susan Martin====
His third marriage, to Susan Martin, lasted from September 1990 until his death in 1994.

====Possible affairs====
Friends say he claimed he was romantically involved with [[Deborah Kerr]] during the filming of ''From Here to Eternity'' in 1953.&lt;ref&gt;Buford 2008, pp. 127–30.&lt;/ref&gt; However, Kerr stated that while there was a spark of attraction,{{Citation needed|date=October 2019}} nothing ever happened. The pair were in two other films together: [[Separate Tables (film)|''Separate Tables'']] and ''[[The Gypsy Moths]]''.

He reportedly had an affair with [[Joan Blondell]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title = Their Stars Shone Brightly | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=vU_3DAAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;q=joan%20blondell | last = Goldbeck, MD | first = Larry O. | publisher = Xlibris | date = August 27, 2016 | isbn = 978-1524532154 | accessdate = October 18, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In her 1980 autobiography, [[Shelley Winters]] claimed to have had a 2-year affair with him, during which time he was considering separation from his wife. In his Hollywood memoirs, friend [[Farley Granger]] recalled an incident when he and Lancaster had to come to Winters' rescue one evening when she had inadvertently overdosed on too much alcohol and sleeping pills.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | url = https://books.google.com/?id=tXCQxD6u584C&amp;pg=PT156&amp;lpg=PT156&amp;dq=include+me+out+burt+lancaster#v=onepage&amp;q=burt%20lancaster&amp;f=false | title = Include Me Out: My Life from Goldwyn to Broadway | isbn = 9781429945448 | last1 = Granger | first1 = Farley | last2 = Calhoun | first2 = Robert | date = March 6, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; She broke up with him for &quot;cheating on her with his wife&quot; after she heard reports of his wife's third or fourth pregnancy.&lt;ref&gt;Winters 1980, p. 259.&lt;/ref&gt; Lancaster and Winters performed together in the 1949 radio play adaptation of [[The Killers (1946 film)|''The Killers'']]. They appeared in 2 films together: ''[[The Young Savages]]'', where she played his character's former lover and ''[[The Scalphunters]]''.

Recent biographers and others suggest that Lancaster was [[bisexual]], and that he had intimate relationships with men as well as women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first = Daniel | last = Jeffreys | url = http://www.independent.ie/world-news/screen-god-burts-sex-life-set-the-stage-for-hollywood-gay-scene-26122343.html | title = Screen god Burt's sex life set the stage for Hollywood gay scene | newspaper = [[The Independent]] | publisher = Independent Print Limited | location = London, England | date = March 18, 2000 | accessdate = February 13, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to testimony in Kate Buford's ''Burt Lancaster: An American Life'', Lancaster was devotedly loyal to his friends and family. Old friends from his childhood remained his friends for life.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | first = Kate | last = Buford | title = Burt Lancaster: An American Life | publisher = Knopf | date = March 14, 2000 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=fTCFAAAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover | isbn = 978-0679446033}}{{page needed|date=October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Legacy===
The [[centennial]] of Lancaster's birth was honored at New York City's [[Film Society of Lincoln Center]] in May 2013 with the screening of 12 of the actor's best-known films, from ''The Killers'' to ''Atlantic City''.&lt;ref name=NYTimes&gt;{{cite news | first = Stephen | last = Holden | authorlink = Stephen Holden | url = https://www.nytimes.com/2013/05/12/movies/lots-of-lancaster-at-lincoln-center.html | title = Film: lots of Lancaster at Lincoln Center | newspaper = [[The New York Times]] | publisher = New York Times Company | location = New York City | date = May 12, 2013 | accessdate = October 24, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lancaster has a star on the [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]], at 6801 Hollywood Boulevard.

===Religion===
Despite his [[Protestant]] background and upbringing,{{Citation needed|date=October 2019}} Lancaster identified as an [[atheist]] later in life.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | first = Kate | last = Buford | title = Burt Lancaster: An American Life | publisher = [[Da Capo Press]] | location = Boston, Massachusetts | date = 2001 | isbn = 978-0306810190 | page = 277}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Health problems==
As Lancaster grew older, he became increasingly wracked with [[atherosclerosis]], and barely survived a routine [[gall bladder]] operation in January 1980. Following two minor [[heart attacks]], he had to undergo an emergency quadruple [[coronary bypass]] in 1983, after which he was extremely weak. However, he still managed to continue acting. In 1988, Lancaster was well enough to attend a Congressional hearing in Washington, D.C. with old colleagues such as [[James Stewart]] and [[Ginger Rogers]] to protest against media magnate [[Ted Turner]]'s plan to [[colorize]] various black-and-white films from the 1930s and 1940s. Lancaster's acting career ended after he suffered a [[stroke]] on November 30, 1990, which left him partially [[paralyzed]] and largely unable to speak.

==Death==
[[File:Burt Lancaster grave at Westwood Village Memorial Park Cemetery in Brentwood, California.JPG|thumb|Lancaster's grave]]
Lancaster died at his apartment in [[Century City, Los Angeles|Century City, California]], after suffering a third heart attack at 4:50 am on October 20, 1994, at the age of 80.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = Oscar Winner Burt Lancaster Dies at 80 | url = http://articles.latimes.com/1994-10-22/news/mn-56956_1_burt-lancaster | date = October 24, 1994 | newspaper = [[Los Angeles Times]] | accessdate = October 18, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; His body was cremated, and his ashes were scattered under a large oak tree in [[Westwood Memorial Park]] which is located in [[Westwood Village]], California. A small, square ground plaque amidst several others, only inscribed with &quot;BURT LANCASTER 1913–1994&quot;, marks the location. Upon his death, as he had previously requested, no memorial or funeral service was held for him.

==Filmography and awards==
===Film===
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! style=width:3% | Year !! style=width:25% | Title !! style=width:22% | Role !! class=&quot;unsortable&quot; | Notes
|-
| 1946
| ''[[The Killers (1946 film)|The Killers]]''
| Ole &quot;Swede&quot; Anderson
| With [[Ava Gardner]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | 1947
| ''[[Brute Force (1947 film)|Brute Force]]''
| Joe Collins
| With [[Hume Cronyn]]
|-
| ''[[Desert Fury]]''
| Tom Hanson
| With [[Lizabeth Scott]]
|-
| ''[[Variety Girl]]''
| Himself
| With [[Mary Hatcher]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;4&quot; | 1948
| ''[[I Walk Alone]]''
| Frankie Madison
| With [[Kirk Douglas]]
|-
| ''[[All My Sons (film)|All My Sons]]''
| Chris Keller
| With [[Edward G. Robinson]]
|-
| ''[[Sorry, Wrong Number]]''
| Henry Stevenson
| With [[Barbara Stanwyck]]
|-
| ''[[Kiss the Blood Off My Hands]]''
| William Earle &quot;Bill&quot; Saunders
| With [[Joan Fontaine]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 1949
| ''[[Criss Cross (film)|Criss Cross]]''
| Steve Thompson
| With [[Yvonne de Carlo]]
|-
| ''[[Rope of Sand]]''
| Michael &quot;Mike&quot; Davis
| With [[Paul Henreid]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 1950
| ''[[The Flame and the Arrow]]''
| Dardo Bartoli
| With [[Virginia Mayo]]
|-
| ''[[Mister 880]]''
| Steve Buchanan
| With [[Dorothy McGuire]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | 1951
| ''[[Vengeance Valley]]''
| Owen Daybright
| With [[Robert Walker (actor, born 1918)|Robert Walker]]
|-
| ''[[Jim Thorpe&amp;nbsp;– All-American]]''
| [[Jim Thorpe]]
| With [[Charles Bickford]]
|-
| ''[[Ten Tall Men]]''
| Sergeant Mike Kincaid
| With [[Jody Lawrance]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 1952
| ''{{sortname|The|Crimson Pirate}}''
| Capitan Vallo
| With [[Nick Cravat]]
|-
| ''[[Come Back, Little Sheba (1952 film)|Come Back, Little Sheba]]''
| Doc Delaney
| With [[Shirley Booth]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | 1953
| ''[[South Sea Woman]]''
| Master Gunnery Sgt. James O'Hearn
| With [[Virginia Mayo]]
|-
| ''[[From Here to Eternity]]''
| 1st Sergeant Milton Warden
| [[New York Film Critics Circle Award for Best Actor]]&lt;br/&gt;Nominated—[[Academy Award for Best Actor]]
|-
| ''[[Three Sailors and a Girl]]''
| Marine
| With [[Jane Powell]]&lt;br&gt;Uncredited
|-
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | 1954
| ''[[His Majesty O'Keefe]]''
| [[David O'Keefe (ship captain)|Captain David O'Keefe]] / Narrator
| With [[Joan Rice]]
|-
| ''[[Apache (film)|Apache]]''
| Massai
| With [[Jean Peters]]
|-
| ''[[Vera Cruz (film)|Vera Cruz]]''
| Joe Erin
| With [[Gary Cooper]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 1955
| ''{{sortname|The|Kentuckian|The Kentuckian (1955 film)}}''
| Elias Wakefield (Big Eli)
| Director&lt;br/&gt;Nominated—[[Golden Lion|Golden Lion for Best Director]]
|-
| ''[[The Rose Tattoo (film)|The Rose Tattoo]]''
| Alvaro Mangiacavallo
| With [[Anna Magnani]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 1956
| ''[[Trapeze (film)|Trapeze]]''
| Mike Ribble
| With [[Gina Lollobrigida]] and [[Tony Curtis]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Silver Bear for Best Actor]] at [[6th Berlin International Film Festival|Berlin]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Berlinale 1956&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.berlinale.de/en/archiv/jahresarchive/1956/03_preistr_ger_1956/03_Preistraeger_1956.html | title = 6th Berlin International Film Festival: Prize Winners | accessdate = December 27, 2009 | work = berlinale.de}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| ''{{sortname|The|Rainmaker|The Rainmaker (1956 film)}}''
| Bill Starbuck
| Nominated—[[Golden Globe Award for Best Actor&amp;nbsp;– Motion Picture Drama]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 1957
| ''[[Gunfight at the O.K. Corral (film)|Gunfight at the O.K. Corral]]''
| Marshal [[Wyatt Earp]]
| With [[Kirk Douglas]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Laurel Awards|Laurel Award for Top Male Action Star]]
|-
| ''[[Sweet Smell of Success]]''
| J.J. Hunsecker
| With [[Tony Curtis]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 1958
| ''[[Run Silent, Run Deep (1958 film)|Run Silent, Run Deep]]''
| Lieutenant Commander Jim Bledsoe
| With [[Clark Gable]]
|-
| ''[[Separate Tables (film)|Separate Tables]]''
| John Malcolm
| With [[Rita Hayworth]], [[Wendy Hiller]], [[Deborah Kerr]] and [[David Niven]]
|-
| 1959
| ''{{sortname|The|Devil's Disciple|The Devil's Disciple (1959 film)}}''
| Reverend Anthony Anderson
| With [[Kirk Douglas]] and [[Laurence Olivier]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 1960
| ''{{sortname|The|Unforgiven|The Unforgiven (1960 film)}}''
| Ben Zachary
| With [[Audrey Hepburn]]
|-
| ''[[Elmer Gantry (film)|Elmer Gantry]]''
| Elmer Gantry
| [[Academy Award for Best Actor]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Golden Globe Award for Best Actor – Motion Picture Drama]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Laurel Awards|Laurel Award for Top Male Dramatic Performance]]&lt;br/&gt;[[New York Film Critics Circle Award for Best Actor]]&lt;br/&gt;Nominated—[[BAFTA Award for Best Actor in a Leading Role]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 1961
| ''{{sortname|The|Young Savages}}''
| ADA Hank Bell
| With [[Dina Merrill]]
|-
| ''[[Judgment at Nuremberg]]''
| Dr. Ernst Janning
| With [[Spencer Tracy]]
|-
| 1962
| ''[[Birdman of Alcatraz (film)|Birdman of Alcatraz]]''
| [[Robert Stroud]]
| [[BAFTA Award for Best Actor in a Leading Role]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Volpi Cup|Volpi Cup for Best Actor]]&lt;br/&gt;Nominated—[[Academy Award for Best Actor]]&lt;br/&gt;Nominated—[[Golden Globe Award for Best Actor&amp;nbsp;– Motion Picture Drama]]&lt;br/&gt;Nominated—[[Laurel Awards|Laurel Award for Top Male Dramatic Performance]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | 1963
| ''{{sortname|A|Child Is Waiting}}''
| Dr. Matthew Clark
| With [[Judy Garland]]
|-
| ''{{sortname|The|Leopard|The Leopard (1963 film)}}''
| Prince Don Fabrizio Salina
| With [[Claudia Cardinale]] and [[Alain Delon]]
|-
| ''{{sortname|The|List of Adrian Messenger}}''
| Animal Rights Protester (cameo)
| With [[George C. Scott]]
|-
| 1964
| ''[[Seven Days in May]]''
| General James Mattoon Scott
| With [[Kirk Douglas]], [[Frederic March]] and [[Ava Gardner]]&lt;br/&gt;Nominated—[[Laurel Awards|Laurel Award for Top Male Dramatic Performance]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 1965
| ''[[The Train (1965 film)|The Train]]''
| Paul Labiche
| With [[Jeanne Moreau]]&lt;br/&gt;Nominated—[[Laurel Awards|Laurel Award for Top Male Action Performance]]
|-
| ''{{sortname|The|Hallelujah Trail}}''
| Colonel Thaddeus Gearhart
| With [[Lee Remick]]
|-
| 1966
| ''{{sortname|The|Professionals|The Professionals (1966 film)}}''
| Bill Dolworth
| With [[Lee Marvin]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 1968
| ''{{sortname|The|Scalphunters}}''
| Joe Bass
| With [[Shelley Winters]]&lt;br/&gt;Nominated—[[Laurel Awards|Laurel Award for Top Male Action Performance]]
|-
| ''{{sortname|The|Swimmer|The Swimmer (1968 film)}}''
| Ned Merrill
| With [[Janice Rule]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | 1969
| ''[[Jenny Is a Good Thing]]''
| Narrator
|
|-
| ''[[Castle Keep]]''
| Maj. Abraham Falconer
| With [[Peter Falk]]
|-
| ''{{sortname|The|Gypsy Moths}}''
| Mike Rettig
| With [[Deborah Kerr]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 1970
| ''[[Airport (1970 film)|Airport]]''
| Mel Bakersfeld
| With [[Dean Martin]]
|-
| ''[[King: A Filmed Record... Montgomery to Memphis]]''
| Himself
|
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 1971
| ''[[Lawman (film)|Lawman]]''
| Bannock Marshal Jared Maddox
| With [[Lee J. Cobb]]
|-
| ''[[Valdez Is Coming]]''
| Marshal Bob Valdez
| With [[Susan Clark]]
|-
| 1972
| ''[[Ulzana's Raid]]''
| U.S. Cavalry Scout McIntosh
| With [[Bruce Davison]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 1973
| ''[[Scorpio (film)|Scorpio]]''
| Cross
| With [[Alain Delon]]
|-
| ''[[Executive Action (film)|Executive Action]]''
| James Farrington
| With [[Robert Ryan]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 1974
| ''{{sortname|The|Midnight Man|The Midnight Man (1974 film)}}''
| Jim Slade
| Co-Director
|-
| ''[[Conversation Piece (film)|Conversation Piece]]''
| The Professor
| [[David di Donatello for Best Actor]]&lt;br/&gt;Fotogramas de Plata Award for Best Foreign Movie Performer
|-
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | 1976
| ''[[1900 (film)|1900]]''
| Alfredo Berlinghieri the Elder
| With [[Robert De Niro]]
|-
| ''[[Buffalo Bill and the Indians, or Sitting Bull's History Lesson]]''
| [[Ned Buntline]]
| With [[Paul Newman]]
|-
| ''{{sortname|The|Cassandra Crossing}}''
| Colonel Stephen Mackenzie
| With [[Sophia Loren]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 1977
| ''[[Twilight's Last Gleaming]]''
| General Lawrence Dell
| With [[Richard Widmark]]
|-
| ''{{sortname|The|Island of Dr. Moreau|The Island of Dr. Moreau (1977 film)}}''
| Dr. Paul Moreau
| With [[Michael York]]
|-
| 1978
| ''[[Go Tell the Spartans]]''
| Major Asa Barker
| With [[Craig Wasson]]
|-
| 1979
| ''[[Zulu Dawn]]''
| [[Anthony Durnford|Colonel Anthony Durnford]]
| With [[Peter O'Toole]]
|-
| 1980
| ''[[Atlantic City (1980 film)|Atlantic City]]''
| Lou Pascal
|[[BAFTA Award for Best Actor in a Leading Role]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Boston Society of Film Critics Award for Best Actor]]&lt;br/&gt;[[David di Donatello for Best Actor]]&lt;br/&gt;Fotogramas de Plata Award for Best Foreign Movie Performer&lt;br/&gt;Kansas City Film Critics Circle Award for Best Actor&lt;br/&gt;[[Los Angeles Film Critics Association Award for Best Actor]]&lt;br/&gt;[[National Society of Film Critics Award for Best Actor]]&lt;br/&gt;[[New York Film Critics Circle Award for Best Actor]]&lt;br/&gt;Nominated—[[Academy Award for Best Actor]]&lt;br/&gt;Nominated—[[Genie Award for Best Performance by a Foreign Actor]]&lt;br/&gt;Nominated—[[Golden Globe Award for Best Actor&amp;nbsp;– Motion Picture Drama]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 1981
| ''[[Cattle Annie and Little Britches]]''
| [[Bill Doolin]], the Oklahoma outlaw
| With [[Amanda Plummer]] and [[Diane Lane]]
|-
| ''[[The Skin]]''
| General Mark Cork
| With [[Marcello Mastroianni]], [[Claudia Cardinale]], [[Carlo Giuffrè]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 1983
| ''[[Local Hero (film)|Local Hero]]''
| Felix Happer
| Nominated—[[BAFTA Award for Best Actor in a Supporting Role]]
|-
| ''{{sortname|The|Osterman Weekend|The Osterman Weekend (film)}}''
| CIA Director Maxwell Danforth
| With [[Rutger Hauer]]
|-
| 1985
| ''[[Little Treasure]]''
| Delbert Teschemacher
| With [[Margot Kidder]] and [[Ted Danson]]
|-
| 1986
| ''[[Tough Guys]]''
| Harry Doyle
| With [[Kirk Douglas]]
|-
| 1987
| ''[[Control (1987 film)|Control]]''
| Dr. Herbert Monroe
| With [[Ben Gazzara]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 1988
| ''[[Rocket Gibraltar]]''
| Levi Rockwell
| With [[Patricia Clarkson]]
|-
| ''[[La bottega dell'orefice|The Jeweler's Shop]]''
| The Jeweler
| With [[Olivia Hussey]]
|-
| 1989
| ''[[Field of Dreams]]''
| [[Moonlight Graham|Dr. Archibald 'Moonlight' Graham]]
| With [[Kevin Costner]]
|}

===Television===
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! Year !! Title !! Role !! class=&quot;unsortable&quot; | Notes
|-
| 1969
| ''[[Sesame Street]]''
| Himself
| Sequences on feelings, the alphabet, counting to 10 doing pushups&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url = https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VyDOs8dlzYQ | title = Sesame Street - Burt Lancaster (1969) | via = www.youtube.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 1974
| ''[[Moses the Lawgiver]]''
| [[Moses]]
| Miniseries
|-
| 1976
| ''[[Victory at Entebbe]]''
| [[Shimon Peres]]
| With [[Anthony Hopkins]]
|-
| 1978
| ''{{sortname|The|Unknown War|The Unknown War (documentary)}}''
| Narrator
| 20 episode USA-USSR archival documentary series on World War II
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 1982
| ''[[Marco Polo (miniseries)|Marco Polo]]''
| Teobaldo Visconti ([[Pope Gregory X]])
| Miniseries
|-
| ''[[The Life of Verdi (miniseries)|The Life of Verdi]]''
| Narrator (English version)
| Miniseries
|-
| 1985
| ''[[Scandal Sheet (1985 film)|Scandal Sheet]]''
| Harold Fallen
| With [[Robert Urich]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | 1986
| ''[[On Wings of Eagles (miniseries)|On Wings of Eagles]]''
| [[Arthur D. Simons|Colonel Arthur D. &quot;Bull&quot; Simons]]
| Miniseries
|-
| ''[[Väter und Söhne – Eine deutsche Tragödie|Fathers and Sons: A German Tragedy]]''
| Geheimrat Carl Julius Deutz
| Miniseries
|-
| ''Barnum''
| [[P. T. Barnum|Phineas Taylor &quot;P.T.&quot; Barnum]]
| With [[Hanna Schygulla]]
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 1989
| ''[[Cops (TV series)|Cops]]''
| Narrator
| Provided narration on pilot episode: &quot;Broward County, Florida 1&quot;
|-
| ''[[The Betrothed (miniseries)|The Betrothed]]''
| [[Federico Borromeo|Cardinal Federigo Borromeo]]
| Miniseries
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 1990
| ''{{sortname|The|Phantom of the Opera|The Phantom of the Opera (miniseries)}}''
| Gerard Carriere
| Miniseries&lt;br/&gt;Nominated – [[Golden Globe Award for Best Actor – Miniseries or Television Film]]
|-
| ''[[Voyage of Terror: The Achille Lauro Affair]]''
| [[Leon Klinghoffer]]
| With [[Eva Marie Saint]]
|-
| 1991
| ''[[Separate but Equal (film)|Separate but Equal]]''
| [[John W. Davis]]
| Miniseries, (final appearance)
|}

===Box office ranking===
For a number of years exhibitors voted Lancaster as among the most popular stars:
*1950 – 16th (US)
*1951 – 25th (US)
*1952 – 24th (US)
*1953 – 17th (US)
*1954 – 13th (US), 7th (UK)
*1955 – 16th (US)
*1956 – 4th (US), 3rd (UK)
*1957 – 15th (US), 3rd (UK)
*1958 – 20th (US)
*1960 – 19th (US)
*1961 – 11th (US)
*1962 – 10th (US)

===In other media===
Spanish music group [[Hombres G]] released an album named ''[[La cagaste, Burt Lancaster]]'' (''You messed up, Burt Lancaster'') in 1986.

[[Thomas Hart Benton (painter)|Thomas Hart Benton]] painted a scene from ''The Kentuckian'' as part of the film's marketing. Lancaster posed for the painting, also known as ''[[The Kentuckian (painting)|The Kentuckian]]''.&lt;ref name=LACMA&gt;{{cite web | author1 = painted by Thomas Hart Benton | title = The Kentuckian (painting) | url = http://collections.lacma.org/node/239015 | website = LACMA Collections | date = 1954}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em|refs=
&lt;ref name=&quot;ACLU HQ Serial&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = https://archive.org/details/ACLUHQ1032/page/n1 | title = ACLU HQ serial 1032 | website = archive.org |access-date=October 11, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin}}
* Andreychuk, Ed. ''Burt Lancaster: A Filmography And Biography''. Jefferson, North Carolina: McFarland &amp; Company, Inc., Publishers, 2005. {{ISBN|978-0-7864-2339-2}}.
* Buford, Kate. ''Burt Lancaster: An American Life''. London: Aurum Press, 2008. {{ISBN|1-84513-385-4}}.
* Winters, Shelley. ''Shelley: Also known as Shirley''. New York: Morrow, 1980. {{ISBN|978-0-688-03638-6}}.
* Karney, Robyn. ''Burt Lancaster: A Singular Man''. Trafalgar Square Pub, 1997 {{ISBN|1570760748}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{commons|Burt Lancaster}}
* {{Britannica|328982}}
* {{IMDb name}}
* {{Tcmdb name}}
* {{AllRovi person}}
* {{IBDB name}}
* {{worldcat id|lccn-n83-65628}}
* [http://www.virtual-history.com/movie/person/58/burt-lancaster Literature on Burt Lancaster]
* [http://versewisconsin.org/Issue110/poems/balassone.html The Rainmaker]

{{Navboxes
|title = Awards for Burt Lancaster
|list =
{{AcademyAwardBestActor 1941–1960}}
{{BAFTA Award for Best Actor 1960–1979}}
{{Boston Society of Film Critics Award for Best Actor}}
{{David di Donatello for Best Foreign Actor}}
{{GoldenGlobeBestActorMotionPictureDrama 1943–1960}}
{{Los Angeles Film Critics Association Award for Best Actor}}
{{National Society of Film Critics Award for Best Actor}}
{{New York Film Critics Circle Award for Best Actor}}
{{ScreenActorsGuildAward LifeAchievement 1980–1999}}
{{Silver Bear for Best Actor}}
{{Volpi Cup for Best Actor}}
}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Lancaster, Burt}}
[[Category:1913 births]]
[[Category:1994 deaths]]
[[Category:20th-century American male actors]]
[[Category:American film producers]]
[[Category:American male film actors]]
[[Category:Activists for African-American civil rights]]
[[Category:American anti–Vietnam War activists]]
[[Category:Anti-racism activists]]
[[Category:American army personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:American people of English descent]]
[[Category:American people of Scottish descent]]
[[Category:BAFTA winners (people)]]
[[Category:Best Actor Academy Award winners]]
[[Category:Best Actor BAFTA Award winners]]
[[Category:Best Drama Actor Golden Globe (film) winners]]
[[Category:Best Foreign Actor BAFTA Award winners]]
[[Category:Silver Bear for Best Actor winners]]
[[Category:Volpi Cup for Best Actor winners]]
[[Category:Volpi Cup winners]]
[[Category:Burials at Westwood Village Memorial Park Cemetery]]
[[Category:California Democrats]]
[[Category:David di Donatello winners]]
[[Category:DeWitt Clinton High School alumni]]
[[Category:LGBT rights activists from the United States]]
[[Category:Male Western (genre) film actors]]
[[Category:Military personnel from New York City]]
[[Category:Liberalism in the United States]]
[[Category:New York (state) Democrats]]
[[Category:United States Army personnel]]
[[Category:People from East Harlem]]
[[Category:Male actors from New York City]]
[[Category:People of the New Deal arts projects]]
[[Category:Activists from New York (state)]]
[[Category:Activists from California]]
[[Category:American atheists]]
[[Category:American people of Irish descent]]
[[Category:Stroke survivors]]</text>
      <sha1>sgifbi36eqh9s7e4a6zo0ghdvj1t446</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
