  <page>
    <title>Burroughs Corporation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4524</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939510642</id>
      <parentid>939507981</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-06T22:35:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Dating maintenance tags: {{Cn}}</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=February 2010}}
{{confuse|Bourroughs Wellcome}}

{{Infobox company 
| name = Burroughs, Inc.
| logo = Burroughs Corporation (logo ca. 1947).jpg
| logo_caption = Burroughs Corporation logo
| successor      = 
| location       = 
| foundation     = 1886 
| fate           = Merged with the [[Sperry Corporation]] in 1986 to form [[Unisys]]
| key_people     = [[William Seward Burroughs I]]
| industry       = Hardware
| products       =
| website        =
}}

The '''Burroughs Corporation''' was a major American manufacturer of business equipment. The company was founded in 1886 as the [[American Arithmometer Company]], and after the 1986 merger with [[UNIVAC|Sperry UNIVAC]] was renamed [[Unisys]]. The company's history paralleled many of the major developments in [[history of computing|computing]]. At its start, it produced mechanical [[adding machine]]s, and later moved into programmable ledgers and then computers. It was one of the largest producers of [[mainframe computer]]s in the world, also producing related equipment including [[typewriter]]s and [[Printer (computing)|printer]]s.

==Early history==
[[File:Burrough's Adding Machines, 1914.jpg|thumb|1914 advertisement]]
[[File:BurroughsCorporationAddingMachine.jpg|thumb|An early Burroughs [[adding machine]]]]
[[File:1890s adding machine.jpg|thumb|Desktop model in use around 1910]]

In 1886, the American Arithmometer Company was established in [[St. Louis]], [[Missouri]], to produce and sell an [[adding machine]] invented by [[William Seward Burroughs I|William Seward Burroughs]] (grandfather of [[Beat Generation]] author [[William S. Burroughs]]). In 1904, six years after Burroughs' death, the company moved to Detroit and changed its name to the Burroughs Adding Machine Company. It was soon the biggest adding machine company in America.

==Evolving product lines==
The adding machine range began with the basic, hand-cranked P100 which was only capable of adding. The design included some revolutionary features, foremost of which was the [[dashpot]].{{why|What was it?  How did it work?  Why was it &quot;revolutionary&quot;?|date=February 2020}} The P200 offered a subtraction capability and the P300 provided a means of keeping 2 separate totals. The P400 provided a moveable carriage, and the P600 and top-of-the-range P612 offered some limited programmability based upon the position of the carriage. The range was further extended by the inclusion of the &quot;J&quot; series which provided a single finger calculation facility, and the &quot;c&quot; series of both manual and electrical assisted [[comptometer]]s. In the late 1960s, the Burroughs sponsored [[Nixie tube|&quot;nixi-tube&quot;]] provided an electronic display calculator. Burroughs developed a range of adding machines with different capabilities, gradually increasing in their capabilities. A revolutionary adding machine was the ''Sensimatic'', which was able to perform many business functions semi-automatically. It had a moving programmable carriage to maintain [[general ledger|ledgers]]. It could store 9, 18 or 27 [[Trial balance|balances]] during the ledger posting operations and worked with a mechanical adder named a Crossfooter. The Sensimatic developed into the ''Sensitronic'' which could store balances on a [[Magnetic stripe card|magnetic stripe]] which was part of the ledger card. This balance was read into the accumulator when the card was inserted into the carriage. The Sensitronic was followed by the E1000, E2000, E3000, E4000, E6000 and the E8000, which were computer systems supporting  card reader/punches and a [[line printer]].

Later, Burroughs was selling more than adding machines, including typewriters. 

==Move into computers==
The biggest shift in company history came in 1953: the Burroughs Adding Machine Company was renamed the Burroughs Corporation and began moving into [[digital computer]] products, initially for banking institutions. This move began with Burroughs' purchase in June 1956, of the [[ElectroData Corporation]] in [[Pasadena, California]], a spinoff of the [[Consolidated Engineering Corporation]] which had designed test instruments and had a cooperative relationship with [[California Institute of Technology|Caltech]] in Pasadena.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sawyer&quot;&gt;Sawyer, T.J., [http://tjsawyer.com/B205Home.htm &quot;Burroughs 205 HomePage&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; ElectroData had built the [[Datatron|Datatron 205]] and was working on the Datatron 220.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sawyer&quot;/&gt; The first major computer product that came from this marriage was the B205 tube computer. In the late 1960s the L and TC series range was produced (e.g. the [[Burroughs TC500|TC500]]—Terminal Computer 500) which had a [[IBM Selectric typewriter|golf ball printer]] and in the beginning a 1K (64 bit) disk [[Computer memory|memory]]. These were popular as branch [[Computer terminal|terminal]]s to the B5500/6500/6700 systems, and sold well in the banking sector, where they were often connected to non-Burroughs mainframes. In conjunction with these products, Burroughs also manufactured an extensive range of cheque processing equipment, normally attached as terminals to a larger system such as a B2700 or B1700.

In the 1950s, Burroughs worked with the [[Federal Reserve Bank]] on the development and computer processing of [[magnetic ink character recognition]] (MICR) especially for the processing of bank cheques. Burroughs made special MICR/OCR sorter/readers which attached to their medium systems line of computers ([[Burroughs B2000|2700/3700/4700]]) and this entrenched the company in the computer side of the banking industry.

==A force in the computing industry==
Burroughs was one of the nine major United States computer companies in the 1960s, with [[IBM]] the largest, [[Honeywell]], [[NCR Corporation]], [[Control Data Corporation]] (CDC), [[General Electric]] (GE), [[Digital Equipment Corporation]] (DEC), [[RCA]] and [[Sperry Rand]] ([[UNIVAC]] line). In terms of sales, Burroughs was always a distant second to [[IBM]]. In fact, IBM's market share was so much larger than all of the others that this group was often referred to as &quot;IBM and the Seven Dwarves.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web|
url=http://www.dvorak.org/blog/ibm-and-the-seven-dwarfs-dwarf-one-burroughs/ |
title=IBM and the Seven Dwarfs — Dwarf One: Burroughs|
publisher=Dvorak Uncensored|
author=[[John C. Dvorak|Dvorak, John C.]]|
date=2006-11-25|
accessdate=2010-02-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 1972 when GE and RCA were no longer in the mainframe business, the remaining five companies behind IBM became known as the [[BUNCH]], an [[acronym]] based on their initials.

At the same time, Burroughs was very much a competitor. Like IBM, Burroughs tried to supply a complete line of products for its customers, including Burroughs-designed printers, [[disk drive]]s, [[tape drive]]s, computer printing paper, and even [[typewriter ribbon]]s.

===Developments and innovations===
The Burroughs Corporation developed three highly innovative [[computer architecture|architectures]], based on the design philosophy of &quot;[[language-directed design]]&quot;. Their machine instruction sets favored one or many [[high level programming languages]], such as [[ALGOL]], [[COBOL]] or [[FORTRAN]]. All three architectures were considered [[Mainframe computer|mainframe]] class machines:
* The [[Burroughs large systems]] machines started with the B5000 in 1961. The B5500 came a few years later when large rotating disks replaced drums as the main external memory media.  These B5000 Series systems used the world's first virtual memory multi-programming operating system.{{cn|date=February 2020}}  They were followed by the B6500/B6700 in the later 1960s, the B7700 in the mid 1970s, and the A series in the 1980s. The underlying architecture of these machines is similar and continues today as the [[Unisys]] ClearPath MCP line of computers: [[stack machine]]s designed to be programmed in an extended [[Algol 60]]. Their [[operating system]]s, called MCP ([[MCP (Burroughs Large Systems)|Master Control Program]]&amp;mdash;the name later borrowed by the screenwriters for ''[[Tron]]''), were programmed in [[Executive Systems Problem Oriented Language|ESPOL]] (Executive Systems Programming Oriented Language, a minor extension of ALGOL), and later in NEWP (with further extensions to ALGOL) almost a decade before [[Unix]]. The command interface developed into a compiled [[Structured programming|structured language]] with declarations, statements and procedures called WFL ([[Work Flow Language]]). 

:Many [[computer scientist]]s consider these series of computers to be technologically groundbreaking. Stack oriented processors, with 48 bit word length where each word was defined as data or program contributed significantly to a secure operating environment, long before [[spyware]] and [[Computer virus|viruses]] affected computing. And the modularity of these large systems was also unique: multiple [[CPU]]s, multiple memory modules and multiple [[I/O]] and Data Comm processors permitted incremental and [[cost effective]] growth of system performance and reliability. 

:In industries like banking, where continuous operations was mandatory, Burroughs large systems penetrated most every large bank, including the [[Federal Reserve Bank]]. Burroughs built the backbone [[switching systems]] for [[Society for Worldwide Interbank Financial Telecommunication]] (SWIFT) which sent its first message in 1977. Unisys is still the provider to SWIFT today.

* Burroughs produced the [[Burroughs B2500|B2500]] or &quot;medium systems&quot; computers aimed primarily at the business world. The machines were designed to execute [[COBOL]] efficiently. This included a BCD ([[Binary Coded Decimal]]) based arithmetic unit, storing and addressing the main memory using [[base 10]] numbering instead of [[Binary numeral system|binary]]. The designation for these systems was Burroughs B2500 through B49xx, followed by Unisys V-Series V340 through V560.

* Burroughs produced the [[Burroughs B1700|B1700]] or &quot;small systems&quot; computers that were designed to be [[microprogram]]med, with each process potentially getting its own [[virtual machine]] designed to be the best match to the [[programming language]] chosen for the program being run.

* The smallest general-purpose computers were the B700 &quot;microprocessors&quot; which were used both as stand-alone systems and as special-purpose data-communications or disk-subsystem controllers.

* Burroughs also manufactured an extensive range of [[accounting machine]]s including both stand-alone systems such as the [[Burroughs Sensimatic|Sensimatic]], L500 and B80, and dedicated terminals including the TC500 and specialised check processing equipment.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.picklesnet.com/burroughs/descriptions/b80.htm Burroughs B80 Family]&lt;/ref&gt;

* In 1982, Burroughs began producing [[personal computer]]s, the [[Burroughs B20|B20 and B25]] lines with the [[Intel 8086]]/[[Intel 8088|8088]] family of 16-bit chips as the processor.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oocities.org/siliconvalley/pines/4011/misc-doc/Intro.htm &quot;B25 FAMILY OF UNIVERSAL WORKSTATIONS INTRODUCTION&quot;], 1987&lt;/ref&gt; These ran the [[Convergent Technologies Operating System|BTOS]] operating system, which Burroughs licensed from [[Convergent Technologies (Unisys)|Convergent Technologies]]. These machines implemented an early [[Local Area Network]] to share a [[hard disk]] between [[workgroup (computer networking)|workgroup]] users. These microcomputers were later manufactured in [[Kunming]], [[China]] for use in China under agreement with Burroughs.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/1985/01/03/business/china-deal-for-burroughs.html &quot;China Deal For Burroughs&quot;], ''The New York Times'', [[Associated Press|AP]] story, January 3, 1985&lt;/ref&gt;

* Burroughs collaborated with [[University of Illinois]] on a multiprocessor architecture developing the [[ILLIAC IV]] computer in the early 1960s. The ILLIAC had up to 128 parallel processors while the B6700 &amp; B7700 only accommodated a total of 7 CPUs and/or IO units (the 8th unit was the memory tester).

* Burroughs made military computers, such as the D825 (the &quot;D&quot; prefix signifying it was for defense industrial use), in its Great Valley Laboratory in [[Paoli, Pennsylvania]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.smecc.org/burroughs_buic_-__an_gsa-51__sage_backup.htm &quot;Burroughs BUIC - AN/GSA-51 SAGE Backup&quot;], archived at SMECC&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last1 = Anderson | first1 = J. P. | last2 = Hoffman | first2 = S. A. | last3 = Shifman | first3 = J. | last4 = Williams | first4 = R. J. | chapter = D825 - a multiple-computer system for command &amp; control | doi = 10.1145/1461518.1461527 | title = Proceedings of the December 4-6, 1962, fall joint computer conference on - AFIPS '62 (Fall) | pages = 86 | year = 1962 | pmid =  | pmc = }}&lt;/ref&gt; The D825 was, according to some scholars, the first true multiprocessor computer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Enslow |first=Philip H., Jr. |title=Multiprocessor Organization—A Survey |journal=Computing Surveys |volume=9 |issue=1 |year=1977 |pages=103–129 |doi=10.1145/356683.356688 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Paoli was also home to the Defense and Space Group Marketing Division.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archive.computerhistory.org/resources/text/Burroughs/Burroughs.Display_Systems.1965.102646312.pdf &quot;Burroughs Display Systems&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120324211415/http://archive.computerhistory.org/resources/text/Burroughs/Burroughs.Display_Systems.1965.102646312.pdf |date=2012-03-24 }}, Defense and Space Group Marketing Division, Paoli, Pennsylvania, 1965&lt;/ref&gt;

* In 1964 Burroughs had also completed the D830 which was another variation of the D825 designed specifically for real-time applications, such as airline reservations. Burroughs designated it the B8300 after [[Trans World Airlines]] (TWA) ordered one in September 1965. A system with three instruction processors was installed at TWA's reservations center in [[Rockleigh, New Jersey]] in 1968. The system, which was called George, with an application programmed in [[JOVIAL]], was intended to support some 4000 terminals, but the system experienced repeated crashes due to a filing system disk allocation error when operating under a large load. A fourth processor was added but did nothing to resolve the problem. The problem was resolved in late 1970 and the system became stable. Unfortunately, the decision to cancel the project was being made at the very time that the problem was resolved. TWA cancelled the project and acquired one [[IBM System/360]] Model 75, two IBM System/360 model 65s, and IBM's [[Programmed Airline Reservations System|PARS]] software for its reservations system. TWA sued Burroughs for non-fulfillment of the contract, but Burroughs counter-sued, stating that the basic system did work and that the problems were in TWA's applications software. The two companies reached an out-of-court settlement.&lt;ref name=&quot;B3G&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Gray|first=George|url=http://wiki.cc.gatech.edu/folklore/index.php/Burroughs_Third-Generation_Computers|title=Burroughs Third-Generation Computers|journal=Unisys History Newsletter|volume=3|issue=5|date=October 1999|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171002194413/https://wiki.cc.gatech.edu/folklore/index.php/Main_Page|archive-date=October 2, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* Burroughs developed a half-size version of the D825 called the D82, cutting the word size from 48 to 24 bits and simplifying the computer's instruction set. The D82 could have up to 32,768 words of core memory and continued the use of separate instruction and i/o processors. Burroughs sold a D82 to [[Air Canada]] to handle reservations for trips originating in [[Montreal]] and [[Quebec]]. This design was further refined and made much more compact as the [[Pershing_missile_bibliography#Burroughs|D84]] machine which was completed in 1965. A D84 processor/memory unit with 4096 words of memory occupied just 1.4 cubic feet. This system was used successfully in two military projects: field test systems used to check the electronics of the Air Force [[General Dynamics F-111 Aardvark]] fighter plane{{cn|&quot;Successfully&quot; must be established here, as the plane went on to earn the nickname &quot;Widowmaker&quot; while the Luftwaffe worked out its design failures|date=February 2020}} and systems used to control the countdown and launch of the Army's [[Pershing 1]] and [[Pershing 1a|1a]] missile systems.&lt;ref name=&quot;B3G&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://umedia.lib.umn.edu/node/30883 &quot;Title: Trade show exhibition featuring the D84; Date 1965&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141129081312/http://umedia.lib.umn.edu/node/30883 |date=2014-11-29 }}, University of Minnesota archives&lt;/ref&gt;

==Merger with Sperry==
In September 1986, Burroughs Corporation merged with [[Sperry Corporation]] to form [[Unisys]]. For a time, the combined company retained the Burroughs processors as the A- and V-systems lines. However, as the market for large systems shifted from proprietary architectures to common servers, the company eventually dropped the V-Series line, although customers continued to use V-series systems {{as of | 2010 | lc =on}}. {{As of | 2017}} Unisys continues to develop and market the A-Series, now known as ClearPath.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
 |url          = http://www.unisys.com/unisys/news/detail.jsp?id=1120000970025610156
 |title        = Unisys Awarded Contract to Support IRS Mission-Critical Computing Systems
 |date         = 2013-02-19
 |publisher    = Unisys
 |accessdate   = 2013-03-11
 |quote        = BLUE BELL, Pa., February 19, 2013 - Unisys Corporation (NYSE: UIS) announced today that it has been awarded the Enterprise Computing Center Support (ECCS) contract from the Internal Revenue Service (IRS) [...] Under this single-award indefinite delivery-indefinite quantity (IDIQ) contract, the IRS can award Unisys task orders to provide support and maintenance services for the IRS computing environment, including Unisys ClearPath Dorado servers.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

== Re-emergence of the Burroughs name ==
[[File:Burroughs Payment Systems Plymouth Michigan.JPG|thumb|right|Burroughs Payment Systems in [[Plymouth, Michigan]], 2011]]
In 2010, Unisys sold off its Payment Systems Division to [[Marlin Equity Partners]], a California-based private investment firm, which incorporated it as Burroughs Payment Systems based in [[Plymouth, Michigan]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.burroughs.com/NewsEvents.aspx &quot;Marlin Equity Partners acquires elements of Unisys payment systems&quot;] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100414112030/http://www.burroughs.com/NewsEvents.aspx# |date=2010-04-14 }}, Burroughs press release, February 3, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.burroughs.com Burroughs Payment Systems website].In 2012, the company changed its name to Burroughs, Inc.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References in popular culture==
Burroughs B205 hardware has appeared as props in many [[Cinema of the United States|Hollywood]] television and film productions from the late 1950s. For example, a B205 [[front panel|console]] was often shown in the television series ''[[Batman (TV series)|Batman]]'' as the ''Bat Computer''; also as the computer in ''[[Lost in Space]]''. B205 tape drives were often seen in series such as ''[[The Time Tunnel]]'' and ''[[Voyage to the Bottom of the Sea (TV series)|Voyage to the Bottom of the Sea]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.angelfire.com/scifi/B205/onscreen.html &quot;B205 On Screen&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://starringthecomputer.com/computer.html?c=45 &quot;Starring the Computer: Burroughs B205&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Craig Ferguson]], American talk show host, comedian and actor was a Burroughs apprentice in [[Cumbernauld]], [[Scotland]].

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Allweiss, Jack A., [https://web.archive.org/web/20131202234301/http://jack.hoa.org/hoajaa/Burr126b.html &quot;Evolution of Burroughs Stack Architecture - Mainframe Computers&quot;], 2010
* [[Robert S. Barton|Barton, Robert S.]] &quot;A New Approach to the Functional Design of a Digital Computer&quot; Proc. western joint computer Conf. ACM (1961).
*{{cite journal|last=Gray|first=George|url=https://wiki.cc.gatech.edu/folklore/index.php/Some_Burroughs_Transistor_Computers|title=Some Burroughs Transistor Computers|journal=Unisys History Newsletter|volume=3|issue=1|date=March 1999|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161001200450/https://wiki.cc.gatech.edu/folklore/index.php/Some_Burroughs_Transistor_Computers|archive-date=October 1, 2016}}
*{{cite journal|last=Gray|first=George|url=https://wiki.cc.gatech.edu/folklore/index.php/Burroughs_Third-Generation_Computers|title=Burroughs Third-Generation Computers|journal=Unisys History Newsletter|volume=3|issue=5|date=October 1999|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170926190816/https://wiki.cc.gatech.edu/folklore/index.php/Burroughs_Third-Generation_Computers|archive-date=September 26, 2017}}
*Hauck, E.A., Dent, Ben A. &quot;Burroughs B6500/B7500 Stack Mechanism&quot;, SJCC (1968) pp.&amp;nbsp;245–251.
* Martin, Ian L. (2012) [https://leedsmet.academia.edu/IanMartin/Papers/1583479/Too_far_ahead_of_its_time_Barclays_Burroughs_and_real-time_banking &quot;Too far ahead of its time: Barclays, Burroughs and real-time banking&quot;], ''IEEE Annals of the History of Computing'' 34(2), pp.&amp;nbsp;5–19. {{ISSN|1058-6180}}. (Draft version)
* Mayer, Alastair J.W., [http://www.smecc.org/The%20Architecture%20%20of%20the%20Burroughs%20B-5000.htm &quot;The Architecture of the Burroughs B5000 - 20 Years Later and Still Ahead of the Times?&quot;], ACM Computer Architecture News, 1982 (archived at the Southwest Museum of Engineering, Communications and Computation. Glendale, Arizona)
*[[William M. McKeeman|McKeeman, William M.]] &quot;Language Directed Computer Design&quot;, FJCC (1967) pp.&amp;nbsp;413–417.
*[[Elliott Organick|Organick, Elliot I.]] [https://web.archive.org/web/20100511185718/http://www.bitsavers.org/pdf/burroughs/B5000_5500_5700/Organick_B5700_B6700_1973.pdf &quot;Computer System Organization The B5700/B6700 series&quot;], Academic Press (1973)
*Wilner, Wayne T. &quot;Design of the B1700&quot;, FJCC pp.&amp;nbsp;489–497 (1972).
* Wilner, Wayne T., [http://bitsavers.org/pdf/burroughs/B1700/Wilner_B1700designImp_May72.pdf &quot;B1700 Design and Implementation&quot;], Burroughs Corporation, Santa Barbara Plant, Goleta, California, May 1972.

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
* [http://purl.umn.edu/41129 Burroughs Corporation Records] [[Charles Babbage Institute]] University of Minnesota, Minneapolis. Collection contains the records of the Burroughs Corporation, and its predecessors the American Arithmometer Company and Burroughs Adding Machine Company. Materials include corporate records, photographs, films and video tapes, scrapbooks, papers of employees and the records of companies acquired by Burroughs. CBI's Burroughs Corporation Records includes over 100,000 photographs depicting the entire visual history of Burroughs from its origin as the American Arithmometer Corporation in 1886 to its merger with the Sperry Corporation to form the [[Unisys Corporation]] in 1986.
* [http://www.cbi.umn.edu/images/index.html Burroughs Corporation Photo Database] at the [[Charles Babbage Institute]] University of Minnesota. The searchable photo database permits browsing and retrieval of over 550 historical images.
* [http://purl.umn.edu/107105 &quot;Burroughs B 5000 Conference, OH 98&quot;], Oral history on 6 September 1985, Marina del Ray, California. [[Charles Babbage Institute]], University of Minnesota, Minneapolis. The Burroughs 5000 computer series is discussed by individuals responsible for its development and marketing from 1957 through the 1960s in a 1985 conference sponsored by AFIPS and Burroughs Corporation.
* [http://purl.umn.edu/104351 Oral history interview with Isaac Levin Auerbach] [[Charles Babbage Institute]] University of Minnesota. Auerbach discusses his work at Burroughs 1949–1957 managing development for the [[Semi Automatic Ground Environment|SAGE project]], [[BEAM I computer]], the [[Intercontinental Ballistic Missile System]], a [[magnetic core]] encryption communications system, and [[Atlas missile]].
* [http://purl.umn.edu/107210 Oral history interview with Robert V. D. Campbell]. Discusses his work at Burroughs (1949–1966) as director of research and in program planning.
* [http://purl.umn.edu/107213 Oral history interview with Alfred Doughty Cavanaugh] Cavanaugh discusses the work of his grandfather, A. J. Doughty, with [[William S. Burroughs|William Seward Burroughs]] and the Burroughs Adding Machine Company.
* [http://purl.umn.edu/107630 Oral history interview with Carel Sellenraad] [[Charles Babbage Institute]] University of Minnesota. Sellenraad describes his long association with Burroughs Adding Machine Company, and the impact of World Wars I &amp; II on the sales and service of calculators, and adding and bookkeeping machines in Europe.
* [http://purl.umn.edu/107635 Oral history interview with Ovid M. Smith] [[Charles Babbage Institute]] University of Minnesota. Smith reviews his 46½ year career at Burroughs Adding Machine Company (later Burroughs Corporation).
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120802080919/http://www.cs.virginia.edu/about/museum/ &quot;Early Burroughs Machines&quot;], [[University of Virginia]]'s Computer Museum.
* [http://bitsavers.org/pdf/burroughs/ Older Burroughs computer manuals online]
* [http://ed-thelen.org/comp-hist/BRL64-b.html Burroughs computers such as the D825 at BRL]
* [http://home.ix.netcom.com/~hancockm/ An historical Burroughs Adding Machine Company/Burroughs site]
* [http://home.ix.netcom.com/~hancockm/manufacturing_plants.htm Unofficial list of Burroughs manufacturing plants and labs]
* [http://www.ianjoyner.name Ian Joyner's Burroughs page]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20130521171833/http://jack.hoa.org/hoajaa/b5900.htm The Burroughs B5900 and E-Mode: A bridge to 21st Century Computing] - Jack Allweiss

{{Unisys}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Burroughs Corporation| ]]
[[Category:Defunct computer companies of the United States]]
[[Category:Defunct computer hardware companies]]
[[Category:Mechanical calculator companies]]
[[Category:Unisys]]
[[Category:Companies based in St. Louis]]
[[Category:Manufacturing companies established in 1886]]
[[Category:Manufacturing companies disestablished in 1986]]
[[Category:Technology companies disestablished in 1986]]
[[Category:1886 establishments in Missouri]]
[[Category:1986 establishments in the United States]]
[[Category:Defunct companies based in Missouri]]</text>
      <sha1>bme9ir409vf2uqx9s99ze3vauo5acbn</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
