  <page>
    <title>Balalaika</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4567</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942301625</id>
      <parentid>942300365</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-23T21:20:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TheAwesomeHwyh</username>
        <id>31474557</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/73.110.34.46|73.110.34.46]] ([[User talk:73.110.34.46|talk]]) ([[WP:HG|HG]]) (3.4.9)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about|the musical instrument|other uses|Balalaika (disambiguation)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2016}}
{{Infobox instrument
| name                  = Balalaika
| image                 =Balalaika-player.jpg!PinterestLarge.jpg
| image_size            =200 px
| alt                   =
| caption               =''Boy with Balalaika'', painting by Russian artist [[Nikolay Bogdanov-Belsky|Nikolay Petrovich Bogdanov-Belsky]]
| background            = string
| names                 =
| classification        = [[Plucked string instrument]]
| hornbostel_sachs      = 321.321
| hornbostel_sachs_desc = Composite [[chordophone]]
| inventors             =
| developed             = Late 18th to early 19th centuries
| timbre                =
| volume                =
| attack                =
| decay                 =
| range                 = [[File:Balalaika Range2.svg|center]]
| pitch                 =
| related               = [[Baglama]]

[[Dombra]] 

[[Domra]] 

[[Panduri]] 

[[Topshur]]
| musicians             =
| builders              =
| articles              =
{{Listen
| filename = Ru-балалайка.ogg
| title    = Pronunciation
| embed    = yes
}}}}

The '''balalaika''' ({{lang-ru|link=no|балала́йка}}, {{IPA-ru|bəɫɐˈɫajkə|pron}}) is a Russian [[string instrument|stringed]] [[musical instrument]] with a characteristic triangular wooden, hollow body, fretted neck and three strings. Two strings are usually tuned to the same note and the third string is a [[perfect fourth]] higher. The higher-pitched balalaikas are used to play melodies and chords.The instrument generally has a short [[sustain]], necessitating rapid strumming or plucking when it is used to play melodies. Balalaikas are often used for [[Russian traditional music|Russian folk music]] and [[Russian folk dances|dancing]].

The balalaika ''family of instruments'' includes instruments of various sizes, from the highest-pitched to the lowest: the piccolo balalaika, prima balalaika, secunda balalaika, alto balalaika, bass balalaika, and contrabass balalaika. There are balalaika orchestras which consist solely of different balalaikas; these ensembles typically play Classical music that has been arranged for balalaikas. The prima balalaika is the most common; the piccolo is rare. There have also been ''descant'' and ''tenor'' balalaikas, but these are considered obsolete. All have three-sided bodies; spruce, evergreen, or fir tops; and backs made of three to nine wooden sections (usually maple).

The prima balalaika, secunda and alto are played either with the fingers or a [[plectrum]] (pick), depending on the music being played, and the bass and contrabass (equipped with extension legs that rest on the floor) are played with leather plectra. The rare piccolo instrument is usually played with a pick.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.balalaika.org/_instruments.htm |title=The Washington Balalaika Society |publisher=www.balalaika.org |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090301144711/http://www.balalaika.org/_instruments.htm |archivedate=1 March 2009 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Etymology ==

The earliest mention of the term ''balalaika'' dates back to a 1688 Russian document.&lt;ref&gt;Belinskiy, Dmitry. [http://www.skaz1.com/balalaika.engl.html &quot;Balalaika&quot;]. ''Krymskaya Pravda''. Balalaika music, video.&lt;/ref&gt; Another appearance of the word is registered in a document from Verkhotursky district of Russia, dated October 1700. It also mentioned in a document signed by Peter the Great dated 1714 regarding wedding celebrations of N.M. Zotov in Saint Petersburg.  In [[Ukrainian language]] the word was first documented in the 18th century as &quot;balabaika&quot;, this form is also present in [[Southern Russian dialects|South Russia]]&lt;nowiki/&gt;n dialects and [[Belarus|Belorussian]] language, as well in [[Siberia|Siberian Russia]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://izbornyk.org.ua/djvu/tymchenko_slovnyk.htm Історичний словник українського язика] Під ред. Є. Тимченка; укл.: Є. Тимченко, Є. Волошин, К. Лазаревська, Г. Петренко. — К.-Х., 1930–32. — Т. 1. — XXIV + 948 с. Зошит 1: А — Глу. — С. 52.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://archive.org/details/revelationssibe01felgoog|title=Revelations of Siberia.|last=Felinska|first=Ewa|last2=Lach-Szyrma|first2=Krystyn|date=1852|publisher=London, Colburn and co.|others=University of Michigan}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It made its way to literature and first appeared in &quot;Elysei&quot;, a 1771 poem by V. Maykov.{{citation needed|date=March 2019}} &quot;Balalaika&quot; also appears in Nikolai Gogol's ''Dead Souls'', written between 1837 and 1842.{{citation needed|date=March 2019}}

== Types ==
[[File:Isfl secunda balalaika.png|thumb|Secunda style]]

[[File:Contrabassbalalaika.jpg|thumb|Contrabass style]]

The most common solo instrument is the prima, which is tuned E&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;–E&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;–A&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; (thus the two lower [[strings (music)|strings]] are [[Musical tuning|tuned]] to the same pitch). Sometimes the balalaika is tuned &quot;guitar style&quot; by folk musicians to G&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;–B&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;–D&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; (mimicking the three highest strings of the [[Russian guitar]]), whereby it is easier to play for Russian guitar players, although classically trained balalaika purists avoid this tuning. It can also be tuned to E&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;–A&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;–D&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;, like its cousin, the [[domra]], to make it easier for those trained on the domra to play the instrument, and still have a balalaika sound.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.get-tuned.com/balalaika.php How to tune a Balalaika]&lt;/ref&gt;  The folk (pre-Andreev) tunings D&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;–F{{music|sharp}}&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;–A&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; and C&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;–E&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;–G&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; were very popular, as this makes it easier to play certain [[riff]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://balalaikafr.free.fr/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=18&amp;Itemid=61&amp;lang=us|title=Balalaika.fr – Origins of balalaika|author=Micha Tcherkassky}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The balalaika has been made the following sizes:&lt;ref&gt;Ekkel, Bibs; ''The Complete Balalaika Book''; Mel Bay Publications; Pacific, Missouri:  1997.  pg. 90–92.  {{ISBN|0-7866-2475-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Name !! Length !! Common tuning
|-
| descant{{efn|name=a}} || {{circa}} {{convert|46|cm|in|0|abbr=on}} || E&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt; E&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt; A&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;
|-
| piccolo{{efn|name=b}} || {{circa}} {{convert|61|cm|in|0|abbr=on}} || B&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; E&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt; A&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;
|-
| prima{{efn|name=c}} || {{convert|66|-|69|cm|in|0|abbr=on}} || E&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; E&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; A&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;
|-
| secunda{{efn|name=c}}{{efn|name=d}} || {{convert|68|-|74|cm|in|0|abbr=on}} || A&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; A&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; D&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;
|-
| alto{{efn|name=c}} || {{convert|81|cm|in|0|abbr=on}} || E&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; E&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; A&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;
|-
| tenor{{efn|name=a}} || {{convert|91|-|97|cm|in|0|abbr=on}} || E&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; A&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; E&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;
|-
| bass{{efn|name=c}} || {{convert|104|cm|in|0|abbr=on}} || E&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; A&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; D&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;
|-
| contrabass{{efn|name=b}}{{efn|name=c}} || {{convert|130|-|165|cm|in|0|abbr=on}} || E&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; A&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; D&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;
|}

{{notelist|refs=
{{efn|name=a|Obsolete}}
{{efn|name=b|Rare}}
{{efn|name=c|Members of the modern balalaika orchestra}}
{{efn|name=d|Secundas are often the same instrument as primas, just tuned to a lower pitch range}}
}}
Factory-made six-string prima balalaikas with three sets of double courses are also common. These have three double courses similar to the stringing of the [[mandolin]] and often use a &quot;guitar&quot; tuning.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mandolinluthier.com/balalaika_page.htm   What is a balalaika?]&lt;/ref&gt;

Four string alto balalaikas are also encountered and are used in the orchestra of the [[Piatnistky Folk Choir]].

The piccolo, prima, d secunda balalaikas were originally strung with gut with the thinnest melody string made of stainless steel. Today, nylon strings are commonly used in place of gut.&lt;ref name= &quot;basic info&quot;&gt;[http://www.balalajka.com/info.html Basic Information]&lt;/ref&gt;

Amateur and/or souvenir-style prima balalaikas usually have a total of 16 frets, while in professional orchestra-like ones that number raises to 24.&lt;ref name= &quot;basic info&quot;/&gt;
=== Technique ===

An important part of balalaika technique is the use of the left thumb to fret notes on the lower string, particularly on the prima, where it is used to form [[chord (music)|chords]]. Traditionally, the side of the [[index finger]] of the right hand is used to sound notes on the prima, while a [[plectrum]] is used on the larger sizes.

Because of the large size of the contrabass's strings, it is not uncommon to see players using plectra made from a leather shoe or boot [[heel (shoe)|heel]]. The bass balalaika and contrabass balalaika rest on the ground, on a wooden or metal pin that is drilled into one of its corners.

== History ==
[[File:Stamp-russia2014-musical-instruments-block.png|thumb|300px|right|Balalaika postal stamps]]

It is possible that the emergence and evolutionary of balalaika was a product of interaction with Asian-Oriental cultures too. In addition to European culture, early Russian states, also called [[Rus' (region)|Rus' or Rusi]], were also influenced by Oriental-Asian cultures.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Huns|last=Kim, Hyun Jin, 1982-|publisher=|isbn=9781317340904|location=Milton Park, Abingdon, Oxon|pages=157|oclc=930082848|date = 19 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Chamberlin|first=William Henry|date=1960|title=Russia between East and West|journal=The Russian Review|volume=19|issue=4|pages=309–315|doi=10.2307/126474|issn=0036-0341|jstor=126474}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some theories say that the instrument descended from the [[domra]], an instrument from the [[East Slavs]]. In the [[Caucasus]], similar instruments such as the Mongolian [[topshur]], used in [[Kalmykia]], and the [[Panduri]] used in [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]] are played. It is also similar to the Kazakh [[dombra]], which has two strings&lt;ref&gt;
Findeizen, Nikolai. ''History of Music in Russia from Antiquity to 1800.'' Ed. Miloš Velimirović
 and Claudia Jensen. Vol. 1. Bloomington, IN: Indiana UP, 2008. P. 172.&lt;/ref&gt; 

=== The pre-Andreyev period ===
Early representations of the balalaika show it with anywhere from two to six strings, which resembles certain Central Asian instruments. Similarly, [[fret]]s on earlier balalaikas were made of animal gut and tied to the neck so that they could be moved around by the player at will (as is the case with the modern [[baglama|saz]], which allows for the playing distinctive to Turkish and Central Asian music).

The first known document mentioning the instrument dates back to 1688. A guard's logbook from the [[Moscow Kremlin]] records that two [[commoners]] were stopped from playing the Balalika whilst drunk.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Balalaika orchestra offers glimpse of instruments, music|url=http://www.dailyprogress.com/entertainment/article_3bd28b46-7c32-5f5d-aa33-fd7d73a5a781.html|accessdate=18 December 2012|newspaper=The Daily Progress|date=28 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Further documents from 1700 and 1714 also mention the instrument. In the early 18th century the term appeared in Ukrainian documents, where it sounded like &quot;Balabaika&quot;. Balalaika appeared in &quot;Elysei&quot;, a 1771 poem by V. Maikov.&lt;ref&gt;Аверин, В. А. ''Балалаечное исполнительство в Сибири: Опыт
монографического исследования.'' Енисейский летописец (2013). pp. 31-33.&lt;/ref&gt; In the 19th century, the balalaika evolved into a triangular instrument with a neck that was substantially shorter than that of its Asian counterparts. It was popular as a village instrument for centuries, particularly with the ''[[skomorokh]]s'', sort of free-lance musical [[jester]]s whose tunes ridiculed the [[Tsar]], the [[Russian Orthodox Church]], and Russian society in general.&lt;ref&gt;Шанский Н. М., Иванов В. В., Шанская Т. В. ''Скоморох // Краткий этимологический
словарь русского языка. Пособие для учителя / Под ред. чл.-кор''. АН СССР С. Г.
Бархударова. — М.: Просвещение, 1971. p. 412&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Balalaïka &quot;Москва 80&quot;.jpg|left|thumb|250x250px|Balalaika model of 1980 made for the [[1980 Summer Olympics]] in [[Moscow]]]]

=== The Andreyev period ===

In the 1880s, [[Vasily Vasilievich Andreyev]], who was then a professional violinist in the music salons of St Petersburg, developed what became the standardized balalaika, with the assistance of violin maker V. Ivanov. The instrument began to be used in his concert performances. A few years later, St. Petersburg craftsman Paserbsky further refined the instruments by adding a fully chromatic set of frets and also a number of balalaikas in orchestral sizes with the tunings now found in modern instruments. One of the reasons why the instruments were not standardised, was because people in the outlying areas built their own instruments, because there was so little communication for them. There were no roads and weather conditions were generally bad. Andreyev patented the design and arranged numerous traditional Russian folk melodies for the orchestra. He also composed a body of concert pieces for the instrument.&lt;ref&gt;Прохоров, А. М., ed. ''Большая Советская Энциклопедия.'' 3rd ed. Vol. 2. Москва:
Советская Энциклопедия, 1970. pp. 16-17.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Balalaika orchestra ==
[[File:Balalaika.jpg|thumb|Souvenir style]]

The end result of Andreyev's labours was the establishment of an orchestral folk tradition in Tsarist Russia, which later grew into a movement within the [[Soviet Union]].&lt;ref&gt;Smith, Susannah L. &quot;Folk Music.&quot; Encyclopedia of Russian History. Ed. James R. Millar.
 Vol. 2. New York: Macmillan Reference USA, 2004. p. 510.&lt;/ref&gt;  The balalaika orchestra in its full form consists of balalaikas, [[domra]]s, [[gusli]], [[bayan (music)|bayan]], [[Vladimir Shepherd's Horns]], [[garmoshka]]s and several types of percussion instruments.

With the establishment of the Soviet system and the entrenchment of a proletarian cultural direction, the culture of the working classes (which included that of village labourers) was actively supported by the Soviet establishment. The concept of the balalaika orchestra was adopted wholeheartedly by the Soviet government as something distinctively proletarian (that is, from the working classes) and was also deemed progressive. Significant amounts of energy and time were devoted to support and foster formal study of the balalaika, from which highly skilled ensemble groups such as the [[Osipov State Russian Folk Orchestra]] emerged. Balalaika virtuosi such as [[Boris Feoktistov]] and [[Pavel Necheporenko]] became stars both inside and outside the Soviet Union. The movement was so powerful that even the renowned [[Alexandrov Ensemble|Red Army Choir]], which initially used a normal symphonic orchestra, changed its instrumentation, replacing violins, [[viola]]s, and [[violoncello]]s with orchestral balalaikas and [[domra]]s.&lt;ref&gt;
Schwarz, Boris. ''Music and Musical Life in Soviet Russia.'' Bloomington: Indiana UP, 1983.
 p. 495.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Петров Смотрины-невесты 1861.jpg|left|thumb|Painting from [[Nikolai Petrovich Petrov]] in 1861. The scene portrays the old Russian tradition of the [[bride-show]] while a balalaika is played.]]

== Solo instrument ==

Often musicians perform solo on the balalaika. In particular, [[Alexey Arkhipovsky]] is well known for his solo performances.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.arkhipovskiy.com/|title=Алексей Архиповский|website=Алексей Архиповский|language=ru-RU|access-date=2018-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; In particular, he was invited to play at the opening ceremony of the second semi final of the [[Eurovision Song Contest 2009]] in Moscow because the organizers wanted to give a &quot;more Russian appearance&quot; to the contest.&lt;ref name=&quot;newsmusic&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newsmusic.ru/news_4_18413.htm |script-title=ru:Алексей Архиповский: Выступлением на &quot;Евровидении&quot; я недоволен! |publisher=NEWSmusic.Ru |language=Russian |accessdate=5 May 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110102110204/http://newsmusic.ru/news_4_18413.htm |archivedate=2 January 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== In popular culture ==
[[File:Imperial Russian Balilika Court Orchestra.jpg|thumb|right|1911 advertisement for the Imperial Russian Balalaika Orchestra and [[Victor Records]]]]

Through the 20th century, interest in Russian folk instruments grew outside of Russia, likely as a result of western tours by Andreyev and other balalaika virtuosi early in the century. Significant balalaika associations are found in Washington, D.C.,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://absorchestra.org/|title=The American Balalaika Symphony: Experience It!|author=|date=|work=absorchestra.org|accessdate=23 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Los Angeles,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.russianstrings.com/|title=Los Angeles Balalaika Orchestra|author=|date=|work=russianstrings.com|accessdate=23 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; New York,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.barynya.com/orchestra.htm|title=New York Russian Balalaika Orchestra|author=|date=|work=barynya.com|accessdate=23 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Atlanta&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.atlantabalalaika.com/|title=Atlanta Balalaika Society|author=|date=|work=atlantabalalaika.com|accessdate=23 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Seattle.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.balalaika.org/|title=Washington Balalaika Society – Home|author=|date=|work=balalaika.org|accessdate=23 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Ian Anderson (musician)|Ian Anderson]] plays balalaika on two songs from the 1969 [[Jethro Tull (band)|Jethro Tull]] album ''[[Stand Up (Jethro Tull album)|Stand Up]]'': &quot;Jeffrey Goes to Leicester Square&quot; and &quot;Fat Man&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jethrotull.com/?portfolio=stand-up|title=Stand Up – Jethro Tull|author=|date=|work=jethrotull.com|accessdate=23 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Wes Anderson]]'s 2014 film ''[[The Grand Budapest Hotel]]'' (winner of the 87th [[Academy Award for Best Original Score]])&lt;ref name=&quot;oscars2015&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.oscars.org/oscars/ceremonies/2015 | title=THE 87TH ACADEMY AWARDS 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt; employs many balalaikas in both [[Alexandre Desplat]]'s original score and several sound-track recordings by the [[Osipov State Russian Folk Orchestra]].{{citation needed|date=September 2017}}
* Oleg Bernov of the Russian-American rock band the [[Red Elvises]] played a red electrified contrabass balalaika during the band's North American tours.{{citation needed|date=September 2017}} Dejah Sandoval currently tours with the Red Elvises and plays the bass balalaika.{{citation needed|date=September 2017}}
* [[Kate Bush]], featured the balalaika (played by her brother [[Paddy Bush]]) in two of her Top-40 singles, &quot;[[Babooshka (song)|Babooshka]]&quot; and &quot;[[Running Up That Hill]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.katebushencyclopedia.com/running-up-that-hill  ''Running Up That Hill'']&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Katzenjammer (band)|Katzenjammer]], the Norwegian all-girl pop band, uses two contrabass balalaikas, both of which have cat faces painted on the front. They are named Børge and Akerø.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.facebook.com/AkeroKatzenjammersCatFacedContraBassBalalaika|title=Security Check Required|author=|date=|work=facebook.com|accessdate=23 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite av media|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7Dq5F2gm2Xw|title=Akero – Its All About the Bass – Katzenjammer|author=|date=29 September 2015|publisher=|accessdate=23 February 2016|via=YouTube}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[David Lean]]'s 1965 film ''[[Doctor Zhivago (1965 film)|Doctor Zhivago]]'' features balalaika prominently in the score and the plot.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/filmmusic00russ|url-access=registration|quote=Zhivago balalaika music.|title=Film Music|last=Russell|first=Mark|last2=Young|first2=James Edward|date=2000|publisher=Focal Press|isbn=9780240804415|location=|pages=[https://archive.org/details/filmmusic00russ/page/48 48]–51|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Brassard|first=Jeffrey|date=2017|title=Slavophilism, nostalgia and the curse of Western ideas: Reflections on Russia's past in Alexander Proshkin's 2006 adaptation of Doctor Zhivago|url=http://historicalfictionsjournal.org/pdf/JHF%202017-111.pdf|journal=Journal of Historical Fictions|volume=1|pages=111–129|via=Google Scholar}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=z8eQAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA77&amp;dq=balalaika+zhivago+plot#v=onepage&amp;q=zhivago&amp;f=false|title=Narrative Comprehension, Causality, and Coherence: Essays in Honor of Tom Trabasso|last=Goldman|first=Susan R.|last2=Graesser|first2=Arthur C.|last3=Broek|first3=Paul van den|date=August 1999|publisher=Routledge|isbn=9781135666071|location=|pages=89|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* VulgarGrad, an Australian band fronted by actor [[Jacek Koman]], plays songs of the Russian criminal underground, and uses a contrabass balalaika.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://vulgargrad.com/biography/|title=Band|author=|date=|work=Vulgargrad|accessdate=23 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[RebbeSoul]] plays balalaika on numerous songs on the RebbeSoul albums ''Fringe Of Blue'', ''RebbeSoul-O'', ''Change The World With A Sound'', and ''From Another World''.  He also plays balalaika on the Common Tongue album, ''Step Into My Word'' and on the Shlomit &amp; RebbeSoul album, ''The Seal Of Solomon''.
*The instrument is featured in the episode &quot;The Secret war&quot; of the 2019 Netflix series &quot;Love, Death and Robots&quot;
*The instrument is used alongside a piano and an accordian in the piece &quot;A Journey&quot; from the soundtrack of the 2013 animation &quot;The Wind Rises&quot;

== See also ==

{{Portal|Music|Russia}}

{{See also|Lute#History and evolution of the lute}}
* [[Domra]]
* [[Gibson Flying V]]
* [[Timeline of Russian innovation]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

* Блок В. '''Оркестр русских народных инструментов'''. Москва, 1986.
* Имханицкий М. '''В. В. Андреев – Материалы и документы'''. Москва, 1986.
* Имханицкий М. '''У истоков русской народной оркестровой культуры'''. Москва, 1987.
* Имханицкий М. '''История исполнительства на русских народных инструментах'''. Москва, 2002.
* Пересада А. '''Балалайка'''. Москва, 1990.
* Попонов В. '''Оркестр хора имени Пятницкого'''. Москва, 1979.
* Попонов В. '''Русская народная инструментальная музыка'''. Москва, 1984.
* Вертков К. '''Русские народные музыкальные инструменты'''. Музыка, Ленинград, 1975.

== External links ==

{{Commons category|Balalaika}}
{{Wikisource1911Enc|Balalaïka}}

* (en) [http://www.skaz1.com/balalaika.engl.html &quot;Balalaika&quot;]—article by Dmitry Belinskiy from the newspaper ''Krymskaya Pravda''. Balalaika music, video
* [http://goshabagpiper.narod.ru/history.htm Russian site about balalaika. History of balalaika], by Georgy Nefyodov
* [http://www.andreaslehmann.com/files/andreaslehmann/downloads/chord-reference-for-balalaika.pdf Chord reference for Prima-Balalaika]
* (rus) [http://balalaika.org.ru/ balalaika.org.ru]: music sheets, video, forum, etc.
* {{YouTube|F6pPP2kfHzU|An example of balalaika playing}}
* (de) [http://www.russische-balalaika.de/ russische-balalaika.de – informative Website]
*[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6MTZd6lsd4k An example of a reconstructed pre-Andreyev balalaika with two strings] on YouTube
*[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0Y_-HNU5qag An example of a Bessarabian tune on balalaika, Dieter and Ally Hauptmann] on YouTube. 

{{Russian musical instruments}}
{{Russian souvenirs|state=&quot;expanded&quot;}}
{{Guitars|Strings}}
{{authority control}}

[[Category:Necked bowl lutes]]
[[Category:Russian inventions]]
[[Category:Russian musical instruments]]
[[Category:String instruments]]</text>
      <sha1>70nzessyiyyrhbtnqqb9vy0f800i7hn</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
