  <page>
    <title>Bambara language</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4565</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940386710</id>
      <parentid>938284586</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-12T07:01:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Donaldsoncd</username>
        <id>37094321</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Fixed the N'ko spelling of Bamanankan and Bamanan</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{More citations needed|date=March 2019}}
{{Infobox language
| name = Bambara
| nativename = {{lang|bm|bamanankan}}, {{lang|bm-nkoo|ߓߡߊߣߊ߲ߞߊ߲}}
| states = [[Mali]]
| region = central southern Mali
| ethnicity = [[Bambara people|Bambara]]
| speakers = 4.1 million
| date = 2012
| ref = e18
| speakers2 = 10 million [[L2 speakers]]&lt;br&gt;Spoken to varying degrees by 80% of the population of Mali
| familycolor = Niger-Congo
| fam1 = [[Niger–Congo languages|Niger–Congo]]?
| fam2 = [[Mande languages|Mande]]
| fam3 = Western Mande
| fam4 = ...
| fam5 = [[Manding languages|Manding]]
| fam6 = East Manding
| fam7 = Bambara–Dyula
| iso1 = bm
| iso2 = bam
| iso3 = bam
| glotto = bamb1269
| glottorefname = Bambara
| script = [[Latin script|Latin]], [[N'Ko script|N'Ko]]
| notice = IPA
}}
{{SpecialChars}}

'''Bambara''', also known as '''Bamana''' ([[N'Ko script|N’ko]]: ߓߡߊߣߊ߲ ) or '''Bamanankan''' ([[N'Ko script|N’ko]]: ߓߡߊߣߊ߲ߣߞߊ߲) is a [[lingua franca]] and [[national language]] of [[Mali]] spoken by perhaps 15 million people, natively by 5 million [[Bambara people]] and about 10 million [[Second language|second-language]] users. It is estimated that about 80 percent of the population of Mali speak Bambara as a first or second language. It has a [[subject–object–verb]] clause structure and two lexical [[tone (tonal language)|tone]]s. The native name bamanankan means &quot;the language ({{Lang|bm|kan}}) of heathens ({{Lang|bm|bámànán}}), people who refuse Islam&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Donaldson|first=Coleman|date=2019-03-01|title=Linguistic and Civic Refinement in the N’ko Movement of Manding-Speaking West Africa|url=https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/10.1086/702554|journal=Signs and Society|volume=7|issue=2|page=161|doi=10.1086/702554|issn=2326-4489|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; as opposed to speakers of [[Dyula language|Dyula]], who are Muslim.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/905517929|title=Manding-English Dictionary : (Maninka, Bamana)|last=Vydrin|first=Valentin|publisher=|year=1999|isbn=9780993996931|location=Lac-Beauport|pages=69|oclc=905517929|author-link=Valentin Vydrin}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Classification==
Bambara is a variety of a group of closely related languages called [[Manding languages|Manding]], whose native speakers trace their cultural history to the medieval [[Mali Empire]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://mandelang.kunstkamera.ru/files/mandelang/mandekan.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2012-04-20 |url-status = live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120408104148/http://mandelang.kunstkamera.ru/files/mandelang/mandekan.pdf |archivedate=2012-04-08 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Varieties of Manding are generally considered (among native speakers) to be mutually intelligible &amp;ndash; dependent on exposure or familiarity with dialects between speakers &amp;ndash; and spoken by 30 to 40 million people in the countries [[Burkina Faso]], [[Senegal]], [[Guinea-Bissau]], [[Guinea]], [[Liberia]], [[Ivory Coast]] and [[the Gambia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sil.org/SILESR/2000/2000-003/Manding/Manding.htm|title=Mandé Language Family: Manding|website=www.sil.org|accessdate=1 January 2018|url-status = live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130121102940/http://www.sil.org/SILESR/2000/2000-003/Manding/Manding.htm|archivedate=21 January 2013|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Manding is part of the larger [[Mande languages|Mandé]] family of languages.

==Alphabet and literature==
It uses seven vowels a, e, ɛ, i, o, ɔ and u, each of which can be nasalized, pharyngealized and murmured, giving a total number of 21 vowels (the letters approximate their [[help:IPA|IPA]] equivalents). {{citation needed|date=June 2018}}
Writing with the Latin alphabet began during the [[French West Africa|French]] occupation, and the first orthography was introduced in 1967. Literacy is limited, especially in rural areas. Although written literature is only slowly evolving (due to the predominance of French as the &quot;language of the educated&quot;), there exists a wealth of [[oral history|oral literature]], which is often tales of kings and heroes. This oral literature is mainly tradited by the [[griot]]s (''Jeliw'' in Bambara) who are a mixture of [[storytelling|storyteller]]s, praise singers, and human history books who have studied the trade of singing and reciting for many years. Many of their songs are very old and are said to date back to the old empire of Mali.

==Geographical distribution==
Bambara is spoken throughout Mali as a lingua franca. The language is most widely spoken in the areas east, south, and north of Bamako, where native speakers and/or those that identify as members of the Bambara ethnic group are most densely populated. These regions are also usually considered to be the historical geographical origin of Bambara people, particularly [[Ségou]], after diverging from other Manding groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2000&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sil.org/SILESR/2000/2000-003/Manding/Bamana.htm|title=Mandé Language Family: Maps of Manding-East, North-Eastern Manding, Bamana, Urban  koine|website=www.sil.org|accessdate=1 January 2018|url-status = live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130122172907/http://www.sil.org/SILESR/2000/2000-003/Manding/Bamana.htm|archivedate=22 January 2013|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Dialects==
The main dialect is Standard Bamara, which has significant influence from Maninkakan.{{clarify|date=August 2015}} Bambara has many local dialects: Kaarta, Tambacounda (west); Beledugu, Bananba, Mesekele (north); Jitumu, Jamaladugu, Segu (center); Cakadugu, Keleyadugu, Jalakadougu, Kurulamini, Banimɔncɛ, Cɛmala, Cɛndugu, Baninkɔ, Shɛndugu, Ganadugu (south); Kala, Kuruma, Saro, dialects to the northeast of Mopti (especially Bɔrɛ); Zegedugu, Bɛndugu, Bakɔkan, Jɔnka (southeast).,&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2000&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Vydrine 1999&lt;/ref&gt;

==Writing==
Since 1967, Bambara has mostly been written in the [[Latin script]], using [[African reference alphabet|some additional phonetic characters]]. The vowels are ''a, e, [[ɛ]]'' (formerly ''[[è]]''&lt;span style=&quot;margin-left:3px&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;, ''i, o, [[ɔ]]'' (formerly ''[[ò]]''&lt;span style=&quot;margin-left:3px&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;, ''u''&lt;span style=&quot;margin-left:2px&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; accents can be used to indicate tonality. The former digraph ''ny'' is now written ''[[ɲ]]'' when it designates a palatal nasal glide; the ''ny'' spelling is kept for the combination of a nasal vowel with a subsequent oral palatal glide. Following the 1966 Bamako spelling conventions, a nasal velar glide &quot;[[ŋ]]&quot; is written as &quot;[[ŋ]]&quot;, although in early publications it was often transcribed as ''ng'' or ''nk''.

The [[N'Ko script|N'Ko]] ({{lang-nqo|ߒߞߏ}}) alphabet is a script devised by [[Solomana Kante]] in 1949 as a writing system for the Manding languages of West Africa; N’Ko means 'I say' in all Manding languages. Kante created N’Ko in response to what he felt were beliefs that Africans were a &quot;cultureless people&quot; since prior to this time there had been no indigenous African writing system for his language. N'ko came first into use in Kankan, Guinea as a Maninka alphabet and disseminated from there into other Manding-speaking parts of West Africa. N'ko and the [[Arabic script]] are still in use for Bambara, although the Latin script is much more common.
&lt;!--
There are some or just one? [[User:Guaka|G-u-a-k-@]] hasn't found any yet, after nearly 3 months in Bamako.. :(  newspapers in Bambara. --&gt;

== Phonology ==

=== Consonants ===
{|class=wikitable style=text-align:center
!
!colspan=2|[[Labial consonant|Labial]]
!colspan=2|[[Alveolar consonant|Alveolar]]
!colspan=2|[[Palatal consonant|Palatal]]
!colspan=2|[[Velar consonant|Velar]]
![[Glottal consonant|Glottal]]
|-
![[Nasal consonant|Nasal]]
|colspan=2|m
|colspan=2|n
|colspan=2|ɲ
|colspan=2|ŋ
|
|-
![[Stop consonant|Plosive]]
|style=border-right:0|p||style=border-left:0|b
|style=border-right:0|t||style=border-left:0|d
|style=border-right:0|t͡ʃ‹c›||style=border-left:0|d͡ʒ‹j›
|style=border-right:0|k||style=border-left:0|ɡ
|
|-
![[Fricative consonant|Fricative]]
|colspan=2|f                 
|style=border-right:0|s||style=border-left:0|z
|colspan=2|(ʃ)
|colspan=2|(ɣ)‹kh›
|h
|-
![[Approximant consonant|Approximant]]
|colspan=2|w
|colspan=2|l
|colspan=2|j‹y›
|colspan=2|
|
|-
![[Trill consonant|Trill]]
|colspan=2|
|colspan=2|r
|colspan=2|
|colspan=2|
|
|}

=== Vowels ===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!
![[Front vowel|Front]]
![[Back vowel|Back]]
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
![[Close vowel|Close]]
|i iː ĩ
|u uː ũ
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
![[Close-mid vowel|Close-mid]]
|e eː ẽ
|o oː õ
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
![[Open-mid vowel|Open-mid]]
|ɛ ɛː ɛ̃
|ɔ ɔː ɔ̃
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
![[Open vowel|Open]]
|a aː ã
|
|}

Each consonant represents a single sound. Although, there are some exceptions:
* &quot;W&quot; is pronounced as in English (e.g. wait), but placed at the end of a word, &quot;w&quot; is the plural mark and is pronounced as [u]
* &quot;S&quot; is pronounced most often as in the English word &quot;see&quot;, but sometimes it can be pronounced as &quot;sh&quot; (in phonetic alphabet [ʃ]) as in the word &quot;shoe&quot;, or again as [z]
* &quot;G&quot; is pronounced most often as in the English word &quot;go&quot;, but within a word it can be pronounced as in the Spanish word &quot;abogado&quot; (in phonetic alphabet [ɣ]), and sometimes at the beginning [gw]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Cours pratique de bambara|last=Bailleul|first=Charles|publisher=|year=|isbn=|location=|pages=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Grammar==
Like Turkish and Japanese, it is an agglutinative language, meaning that morphemes are glued together to form a word.

The basic sentence structure is Subject Object Verb.  Take the phrase, &quot;n t'a don&quot; (I don't know [it]). &quot;n&quot; is the subject (me), &quot;a&quot; is the object (it), and &quot;[ka] don&quot; is the verb ([to] know). The &quot;t'&quot; is from the present tense marker &quot;té.&quot; &quot;té&quot; is the negative present tense marker and &quot;bé&quot; is the affirmative present tense marker. Therefore, &quot;n b'a don&quot; would mean &quot;I know it&quot;.

Bambara is an [[subject–object–verb|SOV]] language and has two (mid/standard and high) [[tone (tonal language)|tone]]s; e.g. ''sa'' 'die' vs. ''sá'' 'snake.' The typical argument structure of the language consists of a subject, followed by an aspectival auxiliary, followed by the direct object, and finally a transitive verb.  Naturally, if the verb is intransitive, the direct object is absent.

Bambara does not inflect for gender. Gender for a noun can be specified by adding an adjective, ''-cɛ'' or ''-kɛ'' for male and ''-muso'' for female. The plural is formed by attaching a vocalic suffix ''-u'', most often with a low tone (in the orthography, ''-w'') to nouns or adjectives.

Bambara uses postpositions in much the same manner as languages like English and French use prepositions. These postpositions are found after the verb and are used to express direction, location, and in some cases, possession.

===Loan words===
In urban areas, many Bamanankan conjunctions have been replaced in everyday use by French borrowings that often mark code-switches. The [[Bamako]] dialect makes use of sentences like: ''N taara Kita mais il n'y avait personne là-bas.'' : ''I went to Kita [Bamanankan ] but there was no one there [French].'' The sentence in Bamanankan  alone would be ''Ń taara Kita nka mɔkɔ si tun tɛ yen.'' The French proposition &quot;est-ce que&quot; is also used in Bamanankan ; however, it is pronounced more slowly and as three syllables, {{IPA|[ɛsəkə]}}.

Bamanankan  uses many French loan words. For example, some people might say:
''I ka kulosi ye jauni ye'': &quot;Your skirt is yellow&quot; (using a derivation of the French word for yellow, jaune.)

However, one could also say:
''I ka kulosi ye nɛrɛmukuman ye'', also meaning &quot;your skirt is yellow.&quot; The original Bamanankan  word for yellow comes from &quot;''nɛrɛmuku'',&quot; being flour (''muku'') made from [[Parkia biglobosa|néré]] (locust bean), a seed from a long seed pod. Nɛrɛmuku is often used in sauces in Southern Mali.

Most French loan words are suffixed with the sound 'i'; this is particularly common when using French words which have a meaning not traditionally found in Mali. For example, the Bamanankan  word for [[snow]] is ''niegei'', based on the French word for snow ''neige''. As there has never been snow in Mali, there was no unique word in Bamanankan  to describe it.

===Examples===
:''N bɛ bamanankan mɛn dɔɔni-dɔɔni''
:I understand/hear a little bit of Bambara (lit: I ''aux positive'' Bambara hear small-small)

:''I tɛna dumuni ke wa?''
:Aren't you going to eat? (lit: you ''aux negative future'' eating do ''question particle'')

:''Du Mara be ameriki hali bi wa?''
:Is Dou Mara still living in the United States? (lit: Dou Mara still America in live ''question particle'')

==Music==
Malian artists such as [[Oumou Sangaré]], [[Sidiki Diabaté]], [[Rokia Traoré]], [[Ali Farka Touré]], [[Salif Keita]], [[Habib Koité]], and the married duo [[Amadou &amp; Mariam]] often sing in Bambara.  Aïda of the band [[Métisse (band)|Métisse]] often sings in [[Dyula language|Dioula]], as does [[Mory Kante]], born in Guinea to a Malian mother; his most famous song to date is &quot;Yeke Yeke&quot; ([[Alpha Blondy]]).  Lyrics in Bambara occur on [[Stevie Wonder]]'s soundtrack ''[[Journey through the Secret Life of Plants]]''.
[[Tiken Jah Fakoly]] (reggae) often sings in Dioula and French.

Additionally, in 2010, [[Spain|Spanish]] rock group [[Dover (band)|Dover]] released its 7th studio album [[I Ka Kené]], with the majority of lyrics in the language. American rapper [[Nas]] also released a track titled &quot;Sabari&quot; in 2010, which featured [[Damian Marley]]. ''Sabari'' is a Bambara word that means patience.

==Legal status==
Bambara is one of several languages designated by Mali as a [[national language]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Skattum |first=Ingse |date=2010 |title=L'introduction des langues nationales dans le système éducatif au Mali: objectifs et conséquences |trans-title=The Introduction of National Languages to the Malian Educational System: Problems and Consequences |url=http://booksandjournals.brillonline.com/docserver/19552629/3/1/19552629_003_01_S013_text.pdf?expires=1487354096&amp;id=id&amp;accname=guest&amp;checksum=2A729881414DED33D000C3984B49D9E3 |language=French |journal=Journal of Language Contact |volume=3 |issue=1 |pages=248 |doi=10.1163/19552629-90000013 |access-date=February 17, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
*Bailleul Ch. ''Dictionnaire Bambara-Français.'' 3e édition corrigée. Bamako : Donniya, 2007, 476 p.
*Bird, Charles, Hutchison, John &amp; Kanté, Mamadou (1976) ''An Ka Bamanankan Kalan: Beginning Bambara''. Bloomington: Indiana Univ. Linguistics Club.
*Bird, Charles &amp; Kanté, Mamadou (1977) ''Bambara-English, English-Bambara student lexicon''. Bloomington: Indiana Univ. Linguistics Club.
*Dumestre Gérard. ''Grammaire fondamentale du bambara.'' Paris : Karthala, 2003.
*Dumestre, Gérard. ''Dictionnaire bambara-français suivi d’un index abrégé français-bambara.'' Paris : Karthala, 2011. 1189 p.
*Kastenholz, Raimund (1998) ''Grundkurs Bambara (Manding) mit Texten'' (second revised edition) (Afrikawissenschaftliche Lehrbücher Vol. 1). Köln: Rüdiger Köppe.
*Konaré, Demba (1998) ''Je parle bien bamanan''. Bamako: Jamana.
*Morales, José (2010) ''J'apprends le bambara. 61 conversations'', (book + CD-ROM).  Paris: Editions Karthala. {{ISBN|2-8111-0433-X}}
*Touré, Mohamed &amp; Leucht, Melanie (1996) ''Bambara Lesebuch: Originaltexte mit deutscher und französischer Übersetzung = Chrestomathie Bambara: textes originaux Bambara avec traductions allemandes et françaises'' (with illustrations by Melanie Leucht) (Afrikawissenschaftliche Lehrbücher Vol. 11) . Köln: Rüdiger Köppe.
*[[Valentin Vydrin|Vydrine, Valentin]]. ''Manding-English Dictionary (Maninka, Bamana)''. Vol. 1. St. Petersburg: Dimitry Bulanin Publishing House, 1999, 315 p.

==External links==
{{InterWiki|code=bm}}
{{Wiktionarycat}}
{{Wikibooks|Bambara}}
{{Wikivoyage|Bambara phrasebook}}

===Descriptions===
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20160115094600/http://mali.pwnet.org/history/history_language.htm Mali – History – Language]

===Dictionaries===
*[http://cormand.huma-num.fr/bamadaba.html] online and downloadable Bambara-French Dictionary (about 11,500 entries by the end of 2014), with a French-Bambara index, linked with the Corpus Bambara de Référence
*An ka taa's [http://dictionary.ankataa.com Mobile-friendly Bambara-English dictionary] that includes French and Jula.
*[[wikt:fr:Catégorie:bambara|Bambara entries (&gt;2300) in the French Wiktionary]]
*[http://www.bambara.org/en Bambara-French-English dictionary] online and downloadable lexicons for language learners
*[http://www.bisharat.net/Demos/jiriwso.htm Bambara tree names (scientific name -&gt; common name)]

===Learning materials===
*[http://www.iub.edu/~celtie/bambara.html Online Bambara Course from the Indiana University]
*{{cite web|url=http://www.peacecorp.gov/wws/multimedia/language/transcripts/ML_Bambara_Language_Lessons.pdf |title=AN INTRODUCTION TO BAMBARA |url-status = bot: unknown|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110721061045/http://www.peacecorp.gov/wws/multimedia/language/transcripts/ML_Bambara_Language_Lessons.pdf |archivedate=2011-07-21 }}&amp;nbsp;{{small|(168&amp;nbsp;KB)}} on peacecorps.gov

===Other===
*[http://cormand.huma-num.fr/] Corpus Bambara de Référence, an electronic corpus of Bambara texts (about 2,000,000 words end 2014)
*[http://cormand.huma-num.fr/biblio/index.jsp Bambara Electronic Library, AMALAN - LLACAN]
*[http://www.ankataa.com An ka taa]: a website with a dictionary, resources and media for learning Bambara and Manding more generally.
*[http://fr.wikibooks.org/wiki/Bambara Bambara at French Wikibooks] contains more material
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20140703141254/http://www.vjf.cnrs.fr/clt/php/va/Page_revue.php?ValCodeRev=MDK Mandenkan Journal]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20130516204859/http://www.panafril10n.org/wikidoc/pmwiki.php/PanAfrLoc/Manding PanAfriL10n page on Manding] (includes information on Bambara)
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20090916112516/http://www.maneno.org/bam/ Maneno in Bambara] (a blogging platform with a full Bambara interface)
&lt;!-- {{Wikibookspar||Bambara}} ugly, since it ruins layout--&gt;

{{navboxes|
|list=
{{Languages of Burkina Faso}}
{{Languages of Ghana}}
{{Languages of Guinea}}
{{Languages of Ivory Coast}}
{{Languages of Mali}}
{{Languages of Mauritania}}
{{Mande languages}}
}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bambara Language}}
[[Category:Bambara language| ]]
[[Category:Languages of Burkina Faso]]
[[Category:Languages of Ghana]]
[[Category:Languages of Guinea]]
[[Category:Languages of Ivory Coast]]
[[Category:Languages of Mali]]
[[Category:Languages of Senegal]]
[[Category:Manding languages]]
[[Category:Subject–object–verb languages]]</text>
      <sha1>93qpno6d6byr1evysu1nr3sh4q2o59i</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
