  <page>
    <title>Backbone cabal</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4505</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940724147</id>
      <parentid>940684302</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-14T05:43:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Dating maintenance tags: {{Reference needed}}</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Group of administrators on Usenet in the late 80s to early 90s}}
The '''backbone cabal''' was an informal organization of large-site [[Sysop|administrators]] of the worldwide distributed [[newsgroup]]-based discussion system [[Usenet]]. It existed from about 1983 at least into the 2000s.{{reference needed|date=February 2020}}

The [[cabal]] was created in an effort to facilitate reliable propagation of new Usenet posts. While in the 1970s and 1980s many news servers only operated during night time to save on the cost of long distance communication, servers of the backbone cabal were available 24 hours a day. The administrators of these servers gained sufficient influence in the otherwise anarchic Usenet community to be able to push through controversial changes, for instance the [[Great Renaming]] of [[Usenet]] newsgroups during 1987.

== History ==
As Usenet has few technologically or legally enforced hierarchies, just about the only ones that formed were [[social hierarchy|social]]. People acquired power through persuasion (both publicly and privately), public debate, force of will (often via aggressive [[flaming (Internet)|flames]]), garnering authority and respect by spending much time and effort contributing to the community (by being a maintainer of a [[FAQ]], for example; see also [[James Parry|Kibo]], etc.).

[[Mary Ann Horton]] recruited membership in&lt;ref&gt;[https://groups.google.com/d/msg/net.news/ofK8vw8_0iw/ALocRFpIfdcJ/ Usenet posting: &quot;backbone sites needed&quot;], by Mark (now Mary Ann) Horton, 15 February 1983&lt;/ref&gt; and designed the original physical topology of the Usenet Backbone in 1983.&lt;ref&gt;[https://groups.google.com/d/msg/net.news/j5VzSthSX_g/97VUfHIpYm0J/ Usenet posting: &quot;proposed USENET backbone&quot;], by Mark (now Mary Ann) Horton, 21 March 1983&lt;/ref&gt; [[Gene Spafford|Gene &quot;Spaf&quot; Spafford]] then created an email list of the backbone administrators, plus a few influential posters. This list became known as the Backbone Cabal and served as a &quot;political (i.e. decision making) backbone&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[https://shikan.org/bjones/Usenet.Hist/Nethist/0060.html Usenet History email: &quot;Usenet backbone&quot;], by Gene Spafford, 17 October 1990&lt;/ref&gt; Other prominent members of the cabal were [[Brian Reid (computer scientist)|Brian Reid]], Richard Sexton, [[Chuq von Rospach]] and [[Rick Adams (Internet pioneer)|Rick Adams]].

== In Internet culture ==
During most of its existence, the cabal (sometimes capitalized) steadfastly denied its own existence; those involved would often respond &quot;[[There is no Cabal]]&quot; (sometimes abbreviated as &quot;TINC&quot;), whenever the existence or activities of the group were speculated on in public. It is sometimes used humorously to dispel cabal-like organizational conspiracy theories, or as an ironic statement, indicating one who knows the existence of &quot;the cabal&quot; will invariably deny there is one.

This belief became a model for various conspiracy theories about various Cabals with dark nefarious objectives beginning with taking over Usenet or the Internet. [[Website spoofing|Spoofs]] include the &quot;Eric Conspiracy&quot; of moustachioed hackers named &quot;Eric&quot;; ex-members of the [[P.H.I.R.M.]]; and the [[Lumber Cartel]] putatively funding anti-[[spamming|spam]] efforts to support the paper industry.

The result of this policy was an aura of mystery, even a decade after the cabal mailing list disbanded in late 1988 following an internal fight.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.techweb.com/encyclopedia/defineterm.jhtml?term=backbone+cabal |title=backbone cabal |publisher=TechWeb|accessdate=2007-09-07 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070927000916/http://www.techweb.com/encyclopedia/defineterm.jhtml?term=backbone+cabal |archivedate=2007-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
*[[Image:PD-icon.svg|15px|link=|alt=]]&amp;nbsp;''This article incorporates text from [http://www.catb.org/~esr/jargon/html/B/backbone-cabal.html the corresponding entry in the Jargon File], which is in the [[public domain]] according to [http://www.catb.org/~esr/jargon/html/online-preface.html its Introduction].''
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
# Henry Edward Hardy, 1993. ''[https://web.archive.org/web/20111101160821/http://internet.eserver.org/Hardy-Usenet-System.txt The Usenet System]'', ITCA Teleconferencing Yearbook 1993, ITCA Research Committee, International Teleconferencing Association, Washington, DC. pp 140–151, esp. subheading ''&quot;The Great Renaming&quot; and &quot;The Breaking of the Backbone Cartel&quot;''.

==External links==
* [http://www.catb.org/~esr/jargon/html/B/backbone-cabal.html Jargon File entry]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20130524051637/http://www.faqs.org/faqs/usenet/cabal-conspiracy-FAQ/ Cabal Conspiracy FAQ] (archived May 2013)
* [http://www.catb.org/esr/jargon/html/L/Lumber-Cartel.html Lumber Cartel]
* [http://catb.org/~esr/jargon/html/T/TINC.html Entry for &quot;TINC&quot;] at the [[Jargon File]]
* [http://www.faqs.org/faqs/usenet/cabal-conspiracy-FAQ/ alt.conspiracy.usenet-cabal FAQ on the Cabal and TINC]
* [http://catb.org/~esr/ecsl/ The Eric Conspiracy]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Backbone Cabal}}
[[Category:Usenet]]
[[Category:Internet memes]]
[[Category:1980s in Internet culture]]</text>
      <sha1>o3rilrhwzf5s2hakpckolw4boiwqgw1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
