  <page>
    <title>Boudica</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4517</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942252796</id>
      <parentid>942252412</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-23T15:43:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Materialscientist</username>
        <id>7852030</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/92.40.174.79|92.40.174.79]] identified as test/vandalism using [[WP:STiki|STiki]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Queen of the British Iceni tribe}}
{{redirect|Boudicca|the cruise ship|MV Boudicca}}
{{redirect|Boadicea}}
{{for|the 2003 film also known as &quot;Warrior Queen&quot;|Boudica (film)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{Infobox person
|image = Boadicea Haranguing the Britons (called Boudicca, or Boadicea) by John Opie.jpg
|image_size =
|caption = Queen Boudica in [[John Opie]]'s painting ''Boadicea Haranguing the Britons''
|birth_date =
|birth_place = [[Roman Britain|Britannia]]
|death_date = {{Circa|60}} or 61 AD
|other_names = Boudicea, Boadicea, {{lang|cy|Buddug}}
|occupation = Queen of the [[Iceni]]
|spouse = [[Prasutagus]]
}}

'''Boudica''' or '''Boudicca''' ({{IPAc-en|UK|ˈ|b|uː|d|ɪ|k|ə|,_|b|oʊ|ˈ|d|ɪ|k|ə}}, {{IPAc-en|US|b|uː|ˈ|d|ɪ|k|ə}}), also known as '''Boadicea''' ({{IPAc-en|ˌ|b|oʊ|(|ə|)|d|ᵻ|ˈ|s|iː|ə}}, &lt;small&gt;also&lt;/small&gt; {{IPAc-en|US|ˌ|b|oʊ|æ|d|-}}) or '''Boudicea''', and in [[Welsh language|Welsh]] as '''{{lang|cy|[[Buddug]]|italics=no}}''' ({{IPA-cy|ˈbɨðɨɡ|IPA}}),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=John Davies|title=A History of Wales|publisher=Penguin|year=1993 |location=London|page=28|isbn=0-14-014581-8 |author-link=John Davies (historian)}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Warrior Queens|last=Fraser|first=Antonia|publisher=Penguin books Canada|year=1990|isbn=0140085173|location=Ontario|pages=3.4}}&lt;/ref&gt; was a queen of the [[Celtic Britons|British Celtic]] [[Iceni]] tribe who led an uprising against the [[Roman Britain|occupying forces]] of the [[Roman Empire]] in AD 60 or 61. She died shortly after its failure and was said to have poisoned herself. She is considered a British folk hero.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.history.com/news/ask-history/who-was-boudica|title=Who was Boudica?|last=Pruitt|first=Sarah|date=31 May 2016|work=History.com|access-date=2018-01-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Boudica's husband [[Prasutagus]], with whom she had two children whose names are unknown, ruled as a nominally independent ally of Rome, and left his kingdom jointly to his daughters and to the [[Roman emperor]] in his will. However, when he died, his will was ignored, and the kingdom was annexed and his property taken. According to [[Tacitus]], Boudica was flogged and her daughters [[wartime sexual violence|raped]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;iam primum uxor eius Boudicca verberibus adfecta et filiae stupro violatae sunt&quot; Tacitus, Annales 14.31&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cassius Dio]] explains Boudica's response by saying that previous imperial donations to influential Britons were confiscated and the Roman financier and philosopher [[Seneca the Younger|Seneca]] called in the loans he had forced on the reluctant Britons.&lt;ref&gt;Cassius Dio, [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Cassius_Dio/62*.html Epitome of Book LXII, 2]&lt;/ref&gt;

In AD 60 or 61, when the [[Governors of Roman Britain|Roman governor]] [[Gaius Suetonius Paulinus]] was campaigning on the island of [[Anglesey|Mona]] (modern Anglesey) on the northwest coast of [[Wales]], Boudica led the Iceni, the [[Trinovantes]], and others in revolt.&lt;ref name=&quot;hingleyunwin&quot;&gt;{{cite book|authors=Richard Hingley and Christina Unwin|title=Boudica: Iron Age Warrior Queen|publisher=Hambledon Continuum|edition=New|date=2006|isbn=978-1-85285-516-1|pages=44, 61}}&lt;/ref&gt; They destroyed {{lang|la|[[Camulodunum]]}} (modern [[Colchester]]), earlier the capital of the Trinovantes but at that time a {{lang|la|[[colonia (Roman)|colonia]]}}, a settlement for discharged Roman soldiers and site of a temple to the former Emperor [[Claudius]]. Upon hearing of the revolt, Suetonius hurried to {{lang|la|[[Londinium]]}} (modern [[London]]), the 20-year-old commercial settlement that was the rebels' next target. He lacked sufficient numbers to defend the settlement, and he evacuated and abandoned {{lang|la|Londinium}}. Boudica led a very large army of Iceni, Trinovantes, and others against a detachment of {{lang|la|Legio IX Hispana|[[Legio IX ''Hispana'']]}}, defeating them, and burning {{lang|la|Londinium}} and {{lang|la|[[Verulamium]]}}.

An estimated 70,000–80,000 Romans and British were then killed in the three cities by those following Boudica,&lt;ref name=&quot;TAnn14.33&quot;&gt;[[Tacitus]], ''[[Annals (Tacitus)|Annals]]'' [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.02.0078%3Abook%3D14%3Achapter%3D33 14.33]&lt;/ref&gt; many by [[Torture#Historical methods of execution and capital punishment|torture]].&lt;ref name=&quot;TAnn14.33&quot; /&gt; Suetonius, meanwhile, regrouped his forces, possibly in the [[West Midlands (region)|West Midlands]]; despite being heavily outnumbered, he [[Defeat of Boudica|decisively defeated the Britons]]. The crisis caused [[Nero]] to consider withdrawing all Roman forces from Britain, but Suetonius' victory over Boudica confirmed Roman control of the province. Boudica then either killed herself to avoid capture (according to Tacitus),&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, {{lang|la|[[Agricola (book)|Agricola]]}} [[s:Agricola#14|14–16]]; ''Annals'' [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?lookup=Tac.+Ann.+14.29 14:29–39]&lt;/ref&gt; or died of illness (according to Cassius Dio).&lt;ref&gt;[[Cassius Dio]], ''Roman History'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Cassius_Dio/62*.html#1 62:1–12]&lt;/ref&gt;

Interest in these events was revived in the [[English Renaissance]] and led to Boudica's fame in the [[Victorian era]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Gentleman's Magazine|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MFZIAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA541|year=1854|publisher=W. Pickering|pages=541–}}&lt;/ref&gt; Boudica has remained an important [[cultural icon|cultural symbol]] in the United Kingdom.

== Name ==
Boudica has been known by several versions of her name. [[Raphael Holinshed]] calls her '''Voadicia''', while [[Edmund Spenser]] calls her '''Bunduca''', a version of the name that was used in the popular Jacobean play ''[[Bonduca]]'', in 1612.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonduca&quot;&gt;[[Francis Beaumont]] and [[John Fletcher (playwright)|John Fletcher]], ''[http://www.bibliomania.com/0/6/1/1975/frameset.html Bonduca]''&lt;/ref&gt; [[William Cowper]]'s poem, ''Boadicea, an ode'' (1782) popularised an alternative version of the name.&lt;ref name=&quot;Boadicea, an ode&quot;&gt;[[William Cowper]], ''[http://www.bartleby.com/41/320.html Boadicea, an ode]''&lt;/ref&gt; From the 19th century until the late 20th century, '''Boadicea''' was the most common version of the name, which is probably derived from a mistranscription when a manuscript of [[Tacitus]] was copied in the [[Middle Ages]].

Her name was clearly spelled '''Boudicca''' in the best manuscripts of Tacitus, but also {{lang|grc|Βουδουικα}}, {{lang|grc|Βουνδουικα}}, and {{lang|grc|Βοδουικα}} in the (later and probably secondary) [[epitome]] of [[Cassius Dio]].

[[Kenneth H. Jackson|Kenneth Jackson]] concludes, based on the later development in Welsh ({{lang|cy|Buddug}}) and Irish ({{lang|ghc|Buaidheach}}), that the name derives from the [[Proto-Celtic language|Proto-Celtic]] feminine adjective ''*boudīkā'' 'victorious', that in turn is derived from the [[Celtic languages|Celtic]] word ''*boudā'' 'victory' (cf. [[Irish language|Irish]] {{lang|ga|bua}} (Classical Irish {{lang|ghc|buadh}}) 'victory', [[Scottish Gaelic]] {{lang|ghc|buaidheach}} 'victorious; effective', [[Welsh language|Welsh]] {{lang|cy|buddug}}, {{lang|cy|buddugol}} 'victorious', {{lang|cy|buddugoliaeth}} 'victory'), and that the correct spelling of the name in [[Common Brittonic]] (the British Celtic language) is ''Boudica'', pronounced {{IPA-cel|bɒʊˈdiːkaː}}. The [[Gaulish language|Gaulish]] version is attested in inscriptions as '''Boudiga''' in [[Bordeaux]], '''Boudica''' in [[Lusitania]], and '''Bodicca''' in [[Algeria]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Graham Webster 1978&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Graham Webster|title=Boudica: The British Revolt against Rome AD 60|year=1978}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Guy de la Bédoyère|url=http://www.romanbritain.freeserve.co.uk/Legions.htm|title=The Roman Army in Britain|accessdate=5 July 2005|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080310172023/http://www.romanbritain.freeserve.co.uk/Legions.htm|archivedate=10 March 2008|df=dmy-all|author-link=Guy de la Bédoyère}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The closest English equivalent to the vowel in the first syllable is the ''ow'' in &quot;bow-and-arrow&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Kenneth Jackson|title=Queen Boudica?|journal=Britannia|volume=10|year=1979|page=255|doi=10.2307/526060|author-link=Kenneth H. Jackson|jstor=526060}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[John Rhys]] suggested that the most comparable Latin name, in meaning only, would be &quot;Victorina&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=John|last=Rhys|authorlink=John Rhys|year=1908|publisher=General Literature Committee: Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge (Great Britain)|title=Early Britain, Celtic Britain|page=284|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VLpCAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA284|accessdate=24 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==

=== Historical sources ===
Tacitus took a particular interest in Britain as his father-in-law [[Gnaeus Julius Agricola]] served there three times (and was the subject of his first book). Agricola was a military tribune under Suetonius Paulinus, which almost certainly gave Tacitus an eyewitness source for Boudica's revolt. Cassius Dio's account is only known from an [[epitome]], and his sources are uncertain. He is generally agreed to have based his account on that of Tacitus, but he simplifies the sequence of events and adds details, such as the calling in of loans, that Tacitus does not mention.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://towcestermuseum.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/The-Defeat-of-Boudiccas-Rebellion.pdf|title=The defeat of Boudicca's Rebillion|last=Evans|first=Martin Marix|date=2004|website=Towcester Museum|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Background ===
[[File:Map of the Territory of the Iceni.svg|thumb|Location of [[Iceni]] territory in eastern England; modern county borders are shown.]]
It is agreed that Boudica was of [[Royal family|royal]] descent. Cassius Dio describes her as tall, with [[Tawny (color)|tawny]] hair hanging down to below her waist, a harsh voice and a piercing glare. He writes that she habitually wore a large golden necklace (perhaps a [[torc]]), a colourful tunic, and a thick cloak fastened by a [[brooch]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=https://www.academia.edu/548341|title=Boudica, Cartimandua, Messalina and Agrippina the Younger. Independent Women of Power and the Gendered Rhetoric of Roman History|author=Peter Keegan|work=academia.edu|accessdate=24 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The term {{lang|grc-Latn|xanthotrichos}} translated in this passage as red–brown or tawny can also mean auburn, or a shade ''short'' of brown, but most translators now agree a colour in between light and browny red – ''tawny''. {{cite book|title=Boudica and her stories: narrative transformations of a warrior queen|author=Carolyn D. Williams|publisher=University of Delaware Press|year=2009|page=62}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Boudica's husband, Prasutagus, was the king of the Iceni, a people who inhabited roughly what is now [[Norfolk]]. During Claudius's conquest of southern Britain in AD 43, the Iceni initially allied with Rome. They were proud of their independence, and had revolted in AD 47 when the then Roman governor [[Publius Ostorius Scapula]] planned to disarm all the peoples in the area of Britain under Roman control following a number of local uprisings. Ostorius defeated them and went on to put down other uprisings around Britain.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''The Annals'', 12.31–32&lt;/ref&gt; The Iceni remained independent under Prasutagus. It is unknown whether he became the king only after Ostorius's defeat of the Iceni; Tacitus does not date the start of Prasutagus's reign and first mentioned him, as a long-reigning king who had died, when he wrote about Boudica's rebellion.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/~grout/encyclopaedia_romana/britannia/boudica/boudicanrevolt.html|title=Boudica|website=penelope.uchicago.edu|access-date=2016-10-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Tacitus mentions longstanding reasons for the Trinovantes to hate Rome: &quot;It was against the veterans that their hatred was most intense. For these new settlers in the colony of Camulodunum drove people out of their houses, ejected them from their farms, called them captives and slaves ....&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tacitus, The Annals, 14.31&quot; /&gt;

The immediate cause of the rebellion was gross mistreatment by the Romans. Tacitus wrote, &quot;The Icenian king Prasutagus, celebrated for his long prosperity, had named the emperor his heir, together with his two daughters; an act of deference which he thought would place his kingdom and household beyond the risk of injury. The result was contrary – so much so that his kingdom was pillaged by centurions, his household by slaves; as though they had been prizes of war.&quot; He added that Boudica was lashed, her two daughters were raped, and that the estates of the leading Iceni men were confiscated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tacitus, The Annals, 14.31&quot;&gt;Tacitus, ''The Annals'', 14.31&lt;/ref&gt; Cassius Dio wrote: &quot;An excuse for the war was found in the confiscation of the sums of money that Claudius had given to the foremost Britons; for these sums, as [[Catus Decianus|Decianus Catus]], the procurator of the island maintained, were to be paid back.&quot; He also said that another reason was &quot;the fact that [[Seneca the Younger|Seneca]], in the hope of receiving a good rate of interest, had lent to the islanders 40,000,000 sesterces that they did not want, and had afterwards called in this loan all at once and had resorted to severe measures in exacting it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Cassius Dio, ''Roman History'', 62.2&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Uprising ===
{{Anchor|Boudica's uprising}}
In AD 60 or 61, while the current governor, [[Gaius Suetonius Paulinus]], was leading a campaign against the island of {{lang|la|Mona}} (modern [[Anglesey]]) in the north of Wales, which was a refuge for British rebels and a stronghold of the [[druid]]s, the Iceni conspired with their neighbours the Trinovantes, amongst others, to revolt. Boudica was chosen as their leader. Tacitus records that she addressed her army with these words, &quot;It is not as a woman descended from noble ancestry, but as one of the people that I am avenging lost freedom, my scourged body, the outraged chastity of my daughters,&quot; and concluded, &quot;This is a woman's resolve; as for men, they may live and be slaves.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;Tacitus, Publius, Cornelius, The Annals, Book 14, Chapter 35&lt;/ref&gt; According to Tacitus, they drew inspiration from the example of [[Arminius]], the prince of the [[Cherusci]] who had driven the Romans out of Germany in AD 9, and their own ancestors who had driven [[Julius Caesar]] from Britain.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, {{lang|la|Agricola}} [[s:Agricola#15|15]]&lt;/ref&gt; Dio says that at the outset Boudica employed a form of [[divination]], releasing a [[hare]] from the folds of her dress and interpreting the direction in which it ran, and invoked [[Andraste]], a British [[goddess]] of [[Victoria (mythology)|victory]].
[[File:Yorkshire Museum, York (Eboracum) (7685208580) 2.jpg|thumb|Memorial to Lucius Duccius Rufinus, a standard bearer of the Ninth Legion, [[Yorkshire Museum]], York]]

The rebels' first target was {{lang|la|[[Camulodunum#Iceni Revolt|Camulodunum]]}} (modern [[Colchester]]), the former Trinovantian capital and, at that time, a Roman {{lang|la|[[Colonia (Roman)|colonia]]}}. The Roman veterans who had been settled there had mistreated the locals, and a temple to the former emperor [[Claudius]] had been erected there at local expense, making the city a focus for resentment. The Roman inhabitants sought reinforcements from the procurator, Catus Decianus, but he sent only two hundred [[Auxiliaries (Roman military)|auxiliary troops]]. Boudica's army fell on the poorly defended city and destroyed it, besieging the last defenders in the temple for two days before it fell. A bronze statue to the emperor [[Nero]], which probably stood in front of the temple, was decapitated and its head taken as a trophy by Boudica's army&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | doi=10.1017/S1047759413000214|title = A case of mistaken identity? Laser-scanning the bronze &quot;Claudius&quot; from near Saxmundham| journal=Journal of Roman Archaeology|volume = 26| issue=26|pages = 393–408|year = 2013|last1 = Russell|first1 = Miles| last2=Manley| first2=Harry|url = http://eprints.bournemouth.ac.uk/25979/1/div-class-title-a-case-of-mistaken-identity-laser-scanning-the-bronze-claudius-from-near-saxmundham-div.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Archaeology|Archaeologists]] have shown that the city was methodically demolished.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Jason Burke |url=https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2000/dec/03/jasonburke.theobserver |title=Dig uncovers Boudicca's brutal streak |work=[[The Observer]] |date=3 December 2000 |accessdate=5 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The future governor [[Quintus Petillius Cerialis]], then commanding the [[Legio IX Hispana|Legio IX ''Hispana'']], attempted to relieve the city, but suffered an overwhelming defeat. The infantry with him were all killed – only the commander and some of his cavalry escaped. &quot;The victorious enemy met Petilius Cerialis, commander of the ninth legion, as he was coming to the rescue, routed his troops, and destroyed all his infantry. Cerialis escaped with some cavalry into the camp, and was saved by its fortifications.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;[[Tacitus]], ''[[Annals (Tacitus)|Annals]]'' [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?lookup=Tac.+Ann.+14.32 14.32]&lt;/ref&gt; The location of this battle is unknown, but has been claimed by some modern localities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Haverhill From the Iron Age to 1899|url=http://www.stedmundsbury.gov.uk/sebc/visit/hh-to-1899.cfm|publisher=St. Edmundsbury Borough Council|accessdate=24 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; After this defeat, Catus Decianus fled to [[Gaul]].

When news of the rebellion reached Suetonius, he hurried along [[Watling Street]] through hostile territory to {{lang|la|Londinium}}. {{lang|la|Londinium}} was a relatively new settlement, founded after the conquest of AD 43, but it had grown to be a thriving commercial centre with a population of traders, and, probably, Roman officials. Suetonius considered giving battle there, but considering his lack of numbers and chastened by Petillius's defeat, decided to sacrifice the city to save the province.

&lt;blockquote&gt;Alarmed by this disaster and by the fury of the province which he had goaded into war by his rapacity, the procurator Catus crossed over into Gaul. Suetonius, however, with wonderful resolution, marched amidst a hostile population to Londinium, which, though undistinguished by the name of a colony, was much frequented by a number of merchants and trading vessels. Uncertain whether he should choose it as a seat of war, as he looked round on his scanty force of soldiers, and remembered with what a serious warning the rashness of Petillius had been punished, he resolved to save the province at the cost of a single town. Nor did the tears and weeping of the people, as they implored his aid, deter him from giving the signal of departure and receiving into his army all who would go with him. Those who were chained to the spot by the weakness of their sex, or the infirmity of age, or the attractions of the place, were cut off by the enemy.&lt;small&gt;— Tacitus&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TAnn14.33&quot; /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Londinium was abandoned to the rebels, who burnt it down, torturing and killing anyone who had not evacuated with Suetonius. Archaeology shows a thick red layer of burnt debris covering coins and pottery dating before AD 60 within the bounds of Roman Londinium;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=George Patrick Welch|title=Britannia: The Roman Conquest &amp; Occupation of Britain|year=1963|page=107}}&lt;/ref&gt; while Roman-era skulls found in the [[Walbrook]] in 2013 may have been victims of the rebels.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/science/2013/oct/02/roman-skulls-crossrail-london-boudicca|title=Roman skulls found during Crossrail dig in London may be Boudicca victims|author=Maev Kennedy |newspaper=[[The Guardian]]|accessdate=24 February 2016|date=2 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{lang|la|[[Verulamium]]}} ([[St Albans]]) was next to be destroyed.

In the three settlements destroyed, between seventy and eighty thousand people are said to have been killed. Tacitus says that the Britons had no interest in taking or selling prisoners, only in slaughter by [[gibbet]], fire, or cross.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus:text:1999.02.0078:book=14:chapter=33|title=Cornelius Tacitus, The Annals, Book XIV, chapter 33|website=www.perseus.tufts.edu|access-date=2018-02-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dio's account gives more detail; that the noblest women were impaled on spikes and had their breasts cut off and sewn to their mouths, &quot;to the accompaniment of sacrifices, banquets, and wanton behaviour&quot; in sacred places, particularly the groves of Andraste.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=cC19DAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA55&amp;lpg=PA55&amp;dq=to+the+accompaniment+of+sacrifices,+banquets,+and+wanton+behaviour#v=onepage&amp;q=to%20the%20accompaniment%20of%20sacrifices,%20banquets,%20and%20wanton%20behaviour&amp;f=false|title=Folly and Fortune in Early British History: From Caesar to the Normans|last=Henshall|first=K.|date=2008|publisher=Springer|isbn=978-0230583795|location=|page=55|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Romans rally ====

{{Main|Defeat of Boudica}}
While Boudica's army continued their assault in Verulamium (St. Albans), Suetonius regrouped his forces. According to Tacitus, he amassed a force including his own [[Legio XIV Gemina|Legio XIV ''Gemina'']], some ''vexillationes'' (detachments) of the [[Legio XX Valeria Victrix|XX ''Valeria Victrix'']], and any available auxiliaries.&lt;ref name=&quot;TacAnn14.34&quot;&gt;Tacitus, ''Annals'' [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?lookup=Tac.+Ann.+14.34 14.34]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[prefect]] of {{lang|la|[[Legio II Augusta]]}}, [[Poenius Postumus]], ignored the call,&lt;ref name=&quot;TacAnn14.37&quot;&gt;Tacitus, ''Annals'' [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?lookup=Tac.+Ann.+14.37 14.37]&lt;/ref&gt; and a fourth legion, {{lang|la|[[Legio IX Hispana|IX Hispana]]}}, had been routed trying to relieve {{lang|la|Camulodunum}},&lt;ref name=&quot;TacAnn14.32&quot;&gt;Tacitus, ''Annals'' [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?lookup=Tac.+Ann.+14.32 14.32]&lt;/ref&gt; but nonetheless the governor now commanded an army of almost ten thousand men.

Suetonius took a stand at an unidentified location, probably in the [[West Midlands (region)|West Midlands]] somewhere along the [[Roman road]] now known as [[Watling Street]], in a [[Defile (geography)|defile]] with a wood behind him&amp;nbsp;– but his men were heavily outnumbered. Dio says that, even if they were lined up one deep, they would not have extended the length of Boudica's line. By now the rebel forces were said to have numbered 230,000–300,000. However, this number should be treated with scepticism&amp;nbsp;– Dio's account is known only from a late [[epitome]].

Boudica exhorted her troops from her [[chariot]], her daughters beside her. Tacitus records her giving a short speech in which she presents herself not as an [[Aristocracy (class)|aristocrat]] avenging her lost wealth, but as an ordinary person, avenging her lost freedom, her battered body, and the abused chastity of her daughters. She said their cause was just, and the deities were on their side; the one legion that had dared to face them had been destroyed. She, a woman, was resolved to win or die; if the men wanted to live in slavery, that was their choice.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;At first, the legionaries stood motionless, keeping to the defile as a natural protection: then, when the closer advance of the enemy had enabled them to exhaust their missiles with certitude of aim, they dashed forward in a wedge-like formation. The auxiliaries charged in the same style; and the cavalry, with lances extended, broke a way through any parties of resolute men whom they encountered. The remainder took to flight, although escape was difficult, as the cordon of wagons had blocked the outlets. The troops gave no quarter even to the women: the baggage animals themselves had been speared and added to the pile of bodies. The glory won in the course of the day was remarkable, and equal to that of our older victories: for, by some accounts, little less than eighty thousand Britons fell, at a cost of some four hundred Romans killed and a not much greater number of wounded. Boudica ended her days by poison; while [[Poenius Postumus]], camp-prefect of the second legion, informed of the exploits of the men of the fourteenth and twentieth, and conscious that he had cheated his own corps of a share in the honours and had violated the rules of the service by ignoring the orders of his commander, ran his sword through his body.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

According to Tacitus in his ''Annals'', Boudica poisoned herself, though in the {{lang|la|Agricola}} which was written almost twenty years before the ''Annals'' he mentions nothing of suicide and attributes the end of the revolt to {{lang|la|socordia}} (&quot;indolence&quot;); Dio says she fell sick and died and then was given a lavish burial.

[[Catus Decianus]], who had fled to Gaul, was replaced by [[Gaius Julius Alpinus Classicianus]]. Suetonius conducted punitive operations, but criticism by Classicianus led to an investigation headed by [[Nero]]'s [[freedman]] [[Polyclitus (freedman)|Polyclitus]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://wc.rootsweb.com/cgi-bin/igm.cgi?op=GET&amp;db=stanwardine&amp;id=I2736|title=Bodicea Queen Of The Iceni|access-date=9 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fearing Suetonius's actions would provoke further rebellion, Nero replaced the governor with the more conciliatory [[Publius Petronius Turpilianus]].&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annals'' [[s:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 14#39|14.39]]&lt;/ref&gt; The historian [[Suetonius|Gaius Suetonius Tranquillus]] tells us the crisis had almost persuaded Nero to abandon Britain.&lt;ref&gt;[[Suetonius]], ''Nero'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Suetonius/12Caesars/Nero*.html#18 18], [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Suetonius/12Caesars/Nero*.html#39 39–40]&lt;/ref&gt; No historical records tell what had happened to Boudica's two daughters.

==== Location of her defeat ====
The location of Boudica's defeat is unknown.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/history/historic_figures/boudicca.shtml|title=BBC – History – Boudicca|access-date=2017-04-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many historians favour a site in the [[West Midlands (county)|West Midlands]], somewhere along the Roman road now known as [[Watling Street]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Boudicca&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.ancient.eu/Boudicca/|title=Boudicca|work=Ancient History Encyclopedia|access-date=2017-04-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Boudicca&quot; /&gt; Kevin K. Carroll suggests a site close to [[High Cross, Leicestershire]], on the junction of Watling Street and the [[Fosse Way]], which would have allowed the [[Legio II Augusta]], based at [[Exeter]], to rendezvous with the rest of Suetonius's forces, had they not failed to do so.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Kevin K. Carroll |title=The Date of Boudicca's Revolt |journal=Britannia |volume=10 |year=1979 |pages=197–202 |doi=10.2307/526056 |jstor=526056 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Manduessedum]] ([[Mancetter]]), near the modern town of [[Atherstone]] in [[Warwickshire]], has also been suggested,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Sheppard Frere |title=Britannia: A History of Roman Britain |year=1987 |page=73 |author-link=Sheppard Frere }}&lt;/ref&gt; and according to legend &quot;The Rampart&quot; near [[Messing, Essex|Messing]], [[Essex]] and [[Ambresbury Banks]] in [[Epping Forest]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |publisher=Messing-cum-Inworth Community Website |url=http://messing-cum-inworth-pc.gov.uk/messVill.htm |title=Messing Village |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090530121347/http://www.messing-cum-inworth-pc.gov.uk/messVill.htm |archivedate=30 May 2009 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; More recently, a discovery of Roman artefacts in [[Kings Norton]] close to [[Birmingham military history|Metchley Camp]] has suggested another possibility,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/england/west_midlands/5016126.stm |title=Is Boudicca buried in Birmingham? |work=[[BBC News Online]] |date=25 May 2006 |accessdate=9 September 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and a thorough examination of a stretch of Watling Street between St. Albans, Boudica's last known location, and the Fosse Way junction has suggested the Cuttle Mill area of [[Paulerspury]] in Northamptonshire, which has [[topography]] very closely matching that described by Tacitus of the scene of the battle,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://paulerspury.org/content/view/18/49/ |title=Paulerspury – History |work=paulerspury.org |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100819032234/http://paulerspury.org/content/view/18/49 |archivedate=19 August 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and where large quantities of human bones of both sexes, and including children, have been found over a wide area together with fragments of Roman pottery from the 1st century.&lt;ref&gt;British History Online, Paulerspury pp. 111–117, last paragraph. http://www.british-history.ac.uk/rchme/northants/vol4/pp111-117&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, it was suggested that the Iceni were returning to East Anglia along the [[Icknield Way]] when they encountered the Roman army in the vicinity of [[Arbury Banks, Hertfordshire]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Grahame Appleby |year=2009 |title=The Boudican Revolt: Countdown to Defeat |journal=Hertfordshire Archaeology and History |volume=16 |pages=57–66 |url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/280564223|accessdate=24 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In March 2010, evidence was published suggesting the site may be located at [[Church Stowe]], Northamptonshire.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.craftpegg.com/Battle_Church_Stowe_CP.pdf |title=Landscape Analysis and Appraisal Church Stowe, Northamptonshire, as a Candidate Site for the Battle of Watling Street |website=craftpegg.com |accessdate=24 February 2016 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160303233915/http://www.craftpegg.com/Battle_Church_Stowe_CP.pdf |archivedate=3 March 2016 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy and legends==
In his 6th-century work ''[[De Excidio et Conquestu Britanniae|On the Ruin and Conquest of Britain]]'', the monk [[Gildas]] demonstrates his knowledge of a female leader whom he describes as &quot;treacherous&quot;:

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;A treacherous lioness butchered the governors who had been left to give fuller voice and strength to the endeavors of Roman rule&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;hingleyunwin&quot; /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

''Buddug'' has yet to be conclusively identified within the canon of [[medieval Welsh literature]] and she is not apparent in the {{lang|la|[[Historia Brittonum]]}}, the {{lang|cy|[[Mabinogion]]}} or [[Geoffrey of Monmouth]]'s ''[[History of the Kings of Britain]]''.

The area of [[King's Cross, London]] was previously a village known as Battle Bridge which was an ancient crossing of the [[River Fleet]]. The original name of the bridge was Broad Ford Bridge. The name &quot;Battle Bridge&quot; led to a tradition that this was the site of a major battle between the Romans and the Iceni tribe led by Boudica.&lt;ref name=&quot;thornbury&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.aspx?compid=45097 |title=Highbury, Upper Holloway and King's Cross |work=Old and New London: Volume 2 |author=Walter Thornbury |authorlink=George Walter Thornbury |year=1878 |pages=273–279 |accessdate=11 November 2010 |publisher=British History Online }}&lt;/ref&gt; The tradition is not supported by any historical evidence and is rejected by modern historians. However, [[Lewis Spence]]'s 1937 book ''Boadicea – warrior queen of the Britons'' went so far as to include a map showing the positions of the opposing armies. There is a belief that she was buried between platforms 9 and 10 in [[London King's Cross railway station|King's Cross station]] in London, England. There is no evidence for this and it is probably a post-[[World War II]] invention.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The &quot;Warrior Queen&quot; under Platform 9 |url=http://www.museumoflondon.org.uk/English/Learning/Learningonline/features/roman/roman_london_7.htm |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090301192533/http://www.museumoflondon.org.uk/English/Learning/Learningonline/features/roman/roman_london_7.htm |publisher= Museum of London |archivedate=1 March 2009 |accessdate=13 August 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first English writings appear during the reign of [[Elizabeth I of England|Queen Elizabeth]] following the rediscovery of the works of Tacitus. [[Polydore Vergil]] may have reintroduced her to British history as &quot;Voadicea&quot; in 1534.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Polydore Vergil's English History, Book 2 |url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=hSAIAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA59 |pages=69–72 |last1 = Vergil|first1 = Polydore|year = 1846}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Raphael Holinshed]] also included her story in his ''Chronicles'' (1577), based on Tacitus and Dio,&lt;ref&gt;[[Raphael Holinshed]], ''Chronicles'': History of England [http://www.gutenberg.org/files/16536/16536-h/16536-h.htm#page494 4.9-13]&lt;/ref&gt; and inspired [[William Shakespeare|Shakespeare's]] younger contemporaries [[Francis Beaumont]] and [[John Fletcher (playwright)|John Fletcher]] to write a play, ''[[Bonduca]]'', in 1610.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonduca&quot; /&gt; [[William Cowper]] wrote a popular poem, &quot;Boadicea, an ode&quot;, in 1782.&lt;ref name=&quot;Boadicea, an ode&quot; /&gt;

It was in the [[Victorian era]] that Boudica's fame took on legendary proportions as [[Queen Victoria]] came to be seen as Boudica's &quot;namesake&quot;, their names being identical in meaning. Victoria's [[Poet Laureate]], [[Alfred, Lord Tennyson]], wrote a poem, &quot;Boadicea&quot;, and [[HMS Boadicea|several ships]] were named after her.&lt;ref&gt;[[Alfred, Lord Tennyson]], ''[http://oldpoetry.com/opoem/8721-Alfred-Lord-Tennyson-Boadicea Boadicea]''&lt;/ref&gt;

== Statues ==
[[File:Boudica (Aldaron).jpg|thumb|Detail of [[Thomas Thornycroft]]'s ''[[Boadicea and Her Daughters]]'']]
''[[Boadicea and Her Daughters]]'', a statue of the queen in her [[war chariot]] ([[Anachronism|anachronistically]] furnished with [[Scythed chariot|scythes]] after the [[Achaemenid Empire|Persian]] fashion) was executed by [[Thomas Thornycroft]] over the 1850s and 1860s with the encouragement of [[Prince Albert, Prince Consort|Prince Albert]], who lent his horses for use as models.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Images of Women in Peace &amp; War: Cross-Cultural &amp; Historical Perspectives |chapter-url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=SCUbpgTPeOgC&amp;pg=PA53 |p=[https://archive.org/details/imagesofwomeninp00macd/page/53 53] |publisher=Macmillan Press |date=1987 |location=London |chapter=Boadicea: Warrior, Mother, and Myth |last=Macdonald |first=Sharon |isbn=0-299-11764-2 |url=https://archive.org/details/imagesofwomeninp00macd/page/53 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Thornycroft exhibited the head separately in 1864. It was cast in bronze in 1902, 17 years after Thornycroft's death, by his son [[John Isaac Thornycroft|Sir John]], who presented it to the [[London County Council]]. They erected it on a plinth on the [[Victoria Embankment]] next to [[Westminster Bridge]] and the [[Palace of Westminster|Houses of Parliament]], inscribed with the following lines from Cowper's poem:&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;poem&gt;
Regions Caesar never knew
Thy posterity shall sway.
&lt;/poem&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The great anti-imperialist rebel was now identified with the head of the [[British Empire]], and her statue&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.culture24.org.uk/history+%2526+heritage/war+%2526+conflict/pre%252d20th+century+conflict/tra22669 |title=Battlefield Britain – Boudicca's revolt against the Romans |author=Corinne Field |date=30 April 2006 |publisher=Culture24 |accessdate=8 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; stood guard over the city she razed to the ground.&lt;ref name=&quot;Graham Webster 1978&quot; /&gt;

Boudica (Buddug) was chosen by the Welsh public as one of eleven statues of historical figures to be included in the Marble Hall at [[Cardiff City Hall]]. The statue was unveiled by [[David Lloyd George]] on 27 October 1916. Unlike the London chariot statue, it shows her as a more motherly figure without warrior trappings. The popularity of Buddug alongside other Welsh heroes such as [[Saint David]] and [[Owain Glyndŵr]] was surprising to many{{snd}}of the statues, Buddug is the most ancient, the only female, and the only antecedent from outside the [[Wales|modern Welsh nation]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Chappell&quot;&gt;{{cite book
 |last = Chappell
 |first = Edgar L.
 |title = Cardiff's Civic Centre: A historical guide
 |publisher = Priory Press
 |year = 1946|pages= 21–26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Div col|colwidth=20em}}
* {{lang|cy|[[Gwenllian ferch Gruffydd]]}}
* [[List of women warriors in folklore]]
* [[Women in ancient warfare]]
* ''[[The Wrath of the Iceni]]''
* ''[[Warrior Queen]]''
* ''[[Boudica (film)|Boudica]]''
* [[Boodikka]]
* [[Ambiorix]]
* [[Alaric I]]
* [[Ardaric]]
* [[Athanaric]]
* [[Autaritus]]
* [[Battle of Baduhenna Wood]]
* [[Bato (Daesitiate chieftain)]]
* [[Fritigern]]
* [[Gaius Julius Civilis]]
* [[John of Gothia]]
* [[Spartacus]]
* [[Totila]]
* [[Vercingetorix]]
* [[Viriathus]]
{{div col end}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* {{cite book |last=Aldhouse-Green |first=M. |title=Boudica Britannia: Rebel, War-Leader and Queen |publisher=Pearson Longman |year=2006 }}
* {{cite book |last=de la Bédoyère |first=Guy |authorlink=Guy de la Bédoyère |year=2003 |chapter=Bleeding from the Roman Rods: Boudica |title=Defying Rome: The Rebels of Roman Britain |location=Tempus |publisher=Stroud }}
* {{cite book |last=Böckl |first=Manfred |title=Die letzte Königin der Kelten |trans-title=The last Queen of the Celts |language=German |publisher=Aufbau Verlag |location=Berlin |year=2005 }}
* {{cite book |last=Cassius Dio Cocceianus |authorlink=Cassius Dio |title=Dio's Roman History |url=https://archive.org/details/diosromanhistory08cassuoft |year=1914–1927 |publisher=Harvard University Press |location=Cambridge, Massachusetts |others=Earnest Cary trans |volume=8 }}
* {{cite book |last=Collingridge |first=Vanessa |authorlink=Vanessa Collingridge |title=Boudica |publisher=Ebury |location=London |year=2004 }}
* {{cite book |last1=Dudley |first1=Donald R |last2=Webster |first2=Graham |title=The Rebellion of Boudicca |year=1962 |publisher=Routledge |location=London }}
* {{cite book |last=Fraser |first=Antonia |title=The Warrior Queens |year=1988 |publisher=Weidenfeld and Nicolson |location=London }}
* {{cite book |last=Godsell |first=Andrew |authorlink=Andrew Godsell |chapter=Boadicea: A Woman's Resolve |title=Legends of British History|publisher=Wessex Publishing|year=2008}}
* {{cite book|last1=Hingley |first1=Richard |first2=Christina|last2=Unwin|title=Boudica: Iron Age Warrior Queen |location=London |publisher=Hambledon and London |year=2004 }}
* {{cite book |last=Roesch |first=Joseph E. |title=Boudica, Queen of The Iceni |location=London |publisher=Robert Hale Ltd |year=2006 }}
* {{cite book |last=Tacitus |first=Cornelius |authorlink=Tacitus |title=Tacitus on Britain and Germany|url=https://archive.org/details/tacitusonbritain00taci |url-access=registration |year=1948|publisher=Penguin |location=London |others=H. Mattingly trans }}
* {{cite book |last=Tacitus |first=Cornelius |authorlink=Tacitus |title=The Annals of Imperial Rome |url=https://archive.org/details/annalsofimperial1988taci |url-access=registration |year=1989 |publisher=Penguin |location=London |others=M. Grant trans }}
* {{cite book |last=Taylor |first=John |title=Tacitus and the Boudican Revolt |year=1998 |publisher=Camvlos |location=Dublin }}
* {{cite book |last=Webster |first=Graham |title=Boudica |year=1978 |publisher=Rowman and Littlefield |location=Totowa, NJ }}
* {{cite book |last=Cottrell |first=Leonard |authorlink=Leonard Cottrell |title=The Great Invasion |year=1958 |publisher=Evans Brothers Limited }}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Boudica}}
{{Wikisource1911Enc|Boadicea}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/2732 |title=Boudicca (d. AD 60/61) |last=Potter |first=T. W. |work=Oxford Dictionary of National Biography |publisher=Oxford University Press |accessdate=4 October 2010 |url-access=subscription  |doi=10.1093/ref:odnb/2732 |year=2004 }} {{DNBfirst|wstitle=Boadicea}}
* [https://www.britishmuseum.org/explore/highlights/highlight_objects/pe_prb/h/hoard_of_iceni_silver_coins.aspx The Iceni Hoard at the British Museum]

{{Ancient Roman Wars}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Boudica| ]]
[[Category:60s in the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:61 deaths]]
[[Category:60s conflicts]]
[[Category:1st-century monarchs in Europe]]
[[Category:1st-century women rulers]]
[[Category:Ancient people who committed suicide]]
[[Category:Briton rulers]]
[[Category:Celtic women warriors]]
[[Category:Female suicides]]
[[Category:Iceni]]
[[Category:Pagans]]
[[Category:People from Norfolk]]
[[Category:Queens regnant in the British Isles]]
[[Category:Rebellions against the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:British rebels]]
[[Category:Royalty who committed suicide]]
[[Category:Wartime sexual violence]]
[[Category:Women in 1st-century warfare]]
[[Category:Women in ancient European warfare]]
[[Category:Year of birth unknown]]
[[Category:Women in war in Britain]]</text>
      <sha1>mvimpvnhuy32sckv4719k4vrbjrpwok</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
