  <page>
    <title>Blue Öyster Cult</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4579</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942024021</id>
      <parentid>940472222</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-22T03:10:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Acrouch</username>
        <id>1102565</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Added two citations for lyricists, as part of project to clean up missing Citations backlog.  Note:  Danny Miranda is listed as co-songwriter on last 2 BOC recordings - may be appropriate to list him as a lyricist as well. Still looking for a specific exact source to cite.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|American hard rock band}}
{{Infobox musical artist &lt;!-- See Wikipedia:WikiProject Musicians --&gt;
| name             = Blue Öyster Cult
| image            = Blue Oyster Cult 1977 publicity photo.jpg
| caption          = 1977 publicity photo of Blue Öyster Cult with the 1971–81 lineup, L–R: [[Buck Dharma|Donald &quot;Buck Dharma&quot; Roeser]] (bottom); [[Eric Bloom]]; [[Albert Bouchard]]; [[Allen Lanier]]; [[Joe Bouchard]]
| image_size       = 300
| landscape        = yes
| background       = group_or_band
| origin           = [[Stony Brook, New York|Stony Brook]], [[New York (state)|New York]], U.S.
| genre            = {{flatlist|
* [[Hard rock]]
* [[heavy metal music|heavy metal]]
* [[occult rock]]&lt;ref name=&quot;It Djents&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last1=Paliwal |first1=Vidur |title=REVIEWSREVIEW: Earthless – &quot;Black Heaven&quot; |url=http://www.itdjents.com/reviews-2/review-earthless-black-heaven/ |accessdate=16 June 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180619114859/http://www.itdjents.com/reviews-2/review-earthless-black-heaven/ |archive-date=19 June 2018 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Stannard |first1=Joseph |title=A Disease with a Long Incubation: Blue Öyster Cult's Imaginos |url=http://thequietus.com/articles/12881-blue-oyster-cult-imaginos-review-anniversary |website=[[The Quietus]] |accessdate=16 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[progressive rock]]
* [[psychedelic rock]] (early)
* [[acid rock]] (early)
}}
| years_active     = 1967–present
| label            = {{flatlist|
* [[Columbia Records|Columbia]]
* [[CMC International|CMC]]
}}
| associated_acts  = {{flatlist|
* [[Alice Cooper]]
* [[Black Sabbath]]
* [[Brain Surgeons]]
* [[Patti Smith]]
}}
| alias            = {{flatlist|
* Soft White Underbelly &lt;small&gt;(1967–1969)&lt;/small&gt;
* Oaxaca &lt;small&gt;(1970)&lt;/small&gt;
* Stalk-Forrest Group &lt;small&gt;(1970)&lt;/small&gt;
* Santos Sisters &lt;small&gt;(1970)&lt;/small&gt;
}}
| website          = {{URL|blueoystercult.com}}
| current_members  = * [[Buck Dharma]]
* [[Eric Bloom]]
* [[Danny Miranda]]
* [[Richie Castellano]]
* Jules Radino
}}

'''Blue Öyster Cult''' (often abbreviated '''BÖC''' or '''BOC''') is &lt;!--Article is using USA format. This means 'is' and not 'are' a group --&gt; an American [[Rock music|rock]] band formed in [[Stony Brook, New York]] in 1967, perhaps best known for the singles &quot;[[(Don't Fear) The Reaper]]&quot;, &quot;[[Burnin' for You]]&quot;, &quot;[[Cities on Flame with Rock and Roll]]&quot;, and &quot;[[Godzilla (song)|Godzilla]].&quot; Blue Öyster Cult has sold more than 24 million records worldwide, including 7 million in the United States alone.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://tahoesouth.com/events/blue-oyster-cult-at-harrahs-lake-tahoe/|title=Blue Oyster Cult, Harrah's South Shore Room - Tahoe South|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The band's [[music video]]s, especially &quot;Burnin' for You,&quot; received heavy rotation on [[MTV]] when the music television network premiered in 1981, cementing the band's contribution to the development and success of the music video in modern popular culture.

Blue Öyster Cult's longest-lasting and most commercially successful lineup included [[Buck Dharma|Donald &quot;Buck Dharma&quot; Roeser]] (lead guitar, vocals), [[Eric Bloom]] (lead vocals, &quot;[[rhythm guitar|stun guitar]]&quot;, keyboards, synthesizers), [[Allen Lanier]] (keyboards, rhythm guitar, backing vocals), [[Joe Bouchard]] (bass, vocals), [[Albert Bouchard]] (drums, percussion, cowbell, vocals). The band's current lineup includes Roeser and Bloom, as well as Danny Miranda (bass, backing vocals), Jules Radino (drums, percussion) and [[Richie Castellano]] (keyboard, rhythm guitar, lead and backing vocals).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Official Website|url=http://www.blueoystercult.com/Band-main.html|publisher=Blueoystercult.com|accessdate=2012-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

===Early years as Soft White Underbelly (1967–1971)===
The band originated as a group called Soft White Underbelly (a name the band would occasionally revive in the 1970s and 1980s to play small club gigs around the United States and UK&lt;ref&gt;Concert Ticket http://theticketmeister.co.uk/soft-white-underbelly-the-venue-1981&lt;/ref&gt;) in 1967 in the vicinity of [[Stony Brook University]] on Long Island, at the prompting of critic and manager [[Sandy Pearlman]].  The group consisted of guitarist Buck Dharma, drummer Albert Bouchard, keyboardist Allen Lanier, singers Jeff Kagel (aka [[Krishna Das (singer)|Krishna Das]]) and Les Braunstein and bassist Andrew Winters.&lt;ref name=&quot;ecfjhn&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Berelian |first=Essi |title=The Rough Guide to Heavy Metal |publisher=Rough Guides |isbn=1-84353-415-0 |page=41|year=2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Pearlman wanted the group to be the American answer to [[Black Sabbath]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://classicrock.about.com/od/artistsae1/a/eric_bloom.htm |title=Interview with Eric Bloom of Blue Oyster Cult |publisher=Classicrock.about.com |date=2010-06-11 |accessdate=2010-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pearlman was important to the band&amp;nbsp;– he was able to get them [[concert|gigs]] and recording contracts with [[Elektra Records|Elektra]] and [[Columbia Records|Columbia]], and he provided them with his poetry for use as lyrics for many of their songs, including &quot;Astronomy&quot;. Writer [[Richard Meltzer]] also provided the band with lyrics from their early days up through their most recent studio album. Pearlman also gave stage names to each of the band members (Jesse Python for Eric Bloom, Andy Panda for Andy Winters, Prince Omega for Albert Bouchard, La Verne for Allen Lanier) but only Buck Dharma kept his.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Popoff |first=Martin |title=Blue Oyster Cult, Secrets Revealed! |publisher=Metal Blade Records, Inc. |isbn=0-9752807-0-8 |page=9|year=2004 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The band recorded an album's worth of material for [[Elektra Records]] in 1968. When Braunstein departed in early 1969, Elektra shelved the album. In 1968, the band moved in together at their first house in the [[Thomaston, New York|Thomaston]] area of [[Great Neck, New York]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.newsday.com/entertainment/music/blue-oyster-cult-s-40th-anniversary-cd-1.4147975|title=Blue Oyster Cult's 40th anniversary CD|last=October 26|first=STEVE KNOPPER Special to Newsday Updated|last2=Pm|first2=2012 2:26|website=Newsday|language=en|access-date=2020-01-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Eric Bloom]] was hired by the band as their [[acoustical engineering|acoustic engineer]] and eventually became lead singer, replacing Braunstein, through a series of three unlikely coincidences, one in which Lanier decided to join Bloom on a drive to an [[upstate New York|upstate]] gig where he spent the night with Bloom's old college bandmates and got to hear old tapes of Bloom's talent as lead vocalist.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JR1NpyxowP4 &quot;Three Strokes of Fate&quot;], Living Legends Music interview (posted to YouTube on Nov 4, 2008) where Bloom explains three highly unlikely events that happened in which he ended up joining the band and becoming their lead singer:&lt;br /&gt;1) Being their amp salesperson at Sam Ash,&lt;br /&gt;2) Telling one person where he was staying in NYC and getting the soundboard job offer,&lt;br /&gt;3) Upstate roadtrip where Lanier decided to join and got to hear Bloom's old band tapes as lead vocalist.&lt;/ref&gt;  Because of this, Bloom was offered the job of lead singer for Soft White Underbelly. However, a bad review of a 1969 Fillmore East show caused Pearlman to change the name of the band&amp;nbsp;– first to Oaxaca, then to the Stalk-Forrest Group. The band recorded yet another album's worth of material for Elektra, but only one single (&quot;What Is Quicksand?&quot; b/w &quot;Arthur Comics&quot;) was released (and only in a promo edition of 300 copies) on [[Elektra Records]] (this album was eventually released, with additional outtakes, by Rhino Handmade Records as ''[[St. Cecilia: The Elektra Recordings]]'' in 2001). The album featured Bloom as their main lead singer, but Roeser also sang lead on a few songs, a pattern of sharing lead vocals that has continued throughout the band's career.

After a few more temporary band names, including the Santos Sisters, the band settled on Blue Öyster Cult in 1971 (see [[#Band name and logo|below]] for its origin).

New York City producer/composer and jingle writer [[David Lucas (composer)|David Lucas]] saw the band perform and took them into his Warehouse Recording Studio and produced four demos, with which Pearlman was able to get the renamed band another audition with [[Columbia Records]]. [[Clive Davis]] liked what he heard, and signed the band to the label. The first album was subsequently produced and recorded by Lucas on eight track at Lucas' studio.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blueoystercult.com/Studio/SWbios.html#Lucas |title='David Lucas' in band-relations bio page|publisher=Official BÖC website |date= |accessdate=2011-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Winters would leave the band and be replaced by Bouchard's brother, [[Joe Bouchard]].

===Black-and-white years (1971–1975)===
Their debut album ''[[Blue Öyster Cult (album)|Blue Öyster Cult]]'' was released in January 1972, with a black-and-white cover designed by artist Bill Gawlik. The album featured the songs &quot;[[Cities on Flame with Rock and Roll]]&quot;, &quot;Stairway to the Stars&quot; and &quot;Then Came the Last Days of May&quot;. By this time, the band's sound had become more oriented toward hard rock, but songs like &quot;She's As Beautiful As a Foot&quot; and &quot;Redeemed&quot; also showed a strong element of the band's psychedelic roots. All of the band members except for Allen Lanier sang lead, a pattern that would continue on many subsequent albums, although lead singer Eric Bloom sang the majority of the songs. The album sold well, and Blue Öyster Cult toured with artists such as [[the Byrds]], [[Mahavishnu Orchestra]] and [[Alice Cooper]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Perry |first=Shawn |url=http://www.vintagerock.com/ebloom_interview.aspx |title=The Eric Bloom Interview |publisher=Vintagerock.com |accessdate=2010-09-23 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070720122423/http://www.vintagerock.com/ebloom_interview.aspx |archivedate=2007-07-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt; During the touring process, the band's sound became heavier and more direct.

Their next album ''[[Tyranny and Mutation]]'', released in 1973, was written while the band was on tour for their first LP. It contained songs such as &quot;The Red and the Black&quot; (an ode to the [[Royal Canadian Mounted Police]] and a rewrite of &quot;I'm On the Lamb But I Ain't No Sheep&quot; from the debut album, and also a reference to [[The Red and the Black|the novel by Stendhal of the same name]]), &quot;Hot Rails to Hell&quot; and &quot;Baby Ice Dog&quot;, the first of the band's many collaborations with [[Patti Smith]]. It featured a harder-rocking approach than before, though the band's songs were also growing more complex. The album outsold its predecessor, a trend that would continue with their next few albums.

The band's third album, ''[[Secret Treaties]]'' (1974)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://texasarchive.org/2010_03463|title=Blue Öyster Cult Concert and Interview (1975)|last=|first=|date=|website=Texas Archive of the Moving Image|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=December 1, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; received positive reviews, featuring songs such as &quot;Career of Evil&quot; (co-written by Patti Smith), &quot;Dominance and Submission&quot; and &quot;[[Astronomy (song)|Astronomy]]&quot;. As a result of constant touring, the band was now capable of headlining arenas. The album continued the trend of growing sales, and would eventually go gold.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.riaa.com/gold-platinum/?tab_active=default-award&amp;se=blue+oyster+cult+secret+treaties#search_section|title=Gold &amp; Platinum - RIAA|work=RIAA|access-date=2018-03-13|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As the three albums during this formative period all had black-and-white covers, the period of their career has been dubbed the 'black and white years' by fans and critics.

===Commercial success (1975–1981)===
The band's first live album ''[[On Your Feet or on Your Knees]]'' (1975) achieved greater success and went gold. Its success gave the band more time to work on a follow-up. The band members were able to purchase home recording units to record demos for their next album.

Their next studio album, ''[[Agents of Fortune]]'' (1976), was their first to go platinum and was again produced by David Lucas. It contained the hit single &quot;[[(Don't Fear) The Reaper]]&quot;, which reached number 12 on the Billboard charts and has become a classic of the hard rock genre. Other major songs on the album were &quot;(This Ain't) The Summer of Love&quot;, &quot;E.T.I. (Extra-Terrestrial Intelligence)&quot; and &quot;The Revenge of Vera Gemini&quot;. Having recorded demos of the songs at home before recording the album, the band's songwriting process had become more individual, with none of the songs featuring the collaborative writing between the band members that had been common on their earlier albums.  Although the album still featured their trademark hard rock with sinister lyrics, the songs had become more conventional in structure, and the production was more polished.  For the first and only time, the album featured lead vocals from all five band members, with Allen Lanier singing lead on the song ''True Confessions.'' With Albert Bouchard singing lead on three songs and Joe Bouchard and Donald Roeser singing lead on one each, Eric Bloom ended up taking the lead on only four of the album's ten songs.

For the tour, the band added lasers to their light show, for which they became known. They were among the first acts to use lasers in performance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blueoystercult.com/History/history6.html|publisher=Blue Oyster Cult.com|title=The History of BÖC|accessdate=2008-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Their next album, ''[[Spectres (album)|Spectres]]'' (1977), had the FM radio hit &quot;[[Godzilla (song)|Godzilla]]&quot;, and would become the one of the band's better-selling albums, with other well-known songs like &quot;I Love The Night&quot; and &quot;Goin' Through The Motions.&quot; However, its sales were not as strong as those for the previous album, going gold but not platinum, becoming their first album to sell less than its predecessor. It featured even more polished production, and continued the trend of the lead vocals extensively shared between members, although Allen Lanier did not sing lead. As with the previous album, Eric Bloom sang lead on fewer than half the songs.

The band then released another live album, ''[[Some Enchanted Evening (Blue Öyster Cult album)|Some Enchanted Evening]]'' (1978). Though it was intended as another double-live album in the vein of ''On Your Feet or on Your Knees'', Columbia insisted that it be edited down to single-album length. It was a resounding commercial success, becoming Blue Öyster Cult's most popular album and eventually selling over 2 million copies. It also revealed that while the band's studio work was becoming increasingly well-produced, they were still very much a hard rock band on stage.

It was followed by the studio album ''[[Mirrors (Blue Öyster Cult album)|Mirrors]]'' (1979). For ''Mirrors'', instead of working with previous producers Sandy Pearlman (who instead went on to manage [[Black Sabbath]]) and Murray Krugman, Blue Öyster Cult chose [[Tom Werman]], who had worked with acts such as [[Cheap Trick]] and [[Ted Nugent]]. It featured the band's glossiest production to date. It also gave Roeser, the lead vocalist on the band's biggest hits, bigger prominence as a vocalist, singing lead on four of the nine songs.  However, the resulting album sales were disappointing.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://worldhistoryproject.org/1979/6/blue-oyster-cult-releases-mirrors|title=Blue Öyster Cult releases Mirrors|website=World History Project}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Pearlman's association with Black Sabbath led to Sabbath's ''[[Heaven and Hell (Black Sabbath album)|Heaven and Hell]]'' producer [[Martin Birch]] being hired for the next Blue Öyster Cult record. The album found the band returning to their hard rock roots, and although both of the Bouchard brothers and guitarist Roeser all got lead vocal turns, Bloom would sing the majority of the tracks. The result was positive, with ''[[Cultösaurus Erectus]]'' (1980) receiving good reviews. The album went to number 12 in the United Kingdom, but did not do as well in the United States. The song &quot;[[Black Blade (song)|Black Blade]]&quot;, which was written by Bloom with lyrics by science fiction and fantasy author [[Michael Moorcock]], is a kind of retelling of Moorcock's epic [[Elric of Melniboné]] saga. The band also did a co-headlining tour with Black Sabbath in support of the album, calling the tour &quot;[[Black and Blue (video)|Black and Blue]]&quot;.

Birch produced the band's next album as well, ''[[Fire of Unknown Origin]]'' (1981). The biggest hit on this album was the Top 40 hit &quot;[[Burnin' for You]]&quot;, a song Roeser had written with a [[Richard Meltzer]] lyric. He had intended to use it on his solo album, ''[[Flat Out (Buck Dharma album)|Flat Out]]'' (1982), but he was convinced to use it on the Blue Öyster Cult album instead. The revival of the band's heavier sound continued, albeit with fairly heavy use of synthesizers and some noticeable [[New wave music|New Wave]] influence on a few tracks. It contained other fan favorites such as &quot;[[Joan Crawford]]&quot; (inspired by the book and film ''[[Mommie Dearest]]'') and &quot;[[Veteran of the Psychic Wars]]&quot;, another song co-written by Moorcock. Several of the songs had been written for the animated film ''[[Heavy Metal (film)|Heavy Metal]]'', but only &quot;Veteran of the Psychic Wars&quot; (which had not been written for ''Heavy Metal'') was actually used in the movie. The album marked a strong commercial resurgence for the band and achieved gold status, their first studio album since ''Spectres'' to do so.

During the tour for ''Fire of Unknown Origin'', Albert Bouchard had a falling out with the others and left the band, and Rick Downey (formerly the band's lighting designer) replaced him on drums. This marked the end of the band's original and best-known lineup.

===Decline and fall (1982–1987)===
After leaving the band, Albert Bouchard spent five years working on a solo album based on Sandy Pearlman's poem &quot;Imaginos&quot;. Blue Öyster Cult also released a third live album ''[[Extraterrestrial Live]]''.

The band then went to the studio for the next album, ''[[The Revölution by Night]]'' (1983), with [[Bruce Fairbairn]] as producer. After two albums of a return to a harder rocking sound, the band adopted a more radio-friendly, AOR-oriented sound with Fairbairn providing a 1980s-style production. This approach met with some success, especially on its highest-charting single, Roeser's &quot;[[Shooting Shark]]&quot;, co-written by Patti Smith and featuring [[Randy Jackson]] on bass, which reached number 83 on the charts. Bloom's &quot;[[Take Me Away (Blue Öyster Cult song)|Take Me Away]]&quot; also achieved some FM radio play. However, the album did not match the sales of its predecessor, failed to go gold, and marked the beginning of the band's second commercial decline. After touring for ''Revölution'', Rick Downey left, leaving Blue Öyster Cult without a drummer.

The band re-united with Albert Bouchard for a California tour in February 1985, infamously known as the &quot;Albert Returns&quot; Tour. This arrangement was only temporary, and caused more tensions between the band and Bouchard, as he had thought he would be staying on permanently, which was not the case. The band had only intended to use him as a last-minute fill-in until another drummer could come on board, which resulted in Bouchard's leaving after the tour. Allen Lanier also quit the band shortly thereafter, leaving the band without a keyboardist and with only three remaining original members. This incarnation of the band would sometimes be referred to as '3ÖC' by fans, a pun on the number of original members left.

Blue Öyster Cult hired drummer Jimmy Wilcox and keyboardist Tommy Zvoncheck to finish the album ''[[Club Ninja]]'', which was poorly received, with only &quot;Dancin' In the Ruins&quot;—one of several songs on the record written entirely by outside songwriters—enjoying minimal success on radio and [[MTV]]. The best-known original on the album is &quot;Perfect Water&quot; written by Dharma and [[Jim Carroll]] (noted author of ''[[The Basketball Diaries (book)|The Basketball Diaries]]''). While the band members have generally been disparaging about the album in retrospect, Joe Bouchard has stated that &quot;Perfect Water&quot; is &quot;perfect genius.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Blue Öyster Cult: Secrets Revealed!|last1=Popoff|first1=Martin|date=March 2009|publisher=Power Chord Press|isbn=978-0-9752807-0-6|edition=2|location=[[Toronto]], Ontario, Canada|page=218|chapter=Club Ninja|authorlink1=Martin Popoff}}&lt;!--| accessdate = 2012-03-17 --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

The band toured in Germany, after which bassist Bouchard left, leaving only two members of the classic lineup, Eric Bloom and Donald Roeser—some referred to the band as &quot;Two Öyster Cult&quot; during this period. Jon Rogers was hired to replace Joe, and this version of the band finished out the 1986 tour. After the tour wound up that year, the band took a temporary break from recording and touring.[[File:Blue Öyster Cult Sweden Rock 2008.jpg|thumb|Blue Öyster Cult performing at the [[Sweden Rock Festival]], 2008.]] When Blue Öyster Cult received an offer to tour in Greece in the early summer of 1987, the band reformed. Allen Lanier had agreed to rejoin, so the new line-up now featured three founding members, along with Jon Rogers returning on bass, and Ron Riddle as the band's newest drummer.

[[Columbia Records]] was not interested in releasing the ''[[Imaginos]]'' project as an Albert Bouchard solo album, so it was arranged for it to be released in 1988 by Columbia as a Blue Öyster Cult album, with some new lead vocal overdubs from Bloom and Roeser and lead guitar overdubs from Roeser. These replaced most of Albert Bouchard's lead vocals, as well as many lead guitar parts that had been recorded by session musicians. Joe Bouchard and Allen Lanier had earlier contributed some minor keyboard and backing vocal parts to the album, allowing all 5 original members to be credited. The album did not sell well (despite a positive review in ''Rolling Stone'' magazine), and though the then-current Blue Öyster Cult lineup (minus both Bouchard brothers) did tour to promote ''Imaginos'', promotion by the label was virtually non-existent. When Columbia Records' parent company CBS Records was purchased by [[Sony]] and became [[Sony Music Entertainment]], Blue Öyster Cult were dropped from the label.

=== 1990s and early 2000s ===
The band spent the next 11 years touring without releasing an album of new material, though they did contribute two new songs to the ''[[Bad Channels]]'' movie soundtrack, released in 1992, and also released an album of re-recorded songs from the band's original lineup called ''[[Cult Classic]]'' in 1994. During these years, while the three original members remained constant, there were several changes in the band's rhythm section. Ron Riddle quit in 1991 and was followed by a series of other drummers including
[[Chuck Burgi]] (1991–1992, 1992–1995, 1996–1997), [[John Miceli]] (1992, 1995), John O'Reilly (1995–1996) and [[Bobby Rondinelli]] (1997–2004). As for the bass position, Rogers left in 1995, and was replaced by Danny Miranda.

[[File:Blue Öyster Cult 2012 Edmonton 223b.JPG|thumb|right|Blue Öyster Cult performs in [[Edmonton|Edmonton, Alberta]], Canada on August 18, 2012.]]
In the late 1990s, Blue Öyster Cult secured a recording contract with CMC Records (later purchased by [[Sanctuary Records]]), and continued to tour frequently. Two studio albums were released, ''[[Heaven Forbid]]'' (1998) and ''[[Curse of the Hidden Mirror]]'' (2001). Both albums featured songs co-written by cyberpunk/horror novelist [[John Shirley]]. The first mostly featured Miranda on bass and Burgi on drums, though a few tracks feature earliest bassist Jon Rogers and one track features Rondinelli on drums, who had joined the band near the end of the recording. ''Curse of the Hidden Mirror'' features Miranda and Rondinelli as the rhythm section, and the pair contributed to the songwriting as well. Neither album sold well.

Another live record, ''[[A Long Day's Night]]'' and DVD (same title), followed in 2002, both drawn from one concert in Chicago. This album also featured the Bloom, Roeser, Lanier, Miranda, Rondinelli lineup.

Although the band's lineup had remained stable from 1997 to 2004, they began to experience personnel changes again in 2004. Rondinelli left in 2004, and was replaced by Jules Radino. Miranda left during the same year and ended up as the bassist for [[Queen + Paul Rodgers]]. He was replaced by Richie Castellano, who would also take occasional turns as a lead vocalist onstage.

In 2001, Sony/Columbia's reissue arm, [[Legacy Records]] issued expanded versions of the first four Blue Öyster Cult studio albums, including some previously unreleased demos and outtakes from album sessions, live recordings (from the ''Live 72'' EP), and post-St. Cecilia tunes from the Stalk-Forrest Group era.

[[File:Allenlanier.JPG|right|thumb|Blue Öyster Cult live in 2006]]

=== Recent events ===
Allen Lanier retired from live performances in 2007 after not appearing with the band since late 2006. Castellano switched to rhythm guitar and keyboards (Castellano also filled in on lead guitar and vocals for an ailing Buck Dharma in two shows in 2005), and the position of bassist was taken up by [[Rudy Sarzo]] (previously a member of [[Quiet Riot]], [[Whitesnake]], [[Ozzy Osbourne]] and [[Dio (band)|Dio]]), with the band employing Danny Miranda and Jon Rogers as guest bassists to fill in when Sarzo was unavailable. Sarzo then joined as an official member of the band, although Rogers continued to occasionally fill in when Sarzo was busy.

In February 2007, the Sony Legacy remaster series continued, releasing expanded versions of studio album ''[[Spectres (album)|Spectres]]'' and live album ''[[Some Enchanted Evening (Blue Öyster Cult album)|Some Enchanted Evening]]''.

In June 2012, the band announced that bassist [[Rudy Sarzo]] was leaving the band and was being replaced by former [[Utopia (American band)|Utopia]] bassist [[Kasim Sulton]].

In August of the same year, it was announced that Sony Legacy would be releasing a 17-disc boxed set entitled ''The Complete Columbia Albums Collection'' on October 30, 2012. The set includes the first round of the remastered series plus the long-awaited remastered versions of ''On Your Feet or on Your Knees'' (1975), ''[[Mirrors (Blue Öyster Cult album)|Mirrors]]'', ''[[Cultösaurus Erectus]]'', ''[[Fire Of Unknown Origin]]'', ''[[Extraterrestrial Live]]'', ''[[The Revölution by Night]]'', ''[[Club Ninja]]'' and ''[[Imaginos]]''. Also exclusive to this set are two discs of rare and unreleased B-sides, demos and radio broadcasts.

Also in 2012, celebrating the 40th anniversary of Blue Öyster Cult, the then-current incarnation of the band reunited for the first time in 25 years with other original members Joe and Albert Bouchard and Allen Lanier as guests for a special event in New York.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://ultimateclassicrock.com/original-blue-oyster-cult-lineup-reunites-new-york-city/|title=Original Blue Oyster Cult Lineup Reunites in New York City|website=Ultimate Classic Rock|language=en|access-date=2018-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Founding keyboardist/guitarist Allen Lanier died of [[chronic obstructive pulmonary disease]] on August 14, 2013.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.noise11.com/news/allen-lanier-of-blue-oyster-cult-dead-at-66-20130815 Allen Lanier of Blue Oyster Cult Dead At 66 | News | Music News]. Noise11 (2013-08-15). Retrieved on 2013-09-03.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2016, Albert Bouchard played again as guest with the current line-up of the band, playing at shows in New York, Los Angeles, Dublin and London, where BÖC played the album ''Agents of Fortune'' in its entirety. The shows featured songs from ''Agents of Fortune'' that had either not been played live before (&quot;True Confessions&quot;, &quot;The Revenge of Vera Gemini&quot;, &quot;Sinful Love&quot;, &quot;Tenderloin&quot;, &quot;Debbie Denise&quot;), songs that had not been played since the album's debut tour (&quot;Morning Final&quot;), and songs that were either no longer or never were played frequently (&quot;This Ain't the Summer of Love&quot;, &quot;Tattoo Vampire&quot;), as well as the fan favorite &quot;Five Guitars&quot;, which had not been played since Albert initially left the band in 1981. Albert played in the following songs at the show: &quot;The Revenge of Vera Gemini&quot; (vocals, guitar), &quot;Sinful Love&quot; (vocals, guitar), &quot;Tattoo Vampire&quot; (guitar), &quot;Morning Final&quot; (guitar), &quot;Tenderloin&quot; (cymbals), &quot;Debbie Denise&quot; (vocals, acoustic guitar), &quot;Cities on Flame with Rock and Roll&quot; (vocals, drums), and &quot;Five Guitars&quot; (guitar).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://getreadytorock.me.uk/blog/2016/07/gig-review-blue-oyster-cult-kentish-town-forum-29-july-2016/|title=Gig review: BLUE OYSTER CULT – Kentish Town Forum, London, 29 July 2016|work=Get Ready to ROCK! News {{!}} Reviews {{!}} Interviews {{!}} Radio|access-date=2018-03-13|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a May 2017 appearance on Castellano's &quot;Band Geek&quot; podcast, Bloom confirmed that there were tentative plans to release a new album in 2018 and that the band was currently considering offers from multiple record labels. He also stated that former bassist Danny Miranda would be playing with the band for the remainder of the year due to Sulton's prior touring commitments with [[Todd Rundgren]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://riotcast.com/bandgeek|title=Band Geek|website=riotcast.com|access-date=2017-01-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; The band's official website has since started to list Miranda as an official member, stating that Miranda had &quot;returned to BÖC&quot; in early 2017.

Buck Dharma stated in February 2019 that the band would be recording a new album to be released by fall.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.themidlandsrocks.com/blue-oyster-cults-buck-dharma-interview-ahead-of-uk-tour/|title=Blue Oyster Cult's Buck Dharma interview ahead of UK tour |website=Themidlandsrocks.com|accessdate=October 17, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; On July 10, 2019, it was announced that the band had signed to Frontiers Music, and would in fact be releasing the new album in 2020. &quot;It's been a long time since BÖC's last studio album. Recording with Danny, Richie and Jules should be a great experience as we've been touring together for years, and Buck and I look forward to including them in the creative and recording process,&quot; said Bloom. &quot;The current band is GREAT and has never been recorded other than live, so we feel now's the time for new songs to be written and recorded. About half of the songs for the new record exist and the rest will be finished during the process,&quot; added Buck Dharma.

== Musical style ==
Blue Öyster Cult is a [[hard rock]] band, whose music has been described as [[Heavy metal music|heavy metal]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.artistwd.com/joyzine/music/boc/boc.php|title=JoyZine - Interview with Blue Öyster Cult by Melissa Bennett|last=Design|first=Joy Williams—Artist Web|website=Artistwd.com|language=en|access-date=2018-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[psychedelic rock]], [[occult rock]], biker boogie, [[acid rock]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Secret History of Rock 'n' Roll|last=Christopher|first=Knowles|date=2010|publisher=Viva Editions|isbn=9781573445641|edition=1st|location=Berkeley, Calif.|pages=200|oclc=748093098}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[progressive rock]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Blue Oyster Cult, Secrets Revealed!|last=Popoff|first=Martin|publisher=Metal Blade Records, Inc.|year=2004|isbn=0-9752807-0-8|location=|page=37}}&lt;/ref&gt; They have also been recognized for helping pioneer genres such as [[Stoner rock|stoner metal]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.allmusic.com/style/stoner-metal-ma0000011961|title=Stoner Metal Music Genre Overview {{!}} AllMusic|website=AllMusic|access-date=2018-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[speed metal]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.altx.com/int2/john.shirley.html|title=An Interview with John Shirley|website=Altx.com|access-date=2018-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The band has also experimented with additional genres on specific albums. An example of this is [[Mirrors (Blue Öyster Cult album)|Mirrors]] (1979), which is primarily a [[power pop]] record.

The band is influenced by artists such as [[Alice Cooper]],&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; [[Grateful Dead]], [[The Doors]], [[Jefferson Airplane]], [[MC5]],&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; [[The Blues Project]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.vintageguitar.com/2830/buck-dharma/|title=Buck Dharma|last=Moseley|first=Willie G.|date=2001-10-10|work=Vintage Guitar® magazine|access-date=2018-05-23|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jimi Hendrix]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ram.org/music/articles/dharmainterview.html|title=Interview with Buck Dharma of Blue Öyster Cult|website=Ram.org|access-date=2018-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Black Sabbath]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

While Blue Öyster Cult has been noted for heavy rock, they would often add their own tongue-in-cheek style.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; Keeping with their image, the band would often include out-of-context fragments of Pearlman's ''The Soft Doctrines of Imaginos'' into their lyrics, giving their songs cryptic meanings.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; Additionally, the band would keep a folder of Meltzer's and Pearlman's word associations to insert into their music.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Blue Öyster Cult|last=Lenny|first=Kaye|publisher=Sony Music Corporation|year=2001|isbn=|location=|pages=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Band name and logo==
[[File:Hook-and-cross white.svg|thumb|upright=0.5|The hook-and-cross logo]]
[[File:Saturn symbol.svg|thumb|upright=0.5|One variant of the [[lead]] symbol in [[alchemy]], also used to represent the planet [[Planets in astrology|Saturn]] in [[astrology]]]]
The name &quot;Blue Öyster Cult&quot; came from a 1960s poem written by manager [[Sandy Pearlman]]. It was part of his &quot;Imaginos&quot; poetry, later used more extensively on their album ''[[Imaginos]]'' (1988). Pearlman had also come up with the band's earlier name, &quot;Soft White Underbelly&quot;, from a phrase used by [[Winston Churchill]] in describing [[Italy]] during [[World War II]]. In Pearlman's poetry, the &quot;Blue Oyster Cult&quot; was a group of aliens who had assembled to secretly guide Earth's history. &quot;Initially, the band was not happy with the name, but settled for it, and went to work preparing to record their first release...&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;blueoystercult.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blueoystercult.com/History/history3.html |title=The History of BÖC |publisher=Blueoystercult.com |date= |accessdate=2010-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 1976 interview published in the U.K. music magazine ''[[ZigZag (magazine)|ZigZag]]'', Pearlman told the story explaining the origin of the band's name was an anagram of &quot;Cully Stout Beer&quot;.

The addition of an [[Diaeresis (diacritic)|umlaut]] was suggested by [[Allen Lanier]], but rock critic [[Richard Meltzer]] claims to have suggested it just after Pearlman came up with the name, reportedly &quot;because of the [[Wagnerian rock|Wagnerian]] aspect of Metal&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rateyourmusic.com/lists/list_view?list_id=35734&amp;show=25&amp;start=25 |title=Why are they called Duran Duran? A guide to band name etymologies |publisher=Rate Your Music | accessdate=2013-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other bands later copied [[Metal umlaut|the practice of using umlauts or diacritic marks]] in their own band names, such as [[Motörhead]], [[Mötley Crüe]], [[Queensrÿche]] and parodied by [[Spinal Tap (band)|Spın̈al Tap]].&lt;ref name=&quot;faq&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://members.aol.com/bocfaqman/boc_faq.html|title=BOC FAQ|date=2001-12-10|author=John Swartz|accessdate=2007-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The hook-and-cross logo was designed by Bill Gawlik&lt;ref name=&quot;ecfjhn&quot;/&gt; in January 1972,&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blueoystercult.com/History/history4.html |title=The History of BÖC |publisher=Blueoystercult.com |date= |accessdate=2010-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; and appears on all of the band's albums.&lt;ref name=faq/&gt; In Greek mythology, &quot;... the hook-and-cross symbol is that of [[Cronus|Kronos (Cronus)]], the king of the Titans and father of Zeus ... and is the alchemical symbol for [[lead]] (a [[Heavy metal (chemistry)|heavy metal]]), one of the heaviest of metals.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dinesh.com/history_of_logos/rock_band_logos/blue_oyster_cult_logo_-_design_and_history.html |title=Blue Oyster Cult Logo – Design and History |publisher=Dinesh.com |date=2010-08-25 |accessdate=2010-09-23 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100731020016/http://www.dinesh.com/history_of_logos/rock_band_logos/blue_oyster_cult_logo_-_design_and_history.html |archivedate=2010-07-31 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Sandy Pearlman considered this, combined with the heavy and distorted guitar sound of the band and decided the description &quot;[[Heavy metal music|heavy metal]]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;The term &quot;heavy metal&quot; was first used by [[Mike Saunders]] in 1970.[http://www.headheritage.co.uk/unsung/albumofthemonth/1430]&lt;/ref&gt; would be aptly applied to Blue Öyster Cult's musical sound. The hook-and-cross symbol also resembled the astrological symbol for [[Planets in astrology|Saturn]], the Roman god of agriculture,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.loggia.com/myth/saturn.html |title=Mythography &amp;#124; The Roman god Saturn in Myth and Art |publisher=Loggia.com |accessdate=2010-09-23 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101209084719/http://www.loggia.com/myth/saturn.html# |archive-date=2010-12-09 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[sickle]], which is associated with both Kronos (Cronus) and Saturn (both the [[Saturn|planet]] and the Roman god).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wordsources.info/saturn.html |title=Saturn, Roman god of the harvest and a planet |publisher=Wordsources.info |date= |accessdate=2010-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The logo's &quot;... metaphysical, alchemical and mythological connotations, combined with its similarity to some religious symbols gave it a flair of decadence and mystery ...&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

The band was billed, for the only time, as &quot;''The'' Blue Öyster Cult&quot; on the cover and label of their second album, ''[[Tyranny and Mutation]]''.

==Legacy and influence==
Blue Öyster Cult have been influential to the realm of hard rock and heavy metal, leading them to being referred to as “the thinking man’s heavy metal band” due to their often cryptic lyrics, literate songwriting, and links to famous authors.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Blue Oyster Cult: Secrets Revealed!|last=Popoff|first=Martin|date=2004|publisher=Metal Blade Records|isbn=0975280708|location=Simi Valley, CA|page=181|oclc=263055280}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Encyclopedia of Heavy Metal|last=Daniel.|first=Bukszpan|date=2003|publisher=Barnes &amp; Noble Books|isbn=0760742189|location=New York|page=24|oclc=51804645}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allmusic.com/artist/blue-%25C3yster-cult-mn0000061938/biography|title=Blue Öyster Cult {{!}} Biography &amp; History {{!}} AllMusic|website=AllMusic|access-date=2017-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; They have influenced many acts including [[Iron Maiden]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://thequietus.com/articles/10360-iron-maiden-steve-harris-interview|title=The Quietus {{!}} Features {{!}} A Quietus Interview {{!}} Iron Lion Scion: Steve Harris Interviewed|work=The Quietus|access-date=2017-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Metallica]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.inquisitr.com/opinion/4317001/metallicas-lars-ulrich-favorite-albums-and-influences/|title=Metallica's Lars Ulrich Favorite Albums And Influences [Opinion]|date=2017-06-23|work=The Inquisitr|access-date=2017-09-29|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thrashermagazine.com/articles/music-interviews/metallica-interview/|title=Thrasher Magazine - Metallica Interview|website=Thrashermagazine.com|language=en|access-date=2017-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Fates Warning]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://fateswarning.com/2013/11/20/an-interview-with-fates-warning-searching-for-a-different-light-11202013/|title=An Interview with Fates Warning: Searching For A Different Light (11/20/2013)|work=Fates Warning|access-date=2017-09-29|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Iced Earth]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.wikimetal.com.br/site/interview-with-jon-schaffer-iced-earth/|title=Interview with Jon Schaffer (Iced Earth)|date=2012-02-16|work=Wikimetal - ROCK &amp; METAL LEVADO A SÉRIO|access-date=2017-09-29|language=pt-BR}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cirith Ungol (band)|Cirith Ungol]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://clrvynt.com/cirith-ungol-interview/|title=Proto-Doom Heroes Cirith Ungol Take a Giant Step Out of Hell|first=Chris|last=Corry|website=CLRVYNT}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Alice in Chains]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allmusic.com/artist/alice-in-chains-mn0000007920/related|title=Alice in Chains {{!}} Influenced By {{!}} AllMusic|last=|first=|date=|website=AllMusic|access-date=2017-09-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Twisted Sister]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allmusic.com/artist/twisted-sister-mn0000165663/related|title=Twisted Sister {{!}} Influenced By {{!}} AllMusic|last=|first=|date=|website=AllMusic|access-date=2017-09-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ratt]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.knac.com/article.asp?ArticleID=23163|title=KNAC.COM - Features - Exclusive Interview: STEPHEN PEARCY|website=Knac.com|access-date=2017-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://musicexistence.com/blog/2017/01/13/interview-stephen-pearcy-on-new-album-smash-and-ratt-reunion/|title=Interview: Stephen Pearcy on new album 'Smash' and Ratt reunion – Music Existence|website=musicexistence.com|language=en-US|access-date=2017-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Steel Panther]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.premierguitar.com/articles/Interview_Steel_Panthers_Satchel?page=2|title=Interview: Steel Panther's Satchel|access-date=2017-09-29|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Green River (band)|Green River]] (and later [[Mudhoney]]),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.allmusic.com/album/rehab-doll-mw0000854412|title=Rehab Doll - Green River {{!}} Songs, Reviews, Credits {{!}} AllMusic|website=AllMusic|access-date=2018-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Body Count (band)|Body Count]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theaquarian.com/2014/07/30/an-interview-with-ice-t-from-body-count-cold-metal/|title=An Interview with Ice-T from Body Count: Cold Metal|website=The Aquarian|language=en-US|access-date=2017-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Possessed (band)|Possessed]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=mBlbAwAAQBAJ&amp;q=Possessed#v=twopage&amp;q=possessed&amp;f=false|title=Metallica: Justice for All (New Revised Edition)|last=McIver|first=Joel|date=2014-06-16|publisher=Omnibus Press|isbn=9781783231232|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Candlemass (band)|Candlemass]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrrecords.de/high_roller/sites/release_detail.php?relno=155|title=CANDLEMASS - Don't Fear The Reaper 12|website=Hrrecords.de|access-date=2017-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Saint Vitus (band)|Saint Vitus]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.roomthirteen.com/features/1105/Saint_Vitus_Interview.html|title=- Saint Vitus Interview - RoomThirteen - Online Rock Metal Alternative Music Magazine - Reviews Interviews News Tours|website=Roomthirteen.com|language=en|access-date=2017-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Trouble (band)|Trouble]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.prog-nose.org/metal-nose/engels/interviews/wet_animal.htm|title=Wet Animal|date=2016-08-03|access-date=2017-09-29|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160803031458/http://www.prog-nose.org/metal-nose/engels/interviews/wet_animal.htm|archivedate=2016-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Opeth]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.heavyhardes.de/interview-402.html|title=Opeth - Interview - Heavyhardes.de|last=Fall|first=Thorsten|website=Heavyhardes.de|access-date=2017-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[White Zombie (band)|White Zombie]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://film.list.co.uk/article/32670-shock-rocker-and-horror-film-director-rob-zombie-full-interview-transcript/|title=Shock rocker and horror film director Rob Zombie - full interview transcript|date=2011-02-15|work=The List|access-date=2017-09-29|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kvelertak]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://noisecreep.com/kvelertak-meir-interview/|title=Kvelertak Frontman on Their Upcoming Album, Norwegian Trolls + Dave Grohl|website=Noisecreep|language=en-US|access-date=2017-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://newnoisemagazine.com/kvelertak-on-signing-with-roadrunner-records-and-their-debut-album-by-brandon-ringo/#|title=Kvelertak on signing with Roadrunner Records and their debut album - By Brandon Ringo - New Noise Magazine|date=2013-03-19|work=New Noise Magazine|access-date=2017-09-29|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[HIM (Finnish band)|HIM]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oocities.org/himdiaboli/interview.htm|title=Our Diabolikal Rapture - Interviews|last=Éva|first=Darabos|website=Oocities.org|access-date=2017-09-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Turbonegro]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allmusic.com/artist/turbonegro-mn0000806740/related|title=Turbonegro {{!}} Influenced By {{!}} AllMusic|last=|first=|date=|website=AllMusic|access-date=2017-09-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Radio Birdman]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://ilikeyouroldstuff.com/blog/hanging-on-an-interview-with-radio-birdmans-deniz-tek|title=HANGING ON: AN INTERVIEW WITH RADIO BIRDMAN's DENIZ TEK|date=2017-04-02|work=I Like Your old stuff|access-date=2017-09-29|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://magazine.100percentrock.com/interviews/201411/86122|title=INTERVIEW – Rob Younger, Radio Birdman – October 2014|date=2014-11-06|work=100% ROCK MAGAZINE|access-date=2017-09-29|language=en-US|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170930041143/http://magazine.100percentrock.com/interviews/201411/86122#|archive-date=2017-09-30|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[The Cult]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/music/2016/mar/24/primal-scream-cult-ultravox-bands-change-direction|title='People started punching the air': how Primal Scream, Ministry, the Cult and Misty Miller reinvented their sound|last=Simpson|first=Dave|date=2016-03-24|work=The Guardian|access-date=2017-09-29|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Minutemen (band)|The Minutemen]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dementlieu.com/users/obik/arc/other/mmen_tn10.html|title=Dementlieu Punk Archive: Minutemen interview|website=Dementlieu.com|access-date=2017-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Firehose (band)|Firehose]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allmusic.com/artist/firehose-mn0000143749/related|title=fIREHOSE {{!}} Influenced By {{!}} AllMusic|last=|first=|date=|website=AllMusic|access-date=2017-09-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hoodoo Gurus]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.smh.com.au/entertainment/music/reaping-their-rewards-20130411-2hnsz.html|title=Reaping their rewards|last=Dwyer|first=Michael|date=2013-04-12|work=The Sydney Morning Herald|access-date=2017-09-29|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Widespread Panic]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jambands.com/features/2013/05/13/tossing-the-ball-with-dave-schools-ten-years-on|title=Tossing The Ball with Dave Schools (Ten Years On)|website=Jambands.com|access-date=2017-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Queens of the Stone Age]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allmusic.com/artist/queens-of-the-stone-age-mn0000376422/related|title=Queens of the Stone Age {{!}} Influenced By {{!}} AllMusic|last=|first=|date=|website=AllMusic|access-date=2017-09-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Umphrey's McGee]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bassmusicianmagazine.com/2011/01/progressive-rock-with-brad-houser-umphreys-mcgees-mantis-bassist-ryan-stasik/|title=Progressive Rock With Brad Houser: Umphrey's McGee Bassist Ryan Stasik|website=bassmusicianmagazine.com|language=en-US|access-date=2017-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Stabbing Westward]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.concertlivewire.com/interviews/stabbing.htm|title=One on One - Stabbing Westward|website=Concertlivewire.com|access-date=2017-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Royal Trux]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.chicagoreader.com/Bleader/archives/2015/06/03/a-wide-ranging-interview-with-neil-michael-hagerty-and-jennifer-herrema-of-royal-trux|title=A wide-ranging interview with Neil Michael Hagerty and Jennifer Herrema of Royal Trux|last=Dugan|first=John|work=Chicago Reader|access-date=2017-09-29|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Moe (band)|Moe]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allmusic.com/artist/moe-mn0000574143/related|title=moe. {{!}} Influenced By {{!}} AllMusic|last=|first=|date=|website=AllMusic|access-date=2017-09-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The band's influence has extended beyond the musical sphere. The lyrics of &quot;Astronomy&quot; have been named by author Shawn St. Jean as inspirational to the later chapters of his fantasy novel ''Clotho's Loom'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://clothosloom.wordpress.com/2012/09/20/intertwining-high-culture-and-low-culture/ &quot;Intertwining High and Low Culture&quot;].  Clotho's Loom.  Retrieved 2013-05-03.&lt;/ref&gt; wherein Sandy Pearlman's &quot;Four Winds Bar&quot; provides the setting for a portion of the action.Titles and lines from the band's songs provided structure and narrative for the third Robert Galbraith (pseudonym for [[J. K. Rowling]]) novel – ''[[Career of Evil]]'' (a Cormoran Strike novel).&lt;ref name=&quot;Strike&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hypable.com/cormoran-strike-book-3-title/|title=J.K. Rowling's third Cormoran Strike novel titled 'Career of Evil' arrives this fall|last1=Sims|first1=Andrew|date=24 April 2015|website=Hypable|accessdate=9 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GuardianBOD&quot;&gt;Christobel Kent, [https://www.theguardian.com/books/2015/oct/21/career-of-evil-by-robert-galbraith-review Career of Evil by Robert Galbraith review – a daft but enjoyable hunt for a serial killer], The Guardian, 21 October 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

Their hit single &quot;(Don't Fear) The Reaper&quot; was featured in the famous ''Saturday Night Live'' sketch, &quot;[[More cowbell]]&quot;. The original recording was produced at The Record Plant in New York by [[David Lucas (producer)|David Lucas]], who sang background vocals with Roeser and played the now famous cowbell part.

&quot;(Don't Fear) The Reaper&quot; was also used in writer/director [[John Carpenter]]'s horror film classic, ''[[Halloween (1978 film)|Halloween]]'' (1978),&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=Halloween (1978)|url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0077651/soundtrack|accessdate=2018-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; the opening sequence of the miniseries adaptation of ''[[The Stand (1994 miniseries)|The Stand]]'' (1994) by [[Stephen King]], and covered by [[The Mutton Birds]] for [[Peter Jackson]]'s horror-comedy film ''[[The Frighteners]]'' (1996).&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=The Frighteners (1996)|url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0116365/soundtrack|accessdate=2018-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;(Don't Fear) The Reaper&quot; was also used throughout the comedy film ''[[The Stoned Age]]'' (1994) and plays a role in its storyline. The song was also featured as the opening theme and main story element in the 1996 FMV computer game &quot;Ripper&quot;, by Take Two Interactive.

==Members==
{{main|List of Blue Öyster Cult members}}
'''Current members'''
* [[Buck Dharma]]&amp;nbsp;– [[lead guitar]], [[singing|vocals]] (1967–present)
* [[Eric Bloom]]&amp;nbsp;– [[lead vocals]], [[guitar|stun guitar]], [[Keyboard instrument|keyboards]], synthesizers (1969–present)
* Danny Miranda&amp;nbsp;– [[bass guitar|bass]], [[backing vocals]] (1995–2004, 2017–present)
* [[Richie Castellano]]&amp;nbsp;– keyboards, [[rhythm guitar]], backing vocals (2007–present), bass (2004–2007)
* Jules Radino&amp;nbsp;– [[drum kit|drums]], [[percussion instrument|percussion]] (2004–present)

==Lyrics==
During their career, Blue Öyster Cult have frequently collaborated with outside lyricists, though in the late 70's, the band members also wrote lyrics for some of their songs. Lyricists for Blue Öyster Cult have included all the original members (Bloom, Roeser, Albert &amp; Joe Bouchard, and Lanier), producer Sandy Pearlman, and writers [[Richard Meltzer]], [[Patti Smith]], [[Michael Moorcock]], [[Eric Van Lustbader]], [[Jim Carroll]], Broadway Blotto and [[John Shirley]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blueoystercult.com/Band-main.html| title=The Band: Blue Oyster Cult Today|access-date=2020-02-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://dangerousminds.net/comments/patti_smiths_career_of_evil_with_blue_yster_cult| title=Patti Smith's Career of Evil with Blue Öyster Cult|access-date=2020-02-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Discography==
{{Main|Blue Öyster Cult discography}}

* ''[[Blue Öyster Cult (album)|Blue Öyster Cult]]'' (1972)
* ''[[Tyranny and Mutation]]'' (1973)
* ''[[Secret Treaties]]'' (1974)
* ''[[Agents of Fortune]]'' (1976)
* ''[[Spectres (album)|Spectres]]'' (1977)
* ''[[Mirrors (Blue Öyster Cult album)|Mirrors]]'' (1979)
* ''[[Cultösaurus Erectus]]'' (1980)
* ''[[Fire of Unknown Origin]]'' (1981)
* ''[[The Revölution by Night]]'' (1983)
* ''[[Club Ninja]]'' (1985)
* ''[[Imaginos]]'' (1988)
* ''[[Heaven Forbid]]'' (1998)
* ''[[Curse of the Hidden Mirror]]'' (2001)

==Music videos==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! style=&quot;background:#ccc;&quot;| Year
! style=&quot;background:#ccc;&quot;| Title
|-
|rowspan=&quot;3&quot;| 1981
| &quot;The Marshall Plan&quot;
|-
| &quot;[[Burnin' for You]]&quot;
|-
| &quot;[[Joan Crawford (song)|Joan Crawford]]&quot;
|-
|rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|1983
| &quot;[[Take Me Away (Blue Öyster Cult song)|Take Me Away]]&quot;
|-
| &quot;[[Shooting Shark]]&quot;
|-
| 1986
| &quot;[[Dancin' in the Ruins]]&quot;
|-
| 1988
| &quot;[[Astronomy (song)|Astronomy]]&quot;
|}

==Bibliography==
* ''BLUE ÖYSTER CULT: Secrets Revealed!'', by Martin Popoff, 303&amp;nbsp;pages (Canada, 2009)
* ''BLUE ÖYSTER CULT: La Carrière du mal'', by Mathieu Bollon and Aurélien Lemant, Camion Blanc publishing, 722 pages (France, 2013)

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==

{{commons|Blue Oyster Cult}}
*{{Official website}}
*{{Curlie|Arts/Music/Bands_and_Artists/B/Blue_Öyster_Cult/}}

{{Blue Öyster Cult|status=uncollapsed}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Blue Oyster Cult}}
[[Category:Blue Öyster Cult| ]]
[[Category:1967 establishments in New York (state)]]
[[Category:Articles which contain graphical timelines]]
[[Category:Columbia Records artists]]
[[Category:Hard rock musical groups from New York (state)]]
[[Category:Heavy metal musical groups from New York (state)]]
[[Category:Musical groups established in 1967]]
[[Category:Musical groups from Long Island]]
[[Category:Musical quintets]]
[[Category:Occult rock musical groups]]
[[Category:Psychedelic rock music groups from New York (state)]]</text>
      <sha1>d5lfytwtcsdk2yldtau372kz185q5pp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
