  <page>
    <title>Bank of China Tower (Hong Kong)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4568</id>
    <revision>
      <id>935209125</id>
      <parentid>935209120</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-11T05:33:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contribs/203.186.21.103|203.186.21.103]] to version by Citobun. [[WP:CBFP|Report False Positive?]] Thanks, [[WP:CBNG|ClueBot NG]]. (3689192) (Bot)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Skyscraper in Central, Hong Kong}}
{{distinguish|Bank of China Building (Hong Kong)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2011}}
{{Use Hong Kong English|date=December 2018}}
{{Infobox building
|name               = Bank of China Tower 
|native_name        = 中銀大廈
|image              = File:HK Bank of China Tower View.jpg
|location           = 1 [[Garden Road, Hong Kong|Garden Road]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Central, Hong Kong|Central]], [[Hong Kong]] 
|coordinates        = {{coord|22|16|45|N|114|09|41|E|region:HK|display=inline,title}}
|status             = Complete
|start_date         = 18 April 1985
|completion_date    = 1990
|opening            = 17 May 1990
|building_type      = Commercial offices
|architectural      = {{convert|367.4|m|ft|1|abbr=on}}
|roof               = {{convert|315.0|m|ft|1|abbr=on}}
|top_floor          = {{convert|288.3|m|ft|1|abbr=on}}
|floor_count        = 72 &lt;small&gt;(+4 basement floors)&lt;/small&gt;
|elevator_count     = 49
|cost               =
|floor_area         = {{convert|135000|m2|abbr=on}}
|architect          = [[I. M. Pei|I. M. Pei &amp; Partners]]&lt;br&gt; Sherman Kung &amp; Associates Architects Ltd. Thomas Boada S.L.
|structural_engineer=Leslie E. Robertson Associates RLLP
|main_contractor    = [[HKC (Holdings) Ltd]]&lt;br&gt;Kumagai HK
|developer          =
|owner              =
|management         =
|references         = &lt;ref name=skyscraperCenter&gt;{{ctbuh|287}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=skyscraperpage&gt;{{skyscraperpage|13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=emporis&gt;{{emporis|120582}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{structurae|20000093}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
{{Infobox Chinese
|title=Bank of China Tower
|t=中銀大廈
|s=中银大厦
|showflag=y
|y=Jūngngán Daaihhah
|ci={{IPAc-yue|z|ung|1|.|ng|an|2|-|d|aai|6|.|h|aa|6}}
|j=Zung1ngan2 Daai6haa6
|p=Zhōngyín Dàshà
}}
The '''Bank of China Tower''' ({{Zh|t=中銀大廈|s=中银大厦|first=t}}), abbreviated the '''BOC Tower''', is a skyscraper located in [[Central, Hong Kong|Central]], [[Hong Kong]]. Located at 1 [[Garden Road, Hong Kong|Garden Road]] on Hong Kong Island, the tower houses the headquarters of the [[Bank of China (Hong Kong) Limited]].&lt;ref name=&quot;bochk&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bochk.com/web/common/multi_section.xml?section=about&amp;level_2=boc_tower&amp;fldr_id=326 |title=Bank of China (Hong Kong) Limited – About Us &gt; About BOC Tower &gt; Introduction |accessdate=8 November 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110105025749/http://www.bochk.com/web/common/multi_section.xml?section=about&amp;level_2=boc_tower&amp;fldr_id=326 |archivedate=5 January 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; One of the most recognisable landmarks in Hong Kong, the building is notable for its distinct shape and design, consisting of triangular frameworks covered by glass curtain walls.

The building was designed by Chinese-American architect [[I. M. Pei]] and L.C Pei of I.M Pei and Partners. At a height of  {{convert|315.0|m|ft|1|abbr=on}}, reaching {{convert|367.4|m|1|abbr=on}} high including masts&lt;ref name=&quot;bochk&quot; /&gt;, the building is the fourth tallest skyscraper in Hong Kong, after [[International Commerce Centre]], [[Two International Finance Centre]] and [[Central Plaza (Hong Kong)|Central Plaza]]. It was the [[List of tallest buildings in Hong Kong|tallest building in Hong Kong]] and Asia from 1989 to 1992, and it was the first [[supertall skyscraper]] outside the United States, the first to break the 305 m (1,000&amp;nbsp;ft) mark. It was surpassed by [[Central Plaza (Hong Kong)|Central Plaza]] on the same island in 1992. 

Construction began in 1985 on the former site of [[Murray House]], and was completed five years later in 1990. Sporting a steel-column design, the building is accessible from the MTR's [[Central station (MTR)|Central station]]. The building lies between [[Cotton Tree Drive]] and [[Garden Road, Hong Kong|Garden Road]]. 

==History==
=== Site===
The {{convert|6700|m2|abbr=on}} site on which the building is constructed was formerly the location of [[Murray House]]. After its brick-by-brick relocation to [[Stanley, Hong Kong|Stanley]], the site was sold by the Government for &quot;only HK$1 billion&quot; in August 1982 amidst growing concern over the future of Hong Kong in the run-up to the [[Transfer of sovereignty of Hong Kong|transfer of sovereignty]].

The building was initially built by the Hong Kong Branch of the Bank of China; its Garden Road entrance continues to display the name &quot;Bank of China&quot;, rather than BOCHK. The top four and the bottom 19 storeys are used by the Bank, while the other floors are leased out.&lt;!--from Chinese article --&gt; Ownership has since been transferred to BOCHK, although the Bank of China has leased back several floors for use by its own operations in Hong Kong.{{Citation needed|date=November 2007}}

===Favouritism controversy===
The Government had apparently given preferential treatment to Chinese companies, and was again criticised for the apparent preferential treatment to the BOCHK.&lt;ref name=&quot;dearfriends&quot; /&gt;

The price paid was half the amount of the 6,250 m² Admiralty II plot, for which the [[MTR Corporation]] paid HK$1.82 billion in cash. The BOC would make initial payment of $60 million, with the rest payable over 13 years at 6% interest. The announcement of the sale was also poorly handled, and a dive in business confidence ensued. The [[Hang Seng Index]] fell 80 points, and the [[Hong Kong dollar|HK$]] lost 1.5% of its value the next day.&lt;ref name=&quot;dearfriends&quot; /&gt;

=== Construction ===
[[File:HK-architecture-BOCHK-Bank-of-China-Building-under-construction-1988-00.jpg|thumb|left|The Bank of China Building under construction in 1988]]

The tower was built by Japanese contractor [[Kumagai Gumi]]. Superstructure work began in May 1986.&lt;ref name=&quot;checkon&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last1=Yu|first1=Lulu|title=Check on asbestos at China bank|work=South China Morning Post|date=24 November 1987|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The tower is a steel-frame structure. The spray-on fireproofing material applied to the steel structure, a product called Monokote MK-5, was a source of controversy as it contains asbestos.&lt;ref name=&quot;checkon&quot;/&gt; At the time, the use of asbestos was only partially banned in Hong Kong.

The [[Tiananmen Square protests of 1989]] interrupted publicity surrounding the building's design and construction. A press conference scheduled for 24 May 1989, two weeks before the massacre, was intended to show off the building's &quot;designer socialist furnishings&quot;, but was called off as the student demonstrations in [[Beijing]] escalated. The public relations firm that organised the conference explained to the ''South China Morning Post'' that &quot;under the circumstances, it has been decided to stop any publicity to do with the Bank of China.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;lowprofile&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Bank of China designers keeping a low profile|work=South China Morning Post|date=23 May 1989|page=8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Once developed, gross floor area was expected to be 100,000 m².&lt;ref name=&quot;dearfriends&quot;&gt;Philip Bowring &amp; Mary Lee, [http://sunzi1.lib.hku.hk/newspaper/view/25_01.02/19852.pdf Dear friends...], pg 114 ''[[Far Eastern Economic Review]]'', 13 August 1982&lt;/ref&gt; The original project was intended for completion on the [[Numbers in Chinese culture|auspicious]] date of 8 August 1988. However, owing to project delays, groundbreaking took place in March 1985, almost two years late. It was topped out in 1989, and occupied on 15 June 1990.&lt;!--from Chinese article --&gt;

== Design ==
[[File:Bank of China Tower massing model.svg|thumb|right|[[Massing]] model showing the shape of the Bank of China Tower. The labels correspond to the number of 'X' shapes on each outward facing side.]]

Designed by [[Pritzker Prize]]-winning architect [[I. M. Pei]], the building is {{convert|315.0|m|ft|1|abbr=on}} high with two masts reaching {{convert|367.4|m|ft|1|abbr=on}} high. The 72-storey building is located near [[Central (MTR)|Central MTR station]]. This was the tallest building in Hong Kong and Asia from 1990 to 1992, the first building outside the United States to break the 305 m (1,000&amp;nbsp;ft) mark, and the first composite [[space frame]] high-rise building. That also means it was the tallest outside the United States from its completion year, 1990. It is now the fourth tallest skyscraper in Hong Kong, after [[International Commerce Centre]], [[Two International Finance Centre]] and [[Central Plaza (Hong Kong)|Central Plaza]].

A small observation deck on the 43rd floor of the building was once open to the public,&lt;ref name=&quot;chec_Bank&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |title=Bank of China tower observation deck - Checkerboard Hill |author= |work=Checkerboard Hill |date= |access-date=13 March 2019 |url= https://www.checkerboardhill.com/2011/02/bank-of-china-tower-observation-deck/}}&lt;/ref&gt; but is now closed.&lt;ref name=&quot;thef_Hong&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |title=Hong Kong from high up: three buildings to explore {{!}} The Foreign Architect |author= |work=The Foreign Architect |date= |access-date=13 March 2019 |url= https://theforeignarchitect.com/hong-kong-high-three-buildings-explore/}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;trip_Obse&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |title=Observation deck closed - Bank of China Tower, Hong Kong Traveller Reviews - TripAdvisor |author= |work=TripAdvisor |date= |access-date=13 March 2019 |url= https://www.tripadvisor.com.au/ShowUserReviews-g294217-d590805-r548560157-Bank_of_China_Tower-Hong_Kong.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The whole structure is supported by the four steel columns at the corners of the building, with the triangular frameworks transferring the weight of the structure onto these four columns. It is covered with glass curtain walls.

While its distinctive look makes it one of Hong Kong's most identifiable landmarks today, it was the source of some controversy at one time, as the bank is the only major building in Hong Kong to have bypassed the convention of consulting with [[feng shui]] masters on matters of design prior to construction.

The building has been criticised by some practitioners of feng shui for its sharp edges and its negative symbolism by the numerous 'X' shapes in its original design, though Pei modified the design to some degree before construction following this feedback. The building's profile from some angles resembles that of a [[Cleaver (knife)|meat cleaver]] and it is sometimes referred to as a &quot;vertical knife&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.cnn.com/style/article/100-years-of-i-m-pei-bank-of-china/index.html|title=How I.M. Pei's Bank of China Tower changed Hong Kong's skyline|date=2017-12-21|work=CNN Style|access-date=2018-01-21|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; This earned it the nickname “一把刀” (Yaat Baa Dou) in Cantonese, literally meaning 'One Knife'.

==Transport==
The Bank Of China Tower can be accessed by the Mass Transit Railway (MTR) by walking through Chater Garden from [[Central Station (MTR)|Central Station]] Exit J2.

==In popular culture==
* In the 2012 film ''[[Battleship (film)|Battleship]]'', the building is torn in half by a crashing alien spaceship and its spire falls into the streets of Hong Kong, killing many people.
* In ''[[Star Trek: Voyager]]'', the building is used as the exterior of [http://en.memory-alpha.org/wiki/Starfleet_Communications Starfleet Communications] Research Center.
* The building in seen on the attraction [[It's a Small World]] at [[Hong Kong Disneyland]].
* The building was featured in the film ''[[Transformers: Age of Extinction]]'', where Bumblebee and Dinobot Strafe makes their final stand against the Decepticon drone Stinger.
* The building appears in ''[[Cardcaptor Sakura: The Movie]]'' for several scenes.

== See also ==
* [[Bank of China Building (Hong Kong)|Bank of China Building]], the old headquarters of the Bank of China
* [[List of tallest buildings in Hong Kong]]
* [[List of buildings and structures in Hong Kong]]
* [[List of tallest freestanding structures in the world]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Bank of China Tower}}
* [http://www.bochk.com/en/aboutus/corpprofile/boctower.html About BOC Tower] on Bank of China (Hong Kong) website
* [http://www.greatbuildings.com/buildings/Bank_of_China.html Great Buildings Online site on BOC Tower]
* [http://skyscrapermodels.us/models/Bank_China_HKC.html Buildable paper model of the tower]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090329054505/http://www.hku.hk/bse/bbse2001/lift-example02.gif Elevator Layout]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090220182116/http://www.bankofchinalocations.com/china/hong_kong_island_central_western_district.html Branch Details for Hong Kong Bank of China Tower]
{{Central, Hong Kong}}
{{Buildings in Hong Kong timeline}}
{{Hong Kong Skyscrapers}}
{{I. M. Pei}}
{{Supertall skyscrapers | current}}
{{Bank of China}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bank Of China Tower, Hong Kong}}
[[Category:A Symphony of Lights]]
[[Category:Bank buildings in Hong Kong]]
[[Category:Bank of China]]
[[Category:Central, Hong Kong]]
[[Category:I. M. Pei buildings]]
[[Category:Landmarks in Hong Kong]]
[[Category:Office buildings completed in 1990]]
[[Category:Skyscraper office buildings in Hong Kong]]</text>
      <sha1>jytr5ebm5f1ukurc1iqpjqtomlkzg3v</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
