  <page>
    <title>Bud Selig</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4582</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942567940</id>
      <parentid>931380225</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-25T13:34:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelink 1 book for [[Wikipedia:Verifiability|verifiability]]. [goog]) #IABot (v2.0) ([[User:GreenC bot|GreenC bot]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=June 2015}}
{{Infobox officeholder
|name=Bud Selig
|image=Bud Selig on October 31, 2010.jpg
|image_size=220px
|caption=Selig in October 2010
|birth_name=Allan Huber Selig
|birth_date={{birth date and age|mf=yes|1934|7|30}}
|birth_place=[[Milwaukee]], Wisconsin
|death_date=
|death_place=
|death_cause=
| office          = Commissioner Emeritus of Baseball
| term_start     = January 25, 2015
| term_end        =
| predecessor    = Position created
| successor      =
| office2          = Commissioner of Baseball
| order2          = 9th
| term_start2     = July 9, 1998
| term_end2        =January 25, 2015&lt;br&gt;Acting: September 7, 1992 – July 9, 1998
| predecessor2    = [[Fay Vincent]]
| successor2      = [[Rob Manfred]]
|alma_mater=[[University of Wisconsin–Madison]] ([[Bachelor of Arts|B.A.]])
|blank1 =
|data1 =
|spouse= {{Marriage|Donna Chaimson|1956|1976|end=divorced}} &lt;br&gt; {{Marriage|Suzanne Lappin Steinman|1977}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.jrank.org/pages/4377/Selig-Bud-Chronology.html|title=Bud Selig – Chronology|work=jrank.org|accessdate=June 23, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| module =
{{Infobox baseball biography | embed=yes
|name=
|hoflink = National Baseball Hall of Fame and Museum
|hoftype = National
| hofdate = [[Baseball Hall of Fame balloting, 2017|2017]]
| hofvote = [[Baseball Hall of Fame balloting, 2017|93.7%]] (15 of 16)
| hofmethod = Today's Game Committee&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|url=http://baseballhall.org/selig-schuerholz-elected-to-hof |title=John Schuerholz, Bud Selig Elected to National Baseball Hall of Fame by Today's Game Committee |publisher=National Baseball Hall of Fame and Museum |date=December 4, 2016 |accessdate=December 6, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
}}
'''Allan Huber &quot;Bud&quot; Selig'''&lt;ref name=&quot;SI-Posnanski&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Posnanski|first=Joe|title=In appreciation of Bud Selig|work=Time|date=October 29, 2008|url=http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/2008/writers/joe_posnanski/10/29/selig/index.html|accessdate=November 13, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;USAToday&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Bodley|first=Hal
|title=Selig: Creature of habit, agent of change|work=USA Today|date=March 27, 2007|url=https://www.usatoday.com/sports/baseball/2007-03-26-selig_N.htm|accessdate=November 13, 2008}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Encarta&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |author=Microsoft Corporation |title=Bud Selig |work=Microsoft Encarta Online Encyclopedia 2008 |publisher=Microsoft Corporation |year=2008 |url=http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_1741502266/bud_selig.html |accessdate=November 13, 2008 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091031234838/http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_1741502266/Bud_Selig.html |archivedate=October 31, 2009 |url-status = dead|df=mdy}}&lt;/ref&gt; ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|s|iː|l|ᵻ|ɡ}}; born July 30, 1934) is an American baseball executive who currently serves as the Commissioner Emeritus of Baseball. Previously, he served as the ninth [[Commissioner of Baseball]]. He initially served as the acting commissioner beginning in 1992 before being named the official commissioner in 1998.&lt;ref name=&quot;Extension&quot;&gt;{{cite news |author1=ANDREW BAGNATO |url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/n/a/2008/01/17/sports/s105517S11.DTL |title=Selig Given 3-Year Contract Extension |publisher=Sfgate.com |date=January 18, 2008 |accessdate=October 17, 2009 |url-status = dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090521115859/http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=%2Fn%2Fa%2F2008%2F01%2F17%2Fsports%2Fs105517S11.DTL |archivedate=May 21, 2009 |df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Selig oversaw baseball through the [[1994–95 Major League Baseball strike|1994 strike]], the introduction of the [[Major League Baseball wild card|wild card]], [[interleague play]], and the merging of the [[National League|National]] and [[American League]]s under the Office of the Commissioner. He was instrumental in organizing the [[World Baseball Classic]] in 2006.&lt;ref name=&quot;Extension&quot; /&gt; Selig also introduced revenue sharing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Selig best&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.usatoday.com/sports/baseball/columnist/bodley/2004-08-20-bodley_x.htm |title=Selig emerges as the best of all of baseball's bosses |publisher=Usatoday.com |date=August 20, 2004 |accessdate=October 17, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is credited for the financial turnaround of baseball during his tenure with a 400 percent increase in the revenue of MLB and annual record breaking attendance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Extension&quot; /&gt;

During Selig's term of service, [[Banned substances in baseball|the use of steroids and other performance-enhancing drugs]] became a public issue. The [[Mitchell Report (baseball)|Mitchell Report]], commissioned by Selig, concluded that the MLB commissioners, club officials, the [[Major League Baseball Players Association|Players Association]], and the players all share &quot;to some extent in the responsibility for the steroid era.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;report_pg_conc&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://files.mlb.com/mitchrpt.pdf |title=Mitchell Report |format=PDF |pages=310–311 |accessdate=December 13, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the release of the Mitchell Report, Congressman [[Cliff Stearns]] called publicly for Selig to step down as commissioner, citing his &quot;glacial response&quot; to the &quot;growing stain on baseball.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Extension&quot; /&gt; Selig has pledged on numerous occasions to rid baseball of performance-enhancing drugs, and has overseen and instituted many rule changes and penalties to that end.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2007/12/15/SPRQTV1S2.DTL |title=Selig unlikely to penalize Giants execs Assigning blame could be difficult |work=San Francisco Chronicle |date=December 15, 2007 |accessdate=October 17, 2009 |first=Henry |last=Schulman}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Failed verification|date=February 2011}}

A Milwaukee native, Selig was previously the owner and team president of the [[Milwaukee Brewers]]. The franchise, originally known as the [[Seattle Pilots]], was acquired by Selig in bankruptcy court in 1970, and renamed after the [[Milwaukee Brewers (minor league baseball team)|minor league team of the same name]] that he had watched in his youth and had existed until the arrival of the [[Atlanta Braves|Braves]] in Milwaukee in 1953. Selig was credited with keeping baseball in Milwaukee. The Brewers went to the [[1982 World Series]] (but were defeated in seven games by the [[St. Louis Cardinals]], an event that Selig laments to this very day), and won seven Organization of the Year awards during his tenure. Selig remains a resident of Milwaukee.

On January 17, 2008, Selig's contract was extended through 2012, after which he planned to retire,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Barry M. Bloom |url=http://mlb.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20080117&amp;content_id=2347936&amp;vkey=news_mlb&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=mlb |title=The Official Site of Major League Baseball: News: Major League Baseball News |publisher=Mlb.mlb.com |date= |accessdate=October 17, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; but he then decided to stay as commissioner until the end of the 2014 season, a move approved by the owners on January 12, 2012,&lt;ref name=&quot;Bloom&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mlb.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20120112&amp;content_id=26327342&amp;vkey=news_mlb&amp;c_id=mlb|title=Selig's contract extended through 2014;  Commissioner paved way for Interleague, Wild Cards, testing|last=Bloom|first=Barry|date=January 12, 2012|publisher=[[MLB.com]]|accessdate=January 13, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; which would take his leadership past his 80th birthday. Selig made $14.5 million in the 12-month period ending October 31, 2005.&lt;ref name=&quot;Extension&quot; /&gt; Selig announced on September 26, 2013, that he would retire in January 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=MLB Commissioner Bud Selig to formally announce retirement |url=http://www.baltimorenewsjournal.com/2013/09/26/mlb-commissioner-bud-selig-to-formally-announce-retirement/ |work=Baltimore News Journal |accessdate=September 26, 2013 |url-status = dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130928025801/http://www.baltimorenewsjournal.com/2013/09/26/mlb-commissioner-bud-selig-to-formally-announce-retirement/ |archivedate=September 28, 2013 |df=mdy}}&lt;/ref&gt; On January 22, 2015, [[MLB]] announced that Selig would formally step down from the office when his current term expired on January 24, 2015.&lt;ref name=retirement&gt;{{cite web|title=Selig will retire as Commissioner in January 2015|url=http://m.mlb.com/news/article/61825598/|website=[[MLB.com]]|accessdate=January 23, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=new&gt;{{cite web|title=Bud Selig named Commissioner Emeritus, to make $6M pension|url=http://www.cbssports.com/mlb/eye-on-baseball/24902503/bud-selig-named-commissioner-emeritus-to-make-6m-pension|publisher=[[CBS Sports]]|accessdate=January 24, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was inducted into the [[Baseball Hall of Fame]] in 2017.

== Early life ==
Selig was born in [[Milwaukee]], and grew up in a [[Jewish]] family. His father, Ben Selig, had come to the United States from [[Romania]] with his family when he was four years old.&lt;ref name=&quot;bookref1&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=[[Andrew Zimbalist]]|title=In the Best Interests of Baseball? The Revolutionary Reign of Bud Selig|year=2007|page=[https://archive.org/details/inbestinterestso00andr/page/111 111]|isbn=0-470-12824-0|url=https://archive.org/details/inbestinterestso00andr/page/111}}&lt;/ref&gt; Selig graduated from the [[University of Wisconsin–Madison]] with a [[Bachelor of Arts|B.A.]] in [[American history]] and [[political science]] in 1956.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bio&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mlb.mlb.com/mlb/official_info/about_mlb/executives.jsp?bio=selig_bud |title=MLB Bio |publisher=Mlb.mlb.com |date= |accessdate=October 17, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; He served two years in the [[U.S. Army]] before working with his father who owned a car leasing business in Milwaukee.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bio&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BenSeligLeasingBusiness&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Automotive Fleet |title=Encyclopedia: Rose, Sid |publisher=Automotive Fleet |year=2011 |url=http://www.automotive-fleet.com/Encyclopedia/Rose-Sid.aspx|accessdate=June 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Selig continues to be involved in the automotive industry, serving as president of the Selig Executive Lease Company.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bio&quot; /&gt;

Selig's interest in baseball came from his mother. An immigrant from [[Ukraine]], Marie Selig attended college, a rare accomplishment for a woman in the early 20th century, and became a school teacher. When Selig was only three, Marie began taking him and his older brother, Jerry, to [[Borchert Field]], where the minor league [[Milwaukee Brewers (minor league baseball team)|Milwaukee Brewers]] played. When the [[Boston Braves (baseball)|Boston Braves]] relocated to Milwaukee in 1953, Selig switched allegiances, and eventually became the team's largest public stockholder. Selig was devastated when he learned that the Braves were going to leave Milwaukee in favor of [[Atlanta]]. In 1965, when the Braves left Milwaukee, he divested his stock in the team. As a youngster, Selig's favorite player was [[Hersh Martin|Hershel Martin]].

== Milwaukee Brewers owner ==
{{see also|Milwaukee Brewers}}

As a minority owner of the [[Milwaukee Braves (1953–65)|Milwaukee Braves]], Selig founded the organization '''''Teams, Inc.''''', in an attempt to prevent the majority owners (based out of Chicago) from moving the club to a larger television market. This was challenged legally on the basis that no prior team relocations (in the modern era) left a city without a team. Prior movements had all originated in cities which were home to at least two teams. When his quest to keep the team in Milwaukee finally failed after the [[1965 in baseball|1965 season]], he changed the group's name to Milwaukee Brewers Baseball Club, Inc., after the [[Milwaukee Brewers (minor league baseball team)|minor league baseball team]] he grew up watching, and devoted himself to returning Major League Baseball to Milwaukee.

Selig arranged for major league games to be played at [[Milwaukee County Stadium]]. The first, a pre-season match-up between the [[Chicago White Sox]] and [[Minnesota Twins]], drew more than 51,000 spectators. Selig followed this up by hosting nine White Sox regular-season games in 1968 and eleven in 1969. One of the games played in Milwaukee that year was against the expansion [[Seattle Pilots]], the team that would become the Brewers. Those Milwaukee &quot;home&quot; games were phenomenally successful, with the handful of games accounting for about ''one-third'' of total White Sox home attendance.

To satisfy that fan base, Selig decided to purchase the White Sox (with the intention of moving them to Milwaukee) in 1969. He entered into an agreement to buy the club, but the [[American League]] vetoed the sale, preferring to keep an American League team in Chicago, which at the time was still America's second largest city. Selig turned his attention to other franchises.

[[File:Bud Selig statue.jpg|thumb|right|''[[Selig Monument]]'' outside of [[Miller Park (Milwaukee)|Miller Park]]]]

In 1970, he purchased the bankrupt Seattle Pilots franchise, moving them to his hometown and officially renaming the team the ''Brewers''.

During Selig's tenure as club president, the Brewers participated in postseason play in 1981, when the team finished first in the American League East during the second half of the season, and in 1982, when the team made it to the [[1982 World Series|World Series]], under the leadership of future [[Baseball Hall of Fame|Hall of Famers]] [[Robin Yount]] and [[Paul Molitor]]. Under Selig's watch, the Brewers also won seven Organization of the Year awards. Selig was part of the owners' [[Baseball collusion#1985–1987|collusion]] in 1985–1987, resulting in the owners paying US$280 million in damages to the players.

Upon his assumption of the commissioner's role, Selig transferred his ownership interest in the Brewers to his daughter [[Wendy Selig-Prieb]] in order to remove any technical conflicts of interest, though it was widely presumed he maintained some hand in team operations. Although the team has been sold to [[Los Angeles]] investor [[Mark Attanasio]], questions remain regarding Selig's past involvement. Selig's defenders point to the poor management of the team after Selig-Prieb took control as proof that Selig was not working behind the scenes.

Selig was elected to the [[Wisconsin Athletic Hall of Fame]] in 2001.

On August 24, 2010, a statue of Selig, the ''[[Selig Monument]]'', commissioned by Brewers owner Mark Attanasio and designed by artist Brian Maughan, was unveiled outside Miller Park in Milwaukee.

== Acting Commissioner (1992–1998) ==
Selig became an increasingly vocal opponent of Commissioner [[Fay Vincent]], and soon became the leader of a group of owners seeking his removal. Selig has never stated that the owners [[Baseball collusion|colluded]], while Vincent has:

{{quote|The [[Major League Baseball Players Association|Union]] basically doesn't trust the ownership because [[Baseball collusion|collusion]] was a US$280 million theft by Selig and [[Jerry Reinsdorf]] of that money from the players. I mean, they rigged the signing of [[free agent]]s. They got caught. They paid $280 million to the players. And I think that's polluted labor relations in baseball ever since it happened. I think it's the reason [[MLBPA]] executive director [[Donald Fehr]] has no trust in Selig.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bizofbaseball.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=1173&amp;Itemid=81 |title=Interview with Fay Vincent |publisher=Bizofbaseball.com |date=November 9, 2005 |accessdate=October 17, 2009 |url-status = dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070713054852/http://www.bizofbaseball.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=1173&amp;Itemid=81 |archivedate=July 13, 2007 |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;|Fay Vincent}}

Following an 18-9 [[no-confidence vote]], Vincent resigned. Selig had by this time become chairman of the '''Executive Council of Major League Baseball''', and as such became [[de facto]] acting commissioner.

His first major act was to institute the [[MLB Wild Card|Wild Card]] and divisional playoff play, which has created much controversy amongst baseball fans. Those against the Wild Card see it as diminishing the importance of the [[pennant race]] and the regular season, with the true race often being for second rather than first place, while those in favor of it view it as an opportunity for teams to have a shot at the playoffs even when they have no chance of a first-place finish in their division, thus maintaining fan interest later in the season.

Selig suspended [[Cincinnati Reds]] owner [[Marge Schott]] for a year in 1993 for repeated racially insensitive and prejudicial remarks and actions. The same year, [[New York Yankees]] owner [[George Steinbrenner]] was reinstated from a lifelong suspension that was instituted by Selig's predecessor [[Fay Vincent]]. [[Pete Rose]] has claimed that he applied for reinstatement over the years and received no such consideration. Rose, along with his close friend and former teammate [[Mike Schmidt]] (who is a strong supporter of Rose's reinstatement into baseball), met with Selig in 2002, where Rose privately admitted to Selig (two years before going public with his admission) about [[Dowd Report|betting on baseball]]. Bud Selig was a close friend of the late [[A. Bartlett Giamatti|Bart Giamatti]], who was the commissioner when Rose was first banned from the sport in 1989.

As acting commissioner, Selig represented MLB during the [[1994–95 Major League Baseball strike|1994 players strike]] and cancelled the [[1994 World Series|World Series]], marking the first time the annual event had not been staged since [[1904 World Series|1904]].

== Commissioner (1998–2015) ==

After a six-year search for a new commissioner, the owners voted to give Selig the title on a permanent basis midway through the [[1998 in baseball|1998 season]].

During his tenure the game avoided a third work stoppage in 2002, and has seen the implementation of [[interleague play]].

Whereas in the past, the [[National League|National]] and [[American League|American]] leagues had separate administrative organizations (which, for example, allowed for the introduction of different rules such as the [[designated hitter]]), under Selig, Major League Baseball consolidated the administrative functions of both leagues into the Commissioner's Office in 2000. The last official presidents of the NL and AL were [[Leonard S. Coleman Jr.]] and Dr. [[Gene Budig]] respectively.

=== Reaction after September 11, 2001 ===

On September 11, 2001, Selig ordered all baseball games postponed for a week because of the [[September 11, 2001 attacks|terror attacks on New York and Washington]]. The games were postponed not only out of respect and mourning for the victims, but also out of concern for the safety and security of fans and players.

===2001 contraction attempt===
{{main|2001 Major League Baseball contraction plan}}
After the conclusion of the [[2001 World Series]], Selig held a vote on contracting two teams, reportedly the [[Minnesota Twins]] and [[Montreal Expos]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ESPN-ContractionTimeline&quot;&gt;{{cite web| last = Schoenfield| first = David| title = Still 30 teams: Contraction timeline| publisher = ESPN.com| date = February 5, 2002| url = http://static.espn.go.com/mlb/s/2002/0205/1323230.html| accessdate = October 7, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  This action led to Selig (along with former Expos owner [[Jeffrey Loria]]) being sued for racketeering and conspiring with Loria to deliberately defraud the Expos minority owners.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Chass|first1=Murray|authorlink1=Murray Chass|title=A Group's Racketeering Suit Brings Baseball to Full Bristle|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/17/sports/baseball-a-group-s-racketeering-suit-brings-baseball-to-full-bristle.html|accessdate=February 11, 2016|work=New York Times|date=July 17, 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Joseph|first1=Dave|title=Keep An Eye On Selig, Loria|url=http://articles.sun-sentinel.com/2002-07-17/sports/0207170092_1_marlins-bud-selig-suit|accessdate=February 11, 2016|work=Sun Sentinel|date=July 17, 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; If found liable, the league could have been ordered to pay as much as $500 million in total damages.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Grace|first1=Francie|title=Racketeering Suit Names Baseball Execs|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/news/racketeering-suit-names-baseball-execs/|accessdate=February 11, 2016|agency=Reuters|publisher=CBS News|date=July 17, 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; The judge ruled that the Expos could not be moved or contracted until the case was over.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Talalay|first1=Sarah|title=Suit Against Marlins' Loria Put On Hold Pending Arbitration Ruling|url=http://articles.sun-sentinel.com/2002-11-16/sports/0211150867_1_jeffrey-loria-loria-and-samson-arbitration|accessdate=February 11, 2016|work=Sun Sentinel|date=November 16, 2002|quote=Kessler was also not disappointed by the judge's ruling, which allows the partners to come back to court to request an injunction to prevent the Expos from being relocated, should baseball try to move them before the arbitration is resolved.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The case eventually went to arbitration and was settled out of court for an undisclosed sum.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Once panel makes decision, other options then unfold|url=http://espn.go.com/espn/print?id=1461497&amp;type=news|accessdate=February 11, 2016|agency=Associated Press|publisher=ESPN.com|date=November 15, 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=How Jeff Loria became the miracle Marlin|url=https://www.forbes.com/sites/nathanvardi/2011/11/14/how-jeff-loria-became-the-miracle-marlin/|accessdate=February 11, 2016|first1=Nathan|last1=Vardi|work=Forbes|date=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A week after Selig's announcement, Hennepin County Judge Harry Seymour Crump issued a temporary restraining order that forced the Twins to honor their lease and play the 2002 season at the [[Metrodome]].&lt;ref name=ipppav&gt;http://www.twincities.com/2014/07/10/contraction-nearly-stole-twins-baseball-from-minnesota/&lt;/ref&gt;  In August 2002, the effort to contract the Twins officially fizzled as players and owners reached a consensus on a new labor agreement which extended the team's Metrodome lease.&lt;ref name=ipppav /&gt;

=== Changes to the MLB All-Star Game ===

The [[2002 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|2002 All-Star Game]], played in Selig's hometown of [[Miller Park (Milwaukee)|Milwaukee]], was tied 7–7 after nine innings, and remained tied after the bottom of the 11th inning. Due to the recent managerial trend of granting playing time to as many available players as possible within the regulation nine innings, both managers had used their entire roster. Concerned for the arms of the pitchers currently on the mound, Selig made the controversial decision to declare the game a tie,&lt;ref name=&quot;usaToday-2007-07-10&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.usatoday.com/sports/baseball/allstar/2007-07-10-AllStartiegamefeature_N.htm | work=USA Today | title=Tie in '02 All-Star Game mattered | first=Bob | last=Nightengale | date=July 11, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; to the dissatisfaction of the Milwaukee fans. Selig later said that this call was &quot;embarrassing&quot; and that he was &quot;tremendously saddened&quot; by the outcome of the game.&lt;ref name=&quot;usaToday-2007-07-10&quot;/&gt;

Selig subsequently tried to reinvigorate the All-Star Game by awarding the winning league home-field advantage in the World Series; that practice was initiated in 2003 and continued through 2016. The [[2003 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|2003 All-Star Game]] had the same U.S. viewership as 2002 (9.5 [[Share (ratings)|rating]]; 17 [[Ratings share|share]]) and the ratings declined in 2004 (8.8 rating; 15 share) and 2005 (8.1 rating; 14 share).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-almanac.com/asgbox/asgtv.shtml |title=All-Star Game Television Ratings on Baseball Almanac |publisher=Baseball-almanac.com |date= |accessdate=October 17, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The American television audience increased in 2006 (9.3 rating; 16 share).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/2006/baseball/mlb/specials/all_star/2006/07/12/bc.bbo.all.starratings.ap/index.html |title=SI.com&amp;nbsp;— MLB - 2006 All Star Game&amp;nbsp;— Ratings up for All-Star Game, HR Derby&amp;nbsp;— Wednesday July 12, 2006 6:41PM |work=Sports Illustrated|date=July 12, 2006 |accessdate=October 17, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Disciplinary actions ===

On July 1, 2005, Selig suspended [[Texas Rangers (baseball)|Texas Rangers]] pitcher [[Kenny Rogers (baseball)|Kenny Rogers]] for 20 games and fined him US$50,000. On June 29, 2005, Rogers had purposely grabbed the camera of a cameraman, resulting in one camera falling to the ground. When the cameraman proceeded to pick up his camera, Rogers went back to him in an arguably threatening way. One of the reporters then resumed filming and Rogers knocked him down again.&lt;ref name=&quot;ESPN-KennyRogers&quot;&gt;{{cite news| agency = Associated Press| authorlink = Associated Press| title = Rangers pitcher threatens and confronts cameramen| publisher = ESPN.com| date = June 30, 2005| url = http://sports.espn.go.com/mlb/news/story?id=2097491| accessdate = January 16, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; While an appeal of his suspension was pending, Rogers appeared at the [[2005 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|2005 All-Star Game]] in [[Detroit Michigan|Detroit]], where fans loudly booed him. On July 22, 2005, Selig heard Rogers' appeal of his suspension. Selig decided to uphold the 20 games, however, an independent arbitrator ruled that Selig had exceeded his authority and reduced it to 13 games, but upheld the fine.

=== Performance-enhancing drugs ===
{{main|2006 Baseball steroids investigation}}

In 2005, Selig faced [[U.S. Congress|Congress]] on the issue of [[Anabolic steroids|steroids]]. After the Congressional hearings in early 2005, and with the scrutiny of the sports and national media upon this issue, Selig put forth a proposal for a stricter performance-enhancing drug testing regime to replace the current system. This proposal also included the banning of [[amphetamines]], a first for the major North American sports leagues. The [[Major League Baseball Players Association|MLB Players Association]] and MLB reached an agreement in November on the new policy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title = MLBPA/MLB joint announcement |url = http://mlbplayers.mlb.com/pa/releases/releases.jsp?content=111505 |publisher = MLBPA |date = November 15, 2005 |accessdate = March 21, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Selig's testimony on the subject has been contradictory.  In 2005, Selig told reporters, &quot;I never even heard about them [steroids] until 1998 or 1999.  I ran a team and nobody was closer to their players and I never heard any comment from them.  It wasn't until 1998 or '99 that I heard the discussion.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.commondreams.org/views05/0215-23.htm Bashing Bush: Jose Canseco Comes Clean&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120623020901/http://www.commondreams.org/views05/0215-23.htm |date=June 23, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  But a year later, testifying to Congress in 2006, Selig claimed personal credit for spotting the problem early: &quot;In 1994, before anybody was really talking about steroids in baseball, we proposed a program of testing for such substances to the MLBPA.  As early as 1998, I began formulating a strategic plan to eliminate the use of performance-enhancing substances from the game.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseballinvestigation.com/commissioners-statement.htm|title=Independent Investigation –  Statement Of Commissioner Allan H. (Bud) Selig|work=baseballinvestigation.com|accessdate=June 23, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;  During the [[1988 American League Championship Series|1988 ALCS]], [[Oakland Athletics|Oakland]]'s [[Jose Canseco]] had been repeatedly taunted by [[Boston Red Sox|Boston]] fans with a chant of &quot;ster-oids, ster-oids, ster-oids.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.usnews.com/opinion/articles/2009/07/21/baseballs-steroid-era-was-no-surprise-so-hall-of-fame-voters-should-accept-it|title=Baseball's Steroid Era Was No Surprise, So Hall of Fame Voters Should Accept It|author=David Ezra|work=US News &amp; World Report|accessdate=June 23, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Speaking at the 2013 All-Star Game, Selig complained, &quot;People say, 'Well, you were slow to react.' We were not slow to react. In fact, I heard that this morning, and it aggravated me all over again.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/sport/2013/aug/05/mlb-commissioner-bud-selig-drugs-peds|title=MLB commissioner Bud Selig knows drugs bans may define his legacy|author=Evan Weiner|work=The Guardian|accessdate=June 23, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By early 2006, Selig was forced to deal with the issue of steroid use.  On March 30, 2006, as a response to the controversy of the use of performance-enhancing drugs and the anticipated career home run record to be set by [[Barry Bonds]], Selig asked former [[United States Senate|U.S. Senator]] [[George J. Mitchell]]  to lead an independent investigation into the use of steroids in baseball's recent past. [[Joe Sheehan]] from ''[[Baseball Prospectus]]'' wrote that the commission has been focusing &quot;blame for the era exclusively on uniformed personnel&quot;, and failing to investigate any role played by team ownership and management.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Sheehan | first = Joe | title = Prospectus Today&amp;nbsp;— Break with the Past | publisher = Baseball Prospectus | date = May 22, 2007 | url = http://www.baseballprospectus.com/article.php?articleid=6261 | accessdate = August 14, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Much controversy surrounded Selig and his involvement in Bonds' all-time home run record chase. For months, speculation surrounded Selig and the possibility that he and [[Hank Aaron|Henry Aaron]] would not attend Bonds' games as he closed in on the record. Selig announced in July 2007 when Bonds was near 755 home runs that he would attend the games. Selig was in attendance for Bonds' record-tying home run against the [[San Diego Padres]], sitting in Padres owner [[John Moores (baseball)|John Moores]]' private suite. When Bonds hit his 755th home run, Selig refused to applaud Bonds' accomplishment, instead choosing to keep his hands in his pockets and have a look of disdain on his face. Bud Selig also did not attend the [[San Francisco Giants]]' game on August 7 when Barry Bonds hit his record-breaking 756th home run against the [[Washington Nationals]]; after the event, Selig released a statement congratulating Bonds.

On December 13, 2007, former senator Mitchell released his [[Mitchell Report (baseball)|report on the use of performance-enhancing substances by MLB players]]. The report names many current and former players who allegedly used performance-enhancing drugs during their career.

Selig has been widely criticized for not taking an active enough role to stem the tide of steroid use in baseball until it had blossomed into a debilitating problem for the industry. ''[[Chicago Sun-Times]]'' columnist [[Jay Mariotti]] called Selig the &quot;Steroids Commissioner.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.suntimes.com/sports/mariotti/742620,mariotti011608.article Selig's only legacy: S-T-E-R-O-I-D-S]  {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080324132320/http://www.suntimes.com/sports/mariotti/742620%2Cmariotti011608.article |date=March 24, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Selig has been called to [[United States Congress|Congress]] several times to testify on performance-enhancing drug use. Congressman [[Cliff Stearns]] said in December 2007 that Selig should resign because of use of performance-enhancing drugs in baseball during his tenure.&lt;ref name=&quot;Extension&quot;/&gt;

=== Post-season schedule ===
Selig's decision to extend the traditional post-season schedule into November in an attempt to increase Nielsen ratings was met with widespread disdain, both inside and outside the baseball community. [[Mike Scioscia]], manager of the American League West Division Champion Los Angeles Angels, dismissed the decision as &quot;Ridiculous. I don't know. Can I say it any clearer than that? We should have never had a day off last Wednesday. We should never have three days off after the season. You shouldn't even have two days off after the season.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/25/sports/baseball/25yankees.html?hpw &quot;Another Day Off for Yankees and Angels, and It’s Not Exactly Welcome&quot;] ''[[The New York Times]]'', October 25, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Controversies ===

Related to the contraction controversy in 2001, [[Rob Dibble]] posted an open letter to Bud Selig, criticizing his actions for benefiting only the Milwaukee Brewers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Rob Dibble. |url=http://espn.go.com/talent/danpatrick/s/2001/1119/1280454.html |title=Open letter to Bud Selig |publisher=ESPN.com |date=December 1, 2001 |accessdate=November 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Dibble cites that the contraction of the Twins would benefit the Brewers, as they would potentially claim the Twins' share of the upper Midwest market.

Selig has made some decisions involving the [[Houston Astros]] that were unpopular with their supporters. He ordered the roof at [[Minute Maid Park]] to be opened for games three and four of the [[2005 World Series]], pre-empting the authority held by the Astros. The roof was closed for all prior playoff games and similar weather conditions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=John Shea. |url=http://articles.sfgate.com/2005-10-25/sports/17394710_1_general-manager-tim-purpura-roof-astros |title=WORLD SERIES NOTES Roof's not an open and shut case |publisher=Hearst Communications |date=October 25, 2005 |accessdate=November 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; For [[Hurricane Ike]] in 2008, Selig mandated that the Astros play two home games against the [[Chicago Cubs]] in his hometown of Milwaukee despite proximity to the visiting Cubs; the home ballparks for the [[Texas Rangers (baseball)|Texas Rangers]] and [[Atlanta Braves]] were both available to host the games. The Astros subsequently were victims of a no-hitter by [[Carlos Zambrano]] and recorded a single hit in the following game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Karen Crouse. |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2008/09/18/sports/baseball/18astros.html |title=Hurricane Sent Astros Into a Spin |work=The New York Times |date=September 17, 2008 |accessdate=November 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the midst of the playoff race, this decision and its impact deeply affected the playoff race and seedings with eight teams holding winning records at the moment. The Milwaukee Brewers benefited from these events by qualifying in the playoffs as a Wild Card team, only to lose in the [[2008 National League Division Series|NLDS]] to the [[Philadelphia Phillies]], the eventual World Series winner. In 2011, Selig also demanded that the Astros move to the [[American League West]] as a condition of the sale of the franchise to businessman Jim Crane; the team switched leagues in 2013 in return for $70 million discount in the purchase price.&lt;ref name=&quot;MLB-Astros-AL-approved&quot;&gt;{{cite web| last = Bloom| first = Barry M.| title = Astros sale to Crane, move to AL approved| publisher = MLB Advanced Media| date = November 17, 2011| url = http://mlb.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20111117&amp;content_id=25992120| accessdate = May 1, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

United States bankruptcy judge Kevin Gross rendered a stern warning to Selig in regards to the [[2011 Los Angeles Dodgers ownership dispute]].  Treating other teams differently in regards to their media contracts drew accusations that Selig did not act in good faith with respect to the [[Los Angeles Dodgers]].  Selig rejected the television deal that [[Frank McCourt (executive)|Frank McCourt]] negotiated that intended to bring the franchise out of bankruptcy, claiming McCourt violated the Baseball Agreement. In comparison, no action was taken against [[New York Mets]] owner [[Fred Wilpon]] despite being in a similar position.  Gross stated, &quot;Should the Commissioner falter in proving alleged wrongdoing, the Court may allow LAD (Los Angeles Dodgers) to take further, limited discovery.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Bill Shaikin |url=http://articles.latimes.com/2011/oct/07/sports/la-sp-dodgers-mccourt-20111008 |title=Judge sides with MLB, but warns Bud Selig |work=Los Angeles Times |date=October 17, 2011 |accessdate=November 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some critics have used Selig's handling of the Dodgers to point out a double standard in treatment of MLB owners. More specifically in regards to the Mets, critics point out that with Selig's personal relationship with Wilpon has motivated him to stall any possible removal of Wilpon as that club's principal owner.

Selig also notably failed to resolve a 6-year conflict between the [[San Francisco Giants]] and the [[Oakland Athletics]] regarding the Athletics' proposed move to [[San Jose, California|San Jose]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=sfgate.com | url=http://www.sfgate.com/athletics/jenkins/article/Oakland-situation-leaves-a-hole-in-Selig-s-legacy-5699653.php |title= Oakland situation leaves a hole in Selig's legacy | accessdate= August 21, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Selig established a blue-ribbon panel in 2009 to resolve the dispute;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=espn |url=http://espn.go.com/blog/sweetspot/post/_/id/37163/time-for-mlb-to-let-the-as-move | title=Time for MLB to let the A's move | accessdate= August 21, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; however, despite years to find a resolution, the blue-ribbon panel completely failed to make any progress toward resolving the issue, leading San Jose to sue MLB.  The lawsuit, which is currently ongoing, questions the league's anti-trust exemption and its ability to enforce particular clubs' geographic territories.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=cbs|url=http://sanfrancisco.cbslocal.com/2014/08/12/san-jose-gets-day-in-court-with-mlb-over-antitrust-claim-in-planned-as-move-athletics-sj-ballpark-anti-trust-court-federal-9th-circut-court-of-appeals/ | title = San Jose gets day in court with MLB over antitrust claim in planned A's move | accessdate= August 21, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Term of service ===

On December 1, 2006, Selig announced that he would be retiring as commissioner of baseball upon the expiration of his contract in 2009. Selig earned $14.5 million from MLB over the timespan October 31, 2005 to October 31, 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Press | first = Canadian | title = MLB: Selig made $14.5 million last year | publisher = The Sports Network (TSN) | date = April 3, 2007 | url = https://www.tsn.ca/mlb/news_story/?ID=202619&amp;hubname= | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20080122184319/http://www.tsn.ca/mlb/news_story/?ID=202619&amp;hubname= | archivedate = January 22, 2008 | accessdate = September 12, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in January 2008, Selig agreed to a three-year contract extension, announcing he planned to retire after the 2012 season.&lt;ref name=&quot;USAToday-extension2012&quot;&gt;{{cite web| last = Nightengale| first = Bob| title = MLB gives Selig contract extension through 2012| work=USA Today| date = January 18, 2008| url = https://www.usatoday.com/sports/baseball/2008-01-17-selig-extension_N.htm| accessdate = November 16, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; He further decided against retirement, and after a two-year extension for the previous deal was agreed to on January 12, 2012, it was announced that Selig would remain commissioner until the end of the 2014 season.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bloom&quot;/&gt;

== Notable changes to Major League Baseball ==
Bud Selig has overseen the following changes in Major League Baseball:
* Realignment of teams into three divisions per league, and the introduction of playoff [[MLB Wild Card|wild card]] teams (1994)
* [[Interleague play]] (1997)
* Retired [[Jackie Robinson]]'s uniform number, 42, across all MLB teams (1997)
* Two additional franchises: the [[Arizona Diamondbacks]] and the [[Tampa Bay Devil Rays]], now the Tampa Bay Rays (1998)
* Transfer of the [[Milwaukee Brewers]] from the American League to the National League (1998)
* Abolition of the [[American League|American]] and [[National League|National league]] offices and presidencies, and inclusion of all [[umpire (baseball)|umpiring crews]] into a common pool for AL and NL games, instead of having separate pools per league (2000)
* Unbalanced schedule (2001)&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/06/sports/baseball-division-race-just-got-harder-for-mets.html Division Race Just Got Harder For Mets] ''[[The New York Times]]''&lt;/ref&gt;
* Home field advantage in the [[World Series]] granted to the winner of the [[Major League Baseball All-Star Game|All Star Game]] in the same season (2003)
* Transfer of [[Montreal Expos]] franchise to Washington, D.C., becoming the [[Washington Nationals]] (2004)
* Dedicating April 15 as [[Jackie Robinson Day]] (2004)
* Stricter [[Major League Baseball drug policy|Major League Baseball performance-enhancing drug testing policy]] (2005)
* [[World Baseball Classic]] (2006)
* Introduction of [[instant replay in Major League Baseball|instant replay]] in the event of a disputed [[home run]] call (2008)
* Addition of a second wild card playoff team in each league (2012)
* Transfer of the [[Houston Astros]] from the National League to the American League (2013), as a condition of the sale of the team to [[Jim Crane]], resulting in each league having the same number of teams (15) and interleague play throughout the season
* [[Instant replay in Major League Baseball#Expanded replay approved for 2014|Expanded instant replay]] (2014) and the institution of the manager challenge system

During Selig's terms as Executive Council Chairman (from 1992–1998) and Commissioner, new stadiums have opened in [[Chase Field|Arizona]], [[Turner Field|Atlanta]], [[Great American Ball Park|Cincinnati]], [[Progressive Field|Cleveland]], [[Coors Field|Colorado]], [[Comerica Park|Detroit]], [[Minute Maid Park|Houston]], [[Marlins Park|Miami]], [[Miller Park|Milwaukee]], [[Target Field|Minneapolis]], New York City ([[Citi Field|Flushing, Queens]] and [[Yankee Stadium|the Bronx]]), [[Citizens Bank Park|Philadelphia]], [[PNC Park|Pittsburgh]], [[Petco Park|San Diego]], [[Oracle Park|San Francisco]], [[T-Mobile Park|Seattle]], [[Globe Life Park in Arlington|Arlington]], [[Busch Stadium|St. Louis]], and [[Nationals Park|Washington, D.C.]]

== Israel Baseball League ==

Selig and his family served a supportive role on the Advisory Board of the [[Israel Baseball League]] during its inaugural season in 2007. In response to issues with the league's financial management, after the season, the Selig family requested that their names be removed from the list of board members.&lt;ref name=&quot;JerusalemPost-IBL&quot;&gt;{{Cite news | last = Wohlgelernter | first = Elli | title = Field of Failed Dreams | newspaper = The Jerusalem Post | date = July 24, 2008 | url = http://fr.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?cid=1215331082409&amp;pagename=JPost%2FJPArticle%2FPrinter | accessdate = July 28, 2008 | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt; |url-status = dead| archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20110916214127/http://fr.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?cid=1215331082409&amp;pagename=JPost%2FJPArticle%2FPrinter | archivedate = September 16, 2011 | df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==''Selig Experience''==
In May 2015, the Milwaukee Brewers honored Bud Selig with the unveiling of the ''Selig Experience'' exhibit at [[Miller Park (Milwaukee)|Miller Park]]. The ''Selig Experience'' is a fifteen-minute documentary showing Bud Selig's life and work for the Milwaukee Brewers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://journaltimes.com/sports/baseball/selig-experience-it-s-worth-the-visit/article_712a9960-83a7-576a-b985-b53bd8ffd845.html Selig Experience: It's worth the visit]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://milwaukee.brewers.mlb.com/mil/fan_forum/selig_experience.jsp Selig Experience]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Personal life ==
Selig has been married twice. He married his first wife, Donna, in the 1950s, and they had two children: Sari (born 1957) and Wendy (born 1960). The couple divorced in 1976 after 19 years of marriage on the grounds that Selig had been &quot;unduly absenting yourself from the home of the parties and isolating yourself ... in pursuit of your baseball interests to the detriment of your marriage.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.si.com/vault/2014/10/20/106650435/for-love-and-money|title=FOR LOVE AND MONEY|last=Reiter|first=Ben|website=Vault|language=en|access-date=2018-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Donna Selig later stated that ended the marriage because her husband &quot;divorced me and married baseball.&quot; Since 1977, Selig has been married to the former Suzanne Steinman, who has a daughter from a previous marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/inbestinterestso00andr|url-access=registration|page=[https://archive.org/details/inbestinterestso00andr/page/123 123]|quote=bud selig divorced me and married baseball.|title=In the Best Interests of Baseball: The Revolutionary Reign of Bud Selig|last=Zimbalist|first=Andrew|date=2007-06-22|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|isbn=9780470128244|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Teaching ==
In 2009, Selig began teaching as an adjunct professor of sports law and policy at [[Marquette University Law School]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://law.marquette.edu/faculty-staff/selig-named-adjunct-law-professor-marquette Selig Named Adjunct Law Professor At Marquette] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120606210333/http://law.marquette.edu/faculty-staff/selig-named-adjunct-law-professor-marquette |date=June 6, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  His classes have covered numerous topics, including &quot;the history of collective bargaining and free agency, baseball's antitrust exemption, revenue sharing – as well as finer points of sports law like intellectual property rights, ambush marketing, and why baseball does not allow game footage on YouTube.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/22/sports/baseball/22selig.html?pagewanted=all Selig Finally Finds Peace as He Looks Toward Next Job]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010, Selig endowed the Allan H. Selig Chair in the History of Sport and Society in the United States, as well as a Distinguished Lecture Series in Sport and Society at his alma mater, the University of Wisconsin–Madison.  The inaugural lecture was given by Adrian Burgos&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.news.wisc.edu/18868 |title=Professor to present first Selig Distinguished Lecture in Sport and Society (Jan. 21, 2011) |publisher=News.wisc.edu |date=January 21, 2011 |accessdate=October 30, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Prof. Sean Dinces has held the Chair since 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://history.wisc.edu/history_newsletter2013.pdf&amp;sa=U&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiOp5jj8rjLAhUDmIMKHRCLDy0QFggNMAQ&amp;client=internal-uds-cse&amp;usg=AFQjCNETETlX7elg8C9tHMmTmlYBp3SFKQ |title=UW-Madison Department of History: 2013 History Department Newsletter |publisher=history.wisc.edu |date= |accessdate=March 11, 2016 }}{{dead link|date=July 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2016, Selig joined the [[Sandra Day O'Connor College of Law]] at Arizona State University.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Bud Selig to teach at Arizona State's College of Law|url=http://espn.go.com/espn/wire?section=mlb&amp;id=14750705|accessdate=February 11, 2016|agency=Associated Press|publisher=ESPN.com|date=February 9, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Honors==
Selig was awarded the U.S. [[Department of the Army Outstanding Civilian Service Award]] in April 2015 for supporting soldiers, veterans and their families through his work in Major League Baseball.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Department of the Army Outstanding Civilian Service Award|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/espn/wire?section=mlb&amp;id=12690214|accessdate=April 15, 2015|date=April 15, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; On April 6, 2015, the [[Milwaukee Brewers]] retired [[uniform number]] 1 in his honor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://m.mlb.com/news/article/116595932/honored-by-brewers-selig-throws-out-first-pitch|title=Honored by Brewers, Selig throws out first pitch|work=Major League Baseball|accessdate=June 23, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On December 4, 2016, it was announced Selig was elected into the National Baseball Hall of Fame class of 2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://m.mlb.com/news/article/210231272/bud-selig-john-schuerholz-elected-to-hall/|title=Selig, Schuerholz elected to Hall of Fame|work=Major League Baseball|accessdate=December 4, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2016, Selig was honored with the &quot;Lombardi Award of Excellence&quot; from the Vince Lombardi Cancer Foundation. The award was created to honor Coach [[Vince Lombardi|Lombardi]]'s legacy, and is awarded annually to an individual who exemplifies the spirit of the Coach.

==Publications==
* Foreword to ''American Jews and America's Game: Voices of a Growing Legacy in Baseball'' by [[Larry Ruttman]]. Lincoln, Nebraska and London, England: University of Nebraska Press, 2013.

== References ==

{{reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book|last=Ruttman|first=Larry|authorlink=Larry Ruttman|title=American Jews and America's Game: Voices of a Growing Legacy in Baseball|date=2013|publisher=University of Nebraska Press|location=Lincoln, Nebraska and London, England|isbn=978-0-8032-6475-5|pages=325–335|chapter=Allan H. &quot;Bud&quot; Selig: Innovative and Controversial Commissioner of Major League Baseball}} This chapter in Ruttman's history, based on a January 16, 2009 interview with Selig conducted for the book, discusses Selig's American, Jewish, baseball, and life experiences from youth to the present.
* {{cite book|last=Zimbalist|first=Andrew|authorlink=Andrew Zimbalist|title=In the Best Interests of Baseball? The Revolutionary Reign of Bud Selig|date=2006|publisher=Wiley|location=Hoboken, New Jersey|isbn=0-471-73533-7|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/inbestinterestso00andr}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Bud Selig}}
{{wikiquote}}
{{Portal|Biography|Baseball}}
* [http://budselig.com/ Official website]
* [http://mlb.mlb.com/mlb/official_info/about_mlb/executives.jsp?bio=selig_bud MLB.com: Official info]
* [http://www.baseball-almanac.com/articles/bud_selig_biography.shtml Bud Selig Biography by Baseball Almanac]
* [https://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/12/sports/baseball/12selig.html The Commissioner of Baseball Is on Deck] www.nytimes.com
* [http://bballbiz.blogspot.com/2007/02/mlb-commissioner-bud-seligs-speech-at_16.html Video Of MLB Commissioner's Speech On The State Of Baseball, February 8, 2007]
* [http://www.slate.com/id/2118114/ &quot;Bud Selig: A baseball hero. Really.&quot;] – Nicholas Thompson, [[Slate.com]], May 5, 2005
* {{C-SPAN|allanselig}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-sport}}
{{s-new|office}}
{{s-ttl|title=Owner of the [[Milwaukee Brewers]] franchise|years=1970–1998}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Wendy Selig-Prieb]]}}
{{s-hon}}
{{s-new|title}}
{{s-ttl|title=Commissioner Emeritus of Baseball|years=2015–present}}
{{s-inc}}
{{s-end}}

{{Milwaukee Brewers retired numbers}}
{{Baseball Commissioners}}
{{Milwaukee Brewers owners}}
{{Baseball Hall of Fame members}}
{{2017 Baseball HOF}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Selig, Bud}}
[[Category:1934 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:American people of Romanian-Jewish descent]]
[[Category:American people of Ukrainian-Jewish descent]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball commissioners]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball executives]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball owners]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball team presidents]]
[[Category:Military personnel from Milwaukee]]
[[Category:Milwaukee Braves owners]]
[[Category:Milwaukee Brewers executives]]
[[Category:Milwaukee Brewers owners]]
[[Category:National Baseball Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:Jewish American baseball people]]
[[Category:Sportspeople from Milwaukee]]
[[Category:United States Army soldiers]]
[[Category:University of Wisconsin–Madison alumni]]</text>
      <sha1>4iy5jnr4yctlpxwx1dujp7kqqxwpb1s</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
