  <page>
    <title>Béla Bartók</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4527</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939966785</id>
      <parentid>939680783</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-09T19:50:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2601:186:837F:F3D0:9C87:46AE:6771:D17</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Childhood and early years (1881–98) */Edited flow</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Hungarian composer and pianist}}
{{redirect|Bartok}}
{{pp-move-vandalism|small=yes}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2016}}
{{Use Harvard referencing|date=May 2019}}
{{eastern name order|Bartók Béla Viktor János}}
[[File:Bartók Béla 1927.jpg|thumb|Béla Bartók in 1927]]

'''Béla Viktor János Bartók''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|b|eɪ|l|ə|_|ˈ|b|ɑːr|t|ɒ|k}}; {{lang-hu|Bartók Béla}}, {{IPA-hu|ˈbɒrtoːk ˈbeːlɒ|pron}}; 25 March 1881 – 26 September 1945) was a [[Hungarians|Hungarian]] composer, pianist, and [[ethnomusicologist]]. He is considered one of the most important composers of the 20th century; he and [[Franz Liszt]] are regarded as Hungary's greatest composers {{harv|Gillies |2001}}. Through his collection and analytical study of [[folk music]], he was one of the founders of comparative musicology, which later became ethnomusicology.

==Biography==
===Childhood and early years (1881–98)===
{{refimprove section|date=July 2019}}
Bartók was born in the [[Banat]]ian town of Nagyszentmiklós in the [[Kingdom of Hungary]] (since 1920 [[Sânnicolau Mare]], Romania) on 25 March 1881.

Bartók had a diverse ancestry. On his father's side, the Bartók family was a Hungarian lower noble family, originating from [[Borsodszirák]], [[Borsod County|Borsod]] {{harv|Móser|2006a|loc=44}}. His paternal grandmother was a [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] of [[Bunjevci]] origin, but considered herself Hungarian {{harv|Szekernyés|2017}}. Bartók's father was also named Béla; although his mother, Paula (née Voit), had ethnic German roots, she spoke [[Hungarian language|Hungarian]] fluently {{harv|Hooker|2001|loc=16}}. She was a native of Turócszentmárton (now [[Martin, Slovakia]]) {{harv|Cooper|2015|loc=6}}. Paula also had Hungarian (Teréz Fegyveres) and Slavic (Polereczky: Magyarized Slavic {{harv|Anon.|n.d.(c)}}) ancestors.{{citation needed|date=July 2019}}

Béla displayed notable musical talent very early in life: according to his mother, he could distinguish between different dance [[rhythm]]s that she played on the [[piano]] before he learned to speak in complete sentences {{harv|Gillies|1990|loc=6}}. By the age of four he was able to play 40 pieces on the piano and his mother began formally teaching him the next year.

Béla was a sickly child and suffered from severe [[eczema]] until the age of five {{harv|Gillies|1990|loc=5}}, as a result of an inoculation with a faulty [[smallpox vaccine]], with his facial disfigurement causing him to avoid people {{harv|Suchoff|2001|loc=15}}. In 1888, when he was seven, his father (the director of an agricultural school) died suddenly. His mother then took him and his sister, Erzsébet, to live in Nagyszőlős (today [[Vynohradiv]], Ukraine) and then to Pozsony (present-day [[Bratislava]], Slovakia).

He gave his first public recital aged 11 in Nagyszőlős, to a warm critical reception {{harv|Griffiths|1988|loc={{Page needed|date=April 2016}}}}. Among the pieces he played was his own first composition, written two years previously: a short piece called &quot;The Course of the Danube&quot; {{harv|de Toth|1999}}. Shortly thereafter László Erkel accepted him as a pupil {{harv|Stevens|1964|loc=8}}.

===Early musical career (1899–1908)===
[[File:Bartok tablo.jpg|thumb|left|Bartók's signature on his high-school-graduation photograph, dated 9 September 1899]]

From 1899 to 1903, Bartók studied piano under [[István Thomán]], a former student of [[Franz Liszt]], and composition under [[János Koessler]] at the [[Royal Academy of Music in Budapest]] {{harv|Anon.|2018}}. There he met [[Zoltán Kodály]], who made a strong impression on him and became a lifelong friend and colleague {{harv|Rockwell|1982}}. In 1903, Bartók wrote his first major orchestral work, ''Kossuth'', a [[symphonic poem]] which honored [[Lajos Kossuth]], hero of the [[Hungarian Revolution of 1848]] {{harv|Stevens|2018}}.

The music of [[Richard Strauss]], whom he met in 1902 at the [[Budapest]] premiere of ''[[Also sprach Zarathustra (Strauss)|Also sprach Zarathustra]]'', strongly influenced his early work {{harv|Wilhelm|1989|loc=73}}. When visiting a holiday resort in the summer of 1904, Bartók overheard a young nanny, Lidi Dósa from [[Kibéd]] in Transylvania, sing folk songs to the children in her care. This sparked his lifelong dedication to folk music {{harv|Kory|2007}}.

From 1907, he also began to be influenced by the French composer [[Claude Debussy]], whose compositions Kodály had brought back from [[Paris]]. Bartók's large-scale orchestral works were still in the style of [[Johannes Brahms]] and Richard Strauss, but he wrote a number of small piano pieces which showed his growing interest in [[folk music]]. The first piece to show clear signs of this new interest is the [[String Quartet No. 1 (Bartók)|String Quartet No. 1]] in A minor (1908), which contains folk-like elements {{harv|Rodda|1990–2018}}.

In 1907, Bartók began teaching as a piano professor at the [[Royal Academy]] {{harv|Anon.|1945}}. This position freed him from touring Europe as a pianist and enabled him to work in Hungary. Among his notable students were [[Fritz Reiner]], [[Sir Georg Solti]], [[György Sándor]], [[Ernő Balogh]], and [[Lili Kraus]]. After Bartók moved to the United States, he taught [[Jack Beeson]] and [[Violet Archer]].

In 1908, he and Kodály traveled into the countryside to collect and research old [[Hungarian people|Magyar]] folk melodies. Their growing interest in folk music coincided with a contemporary social interest in traditional national culture. They made some surprising discoveries. Magyar folk music had previously been categorised as [[Romani people|Gypsy]] music. The classic example is Franz Liszt's famous ''[[Hungarian Rhapsodies]]'' for piano, which he based on popular art songs performed by [[Romani people|Romani]] bands of the time. In contrast, Bartók and Kodály discovered that the old Magyar folk melodies were based on [[pentatonic scale]]s, similar to those in [[Asian music|Asian folk traditions]], such as those of Central Asia, Anatolia and Siberia.{{citation needed|date=July 2019}}

Bartók and Kodály quickly set about incorporating elements of such Magyar peasant music into their compositions. They both frequently quoted folk song melodies ''verbatim'' and wrote pieces derived entirely from authentic songs. An example is his two volumes entitled ''For Children'' for solo piano, containing 80 folk tunes to which he wrote accompaniment. Bartók's style in his art music compositions was a synthesis of folk music, classicism, and modernism. His melodic and harmonic sense was profoundly influenced by the folk music of Hungary, Romania, and other nations. He was especially fond of the asymmetrical dance rhythms and pungent harmonies found in [[Bulgarian music]]. Most of his early compositions offer a blend of nationalist and late Romanticism elements.

===Middle years and career (1909–39)===

====Personal life====
In 1909, at the age of 28, Bartók married Márta Ziegler (1893–1967), aged 16. Their son, Béla Bartók III, was born the next year. After nearly 15 years together, Bartók divorced Márta in June 1923. Two months after his divorce, he married [[Ditta Pásztory-Bartók|Ditta Pásztory]] (1903–1982), a piano student, ten days after proposing to her. She was aged 19, he 42. Their son, Péter, was born in 1924 {{harv|Vetter|2007|loc=22}}.

====Opera====
In 1911, Bartók wrote what was to be his only opera, ''[[Bluebeard's Castle]]'', dedicated to Márta. He entered it for a prize by the Hungarian Fine Arts Commission, but they rejected his work as not fit for the stage {{harv|Chalmers|1995|loc=93}}. In 1917 Bartók revised the score for the 1918 première, and rewrote the ending. Following the [[Hungarian Soviet Republic|1919 revolution]] in which he actively participated, he was pressured by the [[Horthy's Hungary|Horthy regime]] to remove the name of the librettist [[Béla Balázs]] from the opera {{harv|Chalmers|1995|loc=123}}{{Failed verification|date=September 2016}}&lt;!--Horthy's name does not even occur on p. 123 of Chalmers's book, and Horthy was certainly no Communist!--&gt;, as he was blacklisted and had left the country for Vienna. ''Bluebeard's Castle'' received only one revival, in 1936, before Bartók emigrated. For the remainder of his life, although he was passionately devoted to Hungary, its people and its culture, he never felt much loyalty to the government or its official establishments.

====Folk music and composition====
[[File:Bartok recording folk music.jpg|thumb|Béla Bartók using a [[phonograph]] to record folk songs sung by peasants in what is now [[Slovakia]]]]

After his disappointment over the Fine Arts Commission competition, Bartók wrote little for two or three years, preferring to concentrate on collecting and arranging folk music. He found the phonograph  an essential tool for collecting folk music for its accuracy, objectivity, and manipulability {{harv|Bartók|1976|loc=14}}. He collected first in the [[Carpathian Basin]] (then the [[Kingdom of Hungary in the 18th and 19th century|Kingdom of Hungary]]), where he notated [[Hungarian folk music|Hungarian]], [[Music of Slovakia|Slovak]], [[Music of Romania|Romanian]], and [[Music of Bulgaria|Bulgarian]] folk music. He also collected in [[Moldavia]], [[Wallachia]], and (in 1913) [[Algeria]]. The outbreak of [[World War I]] forced him to stop the expeditions, but he returned to composing with a [[ballet]] called ''[[The Wooden Prince]]'' (1914–16) and the [[String Quartet No. 2 (Bartók)|String Quartet No. 2]] in (1915–17), both influenced by [[Debussy]].

Raised as a [[Catholic Church|Catholic]], by his early adulthood Bartók had become an [[atheist]]. He later became attracted to [[Unitarianism]] and publicly converted to the [[Unitarianism|Unitarian]] faith in 1916. Although Bartók was not conventionally religious, according to his son Béla Bartók III, &quot;he was a nature lover: he always mentioned the miraculous order of nature with great reverence.&quot; As an adult, Béla III later became lay president of the Hungarian Unitarian Church {{harv|Hughes|1999–2007}}.

Bartók's ''[[libretto]]'' for ''[[The Miraculous Mandarin]]'', another ballet, was influenced by [[Igor Stravinsky]], [[Arnold Schoenberg]] and Richard Strauss. Though started in 1918 the story of prostitution, robbery, and murder was not performed on the stage until 1926 because of its sexual content. He next wrote his two [[violin sonata]]s (written in 1921 and 1922 respectively), which are harmonically and structurally some of his most complex pieces.{{citation needed|date=July 2019}}

In 1927–28, Bartók wrote his [[String Quartet No. 3 (Bartók)|Third]] and [[String Quartet No. 4 (Bartók)|Fourth String Quartets]], after which his compositions demonstrated his mature style. Notable examples of this period are ''[[Music for Strings, Percussion and Celesta]]'' (1936) and [[Divertimento for String Orchestra (Bartók)|Divertimento for String Orchestra]] (1939). The [[String Quartet No. 5 (Bartók)|Fifth String Quartet]] was composed in 1934, and the [[String Quartet No. 6 (Bartók)|Sixth String Quartet]] (his last) in 1939.

In 1936 he travelled to [[Turkey]] to collect and study [[Turkish folk music]]. He worked in collaboration with Turkish composer [[Ahmet Adnan Saygun]] mostly around [[Adana]] ({{harvnb|Özgentürk|2008}}; {{harvnb|Sipos|2000}}).

===World War II and last years in America (1940–45)===
In 1940, as the European political situation worsened after the outbreak of [[World War II]], Bartók was increasingly tempted to flee Hungary. He strongly opposed the [[Nazis]] and Hungary's alliance with Germany and the [[Axis powers]] under the [[Tripartite Pact]]. After the Nazis came to power in the early 1930s, Bartók refused to give concerts in Germany and broke away from his publisher there. His anti-fascist political views caused him a great deal of trouble with the establishment in Hungary. Having first sent his manuscripts out of the country, Bartók reluctantly emigrated to the U.S. with his wife [[Ditta Pásztory-Bartók|Ditta]] in October that year. They settled in New York City after arriving on the night of 29–30 October 1940 via a steamer from Lisbon. After joining them in 1942, their younger son, Péter Bartók, enlisted in the [[United States Navy]] where he served in the Pacific during the remainder of the war and later settled in Florida where he became a recording and sound engineer. His elder son, by his first marriage, Béla Bartók III, remained in Hungary and later worked as a railroad official until his retirement in the early 1980s.

Although he became an American citizen in 1945, shortly before his death {{harv|Gagné|2012|loc=28}}, Bartók never felt fully at home in the USA. He initially found it difficult to compose. Although he was well known in America as a pianist, ethnomusicologist and teacher, he was not well known as a composer. There was little American interest in his music during his final years. He and his wife Ditta gave some concerts, although demand for them was low.{{Citation needed|date=January 2014}} Bartók, who had made some recordings in Hungary, also recorded for [[Columbia Records]] after he came to the US; many of these recordings (some with Bartók's own spoken introductions) were later issued on LP and CD {{harvard citations |last=Bartók|year=1994 |year2=1995a |year3=1995b |year4=2003 |year5=2007 |year6=2008 |year7=2016}}.

Supported by a research fellowship from [[Columbia University]], for several years, Bartók and Ditta worked on a large collection of [[Serbian language|Serbian]] and [[Croatian language|Croatian]] folk songs in Columbia's libraries. Bartók's economic difficulties during his first years in America were mitigated by publication royalties, teaching and performance tours. While his finances were always precarious, he did not live and die in poverty as was the common myth. He had enough friends and supporters to ensure that there was sufficient money and work available for him to live on. Bartók was a proud man and did not easily accept charity. Despite being short on cash at times, he often refused money that his friends offered him out of their own pockets. Although he was not a member of the [[ASCAP]], the society paid for any medical care he needed during his last two years. Bartók reluctantly accepted this {{harv|Chalmers|1995|loc=196–203}}.

The first symptoms of his health problems began late in 1940, when his right shoulder began to show signs of stiffening. In 1942, symptoms increased and he started having bouts of fever, but no underlying disease was diagnosed, in spite of medical examinations. Finally, in April 1944, [[leukemia]] was diagnosed, but by this time, little could be done {{harv|Chalmers|1995|loc=202–07}}.

As his body slowly failed, Bartók found more creative energy, and he produced a final set of masterpieces, partly thanks to the violinist [[Joseph Szigeti]] and the conductor [[Fritz Reiner]] (Reiner had been Bartók's friend and champion since his days as Bartók's student at the Royal Academy). Bartók's last work might well have been the String Quartet No. 6 but for [[Serge Koussevitzky]]'s [[commission (art)|commission]] for the [[Concerto for Orchestra (Bartók)|Concerto for Orchestra]]. Koussevitsky's [[Boston Symphony Orchestra]] premièred the work in December 1944 to highly positive reviews. The Concerto for Orchestra quickly became Bartók's most popular work, although he did not live to see its full impact. In 1944, he was also commissioned by [[Yehudi Menuhin]] to write a [[Sonata for Solo Violin (Bartók)|Sonata for Solo Violin]]. In 1945, Bartók composed his [[Piano Concerto No. 3 (Bartók)|Piano Concerto No. 3]], a graceful and almost neo-classical work, as a surprise 42nd birthday present for Ditta, but he died just over a month before her birthday, with the scoring not quite finished. He had also sketched his [[Viola Concerto (Bartók)|Viola Concerto]], but had barely started the scoring at his death, leaving completed only the viola part and sketches of the orchestral part.

[[File:HUF 1000 1983 obverse.jpg|thumb|Béla Bartók's portrait on 1,000 [[Hungarian forint]] banknote (printed between 1983 and 1992; no longer in circulation)]]
Béla Bartók died at age 64 in a hospital in New York City from complications of [[leukemia]] (specifically, of secondary [[polycythemia]]) on 26 September 1945. His funeral was attended by only ten people. Among them were his wife Ditta, their son Péter, and his pianist friend [[György Sándor]] {{harv|Anon.|2006}}.

Bartók's body was initially interred in [[Ferncliff Cemetery]] in Hartsdale, New York. During the final year of communist Hungary in the late 1980s, the Hungarian government, along with his two sons, Béla III and Péter, requested that his remains be exhumed and transferred back to [[Budapest]] for burial, where Hungary arranged a [[state funeral]] for him on 7 July 1988. He was reinterred at Budapest's [[Farkasréti Cemetery]], next to the remains of Ditta, who died in 1982, the year after his centenary {{harv|Chalmers |1995|loc=214}}.

The two unfinished works were later completed by his pupil [[Tibor Serly]]. György Sándor was the soloist in the first performance of the Third Piano Concerto on February&amp;nbsp;8, 1946. Ditta Pásztory-Bartók later played and recorded it. The Viola Concerto was revised and published in the 1990s by Bartók's son, Peter {{harv|Maurice|2004|loc={{Page needed|date=October 2017}}}}; this version may be closer to what Bartók intended {{harv|Chalmers|1995|loc=210}}.

Concurrently, Peter Bartók, in association with Argentinian musician [[Nelson Dellamaggiore]], worked to reprint and revise past editions of the Third Piano Concerto {{harv|Somfai|1996}}.

==Statues==
[[File:Statue of Béla Bartók.JPG|thumb|right|Statue of Bartók in [[Makó]], Hungary]]
* A statue of Bartók stands in Brussels, Belgium, near the [[Brussels Central Station|central train station]] in a public square, Spanjeplein-Place d'Espagne ({{harvnb|Anon.|2014}}; {{harvnb|Dicaire|2010|loc=145}})
* A statue stands outside Malvern Court, London, south of the [[South Kensington tube station]], and just north of 7 Sydney Place, where he stayed when performing in London. An [[English Heritage]] [[blue plaque]], unveiled in 1997, now commemorates Bartók at 7 Sydney Place ({{harvnb|Anon.|n.d.(a)}}; {{harvnb|Jones|2012}}).
* A statue of him was installed in front of the house in which Bartók spent his last eight years in Hungary, at Csalán út 29, in the hills above Budapest. It is now operated as the Béla Bartók Memorial House (Bartók Béla Emlékház) {{harv|Tudzin|2010}}.
* A bust and plaque located at his last residence, in New York City at 309 W. [[57th Street (Manhattan)|57th Street]], inscribed: &quot;The Great Hungarian Composer / Béla Bartók / (1881–1945) / Made His Home In This House / During the Last Year of His Life&quot; {{harv|Matthews|2012}}
* A bust of him is located in the front yard of [[Ankara State Conservatory]], Ankara, Turkey, right next to the bust of [[Ahmet Adnan Saygun]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2014}}
* A bronze statue of Bartók, sculpted by Imre Varga in 2005, stands in the front lobby of the Royal Conservatory of Music, 273 Bloor Street West, Toronto, Ontario, Canada.
* A statue of Bartók, sculpted by Imre Varga, stands near the river [[Seine]] in the public park at {{ill|Square Béla Bartók|fr}}, 26 place de Brazzaville, in Paris, France {{harv|Anon.|n.d.(b)}}.
* Also to be noted, in the same park, a sculptural transcription of the composer's research on tonal harmony, the fountain/sculpture ''Cristaux'' designed by [[Jean-Yves Lechevallier]] in 1980.
* An expressionist sculpture by Hungarian sculptor [[András Beck]] in {{ill|Square Henri-Collet|fr}}, Paris [[16th arrondissement of Paris|16th arrondissement]].
* A statue of him also stands in the city centre of [[Târgu Mureș]], Romania.{{citation needed|date=July 2019}}

==Music==
{{Further|List of compositions by Béla Bartók|List of solo piano compositions by Béla Bartók}}

Bartók's music reflects two trends that dramatically changed the sound of music in the 20th century: the breakdown of the [[diatonic]] system of harmony that had served composers for the previous two hundred years {{harv|Griffiths|1978|loc=7}}; and the revival of nationalism as a source for musical inspiration, a trend that began with [[Mikhail Glinka]] and [[Antonín Dvořák]] in the last half of the 19th century {{harv|Einstein|1947|loc=332}}. In his search for new forms of tonality, Bartók turned to Hungarian folk music, as well as to other folk music of the [[Carpathian Basin]] and even of Algeria and Turkey; in so doing he became influential in that stream of modernism which exploited indigenous music and techniques {{harv|Botstein|[n.d.]|loc=§6}}.

One characteristic style of music is his [[Night music (Bartók)|Night music]], which he used mostly in slow movements of multi-movement ensemble or orchestral compositions in his mature period. It is characterised by &quot;eerie dissonances providing a backdrop to sounds of nature and lonely melodies&quot; {{harv|Schneider|2006|loc=84}}. An example is the third movement (Adagio) of his ''Music for Strings, Percussion and Celesta''.

His music can be grouped roughly in accordance with the different periods in his life.

===Early years (1890–1902)===
The works of Bartók's youth were written in a classical and early romantic style touched with influences of popular and Gypsy music {{harv|Citron|1963|loc={{Page needed|date=September 2018}}}}. Between 1890 and 1894 (nine to 13 years of age) he wrote 31 piano pieces with corresponding opus numbers. Although most of these were simple dance pieces, in these early works Bartók began to tackle some more advanced forms, as in his ten-part programmatic ''A Duna folyása'' (&quot;The Course of the Danube&quot;, 1890–94), which he played in his first public recital in 1892 {{harv|Cooper|2015|loc=11}}.

In Catholic grammar school Bartók took to studying the scores of composers &quot;from [[Bach]] to [[Wagner]]&quot; {{harv|Moreux|1974|loc=18}}, his compositions then advancing in style and taking on similarities to [[Schumann]] and [[Brahms]] {{harv|Cooper|2015|loc=14}}. Following his matriculation into the Budapest Academy in 1890 he composed very little, though he began to work on exercises in orchestration and familiarized himself thoroughly with the operas of Wagner {{harv|Stevens|1993|loc=12}}. In 1902 his creative energies were revitalized by the discovery of the music of Richard Strauss, whose tone poem ''Also sprach Zarathustra'', according to Bartók, &quot;stimulated the greatest enthusiasm in me; at last I saw the way that lay before me.&quot; Bartók also owned the score to [[Ein Heldenleben|''A Hero's Life'']], which he transcribed for the piano and committed to memory {{harv|Stevens|1993|loc=15–16}}.

===New influences (1903–11)===
Under the influence of Strauss, Bartók composed in 1903 ''Kossuth'', a symphonic poem in ten tableaux on the subject of the 1848 Hungarian war of independence, reflecting the composers growing interest in musical nationalism {{harv|Stevens|1993|loc=17}}. A year later he renewed his opus numbers with the [[Rhapsody, Op. 1 (Bartók)|''Rhapsody for Piano and Orchestra'']] serving as Opus 1. Driven by nationalistic fervor and a desire to transcend the influence of prior composers, Bartók began a lifelong devotion to folk music which was sparked by his overhearing nanny Lidi Dósa's singing of Transylvanian folk songs at a Hungarian resort in 1904 {{harv|Stevens|1993|loc=22}}. Bartók began to collect Magyar peasant melodies, later extending to the folk music of other peoples of the Carpathian Basin {{harv|Moreux|1974|loc=60}}. His compositional output would gradually prune away romantic elements in favour of an idiom that embodied folk music as intrinsic and essential to its style. Later in life he would have this to say on the incorporation of folk and art music:

&lt;blockquote&gt;The question is, what are the ways in which peasant music is taken over and becomes transmuted into modern music? We may, for instance, take over a peasant melody unchanged or only slightly varied, write an accompaniment to it and possibly some opening and concluding phrases. This kind of work would show a certain analogy with Bach's treatment of chorales. ... Another method ... is the following: the composer does not make use of a real peasant melody but invents his own imitation of such melodies. There is no true difference between this method and the one described above. ... There is yet a third way ... Neither peasant melodies nor imitations of peasant melodies can be found in his music, but it is pervaded by the atmosphere of peasant music. In this case we may say, he has completely absorbed the idiom of peasant music which has become his musical mother tongue. {{harv|Fisk|1997|loc=271}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Bartók became first acquainted with Debussy's music in 1907 and regarded his music highly. In an interview in 1939 Bartók said
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Debussy's great service to music was to reawaken among all musicians an awareness of harmony and its possibilities. In that, he was just as important as Beethoven, who revealed to us the possibilities of progressive form, or as Bach, who showed us the transcendent significance of counterpoint. Now, what I am always asking myself is this: is it possible to make a synthesis of these three great masters, a living synthesis that will be valid for our time? {{harv|Moreux|1953|loc=92}} &lt;/blockquote&gt; Debussy's influence is present in the Fourteen Bagatelles (1908). These made [[Ferruccio Busoni]] exclaim 'At last something truly new!' {{harv|Bartók|1948|loc=2:83&lt;!--It would be preferable to cite the letter from the English edition, for the benefit of readers not fluent in Hungarian.--&gt;}}. Until 1911, Bartók composed widely differing works which ranged from adherence to romantic-style, to folk song arrangements and to his modernist opera ''Bluebeard's Castle''. The negative reception of his work led him to focus on folk music research after 1911 and abandon composition with the exception of folk music arrangements ({{harvnb|Gillies|1993|loc=404}}; {{harvnb|Stevens|1964|loc=47–49}}).

===New inspiration and experimentation (1916–21)===
His pessimistic attitude towards composing was lifted by the stormy and inspiring contact with Klára Gombossy in the summer of 1915 {{harv|Gillies|1993|loc=405}}. This interesting episode in Bartók's life remained hidden until it was researched by Denijs Dille between 1979 and 1989 {{harv|Dille|1990|loc=257–77}}. Bartók started composing again, including the Suite for piano opus 14 (1916), and ''The Miraculous Mandarin'' (1918) and he completed ''The Wooden Prince'' (1917).

Bartók felt the result of World War I as a personal tragedy {{harv|Stevens|1993|loc=3&lt;!--If the page number is from the first edition of 1953, this may require correction. The ISBN cited in the bibliography was for the third edition of 1993.--&gt;}}. Many regions he loved were severed from [[Hungary]]: [[Transylvania]], the [[Banat]] where he was born, and Pozsony where his mother lived. Additionally, the political relations between Hungary and the other successor states to the [[Austro-Hungarian empire]] prohibited his folk music research outside of Hungary {{harv|Somfai|1996|loc=18}}. Bartók also wrote the noteworthy ''[[Eight Improvisations on Hungarian Peasant Songs]]'' in 1920, and the sunny ''[[Dance Suite (Bartók)|Dance Suite]]'' in 1923, the year of his second marriage.

===&quot;Synthesis of East and West&quot; (1926–45)===
In 1926, Bartók needed a significant piece for piano and orchestra with which he could tour in Europe and America. In the preparation for writing his [[Piano Concerto No. 1 (Bartók)|First Piano Concerto]], he wrote his Sonata, ''[[Out of Doors (Bartók)|Out of Doors]]'', and ''Nine Little Pieces'', all for solo piano {{harv|Gillies|1993|loc=173}}. He increasingly found his own voice in his maturity. The style of his last period—named &quot;Synthesis of East and West&quot; {{harv|Gillies|1993|loc=189}}—is hard to define let alone to put under one term. In his mature period, Bartók wrote relatively few works but most of them are large-scale compositions for large settings. Only his voice works have programmatic titles and his late works often adhere to classical forms.{{citation needed|date=November 2018}}

Among his most important works are all the six [[List of string quartets by Béla Bartók|string quartets]] (1908, 1917, 1927, 1928, 1934, and 1939), the ''[[Cantata Profana]]'' (1930, Bartók declared that this was the work he felt and professed to be his most personal &quot;credo&quot; {{harv|Szabolcsi|1974|loc=186}}, the ''Music for Strings, Percussion and Celesta'' (1936) {{harv|Gillies|2001}}, the Concerto for Orchestra (1943) and the Third Piano Concerto (1945) {{harv|Cooper|2015|loc={{Page needed|date=January 2019}}}}.

Bartók also made a lasting contribution to the literature for younger students: for his son Péter's music lessons, he composed ''[[Mikrokosmos (Bartók)|Mikrokosmos]]'', a six-volume collection of graded piano pieces {{harv|Gillies|2001}}.

==Musical analysis==
[[File:Bartok Bela Baja.jpg|thumb|right|Béla Bartók memorial plaque in [[Baja, Hungary]]]]
[[File:Musik Meile Wien, Béla Bartók (30).jpg|thumb|upright|''Walk of Fame Vienna'']]
[[Paul Wilson (music theorist)|Paul Wilson]] lists as the most prominent characteristics of Bartók's music from late 1920s onwards the influence of the [[Carpathian basin]] and European art music, and his changing attitude toward (and use of) tonality, but without the use of the traditional [[Diatonic functionality|harmonic functions]] associated with major and minor scales {{harv|Wilson|1992|loc=2–4}}.

Although Bartók claimed in his writings that his music was always tonal, he rarely uses the chords or scales of tonality, and so the descriptive resources of tonal theory are of limited use. [[George Perle|George]] {{harvtxt|Perle|1955}} and Elliott {{harvtxt|Antokoletz|1984}} focus on alternative methods of signaling tonal centers, via axes of inversional symmetry. Others view Bartók's axes of symmetry in terms of atonal analytic protocols. [[Richard Cohn|Richard]] {{harvtxt|Cohn|1988}} argues that [[Inversion (music)#Inversional equivalency|inversional symmetry]] is often a byproduct of another atonal procedure, the formation of chords from transpositionally related dyads. Atonal pitch-class theory also furnishes the resources for exploring [[polymodal chromaticism]], [[projected set]]s, [[privileged pattern]]s, and large set types used as source sets such as the equal tempered twelve tone [[tone row#total chromatic|aggregate]], [[octatonic scale]] (and [[alpha chord]]), the diatonic and ''heptatonia secunda'' seven-note scales, and less often the whole tone scale and the primary pentatonic collection {{harv|Wilson|1992|loc=24–29}}.

He rarely used the simple aggregate actively to shape musical structure, though there are notable examples such as the second theme from the first movement of his Second Violin Concerto, commenting that he &quot;wanted to show [[Arnold Schoenberg|Schoenberg]] that one can use all twelve tones and still remain tonal&quot; {{harv|Gillies|1990|loc=185}}. More thoroughly, in the first eight measures of the last movement of his Second Quartet, all notes gradually gather with the twelfth (G{{music|♭}}) sounding for the first time on the last beat of measure 8, marking the end of the first section. The aggregate is partitioned in the opening of the Third String Quartet with C{{music|♯}}–D–D{{music|♯}}–E in the accompaniment (strings) while the remaining pitch classes are used in the melody (violin 1) and more often as 7–35 (diatonic or &quot;white-key&quot; collection) and 5–35 (pentatonic or &quot;black-key&quot; collection) such as in no. 6 of the ''Eight Improvisations''. There, the primary theme is on the black keys in the left hand, while the right accompanies with triads from the white keys. In measures 50–51 in the third movement of the Fourth Quartet, the first violin and cello play black-key chords, while the second violin and viola play stepwise diatonic lines {{harv|Wilson|1992|loc=25}}. On the other hand, from as early as the Suite for piano, Op. 14 (1914), he occasionally employed a form of [[serialism]] based on compound interval cycles, some of which are maximally distributed, multi-aggregate cycles ({{harvnb|Martins|2006}}; {{harvnb|Gollin|2007}}).

[[Ernő Lendvai]] analyses Bartók's works as being based on two opposing tonal systems, that of the [[acoustic scale]] and the [[axis system]], as well as using the [[golden ratio|golden section]] as a structural principle {{harv|Lendvai|1971}}.

[[Milton Babbitt]], in his 1949 critique of Bartók's string quartets, criticized Bartók for using tonality and non tonal methods unique to each piece. Babbitt noted that &quot;Bartók's solution was a specific one, it cannot be duplicated&quot; {{harv|Babbitt|1949|loc=385}}. Bartók's use of &quot;two organizational principles&quot;—tonality for large scale relationships and the piece-specific method for moment to moment thematic elements—was a problem for Babbitt, who worried that the &quot;highly attenuated tonality&quot; requires extreme non-harmonic methods to create a feeling of closure {{harv|Babbitt|1949|loc=377–78}}.

==Catalogues and opus numbers==
The cataloguing of Bartók's works is somewhat complex. Bartók assigned opus numbers to his works three times, the last of these series ending with the Sonata for Violin and Piano No. 1, Op. 21 in 1921. He ended this practice because of the difficulty of distinguishing between original works and ethnographic arrangements, and between major and minor works. Since his death, three attempts—two full and one partial—have been made at cataloguing. The first, and still most widely used, is [[András Szőllősy]]'s chronological Sz. numbers, from 1 to 121. {{ill|Denijs Dille|nl}} subsequently reorganised the juvenilia (Sz. 1–25) thematically, as DD numbers 1 to 77. The most recent catalogue is that of [[László Somfai]]; this is a chronological index with works identified by BB numbers 1 to 129, incorporating corrections based on the Béla Bartók Thematic Catalogue.{{Citation needed|date=November 2007}}

On 1 January 2016, his works entered the [[public domain]] in the [[European Union]] {{harv|Anon.|2016}}.

==Discography==

Together with his like-minded contemporary [[Zoltán Kodály]], Bartók embarked on an extensive programme of field research to capture the folk and peasant melodies of [[Hungarian language|Magyar]], [[Slovak language|Slovak]] and Rumanian language territories {{harv|Moreux|1974|loc=60}}. At first they would transcribe the melodies by hand, but later they began to use a wax cylinder recording machine invented by [[Thomas Edison]] {{harv|Music|2018}}. Compilations of Bartók's field recordings, interviews, and original piano playing have been released over the years, largely by the Hungarian record label [[Hungaroton]]:
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Bartók|1994}}|reference=Bartók, Béla. 1994. ''Bartók at the Piano''. Hungaroton 12326. 6-CD set.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Bartók|1995a}}|reference=Bartók, Béla. 1995a. ''Bartók Plays Bartók – Bartók at the Piano 1929–41''. Pearl 9166. CD recording.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Bartók|1995b}}|reference=Bartók, Béla. 1995b. ''Bartók Recordings from Private Collections''. Hungaroton 12334. CD recording.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Bartók|2003}}|reference=Bartók, Béla. 2003. ''Bartók Plays Bartók''. Pearl 179. CD recording.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Bartók|2007}}|reference= Bartók, Béla. 2007. ''Bartók: Contrasts, Mikrokosmos''. Membran/Documents 223546. CD recording.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Bartók|2008}}|reference= Bartók, Béla. 2008. ''Bartók Plays Bartók''. Urania 340. CD recording.}}
* &lt;!-- {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Bartók|2016}}|reference= --&gt;Bartók, Béla. 2016. ''Bartók the Pianist''. Hungaroton HCD32790-91. Two CDs. Works by Bartók, Domenico Scarlatti, Zoltán Kodály, and Franz Liszt. &lt;!-- }} --&gt;
A compilation of field recordings and transcriptions for two violas was also recently released by Tantara Records in 2014 {{harv|Fulop et al.|2014}}.

On 18 March 2016 [[Decca Classics]] released ''Béla Bartók: The Complete Works'', the first ever complete compilation of all of Bartók's compositions, including new recordings of never-before-recorded early piano and vocal works. However, none of the composer's own performances are included in this 32-disc set {{harv|Binder et al.|2016}}.

==References==
{{div col|colwidth=45em}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Anon.|n.d.(a)}}|reference=Anon. n.d.(a) &quot;[http://www.english-heritage.org.uk/discover/blue-plaques/search/bartok-bela-1881-1945 Bartók, Béla (1881–1945) Plaque erected in 1997 by English Heritage at 7 Sydney Place, South Kensington, London SW7 3NL, Royal Borough of Kensington and Chelsea]&quot;. English Heritage website (Accessed 19 October 2012).}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Anon.|n.d.(b)}}|reference=Anon. n.d.(b). &quot;[http://www.eutouring.com/square_bela_bartok.html Square Béla Bartók in Paris]&quot; Eutouring.com website (2 August) (accessed 4 July 2014).}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Anon.|n.d.(c)}}|reference=Anon. n.d.(c). &quot;[https://www.arcanum.hu/hu/online-kiadvanyok/Nagyivan-nagy-ivan-magyarorszag-csaladai-1/kilencedik-kotet-796B/polereczky-csalad-85C6/#Nagyivan%5EDestination-1667 Polereczky család]&quot;. Arcanum.hu website (accessed 30 December 2019).}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Anon.|1945}}|reference=Anon. 1945. {{cite news|url=https://archive.nytimes.com/www.nytimes.com/learning/general/onthisday/bday/0325.html|title=Béla Bartók Dies In Hospital Here|work=archive.nytimes.com}} (27 September).}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Anon.|2006}}|reference=Anon. 2006. &quot;[http://www.juilliard.edu/update/journal/j_articles785.html Gyorgy Sandor, Pianist and Bartók Authority, Dies at 93]&quot;. ''The Juilliard Journal Online'' 21, no. 5 (February) (accessed 15 September 2010).}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Anon.|2014}}|reference=Anon. 2014. [http://www.brusselsremembers.com/memorials/bela-bartok Statue: Béla Bartók]. Brussels Remembers: Memorials of Brussels (accessed 17 June 2014).}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Anon.|2016}}|reference=Anon. 2016. [https://law.duke.edu/cspd/publicdomainday/2016/ Public Domain Day 2016]. [[Center for the Study of the Public Domain]] (accessed 15 October 2018)}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Anon.|2018}}|reference=Anon. 2018. &quot;[http://www.boosey.com/pages/cr/composer/composer_main?composerid=2694&amp;ttype=BIOGRAPHY Béla Bartók]&quot;. Boosey &amp; Hawkes website (accessed 27 September 2018).}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Antokoletz|1984}}|reference=Antokoletz, Elliott. 1984. ''The Music of Béla Bartók: A Study of Tonality and Progression in Twentieth-Century Music''. Berkeley and Los Angeles: University of California Press. {{ISBN|0-520-04604-8}}.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Babbitt|1949}}|reference=[[Milton Babbitt|Babbitt, Milton]]. 1949. &quot;The String Quartets of Bartók&quot;. ''Musical Quarterly'' 35 (July): 377–85. Reprinted in ''The Collected Essays of Milton Babbitt'', edited by Stephen Peles, with Stephen Dembski, Andrew Mead, and Joseph N. Straus, [http://press.princeton.edu/chapters/s7616.pdf 1–9]. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2003. {{ISBN|0-691-08966-3}}.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Bartók|1948}}|reference=Bartók, Béla. 1948. ''Levelek, fényképek, kéziratok, kották.'' [Letters, photographs, manuscripts, scores], ed. János Demény, 2 vols. A Muvészeti Tanács könyvei, 1.–2. sz. Budapest: Magyar Muvészeti Tanács. English edition, as ''Béla Bartók: Letters'', translated by Péter Balabán and István Farkas; translation revised by Elisabeth West and Colin Mason (London: Faber and Faber Ltd.; New York: St. Martin's Press, 1971). {{ISBN|978-0-571-09638-1}}}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Bartók|1976}}|reference=Bartók, Béla. 1976. ''Essays'', selected and edited by Benjamin Suchoff. The New York Bartók Archive Studies in Musicology, No. 8. London: Faber &amp; Faber; New York: St. Martin's Press. {{ISBN|978-0-571-10120-7}}.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Binder et al.|2016}}|reference=Binder, [rest of authors needed]. 2016. {{Full citation needed|date=September 2018}}.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Botstein|[n.d.]}}|reference=[[Leon Botstein|Botstein, Leon]]. [n.d.]  &quot;Modernism&quot;, ''Grove Music Online'', ed. L. Macy (Accessed 29 April 2008), [http://www.grovemusic.com (subscription access)].}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Chalmers|1995}}|reference=Chalmers, Kenneth. 1995. ''Béla Bartók''. 20th-Century Composers. London: Phaidon Press. {{ISBN|0-7148-3164-6}} (pbk).}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Citron|1963}}|reference=Citron, Pierre. 1963. ''Bartók''. {{Full citation needed|date=September 2018}}.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Cohn|1988}}|reference=Cohn, Richard, 1988. &quot;Inversional Symmetry and Transpositional Combination in Bartók.&quot; ''Music Theory Spectrum'' 10:19–42.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Cooper|2015}}|reference=Cooper, David. 2015. ''Béla Bartók''. New Haven and London: Yale University Press. {{ISBN|978-0-300-21307-2}}.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|de Toth|1999}}|reference=de Toth, June. 1999. &quot;Béla Bartók: A Biography&quot;. [https://web.archive.org/web/20070408124358/http://www.bartokcds.com/bio.html Béla Bartók Biography Liner notes to ''Béla Bartók: Complete Piano Works''] 7-CD set, Eroica Classical Recordings{{Full citation needed|date=November 2007}}&lt;!--Catalog number(s) needed--&gt;.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Dicaire|2010}}|reference=Dicaire, David. 2010. ''The Early Years of Folk Music: Fifty Founders of the Tradition''. Jefferson, N.C.: McFarland. {{ISBN|9780786457373}}.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Dille|1990}}|reference=Dille, Denijs. 1990. Béla Bartók: Regard sur le Passé. (French, no English version available). Namur: Presses universitaires de Namur. {{ISBN|2-87037-168-3|978-2-87037-168-8}}.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Einstein|1947}}|reference=[[Alfred Einstein|Einstein, Alfred]]. 1947. ''Music in the Romantic Era''. New York: W. W. Norton.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Fisk|1997}}|reference=Fisk, Josiah (ed.). 1997. ''Composers on Music: Eight Centuries of Writings: A New and Expanded Revision of Morgenstern's Classic Anthology''. Boston: Northeastern University Press. {{ISBN|9781555532796}}.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Fulop et al.|2014}}|reference=Fulop, {{Full citation needed|date=September 2018}}&lt;!--Fulop's first name, and the other four or more authors' names needed.--&gt; ''Voices From The Past: Béla Bartók's 44 Duos &amp; Original Field Recordings''. Tantara Records.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Gagné|2012}}|reference=Gagné, Nicole V. 2012. ''Historical Dictionary of Modern and Contemporary Classical Music''. Historical Dictionaries of Literature and the Arts. Lanham, Maryland: Scarecrow Press. {{ISBN|978-0-8108-6765-9}}.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Gillies|1990}}|reference=[[Malcolm Gillies|Gillies, Malcolm]] (ed.). 1990. ''Bartók Remembered''. London: Faber. {{ISBN|0-571-14243-5}} (cased) {{ISBN|0-571-14244-3}} (pbk).}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Gillies|1993}}|reference=Gillies, Malcolm (ed.). 1993. ''The Bartók Companion''. London: Faber. {{ISBN|0-571-15330-5}} (cloth), {{ISBN|0-571-15331-3}} (pbk); New York: Hal Leonard. {{ISBN|0-931340-74-8}}.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Gillies|2001}}|reference=Gillies, Malcolm. 2001. &quot;Béla Bartók&quot;. ''The New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians'', second edition, edited by [[Stanley Sadie]] and [[John Tyrrell (musicologist)|John Tyrrell]]. London: Macmillan Publishers. Also in ''Grove Music Online'', ed. L. Macy (Accessed 23 May 2006), [http://www.grovemusic.com (subscription access)].}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Gollin|2007}}|reference=Gollin, Edward. 2007. &quot;Multi-Aggregate Cycles and Multi-Aggregate Serial Techniques in the Music of Béla Bartók&quot;. ''Music Theory Spectrum'' 29, no. 2 (Fall): 143–76.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Griffiths|1978}}|reference=[[Paul Griffiths (writer)|Griffiths, Paul]]. 1978. ''A Concise History of Modern Music''. London: Thames and Hudson. {{ISBN|0-500-20164-1}}.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Griffiths|1988}}|reference=Griffiths, Paul. 1988. ''Bartók''. London: JM Dent &amp; Sons Ltd.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Hooker|2001}}|reference=Hooker, Lynn. 2001. &quot;The Political and Cultural Climate in Hungary at the Turn of the Twentieth Century&quot;. In ''[https://books.google.com/books/about/The_Cambridge_Companion_to_Bartók.html?id=4uInwtVVfxMC The Cambridge Companion to Bartók]'', edited by Amanda Bayley, 7–23. [[Cambridge Companions to Music]]. Cambridge and New York: Cambridge University Press. {{ISBN|0-521-66010-6}} (cloth); {{ISBN|0-521-66958-8}} (pbk).}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Hughes|1999–2007}}|reference=Hughes, Peter. 1999–2007. &quot;[https://web.archive.org/web/20131207194032/https://www25.uua.org/uuhs/duub/articles/belabartok.html Béla Bartók]&quot; in ''Dictionary of Unitarian and Universalist Biography''. [n.p.]: Unitarian Universalist Historical Society. Archive from 7 December 2013 (accessed 24 October 2017).}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Jones|2012}}|reference=Jones, Tom. 2012. &quot;[http://www.tiredoflondontiredoflife.com/2012/10/see-bela-bartok.html See Béla Bartók]&quot;. Tired of London, Tired of Life blog site (8 October) (accessed 4 July 2014).}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Kory|2007}}|reference=Kory, Agnes. 2007. &quot;[http://www.bbcm.co.uk/main/fiddle.htm#1 Kodály, Bartók, and Fiddle Music in Bartók's Compositions]&quot;.  Béla Bartók Centre for Musicianship website (accessed 27 September 2018).}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Lendvai|1971}}|reference=[[Ernő Lendvai|Lendvai, Ernő]]. 1971. ''Béla Bartók: An Analysis of His Music'', introduced by [[Alan Bush]]. London: Kahn &amp; Averill. {{ISBN|0-900707-04-6}} {{oclc|240301}}.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Martins|2006}}|reference=Martins, José António Oliveira. 2006. &quot;Dasian, Guidonian, and Affinity Spaces in Twentieth-century Music&quot;. Ph.D. diss. Chicago: University of Chicago.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Matthews|2012}}|reference=Matthews, Peter. 2012. &quot;[http://www.feastofmusic.com/feast_of_music/2012/01/bart%C3%B3k-in-new-york.html Bartók in New York]&quot;. Feast of Music website #1Lib1Ref (accessed 26 September 2018).}}{{unreliable source?|reason=blog site|date=September 2018}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Maurice|2004}}|reference=Maurice, Donald. 2004. ''[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=sI4sRzCR-s8C&amp;pg=PA205&amp;lpg=PA205 Bartók's Viola Concerto: The Remarkable Story of His Swansong]''. Oxford and New York: Oxford University Press. {{ISBN|978-0-19-534811-8}} (accessed 19 October 2017)}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Moreux|1953}}|reference=Moreux, Serge. 1953. ''Béla Bartók'', translated [[G. S. Fraser]] and [[Erik de Mauny]]. London: The Harvill Press.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Moreux|1974}}|reference=Moreux. 1974. ''Béla Bartók'', translated [[G. S. Fraser]] and [[Erik de Mauny]], with a preface by [[Arthur Honegger]]. Partial reprint of {{harv|Moreux|1953}}. New York: Vienna House.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Móser|2006a}}|reference=Móser, Zoltán. 2006a. &quot;[http://epa.oszk.hu/00700/00713/00175/pdf/2006_03.pdf Szavak, feliratok, kivonatok]&quot;. ''Tiszatáj'' 60, no. 3 (March): 41–45.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Music|2018}}|reference=Music, Chester. 2018. &quot;Music: Béla Bartók Romanian Folk Dances&quot;.{{Full citation needed|date=September 2018}}&lt;!--If this is an article, then the journal title, volume, and page range are needed; if a book, then the title should be italicized, and the place, publisher, and ISBN are needed.--&gt;.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Özgentürk|2008}}|reference=Özgentürk, Nebil. 2008. ''Türkiye'nin Hatıra Defteri'', episode 3. Istanbul: Bir Yudum İnsan Prodüksiyon LTD. ȘTİ. Turkish CNN television documentary series.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Perle|1955}}|reference=[[George Perle|Perle, George]]. 1955. &quot;Symmetrical Formations in the String Quartets of Béla Bartók&quot;. ''Music Review'' 16, no. 4 (November 1955). Reprinted in ''The Right Notes: Twenty-Three Selected Essays by George Perle on Twentieth-Century Music'', foreword by Oliver Knussen, introduction by David Headlam, 189–205. Monographs in Musicology. Stuyvesant, NY: Pendragon Press. {{ISBN|0-945193-37-8}}.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Rockwell|1982}}|reference=[[John Rockwell|Rockwell, John]]. 1982. &quot;Kodaly Was More Than a Composer&quot;. ''The New York Times'' (12 December).}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Rodda|1990–2018}}|reference=Rodda, Richard E. 1990–2018. &quot;[http://www.kennedy-center.org/artist/composition/2236 String Quartet No. 1 in A minor, Op. 7/Sz 40: About the Work]&quot;. The Kennedy Center website (accessed 27 September 2018).}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Schneider|2006}}|reference=Schneider, David E. 2006. ''Bartók, Hungary, and the Renewal of Tradition: Case Studies in the Intersection of Modernity and Nationality''. California Studies in 20th-Century Music 5. Berkeley: University of California Press. {{ISBN|978-0-520-24503-7}}.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Sipos|2000}}|reference=Sipos, János (ed.). 2000. ''In the Wake of Bartók in Anatolia 1: Collection Near Adana''. Budapest: Ethnofon Records.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Somfai|1996}}|reference=[[László Somfai|Somfai, László]]. 1996. ''Béla Bartók: Composition, Concepts, and Autograph Sources''. Ernest Bloch Lectures in Music 9. Berkeley : University of California Press. {{ISBN|978-0-520-08485-8}}.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Stevens|1964}}|reference=Stevens, Halsey. 1964. ''The Life and Music of Béla Bartók'', second edition. New York: Oxford University Press. ASIN: B000NZ54ZS (Third edition, prepared by Malcolm Gillies, 1993, {{ISBN|978-0-19-816349-7}}).}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Stevens|1993}}|reference=Stevens, Halsey. 1993. ''The Life and Music of Béla Bartók'', third edition, prepared by Malcolm Gillies. New York: Oxford University Press. {{ISBN|978-0-19-816349-7}}.}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Stevens|2018}}|reference=Stevens, Halsey. 2018. &quot;[https://www.britannica.com/biography/Bela-Bartok#ref84023 Béla Bartók: Hungarian Composer]&quot;. ''Encyclopædia Britannica'' online (accessed 27 September 2018).}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Suchoff|2001}}|reference=Suchoff, Benjamin. 2001 ''[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=a1YQBD2ERgUC Béla Bartók: Life and Work]''. Lanham, Maryland: Scarecrow Press. {{ISBN|978-0-8108-4076-8}} – via Google Books. (2001) (accessed 29 July 2019).}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Szabolcsi|1974}}|reference=Szabolcsi, Bence. 1974. &quot;Bartók Béla: Cantata profana&quot;. In &quot;Miért szép századunk zenéje?&quot; (Why is the music of the Twentieth century so beautiful), ed. György Kroó. Budapest.{{Full citation needed|date=January 2014}}&lt;!--Inclusive page numbers of Szabolcsi's chapter are needed, as well as the book's publisher. An ISBN would also be helpful.--&gt;}}
*{{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Szekernyés|2017}}|reference=Szekernyés János. 2017. &quot;[https://muvelodes.net/enciklopedia/bartokek-nagyszentmikloson Bartókék Nagyszentmiklóson]&quot; [Bartók in Nagyszentmiklós]. ''Művelődés'' 70 (July) (accessed 10 March 2019).}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Tudzin|2010}}|reference=Tudzin, Jessica Taylor. 2010. &quot;[https://web.archive.org/web/20140714181240/http://www.bohemianink.net/?p=1384 Schooled in Bartók]&quot;. Bohemian Ink blog site (2 August) (accessed 4 July 2014).}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Vetter|2007}}|reference=Vetter, Herbert. 2007. ''[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=w5vIopoWMaUC&amp;pg=PA22 Notable American Unitarians 1936–1961]''. {{Full citation needed|date=April 2018}}}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|title=Richard Strauss – An intimate Portrait|last1=Wilhelm|first1=Kurt|date=1989|publisher=Thames and Hudson|location=London}}
* {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Wilson|1992}}|reference=Wilson, Paul. 1992. ''The Music of Béla Bartók''. New Haven: Yale University Press. {{ISBN|0-300-05111-5}}.}}
{{div col end}}

==Further reading==
{{div col|colwidth=45em}}
* Anon. 2003. &quot;[http://www.websophia.com/faces/bartok.html Béla Bartók 1881–1945]&quot;. ''[http://www.websophia.com/ Websophia.com]''. (Accessed 25 March 2009)
* Bartók, Béla. 1976. &quot;The Influence of Peasant Music on Modern Music (1931)&quot;. In ''Béla Bartók Essays'', edited by Benjamin Suchoff, 340–44. London: [[Faber &amp; Faber]]. {{ISBN|0-571-10120-8}} {{oclc|60900461}}
* &lt;!-- {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Bartók|1981}}|reference= --&gt;Bartók, Béla. 1981. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=DxsJAQAAMAAJ&amp;q=szuhafo+bartok&amp;dq=szuhafo+bartok The Hungarian Folk Song]'', second English edition, edited by Benjamin Suchoff, translated by Michel D. Calvocoressi, with annotations by Zoltán Kodály. The New York Bartók Archive Studies in Musicology 13. Albany: State University of New York Press. &lt;!-- }} --&gt;
* Bartók, Peter. 2002. &quot;My Father&quot;. Homosassa, Florida, Bartók Records ({{ISBN|0-9641961-2-3}}).
* &lt;!-- {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Bayley|2001}}|reference= --&gt;Bayley, Amanda (ed.). 2001. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=4uInwtVVfxMC&amp;pg=PA16 The Cambridge Companion to Bartók]''. [[Cambridge Companions to Music]]. Cambridge and New York: Cambridge University Press. {{ISBN|0-521-66010-6}} (cloth); {{ISBN|0-521-66958-8}} (pbk). &lt;!-- }} --&gt;
* Bónis, Ferenc. 2006. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=W7-iAQAACAAJ&amp;dq=%C3%89LET-K%C3%89PEK:+BART%C3%93K+B%C3%89LA Élet-képek: Bartók Béla]''. Budapest: Balassi Kiadó: Vávi Kft., Alföldi Nyomda Zrt. {{ISBN|963-506-649-X}}.
* Boys, Henry. 1945. &quot;Béla Bartók 1881–1945&quot;. ''[[The Musical Times]]'' 86, no. 1233 (November): 329–31.
* Cohn, Richard, 1992. &quot;Bartók's Octatonic Strategies: A Motivic Approach.&quot; ''Journal of the American Musicological Society'' 44
* Czeizel, Endre. 1992. ''Családfa: honnan jövünk, mik vagyunk, hová megyünk?'' [Budapest]: Kossuth Könyvkiadó. {{ISBN|963-09-3569-4}}
* &lt;!-- {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Decca|2016}}|reference= --&gt;Decca. 2016. &quot;[http://www.deccaclassics.com/gb/cat/4789311 Béla Bartók: Complete Works: Int. Release 18 Mar. 2016: 32 CDs, 0289 478 9311 0]&quot;. Welcome to Decca Classics: Catalogue, www.deccaclassics.com (accessed 19 August 2016).&lt;!-- }} --&gt;
* Jyrkiäinen, Reijo. 2012. &quot;Form, Monothematicism, Variation and Symmetry in Béla Bartók's String Quartets&quot;. Ph.D. diss. Helsinki: University of Helsinki. {{ISBN|978-952-10-8040-1}} ([https://helda.helsinki.fi/handle/10138/33683 Abstract]).
* Kárpáti, János. 1975. ''Bartók's String Quartets'', translated by Fred MacNicol. Budapest: Corvina Press.
* Kasparov, Andrey. 2000. &quot;Third Piano Concerto in the Revised 1994 Edition: Newly Discovered Corrections by the Composer&quot;. ''Hungarian Music Quarterly'' 11, nos. 3–4:2–11.
* Leafstedt, Carl S. 1999. ''Inside Bluebeard's Castle''. New York: Oxford University Press. {{ISBN|0-19-510999-6}}
* &lt;!-- {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Lendvai|1972}}|reference= --&gt;Lendvai, Ernő. 1972. &quot;Einführung in die Formen- und Harmoniewelt Bartóks&quot; (1953). In his ''Béla Bartók: Weg und Werk'', edited by [[Bence Szabolcsi]], 105–49. Kassel: Bärenreiter.&lt;!-- }} --&gt;
* Loxdale, Hugh D., and Adalbert Balog. 2009. &quot;Béla Bartók: Musician, Musicologist, Composer, and Entomologist!.&quot; ''Antenna'' – Bulletin of the [[Royal Entomological Society of London]] 33, no. 4:175–82.
* &lt;!-- {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Maconie|2005}}|reference= --&gt;[[Robin Maconie|Maconie, Robin]]. 2005. ''Other Planets: The Music of Karlheinz Stockhausen''. Lanham, MD, Toronto, Oxford: The Scarecrow Press, Inc. {{ISBN|978-0-8108-5356-0}}.&lt;!-- }} --&gt;
* &lt;!-- {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Martins|2015}}|reference= --&gt;Martins, José Oliveira. 2015. &quot;Bartók's Polymodality: the Dasian and other Affinity Spaces&quot;. ''Journal of Music Theory'' 59, no. 2 (October): 273–320. &lt;!-- }} --&gt;
* Móser, Zoltán. 2006b. &quot;Bartók-õsök Gömörben&quot;. [http://www.hnm.hu/honismeret/folyoirat/2006-2-honismeret1.pdf ''Honismeret: A Honismereti Szövetség folyóirata'' ]{{dead link|date=November 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }} 34, no. 2 (April): 9–11.
* [http://digitalcommons.cedarville.edu/musicalofferings/vol3/iss2/2 Nelson, David Taylor (2012). &quot;Béla Bartók: The Father of Ethnomusicology&quot;, Musical Offerings: Vol. 3: No. 2, Article 2.]
* Sluder, Claude K. 1994. &quot;Revised Bartók Composition Highlights Pro Musica Concert&quot;. ''[[The Republic (Columbus)|The Republic]]'' (16 February).
* &lt;!-- {{wikicite|ref={{harvid|Smith|1965}}|reference= --&gt;Smith, Erik. 1965. ''A discussion between [[István Kertész (conductor)|István Kertész]] and the producer''. DECCA Records (liner notes for ''[[Bluebeard's Castle]]'').&lt;!-- }} --&gt;
* Somfai, László. 1981. ''Tizennyolc Bartók-tanulmány'' [Eighteen Bartók Studies]. Budapest: Zeneműkiadó. {{ISBN|963-330-370-2}}.
* Wells, John C. 1990. &quot;Bartók&quot;, in ''Longman Pronunciation Dictionary'', 63. Harlow, England: Longman. {{ISBN|0-582-05383-8}}.
{{div col end}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
{{Wikiquote}}
* {{Britannica|54394}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Béla Bartók}}
* [http://www.lieder.net/lieder/b/bartok.html The Lied and Art Song Texts Page]{{dead link|date=November 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }} Original texts of the songs of Bartók with translations in various languages.
* [http://www.bartokmuseum.hu Bartók Béla Memorial House, Budapest]
* [http://bartok.kbr.be The Belgian Bartók Archives, housed in the Brussels Royal Library and founded by Denijs Dille]
* {{BBC composer page|bartok|Bartók}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070927070327/http://www.gallery-diabolus.com/gallery/artist.php?language=english&amp;id=utisz&amp;page=205%2F Gallery of Bartók portraits]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20160312045308/http://www.zti.hu/bartok/exhibition/main.htm Virtual Exhibition on Bartók]
{{ContemporaryMusicOnline|Bartok|works}}
* {{IMSLP|Bartók, Béla}}
* [http://www.soundfountain.org/rem/dongabor2.html#bartok Bartók plays Bartók for Don Gabor's Continental record label later reissued on Remington Records]

{{Béla Bartók}}
{{Modernist composers}}
{{Musical nationalism}}
{{Portal bar|Biography|Classical music}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bartok, Bela}}
[[Category:Béla Bartók| ]]
[[Category:1881 births]]
[[Category:1945 deaths]]
[[Category:20th-century classical composers]]
[[Category:Anton Rubinstein Competition prize-winners]]
[[Category:Ballet composers]]
[[Category:Composers for piano]]
[[Category:Burials at Ferncliff Cemetery]]
[[Category:Burials at Farkasréti Cemetery]]
[[Category:Deaths from cancer in New York (state)]]
[[Category:Deaths from leukemia]]
[[Category:Ethnomusicologists]]
[[Category:Franz Liszt Academy of Music alumni]]
[[Category:Franz Liszt Academy of Music faculty]]
[[Category:Hungarian classical composers]]
[[Category:Hungarian classical pianists]]
[[Category:Male pianists]]
[[Category:Hungarian educators]]
[[Category:Hungarian emigrants to the United States]]
[[Category:Hungarian entomologists]]
[[Category:Hungarian folk-song collectors]]
[[Category:Hungarian music educators]]
[[Category:Hungarian opera composers]]
[[Category:Hungarian people of German descent]]
[[Category:Hungarian refugees]]
[[Category:Hungarian song collectors]]
[[Category:Hungarian atheists]]
[[Category:Hungarian Unitarians]]
[[Category:Hungarian male classical composers]]
[[Category:Male opera composers]]
[[Category:Members of the Hungarian Academy of Sciences]]
[[Category:Members of the Romanian Academy elected posthumously]]
[[Category:Modernist composers]]
[[Category:People from Sânnicolau Mare]]
[[Category:People from Saranac Lake, New York]]
[[Category:Pupils of István Thomán]]
[[Category:Pupils of Hans von Koessler]]
[[Category:String quartet composers]]
[[Category:20th-century musicologists]]
[[Category:Former Roman Catholics]]</text>
      <sha1>2qb8x81mbt19lx2werlkvihfcquki48</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
