  <page>
    <title>Beaver</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4399</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943120841</id>
      <parentid>942745643</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T23:46:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Purplebackpack89</username>
        <id>8259432</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Others */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Genus of mammals}}
{{About|all beaver species worldwide|the North American beaver|North American beaver|the Eurasian beaver|Eurasian beaver|the unrelated genus of mountain beaver|Mountain beaver|other uses|Beaver (disambiguation)}}
{{pp-semi-protected|small=yes}}
{{pp-move-indef|small=yes}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=June 2012}}
{{Automatic taxobox
| name              = Beaver 
|latin              = Nabil 
| fossil_range      = {{fossil range|24|0}}&lt;small&gt;Late [[Miocene]]{{nbsp}}– Recent&lt;/small&gt;
| image             = American Beaver.jpg
| image_caption     = [[North American beaver]] (''Castor canadensis'')
| taxon             = Castor
| authority         = [[Carl Linnaeus|Linnaeus]], [[10th edition of Systema Naturae|1758]]
| subdivision_ranks = Species
| subdivision       = ''[[Eurasian beaver|C. fiber]]'' – Eurasian beaver&lt;br /&gt;''[[North American beaver|C. canadensis]]'' – North American beaver&lt;br /&gt;
†''[[Castor californicus|C. californicus]]''
}}

The '''beaver''' ([[genus]] '''''Castor''''') is a large, primarily [[nocturnal animal|nocturnal]], [[List of semiaquatic tetrapods|semiaquatic]] [[rodent]]. ''Castor'' includes two [[extant taxon|extant]] species, the [[North American beaver]] (''Castor canadensis'') (native to North America) and [[Eurasian beaver]] (''[[Eurasian beaver|Castor fiber]]'') ([[Eurasia]]).&lt;ref name = MSW3&gt;{{MSW3 Castoridae | id = 12600003 | pages = 842–843 | heading = Genus ''Castor''}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beavers are known for building dams, canals, and lodges (homes). They are the second-largest rodent in the world (after the [[capybara]]). Their colonies create one or more dams to provide still, deep water to protect against predators, and to float food and building material. The North American beaver population was once more than 60 million, but as of 1988 was 6–12 million. This population decline is the result of extensive hunting for fur, for glands used as medicine and perfume, and because the beavers' harvesting of trees and flooding of waterways may interfere with other land uses.&lt;ref name=&quot;MotW5&quot;&gt;Nowak, Ronald M. 1991. pp. 364–367. ''Walker's Mammals of the World'' Fifth Edition, vol. I. Johns Hopkins University Press, Baltimore.&lt;/ref&gt;

==General==
Beavers, along with [[Geomyidae|pocket gophers]] and [[Heteromyidae|kangaroo rats]], are [[Castorimorpha|castorimorph]] rodents, a suborder of rodents mostly restricted to North America. Although just two closely related species exist today, beavers have a long fossil history in the Northern Hemisphere beginning in the [[Eocene]], and many species of giant beaver existed until quite recently, such as ''[[Trogontherium]]'' in Europe, and ''[[Castoroides]]'' in North America.
[[File:American Beaver, tree cutting.jpg|thumb|A beaver using its teeth to cut down a tree]]
Beavers are known for their natural trait of building dams on rivers and streams, and building their homes (known as &quot;lodges&quot;) in the resulting pond. Beavers also build canals to float building materials that are difficult to haul over land.&lt;ref name=Salvesen&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Salvesen|first1=Sigvald|title=The Beaver in Norway |date=May 1928|pages=99–104 |doi=10.2307/1373424|volume=9|issue=2|journal=Journal of Mammalogy|jstor=1373424}}&lt;!--|accessdate=2 April 2015--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.animaltrial.com/beaver/beaverdamandcanals.html|title=Beaver Dams and Canals|publisher=animaltrail|accessdate=June 26, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; They use powerful front teeth to cut trees and other plants that they use both for building and for food. In the absence of existing ponds, beavers must construct dams before building their lodges. First they place vertical poles, then fill between the poles with a crisscross of horizontally placed branches. They fill in the gaps between the branches with a combination of weeds and mud until the dam impounds sufficient water to surround the lodge.

They are known for their alarm signal: when startled or frightened, a swimming beaver will rapidly dive while forcefully slapping the water with its broad tail, audible over great distances above and below water. This serves as a warning to beavers in the area. Once a beaver has sounded the alarm, nearby beavers will dive and may not reemerge for some time. Beavers are slow on land, but are good swimmers, and can stay under water for as long as 15 minutes.

Beavers do not hibernate, but store sticks and logs in a pile in their ponds, eating the underbark. Some of the pile is generally above water and accumulates snow in the winter. This insulation of snow often keeps the water from freezing in and around the food pile, providing a location where beavers can breathe when outside their lodge.
[[File:Picture Natural History - No 40 41 42 - Beaver feet and tail.png|thumb|left|The fore foot, hind foot, and tail of a beaver. The hind feet of beavers are [[webbed foot|webbed]].]]
Beavers have [[webbed foot|webbed hind-feet]], and a broad, scaly tail. They have poor eyesight, but keen senses of hearing, smell, and touch. A beaver's teeth grow continuously so they will not be worn down by chewing on wood.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.beaversolutions.com/about_beaver_biology.asp |title=Beaver Biology |publisher=Beaver Solutions |accessdate=2010-03-15 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100414110435/http://www.beaversolutions.com/about_beaver_biology.asp |archivedate=April 14, 2010 |url-status=dead |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Their four incisors are composed of hard orange enamel on the front and a softer [[dentin]] on the back. The chisel-like ends of incisors are maintained by their self-sharpening wear pattern. The enamel in a beaver's incisors contains iron and is more resistant to acid than enamel in the teeth of other mammals.&lt;ref name=NW&gt;{{cite web|author1=Megan Fellman|title=Making Teeth Tough: Beavers Show Way To Improve Our Enamel (Discovery could lead to better understanding of tooth decay process, early detection)|url=http://www.northwestern.edu/newscenter/stories/2015/02/making-teeth-tough-beavers-show-way-to-improve-our-enamel-.html|website=www.northwestern.edu|accessdate=February 19, 2015|date=February 12, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Beavers continue to grow throughout their lives. Adult specimens weighing over {{convert|25|kg|lb|abbr=on}} are not uncommon. Females are as large as or larger than males of the same age, which is uncommon among [[mammal]]s. Beavers live up to 24 years of age in the wild.

==Etymology==
The English word &quot;beaver&quot; comes from the [[Old English]] word ''beofor'' or ''befer'' (recorded earlier as ''bebr''), which in turn sprang from the [[Proto-Germanic language|Proto-Germanic]] root ''*bebruz''. [[Cognate]]s in other [[Germanic languages]] include the [[Old Saxon]] ''bibar'', the [[Old Norse]] ''bjorr'', the [[Middle Dutch]] and [[Dutch language|Dutch]] ''bever'', the [[Low German]] ''bever'', the [[Old High German]] ''bibar'' and the [[German language|Modern German]] ''Biber''. The Proto-Germanic word in turn came from the [[Proto-Indo-European language|Proto-Indo-European]] (PIE) word ''*bhebhrus'', a reduplication of the PIE root ''*bher-'', meaning &quot;brown&quot; or &quot;bright&quot;, whose own descendants now include the [[Lithuanian language|Lithuanian]] ''bebras'' and the [[Czech language|Czech]] ''bobr'', as well as the Germanic forms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=beaver|title=Online Etymology Dictionary|publisher=|accessdate=January 18, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Species==
[[File:Castor fiber vs. Castor canadensis skulls.jpg|thumb|Skulls of a [[Eurasian beaver]] and a [[North American beaver]].]]
The North American and Eurasian beavers are the only [[extant taxon|extant]] members of the [[family (biology)|family]] [[Castoridae]], contained within the [[Monotypic taxon|monotypic]] [[genus]], ''Castor''. [[genetics|Genetic]] research has shown the modern European and North American beaver populations to be distinct species and that [[hybrid (biology)|hybridization]] is unlikely. Although superficially similar to each other, there are several important differences between the two species. Eurasian beavers tend to be slightly larger, with larger, less rounded heads, longer, narrower muzzles, thinner, shorter and lighter underfur, narrower, less oval-shaped tails and shorter shin bones, making them less capable of bipedal locomotion than the North American species. Eurasian beavers have longer nasal bones than their North American cousins, with the widest point being at the end of the snout for the former, and in the middle for the latter. The nasal opening for the Eurasian species is triangular, unlike that of the North American race, which is square. The ''[[foramen magnum]]'' is rounded in the Eurasian beaver and triangular in the North American. The [[anal gland]]s of the Eurasian beaver are larger and thin-walled with a large internal volume compared to that of the North American species. The guard hairs of the Eurasian beaver have a longer hollow medulla at their tips. Fur colour is also different. Overall, 66% of Eurasian beavers have pale brown or beige fur, 20% have reddish brown, nearly 8% are brown and only 4% have blackish coats. In North American beavers, 50% have pale brown fur, 25% are reddish brown, 20% are brown and 6% are blackish.&lt;ref name=&quot;andy&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Kitchener, Andrew |url= |title=Beavers |year=2001 |isbn=978-1-873580-55-4 |page=144 |publisher=Whittet |location=Stowmarket }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The two species are not genetically compatible. North American beavers have 40 [[chromosomes]], while Eurasian beavers have 48. More than 27 attempts were made in Russia to hybridize the two species, with one breeding between a male North American beaver and a female European resulting in a single stillborn kit. These factors make interspecific breeding unlikely in areas where the two species' ranges overlap.&lt;ref name=&quot;andy&quot; /&gt;

===Eurasian beaver===
{{Main|Eurasian beaver}}
[[File:Castor fiber eating in Eskilstuna, Sweden.jpg|thumb|A Eurasian beaver feeding.]]
The Eurasian beaver (''Castor fiber'') was hunted nearly to [[extinction]] in Europe, both for fur and for ''[[castoreum]]'', a secretion from its scent gland believed to have medicinal properties. However, the beaver is now being re-introduced throughout Europe. Several thousand live on the [[Elbe]] and the [[Rhône]] and in parts of [[Scandinavia]]. A thriving community lives in northeast Poland, and the Eurasian beaver also returned to the [[Morava (river)|Morava River]] banks in Slovakia and the Czech Republic. They have been [[reintroduction|reintroduced]] in Scotland ([[Knapdale]]),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2008/may/26/endangeredspecies.conservation |title=Beavers returning to UK after 400 years |work=The Guardian | location=London | first=Severin | last=Carrell | date=26 May 2008 | accessdate=2010-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bavaria]], Austria, Netherlands, Serbia ([[Zasavica (bog)|Zasavica]] bog), Denmark (West [[Jutland]]) and Bulgaria and are spreading to new locations. The beaver became extinct in Great Britain in the sixteenth century: [[Giraldus Cambrensis]] reported in 1188 (''Itinerarium'' ii.iii) that it was to be found only in the [[Teifi]] in Wales and in one river in Scotland, though his observations are clearly second hand. In 2001, [[Kent Wildlife Trust]] successfully introduced a family of beavers at Ham Fen, the last remaining ancient fenland in the county close to the town of [[Sandwich, Kent|Sandwich]]; these are now established and are breeding. In October 2005, six Eurasian beavers were reintroduced to Britain in Lower Mill Estate in [[Gloucestershire]]; in July 2007 a colony of four Eurasian beavers was established at [[Martin Mere]] in Lancashire,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/england/lancashire/6291260.stm |title=Beavers are back after 500 years |date=11 July 2007 |work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a small population of probably Eurasian beavers is being monitored in Devon.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-31019595|title='Mystery' beavers permitted to stay|first=Claire|last=Marshall|date=January 28, 2015|publisher=|accessdate=January 18, 2017|via=www.bbc.co.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt; A trial re-introduction occurred in Scotland in May 2009. Feasibility studies for a reintroduction to Wales are at an advanced stage and a preliminary study for a reintroduction of beavers to the wild in England has recently been published.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msn.co.uk/htx/returnofthebeaver/|title=MSN UK - Outlook.com formerly Hotmail, Skype, Bing and Latest News|publisher=|accessdate=January 17, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/scotland/7158210.stm |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080206025535/http://www.msn.co.uk/htx/returnofthebeaver/| archivedate=February 6, 2008|publisher=BBC |title=Beavers could be released in 2009 |date=24 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===North American beaver===
{{Main|North American beaver}}
[[File:Castor canadensis1.jpg|thumb|left|A North American beaver shortly after leaving the water.]]
The North American beaver (''Castor canadensis''), also called the Canadian beaver (which is also the name of a subspecies), American beaver, or simply beaver in North America, is native to Canada, much of the United States and the states of Sonora and Chihuahua in northern Mexico.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Status of beaver (Castor canadensis frondator) in Río Bavispe, Sonora, Mexico |author=Juan Pablo Gallo-Reynoso, Gabriela Suarez-Gracida, Horacia Cabrera-Santiago, Elsa Coria-Galindo, Janitzio Egido-Villarreal, and Leo C. Ortiz |journal=Southwestern Naturalist |volume=47 |issue=3 |pages=501–504 |year=2002 |jstor=3672516|doi=10.2307/3672516 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Habitat and Conservation Status of the Beaver in the Sierra San Luis Sonora, México |authors=Karla Pelz Serrano, Eduardo Ponce Guevara, and Carlos A. López González |journal=USDA Forest Service Proceedings RMRS-P-36 |url=https://www.fs.fed.us/rm/pubs/rmrs_p036/rmrs_p036_429_433.pdf |accessdate=December 5, 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Nice surprise: camera discovers that there are otters in Chihuahua |author=El Heraldo de Chihuahua |newspaper=El Sol de Mexico |date=December 5, 2017 |url=https://www.elsoldemexico.com.mx/doble-via/ecologia/bonita-sorpresa-camara-descubre-que-hay-nutrias-en-chihuahua-385554.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; This species was introduced to the Argentine and Chilean Tierra del Fuego, as well as Finland, France, Poland and Russia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Engineering by an invasive species alters landscape-level ecosystem function, but does not affect biodiversity in freshwater systems |authors=Christopher B. Anderson, María Vanessa Lencinas, Petra K. Wallem, Alejandro E. J. Valenzuela, Michael P. Simanonok and Guillermo Martinez Pastur |journal=Diversity and Distributions |volume=20 |issue=2 |year=2013 |pages=1–9 |doi=10.1111/ddi.12147}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Genetic Variation and Population Structure of the Eurasian Beaver Castor Fiber in Eastern Europe and Asia |authors=Jean-Francois Ducroz, Michael Stubbe, Alexander P Saveljev, Dietrich Heideke, Rivcan Samjaa, Alius Ulevicius, Annegret Stubbe, and Walter Durka |journal=Journal of Mammalogy |volume=86 |issue=6 |pages=1059–1067 |year=2005 |doi=10.1644/1545-1542(2005)86[1059:gvapso]2.0.co;2 |jstor=4094529|doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The North American beavers prefer the (inner) bark of aspen and poplar but will also take birch, maple, willow, alder, black cherry, red oak, beech, ash, hornbeam and occasionally pine and spruce.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Beaver: Natural History of a Wetlands Engineer |pages=67–75 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=eqIenKko3lAC|publisher=Cornell University Press |year=2003 |isbn=978-0-8014-4098-4 |author1=Müller-Schwarze, Dietland |author2=Sun, Lixing |lastauthoramp=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; They will also eat [[cattails]], [[Nymphaeaceae|water lilies]] and other aquatic vegetation, especially in the early spring (and contrary to widespread belief,&lt;ref&gt;Young, Mary Taylor (August 13, 2007).{{cite web|url=http://wildlife.state.co.us/Education/TeacherResources/ColoradoWildlifeCompany/CWCSum91Beavers.htm |title=Colorado Division of Wildlife: Do Beavers Eat Fish? |accessdate=2015-05-18 |url-status=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100910012112/http://wildlife.state.co.us/Education/TeacherResources/ColoradoWildlifeCompany/CWCSum91Beavers.htm |archivedate=September 10, 2010 |df=mdy }} wildlife.state.co.us&lt;/ref&gt; they do not eat fish).

These animals are often trapped for their fur. During the early 19th century, trapping eliminated this animal from large portions of its original range. Beaver furs were used to make clothing and top-hats. Much of the early exploration of North America was driven by the quest for this animal's fur.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mountainsofstone.com/oregon_country.htm Manifest Destiny: The Oregon Country and Westward Expansion] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100511214616/http://www.mountainsofstone.com/oregon_country.htm |date=May 11, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Innis
 | first = Harold A.
 | authorlink = Harold Innis
 | year = 1999
 | title = The Fur Trade in Canada: An Introduction to Canadian Economic History. Revised and reprinted.
 | publisher = University of Toronto Press
 | location = Toronto
 | isbn = 978-0-8020-8196-4
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;[http://imnh.isu.edu/digitalatlas/geog/explore/expand.pdf Idaho Museum of Natural History]&lt;/ref&gt;
Native peoples and early settlers also ate this animal's meat. The Federal Lacey Act was passed by the US Fish and Wildlife Service in 1900 which forbade any take of wildlife or plants in violation of Indian, State or foreign law.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.fws.gov/international/laws-treaties-agreements/us-conservation-laws/lacey-act.html|title=Lacey Act|website=www.fws.gov|access-date=2018-03-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Through trap and transfer and [[habitat conservation]], beavers made a nearly complete recovery by the 1940s.The current beaver population has been estimated to be 10 to 15 million; one estimate claims there may have been at one time as many as 90 million.&lt;ref&gt;Seton-Thompson, cited in {{cite book
  | last =Sun
  | first =Lixing
  |author2=Dietland Müller-Schwarze
  | title =''The Beaver: Natural History of a Wetlands Engineer''
  | publisher =Cornell University Press
  | year =2003
  | url =
  | id =
  | isbn = 978-0-8014-4098-4}} pp. 97–98; but note that to arrive at this figure he assumed a population density throughout the range equivalent to that in [[Algonquin Park]]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Habitat==
[[File:Beaver Dam.jpg|thumb|A beaver lodge at the edge of a stream. Beavers generally live in the [[riparian zone]], an area between the land and a river or stream.]]
The primary habitat of the beaver is the [[riparian zone]], inclusive of stream bed. The actions of beavers for hundreds of thousands of years &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.natureworldnews.com/articles/14917/20150529/new-beaver-species-discovered-in-oregon.htm|title=New Beaver Species Discovered in Oregon|last=NatureWorldNews|date=May 29, 2015|publisher=|accessdate=January 18, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; in the [[Northern Hemisphere]] have kept these watery systems healthy and in good repair. However, some beavers inhabit the [[intertidal zone]] in river estuaries, building dams to trap high tides in a beaver pond for similar purposes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Goldfarb |first1=Ben |title=The Gnawing Question of Saltwater Beavers |url=https://www.hakaimagazine.com/features/the-gnawing-question-of-saltwater-beavers/ |accessdate=1 February 2019 |work=[[Hakai magazine]] |date=29 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Hood |first1=W. Gregory |title=Beaver in Tidal Marshes: Dam Effects on Low-Tide Channel Pools and Fish Use of Estuarine Habitat |journal=Wetlands |volume=32 |issue=3 |pages=401–410 |date=16 February 2012 |doi=10.1007/s13157-012-0294-8 |url=https://beaverinstitute.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/TidalMarshBeavers2012.pdf |accessdate=1 February 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The beaver works as a [[keystone species]] in an [[ecosystem]] by creating [[wetlands]] that are used by many other species. Next to humans, no other extant animal appears to do more to shape its landscape.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Beaver (beavers 'second only to humans in their ability to manipulate and change their environment') |work=[[National Geographic]] |accessdate=October 6, 2019|url=https://www.nationalgeographic.com/animals/mammals/b/beaver/}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beavers potentially even affect [[climate change]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Wohl|first=Ellen|title=Landscape-scale carbon storage associated with Beaver Dams|journal=Geophysical Research Letters|year=2013|doi=10.1002/grl.50710|volume=40|issue=14|pages=3631–3636}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Beavers fell trees for several reasons. They fell large mature trees, usually in strategic locations, to form the basis of a dam, but European beavers tend to use small diameter (&lt;10{{nbsp}}cm) trees for this purpose. Beavers fell small trees, especially young second-growth trees, for food.

Broadleaved trees re-grow as a [[coppice]], providing easy-to-reach stems and leaves for food in subsequent years. Ponds created by beavers can also kill some tree species by drowning, but this creates standing dead wood, which is very important for a wide range of animals and plants.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://extension.psu.edu/natural-resources/wildlife/habitat-management/dead-wood-for-wildlife|title=Dead Wood for Wildlife (Wildlife Outreach Center)|website=Wildlife Outreach Center (Penn State Extension)|access-date=2016-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Dams===
{{Main|Beaver dam}}
{{Multiple image
| direction = horizontal
| align = left
| header = Beaver dam enlargement
| width1 = 165
| image1 = Beaver dam - geograph.org.uk - 1452003.jpg
| caption1 = September 2009
| width2 = 165
| image2 = Beaver dam - four months on - geograph.org.uk - 1623430.jpg
| caption2 = December 2009
| footer = Images of a beaver dam over a four month period. Beavers are able to enlarge their dams quickly.
}}
Beaver dams are created as a protection against predators, such as coyotes, wolves and bears, and to provide easy access to food during winter. Beavers always work at night and are prolific builders, carrying mud and stones with their fore-paws and timber between their teeth. Because of this, destroying a beaver dam without removing the beavers is difficult, especially if the dam is downstream of an active lodge. Beavers can rebuild such primary dams overnight, though they may not defend secondary dams as vigorously. Beavers may create a series of dams along a river.

===Lodges===
{{redirect|Beaver lodge|the town in Alberta, Canada|Beaverlodge}}
The ponds created by well-maintained dams help isolate the beavers' homes, which are called ''lodges''. These are created from severed branches and mud. The beavers cover their lodges late each autumn with fresh mud, which freezes when frosts arrive. The mud becomes almost as hard as stone, thereby preventing [[gray wolf|wolves]] and [[wolverine]]s from penetrating the lodge.
[[File:BeaverLodgeDiagram.svg|thumb|This diagram depicts the parts of a beaver lodge. A. vent, B. feeding chamber, C. nesting chamber, D. entrance]]
The lodge has underwater entrances, which makes entry nearly impossible for any other animal, although [[muskrats]] have been seen living inside beaver lodges with the beavers who made them.&lt;ref&gt;''The Life of Mammals'' Episode 4, &quot;Chisellers&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; Only a small amount of the lodge is actually used as a living area. Beavers dig out their dens with underwater entrances after they finish building the dams and lodge structures. There are typically two dens within the lodge, one for drying off after exiting the water and another, drier one, in which the family lives.

Beaver lodges are constructed with the same materials as the dams, with little order or regularity of structure. They seldom house more than four adults and six to eight juveniles. Some larger lodges have one or more partitions, but these are only posts of the main building left by the builders to support the roof. Usually, the dens have no connection with each other except by water.

When the ice breaks up in spring, beavers usually leave their lodges and roam until just before autumn, when they return to their old lodges and gather their winter stock of wood. They seldom begin to repair the lodges until the frost sets in, and rarely finish the outer coating until the cold becomes severe. When they erect a new lodge, they fell the wood early in summer but seldom begin building until nearly the end of August.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB11&quot;&gt;{{EB1911|inline=1 |wstitle=Beaver |volume=3 |page=600 |first=Richard |last=Lydekker |authorlink=Richard Lydekker}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Water quality and beavers===
[[File:Lundy Canyon Beaver Dam.jpg|thumb|left|A beaver dam at [[Mill Creek (Mono Lake)|Mill Creek]]. Beaver dams are able to remove sediment, and pollutants from waterways.]]
Beaver ponds, and the wetlands that succeed them, remove sediments and pollutants from waterways, including total suspended solids, total nitrogen, phosphates, carbon and silicates.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Beaver pond biogeochemical effects in the Maryland Coastal Plain |journal=Biogeochemistry |date=June 2000 |pages=217–239 |jstor=1469618 |author1=David L. Correll |author2=Thomas E. Jordan |author3=Donald E. Weller |volume=49 |issue=3 |doi=10.1023/a:1006330501887}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Muskopf&gt;{{cite thesis |title=The Effect of Beaver (Castor canadensis) Dam Removal on Total Phosphorus Concentration in Taylor Creek and Wetland, South Lake Tahoe, California |author=Sarah Muskopf |publisher=Humboldt State University, Natural Resources |date=October 2007 |hdl=2148/264 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term &quot;beaver fever&quot; is a misnomer coined by the American press in the 1970s, following findings that the parasite ''[[Giardia lamblia]]'', which causes [[Giardiasis]], is carried by beavers. However, further research has shown that many animals and birds carry this parasite, and the major source of water contamination is other humans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Reintroducing the European Beaver in Britain |journal=British Wildlife |year=2008 |url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/286869238 |accessdate=20 January 2018 |author1=Martin Gaywood |author2=Dave Batty |author3=Colin Galbraith }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= Waterborne giardiasis: sources of Giardia cysts and evidence pertaining to their implication in human infection in P. M. Wallis and B. R. Hammond (ed.), Advances in Giardia research. |year=1988 |pages=227–236 |publisher=University of Calgary Press |location=Calgary, Alberta, Canada |author1=Erlandsen, S. L. |author2=W. J. Bemrick  |lastauthoramp=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Prevalence of Giardia spp. in Beaver and Muskrat Populations in Northeastern States and Minnesota: Detection of Intestinal Trophozoites at Necropsy Provides Greater Sensitivity than Detection of Cysts in Fecal Samples |journal=Applied and Environmental Microbiology |date=January 1990 |pages=31–36 |pmc=183246|url=http://aem.asm.org/cgi/reprint/56/1/31?maxtoshow=&amp;hits=10&amp;RESULTFORMAT=&amp;fulltext=erlandsen&amp;searchid=1&amp;FIRSTINDEX=0&amp;resourcetype=HWCIT |accessdate=2011-03-05 |vauthors=Erlandsen SL, Sherlock LA, Bemrick WJ, Ghobrial H, Jakubowski W |pmid=2178552 |volume=56|issue=1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Norway has many beavers but has not historically had giardia, and New Zealand has giardia but no beaver. Recent concerns point to domestic animals as a significant vector of giardia, with young calves in dairy herds testing as high as 100% positive for giardia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=R. C. A. Thompson|date=November 2000|title=Giardiasis as a re-emerging infectious disease and its zoonotic potential|journal=International Journal for Parasitology|volume=30|issue=12–13|pages=1259–1267|doi=10.1016/S0020-7519(00)00127-2|pmid=11113253}}&lt;!--|accessdate=2011-03-05 --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, fecal coliform and streptococci bacteria excreted into streams by grazing cattle have been shown to be reduced by beaver ponds, where the bacteria are trapped in bottom sediments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Stream Water Quality as Influenced by Beaver within Grazing Systems in Wyoming |journal=Journal of Range Management |date=March 1984 |pages=142–146 |jstor=3898902 |author1=Quentin D. Skinner |author2=John E. Speck |author3=Michael Smith |author4=John C. Adams |volume=37 |issue=2 |doi=10.2307/3898902}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Urban beavers in North America===
[[File:Beaver fences High Park.jpg|thumb|Wire mesh fences installed around trees in [[High Park, Toronto|High Park]], [[Toronto]]. Cities in Canada occasionally use mesh fences to prevent beaver damage.&lt;ref name=mesh&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.toronto.ca/311/knowledgebase/kb/docs/articles/parks,-forestry-and-recreation/urban-forestry/trees-in-parks-and-ravines-beavers.html|title=Trees in parks &amp; ravines - beavers|publisher=City of Toronto|work=311 Toronto|year=2018|accessdate=29 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Beaver populations in Canadian cities have seen a resurgence in numbers in the decades since the decline of the fur trade.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.macleans.ca/news/canada/canadas-beaver-problem/|title=Canada's beaver problem|last=Campbell|first=Meagan|date=5 July 2017|accessdate=29 July 2019|publisher=Rogers Digital Media|work=Maclean's}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://globalnews.ca/news/2747760/hes-quite-shy-beaver-sightings-on-the-rise-in-calgary/|title='He's quite shy': Beaver sightings on the rise in Calgary|date=7 June 2016|work=Global News|publisher=Corus Entertainment Inc.|accessdate=29 July 2019|last=Smith|first=Kim}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Torbe&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/national/leave-it-to-beavers-theyre-loving-the-big-city-life/article4145097/|title=Leave it to beavers, they're loving the big-city life|work=The Globe and Mail|publisher=The Woodbridge Company|first=Martin|last=Mittelstaedt|date=5 March 2001|accessdate=29 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2016, approximately 200 beavers live within the city limits of [[Calgary]], while an estimated 100 beavers live in [[Winnipeg]].&lt;ref name=canurnu&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/british-columbia/vancouvers-urban-beaver-plan-focuses-on-enhancing-habitats/article28530523/|title=Vancouver's urban-beaver plan focuses on enhancing habitats|work=The Globe and Mail|publisher=The Woodbridge Company|accessdate=29 July 2019|date=2 February 2016|last=McCutcheon|first=Andrew}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the same year, it was estimated that several dozen beavers live within the city limits of [[Vancouver]].&lt;ref name=canurnu/&gt; [[Toronto]] does not keep count of its local beaver population,&lt;ref name=canurnu/&gt; although an estimate from 2001 places its local beaver population at several hundred.&lt;ref name=Torbe/&gt;

Several cities in the United States have seen the reintroduction of beavers within their city limits. Beavers were trapped to near [[Local extinction|extirpation]] and had not been seen in New York City since the early 1800s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Manhattan Before New York: When Henry Hudson first looked on Manhattan in 1609, what did he see? |author=Peter Miller |url=http://ngm.nationalgeographic.com/2009/09/manhattan/miller-text |journal=National Geographic |date=September 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; After 200 years, a beaver has returned to New York City, making its home along the [[Bronx River]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=New York City Beaver Returns |newspaper=Science Daily |url=https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2008/12/081218080817.htm |date=December 20, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In Chicago, several beavers have returned and made a home near the [[Lincoln Park]]'s North Pond. The &quot;[[Lincoln Park beaver]]&quot; has not been as well received by the [[Chicago Park District]] and the [[Lincoln Park]] Conservancy, which was concerned over damage to trees in the area. In March 2009, they hired an exterminator to remove a beaver family using live traps, and accidentally killed the mother when she got caught in a snare and drowned.&lt;ref name=&quot;Inside&quot;&gt;{{cite news |author=Boehm, Kiersten |title=Lincoln Park Beaver Relocated |newspaper=Inside at Your News Chicago, Illinois Edition |date=November 14, 2008 |url=http://www.insideonline.com/ |accessdate=December 4, 2009 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20091213145734/http://www.insideonline.com/| archivedate= December 13, 2009 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Outside San Francisco, in downtown [[Martinez, California]], a male and female beaver arrived in [[Alhambra Creek]] in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Moment of truth for Martinez beavers |author=Carolyn Jones |newspaper=San Francisco Chronicle |date=April 16, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Martinez beavers]] built a dam 30 feet wide and at one time six feet high, and chewed through half the willows and other creekside landscaping the city planted as part of its $9.7 million 1999 flood-improvement project. When the city council wanted to remove the beavers because of fears of flooding, local residents organized to protect them, forming an organization called &quot;Worth a Dam&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Worth a Dam website|url=http://www.martinezbeavers.org }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===As an introduced non-native species===
{{See also|Beaver eradication in Tierra del Fuego}}
[[File:Beaver damage navarino chile.JPG|thumb|left|Beaver damage on the north shore of Robalo Lake, [[Navarino Island]], Chile]]
In the 1940s, beavers were brought from northern Manitoba in Canada to the island of [[Tierra Del Fuego]] in southern [[Chile]] and [[Argentina]], for commercial fur production. However, the project failed and the beavers, ten pairs, were released into the wild. Having no natural predators in their new environment, they quickly spread throughout the island, and to other islands in the region, reaching a number of 100,000 individuals within just 50 years. They are now considered a serious [[invasive species]] in the region, due to their massive destruction of forest trees, and efforts are being made for their eradication.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://edition.cnn.com/NATURE/9907/09/argentina.beaver/ | work=CNN | title=Argentina eager to rid island of beavers | accessdate=May 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The drastically different ecosystem has led to substantial environmental damage, as the ponds created by the beavers have no ecological purpose (wetlands do not form there as they do in the beavers' native territory) and there are no native, large predators.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}} They have also been found to cross salt water to islands northward; a possible encroachment on the mainland has naturalists highly concerned.

In contrast, areas with introduced beaver were associated with increased populations of native [[Common galaxias|puye]] fish (''Galaxias maculatus''), whereas the exotic [[brook trout]] (''Salvelinus fontinalis'') and [[rainbow trout]] (''Oncorhynchus mykiss'') had negative effects on native stream fishes in the [[Cape Horn Biosphere Reserve]], Chile.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1577/T08-081.1 |title=Implications of Beaver Castor canadensis and Trout Introductions on Native Fish in the Cape Horn Biosphere Reserve, Chile |author1=Michelle C. Moorman |author2=David B. Eggleston |author3=Christopher B. Anderson |author4=Andres Mansilla |author5=Paul Szejner |journal=Transactions of the American Fisheries Society |volume=138 |year=2009 |pages=306–313 |issue=2 }}{{dead link|date=October 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Beavers are classed as a &quot;prohibited new organism&quot; under New Zealand's [[Hazardous Substances and New Organisms Act 1996]], preventing them from legally being imported into the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://legislation.govt.nz/act/public/1996/0030/latest/DLM386556.html#DLM386556|title=Hazardous Substances and New Organisms Act 2003 – Schedule 2 Prohibited new organisms|publisher=New Zealand Government|accessdate=January 26, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Social behavior==
===Family life===
[[File:Beaver 2.jpg|thumb|A pair of beavers. Beavers are monogamous, with a beaver's social organization consisting of a pair of adults, and its offspring.]]
The basic units of beaver social organization are families consisting of an adult male and adult female in a monogamous pair and their kits and yearlings.&lt;ref name= &quot;Lixing 2003&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Beaver: Natural History of a Wetlands Engineer |authors=Dietland Müller-Schwarze, Lixing Sun |page=80 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=eqIenKko3lAC&amp;q=estrus#v=onepage&amp;q=reproduction&amp;f=false |accessdate=2011-06-25 |publisher=Cornell University Press |year=2003 |isbn=978-0-8014-4098-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Beaver families can have as many as ten members in addition to the monogamous pair. Groups this size or close to this size build more lodges to live in while smaller families usually need only one.&lt;ref name= &quot;Lixing 2003&quot;/&gt; However, large families in the Northern Hemisphere have been recorded living in one lodge. Beaver pairs mate for life; however, if a beaver's mate dies, it will partner with another one. Extra-pair copulations also occur.&lt;ref name= &quot;Lixing 2003&quot;/&gt; In addition to being monogamous, both the male and female take part in raising offspring. They also both mark and defend the territory and build and repair the dam and lodge.&lt;ref name= &quot;Lixing 2003&quot;/&gt; When young are born, they spend their first month in the lodge and their mother is the primary caretaker while their father maintains the territory. In the time after they leave the lodge for the first time, yearlings will help their parents build food caches in the fall and repair dams and lodges. Still, adults do the majority of the work and young beavers help their parents for reasons based on natural selection rather than kin selection. They are dependent on them for food and for learning life skills.&lt;ref name= &quot;Lixing 2003&quot;/&gt; Young beavers spend most of their time playing but also copy their parents' behavior. However, while copying behavior helps imprint life skills in young beavers, it is not necessarily immediately beneficial for parents as the young beaver do not perform the tasks as well as the parents.&lt;ref name= &quot;Lixing 2003&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Beaver family upper Los Gatos Creek 2008 Mercury Freedom.jpg|thumb|left|A beaver family, with the centre pair grooming one another.]]
Older offspring, which are around two years old, may also live in families and help their parents. In addition to helping build food caches and repairing the dam, two-year-olds will also help in feeding, grooming and guarding younger offspring.&lt;ref name= &quot;Lixing 2003&quot;/&gt; Beavers also practice [[Alloparenting|alloparental care]], in which an older sibling may take over the parenting duties if the original parents die or are otherwise separated from them. This behavior is common and is seen in many other animal species, such as the elephant and [[fathead minnow]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Riedman | first1 = Marianne L. | year = 1982 | title = The Evolution of Alloparental Care in Mammals and Birds | url = | journal = The Quarterly Review of Biology | volume = 57 | issue = 4| pages = 405–435 | doi=10.1086/412936}}&lt;/ref&gt; While these helping two-year-olds help increase the chance of survival for younger offspring, they are not essential for the family, and two-year-olds stay and help their families only if there is a shortage of resources in times of food shortage, high population density, or drought.&lt;ref name= &quot;Lixing 2003&quot;/&gt; When beavers leave their natal territories, they usually do not settle far.&lt;ref name= &quot;Bjorkoyli 2002&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Bjorkoyli | first1 = Tore | last2 = Rosell | first2 = Frank | year = 2002 | title = A Test of the Dear Enemy Phenomenon in the Eurasian Beaver | url = https://semanticscholar.org/paper/9911bc0ec7109df24f75367f0c9c04411870db6a| journal = Animal Behaviour | volume = 63 | issue = 6| pages = 1073–78 | doi = 10.1006/anbe.2002.3010 | hdl = 11250/2437993 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Beavers can recognize their kin by detecting differences in anal gland secretion composition using their keen sense of smell.&lt;ref name= &quot;Lixing 1998&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Sun | first1 = Lixing | last2 = Muller-Schwarze | first2 = Dietland | year = 1998 | title = Anal Gland Secretion Codes for Relatedness in the Beaver, Castor Canadensis | url = | journal = Ethology | volume = 104 | issue = 11| pages = 917–27 | doi=10.1111/j.1439-0310.1998.tb00041.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; Related beavers share more features in their anal gland secretion profile than unrelated beavers.&lt;ref name= &quot;Lixing 1998&quot;/&gt; Being able to recognize kin is important for beaver social behavior, and it causes more tolerant behavior among neighboring beavers.&lt;ref name= &quot;Bjorkoyli 2002&quot;/&gt;

===Territories and spacing===
[[File:AmericanBeaver.JPG|thumb|A beaver atop its dam.]]
Beavers maintain and defend territories, which are areas for feeding, nesting and mating.&lt;ref name= &quot;Lixing 2003&quot;/&gt; They invest much energy in their territories, building their dams and becoming familiar with the area.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rosell 1997&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Rosell | first1 = Frank | last2 = Nolet | first2 = Bart A. | year = 1997 | title = Factors Affecting Scent-Marking Behavior in Eurasian Beaver (Castor Fiber) | url = https://teora.hit.no/bitstream/2282/322/1/JCE296.pdf | journal = Journal of Chemical Ecology | volume = 23 | issue = 3 | pages = 673–89 | doi = 10.1023/B:JOEC.0000006403.74674.8a | hdl = 11250/2438031 }}{{Dead link|date=July 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; Beavers mark their territories by constructing scent mounts made of mud, debris and castoreum,&lt;ref name= &quot;Rosell 2000&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Rosell | first1 = Frank | last2 = Czech | first2 = Andrezej | year = 2000 | title = Response of Foraging Eurasian Beavers Castor Fiber to Predator Odours | url = https://openarchive.usn.no/usn-xmlui/bitstream/11250/2438045/1/Wildlifeim.pdf | journal = Wildlife Biology | volume = 6 | issue = 1 | pages = 13–21 | doi = 10.2981/wlb.2000.033 | hdl = 11250/2438045 }}{{Dead link|date=December 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; a urine based substance excreted through the beavers [[castor sac]]s between the pelvis and base of the tail.&lt;ref name= &quot;Rosell 1997&quot;/&gt; These scent mounts are established on the border of the territory.&lt;ref name= &quot;Rosell 2000&quot;/&gt; Once a beaver detects another scent in its territory, finding the intruder takes priority, even over food.&lt;ref name= &quot;Rosell 2000&quot;/&gt;
Because they invest so much energy in their territories, beavers are intolerant of intruders and the holder of the territory is more likely to escalate an aggressive encounter.&lt;ref name= &quot;Rosell 1997&quot;/&gt; These encounters are often violent. To avoid such situations, a beaver marks its territory with as many scent mounds as possible, signaling to intruders that the territory holder has enough energy to maintain its territory and is thus able to put up a good defense. As such, territories with more scent mounts are avoided more often than ones with fewer mounts.&lt;ref name= &quot;Rosell 1997&quot;/&gt; Scent marking increases in August during the dispersal of yearlings, in an attempt to prevent them from intruding on territories.&lt;ref name= &quot;Rosell 1997&quot;/&gt; Beavers also exhibit a behavior known as the &quot;[[dear enemy effect]]&quot;. A territory-holding beaver will investigate and become familiar with the scents of its neighbors.&lt;ref name= &quot;Bjorkoyli 2002&quot;/&gt; As such they respond less aggressively to intrusions by their territorial neighbours than those made by non-territorial floaters or &quot;strangers&quot;.&lt;ref name= &quot;Bjorkoyli 2002&quot;/&gt;

Occurrences of beaver aggression, however, have been reported. In April 2013, an [[Angling|angler]], near Minkovichi in the [[Brest, Belarus|Brest region]] of [[Belarus]], died after being bitten twice on the leg by a wild Eurasian beaver.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/belarus/9987265/Beaver-bites-man-to-death.html |title=Beaver 'bites man to death' |author=Tom Parfitt |newspaper=[[The Daily Telegraph]] |date=11 April 2013 |accessdate=11 April 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Commercial uses==
{{further|Fur trade}}
[[File:Beaverbollocks.jpg|thumb|Depiction of a beaver hunt from a medieval [[bestiary]]. Beaver testicles has historically been an item of trade, for use in traditional medicine.]]
Both beaver [[testicles]] and [[castoreum]], a bitter-tasting secretion with a slightly fetid odor contained in the castor sacs of male or female beaver, have been articles of trade for use in traditional medicine. [[Yupik peoples|Yupik]] medicine used dried beaver testicles like willow bark to relieve pain. Dried beaver testicles were also used as contraception.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Stewart|first=William Brenton |title=Medicine in New Brunswick : a history of the practice of medicine{{nbsp}}... from prior to the arrival of the white man in America to the early part of the twentieth century|year=1974|publisher=The New Brunswick Medical Society|location=Moncton|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beaver testicles were used as medicine in Iraq and Iran during the tenth to nineteenth century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 12576209 | volume=85 | issue=1 | title=Traditional healing with animals (zootherapy): medieval to present-day Levantine practice |date=March 2003| journal=J Ethnopharmacol | pages=107–18 | author=Lev E | doi=10.1016/S0378-8741(02)00377-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Aesop]]'s ''Fables'' describes beavers chewing off their testicles to preserve themselves from hunters, which is not possible because the beaver's testicles are inside its body. This belief, also recorded by [[Pliny the Elder]], persisted in medieval [[bestiary|bestiaries]].&lt;ref&gt;Badke, David. [http://bestiary.ca/beasts/beast152.htm The Medieval Bestiary: Beaver]&lt;/ref&gt;

European beavers (''[[Castor fiber]]'') were eventually hunted nearly to extinction in part for the production of castoreum, which was used as an [[analgesic]], [[anti-inflammatory]], and [[antipyretic]]. Castoreum was described in the 1911 [[British Pharmaceutical Codex]] for use in [[dysmenorrhea]] and [[hysteria|hysterical]] conditions (i.e. pertaining to the womb), for raising [[blood pressure]] and increasing [[cardiac output]]. The activity of castoreum has been credited to the accumulation of [[salicin]] from willow trees in the beaver's diet, which is transformed to [[salicylic acid]] and has an action very similar to aspirin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.the-scientist.com/2005/03/28/S31/1/ |title=The quest for pain relief: how much have we improved on the past? |author=Stephen Pincock |date=28 March 2005 |accessdate=2007-06-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Castoreum continues to be used in perfume production.&lt;ref name=snopes&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.snopes.com/food/ingredient/castoreum.asp|title=Castoreum Is Produced from Beaver Secretions?|first=David|last=Mikkelson|publisher=|accessdate=January 18, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Castoreum can be used as an enhancer of vanilla, strawberry and raspberry flavorings. It is sometimes added to frozen dairy, gelatins, candy, and fruit beverages. Due to the difficulty and expense in obtaining castoreum, it is very rarely used in common food products.&lt;ref name=snopes /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Fenaroli's Handbook Of Flavor Ingredients'' puts total annual national consumption of castoreum, castoreum extract, and castoreum liquid at about 292 pounds, i.e. per capita consumption of castoreum extract is only .000081 mg/kg/day.&lt;/ref&gt;

Much of the early European exploration and trade of Canada was based on the quest for beaver.&lt;ref&gt;See [[Canadian canoe routes (early)]] and related articles.&lt;/ref&gt; The most valuable part of a beaver is its inner fur whose many minute barbs make it excellent for [[felt]]ing, especially for hats. In Canada a &quot;made beaver&quot; or ''castor gras'' that a [[Aboriginal peoples in Canada|native]] had worn or slept on was more valuable than a fresh skin since this tended to wear off the outer guard hairs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Brown |first1=Jennifer S.H. |title=Beaver Pelts |url=https://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.ca/en/article/beaver-pelts |website=The Canadian Encyclopedia |accessdate=14 February 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Trapping&lt;!-- [[Beaver pelt]] redirects to this heading --&gt;===
[[File:BeaverPelt (5118396762).jpg|thumb|A beaver pelt. Beaver pelts was the driving force of the [[North American fur trade]].]]
Beavers have been [[animal trapping|trapped]] for millennia, and this continues to this day.&lt;ref name=&quot;myfoxchicago.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Park District Kills Beaver in Lincoln Park |date=April 2009 |newspaper=MyFoxChicago.com |url=http://www.myfoxchicago.com/dpp/news/beaver_north_pond_apr09 |accessdate=December 4, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Beaver [[fur|pelts]] were used for [[barter (economics)|barter]] by [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Native Americans]] in the 17th century to gain European goods. They were then shipped back to Great Britain and France where they were made into clothing items. Widespread hunting and trapping of beavers led to their [[endangered species|endangerment]]. Eventually, the [[fur trade]] declined due to decreasing demand in Europe and the takeover of trapping grounds to support the growing agriculture sector. A small resurgence in beaver trapping has occurred in some areas where there is an over-population of beaver; trapping is done when the fur is of value, and the remainder of the animal may be used as feed. In the 1976/1977 season, 500,000 beaver pelts were harvested in North America.&lt;ref&gt;Nowak, Ronald M. 1991. pp. 638. ''Walker's Mammals of the World'' Fifth Edition, vol. I. Johns Hopkins University Press, Baltimore.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!--The only fur in North America surpassing the beaver's in commercial value was that of the silver morph [[red fox]], said to be forty times more valuable.&lt;ref name=&quot;NEC&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Morton, Thomas |title=New English Canaan: Or, New Canaan (Research Library of Colonial Americana) |year=1972 |page=188 |isbn=0-405-03309-5 |publisher=Arno Press |location=New York}}&lt;/ref&gt; What period was this?? Does this include domesticated animals ?? --&gt;

==In culture==
In wider culture, the beaver is famed for its industriousness and its building skills. The English verb &quot;to beaver&quot; means to work hard and constantly.

''[[Beverly (disambiguation)|Beverly]]'' or ''Beverley'', a placename found at various locations in the English-speaking world and also commonly used as a first name, derives from [[Old English]], combining the words ''befer'' (&quot;beaver&quot;) and ''leah'' (&quot;clearing&quot;).

The show ''[[Happy Tree Friends]]'' features Toothy and Handy who are beavers.

The animated Nickelodeon show ''[[The Angry Beavers]]'' features Daggett and Norbert.

The anthropomorphic [[Mr. and Mrs. Beaver]] have an important role in the plot of ''[[The Lion, the Witch and the Wardrobe]]'', first part of [[C.S.Lewis]]' ''The Chronicles of Narnia''.

The first ''[[Redwall (novel)|Redwall]]'' book features an unnamed beaver who helps Constance the badger build a bow, the only one ever seen before the books shifted to focus on animals commonly native to the British Isles.

The 2014 American [[Horror comedy (genre)|horror comedy]] film ''[[Zombeavers]]'', directed by Jordan Rubin, follows a group of college students on a camping trip that are attacked by a swarm of [[zombie]] beavers.

===As an emblem===
====National====
[[File:Beaver sculpture, Centre Block.jpg|thumb|Beaver sculpture over entrance to [[Canadian Parliament Buildings|Canadian Parliament Building]].]]
The importance of the beaver in the development of Canada through the fur trade led to its official designation as the [[List of national animals|national animal]] in 1975. The animal has long been associated with Canada, appearing on the coat of arms of the [[Hudson's Bay Company]] in 1678.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=White|first=Shelley|title=The Beaver As National Symbol: Why Is A Furry Mammal Still An Emblem of Canada?|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.ca/2011/07/01/canadian-symbols-beaver_n_886777.html#s300503&amp;title=Beaver|work=Huffington Post|accessdate=July 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is depicted on the [[Nickel (Canadian coin)|Canadian five-cent piece]] and was on the first pictorial postage stamp issued in the [[British North America|Canadian colonies]] in 1849 (the so-called &quot;[[Postage stamps and postal history of Canada|Three-Penny Beaver]]&quot;). As a [[national symbol]], the beaver was chosen to be the mascot of the [[1976 Summer Olympics]] held in [[Montreal]] with the name &quot;[[Amik]]&quot; (&quot;beaver&quot; in [[Ojibwe language|Ojibwe]]). The beaver is also the symbol of many units and organizations within the [[Canadian Forces]], such as on the cap badges of the [[Royal 22e Régiment|Royal 22&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; Régiment]], the [[Calgary Highlanders]], the [[Royal Westminster Regiment]] and the [[Canadian Military Engineers]]. [[Toronto Police Services]], [[London Police Service]], [[Canadian Pacific Railway Police Service]] and [[Canadian Pacific Railway]] bear the beaver on their crest or coat of arms.

====Others====
The beaver is used as a mascot of several colleges and universities, often universities with heritages in engineering and forestry.  Others who have used the beaver in their company or organizational symbol or as their mascot include:
{{col div}}
* [[The Beaver (magazine)]]
* [[Beaver Buzz]] energy drink
* [[Beaver Lumber]]
* [[Bemidji State University]]
* [[Beverley]], East Riding of Yorkshire, UK
* [[Buc-ee's]], a chain of [[convenience stores]] in [[Texas]]
* [[Buena Vista University]]
* [[California Institute of Technology]]
* [[Canadian Pacific Railway]]
* [[City College of New York]]
* [[F.C. Paços de Ferreira]]
* [[Harper Creek High School]] (Battle Creek, Michigan)
* [[Huron University College]]
* The [[London School of Economics]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://beginnings.ioe.ac.uk/begslse.html |title=AAC template |publisher=Beginnings.ioe.ac.uk |accessdate=2010-03-15 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090926011322/http://beginnings.ioe.ac.uk/begslse.html |archivedate=September 26, 2009 |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]
* [[McMaster University]] Society of Off-Campus Students
* [[Parks Canada]]
* New York City
* [[Oregon State University]]
* [[Roots Canada]] retail company
* [[St Anne's College, Oxford]]
* The State of New York
* The State of [[Oregon]]
* The [[University of Alberta]] Faculty of Engineering
* The [[University of Toronto]]
* [[Washington State Park System|Washington State Parks and Recreation Commission]]
* [[Wilfrid Laurier University]]
{{col div end}}

===In dietary law===
In the 17th century, based on a question raised by the [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Quebec|Bishop of Quebec]], the Roman Catholic Church ruled that beavers are fish (beaver flesh was a part of the Yuko&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Kuhnlein |first1=Harriet |title=Beaver |url=http://traditionalanimalfoods.org/mammals/furbearers/page.aspx?id=6142 |website=Traditional Animal Foods of Indigenous Peoples of Northern North America |publisher=McGill University |accessdate=30 October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; indigenous peoples' diet, prior to the Europeans' arrival{{sfn|Lydekker|1911}}) for purposes of dietary law. Therefore, the general prohibition on the consumption of meat on Fridays did not apply to beaver meat.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chowdc.org/Papers/Saunders%202001.html] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090930112945/http://www.chowdc.org/Papers/Saunders%202001.html|date=September 30, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jimmyakin.org/2005/02/lent_roundup.html |title=Lenten Reader Roundup |publisher=Jimmy Akin.Org |accessdate=2010-03-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{in lang|fr}}Lacoursière, Jacques. ''Une histoire du Québec'' {{ISBN|2-89448-050-4}} Explains that Bishop François de Laval in the 17th century posed the question to the theologians of the [[Collège de Sorbonne|Sorbonne]], who ruled in favour of this decision.&lt;/ref&gt; The legal basis for the decision probably rests with the ''[[Summa Theologica]]'' of [[Thomas Aquinas]], which bases animal classification as much on habit as anatomy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/summa/3147.htm ''The Summa Theologica of St. Thomas Aquinas''] II. 147:8 provides legal foundation on which theologians argued in favour of beaver being like fish.&lt;/ref&gt; This is similar to the Church's classification of other semi-aquatic rodents, such as the [[capybara]] and [[muskrat]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nysun.com/foreign/in-days-before-easter-venezuelans-tuck-into/11063/ |title=In Days Before Easter, Venezuelans Tuck Into Rodent-Related Delicacy |newspaper=The New York Sun|date=24 March 2005 |accessdate=2010-03-15| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20100225220709/http://www.nysun.com/foreign/in-days-before-easter-venezuelans-tuck-into/11063/| archivedate= February 25, 2010 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://webarchive.loc.gov/all/20070313185252/http%3A//www.catholicnews.com/data/stories/cns/0701338.htm Muskrat Love: A Lenten Friday night for some Michiganders]&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* {{Cite book |last =Busher |first = Peter E |year =1999 |title =Beaver protection, management, and utilization in Europe and North America |url =https://books.google.com/books?id=R-FX76TxRVsC&amp;lpg=PA8&amp;dq=North%20american%20Beaver&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true |publisher= Kluwer Academic/Plenum Publ|isbn=978-0-306-46121-7 }}
* {{cite journal |journal=Current Archaeology |date=July–August 2007 |volume=18, No.6 |issue=210 |pages=17–25 |title=Damming Evidence |author=Coles, Bryony |url= |format= |accessdate= }} Article on the history of beavers in Britain.
* {{Cite book |last =Lee Rue |first = Leonard |year = 2001|title =Beavers|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VMk92ARQajEC&amp;lpg=PA61&amp;dq=North%20american%20Beaver&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true |publisher= Voyageur Press|isbn= 978-0-89658-548-5}}
* {{Cite journal |last =Morgan |first =Lewis Henry |year =1868 |title =The American beaver and His Works |url=https://archive.org/details/americanbeavera00morggoog |quote =The American beaver and His Works. |publisher= J.B. Lippincott &amp; Co|isbn= }}
* {{Cite book |last = Müller-Schwarze|first = Dietland|author2=Lixing Sun |year = 2003|title = The beaver: natural history of a wetlands engineer|url =https://books.google.com/books?id=eqIenKko3lAC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;dq=Beaver&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true |publisher= Comstock Pub. Associates |isbn= 978-0-8014-4098-4}}
* {{Cite journal |last =National Parks|first = January–February |year =2003 |title = The Benefits of Beavers |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=DZXWz-RfcPYC&amp;lpg=PA30&amp;dq=Beavers&amp;pg=PA30#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true|pages=30–35|publisher= National Parks magazine|isbn= }}
* ''The Tent Dwellers'' – [http://www.treesearch.fs.fed.us/pubs/23250 Beavers' habits, habitat and conservation status (as of 1908) are recurring themes] by Albert Bigelow Paine.
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons and category|Beaver|Castor}}
{{Wikispecies|Castor}}
{{Wikisource|Portal:Mammals#Beaver|Beaver}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20081029222026/http://animal.discovery.com/mammals/beaver/ Beaver Facts &amp; Pictures]
* [http://northernbushcraft.com/animalTracks/beaver/notes.htm Beaver Tracks]: How to identify beaver tracks in the wild
* ''[https://archive.org/details/romanceofbeaverb00dugmiala The Romance of the Beaver: Being the History of the Beaver in the Western Hemisphere]'' by A. Radclyffe Dugmore
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070921033600/http://www.aigas.co.uk/2007-beaver-diary-g.asp Aigas Field Centre Beaver Project] – history of a pair of European beavers released into a large enclosure in the Highlands of Scotland.
* [http://thecanadianencyclopedia.com/articles/beaver-rodent The Canadian Encyclopedia, The Beaver]
* [https://archive.is/20130628033353/http://blog.scottishbeavers.org.uk/tag/beaver-canal/ Video of a beaver building a canal]

{{Authority control}}
{{Taxonbar|from=Q47542}}

[[Category:Beavers| ]]
[[Category:Rodents of North America]]
[[Category:Symbols of Oregon]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Extant Miocene first appearances]]
[[Category:Taxa named by Carl Linnaeus]]
[[Category:Semiaquatic mammals]]</text>
      <sha1>pszxq7p3m1p2xgj5idbsds1zch5q3yi</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
