  <page>
    <title>Book of Ruth</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4381</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940957891</id>
      <parentid>940949354</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-15T18:44:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tgeorgescu</username>
        <id>6525</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted [[WP:AGF|good faith]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/Garrettr839|Garrettr839]] ([[User talk:Garrettr839|talk]]): [[MOS:GOD]] ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|the ancient Hebrew religious text|the 20th-century English language novel|The Book of Ruth (novel)|the 1960 film|The Story of Ruth|the 2009 film|The Book of Ruth: Journey of Faith}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2011}}
{{Tanakh OT |Ketuvim |historical}}
The '''Book of Ruth''' (abbreviated '''Rth''') ({{lang-he|מגילת רות}}, ''Megilath Ruth'', &quot;the Scroll of Ruth&quot;, one of the [[Five Megillot]]) is included in the third division, or the Writings ([[Ketuvim]]), of the [[Hebrew Bible]]; in most [[Old Testament|Christian canons]] it is treated as a history book and placed between [[Book of Judges|Judges]] and [[1 Samuel]].{{sfn|Coogan|2008|p=8}}

The book tells of Ruth accepting the god of the Israelites as her god and the Israelite people as her own. In [[Ruth 1:16]]–17, Ruth tells [[Naomi (biblical figure)|Naomi]], her Israelite [[Parent-in-law#Mothers-in-law|mother-in-law]], &quot;Where you go I will go, and where you stay I will stay. Your people will be my people and your God my God. Where you die I will die, and there I will be buried. May the Lord deal with me, be it ever so severely, if even death separates you and me.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://biblehub.com/niv/ruth/1.htm New International Version]&lt;/ref&gt; The book is held in esteem by Jews who fall under the category of [[Conversion to Judaism|Jews-by-choice]], as is evidenced by the considerable presence of [[Boaz]] in rabbinic literature. The Book of Ruth also functions liturgically, as it is read during the [[Jewish holiday]] of [[Shavuot]] (&quot;Weeks&quot;).{{sfn|Atteridge|2006|p=383}}

==Structure==
The book is structured in four chapters:{{sfn|West|2003|p=209}}

Act 1: Prologue and Problem: Death and Emptiness (1:1–22)
*Scene 1: Setting the scene (1:1–5)
*Scene 2: Naomi returns home (1:6–18)
*Scene 3: Arrival of Naomi and Ruth in Bethlehem (1:19–22)

Act 2:  Ruth Meets Boaz, Naomi's Relative, on the Harvest Field (2:1–23)
*Scene 1: Ruth in the field of Boaz (2:1–17)
*Scene 2: Ruth reports to Naomi (2:18–23)

Act 3:  Naomi Sends Ruth to Boaz on the Threshing Floor (3:1–18)
*Scene 1: Naomi Reveals Her Plan (3:1–5)
*Scene 2: Ruth at the threshing-floor of Boaz (3:6–15)
*Scene 3: Ruth reports to Naomi (3:16–18)

Act 4:  Resolution and Epilogue:  Life and Fullness (4:1–22)
*Scene 1: Boaz with the men at the gate (4:1–12)
*Scene 2: A son is born to Ruth (4:13–17) &lt;!-- &quot;Naomi&quot; is correct see Ruth 4:17 --&gt;

Genealogical appendix (4:18–22)

==Summary==
[[Image:1795-William-Blake-Naomi-entreating-Ruth-Orpah.jpg|thumb|left|300px|Naomi entreating Ruth and Orpah to return to the land of Moab by [[William Blake]], 1795]]

During the time of the [[Biblical judges|judges]], an Israelite family from [[Bethlehem]]&amp;nbsp;– Elimelech, his wife [[Naomi (Bible)|Naomi]], and their sons [[Mahlon and Chilion]]&amp;nbsp;– emigrated to the nearby country of [[Moab]]. Elimelech died, and the sons married two Moabite women: Mahlon married [[Ruth (biblical figure)|Ruth]] and Chilion married [[Orpah]].

After about ten years, the two sons of Naomi also died in Moab ([[Ruth 1#Verse 4|1:4]]). Naomi decided to return to Bethlehem. She told her daughters-in-law to return to their own mothers and remarry. Orpah reluctantly left; however, Ruth said,  &quot;Do not urge me to leave you, to turn back and not follow you. For wherever you go, I will go; wherever you lodge, I will lodge; your people shall be my people, and your God my God. Where you die, I will die, and there I will be buried. Thus and more may the Lord do to me if anything but death parts me from you.&quot; (Ruth 1:16–17 NJPS).

The two women returned to Bethlehem at the beginning of the barley harvest, and in order to support her mother-in-law and herself, Ruth went to the fields to [[gleaning|glean]]. As it happened, the field she went to belonged to a man named [[Boaz]], who was kind to her because he had heard of her loyalty to her mother-in-law. Ruth told Naomi of Boaz's kindness, and she gleaned in his field through the remainder of barley and wheat harvest.

Boaz was a close relative of Naomi's husband's family. He was therefore obliged by the [[Yibbum|Levirate]] law to marry Mahlon's widow, Ruth, in order to carry on his family's inheritance. Naomi sent Ruth to the threshing floor at night and told her to go where he slept, and &quot;uncover his feet and lie down. He will tell you what you are to do.&quot; ([[Ruth 3#Verse 4|3:4]]). Ruth did so. Boaz asked her who she was, and she replied: &quot;I am your handmaid Ruth. Spread your robe over your handmaid, for you are a redeeming kinsman&quot; (3:9 NJPS). Boaz blessed her and agreed to do all that is required, and he noted that, &quot;all the elders of my town know what a fine woman you are&quot; (3:11 NJPS). He then acknowledged that he was a close relative, but that there was one who was closer, and she remained in submission at his feet until she returned into the city in the morning.

Early that day, Boaz went to the city gate to meet with the other male relative before the town elders. The relative is not named: Boaz addresses him as ''[[Ploni Almoni|ploni almoni]]'', literally &quot;so and so&quot;. The unnamed relative is unwilling to jeopardize the inheritance of his own estate by marrying Ruth, and so relinquished his right of redemption, thus allowing Boaz to marry Ruth. They transferred the property and redeemed it, ratified by the nearer kinsman taking off his shoe and handing it over to Boaz. [[Ruth 4#Verse 7|Ruth 4:7]] notes for later generations that:
:Now this was formerly done in Israel in cases of redemption or exchange: to validate any transaction, one man would take off his sandal and hand it to the other. Such was the practice in Israel. (NJPS)

Boaz and Ruth were then married and have a son. The women of the city celebrate Naomi's joy, for Naomi found a redeemer for her family name, and Naomi takes the child and places it in her bosom.

The child is named [[Obed (biblical figure)|Obed]], who we discover is &quot;the father of [[Jesse]], the father of David&quot; (Ruth 4:13–17), that is, the grandfather of [[King David]].

The book concludes with an appendix which traces the Davidic genealogy all the way back from [[Perez (son of Judah)|Perez]], &quot;whom [[Tamar (Genesis)|Tamar]] bore to [[Judah (son of Jacob)|Judah]]&quot;, through to Obed, down to David.

==Composition==
The book does not name its author.{{sfn|Hubbard|1988|p=23}} It is traditionally ascribed to the prophet [[Samuel]], but Ruth's identity as a non-Israelite and the stress on the need for an inclusive attitude towards foreigners suggests an origin in the fifth century BC, when [[Exogamy|intermarriage]] had become controversial (as seen in [[Ezra–Nehemiah|Ezra]] 9:1 and [[book of Nehemiah|Nehemiah]] 13:1).{{sfn|Leith|2007|p=391}} A substantial number of scholars therefore date it to the [[Achaemenid Empire|Persian period]] (6th–4th centuries BC).{{sfn|Grabbe|2004|p=105}} The genealogy that concludes the book is believed to be a post-exilic [[Priestly source|Priestly]] addition, as it adds nothing to the plot; nevertheless, it is carefully crafted and integrates the book into the [[history of Israel]] running from Genesis to Kings.{{sfn|West|2003|p=211}}

==Themes and background==
[[File:Julius Schnorr von Carolsfeld- Ruth im Feld des Boaz.jpg|thumb|300px|[[Julius Schnorr von Carolsfeld]]: ''Ruth in Boaz's Field'', 1828]]
===&lt;span id=&quot;Levirate&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Levirate marriage and the &quot;redeemers&quot;===
The Book of Ruth illustrates the difficulty of trying to use laws given in books such as [[Deuteronomy]] as evidence of actual practice.{{sfn|Grabbe|2004|p=105}} Naomi plans to provide security for herself and Ruth by arranging a [[Levirate marriage]] with Boaz. She instructs Ruth to uncover Boaz's feet after he has gone to sleep and lie down. When Boaz wakes up, surprised to see a woman at his feet, Ruth explains she wants him to redeem (and thus marry) her. Many modern commentators see sexual allusions in this part of the story, with 'feet' as a [[euphemism]] for genitals.{{sfn|West|2003|p=210}}&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot; name=&quot;Genitals&quot;&gt;For &quot;feet&quot; as a euphemism for genitals see, for example, Amy-Jill Levine, &quot;Ruth,&quot; in Newsom and Ringe (eds.), ''The Women's Bible Commentary'', pp.78-84. The usual interpretation, as given here, is that Ruth is told to uncover Boaz's genitals, but see Kirsten Nielsen, &quot;Other Writings,&quot; in McKenzie and Graham (eds.), ''The Hebrew Bible Today'', pp.175-176, where it is argued that Ruth is to uncover herself.&lt;/ref&gt;

Since there was no heir to inherit Elimelech's land, custom required a close relative (usually the dead man's brother) to marry the widow of the deceased in order to continue his family line ([[Deuteronomy]] 25:5–10). This relative was called the [[go'el]], the &quot;kinsman-redeemer&quot;. As Boaz is not Elimelech's brother, nor is Ruth his widow, scholars refer to the arrangement here as &quot;Levirate-like&quot;.{{sfn|Allen|1996|p=521-522}} A complication arises in the story: another man is a closer relative to Elimelech than Boaz and has first claim on Ruth. It is resolved through the custom that required land to stay in the family: a family could mortgage land to ward off poverty, but the law required a kinsman to purchase it back into the family (Leviticus 25:25ff). Boaz meets the near kinsman at the city gate (the place where contracts are settled); the kinsman first says he will purchase Elimelech's (now Naomi's) land, but, upon hearing he must also take Ruth as his wife, withdraws his offer. Boaz thus becomes Ruth and Naomi's &quot;kinsman-redeemer.&quot;{{sfn|Allen|1996|p=521-522}}

===Mixed marriage===
The book can be read as a political parable relating to issues around the time of [[Ezra]] and [[Nehemiah]] (the 4th century BCE).{{sfn|West|2003|p=209}} The realistic nature of the story is established from the start through the names of the participants: the husband and father is Elimelech, meaning &quot;My God is King&quot;, and his wife is Naomi, &quot;Pleasing&quot;, but after the deaths of her sons Mahlon, &quot;Sickness&quot;, and Chilion, &quot;Wasting&quot;, she asks to be called Mara, &quot;Bitter&quot;.{{sfn|West|2003|p=209}} The reference to [[Moab]] raises questions, since in the rest of the biblical literature it is associated with hostility to Israel, sexual perversity, and [[idolatry]], and {{bibleref2|Deut.|23:3–6|9|Deuteronomy 23:3–6}} excluded an Ammonite or a Moabite from &quot;the congregation of the {{LORD}}; even to their tenth generation&quot;.{{sfn|West|2003|p=209}} Despite this, Ruth the Moabite married a Judahite and even after his death still regarded herself a member of his family; she then married another Judahite and bore him a son who became an ancestor of [[David]].{{sfn|Grabbe|2004|p=312}} Contrary to the message of [[Ezra–Nehemiah]], where marriages between Jewish men and non-Jewish women were broken up, Ruth teaches that foreigners who convert to Judaism can become good Jews, foreign wives can become exemplary followers of Jewish law, and there is no reason to exclude them or their offspring from the community.{{sfn|Grabbe|2004|p=312}}

===Contemporary interpretations===
Scholars have increasingly explored Ruth in ways which allow it to address contemporary issues. [[feminism|Feminists]], for example, have recast the story as one of the [[dignity of labour]] and female self-sufficiency, and even as a model for [[lesbianism|lesbian]] relations, while others have seen in it a celebration of the relationship between strong and resourceful women. Others have criticised it for its underlying, and potentially exploitative, acceptance of a system of patriarchy in which a woman's worth can only be measured through marriage and child-bearing. Others again have seen it as a book that champions outcast and oppressed peoples.{{sfn|Irwin|2008|p=699}}

==Genealogy: the descent of David from Ruth==
{{chart/start}}
{{chart | |F|~|~|~|~|~|~|~|~|~|~|~|~|~|~|~|~|7| | | | | | | | | }}
{{chart | |:| | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | ELI |y| NAO | | | | ELI=[[Elimelech]]| NAO=[[Naomi (biblical figure)|Naomi]]|}}
{{chart | |:| | | | | | | | | | | |,|-|-|-|-|-|-|^|-|-|-|-|.| | }}
{{chart | BOA |~|y|~| RUT |~|~|~| MAH | | | | ORP |~|~|~| CHIL | BOA=[[Boaz]]| RUT='''Ruth'''| MAH=[[Mahlon and Chilion|Mahlon]]| ORP=[[Orpah]]| CHIL=[[Mahlon and Chilion|Chilion]]|}}
{{chart | | | | |!| | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | }}
{{chart | | | | OBE | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | OBE=[[Obed (biblical figure)|Obed]]|}}
{{chart | | | | |!| | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | }}
{{chart | | | | JES | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | JES=[[Jesse]]|}}
{{chart | | | | |!| | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | }}
{{chart | | | | DAV | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | DAV=[[David]]|}}
{{chart/end}}

==See also==
* [[Goel]]
*[[Gleaning]]
*[[Levirate marriage]]
*[[Genealogy of Jesus]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist |group=&quot;Note&quot;}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite book |last=Allen |first=Leslie C. |chapter=Ruth |editor1-last=LaSor |editor1-first=William Sanford |editor2-last=Hubbard |editor2-first=David Allan  |editor3-last=Bush |editor3-first=Frederic William |display-editors = 3 |editor4-last=Allen |editor4-first=Leslie C. |title=Old Testament Survey: The Message, Form, and Background of the Old Testament |year=1996 |publisher=Eerdmans |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6wSWpZmmlAoC&amp;pg=PA521 |ref=harv |isbn=9780802837882}}
* {{cite book |last=Atteridge |first=Harold W. |title=The HarperCollins Study Bible |year=2006 |publisher=HarperCollins |url= |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book |last=Coogan |first=Michael D. |authorlink=Michael D. Coogan |title=A Brief Introduction to the Old Testament: The Hebrew Bible in Its Context |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=2008 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=2rxBAQAAIAAJ|isbn=9780195332728 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Grabbe |first=Lester L. |authorlink=Lester L. Grabbe |title=The History of the Jews and Judaism in the Second Temple Period, Volume 1: Yehud, the Persian Province of Judah |year=2004 |publisher=Continuum |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-MnE5T_0RbMC&amp;pg=PA105|ref=harv |isbn=9780567089984 |pages=105 &amp;amp; 312}}
* {{cite book |last=Hubbard |first=Robert L. Jr. |title=The Book of Ruth |year=1988 |publisher=Eerdmans |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wJQvoHg91QkC&amp;pg=PA23|ref=harv |isbn=9780802825261}}
* {{cite book 
|last=Irwin
|first=B.P.
|chapter=Ruth 4: Person
|editor1-last=Longman  
|editor1-first=Tremper 
|editor2-last=Enns
|editor2-first=Peter
|title=Dictionary of the Old Testament: Wisdom, Poetry &amp; Writings
|year=2008 
|publisher=InterVarsity Press 
|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kE2k36XAkv4C&amp;pg=PA699
|ref=harv
|isbn=9780830817832
}}
* {{cite book |last=Leith |first=Mary Joan Winn |chapter=Ruth |editor1-last=Coogan |editor1-first=Michael D.  |editor2-last=Brettler |editor2-first=Marc Zvi  |editor3-last=Newsom |editor3-first=Carol Ann |display-editors = 3 |editor4-last=Perkins |editor4-first=Pheme |title=The New Oxford Annotated Bible with the Apocryphal/Deuterocanonical Books: New Revised Standard Version |year=2007 |publisher=Oxford University Press |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Nc-i_pQsiW8C&amp;pg=PA391|ref=harv |isbn=9780195288803}}
* {{cite book |last=West |first=Gerald |chapter=Ruth |editor1-last=Dunn  |editor1-first=James D.G. |editor2-last=Rogerson |editor2-first=John William |title=Eerdmans Commentary on the Bible |year=2003 |publisher=Eerdmans |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2Vo-11umIZQC&amp;pg=PA211|ref=harv |isbn=9780802837110}}
{{Refend}}

== External links ==
{{wikisource|Ruth (Bible)}}
{{Commons category|Book of Ruth}}
;Jewish translations and study guides
* [http://www.mechon-mamre.org/e/et/et2901.htm ''Ruth'' at Mechon Mamre – (Jewish Publication Society of America Version, 1917)]
* [https://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/Bible/Ruthtoc.html Jewish Virtual Library]
* [http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=483&amp;letter=R&amp;search=ruth Jewish Encyclopedia]
* [http://www.chabad.org/library/article_cdo/aid/15778/jewish/Ruth.htm Ruth – English translation [with Rashi commentary&amp;#93;]

;Christian translations and study guides
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070219150900/http://www.hopeofisrael.net/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=37&amp;Itemid=32 The Kinsman Redeemer]
* [http://www.gospelhall.org/bible/bible.php?passage=Ruth+1 ''Online Bible'' – GospelHall.org]
* [http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Ruth;&amp;version=31; Biblegateway]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060522235628/http://www.intervarsity.org/ism/article/1827 Bible Study on Cross-Cultural Love – InterVarsity website]
* [http://www.meakc.com/book-of-ruth Redeemed]
* {{librivox book | dtitle=Book of Ruth| stitle=Bible Ruth}} Various versions


;Encyclopedic entries
* [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/13276a.htm Catholic Encyclopedia]

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou | [[Ketuvim|History books]]|||}}
{{s-bef | before = [[Song of Songs]] }}
{{s-ttl | title  = [[Tanakh|Hebrew Bible]] }}
{{s-aft | after  = [[Book of Lamentations|Lamentations]] }}
{{s-bef | before = [[Book of Judges|Judges]] }}
{{s-ttl | title = Christian&lt;br&gt;[[Old Testament]] }}
{{s-aft | after  = [[Books of Samuel|1–2 Samuel]] }}
{{s-end}}
{{Book of Ruth}}
{{Books of the Bible}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ruth, Book Of}}
[[Category:6th-century BC books]]
[[Category:5th-century BC books]]
[[Category:4th-century BC books]]
[[Category:Book of Ruth| ]]
[[Category:Ketuvim]]
[[Category:Moab]]
[[Category:Shavuot]]</text>
      <sha1>su5vwj45988lec8amkriq1aigg5kg6i</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
