  <page>
    <title>Boomerang</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4359</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942879570</id>
      <parentid>942812225</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T12:42:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mitch Ames</username>
        <id>6326132</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Remove supercategory of existing diffusing subcategory per [[WP:SUBCAT]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|the wooden implement|other uses}}
{{Use Australian English|date=March 2013}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2020}}
{{Infobox sport
| name       = Boomerang
| image      = Boomerang.jpg
| imagesize  = 220px
| caption    = Aerodynamic returning boomerang
| union      = 
| first      = Ancient
| firstlabel =
| country/region = Australia
| registered =
| clubs      =
| contact    = No
| team       =
| mgender    = No
| category   = Throwing sport
| equipment  = Boomerang
| venue      =
| obsolete   =
| olympic    = No
| paralympic =
| IWGA       = [[1989 World Games|1989]] (invitational)
}}

A '''boomerang''' is a thrown tool, typically constructed as a flat [[airfoil]], that is designed to spin about an axis perpendicular to the direction of its flight. A returning boomerang is designed to return to the thrower. It is well-known as a weapon used by some [[Aboriginal Australian]] peoples for hunting.

Boomerangs have been historically used for [[Hunting in Australia|hunting]], as well as sport and entertainment. They are commonly thought of as an Australian icon,&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title = Boomerang: Behind an Australian Icon|last = Jones|first = Philip|publisher = Wakefield Press|year = 1996|isbn = 9781862543829|location = |pages = }}&lt;/ref&gt; and come in various shapes and sizes.

== Description ==
{{unreferenced|section|date=October 2019}}
A boomerang is a [[throwing stick]] with certain [[Aerodynamics|aerodynamic]] properties, traditionally made of wood, but boomerang-like devices have also been made from bones. Modern boomerangs used for sport may be made from plywood or plastics such as [[Acrylonitrile butadiene styrene|ABS]], [[polypropylene]], [[phenolic paper]], or [[Carbon fiber-reinforced polymer|carbon fibre-reinforced plastics]]. Boomerangs come in many shapes and sizes depending on their geographic or tribal origins and intended function. Many people think of a boomerang as the Australian type, although today there are many types of more easily usable boomerangs, such as the cross-stick, the pinwheel, the tumble-stick, the Boomabird, and many other less common types.

An important distinction should be made between returning boomerangs and non-returning boomerangs. Returning boomerangs fly and are examples of the earliest heavier-than-air human-made flight. A returning boomerang has two or more [[airfoil]] wings arranged so that the spinning creates unbalanced [[aerodynamic]] forces that curve its path so that it travels in an [[ellipse]], returning to its point of origin when thrown correctly. While a [[throwing stick]] can also be shaped overall like a returning boomerang, it is designed to travel as straight as possible so that it can be aimed and thrown with great force to bring down the game. Its surfaces are therefore symmetrical and not with the aerofoils that give the returning boomerang its characteristic curved flight.

The most recognisable type of the boomerang is the L-shaped returning boomerang; while non-returning boomerangs, throwing sticks (or kylies) were used as weapons, returning boomerangs have been used primarily for leisure or recreation. Returning boomerangs were also used to decoy birds of prey, thrown above the long grass to frighten [[game (food)|game]] birds into flight and into waiting nets. Modern returning boomerangs can be of [[#Modern usage|various shapes or sizes]].

Just like the hunting [[boomerang]] of the Aboriginal Australians, the valari also did not return to the thrower but flew straight. Boomerangs used in competitions have specially designed air-foiling mechanism to enable return, but the hunting Boomerangs are meant to float straight and hit the target. Valaris are made in many shapes and sizes. The history of the valari is rooted in ancient times and evidences can be found in Tamil Sangam literature &quot;Purananuru&quot;. The usual form consists of two limbs set at an angle; one is thin and tapering while the other is rounded and is used as a handle. Valaris are usually made of iron which is melted and poured into moulds, although some may have wooden limbs tipped with iron. Alternatively, the limbs may have lethally sharpened edges; special daggers are known as [[kattari]], double-edged and razor sharp, may be attached to some valari.

== Etymology ==
The origin of the term is uncertain. One source asserts that the term entered the language in 1827, adapted from an extinct [[Australian Aboriginal language|Aboriginal language]] of [[New South Wales]], Australia, but mentions a variant, ''wo-mur-rang'', which it dates to 1798.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?search=boomerang&amp;searchmode=none Boomerang], [http://www.etymonline.com/ Online Etymology Dictionary].&lt;/ref&gt; The first recorded encounter with a boomerang by Europeans was at [[Farm Cove, New South Wales|Farm Cove]] ([[Port Jackson]]), in December 1804, when a weapon was witnessed during a tribal [[Skirmisher|skirmish]]:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article626558 |title=SYDNEY |publisher= NLA Australian Newspapers |accessdate=3 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|... the ''white'' spectators were justly astonished at the dexterity and incredible force with which a bent, edged waddy resembling slightly a Turkish [[scimitar|scimytar]], was thrown by ''Bungary'', a native distinguished by his remarkable courtesy. The weapon, thrown at 20 or 30 yards [18 or 27 m] distance, twirled round in the air with astonishing velocity, and alighting on the right arm of one of his opponents, actually rebounded to a distance not less than 70 or 80 yards [64 or 73 m], leaving a horrible contusion behind, and exciting universal admiration.|''The Sydney Gazette and New South Wales Advertiser'', 23 December 1804.}}

[[David Collins (governor)|David Collins]] listed &quot;Wo-mur-rāng&quot; as one of eight Aboriginal &quot;Names of clubs&quot; in 1798.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |chapter-url= http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/12565 |title = An Account of the English Colony in New South Wales |last= Collins |first= David | year=1798 |chapter= Appendix XII (Language) |page= 554 }}&lt;/ref&gt; but was probably referring to the [[Woomera (spear-thrower)|woomera]], which is actually a [[spear]]-thrower. An anonymous 1790 [[manuscript]] on Aboriginal languages of New South Wales reported &quot;Boo-mer-rit&quot; as &quot;the Scimiter&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrelp.org/dawes/img/Boo-mer-rit.gif Image of handwritten note], in &quot;[http://www.hrelp.org/dawes/ The notebooks of William Dawes on the Aboriginal language of Sydney]&quot;. [http://www.hrelp.org/ The Hans Rausing Endangered Languages Project].&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1822, it was described in detail and recorded as a &quot;bou-mar-rang&quot; in the language of the [[Turuwal]] people (a sub-group of the [[Darug]]) of the [[Georges River]] near Port Jackson. The Turawal used other words for their hunting sticks but used &quot;boomerang&quot; to refer to a returning [[Throwing stick|throw-stick]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.boomerang.org.au/articles/article-what-is-a-boomerang.html |title= What is a Boomerang? |publisher= Boomerang Association of Australia |date= 15 September 1961 |accessdate= 3 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
[[File:Australia Boomerang Distribution.PNG|thumb|Distribution of boomerangs in Australia]]
[[File:Australia Cairns Boomerang.jpg|thumb|left|Australian Aboriginal boomerangs]]

Boomerangs were, historically, used as hunting weapons, [[Percussion instrument|percussive musical instruments]], battle [[Club (weapon)|clubs]], fire-starters, [[decoy]]s for hunting [[waterfowl]], and as recreational play toys. The smallest boomerang may be less than {{convert|10|cm|in|0}} from tip to tip, and the largest over {{cvt|180|cm|ft|1}} in length.&lt;ref name=&quot;Largest&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.flight-toys.com/boomerang/boomnews/worldslargestboom.html |author=Ted Bailey |title= Worlds Largest Boomerang |publisher= flight-toys.com |accessdate= 17 October 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[tribe|Tribal]] boomerangs may be inscribed or painted with designs meaningful to their makers. Most boomerangs seen today are of the tourist or competition sort, and are almost invariably of the returning type.
Depictions of boomerangs being thrown at animals, such as kangaroos, appear in some of the oldest rock art in the world, the [[Indigenous Australian art|Indigenous Australian rock art]] of the Kimberly region, which is potentially up to 50,000 years old.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url= http://www.abc.net.au/news/2015-11-02/indigenous-rock-art-could-be-among-oldest-in-world/6906476 |title= Kimberley rock art could be among oldest in the world |website= ABC News AU  |accessdate= 7 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stencils and paintings of boomerangs also appear in the rock art of [[Western New Guinea|West Papua]], including on [[Bird's Head Peninsula]] and [[Kaimana]], likely dating to the [[Last Glacial Maximum]], when lower sea levels led to cultural continuity between Papua and [[Arnhem Land]] in Northern Australia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url= http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0013/001355/135558e.pdf |title= Rock Art in West Papua |last=Arifin |first=Karina |publisher=UNESCO Publishing |year=2004 |isbn= |location= |pages= }}&lt;/ref&gt; The oldest surviving [[Australian Aborigines|Australian Aboriginal]] boomerangs come from a cache found in a peat bog in the Wyrie Swamp of [[South Australia]] and date to [[8th millennium BC|10,000 BC]].

Although traditionally thought of as Australian, boomerangs have been found also in ancient Europe, Egypt, and North America. There is evidence of the use of non-returning boomerangs by the Native Americans of California and [[Arizona]], and inhabitants of southern [[India]] for killing birds and rabbits.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brittanica&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |entry=Boomerang |encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Britannica |entry-url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/73646/boomerang |access-date=25 January 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Some boomerangs were not thrown at all, but were used in [[hand to hand combat]] by [[Indigenous Australians]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Harris |first=Tom |url= http://www.howstuffworks.com/boomerang.htm/printable |title= Battle Boomerangs |publisher= Howstuffworks.com |accessdate=3 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ancient Egypt]]ian examples, however, have been recovered, and experiments have shown that they functioned as returning boomerangs.&lt;ref&gt;Rivers, Pitt. &quot;On the Egyptian Boomerang and its Affinities&quot;. ''The Journal of the Anthropological Institute of Great Britain and Ireland. 1883. '''12''': 454–463.&lt;/ref&gt;Hunting sticks discovered in Europe seem to have formed part of the [[Stone Age]] arsenal of weapons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Boomer&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.rangs.co.uk/boomhistory.htm|title=Boomerang History |publisher= rangs.co.uk |accessdate= 17 October 2008 |url-status=dead |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070630052119/http://www.rangs.co.uk/boomhistory.htm |archivedate= 30 June 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; One boomerang that was discovered in [[Obłazowa Cave]] in the [[Carpathian Mountains]] in Poland was made of mammoth's tusk and is believed, based on [[Accelerator mass spectrometry|AMS dating]] of objects found with it, to be about 30,000 years old.&lt;ref&gt;Valde-Nowak ''et al''. (1987). Upper Palaeolithic boomerang made of a mammoth tusk in south Poland. ''Nature'' '''329''': 436–438 (1 October 1987); [http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v329/n6138/abs/329436a0.html doi:10.1038/329436a0].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title= Er fliegt! |journal=Bumerang Welt |year=1995 |url= https://www.bumerangs.de/bw-archiv/95/95103.htm |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20071031013513/http://www.bumerangs.de/bw-archiv/95/95103.htm |archivedate=31 October 2007 }}. English translation: &quot;Paleolithic Throwing Object&quot; {{cite web |url= http://www.rediboom.com/englisch/geschich/polen.html |title=Archived copy |accessdate= 6 September 2008 |url-status=bot: unknown |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20081205065827/http://www.rediboom.com/englisch/geschich/polen.html |archivedate=5 December 2008 }} – Throwing experiments with the Palaeolithic throwing object from the Oblazowa in the Polish Carpathians&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Netherlands]], boomerangs have been found in [[Vlaardingen]] and [[Velsen]] from the first century BC. &lt;!-- (''photograph,'' worth of uploading to Wikipedia—must be [[public domain]] because published by [[Polish Academy of Sciences]])--&gt; [[Tutankhamun|King Tutankhamun]], the famous [[Pharaoh]] of ancient Egypt, who died over 3,300 years ago, owned a collection of boomerangs of both the straight flying (hunting) and returning variety.&lt;ref name=&quot;Boomer&quot; /&gt;
[[File:4 boomerangs du tombeau de Toutânkhamon.jpg|thumb|4 boomerangs of the tomb of pharahoh Tutankhamun (−1336-1326 BC). These hardwood boomerangs could not return to their launcher due to their curvature unlike other boomerangs found in the tomb.]]

No one knows for sure how the returning boomerang was invented, but some modern boomerang makers speculate that it developed from the flattened throwing stick, still used by the [[Australian Aborigines]] and other indigenous peoples around the world, including the [[Navajo people|Navajo]] in North America. A hunting boomerang is delicately balanced and much harder to make than a returning one. The curving flight characteristic of returning boomerangs was probably first noticed by early hunters trying to &quot;tune&quot; their throwing sticks to fly straight.&lt;ref name=&quot;Boomer&quot; /&gt;

It is thought by some that the shape and elliptical flight path of the returning boomerang makes it useful for hunting birds and small animals, or that noise generated by the movement of the boomerang through the air, or, by a skilled thrower, lightly clipping leaves of a tree whose branches house birds, would help scare the birds towards the thrower. It is further supposed by some that this was used to frighten flocks or groups of birds into nets that were usually strung up between trees or thrown by hidden hunters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1= Lloyd |first1= John |last2= Mitchinson |first2= John |title= The Book of General Ignorance |year=2006 |publisher= Mackays of Chatham |isbn= 978-0-571-23368-7 |page= 244 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In southeastern Australia, it is claimed that boomerangs were made to hover over a flock of ducks; mistaking it for a hawk, the ducks would dive away, toward hunters armed with nets or clubs.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

Traditionally, most boomerangs used by Aboriginal groups in Australia were non-returning. These weapons, sometimes called &quot;throwsticks&quot; or &quot;kylies&quot;, were used for hunting a variety of prey, from [[kangaroo]]s to parrots; at a range of about {{convert|100|m}}, a 2-kg (4.4 lb) non-returning boomerang could inflict mortal injury to a large animal.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; A throwstick thrown nearly horizontally may fly in a nearly straight path and could fell a kangaroo on impact to the legs or knees, while the long-necked emu could be killed by a blow to the neck.{{citation needed|date=October 2013}}  Hooked non-returning boomerangs, known as &quot;beaked kylies&quot;, used in northern Central Australia, have been claimed to kill multiple birds when thrown into a dense flock. Throwsticks are used as multi-purpose tools by today's Aboriginal peoples, and besides throwing could be wielded as clubs, used for digging, used to start friction fires, and are sonorous when two are struck together.

== Modern usage ==
[[File:sportbumerangs.jpg|thumb|Sport boomerangs]]
Today, boomerangs are mostly used for recreation. There are different types of throwing contests: accuracy of return; Aussie round; trick catch; [[maximum time aloft]]; fast catch; and endurance (see below). The modern sport boomerang (often referred to as a 'boom' or 'rang') is made of Finnish birch [[plywood]], [[hardwood]], plastic or [[composite material]]s and comes in many different shapes and colours. Most sport boomerangs typically weigh less than {{convert|100|g|oz}}, with MTA boomerangs (boomerangs used for the maximum-time-aloft event) often under {{convert|25|g|oz|1}}.

Boomerangs have also been suggested as an alternative to [[clay pigeons]] in shotgun sports, where the flight of the boomerang better mimics the flight of a bird offering a more challenging target.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite av media |url= https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Fwv2BhJEjDo |title= Aussie Boomerang Shootin' |date= 15 October 2012 |via= YouTube}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The modern boomerang is often [[computer-aided design]]ed with precision airfoils. The number of &quot;wings&quot; is often more than 2 as more lift is provided by 3 or 4 wings than by 2.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.boomerangs.com/aerodynamics.html Boomerang Aerodynamics], [http://www.boomerangs.com/ boomerangs.com].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Saulius Pakalnis, [http://www.researchsupporttechnologies.com/boomerang_site/boomerang1.htm Aerodynamics of Boomerang], 21 April 2006, [http://www.researchsupporttechnologies.com/ researchsupporttechnologies.com].&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1992, German astronaut [[Ulf Merbold]] performed an experiment aboard [[Spacelab]] that established that boomerangs function in [[Weightlessness|zero gravity]] as they do on Earth. French Astronaut [[Jean-François Clervoy]] aboard Mir repeated this in 1997.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.flight-toys.com/boomerang/boomnews/spacebooms.html |title=Boomerangs in Space |publisher= Flight-toys.com |date= 18 March 2008 |accessdate=3 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, Japanese astronaut [[Takao Doi]] again repeated the experiment on board the [[International Space Station]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.news.com.au/couriermail/story/0,23739,23411383-952,00.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080324172123/http://www.news.com.au/couriermail/story/0%2C23739%2C23411383-952%2C00.html |archivedate= 24 March 2008 |title= Boomerang works in space, says astronaut |publisher= News.com.au |date= 21 March 2008 |accessdate=3 March 2010 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.universetoday.com/2008/03/24/does-a-boomerang-work-in-space/ |title= Does a Boomerang Work in Space? |work= Universetoday.com |date= 24 March 2008 |accessdate= 3 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Boomerangs - melbourne show 2005.jpg|thumb|Boomerangs for sale at the 2005 Melbourne Show]]
Beginning in the later part of the twentieth century, there has been a bloom in the independent creation of unusually designed art boomerangs. These often have little or no resemblance to the traditional historical ones and on first sight some of these objects may not look like boomerangs at all. The use of modern thin plywoods and synthetic plastics have greatly contributed to their success. Designs are very diverse and can range from animal inspired forms, humorous themes, complex calligraphic and symbolic shapes, to the purely abstract. Painted surfaces are similarly richly diverse. Some boomerangs made primarily as art objects do not have the required aerodynamic properties to return.

== Aerodynamics ==
A returning boomerang is a rotating wing. It consists of two or more arms, or wings, connected at an angle; each wing is shaped as an [[airfoil]] section. Although it is not a requirement that a boomerang be in its traditional shape, it is usually flat.

Boomerangs can be made for right or left handed throwers. The difference between right and left is subtle, the planform is the same but the leading edges of the aerofoil sections are reversed. A right-handed boomerang makes a counter-clockwise, circular flight to the left while a left-handed boomerang flies clockwise to the right.
Most sport boomerangs weigh between {{convert|70|to|110|g|oz}}, have a wingspan of {{convert|250|to|350|mm|inch}} and a range of between {{cvt|20|and|40|m|yd|0}}.

A falling boomerang starts spinning, and most then fall in a spiral. When the boomerang is thrown with high spin, a boomerang flies in a curved rather than a straight line. When thrown correctly, a boomerang returns to its starting point.
As the wing rotates and the boomerang moves through the air, the airflow over the wings creates lift on both &quot;wings&quot;. However, during one-half of each blade's rotation, it sees a higher airspeed, because the rotation tip-speed and the forward speed add, and when it is in the other half of the rotation, the tip speed subtracts from the forward speed. Thus if thrown nearly upright each blade generates more lift at the top than the bottom.&lt;ref name=hyper&gt;{{cite web |url= http://hyperphysics.phy-astr.gsu.edu/hbase/brng.html |title= Boomerang |work=gsu.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; While it might be expected that this would cause the boomerang to tilt around the axis of travel, because the boomerang has significant angular momentum, the [[gyroscopic precession]] causes the plane of rotation to tilt about an axis that is 90 degrees to the direction of flight causing it to turn.&lt;ref name=hyper/&gt; When thrown in the horizontal plane, as with a [[Flying disc|Frisbee]], instead of in the vertical, the same gyroscopic precession will cause the boomerang to fly violently, straight up into the air and then crash.

Fast Catch boomerangs usually have three or more symmetrical wings (seen from above), whereas a Long Distance boomerang is most often shaped similar to a question mark.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.baggressive.com/copper/thumbnails.php?album=6 |title= baggressive.com |publisher= Baggressive.com |date= 19 April 2005 |accessdate= 3 March 2010 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20081224082313/http://www.baggressive.com/copper/thumbnails.php?album=6 |archive-date= 24 December 2008 |url-status= dead |df= dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Maximum Time Aloft boomerangs mostly have one wing considerably longer than the other. This feature, along with carefully executed bends and twists in the wings help to set up an 'auto-rotation' effect to maximise the boomerang's hover-time in descending from the highest point in its flight.

Some boomerangs have [[turbulator]]s—bumps or pits on the top surface that act to increase the lift as boundary layer transition activators (to keep attached turbulent flow instead of laminar separation).

== Throwing technique ==
{{Unreferenced|section|date=October 2019}}

Boomerangs are generally thrown in unobstructed, open spaces at least twice as large as the range of the boomerang. The flight direction, left or right will depend upon the boomerang, not the thrower. A right-handed or left-handed boomerang can be thrown with either hand, but throwing a boomerang with the wrong hand requires a throwing motion that many throwers find awkward. The following technique applies to a right-handed boomerang, the directions are mirrored for a left-handed boomerang. Different boomerang designs have different flight characteristics and are suitable for different conditions. The accuracy of the throw depends on understanding the weight and aerodynamics of that particular boomerang, and the strength, consistency and direction of the wind; from this, the thrower chooses the angle of tilt, the angle against the wind, the elevation of the trajectory, the degree of spin and the strength of the throw. A great deal of trial and error is required to perfect the throw over time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.rangsboomerangs.com/boomerang-list/boomerang-throwing-instructions|title=BOOMERANG THROWING INSTRUCTIONS|website=www.rangsboomerangs.com|access-date=2020-02-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A properly thrown boomerang will travel out parallel to the ground, sometimes climbing gently, perform a graceful, anti-clockwise, circular or tear-drop shaped arc, flatten out and return in a hovering motion, coming in from the left or spiralling in from behind. Ideally, the hover will allow a practiced catcher to clamp their hands shut horizontally on the boomerang from above and below, sandwiching the centre between their hands.

The grip used depends on size and shape; smaller boomerangs are held between finger and thumb at one end, while larger, heavier or wider boomerangs with one or two fingers wrapped over the top edge in order to induce a spin. The aerofoil shaped section must face the inside of the thrower and the flatter side outwards. It is usually inclined outwards, from a near-vertical position to 20&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt; or 30&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;; the stronger the wind, the closer to vertical.  The elbow of the boomerang can point forwards or backwards, or it can be gripped for throwing; it just needs to start spinning on the required inclination, in the desired direction, with the right force.    

The boomerang is aimed to the right of the oncoming wind; the exact angle will depend on the strength of the wind and the boomerang itself. Left-handed boomerangs are thrown to the left of the wind and will fly a clockwise flight path. The trajectory is either parallel to the ground or slightly upwards. The boomerang can return without the aid of any wind but even very slight winds must be taken into account however calm it may seem. Little or no wind is preferable for an accurate throw, light winds up to three to five knots are manageable with skill. If the wind is strong enough to fly a kite, then it may be too strong without a skilled thrower with a boomerang designed for stability in stronger winds. Gusty days are a great challenge and the thrower must be keenly aware of the ebb and flow of the wind strength finding appropriate lulls in the gusts to launch their boomerang.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.wikihow.com/Throw-a-Boomerang|title=How to Throw a Boomerang|website=wikiHow|language=en|access-date=2020-02-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.boomerangs.com/pages/how-to-throw-boomerangs|title=How To Throw Boomerangs!|website=Boomerangs.com|access-date=2020-02-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://entertainment.howstuffworks.com/throw-boomerang.htm|title=How Do You Throw a Boomerang So That It Comes Back to You?|date=2001-09-06|website=HowStuffWorks|language=en|access-date=2020-02-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Competitions and records ==


A World Record achievement was made on 3 June 2007 by Tim Lendrum in Aussie Round. Tim scored 96 out of 100, giving him a National Record as well as an equal World Record throwing an &quot;AYR&quot; made by expert boomerang maker Adam Carroll. 

In international competition, a ''world cup'' is held every second year. {{as of|2017}}, teams from Germany and the United States dominated international competition. The individual World Champion title was won in 2000, 2002, 2004, 2012 and 2016 by Swiss thrower Manuel Schütz. In 1992, 1998, 2006 and 2008 Fridolin Frost from Germany won the title.

The team competitions of 2012 and 2014 were won by Boomergang (an international team). World champions were Germany in 2012 and Japan in 2014 for the first time. Boomergang was formed by individuals from several countries, including the Colombian Alejandro Palacio. In 2016 USA became team world champion.

=== Competition disciplines ===

Modern boomerang tournaments usually involve some or all of the events listed below&lt;ref name=&quot;German Wikipedia&quot;&gt;Based on original text from German wiki.[[:de:Bumerang]]{{Better source|date=November 2016|reason=[[WP:CIRCULAR]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In all disciplines the boomerang must travel at least {{convert|20|m|ft|0}} from the thrower. Throwing takes place individually. The thrower stands at the centre of concentric rings marked on an open field.

Events include:

* ''Aussie Round'': considered by many to be the ultimate test of boomeranging skills. The boomerang should ideally cross the {{convert|50|m|ft|adj=on}} circle and come right back to the centre. Each thrower has five attempts. Points are awarded for distance, accuracy and the catch.
* ''Accuracy'': points are awarded according to how close the boomerang lands to the centre of the rings. The thrower must not touch the boomerang after it has been thrown. Each thrower has five attempts. In major competitions there are two accuracy disciplines: Accuracy 100 and Accuracy 50.
* ''Endurance'': points are awarded for the number of catches achieved in 5 minutes.
* ''Fast Catch'': the time taken to throw and catch the boomerang five times. The winner has the fastest timed catches.
* ''Trick Catch/Doubling'': points are awarded for trick catches behind the back, between the feet, and so on. In Doubling, the thrower has to throw two boomerangs at the same time and catch them in sequence in a special way.
* ''Consecutive Catch'': points are awarded for the number of catches achieved before the boomerang is dropped. The event is not timed.
* ''MTA 100'' (''Maximal Time Aloft'', {{convert|100|m|ft|0}}): points are awarded for the length of time spent by the boomerang in the air. The field is normally a circle measuring 100&amp;nbsp;m. An alternative to this discipline, without the 100&amp;nbsp;m restriction is called ''MTA unlimited''.
* ''Long Distance'': the boomerang is thrown from the middle point of a {{convert|40|m|ft|adj=on}} baseline. The furthest distance travelled by the boomerang away from the baseline is measured. On returning, the boomerang must cross the baseline again but does not have to be caught. A special section is dedicated to LD below.
* ''Juggling'': as with Consecutive Catch, only with two boomerangs. At any given time one boomerang must be in the air.

=== World records ===
{{updated|September 2017}}

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Discipline
! Result
! Name
! Year
! Tournament
|-
| Accuracy 100
| 99 points
| {{flagicon|GER}} Alex Opri
| 2007
| {{flagicon|ITA}} [[Viareggio]]
|-
| Aussie Round
| 99 points
| {{flagicon|GER}} Fridolin Frost
| 2007
| {{flagicon|ITA}} Viareggio
|-
| Endurance
| 81 catches
| {{flagicon|SWI}} Manuel Schütz
| 2005
| {{flagicon|ITA}} [[Milan]]
|-
| Fast Catch
| 14.07 s
| {{flagicon|SWI}} Manuel Schütz
| 2017
| {{flagicon|FRA}} [[Besançon]]
|-
| Trick Catch/Doubling
| 533 points
| {{flagicon|SWI}} Manuel Schütz
| 2009
| {{flagicon|FRA}} [[Bordeaux]]
|-
| Consecutive Catch
| 2251 catches
| {{flagicon|JPN}} Haruki Taketomi
| 2009
| {{flagicon|JPN}} Japan
|-
| MTA 100
| 139.10 s
| {{flagicon|USA}} Nick Citoli
| 2010
| {{flagicon|ITA}} Rome
|-
| MTA unlimited
| 380.59 s
| {{flagicon|USA}} Billy Brazelton
| 2010
| {{flagicon|ITA}} Rome
|-
| Long Distance
| 238 m
| {{flagicon|SWI}} Manuel Schütz
| 1999
| {{flagicon|SWI}} [[Kloten]]
|}

=== Guinness World Record – Smallest Returning Boomerang ===

''Non-discipline record'': Smallest Returning Boomerang: Sadir Kattan of Australia in 1997 with {{convert|48|mm|in}} long and {{convert|46|mm|in}} wide. This tiny boomerang flew the required {{convert|20|m|yd}}, before returning to the accuracy circles on 22 March 1997 at the Australian National Championships.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://boomerang.org.au/wp/photos/boomerangs/boomerangs-sadir-kattan-and-worlds-smallest-boomerang/ |title=World's smallest boomerang |publisher=boomerang.org.au |date=12 April 2008 |accessdate=3 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Guinness World Record – Longest Throw of Any Object by a Human ===

A boomerang was used to set a [[Guinness World Records|Guinness World Record]] with a throw of {{convert|427.2|m|ft}} by David Schummy on [[Portal:Current events/2005 March 15|15 March 2005]] at [[Murrarie Recreation Ground]], Australia.&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube|LQ5dW5pHPYk|Longest Boomerang Throw}}&lt;/ref&gt; This broke the record set by Erin Hemmings who threw an [[Aerobie]] {{convert|406.3|m|ft}} on 14 July 2003 at [[Fort Funston]], San Francisco.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=First quarter Mile Throw in History at Fort Funston |url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0EIN/is_2003_July_16/ai_105504992/ |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20050419091733/http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0EIN/is_2003_July_16/ai_105504992 |url-status=dead |archive-date=19 April 2005 |agency=[[Business Wire]] |date=16 July 2003 |accessdate=28 May 2009 |work=Business Wire }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Long-distance versions ==
{{multiple issues|section=yes|
{{unreferenced section|date=December 2012}}
{{original research|section|date=October 2009}}
}}
Long-distance boomerang throwers aim to have the boomerang go the furthest possible distance while returning close to the throwing point. In competition the boomerang must intersect an imaginary surface defined as an [[infinity|infinite]] [[Vertical angles|vertical]] projection of a {{convert|40|m|yd|adj=on}} line centred on the thrower. Outside of competitions, the definition is not so strict, and throwers may be happy simply not to walk too far to recover the boomerang.

=== General properties ===
Long-distance boomerangs are optimised to have minimal drag while still having enough lift to fly and return. For this reason, they have a very narrow throwing window, which discourages many beginners from continuing with this discipline. For the same reason, the quality of manufactured long-distance boomerangs is often non-deterministic.

Today's long-distance boomerangs have almost all an ''S'' or ''? – question mark'' shape and have a [[bevel]]ed edge on both sides (the bevel on the bottom side is sometimes called an undercut). This is to minimise drag and lower the lift. Lift must be low because the boomerang is thrown with an almost total layover (flat). Long-distance boomerangs are most frequently made of composite material, mainly fibre glass [[epoxy]] composites.

=== Flight path ===
The projection of the flight path of long-distance boomerang on the ground resembles a [[Drop (liquid)|water drop]]. For older types of long-distance boomerangs (all types of so-called big hooks), the first and last third of the flight path are very low, while the middle third is a fast climb followed by a fast descent. Nowadays, boomerangs are made in a way that their whole flight path is almost planar with a constant climb during the first half of the trajectory and then a rather constant descent during the second half.

From theoretical point of view, distance boomerangs are interesting also for the following reason: for achieving a different behaviour during different flight phases, the ratio of the rotation frequency to the forward velocity has a U-shaped function, i.e., its [[derivative]] crosses 0. Practically, it means that the boomerang being at the furthest point has a very low forward velocity. The [[kinetic energy]] of the forward component is then stored in the [[potential energy]]. This is not true for other types of boomerangs, where the loss of kinetic energy is non-reversible (the MTAs also store kinetic energy in potential energy during the first half of the flight, but then the potential energy is lost directly by the drag).

== Related terms ==
In [[Noongar language]], ''kylie'' is a flat curved piece of wood similar in appearance to a boomerang that is thrown when hunting for birds and animals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Language {{!}} Kaartdijin Noongar |url= https://www.noongarculture.org.au/language/ |website= www.noongarculture.org.au |publisher= SWLASC |accessdate= 6 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&quot;Kylie&quot; is one of the Aboriginal words for the hunting stick used in warfare and for hunting animals.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.bumerang-sport.de/story/history.htm|title=Whence comes, and what is a boomerang|website=bumerang-sport.de|access-date=26 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Instead of following curved flight paths, kylies fly in straight lines from the throwers. They are typically much larger than boomerangs, and can travel very long distances; due to their size and hook shapes, they can cripple or kill an animal or human opponent. The word is perhaps an English corruption of a word meaning &quot;boomerang&quot; taken from one of the Western Desert languages, for example, the [[Warlpiri language|Warlpiri]] word &quot;karli&quot;.

== Cultural references ==
Trademarks of Australian companies using the boomerang as a symbol, emblem or logo proliferate, usually removed from Aboriginal context and symbolising 'returning'&lt;ref&gt;Jones, P. (1992). 'The boomerang's erratic flight: The mutability of ethnographic objects.' In Journal of Australian Studies, 16(35), 59-71.&lt;/ref&gt; or to distinguish an Australian brand.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;Spearritt, P. (1997). 'Symbols for Australia:The changes to the iconography of political and corporate advertising.' In Artlink, 17(3), 58.&lt;/ref&gt; Early examples included Bain's White Ant Exterminator (1896); Webendorfer Bros. explosives (1898); E. A. Adams Foods (1920); and by the (still current) Boomerang Cigarette Papers Pty. Ltd.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | author1=[[Mimmo Cozzolino|Cozzolino, Mimmo]] | author2=Rutherford, G. Fysh (Graeme Fysh), 1947- | title=Symbols of Australia | date=2000 | page=62 | publisher=Mimmo Cozzolino | edition=20th anniversary | isbn=978-0-646-40309-0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;Aboriginalia&quot;, including the boomerang, as symbols of Australia dates from the late 1940s and early 1950s and was in widespread use by a largely European arts, crafts and design community.&lt;ref&gt;Hume, D. L. (2009). The development of tourist art and souvenirs—the arc of the boomerang: from hunting, fighting and ceremony to tourist souvenir. International journal of tourism research, 11(1), 55-70.&lt;/ref&gt; By the 1960s, the Australian tourism industry extended it to the very branding of Australia,&lt;ref&gt;Prideaux, B., &amp; Timothy, D. J. (2008). Themes in cultural and heritage tourism in the Asia Pacific region. Cultural and heritage tourism in Asia and the Pacific, 1-14.&lt;/ref&gt; particularly to overseas and domestic tourists as souvenirs and gifts and thus Aboriginal culture. At the very time when Aboriginal people and culture were subject to [[White Australia policy|policies]] that [[Stolen Generations|removed]] them from their homelands and sought to assimilate them (physiologically and culturally) into mainstream white Australian culture,&lt;ref&gt;Scates, B. (1997). '‘We Are Not...[A] boriginal... We Are Australian’: William Lane, Racism and the Construction of Aboriginality.' In ''Labour History: A Journal of Labour and Social History'', (72), 35-49.&lt;/ref&gt; Aboriginalia found an ironically &quot;nostalgic&quot;, entry point into Australian popular culture at important social locations: holiday resorts and in Australian domestic interiors. In recent years souvenir objects depicting Aboriginal peoples, symbolism and motifs including the boomerang, from the 1940s–1970s, regarded as kitsch and sold largely to tourists in the first instance, has become highly sought after by both Aboriginal and non-Aboriginal collectors and has captured the imagination of Aboriginal artists and cultural commentators. &lt;ref&gt;Franklin, A. (2010). 'Aboriginalia: Souvenir Wares and the ‘Aboriginalisation’ of Australian Identity.' In ''Tourist Studies'', 10(3), 195-208.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Batarang]]
* [[Bat'leth]]
* [[Captain Boomerang]]
* [[Chakram]]
* [[Commonwealth Boomerang]], a [[World War II]] fighter-plane
* [[Frisbee]]
* [[Googie_architecture|Googie]], boomerang-shaped architecture
* [[Shuriken]]
* [[Throwing stick]]
* [[Valari]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* [http://www.encyclopedia.com/topic/boomerang.aspx Boomerang] (Encyclopaedia.com) 
*{{cite web | title=Meanings and origins of Australian words and idioms: B | website=ANU School of Literature, Languages and Linguistics | date=19 October 2017 | url=https://slll.cass.anu.edu.au/centres/andc/meanings-origins/b}} 
* [[Yukata Nishiyama|Nishiyama, Yutaka]], [http://ijpam.eu/contents/2012-78-3/5/5.pdf Why do boomerangs come back?], Int. J. of Pure and Appl. Math. 78(3), 335–347, 2012. 
* Valde-Nowak ''et al''. (1987). &quot;Upper Palaeolithic boomerang made of a mammoth tusk in south Poland&quot;. ''Nature'' '''329''': 436–438 (1 October 1987); [http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v329/n6138/abs/329436a0.html doi:10.1038/329436a0].

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Boomerangs}}
{{Wiktionary|boomerang}}
* [http://www.ifba-online.com/ International Federation of Boomerang Associations]
* {{cite web | title=Unspinning the boomerang | website=plus.maths.org | date=1 January 1999 | url=https://plus.maths.org/content/unspinning-boomerang}} 
* [http://www.boomerangs.com/aerodynamics.html Boomerang aerodynamics: an online dissertation]
* [http://www.boomerang.org.au/articles/article-what-is-a-boomerang.html Explanation of the origin of the word 'Boomerang'] &lt;!-- We should really merge info from this source --&gt;
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120425162139/http://www.boomerangs.com/boomerang-info41.html How to Throw a Boomerang]
*{{Cite EB1911|wstitle=Boomerang}}

{{Prehistoric technology}}
{{Indigenous Australians|state=expanded}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Australian Aboriginal bushcraft]]
[[Category:Individual sports]]
[[Category:Recreational weapons]]
[[Category:Sports equipment]]
[[Category:Throwing clubs]]
[[Category:Australian inventions]]
[[Category:Sports originating in Australia]]
[[Category:Physical activity and dexterity toys]]
[[Category:Australian English]]
[[Category:Hunting equipment]]
[[Category:National symbols of Australia]]
[[Category:Primitive weapons]]
[[Category:Weapons of Australia]]</text>
      <sha1>sjw8mux10p6zk6w6dluufvindplhywm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
