  <page>
    <title>Blackadder</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4326</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943092431</id>
      <parentid>943080409</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T19:50:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MarnetteD</username>
        <id>220924</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>if you are going to do that then the pipe isn't needed</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses|Black adder (disambiguation){{!}}Black adder|Blackadder (disambiguation)}}
{{short description|British television comedy}}
{{Use British English|date=May 2011}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2012}}
{{Infobox television
| show_name            = Blackadder
| image                = Ba4.jpg
| caption              = Left to right: Tim McInnerny, Rowan Atkinson, Stephen Fry, Tony Robinson and Hugh Laurie in ''Blackadder Goes Forth''
| genre                = [[Period piece|Period]] [[sitcom]]
| creator              = [[Richard Curtis (screenwriter)|Richard Curtis]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Rowan Atkinson]]
| writer               = Richard Curtis&lt;br /&gt;Rowan Atkinson (series 1)&lt;br /&gt;[[Ben Elton]] (series 2–4)
| developer            =
| presenter            =
| starring             = Rowan Atkinson&lt;br /&gt;[[Tony Robinson]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Tim McInnerny]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Miranda Richardson]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Stephen Fry]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Hugh Laurie]]
| voices               =
| narrated             =
| theme_music_composer = [[Howard Goodall]]
| opentheme            =
| endtheme             =
| country              = United Kingdom
| company= [[BBC]]
| distributor =  [[BBC Worldwide]]&lt;br /&gt;[[2entertain]]
| language             = English
| num_series           = 4
| num_episodes         = 24 (plus 3 [[Television special|specials]])
| list_episodes        = List of Blackadder episodes
| producer             = [[John Lloyd (producer)|John Lloyd]]
| executive_producer   =
| camera               = [[Multi-camera]]
| runtime              = 30 minutes approx
| network              = [[BBC1]]
| picture_format       = [[PAL]] ([[576i]])
| audio_format         = Monaural sound
| first_run            =
| first_aired          = {{Start date|1983|6|15|df=y}}
| last_aired           = {{End date|1989|11|2|df=y}}
| preceded_by          =
| followed_by          =
| related              =
| website              = https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b006xxw3
}}

'''''Blackadder''''' is a series of four [[BBC One]] [[Pseudohistory|pseudohistorical]] [[British sitcom]]s, plus several one-off instalments, which originally aired from 1983-1989. All television episodes starred [[Rowan Atkinson]] as the [[antihero]] [[Edmund Blackadder]] and [[Tony Robinson]] as Blackadder's [[dogsbody]], [[Baldrick]]. Each series was set in a different historical period, with the two [[protagonist]]s accompanied by different characters, though several reappear in one series or another, e.g., [[Melchett (Blackadder)|Melchett]] ([[Stephen Fry]]) and [[Lord Flashheart]] ([[Rik Mayall]]).

The first series, ''[[The Black Adder]]'', was written by [[Richard Curtis]] and Rowan Atkinson, while subsequent episodes were written by Curtis and [[Ben Elton]]. The shows were produced by [[John Lloyd (producer)|John Lloyd]]. In 2000, the fourth series, ''[[Blackadder Goes Forth]]'', ranked at 16 in the [[100 Greatest British Television Programmes]], a list created by the [[British Film Institute]]. In a 2001 poll by [[Channel 4]] Edmund Blackadder was ranked third on their list of the [[100 Greatest (TV series)|100 Greatest TV Characters]].&lt;ref name=&quot;GreatestTVcharacters&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.channel4.com/entertainment/tv/microsites/G/greatest/tv_characters/results.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090531160558/http://www.channel4.com/entertainment/tv/microsites/G/greatest/tv_characters/results.html |archivedate=31 May 2009 |title=100 Greatest TV Characters |accessdate=26 May 2019 |publisher=[[Channel 4]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 2004 TV poll to find [[Britain's Best Sitcom]], ''Blackadder'' was voted the second-best British sitcom of all time, topped by ''[[Only Fools and Horses]]''. It was also ranked as the 9th-best TV show of all time by ''[[Empire (magazine)|Empire]]'' magazine.&lt;ref name=&quot;empire&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.empireonline.com/50greatesttv/default.asp?tv=20 |title=The 50 Greatest TV Shows of All Time – Number 20: Blackadder |work=Empire  |accessdate=5 April 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Premise==
{{more citations needed section|date=August 2018}}
Although each series is set in a different era, all follow the misfortunes of [[Edmund Blackadder]] (played by Atkinson), who in each is a member of a British family dynasty present at many significant periods and places in British history. It is implied in each series that the Blackadder character is a descendant of the previous one (the end theme lyrics of series 2 episode &quot;Head&quot; specify that he is the great-grandson of the previous), although it is never specified how or when any of the Blackadders (who are usually bachelors) managed to father children.&lt;ref name=bcg&gt;{{British Comedy Guide|sitcom|blackadder}}, URL accessed 25 July 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

In series one, Edmund Blackadder is not particularly bright, and is much the intellectual inferior of his servant, Baldrick (played by [[Tony Robinson]]). However, in subsequent series the positions are reversed: Blackadder is clever, shrewd, scheming and manipulative while Baldrick is extremely dim. Each incarnation of Blackadder and Baldrick is also saddled with tolerating the presence of a dimwitted [[aristocracy|aristocrat]]. This role was taken in the first two series by [[Lord Percy Percy]], played by [[Tim McInnerny]], with [[Hugh Laurie]] playing the role in the third and fourth series, as [[George (Blackadder)|Prince George, Prince Regent]] and [[George (Blackadder)|Lieutenant George]], respectively.

Each series is set in a different period of [[History of the British Isles|British history]], beginning in 1485 and ending in 1917, and comprises six half-hour episodes. The first series, made in 1983, was called ''[[The Black Adder]]'' and was set in the fictional reign of &quot;[[Richard IV of England (Blackadder)|Richard IV]]&quot;. The second series, ''[[Blackadder II]]'' (1986), was set during the reign of [[Queenie (Blackadder)|Elizabeth I]]. ''[[Blackadder the Third]]'' (1987) was set during the late 18th and early 19th centuries in the reign of [[George III of the United Kingdom|George III]], and  ''[[Blackadder Goes Forth]]'' (1989) was set in 1917 in the trenches of the [[World War I|Great War]].

==Episodes==
{{main|List of Blackadder episodes}}
{{:List of Blackadder episodes}}

===Series 1: ''The Black Adder''===
{{Main|The Black Adder}}
''The Black Adder'', the first series of ''Blackadder'', was written by [[Richard Curtis]] and [[Rowan Atkinson]] and produced by [[John Lloyd (producer)|John Lloyd]]. It originally aired on [[BBC1]] from 15 June 1983 to 20 July 1983, and was a joint production with the Australian [[Seven Network]].

Set in 1485 at the end of the [[Britain in the Middle Ages|British Middle Ages]], the series is written as an [[Counterfactual history|alternative history]] in which [[Richard III of England|King Richard III]] won the [[Battle of Bosworth Field]] only to be mistaken for someone else and murdered, and is succeeded by [[Richard IV of England (Blackadder)|Richard IV]] ([[Brian Blessed]]), one of the [[Princes in the Tower]]. The series follows the exploits of Richard IV's unfavoured second son [[Prince Edmund (Blackadder)|Edmund, the Duke of Edinburgh]] (who calls himself &quot;The Black Adder&quot;) in his various attempts to increase his standing with his father and his eventual quest to overthrow him.

Conceived while Atkinson and Curtis were working on ''[[Not the Nine O'Clock News]]'', the series dealt comically with a number of aspects of medieval life in Britain: [[witchcraft]], royal succession, European relations, the [[Crusade]]s, and the conflict between the Church and the Crown. Along with the secret history, many historical events portrayed in the series were [[anachronism|anachronistic]] (for example, [[Fall of Constantinople|Constantinople]] had already fallen to the [[Ottoman Empire]] in 1453, predating the events in the episode by 33 years); this dramatic licence would continue in the subsequent ''Blackadders''. The filming of the series was highly ambitious, with a large cast and much location shooting. The series also featured [[William Shakespeare|Shakespearean]] dialogue, often adapted for comic effect; the end credits featured the words &quot;Additional Dialogue by William Shakespeare&quot;.

===Series 2: ''Blackadder II''===
{{Main|Blackadder II}}
''Blackadder II'' is set in [[Kingdom of England|England]] during the reign of [[Queenie (Blackadder)|Queen Elizabeth I]] (1558–1603), who is portrayed by [[Miranda Richardson]]. The principal character is [[Lord Blackadder|Edmund, Lord Blackadder]], the great-grandson of the original Black Adder. During the series, he regularly deals with the [[British monarchy|Queen]], her obsequious [[Lord Chamberlain]] [[List of Blackadder characters#Melchett|Lord Melchett]] ([[Stephen Fry]]) – his rival – and the Queen's demented former nanny [[Nursie]] ([[Patsy Byrne]]).

Following the BBC's request for improvements (and a severe budget reduction), several changes were made. The second series was the first to establish the familiar Blackadder character: cunning, shrewd and witty, in sharp contrast to the first series' bumbling [[Prince Edmund (Blackadder)|Prince Edmund]]. To reduce the cost of production, it was shot with virtually no outdoor scenes (the first series was shot largely on location) and several frequently used indoor sets, such as the Queen's [[throne room]] and Blackadder's front room.

A quote from this series ranked number three in a list of the top 25 television &quot;putdowns&quot; of the last 40 years by the ''[[Radio Times]]'' magazine: &quot;The eyes are open, the mouth moves, but Mr. Brain has long since departed, hasn't he, Percy?&quot;

===Series 3: ''Blackadder the Third''===
{{Main|Blackadder the Third}}

''Blackadder the Third'' is set in the late 18th and early 19th centuries, a period known as the [[English Regency|Regency]]. In the series, [[Mr. E. Blackadder|Edmund Blackadder]] Esquire is the butler to the [[Prince Regent]], the [[George (Blackadder)|Prince of Wales]] (the prince is played by [[Hugh Laurie]] as a complete [[fop]] and idiot). Despite Edmund's respected intelligence and abilities, he has no personal fortune to speak of, apart from his frequently fluctuating wage packet (as well, it seems, from stealing and selling off the Prince's socks) from the Prince: &quot;If I'm running short of cash, all I have to do is go upstairs and ask Prince Fathead for a rise.&quot;

As well as Rowan Atkinson and Tony Robinson in their usual roles, this series starred [[Hugh Laurie]] as the [[George (Blackadder)|Prince Regent]], and [[Helen Atkinson-Wood]] as [[Mrs. Miggins]]. The series features [[Samuel Johnson|Dr. Samuel Johnson]] ([[Robbie Coltrane]]); [[William Pitt the Younger]] (Simon Osborne); the [[French Revolution]] (with [[Chris Barrie]], [[Tim McInnerny]] as [[the Scarlet Pimpernel]], and [[Nigel Planer]]); hammy [[English Renaissance theatre|theatrical actors]] ([[Kenneth Connor]] and [[Hugh Paddick]]); a squirrel-hating [[cross-dressing]] [[highwayman]] ([[Miranda Richardson]]); and a [[duel]] with the [[Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of Wellington|Duke of Wellington]] ([[Stephen Fry]]).

===Series 4: ''Blackadder Goes Forth''===
{{Main|Blackadder Goes Forth}}
This series is set in 1917, on the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]] in the trenches of the First World War. Another &quot;big push&quot; is planned, and [[Captain Blackadder]]'s one goal is to avoid being killed, but his schemes always land him back in the trenches. Blackadder is joined by his [[batman (military)|batman]] [[Baldrick#Blackadder Goes Forth|Private S. Baldrick]] (Tony Robinson) and idealistic [[Edwardian period|Edwardian]] twit [[George (Blackadder)#Blackadder Goes Forth|Lieutenant George]] ([[Hugh Laurie]]). [[General Melchett]]  (Stephen Fry) rallies his troops from a French [[château]] thirty-five miles from the front, where he is aided and abetted by his assistant, [[Kevin Darling|Captain Kevin Darling]] (Tim McInnerny), pencil-pusher supreme and Blackadder's nemesis, whose name is played on for maximum comedic value.

The series' tone is somewhat darker than the other ''Blackadder''s; it details the deprivations of trench warfare as well as the incompetence and life-wasting strategies of the top brass. For example, Baldrick is reduced to making coffee from mud and cooking rats, while General Melchett hatches a plan for the troops to walk very slowly toward the German lines, because &quot;it'll be the last thing Fritz will expect.&quot;

The final episode, &quot;[[Goodbyeee]]&quot;, is known for being extraordinarily poignant for a comedy – especially the final scene, which sees the main characters (Blackadder, Baldrick, George, and Darling) finally going &quot;[[Trench warfare|over the top]]&quot; and charging off into the fog and smoke of [[no man's land]] presumably to die. In a list of the [[100 Greatest British Television Programmes]], drawn up by the [[British Film Institute]] in 2000 and voted for by industry professionals, ''Blackadder Goes Forth'' was placed 16th.

===Specials===
{{unreferenced section|date=August 2018}}

====Pilot episode====
{{Main|The Black Adder (pilot episode)}}
The ''Blackadder'' pilot was shot but never broadcast on terrestrial TV in the UK (although some scenes were shown in the 25th anniversary special ''Blackadder Rides Again''). One notable difference in the pilot, as in many pilots, is the casting. Baldrick is played not by Tony Robinson, but by [[Philip Fox (actor)|Philip Fox]]. Another significant difference is that the character of Prince Edmund presented in the pilot is much closer to the intelligent, conniving Blackadder of the later series than the snivelling, weak buffoon of the original. Set in the year 1582, the script of the pilot is roughly the same as the episode &quot;[[Born to Be King (Blackadder)|Born to Be King]]&quot;, albeit with some different jokes, with some lines appearing in other episodes of the series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blackadderhall.com/?page_id=276 |title=The Pilot Episode |publisher=Blackadderhall.com |date=20 June 1982 |accessdate=8 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====''Blackadder: The Cavalier Years''====
{{Main|Blackadder: The Cavalier Years}}
This special, set in the [[English Civil War]], was shown as part of [[Comic Relief (charity)|Comic Relief]]'s [[Comic Relief (charity)|Red Nose Day]] on Friday 5 February 1988. The 15-minute episode is set in November 1648, during the last days of the Civil War. Sir Edmund Blackadder and his servant, Baldrick, are the last two men loyal to the defeated King [[Charles I of England]] (played by Stephen Fry, portrayed as a soft-spoken, ineffective, naive character, with the voice and mannerisms of Charles I's namesake, the [[Charles, Prince of Wales|current Prince of Wales]]). However, due to a misunderstanding between [[Oliver Cromwell]] (guest-star [[Warren Clarke]]) and Baldrick, the king is arrested and sent to the [[Tower of London]]. The rest of the episode revolves around Blackadder's attempts to save the king, as well as improve his standing.

====''Blackadder's Christmas Carol''====
{{Main|Blackadder's Christmas Carol}}
The second special was broadcast on Friday 23 December 1988. In a twist on [[Charles Dickens]]' ''[[A Christmas Carol]]'', [[Ebenezer Blackadder]] is the &quot;kindest and loveliest&quot; man in England. The Spirit of Christmas shows Blackadder the contrary antics of his ancestors and descendants, and reluctantly informs him that if he turns evil his descendants will enjoy power and fortune, while if he remains the same a future Blackadder will live shamefully subjugated to a future incompetent Baldrick. This remarkable encounter causes him to proclaim, &quot;Bad guys have all the fun&quot;, and adopt the personality with which viewers are more familiar.

====''Blackadder: Back &amp; Forth''====
{{Main|Blackadder: Back &amp; Forth}}
''Blackadder: Back &amp; Forth'' was originally shown in the [[Millennium Dome]] in 2000, followed by a screening on [[Sky1|Sky One]] in the same year (and later on BBC1). It is set on the turn of the [[millennium]], and features Lord Blackadder placing a bet with his friends&amp;nbsp;– modern versions of Queenie (Miranda Richardson), Melchett (Stephen Fry), George (Hugh Laurie) and Darling (Tim McInnerny)&amp;nbsp;– that he has built a working [[Time travel in fiction|time machine]]. While this is intended as a clever [[confidence trick|con trick]], the machine surprisingly works, sending Blackadder and Baldrick back to the [[Cretaceous period]], where they manage to cause [[Cretaceous extinction event|the extinction]] of the [[dinosaur]]s through the use of Baldrick's best-worst-and-only pair of underpants as a weapon against a hungry [[Tyrannosaurus|T. Rex]]. Finding that Baldrick has forgotten to write dates on the machine's dials, the rest of the film follows their attempts to find their way back to 1999, often creating huge historical anomalies in the process that must be corrected before the end. The film includes [[cameo appearance]]s from [[Kate Moss]] and [[Colin Firth]].

===Live stage performances===

In 1998, as part of HRH [[Prince Charles]]' 50th Birthday Gala televised on ITV, Atkinson returned to the Cavalier incarnation of Blackadder reading aloud a letter to the Privy Council of King Charles I. He colorfully refuses their invitation to stage a royal gala, calling such occasions &quot;very, very, very dull&quot; and asserting that there was &quot;more musical talent on display when my servant Baldrick breaks wind.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The King's Birthday |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lp07YFH1Op0 |website=YouTube |accessdate=18 February 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2000, on the BBC's annual [[Royal Variety Performance]], Atkinson portrayed Blackadder as a present-day officer in &quot;Her Majesty's Royal Regiment of Shirkers&quot; and delivered a monologue titled &quot;Blackadder: The Army Years,&quot; proposing that Britain regain her former greatness by invading (or at least buying) France.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=&quot;BIackadder, The Army Years. Royal Variety Performance 2000&quot; |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZQCQDvAnbGI&amp;list=PLE7AED796B480E86B&amp;index=61&amp;t=0s |website=YouTube |accessdate=18 February 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2012, as part of the [[Prince's Trust]] charity show ''We Are Most Amused'', Atkinson and Robinson reprised their roles as Blackadder and Baldrick in a comedy sketch featuring [[Miranda Hart]] as leader of a government inquiry into the recent banking crisis. Blackadder, chief executive of a fictional British bank, appearing with Baldrick as his gardener, convinces the panel to publicly blame the entire crisis on Baldrick, to the latter's consternation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Blackadder 2012 (subs) |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a2jQ7jJSZoY&amp;list=PLE7AED796B480E86B&amp;index=60&amp;t=0s |website=YouTube |accessdate=18 February 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Chronological order===
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! Title !! Type !! Production / air date !! Set in century
|-
| ''[[The Black Adder (pilot episode)|The Black Adder (pilot)]]'' || [[Television Pilot|Pilot]] || 1982 (unaired) || 16th
|-
| ''[[The Black Adder]]'' || Series || 1983 || 15th
|-
| ''[[Blackadder II]]'' || Series || 1986 || 16th
|-
| ''[[Blackadder the Third]]'' || Series || 1987 || 18th-19th
|-
| ''[[Blackadder: The Cavalier Years]]'' || [[Comic Relief]] Special || 1988 || 17th
|-
| ''[[Children in Need]]''&lt;ref&gt;J.F. Roberts, The True History of the Black Adder: The Unadulterated Tale of the Creation of a Comedy Legend (Preface publishing, 2000) 253–254.&lt;/ref&gt; || Special || 1988 || Unclear (anachronistic)
|-
| ''[[Blackadder Rides Again|Clown Court]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blackadderhall.com/?p=370 |title=Clown Court on Blackadder Hall|date=2011-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; || Special || 1988 || Unclear (anachronistic)
|-
| ''[[Blackadder's Christmas Carol]]'' || Christmas Special || 1988 || 19th
|-
| ''[[Woman's Hour]] Invasion''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blackadderhall.com/?page_id=261 |title=The ''Woman's Hour'' invasion on Blackadder Hall|date=2011-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; || Radio || 1988 || 20th, Various
|-
| ''[[Blackadder Goes Forth]]'' || Series || 1989 || 20th
|-
| ''[[Blackadder Rides Again|Blackadder and the King's Birthday]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blackadderhall.com/?p=252 |title=The King's Birthday on Blackadder Hall|date=2011-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; || Sketch || 1998 || 17th
|-
| ''[[Blackadder: Back &amp; Forth]]'' || Millennium Special || 1999 || 20th, Various
|-
| ''[[Blackadder Rides Again|Blackadder: The Army Years]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blackadderhall.com/?p=245 |title=The Army Years on Blackadder Hall|date=2011-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; || Theatre || 2000 || 21st
|-
| ''[[Blackadder Rides Again|The Royal Gardener/The Jubilee Girl]]'' (for the [[Party at the Palace]])|| Sketch || 2002 || 21st
|-
| ''[[Blackadder Rides Again|Blackadder Exclusive: The Whole Rotten Saga]]'' || Documentary || 2008 || n/a
|-
| ''[[Blackadder Rides Again]]'' || Documentary || 2008 || n/a
|-
| ''[[Blackadder Rides Again|CEO of Melchett, Melchett and Darling Inquiry]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blackadderhall.com/?p=884 |title=The 2012 sketch on Blackadder Hall|date=2012-11-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 || Theatre || 2012 || 21st
|}

==Production==

===Series development===
Rowan Atkinson and Richard Curtis developed the idea for the sitcom while working on ''[[Not the Nine O'Clock News]]''. Eager to avoid comparisons to the critically acclaimed ''[[Fawlty Towers]]'', they proposed the idea of a historical sitcom.&lt;ref name=&quot;Interviews&quot;&gt;''I Have a Cunning Plan – 20th Anniversary of Blackadder'', [[BBC Radio 4]] documentary broadcast 23 August 2003. Excerpts available at [https://www.bbc.co.uk/comedy/blackadder/interviews/ bbc.co.uk], URL accessed 17 April 2008&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Curtis interview&quot;&gt;[http://www.blackadderhall.com/library/richard_interview.html Interview] at Blackadder Hall, URL accessed 17 April 2008 {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110927024255/http://www.blackadderhall.com/library/richard_interview.html |date=27 September 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; An [[The Black Adder (unaired pilot)|unaired pilot episode]] was made in 1982, and a six-episode series was commissioned. The budget for the series was considerable, with much location shooting particularly at [[Alnwick Castle]] in Northumberland and the surrounding countryside in February 1983.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.alnwickcastle.com/television.php Alnwick Castle official website], URL accessed 2 June 2008 {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081228031113/http://www.alnwickcastle.com/television.php |date=28 December 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0084988/locations Locations] at the [[Internet Movie Database]], URL accessed 17 April 2008&lt;/ref&gt; The series also used large casts of extras, horses and expensive medieval-style costumes. Atkinson has said about the making of the first series:

&lt;blockquote&gt;The first series was odd, it was very extravagant. It cost a million pounds for the six programmes&amp;nbsp;... [which] was a lot of money to spend&amp;nbsp;... It looked great, but it wasn't as consistently funny as we would have liked.&lt;ref name=&quot;Interviews&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Due to the high cost of the first series, the then-controller of programming of [[BBC1]], [[Michael Grade]], was reluctant to sign off a second series without major improvements to the show and drastic cost-cutting, leaving a gap of three years between the two series.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewisohn&quot;&gt;Lewisohn, Mark, [https://web.archive.org/web/20050408071319/http://www.bbc.co.uk/comedy/guide/articles/b/blackadderthe_7770760.shtml ''The Black Adder] at the former [[BBC Guide to Comedy]], URL accessed 17 April 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Atkinson did not wish to continue writing for the second series.{{citation needed|date=August 2018}}

A chance meeting between Richard Curtis and comedian [[Ben Elton]] led to the decision to collaborate on a new series of Blackadder. Recognising the main faults of the first series, Curtis and Elton agreed that ''Blackadder II'' would be a studio-only production (along with the inclusion of a live audience during recording, instead of showing the episodes to an audience after taping). Besides adding a greater comedy focus, Elton suggested a major change in character emphasis: Baldrick would become the stupid [[sidekick]], while Edmund Blackadder evolved into a cunning [[sycophant]]. This led to the familiar set-up that was maintained in the following series.&lt;ref name=&quot;Britain's Best Sitcom&quot;&gt;''[https://www.bbc.co.uk/sitcom/advocate_blackadder.shtml Britain's Best Sitcom – Blackadder]'', 2004 BBC Television documentary, presented by [[John Sergeant (journalist)|John Sergeant]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Only in the ''Back &amp; Forth'' millennium special was the shooting once again on location, because this was a production with a budget estimated at £3&amp;nbsp;million, and was a joint venture between [[Tiger Aspect Productions|Tiger Aspect]], [[Sky Television plc|Sky Television]], the New Millennium Experience Company and the BBC, rather than the BBC alone.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/419247.stm Blackadder's millennium duel]'', [[BBC News]], Friday, 13 August 1999&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;'[http://www.blackadderhall.com/library/skyview.html Black to the Future – Interview with Tony Robinson]' in ''Skyview'', January 2000 {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110927024303/http://www.blackadderhall.com/library/skyview.html |date=27 September 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0212579/trivia Trivia] at the Internet Movie Database, URL accessed 20 April 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

===Casting===
{{unreferenced section|date=August 2018}}
{{Main|List of Blackadder characters}}
Each series tended to feature the same set of regular actors in different period settings, although throughout the four series and specials, only Blackadder and Baldrick were constant characters. Several regular cast members recurred as characters with similar names, implying, like Blackadder, that they were descendants.

====Recurring cast====
{{unreferenced section|date=August 2018}}
Various actors have appeared in more than one of the Blackadder series and/or specials. These are:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:140px;&quot;|
! style=&quot;width:120px;&quot;|''[[The Black Adder]]''
! style=&quot;width:120px;&quot;|''[[Blackadder II]]''
! style=&quot;width:120px;&quot;|''[[Blackadder the Third]]''
! style=&quot;width:120px;&quot;|''[[Blackadder Goes Forth]]''
! style=&quot;width:120px;&quot;|''[[Blackadder: The Cavalier Years]]''
! style=&quot;width:120px;&quot;|''[[Blackadder's Christmas Carol]]''
! style=&quot;width:120px;&quot;|''[[Blackadder: Back and Forth]]''
|-
| align=left|[[Rowan Atkinson]]
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
|-
| align=left|[[Tony Robinson]]
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
|-
| align=left|[[Tim McInnerny]]
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
| 
| 
| {{ya}}
|-
| align=left|[[Hugh Laurie]]
|
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
| 
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
|-
| align=left|[[Stephen Fry]]
|
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
|-
| align=left|[[Miranda Richardson]]
|
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
|
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
|-
| align=left|[[Rik Mayall]]
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
|
| {{ya}}
|
| 
| {{ya}}
|-
| align=left|[[Miriam Margolyes]]
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
|
|
|
| {{ya}}
| 
|-
| align=left|[[Gabrielle Glaister]]
| 
| {{ya}}
|
|{{ya}}
|
| 
| 
|-
| align=left|[[Bill Wallis]]
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
|
| {{ya}}
|
| 
| 
|-
| align=left|[[Robbie Coltrane]]
| 
| 
| {{ya}}
| 
|
| {{ya}}
| 
|-
| align=left|[[Jim Broadbent]]
| {{ya}}
| 
|
| 
| 
| {{ya}}
| 
|-
| align=left|[[Stephen Frost]]
| {{ya}}
| 
|
| {{ya}}
| 
| 
| 
|-
| align=left|[[Mark Arden]]
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
|
| 
| 
| 
| 
|-
| align=left|[[Lee Cornes]]
| 
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
| 
| 
| 
|-
| align=left|[[Patsy Byrne]]
| 
| {{ya}}
|
| 
|
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
|-
| align=left|[[Warren Clarke]]
| 
| 
| {{ya}}
| 
| {{ya}}
| 
| 
|-
| align=left|[[Philip Pope]]
| 
| {{ya}}
|
| 
| 
| {{ya}}
| 
|-
| align=left|Barbara Miller
| {{ya}}
| {{ya}}
|
| 
| 
| 
| 
|-
| align=left|[[David Nunn (actor)|David Nunn]]
| {{ya}}
| 
|
| 
| 
| {{ya}}
| 
|-
| align=left|[[Denis Lill]]
| 
| 
| {{ya}}
| 
| 
| {{ya}}
| 
|}

====Main cast====
*[[Rowan Atkinson]] as [[Edmund Blackadder]], the series' protagonist.
*[[Tony Robinson]] as [[Baldrick|S. Baldrick]], his servant.
*[[Stephen Fry]] played Melchett in two series, first as [[List of Blackadder characters#Melchett|Lord Melchett]], the sycophantic adviser to [[Queenie (Blackadder)|Queen Elizabeth I]] in series two and secondly as [[General Melchett]], a blustering buffoon and presumed descendant in series four. Fry also appeared as [[Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of Wellington|Arthur Wellesley]], The Duke Of Wellington in series three and as various characters in ''Blackadder Back &amp; Forth''.
*[[Tim McInnerny]] played [[Lord Percy Percy]], Blackadder's dimwitted sidekick in series one and two before a change of character to antagonistic rival Captain [[Kevin Darling]] in series four. He also appeared as [[The Scarlet Pimpernel]] (alias Lord Topper and [[Le Comte de Frou Frou]]) for one episode in the third series, and reprised his role as Darling in ''Blackadder: Back &amp; Forth''.
*[[Hugh Laurie]] played [[George (Blackadder)|George]] in series three and four, first as [[George IV of the United Kingdom|The Prince Regent]], and later Lieutenant George in series four. Laurie also appeared twice in series two; firstly as Simon &quot;Farters Parters&quot; Partridge and then as Prince Ludwig the Indestructible in the final instalment of ''Blackadder II''. He similarly reprised this role in ''Back &amp; Forth''.
*[[Miranda Richardson]] was only a regular cast member for series two, in which she played [[Queenie (Blackadder)#Blackadder II|Queen Elizabeth I]], reprising the role in ''Blackadder's Christmas Carol'' and ''Back &amp; Forth''. However, she also played significant one-off roles as [[Amy Hardwood]] (a.k.a. The Shadow) in &quot;[[Amy and Amiability (Blackadder)|Amy and Amiability]]&quot; in the third series and Mary Fletcher-Brown, a dutiful nurse in &quot;[[General Hospital (Blackadder)|General Hospital]]&quot; from the fourth.

====Non-recurring cast====
*[[Brian Blessed]], [[Elspet Gray]] and [[Robert East (actor)|Robert East]] appeared in all six episodes of the first series as the Black Adder's father, mother and brother respectively. Gray had also appeared in the non-broadcast pilot.
*[[Patsy Byrne]] played Nursie in all six episodes of ''[[Blackadder II]]'', but never featured in either of the subsequent series, either as a regular character or one-off. She briefly reprised the character in ''[[Blackadder: Back &amp; Forth]]'' and ''[[Blackadder's Christmas Carol]]''.
*[[Helen Atkinson-Wood]] played the role of [[Mrs. Miggins]] in all six episodes of ''[[Blackadder the Third]]'', but did not appear again in the series, although the character was mentioned several times in ''Blackadder II'' and in the final episode of ''[[Blackadder Goes Forth]]''.

====Guest cast====
[[Ben Elton]]'s arrival after the first series heralded the more frequent recruitment of comic actors from the [[alternative comedy]] era for guest appearances, including [[Robbie Coltrane]], [[Rik Mayall]] (who had appeared in the final episode of the first series as &quot;Mad Gerald&quot;), [[Adrian Edmondson]], [[Nigel Planer]], [[Mark Arden]], [[Stephen Frost]], [[Chris Barrie]] and [[Jeremy Hardy]]. Elton himself played an anarchist in ''Blackadder the Third''.

[[Gabrielle Glaister]] played [[Bob (Blackadder character)|Bob]], an attractive girl who poses as a man, in both series 2 and 4. [[Rik Mayall]] plays [[Lord Flashheart]], a vulgar friend in his first appearance and then a successful rival of Blackadder in later episodes of series 2 and 4. He also played a decidedly Flashheart-like [[Robin Hood]] in ''Back &amp; Forth''. [[Lee Cornes]] also appeared in an episode of all three Curtis-Elton series. He appeared as a guard in the episode &quot;Chains&quot; of ''Blackadder II''; as the poet [[Percy Bysshe Shelley|Shelley]] in the episode &quot;Ink and Incapability' of ''Blackadder the Third''; and as firing squad soldier [[Private (rank)|Private]] Fraser in the episode &quot;Corporal Punishment&quot; of ''Blackadder Goes Forth''.

More established actors, some at the veteran stage of their careers, were also recruited for roles. These included [[Peter Cook]], [[John Grillo]], [[Simon Jones (actor)|Simon Jones]], [[Tom Baker]], [[Jim Broadbent]], [[Hugh Paddick]], [[Frank Finlay]], [[Kenneth Connor]], [[Bill Wallis]], [[Ronald Lacey]], Roger Blake, [[Denis Lill]], [[Warren Clarke]] and [[Geoffrey Palmer (actor)|Geoffrey Palmer]], who played [[Douglas Haig, 1st Earl Haig|Field Marshal Sir Douglas Haig]] in &quot;[[Goodbyeee]]&quot;, the final episode of ''Blackadder Goes Forth''. [[Miriam Margolyes]] played three different guest roles: The Spanish Infanta in [[The Queen of Spain's Beard (Blackadder)|The Queen of Spain's Beard]], Lady Whiteadder in [[Beer (Blackadder)|Beer]], and [[Queen Victoria]] in [[Blackadder's Christmas Carol]].

Unusually for a sitcom based loosely on factual events and in the historical past, a man was recruited for one episode essentially to play himself. Political commentator [[Vincent Hanna]] played a character billed as &quot;his own great-great-great grandfather&quot; in the episode &quot;[[Dish and Dishonesty (Blackadder)|Dish and Dishonesty]]&quot; of ''Blackadder the Third''. Hanna was asked to take part because the scene was of a by-election in which Baldrick was a candidate and, in the style of modern television, Hanna gave a long-running &quot;live&quot; commentary of events at the count (and interviewed candidates and election agents) to a crowd through the [[town hall]] window.

===Theme tune===
[[Howard Goodall]]'s [[theme music|theme tune]] has the same [[melody]] throughout all the series, but is played in roughly the [[History of music|style of the period]] in which it is set. It is performed mostly with trumpets and [[timpani]] in ''The Black Adder'', the fanfares used suggesting typical medieval court fanfares; with a combination of [[Recorder (musical instrument)|recorder]], [[string quartet]] and electric guitar in ''Blackadder II'' (the end theme, with different lyrics each time reflecting on the episode's events, was sung by a countertenor); on [[oboe]], cello and [[harpsichord]] (in the style of a [[minuet]]) for ''Blackadder the Third''; by The Band of the [[3rd Battalion, Royal Anglian Regiment]] in ''Blackadder Goes Forth''; sung by [[Carol (music)|carol singers]] in ''Blackadder's Christmas Carol''; and by an orchestra in ''Blackadder: The Cavalier Years'' and ''Blackadder: Back &amp; Forth''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.howardgoodall.co.uk/works/tv-and-film/blackadder |title=List of Musicians and Singers who Played or Sang on Blackadder and Red Dwarf Themes |publisher=Howardgoodall.co.uk |date= |accessdate=8 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards==
In 2000, the fourth series, ''[[Blackadder Goes Forth]]'', ranked at 16 in the &quot;[[100 Greatest British Television Programmes]]&quot;, a list created by the [[British Film Institute]]. In 2004, a BBC TV poll for &quot;[[Britain's Best Sitcom]]&quot;, ''Blackadder'' was voted the second best British sitcom of all time, topped by ''[[Only Fools and Horses]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The Final Top 10 Sitcoms|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/sitcom/winner.shtml|publisher=BBC|date=March 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was also ranked as the 20th Best TV Show of All Time by ''[[Empire (magazine)|Empire]]'' magazine.&lt;ref name=&quot;empire&quot;/&gt;

==Future==
{{more citations needed section|date=August 2018}}
Despite regular statements denying any plans for a fifth series, cast members are regularly asked about the possibility of a new series.

In January 2005, Tony Robinson told [[ITV (TV network)|ITV]]'s ''[[This Morning (TV programme)|This Morning]]'' that Rowan Atkinson was more keen than he has been in the past to do a fifth series, set in the 1960s (centred on a rock band called the &quot;Black Adder Five&quot;, with [[Baldrick]]&amp;nbsp;– a.k.a. 'Bald Rick'&amp;nbsp;– as the drummer). In the documentary ''Blackadder Rides Again'', Robinson stated that the series would present Blackadder as the bastard son of Queen Elizabeth II and running a Beatles-like rock band. Rowan Atkinson, Tony Robinson, Hugh Laurie, Stephen Fry, Tim McInnerny and Miranda Richardson would have reprised their roles, and reportedly, Brian Blessed, Elspet Gray and Robert East would have returned from the first series to play Blackadder's biological family. Robinson in a stage performance 1 June 2007, again mentioned this idea, but in the context of a movie.{{citation needed|date=August 2018}}

One idea mentioned by Curtis was that it was Baldrick who had accidentally [[John F. Kennedy assassination|assassinated]] [[John F. Kennedy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/newstopics/celebritynews/3178382/Richard-Curtis-Blackadder-was-lined-up-to-be-Sixties-entrepreneur.html|title=Richard Curtis: Blackadder was lined up to be Sixties entrepreneur|publisher=[[Sunday Telegraph]]|date=12 October 2008|accessdate=12 October 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, aside from a brief mention in June 2005,&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc-faces&quot;&gt;{{cite news
 | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/magazine/4606743.stm
 | title = Faces of the week: Richard Curtis
 | work=BBC News
 | date = 3 June 2005
 | accessdate = 6 February 2008
 | quote =...&amp;nbsp;Rowan Atkinson, whose collaborations with Curtis include television and cinema's Mr Bean and TV's Blackadder, which is to enjoy a fifth series next year.
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
there have been no further announcements from the BBC that a new series is being planned. Furthermore, in November 2005, Rowan Atkinson told ''[[BBC Breakfast]]'' that, although he would very much like to do a new series set in [[Colditz]] or another [[prisoner-of-war camp]] during World War II, something which both he and Stephen Fry reiterated at the end of ''Blackadder Rides Again'', the chances of it happening are extremely slim.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=theoldonearethebest|title=Blackadder Rides Again Documentary pt 6 6|date=2011-09-05|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YjOoncjwXgg&amp;list=PL398BAFDB3C5E2009&amp;index=7|accessdate=2017-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There were a couple of ideas that had previously floated for the fifth series. ''Batadder'' was intended to be a parody of ''[[Batman (TV series)|Batman]]'' with Baldrick as the counterpart of [[Robin (comics)|Robin]] (suggested by [[John Lloyd (producer)|John Lloyd]]). This idea eventually came to surface as part of the ''[[Comic Relief (charity)|Comic Relief]]'' sketch &quot;[[Spider-Plant Man]]&quot; in 2005, with Atkinson as [[Spider-Man|the title hero]], Robinson as Robin, [[Jim Broadbent]] as Batman and [[Rachel Stevens]] as [[Mary Jane Watson|Mary Jane]]. ''Star Adder'' was to be set in space in the future (suggested by Atkinson),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://filmtv.eserver.org/black-adder.txt |title=Black Adder Program Guide |accessdate=29 October 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121120155502/http://filmtv.eserver.org/black-adder.txt |archive-date=20 November 2012 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; though this too was touched upon in ''Blackadder's Christmas Carol''.{{citation needed|date=August 2018}}

On 10 April 2007, ''[[Hello!]]'' reported that Atkinson was moving forward with his ideas for a fifth series. He said, &quot;I like the idea of him being a prisoner of war in Colditz. That would have the right level of authority and hierarchy which is apparent in all the Blackadders.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hello-Colditz&quot;&gt;{{cite news
 | url = http://www.hellomagazine.com/celebrities/2007/04/10/blackadder-return/
 | title = Rowan toys with idea of 'Blackadder' return
 | work=HelloMagazine.co.uk
 | publisher=[[Hello!]]
 | date = 10 April 2007
 | accessdate = 6 February 2008
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A post on BlackAdderHall.com by Ben Elton in early 2007 said that ''Blackadder'' would return in some form, whether it be a TV series or film. Elton has since not given any more information on the putative ''Blackadder 5''.{{citation needed|date=August 2018}}

During an interview in August 2007 about his film ''[[Mr. Bean's Holiday]]'', Atkinson was asked about the possibility of a further ''Blackadder'' series, to which the simple reply &quot;No, no chance&quot; was given:

:&quot;There was a plan for a film set in the [[Russian Revolution (1917)|Russian revolution]], a very interesting one called ''The Red Adder''. He would have been a lieutenant in the Secret Police. Then the revolution happened and at the end he is in the same office doing the same job but just the colours on his uniform have changed. It was quite a sweet idea and we got quite a long way with it but in the end it died a death.&quot;{{citation needed|date=August 2018}}

Stephen Fry has expressed the view that, since the series went out on such a good &quot;high&quot;, a film might not be a good idea.&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.is/20120529151802/http://www.darkhorizons.com/news06/060620k.php &quot;Atkinson Developing &quot;Black Adder&quot; Film&quot;], Darkhorizons.com&lt;/ref&gt;

During his June 2007 stage performance, chronicled on the Tony Robinson's Cunning Night Out DVD, Robinson states that, after filming the ''Back &amp; Forth special'', the general idea was to reunite for another special in 2010. Robinson jokingly remarked that Hugh Laurie's success on ''[[House (TV series)|House]]'' may make that difficult.{{citation needed|date=August 2018}}

At the end of ''Blackadder Rides Again'', Robinson asked Tim McInnerny if he would do another series and he responded &quot;no&quot;, because he thought people would not want to see them as they are now and would rather remember them for how they were. In the same documentary, Rowan Atkinson voiced his similar view; 'Times past; that's what they were!' However, Miranda Richardson and Tony Robinson expressed enthusiasm towards the idea of a series set in the Wild West, whilst John Lloyd favoured an idea for a series with a [[Neanderthal]] Blackadder. Lastly, Stephen Fry suggested a series set in a prisoner of war camp during [[World War II]], but later remarked that &quot;perhaps it's best to leave these things as a memory.&quot;{{citation needed|date=August 2018}}

On 28 November 2012, Rowan Atkinson reprised the role at the &quot;We are most amused&quot; comedy gala for the [[Prince's Trust]] at the Royal Albert Hall. He was joined by Tony Robinson as Baldrick. The sketch involved Blackadder as CEO of Melchett, Melchett and Darling bank facing an enquiry over the banking crisis.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/stage/2012/nov/29/we-are-most-amused-review|title=We Are Most Amused – review|last=Logan|first=Brian|date=2012-11-29|website=the Guardian|language=en|access-date=2018-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2015, Tony Robinson said in an interview &quot;I do think a new series of Blackadder is on the cards. I have spoken to virtually all the cast about this now. The only problem is Hugh [Laurie]'s fee. He's a huge star now.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/tv-and-radio/2015/aug/23/blackadder-new-series-on-the-cards-tony-robinson|title=Blackadder new series on the cards, says Tony Robinson|newspaper=The Guardian|date=24 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in October 2018, Richard Curtis &quot;dashed hopes&quot; that the show would return for a fifth series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.herald.ie/news/curtis-reveals-why-blackadder-will-not-return-37419169.html|title=Curtis reveals why Blackadder will not return|date=16 October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Home media==
{{unreferenced section|date=August 2018}}
All series and many of the specials are available on DVD and [[VHS|video]]. Many are also available on BBC audio cassette. As of 2008, a &quot;Best of BBC&quot; edition box set is available containing all four major series together with ''Blackadder's Christmas Carol'' and ''Back &amp; Forth''. All four series and the Christmas special are also available for download on [[iTunes]].

===VHS releases===

5 February 1990, BBC Enterprises Ltd released the first series on two single videos.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:99%;&quot;
|-
!VHS video title
!Year of release
!Episodes
!BBFC rating
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
||''The Blackadder- The Foretelling'' (BBCV 4293)
||5 February 1990
||The Foretelling, Born to Be King, the Archbishop
||PG
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
||''The Blackadder- The Queen of Spain's Beard'' (BBCV 4296)
||5 February 1990
||The Queen of Spain's Beard, Witchsmeller Pursuivant, The Black Seal
||15
|}

2 October 1989, BBC Enterprises Ltd released the second series on two single videos.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:99%;&quot;
|-
!VHS video title
!Year of release
!Episodes
!BBFC rating
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
||''Blackadder II- Parte the Firste'' (BBCV 4298)
||2 October 1989
||Bells, Head, Potato
||PG
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
||''Blackadder II- Parte the Seconde'' (BBCV 4299)
||2 October 1989
||Money, Beer, Chains
||15
|}

6 March 1989, BBC Enterprises Ltd released the third series on two single videos.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:99%;&quot;
|-
!VHS video title
!Year of release
!Episodes
!BBFC rating
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
||''Blackadder The Third- Dish and Dishonesty'' (BBCV 4142)
||6 March 1989
||Dish and Dishonesty, Ink and Incapability, Nob and Nobility
||PG
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
||''Blackadder The Third- Sense and Senility'' (BBCV 4143)
||6 March 1989
||Sense and Senility, Amy and Amibility, Duel and Duality
||15
|}

10 September 1990, BBC Enterprises Ltd released the fourth and final series on two single videos.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:99%;&quot;
|-
!VHS video title
!Year of release
!Episodes
!BBFC rating
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
||''Blackadder Goes Forth- Captain Cook'' (BBCV 4349)
||10 September 1990
||Captain Cook, Corporal Punishment, Major Star
||PG
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
||''Blackadder Goes Forth- Private Plane'' (BBCV 4350)
||10 September 1990
||Private Plane, General Hospital, Goodbyeee
||15
|}

On 7 September 1992, all eight single Blackadder video releases were re-released as four &quot;complete&quot; double VHS releases. The four entire series videos were re-released as single video releases on 2 October 1995.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:99%;&quot;
|-
!VHS video title
!Year of release/Cat No. (Double Video)
!Year of release/Cat No. (Single Video)
!Episodes
!BBFC rating

|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
||''The Blackadder- The Complete Entire Historic First Series''
||7 September 1992 (BBCV 4782)
||2 October 1995 (BBCV 5711)
||The Foretelling, Born to Be King, the Archbishop, The Queen of Spain's Beard, Witchsmeller Pursuivant, The Black Seal
||15
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
||''Blackadder II- The Complete Entire Historic Second Series''
||7 September 1992 (BBCV 4785)
||2 October 1995 (BBCV 5712)
||Bells, Head, Potato, Money, Beer, Chains
||15
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
||''Blackadder the Third- The Complete Entire Historic Third Series''
||7 September 1992 (BBCV 4786)
||2 October 1995 (BBCV 5713)
||Dish and Dishonesty, Ink and Incapability, Nob and Nobility, Sense and Senility, Amy and Amibility, Duel and Duality
||15
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
||''Blackadder Goes Forth- The Complete Entire Historic Fourth Series''
||7 September 1992 (BBCV 4787)
||2 October 1995 (BBCV 5714)
||Captain Cook, Corporal Punishment, Major Star, Private Plane, General Hospital, Goodbyeee
||15
|}

On 5 January 1998, five episodes of the first two series were released on a 15 rated compiled video by BBC Worldwide Ltd.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:99%;&quot;
|-
!VHS video title
!Year of release
!Episodes
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
||''The Very Best of Blackadder'' (BBCV 6360)
||5 January 1998
||Series 1, Episode 3- The Archbishop&lt;br&gt;Series 1, Episode 4- The Queen Of Spain's Beard&lt;br&gt;Series 2, Episode 1- Bells&lt;br&gt;Series 2, Episode 2- Head&lt;br&gt; Series 2, Episode 6- Chains
|}

On 4 November 1991, ''Blackadder's Christmas Carol'' was released on a single video release rated PG (Cat. No. BBCV 4646)

===Single DVD releases===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;text-align:center;&quot;
|-
!DVD title !! Region 1 !! Region 2 !! Region 4
|-
|style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;|Series 1&lt;br /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;''[[The Black Adder]]''&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br /&gt;|| 26 June 2001 || 1 November 1999 || 29 November 1999
|-
|style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;|Series 2&lt;br /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;''[[Blackadder II]]''&lt;/sup&gt; || 26 June 2001 || 6 November 2000 || 11 July 2001
|-
|style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;|Series 3&lt;br /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;''[[Blackadder the Third]]''&lt;/sup&gt;|| 26 June 2001 || 5 February 2001 || 3 October 2001
|-
|style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;|Series 4&lt;br /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;''[[Blackadder Goes Forth]]''&lt;/sup&gt; || 26 June 2001 || 22 October 2001 || 28 February 2002
|-
|style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;|Special 1 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&quot;[[Blackadder's Christmas Carol]]&quot;&lt;/sup&gt; || 26 June 2001 || 18 November 2002 || 4 November 2002
|-
|style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;|Special 2&lt;br /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&quot;[[Blackadder: Back &amp; Forth]]&quot;&lt;/sup&gt; || 26 June 2001 || 15 September 2003 || 11 November 2004
|}

===Box set DVD releases===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:90%;&quot;
|-
!DVD title !! DVD content !! Region 1 !! Region 2 !! Region 4
|-
| The Complete Blackadder – All Four Series ||[[The Black Adder]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Blackadder II]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Blackadder The Third]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Blackadder Goes Forth]]&lt;br /&gt;|| {{n/a}} || 12 November 2001 || 3 October 2002
|-
| Blackadder – The Complete Series ||[[The Black Adder]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Blackadder II]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Blackadder The Third]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Blackadder Goes Forth]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Blackadder's Christmas Carol]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Blackadder: Back &amp; Forth]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Blackadder: The Cavalier Years]]&lt;br /&gt;|| 26 June 2001 || 3 October 2005 || {{n/a}}
|-
| Blackadder Remastered – The Ultimate Edition ||[[The Black Adder]] (Remastered)&lt;br /&gt;[[Blackadder II]] (Remastered)&lt;br /&gt;[[Blackadder the Third]] (Remastered)&lt;br /&gt;[[Blackadder Goes Forth]] (Remastered)&lt;br /&gt;[[Blackadder's Christmas Carol]] (Remastered)&lt;br /&gt;[[Blackadder: Back &amp; Forth]] (Remastered)&lt;br /&gt;[[Blackadder: The Cavalier Years]] (Remastered)&lt;br /&gt;Blackadder Rides Again&lt;br /&gt;+Audio Commentary&lt;br /&gt;+Interviews&lt;br /&gt;|| 20 October 2009 || 15 June 2009 || 1 October 2009
|}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Literature==
* Richard Curtis, Ben Elton, and Rowan Atkinson, ''Blackadder: The Whole Damn Dynasty 1485–1917'' (Penguin Books, 2000). {{ISBN|0-14-029608-5}}. Being the – almost – complete scripts of the four regular series.
* Chris Howarth, and Steve Lyons, ''Cunning: The Blackadder Programme Guide'' (Virgin Publishing, 2002). {{ISBN|0-7535-0447-2}}. An unofficial guide to the series, with asides, anecdotes and observations.
* Richard Curtis and Ben Elton, ''Blackadder: Back &amp; Forth'' (Penguin Books, 2000). {{ISBN|0-14-029135-0}}. A script book with copious photographs from the most recent outing.
* J.F. Roberts, ''The True History of the Black Adder: The Unadulterated Tale of the Creation of a Comedy Legend'' (Preface publishing, 2000). {{ISBN|978-1-84809-346-1}}. A 420-page history of the Blackadder episodes and characters, as well as its birth, its writers and actors, and all the specials.

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
*{{BBC programme}}
*{{tv.com show|blackadder}}
*{{British Comedy Guide|tv|blackadder}}
{{Blackadder}}

[[Category:Blackadder| ]]
[[Category:1983 British television series debuts]]
[[Category:1980s British sitcoms]]
[[Category:BBC television sitcoms]]
[[Category:English-language television programs]]
[[Category:Period television series]]</text>
      <sha1>19jl46sy9r0qif7ov2iyqf1rmt0m006</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
