  <page>
    <title>Backgammon</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4329</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942867152</id>
      <parentid>942404373</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-27T10:19:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JzG</username>
        <id>760284</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* top */Addind &quot;self-published source&quot; inside ref tags where tagged inline only</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about||the 2015 film|Backgammon (film)|the jazz album|Backgammon (album)}}
{{Infobox game
| italic title  = no
| title         = Backgammon
| image_link    = Backgammon lg.png
| image_caption = A backgammon set, consisting of a board, two sets of 15 checkers, two pairs of dice, a doubling cube, and dice cups
| years         = Approximately 5,000 years ago in the [[Middle East]] to present
| genre         = [[Board game]] &lt;br /&gt;[[Race game]] &lt;br /&gt;[[Dice game]] &lt;br /&gt;[[Mind sport]]
| players       = 2
| setup_time    = 10–30 seconds
| playing_time  = 5–60 minutes
| random_chance = Medium ([[dice]] rolling)
| skills        = [[Strategy game|Strategy]], [[Tactic (method)|tactics]], [[counting]], [[probability]]
}}

'''Backgammon''' is one of the oldest known [[board game]]s. Its history can be traced back nearly 5,000 years to archeological discoveries in [[Mesopotamia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wilkinson&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Wilkinson|first=Charles K|date=May 1943|title=Chessmen and Chess|journal=The Metropolitan Museum of Art Bulletin|volume=New Series 1|issue=9|pages=271–279|doi=10.2307/3257111|jstor=3257111}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;murray&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=A History of Board-Games Other than Chess|last=Murray|first=H. J. R.|publisher=Hacker Art Books|year=1952|isbn=978-0-87817-211-5|chapter=6: Race-Games|authorlink=H. J. R. Murray}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bray2011&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Chris Bray|title=Backgammon For Dummies|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0SoloeOOtSkC&amp;pg=PP31|date=14 February 2011|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|isbn=978-1-119-99674-3|pages=31–}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bray2012&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Chris Bray|title=Backgammon to Win|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=m6PfAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA6|year=2012|publisher=Lulu Com|isbn=978-1-291-01965-0|pages=6–}}{{self-published source|date=February 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{self-published inline|date=February 2020}} It is a two-player game where each player has fifteen pieces (''checkers'' or ''men'') that move between twenty-four triangles (''points'') according to the roll of two [[dice]]. The objective of the game is to be first to ''bear off'', i.e. move all fifteen checkers off the board. Backgammon is a member of the [[Tables (board game)|tables]] family, one of the oldest classes of board games.

Backgammon involves a combination of strategy and luck (from rolling dice). While the dice may determine the outcome of a single game, the better player will accumulate the better record over series of many games. With each roll of the dice, players must choose from numerous options for moving their checkers and anticipate possible counter-moves by the opponent. The optional use of a doubling cube allows players to raise the stakes during the game.

Like [[chess]], backgammon has been studied with great interest by [[Computer science|computer scientists]]. Owing to this research, backgammon software has been developed that is capable of beating world-class human players (see [[TD-Gammon]] for an example).

==Rules==
[[Image:BackgammonBoard.svg|thumb|Board in starting position with two dice and doubling cube]]
[[Image:Bg-movement.svg|thumb|Paths of movement for red and black, with checkers in the starting position; viewed from the black side, with home or inner board at lower right]]

Backgammon is not controlled by a dominating authority, yet the &quot;rules of play&quot; are agreed by the international tournaments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Murphy |first=Daniel |date=30 April 2001 |title=Re: International Tourny Formats Rules - Who Can Help? |url=https://bkgm.com/rgb/rgb.cgi?view+688 |quote=Rules of play describe a particular variation of backgammon and on this there is no disagreement among international tournaments. In fact, tournament rules sets do not usually specify these rules but might instead refer, as in the US Rules, to the 'commonly accepted rules of backgammon.' It is understood that this means backgammon as played at international tournaments, not another variant in its own right such as plakoto, portes, fevka or portos.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Backgammon playing pieces may be termed checkers, draughts, stones, men, counters, pawns, discs, pips, chips, or nips.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=0SoloeOOtSkC&amp;pg=PP23#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|page=23|title=Backgammon For Dummies|author= Chris Bray}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=sfZ6DQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT39#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|page=39|title=Gaming Guide - Gambling in Europe|author=Nicolae Sfetcu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The objective is for players to remove (''bear off'') all their checkers from the board before their opponent can do the same. As the playing time for each individual game is short, it is often played in matches where victory is awarded to the first player to reach a certain number of points.

===Setup===
Each side of the board has a track of 12 long triangles, called points. The points form a continuous track in the shape of a [[horseshoe]], and are numbered from 1 to 24. In the most commonly used setup, each player begins with fifteen chips, two are placed on their 24-point, three on their 8-point, and five each on their 13-point and their 6-point. The two players move their chips in opposing directions, from the 24-point towards the 1-point.&lt;ref name=&quot;robertie-winners&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Robertie |first=Bill |authorlink=Bill Robertie |title=Backgammon for Winners |edition=Third |year=2002 |publisher=Cardoza |isbn=978-1-58042-043-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Points 1 through 6 are called the home board or inner board, and points 7 through 12 are called the outer board. The 7-point is referred to as the bar point, and the 13-point as the midpoint.&lt;ref name=&quot;robertie-winners&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;hoyle&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Hoyle's Rules of Games |url=https://archive.org/details/hoylesruleso8fav00hoyl |url-access=registration |edition=Third Revised and Updated |publisher=Signet |year=2001 |pages=321–330 |isbn=978-0-451-20484-4 |author=edited by Albert H. Morehead and Geoffrey Mott-Smith.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Movement===
[[File:Backgammon example.ogv|thumb|Video of a game of backgammon, showing movement around the board, entering from the bar, formation of primes, use of the doubling cube and bearing off]]

To start the game, each player rolls one die, and the player with the higher number moves first using the numbers shown on both dice.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Rules of Backgammon |publisher=Backgammon Galore |url=https://www.bkgm.com/rules.html |quote=To start the game, each player throws a single die. This determines both the player to go first and the numbers to be played. }}&lt;/ref&gt; If the players roll the same number, they must roll again. Both dice must land completely flat on the right-hand side of the gameboard. The players then take alternate turns, rolling two dice at the beginning of each turn.&lt;ref name=&quot;robertie-winners&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;hoyle&quot;/&gt;

After rolling the dice, players must, if possible, move their checkers according to the number shown on each die. For example, if the player rolls a 6 and a 3 (denoted as &quot;6-3&quot;), the player must move one checker six points forward, and another or the same checker three points forward. The same checker may be moved twice, as long as the two moves can be made separately and legally: six and then three, or three and then six. If a player rolls two of the same number, called doubles, that player must play each die twice. For example, a roll of 5-5 allows the player to make four moves of five spaces each. On any roll, a player must move according to the numbers on both dice if it is at all possible to do so. If one or both numbers do not allow a legal move, the player forfeits that portion of the roll and his or her turn ends. If moves can be made according to either one die or the other, but not both, the higher number must be used. If one die is unable to be moved, but such a move is made possible by the moving of the other die, that move is compulsory.

In the course of a move, a checker may land on any point that is unoccupied or is occupied by one or more of the player's own checkers. It may also land on a point occupied by exactly one opposing checker, or &quot;blot&quot;. In this case, the blot has been &quot;hit&quot;, and is placed in the middle of the board on the bar that divides the two sides of the playing surface. A checker may never land on a point occupied by two or more opposing checkers; thus, no point is ever occupied by checkers from both players simultaneously.&lt;ref name=&quot;robertie-winners&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;hoyle&quot;/&gt; There is no limit to the number of checkers that can occupy a point at any given time.

Checkers placed on the bar must re-enter the game through the opponent's home board before any other move can be made. A roll of 1 allows the checker to enter on the 24-point (opponent's 1), a roll of 2 on the 23-point (opponent's 2), and so forth, up to a roll of 6 allowing entry on the 19-point (opponent's 6). Checkers may not enter on a point occupied by two or more opposing checkers. Checkers can enter on unoccupied points, or on points occupied by a single opposing checker; in the latter case, the single checker is hit and placed on the bar. More than one checker can be on the bar at a time. A player may not move any other checkers until all checkers on the bar belonging to that player have re-entered the board.&lt;ref name=&quot;robertie-winners&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;hoyle&quot;/&gt; If a player has checkers on the bar, but rolls a combination that does not allow any of those checkers to re-enter, the player does not move. If the opponent's home board is completely &quot;closed&quot; (i.e. all six points are each occupied by two or more checkers), there is no roll that will allow a player to enter a checker from the bar, and that player stops rolling and playing until at least one point becomes open (occupied by one or zero checkers) due to the opponent's moves.

===Bearing off===
When all of a player's checkers are in that player's home board, that player may start removing them; this is called &quot;bearing off&quot;. A roll of 1 may be used to bear off a checker from the 1-point, a 2 from the 2-point, and so on. If all of a player's checkers are on points lower than the number showing on a particular die, the player must use that die to bear off one checker from the highest occupied point.&lt;ref name=&quot;robertie-winners&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;hoyle&quot;/&gt; For example, if a player rolls a 6 and a 5, but has no checkers on the 6-point and two on the 5-point, then the 6 and the 5 must be used to bear off the two checkers from the 5-point. When bearing off, a player may also move a lower die roll before the higher even if that means the full value of the higher die is not fully utilized. For example, if a player has exactly one checker remaining on the 6-point, and rolls a 6 and a 1, the player may move the 6-point checker one place to the 5-point with the lower die roll of 1, and then bear that checker off the 5-point using the die roll of 6; this is sometimes useful tactically. As before, if there is a way to use all moves showing on the dice, by moving checkers within the home board or bearing them off, the player must do so. If a player's checker is hit while in the process of bearing off, that player may not bear off any others until it has been re-entered into the game and moved into his/her home board, according to the normal movement rules.

The first player to bear off all fifteen of his/her own checkers wins the game. If the opponent has not yet borne off any checkers when the game ends, the winner scores a ''gammon'', which counts for double stakes. If the opponent has not yet borne off any checkers and has some on the bar or in the winner's home board, the winner scores a ''backgammon'', which counts for triple stakes.&lt;ref name=&quot;robertie-winners&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;hoyle&quot;/&gt;

===Doubling cube===
[[Image:Backgammon DoublingCube.jpg|thumb|Doubling cube]]
To speed up match play and to provide an added dimension for strategy, a doubling cube is usually used. The doubling cube is not a die to be rolled, but rather a marker with the numbers 2, 4, 8, 16, 32, and 64 inscribed on its sides, to denote the current stake. At the start of each game, the doubling cube is placed on the midpoint of the bar with the number 64 showing; the cube is then said to be &quot;centered, on 1&quot;. When the cube is centered, either player may start their turn by proposing that the game be played for twice the current stakes. Their opponent must either accept (&quot;take&quot;) the doubled stakes or resign (&quot;drop&quot;) the game immediately.

Whenever a player accepts doubled stakes, the cube is placed on their side of the board with the corresponding [[power of two]] facing upward, to indicate that the right to re-double belongs exclusively to that player.&lt;ref name=&quot;robertie-winners&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;hoyle&quot;/&gt; If the opponent drops the doubled stakes, he or she loses the game at the current value of the doubling cube. For instance, if the cube showed the number 2 and a player wanted to redouble the stakes to put it at 4, the opponent choosing to drop the redouble would lose two, or twice the original stake.

There is no limit on the number of redoubles. Although 64 is the highest number depicted on the doubling cube, the stakes may rise to 128, 256, and so on. In money games, a player is often permitted to &quot;'''beaver'''&quot; when offered the cube, doubling the value of the game again, while retaining possession of the cube.&lt;ref name=&quot;bill_robertie-beavers&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gammonvillage.com/backgammon/news/early_beavers.cfm |title=Backgammon Beavers |accessdate=2007-10-17 |last=Robertie |first=Bill |publisher=GammonVillage }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A variant of the doubling cube &quot;beaver&quot; is the &quot;'''raccoon'''&quot;. Players who doubled their opponent, seeing the opponent beaver the cube, may in turn then double the stakes once again (&quot;raccoon&quot;) as part of that cube phase before any dice are rolled. The opponent retains the doubling cube. E.g. White doubles Black to 2 points, Black accepts then beavers the cube to 4 points; White, confident of a win, raccoons the cube to 8 points, while Black retains the cube. Such a move adds greatly to the risk of having to face the doubling cube coming back at 8 times its original value when first doubling the opponent (offered at 2 points, counter offered at 16 points) should the luck of the dice change.

Some players may opt to invoke '''The Murphy rule''' or the &quot;automatic double rule&quot;. If both opponents roll the same opening number, the doubling cube is incremented on each occasion yet remains in the middle of the board, available to either player. The Murphy rule may be invoked with a maximum number of automatic doubles allowed and that limit is agreed to prior to a game or match commencing. When a player decides to double the opponent, the value is then a double of whatever face value is shown (e.g. if two automatic doubles have occurred putting the cube up to 4, the first in-game double will be for 8 points). The Murphy rule is not an official rule in backgammon and is rarely, if ever, seen in use at officially sanctioned tournaments.

The '''Jacoby rule''', named after [[Oswald Jacoby]], allows gammons and backgammons to count for their respective double and triple values only if the cube has already been offered and accepted. This encourages a player with a large lead to double, possibly ending the game, rather than to play it to conclusion hoping for a gammon or backgammon. The Jacoby rule is widely used in money play but is not used in match play.&lt;ref name=&quot;robertie-serious&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Robertie |first=Bill |authorlink=Bill Robertie |title=Backgammon for Serious Players |edition=Second |year=2006 |pages=19–22 |publisher=Cardoza |isbn=978-0-940685-68-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The '''Crawford rule''', named after [[John R. Crawford]], is designed to make match play more equitable for the player in the lead. If a player is one point away from winning a match, that player's opponent will always want to double as early as possible in order to catch up. Whether the game is worth one point or two, the trailing player must win to continue the match. To balance the situation, the Crawford rule requires that when a player first reaches a score one point short of winning, neither player may use the doubling cube for the following game, called the '''Crawford game'''. After the Crawford game, normal use of the doubling cube resumes. The Crawford rule is routinely used in tournament match play.&lt;ref name=&quot;robertie-serious&quot;/&gt; It is possible for a Crawford game never to occur in a match.

If the Crawford rule is in effect, then another option is the '''Holland rule''', named after
[[Tim Holland (backgammon)|Tim Holland]], which stipulates that after the Crawford game, a player cannot double until after at least two rolls have been played by each side. It was common in tournament play in the 1980s but is now rarely used.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bkgm.com/gloss/lookup.cgi?pat=holland+rule |title=Backgammon Glossary/Holland Rule |publisher=Bkgm.com |date= |accessdate=2009-02-26 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160312074549/http://bkgm.com/gloss/lookup.cgi?pat=holland+rule |archive-date=2016-03-12 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Variants===
{{Main|Tables (board game)}}
[[Image:Alfonso-todas-tablas.jpg|thumb|''Todas tablas'' from the [[Libro de los juegos]]]]
There are many variants of standard backgammon rules. Some are played primarily throughout one geographic region, and others add new tactical elements to the game. Variants commonly alter the starting position, restrict certain moves, or assign special value to certain dice rolls, but in some geographic regions even the rules and directions of the checkers' movement change, rendering the game fundamentally different.

'''[[Acey-deucey]]''' is a variant of backgammon in which players start with no checkers on the board, and must bear them on at the beginning of the game. The roll of 1-2 is given special consideration, allowing the player, after moving the 1 and the 2, to select any desired doubles move. A player also receives an extra turn after a roll of 1-2 or of doubles.&lt;ref&gt;''The Backgammon Book'', Chapter 11, O. Jacoby &amp; J. R. Crawford, 1970, Macmillan &amp; Co&lt;/ref&gt;

'''[[Hypergammon]]''' is a variant of backgammon in which players have only three checkers on the board, starting with one each on the 24-, 23- and 22-points. The game has been [[solved game|strongly solved]], meaning that exact [[expected value|equities]] are available for all 32 million possible positions.&lt;ref name=Tesauro2002&gt;{{cite journal | author = Tesauro, G. | year = 2002 | title = Programming backgammon using self-teaching neural nets | journal = Artificial Intelligence | volume = 134 | issue = 1 | pages = 181–199 | url = http://www.math-info.univ-paris5.fr/~bouzy/Doc/PJR/Backgammon.pdf | accessdate = 2007-08-08 | doi = 10.1016/S0004-3702(01)00110-2 | format = PDF | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20070927050304/http://www.math-info.univ-paris5.fr/~bouzy/Doc/PJR/Backgammon.pdf | archive-date = 2007-09-27 | url-status = dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;strato-variants&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gammonlife.com/variants/index.htm |title=Backgammon Variants |accessdate=2007-08-08 |last=Strato |first=Michael |publisher=Gammonlife | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070913213206/http://www.gammonlife.com/variants/index.htm| archivedate= 13 September 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''[[Nərd]]''' is a traditional variant from [[Azerbaijan]] in which basic rules are almost the same except that even a single piece is 'safe'. There are also different starting positions.{{Citation needed|reason=Redlink. Is this a lame joke?|date=April 2017}}

'''Nackgammon''' is a variant of backgammon invented by Nick &quot;Nack&quot; Ballard&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://home.flash.net/~markthom/html/nackgammon.html |title=Nackgammon |accessdate=2009-02-04 |last=Thompson |first=Mark |publisher=mindfun |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081009231826/http://home.flash.net/~markthom/html/nackgammon.html |archivedate=2008-10-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt; in which players start with one less checker on the six point and midpoint and two checkers on the 23 point.&lt;ref name=&quot;strato-variants&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://gammonline.com/members/Sep01/articles/nackg.htm |title=Nackgammon |accessdate=2007-08-08 |last=Woolsey |first=Kit |date=September 2001 |publisher=Gammonline |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070928125144/http://gammonline.com/members/Sep01/articles/nackg.htm |archive-date=2007-09-28 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Russian backgammon''' is a variant described in 1895 as: &quot;...much in vogue in Russia, Germany, and other parts of the Continent...&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bkgm.com/books/Berkeley/Transcription/#Russian_Backgammon_or_Tric_Trac &quot;Draughts and Backgammon&quot;], 1895, Berkeley&lt;/ref&gt; Players start with no checkers on the board, and both players move in the same direction to bear off in a common home board. In this variant, doubles are more powerful: four moves are played as in standard backgammon, followed by four moves according to the difference of the dice value from 7, and then the player has another turn (with the caveat that the turn ends if any portion of it cannot be completed).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bkgm.com/variants/RussianBackgammon.html |title=Russian Backgammon |publisher=Bkgm.com |accessdate=2009-02-26| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20090313084251/http://bkgm.com/variants/RussianBackgammon.html| archivedate= 13 March 2009 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''[[Gul bara|Gul Bara]]''' and '''[[Tapa (game)|Tapa]]''' are also variants of the game popular in southeastern Europe and Turkey. The play will iterate among Backgammon, Gul Bara, and Tapa until one of the players reaches a score of 7 or 5.

'''[[Coan ki]]''' is an ancient Chinese board game that is very similar.

'''[[Plakoto]]''', '''Fevga''' and '''Portes''' are three versions of backgammon played in Greece. Together, the three are referred to as '''[[Tavli]]'''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bkgm.com/variants/Fevga.html ''&quot;... The three games together are called 'Tavli' and are usually played one after the other in matches of three, five, or seven points...&quot;''], Backgammon Galore! page&lt;/ref&gt;
'''Misere (Backgammon to Lose)''' is a variant of backgammon in which the objective is to lose the game.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bkgm.com/variants/Misere.html&lt;/ref&gt;
Other minor variants to the standard game are common among casual players in certain regions. For instance, only allowing a maximum of five checkers on any point (Britain)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bkgm.com/variants/OldEnglish.html|title=Old English Backgammon|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; or disallowing &quot;hit-and-run&quot; in your home board (Middle East).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bkgm.com/faq/BasicRules.html#is_hit_and_run_allowed_also_known_as_pick_and_pass_|title=Backgammon FAQ: Basic Rules|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://usbgf.org/learn-backgammon/rules-of-backgammon/|title=Backgammon Rules – And How To Play|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''[[Tavla]]''', a Turkish variation.

==Strategy and tactics==
[[Image:Backgammon-set from American civil war.jpeg|thumb|Backgammon set, 19th century]]

Backgammon has an established [[Backgammon opening theory|opening theory]], although it is less detailed than that of chess. The [[Game tree|tree]] of positions expands rapidly because of the number of possible dice rolls and the moves available on each turn. Recent computer analysis has offered more insight on opening plays, but the midgame is reached quickly. After the opening, backgammon players frequently rely on some established general strategies, combining and switching among them to adapt to the changing conditions of a game.

[[File:Backgammon probability.png|thumb|Probability distribution of possible backgammon moves (excluding the use of doubles to move a single checker more than the pips shown on the dice), illustrated by division of probabilities into probability of one die, the sum of two dice and the combined probability of the two cases from 1-12. Six has the highest probability to occur during one move in backgammon (44.44%). {{Confusing section|small=left|reason=The picture is incorrect because it does not take into account that when rolling doubles, a given distance may be traveled using the rolled number 3 or 4 times. For instance, the probability of hitting a blot at distance 6 is 17/36, not 16/36 as claimed, because this may happen not only by rolling a 6 (probability 11/36, correctly shown in the picture) or rolling the sum of 6 (probability 5/36, correctly shown in the picture), but also by rolling 2-2 (probability 1/36, not considered in the picture)|date=November 2018}}]]

A blot has the highest probability of being hit when it is 6 points away from an opponent's checker (see picture). Strategies can derive from that. The most direct one is simply to avoid being hit, trapped, or held in a stand-off. A &quot;running game&quot; describes a strategy of moving as quickly as possible around the board, and is most successful when a player is already ahead in the race.&lt;ref name=&quot;magriel&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Magriel |first=Paul |authorlink=Paul Magriel |title=Backgammon |year=1976 |publisher=Quadrangle/The New York Times Book Co |isbn= 978-0-8129-0615-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; When this fails, one may opt for a &quot;holding game&quot;, maintaining control of a point on one's opponent's side of the board, called an anchor. As the game progresses, this player may gain an advantage by hitting an opponent's blot from the anchor, or by rolling large doubles that allow the checkers to escape into a running game.&lt;ref name=&quot;magriel&quot;/&gt;

The &quot;priming game&quot; involves building a wall of checkers, called a prime, covering a number of consecutive points. This obstructs opposing checkers that are behind the prime. A checker trapped behind a six-point prime cannot escape until the prime is broken.&lt;ref name=&quot;magriel&quot;/&gt; A particularly successful priming effort may lead to a &quot;blitz&quot;, which is a strategy of covering the entire home board as quickly as possible while keeping one's opponent on the bar. Because the opponent has difficulty re-entering from the bar or escaping, a player can quickly gain a running advantage and win the game, often with a gammon.&lt;ref name=&quot;robertie-winners&quot;/&gt;

A &quot;backgame&quot; is a strategy that involves holding two or more anchors in an opponent's home board while being substantially behind in the race.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bkgm.com/gloss/lookup.cgi?back+game%20game|title=Backgammon Glossary/Back Game|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The anchors obstruct the opponent's checkers and create opportunities to hit them as they move home. The backgame is generally used only to salvage a game wherein a player is already significantly behind. Using a backgame as an initial strategy is usually unsuccessful.&lt;ref name=&quot;robertie-winners&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;magriel&quot;/&gt;

&quot;Duplication&quot; refers to the placement of checkers such that one's opponent needs the same dice rolls to achieve different goals. For example, players may position all of their blots in such a way that the opponent must roll a 2 in order to hit any of them, reducing the probability of being hit more than once.&lt;ref name=&quot;robertie-winners&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;magriel&quot;/&gt; &quot;Diversification&quot; refers to a complementary tactic of placing one's own checkers in such a way that more numbers are useful.&lt;ref name=&quot;magriel&quot;/&gt;

Many positions require a measurement of a player's standing in the race, for example, in making a doubling cube decision, or in determining whether to run home and begin bearing off. The minimum total of pips needed to move a player's checkers around and off the board is called the &quot;pip count&quot;. The difference between the two players' pip counts is frequently used as a measure of the leader's racing advantage. Players often use [[mental calculation]] techniques to determine pip counts in live play.&lt;ref name=&quot;magriel&quot;/&gt;

Backgammon is played in two principal variations, &quot;Money&quot; and &quot;Match&quot; play. Money play means that every point counts evenly and every game stands alone, whether money is actually being wagered or not. &quot;Match&quot; play means that the players play until one side scores (or exceeds) a certain number of points. The format has a significant effect on strategy. In a match, the objective is not to win the maximum possible number of points, but rather to simply reach the score needed to win the match. For example, a player leading a 9-point match by a score of 7–5 would be very reluctant to turn the doubling cube, as their opponent could take and make a costless redouble to 4, placing the entire outcome of the match on the current game. Conversely, the trailing player would double very aggressively, particularly if they have chances to win a gammon in the current game. In money play, the theoretically correct checker play and cube action would never vary based on the score.

In 1975, Emmet Keeler and Joel Spencer considered the question of when to double or accept a double using an idealized version of backgammon. In their idealized version, the probability of winning varies randomly over time by [[Brownian motion]], and there are no gammons or backgammons. They showed that the optimal time to offer a double was when the probability of winning reached 80%, and it is wise to accept a double only if the probability of winning is at least 20%. As their assumptions do not correspond perfectly to the real game, actual doubling strategy may vary, but the 80% number still provides a possible rule of thumb.&lt;ref name=&quot;keeler&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Keeler |first=Emmet |last2=Spencer |first2=Joel |date=1975 |title=Optimal Doubling in Backgammon |journal=[[Operations Research (journal)|Operations Research]] |volume=23 |issue=6 |pages=1063–1071 |doi= 10.1287/opre.23.6.1063}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cheating==
To reduce the possibility of cheating, most good quality backgammon sets use [[Dice#Precision dice|precision dice]] and a [[dice cup]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Dummies&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Bray|first1=Chris|title=Backgammon for Dummies|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|year=2008|isbn=978-0-470-69456-5|page=13 and 224}}&lt;/ref&gt; This reduces the likelihood of [[loaded dice]] being used, which is the main way of cheating in face-to-face play.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Harrington Green|first1=Jonathan|title=An exposure of the arts and miseries of gambling|url=https://archive.org/details/anexposureartsa01greegoog|publisher=Redding|year=1845|page=203}}&lt;/ref&gt; A common method of cheating online is the use of a computer program to find the optimal move on each turn; to combat this, many online sites use move-comparison software that identifies when a player's moves resemble those of a backgammon program. Online cheating has therefore become extremely difficult.&lt;ref name=Dummies/&gt;

==Social and competitive play==
[[Image:Wurfzabel.jpg|thumb|Medieval players, from the 13th century [[Carmina Burana]]]]

===Legality===
In ''State of Oregon v Barr'', a 1982 court case pivotal to the continued widespread organised playing of backgammon in the US, the State argued backgammon is a game of chance and that it was therefore subject to Oregon's stringent gambling laws. [[Paul Magriel]] was a key witness for the defence, contradicting Dr. Roger Nelson, the expert prosecution witness, by saying, &quot;Game theory, however, really applies to games with imperfect knowledge, where something is concealed, such as poker. Backgammon is not such a game. Everything is in front of you. The person who uses that information in the most effective manner will win.&quot; After the closing arguments, Judge Stephen S. Walker concluded that backgammon is a game of skill, not a game of chance, and found the defendant, backgammon tournament director Ted Barr, not guilty of promoting gambling.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | newspaper=Backgammon Times | title=The Trial (and Tribulations) of Oregon Promoter Ted Barr | volume=2 | issue=2 | year=1982 | url=http://www.bkgm.com/articles/BackgammonTimes/LuckVsSkill-TrialOfTedBarr/index.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Early Muslim scholars [[haram|forbade]] backgammon.&lt;ref&gt;Rosenthal, Franz. ''Humor in Early Islam'' (2011), [[Brill Publishers|BRILL]] p.98&lt;/ref&gt; The prohibition was based on sayings attributed to the [[Prophet Muhammad]] regarding gambling in general and backgammon in particular, such as: &quot;Whoever plays backgammon it is as if he puts his hand in the pork and pig's blood.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;https://www.islamweb.net/en/fatwa/91109/&lt;/ref&gt; Contemporary Ayatollah [[Ali al-Sistani]] of Iraq, one of the prominent religious leaders of [[Shia Islam|Shia Muslims]], issued ruled that backgammon “is absolutely forbidden even without placing a bet”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jan/21/chess-forbidden-in-islam-rules-saudi-arabia-grand-mufti |newspaper=The Guardian |publicationdate=2016-01-26 |author=Kareem Shaheen|title=Chess forbidden in Islam, rules Saudi mufti, but issue not black and white |accessdate=2019-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Club and tournament play===
Enthusiasts have formed [[Club (organization)|club]]s for social play of backgammon. Local clubs may hold informal gatherings, with members meeting at cafés and bars in the evening to play and converse.&lt;ref name=&quot;sydney&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Tribes of Sydney—Sydney Backgammon Club |work=The Daily Telegraph (Australia) |date=June 24, 2006 |page=95}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bray1&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Bray |first=Chris |title=Backgammon |work=The Independent (London) |date=June 29, 2002 |page=50}}&lt;/ref&gt; A few clubs offer additional services, maintaining their own facilities or offering computer analysis of troublesome plays.&lt;ref name=&quot;bray2&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Bray |first=Chris |title=Backgammon |work=The Independent (London) |date=November 25, 2000 |page=19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some club leaders have noticed a recent{{when|date=October 2014}} growth of interest in backgammon, and attribute it to the game's popularity on the [[Internet]].&lt;ref name=&quot;laverty&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Laverty |first=Roy |title=Backgammon warriors—columnist, club member square off as board game's popularity grows |work=[[Alameda Times-Star]] (Section: Bay Area Living)|date=May 16, 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[backgammon chouette]] permits three or more players to participate in a single game, often for money. One player competes against a team of all the other participants, and positions rotate after each game. Chouette play often permits the use of multiple doubling cubes.&lt;ref name=&quot;robertie-winners&quot;/&gt;

Backgammon clubs may also organize [[tournaments]]. Large club tournaments sometimes draw competitors from other regions, with final matches viewed by hundreds of spectators.&lt;ref name=&quot;magriel-nyt&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Magriel |first=Paul |authorlink=Paul Magriel |title=Backgammon: Before Planning Big Attack, Be Sure to Cover Your Rear |work=The New York Times, Late City Final Edition |date=June 1, 1980 |pages=50, section 1, part 2}}&lt;/ref&gt; The top players at regional tournaments often compete in major national and international championships. Winners at major tournaments may receive prizes of tens of thousands of [[US dollar|dollars]].&lt;ref name=&quot;maxa&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Maxa |first=Rudy |authorlink=Rudy Maxa |title=Where the Rich And the Royal Play Their Games—Monte Carlo's Seven-Day Backgammon Soiree With Countesses, Princes and Other Sharpies |work=The Washington Post |date=September 6, 1981 |page=H1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Starting in January 2018, tournament directors began awarding GammonPoints,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.gammonpoints.com/|title=GammonPoints|website=www.gammonpoints.com|language=en|access-date=2018-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; a free points registry for tournament directors and players, with GammonPoint awards based on the number of players and strength of field.

===International competition===
{{See also|List of World Backgammon champions}}
The first world championship competition in backgammon was held in [[Las Vegas Valley|Las Vegas]], [[Nevada]] in 1967. [[Tim Holland (backgammon)|Tim Holland]] was declared the winner that year and at the tournament the following year. For unknown reasons, there was no championship in 1970, but in 1971, Tim Holland again won the title. The competition remained in Las Vegas until 1975, when it moved to [[Paradise Island]] in the [[Bahamas]]. The years 1976, 1977 &amp; 1978 saw &quot;dual&quot; World Championships, one in the Bahamas attended by the Americans, and the ''European Open Championships'' in [[Monte Carlo]] with mostly European players. In 1979, Lewis Deyong, who had promoted the Bahamas World Championship for the prior three years, suggested that the two events be combined.&lt;ref name=&quot;PLAY65&quot;&gt;[http://www.play65.com/World-Backgammon-Championships-History.html] Play65, The History of the World Backgammon Championships&lt;/ref&gt; Monte Carlo was universally acknowledged as the site of the World Backgammon Championship and has remained as such for thirty years.&lt;ref name=&quot;mindzine&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msoworld.com/mindzine/news/classic/bg/tournaments/world00report.html |title=Backgammon News—World Championships 2000 |author=Michael Crane |publisher=Mind Sports Worldwide |date=July 25, 2000 |accessdate=2006-09-14 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060907014829/http://www.msoworld.com/mindzine/news/classic/bg/tournaments/world00report.html |archivedate=7 September 2006 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Monte Carlo tournament draws hundreds of players and spectators, and is played over the course of a week.&lt;ref name=&quot;maxa&quot;/&gt;

By the 21st century, the largest international tournaments had established the basis of a tour for top professional players. Major tournaments are held yearly worldwide. [[PartyGaming]] sponsored the first [[World Series of Backgammon]] in 2006 from Cannes and later the 'Backgammon Million' tournament held in the [[Bahamas]] in January 2007 with a prize pool of one million dollars, the largest for any tournament to date.&lt;ref name=&quot;partygammon&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=PartyGammon.com to Stage First Ever US$1 Million Backgammon Tournament |work=PR Newswire |date=July 10, 2006 |publisher=[[Lexis-Nexis]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, the [[World Series of Backgammon]] ran the world's largest international events in London, the UK Masters, the biggest tournament ever held in the UK with 128 international class players; the Nordic Open, which instantly became the largest in the world with around 500 players in all flights and 153 in the Championship, and Cannes, which hosted the Riviera Cup, the traditional follow-up tournament to the World Championships. Cannes also hosted the WSOB Championship, the WSOB finale, which saw 16 players play three-point shootout matches for €160,000. The event was recorded for television in Europe airing on Eurosport.

The World Backgammon Association (WBA)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.world-backgammon-association.com|title=World Backgammon Association|website=www.world-backgammon-association.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; has been holding the biggest backgammon Tour of the circuit since 2007, the &quot;European Backgammon Tour&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ebgt.info|title=Home|website=www.ebgt.info}}&lt;/ref&gt; (EBGT). In 2011, the WBA collaborated with the online backgammon provider [[Play65]] for the 2011 season of the European Backgammon Tour and with &quot;Betfair&quot; in 2012. The 2013 season of the European Backgammon Tour featured 11 stops and 19 qualified players competing for 19,000 € in a Grand Finale in [[Lefkosa]], [[Northern Cyprus]].

===Gambling===
When backgammon is [[Gambling|played for money]], the most common arrangement is to assign a monetary value to each point, and to play to a certain score, or until either player chooses to stop. The stakes are raised by gammons, backgammons, and use of the doubling cube. Backgammon is sometimes available in [[casino]]s. Before the commercialization of [[artificial neural network]] programs, [[proposition bet]]s on specific positions were very common among backgammon players and gamblers.&lt;ref&gt;Wachtel, Robert [http://www.backgammon.org/articles/backgammon-proposition-week/ &quot;Backgammon Proposition&quot;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20091010184227/http://www.backgammon.org/articles/backgammon-proposition-week/ |date=2009-10-10 }} backgammon.org&lt;/ref&gt; As with most gambling games, successful play requires a combination of luck and skill, as a single dice roll can sometimes significantly change the outcome of the game.&lt;ref name=&quot;magriel&quot;/&gt;

==Software==
===Internet play===
Backgammon software has been developed not only to play and analyze games, but also to facilitate play between humans over the [[internet]]. Dice rolls are provided by [[random number generator|random]] or [[pseudorandom number generator]]s. Real-time online play began with the [[First Internet Backgammon Server]] in July 1992,&lt;ref name=&quot;fibs-hist&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Schneider |first=Andreas |url=http://www.fibs.com/guide.html#history |title=Brief history of FIBS |publisher=FIBS, the First Internet Backgammon Server |accessdate=2006-08-05 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060813210439/http://www.fibs.com/guide.html#history |archivedate=2006-08-13 |url-status=dead |display-authors=etal }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fibs-announce&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Backgammon server available NOW|last=Schneider|first=Andreas|url=https://groups.google.com/group/rec.games.backgammon/msg/90530ae12919967f?hl=en&amp;dmode=source&quot;|accessdate=2012-02-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; but there are now a range of options;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Keith|first1=Tom|title=Backgammon Play Sites|url=http://www.bkgm.com/servers.html|website=Backgammon galore!|accessdate=6 March 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; many of which are commercial.

===Play and analysis===
[[Image:GNU bg screenshot.png|thumb|A screen shot of GNU Backgammon, showing an evaluation and rollout of possible moves]]
Backgammon has been studied considerably by [[Computer science|computer scientists]]. [[Artificial neural network|Neural networks]] and other approaches have offered significant advances to software for gameplay and analysis.

The first strong computer opponent was BKG 9.8. It was written by [[Hans Berliner]] in the late 1970s on a DEC [[PDP-10]] as an experiment in evaluating board game positions. Early versions of BKG played badly even against poor players, but Berliner noticed that its critical mistakes were always at transitional phases in the game. He applied principles of [[fuzzy logic]] to improve its play between phases, and by July 1979, BKG 9.8 was strong enough to play against the reigning world champion [[Luigi Villa]]. It won the match, 7–1, becoming the first computer program to defeat a world champion in any board game. Berliner stated that the victory was largely a matter of luck, as the computer received more favorable dice rolls.&lt;ref name=&quot;berliner-acm&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Berliner |first=Hans |title=Backgammon program beats world champ |journal=ACM SIGART Bulletin |issue=69 |date=January 1980 |pages=6–9 |doi=10.1145/1056433.1056434}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the late 1980s, backgammon programmers found more success with an approach based on [[artificial neural network]]s. [[TD-Gammon]], developed by Gerald Tesauro of [[IBM]], was the first of these programs to play near the expert level. Its neural network was trained using [[temporal difference learning]] applied to data generated from self-play.&lt;ref name=&quot;tesauro-acm&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Tesauro |first=Gerald |url=http://www.research.ibm.com/massive/tdl.html |title=Temporal difference learning and TD-Gammon |journal=Communications of the ACM |volume=38 |issue=3 |date=March 1995 |pages=58–68 |doi=10.1145/203330.203343}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to assessments by [[Bill Robertie]] and [[Kit Woolsey]], TD-Gammon's play was at or above the level of the top human players in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;tesauro-acm&quot;/&gt; Woolsey said of the program that &quot;There is no question in my mind that its positional judgment is far better than mine.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;tesauro-acm&quot;/&gt;

Tesauro proposed using [[Rollout (backgammon)|rollout analysis]] to compare the performance of computer algorithms against human players.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tesauro2002&quot;/&gt; In this method, a [[Monte Carlo method|Monte-Carlo evaluation]] of positions is conducted (typically thousands of trials) where different random dice sequences are simulated. The rollout score of the human (or the computer) is the difference of the average game results by following the selected move versus following the best move, then averaged for the entire set of taken moves.

Neural network research has resulted in three modern [[Proprietary software|proprietary programs]], JellyFish,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.backgammon.help/software.html|title=Backgammon software - Backgammon Online Guide|website=www.backgammon.help|access-date=2015-08-10|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150816163340/http://www.backgammon.help/software.html|archive-date=2015-08-16|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Snowie&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bgsnowie.com|title=BackgammonSnowie - World class poker coaching software|website=www.bgsnowie.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; and eXtreme Gammon&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.extremegammon.com|title=eXtreme Gammon|website=www.extremegammon.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the [[shareware]] BGBlitz&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bgblitz.com |title=BGBlitz |publisher=BGBlitz |accessdate=2009-02-26| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20090225122525/http://bgblitz.com/| archivedate= 25 February 2009 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[free software]] GNU Backgammon.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gnubg.org GNU Backgammon].&lt;/ref&gt; These programs not only play the game, but offer tools for analyzing games and detailed comparisons of individual moves. The strength of these programs lies in their neural networks' weights tables, which are the result of months of training. Without them, these programs play no better than a human novice. For the bearoff phase, backgammon software usually relies on a database containing precomputed equities for all possible bearoff positions.

Computer-versus-computer competitions are also held at [[Computer Olympiad#Backgammon|Computer Olympiad]] events.

==History==
===Iran (Persia)===
{{See also|Nard (game)}}
Remains of a board game from 3000 BC were found at [[Shahr-e Sukhteh]] ([[Persian language|Persian]] شهر سوخته) in [[Iran]]. The artifacts included two dice and 60 checkers, and the set is believed to be 100 to 200 years older than the [[Royal Game of Ur]]. On the board found in Shahr-e Sukhteh the fields are fashioned by the coils of a snake.&lt;ref name=&quot;Payvand&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.payvand.com/news/04/dec/1029.html|title=World's Oldest Backgammon Discovered In Burnt City|date=December 4, 2004|work=Payvand News|accessdate=2010-05-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Iranica board game&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|title=BOARD GAMES in pre-Islamic Persia|encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Iranica | url=http://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/board-games-in-pre-islamic-persia|accessdate=2018-04-11 | last1=Schädler | first1=Ulrich | last2=Dunn-Vaturi | first2=Anne-Elizabeth}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Board game artifacts found at [[Jiroft]], from about 2000 BC, may represent a game that is more closely related to modern backgammon than those found at Shahr-e Sukhteh and Ur.&lt;ref name=&quot;Iranica board game&quot; /&gt;

[[Touraj Daryaee]] (2006)—on the subject of the first written mention of early precursors of backgammon—writes:
{{quote|The game of backgammon is first mentioned in Bhartrhari’s ''Vairagyasataka'' (p. 39), composed around the late 6th or early 7th century AD. The use of dice for the game is another indication of its Indic origin, since dice and gambling were a favorite pastime in ancient India. The rules of the game, however, first appeared in the [[Middle Persian]] text ''Wızarisnı Catrang ud Nihisnı New Ardaxsır'' (Explanation of Chess and Invention of Backgammon), composed in the 6th century during the rule of the Sasanian king [[Khosrow I]] (530–571). The text assigns its invention to the Persian sage Wuzurgmihr (Persian) [[Burzoe|Buzarjumihr/Bozorgmehr]], who was the minister of King [[Khosrau I|Khosrow I]]. According to the historical legend, the Indian king Dewisarm sends his minister Taxritos to [[Persia]] with the game of [[chess]], and a letter challenging Sasanian King Khosrow I to solve the riddle or rationale for the game. Khosrow asks for three days to decipher the game, but initially no-one in the court is able to make any progress. On the third day, Khosrow's minister, Wuzurgmihr, successfully rises and explains the logic of the game. As a reciprocal challenge, Wuzurgmihr constructs the game of backgammon and delivers it to the Indian king who is unable to decipher the game.&lt;ref&gt;Daryaee, Touraj (2006) in &quot;Backgammon&quot; in ''Medieval Islamic Civilization: An Encyclopedia'' ed. Meri, Josef W. &amp; Bacharach, Jere L, pp. 88-89. Taylor &amp; Francis.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In the 11th century ''[[Shahnameh]]'', the [[Persia]]n poet [[Ferdowsi]] credits [[Burzoe]] with the invention of the tables game ''nard'' in the 6th century. He describes an encounter between Burzoe and a [[Raja]] visiting from India. The Raja introduces the game of [[chess]], and Burzoe demonstrates ''nard'', played with dice made from [[ivory]] and [[teak]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wilkinson&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;murray&quot;/&gt; Today, Nard is the name for the Persian version of backgammon, which has different initial positions and objectives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iranian.com/Alimagham/2006/February/Backgammon/index.html,|title=Backgammon, or Takheth Nard|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; H. J. R. Murray details many versions of backgammon; modern Nard is noted there as being the same as backgammon and maybe dating back to 300–500 AD in the Babylonian Talmud,&lt;ref name=&quot;murray&quot; /&gt; although others believe the Talmud references the Greek race game Kubeia.

===Mesopotamia (Modern Iraq)===
The history of backgammon can be traced back nearly 5,000 years to its origins in Mesopotamia (modern-day Iraq).&lt;ref name=&quot;Bray2011&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bray2012&quot;/&gt; Excavations in [[Iraq]] have shown that a board race game existed there around 5000 BC.{{citation needed|date=January 2019}} The world's oldest set of dice (made from human bone) were recently discovered in that part of the world. Modern Iraqis continue to enjoy playing the game.&lt;ref name=&quot;GrahamMcCoy2008&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Leland Graham|author2=Isabelle McCoy|title=A New Trip Around the World, Grades K - 5: Activities Across the Curriculum for Cuba, the United Kingdom, Afghanistan, Chile, Iraq, Puerto Rico, Ghana, Morocco, Norway, Guatemala, Spain, and Peru|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qfJpAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA85|date=28 August 2008|publisher=Carson-Dellosa Publishing|isbn=978-1-60418-594-2|pages=85–}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The Royal Game of Ur, originating in ancient [[Mesopotamia]] before 2600 BC, may also be an ancestor of modern-day table games like backgammon. It used tetrahedral dice. In the modern Middle East, backgammon is a common feature of [[coffeehouse]]s. Race board games involving dice have a long history in Iraq, including the [[Royal Game of Ur]] in Babylon. Today the game is commonly played in Iraq, Lebanon, Egypt, Syria, Jordan, and other Arab countries.

In the (modern) Arab [[Levant]] and Iraq it is called ''tawle'', which means table, and it is also called ''shesh besh'' (shesh means 6 in [[Hebrew]], [[Aramaic]] and [[Phoenician language|Phoenician]], but derives from Phoenician. However, shesh also means 6 in [[Persian language|Persian]] and 5 is likely to be closely related to &quot;Penj&quot; meaning 5. Shesh Besh is commonly referred to the situation when a player scores a 5 and 6 at the same time on dice).&lt;ref name=&quot;BoueriBoutros2006&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Marijean Boueri|author2=Jill Boutros|author3=Joanne Sayad|title=Lebanon A to Z: A Middle Eastern Mosaic|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VIemBhgNmpAC&amp;pg=PA59|date=April 2006|publisher=PublishingWorks|isbn=978-0-9744803-4-3|pages=59–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Armenia===
Backgammon or [[Nard (game)|nardi]] ({{lang-hy|նարդի}}) is very popular among [[Armenians]]. The word is derived from Persian word ''nard'' ({{lang-fa|نرد}}). There are two games of nardi commonly played:

Short nardi: Set-up and rules the same as backgammon.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.vnews.am/kartch-nardi-xaghalu-kanonnereh-ev-orenkhnereh/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Long nardi: A game that starts with all fifteen checkers placed in one line-on 24-point and on 11-point. The two players move their checkers in opposing directions, from the 24-point towards the 1-point, or home board. In long nardi one checker by itself can block a point. There is no hitting in long nardi. The objective of the game is bearing all checkers off the board. There is no doubling cube.

===Roman and Byzantine Empire===
[[File:Tabula - boardgame - Zeno game.svg|thumb|upright=1.10|right|A game of [[tabula (game)|τάβλη (tabula)]] played by [[Byzantine]] Emperor [[Zeno (emperor)|Zeno]] in 480 and recorded by [[Agathias]] in 530 circa because of a very unlucky dice throw for Zeno (red), as he threw 2, 5 and 6 and was forced to leave eight pieces alone. See &quot;Zeno's Game of τάβλη&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;austin-zeno&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Austin |first=Roland G |title=Zeno's Game of τάβλη |journal=The Journal of Hellenic Studies |volume=54 |issue=2 |year=1934 |pages=202–205 |doi=10.2307/626864 |jstor=626864}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

''[[Tavli|Tάβλη (tavli)]]'' meaning &quot;table&quot; or &quot;board&quot; in [[Byzantine Greek]], is the oldest game with rules known to be nearly identical to backgammon; it is described in an epigram of [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine]] [[Zeno (emperor)|Emperor Zeno]] (AD 476–491).&lt;ref name=&quot;austin-zeno&quot; /&gt; The board was the same with 24 points, 12 on each side. As today, each player had 15 checkers and used cubical dice with sides numbered one to six.&lt;ref name=&quot;austin-zeno&quot; /&gt; The object of the game, to be the first to bear off all of one's checkers, was also the same.&lt;ref name=&quot;austin-zeno&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;austin-roman2&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Austin |first=Roland G. |title=Roman Board Games. II |journal=Greece &amp; Rome |volume=4 |issue=11 |date=February 1935 |pages=76–82 |doi=10.1017/s0017383500003119}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hitting a blot, reentering a piece from the bar, and bearing off, all followed the modern rules. The only differences with modern backgammon were the use of an extra die (three rather than two) and the starting of all pieces off the board (with them entering in the same way that pieces on the bar enter in modern backgammon).&lt;ref name=&quot;bell&quot;&gt;Robert Charles Bell, ''Board and table games from many civilizations'', Courier Dover Publications, 1979, {{ISBN|0-486-23855-5}}, pp. 33–35.&lt;/ref&gt; The name τάβλη is still used for backgammon in Greece, where it is frequently played in town [[plateia]]s and cafes.&lt;ref name=&quot;koukoules&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Koukoules |first=Phaidon |authorlink=Phaidon Koukoules |title=Vyzantinon Vios kai Politismos |year=1948 |volume=1 |pages=200–204 |publisher=Collection de l'institut français d'Athènes}}&lt;/ref&gt; The epigram of Zeno describes a particularly bad dice roll the emperor had for his given position. Zeno, who was white, had a stack of seven checkers, three stacks of two checkers and two ''blots'', checkers that stand alone on a point and are therefore in danger of being put outside the board by an incoming opponent checker. Zeno threw the three dice with which the game was played and obtained 2, 5 and 6. As in backgammon, Zeno could not move to a space occupied by two opponent (black) pieces. The white and black checkers were so distributed on the points that the only way to use all of the three results, as required by the game rules, was to break the three stacks of two checkers into blots, exposing them and ruining the game for Zeno.&lt;ref name=&quot;austin-zeno&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bell&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Roman Game of 12 Lines Board - Aphrodisias.jpg|thumb|upright=1.10|right|Roman [[Ludus duodecim scriptorum]] board from the 2nd century, Aphrodisias]]
The τάβλη of Zeno's time is believed to be a direct descendant of the earlier Roman ''[[Ludus duodecim scriptorum]]'' (&quot;Game of twelve lines&quot;) with that board's middle row of points removed, and only the two outer rows remaining.&lt;ref name=&quot;austin-roman2&quot; /&gt; Ludus duodecim scriptorum used a board with three rows of 12 points each with the 15 checkers being moved in opposing directions by the two players across three rows according to the roll of the three cubical dice.&lt;ref name=&quot;austin-zeno&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;austin-roman2&quot; /&gt; Little specific text about the gameplay of Ludus duodecim scriptorum has survived;&lt;ref name=&quot;austin-roman1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Austin |first=Roland G. |title=Roman Board Games. I |journal=Greece &amp; Rome |volume=4 |issue=10 |date=October 1934 |pages=24–34 |doi=10.1017/s0017383500002941}}&lt;/ref&gt; it may have been related to the older [[Ancient Greek]] dice game Kubeia. The earliest known mention of the game is in Ovid's Ars Amatoria (The Art of Love) (written between 1 BC and 8 AD). In Roman times this game was also known as [[Alea iacta est|alea]], and a likely apocryphal Latin story linked this name, and the game, to a [[Troy|Trojan]] soldier named Alea.&lt;ref&gt;Finkel, Irving L. &quot;Ancient board games in perspective.&quot; British Museum Colloquium. 2007. p. 224&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jacoby, Oswald, and John R. Crawford. ''The backgammon book''. Viking Pr, 1976.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Egypt===
Race board games involving dice have existed for millennia in the [[Near East]] and eastern Mediterranean, including the game [[senet]] of [[Ancient Egypt]]. The ancient Egyptian game senet was excavated, along with illustrations, from Egyptian royal tombs dating to 3500 BC.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Hayes |first=William C.|title=Egyptian Tomb Reliefs of the Old Kingdom |journal=The Metropolitan Museum of Art Bulletin |volume=New Series 4 |issue=7 |date=March 1946 |pages=170–178}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though using a board that is quite different from backgammon, it may be a predecessor.

===Turkey ([[Ottoman Empire]])===
[[File:Tavla oynayan kadınlar, Serik - Women playing backgammon in Turkey.jpg|thumb|upright=1.10|right|Women playing [[tavla]] in southern Turkey]]
Backgammon, which is known as &quot;[[tavla]]&quot;, from [[Byzantine Greek]] [[tabula (game)|τάβλη]],&lt;ref name=&quot;austin-zeno&quot; /&gt; is a very popular game in [[Turkey]], and it is customary to name the dice rolls with their [[Persian language|Persian]] number names, with local spellings: yek (1), dü (2), se (3), cehar (4), penç (5), şeş (6).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=ERGIL|first1=LEYLA YVONNE|title=Top Tavla tips for expats to play like a Turk|url=http://www.dailysabah.com/life/2014/10/11/top-tavla-tips-for-expats-to-play-like-a-turk|website=Daily Sabah|publisher=dailysabah.com|accessdate=1 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The usual Tavla rules are same as in the neighboring Arab countries and Greece, as established over a millennium ago,&lt;ref name=&quot;austin-zeno&quot; /&gt; but there are also many quite different variants. The usual tavla is also known as erkek tavlası meaning boys' or men's tavla. The other variant kız tavlası (i.e. girls' tavla) is a game that depends only on the dice and involves no strategy. Another variant, asker tavlası (meaning soldiers' tavla), has the pieces thrown to the board randomly and the opponents try to flip their pieces over the opponents' pieces to beat them.

===Greece===
Backgammon is popular among [[Greeks]]. It is a game in which Greeks usually tease their opponent and they create a lively atmosphere. The game is called &quot;Tavli&quot;, derived in [[Byzantine]] times from the Latin word &quot;tabula&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;koukoules&quot;/&gt; A game, almost identical to backgammon, called [[Tabula (game)|Tavli]] ([[Byzantine Greek]]: τάβλη) is described in an epigram of the [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine]] [[Zeno (emperor)|Emperor Zeno]] (AD 476–481).&lt;ref name=&quot;austin-zeno&quot; /&gt; There are four games of [[Tavli]] commonly played:

Portes: Set-up and rules the same as backgammon, except that backgammons count as gammons (2 points) and there is no doubling cube.&lt;br&gt;
[[Plakoto]]: A game where one checker can trap another checker on the same point.&lt;br&gt;
Fevga: A game where one checker by itself can block a point.&lt;br&gt;
Asodio: Also known as [[Acey-deucey]] where all checkers are off the board, and you enter by rolling either doubles or acey-deucey.&lt;br&gt;
These games are played one after another, in matches of three, five, or seven points.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite journal |title=backgammon |journal=Internet, Second Edition |url=http://www.bkgm.com/variants/Tavli.html |year=2003 |accessdate=2006-08-05| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20060813073758/http://www.bkgm.com/variants/Tavli.html| archivedate= 13 August 2006 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Before starting a match, each player rolls 1 die, and the player with the highest roll picks up both dice and re-rolls (i.e. it is possible to roll doubles for the opening move). Players use the same pair of dice in turns. After the first game, the winner of the previous game starts first. Each game counts as 1 point, if the opponent has borne off at least 1 stone, otherwise 2 points (gammon/backgammon). There is no doubling cube.

===East Asia===
[[File:Backgammon set,around the 10th century, China.JPG|thumb|upright=1.10|Backgammon set from around the 10th century, China]]
Backgammon was popular in China for a time and was known as &quot;shuanglu&quot; (双陆), with the book [[:zh:譜雙|Pǔ Shuāng (譜雙)]] written during the [[Southern Song]] (1127–1279) period recording over ten variants - but over time it was replaced by other games such as [[xiangqi]] (Chinese chess).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.cctv.com/special/zgctty/20070605/107991.shtml|title=CCTV.com-[博弈篇]舶来棋戏——双陆|website=news.cctv.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Japan ''[[sugoroku|ban-sugoroku]]'' is thought to have been introduced from China in the 6th century and is mentioned in Genji monogatari. As a gambling game it was made illegal several times.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sugoroku.net/history_e/history6.html Origin of Sugoroku in Japan], sugoroku.net&lt;/ref&gt; In the early Edo-era, a new and quick gambling game called ''[[Chō-han]]'' appeared and sugoroku quickly dwindled. By the 13th century, the board game [[Go (game)|Go]], originally played only by the aristocracy, had become popular among the general public.&lt;ref name=HistJapan3&gt;{{Citation|url=http://www.nihonkiin.or.jp/lesson/knowledge-e/history03.htm |publisher=[[Nihon Kiin]] |title=History of Go in Japan: part 3 |accessdate=2007-11-02 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071114231823/http://www.nihonkiin.or.jp/lesson/knowledge-e/history03.htm |archivedate=14 November 2007 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Korea, it is called Ssang-ryuk or Jeopo.

===Western Europe===
[[Image:Codex Manesse 262v Herr Goeli.jpg|thumb|upright=0.85|left|''Herr Goeli'', from the 14th century [[Codex Manesse]]]]
[[Image:Old Backgammon Vasa Edit.jpg|thumb|upright=0.95|right|''[[Brädspel]]'' (&quot;board game&quot;) set recovered from the warship ''[[Vasa (ship)|Vasa]]'', which sank in 1628]]
The ''jeux de tables'' (Games of Tables), predecessors of modern backgammon, first appeared in France during the 11th century and became a favorite pastime of gamblers. In 1254, [[Louis IX of France|Louis IX]] issued a decree prohibiting his court officials and subjects from playing.&lt;ref name=&quot;murray&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;lillich&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Lillich |first=Meredith Parsons |title=The Tric-Trac Window of Le Mans |journal=The Art Bulletin |volume=65 |issue=1 |date=March 1983 |pages=23–33 |doi=10.2307/3050296 |jstor=3050296}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tables games were played in Germany in the 12th century, and had reached [[Iceland]] by the 13th century. In [[Spain]], the [[Alfonso X]] manuscript ''[[Libro de los juegos]]'', completed in 1283, describes rules for a number of dice and table games in addition to its extensive discussion of chess.&lt;ref name=&quot;wollesen&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Wollesen |first=Jens T |title=Sub specie ludi...: Text and Images in Alfonso El Sabio's Libro de Acedrex, Dados e Tablas |journal=Zeitschrift für Kunstgeschichte |volume=53 |issue=3 |year=1990 |pages=277–308 |doi=10.2307/1482540 |jstor=1482540}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the 17th century, table games had spread to [[Sweden]]. A wooden board and checkers were recovered from the wreck of the [[Regalskeppet Vasa|Vasa]] among the belongings of the ship's officers. Backgammon appears widely in paintings of this period, mainly those of Dutch and German painters ([[Adriaen van Ostade|Van Ostade]], [[Jan Steen]], [[Hieronymus Bosch]], [[Pieter Bruegel the Elder|Bruegel]] and others). Some surviving artworks are &quot;[[Cardsharps (Caravaggio)|Cardsharps]]&quot; by [[Caravaggio]] (the backgammon board is in the lower left) and &quot;[[The Triumph of Death]]&quot; by [[Pieter Bruegel the Elder]] (the backgammon board is in the lower right). Others are the Hell of Bosch and interior of an Inn by Jan Steen.

===Great Britain===
[[Image:Hoyle-backgammon.png|thumb|upright=0.95|right|''A Short Treatise on the Game of Back-Gammon'', by Edmond Hoyle]]
In the 16th century, [[Elizabethan]] laws and church regulations prohibited playing tables, but by the 18th century, backgammon was popular among the English clergy.&lt;ref name=&quot;murray&quot;/&gt; [[Edmund Hoyle]] published ''A Short Treatise on the Game of Back-Gammon'' in 1743; this described rules and strategy for the game and was bound together with a similar text on [[whist]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Allee |first=Sheila |url=http://www.utexas.edu/supportut/news_pub/yg_foreedge.html |title=A Foregone Conclusion: Fore-Edge Books Are Unique Additions to Ransom Collection |publisher=The University of Texas at Austin |accessdate=2006-08-08 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060621093338/http://www.utexas.edu/supportut/news_pub/yg_foreedge.html |archive-date=2006-06-21 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In English, the word &quot;backgammon&quot; is most likely derived from &quot;back&quot; and [[Middle English]] &quot;''gamen''&quot;, meaning &quot;game&quot; or &quot;play&quot;. The earliest use documented by the [[Oxford English Dictionary]] was in 1650.&lt;ref name=&quot;oed&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |title=backgammon |journal=The Oxford English Dictionary, Second Edition |url=http://dictionary.oed.com |year=1989 |accessdate=2006-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
The most recent major development in backgammon was the addition of the doubling cube. It was first introduced in the 1920s in [[New York City]] among members of gaming clubs in the [[Lower East Side]].&lt;ref name=&quot;robertie-501&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Robertie |first=Bill |authorlink=Bill Robertie |title=501 Essential Backgammon Problems |edition=Second Printing |year=2002 |page=22 |publisher=Cardoza |isbn=978-1-58042-019-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; The cube required players not only to select the best move in a given position, but also to estimate the probability of winning from that position, transforming backgammon into the [[expected value]]-driven game played in the 20th and 21st centuries.&lt;ref name=&quot;robertie-501&quot;/&gt;

The popularity of backgammon surged in the mid-1960s, in part due to the charisma of [[Prince Alexis Obolensky]] who became known as &quot;The Father of Modern Backgammon&quot;.&lt;ref name=GAM&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gammonlife.com/news/the_inventor_of_doubling_in_backgammon.htm|title=The Inventor of Doubling in Backgammon|website=www.gammonlife.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Obe&quot;, as he was called by friends, co-founded the International Backgammon Association,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gammonvillage.com/backgammon/news/article_display.cfm?resourceid=937|title=The Father Of Modern Backgammon - GammonVillage Magazine|website=www.gammonvillage.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; which published a set of official rules. He also established the World Backgammon Club of Manhattan, devised a backgammon tournament system in 1963, then organized the first major international backgammon tournament in March 1964, which attracted royalty, celebrities and the press. The game became a huge fad and was played on college campuses, in discothèques and at country clubs;&lt;ref name=GAM /&gt; stockbrokers and bankers began playing at conservative men's clubs.&lt;ref name=NYT&gt;{{cite news |author=[[Bernard Weintraub]] |title=Urge to Play Backgammon Sweeping Men's Clubs |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1966/01/13/archives/an-old-old-game-gains-new-favor-urge-to-play-backgammon-sweeping.html?sq=Tim%2520Holland%2520backgammon&amp;scp=14&amp;st=cse |quote=A disk and dice game that has been played in Middle Eastern streets for thousands of years, in English homes for hundreds of years, and on Bronx stoops for dozens of years has suddenly gripped the bankers and brokers of old-line men's clubs all over town. |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=January 13, 1966 |accessdate=2010-09-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt; People young and old all across the country dusted off their boards and checkers. Cigarette, liquor and car companies began to sponsor tournaments and [[Hugh Hefner]] held backgammon parties at the [[Playboy Mansion]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.play65.com/World-Backgammon-Championships-History.html|title=World Backgammon Championships History - Backgammon Masters - Backgammon Articles' Categories - Play65™|website=www.play65.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Backgammon clubs were formed and tournaments were held, resulting in a World Championship promoted in [[Las Vegas, Nevada|Las Vegas]] in 1967.&lt;ref name=PLAY65 /&gt;

Most recently, the United States Backgammon Federation (USBGF) was organized in 2009 to repopularize the game in the United States. Board and committee members include many of the top players, tournament directors and writers in the worldwide backgammon community. The USBGF has recently created a [http://usbgf.org/standards-of-ethical-practice/ Standards of Ethical Practice] to address issues on which tournament rules fail to touch.

==See also==
*[[Backgammon notation]]
*[[:Category:Backgammon players]]
*[[Tables (board game)]]
*[[Tabletop game|Table games]]
*[[TD-Gammon]]

==References==
{{Reflist|35em}}

==External links==
{{Spoken Wikipedia|Backgammon.ogg|2007-12-06|5.2 mega}}
*{{Wiktionary inline|Appendix:Glossary of backgammon terms}}
*{{wikibooks inline|Backgammon}}
*{{Commons category-inline|Backgammon}}
*{{cite EB1911|wstitle=Backgammon |short=x}}

&lt;!-- There are many quality backgammon information and play sites that could be linked here.
Some would add to the value of the article. However, Wikipedia is not a link repository, so
currently what is listed is a link to the Open Directory backgammon category, which lists dozens
of topical sites. Please consider adding your site to the Open Directory category; here it is
only likely to be removed.
--&gt;
*{{curlie|Games/Board_Games/Abstract/Race_Games/Backgammon}}
*[http://ukbgf.com UK Backgammon Federation]
*[http://usbgf.org US Backgammon Federation]
*[http://www.bwcmc.com Backgammon World Championship - Monte Carlo]
{{Tables games}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Backgammon| ]]
[[Category:Tables games]]
[[Category:Traditional board games]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Iranian inventions]]
[[Category:Sports originating in Iran]]</text>
      <sha1>2k02l5f9evsn7opa8aw3d0e9n20tiqm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
