  <page>
    <title>Bodybuilding</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4360</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942429898</id>
      <parentid>942427239</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-24T16:52:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Dating maintenance tags: {{Citation needed}}</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Hatnote|This article is almost exclusively about male-ecentric bodybuilding, for female bodybuilding, see [[Female bodybuilding]].}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2016}}
{{more medical citations needed|date=January 2014}}
{{Infobox sport
| name       = Bodybuilding
| image      = 
| alt        = 
| imagesize  = 
| caption    = 
| union      = [[International Federation of BodyBuilding &amp; Fitness]]
| nickname   = BB
| first      = [[England]]&lt;br /&gt;Late 1800s
| firstlabel = First developed
| region     = Worldwide
| registered = 
| clubs      = 
| contact    = No
| team       = No
| category   = Fitness sports
| mgender    = No
| type       = Indoor
| equipment  = 
| venue      = [[Auditorium]]
| glossary   = 
| olympic    = No
| world      = 
| paralympic = No
| obsolete   = 
| IWGA       = [[1981 World Games|1981]]{{snds}}[[2009 World Games|2009]] 
}}

[[File:Arnold_Schwarzenegger_1974.jpg|thumb|[[Arnold Schwarzenegger]], one of the most notable figures in bodybuilding, in 1974]]
[[File:Falk,_Benjamin_J._(1853-1925)_-_Eugen_Sandow_(1867-1925).jpg|right|thumb|[[Eugen Sandow]], often referred to as the &quot;Father of Modern Bodybuilding&quot;]]

'''Bodybuilding''' is the use of [[Weight training|progressive resistance exercise]] to control and develop one's [[Muscle|musculature]] for aesthetic purposes.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Emery, Michael|url=http://www.bodybuildingreviews.net/Bodybuilding.html|title=Men's Bodybuilding: A Short History|publisher=Bodybuildingreviews.net|accessdate=February 25, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; An individual who engages in this activity is referred to as a '''bodybuilder'''. In competitive bodybuilding, bodybuilders appear in lineups and perform specified poses (and later individual posing routines) for a panel of judges who rank the competitors based on criteria such as symmetry, muscularity, size, conditioning, posing, and stage presentation. Bodybuilders prepare for competitions through the elimination of [[Adipose tissue|nonessential body fat]], enhanced at the last stage by a combination of extracellular [[dehydration]] and [[carbohydrate loading]], to achieve maximum muscular definition and [[vascularity]], as well as [[Sun tanning|tanning]] to accentuate the contrast of the skin under the spotlights. Bodybuilders may use [[anabolic steroid]]s and other performance-enhancing drugs to build muscles.
&lt;!-- IMPORTANT NOTE: Please do not add yourself or other bodybuilders you perceive to be notable. This is an encyclopedia introduction paragraph and is not intended to include a massive dump of everyone who has ever competed or won. Please discuss your additions on the talk page. Random additions of bodybuilders will be removed. --&gt;

The winner of the annual [[International Federation of BodyBuilders|IFBB]] [[Mr. Olympia]] contest is generally recognized as the world's top male [[professional bodybuilding|professional bodybuilder]]. Since 1950, the [[National Amateur Body-Builders' Association|NABBA]] [[Universe Championships]] have been considered the top amateur bodybuilding contests, with notable winners such as [[Reg Park]], [[Lee Priest]], [[Steve Reeves]], and [[Arnold Schwarzenegger]]. Winners generally go on to become professional athletes.

== History==

=== Early history ===
[[File:Sandow_ca1894.ogv|right|thumb|Eugen Sandow in 1894]]

Stone-lifting traditions were practiced in ancient [[Ancient Egypt|Egypt]], [[Ancient Greece|Greece]] and [[Tamilakam]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.thehindu.com/features/magazine/locked-horns-and-a-flurry-of-feathers/article4294435.ece|title=Locked horns and a flurry of feathers|first=D.|last=Karthikeyan|date=January 12, 2013|publisher=|via=www.thehindu.com|newspaper=The Hindu}}&lt;/ref&gt; Western weightlifting developed in Europe from 1880 to 1953, with [[Strongman (strength athlete)|strongmen]] displaying feats of [[Physical strength|strength]] for the public and challenging each other. The focus was not on their physique, and they often had large bellies and fatty limbs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Schwarzenegger, A.|title=The New Encyclopedia of Modern Bodybuilding|year=1999|location=Fireside, NY|isbn=978-0684857213|publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Eugen Sandow ====
Bodybuilding developed in the late 19th century, promoted in England by German [[Eugen Sandow]], now considered as the &quot;Father of Bodybuilding&quot;. He allowed audiences to enjoy viewing his physique in &quot;muscle display performances&quot;. Although audiences were thrilled to see a well-developed physique, the men simply displayed their bodies as part of strength demonstrations or wrestling matches. Sandow had a stage show built around these displays through his manager, [[Florenz Ziegfeld]]. The [[Academy Awards|Oscar]]-winning 1936 [[musical film]] ''[[The Great Ziegfeld]]'' depicts the beginning of modern bodybuilding, when Sandow began to display his body for carnivals.{{Citation needed|date=October 2019}}

Sandow was so successful at flexing and posing his physique that he later created several businesses around his fame, and was among the first to market products branded with his name. He was credited with inventing and selling the first exercise equipment for the masses: machined [[dumbbell]]s, spring [[pulley]]s, and tension bands. Even his image was sold by the thousands in &quot;[[cabinet card]]s&quot; and other prints. Sandow was a perfect &quot;Gracilian&quot;, a standard of [[Golden ratio|ideal body proportion]]s close to those of ancient Greek and [[Ancient Rome|Roman]] statues. Men's physiques were then judged by how closely they matched these proportions.{{Citation needed|date=October 2019}}

====First large-scale bodybuilding competition====
Sandow organized the first bodybuilding contest on September 14, 1901, called the &quot;Great Competition&quot;. It was held at the [[Royal Albert Hall]] in [[London]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Rhodes|first=Jesse|title=Bodybuilders Through the Ages|url=http://www.smithsonianmag.com/history-archaeology/Bodybuilders-Through-the-Ages.html|date=July 19, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Judged by Sandow, Sir Charles Lawes, and [[Arthur Conan Doyle|Sir Arthur Conan Doyle]], the contest was a great success and many bodybuilding enthusiasts were turned away due to the overwhelming amount of audience members. The trophy presented to the winner was a gold statue of Sandow sculpted by Frederick Pomeroy. The winner was William L. Murray of [[Nottingham]]. The silver Sandow trophy was presented to second-place winner D. Cooper. The bronze Sandow trophy — now the most famous of all — was presented to third-place winner A.C. Smythe.{{citation needed|date=February 2020}} In 1950, this same bronze trophy was presented to [[Steve Reeves]] for winning the inaugural [[National Amateur Body-Builders' Association|NABBA]] [[Universe Championships|Mr. Universe]] contest.{{citation needed|date=February 2020}} It would not resurface again until 1977 when the winner of the [[International Federation of BodyBuilders|IFBB]] [[Mr. Olympia]] contest, [[Frank Zane]], was presented with a replica of the bronze trophy. Since then, [[Mr. Olympia]] winners have been consistently awarded a replica of the bronze Sandow.

From December 28, 1903 to January 2, 1904,&lt;ref&gt;''Physical Culture'', vol. 10, no. 6 (December 1903), p. 555.[https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=umn.31951000756772n&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=569]&lt;/ref&gt; the first large-scale bodybuilding competition in America took place at [[Madison Square Garden]] in [[New York City]]. The competition was promoted by [[Bernarr Macfadden]], the father of physical culture and publisher of original bodybuilding [[Magazine|magazines]] such as ''Health &amp; Strength''. The winner was [[Al Treloar]], who was declared &quot;The Most Perfectly Developed Man in the World&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sandowplus.co.uk/Competition/Treloar/treloar.htm|title=Al Treloar at SandowPlus.com|publisher=Sandowplus.co.uk|date=December 28, 1903|accessdate=October 5, 2012|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120629104307/http://www.sandowplus.co.uk/Competition/Treloar/treloar.htm|archivedate=June 29, 2012|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Treloar won a [[US dollar|$]]1,000 cash prize, a substantial sum at that time. Two weeks later, [[Thomas Edison]] made a film of Treloar's posing routine. Edison had also made two films of Sandow a few years before. Those were the first three motion pictures featuring a bodybuilder. In the early 20th century, Macfadden and [[Charles Atlas]] continued to promote bodybuilding across the world.

==== Notable early bodybuilders ====
[[File:Ed_Fury_and_Jackie_Coey,_1953.jpg|left|thumb|Model Jackie Coey with Mr. Los Angeles contestant [[Ed Fury]] in 1953]]

Many other important bodybuilders in the early history of bodybuilding prior to 1930 include: Earle Liederman (writer of some of bodybuilding's earliest books), [[Zishe Breitbart]], [[Georg Hackenschmidt]], Emy Nkemena, George F. Jowett, Finn Hateral (a pioneer in the art of posing), [[Frank Saldo]], [[Monte Saldo]], [[William Bankier]], Launceston Elliot, [[Sig Klein]], Sgt. Alfred Moss, Joe Nordquist, [[Lionel Strongfort]] (&quot;Strongfortism&quot;),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sandowplus.co.uk/Competition/Strongfort/course/lesson1.htm|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080802165327/http://www.sandowplus.co.uk/Competition/Strongfort/course/lesson1.htm|archive-date=August 2, 2008|title=STRONGFORTISM - LESSON ONE}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Gustav Frištenský]], [[Ralph Parcaut]] (a champion wrestler who also authored an early book on &quot;physical culture&quot;), and Alan P. Mead (who became an impressive muscle champion despite the fact that he lost a leg in [[World War I]]). Actor [[Francis X. Bushman]], who was a disciple of Sandow, started his career as a bodybuilder and sculptor's model before beginning his famous [[silent movie]] career.{{Citation needed|date=October 2019}}

=== 1950s{{ndash}}1960s ===
Bodybuilding became more popular in the 1950s and 1960s with the emergence of strength and [[gymnastics]] champions, and the simultaneous popularization of bodybuilding magazines, training principles, nutrition for [[Muscular hypertrophy|bulking up]] and [[Fat loss|cutting down]], the use of [[protein]] and other [[food supplements]], and the opportunity to enter physique contests. The number of bodybuilding organizations grew, and most notably the [[International Federation of Bodybuilders]] (IFBB) was founded in 1946 by Canadian brothers [[Joe Weider|Joe]] and [[Ben Weider]]. Other bodybuilding organizations included the [[Amateur Athletic Union]] (AAU), [[National Amateur Body-Builders' Association|National Amateur Bodybuilding Association]] (NABBA), and the World Bodybuilding Guild (WBBG). Consequently, the contests grew both in number and in size. Besides the many &quot;Mr. XXX&quot; (insert town, city, state, or region) championships, the most prestigious titles{{According to whom|date=February 2017}} were Mr. America, Mr. World, Mr. Universe, Mr. Galaxy, and ultimately Mr. Olympia, which was started in 1965 by the IFBB and is now considered the most important bodybuilding competition in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

During the 1950s, the most successful and most famous competing bodybuilders{{According to whom|date=February 2017}} were [[Bill Pearl]], [[Reg Park]], [[Leroy Colbert]], and [[Clarence Ross]]. Certain bodybuilders rose to fame thanks to the relatively new medium of television, as well as cinema. The most notable{{According to whom|date=February 2017}} were [[Jack LaLanne]], [[Steve Reeves]], Reg Park, and [[Mickey Hargitay]]. While there were well-known gyms throughout the country during the 1950s (such as Vince's Gym in [[North Hollywood, California]] and [[Vic Tanny]]'s chain gyms), there were still segments of the United States that had no &quot;hardcore&quot; bodybuilding gyms until the advent of [[Gold's Gym]] in the mid-1960s.  Finally, the famed [[Muscle Beach]] in [[Santa Monica, California|Santa Monica]] continued its popularity as the place to be for witnessing acrobatic acts, feats of strength, and the like. The movement grew more in the 1960s with increased TV and movie exposure, as bodybuilders were [[Typecasting (acting)|typecast]] in popular shows and movies.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;

===1970s{{ndash}}1990s===
==== New organizations ====
In the 1970s, bodybuilding had major publicity thanks to the appearance of [[Arnold Schwarzenegger]], [[Franco Columbu]], [[Lou Ferrigno]], and others in the 1977 [[docudrama]] ''[[Pumping Iron]]''. By this time, the IFBB dominated the competitive bodybuilding landscape and the [[Amateur Athletic Union]] (AAU) took a back seat. The [[National Physique Committee]] (NPC) was formed in 1981 by [[Jim Manion]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ifbbpro.com/features/jim-manion-chairman-ifbb-professional-league/|title=IFBB Professional League - Jim Manion, Chairman IFBB Professional League|publisher=Ifbbpro.com|date=September 26, 2007|accessdate=October 5, 2012|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120921210350/http://abhivacrossfitarena.com/|archivedate=September 21, 2012|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; who had just stepped down as chairman of the AAU Physique Committee. The NPC has gone on to become the most successful bodybuilding organization in America and is the amateur division of the IFBB. The late 1980s and early 1990s saw the decline of AAU-sponsored bodybuilding contests. In 1999, the AAU voted to discontinue its bodybuilding events.

==== Anabolic/androgenic steroid use ====
[[File:Ronnie_Coleman_8_x_Mr_Olympia_-_2009_-_7.png|right|thumb|[[Ronnie Coleman]], eight-time [[Mr. Olympia]], pictured in October 2009]]

This period also saw the rise of [[anabolic steroid]]s in bodybuilding and many other sports. In bodybuilding lore, this is partly attributed to the rise of &quot;mass monsters&quot;, beginning with [[Arnold Schwarzenegger]], [[Sergio Oliva]], and [[Lou Ferrigno]] in the late 1960s and early 1970s, and continuing through the 1980s with [[Lee Haney]], the 1990s with [[Dorian Yates]], [[Ronnie Coleman]], and [[Markus Rühl]], and up to the present day. Bodybuilders such as [[Greg Kovacs]] attained mass and size never seen previously but were not successful at the pro level. Others were renowned for their spectacular development of a particular body part, like [[Tom Platz]] or [[Paul Demayo]] for their leg muscles. At the time of shooting ''Pumping Iron'', Schwarzenegger (while never admitting to steroid use until long after his retirement) said that &quot;you have to do anything you can to get the advantage in competition&quot;.{{citation needed|date=November 2014}} He would later say that he does not regret using anything.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cbsnews.com/2100-250_162-676684.html|newspaper=CBS|date=February 11, 2009|title=Arnold: No Regrets About Steroids|accessdate=August 13, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

To combat anabolic steroid use and in the hopes of becoming a member of the [[IOC]], the IFBB introduced [[Use of performance-enhancing drugs in sport|doping]] tests for both steroids and other banned substances. Although doping tests occurred, the majority of professional bodybuilders still used anabolic steroids for competition. During the 1970s, the use of anabolic steroids was openly discussed, partly due to the fact they were legal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |last=Theunissen|first=Steve|title=Arnold &amp; Steroids: Truth Revealed|url=http://hjem.get2net.dk/JamesBond/www/artikler/steroidemisbrug/arnoldandsteroids.htm|accessdate=February 27, 2007|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20031008172601/http://hjem.get2net.dk/JamesBond/www/artikler/steroidemisbrug/arnoldandsteroids.htm|archivedate=October 8, 2003|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the Anabolic Steroid Control Act of 1990, [[Congress of the United States|U.S. Congress]] placed anabolic steroids into Schedule III of the [[Controlled Substances Act]] (CSA). In [[Canada]], steroids are listed under Schedule IV of the ''Controlled Drugs and Substances Act'', enacted by the [[Parliament of Canada|federal Parliament]] in 1996.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/C-38.8/|title=Consolidated federal laws of canada, Controlled Drugs and Substances Act|first=Legislative Services|last=Branch|date=September 19, 2019|website=laws-lois.justice.gc.ca}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== World Bodybuilding Federation ====
{{Main|World Bodybuilding Federation}}

In 1990, [[professional wrestling]] promoter [[Vince McMahon]] announced that he was forming a new bodybuilding organization named the [[World Bodybuilding Federation]] (WBF). McMahon wanted to bring [[WWE|WWF]]-style showmanship and bigger prize money to the sport of bodybuilding. A number of IFBB stars were recruited but the roster was never very large and featured the same athletes competing; the most notable winner and first WBF champion was [[Gary Strydom]]. McMahon formally dissolved the WBF in July 1992. Reasons for this reportedly included lack of income from the pay-per-view broadcasts of the contests, slow sales of the WBF's magazine ''Bodybuilding Lifestyles'' (later ''WBF Magazine''), and the expense of paying multiple six-figure contracts while producing two TV shows and a monthly magazine.{{Citation needed|date=October 2019}}

===2000s===
In 2003, [[Joe Weider]] sold Weider Publications to [[American Media (publisher)|AMI]], which owns the ''[[National Enquirer]]''. The position of president of the IFBB was filled by Rafael Santonja following the death of [[Ben Weider]] in October 2008. In 2004, contest promoter Wayne DeMilia broke ranks with the IFBB and AMI took over the promotion of the Mr. Olympia contest.{{Citation needed|date=October 2019}}

In the early 21st century, patterns of [[Consumption (economics)|consumption]] and [[recreation]] similar to those of the United States became more widespread in Europe and especially in Eastern Europe following the collapse of the [[Soviet Union]]. This resulted in the emergence of whole new populations of bodybuilders from former [[Eastern Bloc]] states.{{Citation needed|date=October 2019}}

==== Olympic sport discussion ====
In the early 2000s, the IFBB was attempting to make bodybuilding an [[Olympic Games|Olympic]] sport. It obtained full IOC membership in 2000 and was attempting to get approved as a demonstration event at the Olympics, which would hopefully lead to it being added as a full contest. This did not happen and Olympic recognition for bodybuilding remains controversial since many argue that bodybuilding is not a sport.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |last=Littman|first=Jean|title=Bodybuilding And The Olympics: An Ongoing Controversy|publisher=article99.com|url=http://www.article99.com/recreation-and-sports/olympics/article.php?art=63758|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071205174022/http://www.article99.com/recreation-and-sports/olympics/article.php?art=63758|url-status=dead|archive-date=December 5, 2007|date=November 13, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Areas ==
=== Professional bodybuilding ===
{{Main|Professional bodybuilding}}
[[File:Frank_Zane.jpg|thumb|[[Frank Zane]], three-time Mr. Olympia]]
In the modern bodybuilding industry, the term &quot;[[Professional bodybuilding|professional]]&quot; generally means a bodybuilder who has won qualifying competitions as an amateur and has earned a &quot;pro card&quot; from their respective organization. Professionals earn the right to compete in competitions that include monetary prizes. A pro card also prohibits the athlete from competing in federations other than the one from which they have received the pro card.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ifbb.com/ifbb-faq/ Ifbb Faq – Ifbb]. Ifbb.com (February 22, 1999). Retrieved on 2016-11-29.&lt;/ref&gt; Depending on the level of success, these bodybuilders may receive monetary compensation from sponsors, much like athletes in other sports.

===Natural bodybuilding {{anchor|MuscleMania|UFE|INBF|WNBF|INBA|PNBA|NPC|NANBF}}===
{{Main|Natural bodybuilding}}
Due to the growing concerns of the high cost, health consequences, and illegal nature of some steroids, many organizations have formed in response and have deemed themselves &quot;natural&quot; bodybuilding competitions. In addition to the concerns noted, many promoters of bodybuilding have sought to shed the &quot;freakish&quot; perception that the general public has of bodybuilding and have successfully introduced a more mainstream audience to the sport of bodybuilding by including competitors whose physiques appear much more attainable and realistic.&lt;ref name=&quot;natural&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bodybuilding.com/fun/beginner_natural_bodybuilding_guide.htm|title=Beginner's Guide To Natural Bodybuilding Competition: Disseminating Misconception From Reality!|website=Bodybuilding.com|accessdate=2020-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In natural contests, the testing protocol ranges among organizations from [[Polygraph test|lie detectors]] to [[urinalysis]]. Penalties also range from organization to organization from suspensions to strict bans from competition. It is also important to note that natural organizations also have their own list of banned substances and it is important to refer to each organization's website for more information about which substances are banned from competition. There are many natural bodybuilding organizations; some of the larger ones include: MuscleMania, Ultimate Fitness Events (UFE), INBF/WNBF, and INBA/PNBA. These organizations either have an American or worldwide presence and are not limited to the country in which they are headquartered.&lt;ref name=&quot;natural&quot;/&gt;

=== Men's Physique ===
Due to the number of people who found bodybuilding to be &quot;too big&quot; or &quot;ugly&quot; and unhealthy, a new category was started in 2013. The first MR. Olympia was Mark Wingson, which was followed by Jeremy Buendia for consecutive years. Like bodybuilding, the federations in which you can compete in are all the same, there is natural and regular as well but the main difference between the two is that men's physique pose in board shorts rather than a traditional posing suit. Bodybuilders are much larger than the men physique competitors as well as have an extensive routine when posing while the Physique category only gets judged by the front and back poses. Many of the competitors are not freakishly large and have a bit of a more attainable and aesthetic physique in comparison to bodybuilding. Although this category started off slow, it grew tremendously in the past 5 years, now Men's Physique seems to be the most popular class to be in.{{Citation needed|date=October 2019}}

=== Classic Physique ===
This is the middle ground of both Men's Physique and Bodybuilding. The competitors in this category are not nearly as big as bodybuilders but not as small as mens physique competitors. They pose and perform in mens boxer briefs to show off the legs, unlike Mens Physique which hide the legs in board shorts. Classic physique has only been around for 3 years now as it started in 2016. Danny Hester was the first Classic Physique Mr. Olympia and now Chris Bumstead is the 2019 Mr. Olympia. {{Citation needed|date=October 2019}}

=== Female bodybuilding ===
{{main|Female bodybuilding}}
[[File:Nikki_Fuller.jpg|thumb|Pro female bodybuilder [[Nikki Fuller]] performing a side chest pose]]
The first U.S. Women's National Physique Championship, promoted by Henry McGhee and held in [[Canton, Ohio]] in 1978, is generally regarded as the first true female bodybuilding contest—that is, the first contest where the entrants were judged solely on muscularity.&lt;ref&gt;Todd, Jan, &quot;Bodybuilding&quot;, St. James Encyclopedia of Pop Culture, Gale Group, 1999&lt;/ref&gt; In 1980, the first [[Ms. Olympia]] (initially known as the &quot;Miss&quot; Olympia), the most prestigious contest for professionals, was held. The first winner was [[Rachel McLish]], who had also won the NPC's USA Championship earlier in the year. The contest was a major turning point for female bodybuilding. McLish inspired many future competitors to start training and competing. In 1985, a movie called ''[[Pumping Iron II: The Women]]'' was released. It documented the preparation of several women for the 1983 [[Caesars Palace]] World Cup Championship. Competitors prominently featured in the film were Kris Alexander, Lori Bowen, Lydia Cheng, Carla Dunlap, [[Bev Francis]], and McLish. At the time, Francis was actually a [[Powerlifting|powerlifter]], though she soon made a successful transition to bodybuilding, becoming one of the leading competitors of the late 1980s and early 1990s.

In recent years, the related areas of [[fitness and figure competition]] have increased in popularity, surpassing that of female bodybuilding, and have provided an alternative for women who choose not to develop the level of muscularity necessary for bodybuilding. McLish would closely resemble what is thought of today as a fitness and figure competitor, instead of what is now considered a female bodybuilder. Fitness competitions also have a [[gymnastic]] element to them. A study by the ''[[Clinical Journal of Sport Medicine]]'' found that female bodybuilders who are taking [[anabolic steroid]]s are more likely to have qualified for [[Substance dependence|substance dependence disorder]], to have been diagnosed with a [[psychiatric illness]], or to have a history of [[sexual abuse]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Barnett|first1=Mitchell|title=Women and Anabolic Steroids: An Analysis of a Dozen Users|journal=Clinical Journal of Sport Medicine|date=Nov 2010|volume=20|issue=6|pages=475–81|pmid=21079445|doi=10.1097/JSM.0b013e3181fb5370}}&lt;/ref&gt;

E. Wilma Conner competed in the 2011 NPC Armbrust Pro Gym Warrior Classic Championships in [[Loveland, Colorado]], at the age of 75 years and 349 days.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Guinness World Records 2014|last=Glenday|first=Craig|publisher=The Jim Pattison Group|year=2013|isbn=978-1-908843-15-9|location=|page=[https://archive.org/details/guinnessworldrec0000unse_r3e7/page/60 60]|url=https://archive.org/details/guinnessworldrec0000unse_r3e7/page/60}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Competition ==
[[File:Lukáš_Osladil.jpg|right|thumb|Lukas Osladil posing onstage with a variation of the [[Most Muscular]] pose]]
In competitive bodybuilding, bodybuilders aspire to present an [[Aesthetics|aesthetically]] pleasing body on stage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Top 10 Most Impressive Bodybuilder Physiques of All Time
 | publisher =Muscleprodigy 
 | url = http://www.muscleprodigy.com/top-10-most-impressive-bodybuilder-physiques-of-all-time-arcl-1797.html
 | accessdate = June 14, 2013
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://muscletime.com/news/judging-the-2008-mr-olympia-judges-provide-full-transparency-and-complete-explanation-of-results|title=Judging the 2008 Mr. Olympia: Judges Provide Full Transparency and Complete Explanation of Results|publisher=Muscletime|accessdate=June 14, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In prejudging, competitors do a series of mandatory poses: the front lat spread, rear lat spread, [[wiktionary:front double biceps|front double biceps]], [[wiktionary:back double biceps|back double biceps]], [[wiktionary:side chest|side chest]], [[wiktionary:side triceps|side triceps]], [[Most Muscular]] (men only), [[Abdomen|abdominals]] and [[Thigh|thighs]]. Each competitor also performs a personal choreographed routine to display their physique. A [[posedown]] is usually held at the end of a posing round, while judges are finishing their scoring. Bodybuilders usually spend a lot of time practising their posing in front of mirrors or under the guidance of their coach.

In contrast to [[Strongman (strength athlete)|strongman]] or [[powerlifting]] competitions, where [[physical strength]] is paramount, or to [[Olympic weightlifting]], where the main point is equally split between strength and technique, bodybuilding competitions typically emphasize condition, size, and symmetry. Different organizations emphasize particular aspects of competition, and sometimes have different categories in which to compete.{{Citation needed|date=October 2019}}

=== Preparations ===
==== Bulking and cutting ====
The general strategy adopted by most present-day competitive bodybuilders is to make muscle gains for most of the year (known as the &quot;off-season&quot;) and, approximately 12–14 weeks from competition, lose a maximum of [[Adipose tissue|body fat]] (referred to as &quot;cutting&quot;) while preserving as much muscular mass as possible. The bulking phase entails remaining in a net positive energy balance ([[calorie]] surplus). The amount of a surplus in which a person remains is based on the person's goals, as a bigger surplus and longer bulking phase will create more fat tissue. The surplus of calories relative to one's energy balance will ensure that muscles remain in a state of [[anabolism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.mensjournal.com/food-drink/reverse-dieting-how-go-cut-bulk-without-gaining-fat|work=[[Men's Journal]]|title=Reverse Dieting: How to Go From Cut to Bulk Without Gaining Fat|accessdate=2020-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The cutting phase entails remaining in a net negative energy balance (calorie deficit). The main goal of cutting is to [[Oxidized fats|oxidize]] fat while preserving as much muscle as possible. The larger the calorie deficit, the faster one will lose weight. However, a large calorie deficit will also create the risk of losing muscle tissue.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Lambert|first=Charles|author2=Frank L|author3=Evens W|title=Macronutrient considerations for the sport of bodybuilding.|journal=Sports Med|date=March 2004|volume=34|issue=5|pages=317–27|pmid=15107010|doi=10.2165/00007256-200434050-00004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The bulking and cutting strategy is effective because there is a well-established link between muscle hypertrophy and being in a state of positive energy balance.&lt;ref&gt;the science and development of muscle hypertrophy, Dr. Brad Schoenfeld, page 139-140&lt;/ref&gt; A sustained period of caloric surplus will allow the athlete to gain more fat-free mass than they could otherwise gain under eucaloric conditions. Some gain in fat mass is expected, which athletes seek to oxidize in a cutting period while maintaining as much lean mass as possible.

==== Clean bulking ====
Many non-competitive bodybuilders choose not to adopt this conventional strategy, as it often results in significant unwanted fat gain during the &quot;bulking&quot; phase. The attempt to increase muscle mass in one's body without any gain in fat is called clean bulking. Competitive bodybuilders focus their efforts to achieve a peak appearance during a brief &quot;competition season&quot;.{{Citation needed|date=April 2013}} Clean bulking takes longer and is a more refined approach to achieving the body fat and muscle mass percentage a person is looking for. A common tactic for keeping fat low and muscle mass high would be to have higher calorie and lower calorie days to maintain a balance between gain and loss. Many clean bulk diets start off with a moderate amount of carbs, moderate amount of protein, and a decently low amount of fats. &quot;Gaining lean muscle means going for leaner cuts of meat, like flank steaks and fillets, chicken, and, of course, fish,&quot; says White{{Who|date=January 2019}}. &quot;Enjoy your meat with some starch: rice, beans, quinoa, whole-grain couscous, or sweet potato, for example&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Giblin, Chris. &quot;Clean Bulking: for Frustrated Hard-Gainers, Clean Bulking Is Attainable If You Focus Your Diet Accordingly with the Right Foods and Strategy.&quot; Joe Weider's Muscle &amp; Fitness, vol. 75, no. 8, 2014, p. 89.&lt;/ref&gt; To maintain a clean bulk it is important to reach calorie goals every day. [[Macronutrient]] goals will be different for each person, but, it is ideal to get as close as possible.

====Dirty bulking====
&quot;Dirty bulking&quot; is the process of eating at a massive caloric surplus, without trying to figure out the exact amount of ingested macronutrients (carbs, fats, and proteins). Weightlifters who are attempting to gain mass quickly with no [[Aesthetics|aesthetic]] concerns often choose to use the &quot;dirty bulk&quot; method.&lt;ref&gt;Evans, Rian. (April 6, 2015) [http://www.bodybuilding.com/fun/dirty-bulking-why-you-need-to-know-the-dirty-truth.htm Dirty Bulking: Why You Need To Know The Dirty Truth!]. Bodybuilding.com. Retrieved on 2016-11-29.&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Pre-competition ====
{{Unreferenced section|date=April 2017}}

In the last week leading up to a contest, bodybuilders usually decrease their consumption of [[water]], [[Sodium in biology|sodium]], and [[carbohydrate]]s, the former two to alter how water is retained by the body and the latter to reduce [[glycogen]] in the muscle. The day before the show, water is removed from the diet, and [[diuretic]]s may be introduced, while [[carbohydrate loading]] is undertaken to increase the size of the muscles through replenishment of their glycogen. The goal is to maximize leanness and increase the visibility of veins, or &quot;[[vascularity]]&quot;. The muscular definition and vascularity are further enhanced immediately before appearing on stage by darkening the skin through [[Sunless tanning|tanning products]] and applying [[Vegetable oil|oils]] to the skin to increase shine. Some competitors will eat sugar-rich foods to increase the visibility of their veins. A final step, called &quot;pumping&quot;, consists in performing exercises with light weights or other kinds of low resistance (for instance two athletes can &quot;pump&quot; each other by holding a towel and pulling in turn), just before the contest, to fill the muscles with blood and further increase their size and density.{{Citation needed|date=October 2019}}

== Muscle growth ==
Bodybuilders use three main strategies to maximize [[muscle hypertrophy]]:
* [[Strength training]] through weights or elastic/hydraulic resistance.
* Specialized [[nutrition]], incorporating extra [[protein]] and supplements when necessary.
* Adequate rest, including sleep and recuperation between workouts.

Bodybuilders often shorten these three steps into the well-known motto &quot;eat clean, train hard, sleep well&quot;.

=== Weight training ===
{{Main|Weight training|Strength training}}

Intensive [[weight training]] causes micro-tears to the muscles being trained; this is generally known as [[microtrauma]]. These micro-tears in the muscle contribute to the soreness felt after exercise, called [[delayed onset muscle soreness]] (DOMS). It is the repair of these micro-traumas that results in [[muscle growth]]. Normally, this soreness becomes most apparent a day or two after a workout. However, as muscles become adapted to the exercises, soreness tends to decrease.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid7371625&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|title=Effects of strength training and immobilization on human muscle fibres|year=1980|vauthors=MacDougall JD, Elder GC, Sale DG, Moroz JR, Sutton JR|journal=European Journal of Applied Physiology and Occupational Physiology|volume=43|issue=1|pages=25–34|pmid=7371625|doi=10.1007/BF00421352}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Weight training aims to build muscle by prompting two different types of [[Muscle hypertrophy|hypertrophy]]: sarcoplasmic and myofibrillar. Sarcoplasmic hypertrophy leads to larger muscles and so is favored by bodybuilders more than myofibrillar hypertrophy, which builds athletic strength. Sarcoplasmic hypertrophy is triggered by increasing repetitions, whereas myofibrillar hypertrophy is triggered by lifting heavier weight.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Weight Training Intensity or Volume for Bigger Muscles?|url=http://www.motleyhealth.com/strength/weight-training-intensity-or-volume-for-bigger-muscles|accessdate=February 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In either case, there is an increase in both size and strength of the muscles (compared to what happens if that same individual does not lift weights at all), however, the emphasis is different.{{Citation needed|date=October 2019}}

Many trainees like to cycle between the two methods in order to prevent the body from adapting (maintaining a progressive overload), possibly emphasizing whichever method more suits their goals; typically, a bodybuilder will aim at sarcoplasmic hypertrophy most of the time but may change to a myofibrillar hypertrophy kind of training temporarily in order to move past a plateau. However, no real evidence has been provided to show that trainees ever reach this plateau, and rather was more of a hype created from &quot;muscular confusion&quot;.{{Clarify|date=January 2019}}{{Citation needed|date=January 2019}}

=== Nutrition ===
The high levels of muscle growth and repair achieved by bodybuilders require a specialized diet. Generally speaking, bodybuilders require more [[Food energy|calories]] than the average person of the same weight to provide the protein and energy requirements needed to support their training and increase muscle mass. In preparation of a contest, a sub-maintenance level of food energy is combined with [[cardiovascular exercise]] to lose [[body fat]]. Proteins, carbohydrates and fats are the three major macronutrients that the human body needs in order to build muscle.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Major Nutrients in Food|url=http://www.webmd.com/a-to-z-guides/major-nutrients-in-food-topic-overview|publisher=webMd|accessdate=August 27, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ratios of calories from carbohydrates, proteins, and fats vary depending on the goals of the bodybuilder.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Manoreem MM, Thompson J, Russo M|title=Diet and exercise strategies of a world-class bodybuilder|journal=Int J Sport Nutr.|volume=3|issue=1|pages=76–86|date=March 1993|doi=10.1123/ijsn.3.1.76|pmid=8499940|accessdate=|url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/15139f1395bff0699b645bd96461b0e129a3e8d3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Carbohydrates ====
[[Carbohydrate]]s play an important role for bodybuilders. They give the body energy to deal with the rigors of training and recovery. Carbohydrates also promote secretion of [[insulin]], a hormone enabling cells to get the glucose they need. Insulin also carries amino acids into cells and promotes [[protein synthesis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Skinner|first=Rob|title=Coach &amp; Athletic Director|date=March 2002|volume=71|issue=8|page=3}}&lt;!--|accessdate=November 5, 2012--&gt;{{fcn|date=January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; Insulin has steroid-like effects in terms of muscle gains.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Dimitriadis|first=George|last2=Mitrou|first2=Panayota|last3=Lambadiari|first3=Vaia|last4=Maratou|first4=Eirini|last5=Raptis|first5=Sotirios A.|date=August 2011|title=Insulin effects in muscle and adipose tissue|journal=Diabetes Research and Clinical Practice|volume=93|issue=Suppl 1|pages=S52–59|doi=10.1016/S0168-8227(11)70014-6|issn=1872-8227|pmid=21864752}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is impossible to promote protein synthesis without the existence of insulin, which means that without ingesting carbohydrates or protein—which also induces the release of insulin—it is impossible to add muscle mass.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1007/s00424-007-0368-2|pmid=17957382|title=Effects of contraction and insulin on protein synthesis, AMP-activated protein kinase and phosphorylation state of translation factors in rat skeletal muscle|journal=Pflügers Archiv|volume=455|issue=6|pages=1129–40|year=2007|last1=Miranda|first1=Lisa|last2=Horman|first2=Sandrine|last3=De Potter|first3=Isabelle|last4=Hue|first4=Louis|last5=Jensen|first5=Jørgen|last6=Rider|first6=Mark H.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bodybuilders seek out [[Glycemic index|low-glycemic]] [[polysaccharide]]s and other slowly digesting carbohydrates, which release energy in a more stable fashion than high-glycemic sugars and starches. This is important as high-glycemic carbohydrates cause a sharp insulin response, which places the body in a state where it is likely to store additional food energy as fat. However, bodybuilders frequently do ingest some quickly digesting sugars (often in form of pure [[Glucose|dextrose]] or [[maltodextrin]]) just before, during, and/or just after a workout. This may help to replenish [[glycogen]] stored within the muscle, and to stimulate muscle protein synthesis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=King|first=Michael W.|title=Substrates for Gluconeogenesis|website=|publisher=IU School of Medicine|url=http://web.indstate.edu/thcme/mwking/gluconeogenesis.html|doi=|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Protein ====
[[File:Protein_shake.jpg|thumb|Protein milkshakes, made from protein powder (center) and milk (left), are a common [[bodybuilding supplement]].]]
The motor proteins [[actin]] and [[myosin]] generate the forces exerted by contracting [[muscle]]s. Current recommendations suggest that bodybuilders should consume 25–30% of protein per total [[calorie]] intake to further their goal of maintaining and improving their body composition.&lt;ref name=&quot;LambertCP&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |pmid=15107010|volume=34|issue=5|title=Macronutrient considerations for the sport of bodybuilding|year=2004|journal=Sports Med|pages=317–27|vauthors=Lambert CP, Frank LL, Evans WJ|doi=10.2165/00007256-200434050-00004}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is a widely debated topic, with many arguing that 1&amp;nbsp;gram of protein per pound of body weight per day is ideal, some suggesting that less is sufficient, while others recommending 1.5, 2, or more.&lt;ref&gt;Heller, Samantha (April 2004) [https://web.archive.org/web/20130703013711/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-114819458.html Protein: a guide to maximum muscle: confused? Let us separate the gristle from the meat], ''Men's Fitness'',&lt;/ref&gt; It is believed that protein needs to be consumed frequently throughout the day, especially during/after a workout, and before sleep.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Your nutrition problems solved; This month: pre- and postworkout nutrition, calculating protein intake and adding simple carbs&quot;.
''FLEX Magazine'', January 2005&lt;/ref&gt; There is also some debate concerning the best type of protein to take. Chicken, turkey, beef, pork, fish, eggs and dairy foods are high in protein, as are some nuts, seeds, beans, and lentils. [[Casein]] or [[Whey protein|whey]] are often used to supplement the diet with additional protein. Whey protein is the type of protein contained in many popular brands of protein supplements and is preferred by many bodybuilders because of its high [[Biological Value]] (BV) and quick absorption rates. [[Whey protein]] also has a bigger effect than casein on insulin levels, triggering about double the amount of insulin release.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1017/S0007114511006271|pmid=22289570|title=Greater stimulation of myofibrillar protein synthesis with ingestion of whey protein isolate v. Micellar casein at rest and after resistance exercise in elderly men|journal=British Journal of Nutrition|volume=108|issue=6|pages=958–62|year=2012|last1=Burd|first1=Nicholas A.|last2=Yang|first2=Yifan|last3=Moore|first3=Daniel R.|last4=Tang|first4=Jason E.|last5=Tarnopolsky|first5=Mark A.|last6=Phillips|first6=Stuart M.}}&lt;/ref&gt; That effect is somewhat overcome by combining [[casein]] and [[Whey protein|whey]]. Bodybuilders are usually thought to require protein with a higher BV than that of [[soy]], which is additionally avoided due to its claimed [[estrogenic]] properties. Still, some nutrition experts believe that soy, [[flax seeds]] and many other plants that contain the weak estrogen-like compounds or [[Phytoestrogens|phytoestrogen]]s, can be used beneficially, as phytoestrogens compete with estrogens for receptor sites in the male body and can block its actions. This can also include some inhibition of [[pituitary]] functions while stimulating the P450 system (the system that eliminates hormones, drugs and metabolic waste product from the body) in the liver to more actively process and excrete excess estrogen.&lt;ref name=&quot;MikeFalcon&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Falcon|first=Mike|url=http://www.maxmuscle.com/index.cfm?fa=article&amp;doc_id=116&amp;subcat=science|title=Estrogens, Testosterone &amp; Phytoestrogens|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061025023850/http://www.maxmuscle.com/index.cfm?fa=article&amp;doc_id=116&amp;subcat=science|archive-date=October 25, 2006|website=maxmuscle.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TestosteroneSyndrome&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Eugene Shippen|author2=William Fryer|title=The testosterone syndrome: the critical factor for energy, health, and sexuality: reversing the male menopause|publisher=M. Evans|location=New York|year=1998|isbn=978-0-87131-829-9|doi=|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/testosteronesynd00euge}}{{page needed|date=May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cortisol]] decreases amino acid uptake by muscle, and inhibits protein synthesis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first1=K. L.|last1=Manchester|chapter=Sites of Hormonal Regulation of Protein Metabolism|chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=EgMwXpQRGQ8C&amp;pg=PA229|pages=229–98|editor1-first=H. N.|editor1-last=Munro|year=2012|title=Mammalian Protein Metabolism, Volume 4|isbn=978-0-323-14257-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Contrary to certain rumors that animal-based protein is more suitable to trigger muscle growth than plant-based protein, a study by Mangano et al. (2017) could not provide any evidence for this. In contrast, if combined properly, plant-based protein can even have a higher biological quality. A combination of one part wheat protein (e.g. [[seitan]]) and two parts soy protein (e.g. [[tofu]]) has thus been favored by many bodybuilders. Some bodybuilders, such as [[Patrik Baboumian]] and [[Robert Cheeke]], follow a strict [[Veganism|vegan]] diet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://ajcn.nutrition.org/content/early/2017/02/07/ajcn.116.136762|title=Dietary protein is associated with musculoskeletal health independently of dietary pattern: the Framingham Third Generation Study|first1=Kelsey M.|last1=Mangano|first2=Shivani|last2=Sahni|first3=Douglas P.|last3=Kiel|first4=Katherine L.|last4=Tucker|first5=Alyssa B.|last5=Dufour|first6=Marian T.|last6=Hannan|date=February 8, 2017|journal=The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition|pages=714–722|via=ajcn.nutrition.org|doi=10.3945/ajcn.116.136762|pmid=28179224|volume=105|issue=3|pmc=5320406}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Meals ====
Some bodybuilders often split their food intake into 5 to 7 meals of equal nutritional content and eat at regular intervals (e.g. every 2 to 3 hours). This approach serves two purposes: to limit overindulging in the cutting phase, and to allow for the consumption of large volumes of food during the bulking phase. Eating more frequently does not increase [[Metabolic rate|basal metabolic rate]] when compared to 3 meals a day.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Verboeket-van de Venne|first=W. P.|last2=Westerterp|first2=K. R.|last3=Kester|first3=A. D.|date=July 1993|title=Effect of the pattern of food intake on human energy metabolism|journal=The British Journal of Nutrition|volume=70|issue=1|pages=103–115|issn=0007-1145|pmid=8399092|doi=10.1079/BJN19930108}}&lt;/ref&gt; While food does have a metabolic cost to digest, absorb, and store, called the [[thermic effect of food]], it depends on the quantity and type of food, not how the food is spread across the meals of the day. Well-controlled studies using whole-body calorimetry and [[doubly labeled water]] have demonstrated that there is no metabolic advantage to eating more frequently.&lt;ref name=&quot;BellisleF&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Bellisle F, McDevitt R, Prentice AM|title=Meal frequency and energy balance|journal=Br. J. Nutr.|volume=77|issue=Suppl 1|pages=S57–70|year=1997|pmid=9155494|doi=10.1079/BJN19970104}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TaylorMA&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Taylor MA, Garrow JS|title=Compared with nibbling, neither gorging nor a morning fast affect short-term energy balance in obese patients in a chamber calorimeter|journal=Int. J. Obes. Relat. Metab. Disord.|volume=25|issue=4|pages=519–28|year=2001|pmid=11319656|doi=10.1038/sj.ijo.0801572}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid18053311&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Smeets AJ, Westerterp-Plantenga MS|title=Acute effects on metabolism and appetite profile of one meal difference in the lower range of meal frequency|journal=Br. J. Nutr.|volume=99|issue=6|pages=1316–21|date=June 2008|pmid=18053311|doi=10.1017/S0007114507877646|url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Dietary supplements ====
{{Main|Bodybuilding supplement}}
The important role of nutrition in building muscle and losing fat means bodybuilders may consume a wide variety of [[dietary supplements]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Philen RM, Ortiz DI, Auerbach SB, Falk H|title=Survey of advertising for nutritional supplements in health and bodybuilding magazines|journal=JAMA|year=1992|pages=1008–11|volume=268|issue=8|pmid=1501305|doi=10.1001/jama.268.8.1008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Various products are used in an attempt to augment muscle size, increase the rate of fat loss, improve joint health, increase natural testosterone production, enhance training performance and prevent potential nutrient deficiencies.

=== Performance-enhancing substances ===
Some bodybuilders use drugs such as [[anabolic steroid]]s and precursor substances such as [[prohormone]]s to increase [[muscle hypertrophy]]. Anabolic steroids cause [[hypertrophy]] of both types (I and II) of muscle fibers, likely caused by an increased synthesis of muscle proteins. They also provoke undesired side effects including [[hepatotoxicity]], [[gynecomastia]], [[acne]], the early onset of [[male pattern baldness]] and a decline in the body's own testosterone production, which can cause [[testicular atrophy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Schroeder E, Vallejo A, Zheng L|title=Six-week improvements in muscle mass and strength during androgen therapy in older men|journal=J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci|volume=60|issue=12|pages=1586–92|year=2005|pmid=16424293|doi=10.1093/gerona/60.12.1586|display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Grunfeld C, Kotler D, Dobs A, Glesby M, Bhasin S|title=Oxandrolone in the treatment of HIV-associated weight loss in men: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study|journal=J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr|volume=41|issue=3|pages=304–14|year=2006|pmid=16540931|doi=10.1097/01.qai.0000197546.56131.40}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Giorgi A, Weatherby R, Murphy P|title=Muscular strength, body composition and health responses to the use of testosterone enanthate: a double blind study|journal=Journal of Science and Medicine in Sport / Sports Medicine Australia|volume=2|issue=4|pages=341–55|year=1999|pmid=10710012|doi=10.1016/S1440-2440(99)80007-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other performance-enhancing substances used by competitive bodybuilders include [[Growth hormone treatment|human growth hormone]] (HGH).

Muscle growth is more difficult to achieve in older adults than younger adults because of [[biological aging]], which leads to many metabolic changes detrimental to muscle growth; for instance, by diminishing growth hormone and [[testosterone]] levels. Some recent clinical studies have shown that low-dose HGH treatment for adults with HGH deficiency changes the body composition by increasing muscle mass, decreasing fat mass, increasing [[bone density]] and muscle strength, improves [[cardiovascular]] parameters, and affects the quality of life without significant side effects.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Alexopoulou O, Abs R, Maiter D|title=Treatment of adult growth hormone deficiency: who, why and how? A review|journal=Acta Clinica Belgica|volume=65|issue=1|pages=13–22|year=2010|pmid=20373593|doi=10.1179/acb.2010.002}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Ahmad AM, Hopkins MT, Thomas J, Ibrahim H, Fraser WD, Vora JP|title=Body composition and quality of life in adults with growth hormone deficiency; effects of low-dose growth hormone replacement|journal=Clinical Endocrinology|volume=54|issue=6|pages=709–17|date=June 2001|pmid=11422104|doi=10.1046/j.1365-2265.2001.01275.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{medrs|date=January 2014}}&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid10971102&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Savine R, Sönksen P|title=Growth hormone – hormone replacement for the somatopause?|journal=Hormone Research|volume=53|issue=Suppl 3|pages=37–41|year=2000|pmid=10971102|doi=10.1159/000023531}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Injecting oil into muscles {{anchor|synthol}} ====

A recent trend in bodybuilding is to inject [[Synthol (bodybuilding)|synthol]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |pmid=19580174|url=http://www.polimery.umed.wroc.pl/en/article/2009/39/1/63/|year=2009|last1=Pupka|first1=Artur|title=Stosowanie Syntholu w kulturystyce|trans-title=The usage of the Synthol in the body building|language=Polish|journal=Polimery W Medycynie|volume=39|issue=1|pages=63–5|last2=Sikora|first2=Julita|last3=Mauricz|first3=Jakub|last4=Cios|first4=Dariusz|last5=Płonek|first5=Tomasz}}&lt;/ref&gt; into muscles to create larger bulges, or injecting [[Poly(methyl methacrylate)|PMMA]] into muscles to shape them. Use of PMMA to shape muscles is prohibited in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;http://internationalsurgery.com/pmma-injections-and-bodybuilding/ Retrieved June 22, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;

Site enhancement oil, often called ''santol'' or ''synthol'' (no relation to the [[Synthol (mouthwash)|Synthol]] mouthwash brand), refers to oils injected into muscles to increase the size or change the shape. Some bodybuilders, particularly at the professional level, inject their muscles with such mixtures to mimic the appearance of developed muscle where it may otherwise be disproportionate or lacking.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Jason|first1=P|title=Synthol Abuse in Bodybuilding|url=http://proteinfart.com/64-of-the-grossest-synthol-freaks-you-never-wanted-to-see/|website=ProteinFart.com|date=March 31, 2015|url-status=usurped|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160120003847/http://proteinfart.com/64-of-the-grossest-synthol-freaks-you-never-wanted-to-see/|archivedate=January 20, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is known as &quot;fluffing&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;synthol&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://abcnews.go.com/Health/Fitness/story?id=3179969&amp;page=1|title=Like Implants for the Arms: Synthol Lures Bodybuilders: Risky Injections Mean Massive Muscles for Users|last=Childs|first=Dan|date=May 16, 2007|work=ABC News|accessdate=March 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Synthol is 85% oil, 7.5% [[lidocaine]], and 7.5% alcohol.&lt;ref name=&quot;synthol&quot; /&gt; It is not restricted, and many brands are available on the Internet.&lt;ref name=&quot;popeye&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/uk/health/article1782095.ece|title=Bodybuilders puff up with 'Popeye the Sailorman' oil jab|last=Foggo|first=Daniel|date=May 13, 2007|work=Sunday Times|accessdate=March 4, 2011|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110524043824/http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/uk/health/article1782095.ece|archive-date=May 24, 2011|url-status=dead|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; The use of injected oil to enhance muscle appearance is common among bodybuilders,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Paraffin oil injection in bodybuilders calls for preventive action |last=Henriksen|first=TF|author2=Løvenwald JB|author3=Matzen SH|year=2010|journal=Ugeskrift for Lægerer|volume=172|issue=3|pmid=20089216|language=Danish|pages=219–20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;adv&quot; /&gt; despite the fact that synthol can cause [[pulmonary embolism]]s, nerve damage, infections, [[sclerosing lipogranuloma]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Schaefer|first1=N|title=Muscle enhancement using intramuscular injections of oil in bodybuilding: review on epidemiology, complications, clinical evaluation and treatment|doi=10.1007/s10353-011-0033-z|volume=44|issue=2|journal=European Surgery|pages=109–115|year=2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; stroke,&lt;ref name=&quot;synthol&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Pupka|first=A|author2=Sikora J|author3=Mauricz J|author4=Cios D|author5=Płonek T.|year=2009|title=The usage of synthol in the body building|journal=Polim Med.|volume=39|issue=1|pages=63–5|pmid=19580174|language=Polish}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the formation of oil-filled [[granuloma]]s, [[cyst]]s or ulcers in the muscle.&lt;ref name=&quot;adv&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Iversen|first=Line|author2=Asja Lemcke|author3=Mikael Bitsch|author4=Tonny Karlsmark|year=2008|title=Compression Bandage as Treatment for Ulcers Induced by Intramuscular Self-injection of Paraffin Oil|journal=Acta Derm Venereol|volume=89|issue=2|pages=196–7|doi=10.2340/00015555-0583|pmid=19326015|doi-broken-date=2020-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Darsow|first=Ulf|author2=Harald Bruckbauer|author3=Wolf-Ingo Worret|author4=Heidelore Hofmann|author5=Johannes Ring|year=2000|title=Subcutaneous oleomas induced by self-injection of sesame seed oil for muscle augmentation|journal=Journal of the American Academy of Dermatology|volume=42|issue=2|pages=292–294|doi=10.1016/S0190-9622(00)90144-0|pmid=10642691}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Schäfer|first=C.N.|author2=H. Guldager|author3=H. L. Jørgensen|year=2011|title=Multi-Organ Dysfunction in Bodybuilding Possibly Caused by Prolonged Hypercalcemia due to Multi-Substance Abuse: Case Report and Review of Literature|journal=Int J Sports Med|volume=32|issue=1|pmid=21072745|pages=60–65|doi=10.1055/s-0030-1267200}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rare cases might require surgical intervention to avoid further damage to the muscle and/or to prevent loss of life.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Grenoble|first=Ryan|title=Guy Who Wanted To Be A Real-Life Hulk Almost Had To Have Arms Amputated|work=Huffington Post|accessdate=2017-12-01|date=2015-05-05|url=https://www.huffingtonpost.com/2015/05/05/real-life-hulk-arms-amputated-synthol_n_7214190.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Sesame oil]] is often used in such mixtures, which can cause allergic reactions such as [[vasculitis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Koopman|first=M|author2=C. Richter|author3=R. J. M. Parren|author4=M. Janssen|year=2005|title=Bodybuilding, sesame oil and vasculitis|journal=Rheumatology|volume=44|issue=9|page=1135|pmid=16113147|doi=10.1093/rheumatology/keh712}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As the injected muscle is not actually well-developed, it might droop under gravity.&lt;ref name=&quot;popeye&quot; /&gt;

=== Rest ===
Although muscle ''stimulation'' occurs in the [[gym]] (or home gym) when lifting weights, muscle ''growth'' occurs afterward during rest periods. Without adequate rest and sleep (6 to 8 hours), muscles do not have an opportunity to recover and grow.{{Citation needed|date=December 2018}} Additionally, many athletes find that a daytime nap further increases their body's ability to recover from training and build muscles. Some bodybuilders add a [[massage]] at the end of each workout to their routine as a method of recovering.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Shusterman|first1=Richard|title=Thinking Through the Body: Essays in Somaesthetics|date=2012|page=43|publisher=Cambridge University|isbn=978-1107019065}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Overtraining ===
{{Main|Overtraining}}
Overtraining occurs when a bodybuilder has trained to the point where their workload exceeds their recovery capacity. There are many reasons why overtraining occurs, including lack of adequate nutrition, lack of recovery time between workouts, insufficient sleep, and training at a high intensity for too long (a lack of splitting apart workouts). Training at a high intensity too frequently also stimulates the [[central nervous system]] (CNS) and can result in a hyperadrenergic state that interferes with sleep patterns.&lt;ref name=&quot;LonnieLowery_Overtraining&quot;&gt;Lowery, Lonnie. [https://web.archive.org/web/20070927191307/http://www.t-nation.com/readTopic.do?id=459318 Testosterone Nation – The Warrior Nerd: Overtraining or Under-eating?] Part 1&lt;/ref&gt; To avoid overtraining, intense frequent training must be met with at least an equal amount of purposeful recovery. Timely provision of [[carbohydrate]]s, [[Protein (nutrient)|protein]]s, and various micronutrients such as [[vitamin]]s, [[Dietary mineral|minerals]], phytochemicals, even nutritional supplements are acutely critical. A mental disorder, informally called “bigorexia” (by analogy with [[anorexia]]), may account for overtraining in some individuals. Sufferers feel as if they are never big enough or muscular enough, which forces them to overtrain in order to try to reach their goal physique.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Mosley|first=Philip E.|date=2009-05-01|title=Bigorexia: bodybuilding and muscle dysmorphia|journal=European Eating Disorders Review|volume=17|issue=3|pages=191–198|doi=10.1002/erv.897|pmid=18759381|issn=1099-0968}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An article by ''[[Muscle &amp; Fitness]]'' magazine, &quot;Overtrain for Big Gains&quot;, claimed that overtraining for a brief period can be beneficial. Overtraining can be used advantageously, as when a bodybuilder is purposely overtrained for a brief period of time to super compensate during a regeneration phase. These are known as &quot;shock micro-cycles&quot; and were a key training technique used by Soviet athletes.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid14719980&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|pmid=14719980 |year=2003 |title=A framework for understanding the training process leading to elite performance |journal=Sports Medicine |volume=33 |issue=15 |pages=1103–26 |author=Smith DJ|doi=10.2165/00007256-200333150-00003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{collist|colwidth=18em|
* [[Athletic training]]
* [[Beefcake]]
* [[Body image]]
* [[Bodybuilding supplement]]
* [[Exercise equipment]]
* [[Exercise physiology]]
* [[Female bodybuilding]]
* [[Health club]]
* [[Muscle dysmorphia]]
* [[Physical culture]]
* [[Physical exercise]]
* [[Physical fitness]]
* [[Sports medicine]]
* [[Sports nutrition]]
}}

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
{{Wiktionary category|type=used in bodybuilding|category=Bodybuilding}}
{{wikibooks}}
{{Commons category|Bodybuilding}}
&lt;!--     {{No more links}}

       Please be cautious about adding more external links.

Wikipedia is not a collection of links and should not be used for advertising.

     Excessive or inappropriate links will be removed.

 See [[Wikipedia:External links]] and [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.

If there are already suitable links, propose additions or replacements on
the article's talk page, or submit your link to the relevant category at
the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org) and link there using {{Dmoz}}.
--&gt;

{{Sports of the World Games program}}
{{Strength training exercises}}
{{Strength Sports}}

[[Category:Bodybuilding| ]]
[[Category:Body modification]]
[[Category:Athletic sports]]
[[Category:Individual sports]]
[[Category:Weight training]]
[[Category:Body shape]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]</text>
      <sha1>nuu9oc2u3gs95vq4hk7xj9jvll7haod</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
