  <page>
    <title>Book of Esther</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4382</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943291053</id>
      <parentid>942437174</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T01:22:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>KolbertBot</username>
        <id>31691822</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[User:KolbertBot#Tasks|Task #2]] : Remove link referral data</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About||the 2013 film|The Book of Esther (film)}}
{{short description|Book of the Hebrew Bible and the Christian Old Testament}}
[[File:Book of Esther IMG 1826.JPG|thumb|A 13th/14th-century [[scroll]] of the Book of Esther from [[Fez]], [[Morocco]], held at the [[Musée du quai Branly]] in [[Paris]]. Traditionally, a scroll of ''Esther'' is given only one roller, fixed to its lefthand side, rather than the customary two.&lt;ref name=&quot;RosselTorah212&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Rossel |first=Seymour |authorlink= Seymour Rossel |title=The Torah: Portion by Portion |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=AzZlANCOIRgC&amp;pg=PA212 |access-date=13 October 2013 |year=2007 |publisher=Torah Aura Productions |location= Los Angeles |isbn= 978-1-891662-94-2 |page=212}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
{{Tanakh OT|Ketuvim|historical}}

The '''Book of Esther''', also known in [[Hebrew]] as &quot;the Scroll&quot; (''Megillah''), is a book in the third section (''[[Ketuvim]]'', &quot;Writings&quot;) of the [[Judaism|Jewish]] ''[[Tanakh]]'' (the [[Hebrew Bible]]) and in the Christian [[Old Testament]]. It is one of the five Scrolls (''Megillot'') in the Hebrew Bible.  It relates the story of a [[Israelites|Hebrew]] woman in [[Achaemenid Empire|Persia]], born as Hadassah but known as [[Esther]], who becomes queen of Persia and thwarts a [[genocide]] of her people. The story forms the core of the [[Jewish festival]] of [[Purim]], during which it is read aloud twice: once in the evening and again the following morning. The books of Esther and [[Song of Songs]] are the only books in the Hebrew Bible that do not mention [[God in Judaism|God]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url= http://www.js.emory.edu/BLUMENTHAL/EstherSong.html |title=Where God is Not: The Book of Esther and Song of Songs | first = David R. | last = Blumenthal |access-date= April 19, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Setting and structure ==

=== Setting ===
The biblical Book of Esther is set in the Persian [[Capital city|capital]] of [[Susa]] (''Shushan'') in the third year of the reign of the [[King of Persia|Persian king]] [[Ahasuerus#Book of Esther|Ahasuerus]]. The name ''Ahasuerus'' is equivalent to ''Xerxes''&lt;ref name=&quot;Baumgarten&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|last1= Baumgarten |first1= Albert I. |last2=Sperling |first2=S. David |last3= Sabar |first3=Shalom
|editor1-last= Skolnik |editor1-first=Fred |editor2-last=Berenbaum |editor2-first=Michael
|title= Encyclopaedia Judaica |edition=2nd|volume=18
|location= Farmington Hills, MI |publisher=Macmillan Reference USA|year= 2007 |page= 216}}&lt;/ref&gt; (both deriving from the [[Old Persian|Persian]] ''Khshayārsha''),&lt;ref name=&quot;larkin&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first= Katrina J.A. |last=Larkin |title=Ruth and Esther (Old Testament Guides) |location= Sheffield, UK|publisher= Sheffield Academic Press |year= 1996|page= 71}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Ahasuerus is usually identified in modern sources as [[Xerxes I]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first= Sidnie White |last= Crawford |chapter= Esther |editor-first=Carol A.
|editor-last=Newsom |editor-first2=Sharon H. |editor-last2=Ringe |title= Women's Bible Commentary| location= Louisville|publisher=Westminster John Knox |year=1998|page=202}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Between&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=Jill |last= Middlemas |editor-first=Bob E.J.H. |editor-last= Becking |editor-first2=Lester |editor-last2=Grabbe |title= Between Evidence and Ideology | location=Leiden|publisher= Brill |year=2010|page=145 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=DF7RzZJXM-UC&amp;pg=PA145|isbn= 978-9004187375 }}&lt;/ref&gt; who ruled between 486 and 465 BC,&lt;ref name= &quot;Baumgarten&quot; /&gt; as it is to this monarch that the events described in Esther are thought to fit the most closely.&lt;ref name=&quot;larkin&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first= Carey A. |last=Moore |title= Esther (Anchor Bible) |location= Garden City, NY |publisher= Doubleday|year= 1971 |page= XXXV}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Assuming that Ahasuerus is indeed Xerxes I, the events described in Esther began around the years 483–82 BC, and concluded in March 473 BC.

Classical sources such as [[Josephus]], the Jewish commentary ''[[Esther Rabbah]]'' and the [[Christian theologian]] [[Bar-Hebraeus]],&lt;ref name=&quot;budge&quot;&gt;E.A.W. Budge, ''The Chronography of Bar Hebraeus'', Gorgias Press, reprint 2003&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the [[Koine Greek|Greek]] [[Septuagint]] translation of Esther, instead identify Ahasuerus as either [[Artaxerxes I]] (reigned 465 to 424 BC) or [[Artaxerxes II of Persia|Artaxerxes II]] (reigned 404 to 358 BC).&lt;ref name=&quot;budge&quot; /&gt;

On his accession, however, Artaxerxes II lost Egypt to pharaoh [[Amyrtaeus]], after which it was no longer part of the Persian empire. In his ''Historia Scholastica'' [[Petrus Comestor]] identified Ahasuerus (Esther 1:1) as [[Artaxerxes III]] (358–38 BC) who reconquered Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= https://la.wikisource.org/wiki/Historia_Scholastica/Esther#De_Ocho_seu_Artaxerxe. |title= Historia Scholastica/Esther |website= Wikisource}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Structure ===
The Book of Esther consists of an introduction (or [[exposition (narrative)|exposition]]) in chapters 1 and 2; the main action (complication and resolution) in chapters 3 to 9:19; and a conclusion in 9:20–10:3.{{sfn |Clines|1984|p=9}}

The plot is structured around banquets (''mishteh''), a word that occurs twenty times in Esther and only 24 times in the rest of the Hebrew bible. This is appropriate given that Esther describes the origin of a Jewish feast, the feast of [[Purim]], but Purim itself is not the subject and no individual feast in the book is commemorated by Purim. The book's theme, rather, is the reversal of destiny through a sudden and unexpected turn of events: the Jews seem destined to be destroyed, but instead are saved. In literary criticism such a reversal is termed &quot;[[Peripeteia|peripety]]&quot;, and while on one level its use in Esther is simply a literary or aesthetic device, on another it is structural to the author's theme, suggesting that the power of God is at work behind human events.{{sfn |Jobes|2011|pp =40–41}}

== Summary ==
King Ahasuerus, ruler of the [[Achaemenid Empire|Persian Empire]], holds a lavish 180-day banquet, initially for his court and dignitaries and afterwards a seven-day banquet for all inhabitants of the capital city, [[Susa|Shushan]] (Esther 1:1–9).  On the seventh day of the latter banquet, Ahasuerus orders the queen, [[Vashti]], to display her beauty before the guests by coming before them wearing her crown (1:10–11).  She refuses, infuriating Ahasuerus, who on the advice of his counselors removes her from her position as an example to other women who might be emboldened to disobey their husbands (1:12–19).  A decree follows that &quot;every man should bear rule in his own house&quot; (1:20–22).

[[File:Schnorr von Carolsfeld Bibel in Bildern 1860 129.png|thumb|right|Esther is crowned in this 1860 woodcut by [[Julius Schnorr von Karolsfeld]]]]
Ahasuerus then makes arrangements to choose a new queen from a selection of beautiful young women from throughout the empire (2:1–4).  Among these women is a Jewish [[orphan]] named [[Esther]], who was raised by her cousin or uncle, [[Mordecai]] (2:5–7).  She finds favour in the King's eyes, and is crowned his new queen, but does not reveal her Jewish heritage (2:8–20).  Shortly afterwards, Mordecai discovers a plot by two courtiers, [[Bigthan and Teresh]], to assassinate Ahasuerus. The conspirators are apprehended and hanged, and Mordecai's service to the King is recorded (2:21–23).

Ahasuerus appoints [[Haman]] as his [[viceroy]] (3:1). Mordecai, who sits at the palace gates, falls into Haman's disfavour, as he refuses to bow down to him (3:2–5).  Haman discovers that Mordecai refused to bow on account of his Jewishness, and in revenge plots to kill not just Mordecai, but all the Jews in the empire (3:6).  He obtains Ahasuerus' permission to execute this plan, against payment of ten thousand [[talent (measurement)|talent]]s of silver, and casts lots (&quot;purim&quot;) to choose the date on which to do this{{snd}} the thirteenth of the month of [[Adar]] (3:7–12).  A royal decree is issued throughout the kingdom to slay all Jews on that date. (3:13–15).

When Mordecai discovers the plan, he goes into mourning and implores Esther to intercede with the King (4:1–5).  But she is afraid to present herself to the King unsummoned, an offense punishable by death (4:6–12).  Instead, she directs Mordecai to have all Jews fast for three days for her, and vows to fast as well (4:15–16.).  On the third day she goes to Ahasuerus, who stretches out his sceptre to her to indicate that she is not to be punished (5:1–2).  She invites him to a feast in the company of Haman (5:3–5).  During the feast, she asks them to attend a further feast the next evening (5:6–8).  Meanwhile, Haman is again offended by Mordecai and, at his wife's suggestion, has a [[gallows]] built to hang him (5:9–14).

That night, Ahasuerus cannot sleep, and orders the court records be read to him (6:1). He is reminded that Mordecai interceded in the previous plot against his life, and discovers that Mordecai never received any recognition (6:2–3). Just then, Haman appears to request the King's permission to hang Mordecai, but before he can make this request, Ahasuerus asks Haman what should be done for the man that the King wishes to honor (6:4–6).  Assuming that the King is referring to Haman himself, Haman suggests that the man be dressed in the King's royal robes, and crown and led around on the King's royal horse, while a [[herald]] calls: &quot;See how the King honours a man he wishes to reward!&quot; (6:7–9).  To his surprise and horror, the King instructs Haman to do so to Mordecai (6:10–11).

[[File:Schnorr von Carolsfeld Bibel in Bildern 1860 130.png|thumb|right|Mordecai is honored in this 1860 woodcut by Julius Schnorr von Karolsfeld.]]
Immediately after, Ahasuerus and Haman attend Esther's second banquet. The King promises to grant her any request, and she reveals that she is Jewish and that Haman is planning to exterminate her people, including her (7:1–6).  Overcome by rage, Ahasuerus leaves the room; meanwhile Haman stays behind and begs Esther for his life, falling upon her in desperation (7:7).  The King returns in at this very moment and thinks Haman is assaulting the queen; this makes him angrier and he orders Haman hanged on the very gallows that Haman had prepared for Mordecai (7:8–10).

Unable to annul a formal royal decree, the King instead adds to it, permitting the Jews to join together and destroy any and all of those seeking to oppress them&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://www.chabad.org/library/bible_cdo/aid/16481/jewish/Chapter-8.htm |title = Esther - Chapter 8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://jwa.org/encyclopedia/article/esther-bible |title = Esther: Bible &amp;#124; Jewish Women's Archive}}&lt;/ref&gt; (8:1–14).  On 13 Adar, Haman's ten sons and 500 other men are killed in Shushan (9:1–12).  Upon hearing of this Esther requests it be repeated the next day, whereupon 300 more men are killed (9:13–15).  Over 75,000 people are slaughtered by the Jews, who are careful to take no plunder (9:16–17).  Mordecai and Esther send letters throughout the provinces instituting an annual commemoration of the Jewish people's redemption, in a holiday called [[Purim]] (lots) (9:20–28).  Ahasuerus remains very powerful and continues his reign, with Mordecai assuming a prominent position in his court (10:1–3).

== Authorship and date ==
[[File:Göttingen-Esther.Rolle.0.JPG|thumb|right|Scroll of Esther (Megillah)]]
The ''Megillat Esther'' (Book of Esther) became the last of the 24 books of the [[Tanakh]] to be canonized by the Sages of the [[Great Assembly]]. According to the Talmud, it was a [[redaction]] by the Great Assembly of an original text by Mordecai.&lt;ref&gt;''Babylonian Talmud: Tractate Baba Bathra'' 15a&lt;/ref&gt; It is usually dated to the 4th century BC.&lt;ref&gt;NIV Study Bible, ''Introductions to the Books of the Bible, Esther'', Zondervan, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Jewish Study Bible |url=https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780195297515 |url-access=registration |date=2004 |publisher=Oxford University Press |editor-last1=Berlin |editor-first1=Adele |editor-last2=Brettler |editor-first2=Marc Zvi |editor-last3=Fishbane |editor-first3=Michael |isbn=978-0195297515 |page=[https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780195297515/page/1625 1625]}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Shemaryahu Talmon]], however, suggests that &quot;the traditional setting of the book in the days of Xerxes I cannot be wide off the mark.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Shemaryahu Talmon, [https://www.jstor.org/stable/1516862 &quot;Wisdom in the Book of Esther&quot;], ''[[Vetus Testamentum]]'' 13 (1963), p. 453 (at JSTOR, free subscription needed)&lt;/ref&gt;

The Greek book of Esther, included in the [[Septuagint]], is a retelling of the events of the Hebrew Book of Esther rather than a translation and records [[#Additions to Esther|additional traditions]] which do not appear in traditional Hebrew version, in particular the identification of Ahasuerus with [[Artaxerxes II of Persia|Artaxerxes]] and details of various letters. It is dated around the late 2nd to early 1st century BC.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Freedman |first=David Noel |first2=Allen C. |last2=Myers |first3=Astrid B. |last3=Beck |title=Eerdmans Dictionary of the Bible |publisher=Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing |year=2000 |isbn=9780802824004 |page=428 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=P9sYIRXZZ2MC&amp;pg=PA428 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;George Lyons, ''Additions to Esther'', Wesley Center for Applied Theology, 2000&lt;/ref&gt; The Coptic and Ethiopic versions of Esther are translations of the Greek rather than the Hebrew Esther.

A Latin version of Esther was produced by [[Jerome]] for the [[Vulgate]]. It translates the Hebrew Esther but interpolates translations of the Greek Esther where the latter provides additional material.

Several Aramaic [[targum]]s of Esther were produced in the [[Middle Ages]] of which two survive – the ''[[Targum Rishon]]'' (&quot;First Targum&quot;) and ''[[Targum Sheni]]'' (&quot;Second Targum&quot;)&lt;ref name=&quot;Sokoloff&quot;&gt;Prof. Michael Sokoloff, ''The Targums to the Book of Esther'', Bar-Ilan University 's Parashat Hashavua Study Center, Parashat Tezaveh/Zakhor 5764 March 6, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kaufman&quot;&gt;S. Kaufman, ''Cal Targum Texts, Text base and variants'', The Comprehensive Aramaic Lexicon, Hebrew Union College – Jewish Institute of Religion&lt;/ref&gt; dated c. 500–1000&amp;nbsp;AD.&lt;ref&gt;Alan J. Hauser, Duane Frederick Watson, ''A History of Biblical Interpretation: The Ancient Period'', Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing, 2003&lt;/ref&gt; These were not targums (&quot;translations&quot;) in the true sense but like the Greek Esther are retellings of events and include additional legends relating to Purim.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sokoloff&quot;/&gt; There is also a 16th-century recension of the ''Targum Rishon'', sometimes counted as ''Targum Shelishi'' (&quot;Third Targum&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;Kaufman&quot;/&gt;

== Historicity ==
[[File:Megillat Esther (1).jpg|thumb|235px|The opening chapter of a hand-written scroll of the Book of Esther, with reader's pointer]]
The blatant historical difficulties, the internal inconsistencies, the pronounced symmetry of themes and events, the plenitude of quoted dialogue, and the gross exaggeration in the reporting of numbers (involving time, money, and people) all point to Esther as a work of fiction, its vivid characters (except for Xerxes) being the product of the author's creative imagination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Barton |first1=John |last2=Muddiman |first2=John |title=The Oxford Bible Commentary |date=2007 |publisher=Oxford University Press |isbn=9780199277186 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DWUTDAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA325 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to some sources, it is a [[historical novel]]la, written to [[Myth of origins|explain the origin]] of the Jewish holiday of Purim.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coogan, Michael David Coogan 2009&quot;&gt;Coogan, Michael David, ''A Brief Introduction to the Old Testament: The Hebrew Bible in Its Context'' (New York: Oxford University Press, 2009), 396.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sidnie White Crawford 2003&quot;&gt;Sidnie White Crawford, &quot;Esther&quot;, in ''The New Interpreters Study Bible New Revised Standard Version'' with the Apocrypha, ed. Walter J. Harrison and Donald Senior (Nashville: Abingdon Press, 2003), 689–90.&lt;/ref&gt;

As noted by biblical scholar [[Michael D. Coogan]], the book contains specific details regarding certain subject matter (for example, Persian rule) which are historically inaccurate. For example, Coogan discusses an apparent inaccuracy regarding the age of Esther's cousin (or, according to others, uncle) [[Mordecai]].&lt;ref name= &quot;Coogan, Michael David Coogan 2009&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name= &quot;Sidnie White Crawford 2003&quot; /&gt; In Esther 2:5–6, either Mordecai or his great-grandfather Kish is identified as having been exiled from Jerusalem to Babylon by King [[Nebuchadnezzar II]] in 597&amp;nbsp;BC: &quot;Mordecai son of Jair, the son of Shimei, the son of Kish, who had been carried into exile from Jerusalem by Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon, among those taken captive with [[Jeconiah]] king of Judah&quot;. If this refers to Mordecai, he would have had to live over a century to have witnessed the events described in the Book of Esther.&lt;ref name= &quot;Coogan, Michael David Coogan 2009&quot;/&gt; However, the verse may be read as referring not to Mordecai's exile to Babylon, but to his great-grandfather Kish's exile.&lt;ref&gt;New King James Version, translation of [http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=esther%202:6&amp;version=NKJV Esther 2:6]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ISBE&quot;&gt;{{cite book |editor-last=Bromiley |editor-first=Geoffrey W. |title=International Standard Bible Encyclopedia, Volume II |year=1982 |publisher=Wm. B. Eerdmans Pub. Co. |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=yklDk6Vv0l4C&amp;pg=PA159 |page=159 |chapter=Book of Esther }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Wiersbe |first=Warren W. |url=https://archive.org/details/bibleexpositionc00wier |url-access=registration |title=Bible Exposition Commentary: Old Testament History |publisher=David C Cook |year=2004 |page=712 |isbn=9780781435314 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In her article &quot;The Book of Esther and Ancient Storytelling&quot;, biblical scholar [[Adele Berlin]] discusses the reasoning behind scholarly concern about the historicity of Esther. Much of this debate relates to the importance of distinguishing history and fiction within biblical texts, as Berlin argues, in order to gain a more accurate understanding of the history of the Israelite people.&lt;ref name=&quot;Adele Berlin 2001&quot;&gt;[[Adele Berlin]], &quot;The Book of Esther and Ancient Storytelling&quot;, ''[[Journal of Biblical Literature]]'' 120, no. 1 (Spring 2001): 3–14.&lt;/ref&gt; Berlin quotes a series of scholars who suggest that the author of Esther did not mean for the book to be considered as a historical writing, but intentionally wrote it to be a historical novella.&lt;ref&gt;Berlin, 2001: 6.&lt;/ref&gt;  The genre of novellas under which Esther falls was common during both the Persian and [[Hellenistic period]]s to which scholars have dated the book of Esther.&lt;ref name= &quot;Coogan, Michael David Coogan 2009&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name= &quot;Adele Berlin 2001&quot; /&gt;

There are certain elements of the book of Esther that are historically accurate. The story told in the book of Esther takes place during the rule of Ahasuerus, who [[Ahasuerus#Historical identification|amongst others]] has been identified as the 5th-century Persian king [[Xerxes I]] (reigned 486–465 BC).&lt;ref name= &quot;Between&quot; /&gt; The author also displays an accurate knowledge of Persian customs and palaces.&lt;ref name= &quot;ISBE&quot; /&gt; However, according to Coogan, considerable historical inaccuracies remain throughout the text, supporting the view that the book of Esther is to be read as a historical novella which tells a story describing historical events but is not necessarily historical fact.&lt;ref name= &quot;Coogan, Michael David Coogan 2009&quot;/&gt; [[Edwin M. Yamauchi]] has questioned the reliability of other historical sources, such as [[Herodotus]], to which Esther has been compared. Yamauchi wrote, &quot;[Herodotus] was, however, the victim of unreliable informants and was not infallible.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Yamauchi, Edwin M., 1980&quot;&gt;&quot;The archaeological background of Esther: archaeological backgrounds of the exilic and postexilic era, pt 2&quot;. ''Bibliotheca sacra'' 137, no. 546 (1980), 102.&lt;/ref&gt;  The reason for questioning the historical accuracy of such ancient writers as Herodotus is that he is one of the primary sources of knowledge for this time period, and it has been frequently assumed that his account may be more accurate than Esther's account.

== Historical reading ==
{{More citations needed|date=March 2013}}
[[File:The Feast of Esther - Jan Lievens - Google Cultural Institute.jpg|thumb|right|280px|''The Feast of Esther'' (''Feest van Esther'', 1625) by [[Jan Lievens]], [[North Carolina Museum of Art]].]]

Those arguing in favour of a historical reading of Esther most commonly identify Ahasuerus with [[Xerxes I]] (ruled 486–465&amp;nbsp;BC),&lt;ref name= &quot;Between&quot; /&gt; although in the past it was often assumed that he was [[Artaxerxes II]] (ruled 405–359&amp;nbsp;BC). The [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] ''Ahasuerus'' (''ʔaḥašwērōš'') is most likely derived from [[Persian language|Persian]] ''Xšayārša'', the origin of the [[Greek language|Greek]] ''Xerxes''. The Greek historian [[Herodotus]] wrote that Xerxes sought his [[Harem (household)|harem]] after being defeated in the [[Greco-Persian Wars]]. He makes no reference to individual members of the harem except for a domineering [[Queen consort]] named [[Amestris]], whose father, [[Otanes]], was one of Xerxes's generals.  (In contrast, the Greek historian [[Ctesias]] refers to a similar father-in-law/general figure named Onaphas.) Amestris has often been identified with [[Vashti]], but this identification is problematic, as Amestris remained a powerful figure well into the reign of her son, [[Artaxerxes I]], whereas Vashti is portrayed as dismissed in the early part of Xerxes's reign.{{citation needed|date=January 2018}} Alternative attempts have been made to identify her with [[Esther]], although Esther is an orphan whose father was a Jew named Abihail.

As for the identity of Mordecai, the similar names ''Marduka'' and ''Marduku'' have been found as the name of officials in the Persian court in over thirty texts from the period of Xerxes I and his father [[Darius I]], and may refer to up to four individuals, one of whom might be the model for  the biblical Mordecai.

The &quot;Old Greek&quot; Septuagint version of Esther translates the name Ahasuerus as ''Artaxerxes'',&lt;ref&gt;http://ccat.sas.upenn.edu/nets/edition/17-esther-nets.pdf Note on two Greek versions of the book of Esther.&lt;/ref&gt; a Greek name derived from the [[Persian language|Persian]] ''Artaxšaϑra''. [[Josephus]] too relates that this was the name by which he was known to the Greeks, and the [[Midrash]]ic text ''Esther Rabba'' also makes the identification. [[Bar-Hebraeus]] identified Ahasuerus explicitly as [[Artaxerxes II of Persia|Artaxerxes II]]; however, the names are not necessarily equivalent: Hebrew has a form of the name ''Artaxerxes'' distinct from ''Ahasuerus'', and a direct Greek rendering of ''Ahasuerus'' is used by both Josephus and the Septuagint for occurrences of the name outside the Book of Esther. Instead, the Hebrew name Ahasuerus accords with an inscription of the time that notes that Artaxerxes II was named also ''Aršu'', understood as a shortening of ''Aḫšiyaršu'' the Babylonian rendering of the Persian ''Xšayārša'' (Xerxes), through which the Hebrew ''ʔaḥašwērōš'' (Ahasuerus) is derived.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hosch&quot;&gt;Jacob Hoschander, ''The Book of Esther in the Light of History'', Oxford University Press, 1923&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ctesias]] related that Artaxerxes II was also called ''Arsicas'' which is understood as a similar shortening with the Persian suffix ''-ke'' that is applied to shortened names. [[Deinon]] related that Artaxerxes II was also called ''Oarses'' which is also understood to be derived from ''Xšayārša''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hosch&quot;/&gt;

Another view attempts to identify him instead with [[Artaxerxes I of Persia|Artaxerxes I]] (ruled 465–424&amp;nbsp;BC), whose Babylonian concubine, [[Kosmartydene]], was the mother of his son [[Darius II of Persia|Darius II]] (ruled 424–405&amp;nbsp;BC). Jewish tradition relates that Esther was the mother of a King Darius and so some try to identify Ahasuerus with Artaxerxes I and Esther with Kosmartydene.

Based on the view that the Ahasuerus of the [[Book of Tobit]] is identical with that of the Book of Esther, some have also identified him as Nebuchadnezzar's ally [[Cyaxares]] (ruled 625–585&amp;nbsp;BC). In certain manuscripts of Tobit, the former is called ''Achiachar'', which, like the [[Greek language|Greek]] ''Cyaxares'', is thought to be derived from [[Persian language|Persian]] ''Huwaxšaϑra''. Depending on the interpretation of Esther 2:5–6, Mordecai or his great-grandfather Kish was carried away from [[Jerusalem]] with [[Jeconiah]] by [[Nebuchadnezzar II of Babylon|Nebuchadnezzar]], in 597&amp;nbsp;BC. The view that it was Mordecai would be consistent with the identification of Ahasuerus with Cyaxares. Identifications with other Persian monarchs have also been suggested.

Jacob Hoschander has argued that evidence of the historicity of Haman and his father Hamedatha is seen in ''Omanus'' and ''Anadatus'' mentioned by [[Strabo]] as being honoured with Anahita in the city of [[Zile|Zela]]. Hoschander argues that these were not deities as Strabo supposed but garbled forms of &quot;Haman&quot; and &quot;Hamedatha&quot; who were being worshipped as martyrs. The names are indeed unattested in Persian texts as gods, however the Talmud (''Sanhedrin'' 61b) and [[Rashi]] both record a practice of deifying Haman and Josephus speaks of him being worshipped.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hosch&quot;/&gt; Attempts have been made to connect both &quot;Omanus&quot; and &quot;Haman&quot; with the Zoroastrian term [[Vohu Mana]]; however this denotes the principle of &quot;Good Thoughts&quot; and is not the name of a deity.)

In his ''Historia Scholastica'' [[Petrus Comestor]] identified Ahasuerus (Esther 1:1) as [[Artaxerxes III]] who reconquered Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://la.wikisource.org/wiki/Historia_Scholastica/Esther#De_Ocho_seu_Artaxerxe. | title=Historia Scholastica/Esther - Wikisource}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Interpretation ==
In the Book of Esther the [[Tetragrammaton]] does not appear, but it is present, in hidden form, in four complex [[acrostic]]s in Hebrew: the initial or last letters of four consecutive words, either forwards or backwards comprise YHWH. These letters were distinguished in at least three ancient Hebrew manuscripts in red.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.therain.org/appendixes/app60.html The Name of Jehovah in the Book of Esther.], appendix 60, ''Companion Bible''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=note&gt;These are Est 1:20; 5:4, 13 and 7:7. Additionally, Est 7:5 there is an acrostic referring to the title of God of Exodus 3:14.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Christine Hayes]] contrasts the Book of Esther with [[Apocalyptic literature|apocalyptic writings]], the [[Book of Daniel]] in particular: both Esther and Daniel depict an existential threat to the Jewish people, but while Daniel commands the Jews to wait faithfully for God to resolve the crisis, in Esther the crisis is resolved entirely through human action and national solidarity. God, in fact, is not mentioned, Esther is portrayed as [[cultural assimilation|assimilated]] to Persian culture, and Jewish identity in the book is an [[Jewish peoplehood|ethnic category]] rather than a [[Judaism|religious one]].&lt;ref name=&quot;oyc&quot;&gt;{{cite web |first=Christine |last=Hayes |authorlink=Christine Hayes |year=2006 |url=http://oyc.yale.edu/religious-studies/rlst-145/lecture-24 |website=[[Open Yale Courses]] |publisher=[[Yale University]] |title=&lt;!--RLST 145: --&gt;Introduction to the Old Testament (Hebrew Bible): Lecture 24{{snd}} Alternative Visions: Esther, Ruth, and Jonah}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This contrasts with traditional Jewish commentaries, such as the commentary of the [[Vilna Gaon]], which states &quot;But in every verse it discusses the great miracle.  However, this miracle was in a hidden form, occurring through apparently natural processes, not like the Exodus from Egypt, which openly revealed the might of God.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Commentary of the Vilna Gaon to the Book of Esther 1:1&lt;/ref&gt;  This follows the approach of the [[Talmud]],&lt;ref&gt;Chullin 139b&lt;/ref&gt; which states that &quot;(The Book of) Esther is referenced in the Torah in the verse 'And I shall surely hide (in Hebrew, 'haster astir,' related to 'Esther') My Face  from them on that day.&lt;ref&gt;Deut. 31:18&lt;/ref&gt;

== Additions to Esther ==
{{Anchor|Additions to Esther}}&lt;!--[[Additions to the Book of Esther]] redirects here--&gt;
An additional six chapters appear interspersed in Esther in the [[Septuagint]], the Greek translation of the Bible. This was noted by [[Jerome]] in compiling the Latin [[Vulgate]]. Additionally, the Greek text contains many small changes in the meaning of the main text. Jerome recognized the former as additions not present in the [[Tanakh|Hebrew Text]] and placed them at the end of his Latin translation. This placement and numbering system is used in Catholic Bible translations based primarily on the Vulgate, such as the [[Douay–Rheims Bible]] and the [[Knox Bible]]. In contrast, the 1979 revision of the Vulgate, the [[Nova Vulgata]], incorporates the additions to Esther directly into the narrative itself, as do most modern Catholic English translations based on the original Hebrew and Greek (e.g., [[Revised Standard Version Catholic Edition]], [[New American Bible]], [[New Revised Standard Version Catholic Edition]]). The numbering system for the additions differs with each translation. The Nova Vulgata accounts for the additional verses by numbering them as extensions of the verses immediately following or preceding them (e.g., Esther 11:2–12 in the old Vulgate becomes Esther 1:1a–1k in the Nova Vulgata), while the NAB and its successor, the NABRE, assign letters of the alphabet as chapter headings for the additions (e.g., Esther 11:2–12:6 in the Vulgate becomes Esther A:1–17). The RSVCE and the NRSVCE place the additional material into the narrative, but retain the chapter and verse numbering of the old Vulgate.

These additions include:&lt;ref&gt;see [http://www.usccb.org/bible/scripture.cfm?bk=Esther&amp;ch= the NAB online] for the passages&lt;/ref&gt;
* an opening prologue that describes a dream had by Mordecai
* the contents of the decree against the Jews
* prayers for God's intervention offered by Mordecai and by Esther
* an expansion of the scene in which Esther appears before the king, with a mention of God's intervention
* a copy of the decree in favor of the Jews
* a passage in which Mordecai interprets his dream (from the prologue) in terms of the events that followed
* a colophon appended to the end, which reads: In the fourth year of the reign of Ptolemy and Cleopatra, Dositheus, who said he was a priest and Levite, and his son Ptolemy brought the present letter of Purim, saying that it was genuine and that Lysimachus, son of Ptolemy, of the community of Jerusalem, had translated it.
By the time the Greek version of Esther was written, the foreign power visible on the horizon as a future threat to Judah was the [[Macedon]]ians of [[Alexander the Great]], who defeated the Persian empire about 150 years after the time of the story of Esther; the [[Septuagint]] version noticeably calls Haman a &quot;Bougaion&quot; (βουγαῖον){{Incomprehensible inline|date=February 2020|reason=how does that obscure word 'bougaion' relate to Alexander, Macedonians, etc}} where the Hebrew text describes him as an [[Agagite]].

The canonicity of these Greek additions has been a subject of scholarly disagreement practically since their first appearance in the [[Septuagint]]{{snd}} [[Martin Luther]], being perhaps the most vocal [[Protestant Reformation|Reformation]]-era critic of the work, considered even the original Hebrew version to be of very doubtful value.&lt;ref&gt;Frederic W. Bush, [http://www.biblicalstudies.org.uk/pdf/esther_bush.pdf &quot;The Book of Esther: Opus non gratum in the Christian Canon&quot;], ''[[Bulletin for Biblical Research]]'' 8 (1998), p. 39&lt;/ref&gt; Luther's complaints against the book carried past the point of scholarly critique and may reflect Luther's antisemitism, which is disputed, such as in the biography of Luther by Derek Wilson, which points out that Luther's anger at the Jews was not at their race but at their theology.

The [[Council of Trent]], the summation of the [[Roman Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]] [[Counter-Reformation]], reconfirmed the entire book, both Hebrew text and Greek additions, as canonical. The Book of Esther is used twice in commonly used sections of the Catholic [[Lectionary]]. In both cases, the text used is not only taken from a Greek addition, the readings also are the prayer of [[Mordecai]], and nothing of [[Esther]]'s own words is ever used. The [[Eastern Orthodox Church]] uses the Septuagint version of Esther, as it does for all of the Old Testament.

In contrast, the additions are included in the [[Biblical apocrypha]], usually printed in a separate section (if at all) in Protestant bibles.  The additions, called &quot;The rest of the Book of Esther&quot;, are specifically listed in the [[Thirty-Nine Articles]], Article VI, of the [[Church of England]] as non-canonical.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.churchofengland.org/prayer-and-worship/worship-texts-and-resources/book-common-prayer/articles-religion#VI www.churchofengland.org]: they are included in the section headed: &quot;And the other Books (as Hierome saith) the Church doth read for example of life and instruction of manners; but yet doth it not apply them to establish any doctrine; such are these following:...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

== Modern retelling ==
* There are several [[:Category:Paintings of Esther|paintings depicting Esther]], including one by [[John Everett Millais|Millais]].
*In 1660, Rembrandt van Rijn's painting of ''Esther's Banquet'' depicts how Esther approached the men at their level to make the request of erasing the decree. The painting's clarity is not the best, but the emotion on Haman and the king's face can be seen. There is anger but also fear within their faces. The anger but also concern on the king's face could be inferred that Esther has just told them her true identity and the acts that Haman has committed not only against Esther but every Jew. 
* The [[Italian Renaissance]] poet [[Lucrezia Tornabuoni]] chose Esther as one of biblical figures on which she wrote poetry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Robin, Larsen and Levin | title=Encyclopedia of women in the Renaissance: Italy, France, and England | page=368}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 1689, [[Jean Baptiste Racine]] wrote ''[[Esther (drama)|Esther]]'', a [[tragedy]], at the request of [[Louis XIV]]'s wife, [[Françoise d'Aubigné, marquise de Maintenon]].
* In 1718, [[Handel]] wrote the oratorio ''[[Esther (oratorio)|Esther]]'' based on Racine's play.
* In 1958, a book entitled ''Behold Your Queen!'' was written by [[Gladys Malvern]] and illustrated by her sister, [[Corinne Malvern]]. It was chosen as a selection of the Junior Literary Guild.
* The play entitled ''Esther'' (1960), written by Welsh dramatist [[Saunders Lewis]], is a retelling of the story in [[Welsh language|Welsh]].
* A 1960 movie about the story, ''[[Esther and the King]]'', starring [[Joan Collins]].
* A 1978 [[miniseries]] entitled ''[[The Greatest Heroes of the Bible]]'' starred [[Victoria Principal]] as Esther, [[Robert Mandan]] as Xerxes, and [[Michael Ansara]] as Haman.
* Episode 25 of the 1981 [[anime]] series [[Superbook]] involves this story.
* The 1983 [[Musical theatre|musical]] entitled ''[[Swan Esther]]'' was written by [[J. Edward Oliver]] and [[Nick Munns]] and released as a concept album with [[Stephanie Lawrence]] and [[Denis Quilley]]. ''[[Swan Esther]]'' has been performed by the [[Young Vic]], a national tour produced by [[Bill Kenwright]] and some amateur groups.
* A 1986 Israeli film directed by [[Amos Gitai]] entitled ''[[Esther (1986 film)|Esther]]''.
* In 1992, a 30-minute, fully animated video, twelfth in [[Hanna-Barbera]]'s ''[[The Greatest Adventure: Stories from the Bible|The Greatest Adventure]]'' series, titled ''Queen Esther'' features the voices of [[Helen Slater]] as Queen Esther, [[Dean Jones (actor)|Dean Jones]] as King Ahasuerus, [[Werner Klemperer]] as Haman, and [[Ron Rifkin]] as Mordecai.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.booksofthebible.com/p1958.html|title=I Have A Song – Shannon Wexelberg|author=Books of the Bible Christian Bookstore|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.earthling.com/cgi-bin/google.fcgi/itemKey=1923000071|title=The Internet Antique Shop – The Web's largest antiques &amp; collectibles mall serving collectors since 1995|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* A 1999 TV movie from the ''Bible Collection'' that follows the biblical account very closely, ''[[Esther (1999 film)|Esther]]'', starred [[Louise Lombard]] in the title role and [[F. Murray Abraham]] as Mordecai.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0168331/|title=Esther|author=Tania B|date=5 November 2000|work=IMDb}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In [[2000 in film|2000]], ''[[VeggieTales]]'' released &quot;[[Esther... The Girl Who Became Queen]]&quot;.
* ''Chosen: The Lost Diaries of Queen Esther'' by Ginger Garrett. 2005, NavPress.{{importance inline|date=July 2015}}
* A [[2006 in film|2006]] [[Film|movie]] about Esther and Ahasuerus, entitled ''[[One Night with the King]]'', stars [[Tiffany Dupont]] and [[Luke Goss]]. It was based on the novel ''[[Hadassah: One Night with the King]]'' by [[Tommy Tenney]] and [[Mark Andrew Olsen]].
* Esther is one of the five heroines of the [[Order of the Eastern Star]].
* On March 8, 2011, the [[Maccabeats]] released a music video called &quot;Purim Song&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kgJInVvJSZg&amp;feature=player_embedded |title=The Maccabeats – Purim Song |publisher=YouTube |accessdate=2011-08-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[The Book of Esther (film)|''The Book of Esther'']] is a 2013 movie starring [[Jen Lilley]] as Queen Esther and Joel Smallbone as King Xerxes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt2521404 |title=The Book of Esther (2013) |date=11 June 2013 |work=IMDb}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 2012, a graphic adaptation of the Book of Esther was illustrated by J. T. Waldman and appeared in volume one of ''[[The Graphic Canon]]'', edited by [[Russ Kick]] and published by [[Seven Stories Press]].

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group=&quot;note&quot;}}

== References ==
=== Citations ===
{{Reflist}}

=== Sources ===
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book
  | last      = Clines
  | first     = David J.A. 
  | title     = The Esther Scroll
  | year      = 1984
  | publisher = A&amp;C Black
  | url       = https://books.google.com/books?id=PBediPzesQ0C&amp;pg=PA9
  | ref       = harv
| isbn = 9780567157133 
 }}
* {{cite book
  | last      = Jobes
  | first     = Karen H. 
  | title     = Esther
  | year      = 2011
  | publisher = Zondervan
  | url       = https://books.google.com/books?id=P-LPe-LlivkC&amp;pg=PA40
  | ref       = harv
| isbn = 9780310872146 
 }}
* Beal, Timothy K ([[Timothy Beal]]). ''The Book of Hiding: Gender, Ethnicity, Annihilation, and Esther''. NY: Routledge, 1997. Postmodern theoretical apparatus, e.g. [[Jacques Derrida]], [[Emmanuel Levinas]]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060114082336/http://www.myjewishlearning.com/holidays/Purim/TO_Purim_History/Esther_830.htm Extract from The JPS Bible Commentary: Esther by Adele Berlin]: Liberal Jewish view.
* Grossman, Jonathan, ''Esther: The Outer Narrative and the Hidden Reading'', Winona Lake, IN.: Eisenbrauns, 2011.
* {{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7YTSRwAACAAJ |title=Character and Ideology in the Book of Esther |isbn=9781608994953 |last1=Fox |first1=Michael V. |date=April 2010 }}
* Sasson, Jack M. &quot;Esther&quot; in Alter and Kermode, pp.&amp;nbsp;335–341, literary view
* [http://www.aishdas.org/toratemet/en_esther.html The Historicity of Megillat Esther]: Gil Student's survey of scholarship supporting a historical reading of Esther
* [http://www.ccel.org/wwsb/Esther/index.html ''Esther, Book of'']: A Christian perspective of the book.
* Thespis: Ritual, Myth, and Drama in the Ancient Near East by [[Theodor Gaster]]. 1950.
* White, Sidnie Ann. &quot;Esther: A Feminine Model for Jewish Diaspora&quot; in Newsom
* [http://www.chabad.org/library/archive/LibraryArchive2.asp?AID=15782 Esther (Judaica Press)] translation [with [[Rashi]]'s commentary] at Chabad.org
* Cumming, Rev. J. Elder DD ''The Book of Esther: Its spiritual teaching'' London: The Religious Tract Society, 1913
* Ecker, Ronald L. [http://www.ronaldecker.com/esther.html The Book of Esther], Ecker's Biblical Web Pages, 2007.
* Fischer, James A. ''Song of Songs, Ruth, Lamentations, Ecclesiastes, Esther''. Collegeville Bible Commentary. Collegeville, MN: Liturgical Press, 1986.
* Fox, Michael V. ''Character and Ideology in the Book of Esther''. Grand Rapids, MI: Eerdmans, 2001.
* Hudson, J. Francis ''Esther: For Such a Time as This''. From ''Character and Charisma'' series. Kingsway, 2000.
* Levenson, Jon D. ''Esther''. Old Testament Library Series. Louisville, KY: Westminster John Knox, 1997.
* McConville, John C. L. ''Ezra, Nehemiah, and Esther''. Daily Study Bible Series. Philadelphia: Westminster, 1985.
* Moore, Carey A. ''Esther''. Anchor Bible, vol. 7B. Garden City, NY: Doubleday, 1971.
* [[Lewis B. Paton|Paton, Lewis B]]. ''A Critical and Exegetical Commentary on the Book of Esther''. International Critical Commentary. Edinburgh, Scotland: T&amp;T Clark, 1908.
* [[Yoram Hazony|Hazony, Yoram]]. ''God and Politics in Esther''. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2016.
* {{cite NIE|wstitle=Esther, Book of|year=1905 |short=x}}
* {{cite NIE|wstitle=Esther, Apocryphal Book of|year=1905 |short=x}}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Book of Esther}}
{{Wikisource|Esther (Bible)|Esther}}
{{Wikisource|Bible (King James)/Rest_of_Esther|The King James Version of Rest of Esther}}

=== Text and translations ===
* Jewish translations
** [http://www.chabad.org/library/archive/LibraryArchive2.asp?AID=15782 Esther (Judaica Press)] translation [with [[Rashi]]'s commentary] at Chabad.org
** [http://www.torahvort.com/torah-topics/purim Purim insights to Megillat Esther]
** [http://www.mechon-mamre.org/i/t/t33.htm Mechon Mamre] Full text, [[Aleppo Codex]]: text of Esther in Hebrew
** [https://ph.yhb.org.il/en/05-15-05/ Reading the Megilla and Publicizing the Miracle, minhagim (customs) and halachot (laws) by Rabbi [[Eliezer Melamed]]]
** [https://soundcloud.com/yeshiva-har-bracha/sets/p7tycu9z5ibj Hearing the Book of Esther with a short translation by Rabbi Yonadav Zar In Hebrew] (Audio)
* Christian translations
** [http://www.gospelhall.org/bible/bible.php?passage=Esther+1 ''Online Bible'' at GospelHall.org]
** [http://st-takla.org/pub_Deuterocanon/Deuterocanon-Apocrypha_El-Asfar_El-Kanoneya_El-Tanya__3-Esther.html The Book of Esther] Full text, [[KJV]], (also available at [http://st-takla.org/pub_Deuterocanon/Deuterocanon-Apocrypha_El-Asfar_El-Kanoneya_El-Tanya__3-Esther_.html Arabic])
** [https://web.archive.org/web/20000815062938/http://www.nccbuscc.org/nab/bible/index.htm#esther Esther] in the [[New American Bible|NAB]]
** [http://www.livius.org/es-ez/esther/esther01.html Esther] [[New Revised Standard Version|NRSV translation]] with photos of Susa
** [http://www.biblicalaudio.com/esther.htm Esther: 2012 Critical Translation with Audio Drama] at biblicalaudio
** [http://www.vts.edu/ftpimages/95/download/FM.Crawford.Esther.pdf ''Introduction to the Book of Esther'']
* {{librivox book | dtitle=Bible: Esther| stitle=17: Esther}}

=== Physical relics ===
* [http://www1.yadvashem.org/yv/en/exhibitions/vilna/after/artifacts.asp?WT.mc_id=wiki A Megillah (scroll of the Book of Esther)], found in [[Vilna]] after [[World War II]]
* [http://cja.huji.ac.il/browser.php?mode=treefriend&amp;id=318&amp;f=object Esther scrolls in the Bezalel Narkiss Index of Jewish Art], the [[Center for Jewish Art]] at the Hebrew University of Jerusalem.
*[https://web.nli.org.il/sites/NLI/Hebrew/digitallibrary/pages/viewer.aspx?presentorid=MANUSCRIPTS&amp;docid=PNX_MANUSCRIPTS002591641-1|FL44683512 Scroll of the Book of Esther], illustrated, Italy, 1747.

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou | [[Ketuvim|History books]]|||}}
{{S-bef| before = [[Ecclesiastes]] }}
{{S-ttl| title  = [[Tanakh|Hebrew Bible]] }}
{{s-aft | after = [[Book of Daniel|Daniel]] }}
{{S-bef| before = [[Book of Nehemiah|Nehemiah]] }}
{{S-ttl| title  = [[Protestantism|Protestant]]&lt;br&gt;[[Old Testament]] }}
{{s-aft | after = [[Book of Job|Job]] }}
{{S-bef| before = [[Book of Judith|Judith]] | rows = 2 }}
{{S-ttl| title  = [[Roman Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]]&lt;br&gt;[[Old Testament]] }}
{{s-aft | after = [[1 Maccabees]] | rows = 2 }}
{{S-ttl| title  = [[Eastern Orthodox Church|E. Orthodox]]&lt;br&gt;[[Old Testament]] }}
{{s-end}}

{{Books of the Bible}}
{{Purim footer}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Book Of Esther}}
[[Category:4th-century BC books]]
[[Category:Book of Esther| ]]
[[Category:Deuterocanonical books|Esther (parts)]]
[[Category:Esther]]
[[Category:Ketuvim|Esther, Book of]]
[[Category:Purim]]</text>
      <sha1>o8evj8255t7r4ne83qp7z2vudrxlbdi</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
