  <page>
    <title>Baldric</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4353</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937499590</id>
      <parentid>937269836</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-25T12:01:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jandalhandler</username>
        <id>10031342</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* top */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about|the article of clothing||Baldric (disambiguation)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date= July 2012}}
{{wikt | baldric}}

[[Image:BandRegalBaldric.png|thumb|U.S Army band baldric]]
[[Image:AdamclisiMetope.jpg|thumb |A cavalryman wearing a mail shirt with a baldric over his right shoulder, from the Roman ''Tropaeum Traiani'', built 109 AD in the area of present-day Romania.]]
A '''baldric''' (also '''baldrick''', '''bawdrick''', '''bauldrick''' as well as other rare or obsolete variations) is a [[belt (clothing)|belt]] worn over one shoulder that is typically used to carry a weapon (usually a [[sword]]) or other implement such as a [[bugle (instrument)|bugle]] or [[drum]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bartleby.com/61/86/B0038600.html baldric. The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language: Fourth Edition. 2000&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite EB1911 |wstitle= Baldric |volume= 3 |page= 244}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
The word may also refer to any belt in general, but this usage is poetic or archaic. In modern contexts, [[Drum major (military) |military drum majors]] usually wear a baldric.

==History==
Baldrics have been used since ancient times, usually as part of [[military dress]]. The early Islamic Arabs wore baldrics with their armor. The design offers more support for weight than a standard waist belt, without restricting movement of the arms, and while allowing easy access to the object carried.  Alternatively, and especially in modern times, the baldric may fill a ceremonial role rather than a practical one.

==Roman balteus==
During [[Ancient Rome|ancient Roman times]] the '''balteus'''  (plural ''baltei'') was a type of baldric commonly used to suspend a [[gladius|sword]]. It was a belt generally worn over the shoulder, passing obliquely down to the side, typically made of leather, often ornamented with precious stones, metals or both.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/secondary/SMIGRA*/Balteus.html |title=Baʹlteus from a Dictionary of Greek and Roman Antiquities |page=196 |author=William Smith |location=London |year=1875 |accessdate=4 December 2010 |publisher=John Murray }}&lt;/ref&gt; There was also a similar belt worn by the Romans, particularly by soldiers, called a ''cintus'' (pl. ''cinti'') that fastened around the waist. The word ''accintus'' meaning a soldier (literally, &quot;girt&quot; as for battle) attests to this differing usage.

==Today==
Many non-military or paramilitary organisations include baldrics as part of ceremonial dress.  The [[Knights of Columbus]] 4th Degree Colour Corps uses a baldric as part of their uniform;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kofcsupplies.com/ccp0-catshow/4thdegreecolorcorps.html 4th Degree Colour Corps&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.carr.org/~meripper/kofc/assembly/regalia.asp Knights of Columbus, Emblem, Jewels, and Regalia&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071003195319/http://www.carr.org/~meripper/kofc/assembly/regalia.asp |date=3 October 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; it supports a ceremonial sword.
[[File:A_drum_major_of_the_III_Marine_Expeditionary_Forces_Band,_US_Marine_Corp.jpg|thumb|right|A drum major of the United States' III Marine Expeditionary Forces Band is pictured wearing a baldric in 2019]]
[[Image:IlliniDrumline postgame concert 060916.jpg|thumb|left|The Marching Illini Drumline with double baldrics]]
The University of Illinois Marching Illini wore two baldrics as a part of their uniform until 2009, with one over each shoulder. They crossed in the front and back and were buttoned onto the jacket beneath a cape and epaulets.  Today, the current Marching Illini wears one baldric with two sides:  ILLINI is on one side and the traditional orange and white baldric from the previous uniform.

A crossed pair of baldrics is often worn as part of uniform of [[Morris dance]] sides; different colours of baldric help to distinguish different sides.

==In literature and culture==
The baldric appears in the literary canon. Britomart, in [[Edmund Spenser]]'s [[The Faerie Queene|Faerie Queene]], clothes herself in a borrowed armour &quot;with brave bauldrick garnished&quot; before embarking on her quest (Book III, canto iii).  Benedick, from [[William Shakespeare]]'s ''[[Much Ado About Nothing]]'', says &quot;But that I will have a recheat winded in my forehead or hang my bugle in an invisible baldric all women shall pardon me.&quot; A baldric features prominently in Chapter 4 of [[Alexandre Dumas]]' ''[[The Three Musketeers]]''. The yeoman in [[Chaucer]]'s ''[[Canterbury Tales]] ''is described as wearing a &quot;baldrick of bright green.&quot; The baldric of [[Pallas (son of Evander)|Pallas]] plays a key part in the [[Aeneid]], leading Aeneas to kill Turnus. [[Walter Scott]] in ''[[Ivanhoe]]'' published in 1819 describes a Yeoman &quot;with a baldric and a badge of silver&quot;. In ''[[The Fellowship of the Ring]]'', [[Boromir]] is described: &quot;On a baldric he wore a great horn tipped with silver that now was laid upon his knees.&quot; In [[Sir Gawain and the Green Knight]] Gawain returns from his battle with the Green Knight wearing the green girdle &quot;obliquely, like a baldric, bound at his side,/ below his left shoulder, laced in a knot, in betokening the blame he had borne for his fault.&quot;

Some [[Klingon]]s wear baldrics in ''[[Star Trek]]'', such as [[Kor (Star Trek)|Kor]], [[Koloth]], [[Kang (Star Trek)|Kang]] or [[Worf]] although sometimes they are referred to as a [[sash]].  The character Worf does so in almost every one of his appearances through two series and four films.  In ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation|The Next Generation]]'' episode &quot;[[Conundrum (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Conundrum]]&quot;, Worf, due to amnesia, mistakenly believes that the baldric indicates his rank or authority, so he briefly assumes command of the Enterprise.

[[Baldrick]] is a character in the [[BBC]] comedy series ''[[Blackadder]] ''played by [[Tony Robinson]].

A baldrick is also mentioned in the epic poem by Alfred, Lord Tennyson; [http://www.bbc.co.uk/poetryseason/poems/the_lady_of_shalott.shtml The Lady of Shallot]; in the tenth stanza:
'And from his blazon'd baldric slung, A mighty silver bugle hung'

==See also==
{{Portal|Ancient Rome|War}}
*[[Shoulder belt (military)|Shoulder belt]]
*[[Sam Browne belt]]
*[[Bandolier]]
*[[Baldrick|Baldrick (Blackadder character)]]
* [[Webbing]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Ancient Roman legionary equipment]]
[[Category:Military uniforms]]
[[Category:Ancient Roman military clothing]]
[[Category:Belts (clothing)]]

[[fr:Baudrier]]
[[lt:Perpetė]]</text>
      <sha1>86i28f9yk5v3e0b3a64cdxc7gy9uv8o</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
