  <page>
    <title>Beagle</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4368</id>
    <revision>
      <id>931285565</id>
      <parentid>931245088</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-18T02:08:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>RL0919</username>
        <id>327763</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Removing link(s): [[Wikipedia:Articles for deletion/List of dog breeds recognized by the FCI]] closed as delete ([[WP:XFDC|XFDcloser]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{About|the dog breed}}
{{pp-move|small=yes}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{pp-semi|small=yes}}
{{short description|A breed of small scent hound developed primarily for hunting hare}}
{{featured article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2016}}
{{Infobox dog breed
|name=Beagle
|image=Beagle 600.jpg
|image_alt=Beagle image
|image_caption=Tricolor Beagle
|altname=English Beagle
|country=[[England]]
&lt;!-----Traits-----&gt;
|weight       =
|maleweight   = {{convert|22|-|25|lb|kg|abbr=on}}
|femaleweight = {{convert|20|-|23|lb|kg|abbr=on}}
|height       = {{convert|13|-|16|in|cm|abbr=on}}
|maleheight   = 
|femaleheight = 
|coat         = Short haired, hard coat of medium length
|colour        = Tricolor or white in combination with black &amp; tan/brown or brown/tan
|life_span    = 12–15 years
&lt;!-----Classification and standards-----&gt;
|fcigroup   = 6
|fcisection = 1.3 Scenthounds: Small
|fcinum     = 161
|fcistd     = http://www.fci.be/Nomenclature/Standards/161g06-en.pdf
|akcgroup   = Hound
|akcstd     = http://www.akc.org/dog-breeds/beagle/
|ankcgroup  = Group 4 (Hounds)
|ankcstd    = https://web.archive.org/web/20110316145613/http://www.ankc.org.au/Breed_Details.aspx?bid=107
|ckcgroup   = Group 2 – Hounds
|ckcstd     = https://web.archive.org/web/20141205083201/http://www.ckc.ca/en/Files/Forms/Shows-Trials/Breed-Standards/Group-2-Hounds/BAL-Beagle
|kcukgroup  = Hound
|kcukstd    = http://www.thekennelclub.org.uk/services/public/breed/standard.aspx?id=1005
|nzkcgroup  = Hound
|nzkcstd    = http://www.nzkc.org.nz/breed_info/br416.html
|ukcgroup   = Scenthound
|ukcstd     = https://web.archive.org/web/20091015234641/http://www.ukcdogs.com/WebSite.nsf/Breeds/BeagleRevisedJuly12009
&lt;!-----Notes-----&gt;
|note = 
}}&lt;!-- End Infobox --&gt;

The '''beagle''' is a [[Dog breed|breed]] of small [[hound]] that is similar in appearance to the much larger [[foxhound]]. The beagle is a [[scent hound]], developed primarily for [[Tracking (hunting)|hunting]] [[hare]] ([[beagling]]). Possessing a great sense of smell and superior tracking instincts, the beagle is the primary breed used as [[detection dog]]&lt;nowiki/&gt;s for prohibited agricultural imports and foodstuffs in [[quarantine]] around the world. The beagle is intelligent. It is a popular [[Companion dog|pet]] due to its size, good temper, and a lack of [[Dog health#Genetic diseases|inherited health problems]].

The modern breed was developed in [[United Kingdom|Great Britain]] around the 1830s from several breeds, including the [[Talbot (dog)|Talbot Hound]], the [[North Country Beagle]], the [[Southern Hound]], and possibly the [[Harrier (dog)|Harrier]].

Beagles have been depicted in popular culture since [[Elizabethan era|Elizabethan]] times in literature and paintings, and more recently in film, television, and comic books. [[Snoopy]] of the [[comic strip]] ''[[Peanuts]]'' has been called &quot;the world's most famous beagle&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;mostfamousbeagle&quot;&gt;{{Citation |url= https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=OwtaAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=dUsNAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6491,3147272 |accessdate= 31 May 2013 |title= World's Most Famous Beagle |newspaper = [[The Victoria Advocate]] |date= 15 December 1974 |page= 54 |location= [[Victoria, Texas]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
Small hounds are mentioned in the Forest Laws of [[Canute the Great|Canute]] which exempted them from the ordinance which commanded that all dogs capable of running down a [[Deer|stag]] should have one foot mutilated.&lt;ref&gt;Daglish p.7&lt;/ref&gt; If genuine, these laws would confirm that beagle-type dogs were present in England before 1016, but it is likely the laws were written in the [[Middle Ages]] to give a sense of antiquity and tradition to Forest Law.&lt;ref&gt;Rackham p.130&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Southern Hound.jpg|thumb|left|The [[Southern Hound]] is thought to be an ancestor of the beagle]]

In the 11th century, [[William I of England|William the Conqueror]] brought the [[Talbot (dog)|Talbot hound]] to Britain. The Talbot was a predominantly white, slow, deep-throated, scent hound derived from the [[St. Hubert Hound]] which had been developed in the 8th century. At some point the English Talbots were crossed with [[Greyhound]]s to give them an extra turn of speed.&lt;ref&gt;Smith p.209&lt;/ref&gt; Beagles are similar to the [[Harrier (dog)|Harrier]] and the extinct [[Southern Hound]], though smaller and slower.&lt;ref name=&quot;Y110&quot;/&gt;{{Ref label|B|b|none}}

From medieval times, ''beagle'' was used as a generic description for the smaller hounds, though these dogs differed considerably from the modern breed. Miniature breeds of beagle-type dogs were known from the times of [[Edward II of England|Edward II]] and [[Henry VII of England|Henry VII]], who both had packs of Glove Beagles, so named since they were small enough to fit on a glove, and [[Elizabeth I of England|Queen Elizabeth I]] kept a breed known as a Pocket Beagle, which stood {{convert|8|to|9|in|cm}} at the shoulder. Small enough to fit in a &quot;pocket&quot; or saddlebag, they rode along on the hunt. The larger hounds would run the prey to ground, then the hunters would release the small dogs to continue the chase through underbrush. Elizabeth I referred to the dogs as her ''singing beagles'' and often entertained guests at her royal table by letting her Pocket Beagles cavort amid their plates and cups.&lt;ref name=&quot;J1858&quot;&gt;Jesse (1858) pp.438–9&lt;/ref&gt; 19th-century sources refer to these breeds interchangeably and it is possible that the two names refer to the same small variety. In George Jesse's ''Researches into the History of the British Dog'' from 1866, the early 17th-century poet and writer [[Gervase Markham]] is quoted referring to the beagle as small enough to sit on a man's hand and to the: {{quote|little small mitten-beagle, which may be companion for a ladies kirtle, and in the field will run as cunningly as any hound whatere, only their musick is very small like reeds.&lt;ref&gt;G. Jesse vol II, pp.223–232&lt;/ref&gt;}} Standards for the Pocket Beagle were drawn up as late as 1901; these genetic lines are now extinct, although modern breeders have attempted to recreate the variety.&lt;ref name=&quot;PB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://clubs.akc.org/NBC/NBC_FAQs.html#24.|title=What is a Pocket Beagle?|publisher=American Kennel Club|accessdate=9 July 2007| archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070609070137/http://clubs.akc.org/NBC/NBC_FAQs.html| archivedate = 9 June 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Beagle ancient.jpg|thumb|right|This image from the turn of the 19th century shows a dog with a heavier body and lacking the features of later strains.]]

By the 18th century two breeds had been developed for hunting hare and rabbit: the [[Southern Hound]] and the [[North Country Beagle]] (or Northern Hound). The Southern Hound, a tall, heavy dog with a square head, and long, soft ears, was common from south of the [[River Trent]] and probably closely related to the [[Talbot (dog)|Talbot Hound]]. Though slow, it had stamina and an excellent scenting ability. The North Country Beagle, possibly a cross between an offshoot of the Talbot stock and a Greyhound, was bred chiefly in [[Yorkshire]] and was common in the northern counties. It was smaller than the Southern Hound, less heavy-set and with a more pointed muzzle. It was faster than its southern counterpart but its scenting abilities were less well developed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=The fox-hound, and fox-hunting|journal=The New Sporting Magazine|publisher=Baldwin and Craddock|year=1833|volume=4|page=164}}&lt;/ref&gt; As [[fox hunting]] became increasingly popular, numbers of both types of hound diminished. The beagle-type dogs were crossed with larger breeds such as Stag Hounds to produce the modern [[English Foxhound|Foxhound]]. The beagle-size varieties came close to extinction but some farmers in the South ensured the survival of the prototype breeds by maintaining small [[rabbit-hunting]] packs.

===Development of the modern breed===
Reverend Phillip Honeywood established a beagle pack in [[Essex]] in the 1830s and it is believed that this pack formed the basis for the modern breed. Although details of the pack's lineage are not recorded it is thought that North Country Beagles and Southern Hounds were strongly represented; [[William Youatt]] suspected that [[Harrier (dog)|Harriers]] formed a good majority of the beagle's bloodline, but the origin of the Harrier is itself obscure.&lt;ref name=&quot;Y110&quot;&gt;Youatt. p.110&lt;/ref&gt; Honeywood's Beagles were small, standing at about {{convert|10|in|cm}} at the shoulder, and pure white according to John Mills (writing in ''The Sportsman's Library'' in 1845). [[Albert, Prince Consort|Prince Albert]] and [[Edward Turnour, 4th Earl Winterton|Lord Winterton]] also had Beagle packs around this time, and royal favour no doubt led to some revival of interest in the breed, but Honeywood's pack was regarded as the finest of the three.&lt;ref&gt;Mills p.172&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:4-beagles.jpg|thumb|right|Early images of the Beagle (clockwise from top left): 1833, 1835, [[John Henry Walsh|Stonehenge]]'s Medium (1859, reusing [[William Youatt|Youatt]]'s 1852 &quot;Beagle&quot; image) and Dwarf Beagle (1859).]]

Although credited with the development of the modern breed, Honeywood concentrated on producing dogs for hunting and it was left to Thomas Johnson to refine the breeding to produce dogs that were both attractive and capable hunters. Two strains were developed: the rough- and smooth-coated varieties. The rough-coated beagle survived until the beginning of the 20th century, and there were even records of one making an appearance at a dog show as late as 1969, but this variety is now extinct, having probably been absorbed into the standard beagle bloodline.&lt;ref name=&quot;K7&quot;&gt;Kraeuter p.7&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1840s, a standard beagle type was beginning to develop; the distinction between the North Country Beagle and Southern Hound had been lost, but there was still a large variation in size, character, and reliability among the emerging packs.&lt;ref&gt;Scott pp.75–8&lt;/ref&gt; In 1856, &quot;Stonehenge&quot; (the pseudonym of [[John Henry Walsh]]), writing in the ''Manual of British Rural Sports'', was still dividing beagles into four varieties: the medium beagle; the dwarf or lapdog beagle; the fox beagle (a smaller, slower version of the Foxhound); and the rough-coated or terrier beagle, which he classified as a cross between any of the other varieties and one of the Scottish [[terrier]] breeds.&lt;ref name=&quot;S98&quot;&gt;&quot;Stonehenge&quot; pp.98–9&lt;/ref&gt; Stonehenge also gives the start of a standard description:

{{quote|In size the beagle measures from 10 inches, or even less, to 15. In shape they resemble the old southern hound in miniature, but with more neatness and beauty; and they also resemble that hound in style of hunting.&lt;ref name=&quot;S98&quot; /&gt;}}

By 1887 the threat of extinction was on the wane: there were 18 beagle packs in England.&lt;ref name=&quot;K9&quot;&gt;Krauter p.9&lt;/ref&gt; The Beagle Club was formed in 1890 and the first standard drawn up at the same time.&lt;ref name=&quot;A12&quot;&gt;Arnold p.12&lt;/ref&gt; The following year the Association of Masters of Harriers and Beagles was formed. Both organisations aimed to further the best interests of the breed, and both were keen to produce a standard type of beagle.&lt;ref&gt;Daglish p.9&lt;/ref&gt; By 1902, the number of packs had risen to 44.&lt;ref name=&quot;K9&quot; /&gt;

===Export===
Beagles were in the United States by the 1840s at the latest, but the first dogs were imported strictly for hunting and were of variable quality. Since Honeywood had only started breeding in the 1830s, it is unlikely these dogs were representative of the modern breed and the description of them as looking like straight-legged [[Dachshund]]s with weak heads has little resemblance to the standard. Serious attempts at establishing a quality bloodline began in the early 1870s when General [[Richard Rowett]] from [[Illinois]] imported some dogs from England and began breeding. Rowett's Beagles are believed to have formed the models for the first American standard, drawn up by Rowett, L. H. Twadell, and Norman Ellmore in 1887.&lt;ref&gt;Arnold p.14&lt;/ref&gt; The beagle was accepted as a breed by the [[American Kennel Club]] (AKC) in 1885.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.akc.org/breeds/beagle/index.cfm |title=Get to know the Beagle |publisher=American Kennel Club |accessdate=29 April 2014 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140330133037/http://www.akc.org/breeds/beagle/index.cfm |archivedate=30 March 2014 |url-status=dead |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 20th century the breed has spread worldwide.

===Birth and Reproduction===
The average size of a beagle litter is six puppies. When mother beagles give birth to litters of puppies, the little pups weigh just a few ounces each.&lt;ref&gt;https://pets.thenest.com/newborn-beagle-puppy-information-12444.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Popularity==

[[Image:Beagle Upsy.jpg|thumb|right|An attractive uniform type for the breed developed at the start of the 20th century]]

On its formation, the Association of Masters of Harriers and Beagles took over the running of a regular show at [[Peterborough]] that had started in 1889, and the Beagle Club in the UK held its first show in 1896.&lt;ref name=&quot;A12&quot; /&gt; The regular showing of the breed led to the development of a uniform type, and the beagle continued to prove a success up until the outbreak of [[World War I]] when all shows were suspended. After the war, the breed was again struggling for survival in the UK: the last of the Pocket Beagles was probably lost during this time, and registrations fell to an all-time low. A few breeders (notably Reynalton Kennels) managed to revive interest in the dog and by [[World War II]], the breed was once again doing well. Registrations dropped again after the end of the war but almost immediately recovered.&lt;ref&gt;Daglish pp.10–12&lt;/ref&gt;

As purebred dogs, beagles have always been more popular in the United States and Canada than in their native country England. The National Beagle Club of America was formed in 1888 and by 1901 a beagle had won a Best in Show title. As in the UK, activity during World War I was minimal, but the breed showed a much stronger revival in the U.S. when hostilities ceased. In 1928 it won a number of prizes at the [[Westminster Kennel Club]]'s show and by 1939 a beagle – Champion Meadowlark Draughtsman – had captured the title of top-winning American-bred dog for the year.&lt;ref&gt;Arnold pp.14–5&lt;/ref&gt;  On 12 February 2008, a beagle, [[K-Run's Park Me In First|K-Run's Park Me In First (Uno)]], won the Best In Show category at the Westminster Kennel Club show for the first time in the competition's history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=20601088&amp;sid=aS4PHV8NjOW8|title=Beagle Breakthrough: Westminster Crowd Favorite Uno Is Top Dog|publisher=Bloomberg|date=12 February 2008|accessdate=13 February 2008|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080413162716/http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=20601088|archivedate=13 April 2008|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; In North America they have been consistently in the top-ten most-popular breeds for over 30 years. From 1953 to 1959 the beagle was ranked No. 1 on the list of the [[American Kennel Club]]'s registered breeds;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.akc.org/pdfs/press_center/popular_pooches.pdf|title=AKC Registration Statistics|publisher=American Kennel Club|year=2006|accessdate=11 July 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; in 2005 and 2006 it ranked 5th out of the 155 breeds registered.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.akc.org/reg/dogreg_stats.cfm|title=AKC Breed Registration Statistics|publisher=American Kennel Club|year=2006|accessdate=11 July 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070716173939/http://www.akc.org/reg/dogreg_stats.cfm| archivedate= 16 July 2007 | url-status= dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the UK they are not quite so popular, placing 28th and 30th in the rankings of registrations with the Kennel Club in 2005 and 2006 respectively.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thekennelclub.org.uk/cgi-bin/item.cgi?id=926&amp;d=pg_dtl_art_news&amp;h=242&amp;f=0|title=Registration statistics for all recognised dog breeds – 2005 and 2006|publisher=The Kennel Club|accessdate=9 July 2007|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070628220058/http://www.thekennelclub.org.uk/cgi-bin/item.cgi?id=926&amp;d=pg_dtl_art_news&amp;h=242&amp;f=0|archivedate=28 June 2007|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States the beagle ranked 4th most popular breed in 2012 and 2013, behind the [[Labrador Retriever]] (#1), [[German Shepherd]] (#2) and [[Golden Retriever]] (#3) breeds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.akc.org/reg/dogreg_stats.cfm |title=American Kennel Club 2013 Dog Registration Statistics Historical Comparisons &amp; Notable Trends |publisher=American Kennel Club |accessdate=29 April 2014 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140405102213/http://www.akc.org/reg/dogreg_stats.cfm |archivedate=5 April 2014 |url-status=dead |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Name==
According to the ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'', the first mention of the beagle by name in English literature dates from c. 1475 in ''[[The Squire of Low Degree]]''. The origin of the word &quot;beagle&quot; is uncertain, although it has been suggested that the word derives from the French ''begueule''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/16481?rskey=OXzGmu&amp;result=1#eid |title=Beagle |accessdate=3 October 2016 |work=Oxford English Dictionary |url-access=subscription }}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is not known why the black and tan [[Kerry Beagle]], present in Ireland since [[Celt]]ic times, has the ''beagle'' description, since at {{convert|22|to|24|in|cm}} it is significantly taller than the modern day beagle, and in earlier times was even larger. Some writers suggest that the beagle's scenting ability may have come from cross-breeding earlier strains with the Kerry Beagle. Originally used for hunting stags, it is today used for hare and [[drag hunting]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thebreedsofdogs.com/KERRY_BEAGLE.htm|title=Kerry Beagle |publisher=Breeds of Dog |accessdate=9 July 2007 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070813223627/http://www.thebreedsofdogs.com/KERRY_BEAGLE.htm |archivedate=13 August 2007 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Appearance==
[[Image:Beagle portrait Camry.jpg|thumb|left|The Kennel Club (UK) standard states the beagle should give the impression of quality without coarseness.]]

The general appearance of the beagle resembles a miniature [[Foxhound]], but the head is broader and the muzzle shorter, the expression completely different and the legs shorter in proportion to the body.&lt;ref&gt;Daglish p.37&lt;/ref&gt;  They are generally between {{convert|13|and|16|in|cm}} high at the [[withers]] and weigh between {{convert|18|and|35|lb|kg|abbr=on}}, with females being slightly smaller than males on average.&lt;ref&gt;Rice p.147&lt;/ref&gt;

They have a smooth, somewhat domed [[skull]] with a medium-length, square-cut [[snout|muzzle]] and a black (or occasionally liver) gumdrop nose. The jaw is strong and the teeth scissor together with the upper teeth fitting perfectly over the lower teeth and both sets aligned square to the jaw. The eyes are large, hazel or brown, with a mild hound-like pleading look. The large ears are long, soft and low-set, turning towards the cheeks slightly and rounded at the tips. Beagles have a strong, medium-length neck (which is long enough for them to easily bend to the ground to pick up a scent), with little folding in the skin but some evidence of a [[dewlap]]; a broad chest narrowing to a tapered [[abdomen]] and waist and a long, slightly curved tail (known as the &quot;stern&quot;) tipped with white. The white tip, known as the flag. has been selectively bred for, as it allows the dog to be easily seen when its head is down following a scent.&lt;ref name=&quot;QLD&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.beagleclubqld.org/documents/booklet.pdf|title=What you need to know about Beagles|publisher=The Beagle Club of Queensland|accessdate=14 October 2011|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110925110905/http://www.beagleclubqld.org/documents/booklet.pdf|archivedate=25 September 2011|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; The tail does not curl over the back, but is held upright when the dog is active. The beagle has a muscular body and a medium-length, smooth, hard coat. The front legs are straight and carried under the body while the rear legs are muscular and well bent at the [[Stifle joint|stifles]].&lt;ref&gt;See various breed standards linked from the breed box at the top of the article.&lt;/ref&gt;

The tricolored beagle{{mdash}}white with large black areas and light brown shading{{mdash}}is the most common.  Tricolored beagles occur in a number of shades, from the &quot;Classic Tri&quot; with a jet black saddle (also known as &quot;Blackback&quot;), to the &quot;Dark Tri&quot; (where faint brown markings are intermingled with more prominent black markings), to the &quot;Faded Tri&quot; (where faint black markings are intermingled with more prominent brown markings). Some tricolored dogs have a broken pattern, sometimes referred to as ''pied''. These dogs have mostly white coats with patches of black and brown hair. Tricolor beagles are almost always born black and white. The white areas are typically set by eight weeks, but the black areas may fade to brown as the puppy matures.  (The brown may take between one and two years to fully develop.) Some beagles gradually change color during their lives, and may lose their black markings entirely.
[[File:Beagle-Farben.jpg|thumb|Beagle hound colors: Two-colored &quot;tan and white&quot; (older female with fading color), tricolored broken, two-colored &quot;red and white&quot;, &quot;tricoloured&quot;]]
Two-color varieties always have a white base color with areas of the second color. Tan and white is the most common two-color variety, but there is a wide range of other colors including lemon, a very light tan; red, a reddish, almost orange, brown; and liver, a darker brown, and black. Liver is not common and is not permitted in some standards; it tends to occur with yellow eyes. Ticked or mottled varieties may be either white or black with different colored flecks (''ticking''), such as the blue-mottled or bluetick beagle, which has spots that appear to be a midnight-blue color, similar to the coloring of the [[Bluetick Coonhound]]. Some tricolor beagles also have ticking of various colors in their white areas.&lt;ref&gt;Daglish p.44&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://clubs.akc.org/NBC/beagle_colors.htm|title=Beagle Colors|publisher=American Kennel Club|accessdate=9 July 2007| archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070629065433/http://clubs.akc.org/NBC/beagle_colors.htm| archivedate = 29 June 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sense of smell==
Alongside the [[Bloodhound]] and [[Basset Hound]], the beagle has one of the best developed senses of smell of any dog.&lt;ref name=&quot;F40&quot;&gt;Fogle p.40&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1950s, John Paul Scott and John Fuller began a 13-year study of canine behavior. As part of this research, they tested the scenting abilities of various breeds by putting a mouse in a one-[[acre]] field and timing how long it took the dogs to find it. The beagles found it in less than a minute, while [[Fox Terrier]]s took 15 minutes and [[Scottish Terrier]]s failed to find it at all. Beagles are better at ground-scenting (following a trail on the ground) than they are at air-scenting, and for this reason they have been excluded from most [[mountain rescue]] teams in favor of [[collie]]s, which use sight in addition to air-scenting and are more biddable.&lt;ref name=&quot;F40&quot; /&gt; The long ears and large lips of the beagle probably assist in trapping the scents close to the nose.&lt;ref&gt;Fogle p.173&lt;/ref&gt;

==Variations==

===Breed varieties===
The [[American Kennel Club]] recognizes two separate varieties of beagle: the 13-inch for hounds less than {{convert|13|in|cm}}, and the 15-inch for those between {{convert|13|and|15|in|cm}}. The [[Canadian Kennel Club]] recognizes a single type, with a height not exceeding {{convert|15|in|cm}}.  The [[Kennel Club (UK)]] and [[Fédération Cynologique Internationale|FCI]] affiliated clubs recognize a single type, with a height of between {{convert|13|and|16|in|cm}}.

[[Image:BraxtonPuggle-edit1.jpg|thumb|right|A [[Puggle]], a beagle/pug cross, shows traits from both breeds.]]

English and American varieties are sometimes mentioned. However, there is no official recognition from any Kennel Club for this distinction. Beagles fitting the American Kennel Club standard – which disallows animals over {{convert|15|in|cm}} – are smaller on average than those fitting the Kennel Club standard which allows heights up to {{convert|16|in|cm}}.

Pocket Beagles are sometimes advertised for sale but while the UK Kennel Club originally specified a standard for the Pocket Beagle in 1901, the variety is now not recognized by any Kennel Club.
  
A strain known as Patch Hounds was developed by Willet Randall and his family from 1896 specifically for their rabbit hunting ability. They trace their bloodline back to Field Champion Patch, but do not necessarily have a patchwork marking.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Rabbit hunting |author=Fisher, Dave |publisher=Woods N' Water, Inc |year=2002 |isbn=0-9707493-6-8 |pages=22–23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.lanelinebeagles.zoomshare.com/files/Willet_Randall_His_Patch_Hounds.pdf | title=Randall. The Patch Era at Beaver Meadows | author=Libby, Ray | url-status=dead | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111114013624/http://lanelinebeagles.zoomshare.com/files/Willet_Randall_His_Patch_Hounds.pdf | archivedate=14 November 2011 | df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Crossbreeds===
In the 1850s, Stonehenge recommended a cross between a Beagle and a [[Scottish Terrier]] as a retriever. He found the [[crossbreed]] to be a good worker, silent and obedient, but it had the drawback that it was small and could barely carry a hare.&lt;ref&gt;Stonehenge p.46&lt;/ref&gt;

More recently the trend has been for &quot;[[dog crossbreeds|designer dogs]]&quot; and one of the most popular has been the Beagle/[[Pug]] cross known as a [[Puggle]]. Some puppies of this cross are less excitable than a Beagle and with a lower exercise requirement, similar to the Pug parent; but many are highly excitable and require vigorous exercise.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,174475,00.html |title=Designer Dogs: Meet the Puggle |author=Raakhee Mirchandani |publisher=Fox News |date=4 November 2005 |accessdate=9 July 2007 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070629093827/http://www.foxnews.com/story/0%2C2933%2C174475%2C00.html |archivedate=29 June 2007 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;br /&gt;* {{cite web |url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2006/05/21/sunday/main1638400.shtml |title=Designing A Cuter Dog |publisher=CBS |date=6 August 2006 |accessdate=9 July 2007 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070701045342/http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2006/05/21/sunday/main1638400.shtml |archivedate=1 July 2007 |url-status=live }}&lt;br /&gt;*
{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/4684770.stm |title=Stars fuel designer dogs fashion |work=BBC News |date=6 February 2006 |accessdate=9 July 2007 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070716025222/http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/4684770.stm |archivedate=16 July 2007 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Temperament==
[[Image:BeagleNiniJule.jpg|thumb|left|Beagles are happy to rest without being exercised to exhaustion.|194x194px]]

The beagle has an even temper and gentle disposition. Described in several breed standards as &quot;merry&quot;, they are amiable and typically neither aggressive nor timid, although this depends on the individual. They enjoy company, and although they may initially be standoffish with strangers, they are easily won over. They make poor [[guard dogs]] for this reason, although their tendency to bark or howl when confronted with the unfamiliar makes them good watch dogs. In a 1985 study conducted by Ben and Lynette Hart, the beagle was given the highest excitability rating, along with the [[Yorkshire Terrier]], [[Cairn Terrier]], [[Miniature Schnauzer]], [[West Highland White Terrier]], and [[Fox Terrier]].&lt;ref&gt;Fogle pp.176–7&lt;/ref&gt;{{Ref label|C|c|none}}

Beagles are intelligent but, as a result of being bred for the long chase, are single-minded and determined, which can make them hard to train. They can be difficult to recall once they have picked up a scent, and are easily distracted by smells around them. They do not generally feature in obedience trials; while they are alert, respond well to food-reward training, and are eager to please, they are easily bored or distracted. They are ranked 72nd in [[Stanley Coren]]'s ''[[The Intelligence of Dogs]]'', as Coren places them among the group with the lowest degree of working/obedience intelligence. Coren's scale, however, does not assess understanding, independence, or creativity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://petrix.com/dogint/70-79.html | title=The Intelligence of Dogs. Ranks 70 to 79 | work=Ranking of Dogs for Obedience/Working Intelligence by Breed | accessdate=26 October 2011 | url-status=dead | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111024040905/http://petrix.com/dogint/70-79.html | archivedate=24 October 2011 | df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/canine-corner/200907/canine-intelligence-breed-does-matter |title=Canine Intelligence—Breed Does Matter |work=Canine Corner. The human-animal bond |publisher=Psychology Today |author=Stanley Coren |date=15 July 2009 | accessdate=26 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Young beagle at rest.jpg|thumb|A beagle at rest]]
Beagles are excellent with children and this is one of the reasons they have become popular family pets. But as beagles are pack animals, they are prone to [[separation anxiety in dogs|separation anxiety]],&lt;ref&gt;Kraeuter pp.77–8&lt;/ref&gt; a condition which causes them to destroy things when left unattended.  Not all beagles will howl, but most will bark when confronted with strange situations, and some will bay (also referred to as &quot;speaking&quot;, &quot;giving tongue&quot;, or &quot;opening&quot;) when they catch the scent of potential quarry.&lt;ref&gt;Kraeuter pp.96&lt;/ref&gt; They also generally get along well with cats and other dogs. They are not too demanding with regard to exercise; their inbred stamina means they do not easily tire when exercised, but they also do not need to be worked to exhaustion before they will rest. Regular exercise helps ward off the weight gain to which the breed is prone.&lt;ref&gt;Daglish p.55&lt;/ref&gt;

==Health==
[[Image:Beagles Puppies.png|right|thumbnail|Day-old beagle puppies]]

The typical longevity of beagles is 12–15 years,&lt;ref name=&quot;Cassidy Data&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://users.pullman.com/lostriver/breeddata.htm|title=Dog Longevity: Breed Longevity Data|author=K. M. Cassidy|year=2007|accessdate=21 July 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070717143605/http://users.pullman.com/lostriver/breeddata.htm| archivedate= 17 July 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; which is a common lifespan for dogs of their size.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cassidy Weight&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://users.pullman.com/lostriver/weight_and_lifespan.htm|title=Dog Longevity: Breed Weight and Lifespan|author=K. M. Cassidy|year=2007|accessdate=21 July 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070714125150/http://users.pullman.com/lostriver/weight_and_lifespan.htm| archivedate= 14 July 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Beagles may be prone to [[epilepsy]], but this can often be controlled with medication. [[Hypothyroidism]] and a number of types of [[dwarfism]] occur in beagles. Two conditions in particular are unique to the breed: &quot;Funny Puppy&quot;, in which the puppy is slow to develop and eventually develops weak legs, a crooked back and although normally healthy, is prone to a range of illnesses;&lt;ref name=&quot;Probs&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://clubs.akc.org/NBC/beagle_health_problems.htm|title=Beagle Health Problems|publisher=American Kennel Club|accessdate=9 July 2007| archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070611181229/http://clubs.akc.org/NBC/beagle_health_problems.htm| archivedate = 11 June 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Musladin-Lueke Syndrome (MLS) in which the eyes are slanted and the outer toes are underdeveloped but otherwise development is as normal.&lt;ref name=thebeagleclub1&gt;{{cite web|publisher=The Beagle Club|url=http://www.thebeagleclub.org/users/UserFiles/File/The%20Beagle-health%20leaflet%202018%20Final%20Version2.pdf|title=The Beagle - a Healthy Breed|date=Jun 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hip dysplasia (canine)|Hip dysplasia]], common in Harriers and in some larger breeds, is rarely considered a problem in beagles.&lt;ref&gt;Rice p.161&lt;/ref&gt; Beagles are considered a [[chondrodystrophy|chondrodystrophic]] breed, meaning that they are prone to types of disk diseases.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.spinejournal.com/pt/re/spine/abstract.00007632-200605010-00005.htm;jsessionid=L2pTpfpWkgBFWsmLcwG6hQ6Qv3pwkvpgnK2Gxpz06bnGwSgLNBmH!-815685239!181195629!8091!-1 |title=Spine – Abstract: Volume 31(10) May 1, 2006 p 1094-1099 Notochord Cells Regulate Intervertebral Disc Chondrocyte Proteoglycan Production and Cell Proliferation |publisher=Spinejournal.com |accessdate=3 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Beagle 745.jpg|thumb|Weight gain can be a problem in older or sedentary dogs, which in turn can lead to heart and joint problems.]]

In rare cases, beagles may develop [[immune mediated polygenic arthritis]] (where the immune system attacks the joints) even at a young age. The symptoms can sometimes be relieved by [[Corticosteroid#Uses|steroid]] treatments.&lt;ref name=&quot;Probs&quot; /&gt; Another rare disease in the breed is neonatal [[Cerebellar abiotrophy|cerebellar cortical degeneration]]. Affected puppies are slow, have lower co-ordination, fall more often and don't have a normal gait. It has an estimated carrier rate of 5% and affected rate of 0.1%. A genetic test is available.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Neonatal Cerebellar Cortical Degeneration|url=http://www.aht.org.uk/cms-display/genetics_nccd.html|publisher=Animal Health Trust|accessdate=13 May 2013|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130323150342/http://www.aht.org.uk/cms-display/genetics_nccd.html|archive-date=23 March 2013|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Frequency of the neonatal cerebellar cortical degeneration (NCCD) mutations in beagles in the UK|url=http://www.aht.org.uk/skins/Default/pdfs/NCCD_Frequency_Report.pdf|publisher=Kennel Club Genetics Centre at the Animal Health Trust|accessdate=13 May 2013|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141006134215/http://www.aht.org.uk/skins/Default/pdfs/NCCD_Frequency_Report.pdf|archive-date=6 October 2014|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Their long floppy ears can mean that the inner ear does not receive a substantial air flow or that moist air becomes trapped, and this can lead to ear infections. Beagles may also be affected by a range of eye problems; two common ophthalmic conditions in beagles are [[Canine glaucoma|glaucoma]] and [[Corneal dystrophies in dogs|corneal dystrophy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor=Gelatt, Kirk N.|title=Veterinary Ophthalmology|edition=3rd|publisher=Lippincott, Williams &amp; Wilkins|year=1999|pages=656, 718|isbn=0-683-30076-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;[[Cherry eye]]&quot;, a prolapse of the gland of the [[third eyelid]], and [[distichiasis]], a condition in which eyelashes grow into the eye causing irritation, sometimes exist; both these conditions can be corrected with surgery.&lt;ref name=&quot;Probs&quot; /&gt; They can suffer from several types of [[retinal atrophy]]. Failure of the nasolacrimal drainage system can cause dry eye or leakage of tears onto the face.&lt;ref name=&quot;Probs&quot; /&gt;

As field dogs they are prone to minor injuries such as cuts and sprains, and, if inactive, obesity is a common problem as they will eat whenever food is available and rely on their owners to regulate their weight.&lt;ref name=&quot;Probs&quot; /&gt; When working or running free they are also likely to pick up parasites such as [[flea]]s, [[tick]]s, [[harvest mite]]s, and [[tapeworm]]s, and irritants such as grass seeds can become trapped in their eyes, soft ears, or paws.&lt;ref&gt;Rice pp.167–74&lt;/ref&gt;

Beagles may exhibit a behaviour known as [[reverse sneezing]], in which they sound as if they are choking or gasping for breath, but are actually drawing air in through the mouth and nose. The exact cause of this behaviour is not known, but it can be a common occurrence and is not harmful to the dog.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.beagleclubvictoria.com/faq.asp|title=FAQ|publisher=Beagle Club of Victoria|accessdate=9 July 2007|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070804125149/http://www.beagleclubvictoria.com/faq.asp |archivedate=4 August 2007|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Hunting==
{{Main|Beagling}}
[[Image:Caynsham-beagles.jpg|thumb|right|The Caynsham Foot Beagles (c. 1885)]]

Beagles were developed primarily for hunting hare, an activity known as [[beagling]]. They were seen as ideal hunting companions for the elderly who could follow on horseback without exerting themselves, for young hunters who could keep up with them on ponies, and for the poorer hunters who could not afford to maintain a stable of good hunting horses.&lt;ref&gt;Maxwell p.42&lt;/ref&gt; Before the advent of the fashion for foxhunting in the 19th century, hunting was an all day event where the enjoyment was derived from the chase rather than the kill. In this setting the tiny beagle was well matched to the hare, as unlike Harriers they would not quickly finish the hunt, but because of their excellent scent-tracking skills and stamina they were almost guaranteed to eventually catch the hare. The beagle packs would run closely together (&quot;so close that they might be covered with a sheet&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Y110&quot; /&gt;) which was useful in a long hunt, as it prevented stray dogs from obscuring the trail. In thick undergrowth they were also preferred to [[spaniel]]s when hunting [[pheasant]].&lt;ref&gt;Blakey p.77&lt;/ref&gt;

With the fashion for faster hunts, the beagle fell out of favour for chasing hare, but was still employed for rabbit hunting. In ''Anecdotes of Dogs'' (1846), [[Edward Jesse]] says:

{{quote|In rabbit-shooting, in gorse and thick cover, nothing can be more cheerful than the beagle. They also are easily heard over long distances and in thick cover. They have been called rabbit-beagles from this employment, for which they are peculiarly qualified, especially those dogs which are somewhat wire-haired.&lt;ref name=&quot;J1858&quot; /&gt;}}[[Image:Moritz v d Tomburg.jpg|thumb|left|The Beagle has been used for rabbit-hunting since the earliest development of the breed.]]

In the United States they appear to have been employed chiefly for hunting rabbits from the earliest imports.
Hunting hare with beagles became popular again in Britain in the mid-19th century and continued until it was made illegal in Scotland by the [[Protection of Wild Mammals (Scotland) Act 2002]] and in England and Wales by the [[Hunting Act 2004]]. Under this legislation beagles may still pursue rabbits with the [[landowner]]'s permission. [[Drag hunting]] is popular where hunting is no longer permitted or for those owners who do not wish to participate in hunting a live animal, but still wish to exercise their dog's innate skills.

The traditional foot pack consists of up to 40 beagles, marshaled by a Huntsman who directs the pack and who is assisted by a variable number of whippers-in whose job is to return straying hounds to the pack. The Master of the Hunt is in overall day-to-day charge of the pack, and may or may not take on the role of Huntsman on the day of the hunt.

As hunting with beagles was seen as ideal for young people, many of the British [[Independent school (UK)|public schools]] traditionally maintained beagle packs. Protests were lodged against [[Eton College|Eton's]] use of beagles for hunting as early as 1902 but the pack is still in existence today,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Henry Salt: Humanitarian Reformer and Man of Letters|first=George|last=Hendrick|year=1977|publisher=University of Illinois Press|isbn=0-252-00611-9|pages=[https://archive.org/details/henrysalthumanit0000hend/page/68 68–71]|url=https://archive.org/details/henrysalthumanit0000hend/page/68}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a pack used by [[Wye College|Imperial College]] in [[Wye, Kent]] was stolen by the [[Animal Liberation Front]] in 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/1103181.stm |title=Activists steal beagle pack|work=BBC News|date=5 January 2001|accessdate=4 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; School and university packs are still maintained by Eton, [[Marlborough College|Marlborough]], Wye, [[Radley College|Radley]], the [[Royal Agricultural University]] and [[Christ Church, Oxford]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.horseandhound.co.uk/best/article.php?aid=71052&amp;cid=396|title=Directory of UK hunts 2006/2007|publisher=Horse and Hound|date=20 November 2006|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071006200749/http://www.horseandhound.co.uk/best/article.php?aid=71052&amp;cid=396|archivedate=6 October 2007|url-status=dead|access-date=9 July 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to organized beagling, beagles have been used for hunting or flushing to guns (often in pairs) a wide range of game including [[snowshoe hare]], [[cottontail rabbit]]s, [[game bird]]s, [[roe deer]], [[red deer]], [[bobcat]], [[coyote]], [[wild boar]] and foxes, and have even been recorded as being used to hunt [[stoat]].&lt;ref name=&quot;K101&quot;&gt;Kraeuter pp.97–104&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.defra.gov.uk/rural/hunting/inquiry/evidence/mammalsoc.htm|archive-url=http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20100512151544/http://www.defra.gov.uk/rural/hunting/inquiry/evidence/mammalsoc.htm|url-status=dead|archive-date=12 May 2010|title=Submission to Lord Burns' Committee of Inquiry into Hunting with Dogs|publisher=The Mammal Society|date=16 March 2000|accessdate=11 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In most of these cases, the beagle is employed as a gun dog, flushing game for hunter's guns.&lt;ref name=&quot;K101&quot; /&gt;

==Detection==
[[Image:CBP Airport.jpg|thumb|Beagles have excellent noses; this dog is employed by the US Customs and Border Protection Agency.]]

Beagles are used as detection dogs in the [[Beagle Brigade]] of the [[United States Department of Agriculture]]. These dogs are used to detect food items in luggage being taken into the United States. After trialling several breeds, beagles were chosen because they are relatively small and unintimidating for people who are uncomfortable around dogs, easy to care for, intelligent and work well for rewards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aphis.usda.gov/lpa/pubs/detdog2.html|title=USDA's Detector Dogs: Protecting American Agriculture: Why Beagles?|publisher=United States Department of Agriculture: Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service|accessdate=2 February 2007|archivedate=2 February 2007|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070202083721/http://www.aphis.usda.gov/lpa/pubs/detdog2.html|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; They are also used for this purpose in a number of other countries including by the [[Ministry of Agriculture and Forestry (New Zealand)|Ministry of Agriculture and Forestry]] in New Zealand, the [[Australian Quarantine and Inspection Service]], and in Canada, Japan and the People's Republic of China.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.people.com.cn/200512/06/eng20051206_226039.html|title=A beagle honored as a defender at national gate|publisher=People's Daily Online|date=6 December 2006|accessdate=9 July 2007}}&lt;br /&gt;* {{cite web|url=http://www.daff.gov.au/about/media-centre/dept-releases/2000/old_dogs_-_new_tricks_original_quarantine_k9s_on_the_scent_of_retirement|title=Old dogs&amp;nbsp;— new tricks Original quarantine K9's on the scent of retirement|publisher=Australian Government: Department of Agriculture, Fisheries and Forestry|date=30 November 2000|accessdate=9 November 2011|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120331055356/http://www.daff.gov.au/about/media-centre/dept-releases/2000/old_dogs_-_new_tricks_original_quarantine_k9s_on_the_scent_of_retirement|archivedate=31 March 2012|df=dmy-all}}&lt;br /&gt;* {{cite web|url=http://www.daff.gov.au/__data/assets/pdf_file/0009/111969/nairn_report.pdf|title=Australian Quarantine a shared responsibility|author1=M.E. Nairn|author2=P.G. Allen|author3=A.R. Inglis|author4=C. Tanner|publisher=Department of Primary Industries and Energy|year=1996|accessdate=9 July 2007|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070710215222/http://www.daff.gov.au/__data/assets/pdf_file/0009/111969/nairn_report.pdf|archivedate=10 July 2007|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Larger breeds are generally used for detection of explosives as this often involves climbing over luggage and on large conveyor belts, work for which the smaller Beagle is not suited.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aphis.usda.gov/lpa/pubs/detdog6.html|title=USDA's Detector Dogs: Protecting American Agriculture: More Detector Dog Programs|publisher=United States Department of Agriculture: Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service|accessdate=9 July 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070810231215/http://www.aphis.usda.gov/lpa/pubs/detdog6.html| archivedate= 10 August 2007 | url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Testing==
Beagles are the dog breed most often used in [[animal testing]], due to their size and passive nature. In the United States, as many as 65,000 beagles are used every year for medical, cosmetic, beauty, and other chemical tests. They are purpose bred and live their lives in cages undergoing experiments.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.beaglerescueleague.org/lab-to-leash/questions-answers|title=Beagle Rescue League, Inc. » Questions &amp; Answers|website=www.beaglerescueleague.org|access-date=2018-08-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Rescue + Freedom Project (formerly Beagle Freedom Project) has successfully advocated for beagles to be released from labs. This organization has freed hundreds of animals.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://rescuefreedomproject.org/|title=Rescue + Freedom Project|website=Rescue + Freedom Project|language=en-US|access-date=2018-08-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Beagles are used in a range of research procedures: fundamental biological research, applied human medicine, applied veterinary medicine, and protection of man, animals or the environment.&lt;ref name=&quot;REP2005&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;UKGOV&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200102/ldselect/ldanimal/150/15004.htm#a10|title=Select Committee on Animals In Scientific Procedures Report |publisher=House of Lords|year=2002|accessdate=9 July 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of the 8,018 dogs used in testing in the UK in 2004, 7,799 were beagles (97.3%).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.official-documents.gov.uk/document/cm67/6713/6713.pdf|title=Statistics of Scientific Procedures on Living Animals Great Britain 2004|year=2004|publisher=Home Office|accessdate=9 July 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070702210136/http://www.official-documents.gov.uk/document/cm67/6713/6713.pdf| archivedate= 2 July 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the UK, the [[Animals (Scientific Procedures) Act 1986]] gave special status to primates, equids, cats and dogs and in 2005 the Animal Procedures Committee (set up by the act) ruled that testing on mice was preferable, even though a greater number of individual animals were involved.&lt;ref name=&quot;RAPC&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.official-documents.gov.uk/document/hc0506/hc16/1660/1660.pdf|title=Report of the Animal Procedures Committee for 2004|year=2004|publisher=Home Office|accessdate=9 July 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070710215220/http://www.official-documents.gov.uk/document/hc0506/hc16/1660/1660.pdf| archivedate= 10 July 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005 beagles were involved in less than 0.3% of the total experiments on animals in the UK, but of the 7670 experiments performed on dogs 7406 involved beagles (96.6%).&lt;ref name=&quot;REP2005&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.official-documents.gov.uk/document/cm68/6877/6877.pdf|title=Statistics of Scientific Procedures on Living Animals Great Britain 2005|year=2005|publisher=Home Office|accessdate=9 July 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070710215223/http://www.official-documents.gov.uk/document/cm68/6877/6877.pdf| archivedate= 10 July 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most dogs are bred specifically for this purpose, by companies such as [[Harlan (company)|Harlan]]. In the UK companies breeding animals for research must be licensed under the Animals (Scientific Procedures) Act.&lt;ref name=&quot;RAPC&quot; /&gt;
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Dogs6CCcopy.jpg|left|thumb|Group housed dogs used in safety testing of pharmaceuticals, August 2000]] --&gt;

Testing of cosmetic products on animals is banned in the member states of the European Community,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ec.europa.eu/enterprise/cosmetics/html/cosm_animal_test.htm|title=Cosmetics and animal tests|publisher=European Commission&amp;nbsp;— Enterprise and Industry Directorate General|year=2007|accessdate=9 July 2007|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070629081459/http://ec.europa.eu/enterprise/cosmetics/html/cosm_animal_test.htm|archivedate=29 June 2007|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; although France protested the ban and has made efforts to have it lifted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=10000085&amp;sid=ahaDhWAXharI&amp;refer=europe|title=Animal-Testing Ban for Cosmetics to Be Upheld, EU Court Rules|publisher=Bloomberg|date=24 May 2005|accessdate=9 July 2007|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070930065529/http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=10000085&amp;sid=ahaDhWAXharI&amp;refer=europe|archivedate=30 September 2007|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is permitted in the United States but is not mandatory if safety can be ascertained by other methods, and the test species is not specified by the [[Food and Drug Administration]] (FDA).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cfsan.fda.gov/~dms/cos-205.html|title=Animal Testing|publisher=US Food and Drug Administration|year=1999|accessdate=9 July 2007 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070523010844/http://www.cfsan.fda.gov/~dms/cos-205.html |archivedate = 23 May 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; When testing toxicity of food additives, food contaminants, and some drugs and chemicals the FDA uses beagles and [[miniature pig]]s as surrogates for direct human testing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.fda.gov/oc/ofacs/fdasbo/businesspub.html|title=How to do Business with FDA|publisher=US Department of Health and Human Services|accessdate=11 July 2007| archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20050803014243/https://www.fda.gov/oc/ofacs/fdasbo/businesspub.html| archivedate = 3 August 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Minnesota was the first state to enact a Beagle freedom adoption law in 2014, mandating that dogs and cats are allowed to be adopted once they have completed with research testing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.startribune.com/politics/statelocal/260128011.html|title=Beagle Freedom Law makes history in Minnesota|publisher=Minnesota Star Tribune|date=21 May 2014|accessdate=22 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Anti-[[Animal testing|vivisection]] groups have reported on abuse of animals inside testing facilities. In 1997&amp;nbsp;footage secretly filmed by a freelance journalist inside [[Huntingdon Life Sciences]] in the UK showed staff punching and screaming at beagles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://dbsst.org/case_histories/full_text?id=79|title = Seeing Is Believing&amp;nbsp;— cruelty to dogs at Huntingdon Life Sciences|author = Zoe Broughton|publisher = The Ecologist|date = March 2001|accessdate = 1 July 2015|via = dbsst.org|url-status = dead|archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20150701132818/http://dbsst.org/case_histories/full_text?id=79|archivedate = 1 July 2015|df = dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Consort Kennels]], a UK-based breeder of beagles for testing, closed down in 1997 after pressure from animal rights groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Nicola Woolcock|url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,2-1749489,00.html|title=Extremists seek fresh targets close to home|work=The Times|date=25 August 2005|accessdate=9 July 2007 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other roles==
Although bred for hunting, Beagles are versatile and are nowadays employed for various other roles in detection, therapy, and as family pets.&lt;ref name=&quot;QLD&quot; /&gt;

Beagles are used as sniffer dogs for [[termite]] detection in Australia,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.k9centre.com/termite-detection-dogs/|title=Termite Detection Dogs|publisher=K9 Centre.com|accessdate=8 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and have been mentioned as possible candidates for drug and explosive detection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://parliament.nsw.gov.au/prod/PARLMENT/hansArt.nsf/V3Key/LC20011213047|title=Police Powers (Drug Detection Dogs) Bill|publisher=Parliament of New South Wales|date=13 December 2001|accessdate=9 July 2007|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070929110512/http://www.parliament.nsw.gov.au/prod/parlment/hansart.nsf/V3Key/LC20011213047|archivedate=29 September 2007|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/magazine/4676233.stm|title=The unlikely enemy of the terrorist|author=Tom Geoghegan|publisher=BBC News Magazine|date=13 July 2005|accessdate=8 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because of their gentle nature and unimposing build, they are also frequently used in [[Animal-assisted therapy|pet therapy]], visiting the sick and elderly in hospital.&lt;ref&gt;Kraeuter pp.89–92&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2006, a trained Beagle assistance dog was credited with saving the life of its owner after using her owner's mobile phone to dial an emergency number.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/5099190.stm?ls|title=Dog praised for life-saving call|date=20 June 2006|work=BBC News|accessdate=9 July 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In the aftermath of the [[2010 Haiti earthquake]], a Beagle [[search and rescue dog]] with a Colombian rescue squad was credited with locating the owner of the [[Hôtel Montana]], who was subsequently rescued after spending 100 hours buried in the rubble.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.twincities.com/prep/ci_14260479|title=In Haiti, a shattered symbol reluctantly yields dead|date=25 January 2010|publisher=Twin Cities Pioneer Press|accessdate=26 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beagles were hired by New York City to help with bedbug detection,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://newyork.cbslocal.com/2011/11/17/nyc-enlists-pair-of-bedbug-detecting-dogs/ | title=NYC Enlists Pair Of Bedbug-Detecting Dogs | publisher=CBS-NY | date=17 November 2011 | accessdate=19 September 2015 | author=The Associated Press.}}&lt;/ref&gt; while the role of such dogs in this type of detection may have doubts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=https://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/12/nyregion/12bedbugs.html?pagewanted=all | title=Doubts Rise on Bedbug-Sniffing Dogs | newspaper=New York Times | date=11 November 2010 | accessdate=19 September 2015 | author=Cara Buckley}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In popular culture==
[[File:Bronco the Beagle.JPG|thumb|A male tricolor Beagle]]

*Beagles appeared in [[funny animal]] [[comic strips]] and [[animated cartoons]] since the 1950s with [[Courage the Cowardly Dog]] and the ''[[Peanuts]]'' character [[Snoopy]] was billed as &quot;the world's most famous Beagle&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;mostfamousbeagle&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.thehansindia.com/posts/index/Cinema/2016-05-22/Cartoons-we-want-as-movies/229794|title=Cartoons we want as movies|publisher=The Hans India|date=22 May 2016|accessdate=8 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Former US President [[Lyndon Baines Johnson]] had several beagles, and caused an outcry when he picked up one of them by its ears during an official greeting on the White House lawn.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lbjlib.utexas.edu/johnson/archives.hom/FAQs/dog/doghouse.asp|title=President Johnson's Dogs|publisher=Lyndon Baines Johnson Library and Museum|accessdate=9 July 2007|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070711110752/http://www.lbjlib.utexas.edu/johnson/archives.hom/FAQs/dog/doghouse.asp|archivedate=11 July 2007|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The ship on which [[Charles Darwin]] made [[Second voyage of HMS Beagle|the voyage]] which provided much of the inspiration for ''[[On the Origin of Species]]'' was named [[HMS Beagle|HMS ''Beagle'']] after the breed, and, in turn, lent its name to the ill-fated British [[Mars|Martian]] lander ''[[Beagle 2]]''.
*An American bred 15 inch male Beagle with the registered name of Ch [[K-Run's Park Me In First]] and the pet name of &quot;Uno&quot; won the 2008 [[Westminster Kennel Club Dog Show]].&lt;ref name=nytimes&gt;{{cite news|last1=Sandomir|first1=Richard|title=Beagle, a Breed Long Unsung, Wins Best in Show|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2008/02/13/sports/othersports/13dogs.html?fta=y|accessdate=February 18, 2015|work=New York Times|date=February 13, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*A Canadian bred 15 inch female Beagle with the registered name of Gr Ch [[Tashtins Lookin For Trouble]] and the pet name of &quot;Miss P&quot; won the 2015 [[Westminster Kennel Club Dog Show]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dogworld.co.uk/product.php/131233/1/canadians_triumph_at_westminster |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150218155819/http://www.dogworld.co.uk/product.php/131233/1/canadians_triumph_at_westminster |url-status=dead |archive-date=18 February 2015 |title=Canadians triumph at Westminster |publisher=[[Dog World (newspaper)|Dog World]] |accessdate=18 February 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable Beagles==
&lt;!-- Don't add fictional dogs (especially animated) unless they meet a strict standard of notability --&gt;
* Frodo, awarded the [[PDSA Gold Medal]] for animal bravery
* Uno, who in 2008 became the first Beagle to win the Westminster Kennel Club Dog Show &lt;ref name=&quot;akc.org&quot;&gt;https://www.akc.org/expert-advice/news/westminster-winners-2008-to-2018/&lt;/ref&gt;
* Miss P, winner of the 2015 Westminster Kennel Club Dog Show &lt;ref name=&quot;akc.org&quot;/&gt;

==References==
'''Informational notes'''
{{refbegin}}
'''a.''' {{Note label|A|a|none}} In this article &quot;Beagle&quot; (with a capital B) is used to distinguish the modern breed from other beagle-type dogs.

'''b.''' {{Note label|B|b|none}} Youatt states that the Southern Hound may have been native to the British Isles and used on hunts by the Ancient Britons.&lt;ref&gt;Youatt p.133&lt;/ref&gt;

'''c.''' {{Note label|C|c|none}} The Harts posed the following question to a panel of 96 experts, half of which were veterinary surgeons and the other half dog obedience trial judges:&lt;br /&gt;
{{quote|A dog may normally be quite calm but can become very excitable when set off by such things as a ringing doorbell or an owner's movement toward the door. This characteristic may be very annoying to some people. Rank these seven breeds from least to most excitable.}}

'''d.''' {{Note label|D|d|none}} The specific references in each of the author's works are as follows:&lt;br /&gt;
Shakespeare: &quot;''Sir Toby Belch'': She's a beagle, true-bred, and one that adores me: what o' that?&quot; ''[[Twelfth Night]]'' (c. 1600) Act II Scene III &lt;br /&gt;
Webster: &quot;''Mistress Tenterhook''': You are a sweet beagle&quot; ''[[Westward Ho (play)|Westward Ho]]'' (1607) Act III Scene IV:2&lt;br /&gt;
Dryden: &quot;The rest in shape a beagle's whelp throughout, With broader forehead and a sharper snout&quot; ''The Cock and the Fox'', and again: &quot;About her feet were little beagles seen&quot; in ''Palamon and Arcite'' both from ''[[Fables, Ancient and Modern]]'' (1700)&lt;br /&gt;
Tickell: &quot;Here let me trace beneath the purpled morn, The deep-mouth'd beagle, and the sprightly horn&quot; ''To a Lady before Marriage'' (published posthumously in 1749)&lt;br /&gt;
Fielding: &quot;'What the devil would you have me do?' cries the Squire, turning to Blifil, 'I can no more turn her, than a beagle can turn an old hare.'&quot; ''[[The History of Tom Jones, a Foundling]]'' (1749) Chapter 7.&lt;br /&gt;
Cowper: &quot;For persevering chase and headlong leaps, True beagle as the staunchest hound he keeps&quot; ''The Progress of Error'' (1782)&lt;br /&gt;
Pope: &quot;Thus on a roe the well-breath'd beagle flies, And rends his hide fresh-bleeding with the dart&quot; ''The Iliad of Homer'' (1715–20) Book XV:697–8
{{refend}}

'''Citations'''
{{Reflist}}

'''Bibliography'''
*{{cite book|title=A New Owner's Guide to Beagles|first=David and Hazel|last=Arnold|publisher=T.F.H. Publications, Inc.|year=1998|isbn=0-7938-2785-X}}
*{{cite book|title=Shooting|first=Robert|last=Blakey|authorlink=Robert Blakey (writer)|publisher=George Routledge and Co.|year=1854}}
*{{cite book|title=Beagles|first=E. Fitch|last=Daglish|publisher=Foyles|location=London|year=1961|isbn=0-7071-0631-1}}
*{{cite book|title=The Dog's Mind|first=Bruce|last=Fogle|publisher=Howell Book House|year=1990|isbn=0-87605-513-7|url=https://archive.org/details/dogsmind00bruc}}
*{{cite book|title=Researches into the History of the British Dog Volume II|first=George|last=Jesse|publisher=Robert Hardwicke|location=London|year=1866}}
*{{cite book|title=Anecdotes of Dogs|url=https://archive.org/details/anecdotesdogs00jessgoog|first=Edward|last=Jesse|publisher=H. G. Bohn|year=1858}}
*{{cite book|title=Training Your Beagle|first=Kristine|last=Kraeuter|publisher=Barron's|year=2001|isbn=0-7641-1648-7|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/trainingyourbeag0000krae}}
*{{cite book|title=The Field Book: Or, Sports and Pastimes of the United Kingdom|url=https://archive.org/details/fieldbookorspor00unkngoog|first=William Hamilton|last=Maxwell|publisher=E. Wilson|year=1833}}
*{{cite book|title=The Sportsman's Library|url=https://archive.org/details/sportsmanslibra00millgoog|first=John|last=Mills|year=1845|publisher=W. Paterson}}
*{{cite book|title=The History of the Countryside|first=Oliver|last=Rackham|authorlink = Oliver Rackham|publisher=Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson History|year=2000|isbn=1-84212-440-4}}
*{{cite book|title=The Beagle Handbook|first=Dan|last=Rice|publisher=Barron's|year=2000|isbn=0-7641-1464-6|url=https://archive.org/details/beaglehandbook00rice}}
*{{cite book|title=The Sportsman's Repository|url=https://archive.org/details/sportsmansrepos00scotgoog|first=John|last=Scott|year=1845|publisher=Henry G. Bohn}}
*{{cite book|title=The Encyclopedia of North American Sporting Dogs|first=Steve|last=Smith|publisher=Willow Creek Press|year=2002|isbn= 1-57223-501-2}}
*{{cite book|title=Manual of British Rural Sports|author=&quot;Stonehenge&quot; (pseudonym of [[John Henry Walsh|J. H. Walsh]])|publisher=G. Routledge and Co.|location=London|year=1856 |url=https://archive.org/stream/manualbritishru00walsgoog#page/n75/mode/2up}}
*{{cite book |title=On Hunting (Cynegeticus) |author=[[Xenophon]] (translated by H. G. Dakyns) |publisher=Macmillan and Co. (published online by eBooks@Adelaide) |url=http://etext.library.adelaide.edu.au/x/xenophon/x5hu/ |origyear=c. 380 BC |year=1897 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070613115649/http://etext.library.adelaide.edu.au/x/xenophon/x5hu/ |archivedate=13 June 2007 |df=dmy-all }}
*{{cite book|title=The Dog|url=https://archive.org/details/dog00youagoog|first=William|last=Youatt|authorlink=William Youatt|publisher=Blanchard and Lea|year=1852}}

==External links==
{{commons|Beagle}}
* {{curlie|Recreation/Pets/Dogs/Breeds/Hound_Group/Beagle/}}

{{Hounds}}
{{English dogs}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:FCI breeds]]
[[Category:Companion dogs]]
[[Category:Scent hounds]]
[[Category:Dog breeds originating in England]]
[[Category:Hunting with hounds]]</text>
      <sha1>ascxjoa5gjinqurf0axc1ua22b4oupj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
