  <page>
    <title>Battle of Waterloo</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4356</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943377954</id>
      <parentid>942751469</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T15:29:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelink 1 book for [[Wikipedia:Verifiability|verifiability]]. [stream]) #IABot (v2.0) ([[User:GreenC bot|GreenC bot]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{other uses}}
{{short description|Battle of the Napoleonic Wars in which Napoleon was defeated}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2013}}
{{Use British English|date=August 2013}}&lt;!-- Neighbour, centre etc., with Cambridge spellings (-is- instead of -iz-). --&gt;
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict = Battle of Waterloo
| partof = the [[Waterloo campaign]]
| image = Battle of Waterloo 1815.PNG
| image_size = 300
| caption = ''[[The Battle of Waterloo (painting)|The Battle of Waterloo]]''
by [[William Sadler (painter)|William Sadler]]
| date = 18 June 1815
| place = [[Waterloo, Belgium|Waterloo]], [[United Kingdom of the Netherlands|Netherlands]], present-day Belgium; {{convert|15|km|abbr=on}} south of Brussels
| coordinates = {{Coord|50.680|N|4.412|E|region:BE_type:event|display=inline,title}}
| map_type = Belgium
| map_relief = 1
| map_size = 290
| map_caption = Location within Belgium, then a part of the United Kingdom of the Netherlands
| result =Decisive Coalition victory
| combatant1 = '''{{Flagcountry|First French Empire}}'''
| combatant2 = {{Flagcountry|United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland}}&lt;br&gt;{{Flagcountry|United Kingdom of the Netherlands}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagdeco|Kingdom of Hanover}} [[Kingdom of Hanover|Hanover]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagdeco|Nassau}} [[Duchy of Nassau|Nassau]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagdeco|Brunswick}} [[Duchy of Brunswick|Brunswick]]&lt;br&gt;{{flag|Prussia|1803}}
| commander1 = {{Flagicon|French First Empire}} [[Napoleon|Napoleon Bonaparte]]
| commander2 = {{Flagicon|United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland}} [[Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of Wellington|Duke of Wellington]]&lt;br/&gt;{{Flagicon|Prussia|1803}} [[Gebhard Leberecht von Blücher]]
| strength1 = '''Total''': 73,000{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|pp=68–69}}
* 50,700 infantry
* 14,390 cavalry
* 8,050 artillery and engineers
* 252 guns
| strength2 = '''Total''': 118,000&lt;br/&gt;
Wellington's army: 68,000&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Hofschröer|1999|p=61}} cites Siborne's numbers.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Hamilton-Williams|1994|p=256}} gives 168,000.&lt;/ref&gt;
* United Kingdom: 25,000 British and 6,000 King's German Legion
* Netherlands: 17,000
* Hanover: 11,000
* Brunswick: 6,000
* Nassau: 3,000{{sfn|Barbero|2005|pp=75–76}}
* 156 guns{{sfn|Hamilton-Williams|1994|p=256}}
Blücher's army:
* Prussians: 50,000{{sfn|Chesney|1874|p=4}}

| casualties1 = '''Total''': 41,000
* 24,000 to 26,000 casualties, including 6,000 to 7,000 captured{{sfn|Barbero|2006|p=312}}
* 15,000 missing{{sfn|Barbero|2005|p=420}}
| casualties2 = '''Total''': 24,000&lt;br/&gt;Wellington's army: 17,000
* 3,500 killed
* 10,200 wounded
* 3,300 missing{{sfn|Barbero|2005|p=419}}
Blücher's army: 7,000
* 1,200 killed
* 4,400 wounded
* 1,400 missing{{sfn|Barbero|2005|p=419}}
}}

{{Campaignbox Waterloo}}
The '''Battle of Waterloo''' was fought on Sunday, 18 June 1815 near [[Waterloo, Belgium|Waterloo]] in [[Belgium]], part of the [[United Kingdom of the Netherlands]] at the time. A French army under the command of [[Napoleon Bonaparte]] was defeated by two of the armies of the [[Seventh Coalition]]: an army consisting of units from the United Kingdom, the German Legion, the Netherlands, Hanover, Brunswick and Nassau, under the command of the [[Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of Wellington|Duke of Wellington]], referred to by many authors as the Anglo-allied army, and a [[Kingdom of Prussia|Prussian]] army under the command of Field Marshal [[Gebhard Leberecht von Blücher|Blücher]]. The battle marked the end of the [[Napoleonic Wars]].

Upon Napoleon's return to power in March 1815, many states that had opposed him formed the Seventh Coalition and began to mobilise armies. Wellington and Blücher's armies were [[canton (military)|cantoned]] close to the northeastern border of France. Napoleon chose to attack them separately in the hope of destroying them before they could join in a coordinated invasion of France with other members of the coalition. On 16 June, he successfully attacked the bulk of the Prussian army at the [[Battle of Ligny]] with his main force, while a portion of the French army simultaneously attacked an Anglo-allied army at the [[Battle of Quatre Bras]]. Despite Wellington holding his ground at the strategic crossroads of [[Quatre Bras]], the defeat of the Prussians forced him to withdraw north to Waterloo on the 17th. Napoleon sent a third of his forces to pursue the Prussians, who had [[Waterloo Campaign: Ligny through Wavre to Waterloo|withdrawn parallel to Wellington]] in good order. This resulted in the separate and simultaneous [[Battle of Wavre]] with the Prussian rear-guard.

Upon learning that the Prussian army was able to support him, Wellington decided to offer battle on the [[Mont-Saint-Jean, Belgium|Mont-Saint-Jean]] escarpment across the Brussels road. Here he withstood repeated attacks by the French throughout the afternoon of the 18th, aided by the progressively arriving Prussians. In the evening, Napoleon committed his last reserves, the senior battalions of the [[French Imperial Guard]] infantry. The desperate final attack of the Guard was narrowly beaten back. With the Prussians breaking through on the French right flank, Wellington's Anglo-allied army counter-attacked in the centre, and the French army was routed.

Waterloo was the decisive engagement of the [[Waterloo Campaign]] and Napoleon's last. According to Wellington, the battle was &quot;the nearest-run thing you ever saw in your life&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[q:Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of Wellington|Wikiquote:Wellington]] citing ''Creevey Papers'', ch. x, p. 236&lt;/ref&gt; [[Abdication of Napoleon, 1815|Napoleon abdicated]] four days later, and coalition forces entered Paris on 7 July. The defeat at Waterloo ended Napoleon's rule as [[Emperor of the French]] and marked the end of his [[Hundred Days]] return from exile. This ended the [[First French Empire]] and set a chronological milestone between serial European wars and decades of [[International relations of the Great Powers (1814–1919)|relative peace]], often referred to as the ''[[Pax Britannica]]''.

The battlefield is located in the Belgian municipalities of [[Braine-l'Alleud]] and [[Lasne]],{{sfn|Marcelis|2015}} about {{convert|15|km|mi}} south of [[Brussels]], and about {{convert|2|km|mi}} from the town of Waterloo. The site of the battlefield today is dominated by the monument of the [[Lion's Mound]], a large artificial hill constructed from earth taken from the battlefield itself; the topography of the battlefield near the mound has not been preserved.

==Prelude==
{{Main|Waterloo Campaign}}
[[File:Strategic Situation of Western Europe 1815.jpg|thumb|upright=1.4|The strategic situation in Western Europe in 1815: 250,000 Frenchmen faced a coalition of about 850,000 soldiers on four [[Front (military)|fronts]]. Napoleon was forced to leave 20,000 men in Western France to reduce a royalist insurrection.]]

On 13 March 1815, six days before Napoleon reached Paris, the powers at the [[Congress of Vienna]] [[s:Declaration at the Congress of Vienna|declared him an outlaw]].{{sfn|''Brown University Library''}} Four days later, the [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|United Kingdom]], [[Russian Empire|Russia]], [[Austrian Empire|Austria]], and [[Kingdom of Prussia|Prussia]] mobilised armies to defeat Napoleon.{{sfn|Hamilton-Williams|1993|p=59}} Critically outnumbered, Napoleon knew that once his attempts at dissuading one or more members of the [[Seventh Coalition]] from invading France had failed, his only chance of remaining in power was to attack before the coalition mobilised.{{sfn|Chandler|1966|pp=1016, 1017, 1093}}

Had Napoleon succeeded in destroying the existing coalition forces south of Brussels before they were reinforced, he might have been able to drive the British back to the sea and knock the Prussians out of the war. Crucially, this would have bought him time to recruit and train more men before turning his armies against the Austrians and Russians.{{citation needed|date=June 2019}}

An additional consideration for Napoleon was that a French victory might cause French-speaking sympathisers in Belgium to launch a friendly revolution. Also, coalition troops in Belgium were largely second-line, as many units were of dubious quality and loyalty, and most of the British veterans of the [[Peninsular War]] had been sent to North America to fight in the [[War of 1812]].{{sfn|Chandler|1966|pp=1016, 1017, 1093}}

The initial dispositions of British commander [[Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of Wellington]], were intended to counter the threat of Napoleon enveloping the Coalition armies by moving through [[Mons]] to the south-west of Brussels.{{sfn|Siborne&lt;!--W--&gt;|1895|p=82}} This would have pushed Wellington closer to the Prussian forces, led by [[Gebhard Leberecht von Blücher]], but might have cut Wellington's communications with his base at [[Ostend]]. In order to delay Wellington's deployment, Napoleon spread false intelligence which suggested that Wellington's supply chain from the channel ports would be cut.{{sfn|Hofschröer|2005|pp=136–160}}

[[File:Napoleon crop.jpg|thumb|upright|The resurgent [[Napoleon]]'s strategy was to isolate the Anglo-allied and Prussian armies and [[Defeat in detail|annihilate each one separately]].]]
[[File:Lord Arthur Wellesley the Duke of Wellington.jpg|thumb|upright|The [[Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of Wellington|1st Duke of Wellington]], commander of the Anglo-allied army]]
[[File:Blücher (nach Gebauer).jpg|thumb|upright|[[Gebhard Leberecht von Blücher]], who had led one of the coalition armies defeating Napoleon at the [[Battle of Leipzig]], commanded the Prussian army]]

By June, Napoleon had raised a total army strength of about 300,000 men. The force at his disposal at Waterloo was less than one third that size, but the rank and file were nearly all loyal and experienced soldiers.{{sfn|Herold|1967|pp= 53, 58, 110}} Napoleon divided his army into a left wing commanded by [[Michel Ney|Marshal Ney]], a right wing commanded by [[Emmanuel, marquis de Grouchy|Marshal Grouchy]] and a reserve under his command (although all three elements remained close enough to support one another). Crossing the frontier near [[Charleroi]] before dawn on 15 June, the French [[Waterloo Campaign: Start of hostilities (15 June)|rapidly overran Coalition outposts]], securing Napoleon's &quot;central position&quot; between Wellington's and Blücher's armies. He hoped this would prevent them from combining, and he would be able to destroy first the Prussian's army, then Wellington's.{{citation needed|date=June 2019}}

Only very late on the night of 15 June was Wellington certain that the Charleroi attack was the main French thrust. In the early hours of 16 June, at the [[Duchess of Richmond's ball]] in Brussels, he received a dispatch from the [[William II of the Netherlands|Prince of Orange]] and was shocked by the speed of Napoleon's advance. He hastily ordered his army to concentrate on [[Quatre Bras]], where the Prince of Orange, with the brigade of [[Bernhard Carl of Saxe-Weimar-Eisenach|Prince Bernhard of Saxe-Weimar]], was holding a tenuous position against the soldiers of Ney's left wing.{{sfn|Longford|1971|p=508}}

Ney's orders were to secure the crossroads of Quatre Bras, so that he could later swing east and reinforce Napoleon if necessary. Ney found the crossroads of [[Battle of Quatre Bras|Quatre Bras]] lightly held by the Prince of Orange, who repelled Ney's initial attacks but was gradually driven back by overwhelming numbers of French troops. First reinforcements, and then Wellington arrived. He took command and drove Ney back, securing the crossroads by early evening, too late to send help to the Prussians, who had already been defeated.{{citation needed|date=June 2019}}

Meanwhile on 16 June, Napoleon attacked and defeated Blücher's Prussians at the [[Battle of Ligny]] using part of the reserve and the right wing of his army. The Prussian centre gave way under heavy French assaults, but the flanks held their ground. [[Waterloo Campaign: Ligny through Wavre to Waterloo|The Prussian retreat from Ligny]] went uninterrupted and seemingly unnoticed by the French. The bulk of their rearguard units held their positions until about midnight, and some elements did not move out until the following morning, ignored by the French.{{sfn|Chesney|1874|p=144}}

Crucially, the Prussians did not retreat to the east, along their own lines of communication. Instead, they, too, fell back northwards—parallel to Wellington's line of march, still within supporting distance and in communication with him throughout. The Prussians rallied on [[Friedrich Wilhelm Freiherr von Bülow|Bülow]]'s IV Corps, which had not been engaged at Ligny and was in a strong position south of [[Wavre]].{{sfn|Chesney|1874|pp=144–145}}

With the Prussian retreat from Ligny, Wellington's position at Quatre Bras was untenable. The next day he withdrew northwards, to a defensive position he had [[reconnaissance|reconnoitred]] the previous year—the low [[ridge]] of Mont-Saint-Jean, south of the village of [[Waterloo, Belgium|Waterloo]] and the [[Sonian Forest]].{{sfn|Longford|1971|p=527}}

Napoleon, with the reserves, made a late start on 17 June and joined Ney at Quatre Bras at 13:00 to attack Wellington's army but found the position empty. The French pursued Wellington's retreating army to Waterloo; however, due to bad weather, mud and the head start that Napoleon's tardy advance had allowed Wellington, apart from a cavalry [[action at Genappe]], there was no substantial engagement.{{citation needed|date=June 2019}}

Before leaving Ligny, Napoleon had ordered Grouchy, who commanded the right wing, to [[Waterloo campaign: Ligny through Wavre to Waterloo|follow up the retreating Prussians]] with 33,000 men. A late start, uncertainty about the direction the Prussians had taken, and the vagueness of the orders given to him, meant that Grouchy was too late to prevent the Prussian army reaching Wavre, from where it could march to support Wellington. More importantly, the heavily outnumbered Prussian rear-guard was able to use the River Dyle to enable a savage and prolonged action to delay Grouchy.{{citation needed|date=June 2019}}

As 17 June drew to a close, Wellington's army had arrived at its position at Waterloo, with the main body of Napoleon's army following. Blücher's army was gathering in and around Wavre, around {{convert|8|mi}} to the east of the city. Early on the morning of the 18th, Wellington received an assurance from Blücher that the Prussian army would support him. He decided to hold his ground and give battle.{{citation needed|date=June 2019}}

==Armies==
{{Main|Order of battle of the Waterloo campaign}}
Three armies were involved in the battle: Napoleon's ''Armée du Nord'', a multinational army under Wellington, and a Prussian army under Blücher.

{{multiple image
|align = right
|direction = vertical
|image1 = Marechal Ney.jpg
|width1 = 180
|alt1 =
|image2 = YoungwilliamII.jpg
|width2 = 180
|alt2 =
|footer = ''Top,'' Marshal [[Michel Ney]], who exercised tactical control of the greater part of the French forces for most of the battle. ''Bottom''  [[William II of the Netherlands|William, Prince of Orange]], commander of the Anglo-allied [[Order of battle of the Waterloo campaign#I Corps 2|I Corps]].
}}

The French army of around 69,000 consisted of 48,000 infantry, 14,000 cavalry, and 7,000 artillery with 250 guns.{{sfn|Barbero|2005|p=75}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Hofschröer|1999|p=68}} gives 73,000.&lt;/ref&gt; Napoleon had used conscription to fill the ranks of the French army throughout his rule, but he did not conscript men for the 1815 campaign. His troops were mainly veterans with considerable experience and a fierce devotion to their Emperor.{{sfn|Glover|2014|page=30}} The cavalry in particular was both numerous and formidable, and included fourteen regiments of armoured [[heavy cavalry]], and seven of highly versatile [[lancers]] who were armed with lances, sabres and firearms.{{citation needed|date=June 2019}}

However, as the army took shape, French officers were allocated to units as they presented themselves for duty, so that many units were commanded by officers the soldiers didn't know, and often didn't trust. Crucially, some of these officers had little experience in working together as a unified force, so that support for other units was often not given.{{citation needed|date=June 2019}}

The French army was forced to march through rain and black coal-dust mud to reach Waterloo, and then to contend with mud and rain as it slept in the open. Little food was available for the soldiers,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Simms|first=Brendan|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=b3LCBAAAQBAJ&amp;newbks=1&amp;newbks_redir=0&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;dq=%22battle%20of%20waterloo%22%20%22food%22&amp;pg=PA29#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=The Longest Afternoon: The 400 Men Who Decided the Battle of Waterloo|publisher=Basic Books|year=2015|isbn=9780465039944|location=New York, NY|pages=29}}&lt;/ref&gt; but nevertheless the veteran French soldiers were fiercely loyal to Napoleon.{{citation needed|date=June 2019}}

Wellington later said that he had &quot;an infamous army, very weak and ill-equipped, and a very inexperienced [[Staff (military)|Staff]]&quot;.{{sfn|Longford|1971|p=485}} His troops consisted of 67,000 men: 50,000 infantry, 11,000 cavalry, and 6,000 artillery with 150 guns. Of these, 25,000 were British, with another 6,000 from the [[King's German Legion]] (KGL). All of the [[British Army]] troops were regular soldiers, but only 7,000 of them were Peninsular War veterans.{{sfn|Longford|1971|p=484}} In addition, there were 17,000 Dutch and Belgian troops, 11,000 from [[Kingdom of Hanover|Hanover]], 6,000 from [[Brunswick-Lüneburg#Brunswick-Wolfenbüttel|Brunswick]], and 3,000 from [[Nassau (duchy)|Nassau]].{{sfn|Barbero|2005|pp=75–76}}

Many of the troops in the Coalition armies were inexperienced.{{efn|Captain [[Cavalié Mercer]] [[Royal Horse Artillery|RHA]], thought the Brunswickers &quot;...perfect children. None of the privates, perhaps were over eighteen years of age&quot; {{Harv|Mercer|1891|p=218}}.}}{{efn|On 13 June, the commandant at [[Ath]] requested powder and cartridges as members of a Hanoverian reserve regiment there had never yet fired a shot {{Harv|Longford|1971|p=486}}.}} The Dutch army had been re-established in 1815, following the earlier defeat of Napoleon. With the exception of the British and some from Hanover and Brunswick who had fought with the British army in Spain, many of the professional soldiers in the Coalition armies had spent some of their time in the French army or in armies allied to the Napoleonic regime. The historian Barbero states that in this heterogeneous army the difference between British and foreign troops did not prove significant under fire.{{sfn|Barbero|2006|p=19}}

Wellington was also acutely short of heavy cavalry, having only seven British and three Dutch regiments. The [[Prince Frederick, Duke of York and Albany|Duke of York]] imposed many of his staff officers on Wellington, including his second-in-command the [[Henry Paget, 1st Marquess of Anglesey|Earl of Uxbridge]]. Uxbridge commanded the cavalry and had [[Blank cheque|carte blanche]] from Wellington to commit these forces at his discretion. Wellington stationed a further 17,000 troops at [[Halle, Belgium|Halle]], {{convert|8|mi|km}} away to the west. They were mostly composed of Dutch troops under the Prince of Orange's younger brother [[Prince Frederick of the Netherlands]]. They were placed as a guard against any possible wide flanking movement by the French forces, and also to act as a rearguard if Wellington was forced to retreat towards Antwerp and the coast.{{sfn|Hamilton-Williams|1993|pp=239–240}}{{efn|The straight-line distance from Halle to Braine-l'Alleud, Wellington's far right flank is nearly the same as the straight-line distance from Wavre to [[Frichermont]], Wellington's far left flank, around {{convert|8|mi|km}}.}}

The Prussian army was in the throes of reorganisation. In 1815, the former Reserve regiments, Legions, and ''Freikorps'' volunteer formations from the wars of 1813–1814 were in the process of being absorbed into the line, along with many ''[[Landwehr]]'' (militia) regiments. The ''Landwehr'' were mostly untrained and unequipped when they arrived in Belgium. The Prussian cavalry were in a similar state.{{sfn|Hofschröer|2005|p=59}} Its artillery was also reorganising and did not give its best performance—guns and equipment continued to arrive during and after the battle.{{sfn|Hofschröer|2005|pp=60–62}}

Offsetting these handicaps, the Prussian Army had excellent and professional leadership in its [[German General Staff|General Staff]] organisation. These officers came from four schools developed for this purpose and thus worked to a common standard of training. This system was in marked contrast to the conflicting, vague orders issued by the French army. This staff system ensured that before Ligny, three-quarters of the Prussian army concentrated for battle with 24 hours' notice.{{sfn|Hofschröer|2005|pp=60–62}}

After Ligny, the Prussian army, although defeated, was able to realign its supply train, reorganise itself, and intervene decisively on the Waterloo battlefield within 48 hours.{{sfn|Hofschröer|2005|pp=60–62}} Two and a half Prussian army corps, or 48,000 men, were engaged at Waterloo; two brigades under Bülow, commander of IV Corps, attacked [[Georges Mouton|Lobau]] at 16:30, while [[Hans Ernst Karl, Graf von Zieten|Zieten]]'s I Corps and parts of [[Pirch I]]'s II Corps engaged at about 18:00.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Prussian March |url=https://www.waterlooassociation.org.uk/2018/06/04/prussian-advance/ |website=Waterloo Association |accessdate=9 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battlefield==
{{further|List of Waterloo Battlefield locations}}
[[File:Belgium-6773 - Battlefield View (14152126362).jpg|thumb|upright=1.4|A view of the battlefield from the Lion's mound. On the top right are the buildings of [[La Haye Sainte]].]]

The Waterloo position was a strong one. It consisted of a long ridge running east–west, perpendicular to, and bisected by, the main road to Brussels. Along the crest of the ridge ran the [[Ohain, Belgium|Ohain]] road, a deep [[sunken lane]]. Near the crossroads with the Brussels road was [[Waterloo Elm|a large elm tree]] that was roughly in the centre of Wellington's position and served as his command post for much of the day. Wellington deployed his infantry in a line just behind the crest of the ridge following the Ohain road.{{sfn|Barbero|2005|pp=78–79}}

Using the [[Reverse slope defence|reverse slope]], as he had many times previously, Wellington concealed his strength from the French, with the exception of his [[skirmisher]]s and artillery.{{sfn|Barbero|2005|pp=78–79}} The length of front of the battlefield was also relatively short at {{convert|2.5|mi|0}}. This allowed Wellington to draw up his forces in depth, which he did in the centre and on the right, all the way towards the village of [[Braine-l'Alleud]], in the expectation that the Prussians would reinforce his left during the day.{{sfn|Barbero|2005|p=80}}

[[File:Waterloo.1816.02.jpg|thumb|left|An 1816 map showing the local geography, with Waterloo defending the approach to [[Brussels]]]]

In front of the ridge, there were three positions that could be fortified. On the extreme right were the château, garden, and orchard of [[Hougoumont (farmhouse)|Hougoumont]]. This was a large and well-built country house, initially hidden in trees. The house faced north along a sunken, covered lane (usually described by the British as &quot;the hollow-way&quot;) along which it could be supplied. On the extreme left was the hamlet of [[Papelotte]].{{sfn|Barbero|2005|p=149}}

Both Hougoumont and Papelotte were fortified and garrisoned, and thus anchored Wellington's [[Flanking maneuver|flanks]] securely. Papelotte also commanded the road to Wavre that the Prussians would use to send reinforcements to Wellington's position. On the western side of the main road, and in front of the rest of Wellington's line, was the farmhouse and orchard of [[La Haye Sainte]], which was garrisoned with 400 light infantry of the King's German Legion.{{sfn|Barbero|2005|p=149}} On the opposite side of the road was a disused sand quarry, where the [[95th Rifles]] were posted as sharpshooters.{{sfn|Parry|1900|p=58}}

Wellington's forces positioning presented a formidable challenge to any attacking force. Any attempt to turn Wellington's right would entail taking the entrenched Hougoumont position. Any attack on his right centre would mean the attackers would have to march between [[Enfilade and defilade|enfilading fire]] from Hougoumont and La Haye Sainte. On the left, any attack would also be enfiladed by fire from La Haye Sainte and its adjoining sandpit, and any attempt at turning the left flank would entail fighting through the lanes and hedgerows surrounding Papelotte and the [[List of Waterloo Battlefield locations#Eastern end of the line of battle|other garrisoned buildings]] on that flank, and some very wet ground in the Smohain [[defile (geography)|defile]].{{sfn|Barbero|2005|pp=141, 235}}

The French army formed on the slopes of another ridge to the south. Napoleon could not see Wellington's positions, so he drew his forces up symmetrically about the Brussels road. On the right was I Corps under [[Jean-Baptiste Drouet, Comte d'Erlon|d'Erlon]] with 16,000 infantry and 1,500 cavalry, plus a cavalry reserve of 4,700. On the left was II Corps under [[Honoré Charles Reille|Reille]] with 13,000 infantry, and 1,300 cavalry, and a cavalry reserve of 4,600. In the centre about the road south of the inn ''[[La Belle Alliance]]'' were a reserve including Lobau's VI Corps with 6,000 men, the 13,000 infantry of the [[Imperial Guard (Napoleon I)|Imperial Guard]], and a cavalry reserve of 2,000.{{sfn|Barbero|2005|pp=83–85}}

In the right rear of the French position was the substantial village of [[Plancenoit]], and at the extreme right, the ''Bois de Paris'' wood. Napoleon initially commanded the battle from Rossomme farm, where he could see the entire battlefield, but moved to a position near ''La Belle Alliance'' early in the afternoon. Command on the battlefield (which was largely hidden from his view) was delegated to Ney.{{sfn|Barbero|2005|p=91}}

[[File:Panorama waterloo v2.jpg|thumb|upright=4|center|A panorama of the Waterloo battlefield in 2012]]

==Battle==
===Preparation===
[[File:Waterloo Campaign map-alt3.svg|thumb|upright=1.4|Map of the Waterloo campaign]]

Wellington rose at around 02:00 or 03:00 on 18 June, and wrote letters until dawn. He had earlier written to Blücher confirming that he would give battle at Mont-Saint-Jean if Blücher could provide him with at least one corps; otherwise he would retreat towards Brussels. At a late-night council, Blücher's chief of staff, [[August Neidhardt von Gneisenau]], had been distrustful of Wellington's strategy, but Blücher persuaded him that they should march to join Wellington's army. In the morning Wellington duly received a reply from Blücher, promising to support him with three corps.{{sfn|Longford|1971|pp=535–536}}

From 06:00 Wellington was in the field supervising the deployment of his forces. At Wavre, the Prussian IV Corps under Bülow was designated to lead the march to Waterloo as it was in the best shape, not having been involved in the Battle of Ligny. Although they had not taken casualties, IV Corps had been marching for two days, covering the retreat of the three other corps of the Prussian army from the battlefield of Ligny. They had been posted farthest away from the battlefield, and progress was very slow. The roads were in poor condition after the night's heavy rain, and Bülow's men had to pass through the congested streets of Wavre and move 88&amp;nbsp;artillery pieces. Matters were not helped when a fire broke out in Wavre, blocking several streets along Bülow's intended route. As a result, the last part of the corps left at 10:00, six hours after the leading elements had moved out towards Waterloo. Bülow's men were followed to Waterloo first by I Corps and then by II Corps.{{sfn|Barbero|2005|p=141}}

Napoleon breakfasted off silver plate at ''Le Caillou'', the house where he had spent the night. When [[Jean-de-Dieu Soult|Soult]] suggested that Grouchy should be recalled to join the main force, Napoleon said, &quot;Just because you have all been beaten by Wellington, you think he's a good general. I tell you Wellington is a bad general, the English are bad troops, and this affair is nothing more than eating breakfast&quot;.{{sfn|Longford|1971|p=547}}

Napoleon's seemingly dismissive remark may have been strategic, given his maxim &quot;in war, morale is everything&quot;. He had acted similarly in the past, and on the morning of the battle of Waterloo may have been responding to the pessimism and objections of his chief of staff and senior generals.{{sfn|Roberts|2001|pp=163–166}}

[[File:Napoleon.Waterloo.jpg|thumb|left|upright=1.3|[[Mont-Saint-Jean, Belgium|Battle of Mont-Saint-Jean]]]]

Later on, being told by his brother, [[Jérôme Bonaparte|Jerome]], of some gossip overheard by a waiter between British officers at lunch at the 'King of Spain' inn in Genappe that the Prussians were to march over from Wavre, Napoleon declared that the Prussians would need at least two days to recover and would be dealt with by Grouchy.{{sfn|Barbero|2005|p=73}} Surprisingly, Jerome's overheard gossip aside, the French commanders present at the pre-battle conference at ''Le Caillou'' had no information about the alarming proximity of the Prussians and did not suspect that Blücher's men would start erupting onto the field of battle in great numbers just five hours later.{{sfn|Roberts|2001|p=xxxii}}

Napoleon had delayed the start of the battle owing to the sodden ground, which would have made manoeuvring cavalry and artillery difficult. In addition, many of his forces had [[bivouac shelter|bivouacked]] well to the south of ''La Belle Alliance''. At 10:00, in response to a dispatch he had received from Grouchy six hours earlier, he sent a reply telling Grouchy to &quot;head for Wavre [to Grouchy's north] in order to draw near to us [to the west of Grouchy]&quot; and then &quot;push before him&quot; the Prussians to arrive at Waterloo &quot;as soon as possible&quot;.{{sfn|Longford|1971|p=548}}

At 11:00, Napoleon drafted his general order: Reille's Corps on the left and d'Erlon's Corps to the right were to attack the village of Mont-Saint-Jean and keep abreast of one another. This order assumed Wellington's battle-line was in the village, rather than at the more forward position on the ridge.{{sfn|Bonaparte|1869|pp=292–293}} To enable this, Jerome's division would make an initial attack on Hougoumont, which Napoleon expected would draw in Wellington's reserves,{{sfn|Fletcher|1994|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=US-QQxjHnn8C&amp;pg=PA20 20]}} since its loss would threaten his communications with the sea. A ''[[Grand Battery|grande batterie]]'' of the reserve artillery of I, II, and VI Corps was to then bombard the centre of Wellington's position from about 13:00. D'Erlon's corps would then attack Wellington's left, break through, and roll up his line from east to west. In his memoirs, Napoleon wrote that his intention was to separate Wellington's army from the Prussians and drive it back towards the sea.{{sfn|Barbero|2005|pp=95–98}}

===Hougoumont===
{{Main|Hougoumont}}
[[File:Nassau - Hougoumont - Papendrecht.jpg|thumb|Nassau troops at the Hougoumont farm]]
[[File:800px-North gate Hougoumont.jpg|thumb|Gate on the north side assaulted by the ''1st Légère'' who were led by ''[[sous-lieutenant]]'' Legros{{sfn|Lamar|2000|p=119}}]]

The historian Andrew Roberts notes that &quot;It is a curious fact about the Battle of Waterloo that no one is absolutely certain when it actually began&quot;.{{sfn|Roberts|2005|p=55}} Wellington recorded in his dispatches that at &quot;about ten o'clock [Napoleon] commenced a furious attack upon our post at Hougoumont&quot;.{{sfn|Wellesley|1815|loc=''To Earl Bathurst. Waterloo, 19th June 1815''}} Other sources state that the attack began around 11:30.{{efn|&quot;The hour at which Waterloo began, though there were 150,000&amp;nbsp;actors in the great tragedy, was long a matter of dispute. The Duke of Wellington puts it at 10:00. General Alava says half-past eleven, Napoleon and Drouet say noon, and Ney 13:00. Lord Hill may be credited with having settled this minute question of fact. He took two watches with him into the fight, one a stop-watch, and he marked with it the sound of the first shot fired, and this evidence is now accepted as proving that the first flash of red flame which marked the opening of the world-shaking tragedy of Waterloo took place at exactly ten minutes to twelve&quot; {{Harv|Fitchett|2006|loc=Chapter: King-making Waterloo}}. &quot;...watches had to be set by solar time, this meant that it was rare for two watches to agree... For example, on 9 June, ... the French I Corps had been at Lille, while the IV Corps was at Metz. Assuming an officer had set his watch at noon and then meticulously wound it twice a day but not reset it during the approach march, by the time the two corps reached the vicinity of Waterloo, the I Corps officer's watch would have read 12:40 p.m. at a time when the IV Corps officer's read 11:20 a.m., and it was noon at Waterloo. This is an extreme example, and unlikely to have actually been the case, but it demonstrates the problem quite well&quot; {{harv|Nofi|1998|p=182}}.}} The house and its immediate environs were defended by four light companies of [[Foot guards|Guards]], and the wood and park by Hanoverian ''[[Jäger (military)|Jäger]]'' and the 1/2nd Nassau.{{efn|That is, the 1st battalion of the 2nd Regiment. Among Prussian regiments, &quot;F/12th&quot; denoted the fusilier battalion of the 12th Regiment.}}{{sfn|Barbero|2005|pp=113–114}}

The initial attack by Bauduin's brigade emptied the wood and park, but was driven back by heavy British artillery fire, and cost Bauduin his life. As the British guns were distracted by a duel with French artillery, a second attack by Soye's brigade and what had been Bauduin's succeeded in reaching the north gate of the house. Sous-Lieutenant Legros, a French officer, broke the gate open with an axe, and some French troops managed to enter the courtyard.{{sfn|Thiers|1862|p=215}} The [[Coldstream Guards]] and the [[Scots Guards]] arrived to support the defence. There was a fierce melee, and the British managed to close the gate on the French troops streaming in. The Frenchmen trapped in the courtyard were all killed. Only a young drummer boy was spared.

Fighting continued around Hougoumont all afternoon. Its surroundings were heavily invested by French light infantry, and coordinated attacks were made against the troops behind Hougoumont. Wellington's army defended the house and the hollow way running north from it. In the afternoon, Napoleon personally ordered the house to be shelled to set it on fire,{{efn|Seeing the flames, Wellington sent a note to the house's commander stating that he must hold his position whatever the cost {{Harv|Barbero|2005|p=298}}.}} resulting in the destruction of all but the chapel. Du Plat's brigade of the King's German Legion was brought forward to defend the hollow way, which they had to do without senior officers. Eventually they were relieved by the [[71st (Highland) Regiment of Foot|71st Highlanders]], a British infantry regiment. Adam's brigade was further reinforced by [[Hugh Halkett]]'s 3rd Hanoverian Brigade, and successfully repulsed further infantry and cavalry attacks sent by Reille. Hougoumont held out until the end of the battle.

{{quote|I had occupied that post with a detachment from General Byng's brigade of Guards, which was in position in its rear; and it was some time under the command of Lieutenant-Colonel MacDonald, and afterwards of Colonel Home; and I am happy to add that it was maintained, throughout the day, with the utmost gallantry by these brave troops, notwithstanding the repeated efforts of large bodies of the enemy to obtain possession of it.|Wellington.{{sfn|Booth|1815|p=10}} }}

{{quote|When I reached Lloyd's abandoned guns, I stood near them for about a minute to contemplate the scene: it was grand beyond description. Hougoumont and its wood sent up a broad flame through the dark masses of smoke that overhung the field; beneath this cloud the French were indistinctly visible. Here a waving mass of long red feathers could be seen; there, gleams as from a sheet of steel showed that the cuirassiers were moving; 400&amp;nbsp;cannon were belching forth fire and death on every side; the roaring and shouting were indistinguishably commixed—together they gave me an idea of a labouring volcano. Bodies of infantry and cavalry were pouring down on us, and it was time to leave contemplation, so I moved towards our columns, which were standing up in square.|Major Macready, Light Division, 30th British Regiment, Halkett's brigade.{{sfn|Creasy|1877|loc=[http://www.standin.se/fifteen15a.htm Chapter XV]}} }}

The fighting at Hougoumont has often been characterised as a diversionary attack to draw in Wellington's reserves which escalated into an all-day battle and drew in French reserves instead.{{sfn|Longford|1971|pp=552–554}} In fact there is a good case to believe that both Napoleon and Wellington thought that holding Hougoumont was key to winning the battle. Hougoumont was a part of the battlefield that Napoleon could see clearly,{{sfn|Barbero|2005|p=298}} and he continued to direct resources towards it and its surroundings all afternoon (33&amp;nbsp;battalions in all, 14,000&amp;nbsp;troops). Similarly, though the house never contained a large number of troops, Wellington devoted 21&amp;nbsp;battalions (12,000&amp;nbsp;troops) over the course of the afternoon in keeping the hollow way open to allow fresh troops and ammunition to reach the buildings. He moved several artillery batteries from his hard-pressed centre to support Hougoumont,{{sfn|Barbero|2005|pp=305, 306}} and later stated that &quot;the success of the battle turned upon closing the gates at Hougoumont&quot;.{{sfn|Roberts|2005|p=57}}

===The Grand Battery starts its bombardment===
[[File:Battle of Waterloo.svg|thumb|upright=1.4|Map of the battle: Napoleon's units are in blue, Wellington's in red, Blücher's in grey.]]

The 80 guns of Napoleon's ''grande batterie'' drew up in the centre. These opened fire at 11:50, according to [[Rowland Hill, 1st Viscount Hill|Lord Hill]] (commander of the Anglo-allied II Corps),{{efn|&quot;Lord Hill may be credited with having settled this minute question of fact. He took two watches with him into the fight, one a stop-watch, and he marked with it the sound of the first shot fired&amp;nbsp;... At ten minutes to twelve the first heavy gun rang sullenly from the French ridge&quot; {{Harv|Fitchett|2006|loc=Chapter: King-making Waterloo}}.}} while other sources put the time between noon and 13:30.{{sfn|Barbero|2005|p=131}} The ''grande batterie'' was too far back to aim accurately, and the only other troops they could see were skirmishers of the regiments of Kempt and Pack, and [[Hendrik George de Perponcher Sedlnitsky|Perponcher]]'s 2nd Dutch division (the others were employing Wellington's characteristic &quot;reverse slope defence&quot;).{{sfn|Hamilton-Williams|1993|p=286}}{{efn|The entire 1st brigade of the 2nd Dutch division, that had been on the forward slope during the night, withdrew to a position behind the ridge between the regiments of Kempt and Pack around 12:00 {{Harv|Bas|Wommersom|1909|pp=332–333}}.}}
Nevertheless, the bombardment caused a large number of casualties. Although some projectiles buried themselves in the soft soil, most found their marks on the reverse slope of the ridge. The bombardment forced the cavalry of the Union Brigade (in third line) to move to its left, as did the Scots Greys, to reduce their casualty rate.{{sfn|Hamilton-Williams|1993|p=287}}

===Napoleon spots the Prussians===
At about 13:00, Napoleon saw the first columns of Prussians around the village of [[Lasne-Chapelle-Saint-Lambert]], four or five miles (six to eight kilometres) away from his right flank—about three hours march for an army.{{sfn|Barbero|2005|p=136}} Napoleon's reaction was to have Marshal Soult send a message to Grouchy telling him to come towards the battlefield and attack the arriving Prussians.{{sfn|Barbero|2005|p=145}} Grouchy, however, had been executing Napoleon's previous orders to follow the Prussians &quot;with your sword against his back&quot; towards Wavre, and was by then too far away to reach Waterloo. Grouchy was advised by his subordinate, [[Étienne Maurice Gérard|Gérard]], to &quot;march to the sound of the guns&quot;, but stuck to his orders and engaged the Prussian III Corps rear guard under the command of [[Lieutenant-General]] [[Baron]] [[Johann von Thielmann]] at the [[Battle of Wavre]]. Moreover, Soult's letter ordering Grouchy to move quickly to join Napoleon and attack Bülow would not actually reach Grouchy until after 20:00.{{Citation needed|date=November 2014}}

===First French infantry attack===
A little after 13:00, I Corps' attack began in large [[column (formation)|columns]]. Bernard Cornwell writes &quot;[column] suggests an elongated formation with its narrow end aimed like a spear at the enemy line, while in truth it was much more like a brick advancing sideways and d'Erlon's assault was made up of four such bricks, each one a division of French infantry&quot;.{{sfn|Cornwell|2015|loc=''Those terrible grey horses, how they fight''}} Each division, with one exception, was drawn up in huge masses, consisting of the eight or nine battalions of which they were formed, deployed, and placed in a column one behind the other, with only five paces interval between the battalions.{{sfn|Haweis|1908|p=228}}

The one exception was the 1st Division (Commanded by [[Joachim Jérôme Quiot du Passage|Quiot]], the leader of the 1st Brigade).{{sfn|Haweis|1908|p=228}} Its two brigades were formed in a similar manner, but side by side instead of behind one another. This was done because, being on the left of the four divisions, it was ordered to send one (Quiot's brigade) against the south and west of La Haye Sainte, while the other ([[Baron Charles-Francois Bourgeois|Bourgeois]]') was to attack the eastern side of the same post.{{sfn|Haweis|1908|p=228}}

The divisions were to advance in [[echelon (formation)|echelon]] from the left at a distance of 400 paces apart—the 2nd Division ([[François-Xavier Donzelot|Donzelot]]'s) on the right of Bourgeois' brigade, the 3rd Division ([[Pierre-Louis Binet de Marcognet|Marcognet]]'s) next, and the 4th Division ([[Pierre François Joseph Durutte|Durutte]]'s) on the right. They were led by Ney to the assault, each column having a front of about a hundred and sixty to two hundred [[File (formation)|files]].{{sfn|Haweis|1908|p=228}}

The leftmost division, advanced on La Haye Sainte. The farmhouse was defended by the King's German Legion. While one French battalion engaged the defenders from the front, the following battalions fanned out to either side and, with the support of several squadrons of [[cuirassiers]], succeeded in isolating the farmhouse. The King's German Legion resolutely defended the farmhouse. Each time the French tried to scale the walls the outnumbered Germans somehow held them off. The Prince of Orange saw that La Haye Sainte had been cut off and tried to reinforce it by sending forward the Hanoverian Lüneberg Battalion in line. Cuirassiers concealed in a fold in the ground caught and destroyed it in minutes and then rode on past La Haye Sainte, almost to the crest of the ridge, where they covered d'Erlon's left flank as his attack developed.{{sfn|Hamilton-Williams|1993|pp=289–293}}

At about 13:30, d'Erlon started to advance his three other divisions, some 14,000&amp;nbsp;men over a front of about {{convert|1,000|m|yd|abbr=off}}, against Wellington's left wing. At the point they aimed for they faced 6,000&amp;nbsp;men: the first line consisted of the Dutch 1st &quot;[[Brigade van Bylandt]]&quot; of the 2nd Dutch division, flanked by the British brigades of Kempt and Pack on either side. The second line consisted of British and Hanoverian troops under [[Sir Thomas Picton]], who were lying down in dead ground behind the ridge. All had suffered badly at Quatre Bras. In addition, the Bijlandt brigade had been ordered to deploy its skirmishers in the hollow road and on the forward slope. The rest of the brigade was lying down just behind the road.{{efn|Website of current Dutch historian&lt;!--s: Erwin van Muilwijk: [http://home.tiscali.nl/erwinmuilwijk/index.htm Tiscali.nl], and... website no longer contains the referenced sources--&gt; Marco Bijl: [http://www.8militia.net/ 8militia.net];{{Harvnb|Eenens|1879|pp=14–30, 131–198}}; De Jongh, W.A.: Veldtocht van den Jare 1815, Historisch verhaal; in De Nieuwe Militaire Spectator (Nijmegen 1866), pp. 13–27.(This is the original account of Colonel de Jongh, commander of the Dutch 8th Militia. It can be downloaded at the site of Marco Bijl above.); Löben Sels, Ernst van Bijdragen tot de krijgsgeschiedenis van Napoleon Bonaparte / door E. van Löben Sels Part 4; Veldtogten van 1814 in Frankrijk, en van 1815 in de Nederlanden (Battles). 1842. 's-Gravenhage : de Erven Doorman, pp. 601–682; Allebrandi, Sebastian. Herinneringen uit mijne tienjarige militaire loopbaan. 1835. Amsterdam : Van Kesteren, pp. 21–30;(Allebrandi was a soldier in the Dutch 7th Militia his account is therefore important).}}{{efn|1=De Bas reprints colonel Van Zuylen's 'History of the 2nd division'. Van Zuylen van Nijevelt was the chief of staff of the 2nd division and located right behind the van Bijlandt brigade during the whole day ({{Harvnb|Bas|Wommersom|1909|pp=134–136}}(vol.2)). He wrote a 32 page report, right after the battle. This report forms the basis of most of the other literature mentioned here: see {{Harvnb|Bas|Wommersom|1909|pp=289–352}}(vol.3). [https://books.google.com/books?id=V5wLAQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA61 Google Books]; Boulger has an English translation of the report {{Harv|Boulger|1901}}.}}

At the moment these skirmishers were rejoining their parent battalions, the brigade was ordered to its feet and started to return fire. On the left of the brigade, where the 7th Dutch Militia stood, a &quot;few files were shot down and an opening in the line thus occurred&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Van Zuylen report {{Harvnb|Bas|Wommersom|1909|pp=338–339}}(vol. 3)&lt;/ref&gt; The battalion had no reserves and was unable to close the gap.{{efn|The brigade's losses were very heavy: one French volley at point blank range decimated the 7th and 8th Militia, who had most of their officers killed or wounded, the brigade commander Bijlandt being one of the wounded who had to be evacuated. The two battalions lost their command structure in one stroke. The total of casualties for the whole brigade for the day was around 800 killed and wounded {{Harv|Hamilton-Williams|1993|pp=310–311}}.}} D'Erlon's troops pushed through this gap in the line and the remaining battalions in the Bylandt brigade (8th Dutch Militia and Belgian 7th Line Battalion) were forced to retreat to the square of the 5th Dutch Militia, which was in reserve between Picton's troops, about 100 paces to the rear. There they regrouped under the command of Colonel [[Pieter Hendrik van Zuylen van Nijevelt|Van Zuylen van Nijevelt]].{{efn|Van Zuylen report; he refers to himself as &quot;the chief-of-staff&quot; ({{Harvnb|Bas|Wommersom|1909|pp=338–339}}(vol. 3)).}}{{efn|Some of the retreating troops panicked and fled. This was not to be wondered at in the circumstances. The British troops of the 1/95th battalion, also under great pressure from the French, did the same at the time. This flight did not involve the whole of the Dutch battalions, as has been asserted by some historians. Van Zuylen rallied 400 men, according to his estimate, who were ready to join the counterattack and even captured two French fanions ({{Harvnb|Bas|Wommersom|1909|pp=338–341}}(vol. 3); {{Harvnb|Hamilton-Williams|1993|pp=293–295}}).}} A moment later the Prince of Orange ordered a counterattack, which actually occurred around 10 minutes later. Bylandt was wounded and retired off the field, passing command of the brigade to Lt. Kol. De Jongh.{{efn|{{Harvnb|Pawly|2001|pp=37–43}}; The following letters are used: the accounts of General Kempt, Calvert of the 32nd infantry, Cruikshank of the 79th, Winchester &amp; Hope of the 92nd, Evans (Ponsonby Cavalry brigade) and Clark Kennedy of the Royal Dragoons {{harv|Glover|2004|p={{page needed|date=June 2015}} }}. These are the only letters that actually state some details about the Dutch and Belgian troops.}}

[[File:Andrieux - La bataille de Waterloo.jpg|thumb|''The Battle of Waterloo'' by [[Clément-Auguste Andrieux]]]]

D'Erlon's men ascended the slope and advanced on the sunken road, ''Chemin d'Ohain'', that ran from behind La Haye Sainte and continued east. It was lined on both sides by thick hedges, with [[Willem Frederik van Bylandt|Bylandt]]'s brigade just across the road while the British brigades had been lying down some 100 yards back from the road, Pack's to Bylandt's left and Kempt's to Bylandt's right. Kempt's 1,900 men were engaged by Bourgeois' brigade of 1,900 men of Quiot's division. In the centre, Donzelot's division had pushed back Bylandt's brigade. On the right of the French advance was Marcognet's division led by Grenier's brigade consisting of the ''45e Régiment de Ligne'' and followed by the ''25e Régiment de Ligne'', somewhat less than 2,000 men, and behind them, Nogue's brigade of the ''21e'' and ''45e'' regiments. Opposing them on the other side of the road was [[Denis Pack|Pack]]'s 9th Brigade consisting of the [[44th Foot]] and three Scottish regiments: the [[Royal Scots]], the 42nd [[Black Watch]], and the 92nd Gordons, totalling something over 2,000 men. A very even fight between British and French infantry was about to occur.{{sfn|Barbero|2006|pp=134–138}}

The French advance drove in the British skirmishers and reached the sunken road. As they did so, Pack's men stood up, formed into a four deep line formation for fear of the French cavalry, advanced, and opened fire. However, a firefight had been anticipated and the French infantry had accordingly advanced in more linear formation. Now, fully deployed into line, they returned fire and successfully pressed the British troops; although the attack faltered at the centre, the line in front of d'Erlon's right started to crumble. Picton was killed shortly after ordering the counter-attack and the British and Hanoverian troops also began to give way under the pressure of numbers.{{sfn|Hamilton-Williams|1993|pp=296–297}} Pack's regiments, all four ranks deep, advanced to attack the French in the road but faltered and began to fire on the French instead of charging. The 42nd Black Watch halted at the hedge and the resulting fire-fight drove back the British 92nd Foot while the leading French ''45e Ligne'' burst through the hedge cheering. Along the sunken road, the French were forcing the Anglo-allies back, the British line was dispersing, and at two o'clock in the afternoon Napoleon was winning the Battle of Waterloo.{{sfn|Barbero|2006|p=138}}

Reports from [[Karl Freiherr von Müffling|Baron von Müffling]], the Prussian liaison officer attached to Wellington's army, relate that: &quot;After 3 o'clock the Duke's situation became critical, unless the succour of the Prussian army arrived soon&quot;.{{sfn|Uffindell|Corum|2002|p=211}}

===Charge of the British heavy cavalry===
{{quote|Our officers of cavalry have acquired a trick of galloping at everything. They never consider the situation, never think of manoeuvring before an enemy, and never keep back or provide a reserve.|Wellington.{{sfn|Barbero|2006|pp=140–142}} }}

[[File:Scotland Forever!.jpg|thumb|upright=1.4|''Scotland Forever!'', the charge of the Scots Greys at Waterloo painted by [[Elizabeth Thompson]]]]

At this crucial juncture, Uxbridge ordered his two brigades of British heavy cavalry—formed unseen behind the ridge—to charge in support of the hard-pressed infantry. The [[1st Cavalry Brigade (United Kingdom)|1st Brigade]], known as the Household Brigade, commanded by Major-General [[Lord Edward Somerset]], consisted of guards regiments: the [[1st Regiment of Life Guards|1st]] and [[2nd Regiment of Life Guards|2nd Life Guards]], the [[Royal Horse Guards]] (the Blues), and the [[1st King's Dragoon Guards|1st (King's) Dragoon Guards]]. The [[2nd Cavalry Brigade (United Kingdom)|2nd Brigade]], also known as the Union Brigade, commanded by Major-General [[William Ponsonby (British Army officer)|Sir William Ponsonby]], was so called as it consisted of an English, the [[1st The Royal Dragoons|1st (The Royals)]]; a Scottish, [[Royal Scots Greys|2nd ('Scots Greys')]]; and an Irish, [[6th (Inniskilling) Dragoons|6th (Inniskilling)]]; regiment of heavy dragoons.{{sfn|Adkin|2001|p=217}}{{sfn|Anglesey|1990|p=125}}

[[File:Knötel IV, 04.jpg|left|thumb|upright|British Household Cavalry charging]]

More than 20&amp;nbsp;years of warfare had eroded the numbers of suitable cavalry mounts available on the European continent; this resulted in the British heavy cavalry entering the 1815 campaign with the finest horses of any contemporary cavalry arm. British cavalry troopers also received excellent mounted swordsmanship training. They were, however, inferior to the French in manoeuvring in large formations, cavalier in attitude, and unlike the infantry some units had scant experience of warfare.{{sfn|Barbero|2006|pp=140–142}} The Scots Greys, for example, had not been in action since 1795.{{sfn|Grant|1972|p=17}} According to Wellington, though they were superior individual horsemen, they were inflexible and lacked tactical ability.{{sfn|Barbero|2006|pp=140–142}} &quot;I considered one squadron a match for two French, I didn't like to see four British opposed to four French: and as the numbers increased and order, of course, became more necessary I was the more unwilling to risk our men without having a superiority in numbers.&quot;{{sfn|Oman|Hall|1902|p=119}}

The two brigades had a combined field strength of about 2,000 (2,651 official strength); they charged with the 47-year-old Uxbridge leading them and a very inadequate number of squadrons held in reserve.{{sfn|Barbero|2005|p=188}}{{efn|The Royal Horse Guards (2 squadrons) were in reserve for the Household Brigade (9 or 10 squadrons strong) but the Union Brigade (9 squadrons) had no reserve (''Letter 5'', {{harvnb|Siborne&lt;!--HT--&gt;|1891|pp=7–10}}; ''Letter 16'' {{harvnb|Glover|2004}}). The total may have been 18&amp;nbsp;squadrons as there is an uncertainty in the sources as to whether the King's Dragoon Guards fielded three or four squadrons. Uxbridge implies 4 squadrons (''Letter 5'' {{harvnb|Siborne&lt;!--HT--&gt;|1891|pp=7–10}}), however, Capt. Naylor of the King's implies 3 when he states he commanded the centre squadron of the regiment (''Letter 21'', {{harvnb|Siborne&lt;!--HT--&gt;|1891|pp=46–47}}).}} There is evidence that Uxbridge gave an order, the morning of the battle, to all cavalry brigade commanders to commit their commands on their own initiative, as direct orders from himself might not always be forthcoming, and to &quot;support movements to their front&quot;.{{sfn|Glover|2004|p=''Letter 16: Frederick Stovin (ADC to Sir Thomas Picton)''}} It appears that Uxbridge expected the brigades of [[Sir John Ormsby Vandeleur]], [[Hussey Vivian, 1st Baron Vivian|Hussey Vivian]] and the Dutch cavalry to provide support to the British heavies. Uxbridge later regretted leading the charge in person, saying &quot;I committed a great mistake&quot;, when he should have been organising an adequate reserve to move forward in support.{{sfn|Siborne&lt;!--HT--&gt;|1891|loc=''Letter 5'', pp. 7–10}}

[[File:Richard Ansdell — The Fight For The Standard.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Charles Ewart|Sergeant Ewart]] of the Scots Greys capturing the eagle of the ''45ème Ligne'' in ''The Fight For The Standard'' by [[Richard Ansdell]]]]

The Household Brigade crossed the crest of the Anglo-allied position and charged downhill. The cuirassiers guarding d'Erlon's left flank were still dispersed, and so were swept over the deeply sunken main road and then routed.{{sfn|Barbero|2005|p=426, note 18}}{{efn|An episode famously used later by [[Victor Hugo]] in ''[[Les Misérables]]''. The sunken lane acted as a trap, funnelling the flight of the French cavalry to their own right and away from the British cavalry. Some of the cuirassiers then found themselves hemmed in by the steep sides of the sunken lane, with a confused mass of their own infantry in front of them, the 95th Rifles firing at them from the north side of the lane, and Somerset's heavy cavalry still pressing them from behind.{{sfn|Siborne&lt;!--W--&gt;|1895|pp=410–411}} The novelty of fighting armoured foes impressed the British cavalrymen, as was recorded by the commander of the Household Brigade.}}

{{quote|The blows of the sabres on the cuirasses sounded like braziers at work.|Lord Edward Somerset.{{sfn|Houssaye|1900|p=182}} }}

Continuing their attack, the squadrons on the left of the Household Brigade then destroyed Aulard's brigade. Despite attempts to recall them, they continued past La Haye Sainte and found themselves at the bottom of the hill on blown horses facing Schmitz's brigade [[infantry square|formed in squares]].{{sfn|Barbero|2013|p=160}}

To their left, the Union Brigade suddenly swept through the infantry lines, giving rise to the legend that some of the [[92nd (Gordon Highlanders) Regiment of Foot|92nd Gordon Highland Regiment]] clung onto their stirrups and accompanied them into the charge.{{efn|The tale was related, in old age, by a [[Sergeant Major]] Dickinson of the Scots Greys, the last British survivor of the charge {{harv|Low|1911|pp=137, 143}}.}} From the centre leftwards, the Royal Dragoons destroyed Bourgeois' brigade, capturing the eagle of the 105th ''Ligne''. The Inniskillings routed the other brigade of Quoit's division, and the Scots Greys came upon the lead French regiment, 45th ''Ligne'', as it was still reforming after having crossed the sunken road and broken through the hedge row in pursuit of the British infantry. The Greys captured the eagle of the 45th ''Ligne''{{sfn|Barbero|2005|pp=198–204}} and overwhelmed Grenier's brigade. These would be the only two [[French Imperial Eagle|French eagles]] captured by the British during the battle.{{sfn|Barbero|2006|p=155}} On Wellington's extreme left, Durutte's division had time to form squares and fend off groups of Greys.

[[File:Napoleon French Lancer by Bellange.jpg|thumb|upright|left|Private of the Chevau-légers of the line (lancers) who routed the Union Brigade]]

As with the Household Cavalry, the officers of the Royals and Inniskillings found it very difficult to rein back their troops, who lost all cohesion. Having taken casualties, and still trying to reorder themselves, the Scots Greys and the rest of the Union Brigade found themselves before the main French lines.{{sfn|Hamilton-Williams|1994|p=304}} Their horses were blown, and they were still in disorder without any idea of what their next collective objective was. Some attacked nearby gun batteries of the Grande Battery.{{sfn|Wooten|1993|p=42}} Although the Greys had neither the time nor means to disable the cannon or carry them off, they put very many out of action as the gun crews were killed or fled the battlefield.{{sfn|Barbero|2005|p=211}} Sergeant Major Dickinson of the Greys stated that his regiment was rallied before going on to attack the French artillery: Hamilton, the regimental commander, rather than holding them back cried out to his men &quot;Charge, charge the guns!&quot;{{sfn|Fletcher|1999|p=252}}

Napoleon promptly responded by ordering a counter-attack by the cuirassier brigades of Farine and Travers and Jaquinot's two [[Chevau-léger]] (lancer) regiments in the I Corps [[light cavalry]] division. Disorganized and milling about the bottom of the valley between Hougoumont and La Belle Alliance, the Scots Greys and the rest of the British heavy cavalry were taken by surprise by the countercharge of [[Édouard Jean Baptiste Milhaud|Milhaud]]'s cuirassiers, joined by lancers from Baron Jaquinot's 1st Cavalry Division.{{sfn|Hamilton-Williams|1994|pp=303–304}}
[[File:Alphonse+Lalauze-P.+Eugene+Of.jpg|thumb|Dutch Belgian carabiniers at Waterloo.]]
As Ponsonby tried to rally his men against the French cuirassers, he was attacked by Jaquinot's lancers and captured. A nearby party of Scots Greys saw the capture and attempted to rescue their brigade commander. However, the French lancer who had captured Ponsonby killed him and then used his lance to kill three of the Scots Greys who had attempted the rescue.{{sfn|Hamilton-Williams|1994|p=304}} By the time Ponsonby died, the momentum had entirely returned in favour of the French. Milhaud's and Jaquinot's cavalrymen drove the Union Brigade from the valley. The result was very heavy losses for the British cavalry.{{sfn|Siborne&lt;!--W--&gt;|1895|pp=425–426}}{{sfn|Hofschröer |1999|p=86}} A countercharge, by British light dragoons under Major-General Vandeleur and Dutch–Belgian light dragoons and [[hussar]]s under Major-General [[Charles Étienne de Ghigny|Ghigny]] on the left wing, and Dutch–Belgian ''[[carabinier]]s'' under Major-General Trip in the centre, repelled the French cavalry.{{sfn|Barbero|2005|pp=219–223}}

All figures quoted for the losses of the cavalry brigades as a result of this charge are estimates, as casualties were only noted down after the day of the battle and were for the battle as a whole.&lt;ref&gt;For initial strengths {{Harv|Adkin|2001|p=217}}.&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|Losses are ultimately from the official returns taken the day after the battle: Household Brigade, initial strength 1,319, killed&amp;nbsp;–&amp;nbsp;95, wounded&amp;nbsp;–&amp;nbsp;248, missing&amp;nbsp;–&amp;nbsp;250, totals&amp;nbsp;–&amp;nbsp;593, horses lost&amp;nbsp;–&amp;nbsp;672.&lt;br/&gt;
Union Brigade, initial strength 1,332, killed&amp;nbsp;–&amp;nbsp;264, wounded&amp;nbsp;–&amp;nbsp;310, missing&amp;nbsp;–&amp;nbsp;38, totals&amp;nbsp;–&amp;nbsp;612, horses lost&amp;nbsp;–&amp;nbsp;631 {{Harv|Smith|1998|p=544}}.}} Some historians, Barbero for example,{{sfn|Barbero|2006|pp=142–143}} believe the official rolls tend to overestimate the number of cavalrymen present in their squadrons on the field of battle and that the proportionate losses were, as a result, considerably higher than the numbers on paper might suggest.{{efn|This view appears to have arisen from a comment by Captain Clark-Kennedy of the 1st Dragoons 'Royals', in a letter in [[H. T. Siborne]]'s book, he makes an estimate of around 900&amp;nbsp;men actually in line within the Union Brigade before its first charge {{harv|Siborne&lt;!--HT--&gt;|1891|loc=''Letter 35'', p. 69}}. Clark-Kennedy does not, however, explain how his estimate was arrived at. The shortfall of 432&amp;nbsp;men (the equivalent of a whole regiment) from the paper strength of the brigade is large. However, another officer of the brigade, John Mills of the 2nd Dragoons, says that the effective strength of the brigade did not &quot;exceed 1,200&quot; {{harv|Glover|2007|p=59}}.}} The Union Brigade lost heavily in both officers and men killed (including its commander, William Ponsonby, and Colonel Hamilton of the Scots Greys) and wounded. The 2nd Life Guards and the King's Dragoon Guards of the Household Brigade also lost heavily (with Colonel Fuller, commander of the King's DG, killed). However, the 1st Life Guards, on the extreme right of the charge, and the Blues, who formed a reserve, had kept their cohesion and consequently suffered significantly fewer casualties.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Siborne&lt;!--W--&gt;|1895|pp=329, 349}} (composition of brigades); pp. 422–424 (actions of brigades).&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|[[William Siborne]] was in possession of a number of eyewitness accounts from generals, such as Uxbridge, down to cavalry cornets and infantry ensigns. This makes his history particularly useful (though only from the British and KGL perspective); some of these eyewitness letters were later published by his son, a British Major General ([[H. T. Siborne]]). Parts of William Siborne's account was, and is, highly controversial. The very negative light shed on the conduct of the Dutch–Belgian troops during the battle by Siborne, which it should be said was a reasonably accurate reflection the opinions of his British informants, prompted a semi-official rebuttal by Dutch historian captain [[Willem Jan Knoop]] in his ''&quot;Beschouwingen over Siborne's Geschiedenis van den oorlog van 1815 in Frankrijk en de Nederlanden&quot; en wederlegging van de in dat werk voorkomende beschuldigingen tegen het Nederlandsche leger''. Breda 1846; 2nd printing 1847. Knoop based his rebuttal on the official Dutch after-battle reports, drawn up within days of the battle, not on twenty-year-old recollections of veterans, like Siborne. Siborne rejected the rebuttal.}} On the rolls the official, or paper strength, for both Brigades is given as 2,651 while Barbero and others estimate the actual strength at around 2,000{{sfn|Barbero|2006|pp=142–143}}{{efn|Barbero points out that in April the minister informed Wellington that cavalry regiments could allow themselves no more than 360 horses. The text of this memorandum from Torrens to Wellington Barbero refers to is available in Hamilton-Williams, p.75.}} and the official recorded losses for the two heavy cavalry brigades during the battle was 1,205 troopers and 1,303 horses.{{sfn|Adkin|2001|p=217}}{{efn|Losses are ultimately from the official returns taken the day after the battle: Household Brigade, initial strength 1,319, killed&amp;nbsp;–&amp;nbsp;95, wounded&amp;nbsp;–&amp;nbsp;248, missing&amp;nbsp;–&amp;nbsp;250, totals&amp;nbsp;–&amp;nbsp;593, horses lost&amp;nbsp;–&amp;nbsp;672.
Union Brigade, initial strength 1,332, killed&amp;nbsp;–&amp;nbsp;264, wounded&amp;nbsp;–&amp;nbsp;310, missing&amp;nbsp;–&amp;nbsp;38, totals&amp;nbsp;–&amp;nbsp;612, horses lost&amp;nbsp;–&amp;nbsp;631 {{Harv|Smith|1998|p=544}}.}}

[[File:De Slag bij Waterloo Rijksmuseum SK-A-1115.jpeg|right|thumb|upright=1.4|[[Jan Willem Pieneman]]'s ''The Battle of Waterloo'' (1824). Duke of Wellington, centre, flanked on his left by Lord Uxbridge in hussar uniform. On the image's far left, Cpl. Styles of the Royal Dragoons flourishes the eagle of the 105''eme'' ''Ligne''. The wounded Prince of Orange is carried from the field in the foreground.]]

Some historians, such as Chandler, Weller, Uffindell, and Corum, assert that the British heavy cavalry were destroyed as a viable force following their first, epic charge.{{sfn|Weller|2010|p=104}}{{sfn|Uffindell|Corum|2002|p=82}} Barbero states that the Scots Greys were practically wiped out and that the other two regiments of the Union Brigade suffered comparable losses.{{sfn|Barbero|2006|p=164}} Other historians, such as Clark-Kennedy and Wood, citing British eyewitness accounts, describe the continuing role of the heavy cavalry after their charge. The heavy brigades, far from being ineffective, continued to provide valuable services. They countercharged French cavalry numerous times (both brigades),{{sfn|Siborne&lt;!--HT--&gt;|1891|loc=Letters: 18, 26, 104}}{{sfn|Clark-Kennedy|1975|p=111}}{{sfn|Fletcher|2001|pp= 142–143}}{{sfn|Wood|1895|pp=164, 171}} halted a combined cavalry and infantry attack (Household Brigade only),{{sfn|Siborne&lt;!--HT--&gt;|1891|p=38}}{{sfn|Anglesey|1990|p=144}}{{sfn|Cotton|1849|pp=90–91}} were used to bolster the morale of those units in their vicinity at times of crisis, and filled gaps in the Anglo-allied line caused by high casualties in infantry formations (both brigades).{{sfn|Siborne&lt;!--HT--&gt;|1891|loc=Letters 9, 18, 36}}{{sfn|Anglesey|1990|p=146}}{{sfn|Clark-Kennedy|1975|pp=110–111}}{{sfn|Wood|1895|p=177}}{{sfn|Fletcher|1999|p=270-271}} This service was rendered at a very high cost, as close combat with French cavalry, carbine fire, infantry musketry, and—more deadly than all of these—artillery fire steadily eroded the number of effectives in the two brigades.{{efn|In a cavalry unit an &quot;effective&quot; was an unwounded trooper mounted on a sound horse. The military term &quot;effective&quot; describes a soldier, piece of equipment (e.g. a tank or aircraft) or military unit capable of fighting or carrying out its intended purpose.}} At 6 o'clock in the afternoon the whole Union Brigade could field only three squadrons, though these countercharged French cavalry, losing half their number in the process.{{sfn|Clark-Kennedy|1975|p=111}} At the end of the fighting, the two brigades, by this time combined, could muster one squadron.{{sfn|Clark-Kennedy|1975|p=111}}{{sfn|Wood|1895|p=177}}{{sfn|Siborne&lt;!--HT--&gt;|1891|p=39}}

Fourteen thousand French troops of d'Erlon's I Corps had been committed to this attack. The I Corps had been driven in rout back across the valley costing Napoleon 3,000 casualties{{sfn|Esposito|Elting|1999|p=354, Map 166}} including over 2,000&amp;nbsp;prisoners taken.{{sfn|Barbero|2006|p=156}} Also some valuable time was lost, as the charge had dispersed numerous units and it would take until 16:00 for d'Erlon's shaken corps to reform. And although elements of the Prussians now began to appear on the field to his right, Napoleon had already ordered Lobau's VI corps to move to the right flank to hold them back before d'Erlon's attack began.

===The French cavalry attack===
[[File:Marechal Ney à Waterloo.jpg|thumb|[[Michel Ney|Marshal Ney]] leading the French cavalry charge, from [[Louis Dumoulin]]'s ''[[Panorama of the Battle of Waterloo]]'']]
A little before 16:00, Ney noted an apparent exodus from Wellington's centre. He mistook the movement of casualties to the rear for the beginnings of a retreat, and sought to exploit it. Following the defeat of d'Erlon's Corps, Ney had few infantry reserves left, as most of the infantry had been committed either to the futile Hougoumont attack or to the defence of the French right. Ney therefore tried to break Wellington's centre with cavalry alone.{{sfn|Siborne&lt;!--W--&gt;|1895|pp=443–449}}
Initially, Milhaud's reserve cavalry corps of cuirassiers and [[Charles Lefebvre-Desnouettes|Lefebvre-Desnoëttes]]' light cavalry division of the Imperial Guard, some 4,800&amp;nbsp;sabres, were committed. When these were repulsed, [[François Étienne de Kellermann|Kellermann]]'s heavy cavalry corps and [[Claude-Étienne Guyot|Guyot]]'s heavy cavalry of the Guard were added to the massed assault, a total of around 9,000&amp;nbsp;cavalry in 67&amp;nbsp;squadrons.{{sfn|Adkin|2001|p=356}} When Napoleon saw the charge he said it was an hour too soon.{{sfn|Esposito|Elting|1999|p=354, Map 166}}

[[File:French cuirassiers vs Nassauers.jpg|thumb|''French [[Cuirassier]]s'', by Louis Dumoulin]]

Wellington's infantry responded by forming squares (hollow box-formations four ranks deep). Squares were much smaller than usually depicted in paintings of the battle—a 500-man battalion square would have been no more than {{convert|60|ft}} in length on a side. Squares that stood their ground were deadly to cavalry, as cavalry could not engage with soldiers behind a hedge of bayonets, but were themselves vulnerable to fire from the squares. Horses would not charge a square, nor could they be outflanked, but they were vulnerable to artillery or infantry. Wellington ordered his artillery crews to take shelter within the squares as the cavalry approached, and to return to their guns and resume fire as they retreated.{{sfn|Siborne&lt;!--W--&gt;|1895|pp=444, 447}}{{sfn|Adkin|2001|pp=273, 414}}

Witnesses in the British infantry recorded as many as 12&amp;nbsp;assaults, though this probably includes successive waves of the same general attack; the number of general assaults was undoubtedly far fewer. Kellermann, recognising the futility of the attacks, tried to reserve the elite ''carabinier'' brigade from joining in, but eventually Ney spotted them and insisted on their involvement.{{sfn|Adkin|2001|p=359}}

A British eyewitness of the first French cavalry attack, an officer in the Foot Guards, recorded his impressions very lucidly and somewhat poetically:

{{quote|About four p.m., the enemy's artillery in front of us ceased firing all of a sudden, and we saw large masses of cavalry advance: not a man present who survived could have forgotten in after life the awful grandeur of that charge. You discovered at a distance what appeared to be an overwhelming, long moving line, which, ever advancing, glittered like a stormy wave of the sea when it catches the sunlight. On they came until they got near enough, whilst the very earth seemed to vibrate beneath the thundering tramp of the mounted host. One might suppose that nothing could have resisted the shock of this terrible moving mass. They were the famous cuirassiers, almost all old soldiers, who had distinguished themselves on most of the battlefields of Europe. In an almost incredibly short period they were within twenty yards of us, shouting ''&quot;Vive l'Empereur!&quot;'' The word of command, &quot;Prepare to receive cavalry&quot;, had been given, every man in the front ranks knelt, and a wall bristling with steel, held together by steady hands, presented itself to the infuriated cuirassiers.|Captain Rees Howell Gronow, Foot Guards.{{sfn|Gronow|1862|loc=''The Duke of Wellington in our square''}} }}

[[File:Artillery in Battle of Waterloo by Jones.jpg|thumb|&quot;The artillery officers had the range so accurately, that every shot and shell fell into the very centre of their masses&quot; (Original inscription and drawing after [[George Jones (painter)|George Jones]])]]

In essence this type of massed cavalry attack relied almost entirely on psychological shock for effect.{{sfn|Weller|1992|pp=211, 212}} Close artillery support could disrupt infantry squares and allow cavalry to penetrate; at Waterloo, however, co-operation between the French cavalry and artillery was not impressive. The French artillery did not get close enough to the Anglo-allied infantry in sufficient numbers to be decisive.{{sfn|Adkin|2001|pp=252, 361}} Artillery fire between charges did produce mounting casualties, but most of this fire was at relatively long range and was often indirect, at targets beyond the ridge. If infantry being attacked held firm in their square defensive formations, and were not panicked, cavalry on their own could do very little damage to them. The French cavalry attacks were repeatedly repelled by the steadfast infantry squares, the harrying fire of British artillery as the French cavalry recoiled down the slopes to regroup, and the decisive countercharges of Wellington's light cavalry regiments, the Dutch heavy cavalry brigade, and the remaining effectives of the Household Cavalry. At least one artillery officer disobeyed Wellington's order to seek shelter in the adjacent squares during the charges. [[Cavalié Mercer|Captain Mercer]], who commanded [[G Parachute Battery (Mercer's Troop) Royal Horse Artillery|'G' Troop]], [[Royal Horse Artillery]], thought the Brunswick troops on either side of him so shaky that he kept his battery of six nine-pounders in action against the cavalry throughout, to great effect.{{sfn|Mercer|1870a|pp=313–315}}{{efn|This qualification may have been self-serving on Mercer's part. Wellington himself sought refuge in the &quot;shaky&quot; Brunswick squares at the time and observed what he interpreted as acts of cowardice by British artillerymen, who &quot;...&amp;nbsp;ran off the field entirely, taking with them limbers, ammunition, and everything&amp;nbsp;...&quot; as he wrote in a letter of 21 December 1815 to the Master-General of the Ordnance, Lord Mulgrave. The incident even justified the denial of pensions to members of the Artillery Corps in his view. So, where Mercer claimed heroism, Wellington saw the opposite. See for the full text of Wellington's letter, and an attempted rebuttal {{citation |last=Duncan |first=F. |year=1879 |title=History of the Royal Regiment of Artillery |chapter=Appendix A |pages=[https://archive.org/stream/historyofroyalre02duncuoft#page/444/mode/2up 444]–464 }} — The letter was originally published in ''WSD'', vol. XIV (1858 ed.), pp. 618–620}}

{{quote|I thus allowed them to advance unmolested until the head of the column might have been about fifty or sixty yards from us, and then gave the word, &quot;Fire!&quot; The effect was terrible. Nearly the whole leading rank fell at once; and the round shot, penetrating the column carried confusion throughout its extent&amp;nbsp;... the discharge of every gun was followed by a fall of men and horses like that of grass before the mower's scythe. |Captain [[Cavalié Mercer]], RHA.{{sfn|Mercer|1870a|p=321}} }}

[[File:Charge of the French Cuirassiers at Waterloo.jpg|right|thumb|upright=1.2|A British square puts up dogged resistance against attacking French cavalry]]

For reasons that remain unclear, no attempt was made to [[Touch hole|spike]] other Anglo-allied guns while they were in French possession. In line with Wellington's orders, gunners were able to return to their pieces and fire into the French cavalry as they withdrew after each attack. After numerous costly but fruitless attacks on the Mont-Saint-Jean ridge, the French cavalry was spent.{{efn|Cavalrymen were not allowed to dismount without orders, so individual initiative in spiking a cannon would have been impossible for any ranker. Each British cannon had a number of headless nails for spiking stored in a box on the gun carriage, so the French would have had the means to disable the guns readily available, had they known {{Harv|Weller|1992|p=114}}.}} Their casualties cannot easily be estimated. Senior French cavalry officers, in particular the generals, experienced heavy losses. Four divisional commanders were wounded, nine brigadiers wounded, and one killed—testament to their courage and their habit of leading from the front.{{sfn|Adkin|2001|p=359}} Illustratively, Houssaye reports that the ''Grenadiers à Cheval'' numbered 796 of all ranks on 15 June, but just 462 on 19 June, while the Empress Dragoons lost 416 of 816 over the same period.{{sfn|Houssaye|1900|p=522}} Overall, Guyot's Guard heavy cavalry division lost 47% of its strength.

===Second French infantry attack===
[[File:Charge des lanciers de la Garde à Waterloo (détail du Panorama de Waterloo).jpg|thumb|left|[[2e régiment de chevau-légers lanciers de la Garde Impériale|2nd Guard Lancers]] with the ''[[Grenadiers à Cheval de la Garde Impériale|Grenadiers à Cheval]]'' in support{{efn|A number of different mounts could have been ridden by Napoleon at Waterloo: Ali, Crebère, Désirée, Jaffa, Marie and Tauris ({{Harvnb|Summerville|2007|loc=[https://books.google.com/books?id=q_cXSrh0C_IC&amp;pg=PA315 p. 315]}}) Lozier states it was Désirée {{harv|Lozier|2010}}.}}]]
Eventually it became obvious, even to Ney, that cavalry alone were achieving little. Belatedly, he organised a combined-arms attack, using Bachelu's division and Tissot's regiment of Foy's division from Reille's II Corps (about 6,500&amp;nbsp;infantrymen) plus those French cavalry that remained in a fit state to fight. This assault was directed along much the same route as the previous heavy cavalry attacks (between Hougoumont and La Haye Sainte).{{sfn|Adkin|2001|p=361}} It was halted by a charge of the Household Brigade cavalry led by Uxbridge. The British cavalry were unable, however, to break the French infantry, and fell back with losses from musketry fire.{{sfn|Siborne&lt;!--HT--&gt;|1891|pp=14, 38–39}}

Uxbridge recorded that he tried to lead the Dutch Carabiniers, under Major-General [[Albert Dominicus Trip van Zoudtlandt|Trip]], to renew the attack and that they refused to follow him. Other members of the British cavalry staff also commented on this occurrence.{{sfn|Siborne&lt;!--HT--&gt;|1891|loc=pp. 14–15 and letters 6, 7 and 9}} However, there is no support for this incident in Dutch or Belgian sources.{{efn|1=On the contrary, many contradicted this British account vehemently. See e.g.{{Harvnb|Eenens|1879|pp= 131–198}}. [https://books.google.com/books?id=sxdJAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PT23 Google Books;] {{citation |author-link=Willem Jan Knoop|last=Knoop |first= W.J. |chapter=Beschouwingen over Siborne's Geschiedenis van den oorlog van 1815 in Frankrijk en de Nederlanden |title=en wederlegging van de in dat werk voorkomende beschuldigingen tegen het Nederlandsche leger |location=Breda |origyear=1846 |edition=2nd |year=1847}}; {{citation |authorlink=Willem Benjamin Craan| last=Craan |first=W.B. |translator-first=A. |translator-last=Gore |year=1817 |title=An historical account of the battle of Waterloo |pages=[https://archive.org/details/anhistoricalacc00goregoog 30]–31}} – written in 1816 on the basis of eyewitness accounts does not mention the incident).}} Meanwhile, Bachelu's and Tissot's men and their cavalry supports were being hard hit by fire from artillery and from Adam's infantry brigade, and they eventually fell back.{{sfn|Adkin|2001|p=361}} Although the French cavalry caused few direct casualties to Wellington's centre, artillery fire onto his infantry squares caused many. Wellington's cavalry, except for Sir John Vandeleur's and Sir Hussey Vivian's brigades on the far left, had all been committed to the fight, and had taken significant losses. The situation appeared so desperate that the Cumberland Hussars, the only Hanoverian cavalry regiment present, fled the field spreading alarm all the way to Brussels.{{sfn|Siborne&lt;!--W--&gt;|1895|p=465}}{{efn|The commander of the Cumberland Hussars, who was later court-martialled and cashiered, claimed that as his troopers (all well-to-do young Hanoverians) owned their own horses he could not order them to remain on the field. Following the battle the regiment was broken up and the troopers assigned duties they, no doubt, considered ignominious. Four were posted to Captain Mercer's horse artillery troop, where he found them &quot;amazingly sulky and snappish with every one&quot;.{{Harv|Mercer|1870b|p=62}} }}

===French capture of La Haye Sainte===
[[File:Knotel - The storming of La Haye Sainte.jpg|thumb|alt=''The storming of La Haye Sainte'' by Knötel|''The storming of La Haye Sainte'' by Knötel]]

At approximately the same time as Ney's combined-arms assault on the centre-right of Wellington's line, rallied elements of D'Erlon's I Corps, spearheaded by the 13th ''Légère,'' renewed the attack on La Haye Sainte and this time were successful, partly because the King's German Legion's ammunition ran out. However, the Germans had held the centre of the battlefield for almost the entire day, and this had stalled the French advance.{{sfn|Simms|2014|pp=59–60, 63–64}}{{sfn|Beamish|1995|p=367}}

With La Haye Sainte captured, Ney then moved skirmishers and [[horse artillery]] up towards Wellington's centre.{{sfn|Siborne&lt;!--W--&gt;|1895|p=483}} French artillery began to pulverise the infantry squares at short range with [[canister shot|canister]].{{sfn|Siborne&lt;!--W--&gt;|1895|p=484}} The 30th and 73rd Regiments suffered such heavy losses that they had to combine to form a viable square.{{sfn|Barbero|2006|p=236}}

{{quote|The possession of La Haye Sainte by the French was a very dangerous incident. It uncovered the very centre of the Anglo-allied army, and established the enemy within 60 yards of that centre. The French lost no time in taking advantage of this, by pushing forward infantry supported by guns, which enabled them to maintain a most destructive fire upon Alten's left and Kempt's right ...|Captain James Shaw, [[43rd Foot]], Chief of Staff 3rd Division.{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|p=134}} }}

The success Napoleon needed to continue his offensive had occurred.{{sfn|Barbero|2006|p=234}} Ney was on the verge of breaking the Anglo-allied centre.{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|p=134}}

Along with this artillery fire a multitude of French ''tirailleurs'' occupied the dominant positions behind La Haye Sainte and poured an effective fire into the squares. The situation for the Anglo-allies was now so dire that the 33rd Regiment's colours and all of Halkett's brigade's colours were sent to the rear for safety, described by historian Alessandro Barbero as, &quot;...&amp;nbsp;a measure that was without precedent&quot;.{{sfn|Barbero|2006|p=241}} Wellington, noticing the slackening of fire from La Haye Sainte, with his staff rode closer to it. French skirmishers appeared around the building and fired on the British command as it struggled to get away through the hedgerow along the road. The Prince of Orange then ordered a single battalion of the KGL, the Fifth, to recapture the farm despite the obvious presence of enemy cavalry. Their Colonel, [[Christian Friedrich Wilhelm von Ompteda]] obeyed and led the battalion down the slope, chasing off some French skirmishers until French cuirassiers fell on his open flank, killed him, destroyed his battalion and took its colour.{{sfn|Barbero|2006|p=234}} A Dutch–Belgian cavalry regiment ordered to charge retreated from the field instead, fired on by their own infantry. Merlen's Light Cavalry Brigade charged the French artillery taking position near La Haye Sainte but were shot to pieces and the brigade fell apart. The Netherlands Cavalry Division, Wellington's last cavalry reserve behind the centre having lost half their strength was now useless and the French cavalry, despite its losses, were masters of the field, compelling the Anglo-allied infantry to remain in square. More and more French artillery was brought forward.{{sfn|Barbero|2006|pp=235–236}}

A French battery advanced to within 300 yards of the 1/1st Nassau square causing heavy casualties. When the Nassauers attempted to attack the battery they were ridden down by a squadron of cuirassiers. Yet another battery deployed on the flank of Mercer's battery and shot up its horses and limbers and pushed Mercer back. Mercer later recalled, &quot;The rapidity and precision of this fire was quite appalling. Every shot almost took effect, and I certainly expected we should all be annihilated. ... The saddle-bags, in many instances were torn from horses' backs ... One shell I saw explode under the two finest wheel-horses in the troop down they dropped&quot;.{{sfn|Barbero|2006|pp=235–236}}{{sfn|Mercer|1870a|pp=325–326}}

French ''tirailleurs'' occupied the dominant positions, especially one on a knoll overlooking the square of the 27th. Unable to break square to drive off the French infantry because of the presence of French cavalry and artillery, the 27th had to remain in that formation and endure the fire of the ''tirailleurs''. That fire nearly annihilated the 27th Foot, the Inniskillings, who lost two thirds of their strength within that three or four hours.{{sfn|Barbero|2006|pp=239}}

{{quote|The banks on the road side, the garden wall, the knoll and sandpit swarmed with skirmishers, who seemed determined to keep down our fire in front; those behind the artificial bank seemed more intent upon destroying the 27th, who at this time, it may literally be said, were lying dead in square; their loss after La Haye Sainte had fallen was awful, without the satisfaction of having scarcely fired a shot, and many of our troops in rear of the ridge were similarly situated.|Edward Cotton, 7th Hussars|{{sfn|Cotton|1849|pp=106–107}} }}

During this time many of Wellington's generals and aides were killed or wounded including Somerset, Canning, de Lancey, Alten and Cooke.{{sfn|Barbero|2006|p=240}} The situation was now critical and Wellington, trapped in an infantry square and ignorant of events beyond it, was desperate for the arrival of help from the Prussians. He later wrote, {{quote|The time they occupied in approaching seemed interminable. Both they and my watch seemed to have stuck fast.{{sfn|Barbero|2006|p=242}} }}

===Arrival of the Prussian IV Corps: Plancenoit===
{{See also|Waterloo Campaign: Ligny through Wavre to Waterloo#Prussians take possession of Wood of Paris|l1=Prussians attack out of the Wood of Paris}}
{{quote|Night or the Prussians must come.|Wellington.{{sfn|Barbero|2006|p=242}} }}

[[File:Prussian Attack Plancenoit by Adolf Northern.jpg|thumb|upright=1.2|The Prussian attack on [[Plancenoit]] painted by [[Adolph Northen]]]]

The [[Order of battle of the Waterloo campaign#Prussian IV Corps|Prussian IV Corps]] (Bülow's) was the first to arrive in strength. Bülow's objective was Plancenoit, which the Prussians intended to use as a springboard into the rear of the French positions. Blücher intended to secure his right upon the [[Châteaux Frichermont]] using the Bois de Paris road.{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|p=116}} Blücher and Wellington had been exchanging communications since 10:00 and had agreed to this advance on Frichermont if Wellington's centre was under attack.{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|p=95}}{{efn|Chesney states that Wellington and the Prussians remained in contact and that it was agreed that Bülow followed by Pirch would take the poorer road to &quot;Froidmont&quot; (Frichermont), while Zieten would take the longer northern, but better made, road via Ohain {{Harv|Chesney|1874|pp=173–178}}.}} General Bülow noted that the way to Plancenoit lay open and that the time was 16:30.{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|p=116}}

At about this time, the [[Order of battle of the Waterloo campaign#Prussian 15th Brigade|Prussian 15th Brigade]] ({{interlanguage link|Michael Heinrich von Losthin|de|lt=Losthin's|vertical-align=sup}}) was sent to link up with the Nassauers of Wellington's left flank in the Frichermont-[[La Haye, Lasne|La Haie]] area, with the brigade's horse artillery battery and additional brigade artillery deployed to its left in support.{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|p=117}} Napoleon sent Lobau's corps to stop the rest of Bülow's IV Corps proceeding to Plancenoit. The 15th Brigade threw Lobau's troops out of Frichermont with a determined bayonet charge, then proceeded up the Frichermont heights, battering French Chasseurs with 12-pounder artillery fire, and pushed on to Plancenoit. This sent Lobau's corps into retreat to the Plancenoit area, driving Lobau past the rear of the ''Armee Du Nord's'' right flank and directly threatening its only line of retreat. Hiller's 16th Brigade also pushed forward with six battalions against Plancenoit.{{citation needed|date=August 2016|reason=from the last citation lots of facts so a citation is needed}}

Napoleon had dispatched all eight battalions of the Young Guard to reinforce Lobau, who was now seriously pressed. The Young Guard counter-attacked and, after very hard fighting, secured Plancenoit, but were themselves counter-attacked and driven out.{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|p=122}} Napoleon sent two battalions of the Middle/Old Guard into Plancenoit and after ferocious bayonet fighting—they did not deign to fire their muskets—this force recaptured the village.{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|p=122}}

===Zieten's flank march===
[[File:Battle of Waterloo map.jpg|thumb|upright=1.4|Situation from 17:30 to 20:00]]

Throughout the late afternoon, the [[Order of battle of the Waterloo campaign#Prussian I Corps|Prussian I Corps]] (Zieten's) had been arriving in greater strength in the area just north of La Haie. General Müffling, the Prussian liaison to Wellington, rode to meet Zieten.

Zieten had by this time brought up the [[Order of battle of the Waterloo campaign#Prussian 1st Brigade|Prussian 1st Brigade]] ([[Karl Friedrich Franciscus von Steinmetz|Steinmetz]]'s), but had become concerned at the sight of stragglers and casualties from the Nassau units on Wellington's left and from the Prussian 15th Brigade (Laurens'). These troops appeared to be withdrawing and Zieten, fearing that his own troops would be caught up in a general retreat, was starting to move away from Wellington's flank and towards the Prussian main body near Plancenoit. Zieten had also received a direct order from Blücher to support Bülow, which Zieten obeyed, starting to march to Bülow's aid.

Müffling saw this movement away and persuaded Zieten to support Wellington's left flank.{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|p=125}} Müffling warned Zieten that &quot;The battle is lost if the corps does not keep on the move and immediately support the English army.&quot;{{sfn|Uffindell|Corum|2002|p=232}} Zieten resumed his march to support Wellington directly, and the arrival of his troops allowed Wellington to reinforce his crumbling centre by moving cavalry from his left.{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|p=125}}

The French were expecting Grouchy to march to their support from Wavre, and when Prussian I Corps (Zieten's) appeared at Waterloo instead of Grouchy, &quot;the shock of disillusionment shattered French morale&quot; and &quot;the sight of Zieten's arrival caused turmoil to rage in Napoleon's army&quot;.{{sfn|Uffindell|Corum|2002|p=233}} I Corps proceeded to attack the French troops before Papelotte and by 19:30 the French position was bent into a rough horseshoe shape. The ends of the line were now based on Hougoumont on the left, Plancenoit on the right, and the centre on La Haie.{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|p=139}} Durutte had taken the positions of La Haie and Papelotte in a series of attacks,{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|p=139}} but now retreated behind Smohain without opposing the Prussian 24th Regiment (Laurens') as it retook both. The 24th advanced against the new French position, was repulsed, and returned to the attack supported by Silesian ''Schützen'' (riflemen) and the F/1st ''Landwehr''.{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|p=140}} The French initially fell back before the renewed assault, but now began seriously to contest ground, attempting to regain Smohain and hold on to the ridgeline and the last few houses of Papelotte.{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|p=140}}

The Prussian 24th Regiment linked up with a Highlander battalion on its far right and along with the [[Order of battle of the Waterloo campaign#Prussian 4th Brigade|13th ''Landwehr'' Regiment]] and cavalry support threw the French out of these positions. Further attacks by the 13th ''Landwehr'' and the 15th Brigade drove the French from Frichermont.{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|p=141}} Durutte's division, finding itself about to be charged by massed squadrons of Zieten's I Corps cavalry reserve, retreated from the battlefield. The rest of d'Erlon's I Corps also broke and fled in panic, while to the west the French Middle Guard were assaulting Wellington's centre.{{sfn|Uffindell|Corum|2002|pp=232–233}}{{sfn|Chesney|1874|pp=187–190}} The Prussian I Corps then advanced towards the Brussels road, the only line of retreat available to the French.

===Attack of the Imperial Guard===
[[File:Crofts-Napoleon's last grand attack at Waterloo.jpg|thumb|Napoleon addresses the [[Old Guard (France)|Old Guard]] as it prepares to attack the Anglo-allied centre at Waterloo]]

Meanwhile, with Wellington's centre exposed by the fall of La Haye Sainte and the Plancenoit front temporarily stabilised, Napoleon committed his last reserve, the hitherto-undefeated Imperial Guard infantry. This attack, mounted at around 19:30, was intended to break through Wellington's centre and roll up his line away from the Prussians. Although it is one of the most celebrated passages of arms in military history, it had been unclear which units actually participated. It appears that it was mounted by five battalions of the Middle Guard,{{efn|Two chasseur battalions of the 4th Chasseurs were merged into one on the day of the battle, so while five Imperial Guard formations went forward, they may have comprised six battalions {{Harv|Barbero|2005|loc={{Page needed|date=May 2010}}}}. Similarly, Lewis, 2013, pp. 188–190.{{Full citation needed|date=December 2016}} }} and not by the grenadiers or chasseurs of the Old Guard. Three Old Guard battalions did move forward and formed the attack's second line, though they remained in reserve and did not directly assault the Anglo-allied line.{{sfn|Adkin|2001|p=391}}{{efn|The attacking battalions were 1st/3rd and 4th Grenadiers and 1st/3rd, 2nd/3rd and 4th Chasseurs of the Middle Guard; those remaining in reserve were the 2nd/2nd Grenadiers, 2nd/1st and 2nd/2nd Chasseurs of the Old Guard {{harv|Adkin|2001|p=392}}.}}

{{quote|...&amp;nbsp;I saw four regiments of the middle guard, conducted by the Emperor, arriving. With these troops, he wished to renew the attack, and penetrate the centre of the enemy. He ordered me to lead them on; generals, officers and soldiers all displayed the greatest intrepidity; but this body of troops was too weak to resist, for a long time, the forces opposed to it by the enemy, and it was soon necessary to renounce the hope which this attack had, for a few moments, inspired. |Marshal M. Ney.{{sfn|Booth|1815|pp=73, 74}} }}

[[File:Soldat-der-Alten-Garde.png|thumb|upright|left|[[Grenadier]] of the [[Old Guard (France)|Old Guard]] in ''[[Le Grenadier]]'' by [[Édouard Detaille]]]]

Napoleon himself oversaw the initial deployment of the Middle and Old Guard. The Middle Guard formed in battalion squares, each about 550 men strong, with the 1st/3rd Grenadiers, led by Generals [[Louis Friant|Friant]] and [[Paul-Jean-Baptiste Poret de Morvan|Poret de Morvan]], on the right along the road, to their left and rear was General Harlet leading the square of the 4th Grenadiers, then the 1st/3rd Chasseurs under General [[Claude-Étienne Michel|Michel]], next the 2nd/3rd Chasseurs and finally the large single square of two battalions of 800 soldiers of the 4th Chasseurs led by General Henrion. Two batteries of Imperial Guard Horse Artillery accompanied them with sections of two guns between the squares. Each square was led by a general and Marshal Ney, mounted on his 5th horse of the day, led the advance.{{sfn|Field|2013|pp=191–192}} Behind them, in reserve, were the three battalions of the Old Guard, right to left 1st/2nd Grenadiers, 2nd/2nd Chasseurs and 1st/2nd Chasseurs. Napoleon left Ney to conduct the assault; however, Ney led the Middle Guard on an oblique towards the Anglo-allied centre right instead of attacking straight up the centre. Napoleon sent Ney's senior ADC Colonel Crabbé to order Ney to adjust, but Crabbé was unable to get there in time.

Other troops rallied to support the advance of the Guard. On the left infantry from Reille's corps that was not engaged with Hougoumont and cavalry advanced. On the right all the now rallied elements of D'Érlon's corps once again ascended the ridge and engaged the Anglo-allied line. Of these, Pégot's brigade broke into skirmish order and moved north and west of La Haye Sainte and provided fire support to Ney, once again unhorsed, and Friant's 1st/3rd Grenadiers. The Guards first received fire from some Brunswick battalions, but the return fire of the grenadiers forced them to retire. Next, Colin Halket's brigade front line consisting of the 30th Foot and 73rd traded fire but they were driven back in confusion into the 33rd and 69th regiments, Halket was shot in the face and seriously wounded and the whole brigade retreated in a mob. Other Anglo-allied troops began to give way as well. A counterattack by the Nassauers and the remains of Kielmansegge's brigade from the Anglo-allied second line, led by the Prince of Orange, was also thrown back and the Prince of Orange was seriously wounded. General Harlet brought up the 4th Grenadiers and the Anglo-allied centre was now in serious danger of breaking.

[[File:General D H Chassé.jpg|thumb|upright|General D H Chassé|General [[David Hendrik Chassé]]]]

It was at this moment that the timely arrival of the Dutch General [[David Hendrik Chassé|Chassé]] turned the tide in favour of the Anglo-allied army.{{sfn|Field|2013|pp=196–199}} Chassé's relatively fresh Dutch division was sent against them, led by a battery of Dutch horse-artillery commanded by Captain [[Carel Frederik Krahmer de Bichin|Krahmer de Bichin]]. The battery opened a destructive fire into the 1st/3rd Grenadiers' flank.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Bas|Wommersom|1909|pp=249–251, 258–259.}} (vol.2)&lt;/ref&gt; This still did not stop the Guard's advance, so Chassé ordered his first brigade, commanded by Colonel [[Hendrik Detmers]], to charge the outnumbered French with the bayonet; the French grenadiers then faltered and broke.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Bas|Wommersom|1909|pp=252–253, 419–424.}} (vol.2)&lt;/ref&gt; The 4th Grenadiers, seeing their comrades retreat and having suffered heavy casualties themselves, now wheeled right about and retired.{{sfn|Field|2013|p=199}}

[[File:Plas Newydd (Anglesey) - Waterloo 1.jpg|thumb|left|British 10th Hussars of Vivian's Brigade (red shakos – blue uniforms) attacking mixed French troops, including a square of Guard grenadiers (left, middle distance) in the final stages of the battle]]

To the left of the 4th Grenadiers were the two squares of the 1st/ and 2nd/3rd Chasseurs who angled further to the west and had suffered more from artillery fire than the grenadiers. But as their advance mounted the ridge they found it apparently abandoned and covered with dead. Suddenly 1,500 British Foot Guards under [[Peregrine Maitland|Maitland]] who had been lying down to protect themselves from the French artillery rose and devastated them with point-blank volleys. The chasseurs deployed to answer the fire, but some 300 fell from the first volley, including Colonel Mallet and General Michel, and both battalion commanders.{{sfn|Field|2013|p=200}} A bayonet charge by the Foot Guards then broke the leaderless squares, which fell back onto the following column. The 4th Chasseurs battalion, 800 strong, now came up onto the exposed battalions of British Foot Guards, who lost all cohesion and dashed back up the slope as a disorganized crowd with the chasseurs in pursuit. At the crest the chasseurs came upon the battery that had caused severe casualties on the 1st and 2nd/3rd Chasseurs. They opened fire and swept away the gunners. The left flank of their square now came under fire from a heavy formation of British skirmishers, which the chasseurs drove back. But the skirmishers were replaced by the [[52nd (Oxfordshire) Regiment of Foot|52nd Light Infantry]], led by [[John Colborne]], which wheeled in line onto the chasseurs' flank and poured a devastating fire into them. The chasseurs returned a very sharp fire which killed or wounded some 150 men of the 52nd.{{sfn|Field|2013|pp=203}} The 52nd then charged,{{sfn|Chesney|1874|pp=214–215}}{{sfn|Parry|1900|p=70}} and under this onslaught, the chasseurs broke.{{sfn|Parry|1900|p=70}}

The last of the Guard retreated headlong. A ripple of panic passed through the French lines as the astounding news spread: &quot;''La Garde recule. Sauve qui peut''!&quot; (&quot;The Guard is retreating. Every man for himself!&quot;) Wellington now stood up in [[Copenhagen (horse)|Copenhagen]]'s stirrups and waved his hat in the air to signal a general advance. His army rushed forward from the lines and threw themselves upon the retreating French.{{sfn|Chesney|1874|pp=192, 225}}{{sfn|Siborne|1895|pp=553–559}}

The surviving Imperial Guard rallied on their three reserve battalions (some sources say four) just south of La Haye Sainte for a [[last stand]]. A charge from [[Frederick Adam|Adam]]'s Brigade and the Hanoverian ''Landwehr'' Osnabrück Battalion, plus Vivian's and Vandeleur's relatively fresh cavalry brigades to their right, threw them into confusion. Those left in semi-cohesive units retreated towards ''La Belle Alliance''. It was during this retreat that some of the Guards were invited to surrender, eliciting the famous, if apocryphal,{{efn|1=&quot;'The Guard dies, but it does not surrender!' is another of these fictitious historical sayings. General Cambronne, to whom it is attributed, never uttered. Victor Hugo, in Les Misérables, has restored the true text. It is composed of a single word [''Merde!'']&quot;.{{harv|Masson|1869}} }} retort &quot;''La Garde meurt, elle ne se rend pas!''&quot; (&quot;The Guard dies, it does not surrender!&quot;).{{sfn|White|2011}}{{efn|The reply is commonly attributed to General [[Pierre Cambronne]], originating from an attribution by the journalist Balison de Rougemont in ''Journal General'' published on 24 June 1815,{{harv|Shapiro|2006|p=128}} although Cambronne claimed he replied &quot;''Merde!''&quot; {{harv|Boller|1989|p=12}} However, according to letters in ''[[The Times]]'' in June 1932, Cambronne was already a prisoner of Colonel [[Hugh Halkett]], so the retort, if ever given, or in whatever form it took, may have come from [[Claude-Etienne Michel|General Michel]] instead.{{harvnb|White|2011}}, and {{Harvnb|Parry|1900|p=70}} }}

==={{anchor|Capture of Plancenoit}}Prussian capture of Plancenoit===
[[File:Ludwig Elsholtz Erstürmung von Planchenois.jpg|thumb|right|The storming of Plancenoit by [[Ludwig Elsholtz]]]]
At about the same time, the Prussian 5th, 14th, and 16th Brigades were starting to push through Plancenoit, in the third assault of the day. The church was by now on fire, while its graveyard—the French centre of resistance—had corpses strewn about &quot;as if by a whirlwind&quot;. Five Guard battalions were deployed in support of the Young Guard, virtually all of which was now committed to the defence, along with remnants of Lobau's corps. The key to the Plancenoit position proved to be the Chantelet woods to the south. Pirch's II Corps had arrived with two brigades and reinforced the attack of IV Corps, advancing through the woods.{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|pp=144–145}}

The 25th Regiment's musketeer battalions threw the 1/2e Grenadiers (Old Guard) out of the Chantelet woods, outflanking Plancenoit and forcing a retreat. The Old Guard retreated in good order until they met the mass of troops retreating in panic, and became part of that rout. The Prussian IV Corps advanced beyond Plancenoit to find masses of French retreating in disorder from British pursuit. The Prussians were unable to fire for fear of hitting Wellington's units. This was the fifth and final time that Plancenoit changed hands.{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|pp=144–145}}&lt;!--This citation is paragraph inclusive.--&gt;

French forces not retreating with the Guard were surrounded in their positions and eliminated, neither side asking for nor offering quarter. The French Young Guard Division reported 96&amp;nbsp;per cent casualties, and two-thirds of Lobau's Corps ceased to exist.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.battleofwaterloo.org/|title=The Battle of Waterloo|website=Battle of Waterloo}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Cuirass holed by a canonball at Waterloo Antoine Fauveau 18Juin 1815.jpg|thumb|upright|''[[Carabiniers-à-Cheval|Carabinier-à-Cheval]]'' cuirass holed by a cannonball at Waterloo, belonging to Antoine Fauveau ([[Musée de l'Armée]])]]

{{quote|Despite their great courage and stamina, the French Guards fighting in the village began to show signs of wavering. The church was already on fire with columns of red flame coming out of the windows, aisles and doors. In the village itself—still the scene of bitter house-to-house fighting—everything was burning, adding to the confusion. However, once Major von Witzleben's manoeuvre was accomplished and the French Guards saw their flank and rear threatened, they began to withdraw. The Guard Chasseurs under General [[Jean-Jacques Germain Pelet-Clozeau|Pelet]] formed the rearguard. The remnants of the Guard left in a great rush, leaving large masses of artillery, equipment and ammunition wagons in the wake of their retreat. The evacuation of Plancenoit led to the loss of the position that was to be used to cover the withdrawal of the French Army to Charleroi. The Guard fell back from Plancenoit in the direction of Maison du Roi and Caillou. Unlike other parts of the battlefield, there were no cries of &quot;Sauve qui peut!&quot; here. Instead, the cry &quot;Sauvons nos aigles!&quot; (&quot;Let's save our eagles!&quot;) could be heard.|Official History of the 25th Regiment, 4 Corps{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|pp=144–145}}}}

===French disintegration===
[[File:Dernier carre de la Garde - gen Hill.png|thumb|left|upright=1.2|[[Rowland Hill, 1st Viscount Hill|Lord Hill]] invites the last remnants of the French Imperial Guard to surrender, painted by [[Robert Alexander Hillingford]].]]

The French right, left, and centre had all now failed.{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|pp=144–145}} The last cohesive French force consisted of two battalions of the Old Guard stationed around ''La Belle Alliance''; they had been so placed to act as a final reserve and to protect Napoleon in the event of a French retreat. He hoped to rally the French army behind them,{{sfn|Kincaid|2006|p=435}} but as retreat turned into rout, they too were forced to withdraw, one on either side of ''La Belle Alliance'', in square as protection against Coalition cavalry. Until persuaded that the battle was lost and he should leave, Napoleon commanded the square to the left of the inn.{{sfn|Creasy|1877|loc=[http://www.standin.se/fifteen15a.htm Chapter XV]}}{{sfn|Comte d'Erlon|1815|loc=}} Adam's Brigade charged and forced back this square,{{sfn|Parry|1900|p=70}}{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|p=149}} while the Prussians engaged the other.

As dusk fell, both squares withdrew in relatively good order, but the French artillery and everything else fell into the hands of the Prussian and Anglo-allied armies. The retreating Guards were surrounded by thousands of fleeing, broken French troops. Coalition cavalry harried the fugitives until about 23:00, with Gneisenau pursuing them as far as Genappe before ordering a halt. There, Napoleon's abandoned carriage was captured, still containing [[s:The Annotated Prince|an annotated copy]] of [[Machiavelli]]'s ''[[The Prince]]'', and diamonds left behind in the rush to escape. These diamonds became part of King Friedrich Wilhelm of Prussia's crown jewels; one Major Keller of the F/15th received the [[Pour le Mérite]] with oak leaves for the feat.{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|p=151}} By this time 78&amp;nbsp;guns and 2,000&amp;nbsp;prisoners had also been taken, including more generals.{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|p=150}}

{{quote|There remained to us still four squares of the Old Guard to protect the retreat. These brave grenadiers, the choice of the army, forced successively to retire, yielded ground foot by foot, till, overwhelmed by numbers, they were almost entirely annihilated. From that moment, a retrograde movement was declared, and the army formed nothing but a confused mass. There was not, however, a total rout, nor the cry of ''sauve qui peut'', as has been calumniously stated in the bulletin.|Marshal M. Ney.{{sfn|Booth|1815|p=74}} }}

{{quote|In the middle of the position occupied by the French army, and exactly upon the height, is a farm (sic), called ''La Belle Alliance''. The march of all the Prussian columns was directed towards this farm, which was visible from every side. It was there that Napoleon was during the battle; it was thence that he gave his orders, that he flattered himself with the hopes of victory; and it was there that his ruin was decided. There, too, it was that, by happy chance, Field Marshal Blücher and Lord Wellington met in the dark, and mutually saluted each other as victors.|General Gneisenau.{{sfn|Booth|1815|p=23}} }}

Other sources agree that the meeting of the commanders took place near ''La Belle Alliance'', with this occurring at around 21:00.{{sfn|Davies|2012|p=244}}{{sfn|Corrigan|2006|p=327}}

==Aftermath==
{{Main|Waterloo Campaign#Invasion of France and the occupation of Paris (18 June – 7 July)|Treaty of Paris (1815)}}
[[File:Morgen nach der Schlacht967b.jpg|thumb|&quot;The morning after the battle of Waterloo&quot;, by [[John Heaviside Clark]], 1816]]

Waterloo cost Wellington around 15,000 dead or wounded and Blücher some 7,000 (810 of which were suffered by just one unit: the 18th Regiment, which served in Bülow's 15th Brigade, had fought at both Frichermont and Plancenoit, and won 33 [[Iron Cross]]es).{{sfn|Mantle|2000}} Napoleon's losses were 24,000 to 26,000 killed or wounded and included 6,000 to 7,000 captured with an additional 15,000 deserting subsequent to the battle and over the following days.{{sfn|Barbero|2006|p=312}}

{{quote|22&amp;nbsp;June. This morning I went to visit the field of battle, which is a little beyond the village of Waterloo, on the plateau of Mont-Saint-Jean; but on arrival there the sight was too horrible to behold. I felt sick in the stomach and was obliged to return. The multitude of carcasses, the heaps of wounded men with mangled limbs unable to move, and perishing from not having their wounds dressed or from hunger, as the Anglo-allies were, of course, obliged to take their surgeons and waggons with them, formed a spectacle I shall never forget. The wounded, both of the Anglo-allies and the French, remain in an equally deplorable state.|Major W. E. Frye.{{sfn|Frye|2004|loc=''June 22''}} }}

[[File:Invasion of France in 1815.jpg|thumb|Invasion of France by the Seventh Coalition armies in 1815]]

At 10:30 on 19 June General Grouchy, still following his orders, defeated General Thielemann at Wavre and withdrew in good order—though at the cost of 33,000 French troops that never reached the Waterloo battlefield. Wellington sent [[s:Wellingon's Waterloo dispatch to Lord Bathurst, 19 June 1815|his official dispatch]] describing the battle to England on 19 June 1815; it arrived in London on 21 June 1815 and was published as a ''[[The London Gazette|London Gazette Extraordinary]]'' on 22 June.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gazette, 17028&quot;&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=17028|page=1213|date=22 June 1815}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wellington, Blücher and other Coalition forces advanced upon Paris.

Napoleon announced his [[Abdication of Napoleon, 1815|second abdication]] on 24 June 1815. In the final skirmish of the Napoleonic Wars, Marshal [[Davout]], Napoleon's minister of war, was defeated by Blücher at [[Battle of Issy|Issy]] on 3 July 1815.{{sfn|Wood|1907}} Allegedly, Napoleon tried to escape to North America, but the [[Royal Navy]] was blockading French ports to forestall such a move. He finally surrendered to [[Captain (Royal Navy)|Captain]] [[Frederick Lewis Maitland|Frederick Maitland]] of [[Her Majesty's Ship|HMS]] ''[[HMS Bellerophon (1786)|Bellerophon]]'' on 15 July. There was a campaign against French fortresses that still held out; [[Longwy]] capitulated on 13 September 1815, the last to do so. [[Louis XVIII]] was restored to the throne of France and Napoleon was exiled to [[Saint Helena]], where he died in 1821. The [[Treaty of Paris (1815)|Treaty of Paris]] was signed on 20 November 1815.{{sfn|Hofschröer|1999|pp=274–276, 320}}

{{quote|Royal Highness, – Exposed to the factions which divide my country, and to the enmity of the great Powers of Europe, I have terminated my political career; and I come, like [[Themistocles]], to throw myself upon the hospitality (''m'asseoir sur le foyer'') of the British people. I claim from your Royal Highness the protections of the laws, and throw myself upon the most powerful, the most constant, and the most generous of my enemies.|Napoleon. (letter of surrender to the [[George IV of the United Kingdom|Prince Regent]]; translation).{{sfn|Booth|1815|p=57}} }}

[[File:David Wilkie Chelsea Pensioners Reading the Waterloo Dispatch.jpg|thumb|upright=1.2|[[David Wilkie (artist)|Sir David Wilkie]], ''[[The Chelsea Pensioners reading the Waterloo Dispatch]]'', 1822]]

Maitland's [[Grenadier Guards|1st Foot Guards]], who had defeated the Chasseurs of the Imperial Guard, were thought to have defeated the Grenadiers, although they had only faced Chasseurs of the newly raised Middle Guard.{{sfn|Barbero|2006|p=264}} They were nevertheless awarded the title of Grenadier Guards in recognition of their feat and adopted bearskins in the style of the Grenadiers. Britain's Household Cavalry likewise adopted the cuirass in 1821 in recognition of their success against their armoured French counterparts. The effectiveness of the lance was noted by all participants and this weapon subsequently became more widespread throughout Europe; the British converted their first light cavalry regiment to lancers in 1816, their uniforms, of Polish origin, were based on those of the [[Polish 1st Light Cavalry Regiment of the Imperial Guard|Imperial Guard lancers]].

Teeth of tens of thousands of dead soldiers were removed by surviving troops, locals or even scavengers who had travelled there from Britain, then used for making denture replacements in Britain and elsewhere.&lt;ref&gt;Paul Kerley: [https://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-33085031 The dentures made from the teeth of dead soldiers at Waterloo], BBC News Magazine (16 June 2015)&lt;/ref&gt; The so-called &quot;Waterloo teeth&quot; were in demand because they came from relatively healthy young men. Despite the efforts of scavengers both human and otherwise, human remains could still be seen at Waterloo a year after the battle.&lt;ref&gt;Shannon Selin, &quot;[https://shannonselin.com/2016/07/napoleonic-battlefield-cleanup/ How were Napoleonic battlefields cleaned up?]&quot;; accessed 2019.06.18.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Analysis==
===Historical importance===

Waterloo proved a decisive battle in more than one sense. Every generation in Europe up to the outbreak of the [[First World War]] looked back at Waterloo as the turning point that dictated the course of subsequent world history, seeing it in retrospect as the event that ushered in the [[Concert of Europe]], an era characterised by relative peace, material prosperity and technological progress.&lt;ref&gt;Barbero (2005), p. 422&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
Compare:
{{cite book
| last1 = Barbero
| first1 = Alessandro
| author-link1 = Alessandro Barbero
| translator1-last = Cullen
| translator1-first = John
| year = 2003
| chapter = Epilogue
| title = The Battle: A new history of Waterloo
| chapter-url = https://books.google.com/books?id=NEoMT0B0CfAC
| location = London
| publisher = Atlantic Books Ltd
| publication-date = 2013
| page =
| isbn = 978-1782391388
| access-date = 2018-01-31
| quote = Most [...] would have agreed with the French writer's statement: 'On that day, the perspective of the human race was altered. Waterloo is the hinge of the Nineteenth Century.' [...] Later, the twentieth century swept away the illusions of unlimited progress and perpetual peace that had become widespread after Waterloo.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
The battle definitively ended the series of wars that had convulsed Europe, and involved many other regions of the world, since the [[French Revolution]] of the early 1790s. It also ended the [[First French Empire]] and the political and military career of Napoleon Bonaparte, one of the greatest commanders and statesmen in history.&lt;ref&gt;Barbero (2005), pp. 422–423&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|Through the finality of Napoleon's defeat, &quot;met his/her Waterloo&quot; has entered the English lexicon as a phrase to describe someone's circumstances when they have met with absolute and final defeat.}}

There followed almost four decades of international peace in Europe. No further major conflict occurred until the [[Crimean War]] of 1853–1856. Changes to the configuration of European states, as refashioned after Waterloo, included the formation of the [[Holy Alliance]] of reactionary governments intent on repressing revolutionary and democratic ideas, and the reshaping of the former [[Holy Roman Empire]] into a [[German Confederation]] increasingly marked by the political dominance of [[Prussia]]. The bicentenary of Waterloo prompted renewed attention to the geopolitical and economic legacy of the battle and to the century of relative transatlantic peace which followed.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Rapport|2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Black|2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Keeling|2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|Napoleon's last escapade was important politically because it &quot;compelled all the powers at Vienna to bury their remaining differences in order to achieve a peace which would enshrine the principles of the balance of power&quot;.{{Harv|Kennedy|1987|p= 37}} &quot;No international disturbance comparable in magnitude...has ever been followed by such a protracted period of peace&quot;. {{Harv|Palmer|1956|p=420}} Recovering, after Waterloo, from six decades of abnormal obstacles to transatlantic commerce (from the Seven Years War onwards), increasingly industrialized Europe and North America, by 1914, accounted for over 90% of global coal, iron and steel production and 76% of international trade.{{Harv|Paxton|1985|p= 2}} }}

===Views on the reasons for Napoleon's defeat===
General [[Antoine-Henri Jomini|Antoine-Henri]], Baron Jomini, one of the leading military writers on the Napoleonic art of war, had a number of very cogent explanations of the reasons behind Napoleon's defeat at Waterloo.{{efn|Jomini was Swiss, but was an officer, eventually a general, in the French army and had served on the staff of Marshal Ney. He later served in the Russian Army.}}

{{quote|
In my opinion, four principal causes led to this disaster:

The first, and most influential, was the arrival, skilfully combined, of Blücher, and the false movement that favoured this arrival;{{efn|This &quot;false movement&quot; was the detachment of Grouchy's force in pursuit of the Prussians: Napoleon had overestimated the extent of his victory at Ligny and underestimated the resilience of the Prussians. He also seems to have discounted the presence of Bülow's substantial corps, which had not been in action at Ligny. Had Napoleon retained Grouchy's 30,000 men as a guard for his right flank, it is likely that these troops could have held off the Prussians and allowed the rest of Napoleon's army to attack Wellington's army unmolested.}} the second, was the admirable firmness of the British infantry, joined to the sang-froid and aplomb of its chiefs; the third, was the horrible weather, that had softened the ground, and rendered the offensive movements so toilsome, and retarded till one o'clock the attack that should have been made in the morning; the fourth, was the inconceivable formation of the first corps, in masses very much too deep for the first grand attack.|Antoine-Henri Jomini.{{sfn|Jomini|1864|pp=223, 224}} }}

The Prussian soldier, historian, and theorist [[Carl von Clausewitz]], who as a young colonel had served as chief-of-staff to Thielmann's Prussian III Corps during the Waterloo campaign, expressed the following opinion:

{{quote|
Bonaparte and the authors who support him have always attempted to portray the great catastrophes that befell him as the result of chance. They seek to make their readers believe that through his great wisdom and extraordinary energy the whole project had already moved forward with the greatest confidence, that complete success was but a hair's breadth away, when treachery, accident, or even fate, as they sometimes call it, ruined everything. He and his supporters do not want to admit that huge mistakes, sheer recklessness, and, above all, overreaching ambition that exceeded all realistic possibilities, were the true causes.|Carl von Clausewitz.{{sfn|Clausewitz|Feldzug von 1815 (''Campaign of 1815'')|loc=''[http://www.clausewitz.com/readings/1815/five1-9.htm#Ch3 Chapter 3]''}} }}

Wellington himself wrote in his official dispatch back to London:

{{quote|I should not do justice to my own feelings, or to Marshal Blücher and the Prussian army, if I did not attribute the successful result of this arduous day to the cordial and timely assistance I received from them. The operation of General Bülow upon the enemy's flank was a most decisive one; and, even if I had not found myself in a situation to make the attack which produced the final result, it would have forced the enemy to retire if his attacks should have failed, and would have prevented him from taking advantage of them if they should unfortunately have succeeded&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gazette, 17028&quot;/&gt;}}
Despite their differences on other matters, discussed at length in Carl von Clausewitz's study of the ''Campaign of 1815'' and ''Wellington's famous 1842 essay'' in reply to it, the Prussian Clausewitz agreed with Wellington on this assessment.{{sfn|Clausewitz|Wellington|2010|loc=''[http://www.clausewitz.com/readings/1815/five1-9.htm Campaign of 1815]'' and ''[http://www.clausewitz.com/readings/1815/six.htm Wellington's famous 1842 essay]''}} Indeed, Clausewitz viewed the battle prior to the Prussian intervention more as a mutually exhausting stalemate than as an impending French victory, with the advantage, if any, leaning towards Wellington.{{sfn|Clausewitz|Wellington|2010|pp=144–145 (Chapter 41 of Clausewitz's ''Feldzug'')}}

An alternative view is that towards the end of the battle Wellington's Anglo-allied army faced imminent defeat without Prussian help. For example, Parkinson (2000) writes: &quot;Neither army beat Napoleon alone. But whatever the part played by Prussian troops in the actual moment when the Imperial Guard was repulsed, it is difficult to see how Wellington could have staved off defeat, when his centre had been almost shattered, his reserves were almost all committed, the French right remained unmolested and the Imperial Guard intact. .... Blücher may not have been totally responsible for victory over Napoleon, but he deserved full credit for preventing a British defeat&quot;.{{sfn|Parkinson|2000|pp=240–241}} Steele (2014) writes: &quot;Blücher's arrival not only diverted vital reinforcements, but also forced Napoleon to accelerate his effort against Wellington. The tide of battle had been turned by the hard-driving Blücher. As his Prussians pushed in Napoleon's flank, Wellington was able to shift to the offensive&quot;.{{sfn|Steele|2014|p=178}}

==Battlefield today==
{{further|List of Waterloo Battlefield locations}}
[[File:0 Braine-l'Alleud 051012 (1).JPG|thumb|The [[Lion's Mound]] at Waterloo]]

Some portions of the terrain on the battlefield have been altered from their 1815 appearance. Tourism began the day after the battle, with Captain Mercer noting that on 19 June &quot;a carriage drove on the ground from Brussels, the inmates of which, alighting, proceeded to examine the field&quot;.{{sfn|Mercer|1870a|p=345}} In 1820, the Netherlands' King [[William I of the Netherlands|William I]] ordered the construction of a monument. The [[Lion's Mound]], a giant artificial hill, was constructed here using {{convert|300000|m3|cuyd}} of earth taken from the ridge at the centre of the British line, effectively removing the southern bank of Wellington's sunken road.

{{quote|Every one is aware that the variously inclined undulations of the plains, where the engagement between Napoleon and Wellington took place, are no longer what they were on 18&amp;nbsp;June 1815. By taking from this mournful field the wherewithal to make a monument to it, its real relief has been taken away, and history, disconcerted, no longer finds her bearings there. It has been disfigured for the sake of glorifying it. Wellington, when he beheld Waterloo once more, two years later, exclaimed, &quot;They have altered my field of battle!&quot; Where the great pyramid of earth, surmounted by the lion, rises to-day, there was a hillock which descended in an easy slope towards the Nivelles road, but which was almost an escarpment on the side of the highway to Genappe. The elevation of this escarpment can still be measured by the height of the two knolls of the two great sepulchres which enclose the road from Genappe to Brussels: one, the English tomb, is on the left; the other, the German tomb, is on the right. There is no French tomb. The whole of that plain is a sepulchre for France.|[[Victor Hugo]], ''[[Les Misérables]]''.{{sfn|Hugo|1862|loc=Chapter VII: Napoleon in a Good Humor}} }}

The alleged remark by Wellington about the alteration of the battlefield as described by Hugo was never documented, however.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/history/10218931/Rescuing-the-farm-where-Wellington-won-the-battle-of-Waterloo.html|title=Rescuing the farm where Wellington won the battle of Waterloo|last=Shute|first=Joe|date=2013-08-02|access-date=2018-01-17|language=en-GB|issn=0307-1235}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other terrain features and notable landmarks on the field have remained virtually unchanged since the battle. These include the rolling farmland to the east of the Brussels–Charleroi Road as well as the buildings at Hougoumont, La Haye Sainte, and La Belle Alliance.

Apart from the Lion Mound, there are several more conventional but noteworthy monuments throughout the battlefield. A cluster of monuments at the Brussels–Charleroi and Braine L'Alleud–Ohain crossroads marks the mass graves of British, Dutch, Hanoverian and King's German Legion troops. A monument to the French dead, entitled ''L'Aigle blessé'' (&quot;The Wounded Eagle&quot;), marks the location where it is believed one of the Imperial Guard units formed a square during the closing moments of the battle.{{sfn|Hoorebeeke|2007|pp=6–21}}

A monument to the Prussian dead is located in the village of Plancenoit on the site where one of their artillery batteries took position. The [[Guillaume Philibert Duhesme|Duhesme]] mausoleum is one among the few graves of the fallen. It is located at the side of Saint Martin's Church in Ways, a hamlet in the municipality of [[Genappe]]. Seventeen fallen officers are buried in the crypt of the [[Brussels Cemetery#The British Waterloo Campaign Monument|British Monument]] in the [[Brussels Cemetery]] in [[Evere]].{{sfn|Hoorebeeke|2007|pp=6–21}} The remains of a 23-year-old soldier named Friederich Brandt were discovered in 2012.{{sfn|Paton|2015}} He was a slightly hunchbacked infantryman, {{convert|1.60|m}} tall, and was hit in the chest by a French bullet. His rifle, coins, and position on the battlefield identified him as an Hanoverian fighting in the King's German Legion.{{sfn|Peel|2012}}

==Coin controversy==
As part of the bicentennial celebration of the battle, in 2015 [[Belgium]] minted a two-[[euro]] coin depicting the Lion monument over a map of the field of battle. France officially protested against this issue of coins, while the Belgian government noted that the French mint sells souvenir medals at Waterloo.{{sfn|Torfs|2015}} After 180,000 coins were minted but not released, the issue was melted. Instead, Belgium issued an identical commemorative coin in the non-standard value of 2{{sfrac|1|2}} euros. Legally valid only within the issuing country (but unlikely to circulate) it was minted in brass, packaged, and sold by the Belgian mint for 6 euros. A ten-euro coin, showing Wellington, Blücher, their troops and the silhouette of Napoleon, was also available in silver for 42 euros.{{sfn|Kottasova|2015}}

==Recent discovery at Mont St. Jean==
On 15 July 2019, archaeologists at [[Mont-Saint-Jean, Belgium]], found evidence of a shooting clash that happened there between attacking French cavalry and defending British infantry, including 58 [[musket ball]]s and 3 amputated human leg bones.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.itv.com/news/2019-07-17/human-remains-and-cannon-ball-unearthed-at-battle-of-waterloo-hospital-site/ |title=Human remains and cannon ball unearthed at Battle of Waterloo hospital site |date=17 July 2019 |access-date=20 September 2019 |work=[[ITV News]] |publisher=[[ITV plc]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/2019/07/17/veterans-unearth-amputated-leg-bones-musket-balls-waterloo-field/ |title=Soldier archaeologists unearth musket balls and amputated leg bones at Battle of Waterloo field hospital site |first=James |last=Crisp |date=17 July 2019 |access-date=20 September 2019 |newspaper=[[Telegraph (newspaper)|Telegraph]] |publisher=[[Telegraph Media Group Limited]] |page=16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|France|War}}
* [[Lord Uxbridge's leg]] was shattered by a [[grape-shot]] at the Battle of Waterloo and removed by a surgeon. The artificial leg used by Uxbridge for the rest of his life was donated to a Waterloo Museum after his death. There is also a second leg on display at his house, Plas Newydd, on Anglesey.
*[[Order of battle of the Waterloo campaign]]
* [[Napoleonic Wars]] (1803–1815): involved Napoleon Bonaparte's French Empire against the United Kingdom and various combinations of other European powers in the [[War of the Third Coalition|Third]] to [[Hundred Days|Seventh]] coalitions.
* [[Timeline of the Napoleonic era]]
* [[Waterloo in popular culture]]: describes the cultural impact of the battle.
* [[Waterloo Medal]] awarded to those soldiers of the [[British Army]] who fought at the battle.
* [[Battle of Waterloo reenactment]]

==Notes==
{{notelist|1}}
{{Reflist}}

==References==
* {{Citation |last=Adkin |first=Mark |year=2001 |title=The Waterloo Companion |publisher=Aurum |isbn=978-1-85410-764-0}}
* {{Citation |last=Anglesey |first=Marquess of (George C.H.V. Paget) |year=1990 |title=One Leg: The Life and Letters of Henry William Paget, First Marquess of Anglesey, K.G. 1768–1854 |publisher=Pen and Sword|isbn=978-0-85052-518-2}}
* {{Citation |last=Barbero |first=Alessandro |year=2005 |title=The Battle: A New History of Waterloo |publisher=Atlantic Books |isbn=978-1-84354-310-7}}
* {{Citation |last=Barbero |first=Alessandro |year=2006 |title=The Battle: A New History of Waterloo (translated by John Cullen)|edition=paperback|publisher=Walker &amp; Company |isbn=978-0-8027-1500-5}}
* {{Citation |last=Barbero |first=Alessandro |year=2013 |title=The Battle: A New History of Waterloo |publisher=Atlantic Books|isbn=978-1-78239-138-8 |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=NEoMT0B0CfAC&amp;pg=PT160 160]}}
* {{Citation |last=Bas |first=F de |authorlink=François de Bas |last2=Wommersom |first2=J. De T'Serclaes de |year=1909 |title=La campagne de 1815 aux Pays-Bas d'après les rapports officiels néerlandais |volume=volumes: I: Quatre-Bras. II: Waterloo. III: Annexes and notes. IV: supplement: maps and plans |publisher=Librairie Albert de Wit |location=Brussels}}
* {{Citation| last=Beamish |first=N. Ludlow |year=1995 |origyear=1832 |title=History of the King's German Legion |publisher=Dallington: Naval and Military Press |isbn=978-0-9522011-0-6}}
* {{Citation |last=Black |first=Jeremy |date=24 February 2015 |title=Legacy of 1815 |url=http://www.historytoday.com/jeremy-black/legacy-1815 |journal=History Today}}
* {{Citation |last=Boller, Jr. |first=Paul F. |last2=George, Jr. |first2=John |year=1989 |title=They Never Said It: A Book of Fake Quotes, Misquotes, and Misleading Attributions |publisher=New York: Oxford University Press |isbn=978-0-19-505541-2 |page=[https://archive.org/details/theyneversaiditb00boll/page/12 &amp;#91;https://books.google.com/books?id=NCOEYJ0q-DUC 12&amp;#93;] |ref={{sfnRef|Boller|1989}} |url=https://archive.org/details/theyneversaiditb00boll/page/12 }}
* {{Citation|last=Bonaparte |first=Napoleon |year=1869 |editor1-last=Polon |editor1-first=Henri |editor2-last=Dumaine |editor2-first=J. |title=Correspondance de Napoléon Ier; publiée par ordre de l'empereur Napoléon III (1858)|chapter-url=https://archive.org/stream/correspondancede28napouoft#page/292/mode/1up |chapter=No. 22060|volume=28 |pages=292, 293}}.
* {{Citation |last=Booth |first=John |year=1815 |title=The Battle of Waterloo: Containing the Accounts Published by Authority, British and Foreign, and Other Relevant Documents, with Circumstantial Details, Previous and After the Battle, from a Variety of Authentic and Original Sources |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9IIBAAAAYAAJ |edition=2 |publisher=London: printed for J. Booth and T. Ergeton; Military Library, Whitehall}}
* {{Citation |last=Boulger |first=Demetrius C. deK. |year=1901 |title=Belgians at Waterloo: With Translations of the Reports of the Dutch and Belgian Commanders |location=London}}
* {{citation |title=Napoleonic Satires |website=Brown University Library |url=http://dl.lib.brown.edu/napoleon/time7.html | ref={{sfnref|Brown University Library}} | accessdate=22 July 2016}}
* {{Citation |last=Chandler |first=David |year=1966 |title=The Campaigns of Napoleon |publisher=New York: Macmillan}}
* {{Citation |last=Chesney |first=Charles C. |year=1874 |title=Waterloo Lectures: A Study Of The Campaign Of 1815 |edition=3rd |publisher=Longmans, Green, and Co |url=https://archive.org/details/waterloolectures00ches}}
* {{Citation |last=Clark-Kennedy |first=A.E. |year=1975 |title=Attack the Colour! The Royal Dragoons in the Peninsula and at Waterloo |publisher=Research Publishing Co. |place=London}}
* {{citation| last=Clausewitz |first=Carl von |last2=Wellington |first2=Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of |year=2010 |title=On Waterloo: Clausewitz, Wellington, and the Campaign of 1815. |editor-first=Christopher |editor-last=Bassford |editor2-first=Daniel |editor2-last=Moran |editor3-last=Pedlow |editor3-first=Gregory W. |publisher=Clausewitz.com |isbn=978-1453701508 |url=http://www.clausewitz.com/readings/1815/index.htm}}
* {{Citation |last=Cornwell |first=Bernard |authorlink=Bernard Cornwell |year=2015 |chapter=Those terrible grey horses, how they fight |title=Waterloo: The History of Four Days, Three Armies and Three Battles |publisher=Lulu Press, Inc|isbn=978-1-312-92522-9 |page= ~[https://books.google.com/books?id=z6N3CgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT137 128]}}
* {{Citation |last=Corrigan |first=Gordon |year=2006 |title=Wellington |edition=reprint, eBook |publisher=Continuum International Publishing Group |isbn=978-0-8264-2590-4 |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=0AgapOzStrAC&amp;pg=PA32 327]}}
* {{Citation |last=Cotton |first=Edward |year=1849 |title=A voice from Waterloo. A history of the battle, on 18 June 1815.| publisher=London: B.L. Green}}
* {{Citation |last=Creasy |first=Sir Edward |year=1877 |url=http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/4061 |title=The Fifteen Decisive Battles of the World: from Marathon to Waterloo |publisher=London: Richard Bentley &amp; Son |isbn=978-0-306-80559-2}}
* {{Citation |last=Davies |first=Huw |year=2012 |title=Wellington's Wars: The Making of a Military Genius |edition=illustrated |publisher=Yale University Press |isbn=978-0-300-16417-6 |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=_sCxNtg1H8IC&amp;pg=PA244 244]}}
* {{Citation |last=Eenens |first=A.M |authorlink=Alexis-Michel Eenens |year=1879 |title=&quot;Dissertation sur la participation des troupes des Pays-Bas a la campagne de 1815 en Belgique&quot;, in: Societé royale des beaux arts et de litérature de Gand, Messager des Sciences Historiques |publisher=Vanderhaegen |location=Gand}}
* {{Citation| last= Comte d'Erlon| first= Jean-Baptiste Drouet| authorlink= Jean-Baptiste Drouet, Comte d'Erlon| year= 1815| title= Drouet's account of Waterloo to the French Parliament| url= http://www.napoleonbonaparte.nl/newspaper/dedham/drouet.html| publisher= Napoleon Bonaparte Internet Guide| accessdate= 14 September 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20071008105416/http://www.napoleonbonaparte.nl/newspaper/dedham/drouet.html| archivedate= 8 October 2007| url-status= dead}}
* {{Citation |last=Esposito |first=Vincent Joseph| last2=Elting| first2=John |year=1999 |title=A Military History and Atlas of the Napoleonic Wars| publisher=Greenhill|isbn=978-1-85367-346-7}}
* {{Citation |last=Field |first=Andrew W. |year=2013 |title= Waterloo The French Perspective |location=Great Britain |publisher=Pen &amp; Sword Books |isbn=978-1-78159-043-0}}
* {{Citation| last=Fitchett |first=W.H. |year=2006 |origyear=1897 |title=Deeds that Won the Empire. Historic Battle Scenes |url=http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/19255 |location=London |publisher=John Murray |chapter-url=http://www.gutenberg.org/files/19255/19255-h/19255-h.htm#chap1900 |chapter=Chapter: King-making Waterloo}} ([[Project Gutenberg]])
* {{Citation |last=Fletcher |first=Ian |year=1994 |title=Wellington's Foot Guards |volume=52 of Elite Series |edition=illustrated |publisher=Osprey Publishing|isbn=978-1-85532-392-6}}
* {{Citation |last=Fletcher |first=Ian |year=1999 |title=Galloping at Everything: The British Cavalry in the Peninsula and at Waterloo 1808–15|publisher=Spellmount|place= Staplehurst|isbn=978-1-86227-016-9}}
* {{Citation |last=Fletcher |first=Ian |year=2001 |title=A Desperate Business: Wellington, The British Army and the Waterloo Campaign'', Spellmount|place=Staplehurst, Kent}}
* {{Citation |last=Frye |first=W.E. |year=2004 |origyear=1908 |url=http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/10939 |title=After Waterloo: Reminiscences of European Travel 1815–1819| publisher=[[Project Gutenberg]]| accessdate=29 April 2015}}
* {{Citation| last=Glover |first=G. |year=2004 |title= Letters from the Battle of Waterloo: the unpublished correspondence by Anglo-allied officers from the Siborne papers |location=London |publisher=Greenhill |isbn=978-1-85367-597-3}}
* {{Citation |last=Glover |first=Gareth |title=From Corunna to Waterloo: the Letters and Journals of Two Napoleonic Hussars, 1801–1816 |location=London |publisher=Greenhill Books |year=2007}}
* {{Citation|first1=Gareth|last1=Glover|title=Waterloo: Myth and Reality|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=GfpsBQAAQBAJ|year=2014|publisher=Pen and Sword|isbn=978-1-78159-356-1}}
* {{Citation |last=Grant |first=Charles |year=1972 |title=Royal Scots Greys (Men-at-Arms)|publisher=Osprey |isbn=978-0-85045-059-0}}
* {{Citation |last=Gronow |first=R.H. |authorlink=Rees Howell Gronow |year=1862 |url=http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/3798 |title=Reminiscences of Captain Gronow|publisher=London |isbn=978-1-4043-2792-4}}
* {{Citation |last=Hamilton-Williams |first=David |year=1993 |title=Waterloo. New Perspectives. The Great Battle Reappraised |publisher=Arms &amp; Armour Press |location=London |isbn=978-0-471-05225-8}}
* {{Citation |last=Hamilton-Williams |first=David |year=1994 |title=Waterloo, New Perspectives, The Great Battle Reappraised|edition=Paperback |location=New York |publisher=John Wiley and Sons|isbn=978-0-471-14571-4}}
* {{Citation |last=Herold |first=J. Christopher |year=1967 |title=The Battle of Waterloo|location=New York |publisher=Harper &amp; Row |isbn=978-0-304-91603-0}}
* {{Citation |last=Haweis |first=James Walter |year=1908 |url=https://archive.org/details/cu31924024320891 |title=The campaign of 1815, chiefly in Flanders |location=Edinburgh |publisher=William Blackwood and Sons |pages=[https://archive.org/stream/cu31924024320891#page/n250/mode/1up 228]–229}}
* {{Citation |last=Hofschröer| first=Peter |year=1999 |title=1815: The Waterloo Campaign. The German Victory |volume=2 |publisher=London: Greenhill Books |isbn=978-1-85367-368-9}}
* {{Citation |last=Hofschröer| first=Peter |year=2005 |title=Waterloo 1815: Quatre Bras and Ligny |publisher=London: Leo Cooper |isbn=978-1-84415-168-4}}
* {{Citation |last=Hoorebeeke |first=C. van |title=Blackman, John-Lucie : pourquoi sa tombe est-elle à Hougomont? |journal=Bulletin de l'Association Belge Napoléonienne |number=118 |date=September–October 2007 |pages=6–21}}
* {{Citation |last=Houssaye |first=Henri |year=1900 |title=Waterloo (translated from the French)|publisher=London}}
* {{Citation |last=Hugo |first=Victor |authorlink=Victor Hugo |year=1862 |title=Les Misérables| chapter-url=http://www.online-literature.com/victor_hugo/les_miserables/77/ |chapter=Chapter VII: Napoleon in a Good Humor | publisher=The Literature Network |accessdate=14 September 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20071012165710/http://www.online-literature.com/victor_hugo/les_miserables/77/| archivedate= 12 October 2007 | url-status= live}}
* {{Citation |last=Jomini |first=Antoine-Henri |authorlink=Antoine-Henri Jomini |year=1864 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=FVdEAAAAIAAJ |title=The Political and Military History of the Campaign of Waterloo| edition=3 |publisher=New York; D. Van Nostrand }} (Translated by Benet S.V.)
* {{Citation |last=Keeling |first=Drew |date=27 May 2015 |url=http://whartonmagazine.com/blogs/business-history-dividends-of-waterloo/ |title=The Dividends of Waterloo|accessdate=3 June 2015}}
* {{Citation |last=Kennedy |first=Paul |year=1987 |title=The Rise and Fall of Great Powers |publisher= New York: Random House}}
* {{Citation |last=Kincaid |first=Captain J. |year=2006 |chapter=The Final Attack The Rifle Brigade Advance 7 pm 18 June 1815 |editor-last=Lewis-Stemple |editor-first=John |title=England: The Autobiography: 2,000 Years of English History by Those Who Saw it Happen |edition=reprint |location=UK |publisher=Penguin |isbn=978-0-14-192869-2 |pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=kRArkAr-yxoC&amp;pg=PT434 434]–436}}
* {{citation |last=Kottasova |first=Ivana |date=10 June 2015 |url=http://money.cnn.com/2015/06/10/news/waterloo-coin-belgium-france/index.html|title=France's new Waterloo? Euro coin marks Napoleon's defeat|work=CNNMoney}}
* {{citation |last=Lamar |first=Glenn J. |year=2000 |title=Jérôme Bonaparte: The War Years, 1800–1815|publisher=Greenwood Press|isbn=978-0-313-30997-7 |page=119 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0NBnAAAAMAAJ}}
* {{Citation |last=Longford |first=Elizabeth |authorlink=Elizabeth Longford |year=1971 |title=Wellington the Years of the Sword |publisher=London: Panther| isbn=978-0-586-03548-1}}
* {{Citation |last=Low |first=E. Bruce |year=1911 |chapter=The Waterloo Papers |editor-last=MacBride |editor-first= M. |title=With Napoleon at Waterloo |location=London |chapter-url=https://archive.org/details/withnapoleonatwa00macbuoft}}
* {{Citation |last=Lozier |first=J.F. |date=18 June 2010 |url=http://www.napoleon-series.org/faq/c_horses.html |title=What was the name of Napoleon's horse? |publisher= The Napoleon Series |accessdate=29 March 2009}}
* {{Citation |last=Mantle |first=Robert |date=December 2000 |title=Prussian Reserve Infantry 1813–1815: Part II: Organisation |publisher=Napoleonic Association |url=http://www.napoleon-series.org/military/organization/c_resinf2.html|accessdate=}}.{{better source|date=June 2013}}
* {{Citation |last=Marcelis |first=David |date=10 June 2015 |url=https://www.wsj.com/articles/when-napoleon-met-his-waterloo-he-was-out-of-town-1433894903 |title=When Napoleon Met His Waterloo, He Was Out of Town |newspaper=Wall Street Journal}}
* {{Citation |last=Mercer |first=A.C. |year=1870a |title=Journal of the Waterloo Campaign: Kept Throughout the Campaign of 1815 |volume=1 |location=Edinburgh and London |publisher=W. Blackwood |url=https://archive.org/details/journalofwaterlo01mercuoft}}
* {{Citation |last=Mercer |first=A.C. |year=1870b |chapter=Waterloo, 18 June 1815: The Royal Horse Artillery Repulse Enemy Cavalry, late afternoon |title=Journal of the Waterloo Campaign: Kept Throughout the Campaign of 1815 |volume=2 |chapter-url=https://archive.org/details/journalofwaterlo02mercuoft}}
* {{citation |author-last=Mercer |author-first=A.C. |author-link=Cavalié Mercer |year=1891 |chapter=No 89:Royal Artillery |editor-last=Siborne |editor-first=Herbert Taylor |chapter-url=https://archive.org/details/waterlooletterss00sibo |title=Waterloo letters: a selection from original and hitherto unpublished letters bearing on the operations of the 16th, 17th, and 18th June, 1815, by officers who served in the campaign |location=London |publisher=Cassell &amp; Company|page=[https://archive.org/stream/waterlooletterss00sibo#page/218/mode/1up 218]}}
* {{citation |first=David |last=Masson |display-authors=etal |title=Historical Forgeries and Kosciuszko's &quot;Finis Poloniae&quot; |journal=Macmillan's Magazine |volume=19 |publisher=Macmillan and Company |year=1869 |page=[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=xt76rS3-RbwC&amp;pg=PA164 164]}}
* {{Citation |last=Nofi |first=Albert A. |year=1998 |origyear=1993 |title=The Waterloo campaign, June 1815 |location=Conshohocken, PA |publisher=Combined Books |isbn=978-0-938289-29-6 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/waterloocampaign0000nofi }}
* {{citation |last1=Oman |first1=Charles |last2=Hall |first2=John A. |year=1902 |title=A History of the Peninsular War |publisher=Clarendon Press |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=q6pBAQAAMAAJ 119]}}
* {{Citation |last=Palmer |first=R.R. |year=1956 |title=A History of the Modern World |publisher= New York: Knopf}}
* {{citation |last=Parkinson |first=Roger |year=2000 |title=Hussar General: The Life of Blücher, Man of Waterloo |publisher=Wordsworth Military Library |isbn=978-1840222531 |pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=x58TZVEU_Q4C&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA240 240]–241}}
* {{Citation |last=Parry |first=D.H. |year=1900 |chapterurl=http://gaslight.mtroyal.ab.ca/waterloo.htm |chapter=Waterloo |title=Battle of the nineteenth century |volume=1 |publisher=London: Cassell and Company |accessdate=14 September 2007 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081216071449/http://gaslight.mtroyal.ab.ca/waterloo.htm |archivedate=16 December 2008 |df=dmy-all }}
* {{citation |last=Paton |first=Callum |date=5 April 2015 |url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/sciencetech/article-3026442/200-year-old-skeleton-hunchback-soldier-killed-battle-Waterloo-Belgian-car-park-believed-trained-Sussex.html |title=Skeleton of soldier killed at Waterloo discovered under a car park like Richard III |newspaper=Daily Mail Online}}
* {{Citation |last=Pawly |first=Ronald |title=Wellington's Belgian Allies |series=Men at Arms nr 98. 1815 |publisher=Osprey |year=2001 |pages=37–43 |isbn=978-1-84176-158-9}}
* {{Citation |last=Paxton |first=Robert O. |year=1985 |title=Europe in the 20th Century |publisher= Orlando: Harcourt Brace Jovanovich}}
* {{Citation |last=Peel |first=Hugues Van |date=11 December 2012 |title=Le soldat retrouvé sur le site de Waterloo serait Hanovrien |publisher=[[RTBF]] |url=http://www.rtbf.be/info/regions/detail_le-soldat-retrouve-sur-le-site-de-waterloo-etait-prussien?id=7890492 |language=French}}
* {{Citation |last=Rapport |first=Mike |date=13 May 2015 |title=Waterloo |newspaper=The New York Times |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2015/05/17/books/review/waterloo.html}}
* {{Citation |last=Roberts |first=Andrew |year=2001 |title=Napoleon and Wellington| publisher=London: Phoenix Press| isbn=978-1-84212-480-2}}
* {{Citation |last=Roberts |first=Andrew |year=2005 |title=Waterloo: 18 June 1815, the Battle for Modern Europe |publisher=New York: HarperCollins |isbn=978-0-06-008866-8 |url=https://archive.org/details/waterloojune181800robe }}
* {{Citation |editor-last=Shapiro |editor-first=Fred R. |year=2006 |title=The Yale Book of Quotations |edition=illustrated |publisher=Yale University Press |isbn=978-0-300-10798-2 |page=[https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780300107982/page/128 &amp;#91;https://books.google.com/books?id=w5-GR-qtgXsC&amp;pg=PA128 128&amp;#93;] |url=https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780300107982/page/128 }}
* {{Citation |last=Siborne |first=Herbert Taylor |authorlink=H. T. Siborne |year=1891 |title=The Waterloo Letters |location=London |publisher=Cassell &amp; Co. |url=https://archive.org/details/waterlooletterss00sibo}}
* {{Citation |last=Siborne |first=William |year=1895 |title=The Waterloo Campaign, 1815 |edition=4th |location=Westminster |publisher=A. Constable |url=https://archive.org/stream/waterloocampaig01sibogoog#page/n6/mode/2up}}
* {{Citation |last=Simms|first=Brendan |year=2014 |title=The Longest Afternoon: The 400 Men Who Decided the Battle of Waterloo |publisher=Allen Lane |isbn=978-0-241-00460-9}}
* {{Citation |last=Smith |first=Digby |year=1998 |title=The Greenhill Napoleonic Wars Data Book |publisher=London &amp; Pennsylvania: Greenhill Books &amp; Stackpole Books |isbn=978-1-85367-276-7}}
* {{citation |last=Steele |first=Charles |year=2014 |title=Germany at War: 400 Years of Military History |editor-last=Zabecki |editor-first=David T. |publisher=ABC-CLIO |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=rCWMBQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA178 178]}}
* {{Citation |last=Summerville |first=Christopher J |year=2007 |title=Who was who at Waterloo: a biography of the battle |publisher=Pearson Education|isbn= 978-0-582-78405-5}}
* {{Citation |last=Thiers|first=Adolphe |year=1862|title=Histoire du consulat et de l'empire, faisant suite à l'Histoire de la révolution française|location=Paris |publisher=Lheureux et Cie.|url=https://archive.org/details/histoireduconsul20thieuoft|volume=20|language=French}}
* {{citation |last=Torfs |first=Michaël |date=12 March 2015 |url=http://deredactie.be/cm/vrtnieuws.english/News/1.2267618 |title=Belgium withdraws 'controversial' Waterloo coin under French pressure, but has a plan B |work=flandersnews.be}}
* {{citation |last=Uffindell |first=Andrew |last2=Corum| first2=Michael |year=2002 |title=On The Fields Of Glory: The Battlefields of the 1815 Campaign |publisher=Frontline Books |isbn=978-1-85367-514-0 |pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=30uaBgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA211 211], 232–233}}
* {{Citation |last=Weller |first=J. |year=1992 |title=Wellington at Waterloo |publisher=London: Greenhill Books |isbn=978-1-85367-109-8}}
* {{Citation |last=Weller |first=J. |year=2010 |title=Wellington at Waterloo |publisher=Frontline Books |isbn=978-1-84832-5-869}}
* {{Citation |last=Wellesley| first=Arthur |authorlink=Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of Wellington |year=1815 |chapterurl=http://www.wtj.com/archives/wellington/1815_06f.htm |chapter=Wellington's Dispatches 19 June 1815 |title=Wellington's Dispatches Peninsular and Waterloo 1808–1815 |publisher=War Times Journal&lt;!-- [http://www.wtj.com/information.htm War Times Journal (Archives)] --&gt;}}
* {{Citation |last=White |first=John |date=14 December 2011 |url=http://www.napoleon-series.org/research/miscellaneous/c_cambronne.html |title=Cambronne's Words, Letters to ''The Times'' (June&amp;nbsp;1932)|publisher=the Napoleon Series |editor-first=Robert |editor-last=Burnham |accessdate=14 September 2007| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070825203333/http://www.napoleon-series.org/research/miscellaneous/c_cambronne.html| archivedate=25 August 2007| url-status= live}}
* {{Citation |last=Wood |first=Evelyn |year=1895 |title=Cavalry in the Waterloo Campaign |publisher=Samson Low, Marston and Company |place=London}}
* {{Cite Nuttall|wstitle=Issy|mode=cs2}}
* {{Citation |last=Wooten |first=Geoffrey |year=1993 |title=Waterloo, 1815: The Birth Of Modern Europe |series=Osprey Campaign Series |volume=15 |location=London |publisher=Reed International Books |page=42}}

==Further reading==
===Articles===
* Anonymous. [http://napoleonistyka.atspace.com/Imperial_Guard_at_Waterloo.htm Napoleon's Guard at Waterloo 1815]
* Bijl, Marco, [https://web.archive.org/web/20160114161435/http://home.scarlet.be/~tsh40803/8/8st.html 8th Dutch Militia] a history of the 8th Dutch Militia battalion and the Bylandt Brigade, of which it was a part, in the 1815 campaign (using original sources from the Dutch and Belgian national archives)
&lt;!-- article removed from web site; dead link
* Muilwijk, Erwin. [http://home.tiscali.nl/erwinmuilwijk/index.htm Contribution of the Netherlands Mobile Army during the 1815 campaign]. Gives full account of the Dutch troops that fought at [[Battle of Quatre Bras|Quatre-Bras]], based on many unknown primary sources.--&gt;
* de Wit, Pierre. [http://www.waterloo-campaign.nl/ The campaign of 1815: a study]. Study of the campaign of 1815, based on sources from all participating armies.
* {{Citation|title=The Cowards at Waterloo|url=http://www.napolun.com/mirror/napoleonistyka.atspace.com/Waterloo_Cowards.html|accessdate=23 March 2013|ref=none}} based on {{citation |last=Dellevoet|first=A. |title=Cowards at Waterloo?: A Re-Examination of Bijlandt's Dutch-Belgian Brigade in the Campaign of 1815 |year=2001|publisher=Stackpole books |ref=none}}

===Books===
* {{Citation| last=Bonaparte| first=Napoleon |year=1995 |editor1-last=Chandler |editor1-first=David G. | editor2-last=Cairnes |editor2-first=William E. |title=The Military Maxims of Napoleon|publisher=Da Capo Press |isbn=978-0-306-80618-6|ref=none}}
* {{Citation |last=Chandler |first=David G. |year=1973 |title=Campaigns of Napoleon |publisher=New York: Scribner |isbn=978-0-02-523660-8 |ref=none |url=https://archive.org/details/campaignsofnapol00chan }}
* {{Citation |last=Chilcott | first=Christopher | year=2015 |title=The Royal Waggon Train: Maintaining the British Army 1803–1833 | publisher=RLC Association Trust Fund |ref=none}}
* {{Citation |last1=[[Carl von Clausewitz|Clausewitz]] |first1=Carl von |last2=Wellesley |first2=Arthur |editor=Christopher Bassford |editor2=Daniel Moran |editor3=Gregory Pedlow |year=2010| url=http://www.clausewitz.com/readings/1815/index.htm |title=On Waterloo: Clausewitz, Wellington, and the Campaign of 1815 | publisher=Clausewitz.com |isbn=978-1-4537-0150-8|ref=none}} This on-line text contains Clausewitz's 58-chapter study of the ''Campaign of 1815'' and Wellington's lengthy 1842 essay written in response to Clausewitz, as well as supporting documents and essays by the editors.
* {{Citation |last=Cookson |first=John E. |year=1996| url=https://books.google.com/books?id=xiV5Q7uupVUC |title=The British Armed Nation, 1793–1815 | publisher=Oxford University Press |isbn=978-0-19-820658-3|ref=none}}
* {{Citation| editor-last=Gleig |editor-first=George Robert |year=1845 |url=http://www.napoleonic-literature.com/Book_24/Book24.htm |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120112122928/http://www.napoleonic-literature.com/Book_24/Book24.htm |archivedate=12 January 2012 |title=The Light Dragoon |publisher=London: George Routledge &amp; Co.|ref=none}}
* {{Citation |last=Glover |first=Michael |year=1973 |title=The Napoleonic Wars: An Illustrated History, 1792–1815 |publisher=Hippocrene Books New York |isbn=978-0-88254-473-1 |ref=none |url=https://archive.org/details/napoleonicwars00glov }}
* {{Citation | last=Hofschröer| first=Peter |year=1998 |title=1815: The Waterloo Campaign: Wellington, His German Allies and the Battles of Ligny and Quatre Bras |volume=1 |publisher=London: Greenhill Books.|isbn=978-1-85367-304-7|ref=none}}
* {{Citation| last=Hofschröer |first=Peter |year=2004 |title=Wellington's Smallest Victory: The Duke, the Model Maker and the Secret of Waterloo |publisher=London: Faber &amp; Faber |isbn=978-0-571-21769-4|ref=none}}
* {{Citation |last=Howarth |first=David |year=1997 |origyear=1968|title=Waterloo a Near Run Thing |publisher=London: Phoenix/Windrush Press |isbn=978-1-84212-719-3|ref=none}}
* {{Citation| last=Keegan| first=John|authorlink=John Keegan|title=The Face of Battle|ref=none| title-link=The Face of Battle}}
* {{Citation |last=Snow |first=Peter |year=2010 |title=To War with Wellington, From the Peninsula to Waterloo |publisher=London: John Murray |isbn=978-1-84854-103-0|ref=none}}

===Historiography and memory===
* {{citation |ref=none |last=Heinzen |first=Jasper |title=A Negotiated Truce: The Battle of Waterloo in European Memory since the Second World War |journal=History &amp; Memory |year=2014 |volume=26 |number=1 |pages=39–74 |url=http://www.muse.jhu.edu/login?auth=0&amp;type=summary&amp;url=/journals/history_and_memory/v026/26.1.heinzen.html |archive-url=https://archive.is/20140506051226/http://www.muse.jhu.edu/login?auth=0&amp;type=summary&amp;url=/journals/history_and_memory/v026/26.1.heinzen.html |url-status=dead |archive-date=2014-05-06 |doi=10.2979/histmemo.26.1.39 }}

===Maps===
* {{citation |ref=none |chapterurl=http://www.lib.utexas.edu/maps/historical/shepherd/waterloo_battle.jpg |chapter=Map of the battlefield |title=Historical Atlas|first=William R. |last=Shepherd |location=New York |publisher=Henry Holt and Company |year=1923 |url=http://www.lib.utexas.edu/maps/historical/history_shepherd_1923.html}} [http://www.lib.utexas.edu/maps/historical/shepherd_1911/shepherd-c-156.jpg The map] from the 1911 edition is also available online.
* [http://napoleonistyka.atspace.com/BATTLE_OF_WATERLOO.htm Battle of Waterloo maps and diagrams]
* [https://maps.google.co.uk/maps/ms?&amp;msa=0&amp;msid=113384660960350206735.00000111ccfa54c3759d7&amp;z=12&amp;om=1 Map of the battlefield on modern Google map and satellite photographs showing main locations of the battlefield]
* [http://nla.gov.au/nla.map-rm1383 1816 Map of the battlefield with initial dispositions] by [[Willem Benjamin Craan]]
* {{citation|ref=none |url=https://www.google.com/maps/d/viewer?mid=z84wlc9K5lB4.k_XQZ6gsCz54 |title=Battle of Waterloo |publisher=Google Maps }}

'''Primary sources'''
{{Wikisource portal|Waterloo Campaign}}
{{Wikisource portal|Hundred Days}}
* [http://www.open.edu/openlearn/history-the-arts/history/world-history/breaking-news-wellington-defeats-napoleon-waterloo Earliest report of the battle in a London newspaper from The Morning Post 22 June 1815]
* {{London Gazette|issue=17037|pages=1359–1362|date=8 July 1815}} Casualty returns.
* {{citation |last=Cook |first=Christopher |url=http://home.iprimus.com.au/cpcook/indexLW.htm |title=Eye witness accounts of Napoleonic warfare |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120903162907/http://home.iprimus.com.au/cpcook/indexLW.htm |archivedate=3 September 2012|ref=none}}
* {{citation |author=Staff |year=2009 |url=http://books.national-army-museum.ac.uk/waterloo-medal-roll-pr-24201.html |title=Book review of the &quot;Waterloo Medal Roll Call&quot; |publisher=The [British] National Archive|archiveurl=http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20091204193626/http://books.national-army-museum.ac.uk/waterloo-medal-roll-pr-24201.html |archivedate=4 December 2009 |ref=none}}
* {{citation |author=Staff |date=9 July 2013 |url=http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/records/research-guides/medals-british-armed-services-campaign-service.htm |title=British military campaign and service medals |publisher=The [British] National Archive|ref=none}} – &quot;For records of medals awarded for service before 1914, search by name on the Ancestry website. There are separate search pages for the [http://search.ancestry.co.uk/search/db.aspx?dbid=1686 Army] (sourced from WO 100)...&quot;
* Staff, ''[https://www.bbc.co.uk/history/british/empire_seapower/battle_waterloo_01.shtml Empire and Sea Power: The Battle of Waterloo]'' Retrieved on 9 June 2006
* [https://www.bbc.co.uk/history/ BBC History Waterloo], Retrieved on 9 June 2006

===Uniforms===
* French, Prussian and Anglo-Allies uniforms during the Battle of Waterloo : [http://centjours.mont-saint-jean.com/unites.php Mont-Saint-Jean] (FR)

==External links==
{{Commons category-inline|Battle of Waterloo}}
{{Wiktionary-inline|meet one's Waterloo}}
* {{cite web |title=Booknotes: Watch |website=Booknotes |date=12 January 2003 |url=http://www.booknotes.org/Watch/174208-1/Andrew+Roberts.aspx |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101116184425/http://booknotes.org/Watch/174208-1/Andrew+Roberts.aspx |url-status=dead |archive-date=16 November 2010}} Interview with Andrew Roberts on ''Napoleon &amp; Wellington: The Battle of Waterloo and the Great Commanders Who Fought It''
* {{cite web |url=http://www.guides1815.org |title= Guides 1815 |language=fr}} Official guides of the Waterloo battlefield.
* {{cite web |title=Waterloo 200 |website=National Army Museum, London |date=10 June 2015 |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081228231423/http://www.waterloo200.org/}} (British site)
* {{cite web |title=Farm of Hougoumont |website=Archaeology @ Waterloo |url=http://tls509.wix.com/archaeologyawaterloo |accessdate=30 July 2015}}
* George Nafgizer collection Waterloo ORBATs for [http://usacac.army.mil/CAC2/CGSC/CARL/nafziger/815FBE.pdf French], [http://usacac.army.mil/CAC2/CGSC/CARL/nafziger/815FBF.pdf Allied].

{{Napoleonic Wars}}
{{Waterloo Campaign}}
{{Waterloo}}
{{Good article}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Waterloo}}
[[Category:1815 in the Southern Netherlands]]
[[Category:Battle honours of the Rifle Brigade]]
[[Category:Battle of Waterloo| ]]
[[Category:Battles involving France]]
[[Category:Battles involving Hanover]]
[[Category:Battles involving Nassau]]
[[Category:Battles involving Prussia]]
[[Category:Battles involving the Netherlands]]
[[Category:Battles involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Battles of the Napoleonic Wars]]
[[Category:Braine-l'Alleud|Battle of Waterloo]]
[[Category:Cavalry charges]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1815]]
[[Category:June 1815 events]]
[[Category:Lasne]]
[[Category:Last stand battles]]
[[Category:Waterloo Campaign]]
[[Category:Waterloo, Belgium]]</text>
      <sha1>b1fddzy8s087ep751bc3p2pp5f229yp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
