  <page>
    <title>Books of Samuel</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4378</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938013677</id>
      <parentid>936949608</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-28T16:35:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>John of Reading</username>
        <id>11308236</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Typo/[[WP:AWB/GF|general]] fixes, replaced: millenium → millennium</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Tanakh OT|Nevi'im|historical}}
The '''Books of Samuel''',{{efn|In Hebrew, 1 and 2 Samuel together comprise simply the &quot;Book of Samuel&quot; ({{hebrew|ספר שמואל}}, ''Sefer Shmuel''). For purposes of chapter and verse numbering, the book is treated as divided into two parts: 1 Samuel and 2 Samuel.}} '''1 Samuel''' and '''2 Samuel''', form part of the narrative history of [[Ancient Israel|Israel]] in the [[Nevi'im]] or &quot;prophets&quot; section of the [[Hebrew Bible]]/[[Old Testament]], called the [[Deuteronomistic history]], a series of books ([[Book of Joshua|Joshua]], [[Book of Judges|Judges]], Samuel and [[Books of Kings|Kings]]) that constitute a theological history of the [[Israelites]] and aim to explain [[Torah|God's law for Israel]] under the guidance of the prophets.{{sfn|Gordon|1986|p=18}} According to Jewish tradition, the book was written by [[Samuel]], with additions by the prophets [[Gad (prophet)|Gad]] and [[Nathan (prophet)|Nathan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|1 Chronicles|29:29|KJV}}&lt;/ref&gt; Modern scholarly thinking is that the entire Deuteronomistic history was composed in the period c. 630–540&amp;nbsp;BC by combining a number of independent texts of various ages.{{sfn|Knight|1995|p=62}}{{sfn|Jones|2001|p=197}}

Samuel begins with the prophet [[Samuel]]'s birth&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|1 Samuel|1:1–20|KJV}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Yahweh|God]]'s call to him as a boy. The story of the [[Ark of the Covenant]] that follows tells of Israel's oppression by the [[Philistines]], which brought about Samuel's anointing of [[Saul]] as Israel's first king. But Saul proved unworthy and God's choice turned to [[David]], who defeated Israel's enemies, purchased the threshing floor ({{bibleverse|2 Samuel|24:24|KJV}}), where his son, Solomon built the Temple and brought the Ark to Jerusalem. God then promised David and his successors an everlasting dynasty.{{sfn|Spieckerman|2001|p=348}}

== Summary ==
[[File:Ernst Josephson. - David och Saul.JPG|thumb|[[Ernst Josephson]], ''David and Saul'', 1878.]]

The childless [[Hannah (biblical figure)|Hannah]] vows to [[Yahweh|Yahweh of hosts]] that if she has a son, he will be dedicated to him. [[Eli (Bible)|Eli]], the priest of [[Shiloh (biblical city)|Shiloh]] (where the [[Ark of the Covenant]] is located), blesses her, and a child named [[Samuel (Bible)|Samuel]] is born. Samuel is dedicated to the Lord as a [[Nazirite]] – the only one besides [[Samson]] to be identified in the Bible. Eli's sons, [[Hophni and Phinehas]], sin against God's laws and the people, of the priesthood and are killed in battle during the [[Battle of Aphek]], but the child Samuel grows up &quot;in the presence of the Lord.&quot;

The [[Philistines]] [[Philistine captivity of the Ark|capture the Ark of the Covenant]] from Shiloh and take it to the temple of their god [[Dagon]], who recognizes the supremacy of Yahweh. The Philistines are afflicted with plagues and return the ark to the Israelites, but to the territory of the [[tribe of Benjamin]] rather than to Shiloh. The Philistines attack the Israelites gathered at [[Mizpah in Gilead (Judges)|Mizpah]] in Benjamin. Samuel appeals to Yahweh, the Philistines are decisively beaten, and the Israelites reclaim their lost territory.

In Samuel's old age, he appoints his sons [[Joel (son of Samuel)|Joel]] and [[Abijah]] as judges, but because of their corruption  the people ask for a king to rule over them. God tells Samuel to anoint [[David]] of [[Bethlehem]] as king, and David enters Saul's court as his [[Squire|armor-bearer]] and [[harp]]ist. Saul's son and heir [[Jonathan (1 Samuel)|Jonathan]] befriends David and recognizes him as the rightful king. Saul plots David's death, but David flees into the wilderness, where he becomes a champion of the Hebrews. David joins the Philistines but continues secretly to champion his own people, until Saul and Jonathan are killed in battle at [[Mount Gilboa]]. At this point, David offers a majestic eulogy, where he praises the bravery and magnificence of both his friend Jonathan and King Saul.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|2 Samuel|1:17–27|KJV}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The elders of Judah anoint David as king, but in the north Saul's son [[Ish-bosheth]], or Ishbaal, rules over the northern tribes. After a long war, Ishbaal is murdered by [[Rechab]] and [[Baanah]], two of his captains who hope for a reward from David; but David has them killed for killing God's anointed. David is then anointed King of all Israel. David captures Jerusalem and brings the Ark there. David wishes to build a temple, but [[Nathan (Prophet)|Nathan]] tells him that one of his sons will be the one to build the temple. David defeats the enemies of Israel, slaughtering Philistines, [[Moab]]ites, [[Edom]]ites, Syrians and [[Arameans]].

David commits adultery with [[Bathsheba]], who becomes pregnant.  When her husband, [[Uriah the Hittite]] returns from battle, David encourages him to go home and see his wife but Uriah declines in case David might need him.  David thus deliberately sends Uriah on a suicide mission; and for this, [[Yahweh]] sends disasters against his house. Nathan tells David that the sword shall never depart from his house. For the remainder of his reign there are problems. [[Amnon]] (one of David's sons) rapes his half-sister [[Tamar (daughter of David)|Tamar]] (one of David's daughters). [[Absalom]] (another son of David) kills Amnon, rebels against his father, and David flees from Jerusalem. Absalom is killed following the [[Battle of the Wood of Ephraim]], David is restored as king, and he returns to his palace. Finally only two contenders for the succession remain, [[Adonijah]], son of David and Haggith, and [[Solomon]], son of David and Bathsheba.

The Second Book of Samuel concludes with four chapters (chapters 21 to 24) which lie outside the chronological narrative of Saul and David. The narrative is resumed with the [[first Book of Kings]], which relates how, as David lies dying, Bathsheba and Nathan ensure Solomon's elevation to the throne.

The four supplementary&lt;ref&gt;Sub-heading in [[Jerusalem Bible]]&lt;/ref&gt; chapters cover a great famine during David's reign,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|2|Samuel|21:1|NKJV}}&lt;/ref&gt; the execution of seven of Saul's remaining descendants, only [[Mephibosheth]] being saved,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|2|Samuel|21:2–9|NKJV}}&lt;/ref&gt; David's [[2 Samuel 22|song of thanksgiving]],&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|2|Samuel|22:1–51|NKJV}}&lt;/ref&gt; which is almost identical to [[Psalm 18]], his last words,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|2|Samuel|23:1-7|NKJV}}&lt;/ref&gt; a list of David's &quot;[[David's Mighty Warriors|mighty warriors]]&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|2|Samuel|23:8–39|NKJV}}&lt;/ref&gt; an offering made by David using water from the well of Bethlehem,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|2|Samuel|23:13–17|NKJV}}&lt;/ref&gt; David's sinful [[Census#Ancient Israel|census]],&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|2|Samuel|24:1–9|NKJV}}&lt;/ref&gt; a plague over Israel which David opted for as preferable to either famine or oppression,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|2|Samuel|24:10–17|NKJV}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the construction of an altar on land he purchased from [[Araunah the Jebusite]].&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|2|Samuel|24:18–25|NKJV}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Composition ==
[[File:David and Bathsheba by Artemisia Gentileschi.jpg|thumb|''David and Bathsheba'', by [[Artemisia Gentileschi]]. David is seen in the background, standing on a balcony.]]

=== Versions ===
What it is now commonly known as '''1 Samuel''' and '''2 Samuel''' are called by [[the Vulgate]], in imitation of [[Septuagint|the Septuagint]], '''1 Kings''' and '''2 Kings''' respectively.&lt;ref&gt;Bechtel, Florentine Stanislaus (1913). &quot;[[:s:Catholic Encyclopedia (1913)/First and Second Books of Kings|First and Second Books of Kings]]&quot;. ''Catholic Encyclopedia''.&lt;/ref&gt; Then, what it is now commonly known as '''1 Kings''' and '''2 Kings''' would be '''3 Kings''' and '''4 Kings''' in old Bibles before the year 1516.&lt;ref&gt;Schets, Joseph (1913). &quot;[[:s:Catholic Encyclopedia (1913)/Third and Fourth Books of Kings|Third and Fourth Books of Kings]]&quot;. ''Catholic Encyclopedia''.&lt;/ref&gt; It was in 1517 that use of the division we know now today used by Protestant Bibles and adopted by Catholics began. Some Bibles still preserve the old denomination, for example, the [[Douay-Rheims Bible]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.drbo.org/ Douay Rheims bible]&lt;/ref&gt;

1 and 2 Samuel were originally (and, in some Jewish bibles, still are&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=t1J-BAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT17&amp;lpg=PT17&amp;dq=1+and+2+Samuel+were+originally+(and,+in+some+Jewish+bibles,+still+are&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=L6XjBvzHdU&amp;sig=JFtLzI6iJlr4bJUhzAA3Ny_x8Jw&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwj2wpaL0tvYAhVLbrwKHcb1AqgQ6AEIRzAF#v=onepage&amp;q=1%20and%202%20Samuel%20were%20originally%20(and,%20in%20some%20Jewish%20bibles,%20still%20are&amp;f=false|title=2 Samuel (Brazos Theological Commentary on the Bible)|last=Barron|first=Robert|year=2015|publisher=Brazos Press|isbn=978-1441221964|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;) a single book, but the first Greek translation, called [[Septuagint]] and produced around the second century BC, divided it into two; this was adopted by the Latin translations used in the early Christian church of the West, and finally introduced into Jewish bibles around the early 16th century.{{sfn|Gordon|1986|pp=19–20}} The Hebrew text, that is used by Jews today, called the [[Masoretic text]], differs considerably from the Hebrew text that was the basis of the first Greek translation, and scholars are still working at finding the best solutions to the many problems this presents.{{sfn|Bergen|1996|pp=25–27}}

=== Authorship and date of composition ===
According to passages 14b and 15a of the [[Bava Basra]] tractate of the [[Talmud]], the book was written by [[Samuel]] up until 1 Samuel 25, which notes the death of Samuel, and the remainder by the prophets [[Gad (prophet)|Gad]] and [[Nathan (prophet)|Nathan]]. Critical scholars from the 19th century onward have rejected this idea. [[Martin Noth]] in 1943 theorized that Samuel was composed by a single author as part of a history of Israel: the [[Deuteronomistic history]] (made up of [[Deuteronomy]], [[Book of Joshua|Joshua]], [[Book of Judges|Judges]], Samuel and [[Books of Kings|Kings]]).{{sfn|Klein|2003|p=316}} Although Noth's belief that the entire history was composed by a single individual has been largely abandoned, his theory in its broad outline has been adopted by most scholars.{{sfn|Tsumura|2007|pp=15–19}}

The Deuteronomistic view is that an early version of the history was composed in the time of king [[Hezekiah]] (8th century BC); the bulk of the first edition dates from his grandson [[Josiah]] at the end of the 7th BC, with further sections added during the [[Babylonian exile]] (6th century BC) and the work was substantially complete by about 550 BC. Further editing was apparently done even after then. For example, A. Graeme Auld, Professor of Hebrew Bible at the University of Edinburgh, contends that the silver quarter-shekel which Saul's servant offers to Samuel in 1 Samuel 9 &quot;almost certainly fixes the date of this story in the Persian or [[Hellenistic period]]&quot; because a quarter-shekel was known to exist in Hasmonean times.{{sfn|Auld|2003|p=219}}

The 6th century BC authors and editors responsible for the bulk of the history drew on many earlier sources, including (but not limited to) an &quot;ark narrative&quot; (1 Samuel 4:1–7:1 and perhaps part of 2 Samuel 6), a &quot;Saul cycle&quot; (parts of 1 Samuel 9–11 and 13–14), the &quot;history of David's rise&quot; (1 Samuel 16:14–2 Samuel 5:10), and the &quot;succession narrative&quot; (2 Samuel 9–20 and 1 Kings 1–2).{{sfn|Knight|1991|p=853}} The oldest of these, the &quot;ark narrative,&quot; may even predate the Davidic era.{{sfn|Tsumura|2007|p=11}}

This view of late compilation for Samuel has faced serious scholarly opposition on the basis that evidence for the Deuteronimistic history is scant, and that Deuteronimistic advocates are not in consensus as to the origin and extent of the History. Secondly, the basic theological concerns identified with the Deuteronimistic school are tenets central to Hebrew theology in texts that are widely regarded as predating Josiah. Thirdly, there are notable differences in style and thematic emphasis between Deuteronomy and Samuel. Finally, there are widely acknowledged structural parallels between the [[Suzerainty#Hittite suzerainty treaty form|Hittite suzerain treaty]] of the second millennium BC and the Book of Deuteronomy itself, far before the time of Josiah. The alternative view is that it is difficult to determine when the events of Samuel were recorded: &quot;There are no particularly persuasive reasons to date the sources used by the compiler later than the early tenth century events themselves, and good reason to believe that contemporary records were kept (cf. 2 Sam. 20:24–25).&quot;{{sfn|Walton|2009|pp=258-259}}

=== Sources ===
The sources used to construct 1 and 2 Samuel are believed to include the following:&lt;ref&gt;Jones, pp. 197–99&lt;/ref&gt;
*''Call of Samuel'' or ''Youth of Samuel'' (1 Samuel 1–7): From Samuel's birth his career as Judge and prophet over Israel. This source includes the ''Eli narrative'' and part of the ark narrative.{{sfn|Soggin|1987|pp=210–11}}
*''Ark narrative'' (1 Samuel 4:1b–7:1 and 2 Samuel 6:1–20): the ark's capture by the Philistines in the time of Eli and its transfer to Jerusalem by David – opinion is divided over whether this is actually an independent unit.{{sfn|Eynikel|2000|p=88}}
*''Jerusalem source'': a fairly brief source discussing David conquering Jerusalem from the [[Jebusite]]s.
*''Republican source'': a source with an anti-monarchial [[bias]]. This source first describes Samuel as decisively ridding the people of the Philistines, and begrudgingly appointing an individual chosen by God to be king, namely Saul. David is described as someone renowned for his skill at playing the harp, and consequently summoned to Saul's court to calm his moods. Saul's son Jonathan becomes friends with David, which [[David and Jonathan|some commentators view as romantic]], and later acts as his protector against Saul's more violent intentions. At a later point, having been deserted by God on the eve of battle, Saul consults a [[Mediumship|medium]] at [[Witch of Endor|Endor]], only to be condemned for doing so by Samuel's ghost, and told he and his sons will be killed. David is heartbroken on discovering the death of Jonathan, tearing his clothes as a gesture of grief.
*''Monarchial source'': a source with a pro-monarchial bias and covering many of the same details as the ''republican source''. This source begins with the divinely appointed birth of Samuel. It then describes Saul as leading a war against the Ammonites, being chosen by the people to be king, and leading them against the Philistines. David is described as a shepherd boy arriving at the battlefield to aid his brothers, and is overheard by Saul, leading to David challenging [[Goliath]] and defeating the Philistines. David's warrior credentials lead to women falling in love with him, including [[Michal]], Saul's daughter, who later acts to protect David against Saul. David eventually gains two new wives as a result of threatening to raid a village, and Michal is redistributed to another husband. At a later point, David finds himself seeking sanctuary amongst the Philistine army and facing the Israelites as an enemy. David is incensed that anyone should have killed Saul, even as an act of mercy, since Saul was anointed by Samuel, and has the individual responsible, an [[Amalekite]], killed.
*''[[Court History of David]]'' or ''Succession narrative'' (2 Samuel 9–20 and 1 Kings 1–2): a &quot;[[Historical fiction#Historical novel|historical novel]]&quot;, in [[Alberto Soggin]]'s phrase, telling the story of David's reign from his affair with [[Bathsheba]] to his death. The theme is of retribution: David's sin against [[Uriah the Hittite]] is punished by God through the destruction of his own family,{{sfn|Soggin|1987|pp=216–17}} and its purpose is to serve as an apology for the coronation of Bathsheba's son [[Solomon]] instead of his older brother [[Adonijah]].{{sfn|Klein|2003|p=316}} Some textual critics have posited that given the intimacy and precision of certain narrative details, the Court Historian may have been an eyewitness to some of the events he describes, or at the very least enjoyed access to the archives and battle reports of the royal house of David.&lt;ref name=Kirsch&gt;{{cite book|last=Kirsch|first=Jonathan|title=King David: The Real Life of the Man Who Ruled Israel|year=2009|publisher=Random House LLC|isbn=978-0307567819|pages=307–09}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
*''Redactions'': additions by the redactor to harmonize the sources together; many of the uncertain passages may be part of this editing.
*''Various'': several short sources, none of which have much connection to each other, and are fairly independent of the rest of the text. Many are poems or pure lists.

== Themes ==
[[File:Hannah VICTORS, Jan.jpg|thumb|[[Hannah (Bible)|Hannah]] presenting [[Samuel (Biblical figure)|Samuel]] to [[Eli (Bible)|Eli]], by [[Jan Victors]], 1645.]]

The Book of Samuel is a theological evaluation of kingship in general and of dynastic kingship and [[David]] in particular.{{sfn|Klein|2003|p=312}} The main themes of the book are introduced in the opening poem (the &quot;[[Song of Hannah]]&quot;): (1) the sovereignty of [[Yahweh]], God of Israel; (2) the reversal of human fortunes; and (3) kingship.{{sfn|Tsumura|2007|p=68}} These themes are played out in the stories of the three main characters, [[Samuel]], [[Saul]] and [[David]].

=== Samuel ===
{{main|Samuel}}
Samuel answers the description of the &quot;prophet like Moses&quot; predicted in Deuteronomy 18:15–22: like Moses, he has direct contact with [[Yahweh]], acts as a judge, and is a perfect leader who never makes mistakes.{{sfn|Beytenbrach|2000|pp=53–55}} Samuel's successful defense of the Israelites against their enemies demonstrates that they have no need for a king (who will, moreover, introduce inequality), yet despite this the people demand a king. But the king they are given is Yahweh's gift, and Samuel explains that kingship can be a blessing rather than a curse if they remain faithful to their God. On the other hand, total destruction of both king and people will result if they turn to wickedness.{{sfn|Klein|2003|p=316}}

=== Saul ===
{{main|Saul}}
Saul is the chosen one, tall, handsome and &quot;goodly&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|1|Samuel|9:2|KJV}}: King James Version&lt;/ref&gt; a king appointed by Yahweh, and anointed by Samuel, Yahweh's prophet, and yet he is ultimately rejected.{{sfn|Hertzberg|1964|p=19}} Saul has two faults which make him unfit for the office of king: carrying out a sacrifice in place of Samuel (1 Samuel 13:8–14), and failing to exterminate the [[Amalekites]], in accordance to God's commands, and trying to compensate by claiming that he reserved the surviving Amalekite livestock for sacrifice (1 Samuel 15).{{sfn|Klein|2003|p=319}}

=== David ===
{{main|David}}
One of the main units within Samuel is the &quot;History of David's Rise&quot;, the purpose of which is to justify David as the legitimate successor to Saul.{{sfn|Dick|2004|pp=3–4}} The narrative stresses that he gained the throne lawfully, always respecting &quot;the Lord's anointed&quot; (i.e. Saul) and never taking any of his numerous chances to seize the throne by violence.{{sfn|Jones|2001|p=198}} As God's chosen king over Israel, David is also the son of God (&quot;I will be a father to him, and he shall be a son to me...&quot; – 2 Samuel 7:14).{{sfn|Coogan|2009|pp=216, 229–33}} God enters into an eternal covenant (treaty) with David and his line, promising divine protection of the dynasty and of Jerusalem through all time.{{sfn|Coogan|2009|p=425}}

[[2 Samuel 23]] contains a prophetic statement described as the &quot;last words of [[David]]&quot; (verses 1–7) and details of the 37 &quot;[[David's mighty men|mighty men]]&quot; who were David's chief warriors ([[2 Samuel 23#Verses 8–39|verses 8–39]]). The [[Jerusalem Bible]] states that last words were attributed to David in the style of [[Jacob]] (see [[Jacob's Blessing]], {{bibleverse|Genesis|49|HE}}) and [[Moses]] (see [[Blessing of Moses]], {{bibleverse|Deuteronomy|33|HE}}). Its editors note that &quot;the text has suffered considerably and reconstructions are conjectural&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Jerusalem Bible, footnote at 2 Samuel 23:1&lt;/ref&gt;

{{bibleverse|1|Kings|2:1–9|NKJV}} contains David's final words to [[Solomon]], his son and successor as [[Kingdom of Israel (united monarchy)|king]].

== See also ==
* [[Biblical judges]]
* [[Midrash Shmuel (aggadah)]]
* [[The Bible and history]]
* [[History of ancient Israel and Judah]]
* [[Kingdom of Israel (Samaria)]]
* [[Kingdom of Judah]]

== Notes ==
{{notelist}}

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== Bibliography ==

=== Commentaries on Samuel ===
{{Refbegin}}

*{{Cite book|last=Auld|first=Graeme|chapter=1 &amp; 2 Samuel|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2Vo-11umIZQC&amp;pg=PA213&amp;lpg=PA213&amp;dq=There+are+two+common+types+of+strategy+for+reading+the+books+of+Samuel#v=onepage&amp;q=There%20are%20two%20common%20types%20of%20strategy%20for%20reading%20the%20books%20of%20Samuel&amp;f=false|editor=James D. G. Dunn and John William Rogerson|title=Eerdmans Commentary on the Bible|publisher=Eerdmans|year=2003|isbn=9780802837110}}
*{{Cite book|last=Bergen|first=David T.|title=1, 2 Samuel|url=https://books.google.com/?id=eGT6fWsajqcC&amp;pg=PA49&amp;dq=I+%26+II+Samuel:+a+commentary+Gordon#v=onepage&amp;q=I%20%26%20II%20Samuel%3A%20a%20commentary%20Gordon&amp;f=false|publisher=B&amp;H Publishing Group|year=1996|isbn=9780805401073}}
*{{Cite book|last=Breytenbach|first=Andries|title=Past, Present, Future: the Deuteronomistic History and the Prophets|publisher=Brill|year=2000|chapter=Who Is Behind The Samuel Narrative?|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=uP22QHpnKq8C&amp;pg=PA50&amp;lpg=PA50&amp;dq=Breytenbach+Who+is+behind+the+Samuel+narrative#v=onepage&amp;q=Breytenbach%20Who%20is%20behind%20the%20Samuel%20narrative&amp;f=false|editor=Johannes Cornelis de Moor and H.F. Van Rooy|isbn=9789004118713}}
*Coogan, Michael D. (2009) ''A Brief Introduction to the Old Testament: The Hebrew Bible in its Context'' Oxford University Press
*{{Cite book|last=Dick|first=Michael B|chapter=The History of &quot;David's Rise to Power&quot; and the Neo-Babylonian Succession Apologies|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Vlkb0cSBGlIC&amp;pg=PA373&amp;lpg=PA373&amp;dq=David+and+Zion:+biblical+studies+in+honor+of+J.J.M.+Roberts#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|editor=Bernard Frank Batto and Kathryn L. Roberts|title=David and Zion: biblical studies in honor of J.J.M. Roberts|publisher=Eisenbrauns|year=2004|isbn=9781575060927}}
*{{Cite book|last=Eynikel|first=Erik|title=Past, present, future: the Deuteronomistic history and the prophets|publisher=Brill|year=2000|chapter=The Relation Between the Eli Narrative and the Ark Narratives|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=uP22QHpnKq8C&amp;pg=PA50&amp;lpg=PA50&amp;dq=Breytenbach+Who+is+behind+the+Samuel+narrative#v=onepage&amp;q=Breytenbach%20Who%20is%20behind%20the%20Samuel%20narrative&amp;f=false|editor=Johannes Cornelis de Moor and H.F. Van Rooy|isbn=9789004118713}}
*{{Cite book|last=Gordon|first=Robert|title=I &amp; II Samuel, A Commentary|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=JMJ1ZAnswuUC&amp;pg=PA338&amp;lpg=PA338&amp;dq=I+%26+II+Samuel:+a+commentary+Gordon#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|publisher=Paternoster Press|year=1986|isbn=9780310230229}}
*{{Cite book|last=Halpern|first=Baruch|title=David's Secret Demons: Messiah, Murderer, Traitor, King|publisher=Eerdmans|year=2001|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=tn8PG4XfuBAC&amp;pg=PA8&amp;lpg=PA8&amp;dq=David's+secret#v=onepage&amp;q=lahmi+bethlehemite&amp;f=false|isbn=9780802827975}}
*{{Cite book|last=Hertzberg|first=Hans Wilhelm|title=I &amp; II Samuel, A Commentary|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=friNN7IdjOIC&amp;pg=PA19#v=onepage&amp;q=Saul%20appointed%20anointed%20instituted&amp;f=false|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|year=1964|edition=trans. from German 2nd edition 1960|isbn=978-0664223182|page=19}}
*{{Cite book|last=Jones|first=Gwilym H|chapter=1 and 2 Samuel|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wCRYl9Ikk6EC&amp;pg=PA196#v=onepage&amp;q=Gwilym%20Jones%201%20and%202%20Samuel&amp;f=false|editor=John Barton and John Muddiman|title=The Oxford Bible Commentary|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2001|isbn=9780198755005}}
*{{Cite book|last=Klein|first=R.W.|chapter=Samuel, books of|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6OJvO2jMCr8C&amp;pg=PA314&amp;lpg=PA314&amp;dq=narrative+sources+books+of+samuel#v=onepage&amp;q=narrative%20sources%20books%20of%20samuel&amp;f=false|editor=Bromiley, Geoffrey W|title=The International Standard Bible Encyclopedia|publisher=Eerdmans|year=2003|isbn=9780802837844}}
*{{Cite book|last=Knight|first=Douglas A|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=SNLN1nEEys0C&amp;pg=PA62#v=onepage&amp;q=630%20BCE&amp;f=false|editor=James Luther Mays, David L. Petersen and Kent Harold Richards|chapter=Chapter 4 Deuteronomy and the Deuteronomists|title=Old Testament Interpretation|publisher=T&amp;T Clark|year=1995|isbn=9780567292896|page=62}}
*{{Cite book|last=Knight|first=Douglas A|chapter=Sources|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=goq0VWw9rGIC#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|editor=Watson E. Mills, Roger Aubrey Bullard|title=Mercer Dictionary of the Bible|publisher=Mercer University Press|year=1991|isbn=9780865543737}}
*McCarter Jr., P. Kyle (1984). ''II Samuel: A New Translation With Introduction and Commentary By''. Anchor Bible. {{ISBN|9780385068086}}.
*{{Cite book|last=Schleffer|first=Eben|title=Past, Present, Future: the Deuteronomistic History and the Prophets|publisher=Brill|year=2000|chapter=Saving Saul from the Deuteronomist|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=uP22QHpnKq8C&amp;pg=PA50&amp;lpg=PA50&amp;dq=Breytenbach+Who+is+behind+the+Samuel+narrative#v=onepage&amp;q=Breytenbach%20Who%20is%20behind%20the%20Samuel%20narrative&amp;f=false|editor=Johannes Cornelis de Moor and H.F. Van Rooy|isbn=9789004118713}}
*{{Cite book|last=Soggin|first=Alberto|title=Introduction to the Old Testament|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|year=1987|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=mqSNsKXnHQgC&amp;pg=PA112&amp;lpg=PA112&amp;dq=Soggin+Introduction+to+the+Old+Testament#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|isbn=9780664221560}}
*{{Cite book|last=Spieckerman|first=Hermann|chapter=The Deuteronomistic History|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=41_0okLzQJkC&amp;pg=PA337&amp;lpg=PA337&amp;dq=The+Deuteronomistic+History+Hermann+Spieckermann#v=onepage&amp;q=The%20Deuteronomistic%20History%20Hermann%20Spieckermann&amp;f=false|editor=Leo G. Perdue|title=The Blackwell Companion to the Hebrew Bible|publisher=Blackwell|year=2001|isbn=9780631210719}}
*{{Cite book|last=Tsumura|first=David Toshio|title=The First Book of Samuel|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=iLKAlhLDkMwC&amp;pg=PA103&amp;lpg=PA103&amp;dq=The+First+book+of+Samuel+Tsumura#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|publisher=Eerdmans|year=2007|isbn=9780802823595}}
*{{Cite book|last=Van Seters|first=John|title=In Search of History: Historiography in the Ancient World and the Origins of Biblical History|publisher=Eisenbrauns|year=1997|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0-skPdXtewwC&amp;pg=PA406&amp;lpg=PA406&amp;dq=Van+Seters+In+Search+of+History#v=onepage&amp;q=Samuel&amp;f=false|isbn=9781575060132}}
*{{Cite book|last=Walton|first=John H|chapter=The Deuteronomistic History|url=https://books.google.com/?id=WC80zxPIgyQC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Hill+Walton+A+Survey+of+the+Old+Testament#v=onepage&amp;q=Hill%20Walton%20A%20Survey%20of%20the%20Old%20Testament&amp;f=false|editor=Andrew E. Hill, John H. Walton|title=A Survey of the Old Testament|publisher=Zondervan|year=2009|isbn=9780631210719}}
{{Refend}}

== External links ==
{{Wikisource|1 Samuel (Bible)}}
{{Wikisource|2 Samuel (Bible)}}
{{Commons category|Books of Samuel}}
{{wikiquote|First Book of Samuel}}

;[[Masoretic Text]]
* [http://www.mechon-mamre.org/p/pt/pt08a01.htm שמואל א ''Shmuel Aleph'' – Samuel A] ([[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] – English at Mechon-Mamre.org)
* [http://www.mechon-mamre.org/p/pt/pt08b01.htm שמואל ב ''Shmuel Bet'' – Samuel B] ([[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] – English at Mechon-Mamre.org)

;Jewish translations
* [http://www.mechon-mamre.org/e/et/et08a01.htm 1 Samuel at Mechon-Mamre] (Jewish Publication Society translation)
* [http://www.mechon-mamre.org/e/et/et08b01.htm 2 Samuel at Mechon-Mamre] (Jewish Publication Society translation)

;Christian translations
* {{librivox book | dtitle=Bible: 1 Samuel| stitle=09: 1 Samuel}}
* {{librivox book | dtitle=Bible: 2 Samuel| stitle=10: 2 Samuel}}

;Related articles
* [http://www.ibs.org/niv/studybible/1samuel.php Introduction to the book of 1 Samuel] from the [[NIV Study Bible]]
* [http://www.ibs.org/niv/studybible/2samuel.php Introduction to the book of 2 Samuel] from the [[NIV Study Bible]]
* [http://www.vts.edu/ftpimages/95/download/FM.Meek.2Samuel.pdf Introduction to the book of 2 Samuel] from [[Forward Movement]]

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou | [[Nevi'im|History books]]|||}}
{{s-bef | before= [[Book of Judges|Judges]] | rows = 1 }}
{{s-ttl | title = [[Tanakh|Hebrew Bible]] }}
{{s-aft | after = [[Books of Kings|Kings]] | rows= 2 }}
{{s-bef | before= [[Book of Ruth|Ruth]] | rows = 1 }}
{{s-ttl | title = [[Christianity|Christian]]&lt;br&gt;[[Old Testament]] }}
{{s-end}}

{{Books of the Bible}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Samuel, Books Of}}
[[Category:8th-century BC books]]
[[Category:7th-century BC books]]
[[Category:6th-century BC books]]
[[Category:Works set in the 11th century BC]]
[[Category:Works set in the 10th century BC]]
[[Category:Nevi'im]]
[[Category:Books of Samuel| ]]
[[Category:Kingdom of Israel (united monarchy)]]</text>
      <sha1>tu3oo1ccj2ggxhe0ib5fegwjavsyh1o</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
