  <page>
    <title>Book of Judges</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4377</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942448083</id>
      <parentid>942312050</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-24T19:03:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GHcool</username>
        <id>327027</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Bibliography */ removed 's</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Seventh book of the Bible}}
{{about|the biblical book||Judge (disambiguation)}}
{{Judges |width=22.0em}}
{{Tanakh OT|Nevi'im|historical}}

The '''Book of Judges''' ({{lang|he|ספר שופטים}}, ''{{transl|he|Sefer Shoftim}}'') is the seventh book of the [[Hebrew Bible]] and the Christian [[Old Testament]]. In the narrative of the Hebrew Bible, it covers the time between the conquest described in the [[Book of Joshua]] and the establishment of a kingdom in the [[Books of Samuel]], during which [[Biblical judges]] served as temporary leaders.{{sfn|Niditch|pp=2–3}} The stories follow a consistent pattern: the people are unfaithful to [[Yahweh]] and he therefore delivers them into the hands of their enemies; the people repent and entreat Yahweh for mercy, which he sends in the form of a leader or champion (a &quot;judge&quot;; see ''[[shophet]]''); the judge delivers the Israelites from oppression and they prosper, but soon they fall again into unfaithfulness and the cycle is repeated.{{sfn|Soggin|p=4}} Scholars consider many of the stories in ''Judges'' to be the oldest in the [[Deuteronomistic history]], with their major redaction dated to the 8th century BCE and with materials such as the [[Deborah#The Song of Deborah|Song of Deborah]] dating from much earlier.{{sfn|Bacon|pp=563–66}}{{sfn|Alter|p=105}}

== Contents ==
''Judges'' can be divided into three major sections: a double prologue (chapters 1:1–3:6), a main body (3:7–16:31), and a double epilogue (17–21).{{sfn|Guest|p=190}}

=== Prologue ===
The book opens with the Israelites in the land that God has promised to them, but worshiping &quot;foreign gods&quot; instead of [[Yahweh]], the God of Israel, and with the [[Canaanites]] still present everywhere.{{sfn|Spieckermann|p=341}} Chapters 1:1–2:5 are thus a confession of failure, while chapters 2:6–3:6 are a major summary and reflection from the [[Deuteronomist |Deuteronomists]].{{sfn|McKenzie|p=14}}

The opening thus sets out the pattern which the stories in the main text will follow:{{sfn|Guest|p=190}}
# Israel &quot;does evil in the eyes of Yahweh&quot;,
# the people are given into the hands of their enemies and cry out to Yahweh,
# Yahweh raises up a leader,
# the &quot;spirit of Yahweh&quot; comes upon the leader,
# the leader manages to defeat the enemy, and
# peace is regained.

Once peace is regained, Israel does right and receives Yahweh's blessings for a time, but relapses later into doing evil and repeats the pattern set forth above.

''Judges'' follows the [[Book of Joshua]] and opens with a reference to [[Joshua]]'s death ({{bibleverse||Joshua|24:29|HE}}; cf. {{bibleverse||Judges|1:1|HE}}). The [[Cambridge Bible for Schools and Colleges]] suggests that &quot;the death of Joshua may be regarded as marking the division between the period of conquest and the period of occupation&quot;, the latter being the focus of the Book of Judges.&lt;ref name = biblehub&gt;[http://biblehub.com/commentaries/cambridge/judges/1.htm Cambridge Bible for Schools and Colleges] on Judges 1, accessed 9 October 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; The Israelites meet, most likely at the sanctuary at [[Gilgal]] or at [[Shechem]] (following on from {{bibleverse||Joshua|24:1–33|HE}}) and ask the Lord who should be first (in order of time, not of rank) to secure the land they are to occupy.&lt;ref name = biblehub /&gt;

=== Main text ===
[[File:12 Tribes of Israel Map.svg|thumb|235px|Map of the tribes of Israel]]
The main text ({{bibleverse-nb||Judges|3:11–16:31|HE}}) gives accounts of six '''major judges''' and their struggles against the oppressive kings of surrounding nations, as well as the story of Abimelech, an Israelite leader (a judge [shofet] in the sense of &quot;chieftain&quot;) who oppresses his own people.  The cyclical pattern set out in the prologue is readily apparent at the beginning, but as the stories progress it begins to disintegrate, mirroring the disintegration of the world of the Israelites.{{sfn|Guest|p=190|2003}} Although some scholars consider the stories not to be presented in chronological order,{{sfn|Amit|p=508}} the judges [[Fabula and syuzhet|in the order in which they appear in the text]] are:
* [[Othniel]] (3:9–11) vs. [[Chushan-Rishathaim]], King of [[Aram-Naharaim|Aram]]; Israel has 40 years of peace until the death of Othniel. (The statement that Israel has a certain period of peace after each judge is a recurrent theme.)
* [[Ehud]] (3:11–29) vs. [[Eglon (king)|Eglon]] of [[Moab]]
* [[Deborah]] the prophetess, accompanied by [[Barak]] the army leader (4–5), vs. [[Jabin]] of [[Tel Hazor|Hazor]] (a city in [[Canaan]]) and [[Sisera]], his captain ([[Battle of Mount Tabor (biblical)|Battle of Mount Tabor]])
* [[Gideon]] (6–8) vs. [[Midian]], [[Amalek]], and the &quot;children of the East&quot; (apparently desert tribes)
* [[Abimelech (Judges)|Abimelech]] (9) (who is traditionally counted as a king not a judge, and is considered evil{{Citation needed|date=February 2019}}) vs. all the Israelites who oppose him
* [[Jephthah]] (11–12:7) vs. the [[Ammon]]ites
* [[Samson]] (13–16) vs. the [[Philistines]]

There are also brief glosses on six '''minor judges''': [[Shamgar]] (3:31), [[Tola (biblical figure)|Tola]] and [[Jair]] (10:1–5), [[Ibzan]], [[Elon (Judges)|Elon]], and [[Abdon (Judges)|Abdon]] (12:8–15).{{sfn|Bacon|pp=563–65}} Some scholars have inferred that the minor judges were actual adjudicators, whereas the major judges were leaders and did not actually make legal judgements.{{sfn|Bacon|p=564}} The only major judge described as making legal judgments is Deborah (4:4).{{sfn|Bacon|p=561}}

=== Epilogue ===
By the end of Judges, the Israelites are in a worse condition than they were at the beginning, with Yahweh's treasures used to make idolatrous images, the Levites (priests) corrupted, the [[tribe of Dan]] conquering a remote village instead of the Canaanite cities, and the [[tribes of Israel]] making war on the [[tribe of Benjamin]], their own kinsmen.{{sfn |Guest|pp= 202–4}}  The book concludes with two appendices ({{bibleverse-nb||Judges|17–21|HE}}), stories which do not feature a specific judge:{{sfn|Soggin|p=5}}
* [[Micah's Idol]] ({{bibleverse-nb||Judges|17–18|HE}}), how the tribe of Dan conquers its territory in the north
* [[Battle of Gibeah]] ({{bibleverse-nb||Judges|19–21|HE}}), a war between Benjamin and the other tribes.
Despite their appearance at the end of the book, certain characters (like [[Jonathan (Judges) |Jonathan]], the grandson of [[Moses]]) and idioms present in the epilogue show that the events therein &quot;must have taken place… early in the period of the judges.&quot;{{sfn|Davis|pp=328–61}}

=== Chronology ===
Judges contains a chronology of its events, assigning a number of years to each interval of judgment and peace. It is overtly schematic and was likely introduced at a later period.{{sfn|Hughes|pp=70–77}}

== Composition ==
[[File:Maarten van Heemskerck 024.jpg|thumb|&quot;Gideon thanks God for the miracle of the dew&quot;, painting by [[Maarten van Heemskerck]] ([[Musée des Beaux-Arts de Strasbourg]])]]

It is unclear if any of the people named as judges existed.&lt;ref name= &quot;Thompson2000&quot;&gt;{{cite book | first =Thomas L. | last = Thompson |title= Early History of the Israelite People: From the Written &amp; Archaeological Sources |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RwrrUuHFb6UC&amp;pg=PA96 |date=1 January 2000|publisher= Brill|isbn=978-90-04-11943-7|page= 96}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= &quot;Brettler2002&quot;&gt;{{cite book | first = Marc Zvi | last = Brettler |title=The Book of Judges |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=9j9Jbcl6g38C&amp;pg=PA107 |year= 2002 |publisher=Psychology Press |isbn=978-0-415-16216-6|page= 107}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= &quot;Davies1995&quot;&gt;{{cite book | first = Philip R. |last = Davies |title= In Search of &quot;Ancient Israel&quot;: A Study in Biblical Origins |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=5D5GNju1-ggC&amp;pg=PA26|year=1995 |publisher=A&amp;C Black|isbn= 978-1-85075-737-5|page= 26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Sources ===
The basic source for Judges was a collection of loosely connected stories about tribal heroes who saved the people in battle.{{sfn |Knight|p=67}} This original &quot;book of saviours&quot; made up of the stories of [[Ehud]], [[Jael]] and parts of [[Gideon]], had already been enlarged and transformed into &quot;wars of Yahweh&quot; before being given the final Deuteronomistic revision.{{sfn|Soggin|pp=5–6}} In the 20th century, the first part of the prologue (chapters 1:1–2:5) and the two parts of the epilogue (17–21) were commonly seen as miscellaneous collections of fragments tacked onto the main text, and the second part of the prologue (2:6–3:6) as an introduction composed expressly for the book. More recently, this view has been challenged, and there is an increasing willingness to see Judges as the work of a single individual, working by carefully selecting, reworking and positioning his source material to introduce and conclude his themes.{{sfn|Guest|pp=201–02}}

=== The Deuteronomistic History ===
A statement repeated throughout the epilogue, &quot;In those days there was no king in Israel&quot; ({{bibleverse||Judges|17:6|HE}}, {{bibleverse-nb||Judges|18:1|HE}}, {{bibleverse-nb||Judges|19:1|HE}}, and {{bibleverse-nb||Judges|21:25|HE}}) implies a date in the monarchic period for the redaction (editing) of Judges.{{sfn|Malamat|p=132}} Twice, this statement is accompanied with the statement &quot;every man did that which was right in his own eyes&quot;, implying that the redactor is pro-monarchy, ({{bibleverse||Judges|17:6|HE}} and {{bibleverse-nb||Judges|21:25|HE}}) and the epilogue, in which the [[tribe of Judah]] is assigned a leadership role, implies that this redaction took place in Judah.{{sfn|Davis|p=328}}

Since the second half of the 20th century most scholars have agreed with [[Martin Noth]]'s thesis that the books of [[Book of Deuteronomy|Deuteronomy]], [[Book of Joshua|Joshua]], Judges, [[Books of Samuel|Samuel]] and [[Books of Kings|Kings]] form parts of a single work.{{sfn|Knoppers|2000a|p=1}} Noth maintained that the history was written in the early [[Babylonian captivity|Exilic period]] (6th century BCE) in order to demonstrate how Israel's history was worked out in accordance with the theology expressed in the book of Deuteronomy (which thus provides the name &quot;Deuteronomistic&quot;).{{sfn|Walton|pp=169–70}} Noth believed that this history was the work of a single author, living in the mid-6th century BCE, selecting, editing and composing from his sources to produce a coherent work.{{sfn|Knoppers|2000b|p=119}} Frank Moore Cross later proposed that an early version of the history was composed in Jerusalem in [[Josiah]]'s time (late 7th century BCE); this first version, Dtr1, was then revised and expanded to create a second edition, that identified by Noth, and which Cross labelled Dtr2.{{sfn|Eynikel|p=14}}

Scholars agree that the Deuteronomists' hand can be seen in ''Judges'' through the book's cyclical nature: the Israelites fall into idolatry, God punishes them for their sins with oppression by foreign peoples, the Israelites cry out to God for help, and God sends a judge to deliver them from the foreign oppression. After a period of peace, the cycle recurs.  Scholars also suggest that the Deuteronomists also included the humorous and sometimes disparaging commentary found in the book such as the story of the [[tribe of Ephraim]] who could not pronounce the word &quot;''[[shibboleth]]''&quot; correctly (12:5–6).{{sfn|Bacon|p=562}}

== Themes and genre ==
[[File:Judges Bib Germ 1485 d.1 375.jpg|thumbnail|right|Illustrated page from the Book of Judges in a German Bible dated 1485 (Bodleian Library)]]
The essence of Deuteronomistic theology is that Israel has entered into a [[covenant (biblical)|covenant]] (a treaty, a binding agreement) with the God Yahweh, under which they agree to accept Yahweh as their God (hence the phrase &quot;God of Israel&quot;) and Yahweh promises them a land where they can live in peace and prosperity. Deuteronomy contains the laws by which Israel is to live in the promised land, Joshua chronicles the conquest of [[Canaan]], the promised land, and its allotment among the tribes, Judges describes the settlement of the land, Samuel the consolidation of the land and people under [[David]], and Kings the destruction of kingship and loss of the land.{{sfn|Knight|p=61}} The final tragedy described in Kings is the result of Israel's failure to uphold its part of the covenant: faithfulness to Yahweh brings success, economic, military and political, but unfaithfulness brings defeat and oppression.{{sfn |Niditch|p=11}}

This is the theme played out in Judges: the people are unfaithful to Yahweh and He therefore delivers them into the hands of their enemies; the people then repent and entreat Yahweh for mercy, which He sends in the form of a judge; the judge delivers the Israelites from oppression, but after a while they fall into unfaithfulness again and the cycle is repeated.{{sfn|Soggin|p=4}}

Further themes are also present: the &quot;sovereign freedom of Yahweh&quot; (God does not always do what is expected of him); the &quot;[[satire|satirisation]] of foreign kings&quot; (who consistently underestimate Israel and Yahweh); the concept of the &quot;flawed agent&quot; (judges who are not adequate to the task before them) and the disunity of the Israelite community (which gathers pace as the stories succeed one another).{{sfn|Guest|pp=193–94}}

The book is as intriguing for the themes it leaves out as for what it includes: the [[Ark of the Covenant]], which is given so much importance in the stories of [[Moses]] and [[Joshua]], is almost entirely missing,{{Efn | The ark of the covenant is mentioned in passing in {{bibleverse ||Judges|20:27|HE}}.}} cooperation between the various tribes is limited, and there is no mention of a central shrine for worship and only limited reference to a [[High Priest of Israel]] (the office to which [[Aaron]] was appointed at the end of [[the Exodus]] story).{{Efn | [[Phinehas]] the son of [[Eleazar]], the son of Aaron is mentioned in passing in {{bibleverse ||Judges|20:28|HE}}.}}{{sfn|Matthews|p=4}}

Although ''Judges'' probably had a monarchist redaction (see above), the book contains passages and themes that represent anti-monarchist views.  One of the major themes of the book is Yahweh's sovereignty and the importance of being loyal to Him and His laws above all other gods and sovereigns.  Indeed, the authority of the judges comes not through prominent dynasties nor through elections or appointments, but rather through the Spirit of God.{{sfn|Alter|p= 106}}  Anti-monarchist theology is most apparent toward the end of the Gideon cycle in which the Israelites beg Gideon to create a dynastic monarchy over them and Gideon refuses.{{sfn|Davis|pp = 326–27}} The rest of Gideon's lifetime saw peace in the land, but after Gideon's death, his son Abimelech ruled [[Shechem]] as a [[Machiavelli|Machiavellian]] tyrant guilty for much bloodshed (see chapters 8 and 9).  However, the last few chapters of ''Judges'' (specifically, the stories of Samson, Micah, and Gibeah) highlight the violence and [[anarchy]] of decentralized rule.{{sfn|Alter|pp=107–9}}

''Judges'' is remarkable for the number of female characters who &quot;play significant roles, active and passive, in the narratives.&quot;{{sfn |Bacon |p= 561}} Rabbi [[Joseph Telushkin]] wrote,
{{quote|Most of the great women in the Bible either are married to a great man or related to one.  … A rare exception to this tradition is the prophetess and judge Deborah, perhaps the Bible's greatest woman figure.  Deborah stands exclusively on her own merits.  The only thing we know about her personal life is the name of her husband, Lapidot.{{sfn|Telushkin|p=58}}}}

== See also ==
* [[Tanakh]]
* [[Biblical canon]]
* [[History of ancient Israel and Judah]]

==Notes==
{{Notelist}}

== References ==
{{reflist|32em}}

== Bibliography ==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite book |authorlink=Robert Alter |last=Alter |first=Robert |url= https://books.google.com./books?id=QuaFlf7_vbwC |title=Ancient Israel: The Former Prophets: Joshua, Judges, Samuel, and Kings |location= New York |publisher= W. W. Norton &amp; Co |year=2013 |isbn= 978-0-39324027-6}}
* Amit, Yairah. &quot;Judges&quot; Introduction and Annotations. ''The Jewish Study Bible''. Ed. Adele Berlin and Marc Zvi Brettler.  New York: Oxford University Press, 2004.  508–57.
* Bacon, Gershon and S. David Sperling.  &quot;Judges (Heb. שופטים), Book of.&quot; ''[[Encyclopaedia Judaica]]''.  2nd ed., vol. 11.  pp.&amp;nbsp;561–66.
* Davis, John J. and Herbert Wolf.  ''Judges'' Introduction and Annotations. ''Zondervan NIV Study Bible (Fully Revised)''.  Ed. Kenneth L. Barker.  Grand Rapids, MI: Zondervan, 2002. 326–63.
* {{Cite book |last= Eynikel |first= Erik |title= The reform of King Josiah and the composition of the Deuteronomistic history |publisher= Brill |year=1996|url= https://books.google.com/?id=Fl9dYJH_xUYC |isbn= 978-90-04-10266-8}}
* {{Cite book |last= Guest |first= P. Deryn |chapter= Judges |chapter-url= https://books.google.com/?id=2Vo-11umIZQC&amp;pg=PA190 |editor1-first = James D. G. | editor1-last = Dunn |editor2-first = John William |editor2-last = Rogerson |title= Commentary on the Bible|publisher= Eerdmans|year=2003|isbn= 978-0-8028-3711-0}}
* {{Cite book |last1 = Hughes |first1 = Jeremy |title = Secrets of the Times: Myth and History in Biblical Chronology |publisher     = A&amp;C Black |year = 1990 |url = https://books.google.com/?id=vPg2cvQLwHAC |ref = harv |isbn = 978-0-56762930-2}}
* {{Cite book|last= Knight |first= Douglas A|chapter= Deuteronomy and the Deuteronomists |chapter-url= https://books.google.com/?id=SNLN1nEEys0C |editor1-first = James Luther | editor1-last = Mays |editor2-first = David L. | editor2-last = Petersen |editor3-first =Kent Harold | editor3-last = Richards|title= Old Testament Interpretation |publisher=T&amp;T Clark |year=1995|isbn= 978-0-567-29289-6}}
* {{Cite book|last= Knoppers |first= Gary |chapter= Introduction |chapter-url= https://books.google.com/?id=CoHhPAKgETkC |editor1-first = Gary N. | editor1-last = Knoppers |editor2-first = J. Gordon | editor2-last = McConville|title= Reconsidering Israel and Judah: recent studies on the Deuteronomistic history|publisher= Eisenbrauns|date= 2000a |isbn=978-1-57506-037-8}}
* {{Cite book|last=Knoppers|first= Gary|chapter=Is There a Future for the Deuteronomistic History?|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/?id=TjfJHpNXUusC |editor=Thomas Romer|title= The Future of the Deuteronomistic History |publisher=Leuven University Press|date=2000b |isbn= 978-90-429-0858-1}}
* Malamat A., &quot;Chapter VII: The Period of the Judges&quot; ''Judges''. The World History of the Jewish People. 3. Givatayim, Israel: Rutgers UP, 1971. pp.&amp;nbsp;129–63.
* {{Cite book|last=Matthews|first= Victor Harold|title= Judges and Ruth|publisher= Cambridge University Press|year= 2004|url= https://books.google.com/?id=vU6DjPDeUUEC|isbn= 978-0-521-00066-6}}
* {{Cite book|last= Miller |first= J Maxwell|chapter=The Ancient Near East and Archaeology |chapter-url= https://books.google.com/?id=SNLN1nEEys0C|editor1-first=James Luther | editor1-last = Mays |editor2-first=David L. | editor2-last = Petersen |editor3-first=Kent Harold | editor3-last = Richards|title= Old Testament Interpretation|publisher=T&amp;T Clark|year=1995|isbn= 978-0-567-29289-6}}
* {{cite book |last1 = Moore |first1 = Megan Bishop |last2 = Kelle |first2 = Brad E. |title = Biblical History and Israel's Past |year = 2011 |publisher = Eerdmans |url = https://books.google.com/?id=Qjkz_8EMoaUC |ref = harv |isbn = 978-0-80286260-0}}
* {{Cite book|last=Niditch |first= Susan|title=Judges: a commentary |publisher= Westminster John Knox Press|year= 2008|url= https://books.google.com/?id=BDGxWlVpQPkC&amp;pg=PA291 |isbn= 978-0-664-22096-9}}
* {{Cite book|last= Perdue |first= Leo G|chapter= Preface: The Hebrew Bible in Current Research |chapter-url= https://books.google.com/?id=41_0okLzQJkC&amp;pg=PA337&amp;lpg=PA337 |editor1-first =Leo G. | editor1-last = Perdue|title=The Blackwell Companion to the Hebrew Bible |publisher= Blackwell |year= 2001|isbn= 978-0-631-21071-9}}
* {{Cite book|last1=De Pury|first1= Albert|last2=Romer|first2= Thomas|chapter= Deuteronomistic Historiography: History of Research and Related Issues |chapter-url= https://books.google.com/?id=rex7ASbY_bkC&amp;pg=PA3|editor= Albert de Pury |editor2=Thomas Romer |editor3-first =Jean-Daniel | editor3-last = Macchi |title= Israël constructs its history: Deuteronomistic historiography in recent research |publisher= Sheffield Academic Press|year= 2000 |isbn= 978-1-84127-099-9}}
* {{Cite book|last= Soggin |first= Alberto |title=Judges|publisher= Westminster John Knox Press |year= 1981 |url= https://books.google.com/?id=5JWz4jhebW8C |isbn= 978-0-664-22321-2}}
* {{Cite book|last=Spieckerman|first= Hermann|chapter=The Deuteronomistic History|chapter-url= https://books.google.com/?id=41_0okLzQJkC&amp;pg=PA337 |editor1-first = Leo G. | editor1-last = Perdue|title=The Blackwell companion to the Hebrew Bible |publisher= Blackwell|year= 2001|isbn= 978-0-631-21071-9}}
* [[Joseph Telushkin|Telushkin, Joseph]]. 'Biblical Literacy: The Most Important People, Events, and Ideas of the Hebrew Bible''.  New York: William Morrow &amp; Co, 1997.
* {{Cite book|last=Van Seters|first= John |title=In search of history: historiography in the ancient world and the origins of biblical history |publisher= Eisenbrauns |year=1997|url= https://books.google.com/?id=0-skPdXtewwC&amp;pg=PA406 |isbn= 978-1-57506013-2}}
* {{Cite book|last= Walton |first= John H |chapter= The Deuteronomistic History |chapter-url= https://books.google.com/?id=FxFZxCIc8OoC&amp;pg=PA169 |editor1-first = Andrew E. | editor1-last = Hill |editor2-first = John H. | editor2-last = Walton|title=A Survey of the Old Testament |publisher= Zondervan |year= 2009 |isbn= 978-0-310-22903-2}}
{{Refend}}

== External links ==
{{Wikisource|Judges (Bible)}}
{{Wiktionary|Judges}}

;Original text
* [http://www.mechon-mamre.org/p/pt/pt0701.htm שֹּׁפְטִים – ''Shoftim'' – Judges] ([[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] – English at Mechon-Mamre.org)
;Jewish translations
* [http://www.mechon-mamre.org/e/et/et0701.htm Judges at Mechon-Mamre] (Jewish Publication Society translation)
* [http://www.chabad.org/library/archive/LibraryArchive2.asp?AID=15750 Shoftim – Judges (Judaica Press)] translation [with [[Rashi]]'s commentary] at Chabad.org
* [http://www.g-dcast.com/judges/ Book of Judges] (G-dcast interpretations)

;Christian translations
* [http://www.biblegateway.com/cgi-bin/bible?language=english&amp;version=NIV&amp;passage=judges Judges at Bible Gateway] (various versions)
* [[s:Bible, King James, Judges|Judges at Wikisource]] (Authorised King James Version)
* {{librivox book | dtitle=Bible: Judges |stitle=07 Judges}} Various versions

;Articles
* [http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=689&amp;letter=J&amp;search=Judges Book of Judges article] (Jewish Encyclopedia)

;Brief introduction
* [http://www.vts.edu/ftpimages/95/download/FM.Wiley.Judges.pdf Book of Judges]

{{eastons}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou | [[Nevi'im|History books]]|||}}
{{s-bef | before= [[Book of Joshua|Joshua]] | rows = 2 }}
{{s-ttl | title = [[Tanakh|Hebrew Bible]] }}
{{s-aft | after = [[Book of Samuel|Samuel]] | rows= 1 }}
{{s-ttl | title = [[Christianity|Christian]]&lt;br&gt;[[Old Testament]] }}
{{s-aft | after = [[Book of Ruth|Ruth]] | rows= 1 }}
{{s-end}}

{{Books of the Bible}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Judges, Book Of}}
[[Category:8th-century BC books]]
[[Category:7th-century BC books]]
[[Category:6th-century BC books]]
 [[Category:Judges of ancient Israel|Book of Judges]]
[[Category:Nevi'im]]
[[Category:Book of Judges]]</text>
      <sha1>qh8e3b426s1yefhi7mojq2vwtl8i42l</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
