  <page>
    <title>Bastarnae</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4342</id>
    <revision>
      <id>933348673</id>
      <parentid>929843850</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-31T11:28:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Krakkos</username>
        <id>17328627</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Primary sources|article|date=October 2011}}

[[File:Dacia 125.png|thumb|right|400px|Map showing [[Roman Dacia]] and surrounding peoples in 125 AD]]
The '''Bastarnae''' ([[Latin language|Latin]] variants: ''Bastarni'', or ''Basternae''; {{lang-grc|Βαστάρναι or Βαστέρναι}}) were an ancient people who between 200 BC and 300 AD inhabited the region between the [[Carpathian Mountains]] and the river [[Dnieper]], to the north and east of ancient [[Dacia]]. The Peucini, described as a branch of the Bastarnae by Greco-Roman writers, occupied the region north of the [[Danube Delta]].

The ethno-linguistic affiliation of the Bastarnae was probably [[Celtic languages|Celtic]], which is supported by the earliest historians.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Plutarch/Lives/Aemilius*.html|title=Plutarch • Life of Aemilius|website=penelope.uchicago.edu|language=en|access-date=2018-08-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Liv.+40+57&amp;fromdoc=Perseus:text:1999.02.0144|title=Titus Livius (Livy), The History of Rome, Book 40, chapter 57|website=www.perseus.tufts.edu|access-date=2018-08-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, later historical sources imply a [[Germanic peoples|Germanic]] or [[Scytho-Sarmatian]] origin.&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Strabo/7B*.html|title=LacusCurtius • Strabo's Geography — Book VII Chapter 2|website=penelope.uchicago.edu|language=en|access-date=2018-08-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Tac.+Ger.+46&amp;fromdoc=Perseus:text:1999.02.0083|title=Cornelius Tacitus, Germany and its Tribes, chapter 46|website=www.perseus.tufts.edu|access-date=2018-08-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/e/roman/texts/cassius_dio/51*.html|title=Cassius Dio — Book 51|website=penelope.uchicago.edu|language=en|access-date=2018-08-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.livius.org/sources/content/zosimus/zosimus-new-history-1/zosimus-new-history-1.71/|title=Zosimus, New History 1.71 – Livius|website=www.livius.org|language=en|access-date=2018-08-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Often they are associated with the Germans, or the peoples &quot;between the Celts and the Germans&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.academia.edu/37948120/%D0%91%D0%B0%D0%BB%D1%82%D1%8B_%D0%B2_%D0%BC%D0%B8%D0%B3%D1%80%D0%B0%D1%86%D0%B8%D1%8F%D1%85_%D0%92%D0%B5%D0%BB%D0%B8%D0%BA%D0%BE%D0%B3%D0%BE_%D0%BF%D0%B5%D1%80%D0%B5%D1%81%D0%B5%D0%BB%D0%B5%D0%BD%D0%B8%D1%8F_%D0%BD%D0%B0%D1%80%D0%BE%D0%B4%D0%BE%D0%B2._%D0%92%D0%B5%D0%BB%D1%8C%D1%82%D1%8B Tarasov I.M. The Balts in the Migration Period. Veleti. // Аллея Науки, № 10 (26), Ноябрь, 2018. P. 258.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Щукин М.Б. На рубеже эр. СПб.: Фарн, 1994. С. 20.&lt;/ref&gt; The most likely scenario is that they were originally a Celtic tribe, originally resident in the lower [[Vistula River]] valley. Around 200 BC, these tribes migrated, possibly accompanied by some Germanic elements, south-eastwards into the North Pontic region. Some elements appear to have become assimilated, to some extent, by the surrounding [[Sarmatians]] by the 3rd century.

Although largely sedentary, some elements may have adopted a semi-nomadic lifestyle. So far, no archaeological sites have been conclusively attributed to the Bastarnae. The archaeological horizons most often associated by scholars with the Bastarnae are the [[Zarubintsy culture|Zarubintsy]] and [[Poienesti-Lukashevka culture|Poienesti-Lukashevka]] cultures.

The Bastarnae first came into conflict with the Romans during the 1st century BC when, in alliance with [[Dacians]] and Sarmatians, they unsuccessfully resisted Roman expansion into [[Moesia]] and [[Pannonia]]. Later, they appear to have maintained friendly relations with the [[Roman Empire]] during the first two centuries AD. This changed c. 180, when the Bastarnae are recorded as participants in an invasion of Roman territory, once again in alliance with Sarmatian and Dacian elements. In the mid-3rd century, the Bastarnae were part of a [[Goths|Gothic]]-led grand coalition of lower Danube tribes that repeatedly invaded the Balkan provinces of the Roman Empire.

Many Bastarnae were resettled within the Roman Empire in the late 3rd century.

== Ancient sources ==
According to [[Polybius]] (200–118 BC):

&quot;A mission from the Dardanians now arrived, telling of the Bastarnae, their numbers, the huge size and the valour of their warriors, and also pointing out that Perseus and the Galatians were in league with this tribe. They said they were much more afraid of him than of the Bastarnae, and they begged for aid.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Polybius/25*.html|title=Polybius • Histories — Book 25|website=penelope.uchicago.edu|language=en|access-date=2018-08-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;''

According to [[Livy]] (64 BC – 17 AD):

&quot;The way to the Hadriatic and to Italy lay through the Scordisci; that was the only practicable route for an army, and the Scordisci were expected to grant a passage to the Bastarnae without any difficulty, for neither in speech nor habits were they dissimilar, and it was hoped that they would unite forces with them when they saw that they were going to secure the plunder of a very wealthy nation.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot; /&gt;

According to [[Strabo]] (64 BC – 24 AD):

&quot;However, it is clear from the &quot;climata&quot; and the parallel distances that if one travels longitudinally towards the east, one encounters the regions that are about the Borysthenes and that are to the north of the Pontus; but what is beyond Germany and what beyond the countries which are next after Germany — whether one should say the Bastarnae, as most writers suspect, or say that others lie in between, either the Iazyges, or the Roxolani, or certain other of the wagon-dwellers — it is not easy to say; nor yet whether they extend as far as the ocean along its entire length, or whether any part is uninhabitable by reason of the cold or other cause, or whether even a different race of people, succeeding the Germans, is situated between the sea and the eastern Germans. And this same ignorance prevails also in regard to the rest of the peoples that come next in order on the north; for I know neither the Bastarnae, nor the Sauromatae, nor, in a word, any of the peoples who dwell above the Pontus, nor how far distant they are from the Atlantic Sea, nor whether their countries border upon it.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt;''

Accroding to [[Plutarch]] (46–120 AD):

&quot;He also secretly stirred up the Gauls settled along the Danube, who are called Basternae, an equestrian host and warlike; and he invited the Illyrians, through Genthius their king, to take part with him in the war. And a report prevailed that the Barbarians had been hired by him to pass through lower Gaul, along the coast of the Adriatic, and make an incursion into Italy.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;''

According to [[Tacitus]] (56–120 AD):

&quot;As to the tribes of the Peucini, Veneti, and Fenni I am in doubt whether I should class them with the Germans or the Sarmatæ, although indeed the Peucini called by some Bastarnæ, are like Germans in their language, mode of life, and in the permanence of their settlements. They all live in filth and sloth, and by the intermarriages of the chiefs they are becoming in some degree debased into a resemblance to the Sarmatæ.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt;

According to [[Cassius Dio]] (155–235 AD):

&quot;During the same period in which these events occurred Marcus Crassus was sent into Macedonia and Greece and carried on war with the Dacians and Bastarnae. I have already stated who the former were and why they had become hostile; the Bastarnae, on the other hand, who are properly classed as Scythians, had at this time crossed the Ister and subdued the part of Moesia opposite them, and afterwards subdued the Triballi who adjoin this district and the Dardani who inhabit the Triballian country.&quot;

According to [[Zosimus|Zosismus]] (490s–510 AD):

&quot;He likewise left in Thrace the Bastarnae, a Scythian people, who submitted to him, giving them land to inhabit there; on which account they observed the Roman laws and customs.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;:4&quot; /&gt;

== Etymology ==
The origin of the tribal name is uncertain. It is not even clear whether it was an exonym (a name ascribed to them by outsiders) or an endonym (a name by which the Bastarnae described themselves). A related question is whether the groups denoted &quot;Bastarnae&quot; by the Romans considered themselves a distinct ethnic group at all (endonym) or whether it was a generic exonym used by the Greco-Romans to denote a disparate group of tribes of the Carpathian region that could not be classified as Dacians or Sarmatians.

One possible derivation is from the [[proto-Germanic]] word ''*bastjan'' (from [[Proto-Indo-European language|Proto-Indo-European]] root *''bʰas-''), meaning &quot;binding&quot; or &quot;tie&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Köbler *''bʰas''&lt;/ref&gt; In this case, ''Bastarnae'' may have had the original meaning of a coalition or ''bund'' of tribes.

It is possible that the Roman term ''[[basterna]]'', denoting a type of wagon or litter, is derived from the name of this people (or, if it is an exonym, that the name of the people is derived from it) who were known, like many Germanic tribes, to travel with a wagon train for their families.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dio LI.24.4&quot;&gt;Dio LI.24.4&lt;/ref&gt;

It has also been suggested that the name is linked with the Germanic word ''bastard'', meaning illegitimate or mongrel, but Batty considers this derivation unlikely.&lt;ref&gt;Batty (2008)&lt;/ref&gt; If the name is an endonym, then this derivation is unlikely, as most endonyms have flattering meanings (e.g. &quot;brave&quot;, &quot;strong&quot;, &quot;noble&quot;).

Trubačev&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Trubačev INDOARICA в Северном Причерноморье, pp. 212–3&lt;/ref&gt; proposes a derivation from [[Old Persian]], [[Avestan]] ''bast-'' &quot;bound, tied; slave&quot; (cf. [[Ossetic]] bættən &quot;bind&quot;, bast &quot;bound&quot;) and [[Iranian languages|Iranian]] ''*arna-'' &quot;offspring&quot;, equating it with the ''δουλόσποροι'' &quot;slave Sporoi&quot; mentioned by [[Nonnus]] and [[Cosmas of Maiuma|Cosmas]], where the [[Sporoi]] are the people [[Procopius]] mentions as the ancestors of the [[Slavs]].&lt;ref&gt;Procopius. Wars (VIII.I4, 22–30)&lt;/ref&gt;

== Territory ==
[[File:Castris rubris tabula peutingeriana1.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Location of ''Blastarni'' and the ''Alpes Bastarnicae'' north of [[Roman Dacia]], as depicted on [[Tabula Peutingeriana]]]]
The original homeland of the Bastarnae remains uncertain. Babeş and Shchukin argue in favour of [[Pomeranian culture|an origin]] in eastern [[Pomerania]] on the [[Baltic sea|Baltic]] coast of today's north-west [[Poland]], on the grounds of correspondences in archaeological material, e.g. a Pomeranian-style [[fibula (brooch)|fibula]] found in a Poieneşti site in [[Moldavia]],&lt;ref&gt;Shchukin (1989) 65-6, 71–2&lt;/ref&gt; although Batty considers the evidence insufficient.&lt;ref&gt;Batty (2008) 248&lt;/ref&gt; Babeş identifies the Sidoni, a branch of the Bastarnae which [[Strabo]] places north of the Danube delta&lt;ref name=&quot;Strabo VII.3.17&quot;&gt;Strabo VII.3.17&lt;/ref&gt; with the ''Sidini'' located by Ptolemy in Pomerania.&lt;ref&gt;Babeş (1969) 195–218&lt;/ref&gt;

Batty argues that Greco-Roman sources of the 1st century AD locate the Bastarnae homeland on the northern side of the [[Carpathians|Northern Carpathian]] mountain range, encompassing south-east Poland and south-west [[Ukraine]] (i.e. the region traditionally known as [[Galicia (Eastern Europe)|Galicia]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Batty 2008 238&quot;&gt;Batty (2008) 238&lt;/ref&gt; Pliny locates the Bastarnae between the [[Suebi]]&lt;ref&gt;Pliny NH IV.81&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Dacians]] (''contermini Dacis'').&lt;ref&gt;Pliny NH IV.100&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Peutinger Map]] (produced ca. 400 AD, but including material from as early as the 1st century) shows the Bastarnae (mis-spelt ''Blastarni'') north of the Carpathian mountains and appears to name the Galician Carpathians as the ''Alpes Bastarnicae''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Batty 2008 238&quot;/&gt;

From Galicia, the Bastarnae expanded into the [[Moldavia]] and [[Bessarabia]] regions, reaching the [[Danube Delta]]. Strabo describes the Bastarnae as inhabiting the territory &quot;between the ''Ister'' (the [[Danube]]) and the ''Borysthenes'' (the [[Dnieper]])&quot;. He identifies three sub-tribes of the Bastarnae: the [[Atmoni]], [[Sidoni]] and [[Peucini]]. The latter derived their name from [[Peuce Island|Peuce]], a large island in the Danube Delta which they had colonised.&lt;ref name=&quot;Strabo VII.3.17&quot;/&gt; The 2nd-century geographer [[Ptolemy]] states that the ''Carpiani'' or [[Carpi (Dacian tribe)|Carpi]] (believed to have occupied Moldavia) separated the Peucini from the other Bastarnae &quot;above [[Dacia]]&quot; (i.e. north of Dacia).&lt;ref&gt;Ptolemy III.5.9&lt;/ref&gt;

It thus appears that the Bastarnae were settled in a vast arc stretching around the northern and eastern flanks of the Carpathians from south-east Poland to the Danube Delta. The larger group inhabited the northern and eastern slopes of the Carpathians and the region between the [[Prut]] and Dnieper rivers (modern-day Moldova/western Ukraine), while a separate group (the Peucini, Sidoni and Atmoni) dwelt in and north of the Danube Delta region.&lt;ref&gt;Barrington Plate 22&lt;/ref&gt;

== Ethno-linguistic affiliation ==
Scholars hold divergent theories about the ethnicity of the Bastarnae. One view, following what appears to be the most authoritative view among earliest scholars, is that they spoke a [[Celtic languages|Celtic language]].&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;/&gt; However others hold that they were Scythian/Germanic,&lt;ref name=&quot;:2&quot; /&gt; or mixed Germanic/Sarmatian.&lt;ref name=&quot;:3&quot; /&gt; A fringe theory is that they were [[Proto-Slavic]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Shchukin argues that the ethnicity of the Bastarnae was unique and rather than trying to label the Bastanae as Celtic, Germanic or Sarmatian, it should be accepted that the &quot;Basternae were the Basternae&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shchukin, 1990. Pg 10&quot;&gt;Shchukin, 1990. Pg 10&lt;/ref&gt; Batty argues that assigning an &quot;ethnicity&quot; to the Bastarnae is meaningless; as in the context of the [[Iron Age]] Pontic-Danubian region, with its multiple overlapping peoples and languages, ethnicity was a very fluid concept: it could and did change rapidly and frequently, according to socio-political vicissitudes. This was especially true of the Bastarnae, who are attested over a relatively vast area.&lt;ref&gt;Batty (2008) 243&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Celtic ===
A leading reason to consider the Bastarnae as Celtic is that the regions they are documented to have occupied (the northern and eastern slopes of the Carpathians) overlapped to a great extent with the locations of Celtic tribes attested in the northern Carpathians. (The modern name of this region, [[Galicia (Eastern Europe)|Galicia]], is generally regarded as having a later origin, in either a Slavic or Turkic language. However, some scholars have instead suggested that the name Galicia may derive from its former Celtic inhabitants the [[Taurisci]], [[Osi (ancient tribe)|Osi]], [[Cotini]] and [[Anartes]] of Slovakia and northern Romania and the [[Britogalli]] of the Danube Delta region.&lt;ref&gt;Batty (2008) 222&lt;/ref&gt;) In addition, archaeological cultures which some scholars have linked to the Bastarnae (Poieneşti-Lukashevka and Zarubintsy) display pronounced Celtic affinities. Finally, the arrival of the Bastarnae in the Pontic-Danubian region, which can be dated to 233–216 BC according to two ancient sources,&lt;ref name=&quot;Batty 2008 237&quot;&gt;Batty (2008) 237&lt;/ref&gt; coincides with the latter phase of [[Celtic settlement of Southeast Europe|Celtic migration into the region]] (400–200 BC).

The earliest historians give a Celtic or Gallic origin to the Bastarnae. Roman historian [[Livy]], writing in c. 10 AD, attests that the Bastarnae spoke Celtic. Relating the Bastarnic invasion of the Balkans of 179 BC (see [[Bastarnae#Allies_of_Philip_of_Macedon_(179-8_BC)|Allies of Philip of Macedon]] below), he describes them then as &quot;they were not very different in either language or manners&quot; to the Celtic tribe of the [[Scordisci]], a tribe of [[Pannonia]]. The Scordisci are described as Celtic by [[Strabo]] (although he adds that they had mingled with Illyrians and Thracians).&lt;ref&gt;Strabo VII.5.2&lt;/ref&gt; The Greek historian [[Plutarch]] inform us that the Roman consul Hostilius &quot;secretly stirred up the Gauls settled along the Danube, who are called Basternae&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;''

However, a Celtic identity for the Bastarnae is apparently contradicted by [[Polybius]] (writing ca. 150 BC), who was an actual contemporary of the events described, unlike Livy, who was writing some 200 years later. Polybius clearly distinguishes the Bastarnae from the &quot;Galatae&quot; (i.e. Celts): &quot;An embassy from the [[Dardani]] arrived [at the [[Roman Senate]]], talking of the Bastarnae, their huge numbers, the strength and valour of their warriors, and also reporting that Perseus [king of Macedon] and the Galatae were in league with this tribe.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Polybius XXV.6.2&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, inscription AE (1905) 14, recording a campaign on the [[Hungarian Plain]] by the Augustan-era general [[Marcus Vinicius (consul 19 BC)|Marcus Vinucius]] (10 BC{{sfn|Almassy|2006|p=253}} or 8 BC{{sfn|CAH Vol X|1996|p=}}), also appears to distinguish the Bastarnae from neighbouring Celtic tribes: &quot;Marcus Vinucius... governor of Illyricum, the first [Roman general] to advance across the river Danube, defeated in battle and routed an army of Dacians and Basternae, and subjugated the Cotini, Osi,...[missing tribal name] and Anartii to the power of the emperor Augustus and of the people of Rome.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Année Epigraphique (1905) no. 14&lt;/ref&gt;

The three names of Bastarnae leaders found in ancient sources are of Celtic origin: Cotto,&lt;ref name=&quot;Livy XL.57&quot;&gt;Livy XL.57&lt;/ref&gt; Clondicus&lt;ref name=&quot;Livy XL.58&quot;&gt;Livy XL.58&lt;/ref&gt; and Teutagonus.&lt;ref&gt;[[Gaius Valerius Flaccus]] ''Argonautica'' VI.97&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Batty (2008) 222. Cotto: cf. [[Cottius]], king of the Alpine [[Salassi]] tribe and friend of [[Augustus]], after whom were named the [[Alpes Cottiae]] Roman province; and the [[Cotini]] Celtic tribe of the northern Carpathians. Both probably derived from ''cotto-'' = &quot;old&quot; or &quot;crooked&quot;). (Faliyeyev (2007) entries 3806, 3890). Clondicus: cf. Klondyke, name of some places in Wales and Scotland. Teutagonus:&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Germanic tribes (750BC-1AD)}}

=== Germanic ===
Greco-Roman geographers of the 1st century AD are unanimous and specific that the Bastarnae were [[Germanic peoples|Germanic]] in language and culture. The Greek geographer [[Strabo]] (writing c. 5–20 AD) says the Bastarnae are &quot;of Germanic stock&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Strabo VII.3.17&quot; /&gt; The Roman geographer [[Pliny the Elder]] (c. 77 AD), classifies the Bastarnae and Peucini as being one of the five main subdivisions of Germanic peoples (the other subdivisions are three [[West Germanic languages|West Germanic]] tribes, the ''Inguaeones'', ''Istuaeones'' and ''Hermiones'', and the [[East Germanic]] ''[[Vandals|Vandili]]'', but he classifies differently{{clarify |date=September 2019 |reason=classifies what differently?}} than the Bastarnae).&lt;ref&gt;Pliny NH IV.14&lt;/ref&gt;

The Roman historian [[Tacitus]] (c. 100 AD) describes the Bastarnae as Germans with substantial Sarmatian influence, but moves on to state: &quot;The Peucini, however, who are sometimes called Bastarnae, are like the Germans in their language, way of life and types of dwelling.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tacitus G.46&quot;&gt;Tacitus G.46&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Scytho-Sarmatian ===
Strabo includes the [[Roxolani]], generally considered by scholars to have been a [[Sarmatian]] tribe, in a list of Bastarnae subgroups.&lt;ref name=&quot;Strabo VII.3.17&quot;/&gt; However, this may simply be an error due to the close proximity of the two peoples north of the Danube Delta. In the 3rd century, the Greek historian [[Dio Cassius]] states that the &quot;Bastarnae are properly classed as Scythians&quot; and &quot;members of the Scythian race&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Dio LI.23.3, 24.2&lt;/ref&gt; Likewise, the 6th-century historian [[Zosimus]], reporting events around 280 AD, refers to &quot;the Bastarnae, a Scythian people&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zosimus I.34&quot;&gt;Zosimus I.34&lt;/ref&gt; However, it appears that these late Greco-Roman chroniclers used the term &quot;Scythian&quot; more often in a geographical sense (for inhabitants of the region they called Scythia, i.e. the Pontic region north of the Danube) rather than in an ethnic one (for members of the [[Scythians|Scythian]] people, steppe nomads of Iranic origin, related to the Sarmatians, who had supplanted the Scythians' dominance of the steppes in the period BC). For example, Zosimus also routinely refers to the [[Goths]], who were undoubtedly Germanic-speakers, as &quot;Scythians&quot;.

It is possible that some Bastarnae may have been assimilated by the surrounding (and possibly dominant) Sarmatians, perhaps adopting their tongue (which belonged to the [[Iranian languages|Iranian]] group of Indo-European languages) and customs. Thus Tacitus' comment that &quot;mixed marriages are giving [the Bastarnae] to some extent the vile appearance of the Sarmatians&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tacitus G.46&quot;/&gt; On the other hand, the Bastarnae maintained a separate name until ca. 300 AD, probably implying retention of their distinctive ethno-linguistic heritage up to that time.&lt;ref&gt;cf. Historia Augusta ''Probus'' 18&lt;/ref&gt; It seems likely, on balance, that the core population of Bastarnae had always been, and continued to be, Germanic in language and culture.

== Material culture ==
[[File:Rekonstruktionsversuch bastarnischer Trachten (eine Gruppe aus Pomoranischer Kultur) von dem Aussere Karpatensenke und Westbeskiden, 2 bis 3 Jh. PR DSC 1317.JPG|thumb|right|200px|Attempt to reconstruct Bastarnae costumes at the [[Archaeological Museum of Kraków]]. Such clothing and weapons were commonplace among peoples on the Roman Empire's borders.]]
[[File:Rome and the Barbarians in Eastern and Central Europe around 100 AD by Shchukin.png|thumb|right|275px|Archaeological cultures in the early Roman period, c. 100 AD]]

According to [[Malcolm Todd]], traditional archaeology has not been able to construct a typology of Bastarnae material culture, and thus to ascribe particular archaeological sites to the Bastarnae.&lt;ref name=&quot;Todd 2004 23-4&quot;&gt;Todd (2004) 23-4&lt;/ref&gt; A complicating factor is that the regions where Bastarnae are attested contained a patchwork of peoples and cultures (Sarmatians, Scythians, Dacians, Thracians, Celts, Germans and others), some [[sedentism|sedentary]], some [[nomad]]ic. In any event, post-1960s archaeological theory has questioned the validity of equating material &quot;cultures&quot;, as defined by archaeologists, with distinct ethnic groups. In this view, it is impossible to attribute a &quot;culture&quot; to a particular ethnic group: it is likely that the material cultures discerned in the region belonged to several, if not all, of the groups inhabiting it. These cultures probably represent relatively large-scale socio-economic interactions between disparate communities of the broad region, possibly including mutually antagonistic groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;Todd 2004 23-4&quot;/&gt;

It is not even certain whether the Bastarnae were sedentary, nomadic or semi-nomadic. Tacitus' statement that they were &quot;German in their way of life and types of dwelling&quot; implies a sedentary bias, but their close relations with the Sarmatians, who were nomadic, may indicate a more nomadic lifestyle for some Bastarnae, as does their attested wide geographical range.&lt;ref name=&quot;Todd 2004 23&quot;&gt;Todd (2004) 23&lt;/ref&gt; If the Bastarnae were nomadic, then the sedentary &quot;cultures&quot; identified by archaeologists in their ''lebensraum'' would not represent them. Nomadic peoples generally leave scant traces, due to the impermanent materials and foundations used in the construction of their dwellings.

Scholars have identified two closely related sedentary &quot;cultures&quot; as possible candidates to represent the Bastarnae (among other peoples) as their locations broadly correspond to where ancient sources placed the Basternae: the [[Zarubintsy culture]] lying in the forest-steppe zone in northern Ukraine and southern Belarus, and the [[Poieneşti-Lukashevka culture]] ([[Lucăşeuca]]) in northern Moldavia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Batty 2008 237&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvtxt|Shchukin|1990|p=10}}&lt;/ref&gt; These cultures were characterised by agriculture, documented by numerous finds of sickles. Dwellings were either of surface or semi-subterranean types, with posts supporting the walls, a hearth in the middle and large conical pits located nearby. Some sites were defended by ditches and banks, structures thought to have been built to defend against nomadic tribes from the steppe.&lt;ref&gt;Mallory. EIEC''. Page 657&lt;/ref&gt; Inhabitants practiced cremation. Cremated remains were either placed in large, hand-made ceramic urns, or were placed in a large pit and surrounded by food and ornaments such as spiral bracelets and Middle to Late [[La Tène culture|La Tène]]-type ''fibulae'' (attesting the continuing strength of Celtic influence in this region).

A major problem with associating the Poieneşti-Lukashevka and Zarubintsy cultures with the Bastarnae is that both cultures had disappeared by the early 1st century AD, while the Bastarnae continue to be attested in those regions throughout the Roman [[Principate]].&lt;ref&gt;Batty (2008) 237-9&lt;/ref&gt; Another issue is that the Poieneşti-Lukashevka culture has also been attributed to the [[Costoboci]], a people considered ethnically [[Dacians|Dacian]] by mainstream scholarship, who inhabited northern Moldavia, according to Ptolemy (ca. 140 AD). Indeed, [[Mircea Babeş]] and [[Silvia Theodor]], the two [[Romanian archaeologists]] who identified Lukashevka as Bastarnic, nevertheless insisted that the majority of the population in the Lukashevka sphere (in northern Moldavia) was &quot;Geto-Dacian&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Batty 2008 238&quot;/&gt; A further problem is that neither of these cultures were present in the Danube Delta region, where a major concentration of Bastarnae are attested by the ancient sources.&lt;ref name=&quot;Batty 2008 237&quot;/&gt;

Starting in about 200 AD, the [[Chernyakhov culture]] became established in the modern-day western Ukraine and Moldova region inhabited by the Bastarnae. The culture is characterised by a high degree of sophistication in the production of metal and ceramic artefacts, as well as of uniformity over a vast area. Although this culture has conventionally been identified with the migration of the [[Goths|Gothic]] ''ethnos'' into the region from the northwest, Todd argues that its most important origin is Scytho-Sarmatian. Although the Goths certainly contributed to it, so probably did other peoples of the region such as the Dacians, [[Early Slavs|proto-Slavs]], [[Carpi (people)|Carpi]] and possibly the Bastarnae.&lt;ref&gt;Todd (2004) 26&lt;/ref&gt;

== Relations with Rome ==

=== Roman Republican era (to 30 BC) ===

==== Allies of Philip of Macedon (179–8 BC) ====
[[File:Philip V of Macedon BM.jpg|thumb|right|Silver [[tetradrachm]] of Philip V of Macedon]]

The Bastarnae first appear in the historical record in 179 BC, when they crossed the Danube in a massive force. They did so at the invitation of their long-time ally, King [[Philip V of Macedon]], a direct descendant of [[Antigonus I Monophthalmus|Antigonus]], one of the [[Diadochi]], the generals of [[Alexander the Great]] who had shared his empire after his death in 323 BC. The Macedonian king had suffered a disastrous defeat at the hands of the Romans in the [[Second Macedonian War]] (200–197 BC), which had reduced him from a powerful [[Hellenistic]] monarch to the status of a petty client-king with a much-reduced territory and a tiny army.{{refn|group=Note|name=cnoteb|The terms imposed on Philip V of Macedon in 196 BC were: (i) loss of all possessions outside [[Macedon]]ia proper (Philip had previously ruled extensive territories in Greece, Thrace and Asia Minor); (ii) standing army limited to 5,000 men and no elephants; (iii) navy limited to 5 warships plus royal galley; (iv) reparation payment of 1,000 [[talent (measurement)|talents]] (c. 26 tonnes) of silver, equivalent then to c. 4 tonnes of gold. (In antiquity, silver was far more valuable than today: the gold/silver value ratio was c. 1:7, compared to c. 1:100 today); (v) prohibited from waging war outside his borders without the Roman Senate's permission&lt;ref&gt;Livy XXXIII.30&lt;/ref&gt;}} After nearly 20 years of slavish adherence to the Roman Senate's dictats, Philip had been goaded by the incessant and devastating raiding of the [[Dardani]], a warlike Thraco-Illyrian&lt;ref&gt;A Mocsy. Pannonia and Upper Moesia&lt;/ref&gt; tribe on his northern border, which his treaty-limited army was too small to counter effectively. Counting on the Bastarnae, with whom he had forged friendly relations, he plotted a strategy to deal with the Dardani and then to regain his lost territories in Greece and his political independence. First, he would [[Dardanian-Bastarnae war|unleash the Bastarnae against the Dardani]]. After the latter had been crushed, Philip planned to settle Bastarnae families in Dardania (southern [[Kosovo]]/[[Skopje]] region) to ensure that the region was permanently subdued. In a second phase, Philip aimed to launch the Bastarnae on an invasion of Italy via the Adriatic coast. Although he was aware that the Bastarnae were likely to be defeated, Philip hoped that the Romans would be distracted long enough to allow him to reoccupy his former possessions in Greece.&lt;ref name=&quot;Livy XL.57&quot;/&gt;

However, Philip, now 60 years of age, died before the Bastarnae could arrive. The Bastarnae host was still ''en route'' through Thrace, where it became embroiled in hostilities with the locals, who had not provided them with sufficient food at affordable prices as they marched through. Probably in the vicinity of [[Plovdiv|Philippopolis]] (modern Plovdiv, Bulgaria), the Bastarnae broke out of their marching columns and pillaged the land far and wide. The terrified local Thracians took refuge with their families and animal herds on the slopes of ''Mons Donuca'' ([[Musala|Mount Musala]]), the highest mountain in Thrace. A large force of Bastarnae chased them up the mountain, but were driven back and scattered by a massive hailstorm. Then the Thracians ambushed them, turning their descent into a panic-stricken rout. Back at their [[wagon fort]] in the plain, around half of the demoralised Bastarnae decided to return home, leaving c. 30,000 to press on to Macedonia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Livy XL.58&quot;/&gt;

Philip's son and successor [[Perseus of Macedon|Perseus]], while protesting his loyalty to Rome, deployed his Bastarnae guests in winter quarters in a valley in Dardania, presumably as a prelude to a campaign against the Dardani the following summer. However, in the depths of winter their camp was attacked by the Dardani. The Bastarnae easily beat off the attackers, chased them back to their chief town and besieged them, but they were surprised in the rear by a second force of Dardani, which had approached their camp stealthily by mountain paths, and proceeded to storm and ransack it. Having lost their entire baggage and supplies, the Bastarnae were obliged to withdraw from Dardania and to return home. Most perished as they crossed the frozen Danube on foot, only for the ice to give way.&lt;ref&gt;Livy XLI.19&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the failure of Philip's Bastarnae strategy, the suspicion aroused by these events in the Roman Senate, which had been warned by the Dardani of the Bastarnae invasion, ensured the demise of Macedonia as an independent state.&lt;ref&gt;Livy XLI.23 and XLII.12-4&lt;/ref&gt; Rome declared war on Perseus in 171 BC and after the Macedonian army was crushed at the [[Battle of Pydna]] (168 BC), Macedonia was split up into four Roman puppet-cantons (167 BC).&lt;ref&gt;Livy XLV.19&lt;/ref&gt; Twenty-one years later, these were in turn abolished and annexed to the [[Roman Republic]] as the [[Macedonia (Roman province)|province of Macedonia]] (146 BC).

==== Allies of Getan high king Burebista (62 BC) ====
[[File:Scythia Minor map.jpg|thumb|right|Map of [[Scythia Minor]] (Dobruja), showing the Greek coastal cities of Histria, Tomis, Callatis and Dionysopolis (Istria, Constanţa, Mangalia and Balchik)]]
[[File:HistriaCoins.jpg|thumb|right|Coin issued by the Greek coastal city of [[Histria (Sinoe)|Histria]] (Sinoe)]]
The Bastarnae first came into direct conflict with Rome as a result of expansion into the lower Danube region by the [[proconsuls]] (governors) of Macedonia in 75–72 BC. [[Gaius Scribonius Curio]] (proconsul 75–73 BC) campaigned successfully against the Dardani and the [[Moesi]], becoming the first Roman general to reach the Danube with his army.&lt;ref&gt;Smith's Dictionary: ''Curio''&lt;/ref&gt; His successor, [[Marcus Terentius Varro Lucullus|Marcus Licinius Lucullus]] (brother of the famous [[Lucullus|Lucius Lucullus]]), campaigned against the Thracian [[Bessi]] tribe and the Moesi, ravaging the whole of [[Moesia]], the region between the Haemus ([[Balkan]]) mountain range and the Danube. In 72 BC, his troops occupied the Greek coastal cities of [[Scythia Minor]] (modern [[Dobruja]] region, Romania/Bulgaria),{{refn|group=Note|name=cnotec|The main ones were: [[Histria (Sinoe)]], [[Constanța|Tomis]], [[Callatis]], [[Sozopol|Apollonia]] (Istria, Constanţa, Mangalia, Sozopol)&lt;ref&gt;Strabo VII.6.1&lt;/ref&gt;}} which had sided with Rome's [[Hellenistic]] arch-enemy, King [[Mithridates VI]] of [[Pontus (region)|Pontus]], in the [[Third Mithridatic War]] (73–63 BC).&lt;ref&gt;Smith's Dictionary: ''Lucullus''&lt;/ref&gt;

The presence of Roman forces in the Danube Delta was seen as a major threat by all the neighbouring transdanubian peoples: the Peucini Bastarnae, the Sarmatians and, most importantly, by [[Burebista]] (ruled 82–44 BC), king of the [[Getae]]. The Getae occupied the region today called [[Wallachia]] as well as Scythia Minor and were either a [[Dacian language|Dacian]]- or [[Thracian language|Thracian]]- speaking people.{{refn|group=Note|name=cnoted|There is controversy about whether the [[Getae]] were Dacian or Thracian speakers and whether those two languages were similar. Strabo claims that the Getae were [[Thracians]].&lt;ref&gt;Strabo VII.3.2&lt;/ref&gt; He adds that the [[Dacians]] spoke the same language as the Getae.&lt;ref&gt;Strabo VII.3.13&lt;/ref&gt; This gave rise to the hypothesis that Thracian and Dacian were essentially the same language (the [[Daco-Thracian]] theory). But the modern linguist [[Vladimir I. Georgiev|Vladimir Georgiev]] disputes that Dacian and Thracian were closely related for various reasons, especially that Dacian and Moesian town names commonly end with the suffix -DAVA, while towns in [[Thrace]] proper generally end in -PARA. According to Georgiev, the language spoken by the Getae should be classified as &quot;Daco-Moesian&quot; and regarded as quite distinct from Thracian.&lt;ref&gt;Vladimir Georgiev (Gheorghiev), ''Raporturile dintre limbile dacă, tracă şi frigiană'', &quot;Studii Clasice&quot; Journal, II, 1960, 39–58.&lt;/ref&gt; Support for the Daco-Moesian theory can be found in Dio, who confirms that the Moesians and Getae on the south bank of the Danube were Dacians.&lt;ref&gt;Dio LI.22.6–7&lt;/ref&gt; But the scant evidence available for these two extinct languages does not permit any firm conclusions. For the dividing-line between the two placename forms, see the following map (lower map, scroll down): [http://members.tripod.com/~Groznijat/thrac/thrac_map.html members.tripod.com]}} Burebista had unified the Getae tribes into a single kingdom, for which the Greek cities were vital trade outlets. In addition, he had established his hegemony over neighbouring Sarmatian and Bastarnae tribes. At its peak, the Getae kingdom reportedly was able to muster 200,000 warriors. Burebista led his transdanubian coalition in a struggle against Roman encroachment, conducting many raids against Roman allies in [[Moesia]] and Thrace, penetrating as far as Macedonia and [[Illyria]].&lt;ref&gt;Strabo VII.3.11–12&lt;/ref&gt;

The coalition's main chance came in 62 BC, when the Greek cities rebelled against Roman rule. In 61 BC, the notoriously oppressive and militarily incompetent proconsul of Macedonia, [[Gaius Antonius Hybrida|Gaius Antonius]], nicknamed ''Hybrida'' (&quot;The Monster&quot;), an uncle of the famous [[Mark Antony]], led an army against the Greek cities. As his army approached [[Histria (Sinoe)|Histria]], Antonius detached his entire mounted force from the marching column and led it away on a lengthy excursion, leaving his infantry without cavalry cover, a tactic he had already used with disastrous results against the Dardani.&lt;ref&gt;Dio XXXVIII.10.2&lt;/ref&gt; Dio implies that he did so out of cowardice, in order to avoid the imminent clash with the opposition, but it is more likely that he was pursuing a large enemy cavalry force, probably [[Sarmatians]]. A Bastarnae host, which had crossed the Danube to assist the Histrians, promptly attacked, surrounded and massacred the Roman infantry, capturing several of their ''[[vexillum|vexilla]]'' (military standards).&lt;ref&gt;Dio XXXVIII.10.3 and LI.26.5&lt;/ref&gt; This battle resulted in the collapse of the Roman position on the lower Danube. Burebista apparently annexed the Greek cities (55–48 BC).&lt;ref&gt;Crişan (1978) 118&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, the subjugated &quot;allied&quot; tribes of Moesia and Thrace evidently repudiated their treaties with Rome, as they had to be reconquered by [[Augustus]] in 29–8 BC (see below).

In 44 BC, Roman [[dictator perpetuus|dictator-for-life]] [[Julius Caesar]] planned to lead a major campaign to crush Burebista and his allies once and for all, but he was assassinated before it could start.&lt;ref&gt;Strabo VII.3.5&lt;/ref&gt; However, the campaign was made redundant by Burebista's overthrow and death in the same year, after which his Getae empire fragmented into four, later five, independent petty kingdoms. These were militarily far weaker, as Strabo assessed their combined military potential at just 40,000 armed men, and were often involved in internecine warfare.&lt;ref&gt;Strabo VII.3.11&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dio LI.26.1&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Geto-Dacians]] did not again become a threat to Roman hegemony in the lower Danube until the rise of [[Decebal]] 130 years later (86 AD).

=== Roman Principate (30 BC – 284 AD) ===

==== Augustan era (30 BC – 14 AD) ====
[[File:Statue-Augustus.jpg|thumb|right|Statue of [[Augustus]] in the garb of Roman ''[[imperator]]'' (military supreme commander). By the end of his sole rule (14 AD), Augustus had expanded the empire to the [[Danube]], which was to remain its central/eastern European border for its entire history (except for the occupation of [[Dacia]] 105–275).]]

Once he had established himself as sole ruler of the Roman state in 30 BC, Caesar's grand-nephew and adopted son [[Augustus]] inaugurated a strategy of advancing the empire's south-eastern European border to the line of the Danube from the [[Alps]], the [[Dinaric Alps]] and Macedonia. The primary objective was to increase strategic depth between the border and Italy and also to provide a major fluvial supply route between the Roman armies in the region.&lt;ref&gt;''Res Gestae'' 30&lt;/ref&gt;

On the lower Danube, which was given priority over the upper Danube, this required the annexation of Moesia. The Romans' target was thus the tribes which inhabited Moesia, namely (from west to east) the [[Triballi]], Moesi and those Getae who dwelt south of the Danube. The Bastarnae were also a target because they had recently subjugated the Triballi, whose territory lay on the southern bank of the Danube between the tributary rivers ''Utus'' ([[Vit]]) and ''Ciabrus'' ([[Tsibritsa]]), with their chief town at [[Oescus]] (Gigen, Bulgaria).&lt;ref&gt;Ptolemy&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, Augustus wanted to avenge the defeat of [[Gaius Antonius Hybrida|Gaius Antonius]] at Histria 32 years before and to recover the lost military standards. These were held in a powerful fortress called [[Genucla]] (Isaccea, near modern Tulcea, Romania, in the Danube Delta region), controlled by [[Zyraxes]], the local Getan king.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dio LI.26.5&quot;&gt;Dio LI.26.5&lt;/ref&gt; The man selected for the task was [[Marcus Licinius Crassus (consul 30 BC)|Marcus Licinius Crassus]], grandson of [[Marcus Licinius Crassus|Crassus]] the [[triumvir]] and an experienced general at 33 years of age, who was appointed proconsul of Macedonia in 29 BC.&lt;ref&gt;Dio LI.23.2&lt;/ref&gt;

The Bastarnae provided the ''casus belli'' by crossing the Haemus and attacking the [[Dentheletae]], a Thracian tribe who were Roman allies. Crassus marched to the Dentheletae's assistance, but the Bastarnae host hastily withdrew over the Haemus at his approach. Crassus followed them closely into Moesia but they would not be drawn into battle, withdrawing beyond the Tsibritsa.&lt;ref&gt;Dio LI.23.5&lt;/ref&gt; Crassus now turned his attention to the Moesi, his prime target. After a successful campaign which resulted in the submission of a substantial section of the Moesi, Crassus again sought out the Bastarnae. Discovering their location from some peace envoys they had sent to him, he lured them into battle near the Tsibritsa by a stratagem. Hiding his main body of troops in a wood, he stationed as bait a smaller vanguard in open ground before the wood. As expected, the Bastarnae attacked the vanguard in force, only to find themselves entangled in the full-scale pitched battle with the Romans that they had tried to avoid. The Bastarnae tried to retreat into the forest but were hampered by the wagon train carrying their women and children, as these could not move through the trees. Trapped into fighting to save their families, the Bastarnae were routed. Crassus personally killed their king, Deldo, in combat, a feat which qualified him for Rome's highest military honour, ''[[spolia opima]]'', but Augustus refused to award it on a technicality.{{refn|group=Note|name=cnotef|Crassus' feat, as Roman commander, of killing the enemy leader in combat arguably entitled him to the highest honour a Roman soldier could gain: the ''[[spolia opima]]'' (literally: &quot;bountiful spoils&quot;, but this term may be a corruption of ''spolia optima'', &quot;supreme spoils&quot;), the right to hang the armour stripped from the enemy leader in the temple of [[Feretrius|Jupiter Feretrius]] in Rome, in emulation of the Founder of Rome [[Romulus]], a privilege granted only twice previously. But Crassus was denied the honour by Augustus on the technicality that he was not commander-in-chief of Roman forces at the time, a position claimed by Augustus himself.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dio LI.24.4&quot; /&gt; Augustus also forbade Crassus to accept the honorary title of ''imperator'' (&quot;supreme commander&quot;) from his troops, traditional for victorious generals. Instead, Augustus claimed the title for himself (for the 7th time).&lt;ref&gt;Dio LI.25.2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;CIL VI.873&lt;/ref&gt; Finally, although Dio states that Crassus was voted a [[Roman triumph|Triumph]] in Rome by the Senate, there is no evidence in inscriptions of that year (27 BC) that it was actually celebrated. After his return to Rome, Crassus disappears from the record altogether, both epigraphic and literary. This is highly unusual in a relatively well-documented period for a person of such distinction who was still only about 33 years old.{{original research inline|date=October 2011}} His tomb has not been found in the excavated Crassus family mausoleum in Rome. This official &quot;air-brushing from history&quot; may imply punitive [[Exile|internal exile]] to a remote location, similar to that inflicted on the contemporary poet, [[Ovid]], who in AD 8, for an unknown offence, was ordered by Augustus to spend the rest of his life in Tomis (Constanţa) on the Black Sea. [[Ronald Syme]] points out the similarity of Crassus' removal from the official record with that of [[Cornelius Gallus]], the contemporary disgraced governor of Egypt, who was recalled by Augustus for assuming inappropriate honours.&lt;ref&gt;Syme (1986) 271-2&lt;/ref&gt;}} Thousands of fleeing Bastarnae perished, many asphyxiated in nearby woods by encircling fires set by the Romans, others drowned trying to swim across the Danube. Nevertheless, a substantial force dug themselves into a powerful hillfort. Crassus laid siege to fort, but had to enlist the assistance of [[Rholes]], a Getan petty king, to dislodge them, for which service Rholes was granted the title of ''socius et amicus populi Romani'' (&quot;ally and friend of the Roman people&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;Dio LI.24&lt;/ref&gt;

The following year (28 BC), Crassus marched on Genucla. Zyraxes escaped with his treasure and fled over the Danube into Scythia to seek aid from the Bastarnae.&lt;ref&gt;Dio LI.26.6&lt;/ref&gt; Before he was able to bring reinforcements, Genucla fell to a combined land and fluvial assault by the Romans.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dio LI.26.5&quot;/&gt; The strategic result of Crassus' campaigns was the permanent annexation of Moesia by Rome.

About a decade later, in 10 BC,{{sfn|Almassy|2006|p=253}} the Bastarnae again clashed with Rome during Augustus' conquest of [[Pannonia]] (the ''bellum Pannonicum'' 14–9 BC). Inscription AE (1905) 14 records a campaign on the [[Hungarian Plain]] by the Augustan-era general [[Marcus Vinicius (consul 19 BC)|Marcus Vinucius]]: &lt;blockquote&gt;Marcus Vinucius...[patronymic], Consul [in 19 BC]...[various official titles], governor of Illyricum, the first [Roman general] to advance across the river Danube, defeated in battle and routed an army of Dacians and Basternae, and subjugated the [[Cotini]], Osi,...[missing tribal name] and [[Anartes|Anartii]] to the power of the emperor Augustus and of the people of Rome.&lt;/blockquote&gt; Most likely, the Bastarnae, in alliance with Dacians, were attempting to assist the hard-pressed Illyrian/Celtic tribes of Pannonia in their resistance to Rome.

==== 1st and 2nd centuries ====
[[File:AdamclisiMetope37.jpg|thumb|right|200px|War scene of the [[Tropaeum Traiani]] (c. 109 AD): a [[Roman legionary]] fighting with a [[Dacians|Dacian]] warrior, while a Germanic warrior (Bastarnae?), who has a [[suede knot]], is wounded on the ground.]]

It appears that in the final years of Augustus' rule, the Bastarnae made their peace with Rome. The ''[[Res Gestae Divi Augusti]]'' (&quot;Acts of the divine Augustus&quot;, 14 AD), an inscription commissioned by Augustus to list his achievements, states that he received an embassy from the Bastarnae seeking a treaty of friendship.&lt;ref&gt;Res Gestae Aug. 31&lt;/ref&gt; It appears that a treaty was concluded and apparently proved remarkably effective, as no hostilities with the Bastarnae are recorded in surviving ancient sources until c. 175, some 160 years after Augustus' inscription was carved. But surviving evidence for the history of this period is so thin that it cannot be excluded that the Bastarnae clashed with Rome during it.{{refn|group=Note|name=cnoteg|The [[Julio-Claudian]] period and the subsequent [[Year of the Four Emperors|Roman Civil War of 68–9]] (until AD 69) is reasonably well-covered by Tacitus' ''[[Annals (Tacitus)|Annales]]'' (although substantial parts are missing) and ''[[Histories (Herodotus)|Historiae]]''. But the loss of Tacitus' narrative for the entire [[Flavian dynasty|Flavian]] period (69–96) and of [[Ammianus Marcellinus]]'s continuation until 353, as well as of most of [[Dio Cassius]]'s History (up to 229), leaves a massive gap in our knowledge of the political history of the early empire, which is only scantily filled by inferior chronicles such as the ''[[Historia Augusta]]'', inscriptions and other evidence}} The Bastarnae [[Battle of Adamclisi|may have been involved]] in the [[Dacian Wars (disambiguation)|Dacian Wars]]&lt;!--intentional link to DAB page--&gt; of [[Domitian]] (86–88) and [[Trajan]] (101–102 and 105–106), since these took place in the lower Danube region and it is known that both sides were supported by neighbouring indigenous tribes.{{original research inline|date=October 2011}}

In the late 2nd century, the ''Historia Augusta'' mentions that in the rule of [[Marcus Aurelius]] (161–180), an alliance of lower Danube tribes including the Bastarnae, the Sarmatian Roxolani and the [[Costoboci]] took advantage of the emperor's difficulties on the upper Danube (the [[Marcomannic Wars]]) to invade Roman territory.&lt;ref&gt;Historia Augusta ''Marcus Aurelius'' II.22&lt;/ref&gt;

==== 3rd century ====
During the late 2nd century, the main ethnic change in the northern Black Sea region was the immigration, from the Vistula valley in the North, of the [[Goths]] and accompanying Germanic tribes such as the [[Taifali]] and the [[Hasdingi]], a branch of the [[Vandal]] people. This migration was part of a series of major population movements in the European ''barbaricum'' (the Roman term for regions outside their empire). The Goths appear to have established a loose political hegemony over the existing tribes in the region.

Under the leadership of the Goths, a series of major invasions of the Roman empire were launched by a grand coalition of lower Danubian tribes from c. 238 onwards. The participation of the Bastarnae in these is likely but largely unspecified, due to Zosimus' and other chroniclers' tendency to lump all these tribes under the general term &quot;Scythians&quot; – meaning all the inhabitants of Scythia, rather than the specific [[Iranic languages|Iranic]]-speaking people called the [[Scythians]].&lt;ref&gt;Wolfram (1988) 45&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, in 250–251, the Bastarnae were probably involved in the Gothic and Sarmatian invasions which culminated in the Roman defeat at the [[Battle of Abrittus]] and the slaying of Emperor [[Decius]] (251).&lt;ref&gt;Wolfram (1988) 45–46&lt;/ref&gt; This disaster was the start of the [[Third Century Crisis]] of the Roman Empire, a period of military and economic chaos. At this critical moment, the Roman army was crippled by the outbreak of a second [[smallpox]] pandemic, the [[plague of Cyprian]] (251–70). The effects are described by Zosimus as even worse than the earlier [[Antonine Plague|Antonine plague]] (166–180), which probably killed 15–30% of the empire's inhabitants.&lt;ref&gt;Zosimus I.16, 21&lt;/ref&gt;

Taking advantage of Roman military disarray, a vast number of barbarian peoples overran much of the empire. The Sarmato-Gothic alliance of the lower Danube carried out major invasions of the Balkans region in 252, and in the periods 253–258 and 260–268.&lt;ref&gt;Zosimus I.16, 20, 21&lt;/ref&gt; The Peucini Bastarnae are specifically mentioned in the 267/268 invasion, when the coalition built a fleet in the estuary of the river ''Tyras'' ([[Dniester]]). The Peucini Bastarnae would have been critical to this venture since, as coastal and delta dwellers, they would have had seafaring experience that the nomadic Sarmatians and Goths lacked. The barbarians sailed along the Black Sea coast to Tomis in Moesia Inferior, which they tried to take by assault without success. They then attacked the provincial capital [[Marcianopolis]] (Devnya, Bulgaria), also in vain. Sailing on through the [[Bosporus]], the expedition laid siege to [[Thessalonica]] in Macedonia. Driven off by Roman forces, the coalition host moved overland into Thracia, where finally it was crushed by Emperor [[Claudius II]] (r. 268–270) at [[Battle of Naissus|Naissus]] (269).&lt;ref&gt;Zosimus I.22-3&lt;/ref&gt;

Claudius II was the first of a sequence of military emperors (the so-called &quot;[[Illyrian emperors]]&quot; from their main ethnic origin) who restored order in the empire in the late 3rd century. These emperors followed a policy of large-scale resettlement within the empire of defeated barbarian tribes, granting them land in return for an obligation of military service much heavier than the usual conscription quota. The policy had the triple benefit, from the Roman point of view, of weakening the hostile tribe, repopulating the plague-ravaged frontier provinces (bringing their abandoned fields back into cultivation) and providing a pool of first-rate recruits for the army. It could also be popular with the barbarian prisoners, who were often delighted by the prospect of a land grant within the empire. In the 4th century, such communities were known as ''[[laeti]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Jones (1964) 620&lt;/ref&gt;

The emperor [[Marcus Aurelius Probus|Probus]] (r. 276–282) is recorded as resettling 100,000 Bastarnae in Moesia, in addition to other peoples, including Goths, Gepids and Vandals. The Bastarnae are reported to have honoured their oath of allegiance to the emperor, while the other resettled peoples mutinied while Probus was distracted by usurpation attempts and ravaged the Danubian provinces far and wide.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zosimus I.34&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Historia Augusta ''Probus'' 18&lt;/ref&gt; A further massive transfer of Bastarnae was carried out by Emperor [[Diocletian]] (ruled 284–305) after he and his colleague [[Galerius]] defeated a coalition of Bastarnae and [[Carpi (Dacian tribe)|Carpi]] in 299.&lt;ref&gt;Eutropius IX.25&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Later Roman empire (305 onwards) ===

The remaining transdanubian Bastarnae disappear into historical obscurity in the late empire. Neither of the main ancient sources for this period, [[Ammianus Marcellinus]] and [[Zosimus]], mention the Bastarnae in their accounts of the 4th century, possibly implying the loss of their separate identity, presumably assimilated by the regional hegemons, the Goths. Such assimilation would have been facilitated if, as is possible, the Bastarnae spoke an [[East Germanic]] language closely related to [[Gothic language|Gothic]]. If the Bastarnae remained an identifiable group, it is highly likely that they participated in the vast Gothic-led migration, driven by [[Hun]]nic pressure, that was admitted into Moesia by Emperor [[Valens]] in 376 and eventually defeated and killed Valens at [[Battle of Adrianople|Adrianople]] in 378. Although Ammianus refers to the migrants collectively as &quot;Goths&quot;, he states that, in addition, &quot;Taifali and other tribes&quot; were involved.&lt;ref&gt;Zosimus IV.104-7; 107&lt;/ref&gt;

However, after a gap of 150 years, there is a final mention of Bastarnae in the mid-5th century. In 451, the Hunnic leader [[Attila]] invaded Gaul with a large army which was ultimately routed at the [[Battle of Châlons]] by a Roman-led coalition under the general [[Flavius Aetius|Aetius]].&lt;ref&gt;Jordanes 38–40&lt;/ref&gt; Attila's host, according to [[Jordanes]], included contingents from the &quot;innumerable tribes that had been brought under his sway&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Jordanes 38&lt;/ref&gt; This included the Bastarnae, according to the Gallic nobleman [[Sidonius Apollinaris]].&lt;ref&gt;Sidonius ''Carmina'' 7.341&lt;/ref&gt; However, E.A. Thompson argues that Sidonius' mention of Bastarnae at Chalons is probably false: his purpose was to write a [[panegyric]] and not a history, and Sidonius added some spurious names to the list of real participants (e.g. [[Burgundians]], [[Scirii|Sciri]] and [[Franks]]) for dramatic effect.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson 1996 149&quot;&gt;Thompson (1996) 149&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Ancient Germanic culture}}
* [[Carpathian Tumuli culture]]
* [[Tiberius Plautius Silvanus Aelianus]]
* [[List of Germanic tribes]]
* [[List of Celtic tribes]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist |group=Note}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Bibliography ==

=== Ancient ===
* ''[[Res Gestae Divi Augusti]]'' (c. 14 AD)
* [[Ammianus Marcellinus]] ''Res Gestae'' (c. 395 AD)
* [[Dio Cassius]] ''Roman History'' (c. 230 AD)
* [[Eutropius (historian)|Eutropius]] ''Historiae Romanae Breviarium'' (c. 360 AD)
* Anonymous ''[[Historia Augusta]]'' (c. 400 AD)
* [[Livy]] ''[[Ab Urbe Condita Libri (Livy)|Ab urbe condita]]'' (c. 20 BC)
* [[Jordanes]] ''[[Getica]]'' (c. 550 AD)
* [[Pliny the Elder]] ''[[Naturalis Historia]]'' (c. 70 AD)
* [[Ptolemy]] ''[[Geographia]]'' (c. 140)
* [[Sextus Aurelius Victor]] ''De Caesaribus'' (c. 380 AD)
* [[Sidonius Apollinaris]] ''Carmina'' (late 5th century AD)
* [[Strabo]] ''[[Geographica]]'' (c. 10 AD)
* [[Tacitus]] ''[[Annals (Tacitus)|Annales]]'' (c. 100 AD)
* [[Tacitus]] ''[[Germania (book)|Germania]]'' (c. 100 AD)
* [[Zosimus]] ''Historia Nova'' (c. 500 AD)

=== Modern ===
* Babeş, Mircea: ''Noi date privind arheologia şi istoria bastarnilor'' in SCIV 20 (1969) 195–218
* Barrington (2000): ''Atlas of the Greek and Roman World''
* Batty, Roger (2008): ''Rome and the Nomads: the Pontic-Danubian region in Antiquity''
* Crişan, Ion (1978): ''Burebista and his Time''
* Faliyeyev, Alexander (2007): ''Dictionary of Continental Celtic Placenames'' (online)
* Goldsworthy, Adrian (2000): ''Roman Warfare''
*{{cite book |last=Hussey |first=Joan Mervyn |authorlink=Joan M. Hussey |ref=harv |title=Cambridge Medieval History |language= |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Zus8AAAAIAAJ |accessdate=5 May 2013 |year=1966 |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press|CUP Archive]] |location= |isbn=0-5200-8511-6 |page= |pages=}}
*{{cite book |last=Heather |first=Peter |authorlink=Peter Heather |ref=harv |title=The Visigoths from the Migration Period to the Seventh Century: An Ethnographic Perspective |language= |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=4MADmH2eaGIC |accessdate=12 April 2014 |year=1999 |publisher=[[Boydell &amp; Brewer]] |location= |isbn=1-8438-3033-7 |page= |pages=}}
* Heather, Peter (2009): ''Empires and Barbarians''
* Jones, A.H.M. (1964): ''Later Roman Empire''
* Köbler, Gerhard (2000): ''Indo-Germanisches Wörterbuch'' (online)
* Müllenhoff, Karl (1887): ''Deutsche altertumskunde'' (vol. II)
* Shchukin, Mark (1989): ''Rome and the Barbarians in central and eastern Europe: 1st century BC – 1st century AD''
* Thompson, E.A. (1996): ''The Huns''
* Todd, Malcolm (2004): ''The early Germans''
* O. N. Trubačev (1999): ''INDOARICA в Северном Причерноморье''
*{{cite book |last=Waldman |first=Carl |last2=Mason |first2=Catherine |authorlink1= |authorlink2= |ref=harv |title=Encyclopedia of European Peoples |language= |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kfv6HKXErqAC |accessdate=5 May 2013 |year=2006 |publisher=[[Infobase Publishing]] |location= |isbn=1-4381-2918-1 |page= |pages=}}
* Wolfram, Herwig (1988): ''History of the Goths''

{{commons category|Bastarnae}}
{{EB1911 poster|Bastarnae}}

[[Category:Bastarnae| ]]
[[Category:Historical Celtic peoples]]
[[Category:Early Germanic peoples]]
[[Category:Wars involving the Roman Republic]]
[[Category:Wars involving the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:Hellenistic-era tribes in the Balkans]]
[[Category:Ancient tribes in Dacia]]
[[Category:Hellenistic Thrace]]
[[Category:Antigonid Macedonia]]</text>
      <sha1>dx6i77s51jdunp9ig30t5exbzmk9g2l</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
