  <page>
    <title>Books of Chronicles</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4319</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943327308</id>
      <parentid>938118927</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T06:58:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BobKilcoyne</username>
        <id>7770027</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Links</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{other uses|Chronicles (disambiguation){{!}}Chronicles}}
{{redirect|Paralipomenon|other uses|Paralipomena (disambiguation){{!}}Paralipomena}}
{{Tanakh OT |Ketuvim |historical}}

The '''Book of Chronicles''' ({{lang-he-n|דִּבְרֵי־הַיָּמִים}} {{transl|he|Diḇrê Hayyāmîm}} 'The Matters [of] the Days') is a [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] [[prose]] work constituting part of [[Judaism|Jewish]] and Christian [[scripture]]. It contains a genealogy from a human being, [[Adam]], and a narrative of the [[history of ancient Judah and Israel]] until [[Cyrus's edict|the proclamation]] of King [[Cyrus the Great]] (c. 540 BC).

Chronicles is the final book of the [[Hebrew Bible]], concluding the third section of ''[[Ketuvim]]'', the last section of the Jewish Tanakh. It was divided into two books in the [[Septuagint]], the {{transl|grc|Paralipoménōn}} ({{lang-grc-gre|Παραλειπομένων||things left on one side}}).{{sfn|Japhet|1993|p=1}} In Christian contexts it is therefore known as the '''Books of Chronicles''', after the Latin name {{lang|la|chronikon}}, given to the text by scholar [[Jerome]] in the 5th century. In the [[Christian Bible]], the books (commonly referred to as '''1 Chronicles''' and '''2 Chronicles''', or '''First Chronicles''' and '''Second Chronicles''') generally follow the two [[Books of Kings]] and precede [[Ezra–Nehemiah]], thus concluding the history-oriented books of the [[Old Testament]].{{sfn|Japhet|1993|p=1-2}}

== Summary ==
[[File:Schnorr von Carolsfeld Bibel in Bildern 1860 113.png|thumb|left|''Rehoboam and Jeroboam I'', 1860 woodcut by [[Julius Schnorr von Karolsfeld]]]]
The Chronicles narrative begins with Adam, [[Seth]] and [[Enos (biblical figure)|Enosh]],&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|1|Chronicles|1:1|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the story is then carried forward, almost entirely through [[Genealogy|genealogical lists]], down to the founding of the first [[Kingdom of Israel (united monarchy)|Kingdom of Israel]] (in the &quot;introductory chapters&quot;, 1 Chronicles 1–9).&lt;ref&gt;Barnes, W. E. (1899), [https://biblehub.com/commentaries/cambridge/1_chronicles/ Cambridge Bible for Schools and Colleges] on 1 Chronicles, accessed 29 January 2020&lt;/ref&gt; The bulk of the remainder of 1 Chronicles, after a brief account of [[Saul]] in chapter 10, is concerned with the reign of [[David]] (1 Chronicles 11–29). The next long section concerns David's son [[Solomon]] (2 Chronicles 1–9), and the final part is concerned with the [[Kingdom of Judah]], with occasional references to the second [[Kingdom of Israel (Samaria)|kingdom of Israel]] (2 Chronicles 10–36). In the final chapter, Judah is destroyed and the people taken into [[Babylonian captivity|exile in Babylon]], and in the final verses the [[Achaemenid Empire|Persian]] king [[Cyrus the Great]] conquers the [[Neo-Babylonian Empire]], and authorises the restoration of the [[Temple in Jerusalem]], and the return of the exiles.{{sfn|Coggins|2003|p=282}}
{{clear|left}}

== Structure ==
Originally a single work, Chronicles was divided into two in the [[Septuagint]], a Greek translation produced in the 3rd and 2nd centuries BC.{{sfn|Japhet|1993|p=2}} It has three broad divisions: (1) the genealogies in chapters 1–9 of 1 Chronicles; (2) the reigns of David and Solomon, taking up the remainder of 1 Chronicles and chapters 1–9 of 2 Chronicles; and (3) the story of the [[Kingdom of Israel (united monarchy)#End|divided kingdom]], in the remainder of 2 Chronicles.

Within this broad structure there are signs that the author has used various other devices to structure his work, notably through drawing parallels between David and Solomon (the first becomes king, establishes the worship of Israel's God in Jerusalem, and fights the wars that will enable the Temple to be built, then Solomon becomes king, builds and dedicates the Temple, and reaps the benefits of prosperity and peace).{{sfn|McKenzie|2004|p=}}

== Composition ==
===Origins===
The last events in Chronicles take place in the reign of [[Cyrus the Great]], the Persian king who conquered Babylon in 539&amp;nbsp;BC; this sets the earliest possible date for the book. It was probably composed between 400–250 BC, with the period 350–300 BC the most likely.{{sfn|McKenzie|2004|p=}} The latest person mentioned in Chronicles is Anani, an eighth-generation descendant of King [[Jehoiachin]] according to the [[Masoretic Text]]. Anani's birth would likely have been sometime between 425 and 400 BC.{{citation needed|date=November 2018}} The [[Septuagint]] gives an additional five generations in the genealogy of Anani. For those scholars who side with the Septuagint's reading, Anani's likely date of birth was a century later.{{sfn|Kalimi|2005|pp=61-64}}

Chronicles appears to be largely the work of a single individual, with some later additions and editing. The writer was probably male, probably a [[Levite]] (temple priest), and probably from Jerusalem. He was well-read, a skilled editor, and a sophisticated theologian. His intention was to use Israel's past to convey religious messages to his peers, the literary and political elite of Jerusalem in the time of the [[Achaemenid Empire]].{{sfn|McKenzie|2004|p=}}

Jewish and Christian tradition identified this author as the 5th century BC figure [[Ezra]], who gives his name to the [[Book of Ezra]]; Ezra was also believed to be the author of both Chronicles and [[Ezra–Nehemiah]], but later critical scholarship abandoned the identification with Ezra and called the anonymous author &quot;[[the Chronicler]]&quot;. One of the most striking, although inconclusive, features of Chronicles is that its closing sentence is repeated as the opening of Ezra–Nehemiah.{{sfn|McKenzie|2004|p=}} The latter half of the 20th century saw a radical reappraisal, and many now regard it as improbable that the author of Chronicles was also the author of the narrative portions of Ezra–Nehemiah.{{sfn|Beentjes|2008|p=3}}

===Sources===
Much of the content of Chronicles is a repetition of material from other books of the Bible, from [[Book of Genesis|Genesis]] to [[Books of Kings|Kings]], and so the usual scholarly view is that these books, or an early version of them, provided the author with the bulk of his material. It is, however, possible that the situation was rather more complex, and that books such as Genesis and [[Book of Samuel|Samuel]] should be regarded as contemporary with Chronicles, drawing on much of the same material, rather than a source for it. There is also the question of whether the author of Chronicles used sources other than those found in the Bible: if such sources existed, it would bolster the Bible's case to be regarded as reliable history. Despite much discussion of this issue, no agreement has been reached.{{sfn|Coggins|2003|p=283}}

===Genre===
The translators who created the Greek version of the Jewish Bible (the [[Septuagint]]) called this book &quot;Things Left Out&quot;, indicating that they thought of it as a supplement to another work, probably Genesis-Kings, but the idea seems inappropriate, since much of Genesis-Kings has been copied almost without change. Some modern scholars proposed that Chronicles is a [[midrash]], or traditional Jewish commentary, on Genesis-Kings, but again this is not entirely accurate since the author or authors do not comment on the older books so much as use them to create a new work. Recent suggestions have been that it was intended as a clarification of the history in Genesis-Kings, or a replacement or alternative for it.{{sfn|Beentjes|2008|p=4-6}}

== Themes ==
[[Presbyterian Church (USA)|Presbyterian]] theologian Paul K. Hooker argues that the generally accepted message the author wished to give to his audience was a theological reflection, not a &quot;history of Israel&quot;:
#God is active in history, and especially the history of Israel. The faithfulness or sins of individual kings are immediately rewarded or punished by God. (This is in contrast to the theology of the [[Books of Kings]], where the faithlessness of kings was punished on later generations through the Babylonian exile).{{sfn|Hooker|2001|p=6}} 
#God calls Israel to a special relationship. The call begins with the genealogies (chapters 1–9 of 1 Chronicles), gradually narrowing the focus from all mankind to a single family, the Israelites, the descendants of [[Jacob]]. &quot;True&quot; Israel is those who continue to worship [[Yahweh]] at the Temple in Jerusalem, with the result that the history of the historical [[Kingdom of Israel (Samaria)|kingdom of Israel]] is almost completely ignored.{{sfn|Hooker|2001|p=7-8}} 
#God chose David and his dynasty as the agents of his will. According to the author of Chronicles, the three great events of David's reign were his bringing the [[Ark of the Covenant]] to Jerusalem, his founding of an eternal royal dynasty, and his preparations for the construction of the Temple.{{sfn|Hooker|2001|p=7-8}} 
#God chose a site in Jerusalem as the location for the Temple, the place where God should be worshiped. More time and space are spent on the construction of the Temple and its rituals of worship than on any other subject. By stressing the central role of the Temple in pre-exilic Judah, the author also stresses the importance of the newly-rebuilt Persian-era [[Second Temple]] to his own readers.
#God remains active in Israel. The past is used to legitimize the author's present: this is seen most clearly in the detailed attention he gives to the Temple built by Solomon, but also in the genealogy and lineages, which connect his own generation to the distant past and thus make the claim that the present is a continuation of that past.{{sfn|Hooker|2001|p=6-10}}

== See also ==
{{Portal|Bible}}
*[[History of ancient Israel and Judah]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

== Bibliography ==
: {{cite book
|last                         = Beentjes
|first                        = Pancratius C.
|editor1-last                 = 
|editor1-first                = 
|editor2-last                 = 
|editor2-first                = 
|chapter                      = 
|title                        = Tradition and Transformation in the Book of Chronicles
|year                         = 2008
|publisher                    = Brill
|url                          = https://books.google.com/?id=rLFXnQ6b9v4C&amp;pg=PR3
|ref                          = harv
|isbn                         = 9789004170445
}}
: {{cite book
|last                         = Coggins
|first                        = Richard J. 
|editor1-last                 = Dunn
|editor1-first                = James D. G.
|editor2-last                 = Rogerson
|editor2-first                = John William
|chapter                      = 1 and 2 Chronicles
|title                        = Eerdmans Commentary on the Bible
|year                         = 2003
|publisher                    = Eerdmans
|url                          = https://books.google.com/?id=2Vo-11umIZQC
|ref                          = harv
|isbn                         = 9780802837110
}}
: {{cite book
|last                         = Hooker
|first                        = Paul K.
|editor1-last                 = Adam G.
|editor1-first                = 
|editor2-last                 = 
|editor2-first                = 
|chapter                      = 
|title                        = First and Second Chronicles
|year                         = 2000
|publisher                    = Westminster John Knox Press
|url                          = https://books.google.com/books?id=QDwEOzTXvb8C&amp;pg=PA12
|ref                          = harv
|isbn                         = 9780664255916
}}
: {{cite book
|last                         = Japhet
|first                        = Sara
|author-link                  = Sara Japhet
|editor1-last                 = Adam G.
|editor1-first                = 
|editor2-last                 = 
|editor2-first                = 
|chapter                      = 
|title                        = I and II Chronicles: A Commentary
|year                         = 1993
|publisher                    = SCM Press
|url                          = https://books.google.com/?id=V0WjzZB2V7cC
|ref                          = harv
|isbn                         = 9780664226411
}}
:{{cite book|author=Isaac Kalimi|title=An Ancient Israelite Historian: Studies in the Chronicler, His Time, Place and Writing|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kmk5CDRsbwMC&amp;pg=PA62|date=January 2005|publisher=Uitgeverij Van Gorcum|isbn=978-90-232-4071-6|ref=harv}}
: {{cite book
|last                         = Kelly
|first                        = Brian E.
|editor1-last                 = 
|editor1-first                = 
|editor2-last                 = 
|editor2-first                = 
|chapter                      = 
|title                        = Retribution and Eschatology in Chronicles
|year                         = 1996
|publisher                    = Sheffield Academic Press
|url                          = https://books.google.com/?id=p7ui2JwhdzEC
|ref                          = harv
|isbn                         = 9780567637796
}}
: {{cite book
|last                         = Klein
|first                        = Ralph W.
|author-link                  = Ralph W. Klein
|editor1-last                 = 
|editor1-first                = 
|editor2-last                 = 
|editor2-first                = 
|chapter                      = 
|title                        = 1 Chronicles: A Commentary
|year                         = 2006
|publisher                    = Fortress Press
|url                          = 
|ref                          = harv
}}
: {{cite book
|last                         = Knoppers
|first                        = Gary N.
|author-link                  = Gary N. Knoppers
|editor1-last                 = 
|editor1-first                = 
|editor2-last                 = 
|editor2-first                = 
|chapter                      = 
|title                        = 1 Chronicles: A New Translation with Introduction and Commentary
|year                         = 2004
|publisher                    = Doubleday
|url                          = 
|ref                          = harv
}}
: {{cite book
|last                         = McKenzie
|first                        = Steven L.
|editor1-last                 = 
|editor1-first                = 
|editor2-last                 = 
|editor2-first                = 
|chapter                      = 
|title                        = 1–2 Chronicles
|year                         = 2004
|publisher                    = Abingdon
|url                          = https://books.google.com/?id=s3weTW7ylToC
|ref                          = harv
|isbn                         = 9781426759802
}}

== External links ==
{{Wikisource|1 Chronicles}}
{{Wikisource|2 Chronicles}}
{{Commons category|Books of Chronicles}}
Translations
* [http://www.chabad.org/library/archive/LibraryArchive2.asp?AID=15776 Divrei Hayamim I – Chronicles I (Judaica Press)] translation [with [[Rashi]]'s commentary] at Chabad.org
* [http://www.chabad.org/library/archive/LibraryArchive2.asp?AID=15777 Divrei Hayamim II – Chronicles II (Judaica Press)] translation [with [[Rashi]]'s commentary] at Chabad.org
* [http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1+Chronicles+1&amp;version=NIV 1 Chronicles at Biblegateway]
* [http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=2%20Chronicles%201&amp;version=NIV 2 Chronicles at Biblegateway]
* [http://bible-book.org/en/historical-books/1-chronicles 1 Chronicles at Bible-Book.org]
* [http://bible-book.org/en/historical-books/2-chronicles 2 Chronicles at Bible-Book.org]
Introductions
* [http://www.vts.edu/ftpimages/95/download/FM.Tuell.1-2-Chronicles.pdf 1 &amp; 2 Chronicles]

Audiobooks
* {{librivox book | dtitle=Bible: Chronicles| stitle=13 Chronicles}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou | [[Historical books|History books]]|||}}
{{s-bef | before = [[Book of Ezra|Ezra]]-[[Book of Nehemiah|Nehemiah]] }}
{{s-ttl | title  = [[Tanakh|Hebrew Bible]] }}
{{s-aft | after  = None }}
{{s-bef | before = [[Books of Kings|1–2 Kings]] | rows = 2 }}
{{s-ttl | title  = [[Western Christianity|Western]] [[Old Testament]] }}
{{s-aft | after  = [[Book of Ezra|Ezra]] }}
{{s-ttl | title  = [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Eastern]] [[Old Testament]]}}
{{s-aft | after  = [[1 Esdras]] }}
{{s-end}}

{{Books of the Bible}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Chronicles, Books Of}}
[[Category:4th-century BC books]]
[[Category:3rd-century BC books]]
[[Category:Ketuvim]]
[[Category:Books of Chronicles]]
[[Category:King lists]]

[[la:Libri Paralipomenon]]</text>
      <sha1>5n5fbyh5ogsw1iv9c8xsc7puks5au8b</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
