  <page>
    <title>Alfred Lawson</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1293</id>
    <revision>
      <id>932293346</id>
      <parentid>931682615</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-24T20:13:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>72.44.238.12</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Lawsonomy (1929–1954) */ Added citation to documentary film about the Racine, WI &quot;University of Lawsonomy&quot;.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{other people|Alfred Lawson}}

{{Infobox person
 | birth_name       = Alfred William Lawson
 | image            = Lawson Alfred W.jpg
 | birth_date       = {{birth date|1869|3|24}}
 | birth_place      = London, England
 | death_date       = {{death date and age|1954|11|29|1869|3|24}}
 | death_place      = [[San Antonio, Texas]]
 | resting_place    = 
 | other_names      = 
 | known_for        = Baseball, Aviation, Philosophy
 | occupation       = 
 | nationality      = Born in the United Kingdom, emigrated to Canada, then the United States by 1872
}}

'''Alfred William Lawson''' (March 24, 1869 – November 29, 1954) was a professional [[baseball#History|baseball]] player, manager, and league promoter from 1887 through 1916 and went on to play a pioneering role in the U.S. aircraft industry. He published two early aviation trade journals.

He is frequently cited as the inventor of the [[airliner]] and was awarded several of the first air mail contracts, which he ultimately could not fulfill. He founded the Lawson Aircraft Company in [[Green Bay, Wisconsin]], to build military training aircraft and later the [[Lawson Airplane Company-Continental Faience and Tile Company|Lawson Airplane Company]] in [[South Milwaukee, Wisconsin]], to build airliners.&lt;ref&gt;Wisconsin Aviation Hall of Fame. [http://www.wisconsinaviationhalloffame.org/inductees/lawson.htm Hall of Fame Inductee: Alfred W. Lawson].&lt;/ref&gt;

The crash of his ambitious [[Lawson L-4]] &quot;Midnight Liner&quot;  during its trial flight takeoff on May 8, 1921, ended his best chance for commercial aviation success.

In 1904 he wrote a novel, ''Born Again'',&lt;ref&gt;Alfred Lawson. [https://books.google.com/books?id=WvwWAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA1 ''Born Again'']. Wox &amp; Conrad: New York, 1904. ([https://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/19459 Online at Project Gutenberg])&lt;/ref&gt; in which he developed the philosophy which later became Lawsonomy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/fadsfallaciesint00gard|title=Fads and fallacies in the name of science|last=1914-2010.|first=Gardner, Martin|date=1957|publisher=Dover Publications|isbn=0486203948|location=New York|oclc=233892}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Baseball career (1888–1907)==
{{Infobox baseball biography
|name=Al Lawson
|image=
|bats=Right
|throws=Right
|debutleague = MLB
|debutdate=May 13
|debutyear=1890
|debutteam=[[Boston Beaneaters]]
|finalleague = MLB
|finaldate=June 2
|finalyear=1890
|finalteam=[[Pittsburgh Alleghenys]]
|statleague = MLB
|stat1label=[[Win–loss record (pitching)|Win–loss record]]
|stat2label=[[Earned run average]]
|stat3label=[[Strikeout]]s
|stat1value=0-3
|stat2value=6.63
|stat3value=3
|teams=
*[[Boston Beaneaters]] ({{Baseball year|1890}})
*[[Pittsburgh Alleghenys]] ({{Baseball year|1890}})
}}

He made one start for the [[Boston Beaneaters]] and two for the [[Pittsburgh Alleghenys]] during the [[1890 Major League Baseball season|1890 season]]. His minor league playing career lasted through 1895. He later managed in the minors from 1905 to 1907.

===Union Professional League===
In 1908 he started a new professional baseball league known as the [[Union Professional League]]. The league took the field in April but folded one month later owing to financial difficulties.&lt;ref name=DC&gt;{{cite news |last=Wagner |first=William |title=D.C. Had Baseball Times Two; One Spring, 2 Leagues Played With Senators |url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-1181828.html |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140611124332/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-1181828.html |url-status=dead |archive-date=June 11, 2014 |accessdate=January 19, 2013 |newspaper=[[The Washington Post]]|date=March 26, 1989|url-access=subscription |via=[[HighBeam Research]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aviation career (1908–1928)==
An early advocate or rather evangelist of aviation, in October 1908 Mr. Lawson started the magazine ''Fly'' to stimulate public interest and educate readers in the fundamentals of the new science of aviation. It sold for 10 cents a copy from newsstands across the country. In 1910, moving to New York City, he renamed the magazine &quot;Aircraft&quot; and published it until 1914. The magazine chronicled the technical developments of the early aviation pioneers. He was the first advocate for commercial air travel, coining the term &quot;airline.&quot; He also advocated for a strong American flying force, lobbying Congress in 1913 to expand its appropriations for Army aircraft.

In early 1913, he learned to fly the Sloan-Deperdussin and the [[Blériot XI|Moisant-Bleriot]] monoplanes, becoming an accomplished pilot. Later that year he bought a Thomas flying boat and became the first air commuter regularly flying from his country house in Seidler's Beach NJ to the foot of 75th Street in NYC (about 35 miles). In 1917, utilizing the knowledge gained from 10 years advocating aviation, he built his first airplane, the Lawson Military Tractor 1 (MT-1) trainer, and founded the Lawson Aircraft Corporation. The company's plant was sited at Green Bay, Wisconsin. There he secured a contract and built the Lawson MT-2. He also designed the steel fuselage Lawson Armored Battler, which never got beyond the drafting board, given doubts within the Army aviation community and the signing of the armistice.

[[File:Lawson T-2.jpg|left|thumb|Lawson C.2 or T-2]]
After the war, in 1919 Lawson started a project to build America's first airline. He secured financial backing, and in five months he had built and demonstrated in flight his biplane airliner, the 18-passenger [[Lawson L-2]]. He demonstrated its capabilities in a 2000-mile multi-city tour from Milwaukee to Chicago-Toledo-Cleveland-Buffalo-Syracuse-New york City-Washington, D.C.-Collinsville-Dayton-Chicago and back to Milwaukee, creating a buzz of positive press.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Alfred|first=Lawson|title=200 Mile Trip in First Airliner|year=1928|url=https://books.google.com/?id=Bb1BAAAAYAAJ&amp;lpg=PA146&amp;dq=%222000%20mile%20trip%20in%20first%22%20alfred%20lawson&amp;pg=PA146#v=onepage&amp;q=%222000%20mile%20trip%20in%20first%22%20alfred%20lawson&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The publicity allowed him to secure an additional $1 million to build the 26-passenger [[Lawson L-4|Midnight Liner]]. The aircraft crashed on takeoff on its maiden flight. In late 1920, he secured government contracts for three airmail routes and to deliver 10 war planes, but owing to the fall 1920 recession, he could not secure the necessary $100,000 in cash reserves called for in the contracts and had to decline them. In 1926 he started his last airliner, the 56-seat, two-tier Lawson super airliner.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Lawson – Aircraft Industry Builder|year=1930|publisher=Humanity publishing company}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In this phase of his life, he was considered one of the leading thinkers in the budding American commercial aviation community, but his troubles with getting financial backing for his ideas led him to turn to economics, philosophy, and organization.

==Lawsonomy (1929–1954)==
In the 1920s, he promoted health practices, including [[vegetarianism]], and claimed to have found the secret of living to 200. He also developed his own highly unusual theories of physics, according to which such concepts as &quot;penetrability&quot;, &quot;suction and pressure&quot; and &quot;zig-zag-and-swirl&quot; were discoveries on par with [[Albert Einstein|Einstein]]'s [[Theory of Relativity]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title = Fads and Fallacies in the Name of Science | author = Martin Gardner | pages = [https://archive.org/details/fadsfallaciesint00gard/page/69 69–79] | isbn = 978-0-486-20394-2 | publisher = Dover Publications | year = 1957 | title-link = Fads and Fallacies in the Name of Science }}&lt;/ref&gt; He published numerous books on these concepts, all set in a distinctive typography. Lawson repeatedly predicted the worldwide adoption of Lawsonian principles by the year 2000.{{fact|date=June 2019}}

He later propounded his own philosophy, Lawsonomy, and the [[Lawsonian religion]]. He also developed, during the [[Great Depression]], the [[Populism|populist]] economic theory of &quot;[[Direct Credit]]s&quot;, according to which banks are the cause of all economic woes, the oppressors of both capital and labour. Lawson believed that the government should replace banks as the provider of loans to business and workers. His rallies and lectures attracted thousands of listeners in the early 1930s, mainly in the upper Midwest, but by the late 1930s the crowds had dwindled.{{fact|date=June 2019}}

In 1943, he founded the [[University of Lawsonomy]] in [[Des Moines, Iowa|Des Moines]], on the site of [[Des Moines University (1865–1929)|Des Moines University]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newspapers.com/newspage/323247306/?terms=%22University+of+Lawsonomy%22|title=List Details Of Lawson School: University to Teach Principles O. K.'d by Founder|page=1|work=Des Moines Tribune|date=November 30, 1943|via=Newspapers.com|accessdate=19 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;, to spread his teachings and offer the degree of &quot;Knowledgian&quot;, but after various IRS and other investigations it was closed and finally sold in 1954, the year of Lawson's death. Lawson's financial arrangements remain mysterious to this day, and in later years he seems to have owned little property, moving from city to city as a guest of his farflung acolytes. In 1952, he was brought before a [[United States Senate]] investigative committee on allegations that his organization had bought war surplus machines and then sold them for a profit, despite claiming [[non-profit]] status. His attempt to explain Lawsonomy to the senators ended in mutual frustration and bafflement.&lt;ref&gt;''Fads and Fallacies in the Name of Science'', p. 77&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,816203,00.html | work=Time | title=Education: Zigzag &amp; Swirl | date=March 24, 1952}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A farm near [[Racine, Wisconsin]], is the only remaining university facility, although a tiny handful of churches may yet survive in places such as [[Wichita, Kansas]]. The large sign, formerly reading &quot;University of Lawsonomy&quot;, was a familiar landmark for motorists in the region for many years and was visible from [[Interstate 94]] about {{convert|13|mi|km}} north of the [[Illinois]] state line, on the east side of the highway. Although the sign still exists, the &quot;of&quot; has now been replaced by the [[Uniform Resource Locator|URL]] of the Lawsonomy website. A storm in the spring of 2009 destroyed the sign, although the supporting posts are still visible. On the northbound side of Interstate 94, a sign on the roof of the building nearest the freeway said &quot;Study Natural Law&quot; until being shingled over in October 2014.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.manlifethemovie.com/|title=Manlife|website=Manlife|language=en-US|access-date=2019-12-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal==
Lawson's brother, George H. Lawson, founded the [[United States Baseball League|United States League]] in 1910. The new professional baseball league had the intent to racially integrate. The league lasted less than a season, but it was revived for one season by George Lawson's associates in 1912.&lt;ref name=George&gt;{{cite news|last=Kuntz|first=Jerry|title=George H. Lawson: The Rogue Who Tried to Reform Baseball|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-193140688.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150713185205/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-193140688.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=July 13, 2015|accessdate=January 19, 2013|newspaper=The Baseball Research Journal|date=January 1, 2008|url-access=subscription |via=[[HighBeam Research]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[List of topics characterized as pseudoscience]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Henry, Lyell D. ''Zig-Zag-and Swirl: Alfred W. Lawson's Quest for Greatness''. Iowa City: University of Iowa Press, 1991.
* [[Kossy, Donna]]. ''Kooks: A Guide to the Outer Limits of Human Belief''. 2nd ed. Los Angeles: [[Feral House]], 2001. {{ISBN|978-0-922915-67-5}}
* Kuntz, Jerry. ''Baseball Fiends and Flying Machines: The Many Lives and Outrageous Times of George and Alfred Lawson''. Jefferson, North Carolina: McFarland Publishing, 2009.
* Lawson, Alfred. ''[http://www.lawsonomy.org/Lawsonomy11.html Lawsonomy, vols. 1-3]''. Detroit: Humanity Benefactor Foundation, 1935–1939.
* {{cite journal|author=The Royal Aero Club of the UK|title=The Lawson Aerial Transport|journal=Flight: The Aircraft Engineer &amp; Airship Weekly|date=September 11, 1919|volume=XI|series=37|issue=559|pages=1220–1222}}

==External links==
{{Baseballstats|br=l/lawsoal01|brm=lawson001al-}}
* {{gutenberg author|id=Alfred_W._Lawson_(1869–1954)}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Alfred William Lawson |birth=1869 |death=1954}}
* {{Librivox author |id=3269}}
* {{Kooks Museum|page=lawsonomy|name=Lawsonomy}}
* [http://www.wisconsinaviationhalloffame.org/blog/?tag=alfred-lawson Lawson Demo Flight Departed 93 Years Ago] at Wisconsin Aviation Hall of Fame
* [http://www.onmilwaukee.com/sports/articles/lawson.html What in the heck is the University of Lawsonomy?] – article about Lawson in a Milwaukee-area magazine
* [https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1499&amp;dat=19810205&amp;id=MmcaAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=xSsEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4434,3295769 End of flight] – newspaper article about 1921 loss of first Lawson Airliner 
* &quot;ASME Milwaukee – History &amp; Heritage&quot;{{cite web|title=LAWSON &quot;AIR LINER&quot; |url=http://sections.asme.org/milwaukee/history/42-lawsonairliner.html |publisher=ASME Milwaukee Chapter |accessdate=30 December 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090122194759/http://sections.asme.org/milwaukee/history/42-lawsonairliner.html |archivedate=January 22, 2009 }}
* {{cite web|last=Who's Who in American Aeronautics|title=Alfred W. Lawson|url=http://www.earlyaviators.com/elawson.htm|accessdate=24 December 2012}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Lawson, Alfred}}
[[Category:1869 births]]
[[Category:1954 deaths]]
[[Category:Pseudophysics|Lawsonomy]]
[[Category:Boston Beaneaters players]]
[[Category:Pittsburgh Alleghenys players]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball pitchers]]
[[Category:19th-century baseball players]]
[[Category:Bloomington Blues players]]
[[Category:Wilmington Blue Hens players]]
[[Category:Harrisburg Ponies players]]
[[Category:Oakland Colonels players]]
[[Category:Pendleton Ho Hos players]]
[[Category:Spokane Bunchgrassers players]]
[[Category:Atlanta Firecrackers players]]
[[Category:Troy Trojans (minor league) players]]
[[Category:Sandusky Sandies players]]
[[Category:Albany Senators players]]
[[Category:Pawtucket Maroons players]]
[[Category:Norfolk Clams players]]
[[Category:Norfolk Crows players]]
[[Category:Sportspeople from London]]
[[Category:Minor league baseball managers]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball players from England]]</text>
      <sha1>i1gzjfgtqu2rwj6nsicwmfzg74teuez</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
