  <page>
    <title>Geography of Alabama</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1285</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940313623</id>
      <parentid>932446903</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-11T20:08:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Gonzo fan2007</username>
        <id>1347436</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Per [[MOS:BOLDAVOID]]: Links should not be placed in the boldface reiteration of the title in the opening sentence of a lead</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{More citations needed|date=April 2007}}
[[Image:Physio-al.jpg|right|frame|Physiographic regions in Alabama]]
[[Image:AlaCounties.png|right|thumb|260px|Political Regions of Alabama]]

The '''geography of Alabama''' describes a [[U.S. state|state]] in the [[Southeastern United States]] in [[North America]]. [[Alabama]] is 30th in size and borders four [[U.S. state]]s: Mississippi, Tennessee, Georgia, and Florida. It also borders the Gulf of Mexico.

==Physical features==
{{See also|Geology of Alabama}}
Extending entirely across the state of Alabama for about {{convert|20|mi|km|0}} northern boundary, and in the middle stretching {{convert|60|mi|km|0}} farther north, is the [[Cumberland Plateau]], or [[Tennessee Valley]] region, broken into broad tablelands by the dissection of rivers. In the northern part of this plateau, west of [[Jackson County, Alabama|Jackson county]], there are about {{convert|1000|sqmi|km2}} of level highlands from {{convert|700|to|800|ft|m|-1}} above sea level. South of these highlands, occupying a narrow strip on each side of the [[Tennessee River]], is a country of gentle rolling lowlands varying in elevation from {{convert|500|to|800|ft|m|-1}}. To the northeast of these highlands and lowlands is a rugged section with steep mountain-sides, deep narrow coves and valleys, and flat mountain-tops. Its elevations range from {{convert|400|to|1800|ft|m|-1}}. In the remainder of this region, the southern portion, the most prominent feature is ''Little Mountain'', extending about {{convert|80|mi|km|0}} from east to west between two valleys, and rising precipitously on the north side {{convert|500|ft|m|-1}} above them or {{convert|1000|ft|m}} above the sea.

Adjoining the Cumberland Plateau region on the southeast is the [[Ridge-and-Valley Appalachians|Appalachian Valley]] (locally known as Coosa Valley) region, which is the southern extremity of the [[Appalachian Mountains]], and occupies an area within the state of about {{convert|8000|sqmi|km2|-3}}. This is a [[limestone]] belt with parallel hard rock ridges left standing by erosion to form mountains. Although the general direction of the mountains, ridges, and valleys is northeast and southwest, irregularity is one of the most prominent characteristics. In the northeast are several flat-topped mountains, of which Raccoon and [[Lookout Mountain|Lookout]] are the most prominent, having a maximum elevation near the [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]] line of little more than {{convert|1800|ft|m|-1}} and gradually decreasing in height toward the southwest, where [[Sand Mountain (Alabama)|Sand Mountain]] is a continuation of Raccoon. South of these the mountains are marked by steep northwest sides, sharp crests and gently sloping southeast sides.

Southeast of the Appalachian Valley region, the [[Piedmont (United States)|Piedmont Plateau]] also crosses the Alabama border from the N.E. and occupies a small triangular-shaped section of which [[Randolph County, Alabama|Randolph]] and [[Clay County, Alabama|Clay]] counties, together with the northern part of [[Tallapoosa County, Alabama|Tallapoosa]] and [[Chambers County, Alabama|Chambers]], form the principal portion. Its surface is gently undulating and has an elevation of about {{convert|1000|ft|m|-2}} above sea level. The Piedmont Plateau is a lowland worn down by erosion on hard crystalline rocks, then uplifted to form a plateau.

The remainder of the state is occupied by the ''Coastal Plain''. This is crossed by foothills and rolling prairies in the central part of the state, where it has a mean elevation of about {{convert|600|ft|m|-1}}, becomes lower and more level toward the southwest, and in the extreme south is flat and but slightly elevated above the sea.
The Cumberland Plateau region is drained to the west-northwest by the [[Tennessee River]] and its tributaries; all other parts of the state are drained to the southwest. In the Appalachian Valley region the [[Coosa River]] is the principal river; and in the Piedmont Plateau, the [[Tallapoosa River]]. In the Coastal Plain are the [[Tombigbee River]] in the west, the [[Alabama River]] (formed by the Coosa and Tallapoosa) in the western central, and in the east the [[Chattahoochee River]], which forms almost half of the Georgia boundary. The Tombigbee and Alabama rivers unite near the southwest corner of the state, their waters discharging into [[Mobile Bay]] by the [[Mobile River|Mobile]] and Tensas rivers. The [[Black Warrior River]] is a considerable stream which joins the Tombigbee from the east.

The valleys in the north and northeast are usually deep and narrow, but in the Coastal Plain they are broad and in most cases rise in three successive terraces above the stream. The harbour of Mobile was formed by the drowning of the lower part of the valley of the Alabama and Tombigbee rivers as a result of the sinking of the land here, such sinking having occurred on other parts of the Gulf coast.

==Flora and fauna==

The fauna and flora of Alabama are similar to those of the Gulf states in general and have no distinctive characteristics. However, the [[Mobile River]] system has a high incidence of endemism among freshwater mollusks and biodiversity is high.

In Alabama, vast forests of [[pine]] constitute the largest proportion of the state's forest growth. There is also an abundance of [[Taxodium|cypress]], [[hickory]], [[oak]], [[populus]], and [[juniperus virginiana|eastern redcedar]] trees. In other areas, [[conium|hemlock]] growths in the north and [[chamaecyparis thyoides|southern white cedar]] in the southwest. Other native trees include [[ash tree|ash]], [[celtis|hackberry]], and [[holly]]. In the Gulf region of the state grow various species of [[Arecaceae|palmetto]] and [[arecaceae|palm]]. In Alabama there are more than 150 [[shrub]]s, including [[kalmia latifolia|mountain laurel]] and [[rhododendron]]. Among cultivated plants are [[wisteria]] and [[camellia]].

While in the past the state enjoyed a variety of mammals such as [[plains bison]], [[eastern elk]], [[North American cougar]], [[bear]], and [[deer]], only the [[white-tailed deer]] remains abundant. Still fairly common are the  [[bobcat]], [[American beaver]], [[muskrat]], [[raccoon]], [[Virginia opossum]], [[rabbit]], [[squirrel]], [[red fox|red]] and [[gray fox]]es, and [[long-tailed weasel]]. [[Coypu]] and [[nine-banded armadillo]] have been introduced to the state and now also common.

Alabama's birds include [[golden eagle|golden]] and [[bald eagle]]s, [[osprey]] and other [[hawk]]s, [[northern flicker|yellow-shafted flickers]], and [[black-and-white warbler]]s. Game birds include [[bobwhite quail]], [[duck]], [[wild turkey]], and [[goose]]. Freshwater fish such as [[bream]], [[shad]], [[bass (fish)|bass]], and [[Catostomidae|sucker]] are common. Along the Gulf Coast there are seasonal runs of [[tarpon]], [[pompano]], [[red drum]], and [[bonito]].&lt;ref name = &quot;gale&quot;&gt;{{Citation
 | editor-last = Gall
 | editor-first = Timothy L.
 | title = Worldmark Encyclopedia of the States
 | page = 2
 | isbn = 0-7876-7338-2
 | publisher = Thomson Gale
 | edition = 6
 | year = 2004
 | author = 
 | oclc = 53464095
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United States Fish and Wildlife Service|U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service]] lists as [[endangered species|endangered]] 99 animals, fish, and birds, and 18 plant species.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
 | last = U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service
 | title = Threatened &amp; Endangered Species System: Alabama
 | accessdate = 2008-07-27
 | url = http://ecos.fws.gov/tess_public//pub/stateListing.jsp?state=AL&amp;status=listed
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The endangered animals include the [[Alabama beach mouse]], [[gray bat]], [[Alabama red-bellied turtle]], [[fin whale|fin]] and [[humpback whale]]s, [[bald eagle]], and [[wood stork]].

[[American black bear]], [[racking horse]], yellow-shafted flicker, wild turkey, [[Atlantic tarpon]], [[largemouth bass]], southern [[longleaf pine]], [[eastern tiger swallowtail]], [[monarch butterfly]], Alabama red-bellied turtle, [[Red Hills salamander]], camellia, [[Hydrangea quercifolia|oak-leaf hydrangea]], [[peach]], [[pecan]], and [[blackberry]] are Alabama's [[List of Alabama state symbols|state symbol]]s.

==Climate and soil==
{{Main|Climate of Alabama}}
The [[climate]] of Alabama is [[humid subtropical climate|humid subtropical]].&lt;ref name=report&gt;[http://nsstc.uah.edu/alclimatereport/ The Alabama Climate Report] Volume1, Number 1 October 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

The heat of summer is tempered in the south by the winds from the [[Gulf of Mexico]], and in the north by the elevation above the sea. The average annual temperature is highest in the southwest along the coast, and lowest in the northeast among the highlands. Thus at Mobile the annual mean is {{convert|67|°F|°C|abbr=on}}, the mean for the summer {{convert|81|°F|°C|abbr=on}}, and for the winter {{convert|52|°F|°C|abbr=on}}; and at Valley Head, in De Kalb county, the annual mean is {{convert|59|°F|°C|abbr=on}}, the mean for the summer {{convert|75|°F|°C|abbr=on}}, and for the winter {{convert|41|°F|°C|abbr=on}}. At Montgomery, in the central region, the average annual temperature is {{convert|66|°F|°C|abbr=on}}, with a winter average of {{convert|49|°F|°C|abbr=on}}, and a summer average of {{convert|81|°F|°C|abbr=on}}. The average winter minimum for the entire state is {{convert|35|°F|°C|abbr=on}}, and there is an average of 35 days in each year in which the thermometer falls below the freezing-point. At extremely rare intervals the thermometer has fallen below zero (-18&amp;nbsp;°C), as was the case in the remarkable cold wave of the 12th-13 February 1899, when an absolute minimum of {{convert|-17|°F|°C|abbr=on}} was registered at [[Valley Head, Alabama|Valley Head]]. The highest temperature ever recorded was {{convert|109|°F|°C|abbr=on}} in [[Talladega County, Alabama|Talladega]] county in 1902.

The amount of precipitation is greatest along the coast (62&amp;nbsp;inches/1,574&amp;nbsp;mm) and evenly distributed through the rest of the state (about 52&amp;nbsp;inches/1,320&amp;nbsp;mm). During each winter there is usually one fall of snow in the south and two in the north; but the snow quickly disappears, and sometimes, during an entire winter, the ground is not covered with snow. Heavy snowfall can occur, such as during the [[New Year's Eve 1963 snowstorm]] and the [[1993 Storm of the Century]]. [[Hail]]storms occur occasionally in the spring and summer, but are seldom destructive. Heavy [[fog]]s are rare, and are confined chiefly to the coast. [[Thunderstorm]]s occur throughout the year - they are most common in the summer, but most severe in the spring and fall, when destructive winds and [[tornado]]es occasionally occur. The prevailing winds are from the news. [[Tropical cyclone|Hurricanes]] are quite common in the state, especially in the southern part, and major hurricanes occasionally strike the coast which can be very destructive.

As regards its soil, Alabama may be divided into four regions. Extending from the Gulf northward for about {{convert|150|mi|km}} is the outer belt of the Coastal Plain, also called the ''Timber Belt,'' whose soil is sandy and poor, but responds well to fertilization. North of this is the inner lowland of the Coastal Plain, or the ''Black Prairie,'' which includes some {{convert|13000|sqmi|km2|-3}} and seventeen counties. It receives its name from its soil (weathered from the weak underlying limestone), which is black in colour, almost destitute of sand and loam, and rich in limestone and marl formations, especially adapted to the production of cotton; hence the region is also called the ''Cotton Belt.'' Between the ''Cotton Belt'' and the [[Tennessee Valley]] is the [[mineral]] region, the ''Old Land'' area—a region of resistant rocks—whose soils, also derived from weathering in silu, are of varied fertility, the best coming from the granites, sandstones and limestones, the poorest from the gneisses, schists and slates. North of the mineral region is the ''Cereal Belt,'' embracing the Tennessee Valley and the counties beyond, whose richest soils are the red clays and dark loams of the river valley; north of which are less fertile soils, produced by siliceous and sandstone formations.

==Wetumpka Meteor Crater==
{{main|Wetumpka crater}}

Wetumpka is the home of &quot;Alabama's greatest natural disaster.&quot;&lt;ref name = &quot;nfqpzf&quot;&gt;[http://www.wetumpkalibrary.com/Default.asp?ID=207 &quot;Wetumpka Impact Crater&quot;] Wetumpka Public Library, accessed Aug. 21, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;  A {{convert|1000|ft|m|-2|adj=on}}-wide&lt;ref name = &quot;nfqpzf&quot;/&gt; meteorite hit the area about 80 million years ago. The hills just east of downtown showcase the eroded remains of the {{convert|5|mi|km|adj=on|spell=in}} wide impact crater that was blasted into the bedrock, with the area labeled the [[Wetumpka crater]] or astrobleme (&quot;star-wound&quot;) for the concentric rings of fractures and zones of shattered rock can be found beneath the surface.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Wetumpka Astrobleme&quot; by John C. Hall, Alabama Heritage, Fall 1996, Number 42.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2002, Christian Koeberl with the Institute of Geochemistry University of Vienna published evidence and established the site as an internationally recognized impact crater.&lt;ref name = &quot;nfqpzf&quot;/&gt;

==Public lands==
Alabama includes several types of public use lands. These include four national forests and one national preserve within state borders that provide over 25% of the state's public recreation land.

* land regions
* [[List of Alabama state parks|Alabama State Parks]]
* [[List of lakes in Alabama|Alabama Public Fishing Lakes]]
* [[Alabama Wildlife Management Areas]]
* [[United States National Monument|National Monuments]]
** [[Little River Canyon National Preserve]]
** [[Russell Cave National Monument]]
* [[United States National Forest|National Forest]]s
** [[Conecuh National Forest]]
** [[Talladega National Forest]]
** [[Tuskegee National Forest]]
** [[William B. Bankhead National Forest]]
* [[U.S. Wilderness Area|Wilderness Areas]]
** [[Cheaha Wilderness]]
** [[Dugger Mountain Wilderness]]
** [[Sipsey Wilderness]]
* [[National Scenic Trail]]
** [[Natchez Trace Trail]]
**[[National Wildlife Funding]]
* [[National Recreation Trail]]
** [[Pinhoti National Recreation Trail]]
* [[National Wildlife Refuge]]
** [[Bon Secour National Wildlife Refuge]]
** [[Cahaba River National Wildlife Refuge]]
** [[Choctaw National Wildlife Refuge]]
** [[Eufaula National Wildlife Refuge]]
** [[Fern Cave National Wildlife Refuge]]
** [[Key Cave National Wildlife Refuge]]
** [[Mountain Longleaf National Wildlife Refuge]]
** [[Sauta Cave National Wildlife Refuge]]
** [[Watercress Darter National Wildlife Refuge]]
** [[Wheeler National Wildlife Refuge]]

==See also==
* [[Alabama]]
* [[Geography of the United States]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.gsa.state.al.us/ State of Alabama Geological Survey]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20010228175717/http://tapestry.usgs.gov/states/alabama.html USGS - Tapestry of Time - Alabama]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110609062317/http://www.al.com/parks/north.html Summary of Alabama Park &amp; Recreation Sites]
* [http://www.stateparks.com/al.html Interactive Map of Park &amp; Recreation Sites]
* [http://encyclopediaofalabama.org/face/Article.jsp?id=h-1830 Encyclopedia of Alabama: Cultural Geography]
* [http://encyclopediaofalabama.org/face/Article.jsp?id=h-2458 Encyclopedia of Alabama: Black Belt Region in Alabama]
{{Alabama}}
{{U.S. political divisions geographies}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Geography Of Alabama}}
[[Category:Geography of Alabama| ]]</text>
      <sha1>hzp37h0r8xhbzacp2b0s91l2bfyiimx</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
