  <page>
    <title>Atomic physics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1200</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942015621</id>
      <parentid>942009239</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-22T01:51:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>KH-1</username>
        <id>21857263</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/2600:387:0:803:0:0:0:2C|2600:387:0:803:0:0:0:2C]] ([[User talk:2600:387:0:803:0:0:0:2C|talk]]) to last version by MaxEnt</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{No footnotes|date=September 2015}}
{{For|the classical view of the atom which developed into atomic physics|atomic theory}}
{{Modern physics}}
'''Atomic physics''' is the field of [[physics]] that studies [[atom]]s as an isolated system of [[electron]]s and an [[atomic nucleus]]. It is primarily concerned with the [[Electron configuration|arrangement of electrons around the nucleus]] and
the processes by which these arrangements change. This comprises [[ion]]s, neutral atoms and, unless otherwise stated, it can be assumed that the term ''atom'' includes ions.

The term ''atomic physics'' can be associated with [[nuclear power]] and [[nuclear weapon]]s, due to the [[synonym]]ous use of ''atomic'' and ''nuclear'' in [[standard English]]. Physicists distinguish between atomic physics—which deals with the atom as a system consisting of a nucleus and electrons—and [[nuclear physics]], which studies [[nuclear reaction]]s and special properties of [[atomic nucleus|atomic nuclei]].

As with many scientific fields, strict delineation can be highly contrived and atomic physics is often considered in the wider context of ''[[atomic, molecular, and optical physics]]''. Physics research groups are usually so classified.

==Isolated atoms==
Atomic physics primarily considers atoms in isolation. Atomic models will consist of a single nucleus that may be surrounded by one or more bound electrons. It is not concerned with the formation of [[molecule]]s (although much of the physics is identical), nor does it examine atoms in a [[solid state physics|solid state]] as [[condensed matter]]. It is concerned with processes such as [[ionization]] and [[excited state|excitation]] by photons or collisions with atomic particles.

While modelling atoms in isolation may not seem realistic, if one considers atoms in a [[gas]] or [[Plasma (physics)|plasma]] then the time-scales for atom-atom interactions are huge in comparison to the atomic processes that are generally considered. This means that the individual atoms can be treated as if each were in isolation, as the vast majority of the time they are.  By this consideration atomic physics provides the underlying theory in [[plasma (physics)|plasma physics]] and [[atmospheric physics]], even though both deal with very large numbers of atoms.

==Electronic configuration==
Electrons form notional [[Electron shells|shells]] around the nucleus. These are normally in a [[ground state]] but can be excited by the absorption of energy from light ([[photon]]s), magnetic fields, or interaction with a colliding particle (typically ions or other electrons).

[[File:Bohr atom model.svg|thumb|In the Bohr model, the transition of an electron with n=3 to the shell n=2 is shown, where a photon is emitted. An electron from shell (n=2) must have been removed beforehand by ionization]] Electrons that populate a shell are said to be in a [[bound state]].  The energy necessary to remove an electron from its shell (taking it to infinity) is called the [[binding energy]].  Any quantity of energy absorbed by the electron in excess of this amount is converted to [[kinetic energy]] according to the [[conservation of energy]].  The atom is said to have undergone the process of [[ionization]].

If the electron absorbs a quantity of energy less than the binding energy, it will be transferred to an [[excited state]]. After a certain time, the electron in an excited state will &quot;jump&quot; (undergo a transition) to a lower state. In a neutral atom, the system will emit a photon of the difference in energy, since energy is conserved.

If an inner electron has absorbed more than the binding energy (so that the atom ionizes), then a more outer electron may undergo a transition to fill the inner orbital. In this case, a visible photon or a [[characteristic x-ray]] is emitted, or a phenomenon known as the [[Auger effect]] may take place, where the released energy is transferred to another bound electron, causing it to go into the continuum.  The Auger effect allows one to multiply ionize an atom with a single photon.

There are rather strict [[selection rule]]s as to the electronic configurations that can be reached by excitation by light — however there are no such rules for excitation by collision processes.

==History and developments==
{{Main|Atomic theory}}
One of the earliest steps towards atomic physics was the recognition that matter was composed
of ''atoms''. It forms a part of the texts written in 6th century BC to 2nd century BC such as those of [[Democritus]] or [[Vaisheshika Sutra]] written by [[Kanad]]. This theory was later developed in the modern sense of the basic unit of a [[chemical element]] by the British chemist and physicist [[John Dalton]] in the 18th century. At this stage, it wasn't clear what atoms were although they could be described and classified by their properties (in bulk). The invention of the [[periodic system of elements]] by [[Dmitri Mendeleev|Mendeleev]] was another great step forward.

The true beginning of atomic physics is marked by the discovery of [[spectral line]]s and attempts to describe the phenomenon, most notably by [[Joseph von Fraunhofer]]. The study of these lines led to the [[Bohr atom model]] and to the birth of [[quantum mechanics]]. In seeking to explain atomic spectra an entirely new mathematical model of matter was revealed. As far as atoms and their electron shells were concerned, not only did this yield a better overall description, i.e. the [[atomic orbital model]], but it also provided a new theoretical basis for [[chemistry]]
([[quantum chemistry]]) and [[spectroscopy]].

Since the [[World War II|Second World War]], both theoretical and experimental fields have advanced at a rapid pace. This can be attributed to progress in computing technology, which has allowed larger and more sophisticated models of atomic structure and associated collision processes.  Similar technological advances in accelerators, detectors, magnetic field generation and [[laser]]s have greatly assisted experimental work.
&lt;!-- Perhaps create to a category list instead and embed names in history/theory section later --&gt;

==Significant atomic physicists==
{{Columns-list|colwidth=30em|
; Pre quantum mechanics
* [[John Dalton]]
* [[Joseph von Fraunhofer]]
* [[Johannes Rydberg]]
* [[J. J. Thomson]]
* [[Ernest Rutherford]] 
; Post quantum mechanics
* [[Alexander Dalgarno]]
* [[David Bates (physicist)|David Bates]]
* [[Niels Bohr]]
* [[Max Born]]
* [[Clinton Joseph Davisson]]
* [[Enrico Fermi]]
* [[Charlotte Froese Fischer]]
* [[Vladimir Fock]]
* [[Douglas Hartree]]
* [[Ernest M. Henley]]
* [[Ratko Janev]]
* [[Harrie Massey|Harrie S. Massey]]
* [[Nevill Mott]]
* [[Isador Isaac Rabi|I. I. Rabi]]
* [[Norman Foster Ramsey Jr.|Norman Ramsey]]
* [[M. J. Seaton|Mike Seaton]]
* [[John C. Slater]]
* [[George Paget Thomson]]
}}

==See also==
*[[Particle physics]]
*[[Isomeric shift]]
*[[Atomic engineering]]

== Bibliography ==
* {{Cite book|title=Physics of Atoms and Molecules|author=Bransden, BH|author2=Joachain, CJ|
    year=2002|publisher=Prentice Hall|edition=2nd|isbn=978-0-582-35692-4}}
* {{Cite book|title=Atomic Physics|author=Foot, CJ|year=2004|
    publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-850696-6}}
*{{Cite book|last=Herzberg |first=Gerhard |title=Atomic Spectra and Atomic Structure
    |year= 1979|origyear=1945 |publisher=Dover |location=New York |isbn=978-0-486-60115-1}}
* {{Cite book|title=The Theory of Atomic Spectra|author1=Condon, E.U.  |author2=Shortley, G.H. |lastauthoramp=yes |year=1935|
    publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-09209-8}}
* {{Cite book|title=The Theory of Atomic Structure and Spectra|author=Cowan, Robert D.|year=1981|
    publisher=University of California Press|isbn=978-0-520-03821-9}}
* {{Cite book|title=Atomic Many-Body Theory|author1=Lindgren, I.  |author2=Morrison, J. |lastauthoramp=yes |year=1986|
    edition=Second|publisher=Springer-Verlag|isbn=978-0-387-16649-0}}

==External links==
{{Commonscat}}
*[http://cuaweb.mit.edu/ MIT-Harvard Center for Ultracold Atoms]
*[http://jqi.umd.edu Joint Quantum Institute at University of Maryland and NIST]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20031204233636/http://plasma-gate.weizmann.ac.il/API.html Atomic Physics on the Internet]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20120305214247/http://jila.colorado.edu/research_highlights JILA (Atomic Physics)]
*[http://www.phy.ornl.gov ORNL Physics Division]

{{Physics-footer}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Atomic Physics}}
[[Category:Atomic physics| ]]
[[Category:Atomic, molecular, and optical physics]]</text>
      <sha1>l6psl5q9s9fvggw22jismajnb7kvsyg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
