  <page>
    <title>Abatis</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2606</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941179144</id>
      <parentid>923550581</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-17T01:56:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Taterian</username>
        <id>26656499</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>image</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=October 2013}}
[[File:Abatis (PSF).png|thumb|right|Abatisses are used in war to keep the approaching enemy under fire for as long as possible.]]
[[File:Abatis in front of the Union trench lines at Petersburg in 1865.jpg|thumb|Abatis in front of the Union trench lines at Petersburg in 1865]]
An '''abatis''', '''abattis''', or '''abbattis''' is a field [[fortification]] consisting of an obstacle formed (in the modern era) of the branches of trees laid in a row, with the sharpened tops directed outwards, towards the enemy. The trees are usually interlaced or tied with [[wire]]. Abatis are used alone or in combination with [[wire entanglement]]s and other obstacles.{{sfn|Chisholm|1911}}

== History ==
[[File:Abatis.jpg|thumb|Abatis improvised by Japanese troops during [[World War II]]]]

There is evidence it was used as early as the [[Roman Empire|Roman Imperial]] period, and as recently as the [[American Civil War]]&lt;ref&gt;Personal Memoirs of U. S. Grant, Complete, Ch. XXII&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Anglo-Zulu War]] of 1879.

A classic use of an abatis was at the [[Battle of Carillon]] (1758) during the Seven Years' War. The 3,600 French troops defeated a massive army of 16,000 British and Colonial troops by fronting their defensive positions with an extremely dense abatis. The British found the defences almost impossible to breach and were forced to withdraw with some 2,600 casualties. Other uses of an abatis can be found at the [[Battle of the Chateauguay]], 26 October 1813, when approximately 1,300 [[Canadian Voltigeurs]], under the command of Charles-Michel de Salaberry, defeated an American corps of approximately 4,000 men, or at the [[Battle of Plattsburgh]].

== Construction ==
[[File:Giant abatis.jpg|thumb|upright|Giant abatis, made from entire trees, can make an effective anti-vehicle obstacle. This formation can be achieved by use of explosives—note the splintered stumps]]

An important weakness of abatis, in contrast to [[barbed wire]], is that it can be destroyed by [[fire]]. Also, if laced together with [[rope]] instead of [[wire]], the rope can be very quickly destroyed by such fires, after which the abatis can be quickly pulled apart by [[grappling hook]]s thrown from a safe distance.

An important advantage is that an improvised abatis can be quickly formed in forested areas. This can be done by simply cutting down a row of trees so that they fall with their tops toward the enemy. An alternative is to place explosives so as to blow the trees down.

== Modern use ==
[[File:The boys of '61; or, Four years of fighting. Personal observation with the army and navy, from the first battle of Bull run to the fall of Richmond (1884) (14753099266).jpg|left|thumb|Depiction of an abatis during the [[American Civil War]]]]
[[File:Abatis Map Symbol.svg|thumb|left|United States military symbol for an abatis]]

Abatis are rarely seen nowadays, having been largely replaced by [[wire obstacle]]s. However, it may be used as a replacement or supplement when [[barbed wire]] is in short supply. A form of giant abatis, using whole trees instead of branches, can be used as an improvised anti-[[tank]] obstacle.

Though rarely used by modern conventional military units, abatises are still officially maintained in [[United States Army]] and [[United States Marine Corps|Marine Corps]] training.  Current US training instructs engineers or other constructors of such obstacles to fell trees, leaving a {{convert|1|or|2|yard||1}} stump, in such a manner as the trees fall interlocked pointing at a 45-degree angle towards the direction of approach of the enemy.  Furthermore, it is recommended that the trees remain connected to the stumps and the length of roadway covered be at least {{convert|80|yard|round=5}}. US military maps record an abatis by use of an inverted &quot;V&quot; with a short line extending from it to the right.&lt;ref&gt;[[United States Army]] and [[United States Marine Corps]], ''FM 101-5-1/MCRP 5-2A Operational Terms and Graphics'', 30 September 1997&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==

*[[Zasechnaya cherta]] (&quot;Great Abatis Line&quot;)

== Notes ==

{{reflist}}

== References ==

{{refbegin}}
*{{EB1911 |wstitle=Abatis|volume=1}}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.pamplinpark.org Pamplin Historical Park &amp; The National Museum of the Civil War Soldier] includes large and authentic reproduction of abatis used in the U.S. Civil War.

{{Fortifications}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}

[[Category:Fortifications by type]]
[[Category:Medieval defences]]</text>
      <sha1>5cna0swm0jhxqyvwmbd14w0p8w5rkn8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
