  <page>
    <title>Agarose</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2635</id>
    <revision>
      <id>931968344</id>
      <parentid>881464505</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-22T15:01:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rjwilmsi</username>
        <id>203434</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* 3D Cell culture */Journal cites:, added 1 PMID</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[File:Two percent Agarose Gel in Borate Buffer cast in a Gel Tray (Front, angled).jpg|right|thumb|An agarose gel in tray used for gel electrophoresis]]
'''Agarose''' is a [[polysaccharide]], generally extracted from certain [[Red algae|red seaweed]].&lt;ref name=&quot;jeppson&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |authors=Jeppson, J. O., C. B. Laurell, and Bi Franzen|title=Agarose gel electrophoresis|journal=Clinical Chemistry|url=http://clinchem.aaccjnls.org/content/25/4/629.long |volume= 25|issue=4 |date=1979|pages= 629–638|pmid=313856 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  It is a linear polymer made up of the repeating unit of agarobiose, which is a [[disaccharide]] made up of [[D-galactose|&lt;small&gt;D&lt;/small&gt;-galactose]] and 3,6-anhydro-&lt;small&gt;L&lt;/small&gt;-galactopyranose.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lsbu.ac.uk/water/hyagar.html Agar] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071016213723/http://www.lsbu.ac.uk/water/hyagar.html |date=October 16, 2007 }} at lsbu.ac.uk Water Structure and Science&lt;/ref&gt;   Agarose is one of the two principal components of [[agar]], and is purified from agar by removing agar's other component, agaropectin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fao.org/docrep/006/y4765e/y4765e06.htm |title=Agar |work=Food and Agricultural Organization of the United Nations }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Agarose is frequently used in [[molecular biology]] for the separation of large molecules, especially [[DNA]], by [[Agarose gel electrophoresis|electrophoresis]].  Slabs of agarose gels (usually 0.7 - 2%) for electrophoresis are readily prepared by pouring the warm, liquid solution into a mold.  A wide range of different agaroses of varying [[molecular weights]] and properties are commercially available for this purpose.  Agarose may also be formed into beads and used in a number of [[Chromatography|chromatographic]] methods for [[protein purification]].

==Structure==
[[File:Agarose polymere.svg|right|thumb|The structure of an agarose polymer.]]
Agarose is a linear polymer with a molecular weight of about 120,000, consisting of alternating &lt;small&gt;D&lt;/small&gt;-[[galactose]] and 3,6-anhydro-&lt;small&gt;L&lt;/small&gt;-galactopyranose linked by α-(1→3) and β-(1→4) glycosidic bonds.  The  3,6-anhydro-&lt;small&gt;L&lt;/small&gt;-galactopyranose is an &lt;small&gt;L&lt;/small&gt;-galactose with an anhydro bridge between the 3 and 6 positions, although some &lt;small&gt;L&lt;/small&gt;-galactose units in the polymer may not contain the bridge. Some &lt;small&gt;D&lt;/small&gt;-galactose and &lt;small&gt;L&lt;/small&gt;-galactose units can be [[methylated]], and [[pyruvate]] and [[sulfate]] are also found in small quantities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fao.org/docrep/x5822e/x5822e03.htm |title= Chapter 1 - Production, Properties and Uses of Agar |author1=Rafael Armisen |author2=Fernando Galatas |publisher=Fao.org }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Each agarose chain contains ~800 molecules of galactose, and the agarose polymer chains form helical fibres that aggregate into supercoiled structure with a radius of 20-30&amp;nbsp;[[Nanometre|nm]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Molecular Cloning - A Laboratory Manual |author1=Tom Maniatis |author2=E. F. Fritsch |author3=Joseph Sambrook |volume=1 |chapter=Chapter 5, protocol 1 |page=5.4  |isbn=978-0879691363 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The fibers are quasi-rigid, and have a wide range of length depending on the agarose concentration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=A-AiYsGTd38C&amp;pg=PA226&amp;lpg=PA226#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=Food Polysaccharides and Their Applications |editor1=Alistair M. Stephen |editor2=Glyn O. Phillips |page=226 |publisher=CRC Press |year=2006 |isbn=978-0824759223 }}&lt;/ref&gt; When solidified, the fibres form a [[Three-dimensional space|three-dimensional]] mesh of channels of diameter ranging from 50&amp;nbsp;nm to &gt;200&amp;nbsp;nm depending on the concentration of agarose used - higher concentrations yield lower average pore diameters.  The 3-D structure is held together with [[hydrogen bond]]s and can therefore be disrupted by heating back to a liquid state.

==Properties==
Agarose is available as a white powder which dissolves in near-boiling water, and forms a gel when it cools. Agarose exhibits the phenomenon of thermal [[hysteresis]] in its liquid-to-gel transition, i.e. it gels and melts at different temperatures.  The gelling and melting temperatures vary depending on the type of agarose.  Standard agaroses derived from ''[[Gelidium]]'' has a gelling temperature of {{convert|34|-|38|C}} and a melting temperature of {{convert|90|-|95|C}}, while those derived from ''[[Gracilaria]]'', due to its higher [[Methoxy group|methoxy]] substituents, has a gelling temperature of {{convert|40|-|52|C}} and melting temperature of {{convert|85|-|90|C}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=YHMrAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA25#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=Workshop on Marine Algae Biotechnology: Summary Report |page=25 |publisher=National Academy Press |year=1986 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The melting and gelling temperatures may be dependent on the concentration of the gel, particularly at low gel concentration of less than 1%.  The gelling and melting temperatures are therefore given at a specified agarose concentration.

Natural agarose contains uncharged methyl groups and the extent of methylation is directly proportional to the gelling temperature.  Synthetic methylation however have the reverse effect, whereby increased methylation lowers the gelling temperature.&lt;ref name=&quot;lonza&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://bio.lonza.com/uploads/tx_mwaxmarketingmaterial/Lonza_BenchGuides_SourceBook_Appendix_B_-_Agarose_Physical_Chemistry.pdf |title=Appendix B: Agarose Physical Chemistry |work=Lonza Group }}&lt;/ref&gt;  A variety of chemically modified agaroses with different melting and gelling temperatures are available through chemical modifications.

The agarose in the gel forms a meshwork that contains pores, and the size of the pores depends on the concentration of agarose added.  On standing the agarose gels are prone to [[Syneresis (chemistry)|syneresis]] (extrusion of water through the gel surface), but the process is slow enough to not interfere with the use of the gel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=7ShrFsmKjT0C&amp;pg=PA149&amp;lpg=PA149#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=Functional Properties of Food Macromolecules |editor= S.E. Hill |editor2= David A. Ledward |editor3= J.R. Mitchell |page=149 |publisher=Springer |year=1998 |isbn=978-0-7514-0421-0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=l_OGMwaGkgQC&amp;pg=PA102&amp;lpg=PA102#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=Biodegradable Hydrogels for Drug Delivery |author= Haesun Park |author2= Kinam Park |author3= Waleed S.W. Shalaby |page=102 |publisher=CRC Press |year=1993 |isbn=978-1566760041 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Agarose gel can have high gel strength at low concentration, making it suitable as an anti-convection medium for [[gel electrophoresis]].  Agarose gels as dilute as 0.15% can form slabs for gel electrophoresis.&lt;ref name=&quot;serwer&quot;/&gt;  The agarose polymer contains charged groups, in particular [[pyruvate]] and [[sulfate]].&lt;ref name=&quot;lonza&quot; /&gt;  These negatively charged groups can slow down the movement of DNA molecules in a process called [[electroendosmosis]] (EEO), and low EEO agarose is therefore generally preferred for use in agarose [[gel electrophoresis of nucleic acids]].  Zero EEO agaroses are also available but these may be undesirable for some applications as they may be made by adding positively charged groups that can affect subsequent enzyme reactions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Molecular Cloning - A Laboratory Manual |author1=Joseph Sambrook |author2=David Russell |volume=1 |edition=3rd |chapter=Chapter 5, protocol 1 |page=5.7 |isbn=978-0-87969-577-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Electroendosmosis is a reason agarose is used preferentially over agar as agaropectin in agar contains a significant amount of negatively charged sulphate and carboxyl groups. The removal of agaropectin in agarose substantially reduces the EEO, as well as reducing the non-specific adsorption of biomolecules to the gel matrix.  However, for some applications such as the electrophoresis of serum protein, a high EEO may be desirable, and agaropectin may be added in the gel used.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=z-bZ_FZHqRcC&amp;pg=PA7#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=Protein Electrophoresis in Clinical Diagnosis|first= David |last=Keren |pages=7–8 |publisher=CRC Press |date=26 September 2003|isbn=978-0340812136 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Low melting and gelling temperature agaroses===
The melting and gelling temperatures of agarose can be modified by chemical modifications, most commonly by hydroxyethylation, which reduces the number of intrastrand hydrogen bonds, resulting in lower melting and setting temperatures than standard agaroses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Molecular Cloning - A Laboratory Manual |author1=Tom Maniatis |author2=E. F. Fritsch |author3=Joseph Sambrook |volume=1 |chapter=Chapter 5, protocol 6 |page=5.29  |isbn=978-0879695774 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The exact temperature is determined by the degree of substitution, and many available low-melting-point (LMP) agaroses can remain fluid at {{convert|30|-|35|C}} range. This property allows [[Enzyme|enzymatic]] manipulations to be carried out directly after the DNA gel electrophoresis by adding slices of melted gel containing DNA fragment of interest to a reaction mixture. The LMP agarose contains fewer sulphates which can affect some enzymatic reactions, and is therefore preferably used for some applications. Hydroxyethylation may reduce the pore size by reducing the packing density of the agarose bundles, therefore LMP gel can also have an effect on the time and separation during electrophoresis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal =J Vis Exp |volume=62|page= 3923. |title=Agarose gel electrophoresis for the separation of DNA fragments |vauthors=Lee PY, Costumbrado J, Hsu CY, Kim YH|date=20 April 2012 | doi=  10.3791/3923|pmid= 22546956 |pmc=4846332 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Ultra-low melting or gelling temperature agaroses may gel only at {{convert|8|-|15|C}}.

==Applications==
[[File:AgarosegelUV.jpg|thumb|An agarose gel with bands of DNA stained with ethidium bromide and visualized under [[Ultraviolet|UV light]] on a UV Transilluminator.]]
Agarose is a preferred matrix for work with [[protein]]s and [[nucleic acid]]s as it has a broad range of physical, chemical and thermal stability, and its lower degree of chemical complexity also makes it less likely to interact with [[biomolecule]]s.  Agarose is most commonly used as the medium for analytical scale [[Electrophoresis|electrophoretic]] separation in [[agarose gel electrophoresis]].  Gels made from purified agarose have a relatively large pore size, making them useful for separation of large molecules, such as proteins and protein complexes &gt;200 kilodaltons, as well as DNA fragments &gt;100 basepairs.   Agarose is also used widely for a number of other applications, for example [[immunodiffusion]] and [[immunoelectrophoresis]], as the agarose fibers functions as an anchor for [[Immune complex|immunocomplexes]].

=== Agarose gel electrophoresis ===
{{Main|Agarose gel electrophoresis}}

Agarose gel electrophoresis is the routine method for resolving [[DNA]] in the laboratory.  Agarose gels have lower resolving power for DNA than acrylamide gels, but they have greater range of separation, and are therefore usually used for DNA fragments with lengths of 50-20,000 bp ([[base pair]]s), although resolution of over 6 Mb is possible with [[pulsed field gel electrophoresis]] (PFGE).&lt;ref name=&quot;maniatis1&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Molecular Cloning - A Laboratory Manual |author1=Tom Maniatis |author2=E. F. Fritsch |author3=Joseph Sambrook |volume=1 |chapter=Chapter 5, protocol 1 |page=5.2–5.3  |isbn=978-0879691363 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  It can also be used to separate large protein molecules, and it is the preferred matrix for the gel electrophoresis of particles with effective [[Radius|radii]] larger than 5-10&amp;nbsp;nm.&lt;ref name=&quot;serwer&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |title=Agarose gels: Properties and use for electrophoresis |author =Philip Serwer |journal=Electrophoresis |volume = 4 |issue =6 |pages =375–382 |year= 1983 |doi=10.1002/elps.1150040602}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The pore size of the gel affects the size of the DNA that can be sieved.  The lower the concentration of the gel, the larger the pore size, and the larger the DNA that can be sieved.  However low-concentration gels (0.1 - 0.2%) are fragile and therefore hard to handle, and the electrophoresis of large DNA molecules can take several days.  The limit of resolution for standard agarose gel electrophoresis is around 750 kb.&lt;ref name=&quot;maniatis1&quot; /&gt;  This limit can be overcome by PFGE, where alternating orthogonal electric fields are applied to the gel.  The DNA fragments reorientate themselves when the applied field switches direction, but larger molecules of DNA take longer to realign themselves when the electric field is altered, while for smaller ones it is quicker, and the DNA can therefore be fractionated according to size.

Agarose gels are cast in a mold, and when set, usually run horizontally submerged in a buffer solution. [[TAE buffer|Tris-acetate-EDTA]] and [[TBE buffer|Tris-Borate-EDTA]] buffers are commonly used, but other buffers such as Tris-phosphate,  barbituric acid-sodium barbiturate or Tris-[[Barbital|barbiturate]] buffers may be used in other applications.&lt;ref name=&quot;jeppson&quot;/&gt; The DNA is normally visualized by staining with [[ethidium bromide]] and then viewed under a [[UV light]], but other methods of staining are available, such as [[SYBR Green I|SYBR Green]], [[GelRed]], [[methylene blue]], and [[crystal violet]]. If the separated DNA fragments are needed for further downstream experiment, they can be cut out from the gel in slices for further manipulation.

[[File:Size_Exclusion_Chromatography_Apparatus.jpg|thumb|Agarose-based gel filtration columns used for protein purification on an AKTA [[Fast protein liquid chromatography|FPLC]] machine.]]

=== Protein purification ===
Agarose gel matrix is often used for [[protein purification]], for example, in column-based preparative scale separation as in [[Size exclusion chromatography|gel filtration chromatography]], [[affinity chromatography]] and [[ion exchange chromatography]].  It is however not used as a continuous gel, rather it is formed into porous beads or resins of varying fineness.&lt;ref name=freifelder&gt;{{cite book |title=Physical Biochemistry: Applications to Biochemistry and Molecular Biology |author =David Freifelder |edition=2nd |year=1982 |publisher=WH Freeman |page=240 |isbn= 978-0716714446}}&lt;/ref&gt; The beads are highly porous so that protein may flow freely through the beads. These agarose-based beads are generally soft and easily crushed, so they should be used under gravity-flow, low-speed centrifugation, or low-pressure procedures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.piercenet.com/method/overview-affinity-purification |title=Overview of Affinity Purification |work=Thermo Scientific }}&lt;/ref&gt; The strength of the resins can be improved by increased cross-linking and chemical hardening of the agarose resins, however such changes may also result in a lower binding capacity for protein in some separation procedures such as [[affinity chromatography]].

Agarose is a useful material for chromatography because it does not absorb biomolecules to any significant extent, has good flow properties, and can tolerate extremes of [[pH]] and [[ionic strength]] as well as high concentration of [[Denaturation (biochemistry)|denaturant]]s such as 8M [[urea]] or 6M [[Guanidinium chloride|guanidine HCl]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Physical Biochemistry: Applications to Biochemistry and Molecular Biology |author =David Freifelder |edition=2nd |year=1982 |publisher=WH Freeman |page= 258 |isbn= 978-0716714446}}&lt;/ref&gt;   Examples of agarose-based matrix for gel filtration chromatography are [[Sepharose]] and WorkBeads 40 SEC (cross-linked beaded agarose), ''Praesto'' and [[Superose]] (highly cross-linked beaded agaroses), and Superdex ([[dextran]] covalently linked to agarose).

For affinity chromatography, beaded agarose is the most commonly used matrix resin for the attachment of the ligands that bind protein.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Encyclopedia of Biological Chemistry |volume= Volume 1 |page=52 |author1=Pedro Cuatrecasas |author2=Meir Wilchek |editor1=William J. Lennarz |editor2=M. Daniel Lane |publisher=Academic Press |isbn= 9780124437104 |year=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ligands are linked covalently through a spacer to activated hydroxyl groups of agarose bead polymer.  Proteins of interest can then be selectively bound to the ligands to separate them from other proteins, after which it can be eluted.  The agarose beads used are typically of 4% and 6% densities with a high binding capacity for protein.

===Solid culture media===
Agarose plate may sometimes be used instead of agar for culturing organisms as agar may contain impurities that can affect the growth of the organism or some downstream procedures such as [[polymerase chain reaction]] (PCR).  Agarose is also harder than agar and may therefore be preferable where greater gel strength is necessary, and its lower gelling temperature may prevent causing [[thermal shock]] to the organism when the cells are suspended in liquid before gelling.  It may be used for the culture of strict autotrophic bacteria, plant [[protoplast]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vjI5KXFZlcoC&amp;pg=PA16#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=In Vitro Culture of Trees|author1=J.M. Bonga |author2=Patrick von Aderkas |page=16 |year= 1992 |publisher=Springer |isbn=978-0792315407 }}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Caenorhabditis elegans]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=bxZeffKo4-8C&amp;pg=PA95&amp;lpg=PA95#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=Integrated Genomics: A Discovery-Based Laboratory Course|author1=Guy A. Caldwell |author2=Shelli N. Williams |author3=Kim A. Caldwell |pages=94–95 |year= 2006 |publisher=Wiley |isbn= 978-0470095027 }}&lt;/ref&gt; other organisms and various cell lines.

=== 3D Cell culture ===
Agarose is often used as a support for the tri-dimensional culture of human and animal [[cell (biology)|cell]]s. Because agarose forms a non-cytotoxic [[hydrogel]]s, it can be utilized to reproduce the natural environment of cells in the human body, the [[extracellular matrix]]. However, agarose forms a stiff inert [[hydrogel]] that does not carry any biological information, thus the human and animal cells can not adhere to the [[polysaccharide]]. Because of these specifics properties, agarose [[hydrogel]] mimics the natural environment of [[cartilage]] cells and have been shown to be support the differentiation of [[chondrocyte]]s into [[cartilage]]. In order to modify the [[mechanical properties]] of agarose to reproduce the natural environment of other human cells, agarose can be chemically modified through the precise oxidation of the primary alcohol of the D-[[galactose]] into [[carboxylic acid]]. This chemical modification provides a novel class of materials named carboxylated agarose. Through the control over the number of carboxylated D-galactose on the [[polysaccharide]] backbone, the mechanical properties of the resulting hydrogel can be precisely controlled. These carboxylated agarose hydrogels can be then covalently bond to [[peptide]]s to form hydrogel on which cells can adhere. These carboxylated agarose hydrogels have been shown to direct the organization of human endothelial cells into polarized lumens.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi= 10.1073/pnas.1222880110 |author1 = A. Forget |author2 = J. Christensen |author3 = S. Lüdeke |author4 = E. Kohler |author5 = S. Tobias |author6 = M. Matloubi |author7 = R. Thomann |author8 = V. P. Shastri |year = 2013 |title = Polysaccharide hydrogels with tunable stiffness and provasculogenic properties via α-helix to β-sheet switch in secondary structure |volume = 110 |issue = 32 |pages = 12887–12892 |journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America|pmc = 3740890 |pmid=23886665}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Mixing of fully carboxylated agarose with natural agarose can be used to make hydrogels that span a whole range of mechanical properties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi= 10.1002/marc.201400353 |year = 2015 |author1 = A. Forget |author2 = R. A. Pique |author3 = V. Ahamadi |author4 = S. Lüdeke |author5 = V. P. Shastri |title = Mechanically tailored agarose hydrogels through molecular alloying with beta-sheet polysaccharides |pages = 196–203 | volume = 36 |issue = 2 |journal = Macromolecular Rapid Communications}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1002/anie.201701019 | year = 2017 | author1 = A. Rüther | author2 = A. Forget | author3 = A. Roy | author4 = C. Carballo | author5 = F. Mießmer | author6 = R. K. Dukor | author7 = L. A. Nafie | author8 = C. Johannessen | author9 = V. P. Shastri | author10 = S. Lüdeke | journal = Angewandte Chemie International Edition | volume = 56 | pages = 1–6 | title = unravelling a direct role for polysaccharide beta-strands in the Higher Order Structure of Physical Hydrogels}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Motility assays ===
Agarose is sometimes used instead of agar to measure microorganism motility and mobility.  Motile species will be able to migrate, albeit slowly, throughout the porous gel and infiltration rates can then be visualized.  The gel's porosity is directly related to the concentration of agar or agarose in the medium, so different concentration gels may be used to assess a cell's [[Flagellar motility|swimming]], [[Swarming motility|swarming]], [[gliding motility|gliding]] and twitching motility. Under-agarose cell migration assay may be used to measure chemotaxis and chemokinesis.  A layer of agarose gel is placed between a cell population and a [[chemoattractant]]. As a concentration gradient develops from the [[diffusion]] of the chemoattractant into the gel, various cell populations requiring different stimulation levels to migrate can then be visualized over time using microphotography as they tunnel upward through the gel against gravity along the gradient.

==See also==
*[[Agar]]
*[[SDD-AGE]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Polysaccharides]]</text>
      <sha1>5zy2kqdshavyijxzod7logb0t4kmh90</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
