  <page>
    <title>Aelia Capitolina</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2632</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941934840</id>
      <parentid>938185459</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-21T15:19:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pete unseth</username>
        <id>5231945</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>wikilink</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox ancient site
|name        = Aelia Capitolina
|native_name = 
|alternate_name = 
|image = 
|alt = 
|caption = 
|map_type    = Jerusalem
|map_alt = 
|map_size    = 250
|location    = [[Jerusalem]]
|region      = [[United Nations Partition Plan for Palestine|Jerusalem Corpus Separatum]]
|coordinates = {{coord|31.775689|35.23104|display=inline}}
|type = 
|part_of = 
|length = 
|width = 
|area = 
|height = 
|builder = 
|material = 
|built = 
|abandoned = 
|epochs = 
|cultures = 
|dependency_of = 
|occupants = 
|event = 
|excavations = 
|archaeologists = 
|condition = 
|ownership = 
|management = 
|public_access = 
|website = 
|notes = 
}}

'''Aelia Capitolina''' (Traditional English Pronunciation: {{IPAc-en|ˈ|iː|l|i|ə|_|ˌ|k|æ|p|ᵻ|t|ə|ˈ|l|aɪ|n|ə}}; [[Latin]] in full: {{sqc|COLONIA AELIA CAPITOLINA}}) was a [[Colonia (Roman)|Roman colony]], built under the emperor [[Hadrian]] on the site of [[Jerusalem]], which was in ruins following the [[Siege of Jerusalem (AD 70)|siege of 70 AD]],&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;&gt;{{Cite EB1911|wstitle=Aelia Capitolina |volume=1|page=256}}&lt;/ref&gt; leading in part to the [[Bar Kokhba revolt]] of 132–136 AD. ''Aelia Capitolina'' remained the official name of Jerusalem&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ancientcoinage.org/coinage-of-aelia-capitolina.html|title=Aelia Capitolina|accessdate=6 August 2016|work=Ancient Numismatic Mythology|publisher=AncientCoinage.Org}}&lt;/ref&gt; until 638 AD, when the Arabs conquered the city and kept the first part of it as 'إلياء' (Iliyā').&lt;ref&gt;[https://efcbbd02-a-62cb3a1a-s-sites.googlegroups.com/site/emmausnicopolis/Palestine%20under%20caliphs%20.jpg?attachauth=ANoY7cqqT0r6XPATN0FhmOFVTEvDN8jEoD6iOHGHF-Zf57D8Pda4rm8b-6uWDM0xDPkYFjs79MOFFQPbEPKIiHd7ylPCUBUF0DHCE1JLFECBLXFy2yXncxrgLOviFesiRBNlYs4CZhwfLgeQIO3sMoArlCx8cDizwvZoqFUGxQwXWPHcfPHKMpV-v4OvymjM0hR5UAC1V8WgOtavsya9TbCdQEPgDCE43YKe_sJvmQiETe3VZjaaT6Y%3D&amp;attredirects=0 Map of the early Arab dominions, showing Iliya]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Name==
''Aelia'' came from Hadrian's ''[[Roman naming conventions|nomen gentile]]'', ''[[Aelia (gens)|Aelius]]'', while ''Capitolina'' meant that the new city was dedicated to ''[[Jupiter (mythology)|Jupiter]] [[Capitoline Hill|Capitolinus]]'', to whom [[Church of the Holy Sepulchre#Connection to Jupiter Capitolinus|a temple was built]] on the [[Temple Mount]]. Under the rule of [[Antiochus IV Epiphanes]], before King Herod's reign, the site of the [[Second Temple]] at the Temple Mount had already been reconsecrated to [[Zeus]]. This led to the [[Maccabean Revolt]]—which resulted in the Jewish-Roman alliance.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

The Latin name ''Aelia'' is the source of the much later [[Arabic language|Arabic]] term Iliyā' (إلياء), a 7th-century [[Islam]]ic name for Jerusalem.

==History==
{{Infobox Historical Era
|name    = Aelia Capitolina (Jerusalem)
|image   = Roman Empire 125.png
|caption = Jerusalem in the Roman empire under [[Hadrian]] showing the location of the Roman legions
|start   = AD 130
|end     = AD 324-325
|before  = [[Jerusalem during the Second Temple Period#Herodian period|Jerusalem during the Early Roman period]]
|after   = [[History of Jerusalem during the Middle Ages#Byzantine rule|Jerusalem during the Byzantine period]]
}}
{{multiple images
| align     = left
| footer    = The first coin issued at the mint of Aelia Capitolina about 130/132 CE. Reverse: COL[ONIA] AEL[IA] CAPIT[OLINA] COND[ITA] ('The founding of Colonia Aelia Capitolina'), showing Hadrian while ploughing the first furrow.
| footer_align = center
| image1    = Hadrian founder Aelia Capitolina.jpg
| width1    = {{#expr: (100 * 500 / 243) round 0}}
| image2    = Dictionary of Roman Coins.1889 P15S0 illus022.gif
| width2    = {{#expr: (100 * 155 / 151) round 0}}}}
[[File:Madaba map.jpg|thumb|left|The [[Madaba Map]] depiction of 6th-century [[Jerusalem]] has the ''[[Cardo]] Maximus'', the town’s main street, beginning at the northern gate (today's [[Damascus Gate]]), and traversing the city in a straight line south to &quot;Nea Church&quot;.]]
{{Jerusalem large}}
Jerusalem, once heavily rebuilt by [[Herod the Great|Herod]], was still in ruins following the decisive [[Siege of Jerusalem (AD 70)|siege]] of the city, as part of the [[First Jewish–Roman War]] in 70 AD. [[Josephus]]—a contemporary historian and proponent of the Judean cause who was born in Jerusalem and fought the [[Roman Empire|Romans]] in that war—reports that &quot;Jerusalem  ... was so thoroughly razed to the ground by those that demolished it to its foundations, that nothing was left that could ever persuade visitors that it had once been a place of habitation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Josephus, ''Jewish War'', 7:1:1&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Talmud]] ([[Makkot]]) tells of [[Rabbi Akiva]] and several other sages visiting the ruins of Jerusalem. His colleagues were aggrieved at seeing a [[fox]] scuttling out of what had been the Temple's Holy of Holies as an indication of the desolation, while Akiva laughed, telling them through what many believe to be divine inspiration that one day the Temple will be rebuilt. 

According to [[Eusebius]], the [[Early centers of Christianity#Jerusalem|Jerusalem church]] was scattered twice, in 70 and 135, with the difference that from 70–130 the bishops of Jerusalem have evidently Jewish names, whereas after 135 the bishops of Aelia Capitolina appear to be Greeks.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Jerusalem in Early Christian Thought&quot; p. 75 ''Explorations in a Christian theology of pilgrimage'' ed Craig G. Bartholomew, Fred Hughes&lt;/ref&gt; Eusebius' evidence for continuation of a church at Aelia Capitolina is confirmed by the [[Itinerarium Burdigalense|Bordeaux Pilgrim]].&lt;ref&gt;Richard Bauckham &quot;The Christian Community of Aelia Capitolina&quot; in ''The Book of Acts in Its Palestinian Setting'' p. 310.&lt;/ref&gt;

When the [[Roman emperor|Roman Emperor]] [[Hadrian]] vowed to rebuild Jerusalem from the wreckage in 130 AD, he considered reconstructing Jerusalem as a gift to the [[Jews|Jewish people]]. The Jews awaited with hope, but after Hadrian visited Jerusalem, he was discouraged from doing so by a [[Samaritan]] (according to rabbinic sources).&lt;ref name=&quot;Peter Schäfer 146&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-0aBAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA146|title=The History of the Jews in the Greco-Roman World: The Jews of Palestine from Alexander the Great to the Arab Conquest|author=Peter Schäfer|date=2 September 2003|publisher=Routledge|isbn=1-134-40316-X|pages=146–}}&lt;/ref&gt; He then decided to rebuild the city as a Roman colony, which would be inhabited by his [[Legionary|legionaries]].&lt;ref&gt;Benjamin Isaac, ''The Near East under Roman Rule: Selected Papers'' (Leiden: Brill 1998){{page needed|date=June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hadrian's new city was to be dedicated to himself and certain Roman gods, in particular [[Jupiter (mythology)|Jupiter]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=A history of Jerusalem|last=Gray|first=John|publisher=Hale|year=1969|isbn=0709103646|location=London|pages=59|oclc=53301}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Jewish [[Bar Kokhba revolt]], which took the Romans three years to suppress, enraged Hadrian, and he became determined to erase Judaism from the province. [[Circumcision controversies|Circumcision]] was forbidden and Jews were expelled from the city. Hadrian renamed [[Iudaea Province]] to ''[[Syria Palaestina]]'', dispensing with the name of Judea.&lt;ref&gt;Elizabeth Speller, {{Google books |id=3c8kB3m0r8kC |page=218 |title=Following Hadrian: A Second-Century Journey Through the Roman Empire }}, Oxford University Press, 2004, p. 218&lt;/ref&gt; There is controversy as to whether the anti-Jewish decrees followed the Bar Kokhba revolt or preceded it and were the cause of the revolt.&lt;ref name=&quot;Peter Schäfer 146&quot;/&gt;

Jerusalem was renamed &quot;Aelia Capitolina&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usd.edu/erp/Palestine/people&amp;p.htm |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080310053409/http://www.usd.edu/erp/Palestine/people%26p.htm |archivedate=10 March 2008 |title=Palestine: People and Places |accessdate=18 April 2007 |last=Lehmann |first=Clayton Miles |work=The On-line Encyclopedia of the Roman Provinces |publisher=The University of South Dakota |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; and rebuilt in the style of a typical Roman town. Jews were prohibited from entering the city on pain of death, except for one day each year, during the holiday of [[Tisha B'Av]]. Taken together, these measures&lt;ref name=&quot;Schäfer2003&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Peter Schäfer|title=The Bar Kokhba war reconsidered: new perspectives on the second Jewish revolt against Rome|url={{Google books |id=1TA-Fg4wBnUC |page=36 |plainurl=yes }} |accessdate=4 December 2011|year=2003|publisher=Mohr Siebeck|isbn=978-3-16-148076-8|pages=36–}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;erp-places&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usd.edu/erp/Palestine/history.htm|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080310053428/http://www.usd.edu/erp/Palestine/history.htm|archivedate=10 March 2008|title=Palestine: History|accessdate=18 April 2007|date=22 February 2007|last=Lehmann|first=Clayton Miles|work=The On-line Encyclopedia of the Roman Provinces|publisher=The University of South Dakota}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Cohen|first=Shaye J. D.|chapter=Judaism to Mishnah: 135–220 C.E|title=Christianity and Rabbinic Judaism: A Parallel History of their Origins and Early Development|editor=Hershel Shanks|year=1996|location=Washington DC|page=196|publisher=Biblical Archaeology Society}}&lt;/ref&gt; (which also affected Jewish Christians)&lt;ref&gt;Emily Jane Hunt, {{Google books |id=Dn5ERgK0djMC |page=7 |title=Christianity in the second century: the case of Tatian}}, Psychology Press, 2003, p. 7&lt;/ref&gt; essentially secularized the city.&lt;ref&gt;E. Mary Smallwood {{Google books |id=nw0VAAAAIAAJ |page=460 |title=The Jews under Roman rule: from Pompey to Diocletian : a study in political relations}} BRILL, 1981, p. 460.&lt;/ref&gt; The ban was maintained until the 7th century,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/mzank/Jerusalem/p/period3-2.htm|last=Zank|first=Michael|publisher=Boston University|title=Byzantian Jerusalem|accessdate=1 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; though Christians would soon be granted an exemption: during the 4th century, the [[Roman Emperor]] [[Constantine I]] ordered the construction of Christian holy sites in the city, including the [[Church of the Holy Sepulchre]]. Burial remains from the Byzantine period are exclusively Christian, suggesting that the population of Jerusalem in Byzantine times probably consisted only of Christians.&lt;ref&gt;Gideon Avni, {{Google books |id=ZLucAgAAQBAJ |page=144 |title=The Byzantine-Islamic Transition in Palestine: An Archaeological Approach}}, Oxford University Press 2014 p.144.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the fifth century, the eastern continuation of the Roman Empire that was ruled from the recently renamed [[Constantinople]], maintained control of the city. Within the span of a few decades, the city shifted from Byzantine to [[Achaemenid Empire|Persian]] rule, then back to Roman-Byzantine dominion. Following [[Sassanid Empire|Sassanid]] [[Khosrau II]]'s early seventh century push through [[Syria]], his generals [[Shahrbaraz]] and [[Shahin Vahmanzadegan|Shahin]] attacked Jerusalem (''{{lang-fa|Dej Houdkh}}'') aided by the Jews of [[Palaestina Prima]], who had risen up against the Byzantines.&lt;ref name=&quot;AntiochusStrategos&quot;&gt;{{Cite book
|last=Conybeare
|first=Frederick C.
|authorlink=Frederick Cornwallis Conybeare
|title=The Capture of Jerusalem by the Persians in 614 AD
|series=English Historical Review 25
|year=1910
|pages=502–517
|isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Siege of Jerusalem (614)|Siege of Jerusalem]] of 614 AD, after 21 days of relentless [[siege|siege warfare]], Jerusalem was captured. Byzantine chronicles relate that the Sassanids and Jews slaughtered tens of thousands of Christians in the city, many at the [[Mamilla Pool]], and destroyed their monuments and churches, including the Church of the Holy Sepulchre. The conquered city would remain in Sassanid hands for some fifteen years until the Byzantine Emperor [[Heraclius]] reconquered it in 629.&lt;ref&gt;Rodney Aist,''The Christian Topography of Early Islamic Jerusalem,''Brepols Publishers, 2009 p.56:'Persian control of Jerusalem lasted from 614 to 629'.&lt;/ref&gt;

Byzantine Jerusalem was conquered by the Arab armies of [[Umar ibn al-Khattab]] in 638 AD,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = Dan Bahat | title = The Illustrated Atlas of Jerusalem | page = 71 | year = 1996}}&lt;/ref&gt; which resulted in the removal of the restrictions on Jews living in the city. Among [[Muslims]] of Islam's earliest era it was referred to as ''Madinat bayt al-Maqdis'' ('City of the Temple')&lt;ref&gt;Ben-Dov, M. ''Historical Atlas of Jerusalem''. Translated by David Louvish. New York: Continuum, 2002, p. 171&lt;/ref&gt; which was restricted to the Temple Mount. The rest of the city was called &quot;Iliya&quot;, reflecting the Roman name Aelia Capitolina.&lt;ref&gt;Linquist, J.M., ''The Temple of Jerusalem'', Praeger, London, 2008, p. 184&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|&quot;Till the time of Constantine, and for at least two centuries later, Aelia remained the official name and usual geographical designation; was still longer continued in Christian writings; and even passed over into Arabic as 'Iliyā'.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.cwru.edu/UL/preserve/Etana/SMITH.JERUv1/SMITH.JERUv1.250.273.pdf|archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20031212012636/http://www.cwru.edu/UL/preserve/Etana/SMITH.JERUv1/SMITH.JERUv1.250.273.pdf |url-status= dead |archive-date= 2003-12-12  |title=The Name Jerusalem and its History }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Plan of the city==
[[File:Roman Jerusalem.PNG|thumb|left|The two pairs of main roads—the cardines (north-south) and decumani (east-west)—in Aelia Capitolina]]

The city was without walls, protected by a light garrison of the [[Legio X Fretensis|Tenth Legion]], during the Late Roman Period. The detachment at Jerusalem, which apparently encamped all over the city's western hill, was responsible for preventing Jews from returning to the city. Roman enforcement of this prohibition continued through the 4th century.

The urban plan of Aelia Capitolina was that of a typical Roman town wherein main thoroughfares crisscrossed the [[Urban planning|urban grid]] lengthwise and widthwise.&lt;ref&gt;[http://jeru.huji.ac.il/ed22.htm The Cardo] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081217114200/http://jeru.huji.ac.il/ed22.htm |date=December 17, 2008 }} Hebrew University&lt;/ref&gt; The urban grid was based on the usual central north-south road (''[[cardo]]'') and central east-west route (''[[Decumanus Maximus|decumanus]]''). However, as the main cardo ran up the western hill, and the [[Temple Mount]] blocked the eastward route of the main decumanus, a second pair of main roads was added; the secondary cardo ran down the [[Tyropoeon Valley]], and the secondary decumanus ran just to the north of the Temple Mount. The main Hadrianic cardo terminated not far beyond its junction with the decumanus, where it reached the Roman garrison's encampment, but in the [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine]] era it was extended over the former camp to reach the southern walls of the city.

The two cardines converged near the ''[[Damascus Gate]]'', and a semicircular [[piazza]] covered the remaining space; in the piazza a columnar monument was constructed, hence the Arabic name for the gate - ''Bab el-Amud'' (''Gate of the Column'').  [[Tetrapylon]]es were constructed at the other junctions between the main roads.

This street pattern has been preserved in the [[Old City (Jerusalem)|Old City of Jerusalem]] to the present. The original thoroughfare, flanked by rows of columns and shops, was about 73 feet (22 meters) wide, but buildings have extended onto the streets over the centuries, and the modern lanes replacing the ancient grid are now quite narrow. The substantial remains of the western cardo have now been exposed to view near the junction with Suq el-Bazaar, and remnants of one of the tetrapylones are preserved in the 19th century [[Franciscan]] chapel at the junction of the Via Dolorosa and Suq Khan ez-Zeit.

As was standard for new Roman cities, Hadrian placed the city's main [[Forum (Roman)|forum]] at the junction of the main cardo and decumanus, now the location for the (smaller) [[Muristan]]. Adjacent to the Forum, at the junction of the same cardo, and the other decumanus, Hadrian built a large temple to [[Venus (mythology)|Venus]], which later became the [[Church of the Holy Sepulchre]]; despite 11th century destruction, which resulted in the modern Church having a much smaller footprint, several boundary walls of Hadrian's temple have been found among the archaeological remains beneath the Church.&lt;ref&gt;[[Virgilio Canio Corbo|Virgilio Corbo]], ''The Holy Sepulchre of Jerusalem'' (1981)&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[Struthion Pool]]'' lay in the path of the northern decumanus, so Hadrian placed [[vault (architecture)|vaulting]] over it, added a large pavement on top, and turned it into a secondary forum;&lt;ref name=&quot;benoit&quot;&gt;Benoit, Pierre, ''The Archaeological Reconstruction of the Antonia Fortress'', in ''Jerusalem Revealed'' (edited by [[Yigael Yadin]]), (1976)&lt;/ref&gt; the pavement can still be seen under the [[Convent of the Sisters of Zion]].&lt;ref name=&quot;benoit&quot; /&gt;

{{multiple image|total_width=400
|image1 = Ecce Homo arch in 1864.jpg
|image2 = Ewilson-ecce-homo-arch.jpg
|caption1 = The remaining two arches of the gateway in 1864; the smaller arch (left) was incorporated in the [[Basilica of Ecce Homo]]. |caption2 = The portion of the arch visible today (approx. 180° opposite the former image)}}
===''Ecce homo'' arch===
Near the Struthion Pool, Hadrian built a triple-arched gateway as an entrance to the eastern forum of Aelia Capitolina.&lt;ref&gt;[[Pierre Benoit (archaeologist)|Benoit, Pierre]], ''The Antonia of Herod the Great, and the East Forum of Aelia Capitolina'' (1971)&lt;/ref&gt; Traditionally, this was thought to be the gate of [[Herod the Great|Herod]]'s [[Antonia Fortress]], which itself was alleged to be the location of [[Jesus]]' trial and [[Pontius Pilate]]'s ''[[Ecce homo]]'' speech as described in {{bibleverse||John|19:13|}}.&lt;ref name=cruise&gt;{{cite book|last1=Warren|first1=E.K.|last2=Hartshorn|first2=W.N.|last3=McCrillis|first3=A.B.|title=Glimpses of Bible Lands: The Cruise of the Eight Hundred to Jerusalem|year=1905|publisher=The Central Committee|location=Boston, MA|page=168}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was due in part to the 1864 discovery of a game etched on a flagstone of the pool. According to the nuns of the convent, the game was played by Roman soldiers and ended in the execution of a 'monk king'.&lt;ref name=video&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jerusalemexperience.com/tour/ecce-homo-arch-notre-dame-de-sion-convent-via-dolorosa/|title=Ecce Homo Arch Video|website=Jerusalem Experience|year=2012}}{{bettersource|date=July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is possible that following its destruction, the Antonia Fortress's pavement tiles were brought to the cistern of Hadrian's plaza.&lt;ref name=video/&gt;

When later constructions narrowed the ''[[Via Dolorosa]]'', the two arches on either side of the central arch became incorporated into a succession of more modern buildings. The [[Basilica of Ecce Homo]] now preserves the northern arch.&lt;ref name=cruise/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Benoit |first1=P. |title=L'Antonia D'Hérode le Grand et le Forum Oriental D'Aelia Capitolina |journal=The Harvard Theological Review |date=1971 |volume=64 |issue=2/3 |pages=135–167 |language=French |issn=0017-8160|jstor=1509294 |doi=10.1017/S0017816000032478 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The southern arch was incorporated into a monastery for [[Uzbeks|Uzbek]] [[dervish]]es belonging to the [[Naqshbandi|Order of the Golden Chain]] in the 16th century,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://madainproject.com/ecce_homo_arch|title=Arch of Hadrian|last=Madain Project|access-date=2019-07-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; but these were demolished in the 19th century in order to found a mosque.&lt;ref&gt;Lewin, Thomas. [https://books.google.ca/books?id=2SldAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA202&amp;lpg=PA202&amp;dq=Via+Dolorosa+south+arch+monastery ''The Siege of Jerusalem by Titus: With the Journal of a Recent Visit to the Holy City, and a General Sketch of the Topography of Jerusalem from the Earliest Times Down to the Siege'']. London: Longman, Green, Longman, Roberts, &amp; Green, 1863: 202. [[Google Books|Google books]]. 2019-07-12.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Jerusalem Mural depicting the Cardo in Byzantine era (6035801113).jpg|thumb|Jerusalem Mural depicting the Cardo in the Byzantine era]]

==See also==
{{Portal|History|Roman Empire|Judaism}}
*[[Alexander of Jerusalem]]
*[[Caesarea Maritima]]
*[[Gabbatha]]
*[[Names of Jerusalem]]

==References==
'''Footnotes'''
{{notelist}}

'''Citations'''
{{reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* [http://www.jesusneverexisted.com/aelia.htm Detailed description (including map) of the city of Aelia Capitolina]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090907043901/http://www.christusrex.org/www1/jhs/TSsptemp.html Pictures of the cave where it is believed by Christians that Jesus was buried and from which it is believed he resurrected and a picture of the remains of the walls of the Temple of Venus previously constructed on that site by the Emperor Hadrian]
* [http://www.haaretz.com/print-edition/features/archaeologists-bringing-jerusalem-s-ancient-roman-city-back-to-life-1.413874 &quot;Archaeologists bringing Jerusalem's ancient Roman city back to life&quot;  by Nir Hasson, Ha'aretz, February 21, 2012]

{{coord|31.775689|N|35.231040|E|display=title}}

{{Roman colonies in ancient Levant}}

[[Category:Jews and Judaism in the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:Classical sites in Jerusalem]]
[[Category:Former populated places in Southwest Asia]]
[[Category:Ancient history of Jerusalem]]
[[Category:Judea (Roman province)]]
[[Category:Nerva–Antonine dynasty]]
[[Category:Populated places established in the 2nd century]]
[[Category:131 establishments]]
[[Category:130s establishments in the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:320s disestablishments in the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:Roman towns and cities in Israel]]
[[Category:Coloniae (Roman)]]
[[Category:State of Palestine in the Roman era]]</text>
      <sha1>gpo551snmw6vvxyi5ctxfy09wwqoziv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
