  <page>
    <title>Abd al-Latif al-Baghdadi</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2674</id>
    <revision>
      <id>931326090</id>
      <parentid>903175021</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-18T07:52:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bluelinking 1 books for [[WP:V|verifiability]].) #IABot (v2.1alpha3</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{for|the 20th-century Egyptian politician|Abdel Latif Boghdadi (politician)}}

'''Abd al-Latif al-Baghdadi''' or '''Abdallatif al-Baghdadi''' ({{lang-ar|عبداللطيف البغدادي}}, 1162 in [[Baghdad]]–1231), short for '''Muwaffaq al-Din Muhammad Abd al-Latif ibn Yusuf al-Baghdadi''' ({{lang-ar|موفق الدين محمد عبد اللطيف بن يوسف البغدادي}}), was a [[Islamic medicine|physician]], [[Historiography of early Islam|historian]], [[Egyptologist]] and traveler, and one of the most voluminous writers of the [[Near East]] in his time.&lt;ref&gt;[[Chambers Biographical Dictionary]], {{ISBN|0-550-18022-2}}, page 3&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biography==
Many details of Abd al-Latif's life are known from his autobiography. As a young man, he studied grammar, law, tradition, medicine, alchemy and philosophy. He focused his studies on ancient authors, in particular [[Aristotle]], after first adopting [[Avicenna]] as his philosophical mentor at the suggestion of a wandering scholar from the [[Maghreb]]. He traveled extensively and resided for a while in [[Mosul]] (in 1189) where he studied the works of al-Suhrawardi before traveling on to [[Damascus]] (1190) and the camp of [[Saladin]] outside [[Acre, Israel|Acre]] (1191). It was at the latter location that he met Baha’ al-Din Ibn Shaddad and ‘Imad al-Din al-Isfahani and acquired the [[qadi]] al-Fadil's patronage. He went on to [[Cairo]], where he met Abu'l-Qasim al-Shari'i, who introduced him to the works of al-Farabi, [[Alexander of Aphrodisias]], and [[Themistius]] and (according to al-Latif) turned him away from Avicenna and alchemy.{{sfnm|Leaman|2015|1p=44|Meri|2005|2p=2}}

He met Saladin himself in 1192 in [[Jerusalem]], then went to Damascus again before returning to Cairo. In later years he again journeyed to Jerusalem and to Damascus in 1207-8, and eventually made his way via [[Aleppo]] to [[Erzindjan]], where he remained at the court of Ala’-al-Din Da’ud until the city was conquered by the [[Sultanate of Rum|Seljuk]] ruler [[Kayqubadh]]. ‘Abd al-Latif returned to Baghdad in 1229, travelling back via [[Erzerum]], [[Kamakh]], [[Diwrigi]] and [[Malatiya]]. He died in Baghdad two years later.{{sfnm|Leaman|2015|1p=44|Meri|2005|2p=2}}

==''Account of Egypt''==
Abdullatif was undoubtedly a man of great knowledge and of an inquisitive and penetrating mind. Of the numerous works (mostly on medicine) which Osaiba ascribes to him, one only, his graphic and detailed ''Account of Egypt'' (in two parts), appears to be known in [[Europe]].&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;&gt;{{EB1911|inline=1|wstitle=Abdallatif|volume=1|pages=30-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Archeology===
Abd-al-Latif was well aware of the value of ancient monuments and praised Muslim rulers for preserving and protecting pre-Islamic artifacts and monuments. He noted that the preservation of antiquities presented a number of benefits for Muslims:{{sfn|El Daly|2004|page=10}}
* &quot;monuments are useful historical evidence for chronologies&quot;;
* &quot;they furnish evidence for Holy Scriptures, since the Qur'an mentions them and their people&quot;;
* &quot;they are reminders of human endurance and fate&quot;;
* &quot;they show, to a degree, the politics and history of ancestors, the richness of their sciences, and the genius of their thought&quot;.

While discussing the profession of [[treasure hunting]], he notes that poorer treasure hunters were often sponsored by rich businessmen to go on [[Archeology|archeological]] expeditions. In some cases, an expedition could turn out to be [[fraud]], with the treasure hunter disappearing with large amounts of money extracted from sponsors. This fraudulent practice continues to the present day, with rich businessmen in Egypt still being deceived by local treasure hunters.{{sfn|El Daly|2004| page=36}}

===Egyptology===
This work was one of the earliest works on [[Egyptology]]. It contains a vivid description of a [[famine]] caused, during the author's residence in Egypt, by the [[Nile]] failing to overflow its banks.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; He also wrote detailed descriptions on [[Ancient Egyptian architecture|ancient Egyptian monuments]].{{sfn|El Daly|2004}}

===Autopsy===
Al-Baghdadi wrote that during the famine in Egypt in 597 AH (1200 AD), he had the opportunity to [[observe]] and [[examine]] a large number of [[skeleton]]s. This was one of the earliest examples of a postmortem [[autopsy]], through which he discovered that [[Galen]] was incorrect regarding the formation of the [[bone]]s of the lower [[jaw]] and [[sacrum]].{{sfn|Savage-Smith|1996 |p=951}}

===Translation===
The Arabic manuscript was discovered in 1665 by [[Edward Pococke]] the [[oriental studies|orientalist]], and preserved in the [[Bodleian Library]].&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; He then published the Arabic manuscript in the 1680s. His son, Edward Pococke the Younger, translated the work into [[Latin]], though he was only able to publish less than half of his work. [[Thomas Hunt (professor)|Thomas Hunt]] attempted to publish Pococke's complete translation in 1746, though his attempt was unsuccessful.{{sfn|Toomer|1996|p=272-273}} Pococke's complete Latin translation was eventually published by [[Joseph White (professor)|Joseph White]] of [[University of Oxford|Oxford]] in 1800. The work was then translated into [[French language|French]], with valuable notes, by [[Silvestre de Sacy]] in 1810.{{sfn|Toomer|1996|p=275}}

==Medical works==

===''Al-Mukhtarat fi al-Tibb''===
Al-Baghdadi's ''Mukhtarat fi al-Tibb'' was one of the earliest works on [[hirudotherapy]]. He introduced a more modern use for [[medicinal leech]], stating that leech could be used for cleaning the [[Tissue (biology)|tissues]] after [[Surgery|surgical]] operations. He did, however, understand that there is a risk over using [[leech]], and advised patients that leech need to be cleaned before being used and that the dirt or dust &quot;clinging to a leech should be wiped off&quot; before application. He further writes that after the leech has sucked out the blood, [[salt]] should be &quot;sprinkled on the affected part of the human body&quot;.{{sfn|Deuraseh|2004|p=18}}

===''Medicine from the Book and the Life of the Prophet''===
He wrote a book called ''Al-Tibb min al-Kitab wa-al-Sunna'' (''Medicine from the Book and the Life of the Prophet'') describing the [[Islamic medicine|Islamic medical]] practices from the time of [[Muhammad]].&lt;ref name=Prophet&gt;{{cite web |url=http://tabsir.net/?p=211 |title=The Prophet’s Medicine: Part One |date=June 26, 2007 |last=Varisco |first=Daniel Martin}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Diabetes===
Al-Baghdadi was also the author of a major book dealing with [[diabetes]].&lt;ref name=Prophet/&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite book |last=Bonadeo  |first=Cecilia Martini |title=Abd al-Laṭif al-Baghdadi's Philosophical Journey: from Aristotle's &quot;Metaphysics&quot; to the &quot;Metaphysical Science |publisher=Brill |year=2013  |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=El Daly |first=Okasha |title=Egyptology: The Missing Millennium: Ancient Egypt in Medieval Arabic Writings |publisher=[[Routledge]] |year=2004 |isbn=1-84472-063-2 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal |last=Deuraseh |first=Nurdeen |title=Ahadith of the Prophet on Healing in Three Things (al-Shifa’ fi Thalatha): An Interpretational |journal=Journal of the International Society for the History of Islamic Medicine |year=2004 |volume=3 |number=6 |pages=14–20 |url=https://ishim.net/ishimj/JISHIMoctober2004.pdf}}
*{{cite book|last=Leaman|first=Oliver|title=The Biographical Encyclopedia of Islamic Philosophy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=zpvKBwAAQBAJ|year=2015|publisher=Bloomsbury Academic|isbn=978-1-4725-6944-8|page=44 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Meri|first=Josef W.|title=Medieval Islamic Civilization: An Encyclopedia|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=H-k9oc9xsuAC|year=2005|publisher=Psychology Press|isbn=978-0-415-96690-0|page=2  |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=de Sacy |first=Silvestre |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=pyYVAAAAQAAJ |title=Relation de l'Egypt par Adb al-Latif |location=Paris |date=1810 |language=fr  |ref=harv}}
*{{cite encyclopedia |first=Emilie |last=Savage-Smith |date=1996 |title=Medicine |editor-first=Roshdi |editor-last=Rashed |encyclopedia=[[Encyclopedia of the History of Arabic Science]] |volume=3 |pages=903–962 |publisher=Routledge |location=London  |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |authorlink=G. J. Toomer |last=Toomer |first=G. J. |year=1996 |title=Eastern Wisedome and Learning: The Study of Arabic in Seventeenth-Century England |publisher=Oxford University Press |ISBN=0-19-820291-1 |ref=harv |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/easternwisedomel0000toom }}

{{Medieval Philosophy}}
{{Islamic medicine}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Latif}}
[[Category:1162 births]]
[[Category:1231 deaths]]
[[Category:Writers from Baghdad]]
[[Category:Abbasids]]
[[Category:Medieval Iraqi physicians]]
[[Category:Egyptologists]]
[[Category:Medieval Arab physicians]]
[[Category:Physicians of medieval Islam]]
[[Category:13th-century physicians]]
[[Category:Medieval travel writers]]
[[Category:13th-century people of the Abbasid Caliphate]]
[[Category:12th-century jurists]]
[[Category:13th-century jurists]]</text>
      <sha1>qlqm99vjh4m5roviu4wxllqwqi1rb39</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
