  <page>
    <title>Abba Arikha</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2670</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937955462</id>
      <parentid>937030365</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-28T07:04:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TRM001</username>
        <id>26150594</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>grammar/sentence fluency</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=June 2013}}
{{Eras of the Halakha}}
'''Abba Arikha''' (175–247 [[Common Era|CE]])&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author-last=Sherira Gaon |first= |author-link=Sherira Gaon |title=The Iggeres of Rav Sherira Gaon |translator=Nosson Dovid Rabinowich | publisher=Rabbi Jacob Joseph School Press - Ahavath Torah Institute Moznaim|date=1988 |location=Jerusalem|page=96 |language=en|oclc=923562173 }}&lt;/ref&gt; ([[Jewish Babylonian Aramaic|Talmudic Aramaic]]: {{lang|tmr|אבא אריכא}}; born: ''Rav Abba bar Aybo'', {{lang-he-n|רב אבא בר איבו}}), commonly known as '''Rav''' ({{lang-he-n|רב}}), was a Jewish [[Amoraim|amora]] of the 3rd century. He  was born and lived in [[Kafri]], [[Sassanid Asuristan|Sassanid Babylonia]]. He established at [[Sura (city)|Sura]] the systematic study of the [[rabbinic]] traditions, which, using the [[Mishnah]] as text, led to the compilation of the [[Talmud]]. With him began the long period of ascendancy of the great academies of Babylonia,&lt;ref&gt;{{Harv|Oesterley|Box|1920}}&lt;/ref&gt; around the year 220. In the Talmud, he is frequently associated with [[Samuel of Nehardea]], with whom he debated many issues.

==Biography==
His surname, '''Arikha''' (English, &quot;Long&quot;—that is, &quot;Tall&quot;; it occurs only once—''Hullin'' 137b), he owed to his height, which exceeded that of his contemporaries. Others, reading '''Arekha,''' consider it an honorary title, &quot;Lecturer&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Weiss, ''Dor,'' 3:147; Jastrow, ''Dictionary'' under the word&lt;/ref&gt; In the traditional literature he is referred to almost exclusively as '''Rav''', &quot;the Master&quot;, (both his contemporaries and posterity recognizing in him a master), just as his teacher, [[Judah HaNasi]], was known simply as ''Rabbi''. He is called Rabbi Abba only in the ''[[tannaitic]]'' literature,&lt;ref&gt;For instance, [[Tosefta]] ''Beitzah '' 1:7&lt;/ref&gt; where a number of his sayings are preserved. He occupies a middle position between the ''Tannaim'' and the ''Amoraim'', and is accorded the right, rarely conceded to one who is only an ''amora'', of disputing the opinion of a ''tanna''.&lt;ref&gt;''Bava Batra'' 42a and elsewhere&lt;/ref&gt;

Rav was a descendant of a distinguished Babylonian family which claimed to trace its origin to [[Shimei]], brother of [[King David]].&lt;ref&gt;''Sanhedrin'' 5a; ''Ketubot'' 62b&lt;/ref&gt; His father, Aibo, was a brother of [[Hiyya the Great]] who lived in [[Palestine (region)|Palestine]], and was a highly esteemed scholar in the collegiate circle of the patriarch [[Judah haNasi]]. From his associations in the house of his uncle, and later as his uncle's disciple and as a member of the academy at [[Sepphoris]], Rav acquired such knowledge of the tradition as to make him its foremost exponent in Babylonia. While Judah haNasi was still living, Rav, having been ordained as teacher (with certain restrictions&lt;ref&gt;''Sanhedrin'' 5a&lt;/ref&gt;), returned to [[Babylonia]], where he at once began a career that was destined to mark an epoch in the development of Babylonian Judaism.

In the annals of the Babylonian schools, the year of his arrival is recorded as the starting-point in the chronology of the Talmudic age. It was the 530th year of the [[Seleucid]]an and the 219th year of the [[common era]]. As the scene of his activity, Rav first chose [[Nehardea]], where the [[exilarch]] appointed him ''[[agoranomos]]'', or market-master, and [[Rav Shela|Rabbi Shela]] made him lecturer (''amora'') of his college.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Jerusalem Talmud]] Bava Batra'' 5 15a; ''Yoma'' 20b&lt;/ref&gt; Then he moved to [[Sura (city)|Sura]], on the [[Euphrates]], where he established a school of his own, which soon became the intellectual center of the Babylonian Jews. As a renowned teacher of the Law and with hosts of disciples, who came from all sections of the Jewish world, Rav lived and worked in Sura until his death. [[Samuel of Nehardea|Samuel]], another disciple of Judah haNasi, at the same time brought to the academy at Nehardea a high degree of prosperity; in fact, it was at the school of Rav that Jewish learning in Babylonia found its permanent home and center. Rav's activity made Babylonia independent of Palestine, and gave it that predominant position which it was destined to occupy for several centuries.

Little is known of Rav's personal life. That he was rich seems probable; for he appears to have occupied himself for a time with commerce and afterward with agriculture.&lt;ref&gt;''Hullin'' 105a&lt;/ref&gt; He is referred to as the son of noblemen,&lt;ref&gt;Shabbat 29a&lt;/ref&gt; but it is not clear if this is an affectionate term or a true description of his status. [[Rashi]] does tell us that he is being described as the son of great men. He was highly respected by the [[Gentile]]s as well as by the Jews of Babylonia, as shown by the friendship which existed between him and the last [[Parthia]]n king, [[Artabanus V (of Parthia)|Artaban]].&lt;ref&gt;''Avodah Zarah'' 10b&lt;/ref&gt; He was deeply affected by the death of Artaban (226) and the downfall of the [[Arsacid Empire|Arsacid]] dynasty, and does not appear to have sought the friendship of [[Ardashir I|Ardeshir]], founder of the [[Sassanian]] dynasty, although [[Samuel of Nehardea]] probably did so.

Rav became closely related, through the marriage of one of his daughters, to the family of the exilarch. Her sons, [[Mar Ukba]] and Nehemiah, were considered types of the highest aristocracy. Rav had many sons, several of whom are mentioned in the Talmud, the most distinguished being the eldest, Chiyya. Chiyya did not, however, succeed his father as head of the academy: this post fell to Rav's disciple [[Rav Huna]]. Two of his grandsons occupied in succession the office of [[exilarch]].&lt;ref&gt;''Hullin'' 92a&lt;/ref&gt;

Rav died at an advanced age, deeply mourned by numerous disciples and the entire Babylonian Jewry, which he had raised from comparative insignificance to the leading position in Judaism.&lt;ref&gt;''Shabbat'' 110a, ''Mo'ed Katan'' 24a&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
The method of treatment of the traditional material to which the Talmud owes its origin was established in Babylonia by Rav. That method takes the [[Mishnah]] of [[Judah haNasi]] as a text or foundation, adding to it the other ''tannaitic'' traditions, and deriving from all of them the theoretical explanations and practical applications of the religious Law. The legal and ritual opinions recorded in Rav's name and his disputes with Samuel constitute the main body of the [[Babylonian Talmud]]. His numerous disciples—some of whom were very influential and who, for the most part, were also disciples of Samuel—amplified and, in their capacity as instructors and by their discussions, continued the work of Rav. In the Babylonian schools, Rav was rightly referred to as &quot;our great master.&quot; Rav also exercised a great influence for good upon the moral and religious conditions of his native land, not only indirectly through his disciples, but directly by reason of the strictness with which he repressed abuses in matters of marriage and divorce, and denounced ignorance and negligence in matters of ritual observance.

Rav, says tradition, found an open, neglected field and fenced it in.&lt;ref&gt;''Hullin'' 110a&lt;/ref&gt;

==Teachings==
He gave special attention to the [[liturgy]] of the [[synagogue]]. The [[Aleinu]] prayer first appeared in the manuscript of the [[Rosh Hashana]] liturgy by Rav. He included it in the Rosh Hashana [[mussaf]] service as a prologue to the Kingship portion of the [[Amidah]]. For that reason some attribute to Rav the authorship, or at least the revising, of Aleinu.&lt;ref&gt;Jacobson, B.S., ''The Weekday Siddur: An Exposition and Analysis of its Structure, Contents, Language and Ideas'' (2nd ed, Tel-Aviv, Sinai Publ'g) page 307; Nulman, Macy, ''Encyclopedia of Jewish Prayer'' (1993, NJ, Jason Aronson) page 24.&lt;/ref&gt; In this noble prayer are evinced profound religious feeling and exalted thought, as well as ability to use the [[Hebrew language]] in a natural, expressive, and classical manner.&lt;ref&gt;''Jerusalem Talmud Rosh Hashanah'' 1 57a&lt;/ref&gt;

The many [[homiletic]] and [[ethical]] sayings recorded of him show similar ability. The greatest aggadist among Babylonian ''[[Amoraim]]'', he is the only one of them whose aggadic utterances approach in number and contents those of the Palestinian haggadists. The [[Jerusalem Talmud]] has preserved a large number of his [[halakha|halakhic]] and [[aggadah|aggadic]] utterances; and the Palestinian ''[[Midrashim]]'' also contain many of his ''aggadot''. Rav delivered homiletic discourses, both in the [[beit midrash]] and in the synagogues. He especially loved to discuss in his homilies the events and personages of Biblical history; and many beautiful and genuinely poetic embellishments of the Biblical record, which have become common possession of the [[aggadah]], are his creations. His ''aggadah'' is particularly rich in thoughts concerning the moral life and the relations of human beings to one another. A few of these teachings may be quoted here:
* &quot;The commandments of the [[Torah]] were only given to purify men's morals&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Genesis Rabbah]] 44&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;Whatever may not properly be done in public is forbidden even in the most secret chamber&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Shabbat'' 64b&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;In the future, a person will give a judgement and accounting over everything that his eye saw and he did not eat.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Jerusalem Talmud]], Kiddushin 4:12&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;Whoever lacks pity for his fellow man is no child of [[Abraham]]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Beitzah'' 32b&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;Better to cast oneself into a fiery furnace than to publicly shame one's fellow man.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Bava Metzia'' 59a&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;One should never betroth himself to a woman without having seen her; one might subsequently discover in her a blemish because of which one might loathe her and thus transgress the commandment: 'Thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Kiddushin'' 41a&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;A father should never prefer one child above another; the example of [[Joseph (Hebrew Bible)|Joseph]] shows what evil consequences may result.&quot;
* &quot;While the dates are still in the borders of your skirt, run off with them to the distillery!&quot; [Meaning, before one wastes what he has, let him convert it into something more productive]&lt;ref&gt;''Pesachim'' 113a&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;Receive the payment. Deliver the goods!&quot; [i.e. do not sell on credit]&lt;ref&gt;''Pesachim'' 113a&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;[Better to come] under the displeasure of Ishmael (i.e. the Arabs) than [the displeasure of] Rome; [better to come] under the displeasure of Rome than [the displeasure of] a Persian; [better to come] under the displeasure of a Persian than [the displeasure of] a disciple of the Sages;  [better to come] under the displeasure of a disciple of the Sages than [the displeasure of] an orphan and widow.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.sefaria.org.il/Shabbat.11a.3?lang=bi&amp;with=all&amp;lang2=en Shabbat 11a]&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;A man ought always to occupy himself in the words of the Law, and in the commandments, even if it were not for their own sake. For eventually he will do it for their own sake&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Sanhedrin'' 105b; ''Pesahim'' 50b&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;A man ought always to look about in search of a [good] city whose settlement is only of late, considering that since its settlement is [relatively] new, its iniquities are also few.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Shabbat'' 10b&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;A disciple of the Sages ought to have in him one-eighth of one-eighth of pride, [and no more].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Sotah'' 5a&lt;/ref&gt;

Rav loved the ''Book of Ecclesiasticus'' ([[Sirach]]), and warned his disciple [[Hamnuna]] against unjustifiable asceticism by quoting its advice that considering the transitoriness of human life, one should not despise the good things of this world.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.sefaria.org.il/Eruvin.54a.5?lang=bi&amp;with=all&amp;lang2=en Eruvin 54a]&lt;/ref&gt;

To the celestial joys of the future he was accustomed to refer in the following poetic words: 
:Nothing on earth compares with the future life. In the world to come there shall be neither eating nor drinking, neither trading nor toil, neither hatred nor envy; but the righteous shall sit with crowns upon their heads, and rejoice in the radiance of the Divine Presence.&lt;ref&gt;Berakhot 17a&lt;/ref&gt;

Rav also devoted much attention to [[Mysticism|mystical]] and [[transcendence (religion)|transcendental]] speculations regarding [[Maaseh Breishit and Maaseh Merkavah|Maaseh Bereshit, Maaseh Merkabah]], and the [[Divine name|Divine Name]]. Many of his important utterances testify to his tendency in this direction.&lt;ref&gt;Hagigah 12a, Kiddushin 71a&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Wikisource1911Enc|'Abba 'Arika}}

== References ==
=== Citations ===
{{Reflist}}

=== Sources ===
{{refbegin}}
* {{JewishEncyclopedia |url = http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?letter=A&amp;artid=127 |article=Abba Arika }}
* {{citation |surname1=Oesterley|given1=W. O. E. |surname2=Box |given2=G. H.|title = A Short Survey of the Literature of Rabbinical and Mediæval Judaism |publisher=Burt Franklin |location = New York, NY |year=1920 }}.
{{refbegin}}

{{-}}
{{Amoraim}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Arika, Abba}}
[[Category:175 births]]
[[Category:247 deaths]]
[[Category:Rabbis of Academy of Sura]]</text>
      <sha1>8bwhr4ojiubjv400gctkt7pdkl742yq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
