  <page>
    <title>Abbahu</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2671</id>
    <revision>
      <id>911729513</id>
      <parentid>910922483</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-08-20T19:17:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ar2332</username>
        <id>6077664</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Eras of the Halakha}}
Rabbi '''Abbahu''' ('''{{lang-he|אבהו}}''') was a [[Jew]]ish [[Talmud]]ist who lived in the [[Land of Israel]] from about 279-320 (3rd generation of [[amoraim]]). He is sometimes cited as ''Rabbi Abbahu of Kisrin'' ([[Caesarea]]).

==Biography==
His [[rabbinic]] education was acquired mainly at [[Tiberias]], in the academy presided over by [[R. Johanan]], with whom his relations were almost those of a son.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Yer.|Yerushalmi]] [[Berakhot (Talmud)|Berakhot]]'' 2:1, page 4b in [[Daniel Bomberg]]'s [[Venice]] edition, ([http://hebrewbooks.org/pdfpager.aspx?req=45298&amp;st=&amp;pgnum=6 ירושלמי דפוס ויניציאה (בומבירגי), ברכות דף ד טור ב] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140228230053/http://hebrewbooks.org/pdfpager.aspx?req=45298&amp;st=&amp;pgnum=6 |date=February 28, 2014 }} ), 12b in current editions ([[s:he:ירושלמי ברכות דף יב ב|ירושלמי ברכות דף יב ב]]); ''[[Gittin]]'' 44b ([[s:he:גיטין מד ב|גיטין מד ב]]), ''[[Bava Batra]]'' 39a ([[s:he:בבא בתרא לט א|בבא בתרא לט א]]).&lt;/ref&gt; He frequently made pilgrimages to Tiberias, even after he had become well known as [[Rector (academia)|rector]] of the Caesarean academy.&lt;ref&gt;''Yerushalmi [[Shab.|Shabbat]]'' 8:1, page 11a in Bomberg's Venice edition ([http://hebrewbooks.org/pdfpager.aspx?req=45298&amp;st=&amp;pgnum=150 ירושלמי דפוס ויניציאה (בומבירגי), שבת דף יא טור א] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141006152939/http://hebrewbooks.org/pdfpager.aspx?req=45298&amp;st=&amp;pgnum=150 |date=October 6, 2014 }}), 54b in current editions ([[s:he:ירושלמי שבת דף נד ב|ירושלמי שבת דף נד ב]]); Yerushalmi ''[[Pesahim]]'' 10:1, page 37c in Bomberg's Venice edition ([http://hebrewbooks.org/pdfpager.aspx?req=45298&amp;st=&amp;pgnum=203&amp;hilite= ירושלמי דפוס ויניציאה (בומבירגי), פסחים דף לז טור ג] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160305012152/http://hebrewbooks.org/pdfpager.aspx?req=45298&amp;st=&amp;pgnum=203&amp;hilite= |date=March 5, 2016 }}).&lt;/ref&gt;

Abbahu was an authority on weights and measures.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Yer.|Yerushalmi]] [[Terumot]]'' 5:3 page 43c in Bomberg's Venice edition ([http://hebrewbooks.org/pdfpager.aspx?req=45298&amp;st=&amp;pgnum=85 ירושלמי דפוס ויניציאה (בומבירגי), תרומות דף מג טור ג] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141006071556/http://hebrewbooks.org/pdfpager.aspx?req=45298&amp;st=&amp;pgnum=85 |date=October 6, 2014 }}; 5:1 in current editions&lt;/ref&gt; He encouraged the study of [[Greek language|Greek]] by [[Jew]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;&gt;{{EB1911|inline=1|wstitle='Abbahu|volume=1|page=9}}&lt;/ref&gt; He learned Greek himself in order to become useful to his people, then under the [[Roman Empire|Roman]] ''[[proconsul]]s'', that language having become, to a considerable extent, the rival of the [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] even in prayer.&lt;ref&gt;''Yerushalmi [[Sotah (Talmud)|Sotah]]'' chapter 7, 21b&lt;/ref&gt; In spite of the bitter protest of [[Shimon bar Abba]], he also taught his daughters Greek.&lt;ref&gt;''Yerushalmi Shabbat'' chapter 6, 7d; ''Yerushalmi Sotah'' chapter 9, 24c; ''[[Sanhedrin (tractate)|Sanhedrin]]'' 14a&lt;/ref&gt; Indeed, it was said of Abbahu that he was a living illustration of the Biblical maxim,&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleverse||Ecclesiastes|7:18|HE}}; compare [[Targum Onkelos|Targum]]&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;It is good that you should take hold of this [the study of the Law]; yea, also from that [other branches of knowledge] withdraw not your hand: for he that fears God shall come forth of them all&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Ecclesiastes Rabbah]]'' to 7:18&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rector in Caesarea===
Being wise, handsome, and wealthy,&lt;ref&gt;''[[Bava Metzia]]'' 84a; ''Yerushalmi Bava Metzia'' chapter 4, 9d&lt;/ref&gt; Abbahu became not only popular with his coreligionists, but also influential with the proconsular government.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Hagigah]]'' 14a; ''[[Ketubot]]'' 17a&lt;/ref&gt; On one occasion, when his senior colleagues, [[Hiyya bar Abba]], [[Rabbi Ammi]], and [[Rabbi Assi]], had punished a certain woman, and feared the wrath of the proconsul, Abbahu was deputed to intercede for them. He had, however, anticipated the rabbis' request, and wrote them that he had appeased the informers but not the accuser. The witty enigmatic letter describing this incident, preserved in the Talmud,&lt;ref&gt;''Yerushalmi [[Meg.|Megillah]]'' chapter 3, 74a&lt;/ref&gt; is in the main pure Hebrew, and even includes Hebrew translations of Greek proper names, to avoid the danger of possible exposure should the letter have fallen into the hands of enemies and informers.&lt;ref&gt;Compare ''[[Eruvin (tractate)|Eruvin]]'' 53b&lt;/ref&gt;

After his ordination he declined a teacher's position, recommending in his stead a more needy friend, [[R. Abba of Acre]], as worthier than himself.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Sotah (Talmud)|Sotah]]'' 40a&lt;/ref&gt; He thereby illustrated his own doctrine that it is a divine virtue to sympathize with a friend in his troubles as well as to partake of his joys.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Tan.]]'', ''[[Vayeshev|Wa-yesheb]]'', ed. [[Salomon Buber|Buber]], 16&lt;/ref&gt; Later he assumed the office of rector in Caesarea, the former seat of [[Hoshaiah Rabbah]], and established himself at the so-called Kenishta Maradta (Insurrectionary Synagogue);&lt;ref&gt;''Yerushalmi [[Nazir (Talmud)|Nazir]]'' chapter 7, 56a; ''Yerushalmi [[San.|Sanhedrin]]'' chapter 1, 18a; compare [[Josephus]], ''B. J.'' ii. 14, § 5; [[Marcus Jastrow|Jastrow]], ''Dict.'' p.&amp;nbsp;838&lt;/ref&gt; from which some of the most prominent teachers of the next generation issued. In Caesarea he originated several ritual rules,&lt;ref&gt;''Yerushalmi [[Demai (tractate)|Demai]]'' chapter 2, 23a, ''[[Rosh Hashanah (tractate)|R.H.]]'' 34a&lt;/ref&gt; one of which (that regulating the sounding of the [[shofar]]) has since been universally adopted, and is referred to by [[rishonim]] as &quot;the Enactment of R. Abbahu&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''Takkanat R. Abbahu''&quot;; compare ''[[Maḥzor Vitry]]'', [[Berlin]], 1893, p.&amp;nbsp;355&lt;/ref&gt;

He did not confine his activity to Caesarea, but also visited and taught in many other Jewish towns.&lt;ref&gt;''Yerushalmi Berakhot'' chapter 8, 12a; ''Yerushalmi Shabbat'' chapter 3, 5c&lt;/ref&gt; On these journeys, Abbahu gathered so many ''[[halakhot]]'' that scholars turned to him for information on mooted questions.&lt;ref&gt;''Yerushalmi Shabbat'' chapter 8, 11a; ''Yerushalmi [[Yevamot]]'' chapter 1, 2d&lt;/ref&gt; In the course of these travels he made a point of complying with all local enactments, even where such compliance laid him open to the charge of inconsistency.&lt;ref&gt;''Yerushalmi Berakhot'' chapter 8, 12a; ''Yerushalmi [[Beitzah]]'' chapter 1, 60d&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, where circumstances required it, he did not spare even the princes of his people.&lt;ref&gt;''Yerushalmi [[Avodah Zarah]]'' chapter 1, 39b&lt;/ref&gt; Where, however, the rigorous exposition of laws worked hardship on the masses, he did not scruple to modify the decisions of his colleagues for the benefit of the community.&lt;ref&gt;''Shabbat'' 134b; ''Yerushalmi Shabbat'' chapter 17, 16b; ''Yerushalmi [[Mo'ed Katan]]'' chapter 1, 80b&lt;/ref&gt; As for himself, he was very strict in the observance of the laws. Once he ordered some [[Samaritan]] wine, but subsequently hearing that the Samaritans no longer strict observed the dietary laws, with the assistance of his colleagues ([[Hiyya bar Abba]], Rabbi Ammi, and Rabbi Assi) he investigated the report, and, ascertaining it to be well founded, ruled the Samaritans to be equivalent to [[Gentiles]] for all ritual purposes.&lt;ref&gt;''Yerushalmi Avodah Zarah'' chapter 5, 44d; ''[[Hullin]]'' [https://www.sefaria.org.il/Chullin.6a.6?lang=bi&amp;with=all&amp;lang2=he 6a]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Abbahu and Hiyya bar Abba===
R. Abbahu's chief characteristic seems to have been modesty. While lecturing in different towns, he met R. [[Hiyya bar Abba]], who was lecturing on intricate ''[[halakhic]]'' themes. As Abbahu delivered popular sermons, the masses naturally crowded to hear him, and deserted the halakhist. At this apparent slight, R. Hiyya manifested chagrin, and R. Abbahu hastened to comfort him by comparing himself to the pedler of glittering fineries that always attracted the eyes of the masses, while his rival was a trader in precious stones, the virtues and values of which were appreciated only by the connoisseur. This speech not having the desired effect, R. Abbahu showed special respect for his slighted colleague by following him for the remainder of that day. &quot;What,&quot; said Abbahu, &quot;is my modesty as compared with that of R. [[Abba of Acre]], who does not even remonstrate with his interpreter for interpolating his own comments in the lecturer's expositions.&quot; When his wife reported to him that his interpreter's wife had boasted of her own husband's greatness, R. Abbahu simply said, &quot;What difference does it make which of us is really the greater, so long as through both of us heaven is glorified?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''[[Sotah (Talmud)|Sotah]]'' 40a&lt;/ref&gt; His principle of life he expressed in the maxim,

{{quote|Let man ever be of the persecuted, and not of the persecutors; for there are none among the birds more persecuted than turtle-doves and pigeons, and the [[Scriptures]] declare them worthy of the [[Altar (Bible)|altar]].&lt;ref&gt;''[[Bava Kamma]]'' 93a&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Later years===
Abbahu had two sons, Zeira and Hanina. Some writers ascribe to him a third son, Abimi.&lt;ref&gt;[[Wilhelm Bacher|Bacher]], ''Agada der Babylonischen Amoräer''&lt;/ref&gt; Abbahu sent Hanina to the academy at Tiberias, where he himself had studied, but the youth occupied himself with the [[burial]] of the dead, and on hearing of this, the father sent him a reproachful message in this laconic style: &quot;Is it because there are no graves in [[Caesarea]]&lt;ref&gt;Compare [[Book of Exodus|Exodus]] 14:11&lt;/ref&gt; that I have sent you off to Tiberias? Study must precede practice&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Yerushalmi Pesahim'' chapter 3, 30b&lt;/ref&gt; Abbahu left behind him a number of disciples, the most prominent among whom were the leaders of the 4th amoraic generation, [[R. Jonah]] and [[R. Jose]]. At Abbahu's death the mourning was so great that it was said, &quot;Even the statues of Caesarea shed tears&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Mo'ed Katan]]'' 25b; ''Yerushalmi Avodah Zarah'' chapter 3, 42c&lt;/ref&gt;

== Against the Christians ==

R. Abbahu, though eminent as a halakhist, was more distinguished as an [[aggadist]] and controversialist. He had many interesting disputes with the [[Christians]] of his day.&lt;ref&gt;''Shabbat'' 152b; ''[[San.|Sanhedrin]]'' 39a; ''[[Avodah Zarah]]'' 4a&lt;/ref&gt; Sometimes these disputes were of a humorous nature. Thus, a heretic bearing the name of Sason (=Joy) once remarked to him, &quot;In the [[Olam Haba|next world]] your people will have to draw water for me; for thus it is written in the [[Bible]],&lt;ref&gt;[[Isaiah]] 12:3&lt;/ref&gt; 'With joy shall ye draw water.'&quot; To this R. Abbahu replied, &quot;Had the Bible said 'for joy' [''le-sason''], it would mean as you say, but since it says 'with joy' [''be-sason''], it means that we shall make bottles of your skin and fill them with water&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Suk.|Sukkah]]'' 48b&lt;/ref&gt; These controversies, though forced on him, provoked resentment, and it is even related that his physician, Jacob the [[Jewish schisms|Schismatic]] (''Minaah''), was slowly poisoning him, but [[R. Ammi]] and [[R. Assi]] discovered the crime in time.&lt;ref&gt;''Avodah Zarah'' 28a&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[Christians|Christian]] (''Minaah'') once asked Abbahu &quot;When does your Messiah come?&quot; in a tone of mockery. Abbahu replied: &quot;When you will be wrapped in darkness, for it says,&lt;ref&gt;[[Isaiah]] 60:2&lt;/ref&gt; 'Behold, darkness shall cover the earth, and gross darkness the nations; then shall the Lord rise upon you and His glory shall be seen on you'.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Sanhedrin'' 99a&lt;/ref&gt; A Christian came to Abbahu with the quibbling question: &quot;How could your God in His priestly holiness bury [[Moses]] without providing for purificatory rites, yet oceans are declared insufficient?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Isaiah 40:12&lt;/ref&gt; Abbahu replied: &quot;Does it not say, 'The Lord comes with fire'&lt;ref&gt;Isaiah 64:15&lt;/ref&gt;? Fire is the true element of purification, according to [[Book of Numbers|Numbers]] 31:23.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Sanhedrin'' 39a&lt;/ref&gt; Another question of the same character: &quot;Why the boastful claim, 'What nation on earth is like Your people Israel',&lt;ref&gt;II [[Books of Samuel|Samuel]] 7:23&lt;/ref&gt; since we read, 'All the nations are as nothing before Him'?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Isaiah 40:17&lt;/ref&gt; Abbahu replied: &quot;Do we not read of Israel, he 'shall not be reckoned among the nations'?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Sanhedrin'' as above&lt;/ref&gt;

Abbahu made a notable exception with reference to the [[Tosefta]]'s statement that the ''[[Gilyonim]]'' M(Evangels) and other books of the heretics (''Minnin'') are not to be saved from a fire on [[Shabbat]]: &quot;the books of those [written by ''Minnin'' for the purpose of debating with Jews] at Abidan may or may not be saved.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Shabbat 116a [[s:he:שבת קטז א|שבת קטז א]] and [[Rashi]]'s commentary (in Hebrew/Aramaic)&lt;/ref&gt; In regard to the line &quot;''Barukh Shem Kevod Malkhuto''&quot; (Blessed be the Name of His glorious Kingdom) recited after the [[Shema Yisrael|Shema]], Abbahu says that in Palestine, where the Christians look for points of controversy, the words should be recited aloud (lest the Jews be accused of silently tampering with the unity of God proclaimed in the ''Shema''), whereas in the Babylonian city of [[Nehardea]], where there are no Christians, the words are recited with a low voice.&lt;ref&gt;''Pesachim'' 56a, [[s:he:פסחים נו א|פסחים נו א]] and Rashi's commentary (in Hebrew/Aramaic)&lt;/ref&gt; Preaching directly against the Christian dogma, Abbahu says: &quot;A king of flesh and blood may have a father, a brother, or a son to share in or dispute his sovereignty, but the Lord says, 'I am the Lord your God! I am the first - that is, I have no father; and I am the last - that is, I have no brother; and besides me there is no God - that is, I have no son'&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Isaiah 44:6; ''[[Exodus Rabbah]]'' 29&lt;/ref&gt; His comment on Numbers 23:19 has a still more polemical tone:&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish&quot;&gt;{{Jewish Encyclopedia|inline=1|article=Abbahu|author=|url=http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?letter=A&amp;artid=164|accessdate=June 18, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;God is not a man that he should lie; neither the son of man, that he should repent; if a man says: 'I am God,' he is a liar; if he says: 'I am a son of man,' he will have cause to regret it; and if he says, 'I will go up to heaven,' he has said [''something''] but will not keep his word&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Yerushalmi [[Ta'anit]]'' 2:1, end, page 65b in Bomberg's Venice edition;[http://hebrewbooks.org/pdfpager.aspx?req=45298&amp;st=&amp;pgnum=258&amp;hilite= ירושלמי דפוס ויניציאה (בומבירגי), תעניות דף סה טור ב] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160305073458/http://hebrewbooks.org/pdfpager.aspx?req=45298&amp;st=&amp;pgnum=258&amp;hilite= |date=March 5, 2016 }} (in Hebrew/Aramaic); 9a in current editions [[s:he:ירושלמי תענית דף ט א|ירושלמי תענית דף ט א]] (in Hebrew/Aramaic)&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of his controversies on Christian theological subjects, as on [[Adam (Bible)|Adam]],&lt;ref&gt;[[Yalkut Shimoni]]'', Genesis 47&lt;/ref&gt; on [[Enoch (ancestor of Noah)|Enoch]],&lt;ref&gt;''[[Genesis Rabbah]]'' 25&lt;/ref&gt; and on the resurrection,&lt;ref&gt;''Shabbat'' 152b&lt;/ref&gt; are less clear and direct.&lt;ref&gt;See Bacher, ''Agada der Pal. Amor.'' ii. 97, 115-118&lt;/ref&gt;

== Other Abbahus ==
There are several other Abbahus mentioned in the [[Talmud]]im and [[Midrashim]], prominent among whom is Abbahu (Abuha, Aibut) b. Ihi (Ittai), a [[Jews of Babylonia|Babylonian]] halakhist, contemporary of [[Samuel of Nehardea|Samuel]] and [[Anan (amora)|Anan]],&lt;ref&gt;''[[Eruvin (tractate)|Eruvin]]'' 74a&lt;/ref&gt; and brother of Minyamin (Benjamin) bar Ihi. While this Abbahu repeatedly applied to Samuel for information, Samuel in return learned many halakhot from him.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Naz.|Nazir]]'' 24b; ''[[Bava Metzia]]'' 14a; 75a&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}
{{Jewish Encyclopedia|inline=1|article=Abbahu|author=|url=http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?letter=A&amp;artid=164|accessdate=June 18, 2013}} It has the following bibliography:
*[[Grätz, Gesch.]] d. Juden, 2d ed., iv. 304, 307-317;
* Jost, ''Gesch. des Judenthums und seiner Sekten'', ii.161-164;
* Frankel, ''Mebo'', pp.&amp;nbsp;58a-60;
* [[Weiss, Dor|Weiss]], ''Dor'', iii. 103-105;
* Bacher, ''Ag. Pal. Amor.'' ii. 88-142.


{{Amoraim}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Abbahu}}
[[Category:Talmud rabbis of the Land of Israel]]
[[Category:Caesarea (Israel)]]
[[Category:Year of birth unknown]]
[[Category:Year of death unknown]]</text>
      <sha1>gpq0tujfz7aus92uh316vnwf6aifjvk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
