  <page>
    <title>Aedui</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2622</id>
    <revision>
      <id>915151695</id>
      <parentid>912482981</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-09-11T14:37:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>PedjaNbg</username>
        <id>12405445</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Added free to read link in citations with [[WP:OABOT|OAbot]] #oabot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Classical age Gaulic people}}{{distinguish|Aedi}}
The '''Aedui''', '''Haedui''', or '''Hedui''' ({{lang-grc|Αἰδούοι}}) were a [[Gauls|Gallic]] people of [[Gallia Lugdunensis]], who inhabited the country between the Arar ([[Saône]]) and Liger ([[Loire]]), in today's France. Their territory thus included the greater part of the modern departments of [[Saône-et-Loire]], [[Côte-d'Or]] and [[Nièvre]].&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;&gt;{{EB1911|inline=1|wstitle=Aedui|volume=1|pages=244–245}} This cites:
* A. E. Desjardins, ''Géographie de la Gaule'', ii. (1876&amp;ndash;1893)
* [[T. Rice Holmes|T. R. Holmes]], ''Caesar's Conquest of Gaul'' (1899).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Geography==
The country of the Aedui is defined by reports of them in ancient writings. The upper [[Loire]] formed their western border,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Caesar|BG|loc=Book vii, Section 5}}.&lt;/ref&gt; separating them from the [[Bituriges]]. The [[Saône]] formed their eastern border, separating them from the [[Sequani]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Caesar|BG|loc=Book I, Section 12}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The Sequani did not reside in the region of the confluence of the [[Doubs]] into the Saône and of the latter into the [[Rhône]], as Caesar says that the [[Helvetii]], following the pass between the [[Jura Mountains]] and the Rhône southwards, which belonged to the Sequani, plundered the territory of the Aedui.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Caesar|BG|loc=Book I, Section 11}}.&lt;/ref&gt; These circumstances explain an apparent contradiction in [[Strabo]], who in one sentence says that the Aedui lived between the Saône and the Doubs, and in the next, that the Sequani lived across the Saône (eastward).&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Strabo|Geography|loc=Book 4, Chapter 3, Section 2}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Both statements are true, the first in the south, and the second to the north.

==History==
[[File:Eduens denier 1st century BCE 1940mg.jpg|thumb|[[Denarius]] of the Aedui, 1st century BCE, 1940mg. [[Hotel de la Monnaie]].]]

Outside of the Roman province and prior to Roman rule, Independent Gaul was occupied by self-governing tribes divided into cantons, and each canton was further divided into communes.  The Aedui, like other powerful tribes in the region (the [[Arverni]], the [[Sequani]], and the [[Helvetii]]), had replaced their monarchy with a council of magistrates called grand-judges.  The grand-judges were under the authority of the senate. The senate was made up of the descendants of ancient royal families. Free men in the tribes were [[vassals]] to the heads of these families in exchange for military, financial and political interests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Malleson|first1=G.B.|title=Vercingetorix|journal=Transactions of the Royal Historical Society|date=1889|volume=4|pages=1–40|doi=10.2307/3678158|jstor=3678158|url=https://zenodo.org/record/1449763/files/article.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[Livy]] (v. 34), they took part in the expedition of [[Bellovesus]] into Italy in the 6th century BC.

Before [[Julius Caesar]]'s time, they had attached themselves to the [[Ancient Rome|Romans]] and were honoured with the title of brothers and kinsmen of the Roman people.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Caesar|BG|loc=Book I, Section 33}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

When the [[Sequani]], their hereditary rivals, with the assistance of a [[Germanic peoples|Germanic]] chieftain named [[Ariovistus]], defeated and massacred the Aedui at the [[Battle of Magetobriga]], the Aedui sent [[Diviciacus (Aedui)|Diviciacus]], the [[Druidry|druid]], to Rome to appeal to the [[Roman Senate|senate]] for help, but his mission was unsuccessful.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

On his arrival in [[Gaul]] (58 BC), Caesar restored their independence. In spite of this, the Aedui joined the Gallic coalition against Caesar (''B. G.'' vii. 42), but after the surrender of [[Vercingetorix]] at the [[Battle of Alesia]], were glad to return to their allegiance. [[Caesar Augustus|Augustus]] dismantled{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}} their native capital [[Bibracte]] on [[Mont Beuvray]] and substituted a new town with a half-Roman, half-Gaulish name, Augustodunum (modern [[Autun]]).

In 21, during the reign of [[Tiberius]], they revolted under [[Julius Sacrovir]], and seized [[Augustodunum]], but they were soon put down by Gaius Silius ([[Gaius Cornelius Tacitus|Tacitus]] ''[[Annals (Tacitus)|Ann.]]'' iii. 43-46). The Aedui were the first of the Gauls to receive from the emperor [[Claudius]] the distinction of ''[[jus honorum]]'', thus being the first Gauls permitted to become senators.&lt;ref name=&quot;test&quot;&gt;Peoples, Nations and Cultures. General Editor Prof John Mackenzie. Weidenfeld and Nicolson. 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

The oration of [[Eumenius]], in which he pleaded for the restoration of the schools of his native place [[Augustodunum]], shows that the district was neglected. The chief magistrate of the Aedui in Caesar's time was called [[Vergobret]]us (according to [[Theodor Mommsen|Mommsen]], &quot;judgment-worker&quot;), who was elected annually, possessed powers of life and death but was forbidden to go beyond the frontier. Certain clientes, or small communities, were also dependent upon the Aedui.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

It is possible that the Aedui adopted many of the governmental practices of the Romans, such as electing magistrates and other officials or perhaps it was a natural development in their political system. It is thought that other Celtic tribes, such as the [[Remi]] and the [[Baiocasses]], also elected their leaders.{{Citation needed|date=November 2008}}

==See also==
* [[List of peoples of Gaul]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==Bibliography==
* 
* {{cite book |first=Julius |last=Caesar |authorlink=Julius Caesar |title=De Bello Gallico |ref=CITEREFCaesarBG|title-link=De Bello Gallico }}
* {{cite book |author=Strabo |authorlink=Strabo |title=Geography |ref=CITEREFStraboGeography}}
*A. E. Desjardins, ''Geographie de la Gaule'', ii. (1876–1893)
*[[T. Rice Holmes]], ''Caesar's Conquest of Gaul'' (1899).
{{Celts}}
{{Peoples of Gaul}}

[[Category:Aedui| ]]
[[Category:Historical Celtic peoples]]
[[Category:Gauls]]
[[Category:Tribes involved in the Gallic Wars]]</text>
      <sha1>bz9s1wlg15z6o1w9nhcsoiuekgo5o8u</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
