  <page>
    <title>Aelianus Tacticus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2634</id>
    <revision>
      <id>928683258</id>
      <parentid>927581143</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-11-30T23:58:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2605:6000:1019:6021:DDE5:C36A:E390:1015</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>The pronunciation guide to the Greek was keyed to modern Greek, which is not at all the same as ancient Greek. Likewise, the accentuation observed modern Greek rules, which are not the same as their ancient counterparts.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|2nd-century Greek military writer}}
{{for|the Roman writer|Claudius Aelianus}}
[[File:Houghton MS Richardson 16 - Tacticus Aelianus.jpg|thumb|''In hoc codice continentur Helianus De instruendis aciebus et Onosander De optimo imperatore'', ca. 1480, by Aelianus Tacticus]]
'''Aelianus Tacticus''' ({{lang-grc-gre|Αἰλιανός ὀ Τακτικός}}; fl. 2nd century AD), also known as '''Aelian''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|iː|l|i|ən}}), was a [[Hellenistic Greece|Greek]] [[military]] writer who lived in [[ancient Rome|Rome]].

==Work==
Aelian's military treatise in fifty-three chapters on the tactics of the Greeks, titled ''On Tactical Arrays of the Greeks'' ({{lang|grc|Περί Στρατηγικών Τάξεων Ἑλληνικών}}), is dedicated to the [[Roman Emperor|Emperor]] [[Hadrian]], though this is probably a mistake for [[Trajan]], and the date 106 has been assigned to it. It is a handbook of Greek, i.e. [[Macedon]]ian, [[parade (military)|drill]] and [[military tactics|tactics]] as practiced by the [[Hellenistic Greece|Hellenistic]] successors of [[Alexander the Great]]. The author claims to have consulted all the best authorities, the most important of which was a lost treatise on the subject by [[Polybius]]. Perhaps the chief value of Aelian's work lies in his critical account of preceding works on the art of [[war]], and in the fullness of his technical details in matters of drill.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;&gt;{{EB1911|inline=1 |wstitle=Aelian (Aelianus Tacticus) |display=Aelian |volume=1 |page=256}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Aelian also gives a brief account of the constitution of a Roman army at that time. The work arose, he says, from a conversation he had with the emperor [[Nerva]] at [[Frontinus]]'s house at [[Formiae]]. He promises a work on Naval Tactics also; but this, if it was written, is lost.&lt;ref name=&quot;dgrbm&quot;&gt;{{Citation  | last = Allen  | first = Alexander  | contribution = Aelianus Tacitus  | editor-last = Smith | editor-first = William  | title = [[Dictionary of Greek and Roman Biography and Mythology]]  | volume = 1  | page = 29  | place = Boston  | year = 1867  | contribution-url = http://www.ancientlibrary.com/smith-bio/0038.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Critics of the 18th century &amp;mdash; Guichard Folard and the Prince de Ligne &amp;mdash; were unanimous in thinking Aelian greatly inferior to [[Arrian]], but Aelian exercised a great influence both on his immediate successors, the [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine]]s, and later on the [[Arab]]s, (who translated the text for their own use). The author of the [[Strategikon of Maurice|''Strategikon'']] ascribed to the Emperor [[Maurice (emperor)|Maurice]] selectively used Aelian's work as a conceptional model, especially its preface.&lt;ref&gt;P. Rance, [https://www.academia.edu/35840787/_Maurice_s_Strategicon_and_the_Ancients_the_Late_Antique_Reception_of_Aelian_and_Arrian_in_P._RANCE_and_N.V._SEKUNDA_edd._Greek_Taktika._Ancient_Military_Writing_and_its_Heritage_Gdańsk_2017_217-255 &quot;Maurice's ''Strategicon'' and the Ancients: the Late Antique Reception of Aelian and Arrian&quot;] in P. Rance and N.V. Sekunda (edd.), ''Greek Taktika. Ancient Military Writing and its Heritage'' (Gdańsk 2017) 217-255.&lt;/ref&gt; Emperor [[Leo VI the Wise]] incorporated much of Aelian's text in his own [[Tactica of Emperor Leo VI the Wise|''Taktika'']]. The Arabic version of Aelian was made about 1350.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt; It was first translated into Latin by Theodore Gaza, published at Rome in 1487.&lt;ref name=&quot;dgrbm&quot;/&gt; The Greek editio princeps was edited by Francesco Robortello and published at Venice in 1552.

In spite of its academic nature, the copious details to be found in the treatise rendered it of the highest value to the army organisers of the 16th century, who were engaged in fashioning a regular military system out of the semi-[[feudal]] systems of previous generations. The [[Macedonian phalanx]] of Aelian had many points of resemblance to the solid masses of [[pikemen]] and the [[Squadron (cavalry)|squadrons]] of [[cavalry]] of the [[Spain|Spanish]] and [[Netherlands|Dutch]] systems, and the translations made in the 16th century formed the groundwork of numerous books on drill and tactics.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB1911&quot;/&gt;

The first significant reference to the influence of Aelian in the 16th century is a letter to [[Maurice of Nassau, Prince of Orange]] from his cousin [[William Louis, Count of Nassau-Dillenburg]] on December 8, 1594. The letter is influential in supporting the thesis of the early-modern [[Military Revolution]]. In the letter, William Louis discusses the use of ranks by soldiers of Imperial Rome as discussed in Aelian's Tactica. Aelian was discussing the use of the counter march in the context of the Roman sword [[gladius]] and spear [[pilum]]. William Louis in a 'crucial leap' realised that the same technique could work for men with firearms.&lt;ref&gt;Parker, Geoffrey &quot;Military Revolutions, Past and Present&quot; in ''Recent Themes in Military History''. Ed Donald A Yerxa. University of South Carolina Press 2008 p. 13&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Sources==
*{{SmithDGRBM|title= Aelianus Tacitus}}
*{{Cite book|author=Aelian |editor=Henry Augustus |title=The Tactics of Aelian |publisher=Cox and Baylis |location=London |publication-date=1814 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=khVicgAACAAJ&amp;dq=the+tactics+of+aelian&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=6FQrU8T_B8-9oQTosYKoCg&amp;ved=0CDMQ6AEwAQ}}

{{Authority control}}


[[Category:Ancient Greek writers]]
[[Category:Roman-era Greeks]]
[[Category:2nd-century writers]]
[[Category:Ancient Macedonian army]]
[[Category:Ancient Greek military writers]]
[[Category:2nd-century Greek people]]</text>
      <sha1>ghx8i2d5ovspmtfeje7u8nxb8xfe6a7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
