  <page>
    <title>Draupnir</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8326</id>
    <revision>
      <id>930934717</id>
      <parentid>930934652</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-12-15T23:20:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Goustien</username>
        <id>4440889</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>already in subcategory</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Gold ring possessed by the god Odin in Norse mythology}}
{{Other uses}}
[[File:The third gift — an enormous hammer by Elmer Boyd Smith.jpg|thumb|''The third gift — an enormous hammer'' (1902) by [[Elmer Boyd Smith]]. The ring Draupnir is visible among other creations by the [[Sons of Ivaldi]].]]
In [[Norse mythology]], '''Draupnir''' ([[Old Norse]] &quot;the dripper&quot;&lt;ref name=ORCHARD34&gt;Orchard (1997:34).&lt;/ref&gt;) is a gold ring possessed by the god [[Odin]] with the ability to multiply itself: Every ninth night, eight new rings 'drip' from Draupnir, each one of the same size and weight as the original.

Draupnir was forged by the [[Norse dwarves|dwarven]] brothers [[Brokkr]] and [[Eitri]] (or [[Sindri (mythology)|Sindri]]). Brokkr and Eitri made this ring as one of a set of three gifts which included [[Mjöllnir]] and [[Gullinbursti]]. They made these gifts in accordance with a wager [[Loki]] made saying that Brokkr and Eitri could not make better gifts than the three made by the [[Sons of Ivaldi]]. In the end, [[Mjöllnir]], [[Thor]]'s hammer, won the contest for Brokkr and Eitri. Loki used a [[loophole]] to get out of the wager for his head (the wager was for Loki's head only, but he argued that, to remove his head, they would have to injure his neck, which was not in the bargain) and Brokkr punished him by sealing his lips shut with wire.

The ring was placed by Odin on the funeral pyre of his son [[Baldr]]:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Odin laid upon the pyre the gold ring called Draupnir; this quality attended it: that every ninth night there fell from it eight gold rings of equal weight. (from the ''[[Gylfaginning]]'').
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The ring was subsequently retrieved by [[Hermóðr]]. It was offered as a gift by [[Freyr]]'s servant [[Skírnir]] in the wooing of [[Gerðr]], which is described in the poem ''[[Skírnismál]]''.

==In popular culture==

Draupnir is represented as a card in the [[Yu-Gi-Oh Trading Card Game]]. It has an effect that mimics the multiplication ability of the mythological version. If it is destroyed by another card's effect, you can add another &quot;Nordic Relic&quot; card to your hand. The art represents it as an arm brace, with another brace seemingly growing from it, once again mimicking the story.

''DRAUPNIR'' was revealed as the key to a website that [[Neal Caffrey]] and [[Mozzie (White Collar)|Mozzie]] used to view their stolen Nazi U-boat treasure in &quot;Taking Account&quot;, the seventh episode of the third season of ''[[White Collar (TV series)|White Collar]]''.

It also appeared in episode 11 of ''[[Saint Seiya: Soul of Gold]]'' as a tool to seal Loki's spirit.

The Draupnir is never called by name but is simply known as Odin's ring in the first three books of the [[Witches of East End]] novels. This rings allows the wearer to teleport to any place of the nine worlds, and a copy of equal power was once owned by Loki before it was destroyed by Freya.

==Notes==
{{commons category|Draupnir}}
{{reflist}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* Orchard, Andy (1997). ''Dictionary of Norse Myth and Legend''. [[Orion Publishing Group|Cassell]]. {{ISBN|0-304-34520-2}}
{{refend}}

{{Norse mythology}}

[[Category:Artifacts in Norse mythology]]
[[Category:Odin]]
[[Category:Individual rings]]</text>
      <sha1>e8sj1fow8mkb0tzbszwpr2b0nfr2bmj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
