  <page>
    <title>Diego de Almagro</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8362</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943034962</id>
      <parentid>941324382</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T12:24:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Revirvlkodlaku</username>
        <id>4904587</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{about||the city in Chile|Diego de Almagro, Chile|the island of Chile|Diego de Almagro Island}}
{{short description|Spanish conquistador (1475-1538)}}
{{Infobox officeholder
|name        = Diego de Almagro
|image       = Diego de Almagro.JPG
| honorific-prefix= [[Adelantado]]
|image_size  = 250px
|birth_date  = {{circa}}1475
|birth_place = [[Almagro, Ciudad Real|Almagro]], [[Crown of Castile]]
|death_date  = July 8, {{Death year and age|1538|1475}}
|death_place = [[Cusco|Cuzco]], [[Governorate of New Castile|New Castile]], [[Spanish Empire]]
|known_for   = [[Spanish conquest of the Chibchan Nations#Kuna|Exploration of the Kuna]]&lt;br&gt;[[Spanish conquest of the Inca Empire|Conquest of Peru]]&lt;br&gt;[[Discovery of Chile]]
|occupation  = Conquistador
|nationality = [[Crown of Castile|Castilian]]
|father      = Juan de Montenegro
|mother      = Elvira Gutiérrez
|spouse      = Ana Martínez&lt;br&gt;Mencia
|children    = [[Diego de Almagro II]] (son)&lt;br&gt;Isabel de Almagro (daughter)
|battles      =[[Spanish conquest of the Inca Empire|Conquest of Peru]]
*[[Battle of Cajamarca]]
*[[Battle of Vilcaconga]]
*[[Battle of Abancay]]
*[[Battle of Las Salinas]]
|footnotes   = {{center|&lt;ref name=GeniAlmagro&gt;[https://www.geni.com/people/Diego-de-Almagro-conquistador-de-Per%C3%BA/6000000001120218366 Diego de Almagro] - Geni&lt;/ref&gt;}}
}}
'''Diego de Almagro''' ({{IPA-es|ˈdjeɣo ðe alˈmaɣɾo|lang}}; {{circa|lk=no|1475}}&lt;ref&gt;{{in lang|de}} {{cite LSA |last=García |first=Celso |las2=De Carvajal |first2=Gaspar |last3=Fritz |first3=Samuel |last4=Grün |first4=Evamaria |year=1973 |title=Die Eroberung von Peru: Pizarro und andere Conquistadoren, 1526-1712 |publisher=Erdmann: Horst Erdmann Verlag |page=96}}&lt;/ref&gt; &amp;ndash;  July 8, 1538), also known as '''[[Adelantado|El Adelantado]]''' and '''El Viejo''', was a Spanish [[conquistador]] known for his exploits in western South America. He participated with [[Francisco Pizarro]] in the [[Spanish conquest of Peru]]. From Peru Almagro led an expedition that made him the second European to set foot in central [[Chile]] (after [[:es:Gonzalo Calvo de Barrientos|Gonzalo Calvo de Barrientos]]). Back in Peru a longstanding conflict with Pizarro over the control of the former [[Inca Empire|Inca]] capital of [[Cuzco]] erupted into a civil war between the two bands of conquistadores. In the [[battle of Las Salinas]] in 1538 Almagro was defeated by the [[Pizarro brothers]] and months later he was executed.

== Early years ==
[[File:Escudo de Diego de Almagro.svg|left|80px|thumb|Shield of Diego de Almagro]]
The origins of Diego de Almagro remain obscure. He was born in 1475 in the village of [[Almagro, Ciudad Real|Almagro]], in [[Ciudad Real]], where he took the surname for being the illegitimate son of Juan de Montenegro and Elvira Gutiérrez. In order to save the honor of the mother, her relatives took her infant and moved him to the nearby town of [[Bolaños de Calatrava]], being raised in this town and in [[Aldea del Rey]], run by [[Sancha López del Peral]].

When he turned four he returned to Almagro, being under the tutelage of an uncle named Hernán Gutiérrez until he was fifteen years old, when due to his uncle's hardness he ran away from home. He went to the home of his mother, who was now living with her new husband, to tell her what had happened and that he was going to travel the world, asking for some bread to help her live in her misery. His mother, anguished, gave him a piece of bread and some coins and said: ''&quot;Take, son, and do not give me more pressure, and go, and God help  in your adventure.&quot;''

He went to [[Seville]] and after probably stealing to survive the boy becomes a &quot;criado&quot; or servant and raised by Don [[San Nicolás de Bari, Burgos#The Polanco Family|Luis de Polanco]], one of the four mayors of the [[Catholic Monarchs]] and later his counselor, and who was mayor of that city. While performing his duties as a servant, Almagro stabbed another servant for certain differences, leaving him with injuries so serious that they motivated that a trial against him be promoted.

Being wanted for justice, Don Luis de Polanco, making use of his influence, got Don [[Pedro Arias Dávila|Pedro Arias de Avila]] to allow him to embark  in one of the ships that would go to the New World from the port of [[Sanlúcar de Barrameda|Sanlucar de Barrameda]]. The [[Casa de Contratación|Casa de Contratacion]] demanded that the men who crossed the Indies carry their own weapons, clothes, and farming tools, which Don Polanco provided to his servant.{{clearleft}}

== Arrival in America ==
{{see also|Spanish conquest of the Chibchan Nations}}
[[File:Conquest_of_Colombia.png|right|thumb|Conquest of Colombia&lt;br&gt;Route by Diego de Almagro shown in '''{{purple|purple}}''']]
Diego de Almagro arrived in the [[New World]] on June 30, 1514, under the expedition that [[Ferdinand II of Aragon]] had sent under the guidance of [[Pedrarias Dávila]]. The expedition had landed in the city of [[Darién Province|Santa María la Antigua del Darién]], [[Panama]], where many other future conquistadors had already arrived, among them Francisco Pizarro.

There are not many details of Almagro's activities during this period, but it is known that he accompanied various sailors who departed from the city of Darien between 1514 and 1515. De Almagro eventually returned and settled in Darien, where he was granted an [[encomienda]]. He built a house and made a living from agriculture.

De Almagro undertook his first conquest on November 1515, commanding 260 men as he founded [[Acla|Villa del Acla]], named after the Indian place. Due to illness he had to leave behind this mission to the licenciate [[Gaspar de Espinosa]].

Espinosa decided to undertake a new expedition, which departed in December 1515 with 200 men, including De Almagro and Francisco Pizarro, who for the first time was designated as a captain. During this expedition, which lasted 14 months, De Almagro, Pizarro and [[Hernando de Luque]] became close friends.

Also during this time De Almagro established a friendship with [[Vasco Núñez de Balboa]], who was in charge of Acla. De Almagro wanted to have a ship built with the remaining materials of the Espinosa expedition, to be finished on the coast of the &quot;Great South Sea&quot;, as the Pacific Ocean was first called by the Spanish. Current historians do not believe that De Almagro was expected to participate in Balboa's expedition and probably returned to Darien.

De Almagro took part in the various expeditions that took place in the [[Gulf of Panama]], taking part again in Espinosa's parties. Espinosa was supported by using Balboa's ships. De Almagro was recorded as a witness on the lists of natives whom Espinosa ordered to be carried. De Almagro remained as an early settler in the newly founded city of Panama. For four years he stayed there, working at the management of his properties and those of Pizarro. He took Ana Martínez, an indigenous woman, as a common-law wife. In this period, his first son, el &quot;Mozo&quot;, was born to them.

== Conquest of Peru ==
{{main|Spanish conquest of the Inca Empire}}
By 1524 an association of conquest regarding South America was formalized among Almagro, Pizarro and Luque.&lt;ref name=Hemming&gt;{{cite LSA |last=Hemming |first=J. |year=1970 |title=The Conquest of the Incas |publisher=Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, Inc., New York |isbn=0151225605}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|24}} By the beginning of August 1524, they had received the requisite permission to discover and conquer lands further south. De Almagro would remain in Panama to recruit men and gather supplies for the expeditions led by Pizarro.&lt;ref name=Prescott/&gt;{{rp|92–102}}

After several expeditions to South America, Pizarro secured his stay in Peru with the ''Capitulation'' on 6 July 1529.&lt;ref name=Prescott&gt;{{cite LSA |last=Prescott |first=W.H. |year=2011 |title=The History of the Conquest of Peru |publisher=Digireads.com Publishing |isbn=9781420941142}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|133}} During Pizarro's continued exploration of Incan territory, he and his men succeeded in defeating the Inca army under Emperor [[Atahualpa]] during the [[Battle of Cajamarca]] in 1532. De Almagro joined Pizarro soon afterward, bringing more men and arms.&lt;ref name=Leon&gt;{{cite LSA |last=Leon |first=P. |year=1998 |title=The Discovery and Conquest of Peru, Chronicles of the New World Encounter |publisher=Duke University Press |isbn=9780822321460}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|219–222,233}}

After Peru fell to the Spanish, both Pizarro and De Almagro initially worked together in the founding of new cities to consolidate their dominions. As such, Pizarro dispatched De Almagro to pursue [[Quizquiz]], fleeing to the Inca Empire's northern city of [[Quito]]. Their fellow conquistador [[Sebastián de Belalcázar]], who had gone forth without Pizarro's approval, had already reached Quito and witnessed the destruction of the city by Inca general [[Rumiñawi (Inca warrior)|Rumiñawi]]. The Inca warrior had ordered the city to be burned and its gold to be buried at an undisclosed location where the Spanish could never find it. The arrival of [[Pedro de Alvarado]] from Guatemala, in search of Inca gold further complicated the situation for Almagro and Belalcázar. Alvarado's presence, however, did not last long as he left South America in exchange for monetary compensation from Pizarro.&lt;ref name=Prescott/&gt;{{rp|223–227}}

In an attempt to claim Quito ahead of Belalcázar, in August 1534 De Almagro founded a city on the shores of Laguna de Colta (Colta Lake) in the foothills of Chimborazo, some {{convert|55|km|mi}} south of present-day Quito, and named it &quot;Santiago de Quito.&quot; Four months later would come the foundation of the Peruvian city of [[Trujillo, Peru|Trujillo]], which Almagro named as &quot;Villa Trujillo de Nueva Castilla&quot; (the Village of Trujillo in New Castille) in honor of Francisco Pizarro's birthplace, Trujillo in Extremadura, Spain. These events were the height of the Pizarro-Almagro friendship, which historians describe as one of the last events in which their friendship soon faded and entered a period of turmoil for the control of the Incan capital of Cuzco.

== Conflict with Pizarro ==
[[File:Diego de Almagro y Francisco Pizarro en Castilla.jpg|thumb|right|Diego de Almagro with Francisco Pizarro in Castile&lt;br&gt;''drawing from 1615'']]
After splitting the treasure of Inca emperor Atahualpa, both Pizarro and Almagro left towards [[Cusco|Cuzco]] and took the city in 1533. However, De Almagro's friendship with Pizarro showed signs of deterioration in 1526 when Pizarro, in the name of the rest of the conquistadors, called forth the &quot;Capitulacion de Toledo&quot; law in which [[Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor|King Charles I]] of Spain had laid out his authorization for the [[Spanish conquest of the Inca Empire|conquest of Peru]] and the awards every conquistador would receive from it. Long before, however, each conquistador had promised to equally split the benefits. Pizarro managed to have a larger stake and awards for himself. Despite this, De Almagro still obtained an important fortune for his services, and the King awarded him in November 1532 the noble title of &quot;Don&quot; and he was assigned a personal coat of arms.

Although by this time Diego de Almagro had already acquired sufficient wealth in the conquest of Peru and was living a luxurious life in Cuzco, the prospect of conquering the lands further south was very attractive to him. Given that the dispute with Pizarro over Cuzco had kept intensifying, Almagro spent a great deal of time and money equipping a company of 500 men for a new exploration south of Peru.

By 1534 the Spanish crown had determined to split the region in two parallel lines, forming the governorship of &quot;Nueva Castilla&quot; (from the 1° to the 14° latitude, close to [[Pisco, Peru|Pisco]]), and that of &quot;Nueva Toledo&quot; (from the 14° to the 25° latitude, in [[Taltal]], Chile), assigning the first to Francisco Pizarro and the second to Diego de Almagro. The crown had previously assigned Almagro the governorship of Cuzco, and as such De Almagro was heading there when Charles V divided the territory between Nueva Castilla and Nuevo Toledo. This might have been the reason why Almagro did not immediately confront Pizarro for Cuzco, and promptly decided to embark on his new quest for the discovery of the riches of Chile.

== Discovery of Chile ==
{{Main|Discovery of Chile}}
[[File:Descubrimiento de Chile por Diego de Almagro.jpg|thumb|right|Almagro takes possession of Chile in the valley of Copiapó&lt;br&gt;''painting from first half 20th century'']]

=== The preparations ===
[[Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor|Charles V]] had given Diego a grant extending two hundred [[league (unit)|leagues]] south of Francisco Pizarro's. Francisco and Diego concluded a new contract on 12 June 1535, in which they agreed to share future discoveries equally. Diego raised an expedition for Chile, expecting it &quot;would lead to even greater riches than they had found in Peru.&quot;&lt;ref name=Prescott/&gt;{{rp|230,233–234}} Almagro prepared the way by sending ahead three of his Spanish soldiers, the religious chief of the Inca empire, [[Willaq Umu]], and Paullo Topa, brother of [[Manco Inca Yupanqui]]. De Almagro sent [[Juan de Saavedra]] forward with one hundred and fifty men, and soon followed them with additional forces.&lt;ref name=Prescott/&gt;{{rp|230,233–234}} Saavedra established on January 23, 1535 the first Spanish settlement in Bolivia near the [[Inca Empire|Inca]] regional capital of [[Paria, Bolivia|Paria]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Hace 476 años el Capitán Juan de Saavedra fundó Paria la Nueva,&quot; ''La Patria'', http://www.lapatriaenlinea.com/?nota=56188, accessed 10 June 2016&lt;/ref&gt;

===Following the Inca Trail and crossing the Andes===
Almagro left Cuzco on July 3, 1535 with his supporters and stopped at [[Moina]] until the 20th of that month. Meanwhile, Francisco Pizarro's brother, Juan Pizarro, had arrested Inca [[Manco Inca Yupanqui]], further complicating De Almagro's plans as it heavily increased the dissatisfaction of the Indians submitted to Spanish rule. Not having formally been appointed governor of any territories in the [[Capitulation of Toledo]] in 1528, however, forcing him to declare himself ''adelantado'' (governor) of Nueva Toledo, or southern Peru and present-day Chile. Some sources suggest Almagro received such a requirement in 1534 by the Spanish king and was officially declared governor of New Toledo.

Once he left Moina, De Almagro followed the Inca trail followed by 750 Spaniards deciding to join him in quest for the gold lost in the [[Ransom Room|ransom of Atahualpa]], which had mainly benefited the Pizarro brothers and their supporters. After crossing the Bolivian mountain range and traveling past [[Lake Titicaca]], Almagro arrived on the shores of the [[Desaguadero River (Bolivia)|Desaguadero River]] and finally set up camp in [[Tupiza]]. From there, the expedition stopped at [[Chicoana]] and then turned to the southeast to cross the [[Andes]] mountains.

The expedition turned out to be a difficult and exhausting endeavor. The hardest phase was the crossing of the Andean cordilleras: the cold, hunger and tiredness meant the death of various Spanish and natives, but mainly slaves who were not accustomed to such rigorous climate.&lt;ref name=Prescott/&gt;{{rp|252–253}}

Upon this point, De Almagro determined everything was a failure. He ordered a small group under [[Rodrigo Orgonez]] on a [[reconnaissance]] of the country to the south.&lt;ref name=Prescott/&gt;{{rp|253}}

By luck, these men found the Valley of [[Copiapó]], where Gonzalo Calvo Barrientos, a Spanish soldier whom Pizarro had expelled from Peru for stealing objects the Inca had offered for his ransom, had already established a friendship with the local natives. There, in the valley of the river Copiapó, Almagro took official possession of Chile and  claimed it in the name of King Charles V.

== Dismayed in Chile ==
[[File:Estatua de Diego de Almagro en Almagro (España).jpg|thumb|right|Statue of De Almagro in Almagro, Spain]]
De Almagro promptly initiated the exploration of the new territory, starting up the valley the [[Aconcagua River]], where he was well received by the natives. However, the intrigues of his interpreter, [[Felipillo]], who had previously helped Pizarro in dealing with ''[[Atahualpa]]'', almost thwarted De Almagro's efforts. Felipillo had secretly urged the local natives to attack the Spanish, but they desisted, not understanding the dangers that they posed. De Almagro directed Gómez de Alvarado along with 100 horsemen and 100 foot to continue the exploration, which ended in the confluence of the Ñuble and Itata rivers. The Battle of [[Reynogüelén|Reinohuelén]] between the Spanish and hostile [[Mapuche]] Indians forced the explorers to return to the north.

De Almagro's own reconnaissance of the land and the bad news of Gómez de Alvarado's encounter with the fierce Mapuche, along with the bitter cold winter that settled ferociously upon them, only served to confirm that everything had failed. He never found gold or the cities which Incan scouts had told him lay ahead, only communities of the indigenous population who lived from subsistence agriculture. Local tribes put up fierce resistance to the Spanish forces. The exploration of the territories of Nueva Toledo, which lasted 2 years, was marked by a complete failure for De Almagro. Despite this, at first he thought staying and founding a city would serve well for his honor. The initial optimism that led Almagro to bring his son he had with the indigenous Panamanian Ana Martínez to Chile had faded.

Some historians have suggested that, but for the urging of his senior explorers, De Almagro would probably have stayed permanently in Chile. He was urged to return to Peru and this time take definitive possession of [[Cuzco]], so as to consolidate an inheritance for his son. Dismayed with his experience in the south, Almagro made plans of return to Peru. He never officially founded a city in the territory of what is now Chile.&lt;ref name=Prescott/&gt;{{rp|254}}

The withdrawal of the Spanish from valleys of Chile was violent: Almagro authorized his soldiers to ransack the natives' properties, leaving their soil desolate. In addition, the Spanish soldiers took natives captive to serve as slaves. The locals were captured, tied together, and forced to carry the heavy loads belonging to the conquistadors.

== Return to Peru ==
[[File:Diego-de-Almagro.png|thumb|right|Capture and execution of Diego de Almagro in [[Cusco]]. Engraving, circa 1600]]
After the exhausting crossing of the [[Atacama Desert]], mainly due to the weather conditions, Almagro finally reached Cuzco, Peru, in 1537.&lt;ref name=Prescott/&gt;{{rp|254}} According to some authors, it was during this time that the Spanish term ''&quot;[[roto]]&quot;'' (torn), used by Peruvians to refer to Chileans, was first coined. De Almagro's disappointed troops returned to Cuzco with their &quot;torn clothes&quot; due to the extensive and laborious passage on foot by the Atacama Desert.

After his return, De Almagro was surprised to learn of the Inca [[Manco Inca Yupanqui|Manco]]'s rebellion. Diego de Almagro sent an embassy to the Inca, but they mistrusted all of the Spaniards by this time. [[Hernando Pizarro]]'s men formed an uneasy truce with De Almagro's men, surveying to determine the boundaries of their leaders' royal grants. They needed to determine in which portion the city of Cuzco was located. However, De Almagro's troops quickly took the city and imprisoned the [[Pizarro brothers]], Hernando and Gonzalo, on the night of 8 April 1537.&lt;ref name=Prescott/&gt;{{rp|254–256}}

After occupying Cuzco, De Almagro confronted an army sent by Francisco Pizarro to liberate his brothers. [[Alonso de Alvarado]] commanded it and was defeated during the [[Battle of Abancay]] on July 12, 1537.&lt;ref name=Prescott/&gt;{{rp|257}} He and some of his men were imprisoned. Later, Gonzalo Pizarro and De Alvarado escaped prison. Subsequent negotiations between Francisco Pizarro and De Almagro concluded with the liberation of Hernando, the third Pizarro brother, in return for conceding control and administration of Cuzco to De Almagro. Pizarro never intended to give up the city permanently, but was buying time to organize an army strong enough to defeat Almagro's troops.&lt;ref name=Prescott/&gt;{{rp|260–262}} &lt;ref name=&quot;Andagoya&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Narrative_of_the_Proceedings_of_Pedrarias_Davila/Narrative_of_Pascual_de_Andagoya|title=Narrative of the Proceedings of Pedrarias Davila|first=Pascual de|last=Andagoya|publisher=The Hakluyt Society|page=54 |accessdate=21 June 2019|via=Wikisource}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During this time Almagro fell ill, and Pizarro and his brothers grabbed the opportunity to defeat him and his followers. The Almagristas were defeated at [[Battle of Las Salinas|Las Salinas]] in April 1538, with Orgóñez being killed on the field of battle. De Almagro fled to Cuzco, still in the hands of his loyal supporters, but found only temporary refuge; the forces of the Pizarro brothers entered the city without resistance. Once captured, Almagro was humiliated by Hernando Pizarro and his requests to appeal to the King were ignored.

When Diego de Almagro begged for his life, Hernando responded:&lt;ref name=Prescott/&gt;{{rp|262–268}}

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;-he was surprised to see Almagro demean himself in a manner so unbecoming a brave cavalier, that his fate was no worse than had befallen many a soldier before him; and that, since God had given him the grace to be a Christian, he should employ his remaining moments in making up his account with Heaven!&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Almagro was condemned to death and executed by ''[[garrote]]'' in his dungeon, and then decapitated, on July 8, 1538. His corpse was taken to the public Plaza Mayor of Cuzco, where a herald proclaimed his crimes. [[Hernán Ponce de León]] took his body and buried him in the church of Our Lady of Mercy in Cuzco.&lt;ref name=Prescott/&gt;{{rp|269}}

== El Mozo ==
[[Diego de Almagro II]] (1520–1542), known as ''El Mozo'' (The Lad), son of Diego de Almagro I, whose mother was an Indian girl of [[Panama City, Panama|Panama]], became the foil of the conspirators who had put [[Francisco Pizarro|Pizarro]] to the sword. Pizarro was murdered on June 26, 1541; the conspirators promptly proclaimed the lad De Almagro Governor of Peru. From various causes, all of the conspirators either died or were killed except for one, who was executed after the lad Almagro gave an order. The lad De Almagro fought the desperate [[battle of Chupas]] on September 16, 1542, escaped to [[Cusco|Cuzco]], but was arrested, immediately condemned to death, and executed in the great square of the city.

== See also ==
{{Portal|Chile|Colombia|History|Peru}}
*[[History of Cusco]]
*[[List of conquistadors in Colombia]]
*[[Spanish conquest of the Muisca]]
*[[Spanish conquest of the Chibchan Nations#Kuna|Spanish conquest of the Kuna]]
*[[Spanish conquest of the Inca Empire]]
*[[History of Chile]]
*[[Pedro de Valdivia]], [[Alonso de Ojeda]]

{{clearboth}}

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== Further reading ==
{{Library resources box|by=no|onlinebooks=yes|viaf=77088464}}
* {{in lang|es}} {{cite LSA |last=Amunátegui |first=Miguel Luis  |author-link= Miguel Luis Amunátegui |year=1862 |url=http://www.memoriachilena.cl/archivos2/pdfs/MC0012618.pdf |title=Discovery and conquest of Chile - Study of Diego de Almagro   |pages=37-179 |accessdate=2005-02-13}}
* {{in lang|es}} {{cite LSA |last=Ballesteros Gaibrois |first=Manuel |year=1977 |title=Diego de Almagro |isbn=84-500-2085-9}}
* {{in lang|es}} {{cite LSA |last=Dermit |first=Pedro |year=1998 |title=La expedición de Diego de Almagro |journal=DMS |volume=6 |pages=55–79}}
* {{cite LSA |last=[[Carlos Keller|Keller]] |first=Carlos |year=s.a |url=http://www.carloskeller.cl/Bibliografia/MichimaloncoPedrodeValdivia.htm |title=Michimalonco, Pedro de Valdivia and the birth of Chile |accessdate=2005-02-14}}
* {{cite LSA |last=[[Carlos Keller|Keller]] |first=Carlos |year=s.a |url=http://www.carloskeller.cl/Bibliografia/LaconsolidaciondeldominioespañolenChile.htm |title=The consolidation of the Spanish dominion in Chile |accessdate=2005-02-14}}
* {{in lang|es}} {{cite LSA |last=Larraín Valdés |first=Gerardo |year=2001 |title=Diego de Almagro |publisher=Editorial Luxemburgo |isbn=956-272-488-3 |pages=_}}
* {{cite LSA |last=MacQuarrie |first=Kim |year=2007 |title=The Last Days of the Incas |publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |isbn=978-0-7432-6049-7}}
* {{in lang|es}} {{cite LSA |last=Pizarro |first=Fernando |year=s.a. |url=http://www.memoriachilena.cl/archivos2/pdfs/MC0012617.pdf |title=Vida del mariscal y adelantado Don Diego de Almagro el viejo y de su hijo Don Diego de Almagro |accessdate=2005-02-13}}
* {{in lang|es}} {{cite LSA |last=Pucci |first=Lucas |year=1998 |url=http://alipso.com/monografias/almagro/ |title=Vida y obra de Diego de Almagro |accessdate=2005-02-13}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Diego de Almagro}}
* {{in lang|es}} [http://www.historia.uchile.cl Documental sources and bibliographies for the study of the History of Chile] by the [[University of Chile]]
* {{in lang|es}} [http://www.puc.cl/sw_educ/historia/conquista/parte3/html/h51.html The conquistadores], description of the profile of the conquistadors that arrived in America in search of honor and fortune in the name of the [[Spanish monarchy]] and the [[Roman Catholic Church]]
* {{in lang|es}} [https://web.archive.org/web/20060901033707/http://www.er.uqam.ca/nobel/r27020/id27.htm History of Chile] by José Del Pozo

{{Spanish Empire}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Almagro, Diego De}}
[[Category:1470s births]]
[[Category:1538 deaths]]
[[Category:People from the Province of Ciudad Real]]
[[Category:Castilian-Manchegan conquistadors]]
[[Category:Spanish explorers of South America]]
[[Category:Spanish generals]]
[[Category:City founders]]
[[Category:Captaincy General of Chile]]
[[Category:Colonial Peru]]
[[Category:Explorers of Chile]]
[[Category:Executed Spanish people]]
[[Category:People executed by Spain by decapitation]]
[[Category:16th-century executions by Spain]]
[[Category:16th-century Peruvian people]]
[[Category:British people with disabilities]]</text>
      <sha1>giffgfdipi39phwwyit35aujyaps6yp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
