  <page>
    <title>Divinity</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8363</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940513010</id>
      <parentid>940512815</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-13T00:07:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Flyer22 Frozen</username>
        <id>4293477</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/2601:2C5:C480:4DE0:605B:5F88:B7:5D66|2601:2C5:C480:4DE0:605B:5F88:B7:5D66]] ([[User talk:2601:2C5:C480:4DE0:605B:5F88:B7:5D66|talk]]) ([[WP:HG|HG]]) (3.4.9)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{other uses}}
{{redirect|Divine}}
{{Multiple issues|
{{More citations needed|date=August 2019}}
{{Religious text primary|date=August 2019}}
}}
[[File:Isaac Oliver Elizabeth I and the Three Goddesses.jpg|thumb|250px|''Elizabeth I and the Three Goddesses'' ([[Juno (mythology)|Juno]], [[Minerva]], and [[Venus (mythology)|Venus]]), by [[Isaac Oliver]], c. 1558]]
In [[religion]], '''divinity''' or '''Godhead''' is the state of things that are believed to come from a [[supernatural power]] or [[deity]], such as [[God]], the supreme being, [[creator deity]], or [[spirit]]s, and are therefore regarded as [[sacred]] and [[holy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;dictionary.com&quot;&gt;[http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/divine divine] - Dictionary.com.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/divine divine] - Merriam Webster.&lt;/ref&gt; Such things are regarded as divine due to their [[transcendence (religion)|transcendental]] origins or because their attributes or qualities are superior or supreme relative to things of the [[Earth]]. Divine things are regarded as [[eternity|eternal]] and based in [[truth]], while material things are regarded as [[ephemeral]] and based in [[illusion]]. Such things that may qualify as divine are [[apparitional experience|apparitions]], [[Vision (spirituality)|vision]]s, [[prophecy|prophecies]], [[miracle]]s, and in some views also the [[soul]], or more general things like [[resurrection]], [[immortality]], [[divine grace|grace]], and [[salvation]]. Otherwise what is or is not divine may be loosely defined, as it is used by different [[belief system]]s.

The root of the word &quot;divine&quot; is literally &quot;godly&quot; (from the Latin ''deus'', cf. ''[[Dyaus Pita|Dyaus]]'', closely related to Greek ''[[zeus]]'', ''[[Daeva|div]]'' in [[Persian language|Persian]] and ''[[Deva (Hinduism)|deva]]'' in [[Sanskrit]]), but the use varies significantly depending on which deity is being discussed. This article outlines the major distinctions in the [[conventional]] use of the terms.

For specific related [[academic]] terms, see [[Divinity (academic discipline)]], or [[Anglican divine|Divine (Anglican)]].

== Usages ==
Divinity as a quality has two distinct usages:
* [[#Divine force or power|Divine force or power]] - powers or forces that are universal, or transcend human capacities
* [[#Mortals|Divinity applied to mortals]] - qualities of individuals who are considered to have some special access or relationship to the divine.

Overlap occurs between these usages because [[deities]] or godly entities are often identical with or identified by the powers and forces that are credited to them&amp;nbsp;— in many cases a deity is merely a power or force personified&amp;nbsp;— and these powers and forces may then be extended or granted to [[Human|mortal]] individuals. For instance, [[Jehovah]] is closely associated with storms and thunder throughout much of the [[Old Testament]]. He is said to speak in thunder, and thunder is seen as a token of his anger. This power was then extended to [[Prophets in Judaism|prophets]] like [[Moses]] and [[Samuel (Bible)|Samuel]], who caused thunderous storms to rain down on their enemies. (See {{bibleverse||Exodus|9:23}} and [[Books of Samuel|1 Samuel]] 12:18.)
Divinity always carries connotations of [[good and evil|goodness]], [[beauty]], beneficence, [[justice]], and other positive, pro-social attributes. In [[monotheistic]] faiths there is an equivalent cohort of malefic [[supernatural]] beings and powers, such as [[demons]], [[devil]]s, [[afreet]], etc., which are not conventionally referred to as divine; ''demonic'' is often used instead. [[Pantheistic]] and [[polytheistic]] faiths make no such distinction; gods and other beings of [[transcendence (religion)|transcendent]] power often have complex, ignoble, or even [[irrational]] motivations for their acts. Note that while the terms ''demon'' and ''demonic'' are used in [[monotheistic]] faiths as [[antonyms]] to ''divine'', they are in fact derived from the [[Greek language|Greek]] word ''[[Daemon (classical mythology)|daimón]]'' (δαίμων), which itself translates as ''divinity''.

There are three distinct usages of ''divinity'' and ''divine'' in religious [[discourse]]:

=== Entity ===
{{Main|Deity}}
In monotheistic faiths, the word ''divinity'' is often used to refer to the [[singular God]] central to that faith. Often the word takes the [[definite article]] and is capitalized&amp;nbsp;— ''&quot;the Divinity&quot;''&amp;nbsp;— as though it were a [[proper name]] or definitive honorific. 
''Divine''&amp;nbsp;— capitalized&amp;nbsp;— may be used as an adjective to refer to the manifestations of such a Divinity or its powers: e.g. &quot;basking in the Divine presence...&quot;

The terms ''divinity'' and ''divine''&amp;nbsp;— uncapitalized, and lacking the definite article&amp;nbsp;— are sometimes used as to denote 'god(s)&lt;ref&gt;See, for example [http://www.stavacademy.co.uk/mimir/greatstag.htm &quot;The Great Stag: A Sumerian Divinity&quot;] by Bobula Ida (''Yearbook of Ancient and Medieval History'' 1953)&lt;/ref&gt; or certain other beings and entities which fall short of absolute Godhood but lie outside the human realm. These include (by no means an exhaustive list):

=== Divine force or power ===
As previously noted, divinities are closely related to the transcendent force(s) or power(s) credited to them,&lt;ref&gt;note Augustine's argument that divinity is not a quality of God, but that &quot;God is [...] Divinity itself&quot; (Nature and Grace, part I, question 3, article 3) [http://www.ccel.org/ccel/aquinas/nature_grace.vi.iii.iii.html &quot;Whether God is the Same as His Essence or Nature&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; so much so that in some cases the powers or forces may themselves be invoked independently. This leads to the second usage of the word ''divine'' (and a less common usage of ''divinity''): to refer to the operation of transcendent power in the world.

In its most direct form, the operation of transcendent power implies some form of [[Miracle|divine intervention]]. For pan- and polytheistic faiths this usually implies the direct action of one god or another on the course of human events. In Greek [[legend]], for instance, it was [[Poseidon]] (god of the sea) who raised the storms that blew [[Odysseus]]'s craft off course on his return journey, and [[Japan]]ese tradition holds that a [[Kamikaze#Origin of the word Kamikaze|god-sent wind]] saved them from Mongol invasion. [[Prayer]]s or propitiations are often offered to specific gods of [[pantheism]]s to garner favorable interventions in particular enterprises: e.g. safe journeys, success in war, or a season of bountiful crops. Many faiths around the world&amp;nbsp;— from Japanese [[Shinto]] and Chinese traditional religion, to certain African practices and the faiths derived from those in the Caribbean, to Native American beliefs&amp;nbsp;— hold that [[ancestral]] or [[household deity|household deities]] offer daily protection and [[blessing]]s. In monotheistic religions, divine intervention may take very direct forms: [[miracles]], [[vision (spirituality)|vision]]s, or [[Intercession of saints|intercessions]] by blessed figures.

Transcendent force or power may also operate through more subtle and indirect paths. Monotheistic faiths generally support some version of [[divine providence]], which acknowledges that the divinity of the faith has a profound but unknowable plan always unfolding in the world. Unforeseeable, overwhelming, or seemingly unjust events are often thrown on 'the will of the Divine', in deferences like the [[Muslim]] ''inshallah'' ('as God wills it') and Christian 'God works in mysterious ways'. Often such faiths hold out the possibility of [[divine retribution]] as well, where the divinity will unexpectedly bring [[evil]]-doers to justice through the conventional workings of the world; from the subtle redressing of minor personal [[wrongs]], to such large-scale havoc as the destruction of [[Sodom and Gomorrah]] or the biblical [[Great Flood]]. Other faiths are even more subtle: the doctrine of ''[[karma]]'' shared by [[Buddhism]] and [[Hinduism]] is a [[divine law]] similar to [[divine retribution]] but without the connotation of punishment: our acts, good or bad, intentional or unintentional, reflect back on us as part of the natural working of the [[universe]]. Philosophical [[Taoism]] also proposes a transcendent operant principle&amp;nbsp;— transliterated in English as ''tao'' or ''dao'', meaning 'the way'&amp;nbsp;— which is neither an entity or a being per se, but reflects the natural ongoing process of the world. Modern [[western mysticism]] and [[new age]] philosophy often use the term 'the Divine' as a noun in this latter sense: a non-specific [[principle]] or being that gives rise to the world, and acts as the source or [[wellspring of life]]. In these latter cases the faiths do not promote deference, as happens in monotheisms; rather each suggests a path of action that will bring the practitioner into conformance with the divine law: ''ahimsa''&amp;nbsp;— 'no harm'&amp;nbsp;— for Buddhist and Hindu faiths; ''de'' or ''te''&amp;nbsp;— 'virtuous action'&amp;nbsp;— in Taoism; and any of numerous practices of peace and love in new age thinking.

=== Mortals ===
{{main|apotheosis}}
In the third usage, extensions of divinity and divine power are credited to living, mortal individuals. Political leaders are known to have claimed actual divinity in certain early societies&amp;nbsp;— the ancient [[Egyptian Pharaohs]] being the premier case&amp;nbsp;— taking a role as objects of worship and being credited with superhuman status and powers. More commonly, and more pertinent to recent history, leaders merely claim some form of divine [[mandate (theology)|mandate]], suggesting that their rule is in accordance with the will of God. The doctrine of the [[divine right of kings]] was introduced as late as the 17th century, proposing that [[king]]s rule by divine decree; Japanese Emperors ruled by divine mandate until the inception of the [[Japanese constitution]] after [[World War II]].

Less politically, most faiths have any number of people that are believed to have been touched by divine forces: [[saint]]s, [[prophet]]s, [[hero]]es, [[oracle]]s, [[martyr]]s, and enlightened beings, among others. [[Saint Francis of Assisi]], in Catholicism, is said to have received instruction directly from [[God]] and it is believed that he grants [[plenary indulgence]] to all who confess their sins and visit his chapel on the appropriate day.  In Greek mythology, [[Achilles]]' mother bathed him in the [[river Styx]] to give him immortality, and [[Hercules]]&amp;nbsp;— as the son of [[Zeus]]&amp;nbsp;— inherited near-godly powers. In religious [[Taoism]], [[Lao Tsu]] is venerated as a saint with his own powers. Various individuals in the Buddhist faith, beginning with [[Gautama Buddha|Siddhartha]], are considered to be enlightened, and in religious forms of Buddhism they are credited with divine powers. Christ in the Bible is said to be God's Son and is said to have performed divine miracles.

In general, mortals with divine qualities are carefully distinguished from the deity or deities in their religion's main [[pantheon (gods)|pantheon]].&lt;ref&gt;This is sometimes a [[controversial]] issue, however; see [http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/shinto/features/emperor/index.shtml], for example, for a discussion of the status of the [[Japan]]ese emperor.&lt;/ref&gt; Even the Christian faith, which generally holds Christ to be identical to God, distinguishes between God the Father and Christ the begotten Son.&lt;ref&gt;See, for example, [http://www.users.globalnet.co.uk/~emcd/index20.htm &quot;The Divinity of Alpha's Jesus&quot;] by Peterson &amp; McDonald (''Media Spotlight'' 25:4, 2002)&lt;/ref&gt; There are, however, certain esoteric and mystical schools of thought, present in many faiths&amp;nbsp;— [[Sufi]]s in Islam, [[Gnostic]]s in Christianity, Advaitan Hindus, [[Zen Buddhist]]s, as well as several non-specific perspectives developed in new age philosophy&amp;nbsp;— which hold that all humans are in [[essence]] divine, or unified with the Divine in a non-trivial way. Such divinity, in these faiths, would express itself naturally if it were not obscured by the social and physical worlds we live in; it needs to be brought to the fore through appropriate [[spiritual practice]]s.&lt;ref&gt;See, for example, [http://www.crimsoncircle.com/AboutUs/AboutTobias/TheAwakeningSigns.aspx &quot;Twelve Signs of Your Awakening Divinity&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131202223313/http://www.crimsoncircle.com/AboutUs/AboutTobias/TheAwakeningSigns.aspx |date=December 2, 2013 }} by Geoffrey Hoppe and Tobias&lt;/ref&gt;

== Christianity ==

In traditional [[Christian theology]], the concept and nature of divinity always has its source ultimately from God himself. It's the state or quality of being divine, and the term can denote Godly nature or character.  In Hebrew, the terms would usually be &quot;[[El (deity)|el]]&quot;, &quot;[[elohim]]&quot;, and in Greek usually &quot;theos&quot;, or &quot;theias&quot;. The divinity in the Bible is considered the Godhead itself, or God in general. Or it may have reference to a deity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thefreedictionary.com/divinity divinity] - The Free Dictionary.&lt;/ref&gt; Even angels in the [[Psalms]] are considered divine or ''elohim'', as spirit beings, in God's form.

In the [[New Testament]] the Greek word θεῖον (''theion'') in the [[Douay–Rheims Bible|Douay Version]], is translated as &quot;divinity&quot;. Examples are below:
* Acts 17:29
:&quot;Being therefore the offspring of God, we must not suppose the divinity to be like unto gold, or silver, or stone, the graving of art, and device of man.&quot;
* Romans 1:20
:&quot;For the invisible things of him, from the creation of the world, are clearly seen, being understood by the things that are made; his eternal power also, and divinity: so that they are inexcusable.&quot;
* Revelation 5:12
:&quot;Saying with a loud voice: The Lamb that was slain is worthy to receive power, and divinity, and wisdom, and strength, and honour, and glory, and benediction.&quot;

The word translated as either &quot;deity&quot;, &quot;Godhead&quot;, or &quot;divinity&quot; in the Greek New Testament is also the Greek word θεότητος (''theotētos''), and the one Verse that contains it is this:
Colossians 2:9
:&quot;Quia in ipso inhabitat omnis plenitudo divinitatis [divinity] corporaliter.&quot; (Vulgate)
:&quot;For in him dwelleth all the fulness of the Godhead bodily.&quot; (KJV)
:&quot;Because it is in him that all the fullness of the divine quality dwells bodily.&quot; (NWT)
:&quot;For in him all the fullness of deity lives in bodily form.&quot; (NET)
:&quot;For the full content of divine nature lives in Christ.&quot; (TEV)

The word &quot;divine&quot; in the New Testament is the Greek word θείας (''theias''), and is the adjective form of &quot;divinity&quot;. Biblical examples from the [[King James Bible]] are below:
* 2 Peter 1:3
:&quot;According as his divine power hath given unto us all things that pertain unto life and godliness, through the knowledge of him that hath called us to glory and virtue.&quot;
* 2 Peter 1:4
:&quot;Whereby are given unto us exceeding great and precious promises: that by these ye might be partakers of the divine nature, having escaped the corruption that is in the world through lust.&quot;

=== Latter-day Saints ===
{{main|God in Mormonism|Plan of salvation (Latter Day Saints)|Mormon cosmology}}

The most prominent conception of divine entities in [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] (LDS Church) is the [[Godhead in Christianity|Godhead]], a divine council of three distinct beings: [[Elohim]] ([[God the Father|the Father]]), [[Jehovah]] ([[God the Son|the Son]], or [[Jesus]]), and the [[Holy Spirit (Christian denominational variations)#Latter Day Saints|Holy Spirit]]. [[Joseph Smith]] described a [[Nontrinitarianism|nontrinitarian]] Godhead, with God the Father and Jesus Christ each having individual physical bodies, and the Holy Spirit as a distinct personage with a [[spirit body]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/130.22?lang=eng D&amp;C 130:22] &quot;The Father has a body of flesh and bones as tangible as man's; the Son also; but the Holy Ghost has not a body of flesh and bones, but is a personage of Spirit. Were it not so, the Holy Ghost could not dwell in us.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title= Godhead |work= True to the Faith |publisher= LDS Church |year= 2004 |url= https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/manual/true-to-the-faith/godhead}}. See also: {{citation |title= God the Father |work= True to the Faith |publisher= LDS Church |year= 2004 |url= https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/manual/true-to-the-faith/god-the-father}}&lt;/ref&gt; Smith also introduced the existence of a [[Heavenly Mother (Mormonism)|Heavenly Mother]] in the [[King Follett Discourse]], but very little is acknowledged or known beyond her existence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|chapter-url= https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/manual/gospel-principles/chapter-2-our-heavenly-family?lang=eng|chapter=Chapter 2: Our Heavenly Family|title=[[Gospel Principles]]|year= 2009|publisher=LDS Church}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first= Spencer W. |last= Kimball |authorlink= Spencer W. Kimball |url= https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/ensign/1978/05/the-true-way-of-life-and-salvation?lang=eng|title=The True Way of Life and Salvation |journal=[[Ensign (LDS magazine)|Ensign]]|date=May 1978|publisher=LDS Church}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Mormons]] hold a belief in the divine potential of humanity; Smith taught a form of [[Divinization (Christian)|divinization]] where mortal men and women can become like god through [[Plan of salvation (Latter Day Saints)|salvation]] and [[Exaltation (Mormonism)|exaltation]]. [[Lorenzo Snow]] succinctly summarized this using a [[couplet]], which is often repeated within the LDS Church: &quot;As man now is, God once was: As God now is, man may be.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last= Lund |first= Gerald N. |authorlink= Gerald N. Lund |date= February 1982 |title= I Have a Question: Is President Lorenzo Snow’s oft-repeated statement—&quot;As man now is, God once was; as God now is, man may be&quot;—accepted as official doctrine by the Church? |url= https://www.churchofjesuschrist.org/study/ensign/1982/02/i-have-a-question?lang=eng |journal= [[Ensign (LDS magazine)|Ensign]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |last= Millet |first= Robert L. |authorlink= Robert L. Millet |last2= Reynolds |first2= Noel B. |authorlink2= Noel B. Reynolds |year= 1998 |contribution= Do Latter-day Saints believe that men and women can become gods? |contribution-url= http://maxwellinstitute.byu.edu/publications/books/?bookid=45&amp;chapid=534 |title= Latter-day Christianity: 10 Basic Issues |location= Provo, Utah |publisher= [[Foundation for Ancient Research and Mormon Studies]] |isbn= 0934893322 |oclc= 39732987 |url-access= registration |url= https://archive.org/details/latterdaychristi00mill }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Apotheosis]]
* [[Catholic views on God]]
* [[Christology]]
* [[Deity]]
* [[Ho'oponopono]] (Morrnah section)
* [[List of deities]]
* [[Divinization (Christian)|Theosis]]

== Notes and references ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
{{wikiquote}}

{{Theism}}
{{Belief systems}}
{{Theology}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Conceptions of God]]
[[Category:Religious belief and doctrine]]
[[Category:Philosophy of religion]]
[[Category:Deities]]</text>
      <sha1>tgjgqsd3qnbtm843vl54w8i8xwfpqii</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
