  <page>
    <title>Animation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>593</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943355414</id>
      <parentid>943181781</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-01T11:56:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>OldUncleRemus</username>
        <id>36488001</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Animated features */Acknowledging Ralph Bakshi; Pixar was part of Disney</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Method of creating moving pictures}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2020}}
{{multiple image
| align = right
| direction = vertical
| width = 150
| image1 = Animexample3edit.png
| width1 = 150
| caption1 = The [[bouncing ball]] animation (below) consists of these six frames.
| image2 = Animexample.gif
| width2 = 85
| caption2 = This animation moves at 10 frames per second.
| footer_align = center
| height1 = 160
| height2 = 80
| total_width = 
| alt1 = Weare
}}
'''Animation''' is a method in which [[Image|pictures]] are manipulated to appear as moving images. In [[traditional animation]], images are drawn or painted by hand on transparent [[cel|celluloid sheets]] to be photographed and exhibited on [[film]]. Today, most animations are made with [[computer-generated imagery]] (CGI). [[Computer animation]] can be very detailed [[3D computer graphics|3D animation]], while [[2D computer graphics|2D computer animation]] can be used for stylistic reasons, low bandwidth or faster [[real-time rendering]]s. Other common animation methods apply a [[stop motion]] technique to two and three-dimensional objects like [[cutout animation|paper cutouts]], [[puppet]]s or [[Clay animation|clay figures]].

Commonly the effect of animation is achieved by a rapid succession of sequential images that minimally differ from each other. The illusion—as in motion pictures in general—is thought to rely on the [[phi phenomenon]] and [[beta movement]], but the exact causes are still uncertain.
[[Analog device|Analog]] mechanical animation media that rely on the rapid display of sequential images include the [[phenakistiscope|phénakisticope]], [[zoetrope]], [[flip book]], [[praxinoscope]] and film. [[Television]] and [[video]] are popular electronic animation media that originally were analog and now operate [[digital media|digitally]]. For display on the computer, techniques like [[animated GIF]] and [[Flash animation]] were developed.

Animation is more pervasive than many people realize. Apart from [[short films]], [[feature films]], animated GIF's and other media dedicated to the display of moving images, animation is also prevalent in [[video game]]s, [[motion graphics]], [[user interface]]s and [[visual effects]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.nl/books?id=ZeiAAAAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;dq=pervasive+animation&amp;pg=PT19#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=Pervasive Animation|first=Suzanne|last=Buchan|date=22 August 2013|publisher=Routledge}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The physical movement of image parts through simple mechanics – in for instance moving images in [[magic lantern]] shows – can also be considered animation. The mechanical manipulation of three-dimensional puppets and objects to emulate living beings has a very long history in [[automaton|automata]]. Electronic automata were popularized by [[Disney]] as [[animatronics]].

[[Animator]]s are artists who specialize in creating animation.
{{TOC limit|3}}

==Etymology==
The word &quot;animation&quot; stems from the Latin &quot;animātiōn&quot;, stem of &quot;animātiō&quot;, meaning &quot;a bestowing of life&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://www.dictionary.com/browse/animation | title=The definition of animation on dictionary.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; The primary meaning of the English word is &quot;liveliness&quot; and has been in use much longer than the meaning of &quot;moving image medium&quot;.

== History ==
{{Main|History of animation}}

===Before cinematography===
Although examples of sequential images can be found occasionally throughout the history of art, there is no evidence of any related technology that enabled the artists to view their creations in motion before 1833. Other ways to create moving images, by manipulating figures by hand or with mechanics, can be recognized in [[puppetry]], [[automaton|automata]], [[shadow play]] and (since around 1659) the [[magic lantern]].

[[File:Prof. Stampfer's Stroboscopische Scheibe No. X.gif|thumb|Nr. 10 in the reworked second series of Stampfer's stroboscopic discs published by Trentsensky &amp; Vieweg in 1833.]]
In 1833, the [[phenakistiscope|phénakisticope]] introduced the [[stroboscope|stroboscopic]] principle of modern animation, which would also provide the basis for the [[zoetrope]] (1866), the [[flip book]] (1868), the [[praxinoscope]] (1877), Muybridge's [[zoopraxiscope]] (1879) and [[cinematography]].

[[File:Lanature1882 praxinoscope projection reynaud.png|thumb|A projecting [[praxinoscope]], 1882, here shown superimposing an animated figure on a separately projected background scene]]
A few years before the breakthrough of cinema in 1895, [[Charles-Émile Reynaud]] had much succes with his ''[[Théâtre Optique|Pantomimes Lumineuses]]''. These animated films each contained 300 to 700 frames that were manipulated back and forth to last 10 to 15 minutes per film. Piano music, song, and some dialogue were performed live, while some sound effects were synchronized with an electromagnet. From 28 October 1892 to March 1900, Reynaud gave over 12,800 shows to a total of over 500,000 visitors at the [[Musée Grévin]] in Paris

===Silent era===
A few years after film became a popular medium, some manufacturers of optical toys produced many [[chromolithography]] film loops for adapted toy magic lanterns, usually with images traced from live-action film footage. At a time when hardly any animations could be seen in theaters, kids would project these animation loops at home.
 
Some early filmmakers, including [[J. Stuart Blackton]], [[Arthur Melbourne-Cooper]], [[Segundo de Chomón]] and [[Edwin S. Porter]] experimented with stop-motion animation, possibly since around 1899. Blackton's ''The Haunted Hotel'' (1907) was the first huge success that baffled audiences with objects apparently moving by themselves. The short film inspired other filmmakers to try the technique.

J. Stuart Blackton's ''[[Humorous Phases of Funny Faces]]'' (1906) is usually regarded as the first animated film on [[standard picture film]]. It was partly animated on a chalkboard and partly with cut-outs.

[[File:Fantasmagorie (Cohl).GIF|thumb|''[[Fantasmagorie (1908 film)|Fantasmagorie]]'' (1908) by [[Émile Cohl]]]]
[[Émile Cohl]]'s ''[[Fantasmagorie (1908 film)|Fantasmagorie]]'' (1908) is the oldest known example of what became known as [[traditional animation|traditional (hand-drawn) animation]].

Great artistic and very influential animations were made by [[Ladislas Starevich]] with his puppet animations since 1910 and by [[Winsor McCay]] with detailed drawn animation in films such as ''[[Little Nemo (1911 film)|Little Nemo]]'' (1911) and ''[[Gertie the Dinosaur]]'' (1914). Gertie was also an early example of character development in drawn animation{{sfn|Canemaker|2005|p=171}} and featured a scene with a live-action recording of McCay interacting with Gertie in a drawn landscape.

During the 1910s, the production of animated &quot;[[cartoons]]&quot; became an industry.{{sfn|Solomon|1989|p=28}} The most successful producer at the time was [[John Randolph Bray]], who, along with animator [[Earl Hurd]], patented the [[cel animation]] process that dominated the animation industry for the rest of the century.{{sfn|Solomon|1989|p=24}}{{sfn|Solomon|1989|p=34}}

[[File:Quirino Cristiani con una figura.jpg|thumb|upright=0.8|Italian-Argentine cartoonist [[Quirino Cristiani]] showing the cut and articulated figure of his satirical character ''El Peludo'' (based on President [[Hipólito Yrigoyen|Yrigoyen]]) patented in 1916 for the realization of his films, including the world's first animated feature film ''[[El Apóstol]]''.{{sfn|Bendazzi|1994|p=49}}]]
In 1917, Argentine director [[Quirino Cristiani]] made the first feature-length film ''[[El Apóstol]]'' (now lost), which became a critical and commercial success. It was followed by Cristiani's ''[[Sin dejar rastros]]'' in 1918, but one day after its premiere the film was confiscated by the government.

In 1919, the silent animated short ''[[Feline Follies]]'' marked the debut of [[Felix the Cat]], becoming the first animated character in the silent film era to gain significant popularity.

After working on it for three years, [[Lotte Reiniger]] released the German feature-length silhouette animation ''[[Die Abenteuer des Prinzen Achmed]]'' in 1926.

===1928-1960s: Golden age of American animation===
In 1928, ''[[Steamboat Willie]]'', featuring [[Mickey Mouse]], popularized film with synchronized sound and put [[Walt Disney]]'s studio at the forefront of the animation industry. In 1932, Disney also introduced the innovation of full colour (in ''[[Flowers and Trees]]'') as part of a three-year long exclusive deal with [[Technicolor]].

The enormous success of Mickey Mouse is seen as the start of the [[golden age of American animation]] that would last until 1960s. The United States dominated the world market of animation with a plethora of cel-animated theatrical shorts. Several studios would introduce characters that would become very popular and would have long lasting careers, including [[Walt Disney Productions]]' [[Goofy]] (1932) and [[Donald Duck]] (1934), [[Warner Bros. Cartoons]]' [[Looney Tunes]] characters like [[Daffy Duck]] (1937), [[Bugs Bunny]] (1938/1940), [[Tweety]] (1941/1942), [[Wile E. Coyote and Road Runner]] (1949), [[Fleischer Studios]]/[[Paramount Cartoon Studios]]' [[Betty Boop]] (1930), [[Popeye#Theatrical animated cartoons|Popeye]] (licensed by King Feature Syndicate) (1933), [[Superman (1940s cartoons)|Superman]] (licensed by DC Comics) (1941) and [[Casper the friendly ghost|Casper]] (1945), [[Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer cartoon studio|MGM cartoon studio]]: [[Tom and Jerry]] (1940) and [[Droopy]], [[Walter Lantz Productions]]/[[Universal Studio Cartoons]]'s [[Woody Woodpecker]] (1940), [[Terrytoons]]/[[20th Century Fox]]'s [[Mighty Mouse]] (1942) and [[United Artists]]' [[Pink Panther (character)|Pink Panther]] (1963). Apart from their success in theaters, such characters would also prove very lucrative when licensed for all kinds of merchandise.

===Animated features===
In 1937, Disney released their first animated feature film &quot;[[Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs (1937 film)|Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs]]&quot;. It was a tremendous success worldwide. The Fleischer studios followed this example in 1939 with ''[[Gulliver's Travels (1939 film)|Gulliver's Travels]]'' with some success. Partly due to foreign markets being cut off by the Second World War, Disney's next features ''[[Pinocchio]]'', ''[[Fantasia (1940 film)|Fantasia]]'' (both 1940) and Fleischer Studios' second animated feature ''[[Mr. Bug Goes to Town]]'' (1941/1942) failed at the box office. For decades afterwards Disney would be the only American studio to regularly produce animated features. Competition came in the 1970s from [[Ralph Bakshi]], who produced 8 theatrically released animated features aimed at adult audiences from 1972 to 1982. Following him, Sullivan-Bluth Studios began to regularly produce animated features starting with ''[[An American Tail]]'' in 1986.

===Early animated series on television===
Animation became very popular on television. In the United States and many other countries, cartoons were [[Saturday-morning cartoon|programmed on Saturday-mornings]] and other time slots that were convenient for children.

The back catalog of animated cartoons, originally produced for a short theatrical run, now proved very valuable for television broadcast and many classical series thus found a new life, with many reruns.

At the end of the 1950s, production of animated cartoons started to shift from theatrical releases to TV series. The constraints of American television programming resulted in cheaper and quicker [[limited animation]] methods.

[[Hanna-Barbera Productions]] was especially prolific on television with programs such as ''[[The Ruff and Reddy Show]]'' (1957-1960),''[[The Huckleberry Hound Show]]'' (1958, the first half-hour television program to feature only animation),{{sfn|Bendazzi|1994|pp=234–35}} ''[[The Quick Draw McGraw Show]]'' (1959-1961), ''[[The Flintstones]]'' (1960-1966) (the first [[prime time]] animated series), ''[[The Yogi Bear Show]]'' (1961-1962), ''[[The Jetsons]]'' (1962) and ''[[Scooby-Doo, Where Are You!]]''.

Other early televised hit series were Terrytoons' ''[[Tom Terrific]]'' (1958) and ''[[Deputy Dawg]]'' (1962).

===Since 1960s===

Japanese [[anime]] productions became very popular since the 1970s. Relatively cheap licensing ensured wide international distribution.

[[Computer animation]] has become popular since ''[[Toy Story]]'' (1995), the first feature-length animated film completely made using this technique.{{sfn|Masson|2007|p=432}}

===2000s===
In 2008, the animation market was worth US$68.4 billion.{{sfn|Board of Investments|2009}} Animation as an art and industry continues to thrive as of the mid-2010s because well-made animated projects can find audiences across borders and in all [[Four-quadrant movie|four quadrants]]. Animated feature-length films returned the highest [[gross margin]]s (around 52%) of all [[film genre]]s in 2004–2013.{{sfn|McDuling|2014}}

Traditional animation film studios switched to producing mostly computer animated films since the 1990s, as box office statistics deemed cheaper and more profitable. However 3d animation is not without its limitations; the unique attractions of 2d art like [[Osamu Tezuka]]'s cannot be rendered properly. Studio sought to evolve the medium and overcome some of the technical limitations that traditional animation had, focusing on organic and volumetric lighting and texturing to give their films a unique look, while maintaining a hand-crafted feel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.cartoonbrew.com/interviews/sergio-pablos-talks-about-his-stunning-hand-drawn-project-klaus-exclusive-113621.html |title=Sergio Pablos Talks About His Stunning Hand-Drawn Project 'Klaus' |last=Amidi |first=Amid |date=1 June 2015 |website=[[Cartoon Brew]] |access-date=12 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FHxhr6KAaUw |title=The Origins of Klaus |date=10 October 2019 |website=[[YouTube]] |access-date=12 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;  &quot;2D and 3D technology hybrids&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Bernstein|first=Abbie|title=Assignment X|url=http://www.assignmentx.com/2013/exclusive-interview-john-kahrs-kristina-reed-on-paperman/|work=Exclusive Interview: John Kahrs &amp; Kristina Reed on PAPERMAN|publisher=Midnight Productions, Inc|accessdate=6 October 2013|date=25 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; allow for unique style of animation&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://insidemovies.ew.com/2012/06/28/first-look-paperman/2/#id=I2_1340992465384&amp;parent=http%3A%2F%2Finsidemovies.ew.com&amp;rpctoken=342270562&amp;_methods=onPlusOne%2Constartinteraction%2C_ready%2C_close%2C_open%2C_resizeMe%2C_renderstart|title=FIRST LOOK: Disney's 'Paperman' fuses hand-drawn charm with digital depth|work=EW.com|accessdate=2 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; that combine expressiveness of 2D drawing with the dimensionality of CG.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Sarto|first=Dan|title=Inside Disney’s New Animated Short Paperman|url=http://www.awn.com/articles/short-films/inside-disney-s-new-animated-short-paperman|publisher=Animation World Network|accessdate=5 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.3dworldmag.com/2012/06/29/disneys-paperman-animated-short-fuses-cg-and-hand-drawn-techniques/|title=Disney’s Paperman animated short fuses CG and hand-drawn techniques|accessdate=2 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Animated commercials==
Animation has been very popular in television commercials, both due to its graphic appeal, and the humour it can provide. Some animated characters in commercials have survived for decades, such as [[Snap, Crackle and Pop]] in advertisements for Kellogg's cereals.{{citation needed|date=April 2019}} The legendary animation director [[Tex Avery]] was the producer of the first [[Raid (insecticide)|Raid]] &quot;[[Kills Bugs Dead]]&quot; commercials in 1966, which were very successful for the company.{{citation needed|date=April 2019}}

==Criticism==
Criticism of animation has been common in media and cinema since its inception. With its popularity, a large amount of criticism has arisen, especially animated feature-length films.{{sfn|Amidi|2011}} Many concerns of cultural representation, psychological effects on children have been brought up around the animation industry, which has remained rather politically unchanged and stagnant since its inception into mainstream culture.{{sfn|Nagel|2008}} In more recent times Disney has been trying to make up for the criticism regarding their racism against Africanism.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Breaux|first=Richard|date=26 July 2010|title=After 75 Years of Magic: Disney Answers Its Critics, Rewrites African American History, and Cashes in on Its Racist Past|url=https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s12111-010-9139-9|journal=Journal of African American Studies|volume=14|pages=398–416|via=Springerlink}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, in the movie Princess and the Frog, Africanism is seen in almost every corner of the movie.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; When they are singing &quot;Dig a little deeper&quot;, there are colorful bottles seen hanging from the trees, which African Americans communities believed that the bottles warned off evil spirits.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; During the 1600–1800, enslaved Africans brought these beliefs back with them from Africa.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt; Mama Odie from Princess and the Frog is depicted as a voodoo priestess of Louisiana from generations of voodoo.&lt;ref name=&quot;:0&quot; /&gt;

==Awards==
{{Main|Animation studio#American studios}}
As with any other form of media, animation has instituted awards for excellence in the field. The original awards for animation were presented by the [[Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences]] for animated shorts from the year 1932, during the 5th [[Academy Awards]] function. The first winner of the [[5th Academy Awards|Academy Award]] was the short ''Flowers and Trees'',{{sfn|Walt Disney Family Museum|2013}} a production by [[Walt Disney Productions]].{{sfn|Beckerman|2003|p=37}}{{sfn|Shaffer|2010|page=211}} The Academy Award for a feature-length animated motion picture was only instituted for the year 2001, and awarded during the 74th Academy Awards in 2002. It was won by the film ''[[Shrek]]'', produced by [[DreamWorks Animation|DreamWorks]] and [[Pacific Data Images]].{{sfn|Beckerman|2003|pp=84–85}} [[Disney]]/[[Pixar]] have produced the most films either to win or be nominated for the award.
* [[Academy Award for Best Animated Feature]]
* [[Academy Award for Best Animated Short Film]]

Several other countries have instituted an award for best-animated feature film as part of their national film awards: [[Africa Movie Academy Award for Best Animation]] (since 2008), [[BAFTA Award for Best Animated Film]] (since 2006), [[César Award for Best Animated Film]] (since 2011), [[Golden Rooster Award for Best Animation]] (since 1981), [[Goya Award for Best Animated Film]] (since 1989), [[Japan Academy Prize for Animation of the Year]] (since 2007), [[National Film Award for Best Animated Film]] (since 2006). Also since 2007, the [[Asia Pacific Screen Award for Best Animated Feature Film]] has been awarded at the [[Asia Pacific Screen Awards]]. Since 2009, the [[European Film Awards]] have awarded the [[European Film Award for Best Animated Film]].

The [[Annie Award]] is another award presented for excellence in the field of animation. Unlike the Academy Awards, the Annie Awards are only received for achievements in the field of animation and not for any other field of technical and artistic endeavor. They were re-organized in 1992 to create a new field for Best Animated Feature. The 1990s winners were dominated by Walt Disney, however, newer studios, led by Pixar &amp; DreamWorks, have now begun to consistently vie for this award. The list of awardees is as follows:
* [[Annie Award for Best Animated Feature]]
* [[Annie Award for Best Animated Short Subject]]
* [[Annie Award for Best Animated Television Production]]

==Production==
[[File:Joy &amp;amp; Heron - Animated CGI Spot by Passion Pictures.webm|thumb|Joy &amp;amp; Heron - A featured video]]
The creation of non-trivial animation works (i.e., longer than a few seconds) has developed as a form of [[filmmaking]], with certain unique aspects.{{sfn|Laybourne|1998|p=117}} Traits common to both live-action and animated [[Feature film|feature-length films]] are labor-intensity and high production costs.{{sfn|Solomon|1989|p=274}}

The most important difference is that once a film is in the production phase, the [[marginal cost]] of one more shot is higher for animated films than live-action films.{{sfn|White|2006|p=151}} It is relatively easy for a director to ask for one more [[take]] during [[principal photography]] of a live-action film, but every take on an animated film must be manually rendered by animators (although the task of rendering slightly different takes has been made less tedious by modern computer animation).{{sfn|Laybourne|1998|p=339}} It is pointless for a studio to pay the salaries of dozens of animators to spend weeks creating a visually dazzling five-minute scene if that scene fails to effectively advance the plot of the film.{{sfn|Culhane|1990|p=55}} Thus, animation studios starting with Disney began the practice in the 1930s of maintaining story departments where [[storyboard artist]]s develop every single scene through [[storyboard]]s, then handing the film over to the animators only after the production team is satisfied that all the scenes make sense as a whole. {{sfn|Solomon|1989|p=120}} While live-action films are now also storyboarded, they enjoy more latitude to depart from storyboards (i.e., real-time improvisation).{{sfn|Laybourne|1998|pp=100–01}}

Another problem unique to animation is the requirement to maintain a film's consistency from start to finish, even as films have grown longer and teams have grown larger. Animators, like all artists, necessarily have individual styles, but must subordinate their individuality in a consistent way to whatever style is employed on a particular film.{{sfn|Masson|2007|p=94}} Since the early 1980s, teams of about 500 to 600 people, of whom 50 to 70 are animators, typically have created feature-length animated films. It is relatively easy for two or three artists to match their styles; synchronizing those of dozens of artists is more difficult.{{sfn|Beck|2004|p=37}}

This problem is usually solved by having a separate group of visual development artists develop an overall look and palette for each film before the animation begins. Character designers on the visual development team draw [[model sheet]]s to show how each character should look like with different facial expressions, posed in different positions, and viewed from different angles.{{sfn|Williams|2001|p=34}}{{sfn|Culhane|1990|p=146}} On traditionally animated projects, [[maquette]]s were often sculpted to further help the animators see how characters would look from different angles.{{sfn|Williams|2001|pp=52–57}}{{sfn|Williams|2001|p=34}}

Unlike live-action films, animated films were traditionally developed beyond the synopsis stage through the storyboard format; the storyboard artists would then receive credit for writing the film.{{sfn|Laybourne|1998|pp=99–100}} In the early 1960s, animation studios began hiring professional screenwriters to write screenplays (while also continuing to use story departments) and screenplays had become commonplace for animated films by the late 1980s.

=== Animator ===
{{Main|Animator}}
An animator is an artist who creates a visual sequence (or audio-visual if added sound) of multiple sequential images that generate the illusion of movement, that is, an animation. Animations are currently in many areas of technology and video, such as [[Film|cinema]], [[television]], [[video game]]s or the [[internet]]. Generally, these works require the collaboration of several animators. The methods to create these images depend on the animator and style that one wants to achieve (with images generated by a computer, manually ...).

Animators can be divided into animators of '''characters''' (artists who are specialized in the movements, dialogue and acting of the characters) and animators of '''special effects''' (for example vehicles, machinery or natural phenomena such as water, snow, rain).

== Techniques ==

=== Traditional animation ===

{{Main|Traditional animation}}

[[File:Animhorse.gif|thumb|An example of traditional animation, a horse animated by [[rotoscoping]] from [[Eadweard Muybridge]]'s 19th-century photos]]

'''Traditional animation''' (also called cel animation or hand-drawn animation) was the process used for most animated films of the 20th century.{{sfn|White|2006|p=31}} The individual frames of a traditionally animated film are photographs of drawings, first drawn on paper.{{sfn|Beckerman|2003|p=153}} To create the illusion of movement, each drawing differs slightly from the one before it. The animators' drawings are traced or photocopied onto transparent acetate sheets called [[cel]]s,{{sfn|Thomas|Johnston|1981|pp=277–79}} which are filled in with paints in assigned colors or tones on the side opposite the line drawings.{{sfn|Laybourne|1998|p=203}} The completed character cels are photographed one-by-one against a painted background by a [[rostrum camera]] onto motion picture film.{{sfn|White|2006|pp=195–201}}

The traditional cel animation process became obsolete by the beginning of the 21st century. Today, animators' drawings and the backgrounds are either scanned into or drawn directly into a computer system.{{sfn|Buchan|2013}}{{sfn|White|2006|p=394}} Various software programs are used to color the drawings and simulate camera movement and effects.{{sfn|Culhane|1990|p=296}} The final animated piece is output to one of several delivery media, including traditional [[35mm movie film|35&amp;nbsp;mm film]] and newer media with [[digital video]].{{sfn|Laybourne|1998|pp=35–36, 52–53}}{{sfn|Buchan|2013}} The &quot;look&quot; of traditional cel animation is still preserved, and the [[character animator]]s' work has remained essentially the same over the past 70 years.{{sfn|Williams|2001|pp=52–57}} Some animation producers have used the term &quot;tradigital&quot; (a play on the words &quot;traditional&quot; and &quot;digital&quot;) to describe cel animation that uses significant computer technology.

Examples of traditionally animated feature films include ''[[Pinocchio (1940 film)|Pinocchio]]'' (United States, 1940),{{sfn|Solomon|1989|pp=63–65}} ''[[Animal Farm (1954 film)|Animal Farm]]'' (United Kingdom, 1954), ''[[Lucky and Zorba]]'' (Italy, 1998), and ''[[The Illusionist (2010 film)|The Illusionist]]'' (British-French, 2010). Traditionally animated films produced with the aid of computer technology include ''[[The Lion King]]'' (US, 1994), ''[[The Prince of Egypt]]'' (US, 1998), ''[[Akira (1988 film)|Akira]]'' (Japan, 1988),{{sfn|Beckerman|2003|p=80}} ''[[Spirited Away]]'' (Japan, 2001), ''[[The Triplets of Belleville]]'' (France, 2003), and ''[[The Secret of Kells]]'' (Irish-French-Belgian, 2009).

==== Full animation ====
'''Full animation''' refers to the process of producing high-quality traditionally animated films that regularly use detailed drawings and plausible movement,{{sfn|Culhane|1990|p=71}} having a smooth animation.{{sfn|Culhane|1990|pp=194–95}} Fully animated films can be made in a variety of styles, from more realistically animated works like those produced by the [[Walt Disney Animation Studios|Walt Disney studio]] (''[[The Little Mermaid (1989 film)|The Little Mermaid]]'', ''[[Beauty and the Beast (1991 film)|Beauty and the Beast]]'', ''[[Aladdin (1992 Disney film)|Aladdin]]'', ''The Lion King'') to the more 'cartoon' styles of the [[Warner Bros. Cartoons|Warner Bros. animation studio]]. Many of the [[Disney animated features]] are examples of full animation, as are non-Disney works, ''[[The Secret of NIMH]]'' (US, 1982), ''[[The Iron Giant]]'' (US, 1999), and ''[[Nocturna (Film)|Nocturna]]'' (Spain, 2007). Fully animated films are animated at 24 frames per second, with a combination of animation on ones and twos, meaning that drawings can be held for one frame out of 24 or two frames out of 24.{{sfn|Laybourne|1998|pp=25–26}}

==== Limited animation ====

{{Main|Limited animation}}

'''[[Limited animation]]''' involves the use of less detailed or more stylized drawings and methods of movement usually a choppy or &quot;skippy&quot; movement animation.{{sfn|Beckerman|2003|p=142}} Limited animation uses fewer drawings per second, thereby limiting the fluidity of the animation. This is a more economic technique. Pioneered by the artists at the American studio [[United Productions of America]],{{sfn|Beckerman|2003|pp=54–55}} limited animation can be used as a method of stylized artistic expression, as in ''[[Gerald McBoing-Boing]]'' (US, 1951), ''[[Yellow Submarine (1968 film)|Yellow Submarine]]'' (UK, 1968), and certain [[anime]] produced in Japan.{{sfn|Ledoux|1997|p=24, 29}} Its primary use, however, has been in producing cost-effective animated content for media for television (the work of Hanna-Barbera,{{sfn|Lawson|Persons|2004|p=82}} [[Filmation]],{{sfn|Solomon|1989|p=241}} and other TV animation studios{{sfn|Lawson|Persons|2004|p=xxi}}) and later [[the Internet]] ([[web cartoon]]s).

==== Rotoscoping ====

{{Main|Rotoscoping}}

'''Rotoscoping''' is a technique patented by [[Max Fleischer]] in 1917 where animators trace live-action movement, frame by frame.{{sfn|Crafton|1993|p=158}} The source film can be directly copied from actors' outlines into animated drawings,{{sfn|Laybourne|1998|pp=163–64}} as in ''[[The Lord of the Rings (1978 film)|The Lord of the Rings]]'' (US, 1978), or used in a stylized and expressive manner, as in ''[[Waking Life]]'' (US, 2001) and ''[[A Scanner Darkly (film)|A Scanner Darkly]]'' (US, 2006). Some other examples are ''[[Fire and Ice (1983 film)|Fire and Ice]]'' (US, 1983), ''[[Heavy Metal (film)|Heavy Metal]]'' (1981), and ''[[The Flowers of Evil (manga)|Aku no Hana]]'' (2013).

==== Live-action/animation ====

{{Main|Films with live action and animation}}

'''[[Films with live action and animation|Live-action/animation]]''' is a technique combining hand-drawn characters into live action shots or live action actors into animated shots.{{sfn|Laybourne|1998|pp=162–63}} One of the earlier uses was in [[Koko the Clown]] when Koko was drawn over live action footage.{{sfn|Beck|2004|pp=18–19}}. Walt Disney and Ub Iwerks created a series of ''[[Alice comedies]]'' (1923-1927), in which a live-action girl enters an animated world. Other examples include ''[[Allegro Non Troppo]]'' (Italy, 1976), ''[[Who Framed Roger Rabbit]]'' (US, 1988), ''[[Space Jam]]'' (US, 1996) and ''[[Osmosis Jones]]'' (US, 2001).

=== Stop motion animation ===
{{Main|Stop motion}}

'''Stop-motion animation''' is used to describe animation created by physically manipulating real-world objects and photographing them one frame of film at a time to create the illusion of movement.{{sfn|Solomon|1989|p=299}} There are many different types of stop-motion animation, usually named after the medium used to create the animation.{{sfn|Laybourne|1998|p=159}} Computer software is widely available to create this type of animation; traditional stop motion animation is usually less expensive but more time-consuming to produce than current computer animation.{{sfn|Laybourne|1998|p=159}}
* '''[[Puppet animation]]''' typically involves stop-motion puppet figures interacting in a constructed environment, in contrast to real-world interaction in model animation.{{sfn|Solomon|1989|p=171}} The puppets generally have an [[armature (sculpture)|armature]] inside of them to keep them still and steady to constrain their motion to particular joints.{{sfn|Laybourne|1998|pp=155–56}} Examples include ''[[The Tale of the Fox]]'' (France, 1937), ''[[The Nightmare Before Christmas]]'' (US, 1993), ''[[Corpse Bride]]'' (US, 2005), ''[[Coraline (film)|Coraline]]'' (US, 2009), the films of [[Jiří Trnka]] and the adult animated sketch-comedy television series ''[[Robot Chicken]]'' (US, 2005–present).
** '''[[Puppetoon]]''', created using techniques developed by [[George Pal]],{{sfn|Beck|2004|p=70}} are puppet-animated films that typically use a different version of a puppet for different frames, rather than simply manipulating one existing puppet.{{sfn|Beck|2004|pp=92–93}}
[[File:Claychick.jpg|thumb|A clay animation scene from a [[Finland|Finnish]] television commercial]]
* '''[[Clay animation]]''', or [[Plasticine]] animation (often called ''claymation'', which, however, is a [[Laika (company)|trademarked]] name), uses figures made of clay or a similar malleable material to create stop-motion animation.{{sfn|Solomon|1989|p=299}}{{sfn|Laybourne|1998|pp=150–151}} The figures may have an [[armature (sculpture)|armature]] or wire frame inside, similar to the related puppet animation (below), that can be manipulated to pose the figures.{{sfn|Laybourne|1998|pp=151–54}} Alternatively, the figures may be made entirely of clay, in the films of [[Bruce Bickford (animator)|Bruce Bickford]], where clay creatures morph into a variety of different shapes. Examples of clay-animated works include ''[[Gumby|The Gumby Show]]'' (US, 1957–1967), ''[[Mio Mao]]'' (Italy, 1974–2005), ''[[Morph (animation)|Morph]]'' shorts (UK, 1977–2000), ''[[Wallace and Gromit]]'' shorts (UK, as of 1989), [[Jan Švankmajer]]'s ''[[Dimensions of Dialogue]]'' ([[Czechoslovakia]], 1982), ''[[The Trap Door]]'' (UK, 1984). Films include ''[[Wallace &amp; Gromit: The Curse of the Were-Rabbit]]'', ''[[Chicken Run]]'' and ''[[The Adventures of Mark Twain (1985 film)|The Adventures of Mark Twain]]''.{{sfn|Beck|2004|p=250}}
** '''[[Strata-cut animation]]''', Strata-cut animation is most commonly a form of clay animation in which a long bread-like &quot;loaf&quot; of clay, internally packed tight and loaded with varying imagery, is sliced into thin sheets, with the animation camera taking a frame of the end of the loaf for each cut, eventually revealing the movement of the internal images within.{{sfn|Furniss|1998|pp=52–54}}
* '''[[Cutout animation]]''' is a type of stop-motion animation produced by moving two-dimensional pieces of material paper or cloth.{{sfn|Laybourne|1998|pp=59–60}} Examples include [[Terry Gilliam]]'s animated sequences from ''[[Monty Python's Flying Circus]]'' (UK, 1969–1974); ''[[Fantastic Planet]]'' (France/Czechoslovakia, 1973) ; ''[[Tale of Tales (1979 film)|Tale of Tales]]'' (Russia, 1979), The pilot episode of the adult television sitcom series (and sometimes in episodes) of ''[[South Park]]'' (US, 1997) and the music video Live for the moment, from Verona Riots band (produced by Alberto Serrano and Nívola Uyá, Spain 2014).
** '''[[Silhouette animation]]''' is a variant of cutout animation in which the characters are backlit and only visible as silhouettes.{{sfn|Culhane|1990|pp=170–171}} Examples include ''[[The Adventures of Prince Achmed]]'' ([[Weimar Republic]], 1926) and ''[[Ciné si|Princes et princesses]]'' (France, 2000).
* '''[[Model animation]]''' refers to stop-motion animation created to interact with and exist as a part of a live-action world.{{sfn|Harryhausen|Dalton|2008|pages=9–11}} Intercutting, [[matte (filmmaking)|matte]] effects and split screens are often employed to blend stop-motion characters or objects with live actors and settings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harryhausen_Dalton222–226&quot; /&gt; Examples include the work of [[Ray Harryhausen]], as seen in films, ''[[Jason and the Argonauts (1963 film)|Jason and the Argonauts]]'' (1963),&lt;ref name=&quot;Harryhausen_Dalton18&quot; /&gt; and the work of [[Willis H. O'Brien]] on films, ''[[King Kong (1933 film)|King Kong]]'' (1933).
** '''[[Go motion]]''' is a variant of model animation that uses various techniques to create [[motion blur]] between frames of film, which is not present in traditional stop-motion.{{sfn|Smith|1986|p=90}} The technique was invented by [[Industrial Light &amp; Magic]] and [[Phil Tippett]] to create [[special effect]] scenes for the film ''[[The Empire Strikes Back]]'' (1980).{{sfn|Watercutter|2012}} Another example is the dragon named &quot;Vermithrax&quot; from ''[[Dragonslayer (1981 film)|Dragonslayer]]'' (1981 film).{{sfn|Smith|1986|pages=91–95}}
* '''[[Object animation]]''' refers to the use of regular inanimate objects in stop-motion animation, as opposed to specially created items.{{sfn|Laybourne|1998|pp=51–57}}
** '''[[Graphic animation]]''' uses non-drawn flat visual graphic material (photographs, newspaper clippings, magazines, etc.), which are sometimes manipulated frame-by-frame to create movement.{{sfn|Laybourne|1998|p=128}} At other times, the graphics remain stationary, while the stop-motion camera is moved to create on-screen action.
** '''[[Brickfilm]]''' are a subgenre of object animation involving using [[Lego]] or other similar brick toys to make an animation.{{sfn|Paul|2005|pages=357–63}}{{sfn|Herman|2014}} These have had a recent boost in popularity with the advent of video sharing sites, [[YouTube]] and the availability of cheap cameras and animation software.{{sfn|Haglund|2014}}
* '''[[Pixilation]]''' involves the use of live humans as stop motion characters.{{sfn|Laybourne|1998|pp=75–79}} This allows for a number of surreal effects, including disappearances and reappearances, allowing people to appear to slide across the ground, and other effects.{{sfn|Laybourne|1998|pp=75–79}} Examples of pixilation include ''[[The Secret Adventures of Tom Thumb]]'' and ''[[Angry Kid]]'' shorts, and the [[academy award]]-winning ''[[Neighbours (1952 film)|Neighbours]]'' by [[Norman McLaren]].

=== Computer animation ===
{{Main|Computer animation}}
'''Computer animation''' encompasses a variety of techniques, the unifying factor being that the animation is created digitally on a computer.{{sfn|Culhane|1990|p=296}}{{sfn|Serenko|2007}} 2D animation techniques tend to focus on image manipulation while 3D techniques usually build virtual worlds in which characters and objects move and interact.{{sfn|Masson|2007|p=405}} 3D animation can create images that seem real to the viewer.{{sfn|Serenko|2007|p=482}}

==== 2D animation ====
{{main|2D computer graphics}}
[[File:Catenary animation.gif|thumb|A 2D animation of two circles joined by a chain]]

[[2D computer graphics|2D animation]] figures are created or edited on the computer using 2D [[Raster graphics|bitmap graphics]] and 2D [[vector graphics]].{{sfn|Masson|2007|p=165}} This includes automated computerized versions of traditional animation techniques, [[Interpolation|interpolated]] [[morphing]],{{sfn|Sito|2013|pp=32, 70, 132}} [[onion skinning]]{{sfn|Priebe|2006|pp=71–72}} and interpolated rotoscoping.

2D animation has many applications, including [[Scanimate|analog computer animation]], [[Flash animation]], and [[PowerPoint animation]]. [[Cinemagraph]]s are [[Still life photography|still photographs]] in the form of an [[animated GIF]] file of which part is animated.{{sfn|White|2006|p=392}}

Final line [[advection]] animation is a technique used in 2D animation,{{sfn|Lowe|Schnotz|2008|pp=246–47}} to give artists and animators more influence and control over the final product as everything is done within the same department.{{sfn|Masson|2007|pp=127–28}} Speaking about using this approach in ''[[Paperman]]'', John Kahrs said that &quot;Our animators can change things, actually erase away the CG underlayer if they want, and change the profile of the arm.&quot;{{sfn|Beck|2012}}

==== 3D animation ====
{{Main|Computer animation|3D computer graphics}}
3D animation is digitally modeled and manipulated by an animator. The animator usually starts by creating a 3D [[polygon mesh]] to manipulate.{{sfn|Masson|2007|p=88}} A mesh typically includes many vertices that are connected by edges and faces, which give the visual appearance of form to a 3D object or 3D environment.{{sfn|Masson|2007|p=88}} Sometimes, the mesh is given an internal digital skeletal structure called an [[Armature (computer animation)|armature]] that can be used to control the mesh by weighting the vertices.{{sfn|Sito|2013|p=208}}{{sfn|Masson|2007|pp=78–80}} This process is called rigging and can be used in conjunction with keyframes to create movement.{{sfn|Sito|2013|p=285}}

Other techniques can be applied, mathematical functions (e.g., gravity, particle simulations), simulated fur or hair, and effects, fire and [[fluid animation|water simulations]].{{sfn|Masson|2007|p=96}} These techniques fall under the category of 3D dynamics.{{sfn|Lowe|Schnotz|2008|p=92}}

===== 3D terms =====
* '''[[Cel-shaded animation]]''' is used to mimic traditional animation using computer software.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Cel Shading: the Unsung Hero of Animation?|url=http://www.animatormag.com/computer/cel-shading-hero-animation/|publisher=Animator Mag|accessdate=20 February 2016|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160305090445/http://www.animatormag.com/computer/cel-shading-hero-animation/|archivedate=5 March 2016|date=17 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shading looks stark, with less blending of colors. Examples include ''[[Skyland]]'' (2007, France), ''[[The Iron Giant]]'' (1999, United States), ''[[Futurama]]'' (Fox, 1999) ''[[Appleseed Ex Machina]]'' (2007, Japan), ''[[The Legend of Zelda: The Wind Waker]]'' (2002, Japan), ''[[The Legend of Zelda: Breath of the Wild]]'' (2017, Japan)
* '''[[Machinima]]''' – Films created by screen capturing in video games and virtual worlds. The term originated from the software introduction in the 1980s [[demoscene]], as well as the 1990s recordings of the [[first-person shooter]] video game ''[[Quake (video game)|Quake]]''.
* '''[[Motion capture]]''' is used when live-action actors wear special suits that allow computers to copy their movements into CG characters.{{sfn|Sito|2013|pp=207–08}}{{sfn|Masson|2007|p=204}} Examples include ''[[The Polar Express (film)|Polar Express]]'' (2004, US), ''[[Beowulf (2007 film)|Beowulf]]'' (2007, US), ''[[A Christmas Carol (2009 film)|A Christmas Carol]]'' (2009, US), ''[[The Adventures of Tintin (film)|The Adventures of Tintin]]'' (2011, US) ''[[Kochadaiiyaan|kochadiiyan]]'' (2014, India)
* '''[[Computer animation|Photo-realistic animation]]''' is used primarily for animation that attempts to resemble real life, using advanced rendering that mimics in detail skin, plants, water, fire, clouds, etc.{{sfn|Parent|2007|p=19}} Examples include ''[[Up (2009 film)|Up]]'' (2009, US), ''[[How to Train Your Dragon (film)|How to Train Your Dragon]]'' (2010, US)
* '''[[Physically based animation]]''' is animation using [[computer simulation]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Donald H. House|author2=John C. Keyser|title=Foundations of Physically Based Modeling and Animation|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ELXZDQAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q=animation&amp;f=false|date=30 November 2016|publisher=CRC Press|isbn=978-1-315-35581-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Mechanical animation ===
* '''[[Animatronics]]''' is the use of [[mechatronics]] to create machines that seem animate rather than robotic.
** '''[[Audio-Animatronics|Audio-Animatronics and Autonomatronics]]''' is a form of [[robotics]] animation, combined with 3-D animation, created by [[Walt Disney Imagineering]] for shows and attractions at Disney theme parks move and make noise (generally a recorded speech or song).{{sfn|Pilling|1997|p=249}} They are fixed to whatever supports them. They can sit and stand, and they cannot walk. An Audio-Animatron is different from an [[android (robot)|android]]-type robot in that it uses prerecorded movements and sounds, rather than responding to external stimuli. In 2009, Disney created an interactive version of the technology called Autonomatronics.{{sfn|O'Keefe|2014}}
** '''Linear Animation Generator''' is a form of animation by using static picture frames installed in a tunnel or a shaft. The animation illusion is created by putting the viewer in a linear motion, parallel to the installed picture frames.{{sfn|Parent|2007|pages=22–23}} The concept and the technical solution were invented in 2007 by Mihai Girlovan in Romania.
* '''[[Chuckimation]]''' is a type of animation created by the makers of the television series ''[[Action League Now!]]'' in which characters/props are thrown, or chucked from off camera or wiggled around to simulate talking by unseen hands.{{sfn|Kenyon|1998}}
* The '''[[Magic lantern#Moving images|magic lantern]]''' used mechanical slides to project moving images, probably since Christiaan Huygens invented this early image projector in 1659.

=== Other animation styles, techniques, and approaches ===
[[File:World of Color overview.jpg|thumb|''[[World of Color]]'' hydrotechnics at [[Disney California Adventure]] creates illusion of motion using 1200 fountains with high-definition projections on mist screens.]]
* '''Hydrotechnics''': a technique that includes lights, water, fire, fog, and lasers, with high-definition projections on mist screens.
* '''[[Drawn on film animation]]''': a technique where footage is produced by creating the images directly on [[film stock]], for example by [[Norman McLaren]],{{sfn|Faber|Walters|2004|p=1979}} [[Len Lye]] and [[Stan Brakhage]].
* '''[[Paint-on-glass animation]]''': a technique for making animated films by manipulating slow drying [[oil paint]]s on sheets of glass,{{sfn|Pilling|1997|p=222}} for example by [[Aleksandr Petrov (animator)|Aleksandr Petrov]].
* '''Erasure animation''': a technique using traditional 2D media, photographed over time as the artist manipulates the image. For example, [[William Kentridge]] is famous for his [[charcoal]] erasure films,{{sfn|Carbone|2010}} and [[Piotr Dumała]] for his auteur technique of animating scratches on plaster.
* '''[[Pinscreen animation]]''': makes use of a screen filled with movable pins that can be moved in or out by pressing an object onto the screen.{{sfn|Neupert|2011}} The screen is lit from the side so that the pins cast shadows. The technique has been used to create animated films with a range of textural effects difficult to achieve with traditional cel animation.{{sfn|Pilling|1997|p=204}}
* '''[[Sand animation]]''': sand is moved around on a back- or front-lighted piece of glass to create each frame for an animated film.{{sfn|Brown|2003|p=7}} This creates an interesting effect when animated because of the [[light]] [[Contrast (vision)|contrast]].{{sfn|Furniss|1998|pp=30–33}}
* '''[[Flip book]]''': a flip book (sometimes, especially in British English, called a flick book) is a book with a series of pictures that vary gradually from one page to the next, so that when the pages are turned rapidly, the pictures appear to animate by simulating motion or some other change.{{sfn|Laybourne|1998|pp=22–24}}{{sfn|Solomon|1989|pp=8–10}} Flip books are often illustrated books for children,{{sfn|Laybourne|1998|p=xiv}} they also be geared towards adults and employ a series of photographs rather than drawings. Flip books are not always separate books, they appear as an added feature in ordinary books or magazines, often in the page corners.{{sfn|Laybourne|1998|pp=22–24}} Software packages and websites are also available that convert digital video files into custom-made flip books.{{sfn|White|2006|p=203}}
* '''[[Character animation]]'''
* '''[[Multi-sketch]]ing'''
* '''[[Special effects animation]]'''

== See also ==
{{Portal|size=tiny|Animation}}
{{Wikipedia books|1=Animation}}
{{Div col|colwidth=20em}}
* [[12 basic principles of animation]]
* [[War film#Animated|Animated war film]]
* [[Animation department]]
* [[Animation software]]
* [[Anime]]
* [[Architectural animation]]
* [[Avar (animation variable)]]
* [[Computer-generated imagery]]
* [[Independent animation]]
* [[International Animated Film Association]]
* [[International Tournée of Animation]]
* [[List of film-related topics|List of motion picture topics]]
* [[Model sheet]]
* [[Motion graphic design]]
* [[Society for Animation Studies]]
* [[Tradigital art]]
* [[Wire-frame model]]

{{Div col end}}

== References ==
=== Citations ===
{{reflist|22em|refs=
&lt;ref name=&quot;Harryhausen_Dalton18&quot;&gt;{{Harvard citation no brackets|Harryhausen|Dalton|2008|page=18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Harryhausen_Dalton222–226&quot;&gt;{{Harvard citation no brackets|Harryhausen|Dalton|2008|pages=222–26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

=== Sources ===
; Journal articles
{{refbegin|35em}}
* {{cite journal
 |url = http://www.uca.edu/org/ccsmi/ccsmi/classicwork/Myth%20Revisited.htm |title = Journal of Film and Video
 |date=Spring 1993
 |journal=The Myth of Persistence of Vision Revisited
 |volume=45
 |issue=1
 |pages=3–13
 |last=Anderson
 |first=Joseph and Barbara
 |url-status=dead
 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20091124182503/http://www.uca.edu/org/ccsmi/ccsmi/classicwork/Myth%20Revisited.htm
 |archive-date=24 November 2009
}}
* {{cite journal
 |last=Serenko
 |first=Alexander
 |year=2007
 |title = Computers in Human Behavior
 |url = http://www.aserenko.com/papers/Serenko_Animation_Scale.pdf
 |journal=The Development of an Instrument to Measure the Degree of Animation Predisposition of Agent Users
 |volume=23
 |number=1
 |pages=478–95
 |ref=harv
}}
{{refend}}

; Books
{{refbegin|35em}}
* {{cite book
 |last=Baer
 |first=Eva
 |title=Metalwork in Medieval Islamic Art
 |year=1983
 |publisher=[[State University of New York Press]]
 |isbn=978-0-87395-602-4
 |pages=58, 86, 143, 151, 176, 201, 226, 243, 292, 304
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |last=Beck
 |first=Jerry
 |title=Animation Art: From Pencil to Pixel, the History of Cartoon, Anime &amp; CGI
 |year=2004
 |location=Fulhamm London
 |publisher=Flame Tree Publishing
 |isbn=978-1-84451-140-2
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |last=Beckerman
 |first=Howard
 |title=Animation: The Whole Story
 |publisher=Allworth Press
 |year=2003
 |isbn=978-1-58115-301-9
 |ref=harv
 |url = https://archive.org/details/animationwholest00beck
 }}
* {{cite book
 |last=Bendazzi
 |first=Giannalberto
 |title = Cartoons: One Hundred Years of Cinema Animation
 |url = https://archive.org/details/cartoons00gian
 |url-access=registration
 |location=Bloomington, Indiana
 |publisher=Indiana University Press
 |year=1994
 |isbn=978-0-253-20937-5
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |last=Buchan
 |first=Suzanne
 |title=Pervasive Animation
 |location=New York and London
 |publisher=Routledge
 |year=2013
 |isbn=978-0-415-80723-4
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |last = Canemaker
 |first = John
 |author-link = John Canemaker
 |title = Winsor McCay: His Life and Art
 |edition = Revised
 |year = 2005
 |publisher = Abrams Books
 |isbn = 978-0-8109-5941-5
 |ref = harv
 |url = https://archive.org/details/winsormccayhisli00cane
 }}
* {{cite book
 |last=Crafton
 |first=Donald
 |year=1993
 |title=Before Mickey: The Animated Film 1898–1928
 |publisher=University of Chicago Press
 |location=Chicago
 |isbn=978-0-226-11667-9
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |author-link = Shamus Culhane
 |last=Culhane
 |first=Shamus
 |title=Animation: Script to Screen
 |publisher=St. Martin's Press
 |year=1990
 |isbn=978-0-312-05052-8
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |last=Drazin
 |first=Charles
 |title=The Faber Book of French Cinema
 |year=2011
 |publisher=Faber &amp; Faber
 |isbn=978-0-571-21849-3
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |last=Finkielman
 |first=Jorge
 |title=The Film Industry in Argentina: An Illustrated Cultural History
 |year=2004
 |publisher=McFarland
 |location=North Carolina
 |isbn=978-0-7864-1628-8
 |page=[https://archive.org/details/filmindustryinar00fink/page/20 20]
 |ref=harv
 |url = https://archive.org/details/filmindustryinar00fink/page/20
 }}
* {{cite book
 |last=Furniss
 |first=Maureen
 |title=Art in Motion: Animation Aesthetics
 |year=1998
 |publisher=Indiana University Press
 |isbn=978-1-86462-039-9
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |last1=Faber
 |first1=Liz
 |last2=Walters
 |first2=Helen
 |title=Animation Unlimited: Innovative Short Films Since 1940
 |publisher=Laurence King Publishing
 |location=London
 |year=2004
 |isbn=978-1-85669-346-2
 |ref=harv
 |url-access=registration
 |url = https://archive.org/details/animationunlimit0000fabe
 }}
* {{cite book |last1=Godfrey |first1=Bob |last2=Jackson |first2=Anna |title=The Do-It-Yourself Film Animation Book |publisher=BBC Publications |year=1974 |isbn=978-0-563-10829-0 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book
 |first1=Ray
 |last1=Harryhausen
 |author1-link = Ray Harryhausen
 |last2=Dalton
 |first2=Tony
 |author2-link = Tony Dalton
 |title = A Century of Model Animation: From Méliès to Aardman
 |year=2008
 |publisher=Aurum Press
 |isbn=978-0-8230-9980-1
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |author-link = Kit Laybourne
 |last=Laybourne
 |first=Kit
 |title = The Animation Book: A Complete Guide to Animated Filmmaking – from Flip-books to Sound Cartoons to 3-D Animation
 |publisher=Three Rivers Press
 |location=New York
 |year=1998
 |isbn=978-0-517-88602-1
 |ref=harv
 |url = https://archive.org/details/animationbookcom00layb
 }}
* {{cite book
 |last=Lawson
 |first=Tim
 |last2=Persons
 |first2=Alisa
 |title = The Magic Behind the Voices
|title-link=The Magic Behind the Voices
 |trans-title = A Who's Who of Cartoon Voice Actors
 |publisher=University Press of Mississippi
 |year=2004
 |isbn=978-1-57806-696-4
 |ref=harv
 }}
* {{cite book
 |last=Ledoux
 |first=Trish
 |title = Complete Anime Guide: Japanese Animation Film Directory and Resource Guide
 |publisher=Tiger Mountain Press
 |year=1997
 |isbn=978-0-9649542-5-0
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |editor1-last = Lowe
 |editor1-first = Richard
 |editor2-last = Schnotz
 |editor2-first = Wolfgang
 |title = Learning with Animation. Research implications for design
 |publisher=Cambridge University Press
 |location=New York
 |year=2008
 |isbn=978-0-521-85189-3
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |last=Masson
 |first=Terrence
 |author-link = Terrence Masson
 |year=2007
 |title = CG101: A Computer Graphics Industry Reference
 |url = https://archive.org/details/isbn_9780977871001
 |series = Unique and personal histories of early computer animation production, plus a comprehensive foundation of the industry for all reading levels.
 |location=Williamstown, MA
 |publisher=Digital Fauxtography
 |isbn=978-0-9778710-0-1
 |ref=harv
 }}
* {{cite book
 |last=Needham
 |first=Joseph
 |year=1962
 |title=Physics and Physical Technology
 |publisher=Cambridge University Press
 |chapter=Science and Civilization in China
 |volume=IV
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |last1=Parent
 |first1=Rick
 |title=Computer Animation: Algorithms &amp; Techniques
 |year=2007
 |publisher=Morgan Kaufmann
 |location=Ohio State University
 |isbn=978-0-12-532000-9
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |last=Paul
 |first=Joshua
 |title=Digital Video Hacks
 |year=2005
 |publisher=O'Reilly Media
 |isbn=978-0-596-00946-5
 |ref=harv
 |url = https://archive.org/details/digitalvideohack00paul_0
 }}
* {{cite book
 |last=Pilling
 |first=Jayne
 |title = A Reader in Animation Studies
 |year=1997
 |publisher=Indiana University Press
 |editor=Society of Animation Studies
 |isbn=978-1-86462-000-9
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |first=Ken A.
 |last=Priebe
 |title=The Art of Stop-Motion Animation
 |year=2006
 |publisher=Thompson Course Technology
 |isbn=978-1-59863-244-6
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |first=Richard
 |last=Neupert
 |title=French Animation History
 |year=2011
 |publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons
 |isbn=978-1-4443-3836-2
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |last1=Rojas
 |first1=Carlos
 |last2=Chow
 |first2=Eileen
 |title = The Oxford Handbook of Chinese Cinemas
 |year=2013
 |publisher=Oxford University Press
 |isbn=978-0-19-998844-0
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |last=Herman
 |first=Sarah
 |year=2014
 |title = Brick Flicks: A Comprehensive Guide to Making Your Own Stop-Motion LEGO Movies
 |publisher=Skyhorse Publishing
 |location=New York
 |isbn=978-1-62914-649-2
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |last=Shaffer
 |first=Joshua C.
 |title = Discovering The Magic Kingdom: An Unofficial Disneyland Vacation Guide
 |year= 2010
 |publisher=Author House
 |location=Indiana
 |isbn=978-1-4520-6312-6
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |last=Solomon
 |first=Charles
 |year=1989
 |title = Enchanted Drawings: The History of Animation
 |location=New York
 |publisher=Random House, Inc.
 |isbn=978-0-394-54684-1
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |last=Thomas
 |first=Bob
 |title = Walt Disney, the Art of Animation: The Story of the Disney Studio Contribution to a New Art
 |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=Pw3WAAAAMAAJ
 |year=1958
 |work=Walt Disney Studios
 |publisher=Simon and Schuster
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |last1=Thomas
 |first1=Frank
 |author1-link = Frank Thomas (animator)
 |last2=Johnston
 |first2=Ollie
 |author2-link = Ollie Johnston
 |title = Disney Animation: The Illusion of Life
 |title-link=Disney Animation: The Illusion of Life
 |publisher=Abbeville Press
 |year=1981
 |isbn=978-0-89659-233-9
 |ref=harv
 }}
* {{cite book
 |first1=Siegfried
 |last1=Zielinski
 |title=Audiovisions: Cinema and Television as Entr'actes in History
 |year=1999
 |publisher=Amsterdam University Press
 |isbn=978-90-5356-303-8
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |last=Sito
 |first=Tom
 |title = Moving Innovation: A History of Computer Animation
 |year=2013
 |location=Massachusetts
 |publisher=[[MIT Press]]
 |isbn=978-0-262-01909-5
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |title = Industrial Light &amp; Magic: The Art of Special Effects
 |first = Thomas G.
 |last = Smith
 |year = 1986
 |publisher = Ballantine Books
 |location = New York
 |isbn=978-0-345-32263-0
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |last=White
 |first=Tony
 |title = Animation from Pencils to Pixels: Classical Techniques for the Digital Animator
 |year=2006
 |location=Milton Park
 |publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis
 |isbn=978-0-240-80670-9
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |last=Williams
 |first=Richard
 |author-link = Richard Williams (animator)
 |title = The Animator's Survival Kit
 |title-link = The Animator's Survival Kit
 |year=2001
 |publisher=Faber and Faber
 |isbn=978-0-571-20228-7
 |ref=harv
 }}
{{refend}}

; Online sources
{{refbegin|35em}}
* {{cite web |last=Amidi |first=Amid |title = NY Film Critics Didn't like a Single Animated Film This Year |url = http://www.cartoonbrew.com/feature-film/ny-film-critics-didnt-like-a-single-animated-film-this-year-53464.html |publisher=Cartoon Brew |access-date=19 February 2016 |date=2 December 2011
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite magazine
 |last=Ball
 |first=Ryan
 |title=Oldest Animation Discovered in Iran
 |url = http://www.animationmagazine.net/features/oldest-animation-discovered-in-iran/
 |magazine=Animation Magazine
 |accessdate=15 March 2016
 |date=12 March 2008
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite web
 |url = http://www.cartoonbrew.com/cgi/a-little-more-about-disneys-paperman-63782.html
 |title=A Little More About Disney's &quot;Paperman&quot;
 |last=Beck
 |first=Jerry
 |date=2 July 2012
 |publisher=Cartoon Brew
 |access-date=
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite web
 |url = http://www.awn.com/mag/issue1.4/articles/bendazzi1.4.html
 |title = The Untold Story of Argentina's Pioneer Animator |publisher=Animation World Network
 |last=Bendazzi
 |first=Giannalberto
 |year=1996
 |access-date=29 April 2016
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite web
 |url = http://www.boi.gov.ph/pdf/valuepropositions/Animation/Animation.pdf
 |title=Animation
 |date=November 2009
 |access-date=24 July 2012
 |website=boi.gov.ph
 |publisher=Board of Investments
 |url-status=dead
 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20121019232801/http://www.boi.gov.ph/pdf/valuepropositions/Animation/Animation.pdf
 |archive-date=19 October 2012
 |df=
 |ref = {{SfnRef|Board of Investments |2009 }}
}}
* {{cite web |url = http://academic.evergreen.edu/curricular/eat/handouts/Pictures/CutSandPaintRules.pdf |title = Experimental Animation Techniques |year=2003 |last=Brown |first=Margery |access-date=11 November 2005 |publisher=Evergreen State Collage |location=Olympia, WA |url-status=dead |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20080307025951/http://academic.evergreen.edu/curricular/eat/handouts/Pictures/CutSandPaintRules.pdf |archive-date=7 March 2008 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite magazine
 |last=Carbone
 |first= Ken
 |title=Stone-Age Animation in a Digital World: William Kentridge at MoMA
 |url = http://www.fastcompany.com/1561390/stone-age-animation-digital-world-william-kentridge-moma
 |magazine=Fast Company
 |access-date=7 March 2016
 |date=24 February 2010
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite magazine
 |last=Haglund
 |first=David
 |title = The Oldest Known LEGO Movie
 |url = http://www.slate.com/blogs/browbeat/2014/02/07/lego_movie_brickfilms_go_back_to_1973_watch_the_very_first_video.html
 |magazine=Slate
 |access-date=25 February 2016
 |date=7 February 2014
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite web
 |url = http://www.theheritagetrust.wordpress.com/2012/07/25/worlds-oldest-animation
 |title = World's Oldest Animation?
 |publisher=The Heritage Trust
 |website=theheritagetrust.wordpress.com
 |date=25 July 2012
 |ref = {{SfnRef|The Heritage Trust|2012 }}
 |url-status=dead
 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20151022192615/https://theheritagetrust.wordpress.com/2012/07/25/worlds-oldest-animation/
 |archive-date=22 October 2015
 }}
* {{cite web
 |last = Kenyon
 |first = Heather
 |title = How'd They Do That?: Stop-Motion Secrets Revealed
 |url = http://www.awn.com/animationworld/howd-they-do-stop-motion-secrets-revealed
 |publisher=Animation World Network
 |access-date=2 March 2016
 |date=1 February 1998
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite web
 |last=Nagel
 |first=Jan
 |title = Gender in Media: Females Don't Rule
 |url = http://www.awn.com/animationworld/gender-media-females-dont-rule
 |publisher=Animation World Network
 |accessdate=3 March 2016
 |date=21 May 2008
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite news
 |last=McDuling
 |first=John
 |title = Hollywood Is Giving Up on Comedy
 |url = https://www.theatlantic.com/entertainment/archive/2014/07/the-completely-serious-decline-of-the-hollywood-comedy/373914/
 |access-date=20 July 2014
 |work=The Atlantic
 |publisher=The Atlantic Monthly Group
 |date=3 July 2014
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite web
 |last=McLaughlin
 |first=Dan
 |title = A Rather Incomplete But Still Fascinating
 |url = http://animation.filmtv.ucla.edu/NewSite/WebPages/Histories.html
 |website = Film TV
 |publisher=UCLA
 |year=2001
 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20091119055944/http://animation.filmtv.ucla.edu/NewSite/WebPages/Histories.html
 |archive-date=19 November 2009
 |access-date=12 February 2013
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite web
 |last = O'Keefe |first = Matt
 |url = http://www.themeparktourist.com/features/20141110/29600/6-major-innovations-sprung-heads-disney-imagineers
 |title = 6 Major Innovations That Sprung from the Heads of Disney Imagineers
 |publisher=Theme Park Tourist
 |access-date=9 March 2016
 |date=11 November 2014
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite journal
 |last=Watercutter
 |first=Angela
 |url = https://www.wired.com/2012/05/phil-tippett-feature/
 |title=35 Years After Star Wars, Effects Whiz Phil Tippett Is Slowly Crafting a Mad God
 |journal=Wired
 |date=24 May 2012
 |access-date=6 February 2016
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite magazine
 |url = http://www.vanityfair.com/culture/2010/03/disney-animation-girls-201003
 |title=Coloring the Kingdom
 |last=Zohn
 |first=Patricia
 |date=28 February 2010
 |magazine=[[Vanity Fair (magazine)|Vanity Fair]]
 |access-date=7 December 2015
 |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite web
 |title = Walt Disney's Oscars
 |url = http://www.waltdisney.org/blog/walt-disneys-oscars%C2%AE
 |date = 22 February 2013
 |publisher = The Walt Disney Family Museum
 |access-date = 22 February 2016
 |ref = {{SfnRef|Walt Disney Family Museum|2013}}
 |archive-url  = https://web.archive.org/web/20150322054517/http://www.waltdisney.org/blog/walt-disneys-oscars%C2%AE
 |archive-date = 22 March 2015
 |url-status = dead
 |df = dmy-all
}}
* {{cite web
 |title = Władysław Starewicz – Biography
 |url = http://culture.pl/en/artist/wladyslaw-starewicz
 |website=culture.pl
 |date=16 April 2012
 |publisher=Adam Mickiewicz Institute
 |access-date=9 February 2016
 |ref = {{SfnRef|Adam Mickiewicz Institute|2012}}
}}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Wiktionary|animation}}
{{Commons category|Animations}}
{{Library resources box
|by=no
|onlinebooks=no
|others=no
|about=yes
|label=Animation }}
* [http://www.sparetimelabs.com/animato/animato/cartoon/cartoon.html The making of an 8-minute cartoon short]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20091001071111/http://www.nfb.ca/film/animando_english/ &quot;Animando&quot;], a 12-minute film demonstrating 10 different animation techniques (and teaching how to use them).
* [https://www.histv.net/animation Bibliography on animation – Websiite &quot;Histoire de la télévision&quot;]
* {{curlie|Arts/Animation}}

{{Animation}}
{{Film genres}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Animation}}
[[Category:Cartooning]]
[[Category:Animation| ]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Film and video technology]]</text>
      <sha1>fkcd90sf1izt4h7iowtvp62rav9p5t9</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
