  <page>
    <title>Politics of Ivory Coast</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5567</id>
    <revision>
      <id>927864680</id>
      <parentid>922315443</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-11-25T07:23:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>182.233.134.154</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Politics of Côte d'Ivoire}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2011}}
The '''Politics of [[Ivory Coast]]''' takes place in a framework of a [[Presidential system|presidential]] [[Representative democracy|representative democratic]] [[republic]], whereby the [[President of Ivory Coast]] is both [[head of state]] and [[head of government]], and of a [[multi-party system]]. [[Executive power]] is exercised by the President and the Government. [[Legislative power]] is vested in both the government and parliament.

The capital since 1983 is [[Yamoussoukro]]; however, [[Abidjan]] remains the  commercial  center. Most countries maintain their embassies in Abidjan. A civil war was fought in Ivory Coast between 2002–2004 and a second civil war broke out in March 2011 following contested elections that saw president-elect Alassane Ouattara come into power in 2011 and reelected in 2015. 

==Civil war==
{{further|Civil war in Côte d'Ivoire}}

Troops, mostly hailing from the north of the country, mutinied in the early hours of September 19, 2002. They soon after launched attacks in many cities, including Abidjan. By lunchtime, they had control of the north of the country. Their principal claim relates to the definition of who is a citizen of Ivory Coast (and so who can stand for election as president), voting rights and their representation in government in [[Abidjan]]. The events in Abidjan shows that it is not a tribal issue, but a crisis of transition from a dictatorship to a democracy, with the clashes inherent in the definition of citizenship.
Forces involved in the conflict include:
* Government forces, the National Army (FANCI), also called ''loyalists'', formed and equipped essentially since 2003
* The ''[[Congrès Panafricain des Jeunes et des Patriotes|Young Patriots]]'': nationalist groups aligned with President [[Laurent Gbagbo]]
* [[Mercenaries]] recruited by President Gbagbo:
** allegedly, [[Belarus]]ians
** some former combatants of [[Liberia]], including under-17 youths, forming the so-called &quot;Lima militia&quot; [http://hrw.org/english/docs/2005/03/30/cotedi10404.htm]
* ''[[Forces Nouvelles de Côte d'Ivoire|New Forces]]'' (Forces Nouvelles, FN), ex-northern rebels, who hold 60% of the country; their political expression is the ''Mouvement patriotique de Côte d'Ivoire'', or MPCI
* French forces: troops sent within the framework of [[Operation Unicorn]] and under [[UN Mandate|UN mandate]] ([[United Nations Operation in Côte d'Ivoire]]), 3000 men in February 2003 and 4600 in November 2004;
* Soldiers of the [[Economic Community of West African States]] (ECOWAS), ''White helmets'', also under the UN.
&lt;!--

==Political conditions==
In a region whose political systems have otherwise been noted for lack of stability, Ivory Coast showed remarkable political stability since its independence from France in 1960, until 2002.

''The contents of this section are outdated. See [[Civil war in Côte d'Ivoire]] for recent data.''

When many other countries in the region were undergoing repeated [[military coup]]s, experimenting with [[Marxism]], and developing ties with the [[Soviet Union]] and the People's Republic of China, Ivory Coast - under [[Félix Houphouët-Boigny]], president from independence until his death in December 1993 - maintained a close political allegiance to the Western World and good relationships with France and the United States. President Bédié is very familiar with the United States, having served as Ivory Coast's first [[Ambassador (diplomacy)|ambassador]] to this country.

Looking toward the country's future, the fundamental issue is whether its political system will maintain the stability which is the [[sine qua non]] for investor confidence and further economic development. Ivory Coast evolved, with relatively little violence or dislocation, from a single-party state, beginning in 1990. Opposition parties, independent newspapers, and independent [[trade union]]s were made legal at that time. Since those major changes occurred, the country's pace of political change has been slow. Whether further [[democracy|democratic]] reform will take place, adequate to meet future challenges, is unknown. As is generally true in the region, the business environment is one in which personal contact and connections remain important, where rule of law does not prevail with assurance, and where the legislative and judicial branches of the government remain weak. The political system remains highly centralized with the president dominating both the ruling party and the legislature and judiciary. Ivory Coast's efforts to break down central state control of the economy are undermined by the state's continued central control of the political system.

Ivory Coast has a high [[population growth rate]], a high crime rate (particularly in Abidjan), a high incidence of AIDS, a multiplicity of [[tribe]]s, sporadic student unrest, a different rate of in-country development according to region, and a dichotomy of religion associated with region and tribe. These factors put stress on the political system and will become more of a problem if the economy-not quite as dependent today on [[cocoa]] and coffee as it was some years ago but still dependent - takes a plunge similar to that of the 1980s.

The political system in Ivory Coast is president-dominated. The Prime Minister concentrates principally on coordinating and implementing economic policy. The key decisions - political, military, or economic - continue to be made by President Bédié, as they were made by President Houphouët-Boigny. However, political dialogue is much freer today than prior to 1990, especially due to the opposition press, which vocalizes its criticism of the regime. The Ivorian Constitution affords the legislature some independence, but it has not been widely exercised. Until 1990, all legislators were from the [[Democratic Party of Côte d'Ivoire – African Democratic Rally|Democratic Party of Côte d'Ivoire]] (PDCI). After the most recent elections (1995-1996), the PDCI continues to hold 149 out of 175 seats. The PDCI's &quot;core&quot; region may be described as the terrain of the [[Baoule]] tribe in the country's center, home of both Houphouët-Boigny and Bédié; however, the PDCI is well-entrenched in all parts of Ivory Coast.

The remaining 26 seats in the National Assembly are divided equally by the only two other parties of national scope-the FPI [[Ivorian Popular Front]] (FPI) and Rally of Republicans (RDR). The oldest opposition party is the FPI, a moderate party which has a socialist coloration but which is more concerned with democratic reform than radical economic change; it is strongest in the terrain of its Bete tribe leader, Laurent Gbagbo. The non-ideological RDR was formed in September 1994 by former members of the PDCI's reformist wing who hoped that former Prime Minister Alassane Ouattara would run and prevail in the 1995 presidential election (but who was disqualified by subsequent legislation requiring 5-year residency); it is strongest in the Muslim north.

The presidential election of October 1995 was boycotted by the FPI and RDR because of Ouattara's disqualification and the absence of an independent electoral commission (among other grievances). Their &quot;active boycott&quot; produced a certain amount of violence and hundreds of arrests (with a number of the arrestees not tried for 2-1/2 years). These grievances remain unaddressed, with the next round of elections coming in the year 2000.--&gt;

==Executive branch==
{{office-table}}
|[[President of Ivory Coast|President]]
|[[Alassane Ouattara]]
|[[Rally of the Republicans]]
|4 December 2011
|- 
|[[Vice-President of Ivory Coast|Vice-President]]
|[[Daniel Kablan Duncan]]
|[[Democratic Party of Côte d'Ivoire – African Democratic Rally|Democratic Party]]
|10 January 2017
|- 
|[[List of heads of government of Ivory Coast|Prime Minister]]
|[[Amadou Gon Coulibaly]]
|[[Rally of the Republicans]]
|10 January 2017
|}

[[Ivory Coast]]'s 1959 constitution provides for strong presidency within the framework of a [[separation of powers]]. The executive is personified in the [[President of Ivory Coast|president]], elected for a five-year term. The president is commander in chief of the armed forces, may negotiate and ratify certain [[treaty|treaties]], and may submit a bill to a national [[referendum]] or to the [[National Assembly of Ivory Coast|National Assembly]]. According to the constitution, the President of the National Assembly assumes the presidency in the event of a vacancy, and he completes the remainder of the deceased president's term. The cabinet is selected by and is responsible to the president. Changes are being proposed to some of these provisions, to extend term of office to 7 years, establish a senate, and make president of the [[senate]] interim successor to the president.

Laurent Gbagbo took power following a popular overthrow of the interim leader Gen. [[Robert Guéï]] who had claimed a dubious victory in presidential elections; Gen. Guéï himself had assumed power on 25 December 1999, following a military coup against the government of former President [[Henri Konan Bédié]]. Gbagbo was elected president in 2000 in an election boycotted by many oppositional forces. The president is elected by popular vote for a five-year term. The prime minister is appointed by the president.[[Alassane Ouattara]] is currently the president of Ivory Coast. He was reelected in the [[Ivorian presidential election, 2015|2015 Ivorian presidential election]].

After a new [[Constitution of Ivory Coast|constitution]] was approved by [[Ivorian constitutional referendum, 2016|referendum]], it is expected President [[Alassane Ouattara]] would appoint a [[Vice-President of Ivory Coast|Vice-President]] before [[Ivorian presidential election, 2020|2020]].
The [[President of Ivory Coast|President]] and [[Vice-President of Ivory Coast|Vice-President]] will run on a joint ticket from [[Ivorian presidential election, 2020|2020]]. They will be both elected for a five-year term, with only one possible reelection. The [[Vice-President of Ivory Coast|Vice-President]] will replace the [[President of Ivory Coast|President]] in case of death, resignation and any other vacancy, .

==Legislative branch==

[[File:Asnat codivoire.jpg|thumb|[[National Assembly of Ivory Coast]].]]
[[Parliament of Ivory Coast]] is a bicameral body composed by the [[National Assembly of Ivory Coast|National Assembly]] and the [[Senate (Ivory Coast)|Senate of Ivory Coast]]. Prior to November 2016 and the future creation of the Senate, the [[Parliament of Ivory Coast]] was only composed of the [[National Assembly of Ivory Coast|National Assembly]].
The [[National Assembly of Ivory Coast|National Assembly]] (''Assemblée Nationale'') has 255 members, elected for a five-year term in single-seat [[constituency|constituencies]]. It passes on legislation typically introduced by the president although it also can introduce legislation.
The [[Senate (Ivory Coast)|Senate of Ivory Coast]] (''Sénat'') will have two third of senators indirectly elected and one third appointed by the president-elect, elected five-year term in single-seat [[constituency|constituencies]]. 
Ivory Coast is a [[one party dominant state]] with the [[Rally of the Republicans]] in power.

==Judicial branch==
{{Main|Judicial system of the Ivory Coast}}
The judicial system culminates in the [[Supreme Court of Ivory Coast]]. The High Court of Justice is competent to try government officials for major offenses. The Supreme Court or Court Supreme consists of four chambers: Judicial Chamber for criminal cases, Audit Chamber for financial cases, Constitutional Chamber for judicial review cases, and Administrative Chamber for civil cases; there is no legal limit to the number of members.

==Political parties and elections==
{{elect|List of political parties in Ivory Coast|Elections in Ivory Coast}}
{{Ivorian presidential election, 2010}}
{{Ivorian parliamentary election, 2001}}

After five years of delays, new elections were finally held in 2010. The first round of elections were held peacefully, and widely hailed as free and fair. Runoffs are scheduled for 28 November 2010, after being delayed one week from the original date of 21 November. Laurent Gbagbo will defend his post as president against former Prime Minister Alassane Ouattara.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.cnn.com/2010/WORLD/africa/11/10/ivory.coast.runoff/ |title=Ivory Coast postpones presidential runoff vote |author=Eric Agnero |date=10 November 2010 |publisher=CNN |accessdate=11 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Administrative divisions==
{{main|Departments of Ivory Coast}}
For administrative purposes, Ivory Coast is divided into 58 [[Department (subnational entity)|departments]], each headed by a [[prefect]] appointed by the central government. There are 196 [[commune (subnational entity)|commune]]s, each headed by an elected mayor, plus the city of [[Abidjan]] with ten mayors.

The 58 departments (''départements'', singular - ''département'') are listed in the article [[Departments of Ivory Coast]].

==International organization participation==
[[ACP (Lomé Convention)|ACP]], [[African Development Bank|AfDB]], [[United Nations Economic Commission for Africa|ECA]], [[Economic Community of West African States|ECOWAS]], [[Conseil de l'Entente|Entente]], [[Food and Agriculture Organization|FAO]], [[Franc zone|FZ]], [[Group of 24|G-24]], [[Group of 77|G-77]], [[International Atomic Energy Agency|IAEA]], [[International Bank for Reconstruction and Development|IBRD]], [[International Civil Aviation Organization|ICAO]], [[International Criminal Court|ICCt]] (signatory), [[International Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement|ICRM]], [[International Development Association|IDA]], [[Islamic Development Bank|IDB]], [[International Fund for Agricultural Development|IFAD]], [[International Finance Corporation|IFC]], [[International Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement|IFRCS]], [[International Labour Organization|ILO]], [[International Monetary Fund|IMF]], [[International Maritime Organization|IMO]], [[Interpol (organization)|Interpol]], [[IOC]], [[International Organization for Migration|IOM]], [[International Organization for Standardization|ISO]], [[International Telecommunication Union|ITU]], [[International Trade Union Confederation|ITUC]], [[MONUC]], [[Non-Aligned Movement|NAM]], [[Organisation of African Unity|OAU]], [[Organisation of Islamic Cooperation|OIC]], [[Organisation for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons|OPCW]], UN, [[United Nations Conference on Trade and Development|UNCTAD]], [[UNESCO]], [[United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees|UNHCR]], [[United Nations Industrial Development Organization|UNIDO]], [[Universal Postal Union|UPU]], [[West African Development Bank|WADB]] (regional), [[West African Economic and Monetary Union|WAEMU]], [[World Customs Organization|WCO]], [[World Federation of Trade Unions|WFTU]], [[World Health Organization|WHO]], [[World Intellectual Property Organization|WIPO]], [[World Meteorological Organization|WMO]], [[World Tourism Organization|WToO]], [[World Trade Organization|WTrO]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links and references==
* [[CIA World Factbook]] 2003
*[https://2009-2017.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2846.htm]

{{Côte d'Ivoire topics}}
{{Africa in topic|Politics of}}

[[Category:Politics of Ivory Coast| ]]</text>
      <sha1>81v8rku0avielez2188c0bwp3ook9q5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
