  <page>
    <title>Politics of Croatia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5577</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941726587</id>
      <parentid>940884674</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-20T08:19:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Nightstallion</username>
        <id>149211</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Executive */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Politics of Croatia}} 
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2012}}
The '''politics of Croatia''' are defined by a [[parliamentary system|parliamentary]], [[representative democracy|representative democratic]] [[republic]] framework, where the [[Prime Minister of Croatia]] is the head of government in a [[multi-party system]]. [[Executive power]] is exercised by the [[Croatian Government|Government]] and the [[President of Croatia]]. [[Legislative power]] is vested in the [[Croatian Parliament]] ({{lang-hr|Sabor}}). The [[Judiciary]] is independent of the executive and the legislature. The parliament adopted the current [[Constitution of Croatia]] on 22 December 1990 and decided to declare independence from [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]] on 25 May 1991. The Constitutional Decision on the Sovereignty and Independence of the Republic of Croatia
came into effect on 8 October 1991. The constitution has since been amended several times.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Chronology|url=https://www.constituteproject.org/ontology/chronology?lang=en|website=Constitute|accessdate=28 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first modern parties in the country developed in the middle of the 19th century, and their agenda and appeal changed, reflecting major social changes, such as the breakup of [[Austria-Hungary]], the [[Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes]], dictatorship and social upheavals in the kingdom, [[World War II]], the establishment of Communist rule and the breakup of the [[SFR Yugoslavia]].

The President of the Republic ({{lang-hr|Predsjednik/ica Republike}}) is the [[head of state]] and the [[commander in chief]] of the [[Military of Croatia|Croatian armed forces]] and is directly elected to serve a five-year term.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Croatia 1991 (rev. 2010)|url=https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Croatia_2010?lang=en#397|website=Constitute|accessdate=28 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Government of Croatia|government]] ({{lang-hr|Vlada}}), the main executive power of Croatia, is headed by the prime minister, who has four deputy prime ministers who serve also as government ministers. Twenty ministers are in charge of particular activities. The executive branch is responsible for proposing legislation and a budget, executing the laws, and guiding the foreign and internal policies. The [[Parliament of Croatia|parliament]] is a [[unicameral]] legislative body. The number of ''Sabor'' representatives (MPs) ranges from 100 to 160; they are elected by popular vote to serve four-year terms. The powers of the legislature include enactment and amendment of the constitution and laws; adoption of the [[government budget]], declarations of war and peace, defining national boundaries, calling [[referendum|referenda]] and elections, appointments and relief of officers, supervising the Government of Croatia and other holders of public powers responsible to the Sabor, and granting of amnesties. The Croatian constitution and legislation provides for regular presidential and parliamentary elections, and the election of county prefects (county presidents) and assemblies, and city and municipal mayors and councils.

Croatia has a three-tiered, independent judicial system governed by the Constitution of Croatia and national legislation enacted by the Sabor. The [[Croatian Supreme Court|Supreme Court]] ({{lang-hr|Vrhovni sud}}) is the highest court of appeal in Croatia,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Croatia 1991 (rev. 2010)|url=https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Croatia_2010?lang=en#514|website=Constitute|accessdate=28 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; while municipal and county courts are courts of [[general jurisdiction]]. Specialised courts in Croatia are: [[Commercial Court (Croatia)|commercial court]]s and the Superior Commercial Court, [[misdemeanour]] courts and the Superior Misdemeanour Court, [[administrative court]]s and the Superior Administrative Court. [[Croatian Constitutional Court]] ({{lang-hr|Ustavni sud}}) is a court that deals primarily with constitutional law. Its main authority is to rule on whether laws that are challenged are in fact unconstitutional, i.e., whether they conflict with constitutionally established rights and freedoms. The [[State Attorney's Office]] represents the state in legal proceedings.

{{Democracy Index rating|Croatia|flawed democracy|2019}}

==Legal framework==
{{main|Constitution of Croatia}}
Croatia is a [[unitary state|unitary]] democratic parliamentary republic. Following the collapse of the ruling [[Communist League of Yugoslavia|Communist League]], Croatia adopted a new [[Constitution of Croatia|constitution]] in 1990 – which replaced the 1974 constitution adopted by the [[Socialist Republic of Croatia]] – and organised its first multi-party elections.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTimes-Elections2-HRV1990&quot;&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=The New York Times|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1990/05/09/world/evolution-in-europe-conservatives-win-in-croatia.html?ref=croatia|title=EVOLUTION IN EUROPE; Conservatives Win in Croatia|date=9 May 1990|accessdate=14 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; While the 1990 constitution remains in force, it has been amended four times since its adoption—in 1997, 2000, 2001 and 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;CC-Hist&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JL-ustav&quot;/&gt; Croatia declared independence from Yugoslavia on 8 October 1991, which led to the [[breakup of Yugoslavia]]. Croatia's status as a country was internationally recognised by the United Nations in 1992.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sabor-Independence-8Oct1991&quot;&gt;{{cite web|work=Official web site of the Parliament of Croatia|publisher=Sabor|url=http://www.sabor.hr/Default.aspx?art=20091&amp;sec=2462|title=Ceremonial session of the Croatian Parliament on the occasion of the Day of Independence of the Republic of Croatia|date=7 October 2004|accessdate=29 July 2012|archivedate=6 August 2010|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100806100830/http://www.sabor.hr/Default.aspx?art=20091&amp;sec=2462}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT-UN-membership&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1992/05/23/world/3-ex-yugoslav-republics-are-accepted-into-un.html|title=3 Ex-Yugoslav Republics Are Accepted Into U.N.|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|author=Paul L. Montgomery|date=23 May 1992|accessdate=29 July 2012|archivedate=16 April 2009|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090416092940/http://www.nytimes.com/1992/05/23/world/3-ex-yugoslav-republics-are-accepted-into-un.html|author-link=Paul L. Montgomery}}&lt;/ref&gt; Under its 1990 constitution, Croatia operated a [[semi-presidential system]] until 2000 when it switched to a [[parliamentary system]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC-CroProfile&quot;&gt;{{cite news|work=BBC News|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/country_profiles/1097128.stm|title=Croatia country profile|date=20 July 2011|accessdate=14 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Government powers in Croatia are divided into legislative, executive and judiciary powers.&lt;ref name=&quot;VRH-PoliticalStructure&quot;&gt;{{cite web|publisher=[[Government of Croatia]]|url= http://www.vlada.hr/en/about_croatia/information/political_structure| title=Political Structure|date=6 May 2007|accessdate=14 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The legal system of Croatia is [[civil law (legal system)|civil law]] and, along with the institutional framework, is strongly influenced by the legal heritage of Austria-Hungary.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Tomasz Giaro|title=Modernisierung durch Transfer im 19. und frühen 20. Jahrhundert Von Tomasz Giaro|url=https://books.google.com/?id=I_roYQzSkVoC|year=2006|publisher=Vittorio Klostermann|isbn=978-3-465-03489-6|language=German|accessdate=15 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the time [[Accession of Croatia to the European Union|EU accession negotiations]] were completed on 30 June 2010, Croatian legislation was fully harmonised with the [[Community acquis]].&lt;ref name=&quot;DELHRV-overview&quot;&gt;{{cite web|publisher=Delegation of the European Union to the Republic of Croatia|url=http://www.delhrv.ec.europa.eu/?lang=en&amp;content=62|title=Overview of EU – Croatia relations|accessdate=14 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Croatia became a member state of the [[European Union]] on 1 July 2013.

==Executive==
{{main|Government of Croatia|President of Croatia}}
[[File:Vlada Republike Hrvatske.jpg|thumb|[[Banski dvori]], seat of the [[Government of Croatia]]]]
The President of the Republic ({{lang-hr|Predsjednik/ica Republike}}) is the head of state; he or she is directly elected and serves a five-year term. The president is the commander in chief of the [[Military of Croatia|armed forces]], has the procedural duty of appointing the prime minister with the consent of the Sabor (Parliament) through a majority vote (majority of all MPs), and has some influence on foreign policy.&lt;ref name=&quot;VRH-PoliticalStructure&quot;/&gt; The most recent presidential election was held on 11 January 2015 and was won by [[Kolinda Grabar-Kitarović]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The President of the Republic of Criatia. Kolinda Grabar-Kitarović - Biography|url=http://predsjednica.hr/stranica/5/|accessdate=15 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; She took the [[oath of office]] on 15 February 2015. The constitution limits holders of the presidential office to a maximum of two terms and prevents the president from being a member of any political party.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ustav-RH&quot;/&gt; Consequently, the president-elect withdraws from party membership before inauguration.

The government ({{lang-hr|Vlada}}), the main executive power of Croatia, is headed by the prime minister who has four deputies, who also serve as government ministers. There are 16 other ministers who are appointed by the prime minister with the consent of the Sabor (majority of all MPs); these are in charge of particular sectors of activity. As of 19 October 2016, the Deputy Prime Ministers are [[Martina Dalić]], [[Davor Ivo Stier]], [[Ivan Kovačić]], and [[Damir Krstičević]]. Government ministers are from the [[Croatian Democratic Union]] (HDZ), and the [[Bridge of Independent Lists]] (MOST) with five [[independent (politics)|independent]] ministers. The [[Executive (government)|executive branch]] is responsible for proposing legislation and a budget, executing the laws, and guiding the country's foreign and domestic policies. The government's official residence is at [[Banski dvori]].&lt;ref name=&quot;VRH-PoliticalStructure&quot;/&gt; As of 19 October 2016, the prime minister is [[Andrej Plenković]].

{{office-table}}
|[[Presidents of Croatia|President]]
|[[Zoran Milanović]]
|[[Social Democratic Party of Croatia]]
|19 February 2020
|-
|[[Prime Minister of Croatia|Prime Minister]]
|[[Andrej Plenković]]
|[[Croatian Democratic Union]]
|19 October 2016
|}

==Legislature==
{{main|Parliament of Croatia}}
[[File:Croatian Parlament Sabor.jpg|thumb|Building of the [[Parliament of Croatia]]]]
The Parliament of Croatia ({{lang-hr|Sabor}}) is a unicameral legislative body. A second chamber, the ''Chamber of Counties'' ({{lang-hr|Županijski dom}}), was set up in 1993 pursuant to the 1990 Constitution. The Chamber of Counties was originally composed of three deputies from each of the twenty counties and the city of [[Zagreb]]. However, as it had no practical power over the Chamber of Representatives, it was abolished in 2001 and its powers were transferred to the county governments. The number of Sabor representatives can vary from 100 to 160; they are all elected by popular vote and serve four-year terms. 140 members are elected in multi-seat [[constituency|constituencies]], up to six members are chosen by [[proportional representation]] to represent Croatians living abroad and five members represent ethnic and national communities or minorities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sabor-about&quot;&gt;{{cite web|publisher=Sabor|url= http://www.sabor.hr/Default.aspx?sec=713|title=About the Parliament|accessdate=14 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The two largest political parties in Croatia are the [[Croatian Democratic Union]] (HDZ) and the [[Social Democratic Party of Croatia]] (SDP). The last parliamentary election was held on 11 September 2016 in Croatia and on 10 and 11 September 2016 abroad.

The Sabor meets in public sessions in two periods; the first from 15 January to 30 June, and the second from 15 September to 15 December. Extra sessions can be called by the President of the Republic, by the president of the parliament or by the government. The powers of the legislature include enactment and amendment of the constitution, enactment of laws, adoption of the state budget, declarations of war and peace, alteration of the country's boundaries, calling and conducting referenda and elections, appointments and relief of office, supervising the work of the Government of Croatia and other holders of public powers responsible to the Sabor, and granting amnesty. Decisions are made based on a majority vote if more than half of the Chamber is present, except in cases of constitutional issues.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sabor-about&quot;/&gt;

== Elections ==
{{elect|List of political parties in Croatia|Elections in Croatia}}
[[File:Josipovic election night.jpg|thumb|Ivo Josipović, 2010 election victory speech]]
The Croatian constitution and legislation provides for regular elections for the office of the President of the Republic, parliamentary, county prefects, county assemblies, city and municipal mayors and city and municipal councils. The President of the Republic is elected to a five-year term by a direct vote of all citizens of Croatia. A majority vote is required to win. A [[Two-round system|runoff election]] round is held in cases where no candidate secures the majority in the first round of voting. The presidential elections are regulated by the constitution and dedicated legislation; the latter defines technical details, appeals and similar issues.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ustav-RH&quot;&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=Narodne Novine|language=Croatian|url=http://narodne-novine.nn.hr/clanci/sluzbeni/2010_07_85_2422.html|title=Ustav Republike Hrvatske|trans-title=Constitution of the Republic of Croatia|date=9 July 2010|accessdate=11 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

140 members of parliament are elected to a four-year term in ten multi-seat constituencies, which are defined on the basis of the existing county borders, with amendments to achieve a uniform number of eligible voters in each constituency to within 5%. Citizens of Croatia living abroad are counted in an eleventh constituency; however, its number of seats was not fixed for the last parliamentary election. It was instead calculated based on numbers of votes cast in the ten constituencies in Croatia and the votes cast in the eleventh constituency. In the [[2007 Croatian parliamentary election|2007 parliamentary election]] the eleventh constituency elected five MPs. Constitutional changes first applied in the [[2011 Croatian parliamentary election|2011 parliamentary election]] have abolished this scheme and permanently assigned three MPs to the eleventh constituency.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sabor-Izbori2011&quot;&gt;{{cite web|publisher=[[Sabor]]|url=http://www.sabor.hr/Default.aspx|language=Croatian|title=U novi saziv Hrvatskoga sabora bira se 151 zastupnik|trans-title=151 MPs to be Elected to the next Sabor|accessdate=9 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, eight members of parliament are elected by voters belonging to twenty-two recognised minorities in Croatia: the [[Serbs of Croatia|Serb minority]] elects three MPs, [[Hungarians of Croatia|Hungarians]] and [[Italians of Croatia|Italians]] elect one MP each, [[Czechs of Croatia|Czech]] and [[Slovaks of Croatia|Slovak]] minorities elect one MP jointly, while all other minorities elect two more MPs to the parliament.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=[[Narodne Novine]]|language=Croatian|title=Zakon o izborima zastupnika u Hrvatski Sabor|trans-title=Croatian Parliament Members Election Act|url=http://narodne-novine.nn.hr/clanci/sluzbeni/305405.html|date=23 April 2003|accessdate=9 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[D'Hondt method|Standard D'Hondt formula]] is applied to the vote, with a 5% [[election threshold]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=[[Večernji list]]|language=Croatian|url=http://www.vecernji.hr/vijesti/kukuriku-koalicija-podijelila-mjesta-listama-ali-ne-resore-clanak-310528|title=Kukuriku-koalicija podijelila mjesta na listama, ali ne i resore|trans-title=Kukuriku coalition carves out candidate lists, not the ministries|date=15 July 2011|authors=Petra Maretić-Žonja, Vojislav Mazzocco|accessdate=9 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=State Electoral Commission|url=http://www.izbori.hr/izbori/ip.nsf/WPDS/F70CFD524E0E4545C1257455004696F5?open&amp;1|title=Izborni postupak u izborima za Hrvatski sabor|trans-title=Election process for Croatian parliamentary elections|language=Croatian|accessdate=21 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The last parliamentary election, held in 2016, elected 151 MPs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sabor-Izbori2011&quot;/&gt;

The county prefects and city and municipal mayors are elected to four-year terms by majority of votes cast within applicable local government units. A runoff election is held if no candidate achieves a majority in the first round of voting.&lt;ref name=&quot;narodne-novine.nn.hr&quot;&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=Narodne Novine|language=Croatian|url=http://narodne-novine.nn.hr/clanci/sluzbeni/329427.html|title=Zakon o izborima općinskih načelnika, gradonačelnika, župana i gradonačelnika grada Zagreba|trans-title=Municipal Mayor, City Mayor, County Prefect and the City of Zagreb Mayor Election Act|date=24 October 2007|accessdate=9 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Members of county, city, and municipal councils are elected to four-year terms through [[proportional representation]]; the entire local government unit forms a single constituency. The number of council members is defined by the councils themselves based on applicable legislation. Electoral committees are then tasked with determining whether the national minorities are represented in the council as required by the constitution. If the minorities are not represented, further members, who belong to the minorities and who have not been elected through the proportional representation system, are selected from electoral candidate lists and added to the council.&lt;ref name=&quot;http&quot;&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=Narodne Novine|language=Croatian|title=Zakon o izboru članova predstavničkih tijela jedinica lokalne i područne (regionalne) samouprave|trans-title=Members of Local and Regional Self-Government Representation Bodies Election Act|url=http://narodne-novine.nn.hr/clanci/sluzbeni/288356.html|date=5 April 2005|accessdate=9 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Latest presidential election===
{{main|2014–15 Croatian presidential election}}
{{#section-h:2014–15 Croatian presidential election|Results}}

===Latest parliamentary election===
{{main|Croatian parliamentary election, 2016}}

{| class=wikitable
|-
! style=&quot;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; colspan=3 | Parties and coalitions
! style=&quot;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot;|Votes
! style=&quot;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot;|%
! style=&quot;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot;|Swing
! style=&quot;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot;|Seats
! style=&quot;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | +/–
|-
| colspan=&quot;9&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Croatian Parliament electoral districts|Domestic electoral districts (1st–10th)]]
|-
|width=5px style=&quot;background-color:{{Croatian Democratic Union/meta/color}}&quot;|
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | HDZ Coalition
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | [[Croatian Democratic Union|HDZ]], [[Croatian Social Liberal Party|HSLS]], [[Croatian Christian Democratic Party|HDS]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 682,687
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 36.27%
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | +2.91%
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 59
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | +3
|-
| style=&quot;background-color:{{Social Democratic Party of Croatia/meta/color}}&quot; |
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | [[People's Coalition (Croatia)|People's Coalition]]
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | [[Social Democratic Party of Croatia|SDP]], [[Croatian People's Party-Liberal Democrats|HNS]], [[Croatian Party of Pensioners|HSU]], [[Croatian Peasant Party|HSS]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 636,602
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 33.82%
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | +0.62%
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 54
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | -2
|-
| style=&quot;background-color:{{Bridge of Independent Lists/meta/color}}&quot; |
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; colspan=2 | [[Bridge of Independent Lists]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 186,626 
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 9.91%
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | -3.60%
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 13
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | -6
|-
| style=&quot;background-color:{{Human Blockade/meta/color}}&quot; |
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | The Only Option Coalition
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | [[Human Blockade]], Change Croatia, Youth Action, Alphabet of democracy, [[Croatian Democratic Peasant Party|HDSS]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 117,208
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 6.23%
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | +1.99%
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 8
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | +7
|-
! style=&quot;background-color: {{Milan Bandić 365 - The Party of Labour and Solidarity/meta/color}}&quot; |
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | For Prime Minister Coalition
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | [[Milan Bandić 365 - The Party of Labour and Solidarity|BM 365]], [[People's Party - Reformists|Reformisti]], Novi val, HSS SR, BUZ
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 76,054
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 4.04%
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | +0.72%
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 2
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | ±0
|-
! style=&quot;background-color: {{Istrian Democratic Assembly/meta/color}}&quot; |
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | Even Stronger Istria Coalition
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | [[Istrian Democratic Assembly|IDS]], [[Alliance of Primorje-Gorski Kotar|PGS]], [[Lista za Rijeku - Lista per Fiume|List for Rijeka]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 43,180
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 2.29%
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | +0.46%
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 3
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | ±0
|-
! style=&quot;background:#141c40;&quot;|
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | Turn Croatia Around Coalition
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | Pametno, Za Grad
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 38,812
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 2.06%
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | ''New''
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 0
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | ''New''
|-
|style=&quot;background-color:{{Croatian Democratic Alliance of Slavonia and Baranja/meta/color}}&quot; |
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | HDSSB Coalition
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | [[Croatian Democratic Alliance of Slavonia and Baranja|HDSSB]], [[Croatian Conservative Party|HKS]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 23,573
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 1.25%
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | -0.11%
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 1
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | -1
|-
|style=&quot;background-color:{{Croatian Party of Rights dr. Ante Starčević/meta/color}}&quot; |
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | Homeland Coalition
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | [[Croatian Party of Rights dr. Ante Starčević|HSP AS]], Desno, [[Croatian Christian Democratic Union|HKDU]], USP, HDS
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 11,100
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 0.59%
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 0
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | -3
|-
| style=&quot;background-color:{{Croatian Labourists - Labour Party/meta/color}}&quot; |
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; colspan=2 | [[Croatian Labourists - Labour Party]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 4,821
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 0.26%
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 0
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | -1
|-
|style=&quot;background-color: white&quot;|
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; colspan=2 | Other parties and independent lists
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 61,654
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 3.28%
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 0
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | ±0
|-
| style=&quot;background-color: white&quot;|
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; colspan=2 | Invalid
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 36,871
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 1.92%
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | -
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; |  -
|-
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | Domestic total
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | 1,919,188 
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | 100%
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | -
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | 140
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | ±0
|-
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | Registered voters / turnout
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | 3,531,279
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | 54.35%
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | -6.47%
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | -
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | -
|-
| colspan=&quot;9&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Croatian Parliament electoral districts|District XI – Croatian citizens living abroad]]
|-
| width=5px style=&quot;background-color:{{Croatian Democratic Union/meta/color}}&quot;|
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | [[Croatian Democratic Union]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 13,117
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 62.72%
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | -22.97%
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 2
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | -1
|-
| style=&quot;background-color:white&quot; |
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;| Independent list led by Željko Glasnović
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 5,211
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 24.91%
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | ''New''
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 1
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | ''New''
|-
! style=&quot;background-color: {{Milan Bandić 365 - The Party of Labour and Solidarity/meta/color}}&quot; |
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | For Prime Minister Coalition
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | [[Milan Bandić 365 - The Party of Labour and Solidarity|BM 365]], [[People's Party - Reformists|Reformisti]], Novi val, HSS SR, BUZ
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 936
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 4.47%
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | +0.17%
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 0
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | ±0
|-
| style=&quot;background-color:{{Bridge of Independent Lists/meta/color}}&quot; |
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; colspan=2 | [[Bridge of Independent Lists]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 656 
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 3.13%
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | -0.76%
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 0
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | ±0
|-
| style=&quot;background-color: white&quot; |
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; | Other District XI lists
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 993
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 4.75%
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | 0
| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot; | ±0
|-
| style=&quot;background-color: white&quot;|
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; colspan=2 | Invalid
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 295
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 1.39%
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | -
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | -
|-
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | District XI total
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | 21,208
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | 100%
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | -
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | 3
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | ±0
|-
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | Registered voters / turnout
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | 21,223
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | 99.93%
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | +0.02%
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | -
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | -
|-
| colspan=&quot;9&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | [[Croatian Parliament electoral districts|District XII – National minority electoral district]]
|-
| style=&quot;background-color:{{Independent Democratic Serb Party/meta/color}}&quot; |
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; colspan=2 | [[Independent Democratic Serb Party]]
| colspan=3 rowspan=6 style=&quot;text-align:center; | ''Differing election system''
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 3
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | ±0
|-
| style=&quot;background-color:orange&quot; |
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; colspan=2 | [[Democratic Union of Hungarians of Croatia]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 1
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | +1
|-
| style=&quot;background-color:white&quot; |
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; colspan=2 | Union of Roma in Croatia &quot;Kali Sara&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 1
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | ±0
|-
| style=&quot;background-color:white&quot; |
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; colspan=2 | Union of Albanians in Croatia
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 1
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | +1
|-
| style=&quot;background-color:white&quot; |
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; colspan=2 | Independents (Italian minority)
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 1
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | ±0
|-
| style=&quot;background-color:white&quot; |
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; colspan=2 | Independents (Czech/Slovak minority)
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | 1
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot; | ±0
|-
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | District XII total
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | 37,902
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | 100%
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | -
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | 8
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | ±0
|-
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | Registered voters / turnout
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | 211,267
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | 17.94%
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | -1.14%
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | -
| style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | -
|-
| colspan=&quot;6&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | Total parliamentary seats
| width=&quot;30&quot; style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | 151
| width=&quot;30&quot; style=&quot;text-align:right;background-color:#E9E9E9&quot; | ±0
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; colspan=&quot;9&quot; | Sources: State Election Committee;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.izbori.hr/214zas/rezult/1/nrezultati.html | title = Izbori 2016 - Rezultati | language = Croatian | publisher = State Election Committee of the Republic of Croatia | date = 2016-09-16 | accessdate = 2016-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

==Judiciary==
{{main|Judiciary of Croatia}}
[[File:Supreme Court of the Republic of Croatia.jpg|thumb|[[Croatian Supreme Court]] building]]
Croatia has a three-tiered, independent judicial system governed by the constitution and national legislation enacted by the Sabor. The [[Croatian Supreme Court|Supreme Court]] ({{lang-hr|Vrhovni sud}}) is the highest court of appeal in Croatia; its hearings are open and judgments are made publicly, except in cases where the privacy of the accused is to be protected. Judges are appointed by the National Judicial Council and judicial office is permanent until seventy years of age. The president of the Supreme Court is elected for a four-year term by the Croatian Parliament at the proposal of the President of the Republic. As of 2017, the president of the Supreme Court is [[Đuro Sessa]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Supreme1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|publisher=Croatian Supreme Court|url=http://www.vsrh.hr/EasyWeb.asp?pcpid=42|language=Croatian|title=O Vrhovnom sudu|trans-title=About the Supreme Court|date=14 October 2011|accessdate=9 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;VSRH-about&quot;&gt;{{cite web|publisher=[[Croatian Supreme Court]]|url=http://www.vsrh.hr/EasyWeb.asp?pcpid=31|language=Croatian|title=Ustavne odredbe|trans-title=Provisions of the Constitution|date=21 May 2010|accessdate=14 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Supreme Court has civil and criminal departments.&lt;ref name=&quot;Supreme1&quot; /&gt; The lower two levels of the three-tiered judiciary consist of county courts and municipal courts.&lt;ref name=&quot;VSRH-about&quot;/&gt; There are fifteen county courts and sixty-seven municipal courts in the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=[[Narodne Novine]]|language=Croatian|url=http://narodne-novine.nn.hr/clanci/sluzbeni/2010_12_144_3625.html|title=Zakon o područjima i sjedištima sudova|trans-title=Court Districts and Headquarters Act|date=22 December 2010|accessdate=9 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are other specialised courts in Croatia; commercial courts and the Superior Commercial Court, [[misdemeanour]] courts that try trivial offences such as [[traffic violation]]s, the Superior Misdemeanour Court, the Administrative Court and the [[Croatian Constitutional Court]] ({{lang-hr|Ustavni sud}}).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=Croatian Supreme Court|language=Croatian|title=Sudbena vlast|trans-title=Judiciary|url=http://www.vsrh.hr/EasyWeb.asp?pcpid=30|accessdate=9 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Constitutional Court rules on matters regarding compliance of legislation with the constitution, repeals unconstitutional legislation, reports any breaches of provisions of the constitution to the government and the parliament, declares the speaker of the parliament acting president upon petition from the government in the event the country's president becomes incapacitated, issues consent for commencement of criminal procedures against or arrest of the president, and hears appeals against decisions of the [[Croatian National Judicial Council|National Judicial Council]]. The court consists of thirteen judges elected by members of the parliament for an eight-year term. The president of the Constitutional Court is elected by the court judges for a four-year term.&lt;ref name=&quot;CC-Hist&quot;&gt;{{cite web|publisher=[[Croatian Constitutional Court]]|url=http://www.usud.hr/default.aspx?Show=c_o_sudu&amp;G1=&amp;G2=&amp;G3=&amp;m1=15&amp;m2=0&amp;Lang=en|title=History of Croatian Constitutional Judicature|accessdate=9 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of June 2012, the president of the Constitutional Court is [[Jasna Omejec]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=Croatian Constitutional Court|url=http://www.usud.hr/default.aspx?Show=suci&amp;G1=&amp;G2=&amp;G3=&amp;m1=15&amp;m2=31&amp;Lang=en|title=Judges of the Constitutional Court of the Republic of Croatia|accessdate=9 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Croatian National Judicial Council|National Judicial Council]] ({{lang-hr|Državno Sudbeno Vijeće}}) consists of eleven members, specifically seven judges, two university professors of law and two parliament members, nominated and elected by the Parliament for four-year terms, and may serve no more than two terms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=[[Croatian National Judicial Council]]|url=http://www.dsv.pravosudje.hr/index.php/dsv/o_nama|language=Croatian|title=O nama|trans-title=About us|accessdate=9 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It appoints all judges and court presidents, except in case of the Supreme Court. As of January 2015, the president of the National Judicial Council is [[Ranko Marijan]], who is also a Supreme Court judge.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=Croatian National Judicial Council|language=Croatian|url=http://www.dsv.pravosudje.hr/index.php/dsv/clanovi|title=Članovi|trans-title=Members|accessdate=19 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[State Attorney's Office (Croatia)|State Attorney's Office]] represents the state in legal procedures. As of April 2018, [[Dražen Jelenić]] is the General [[State Attorney]], and there are twenty-three deputies in the central office and lower-ranking State Attorneys at fifteen county and thirty-three municipal State Attorney's Offices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=Croatian State Attorney's Office|language=Croatian|url=http://www.dorh.hr/Default.aspx?sec=630|title=Opći podaci|trans-title=General Data|accessdate=9 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=Croatian State Attorney's Office|language=Croatian|url=http://www.dorh.hr/Default.aspx?sec=32|title=Županijska i općinska državna odvjetništva|trans-title=County and Municipal State Attorney's Offices|accessdate=9 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The General State Attorney is appointed by the parliament.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=[[Poslovni dnevnik]]|url=http://www.poslovni.hr/vijesti/sabor-imenovao-bajica-na-treci-mandat--139724.aspx|language=Croatian|title=Sabor imenovao Bajića na treći mandat|trans-title=Sabor appoints Bajić for the third term|date=12 February 2010|accessdate=9 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A special State Attorney's Office dedicated to combatting corruption and organised crime, [[USKOK]], was set up in late 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=[[USKOK]]|url=http://www.dorh.hr/Default.aspx?sec=607|title=O USKOK-u|trans-title=About USKOK|language=Croatian|accessdate=9 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Local government==
{{multiple image
| align = right
| image1 = Croatia 2009 map results local council.PNG
| width1 = 160
| alt1 = 
| caption1 = 
| image2 = Croatia 2009 map results local prefect.PNG
| width2 = 160
| alt2 = 
| caption2 = 
| footer = 2009 Local elections: County council election winners (left), and county prefect election winners (right)&lt;br /&gt; {{legend inline|#698dc5|[[Croatian Democratic Union|HDZ]]}} {{legend inline|#ff8080|[[Social Democratic Party of Croatia|SDP]]}} {{legend inline|green|[[Croatian Peasant Party|HSS]]}} {{legend inline|#9ACD32|[[Istrian Democratic Assembly|IDS]]}} {{legend inline|orange|[[Croatian People's Party - Liberal Democrats|HNS-LD]]}} {{legend inline|#B5A642|[[Croatian Democratic Assembly of Slavonia and Baranja|HDSSB]]}}
}}
{{Main|Counties of Croatia}}
Croatia was first subdivided into counties ({{lang-hr|županija}}) in the [[Middle Ages]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Medieval-Counties&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|publisher=[[Školska knjiga]]|journal=Historijski Zbornik|volume=5|issue=1–2|year=1952|url=http://www.historiografija.hr/hz/1952/HZ_5_11_MANDIC.pdf|author=Oleg Mandić|language=Croatian|title=O nekim pitanjima društvenog uređenja Hrvatske u srednjem vijeku|trans-title=On some issues of social system of Croatia in the Middle Ages|pages=131–138|accessdate=9 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The divisions changed over time to reflect losses of territory to Ottoman conquest and the subsequent recapture of the same territory, and changes to the political status of [[Dalmatia]], [[Dubrovnik]] and [[Istria]]. The traditional division of the country into counties was abolished in the 1920s, when the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes and the subsequent Kingdom of Yugoslavia introduced [[oblast]]s and [[Subdivisions of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia|banovinas]] respectively.&lt;ref name=&quot;frucht429&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=lVBB1a0rC70C|author=Richard C. Frucht|title=Eastern Europe: An Introduction to the People, Lands, and Culture|year=2005|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn= 978-1-57607-800-6|accessdate=18 October 2011|page=429}}&lt;/ref&gt; After 1945 under Communist rule, Croatia, as a constituent part of Yugoslavia, abolished these earlier divisions and introduced municipalities, subdividing Croatia into approximately one hundred municipalities. Counties, significantly altered in terms of territory relative to the pre-1920s subdivisions, were reintroduced in 1992 legislation. In 1918, the [[Transleithania]]n part of Croatia was divided into eight counties with their seats in Bjelovar, Gospić, Ogulin, Požega, Vukovar, Varaždin, Osijek and Zagreb; the 1992 legislation established fifteen counties in the same territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;biondich11&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Mark Biondich|title=Stjepan Radić, the Croat Peasant Party, and the politics of mass mobilization, 1904–1928|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dZBgIIZ18WMC|year=2000|publisher=[[University of Toronto Press]]|isbn=978-0-8020-8294-7|accessdate=18 October 2011|page=11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CountiesAct1992&quot;&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=[[Narodne novine]]|date=30 December 1992|accessdate=9 September 2011|language= Croatian|title=Zakon o područjima županija, gradova i općina u Republici Hrvatskoj|trans-title=Territories of Counties, Cities and Municipalities of the Republic of Croatia Act|url=http://narodne-novine.nn.hr/clanci/sluzbeni/1992_12_90_2333.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since the counties were re-established in 1992, Croatia is divided into twenty counties and the capital city of Zagreb, the latter having the authority and legal status of a county and a city at the same time. In some instances, the boundaries of the counties have been changed, with the latest revision taking place in 2006. The counties subdivide into 128 [[List of cities in Croatia|cities]] and 428 [[Municipalities of Croatia|municipalities]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CountiesAct2006&quot;&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=Narodne novine|date=28 July 2006|accessdate=9 September 2011|language=Croatian|title=Zakon o područjima županija, gradova i općina u Republici Hrvatskoj|trans-title=Territories of Counties, Cities and Municipalities of the Republic of Croatia Act|url=http://narodne-novine.nn.hr/clanci/sluzbeni/2006_07_86_2045.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The county [[prefect]]s, [[List of cities in Croatia|city]] and [[Municipalities of Croatia|municipal]] mayors are elected to four-year terms by a majority of votes cast within applicable [[Administrative divisions of Croatia|local government units]]. If no candidate achieves a majority in the first round, a [[Two-round system|runoff election]] is held.&lt;ref name=&quot;narodne-novine.nn.hr&quot;/&gt; Members of county, city and municipal councils are elected to four-year terms, through [[proportional representation]] with the entire local government unit as a single constituency.&lt;ref name=&quot;http&quot;/&gt;

The number of members of the councils is defined by the councils themselves, based on applicable legislation. Electoral committees are then tasked with determining whether the national ethnic minorities are represented on the council as required by the [[Constitution of Croatia|constitution]]. Further members who belong to the minorities may be added to the council in no candidate of that minority has been elected through the proportional representation system.&lt;ref name=&quot;http&quot;/&gt; Election silence, as in all other types of elections in Croatia, when campaigning is forbidden, is enforced the day before the election and continues until 19:00 hours on the election day when the polling stations close and exit polls may be announced.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=[[Jutarnji list]]|url=http://www.jutarnji.hr/lokalni-izbori--pocela-izborna-sutnja/205765/|language=Croatian|title=Lokalni izbori: Počela izborna šutnja|trans-title=Local elections: Election silence starts|date=16 May 2009|accessdate=21 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eight nationwide local elections have been held in Croatia since 1990, the most recent being the [[2017 Croatian local elections|2017 local elections]] to elect county prefects and councils, and city and municipal councils and mayors. In 2017, the HDZ-led coalitions won a majority or [[Plurality (voting)|plurality]] in fifteen county councils and thirteen county prefect elections. SDP-led coalitions won a majority or plurality in five county councils, including the city of Zagreb council, and the remaining county council election was won by IDS-SDP coalition. The SDP won two county prefect elections, the city of Zagreb mayoral election, the HSS and the HNS won a single county prefect election each.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arhiva-Izbora&quot;/&gt;
{{Croatian counties|style=float:left; font-size:95%; border:3px; max-width:480px; width:50%;}}
{| class=&quot;sortable wikitable&quot; style=&quot;background:none; cellspacing=2px; text-align:left; font-size:90%;&quot;
|- style=&quot;font-size:100%; text-align:right;&quot;
! style=&quot;width:120px;&quot;| [[Counties of Croatia|County]] !! style=&quot;width:75px;&quot;| Seat !! style=&quot;width:75px;&quot;| Area (km²)!! style=&quot;width:85px;&quot;| Population
|-
| [[Bjelovar-Bilogora County|Bjelovar-Bilogora]] || [[Bjelovar]] || style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|2,652|| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|119,743
|-
| [[Brod-Posavina County|Brod-Posavina]] || [[Slavonski Brod]] || style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|2,043|| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|158,559
|-
| [[Dubrovnik-Neretva County|Dubrovnik-Neretva]] || [[Dubrovnik]] || style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|1,783|| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|122,783
|-
| [[Istria County|Istria]] || [[Pazin]] || style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|2,820|| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|208,440
|-
| [[Karlovac County|Karlovac]] || [[Karlovac]] || style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|3,622|| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|128,749
|-
| [[Koprivnica-Križevci County|Koprivnica-Križevci]] || [[Koprivnica]] ||style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|1,746|| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|115,582
|-
| [[Krapina-Zagorje County|Krapina-Zagorje]] || [[Krapina]] || style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|1,224|| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|133,064
|-
| [[Lika-Senj County|Lika-Senj]] || [[Gospić]] || style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|5,350|| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|51,022
|-
| [[Međimurje County|Međimurje]] || [[Čakovec]] || style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|730|| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|114,414
|-
| [[Osijek-Baranja County|Osijek-Baranja]] || [[Osijek]] || style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|4,152|| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|304,899
|-
| [[Požega-Slavonia County|Požega-Slavonia]] || [[Požega, Croatia|Požega]] || style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|1,845|| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|78,031
|-
| [[Primorje-Gorski Kotar County|Primorje-Gorski Kotar]] || [[Rijeka]] || style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|3,582|| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|296,123
|-
| [[Šibenik-Knin County|Šibenik-Knin]] || [[Šibenik]] || style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|2,939|| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|109,320
|-
| [[Sisak-Moslavina County|Sisak-Moslavina]] || [[Sisak]] ||style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|4,463|| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|172,977
|-
| [[Split-Dalmatia County|Split-Dalmatia]] || [[Split, Croatia|Split]] || style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|4,534|| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|455,242
|-
| [[Varaždin County|Varaždin]] || [[Varaždin]] || style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|1,261|| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|176,046
|-
| [[Virovitica-Podravina County|Virovitica-Podravina]] || [[Virovitica]] || style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|2,068|| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|84,586
|-
| [[Vukovar-Srijem County|Vukovar-Srijem]] || [[Vukovar]] || style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|2,448|| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|180,117
|-
| [[Zadar County|Zadar]] || [[Zadar]] || style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|3,642|| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|170,398
|-
| [[Zagreb County]] || [[Zagreb]] || style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|3,078|| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|317,642
|-
| [[City of Zagreb]] || [[Zagreb]] ||style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|641|| style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;|792,875
|}

==History==
{{see also|History of Croatia}}

===Within Austria-Hungary===
[[File:Dragutin Weingärtner, Hrvatski sabor 1848. god.jpg|thumb|Meeting of the [[Sabor]] in 1848]]

[[Revolutions of 1848|Events of 1848]] in Europe and the [[Revolutions of 1848 in the Habsburg areas|Austrian Empire]] brought dramatic changes to Croatian society and politics, provoking the [[Croatian national revival]] that strongly influenced and significantly shaped political and social events in Croatia. At the time, the [[Sabor]] and Ban [[Josip Jelačić]] advocated the severance of ties with the [[Kingdom of Hungary (1538–1867)|Kingdom of Hungary]], emphasising links to other [[South Slavs|South Slavic]] lands within the empire. Several prominent Croatian political figures emerged, such as [[Ante Starčević]], [[Eugen Kvaternik]], [[Franjo Rački]] and [[Josip Juraj Strossmayer]]. A period of [[neo-absolutism]] was followed by the [[Austro-Hungarian Compromise of 1867]] and the [[Croatian–Hungarian Settlement]], which granted limited independence to Croatia. This was compounded by Croatian claims of uninterrupted statehood since the early Middle Ages as a basis for a modern state. Two political parties that evolved in the 1860s and contributed significantly to the sentiment were the [[Party of Rights (1861–1929)|Party of Rights]], led by Starčević and Kvaternik, and the [[People's Party (Kingdom of Croatia)|People's Party]], led by [[Janko Drašković]], [[Ivan Kukuljević Sakcinski]], [[Josip Juraj Strossmayer]] and [[Ivan Mažuranić]]. They were opposed by the [[National Constitutional Party]], which was in power for most of the period between the 1860s and the 1918, and advocated closer ties between Croatia and Hungary.&lt;ref name=&quot;Matković-parties&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|journal=Review of Croatian History|issn=1845-4380|publisher=Croatian Institute of History|volume=6|issue=1|date=April 2011|author=Stjepan Matković|title=Croatian-Slovenian relations in politics, 1848–1914: examples of mutual ties|pages=115–132|url=http://hrcak.srce.hr/index.php?show=clanak&amp;id_clanak_jezik=100777|accessdate=15 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other significant parties formed in the era were the [[Serb People's Independent Party]], which later formed the [[Croat-Serb Coalition]] with the Party of Rights and other Croat and Serb parties. The Coalition ruled Croatia between 1903 and 1918. The leaders of the Coalition were [[Frano Supilo]] and [[Svetozar Pribićević]]. The [[Croatian Peasant Party]] (HSS), established in 1904 and led by [[Stjepan Radić]], advocated Croatian autonomy but achieved only moderate gains by 1918.&lt;ref name=&quot;Matković-parties&quot;/&gt; In [[Kingdom of Dalmatia|Dalmatia]], the two major parties were the [[People's Party (Kingdom of Dalmatia)|People's Party]] – a branch of the People's Party active in Croatia-Slavonia – and the [[Autonomist Party]], advocating maintaining autonomy of Dalmatia, opposite to the People's Party demands for unification of Croatia-Slavonia and Dalmatia. The Autonomist Party, most notably led by [[Antonio Bajamonti]], was also linked to [[Italian irredentism]]. By 1900, the Party of Rights had made considerable gains in Dalmatia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|journal=Radovi Zavoda Za Povijesne Znanosti HAZU U Zadru|publisher=[[Croatian Academy of Sciences and Arts]]|issn=1330-0474|title=O broju Talijana/talijanaša u Dalmaciji XIX. stoljeća|language=Croatian|trans-title=Concerning the Number of Italians/Pro-Italians in Dalmatia in the 19th century|author=Šime Peričić|issue=45|date=September 2003|pages=327–355|url=http://hrcak.srce.hr/12136?lang=en|accessdate=12 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Autonomists won the first three elections, but all elections since 1870 were won by the People's Party. In the period 1861–1918 there were seventeen elections in the [[Kingdom of Croatia-Slavonia]] and ten in the [[Kingdom of Dalmatia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Matković-parties&quot;/&gt;

===First and Second Yugoslavia===
[[File:Session of Sabor.jpg|thumb|A session of [[Sabor]], 29 October 1918]]
After the establishment of the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes, the HSS established itself as the most popular Croatian political party and was very popular despite efforts to ban it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|magazine=[[Newsweek]]|title=YUGOSLAVIA: The Opposition|url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,720153,00.html|date=6 April 1925|accessdate=15 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Vidovdan Constitution|1921 constitution]] defined the kingdom as a [[unitary state]] and abolished the historical administrative divisions, which effectively ended Croatian autonomy; the constitution was opposed by HSS.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|journal=Scrinia Slavonica|publisher=Croatian Institute of History – Slavonia, Syrmium and Baranya history branch|issn=1332-4853|url=http://hrcak.srce.hr/index.php?show=clanak&amp;id_clanak_jezik=31497|volume=3|issue=1|date=November 2003|title=Parlamentarni izbori u Brodskom kotaru 1923. godine|language=Croatian|trans-title=Parliamentary Elections in the Brod District in 1932|accessdate=17 October 2011|pages=452–470}}&lt;/ref&gt; The political situation deteriorated further as Stjepan Radić of the HSS was assassinated in the [[Yugoslav Parliament]] in 1928, leading to the dictatorship of King [[Alexander I of Yugoslavia|Alexander]] in January 1929.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|journal=Radovi Zavoda Za Povijesne Znanosti HAZU U Zadru|publisher=[[Croatian Academy of Sciences and Arts]]|issn=1330-0474|url=http://hrcak.srce.hr/index.php?show=clanak&amp;id_clanak_jezik=74560|pages=203–218|issue=51|date=November 2009|author=Zlatko Begonja|title=Ivan Pernar o hrvatsko-srpskim odnosima nakon atentata u Beogradu 1928. godine|language=Croatian|trans-title=Ivan Pernar on Croatian-Serbian relations after 1928 Belgrade assassination|accessdate=17 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The HSS, now led by [[Vladko Maček]], continued to advocate the [[federalization|federalisation]] of Yugoslavia, resulting in the [[Cvetković–Maček Agreement]] of August 1939 and the autonomous [[Banovina of Croatia]]. The Yugoslav government retained control of defence, internal security, foreign affairs, trade, and transport while other matters were left to the Croatian Sabor and a crown-appointed Ban.&lt;ref name=&quot;Klemencic-Zagar-121-123&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ORSMBFwjAKcC|author1=Matjaž Klemenčič|author2=Mitja Žagar|title=The former Yugoslavia's diverse peoples: a reference sourcebook|publisher=[[ABC-CLIO]]|year=2004|isbn=978-1-57607-294-3|accessdate=17 October 2011|pages=121–123}}&lt;/ref&gt; This arrangement was soon made obsolete with the beginning of [[World War II]], when the [[Independent State of Croatia]], which banned all political opposition, was established.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=c5opW1yV7FcC|title=The Oxford handbook of fascism|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|year=2009|isbn=978-0-19-929131-1|author=R.J.B. Bosworth|page=431|author-link=R.J.B. Bosworth}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since then, the HSS continues to operate abroad.&lt;ref name=&quot;HSS-Statut&quot;&gt;{{cite web|publisher=[[Croatian Peasant Party]]|url=http://www.hss.hr/o-nama/statut|language=Croatian|title=Statut|trans-title=Constitution|accessdate=15 November 2011|date=19 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1945 election, the Communists were unopposed because the other parties abstained.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|journal=Zbornik Radova Pravnog Fakulteta U Splitu|publisher=[[University of Split]], Faculty of Law|issn=0584-9063|title=Jugoslavija: unitarna država ili federacija povijesne težnje srpskoga i hrvatskog naroda – jedan od uzroka raspada Jugoslavije|language=Croatian|trans-title=Yugoslavia: A Unitary State or Federation (Conflicting historical tensions – one of the causes of the dissolution of Yugoslavia)|author1=Davorin Rudolf|author2=Saša Čobanov|pages=287–317|volume=46|issue=2|date=June 2009|url=http://hrcak.srce.hr/index.php?show=clanak&amp;id_clanak_jezik=60049|accessdate=15 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Once in power, the Communists introduced a single-party political system, in which the [[Communist Party of Yugoslavia]] was the ruling party and the [[Communist Party of Croatia]] was its branch.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|journal=Arhivski Vjesnik|publisher=Croatian State Archive|issn=0570-9008|url=http://hrcak.srce.hr/9046?lang=en|language=Croatian|title=Prilog poznavanju institucija: Sabor Narodne Republike Hrvatske, saziv 1953–1963.|trans-title=Contribution to the History of Institutions: Parliament of the People's Republic of Croatia, Convocation 1953–1963|author=Marina Štambuk-Škalić|issue=45|date=April 2003|accessdate=15 November 2011|pages=83–102}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1971, the Croatian national movement, which sought greater civil rights and the decentralisation of the Yugoslav economy, culminated in the [[Croatian Spring]], which was suppressed by the Yugoslav leadership.&lt;ref name=&quot;JL-Savka&quot;&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=[[Jutarnji list]]|language=Croatian|url=http://www.jutarnji.hr/heroina-hrvatskog-proljeca/305499/|title=Heroina Hrvatskog proljeća|trans-title=Heroine of the Croatian Spring|date=6 August 2009|author=Vlado Vurušić|accessdate=14 October 2011|archivedate=13 August 2011|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110813053815/http://www.jutarnji.hr/heroina-hrvatskog-proljeca/305499/}}&lt;/ref&gt; In January 1990, the Communist Party fragmented along national lines; the Croatian faction demanded a looser federation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pauković-14Congress-2009&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|author=Davor Pauković|publisher=Centar za politološka istraživanja|url=http://hrcak.srce.hr/index.php?show=clanak&amp;id_clanak_jezik=55640|language=Croatian|title=Posljednji kongres Saveza komunista Jugoslavije: uzroci, tijek i posljedice raspada|trans-title=Last Congress of the League of Communists of Yugoslavia: Causes, Consequences and Course of Dissolution|date=1 June 2008|journal=Časopis Za Suvremenu Povijest|volume=1|issue=1|pages=21–33|format=PDF|issn=1847-2397|accessdate=11 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Modern Croatia===
[[File:Vlada12.jpg|thumb|[[Cabinet of Zoran Milanović]] in December 2011]]
In 1989, the government of the [[Socialist Republic of Croatia]] decided to tolerate political parties in response to growing demands to allow political activities outside the Communist party. The first political party founded in Croatia since the beginning of the Communist rule was the [[Croatian Social Liberal Party]] (HSLS), established on 20 May 1989, followed by the [[Croatian Democratic Union]] on 17 June 1989. In December 1989, [[Ivica Račan]] became the head of the reformed Communist party. At the same time, the party cancelled political trials, released political prisoners and endorsed a multi-party political system. The Civil Organisations Act was formally amended to allow political parties on 11 January 1990, legalising the parties that were already founded.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dunatov&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|journal=Radovi Zavoda Za Povijesne Znanosti HAZU U Zadru|publisher=Croatian Academy of Sciences and Arts|issn=1330-0474|language=Croatian|url=http://hrcak.srce.hr/index.php?show=clanak&amp;id_clanak_jezik=95848|title=Začetci višestranačja u Hrvatskoj 1989. godine|trans-title=The Origins of the Multi-Party System in Croatia in 1989|author=Šime Dunatov|issue=52|date=December 2010|pages=381–397|accessdate=15 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By the time of the first round of the [[1990 Croatian parliamentary election|first multi-party elections]], held on 22 April 1990, there were 33 registered parties. The most relevant parties and coalitions were the League of Communists of Croatia – Party of Democratic Changes (the renamed Communist party), the  Croatian Democratic Union (HDZ), and the [[Coalition of People's Accord]] (KNS), which included the HSLS led by [[Dražen Budiša]], and the HSS, which resumed operating in Croatia in December 1989.&lt;ref name=&quot;HSS-Statut&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dunatov&quot; /&gt; The runoff election was held on 6 May 1990. The HDZ, led by [[Franjo Tuđman]], won ahead of the reformed Communists and the KNS. The KNS, led by [[Savka Dabčević-Kučar]] and [[Miko Tripalo]] – who had led the Croatian Spring – soon splintered into individual parties. The HDZ maintained a parliamentary majority until the [[2000 Croatian parliamentary election|2000 parliamentary election]], when it was defeated by the [[Social Democratic Party of Croatia]] (SDP), led by Račan. [[Franjo Gregurić]], of the HDZ, was appointed prime minister to head a [[national unity government]] in July 1991 as the [[Croatian War of Independence]] escalated in intensity. His appointment lasted until August 1992.&lt;ref name=&quot;VRH-Prethodne&quot;&gt;{{cite web|publisher=Government of Croatia|url=http://www.vlada.hr/hr/naslovnica/o_vladi_rh/prethodne_vlade_rh|language=Croatian|title=Prethodne vlade RH|trans-title=Previous governments of the Republic of Croatia|accessdate=10 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; During his term, Croatia's declaration of independence from Yugoslavia took effect on 8 October 1991.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sabor-Independence-8Oct1991&quot;/&gt; The HDZ returned to power in the [[2003 Croatian parliamentary election|2003 parliamentary election]], while the SDP remained the largest opposition party.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arhiva-Izbora&quot;&gt;{{cite web|publisher=State Election Commission|url=http://www.izbori.hr/arhiva/arhiva.html|title=Arhiva izbora|trans-title=Elections Archive|language=Croatian|accessdate=13 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Franjo Tuđman won the presidential elections in [[1992 Croatian presidential election|1992]] and [[1997 Croatian presidential election|1997]]. During his terms, the [[Constitution of Croatia]], adopted in 1990, provided for a [[semi-presidential system]].&lt;ref name=&quot;JL-ustav&quot;&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=[[Jutarnji list]]|language=Croatian|url=http://www.jutarnji.hr/arlovic-i-seks--bilo-bi-dobro-da-ovaj-ustav-izdrzi-dulje--ali-me-strah-da-ipak-nece/838714/|title=Arlović: Bilo bi dobro da ovaj Ustav izdrži dulje, ali me strah da ipak neće|trans-title=Arlović: It would be good if this constitution lasts, but I fear i will not|author=Veronika Rešković|date=17 June 2010|accessdate=19 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; After Tuđman's death in 1999, the constitution was amended and much of the presidential powers were transferred to the parliament and the government.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC-CroProfile&quot;/&gt; [[Stjepan Mesić]] won two consecutive terms in [[2000 Croatian presidential election|2000]] and [[2005 Croatian presidential election|2005]] on a [[Croatian People's Party – Liberal Democrats|Croatian People's Party]] (HNS) ticket. [[Ivo Josipović]], an SDP candidate, won the presidential elections in [[Croatian presidential election, 2009–2010|December 2009 and January 2010]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Arhiva-Izbora&quot;/&gt; [[Kolinda Grabar-Kitarović]] defeated Josipović in the January 2015 election run-off, becoming the first female president of Croatia.

==See also==
* [[List of political parties in Croatia]]
* [[Foreign relations of Croatia]]
* [[Military of Croatia]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group=upper-alpha|colwidth=30em}} &lt;!-- for template - don't remove, please! --&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

{{Croatia topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Politics of Europe}}

{{Good Article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Politics Of Croatia}}
[[Category:Politics of Croatia| ]]</text>
      <sha1>lvsiaxg2eyomxlu4nlbakc21tm8n7sn</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
