  <page>
    <title>Transport in Croatia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5580</id>
    <revision>
      <id>925348969</id>
      <parentid>921152364</parentid>
      <timestamp>2019-11-09T14:59:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>RudnikU</username>
        <id>33694002</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Motorways */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[File:Kroatien Autobahnen (aktueller Stand).svg|thumb|300px|Highway network in Croatia]]

'''Transport in Croatia''' relies on several main modes, including [[Transportation|transport]] by road, rail, water and air. Road transport incorporates a comprehensive network of state, county and local routes augmented by a network of highways for long-distance travelling. Water transport can be divided into sea, based on the ports of [[Rijeka]], [[Ploče]], [[Split (city)|Split]] and [[Zadar]], and river transport, based on [[Sava]], [[Danube]] and, to a lesser extent, [[Drava]]. [[Croatia]] has 68 airports, nine of which are international. The country also has several airlines, of which the most notable are [[Croatia Airlines]] and [[Trade Air]]. Rail transport is fairly developed, with dual track and electrification not very common, although high-speed tilting trains are used on some routes. However, bus still tends to be more common than rail as a mode of inter-city transport.

==Airports==
[[File:Croati Airlines A319.jpg|thumb|right|National carrier [[Croatia Airlines]] taking off at [[Zagreb International Airport|Franjo Tuđman Airport]] ]]
There are international [[airport]]s in [[Zagreb International Airport|Zagreb]], [[Split Airport|Split]], [[Dubrovnik Airport|Dubrovnik]], [[Zadar Airport|Zadar]], [[Pula Airport|Pula]], [[Rijeka Airport|Rijeka]] (on the island of [[Krk]]), [[Osijek Airport|Osijek]], [[Brač Airport|Bol]] and [[Lošinj Airport|Mali Lošinj]].

Currently, the following low cost airlines are flying to Croatia: Jet2, [[EasyJet]], [[Eurowings]], [[TUIfly]], [[Ryanair]], [[Thomson Airways|Thomson]], [[flydubai]] and [[Wizz Air]]. Major established companies that fly to Croatia include the domestic [[Croatia Airlines]] (member of the [[Star Alliance]]), [[Air France]], [[Aeroflot]], [[Lufthansa]], [[Emirates (airline)|Emirates]], [[Finnair]], [[Austrian Airlines]], [[KLM]], [[Qatar Airways]], [[Swiss International Air Lines]], [[British Airways]] and [[Turkish Airlines]]. Seasonal intercontinental flights also operate from and to Croatia.

In January 2011 the U.S. [[Federal Aviation Administration]] (FAA) assessed the Government of Croatia's Civil Aviation Authority announcing that Croatia complied with [[International Civil Aviation Organization]] (ICAO) aviation safety standards for oversight of Croatia's air carrier opinions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.faa.gov/news/press_releases/news_story.cfm?newsId=12337 | title = FAA Raises Safety Rating for Croatia | publisher = Federal Aviation Administration | date = 2011-01-26 | accessdate = 2011-01-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; IASA Category 1 rating and that Croatian air carriers are authorized Croatia to the US.

'''Statistics:'''

Overall: 68 airports (2004 estimate)

Airports with paved [[runway]]s (2004 est.):
* total: 23
* {{convert|10,000|ft|m|abbr=on}} or more: 2
* {{convert|8,000|to|9,999|ft|m|abbr=on}}: 6
* {{convert|5,000|to|7,999|ft|m|abbr=on}}: 2
* {{convert|3,000|to|4,999|ft|m|abbr=on}}: 4
* under {{convert|3,000|ft|m|abbr=on}}: 9

Airports with unpaved runways (2004 est.):
* total: 45
* {{convert|5,000|to|7,999|ft|m|abbr=on}}: 1
* {{convert|3,000|to|4,999|ft|m|abbr=on}}: 7
* under {{convert|3,000|ft|m|abbr=on}}: 37

[[Heliport]]s: 3 (2008)

'''Airports:'''
[[File:Aeropuertos de Croacia.svg|right|thumb|Civil airports in Croatia]]
* [[Zagreb Airport|Franjo Tuđman Airport]]
* [[Split Airport]]
* [[Rijeka Airport]]
* [[Osijek Airport]]
* [[Zadar Airport]]
* [[Dubrovnik Airport]]
* [[Pula Airport]]
* [[Brač Airport]]
* [[Lošinj Airport]]

{{See also|List of airports in Croatia}}

==Rail transport==
[[File:Railway map of Croatia and Bosnia and Herzegovina.png|thumb|left|Railway network in Croatia and Bosnia and Herzegovina]]
{{see also|List of railways in Croatia|Croatian Railways}}

The Croatian railway network is classified into three groups: railways of international, regional and local significance.&lt;ref name=NN81-2006&gt;{{cite web|publisher=[[Government of Croatia]]|url=http://digured.hr/cadial/searchdoc.php?query=&amp;lang=hr&amp;bid=nJbXVZkld1Kh4b1smwO6jA%3D%3D|title=Odluka o razvrstavanju željezničkih pruga|language=Croatian|trans-title=Decision on Classification of Railways|work=[[Narodne novine]]|issue=81|year=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=NN13-2007&gt;{{cite web|publisher=[[Government of Croatia]]|url=http://digured.hr/cadial/searchdoc.php?query=&amp;lang=hr&amp;annotate=on&amp;bid=wj6f4ZQU2PzTf%2bZonMsbkg%3d%3d|title=Odluka o izmjeni i dopuni Odluke o razvrstavanju željezničkih pruga |language=Croatian|trans-title=Decision on changes and additions to the Decision on Classification of Railways|work=[[Narodne novine]]|issue=13|year=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The most important railway lines follow [[Pan-European corridors]] V (branch B) and X, they connect at Zagreb with each other. There are connections to the railway networks of [[Slovenia]], [[Hungary]], [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]] and [[Serbia]].

The railways need to be modernized because the lion's share of the railway infrastructure in Croatia dates back from the pre-WW2 period and more than half of the core routes were, in fact, built during the [[Habsburg Monarchy]] i.e. before the [[First World War]]. As a result, most of the routes are not electrified, are only single track traffic around 'bends' and lag significantly behind the West-European standards. Some limited improvements, however, have been made in recent times. A result of this has been an increase in the maximum speed on the railway line on the [[Pan-European Corridor X]], from the Slovenian border via Zagreb, Novska, Vinkovci to the Serbian border (lines [[M101 railway (Croatia)|M101]] through [[M105 railway (Croatia)|M105]]). In places the line's speed limit has been raised from {{convert|80|km/h|mph|abbr=on}} to {{convert|120|km/h|mph|abbr=on}}, and plans have been made to raise this further to {{convert|160|km/h|mph|-1|abbr=on}} on certain sections. The railway line of the [[Pan-European Corridor Vb]], from the Hungarian border via Koprivnica, Zagreb, Karlovac to the [[Port of Rijeka]] (lines [[M201 railway (Croatia)|M201]], [[M102 railway (Croatia)|M102]] and [[M202 railway (Croatia)|M202]]) has a slow section through [[Gorski Kotar]], which is planned to undergo a major overhaul. The railway line of the [[Pan-European Corridor Vc]], from the Hungarian border via Beli Manastir, Osijek, Đakovo or Vinkovci, Slavonski Šamac, to the border of Bosnia and Herzegovina (lines [[M301 railway (Croatia)|M301]], [[M302 railway (Croatia)|M302]] and [[M303 railway (Croatia)|M303]]), is also being modernised, the aim is to allow speeds of up to 160&amp;nbsp;km/h along the entire length.

The official rail speed record in Croatia is {{convert|181|km/h|abbr=on}}. Maximum speed reached in regular service is {{convert|160|km/h|abbr=on}} on parts of the [[M105 railway (Croatia)|Novska–Tovarnik line]].
[[File:Croatian railways tilting and regional.png|thumb|[[Croatian Railways]] trains pass on Zagreb-Split line]]

Recently [[Croatian Railways]] introduced a series of modern [[tilting train]]s produced by the German branch of [[Bombardier Transportation]]. They usually deployed on the mountainous route between the two largest Croatian cities, [[Zagreb]] and [[Split, Croatia|Split]]. Although they can sometimes be found on other routes in the country. Contrary to regular overnight fast trains between Zagreb and Split with scheduled travelling time of circa 8 hours in total, tilting trains on the Zagreb–Split route (lines [[M202 railway (Croatia)|M202]] and [[M604 railway (Croatia)|M604]]) offer passengers a faster journey with a journey time of about 6 hours.

Croatian Railways aims to revitalize rail traffic through further improvements. Thus, establishing rail as serious competitor to the car, particularly during the busy the summer months.

Croatian Railways' plan to build their first [[high-speed railway]] service is progressing. Construction of an entirely new line from [[Karlovac]] to [[Rijeka]], and reconstruction of the line from the [[Hungary|Hungarian]] border to Karlovac should have originally begun in the fall of 2007. The line is going to be entirely electrified and in order to speed up the journey even more shall be {{convert|269|km|mi|abbr=on}} long from end to end, {{convert|61|km|mi|abbr=on}} shorter than the existing line. The journey from [[Zagreb]] to [[Rijeka]] will be cut to one hour compared to 4 hours with the existing track. The line is intended to carry the increasing amount of goods that enter Europe, at the Croatian [[Port of Rijeka]] and are then transported to destinations across central and [[eastern Europe]]. The plans have originally foreseen 2008-2010 as the date for completion. Due to the [[Global financial crisis of 2008–2009|world economic crisis]], building start date is prolonged to a yet undefined date. The project plans have been drawn, however.

[[Pan-European Corridor X]] is going to be upgraded to higher speed sometime in the future. Possibly by building a new high capacity connection line from [[Sisak]] via [[Kutina]] to [[Lipovljani]]. The line should allow for speeds of up to 250&amp;nbsp;km/h.

'''Statistics:'''

Railway length ({{as of|2011|lc=on}}):&lt;ref name=&quot;Factbook&quot;/&gt;
* total: {{convert|2722|km|mi|abbr=on}}
* standard gauge, {{RailGauge|1435mm}}: {{convert|2722|km|mi|abbr=on}} ({{convert|984|km|mi|abbr=on|disp=or}} electrified)

===Rail links with adjacent countries===
* [[Transport in Slovenia|Slovenia]]
* [[Transport in Hungary|Hungary]]
* [[Transport in Serbia|Serbia]]
* [[Transport in Bosnia and Herzegovina|Bosnia and Herzegovina]]

== Road transport ==
[[File:A1 tolls Maslenica.jpg|thumb|[[A1 (Croatia)|A1]] motorway near [[Maslenica]]]]
From the time of [[Napoleon]] and building the [[Louisiana road (Croatia)|Louisiana road]], the road transport in Croatia has significantly improved, topping most European countries. Croatian [[highway]]s are widely regarded as being one of the most modern and safe in Europe.&lt;ref name=openeurope&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.open-europe-consulting.de/?en=1210664140
| title = Croatia, Events and Exhibitions
| accessdate = 2008-11-24
| work = Open Europe Consulting
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=bgeu&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.euro2001.net/index.shtml?page=issuecontent&amp;file=issues/2_2007/english_ver.html
| title = 15 years since the international recognition of Croatia
| year = 2007
| accessdate = 2008-11-24
| work = Европа 2001
}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is because the largest part of the Croatian motorway and expressway system (''autoceste'' and ''brze ceste'', resp.)  has been recently constructed (mainly in the 2000s), and further construction is continuing. The [[motorways in Croatia]] connect most major Croatian cities and all major seaports. The two longest routes, the [[A1 (Croatia)|A1]] and the [[A3 (Croatia)|A3]], span the better part of the country and the motorway network connects most major border crossings.

[[Tourism]] is of major importance for the Croatian economy, and as most tourists come to vacation in Croatia in their own cars, the highways serve to alleviate summer jams. They have also been used as a means of stimulating urgently needed economic growth, and for the sustainable development of this country. Croatia now has a considerable highway density for a country of its size, helping it cope with the consequences of being a [[transition economy]] and having suffered in the [[Croatian War of Independence]].

{{As of|2011}}, Croatia has a total of {{convert|29410|km|sp=us}} of roads.&lt;ref name=&quot;Factbook&quot;&gt;{{CIA World Factbook link|hr|Croatia}}&lt;/ref&gt; [http://url.googluj.cz/m61 Travel Organiser (2007)]

===Traffic laws===
The [[traffic sign]]s adhere to the [[Vienna Convention on Road Signs and Signals]].

The general [[speed limit]]s are:
* in inhabited areas 50&amp;nbsp;km/h
* outside of inhabited areas 90&amp;nbsp;km/h
* on marked expressways 110&amp;nbsp;km/h
* on marked motorways 130&amp;nbsp;km/h

In 2004, a controversial new traffic law was introduced, which provides for drastic safety measures for drunken or dangerous driving: it reduced the blood alcohol limit to 0‰ of alcohol in blood. In 2008 this law was reversed to 0.5‰ of alcohol in blood.

Some of the more technical safety measures include that all new Croatian [[tunnel]]s have modern safety equipment and there are several control centers, which monitor highway traffic.

===Motorways===
{{main article|Highways in Croatia}}
Motorways ({{lang-hr|Autocesta}}, plural {{lang-hr|autoceste}}) in Croatia applies to dual carriageway roads with at least two [[traffic lanes]] in each driving direction and an [[emergency lane]]. Direction [[road sign]]s at Croatian motorways have green background with white lettering similar to the Swiss [[Autobahn]]. The designations of motorways are &quot;A&quot; and the motorway number. {{As of|2014}}, the Croatian motorway network is {{convert|1313.8|km}} long.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.huka.hr/mreza-autocesta | title=Mreža autocesta | publisher = Croatian Association of Motorway Concessionaires (HUKA) | work=huka.hr | year = 2014 | language=Croatian | accessdate=2014-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The list of completed motorways is as follows (see individual articles for further construction plans and status):

*'''[[A1 (Croatia)|A1]]''', [[Zagreb]] - [[Bosiljevo 2 interchange|Bosiljevo]] - [[Split, Croatia|Split]] - [[Ploče]] ([[European route E71|E71]], [[European route E65|E65]])
*'''[[A2 (Croatia)|A2]]''', [[Zagreb bypass|Zagreb]] - [[Krapina]] - [[Macelj]] ([[European route E59|E59]])
*'''[[A3 (Croatia)|A3]]''', [[Bregana]] - [[Zagreb bypass|Zagreb]] - [[Lipovac, Vukovar-Syrmia County|Lipovac]] ([[European route E70|E70]])
*'''[[A4 (Croatia)|A4]]''', [[Goričan]] - [[Varaždin]]/[[Čakovec]] - [[Zagreb bypass|Zagreb]] ([[European route E71|E71]])
*'''[[A5 (Croatia)|A5]]''', [[Osijek]] - [[Đakovo]] - [[Sredanci interchange|Sredanci]] ([[European route E73|E73]])
*'''[[A6 (Croatia)|A6]]''', [[Bosiljevo 2 interchange|Bosiljevo]] - [[Rijeka]] ([[European route E65|E65]])
*'''[[A7 (Croatia)|A7]]''', [[Rupa, Croatia|Rupa]] - [[Rijeka bypass]] ([[European route E61|E61]])
*'''[[A9 (Croatia)|A9]]''', [[Umag]] - [[Pula]] ([[European route E751|E751]])
*'''[[A10 (Croatia)|A10]]''', A1 Ploče interchange - Metković border crossing
*'''[[A11 (Croatia)|A11]]''', [[Velika Gorica]] - Buševec

Toll is charged on most [[Croatian motorways]], and exceptions are the A11 motorway, [[Zagreb bypass]] and [[Rijeka bypass]], as well as sections adjacent to border crossings (except eastbound A3). Payment in [[Croatian kuna|kuna]], all major credit cards and [[euro]]s are accepted at all toll gates. Most motorways are covered by the [[closed toll collection]] system, where a driver receives a ticket at the entrance gates and pays at the exit gates according to the number of sections travelled. [[Open toll collection]] is used on some bridges and tunnels and short stretches of tolled highway, where drivers immediately pay the toll upon arriving. Various forms of prepaid [[electronic toll collection]] systems are in place which allow quicker collection of toll, usually at a discounted rate, as well as use of dedicated toll plaza lanes (for ''ENC system'' of the electronic toll collection).

All heavily traveled routes towards [[Slovenia]], [[Hungary]] and [[Serbia]] are motorway connections, and almost all parts of Croatia are now easy to reach using motorways.

The 479&amp;nbsp;km long motorway A1 [[Zagreb]] - [[Split (city)|Split]] - [[Ploče]] connects the continental part of Croatia with Mediterranean [[Dalmatia]]. It is complete with two lanes in both directions in its full length. The highway winds itself as a panoramic road through the Croatian hills. The highway currently ends near the [[Ploče]] sea port, but is planned to continue further on to [[Dubrovnik]].

The most important edifice on the A1 is the [[Sveti Rok Tunnel]] (5.687&amp;nbsp;m), which goes through the famous [[Velebit]] mountain range barrier. The most modern, and at the same time the longest Croatian tunnel, is also along the A1: the [[Mala Kapela Tunnel]] (length 5,780&amp;nbsp;m), which passes through the [[Mala Kapela]] mountain range. The [[Sveti Ilija Tunnel]] through [[Biokovo]] (4,249&amp;nbsp;m) connects the [[Makarska]] riviera with the A1.

Since June 2005 the [[Istrian Y]] extends from the Slovenian border in [[Istria]] and the A7 connects Slovenia to [[Rijeka]]. The A2 connection between [[Zagreb]] via [[Hrvatsko Zagorje]] to [[Maribor]] was completed in May 2007.

Motorway A3 extends from Slovenia via the [[Zagreb bypass]] through the length of [[Slavonia]] to the [[Serbia]]n border. In Slavonia there is now another motorway, A5, along the [[European route E73]] (European north-south corridor Vc) between the [[Hungary|Hungarian border]] at [[Beli Manastir]], [[Osijek]] and the [[Bosnia and Herzegovina|Bosnian border]]. This route will eventually continue as a modern motorway towards [[Sarajevo]] and further on to the Croatian sea port of [[Ploče]].

The A4 connection from Zagreb to [[Varaždin]] and [[Čakovec]] exists since 2003, which was extended to the Hungarian border in 2008 to complete the upgrade of the [[European route E71]]. The A6 route between [[Rijeka]] and [[Zagreb]] was constructed as an expressway in spring 2004, and upgraded to a full motorway in 2008, thus upgrading the Croatian section of the [[European route E65]]. Together these two upgrades completed the European north-south corridor Vb.

A motorway connection of [[Zagreb]] to the important industrial city of [[Sisak]] is planned to be constructed as [[A11 (Croatia)|A11]].

Significant tunnel and bridge construction projects in the south of Dalmatia are planned, such as a {{convert|2374|m|ft|abbr=on}} long [[Pelješac bridge]], connecting the [[Pelješac]] peninsula to the Croatian mainland.

By 2008, numerous service areas and petrol stations had been constructed along all Croatian motorways. All Croatian motorways are equipped with enclosed service areas with gas stations and parking. Many areas have restaurants and children's playgrounds.

===Expressways===
{{main article|Expressways in Croatia}}
The term ''brza cesta'' or ''expressway'' refers to [[limited-access road]]s specifically designated as such by legislation and marked with appropriate [[limited-access road]] traffic signs. The expressways may comprise two or more traffic lanes, while they normally do not have emergency lanes.

''Polu-autocesta'' or ''[[semi-highway]]'' refers to a two-lane, undivided road running on one roadway of a motorway while the other is in construction. By legal definition, all semi-highways are expressways.

The expressway routes in Croatia usually correspond to a state road (see below) and are marked a &quot;D&quot; followed by a number. The &quot;E&quot; numbers are designations of [[European route]]s.

===Major roads===
{{Main article|State roads in Croatia}}
Major roads that aren't part of the motorway system are ''državne ceste'' (state routes). They are marked with the letter D and the road's number.

The most traveled state routes in Croatia are:
* '''[[D1 (Croatia)|D1]]''', connects [[Zagreb]] and Split via [[Lika]] - passes through [[Karlovac]], [[Slunj]], [[Plitvička Jezera|Plitvice]], [[Korenica]], [[Knin]], [[Sinj]].
* '''[[D2 (Croatia)|D2]]''', connects [[Varaždin]] and [[Osijek]] via [[Podravina]] - passes through [[Koprivnica]], [[Virovitica]], [[Slatina, Croatia|Slatina]], [[Našice]].
* '''[[D8 (Croatia)|D8]]''', connects [[Rijeka]] and [[Dubrovnik]], widely known as ''[[Jadranska magistrala]]'' and part of [[European route E65|E65]] - runs along the coastline and connects many cities on the coast, including [[Crikvenica]], [[Senj]], [[Zadar]], [[Šibenik]], [[Trogir]], [[Split (city)|Split]], [[Omiš]], [[Makarska]] and [[Ploče]].

Since the construction of [[A1 (Croatia)|A1]] motorway beyond [[Gorski kotar]] started, D1 and D8 are much less used.

These routes are monitored by Croatian roadside assistance because they connect important locations. Like all state routes outside major cities, they are only two-lane arterials and do not support heavy traffic. All state routes are routinely maintained by Croatian road authorities. The road sign for a state route has a blue background and the route's designation in white. State routes have one, two or three-digit numbers.

===Minor roads===
Secondary routes are known as county roads. They are marked with signs with yellow background and road number. These roads' designations are rarely used, but usually marked on regional maps if these roads are shown. Formally, their designation is the letter Ž and the number. County roads have four-digit numbers.

The least known are the so-called local roads. Their designations are never marked on maps or by roadside signs and as such are virtually unknown to public. Their designations consist of the letter L and a five-digit number.

=== Bus traffic ===
In contrast to the fairly underdeveloped rail traffic, [[bus]]es represent the most-accepted, cheapest and widely used means of public transport. National bus traffic is very well developed and it is very easy to reach even the remotest parts of Croatia by bus. Almost all buses on national routes are air-conditioned and offer pleasant traveling comfort. The Croatian parliament has passed a law that no bus should be older than 12 years - however, this decision is currently frozen because of the high cost for bus operators.

In practice, bus fares are collected on the bus while traveling, which is sometimes even cheaper than when paying at the ticket office (there is an additional fee for stored luggage) and sometimes a &quot;ticket office fee&quot;.

From Croatia, there are many international bus routes to the neighboring countries ([[Slovenia]], [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]], [[Serbia]] etc.), as well as to Austria, Germany, Slovenia, Switzerland and to other European countries. International buses correspond to European standards.

[[Zagreb]] has the largest and most modern bus terminal in Croatia. It is located near the downtown in [[Trnje, Zagreb|Trnje]] district on the [[Marin Držić Avenue]]. It sports specially designed waiting areas above the bus stopping and parking area. The Zagreb bus terminal is close to the central train station, Glavni kolodvor and it is easy to reach by [[tram]] lines and by car.

==Water transport==

===Sea transport===
[[File:Rijeka luka pano 180909.jpg|thumb|upright=1.5|Panorama of [[Port of Rijeka]]]]
Croatia has several large [[seaport]]s. The largest seaport with the deepest channel to a port in the Adriatic is [[Port of Rijeka]] on the northern Croatian coast, followed by [[Ploče]] in southern Dalmatia. The port of Ploče is of strategic importance for the industries of [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]]. The largest Croatian passenger port is [[Port of Split|Split]] in [[Dalmatia]], also called ''gateway to the islands'', followed by [[Zadar]]. There are 66 inhabited islands along the Croatian coast which means there is a large number of local ferry connections.

'''Ports and harbors:'''
* major transport seaports: [[Omišalj]], [[Port of Ploče|Ploče]], [[Port of Rijeka|Rijeka]], [[Šibenik]]
* other seaports: [[Dubrovnik]], [[Dugi Rat]], [[Pula, Croatia|Pula]], [[Port of Split|Split]], [[Zadar]]
* inland waterway ports: [[Vukovar]] (on [[Danube]]), [[Sisak]] (on [[Sava]]), [[Slavonski Brod]] ([[Sava]] river), [[Zupanja]] ([[Sava]] river), [[Osijek]] ([[Drava]] river)

[[Merchant marine]] ({{as of|2010|lc=on}}):&lt;ref name=&quot;Factbook&quot;/&gt;
* ''total:'' 77 ships
* ''ships by type:''
** [[bulk carrier]] 24
** cargo 7
** [[chemical tanker]] 8
** passenger/cargo 27
** [[oil tanker|petroleum tanker]] 10
** refrigerated cargo 1
** foreign-owned ships registered here as a [[flag of convenience]]: 2
*** Norway 2
** registered in other countries: 31
*** Bahamas 1, Belize 1, Liberia 1, Malta 6, Marshall Islands 12, Panama 2, Saint Vincent and the Grenadines 8

An extensive system of ferries, operated by [[Jadrolinija]], serves Croatia's many islands and links coastal cities. Ferry services to Italian cities of [[Venice]], [[Ancona]], [[Pescara]] and [[Bari]] from around a dozen of Croatian sea ports, most notably [[Rovinj]], [[Rijeka]], [[Zadar]], [[Split (city)|Split]], [[Korčula]] and [[Dubrovnik]], is available on a daily or weekly basis. From April to September the schedule is denser and can include several round trips within a day.

===River transport===
Croatia is also on the important [[Danube]] waterway, which connects Eastern and Central Europe. The major Danube port is [[Vukovar]].

Perennially navigable rivers:
* [[Danube]] (section from Batina to Ilok which is in Croatia)
* [[Sava]] - from [[Rugvica]] until it exits Croatia near Gunja. The most upstream port is in [[Sisak]].

Total [[waterway]] length ({{as of|2009|lc=on}}): 785&amp;nbsp;km&lt;ref name=&quot;Factbook&quot;/&gt;

== Pipelines ==
There are {{convert|610|km|abbr=off}} of crude oil pipelines in Croatia, connecting the Port of Rijeka oil terminal with refineries in Rijeka and Sisak, as well as several transhipment terminals. The system has a capacity of 20&amp;nbsp;million tonnes per year.&lt;ref name=&quot;JANAF-system&quot;&gt;{{cite web|publisher=[[Jadranski naftovod]]|url=http://www.janaf.hr/index.php?option=sustav&amp;lang=en|title=The JANAF system|accessdate=8 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The natural gas transportation system comprises {{convert|2113|km|abbr=off}} of trunk and regional natural gas pipelines, and more than 300 associated structures, connecting production rigs, the [[Okoli, Croatia|Okoli]] natural gas storage facility, 27 end-users and 37 distribution systems.&lt;ref name=&quot;Plinacro-system&quot;&gt;{{cite web|publisher=[[Plinacro]]|url=http://www.plinacro.hr/default.aspx?id=264|title=Transportni sustav|trans-title=Transport system|language=Croatian|accessdate=8 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Croatian car number plates]]
* [[Transport in Zagreb]]
* [[Hrvatske autoceste]]
* [[Croatian Railways]]

== References ==
{{Commons category}}
{{Reflist}}

{{Croatia topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Transportation in Europe}}

[[Category:Transport in Croatia| ]]</text>
      <sha1>d5n3qlgp4yfwxys5fxg56tmk7rezarz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
