  <page>
    <title>Couplet</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6530</id>
    <revision>
      <id>942471783</id>
      <parentid>942440442</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-24T21:52:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Robby.is.on</username>
        <id>5230605</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/87.221.120.208|87.221.120.208]] ([[User talk:87.221.120.208|talk]]) to last revision by 2001:56A:7042:6000:614D:3605:8D1E:3339 ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{other uses}}
{{refimprove|date=September 2014}}

A '''couplet''' is a pair of successive lines of [[Metre (poetry)|metre]] in poetry.  A couplet usually consists of two successive lines that [[rhyme]] and have the same metre. A couplet may be formal (closed) or run-on (open).  In a formal (or closed) couplet, each of the two lines is end-stopped, implying that there is a grammatical pause at the end of a line of verse.  In a run-on (or open) couplet, the meaning of the first line continues to the second.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;couplet.&quot; [[Encyclopædia Britannica]]. Encyclopædia Britannica Online Academic Edition. Encyclopædia Britannica Inc., 2013. Web. 12 Nov. 2013&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
The word &quot;couplet&quot; comes from the French word meaning &quot;two pieces of iron riveted or hinged together.&quot; The term &quot;couplet&quot; was first used to describe successive lines of verse in Sir P. Sidney's '' Arcadia '' in 1590: &quot;In singing some short coplets, whereto the one halfe beginning, the other halfe should answere.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oed.com/;jsessionid=21C3D384C49DB50A2116A667211BE681?authRejection=true&amp;url=%2Fview%2FEntry%2F43139%3Frskey%3DnmXq3u%26result%3D47784|title=Home : Oxford English Dictionary|website=oed.com|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20180514183041/http://www.oed.com/;jsessionid=21C3D384C49DB50A2116A667211BE681?authRejection=true&amp;url=%2Fview%2FEntry%2F43139%3Frskey%3DnmXq3u%26result%3D47784|archivedate=2018-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While couplets traditionally rhyme, not all do. Poems may use white space to mark out couplets if they do not rhyme. Couplets in [[iambic pentameter]] are called ''[[heroic couplet]]s''. [[John Dryden]] in the 17th century and [[Alexander Pope]] in the 18th century were both well known for their writing in heroic couplets.  The [[Poetic epigram]] is also in the couplet form. Couplets can also appear as part of more complex [[rhyme scheme]]s, such as [[sonnet]]s.

Rhyming couplets are one of the simplest rhyme schemes in poetry.  Because the rhyme comes so quickly, it tends to call attention to itself. Good rhyming couplets tend to &quot;explode&quot; as both the rhyme and the idea come to a quick close in two lines. Here are some examples of rhyming couplets where the sense as well as the sound &quot;rhymes&quot;:

:: True wit is nature to advantage dress'd;
:: What oft was thought, but ne'er so well express'd.
:: — Alexander Pope

:: Whether or not we find what we are seeking
:: Is idle, biologically speaking.
:: — [[Edna St. Vincent Millay]] (at the end of a sonnet)

On the other hand, because rhyming couplets have such a predictable rhyme scheme, they can feel artificial and plodding. Here is a Pope parody of the predictable rhymes of his era:
:: Where-e'er you find &quot;the cooling western breeze,&quot;
:: In the next line, it &quot;whispers through the trees;&quot;
:: If crystal streams &quot;with pleasing murmurs creep,&quot;
:: The reader's threatened (not in vain) with &quot;sleep.&quot;

==In English poetry==
Rhyming couplets are often used in [[Early Modern English]] poetry, as seen in [[Chaucer]]'s ''[[The Canterbury Tales]]''.  This work of literature is written almost entirely in rhyming couplets.  Similarly, [[Shakespearean]] [[sonnet]]s often employ rhyming couplets at the end to emphasize the theme. Take one of Shakespeare's most famous sonnets, [[Sonnet 18]], for example (the rhyming couplet is shown in italics):

:: Shall I compare thee to a summer's day?
:: Thou art more lovely and more temperate:
:: Rough winds do shake the darling buds of May,
:: And summer's lease hath all too short a date:
:: Sometimes too hot the eye of heaven shines,
:: And often is his gold complexion dimm'd;
:: And every fair from fair sometime declines,
:: By chance or nature's changing course untrimm'd;
:: But thy eternal summer shall not fade
:: Nor lose possession of that fair thou owest;
:: Nor shall Death brag thou wander'st in his shade,
:: When in eternal lines to time thou growest:
:: ''So long as men can breathe or eyes can see,''
:: ''So long lives this and this gives life to thee.''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shakespeare-online.com/sonnets/18.html|title=Shakespeare Sonnet 18 - Shall I compare thee to a summer's day|first=Amanda|last=Mabillard|website=www.shakespeare-online.com|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131112213943/http://www.shakespeare-online.com/sonnets/18.html|archivedate=2013-11-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In Chinese poetry==
[[File:Chinese Marks Door.JPG|thumb|A Chinese couplet on doorway]]
[[Chinese couplet]]s or &quot;contrapuntal couplets&quot; may be seen on doorways in Chinese communities worldwide. Couplets displayed as part of the [[Chinese New Year]] festival, on the first morning of the New Year, are called ''chunlian'' (春联). These are usually purchased at a market a few days before and glued to the doorframe. The text of the couplets is often traditional and contains hopes for prosperity. Other chunlian reflect more recent concerns. For example, the [[CCTV New Year's Gala]] usually promotes couplets reflecting current political themes in [[mainland China]].

Some Chinese couplets may consist of two lines of four [[Chinese character|characters]] each.  Couplets are read from top to bottom where the first pline starts from the right. But is also a 6 word diagraph with 19 lines

==In Tamil poetry==
[[File:Kural in Chennai Metro Train.jpg|thumb|A [[Tirukkural|Kural]] couplet on display inside a [[Chennai Metro]] train]]
[[Tamil literature]] contains some of the best known examples of ancient couplet poetry. The [[Tamil language]] has a rich and refined grammar for couplet poetry, and distichs in Tamil poetry follow the [[venpa]] metre.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zvelebil1973&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Kamil Zvelebil|title=The smile of Murugan: On Tamil literature of South India|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VF2VMUoY_okC&amp;pg=PA156|accessdate=11 December 2010|year=1973|publisher=BRILL|isbn=978-90-04-03591-1|pages=156–171}}&lt;/ref&gt; The most famous example for Tamil couplet poetry is the ancient Tamil moral text of [[Tirukkural]], which contains a total of 1330 couplets written in the [[kural (poetic form)|kural venpa]] metre from which the title of the work was derived centuries later. Each Kural couplet is made of exactly 7 words—4 in the first line and 3 in the second.&lt;ref name=&quot;GUPope_SacredKurral&quot;&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Pope 
 | first = G. U. 
 | title = The Sacred Kurral of Tiruvalluva Nayanar 
 | url = https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.43871
 | publisher = Asian Educational Services
 | edition =
 | date = 1886
 | location = New Delhi
 | pages = }}&lt;/ref&gt; The first word may rhyme with the fourth or the fifth word. Below is an example of a couplet:

:{{lang|ta|இலன்என்று தீயவை செய்யற்க செய்யின்}}
:{{lang|ta|இலனாகும் மற்றும் பெயர்த்து}}. (Couplet 205)

::''Transliteration'': Ilan endru theeyavai seyyarkka seyyin
::Ilanaagum matrum peyartthu

::''Translation'': Make not thy poverty a plea for ill;
::Thine evil deeds will make thee poorer still. ([[George Uglow Pope|Pope]], 1886)&lt;ref name=&quot;GUPope_SacredKurral&quot;/&gt;

==Distich==
The American poet [[J. V. Cunningham]] was noted for many distichs included in the various forms of [[epigram]]s included in his poetry collections, as exampled here:

Deep summer, and time passes. Sorrow wastes&lt;br&gt;To a new sorrow. While Time heals time hastes&lt;ref&gt;Barber, David 'A Brief for Epigrams' Parnassus Poetry Aug 19 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Antithetical couplet]]
* [[Biblical poetry]]
* [[Chastushka]]
* [[Closed couplet]]
* [[Coupletist]]
* [[wikt:distich|Distich]]
* [[Elegiac couplet]]
* [[Kabirdas]]
* [[Monostich]]
* [[Parallelism (rhetoric)|Parallelism]]
* [[Tristich]]

==References==
{{reflist}}
{{Wikisource}}

{{Poetic forms}}

[[Category:Poetic form]]
[[Category:Poetic rhythm]]
[[Category:2 (number)]]</text>
      <sha1>ch2wkuxvifwypvpo3ccmckd71vfp3nh</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
