  <page>
    <title>Columba</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6561</id>
    <revision>
      <id>937297792</id>
      <parentid>937107475</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-24T03:26:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jbening</username>
        <id>4936305</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>This is a relevant piece of information. Note for example the discussion on the talk page about changing the article title to Colmcille. Also, the use of the name in the Ireland section makes no sense without this.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{distinguish|text=[[Columbanus]], the Irish missionary monk who founded monasteries in France and Italy}}
{{other uses|Columba (disambiguation)|Saint Columba (disambiguation)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2019}}
{{Infobox saint
|name= Saint Columba
|image=Columba at Bridei's fort.jpg
|caption=Saint Columba, Apostle to the [[Picts]]
|titles=Apostle of the [[Picts]]
|birth_date=7 December 521
|birth_place=[[Gartan]], [[County_Donegal|Donegal]], [[Ireland]]
|death_date=9 June 597 (aged 75)
|death_place=[[Iona]], [[Scotland]]
|feast_day=9 June
|venerated_in=[[Roman Catholic Church]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Orthodox Church]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Anglican Communion]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Presbyterian Church]]
|beatified_date=
|beatified_place=
|beatified_by=
|canonized_date=
|canonized_place=
|canonized_by=
|major_shrine=[[Iona]], Scotland
|attributes=Monk's robes, Celtic tonsure and crosier.
|patronage=[[Derry]], [[floods]], [[bookbinding|bookbinders]], [[poet]]s, Ireland, and Scotland.
|issues=
|suppressed_date=
}}

'''Columba''' ({{lang-ir|Colm Cille}}, 'church dove';{{Efn | Other names include Irish Gaelic ''Chille'', Scots Gaelic ''Calum Cille'', Manx Gaelic ''Colum Keeilley'', and Old Norse ''Kolban'' or ''Kolbjørn''.}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = Kenyon | first = Sherrilyn | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=y6mYHORNa5IC&amp;pg=PA358 | title = The Writer's Digest character naming sourcebook | series = Writer's Digest Books | year = 2005 | page = 358}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | url = http://www.keltiskfromhet.no/ressurser/helligsky/pdf-filer/HlSky23_Columba.pdf| publisher = Keltiskfromhet | title = Columba | place = [[Norway|NO]] | language = no}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{lang-sco|Columbkille}};{{sfn|Father Colgan|1844|p=11}} 7 December 521 – 9 June 597) was an [[Gaelic Ireland|Irish]] [[abbot]] and missionary evangelist credited with spreading Christianity in what is today [[Scotland]] at the start of the [[Hiberno-Scottish mission]]. He founded the important [[Iona Abbey|abbey]] on [[Iona]], which became a dominant religious and political institution in the region for centuries. He is the patron saint of [[Derry]]. He was highly regarded by both the [[Gaels]] of [[Dál Riata]] and the [[Picts]], and is remembered today as a Catholic [[saint]] and one of the [[Twelve Apostles of Ireland]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Gratton-Flood1&quot;&gt;{{cite CE1913|first=W.H. |last=Gratton-Flood |wstitle=  Twelve Apostles of Erin|volume=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Ireland, he is commonly known as Colmcille.

Columba studied under some of Ireland's most prominent church figures and founded several monasteries in the country. Around 563 he and his twelve companions crossed to Dunaverty near [[Southend, Argyll]], in [[Kintyre]] before settling in Iona in Scotland, then part of the Ulster kingdom of Dál Riata, where they founded a new abbey as a base for spreading Celtic Christianity among the [[Fortriu|northern Pictish kingdoms]]{{sfn|Charles-Edwards|2000|p=303}}{{sfn|Wagner|Konstam|2012|p=14|ps=: states the Northern Pictish nations were still pagan while the southern Pictish kingdoms were Catholic}} who were pagan. He remained active in Irish politics, though he spent most of the remainder of his life in Scotland. Three surviving early medieval Latin [[hymn]]s may be attributed to him.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite EB1911|wstitle=Columba, Saint|volume=6|page=737|first=Edmund Crosby |last=Quiggin}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life in Ireland==
Columba was born to Fedlimid and Eithne of the [[Cenel Conaill]] in [[Gartan]], a district beside Lough Gartan, in [[Tír Chonaill]] (mainly modern [[County Donegal]]) in the north of [[Ireland]]. On his father's side, he is claimed as being great-great-grandson of [[Niall of the Nine Hostages]], a pseudo-historical [[High King of Ireland|Irish high king]] of the 5th century. He was [[Baptism|baptised]] in Temple-Douglas, in the County Donegal parish of [[Conwal and Leck|Conwal]] (midway between Gartan and [[Letterkenny]]), by his teacher and foster-uncle [[Cruithnechán]].{{sfn|Reeves|1850|p=82}}{{sfn|Munn|1985|p=}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Ordnance1986p&quot;&gt;{{Citation | title = Ordnance Survey Memoirs for the Parishes of Desertmartin and Kilcronaghan | publisher = Ballinascreen Historical Society | year = 1986}}.&lt;/ref&gt; It is not known for sure if his name at birth was Colmcille or if he adopted this name later in life; [[Adomnán]] (Eunan) of Iona thought it was his birth name but other Irish sources have claimed his name at birth was Crimthann (meaning 'fox').{{sfn|Adomnan of Iona|1995|p=}} In the Irish language his name means 'dove', which is the same name as the Prophet Jonah (Jonah in Hebrew is also 'dove'), which Adomnán of Iona as well as other early Irish writers were aware of, although it is not clear if he was deliberately named after Jonah or not.

[[File:St Columba's church, Gartan, Donegal.jpg|left|thumb|The remains of St. Columba's Church, [[Gartan]], [[County Donegal]].]]
When sufficiently advanced in letters he entered the monastic school of Movilla, at [[Newtownards]], under [[Finnian of Movilla]] who had studied at [[Ninian]]'s &quot;Magnum Monasterium&quot; on the shores of [[Galloway]]. He was about twenty, and a deacon when, having completed his training at Movilla, he travelled southwards into [[Leinster]], where he became a pupil of an aged bard named Gemman. On leaving him, Columba entered the monastery of [[Clonard Abbey|Clonard]], governed at that time by [[Finnian of Clonard|Finnian]], noted for sanctity and learning. Here he imbibed the traditions of the Welsh Church, for Finnian had been trained in the schools of [[Saint David]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Edmonds&quot;&gt;{{cite CE1913|last=Edmonds|first= Columba|wstitle=St. Columba, Abbot of Iona|volume=4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[History of Ireland (400–800)|early Christian Ireland]] the [[druid]]ic tradition collapsed due to the spread of the new Christian faith. The study of [[Latin]] learning and [[Christian theology]] in [[Monastery|monasteries]] flourished. Columba became a pupil at the monastic school at [[Clonard Abbey]], situated on the [[River Boyne]] in modern [[County Meath]]. During the sixth century, some of the most significant names in the history of Celtic Christianity studied at the Clonard monastery. The average number of scholars under instruction at Clonard was said to be 300.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gratton-Flood1&quot; /&gt; Columba was one of twelve students of [[Finnian of Clonard|St Finnian]] who became known as the [[Twelve Apostles of Ireland]]. He became a monk and eventually was [[Ordination|ordained]] a [[Presbyter|priest]].

Another preceptor of Columba was [[Mobhí Clárainech|St Mobhi]], whose monastery at [[Glasnevin]] was frequented by such famous men as [[St Canice]], [[St Comgall]], and [[St Ciarán]]. A pestilence which devastated Ireland in 544 caused the dispersion of Mobhi's disciples, and Columba returned to [[Ulster]], the land of his kindred. He was a striking figure of great stature and powerful build, with a loud, melodious voice which could be heard from one hilltop to another.&lt;ref name= crawley&gt;{{cite book |chapter-url=http://www.ewtn.com/library/MARY/COLUMBA.htm |chapter=Saint Columba, Abbot and Confessor—521-597 |last=Crawley |first=John J |title=Lives of the Saints |publisher=John J. Crawley &amp; Co |via=EWTN |date=1954}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following years were marked by the foundation of several important monasteries: [[Derry]], at the southern edge of [[Inishowen]]; Durrow, County Offaly; Kells, County Meath; and [[Swords, Dublin|Swords]].{{sfn|Sidwell|1995|p=70}} While at Derry it is said that he planned a pilgrimage to Rome and Jerusalem, but did not proceed farther than [[Tours, France|Tours]]. Thence he brought a copy of those gospels that had lain on the bosom of [[St. Martin of Tours|St. Martin]] for the space of 100 years. This relic was deposited in Derry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Edmonds&quot; /&gt;

Some traditions assert that sometime around 560 Columba became involved in a quarrel with [[Finnian of Moville]] of [[Movilla Abbey]] over a [[psalter]].  Columba copied the manuscript at the [[scriptorium]] under Finnian, intending to keep the copy. Finnian disputed his right to keep it. There is a suggestion that this conflict resulted in the [[Battle of Cúl Dreimhne]] in [[Cairbre Drom Cliabh]] (now in [[County Sligo]]) in 561, during which many men were killed. Richard Sharpe, translator of Adomnán's Life of St. Columba (referenced in the bibliography below) makes a stern caution at this point against accepting the many references that link the battle and Columba's leaving of Ireland, even though there is evidence in the annals that Columba supported his own king against the high king.  Political conflicts that had existed for some time resulted in the clan Neill's battle against King Diarmait at Cooldrevny in 561. An issue, for example, was the king's violation of the right of sanctuary belonging to Columba's person as a monk on the occasion of the murder of Prince Curnan, the Columba's kinsman.&lt;ref name=&quot;Edmonds&quot; /&gt; Prince Curnan of Connacht, who had fatally injured a rival in a hurling match and had taken refuge with Columba , was dragged from his protector's arms and slain by Diarmaid's men, in defiance of the rights of sanctuary.&lt;ref name=crawley/&gt;

A [[synod]] of [[clerics]] and scholars threatened to [[Excommunication|excommunicate]] him for these deaths, but [[Brendan of Birr]] spoke on his behalf. Eventually the process was deemed a miscarriage of justice. Columba's own conscience was uneasy, and on the advice of an aged hermit, Molaise, he resolved to expiate his sense of offence by departing Ireland. The term &quot;exile&quot; is used in some references. This, too, can be disputed, for the term &quot;pilgrimage&quot; is used more frequently in the literature about him. He left Ireland, but through the following years he would return several times in relationships with the communities he had founded there. Columba's copy of the [[psalter]] has been traditionally associated with the [[Cathach of St. Columba]]. In 574/5 during his return for the Synod of Drum Ceat he founded the [[Drumcliff monastery, County Sligo|monastery of Drumcliff]] in Cairbre, now County Sligo, near the battlefield.

==Scotland==
In 563, he travelled to [[Scotland]] with twelve companions (said to include [[Odran of Iona]]) in a wicker [[currach]] covered with leather. According to legend he first landed on the [[Mull of Kintyre|Kintyre]] Peninsula, near [[Southend, Kintyre|Southend]]. However, being still in sight of his native land, he moved farther north up the west coast of Scotland. The island of [[Iona]] was made over to him by his kinsman [[Conall mac Comgaill]] [[List of kings of Dál Riata|King of Dál Riata]],  who perhaps had invited him to come to Scotland in the first place.&lt;ref name=crawley/&gt; However, there is a sense in which he was not leaving his native people, as the Ulster [[Gaels]] had been colonising the west coast of Scotland for the previous couple of centuries.{{sfn|Fletcher|1989|pp=23-24}} Aside from the services he provided guiding the only centre of [[literacy]] in the region, his reputation as a holy man led to his role as a diplomat among the tribes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stcolumbaretreathouse.com/saint_columba.htm|title=Who is St. Columba?|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090113152508/http://www.stcolumbaretreathouse.com/saint_columba.htm |archive-date=13 January 2009|publisher=St. Columba Retreat House|access-date=6 October 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are also many stories of miracles which he performed during his work to [[religious conversion|convert]] the Picts, the most famous being his encounter with an unidentified animal that some have equated with the [[Loch Ness Monster]] in 565. It is said that he banished a ferocious &quot;water beast&quot; to the depths of the [[River Ness]] after it had killed a Pict and then tried to attack Columba's disciple named Lugne (see Vita Columbae Book 2 below). He visited the [[Paganism|pagan]] King [[Bridei I of the Picts|Bridei]], King of [[Fortriu]], at his base in [[Inverness]], winning Bridei's respect, although not his conversion.  He subsequently played a major role in the politics of the country.  He was also very energetic in his work as a missionary, and, in addition to founding several churches in the [[Hebrides]], he worked to turn his monastery at Iona into a school for missionaries.  He was a renowned [[man of letters]], having written several [[hymns]] and being credited with having [[Calligraphy|transcribe]]d 300 books.  One of the few, if not the only, times he left Scotland was towards the end of his life, when he returned to Ireland to found the [[Durrow Abbey|monastery]] at [[Durrow, County Offaly|Durrow]].

Columba died on Iona and was buried in 597 by his [[monk]]s in the [[abbey]] he created. In 794 the Vikings descended on Iona. Columba's relics were finally removed in 849 and divided between Scotland and Ireland.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/scotland/history/articles/columba/ |title=Scotland's History – Columba |publisher=BBC |date=1 January 1970 |accessdate=17 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The parts of the relics which went to Ireland are reputed to be buried in [[Downpatrick]], [[County Down]], with [[Saint Patrick]] and [[Brigid of Kildare]] or at Saul Church neighbouring Downpatrick.  (Names of Iona), [[Inchcolm]] and [[Eilean Chaluim Chille]].

==Legacy==

===Ireland===
Colmcille is one of the three patron saints of Ireland, after [[Saint Patrick|Patrick]] and [[Brigid of Kildare]].&lt;ref name=&quot;IP&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.irishpost.com/life-style/125140-2-125140 |title=11 facts about St Colmcille – the Irish patron saint who was banished from Ireland for starting a tribal war |last=Lonergan |first=Aidan |date=9 June 2017 |work=[[The Irish Post]] |access-date=23 May 2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Colmcille is the patron-saint of the city of [[Derry]], where he founded a monastic settlement in c. 540.&lt;ref name=&quot;IP&quot; /&gt; The name of the city in [[Irish Gaelic|Irish]] is ''Doire Colmcille'' and is derived from the native oak trees in the area and the city's association with Colmcille. The Catholic Church of Saint Colmcille's Long Tower, and the Church of Ireland St Augustine's Church both claim to stand at the spot of this original settlement. The [[Church of Ireland]] Cathedral in Derry is dedicated to St Colmcille.

St. Columba's Primary School in Drumcondra is a girl's school named after the saint.
 
St. Colmcille's Primary School&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stcolmcilles.org/ |title= St Colmcilles |accessdate= 12 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; and St. Colmcille's Community School&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title =St. Colmcille’s Community School |url=http://www.stcolmcilles.ie/ |date= 8 May 2014 |accessdate=12 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; are two schools in [[Knocklyon]], Dublin, named after him, with the former having an annual day dedicated to the saint on 9 June.

The town of [[Swords, Dublin]] was reputedly founded by Colmcille in 560 AD.{{sfn|Sidwell|1995|p=70}} St Colmcille’s Boys’ National School and St. Colmcille’s Girls’ National School, both located in the town of Swords, are also named after the saint.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://stcolmcillesgns.scoilnet.ie/blog/|title=St. Colmcille's Girls' N.S. - Fáilte chuig suíomh idirlíon Scoil Cholmcille na gCailíní|website=stcolmcillesgns.scoilnet.ie}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[http://www.columba.ie/ The Columba Press], a religious and spiritual book company based in Dublin, is named after Colmcille.

[[Aer Lingus]], Ireland's national [[flag carrier]] has named one of its [[Airbus A330]] aircraft in commemoration of the saint (reg: EI-DUO).&lt;ref name=&quot;IP&quot; /&gt;

===Scotland===
Columba is credited as being a leading figure in the revitalisation of [[monasticism]]. The [[Clan MacCallum|Clan Malcolm/Clan McCallum]] claims its name from Columba and was reputedly founded by the descendants of his original followers.&lt;ref name=&quot;IP&quot; /&gt; It is also said that [[Clan Robertson]] Clan Donnachaidh / Duncan are heirs of Columba. [[Clan MacKinnon]] may also have some claim to being spiritual descendants of St Columba as after he founded his monastery on Isle [[Iona]], the MacKinnons were the [[abbot]]s of the Church for centuries.  This would also account for the fact that Clan MacKinnon is amongst the ancient clans of Scotland.{{sfn|Dowley|1977|p=}}{{pn|date=May 2019}}

The cathedral of the [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Argyll and the Isles|Catholic Diocese of Argyll and the Isles]] is placed under the patronage of Saint Columba,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://rcdai.org.uk/saint-columba/ |title=Saint Columba |website=Diocese of Argyll &amp; the Isles  |access-date=23 May 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; as are numerous [[Catholic school]]s and parishes throughout the nation. The [[Scottish Episcopal Church]], the [[Church of Scotland]], and the [[Evangelical Lutheran Church of England]] also have parishes dedicated to him.{{cn|date=May 2019}} The village of [[Kilmacolm]] in [[Renfrewshire (historic)|Renfrewshire]] is also derived from Colmcille's name.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url= http://www.scottish-places.info/parishes/parhistory752.html |publisher= University of Edinburgh |author= The Editors of the Gazetteer for Scotland |date= |accessdate=13 June 2009 |title= Kilmacolm history, Gazetteer for Scotland}}&lt;/ref&gt;

St Columba's Hospice, a prominent hospice in [[Edinburgh]], is named after the saint.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stcolumbashospice.org.uk|title=St Columba's Hospice, Palliative Care in Edinburgh,|website=www.stcolumbashospice.org.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Poetry ===
Columba currently has two poems attributed to him: &quot;Adiutor Laborantium&quot; and &quot;[[Altus Prosator]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ailb_Help&quot;&gt;{{Cite web | title = Helper of Workers | last = Moore | first = T.M. | work = The Fellowship of Ailbe | date = 23 August 2014 | accessdate = 10 June 2018 | url = https://www.ailbe.org/columns/item/5470-helper-of-workers | quote =  }}&lt;/ref&gt; Both poems are examples of [[Abecedarian hymn]]s in Latin written while Columba was at the [[Iona Abbey]].

The shorter of the two poems, &quot;Adiutor Laborantium&quot; consists of twenty-seven lines of eight syllables each, with each line following the format of an [[Abecedarian hymn]] using the [[Classical Latin alphabet]] save for lines 10-11 and 25-27. The content of the poem addresses God as a helper, ruler, guard, defender and lifter for those who are good and an enemy of sinners whom he will punish.{{sfn|Clancy|Gilbert|1995|p=73}}

&quot;[[Altus Prosator]]&quot; consists of twenty-three stanzas sixteen syllables long, with the first containing seven lines and six lines in each subsequent stanza. It uses the same format and alphabet as &quot;Adiutor Laborantium&quot; except with each stanza starting with a different letter rather than each line. The poem tells a story over three parts split into the beginning of time, history of Creation, and the Apocalypse or end of time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Wesseling|first=Margaret|year=1988|title=Structure and Image in the &quot;Altus Prosator&quot;: Columba's Symmetrical Universe|jstor=20557197|journal=Proceedings of the Harvard Celtic Colloquium|volume=8|pages=46–57}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other===
As of 2011, Canadians who are of [[Scottish Canadian|Scottish]] ancestry are the third largest [[ethnic group]] in the country and thus Columba's name is to be found attached to Catholic, [[Anglican Church of Canada|Anglican]] and [[Presbyterian]] parishes. This is particularly the case in eastern Canada, apart from French-speaking [[Quebec]].{{cn|date=May 2019}}

Throughout the US there are numerous parishes within the [[Latin liturgical rites|Catholic]] and [[Episcopal Church (United States)|Episcopalian]] denominations dedicated to Columba.{{cn|date=May 2019}} Within the [[Protestant]] tradition the [[Presbyterian Church (USA)|Presbyterian Church]] (which has its roots in Scottish Presbyterianism) also has parishes named in honour of Columba.{{cn|date=May 2019}} There is even an [[Orthodox Church]] monastery dedicated to the saint in the [[Massachusetts]] town of [[Southbridge, Massachusetts|Southbridge]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.aoiusa.org/new-monastery-founded/ |title=New Monastery Founded |last=Jacobse |first=Johannes |website=American Orthodox Institute  |access-date=23 May 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Columba is the patron saint of the [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Youngstown]], Ohio. The Cathedral there is named for him.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.stcolumbacathedral.org/history |title=History |website=Saint Columba Cathedral  |access-date=23 May 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Iona College (New York)|Iona College]], a small [[List of Roman Catholic universities and colleges in the United States|Catholic liberal arts college]] in [[New Rochelle, New York]], is named after the island on which Columba  established his first monastery in Scotland,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.iona.edu/about/history-mission/catholic-heritage.aspx |title=Catholic Heritage |website=Iona College |access-date=23 May 2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt; as is [[Iona College (Windsor, Ontario)|Iona College]] in [[Windsor, Ontario]],{{cn|date=May 2019}} [[Iona Presentation College, Perth]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.iona.wa.edu.au/view/welcome/history-presentation |title=History and the Presentation Sisters |website=Iona Presentation College  |access-date=23 May 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Iona College Geelong in [[Charlemont, Victoria]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://iona.vic.edu.au/welcome-to-iona-college-geelong/ |title=Welcome to Iona College Geelong |website=Iona College Geelong  |access-date=23 May 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are at least four [[pipe band]]s named for him; one each from [[Tullamore]], Ireland,&lt;ref&gt;{{Facebook|StColmcillesPipeBand |St Colmcille's Pipe Band, Tullamore }}&lt;/ref&gt; from [[Derry]], Northern Ireland,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.colmcillepipeband.com/ |title=colmcillepipeband.com |publisher=colmcillepipeband.com |date= |accessdate=12 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; from [[Kearny, New Jersey]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://stcolumcille.com/ |title=stcolumcille.com |publisher=stcolumcille.com |date= |accessdate=12 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; and from [[Cape Cod, Massachusetts]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.capecodpipesanddrums.com |title=capecodpipesanddrums.com |publisher=capecodpipesanddrums.com |date= |accessdate=12 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[St. Columba's School, Delhi|St. Columba's School]] one of the most prominent English-Medium schools in [[India]] run by the [[Congregation of Christian Brothers|Irish Christian Brothers]] is also named after the saint.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.stcolumbas.edu.in/about-school.html |title=About School |website=St. Columba's School, New Delhi |access-date=23 May 2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Munich [[Gaelic Athletic Association|GAA]] is named [[München]] Colmcilles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.munichgaa.de/ |title=munichgaa.de |publisher=munichgaa.de |date= |accessdate=12 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Saint Columba's Feast Day, 9 June, has been designated as International Celtic Art Day. The Book of Kells and the Book of Durrow, great medieval masterpieces of Celtic art, are associated with Columba.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.celticartday.com/photos |title=Why June 9 |website=International Day of Celtic Art  |access-date=23 May 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Benjamin Britten composed ''[[A Hymn of St Columba]]'' for choir and organ in 1962, setting a poem by the saint, on the occasion of the 1,400th anniversary of his voyage to Iona.&lt;ref name=&quot;Spicer&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| last = Spicer
| first = Paul
| authorlink = Paul Spicer
| url = http://www.boosey.com/downloads/brittenchoralenglish.pdf
| title = A Hymn of St Columba
| work = Britten Choral Guide
| publisher = [[Boosey &amp; Hawkes]]
| pages = 8–9
| accessdate = 13 November 2019
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==''Vita Columbae''==
[[File:Saint Columba.jpg|thumb|upright|Saint Columba. [[Stained glass]] window in [[Iona Abbey]]]]

The main source of information about Columba's life is the Vita Columbae, a hagiography written in the style of &quot;saint's lives&quot; narratives that had become widespread throughout medieval Europe. Compiled and drafted by scribes and clergymen, these accounts were written in Latin and served as written collections of the deeds and miracles attributed to the saint, both during his or her life or after death.&lt;ref name=Stansbury&gt;[http://foundationsirishculture.ie/essays/Stansbury.Composition.of.the.VC.pdf Stansbury, Mark. 'The Composition of Adomnan's Vita Columbae&quot;, ''Peritia'', 17-18 (2003-2004) 154-82]{{ISBN|2-503-51575-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; The canonization of a saint, especially one who had lived on the fringes of the medieval Christian world like Columba, required a well-written hagiography to be submitted to Rome, but popular belief and local cults of sainthood often led to the veneration of these men and women without official approval from the Church.

Writing a century after the death of Columba, the author [[Adomnán]] (also known as Eunan), served as the ninth Abbot of Iona until his death in 704.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gratton-Flood2&quot;&gt;{{CathEncy|first=W.H. |last=Gratton-Flood |title= St. Adamnan|id=01135c}}&lt;/ref&gt; James Earle Fraser asserts that Adomnán drew extensively from an existing body of accounts regarding the life of Columba, including a Latin collection entitled &quot;De uirtutibus sancti Columbae&quot;, composed c. 640 A.D. This earlier work is attributed to Cummene Find, who became the abbot of Iona and served as the leader of the monastic island community from 656 until his death in 668 A.D. or 669 A.D.{{sfn|Fraser|2009|p=98}}

While the Vita Columbae often conflicts with contemporaneous accounts of various battles, figures, and dates, it remains the most important surviving work from early medieval Scotland and provides a wealth of knowledge regarding the Picts and other ethnic and political groups from this time period. The Vita also offers a valuable insight into the monastic practices of Iona and the daily life of the early medieval Gaelic monks.

The surviving manuscripts include:

* A Generalia 1, Stadtbibliothek Schaffhausen, Switzerland; vellum, probably written before 713
* B1 British Library Add MS 35110 (B1), folios 96v-143r, probably written before 1165.
* B2 British Library Cotton MS Tiberius D III (B2), folios 192r-217r, written end of 12th to early 13th century. Due to fire damage in 1731, there are missing illegible portions on every page, and six folios [Book I, ch. 2 (diebus) to 22 (genibus) and 36 (viro) to 49 (omnia quae)] are missing completely.&lt;ref name=Stansbury/&gt;
* B3 British Library Royal MS 8 D IX (B3), folios 1r-70r, written in the fifteenth or early sixteenth century. The first 8 folios, [to I, 3 (haec puro pectore)] are missing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ucc.ie&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ucc.ie/celt/published/T201040/index.html |title=Life of St. Columba |publisher=Ucc.ie |date= |accessdate=17 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Instead of relying on chronological order, Adomnán categorises the events recorded in the ''Vita Columbae'' into three different books: Columba’s Prophecies, Columba’s Miracles, and Columba’s Apparitions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ucc.ie&quot; /&gt;

===Book one (Of his Prophetic Revelations)===

In the first book, the author Adomnán lists Columba's prophetic revelations, which come as a result of the his ability to view the present and the future simultaneously. Most of the short chapters begin with Columba informing his fellow monks that a person will soon arrive on the island or an event will imminently occur.

In one notable instance, Columba appears in a dream to King Oswald of Northumbria, and announces the king's incoming victory against the King Catlon (Cadwallon of Wales) in the Battle of Heavenfield. The people of Britain promise to convert to Christianity and receive baptism after the conclusion of the war. This victory signals the re-Christianizing of pagan England, and establishes King Oswald as ruler of the entirety of Britain.

Columba's other prophecies include when he sends a man named Batain off to perform his penance, but then Columba  turns to his friends and says Batain will instead return to Scotia and be killed by his enemies. Several of Saint Columba's prophecies reflect the scribal culture in which he was immersed, such his miraculous knowledge of the missing letter &quot;I” from Baithene's psalter or when he prophecies that an eager man will knock over his inkhorn and spill its contents.{{sfn|Adomnan of Iona|1995|loc=Book one, Chapter 17}}

=== Book two (Of his Miraculous Powers) ===

In the second book, Columba performs various miracles such as healing people with diseases, expelling malignant spirits, subduing wild beasts, calming storms, and even returning the dead to life. He also performs agricultural miracles that would hold a special significance to the common people of Ireland and the Britain such as when he casts a demon out of a pail and restores the spilt milk to its container.

The Vita contains a story that has been interpreted as the first reference to the Loch Ness Monster. According to Adomnán, Columba came across a group of Picts burying a man who had been killed by the monster. Columba saves a swimmer from the monster with the sign of the Cross and the imprecation, &quot;Thou shalt go no further, nor touch the man; go back with all speed.&quot; The beast flees, terrified, to the amazement of the assembled Picts who glorified Columba's God. Whether or not this incident is true, Adomnan's text specifically states that the monster was swimming in the River Ness – the river flowing from the loch – rather than in Loch Ness itself.{{sfn|Adomnan of Iona|1995|loc=Book two, Chapter 28}}

=== Book three (The Apparitions of Angels) ===

In book three, Adomnán describes different apparitions of the Saint, both that Columba receives and those that are seen by others regarding him. He mentions that, &quot;For indeed after the lapse of many years, ... St. Columba was excommunicated by a certain synod for some pardonable and very trifling reasons, and indeed unjustly&quot; (P.79- 80).

In one of the accounts, Columba, in this period of excommunication, goes to a meeting held against him in Teilte. Brendán, despite of all the negative reactions among the seniors toward Columba, kisses him reverently and assures that Columba is the man of God and that he sees Holy Angels accompanying Columba on his journey through the plain.{{sfn|Adomnan of Iona|1995|loc=Book three, Chapter 3}}

In the last Chapter, Columba foresees his own death when speaking to his attendant: &lt;blockquote&gt;This day in the Holy Scriptures is called the Sabbath, which means rest. And this day is indeed a Sabbath to me, for it is the last day of my present laborious life, and on it I rest after the fatigues of my labours; and this night at midnight, which commenceth the solemn Lord's Day, I shall, according to the sayings of Scripture, go the way of our fathers. For already my Lord Jesus Christ deigneth to invite me; and to Him, I say, in the middle of this night shall I depart, at His invitation. For so it hath been revealed to me by the Lord himself. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

And when the bell strikes midnight, Columba goes to the church and kneels beside the altar. His attendant witnesses heavenly light in the direction of Columba, and angels join him in his passage to the Lord: &lt;blockquote&gt;And having given them his holy benediction in this way, he immediately breathed his last. After his soul had left the tabernacle of the body, his face still continued ruddy, and brightened in a wonderful way by his vision of the angels, and that to such a degree that he had the appearance, not so much of one dead, as of one alive and sleeping.{{sfn|Adomnan of Iona|1995|loc=Book three, Chapter 23}} &lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Other early sources of Columba's life==
Both the ''Vita Columbae'' and the [[Bede]] (672/673-735) record Columba's visit to [[Bridei I of the Picts|Bridei]]. Whereas Adomnán just tells us that Columba visited Bridei, Bede relates a later, perhaps Pictish tradition, whereby Columba actually converts the Pictish king. Another early source is a poem in praise of Columba, most probably commissioned by Columba's kinsman, the King of the [[Uí Néill]] clan. It was almost certainly written within three or four years of Columba's death and is the earliest vernacular poem in European history. It consists of 25 [[stanza]]s of four verses of seven syllables each, called the [[Amra]] Coluim Chille.

Through the reputation of its venerable founder and its position as a major European centre of learning, Columba's Iona became a place of [[pilgrimage]]. Columba is historically revered as a warrior saint, and was often invoked for victory in battle.
His relics were finally removed in 849 and divided between [[Alba]] and Ireland. Relics of Columba were carried before Scottish armies in the reliquary made at Iona in the mid-8th century, called the Brecbennoch. Legend has it that the Brecbennoch was carried to the [[Battle of Bannockburn]] (24 June 1314) by the vastly outnumbered Scots army and the intercession of Columba helped them to victory. Since the 19th century the &quot;Brecbennoch of St. Columba&quot; has been identified with the [[Monymusk Reliquary]], although this is now doubted by scholars.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://local.nationalmusuems/explore-our-collections/stories/scottish-history-and-archaeology/monymusk-reliquary/|title=Monymusk reliquary|first1=Scottish|last1=History|first2=Archaeology 5 min|last2=read|website=National Museums Scotland}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Antiphoner]] of [[Inchcolm Abbey]], the &quot;Iona of the East&quot; (situated on an island in the [[Firth of Forth]]), a 14th-century prayer begins ''O Columba spes Scotorum...'' &quot;O Columbus, hope of the Scots&quot;.{{sfn|Gillespie|2016|p=133}}

==See also==
*[[St Columb's College]]
*[[Columba College]]
*[[Irish Golden Age|Early Christian Ireland]]
*[[Celtic Christianity]]
*[[List of people on stamps of Ireland]]
*[[Old High St Stephen's, Inverness]]
*[[Sainte-Colombe (disambiguation)|Sainte-Colombe]]
*[[Scoil Colmcille, Letterkenny|Scoil Colmcille]]
*[[Scotland in the Early Middle Ages]]
*[[St. Columba's School (disambiguation)]]

==References==
===Notes===
{{Notelist}}

===Citations===
{{Reflist}}

===Sources===
{{refbegin|2|indent=yes}}

*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Adomnán |author-link=Adomnán | orig-year=c. 700|editor-last=Reeves |editor-first=William|title=Life of Saint Columba, Founder of Hy|publisher = Edmonston and Douglas|publication-date=1874|publication-place=Edinburgh|url=http://www.ucc.ie/celt/published/T201040/|accessdate=14 September 2008}}

*{{cite book|ref=harv|author=Adomnan of Iona|authorlink=Adomnan of Iona|title=Life of St Columba|url={{google books|id=j7yFjie05bcC|plainurl=yes|keywords=Crimthann}}|year=1995|publisher=Penguin Books|isbn=978-0-14-190741-3}}

*{{cite book|editor-last=Anderson|editor-first=Alan Orr|editor-last2=Anderson|editor-first2=Marjorie Ogilvie|title=Adomnan's Life of Columba|publisher=Clarendon Press|year=1991}}

*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Charles-Edwards|first=T. M. |title=Early Christian Ireland|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=g6yq2sKLlFkC&amp;pg=PA303|year=2000|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-36395-2}}

*{{Cite book|title=Iona: The earliest poetry of a Celtic monastery|last=Clancy|first=Thomas Owen|last2 =Gilbert|first2 =Márkus|publisher =Edinburgh University Press|year=1995|isbn=978-0748605316 | location= |ref = harv|url= https://books.google.com/books?id=Z2piAAAAMAAJ}}

*{{cite book|ref=harv|author=Father Colgan|title=The Saintly Triad, Or The Lives of St. Patrick, St. Columbkille, and St. Bridget|url=https://archive.org/stream/saintlytriadorl00unkngoog#page/n10/mode/2up|year=1844|location=Dublin}}

*{{cite book|ref=harv|editor-first=Tim |editor-last=Dowley|title=Eerdman's handbook to the history of Christianity|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VQgZAQAAIAAJ|date=1977|publisher=Eerdmans|isbn=978-0-8028-3450-8}}

*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Fletcher|first=Richard A. |title=Who's who in Roman Britain and Anglo-Saxon England|url={{google books|id=q1wiAAAAMAAJ|plainurl=yes|page=23|keywords=columba}}|year=1989|publisher=Shepheard-Walwyn|isbn=978-0-85683-089-1}}

*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Fraser|first=James Earle |title=From Caledonia to Pictland: Scotland to 795|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=JaliXwNMpFsC&amp;pg=PA98|year=2009|publisher=Edinburgh University Press|isbn=978-0-7486-1232-1}}

*{{Cite book|title=Lochaber Lights|last=Gillespie|first=Donald S.|publisher=Holy Fire Publishing|year=2016|isbn=9781603835121|location=|ref=harv|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qCtyDAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA133}}

*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Munn|first=Alfred Moore |title=Notes on the Place Names of the Parishes and Townlands of the County of Londonderry|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jCJhPAAACAAJ|year=1985|publisher=Ballinascreen Historical Society}}

*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Sidwell|first=Keith |title=Reading Medieval Latin|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=fEbP_0FBNKcC&amp;pg=pa70|year=1995|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-44747-8}}

*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Reeves|first=William|title=Acts of Archbishop Colton in His Metropolitan Visitation of the Diocese of Derry, A.D. 1397; With a Rental of the See Estates at that Time; Edited, from the Original Roll Preserved in the Archiepiscopal Record Closet of Armagh|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Qa1jAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA82|year=1850|publisher=Irish Archaeological Society}}

*{{cite book|ref=harv|last1=Wagner|first1=Paul |last2=Konstam|first2=Angus |title=Pictish Warrior AD 297-841|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=EafvCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA14|year=2012|publisher=Bloomsbury Publishing|isbn=978-1-78200-216-1}}

{{refend}}

===Further reading===
{{refbegin}}
*{{Citation
|last=Broun |first=Dauvit |year=1999 |editor-last=Thomas |editor-first=Owen Clancy
|title=Spes Scotorum, Hope of Scots: Saint Columba, Iona and Scotland |publisher= T&amp;T Clark
|url=https://books.google.com/?id=fJcEAAAACAAJ |accessdate=14 September 2008
|isbn =0-567-08682-8}}
* Bullough, Donald A. &quot;Columba, Adomnan, and the Achievement of Iona,&quot; ''Scottish Historical Review'' 43, 44 (1964–65): 111–30, 17–33.
*{{Citation |last=Campbell |first=George F |year=2006 |title=The First and Lost Iona |publisher=Candlemas Hill |url=http://www.corbie.com/campbellbook.htm |isbn=1-873586-13-2 |publication-place=Glasgow |access-date=3 March 2010 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100614060759/http://www.corbie.com/campbellbook.htm |archive-date=14 June 2010 |url-status=dead  }}
* Finlay, Ian, ''Columba'' London: Gollancz, 1979. 
* Forbes, Andrew ; Henley, David (2012). ''Pages from the Book of Kells''. Chiang Mai: Cognoscenti Books. ASIN: B00AN4JVI0
*{{Citation
|last=Lewis |first=James |year=2007
|title=Paths of Exile: Narratives of St. Columba and the Praxis of Iona
|publisher=Cloverdale
|url=https://books.google.com/?id=DN6RHgAACAAJ |accessdate=14 September 2008
|isbn =1-929569-24-6}}
* {{cite book |last1= Healy |first1=John |author-link1=John Healy (bishop) |year=1892 |chapter= [[s:The ancient Irish church/Chapter 5|Saint Columba]] |title= The ancient Irish church|language= English|edition=1 |location=London |publisher=Religious Tract Society |pages=52–69 }}
*{{Citation
|last=Herbert |first=Máire |year=1996
|title=Iona, Kells, and Derry: The History and Hagiography of the Monastic &quot;Familia&quot; of Columba.
|publisher=Four Courts Press
|isbn=978-1851822447}} 
*{{Citation
|last=Magnusson |year=1990
|title=The Cambridge Biographical Dictionary
|publisher=Cambridge University Press
|url=https://books.google.com/?id=DN6RHgAACAAJ |accessdate=14 September 2008
|isbn =0-521-39518-6}}
* McLean,  Scott A. &quot;Columba 521–597,&quot; in ''Reader's Guide to British History'' (London: Routledge, 2003) online at Credo Reference. Historiography
*{{Citation
|last=Tranter |first=Nigel G. |author-link=Nigel Tranter |year=1987
|title=Columba |publisher=Hodder &amp; Stoughton
|url=https://books.google.com/?id=rJpjAAAAMAAJ |accessdate=14 September 2008
|isbn =0-340-40699-2}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{commonscat|Saint Columba|Columba}}
*[http://www.ucc.ie/celt/published/T201011/index.html CELT: ''On the Life of Saint Columba (Betha Choluim Chille)'' (tr. W. Stokes)]
*[http://www.ucc.ie/celt/published/T201040/index.html CELT: ''The Life of Columba, written by Adamnan'' (tr. W. Reeves)]
*{{CathEncy|id=04136a|title=St. Columba|short=yes}}
*[https://www.bbc.co.uk/history/scottishhistory/earlychurch/features_earlychurch_iona.shtml BBC: St Columba]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20051026164625/http://www.angelforce.co.uk/stmichael/columba.html The Church of St Michael and All Angels website: St Columba of Iona, Apostle to the Picts]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20060813184854/http://www.stthomasirondequoit.com/SaintsAlive/id176.htm St Columba on SaintsAlive]
*[http://www.a-wee-bit-of-ireland.com/eire_2007/gartan_05.html Photo of the birthplace of Columcille at Gartan]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20081014012738/http://www.columba.school.nz/ Coláiste Choilm]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20140714180302/http://armagh.anglican.org/index.php/parishes/portadown-st-columbus/ St Columba's Church of Ireland in Portadown]
* {{librivox book | title=The Life of Saint Columba Apostle of Scotland | author=Frances Alice FORBES}}
{{s-start}}
{{s-new|creation}} 
{{s-ttl|title=[[Abbot of Iona]]|years= died 597}} 
{{s-aft|after=[[Baithéne of Iona|Baithéne]]}}
{{s-end}}
* http://foundationsirishculture.ie/record/?id=52

{{Twelve Apostles of Ireland}}
{{Uí Néill}}
{{Portal bar|Saints}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Medieval Gaels from Scotland]]
[[Category:People from County Donegal]]
[[Category:Pictish people]]
[[Category:Abbots of Iona]]
[[Category:Scottish folklore]]
[[Category:Arthurian legend]]
[[Category:6th-century Latin writers]]
[[Category:6th-century Irish people]]
[[Category:6th-century Christian saints]]
[[Category:Medieval Irish saints]]
[[Category:Medieval Scottish saints]]
[[Category:Burials in Iona]]
[[Category:Irish expatriates in Scotland]]
[[Category:Medieval Irish writers]]
[[Category:521 births]]
[[Category:597 deaths]]
[[Category:Angelic visionaries]]
[[Category:6th-century Scottish people]]
[[Category:Irish Christian missionaries]]
[[Category:Scottish Roman Catholic saints]]
[[Category:Christian missionaries in Scotland]]</text>
      <sha1>8hbhicmwxae7rs5cu67i00k86cre6ui</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
