  <page>
    <title>Columbanus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6501</id>
    <revision>
      <id>936795307</id>
      <parentid>935791372</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-21T01:43:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Manannan67</username>
        <id>36671443</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Hatnote|Not to be confused with [[Columba]], the Irish missionary to Scotland}}
{{EngvarB|date=October 2013}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2013}}
{{Infobox saint
| name            = Saint Columbanus
| image           = Saint Columbanus window at Abbey of Bobbio.jpg
| imagesize       =
| alt             = Picture of Saint Columbanus
| caption         = Saint Columbanus, stained glass window, [[Bobbio Abbey]] crypt
| titles          =
| birth_date      = 540
| birth_place     = [[Leinster]], [[Kingdom of Meath]]
| death_date      = 21 November 615
| death_place     = [[Bobbio|Bobium]], [[Kingdom of the Lombards]]
| venerated_in    = [[Eastern Orthodox Church]]&lt;br&gt;[[Roman Catholic Church]]
| beatified_date  =
| beatified_place =
| beatified_by    =
| canonized_date  =
| canonized_place =
| canonized_by    =
| major_shrine    =
| feast_day       = 21 November, 23 November
| attributes      =
| patronage       = Motorcyclists
| issues          =
| suppressed_date =
| suppressed_by   =
| tradition       =
| major_works     =
}}
'''Columbanus''' ({{lang-ga|Columbán}}, 540 – 21 November 615),&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt; also known as '''St. Columban''',&lt;ref name=UCANews&gt;{{cite news|title=St. Columban’s 1400th death anniversary celebrated in Hong Kong|url=http://directory.ucanews.com/news/st-columbans-1400th-death-anniversary-celebrated-in-hong-kong/2928|accessdate=19 December 2015|agency=Sunday Examiner|publisher=UCAN|date=December 11, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; was an [[Hiberno-Scottish mission|Irish missionary]] notable for founding a number of [[monastery|monasteries]] from around 590 in the [[Franks|Frankish]] and [[Lombards|Lombard]] kingdoms, most notably [[Luxeuil Abbey]] in present-day France and [[Bobbio Abbey]] in present-day Italy. He is remembered as a key figure in the [[Hiberno-Scottish mission]], or Irish missionary activity in early medieval Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|last=Edmonds |first=Columba |title=St. Columbanus |encyclopedia=The Catholic Encyclopedia |volume=4 |pages= |publisher=Robert Appleton Company |location=New York |year=1908 |id= |url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/04137a.htm |accessdate=15 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In recent years, however, as Columbanus's deeds and legacy have come to be re-examined by historians, the traditional narrative of his career has been challenged and doubts have been raised regarding his actual involvement in missionary work and the extent to which he was driven by purely religious motives or also by a concern for playing an active part in politics and church politics in [[Francia]].&lt;ref&gt;Flechner and Meeder, ''The Irish in Early Medieval Europe'', pp. 195–213, 231–41, [https://books.google.com/books?id=U5wmDAAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false on Googlebooks]&lt;/ref&gt;{{clarification|date=January 2020}}

Columbanus taught an Irish monastic rule and penitential practices for those repenting of sins, which emphasised private confession to a priest, followed by penances levied by the priest in reparation for the sins. Columbanus is one of the earliest identifiable [[Hiberno-Latin]] writers.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt;

==Sources==
Most of what we know about Columbanus is based on Columbanus' own works (as far as they have been preserved)&lt;ref name=&quot;walker&quot;&gt;{{cite book|editor-last=Walker |editor-first=G. S. Murdoch |title=Columbani Opera |publisher=The Dublin Institute for Advanced Studies |location=Dublin |year=1957 |isbn=978-1-85500-050-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;lapidge&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Lapidge |first=Michael |title=Columbanus: Studies on the Latin Writings |year=1997 |publisher=Boydell Press |location=Woodbridge |isbn=978-0-85115-667-5 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=odZIo0Q6z90C}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Jonas of Bobbio|Jonas from Susa]]'s ''Vita Columbani'' (''Life of Columbanus''), which was written between 639 and 641.{{#tag:ref|Walker's edition is also available on [http://www.ucc.ie/celt/ CELT] (University College Cork), a website that provides Irish medieval sources with English translations. A critical edition of Jonas' ''Vita Columbani'' was published in 1905 by Bruno Krusch in ''[http://www.dmgh.de/de/fs1/object/display/bsb00000740_meta:titlePage.html?sortIndex=010:070:0037:010:00:00 Monumenta Germaniae Historica]''[http://www.dmgh.de/de/fs1/object/display/bsb00000740_meta:titlePage.html?sortIndex=010:070:0037:010:00:00 , ''Scriptores Rerum Germaincarum'' ''in usum schoarum'', vol. 37, Hannover: Hahn 1905]. See also [http://legacy.fordham.edu/halsall/basis/columban.asp Internet Medieval Sourcebook].|group=Note}} Jonas entered Bobbio after Columbanus' death but relied on reports of monks who still knew Columbanus.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt; A description of miracles of Columbanus written by an anonymous monk of Bobbio is of much later date.&lt;ref name=&quot;ohara&quot;&gt;O'Hara, Alexander, and Faye Taylor. &quot;Aristocratic and Monastic Conflict in Tenth-Century Italy: the Case of Bobbio and the ''Miracula Sancti Columbani''&quot; in ''Viator. Medieval and Renaissance Studies''. 44:3 (2013), pp. 43–61.&lt;/ref&gt; In the second volume of his ''Acta Sanctorum O.S.B.'', Mabillon gives the life in full, together with an appendix on the miracles of the saint, written by an anonymous member of the Bobbio community.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt;

==Biography==
===Early life===
Columbanus (the Latinised form of ''Columbán'', meaning ''the white dove'') was born in the [[Kingdom of Meath]], now part of [[Leinster]], in Ireland in 540,&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt; the year [[Benedict of Nursia|Saint Benedict]] died at Monte Cassino.&lt;ref name=&quot;smith&quot;&gt;Smith 2012, p. 201.&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to his birth, his mother was said to have had visions of bearing a child who, in the judgment of those interpreting the visions, would become a &quot;remarkable genius&quot;.&lt;ref name=jonas-6&gt;Jonas 643, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; Columbanus was well-educated in the areas of grammar, rhetoric, geometry, and the Holy Scriptures.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=jonas-7&gt;Jonas 643, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt;

Columbanus left home to study under Sinell, Abbot of Cleenish in [[Lough Erne]].{{refn|Cleenish is derived from the Irish words &quot;Claon Inis&quot;, which mean &quot;sloping island&quot;. The remains of the monastery can be seen at [[Bellanaleck]], [[County Fermanagh]].|group=Note}} Under Sinell's instruction, Columbanus composed a commentary on the [[Psalms]]. He then moved to [[Bangor Abbey]] on the coast of [[Bangor, County Down|Down]], where [[Comgall|Saint Comgall]] was serving as the abbot. He stayed at Bangor until his fortieth year,&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt; when he received Comgall's permission to travel to the continent.&lt;ref name=&quot;wallace&quot;&gt;Wallace 1995, p. 43.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=jonas-10&gt;Jonas 643, p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Frankish Gaul===
{{Location map+ | France |relief=1
| places =
  {{Location map~ | France
    | label = Saint-Malo
    | lat_deg = 48.6481
    | lon_deg = -2.0075 }}
  {{Location map~ | France
    | label = Luxeuil
    | lat_deg = 47.4859
    | lon_deg = 6.2253 }}
  {{Location map~ | France
    | label = Soissons
    | lat_deg = 49.3817
    | lon_deg = 3.3236 }}
  {{Location map~ | France
    | label = Nantes
    | lat_deg = 47.2181
    | lon_deg = -1.5528 }}
| caption = Columbanus in Frankish Gaul
}}
Columbanus gathered twelve companions for his journey—[[Saint Attala]], Columbanus the Younger, Cummain, Domgal ([[Deicolus]]), Eogain, Eunan, [[Saint Gall]], Gurgano, Libran, Lua, Sigisbert, and Waldoleno—and together they set sail for the continent. After a brief stop in Britain, most likely on the Scottish coast, they crossed the channel and landed in Brittany in 585.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt; At [[Saint-Malo]] in Brittany, there is a granite cross bearing the saint's name to which people once came to pray for rain in times of drought. The nearby village of [[Saint-Coulomb]] commemorates him in name.&lt;ref name=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Columbanus Today: Places of His Ministry |work=Monastic Ireland |date= |url=http://www.monasticireland.com/storiesofsaints/columbanustoday.htm |accessdate=15 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Columbanus and his companions were received with favour by [[Guntram|King Gontram of Burgundy]], and soon they made their way to [[Annegray]], where they founded a monastery in an abandoned Roman fortress. Despite its remote location in the [[Vosges Mountains]], the community became a popular pilgrimage site that attracted so many monastic vocations that two new monasteries had to be formed to accommodate them.&lt;ref name=&quot;cna&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=St. Columbanus |work=Catholic News Agency |date= |url=http://www.catholicnewsagency.com/saint.php?n=716 |accessdate=16 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 590, Columbanus obtained from King Gontram the Gallo-Roman castle called ''Luxovium'' in present-day [[Luxeuil-les-Bains]], some eight miles from Annegray.&lt;ref name=jonas-17&gt;Jonas 643, p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; The castle, soon transformed into a monastery, was located in a wild region, thickly covered with pine forests and brushwood. Columbanus erected a third monastery called ''Ad-fontanas'' at present-day [[Fontaine-lès-Luxeuil]], named for its numerous springs.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=jonas-17/&gt; These monastic communities remained under Columbanus' authority, and their rules of life reflected the Irish tradition in which he had been formed. As these communities expanded and drew more pilgrims, Columbanus sought greater solitude, spending periods of time in a hermitage and communicating with the monks through an intermediary. Often he would withdraw to a cave seven miles away, with a single companion who acted as messenger between himself and his companions.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;cna&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=jonas-17/&gt;

During his twenty years in [[Gaul]] (in present-day France), Columbanus became involved in a dispute with the Frankish bishops who may have feared his growing influence. During the first half of the sixth century, the councils of Gaul had given to bishops absolute authority over religious communities. As heirs to the Irish monastic tradition, Columbanus and his monks used the Irish Easter calculation, a version of [[Bishop Augustalis]]'s 84-year ''[[computus]]'' for determining the date of Easter ([[Quartodecimanism]]), whereas the [[Franks]] had adopted the [[Victorius of Aquitaine|Victorian]] cycle of 532 years. The bishops objected to the newcomers' continued observance of their own dating, which—among other issues—caused the end of [[Lent]] to differ. They also complained about the distinct [[Celtic Christianity#Monastic tonsure|Irish tonsure]]. In 602, the bishops assembled to judge Columbanus, but he did not appear before them as requested. Instead, he sent a letter to the prelates—a strange mixture of freedom, reverence, and charity—admonishing them to hold synods more frequently, and advising them to pay more attention to matters of equal importance to that of the date of Easter. In defence of his following his traditional paschal cycle, he wrote:
{{quote|I am not the author of this divergence. I came as a poor stranger into these parts for the cause of Christ, Our Saviour. One thing alone I ask of you, holy Fathers, permit me to live in silence in these forests, near the bones of seventeen of my brethren now dead.&lt;ref name=&quot;smith&quot;/&gt;}}
When the bishops refused to abandon the matter, Columbanus, following Saint Patrick's canon, appealed directly to [[Pope Gregory I]]. In the third and only surviving letter, he asks &quot;the holy Pope, his Father&quot; to provide &quot;the strong support of his authority&quot; and to render a &quot;verdict of his favour&quot;, apologising for &quot;presuming to argue as it were, with him who sits in the chair of Peter, Apostle and Bearer of the Keys&quot;. None of the letters were answered, most likely due to the pope's death in 604.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt; Columbanus then sent a letter to Gregory's successor, [[Pope Boniface IV]], asking him to confirm the tradition of his elders—if it is not contrary to the Faith—so that he and his monks can follow the rites of their ancestors. Before Boniface responded, Columbanus moved outside the jurisdiction of the Frankish bishops. Since the Easter issue appears to end around that time, Columbanus may have stopped celebrating Irish date of Easter after moving to Italy.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt;{{refn|The Italians themselves followed a third system of reckoning Easter, based on the improvements to Victorius's system introduced by [[Dionysius Exiguus]] at the time he devised the [[Anno Domini]] dating system.&lt;ref&gt;Blackburn 1999, p. 767.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}}

Columbanus was also involved in a dispute with members of the Frankish royal family. Upon the death of King Gontram of Burgundy, the succession passed to his nephew, [[Childebert II]], the son of his brother [[Sigebert I|Sigebert]] and Sigebert's wife [[Brunhilda of Austrasia]]. When Childebert II died, he left two sons, [[Theuderic II]] who inherited the Kingdom of [[Burgundy]], and [[Theudebert II]] who inherited the Kingdom of [[Austrasia]]. Since both were minors, Brunhilda, their grandmother, declared herself their guardian and controlled the governments of the two kingdoms.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt;

Theuderic II venerated Columbanus and often visited him, but the saint admonished and rebuked him for his behaviour.  When Theuderic began living with a mistress, the saint objected, earning the displeasure of Brunhilda, who thought a royal marriage would threaten her own power.&lt;ref name=&quot;cna&quot;/&gt; The saint did not spare the demoralised court, and Brunhilda became his bitterest foe.&lt;ref name=&quot;cusack&quot;&gt;Cusack 2002, p. 173.&lt;/ref&gt; Angered by the saint's moral stand, Brunhilda stirred up the bishops and nobles to find fault with his monastic rules. When Theuderic II finally confronted Columbanus at Luxeuil, ordering him to conform to the country's conventions, the saint refused and was then taken prisoner to [[Free Imperial City of Besançon|Besançon]]. Columbanus managed to escape his captors and returned to his monastery at Luxeuil. When the king and his grandmother found out, they sent soldiers to drive him back to Ireland by force, separating him from his monks by insisting that only those from Ireland could accompany him into exile.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt;

Columbanus was taken to [[Nevers]], then travelled by boat down the [[Loire]] river to the coast. At [[Tours]] he visited the tomb of [[Martin of Tours|Saint Martin]], and sent a message to Theuderic II indicating that within three years he and his children would perish. When he arrived at [[Nantes]], he wrote a letter before embarkation to his fellow monks at Luxeuil monastery. Filled with love and affection, the letter urges his brethren to obey [[Saint Attala|Attala]], who stayed behind as abbot of the monastic community.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt; The letter concludes:
{{quote|They come to tell me the ship is ready. The end of my parchment compels me to finish my letter. Love is not orderly; it is this which has made it confused. Farewell, dear hearts of mine; pray for me that I may live in God.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt;}}
Soon after the ship set sail from Nantes, a severe storm drove the vessel back ashore. Convinced that his holy passenger caused the tempest, the captain refused further attempts to transport the monk. Columbanus made his way across Gaul to visit King [[Chlothar II]] of Neustria at [[Soissons]] where he was gladly received. Despite the king's offers to stay in his kingdom, Columbanus left Neustria in 611 for the court of King [[Theudebert II]] of [[Austrasia]] in the northeastern part of the Kingdom of the [[Merovingian dynasty|Merovingian Franks]].&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt;

===The Alps===
Columbanus travelled to [[Metz]], where he received an honourable welcome, and then proceeding to [[Mainz]], where he sailed upwards the [[Rhine]] river to the lands of the [[Suebi]] and [[Alemanni]] in the northern Alps, intending to preach the Gospel to these people. He followed the Rhine river and its tributaries, the [[Aar]] and the [[Limmat]], and then on to [[Lake Zurich]]. Columbanus chose the village of [[Tuggen]] as his initial community, but the work was not successful.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt; He continued north-east by way of Arbon to [[Bregenz]] on [[Lake Constance]]. Here the saint found an [[Oratory (worship)|oratory]] dedicated to Saint Aurelia containing three brass images of their tutelary deities. Columbanus commanded [[Saint Gall|Gallus]], who knew the local language, to preach to the inhabitants, and many were converted. The three brass images were destroyed, and Columbanus blessed the little church, placing the relics of Saint Aurelia beneath the altar. A monastery was erected, [[Wettingen-Mehrerau Abbey|Mehrerau Abbey]], and the brethren observed their regular life. Columbanus stayed in Bregenz for about one year.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt; Following an uprising against the community, possibly related to that region being taken over by the saint's old enemy King Theuderic II, Columbanus resolved to cross the Alps into Italy.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt; Gallus remained in this area and died there 646. About seventy years later  at the place of Gallus' cell the [[Abbey of St Gall|Monastery of Saint Gall]] was founded, which in itself was the origin of the city of [[St. Gallen]] again about another three hundred years later.

===Italy===
{{Location map+ | Alps
| relief = Y
| default_width = 300
| places =
  {{Location map~ | Alps
    | label = Tuggen
    | lat_deg = 47.2011
    | lon_deg = 8.94103 }}
  {{Location map~ | Alps
    | label = Bregenz
    | lat_deg = 47.50343
    | lon_deg = 9.74732 }}
  {{Location map~ | Alps
    | label = Milan
    | lat_deg = 45.46427    
    | lon_deg = 9.18951 }}
  {{Location map~ | Alps
    | label = Bobbio
    | lat_deg = 44.7716    
    | lon_deg = 9.38641 }}
| caption = Columbanus in the Alps and Italy
}}
Columbanus arrived in [[Milan]] in 612 and was warmly greeted by King [[Agilulf]] and Queen [[Theodelinda]] of the [[Lombards]].{{refn|Some scholars believe that Columbanus made two journeys into Italy, which were confounded by Jonas. On his first journey, Columbanus went to Rome and received from Pope Gregory I sacred relics.&lt;ref name=&quot;stokes&quot;&gt;Stokes 2007, p. 132&lt;/ref&gt; This may possibly explain the traditional spot in St. Peter's, where Pope Gregory I and Columbanus are supposed to have met.&lt;ref name=&quot;moran&quot;&gt;Moran 2010, p. 105&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}} He immediately began refuting the teachings of [[Arianism]], which had enjoyed a degree of acceptance in Italy. He wrote a treatise against Arianism, which has since been lost. Queen Theodelinda, the devout daughter of Duke [[Garibald I of Bavaria]], played an important role in restoring [[Nicene Christianity]] to a position of primacy against Arianism, and was largely responsible for the king's conversion to Christianity.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt;

At the king's request, Columbanus wrote a letter to [[Pope Boniface IV]] on the controversy over the ''[[Three-Chapter Controversy|Three Chapters]]''—writings by Syrian bishops suspected of [[Nestorianism]], which had been condemned in the fifth century as [[heresy]]. [[Pope Gregory I]] had tolerated in Lombardy those persons who defended the ''Three Letters'', among them King Agilulf. Columbanus agreed to take up the issue on behalf of the king. The letter begins with an apology that a &quot;foolish Scot (''Scottus'', Irishman)&quot; would be writing for a Lombard king. After acquainting the pope with the imputations brought against him, he entreats the pontiff to prove his orthodoxy and assemble a council. He writes that his freedom of speech is consistent with the custom of his country.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt; Some of the language used in the letter might now be regarded as disrespectful, but in that time, faith and austerity could be more indulgent.&lt;ref name=&quot;montalembert-440&quot;&gt;Montalembert 1861, p. 440.&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, the letter expresses the most affectionate and impassioned devotion to the Holy See.
{{quote|We Irish, though dwelling at the far ends of the earth, are all disciples of Saint Peter and Saint Paul ... we are bound to the Chair of Peter, and although Rome is great and renowned, through that Chair alone is she looked on as great and illustrious among us ... On account of the two Apostles of Christ, you are almost celestial, and Rome is the head of the whole world, and of the Churches.}}
If Columbanus' zeal for orthodoxy caused him to overstep the limits of discretion, his real attitude towards Rome is sufficiently clear, calling the pope &quot;his Lord and Father in Christ&quot;, the &quot;Chosen Watchman&quot;, and the &quot;First Pastor, set higher than all mortals&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;allnatt&quot;&gt;Allnatt 2007, p. 105.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Bobbio-abbazia di san colombano-esterno6.jpg|thumb|left|Facade of the Abbey in Bobbio]]
King Agilulf gave Columbanus a tract of land called [[Bobbio]] between Milan and Genoa near the [[Trebbia]] river, situated in a [[defile (geography)|defile]] of the [[Apennine Mountains]], to be used as a base for the conversion of the Lombard people. The area contained a ruined church and wastelands known as ''Ebovium'', which had formed part of the lands of the papacy prior to the Lombard invasion. Columbanus wanted this secluded place, for while enthusiastic in the instruction of the Lombards he preferred solitude for his monks and himself. Next to the little church, which was dedicated to [[Saint Peter]], Columbanus erected a monastery in 614. [[Bobbio Abbey]] at its foundation followed the Rule of Saint Columbanus, based on the monastic practices of [[Celtic Christianity]]. For centuries it remained the stronghold of orthodoxy in northern Italy.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt;{{refn|Bobbio Abbey may have been the model for the monastery in northern Italy in [[Umberto Eco]]'s novel ''[[The Name of the Rose]]''.|group=Note}}

===Death===
[[Image:Bobbio bridge.jpg|thumb|Stone bridge over the Trebbia river leading to [[Bobbio Abbey]] in northern Italy]]
During the last year of his life, Columbanus received messenges from King [[Chlothar II]], inviting the saint to return to Burgundy, now that his enemies were dead. Columbanus did not return, but requested that the king should always protect his monks at [[Luxeuil Abbey]]. He prepared for death by retiring to his cave on the mountainside overlooking the Trebbia river, where, according to a tradition, he had dedicated an oratory to Our Lady.&lt;ref name=&quot;montalembert-444&quot;&gt;Montalembert 1861, p. 444.&lt;/ref&gt; Columbanus died at Bobbio on 21 November 615.

==Rule of Saint Columbanus==
The Rule of Saint Columbanus embodied the customs of [[Bangor Abbey]] and other Irish monasteries. Much shorter than the [[Rule of Saint Benedict]], the Rule of Saint Columbanus consists of ten chapters, on the subjects of obedience, silence, food, poverty, humility, chastity, choir offices, discretion, mortification, and perfection.&lt;ref name=&quot;ucc&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Columbanus Hibernus |editor-last=Walker |editor-first=G.S.M. |title=Monk's Rules |work=Corpus of Electronic Texts |publisher=University College Cork |date= |url=http://www.ucc.ie/celt/online/T201052.html |accessdate=19 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the first chapter, Columbanus introduces the great principle of his Rule: obedience, absolute and unreserved. The words of seniors should always be obeyed, just as &quot;Christ obeyed the Father up to death for us.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ucc&quot;/&gt; One manifestation of this obedience was constant hard labour designed to subdue the flesh, exercise the will in daily self-denial, and set an example of industry in cultivation of the soil. The least deviation from the Rule entailed corporal punishment, or a severe form of fasting.&lt;ref name=&quot;smith&quot;/&gt; In the second chapter, Columbanus instructs that the rule of silence be &quot;carefully observed&quot;, since it is written: &quot;But the nurture of righteousness is silence and peace&quot;. He also warns, &quot;Justly will they be damned who would not say just things when they could, but preferred to say with garrulous loquacity what is evil ...&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ucc&quot;/&gt; In the third chapter, Columbanus instructs, &quot;Let the monks' food be poor and taken in the evening, such as to avoid repletion, and their drink such as to avoid intoxication, so that it may both maintain life and not harm ...&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ucc&quot;/&gt; Columbanus continues:
{{quote|For indeed those who desire eternal rewards must only consider usefulness and use. Use of life must be moderated just as toil must be moderated, since this is true discretion, that the possibility of spiritual progress may be kept with a temperance that punishes the flesh. For if temperance exceeds measure, it will be a vice and not a virtue; for virtue maintains and retains many goods. Therefore we must fast daily, just as we must feed daily; and while we must eat daily, we must gratify the body more poorly and sparingly ...&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ucc&quot;/&gt;}}

[[Image:Columbanus at Bobbio.jpg|thumb|upright|Fresco of Saint Columbanus in [[Brugnato Cathedral]]]]
In the fourth chapter, Columbanus presents the virtue of poverty and of overcoming greed, and that monks should be satisfied with &quot;small possessions of utter need, knowing that greed is a leprosy for monks&quot;. Columbanus also instructs that &quot;nakedness and disdain of riches are the first perfection of monks, but the second is the purging of vices, the third the most perfect and perpetual love of God and unceasing affection for things divine, which follows on the forgetfulness of earthly things. Since this is so, we have need of few things, according to the word of the Lord, or even of one.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ucc&quot;/&gt; In the fifth chapter, Columbanus warns against vanity, reminding the monks of Jesus' warning in Luke 16:15: &quot;You are the ones who justify yourselves in the eyes of others, but God knows your hearts. What people value highly is detestable in God's sight.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ucc&quot;/&gt; In the sixth chapter, Columbanus instructs that &quot;a monk's chastity is indeed judged in his thoughts&quot; and warns, &quot;What profit is it if he be virgin in body, if he be not virgin in mind? For God, being Spirit.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ucc&quot;/&gt;

In the seventh chapter, Columbanus instituted a service of perpetual prayer, known as ''[[laus perennis]]'', by which choir succeeded choir, both day and night.&lt;ref name=&quot;montalembert-405&quot;&gt;Montalembert 1898, II p. 405.&lt;/ref&gt; In the eighth chapter, Columbanus stresses the importance of discretion in the lives of monks to avoid &quot;the downfall of some, who beginning without discretion and passing their time without a sobering knowledge, have been unable to complete a praiseworthy life.&quot; Monks are instructed to pray to God for to &quot;illumine this way, surrounded on every side by the world's thickest darkness&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ucc&quot;/&gt; Columbanus continues: 
{{quote|So discretion has got its name from discerning, for the reason that it discerns in us between good and evil, and also between the moderate and the complete. For from the beginning either class has been divided like light and darkness, that is, good and evil, after evil began through the devil's agency to exist by the corruption of good, but through God's agency Who first illumines and then divides. Thus righteous Abel chose the good, but unrighteous Cain fell upon evil.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ucc&quot;/&gt;}}

In the ninth chapter, Columbanus presents mortification as an essential element in the lives of monks, who are instructed, &quot;Do nothing without counsel.&quot; Monks are warned to &quot;beware of a proud independence, and learn true lowliness as they obey without murmuring and hesitation.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ucc&quot;/&gt; According to the Rule, there are three components to mortification: &quot;not to disagree in mind, not to speak as one pleases with the tongue, not to go anywhere with complete freedom.&quot; This mirrors the words of Jesus, &quot;For I have come down from heaven not to do my will but to do the will of him who sent me.&quot; (John 6:38) In the tenth and final chapter, Columbanus regulates forms of [[penance]] (often corporal) for offences, and it is here that the Rule of Saint Columbanus differs significantly from that of Saint Benedict.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt;

The Communal Rule of Columbanus required monks to fast every day until ''[[Nones (liturgy)|None]]'' or 3 p.m., this was later relaxed and observed on designated days.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frantzen 2014&quot;&gt;Frantzen, Allen J. (2014). ''Food, Eating and Identity in Early Medieval England''. The Boydell Press. p. 184. {{ISBN|978-1-84383-908-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; Columbanus' Rule regarding diet was very strict. Monks were to eat a limited diet of beans, vegetables, flour mixed with water and small bread of a loaf, taken in the evenings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frantzen 2014&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;O'Hara, Alexander. (2018). ''Jonas of Bobbio and the Legacy of Columbanus''. Oxford University Press. p. 59. {{ISBN|978-0-19-085800-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The habit of the monks consisted of a tunic of undyed wool, over which was worn the [[cuculla]], or cowl, of the same material. A great deal of time was devoted to various kinds of [[manual labour]], not unlike the life in monasteries of other rules. The Rule of Saint Columbanus was approved of by the [[Fourth Council of Mâcon]] in 627, but it was superseded at the close of the century by the Rule of Saint Benedict. For several centuries in some of the greater monasteries the two rules were observed conjointly.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt;

==Character==
Columbanus did not lead a perfect life. According to Jonas and other sources, he could be impetuous and even headstrong, for by nature he was eager, passionate, and dauntless. These qualities were both the source of his power and the cause of his mistakes.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt; His virtues, however, were quite remarkable. Like many saints, he had a great love for God's creatures. Stories claim that as he walked in the woods, it was not uncommon for birds to land on his shoulders to be caressed, or for squirrels to run down from the trees and nestle in the folds of his cowl.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt; Although a strong defender of Irish traditions, he never wavered in showing deep respect for the Holy See as the supreme authority. His influence in Europe was due to the conversions he effected and to the rule that he composed. It may be that the example and success of Saint [[Columba]] in Caledonia inspired him to similar exertions.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt; The life of Columbanus stands as the prototype of missionary activity in Europe, followed by such men as [[Saint Kilian]], [[Vergilius of Salzburg]], [[Donatus of Fiesole]], [[Wilfrid]], [[Willibrord]], [[Suitbert of Kaiserwerdt]], [[Saint Boniface]], and [[Ursicinus of Saint-Ursanne]].&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt;

==Miracles==
The following are the principal miracles attributed to his intercession:&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt;
# Procuring food for a sick monk and curing the wife of his benefactor
# Escaping injury while surrounded by wolves
# Causing a bear to evacuate a cave at his biddings
# Producing a spring of water near his cave
# Replenishing the Luxeuil granary
# Multiplying bread and beer for his community
# Curing sick monks, who rose from their beds at his request to reap the harvest
# Giving sight to a blind man at Orleans
# Destroying with his breath a cauldron of beer prepared for a pagan festival
# Taming a bear and yoking it to a plough

Jonas relates the occurrence of a miracle during Columbanus' time in Bregenz, when that region was experiencing a period of severe famine.
{{quote|Although they were without food, they were bold and unterrified in their faith, so that they obtained food from the Lord. After their bodies had been exhausted by three days of fasting, they found so great an abundance of birds, just as the quails formerly covered the camp of the children of Israel, that the whole country near there was filled with birds. The man of God knew that this food had been scattered on the ground for his own safety and that of his brethren, and that the birds had come only because he was there. He ordered his followers first to render grateful praises to the Creator, and then to take the birds as food. And it was a wonderful and stupendous miracle; for the birds were seized according to the father's commands and did not attempt to fly away. The manna of birds remained for three days. On the fourth day, a priest from an adjacent city, warned by divine inspiration, sent a supply of grain to Saint Columban. When the supply of grain arrived, the Omnipotent, who had furnished the winged food to those in want, immediately commanded the phalanxes of birds to depart. We learned this from Eustasius, who was present with the others, under the command of the servant of God. He said that no one of them remembered ever having seen birds of such a kind before; and the food was of so pleasant savor that it surpassed royal viands. Oh, wonderful gift of divine mercy!&lt;ref name=jonas-54&gt;Jonas 643, p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Legacy==
[[File:Annegray.JPG|thumb|Monastery ruins at Annegray]]
[[File:Bobbio Coat of Arms.png|thumb|left|100px|Coat of Arms of Bobbio with doves, symbol of Columbanus]]
One historians states Columbanus had a &quot;very strong sense of Irish identity...He’s the first person to write about Irish identity, he’s the first Irish person that we have a body of literary work from, so even on that point of view he’s very important in terms of Irish identity.”&lt;ref&gt;https://www.irishcatholic.com/europes-forgotten-founding-fathers/&lt;/ref&gt; In 1950 a congress celebrating the 1400 anniversary of his birth took place in [[Luxeuil]], [[France]]. It was attended by [[Robert Schuman]], [[Sean MacBride]], future [[Pope John XXIII]] and [[John A. Costello]] who said  “All statesmen of today might well turn their thoughts to St Columban and his teaching. History records that it was by men like him that civilisation was saved in the 6th century.”&lt;ref&gt;https://www.irishtimes.com/opinion/columban-the-patron-saint-of-a-united-europe-1.961368&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://www.irishtimes.com/culture/books/the-first-poem-about-ireland-by-monk-who-inspired-heaney-and-eu-s-architect-1.3013550&lt;/ref&gt;

Columbanus is also remembered as the first Irish person to be the subject of a biography. An Italian monk named [[Jonas of Bobbio]] wrote a biography of him some 20 years after Columbanus’ death.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.irishtimes.com/culture/books/the-first-poem-about-ireland-by-monk-who-inspired-heaney-and-eu-s-architect-1.3013550&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://www.irishtimes.com/opinion/columban-the-patron-saint-of-a-united-europe-1.961368&lt;/ref&gt; His use of the phrase in 600  AD totius Europae (all of Europe) in a letter to [[Pope Gregory the Great]] is the first known use of the expression.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.historyireland.com/20th-century-contemporary-history/sidelines-20/&lt;/ref&gt;

In France, the ruins of Columbanus' first monastery at [[Annegray]] are legally protected through the efforts of the Association Internationale des Amis de St Columban, which purchased the site in 1959. The association also owns and protects the site containing the cave, which acted as Columbanus' cell, and the holy well, which he created nearby.&lt;ref name=&quot;mi&quot;/&gt; At [[Luxeuil-les-Bains]], the Basilica of Saint Peter stands on the site of Columbanus' first church. A statue near the entrance, unveiled in 1947, shows him denouncing the immoral life of King [[Theuderic II]]. Formally an abbey church, the basilica contains old monastic buildings, which have been used as a minor seminary since the nineteenth century. It is dedicated to Columbanus and houses a bronze statue of him in its courtyard.&lt;ref name=&quot;mi&quot;/&gt;

In Lombardy, [[San Colombano al Lambro]] in Milan, [[San Colombano Belmonte]] in Turin, and [[San Colombano Certénoli]] in Genoa all take their names from the saint.&lt;ref name=&quot;webb&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Webb |first=Alfred |title=A Compendium of Irish Biography |publisher=BiblioLife |location=Charleston |year=2009 |url=http://www.libraryireland.com/biography/SaintColumbanus.php |isbn=978-1116472684}}&lt;/ref&gt; The last monastery erected by Columbanus at [[Bobbio]] remained for centuries the stronghold of orthodoxy in northern Italy.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt;

If [[Bobbio Abbey]] in Italy became a citadel of faith and learning, [[Luxeuil Abbey]] in France became the &quot;nursery of saints and apostles&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;edmonds&quot;/&gt; The monastery produced sixty-three apostles who carried his rule, together with the Gospel, into France, Germany, Switzerland, and Italy.&lt;ref name=&quot;stokes-254&quot;&gt;Stokes, p. 254.&lt;/ref&gt; These disciples of Columbanus are accredited with founding over one hundred different monasteries.&lt;ref name=&quot;stokes-74&quot;&gt;Stokes, p. 74.&lt;/ref&gt; The canton and town still bearing the name of [[St. Gallen]] testify to how well one of his disciples succeeded.

The [[Missionary Society of Saint Columban]], founded in 1916, and the [[Missionary Sisters of St. Columban]], founded in 1924, are both dedicated to Columbanus.

==Veneration==
[[Image:Bobbio-abbazia di san colombano-cripta3.jpg|thumb|Remains of Columbanus, [[Bobbio Abbey]] crypt]]
The remains of Columbanus are preserved in the crypt at [[Bobbio Abbey]]. Many miracles have been credited to his intercession. In 1482, the relics were placed in a new shrine and laid beneath the altar of the crypt. The sacristy at Bobbio possesses a portion of the skull of the saint, his knife, wooden cup, bell, and an ancient water vessel, formerly containing sacred relics and said to have been given to him by [[Pope Gregory I]]. According to some authorities, twelve teeth of the saint were taken from the tomb in the fifteenth century and kept in the treasury, but these have since disappeared.&lt;ref name=&quot;stokes-183&quot;&gt;Stokes, p. 183.&lt;/ref&gt;

Columbanus is named in the [[Roman Martyrology]] on 23 November, which is his feast day in Ireland. His feast is observed by the Benedictines on 21 November. Columbanus is the patron saint of motorcyclists. In art, Columbanus is represented bearded bearing the monastic cowl, holding in his hand a book with an Irish [[satchel (bag)|satchel]], and standing in the midst of wolves. Sometimes he is depicted in the attitude of taming a bear, or with sun-beams over his head.&lt;ref name=&quot;husenheth&quot;&gt;Husenheth, p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==

===Notes===
{{Reflist|group=Note}}

===Citations===
{{Reflist}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite book|last=Allnatt |first=Charles F. B. |title=Cathedra Petri |publisher=Kessinger Publishing |location=Whitefish, Montana |year=2007 |isbn=978-0548785072}}
* {{cite book |last1=Blackburn |first1=Bonnie |last2=Holford-Strevens |first2=Leofranc |title=The Oxford Companion to the Year |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=1999 |isbn=978-0192142313 |url=https://archive.org/details/oxfordcompaniont00blac }}
* {{cite book|last=Concannon |first=Thomas |title=The Life of St. Columban |publisher=BCR |location=Wimpole Close |year=2010 |isbn=978-1117876894}}
* {{cite book |last=Cusack |first=Margaret Anne |title=The Illustrated History of Ireland |publisher=Gramercy |location=New York |year=2002 |url=https://archive.org/details/illustratedhisto00cusa |isbn=978-0517629147 }}
* {{cite encyclopedia|last=Edmonds |first=Columba |title=St. Columbanus |encyclopedia=The Catholic Encyclopedia |volume=4 |pages= |publisher=Robert Appleton Company |location=New York |year=1908 |id= |url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/04137a.htm |asin=B000R4GCD8}}
* {{Cite book|editor-last=Flechner |editor-first=Roy |editor2-last=Meeder |editor2-first=Sven| title=The Irish in Early Medieval Europe: Identity, Culture and Religion|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=U5wmDAAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |year= 2016|location=London |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |isbn=9781137430595}}
* Gray, Patrick T. R., and Michael W. Herren (1994). &quot;Columbanus and the Three Chapters Controversy&quot; in ''Journal of Theological Studies'', NS, 45, pp.&amp;nbsp;160–170.
* {{cite book |last1= Healy |first1=John |author-link1=John Healy (bishop) |year=1892 |chapter= [[s:The ancient Irish church/Chapter 6|Saint Columbanus]]|title= The ancient Irish church|language= English|edition=1 |location=London |publisher=Religious Tract Society |pages= 70–81}}
* {{cite book|last=Jonas |first= |title=Life of St. Columban |publisher=BiblioLife |location=Charleston |year=2009 |url=http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/basis/columban.asp |isbn=978-1113338648}}
* {{cite book|last=Lapidge |first=Michael, ed |title=Columbanus: Studies in Latin Writings |publisher=Boydell Press |location=London |year=1997 |isbn=978-0851156675}}
* {{cite book|last=Mc Sweeney |first=Richard |title=Abiding in Bobbio |publisher=Lulu |location=Raleigh, North Carolina |year=2015 |isbn=978-1329382237}}
* {{cite book|last=Montalembert |first=Charles Forbes |title=The Monks of the West |volume=2 |publisher=William Blackwood |location=London |year=1861 |isbn= }}
* {{cite book|last=Moran |first=Patrick Francis |title=Irish Saints in Great Britain |publisher=Nabu Press |location=Charleston |year=2010 |isbn=978-1176742925}}
* {{cite book|last=Ó Fiaich |first=Tomás |title=Columbanus in His Own Words |publisher=Veritas |location=Dublin |year=2012 |isbn=978-1847303578}}
* {{cite book|last=O'Hara |first=Alexander |title=Saint Columbanus: Selected Writings |publisher=Veritas |location=Dublin |year=2015 |isbn=978-1847305879}}
* {{cite book|last=Richter |first=Michael |title=Bobbio in the Early Middle Ages: The Abiding Legacy of Columbanus |publisher=Four Courts Press |location=Dublin |year=2008 |isbn=978-1846821035}}
* {{cite book|last=Smith |first=Sir William |last2=Wace |first2=Henry |title=A Dictionary of Christian Biography, Literature, Sects and Doctrines |publisher=Nabu Press |location=Charleston |year=2012 |isbn=978-1286170847}}
* {{cite book|last=Stokes |first=Margaret |title=Six Months in the Apennines |publisher=Kessinger Publishing |location=Whitefish, Montana |year=2007 |isbn=978-0548271971}}
* {{cite book|last=Wallace |first=Martin |title=A Little Book of Celtic Saints |publisher=Appletree Press |location=Belfast |year=1995 |isbn=978-0862814564}}
* {{cite book|last=Wilson |first=James |title=Life of St. Columban |publisher=Clonmore and Reynolds Ltd |location=Dublin |year=1954 |isbn= |asin=B0007IWDF0}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
* [http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/basis/columban.asp The Life of St. Columban, by the Monk Jonas] ([[Internet History Sourcebooks Project|Internet Medieval Sourcebook]])
* {{CathEncy|wstitle=St. Columbanus|short=x}}
* {{Cite NIE|wstitle=Columban, Saint|short=x}}
* [http://www.knightsofstcolumbanus.ie/ The Order of the Knights of Saint Columbanus]
* [https://celt.ucc.ie//published/T201053/index.html Sermons of Columbanus] ([[Corpus of Electronic Texts|CELT]])
* [https://celt.ucc.ie/published/T201054/index.html Letters of Columbanus] (CELT)

{{Hiberno-Latin authors}}
{{Canonization}}
{{Subject bar |portal1= Biography |portal2= Catholicism |portal3= Ireland}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Irish writers]]
[[Category:Irish literature]]
[[Category:6th-century Latin writers]]
[[Category:7th-century Latin writers]]
[[Category:543 births]]
[[Category:615 deaths]]
[[Category:Irish Christian missionaries]]
[[Category:Founders of Catholic religious communities]]
[[Category:7th-century Christian saints]]
[[Category:Burials at Bobbio Abbey]]
[[Category:6th-century Christians]]
[[Category:Medieval Irish saints]]
[[Category:6th-century Irish people]]
[[Category:7th-century Irish people]]
[[Category:People from County Meath]]
[[Category:Irish expatriates in France]]
[[Category:Irish expatriates in Italy]]
[[Category:Medieval Irish saints on the Continent]]
[[Category:Medieval Irish writers]]
[[Category:Founders of Christian monasteries]]
[[Category:7th-century Irish writers]]
[[Category:6th-century Irish writers]]
[[Category:Latinists]]</text>
      <sha1>ndp5u3b2rsmk736wlinpa2n8vb2iav8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
