  <page>
    <title>Curry</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6597</id>
    <revision>
      <id>939865080</id>
      <parentid>938287176</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-09T05:17:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ranjithsiji</username>
        <id>13289863</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Gallery */ add image</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Bhuna|the place|Bhuna, Fatehabad|other uses|Curry (disambiguation)}}
{{pp-vandalism|small=yes}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2020}}
{{Infobox food
| name            = Curry
| image           = Indiandishes.jpg
| image_size      = 
| caption         = A variety of vegetable curries from India
| alternate_name  = 
| country = [[Indian subcontinent]]
| region = Worldwide
| main_ingredient = [[Spice]]s, [[herb]]s, usually fresh or dried hot [[Black pepper|pepper]]s or [[Chili pepper|chillies]]
| calories        = 
| other           = 
}}

'''Curry''' (plural '''curries''') is a variety of dishes originating in the [[Indian subcontinent]], dating back to the [[Indus Valley Civilisation]],&lt;ref name=IVC&gt;
Soity Banerjee (22 June 2016), [https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-india-36415079 Cooking the world's oldest known curry], BBC News;
Kate Springer (23 January 2020), [https://edition.cnn.com/travel/article/curry-origins-history/index.html &quot;From Pakistan to the Caribbean: Curry's journey around the world&quot;], ''CNN'';
D. Balasubramanian (22 January 2017), [https://www.thehindu.com/sci-tech/health/Spicy-food-leads-to-longer-life/article17077718.ece Spicy food leads to longer life], ''The Hindu''
&lt;/ref&gt; that use a complex [[spice mix|combination of spices or herbs]], usually including ground [[turmeric]], [[cumin]], [[coriander]], [[ginger]], and fresh or dried [[chili pepper|chilies]]. Curry is generally prepared in a sauce.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.macmillandictionary.com/dictionary/british/curry_1 |title=Curry definition and synonyms |work=Macmillan Dictionary |access-date=13 December 2016 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180612162302/https://www.macmillandictionary.com/dictionary/british/curry_1 |archive-date=12 June 2018 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; Curry dishes prepared in the southern states of India, where the word also originated, may be spiced with leaves from the [[curry tree]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |work=NPR |url=https://www.npr.org/2011/09/28/140735689/fresh-curry-leaves-add-a-touch-of-india |date=28 September 2011 |title=Fresh Curry Leaves Add a Touch of India}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are many varieties of dishes called 'curries'. For example, in original traditional cuisines, the precise selection of spices for each dish is a matter of national or regional cultural tradition, religious practice, and, to some extent, family preference. Such dishes are called by specific names that refer to their ingredients, spicing, and cooking methods.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Collingham, Lizzie|title=Curry: A Tale of Cooks and Conquerors|url=https://archive.org/details/curry00lizz|url-access=registration|location=New York, NY|publisher= Oxford University Press|date= 2006|page=[https://archive.org/details/curry00lizz/page/115 115]}} &quot;No Indian, however, would have referred to his or her food as a curry. The idea of a curry is, in fact, a concept that the Europeans imposed on India's food culture. Indians referred to their different dishes by specific names ... But the British lumped all these together under the heading of curry.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Spices are used both whole and ground, cooked or raw, and they may be added at different times during the cooking process to produce different results. The main spices found in most curry powders of the Indian subcontinent are coriander, cumin, and turmeric. A wide range of additional spices may be included depending on the geographic region and the foods being included (fish, lentils, red or white meat, rice, and vegetables).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Raghavan, S. |title=Handbook of Spices, Seasonings and Flavourings|publisher= CRC Press|date= 2007 |isbn=0-8493-2842-X|page= 302}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Curry powder]], a commercially prepared mixture of spices, is largely a Western creation, dating to the 18th century. Such mixtures are commonly thought to have first been prepared by Indian merchants for sale to members of the [[British Raj|British Colonial government and army]] returning to Britain.

Outside of the Indian subcontinent, &quot;curry&quot; may also be used to describe the various unrelated native dishes of [[Island Southeast Asia]], [[Mainland Southeast Asia]], and [[Oceania]] which use coconut milk or spice pastes and are commonly eaten over rice (like the Filipino ''[[ginataan]]'' and Thai ''[[gaeng]]'' class of dishes).&lt;ref name=&quot;Van Esterik&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Van Esterik |first1=Penny |title=Food Culture in Southeast Asia |date=2008 |publisher=ABC-CLIO |isbn=9780313344206 |pages=58–59}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dishes called 'curry' may contain fish, meat, poultry, or shellfish, either alone or in combination with vegetables. Additionally, many instead are entirely vegetarian, eaten especially among those who hold ethical or religious proscriptions against eating meat or seafood.

Curries may be either 'dry' or 'wet'. Dry curries are cooked with very little liquid which is allowed to evaporate, leaving the other ingredients coated with the spice mixture. Wet curries contain significant amounts of sauce or gravy based on [[broth]], [[coconut cream]], [[coconut milk]], dairy [[cream]], legume purée, sautéed crushed onion, [[tomato purée]] or [[yogurt]].

==Etymology==
[[File:To make a Currey the India Way - Hannah Glasse 1748.jpg|thumb|upright=1.5|Glasse's recipe for curry, first published in 1747; the first known anglicised form of kaṟi]]

''Curry'' is an [[Anglicisation|anglicised]] form of the [[Tamil language|Tamil]] word ''{{IAST|kaṟi}}'' meaning 'sauce' or 'relish for rice' that uses the leaves of the [[curry tree]] (''Murraya koenigii'').&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=AS |first1=Senthil Kumar |title=AN ETYMOLOGICAL DICTIONARY OF TAMIL LOANWORDS IN ENGLISH, HINDI, SANSKRIT, GREEK, MINOAN AND CYPRO-MINOAN LANGUAGES |date=2017 |publisher=senthil kumar a s |page=83 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6PPEDgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA83&amp;dq=Murraya+koenigii+curry+tamil+kari+portuguese&amp;hl=en&amp;newbks=1&amp;newbks_redir=0&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwij5bqD2pjnAhWTLH0KHX5FCc8Q6AEwAHoECAUQAg#v=onepage&amp;q=Murraya%20koenigii%20curry%20tamil%20kari%20portuguese&amp;f=false |accessdate=23 January 2020 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;oed&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Curry |url=https://www.etymonline.com/word/curry#etymonline_v_491 |publisher=Online Etymology Dictionary, Douglas Harper |accessdate=8 October 2018 |date=2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Kaṟi'' is described in a mid-17th century [[Portuguese cuisine|Portuguese]] cookbook by members of the British [[East India Company]],&lt;ref name=taylor/&gt; who were trading with Tamil merchants along the [[Coromandel Coast]] of southeast India,&lt;ref name = &quot;SahniCur&quot;&gt;Sahni, Julie. ''Classic Indian Cooking''. (New York, NY: William Morrow and Company, Inc., c.1980), p.39-40.&lt;/ref&gt; becoming known as a &quot;spice blend ... called ''kari podi'' or curry powder&quot;.&lt;ref name = &quot;SahniCur&quot; /&gt; The first known appearance in its anglicised form (spelt ''currey'') appears in a 1747 book of recipes published by [[Hannah Glasse]].&lt;ref name=oed/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;taylor&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/food/0/24432750|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140329151125/http://www.bbc.co.uk/food/0/24432750|url-status=dead|archive-date=29 March 2014|title=Curry: Where did it come from?|author=Taylor, Anna-Louise|date=11 October 2013|publisher=BBC: Food Knowledge and Learning|accessdate=4 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The word ''cury'' appears in the 1390s English cookbook, ''[[The Forme of Cury]]'',&lt;ref name=taylor/&gt; but is unrelated and comes from the Middle French word ''[[wikt:cuire|cuire]]'', meaning 'to cook'&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Thys fourme of cury ys compyled of þe mayster cokes of kyng Richard þe secund ... by assent of Maysters of physik and of phylosophye&quot;.--&quot;Things sweet to taste: selections from the Forme of Cury&quot;. 1996 {{ISBN|0-86373-134-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origins, history and dissemination==
Archaeological evidence dating to 2600 BCE from [[Mohenjo-daro]] suggests the use of mortar and pestle to pound spices including mustard, fennel, cumin, and tamarind pods with which they flavoured food.&lt;ref&gt;Iyer, Raghavan. ''660 Curries''. (New York, NY: Workman Publishing, c.2008), p.2-3.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Black pepper]] is native to the [[Indian subcontinent]] and [[Southeast Asia]] and has been known to [[Indian cuisine|Indian cooking]] since at least 2000 BCE.&lt;ref name=DS&gt;Davidson &amp; Saberi 178&lt;/ref&gt; Domesticated Pacific [[coconut]]s and [[coconut milk]] extraction technology was introduced to southern India and Sri Lanka by the ancient [[Austronesian maritime trade network|maritime trade network]] of the [[Austronesian peoples]], which influenced the curries of these regions.&lt;ref name=&quot;mahdi&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first1=Waruno|last1=Mahdi|editor1-first=Roger|editor1-last=Blench|editor2-first=Matthew|editor2-last=Spriggs|title =Archaeology and Language III: Artefacts, languages, and texts|chapter =The Dispersal of Austronesian boat forms in the Indian Ocean|publisher =Routledge|series =One World Archaeology|volume=34|year =1999|page=144|isbn =0415100542|url =https://www.academia.edu/8669249/The_Dispersal_of_Austronesian_boat_forms_in_the_Indian_Ocean}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lutz&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last1=Lutz |first1=Diana |title=Deep history of coconuts decoded |url=https://source.wustl.edu/2011/06/deep-history-of-coconuts-decoded/ |website=theSource |accessdate=16 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The establishment of the [[Mughal Empire]], in the early 15th century, also influenced some curries, especially in the north. Another influence was the establishment of the Portuguese trading centre in [[Goa]] in 1510, resulting in the introduction of [[chili pepper]] to India from the Americas, as a byproduct of the [[Columbian Exchange]].

Curry was introduced to [[English cuisine]] starting with [[Anglo-Indian cuisine|Anglo-Indian cooking]] in the 17th century as spicy sauces were added to plain boiled and cooked meats.&lt;ref name=Collingham&gt;{{cite book |last1=Collingham |first1=Lizzie |title=Curry: A Biography |date=2005 |location=London |page=115}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 1758 edition of [[Hannah Glasse]]'s ''[[The Art of Cookery]]'' contains a recipe &quot;To make a curry the Indian way&quot;.&lt;ref name=DicksonWright304&gt;[[Clarissa Dickson Wright|Dickson Wright, Clarissa]] (2011) ''A History of English Food''. London: Random House. Pages 304–305&lt;/ref&gt; Curry was first served in coffee houses in Britain from 1809, and has been increasingly popular in Great Britain, with major jumps in the 1940s and the 1970s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/8370054.stm |title=How Britain got the hots for curry |publisher=BBC |date=26 November 2009 |accessdate=29 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the 19th century, curry was also carried to the Caribbean by Indian [[indenture]]d workers in the British sugar industry. Since the mid-20th century, curries of many national styles have become popular far from their origins, and increasingly become part of international [[fusion cuisine]].

==Indian subcontinent==
From the culinary point of view, it is useful to consider the [[Indian subcontinent]] to be the entire historical region encompassed prior to independence since August 1947; that is, the modern countries of India, Bangladesh, Pakistan and Sri Lanka. It is usual to distinguish broadly between northern and southern styles of Indian cuisine, recognising that within those categories are innumerable sub-styles and variations.&lt;ref name = &quot;CamNS&quot;&gt;Kiple, Kenneth F. and Kriemhild Coneè Ornelas, eds. ''Cambridge World History of Food, The.'' (Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press, c.2000), vol.2, p.1149f.&lt;/ref&gt; The distinction is commonly made with reference to the staple starch: wheat in the form of unleavened breads in the north; rice in the east; rice and [[millet]] in the south.&lt;ref name = &quot;CamNS&quot; /&gt;

===Bangladesh and West Bengal===
{{Main|Bangladeshi cuisine|Bengali cuisine|}}

[[File:Pointed Gourd Curry - Kolkata 2011-09-20 5428.JPG|right|thumb|Bengali gourd curry]]

[[Bengali cuisine]], which refers to the [[cuisine of Bangladesh]] and the [[West Bengal]] state of India, includes curries, including seafood and fresh fish. Mustard seeds and mustard oil are added to many recipes, as are poppy seeds. [[British Bangladesh|Emigrants]] from the [[Sylhet district]] of Bangladesh founded the curry house industry in Britain and in [[Sylhet]] some restaurants run by expatriates specialise in British-style Indian food.&lt;ref name=Guardian62002&gt;{{cite news|author1=Audrey Gillan|title=From Bangladesh to Brick Lane|url=https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2002/jun/21/religion.bangladesh|accessdate=4 November 2015|work=The Guardian|date=20 June 2002|quote=Some are even opening British-style curry restaurants with names like Taste of Bengal and the Last Days of the Raj.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Northern India===
{{more citations needed|date=October 2018}}
{{Main|Indian cuisine}}
[[File:Rajma Chawal, from India.jpg|thumb|upright|''[[Rajma]]-[[Chawal]]'', curried red kidney beans with steamed rice, from India]]
Curries are the most well-known part of Indian cuisine. Most Indian dishes are usually curry based, prepared by adding different types of vegetables, lentils or meats in the curry. The content of the curry and style of preparation varies per the region. Most curries are water based, with occasional use of dairy and coconut milk. Curry dishes are usually thick and spicy and are eaten along with steamed rice and variety of Indian breads.

====Gujarat====
{{Main|Gujarati cuisine}}
Although wet curries play a smaller role in Gujarat than elsewhere, there are a number of vegetarian examples with gravies based on buttermilk or coconut milk. The main ingredient may variously be brinjal ([[eggplant]]/aubergine), potatoes, fresh corn kernels, [[okra]], tomatoes, etc. In addition, there are several common [[kofta]] dishes which substitute vegetables for meat.&lt;ref&gt;Reejhsinghani, Aroona. ''Vegetarian Wonders from Gujarat''. (Mumbai: Jaico Publishing House, c.2002), p.123-128.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Undhiyu]], a Gujarati specialty, is a spicy 'wet' mixed-vegetable 'casserole' cooked in an earthenware pot, often eaten during the winter months.
&lt;!-- Curry varies in flavour and heat. Mild curry could be made of [[cardamom]], [[coriander]], [[cumin]], turmeric, [[star anise]], and salt.--&gt;

====Maharashtra====
{{more citations needed|date=October 2018}}
{{Main|Maharashtrian cuisine}}
[[File:Solkadi and Bangda Fry.jpg|thumb|A [[Maharashtra|Maharastrian]] ''[[thali]]'' with [[solkadhi]], a type of curry usually eaten with rice]]

The curries of [[Maharashtra]] vary from mildly spicy to very spicy and include vegetarian, mutton, chicken and fish. Coastal Maharashtrian – Konkani – curries use coconut extensively along with spices. In western Maharashtra, curries are very spicy, often with [[peanut]] powder. [[Vidarbha|Vidharba's cuisine]] is usually spicier than that of the coastal and southern regions. The ingredients commonly used are besan ([[gram flour]]), or [[chickpea]] flour, and groundnut powder. As a result of the [[Mughal Empire|Mughal]] rule in the region, the cuisine of [[Aurangabad, Maharashtra|Aurangabad]] has been highly influenced by the North Indian method of cooking. [[Khandesh]]i food is very spicy and the most famous dish is shev bhaji. Others include Eggplant [[Baingan bharta|bharta]] (wangyache bhareet), ([[Vigna mungo|urid dal]]), stuffed eggplant (bharleli wangi), bhaakari with [[thecha]] etc. The majority of Maharashtrian people are farmers living in the rural areas and therefore their traditional food is very simple.

====Punjab====
{{more citations needed|date=October 2018}}
{{Main|Punjabi cuisine}}
Most Punjabi dishes are prepared using ''[[Tempering (Spices)|tadka]]'', which is made with the frying of a &quot;[[masala (spice)|masala]]&quot;, which is a mix of ginger, garlic, onions and tomatoes with some dried spices. This is followed by the addition of other ingredients, water, and occasionally milk. Normally spicy, spice levels vary greatly depending on the household itself. [[Ghee]] and [[mustard oil]] are the most commonly used cooking fats. Many popular Punjabi dishes such as [[butter chicken]] and [[rajma]] are curry-based. These dishes are usually served with steamed rice and [[chapati]]s.

====Rajasthan====
{{more citations needed|date=October 2018}}
{{Main|Rajasthani cuisine}}

[[Rajasthan]]i cuisine was influenced both by the war-like lifestyles of its inhabitants and the availability of ingredients in this arid region.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dubey&quot;&gt;Krishna Gopal Dubey, The Indian Cuisine, PHI Learning Pvt. Ltd., pp.193&lt;/ref&gt; Food that could last for several days and could be eaten without heating was preferred. Scarcity of water and fresh green vegetables have each had their effect on the cooking. Hence the curries in Rajasthan are usually made using dry spices and herbs and other dry items like gram flour. ''[[Kadhi]]'' is a popular gram flour curry, usually served with steamed rice and bread. To decrease the use of water in this desert state they use a lot of milk and milk-products to cook curries. [[Laal maans]] is a popular meat curry from Rajasthan.

===Southern India===
{{Main|South Indian cuisine}}

====Andhra Pradesh and Telangana====
{{Main|Telugu cuisine}}

The food in general from Andhra Pradesh and Telangana, both with Telugu-speaking natives, is considered the hottest in India. The state, being the leading producer of red chilli and green chilli, influences the liberal use of spices, making their curries, chutneys, savories and pickles the hottest and spiciest in taste.

====Goa====

Curries known as [[vindaloo]] have become well known in Great Britain, America, and elsewhere, where the name is usually used simply to indicate a fiery dish of lamb or chicken frequently including potatoes. Such dishes are far from the Goan originals.

The name &quot;vindaloo&quot; derives from the Portuguese ''vinha d'alhos'' or wine (''vinho'') and garlic (''alho''), the two definitive flavour ingredients. The dish was originally made with pork, not taboo to the Christian Portuguese. The inclusion of potatoes was a later Indian addition, thought to be the result of confusion with the Hindi word for potato, ''aloo''. Throughout the years &quot;vindaloo&quot; has been altered to appeal to many people by adding spices and different wines.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.saveur.com/article/cooking/the-history-of-vindaloo|title=Fired Up: The History of Vindaloo|work=SAVEUR|access-date=27 November 2017|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Karnataka====
{{Main|Cuisine of Karnataka}}

The curries of Karnataka are typically vegetarian or with meat and fish around mostly coastal areas. They use a wide variety of vegetables, spices, coconut and [[jaggery]]. There are dry and sauce-based curries. Some typical sauce-based dishes include [[saaru]], gojju, thovve, huli, majjige huli (which is similar to the ''kadi'' made in the north), sagu or kootu, which is eaten mixed with hot rice.

====Kerala====
{{Main|Cuisine of Kerala}}

[[Malayali]] curries of [[Kerala]] typically contain shredded [[coconut]] paste or [[coconut milk]], curry leaves, and various spices. Mustard seeds are used in almost every dish, along with onions, curry leaves, and sliced red chilies fried in hot oil. Most of the non-vegetarian dishes are heavily spiced. Kerala is known for its traditional [[sadya]], a vegetarian meal served with boiled rice and a host of side dishes such as [[parippu]] (green gram), [[papadum]], ghee, [[Sambar (dish)|sambar]], [[rasam]], [[aviyal]], [[kaalan]], [[kichadi]], [[pachadi]], [[injipuli]], [[Koottukari]], [[Indian pickle|pickles]] (mango, lime), [[thoran]], one to four types of [[payasam]], [[Boli (food)|boli]], [[Olan (dish)|olan]], pulissery, moru ([[buttermilk]]), upperi, and [[banana]] chips. The sadya is customarily served on a banana leaf.

====Tamil Nadu====
{{Main|Tamil cuisine}}

[[Tamil cuisine]]'s distinctive flavour and aroma is achieved by a blend and combination of [[spice]]s including curry leaves, [[tamarind]], [[coriander]], [[ginger]], [[garlic]], chili, [[black pepper|pepper]], [[poppy seed]]s, [[mustard seed]]s, [[cinnamon]], [[clove]]s, [[cardamom]], cumin, [[fennel]] or [[anise]] seeds, [[fenugreek seed]]s, [[nutmeg]], [[coconut]], turmeric root or powder, and [[rosewater]]. [[Lentil]]s, [[vegetable]]s and [[dairy product]]s are essential accompaniments and are often served with rice. Traditionally vegetarian foods dominate the menu with a range of non-vegetarian dishes including [[freshwater]] [[Fish (food)|fish]] and [[seafood]] cooked with spices and seasoning.

===Kashmir===
{{Main|Kashmiri cuisine}}
In the West, the best-known [[Kashmir]]i curry is ''[[rogan josh]]'', a wet curry of lamb with a brilliant red gravy whose colour is derived from a combination of Kashmiri chillies and an extract derived from the red flowers of the [[Celosia|cockscomb plant]] (''mawal'').&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Rogan Josh,&quot; in Khan Mohammed Sharief Waza, Khan Mohammed Shafi Waza, and Khan Mohammed Rafiq Waza. ''Wazwaan: Traditional Kashmiri Cuisine.'' (New Delhi: Roli &amp; Janssen BV, c.2007), p.34.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Goshtaba'' (large lamb meatballs cooked in yoghurt gravy) is another curry dish from the [[Wazwan]] tradition occasionally found in Western restaurants.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Ghushtaba&quot; in Khan Mohammed Sharief Waza, Khan Mohammed Shafi Waza, and Khan Mohammed Rafiq Waza. ''Wazwaan: Traditional Kashmiri Cuisine.'' (New Delhi: Roli &amp; Janssen BV, c.2007), p.37.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--''[[Kadhi]]'' is a specific dish from Punjab, made by stirring [[dahi (curd)|dahi]] (yogurt) into a [[roux]] of ghee and [[Gram flour|besan]]. The spices added vary, but usually include turmeric, [[black mustard]] seed, and curry leaves. It is often eaten with rice. [[North India]], where dishes are classified as ''sukhi'' (dry) and ''tari'' (with liquid), the word ''curry'' is often confounded with the similar-sounding [[Hindi]] word ''tari'' (from the [[Persian language|Persian]]-derived ''tar'' meaning ''wet'') and has no implications for the presence or absence of spice, or whether the dish is Indian or not (e.g. any stew, spicy or not, would be considered a curry dish, simply because it is wet).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Fk8FQa2ZSFQC |title=India| author=Sarina Singh |publisher=Lonely Planet |accessdate=17 May 2010|quote=generally cooked sukhi (dry) or tari (in a sauce) | isbn=978-1-74059-694-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=E2saAQAAIAAJ|title=Hanklyn-janklin: a stranger's rumble-tumble guide to some words, customs, and quiddities, Indian and Indo-British| author=Nigel B. Hankin |publisher=Banyan Books |accessdate=17 May 2010|quote=In the north, a hot savoury gravy-like sauce, ideally containing ghee, added to vegetables or into which a chapati may be dipped, will be termed tari}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=HkPwaXWipVcC|title=Colloquial Urdu: the complete course for beginners|author=Tej K. Bhatia, Ashok Koul|publisher=Routledge|accessdate=17 May 2010|quote=&quot;Do you like spicy food or curry? In America, curry is the name of a dish but this is not the case in India. Curry is neither always spicy, nor is curry powder usually sold. Curry is usually liquid (tari vali)&quot; tar:wet, tari:liquid, tari vali sabzi | isbn=978-0-415-13540-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Urdu]], curry is usually referred to as ''saalan'' (سالن). The equivalent word for a spiced dish in Hindi is ''masaledar'' (i.e. with ''[[spice mix|masala]]'').&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=HkPwaXWipVcC|title=Colloquial Urdu: the complete course for beginners|author=Tej K. Bhatia, Ashok Koul|publisher=Routledge|accessdate=17 May 2010|quote=&quot;Hamare yahan (America) curry ka matlab koi masaledar Hindustani khana hai. In America, curry is any spicy (masaledar) Indian dish&quot; | isbn=978-0-415-13540-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;

===Maldives===
{{Main|Maldivian cuisine}}

The most important curry in the cuisine of the Maldives is cooked with diced fresh [[tuna]] and is known as ''[[mas riha]]''. ''Kukulhu riha'', [[chicken curry]], is cooked with a different mixture of spices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.academia.edu/4398927/Eating_on_the_Islands_-_As_times_have_changed_so_has_the_Maldives_unique_cuisine_and_culture|title=Eating on the Islands - As times have changed, so has the Maldives' unique cuisine and culture|author=Xavier Romero-Frias|work=academia.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Traditional vegetable curries in the Maldives include those that use ''bashi'' ([[eggplant|eggplant/aubergine]]), ''tora'' (''[[Luffa aegyptiaca]]''), ''barabō'' ([[pumpkin]]), ''chichanda'' (''[[Trichosanthes cucumerina]]'') and ''muranga'' (''[[Moringa oleifera]]''), as well as green unripe [[banana]]s and certain leaves as their main ingredients. Pieces of [[Maldive fish]] are normally added to give the vegetable curry a certain flavour.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;[[Xavier Romero-Frias]], ''The Maldive Islanders, A Study of the Popular Culture of an Ancient Ocean Kingdom'', Barcelona 1999, {{ISBN|84-7254-801-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Nepal===
{{Main|Nepalese cuisine}}

The curries of Nepalese cuisine have been influenced by its neighbours, mainly [[Indian cuisine|India]] and [[Tibetan cuisine|Tibet]]. Well known Indian spices are used less. Goat is a popular meat in the Himalayan region of Nepal.

[[Daal bhaat]] (rice and [[lentil soup]]) is a staple dish of Nepal. [[Newa cuisine]] is a type of cuisine developed over centuries by the [[Newar]]s of Nepal.

===Pakistan===
{{Main|Pakistani cuisine}}

Pakistani curries, especially in the provinces of Punjab and Sindh, are basically similar to their counterparts in northern India. Mutton and beef are common ingredients. A typical Pakistani lunch or dinner often consists of some form of bread (such as naan or roti) or rice with a meat or vegetable-based curry. Barbecue style or roasted meats are also very popular in the form of kebabs.

It is worth noting that the term ''curry'' is virtually never used inside the country; instead, regional words such as ''salan'' or ''shorba'' are used to denote what is known outside the country as a &quot;curry&quot;.

Several different types of curries exist, depending on the cooking style, such as bhuna, bharta, roghan josh, qorma, qeema, and shorba. A favourite Pakistani curry is [[karahi]], which is either mutton or chicken cooked in a cooking utensil called karahi, which is similar in shape to a wok. Lahori karahi incorporates garlic, ginger, fresh chillies, tomatoes and select spices. Peshawari karahi is another very popular version made with just meat, salt, tomatoes, and coriander.

====Khyber Pakhtunkhwa====
{{Main|Afghan cuisine|Pashtun cuisine}}

The cuisine from the [[Khyber Pakhtunkhwa]] province of Pakistan is somewhat similar to the cuisine of neighbouring Afghanistan. Extreme winters in some areas made the supply of fresh vegetables impossible, so a lot of dried fruits and vegetables are incorporated in the cuisine. The province still produces a large amount of nuts which are used abundantly in traditional cooking, along with cereals like wheat, maize, barley, and rice. Accompanying these staples are dairy products (yoghurt, whey), various nuts, native vegetables, and fresh and dried fruits. Peshawari karahi from the provincial capital of [[Peshawar]] is a popular curry all over the country.

====Punjab====
{{Main|Punjabi cuisine}}
Cuisine in Pakistani Punjab differs from Indian Punjab on account of contents and religious diet rules. A typical Punjabi meal consists of some form of bread or rice with a ''salan'' (curry). Most preparations start with the frying of a [[spice mix|masala]] which is a concoction of ginger, garlic, onions, tomatoes, and dried spices.  Various other ingredients are then added.  Spice level varies greatly depending on the sub-region as well as the household itself. A popular cooking fat is desi ghee with some dishes enriched with liberal amounts of [[butter]] and [[cream]]. There are certain dishes that are exclusive to Punjab, such as maash di dal and saron da saag (sarson ka saag). In Punjab and Kashmir, the only dish known as kardhi (curry) is a dish made of dahi (yogurt) and flour dumplings.

====Sindh====
{{Main|Sindhi cuisine}}

In Pakistan, the provinces of [[Sindh]] and [[Balochistan]] border the [[Arabian Sea]]. Due to this, the Sindhi cuisine often has abundant use of fish in curries. Among Pakistani food, the Sindhi curries generally tend to be the hottest. The daily food in most Sindhi households consists of [[wheat]]-based flatbread ([[phulka]]) and rice accompanied by two dishes, one [[gravy]] and one dry.

===Sri Lanka===
{{Main|Sri Lankan cuisine}}

In Sri Lankan cuisine, [[rice]], which is usually consumed daily, can be found at any special occasion, while spicy curries are favourite dishes for lunch and dinner. &quot;[[Rice and curry]]&quot; refers to a range of Sri Lankan dishes.

==Southeast Asia==
{{See also|Cambodian cuisine|Lao cuisine|Singaporean cuisine}}

===Burma===
{{See also|Burmese cuisine}}
Burmese cuisine is based on a very different understanding of curries. The principal ingredients of almost all Burmese curries are fresh onion (which provides the gravy and main body of the curry), Indian spices and red chilies. Usually, meat and fish are the main ingredients for popular curries.

Burmese curries can be generalised into two types – the hot spicy dishes which exhibit north Indian or Pakistani influence, and the milder &quot;sweet&quot; curries. Burmese curries almost overwhelmingly lack coconut milk, setting them apart from most southeast Asian curries.

Regular ingredients include fresh onion, garlic and [[Chili pepper paste|chili paste]]. Common spices include [[garam masala]], dried chili powder, cumin powder, turmeric and [[Cuisine of Burma#Ngapi|ngapi]], a fermented paste made from either fish or prawns. Burmese curries are quite oily, as the extra oil helps the food to last longer. A spaghetti equivalent called [[Nan gyi thohk]] exists, in which wheat or rice noodles are eaten with thick chicken curry.

===Indonesia===
{{See also|Indonesian cuisine}}
[[File:Roti Cane Kari Kambing.jpg|thumb|''Kari kambing'' (mutton curry) served with ''[[roti canai]]'' in [[Sumatra]].]]
In Indonesia curry is called ''kari'' or ''kare''. The most common type of ''kari'' consumed in Indonesia is ''kari ayam'' (chicken curry) and ''kari kambing'' (goat meat curry). In [[Aceh]] and [[North Sumatra]] [[Roti Canai|roti cane]] is often eaten with ''kari kambing''. Other dishes such as [[gulai]] and [[Opor ayam|opor]] are dishes based on curry. They are often highly localised and reflect the meat and vegetables available. They can therefore employ a variety of meats (chicken, beef, water buffalo and goat as in the flavoursome ''gulai kambing''), seafood (such as prawn, crab, mussel, clam, and squid), fish (tuna, mackerel, carp, pangasius, catfish), or vegetables (young [[jackfruit]], common beans, [[cassava]] leaf) dishes in a spiced sauce. They use local ingredients such as chili peppers, [[kaffir lime]] leaves, [[lemongrass]], [[galangal]], [[Bay leaf#Taxonomy|Indonesian bay leaves]] (salam leaf), [[candlenut]]s, turmeric, turmeric leaves, [[Garcinia atroviridis|asam gelugur]] and [[Garcinia#Selected species|asam kandis]] (sour [[Garcinia|mangosteens]] similar to [[tamarind]]), [[terasi|shrimp paste]] (terasi), cumin, coriander seed and [[coconut milk]]. In Aceh, curries use ''daun salam koja'' or ''daun kari'' (''[[Murraya koenigii]]'') translated as &quot;curry leaves&quot;.

One popular dish, [[rendang]] from [[Minangkabau cuisine|West Sumatran cuisine]], is often described as caramelised beef dry curry. In Indonesia, rendang is usually not considered to be curry since it is richer and contains less liquid than is normal for Indonesian curries. Authentic rendang uses water buffalo meat slow-cooked in thick coconut milk for a number of hours to tenderise, caramelise, and flavour the meat. [[Opor Ayam]] is another variation of curry, which tastes very similar to gulai. Opor is usually whitish in colour and uses neither cinnamon nor turmeric, while gulai may contain either or both. Opor is also often part of a family meal around [[Eid ul-Fitr|Lebaran]], while gulai can be commonly found in [[Padang food|Padang restaurants]].

===Malaysia===
{{See also|Malaysian cuisine}}
Being at the crossroads of ancient trade routes has left a mark on Malaysian cuisine. While curry may have initially found its way to Malaysian shores via the Indian population, it has since become a staple among the Malays and Chinese. Malaysian curries differ from state to state, even within similar ethnic groupings, as they are influenced by many factors, be they cultural, religious, agricultural or economical.

Malaysian curries typically use turmeric-rich curry powders, coconut milk, shallots, ginger, [[belacan]] (shrimp paste), chili peppers, and garlic. [[Tamarind]] is also often used. [[Rendang]] is another form of curry consumed in Malaysia, Singapore, Indonesia and the Philippines; it is drier and contains mostly meat and more coconut milk than a conventional Malaysian curry. Rendang was mentioned in Malay literature [[Hikayat Amir Hamzah]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Hikayat Amir Hamzah 1 (Menentang Jin di Bukit Qaf)|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rahQDaE0bD8C&amp;pg=PA10|year=2008|publisher=PTS Fortuna|isbn=978-983-192-116-6|page=10}}&lt;/ref&gt; (1550s) and is popular among Indonesians, Singaporeans and Malaysians. All sorts of things are curried in Malaysia, including mutton, chicken, [[tofu]], shrimp, cuttlefish, fish, [[eggplant]]s, eggs, and vegetables.

===Philippines===
{{See also|Ginataan|Philippine cuisine}}
[[File:Philippine Chicken curry.jpg|thumb|[[Filipino chicken curry]], a variant of the native ''[[ginataang manok]]'' with [[curry powder]]]]
In the Philippines, two kinds of curry traditions are seen corresponding with the cultural divide between the Hispanicised north and Indianised/Islamised south. In the northern areas, a linear range of new curry recipes could be seen. The most common is a variant of the native ''[[ginataang manok]]'' (chicken is cooked in coconut milk) dish with the addition of [[curry powder]], known as the &quot;[[Filipino chicken curry]]&quot;. This is the usual curry dish that northern Filipinos are familiar with. Similarly, other northern Filipino dishes that can be considered &quot;curries&quot; are usually ''[[ginataan]]'' (cooked with coconut milk) variants of other native meat or seafood dishes such as ''[[adobo]]'', ''[[kaldereta]]'', and ''[[mechado]]'', that simply add curry powder or non-native Indian spices.&lt;ref name=&quot;pp&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Pinoy Chicken Curry Recipe |url=https://panlasangpinoy.com/chicken-curry-pinoy-style/ |website=Panlasang Pinoy |accessdate=20 April 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In southern areas of the [[Visayas]], Mindanao, the Sulu Archipelago and southern Palawan, various older curry recipes are seen, and owe their origins to the limited influence of the Spanish in these regions that preserved older culinary traditions; as well as closer historical ties to Malay states like the [[Sultanate of Brunei]]. These Mindanaoan curries include ''kulma'', synonymous with the Indian ''[[korma]]''; ''[[tiyula itum]]'' which is a beef curry blackened with burned coconut-meat powder; and ''[[rendang]]'', also eaten in Indonesia and Malaysia. Meats used in these curries include beef, goat, mutton, lamb, seafood and chicken. Pork is not used, in accordance with Islamic dietary laws.

===Thailand===
{{Main|Thai curry}}
[[File:Phanaeng mu.jpg|thumb|Thai ''phanaeng'' with pork]]
In Thai cuisine, curries are called ''kaeng'', and usually consist of meat, fish or vegetables in a sauce based on a paste made from chilies, onions or shallots, garlic, and [[shrimp paste]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thaicooking.nationmultimedia.com/?p=1382 |title=Thai cooking, food thai, Thai menu, pad thai recipe |publisher=Thaicooking.nationmultimedia.com |accessdate=22 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additional spices and herbs define the type of curry. Local ingredients, such as chili peppers, [[kaffir lime]] leaves, [[lemongrass]], [[galangal]] are used and, in central and southern Thai cuisine, coconut milk. Northern and northeastern Thai curries generally do not contain coconut milk. Due to the use of sugar and coconut milk, Thai curries tend to be sweeter than Indian curries. In the West, some of the Thai curries are described by colour; [[red curry|red curries]] use red chilies while [[green curry|green curries]] use green chilies. [[Yellow curry]]—called ''kaeng kari'' (by various spellings) in [[Thai language|Thai]], of which a literal translation could be &quot;curry soup&quot;—is more similar to Indian curries, with the use of turmeric, cumin, and other dried spices. A few stir-fried Thai dishes also use an Indian style curry powder (Thai: ''phong kari'').

Thai curries:
* [[Yellow curry]]
* [[Massaman curry]]
* [[Green curry]]
* [[Red curry]]
* [[Phanaeng curry]]
* [[Khao soi]]
* [[Kaeng hang le]]
* [[Kaeng som]]

===Vietnam===
{{See also|Vietnamese cuisine}}

In Vietnam where curry is called ''cà ri'', curry features include coconut milk, potato, sweet potato, [[taro]] roots, chicken garnished with [[coriander]], and green onion. It is more soup-like than Indian curry. The curry is usually eaten with a [[baguette]], rice [[vermicelli]] or steamed rice. Some dishes use a curry-based stew, such as [[snail]] dishes, [[phá lấu]], stewed frogs or eels.

==East Asia==

===China===
{{more citations needed section|date=January 2017}}
{{See also|Chinese cuisine}}
Although not an integral part of Chinese cuisine, curry powder is added to some dishes in southern part of China. The curry powder sold in Chinese grocery stores is similar to Madras curry powder but with addition of [[Illicium verum|star anise]] and cinnamon.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sen2009&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Colleen Taylor Sen|title=Curry: A Global History|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=94tRvbuCqWcC&amp;pg=PA1|date=15 November 2009|publisher=Reaktion Books|isbn=978-1-86189-704-6|page=105}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Chinese curries (咖哩, gā lǐ) typically consist of chicken, beef, fish, lamb, or other meats, green peppers, onions, large chunks of potatoes, and a variety of other ingredients and spices in a mildly spicy yellow curry sauce, and topped over [[steamed rice]]. White pepper, soy sauce, hot sauce or hot chili oil may be applied to the sauce to enhance the flavour of the curry.

The most common Chinese variety of curry sauce is usually sold in powder form.{{Citation needed|date=June 2012}} The ethnic Cantonese being dominant in [[Kuala Lumpur]], this yellow [[Malaysian Chinese|Chinese-Malaysian]] variety was naturally introduced to China by the Cantonese. It features typically in Hong Kong cuisine, where curry is often cooked with [[brisket]] or [[fish balls]]. Malay satay seems to have been introduced to China with wider success by the ethnic [[Teochew people|Teochew]], who make up the second largest group of Chinese of [[Chinese Singaporean|Singapore]] and are the dominant group in [[Thai Chinese|Thailand]].

===Hong Kong===
{{See also|Hong Kong-style Western cuisine}}
In [[Hong Kong]], curry [[fish balls]] are a street snack, and curried [[brisket]] is a typical main course in [[cha chaan teng]] and fast food restaurants.

===Japan===
{{Main|Japanese curry}}
[[File:Japanese food by Naoki Nakashima 103.jpg|thumb|Japanese style ''Karē-Raisu'' (Curry rice)]]
[[File:Curry-bun,curry-pan,katori-city,japan.JPG|thumb|''Karē-Pan'' (Curry bread)]]

{{Nihongo|Japanese curry|カレー|karē}} is usually eaten as ''karē raisu'' — curry, rice, and often pickled vegetables, served on the same plate and eaten with a spoon, a common lunchtime canteen dish. It is less spicy and seasoned than Indian and Southeast Asian curries, being more of a thick stew than a curry.

British people brought curry from the [[British Raj|Indian colony]] back to Britain&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sb-worldwide.com/curry/history.html|title=History of Japanese curry|author=S&amp;B Company|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://archive.today/20130411190436/http://www.sb-worldwide.com/curry/history.html|archivedate=11 April 2013|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; and introduced it to Japan during the [[Meiji period]] (1868 to 1912), after Japan ended its policy of national self-isolation (''[[sakoku]]''), and curry in Japan was categorised as a [[Yōshoku|Western dish]]. Its spread across the country is commonly attributed to its use in the [[Imperial Japanese Army|Japanese Army]] and [[Imperial Japanese Navy|Navy]] which adopted it extensively as convenient field and naval canteen cooking, allowing even conscripts from the remotest countryside to experience the dish. The [[Japan Maritime Self-Defense Force]] traditionally have curry every Friday for lunch and many ships have their own unique recipes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.japantimes.co.jp/life/2011/08/26/food/curry-its-more-japanese-than-you-think/|title=Curry – it’s more 'Japanese' than you think|last=Itoh|first=Makiko|date=26 August 2011|work=The Japan Times Online|access-date=8 January 2018|language=en-US|issn=0447-5763}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The standard Japanese curry contains [[onion]]s, [[carrot]]s, [[potato]]es, and sometimes [[celery]], and a meat that is cooked in a large pot. Sometimes grated [[apple]]s or [[honey]] are added for additional sweetness and other vegetables are sometimes used instead. For the meat, [[pork]], [[beef]], and [[Chicken (food)|chicken]] are the most popular, in order of decreasing popularity. In northern and eastern Japan including [[Tokyo]], pork is the most popular meat for curry. Beef is more common in western Japan, including [[Osaka]], and in [[Okinawa Prefecture|Okinawa]], chicken is favoured.&lt;ref&gt;[http://curryken.fc2web.com/minzoku/minzoku.htm The Curry Rice Research] (in Japanese)&lt;/ref&gt; Curry seasoning is commonly sold in the form of a condensed brick, similar to a [[bouillon cube]], which dissolves in the mixture of meat and vegetables.

Sometimes the curry-rice is topped with breaded pork cutlet ([[tonkatsu]]); this is called &quot;[[katsukarē]]&quot;. [[Korokke]] (potato croquettes) are also a common topping.

Apart from with rice, curry is also served over [[noodle]]s, possibly even on top of broth in addition, in dishes such as curry [[udon]] and curry [[ramen]]. It is also used as the filling in a fried [[curry bread]] pastry.

===Korea===
Though curry was introduced to Korea in the 1940s, the Indian dish was only popularized decades later, when [[Ottogi]] entered the Korean food industry by launching its powder-type curry product in 1969.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.koreaherald.com/view.php?ud=20150625001118|title=[Best Brand] Ottogi becomes Korea’s representative curry product|date=25 June 2015|newspaper=[[The Korea Herald]]|access-date=10 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sohn&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.korea.net/NewsFocus/Business/view?articleId=122393|title=Ottogi Curry brings Indian cuisine to the table|last=Sohn|first=JiAe|date=24 October 2014|access-date=10 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Korean curry, usually served with rice, is characterized by the golden yellow colour from turmeric.

Curry [[tteokbokki]], along with curry rice, is one of the most popular curry dishes in Korea. It is made of [[tteok]] (rice cakes), [[eomuk]] (fish cakes), eggs, vegetables, and curry. Curry can be added to various Korean dishes such as [[bokkeumbap]] (fried rice), [[sundubujjigae]] (silken tofu stew), fried chicken, vegetable stir-fries, and salads. Curry is also used in [[Fusion cuisine|Korean-style western food]] such as pasta and steak, as well as [[Fusion cuisine|Korean-style Japanese food]] such as cream [[udon]].

==United Kingdom==
{{for|the cuisine of Indian immigrants to English-speaking countries see|Anglo-Indian cuisine}}
[[File:Chicken Tikka Masala-01.jpg|thumb|right|[[Chicken tikka masala]]]]
Curry is very popular in the United Kingdom, with a curry house in nearly every town.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Jahangir |first=Rumeana |title=How Britain got the hots for curry |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/8370054.stm |work=BBC News |date=26 November 2009 |accessdate=14 October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=National Curry Week: Why Britain loves curry |url=http://www.fsc.uk.com/national-curry-week-britain-loves-curry/ |work=Fleet Street Communications}}&lt;/ref&gt; Such is the popularity of curry in the United Kingdom, it has frequently been called its &quot;adopted national dish&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Spinks |first=Rosie |title=Curry on cooking: how long will the UK's adopted national dish survive? |url=https://www.theguardian.com/sustainable-business/2015/jul/08/uk-indian-restaurants-struggling-to-curry-on-lack-of-chefs |work=The Guardian |date=8 July 2005 |accessdate=14 October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was estimated that in 2016 there were 12,000 curry houses, employing 100,000 people and with annual combined sales of approximately £4.2 billion.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Moore |first=Malcolm |title=The great British curry crisis |url=https://www.ft.com/content/2165379e-b4b2-11e5-8358-9a82b43f6b2f |work=The Financial Times |date=8 January 2016 |accessdate=14 October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In general the food offered is Indian food cooked to British taste; however, there is increasing demand for authentic Indian food. As of 2015 curry houses accounted for a fifth of the restaurant business in the U.K. but, being historically a low wage sector, they were plagued by a shortage of labour. Established Indian immigrants from South Asia were moving on to other occupations; there were difficulties in training Europeans to cook curry; and immigration restrictions, which require payment of a substantial wage to skilled immigrants, had crimped the supply of new cooks.&lt;ref name=NYT11415&gt;{{cite news|author1=Kimiko de Freytas-Tamura|title=Britons Perturbed by a Troubling Shortage of Curry Chefs|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2015/11/05/world/europe/britain-curry-house-shortage-chefs.html|accessdate=4 November 2015|work=The New York Times|date=4 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Historical development===
[[File:Hannah Glasse To make a Currey the Indian Way 1758 edition.jpg|thumb|The recipe for &quot;currey&quot; from the 1747 book by Hannah Glasse (1758 edition, mentioning ginger and turmeric)]]
Historically, the word &quot;curry&quot; was first used in [[British cuisine]] to denote dishes of meat (often leftover lamb) in a Western-style sauce flavoured with [[curry powder]].

The first curry recipe in Britain appeared in ''[[Art of Cookery|The Art of Cookery made Plain and Easy]]'' by [[Hannah Glasse]] in 1747.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| title= The art of cookery, made plain and easy | author=Hannah Glasse | oclc=4942063 | year = 1747}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first edition of her book used only black pepper and coriander seeds for seasoning of &quot;currey&quot;. By the fourth edition of the book, other ingredients such as turmeric and ginger were called for. The use of hot spices was not mentioned, which reflected the limited use of chili in India — [[chili pepper|chili plants]] had only been introduced into India around the late 16th century and at that time were only popular in southern India.

Many curry recipes are contained in 19th century cookbooks such as those of [[Charles Elmé Francatelli]] and [[Mrs Beeton]]. In ''[[Mrs Beeton's Book of Household Management]]'', a recipe for curry powder is given that contains coriander, turmeric, cinnamon, cayenne, mustard, ginger, allspice and fenugreek; although she notes that it is more economical to purchase the powder at &quot;any respectable shop&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| title= Mrs. Beeton's book of household management | author=Isabella Mary Beeton | page=215 | isbn=0-304-35726-X | year = 1861}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--However, the use of fresh spices such as ginger and [[garlic]], and preparation of an initial masala from freshly ground dried spices are sometimes used.--&gt;
According to legend, one 19th century attempt at curry resulted in the invention of [[Worcestershire sauce]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| title= Curry: A tale of cooks and conquerors | author=Lizzie Collingham | isbn=0-09-943786-4 | year = 2006 | publisher = Vintage | chapter = Curry Powder| pages=149–150 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Throughout the 19th and early 20th centuries, curry grew increasingly popular in Britain owing to the large number of British civil servants and military personnel associated with the [[British Raj]]. Following World War II, curry became even more popular in Britain owing to the large number of immigrants from South Asia.

Curry has become an integral part of British cuisine, so much so that, since the late 1990s, [[chicken tikka masala]] has been referred to as &quot;a true British national dish&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/race/story/0,,657407,00.html|title=Robin Cook's chicken tikka masala speech|accessdate=12 December 2006 | work=The Guardian | location=London | date=19 April 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other British curry derivatives include &quot;[[Coronation chicken]]&quot;, a cold dish, often used as a sandwich filling, invented to commemorate the coronation of [[Elizabeth II of the United Kingdom|Queen Elizabeth II]] in 1953 – and '''curry sauce''' (or '''curry gravy'''), usually served warm with traditional British fast food dishes such as [[French fried potatoes|chips]]. Curry sauce occasionally includes [[Sultana (grape)|sultana]]s or other [[dried fruits]].

====Curry house====
In 1810, the entrepreneur [[Sake Dean Mahomed]], from the [[Bengal Presidency]], opened the first Indian curry house in England: the [[Hindoostanee Coffee House]] in London.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Curry house founder is honoured|date=29 September 2005|work=BBC News|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/london/4290124.stm|accessdate=9 October 2008 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; (Curry was served prior to this in some London [[Coffee House|coffee houses]].)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Jahangir |first=Rumeana |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/8370054.stm |title=How Britain got the hots for curry |work=BBC News |date=26 November 2009 |accessdate=22 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first modern &quot;upscale&quot; Indian restaurant in Britain is thought to have been The Shafi in 1915,&lt;ref&gt;Grove, Peter and Colleen.  ''The Flavours of History''. (London?: Godiva Books, 2011).&lt;/ref&gt; followed by [[Veeraswamy]] in London's Regent Street, founded in 1926;&lt;ref&gt;Basu, Shrabani. ''Curry: The Story of the Nation's Favourite Dish.'' (Stroud, Gloucestershire: Sutton Publishing, c.2003), p.127.&lt;/ref&gt; the latter is still standing and is the oldest surviving Indian restaurant in Britain.&lt;ref name=&quot;hindu1&quot;&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.hindu.com/mp/2006/04/26/stories/2006042600140500.htm |title=Metro Plus Chennai |last=Singh |first=Rashmi Uday |date=26 April 2006 |work=[[The Hindu]] |accessdate=13 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;times1&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/life_and_style/food_and_drink/eating_out/a_a_gill/article705029.ece |title=Veeraswamy |last=Gill |first=AA  |work=[[The Times]] |accessdate=13 June 2009| location=London| date=23 April 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bengalis in the UK settled in big cities with industrial employment. In London, they settled in the East End, which for centuries has been the first port of call for many immigrants working in the docks and shipping from east Bengal. Their regular stopover paved the way for food and curry outlets to be opened up catering for an all-male workforce as family migration and settlement took place some decades later. [[Brick Lane]] in the East [[London Borough of Tower Hamlets]] is famous for its many curry houses.

Until the early 1970s, more than three-quarters of Indian restaurants in Britain were identified as being owned and run by people of Bengali origin. Most were run by migrants from East Pakistan, which became Bangladesh in 1971. Bangladeshi restaurateurs overwhelmingly come from the northeastern division of [[Sylhet Division|Sylhet]]. Until 1998, as many as 85% of curry restaurants in the UK were [[British Bangladeshi]] restaurants,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.curryhouse.co.uk/scene/ethnshow.htm|title=UK Curry Scene|accessdate=12 December 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; but in 2003 this figure declined to just over 65%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/worldservice/specials/177_food/page5.shtml|title=Indian Curry in London|accessdate=12 December 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; The dominance of Bangladeshi restaurants is generally declining in some parts of London and the further north one travels. In Glasgow, there are more restaurants of Punjabi origin than any other.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.menumagazine.co.uk/book/restauranthistory.html|title=The history of the &quot;ethnic&quot; restaurant in Britain|accessdate=12 December 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early 2010s the popularity of the curry house saw a decline. This has been attributed to the sale of this style of food in generic restaurants, increased home cooking of this style of food with easy supermarket availability of ingredients, and [[Modern immigration to the United Kingdom|immigration restrictions brought in from 2008]] making the availability of low-wage chefs and other staff difficult.&lt;ref name=observer-20120108&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2012/jan/08/britains-curry-crisis-chefs-immigration |title=The curry crisis |author=Homa Khaleeli |newspaper=The Observer |date=8 January 2012 |accessdate=14 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=guardian-20170112&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2017/jan/12/who-killed-the-british-curry-house |title=Who killed the great British curry house? |newspaper=The Guardian |date=12 January 2017 |accessdate=14 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Regardless of the ethnic origin of a restaurant's ownership, the menu will often be influenced by the wider [[South Asia]] (sometimes including [[Nepalese cuisine|Nepalese dishes]]), and sometimes cuisines from further afield (such as [[Cuisine of Iran|Persian dishes]]). Some British variations on Indian food are now being exported from the U.K. to India.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/8635456.stm|title=Can the British curry take off in India?|accessdate=23 April 2010 | work=BBC News | date=21 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Curry restaurants of more-or-less the British style are also popular in Canada, Australia and New Zealand.

This cuisine is characterised by the use of a common base for all the sauces to which spices are added when individual dishes are prepared. The standard &quot;feedstock&quot; is usually a sautéed mixture of onion, garlic and fresh ginger, to which various spices are added, depending on the recipe, but which may include: cloves, cinnamon, cardamom, chilies, peppercorns, cumin and mustard seeds. Ground coriander seed is widely used as a thickening agent, and turmeric is added for colour and its digestive qualities.{{citation needed|date=June 2017}} Fresh or canned tomatoes and bell peppers are a common addition.

Better quality restaurants will normally make up new sauces on a daily basis, using fresh ingredients wherever possible and grinding their own spices. More modest establishments are more likely to resort to frozen or dried ingredients and pre-packaged spice mixtures.{{citation needed|date=July 2014}}

====Terminology====
Restaurants in Great Britain have adopted a number of Indian terms to identify popular dishes. Although the names may derive from traditional dishes, often the recipes do not. Representative names include:

* Bhuna – medium, thick sauce, some vegetables (''bhunna'' in Urdu means &quot;to be fried&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/bhuna |title=Bhuna &amp;#124; Define Bhuna at Dictionary.com |publisher=Dictionary.reference.com |accessdate=22 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Biryani]] – spiced rice and meat cooked together and usually served with vegetable curry sauce.
* Curry – the most common name for a meat dish (most often chicken or lamb) with a medium-spicy, brown, gravy-like sauce.
* [[Dhansak]] – in the curry house, it may be made with either lamb or chicken and frequently contains pineapple, though this is not original.&lt;ref&gt;Chapman, Pat. ''Favourite Restaurant Curries''. (The Curry Club). (London: Piatkus, c.1988), p.96.&lt;/ref&gt; The name derives from a Parsi dish of mutton cooked with lentils (''dal'') and vegetables.
* [[Dupiaza]]/dopiaza – medium curry (the word means &quot;double onion&quot;, referring to the boiled and fried onions used as its primary ingredient).
* [[Jalfrezi]] – onion, green chili and a thick sauce.
* [[Kofta]] – refers to dishes containing meatballs (most frequently lamb), or vegetable meat-substitutes (most often ground nuts).
* [[Korma]]/kurma – mild, yellow in colour, with almond and coconut powder.
* [[Madras curry sauce|Madras curry]] – &quot;the standard hot, slightly sour curry at the Indian restaurant.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chapman, Pat 1988 p.34&quot;&gt;Chapman, Pat. ''Favourite Restaurant Curries''. (The Curry Club). (London: Piatkus, c.1988), p.34.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Pasanda]] – in the UK, a mild curry sauce made with cream, coconut milk, and almonds or cashews, served with lamb, chicken, or king prawns (US: jumbo shrimp). The name was derived from a Mughlai dish of lamb strips beaten to make them tender.
* Naga curry – relatively new extremely hot dish with unique savoury taste made with the highly aromatic [[Ghost pepper|Naga Morich]] or Bhut Jolokia chilli pepper.
* [[Pathia]] – a hot curry, generally similar to a &quot;Madras&quot; with the addition of lemon juice and tomato purée.
* [[Phall|Phaal]] – &quot;this is the hottest curry the restaurants can make. There is nothing like it in India – it is pure invention.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Chapman, Pat. ''Favourite Restaurant Curries''. (The Curry Club). (London: Piatkus, c.1988), p.35.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Rogan josh|Roghan josh]] – a medium-spicy curry, usually of lamb, with a deep red sauce containing tomatoes and paprika. It derives from a Kashmiri dish of the same name.
* [[Sambar (dish)|Sambar]] – medium-heat, sour curry made with lentils and tamarind.
* [[Vindaloo]] – generally regarded as the classic &quot;hot&quot; restaurant curry. Progressively hotter versions are sometimes called &quot;tindaloo&quot; and &quot;bindaloo&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chapman, Pat 1988 p.34&quot;/&gt;
&lt;!-- although a true vindaloo does not specify any particular level of spiciness. The name has European origins, derived from the Portuguese term &quot;vinha d'alhos&quot;, a marinade containing [[wine]] (&quot;vinho&quot;), or sometimes vinegar, and [[garlic]] (&quot;alho&quot;), used to prevent the pork from going off in hot weather.--&gt;

The [[tandoor]] was introduced into Britain in the 1960s, and [[tandoori]] and tikka chicken became popular dishes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://fooddetectivesdiary.blogspot.com/2011/02/brief-history-of-chicken-tikka-masala.html|title=Food Detective's Diary: A brief history of Chicken Tikka Masala|last=Jina|date=19 February 2011|website=Food Detective's Diary|access-date=2019-10-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2017/jan/12/who-killed-the-british-curry-house|title=Who killed the curry house?|first=Bee|last=Wilson|date=12 January 2017|work=The Guardian|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other dishes may feature with varying strengths, with those of north Indian origin, such as [[butter chicken]], tending to be mild, and recipes from the south of India tending to be hotter.

====Balti====
{{Main|Balti (food)}}
Baltis are a style of curry thought to have been developed in [[Birmingham]], England&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://oed.com/bbcwordhunt/list.html#balti |title=Wordhunt appeal list - Balderdash Wordhunt - Oxford English Dictionary |publisher=Oed.com |accessdate=8 June 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090709215254/http://www.oed.com/bbcwordhunt/list.html#balti |archivedate=9 July 2009 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; which have spread to other western countries and are traditionally cooked and served in the same pot, typically made of cast iron, called a &quot;balty&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-birmingham-18490695 |title=Birmingham Balti curry seeks EU protected status |work=BBC News |date=19 June 2012 |accessdate=22 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==South Africa==
{{Main|South African cuisine#Indian cookery}}

[[African cuisine|African]] curries, [[Cape Malay]] curries and [[KwaZulu-Natal|Natal]] curries include the traditional Natal curry, the Durban curry, [[bunny chow]], and roti rolls. South African curries appear to have been founded in two distinct regions &amp;ndash; one in the east ([[KwaZulu-Natal]]) and the other in the west ([[Western Cape]]) &amp;ndash; with a variety of other curries developing across the country over the late 20th century and early 21st century to include ekasi, coloured, and [[Afrikaner]] curries.&lt;ref name=&quot;seid&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last1=Seid|first1=Shelley|title=Curry is the story of South Africa on a plate|url=https://www.timeslive.co.za/sunday-times/lifestyle/food/2017-10-18-curry-is-the-story-of-south-africa-on-a-plate/|accessdate=27 January 2018|newspaper=Sunday Times|date=19 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Durban]] has the largest single population of Indians outside of India, who have been developing traditional Natal curries since their arrival in the late 19th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;ishay&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Govender-Ypma|first1=Ishay|title=The Brutal History of South Africa's Most Famous Curry|url=https://munchies.vice.com/en_us/article/qv3njv/the-brutal-history-of-south-africas-most-famous-curry|publisher=Munchies|accessdate=27 January 2018|date=11 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Natal curries are mostly based on South Indian dishes and mostly consist of simple spiced lamb and chicken dishes (with large amounts of [[ghee]] and oils), but also include very complex and elaborate seafood, chicken and lamb specialties (chicken and prawn curry is a Natal favourite). Continental and British recipes have also evolved alongside [[Indian South African]] curries. Continental and British versions use mainly traditional recipes with the addition of [[wine|red wine]], [[milk]], [[cream]], vanilla or [[butter]] instead of ghee.

Bunny chow or a &quot;set&quot;, a South African standard, has spread in popularity throughout the country and into other southern African countries and countries with large South African immigrant populations.&lt;ref name=seid/&gt;&lt;ref name=ishay/&gt; It consists of either lamb, chicken or bean curry poured into a tunnelled-out loaf of [[bread]] to be eaten with one's fingers.&lt;ref name=ishay/&gt; The roti roll is another classic takeaway curry that could either be a curry in a flat roti bread (similar to a [[kebab]] bread) or the classic &quot;chip, cheese and curry&quot; roll which basically consists of [[French fries|fried chips]] with melted [[cheese]] and curry gravy rolled into a roti roll.

==West Indies==
In the [[West Indies]], curry is a very popular dish. The Indian indentured servants that were brought over from India by different European powers brought this dish to the West Indies. In Jamaica and Trinidad, curried goat is prominently featured. Curry can be found at both inexpensive and upscale Caribbean restaurants, and ingredients can range from chicken or vegetables to shellfish such as shrimp and scallops. Examples of curries in the West Indies include:

* [[Cuisine of Guyana|Guyana]]: Chicken, goat, duck, shrimp, beef, &quot;aloo&quot; (potato), channa, fish (different varieties) and crab curry are very popular among Guyana, predominantly within [[Indo-Guyanese people]].
* [[Cuisine of Trinidad and Tobago|Trinidad and Tobago]]: Especially curried chicken, crab, duck, goat, beef, shrimp, and &quot;aloo&quot; (potato), along with wild meats.
* [[Cuisine of Jamaica|Jamaica]]: Especially curried chicken, [[Curry goat|goat]], fish and shrimp.
* Bahamas: Curried mutton (goat or lamb), curried chicken, curried pork chops.

==Other countries==

===Fiji===
In Fiji curries are made in most Indian homes and are eaten with rice or [[roti]]. Roti (circle or square) is mainly eaten for breakfast with vegetable curries. Lunch is often dal and rice with some side dishes. Most working people take roti and curry for their lunch.{{citation needed|date=June 2017}} Dinner is usually curry, rice with some chutneys. Curries are normally cooked in vegetable oil. Ghee is mainly used to fry dal, to make puris or sweets. To make a curry, spices like cumin, fenugreek, mustard, and curry leaves are added to the hot oil. Onion is chopped or sliced and garlic crushed and added to the pot. Once the onion and garlic have turned slightly golden then turmeric and garam masala are added. For every 1 tsp turmeric normally 2 tsp masala is added.{{citation needed|date=June 2017}} Salt and chillies are added according to taste. Curry is simmered on low heat until well cooked. Water is added so that it can be mixed with rice. If coriander leaves are available then they are added for extra flavour.

Sometimes potatoes or vegetables are also added to curries to increase volume and make them more nutritious. Often coconut cream is added to seafood curries, such as prawn, crab or fish curries. Dal is often cooked with only turmeric and then fried in cumin, onion, and garlic. Sometimes carrots and leafy vegetables like ''chauraiya'' or ''saijan'' are added for extra flavor and nutrients.

===Similar dishes===
* [[African cuisine|Central Africa]]: Groundnut stew, though not technically a curry, is a similar style.
* [[Central Europe]]: [[Goulash]] is a spicy stew or soup usually made with paprika, garlic, potatoes, beef or pork and dill. The dish is not served with rice.
* [[Ethiopian cuisine|Ethiopia]]: [[Wat (food)|Wat]], a thick, heavily spiced stew.
* Fiji, Samoa, and Tonga: Generally known as &quot;kare&quot; or &quot;kale&quot;, curry is popular in curried lamb, mutton, and chicken stew. Often prepared with coconut milk and accompanied by rice or taro.
* [[German cuisine|Germany]]: [[Currywurst]].
* Mexico: Mole, which also originally meant sauce, features different regional variations and combinations of chilies, spices, and chocolate.

==Curry powder==
{{Main| Curry powder}}
Curry powder is a spice mixture of widely varying composition developed by the British during the days of the Raj as a means of approximating the taste of Indian cuisine at home. [[spice mix|Masala]] refers to spices, and this is the name given to the thick and pasty sauce based on a combination of spices with ghee (clarified butter), butter, palm oil or coconut milk. Most commercial curry powders available in Britain, the U.S. and Canada rely heavily on ground turmeric, in turn producing a very yellow sauce. Lesser ingredients in these Western yellow curry powders are often coriander, cumin, [[fenugreek]], mustard, chili, black pepper and salt. By contrast, curry powders and curry pastes produced and consumed in India are extremely diverse; some red, some yellow, some brown; some with five spices and some with as many as 20 or more. Besides the previously mentioned spices, other commonly found spices in different curry powders in India are allspice, white pepper, ground mustard, ground ginger, cinnamon, roasted cumin, cloves, nutmeg, mace, green cardamom seeds or black cardamom pods, bay leaves and coriander seeds.

Curry powder is used as an incidental ingredient in other cuisines, including for example a &quot;curry sauce&quot; (''sauce au curry'', sometimes even ''au cari'') variation of the classic French [[béchamel]].

==See also==
{{portal|Food}}
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [[Curry Awards]]
* [[Fish curry (disambiguation)|Fish curry]]
* [[Kuzhambu]]
* [[Mutton curry]]
* [[Rice and curry]]
* [[Shrimp curry]]
* [[The British Curry Awards]]
* [[The Curry Club]]
* [[Wrap roti]]
{{div col end}}

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Chicken makhani.jpg|[[Butter chicken]] served in an Indian restaurant
File:Red roast duck curry.jpg|Red roast duck curry (hot and spicy) from Thailand
File:Rice and chenopodium album leaf curry with potatoes and onions40.JPG|[[Rice]] and ''[[Chenopodium album]]'' leaf curry with onions and potatoes; a [[vegetarian]] curry
File:Homemade chicken tikka masala.jpg|Homemade [[chicken tikka masala]]
File:Balti gosht.jpg|A Balti lamb curry
File:Kadhi Chawal from India.jpg|yoghurt and gram flour curry
File:Vindalho.jpg|Pork Vindaloo in a Goan restaurant
File:Karnatakadishes.jpg|Karnataka Food
File:Rogan josh02.jpg|Rogan Josh curry
File:Chicken Curry 1.JPG|[[Curry chicken]] from Pakistan
File:Nihari.JPG|Nihari with nihari salad
File:Korean curry rice.jpg|Korean curry rice
File:Kaeng kari kai.JPG|Yellow curry
File:Meen curry 2.JPG|Indian fish Curry
Angamaly mango curry with mango.jpg|Mango Curry from Kerala
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* [[Pat Chapman|Chapman, Pat]]. ''Curry Club Indian Restaurant Cookbook''. [[London]]&amp;nbsp;– Piatkus.{{ISBN|0-86188-378-0}} &amp; {{ISBN|0-86188-488-4}} (1984 to 2009)
* [[Pat Chapman|Chapman, Pat]]. ''The Little Curry Book''. [[London]]&amp;nbsp;– Piatkus.{{978-0861883646}}  (1985)
* Achaya, K.T. ''A Historical Dictionary of Indian Food''. [[Delhi]], [[Oxford University Press]] (1998)
* Achaya, K.T. ''A Historical Dictionary of Indian Food''. [[Delhi]], [[Oxford University Press]] (1998)
* Grove, Peter &amp; Colleen. ''The Flavours of History''. London, Godiva Books (2011)
* [[Pat Chapman|Chapman, Pat]]. ''India: Food &amp; Cooking''. London, New Holland&amp;nbsp;– {{ISBN|978-1-84537-619-2}} (2007)
* ''Indian Food: A Historical Companion''. Delhi, Oxford University Press, 1994
* David Burton. ''The Raj at Table''.  London, [[Faber and Faber]] (1993)
* ''[[Pat Chapman]]'s Curry Bible''. Hodder &amp; St&amp;nbsp;– {{ISBN|0-340-68037-7}} &amp;  {{ISBN|0-340-68037-7}} &amp; {{ISBN|0-340-68562-X}} &amp; {{ISBN|0-340-68562-X}} (1997)
* ''New Curry Bible'', An unaltered edition of ''[[Pat Chapman]]'s Curry Bible'' published by John Blake Publishers. {{ISBN|978-1-84358-159-8}} (2005)
* E.M. Collingham. ''Curry: A Biography''. London, [[Chatto &amp; Windus]], 2005
* ''An Invitation to Indian Cooking''. London, Penguin, 1975
* [[Madhur Jaffrey|Jaffrey, Madhur]]. Various books on curry from 1973 to 2015.
* [[Pat Chapman|Chapman, Pat]]. ''Petit Plats Curry''. Paris. Hachette Marabout. {{ISBN|2-501-03308-6}} (2000)

==External links==
{{Sisterlinks|d=Q164606|b=Cookbook:Curry|wikt=curry|n=no|v=no|voy=no|species=no|mw=no|m=no|q=no|commons=Category:Curry|s=1911 Encyclopædia Britannica/Curry}}
*{{Curlie|Shopping/Food/Seasonings/Curry/}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Curry| ]]
[[Category:Pakistani cuisine]]
[[Category:Punjabi cuisine]]
[[Category:Indian cuisine]]
[[Category:Indonesian cuisine]]
[[Category:Japanese cuisine]]
[[Category:Vietnamese cuisine]]
[[Category:Bengali cuisine]]
[[Category:Nepalese cuisine]]
[[Category:Thai cuisine]]
[[Category:Malaysian cuisine]]
[[Category:Malay cuisine]]
[[Category:Karnataka cuisine]]
[[Category:Tamil cuisine]]
[[Category:Sri Lankan cuisine]]
[[Category:Fijian cuisine]]
[[Category:British cuisine]]
[[Category:Chinese cuisine]]
[[Category:Mongolian cuisine]]
[[Category:Burmese cuisine]]
[[Category:Lao cuisine]]
[[Category:Cambodian cuisine]]
[[Category:Asian cuisine]]
[[Category:Ancient dishes]]
[[Category:Types of food]]
[[Category:Indian words and phrases]]</text>
      <sha1>1qby55knuo4by3lpdwaj9eacur0c07e</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
