  <page>
    <title>Carnivore</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6543</id>
    <revision>
      <id>941057481</id>
      <parentid>941057395</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-16T10:08:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Artoria2e5</username>
        <id>18040497</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Organism that eats mostly or exclusively animal tissue}}
{{pp-protected|small=yes}}
{{about|the general concept of a meat-eating animal|the mammal order|Carnivora|other uses}}
[[File:Carnivore-lion.jpg|thumb|Lions are [[wikt:obligate|obligate]] carnivores consuming only animal flesh for their nutritional requirements]]

A '''carnivore''' {{IPAc-en|ˈ|k|ɑr|n|ɪ|v|ɔər}}, meaning &quot;[[meat]] eater&quot; ([[Latin]], ''caro'', genitive ''carnis'', meaning &quot;meat&quot; or &quot;flesh&quot; and ''vorare'' meaning &quot;to devour&quot;), is an [[organism]] that derives its [[energy]] and [[nutrient]] requirements from a [[List of feeding behaviours|diet]] consisting mainly or exclusively of [[animal]] [[Tissue (biology)|tissue]], whether through [[predation]] or [[scavenger|scavenging]].&lt;ref&gt;Nutrient Requirements: Carnivores. Duane E. Ullrey. Encyclopedia of Animal Science.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MC&quot;&gt;Mammals: carnivores. Duane E. Ullrey. Encyclopedia of Animal Science.&lt;/ref&gt; Animals that depend solely on animal flesh for their nutrient requirements are called [[wikt:obligate|obligate]] carnivores while those that also consume non-animal food are called [[wikt:facultative|facultative]] carnivores.&lt;ref name=&quot;MC&quot;/&gt; [[Omnivore]]s also consume both animal and non-animal food, and, apart from the more general definition, there is no clearly defined ratio of plant to animal material that would distinguish a facultative carnivore from an omnivore.&lt;ref&gt;Mammals&quot;' Omnivores. Duane E. Ullrey. Encyclopedia of Animal Science.&lt;/ref&gt; A carnivore at the top of the [[food chain]], not preyed upon by other animals, is termed an [[apex predator]].

&quot;Carnivore&quot; also may refer to the [[mammal]]ian order [[Carnivora]], but this is somewhat misleading: many, but not all, Carnivora are meat eaters, and even fewer are true obligate carnivores (see below). For example, while the Arctic [[polar bear]] eats meat almost exclusively (more than 90% of its diet is meat), most species of [[bear]]s are [[omnivore|omnivorous]], and the [[giant panda]] is exclusively [[herbivore|herbivorous]]. There are also many carnivorous species that are not members of Carnivora. The correct term for mammals in this group is &quot;carnivoran&quot;. 

Outside the animal kingdom, there are several genera containing [[carnivorous plant]]s (predominantly insectivores) and several phyla containing [[carnivorous fungus|carnivorous fungi]] (preying mostly on microscopic [[invertebrate]]s such as [[nematode]]s, [[amoebae]] and [[springtail]]s).

[[File:Venus_Flytrap_showing_trigger_hairs.jpg|thumb|Members of the vegetable kingdom can live on meat too, such as the [[Venus flytrap]], a [[carnivorous plant]]]] 

Carnivores are sometimes characterized by their [[List of feeding behaviours#By food type|type of prey]]. For example, animals that eat mainly [[insect]]s and similar invertebrates are called [[insectivore]]s, while those that eat mainly [[fish]] are called [[piscivore]]s. The first [[tetrapod]]s, or land-dwelling [[vertebrate]]s, were piscivorous amphibians known as [[Labyrinthodontia|labyrinthodonts]]. They gave rise to insectivorous vertebrates and, later, to predators of other tetrapods.&lt;ref name=&quot;SahneyBentonFerry2010RainforestCollapse&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | url=http://geology.geoscienceworld.org/cgi/content/abstract/38/12/1079 | author= Sahney, S., Benton, M.J. &amp; Falcon-Lang, H.J. | year=2010 | title= Rainforest collapse triggered Pennsylvanian tetrapod diversification in Euramerica | journal=Geology | volume = 38 | pages = 1079–1082 | format=PDF | doi=10.1130/G31182.1 | issue=12 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Carnivores may alternatively be classified according to the percentage of meat in their diet. The diet of a [[hypercarnivore]] consists of more than 70% meat, that of a [[mesocarnivore]] 30–70%, and that of a [[hypocarnivore]] less than 30%, with the balance consisting of non-animal foods such as [[fruit]]s, other plant material, or [[fungi]].

==Obligate carnivores==
[[File:Tigre d'Asie à robe blanche.jpg|thumb|The [[Bengal tiger]]'s large [[canine tooth|canines]] and strong jaws reveal its place as an [[apex predator]]]]
[[File:Male_Lion_and_Cub_Chitwa_South_Africa_Luca_Galuzzi_2004.JPG|thumb|[[Lion]]s are voracious carnivores; they require more than 7 kilograms of meat daily. A major component of their diet is the meat of large [[mammal]]s, such as this [[African buffalo|buffalo]].]]

Obligate or &quot;true&quot; carnivores are those whose diet requires nutrients found only in animal flesh. While obligate carnivores might be able to [[ingestion|ingest]] small amounts of plant matter, they lack the necessary [[physiology]] required to [[digestion|digest]] it. In fact, some obligate carnivorous mammals will only ingest vegetation for the sole purpose of its use as an [[emetic]], to self-induce vomiting of the vegetation along with the other food it had ingested that upset its stomach.

Obligate carnivores include the [[axolotl]], which consumes mainly worms and larvae in its environment, but if necessary will consume algae, as well as all [[Felidae|felids]] (including the [[domestic cat]]) which require a diet of primarily animal flesh and organs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Velegrand-Defretin|first=Veronique|title=Differences between cats and dogs: a nutritional view|journal=Proceedings of the Nutrition Society|year=1994|volume=53|pages=15–24|url=http://journals.cambridge.org/download.php?file=%2FPNS%2FPNS53_01%2FS0029665194000066a.pdf&amp;code=b428e668252a801500828a47df480146|doi=10.1079/pns19940004}}&lt;/ref&gt; Specifically, cats have high protein requirements and their metabolisms appear unable to synthesize essential nutrients such as [[retinol]], [[arginine]], [[taurine]], and [[arachidonic acid]]; thus, in nature, they must consume flesh to supply these nutrients.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Ullrey, D. E.|editor1-last=Pond|editor1-first=Wilson|title=Encyclopedia of Animal Science|date=2004|publisher=CRC Press|isbn=978-0-8247-5496-9|page=591|chapter=Mammals: Carnivores|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=1SQl7Ao3mHoC&amp;pg=PA591 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Ullrey, D. E.|editor1-last=Pond|editor1-first=Wilson|title=Encyclopedia of Animal Science|date=2004|publisher=CRC Press|isbn=978-0-8247-5496-9|page=670|chapter=Nutrient Requirements: Carnivores|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=1SQl7Ao3mHoC&amp;pg=PA670 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Characteristics of carnivores ==
Characteristics commonly associated with carnivores include strength, speed, and keen senses for hunting, as well as teeth and claws for capturing and tearing prey. However, some carnivores do not hunt and are [[scavenger]]s, lacking the physical characteristics to bring down prey; in addition, most hunting carnivores will scavenge when the opportunity arises. Carnivores have comparatively short digestive systems, as they are not required to break down the tough cellulose found in plants.

Many hunting animals have evolved eyes facing forward, enabling depth perception. This is almost universal among mammalian predators, while most reptile and amphibian predators have eyes facing sideways.

==Prehistoric carnivores==
{{main|Predation#Evolutionary history|Evolutionary history of life}}
''[[Predation]]'' (the eating of one living creature by another for nutrition) predates the rise of commonly recognized carnivores by hundreds of millions (perhaps billions) of years. The earliest predators were microbial organisms, which engulfed or grazed on others. Because the fossil record is poor, these first predators could date back anywhere between 1 and over 2.7 Gya (billion years ago).&lt;ref name=&quot;bengtson&quot;&gt;[https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/the-paleontological-society-papers/article/origins-and-early-evolution-of-predation/54E8168EC25E08AFCAEF69C63A49C491 Origins and Early Evolution of Predation, 2002] ([http://www.nrm.se/download/18.4e32c81078a8d9249800021552/Bengtson2002predation.pdf full paper])&lt;/ref&gt; The rise of [[eukaryotic]] cells at around 2.7 Gya, the rise of multicellular organisms at about 2 Gya, and the rise of mobile predators (around 600 Mya – 2 Gya, probably around 1 Gya) have all been attributed to early predatory behavior,&lt;ref name=&quot;bengtson&quot;/&gt; and many very early remains show evidence of boreholes or other markings attributed to small predator species.&lt;ref name=&quot;bengtson&quot;/&gt;

Among more familiar species, the first vertebrate carnivores were fish, and then amphibians that moved on to land. Early [[tetrapods]] were large amphibious [[piscivores]]. Some scientists assert that ''[[Dimetrodon]]'' &quot;was the first terrestrial vertebrate to develop the curved, serrated teeth that enable a predator to eat prey much larger than itself.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.natureworldnews.com/articles/5928/20140207/carnivorous-pre-dinosaur-predator-first-evolve-steak-knife-teeth.htm |author= Foley, James A. |date= February 7, 2014 |title= Carnivorous, Pre-Dinosaur Predator was First to Evolve Steak Knife-like Teeth |publisher= Nature World News |accessdate= May 3, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; While amphibians continued to feed on fish and later insects, reptiles began exploring two new food types: tetrapods (carnivory) and then plants (herbivory). Carnivory was a natural transition from insectivory for medium and large tetrapods, requiring minimal adaptation; in contrast, a complex set of adaptations was necessary for feeding on highly fibrous plant materials.&lt;ref name=&quot;SahneyBentonFerry2010RainforestCollapse&quot; /&gt;

In the [[Mesozoic]], some [[theropod]] [[dinosaur]]s such as ''[[Tyrannosaurus|Tyrannosaurus rex]]'' were probably obligate carnivores. Though the theropods were the larger carnivores, several carnivorous mammal groups were already present. Most notable are the [[Gobiconodontidae|gobiconodontids]], the [[Triconodontidae|triconodontid]] ''[[Jugulator (mammal)|Jugulator]]'', the [[Deltatheroida|deltatheroideans]] and ''[[Cimolestes]]''. Many of these, such as ''[[Repenomamus]]'', ''Jugulator'' and ''Cimolestes'', were among the largest mammals in their faunal assemblages, capable of attacking dinosaurs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ref-1&quot;&gt;Zofia Kielan-Jaworowska, Richard L. Cifelli, Zhe-Xi Luo (2004). &quot;Chapter 12: Metatherians&quot;. Mammals from the Age of Dinosaurs: origins, evolution, and structure. New York: Columbia University Press. pp. 425–262. {{ISBN|0-231-11918-6}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Richard C. |last=Fox |year=2015 |title=A revision of the Late Cretaceous–Paleocene eutherian mammal Cimolestes Marsh, 1889 |journal=Canadian Journal of Earth Sciences |volume=52 |issue=12 |pages=1137–1149 |doi=10.1139/cjes-2015-0113 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Cifelli |first=Richard L. |last2=Madsen |first2=Scott K. |year=1998 |title=Triconodont mammals from the medial Cretaceous of Utah |journal=Journal of Vertebrate Paleontology |volume=18 |issue=2 |pages=403–411 |doi=10.1080/02724634.1998.10011068 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early-to-mid-Cenozoic, the dominant predator forms were mammals: [[Hyaenodonta|hyaenodonts]], [[Oxyaenidae|oxyaenids]], [[entelodont]]s, [[ptolemaiida]]ns, [[Arctocyonidae|arctocyonids]] and [[mesonychia]]ns, representing a great diversity of [[eutheria]]n carnivores in the northern continents and [[Africa]]. In [[South America]], [[Sparassodonta|sparassodonts]] were dominant, while [[Australia]] saw the presence of several [[marsupial]] predators, such as the [[Dasyuromorphia|dasyuromorphs]] and [[Thylacoleonidae|thylacoleonids]]. From the [[Miocene]] to the present, the dominant carnivorous mammals have been [[Carnivoramorpha|carnivoramorphs]].

Most carnivorous mammals, from [[dog]]s to ''[[Deltatheridium]]'', share several dental adaptations, such as [[carnassial]]iforme teeth, long [[canine tooth|canine]]s and even similar tooth replacement patterns.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Christian |last=De Muizon |first2=Brigitte |last2=Lange-Badré |title=Carnivorous dental adaptations in tribosphenic mammals and phylogenetic reconstruction |journal=[[Lethaia]] |volume=30 |issue=4 |year=1997 |pages=353–366 |doi=10.1111/j.1502-3931.1997.tb00481 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Most aberrant are [[thylacoleonids]], with a diprodontan dentition completely unlike that of any other mammal; and [[eutriconodonts]] like gobioconodontids and ''Jugulator'', with a three-cusp anatomy which nevertheless functioned similarly to carnassials.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ref-1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Eating Encyclopedia. ''[https://quecome.net/animales-carnivoros/ Animales Carnivoros. Ejemplos, alimentacion y curiosidades]''. {{in lang|es}} 02-02-2017.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Mesocarnivore]]
*[[Herbivore]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
*Glen, Alistair &amp; Dickman, Christopher (Eds) 2014, Carnivores of Australia, CSIRO Publishing, Melbourne, {{ISBN|978-0-643-10310-8}}.

{{Biological interaction-footer}}
{{feeding}}
{{modelling ecosystems}}

[[Category:Biological interactions]]
[[Category:Carnivory| ]]
[[Category:Animals by eating behaviors]]
[[Category:Ethology]]
[[Category:Meat|*]]</text>
      <sha1>m1mxoyc9mm030tc8e1mg983e0gmpxg6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
