  <page>
    <title>Coercion</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6512</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940931084</id>
      <parentid>923130877</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-15T15:11:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Citation bot</username>
        <id>7903804</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Alter: url. Add: archive-date, archive-url. | You can [[WP:UCB|use this bot]] yourself. [[WP:DBUG|Report bugs here]]. | Activated by [[User:Neko-chan]] | [[Category:Psychological abuse]] | via #UCB_Category</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Forcing involuntary behavior in another}}
{{Refimprove|article|date=February 2015}}
{{Other uses}}
{{redirects|Duress}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
'''Coercion''' ({{IPAc-en|k|oʊ|ˈ|ɜr|ʒ|ən|,_|-|ʃ|ən}}) is the practice of forcing another party to act in an involuntary manner by use of [[threat]]s or force.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/coercion|title=Definition of coercion|work=Merriam-Webster}}&lt;/ref&gt; It involves a set of various types of forceful actions that violate the [[free will]] of an individual to induce a desired response, for example: a bully demanding lunch money from a student or the student gets beaten. These actions may include [[extortion]], [[blackmail]], [[torture]], threats to induce favors, or even [[sexual assault]]. In law, coercion is codified as a '''duress''' crime. Such actions are used as leverage, to force the victim to act in a way contrary to their own interests. Coercion may involve the actual infliction of physical pain/injury or psychological harm in order to enhance the [[credibility]] of a threat. The threat of further harm may lead to the [[co-operation|cooperation]] or [[Obedience (human behavior)|obedience]] of the person being coerced.

==Overview==
The purpose of coercion is to substitute one's aims to those of the victim. For this reason, many social philosophers have considered coercion as the polar opposite to [[Political freedom|freedom]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=wg1dvc2lfcEC&amp;pg=PA160&amp;lpg=PA160&amp;dq=%22The+purpose+of+coercion+is+to+substitute+one's+aims+to+those+of+the+victim.+For+this+reason,+many+social+philosophers+have+considered+coercion+as+the+polar+opposite+to+freedom%22#v=onepage&amp;q=%22The%20purpose%20of%20coercion%20is%20to%20substitute%20one's%20aims%20to%20those%20of%20the%20victim.%20For%20this%20reason,%20many%20social%20philosophers%20have%20considered%20coercion%20as%20the%20polar%20opposite%20to%20freedom%22&amp;f=false|title=Textbook on Legal Language and Legal Writing|last=Bhatia|first=Prof Dr K. L.|date=2010-01-01|publisher=Universal Law Publishing|isbn=9788175348943|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Various forms of coercion are distinguished: first on the basis of the ''kind of injury'' threatened, second according to its ''aims'' and ''scope'', and finally according to its ''effects'', from which its legal, social, and ethical implications mostly depend.

===Physical===
Physical coercion is the most commonly considered form of coercion, where the content of the conditional threat is the [[use of force]] against a victim, their relatives or property. An often used example is &quot;putting a gun to someone's head&quot; (''at gunpoint'') or putting a &quot;knife under the throat&quot; (''at knifepoint'' or cut-throat) to compel action or the victim gets killed or injured. These are so common that they are also used as metaphors for other forms of coercion.

Armed forces in many countries use [[firing squad]]s to maintain [[discipline]] and intimidate the masses, or opposition, into submission or silent [[Compliance (psychology)|compliance]]. However, there also are nonphysical forms of coercion, where the threatened injury does not immediately imply the use of force. Byman and Waxman (2000) define coercion as &quot;the use of threatened force, including the limited use of actual force to back up the threat, to induce an adversary to behave differently than it otherwise would.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Byman, Daniel L.; Waxman, Matthew C.: ''Kosovo and the Great Air Power Debate'', ''[[International Security]]'', Vol. 24, No. 4 (Spring, 2000), pp. 5–38.&lt;/ref&gt; Coercion does not in many cases amount to destruction of property or life since compliance is the goal.

===Psychological===
In [[psychological coercion]], the threatened injury regards the victim's relationships with other people. The most obvious example is ''[[blackmail]]'', where the threat consists of the dissemination of damaging information. However, many other types are possible e.g. &quot;[[emotional blackmail]]&quot;, which typically involves threats of rejection from or disapproval by a peer-group, or creating feelings of guilt/obligation via a display of anger or hurt by someone whom the victim loves or respects. Another example is [[coercive persuasion]].

Psychological coercion – along with the other varieties – was extensively and systematically used by the government of the [[People's Republic of China]] during the &quot;[[Thought reform in China|Thought Reform]]&quot; campaign of 1951–1952. The process – carried out partly at &quot;revolutionary universities&quot; and partly within prisons – was investigated and reported upon by [[Robert Jay Lifton]], then Research Professor of Psychiatry at Yale University: see Lifton (1961). The techniques used by the Chinese authorities included a technique derived from standard [[group psychotherapy]], which was aimed at forcing the victims (who were generally intellectuals) to produce detailed and sincere ideological &quot;confessions&quot;. For instance, a professor of [[formal logic]] called Chin Yueh-lin – who was then regarded as China's leading authority on his subject – was induced to write: &quot;The new philosophy [of [[Marxism-Leninism]]], being scientific, is the supreme truth&quot; [Lifton (1961) p.&amp;nbsp;545].

==See also==
{{columns-list|colwidth=30em|
* [[Abusive power and control]]
* [[Coercive control]]
* [[Coercive power]]
* [[Deterrence (legal)]]
* [[Duress in American law]]
* [[Duress in English law]]
* [[Marital coercion]]
* [[Monopoly on violence]]
* [[Punishment (psychology)]]
}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
* {{cite web | last=Anderson | first=Scott A. | date=n.d. | title=Towards a Better Theory of Coercion, and a Use for It | publisher=The University of Chicago | url=http://ptw.uchicago.edu/Anderson02.pdf | accessdate=12 October 2018 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20050308180431/http://ptw.uchicago.edu/Anderson02.pdf | archive-date=8 March 2005 }}
* Lifton, Robert J. (1961) ''Thought Reform and the Psychology of Totalism'', Penguin Books.

==External links==
*{{Commonscatinline}}
{{Wiktionary|coercion|at gunpoint|at knifepoint}}
{{wikiquote}}
*{{cite SEP |url-id=coercion |title=Coercion |last=Anderson |first=Scott}}.
* Carter, Barry E. [http://opil.ouplaw.com/view/10.1093/law:epil/9780199231690/law-9780199231690-e1518?prd=EPIL Economic Coercion], ''Max Planck Encyclopedia of Public International Law'' (subscription required)

{{*mail}}
{{Bullying}}

[[Category:Abuse]]
[[Category:Authority]]
[[Category:Bullying]]
[[Category:Legal terminology]]
[[Category:Psychological abuse]]
[[Category:Coercion| ]]
[[Category:Interrogation techniques]]
[[Category:Power (social and political)]]</text>
      <sha1>r3pg4w02kickz59kbtd8u10x4uw165m</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
