  <page>
    <title>Delaware General Corporation Law</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8933</id>
    <revision>
      <id>940908159</id>
      <parentid>940908110</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-15T11:17:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SUM1</username>
        <id>12712128</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Year needed in lead</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{short description|The statute governing corporate law in the U.S. state of Delaware}}
{{Corporate law|USA}}

The '''Delaware General Corporation Law''' (Title 8, Chapter 1 of the Delaware Code) is the [[statute]] governing [[corporate law]] in the [[U.S. state]] of [[Delaware]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Delaware General Corporation Law |url=http://delcode.delaware.gov/title8/c001/ |website=Delaware Code Online |accessdate=21 December 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Originally adopted in 1899, it has been the most important jurisdiction in [[United States corporate law]] since the early 20th century. Over 50% of [[Public company|publicly traded]] corporations in the United States and 60% of the [[Fortune 500]] are [[Incorporation (business)|incorporated]] in the state.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.corp.delaware.gov/aboutagency.shtml |title=About the Division of Corporations |publisher=Delaware Division of Corporations |accessdate=1 January 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{see also|Regulatory competition|Race to the bottom}}
Delaware acquired its status as a corporate haven in the early 20th century. Following the example of [[New Jersey]], which enacted corporate-friendly laws at the end of the 19th century to attract businesses&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Cary|first1=William L.|title=Cases and Materials on Corporations|date=1969|publisher=The Foundation Press, Inc.|location=Mineola|page=9}}&lt;/ref&gt; from [[New York (state)|New York]], Delaware adopted on March 10, 1899, a general incorporation act aimed at attracting more businesses. The group that pushed for this legislation intended to establish a corporation that would sell services to other businesses incorporating in Delaware.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.djcl.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/A-History-of-Delaware-Corporation-Law1.pdf A History of Delaware Corporation Law], S. Samuel Arsht, ''Delaware Journal of Corporate Law'', 1976, pg. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; Before the rise of general incorporation acts, forming a corporation required a special act of the state legislature. General incorporation allowed anyone to form a corporation by simply raising money and filing articles of incorporation with the state's Secretary of State.

==Other legal aspects==
Because of the extensive experience of the Delaware courts, Delaware has a more well-developed body of case law than other states,&lt;ref&gt;https://www.economist.com/business/2013/11/23/a-new-judicial-boss&lt;/ref&gt; which serves to give corporations and their counsel greater guidance on matters of corporate governance and transaction liability issues. Disputes over the internal affairs of Delaware corporations are usually filed in the [[Delaware Court of Chancery]], which is a separate [[court of equity]], as opposed to a [[court of law]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://courts.delaware.gov/overview.stm |title=Overview of the Delaware Court System |publisher=Delaware State Courts}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because it is a court of equity, there are no juries; its cases are heard by judges, called chancellors. Since 1989, the court has consisted of one chancellor and four vice-chancellors. The court is a trial court, with one chancellor hearing each case. Litigants may appeal final decisions of the Court of Chancery to the [[Delaware Supreme Court]].

Delaware has also attracted major credit card banks because of its relaxed rules regarding [[interest]]. Many U.S. states have [[usury]] laws limiting the amount of interest a lender can charge. Federal law allows a national bank to &quot;import&quot; these laws from the state in which its principal office is located.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.occ.gov/static/interpretations-and-precedents/mar98/int822.pdf |title=Interpretive Letter #822 |work=Interpretations and Actions |publisher=[[Office of the Comptroller of the Currency]] |volume=11 |number=3 |date=March 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt; Delaware (amongst others) has relatively relaxed interest laws,&lt;ref name=&quot;USA_Corp&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Usa Ibp Usa|title=Us Company Laws and Regulations Handbook Volume 2 Delaware|date=2009|publisher=Int'l Business Publications|isbn=1433070820|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=EWI__tnGDJ0C&amp;lpg=PA48&amp;ots=HX6cP5_YhT&amp;dq=delaware%20relaxed%20interest%20laws&amp;pg=PA48#v=onepage&amp;q=delaware%20relaxed%20interest%20laws&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; so several national banks have decided to locate their principal office in Delaware. National banks are, however, corporations formed under federal law, not Delaware law. A corporation formed under Delaware state law benefits from the relaxed interest rules to the extent it conducts business in Delaware,&lt;ref name=&quot;Webber_DE&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last1=Webber|first1=Annie|title=Delaware, the Tiny Capital of Big Business|url=http://blog.legalhero.com/blog/delaware-the-tiny-capital-of-big-business|agency=Legal Hero|date=21 Jul 2015|access-date=13 April 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141026121153/http://blog.legalhero.com/blog/delaware-the-tiny-capital-of-big-business|archive-date=26 October 2014|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; but is subject to restrictions of other states' laws if it conducts business in other states.&lt;ref name=&quot;USA_Corp&quot;/&gt;

Pursuant to the &quot;[[internal affairs doctrine]]&quot;, corporations which act in more than one state are subject only to the laws of their state of incorporation with regard to the regulation of the internal affairs of the corporation.&lt;ref&gt;''Edgar v. MITE Corp'', {{ussc|457|624|1982}}.&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, Delaware corporations are subject almost exclusively to Delaware law, even when they do business in other states.

While most states require a for-profit corporation to have at least one director and two officers, Delaware laws do not have this restriction.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reuters_DECorp&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=DEL CODE § 141 : Delaware Code - Section 141: BOARD OF DIRECTORS|url=http://codes.lp.findlaw.com/decode/8/1/IV/141|website=Findlaw.com|publisher=Thompson Reuters}}&lt;/ref&gt; All offices may be held by a single person who also can be the sole shareholder. The person, who does not need to be a U.S. citizen or resident, may also operate anonymously with only the listing agent through whom the company is registered named.&lt;ref name=&quot;Watson_DELLC&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last1=Watson|first1=Libby|title=Why are there so many anonymous corporations in Delaware?|url=https://sunlightfoundation.com/blog/2016/04/06/why-are-there-so-many-anonymous-corporations-in-delaware/|agency=Sunlight Foundation|date=6 Apr 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Case of TransPerfect===
According to Section 226 of the Delaware General Corporation Law (DGCL) the Court of Chancery is permitted to appoint a receiver or custodian for a corporation when its stockholders or directors are divided and the deadlock is injurious to the corporation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Findlaw&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=DEL CODE § 226 : Delaware Code - Section 226: APPOINTMENT OF CUSTODIAN OR RECEIVER OF CORPORATION ON DEADLOCK OR FOR OTHER CAUSE|url=http://codes.lp.findlaw.com/decode/8/1/VII/226|website=Findlaw}}&lt;/ref&gt; In August 2015, the head of the [[Delaware Court of Chancery|Delaware Chancery]], Chancellor [[André Bouchard (Judge)|Andre Bouchard]] employed 226(a) of the DGCL to order the auction of the shares of a company that was not in financial distress, nor at risk of insolvency, because its co-owners could not get along.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gerasimovich_TransPerfect&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last1=Gerasimovich|first1=Kenneth|title=Delaware Chancery Court Appoints a Custodian to Sell Deadlocked Company|url=http://www.lexology.com/library/detail.aspx?g=9ed30bca-f677-43f1-ac02-95808beff2e8|agency=Lexology|publisher=Globe Business Media Group|date=15 Dec 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The forced sale of [[TransPerfect]] is the first time a company that did not meet the criteria for receivership and mandated sale under Delaware law was being forced to dissolve, to award one board member who wanted to exit with a [[control premium]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Waltz_1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last1=Waltz|first1=Samuel|title=Giuliani steps into ‘business divorce’ case in Chancery|url=http://www.delawarebusinesstimes.com/giuliani-steps-business-divorce-case-chancery/|work=&quot;The Chancellor appears to want to not merely force the sale of the company, but to award the control premium to one party alone. That is not equitable, and this is an equity court.”|agency=Delaware Business Times|date=26 Apr 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Elstein_TP&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last1=Elstein|first1=Aaron|title=Court orders feuding biz partners, ex-lovers, to sell their profitable translation firm|url=http://www.crainsnewyork.com/article/20150825/BLOGS02/150829916/court-orders-feuding-biz-partners-ex-lovers-to-sell-their-profitable-translation-firm|agency=Crain's NY|date=25 Aug 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Former New York Mayor [[Rudolph Giuliani]] has taken an interest in this case because he views it as &quot;contradictory&quot; to the Delaware corporate laws.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mordock&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last1=Mordock|first1=Jeffrey|title=Giuliani blasts Delaware court for decision in lover's spat|url=http://www.delawareonline.com/story/money/2016/04/22/giuliani-blasts-delaware-court-decision-lovers-spat/83345454/|agency=Delaware New Journal|date=22 Apr 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under the law, the Chancery is not obligated or even mandated to make accommodations for any party to sell his or her interest. The only concern for the Delaware court is to make sure that a company is run well and not being harmed. In this regard, the case of TransPerfect can seem at odds with the court's mandate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gerasimovich&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last1=Gerasimovich|first1=Kenneth|title=Delaware Chancery Court Appoints a Custodian to Sell Deadlocked Company|url=http://www.gtlaw.com/News-Events/Publications/Alerts/190560/Delaware-Chancery-Court-Appoints-a-Custodian-to-Sell-Deadlocked-Company|agency=GTLaw Newsletter|publisher=Greenberg Traurig, LLP|date=15 Dec 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Chancellor decided to mandate the sale of the company because the two directors were locked in a dispute that left them unable to negotiate among themselves.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pepper Hamilton&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last1=Cline|first1=Joanna|last2=Levine|first2=James|last3=Chuff|first3=Christopher|title=CHANCERY ORDERS SALE OF SOLVENT COMPANY TO RESOLVE BOARD DEADLOCK|url=http://www.pepperlaw.com/publications/chancery-orders-sale-of-solvent-company-to-resolve-board-deadlock-2015-09-03/|agency=Pepper Hamilton LLP|date=3 Sep 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; At issue, however, is that in doing so, the Chancery and the Chancellor appear to be seeking an inequitable share for one of the partners who wanted to exit and asked for an offer to leave, forcing the partner who would prefer to remain and operate the firm to exit as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bouchard Decision&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|title=In re: SHAWE &amp; ELTING LLC|journal=Delaware Court Decision Elting V Shawe|date=13 Aug 2015|volume=&quot;The distinct possibility also exists that Shawe would be the most logical purchaser of the business or that a third party would be unwilling to acquire the Company without securing his participation and expertise.&quot;|issue=C.A. No. 9700-CB|page=83|url=http://courts.state.de.us/opinions/download.aspx?ID=228080|ref=324}}&lt;/ref&gt; The court cited employee affidavits attesting to one party's commitment over the other's.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bouchard Decision&quot;/&gt;

On April 27, 2016,&lt;ref name=&quot;Waltz_RGWelcome&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last1=Waltz|first1=Samuel|title=Former NYC Mayor Giuliani’s 2 cents’ worth seems very welcome|url=http://www.delawarebusinesstimes.com/former-nyc-mayor-giulianis-2-cents-worth-seems-welcome/|agency=Delaware Business Times|date=26 Apr 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; rather than sealing his decision, Chancellor Bouchard told the parties to take more time and to come to a resolution outside of the courtroom. One party then made a public offer of $300 million to the other.&lt;ref name=&quot;Elstein_300M&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last1=Elstein|first1=Aaron|title=Feuding ex-lovers inch closer to a TransPerfect divorce|url=http://www.crainsnewyork.com/article/20160502/BLOGS02/160509974|agency=Crain's New York|publisher=Crain Communications|date=2 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Tax benefits and burdens==
Delaware charges no [[income tax]] on corporations not operating within the state, so taking advantage of Delaware's other benefits does not result in taxation.&lt;ref&gt;http://corplaw.delaware.gov/delaware_law.shtml&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, Delaware has a particularly aggressive tax on banks that locate in the state. However, in general, the state is viewed as a positive location for corporate tax purposes because favorable laws of incorporation allow companies to minimize corporate expenditures (achieved through legal standardization of corporate legal processes), creating a nucleus in Delaware with operating companies often in other states.&lt;ref name=delawareofeurope&gt;{{cite journal |ssrn=763164 |title=Will There Ever Be a Delaware of Europe? |first=Patrick S. |last=Ryan |journal=Columbia Journal of European Law |volume=11 |page=187 |date=Winter 2004–2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition, Delaware has used its position as the state of incorporation to generate revenue from its abandoned and unclaimed property laws. Under U.S. Supreme Court precedent, the state of incorporation gets to keep any [[Lost, mislaid, and abandoned property|abandoned and unclaimed property]], such as uncashed checks and unredeemed gift certificates, if the corporation does not have information about the location of the owner of the property.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://finance.delaware.gov/publications/fiscal_notebook_07/Section02/sec2page24.pdf |title=State General Fund Revenues by Category (F.Y. 2002 - F.Y. 2005) |work=Delaware 2005 Fiscal Notebook |publisher=Delaware Department of Finance |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110816093426/http://finance.delaware.gov/publications/fiscal_notebook_07/Section02/sec2page24.pdf |archivedate=2011-08-16 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A state may levy, however, a [[franchise tax]] on the corporations incorporated in it. Franchise taxes in Delaware are actually far higher than in most other states which typically charge little or nothing beyond corporate income taxes on the portion of the corporation's business done in that state. Delaware's franchise taxes supply about one-fifth of its state revenue.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;/&gt;

In February 2013, ''[[The Economist]]'' published an article on tax-friendly jurisdictions, commenting that Delaware stood for &quot;Dollars and Euros Laundered And Washed At Reasonable Expense&quot;. [[Jeffrey W. Bullock]], Delaware's Secretary of State, insists that the state has struck the right balance between curbing criminality and &quot;paying deference to the millions of legitimate businesspeople who benefit&quot; from hassle-free incorporation.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.economist.com/news/special-report/21571554-some-onshore-jurisdictions-can-be-laxer-offshore-sort-not-palm-tree-sight &quot;Onshore financial centres: Not a palm tree in sight&quot;]. ''The Economist'' (2013-02-16). Retrieved on 2013-09-05.&lt;/ref&gt;

==2013 amendments==
On June 30, 2013, Delaware Governor [[Jack Markell]] signed into law amendments to the Delaware General Corporation Law that affect several provisions in the current law and could substantially affect the process through which public companies are merged. The new legislation took effect August 1, 2013, except for ratification of defective corporate acts amendment which took effect in 2014.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hklaw.com/publications/Significant-Amendments-to-Delaware-General-Corporation-Law-Enacted-08-05-2013/ |archive-url=https://archive.is/20130806234639/http://www.hklaw.com/publications/Significant-Amendments-to-Delaware-General-Corporation-Law-Enacted-08-05-2013/ |url-status=dead |archive-date=August 6, 2013 |title=Significant Amendments to Delaware General Corporation Law Enacted |journal=Holland &amp; Knight Securities Bulletin |date=August 5, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Companies}}
*[[Combined reporting]]
*[[Corporation Service Company]]
*[[Corporation Trust Center (CT Corporation)]], Wilmington, Delaware, home to over 6,500 Delaware corporations
*[[Corporation]]
*[[Corporate haven]]
*''[[Delaware Journal of Corporate Law]]''
*[[Say on pay]]
*[[Flag of convenience (business)]]
*[[United Kingdom company law]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20070929205846/https://sos-res.state.de.us/tin/GINameSearch.jsp Delaware Department of State, Division of Corporations] Official website, corporation name search.
*[http://delcode.delaware.gov/title8/c001/index.shtml Delaware's General Corporation Law]
*[http://www.corp.delaware.gov/ Delaware Division of Corporations]
*[http://www.djcl.org/ The Delaware Journal of Corporate Law]

[[Category:Types of business entity]]
[[Category:Delaware statutes|Corporation]]
[[Category:United States corporate law]]</text>
      <sha1>1wi7y2vqtl7ftevn8s78agmjzuh8wwf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
